<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>oai:cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org:p15795coll17/2</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-28</datestamp><setSpec>p15795coll17</setSpec></header><metadata><oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"><dc:title>Harlan and Marcia Conn Interview</dc:title><dc:creator>Conn, Harlan; Conn, Marcia</dc:creator><dc:date>1973-02-01</dc:date><dc:description>Harlan Conn served as The American University in Cairo’s top financial officer, its Controller and Bursar, from the 1930s to 1950s, and was married to Marcia Conn, who taught at AUC at times. The couple recollects their experiences at AUC, both professional and social, describing a university smaller in scope, size, and budget than at the time of their oral history. They provide a portrait of the personalities, reputations, connections to Egyptian elites, Arabic language skills, and working styles of Presidents Charles Watson and John Badeau, Deans Robert McClenahan, Russell Galt, and Worth Howard, and other administrators and faculty (including University Physician Gilbert Ibrahim). The academic program, students, and leadership (Amir Boktor) of AUC’s School of Education (for which Mrs. Conn taught some courses) are covered, as are the director (Wendell Cleland) and other programs of the Extension Division. The couple speak about what it was like to study Arabic language in AUC’s School of Oriental Studies, and describe its program, students, and faculty including Arthur Jeffrey, mentioned as the only one conducting research at AUC in the 1930s and 1940s due to heavy class teaching loads and minimal financial support. The Conns recall aspects of life at AUC during the Second World War, including administrators and faculty hosting dinners for soldiers and taking refuge in a campus bomb shelter during air raid warnings, and the United States military’s rental of Ewart Hall for performances to entertain the troops and other university facilities to house an Armed Forces Institute correspondence course operation.  Other topics covered are President Watson’s resistance to accepting U.S. government funding, the state of relations between AUC and the Presbyterian American Mission in Egypt, and conditions after the 1952 revolution. The university’s plans to build and relocate to a suburban campus near the Pyramids in Giza, and the property acquired there and the purchase of the downtown campus palace, are also discussed.
</dc:description><dc:subject>American University in Cairo--History.</dc:subject><dc:publisher>Rare Books and Special Collections Library; The American University in Cairo</dc:publisher><dc:language>English</dc:language><dc:format>oral histories (document genres)</dc:format><dc:source>AUC Oral Histories; Rare Books and Special Collections Library; The American University in Cairo</dc:source><dc:rights>Copyright 2017, American University in Cairo. All rights reserved.</dc:rights><dc:rights>To inquire about permissions or reproductions, contact the Rare Books and Special Collections Library, The American University in Cairo at +20.2.2615.3676 or rbscl-ref@aucegypt.edu.</dc:rights><dc:identifier>http://cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15795coll17/id/2</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc></metadata></record>