<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>oai:cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org:p15795coll17/219</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-27</datestamp><setSpec>p15795coll17</setSpec></header><metadata><oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"><dc:title>Farouk El-Hitami interview</dc:title><dc:creator>El-Hitami, Farouk</dc:creator><dc:date>2006-05-17</dc:date><dc:description>Farouk El-Hitami joined AUC in 1966 as a faculty member teaching business, and served as Director of the Management Center, Dean of the School of Business, Economics, and Communication in the 1990s, and Vice President for Student Affairs in the early 2000s. He recounts being hired as part of efforts to revitalize business education at AUC in the mid-1960s, and recalls AUC in the aftermath of the 1967 War. El-Hitami also gives an account of his role in the acquisition of the university’s first computer in the late 1960s and his role as first director of AUC’s Computer Center. He traces developments in business education at AUC, like the emergence of extension offerings, the operations of the Management Center, and the establishment of undergraduate degree programs (the latter prompted in part by the desire to enroll more male students at AUC to balance male-female enrollment). Comparisons of the background and attitudes of AUC students over the years are also offered. El-Hitami’s role in the building of the Jameel Center Building on the downtown Greek Campus in the 1980s is covered, as are developments during his time as Dean of the School of Business, Economics, and Communication. He also addresses faculty issues like disparities in compensation between Egyptian and foreign faculty. El-Hitami also mentions his time as Vice President for Student Affairs in the early 2000s, including issues like the court cases arising from the university prohibiting the wearing of niqab face veils on campus.</dc:description><dc:subject>American University in Cairo--History.</dc:subject><dc:publisher>Rare Books and Special Collections Library; The American University in Cairo</dc:publisher><dc:language>English</dc:language><dc:format>oral histories (document genres)</dc:format><dc:source>AUC Oral Histories; Rare Books and Special Collections Library; The American University in Cairo</dc:source><dc:rights>Copyright 2017, American University in Cairo. All rights reserved.</dc:rights><dc:identifier>http://cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15795coll17/id/219</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc></metadata></record>