<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>oai:cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org:p15795coll17/20</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-24</datestamp><setSpec>p15795coll17</setSpec></header><metadata><oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"><dc:title>Ghali Amin interview</dc:title><dc:creator>Amin, Ghali</dc:creator><dc:date>1973-06-02</dc:date><dc:description>Ghali Amin served as a staff member with AUC’s Extension Division from 1936 to the 1950s, having studied from 1926 in AUC’s “government” course primary and secondary education program.  He outlines the Division’s public programming, including forums in Oriental Hall and lectures at Ewart Hall that drew large crowds of a thousand attendees (including Al Azhar University and medical students), noting that no other institution in the country (like the Egyptian university) offered such events at the time.   Presented in fall and spring seasons, the lectures addressed topics of interest in Egypt including health (such as Ahmed Fakhry’s talks on venereal disease) and social insurance (through forums introducing Egyptians to the program launched by Minister of Social Welfare Ahmed Hussein, whose position Cleland had lobbied the government to establish); some were broadcast on radio.  An advisory committee featuring leading Egyptian educators like Taha Hussein reviewed the topics and speakers Cleland suggested. Ghali notes hostility that emerged in the Egyptian press, for example after an incident where Abdel Kader Husseini felt he was insulted during his introduction at a lecture he gave at Ewart Hall, including accusations that AUC insulted Islam and was trying to convert Muslims to Christianity. Ghali describes the cinema program (which he managed) launched in the mid-1930s to generate income, at which commercial movies with historic or literary themes were shown, in addition to the religious film “King of Kings” played before Christian audiences; Amin mentions that actors were invited to introduce Arabic language films, and a visit by the American director Cecil B. DeMille. Musical programming included concerts by Umm Kulthum (with uncontrolled audience behavior), performances by the Palestine orchestra, and an innovative 1951 oriental music concert; these were often broadcast on Egyptian radio. Other uses of Ewart Hall organized by the Extension Division included amateur Arabic drama productions, and AUC’s Commencement. Ghali also describes the personality and style of Extension Division Wendell Cleland and Presidents Charles Watson and (previously Dean) John Badeau.  This interview is documented through notes taken by interviewer Lawrence Murphy rather than a verbatim transcript; there is no audio for this interview.</dc:description><dc:subject>American University in Cairo--History.</dc:subject><dc:publisher>Rare Books and Special Collections Library; The American University in Cairo	</dc:publisher><dc:language>English</dc:language><dc:type>Text</dc:type><dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format><dc:format>oral histories (document genre)</dc:format><dc:source>AUC Oral Histories; Rare Books and Special Collections Library; The American University in Cairo</dc:source><dc:rights>Copyright 2017, American University in Cairo. All rights reserved.</dc:rights><dc:rights>To inquire about permissions or reproductions, contact the Rare Books and Special Collections Library, The American University in Cairo at +20.2.2615.3676 or rbscl-ref@aucegypt.edu.	</dc:rights><dc:identifier>http://cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15795coll17/id/20</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc></metadata></record>