<oai_dc:dc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
            <dc:title>The   Turkish Empire in Europe, Asia, and Africa: dividid into all its governments, together with the other territories that are tributary to it, as also the dominions of ye Emperor of Marocco [sic] according to the newest and most exact observations</dc:title>
            <dc:creator>Moll, Herman , -1732</dc:creator>
            <dc:contributor>Bruyn, Cornelis de , 1652-1727</dc:contributor>
            <dc:contributor>King, John.</dc:contributor>
            <dc:contributor>Bowles, Thomas , -1767</dc:contributor>
            <dc:contributor>Bowles, John , 1701-1779</dc:contributor>
            <dc:contributor>Vernon, Thomas , 1654-1721</dc:contributor>
            <dc:date>[1714?]</dc:date>
            <dc:date>1714</dc:date>
            <dc:publisher>Widener Library, Harvard University Widener Library, Harvard University Tozzer Library, Harvard University Harvard Map Collection, Harvard University Tozzer Library, Harvard University Harvard Map Collection, Harvard University Tozzer Library, Harvard University Harvard Map Collection, Harvard University Widener Library, Harvard University Widener Library, Harvard University Harvard Law School Library, Harvard University Widener Library, Harvard University Houghton Library, Harvard University Widener Library, Harvard University Houghton Library, Harvard University Widener Library, Harvard University</dc:publisher>
            <dc:publisher>Printed for H. Moll over against Devereux Court in ye Strand, and Iohn Bowles at the Black Horse in Cornhill, and T. Bowles Print &amp; Mapseller, and Iohn King</dc:publisher>
            <dc:language>eng English</dc:language>
            <dc:format>1 map on 2 sheets ; 61 x 101 cm, sheets 66 x 56 cm.</dc:format>
            <dc:description>by H. Moll.</dc:description>
            <dc:description>Covers Spain, North Africa, the Arabian Peninsula, the Middle East, the Balkan Peninsula, Italy, Switzerland and portions of Russia and France.</dc:description>
            <dc:description>Relief shown pictorially.</dc:description>
            <dc:description>Prime meridian: London and Ferro.</dc:description>
            <dc:description>Dedication: To the honourable Tho. Vernon Esqr. one of ye Commissrs. of Trade for ye Plantations, of His Majesty of Gr. Britain. This map is most humbly dedicated by your most Humble Servant Her. Moll Geographer.</dc:description>
            <dc:description>Insets: Plan of Constantinople -- Draught of the City of Jerusalem as it is now, taken from the south east by Corneille Le Bruyn -- Church of the Holy Sepulcre (3 views), J. Harris, fecit. -- Smirna.</dc:description>
            <dc:description>Includes notes.</dc:description>
            <dc:subject>Scale [ca. 1:7,000,000].</dc:subject>
            <dc:subject>Turkey</dc:subject>
            <dc:subject/>
            <dc:identifier>oclc:on1032646155</dc:identifier>
            <dc:identifier>oclc:81322200</dc:identifier>
            <dc:identifier>https://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL:3021671?buttons=Y</dc:identifier>
            <dc:identifier>https://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL:3021671?width=150&amp;height=150&amp;usethumb=y</dc:identifier>
            <dc:identifier>https://id.lib.harvard.edu/curiosity/islamic-heritage-project/40-990048123180203941_FHCL:3021671</dc:identifier>
            <dc:identifier>https://id.lib.harvard.edu/digital_collections/990048123180203941_FHCL:3021671</dc:identifier>
         </oai_dc:dc>
      
