<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <identifier>4587</identifier>
  <datestamp>2019-02-27T12:33:44Z</datestamp>
  <dc:title>Interview with Aḥmad Maḥmūd Karbūn</dc:title>
  <dc:title>مقابلة مع أحمد محمود كربون</dc:title>
  <dc:interviewer>Suwayd, Ḥasīb</dc:interviewer>
  <dc:interviewerAR>سويد، حسيب</dc:interviewerAR>
  <dc:interviewee>Karbūn, Aḥmad Maḥmūd</dc:interviewee>
  <dc:intervieweeAR>كربون، أحمد محمود</dc:intervieweeAR>
  <dc:contributor />
  <dc:contributor>كربون، أحمد محمود</dc:contributor>
  <dc:contributor>سويد، حسيب</dc:contributor>
  <dc:subject>Battles--Palestine--History--To 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>المعارك--فلسطين--تاريخ--حتى 1948</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Revolutionaries--Palestine--Attitudes--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الثوار--فلسطين--مواقف--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--Zionist invasion, 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الإجتياح الصهيوني، 1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Expulsion--Palestine--History--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>التهجير--فلسطين--تاريخ--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>War and families--Palestine--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الحرب والعائلات--فلسطين--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Refugee camps--Lebanon--Social conditions</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>مخيمات اللاجئين--لبنان--الأحوال الإجتماعية</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Refugees, Palestinian--Lebanon--Social conditions</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>اللاجئون الفلسطينيون--لبنان--الأحوال الإجتماعية</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Arab countries--Foreign relations--Palestine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>البلدان العربية--العلاقات الخارجية--فلسطين</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--Foreign relations--Arab countries</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--العلاقات الخارجية--البلدان العربية</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestinian diaspora</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الشتات الفلسطيني</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Israel-Arab War, 1948-1949</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الحرب الإسرائيلية-العربية، 1948-1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--British Mandate, 1922-1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الإنتداب البريطاني، 1922-1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--Nakba, 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--النكبة، 1948</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:otherSubject>Boats; British colonialism; Businesses; Children; Collaborationists; Daughters; Desserts; Displacement; Expulsion from Palestine; Family structure; Forgiveness; Haifa (Palestine); Hospitals; Housing; Injuries; Jamʻiyyat al-Kaff al-Aswad; Killing; Lajnat al-Difāʻ ʻan Filastīn; Living conditions; Maktab Filasṭīn al-Dāʼim fī Beirut; Mawlid; Medical care; Money; Pregnancies; Uncles; Wahhāb, Shakīb, 1890-1980; Wives; Abdullah, King of Jordan, 1882-1951; al-Difāʻ (Newspaper); al-Hayʼah al-ʻArabīyah al-ʻUlyā; al-Ḥusaynī, Amīn, 1895-1975; al-Ḥusaynī, ʻAbd al-Qādir Mūsá, 1908-1948; al-Jāmiʻah al-ʻArabīyah; al-Qassām, ʻIzz al-Dīn, 1882-1935; al-Qasṭal Battle, 1948; Arab Revolt, 1936-1939; Assassination; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; Brutal treatment; Burial; Collaborationists; Damascus (Syria); Executions; Expulsion from Palestine; Haifa (Palestine); Kīlānī, Rashīd ʻĀlī, 1893-1965; Police stations; Ports; Protests against occupation; Resistance movements; Revolutionary leadership; Urban planning; World War, 1939-1945; al-Hayʼah al-ʻArabīyah al-ʻUlyā; al-Ḥusaynī, Amīn, 1895-1975; Ammunition; Arab countries; Bombardment; British Army; Explosions; Expulsion from Palestine; Haifa Battle, 1948; Injuries; Jabal al-Karmil (Palestine); Jewish settlements; Jordanian Army; Martyrdom; Palestinian Jews; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Ports; Religious diversity; Settler colonialism; Ships; Military tactics; Weapon acquisition; Weapon smuggling; al-Hayʼah al-ʻArabīyah al-ʻUlyā; Arab Revolt, 1936-1939; Boats; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; British police forces; Collaborationists; Displacement; Expulsion from Palestine; Ḥaṭṭah; Homeland; Identity cards; Land sale; Lebanon; Psychological warfare; Revolutionary leadership; Strikes; Akka (Palestine); Arab Salvation Army; Bombardment; British Army; Daughters; Emotions; Expulsion from Palestine; Forced migration; Injuries; Lebanon; Money; Nakba; Ports; Refugee aid; Refugee experience; Suffering; Women in armed conflicts; Zionist occupation; Arab Salvation Army; Armenians; Attempt at return; Bombardment; British; Expulsion from Palestine; Grenades; Haifa Battle, 1948; Hizballah; Mortars; Nakba; Naturalization refusal; Resistance movements; Return; Revolutionary songs; Rifles; Terrorism; Truces; Weapons; Zionist Invasion of Palestine, 1948; Akka (Palestine); al-Hayʼah al-ʻArabīyah al-ʻUlyā; al-Ḥusaynī, Amīn, 1895-1975; Boats; Bombardment; Customs; Health services; Injuries; International Committee of the International Committee of the Red Cross; Lajnat al-Difāʻ ʻan Filastīn; Mosques; Municipalities; Ports; Refugee aid; Refugee camp conditions; Refugee experience; Shaykhs; Suffering; Tripoli (Lebanon); United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East; al-Ḥusaynī, Amīn, 1895-1975; Arab countries; Arafat, Yasir, 1929-2004; Asad, Ḥāfiẓ, 1930-2000; Chamoun, Camille, 1900-1987; Child mortality; Collaborationists; Conduct of life; Coups d'état; Custody; Education; Family relations; Family structure; Feasts; Ḥusayn, King of Jordan, 1935-1999; Identity cards; Imprisonment; Jordan; Letters; Naturalization refusal; Orphans; Palestinian diaspora; Palestinian resistance movements; Palestinian resistance organizations; Refugee aid; Refugee camps; Refugees; Return; Syria; Traitors; Truces; Wars; Work; al-Baddāwī (Palestinian refugee camp: Lebanon); Arab countries; Arab nationalism; Arab Salvation Army; Arabs; Armenians; Building practices; Christians; City occupation; Clans; Disputes; Driving licence; Expulsion from Palestine; Floods; Haifa (Palestine); Hospitals; Housing; Identity cards; Injuries; Junblāṭ, Walīd, 1948-; Land brokers; Leaders; Money; Nahr al-Bārid (Palestinian refugee camp: Lebanon); Naturalization; Palestinian diaspora; Reconstructed urban setting; Refugee camp conditions; Socio-economic conditions; State of Israel; Truces; United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East</dc:otherSubject>
  <dc:otherSF>Naffā‘, Yūnus (Leader); Nāyif, Aḥmad (Officer); Basṭah, Ḥalīm (Officer); al-Bard, Fakhrī (Resistance leader); al-Ḥamad, Muḥammad (Arab Salvation Army commander); Srūr, Fahd (Resistance leader); al-Quzuq, ʻAbd al-ʻĀl (Resistance leader); Ṭāhā , Khalīl (Leader); Ṭāhā , Muḥammad Khalīl  (Doctor); Naffā‘, Yūnūs (Resistance leader); ‘Awdah, Abū Ṭāriq (Resistance leader); Abū  Hārūn, Tawfīq (Artist); al-Ḥāj Ibrāhīm, Rashīd (Resistance leader); Dallūl, Abū  ‘Alī (Resistance leader); al-Hāshimī, Ṭāhā(Resistance leader); Srūr, Jamāl (Resistance fighter); Karbūn, Aḥmad  (Resistance fighter); al-Nabahānī, Muḥammad Khayr (Camp leader); Ṣawwān, Jum‘ah (Camp leader); Bākīr, Abū Salīm (Camp leader); al- Nāẓir, Ṣalāḥ (Camp leader); al-Ṣalāḥī, Muḥammad (Camp leader); Sirḥān, Fāris (Camp leader); ‘Abd al-Majīd, Ibrāhīm (camp leader); al-Najim, Mūsá (Camp leader).</dc:otherSF>
  <dc:otherSFAR>نفّاع، يونس ( قائد مقاومة); نايف، احمد (ضابط عسكري); بسطة، حليم (ضابط); البرد، فخري (قائد مقاومة); الحمد، محمد (قائد جيش الانقاذ العربي); سرور، فهد (قائد مقاومة); القزق، عبد العال (قائد مقاومة); طه، خليل (قائد); طه، محمد خليل (دكتور); نفّاع، يونس ( قائد مقاومة); عودة، ابو طارق (زعيم مقاومة); ابو هارون، توفيق (فنان); الحاج إبراهيم، رشيد (قائد مقاومة); دلّول ابو علي (قائد مقاومة); الهاشمي، طه (مقاوم); سرور، جمال (مقاوم); كربون، احمد (مقاوم); النبهاني، محمد خير  (قائد مخيّم); صوّان، جمعة (قائد مخيّم); باكير، ابو سليم (قائد مخيّم); الناظر، صلاح (قائد مخيم); الصلاحي، محمد (قائد مخيّم); سرحان، فارس (قائد مخيّم); عبد المجيد، إبراهيم (زعيم مخيم); النجم ، موسى (قائد مخيّم).</dc:otherSFAR>
  <dc:otherF>Sursuq; Salām; al-Ni‘mānī; al-Shahāl; al-Ḍinnāwī.</dc:otherF>
  <dc:otherFAR>سرسق;  سلام; النعماني; الشهال; الضنّاوي.</dc:otherFAR>
  <dc:otherLPW>Jāmiʻ al-Jraynī (Mosque); Jāmiʻ al-Istiqlāl (Mosque); Jāmi‘ al-Jraynī (Mosque).</dc:otherLPW>
  <dc:otherLPWAR>جامع الجريني; جامع الاستقلال; جامع الجريني.</dc:otherLPWAR>
  <dc:otherLCTI>Ḥisbat Haifa (Market); Qahwat al-Karmilīt (Coffeehouse); al-Jāmiʻah al-Nabulsīyah (ِAssociation).</dc:otherLCTI>
  <dc:otherLCTIAR>سوق حسبة حيفا; قهوة الكرمليين; الجامعة النابلسية.</dc:otherLCTIAR>
  <dc:biography>The interview was recorded on May 6, 1997 with Aḥmad Maḥmūd Karbūn, male, born in 1924 in Haifa, Palestine and resides in al-Baddāwī Palestinian Refugee Camp, Lebanon.</dc:biography>
  <dc:biographyAR>سجلت المقابلة مع أحمد محمود كربون في 6 أيار مايو عام 1997، ذكر، ولد عام 1924 في حيفا، فلسطين ويقيم في مخيم البداوي للاجئين الفلسطينيين.</dc:biographyAR>
  <dc:toc>Political turmoil and forced departure from Palestine. (@ 0:00)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الاضطراب السياسي والترحيل القسري من فلسطين. (@ 0:00)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Palestinian popular resistance and political leadership. (@ 7:40)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>القيادة السياسية والمقاومة الشعبية الفلسطينية. (@ 7:40)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Land, defense and revolutionaries. (@ 16:20)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الأرض والدفاع والثوار. (@ 16:20)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>War time and military occupation. (@ 25:12)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>زمن الحرب والاحتلال العسكري. (@ 25:12)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Forced departure from Palestine. (@ 30:40)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الترحيل القسري من فلسطين. (@ 30:40)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Zionist occupation of Haifa. (@ 41:1)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الاحتلال الصهيوني لحيفا. (@ 41:1)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Refugee life in Lebanon. (@ 48:0)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>حياة اللجوء في لبنان. (@ 48:0)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Exile and immigration. (@ 59:13)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الطرد والتهجير. (@ 59:13)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Refugees : perspectives on the experience of forced migration  . (@ 71:10)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>اللاجئون: وجهات نظر حول الهجرة القسرية. (@ 71:10)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:description>Made available in DSpace on 2019-02-27T12:33:44Z (GMT). No. of bitstreams: 0
  Previous issue date: 1997</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1997-05-06</dc:date>
  <dc:issuedDate>1997</dc:issuedDate>
  <dc:createdDate>2017-05-03</dc:createdDate>
  <dc:availableDate>2019-02-27T12:33:44Z</dc:availableDate>
  <dc:accessionedDate>2019-02-27T12:33:44Z</dc:accessionedDate>
  <dc:date>yyyy-mm-dd</dc:date>
  <dc:type>Sound</dc:type>
  <dc:identifierURI>https://n2t.net/ark:/86073/b3z338?src=poha-oai</dc:identifierURI>
  <dc:identifierURL>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/render.php?cachefile=jn_0046_ahmad_qarbun.xml</dc:identifierURL>
  <dc:collectionName>POHA, Al-Jana, Nakba Collection</dc:collectionName>
  <dc:collectionNameAR>مجموعة الجنى : النكبة</dc:collectionNameAR>
  <dc:collectionID>68</dc:collectionID>
  <dc:localID>jn_0046</dc:localID>
  <dc:identifier>jn_0046_ahmad_qarbun.xml</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>Arabic</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>POHA, Al-Jana, Nakba Collection</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>0</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights>The copyright holder of this interview is the Nakba Archive, all rights reserved.</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights />
  <dc:format>audio</dc:format>
  <dc:duration>01:30:45</dc:duration>
  <dc:format>mp3</dc:format>
  <dc:village>Haifa</dc:village>
  <dc:villageAR>حيفا</dc:villageAR>
  <dc:interviewee_delimited>Karbun, Ahmad Mahmud|Karbūn, Aḥmad Maḥmūd</dc:interviewee_delimited>
  <dc:village_delimited>Haifa|Haifa</dc:village_delimited>
  <dc:hierarchy_browse>POHA, Al-Jana, Nakba Collection{{{_ID_}}}68</dc:hierarchy_browse>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_id>68</dc:hierarchy_top_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_title>POHA, Al-Jana, Nakba Collection</dc:hierarchy_top_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>مجموعة الجنى : النكبة</dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_id>68</dc:hierarchy_parent_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_title>POHA, Al-Jana, Nakba Collection</dc:hierarchy_parent_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_sequence>35</dc:hierarchy_sequence>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_id>4587</dc:is_hierarchy_id>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_title>مقابلة مع أحمد محمود كربون</dc:is_hierarchy_title>
  <dc:thumbnail>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/content/thumbnails/audio.jpg</dc:thumbnail>
</oai_dc:dc>