<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <identifier>4710</identifier>
  <datestamp>2019-02-27T12:34:30Z</datestamp>
  <dc:title>Interview with Nawfal Yāsīn</dc:title>
  <dc:title>مقابلة مع نوفل ياسين</dc:title>
  <dc:interviewer>Ghunaym, Aḥmad</dc:interviewer>
  <dc:interviewerAR>غنيم، أحمد</dc:interviewerAR>
  <dc:interviewee>Yāsīn, Nawfal</dc:interviewee>
  <dc:intervieweeAR>ياسين، نوفل</dc:intervieweeAR>
  <dc:contributor />
  <dc:contributor>ياسين، نوفل</dc:contributor>
  <dc:contributor>غنيم، أحمد</dc:contributor>
  <dc:subject>Jewish-Palestinian relations</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>العلاقات اليهودية-العربية</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Weddings--Palestine--Folklore</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الأعراس--فلسطين--الفولكلور</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:otherSubject>Agricultural economics; Agricultural products; Children's games; Circassians; Disputes; Farm animals; Football; Land expropriation; Land ownership; Mosques; Olive oil mills; Olive trees; Places of worship; Pre-Nakba geographical territories; Rural life; Schools; Shaykhs; Social relations; Students; Wādī al-Ḥundāj (Palestine); al-Hayb (Arab tribe); Beliefs; Bribery; Caves; Education; Expulsion; Folktales; Graveyards; Haganah; Israelites; Jewish immigrants; Jinn; Maiden; Mines; Prayers; Sheep; Shepherds; Teachers; ʻAlmā (Palestine); Community support; Compensation; Death; Dhabīḥah; Dietary practices; Farmers; Farming practices; Grooms; Hospitality; Intervillage relations; Jewish settlers; Kidnapping; Najmat al-Ṣubuḥ (Jewish settlement: Palestine); Palestinian-Jewish relations; Poets; Schools; Sheep; Trees; Wedding customs; ʻAlmā (Palestine); Agricultural income; Anti-Palestinian economic measures; Balfour Declaration, 1917; British army camps; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; Currency convertibility; Dowry; Husayn Ibn Ali, King of Hejaz, 1853?-1931; Income; Jewish immigrants; Letters; Marriage; Military training; Najmat al-Ṣubuḥ (Jewish settlement: Palestine); Officers; Palestinian Jews; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Weapons; al-Jāʻūnah (Palestine); Arbitration; Circumcision; Customs and traditions; Dabkah; Dhabīḥah; Dietary practices; Disputes; Dowry; Funeral rites and ceremonies; Interpersonal relations; Intervillage relations; Qaddītā (Palestine); Ramaḍān; Snakes; Village leaders; Wedding celebration; Wedding customs; Wedding songs; ʻAtābā; Aerial bombing; Agricultural products; al-Mālikīyah (Palestine); al-Ṣafṣāf (Palestine); Arbitration; Archival documents; Battles; Explosions; Expulsion from Palestine; Ḥaj; Ḥaṭṭah; Income; Injuries; Jaffa (Palestine); Lebanese Army; Lebanon; Means of transportation; Mines; Poetry; Relief; Return; Revolutionaries; Ṭarbūsh; Water resources; Work; Zionist invasion of Palestine, 1948</dc:otherSubject>
  <dc:otherSF>Inkhil, ʻAbd al-Hamīd (Shaykh); al-Dirbās, Muḥammad ʻĪsá (Businessman); al-Ḥāj, Muḥammad Fāris (Businessman); Mūsá, Aḥmad ʻUmar (Teacher); al-Karmī, ʻAbd al-Rahīm (Teacher); al-Fahūmī, Dyāb (Teacher); al-Shihāb, Fawzī (Teacher); Ḥamad, Muḥammad Ṭālib (Teacher); Ḥawwā, Aḥmad Ḥasan (Teacher); Qaddūrah,  Ḥikmat (Teacher); Yūnus, Ahmad (Teacher); Suwaydān, ʻAbd al-Laṭīf (Teacher); ʻĪsá, ʻAbd al-Raḥmān al-Ḥāj (Teacher), Ghaṭṭās, Ghaṭṭās Yūsuf (School principal); Abū Shiḥādah, Maḥmūd (Martyr); ʻAbdullāh, Muḥammad Ḥasan (Martyr); Saʻīd, Aḥmad Muḥammad (Mayor); ʻAṭāyā, Sulymān (Teacher); al-Rifāʻī, Ibrāhīm (Shaykh); al-Rifāʻī, Muḥammad (Shaykh); Shiblī, Nimir (Mayor); Ghannām, Ḥasan ʻAlī (Martyr); Shiḥādah, Saʻīd (Martyr).</dc:otherSF>
  <dc:otherSFAR>إنخيل، عبد الحميد (شيخ); الدرباس، محمد عيسى (رجل اعمال); الحاج، محمد فارس (رجل اعمال); موسى، احمد عمر (مدرّس); الكرمي، عبد الرحيم (مدرّسة); الفاهومي، دياب (مدرّس); الشهاب، فوزي (مدرّس); حمد، محمد طالب (مدرّس); حوّا، احمد (مدرّس); قدّورة، حكمت (مدرّس); يونس، احمد (مدرّس); سويدان، عبد اللطيف (مدرّس); عيسى، عبد الرحمن الحاج (مدرّس)//غطّاس، غطّاس يوسف (ناظر مدرسة); ابو شحادة، محمود (شهيد); عبد الله، محمد حسن (شهيد); سعيد، احمد محمد (رئيس بلدية); عطايا، سليمان (مدرّس); الرفاعي، إبراهيم (شيخ); الرفاعي، محمد (شيخ); شبلي، نمر (رئيس بلدية); شبلي، نمر (رئيس بلدية); غنّام، حسن علي (شهيد); شحادة، سعيد (شهيد); شحادة، سعيد (شهيد).</dc:otherSFAR>
  <dc:otherF>Shaḥrūr; Sulaymān; Mirʻī; Azzām; ʻAṭīyah; ʻAql; Abū Ṭaʻʻān; Hajāj; Dʻaybis; Ghannām; Yāsīn; Abbās; al-Ḥāj Khalīl; ʻAjjāwī; al-ʻAynah; al-Khaḍrah.</dc:otherF>
  <dc:otherFAR>شحرور; سليمان; مرعي; ازّام; عطية; عقل; ابو طعّان; حجاج; دعيبس; غنّام; ياسين; عبّاس; الحاج خليل; عجّاوي; العينة; الخضرة.</dc:otherFAR>
  <dc:otherLPW>Jāmiʻ al-ʻUmarī (Mosque); al-Siddīq (Maqām); Muḥammad al-Assūm (Maqām); al-Nabī Yūshaʻ (Maqām); Munṭār (Maqām).</dc:otherLPW>
  <dc:otherLPWAR>جامع العمري; مقام الصدّيق; مقام محمد الاسّوم; مقام النبي يوشع; مقام منطار.</dc:otherLPWAR>
  <dc:otherLM>Mghārat Namnūmī (Caves); al-Dulbī (Caves); Maghārat al-Dabiʻ (Cave).</dc:otherLM>
  <dc:otherLMAR>مغارة نمنومي; مغارة الدبلي; مغارة الضبع.</dc:otherLMAR>
  <dc:otherLPRI>Mustashfá Ḥamzah (Hospital); Egged Bus Comapny (Corporation); Mustashfá Ṭabaryā (Hospital).</dc:otherLPRI>
  <dc:otherLPRIAR>مستشفى حمود; شركة باصات ايجد; مستشفى طبريا.</dc:otherLPRIAR>
  <dc:otherL>Nahr al-Ḥundāj (River); Wādī Fārah (Valley).</dc:otherL>
  <dc:otherLAR>نهر الحنداج; وادي فرح.</dc:otherLAR>
  <dc:biography>The interview was recorded on November 2, 1987 with Nawfal Yāsīn, male, born in 1929 in ʻAlmā, Palestine and resides in al-Rashīdīyah Palestinian Refugee Camp, Lebanon. </dc:biography>
  <dc:biographyAR>سجلت المقابلة مع نوفل ياسين في 2 تشرين الثاني نوفمبر عام 1987، ذكر، ولد عام 1929 في علما، فلسطين ويقيم في مخيم الرشيدية للاجئين الفلسطينيين، لبنان.</dc:biographyAR>
  <dc:toc>Agriculture, childhood, and community life in ʻAlmā . (@ 0:00)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الزراعية والطفولة وحياة المجتمع في علما. (@ 0:00)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Antiquities and caves in Palestine. (@ 25:31)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الآثار والكهوف في فلسطين. (@ 25:31)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Social life and customs. (@ 52:20)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الحياة الاجتماعية والعادات. (@ 52:20)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>British mandate and employment . (@ 75:56)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الإنتدا بالبريطاني والتوظيف. (@ 75:56)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Wedding traditions, religious events and funeral traditions. (@ 93:21)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>تقاليد العرس والمناسبات الدينية وتقاليد الجنازة. (@ 93:21)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Miscellaneous narratives and explusion to Lebanon. (@ 134:0)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>قصص متنوعة والطرد إلى لبنان. (@ 134:0)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:description>Made available in DSpace on 2019-02-27T12:34:30Z (GMT). No. of bitstreams: 0
  Previous issue date: 1987</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1987-11-02</dc:date>
  <dc:issuedDate>1987</dc:issuedDate>
  <dc:createdDate>2017-09-15</dc:createdDate>
  <dc:availableDate>2019-02-27T12:34:30Z</dc:availableDate>
  <dc:accessionedDate>2019-02-27T12:34:30Z</dc:accessionedDate>
  <dc:date>yyyy-mm-dd</dc:date>
  <dc:type>Sound</dc:type>
  <dc:identifierURI>https://n2t.net/ark:/86073/b39922?src=poha-oai</dc:identifierURI>
  <dc:identifierURL>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/render.php?cachefile=jb_0007_nawfal_yasin.xml</dc:identifierURL>
  <dc:collectionName>POHA, Al-Jana, Biographies Collection</dc:collectionName>
  <dc:collectionNameAR>مجموعة الجنى : السير الذاتية</dc:collectionNameAR>
  <dc:collectionID>36</dc:collectionID>
  <dc:localID>jb_0007</dc:localID>
  <dc:identifier>jb_0007_nawfal_yasin.xml</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>Arabic</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>POHA, Al-Jana, Biographies Collection</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>0</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights>The copyright holder of this interview is the Nakba Archive, all rights reserved.</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights />
  <dc:format>audio</dc:format>
  <dc:duration>03:20:01</dc:duration>
  <dc:format>mp3</dc:format>
  <dc:village>ʻAlmā</dc:village>
  <dc:villageAR>علما</dc:villageAR>
  <dc:interviewee_delimited>Yasin, Nawfal|Yāsīn, Nawfal</dc:interviewee_delimited>
  <dc:village_delimited>Alma|ʻAlmā</dc:village_delimited>
  <dc:hierarchy_browse>POHA, Al-Jana, Biographies Collection{{{_ID_}}}36</dc:hierarchy_browse>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_id>36</dc:hierarchy_top_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_title>POHA, Al-Jana, Biographies Collection</dc:hierarchy_top_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>مجموعة الجنى : السير الذاتية</dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_id>36</dc:hierarchy_parent_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_title>POHA, Al-Jana, Biographies Collection</dc:hierarchy_parent_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_sequence>67</dc:hierarchy_sequence>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_id>4710</dc:is_hierarchy_id>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_title>مقابلة مع نوفل ياسين</dc:is_hierarchy_title>
  <dc:thumbnail>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/content/thumbnails/audio.jpg</dc:thumbnail>
</oai_dc:dc>