<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003dd_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T21:03:50.200Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003dd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/24</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003dd</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003dd/IOR_L_PS_10_24_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/24</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 664/1904 'Turkish Arabia: Status of British Protected Persons'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1911</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-25T09:09:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (201 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 201; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding the status of British-protected persons (primarily from the native states of India) within the territory of the Ottoman Empire. The topics discussed in the file include the consular representation of poor British Indian subjects in the vilayet (province) of Baghdad, the status of Baluchis resident in Basra, the granting of visas to Afghan pilgrims in Mesopotamia (Iraq), an application to be registered as a British-protected person made by Shaikh Omar Abdullah Basaar, a resident of Hodeida (al-Hudaydah) in Yemen and the status of Kashmiris resident in the city of Kerbala. The correspondence is primarily between officials of the Foreign Office, the India Office and the Government of India. The file also contains a copy of a letter in French sent from the Ottoman Ambassador in London to the Foreign Office concerning the status of natives of Afghanistan and Baluchistan within the Ottoman Empire (folios 81-82). The volume includes a divider which gives the year that the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained in it arranged by year. This divider is placed at the front of the volume.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Ottoman Empire</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Nationality</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003dd#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003dd#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003dd#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>