<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003cf_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T22:54:45.979Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003cf_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/608</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003cf</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003cf/IOR_R_15_2_608_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/608</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'21/5 QATAR HOSPITAL'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-18T21:51:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (22 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. File notes appear at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 24; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the construction of the first hospital at Doha, Qatar, in the mid-1940s. Correspondents in this file include: Lieutenant-Colonel Arnold Crawshaw Galloway, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bahrain; Cornelius James Pelly, Political Agent at Bahrain; E P Donaldson, India Office, London; Dr W N Storm and Dr Paul Wilberforce Harrison of the American Mission at Bahrain.Details include funding by the American Mission and the possibility of funding from the Government of India based on the scale of that provided for medical facilities at Dubai; the necessity of medical facilities to service the oil industry and for a Political Officer to reside at Doha under Article 8 of the Anglo-Qatar treaty of 1916; relations between the American Mission and Qatar and the British administration; and the possibility of posting an European doctor to Qatar. Notable documents include a letter, dated 6 Dhu al-Qidah 1366 (20 September 1947), from ‘Abdullāh bin Jāsim Āl Thānī to the Political Agent at Bahrain regarding the construction of the hospital and a report by Storm and Harrison about their trip to the hospital at Doha in October 1947.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>American Mission Hospital, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Hospital administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Building construction</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003cf#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003cf#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003cf#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>