<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b7_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T15:59:22.959Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/216</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b7</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b7/IOR_R_15_2_216_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/216</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. 5/7 I Jufair Naval Base'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-03T00:03:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (106 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation squence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are circled and written in pencil in the top right hand corner of the recto side of each folio. Foliation anomalies: 53A, 53B, 91A-91D</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the British Political Agent at Bahrain; the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire; Gilbert Laithwaite, India Office, London; the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf; the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, Martin Eric Dunbar-Nasmith; Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Bahrain Government; Sir Samuel Hoare, Secretary of State for India, London; and Paymaster Commander J Dent.The papers within this file begin with a number of items of correspondence concerning customs duties charged on imports by the Royal Navy at Bahrainbetween 1932 and 1933 (ff 6-10). From March 1933 onwards, the correspondence concerns the purchase of land in Bahrain for establishment of a naval base at Jufair [Jufayr], Bahrain, in the event of the British evacuation from Henjam [Hangām] island. Included within the correspondence are notes on meetings held by the Admiralty in London on 27 July 1933 (ff. 12-19) and 6 November 1933 (ff. 71-81); a report by the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, Captain J V Creagh, entitled 'Naval Base at Bahrain', dated 17 October 1933 (ff. 39-43); valuation and details concerning ownership of the land to be purchased made by Belgrave (ff 54-55); permission granted by the Secretary of State for India to purchase the land (ff. 83-84); details of the negotiations with Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah and other members of the ruling family for the purchase of the land (ff. 85-89); and a translation of deed for the land sealed by Shaikh Ḥamad and signed by Belgrave and M Khalil, Superintendent of Land Settlement Department, Bahrain (ff. 90-91), dated 30 Dhū al-Ḥijjah 1352 (14 April 1934).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b7#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b7#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003b7#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>