<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000c3_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T21:52:25.912Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000c3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/204</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000c3</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000c3/IOR_R_15_5_204_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/204</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/19 Smuggling of Unlicensed Tea from India by Kuwait'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-03T23:03:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (139 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 141; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding the alleged smuggling of tea into Iraq from India and Ceylon by Kuwaiti traders. Towards the end of the file, more general information concerning the importation of tea from India into Kuwait is also contained, including details of the Kuwaiti merchants involved in this trade.In addition to correspondence between British officials in the Gulf and India, the file also contains letters that were exchanged between the Political Agency in Kuwait and the country's ruler, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah (in Arabic with English translations).The file also contains a copy, in both Arabic original and English translation, of a petition that was sent to Ruler of Kuwait from several Kuwaiti merchants that were active in the tea trade on 15 January 1938 (folios 39-40).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Smuggling</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tea</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000c3#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000c3#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000c3#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>