<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024189687.0x000012_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T16:45:15.323Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024189687.0x000012_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/44, ff 60-61</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024189687.0x000012</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x0003b7/Mss Eur F126_44_0121.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/44, ff 60-61</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Copies of despatches sent under flying seal to the Governor General of India by his Excellency Mr Alison</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1865/1865</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-29T03:37:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Copies of 2 despatches from Tehran to The Right Honourable, The Earl Russell, Governor General of India:Copy of despatch No. 102, 1 October 1865, regarding British suspicions of a 'secret understanding' between the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Russian Minister regarding reducing Telegraph rates which would considerably increase the traffic on the Persian-Russian line, to the detriment of the Turkish line between Constantinople [Istanbul] and Fao [Faw]. The despatch goes on to report that Colonel Goldsmid has questioned the minister on the matter who assured him that the rates are those set out in the Russo-Persian Treaty however the information published by the 'Russian departmental authorities' suggests the rates are lower than the chargeable rate set out in the treaty.Copy of despatch No.105, 24 October 1865, enclosing a translation of a letter from the Agent at Meshed [Mashhad] reporting news from Central Asia and alleged movements by Persia towards Seistan [Sistan]. The enclosed letter, dated 10 October 1865, reports on the uniting of the Ameer [Amir] of Bokhara [Bukhara] and the ruler of Kokan [Kokand] against the Russians and the Russians offer to leave Kokan alone; Matters in Balkh and Kondooz [Kunduz] with Abder Rahman Khan [Abdur Rahman Khan] fleeing to Bokhara, Ameer Shere Ali Khan [Sher Ali Khan] taking the brother Mahomed Afzul Khan [Mohammad Afzal Khan] prisoner, Abder Rahman Khan departing Bokhara for Balkh with 3,000 Turkestan and Afghan soldiers and Ameer Shere Ali Khan going to Candahar [Kandahar] and taking Balkh, Kondooz and Serpool [Sar-e-pol] and from there going to Cabool [Kabul] instead of Herat in order to turn towards Turkestan. Other matters reported include the Turcoman horsemen of Subzawar [Sabzevar]'s raids and plundering of Caravans; Prince Tahmasp Mirza's plans to send an envoy to Candahar and Cabul and Mirza Mahomed Ali Khan being sent to Seistan and the likelihood that an army will follow him including details of the numbers of troops, infantry and horse likely to be sent.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024189687.0x000012#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>