<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000150_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T15:07:34.894Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000150_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/321</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000150</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000150/IOR_R_15_2_321_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/321</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/18 Iraq: Review of Events, 1933'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-05T21:10:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 28; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains an intelligence report and analysis of events and affairs in Iraq during the year 1933, produced by British Air Headquarters at Hinaidi, Iraq. The report is written by Wing Commander John L Vachell of Air Staff Intelligence.The report is divided into five main sections relating to a different subject. Each of these is further divided into sub-sections with a different focus, as follows:Section I - Political and Social: Home Politics; Social and Economic;Section II - Internal Security: Northern Iraq; Central and Southern Iraq;Section III - Industries and Resources: General Survey; Oil; Civil Aviation; The Desert Route;Section IV - Army and Air Forces: Iraq Army; Royal Iraq Air Force;Section V - Foreign Relations: Turkey; Persia; Saudi Arabia; Palestine; Syria.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000150#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>