<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000258_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T07:52:23.703Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000258_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1865</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000258</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000258/IOR_R_15_2_1865_00001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1865</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File B/9 I (30/9-II) Residency Agent, Sharjah’s News Reports’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-19T22:41:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (418 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 420; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Additional foliation sequences are present in parallel between ff 2-383, and ff 385-418; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a series of bi-monthly news summaries about events in Trucial Oman, for the years 1935 and 1936, compiled by the Residency Agent, Sharjah and sent to the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire. The news summaries are also referred to in the correspondence as the Residency Agent’s fortnightly diaries. They cover several topics including: air and sea traffic, kidnapping and raids by Bedouin, the diving and pearl trade, public health, theft and other crimes, relations between the ruling shaikhs, ceremonial visits and occasions in the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms. Particular attention is paid to the actions of the Trucial shaikhs with regard to the maintenance of law and order in their territories, such as the peaceful resolution of tribal conflicts, the protection of their subjects and the dispensation of justice.There are also letters from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to the Political Agent, Bahrain reporting cases of assault, murder and other incidents. The news summaries and letters from the Residency Agent, Sharjah are in both Arabic and English.In addition, there is protracted correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Political Resident about the protection of British Indian subjects from punishment according to Sharia Law, for an infringement of local laws in the Trucial States, by the creation of a Trucial Coast Order in Council, so that such offences would be prosecuted under Indian law by British authorities.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Trucial Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Administration of Justice</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trucial Coast Order in Council</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rulers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000258#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000258#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000258#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>