<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003c2_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T16:00:53.099Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003c2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/227</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003c2</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003c2/IOR_R_15_2_227_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/227</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/23 Visits of U.S. Naval Vessels to the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-02T15:21:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (52 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order. Circled index numbers written using red and blue crayon are also present in the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences on the page following the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil and can be found in the top right of the recto side of each folio. There is a gap between f. 37 and f. 41.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between Cornelius James Pelly, British Political Agent at Bahrain; Liuetenant-Colonel William Rupert Hay, British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bahrain; the Commonwealth Relations Office, London; the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf; Captain T R Frederick of the USS
                           Rendova; Ernest Bevin, Foreign Secretary; Shaikh Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah; and Shaikh ‘Abdullāh bin Jāsim Āl Thānī.The correspondence concerns visits of United States Naval ships to the Persian Gulf between 1947 and in 1949, including U.S.S.
                           Toledo(May 1947); U.S.S.
                           Valley Forge(March 1948); U.S.S.
                           Rendovaand U.S.S.
                           C H Roan(May 1948); USS
                           Greenwich Bay, USS
                           Carpellottiand USS
                           Siboney(August 1948); and USS
                           Maury(November 1949). There are details the United States Naval Task Force in the Persian Gulf and its photographic survey activities, as well as United States Navy relations with the British Agency and Residency at Bahrain, the Sheikhs of Bahrain and Qatar, Arab merchants, and the European and American communities in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003c2#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003c2#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>