<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100025472967.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T03:41:16.604Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100025472967.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/10/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100025472967.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100025472967.0x000001/IOR_L_MIL_17_15_10_1_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/10/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Military Report on S.-W. Persia, Vol. I. Bakhtiari Garmsir'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1909</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-19T01:25:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (80 folios)</extent><extent>The item consists of a single report and an accompanying map enclosed in a pocket on the inside back cover. A contents page at the front of the volume (f 4) and index at the rear (ff 72-79) both reference the volume’s original printed pagination.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 82; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>It consists of a military report on S W Persia, specifically Bakhtiari Garmsir [Bakhtīārī], created for the personal information of the officers of the Army in India. Compiled in the Division of the Chief of the Staff, Army Head Quarters, India. Printed at the Government Monotype Press, Simla, 1909.It includes: a preface by Wilfrid Malleson, Assistant Quarter-Master General, Intelligence Branch; an account of the tribal and political aspect of the district by the British Consul for Arabistan [Khūzestān], David Lockhart Robertson Lorimer; and a note on medical matters by Dr M Y Young of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited.It is divided into the following sections:general – geographical, geological, zoological, tribal, strategical, archaeological, and linguistic;military – climate, supplies, transport, communications, and medical;route reports - compiled in 1908 covering the whole area with a network of known tracks;Gazetteer notes – geographical information;appendices – including a statement of resources in the district, traffic returns, reports on the carrying capacity of steamers on the Kārūn and the tramway at Nasiri, genealogical trees, and a note on the operations of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company.Also includes one map on folio 81: 'MAP to illustrate Military Report on S.W. PERSIA'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government Monotype Press, Simla, publishers</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Quarter Master General's Department, Intelligence Branch</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Arabistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Division of the Chief of the Staff, Army Head Quarters, India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bakhtiari Garmsir</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100025472967.0x000001#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100025472967.0x000001#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>