<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000114_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T02:46:22.775Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000114_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1541</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000114</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000114/IOR_R_15_2_1541_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1541</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 16/36 Miscellaneous. Certificates for Animal casings and other articles exported from Bahrain – Countersigned by P.A.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-15T22:08:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (13 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 15; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 4-14; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and papers relating to the export of animal casings from Bahrain. An exchange of correspondence in 1932 between the Political Agent at Bahrain (Captain Charles Geoffrey Prior) and the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain (Charles Dalrymple Belgrave) refers to the question of authority for the issue of certificates for animal casings in Bahrain (ff 4-5). The remainder of the file is comprised of copies of certificates, all bar one of which are entitled ‘Foreign Official Certificate for Animal Casings’. The certificates detail packages of sheep casings exported to The Standard Casing Company Incorporated of New York, and are signed and stamped by the Political Agent and Manama Municipality. The remaining certificate refers to the physical health and lack of evidence of disease in three white Bahrain monkeys (f 8).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>The Standard Casing Company, Inc, New York</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Manamah Municipality</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Animal diseases</topic></subject><subject><topic>Animal products</topic></subject><subject><topic>Certificates</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000114#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000114#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>