<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019e_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T12:26:54.649Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3846</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019e</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019e/IOR_L_PS_12_3846_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3846</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/117 'Persian Gulf. Bahrain Grievances of the Baharinah.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-12-17T22:06:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (100 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 101; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 76-101; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The papers in this file relate to the grievances of the Baharnah (the native population of Bahrain). The papers include: The petition of the Baharnah to the Ruler of Bahrain Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa requesting the adoption of a
                           Qanun(code of laws) in the courts, proportional representation in the
                           Majalis al Tujjarahand
                           Baladiyyahat Manama and Muharraq, and restoration of their rights on the Board of Education, 30 December 1934-21 April 1936; the reservations of the Secretary of State for India the 2nd Marquess of Zetland about providing constitutional advice to the Gulf principalities, 20-27 September 1935; the instructions from the Government of India on reforming the courts of Bahrain, proportional representation, education, and pasturage of the Ruler’s camels, 6 November 1935-22 February 1936; the growth of popular movements in Kuwait, Debai [Dubai], and Bahrain, 18 July-16 November 1938; the agitation against the Shi’a
                           Shar’Court, Bahraini courts, and the educational system in Bahrain, a strike on the premises of the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO), and a demonstration in the bazaar at Manama, 31 October-24 November 1938; a request by Shaikh Hamad for the recruitment of two Egyptian or Sudanese magistrates to compile a civil and criminal ‘Bahrain Code’ from all previously issued
                           a’lansand to provide practical advice to current magistrates inside and outside the courts of Bahrain, 24 November 1938-5 August 1939; the report of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Lieutenant Colonel T C W Fowle to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department Sir Herbert Aubrey Francis Metcalfe on future policy towards popular agitation in Bahrain, 14 April-23 May 1939; and the Ruler of Dubai Shaikh Sa’id bin Maktoum Al Maktoum’s forcible dissolution of the
                           Majlisin Dubai, 5-15 June 1939.The correspondence in this file is primarily between the British Political Agent in Bahrain; Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire [Bushehr]; Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department; Foreign Secretary to the Government of India; Secretary of State for India; India Office; Secretary of the Government of India in the External Affairs Department; Foreign Office; HM Ambassador to Egypt; and the Ruler of Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Baharnah</topic></subject><subject><topic>Political representation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Proportional representation</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Manama</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Debai</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Courts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Legislation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Education</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reform movements</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019e#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019e#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019e#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>