<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000214_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-22T03:56:01.938Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000214_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1994</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000214</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000214/IOR_L_PS_12_1994_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1994</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/40 ‘Air Route to India (Persian Gulf): Increase in frequency of Imperial Airways Service’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-20T01:05:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (17 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 19; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is present between ff 15-18 and is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a notification from the Air Ministry (folio 18) dated 10 December 1934, informing the India Office of a proposal by Imperial Airways to duplicate their service between the United Kingdom (UK) and India. It also contains an explanatory note prepared for a meeting at the Air Ministry on 22 March 1935, on the necessity of introducing night flying between Cairo and Calcutta early in 1936, in order to facilitate the Empire Air Mail Scheme: see folios 2-6. A draft memorandum for transmission to HM representatives in Egypt, Palestine, and Iraq, outlines the facilities required in these countries to enable night flying: see folios 7-16.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Night flying</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Airways</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Palestine</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Egypt</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Air mail</topic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000214#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>