<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T15:38:06.336Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/198</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5/IOR_R_15_2_198_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/198</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'4/1 Bahrain State Finances 4'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-29T00:12:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (270 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present between ff 10-253; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out to prevent confusion with the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains copies of the financial records of the Government of Bahrain that were sent to the British Political Agency in Bahrain by Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. The records cover the years 1359-1363AH (1941-1945). These records include details of the expenditure and budget of the government. A number of lists containing details of the salaries and allowances of members of the Al Khalifa family are also included throughout the file.The file contains correspondence that discusses Bahrain's financial situation, notably details of how and where investments should be made for Bahrain's state reserve fund, details of Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa's [Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah] excessive spending habits and the impact of the Second World War on Bahrain.The file also contains copies (in English and Arabic) of correspondence between Charles Geoffrey Prior, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa.Of note are folios 198v and 199v, on which financial details from 1943/44 have been printed on the reverse of two unrelated British Government propaganda posters - presumably due to a paper shortage during war time.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0003a5#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>