<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001fe_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T07:03:20.124Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001fe_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/537</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001fe</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001fe/IOR_R_15_1_537_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/537</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/83 VII (D 147) Kuwait Iraq Smuggling'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T11:01:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (253 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.An index of topics discussed in the file is contained on folio 1C.</extent><extent>Condition: A bound correspondence volume.Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences at the title page and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.The file contains the following foliation errors: 1, 1A, 1B, 1C, and 1D and has the following omissions: 68, 126, 128, 131.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding alleged smuggling activities from Kuwait into Iraq. The majority of the correspondence discusses details regarding arms trafficking from Kuwait into Iraq and incursions into Kuwaiti territory made by Iraqi Customs and Police Forces.Primarily, the file contains internal correspondence between British officials. It also contains translated copies of correspondence between Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ, the ruler of Kuwait and the British Political Agent in Kuwait as well as correspondence between the British Embassy in Baghdad and the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs.The file contains a write-up of a meeting held at the Foreign Office in London in October 1938 that was attended by Taufiq Suwaidi, the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs (ff 125-129).The file also contains a report on arms traffic in the region from December 1938 that was compiled by a Saudi informant (ff 165-169). The report includes a comparative table of the prices of rifles and ammunition in Saudi Arabia, Iraq and Kuwait.A large hand-drawn map of the Arabian Peninsula is contained in the file on folio 173.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Smuggling</topic></subject><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001fe#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>