<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T17:49:32.952Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1014</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021d/IOR_R_15_2_1014_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1014</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/25 Correspondence re Additional Clerk (Confidential Clerk)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-02T00:06:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (244 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file. An index of names appears on f. 1A, but breaks off after only only two names and four references (covering the file as far as f. 8).</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 242 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1, 1A, 1B. The following folios need to be folded out to be read: 111, 212. There are two other foliation sequences: the first, numbered 58-230, runs through ff. 56-213, consists of numbers written in pencil in the same position as the main sequence, and is crossed through; the second, numbered 1-27, runs through most of the notes at the rear of the file, ff. 215-235, is written in pencil in the same position as the main sequence, and is also crossed through.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the appointment and service of holders of the position of Additional Clerk (Confidential Clerk from April 1937) at the Political Agency, Bahrain. The papers, which consist of correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, sanction orders, receipts, last pay certificates, other certificates, statements, office orders, and a bill of lading, cover the following topics: leave; appointment and transfer; travel arrangements and travel allowance; pay and allowances; house rent allowance; passport; correspondence concerning service books and last pay statements; recovery of sum owed for electricity; correspondence concerning medical certificates; addresses; correspondence concerning bill for health care, November 1939; resignation; accounts; and transport of personal effects.The covering dates of the correspondence in this file (the main body of papers) are 8 August 1935 to 3 January 1945. The closing date of the overall date range is supplied by an entry in the notes at the rear of the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Additional Clerk</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Clerk</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021d#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021d#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>