<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00001b_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T14:59:58.181Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00001b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B465</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00001b</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00001b/IOR_L_PS_18_B465_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B465</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Sultanate of Muscat and Oman [Oil concession agreement]'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-13T22:18:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single document.</extent><extent>The foliation sequence commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file is concerned with an agreement relating to an oil concession at Muscat, which was made between Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd], Sultan of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman, and Petroleum Concessions Limited on 24 June 1937. The agreement details the terms and conditions of the concession including the price to be paid to the Sultan by the company, the areas within which the company can drill for oil, and the rights to which the company will and will not have in undertaking their work. An amendment to the agreement is included on the final folio, and includes a prohibition against the importation of firearms by the company or its employees and a further prohibition against the importation and consumption of alcohol, except by foreign subjects (those who were not citizens of the Sultanate).The agreement was signed by the Sultan; Ralph Ponsonby Watts, Political Agent and HBM's Consul at Muscat; and Basil Henry Lermitte, on behalf of Petroleum Concessions Limited; on the 24 June 1937.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">signer</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">signer</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">witness</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Muscat</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00001b#share">Unknown</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>