<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000087_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-11-04T12:02:11.322Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000087_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F112/450</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000087</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000087/Mss Eur F112_450_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F112/450</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Volume II. MEMORANDA REGARDING OTHER EXTERNAL AFFAIRS. 1905.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1905/1905</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2019-08-23T00:41:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (110 folios)</extent><extent>The memoranda are arranged in chronological order within in each grouping from the front to the back of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 112; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains printed monthly memoranda of information received by the Government of India 'regarding external affairs other than those relating to the North-West Frontier, Afghanistan, and Persia' for the months of January to March 1905 inclusive (folios 4-17); memoranda of information received 'regarding external affairs relating to Arabia' for the months of April to December 1905 inclusive (folios 18-54); and memoranda of information received 'regarding external affairs relating to the North-East Frontier, Burma, Siam, and China', for the months of April to December 1905 inclusive (folios 55-108). A note accompanying each memorandum states that they are 'based upon reports, the accuracy of which it is not always possible to guarantee'.The combined 'other external affairs' reports (folios 4-17) relate to Arabia (Aden), Turkish Arabia, the Persian Gulf, China, Tibet, and Bhutan; the Arabia memoranda (folios 18-54) relate to Aden, Turkish Arabia, and the Persian Gulf; and the North-East Frontier etc. memoranda (folios 55-108) relate to Tibet, Bhutan, China, Siam [Thailand], Nepal, Burma, and Assam.Memoranda covering the Persian Gulf include intelligence reports concerning Maskat [Muscat], Koweit [Kuwait], Nejd [Najd], Bahrein [Bahrain], Katif [Al-Qatif], El Katr/Katar [Qatar], the Arab Coast, Musandim [Musandam], and the Pirate Coast.The memoranda relating to Arabia include references to the following subjects: political intelligence, tribal affairs, relations with the Ottoman Government, frontier settlement, pearl fisheries, quarantine, and slavery.The memoranda regarding affairs on and beyond the North-East Frontier of India cover a similar broad range of political and economic intelligence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Aden</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>China</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Siam</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Burma</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Turkish Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Political intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000087#share">Creative Commons Attribution Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>