<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000097_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T13:07:18.747Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000097_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/280</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000097</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000097/IOR_R_15_2_280_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/280</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 7/14 I R.A.F. wards in Bahrain Govt. hospital’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-02T00:06:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (12 folios)</extent><extent>The contents of the file have been arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest items at the front to the latest at the rear. Circled index numbers written in blue and red crayon can also be found throughout the volume, which refer to the office notes at the end of the file (folio 12).</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence begins on the front cover and finishes on the back cover; using numbers written in pencil, found in the top-right corner of each recto. Foliation anomalies: 1 and 1A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The correspondence in the file relates to a request for new arrangements in the allocation of wards at the Bahrain Government Hospital. In March 1945 Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, formally made a request to the Political Agent at Bahrain that the one or both of the wards at the hospital, currently reserved for patients of the Royal Navy, Army, and RAF, be transferred back to the Bahrain Government (folios 1A-3). The request was relayed to RAF Iraq and Persia Headquarters, with acceptance of the transfer being confirmed in January 1946 (folio 10).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000097#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000097#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>