<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000a8_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T01:14:52.161Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000a8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1433</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000a8</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000a8/IOR_R_15_2_1433_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1433</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 15/1 Vol IV Rules and Regulations Finance Department Circulars received from the Government of India’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-16T00:02:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (269 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged chronologically, according to the date they were circulated to the Political Agent, Bahrain and others.</extent><extent>Foliation: numbered 1A, 1B, 2-142, 143, 143A, 143B, 144-145, 147-202, 203A, 203B, 204-269. Folio 145 has been additionally numbered 146 on the verso. The numbering is written mainly in pencil in the top right corner of the folio, starting at the front of the file, on the file cover (f 1A) and ending on the inside cover at the back of the file (f 269).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists mainly of Government of India circulars issued by the Finance Department, which were circulated by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to the Political Agent, Bahrain and others, for information and guidance. They are routine notifications of amendments to regulations and procedures governing the appointment, pay, pension and other conditions of service of Government of India employees, such as their entitlement to leave and travel expenses, their contributions to the General Provident Fund and other Indian Civil Service family welfare funds.The file contains correspondence between the Government of India Finance Department and the India Office, London about amendments to Article 934 of the Civil Service Regulations (CSR) with regard to the rate of exchange to be applied to Government of India rupee pensions. Also discussed is the provision of a temporary concession for Ghurkha pensioners of the Indian Army resident in Nepal, experiencing hardship owing to the depreciation in Nepal of the Indian rupee, attributed to war conditions.The earliest document in the file is a copy of an office memorandum dated 1938 (folio 95). It was recirculated in 1945 to remind government officials of the instructions it contains (folio 94). The majority of documents in the file date from 1944 onwards.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000a8#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>