<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024c_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-11-08T18:13:20.559Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1029</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024c</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024c/IOR_R_15_2_1029_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1029</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/38 Papers regarding the Appointment of a Driver-Mechanic for the Motor Car of the Political Agent, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-03T00:14:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (54 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the third page after the front cover, and finishes at 47 on the second page before the back cover. None of the folios omitted from this sequence (apart from the front cover) has any text. The sequence is written in pencil and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 28, 28B, 28C.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to holders of the position of Driver (Chauffeur) at the Political Agency, Bahrain. The papers consist of correspondence and memoranda, and cover the following topics: request for advance of pay in order to pay off personal debts; discharge from service; enquiries to find a suitable replacement Driver for the Agency; references of candidates; terms and conditions of appointment; appointment of new Driver; provision of driving licence; and leave. The file includes one letter in Arabic.The correspondence in this file covers the period 30 October 1935 to 1 April 1937. The overall date range is supplied by entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Chauffeur</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024c#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024c#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>