<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100048155982.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T13:41:53.214Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100048155982.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 9128</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100048155982.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100048155982.0x000001/Or 9128_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 9128</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb al-taysīr fī al-mudāwāt wa-al-tadbīr كتاب التيسير في المداواة والتدبير  Ibn Zuhr, ʻAbd al-Malik ibn Abī al-ʻAlāʼ ابن زهر، عبد الملك بن أبي العلاء</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1300/1399</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-30T22:01:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. iv+234+ii</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 234 x 171 mm leaf [197 x 130 mm written]Foliation: Eastern Arabic foliation in black ink (begins at 1 at beginning of each section [جزء]: ff. 1r, 117r and 212r); British Museum foliation in pencilRuling: No ruling visible; 17 lines per page; vertical spacing 9 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           MaghribīInk: Black ink, with some marginal headings in red and green inkDecoration: NoneBinding: British Museum half-leather binding; damage to f. 155 indicates that the manuscript was previously bound in a binding with a flapCondition: All folios guarded; some margins mutilated and repaired, worse towards front and back of volume; insect damage, some repaired with silk gauze; minor iron-gall ink corrosion, some repaired with silk gauze; f. 1r mostly illegible due to abrasion, insect damage and overlaid silk gauze; damage with loss of text on f. 155 due to iron-gall ink corrosionMarginalia: Few by more than one handSeals: None</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Medical compendium on drug therapy, dietetics and pharmacopoeia by the Andalusian physician Abū Marwān ‘Abd al-Malik ibn Abī al-‘Alā’ Zuhr (أبو مروان عبد الملك بن أبي العلاء زهر, d. 1162), known as Ibn Zuhr (ابن زهر), Latinised as Avenzoar.The text is divided into three sections (أجزاء) or books (أسفار):Book One (السفر الأول, ff. 1r-115r);Section Two (الجزء الثاني, ff. 117r-211r);Section Three (الجزء الثالث, ff. 211v-234r).The last page (f. 234r) has been replaced by a much later hand.Begins (f. 1r, lines 4-5):كتاب التيسير في المداواة والتدبيرقال عبد الملك بن زهر الحمد لله ...Ends (f. 234r, lines 3-7):وجعلت هذا الجزء لكتابي هذا كالختم وجعلت هذاالقانون الكلي والطريق السهل ختمًا أيضًا فإن يكنأمانة بتوفيق الله تعلى (!) وإن يكن تقصير فقد اجتهدتوالله تعلى (!) شاهدي وهو سبحانه ينفع بكتابي ويعليأمرك وذكرك بمنه والسلام ...Colophon (f. 234r, lines 7-8):... تم الكتاب بحمد الله وحسنعونه وصلى الله على سيدنا ومولانا محمد</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>‘Abd al-Malik ibn Abī al-‘Alā’ Ibn Zuhr</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100048155982.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>