<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023667258.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T18:16:46.157Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023667258.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IO Islamic 1148, ff 1v-63r</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023667258.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100022506131.0x000001/IO Islamic 1148_0019.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IO Islamic 1148, ff 1v-63r</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>تحرير المجسطي Taḥrīr al-Majisṭī  طوسي، نصير الدين محمد بن محمد Ṭūsī, Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1322/1322</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-21T00:10:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>ff. 1v-63r</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Naṣīr al-Dīn al-Ṭūsī's (AD 1201-1274) edition (تحرير) of the Arabic translation of the
                           Almagest(كتاب المجسطي), an Arabic version of the Μαθηματικῆς σύνταξις of Ptolemy (Claudius Ptolemaeus; AD c 90-c 168), thought to have been translated by Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq al-‘Ibādī (AD c 809-873).The copy was completed on 6 Muḥarram 722/25 January 1322, at Sulṭānīyah (in the Zanjan province in the north-west of modern Iran) by Ḥamzah ibn ‘Alī ibn Ḥamzah al-Qazwīnī al-Bayhaqī, known as Sa‘d al-Khurāsānī (حمزة بن على بن حمزة القزويني البيهقي المشهور بسعد الخراساني; see colophon on f. 62r; transcribed below). Two notes next to the colophon, both in the hand of the copyist, state that his exemplar was a copy of the author's own copy, and that he collated his copy in Muḥarram 723/January-February 1323, at Sulṭānīyah, in the Rashīdīyah Madrasah.Almost no diacritical points are use, so the following transcriptions are imprecise.Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-5):الحمد لله مبداء كال مبادئ غاية كل غايب ومفيض كل خير وولي كل هدانة ...وبعد فقد كنت برهة من الزمان عازمًا على أن أحرّر لنفسي ولسائر طلبة العلم من الإخوان كتاب المجسطي المنسوب إلىبطلميوس القلوذي ...Ends (f. 62r, lines )... وأقول وإذ وقفني الله تعلاى لا تمام ما قصد به وإنجاز ما وعد به فلا قطع الكلام حامدًا لهعلى الأية ومصليًا على جميع أوليائه خصوصًا على خاتم أنبيائه وبردة من آله واحتابهColophon (f. 62r, lines )... وقد اتفق الفراغ من انتساخه يوم الثلثاءلست خلون من محرّم الحرام عام اثنتين وعشرين وسبعمائة هجرية بمدينة سلطانية أقار الله تعالى برهان بابها بأحواج عباد اللهحالي إلى رحمته حمزة بن على بن حمزة القزويني البيهقي المشهور بسعد الخراساني سائلًا من ربه الهدانة إلى سواء الطريق والتوفيقلكشف المحصلات بالتحقيق أنّه ولي الإجابةThis text is followed by two short supplements (ff. 62v-63r), both related to Ptolemy's
                           Almagest. The first is inscribed في تشكل الزهرة في الفصل الثاني من المقالة العاشرة من المجسطي (
                           Fī tashakkulal-zuharah fī al-faṣl al-thānī min al-maqālah al-‘āshirah min al-Majisṭī, 'On the formation of Venus in Part two of Chapter ten of the
                           Almagest'; f. 62v, line 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript item</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Claudius Ptolemaeus (Ptolemy)</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad Ṭūsī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq al-'Ibādī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Astronomy--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023667258.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>