<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000263_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T13:47:41.296Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000263_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/1241</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000263</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000263/IOR_L_PS_10_1241_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/1241</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 57/1928 Pt 10 'Nejd-Transjordanian Frontier: Situation. 1928-29'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-10-09T22:01:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (892 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. The subject 57 (Iraq-Nejd Relations) consists of sixteen volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/1234-1249. The volumes are divided into nineteen parts, with each part comprising one volume, apart from parts 4-5, 7-8, and 17-18, which each comprise a single volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 888; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 338-888; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume concerns the situation on the frontier between Transjordan and the Kingdom of Hejaz [al-Ḥijāz] and Nejd (usually referred to separately as Hejaz or Nejd), particularly in terms of crossborder raids into both states.The papers cover: reports of raids (dates, identity of leaders, locations, casualties, and details of camels and other property looted); reports of the alleged crossing of the Nejd frontier by British aircraft from Transjordan, including an apology by the British Government for one such incident in May 1929; the levying of customs duties on the border; reports of raids from Transjordan into Nejd; complaints about raids into Nejd by Ibn Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd], and officials of the Government of Hejaz and Nejd; arms trafficking; the British response to raids from Transjordan (the British admitted the validity of Ibn Saud's complaints, folio 618); frontier infringements by government officials; measures for the protection of caravans (folios 439-441); British protests over raids into Transjordan; records of interdepartmental discussions by British officials concerning the raids; a despatch concerning the raids from the High Commissioner for Transjordan, including a report by Air Vice Marshall Hugh Caswall Tremenheere Dowding (folios 290-318); papers concerning the investigations of Mervyn Sorley MacDonnell, who was appointed by the British Government to examine claims arising from the raids; and suggestions that arms and ammunition landed at Jeddah were for the use of tribesmen on the Transjordan 'front', September 1930.The volume includes correspondence from: the Colonial Office; the Foreign Office; the High Commissioner for Transjordan; HM Agent and Consul, Jeddah; HM Chargé d’Affaires, Jeddah; HM Minister, Jeddah; Ibn Saud; and Fuad Hamza, Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, Kingdom of Hejaz and Nejd.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Raids (Military science)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Hejaz and Najd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Palestine and Transjordan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Saudi Arabia, Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Frontiers</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arbitration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000263#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000263#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000263#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>