<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00022f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T00:12:56.998Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00022f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/664</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00022f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00022f/IOR_L_PS_10_664_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/664</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 815/1917 Pt 13 'Persian Gulf: lighting and buoying service; Shatt al-Arab Conservancy Board'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-11-23T23:11:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (338 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 815 (Persian Gulf) consists of 6 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/659-664. The volumes are divided into 13 parts, with part 1 (A-G) comprising one volume, part 2 comprising the second volume, parts 3-9 comprising the third volume, part 10 comprising the fourth volume, parts 11-12 comprising the fifth volume, and part 13 comprising the sixth volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 340; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The volume has one foliation anomaly, f 89a.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume is composed of interdepartmental correspondence relating to the future administration of the lighting and buoying service in the Persian Gulf.The correspondence discusses the possibility of control of buoying and lighting in the Persian Gulf being transferred to the Government of Persia. At this time the service was being maintained by the Royal Indian Marine, with its financing being shared between the British Imperial Government (specifically the Foreign Office) and the Government of India. The correspondence includes the point of view of the Government of India on the suggestion that the Shatt-Al-Arab Conservancy board should also be responsible for lighting and buoying along the Gulf coast. Furthermore, it discusses the major point to be settled in the present negotiations with Persia during 1928-30, which is the international boundary in the Shatt-el-Arab, as defined in the Treaty of Erzurum of 1847, and the Persia-Turkish Frontier Delimitation Agreement of 1913. The correspondence then moves on to cover the organisation and discussion of the tripartite conference taking place in Iraq regarding the future administration of the lighting and buoying service on the coast of the Persian Gulf, with the participating countries being Iraq, Persia and Great Britain (with India).Notable correspondents include the following: the Viceroy of India; the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf; the High Commissioner Iraq; the Director of the Royal Indian Marine; officials of the India Office, the Foreign Office, the Admiralty, the Treasury, and the Government of India's Marine Department; the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf; the Commander-in-Chief of the Royal Navy, East India Section; the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Iraq; the Government of Iraq; the Council of Ministers, Iraq; the Port Directorate in Basra.In addition to correspondence, the volume contains the following: minutes of an interdepartmental conference held at the India Office in 1931 (ff 26-28), copies of an India Office memorandum entitled 'Memorandum on the Lighting and Buoyage of the Persian Gulf', dated 1931 (ff 62-64).The volume includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Lighting Service</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Council of Ministers</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Indian Marine, Director</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Navy, Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Port Directorate, Basra</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Lights</topic></subject><subject><topic>Buoys</topic></subject><subject><topic>Lighthouses</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00022f#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00022f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>