<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000138_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T16:23:32.637Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000138_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/18</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000138</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000138/IOR_L_MIL_17_15_18_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/18</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘A Report on the Tribes of Fars’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-19T22:14:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (89 folios)</extent><extent>A general index at the front of the report (f 5) and a detailed index at the rear (ff 81-87) both reference the report’s original pagination sequence.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 91; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Confidential report on the tribes of the Fars region of Persia [Iran], produced by Captain A J Christian of the General Staff, Shiraz, 1918. The report was printed at the Government Monotype Press, Simla [Shimla], 1919.The report covers a number of tribal groupings: the Khamseh, Qashgai [Qashqai], Mamassani, Lashani, Mishmast, Boir Ahmadi, and Dushmanziari [Doshman Zīārī]. Aspects covered include: origins and history of tribes; organisation; assessments of their general character; habitat; strength and fighting strength (expressed as numbers of men); arms and ammunition; language; revenue; subtribes. The bulk of the report is given over the Qashgai tribe, with detailed descriptions of its subtribes, and seven appendices (labelled A to G) as follows:appendix A – a genealogical table of the Qashgai Ilkhanis;B – notes on some of the Qashgai Khans;C – weights, measures, coinage used by the Qashgai;D – archaeological remains associated with the Qashgai;E – mineralogical deposits in areas associated with the Qashgai;F – agriculture of the Qashgai;G – the Amaleh.The report finishes with a list of smaller tribes, giving details of their leader, number of families, and habitat. The volume contains a single map of the Fars district, with areas occupied by some of the tribes indicated (folio 90).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>General Staff Branch, India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government Monotype Press, Simla, publishers</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Qashqai (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Fars</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Surveys</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000138#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>