<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-11-27T01:17:26.279Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/F/4/182/3486</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370/IOR_F_4_182_3486_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/F/4/182/3486</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Measures adopted for the recovery of the country ship
                              Alert, seized by her Native Crew, who after murdering her European captain and officers carried her into Mockulla on the coast of Arabia’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1804/1805</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2019-03-19T22:02:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (32 folios)</extent><extent>The contents of the item have been arranged chronologically from the front to the rear.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description (used for referencing) commences at f 94, and terminates at f 125, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the bottom right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This item consists of different extracts of the Bombay Public Consultations, regarding an act of piracy and murder that was reportedly committed by the native crew of the country ship
                           Alert. The
                           Alertwas bound for Bengal port laden with dispatches principally belonging to the East India Company. The letters report that part of her native crew seized the ship, murdered the European Captain and officers, and sailed the ship to the port of Mockulla [Mukalla] on the coast of Arabia.The item contains a description of the act of piracy on the
                           Alertship and its aftermath, including the following: measures taken by the Company to secure the return of the ship; negotiations with the Hakim regarding the restitution of the
                           Alertand her cargo; reports from the Customs Master at Bombay; the involvement of the
                           Princess Augustacruiser; the appointment of a commissioner, Samuel Sparks, to start negotiations with Hakim on the restitution of the
                           Alertand its cargo; a memorandum on the
                           Alert'scargo.Notable correspondents include the following: James Augustus Grant, Secretary to the Government of Bombay; Jonathan Duncan, Governor of Bombay; Forbes &amp; Co; Virja Nanjis Searkrun; the East India Company's Broker in Mocha; Sir John Malcolm; Samuel Sparks, Commissioner; the Phoenix Assurance Company; John Pringle, Resident at Mocha.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival item</genre><subject><geographic>Mockulla</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Cargo ships</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Alert, brig</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bombay, Chief Secretary</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Freight transport</topic></subject><subject><topic>Homicide</topic></subject><subject><topic>Piracy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001673.0x000370#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>