<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0001f0_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-22T02:57:53.507Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0001f0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1958</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0001f0</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0001f0/IOR_L_PS_12_1958_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1958</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/13 ‘Afghanistan: Reports on condition of Afghan Air Force’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-20T23:41:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (51 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 53; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 9-26; these numbers are also written in pencil or printed, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a number of reports submitted by Francis Henry Humphrys, HM Minister at Kabul, regarding the Afghan Air Force and the development of aviation in Afghanistan. These reports generally provide information on the following: the aircraft in use, the personnel employed, the armament available, the equipment and fuel stores, details on flight operations, and ground facilities.Two particularly substantial reports included are as follows:A report on a conversation held by HM Minister with Mr Patwardhan of the Afghan Air Force in September 1926 (see folio 46).A report dated 7 January 1929 by C W L Trusk of the Royal Air Force on observations made between 18 December 1928 and 7 January 1929 (see folios 9-26 typed copy, and folios 27-32 for printed copy).The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Afghan Air Force</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0001f0#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>