<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036e_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:32:28.778Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B372</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036e</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036e/IOR_L_PS_18_B372_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B372</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from Sir Frederic Aarthur Hirtzel, India Office, to the Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, dated 13 Sep 1922</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1922/1922</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T09:24:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: The volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This secret printed memorandum is a copy of a letter from Sir Frederic Arthur Hirtzel, India Office, to the Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, dated 13 Sep 1922, concerning the proposed amendment of the articles of the Treaty of Sévres which have been represented as interfering with the 'spiritual power' of the Caliph. The letter is accompanied by a section of enclosures (folios 2-5) which includes fourteen enclosures consisting of various telegrams between the Secretary of State and the Viceroy of India, the Foreign Secretary of the Government of India and the India Office dated between 21 March 1922 and 1 September 1922. Enclosure No 7 includes an annex which is a minute entitled 'The Caliph's Religious Position' by Sir Muhammad Shafi.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Deputy Under-Secretary of State for India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Khan Bahadur Mian Muhammad Shafi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Treaty of Sèvres (1920)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Islam</topic></subject><subject><topic>Caliphate</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00036e#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>