<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T00:42:05.400Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3517</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d/IOR_L_PS_12_3517_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3517</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/106 ‘Persia. Infiltration of British agents.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-14T22:05:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (52 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 54; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, some marked Most Secret, discussing ways in which British agents could be deployed in Persia [Iran] and other countries in the region (Iraq, Afghanistan) to counter German influence during the Second World War. The correspondence discusses: how British firms operating in Iran could recruit employees to act as agents; the redeployment and use of existing consular staff in Iran for intelligence purposes; the use of British (or European) engineers on Iranian water irrigation schemes, to counter German influence in that area; the distribution of British propaganda in Iran. The file’s principal correspondents are: the British Ambassador at Tehran, Reader William Bullard; the Foreign Office; the External Affairs Department of the Government of India.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Spies</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00004d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>