<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-20T13:41:37.778Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/521/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a0/IOR_L_PS_10_521_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/521/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'P. 5085/1914 Pt 2 German War: Turkey: Jedda; British interests'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-16T22:08:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (50 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, printed reports and notes, relating to the Consulate Affairs in Jeddah. The discussion in the volume relates to the withdrawal of the British consul from Jeddah with the declaration of war with the Ottoman Empire and arrangements for the maintenance of the building and payment of staff.Further discussion surrounds correspondence with Italy and the Netherlands over such arrangments and the refusal of the Turkish Government to allow the American Consular Agent in Aden to visit Jeddah. The correspondence also discusses arrangements for the safety of British subjects conducting pilgrimage to Mecca.The principal correspondents in the volume include the Viceroy; the Political Resident, Aden, the Paymaster General's Office; the Under-Secretary of State for India and the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed in the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>