<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000ee_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:09:21.838Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000ee_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B79</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000ee</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000ee/IOR_L_PS_18_B79_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B79</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memoir on Part of Mesopotamia contained between Sheriat-el-Beytha on the Tigris to Tel Ibrahim, by Lieutenant J B Bewsher, Surveyor in Mesopotamia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1866/1866</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-24T00:18:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (7 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 113, and terminates at f 119, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is a memoir that describes part of Mesopotamia [Iraq] between Sheriat-el-Beytha (ten miles north-west of Baghdad) and the large mound of Tel Ibrahim (nineteen miles north-east of Hillah). The memoir contains details of historical sites, agriculture and irrigation in the region.The memoir was written by Lieutenant J B Bewsher, Commanding Her Majesty's Ship
                           Comet,B. M. and Surveyor in Mesopotamia.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0000ee#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>