<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001598.0x0000f0_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T17:01:49.764Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001598.0x0000f0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Royal MS 16 A VIII</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001598.0x0000f0</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001598.0x0000f0/Royal MS 16 A VIII_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Western Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Royal MS 16 A VIII</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Taḥrīr kitāb al-majisṭī تحرير كتاب المجسطي  Ptolemy بطلميوس  Ṭūsī, Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad  طوسي، نصير الدين محمد بن محمد</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1400/1599</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-01-10T00:12:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. iv+192+iv</extent><extent>Physical characteristics:Material: Paper (beige with some light red leaves)Dimensions: 199 x 123 mm leaf [127 x 59 mm written]Foliation: Pagination in pencil of even-numbered pages in Western Arabic numerals (above) and British Museum foliation in pencil (below)Ruling: none visible; 23 lines per page; vertical spacing 18 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           NaskhInk: Black ink, with headings, tables and figures in gold and some table text in redDecoration: Text area on all pages bordered in gold; frontispiece in blue, green, red, black and gold (f. 2v)Binding: British Museum binding in brown leather with gilt-tooled double border and decorations on edges of boards; initials M.B. (Museum Britannicum) gilt-tooled on left board; marbled paper pastedownsCondition: Excellent; some water damage and foxing towards back of volumeMarginalia: Interlinear Latin glosses in pencil (ff. 1v-2r)Seals: f. 1r</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The Almagest (كتاب المجسطي), an Arabic version of the Μαθηματικῆς σύνταξις of Ptolemy (Claudius Ptolemaeus; c 90-c 168), in the annotated edition (تحرير) of Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad al-Ṭūsī (نصير الدين محمد بن محمد الطوسي; d. 1274). This was the most influential and enduring astronomical text to have survived from the ancient world and its Arabic translation, and al-Ṭūsī's annotated edition in particular, had an immense impact on the medieval world view in both Christian and Islamic lands.The text is divided into thirteen chapters (مقالات) further subdivided into sections (فصول), and contains numerous diagrams and tables.Contents:Chapter One (المقالة الأولى; ff. 2r-23r);Chapter Two (المقالة الثانية; ff. 23r-39v);Chapter Three (المقالة الثالثة; ff. 39v-51v);Chapter Four (المقالة الرابعة; ff. 51v-67v);Chapter Five (المقالة الخامسة; ff. 67v-85r);Chapter Six (المقالة السادسة; ff. 85r-100v);Chapter Seven (المقالة السابعة; ff. 100v-114v);Chapter Eight (المقالة الثامنة; ff. 115r-130v);Chapter Nine (المقالة التاسعة; ff. 130v-150r);Chapter Ten (المقالة العاشرة; ff. 150v-155v);Chapter Eleven (المقالة الحادية عشر; ff. 155v-169r);Chapter Twelve (المقالة الثانية عشر; ff. 169r-178v);Chapter Thirteen (المقالة الثالثة عشر; ff. 178v-191v).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-9):أحمد الله مبدأ كلّ مبدأ وغاية كلّ غاية ومفيض كلّ خير وولي كلّ ميدانهوأرجو حسن توفيقه في كلّ بداية ونهاية وأصلّي على عباده المخصوصينبالعناية والدراية سيّما على محمد وآله الموسومين بالنبوة والولايةالمنقذين من كلّ عماية وغواية وبعد فقد كنت برتبه (؟) من الزمانعان ما على أن أحرّر لنفسي ولطلبته العلم من الإخوان كتاب المجسطيالمنسوب إلى بطلميوس القلوذي الذي هو الدستور العظيم لأصحابصناعة الهيئة والتنجيم تحريرًا لا يفوته مقاصد ذلك الكتاب النظريةومناهجه العليّة ...Ends (f. 191v, lines 5-10):... وأقول وإذ وفقنيالله تعالى أيضًا لا تمام ما قصدته وإنجان ما وعدتهفلا قطع الكلام حامدًا له على آلائه ومصليًّاعلى جميع أوليائه خصوصًا على خاتمأنبيائه والبردة من آله وأحبّائه</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad Ṭūsī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Claudius Ptolemaeus (Ptolemy)</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Islamic astronomy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy, Ancient</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy, Arab</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy, Greek</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy--Mathematics</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy, Medieval</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy, Roman</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy--Tables</topic></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001598.0x0000f0#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001598.0x0000f0#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>