<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000007_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T19:04:30.511Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000007_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>1781.b.6/69</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000007</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100022547736.0x000001/1781.b.6_0120.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>1781.b.6/69</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Pilger aus Korintji (Sumátra)'. Photographer: Christiaan Snouck Hurgronje</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1888/1888</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-23T05:12:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ger</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 collotype print</extent><extent>Dimensions:187 x 246 mmFormat:1 collotype printCondition:The print is in good condition.Foliation:‘XXXIV’</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Genre/Subject Matter:This full-length seated portrait shows five pilgrims from Korintji (Koerintji) in Indonesia and a sixth man described as a sheikh who comes from Korintji. They sit or squat face forward, looking towards the camera.From right to left the men wear: a white
                           thawband white skull cap; a pale-coloured shirt, checked trousers and white turban; white
                           thawband turban; dark jacket, white button-up shirt, checked turban and a ring on the little finger of his right hand; white
                           thawb, turban and a ring on the little finger of his right hand; white shirt under a striped waistcoat, white trousers, hat and a ring on the little finger of his right hand. All five men at the front hold pieces of paper in their hands while the man second from right holds a cloth in this left hand.The men are photographed in a courtyard-like space with plants – some in wide wooden pots – foliage and a window, fronted by bars, visible in the background.The negative has had hand-work applied, causing it to take on a soft-shaded paint-like quality in places.Inscriptions:Printed above image, in ink:XXXIVPrinted beneath image, in ink:‘Pilger aus Korintji (Sumátra); der hinter ihnen sitzende Schēch stammt auch aus Korintji.’A circular 'British Museum' blind stamp is located in the lower left corner.</abstract><typeOfResource>still image</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Photograph</genre><subject><topic>Portrait photography</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000007#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>