<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000dd_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T03:58:46.067Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000dd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3659</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000dd</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000dd/IOR_L_PS_12_3659_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3659</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/83 'Expenditure on the Bahrain, Muscat and Kuwait Agencies'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1911/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T10:50:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (110 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 112; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns expenditures on the Political Agencies at Bahrain, Muscat and Kuwait.The file covers:proposal by Government of India that Imperial Revenues should bear half the expenditure at Bahrain and Muscat, in particular: cost of dispensary and medical work on the Trucial Coast and creation of the role of Assistant Political Agent at Bahrain, 1936provision of accommodation for the staff of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf when on tour at Bahrain, 1936recovery of electrical charges in respect of offices and public portions of residential buildings in the Persian Gulf, 1938Muscat Political Agency Office allowance, 1938water-borne sanitation in the Political Agency Building at Bahrain, 1938repairs to the roof of the verandah at the Political Agency Building at Bahrain, 1939air-conditioning of buildings at Muscat and Kuwait, 1946.The file is composed of correspondence between the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the Political Agency at Bahrain, the Foreign Office, the India Office, and the Government of India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000dd#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>