<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000218_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T17:47:44.699Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000218_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2992</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000218</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000218/IOR_L_PS_12_2992_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2992</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/32 'Muscat: Question of succession to Sultanate'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-13T22:19:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (30 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 32; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the question of a successor for the Sultan of Muscat, Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd]. The principal correspondents are officials at the Political Agency in Muscat, Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, and the Government of India (External Affairs Department).The file contains:correspondence regarding the Sultan's wish to discuss the question of his successor with the Political Resident (folios 27-31)correspondence, including with Buckingham Palace, following the birth of the Sultan's son in 1940 conveying messages of congratulation and thanks (folios 10-23)correspondence, including with the Foreign Office, discussing the Sultan's request that a British Officer act as regent in the event of his early death (folios 3-9)an extract from Muscat Intelligence Summary No. 5, 16-29 February 1940, in which details of the visit to Muscat of Major Jenabi of the Iraq Air Force are given, including his questioning of the Political Agent over Iraqi press reports of the British role in the accession of the current Sultan (folio 26).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Kings and rulers--Succession</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000218#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>