<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T13:32:06.684Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/1240</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262/IOR_L_PS_10_1240_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/1240</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 57/1928 Pt 9 'Iraq-Nejd Relations: Discussions with Ibn Saud.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-10-10T22:01:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (751 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. The subject 57 (Iraq-Nejd Relations) consists of sixteen volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/1234-1249. The volumes are divided into nineteen parts, with each part comprising one volume, apart from parts 4-5, 7-8, and 17-18, which each comprise a single volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 747; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 132-747; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume concerns relations between Iraq (and Koweit [Kuwait]), and the Kingdom of Hijaz [al-Ḥijāz], Nejd, and Dependencies (usually referred to as Nejd), and its King, Ibn Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd], particularly in terms of raids along the frontier between the states by Akhwan [Ikhwan] tribesmen (also referred to as 'Wahabis').In addition to India Office correspondence and memoranda, the file includes correspondence from: the Colonial Office, the Foreign Office, the Air Ministry, the High Commissioner for Iraq, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the British Agent and Consul, Jeddah, the Political Agent, Kuwait, and Ibn Saud.The volume covers: the response to the mission of Sir Gilbert Falkingham Clayton to Ibn Saud in 1928; proposals for arbitration over matters in dispute between Iraq and Nejd; reconnaissance of landing grounds on the Hasa coast, December 1928; intelligence on tribal movements; reports of Akhwan raids (especially by the Mutair [Muṭayr], Harb, Shammar, and Ajman [‘Ajmān]); reports by Captain John Bagot Glubb, Administrative Inspector, Southern Desert, Government of Iraq; proposals for air action against the Akhwan; the interpretation of the Uqair (also referred as Ojair) Protocol; references to the death of Henry Arjen Bilkert, an American citizen, who was killed by the Akhwan (e.g. folio 252); the question of the pursuit of raiders across the Nejd frontier; complaints by Ibn Saud and the Government of Nejd against the activities of Captain Glubb; the policy of the Shaikh of Kuwait towards Nejdi rebels taking refuge in his territory; minutes of interdepartmental conferences, and drafts of a proposed agreement, concerning arbitration between Iraq and Nejd; correspondence concerning the alleged execution of eight Nejdis by the British and Iraqi authorities, April-May 1929; and papers concerning the interpretation of Article 6 of the Bahra Agreement.The volume also contains a copy of the Bahra Agreement, between the British Government and Ibn Saud, dated 1 November 1925.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Raids (Military science)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Hejaz and Najd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ikhwan, military and religious brotherhood</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Frontiers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000262#share">Copyright or data protection restrictions</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>