<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T17:46:24.401Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1011</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a/IOR_R_15_2_1011_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1011</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/24 III Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-15T00:03:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (306 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1A on the front cover, and continues through to 330 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1A, 1B, 1C; ff. 23A, 23B; ff. 55A, 55B; ff. 104A, 104B; ff. 115A, 115B; ff. 135A, 135B; ff. 140A, 140B; ff. 141A, 141B; ff. 258A, 258B. The following numbers not appear in the sequence: 85, 196-202. Pagination ranges: 68-69, 166-67, 273-76, 279-98. A second foliation sequence, numbered 1-8, runs through the notes at the rear of the file between ff. 315-22. These numbers are also written in pencil, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the appointment and service of holders of the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.The papers, which include correspondence, certificates, claim forms for the payment of overseas pay in England, charge certificates, telegrams, last pay certificates, draft notifications, forms, memoranda, personal letters, and sanction orders, cover the following topics: enquiry from Government of India concerning qualifications, October 1936; leave; leave salary; certificate that the holder was a Government servant; pay and allowances; correspondence concerning charge certificates and last pay statements; travel arrangements and expenses; notes on etiquette in the light of a visit from the Ruler of Bahrain, December 1936; correspondence with banks; correspondence with the office of the Accountant-General, Central Revenues of the Government of India; correspondence concerning Departmental examinations; appointment; complaint from Political Agent about continual changing of Assistant Political Agents, June 1937; administrative arrangements in the absence of the Political Agent, July 1937; cook, February 1938; correspondence concerning the Indian Military Widows and Orpans Fund; bilingual correspondence in English and Arabic with the Residency Agent, Sharjah; and bilingual correspondence in English and Arabic with various Gulf rulers concerning appointments of Assistant Political Agent, including the Rulers of Bahrain, Qatar, Dubai, Umm al Qaiwain, Kalba, Abu Dhabi, Ras al Khaimah, and Ajman.The file also includes a bilingual letterhead in English and Arabic of the Bahrain Government Electric Supply Department, September 1937.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00021a#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>