<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000106_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T02:47:05.314Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000106_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/289</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000106</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000106/IOR_R_15_1_289_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/289</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'14/240 I B. 69. JURISDICTION IN THE TRUCIAL SHAIKHDOMS'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:17:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (217 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: Foliation starts on front cover of file, in pencil in uncircled (later circled) numbers in top right corner of the recto of each folio, and continues to the end of the file. A former pagination sequence starts on the verso of folio 128 with 132. Foliation anomaly: 1A  and 1B.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence relating to jurisdiction in the Trucial Shaikhdoms. The main correspondents are the India Office, Foreign Office, Political Resident Persian Gulf; Political Agent, Bahrain.The correspondence discusses the creation of new Orders-in-Council for the Trucial Coast and whether this is needed before Petroleum Concessions progresses its oil discoveries. The file contains the Draft Trucial Coast Order in Council. Letters discuss whether war-time contingencies require new legal measures to deal with hostile persons. Also discussed are measures to contain the possibility of post-war attempts at penetration by foreigners including the American oil company and how to reply to a letter from the American Embassy. The file also includes letters from Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, ruler of Ras al Khaimah and Shaikh Shakbut bin Sultan bin Zayid, ruler of Abu Dhabi. There is a printed report of the External Affairs Department Trucial States Order-in-Council 1946.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Jurisdiction</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trucial Coast Order in Council</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000106#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000106#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000106#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>