<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b8_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T19:33:31.094Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3399</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b8</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b8/IOR_L_PS_12_3399_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3399</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/5 ‘Railways &amp;c; Mirjawa-Duzdap section of Duzdap Railway; Effect on roads’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-05T00:12:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (428 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the first folio with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 428; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is present between ff 391-428 and is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out. The front and back covers, along with the two leading flyleaves and single ending flyleaf, have not been foliated.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Papers relating to the transfer of ownership of the railway line running between Mirjawa [Mīrjāveh] and Duzdap [Zahedan] in eastern Persia [Iran], from the Government of India to the Persian Government.The volume begins with reports of interruptions to monthly rations trains, prompting the Government of India to close down the line. The remainder of the correspondence covers negotiations for the transfer and reopening of the railway:The impact of the railway’s closure on trade, water supply to the region, smuggling, road traffic.The British Government’s initial desire to use the transfer of the railway as a
                              quid pro quofor an extension to the south Persia air route used by Imperial Airways.Statements showing income and losses made by the railway between 1923 and 1931 (ff 205-208).A report by John Gilbert Laithwaite of the India Office, undated but likely written in early 1933, containing a comprehensive summary to date of agreements and operations of the railway, between the Government of India and the Persian Government (ff 132-148).A copy of an agreement for the sale of railway plant and rolling stock, with a list of equipment, quantity and prices (quoted in Indian rupees) (ff 94-104).Draft copies of an agreement (in French) for the transfer of the railway.The volume’s principal correspondents are: the British Legation at Tehran (Robert Henry Clive; Reginald Hervey Hoare); the British Vice-Consul at Sistan and Kain [Ka’īn] (Major Clive Kirkpatrick Daly); the India Office (Laithwaite); the Foreign Office (Charles William Baxter; George William Rendel).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Mirjawa</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Seistan and Kain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Duzdap</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><subject><topic>Bilateral agreements</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b8#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b8#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b8#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>