<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00032f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:30:20.272Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00032f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B341</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00032f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00032f/IOR_L_PS_18_B341_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B341</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Mesopotamia and Middle East: Question of Future Control'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1920/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-17T11:13:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this sequence commences at folio 108, and terminates at folio 109, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 7-153; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This is a secret printed memorandum, dated 1 June 1920, with an introductory note, dated 2 June 1920, by the Edwin Samuel Montagu (initialled E S M), Secretary of State for India. It concerns the question of future British control in Mesopotamia [Iraq] and Middle East. The memorandum discusses the current administrative arrangements in the region following the First World War, the idea of establishing a 'Middle East Office', and considers which department of state (India Office, Foreign Office or Colonial Office) is best qualified to undertake the task of administering Britain's Middle Eastern affairs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Middle East</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00032f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>