<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100050902515.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T14:01:13.845Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100050902515.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 1348</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100050902515.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100050902515.0x000001/Or 1348_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 1348</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb al-uṣūl fī sharḥ al-fuṣūl كتاب الأصول في شرح الفصول  Ibn al-Quff, Yaʿqūb ibn Isḥāq ابن القف ,أبو الفرج بن يعقوب بن إسحاق</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1385/1385</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-20T22:03:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. i+179+i</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 262 x 175 mm leaf [195 x 130 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencil; quire marks (mostly quinions) on ff. 9r, 19r, 29r, 50r, 59r, 69r, 78r, 88r, 98r, 108r, 116r, 125r, 135r, 163r, and 173rRuling: No ruling visible; average 42 lines per page; average vertical spacing 23 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Naskh; the scribe is Khalīl ibn ‘Abd Allāh ibn Sulaymān (خليل ابن عبد الله بن سليمان, f. 178v, line 35)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated headingsDecoration: Illuminated title page (f. 1r)Binding: Red, leather British Museum binding, with blind-tooled medallion and corner-piecesCondition: Minor tidemarks towards head and tailMarginalia: Numerous by many handsSeals: None</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Commentary by Amīn al-Daulah Abū al-Faraj ibn Ya‘qūb ibn Isḥāq ibn al-Quff (أمين الدولة أبو الفرج بن يعقوب بن إسحاق بن القف, d. 1286) on the
                           Aphorisms(
                           Kitāb al-fuṣūl) of Hippocrates (أبقراط, d. ca 370 BC).Folio 1 has been bound into the volume upside down.The copy was completed on Friday 6 Shawwāl 787/10 November 1385 by Khalīl ibn ‘Abd Allāh ibn Sulaymān (خليل ابن عبد الله بن سليمان), who copied the text for his own use (f. 178v, lines 32-35, see colophon, transcribed below).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-5):قال الشيخ الفاضل أبو الفرج بن يعقوب المسيحي الملكي المتطبب المعروف بابن القفالحمد لله خالق الخلق ومبدئه وباسط الرزق ومنيه ومقدر العمر ومحصيه وموجدالمرض ومنشفيه ورضوانه على أنبيائه وأوليائه أجمعين وبعد فقد سألني بعض مناشتغل بصناعة الطب أن أشرح له كتاب الفصول للإمام أبقراط ...Ends (f. 178v, lines 28-31):... وهو أن تكونالأغذية الكثيرة المقدار بعيدة العهد بالاستعمال فيستعملوها يكونون مرضى فإن مواد هذه الأغذية إذا طال زمانهافي البدن ولم تستفرغ أوجبت أخلاطًا فاسدة وهذه الأخلاط الفاسدة لا شك أن القوى تكون معها ضعيفةواستيصال هذه المادة وتنقية البدن منها يكون بالإسهال وذلك من أسفل والله أعلمColophon (f. 178v, lines 32-36):تمت المقالة السابعة من فصول الإمام أبقراط شرح الشيخ أبو الفرج ابن القففي يوم الجمعة المبارك سادس شهر شوال سنة سبع وثمانين وسبع مائةأحسن الله عاقبتهاعلقه لنفسه الفقير الله تعالى خليل ابن عبد الله بن سليمان المتطبب عفا الله عنهماوالحمد لله وحده وصلواته على سيدنا محمد وآله وصحبه وسلم وحسبنا الله ونعم والوكيل</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Hippocrates</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Abū al-Faraj ibn Ya'qūb ibn Isḥāq Ibn al-Quff</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100050902515.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>