<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T05:47:09.412Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur C600/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001/Mss Eur C600_2_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur C600/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'THE PERSIAN GULF'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-09T22:42:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (32 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the first folio with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 32; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is present between ff 1-32 and is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains two versions of a paper by Captain Maurice Patrick O'Connor Tandy entitled 'The Persian Gulf'. The paper was clearly intended to be a guide for British officials who had been newly posted to the region.The paper gives information on the geography and history of the Persian Gulf; descriptions of individual states in the region; a section entitled 'How to Behave' (expanded in the second version under the title 'Arab Religion and Manners'); and a note on currency.The file also contains covering correspondence from the Middle East Department of the Foreign Office, dated May 1946.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Guides</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031201075.0x000001#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>