<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000148_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T16:34:44.270Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000148_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/34</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000148</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000148/IOR_L_MIL_17_15_34_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/34</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Despatch by Lieutenant-General R. Wapshare, C.B., C.S.I. on the Organization and Working of the East Persian Line of Communications. From 1st April 1918 to 15th January 1919'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-20T22:00:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (65 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single document.A contents page for Appendix 5 is included on folio 18.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 67; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a despatch from Lieutenant-General Richard Wapshare, General Officer Commanding, 4th (Quetta) Division to the Chief of General Staff, Army Headquarters, Delhi, dated 8 March 1919, concerning the organization and working of the East Persian line of communications, covering the period from 1 April 1918 to 15 January 1919.It includes topics such as topography; the East Persian Cordon Field Force; administration; troop movements; railway defence troops; work on the railway; financial problems; road and rail lines of communications; supply areas; transport; trade; the capacity of the railway; supplies; medical and veterinary arrangements; and ordnance services.Appendices 1 and 2 consist of maps and sketches not reproduced in this file.Appendix 3 –
                           Report on the working of the Nushki Extension Railway from 1st April 1918 to 15th January 1919, by Colonel Frederick Warner Allum, Engineer-in-Chief, Nushki Extension Railway, dated 6 February 1919.Appendix 4 –
                           Note on the Field Work of the Nushki Extension (Railway) Reconnaissance, June 1918 to January 1919, by Major Lewis Egerton Hopkins, Engineer-in-Chief, N. E. Reconnaissance, dated 6 February 1919. Covering the object and length of the survey; wells, tanks and water supply; transport; illness; list of officers and subordinates, etc., who served in Persia; and caravan routes.Appendix 5 –
                           Report on the working of the line of communications East Persia from September 1918 to January 15th 1919, by Brigadier-General William Edmund Ritchie Dickson, Inspector General of Communications, East Persia, dated 5 February 1919. It is broken down into the following topics: general; supply and transport; medical; ordnance; veterinary; works; surveys; finance; ecclesiastical; and posts and telegraphs.It also includes a series of seventeen annexures with various tables covering: administrative standing orders; the transport situation and forecast of transport requirements; instructions for moving stores along the line of communications; the chain of supply and transport responsibility; transport units; distribution of supply units; supplies carried on lines of communication; medical requirements; clothing and ordnance stores; progress of building works; and finances.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>General Officer Commanding, 4th (Quetta) Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Inspector General of Communications, East Persia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Quartermaster General, Communications, East Persia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Nushki Extension Railway</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Engineer-in-Chief, N. E. Reconnaissance</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Nushki Extension Railway, Engineer-in-Chief</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief of the General Staff, India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Eastern Persian Cordon Field Force</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Communication methods</topic></subject><subject><topic>Administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Supplies</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Transport</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000148#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>