<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000014_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T23:15:49.614Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000014_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3466</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000014</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000014/IOR_L_PS_12_3466_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3466</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/60(1) ‘Persia. Treatment of Foreigners; Position of British subjects, and British Consular Representatives, etc.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-26T22:01:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (470 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 467; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, reports and other papers relating to the ill-treatment of foreigners (specifically British or British Indian subjects) in Persia [Iran] at the hand of the Persian authorities. The file’s principal correspondents are: HM’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary, Robert Henry Clive, Reginald Hervey Hoare, Hughe Montgomery Knatchbull-Hugessen, Horace James Seymour; the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mirza Mohamed Ali Khan Feroughi; Bagher Kazemi; HM’s Consul for Khuzistan [Khūzestān], Arnold Edwards Watkinson; the Foreign Office; the India Office.The file includes: 1931 correspondence relating to a claim for compensation, made by the British Government against the Persian Government, for the ill-treatment of a British Indian subject in the Persian Gulf port of Charbar [Chābahār]; correspondence throughout concerning reports about the Shah of Persia’s negative attitude to foreigners in Persia; correspondence dated 1933 relating to the detention by the Persian authorities of two British male subjects suspected of being involved in espionage and gold smuggling; the treatment of Indian pilgrims in East Persia; the treatment of the Hazara-Berberi people in East Persia; a note dated 2 August 1935 about the Berberis of East Iran, written by HM’s Consul for Khorassan [Khorāsān], Lieutenant-Colonel Clive Kirkpatrick Daly (ff 108-115).A small number of items in the volume (Persian Government correspondence, texts of laws and regulations) are in French.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Iranian Army</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Ethnic discrimination</topic></subject><subject><topic>Ethnic groups</topic></subject><subject><topic>Pilgrims</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Charbar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreigners</topic></subject><subject><topic>Aggression and violence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Compensation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000014#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000014#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000014#share">Copyright or data protection restrictions</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>