<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:23:34.620Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B220</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024d/IOR_L_PS_18_B220_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B220</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Advance to Baghdad – Political Considerations. Note by Political Department, India Office.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-25T14:39:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 119, and terminates at f 119, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and won't be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Note written by John Evelyn Shuckburgh, Assistant Secretary of the Political Department, India Office, on the political and strategic importance that would be associated with British forces taking Baghdad, and the likely political and strategic injury that the British would incur should they fail to take Baghdad. Following Shuckburgh’s note is a reply, written by the Secretary of the Political Department, Sir (Frederic) Arthur Hirtzel, dated 6 October 1915, concurring with Shuckburgh’s assessment, and commenting on the chances of withdrawal from Kut-el-Amara [Kut al Amara] should sufficient Turco-German troops be fielded in the region.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Baghdad</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kut</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>