<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000334_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:30:34.584Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000334_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B346</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000334</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000334/IOR_L_PS_18_B346_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B346</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Mesopotamia. Proposed Constitution: Telegraphic Correspondence with Baghdad'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1920/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T13:38:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this sequence commences at folio 118, and terminates at folio 123, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 7-153; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum, dated July 1920, contains a series of reprinted telegrams in a single collection for the purposes of facilitating the discussions with Sir Percy Zachariah Cox on the proposed constitution for Mesopotamia [Iraq]. It is noted that the series is not complete, but contains all but vital telegrams. The series contains twenty telegrams between 20 March 1920 and 9 July 1920, between the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, and the Secretary of State. Topics covered include an overview of the ethnic and religious makeup of Mesopotamia, matters relating to the constitution and proposed Legislative Assembly, the San Remo Conference, and the decision to grant a mandate to Mesopotamia.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Percy Zachariah Cox</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Constitutions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000334#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>