<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00021d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T15:26:31.086Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00021d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3968B</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00021d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00021d/IOR_L_PS_12_3968B_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3968B</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/224 'Currency Arrangements in the Arab Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-17T22:19:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (74 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file. There are file notes on folios 2-11: these notes are in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 74; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are printed, and are not circled. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns currency arrangements in the Arab states of the Persian Gulf that were under British influence.The papers cover: allegations by the Government of Pakistan and in the Pakistani press of discrimination against Pakistan currency in Bahrain; exchange control policy; 'Report on Persian Gulf Tour of Treasury Representative [Leonard Waight]', dated June 1949, covering the use of the Indian rupee as the official currency of the Persian Gulf sheikhdoms, the long-term implications of the increase in oil revenue in the region and the use of surplus funds (with particular reference to Kuwait and Bahrain), and the working of exchange control, with conclusions and recommendations (folios 28-41); the comments of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel Sir William Rupert Hay) on Waight's report (folios 17-20); and a note of a visit to Bahrain by a representative of the State Bank of Pakistan in September 1949.The file contains also correspondence from the Bank of England.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Financial control</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Pakistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Currencies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00021d#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00021d#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00021d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>