<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cf_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T06:10:58.755Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cf_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/490</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cf</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cf/IOR_R_15_1_490_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/490</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/11 VIII (D 98) Date Gardens of Shaikhs of Kuwait and Mohammerah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T09:57:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">tur</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (286 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>Condition: Formerly a bound correspondence volume, the file's sheets have been unbound and are now loose.Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using uncircled pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto.The following foliation anomalies occur: 1a-1e, 27a, 140a-140f, 142a, 146a, 237a.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding date gardens in southern Iraq owned by the rulers of Mohammerah and Kuwait. The correspondence discusses changes in legislation proposed by the Government of Iraq regarding the collection of land rent and land produce duties, and the impact of these changes to the ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ.In particular, the correspondence concerns the Government of Iraq's decision to end the immunity from taxation (on the gardens) that had been granted to the former ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ and the Shaikh of Mohammerah, Khaz‘al bin Jābir al-Ka‘bī by the British Government in return for their military support against the Ottoman Empire in World War 1.The file contains details regarding a legal case brought against Shaikh Aḥmad by members of the Al Zuhair family regarding the ownership of some of his land holdings in Iraq.Correspondence in the file states that the problems between Shaikh Aḥmad and fellaheen (agricultural workers) on his land - as described in detail in IOR/R/15/1/489 - had been resolved.The file contains correspondence regarding Jacob Gabriel, the Armenian legal representative of Shaikh Ahmad (ff. 5-13) as well as minutes from two meetings held at the Foreign Office with representatives from the India Office, the Treasury, the Treasury Solicitor's Department and the Foreign Office (ff.167-183 &amp; ff. 187-200).The file also contains the following:An English translation of an article which appeared in the Iraqi newspaper
                              Al Ahaliin December 1933. The article accuses the Al Sabah family of 'meddling' with fellaheen in order to preserve control over their lands in Iraq (f.111).A copy (in Arabic) of Iraq's Land Laws (ff. 120-130).Detailed figures concerning the produce of Shaikh Aḥmad's lands and the amount of tax and export duties paid on them (ff. 214-227).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cf#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cf#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cf#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>