<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000041.0x0001c1_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T16:42:59.180Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000041.0x0001c1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 19547</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000041.0x0001c1</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000041.0x0001c1/Add MS 19547_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 19547</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>al-Ṣulḥ bayna al-ikhwān fī ḥukm ibāḥat al-dukhān الصلح بين الإخوان في حكم إباحة الدخان  Nābulusī, ‘Abd al-Ghanī ibn Ismā‘īl نابلسي، عبد الغني بن إسماعيل</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1748/1748</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-12T09:38:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. v+125+vi</extent><extent>Material: Western laid paperDimensions: 214 x 140 mm leaf [160 x 76 mm written]Foliation: Eastern Arabic foliation in black ink; British Museum foliation in pencilRuling: No ruling visible; 15 lines per page; vertical spacing 10 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           NaskhInk: Black ink, with rubricated headings and text frames in red and greenDecoration: Illuminated incipit with gold and floral pattern; each page has a text frame in red and greenBinding: Ottoman boards and envelope flap of red leather binding attached to new, rounded (European style) spine; boards and envelope flap have block stamped medallions and bordersCondition: Excellent; extremely minor water damage to head towards front and back of volumeMarginalia: Very few; all (?) by hand of scribeSeals: None</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Treatise in defense of tobacco smoking (شَرَب التُتُن) on medical and legal grounds, written in 1092/1682 (see Author's Colophon, f. 127v, lines 11-13, transcribed below) by ‘Abd al-Ghanī ibn Ismā‘īl al-Nābulusī (عبد الغني بن إسماعيل النابلسي, b. 1641, d. 1731).The copy was completed at the end of Muḥarram 1161/January-February 1748 (see Scribe's Colophon, f. 127v, lines 14-16, transcribed below).On the title page are recorded two lines (بيتان) of verse on the theme of smoking by Shaykh al-Zarqānī between the two hemistichs of which two new hemistichs have been inserted (a poetic practice known as تشطير) by al-Shaykh al-Ṣafwānī al-Rashīdī.The treatise is divided into seven chapters (فصول), a list of which is given in the introduction (ff. 6v-7v):Chapter One: Explanation of why people disagree over judging some things permissable, and why fatwas from the ulamas disagree over allowing or prohibiting tobacco smoking (الفصل الأول في بيان سبب اختلاف الناس في حكم بعض الأشياء المباحة وسبب اختلاف الفتاوى من العلماء في حل شرب التتن وحرمته; ff. 7v-21v);Chapter Two: The initial use of this special plant known as tobacco, the origin of the method of smoking it in this special way, a discussion of its appearance in the Levant and elsewhere, an explanation of its names and the names of its paraphernalia (الفصل الثاني في ابتداء استعمال هذا النبات المخصوص المعروف بالتتن وأصل كيفية شربه على هذا الوجه المخصوص وذكر أول حدوثه بالبلاد الشامية وغيرها وبيان أسمائه وأسماء آلاته; ff. 21v-28r);Chapter Three: Explanation of the origin of smoke in general, knowledge of how it is produced, and a discussion of its benefits and harms (الفصل الثالث في بيان أصل الدخان المطلق ومعرفة كيفية تولده وذكر منافعه ومضاره; ff. 28r-34v);Chapter Four: Explanation of this special plant called tobacco, and a discussion of its smoke and benefits (الفصل الرابع في بيان هذا النبات المخصوص المسمى بالتتن وذكر دخانه ومنافعه; ff. 34v-44v);Chapter Five: Explanation of the flawed evidence adduced by those who say the use of tobacco is forbidden (الفصل الخامس في بيان الأدلة الفاسدة التي استدل بها من حرم استعمال التتن; ff. 44v-104r);Chapter Six: Summary of what is said in the statement allowing the smoking of tobacco after forbidding it has been refuted, prohibitive and abstinential disgust, and the difference of the first (الفصل السادس في ملخص ما يقال من التصريح بإباحة شرب التتن بعد انتفاء الحرمة عنه والكراهة التحريمية والتنزيهية وخلاف الأولى; ff. 104r-119r);Chapter Seven: What we have discovered about the truth of tobacco smoking according to the moderns from poetic verses and refined love poems, and what we have written of this sort as a conclusion for what we have intended in writing these chapters (الفصل السابع فيما وجدناه في حق شرب التتن للمتأخرين من الأبيات الشعرية والتغزلات الأدبية وما لنا في ذلك على هذا المثال تتميمًا لما قصدناه من تحرير المقال; ff. 119r-127v).Begins (f. 2v, lines 2-6):الحمد لله الذي جعل استعمال دخان التتننافعًا بتجفيفه الرطوبات الزائدة في الأجسامومحللًا لما تكاثف في الصدر من لزوجة البلغمومهضمًا عن المعدة ثقل الطعام وطاردًاللرياح المحتبسة في العروق ...Ends (f. 127v, lines 9-11):هذا آخر ما أردنا إراده في بيان هذه المسئلةنفّع الله تعالى بها الأمة وأزال بسببهاعنهم في ذلك الغمة ...Author's Colophon (f. 127v, lines 11-13):... وقد وافق فراغ تبييضهانهار الأربع أواخر شهر ذي الحجة المباركةختام سنة 1092 أثنين وتسعين وألفScribe's Colophon (f. 127v, lines 14-16):ووافق أيضًا انتهاء تحرير هذه النسخة نهارالجمعة المباركة ختام شهر محرم الحرام المبارك(له 27 ع ؟) سنة 1161</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>‘Abd al-Ghanī ibn Ismā‘īl Nābulusī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Smoking (Islamic law)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000041.0x0001c1#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>