<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000073_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T02:21:03.087Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000073_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3554</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000073</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000073/IOR_L_PS_12_3554_0003.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3554</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/2(3) 'Royal Naval Base Bahrain: transfer and adaptation for use as Political Residency'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-01T10:57:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (367 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 368; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-368; these numbers are also written in pencil, but the majority are not circled, where these have previously been circled they have been crossed through.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the transfer of the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf from Bushire to Bahrain in 1946, and the conversion of the Royal Navy Base in Bahrain for the use of the Political Resident.The file is composed solely of internal correspondence between British officials including the India Office, Admiralty, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, the Secretary of State for India, HM Treasury, the Public Works Department of the Government of India, the Ministry of Works, the Commonwealth Relations Office.The correspondence relates specifically to the following:new buildings required at the Naval Base, including four architectural drawings (ff 359-361, f 285)conversion of Jufair Naval buildings as site for the new Residencywireless transmitting stationlist of building and works at the Naval Base taken over by the Political Resident in August 1946 (ff 304-319)estimate of costsplan of empty land situated at Qadhibia (outskirts of Manama), Harbour of Bahrain, which has been sold by the Government of Bahrain to the Government of Great Britain (f 208)air conditioning in the new Residency buildingregulations relating to the occupation of Embassy and Legation houses, the property of, or leased by, His Majesty's Government (ff 122-125)Ministry of Works report of visit to Bahrain and plans to build a new Residency (ff 107-117)Admiralty's need to reoccupy buildings in the Naval base at Jufair.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Public Building and Works</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Navy, HMS Jufair, Naval Base</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Manama</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Building maintenance</topic></subject><subject><topic>British</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000073#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000073#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>