<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x000302_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T17:25:09.485Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x000302_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/A145</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x000302</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x000302/IOR_L_PS_18_A145_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/A145</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Baluchistan and Persia. Note by Sir Dennis Fitzpatrick'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1899/1899</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-05-21T00:36:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of one note which is divided into a series of numbered paragraphs, which proceed from 1 to 15.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the first folio, and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a note, written by Sir Dennis Fitzpatrick, member of the Council of India, on the subject of the northernmost portion of land in the province of Baluchistan [Balochistān], south of the Durand line, which is described as being situated between British India and Kelat [Kalat] on the east side, and Persia on the west side.The note begins by referring directly to the following letter of correspondence: 'Letter from India, No. 189, Secret,' dated 19 October 1899. The note is principally concerned with the costs and benefits of a proposed railway line, which would run from Nushki (recently taken over by the British from the Khan of Kelat) to Koh-i-Malik-Siah [Malek Sīāh Kūh], in Seistan [Sīstān].The file questions the argument that such a railway line would counteract Russian influence in Seistan. Also discussed is the extent to which the Government of India should be expected to finance such a scheme. Fitzpatrick makes the argument that it is wider Imperial interests, rather than those of the Government of India, which are most at stake, and that therefore a distribution of the cost should be made by fixed shares, rather than by relying solely on Indian revenues. He concludes by referring to a note that he wrote some months earlier, in which he advised that the control of all British affairs west of Baluchistan and Afghanistan should be vested exclusively in the Foreign Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Khan of Kalāt, rulers of Kalāt</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Council of India</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Dennis Fitzpatrick</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Durand Line</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Seistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Koh-i-Malik-Siah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kelat</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Baluchistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Railway lines</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade routes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x000302#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>