<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00006f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T23:22:05.433Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00006f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/138</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00006f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00006f/IOR_R_15_1_138_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/138</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Vol 186 1853/54 Bahrain; Arabian Coast and Muscat; Slave Trade'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1853/1854</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-11-07T00:07:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 volumes, 107 items (424 folios)</extent><extent>The letterbook is divided into three subjects: correspondence concerning Bahrain, correspondence concerning the Arab Coast and Muscat, and correspondence concerning the slave trade. Each subject has a title sheet.Within each subject, the correspondence is arranged in chronological order, based on the date of the outward letter. Enclosures included immediately after the outward letter are chronologically earlier than the letter they are enclosed with. Inward correspondence, chiefly in the form of replies from the Government of India, is placed immediately after the letter they acknowledge receipt of. Because of the long periods of time taken for mail to travel, the inward replies are of a much later date (approximately three to four months) than the outward correspondence.</extent><extent>Foliation: The letterbook has been split into two volumes, ending at folio 208 in the first volume, and picking up at folio 209 in the second. Foliation begins on the first page of text in the first volume, and ends on the last page of the original letterbook in the second volume. The foliation system uses pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. An original pagination system, written in ink in the top-left corner of versos and the top-right corner of rectos, runs through both volumes.The front cover, inside cover, front flyleafs, rear flyleafs and inside back cover of each volume are unfoliated.The following foliation anomalies occur: 41A, 74A, 74B (no 74), 179A, 179B (no 179), 184A, 184B (no 184), 187A, 194A, 194B (no 194), 196A, 196B (no 196), 203A, 263A, 282A, 282B (no 282), 295A, 295B (no 295), 331A, 331B (no 331).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letterbook is comprised of correspondence sent between the Resident in the Persian Gulf, Captain Arnold Kemball, and the Chief Secretary of the Government in Bombay, Arthur Malet, relating to events at Bahrain (folios 1-61), on the Arabian Coast and Muscat (folios 63-256), and the slave trade (folios 258-414).Correspondence relating to Bahrain, the Arab Coast and Muscat, chiefly concerns relations (including conflicts and settlements) between the Arab tribes, occasional breaches of the maritime peace, and the movements of a Wahhabi army eastwards from the Arabian interior, towards Al-Buraimi and Muscat. Correspondence relating to the slave trade chiefly concerns instances of slaves being imported into Persia from Zanzibar, occasionally via the Batinah and Arab coasts.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter book</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Zanzibar</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Wahabi (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Qawāsim (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>'Utūb (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bassidore</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Brymee</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sohar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Slave emancipation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00006f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>