<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000aa_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T21:15:32.991Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000aa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/183</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000aa</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000aa/IOR_R_15_5_183_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/183</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/5 Kuwait State: Shaikh of Kuwait, Status of and Salutes for'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-02T22:33:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (183 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 185; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-184; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials concerning issues related to the number of official gun salutes that the British Government assigned to rulers in the Persian Gulf as well as the titles that should be used for them in official correspondence.Specifically, the majority of the correspondence in the file relates to two main issues:Britain's decision to increase the official gun salute of the rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait from seven to eleven in 1933.Britain's decision to grant the rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait the title of 'His Excellency' in 1937.The file contains two lists of all the region's rulers and their respective gun salutes/titles, one from 1936 (folios 73-75) and another from 1949 (folio 183).The main correspondents in the file are British officials from the Political Residency, the Political Agencies in Bahrain and Kuwait and the Admiralty. It also contains a limited amount of correspondence between the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah and the Political Agency in Kuwait, some of which is in Arabic.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Military ceremonies, honours, and salutes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000aa#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000aa#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>