<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T20:28:24.893Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/10, ff 156-162</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000002</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003de/IOR_R_15_1_10_0351.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/10, ff 156-162</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from William Bruce, Acting Political Resident at Bushire to Neil Benjamin Edmonstone, Secretary in the Secret, Political and Foreign Department, Fort William, Calcutta</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1808/1808</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-01-27T00:22:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>7 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is forwarding copies, extracts and translations of correspondence to illustrate the current state of affairs in the region for the current quarter. A list of the enclosed correspondence is included in the margin of the letter, however not all of these enclosures have been transcribed with this item.Three enclosures:1. Letter from Captain Charles Pasley, Acting Envoy Extraordinary to Persia to William Bruce, dated 1 September 1808. In addition to enclosing letters for correspondents in Persia, the letter covers a range of subjects. It considers his departure from Bushire and the fact the Captain did not have reliable enough information on Abdulla Khan's impending arrival at Bushire to justify delaying his trip. He speculates on the purpose of Abdulla Khan's mission to Bushire and discusses the compensation for Jaffer Ali Khan [Ja‘afar ‘Alī Khān] for losses as a result of a robbery, which took place while he was undertaking services on behalf of the British.2. Copy of a letter from Jafer Allee Khan [Ja‘afar ‘Alī Khān] to Captain Charles Pasley, received at Bushire 13 September 1808. The letter concerns the departure of the Captain from Bushire, following a suspected plot from Shiraz, and the consequences faced by Jafer Allee Khan . It mentions that 'the Wheskerander' has departed for Tehran, but that he has promised not to mention his conduct in the aforementioned matter to the King.Jafer Allee Khan further mentions that the King of Persia believes the Shaik of Chaby is in league with the British, and plotting against the Persian Government; he has therefore instructed the Prince at Sheraz [Shiraz] to march on Chaby with an army in order to punish and replace him. The various preparations being made to effect this are described in the letter. He also discusses the prevention of letters and goods from being delivered to Persian merchants at Bushire by William Bruce, a measure he approves of and warns that the King of Persia must have hostile intentions towards the British.3. Extract of a letter from Jafer Allee Khan to Captain Charles Pasley, received at Bushire 13 September 1808. The letter concerns his attempts to uncover the business that Mohumed Shurif Khan has with the Minister of Isfahan, which he has not not yet been able to do.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000002#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>