<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000153_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T08:26:57.791Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000153_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3772</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000153</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000153/IOR_L_PS_12_3772_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3772</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/55 'Persian Gulf. Trucial Oman + Other Trucial Shaikhdoms: Persian Interference with Trucial Coast Dhows'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-01-11T22:00:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (139 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 140; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British diplomatic and naval officials regarding a number of alleged instances of interference with shipping vessels from Oman and Dubai by Government of Iran naval vessels and customs officials.The file also contains English translations of letters that were sent to British authorities by the rulers of Dubai (folios 28-30) and Kuwait (folio 101).As well as discussion of a number of specific incidents, the correspondence also covers broader issues concerning the position of the Arab Shaikhdoms of the Gulf in relation to treaties and international conventions and what flags their vessels should display.In addition to correspondence, the file also contains a memorandum entitled 'Cases of interference with vessels or violation of territory belonging to the Arab protégés of His Majesty's Government in the Persian Gulf by Persian Warships or Customs Authorities' (folios 102-104).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000153#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000153#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000153#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>