<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T14:36:52.714Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/145</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370/IOR_R_15_2_145_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/145</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/A/13 I Transhipment of Cargo at Bahrain.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-21T18:20:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (279 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are filed in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after the relevant covering letter. Single pages of notes occur at intervals between folios 210-267.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 281; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-281; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the transhipment of goods from merchant ships to dhows in Bahrain harbour (also referred as Bahrein) in order to avoid paying customs duty; the effect of this on the Bahrain economy; the levying by Bahrain of transit dues on shipping; and relations between Bahrain and the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.The correspondence is mainly between the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. There is also correspondence from Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; from Mackinnon, Mackenzie &amp; Company, and the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, agents of the British India Steam Navigation Company Limited; and from staff and agents of the Eastern Steam Navigation Company Limited. Enclosures to correspondence from the Political Resident to the Political Agent, Bahrain include correspondence from the British Legation, Jedda [Jeddah]; the Foreign Office; the India Office; the Board of Trade; and the Government of India.The papers cover: the level and nature of the customs dues set by the Bahrain State; the importance of customs revenue to the Bahrain economy (e.g. folios 10 and 109); the transhipment (also known as 'overside delivery') of goods shipped by Mackinnon, Mackenzie &amp; Company, and the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, which were bound for Ojair [al-‘Uqayr] in Saudi Arabia, and the role of Captain Charles Geoffrey Prior in arranging an agreement to discontinue transhipment, October 1931 - June 1932; the imposition by Bahrain of transit dues on the Eastern Steamship Company ship SS
                           Ahmedi, which was carrying goods for Bahrain and Ojair, October 1932 - January 1933; and protests by Saudi Arabia, December 1932. (The dates given refer to main items of correspondence, which may include enclosures of an earlier date.)The date range gives the overall covering dates of the correspondence; the last dated addition to the file is a note on folio 275 dated 1 February 1933.The Arabic language content of the file consists of seven folios: principally a letter (with translation in English) from Sheikh Hamad bin Isa Al-Khalifah [Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah] to the Political Resident on folios 57-61.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>SS Ahmedi, ship</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Transshipment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping dues</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000370#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>