<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000221_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T15:27:50.487Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000221_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3972</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000221</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000221/IOR_L_PS_12_3972_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3972</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/228 'COMMUNAL SITUATION IN PERSIAN GULF.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-12T22:12:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>There is a set of file notes on folio 2.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a single item of correspondence from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel Sir William Rupert Hay) to the Commonwealth Relations Office, London, concerning communal relations between Muslims, Jews, Sikhs, and Hindus in the Persian Gulf.The enclosures to the letter include a copy of a letter from the Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations of the Government of India, alleging acts of looting, rape, and murder by members of the Muslim League against the Jewish community in Bahrain, and asking the Resident to take measures to ensure the safety of Indian nationals there. The Resident in response acknowledged that some anti-Jewish rioting had taken place in Bahrain in December 1947, and mentioned rumours of intended attacks by Pakistani Muslim employees of Petroleum Development Qatar against the Company's Sikh employees in Qatar, but felt that no special measures were required for the protection of Indian nationals in the Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Riots</topic></subject><subject><topic>Aggression and violence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious minorities</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000221#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000221#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>