<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T12:51:58.971Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/4/12</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396/IOR_R_15_4_12_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/4/12</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 24/2 Oil concessions, Volume II'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-03T10:48:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (200 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 202; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-198; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the negotiations and signing of oil concessions in the Trucial Coast (United Arab Emirates). The correspondence is principally between the British Agency in Sharjah, the Political Agency in Bahrain, the Political Agency in Muscat, representatives of Petroleum Concessions Limited (mostly Frank Holmes), and various rulers of the Trucial Shaikhdoms.The matters covered by the file include:the question of whether to include Kalbah within the Muscat concession;the British Government's policy of only permitting ruling Shaikhs to grant concessions to Petroleum Concessions Limited, and the wish of the rulers of Sharjah, Dubai, and Ras al-Khaimah to negotiate with the Standard Oil of California;the intentions of Shaikh Said bin Maktum [Sa‘īd bin Maktūm Āl Maktūm], ruler of Dubai, and Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr [Sulṭān II bin Saqr Āl Qasimī], ruler of Sharjah, to open a bank branch in their territories;the conduct of Frank Holmes;the negotiations over the Dubai, Sharjah, and Ras al-Khaimah concessions;the visit of Imperial Airways agents to Umm al-Qaiwain with a view to opening permanent facilities there;the visit of Basil Henry Lermitte, representative of Petroleum Concessions Limited, to the Trucial Coast to begin negotiations for the Ajman, Ras al-Khaimah, Umm al-Qaiwain, and Abu Dhabi concessions;reports of communication between Hajj Abdullah Williamson [William Richard Williamson], agent of Petroleum Concessions Limited, and the rulers of Ras al-Khaimah and Abu Dhabi, urging them to hold out for better terms;arrangements for a geological survey of Jabal Hafit;negotiations with Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr over the political agreement between Petroleum Concessions Limited and the British Government;reports of American geologists seen working in Abu Dhabi territory.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Muscat Political Agency and Consulate</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Airways</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Frank Holmes</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Trucial Coast</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000396#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>