<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000385_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T12:39:46.761Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000385_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/190</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000385</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000385/IOR_R_15_6_190_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/190</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/9 FINANCE REVENUE &amp; TAXES. CUSTOMS TARIFF 1932-1939'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-18T00:21:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (372 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 374; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume relates to the finances of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. The correspondence is primarily concerned with the Sultanate's customs tariffs. It features extensive discussion between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Political Agent and Consul at Muscat and officials of the India Office, Foreign Office, Dominions Office, Government of India, and the Board of Trade on the following related matters: Muscat's existing treaties with the United States and France (dated 1833 and 1844 respectively), and the advisability of these treaties – or at least their commercial clauses – being modified or denounced by the Sultan; the case for increasing customs import duties on certain goods (e.g. tobacco and alcohol), in an effort to increase revenue and restore the stability of the Sultanate's finances, and the likely effects that such an action would have on trade; the threshold (based on alcoholic content) to be used for identifying which alcoholic drinks should be subject to the proposed customs duty increase for alcohol, and the difficulty in translating the technical phrase 'under proof' into Arabic; the efforts of the British Government to secure the agreements of the Sultanate's other treaty partners (namely Canada, the Irish Free State, and France) regarding the proposed customs duty increase.The French language material consists of letters from the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs to the British representative in Paris. The Arabic language material mainly consists of letters between British representatives and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, most of which include English translations.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>France, Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Dominions Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Sultanate of Muscat and Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Customs duty</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000385#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000385#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>