<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000df_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T14:11:56.047Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000df_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/800</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000df</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000df/IOR_R_15_2_800_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/800</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 30/7 Review of Middle Eastern Economic and Social Policy'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-20T10:44:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (25 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file. There are file notes on folio 24.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 25; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional mixed foliation/pagination sequence is also present in parallel between ff 1-24; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. They are located in the same position as the main sequence, except for a few instances which are located on the verso.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence relating to the submission of information on the Persian Gulf states for a review of Middle East economic and social policy prepared by the Middle East Secretariat of the Foreign Office. The file includes:notes (ff 6-9) on Bahrain compiled by Herbert George Jakins, Political Agent, Bahrain;a copy (ff 14-18) of the Cabinet (Middle East) Official Committee statement of general policy entitled 'The Social and Internal Political Implications of Economic Development in the Middle East';a paper entitled 'Economic and Social Development in the Middle East: Persian Gulf States'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Social policy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic policy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000df#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>