<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002ce_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T20:50:50.936Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002ce_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/331</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002ce</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002ce/IOR_L_PS_12_331_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/331</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 645/40(2) ‘Persian Gulf. Movement of the Political Resident (&amp; temporary addresses)’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-23T22:13:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (200 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 202; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence, mainly telegrams, from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the India Office, London, and the External Affairs Department of the Government of India, New Delhi. These relate to the Resident’s movements and temporary addresses, as well as the acting arrangements put in place during his absences from the Political Residency at Bushire and later Bahrain, on official tours and other duties, on leave of absence and on other visits abroad. These include arrangements for the Resident’s visit to London on deputation in 1946, to discuss the transfer of responsibility for the Persian Gulf Residency from the Government of India to the Home Government in London. There is also a report by the Resident (Sir Geoffrey Prior) of his visit to King Ibn Saud in 1946. The file includes three dividers, which give a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. These are placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Tours</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002ce#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002ce#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>