<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>oai:cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org:p15795coll7/703</identifier><datestamp>2016-10-23</datestamp><setSpec>p15795coll7</setSpec></header><metadata><oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"><dc:title>20110822 interview</dc:title><dc:description>######, a staff worker at the dormitories of the American University in Cairo, describes his experience of the 2011 Egyptian revolution.  Fahd states that his political awareness developed during the AUC workers strike in 2010, and he offers his views about a lack of social justice and job opportunities in Egypt (using his brother’s situation as an example) under the old regime.  He recalls attending the January 25 demonstration at Tahrir Square, where observed the participation of AUC students he recognized, after being informed that he did not have to report to work that day.  According to ######, he served on the “ligan sha’abiyah” watch group in his neighborhood, Faisal, in response to rumors about escaped prisoners and thugs attacking people and property.  ###### tells of witnessing an incident at the police station in Bulaq in which police officers and soldiers shot at people in the street from the roof a nearby hospital, causing several deaths.  He also discusses how the formation of the independent workers syndicate at the university was a sign of the greater freedom of expression that emerged at AUC since the revolution.  </dc:description><dc:date>2011-08-21</dc:date><dc:format>oral histories (document genres)</dc:format><dc:language>Arabic</dc:language><dc:identifier>20110822</dc:identifier><dc:relation>University on the Square: Documenting Egypt's 21st Century Revolution</dc:relation><dc:source>University on the Square: Documenting Egypt's 21st Century Revolution oral histories; Rare Books and Special Collections Library; American University in Cairo</dc:source><dc:rights>Copyright 2012, American University in Cairo. All rights reserved.</dc:rights><dc:rights>To inquire about permissions or reproductions, contact the Rare Books and Special Collections Library, The American University in Cairo at +20.2.2615.3676 or rbscl-ref@aucegypt.edu.</dc:rights><dc:description>The University on the Square: Documenting Egypt's 21st Century Revolution project was made possible by a grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</dc:description><dc:identifier>http://cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15795coll7/id/703</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc></metadata></record>