<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100026969911.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T10:28:49.739Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100026969911.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/39, f 28</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100026969911.0x000002</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x00037c/IOR_L_PS_10_39_0061.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/39, f 28</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Sketch to illustrate cable dispute, Bunder Abbas’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1906/1906</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-29T21:45:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 map</extent><extent>Materials:Black ink on paper.Dimensions:420 x 420 mm.Foliation:The map is foliated in the top right corner with a circled pencil number.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The map, drawn on sectional paper with quarter inch squares, covers an area to the east of Bunder Abbas [Bandar-e ʻAbbās] town, with indications of proposed routes of the telegraph cable (linking the town with Jazīreh-ye Hengām) and its associated buildings. The map should be read in conjunction with a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Major Percy Zachariah Cox, to HM’s Minister at Tehran, dated 17 August 1906 (ff 24-25 in the same volume), which outlines the proposed routes for the telegraph cable (and the technical difficulties associated with the proposed routes) in an attempt to resolve the dispute between the British and Persian authorities over the position of the telegraph office at Bunder Abbas. In addition to the proposed routes of the cable, the cable house, and Bunder Abbas town, the map also indicates the position of the new British consulate buildings, Monsier Stas’s house, and a Persian guard house. Points on the map marked with the alphabetical labels A through to L are referred to in Cox’s letter.</abstract><typeOfResource>cartographic</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Map</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100026969911.0x000002#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>