<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000249_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T18:45:08.292Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000249_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1026</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000249</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000249/IOR_R_15_2_1026_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1026</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/35 Departmental Examinations of Officers of the Foreign and Political Department'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-15T00:03:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (22 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 20 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, enclosed in a circle, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1A, 1B, 1C.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to administrative arrangements for examinations of Officers of the Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India (later in the file referred to as probationers of the Indian Political Service), specifically to examinations taken by several holders of the post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.The papers cover syllabus; arrangements for date of examination; arrangements for oral examination, which was carried out by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; notification of result; and correspondence relating to a successful appeal by the Political Agent, Bahrain to a decision by the Government of India on an experimental basis to hold no local exminations in 1938: the Political Agent requested that his Assistant be permitted to sit the examination in Bahrain instead of Bushire, which would have entailed his being absent from Bahrain for a period of one-two weeks, September 1937 to May 1938.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Examinations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000249#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>