<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b3_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:27:26.067Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B289</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b3</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b3/IOR_L_PS_18_B289_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B289</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Administration of Mesopotamia. Fortnightly Report by the Civil Commissioner, No. 17 (1st - 15th July [1918])</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1918</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-12T15:04:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 folios</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 92, and terminates at folio 94, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 11-158; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum is a fortnightly administrative report (No 17) submitted by Arnold Talbot Wilson, Civil Commissioner in Baghdad, covering the period 1 to 15 July 1918. The report is split into four sections: (I) Administrative, which includes District Organisation, Revenue Board, Irrigation and Agricultural Departments, Blockade and Customs; (II) Judicial Department; (III) Civil Police; and (IV) Finance Branch, which includes details of the Control of Expenditure, Separation of Sanctioning and Audit Functions, Organisation of a Cadre of Accountants, Pay of Officers, Revenue Accounts, Pensions Office, and Local Inpsection of Accounts. The report also includes an appendix (folio 94v) concerning the 'Organization of Civil Administration in Baghdad Vilayet', listing divisions and districts.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Civil Commissioner, Mesopotamia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002b3#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>