<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00013f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T16:30:04.699Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00013f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/25</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00013f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00013f/IOR_L_MIL_17_15_25_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/25</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum of information received during the month of August 1909, relating to affairs in Persia, and on the Arabian shore of the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1909</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-02-19T19:49:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single memorandum, and includes a table of contents (f  2).</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the outside front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a memorandum written by Leonard William Reynolds, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, at Simla, 1 September 1909.Based upon a series of reports it covers: the situation in Persia - Azerbaijan, Shiraz, and Kerman; the Zil-es-Sultan; telegraph lines in Persia; the Russian Bank and Russian Consular Staff in Seistan; the proposed establishment of a customs Bureau at Birjand; the Russian Military Attaché in Seistan; the seizure of a Maskat [Muscat] dhow by the Italian authorities on the Benadir coast; the opening of a dispensary at Matrah by the American Mission at Maskat; Persia's claim to sovereignty over Bahrain; Nejd affairs; an attempt by Turkish authorities to register the Shaikh of Koweit [Kuwait] as a Turkish subject; and the murder of certain subjects of the Chief of Abu Thabi by residents of Taona.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x00013f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>