<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000008_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:44:56.733Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000008_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/233</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000008</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000008/IOR_R_15_6_233_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/233</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/52 MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: SHAIKH ISSA BIN SALEH AND HIS FATHER'S CAREER (SHAIKH OF OMAN)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-19T22:05:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (21 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 23; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-23; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a report entitled 'Sketch of the Careers of Saleh Bin Ali and his son Isa Bin Saleh: The Stormy Petrels of Oman Politics.' Written by the Political Agent and Consul at Muscat, the report comprises an account of the career of Saleh bin Ali bin Nasir of the El Harth tribe [Shaikh Ṣāliḥ bin ‘Alī al-Ḥārthī], of which there are two copies, plus an account of the activities of his son, Isa bin Ali [Shaikh ‘Īsá bin Ṣāliḥ al-Ḥārthī]. The report is produced by the Political Agent and Consul at Muscat, and is preceded by a covering letter, which is addressed to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and is dated 14 April 1930.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Ṣāliḥ bin ‘Alī al-Ḥārthī</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh 'Īsá bin Ṣāliḥ al-Ḥārithī</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000008#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>