<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000139_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T01:27:43.235Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000139_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/39</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000139</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000139/IOR_L_PS_12_39_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/39</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 5615/31 'Hejaz-Nejd: Hejazi representation at The Hague &amp; in Batavia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2019-05-28T22:35:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description (used for referencing) commences at f 538, and terminates at f 543, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises correspondence relating to the diplomatic representation of the Kingdom of Hejaz and Najd at The Hague and in Batavia.The file includes a letter from HBM Minister, Jedda (Cecil Gervase Hope Gill) to HM Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, with background information on the representatives: Ibn Saud's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at The Hague (Shaikh Hafidh Wahba); the First Secretary in charge of the Hejazi Legation at the Hague (Shaikh Abdulla Ibrahim al Fadhl); and Hejazi Consul in Batavia (Seyyid Hamza al Ghouth). Also discussed is the issue of the financing of these posts by the Government of Hejaz and Najd.Correspondence also discusses the potential role of a Dutch bank in financing the delegation. Other correspondents include the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; the Under-Secretary of State for India; and the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, India Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Hejaz and Najd</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Najd</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hejaz</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000139#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>