<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000005_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T19:04:30.511Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000005_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>1781.b.6/71</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000005</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100022547736.0x000001/1781.b.6_0124.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>1781.b.6/71</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Pilger aus Gross-Atjeh mit zwei “Wakīl’s”'. Photographer: Christiaan Snouck Hurgronje</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1888/1888</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-23T05:13:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ger</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 collotype print</extent><extent>Dimensions:188 x 235 mmFormat:1 collotype printCondition:The print is in good condition.Foliation:‘XXXVI’</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Genre/Subject Matter:This full-length portrait shows four pilgrims from Aceh, Indonesia with two ‘wakeels’, presumably the men standing in the background. They all face forward, looking towards the camera.The man on the right wears a white open shirt, dark-coloured trousers, sandals and a dark coloured fez-like hat. The standing man second from right wears a white turban and
                           thawbwith a sash at his waist, a mid-coloured waistcoat and a shawl slung over his left shoulder. The seated man third from right wears a striped waistcoat over a white
                           thawb, checked trousers and a white shawl slung over his left shoulder. The seated man third from left wears a white shirt, dark-coloured trousers and a white turban. The standing man second from left wears a white
                           thawb, turban and patterned waistcoat. The man at left wears a white
                           thawb, dark-coloured waistcoat, checked shawl and mid-coloured turban.The men are photographed in a courtyard-like space with plants – some in wide wooden pots and barrels – foliage and a window, fronted by bars, visible in the background.The negative has had hand-work applied, causing it to take on a soft-shaded paint-like quality in places.Inscriptions:Printed above image, in ink:XXXVIPrinted beneath image, in ink:‘Pilger aus Gross-Atjeh mit zwei „Wakil’s.“’A circular 'British Museum' blind stamp is located in the lower left corner.</abstract><typeOfResource>still image</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Photograph</genre><subject><topic>Portrait photography</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000005#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>