<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000067_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T13:59:22.138Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000067_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F111/535</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000067</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000067/MSS EUR F111_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F111/535</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'PRINCIPAL DESPATCHES AND CORRESPONDENCE RELATING TO PERSIA CONNECTED WITH THE SUMMARY OF EVENTS AND MEASURES OF VICEROYALTY OF HIS EXCELLENCY LORD CURZON OF KEDDLESTON IN THE FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. JANUARY 1899 TO NOVEMBER 1905. VOLUME IV-PART IV. PERSIA.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>0000/0000</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-08-03T09:27:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (64 folios)</extent><extent>The despatches and correspondence are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. There is a list of contents on folio 6, giving details of name and date of paper, subject, and page number.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 66; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the volume also contains an original manuscript pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Published by Superintendent Government Printing, India, Calcutta.The volume consists of a draft Part IV to the
                           Summary of the Principal Events and Measures of the Viceroyalty of His Excellency Lord Curzon of Keddleston, Viceroy and Governor-General of India in the Foreign Department. I. January 1899-April 1904. II. December 1904-November 1905. Volume IV. Persia and the Persian Gulf(Parts I-III), published by GC [Government Central] Press, Simla, 1907 [Mss Eur F111/531-534].The volume includes a letter from the Foreign Department, Government of India, to Lord Curzon, dated 27 August 1908, stating that an examination of their records had shown that these were the essential despatches, and hoping that the volume would answer Lord Curzon's purpose.The despatches and correspondence cover the period 1899-1905, and include correspondence from the Secretary of State for India, and HBM's Minister at Tehran, and cover the question of the appointment of an additional consular officer in Persia, 1899 (with map); relations between Britain and Persia; the protection of British interests in Persia; British policy on Persia; the political and financial situation in Persia; and the threat of Russian encroachment.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Colonial policy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000067#share">Creative Commons Attribution Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000067#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001491.0x000067#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>