<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100046596924.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T11:40:33.148Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100046596924.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 2408</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100046596924.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100046596924.0x000001/Or 2408_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 2408</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb al-mughnī fī al-adwiyah al-mufradah كتاب المغني في الأدوية المفردة  Ibn al-Bayṭār, ʻAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad ابن البيطار، عبد الله بن أحمد</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1447/1447</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-30T22:01:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. i+287+ii</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 260 x 170 mm leaf [190 x 120 mm written]Foliation: Eastern Arabic pagination in black ink extends only as far as p. 200 (f. 102r), British Museum foliation in pencilRuling: No ruling visible; 15 lines per page; vertical spacing 8 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Naskh; the scribe is Ways ibn ‘Awaḍ (ويس ابن عوض, see colophon, f. 287r, lines 4-7)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated headings and occasional punctuation and overlinings in redDecoration: Calligraphic
                           basmalain thuluth script (f. 2v)Binding: Red leather Western binding, with blind-tooled medallions and bordersCondition: Tidemarks at tail towards front of volume and at head towards back of volume, edge corners mutilated and repaired on ff. 1-15 and 271-87 with no loss of text, minor insect damageMarginalia: Very fewSeals: f. 287r</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Volume One (المجلد الأول) of a medical compendium on the use of simples to cure various ailments by the Andalusian botanist Ḍiyā’ al-Dīn Abū Muḥammad ʻAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad al-Mālaqī (ضياء الدين أبو محمد عبد الله بن أحمد بن محمد المالقي; d. 1248), known as Ibn al-Bayṭār (ابن البيطار), Chief Herbalist (رئيس العشابين) to the Ayyubid sultan al-Malik al-Kāmil (reg. 1218-38). The text is dedicated to al-Malik al-‘Ādil II (الملك العادل سيف الدين أبو بكر بن الملك الكامل, reg. 1238-40, see. f. 3v, lines 5-12).The text is arranged by affected part from head to toe in twenty chapters (باب), of which this copy contains the first eight. Each chapter is then subdivided by ailment into sections (فصول). A list of all twenty chapters and their titles is found on ff. 4r-4v. The contents of the present volume are as follows:Chapter One: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Head (الباب الأول في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض الرأس, ff. 5r-59r);Chapter Two: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Eye (الباب الثاني في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض العين, ff. 59r-89v);Chapter Three: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Ear (الباب الثالث في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض الأذن, ff. 89v-101v);Chapter Four: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Nose (الباب الرابع في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض الأنف, ff. 101v-105v);Chapter Five: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Mouth (الباب الخامس في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض الفم, ff. 105v-129r);Chapter Six: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Throat, Organs of Respiration, the Chest and its Contents (الباب السادس في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض الحلق وآلات التنفس والصدر وما يحويه, ff. 129r-180v);Chapter Seven: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Stomach, Liver and Spleen (الباب السابع في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض المعدة والكبد والطحال, ff. 180v-236v);Chapter Eight: Simple Drugs Beneficial for Ailments of the Intestines (الباب الثامن في الأدوية المفردة النافعة من أمراض الأمعاء, ff. 236v-287r).The title page (f. 2r) claims that the volume was owned by the Ottoman sultan Bāyezīd II (بايزيد بن محمد خان مظفر دائمًا, reg. 1481-1512). This claim is substantiated by what appears to be the defaced seal of Bāyezīd II to the left of the colophon on f. 287r (see Chester Beatty Library Islamic Seals Database no. 2 and cf. impressions of this seal in Add. MS 18866, f 292r and Add. MS 7515, ff. 1r and 132v).The copy was completed in early Jumādá I 851/second half of July 1447 by Ways ibn ‘Awaḍ (ويس ابن عوض, see colophon, f. 287r, lines 4-7, transcribed below).Begins (f. 2v, lines 2-4):الحمد لله الذي أنزل لكل داء دواء فاستحق بوجود نعمائه على عبادهحمدًا وثناءً وأقام لكل علم حملة جمعوا منها اشتاتًا وتحملواله أعباءً فإن احوا (!) من كد النصب من سلك سبيلهم اقتدا ...Ends (f. 286v, line 13-f. 287r, line 1):قال أبو جريح يولد الحيات في البطن من الأشياءالفجة اللينة مثل القمح والفول واللوبيا والحمص وأكل اللحم الفتيمن لحم الخنزير وسف الدقيق وإدمان شرب اللبن وشرب العسل بالماءبالماء (!) بعد الطعام كثيرًا ومن أكل الخبز الوسخ الحبColophon (f. 287r, lines 2-9):تم المجلد الأول من الكتابالمرسوم بمفردات ابن بيطار رحمه اللهرحمة واسعة حرر في أوائلجمادى الآخرة أحد شهورسنة إحدى وخمسين وثمانيةكتبه ويس ابن عوض غفر الله لهولجميع المسلمين والمسلمات والمؤمنين والمؤمناتبرحمتك يا أرحم الراحمين</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript item</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Chief Herbalist ʻAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad Ibn al-Bayṭār</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100046596924.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>