<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T11:36:44.990Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3833</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191/IOR_L_PS_12_3833_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3833</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/108(2) 'Quarantine Medical Officers at Bahrain, Koweit and Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-01T22:55:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (45 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 47; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the appointment, and terms and conditions of Quarantine Medical Officers at Bahrain, Koweit [Kuwait] and Muscat.The papers include a 'Report of Dr Pridie, Medical Adviser to the British Middle East Office on Medical, Sanitary and Quarantine arrangements in the Gulf States' (folios 42-45); a report by Lieutenant-Colonel William Joseph Moody (Medical Adviser to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) concerning reliefs for the Quarantine Medical Officers at Bahrain and Kuwait (folios 24-25); and a report on quarantine and medical arrangements at Sitra, which advocated the need for a full-time Quarantine Medical Officer there (folios 20-22).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Koweit</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Quarantine</topic></subject><subject><topic>Medical personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>