<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ac_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T11:04:13.681Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ac_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/710</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ac</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ac/IOR_R_15_1_710_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/710</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Administration Reports 1905-1910'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1907/1911</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-18T00:07:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (304 folios)</extent><extent>There is a list of contents at the front of each Report.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at 1 on the front cover and terminates at 306 on the back cover. These numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. The following folios need to be folded out to be read: ff. 40, 261.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains
                           Administration Report on the Persian Gulf Political Residency for 1905-1906(Calcutta: Office of the Superintendent of Government Printing, India, 1907);
                           Administration Report on the Persian Gulf Political Residency and Maskat Political Agency for 1906-1907(Calcutta: Superintendent Government Printing, India, 1908);
                           Administration Report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency and the Maskat Political Agency for 1907-1908(Calcutta: Superintendent Government Printing, India, 1909);
                           Administration Report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency and the Maskat Political Agency for April-December1908(Calcutta: Superintendent Government Printing, India, 1909);
                           Administration Report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency for the Year Ending 31st December 1909(Calcutta: Superintendent Government Printing, India, 1911); and
                           Administration Report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency for the Year 1910(Calcutta: Superintendent Government Printing, India, 1911).The Reports contain reviews by the Political Resident and chapters on each of the consulates, agencies, and other administrative regions that made up the Persian Gulf Residency. The Reports contain information on political developments, territorial divisions, local administration, principal tribes, British personnel and appointments, trade and commerce, naval and marine matters, communications, judicial matters, archaeology, pearl fisheries, the slave trade, arms and ammunition traffic, medical matters and public health, oil, notable visitors and events, meteorological data, and related topics.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ac#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>