<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000398_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T15:30:08.535Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000398_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/185</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000398</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000398/IOR_R_15_2_185_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/185</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 3/11 Creation of Post of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-23T00:08:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (287 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged approximately in chronological order. There are file notes at the end of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: There is one foliation sequence that runs from the first page of text until the file notes that follow folio 266. These numbers appear in the top right hand of the recto side of the folio and are written in pencil. The file notes consist of 20 folios and run until the back cover. Foliation annomalies: 36b; foliations skips 224 and 225.Condition: There is tear damage on folio 197 causing some of the text in the top and bottom right of the folio to be missing.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the British Political Agent at Bahrain; the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire; Charles Mylles, Anglo-Persian Oil Company at Abadan; R Holmes, Assistant Surgeon, Victoria Memorial Hospital; R I Hallows; C R Latimer; Secretary to the Government of Bombay; Captain C A R Shillington, Naval Officer in Charge, Bahrain; Naval Officer in Charge, Basra; Royal Air Force, Sharjah; Political Officer in the Trucial Coast at Sharjah; and T P Tandy.These correspondence concern the creation of the post of Assistant Political Agent in 1935 and those who held the position until 1945, including: Meredith Worth; George Ashmead Cole; Roy Douglas Metcalfe; Tom Hickinbotham; John Baron Howes; Arnold Crashaw Galloway; Richard Ernest Bird; R I Hallows; Gordon Noel Jackson; Michael Gray Dixon; Reginald Michael Hadow; T E Rogers; and Maurice Patrick O'Connor Tandy.Included within these papers are correspondence relating to setting up of the post of Assistant Political Agent as a temporary position as a result of the increase work load due to oil concession and the Imperial Airways air route (ff. 1-11); subsequent correspondence extending the appointment for periods of six months (ff. 15-16, 32); correspondence reiterating the importance of the post and requesting it to be made on permanent (ff. 17-21, 37-42, 261-264); correspondence relating to appointments to the post; correspondence related to post holders wishing to take war employment during the Second World War (ff. 161-170, 196-198); and correspondence relating to the Assistant Political Agent's role in the Bahrain judicial system (ff. 243-246).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000398#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000398#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000398#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>