<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f5_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-22T08:57:02.011Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2219</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f5</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f5/IOR_L_PS_12_2219_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2219</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/48A 'Afghanistan: sale of surplus American military equipment to'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-16T10:56:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (21 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 22; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence between the Government of India External Affairs Department, the India Office Political Department, and HM Legation Kabul, regarding approaches made by the Afghan Government to purchase military and civil equipment from American surplus stock. The correspondence includes discussion of the sale of equipment under lend/lease arrangements, and British and Indian concerns over Afghanistan acquiring arms or ammunition from other sources.A communication from the Afghan Foreign Ministry, sending a list of members of an Afghan Commission to India with a view to purchasing American equipment, can be found at folio 8. Heads of Agreement between the Governments of India and the USA regarding the disposal of surplus American equipment in India can be found at folio 5.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Bilateral relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Lend-lease operations (1941-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f5#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002f5#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>