<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100049407246.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T13:55:27.449Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100049407246.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 5839</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100049407246.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100049407246.0x000001/Or 5839_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 5839</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Jāmiʿ li-mufradāt al-adwiyah wa-al-aghdhiyah جامع لمفردات الأدوية والأغذية  Ibn al-Bayṭār, ʻAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad ابن البيطار، عبد الله بن أحمد</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1303/1303</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-23T22:04:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. i+198+i</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 260 x 180 mm leaf [185 x 125 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencilRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 23 lines per page; vertical spacing 13 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Naskh; the scribe is Muḥammad ibn ‘Abd al-Raḥmān ibn ‘Abd Allāh al-‘Umarī (محمد بن عبد الرحمن ابن عبد الله العمري, see colophon, f. 198r, lines 15)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated headings and lemmata and marginal headings in redDecoration: NoneBinding: British Museum half-leather bindingCondition: Minor insect damage, tidemarks in edge margin towards front of volume; ff. 1-8 mutilated and repaired at head marginMarginalia: Moderate amount by more than one handSeals: ff. 1r and 1v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Part (جزء) three of four (containing entries زنجار to قشبة) of one of the most influential and important Arabic handbooks of materia medica, written by the Andalusian botanist Ḍiyā’ al-Dīn Abū Muḥammad ʻAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad (ضياء الدين أبو محمد عبد الله بن أحمد; d. 1248), known as Ibn al-Bayṭār (ابن البيطار), Chief Herbalist (رئيس العشابين) to the Ayyubid sultan al-Malik al-Kāmil (reg. 1218-38).The copy was completed on Thursday 27 Jumādá I 702/17 January 1303 by Muḥammad ibn ‘Abd al-Raḥmān ibn ‘Abd Allāh al-‘Umarī (محمد بن عبد الرحمن ابن عبد الله العمري), who created the copy for his own use (see colophon, f. 198r, lines 14-18, transcribed below).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-4):زنجار ديسقوريدوس في 5 ما كان منه تسميه اليونان قسنـ[...]مسينطوس (؟) ومعناه المجرود فإنه يعمل على هذه الصفة يصب خل ثقيـ[...]في إجابة أو في إناء آخر يشبه بالخابية ويغطا الإناء بغطاء من نحاس ...Ends (f. 198r, lines 7-11):قشبه كتاب الرحلة القشبة اسم حجازي لقشر مجلوب إلى مكه (؟) يشبه ما غلظ من قشر السليخة الحمراء تشوبهخضرة يسيرة طعمه منه قبوضة وعفوصة يسيرة يستعملونهفي بخورات النساء يؤتى به من اليمن أول الاسم قاف مكسورة ثم شين معجمة ساكنة ثم باء بواحدة مفتوحة بعدها هاءColophon (f. 198r, lines 12-23):نجز الجزء الثالث من أربعة أجزاء من كتاب الجامعلقوى الأدوية المفر[د]ة والحمد لله وحدهنسخـ[ـه] بيده لنفسه العبد الفقير إلى رحمة ربه المعترف بخطاياهوذنبه محمد بن عبد الرحمن ابن عبد الله العمريعفا الله عنه وعن والديه وعن جميع المسلمين[كا]ن الفراغ منه ليلة يسفر صباحها عن يوم الخميس السابع والعشرينمن شهر جمادى الأولى سنة أثنين وسبعمائة للهجرة النبوية المحمديةصلى الله عليه وعلى آله وصحبه وسلميتلوه الجزء الرابع إن شاء الله وهو بقية حرف القاف وأولهقصب ديسقوريدوس في الأولىمنه ما يقال له ناسطوس وهو المصمتوالحمد لله سبحانه كثيرًا وصلواته على خير خلقه وعبيده محمد وآله الطييبين والطاهرين</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Chief Herbalist ʻAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad Ibn al-Bayṭār</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100049407246.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>