<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T21:06:07.831Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1136</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307/IOR_R_15_2_1136_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1136</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/20 III Recoveries of amounts spent on behalf of R.A.F. Hinaidi.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T12:01:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (456 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminates with a set of notes between folios 433-457. Circled reference numbers in blue and red crayon refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 458; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 3-432; these numbers are written in a combination of blue crayon and pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the payment by the Political Agency, Bahrain of expenses incurred by the Royal Air Force (RAF) and its personnel in Bahrain (also spelled Bahrein) and the Trucial Coast, particularly payments to Shaikh Said bin Maktum [Saʻīd bin Maktūm], Ruler of Dubai, and Shaikh Sultan bin Salim [Sulṭān bin Sālim Āl Qasimī], Ruler of Ras al Khaimah.The correspondence is mainly from the Political Agent, Bahrain; staff of Air Headquarters, British Forces in Iraq, Hinaidi; the Residency Agent, Sharjah; and the Air Liaison Officer, RAF Bahrain. There is also some correspondence from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Government of India and the India Office.The papers cover: correspondence and receipts recording monthly payments made by the Political Agency, Bahrain (through the Residency Agent, Sharjah) to the Ruler of Dubai for hire of a petrol dhow and pay for its guards, for the period December 1937 to November 1941, and to the Ruler of Ras al Khaimah for pay of guards on the petrol barge, for the period December 1937 to June 1942; monthly bills of expenditure incurred by the Political Agency, Bahrain on behalf of the RAF, sent to the Command Accountant, British Forces in Iraq, Hinaidi; correspondence concerning payment of sundry expenses incurred by the RAF in Bahrain, (e.g. the use by RAF personnel of the Bahrain Rest House); correspondence concerning accounting arrangements for the payment of expenses incurred by the RAF, including the handover of responsibility for all payments other than those to the rulers of Dubai and Ras al Khaimah to the Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain (from September 1939); and correspondence between the British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC) and the Political Agent, Bahrain concerning the transfer of responsibility for payments for the guards on the petrol barge at Ras al Khaimah to BOAC, October 1942.The Arabic language content of the file consists of approximately eighty items of correspondence (all with translations into English) between the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Residency Agent, Sharjah; and approximately twenty other items, mostly receipts issued by the Rulers of Dubai and Ras al Khaimah (all with translations into English).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Forces in Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Dubai, Āl Maktūm dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>RAF Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Ra's al-Khaymah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Air force personnel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Army</topic></subject><subject><topic>Travel allowances</topic></subject><subject><topic>Coffee</topic></subject><subject><topic>Hospitality</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000307#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>