<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000016_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T23:01:25.707Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000016_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/132, ff 54-57</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000016</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000069/IOR_R_15_1_132_0109.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/132, ff 54-57</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 2 of 1853 from Captain Arnold Burrowes Kemball, Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bushire to Arthur Malet, Chief Secretary to the Government, Secret Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1853/1853</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-15T00:33:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>4 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is enclosing extracts from the British Agents at Muscat, Khoja Hiskael, and Bahrein [Bahrain], Hajee Jassem. The extracts report on a visit to these places made by Behjut Effendi, who has been deputed by Abbas Pasha, the Viceroy of Egypt [Wāli of Egypt and Sudan] to purchase horses. It notes that the Resident has not uncovered any evidence through his investigations at Bahrein indicating that he is engaging in intrigues prejudicial to British interests.Note that Behjut Effendi is also spelt Bihjet Effendi in the item.The item has three enclosures:1. Translated extract of a letter from the British Agent at Muscat to the Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated 2 May 1853.The enclosure reports the arrival of Behjut Effendi at Muscat aboard the
                           Bombay; it indicates that he is bound for Bahrein, and is expected to touch at Sohar [Ṣuḥār]. It notes that he has had an interview with Syed Mahomed ben Salim.2. Translated extract of a letter from the British Agent at Muscat to the Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated 4 May 1853.The enclosure reports that Behjut Effendi has been deputed to purchase horses, and has no other object in mind. It notes he has been presented with five horses by Syed Mahomed ben Salim at Muscat; this was authorised by Syed Saeed [Sa‘īd bin Sultān Āl Sa‘īd], the Imam.3. Translated extract of a letter from the British Agent at Bahrein to the Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated 12 May 1853.The enclosure reports the arrival of Behjut Effendi at Bahrain aboard the
                           Bombay. It notes that he has had a meeting with Shaikh Mahomed ben Khuleefa [Muḥammed bin Khalīfah Āl Khalīfah], and presented gifts to him from Abbas Pasha; in return, it notes he has been presented with more horses than he had originally requested. It also outlines certain political favours that the Shaikh hopes to obtain in return for his generosity.It states that once the
                           Bombayreturns to Bahrein from Muscat with the remaining horses, Behjut Effendi intends to proceed with them to Egypt via the overland route.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000016#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>