<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001e1_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T11:14:55.597Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001e1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/16/16</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001e1</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001e1/IOR_L_MIL_17_16_16_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/16/16</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Military Lessons of the Arab Rebellion in Palestine 1936'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-07T14:39:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (142 folios)</extent><extent>The volume contains a contents page on folio 3.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 144; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Report detailing the military lessons of the Arab rebellion in Palestine in 1936 that was compiled by General Staff, Headquarters, The British Forces, Palestine &amp; Trans-Jordan.The report is divided up into chapters as follows:IntroductionA Short History of the Rebellion I - to the end of June, 1936A Short History of the Rebellion II - from the 1st July, 1936 to the end of the yearConditions in Palestine as Affecting OperationsCommanders and StaffsIntelligenceIntercommunicationAdministrationTransportWeapons and EquipmentThe Employment of Various ArmsThe Employment of Aircraft in Co-operation with TroopsDefensive ActionProtection of CommunicationsOffensive ActionConclusion - Summary of Main LessonsThe report contains 46 photographs and a number of diagrams which are located throughout the volume. It also contains four maps, found at folios 140-143.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Arab Revolt (1936-1939)</topic></subject><subject><geographic>Palestine</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military operations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001e1#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>