<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000033_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T19:04:30.511Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000033_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>1781.b.6/63</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000033</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100022547736.0x000001/1781.b.6_0108.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>1781.b.6/63</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Pilger aus Sambas (Borneo)'. Photographer: Christiaan Snouck Hurgronje</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1888/1888</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-23T05:12:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ger</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 collotype print</extent><extent>Dimensions:187 x 240 mmFormat:1 collotype printCondition:The print is in good condition.Foliation:‘XXVIII’</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Genre/Subject Matter:This full-length portrait shows seven men, described as pilgrims from the Sultanate of Sambas, in modern day Indonesia on the island of Borneo.Six of the men squat face forward, looking towards the camera. The man standing behind them, left of centre is described as the wakeel (representative) of the sheikh.From right to left the men wear: a white
                           thawband patterned turban; a white outer robe over a dark shirt, a ring on the little finger of his right hand, and a dark, patterned turban; a light-coloured outer robe over a button-up shirt, a patterned turban and rings on the little finger of each hand; a light-coloured button-up
                           thawb, and a mid-coloured turban; a dark coloured waistcoat with embroidered lapels, a white shirt, mid-coloured trousers, rings on the little finger of each hand and a light-coloured turban; white
                           thawb, mid-coloured trousers and dark-coloured turban. The standing man wears a white outer robe over a dark-coloured, striped waistcoast and a white
                           thawbwith a light-coloured turban.The men are photographed in a courtyard-like space with plants – some in wide wooden pots – foliage and a window, fronted by bars, visible in the background.The negative has had hand-work applied, causing it to take on a soft-shaded paint-like quality in places.Inscriptions:Printed above image, in ink:XXVIIIPrinted beneath image, in ink:‘Pilger aus Sambas (Borneo) hinter den Pilgern steht der Wakil (Bevollmächtigte) des Schēchs.’A circular 'British Museum' blind stamp is located in the lower left corner.</abstract><typeOfResource>still image</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Photograph</genre><subject><topic>Portrait photography</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023619120.0x000033#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>