<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00020d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T07:19:58.739Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00020d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/552</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00020d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00020d/IOR_R_15_1_552_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/552</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 59/15 B (A 14) Muscat: slave trade under cover of French flag'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1902/1904</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (163 folios)</extent><extent>The papers contained in the volume have been arranged in rough chronological order, from the earliest piece at the front of the volume to the latest at the end.There are two indexes at the front of the volume. The first (found on folio 1A) includes a list of subjects with folio numbers. The second is titled an 'Index of references' (folios 1D-1E), and includes descriptions of correspondence with folio numbers.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to last page, using a combination of two numbering systems. The first foliation system uses blue or red pencil numbers in the top-right of recto and top-left of verso pages. This foliation system is the original foliation system, and is used in the references index pages (folios 1D-1E). This foliation is used on all pages with text, both recto and verso. The second, more recent foliation system uses circled pencil numbers in the top-right corner of recto pages only, and is intended to fill the gaps left by the earlier foliation system. Foliation anomalies: 1A, 1B, 1C, 1D, 1E, 1F, 145A, 145B, 146C, 145D. Foldout item on folio 169.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises correspondence and other papers relating to competing British and French interests in Muscat and Oman at the beginning of the twentieth century. The principal point of contention between British officials, represented by Percy Cox (Muscat Political Agent 1899-1903), was the use of the French flag by Omani vessels, permitted by the French Vice-Consul to Muscat, and regarded by the British as being exploited by the region's slave traders as a means of avoiding interference by British ships.Items of note include a letter from Cox to the Political Resident (Charles Kemball), dated 2 January 1902, discussing relations since 1891 between the Sultan of Muscat and British and French officials, the abuse of the French flag in the town, and the need for diplomatic negotiations between Britain, France and the Sultan to resolve the situation (folios 1F-37). Enclosed with Cox's letter is an eyewitness account (from a British Indian subject residing in Soor [Sur]) of slave trading activity in the town during 1901 (folios 31-35). The file also includes a letter from Cox to his French counterpart (Roger Laronce), dated February 1902, explaining that the Sultan protests at what he describes as the French Government's claims to exercise jurisdiction in Muscat territory over Omani subjects (folios 70-71), and Laronce's reply (folion 73); and a report of a tour of the Muscat coast aboard HMS "Amphritite" by Cox (folios 120-22) and Charles Windham, the "Amphritites's" captain (folios 147-49).Reference is made in a number of pieces of correspondence to a confrontation between Arab slave traders and the Portuguese in Mozambique on 18 March 1902 (folios 117-118, and 140-141). In May 1903 Cox writes to the Political Resident, informing him that he has received information from the British Vice-Consul at Mozambique, of around 100 inhabitants of Muscat and Sur being captured and killed in the confrontation (folios 178-180). Cox uses this incident to repeat his recommendation that a British Agent be installed at Sur (folios 145b-145d). Arrangements are also made to loan the Sultan of Muscat funds to enable him to buy his own steamer (folios 123-127), which Cox hopes will encourage the Sultan to take responsibility for his coast, and in particular Sur (folios 135-138). A blueprint of the steamer acquired for the Sultan is included in the file (foldout plan, folio 169).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman Fayṣal bin Turkī Āl Bū Sa'īd</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00020d#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00020d#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00020d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>