<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00007e_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:05:14.998Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00007e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C41/5</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00007e</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00007e/IOR_L_PS_18_C41_5_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C41/5</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Correspondence respecting the occupation of Merv by Russia and her proceedings on the Khorassan Frontier of Persia.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1884/1884</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-30T09:22:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (13 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 110 and terminates at the last folio with 122, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 110-122; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is a memorandum written by Adolphus Warburton Moore, Political and Secret Department, of historical events and correspondence relating to the occupation of Merv by Russia, and to Russian activity in Khorassan, on the Persian boundary.The memorandum reproduces a despatch to the Russian Ambassador to London, in which Lord Granville, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, expresses the British Government's displeasure at hearing of the Russian annexation of Merv, against assurances previously given by the Government of the Russian Empire. The memorandum gives the Russian response, describing the annexation as merely an act of local administration without political pre-meditation on the part of Russia, who continue to seek co-operation and friendly relations with the British Government.The memorandum goes on to describe British concerns and Russian denials that they next intended to annexe Sarakhs on the Persian border, and, upon the arrival of Russian troops at Sarakhs and in other parts of Khorassan, Persian protests to the Russian Government.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ambassador of the Russian Federation to the United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of the Russian Empire</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Persia, Qajar dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Khorasan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sarakhs</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Merv</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military occupation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00007e#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00007e#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00007e#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>