<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100046067744.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T11:32:46.762Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100046067744.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 7484</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100046067744.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100046067744.0x000001/Add MS 7484_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 7484</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb al-ta‘dīl fī al-hay’ah كتاب التعديل في الهيئة  Maḥbūbī, ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Masʿūd محبوبي، عبيد الله بن مسعود</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1420/1420</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-10T22:06:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. ii+70+ii</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 173 x 125 mm leaf [110 x 80 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencil; nine quires (eight quaternions and one ternion) with mid-quire marks and quire signatures visible on ff. 9r, 17r, 26r, 34r, 42r, 50r, 58r, and 66rRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 19 lines per page; vertical spacing 17 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Nasta‘līq; the scribe isAḥmad b. Sirāj al-Dīn al-Ghijduwānī (أحمد بن سراج الدين الغجدواني, see scribe's colophon, f. 70r)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated headings, abbreviations, overlinings and diagrams in redDecoration: NoneBinding: Half-leather binding with marbled paper on boardsCondition: Tidemarks towards head of volume; black ink stain in lower edge corner; some foxingMarginalia: Annotations by more than one handSeals: f. 1r</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Commentary by ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Masʿūd al-Maḥbūbī al-Bukhārī al-Ḥanafī (عبيد الله بن مسعود المحبوبي البخاري الحنفي, d. 1346 or 47) known as Ṣadr al-Sharīʿa al-Thānī (صدر الشريعة الثاني) on his own treatise on astronomy. The treatise, without commentary, formed the third and final part of his encyclopaedia of sciences known as the
                           Adjustment of the Sciences(تعديل العلوم). The composition of the text was completed at noon on Wednesday 6 Rabī‘ II 747/26 July 1346, in the shrine or district of Shara‘ābād (مقام شرعآباد) in Bukhārā (see author's colophon, f. 70r, lines 18-19, transcribed below).The lemmata of the text commented upon are indicated by the abbreviation م (= متن), and the commentary is indicated by س or ش (= شرح).The title page (f. 1r) reads:كتابالتعديل في الهيئةلخان صدر الشريعةالبخاريThe copy was completed at Bukhārā in mid-Rajab 823/mid-July 1420 by Aḥmad b. Sirāj al-Dīn al-Ghijduwānī (أحمد بن سراج الدين الغجدواني), who praises the ruler and well-known patron of mathematics and astronomy Ulugh Beg (ألغ بگ, d. 1449; see scribe's colophon, f. 70r, transcribed below).The text contains numerous diagrams, and some spaces have been left blank for diagrams that were never added (see e.g. f. 68v). A slip of paper containing two diagrams of planetary revolutions has been bound into the volume as f. 18.This copy was used as the primary witness for the edition prepared by Dallal (1995, see p. 4).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-4):م الحمد لله الذي زين السماء بالبروج بعدما أحكم بناءها فقال وزيناها وما لها من فروجوالصلوة على رسوله الذي جعل سراجًا منيرًا ومن نوره مستنيرًا وجعل اله وآله وأصحابه نجومًاولشياطين الإنس رجومًا ...Ends (f. 70r, lines 16-18):فإذا كان الارتفاع الغربي ذلك المقدار تنصب خشبة أو يعلق شاقول فظل الخشبة أو ظل خيط الشاقولهو سمت القبلة هذا العمل لا يحتاج إلى الشرح بل يحتاج إلى معرفة الأصطرلاب وبعد معرفة العمل سهل واللههو المسهل لكل عين ...Author's colophon (f. 70r, lines 18-19):... تم تصنيفه ظهيرة يوم الأربعاء السادس من ربيع الآخر سنة سبع وأربعينوسبعمائة في مقام شرعآباد من مدينة بخارا صانها الله تعالى مع سائر بلاد المسلمين عن الآفات والمخافاتScribe's colophon (f. 70r, written diagonally to main text block, below author's colophon):تمت كتابته على يد العبد المذنب الجانيأحمد بن سراج الدين الغجدوانيفي أواسط رجب سنة 823بفاخرة بخارا صينت عن البلاياوهي من ممالك السلطان الأعظموالخاقان المكرم العالم بدقائق العلوم والحكممعين الدين ظهير الدولة أميرزادهألغ بيگ كورگان زيد عدلهورأفته على أصل الإيمانبمنه وكنه</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>‘Ubayd Allāh ibn Mas‘ūd Maḥbūbī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Astronomy--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100046067744.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>