<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000069_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T23:40:03.368Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000069_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/143, ff 372-377</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000069</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000074/IOR_R_15_1_143_0770.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/143, ff 372-377</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter no.230 of 1854 from Captain Arnold Kemball, Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Henry Anderson, Secretary to the Government of Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1854/1854</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-20T00:57:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>6 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter relates to the import of slaves into the Persian port of Charrack [Bandar-e Chārak] last season, and arrangements to ensure that Shaikh Hassan ben Abdullah of Bandar-e Chārak fulfils the terms of the bond executed by him. The following enclosures are included with Kemball’s letter:1. Letter no.91 of 1854 (folios 373-75) from Kemball to William Taylour Thomson, His Majesty’s Chargé D’Affaires at the Court of Persia, Tehran, dated 15 March 1854. The letter is an account of Shaikh Hassan’s visit to Bushire, and his interviews with Kemball over the slave trade at Bandar-e Chārak. Kemball writes that, though Shaikh Hassan initially denied that slaves had been imported into his dominions, he later conceded that ten slaves had been imported and were still in Bandar-e Chārak. Kemball writes that the fine due from Shaikh Hassan is fifty Tomans. Included with Kemball’s letter is the translation of a written promise (folio 375) from Shaikh Hassan to Kemball, to hand over the ten slaves in his possession to the Persian Slave Trade Commissioner, Meerza Mahmood Khan.2. Letter no.229 of 1854 (folios 376-77) from Kemball to Commodore George Robinson, Commanding Officer Persian Gulf Squadron, dated 25 June 1854, in which Kemball requests that Robinson despatch the steam frigate
                           Ferozeto Bandar-e Chārak, with one of the Persian Slave Trade Commissioner’s deputies on board, in order to retrieve the ten slaves and fine from Shaikh Hassan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000069#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>