<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T14:35:54.027Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/836</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f/IOR_R_15_2_836_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/836</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 33/11 Supply of Electricity to RAF by Bahrain Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-04T00:15:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (49 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence concerning the electricity supply of the Royal Air Force (RAF) and British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC) establishments in Bahrain.The correspondence is primarily between Arnold Crawshaw Galloway, Britain's Political Agent in Bahrain; Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; and William Benjamin Steele, State Engineer of Bahrain. Also enclosed are letters from various Royal Air Force officials and W P Anderson of the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO).The file contains two agreements:1) 'Agreement between the Government of Bahrain and the Air Ministry of Great Britain for supply of electricity to the Royal Air Force on Muharraq' (ff 16-18);2) 'Agreement between Government of Bahrain Electricity Supply Department and the Air Ministry of Great Britain for the supply of electricity to Royal Air Force and British Overseas Airways establishments - Manamah and Muharraq' (ff 39-44).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00010f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>