<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000123_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T05:24:24.783Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000123_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3727</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000123</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000123/IOR_L_PS_12_3727_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3727</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/17(S) 'Persian Gulf: Policy of H.M.G. Strategical Position &amp; Imperial Considerations; Defence of Persian Gulf in time of War'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-13T22:00:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (324 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 326; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials that discusses the measures put in place to defend the Persian Gulf in the event of a major war. The correspondence discusses both the strategic importance of the region to the British Empire and the military steps that were required in order to defend it adequately.In addition to correspondence, the file contains the following:'Main Items of Expenditure Proposed in the Defence Appreciations for the Arab Gulf States' (folios 40-41)Minutes of the Overseas Defence Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, 14 June 1939 (folios 53-58)'The Importance of Oil Supplies from Bahrein [Bahrain]. Memorandum by the Petroleum Department', 11 April 1938 (folios 162-163)Minutes of the Overseas Defence Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, 11 April 1938 (folios 167-169)'Record of an Informal Discussion held at the India Office on 14th April [1938] to consider the Political Resident's Memorandum regarding the Defence of the Persian Gulf in the Event of a Major War' (folios 190-194)A demi-official note entitled "Defence of the Persian Gulf in the Event of a Major War" (folios 230-251)'General Staff Appreciation of the Situation in the Persian Gulf' written by Lieutenant-General A Skeen, Chief of the General Staff, India, 5 October 1928 (folios 296-299)'Defence Scheme for Bahrein [Bahrain]' by the Committee of Imperial Defence, July 25 1938 (folio 320).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Imperialism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military strategy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000123#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>