<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000007_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T16:22:11.514Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000007_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/38, ff 24v-28</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000007</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x0003b1/Mss Eur F126_38_0048.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/38, ff 24v-28</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 7 of 1866 from Lewis Pelly, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, on board Her Majestys Steamer
                              Berenice, off Soor [Sur] to Charles Gonne, Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1866/1866</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-30T01:16:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>5 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter regarding the completion of Captain Pasley's objective to destroy a Wahabee [Wahhabi] fort on the coast and his ship
                           Highflyer's inability to complete remaining task in blockading other Wahabee forts owing to their having been re-enforced and the need for native pilots from Bahrein [Bahrain].The letter goes on to report on the need for a prompt and severe example for those implicated with the Wahabees in the plunder and murder of British Indian subjects and for arrangements to be made by the British Government in Bombay for the bombing of two further Wahabee forts.Enclosed is a letter from Lewis Pelly to Captain Pasley, 09 February 1866 regarding the shallowness of the water and other checks which had prevented the Captain from reaching Dammauer and the need to punish those implicated in the plunder and butchery of British Subjects. The enclosure goes on to discuss Captain Pasley bringing the
                           Highflyerto Soor [Sur] and Pelly's intention of forwarding mentions of favourable conduct of several of the Captain's men to the Government of India.The Government's reply No. 573 of 1866 can be found on folio 63</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024174347.0x000007#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>