<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001aa_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T05:24:37.017Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001aa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/453</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001aa</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001aa/IOR_R_15_1_453_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/453</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Muscat, Wazir of - Appointment, Leave, Pay, etc'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (241 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file. There is an index at the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: The main foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerns Stuart Edwin Hedgcock, Financial Adviser, Muscat, and the termination of his services and proposed reinstatement. The correspondence notes the detailed scrutiny of the State's budget by Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr].Also discussed is the Muscat Levy Corps budget: the object, strenght and composition of the Corps; present strength of Corps; Headquarters Staff; Non Commissioned Officers; Followers; pay. Correspondence also deals with the alleged irregularities of Captain Alan Robertson Walker, Commanding Officer, Muscat Levies.Correspondents include Major Trenchard Craven W Fowle, Political Agent, Muscat; Captain Reginald George Alban, Political Agent, Muscat; Lieutenant-Colonel Hugh Vincent Biscoe, Political Resident Persian Gulf; Stuart Edwin Hedgecock, Financial Adviser, Muscat; Sayyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat;</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Financial Advisor to the Sultan of Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Muscat Regiment</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001aa#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001aa#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>