<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T02:43:45.528Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1536</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010f/IOR_R_15_2_1536_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1536</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 16/32-A Purchases on behalf of Bushire Residency’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-18T22:24:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (170 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 156-171) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 172; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-53; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and other papers, exchanged between staff at the Political Agency in Bahrain and others, including the British Residency and Consulate in Bushire and the Government of Bahrain, relating to the order or exchange of goods from suppliers, merchants and colleagues, with shipping arrangements frequently made with the Bahrain shipping agent Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited. Goods discussed include:Electrolux refrigerators, ordered through the Bahrain merchant Yousuf Abdul Rahman Fakhroo, and including correspondence for the delivery of one refrigerator to H Borovitz of the Etimadeyah Spinning and Weaving Company in Bushire;medical supplies, including quinine, and a request from the Chief Medical Officer for the Government of Bahrain for Penicillin, with correspondence following on arrangements for the quick delivery of Penicillin to Bahrain;other miscellaneous items including coke, washing soda, vegetable ghee, electrical wiring, coir matting, car batteries, and stamps.A small number of papers in the file are in Arabic.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Abdulla Yousif Fakhro Group, merchant</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Penicillin</topic></subject><subject><topic>Refrigerators</topic></subject><subject><topic>Supplies</topic></subject><subject><topic>Freight services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010f#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010f#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>