<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023593365.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T15:20:33.138Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023593365.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/4, ff 4-7</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023593365.0x000002</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00037c/Mss Eur F126_4_0007.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/4, ff 4-7</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from Charles Umpherston Aitchison, Simla to Lewis Pelly</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1873/1873</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-30T17:04:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>4 folios</extent><extent>Condition: A large piece of the paper booklet forming the bottom left corner of folios two and three has been torn off, however it does not affect the written contents of the letter.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter providing Pelly with information about Rajpootana [Rajasthan] including how British relations with the local Chiefs operate there; the limits of British intereference in the area, and when it should be applied.The letter goes on to discuss Nawab Faiz Ali's resignation as Minister in Jeypoor [Jaipur] and suggest he be appointed to Kotale [Kotali] as well as advising that he be given sufficient powers and support to undertake the difficult work there.The letter also discusses matters of internal governance and concurs with Pelly that such matters should be handled by native rulers and ministers and not subsumed into European affairs, suggesting that Pelly may wish to have an Agent to handle matters relating to relations between the state and British Government only.The letter also gives news from the Persian Gulf, including that there has been no evidence of Abdool Aziz [Abd'al Aziz al-Said] having succeeded in taking Gwadar and that Torkee [Turki bin Said] had strengthened the garrison there as a precaution. Also relayed is the news that Torkee had taken Sohar, but that nothing had as yet been heard about what had become of Ibrahim bin Ghes [Ibrahim bin Qais] and speculation that Torkee's recent success may be due to his having received the (Zanzibar) subsidy money.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023593365.0x000002#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>