<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023516761.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T23:36:55.141Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023516761.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOL.1947.a.2083.</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023516761.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100023516761.0x000001/IOL.1947.a.2083._0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOL.1947.a.2083.</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Narrative of a journey to the site of Babylon in 1811, now first published: memoir on the ruins; with engravings from the original sketches by the author: remarks on the topography of ancient Babylon, by Major Rennell; in reference to the memoir: second memoir on the ruins; in reference to Major Rennell's remarks: with narrative of a journey to Persepolis: now first printed, with hitherto unpublished cuneiform inscriptions copied at Persepolis: by the late Claudius James Rich, Esq., formerly the Resident of the Hon. East India Company at Bagdad. Edited by his widow.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1899/1899</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-29T10:22:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (324 pages)</extent><extent>The volume contains a table of contents with chapter headings with page references (pp xi-xv). Each chapter heading is followed by a detailed breakdown of the contents of that chapter. There is a list of illustrations (p xvi) with facing page references.</extent><extent>Dimensions: 220mm x 135mm.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Narrative of a journey to the site of Babylon in 1811, now first published: memoir on the ruins; with engravings from the original sketches by the author: remarks on the topography of ancient Babylon, by Major Rennell; in reference to the memoir: second memoir on the ruins; in reference to Major Rennell's remarks: with narrative of a journey to Persepolis: now first printed, with hitherto unpublished cuneiform inscriptions copied at Persepolis: by the late Claudius James Rich, Esq., formerly the Resident of the Hon. East India Company at Bagdad, by Claudius James Rich.Publication details: Printed by William Clowes and Sons, Duke-street, Stamford Street, London. Published by Duncan and Malcolm, Paternoster Row, MDCCCXXXIX [1839].Physical description: Includes plates, illustrations, plan; octavo.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Volume</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>William Clowes and Sons, Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Duncan and Malcolm</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Claudius James Rich</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Mary Rich</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">editor</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>James Rennell</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Iran--Description and travel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Iraq--Description and travel.</topic></subject><subject><topic>Babylon (extinct city)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023516761.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>