<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001ce_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T13:49:16.430Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001ce_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3894A</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001ce</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001ce/IOR_L_PS_12_3894A_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3894A</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/158 'Koweit: Disturbances, 1938, and consequent administrative changes. Koweit Council.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-01-24T22:49:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (347 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 348; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the circumstances surrounding the recognition by the Ruler of Kuwait [Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ] of an elected Legislative Council (Majlis) in June 1938; and the subsequent administration of the state.The papers include correspondence and reports from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the Political Agent, Kuwait; Kuwait intelligence summaries; translated extracts of reports in the Arabic language press; correspondence from other British Government bodies; and India Office minutes concerning developments in Kuwait, and the attitude of the British Government.The papers cover: reports of agitation against the Shaikh of Kuwait in early 1938; reports on the events in the Iraqi press; suggestions by British officials that the idea of a Council should be revived (e.g. folio 293); the Shaikh's agreement to the proposal, and a list of the Council's powers (folios 261-262); disagreement between the Shaikh and the Council over the Shaikh's Secretary; proposals for the appointment of a British Adviser to assist the Shaikh (e.g. folios 137v and 52); discussion of the position of the large Shiah minority in Kuwait; a list of improvements introduced by the Council since its formation (folios 132-134); the dissolution of the Council by the Shaikh in December 1938; reports of meetings between the British and the Shaikh of Kuwait, including a list of the Shaikh's grievances against British officials, November 1939 (folios 56-59); and further reports on the attitude of the Shaikh, and political developments in Kuwait, 1940-44.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Legislative Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001ce#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001ce#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>