<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T17:44:51.039Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2985</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211/IOR_L_PS_12_2985_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2985</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/25 'Muscat: Kalat-Gwadar Relations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-14T22:08:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (201 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 203; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-203; these numbers are also written in pencil and circle.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, notes, and memoranda relating to relations between Kalat State and Gwadur [Gwadar], the latter being part of the Sultan of Muscat's territory.the Kalat State's request for postal and telegraphic offices to be established at Jiuni [Jīwanī] and for British India Steam Navigation Company steamers to make fortnightly calls therethe Burmah Oil Company Limited's application for an oil prospecting licence in the Gwadur areathe demarcation of the boundary between the two territories, necessitated largely by oil explorationthe Sultan's complaints about a blockade of Gwadur by the Kalat State and encroachments over the border by Kalat State officials and American geologistsarrangements for a meeting between the Sultan of Muscat and the Khan of Kalat (which never took place)the Royal Air Force's use of facilities in Gwadur and Jiwanithe question of the strategic importance of Gwadur to the British and whether to induce the Sultan to sell the enclave back to the Kalat Statethe status of Kalat following India's independence and the creation of the Dominion of Pakistan, including a memorandum by the Minister of State for Commonwealth Relations, dated 12 September 1947, that deals with the legislative and political relations between certain 'Princely States' and the Dominion of India (folios 42-51).The principal correspondents include the Government of India (External Affairs Department), Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Political Agent at Kalat and Chagai, Agent to the Governor-General in Baluchistan, Political Agent at Muscat, Admiralty, Air Ministry, British Agent at Gwadur, Commonwealth Relations Office, and the High Commissioner for the United Kingdom in Pakistan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner to Pakistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kalat and Bolan Pass</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Agent to the Governor-General, Resident and Chief Commissioner, Baluchistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Gwadur</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kalat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>