<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T07:09:25.057Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/541</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202/IOR_R_15_1_541_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/541</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/87 II (D 152) British Policy in Kuwait'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T11:04:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (213 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.Circled index numbers written in blue crayon can also be found throughout the volume and refer to the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Condition: A bound correspondence volume.Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences at the title page and terminates at the last page of text; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A second foliation sequence is present between ff 3-193; these numbers are written in pencil and blue crayon, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding British policy in Kuwait.Much of the correspondence relates to a proposal for the construction of an Iraqi-controlled port in Kuwaiti territory that would be linked to Basra by rail.The file also contains correspondence regarding the international status of Kuwait and discussions regarding an attempt by Nasir bin Ali as-Subah [Nāṣir bin ‘Alī Āl Ṣabāḥ], a member of the Al Sabah family resident in Iraq, to avoid serving as a conscript in the Iraqi army.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000202#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>