<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000023_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T18:15:48.383Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000023_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/88</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000023</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000023/IOR_R_15_5_88_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/88</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 32/6 Estates of British subjects'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1912/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-25T23:06:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (54 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in rough chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 56; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-15; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out. Folios 5, 8, and 16 have attached a's and b's.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to the estates of two British subjects who died in Kuwait: Ibrahim Khan, servant of Lieutenant F H Townshend, and Captain William Henry Irvine Shakespear, Political Agent, Kuwait. The file includes:correspondence between Lieutenant Townshend, Royal Engineer, Doctor Paul Wilberforce Harrison of the American Mission Hospital, Kuwait, and Captain Shakespear connected to the death of Ibrahim Khan, including reports of his death, arrangements for his burial and collection and disposal of his possessions, and a copy of his death certificatecorrespondence between Percy Zachariah Cox, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Lieutenant-Colonel William George Grey and the Political Agent, Kuwait, connected to the death of Captain Shakespear, including witness statements, arrangements for the collection and shipment of his possessions, and claims against his estate by former employees</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>American Mission Hospital</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>William Henry Irvine Shakespear</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000023#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000023#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>