<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00003c_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T11:49:45.883Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00003c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/667</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00003c</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00003c/IOR_R_15_2_667_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/667</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/1 N II Bahrain oil – production figures’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-26T21:05:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (28 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 28-29) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 30; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file notes (ff 28-29) have been paginated in pencil; these numbers are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises correspondence and statistical tables relating to the production of oil and associated petroleum products by the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) after the Second World War. The principal correspondents in the file are the Chief Local Representative for BAPCO (R M Brown, replacing Ward P Anderson) and the Political Agent in Bahrain (Lieutenant-Colonel Arnold Galloway; Cornelius Pelly). The file is a direct chronological continuation of ‘File 28/1 N I Bahrain oil’ (IOR/R/15/2/666).The file includes:monthly oil production reports, submitted by BAPCO to the Political Agency between March 1946 and June 1946, containing monthly output volumes (in barrels and tons) for: crude oil throughput, and output of motor spirits, kerosene, power kerosene, diesel oil, fuel oil and aviation spirits (ff 2-11);correspondence from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel William Rupert Hay), to Pelly, in May 1947, concerning a request from the Petroleum Representative of the Ministry of Fuel and Power, Middle East Office, for statistical data on BAPCO’s crude oil throughput and oil refinery output, for the period July 1946 onwards (f 14);compiled statistical data for the period July 1946 to April 1947, for production and output at the Bahrain refinery, including motor spirit, kerosene (burning oil), kerosene (vaporising), gas oil, diesel oil, fuel oil and aviation spirit, and refinery input figures for both Bahrain and Arabian crude, given in ‘tons of 2,240 lbs’ (ff 16-25).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company, Chief Local Representative</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum products</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum refineries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Fuel production</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00003c#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00003c#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>