<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d9_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T21:02:23.429Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/342</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d9</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d9/IOR_L_PS_12_342_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/342</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 1076/40 ‘Arms Traffic Persian Gulf. Licences for export of Arms etc to the Persian Gulf Ports’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-08-31T22:07:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (356 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 357; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists largely of monthly returns compiled by the Board of Trade and which relate to the licensing of British arms exports by sea to Muscat and the ports of the Persian Gulf, notably Basra (or Basrah). The returns contain the following information for every arms export listed: the export licence number issued by the Board of Trade, the name and address of the consignor and the consignee, the name of the landing port, and a brief description of the type and quantity of the goods consigned. The main correspondent is the Board of Trade, Imports and Exports Licensing Section, London, who sends copies of the returns to the Under-Secretary of State for India, India Office, Political Department, London. Copies are also sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to help local British officials combat arms smuggling in the Arab shaikhdoms of the Persian Gulf.The file includes three dividers, which give a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. Two of these are placed at the back of the correspondence. The other is placed at the front of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Export licences</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade, Commercial Relations and Treaties Department, Imports and Exports Licensing Section</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms sales</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d9#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>