<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023667520.0x000005_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T22:41:44.137Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023667520.0x000005_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/126, ff 10-11</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023667520.0x000005</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000063/IOR_R_15_1_126_0019.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/126, ff 10-11</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter (Office No 28 Cons No 5 of 1851) from Lieutenant Colonel Samuel Hennell, Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bushire to Arthur Malet, Chief Secretary to the Government, Political Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1851/1851</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-21T00:48:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is reporting that the Resident has dispatched the HC Schooner
                           Constanceto Inderabia [Hendorābī, Jazīreh-ye] in response to reports that two boats are engaged in pirate activity in the area. It explains that the Resident believes that the boats in question were sent by the Asseeloo , in order to intercept Shaikh Houssein bin Jubarah on his return to Congoon.It further notes that the Resident has been able to examine one of the crew members of the Fyzool Kurreem, and that he does not think the conduct of Abdool Ruzzak, Shaikh of Inderabia - though unfriendly - warrants further British interference.It explains that both the Nakhoda and Shaikh Houssein bin Jubarah prevented British goods from being plundered, and that most of the valuables were saved; it notes that what was removed was taken after the vessel was wrecked, either from diving, or the goods washing ashore.The letter is enclosing a copy of Lieutenant Charles Constable's report of his investigation into the incident (see ff 7-9).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival item</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023667520.0x000005#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>