<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023193457.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T20:17:58.029Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023193457.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/72/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023193457.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100023193457.0x000001/IOR_L_MIL_17_15_72_1_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/72/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Critical Study of the Campaign in Mesopotamia up to April 1917: Part I - Report'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1925/1925</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-13T12:17:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (208 folios)</extent><extent>There is a table of contents on folio 4. The volume also contains a list of illustrations (f 6) and list of maps and sketches that appear in Part II [IOR/L/MIL/17/15/72/2] (f 5). There is an index to the volume between ff 205-208.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at 1 on the front cover and terminates at 210 on the inside back cover. The numbers are written in pencil, are enclosed in a circle, and appear in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. This is the sequence used to determine the order of pages.Pagination: there is also an original printed pagination sequence numbered 2-361 (ff 8-208).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume
                           is Critical Study of the Campaign in Mesopotamia up to April 1917. Compiled by officers of the Staff College, Quetta, October-November 1923. Part I - Report(Calcutta: Government of India Press, 1925). The volume is published by the General Staff Army Headquarters, India.The volume is divided into twenty-five chapters, which cover the whole campaign in detail from December 1914 to April 1917, including the origins of the campaign; the British advance on Baghdad-Ctesiphon; operations at Kut [Al-Kūt]; the capture of Baghdad; and general reflections on the campaign.The volume includes nineteen photographic illustrations.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Al-Kūt </geographic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023193457.0x000001#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>