<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00015c_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:14:39.094Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00015c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B125</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00015c</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00015c/IOR_L_PS_18_B125_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B125</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Prevention of the slave trade in the Persian Gulf: question of increased facilities for passing under the British flag.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1899/1899</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-12T15:15:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent><extent>The printed correspondence is arranged in chronological order, with the earliest piece first.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence begins on the first folio and ends on the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top-right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: The booklet also contains an original typed pagination sequence; p.4 is mistakenly printed p.3.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Printed correspondence relating to the prevention of the slave trade in the Persian Gulf, with particular reference to the persistence of the slave trade at Muscat under the French flag, and proposals for increasing facilities for vessels to sail under the British flag.The correspondence comprises brief notes written by Sir Arthur Godley, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for India, dated 25 January 1899 (folio 1) and Sir Alexander Wilson (Chairman of the Mercantile Bank in India), dated 4 August 1899 (folio 2), and two more extensive sets of minutes, written by Sir Dennis Fitzpatrick of the Council of India, dated 25 April 1899 and 10 October 1899 respectively (folios 1 and 2). Fitzpatrick’s minutes chiefly relate to the legal aspect of increasing facilities for passing under the British flag, in reference to the 1890 Brussels Conference Act.Typographic errors in the correspondence (Mr Murton for Mr Martin) have been corrected with red ink.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Slave trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00015c#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>