<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00011e_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T14:45:27.927Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00011e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/847</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00011e</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00011e/IOR_R_15_2_847_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/847</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 35/2 (16/6) Agitation Regarding Administration of Estates and Proposed Reforms'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-09T12:14:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 25; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-24; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding disturbances that occurred in Bahrain following a government proclamation concerning inheritance law. The correspondence is primarily between Captain Charles Geoffrey Prior, Political Agent in Bahrain and Lieutenant-Colonel Hugh Vincent Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.The file contains a letter sent from Prior to Biscoe in February 1932 that contains a detailed narrative of the events that occurred following the proclamation and Prior's role in ending them (ff 4-18).Also enclosed is a copy of the relevant Government of Bahrain proclamation 'No. 34 of 1350' (f 19).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Political reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social conflicts</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00011e#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00011e#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>