<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100022583159.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T19:19:08.071Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100022583159.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 11209</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100022583159.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100022583159.0x000001/Or 11209_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 11209</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb al-tadhkirah fī al-hay’ah كتاب التذكرة في الهيئة  Ṭūsī, Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad طوسي، نصير الدين محمد بن محمد</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1289/1289</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-01T00:01:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. i+74+i</extent><extent>Material: PaperDimensions: 191 x 123 mm leaf [147 x 90 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencil; eastern Arabic foliation in black ink (the discrpepancy between the two is accounted for by f. 10, which is skipped in the Arabic foliation)Ruling: No ruling visible; 19 lines per page; vertical spacing 13 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           NaskhInk: Black ink, with rubricated headings, and overlinings and diagrams in redBinding: British Museum bindingCondition: Ff. 1-5 and 71-74 have been repairedMarginalia: Short marginal corrections and notes by many handsSeals: f. 1r</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A treatise on astronomy which summarises, rationalises and improves upon the system presented in the Almagest of Ptolemy (Claudius Ptolemaeus; c 90-c 168). The text was composed after 1256 by Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad al-Ṭūsī (نصير الدين محمد بن محمد الطوسي; d. 1274).The text is divided into four chapters (أبواب):Chapter One (الباب الأول, ff.1v-4v);Chapter Two (الباب الثاني, ff. 4v-45v);Chapter Three (الباب الثالث, ff. 45v-65r);Chapter Four (الباب الرابع, ff. 65r-74r).The manuscript contains twenty-six diagrams. The eleventh diagram (f. 32v) depicts the so-called 'Tusi couple', which demonstrates how linear motion can result from circular motion.The copy was completed in Ḥamāh, on 11 Shawwāl 688/28 October 1289 by ‘Alī ibn Aḥmad ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Mashraf (علي بن أحمد بن إبراهيم بن مشرف, see colophon, f. 74r, lines 6-8, transcribed below).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-4):الحمد لله مفيض الخير وملهم الصوابوصلوته على محمد المبحوثبفسف الخطاب وعلى آله خير آل وأصحابه خير أصحاب.نريد أن نورد جملًا من علم الهيئة تذكرة لبعض الأحباب...Ends (f. 74r, lines 1-5):مركز الأرض فكان خمسة وعشرين ألف ألف وأربعمائةوإثنا عشر ألفًا وثمان مائة وتسعة وسبعين فرسخًاولنختم الكتاب هاهنا حامدين لله تعالى ومصلين علىنبيه المصطفى والحمد لواهب العقل ومبدع والكل وعليهالتكملان (؟) انه الملك الديان وحسبنا الله ونعم الوكيلColophon (f. 74r, lines 6-9):وقع الفراغ منه في يوم الخميس الحادي عشرمن شوال سنة ثمان وثمانين وستمائة هجريةبحماه المحروسة كتبه علي بن أحمد بن إبراهيم بن مشرفمصليًا على محمد وآله ومسلّمًا تسليمًا كثيرًا</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad Ṭūsī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Claudius Ptolemaeus (Ptolemy)</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Astronomy--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100022583159.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>