<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000196_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T04:40:40.889Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000196_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1671</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000196</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000196/IOR_R_15_2_1671_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1671</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. 20/6 Ceremonials &amp; Honours. At Home Circulars'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-10T12:46:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (82 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Folios 81-83 are file notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 84; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-80; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains circulars sent by the Political Agency in Bahrain. The circulars are mainly to report whether the Political Agent will be ‘At Home’ for social visits or not. These visits usually took place on Friday afternoons of each month. Sometimes the circular indicates whether the Political Agent will be attending some sporting events such as tennis and golf or not. Each circular contains a list of people to be circulated to; those include British officials, members of the European community, and staff of The Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO). The invitees usually signed their initials beside their names on the lists. Sometimes the names of the invitees are accompanied by those of their wives. The circulars were sometimes about parties taking place at the Agency such as zakuski parties and cocktail parties, or about receiving a particular guest including Shaikh Hamad bin ‘Isa al-Khalifa, and the British Minister in Tehran and his wife.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000196#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>