<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002a1_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T20:40:38.267Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002a1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/1271</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002a1</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002a1/IOR_L_PS_10_1271_00001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/1271</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4535/1928 Pt 8, 11 ‘PERSIAN GULF: POLICY &amp; NEGOTIATIONS’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1927/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-10-05T22:00:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (289 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of each part of the volume.The subject 4535 (Persian Gulf, and Persia: telegraphs) consists of nine files (seven volumes and two physical files), IOR/L/PS/10/1266-1274. The files are divided into seventeen parts, with parts 1 and 3 comprising one volume, part 2 comprising the second volume, part 5 comprising the third file, part 7 comprising the third and fourth volumes, parts 8 and 11 comprising the fifth volume, parts 13 to 15 comprising the sixth volume, part 16 comprising the seventh file, and parts 10 and 17 comprising the eighth volume.A location list on folio 5 of IOR/L/PS/10/1271 and IOR/L/PS/10/1272 states that part 4 is Coll 30/75 (IOR/L/PS/12/3792), part 6 is Coll 29/68 (IOR/L/PS/12/3644), part 9 is Coll 30/17 (IOR/L/PS/12/3727), and part 12 is P 4480/1923 Pt 2 (IOR/L/PS/10/1099).</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 291; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume contains papers relating to the policy of HM Government in the Persian Gulf, and negotiations between the British and Persian [Iranian] Governments for a general treaty between the United Kingdom and Persia.Part 8 mostly concerns the question of whether Kuwait, Bahrain, Muscat, and the Trucial Coast Shaikhdoms should become formal British protectorates. Part 11 concerns the policy of HM Government in the Persian Gulf in relation to the treaty negotiations.Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Committee of Imperial Defence, Persian Gulf Sub-Committee</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Negotiation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002a1#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>