<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051547.0x00005d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T22:55:26.396Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051547.0x00005d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/130, ff 248-56</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051547.0x00005d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000067/IOR_R_15_1_130_0526.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/130, ff 248-56</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter no.165 of 1852 from Captain Arnold Kemball, Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Arthur Malet, Chief Secretary of the Government Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1852/1852</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-21T00:41:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>9 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter with four enclosures; a series of correspondence between Kemball and Commodore J. P. Porter, Commanding Indian Naval Squadron, Persian Gulf, relating to the resourcing of the Persian Gulf Indian Naval Squadron, both in terms of ships and crew, for the suppression of the slave trade. The enclosures are as follows:1) Letter no.138 of 1852 (ff 251-53) from Kemball to Porter, dated 12 May 1852. Kemball instructs Porter to despatch the schooner
                           Constanceto the Arab coast for the purpose of suppressing the slave trade, and encloses copies of the appropriate treaties in their 'original' languages (not included in volume) for distribution;2) Letter no.89 of 1852 (f 254) from Porter to Kemball, dated 13 May 1852, responding positively to Kemball's instructions in his last letter (ff 251-53);3) Letter no.94 of 1852 (f 255) from Porter to Kemball, dated 17 May 1852. Porter reports that the Commander-in-Chief of the Indian Navy has instructed the schooner
                           Constanceto be despatched from the Gulf to Bombay for refitting;4) Letter no.157 of 1852 (f 256) from Kemball to Porter, dated 18 May 1852, Kemball responds to Porter's last letter (f 255), agreeing to the despatch of the
                           Constanceto Bombay for refitting.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051547.0x00005d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>