<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000214_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T17:46:59.956Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000214_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2988</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000214</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000214/IOR_L_PS_12_2988_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2988</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/28 'Muscat: Arms Traffic Subsidy'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-13T22:17:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (203 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 204; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-204; these numbers are also written in pencil and circled.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, minutes, and memoranda relating to the payment of subsidies to the Sultan of Muscat, in particular that of the Arms Traffic Subsidy. The principal correspondents are officials at the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Government of India (Foreign and Political Department), India Office, Foreign Office, and the Political Agency in Muscat. The papers deal with the question of the renewal of the Arms Traffic Subsidy at various times:In February 1932, when Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] succeeded his father as Sultan (this is also when the payment of the Zanzibar Subsidy was questioned)At the beginning 1935 when a three year extension was due to lapseAt the end of 1935 when it was decided to discontinue the subsidyIn November 1937 after the Sultan had requested the subsidy to be restoredIn 1939-45 when the payment of a War Subsidy was also considered.Also contained within the file is correspondence discussing the right of the Sultan to import arms following the end of the Arms Traffic Subsidy and the question over the likelihood he might do so. Connected to this are communications from the Intelligence Bureau concerning suspicion over the activities of the Sultan's father in Japan (folios 128-30, 132-42).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Subsidies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000214#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000214#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>