<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000219_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T07:36:22.582Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000219_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/564</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000219</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000219/IOR_R_15_1_564_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/564</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 61/11 I (D 41) Relations between Nejd and Hejaz'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1923/1924</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-02T11:55:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (295 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is arranged chronologically. The internal office notes at the back of the volume (renumbered as folios 247-258) include a chronological list of the main contents, together with a simple, running index number from 1 to 111. These index numbers are also written on the front of the documents they refer to, in red or blue crayon and encircled, to help identify and locate them within the volume.</extent><extent>Main foliation sequence: numbers are written in pencil and circled, in the top right corner on the recto of each folio. The numbering, which starts on the front cover of the volume and ends on the inside back cover, is as follows: 1A-1D, 2-262.Secondary and earlier foliation sequence: the numbers 1 to 322 are written in pencil in the top right corner on the recto of each folio, except for the internal office notes at the back of the volume, which are paginated in pencil from 1 to 23. Published copies of four British Government reports at the front of the volume (renumbered as folios 2-63) also have pencilled page numbers written on them.Condition: broken spine cover.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume consists of letters, telegrams, and memoranda relating to relations between Najd and the Hejaz. The majority of the correspondence is between Reader Bullard, the British Agent in Jeddah, the Political Residency in Bushire, the Political Agency in Bahrain, the Political Agency in Kuwait, the High Commissioner in Baghdad, the Colonial and Foreign Offices, both in London, the High Commissioner in Jerusalem, the Government of India, and Ibn Sa'ud himself, or his representatives.Most of the volume covers events leading up to, and immediately after, the Ikhwan's capture of Taif, including Hussein ibn 'Ali's abdication and his son 'Ali's attempts to retain control of the Hejaz. There is a detailed report of the capture of Taif by Bullard (folios 186-201, 273-281). The documents reflect British concern with the reaction of Indian Muslims, with duplicates of correspondence regularly forwarded to numerous offices back in India. Some papers are about the effort to evacuate British Indian refugees and pilgrims from the region.Other subjects covered in the volume are:the build-up to and ultimate failure of the Kuwait Conference of 1923-24;King Fuad of Egypt's suspected financial backing of Ibn Sa'ud's takeover of the Hejaz;the defining of the Hejaz-Trans-Jordan border;the motivations and movements of St John Philby and Rosita Forbes, both of whom were thought to be trying to gain entryinto Central Arabia.Notable in the volume are a newspaper cutting from
                           The Times of Mesopotamia, dated 13 July 1923, regarding treaty negotiations between Britain and King Hussein (folio 4), and extracts of letters from Ameen Rihani to Ibn Sa'ud that had been intercepted by the British and which offer advice on foreign policy.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ikhwan, military and religious brotherhood</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Palestine and Transjordan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Hejaz Ḥusayn bin 'Alī al-Hāshimī</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Egypt Fuad I</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Harry St John Bridger Philby</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Joan Rosita Forbes</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Hejaz 'Alī bin Ḥusayn al-Hāshimī</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Ameen Fares Rihani</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Trans-Jordan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hejaz</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Taif</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Muslim pilgrims and pilgrimages</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000219#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000219#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>