<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024174347.0x00000d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T16:22:12.001Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024174347.0x00000d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/38, ff 38-45</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024174347.0x00000d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x0003b1/Mss Eur F126_38_0075.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/38, ff 38-45</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 17 of 1866 from Lewis Pelly, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Charles Gonne, Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1866/1866</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-30T01:16:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>8 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter regarding letters received by the local agent in Muskat [Muscat] and Sayed Soulem [Salim II bin Thuwaini] regarding the death of Sayed Towaynee [Thuwaini bin Said] and Sayed Soulem's intention to conduct his government under counsel from Pelly whose presence he requests in Muskat.The letter also informs the British government of previous attempts by Sayed Soulem to dethrone his father; Pelly's own observations of the contempt which heappeared to hold towards his father; and the lack of appearance of any ill health in the Sultan which has led him to assume foul play in his death, and which independent reports and sources have since corroborated, that Sayed Soulem had shot and killed his own father.Pelly goes on to report on his travels to Sohar [Suhar] where he discovers a man 'o' war with instructions to throw Sayed Torkee [Turki bin Said] overboard, his actions in writing to those intending to fulfill this order and their resolution in handing Sayed Torkee over to Pelly on the
                           Berenice. The letter goes on to give Sayed Torkee's account of events and what he was told by the Governor of the fort of Sohar about his brother's death.Pelly goes on to report on his arrival off the coast of Muskat and that the Minister, local agent and other Christian/Indian subjects came onboard his vessel to 'escape the terror in Muskat'; his continued refusal to reply to or acknowledge communications from Sayed Soulem until a response was received from the British Government; his discussions with the emissaries of Soulem; reactions to rumours and intelligence of threats to British Subjects still remaining in Muskat; reporting on the various religious and tribal leaders arriving in Muskat to advise Sayed Soulem; a plot to board the
                           Bereniceby Muscat which led to Pelly returning to Mussundoom [Musandam]; his thoughts on the developing political situation and his recommendation that the British government withdraw from Muskat affairs, including removing their agent. Pelly finishes his letter by commending the actions of Lieutenant Warner.Numerous enclosures are referenced in the letter, including translations of letters from Sayed Towaynee, Sayed Soulem and other ministers, none of which are enclosed.The Government reply No. 821 of 1866 to the letter can be found on folio 69.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024174347.0x00000d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>