<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ea_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T09:54:22.299Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ea_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/2011</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ea</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ea/IOR_R_15_2_2011_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/2011</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 22/21 Shaikh Sultan bin Salim of Ras-Al-Khaimah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-11T18:40:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (315 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 315; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top centre of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-292; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence between ff 104-314, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding political developments in Ras Al Khaimah [Ra's al-Khaymah], particularly regarding its ruler, Shaikh Sultan bin Salim Āl Qāsimī.The correspondence discusses tensions and sporadic conflict that arose between Shaikh Sultan and members of his family, primarily with his brother Muhammad bin Salim (and his sons). In 1948, this conflict resulted in Shaikh Sultan's nephew, Shaikh Saqr bin Muhammad bin Salim, seizing the town (with permission of its inhabitants) and replacing Shaikh Sultan as its ruler.The subsequent correspondence in the file discusses Shaikh Saqr's recognition as ruler by the British and their attempts to detain and punish Shaikh Sultan for his actions.The file contains a mixture of internal correspondence between British officials that is in English, but also holds a large number of letters from local rulers that are in Arabic (with English translations).On folio 83, the file contains a family tree of the Jawasim (Āl Qawāsim ), the rulers of Sharjah, Ras Al Khaimah and Kalba.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Emir of Ra's al-Khaymah Sultan bin Salim Āl Qāsimī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Ras al-Khaimah</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ea#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ea#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002ea#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>