<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T11:24:10.380Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/266</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f/IOR_R_15_2_266_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/266</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 7/2 IV R.A.F. Landing Grounds &amp; Anchorages’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-02T00:05:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (265 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest items at the front of the volume to the latest at the rear. Some items in the volume are marked with red or blue crayon numbers (for incoming or outgoing items respectively). This numbering system constitutes part of the original filing arrangement, and is referred to in the office notes at the end of the file (folios 250-63).</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. The following anomalies occur in the main foliation system: 1a-1e, 226A, 226B. Folio 150 is missing, folio 230 is bound out of order. The following folios are fold-outs: 2, 8, 18, 19, 26, 100, 109, 110, 170.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume’s correspondence and other papers relate to the construction of air facilities along the Arab coast of the Gulf, and as such is a continuation of volumes IOR/R/15/2/263-265. The principal correspondents in the volume are the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Craven Fowle, the Political Agent at Bahrain, Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Gordon Loch, and his deputy, Captain Tom Hickinbotham, Husain bin Hasan ‘Amad, in charge of the duties of the Residency Agent at Sharjah until May 1936, and his successor as Residency Agent, Sayid ‘Abd al-Razzaq.The volume’s correspondence deals with a number of proposals for facilities (including landing strips, wireless stations, accommodation, petrol stores, beacons), in particular an aerodrome at Kalba, but also extended aerodrome facilities at Sharjah, a renewal of the lease for the petrol storage facility at Ra’s al Khaymah, a seaplane anchorage for Imperial Airways in the lagoon at Umm al-Qaywayn, and a seaplane anchorage at Dubai creek. The correspondence chiefly concerns the negotiations between the Residency Agent and the various shaikhs of the region, on permission for the British to install facilities along the coast as part of the improved air route to India. Correspondence also documents arrangements for the survey of potential sites, and the construction of facilities. The proposal for a landing strip at Kalba occupies the largest proportion of the file; a result of the shaikh of Kalba’s initial resistance to the proposal, and questions over the extent of his independence from the authority of the shaikh of Sharjah, and British recognition of this independence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00000f#share">Copyright or data protection restrictions</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>