<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001ef_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T02:30:32.346Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001ef_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/600</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001ef</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001ef/IOR_L_PS_10_600_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/600</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>P 2100/1916 Pt 5 'German War: Arab Revolt'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-05T11:27:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (220 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 2100 (German War: Arab Revolt) consists of 6 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/597-602. The volumes are divided into 7 parts, with parts 1, 2, 5, 6, and 7 comprising one volume each, and parts 3 and 4 comprising the third volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 222; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The front and back covers, along with the leading flyleaf and ending flyleaf, have not been foliated.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume consists of letters, telegrams, memoranda and printed reports relating to the Arab revolt against Ottoman rule in the Hejaz region of the Arabian Peninsula during the First World War (1914-1918). The papers tell of the British response to the situation, covering the following matters:evacuation of Kunfuda by the Imam of ʻAsīr (Sayyid Muḥammad bin ‘Alī al-Idrīsī) (ff 216-222)the position of the military forces of the Sherif of Mecca (Ḥusayn bin ‘Alī al-Hāshimī ) between Medina and Rabegh and the logistic of supplying him (ff 206-215)the submission of the Sheikh of Rabegh to the Sherif of Mecca (200-205)reports by Lieutenant-Colonel Cyril Edward Wilson on the situation in Hejazthe Turkish advance towards Rabeghdiscussion of British policy towards operations in Hejaz and the decision not to send troops to Hejazarrangements concerning political controlthe Grand Sherif's request for troops and the promise of French troopsIncluded (ff 190-192) in the volume is a copy of 'Report of a visit to the Idrisi Saiyid Muhammad bin Ali bin Muhammad bin Ahmed at Jezzan', dated 17 January 1916, by the First Assistant Resident, Aden (Lieutenant-Colonel Harold Fenton Jacob).Principal correspondents include the Political Resident, Aden; the Secretary of State for India; and the High Commissioner for Egypt.Each part includes a divider, which gives the subject and part numbers, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Grand Sharif of Mecca</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Idrīsī Imām of ʻAsīr</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>First Assistant Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Hijaz</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Arabian Peninsula</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Rebellions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab Revolt (1916-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001ef#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001ef#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001ef#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>