<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001bc_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T05:38:05.839Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001bc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/471</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001bc</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001bc/IOR_R_15_1_471_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/471</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/1, 3, 5, 6 A (D 1) Koweit [Kuwait] affairs, 1896-1901'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1896/1900</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T09:08:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (387 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order and is divided into four sections as follows:Pages 1-86: 53/1 Koweit [Kuwait] Affairs 1896-1897Pages 87-216: 53/3 Koweit [Kuwait] Affairs 1897-1898Pages 217-349: 53/5 Koweit [Kuwait] Affairs 1899-1900Pages 350-373: 53/6A Koweit [Kuwait] Affairs 1899 - 1901A title page is included in the file at the beginning of each new section and an index of topics discussed in the file is contained on folios 2-5.The page numbers used in both the index and the four chronological sections relate to the original foliation system of the file that uses a mechanical stamp.</extent><extent>Condition: Formerly a bound correspondence volume, the file's sheets have been unbound and are now loose.Foliation: The volume has been foliated from the first page of text in the volume until to the inside back cover using circled pencil numbers in the top right-corner of each recto. There is an earlier, possibly original, foliation sequence that runs through the volume, which uses a mechanical stamp.The following foliation anomalies occur in the file: 27a, 27b, 130a, 130b, 170a, 170b, 174a, 179a, 179b, 293a, 293b, 310a, 310b, 323a and 323b.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between various British officials regarding political affairs in Kuwait.The file includes copies of direct correspondence between Shaikh Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ, the ruler of Kuwait and British officials regarding Mubarak's desire for British protection and the nature of Kuwait's relationship with the Ottoman Empire.The file contains a number of reports (in their original Arabic with English translations attached) concerning political affairs in Kuwait that were written by Ali bin Ghulam Reza, a news agent in Kuwait employed by the British.On folio 7 the file contains a geographical and historical summary of Kweit [Kuwait] that gives details regarding the recent takeover of power by Moubarec [Mubārak]. The file contains further information on the location, population and economy of Kuwait on folio 99.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001bc#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>