<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054291.0x000045_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T19:01:19.561Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054291.0x000045_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/22, ff 41-42</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054291.0x000045</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x000004/IOR_R_15_1_22_0086.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/22, ff 41-42</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from William Bruce, Resident, Bushire, to the Honourable Mountstuart Elphinstone, President and Governor in Council, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1820/1820</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-01T01:12:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>In this letter, William Bruce, Resident at Bushire, recounts a recent discussion with Rahma Bin Jauber [Rahma bin Jabir], whom he describes as having been one of the predatory chiefs who disturbed the tranquility of the Gulf. Bruce states that he inquired into the terms of the recent treaty between the Shaiks [Shaikhs] of Bahrain and His Highness the Imam of Muscat [Sa‘īd bin Sultān Āl Sa‘īd], as Rahma Bin Jauber was one of the parties concerned. Rahma Bin Jauber informed him that His Highness had agreed to give up 12,000 of the 30,000 German crowns that the Shaiks were to pay him annually. Bruce reports that Rahma Bin Jauber refused to subscribe to the recent treaty that was entered into with the chiefs of the Arab side of the Gulf [General Maritime Treaty, 1820], on the grounds that he was now in the service of the Persian Government. Bruce states that the Governor of Bushire has assured him that Rahma Bin Jauber cannot go to sea except as part of an expedition under orders of the Prince.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054291.0x000045#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>