<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100027071651.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T07:10:26.306Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100027071651.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1820, f 6, f 8</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100027071651.0x000002</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00022b/IOR_R_15_2_1820_0014.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1820, f 6, f 8</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Sketch of Manama and Camp Sites A and B’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-11-10T21:09:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 map</extent><extent>Materials: Paper folio.Dimensions: 342 x 420 mm.Foliation: The map is foliated in the top right corner with a circled pencil number.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The map, drawn in pencil with red pen annotations, indicates proposed campsites (labelled A, B and C) for regiments of Indian Expeditionary Force D, outside of Manama town in Bahrain. The map indicates: principal buildings and thoroughfares in Manama and its vicinity (including the Political Agency, Victoria Memorial hospital, bazaar, Quarantine station); paths; date palm gardens (in green pencil); wells and other sources of water (in blue pencil); the coastline around Manama. Pencil annotations note the availability of drinking water for men and animals, and the passable nature of the date palms for infantry. A set of notes below the map states distances between various points on the map (customs house, site A, site B), and formations to be used for infantry and animals.The map should be read in conjunction with the notes enclosed between the map’s two folios (f 7), which indicate: distances between various points on the map; recommended marching formations for infantry and animals; visibility of points for signalling stations.</abstract><typeOfResource>cartographic</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Map</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100027071651.0x000002#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>