<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000326_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T13:37:48.618Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000326_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/71</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000326</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000326/IOR_R_15_2_71_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/71</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Miscellaneous reports and correspondence relating to Kuwait</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-03-28T00:05:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (41 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at 1 on the front cover and terminates at 42 on the last folio before the back cover. These numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and appear in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence of the Political Agency, Bahrain relating to Kuwait, and reports concerning Kuwait circulated to the Agency.The papers include:report entitled 'Situation in Kuwait' by Lieutenant-Colonel Robert Edward Archibald Hamilton, Political Agent, Kuwait, [March 1918];'Report on Institution and Working of the Blockade at Kuwait', by Captain Percy Gordon Loch, Political Agent, Kuwait, September 1918;printed copy of
                                 Diaryof Lieutenant-Colonel Robert Edward Archibald Hamilton, Political Agent, Kuwait, of his journey to Najd and back, February 1918;copies of telegrams between the Political Agent Koweit [Kuwait], the Political Agent Bahrein [Bahrain], and the Political Resident, Bushire concerning the movements of caravans containing foodstuffs from Bahrein that had been turned away from the blockade of Kuwait, April - May 1918;memorandum of the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf requesting the periodical visit of a British warship to Bahrain in order to prevent possible smuggling of tea or ammunition from Bahrain and Qatar to the Persian Littoral, and to act as a reminder of the British presence in Bahrain, March 1920.The Arabic language content of this file consists of a few Arabic versions of personal and place names that occur in the official print in folios 21-33.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000326#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>