<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001da_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T11:08:22.095Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001da_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/16/9</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001da</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001da/IOR_L_MIL_17_16_9_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/16/9</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'An Account of the Arab Tribes in the Vicinity of Aden'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1909</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-10T22:05:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 volumes (194 folios)</extent><extent>There is a table of contents on folio 4 and a separate pouch that contains three maps.</extent><extent>Foliation: this file consists of two physical volumes. The foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover of volume one (ff 1-193) and terminates at the inside back cover of the second volume (ff 194-198); these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: volume one also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>'An Account of the Arab tribes in the Vicinity of Aden' that was originally compiled by Captain F M Hunter and C W H Sealy in 1886, added to intermittently by various officers of the Aden Residency and re-published and revised in September 1907 by Captain Arthur Henry Eyre Moose, Assistant Political Resident. The report is dated 1909 and was printed at the Government Central Press, Bombay.The account covers:the 'Abdalithe Subehithe 'Akrabithe Fadthlithe Haushabithe 'Aulakithe Yafaithe 'Alawithe 'Amir of Dthalathe Wahidithe Shaikh of 'Irkathe Shaikh of Lower HauraKishn and Sokotrathe Kasadithe Kaitithe Kathirihistorical resumé of Mokalla, Shehr and the HadthramutBehan al Kasabthe 'AudaliBeda.Appendix A is a detailed statement of tribes and chiefs in relations with the Aden Residency, Appendix B is a list of relevant treaties and engagements, Appendix C is a list of places visited from time to time by the Aden Troop, Appendix D is a number of genealogical tables and Appendix E is a list of notable personages in the Aden Protectorate.In a separate pouch, the file contains three maps as follows: Map of the Arabian Coast from Hiswa Mukaidthir to Makatin (folio 195), Map of the Arabian Coast from Makatin to Bandar Janjari (folio 196) and Map showing Tribes and New Boundary of the Aden Protectorate (folio 197).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Aden Protectorate</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001da#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>