<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100055234090.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-22T14:21:15.925Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100055234090.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IO Islamic 854</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100055234090.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100055234090.0x000001/IO ISLAMIC 854_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IO Islamic 854</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>al-Tuḥfah al-saʿdīyah التحفة السعدية  Quṭb al-Dīn al-Shīrāzī, Maḥmūd ibn Masʿūd قطب الدين الشيرازي، محمود بن مسعود</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1600/1799</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-26T22:00:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. ii+676+iv</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 270 x 170 mm leaf [written area varies as scribal hand changes]Foliation: India Office Library foliation pencilRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 23-24 lines per page; number of lines and vertical spacing varies as scribal hand changesScript:
                           Naskh; numerous scribal hands are discernableInk: Black ink, with rubricated headings and overlinings in redDecoration: NoneBinding: India Office binding with marbled boards, fragments of previous spine removed during conservation work are contained in box with manuscriptCondition: Insect damage some repaired, foxing, tidemarks towards head and tailMarginalia: Moderate amount by more than one hand, many lost or partially lost due to page trimming especially towards end of volumeSeals: ff. 2r and 676v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Commentary by Quṭb al-Dīn Maḥmūd ibn Mas‘ūd al-Shīrāzī (قطب الدين محمود بن مسعود الشيرازي; d. 1310, see f. 2v, line 10 ) on the
                           Colliget(كتاب الكلية), the first book of the
                           Canon of Medicine(القانون في الطب) by Ibn Sīnā (ابن سينا, d. 1037). Al-Shīrāzī composed the commentary in the context of his work as a physician and ophthalmologist at the Muẓaffarī Hospital (المارستان المظفري) in Shīrāz where he was employed for fourteen years (f. 4r, lines 6-7). He completed the commentary in 682/1283 (see f. 5r, line 23), dedicating it to Sa‘d al-Dīn (سعد الدين, see f. 5v, line 23), vizier to the Il Khānid sultan Muḥammad Khudābandah Ūljāytū (محمد خدابنده أولجايتو, reg. 1304-16), whence its title
                           The Sa‘dian Gift(التحفة السعدية).The text is defective at end, breaking off abrubtly in the second
                           fann(فن).Begins (f. 2v, lines 2-4):إن أولى ما افتتح به خطاب وإحدى ما ابتداء به كتاب حمد الله المنعم بحيوة النفوسوصحة الأجسام المنقذ من الأدواء المعضلة والأسقام الشافي بما ركب في الورى منالقوي الحافظة للصحة المبرئة من الألام الكافي بحا فهم من صناعة الطب ...Ends (f. 676v, lines 15-18, defective at end):الفصل الخامس في علامات من ليس يجيد الحال في خلقته سواء كان الاختلاف في أعضائهفي الشهيات وفي الأمزجة على ما هو المذكور في الفصل وفي بعض النسخ يوجد الفصل شرحًا بتفسير هذاما الترجمة هكذا في علامات من خرج عن الاعتدال بإفراط وهذه النسخة ليست بصحيحة لأنالمذكور في الفصل لا يناسب هذه الترجمة فإن من إفراط خروجه عن الاعتدال كان مريضًا</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Maḥmūd ibn Mas'ūd Quṭb al-Dīn al-Shīrāzī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Avicenna</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100055234090.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>