<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000bb_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T13:41:54.422Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000bb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/774</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000bb</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000bb/IOR_R_15_2_774_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/774</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 29/20 ii BAHRAIN &amp; TRUCIAL COAST STOCK POSITION AND STATEMENT OF BAHRAIN IMPORTS, EXPORTS AND RE-EXPORTS OF CERTAIN FOODSTUFFS’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-27T21:17:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (209 folios)</extent><extent>Files papers are arranged more or less chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 210; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-194; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. Condition: the back file cover is lacking.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This is a correspondence file about the importation of essential food commodities and cotton piece goods from India to Bahrain and the Trucial Coast ports of Dubai and Sharjah, under the quota system and the export licensing restrictions imposed by the Government of India during the Second World War (1939-1945), due to wartime shortages. The file contains the correspondence of the Political Agent, Bahrain with the Political Officer for the Trucial Coast and the Residency Agent, both Sharjah; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; the Director of Customs and Port Officer for the Government of Bahrain and the shipping agent Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited, Bahrain. They exchange information about existing stock levels of imported quota foodstuffs such as rice, wheat, flour, tea, coffee and sugar, as well as cotton piece goods for clothing. They also discuss arrangements for the timely shipment and distribution of new supplies, for local consumption in Bahrain and the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms, as well as re-exportation to Saudi Arabia in exchange for other essential commodities in short supply. Included in the file are numerous lists that were regularly compiled and circulated by the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain; the Political Officer for the Trucial Coast and the Residency Agent, both Sharjah and also Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited, acting as agent for the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation (Iraq) Limited. These lists show existing levels of essential food stocks in Bahrain and the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms, how long these were expected to last and details about shipments of new supplies from India, to maintain or replenish exhausted stocks.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Food resources</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food statistics</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><subject><topic>Cereals</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000bb#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000bb#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000bb#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>