<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T18:45:01.091Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1025</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248/IOR_R_15_2_1025_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1025</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/33 Six-Monthly Returns of Contemplated Leave by the Clerical Establishment'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-03-28T00:06:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (80 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 80 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. There are also two incomplete foliation sequences written in pencil (uncircled) and appearing in the same portion of most of the folios.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file includes half-yearly statements (returns) showing the leave contemplated by the Clerical Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, 1935 to 1945 inclusive; correspondence between the Political Agent and the office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf relating to the returns, leave of individuals, appointment of reliefs, and effect of war on applications for leave; correspondence from individual members of the Clerical Establishment requesting leave; and papers relating to travel arrangements.The last item of correspondence in this file is dated 3 July 1945. The overall date range is supplied by an entry in the notes at the end of the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Clerical Establishment</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>