<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054362.0x00006d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T21:29:04.193Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054362.0x00006d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/30, ff 91v-92</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054362.0x00006d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000003/IOR_R_15_1_30_0192.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/30, ff 91v-92</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No 1 of 1823 from Ephraim Gerrish Stannus, Resident in the Gulf of Persia, at Muscat roads on board the HC Cruizer
                              Aurorato William Newnham, Chief Secretary to the Government, Political Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1823/1823</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-09T02:25:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter reports that the Resident has arrived at Muscat aboard the HC Cruizer
                           Aurora, and that he has been received by Sa‘īd bin Sultān Āl Sa‘īd, the Imam of Muscat.It further notes that he has had a meeting with the Shaikh of Bushire; it reports that the Resident believes his visit to Muscat to be of an entirely private nature, and centres on securing a retreat in the event the Shaikh incurs the displeasure of the Persian Government. He does not think his visit is connected to the affairs of Bahrain, and considers the prospect of the Imam providing the Persians with assistance against the island to be remote.It also outlines the Resident's findings with respect to a Persian expedition against Bahrain, which the Resident considers extremely unlikely in the near future. In respect of rumours that Sooltan bin Suggar [Sulṭān bin Saqr] has sent a boat on a piratical cruise, it reports that these appear unfounded.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054362.0x00006d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>