<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c6_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T11:29:32.497Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/735</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c6</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c6/IOR_R_15_1_735_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/735</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Existing Treaties between the British Government and the Trucial Chiefs, 1906'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1906/1906</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-04T11:23:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 volumes (68 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence is split between three identical volumes, the covers of which are not included. The sequence is as follows: Volume 1: ff. 1-23; Volume 2: ff. 24-46; Volume 3: ff. 47-68. These numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Each volume is split into English and Arabic sections. These each contain a separate pagination sequence, which mirror each other in their respective languages. These numbers are printed, and can be found in the top centre of each page.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume is accompanied by two duplicate copies. The volume is subtitled
                           Treaties and Engagements in Force on 1st January 1906 between the British Government and the Trucial Chiefs of the Arab Coast; to which is Prefixed an Address Delivered by His Excellency Lord Curzon, Viceroy and Governor-General of India, to the Trucial Chiefs of the Arab Coast, at a Public Durbar Held at Shargah [Sharjah] on the 21st November 1903, and consists of a set of documents in English followed by versions in Arabic. The documents included are:General Treaty with the Arab Tribes of the Persian Gulf, 1820;Engagement entered into by Sheikh Sultan bin Suggur, Chief of Ras-ool-Kheimah [Ra's al-Khaymah] and Shargah [Sharjah], for the abolition of the African slave trade in his ports, 1847;Treaty of Peace in perpetuity agreed upon by the Chiefs of the Arabian Coast on behalf of themselves, their heirs and successors, under the mediation of the Resident in the Persian Gulf, 1853;Further engagement entered into by Sheikh Sultan bin Suggur, of Jowasmee, with the British Government, for the more effectual suppression of the slave trade, 1856;Additional Article for the protection of the Telegraph Line and Stations, agreed to before Lieutenant-Colonel Lewis Pelly, Acting British Political Resident, Persian Gulf, and appended to the Treaty of Peace of 4 May 1853, 1864;Mutual agreement entered into by the Trucial Chiefs of the Oman Coast through the medium of Haji Abul Cassim, Munshi, especially deputed on this service, and Haji Abdur Rahman, Government Agent, Arab Coast, written on the 3rd Rajeb 1296, corresponding with 24 June 1879;Protectorate Treaties, 1892;Agreement for the prohibition of the Arms Traffic, 1902.In the event of any doubt arising about the interpretation of the treaty stipulations, the English text was to be considered decisive.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Trucial States</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abū-Shahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hormuz Isle</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c6#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>