<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T11:14:13.708Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/61</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295/IOR_R_15_6_61_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/61</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File XXXVIII/2 Sur and the Amirs of Ja‘alan. Amirs of Ja‘alan 1923. 1923 to 1926.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1920/1926</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-07T11:10:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (94 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 96; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-95; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of letters, enclosures and reports related to the Amirs of Ja'alan [Emirs of Ja‘lan] Bani Bu Ali and their claim of independence in Sur. Considering themselves to be independent rulers over southern Oman, the Amirs of Ja‘alan requested that the Government of India consult them before any planned visit to the region by geologists of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company.The file contains correspondence regarding an application from the Amir of Ja‘alan to export arms and ammunition from India. It also contains correspondence regarding a proposed visit to Sur by the Political Agent, Muscat. In addition, the file contains a detailed report (ff 40-50) issued by the Political Agency, Muscat, about Ja‘alan, its Amirs, the Bani Bu Ali tribe and the areas and tribes belonging to them, and the affairs at Sur.The main correspondents in the file are the following: the Amirs of Ja‘alan; the Political Agency, Muscat; the Political Residency, Bushire; the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Delhi. Most of the correspondence in the file is dated 1926.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>