<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>oai:cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org:p15795coll19/28</identifier><datestamp>2017-03-27</datestamp><setSpec>p15795coll19</setSpec></header><metadata><oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd"><dc:title>19 February: A New History for the Feminist Movement</dc:title><dc:title>فبراير: تاريخ جديد للحركة النسائية 19</dc:title><dc:creator>Nasr Allah, Aida</dc:creator><dc:date>1951-03</dc:date><dc:publisher>Bint al-Nil</dc:publisher><dc:description>This article talks about the feminist conference that was held at Ewart hall on the 19th of February, 1951 and brought together a number of influential feminists. Doria Shafik stated that the conference is the first parliamentary conference for Egyptian women. After the conference, many women and men raised their voices and demonstrated in front of the Egyptian parliament, demanding justice and equality between men and women.</dc:description><dc:description>تتحدث هذه المقالة عن المؤتمر النسوي الذي عقد في قاعة يوارت حيث اجتمعت العديد من النساء المؤثرات في الحركة النسوية في مصر. و قد أعلنت درية شفيق بأن ذلك المؤتمر هو المؤتمر البرلماني الأول للمرأة المصرية، مطالبين بالعدالة الاجتماعية و الانتخابية. و قد قامت النساء و بعض الرجال بعمل مظاهرات أمام البرلمان المصري مطالبين بتحقيق العدالة و المساواة بين الرجل و المرأة.</dc:description><dc:subject>Women's rights -- Egypt; Women -- Arab countries -- Periodicals</dc:subject><dc:language>Arabic</dc:language><dc:type>Still Image; Text</dc:type><dc:format>image/jpeg</dc:format><dc:format>Article</dc:format><dc:source>Rare Books and Special Collections Library; The American University in Cairo</dc:source><dc:rights>Women and Memory Forum are copyright holders of the Bint al-Nil Journal Collection.</dc:rights><dc:identifier>http://cdm15795.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15795coll19/id/28</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc></metadata></record>