<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <identifier>4493</identifier>
  <datestamp>2019-02-27T12:32:16Z</datestamp>
  <dc:title>Interview with Ḥasan ‘Alī ʻĪsá</dc:title>
  <dc:title>مقابلة مع حسن علي عيسى</dc:title>
  <dc:interviewer>[Shmaysī, Shafīq Khālid]  [</dc:interviewer>
  <dc:interviewerAR>شميسي، شفيق خالد]</dc:interviewerAR>
  <dc:interviewee>ʻĪsá, Ḥasan ‘Alī</dc:interviewee>
  <dc:intervieweeAR>عيسى، حسن علي</dc:intervieweeAR>
  <dc:contributor />
  <dc:contributor>عيسى، حسن علي</dc:contributor>
  <dc:contributor>شميسي، شفيق خالد]</dc:contributor>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--Zionist colonization--History--To 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--الإستعمار الصهيوني--تاريخ--حتى 1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestinian-Jewish relations--Palestine--History--To 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>العلاقات الفلسطينية-اليهودية--فلسطين--تاريخ--حتى 1948</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--Arab rebellion, 1936-1939</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الثورة العربية، 1936-1939</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Economic sanctions--Palestine--History--To 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>العقوبات الإقتصادية--فلسطين--تاريخ--حتى 1948</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Battles--Palestine--History--To 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>المعارك--فلسطين--تاريخ--حتى 1948</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--British Mandate, 1922-1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الإنتداب البريطاني، 1922-1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Massacres--Palestine--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>المجازر--فلسطين--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Refugees, Palestinian--Lebanon--Social conditions</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>اللاجئون الفلسطينيون--لبنان--الأحوال الإجتماعية</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--Zionist invasion, 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الإجتياح الصهيوني، 1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Expulsion--Palestine--History--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>التهجير--فلسطين--تاريخ--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Israel-Arab War, 1948-1949</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الحرب الإسرائيلية-العربية، 1948-1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Crimes against humanity--Palestine--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الجرائم ضد الإنسانية -- فلسطين -- القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:otherSubject>Battles; British army camps; British Army, Royal Engineers; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; British officers; Children's games; Discriminatory measures; Education; Farmers; Ḥiṭṭīn Battle, 1948; Hunting; Languages; Machination; Military training; Moshavim; Nahalal (Jewish settlement: Palestine); Orchards; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Police; Public schools; Rural life; Skirmishes; Trains; Trans-Jordan Frontier Forces; Weapons; Women education; Aerial bombing; al-Aṣbaḥ, ‘Abdullāh, 1910-1938; al-Ḥusaynī, Amīn, 1895-1975; al-Qassām, ʻIzz al-Dīn, 1882-1935; Arab Revolt, 1936-1939; Arab Salvation Army; Arabic patriotic poetry; Battles; British Army; Haganah; Ḥiṭṭīn Battle, 1948; Ibrāhīm, Nūḥ, 1913-1938; Jamʻiyyat al-Kaff al-Aswad; Jewish settlements; Land sale; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Revolutionary leadership; Road blocks; Settler colonialism; Tiberias (Palestine); Agricultural calendars; Agricultural machinery; Agricultural products; Anti-Palestinian economic measures; Arab countries; British high commissioner; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; British police forces; Chickenpox; Child mortality; Clans; Eldest child; Expulsion from Palestine; Farming practices; Ḥiṭṭīn Battle, 1948; Hospitality; Illness; Income; Intervillage relations; Poetry; Resistance; Revolutionary songs; Rural life; Trade; Traditional medical procedures; Weapon acquisition; Wedding traditions; Zaffah; Zajal; al-Qāwūqjī, Fawzī, 1890-1977; al-Shajarah Battle, 1948; Arab Salvation Army; British army camps; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; British officers; British police forces; Compensation; Humiliation; Identity cards; Income; Lūbyā Battle, 1947; Machination; Martyrs; Military orders; Military superiority; Military training; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Patriotism; Police; Punishment; Revolutionaries; Trucks; Weapon acquisition; Aerial bombing; al-Qāwūqjī, Fawzī, 1890-1977; Arab Salvation Army; Balfour Declaration, 1917; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; British officers; British-Jewish relations; Currency convertibility; Damaged Weapons; Haganah; Ḥiṭṭīn Battle, 1948; Ḥusaynī, ʻAbd al-Qādir Mūsá, 1908-1948; Machination; Martyrs; Massacres; Military superiority; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Relief; Rifles; Truces; Zionist Invasion of Palestine, 1948; Zionist occupation; Agricultural machinery; Ambushes; Ammunition; Arab Salvation Army; Battles; Crops; Damaged Weapons; Expulsion from Palestine; Faith; Guards; Ḥiṭṭīn (Palestine); Homeland; Massacres; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Priests; Resistance; Settler colonialism; Truces; United Nations; Zionist Invasion of Palestine, 1948; Zionist propaganda; Aid distribution; Arab Salvation Army; Arabism; Conspiracy; Cost of living; Distress; Expulsion from Palestine; Family reunification; Frustration; Fuel; Hardship; Homeland; Martyrs; Mayors; Military withdrawal; Moral tales; Refugee aid; Refugee experience; Route choices; Rulers; Survival; Syria; United Nations; Vehicles; ʻAyn al-Ḥilwah (Palestinian refugee camp: Lebanon); Barbed wire; Border cities and towns; British police forces; Family reunification; Generations; Homeland; Hope; Identity cards; Interreligious relations; Israel-Arab border conflicts; Jerusalem (Palestine); Jewish immigrants; Jewish national home; Land appropriation; Land deeds; Landowners; Leaders; Monotheism; Morality; Naturalization refusal; Official documents; Palestinian diaspora; Palestinian resistance; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Peacekeeping operations; Personal belongings; Photographs; Religious belief; Right of return; Sephardim Jews; Treason; al-Ḥusaynī, Amīn, 1895-1975; Arabism; Border guards; Dabkah; Jafrā; Military commanders; Military service; Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1918–1970; Refugee experience; Revolutionary songs; Right of return; Security; Settler colonialism; State of Israel; Syria; Wedding songs; Zajal; ʻAtābah</dc:otherSubject>
  <dc:otherSF>al-Turk, Ghālib (School principal); al-Mun’im,  ’Abd (Policeman); al-Ḥiṭṭīnī, Abū Sa’īd (Poet); al-Ḥiṭṭīnī, Abū Shakīb (Poet); al-Rabāḥ, Aḥmad Qāsim (Mayor); al-Rinnāwī, Tawfīq (Poet); Nādir, Ḥasan (Doctor); al-Rabāḥ, ’Alī Ṣāliḥ (Resistance fighter); Sha’bān, Abū Fawzī (Resistance fighter); al-Rabāḥ, Aḥmad Qāsim  (Mayor); al- ‘Azzām, Muḥammad al-‘Abdullāh (Resistance fighter); Rabāḥ, ‘Ursān ‘Azzām (Resistance fighter); al-Khālid, Muḥammad As’ad (Shaykh); al-Khālid, Muḥammad As‘ad (Martyr); ʻĪsá, Nimir ‘Alī  (Policeman).</dc:otherSF>
  <dc:otherSFAR>الترك، غالب (ناظر مدرسة); المنعم، عبد (شرطي); الحطّيني، ابو سعيد (شاعر); الحطّيني، ابو شكيب (شاعر); الرباح، احمد قاسم (رئيس بلدية); الريناوي، توفيق (شاعر); نادر، حسن (دكتور); الرباح، علي صالح (مقاوم); شعبان، ابو فوزي (مقاوم); الرباح، احمد قاسم (رئيس بلدية); العزّام، محمد العبد الله (مقاوم); رباح، عرسان عزّام (مقاوم); الخالد، محمد اسعد (شيخ); الخالد، محمد اسعد (شهيد); عيسى، نمر (شرطي).</dc:otherSFAR>
  <dc:otherF>Sursuq, Salām; Daḥābirah.</dc:otherF>
  <dc:otherFAR>سرسق، سلام; دحابرة.</dc:otherFAR>
  <dc:otherL>Wādi al Laymūn (Valley).</dc:otherL>
  <dc:otherLAR>وادي الليمون.</dc:otherLAR>
  <dc:biography>The interview was recorded on April 18, 2003 with Ḥasan ‘Alī ʻĪsá, male, born in 1927 in Ḥ̣iṭṭīn, Palestine. He was a policeman with the British Army.</dc:biography>
  <dc:biographyAR>سجلت المقابلة مع حسن علي عيسى في 18 نيسان أبريل عام 2003، ذكر، .ولد عام 1927 في حطين، فلسطين. كان شرطيا مع قوات الجيش البريطاني</dc:biographyAR>
  <dc:toc>Childhood, education and employment in Ḥiṭṭīn
. (@ 0:00)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الطفولة والتربية والتعليم والتوظيف في حطين. (@ 0:00)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Resistance against the military occupation of Ḥiṭṭīn
. (@ 21:13)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>المقاومة ضد الاحتلال العسكري لحطين. (@ 21:13)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Customs and manners in Ḥiṭṭīn. (@ 36:29)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>العادات والأخلاق في حطين. (@ 36:29)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Political turmoil and resistance efforts. (@ 57:42)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الاضطراب السياسي وجهود المقاومة. (@ 57:42)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>City occupation and armed resistance in Ḥ̣iṭṭīn. (@ 72:8)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>إحتلال المدينة والمقاومة المسلحة في حطين. (@ 72:8)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Armed resistance against Zionist occupation and expansion. (@ 87:11)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>المقاومة المسلحة ضد الاحتلال والتوسع الصهيوني. (@ 87:11)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Warfare, displacement and distress
. (@ 102:4)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>العمليات الحربية والتهجير والكآبة. (@ 102:4)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Right of return to Palestine. (@ 116:0)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>حق العودة إلى فلسطين. (@ 116:0)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Remembering the Nakba and the homeland. (@ 135:57)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>تذكر النكبة والوطن. (@ 135:57)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:description>Made available in DSpace on 2019-02-27T12:32:16Z (GMT). No. of bitstreams: 0
  Previous issue date: 2003</dc:description>
  <dc:date>2003-04-18</dc:date>
  <dc:issuedDate>2003</dc:issuedDate>
  <dc:createdDate>Unknown Date</dc:createdDate>
  <dc:availableDate>2019-02-27T12:32:16Z</dc:availableDate>
  <dc:accessionedDate>2019-02-27T12:32:16Z</dc:accessionedDate>
  <dc:date>yyyy-mm-dd</dc:date>
  <dc:type>MovingImage</dc:type>
  <dc:identifierURI>https://n2t.net/ark:/86073/b38p62?src=poha-oai</dc:identifierURI>
  <dc:identifierURL>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/render.php?cachefile=nn_0049_hasan_isa.xml</dc:identifierURL>
  <dc:collectionName>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:collectionName>
  <dc:collectionNameAR>مجموعة النكبة</dc:collectionNameAR>
  <dc:collectionID>93</dc:collectionID>
  <dc:localID>nn_0049</dc:localID>
  <dc:identifier>nn_0049_hasan_isa.xml</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>Arabic</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>0</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights>The copyright holder of this interview is the Nakba Archive, all rights reserved.</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights />
  <dc:format>video</dc:format>
  <dc:duration>02:40:09</dc:duration>
  <dc:format>mp4</dc:format>
  <dc:village>Ḥ̣iṭṭīn</dc:village>
  <dc:villageAR>حطّين</dc:villageAR>
  <dc:interviewee_delimited>Isa, Hasan Ali|ʻĪsá, Ḥasan ‘Alī</dc:interviewee_delimited>
  <dc:village_delimited>Hittin|Ḥ̣iṭṭīn</dc:village_delimited>
  <dc:hierarchy_browse>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection{{{_ID_}}}93</dc:hierarchy_browse>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_id>93</dc:hierarchy_top_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_title>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:hierarchy_top_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>مجموعة النكبة</dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_id>93</dc:hierarchy_parent_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_title>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:hierarchy_parent_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_sequence>336</dc:hierarchy_sequence>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_id>4493</dc:is_hierarchy_id>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_title>مقابلة مع حسن علي عيسى</dc:is_hierarchy_title>
  <dc:thumbnail>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/content/thumbnails/nn_0049.jpg</dc:thumbnail>
</oai_dc:dc>