<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <identifier>4458</identifier>
  <datestamp>2019-02-27T12:32:12Z</datestamp>
  <dc:title>Interview with Muḥammad Ḥusayn Abū Ḥassān</dc:title>
  <dc:title>مقابلة مع محمد حسين أبو حسان</dc:title>
  <dc:interviewer>al-Khaṭīb, Āminah Aḥmad</dc:interviewer>
  <dc:interviewerAR>الخطيب، آمنة أحمد</dc:interviewerAR>
  <dc:interviewee>Abū Ḥassān, Muḥammad Ḥusayn</dc:interviewee>
  <dc:intervieweeAR>أبو حسان، محمد حسين</dc:intervieweeAR>
  <dc:contributor />
  <dc:contributor>أبو حسان، محمد حسين</dc:contributor>
  <dc:contributor>الخطيب، آمنة أحمد</dc:contributor>
  <dc:subject>Crimes against humanity--Palestine--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الجرائم ضد الإنسانية -- فلسطين -- القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--British Mandate, 1922-1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الإنتداب البريطاني، 1922-1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--Socio-economic conditions--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--الأحوال الإجتماعية والإقتصادية--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Education--Palestine--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>التربية--فلسطين--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Manners and customs--Palestine--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>العادات والتقاليد--فلسطين--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--Arab rebellion, 1936-1939</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الثورة العربية، 1936-1939</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Israel-Arab War, 1948-1949</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>الحرب الإسرائيلية-العربية، 1948-1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>al-Ṣafṣāf Massacre, Palestine, 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>مجزرة الصفصاف، فلسطين، 1948</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Battles--Palestine--History--To 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>المعارك--فلسطين--تاريخ--حتى 1948</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Palestine--History--Zionist invasion, 1948</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>فلسطين--تاريخ--الإجتياح الصهيوني، 1949</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:subject>Expulsion--Palestine--History--20th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subjectAR>التهجير--فلسطين--تاريخ--القرن العشرون</dc:subjectAR>
  <dc:otherSubject>Agricultural income; Agricultural products; Building practices; Children's games; Crops; Dwellings; Economic prosperity; Education; Family structure; Harvesting time; Inheritance; Landowners; Orchards; Peasants; Pre-Nakba life; Self-sufficiency; Siblings; Trade; Agricultural products; Anti-Palestinian measures; Armenians; British army camps; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; Carpenters; Coeducational schools; Dairy products; Education; Employment; Farm animals; Folktales; Income; Landowners; Means of transportation; Police; Qurʼānic teaching; Reading; Religious belief; Rural life; Schools; Self-sufficiency; Shoemakers; Social conditions; Socio-economic conditions; Storytelling; Students; Sūq; Tobacco industry; Trade; Urban planning; Agricultural products; British police forces; Cooking; Dietary practices; Economic prosperity; Family relations; Farmers; Harvesters; Intervillage relations; Land ownership; Means of transportation; Nature; Rural life; Socio-economic conditions; Trade; Work; Economic conditions; Economic measures; Family income; Famine; Gambling; Land acquisition; Land ownership; Land sale; Landowners; Lebanon; Locust infestation; Bridal customs; Building practices; Dabkah; Feasts; Housing; Intervillage relations; Love; Marital relations; Marriage; Marriage proposals; Property destruction; Social norms; Wedding celebration; Wedding customs; Wedding songs; Agricultural products; Childbirth; Circumcision; Communal celebrations; Desserts; Dhabīḥah; Dietary practices; Health conditions; Herbal remedies; Illness; Medical care; Right of return; Traditional medical procedures; ʻĪd al-Aḍḥá; ʻĪd al-Fiṭr; ʻĪd celebrations; Agricultural income; Arbitration; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; Condolences; Cooking; Currencies; Dalʻūnā; Dietary practices; Disputes; Entertainment; Folktales; Funeral rites and ceremonies; Interpersonal relations; Interreligious relations; Intervillage relations; Jafrā; Jerusalem Radio; Justice; Leaders; Loans; Maiden; Mayors; Musicians; News; Saʻsaʻ (Palestine); Social norms; al-Aṣbaḥ, ‘Abdullāh, 1910-1938; Arab Revolt, 1936-1939; Assassination; Atrocities of war; Balfour Declaration, 1917; British Army; British army camps; Burial; Disappeared persons; Governors; Home bombing; Imprisonment; Jewish immigrants; Land sale; Mass graves; Mass murder; Minorities; Neighboring villages; Palestinian Jews; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Police; Political parties; Prisoners; Shepherds; Tanks; Terrorism; Tracing; Traitors; Village siege; Water wells; Weapons; al-Qāwūqjī, Fawzī, 1890-1977; al-Shīshaklī, Adīb, 1909-1964; Arab Salvation Army; Atrocities of war; Battles; Border cities and towns; British Mandate of Palestine, 1922-1948; Burials; Death; Defense; Expulsion from Palestine; Funeral rites and ceremonies; Guards; Mass murder; Massacres; Minorities; Moroccans; News; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Revolutionaries; Rifles; Safad Battle, 1948; Social relations; Theft; Treason; Weapon acquisition; Zionist Invasion of Palestine, 1948; Arab Salvation Army; Atrocities of war; Battles; Bombardment; Border cities and towns; Decision making; Expulsion from Palestine; Fall; Homeland; House keys; International Committee of the International Committee of the Red Cross; Jewish immigration; Lebanon; News; Personal belongings; Refugee camps; Refugee experience; Return; Right of return; Route choices; Settler colonialism; Shootings; Socio-economic conditions; Suffering; United Nations; Zionist Invasion of Palestine, 1948; Agricultural land lease; al-Ṣafṣāf Massacre, 1948; British colonialism; Burj al-Barājinah (Palestinian refugee camp: Lebanon); Crimes against humanity; Dispersion; Elderly people; Generations; Capital punishment; Homeland; Hospitality; Identity cards; Lebanon; Liberation movements; Mistreatment; Naturalization refusal; Nostalgia; Passing on memories; Permits; Personal belongings; Right of return; Survival; United Nations; Civil rights; Contracts; Inheritance; Injustice; Islamic law; Jewish immigrants; Judges; Land deeds; Land registration; Landowners; Mayors; Nostalgia; Official documents; Palestinian diaspora; Personal belongings; Political rights; Refugee experience; Right of return; Settler colonialism; United Nations; British colonialism; Generations; Homeland; Hope; Identity cards; Palestinian national identity; Palestinian-Jewish relations; Refugee camp conditions; Refugee experience; Right of return</dc:otherSubject>
  <dc:otherSF>al-Ḥusaynī, ‘Abd al-Qādir (Teacher); Bashīr, ‘Ādil (Teacher); Bal‘ūs, Ḥusnī (Mayor); al-Saʻīd, Maḥmūd (Landowner); ‘Ayzak, Abū Ibrāhīm Zaydān (Mayor); al-Shawīsh, Muḥammad (Wounded); Wākid, Abdū (Vehicle driver); Azzām, Fahd (Martyr).</dc:otherSF>
  <dc:otherSFAR>الحسيني، عبد القادر (مدرّس); بشير، عادل (مدرّسة); بولس، حسني (رئيس بلدية); السعيد، محمود (مالك ارض); عيزق، ابو ابراهيم زيدان (رئيس بلدية); الشاويش، محمد (جريح); واكد، عبدو (سائق); عزّام، فهد (شهيد).</dc:otherSFAR>
  <dc:otherF>Sayyid; Wihbah; Balʻūs; Abū Ḥassān; Khalīl; Abū al-Shabāb; al-Saʻīd; Azzām; Yassīn.</dc:otherF>
  <dc:otherFAR>سيّد; وهبة; بلعوس; ابو حسّان; خليل; ابو الشباب; السعيد; ازّام; ياسين.</dc:otherFAR>
  <dc:otherLPW>Sittī Nafīsah (Maqām).</dc:otherLPW>
  <dc:otherLPWAR>مقام الست نفيسة.</dc:otherLPWAR>
  <dc:otherLPRI>Haifa Cigarettes Manufacture (Corporation).</dc:otherLPRI>
  <dc:otherLPRIAR>شركة الدخان والسجائر الوطنية في حيفا.</dc:otherLPRIAR>
  <dc:otherL>‘Uyūn al-Rakhim (Water resource).</dc:otherL>
  <dc:otherLAR>عيون الرخيم.</dc:otherLAR>
  <dc:biography>The interview was recorded on August 17, 2003 with Muḥammad Ḥusayn Abū Ḥassān, male, born in 1931 in Saʻsaʻ, Palestine and resides in Burj al-Barājinah Palestinian Refugee Camp, Lebanon.</dc:biography>
  <dc:biographyAR>سجلت المقابلة مع محمد حسين أبو حسان في 17 آب أغسطس عام 2003، ذكر، ولد عام 1931 في سعسع، فلسطين ويقيم في مخيم برج البراجنة للاجئين الفلسطينيين، لبنان.</dc:biographyAR>
  <dc:toc>Childhood, agriculture and everyday life. (@ 0:00)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الطفولة والزراعة والحياة اليومية. (@ 0:00)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Education and socio-economic life in Saʻsaʻ. (@ 12:49)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>التربية والتعليم والحياة الاجتماعية والاقتصادية في سعسع. (@ 12:49)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Agriculture and economic measures. (@ 23:39)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الإجراءات الزراعية والاقتصادية. (@ 0:00)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Families and land in Saʻsaʻ. (@ 38:27)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>العائلات والأرض في سعسع. (@ 38:27)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Wedding celebrations and marriage customs. (@ 43:16)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>إحتفالات العرس وعادات الزواج. (@ 43:16)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Community celebrations and customs. (@ 53:2)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>إحتفالات المجتمع والعادات. (@ 53:2)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Social relations, rites and ceremonies. (@ 61:47)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>العلاقات الاجتماعية والطقوس والمناسبات. (@ 61:47)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Political turmoil, revolutionaries and military activity in Sa'sa'. (@ 90:28)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الاضطراب السياسي والثوار والنشاط العسكري في سعسع. (@ 90:28)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Violence, battles and armed resistance. (@ 97:59)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>العنف والمعارك والمقاومة المسلحة. (@ 97:59)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>City occupation, displacement and exile. (@ 114:58)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>إحتلال المدينة والتهجير والطرد. (@ 114:58)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Refugee life, humiliation and isolation. (@ 130:3)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>حياة اللجوء والإذلال والعزلة. (@ 130:3)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Land, refugees and right of return. (@ 146:7)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>الأرض واللاجئون والحق بالعودة. (@ 146:7)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:toc>Return to Palestine. (@ 160:35)</dc:toc>
  <dc:tocAR>العودة لفلسطين. (@ 160:35)</dc:tocAR>
  <dc:description>Made available in DSpace on 2019-02-27T12:32:12Z (GMT). No. of bitstreams: 0
  Previous issue date: 2003</dc:description>
  <dc:date>2003-08-17</dc:date>
  <dc:issuedDate>2003</dc:issuedDate>
  <dc:createdDate>2015-07-26</dc:createdDate>
  <dc:availableDate>2019-02-27T12:32:12Z</dc:availableDate>
  <dc:accessionedDate>2019-02-27T12:32:12Z</dc:accessionedDate>
  <dc:date>yyyy-mm-dd</dc:date>
  <dc:type>MovingImage</dc:type>
  <dc:identifierURI>https://n2t.net/ark:/86073/b32603?src=poha-oai</dc:identifierURI>
  <dc:identifierURL>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/render.php?cachefile=nn_0041_muhammad_abu_hassad.xml</dc:identifierURL>
  <dc:collectionName>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:collectionName>
  <dc:collectionNameAR>مجموعة النكبة</dc:collectionNameAR>
  <dc:collectionID>93</dc:collectionID>
  <dc:localID>nn_0041</dc:localID>
  <dc:identifier>nn_0041_muhammad_abu_hassad.xml</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>Arabic</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>0</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights>The copyright holder of this interview is the Nakba Archive, all rights reserved.</dc:rights>
  <dc:rights />
  <dc:format>video</dc:format>
  <dc:duration>02:46:47</dc:duration>
  <dc:format>mp4</dc:format>
  <dc:village>Saʻsaʻ</dc:village>
  <dc:villageAR>سعسع</dc:villageAR>
  <dc:interviewee_delimited>Abu Hassan, Muhammad Husayn|Abū Ḥassān, Muḥammad Ḥusayn</dc:interviewee_delimited>
  <dc:village_delimited>Sasa|Saʻsaʻ</dc:village_delimited>
  <dc:hierarchy_browse>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection{{{_ID_}}}93</dc:hierarchy_browse>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_id>93</dc:hierarchy_top_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_title>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:hierarchy_top_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>مجموعة النكبة</dc:hierarchy_top_titleAR>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_id>93</dc:hierarchy_parent_id>
  <dc:hierarchy_parent_title>POHA, Al-Nakba Collection</dc:hierarchy_parent_title>
  <dc:hierarchy_sequence>301</dc:hierarchy_sequence>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_id>4458</dc:is_hierarchy_id>
  <dc:is_hierarchy_title>مقابلة مع محمد حسين أبو حسان</dc:is_hierarchy_title>
  <dc:thumbnail>https://libraries.aub.edu.lb/poha-viewer/content/thumbnails/nn_0041.jpg</dc:thumbnail>
</oai_dc:dc>