<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000653.0x0002dc_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T17:12:25.905Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000653.0x0002dc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Sloane MS 3034</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000653.0x0002dc</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000653.0x0002dc/Sloane MS 3034_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Western Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Sloane MS 3034</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Maqālah fī istikhrāj irtifā‘ al-quṭb ‘alá ghāyat al-taḥqīq مقالة في استخراج ارتفاع القطب على غاية التحقيق  Alhazen ابن الهيثم، الحسن بن الحسن</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1646/1646</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-30T00:08:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">lat</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. xxvii+12+ii</extent><extent>Material: PaperDimensions: 250 x 150 mm leaf [164 x 110 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencil; pagination in black ink; front papers are paginated in balck ink pp. 946-993, but not continuously or in orderRuling: Margins ruled, but not lines; 25 lines per page and vertical spacing 16 lines per 10 cm (Arabic); 32 lines per page and vertical spacing 21 lines per 10 cm (Latin)Script:
                           Naskh; the scribe is Nicolaus Petri (نقلاوس بن بطرس) of AleppoInk: Black ink, with one book title in red (f. 8r)Binding: British Museum bindingCondition: Excellent condition; some bleed-through of ink, minor foxingMarginalia: Three marginal correction by hand of scribe (ff. 4r, 6r and 11r)Seals: None</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A short treatise describing a geometrical method for precisely determining latitude by Abū ‘Alī al-Ḥasan ibn al-Ḥasan known as Ibn al-Haytham (أبو علي الحسن بن الحسن known as ابن الهيثم, d c 1039). The Arabic text is accompanied by a Latin translation produced by Jacobus Golius (1596-1667) in 1643 (f. 7v).The text were copied on 2 February 1646 in Leiden by Nicolaus Petri of Aleppo (نقلاوس بن بطرس; see title page, f. 1r). The Arabic text was presumably copied from Leiden MS Or. 14 (see Witkam, Inventory of the Oriental Manuscripts of the Library of the University of Leiden, vol. 1, 2007, pp. 19-20), and the text of Golius' Latin translation is said to have been copied from a manuscript owned by the mathematician Samuel Keihel (see title page to the Latin text, f. 7v).The title page to the Arabic text (f. 1r) reads:2 Febr. st. n. 1646Leidae hoc descripsitNicolaus PetriAleppensiscuius ms. versio addita est àclariss. viro Dno JacoboGolio, et à me descritaiuxta exemplar Dni SamuelisKeihelii mathematiciingeniosissimiThe title page to the Latin text (f. 7v) reads:TractatusHazeni Hei-temidae ArabisDe accuratè inveniendaElevationePoliex Arabico in Lati-num conversus aclariss. viroIacobo GolioProfess. mathem. in Aca-dem. Lugd. Bat.Anno 1643The texts have two diagrams each (ff. 5v, 6v, 10v, and 11v).Contents:1) Ibn al-Haytham (ابن الهيثم),
                           Maqālah fī istikhrāj irtifā‘ al-quṭb ‘alá ghāyat al-taḥqīq(مقالة في استخراج ارتفاع القطب على غاية التحقيق; ff. 2r-7r)2) Jacobus Golius,
                           Tractatus Hazeni Heitemidae arabis de accuratè invenienda elevatione poli(ff. 7v-12r).Arabic text begins (f. 2r, lines 2-6):مقالة للحسن بن الحسين (!) بن الهيثم في استخراج ارتفاع القطبعلى غاية التحقيق ليس واحد من المعاني السماوية المدركة بالإرصاديستغني في رصده عن استعمال ارتفاع القطب عن أفقموضع الرصد ولا يتم وجود الحركات السماوية إلا بالآلات وبتحقيقوضعها على الأفق ...Arabic text ends (f. 7r, lines 8-17):... فالساعات التي توخذ من البنكامتكون محققة والساعات التي تستخرج من الارتفاع ومن موضع الكوكبغير متيقن فالزمان الذي يستخرج بالحساب من ارتفاع الكوكبليس يكون محققًا ولا موثوقًا بصحّته فهذا الذي بيناه هو الطريقإلى معرفة ارتفاع القطب علىغاية التحقيق وذلك ما قصدنافي هذه المقالة تمتوالحمد لله ربالعالمينتمLatin text begins (f. 8r, lines 1-7):Heitemidae seu Al-hazeni Tractactus de accuratèinvenienda elevatione poli.Rerum astronamicarum, quae qui-dem per observationes indagari solent, vix utlae (!)quae ad hoc ipsuim non requirat Altitudinem Po-li ...Latin text ends (f. 12r, lines 21-26):Cum itaque locus stellae certus et accuratus haberi nequeat, nectempus ex altitudine stellae computandum certò ac praecisèdefiniri potest. Atque haec quidem ad cognoscendam ac-curatiorem Elevationem Poli nobis declarandafuerunt.Finis</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Alhazen</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Jacobus Golius</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">translator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Geometry--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000653.0x0002dc#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>