<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002db_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T11:44:33.777Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002db_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/83</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002db</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002db/IOR_R_15_6_83_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/83</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/6 KARACHI-ADEN AIR ROUTE. II-A/8'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:04:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (207 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. Folios 178-203 are file notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 203; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence mainly in the form of telegrams, and letters related to the air facilities/landing grounds at Salalah, Masirah and Ras al-Hadd used by the Royal Air Force (RAF). The correspondence covers the following subjects: the requisitions for workers supplied on the RAF account for stocking petrol; ships loading and unloading; the arrangement for a RAF officer to be sent to the landing ground in order to supervise the work; financial and handing over arrangements; workers’ conditions; water supply; visits to the landing grounds.Workers are referred to in the volume as 'coolies' [a pejorative term used by the British to refer to a non-British labourer].The volume also includes minutes of a conference on the Karachi-Aden Air Route, held on 12-13 June 1942. Representatives of Civil Aviation, India and Air Headquarters, Iraq discussed the handing over of the Karachi-Aden Route to Air Headquarters Middle East, Aden and Iraq.The volume also contains correspondence with the firm of Khimji Ramdas related to outstanding bill payments and bills for unloading RAF explosives and fuel at Ras al-Hadd and Masirah. It also contains correspondence related to the customs duty on equipment imported into the Muscat State in connection with the organisation of the Karachi-Aden Air Route.The main correspondents in the volume are: the Political Agent, Muscat; the Assistant Political Agent, Salalah; His Majesty’s Ambassador in Baghdad; Air Headquarters, Iraq; the Political Resident, Bushire; J H Campbell, Executive Engineer, Civil Aviation Directorate, India; and the firm of Khimji Ramdas Firm.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Khimji Ramdas Group</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Civil Aviation Directorate</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Salalah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Labourers</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air force</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Air Force</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Masirah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Ras al-Hadd</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002db#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002db#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002db#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>