<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T00:06:24.618Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1353</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058/IOR_R_15_2_1353_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1353</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/16 Legislation for preventing the import and sale in Bahrain of foreign imitations of British designs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-09-02T15:11:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the system in use appears in the top right corner of each folio, circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to foreign imitations of British textile designs. The file centres on information provided by the firm of J E Khedouri, import, export and commission agent, relating to the imitation of fabrics made in Manchester, United Kingdom. J E Khedouri (the proprietor) alleges in a letter to the Political Agent in Bahrain dated 6 April 1940 that a certain merchant in Bahrain, who acted as an importer of British goods, was forwarding samples to Japan for imitation. Khedouri says that he was afraid to order a quantity of English voiles, which were in great demand in Bahrain and Nejd [Najd], for fear that they might be Japanese imitations. Khedouri requests discussions on how to ensure the genuineness of British goods imported to Bahrain. A further letter from Khedouri also dated 6 April 1940 makes further allegations against another importer. Correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain, the Political Resident, Bushire, and the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, dated May-August 1940 discusses Khedouri's complaint and what could be done about the problem of Japanese imitations of British goods, which, according to the papers, were prevalent in Bahrain. The file also encloses a pattern book of British fabrics manufactured by the firm of J M Sasha, Manchester, United Kingdom, and examples of Japanese imitations of the same design.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Charles Dalrymple Belgrave</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000058#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>