<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000179.0x0001c5_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-11-18T14:41:25.541Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000179.0x0001c5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MAR/B/572A</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000179.0x0001c5</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000179.0x0001c5/IOR_L_MAR_B_572A_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MAR/B/572A</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Boscawen: Journal</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1748/1751</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2019-02-27T22:19:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (152 folios)</extent><extent>The entries are recorded in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 154; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Journal of the
                           Boscawen, kept by the ship's Captain, Benjamin Braund. The journal covers the ship's voyage to Bombay [Mumbai], Gombroon [Bandar Abbas], and Mocha [al-Mukha]: 5 February 1749, Blackwall, London; 5 July 1749, Joanna Island [Anjouan, Comoros]; 2 August 1749, Bombay; 26 September 1749, Surat; 17 November 1749, Gombroon; 23 December 1749, Bombay; 12 February 1750, Mangulore [Mangaluru]; 17 February 1750, Tillecherry [Thalassery]; 20 March 1750, Socatra [Soqotra]; 29 March 1750, Mocha; 27 August 1750, Bombay; 16 January 1751, Table Bay; 17 February 1751, St Helena; 10 June 1751, Blackwall.At the front of the journal is the inscription 'This is my original journal, B. Braund' (folio 4).The journal begins with daily entries of notes on the preparation and loading of the ship at Blackwall Shipyard, 28 August 1748-5 February 1749 (folios 5-12). These notes include remarks on the weather and other ships in the vicinity.The main body of the journal is a log book containing daily entries in seven columns: H [Hour], K [Knots], F [Fathoms], Courses, Winds, Weather, and a final column containing the date, some remarks, and navigational data. The remarks in the final column include further observations of weather and currents, sightings of land or other vessels, notes on the condition and maintenance of the ship, employment of the crew, and other miscellaneous information. When the ship is at anchor the entries consist of remarks only. Each entry also includes the distance travelled that day (in miles).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Boscawen</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Ships logs</topic></subject><subject><topic>Marine navigation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Weather</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000179.0x0001c5#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>