<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cc_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T06:06:08.004Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/487</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cc</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cc/IOR_R_15_1_487_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/487</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/11 V (D 79) Date Gardens in Irag [Iraq] of the Shaikhs of Mohemmarah and Kuwait'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2019-03-12T22:02:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (266 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 244; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves. The sequence contains 14 foliation anomalies, 1a, 1b, 3a, 8a, 18a, 80a, 85a, 100a, 160a, 160b, 160c, 184a, 198a and 198b.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding date gardens in southern Iraq owned by the rulers of Mohammerah and Kuwait. The correspondence discusses changes in legislation proposed by the Government of Iraq regarding the collection of land rent and land produce duties, and the impact of these proposed changes on the Ruler of Kuwait (Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ). Copies of this legislation are contained in the file on folios 30-52.Correspondence in the file explains that in November 1914, the British authorities had given a letter to the shaikhs of Mohammerah and Kuwait promising them perpetual exemption from taxation on their date gardens in Iraq in return for their assistance against the Ottoman Empire (f 177). Much of the correspondence in the file discusses whether or not this assurance previously given to the Shaikh can be upheld and how the British should react to the Iraqi Government's desire to tax the produce that is grown on Shaikh Ahmad's land and then exported to Kuwait. The broader regional implications of the issue are also discussed at length.The file also contains details regarding a legal case brought against Shaikh Ahmad by members of the Al Zuhair family regarding the ownership of some of his date gardens in Iraq.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cc#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cc#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001cc#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>