<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T11:20:29.733Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/16/28</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed/IOR_L_MIL_17_16_28_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/16/28</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Cyprus.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1878/1878</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-05T01:16:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (91 folios)</extent><extent>A content page at the front of the volume (ff 4-5), and an alphabetically arranged index at the rear (ff 87-89) both refer to the volume’s original printed pagination sequence.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 92; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Report compiled by Captain Albany Robert Savile of the 18th Royal Irish Regiment, in the Intelligence Branch, Quarter Master General’s Department, Horse Guards. The report was published and printed in London under the superintendence of HM’s Stationery Office in 1878. The report contains fourteen chapters, labelled I to XIV, as follows:I: a history of Cyprus, from ancient times to the occuption of the island by Britain in 1878II: geography and topographyIII: towns, villages, and antiquitiesIV: communications (inland, maritime, and telegraphic)V: coast, harboursVI: climateVII: natural historyVIII: agricultural productionIX: geology and mineralogyX: population and inhabitants, including their character, language, religion and educationXI: internal administration (civil, ecclesiastical, military)XII: manufacture and industryXIII: trade and revenueXIV: currency, weights and measures, list of authorities on Cyprus, cartography of CyprusThe volume includes a sketch map of Cyprus at the rear (f 91).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Quarter Master General's Department, Intelligence Branch</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Surveys</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001ed#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>