<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00026f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T15:03:04.829Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00026f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/1253</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00026f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00026f/IOR_L_PS_10_1253_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/1253</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 200/1928 Pt 5 'Persia: Anglo-Persian Relations, Treaty Negotiations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-21T22:17:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (562 folios)</extent><extent>The subject 200 (Anglo-Persian Treaty Negotiations) consists of eight volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/1250-1257. The volumes are divided into ten parts, with parts 1 and 2 comprising one volume, parts 3, 4 and 5 comprising one volume each, parts 6 and 7 comprising the fifth volume, and parts 8, 9 and 10 comprising one volume each.The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 564; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume contains correspondence regarding wide-ranging negotiations that took place between Reza Shah's Minister of Court, ‘Abdolhossein Khan Teymourtache [Teymurtash], and the British Legation in Tehran, the aim of which was the agreement of a bilateral treaty between the two governments in order to resolve a number of outstanding issues. The majority of the correspondence in the volume is internal correspondence between British officials, but it also contains a limited amount of correspondence in French that was exchanged between the British Minister in Tehran, Sir Robert Clive, and Teymourtache.In addition to this correspondence, the volume contains the following documents:'Minutes of an Inter-departmental conference held at the Foreign Office on Wednesday, July 29th, 1931', (folios 6-13)Draft text of general treaty between Persia and Britain written in French, (folios 62-83)Copy of the concession granted to Baron Julius de Reuter to establish a bank in the Persian Empire under the name of 'The Imperial Bank of Persia' in 1889, (folios 341-342).The volume includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Bilateral relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00026f#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00026f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>