<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003de_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:36:02.107Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003de_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B420</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003de</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003de/IOR_L_PS_18_B420_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B420</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Question of British Interference in the Administration of Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-20T10:34:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single despatch.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 105, and terminates at f 108, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Despatch from the Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Cyril Charles Johnson Barrett, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, 28 August 1929. Printed in October 1929.Covering:a brief history of the development of British concern in the internal affairs of Bahrain;fear of interference displayed by the Government of India;behaviour and attitude of the Shaikhs of Bahrain;the Customs Department - contention between Shaikh Isa [Shaikh ‘Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah] and the Government of India, the collection of revenues, and the post of Director of Customs;the question of whether Bahrain has been westernised too hurriedly - lists the reforms instituted and their outcomes, including municipalities, reorganisation of the Customs Department, institution of a proper police force, appointment of an Advisor to the Shaikh, reformed courts, reforms in connection with the pearl fishery, survey, public works, education, and reform of the Waqfs;the necessity to educate natives of Bahrain to take the place of British officials, and educate rulers;recommendations.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign Secretary</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003de#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>