<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000159.0x00001b_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T22:56:56.396Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000159.0x00001b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/27</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x00001b</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x00001b/IOR_R_15_1_27_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/27</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Vol 27 Letters Outward</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1822/1823</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-12-11T12:25:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume, 37 items (23 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is organised chronologically beginning with 12 December 1822 and finishing with 1 September 1823.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover with pencil numbers enclosed in circle in the front top right corner of each folio. An original pagination sequence 1-43 starts on folio 2 and consists of larger pencil numbers on top right of recto and top left of verso of each folio.Condition: There is some insect damage to the bottom right hand corner of the volume causing some of the text to be missing on the bottom right hand corner of the recto and the bottom left hand corner of the verso of the folios 1-7.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A collection of letters outward by John MacLeod, Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, between 12 December 1822 and 1 September 1823. The majority of letters are sent to British officials at Basrah, Tehran and Tabriz, including Captain Robert Taylor and Major Henry Willock, and to British naval and military officers operating in the Persian Gulf, including Captain Frederick Faithfull and his successor, Captain Hardy. These letters cover a number of topics, including MacLeod's 1823 trip to the Arab littoral of the Persian Gulf; procedures for enforcing the General Treaty of 1820 following the withdrawal from Qishm; relations between Britain, Persia, the sheikhs of the Arabian littoral of the Gulf, Raḥmah bin Jābir al-Jalāhimah and the Imam of Muscat; construction works undertaken by the Arab shaikhs; and procedures for pilotage at the port of Bushire.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter book</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander of the Vestal</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Vestal, brig</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Resident, Bussora</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Qishm</geographic></subject><subject><topic>General Maritime Treaty (1820)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x00001b#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>