<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001d7_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T13:57:22.481Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001d7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3901</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001d7</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001d7/IOR_L_PS_12_3901_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3901</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/164 'Oil: Oil Concesssions on the Trucial Coast:- Kalba.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-05T22:41:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (119 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 120; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the signing of the Kalba oil concession. The concession consisted of the commercial agreement between Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad bin Sultan [Khālid bin Aḥmad bin Sulṭān Āl Qasimī], Regent of Kalba, and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, signed on 20 December 1938 (copy folios 94-102); and the political agreement between HM Government and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, signed on 11 April 1940 (signed copy folios 12-13).The papers cover: correspondence from Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, and its parent company, Petroleum Concessions Limited; information on political developments in Kalba; the progress of negotiations over the oil concession; the opinion of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that it was Shaikh Khalid's ambition to reunite the whole of the Qawasim territories under his own rule (folio 108); drafts of the political agreement; comments on the drafts by the Petroleum Department, the Foreign Office, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; British Government approval for the signing of the oil concession; and British satisfaction that the income derived by the Regent of Kalba would be not be 'dissipated, or appropriated to his own use' (e.g. folio 18).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Abu Dhabi Company for Onshore Oil Operations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Regent of Kalba</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kalba</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Kalba</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001d7#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001d7#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001d7#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>