<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100022565463.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T19:13:12.326Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100022565463.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 23409</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100022565463.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100022565463.0x000001/Add MS 23409_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 23409</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb al-‘umdah fī ṣinā‘at al-jirāḥah كتاب العمدة في صناعة الجراحة  Ibn al-Quff, Abū al-Faraj ibn Ya‘qūb ibn Isḥāq ابن القف ,أبو الفرج بن يعقوب بن إسحاق</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1642/1643</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-03-04T00:02:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. ii+131+iv</extent><extent>Material: PaperDimensions: 282 x 180 mm leaf [205 x 113 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencil; previous foliation in western Arabic numerals cancelledRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 33 lines per page; vertical spacing 16 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Naskh; the scribe is ‘Abd al-Laṭīf ibn Muḥammad ibn Taqī al-Dīn ibn Khālid al-Rifā‘ī (عبد اللطيف بن محمد بن تقي الدين بن خالد الرفاعي; f. 2r)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated headings and overlinings in redBinding: Red leather on boards, blind tooled medalion with pendants, no envelope flapCondition: Water damage to outer margins; ff. 114-131 damage to margins of leaves repaired; ff. 130-131 hole in folio repaired with some text missingMarginalia: Marginal corrections thoughout, some longer notes, one in Karshūnī (f. 67r), marks that may be pen trials are visible on many pages</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A general introduction to the the art of surgery by Amīn al-Daulah Abū al-Faraj ibn Ya‘qūb ibn Isḥāq ibn al-Quff (أمين الدولة أبو الفرج بن يعقوب بن إسحاق بن القف; 630/1233-685/1286). The treatise it thought to be the earliest Arabic text devoted to surgery.It comprises twenty chapters (مقالات, subdivided into sections (فصول); the chapters and their titles are listed on ff. 2v-3r. This copy is defective at the end, finishing abruptly on f. 131v in the middle of Chapter Twenty, Section Six (begins at f. 130r, line 1); Sections Seven through Eleven are missing.The title page (f. 2r) contains a bio-bibliographical notice about the author by the hand of the scribe.The manuscript was copied in 1052/1642-3 by ‘Abd al-Laṭīf ibn Muḥammad ibn Taqī al-Dīn ibn Khālid al-Rifā‘ī (عبد اللطيف بن محمد بن تقي الدين بن خالد الرفاعي), who made the copy for his own use (علقه لنفسه; f. 2r).Begins (f. 2v, lines 2-6):قال الفقي إلى الله تعالى أبو الفرج بن يعقوب بن إسحاق المعروف بابن القف المتطبب المسيحي الملكيالمذهب الحمد لله الذي خلق الخلق بقدرته وسهل لهم الطريق إلى الحق بحكمته وهداهم إلى سلوكها برحمتهودعاهم إلى الإطلاع على أنوار ملكوثه وندبهم إلى الوقوف أسرار جبروته وأوصلهم إليه برحمتهوأيقظ أهل العناية لحذمته وبعد فقد شكا إلى بعض جرائحته زماننا قلة اهتمام أربابهذا الفن بأمر هذه الصناعة ...Ends (f. 131v, lines 30-33):... مرهم الافربيون ينفع [تعقد العـ]ـصب ويحلل التربلوينفع من أوذيما وأنواع السلع بمعنى أنه يعين على انضاجها و يحلل موادها أفربيون أربعةدراهم جندبا دستر خمسة دراهم حب غار ستة دراهم [شمع أ]صفر عشرة دراهم دهن بابونجأو دهن زنبق أو دهن سوسن أو زيت عتيق ثلاثون دراهمًا يعمل مرهم ويستعمل قيروطي</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Abū al-Faraj ibn Ya'qūb ibn Isḥāq Ibn al-Quff</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine, Arab</topic></subject><subject><topic>Medicine, Medieval</topic></subject><subject><topic>Surgery--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100022565463.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>