<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100083376667.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T10:47:27.385Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100083376667.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Delhi Arabic 1897, ff 130v-132v</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100083376667.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100042392200.0x000001/Delhi Arabic 1897_0273.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Delhi Arabic 1897, ff 130v-132v</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Excerpt on magic squares (عدد الوفق)  Khuzā‘ī, Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad خزاعي، محمد بن أحمد  and other short extracts and notes (فوائد)</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1627/1627</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-04-19T22:02:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Ff. 130v-132v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Excerpt from a text discussing the construction (إملاء) of magic squares (عدد الوفق) by Jamāl al-Dīn Abū ‘Abd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ‘Umar al-Khuzā‘ī (جمال الدين أبو عبد الله محمد بن أحمد بن عمر الخزاعي). The treatise from which this text is an excerpt may be al-Khuzā‘ī's
                           Introduction to Arithmetic for All New Secretaries(مقدمة في الحساب لعامة أحداث الكتاب; see Rosenfeld and Ekmeleddin,
                           Mathematicians, Astronomers, and Other Scholars of Islamic Civilization and Their Works (7th-19th c.), p. 211, no. 604, text M1 and King,
                           Mathematical Astronomy in Medieval Yemen, appendix A, no. 3.2, p. 55) or his
                           Gems of Arithmetic(جواهر الحساب; see King,
                           Mathematical Astronomy in Medieval Yemen, appendix A, no. 3.3, p. 55).The copy of the excerpt was completed on 2 Jumādá I 1036/19 January 1627.This exterpt is followed by shorter excerpts and notes (فوائد) mostly related to inheritence calculations from various sources.Begins (f. 130v, lines 17-19)ومما أملأه الفقيه محمد بن أحمد الخزاعي في عدد الوفق قال ونرسمه بصورة تأتلف منأعداد محمولة لأشكال موضوعة فكل شكل ينكسر بقدر مربع جانبه موضوعات في كل موضوع محموللها من العدد لأعلى الترتيب إلا الشكل الفرد ...Colophon of excerpt on magic squares (f. 131r, lines 16-17):... تم الإملاء بحمد لله ومنهبتأريخ 2 شهر جمادى الأولى سنة 1036 والحمد لله وحده وصلى الله على من لا نبي بعده وآله وصحبه وسلمEnds (f. 132v, lines 8-11):شخص مات وخلف خمسة عشر ذكورًا فورث خمسة النصف وخمسة الثلث وخسمة السدس والجواب والله أعلمأن يكون عشرة لأم فيرثوا الثلث فيصير لكل خمسة السدس وخمسة من هؤلاء العشرة بنواعم والخمسة الباقينبنواعم أيضًا فيرهوا الثلثين فيصير مع الخمسة بني العم الذين هم أخوة لأم الثلث مع السدس المتقدم فيصير معهم النصفويرثوا مع الخمسة بني العم الذين ليسوا بإخوة لأم الثلث وللخمسة الأخوة للأم فقط السدس والله أعلم</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript item</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100083376667.0x000001#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>