<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-22T10:19:12.470Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2872</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e/IOR_L_PS_12_2872_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2872</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 17/16(1) 'Iraq. The Assyrian Crisis'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-12T22:13:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (514 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 510; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-510; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains papers regarding the Assyrian Crisis in Iraq during 1933. It primarily consists of correspondence between HM Ambassador to Iraq (Sir Francis Humphrys), HM Chargé d’Affaires to Iraq (George Ogilvie-Forbes), and the Foreign Office.The papers document the negotiations between Mar Shimun XXIII Eshai – the Patriarch of the Church of the East – and the Government of Iraq, regarding: the spiritual and temporal authority claimed by the Mar Shimun; the Assyrian Settlement Scheme; areas designated for settlement; and clashes between Assyrians, Iraqis and Kurds.Ogilvie-Forbes and Humphrys reported on the movement of Assyrians into Syria, requests to the Syrian and French authorities that they be allowed to remain, proposals to disarm the group, and clashes with Iraqi troops when numbers of Assyrians returned to Iraq. The papers also document the proposed arrest or exile of the Mar Shimun by the Government of Iraq, and the volume also contains copies of letters exchanged by the Mar Shimun, the Iraqi Interior Ministry, and King Faisal.The papers document the worsening crisis, including reports of looting and village burning at Dohuk [Dahūk], the murder of Assyrian prisoners by Iraqi armed forces led by Bakr Sidqi, and the Simele Massacre of August 1933. These papers include reports submitted by the Head of the British Military Mission in Iraq (Major General Rowan Robinson), the Administrative Inspector at Mosul (Colonel R S Stafford), and Major D B Thomson of the Assyrian Settlement Office. The file concludes with reports on the Simele Massacre, arrangements for the arrival of Mar Shimun and his family in Cyprus, the work of the Refugee Relief Commission in Mosul and Dohuk, and the establishment by the League of Nations of a Small Minorities Commission to investigate the crisis.The volume includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the volume by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Patriarch of the Assyrian Church of the East</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Simele Massacre (1933)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>League of Nations</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Assyrians</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00019e#share">Copyright or data protection restrictions</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>