<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d0_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T21:25:06.227Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/316</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d0</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d0/IOR_L_PS_10_316_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/316</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4648/1912 'Railway projects in South Persia; surveys of Gulf ports'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1912/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-27T23:32:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (129 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. The subject 4648 (Railway projects in South Persia; surveys of Gulf ports) consists of 1 volume, IOR/L/PS/10/316. The explanation of the cover sheet/divider at the front of each volume (regarding the correspondence series numbers which have been put together to form the volumes) will be given in the Scope and Content.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 127; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, notes, and maps relating to the development of railways projects in South Persia and the associated marine surveys of Gulf ports, notably Bandar Abbas and Bushire.The volume includes the report of Lieutenant Arnold Talbot Wilson on the technical issues concerning development of railway lines between Bushire and Shiraz, and Bandar Abbas and Shiraz. Also included is a report on the commercial possibilities of these two developments, compiled by Commercial Adviser, H G Chick. These reports (folios 101-124) are preceded by an accompanying summary and analysis by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Percy Zachariah Cox.Also discussed in the correspondence is the question of concessions for railways in the neutral zone and the relative advantages (climate, water supply) of Bushire and Bandar Abbas as railway termini in the Persian Gulf. The correspondence also features discussion of a rumoured German scheme for a Bushire-Shiraz railway.Further discussion surrounds the arrangements for marine survey work in the region of Henjam and Bandar Abbas to be undertaken by the RIMS
                           Palinurus.A report by the Captain of the Palinurus, Captain B W Mainprise is included along with three marine survey maps (folios 48-50).The principal correspondents in the volume include: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Consul General for Fars (Lieutenant Colonel Percy Zachariah Cox); (Lieutenant Colonel Stuart George Knox); First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Captain L Birdwood; Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department; Under Secretary of State, India Office; Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Sir Edward Grey); Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Louis Mallet); Director, Royal Indian Marine, Walter Lumsden; Officer Comanding, RIMS
                           Palinurus (Captain B W Mainprise); Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department.The volume includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, year the subject file was opened, subject heading, and list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Puhal</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Secretary to the Marine Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Indian Marine, Director</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander of RIMS Palinurus</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bushire</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bandar Abbas</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Shiraz</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Fars</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><subject><topic>Marine navigation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d0#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d0#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>