<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000311_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:29:07.014Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000311_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/D171</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000311</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000311/IOR_L_PS_18_D171_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/D171</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Arms traffic (outside Persian Gulf)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1904</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-05-20T14:24:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>The file consists of a single document which retains its original order, as evidenced by an original pagination sequence.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the first folio and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns arms traffic outside of the Persian Gulf. Specifically, the document discusses what it refers to as the 'spasmodic' illicit traffic of arms (as opposed to 'systematic' traffic) which has been carried out by masters of dhows carrying other merchandise. Most of the file is concerned with the traffic of arms from Jibuti [Djibouti] – which is referred to as '
                           thedistributing centre [original italics]' for the arms trade outside of the Persian Gulf – to ports in the Gulf of Aden.The document provides a brief history (from a British perspective) of traffic from Jibuti in the years since the signing of the Brussels Convention in 1890. It summarises, and provides references to, letters and despatches from a number of British authorities, which discuss various issues relating to the arms trade out of Jibuti, including: the extent to which traffic at Jibuti has been regulated; the possible threat that the traffic poses to the Aden garrison; the effects of measures taken by the French to curtail the traffic from Jibuti; other possible ports of supply, such as Zanzibar, Muscat and the Aden Protectorate ports.Also discussed are the attitudes of the maritime chiefs to the arms traffic, the various preventive measures available to the Resident at Aden for dealing with the effects of the traffic at Aden, an account of measures taken both by the British Somaliland authorities and by the Italian authorities, and an evaluation of the naval measures taken by the British since 1901. The file concludes by noting that one possible solution to the problem could be the deployment of armed dhows, a measure which previously has been advocated by the naval authorities, the Viceroy and the Resident at Aden.The document is attributed to P H D [P H Dumbell, Reading Clerk to the Council, India Office].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Jibuti</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Gulf of Aden</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Aden</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>British Somaliland</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms control</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arms traffic</topic></subject><subject><topic>Dhows</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000311#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>