<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000391_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T13:53:51.058Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000391_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/60</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000391</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000391/IOR_L_PS_10_60_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/60</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 2764/1904 Pt 5 'Baghdad Railway: Anglo-Turkish negotiations; concessions proposed in respect of Kowait; negotations with Hakki Pasha in London; Anglo-Turkish agreement.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1912/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-30T09:35:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (254 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.The subject 2764 (Bagdad Railway) consists of five volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/56-60. The volumes are divided into five parts with each part comprising one volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 256; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, newspaper cuttings, maps and notes, relating to a negotiations over the proposed Berlin to Baghdad Railway in the period 1912-1914.The discussion in the volume relates to the economic, commercial, political and military considerations impinging on British strategy for the international negotiations over the development of a railway to Baghdad and an extension to Basra. In particular the correspondence focuses on:Anglo-Turkish negotiations;concessions proposed in respect of Kuwait;negotiations with Hakki Pasha in London;the Anglo-Turkish convention and declaration signed by Sir Edward Grey and Hakki Pasha, 15th December, 1913.The principal correspondents in the volume are the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Sir Edward Grey); the Secretary to the Board of Trade (Louis Mallet); the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla (Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Henry McMahon); the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Zachariah Cox).Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, year the subject file was opened, subject heading, and list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign Secretary</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000391#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x000391#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>