<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T14:50:51.332Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/214</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd/IOR_R_15_6_214_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/214</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/27 III 1). H.H. THE SULTAN. 2. SULTAN's VISIT TO INDIA AND EUROPE.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-18T23:50:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (179 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 181; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume relates to proposed and planned visits by the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] to Japan, the United States, Europe (i.e. England, France, Germany and Italy), and India.Related matters of discussion include the following: the Sultan's correspondence with foreign powers; arrangements for the Sultan's visit to England in March 1938; details of the Sultan's visit to Bombay in April 1940 for a consultation with an eye specialist; arrangements for the Sultan's trip to Karachi, where his father resides (January 1941).The volume features the following principal correspondents: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Secretary of State for India; the Sultan of Muscat and Oman; officials of the Foreign Office, the India Office and the Government of India's External Affairs Department.Included with the correspondence are the following items: a copy of a programme for the visit to Britain of the Sultan's father [Taymūr bin Fayṣal bin Turkī Āl Bū Sa‘īd] in September-October 1928 (ff 10-17); a copy of a memorandum on the history of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman, produced in preparation of the aforementioned visit (ff 48-52); an India Office account of the Sultan's official visit to England, which began on 28 March and ended on 11 April 1938 (ff 98-101); an original programme for the 1938 visit (ff 112-121).The Arabic language material consists of a single letter received by the Political Agent from the Sultan (an English translation is included). There is no material in the volume covering the year 1939.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Tours</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman Sa'īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa'īd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003dd#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>