<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000109_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T20:29:04.215Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000109_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/10, ff 153-154</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000109</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003de/IOR_R_15_1_10_0344.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/10, ff 153-154</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from William Bruce, Acting Political Resident at Bushire to Lieutenant C Salter, Commander of the
                              WaspSchooner</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1808/1808</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-01-27T00:21:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Instructions to the commander of the
                           Waspon how he is to deliver the enclosed packet to Bussora [Basra].Three enclosures:1. Translation of a letter from William Bruce to Abdulla Khan, dated 13 September 1808. The author explains that he does not know why they are experiencing a delay in receiving a reply from Captain Charles Pasley. He further explains that he cannot reply to the letter he has previously forwarded on behalf of the Persian ministers, as he is unaware of its content.2. Translation of a letter from William Bruce to Nasser Oollah Khan, dated 14 September 1808. Mr Bruce is providing a confirmation that he has forwarded a range of named correspondence on to Captain Charles Pasley.3. Translation of a letter from William Bruce to Abdulla Khan, dated 15 September 1808. The letter concerns responses from Captain Charles Pasley that the author is forwarding via express messenger to various recipients.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000109#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>