<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001d7_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T16:25:09.720Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001d7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/968</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001d7</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001d7/IOR_R_15_2_968_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/968</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/2 I Correspondence re Pensionable Clerical Establishment'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-03-28T00:05:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (331 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximately chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use runs from the third folio after the front cover and continues through to the second folio from the back cover. The sequence appears written in pencil in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. The following foliation anomaly occurs: ff. 15, 15A. The following folio numbers do not appear: 97-99, 257-259, 329-332. The following folios have to be folded out to be read: ff.86, 253, 320 (all A3 size) and f. 128 (larger than A3 size).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the service of members of the clerical establishment at the Political Agency, Bahrain (including Head Clerks, Clerks and Munshis) and mainly covers issues relating to pay, leave, and the transfer and appointment of staff. The papers are in the form of correspondence, memoranda and statements, and also include last pay certificates, references, personal correspondence, statements of office keys and other articles, statements showing valuables in different cases on deposit in the Agency, statements showing cash balances, statements of Government property, statements of other articles handed over and received, statements of Government servants serving at the Agency in both the English and Vernacular Sections (including dates of birth, dates of service and details of education), extracts from service books (career records), and clerical staff establishment lists for both the Agency and the Persian Gulf Residency as a whole. Includes a bilingual notice in English and Arabic recording a personal change of name.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Clerical Establishment</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001d7#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>