<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T20:57:01.977Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1126</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd/IOR_R_15_2_1126_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1126</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/4 VII Budget Estimates for 1945-46.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T12:01:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (60 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, and terminates with a set of notes at folios 56-61. Circled serial numbers in ink, which occur throughout the file (red for incoming, blue/black for outgoing correspondence), refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 62; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-53; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the statement of budget estimates for the Political Agency, Bahrain for the financial year 1945-46, and associated financial statements and correspondence for the same period.The correspondence is mainly between staff of the Political Agency, Bahrain, and the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf. There is also some correspondence with the Political Officer, Trucial Coast (POTC); and the Residency Agent, Sharjah.The budget estimates cover expenditure on pay of officers; pay of establishment; allowances, honoraria etc.; secret expenditure; and other charges. Also included are detailed pay statements for officers and establishment; statements of 'K-Special War Charges'; statements of fixed and contract grants; statements of anticipated excesses and savings; and statements of modifications.The correspondence consists of covering letters, and correspondence concerning particular items of expenditure. The latter particularly concerns the maintenance grant for the truck supplied to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, December 1945 - August 1946.The date range gives the covering dates for the main items of correspondence; the earliest and latest dated additions to the file are entries in the notes dated 25 June 1944 and 15 June 1947.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Motor vehicles</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food prices</topic></subject><subject><topic>Funds</topic></subject><subject><topic>Fees</topic></subject><subject><topic>Cost of living</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air force personnel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Army</topic></subject><subject><topic>Travel allowances</topic></subject><subject><topic>Coffee</topic></subject><subject><topic>Hospitality</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>