<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00037f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T12:32:01.519Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00037f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/184</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00037f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00037f/IOR_R_15_6_184_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/184</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/1 MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: GWADUR/KALAT BOUNDARY'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-18T23:50:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (105 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 107; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-106; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Following on from the previous file (IOR/R/15/6/183), this file mainly concerns issues arising in relation to the boundary between Muscat-controlled Gwadur [Gwadar] and the state of Kalat. It features the following principal correspondents: the British Agent, Gwadur; the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Agent to the Governor-General and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan; the Minister of External Affairs, Muscat and Oman; the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd]; officials of the Government of India's External Affairs Department.The file includes discussion of the following: reports that Kalat state authorities are building a road which will pass through Muscat territory; reports of coast watchers of Kalat state patrolling in the Gwadur area; details of the Gwadur district, including its extent and limits, its customs and its population size; reports of Muscat subjects being mistreated and subjected to forced labour in Kalat state; the case for laying down a 'working line' of the Gwadur-Kalat boundary for the benefit of British political officers on each side, and whether the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Khan of Kalat should both be informed of such an arrangement; whether the question of the formal demarcation of the Gwadur-Kalat boundary should be reopened; dissatisfaction among neighbouring tribal leaders near Gwadur over the Sultan of Muscat's recent decision to cease paying their annuities.Also included in the file are four maps depicting Gwadur and the surrounding region. The Arabic language material mainly consists of correspondence between British officials in the Gulf and representatives of Muscat and Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Annuities</topic></subject><subject><topic>Forced labour</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Agent to the Governor-General, Resident and Chief Commissioner, Baluchistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Gwadur</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kalat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Boundary disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00037f#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00037f#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00037f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>