<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000136_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T16:22:56.980Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000136_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/16</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000136</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000136/IOR_L_MIL_17_15_16_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/16</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Military Report on ’Arabistan (Area No. 13).’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1924/1924</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-19T22:14:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (179 folios)</extent><extent>A contents list (ff 4-5) and index (ff 171-177) reference the report’s original pagination system.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 181; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Confidential military report on Arabistan [Khūzestān] compiled by Air Headquarters, Iraq, and printed by the Government of India Press, 1924.The report contains nine chapters (numbered I-IX) and seven appendices (A-G) as follows:chapter I – history (general, ancient, modern, political attitude);II – geography (boundaries, area, general description, altitude, mountains, rivers and fords, towns and villages, tracts of land, islands, fortified places, political divisions);III – climate (general, temperature, winds, rainfall, mirages, general medical and sanitary conditions, principal diseases, conditions affecting aviation and military operations);IV – economic resources (general, labour, agriculture, livestock, manufacture, power, commerce, customs, banking, revenue, tables of imports and exports);V – ethnography (general, population, races, religions, languages);VI – tribes (general, armed forces, tribes in relation to possible centres of disturbance, political attitudes, military considerations, tribal action, punitive measures, recapitulation, lists of tribes);VII – personalities;VIII – communications (general, communications by sea, inland waterways, railways, telegraphs and telephones, post, aerodromes and possible aerodromes, wireless and visual communication, principal routes by land, sea and river);IX – administration (general, government establishments, northern province, southern province);appendix A – bibliographical notes;B – weights and measures, coinage and time;C – glossary of topographical terms;D – Karun river [Rūd-e Kārūn] regulations;E – concession granted to the “Nasiri Company”;F – customs schedule;G – Anglo-Persian Oil Company.The volume contains a single map in a pocket attached to the inside back cover (folio 180).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government Central Branch Press, Simla</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>AHQ Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Arabistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Karun River</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Gazetteers</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Surveys</topic></subject><subject><topic>Roads</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000136#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000136#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000136#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>