<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T20:44:20.238Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/9</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce/IOR_L_PS_10_9_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/9</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'P. 2. 2410/1903. Persia:- Financial Situation. Loans.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1905/1908</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-07-27T21:23:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (527 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 2410 (Persia Loans) consists of 4 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/8-11. The volumes are divided into 4 parts with each part comprising one volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 527; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises correspondence, telegrams, despatches, notes and memoranda relating to financial loans made by the Governments of Great Britain and Russia to the Government of Persia from 1901 to 1905; and potential loans to be made during 1906 and 1907.The volume discusses the failure of the Persian Government to meet repayment schedules for existing loans and the securities such as customs revenue and concessions which the loans were guaranteed against.Also discussed in the volume are a possible joint Anglo-Russian loan to the Persian Government, which was eventually dismissed owing to the illness and subsequent death of the Shah (Muẓaffari’d-Dīn Shāh Qājār) in January 1907.The principal correspondents in the volume are the British Ambassador to Persia (Sir Cecil Spring Rice), the British Ambassador to Russia (Sir Arthur Nicolson), the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Sir Edward Grey), and representatives of the India Office, Foreign Office, and Treasury.Other correspondents include the Chargé d’Affaires for the British Legation at Tehran (Evelyn Grant Duff), the Russian Imperial Minister for Foreign Affairs (Count Alexander Petrovich Izvolsky) and his Assistant Minister (Count Alexander Petrovich Izvolsky), and the Secretary of State for India (Sir John Morley). Also included is correspondence with the Manager (George Newell) and Chairman (Sir Lepel Griffin) of the Imperial Bank of Persia through whom British loans to the Persian Government had been arranged.The volume is part 2 of 4. Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, year the subject file was opened, subject heading, and list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Bank of Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Russia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Financial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Debts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Loans</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000365.0x0003ce#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>