<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b1_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T19:16:39.624Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3392</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b1</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b1/IOR_L_PS_12_3392_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3392</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/2 ‘Persia. Anti-British propaganda in: Case of Sewa Singh &amp; propaganda in East Persia.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-12T09:40:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (155 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 157; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which exists between ff 2-156 and is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Papers relating to anti-British and pro-Communist activities in East Persia [Iran]. The file consists of reports from British administrators in the region, on the activities of individuals suspected of being involved in anti-British activities, or disseminating anti-British materials:Reports concerning a number individuals reported to be agitating amongst the population in East Persia, including Sewa Singh (mentioned in the file title, who should not be confused with Sewa Singh Thikriwala) who was finally expelled from the country by the Persian authorities.Reports regarding the Soviet Consulate in Sistan, its activities and associates, and reports that the Consulate was being used as a communications channel between Russia and India, via the railway running south through Duzdap [Zahedan].Speculation and reports on the connections of individuals in East Persia with the Ghadr (or Ghadar) Party, based in San Francisco, USA.A review of the mail contract running between Nok Kundi and Mirjawa [Mīrjāveh], in response to reports of the contractor’s connections with the Ghadr Party.Arrangements for the detention, seizure of passports, and expulsion from Persia of suspected agitators.The file’s principal correspondents are: the British Consul at Sistan and Kain [Kā’īn] (Major Clive Kirkpatrick Daly); the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Soviet Consulate</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ghadar Party</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Political activists</topic></subject><subject><topic>Communists</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Seistan and Kain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Duzdap</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Propaganda</topic></subject><subject><topic>Deportation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Political activities</topic></subject><subject><topic>Anti-imperialism</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b1#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003b1#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>