<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T14:54:47.448Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/158</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d/IOR_R_15_2_158_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/158</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/A/38 II Negotiations with Bin Saud re: Eastern boundary of Saudi Arabia with Qatar &amp; Trucial Oman.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-21T18:20:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (232 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 224-229). Serial numbers in red and blue crayon, in the form 'SNo:', followed by the number, refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 234; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 6-229; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume concerns the definition of the eastern boundary of Saudi Arabia with Qatar and Trucial Oman, and negotiations over the boundary between British officials and Ibn Saud (also referred to as Bin Saud) [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd, King of Saudi Arabia].The principal correspondents are the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Political Agent, Bahrain; HM Minister, Jedda [Jeddah] (Sir Andrew Ryan), later the Chargé d'Affaires, Jeddah (Andrew Spencer Calvert); and senior officials of the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, and the Colonial Office.The papers cover: Anglo-Saudi negotiations over basing the frontier on the Blue Line [a line drawn by British and Turkish officials in 1913 from the Gulf of Uqair to parallel 20 degrees North, in the Rub al-Khali], and its extension on the side of Aden, the Violet Line; British proposals to base the frontier on a new line, the Green Line; further papers concerning the eastern, south, and south-eastern boundaries of Saudi Arabia; the effect of the proposed boundaries on the sheikhdom of Abu Dhabi; Foreign Office records of discussions between HM Minister, Jedda (Ryan) and the Deputy Saudi Arabian Minister for Foreign Affairs (Fuad Bey Hamza [Fu’ād Ḥamzah]), June-July 1935 (folios 85-102); papers concerning territorial claims of Ibn Saud in eastern and south-eastern Arabia, July 1935 (folios 103-108); investigations into tribal matters (e.g. folio 117); geological surveys and the likely presence of oil in the area (passim); the Qatar boundary (especially folios 136-173); the Qatar oil concession, September 1935 (folios 174-178); and papers concerning an air reconnaissance by British officials, with the assistance of the Royal Air Force (RAF), in order to determine certain key points on the proposed border in the area south of Qatar, October 1935 (folios 196-223).The Arabic language content of the papers consists of fewer than ten folios, mainly copies of correspondence between Ibn Saud and the Ruler of Qatar [Shaikh ‘Abdullāh bin Jāsim Āl Thānī].The date range gives the covering dates for the main items of correspondence; the earliest dated document is an enclosure to the first item of correspondence, dated 22 February 1935, and the last dated addition to the file is an entry in the notes on folio 229 dated 22 October [1935].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Jeddah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Saudi Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abu Dhabi</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Aerial reconnaissance</topic></subject><subject><topic>Geological surveys</topic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00037d#share">Copyright or data protection restrictions</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>