<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100052721716.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T07:07:20.662Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100052721716.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 5931, ff 173r-185r</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100052721716.0x000002</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100032176486.0x000001/Add MS 5931_0358.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 5931, ff 173r-185r</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Zād al-masīr fī ʿilāj al-bawāsīr زاد المسير في علاج البواسير  Qawṣūnī, Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad قوصوني، محمد بن محمد</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1676/1676</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-07T22:03:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Ff. 173r-184v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Treatise on the treatment of haemorrhoids by Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad al-Qawṣūnī (محمد بن محمد القوصوني, known as Qīṣūnīzādah [قيصوني زاده]), personal physician to the Ottoman sultans Suleiman I the Magnificent (سليمان اول, reg. 1520-66) and Selim II (سليم ثاني, reg. 1566-74). The treatise is divided into four chapters (فصول) and a conclusion (خاطمة). The title is found on folio 173r, line 13.A list of chapter titles is found in the preface (f. 173r):Chapter One: The nature of this disease, its divisions, causes and signs (الفصل الأول في ماهية هذه العلة وأقسامها وأسبابها وعلاماتها, ff. 173r-175r);Chapter Two: Rules that must be followed those suffering from this disease with respect to diet and other things (الفصل الثاني في القوانين التي يجب أن تراعيها أصحاب هذه العلة من جهة الأغذية وغيرها, ff. 175r-176v);Chapter Three: Treatment of this disease (الفصل الثالث في علاج هذه العلة, ff. 176v-181v);Chapter Four: Simple drugs useful for this disease arranged alphabetically (الفصل الرابع في الأدوية المفردة النافيعة في هذه العلة مرتبة على حرف المعجم, ff. 181v-184v);Conclusion: (الخاتمة, announced in the list on folio 173r, but not found at the end of the text).The text is followed by a short extract concerning haemorrhoids from a poem by al-Qawṣūnī (منظوم قيصون زاده, f. 185r).Begins (f. 173r, line 2-5):نحمدك اللهم يا حافظ الصحة على هذه الأبدان ويا مزيل العلل والأدوات رحمةلأفراد نوع الإنسان يقول العبد الفقير إلى الله المجيب محمد بن محمد بن محمد القصونيالقوصوني الطبيب سامحه الله تعالى هذه رسالة لطيفة محتوية على مباحثشريفة تتمعلق بالعلة المعروف ببواسير ...Ends (f. 184v, lines 3-5):... حرف الياء ياسمين دهنه يعجن به بخوراتبخورات (!) البواسير فيزداد نفعها يتوع لبنه يفتح أفواه البواسيروالله أعلم بالصواب ...Colophon (f. 184v, lines 5-8):... كملهذا الكتاب المبارك بسلامفي ثامن عشرين هتور [*] سنة 1087قبطية وهلالية والسلام(* The Coptic month Hatūr is followed by the year 1393 written in Coptic numerals, with the corresponding hijrī year written above it)</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript item</genre><name type="personal"><namePart>Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad Qawṣūnī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100052721716.0x000002#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>