<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001f8_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:21:38.511Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001f8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B197</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001f8</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001f8/IOR_L_PS_18_B197_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B197</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Bagdad Railway and Persian Gulf. The Negotiations with Hakki Pasha [Ibrahim Hakki Pasha]'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1913</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-09T00:12:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (2 folios)</extent><extent>The file is contained within a bound volume that contains a number of other files.Foliation: The foliation for this report commences at f 87, and terminates at f 88, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 7-89; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the bottom right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A report concerning a series of meetings held at the Foreign Office in April/May 1913 between Ottoman diplomat Hakki Pasha [Ibrahim Hakki Pasha] and two British officials, Sir Louis du Pan Mallet and Sir Frederic Arthur Hirtzel.The negotiations concerned the construction of the Gulf section of the Baghdad Railway and broader discussions regarding Ottoman and British interests in the region. Specifically, the report discusses Hakki's responses to various articles contained within in the British Memorandum of 18 July 1912 which the Foreign Office had presented to the Ottoman Ambassador.The file contains a small amount of French quoted within the text, it appears that this is the language in which the negotiations took place.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Baghdad Railway</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Ibrahim Hakki Pasha</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001f8#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>