<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000111_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T14:37:48.965Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000111_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/838</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000111</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000111/IOR_R_15_2_838_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/838</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 34/1 II (4/16 B) Bahrain Schools'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-18T00:04:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (237 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>Condition: The file was previously bound with treasury tags but has since been de-bound and its pages are now loose.Foliation: The file has an incomplete foliation sequence and a complete foliation sequence. In addition, some of the folios have index numbers circled in red and blue crayon. The complete foliation sequence, which should be used for referencing, is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins on the front cover of the file, on number 1, and ends on the inside of the back cover, on number 236.The file contains the following foliation errors: f.234 is followed by f.234A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding education in Bahrain and Kuwait including discussions concerning the Bahrain Technical School.Much of the correspondence concerns the role of the British Council in supporting educational activities in the two countries including a proposal to hold a photography exhibition in Bahrain.The file contains copies of official British Council reports for the second (ff. 4-13) and third (ff. 77-86) quarters of 1944 and budget estimates of its activities in Bahrain and Kuwait for the years 1944-46.The file also contains correspondence regarding the recruitment of Egyptian teachers for service in Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000111#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000111#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000111#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>