<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T23:51:49.804Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/1275</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5/IOR_L_PS_10_1275_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/1275</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4640/1928 Pt 2 ‘Muscat Situation at Sur.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-10-11T22:02:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (396 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 4640 (Muscat) consists of two volumes and one file, IOR/L/PS/10/1275-1277. The volumes and file are divided into two parts, with part 2 comprising one volume, and part 4 comprising the second volume and the file. There is no part 1 or part 3.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 392; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume contains papers concerning the situation at Sur in the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. The papers mainly relate to ‘difficulties’ which had arisen between the tribes of Sur and the Government of Muscat, inter-tribal and inter-factional rivalries, the question of what action the British Government should take to support the authority of the Muscat Government at Sur, and the general question of future British policy in Muscat.It includes papers relating to the following:The claim to independence of Ali bin Abdullah, Shaikh of the Bani Bu Ali (also spelled Beni Bu Ali) tribe and Amir of Jaalan [Emir of Ja‘alān, also spelled Jalan and Jallan]The bombardment of the fort of Said bin Abdullah (also spelled Saeed bin Abdullah) by the Muscat gunboat, and the shelling and destruction of the fort by HMS
                              CyclamenAn incident in which a Hinawi caravan was stopped at Sur by the Amirs of Jaalan, who hoisted a flag in their fort at Aiqa (also spelled Aigah in the volume) which was reportedly the flag of King Ibn Saud, but which the Amirs of Jaalan subsequently stated was their own flagThe Government of India’s recommendation that a regiment be sent to hold SurTribal conflict and rivalries, including the feud between the two main sections of the Jenebeh [al-Janabah] tribe, the Makhanah and the Aramah, which the British Government viewed as being encouraged by Ali bin Abdullah, and the feud between the Beni Bu Ali and the Beni Bu Hassan tribesProposed air operations by aircraft supported by HM Ships against the Bani Bu Ali at Sur.The papers mainly consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, and India Office Political Department minute papers.The main correspondents are as follows: the India Office; the Political Agent and HBM Consul, Muscat; Mahomed bin Nasir Ali Hamud, Amir of Jalan; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Government of India Foreign and Political Department; the Admiralty; the Foreign Office; the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies; and the Air Ministry.The volume includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Navy, Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Ja'alān</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>al-Janabah (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Banī Bū 'Alī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Sur</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Aiqa</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sultanate of Muscat and Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Naval operations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Independence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sovereignty</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002e5#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>