<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000154_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:14:21.613Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000154_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C158</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000154</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000154/IOR_L_PS_18_C158_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C158</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Memorandum by the Chief of Imperial General Staff and a Minute by Edmund George Barrow and John Evelyn Shuckburgh, on the Situation in Southern Persia</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-11-02T21:01:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 40, and terminates at f 45, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns attacks made against the South Persian Rifles [South Persia Rifles] by members of Persian tribes at Kazerun and Dashtistan [Dashtestan] (also spelled as 'Dasht-i-Arjun' and 'Dashtarjin' in the file), and the possibility of sending troops from Bushire.The file consists of a memorandum, dated 25 December 1916, by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff (CIGS) [William Robertson], and a minute, dated 27 December 1916 and written in response to the memorandum, by Edmund George Barrow, Military Secretary, India Office, and John Evelyn Shuckburgh, India Office.The memorandum proposes that control of the South Persian Rifles, commanded by Sir Percy Sykes, should be placed under the Commander-in-Chief in India, Sir Charles Carmichael Monro.The minute, which follows on from the memorandum, disagrees with some of its points. It argues that it is not quite fair to suggest that the failure to deal with the situation in Southern Persia was due solely to a lack of machinery, and suggests that a lack of resources was also a contributing factor. However, the minute does agree with the memorandum's proposal of placing the South Persian Rifles under the control of the Commander-in-Chief in India, so long as military action is taken with due regard both to political and diplomatic considerations and to the views of His Majesty's diplomatic representatives; the minute also advises that the Commander-in-Chief in India should invariably act in consultation with the Viceroy of India [Frederic John Napier Thesiger].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief of the General Staff</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>South Persia Rifles</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander-in-Chief, India</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Military Secretary</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir John Evelyn Shuckburgh</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kazerun</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Dashtistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military operations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Armed forces</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000154#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>