<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023598787.0x000053_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T20:06:31.907Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023598787.0x000053_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/4, ff 58v-60</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023598787.0x000053</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003d8/IOR_R_15_1_4_0129.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/4, ff 58v-60</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 97: Rawson Hart Boddam, Robert Sparks and Richard Church, Public Department at Bombay Castle, to Edward Galley, Resident at Bushire</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1787/1787</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-11-13T00:23:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This letter acknowledges the receipt of Edward Galley's letter of 10 December 1786, which was delivered by the
                           ScorpionSnow on 5 January 1787. The letter reports several changes to the structure of the Presidency and accepts Galley's resignation. The letter includes the following enclosures:Copies of extracts from the Honourable Company's commands (dated 7 April 1786 and received 28 October 1786 from Fort St George);Copies of additional letters from 28 April 1786, which include a copy of the commission appointing Rawson Hart Boddam both as President and Governor of Bombay and as Commander-in-Chief of the forces under his Presidency, and a copy of a document revoking an earlier commission which had appointed Brigadier General Lawrence Nilson as Commander-in-Chief of the Presidency's forces.Of these enclosures, only the extracts from the Company's commands are present, and they appear to be incomplete.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023598787.0x000053#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>