<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000062_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T12:41:00.542Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000062_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/705</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000062</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000062/IOR_R_15_2_705_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/705</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/17-A Action to be taken in the event of entry into the war by Spain’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-21T21:49:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (f 10) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 11; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-7; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises correspondence received from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Government of India, relating to the prospects of Spain entering the war against the Allies. A Government of India telegram, dated 29 June 1940, sets out the immediate actions to be taken in the event of Spain entering the war: detention of Spanish ships; suspension of export licenses for all goods to Spain and Spanish territory; detention of goods of Spanish origin (ff 4-5). Another Government of India telegram, dated 28 August 1941, states that should war appear inevitable, ships and cargoes destined for Portugal and the Portuguese Atlantic, as well as those bound for Spain an Spanish territories, should be delayed.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000062#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>