<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000026_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T18:39:12.906Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000026_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/91</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000026</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000026/IOR_R_15_5_91_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/91</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 34/3 Persian Gulf pearl fisheries'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1906/1924</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-22T22:00:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (37 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 39; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains letters, telegrams, and printed series of correspondence relating to pearl banks in the Persian Gulf. The correspondence is between the following:Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, BushirePolitical Agency, KuwaitPolitical Agency, BahrainPolitical Agency, MuscatMarine Department, Government of IndiaNaval Commander-in-Chief, East IndiesSenior Naval Officer, Persian GulfVice-Consulate, LingahPolitical Department, Government of BombayForeign Department, Government of IndiaThe Ceylon Company of Pearl Fishers Limitedthe ruling shaikhs of Kuwait, Bahrain, Ajman, Dubai, Abu Dhabi, Umm al-Quwain, Ras al-Khaimah, and Sharjahthe Arab merchant, Muhammad bin Abdul Wahab MishariActing Consular Agent for France, AdenSome of the correspondence is in the form of printed series that relate to a particular matter.The file includes:correspondence between Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Zachariah Cox, Political Resident in Bushire, Francis Beville Prideaux, Political Agent in Bahrain, and Major Stuart George Knox, Political Agent in Kuwait connected to information being gathered for the Persian Gulf Pearl Fisheries appendix to John Gordon Lorimer's
                              Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf, Oman and Central Arabiaand including maps of the pearl banks between Kuwait and Dubai (folios 11 and 18)correspondence between Lieutenant-Colonel Cox and Gulf rulers regarding the condition that they must not enter into any agreements over the pearl fisheries without first consulting the Residentcorrespondence between various offices and merchants regarding sovereignty and monopolies over pearl banks, the use of modern diving equipment, and divers' shares of profits</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Pearl fisheries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Pearl divers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000026#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000026#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000026#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>