<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000044.0x0003ca_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T16:45:27.286Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000044.0x0003ca_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 18866</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000044.0x0003ca</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000044.0x0003ca/Add 18866_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 18866</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>نهاية السؤل والامنية في تعلم أعمال الفروسية
                              Nihāyat al-su’l wa-al-umnīyah fī ta‘allum a‘māl al-furūsīyahأقصرائي، محمد بن عيسى بن إسماعيل الحنفي  Aqṣarā’ī, Muḥammad ibn ‘Īsá ibn Ismā‘īl al-Ḥanafī</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1371/1371</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-08-30T00:00:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. ii+292+ii</extent><extent>Material: PaperDimensions: 312 x 214 mm leaf [243 x 155 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencilRuling: Misṭarah; 19 lines per page; vertical spacing 8 lines per 10 cmScript: NaskhInk: Black ink, with rubricated headingsDecoration: Eighteen colour paintings and 25 diagrams in black and red inkBinding: Brown goat-skin binding with envelope flap; blind-tooled circular designs on both covers and flap; probably 8th/14th century with signs of later repairCondition: Exellent condition; small amounts of grime through thumbing; minor water damage to top margin towards back of volumeMarginalia: Infrequent marginal additions and corrections</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A Mamluk manual on horsemanship, military arts and technology by Muḥammad ibn ‘Īsá ibn Ismā‘īl al-Ḥanafī al-Aqṣarā’ī (محمد بن عيسى بن إسماعيل الحنفي الأقصرائي ; d. 1348, Damascus). The manuscript was completed on 10 Muḥarram 773 (25 July 1371) by the scribe Aḥmad ibn ‘Umar ibn Aḥmad al-Miṣrī (see colophon on f. 292r, transcribed below).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-4):الحمد لله ناصر من أطاعه واتّقاه وكاسر من حاده وعصاه ورادع من أغرض عنهوعاداه ووادع من اعتقد أن لا إله سواه أحمده حمد من أيقن بنفعه وضرره وأذعنلقضائه وقدره وبذل مهجته في نصرة دينه وأقرّ بالوحدانية انقياد التمكينه ...Ends (ff. 291v, line 17-292r, line 3):... مرهم النورة المستعمل وحده يؤخذ نورة وتشد[f. 292r] في خرقة رقيقة وتحرك في إناء فيه ماء حتى يخرج ما فيه من النورة ويبقى التفل ويتركحتى يصفوا ثم يصب الماء عنه ويلقى عليه زيت ويضرب حتى يجتمع ويستعملنافع إن شاء الله تعالى ...Colophon (f. 292r, lines 3-14):... تم كتاب السؤل والأمنيةفي تعلم أعمال الفروسية ووافقالفراغ من تحريره بحمد الله تعالى وحسن توفيقهوتيسيره في يوم الخميس يوم عاشور من شهرالله المحرّم سنة ثلاث وسبعين وسبعمائةمن الهجرة النبوية على صاحها أفضل الصلاةوالسلم على يد العبد الفقير إلى اللهأحمد بن عمر بن أحمد المصري الأدمي عفا الله عنه وعن والديه وعن مندعا له بالتوبة والرحمة والمغفرة والتجاوز عنه هو وسائر أموات المسلمينأجمعين من مشارق الأرض إلى مغاربها يا رب العالمين وحسب الله ونعمالوكيل وصلى الله على سيدنا محمد خير خلقه وآله وصحبه وسلم تسليمًا كثيرًاإلى يوم الدينDivision of the text are:Introduction (ff. 1v-27v);الكتاب الثاني في التعليم لرماية النشاب ('Book 2: Instruction in archery'; ff. 27v-);كتاب في العلل التي تلحق الرامي في بدنه ('Book on the illnesses that afflict the archer's body'; ff. 36r-42v);الكتاب الثالث في تعليم الرمح ('Book 3: Instruction in the lance'; ff. 42v-118r);التعليم الثالث في العمل بالسيف ('Teaching 3: Swordsmanship'; ff. 118r-151r);التعليم الرابع في الترس ('Teaching 4: The shield'; ff. 151r-152v);التعليم الخامس في العمل بالعمود ('Teaching 5: Using the mace'; ff. 152v-153r);التعليم السادس في صناعة الجنود والفرسان ('Teaching 6: The art of soldiers and cavalrymen'; ff.153r-161v);التعليم السابع في ذكر الأسلحة ('Teaching 7: Discussion of weapons'; ff. 161v-197v);التعليم الثامن في عقد الجيوش وجمعها وولاتها ('Teaching 8: The conscription, assembling and management of troops'; ff. 197v-211v);التعليم التاسع في تعبية الأمير الصفوف في القتال ('Teaching 9: Arrangement of battle lines by the general'; ff. 211v-235r);التعليم العاشر في المكايد الحربية من تسليط النيران ('Teaching 10: Military strategies with incendiaries'; ff. 235r-240v);التعليم الحادي عشر في قسمة الغنائم والأحكام الشرعية المتعلقة بالجهاد ('Teaching 11: The division of spoils, and legal judgements relating to holy war'; ff. 240v-281r);التعليم الثاني عشر فيما يحتاج إليه المحارب وغيره ('Teaching 12: What the soldier and others require'; ff. 281v-292r)The text includes a number of extracts from other works including a treatise on sword making by the philosopher Kindī and addressed to the Caliph al-Mu‘taṣim (باب في السيوف أنواعها وسقاياتها رسالة أبي إسحق الكندي للمعتصم أمير المؤمنين ; f. 144r ff.).Illustrations:The manuscript contains eighteen coloured paintings and 25 diagrams.Paintings:(f. 97r) صورة فارسين سنان كل واحد منهما بين كتفي صاحبه ('Illustration of two horsemen whose lance-heads are between each other's shoulder-blades');(f. 99r) صورة عدة الفرسان يلعبون ناوردًا ورماحهم على أكتافهم ('Illustration of a number of horsemen taking part in a contest, their lances on their shoulders');(f. 101r) صورة فارس يلعب برمح وسنان الرمح في يده وعقبه إلى خلف ('Illustration of a horseman taking part in a game with a lance, the lance-head being in his hand and its shaft to his rear');(f. 109r) Without caption; a horseman carrying two horizontal lances;(f. 113r) Without caption; a horseman impales a bear with his lance;(f. 121r) صورة فارس يلعب بسيف ('Illustration of a horseman performing a sword exercise');(f. 122v) صورة فارس في يده سيف وكمه ملفوف على يده وهو بارز عن سرجه وهو يضرب بالسيف ('Illustration of a horseman with a sword in his hand and his sleeve wound over his hand as he rises out of his saddle and strikes with the sword');(f. 125r) صورة فارس بيده سيف يضرب به من أذن الفرس إلى كفله الأيمن ('Illustration of a horseman with a sword in his hand with which he strikes from the horse's ear as far back as its right croup');(f. 127v) صورة فارس وذبابة السيف تحت إبطه الأيمن والقائم في يساره مع العنان ('Illustration of a horseman with the edge of the sword under his right armpit, the hilt in his left with the reins');(f. 129v) صورة فارس مقلدٍ بدرقة صغيرة وفي يده سيف يلوح به يمينًا وشمالاً ('Illustration of a horseman with a small sheild around his neck and a sword in his hand which he brandishes to left and right');(f. 130r) صورة فارس درقة على وجهه وذبابة السيف تحت إبطه الأيمن والقائم في شماله ('Illustration of a horseman with a hide shield over his face, the sword edge under his right armpit and the hilt on his left');(f. 131v) صورة فارس على رأسه خوذة حديدة ومعه سيف والنار توجج في الخوذة وفي ذباب السيف وفي [و]سط الترس ('Illustration of a horseman with an iron helmet on his head, with a sword. A fire is lit on the helmet, the sword blade and in the middle of the shield');(f.132v) صورة فارس ومعه سيف في يده اليمنى وذبابة على كتفه الأيسر وفي يده اليسرى سيف وذبابة تحت إبطه اليمنى ('Illustration of a horseman with a sword in his right hand, its blade on his left shoulder and a sword in his left hand whose blade is under his right armpit');(f. 134r) صورة فارس في يده اليسار سيف وذبابة تحت إبطه الأيمن ('Illustration of a horseman with a sword in his left hand and its tip under his left arm pit');(f. 135r) صورة فارسين متجاولين في أيديهما سيفين كل واحد منهما سيفه على متنه ('Illustration of two horsemen wheeling around, with a sword in each one's hand on the horse's back');(f. 136r) صورة فارس ومعه سيفين ودرقتين صغار درقة على وجهه الأخرى في يده مع السيف الواحد ('Illustration of a horseman with two swords and two small hide shields, on up at his face and the other in his hand with the sword');(f. 138v) صورة فارس بيده رمح يجره وراءه وفي يده الأخرى ترس ('Illustration of a horseman with a lance in his hand which he is dragging behind him, and a shield in his other hand');(f. 140r) صورة أربع فوارس مع كل واحد منهم سيف ودرقة وكل منهم درقته على كفل فرسه ('Illustration of four horsemen, each one with a sword and a hide shield, and each one carrying his shield on his horse's croup').Diagrams:(f. 78r) Table (جدول) of the 'dispatches (?) of Shaykh Najm al-Dīn (تساريح الشيخ نجم الدين)';(ff. 90v-93r) Twelve diagrams of dressage patterns;(ff. 93v-94r) Diagram of a parade; grounds;(ff. 209v-210r) Detailed and labeled diagram of the layout of a royal fortress;(ff. 214r, 214v, 216r, 217r, 217v, and 218v) Seven sketches of insignia (أشكال) used to mark various units (صفوف) within an army;(ff. 225v, 226r and 227r) Three sketches of Euclidean figures (أشكال أقليدس; f. 225, line 17) used by the ancient Greeks as military insignia.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Manuscript</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000044.0x0003ca#share">Public Domain</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>