<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002cd_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T20:49:42.342Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002cd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/330</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002cd</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002cd/IOR_L_PS_12_330_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/330</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 645/40(1) 'Persian Gulf Movements of the Political Resident'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-23T11:01:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (407 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 409; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence, mainly telegrams, from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the India Office, London, and the External Affairs Department (formerly the Foreign and Political Department) of the Government of India, New Delhi. These relate to the Resident’s movements and temporary addresses, as well as to the acting arrangements put in place during his absences from the Political Residency at Bushire on official tours and other duties, on leave of absence and on other visits abroad. There are also a large number of circular letters from the Resident to other British officials, outlining his tour programmes, which are predominantly to Bahrein [Bahrain] and the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms, Muscat, Koweit and Katr [Qatar], also Basra in Iraq, Mohammerah [Khorramshahr], Shiraz and Tehran in Persia. The file includes three dividers, which give a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. These are placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Tours</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002cd#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002cd#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>