<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00005f_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T01:47:01.579Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00005f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3534</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00005f</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00005f/IOR_L_PS_12_3534_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3534</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/120(2) ‘Persia. Ahwaz – Consular Diaries’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-08T12:06:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (110 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 111; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Monthly consular diaries submitted by HM Consul-General at Ahwaz [Ahvāz] in Persia [Iran]. The diaries cover the period January 1946 to December 1947, and describe affairs in Ahwaz under various subheadings. Subjects covered include: British officials and visitors; the evacuation of British troops from the region as part of an Anglo-Soviet agreement following the end of the Second World War; Persian officials and visitors; movements of foreigners; Soviet interests; communications, including railways and postal services; agricultural production, including food supply, food prices, and price controls; tribes, including the Bakhtiari; local politics, including the activities of local political parties, in particular the Tudeh Party of Iran; local elections; local press; internal security, and Persian military activities in the region; regional affairs, including the region’s Arab population and affairs in Luristan [Lorestān]; health, including diseases and medicine; education; meteorological observations, including rainfall statistics; the affairs of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (AIOC), including a description of events at Abadan on 14 July 1946, in which a riot at the AIOC refinery resulted in the deaths of at least twenty-four people (ff 39-42). Also included in the file is a report entitled an ‘Appreciation of local conditions from November 1945 to May 1946’ (ff 44-48).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Strikes</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Ahwaz</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Ahwaz</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00005f#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>