<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001e0_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-21T00:16:19.896Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001e0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/585</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001e0</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001e0/IOR_L_PS_10_585_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/585</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 618/1916 'Persia: Swedish gendarmerie affairs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-30T23:59:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (224 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 224; these numbers are written in pencil, are uncircled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains papers relating to the presence and operations of Swedish officers for the purposes of training the Persian Gendarmerie during the First World War. The majority of the papers is comprised of correspondence between the Foreign Office in London, the Government of India, and various British authorities and military intelligence officers operating in Persia during 1914-1918.The papers specifically discuss British unease about the presence of Swedish officers and military personnel due to the possibility of them having pro-German sympathies. The British authorities' exploration of ways to eject the Swedish officers occurs in the context of Anglo-Russian occupation of Persia and diplomatic tensions surrounding their mutual interests in the country.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Military officers</topic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military training</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001e0#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001e0#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>