<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000131_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T20:28:24.893Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000131_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/10, ff 85-87</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000131</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003de/IOR_R_15_1_10_0186.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/10, ff 85-87</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from Nicholas Hankey Smith, Resident at Bushire to Neil Benjamin Edmonstone, Secretary in the Secret, Political and Foreign Department, Fort William, Calcutta</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1808/1808</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-01-27T00:15:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 folios</extent><extent>Condition: The item has suffered from pest damage, which has partially obscured the signature of the letter and almost entirely obscured the date on f 85. In addition, there are a number of minor holes within the bodies of the various enclosures, which can make the text difficult to read in places.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is forwarding a range of correspondence. It also expresses concern that Samuel Manesty's request for Cruizers will once again deprive the Resident of the means of communicating with India. It also notes that intelligence has been forwarded to Captain John Ferrier and that twelve Russian ships carrying supplies and troops have arrived.The dates of surrounding correspondence suggests that the date of this letter lies between 8-10 March 1808.Four enclosures:1. Letter from Nicholas Hankey Smith to Jaffer Ali Khan [Ja‘afar ‘Alī Khān], dated 3 March 1808. The letter concerns gifts intended for Nasser Ulla Khan and warnings about the Shiek Abdul Hassan, who the Resident believes to be treacherous. The letter also discusses the friendly relations France is fostering with both Persia and Russia, along with the threat to British India this represents.2. Letter from Nicholas Hankey Smith to Jaffer Ali Khan, dated 7 March 1808. The letter concerns the French packet (in the possession of Nasser Ulla Khan) that Jaffer Ali Khan has been tasked with acquiring and the rewards he will be furnished with should he succeed, along with what the Resident can do to facilitate this. The Resident also discusses his need for authentic intelligence from Tehran and shares the true purpose behind the British squadron off Muscat.3. Letter from Nicholas Hankey Smith to Jaffer Ali Khan, dated 9 March 1808. The Resident discusses papers he has received from and is returning to Jaffer Ali Khan, as well as a reward for Mohumed Hashem who originally supplied the papers.4. Translation of a note from Mohumed Hashum to Jaffer Ali Khan, enclosed to Nicholas Hankey Smith. Mohumed Hashum is sending his gratitude for the gifts recently awarded to him by the Resident at Bushire; an itemised list of these gifts is included.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100075534085.0x000131#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>