<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00004d_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-18T10:51:34.792Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00004d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/144</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00004d</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00004d/IOR_L_PS_20_144_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/144</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Reconnaissances in Mesopotamia, Kurdistan, North-West Persia, and Luristan from April to October 1888. By Lt F R Maunsell, Intelligence Branch. In Two Volumes. Volume I: narrative report, description of larger towns and routes leading from them. Simla: Intelligence Branch, Quarter Master General's Dept, 1890'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1890/1890</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-10-27T10:13:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (152 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 154; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Narrative report on surveys conducted in Mesopotamia [Iraq], North-West Persia [Iran] and Luristan [Lorestān]. The preface provides the following information:'The object was to explore various tracts of little known country through which roads lead north from the head of the Persian Gulf to the Waliat of Van and North-West Persia near Urmia. To accomplish this, two routes through Luristan from the Tigris valley were travelled. In southern Kurdistan the roads from Kifri to Sulaimaniah, from there to Rawanduz, and Rawanduz to Amadiyeh, were gone over in Turkey, and Suj-Bulak to Karmanshah through Sakiz and Sihna in Persia. The country south of lake Van to Mosul was traversed in the routes Amadiyeh to Mosul, Mosul to Jazirah, Jazirah to Bashkala, Bashkala to Urmia, and Urmia to Suj Bulak through Ushnu.'The report contains the following illustrations:Tak-i-Girra, looking east (f 42).Sketch showing the Town of Rawanduz [Rāwāndūz], (f 63).Sketch showing the bridge at Rawanduz. (f 66).Sketch showing Amadiyeh [Al 'Amādīyah] from the north-east, (f 76).Sketch showing the bridge of Mosul (f 85).The report contains the following maps:Pass of Tak-i-Girra, on the Baghdad-Kermanshah Route, December 1889 (f 41).Country in vicinity of Rawanduz, May 1889 (f 64).Plateau of Amadiyeh and surrounding country, June 1888 (f 74).Plan of Mosul and surrounding country, corrected from Jones' survey, August 1889, (f 87).Country between Feishkhabur [Fīsh Khābūr] and Zakho, June 1888, (f 101).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Quarter Master General's Department, Intelligence Branch</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Luristan</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000912.0x00004d#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>