<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024197023.0x00008c_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T21:55:57.035Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024197023.0x00008c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/40, ff 67-68</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024197023.0x00008c</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00000d/IOR_R_15_1_40_0135.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/40, ff 67-68</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 85 from Ephraim Gerrish Stannus, Resident at Bushire to William Newnham, Chief Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1826/1826</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-11-12T00:19:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter reporting on a incident between Rahma ben Jabir [Rahma bin Jabir] and a Bahrein [Bahrain] Buglow, which resulted in both vessels being destroyed by fire.The letter reports that Rahma ben Jabir was sailing from Daman [Dammām] to secure support from allies elsewhere in the Gulf against the Chiefs of Bahrein and Katiffe [Al Qaţīf] who had united against him; that he had attempted unsuccesfully to enlist support from the Imam of Muscat at Kishm [Qeshm] and Colonel Stannus himself at Bushire. He had then returned to Daman where he had managed to manouevre past the Blockade by the Bahrein fleet and visit his garrison, but that on departure he came under attack from one of the boats commanded by Shaikh Ahmed ben Suleman [Aḥmad bin Suleman] (nephew of Shaikh Abdoola [ʻAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad Āl Khalīfah]) and that a desperate struggle ensued before Rahma ben Jabir set light to the magazines on board his vessel and destroyed both boats, leaving only Shaikh Ahmed and a few followers as survivors of the incident., which it was estimated took 300 lives.The letter concludes by observing that Rahma ben Jabir's brother Bashire was still in control of the fort at Deman, but that it was unlikely he would be able to hold out there for long following his brother's death.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024197023.0x00008c#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>