<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054933.0x000034_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T21:38:55.384Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054933.0x000034_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/35, ff 81-85</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054933.0x000034</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000008/IOR_R_15_1_35_0173.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/35, ff 81-85</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter no.53 of 1825 (Political Department) to William Newnham, Chief Secretary, Government of Bombay, from Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Ephraim Gerrish Stannus, Resident in the Persian Gulf</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1825/1825</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-02-20T05:13:53</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>5 folios</extent><extent>Parts of the letter have been struck through in pencil.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter describes a conversation which took place between Stannus and Shaikh Soultan ben Suggar [Sultan bin Saqr] at Bassidore [Bāsa‘īdū]. Stannus writes that Shaikh Sultan described his circumstances since first being dispossessed of his dominions by the Wahhabis, and his relations with the British Government. Stannus continues by stating that Shaikh Sultan wanted to know what degree of protection he might enjoy from the British, under threat of Wahhabi aggression, and regrets the response that Stannus gives him. The likely involvement of the Imam of Muscat [Sa‘id bin Sulṭān al-Sa‘id] in any conflict, should Wahhabi forces move east towards Brymee [Al Buraymī], is also discussed. Stannus gives his own assessment of the reach of the Wahhabi religion on the Arab coast, and the strength of the Wahhabi army. None of the enclosures to which Stannus alludes are included with the letter.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054933.0x000034#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>