<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000242_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T18:39:47.326Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000242_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1019</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000242</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000242/IOR_R_15_2_1019_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1019</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/28 II Superintendent, Political Agency, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-02T00:06:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (67 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1A on the front cover, and continues through to 66 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, enclosed in a circle, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1A, 1B. f. 36 needs to be folded out to read.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the service of the Superintendent at the Political Agency, Bahrain. The papers include correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, last pay certificates, a bill of lading, a certificate confirming status of holder as a Government servant, an office order, and letters from the Superintendent to the Political Agent, and cover leave, travel arrangements, travel expenses, salary, and appointment.The covering dates of the corespondence in this file are 21 November 1944 to 4 July 1945. The overall date range is supplied by an entry in the notes at the rear of the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Clerical Establishment, Superintendent Clerk</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000242#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000242#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000242#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>