<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000218_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-22T03:57:17.277Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000218_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1998</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000218</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000218/IOR_L_PS_12_1998_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1998</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/45 ‘Persian Gulf: Replacement of sea-plane unit in the Persian Gulf by a land-plane unit based on Bahrain’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-20T00:55:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (36 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 38; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence related to a proposal to transfer Royal Air Force No 203 (General Reconnaissance) Squadron from Basra to Bahrain, and in the process convert the unit from seaplanes to landplanes. It also documents the postponement of this transfer, as a result of the outbreak of the Second World War (1939-1945). Another topic covered in the file is a request for exemption from customs duties on petrol and oil for British military planes for the duration of the war.The main correspondents are as follows: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Trenchard Craven William Fowle), the Political Agent at Bahrain (Hugh Weightman and Reginald George Evelyn William Alban), the Air Officer Commanding in Iraq, officials of the Air Ministry, and officials of the India Office. It also contains a couple of letters from Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Air Force</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000218#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000218#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>