<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001e7_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T06:36:01.255Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001e7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/514</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001e7</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001e7/IOR_R_15_1_514_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/514</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/54 I (D 32) Koweit [Kuwait] Blockade'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T10:49:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (153 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.An index of topics discussed in the file is contained on folio 1B.</extent><extent>Condition: Formerly a bound correspondence volume, the file's pages have been unbound and are now loose.Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.The file contains the following foliation errors: 1, 1A, 1B, 1C and 1D; 62 and 62A; 109 and 109A</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding their attempts to enforce a blockade of Kuwait and to regulate all of its imports and exports. Much of the correspondence also relates more broadly to British-Kuwaiti relations and to the attitude of the ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Sālim al-Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ.A memorandum compiled by Robert Edward Hamilton, the British Political Agent in Kuwait and entitled 'Situation in Kuwait' is contained on folios 25-35. This memorandum discusses the political situation in Kuwait and the British authorities' rationale for enforcing a blockade.On folios 131-138, the file contains a report written by the British Political Agent in Kuwait, Percy Gordon Loch entitled 'Report on institution and working of the Blockade at Kuwait'. This report provides a detailed summary of all the events that are discussed in the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Economic sanctions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001e7#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>