<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000130_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T06:24:46.845Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000130_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3739</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000130</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000130/IOR_L_PS_12_3739_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3739</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/25 'Persian Gulf: Treaties and Agreements between H.M.G. and Arab Chiefs and Rulers; Supply of Copies to Ibn Saud and the Italian Govt.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-12T22:03:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (208 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 210; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume contains correspondence between British officials concerning a number of requests to be sent copies of various treaties agreed between Britain and rulers/states in the Persian Gulf.In addition to this correspondence, the volume also contains copies of many of the treaties that are discussed (some of which are in both English and Arabic) as follows:'Exclusive Agreement of the Chief of Abu Dhabi with the British Government, dated the 6th March, 1892' (folio 53)'Agreement of 23rd January 1899 with Ruler of Kuwait' (folios 54-55)'Exclusive Agreeemnt of the Shaikh of Bahrein with the British Government, dated the 13th March, 1892' (folios 56)'Text of Treaty, dated November 3, 1916, and ratified on March, 23, 1918, with Sheikh Abdullah-bin-Jasim-bin-Thani of El Katr' (folios 57-60)'Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation Between Great Britain and Muscat - 1891. Signed at Muscat. March 19th - 1891. Ratifications were exchanged in 1892' (folios 61-74)'Agreement Regarding the Cession of Territory by the Sultan of Oman, Dated 20th March, 1891' (folio 75-76)'Extract from Treaty of Erzurum concluded between Persia and Turkey on May 31st, 1847' in French (folios 77-78)'Memorandum on Certain Aspects of the Situation in the Persian Gulf as between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom, the Government of India, and the Persian Government' (folios 102-103)'Precis of the Treaties and Engagements between the British Government and the Chiefs of the Arabian Coast of the Persian Gulf' September 29 1928 (folios 106-108)'Memorandum on British Commitments to the Sheikh of Mavia' (folios 179-181)'Idrisi Treaty - Text of Treaty of April 30th, 1915' (folios 184-185)'Treaties and Agreements between the British Government and Certain Arab Rulers and Agreements Between the Said Rulers InterSe Affecting the British Government' Manager of India Press, Calcutta, 1926 (folios 186-210).The volume includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the volume by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000130#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000130#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>