<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000030_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-17T15:01:41.284Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000030_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B485</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000030</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000030/IOR_L_PS_18_B485_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B485</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on Bahrein'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-10T10:44:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (31 folios)</extent><extent>The file contains an index and list of appendices (folio 1) which make reference to paragraph and page numbers.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: The volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum, produced by the Foreign Office, dated 13 Jan 1947, deals with the history of Bahrein [Bahrain] from the point of view of the political status of the islands at various periods and dates since 1783, and contains copies of related correspondence and discussions. The principal authorities quoted in the memorandum are listed on folio 1v and appear as references in the right or left hand margin. The memorandum includes an index on folio 1r and a list of appendices on folio 1v. The index contains the the following sections:Geographical situation;Bahrein priot to 1783;1783-1820;1820-30;1830-40;1840-50;1850-61;1861-67;Discussion and Incidents, 1868-70;1870-80;1880-92. From the conclusion of the First to the conclusion of the Second Exclusive Agreement with Her Majesty's Government;1892-1913. From the Second Exclusive Agreement to the Anglo-Turkish Convention of 1913;1913-34;Summary (A. Claims to or assertions of soverignty over Bahrein, 1783 to 1934. B. Basis of the Persian claim. C. Attitude of His Majesty's Government, 1820-1934);Reference to Law Officers of the Crown;Independent Status of Bahrein;1934-46 (Establishment of Naval Base at Bahrein; Persian Government's refusal to recognise visas and endoresments of Bahrein; Agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Saudi Arabian Government regarding Transit Dues at Bahrein; The Liabilities of His Majesty's Government in the Persian Gulf; Treatment of Bahreinis in Persia; Bahrein Nationality and Property Laws; Treatment of Persians in Bahrein; Postal Services between Persian and Bahrein; Persian Government decree regarding import of Petroleum Products from Bahrein; Remarks of the Persian Prime Minister to the United States Ambassador; Recent references to Bahrein in the Persian Press).The memorandum is marked 'Confidential' and 'The Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><geographic>Bahrain islands</geographic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Territorial disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000030#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000030#share">Creative Commons Non-Commercial Licence</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000030#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>