<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00001c_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-15T22:38:05.284Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00001c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/121, ff 50-51</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00001c</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00005e/IOR_R_15_1_121_0101.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/121, ff 50-51</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from His Excellency Lieutenant-Colonel Justin Sheil CB, Her Majesty's Minister Plenipotentiary and Envoy Extraordinary at the Court of Persia, Tehran, to Lieutenant-Colonel Samuel Hennell, Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1850/1850</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-21T00:44:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Justin Sheil refers to Samuel Hennell's letter of 6 February 1850, no. 57, which concerned the Dashtee vessel that carried slaves to Bushire. Sheil writes that Hennell's suggestion to Bahram Meerza to despatch a mohussil to Hajee Khan of Dashtee is the best course of action. Sheil states that he has reason to think that the Persian Prime Minister [M카rz훮 Taq카 Kh훮n, known as Amir Kabir] has given His Royal Highness orders to the same effect. Sheil goes on to write that he does not think it would be right to call on Sheikh Nasir to expose himself to the emnity of so powerful a chief as Hajee Khan by laying an embargo on the vessel, unless it was done with the aid of British ships. Sheil refers to Hennell's suggestion of making an application to Bahram Meerza for the authority to detain the vessel, should it be met at sea by British cruisers. Sheil suggests that this application should not be made, on the grounds that Sheil is still engaged in a discussion with the Persian Government on this subject. Sheil concludes by stating that he has reason to believe that His Royal Highness will address to Hennell a suggestion to the same effect.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Letter</genre><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00001c#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>