<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000232_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-22T04:45:16.472Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000232_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2024</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000232</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000232/IOR_L_PS_12_2024_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2024</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/62 ‘India-Kabul Route: Question of establishment of an air service between India and Kabul’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-20T23:08:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (336 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 337; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers related to a number of unsuccessful attempts to establish civil aviation services between Afghanistan and India. The file includes related policy discussion over the use of Lend-Lease aircraft supplied by the United States, as a result of wartime proposals. It also includes intelligence report of rival negotiations between the Government of Afghanistan and competing powers: Germany, the Soviet Union (USSR), and the United States.The file also discusses India's post-war civil aviation plans: see folios 122-131. An Indian Delegation sent to Kabul in May 1947 is the predominant topic between folios 7-58: see folios 15-24 for a detailed report on this mission. Folio 318v contains a list of Germans employed in Kabul in 1938.The main correspondents are as follows: HM Minister at Kabul (William Kerr Fraser-Tytler and Giles Frederick Squire), officials of the Foreign Office, officials of the India Office, and representatives of the External Affairs Department of the Government of India.The file does not include any papers for the years 1940 and 1942.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>India</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Lend-lease operations (1941-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000232#share">Public Domain</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000232#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>