<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000384_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-16T22:20:47.551Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000384_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1229</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000384</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000384/IOR_R_15_2_1229_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1229</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/17 III Proclamations and Public Notices issued by the Bahrain Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-26T18:08:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (193 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 195; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains proclamations and public notices issued by the Government of Bahrain. The notices are mostly in Arabic with brief or full translations in English given for many. They are concerned with a wide range of matters relating to boating, driving, trade and pricing, customs, travel documents and restrictions, government office closures, public holidays, property registration and land regulation, health, government appointments, municipal elections, applications for Bahrain citizenship, education, electricity, currency regulation, and numerous miscellaneous prohibitions. Some notices are issued by the Customs House and the Manama Municipality.The file also contains correspondence between the Adviser to the Bahrain Government (Charles Dalrymple Belgrave) and the Political Agent, Bahrain.Folios 172-94 are internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bahrain, Āl Khalīfa dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Public information</topic></subject><subject><topic>Proclamations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000384#share">Unknown</accessCondition><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000384#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>