<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100031719623.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T05:47:41.730Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100031719623.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F112/366</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031719623.0x000001</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100031719623.0x000001/Mss Eur F112_366_0001.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F112/366</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Notebook of George Nathaniel Curzon's travels through Persia</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1889/1890</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-03T13:14:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (90 folios)</extent><extent>The main body of notes proceeds in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume; a separate set of notes begins at the rear of the volume and proceeds towards the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 92; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume is a bound notebook with handwritten notes in pencil by George Nathaniel Curzon. The notes, which follow on from an earlier notebook, Mss Eur F112/365, relate to Curzon's travels through Persia in 1889-90. The notes cover the period 25 November 1889 to 2 January 1890 and particularly relate to Curzon's visits to Teheran [Tehran] and Isfahan. For most of the notebook the notes appear in the form of diary entries that are preceded by date headings. Most of the folios have a vertical line drawn down the centre in pencil or ink; these lines do not represent column divisions, as the notes are written across the lines rather than in columns.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Travel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diaries</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031719623.0x000001#share">Creative Commons Attribution Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>