<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000066_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-10-19T01:51:18.277Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000066_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3541</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000066</url><url access="preview">https://images.qdl.qa/iiif/images/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000066/IOR_L_PS_12_3541_0002.jp2/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3541</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/127(2) ‘Persia. Indian Interest in Cultural &amp; Technical Development.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-08T22:07:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 28; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and other papers relating to Indian interests in commercial and cultural projects in Persia [Iran]. The file includes: the Government of India’s appointment of an Indian Trade Commissioner at Tehran, 1943; identified opportunities in which Indian assistance might be given on infrastructure projects (factories, irrigation systems, road construction) in Persia, 1944; a note on the distribution of Indian-made films in Persia, written by the Director of Public Relations at the British Embassy in Tehran, G W Seager, 1944; the minutes and agenda of a meeting held at the British Embassy in Tehran on 30 June 1944, on post-war planning in Persia, with a particular emphasis on the Indian contribution to commerce, public works, industrial assistance, and cultural exchange (ff 8-16). The file’s principal correspondents are: the British Ambassador at Tehran, Reader William Bullard; the Secretary of the External Affairs Department of the Government of India, Olaf Kirkpatrick Kruuse Caroe.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><genre type="class">Archival file</genre><subject><topic>Cultural exchange</topic></subject><subject><topic>Technical cooperation</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction" xlink:href="http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000066#share">Open Government Licence</accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>