<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T04:05:31.808Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I NOV 1935 964 500 2/26 fz ** , ^ P&amp;-rn c&amp;t- No. 3 . India Office, London, Tbr' 72' 1 : 19 a s: To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. iW ft&amp;eM ^?\-iSlrcVrto- ^ \vvC^\-cwi»V' 5 ^ ^.e^V^VrcovA. 'P 2 .. My Lord, I have to acknowledge the receipt of Your Lfc ^ Cs UtweT) q.\? t Excellency’s Despatch,7No. , dated the \7* ! ' October I93r, RctjuUvco^ transmitting an authentic copy of the noted in the margin, which has been by the Indian 1-^ginhitiK-e CaocrvLoC CL€&gt;At»re&gt;.v Com'accV. and to Leorisbuivo Loimoi-P which Your Excellency has signified your assent. ih 1 have to inform you that I have considered the Art7in Council, and that it will be left to its operation. (Signed) ZETLAND. Ml t&lt; APPROVED COUNC.'i! 'ti APPROVED POt ITICAL TEENo. /3&lt;? of 1936 To The Most Honourable the Marquess of Zetland y P,C«, His Majesty’s Secretary of w&gt;tate for India. Siala f the (1 October, 1935. Subject.- The Aden (Protection of Emigrants) Regulation. 1935. Government of India Act f I have the honour to forward herewith an authentic copy of a Regulation entitled the Aden (Protection of Emignnits) Regulation, 1935, (No.Ill of 1935J, to which I have signified my assent. 2. The Regulation has been, published in the Gazette of India of the 12th October, 1935, under a notification in the Legislative Department No.343/35-P, dated the 8th October, 1935. 3. I also enclose a copy of the correspondence cited in the annexed list, and solicit your attention to the telegram from the Chief Commissioner of Aden, No.63, dated the 15th September 1935, which explains the reasons for the Regulation. Tour Lordship’s most obedisnt, humble servant, My Lord Marquess In accordance with the provisions of section 71(3) of the 3 d/- Willingdon,List of enclosures of Governor General’s letter to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, No. /ZB , Regulation, 1935. 2. Telegram from the Chief Commissioner of Aden, No.63, dated the 15th September 1935. 3. Telegram to the Chief Commissioner, Aden, No.2552, dated the 20th September 1935. 4. Telegram from the Chief Commissioner, Aden, No.68, dated the 21st September 1935. 5. Government of India, Legislative department Notification No.343/35-P, dated the 8th October, 1935. dated the October, 1935. 1. Copy of the Aden (Protection of ^migrants) Sd/- G.H. Spence, Deputy Secretary.REGULATION No. Ill of 1935. a A REGULATION TO Provide fox the safely of persems emigrating from. Aden. A he re a 8 it is expedient to provide for the safety of persons emigrating from Aden ; It is hereby enacted as follows :— 1. (2) This Regulation may be called the Aden Short title and coni' (1 rotection of Emigrants) mcncement. Regulation, 1935. (~) It shall come into force on such date as the t hief Commissioner may, by notification in the Aden Gazette, appoint. 2. No person shall leave the Province of Aden Prohibition of emigration by sea, land or air wil hout 'without permit. -j, \yritten permit issued by 'Or under the orders of the Chief Commissioner. 3. Every application for such a permit shall com Application for permits. t ,! &gt;n particulars of the pro posed destination arid route of the applicant together with such other particulars as the Chief Commissioner may, by general or special order, require. 4. The Chief Commissioner, or anv person autho- Prsvention of contra ven- rised by general or special :tiou8 -. _ order of the Chief Com missioner in this behalf, may use any and every means necessary to prevent any contravention of section 2. 5. The Chief Commissioner may, by notification Power of exemption. b 1 the Aden Gazette, exempt from the provi sion of section 2 persc?is leaving Aden and pro ceeding to or through- (a) any part of His Majesty’s Dominions; or {b) any territory, not being part of His Majesty’s Dominions, in which, in the opinion o’ the Chief Commissioner, ade quate provision has been made for the safety of p tsgus entering such territory. 6. Whoever contiavc ics the provision of see- Penalty. ^ on ^ shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both. I assent to this Regulation. WILLINGDON Viceroy and Governor General. The 3rd October, 1933. An authentic Copv. L. GRAHAM, Secretary to the Government of India, Legislative Department. jGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. LEGISLATIVE DEPARTMENT. A REGULATION TO Provide for tlie safety of persons emigrating from Aden. II 185LD»—73—8-10-3S—Gll’SSr © i Telegram XX No.63 dated lend received.) 15th September f 1935. ... iYom. •••••»•• .Chief Ccumil*? loner• Aden. To.Foreign Simla. (Repea ted to Seore ,ur^ of State for India* London.) FXPHSSS . Seoretery of State f e telegram Ko.2909* paragraph 3. Consider it desirable that Regaletlons err nade to control all departures from Aden.LEGISLATIVE DEPARTMENT. REGULATION No. Ill of 1935. NOTIFICATION. Simla, the 8th October, 1935. No. 343 35-P. —Whereas by Resolution passed by the Secretary of State for India in Council on the 10th day of September, 1884, the provi sions of section I of the Government of India Act, 1870 (33 and 34 Viet., c.3), were declared applicable to the Island of Perim ; And whereas by Resolution passed by the said Secretary of State for India in Council on the 9th day of November, 1886, the provisions of the said section were declared applicable to the Settlement of Aden and its dependencies for the time beinp, inclusive of the villages of Sheikh Othman, Imad and Hiswa, the Island of Perim and Little Aden ; And whereas the places to which the provi sions of the said section were declared applic able by the said Resolutions are territories now under the administration of the Chief Commis sioner of Aden ; And whereas the said provisions having from time to time been repealed, re-enacted and amended, are now incorpora-ed in section 71 of the Government of India Act ; And whereas the said Chief Commissioner of Aden has proposed to the Governor General in Council a draft of the following Regulation, together with the reasons for proposing the same ; And whereas the Governor General in Coun cil has taken the draft and reasons into con sideration, and has approved of the draft and the same has received the assent of the Gov ernor General on the 3rd day of October. 193'5 ; In pursuance of the direction contained m sub-section (2) of section 71 of the Govern ment of India Act, the said Regulation is now published in the Gazette of India. A REGULATION TO Provide for the safety of 'persons emigrating from Aden. Whereas it is expedient to provide for the safety of persons emigrating from Aden ; It is hereby enacted as follows :— 1. (i) This Regulation may be called the Aden Short title and com- (Protection of Emigrants) mencement. Regulation, 1935. {2) It shall come into force on such date as the Chief Commissioner may, by notification in the Aden Gazette, appoint. 2. No person shall leave the Province of Aden Prohibition of emigration tea, land Or air without without permit. a written |)errnit issued by or under the orders of the Chief Commissioner. 3. Every application for such a permit shall con- , .. . . .. tain particulars of the pro- Anphcation for permits. ^ . 1 - posed destination and route of the applicant together with such other particulars as the Chief Commissioner may, by general or special order, require. 4. The Chief Commissioner, or any person autho- Prevention of contraven- rised by general or special tions. order of the Chief Com missioner in this behalf, may use any and every means necessary to prevent any contravention of section 2. 5. The Chief Commissioner may, by notification _ . in the Aden Gazette, Power of exemption. . ’ exempt from the provi sion of section 2 persons leaving Aden and pro ceeding to or through— {a) any part of His Majesty’s Dominions; or (b) any territory, not being part of His Majesty’s Dominions, in which, in the opinion of the Chief Commissioner, ade quate provision has been made for the safety of persons entering such territory. 6 . Whoever contravenes the provision of sec- Penalty ^ ou ^ punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both. L. GRAHAM, Secy, to the Govt, of India. HteH/D 40 -in-io-ss—GIPSREGULATION No. Ill of 1935. A RE GELATION TO Provide for the safely of persons emigrating from Aden. Whereas it is expedient to provide for the scfety of persons emigrating from Aden ; It is hereby enacted as follows :— 1. (2) This Regulation may be called the Aden Short titJe and com- (i rotection of Emigrants) mencement. Regulation, 1935. (2) It shall come into force on such date as the Chief Commissioner may, by notification in the Aden Gazette, appoint. 2. No person shall leave the Province of Aden Prohibition of emigration land Or air without without permit. a written permit issued by or under the orders of the Chief Commissioner. 3. Every application for such a permit shall con- Application for permits. tain Particulars of the pro posed destination and route of the applicant together with such other particulars as the Chief Commissioner may, by general or special order, require. 4. The Chief Commissioner, or any person autho- Prevention of contraven- rised by general or special tions ' order of the Chief Com missioner in this behalf, may use any and everv means necessary to prevent any contravention of section 2. 5. The Chief Commissioner may, by notification Power of exemption. Aden Gazette, exempt from the provi sion of section 2 persons leaving Aden and pro ceeding to or through- - (a) any part of His Majesty’s Dominions; or (b) any territory, not beirg part of His Majesty’s Dominions, in which, in the opinion of the Chief Commissioner, ade quate provisicn has been made for the safety of persons entering such territory. 6. Whoever contravenes the provision of sec- Penalty. ^ on ^ b e punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. LEGISLATIVE DEPARTMENT. A REGULATION TO Provide for the safety of persons emigrating from Aden. MISELE—73—?*iC.3E~GlTSJGS/WB 5523. 3ECYPHBR OF TELEGRAM. ... From (COPIES CIRCULATED) (Joyernment of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India a V \ Dated Simla, 11th October, 1935 0 ReceiTed 3 pom e , 11th October, 1935 0 Addressed to Secretary of .State and repeated to Chief Commissioner, Aden 0 Your telegrams of the 13th ultimo, 2909 and 3223 dated 10th October&lt;» Regulation being published in Gazette of India dated 12th OctoberPARAPICIA&amp;'S • 1 f T GL.'^GHAIi from tho Governor Secretary of State for the Colonies. Dated 4th October, 193b. Received in the Colonial Office at 4.12 p.m. on 4th October, 1935. No.232. Secret. In compliance with your predecessor 1 s telegram Secret rio.90 instructions have been given against the issue of foreign contracts of service to clast? of persons covered by Chapter 139. After reference to Attorney General no authority found enabling this Government to prvovent recruitment before the outbreak of hostilities of British Indians for the purpose ir question in either military or civil capacity. In the event of recruitment for Military and Naval but not civil purposes employment could bo prevented under Section 62 of the Penal Code. 55 Indian artisans and xaotor drivers have it is reported been recruited for Italian Somaliland up to the 20 th September. Please let me have instructions as to the means of prevention. Above refers to your despatch of the 13th September Secret ( 2 ).2681/35 General CYFHSfi Telegram from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Governor of Xac/ftc ^ Sent 11 p.ra. r 9th October,1935, Ne. 284. Secret. Your telegram No, 232. I appreciate difficulties but consider it definitely undesirable to allow recruit ment of British subjects, either European or Indian, even for oetensibly civil employment, in Italian Colonies or Ethiopia. Special amending legislation would clearly be undesirable. Would it be possible to achieve deeired object by administrative action such as withholding passports?(R2C97) Wt 47527/3095 5,000 9/33 H &amp; SP Gp 112 Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, * London, S.W.l. and the following number quoted :— , 2681/35- Reference to 'previous correspondence :— to Letter Colonial Office of the September. (6272/1935-) Downing Street, ' ' -September, 1935 . Sir, 1 v I am directed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to transmit to you for the information of the Marquess of Zetland, a 7) 0 copy of the paperf noted below, on the subject of emigration from Aden to the Italian Colonies or Ethiopia. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant. The Under Secretary of State, J, L. MAFFEY. India Office Date. Description. 14 th September, 1935- Telegram to the Acting Resident at Aden. Copy also sent to F. 0 .2681/35. 6589 | n 1 19^5 J CYPHER TKI^KQRAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Acting Resident at Aden* Sent 6 c O p.ra* 14th Septeniber, 1935. Addressed to Aden NO 068 . Repeated to Government of India No.2933* Your telegram of 23nd August, your telegram) to Oovem'nent of India No.55, Question of proposed issue of regulations under Section 71 of Government of India Act is under consideration by H.M.Government* Pending decision emigration of Yemenis from Aden to Italian Colonies or Ethiopia should be prevented as a matter of administrative practice*From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Resident and Commander-la-Chiefs Aden p to Secretary of State for Indiaj. repeating telegram addressed to Secretary, Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. XXX Aden, 15th September, ^ 1935 6 Received 8 0 45 a^m,, 15th September, 1935. 63 a Addressed to Secretary to Government of India, Foreign and Political Separtroent, and repeated to Secretary of State for India. Secretary oi Statefor India 8 s telegram- *^909, paragraph Uo c 3 e Consider it desirable that regulations are made control all departures from Aden, ECO. P 1 '* 13 SEP 1935 J\ (Minute Paper Department. (&gt;■'1. S'bZ'l/1$, n. The Italians have been making attempts to recruit Arabs at Aden for service as labourers in the Italian Colonies. For some years Aden has been a source from which recruits were obtained for the Italian native levies. In Colonial Office telegram of 25th July, No.47 the Chief Commissioner at Aden was informed that steps should be taken to prevent the employment at the present juncture of British subjects or British protected persons in Ethiopia or the Italian colonies either in a civil capacity or with military forces (P.Z.5115/35). The prevention of such recruitment is desirable in the interests of the individuals who might otherwise go to the Italian Colonies. The health conditions under which they would work would be likely to be dubious and we cannot be confident that they would be well treated. The question of our neutral position is also relevant ; as labourers recruited in Aden for the Italian Colonies would presumably be in effect non-combatant members of the Italian military forces. The Government of India have been instructed to prevent emigration from India to Ethiopia or the Italian colonies for employment in a civil capacity (India Office telegram No.1685 of 31st May and India Office telegram No.2499 of 8 th August). 2. The Chief Commissioner was also instructed to ta.ke the view of the King of the Yemen regarding the recruitment of Yemenis. The King of the Yemen appears to wish such recruitment stopped (Aden telegram of 22nd August, P.Z.5985/35). Sir B.Reilly holds the view that no distinction should be drawn in this matter between Yemenis and others at Aden and the Colonial Office in agreement with the Foreign Office propose so to instruct Colonel Lake. 2956 6000 7/?4 3./3. The Indian Emigration Act provides powers to prevent emigration (as defined in the Act) by native British subjects from the Aden Settlement Jbui: the Chief Commissioner has^ howovory no legal powers to prevent the emigration of British protected persons or Yemenis. The emigration of such persons through Aden has, however, in i the past been controlled without challenge and in Colonial Office telegram No.52 of 12th August, the Chief Commissioner was instructed to exercise this administrative \ y control pending the examination of the question of giving him additional powers (P.Z.5624/35). 4. Owing to the possibility that orders prohibiting the emigration of British protected persons and Yemenis might be challenged in court under the instigation of the Italian Consul at Aden, it seems desirable to give the Chief Commissioner additional powers, by the issue of a Regulation under Section 71 of t the Government of India. Act. The Government of India are ready to take this action (Government of India telegram No.2319 of 31st August, P.Z.6122/35) and at an interdepartmental meeting held on 7th September it appeared that the Colonial Office and Foreign Office were in favour of that course. The view of this Department is simi 1 ar . 5. The contents of this Regulation were * considered at the interdepartmental meeting. It was agreed that it should control emigration from Aden by all persons whether British subjects, British protected persons or Yemenis and that the penalties suggested by the Chief Commissioner at Aden in his telegram No. 55 of 5th September were suitable. The question was considered whether P-2- (a) the Regulation should prohibit emigration both to Ethiopia and to the Italian Colonies except with the permission of the Chief Commissioner, or whetherMinute Paper Department 'f (b) it should not mention these countries by name but instead prohibit emigration to any foreign country until the Chief Commissioner is satisfied that the Government of that country has made such laws and other provisions as he shall consider sufficient for the protection of emigrants. I The first course was suggested by the Government of India in their telegram No.2319 of 31st August (P.Z.5122/35) f while the second is favoured by the Chief Conmissioner. The meeting agreed that the second course is the best for the following reasons. It would give less offence to Italy; it would be applicable in wider circumstances which may arise but cannot now be foreseen; and would enable emigration to the Italian Colonies via French Somaliland or British Colonies to be prevented. 3Ke oeo.^\-oa- 6 . There is a loophole in the Indian Emigration lAct. Under the definition of emigration in the Act it does not give powers to prevent the departure of persons seeking employment who are neither under agreement nor in receipt of assistance. The attention of the Chief Commissioner was drawn to this point in Colonial Office telegram No.47 of 25th July and he was asked whether he considered further powers necessary to guard against this. ! * He has not reverted to the point. If the definition of emigration in the Regulation is the same as that in the Indian Emigration Act, this loophole will be reproduced in the Regulation. The Foreign Office are anxious that if possible it should be closed and I undertook that we should draw the attention of the Government of India to the point and leave them to ddal with it if they and the Chief Commissioner considered it necessary. 2956 6000 7/?4 7./k I think this is really what we have got to do. M . J . C . , 10.9. Mr.Clauson, I am not clear whether the effect of the proposed Regulation is intended to he (1) that no one should be able to leave Aden for any foreign country unless and until the Chief Commissioner has notified as permissible destinations the countries whose Governments he is satisfied have made such laws, etc., when he could leave only for one of the countries named; or (2) that the Chief Commissioner should be empowered to issue notifications prohibiting emigration to particular named countries until he is satisfied, etc. Our telegram of the 20th August seems rather ambiguous, but appears to suggest ( 1 ); on the other hand the Colonial Office telegram of the 2nd August to Somaliland and the Government of India*s telegram of the 31st August seem rather to suggest ( 2 ). ( 1 ) sounds very inconvenient (2) would involve mention of Italian Colonies and Ethiopia by name, though not in the Regulation itself. I gather from the last part of para.5 of the minute that other Departments have definite views as to the course to be taken (? (l) above). If it is desired, to arooumo that Italian colonies are not mentioned by name even by the Chief Commissioner, would it be desirable to make it clearer ? Or can we leave it to India and Aden? Perhaps Sir B.Reilly knows all about it ? L.D.W. , 10 . 10 . I assume that it cannot be contemplated that the Chief Commissioner should simply prohibit individualsas they come along without making any notification. This seems obviously inconsistent with penalties (rather savage as it seems to me) for attempts to contravene the prohibition. bir L.Wakely, I am afraid it is very difficult for us to say what exactly will be done in practice. In any case we do not envisage ( 2 ). Commissioner will have to deal with cases individually as suggested in your footnote - this is done in India in certain circumstances under the Emigration Act, viz. a recruiting agent has to put in a request for permission to recruit certain individuals which may or may not be granted. penalties prescribed will only be imposed on recruiting agents and not on individual recruits (who will merely be prevented from leaving Aden). The only thing to do seems to be to leave the matter to the authorities in India and Aden. It is quite possible that the Chief In any case it seems probable that theExtract from Government of India Act. Regulations and Ordinances. Power to make regu lations. 71. (1) The local government of any part of British India to which this section for the time being applies may propose to the Governor—General in Council the draft of any regulation for the peace and good government of that part, with the reasons for proposing the regulation. (2) Thereupon the Governor-General in Council may take any such draft and reasons into consideration; and, when any such draft has been approved by the Governor- _ General in Council and assented to by the Governor- General, it shall be published in the Gazette of India and in the local official gazette, if any, and shall there upon have the like force of law and be subject to the like disallowance as if it were an Act of the Indian legislature. (3) The Governor-General shall send to the Secretary of State in Council an authentic copy of every regulation to which he has assented under this section. (3a) A regulation made under this section for any territory shall not be invalid by reason only that it confers or delegates power to confer on courts or administrative authorities power to sit or act outside the territory in respect of which they have jurisdiction or functions, or that it confers or delegates power to confer appellate jurisdiction or functions on courts or administrative authorities sitting or acting outside the territory. (4) The Secretary of State may, by resolution in Council/2 . a Council, apply this section to any part of British India, as from a date to be fixed in the resolution, and withdraw the application of this section from any part to which it has been applied.t Draft Paper. ?2, b'XlZj'is. POLITICAL Department. DRAFT TELFGRAM. % &gt; From Secretary of State ^ for India to 1 Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Dept. , Repealed to Chief ^ Commissioner, Aden. \r A ^ XXX &gt;-i a f Copy to F.O. y 1 - 0 ' ^ \^\) ofl&amp; V ^ * * Your telegram No.2319 of 31st August.’ H.M.G. agree that Regulation under Section 71 of Government of India Act should be made. 2. Presumptions (a) and (c) in paragraph 2 of your telegram are correct —^ ^ Ve ^oUoud ^ V-Q^c^vawv Reg]Aat^on_should n-ot opee-ify oountri-e-e &lt;% Vd^ No vv&lt;SV* co^UJbrCe^ ^ emigrat ion-t-^ #hi-oh is con t iK^Aed-. ^ l-./ n/m&gt; t.-r^Trsr * *tm*hj ** TtvvAwc-t iirzXtf*] uuijn^' 3If you afid Chief Commissioner July No.47 to AdenA) consider it necessary, you will no doubt make Regulation control all departures from Aden even by persons^ neither under agreement nor in receipt of assistance (vide Colonial Office telegram of 25th v ' ^ I leave this — &gt; point foj* your decision. ^ 4. It is desirable that Regulation should be published urgently to enable Foreign Office to answer representations regarding Yemenis made by Italian - ^ ^ ^ Embassy and because of instructions in Colonial Office telegram of 12th August o' No.52 to Aden. ‘Q.c^V.cv.V'VOw Cs» . 'V?&amp; FILE COPY T'. v-i. I r o '7 o i rs fch/wb * I 1 1955 J ( 65. groups o ) SECRET 4718, DECYPHEB C F TELEGRAM* Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Chief Commissioner, Aden, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram addressed to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department*, XXX Dated Aden,- 5th September, 1935 0 Received midnight, 4th September, 1935, Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Secretary of State for India*, Your telegram 2319, paragraph 2 0 (a) I agree,. Regulation should control emigration of all three classes 0 (b) I would prefer that specific countries be not mentioned and that regulation be in terms suggested xn secretary of State for India telegram 2654,_July 20th (c) Suggest that, in addition to power forcibly to restrain attempts to contravene prohibition, power to inflict fine up to Rs:l ,000 and/or 6 months* rigorous imprisonment be sanctioned 0\ b) Draft Paper. H.R. Cowell, Esn., C.M.G., C.O. rV '' L^l Department. ^SEP 193E With reference to your letter of 27th August, No. 2681/35, and mine of 29th August, about emigration from Aden, I expect that you will have seen the G. of I.’s telegram of 31st August, of which copy is enclosed for ease of reference. 2 I take it that everyone is agreed as to the desirability of preventing the emigration to the Italian colonies from Aden of British protected persons and - Yemenis as well as British subjects, but as Lake points out in his telegram of 24th August, prohibitive orders resting on no legal basis in the case of the two former classes might be challenged in court by persons instigated by the Italian Consul. Reilly, whom I saw to-day, thinks it very desirable that legislation on the lines suggested by the G. of I. in their telegram of 31st August should be enacted without delay. 3 , Could you tkeae^epe kindly let me know as soon as possible whether the C.O. would like us, if higher authorit^e*- here approver, to instruct the G. of I. to enact such legislation by means of a Regulation made by the G*G. - under Section 71 of the G. of I. Act. This can be quite an expeditious process; the Chief Commissioner would propose a draft to/1 ' ■ n to v to the G. of I. (which he could do by telegraph), the G. of I. would approve it, t ! and it would thereupon be promulgated with ^ force of law. ♦ ^ If you desire this course to be taken, we should be glad to know whether you or the F.O. have any preference as between the suggestion in para. 2(b) of the G. of I.'s telegram, which mentions Abyssinia and the Italian colonies, and the suggestion in our telegram to the G. of I* of 20th August (copy sent to the C.0* with 1.0* printed letter P.Z. 5697/35), which mentions no names, and which was based on C.O. telegram to ^ Somaliland No. 71 of 2nd August. If the latter alternative is preferred, it would be desirable for as, in telegrapfeifig # ^ ? 1 ^/ instrudions to th^ Chief Commissioner, to — ask whether^he sees any administrative L. difficulties in this alternative. j^I am sending a copy of this letter to Stemdale-Bennett. V or t in merely.fhb/wb , SECRET a- &gt; 1 4656 0 D E CYPHER OF TBLEGRA M,_ (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom Dated Received Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India 0 . lW Simla, 31st August, 1935 0 6*30 Romo, 31st August, 1935 f 4 . XXX rfy/k 'v S219, Mdreseed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Adeno ^ Our telegram of the 21st instant, 2186, and Aden reply 45, August 24th 0 As Chief Commissioner anticipates that executive order may he challenged, we are prepared to undertake legislation by means of regulation under Section 71, Government of India Act, to control emigration from Aden 0 2 0 In order to proceed to draft of regulation, we require precise indication of the scope of the legislation ^ rsquired 0 We presumes I'* (a) that it would he (Vomnibus) regulation to control emigration of all 3 classes mentioned incur telegram 2186 0 (b) that it would prohibit emigration both to Abyssinia and to Italian colonies of Eritrea and Italian Somaliland, except with permission of the Chief Commissioner, and, (c) that, in addition to conferring direct power forcibly to restrain attempts to contravene the prohibition, it would apply {?sanctions) in the form of imprisonment and/or fine against such attempts* 3* If, on the other hand, you consider it should be in terms suggested in your telegram of the 20th instant, 2654, and not specify the countries to which emigration is to be prohibited, we would be prepared to draft accordinglyo 4 n We will await your viewsoMy dear Cowell, With reference to yourletter to Rumbold of 27th August, No. 2681/35, regarding emigration from Aden, you will no doubt have seen the Government of India's telegram of 22nd August, No. 2186, and Aden telegram of 24th August, No. 45, of which copies are enclosed for ease of reference. considering whether to undertake legislation by means of a Regulation made by the Governor-General under Section 71 of the Government of India Act, which is the course which the Chief Commissioner prefers. If such legislation were enacted, the question of the emigration of Yemenis through the port of Aden would of course be covered. The Government of India are now no doubt I am sending a copy of this letter t Stemdale-Bennett. H.R. Cowell, Esq., C.M.G. (Sgd.) J.C. Walton.Colonial Office, Downing Street, S.W.l. 5') August, 195b. Sterndale Bennett. 8.S5 j Dear Rumbold, The old question of the recruitment of people in or through Aden for employment in the Italian Colonies or Kthiopia. I enclose a copy of a telegram which we have received from the Acting Resident, which gives the views of the King of Yemen on the question of the recruitment of Yemenis. You will see that it is very satisfactory from our point of view. I also enclose a copy of a letter which I have sent to Sterndale Bennett, at the Foreign Office, which indicates the immediate action which we should now like to take - i.e. that, penning a decision as to the further legal action which may he necessary (in regard to which you will presumably wish to await a reply to your tfyif- telegram to the Government of India No. 2585 of the 15th August) the Acting Resident should he instructed to prevent H.F. RUMBOLD, ES^.n I ^ &gt; i ■ V Zkj*. the emigration of Yemenis from Aden, as a matter of administrative practice, in the same way as he was told to do, in the case of British subjects and protected persons, by our telegram No. ^52 o f the 12th august. Perhaps you will be gooa enough to let me know v/hether the India Office agree that we can proceed on the lines suggested. Yours sincerely, Q£'CYPHJSR TSXEGRAM from the Acting Resident at-Aden to ufcie Secretary of State for the ColonieR* Dated 22nd August. Received 2,5? p.m. 22nd August, 1935, Addressed to Colonial Office repeated to Government of India. Your ;elegram No,47. King of the Yemen wishes to observe strict neutrality and is in general agreement with policy ei undated in your telegram under reference 0y 2681 / 35 . , i, ; ' J ^ y Colonial Ofiico, Downing Street.1. August, 1935. As you probably know, a good deal of consideration has been given recently to the question of whether any steps should be taken to prevent the employment, at the present juncture, of British subjects and British protected persone inthe Italian Colonies or Ethiopia; and toe conclusion has been reached that it is highly undesirable that such employment should take place, and that all possible steps should be taken to stop it. General instructions to this effect were sent to various Colonial Governments in July; and although in some places special legislation may be required, it is not anticipated that most of the Government* concerned will find any difficulty in implementing these instructions. The position at Aden , is, however, peculiarly J.C. -bo,., C.IUG.,M.O.peculiarly complicated. Hot only la it doubtful how far the Keaident haa any legal powers to control the emigration of British subjects or British protected persons from Aden for employment in Ethiopia or the Italian Colonies • but there is an a^deu complication in that attempts may be i m&amp;de to recruit Yemenis, and it is, therefore, necessary to decide whether such recruitment through Aden should also be stopped. borne of the complications arising at Aden were discussed at a meeting here on the nand July when Thompson represented the Foreign Officei and you will see from the enclosed copy of a telegram sent to the Acting liesident on the 25th July that, so far as the recruitment of Yemenis was concerned, the suggestion was made that the *iewa of the King of Yemen should be ascertained before any definite decision was taken. I enclose also copies of subsequent telegraphic correspondence with the Acting Resident, including a copy of his latest telegram in which he' vt-NS-. s - * ^ .‘*.1 i x fci ^•*&gt;&amp;; a f&gt; Mi iOT^ncc c-3 iifevoi i. *; I ^ .iffoaiiK: fc##05iou$ aaiti^.- tlo . j qg£&amp;*i &amp;l %Oi.-' D i.i J1 •'•- !i- : tC • fi»; iXlJ- - tt£ &gt;. *5 ■• **• l.fM et) C. t &lt;ii' w i t 'i#- - '• •' 1 •&gt;* e feXJioile a*i&gt;4 »r iiutf - XutiSt t -ci ; &gt;i 3^ « U O j b i^C* o V j- &amp;%%w a&amp;bt ^Rl*».x*xa BnojU^sii-i&amp;Ci - s&amp;j -v a&amp;d&lt;- %Xa^ 3Q &amp;%*£ i 4 • -- -3 t&gt;I fe€ iJOto-ii.. IXi vox lsu. iooi -i'.. a]--i-xo'i m&amp;$ i-tJ'iso-^'Svi* .lo&amp;q^o jSI* le '^'4 oo ^aoXs«o d^U sso'tlx V Xul* lloCS 9113 10 JOOii'.' fcOi--. »;TJ J ^ae io'ii- b*£il o«f ^Ii : s.--v ii. • f*-t lo 1&lt;. U.. ii;v‘3 OCX#: O«.0XD&amp;9 1 . J ikOiSJtOOAi o^xal 1&amp;&amp; *? -di^ ’^,- 01) * . JtirffcfcC.OJi . ^ . : -U : - !-he says that the king of Yemen 'wishes to observe strict neutrality' 9 and agrees with the policy set out in Colonial Office telegram .o.47 of the 25th July. The present position of the matter oan f therefore, be suanarlaed as follows 5 - (a) Ho decision has yet been taken, pending the receipt of the views of the Government of India, on the question of what legislation will have to be enacted in order to enable the hesideat to give legal effect to the policy decided upon oy His Majesty’s Government. (b) ifeanwhile, however, the acting Resident has been instructed (in the Secretary of State’s telegram of the 12th August} that, despite the legal difficulties, the emigration of British protected persona and British subjects from Aden for employment in Ethiopia or the Italian Colonies, either in a civil or military capacity, should be prevented, by administrative action. (c) The question now arises as to whether, in advance of any decision uhat may be taken on (a) above, the Acting Resident should be informed that steps should similarly be taken (again, as a matter of administr? tive practice}practice) to preyeat the emigration through Aden of for ueryice in the Italian Colonies or Ethiopia. It is on this particular point that we should appreciate your yiewa - naturally, we ourselyes should wish to instruct the Acting Hesident to take action on the lines inaicated, provided that the Foreign Office see no objection to our doing so. In this connection, I ought to say that Sir Bernard Keilly has expressed the view strongly to us in conversation that the prohibition of emigration from Aden to the Italian Colonies or Ethiopia, should be made of general application, i.e. that it should apply to Yemenis as well as to British subjects or British protected persona. Otherwise he thinks that if British subjects or British protected persons are prevented from leaving Aden to take up employment in these countries while Yemenis are left quite free to leave for that purpose, there will be considerable protest, and possibly trouble, from our own Arabs on / the' - CWP/DIA, yc &gt;Ap. * (50 gi*oups) ^0 FILE Cct v, r&gt; •' &gt; V. 4517. P-iOLY P H E r? OF X_£. L E G R A M. Prom (COPIES CUMULATED) Resident, Men, to the Government of India, and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India. Dated Received ' w ” — - y 24th August, 1935, YYY 4=15 p.m. AAA /f stir -r' t 45^ Mdreesed to Government of India repeated to Secretary of State for India* Your telegram No* 218622nd Augusts I concur with paragraphs No8 0 l, 2, 3 and 4* Paragraph 5* Prohibitive orders in case of classes (b) and (c) might he challenged court of law 1Y instigated by foreign consul.* Therefore would prefer regulation under Section 71 (? Government of India) ActoSECRET EE/lJIA. D..-E.C Y P-H E R OF T E L E G RA M o Prom Government of India, Foreign and , Political Department, to Secretary of (COPIES State for India. CIRCULATED) Dated Simla, 22nd August, 1935. Received Slat August, 1935, 11«50 p.m. XXX 2186 . Second Part. 3o 11 emergency power ie required to prohibit emigration of classes (b) and (c) from Men to Italian Colonies» except with permission of the Chief Commissioners, this could be taken in the form of regulation under Section 71 * Government of India Acto All persons for the time being within Aden settlement, irrespective of their national, status, are amenable to law in force in that settlement, and power to legislate for peace and good government of a named territory being a {? plenary) power to enact territorial legislation for that territory 9 there is no room for argument that legislation designed to protect would-be emigrants from probable danger in Italian Colonies or Abyssinia is outside the scope of Section 71 as not being legislation for peace and good government of Aden*SECRET FCN/DIAo (88 groups) 4453 « )B.g . .q,Y R . A X J. £ JIAil* From Government of India-p Foreign and Political Department^ to Secretary (COPIES of State for'India* CIRCULATED) Dated Simla, 22nd August, 1935o Received 21st August, X935 ? 11-.45 XXX SiM* miM^d,LasJ^Parta If legislation were undertaken it would presumably extend to the prohibition of emigration not only to Italian colonies but also to Abyssinia* 5 0 Before we consider whether legislation is necessary, we have asked the Chief Commissioner to inform us whether control cannot be adequately exercised as matter of administrative practice as indicated in final paragraph of your telegram* Class (a) can be dealt with under the Emigration Act, and it seems improbable that classes (b) or (c) ? for whom alone legislation would be required, would be in position to challenge prohibitory orders in court of law*6 'mm- DRAFT TELEGRAM. V 1 SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPA RTMENT. (Retamilla) Repeated to Chief Commissioner, Aden. r lr U $ «££)V gr-Ty DATE j TIM* #£C£. /V Ttf.SCH. \2o[&lt;% \£ $o f it OOSiL, X or XX KXX DESPATCHED ? -3t&gt; f ■ $1 He. OF WORDS Bevorn’3 IKIT.ALS . p r z^lbSJM^ . t ' z£&gt;*~ ,y l'y telegram, 2585; recruitment of laboar for Italian colonies from AdenI s S' In regard to similar question in British Somaliland (fco^have^ asked Governor whether requirements^ wo aid be'' * y * met by an ordinance prohibiting ^ &lt; ^ r~ y emigration to any foreign country until s r' &lt; s ^ he is satisfied that the govt, of that ^ ^ s S' ^ country has made such laws and other provisions as he shall consider sufficient for the orotection of the native r y inhabitants of Somaliland emigrating to that country (this is based on principle' * •/ s s' ' y s of sec. 2 of Ceylon Ordinance ho. 4 of 1882')' ^ ?Gql may Wish Lu CUiisider Regulation under sec. 7I^di the G. of I. Act on similar linein view of fact that Indian immigration Act appears to be inadequate/fbr our present purpose, which yi to control emigration of Arabs fre^-port-o f-rtden, whether they are British subjects, British protectedx &gt; i ^ 5 b f v Down xng Rt.. Dear Yfalton, I enclose, as I promised, copies of our recent telegraphic correspondence with Somaliland about the proposed enactment of an Ordinance there to control emigration - the real purpose of which would he to make illegal emigration from the Protectorate for service in the Italian Colonies or Ethiopia. I also enclose a copy of Ceylon Ordinance No. 4 of 1882 which controls the emigration of labour from Ceylon. Yours sincerely, J. C. WALTON, ESQ., C.B., M.C.2681/35, ( 5 ) lAHAJrHl'iASjii TELKuitA^A froui the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Governor of Somaliland* Sent 3 0 15 ^ota, 2nd Adjust* 1935* IMME D IATE . NOo71 Secret, An Ordinance on less comprehensive lines would V preferable ioe* an Ordinance which prohibits emigration tr any foreign country until the Governor is satisfied that the Government of that country has made such laws and other legislative provisions as the Governor shall consider sufficient for the protection of the native inhabitants oi Somaliland emigrating to that country. Under the powers f Iven by such an Ordinance it would be possible for you to prohibit while present crisis lasts emigration to Italian colonies or Ethiopia, Aouid your requirements be met by such/Ordinal ce? Provisions regarding detention of ships etc* on lines of clause 7 of Order in Council), you will appreciate* may be open to serious objection and I should prefer thst Ordinance should contain no such provisions= Your telegram No,55 refers.* ' * Ordinance No.U of 188^. 1955 An Ordinance relating to the Emigration of Native Labourers from this Island under Contract of Service. (As amended by No.22 of 1384.) ( See No.1 of 1914) Preamble. Whereas it is expedient to regulate the emigration of native labourers under contract of service to labour in places without the limits of this Island: It is hereby enacted by the Governor of Ceylon, with the advice and consent of the Legislative Council thereof, as follows Short title. 1. This Ordinance may be called ‘'The Ceylon Emigration Ordinance, 1882’’, and shall come into force on the passing thereof. Power to Governor, 2. Prom and after the passing of this Ordinance the with the advice of Executive Governor may, with the advice of the Executive Council, Council, to declare emigration from time to time, by notification published in the lawful. Government Gazette, declare that the emigration of the native inhabitants of this Island shall be lawful to any Contracts with natives for performance of labour in any place to which emigration has been authorized made lawful. Such contracts to be signed before a Police Magistrate. place described in such notification, provided that every such notification shall contain also a declaration that the Governor has been duly certified that the Government of the place to which the notification refers has made such laws and other provisions as the Governor in Executive Council shall deem sufficient for the protection of the native inhabitants of Ceylon emigrating to such place . 3. From the date of any such notification contracts may be made with any native inhabitant of Ceylon for labour to be performed in any place to which emigration is authorised in the notification, and it shall be lawful to enable or assist any native inhabitant to emigrate to such place; but all contracts and engagements under such notification shall be made and signed before a Police MagistrateMagistrate, who is hereby authorised to take such signatures after reading over and explaining to the signatories the contract to he entered into by them. Contracts for It shall not be lawful for any person to make performance cf labour in any with any native inhabitant of this Island any contract for I place to which emigration has labour to be performed in any place without the limits of not been authorised unlawful. this Island to which emigration has not been declared law ful in manner aforesaid, and every person who shall make any (§1,22 of 188U) such contract, or who shall knowingly aid or abet any native inhabitant of this Island in emigrating from this Island for the purpose of being employed under contract as a labourer,/except to a place to which emigration shall have been declared lawful^ shall be guilty of an offence, and shall be liable on conviction to a fine not exceeding two hundred rupees for every native inhabitant so contracted with, aided, or abetted. Provided always that nothing in this Ordinance contained shall be taken to apply to any native seaman Exceptions. who shall of his own free will contract to navigate any vessel, or who shall embark on board such vessel in pursuance of such contract, or to any person who shall contract to serve as a menial servant only, or who shall embark as such menial servant. 16th October,18823681/35. ^ 50 PARAPHRA.SH1 Tm&amp;KGRAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Acting Resident at Aden- (Sent 3 p-m. P 14th August, 1935-) Srt(&gt; Addressed to Aden No.55. Repeated to Government of India No.2564. Please refer to my telegram N o-52 of 12th August repeated to Government of India No.2535- Reference in last x^aragraph should be to ny telegram No-47 net No-65-Mra Qians on. (V. L^cVVOirv . o ■x- i\ cs&gt;p^ uKU Vst Vo ^ -vk^ , f u; u*^-* m JUo ♦ # 7^4^ U A. [Zas**- ^ O^j TLj ^ ^v»tv^o ^ d/Tw^/tJ^J -V The Colonial Office have sent a telegram to the Acting Resident at Aden, in which I concur^telling him that the points raised in his telegram of 30th . July are under consideration and that, pending a decision, he should do what he could to stop British subjects and British protected persons leaving Aden to work with the Italians.’ Even if the Resident is right in thinking that the Indian Emigration Act cannot be applied to Arabs, the Aden authorities in the past have acted as if it could. By a species of bluff the Resident will no doubt be able to check emigration to a very great extent. The Colonial Office have, however; discussed the matter with Sir Reilly and he takes the view that it is most undesirable to distinguish between Yemeni subjects and British subjects or British protected persons. Section 31 of the Emigration Act is extremely loose. It would seem impossible to administer it if ,, ^ ^ by (^Indian parentage”^racial distinction is meant. The probability that it means 'a child of parents of Indian British nationality' is borne out by the fact that the rest of the clause deals with 'a subject of a State in India'. vY^'/4- With ti^/compliments of the Under secretary of Gutc fur the Colonies. Colonial Office, Downing Street, S.W.l.' ^ 2681/35. I / / * r a hi. 4 i 1935 ! PARAPHRASE TELEGRAM fyom the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Acting Resident at Aden* Sent 8 p.nn 12th August* 1935* S'id Addressed to Aden No*52, Repeated to Government of India No*2535* Your telegram of 30th July No.32* I appreciate legal difficulties which will be examined in consultation with Government of India, The above quoted telegram should be repeated to that Government, As a matter of administrative practice emigration from or through Aden has I understand,been controlled in the past 4 . without challenge. This control should pending decision on legal points be exercised as regards British protected persons and British subjects in the sense of my telegram of the 25th July receipt of King’s reply Yemenis v/ill be further considered.9th August, 1935. Dear Rumbold, I enclose a copy of the telegram from Aden about the recruitment of labour which I mentioned to you the other day. I p.m very sorry that I have delayed letting you see this; but I have been very tied up with other work. We shall, I imagine, be sending it to you officially, but if meanwhile you would care to discuss it with me naturally I shall be at your disposal. Yours sincerely,PARAPHRASE TELEGRAJA from the Acting Resident at Aden to the Secretary of State for tne Colonies, Dated 30th July, 1933. Received 6.5 p.m. f 30th July. l:o.32. Although Indian ijiftigration Act applies to British subjects and British protected persons it now ap!&gt;e f b fro*n sect ion 31 that strictly legally it cannot be construed to apply to Arabs and dees not In • :a&gt; oar apply to non British subjecta« I Suggest that aa it is practi daily impossible to determine conditions under which individuals are em^ arlc- ing the Government of India should be requested to H ssue orders makin ' it illegal for any British subject Br tiah protected person or non British subject being a native of .Arabia to go to Italian colonies without express pe-uii scion of the Chief Commissioner who if lie considered it c osirable for political reasons would be empowered to refuse psrraisaion. A further oO/rjmi m ication wi 1 1 be mad*3 on r» o 1 pt cf ? ' reply from King of th£ Yemen who has been addressee in the matter. Your telegram of the 25th July ^o,4C ct y? ^ In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. J 3394/1/1. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. 7tn August, 1935* Foreign Office S.W.l. Sir, With reference to your letter No* P.Z.5218/35 of the 2nd August, I am directed by Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to inform you that he concurs in the draft telegram regarding the recruitment of Indians for skilled work in Ethiopia or Italian colonies which it is proposed to address to the Government of India. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India OfficeDowning Street 2, August,1935. SECRET. Dear Walton, Your letter of the 2nd August ( P.Z.5218/35) about the Italian attempt to recruit skilled labour from India. We concur in the terms of the draft telegram which^ you propose to send. Yours sincerely,Register No. P. Z.5218/35 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Esjtter f irom Leiegram Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairm^*!^ Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee / Under Secretary Secretary of State.... / r- ’ / r. C ABYSSINIA. Request by the Italian Consuls at. Cal cutta and Bombay for permission to enlisfr Indian skilled labour . Government of India request guidance of H.M.G. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. (1) Draft telegram to Government of India approving refusal of permission (not to issue without F.O. and G.O. concurrence). (2) Draft d.o. letters to the Foreign Office and Colonial Office seeking concurrence in (1). © tj.o. to &amp;.c&gt;. c.o. 2 AUG1 n7 5 8 AUG1935 Previous Papers :■Minute Paper Department, P.Z. 5218/35 In India Office telegram No. 1685 of 31st May, the Government of India were told that the enlistment of British subjects or British Protected persons, even as non-combatants, in Italian or Ethiopian forces, is out of the question and that a request made by the Italian Consul-General for permission to recruit in India some hundreds of labourers for constructing roads ! in Italian Somaliland, should be refused. More recently the general question of the recruitment of British subjects to work as labourers in the Italian Colonies was considered in connection with the situation at Aden and, with the concurrence of the India Office, Colonial Office telegram No. 47 of B5th July was sent to the Resident at Aden. The papers on this question went to the Government of India by the air mail of 29th July and should be in the hands of the Government of India early next week. A copy of the Indian Emigration Act is flagged on the file. It introduees very rigid restrictions on emigration as defined in section 2(c) of the Act. Of the two alternative methods suggested by the Government of India by which the emigration of skilled labouf for the Italian colonies could be prevented the second seems preferable and it is suggested that, subject to the concurrence of the Foreign Office and Colonial Office, we might telegraph to the Government of India as in the attached draft. It seems unnecessary for us to propose the discussion of this point in the Abyssinia Committee.Draft Paper Department. P.Z. 5218/35 P.S. Scrivener, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.l. ^^x^P'aUa. A csu-q v© cct^tV: / SKvWf.^. I lOO'TVC P 3761 5000 5.35 2 Will you please refer to the Government of India's telegram of 30th —— ’ vP a July, No. 1894,2 copy of which went to the Foreign Office under India Office letter No. P.Z. 5218/35 of 31st July. I enclose a copy of a draft telegram which, subject to the concurrence of CglovUat « the Foreign Office^ 7 , we propose to send to the Government of India. J&amp;r &amp; 1. I should explain that^the Indian /ttU. flZTttrt-' Emigration Actjdeals separately with /emigration for the purpose of unskilled work and emigration for the purpose of skilled work igration is defined in section 2(c) of the Act as 'the departure by sea out of British India of - (1) any person who departs under an agreement to work for hire in any country beyond the limits of India, and (2) any person who is assisted to depart otherwise than by a relative if he departs for the purpose or with the intention of working for hire or engaging in agriculture in any country beyond the limits of India'. Section 10 lays down that '(1) emigration for the purpose of unskilled work shall not be lawful except to such countries and on such terms and conditions as the Governor- General in Council by notification in the Gazette of India may specify in this behalf'^ V'^(2)^ that no notification shall be made under sub-section (1) unless it has been laid in draft before both Chambers of the Indian Legislature and approTed by resolution of each chamber.® ^ Section 16 provides that whoever desires to engage or to assist any person to emigrate for the purpose of skilled work shall apply for permission 6f the local Government having jurisdiction at the port from which such person is to depart and shall give certain information^ ^Section 17 provides that on receiving an application under section 16 the local Government may, after such enquiry as it may deem necessary, grant the permission applied for on such terms emd conditions (if any) and the payments of such fees (if any) as it thinks fit or withhold such permission, and the decision of the local Government shall be final. &gt; Sk Section 21 provides that where the Governor-General in Council has reason to believe that sufficient grounds exist for prohibiting emigration of skilled labourers to any country, he may, by notification in the Gazette of India, declare that such emigration to that country shall cease to be lawful from a date specified in the notification and from that date such emigration to that country shall accordJjigjLy^cease to be l awful^j) m. JThere is a definition of skilledDraft Paper. p ^ 5218/35 Department. ^ r 2 AUG193i I enclose copy of a telegram we i 1 . G. Lee, Esq., Colonial Office, S.W.l. have received from the Government of v€*.e v V.&amp;.C. c ^\raL‘a&gt;A&lt; ) ^ SKiU&lt;&lt;^ Lc\ooa.v India,oi&gt; a fetter v/hich I have ^ Government of India telegram) of 30th July, No. 1894. ) sent to Scrivener at the Foreign Office which we would like to send to the Government of India in reply. I should be grateful if you would let me know as soon as possible whether the Colonial Office have any observations on this draft. v-oir 0 slnOd*O^Sf*3761 5000 5.35 Draft Paper Department y\ Prom Secretary of State for India. To Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department. CYPHER XXX c Your telegram of 30th July, ^ H-ncT ^ No. 1894. It has been decided that it is highly undesirable at the present juncture that British subjects or British protected persons should be employed in Ethiopia or Italian colonies either in a civil capacity ^e.g. as labourers)or with military forceslvide papers regarding recruitment at Aden forwarded by the air mail of 29 th Jul: I therefore agree that request of Italian Consuls should be refused^-an4 L-, I «' ^ oonoider- that course (b) in your telegram is preferable. date xxx i£Lt ‘ fa Of WORDS VEMO£R 8 INITIALSFRB/AW. DBCYPHBR OF TSLBGRAM . From (COPIBS CIRCULATED) Dated Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India* Simla, 30th July, 1935* Received 30th July, 1935, 6,45'p*m. X 1894, (o. Your telegram 1605, May 31et r Italian Consuls, Calcutta and Bombay, now state that they wish to enlist Indian skilled labour. Section 10, Emigration Aot r doea not afford cover for refusal to permit emigration of skilled labour, but it would be possible either - (a) to issue notification, under Section 21, prohibiting such emigration to Italian Somaliland or, preferably, both Italian Somaliland and Abyssinia,, on the ground that state of tension exists between Italy and Abyssinia or ~ (b) to refer Consuls to the Local Governments concerned (who would be advised to refuse permission) under Section 17 which gives such governments discretion to grant or refuse applications for enlisting skilled labour. Course (b) has the advantage of being, in the circumstances, less public refusal than the issue of notification would be in spite of its apparent impartiality* ' We must again request guidance of Hie Majeety• e Government in view of the suggeetion to include Abyssinia in the notification*4m], B \€ Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following number quoted :— /•v Letter Sir, ■ 5116 \ Reference to previous correspondence jl° n w the Colonial Office of the - pj/ 3s Dooming Street, I am directed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to transmit to you f Ci^ cop of the paperj noted below, on the subject of ^ ^ \ t - £ l &lt;, Sir, Your most obedient servant, The Under Secretary of State, J. L. MAFFEY. Office Date. Description. J $ ffi+Ay it it i. * ♦ It* t „ v„, H-l li U* &lt;kc-(z^&gt; VhCiMjL^ No - ^ Copffralso sent to\ ($&gt; * i 46011 / 2 / 35 , 5116 i PARAPHRASE TELEGRAM from the Secretary of -State for the .... Colonies to the Officers Administering the Governments of (1) . (2) U) T4) Malta^ Mauritius, Seychelles, Tanganyika Territory, High (5) Commissioner for the Malay States and the Officer • • ( 6 ) Administering the Government of Hong Kongo Sent 9*0 pcffic 25th July, 1935c Ho«6$ Secret, 78 5fe 139 57 115 It is desirable that you should knoi t ln case Italian Authorities approach you, that H.Mo Government regard it as highly undesirable that British subjects or British protected persons should be employed in Italian colonies or Ethiopia t either in a civil capacity (e,g, as labourers) or with military forces, and that they are anxious that such employment should be prevented» If you are approached in the matter I should be grateful if you liould follow the above policy and report to me, (To 6 only). It is possible fully to justify the prohibition in interests of persons concerned whose protection is responsibility of government. Different considerations are raised by recruitment of aliens but reference should be made to me before any application for recruiting Chinese is entertainedrmmu mmmmmmmmmm ♦ MS ' ~y 46011/2/55 5! 16 I { 19 ; 1 c* -w&gt; D PARAPHRA8K TEIiEORAI^ from the Secretary^ol 4 iHc3t#--4 , o&gt;r the Colonies to the Acting Resident at Aden, Cent 9 0 S5 p,m, 25th July, 1935. riP ORTAirc Ho. 4?. Secrete, Your telegram No.27. It lias heen decided that it is highly undesirable at the present .juncture that British subjects or British protected persons should be employed in Ethiopia or Italian colonies either in a civil capacity (e.g. as labourers) or with military forces, and that steps should be taken as a matter of policy tc prenrent, such employment if at possible. I assume that having regard to terms of the Indian Emigration Act there will be no difficulty in preventing emigration from Aden, and I shtolel be grateful if you ijfould take the necessary measures. I am aware that the Ret might not provide an adequate legal basis for preventing oersons seeking employment who are neither under agreement nor in receipt of assistance from departing j x A om Aden, in view of the definition of emigration. Please report whether you think it necessary that further powers should be ta.K.en to guard against this possibility. It is possible fully to justify the prohibition in interests of oersons concerned for whose protection Government is responsible. Different considerations are raised by recruitment through Aden of non-British subjects, and it is thought that it would be advantageous if the views of the King of Yemen regarding the recruitment of his subjects for service in Ethiopia or the Italian Colonies could be ascertained before any decision is taken in regard to them, I should be grat&lt;£ul ifif you li/rold arrange to ascertain his views and report them to me provided that you see no objection. In approaching him you shoul-d make it clear however that it is for His Majesty* s G-ovornment to make a decision regarding recruitment through .Aden or emoarkation at that port c It would be understood meanwhile that no facilities would be provided at Aden for recruitment of non-British subjects for service in Italian Colonies or Ethiopia but that, provided that their departure involves no breach of .the Indian Immigration Act, i,e* provided that they depart without agreement to work for hire etc, or withou* assistance, steps need not he taken to prevent non--' British sub.1ec.ts from proceeding to Ethiopia or Italian Colonies if they wish to do so in order to take up employment 0© 5 ! 1 6 Oolonlos to the At&gt;aliai8taring the Govermnent of Cyprus e Your tale gram Ho. 51. It Jias decided that it it? highly imdesirable at the present Juncture that British subjects or British protected persons should be employed in Ethiopia or Ita3.ian Colonies, either in a civil capacity e.g. as labourers or with military forces, and that steps should be token as a matter of policy to prevent such employment. I should therefore be grateful you v.ould &amp;&amp;ke the necessary arrangements, (jither by Sent 7 p.EU, 25th July 1955. IMPORT AS - ? . No. 64. Secret withiioldlng pasaporte or other means. Please Inform me of any developments.46011/2/35. EAHAPHHAS3 T'SL’SGRAM from the Soorotnry of Otato for the CoXonles to the Governor of Somaliland* No«65 Secrete l/Iy telegram No.31, Decision has heon reached that objection to British subjects or protected person 3 being enlisted with either Italian or Ethiopian military forces applies equally to employment as labourers etc* in a civil capacity and that steps should bo taken to prevent such employment. Should bo grateful if you Would take nooeesrry measurea. inform me whether there is any truth in the following Gtatomonts :* (a) In report of the Journey which ho recently made across Ethiopia, Dunlop stated that Ethiopian Government had enrolled 60 drivers (mostly Somalis) to drive the Chevrolet tractors which they recently bought and that an order was expected to enrol more Somali drivers: (b) It is alleged by Italian iimbassy that British Somali tribesmen are being recruited, presumably for LUlitary Service, by JSthiopian Consul at Jibuti, and that 50 have so ' fer been enlisted. I should be glad in this connection if you &amp;©uld(J 2598/1/1) HT\^96. (477/11/35). The High Comlssioner for Egypt presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith copies of the under-mentioned paper# CAIRO* June 19» 1935# hescription of Snelosure. Name and Date* Subject. FROM: Khartoum Secretariat* Entry of Sudanese labour No# C*S*/P#&amp; P.5.A#4 of into Eidtrea# June 15th 1936.1 ^ / SUX1AB OOVE.iFaTOT. CIV l SKCHETARY'S DEPARTMENT. C.3.P.&amp; P. 5.A.4. S* 0 *- S-MA —T Jl-' £ ,0 0 KHARTOUJ4, w- : * oo J\me 15th, 1935* Dear Chancery, I encloae for youx Information paraphrases of telegrams exchanged between Sir Sidney Barton, Addle Ababa and Oovemox'-General, Khartoum, on the subject of the entry into Sritrea of Sudanese for service with the Italians. Yours ever, SECRETARIAT.A Proa:- Sir Sidney Barton, Addis Ababa To:- Governor -General, Kliartoim* — 10th , ime&gt; 1:35. I hare been aaiced by the Minister for Foreign Affairs to enquire into the question of the alleged entry into 1‘Jritrea of large numbers of Sudanese for service with the Italians* The Minister is inclined to coiapax*© the attitudes of the Egyptian and Sudan Go/eimients, the former of which, he points out, has already taken steps to prohibit the recruitment and export of Egyptian labour, whereas the latter appears to allow it* I should be grateful if you would give me a short exposition of your attitude*£ OQ Mjsmm Promt- Oovomor-Ganeral, Khartoum. To:- 8ir Sidney Baz*ton, Addia Ababa. M* 71 of June lfith t i^r. ,ver since local contractors couimenced to addi'ess applications to us for pe 'mission to recruit uns'cilled Sudaiiese labour for export to 2ritr*a # we have consistently tumed them down, not only in the interests of our own labour market;, here the supply is hardly adequate for our own requirements, but also on the recoriuend&amp;tion of our medical department who are moat averse to expcaing our Sudanese to infection from tuberculosis or kale az&amp;r and who think, moreover, tnat Sudanese are generally incapable of standing up to the climate of the Hritrean highlands. We have, on the other hand, permitted the ojiport of small prrtles of mechanics snd artisans, particularly in those trades of which we heve a surplus. Artisans, moreover, on account of their higher standard of living and the special nature of their work, are less exposed to and leso likely to succumb t j infection. cannot prevent Individual Sudanese from finding their own way to 3ritre* to sell their labour, though we do what wv con to discourage them for the above reasons.„-3j rwc^***^ r r •• OP 5 D ‘ &lt;J .J NO 1/ J. 3T ul BUTIQN (J2598/1/1) telegram to Sir M. Lampson (Cairo) Foreign Office, 24th July 1955, 6,30 p.m. Ko. 241. Your despatch Ko. 696 (of June 19th: recruitment of Sudanese labourers for service in Sritroa), Conclusion has been reached that employment of British subjects or British protected persons as labourers in Italian colonies or in Abyssinia is highly undesirable at present juncture and that as a matter of policy it should be prevented so far as possible. Flea.se inform Sudan government accordingly.imiA ofiics:, miTmALL, s.w.i. £4tli July, 1935. Lear Janes, I enclose a copy of a letter which I have sent to Thompson at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely, N S. I* Jamies, Esq., Colonial Office, / v /Department. S0« Secret* Your telegram No. 27. Jonolucion ha© been reached that onploymont ol hritieh oubjeote or British protooted pereone for ©eirvioe ao labourer© in Italian ooloaieo or in Kthiopia 1© highly undo air able at preoent juncture and that ae a matter ol policy it Ghould be prevento . I aacurao that nc difficulty would, bo lound in do in, tliic having regard to tonao of tho Indian Inigration Act, and I should bo glad ii you would xurooeed acooixiingly. I an aware that in view ol the definition ol emigration in the Act it might not provide an adequate legal basis for preventing departure from Aden of v\ t vd tr peroono seeking ea^iloyiDent who aro not V'OC under agreement or in receipt of aesistanoe. Pleaeo report whether you consider it neooeoary to take further powers to guard against this possibility. prohibition can fully bo Justified in interests of persons concerned whoso proteotlon is responsibility of Government. recruitment of non-hritlsh oubjooti through Aden raises different considerations and it is thought that before any decision is taken in regard to then it would bo advantageous to 4 riDepartment Draft Paper. aooertain tho viev/o ol the of Yonon as ro^^rdo 2 'ooruitoont of hie oubjoote for oorvico in Italian colonies or Ethiopia* Provided that you ooo no objection should bo Glad if you oould arrange for hio vier/o to be aooertained and reported to oe* Your approach should however oak© it clear that decioion lies with H*M.G. as regards recruitoent through Aden. Hoanwhilo it would bo understood that nothing in the nature of faoilitioo for reoruitnent of non-British subjects for servico in Ethiopia or Italian colonies would be provided at Aden but non-Britiah subjects wishing to proceed to Italian colonies or Ethiopi to tako up eoployncnt neod not be prevented from doing so provided that no breach of the Indian liaigration Act is involved, i.o. provided that thoy depart without assistance or agreement to work for hire etc.c. o. 46011/2/35. Somaliland. Mr ' Lee 22/7/35. Mr. Cowell 23. Mr. £ Sir C. Parkinson. 23/?/35 . Sir G. Tomlinson. Sir C. Bottomley. Sir J. Shuckburgh. X Permt. U.S. of S. Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State. No. Secret. (78074/35 No.17) Your telegram No. 27. Conclusion has 'been reached that recrnritny tt of British subjects or British protected persons DRAFT. TELEGRAM (CYPHER) f ‘ or service as labourers in Italian IMPORTANT. RESIDENT, ADEN. colonies or in Ethiopia is highly undesirable at present juncture and that litr' as a matter of policy s^jj^h-r-ecruLfaj^ent should be prevented. I assume that no difficulty would be found in doing this, P.0, concur / having regard to terms of the Indian Emigration Act, and I should be glad if you would proceed accordingly. ? 1.0. concurrence to be obtained. ^ . . i A J ft' ^ ^ ^ ! Prohibition can fully he j, i h~*- fiustified in interests of persons FURTHER ACTION. Copies to P.0. T -n TToT L * p ' '■'V Copy to go on 78074/35. :oncerned whose protection is responsibility of Government. Recruitment of non-British subjects through Aden raises different considerationsconsiderations and it is thought that before any decision is taken ./it would be advantageous to ascertain the views of the King of Yemen as regards recruitment of his subjects for service in Italian colonies or Ethiopia. Provided that you see no objection should be glad if you could arrange for his views to be ascertained and reported to me.^ r Meanwhile it would be understood that nothing _/ r* a. _ S 6. Uo» A&gt; eo-tr c Ce eA oir SlLste rtBKT ti \^y\C v in the nature of facilities for recruitment of t^C\ f • sc non-British subjects for service in Ethiopia or Italian colonies would be provided at Aden* . * / out non-British subjects wishing to proceed to Italian colonies or Ethiopia to take up employment need not be prevented from doing tbtS ^ Lsi/W&gt;+ /r ' SO. trw. ^ryw*v&gt;0 a ^—/ c L^, 4 ^ACT No. EY OF 1874. Passed by the Governor General op India in Council. (Received the aKX&amp;nt of the Governor General on the 24^ February 1874/ An Act to control recruiting in British India for the service of Foreign States. W/HEREAS it is expedient that the Governor Gen- Preamble. ’ ’ eral in Council should exercise full control over recruiting in British India for the service of Foreign States ; It is hereby enacted as follows :— 1. This Act may be called “ The Foreign Becruit- short title, ing Act, 1871” : It extends to the whole of British India ; Local extent. And it shall come into force on the passing thereof. Commence- ment. 2. In this Act— “ Foreign State” includes any person or persons exercising or assuming to exercise the powers of Gov ernment in or over any country, colony, province, or people beyond the limits of British India. 3. If any person is, within the limits of British India, obtaining or attempting to obtain recruits for the service of any Foreign State in any capacity, the Governor General in Council may, by order in writing signed by a Secretary to the Government of India, either prohibit such person from so doing, oi ^ permit him to do so subject to any conditions which the Governor General in Council thinks fit to impose. 4. The Governor General in Council may from time to time, by general order notified in the Gazette of India, either prohibit recruiting for the service of any Foreign State, or impose upon such recruiting any conditions which he thinks fit. 5. The [Price one anna and three pies^ Interpreta tion-clause. “ Foreign State.” Power to prohibit or permit re cruiting. Power to impose con ditions. —Foreign Recruiting, [act iv, 1874.] Office Supdt. Govt. Friutiug.—No. 358 L, D.—27-2-74.—2,900. Power to rescind or vary orders. Oflences. Place of trial. 5. The Governor General in Council may rescind or vary any order made under this Act in such man ner as he thinks fit. 6 . Whoever, in violation of the prohibition of the Governor General in Council, or of any condition subject to which permission to recruit may have been accorded, (a) induces or attempts to induce any person to accept or agree to accept or to proceed to any place with a view to obtaining any com mission or employment in the service of any Foreign State, or {b) knowingly aids in the engagement of any person so induced, by forwarding or conveying him or by advancing money or in any other way whatever, shall he liable to imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years, or to fine to such amount as the Court thinks fit, or to both. 7. Any offence against this Act may he enquired into and tried, as well in any district in which the person accused may he found, as in any district in which it might be enquired into and tried under the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure.(&gt;2-. U-kOfY Le,p;al A; Please see Foreign Office letter of 11th June and telegram from the Acting Resident at Aden of 26th June. I should he grateful if you could say v/hether the Indian Emigration Act forhids the emigration of individuals from the port of Aden to Eritrea to work as labourers there and whether it also forhids such emigration through the port of Aden hy subjects of the Imam of the Yemen. Please also see Aden telegram of 11th September 1925&gt; flagged in the bound volume# the proposals in v/hich were approved in Colonial Office Despatch oj' 1st October, 1925« Is the arrangement for the annual recruitment from Aden of 500 individuals for service in the Italian Colonial Forces a breach of the Indian Emigration Act? Is there any foreign enlistment legislation Italian Military Forces. *51* oiU a\v»u&gt;sv ee\Vcu.A.U^ eA- v^q. UYjo^cs &lt;0 Shou\a. . o\-A a 0r6Tec VotgI^ JU'o* ^ o\- A&lt;^ 0vO ecVorcAf iGU'o’ coouid labourers^in Eritrea^ai»e non-combatant members of the \'ec&gt;ruJbvvvevA.v* (Dc v^usv- ^ ^ V'e^sovv l'Cr'b€ ^ov € cjs a&gt; vv . v &lt;g . VvV- “Vj.Colonial Office, Downing Street,S.W.1.&gt; ($ July,1935 Dear Rumbold, This is to confirm what I recently told you on the telephone, viz# that the meeting regarding the recruitment of Arab labourers for Eritrea through Aden has been fixed for Monday the 22nd July at 11.30 in the Dominions Office Conference Room. Yours sincerely.EXTRACT PROM PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES HOUSE OP LORDS, MONDAY, 15th JULY 1935. THE ADEN PROTECTORATE. x x x x The noble Lord made no reference to the crisis hut I think he would like some information about that. LORD LAMINGTON: I gave notice of that to the noble Earl, although I forgot to mention it when I was speaking. THE EARL OP PLYMOUTH: I noticed that the noble Lord did not mention that matter but I know he would like some information on the subject. I am afraid I am not in a position to give very much. As far as we are able to judge the Abyssinian crisis has not reacted much upon the position in Aden. There was a question of recruitment which was raised. In the past there has been in operation a system, which has lasted for many years, whereby the Italians were permitted to recruit a certain number of natives from certain parts of the Aden Protectorate and also Yemenis through Aden for service with the Italian Forces in Eritrea and Italian Somaliland. Some months ago the Italians made a request for permission to recruit in excess of the numbers formerly permitted, but in view of the position between Abyssinia and Italy it was decided that this request could not be acceded to. Beyond this, as I have said, as far as we are able to judge we do not think that the crisis in that part of the world has reacted in any way upon Aden affairs.4^® 1 Communications on this subject ‘should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following Number quoted: 46011/2/35. sir, 4697 A/4 ^4 , • (\/- Doivninq Street. . . o g July*$i*935&lt; IMPORTANT. VM 76 ■ I am directed by Mr. Secretary MacDonald to refer to the letter from this Department of the 26th June, numbered as above, regarding the recruitment of labourers through the port of Aden for employment in Eritrea, and to transmit to you to be laid before the Marquis of Zetland a copy of a telegram from the Acting Resident at Aden on this subject. 2. Mr. MacDonald suggests that the question, of what reply should be returned to the Acting Resident’s telegram should be considered at a meeting attended by representatives of the Foreign office, India Office, and Colonial Office, and he requests that, unless the Marquis of Zetland sees any objection, a representative of the India Office may be nominated to attend such a meeting to be held at an early convenient date. A DOPV SE'lT BY MAIL THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE.——&gt;11 11 \iJt A similar letter is teing addressed to the Foreign Office. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant,CYPHER TELEGRAM from the Acting Resident at Aden to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Dated 26th June. Received 11.7 p.m. 2?th June, 1935. No.27. Your telegram No.45 of the 25th of June and telegram of 11th March. No regular application has been received for permits for persons other than British subjects or British protected persons to leave Aden for employment as labourers in Eritrea. Aden is not a port for emigration for skilled or unskilled labohta ? under Indian Emigration Act(s) and strict compliance with Act would close emigration for all labour though an exception is made in cases of Italian colonies for whom labout is permitted to be recruited subject to certain conditions one of which is that it is necessary for labourers recruitedfor Italian colonies to be produced before police authorities for identification before embarking. These conditions were communicated to the Italian Consul on the 3rd March 1929 and again on the 11th of October 1934. Occasions have recently occurred in which the police have become aware of clandestine recruiting of persons ostensibly as labourers ? in Italian (Colonies) In view of your orders not to permit recruiting for Italian colonial forces through Aden I considered that I was justified in refusing permission in all cases in which it was not clear to me that individuals were being enlisted as bone fide labourers. Recruiting of Yemenis for Italian colony of Eritrea is more direct from Hodeidah and other Yemen ports than it is through Aden. I have received no representations from the Italian Consul on this subject. I shall be glad of definite instructions as to recruiting cof labourers for Italian, colonies for future guidance.X UMMMi ■: ' 1a. B i) Communications on this subject shoul^ be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following number quoted :— Refereiick to previous correspondence 4/' Letter the Lolommt Office of the // from Sir, ■ , n Downing Street, 2,6 /*— I am directed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to transmit to you fir &lt;3/ /£-«- S''C++ (^ry */ fry cop u^&gt; of the paperi noted below, on the subject of tec+u of ^ A* C/~* tz, I am. Sir, Your most obedient servant. The Under Secretary of State, Office J. L. MAFFEY. Date. of b~A y j/i Description. SVo . /Kx- 4 c C 'Y COPY SENT B jjk^f ■.fg S JUN 1935 Copy also sent to (R2697) Wt 47527/3095 5,000 9/33 H&amp;Sp Gp 112jr- ^ 46011/2/35* CYPHER TSLKGRAM from the Secretary the Acting Resident at Aden, Sent p.m, 85th June» 1935, NOo45 a Italian Kmbassy hava complained to Foreign Africa that according to reoort from Italian consul at Aden non-Britiah natives are Paing prohihited by authoritioa in port of Aden from embarking either on native canoes or on mail steamers in order to proceed to Krltrea to work as labourers, Italian Embassy added that these natives had been regularly furnished by Italian consulate with official documents for that purpaia. Have you actually received requests for permits for persons other than British subjects or British protected persons to leave Aden for employment as labourers in Eritrea and If so what action hfcve you taken ? L of State for the ColonlaaK*-'[ © © r 'V Mr. Walton^ Please see Foreign Office letter* The Colonial Office instructions to the Resident at Aden at P. Z. 1785/35» only refer to the enlistment of X British Somalis in the Italian or Ethiopian forces# The Foreign Office, in their letter at P. Z. 1739/35* laid o*' down that the recruitment of/British protected persons for service with either the Italian or Ethiopian forces, or the recruitment of foreign subjects for such service through British territory, i. e# Aden, should, if possible, be prevented# Probably a copy of this letter was forwarded to the Resident and he has acted upon it. Actually, both the instructions and the letter refer only to combatants, but the view has since been taken (see Minute at P.Z# 3359/35) that it is equally undesirable that British subjects should be enlisted even as non-combatants in either the Italian or Ethiopian forces# The Foreign Office concur in this view (see their letter at P.Z.3745/35)• The question of upholding and justifying the action of the Aden authorities can, however, wait till we obtain further information as to what exactly has happened# I have talked to Mr. Blaxter of the Colonial Office, and he agrees that it would be better for us to telegraph to the Resident, as the Italian enquiry refers specifically to the Port of Aden. The Colonial Office have been sent a copy of the Foreign Office letter below and they are looking up some papers about An Italian request to enlist labourers from Ceylon# I understand that this request was refused, andaay further communication subject please quote n° J 2241/1/1 and address— not to any person by name but to - The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. i» Sir, I am directed *by Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to invite reference to the letter from this department J 2029/1/1 of 29th May and connected correspondence regarding the recruitment of natives for service in the Italian (or Ethiopian) forces, and to state that on June 4th the First Secretary to the Italian Embassy called at this department to complain that, according to a report from the Italian Consul in Aden, non-British natives were being prohibited by the authorities at that port from embarking 'either on native canoes or on mail steamers' in order to proceed to Eritrea to work as labourers. X v-e Monsieur Fracassi added that these natives had been regularly furnished by the Italian Consulate with official documents for that purpose. 2. I am to enquire what reply should in the opinion of the Secretary of State for India be returned to the above-mentioned informal enquiry on the part of the Italian Embassy. I am, ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 2 5 2 0JUN 1935 FBOM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA 0,-FICE Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, '■'5 India Officea'- &gt;LtO In any ‘further communication on this subject please quote N °'J 2029/1/1 and address— not to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of Stah',' Foreign Office, Ijondon, S.W.l. IMMEDIATE Sir, I * . X / / c r * * v&gt; Foreign Office. S.W. 1. 29th May, 1935. I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to acknowledge receipt of your letter P.Z.3359/35 of 24th May regarding tne proposed recruitment of Indian labourers for road- building in Italian Somaliland, and in reply to state that he agrees that the request made in this connexion by the Italian Consul General in Calcutta should be refused. 2. I am to add that the Secretary of State concurs in the terms of the telegram which it is proposed to address to the Government of India on tne subject. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,(5&gt; Letter SECRET. Y POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Telegram from Dated Rec. 19 Formally acknowledged To Ohairmaji / Under Secretary ... Secretary of State. Committee Under Secretary... Secretary of State.. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. U&gt;. r. lc : y/r ^ M, ETHIOPIA : Renuest by Italian Consul-General, Calcutta, for permission to enrol labourers in India for the construction of roads in Italian Somaliland. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letter to F.O., forwarding and asking concurrence in Dr a f t Jram I o~~G. of I. agreeing that such recruitment is out of the question. 1 Previous Papers 2 4 MAY 19M 1140 1000 8.32The present request is superficially different froir that made at Aden, since it is not for enrolment in the Italian colonial forces but for the recruitment of labour for road construction in Italian Somaliland. But of course the labourers would in effect be non-combatant members of the Italian forces. Section 10 of the Indian Emigration Act seems to give good cover for the refusal which the G. of I. must certainly, on one ground or another, give to the request. ~L h^ U ^ ^ ?■&lt;]. O 1 . ) K+J tMf+s y\&gt; r ■ fa J ■ft''' —~ r^mrz-y- Draft Paper. 0 1 u.s.s., ? . 0 . 'b v Dated 15th May. / . I ^ ^C»-v Department. MAY 1935 Sir, With reference to yoar letter of 27th March, 1935, No. J 1138/1/1, and connected correspondence relative to the recraitment of British sabjects and protected persons* for service with Italian and Ethiopian forces, I am directed by the S. of S. for I. to enclose, for the information of the S. of S. for F. A., copy of a telegram from the G. of I. reporting a request of the Italian Consul-General at Calcutta for permission to enrol labourers for the construction of roads m Italian Somaliland. Secy. Sir Samuel Hoare presumes ~tha^this’r^quest should be refuse^ I am to enquire whether Secy. Sir John Simon concurs in this view, and am to enclose ar draft of a telegram which, subject to his concurrence, it is proposed to address to the G. of 1. I am to explain that Section 10 of the Indian Emigration Act , which is referred to, provides that emigration from British India for the purpose of unskilled work shall not be lawful except £e4' such countries and on such terns and conditions as may be specified by the G. of I. by notification, which must be laid in draft before both Chambers/•— . — Chambers of the Indian Legislature and approved by a resolution of each Chambe r. (MU Jl, a WALlViLChambers of the Indian Legislat are and approved by a resolution of each Chamber. *{COPIES CIBCl L ATiiD) Oo^uiTtment ox India, foreign and Political department, to Secretary of State for India* B_A_4 o Dated Simla« 15th hay, 1935 deceived 15th May' 1935, 8-15 p,Hu I2:(4 t Addressed to Becretery of State for India; repeated to Government of Bengal. Following from Italian Consulate«General to Bengal Goveniment; repeated entrol here some hundreds labourers,, preferably Muhammadans, for constructing roads in Italian Somaliland ask if such enrolment possible and, eventually (sic) urgent and telegraph reply, fends, 8= We presume that, apart from all other considerations, enlistment at present juncture of British subjects of {sic, ? or) British protected persons even aa non -combatants, in Italian or Ethiopian forces is out of the question, vide Foreign Office telegram Id'i of .. to Government oi Indite Begins * My Government wishing particulars and conditions. Please consider this March 11th to Home Please confirm,.ACT No. YII OF 1922. [Passed by the Indian Legislature.] [Received the assent of the Governor General on the 5th March, 1922.) An Act to amend the law relating to emigra tion. TX 7 HERE AS it is expedient to amend the law VV relating to emigration; It is hereby enacted as follows:— CHAPTER I. Preliminary. 1. (f) This Act may be called the Indian Emigra- Short title tion Act, 1922. and cite,,t. ( 2 ) It extends to the whole of British India. 2- {1) In this Act, unless there is anything re- Definitions, pngnant in the subject or context,— (ft) “dependent” means any woman or child who is related to an emigrant and any aged or incapacitated relative of an emi grant ; {b) “ emigrant ” means any person who emi grates or has emigrated or who has been registered as an emigrant under this Act, and includes any dependent of an emi grant, but does not include— (i) any person emigrating to a country in which he has resided for not less than five years or the wife or child of such person, or (ii) the l l Price four\anna8i]Indian Emigration. [ act vn (ii) the wife or child of any jierson who has lawfully emigrated when such wife or child departs for the purpose of joining such person ; (&lt;?) “emigrate” and “emigration” mean the departure by sea out of British India of— (i) any person w r ho departs under an agree ment to work for hire in any country beyond the limits of India, and (ii) any person who is assisted to depart, other wise than by a relative, if he departs, for the purpose or with the intention of working for hire or engaging in agriculture in any country beyond the limits of India; (d) “ prescribe ” means to prescribe by rules made under this Act; (e) “ work,” with its grammatical variations, means skilled or unskilled work ; (/) “ skilled work ” means— (?') working as an artisan ; or (ii) working as a clerk or shop assistant; or (Hi) working for the purpose of any exhibi tion or entertainment; or (iv) service in any restaurant, tea-house, or other place of public resort; or (v) domestic service ; or (vi) any other occupation which the Governor (g) “unskilled work ” includes engaging in agri- (2) In case of any doubt or dispute arising other wise than in the course of any legal proceedings, [as to [whether— (a) any person is an emigrant, ®or General in Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, declare to be skilled work ; culture. 2 (b) any« OF 1922.] Indian Emigration. (b) any work is skilled or unskilled, or (c) any person has been assisted otherwise than by a relative, within the meaning of this Act, the question shall be determined by such person and in such manner as the Local Government may prescribe, and such determination shall be final. CHAPTER II. Pkotectors of Emigrants and Medical Inspec tors. 3. (I) Subject to the control of the Governor Appointment General in Council, the Local Government may^^J^J® appoint a person to be the Protector of Emigrants for any port situate within the territories adminis tered by it from which emigration is lawful. (2) The Local Government may define the area to which the authority of a Protector of Emigrants so appointed shall extend. (3) Eve y Protector of Emigrants shall be a public xl v of i860, servant within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code. 4. Every Protector of Emigrants, in addition to the special duties assigned to him by or under this Act, shall— (a) protect and aid with his advice all emi grants ; (b) cause, so far as he can, all the provisions of this Act and of the rules made_thereunder to be complied with ; (c) inspect, at the time of arrival, to such extent and in such manner as the Local Govern ment may prescribe, vessels bringing return emigrants to the port for which he is Protector ; (d) inquire into the treatment received hy return emigrants both during the period of their residence in the country to wTiich they emigrated a /Indian Emigration. [act vli CHAPTER III I emigrated, and also during the return voyage, arid report thereon to the Local Government ; (e) aid and advise return emigrants so far as he reasonably can; and (/') being satisfied that any person intcndin°* to depart by sea out of British India, comes within one of the classes expressly excluded tiom the definition of emigrant in section 2, furnish such person with a certificate to the effect that such person is not an emigrant for the purpose of this Act. power to 5- (I) In any specified area where there is not a sonstoexer- P^tector of Emigrants, the Local Government, sub* cise functions ]ect to the control of the Governor General in Council rappoint any person to perform all or any of the duties of a Protector of Emigrants under this Act. {2) Every person so appointed shall be a public servant within the meaning of the Indian Penal xlv of i 860 . Appointment of Medical Inspectors. Agents in foreign countries. 6* (/) Local Government may appoint one or more Medical Inspectors of Emigrants at any port from which emigration is lawful or at anv other place, and, where more than one are appointed, mav apportion their respective duties. (5) Every Medical Inspector of Emigrants shall be a public servant within the meaning of the Indian Penai Code. 7. The Governor General in Council may, for the purpose of safeguarding the interests of emigrants in any place outside British India, appoint persons to be agents in such places, and may define their powers Advisory Committees. o. ine -Liocai Government may, for the purpose of assisting any Protector of Emigrants appointed by it or any person appointed by it under section 5, constitute an Advisory Committee in such manner as it may think fit, and may prescribe the procedure to )e followed and the functions to be performed by such committee. •'of 1922.] Indian Emigration. 5 CHAPTER III. Emigration for the Purpose of Unskilled W ORK. 9 . (i) Emigration, for the purpose of unskilled work, shall not be lawful except from the ports oitionofun- Calcutta, Aladras, Bombay, Karachi, Negapatam, ^ Tuticorin and Uhanushkodi, and from such other i aw fui. ports as the Go'vernor General in Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, declare to be ports from which such emigration is lawful. (2) The Local Government may, by notification in the local official Gazette, fix for the purposes of this Act the limits of any port from which such emigration is lawful. 10 (I) Emigration, for the purpose of unskilled countries to work, shall not be lawful except to such countries a ‘ and on such terms and conditions as the Governor General in Council, by notification in the Gazette of ]awfnL India, may specify in this behalf. (£) jKo notification shall be made under sub-section (i) unless it has been laid in draft before both Chambers of the Indian Legislature and has been approved by a resolution of each Chamber, either without modification or addition, or with modifications and additions to which both Chambers agree, but, upon such approval being given, the notification may be issued in the form in which it has been so approved. ll. (I) Where the Governor General in Councilp 0 wer t 0 has reason to believe that in any country to which^“* oncf emigration for the purpose of unskilled work is lawful unskilled iilague or any other epidemic disease dangerous to' or ' crs - human life has broken out, and that emigrants il allowed to emigrate to that country w^ould be exposed to serious risk to liie on arrival there, he may, y notification in the Gazette of India, declare that emigration to that country for the purpose of unskill ed work shall cease to be lawful. {2) Where a Local Government lias reason to believe that such a state of affairs as is desciibed in sub-sectionIndian Emigration. [ act vii 6 CHAPTER IV Revocation prohibition. Powers of Governor General in Council to prohibit emigration to specified country. Saving. sub-section (1) exists in any country to which emigra tion for the purpose of unskilled work is lawful” it may, by notification in the local official Gazette, declare that emigration to that country for the purpose of unskilled work from any port in the territories administered by it shall cease to be lawful pending a reference to the Governor General in Council. (5) The Local Government publishing a notifica tion under sub-section (2) shall forthwith report such notification with the reasons for it to the Governor General in Council, who shall thereupon publish a notification in the Gazette of India confirming or cancelling the notification published by the Local Government. ,f 12. here the Governor General in Council is satisfied that the ground on which a notification under sub-section (2) of section 11, or a notification under sub-section (d) of section 11 confirming a notification of a Local Government has been made with respect to any country, has ceased to exist, he may, by notification in the Gazette of India, declare that emigration to that country for the purpose of unskill ed work shall again be lawful from a date to be specified in the notification. 13- (i) The Governor General in Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, prohibit, from a date, and for reasons, to be specified in the notifica tion, all persons or any specified class of persons from emigrating to any specified country from the territories under the administration of any Local Government or any specified part thereof, for the purpose of unskilled work. (2) Every notification issued under this section shall be laid before both Chambers of the Indian Legislature as soon as may be after it is made. 14- A notification under section 10, section 11, section 12 or section 13 shall not affect any act done, offence committed, or legal proceedings commenced before the date on which such notification takes effect.of 1922.] j Indian Emigration, CHAPTER IV. Emigration for the Purpose of Skilled Work. 15- Emigration, for the purpose of skilled work, shall not be lawful except from a port from which emigration for the purpose of unskilled work is lawful and from such other ports as the Goyernor General in Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, specify in this behalf. 16- (I) Whoever desires to engage, or to assist, any person to emigrate for the purpose of skilled work shall apply for the permission of the Local Government having jurisdiction at the port from which such person is to depart, and shall state in his application— (a) the number of persons whom he proposes so to engage or assist; {b) the place beyond the limits of India to which each such person and his dependents are to proceed; {c) the accommodation to be provided for each such person and his dependents until their departure out of India and during the voyage. (2) TV hoever desires to engage any person for the purpose described in sub-section (1) shall, in addition to the information which he is required by that sub section to supply in his application, further state therein— {a) the provision to be made for the health and well-being oi such person and his depend ents during the period of the proposed engagement and for their repatriation at the end of such period ; (b) the terms of the agreement under which such person is to be engaged ; (&lt;?) the security in British India which he pro poses to furnish for the due observance of such 7 Ports from which emigra tion of skilled workers is lawful. Emigration of skilled workers.Indian Emigration. [-ACT YII 8 Applications how to be disposed of. Appearance of engaged persons before, and registra tion of names by, Protector of Emigrants. Provisions as to security. such agreement anti for the proper treat ment of the person to he engaged and his dependents. 17. On receiving an application under section 16, the Loca] Government may, after such inquiry as it may deem necessary, grant the permission applied for on such terms and conditions (if any) and on payment of such fees (if any) as it thinks fit, or withhold such permission, and the decision of the Local Government shall be final. 18- (1) Before any person departs from British India in accordance with permission granted under section 17, the person by whom he has been engaged or assisted shall appear in person or by his duly authorised agent before the Protector of Emigrants at the port of embarkation with such first-mentioned person and with any persons intending to accompany him as his dependents. (3) If it appears to the Protector of Emigrants— (a) that permission to engage or assist such person has been duly obtained, (&amp;) in the case of an engagement, that the terms of the agreement under which such person has been engaged are in accordance with the terms of the permission granted and are understood hy him, and (c) that the conditions on which the permission was granted have been complied with, he shall register in a book to be kept for the purpose such particulars concerning the person engaged or assisted and his dependents (if any) and concerning the person engaging or assisting him, and in such form, as the Local Government may prescribe. 19. Where such security as is referred to in sub section (3) of section 16 has been furnished, the Local Government may, at any time after making such inquiry as it may deem necessary, pass orders in regard to the forfeiture* of the security in whole or in part and the application of the same or any part thereof, and, on the expiry of the period to which the agree ment24. ( 1 ) The 9 of 1922.] Indian Emigration. ment relates and on being satisfied tbat no ground exists for forfeiting the security in whole or in pait^ order the return of the security or of any part thereof to the person hy whom it was furnished 01 to his representative. 20- The Local Government may, hy notification in the local official Gazette, authorise a Protector of Pro 4 torof Emigrants to receive and dispose of applications made ^gr^of under this Chapter I receive or Provided that an appeal shall lie to the Local applications. Government from every order passed hy a Protector of Emigrants in exercise of the authority so conferred. 21. (i) Where the Governor General in Council power to has reason to believe that sufficient grounds exist for prohibit prohibiting emigration of skilled workers to g].]p e d ticn country, he may, by notification in the Gazette of workers. India, declare that such emigration to that country shall cease to be lawful from a date specified in the notification; and from that date such emigration to that country shall accordingly cease to be lawful. {2) Every notification issued under this section shall be laid before both Chambers of the Indian Legislature as soon as may be after it is made. 22- Nothing in this Chapter shall apply in any Saving, case in which a person engages another to accompany him out of India as his personal domestic servant. 23. Subject to the control of the Governor General power of in Council, the Local Government may, by notifica- ^ 1 rnme tion in the local official Gazette, make rules consistent to make with this Act to prescribe the person by whom any rul&lt;?3 - doubt or dispute referred to in sub-section (£) of section 2 shall be determined and the procedure to be followed and the proof to be required in such cases, and to provide for any other matter which the Local Government is by this Act empowered to prescribe. CHAPTEP V Pules.Indian Emigration. [act VII (i) the Power for the Governor General in Council to make rules. 24.. G) The Governor General in Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, and after previous publication, make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act. {2) In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for— (a) the powers and duties of the several officers appointed by the Governor General in Council under this Act; (b) the licensing, supervision and control of all persons employed in British India in connection with the inducement of persons to emigrate and with the conveyance and accommodation of persons so induced ; (&lt;?) the establishment, supervision and regulation of any places of accommodation provided for emigrants and for their medical care while resident there; {d) the forms to be maintained and the returns to be submitted by persons licensed in accordance with rules framed under clause (6); {e) the information to be furnished by persons licensed in accordance with rules framed under clause (&amp;) to emigrants and the language in which such information is to be furnished ; (/’) the production and examination of emi grants before District Magistrates or such other authorities as may be appointed in this behalf; {g) the age below which joersons of either sex may not emigrate except as dependents; (A) the accommodation, the provisions, fuel and other necessaries, the medical stores and staff, the life-saving and sanitary arrange ments, and the records to be maintained on any ship specially chartered for the transport of emigrants ;OP 1922.] Indian Emigration. (i) the reception and the despatch to their homes of return emigrants; (/) the lees, if any, payable by Emigration Agents to Protectors of Emigrants for each emigrant departing from India; and (&amp;) generally, the security, well-being and protection of emigrants both up to the date of their actual departure from India and on their return to India. CHAPTER VI. Offences. 25- (I) Whoever, except in conformity with the Unlawful provisions of this Act or of the rules made under this SmoT' Act, emigrates or attempts to emigrate shall be punish - t0 emigrate, able with fine which may extend to fifty rupees. (2) ' Whoever, except in conformity with the provisions of this Act or of the rules made under this Act,— (a) makes, or attempts to make, any agreement w T ith any person purporting to bind that person, or any other person, to emigrate, or (&amp;) induces, or attempts to induce, any person to emigrate or to attempt to emigrate or to leave any place for the purpose of emigrat ing, or (c) causes any person engaged or assisted by him, after grant of the permission referred to in section 17, to depart by sea out of British India without registration of the particulars required by sub-section (2) of section 18, shall be punishable with fine, which may extend to five hundred rupees. (3) If any person commits an offence under this section, any police-officer may arrest him without warrant. 26* Wlioever 11Indian Emigration. | act vii Fraudulently inducing to emigrate. 26. Whoever, by means of intoxication, coercion or fraud, causes or induces, or attempts to cause or induce, any person to emigrate, or enter into any agreement to emigrate, or leave any place with a view to emigrating, shall he punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both. False representation of Govern ment author ity. Sanction to prosecutions. Power for Customs- officer to search and detain for purposes of Act. 27. Whoever falsely represents that any emigrants are required by the Government or are to be engaged on behalf of the Government shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both. 28- No prosecution shall be instituted for any offence under this Chapter except with the sanction of a Protector of Emigrants or of a person appointed under section 5 and empowered in this behalf or, where there is no Protector or person so appointed and empowered, of the District Magistrate : Provided that no sanction shall be required when an offence has been committed in respect of an emi grant or an intended emigrant and the complaint is filed by such emigrant, or intended emigrant or, on behalf of such emigrant or intended emigrant, by the father, mother, husband, wife or guardian of such emigrant or intended emigrant or, if such emigrant or intended emigrant is a member of a joint Hindu family, by the manager of that family. 29- All the powers for the time being conferred by law on officers of sea-customs with regard to the searching and detention of vessels or otherwise for the prevention of smuggling on board thereof, may be exercised by those officers for the prevention of offences against this Act. CHAPTER VII. Supplemental. prohibition of 30- (7) The departure by land out of British departure by India of any person under, or with a view to entering an'agreement into, an agreement to work for hire, or when assisted, to work for otherwise 1%of 1922.1 In cha n 'Emig ra Ho n. 13 otherwise than by a relative, so to depart for ilieMre in some purpose or with the intention of working for hire or bey on 1 ? the engaging in agriculture, in any country beyond the sea. sea, is prohibited. (2) Whoever departs, or attempts to depart, by land out of British India in contravention of this section, shall be deemed to have committed an offence under sub-section (1) of section 25. (3) Whoever induces, or attempts to induce, any person to depart by land out of British India in contravention of this section shall be deemed to have committed an offence under sub-section (2) of section 31. Nothing in this Act shall he deemed to apply Application to the departure out of British India of— * of Act. (i) any person who is neither of Indian parent age nor a subject of a State in India, or (ii) any person enrolled under the Indian Army Act, 1911. 32. Notwithstanding anything contained in this Saving. Act, the provisions of this Act shall not apply for a period of twelve months from the date of the commencement of this Act to persons emigrating to Ceylon, the Straits Setthments, or any protected Native State adjoining the Straits Settlements. he Indian Emigration Act, 1908, is hereby Repeal. 25. CHAPTEK VIII. Savings and Eepeal.ACT No. XXVII of 1927 . [Passed by the Indian Legislature. ] (Received the assent of the Governor General on the . 22nd September, 1927.) An Act to amend the Indian Emigration Act, 1922, for a certain purpose. W HEREAS it is expedient to amend the Indian Emigra tion Act, 1922, for the purpose hereinafter appearing; It is hereby enacted as follows: — 1. This Act may be called the Indian Emigration (Amend- short title, ment) Act, 1927. 2. After clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the insertion of vn of 1922 . Indian Emigration Act, 1922 (hereinafter referred to as the said Act), the following clause shall be inserted, namely: — “ (cc) ‘ emigrant ship ’ means any ship specially char tered for the conveyance of emigrants, or conveying emigrants exceeding a number to be prescribed: Provided that the Governor General in Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, declare that ships conveying emigrants to any specified port shall not be deemed to be emigrant ships; 3. (2) In clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section 24 of the Amendmen^of said Act, for the words “ any ship specially chartered for the viiofm’2. transport of emigrants ” the words emigrant ship shall be substituted. (2) In clause (k) of the said sub-section, for the words “ both up to the date of their actual departure from India,” the words “up to the date of their departure from India, during a voyage on an emigrant ship,” shall be substituted. Price 1 anna or l\d.~\ MGIPC—Lr—I-HO— 21 - 11 - 27 — 12 , 600 .Vn of 1922. VII of 1922. ACT No. XXVII OF 1927. [Passed by the Indian Legislature.] [Received the assent of the Governor General on the 22nd September, 1927.) An Act to amend the Indian Emigration Act, 1922, for a certain purpose. W HEREAS it is expedient to amend the Indian Emigra tion Act, 1922, for the purpose hereinafter appearing; It is hereby enacted as follows: — 1. This Act may be called the Indian Emigration (Amend- short title, ment) Act, 1927. 2. After clause (c) of sub-section [1) of section 2 of the insertion of Indian Emigration Act, 1922 (hereinafter referred to as the section 2 , Act 0 v . VII of 1922. said Act), the following clause shall be inserted, namely: — “ (cc) ‘ emigrant ship ’ means any ship specially char tered for the conveyance of emigrants, or conveying emigrants exceeding a number to be prescribed: Provided that the Governor General in Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, declare that ships conveying emigrants to any specified port shall not be deemed to be emigrant ships; ”. 3. (1) In clause (h) of sub-section [2) of section 24 of the Amendment of ' ' ' ' . \ / i p 1 section 24, Act said Act, for the words “ any ship specially chartered for the viiofi922. transport of emigrants ” the words “ emigrant ship ” shall be substituted. [2) In clause (k) of the said sub-section, for the words “ both up to the date of their actual departure from India,” the words “ up to the date of their departure from India, during a voyage on an emigrant ship,” shall be substituted. Price 1 anna or l\d.~\ MGIPC—L—1-110—21-11-27—12,600.VII of 1922. VII of 1922. ACT No. XVI of 1932. [As PASSED BY THE INDIAN LEGISLATURE.] (Received the assent of the Governor General on the 30th September, 1932.) An Act further to amend the Indian Emigration Act, 1922, for certain purposes. W HEliEAS it is expedient further to amend the Indian Emigration Act, 1922, for the purposes hereinafter appearing; It is hereby enacted as follows: — 1. This Act may be called the Indian Emigration (Amend- short title, ment) Act, 1932. 2. For clause (6) of sub-section (2) of section 24 of the Amendment of • * • ' ^ section 24 Indian Emigration Act, 1922 (hereinafter referred to as the Actwn of said Act), the following shall be substituted, namely: — (6) the licensing, supervision and control of persons in British India engaged in causing or assisting per sons to emigrate and in the conveyance and accommodation of emigrants, and the prohibition of unlicensed persons from being so engaged; 3. In section 25 of the said Act,— Amendment of (a) in clause (b) of sub-section (2), for the words “ in- viiofi922. duces, or attempts to induce ” the words “ causes or assists or attempts to cause or assist ” shall be substituted; and (6) sub-section (3) shall be renumbered as sub-section (4), and the following sub-section shall be inserted as sub-section (3), namely: — “ (3) When in the course of any proceedings in con nection with emigration in which a person licensed in accordance with rules framed under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 24 is con cerned, a breach of the provisions of this Act or of 1 Price 1 anna or l\d.~\&gt;■ ■ 1 Amendment of section 30, Act VII of 1922. Indian Emigration {Amendment), [act xvi ot 1932.] of the rules made under this Act is committed, such person shall be liable to the punishment provided by sub-section (2), unless he shows that he was not responsible for and could not have prevented the commission of the breach.” 4. In sub-section (3) of section 30 of the said Act, for the words “ induces, or attempts to induce ” the words “ causes or assists or attempts to cause or assist ” shall be substituted.1935 J JU.TP/DIA. (91 group*}} : J z(5S4. frf'Jyr D i!. C Y_ P-B. *_tt. ■■Q-E T„t_L_-ii_G_R.jLA= Prom Govumment oi India, Foreign and {COPIiiS CIPCi. LATPD) Political Department, to Secretary of State for India, Dated Simla, 15th May, 1935, Keceived 15th May, 1935, 8-15 p ft &gt;'11 Wiij, 1274 , Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Government of Bengal, Following from Italian Consulate-General to Bengal Government, repeated to Government of India, Begins* My Government wishing entrol here some hundreds labourers, preferably Muhammadans, for constructing roads in Italian Somaliland, ask if such enrolment possible and, eventually (sic) particulars and conditions. Please consider this urgent and telegraph reply, gnds . considerations, enlistment at present juncture of British subjects of. {sic, ? or) British protected persons, even as non-combatants, in Italian or Ethiopian forces is out of the question, vide Foreign Office telegram 183 of March 11th to Rome, 2, We presume that, apart from all other j Please confirm.In anj further communication on this subject, please quote - j j'\ % no. j i ill'll { | ;j J Z and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, StV. 1. t / (l2£, 1935 __J % ^ presents THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pres/nts his compliments to eft and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cops of the undermentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 1935 -V? v&lt;\^ Reference to previous correspondence : JvuL+n, *6 20^ fnmJi !^3S ^Jlosbfi/i^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Ama&amp;UL f4 TH' f J? f ‘jufffuXiJL flsu^urns* ^ w sdu^. iHoa lyzs ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER N(X '14 -4 APR 1935 fBQty SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND lEflftET DEPT. INDIA OFFICEy So. 512. (169/289/56) BRITISH XtfBA^ST, RO^K. M«J*ch 19th # 1956. Sir, Tilth raforence to ray savings telegram Ho.24 of March 15fch regarding the decision of 3i« Majesty’s Oovernment not to allow further recruiting by the Italian authorities In East Africa of British or British proteotod native*, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a Rote Verbale on this subject which a rricmber of rcy staff handed on the previous day to the iiead of the African Department In the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. 2. I thought it wise, In waking this communication, not to mention specifically that recruitment would not be allowed either In Italian or in Ethiopian forces. The Italian Govern ment are so sensitive with rocpect to any suggestion that they are to be placed on the same level as a State which they regard as uncivilised and senl-barbaric that I thought that a blunt statement of this kind would only irritate them. In order to cover the point net out In my instructions I therefore used the phracej 'further enlistment in foreign forces'. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient, humble fervent, (SD) W,ir. DRUMMOND The Eight Honourable Sir J ohn &gt; r imon, O.C.S.I., K.C.V.O*, etc., etc•, etc.:nclosure to air arumnond*s despatch No. 312 (lo9/889/36) of the 19 th March. 193^ No. 101. (159/266/35) IICTr: V HBALa . Hie Majesty’s Knbassy present their compliments to the Royal Ministry of Toreign Affair* and have the honour to inforra them that as they will be aware, the Governor of Italian Somali- l?md f recently applied for permission to recruit a fuirther con tingent of 1,000 Arabs for the Italian forces in Italian Somali- land, over and above the 500 which, under standing arrange.;»ents, can be recruited annually. 2. His E&amp;jcsVe Government in the United Kingdom have naturally given the moot careful consideration to this request. As ?! result of their conoideratlon they have regretfully come to the conclusion that they are unable to accede to it. They do not in lact ieel it possible to sanction further enlistment in foreign forces of British or British protected natives beyond the 500 for which arrangements already exist. The Commissioner, British Jomaliland, hfta in consequence been instructed by tele- gram to do what is possible to prevent further recruitment of British or British protected persons. Since extra, enlistment at Men must clearly be treated on the same ba^is, the Resident at Aden is being also informed that the request of the Italian Con ul for permission to recruit a further 1,000 men cannot be approved. 3. In informing the Royal Ministry of this decision, hie ajeoty’a Kmbaasy are to express^] the hope of his Majesty’s Government that the Italian Government will co-operute with then as regards recruiting of Somalis by refusing to e list tribes man known to b© British subjects or British protected persons. British Knibassy, ROMK. 14th March, 1935 .[This Do cument Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office If not required for official use.] FROM ITALY i kj t u o ^ ^ vV j Tolegram (en clair) from Sir M c Drummond (Rome). Do (B y Post ) 15th March 1935. R e 19th March 1935. No 0 24 0 (Saving). if ii if i) if it t; it it tt it it ii it it it n it n it ii n ii n ti Your telegram No ^ IS3. Communication in desired sense was made yesterday to Head of African Department of Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Signor G-uarnaschelli was already aware of adverse decision of His Majesty's Government, having been so informed by Italian Embassy in London* He said that of course the Italian Government were disappointed, and that they did not altogether understand the attitude of His Majesty's Government* But the point was not vital to them* If they could not recruit enough natives on the spot they would send out more troops from Italy*(R2697) Wt 47527/3093 5,000 9/33 H &amp; Sp Gp 112 r Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following number quoted :— ^ j f / &lt;- j nte to metviaiisu correspondence t fgag Letter the Colonial Office of theS^L* Eefere Dooming Street, t 1936'. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to transmit to you The Under Secretary of State, J. L. MAFFEY. k/ Office Date. Description. // pf ■ copy s uy r B F f t Co'py also sent to -© [ ,335 P,WiPimAS3 TICIJCGRAn rron tne Secretary of State for ne Colon!eo to the Resident at Aden* (Sent 9 p.n., 11th ITarch, 1935) ITo*18. Your telegroiii I To*7 of 22nd February. It has 'b decided, in vie^ of strained relations between Italy mid Ethiopia, that proposal to recruit further 1000 i en from or through Aden cannot he approved, and Italian Government have been informed accordingly* Commiesi&lt;ner Somaliland lias been told tliat it has been decided th; t measures should be taken to prevent as far as possib! e enlistment of British Somalis with either Italian or Ethiopian forces and has been requested to do all he an to stop enlistment* The Italian and Ethiopian Governments are being informed and are being asked to co-operate by refra: ing from enlisting tribesmen who are Imown to be British Protected persons*[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gove rnment, and should bo returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] XJ. 758/1/1). To ETHIOIJA. I 1 Cypher telegram to Sir So Barton (Addis Ababa). Foreign Office, 11th March, 1955. 6o45 p.m No. 75. i.y telegram No. 72 (of 7th March: Recruitment of British protected Somalis by Italian and Ethiopian Governments). Please notify Ethiopian Government that Commissioner of British Somaliland and Resident at Aden are being instructed ao stated in my telegram No. 72, and request their co-operation in ieiusing to enlist tribesmen known to be British subjects or British protected persons. Italian Government are being similarly informed.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty 's Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] (J 758/1/1) Cypher telegram to Sir .t. Drummond (Rome) 5 oieign Office; 11th March 1935; 9.15 p.m. No. 183. My despatch No. 1123 of December 29th (1934: recruitment of Arabs in Aden and of British Somalis by Italians and Ethiopians). G-overnor of Italian Somaliland recently applied for permission to recruit further 1,000 ..rabs for Italian forces in Italian Somaliland, over and above the 500 which under standing arrange ment can be recruited annually. His Majesty’s Government regret they cannot accede to this request. The v/hole question of enlistment in existing cir cumstances of British or British protected natives in Italian ano. Ethiopian forces has been under consideration in the light of the Ethiopia Order-in- ✓ Ooanoil of 1934 0 as a result Commissioner of British Somaliland, has Been instructed hy telegram to do everything possible to prevent further recruit ment of British or British protected persons for service on either side. Extra enlistments at Aden ' De legated on same basis and Resident £L b ^ ns - in ? orm S d that request of Italian Consul cI£n8? r te S appfoTOd” crlIlt further «• Please inform Italian government and as records A 0ii ¥U? inyite them to co-operate tribesmen known to oe British subjects or British protected persons.to the Commissioner of Somaliland Sent 8 0 0 p.m. 11th March, l935 e Imnortent ROo^lo Secrete .in view of strained relations between Italy and Ethiopia it has been decided that steps should be taken to prevent as far as possible enlistment of British Comalis with forces of either side, I realise difficulties of preventing individual enlistment, but should be glad if you would do nil you can to stop it, Italian and Ethiopian Governments are being informed and being asked to co-operate by refusing to enlist tribesmen who ore known to be British protected persons, Resident Aden has been informed that oermission cannot be gives for Italians to recruit 1 1 000 further Arabs from or through Aden*A V'-. 05) 46011/2/35. i’. Z. 1414 I i 9 o £ gg February, 1935 Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Cuniiffe-Lister to refer to your letter Ho. J 3140/18/1 of the 28th December 1934 and to transmit to you, to be laid before Secretary Sir John Simon, a copy of a telegram received from the Resident at iden stating that the Italian authorities in Italian Somaliland v/isa to recruit a further 1000 Arabs through Men. 2. Sir Philip Cuniiffe-Lister has considered this proposal in conjunction with the question ol the recruit ment of British protected persons from zritisii Somaliland for service with either the ’ thiopian or the Italian forces - a question discussed in your letter J 557/1/1 oi the 19th February 1935. His view is, briefly, that, having regard to the general deterioration in the relations between Italy and Ethiopia and the fact that an armed conflict UNDSF. S'C.3TARY Oi' STATE, FCRFIGH OPFIC'.conflict within the next few months is by no means unlikely # stops should bo taken to prevent, so far as possible, the recruitment of British subjects or British protected persons for service with either the Italian or the Ethiopian foi-ces, or the recruitment of forei/^n subjects for such service through British territory i*e* .non* It follows from this that, sub ject to Sir John Bimon’s concurrence, the Secretary of Stato would propose to inform the resident at Aden that the proposed recruitment by the Italian authorities of a further 1000 men thron'd! .*don cannot bo arrorovod• It seoms to tho Secretary of &gt;tate that the ppneral critical position ol Italian- thiopian relations would have made it impossible to have approved oven the 'normal * annual recruitment of 500 Arabs through Men had permission for such recruitment boon sought at tho present time: the recruitment oi a further 1GGC men seems tq,hi* cloarly out of the question. 3. As regards recruitment in British Somaliland the Secretary of State would propose to ask Mr Arthur Lawrance by telegram to do all that ho can to stop BritishBritish Somalis from enlisting in either the Italian or the Ethiopian forces. Sir John Simon will appreciate that to stop individual enlistments may well prove quite impossible f &lt;r mv to the noaadic nature of t'm Somali tribes and to the fact that many, if not the majority, of those who enlist are men who are evading arrest or the payment of fines in British Somaliland itp.elf. However, it is certain that Sir Arthur Lawranea will on the receipt of instructions do all he can - whether by warning British tribesman of the legal penalties to which they would be subject, ox otherwise - to check enlistment in either the Italian or the Ethiopian forces. 4. The Secretary of State feels that it would be desirable that both the Italian and Ethiopian Governments should be notified that action is being taken on the above linos, and that they should be invited to co-operate by refusing to enlist tribesmen known to be British subjects or Britisn protected persons. it is probable that such action on the part of the Italian and Ethiopian authorities - assuming, of course, that they are prepared to give and to carry out the necessary instructions will prove the most effective way of preventing the enlistment ofof British tribesmen 5* The Secretary of State requests that he may bo informed whether Sir John Simon concurs in the general action proposed in this letter and, if so, whether he will be prepared to approach the Ethiopian and Italian Governments in the sense* suggested in the previous paragraph. 6. I am to take this opportunity of enclosing a copy of the latest Intelligence lieport received from Somaliland, which contains some interesting references to the presence of British tribesmen with both the Italian and Ethiopian forces. 4 copy of this letter, with the telegram from thn BooMsut at Men is being g&lt;m t to the India Off too. I am Sir, Your moat obedient servant (Signed) J A CALDERf A r ! : „ 14 Z. 14 i PARAPHMSE TELEGRAM from the Resident at Ad'en to- the Secretary of iitate for the Colonies, Rated 22nd February, 1935, Received in the Colonial Office at 2.12 p.m. on 22nd February, 1935. No.7. Addressed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Repeated to Foreign Office Delhi. Your telegram of 1st January No.2. I have given permission for recruitment up to 300 of whom 288 have left. 214 of these were Yemenis and the remainder were from Aden Protectorate. I am now informed by Italian Consul that the Governor of Italian Somaliland has requested him to ask my permission to recruit a further 1,000 Arabs 200 of whom he wishes to obtain immediately. I have informed him that this exceeds my authority but that his request is being referred to you for instructions. Consul seems to regard war as inevitable. I have reminded him that if war breaks out no further recruitment through Aden can be allowed. I shall be glad to receive early orders.I L93JL i CYPHI?!^ TKLKORAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Resident at Aden. (Sent 4.U5 p.m. 1st January 1935). Addressed to Aden No. 2. Repeated to Government of India No.iu Your telegram of 20th December.Recruiting now proposed may be permitted in Protectorate and also in Yemen through Aden but not from Makalla direct. Your assumption as to position in case of war is correct.Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. p. z. 7877/34. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT X Dated Rec. 193 . Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary / Secretary of State... Committee Uk. . ADEN PROTECTORATE.! « Proposed recruitment by Italians of Arabs from the Aden Protectorate and Yemen for service in Italian Somaliland. v V Under Secretary Secretary of State Copy of * * to SEEN POUTICkL COMMITTED 4 JAK boi FOR INFORMATION. The Governor of Italian Somaliland has asked permission of the Resident at Aden to recruit 300 Arabs for service in Italian Somaliland, but in view of the tension between Italy and Ethiopia, the Resident has referred the question home for approval before giving his sanction. The origin of the Italian recruitment of Arabs from the Aden Protectorate dates back to 1906 and the arrangement whereby the Resident is empowered to permit the recruitment of not more than 500 Arabs a year subject to certain conditions was agreed upon in 1925 (see P.3270/25 in the bound volume below). The conditions under which recruitment is permitted are given in paragraph 5 of the Resident’s telegram of 11th September 1925 at P.3270/25 (flagged). It will be/ *be seen from that telegram and from the Colonial Office covering letter of the 22nd September 1925 that the major argument advanced in favour of the arrangement was that if we permitted the Italians to recruit these Arabs within defined limits and under definite conditions we would avoid the risk of their getting into closer touch with the tribes beyond the frontiers of the British Protectorate and could at the same time keep the recruitment under our observation and control. The Colonial Office consider that since the Italian request is in accordance with such a long-standing arrangement, it would be unfriendly towards the Italians to refuse it, and to accede to it in the present circumstances would not give the Ethiopians legitimate ground for complaint. As a state of war between the two countries does not exist, this view seems to be a sound one, and in view of the danger of a refusal driving the Italians to recruit among the Arabs beyond the frontier of the Protectorate, it seems likely that the Foreign Office, for whose views the Colonial Office have asked, will agree that the Italian request may be granted. For information. Cw JU ^Minute Paper. Department. SEEN POLITICAL COMMITTED 4 JAN 1955I am directed by secretary Sir Philip Cunlifle-Lister to refer to previous correspondence regarding the recent encounter between Italian and Ethiopian forces at Walwal and to transmit to you f to be laid before the Secretary of State ior Foreign Affairs# the accompanying copy of a telegram which has been received from the Resident at Aden regarding the proposed recruitment of 300 Arabs from the Aden Protectorate and the Yemen for service with the Italian colonial forces in Italian somalilnnd* 2* Sir John oimon will be aware that there is a standing arrangement whereby the Resident at Aden is authorised to allow the recruitment of not more than 500 Arabs a year for service with the Italian ColorrlaX Forces subject to the fulfilment of certain conditions. Keference is invited in this connection to Foreign Office letter (K.5756/6756/91) of the 28th September, __ 1925, and connected correspondence, (The resident ' gives THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE# FOR ,IGN OFFICE*gives the maximum figure as 400 a years hut it is not clear on what grounds this has heen done, nor is the point relevant to the present question). It may he assumed that the 300 Arabs which the Italian authorities wish to enlist fP^m part of the complement of 500 (or 400) men whose recruitment is normally permitted hy the Resident as a matter of course: hut Sir Bernard Reilly has thought it well, in view of the present tension between Italy and Kthiopia, to refer the question of whether this recruitment should he allowed to His Majesty , 8 Government for decision. 3. This is a question on which Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister would he glad to have the views of the Secretary of State for Foreign vffairs, that Subject to those views, he feels'having regard to the fact that such recruitment would he in accordance with a longstanding arrangement (which, indeed, dates from 1906) it would he difficult to withhold approval, and that the ItalianItalian Government would f not unnaturally 9 regard any such action as shoeing an unjustifiable ausplclon of their future policy via-fr^vla J.tliiopia-aiul a a being tantamount to an unfriendly act. JJor — having regard to the fact that such recruitment would be in accordance with a tending arrangement - would the Ethiopian Government appear to have any cause for complaint if the requisite authority is given. If a state of war were imminent, or actually in being, the position would be entirely different and the Secretary of ttate assumes that in such an event there would be no question of allowing recrultmont from or through /idem or the ^den Protectorate. 4. Ihe Secretary of ^tate would accordi n gl y propose to inform the Kesident that the recruitment now proposed may be permitted, through Aden but not from Mafcalla direct and that the assumption of the Reb* lent as to the position in case of war is correct; but he would be glad to learn whether air t ohn Simon concurs in this proposed action. o. Copies of this letter and its enclosures being sent to the India Office. I aa,.&gt;lr. Your most obedient servant, C~ML dJL are4 l i£±C 1 CYPHKK TKL;«X&gt;RAM from the Resident at Aden to the Secretary of Utate for the Colonies. Dated 20th Oeoe»ber P 1934. Received in the Colonial Office at 5.47 p.a.on 20th Deceaber f 1934). Add reseed to secretary of State for the Colonies repeated to Foreign Office Delhi. From Resident Aden. Italian Consul haa cowaunicated to ne te egraphic request fro» the Governor of Italian Somaliland for permission to recruit 300 Arabs for Italian Somaliland Colonial Forces, enlistment being from the western part of Aden Protectorate and Yemen through Aden and from eastern part of the Protectorate through Makalla. Procedure for such recruiting la governed by your secret despatch 1st October 1985 under (p 34 - 0 j oan authorise enlistment subject to certain conditions up to maximum of 400 per year. In view however of present position between Italy and Jfithiopia I consider it advisable to inform you and to obtain approval before probably would bo necessary 1 assume that in the event of war recruiting of natives of Aden Protectorate would be stopped and also recruiting in Yemen through Aden but that both may continue to be permitted at present through Aden but not Makalla direct which 1 think is inadvisable. If this view is correct may I inform Italian Consul in this sense. I shall be grateful for early instructions. Italian^C^g^Miijn:^ t*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1492</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1492</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 1/54 'Aden. Recruitment of Arabs from the Aden Protectorate and the Yemen for service with the Italian Colonial forces in Italian Somaliland; recruitment of Indians'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-26T14:41:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (160 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 160; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the recruitment of labour from the Aden Settlement, the Aden Protectorate, and Yemen, for service in Italian Somaliland.Following requests from the Italian Consul at Aden for an increased number of labourers to work in Italian Somaliland and Eritrea, the India Office, the Foreign Office and the Aden Chief Commissioner consider the options available to prevent the recruitment of British Subjects or Protected Persons for either the Italian or Ethiopian forces. Following communications with the King of Yemen it is agreed that Yemeni subjects should also be prevented from travelling from Aden ports for that purpose.The file also contains telegraphic correspondence with the Government of India, the Governor-General of Sudan, and British diplomatic staff in British Somaliland, Ethiopia, and Italy, requesting that efforts should be made to prevent recruitment from those locations. The likelihood of war between Italy and Ethiopia is discussed throughout the correspondence.A large part of the correspondence concerns the legality of preventing emigration from Aden ports, and involves discussion of the Indian Emigration Act (1922), and the drafting of the Aden (Protection of Emigrants) Regulation (1935), the published version of which appears at ff 5-13. The Act prohibited emigration from Aden without obtaining a permit.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief Commissioner, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Italian Consul-General, Aden</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Yemen</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Italian Somaliland</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Italo-Ethiopian War (1935-1936)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Regulations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Labour migration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00001b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>