<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000327_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:02:16.276Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">f 6. 333 NOTE ON KUWAIT. P • The r. t0 » n , aud E?' of Kuwait '' as founded on the Arabian shore of the ir'Z G i a \ 0U i? - vear f. a 7? b y tho ancestor of the present ruling Shaikh, Ti n T 1 m 31 ' J races hls llnea g e t0 t}le tribe of Anaza, the noblest of all the Badawm tribes of Arabia. The throne of Kuwait has remained in the Ibn a family, as the dynasty is styled, without a break from the date of its foundation up to tne present tune. r i ^ le 1 m 1 - )St ^ mous ^ ^ Shaikhs of Kuwait was Mubarak Ibn Subah who died in ]91o and was among the greatest men that Arabia has produced during the ast two centuries. J he seaport of Kuwait achieved considerable notoriety in connection with the projected Berlin-Baghdad railway, of which it was designed to be the terminus, and it required all the subtlety and astuteness of a ruler, who has been excelled by few Orientals m the possession of those qualities, to maintain his independence amid the intrigues which his position provoked ; but he pinned his faith unswervingly on His Majesty's Government and largely helped by the treaty relations with us, into which he entered when Lord Curzon was Viceroy'of India he succeeded in steering clear of international complications until the outbreak of war between Britain and Turkey enabled him boldly to espouse the cause which he had always tavoured. -j ! lle ^ Mubarak at an early stage of the war was a heavy loss to Great utan} &gt; he ^ as succeeded by iiis son Jabir, who did not however long survive his accession to power, and was followed by his brother Salim, the present ruler. Shaikh Salim was called upon soon after his accession to the throne to co-operate with the British authorities in the strict enforcement of a blockade of enemy territory ; his port was the most considerable commercial centre on the Arabian coast of the 1 ersnin Gulf, and at the same, time the one most accessible to the enemy ; and, though from time to time contretemps occurred, it may be recorded to Salim's credit that _ some success was achieved in the desired direction as the result of his acqiiiescence in the conduct of the blockade operations by British officers workin 0 * in co-operation with the local staff. Irom time to time Shaikh Salim and his predecessors have received substantial assistance from His Majesty's Government, notably in connection with the improvement of the water supply of Kuwait—a very necessary measure in view of the great commercial importance of the place, and of the fact that it is surrounded on all sides either by the sea or by waterless desert. The population of the town may be some 40,000, all of whom are directly concerned either with commerce—the bulk of the Kuwait trade being with Mesopotamia and India—-or with shipbuilding and other sea-faring occupations. On the invitation of His Majesty's Government Shaikh Salim has sent a delegation headed by his nephew, Ahmad Ibn Jabir, the son of Jabir and grandson of Mubarak, to offer his congratulation on the victory of His Majesty's forces over the enemy. The relations of the ruler of Kuwait with his nearest neighbour, Ibn Sand of Central Arabia, are unfortunately not as happy as • thej^ might be in view r of the intimacy of the two families which marked the reign of Mubarak; but their differences seem to be rather of a personal and perhaps religious^ rather than of a political and permanent character, for Salim—unlike his easy-going father, Mubarak— is as staunch a champion of the orthodox faith as Ibn Saud is of the Wahhabi heresy. On the other hand the ruler of Kuwait is on ihe best of terms with the King of the Hejaz, whom Ahmad Ibn Jabir, the head of the present mission, visited last year during the pilgrimage. Promising signs of oil have recently been discovered in the neighbourhood of the tow T n, but have yet to be developed. Its prosperity, however, depends mainly on the thriving trade which it carries on between the interior of Arabia and Basra and India. At present it is by far the most important avenue of such trade ; which consists chiefly of piece goods, sugar, coffee rice and tea. An American mission provides the inhabitants with education and medical requirements, but since the accession of Salim there has also been a large increase in the number of Muhammadan (Quranic) schools. io 161 20 10 19</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000327_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B333</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000327</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B333</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Note on Kuwait'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-12T15:22:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this sequence commences at folio 81, and terminates at folio 81, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 7-153 of the volume; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This note gives a very short history of Kuwait in eight paragraphs. It provides brief details of the ruling Ibn Subah family [Āl Ṣabāḥ], including Mubarak Ibn Subah [Mubārak bin Ṣabāḥ], Jabir [Jābir bin Mubārak] and Salim [Sālim bin Mubārak], and their relations with the Britain, Ibn Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥman bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd] and the King of Hejaz [Ḥusayn bin ‘Alī al-Hāshimī]. Also mentioned are 'promising signs of oil', trade, the American Mission, and education.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000327#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>