<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000085_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T17:35:35.060Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Notes on Tribes and Boundaries. Note by Mr. J. R. FitzGerald, First Assistant to the A.G.G. for Beluchistan, 20th February 1885. t There is no difTiculty in finding a number of instances in which tribes are divided by territorial boundaries. The Atchakzais are cut in two by the frontier between Pishin and Afghanistan at the Khojak. Of the Sunzakhel section of the Kakar Pathans, some are within our boundary, and others are independent. I believe it will be found that the Baretchis of Shorawak (Afghan) extend into Shorarud (British). The Sinjarani Biluchis are at Chageh subjects of Kelat, at Rudbar and thence to Chakansar subjects of Kabul. I should think it certain that the Afridis are divided. I have no doubt the same thing happens on the Perso-Baluch frontier. People like the Rinds, Rekis, and Damnis will probably be found on both sides the boundary. There is a considerable settlement near Muhsinabad, in Persia, of one of the Char Aimak of Herat, the Firuzkuhis I believe. The above instances are not quite on all fours with the cases of the Turkmans as stated by Russia. If I understand right, the contention is that the tribes being constantly on the move, no member can be said to be an inhabitant of one side or the other of any line drawn through the region within which they wander. But is this so ? I have always understood that (for instance) the Sariks of Yulatan were of a different section from the Sariks of Panjdeh, and that, though there was constant communication between the two places, there was no difficulty in distinguishing between a Yulatan and a Panjdeh Sarik. It is certain that during the last 18 months both Yulangtush Khan and Amin-ullah Khan (the Afghan Governors) have taken revenue from the Panjdeh Turkmans, and of course have not touched those of Yulatan. But if it is granted that the view of Russia is a correct one, it would be difficult perhaps to find an exact parallel on our frontier; so far, at least, as I know. The nearest approach would be the periodical migrations of the Brahuis from the plains of Katchi to the hills round Quetta. Many of the Pathan tribes move in like manner every year. But the Brahuis, if not in the strict sense of the word our subjects, are so completely under our control, whether they are actually in our territory or not, that no difficulty can possibly arise in settling any cases that may occur. The case of the Salors and Sariks, as stated by the Russians, obviously differs from the above, and presents, no doubt, greater difficulty, but I do not see that it is insuperable. J. R. FitzGerald. 20th February 1885. Extract from a Letter, dated 26th December 1874, from Mr. Taylour Thomson, Her Majesty’s Ambassador at Teheran, to the Russian Minister at that Court. I most respectfully remind your Excellency that the arrangement of 1869 was sudden and telegraphic; the heads of matters were stated, but details were not entered into. It does not follow that because all the old established 10748. I, 2429.rights of Persia were not inserted therein, they should be made a subject for ° rpfiitation The fact that tribes move from place to place, wluch *°»^old usaJandthe mode of living of nomad people, does not deprive them of their aUegiance to their lawful State; the Shahseven tabes of Wa for instance! spend half the year in Russian territory, and Persian aXrurkish tribes accommodate themselves to their summer or winter Quarters by crossing over to the territories of both States, their respective nationalities remaining, as before, unaltered. The doubt which has been suggested to your Excellency as to whether the tribes in question pay tribute to any one is unfounded ; they have always been pavers of tribute to Persia, and the amount due by them is registered aTd vearly coUected by the Asterabad authorities If owing to their wild habits and want of education, they occasionally showed a rebellious spirit and refused to pay their tribute, they were soon compelled to do so by the Government of Asterabad. Therefore, as regards their allegiance to Persia, there cannot be, for us, the slightest doubt.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000085_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C48</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000085</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C48</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Notes on tribes and boundaries.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1885/1885</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-24T19:00:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences and terminates at folio 191, as it is part of a larger physical volume; this number is written in pencil, is circled, and is located at the top right corner of the folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; this number is also written in pencil, but is not circled</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a note written by J R Fitzgerald, First Assistant to the Agent to the Governor-General for Beluchistan, in which the author provides a number of instances of tribes divided by territorial boundaries, and casts doubt on the notion that members of those tribes cannot be said to be inhabitants of one side or the other of those boundaries.The file also reproduces an extract from a letter written by Her Majesty's Ambassador at Tehran, dated 26 December 1874, in which the author provides examples of nomadic tribes who migrate across boundary lines, but who nevertheless declare allegiance and pay tribute to one state or the other.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000085#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>