<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c9_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:30:26.931Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">29/22 cD Inter (Ord.). Political Agent, Bahrain. R.A.F#, Sharjah. Telegram From To No, 1. Dated the 2nd January, 1945* % 'i IMPORTANT . Please pass following to P.O.T.C., Sharjah from Political Agent, Bahrain. Following is text of telegram No. ENCOM 310 dated December 28th from U.K.C.C., Baghdad. 1. Shipped from Basra per S.S.'Esang' for Dubai (a) 7680 bags of wheat 646,857 kilogrammes gross (b) 1700 bags of barley 171,700 kilogrammes gross. 2. For Sharjah (a) 2164 bags of wheat 182,218 kilogrammes gross (b) 900 bags of barley 90,900 kilogrammes gross. 3. The c.i.f. prices either port metric ton gross are (a) wheat Rs.351 (b) barley Rs.330, less 2J#. 4. Delivery may be made against payment for gross bill of lading weights to the Agent of the Political Agent. - POLITICAL - R.M.WT (*,^ 1 Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. . Telegram From To No. 2331. Dated the 31st December, 1944 and received 2nd January, 1945. ♦ Your telegram No* 1079 dated December 5th. Barley. Your paragraph No.3. Supply of barley to Trucial Coast by U.K.C.C. will be discontinued with effect from January allotment. - PRIOR - R.M. I. R. 1.I! 1 c T DLG. S. 6. MFT-501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-3G 300,000. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER rv B -This it on ORIGINAL MESSAGE, tent by post to tave telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, 1 o save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Bushire. Political, Bahrain, 318-tf Dated the 18th December^ 4.4 Foreign Express Letter No. D. 17487-ME/44 dated November 30th, 1944. Cost of wheat ex-Masula. 2. Please take action accordingly and report date proceeds are credited to Government. ATTESTED. Sd. GEOFFREY PRIOR POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.2d/l Sc 2a/22 Te-Le^r*m Fro in To No. Dated Po-Liticax Resident, Persian Gulf. Midcile East Supply Centre, Cairo. 2260. tne Idtn December 1^44. I From politicitx Resident Persian Bu^f. Your better FS/12504/PGA/445 JJovember 8th. /V\ 3a-rley f or Shaiiiiicioms. g # It is confirmea that bariey^Gliverea at Kuwait is not as clean as U.rv.C.C. barley but tnis can haiiilly account for whole of difference in price which is more than ID 6 per ton. Kuwait wishes to oe induced in U.K.G.C. barley programme as from 1st May 1^45 out does not require any barley till then. 5. Bahrain and Muscat prefer to continue oeing supplier with barley bj U.n.C.C. 4 # Trucial Coast will obtain 1^45 barley requirements tnroujjn private channels. Pleaoe confirm tnat supply by U.K.C.C. will be discontinued with effecfe from January 1^45 allotment. PRIOti COiMl'J.Dnnllhu Office of tne Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Datfed the 18th December 1044. Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The political Kuwait, with reference to Kuwait telegram No. 885 datea tne 12th Dec / : C • ■ ' 1 - The political A£en£, Bahrain with ref. to Bahrain tel. No. 1070 datea tne 5th December, The Political Aient, Muscat, with reference to Muscat tel. no.C*2005 aatea 15th Becember.2d/l &amp; 2d/22 6) Teleiram From To Repeated No. Date* S(Pa«0 MX6C0, Cairo H*M.Ambassador, Baglnlaa for Representative telegram No, 151. Politica-L Resident, Bushire. 14th received 15th December 1 b44. ^t L Reference telegram No. B1B7 from Poxiticax Resident. We a^ree txiat an^ supplies of rice wnicn may reach shaiKhdoms should oe set off against total cereals required. 2. Balances remaining after such deductions will be supplied by M.b.b.C. in form of two tnirds wheat- flour to one third barley. MbbCO British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, dated tne 15th December 1944. CONFIDENTIAL. . No. 913-S. Copy forwarded with compliments to:- © The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Politicax *Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. in continuation of Residency Endorsement No. 690-^8 dated 8tn llecember 1944. \1 Telegram G.T .0 . From Residency Agent, &gt;harjah. To * Political Agent, Bahrain. l T o. 40 Dated 7tli received 3th January'’ 1945. • ^ © Your / 1 telegram 11 Januarjr 4th Kasula fheat 2. loth the 3hciidiS of Sharjah and Oubai req- ucst that the outstanding sum should he paid the Subsidized Fund as merchants arc not repeat not willing' to pay for more than the quantity actually received and sold at fixed rate. 3 # To avoid delay suggest amount bo drawn from the Susidized Fund and remitted t® you atonce. -BHITAGF1TT. -,i&gt; Chalan No.l Bahrain Political Agency Treasury. Name of person paying in the money- Political Agent, Bahrain, Particulars of payment into the treasury. Amount on pa whose behalf id To whom or what head credited. Recovery of the balance of money due on account of cost of wheat ex aa ' Masula'. Is. 23853-13-0 twenty three thousand eight hundred and fifty three and annas thirteen only. -p G &lt;D W) -I a o Cm Cm' - ' C • O O * G &amp; ^ (D .xS &lt;H 0j rtf ’r-i,-} fkj f-3 •H G ’H G co cd &gt;G cd .d &lt;D ,G &lt;D ,G ,G pc; c/5 .g ^3 vi Creditable to Government 6f India, Gxternal Affairs Dept. Received from the Political Agent, Bahrain. for credit to Government of India. Eg. 23853/13/- (fcWK* twenty three thousand eight hundred and fifty ^ three and annas -/l3/-,■ only. id. IMJ Treasurer ad/ NIU. Accountant Bd/ M.A.Hafiz. Treasury Officer, Bahrain. Bahrain. 14th January, 1945.(i) I s iiiXP fci&amp;iau From poiitiCci-L P^ent, Bahrain, »Pq poiiticax Officer, Iruciai Coast, biic.rjo.ii No c/153. Dateu the 31st January 1345. Reference your telegram No. 1750, aated. December 3rd. Barley. you should maice arrangements accordingly to obtain your requirements through private channels. poriticai Agent, Bahrain, xvM.oTelegram Inter (0). p rora H.M's. Ambassador, Baghdad, •p 0 Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 7. Dated the 17th and received 19th February, 1945. For Gray Mackenzie From U.K.^.^* ^, IL Reference my telegram No. 3. 2. Your Basra Office are telegraphing UiP• Please amend weight 1791 bags, of wheat ex 'Ssang' V41 for Shar;ah to 150,810 kilogrammes gross and collect payment accordingly. - Ar.IBASSADOR - R.M. I.R. 116.URGENT. No. C/262. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 19th February 1945. il (£*) Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., 'n. Bahrain. , I M7.M0RANDUM . following is the text of telegram No. ENCOM 7, dated the 17th February 1945, from U.K.C.C., Baghdad, . 0 Gray Mackenzie. 2. Please fefer U.K.C.C. telegram No. SNCOM 3 and make the amendment as follows:- ' SharMl - (b) The weight of 1791 bags of wheat to 150,810 kilograms gross, 3. further. Payment may be collected accordingly. Your Basra Office will be telegraphing for &lt;ih ^ '^POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMSE« 0. Telegram Cypher, x^rom Ambassador, Baghdad. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No/ 10. Dated the 7th and received 3th March, 1945. IMMEDIATE . . * - (3 groups mutilated). For Gray Mackenzie. Shipped from Basra by “Buraia': (a) To Dubai 3527 bags of wheat ? 608,653 Kilogrammes gross. (b) fo Sharjah 3864 bags of wheat 321,085 kilogrammes gross. (c) To Bahrain for pool stocks 3900 bags of barley 393,900 kilogrammes gross. 2. Please deliver (a) and (b) to Political Agent f s nominee at ports of discharge against payment for gross bill of lading weight. 3. Prices unchanged. ^ - AMBASSADOR - R. i.. I.R. 166. 0 '' • , &lt;s. /O I I** tin B ahrain Receipt ^ /5'f gFor Gray Mackenzie. Following £hippea tey 'Barai-a' from Baara (a) d527 bags wheat gross waight 608653 Kilograms to Dubai. O) 3864 bags wheat gross weignt 321,085 kilograms to Sharjah. C») 3800 bags barley gross weight 393,800 kilo grammes to Banrain for pool stocks. 2. (a) and (b) should be aelivered to Political Agent’s nominee at ports of aischarge against payment for gross »iil of lading weight. 3. Mo change in prices Mo. C/343 Political Agency, Bahrain, 8th March 1845 Copy forwarded to:- Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Lta., Bahrain.No.G318.1225 British ^ency, oharj-h jjax,ed tli« 18 Ui uarch 19^i5. To - T \f/o The political ^ent, Bahrain. Memorandum . -^b » 2^^ f. Befer^ence Residency Agent’s memorandum No.C/1458 dated the 30th September 1944. 2. I shall be grateful if you will kindly let me know whether the Government of India have allotted a separate quota of cloth for dharjah as the Ghaikh of Sharjah is anxious to know the result. (\ Political 'Jfficer, Trucial Coast, oharjah.&lt;3 - n Wo* 1131 - 2*/22. To POuI'IlCiuj iidhWCX, aiJlW • 24th March 1^45. The Political Officer, . Trucial Coast, Uiafi&amp;An. Mi,A40^hUM . / Reference your memorandum No* 0518*1225 dated c the 18th Marcn 1845* /f j am enclosing a copy of my mentor a ndum No*C/l5ob, dated the 3rd November 1844, to the Hon*tele the Political Resident in the Persian Gurf, Bushire, which will enable you to answer the Sheikh of Sharjah’s query. J. po.uiiiUau itUiiiii, BantUilN* O’£. 0 . Cypher. Charge d* Affaires, Baghdad. Political Agent, Bahrain, Telegram From To No. 13 ENCOM# Dated the 2nd and received 3rd April, 1945. &amp;&gt; jf&gt; / ///• v7v IMIvlEDIAT.^ . v For Dray Mackenzie from U.K.C.C. Shipped from Basra to Dubai by •'Wosang' V48 6248 bags of wheat 515,309 kilogrammes gross. 2. Please deliver to Political Agent 1 s nominee against payment for gross bill of lading weight. 3. Prices unchanged. - CHARGE D* AFFAIRES - R.M. I.R. 242.(S&gt; UhGtMI. No. 1315 - 2d/22. FOul'XICiUi AGi^WCY, BiiAtU-Jii. Tne 5rd April 1945. To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Following is the text of telegram No. LNCQM 13 datea tne 2nd April 1945, from , Baghdad to Gray Mackenzie. 1 p* Tne following may please be handed over to political Agent*s nominee against payment for gross bill of -Lading. 3. 6248 bags of wheat weigning ol5,908 kilogrammes gross Shipped from Basra to Dubai by 'Wosang' V48. b* 4 . prices remain unchanged. kMb P ^ for POLITICAL. AGLNT, jdahuaIN.Tea.egram From To No. . &lt;3 G • T • C • Political A^ent, Bahrain. Residency Agent, Sharjah. 233. Dated the 8th April TM5 Understand you have in stock about two montns( supply of wheat. Do you think wheat from Persia will undersell it? POLITICAL..Telegram 1G*T* C. From , Residency Agent, Sharjah. To political Agent, Bahrain. No. 416. Dated and received 10th April 1045. //&gt; s ‘ Your telegram No. 233 of April 8th. Our present stock of wheat will hardly suffice for 2 months. It is too early to say if wheat from Persia will undersell it as harvest has not started yet. The cr °P in ? Persia is ? believed to be very good and there is much hope of price of wheat going down. m . = BhllAULh'I(3 No. 1493 - 29/22. PQ-ulTICiiii hOLNCl, ' BiuiKiilN. The 11th April 1345^ To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. /—'N If \ h : It appears from your report on cereals for tne last tvvo months forwarded under your memoranda Nos. 'C251.1235 dated the 1st March and C281.1230 dated the 2nd April 1345 that only 31 tons of barley was imported to the Trucial Coast during February and March. 'Hi** 2. Imports of barxey under private arrangements should not be shown in your monthly reports but a separate statement showing stock on the 1st of the pre ceding montn, imports, consumption and balance on the 1st of the month should be submitted at the same time. 3. Please confirm that only 31 tons were In fact imported during February and M^rch 1945 and that these were under private arrangements. 3 ^for POiilllCiO, AGiiiX, BAnhAlW. kite0 ^ No. Jo31 - 2^/10. PaiilTlGAL. AGENCY, The 10th April 1945 The Director of Custo ms, Bahrain . The political Officer, Tpuciai Coast, Sharjah. To mORAT! DOm, \ S upplies to Qata=r. It has been decided that until further orders export of all commodities from India for Qatar will be made to Bahrain, through parties nominated by me, and import to # Qatar direct \vi ~1 not be permitted. Sd/- h.E.ti. BIRi. f or POliUTICAh AGEhT, BAHRAIN KMS^.0 From Telegram To Cypher. H.M's. Ambassador, Baghdad Political Agent, Bahrain. No. Encom 16. Dated the 20th and received 21st April, 1945 1 Follov/ing for Gray Mackenzie. Shipped from Basra by S.S. 'Barala': / (a) To Dubai ? 8040 bags wheat 668,363 kilogrammes gross. (b) To Sharjah 1,230 bags wheat 106,363 kilogrammes gross. 2 # Please deliver to Political Agent’s nominees against payment for gross bill of lading weight. 3. Prices unchanged. 3T0NEHE.VERB1RD -URG^'I POulXlCku AGiJiCY # BAiitiAlW. The 21st April 1G45. No. 1656 - 29/22. To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Memorandum . Following is the text of telegram No. LNCQk 16 dated the 20th April 1945 from G.A.G.C., Baghaad to Gray Mackenzie.-' • 2. The following consignments shipped by s.s. ^Barala^ from Basra may please be handed over to Political Agent»s nominee against payment for gross bixl of lading. Dubai 8040 bags of wheat weighing 666,363 kilogrammes gross. Sharjan 1280 bags of wheat weighing 106,363 kilogrammes gro§s. 3 . prices remain unchanged. KM£ A M for POiilflCio. AGhWl’, BAiiHAIU.Telegram From To No. Dated P.O.T'.C. Sharjah. Political Agent, Baju^a in. 465 25th received 26th April, 1245. Kindly cane el U.K.C.C. vj hea t shipment for May only not required duo local harvest and surplus stock. =poi.j:ticai^ Arc. Bahrain Receipt No . 7 . .. Date(j«) Telegram From To No. G.X.C. political Agent, Bahrain, political Officer, Sharjah. 273 Dated the 28th A^rju. 1945. A* Your Tel..Ho. 465 April 25tn. - Figures available here give your estimated stock; on 1st May as 1792 tons only enougn for two months ®^PP^ r uth-i f*h it is nolicv always to Keep in reserve. Do not the^e fore propose cancel May shipment unless'local harvest' figure justifj.es doing so. POnXlICAh KM8 70 J- D ^ . 7URG3flT . ^47r.isi5 British /Uency, ohi-rj»h- ^ t^d the 26th april 1945. i3l) TO 1‘iie political A^ent, Bahrain. £1^ - U WVi Subject:- vheat iuota far the Trucirl te^a t. p em 1 v r^ndum . Reference your memorandum No•1727-29/22 d^ted the 24th^ I h \ „f April 1-945. A/ o. Tt was reperted in this office telegram N».17bo dated the 3rd December 1944 that the 1945 requirements of barley fer the Trueis 1 coast could be obtained privately on more favourable terms rr.nd the supply of barley by the U.K.C-O w-d subsequently ^ discontinued with effect from January (vide your teie.ram do.3 dated the 4th of January 1945;. It was thought that adequate supplies could be obtained privately from Iraq (in this connection * please refer to ysur important telegram fjo,l061 dated the 3otn af November 1944; but these anticipated supplies have not materxalisec ; S the-Iraq Government have apparently refused o© yranc- expert permits, since the discontinuation of the u-K-C.G. supplies.only 31 tons »f barley have been imported privately, m other words, requirements of barley for the rrucial coast ccnnot at present be obtained through private channels and the tfoed committees of jharjah andgubai have iaade ne arrangements for supplementing the wheat quota to over this rosultotif deficit. 3 . on the 1st of February 1945 there was a balance «f 576 tons of barley in hand (vide statement forwarded with my r -memorandum NoC251.1335 dated the 1st of Karen 194oj and a further 31 tons were imported privately during March and these s inc c s becks h. ve/been disposed of. rhe present stocks of wheat amount to 3485 tons (Dubai 2170 tons and Sharjah 315 tons; and will suffice to meet the requirements of the rrucial coast up t# tne end of May, leaving reserve stocks for one month in hand, m this connection kindly refer to my telegram je.465 dated one 25th April 1945 in which I have surrendered the way quota. It ''■'illbe seen 'therefore thac the failure to obtain burley thr^u^h ^ iDrivate channels will result in t monthly deficit ©f 4lo tens a^ from June, the quota for which month will have to be supplemented by this amount (i*e* the quota of barley previously received from U*K*C»C*;* The only possible source of supply which presents itself at present, is Iran, where a _'*®d harvest has been reported. There are, however, no definite indications that this geed harvest will result in substantial supplies 01 - wheat reaching the TruciaX coast and at this stage I consider that i.t would be most unwise te rely on this possiole source to meet eur deficit* 4 . *[ would therefore request that, if the political A^ent agrees, che U*K*C*C* may kindly be requested to increase the monthly quets ©f wheat for the xrucial coast by 41o tons, commencing with the quota for the month of June,until further notice, in the event of the u«K*C*C* net being able t© meet 7 this increase with wheat, then barley may be supplied in lieu. political officer, xrucial coi’at, Sharjah*(3 Telegram From To No. important G.T.C. Political AgrCiit, Bahrain. Political Officer, Sharjah. ^ Dated the 1st May 1945. Your memorandum No. 478.1215 Apriu oGtn. 2. Food Committees Dubai and Sharjah ’Aere Aelx aware tnat we could not revert to obtaining D ^rle&gt; fra U.K.C.C. after they undertook supply xt privuteiy. .s o un to them to fulfil tneir undertaking or ou b 6 e °t feasible alternative. Please inform them accordxngly and report result. = POuIllGa-. KM5hl.C. ItA'iil Telegram cypher. ^ From H.M's. ^mbassaxior, Baghdad* To Political Agent, Bahrain* No. iin^om 19* Dated the 30th April and received 1st May, 1946 §... ■ w (§) Following for Gray Na^kenzie. Shipping shortly by ’ r Barjorn ,{ to Dubai about .660 tons wheat and to Sharjah 200 tons wheat. - AMBASSADOR - RM. I.R. 324iiXPHSSS LETTER jprom: i-he political officer, rrucial uoast, ^harj To? i'he political-Agent, Bahrain. No. 535.1215 Dated the 13th kay 1945. subject:- flheat ^uota for rrucial uoaat : Heierence your telegram no. 288 dated the 1st of i,iay 1945. comprehensive noting and correspondence on this subject it was not possible to accurately ascertain vhat the previous decision and arrange ments were regarding discontinuance of barley quota. demand for baarley on rrucial toast and none is at present being imported, special arrangements to supplement the wheat quota of 82o tons not necessary at present in view of ample stocks of rice and local harvest, should it be necessary in future to supplement wheat quota* requirements will be obtained against barter. In circumstances extra quota from U.K.C.G. not now required. 2 . in the absence in this office of It now appears Chat there is little or no political Offic Trucial ydast bharjahTelegram From To No. Sncom 23. Dated the 22nd and received 23rd May, 1D45. Following for Gray Mackenzie. Shipped per “Barjora' 1 7339 from Basra to (a) Sharjah 2437 bags wheat weighing 202,503 kilogrammes gross. (b) Dubai 8040 bags wheat weighing 663,095 kilogrammes gross. 2. Please deliver to Political Agent's nominees against payment for gross bill of lading weights. 3 . Price unchanged at Bs.351 per metric ton gros G.I.F. port of discharge less 2i$. - AMBASSADOR - ^at9 ^ ^ E.0. Cypher. K.M’s. Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Bahrain. &lt;8&gt; R.M. I.R. 373.I ■ — —UftGhiYT POiilTlCioj The 23rd May, 1345 No. 2133 - 2^/22 To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., MjbMOhANDUM Encom 23, dated the 22nc. May 1345, from - ; .h.C.L. &gt; Baghdad to Gray Mtq&amp;enzie. 2. The following consignments shipped by s.s. WBrrjoraw V333 from Basra may please be handed over to political Agent »s nominee for gross bill of lading. oo Ducal . b04G Dags of wheat weighingi 635,095 kilogrammes gross'. (b) Bhar.jan. 2457 bags of wheat weighing 202,506 kilogrammes gross. 3 . prices are as above tnat is &amp;. 351/- per metric ton gross c.i.f. port of discharge less 2j£$. ior POnifldjUi Aunifl, BAntUvlNINo.595*1210 British Agency, ^harjah. i Dated the 27th May 1945. To i (!*) The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject:- Claims of Dubai Trading Company against U*K*C*C» Memorandum . I enclose herewith a translation of a lettei and its enclosure received from the Auler of Dubai with the request that, if the political A^ent sees no objection, Messrs. Gray Maclcenzie, Bcthiain may kindly be asked to expedite settlement of the claims preferred by the Dubai Trading Company. 2. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie^ Dubai Agent informs me that he forwarded the claims when received (the last being in October 1944) to his head office at Bahrain from where they .vere referred to the U.K.C.C., Baghdad, but that, so far he has received no reply* “— r *- 42 &gt; , Trucial Coast, G^farjah.Translation of latter dax,ed the 2nd Jamadah II,^ ld6&lt;t (14-5-45) from Shaikh Said bin Maktura, huler of ojubai to the Residency Agent, oharjah* y After Compliments, I forward herewith a letter from the Food supply Company, Dubai, on the subject of their claims against UKCC. I request to invite your attention to it for favour of such action as may be deenled necessary. U.3.Translation of letter dated die 2nd Jaraadah ath.Thani, 1364 -v (14-5-45) from the undersigned to the Ruler of Dubai# After Compliments, The members of the Food Company, Dubai have the honour to submit to you the following*- This Company is due hs* 161,432-10-0 from UKCC on accoun of the shortages in respect of goods supplied by the saiu Co. (UKCC) which arrived by 33. Barala, V.350, 33. Fooshing, V.&amp;, S3. Fsang, V.36, S3. Kweiyang and 33. Wosang, V.43. The shortages were arrived at after weighing and calculating with Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie d Co.’s Agent, Dubai about 1C months ago* To explain more fully, we beg to inform you that when Captain Tandy , Political Officer, frucial Coast, was in Sharjah, he used to give us the amount of the shortages from 3ugar Subsidising Fund. Buo later, according to letter l}o.964 dated the 8th June 1944, ,we were instructed to maxe payment in full for UKCC Bill of Lading weights and to submit our claim for shortage to Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &lt;i Co., Dubai, in their capacity as agents of UKCC. We complied with that, paid the whole of the cost, and lodged our claims. But in spite of the lapse of a long period we could get no result, and our claims are ^still outstanding. As the amount is considerably large and its delay would affect this Company, we found it necessary to submit the matter to you, requesting you to refer it to the Residency Agent, Dharjah, so chat our dues may^be recovered from UKCC. Usual Dndings. 3d. Abdul Karim Faruq. '• Abdulla Arjumand for dhaikh Mustafa Abdul Latif 3d. Muhd Ali Badri ” Ahmad Aqil A^»shi ” dhaikh Muhammad dharif M Dhamanraal Isardas Damodardas Heraandas. itn.o &gt;) Telegram Cypher. From IJ.Ii's. Ambassador, Baghdad. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. No. Bncom 26. Dated the llt/i and received 12th J’me, 1945 Following for Iray Liackenzie from United Kingdom Commercial Corporation. Shipped per a.5. '‘Jarala 11 from Basra to Sharjah 1315 bags of wheat 192,368 kilogrammes gross. 2. Please deliver to Political Agent's nominee against payment for gross bill of lading weights. 3 # Price unchanged at As.••■el per metric ton ^ross C.I.F. less 2 ^, 0 . 4. Also shipped by same steamer to Bahrain for pool stocks 3070 basjs of wheat 505,030 kilogrammes gross. *1. in*. I.it. 407. Bahrain Receipt No Aa^ASCaDOA -Telegram From TO Repeated No. Dat ed u • T • U • poiiticaJ. Resident, Busnire. Po-i-iticui A^enL, Banrain/Kuv»dit/Mu.3cat. Haiiov.s. j. 06 £. nth and received x^h june i'^d. Addressed Kuwait Bahrain and Muscat repeated RatioWS• Owing, to the criticai wneat situation piease investigate and report oy telegram possibility oi reduction in your cereal quota lor 5 months July to Septemoer. Ratio 6/3 wheat to ±/5 adulterant should be maintained. Any reduction I may oe prepared to oner will be made conditional on their adhering to agreement tim rice snould be set on against total cereals vide Residency en dorsement On S Decemoer l5th iu44. VJh-i-J uO ilK hi = &gt;-rL].0. ~.( 5 ) Telegram From To No. 1064. Dated the 11th and received 12th June, 1&gt;±5. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Your telegram No. 393 dated June 6th. Trucial Coast barley stock of 6 tons v;ill probably provoke accusation from Riddle Bast Supply Centre that Trucial Coast, who elected to obtain their barley requirements through private channels (Residency endorsement No. 929-S da'ted December 13th, 1944) are feeding wholly on wheat instead of on agreed ratio of one third barley. •Inference is that wheat quota is excess. 2 . Trucial Coast imported 410 tons rice within one month and consumed it. Please keep this in mind in investigating possibility of quota reduction. 2 r ; — VX;xIiIjOvi.ik J. — R. I.R. 408. Bahrain ilecsgt No_..4./.7..Date • /A.T0 Cereal stocks on 1st June ^ ''X mmmm — mm mm mm M/ i / ^JEFAT BARLEY &gt; V v Tons Tons S726 6 ^ ^ ' 7 ' Consumption, TVheat Barley TTKRCH 939 tons 20 9 tons APRIL 590 ' 6 ' MAT 623 ' 9 ' Monthly au6ta ••• 820 tons of v^ieat. PICE. Stock on 1st June 835.10 tons; Consumption during May... 47.10.tons. Barter on rice stopped on 1st April. Pice which arrived on the Trucial Coast on barter basis before 1st April is sold at controlled price, i.e., 1st duality at R s.6/6 a Dubai maund and 2nd quality at Ps.5/2 and Ps. 5/4 a maund.Telegram From G.T.C Political Agent, Bahrain. To Britain, Bushire. ^ 0 . 424. Dated the 14th June 1945. . xv&gt; ^ Your telegram No. 1062 dated June 11th. 2, in view of critical wheat situation am prepared for possible reduction Tpuciai Coast monthly cereal quota from 12&amp;0 half 2460 to 1080 half 2160 tons for three months only. 5 . Trucial Coast will continue arrange for its ovm barley supply. 4. Your paragraph 2 noted. = POLITICAL, KMS _____Ref. Y/8 loth May 1945. x/l P/79 Tue Politicai. Resident, Persian Gulf, BUbHIRb. Wniliill tDUPPjjXlliO — ilUii-b dxiiiljd. Due to circumstances beyond our control, the now Canada. This change in source of supply will necessitate an increase in our prices and for the first cargo advised to us, tne following prices will rule:- MUbCAi &amp; TKUClAij COnbl - ID. 30/250 per metric ton gross According to M.n.o.C^ present programme our stocKS of Australian wheat at Basra will be exhausted by the end of June ana on Bahrain island some time during that month, after which times we propose delivering Canadian wheat to the Spates. Dear Sir, loading area for wheat supplies to the Persian Gulf is C.I.F. subject to a discount BiUtiAlN - ID.30/250 per metric ton gross ex store. KUWAIT -ID.26/750 per metric ton gross ex sief Basra. Yours faithfully, u.h.C.C. ^1 mi/ Sa/-d. W • auiihCKOno On Ini ctnP cil^nn i A1‘ IVn Copy to ; — M. b. d . C •' BAGiiD±iD • A. BAutialn. p . a. j^lUSCAI. P.A. ftUABxT. AMSCode. / Telegram No... ksx ..Date. From Political Resident, Bushire. To. Ambassador, Baghdad, (for M.E.S.C.) Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. -do- Muscat, -do- Kuwait. and -do- care Sind Government, Karachi No. 1126 Dated 23rd Received 24th June, 1945. V i In view of critical wheat situation I have been investigating possibility of temporary reduction of quotas of Shaikhdoms and of deductions against rice imports. (a) TRUCIAL COAST: Reduction of wheat quota by hundred (half 200) tons per month for 3 months July, August, September. (b) MUSCAT: Reduction for same period of months of quota to wheat 310 half 620 tons and Barley 190 half 380 tons against 400 half 800 tons Persian rice recently imported the details of which are 320 half 640 tons SADRA at Rs. 120 half 240 per ton and 80 half 160 tons CHAMPA at Rs. 90 half 180 per ton f.o.b. Khorrarashahr. Kuwait and Bahrain after investigation of recent reports of imports of rice. 2 Following temporary reductions now possible: 2 Further communication will be made regarding =GALL0WAY» NS.Telegram From To No. Dated (bi) I5.T.C. Babraii Receipt Political Resident, Bushlre. Political Agent, Bahrain. 1175 29th received 30th June, 1945. / My telegram 424 June 14th. Reduction of Trucial Coast cereals quota. 2. Please telegranh division on reduced wheat quota between Sharjah % and Dubai. =GALL0WAY= AMO2705 ' The Political A^ent, oairain, presents his cowplimencs The Political Officer, Traciai Coast, Sharjah. ■ Reference to previous correspondence: l^y telegram No. 404, dated the 10th June 1045. Description of enclosure. 1. Copy of telegram No. 1062, ; dated the 11th June 1D45, ; from the Political Resident) Bushire, to the political ‘ Agent, Banrain/Ku\\ait/llusca^ repeated Hallows. | dated the 14th June 1945, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Political Resident, Bushire. the 30th June 1945 Political Agency, niLuUilii Dated i'aiae and Date bub.i act : KhDUCIlOHl To Whi_Al i^UOTA 2. Copy of telegram No. 424, j auaINci' IMi'Onle OFTelegram From To m. li.T.C. \ Political Agent, Bcthraia. Political Officer, Sharjah, 45j. Dated the 30th June 1945 IMPQKTiUMf please confirm Sharjah’s share of Trucial Coast cereal quota is one fifth. POUT iCAiiV —c* f ^ . S A VINCI TELEGRAM To * Nairobi Confgov Retd s Baghdad (MESC) Bushire (PRPG) Aden(Direcon) From J M.E.3.C. No. 53 Saving. v, ; No.250 Saving. No. 10 Saving. No.194 Saving. p j ^ Dated 9th June, 1945. &gt;at9. I 0 EXPORTo OF FOODSTUFFS TO ARABIA . Reference your Savingram 16 of l*ay 29th. 1. Viuscat, Dubai and Kuwait receive monthly cereals quotas from I4E3C In agreement with the P.R.P.G. but the Centre has no objection to the additional import of 300 tons of Millet of Congo origin to which you refer. Such imports would not be made under M.E.3.C. auspices and would be wholly subject to local regulations. v 2. Imports into Mukalla bi^ private trade are a matter for the Aden Government to whom merchants should apply for their import licences. ^ \ CONFIDENTIAL Nn. 690-S. Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, 26th June, 1945. Copies forwarded with compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahraini The Political Agent, Muscat.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA POLITICAL AGENCY Department. •?/ ci) EXPRESS LETTER ^ an ORIGINAL MT5SSAG1S, sent by pout w&gt; s»vie t»*i«^raphlo expense and undue use of ike wiree, but tnteiuled to be Seated, oa receipt, with the same expedition tu&gt; il it ha&lt;i beca teleifraphed. To save sstfne Md formaiitiea It is worded aod tOgaed as il it had been tso despatched. Vj 2855 - 29/22. T' Datea Bahrain, ^&lt;14th July IS Political Officer, Slwrjah. My printed letter No, 2703-29/21 of June 30th. 2. Political Resident has recormended division of reduced Trucial Coast monthly wheat quota as 660 tons to Dubai and 160 tons to Sharjah. ^for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. S. 6. MFP—627 S&amp;P—6768—(M-1259&gt;—24-11-42—800,000.r 7^ •V. Qrs) 'f- No ^..”,9..?...Date. UKGC/d/37• Bahrein, 22nd July, 45, ^ray rmcken-ie &amp; Co Ltd#, Dubai, h r° The following is the substance oi letter received oy us from the political Agent, Bahrein : - •i j; crU JJDm 'ub'ect* claims of Dubai Trading Co., gainst U# K. C. C. The Dubai Trading Co., Dubai have claiiLea an imoLint of Re;. 161,432-10-0 from U. K. C. C . on account Df shortiiges of supplies and submitted them to your agent it Dubai. It is understood that you then reierred the natter to the U, K, C, C., Baghdad, I shall be glac to know as early as possible whether their claims are being met. 3d/- R. 3. R. BIRD, for POLITICAL AG2NT,BAHREIN.” Will you please give us all the information regarding this at your earliest convenience. c.c. Political Agent, Bahrein. AC.Telegram From 29/20 &amp; 29/22. &amp; , o No. GT~. Political 'vesidenl at Shiraz. Hiddle dost Supply ^entre, ^alro. H.M’s Ambassador, Baghdad ( FCd IlES^ ) T/156. Dated the 22nd July 1945. My telegram No. 1281 of July 12th. ^ereals stocks in tons on Tru^ial ^oast June 30th. Wheat 2x11 Barley nil Bi^e 788. 2. Bi^e has been imported in small quantities over a long ueriod and 450 half 900 tons thereof should be v/ritten off against reduction of wheat quota for current quarter suggested in paragraph 2(a) of my telegram No.1126 of 23rd June. 3. Please telegraph repeating to Political Agent Bahrain quantity of next 'consignment of wheat for Tru^ial '■’oast and when it will arrive. Galloway. 'CNFTDKNTTAL. No. ^/117. office of the Politi-al Resident, Persian Gulf. '■’amp Shiraz, i’he 22nd July 1945. '■’opy forwarded with compliments to:- 7D The Political Agent, 'Bahrain. 0 3V ?7 ( 5 &gt; 11 Telegram, Code. From. Charge D'Affaires, Baghdad. To. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 32 Dated 6th and received 3th August, 1945. (After repetition) IMPORTANT For Gray Mackenzie frok U.K.C.C. Shipped to Sharrjah pej^BARJOftA V340 2809 bags .VHhAT \ 192,838 Kilogrammes gross. 2# Please deliver to marked Agents nominated against pay ment for gross bill of lading weights price being Rupees 408 per metric ton gross less two and a half discount. Bahrain Receipt LR. I.R. No. 535 CHARGE D’AFFAIRES. jURGI-lN'I BOiil'XlCAu AGENCY, BAiiRAIN. The ath August 1945 No. 3&lt;dl5 - 29/9S To Messrs. Gray, M&amp;ekenzie &amp; Oo*, Ltd., Bahrain. ' 7 * ll Following is the text of telegram No. 32 dated the 6th August li*4o from Baghdad to G-^ay Mackenzie. 2809 bags of wheat weighing 192,838 kilogrammes gross shipped to Sharjah ex- s.s. tBarjora* V340 may please be delivered to marked agents nominated against payment for gross bill of lading weight at the price of fc. 408 per metric ton less discount. f I ^ for POLITICAL AGLNT, BAHRAIN1 °\ * No.3237-29/22 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 11th August, 1945. To The Residency Agent, SHARJAH. Reference your memorandum No.595.1210 dated the 27th May, 1945. 2. The U.K.C.C. have telegraphed to Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain that they expect to reply to them shortly regarding the claims of Ouoai Company. for Political Agent, Bahrain. AMO.if i mamTelegram. From. To. Cypher. Political Resident, at Shiraz* Political Agent, Bahrain. V* No. T/343 Dated 20th and received 22nd August 1945. For Bird from Pelly. The following message, suitably paraphrased, should be transmitted to Residency Agent, Sharjah, from me by Confidential express Letter. Begins: Trucial Coast promised to import and consume stocks * of barlex_to/ ^ starting ofr- set reduction in wheat quotas yet Barley stocks have been reported to be nil at the end of June and July. M«E*S.C. will certainly take this as reported and probably demand further reduction in wheat quotas. You should bring these xacts to notice of Shaikhs and inform them that unless they give me an assurance that the agreed ? propo rtion of Barley will be imported and consumed with Immediate effect, I shall be unable to resist demand for a further reduction of wheat quotas to take effect during coming winter and cannot be taken up for any hardship arising therefrom. Ends. * by bne change GALLOWAY. LR. I.R. No. 567 ^GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, *9 Dbpakimemt. Poll \N.B.-This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the mres, but intended to be treated, on receipt, mth the same expedition as it bad been telegraphed, lo save' time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched^ From Political* Bahrain. To Britagent, Sharjah. No. 3400 - 29/22, Dated 19$ . Bahrain, the 26th August x945* Follov/ing is the substance of telegram No.T/343 of 20th lugust from the Political Agent, Bahrain, Caup at Shiraz to trie Residency Agent, Sharjah. ’’Trucial Coast promised to make their oiffi arrange- m nts for the import of barley but none has been imported tince March 1945. Stocks of barley on the Truclal Coast vjere reported as nil at the end of June and July, and M.k.S.C. will almost certainly demand a further reduction in the wheat auita. Please bring these facts to the notice of the Shaikhs and tell them that, unless t»-ey gj-Vu me an assurance that they will import and consume the agreed proportion of barley with immediate effect, it will be impossible for me to resist a demand for a further reduction in wheat quota during the coming winter. If that should occur any hardship arisiiig therefrom would be on them.” Rods. ms S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000. J POLITICAL AliANT, .it, tRAIIJ.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER t B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,} CONFIDENTIAL, From Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, SHIRAZ . To Political Agent, BAHRAIN at Shiraz. Political Agent, KUWAIT at Shiraz. No. C/191. Dated 18th August lofcS 19&amp;S. Reference my telegram No.1065 dated 11th June 1945 (not repeated to Kuwait). BARLEY. 2. Barley stocks both at Kuwait and on Trucial Coast have been reported to be nil at the end of June and July. M.E.S.C. will certainly take this up and probably demand a reduction in wheat quotas. We have accepted the principle of adulteration of wheat or wheat flour because of their short supply and unless you can obtain an assurance tnat the agreed proportion of barley will be imported and consumed with immediate effect it will be impossible to refuse a demand for the revision of wheat quotas. Sd. A.C.GALLOWAY. » Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED . fdl* Secretary to Political Resident, Persian Gulf, RHL. S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P-(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA; Department* EXPRESS LETTER [N. B'—This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed, as if 'it had been so despatched*] From - Britagent, Sharjah. Na % 948.1225 Sharjah, 25th September 194S33 Subject: Imports of Barley . Your express letter No. 5400-29/22 dated 26th August 1945. 2. I have addressed the Shaikhs of Dubai and Sharjah in terms of the Political Agent, Bahrain’s telegram No.T/543 dated 20th August 1945 and the following is a gist of their reply:- Tt Import of barley into the Trucial Coast depends on the opening of barter by the Agency. v fe .have actual3.y issued ’Alans to that effect as a result of which a substantial amount of barley has been imported from Tran and Iraq. Further quantities will continue to be imported as long as barter is allowed and the price of sugar and tea is good abroad. We hope that this will help in preventing a reduction in the Trucial Coast’s wheat quota during the coming winter.” 3. Barter for barley was opened by me as a result of which about 450 tons have so far been imported and taken over by the Dubai Food Company. Further consignments will be arriving and it is expected that Imports will continue so long as the price of sugar and tea is good in Persia. s. 6. MFP—785S&amp;P—(M-1014)—18-8-33—'2,00 000.29/1 &amp; 29/22 No* 936 r S* The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait/Bahrain/Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents* Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire* Dated the 18th Novmeber 1945. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure* Name and Date* Subject* Extract from British Supply Mission (M.E.) Memorandum No* 11140 dated the 5th November Wheat for the Persian 1M5. ^ £ ‘ ^ Gulf Shaikhdoms. Residency Express Letter No* 931-3, dated the 15th November 1945* ^Extract from raemD»andum No* 11140 dated the 5th November 1945 ? from the Director^ British Supply Mission, Middle East, Cairo* Wheat for the Persian Gulf Are&amp;* With the closing down of M*E.S.C* the responsibility for maintaining supplies of wheat to the P.G*A. devolves upon this Mission. As, however, the Mission has no representative in Ifcaq, releases will in future be made from Cairo and we understand that all correspondence in this connection should be addressed to you. 2. Commitments in the P.G.&amp;. are as follows These quotas are liabie to minor adjustments, a s it has been the practice to reduce them ton for ton for any rice which may reach the Sheikhdoms through private channels. Information in this respect has in the past hx been supplied by the P.R. P.G. and it is hoped that he will continue to forward this information. Allocations have already been made covering the above requirements until the end or November and we shall in due course request you to arrange for the release of the December quotas under a British Supply Mission Serial Number. (a) The standard monthly quotas for the Shaikhdoms are s- Trucial Coast 820 tons Muscat Kuwait Bahrain 2.600 tons MSGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, DBPA.RTMINT, EXPRESS LETTER fxY. B.— This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, f/ut intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if U had been telegraphed, lo save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. The Honourable the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire. The British Supply Mission (Middle East), Cairo. No* 931-3. Dated 15th November, &amp; 'h ' ^ l /&gt;&gt; 6 Wheat for the Pe6sfcan Gulf area . / Reference pragraph 2(a) of your memorandum No. 11140 dated the 5th November 1045. 2. The statement that it has been the pradtice to reduce the wheat quotas of the Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms ton forton for any rice which may reach them through private channels is incorrect, as the M.E.S.C. had accepted the principle of the set-off of rice against |11 cereals i.e. not against wheat only but against the total quotas of wheat and barley and/or millet. Please see in thi^. connection my telegram No.2197 dated 8th December 1944 and connect! ? No.2rdated the 14th December 1944 (copy enclosed for fgady reference). As the agreed proportions of wheat to adulterants are two-thirds and one-third, this m^ans in Effect that reductions in wheat quotas amount to two-thirds of the tonnage of rice imported. Information regarding rice imported into the Shaikhdoms will be furnished as hitherto together with recommendations for consequent reductions in wheat quotas. Sd. Geoffrey Prior. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. Sd. J.Croning. for Secretary to the Political s.6. Resident,in Persian Gulf. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2-3() -200,000 KWTqPOLITICAL AGfciNCY, BAHRAIN. No. 4914 - 29/22. The 29th November 1945. The Residency Agent* Sharjah. Mi^QRANDUM Wheat for Trucl^i.Coast . With the closing down of Middle East Supply Centre the responsibility for maintaining supplies of wheat to Persian Gulf area has been taken up by the British Supply Mission* Middle East* Cairo. Future releases of quotas from December 1945 will be made by this Mission. The Mission has no representative in Iraq and releases will be made from Cairo. S' i &amp; % for POLITICAL AUKNT, BAHRAIN.Telegram i£n Clair* From Political Resident, Nearchus, Bahrain Radio. To Political Agent, Bahrain. * No. T/716. Dated the 12th December 1945. Following is repetition of British Supply Mission Middle Bast Cairo Telegram No.7 December 11th. Begins: Cereals for the Shaikhdoms. With effect from January 1st the Basra Offices of the U.K.C.C. will be utilised only for the handling of documents invoicing and collection of payments. 2. Allocation of cereals to the Shaikhdoms will continue to be made by this Mission and it is suggested by the II.K.C.C. London tnat the sales against these allocations should in future be made by U.K.C.C. Basra to establisned reputable firms such as Btricks African and Bastern Gray Mackenzie on C.I.F. terms cash against documents it then being the responsibility of the firm to arrange storage distribution and sale to the territory concerned. It is further suggested tmat the firms would be re quired to continue this procedure so long as the allocation system is operated by this Mission. I 3. Please comment urgently upon this proposal if it is acceptable to you U.K.C.C. will then approach one or other of the firms concerned with a view to seeing whether the foregoing suggestion is practicable. finds. 2. Please telegraph your views. PRIORTelegram From To No. 2 . involved. KMS i2n Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resid nt on board Nearchus. 867. Dated the 14th December 1945. Your telegram T 716 of December 12th. Cereals. No objection provided no increase price at POLITICALr No -5162 - 29/22 (!) The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, SHARJAH. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentiond document ( s ) for inforaation. Thb Agbncy, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Date thel?th-December 1945^ - Reference to previous correspondence : Discript'ion of Enclosure. Name and Date. % !• Telegram No. T/716, dated the 12th December 1945, from the Political Resident, Nearchus, Bahrain Radibo, to the Political Agent, Bahraini 2. Telegram No,867, dated the 14th December 1945 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Political Resident on board Neachus. Subject, CiiRKALB FOR THA SHAIKHD04S,teai*j\ 4 2 ifi (S&gt; °f I relegram iin Clair. ^rom Co Political Resident, Bushire. British Supply Mission, Middle Bast Repeated Political, Bahrain/Kuwait/Muscat. fo. 1822 Coolie. r*' Your telegrams ind Four coilie December 19th. A Seven coolie December 11 th Cereals for Shaikhdoms. 2. No objection to procedure being adopted it Bahrain Muscat and Trucial Coast provided no increase In price is involved. Gray Mackenzie is only firm that could be employed. As alternative Bahrain government are prepared to purchase their own ^uota direct from U.K.C.C. leaving to Gray Mackenzie handling of cereals stores in Bahrain for transhipment. 3. Kuwait quota is at present handled by Government Agent Ahmed A1 Abdul Latif A1 Hammad who takes over wheat at Basra and arranges storage and shipment to Kuwait. As he is reputable merchant of extensive means Kuwait Government request and I recommend that his services be retained. =PRIOii&amp;UNITED KINGDOM COMMERCIAL CORPORATION (Iraq), Ltd. Please be advised that the Head Office of this Corporation will be transferred to BASRA and as from the 1st January 1946 our only address in Iraq will be :— 3/z/lO Mandil Road, Ashar, BASRA . Telephone No. 02-547. {Incorporated In England) telephone no. 4136/7 The/Messrs. Political Arcnt, BAHREIN G. BARFOOT CARE, CHIEF REPRESENTATIVE \(3 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAKRAIN• No. 35 - 29/22. The 5th January 1946. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, MEMORANDUM The Head Office of the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation (Iraq), Ltd., is transferred to Basra and as from 1st January 1946 their address in Iraq is 3/2/10 Mandil Road, Ashar, Basra. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMS/ Telegram From To No. August. G.T.C. / Political Office^, Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain. 38 . Dated the 12th January' 1946. A (§&gt; Your memorandum No. 3237* dated the 11-th Claims of Dubai Food Company from U.K.C.C. Grateful if settlement of claims is expedited as Food Company is pressing. POLITICAL KMS Bahrain Receipt NTo ... A $ Date 1No. 179 - 29/22. To Messrs. Gray* • (5) ' POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 15th January 194-6. Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Please refer to your dated the 6th August 194-5. endorsement No. UKCC/D/4-0, 2 I shall be glad if the of the Dubai Trading Company can settlement of the claims be expedited. Yours' faithfully, Ir^l' for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMSGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltl». (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND; HEAD OFFICE.*^ 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C 3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BRANCHES: BUSR EH A M A R A H KUT KHORAMSHAH R AH WAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BAI SHARJAH MUSCAT Bahrein, IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no. JJKCC/G/7. 19th January, jg 46. H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. No ~ pi».Receipt Dear Sir, We have for acknowledgement your letter No.179 - 29/22 of the 15th instant regarding settlement of the claims of the Dubai Trading Company. Copy of our letter to our Dubai Office in this connection is attached, and we will write you further in this matter on receipt of their reply. Yours faithfully. Tor 8IUY, M A ( ’KKN7JK * Oo^ U*FROM TO Mackenzie &amp; Co# DUBAI • GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO., LTD. Gray, BAHRSIK mmmw no..^TOCC/D/4 17 t.b..January» 19..4.6. 276 Bags Wheat ex 3 &gt;s» tf Barala w V«357 . W© refer to your letter TTD/F00D/52 of the 2 lst July last, and attach hereto copies of letters In this connection received from U*K»C#C» Baghdad* Xt will he observed that U»K*U*0« consider that these claims snould have oeen submitted through the Political Resident Persian Gulf, and as requested in their letter X/l(e) of the 2lst Kovembor, 1945 / shall be olease^to receive,if any f copies of correspondence passed betweer yourselves and the Rulers of Sharjah and Dubai and/or between yourselves and the Political Agent or P.R.P.G* Tor gray, macthwhs A u* / Ends SNo. 262 - 29/22 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 23rd January 1946 To The Political Office?, Trucial Coast, SHARJAH. MEMORANDUM V V Reference your telegram No. 38 , dated the 12th January 1946. 2. A copy of letter No. U—CC/D/4, dated the l?th January 1946, from Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, to their Dubai office is enclosed herewith for information for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAINNo.182.1215 &amp;Cf British Agency, Sharjah. ^ Dated 16th february 1946. -r.i A. C • W *. Date To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum . In view of the serious world shortage of grain may I kindly be informed if I should anticipate a reduction in the monthly quota of 820 tons of wheat supplied for the Trucial Coast and endeavour to build up a reserve by reducing issues to the Shaikhdoms? « i S rt ^7 Political Officer, Coast, Trucial Sharjahc0 u2&gt; No. 621 - 29/22. To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 23 rd Febru=ary 1946'. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, SHARJAH. r. MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No. 182.1215, dated the l 6 th February 194-6. 2. We have not received any intimation that reduction will be made but I think it probable that this will take place. Please let me know, without making public enquiries, what reduction in your opinion the Trucial Coast could make if called upon to do so. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMSNo. 1070 - 29/22 To The Political Officer Trucial Co POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 4th April 1946. MEMORANDUM With effett from 1st April 1946 the United kingdom Commercial Corporation Offices in Cairo and Basrah are being taken over by the Ministry of Food, and the work hitherto performed by the United Kingdom Corporation in respect of pooled {stocks of cereals and sugar will be undertaken after that date by the Ministry of Food. r~ for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN KMS29/1 &amp; 29/22. G.T.C. Britain, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain/Muscat. ^ 572. Dated the l?th April 194-6. ✓f^i' endorsement 438 S April 11th. 2. Ministry of Food Basrah advise space secured for the following wheat shipments (a) By Barjora sailing second half of April 150 tons Sharjah 550 tons Dubai 590 tons Bahrain. (b) by Dalgoma sailing May 640 tons Sharjah 180 tons Dubai 400 tons Muscat. = BRITAINNo. 1215 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The iPth April 1946. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, SHARJAH. MEMORANDUM The Ministry of Food Basrah informs me that space has been secured for the following wheat shipments: (a) by s.s. Barjora sailing during second half of April, 150 tons for Sharjah and 550 tons for Dubai. (b) by s.s. Dalgoma sailing during May, 640 tons for Sharjah and 180 tons for Dubai. f for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.r\ r No. 1298 - 29/22. To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAIHiAIN. The 27th April 1946 &lt;1 The Political Officer, Trueial Coast, SHARJAH. MEMORANDUM Reference my express letter Uo.C/1539 dated the 31st January 1945. 2. It is requested that private purchases of barley should be arranged as far In advance as possible so that shipments can be suitably spread, as the number Ox vessels at present available for the British S* India Steam Navigation Co,, Ltd.,* s Persian Gulf service is limited. o According to present anticipations there ^e five departures of steamers from Basrah during the months of April and May 1946. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KESr i) Extract from British Middle E asjLP rQflrcss Report for February l_9_4o . Wheat . The stocks nov/ held in the Middle East, or likely to be held in the area over the coming months, constitute no more than the barest working stock. They include no reserves and the forward proygamne of the British Supply Mission can aim no higher than to insure that the grain required for consumption in any one month shalj ariive in the territory during the previous month. Supplies may consist of North American wheat or Australian flour and territories will have no choice nor will they have more than one or two week's notice of 'whether wheat or flour is being allocated to them. No. 442-S. Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. 13th April 194-6. Copy forwardecf, ^/ith compliments, to The Political Agent, Kuwait/Bahrain/Muscat. No. 134-2 - 29/22. Copy forwarded to:- POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 29th April 194-6. for information The Political Officer, . , Trucial Coast, Sharjah, Sd/- H.D.H.RANGE, for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMSdu Telegram From To G T C Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain (No.666), Political Agent, Muscat (No.665) Political Agent, Kuwait (by bag) the 30th April 194-6. Dated / / Examination of your cereals consumption figures for the first quarter of 194-6 show that (a) Muscat has exceeded its wheat quota in January and February (b) All states particularly Muscat have consumed less than adulterant they should have (half of wheat consumed). 2 # Please impress on state necessity at this critical juncture of (1) Not allowing consumption of wheat to exceed quota. (3) Consume full proportion adulterant. ( 3 ) Taking every step possible to prevent waste and to conserve supplies. PRIOR No. 1409 - 29/22 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 4th May 1946. Copy forwarded tos- The Political Officer . UI J. , Trucial Coast, SHARJAH for information • e for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN KMS11140 BRITISH SUPPLY MISSION (MIDDLE EAST) 10, SHARIA TOLUMBAT, »c CAIRO. ‘ 21st May* 1946* The Political Agent, BAHREIN, WHEAT FOR TRUCIAL COAST 1, Reference your letter No, 1433-29/20, dated the 7th of May, 1946, 2, From the information contained in your letter under reference, our estimate of the Trucial Coast * s forward position in regard to wheat supplies, is as follows :« 3» These total availabilities of, say, 4,100 tons, are sufficient to meet Trucial Coast 9 s requirements of 820 tons per month until the 30th of September, 4* Because of the critical world wheat shortage, which has now shown its full effect on the Middle East, we had no alternative but to request all territories to whom we supply wheat to eat down their own slender reserves, „ This they did,®*, and as a result, they are now living on a hand to mouth basis. You will, t here fore, appreciate that the Trucial Coast is in a far better position T»~T»ther consumers in the Middle East, 5, In view of the foregoing, we should be most grateful if you would kindly agree to the Trucial Coast foregoing at least two months supply of wheat, i,e, 1,640 tons, which would still leave them with 3 months reserves. Such a saving would be a great help in alleviating the precarious position of Pool Stocks at the present time* 6, May we please have a reply at your earliest convenience. Stocks on May Isrt 2,443 Adds Their April allocation which has been released but which has not yet been shipped. 820 Their May allocation which has been released but which has not yet been shipped 820 Total Availabilities 4,083 for DIRECTOR-GENERAL,Jlo. 1743 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGEHCY, BAHRAIN. The 2nd June 1946. To The British Supply Mission (Middle East), 10, Sharia Tolumbat, Cairo, iw \ / MEMORANDUM Referonce your meraorand'cun No, 1140, datod the 21st May 1946. 2 # The wheat reQuirements of the Trucial Coast are being re-examined, and it is agreed that in the meanwhile the allocationsfor April and May need not be shipped. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.The fir»t line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named Prefix letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin Number of Words, Date, Time handed In and Official instructions—if any. , QlfrinU/ri Jui iKriKland. Sept. 1941. (1,200 pads) &gt; CABLE AND WIRELESS (MID-EAST) LIMITED. 6/-184 Clark’* Time Circuit. Name. Received. H:CG, 1 125 o ( VO \t\\~ I XASV26 3 CAIRO 44 U 2^30 uG POLITICAL BAHaEIN 000LIL 09712 YOUR LETTER DATtJ 2uD JURE 1946 2 WE ^'tSUl.'u (RUCIAL COAST AGREE TO THE CAilCt-LLAT I ON OF TTO mONTHS SUPPLIES OF si/HEAT FROI.I POOL STOCKS AND HOT JUST A DEF El-Uv'.ti. f OF APRIL ftUD LaY LOhTHLY SHI PL ENTS j PLEASE OOi+F I RM .EARL I EST REPLY^ ' € Dia JmA&amp;ualZ NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. REPLIES SHOULD BE HANDED IN AT ONE OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.Telegram From To No. 13th June. cancellation En Clair. Political, Bahrain. \ ! Merain, Cairo. 351. Dated the 20th June 1946. Reference your coolie 09712 dated Confirmed that Trucial Coast agree to of two months wheat supplies. POLITICALRef: 11140 10, SHARIA TOLUMBAT, CAIRO. 13th June, 1946. Ministry of Food 14, Sh. Darih Saad, CAIRO . V FOR TII^ TdhOIkh CO ST The Trucial Coast have accumulated a surplus of wheat from past allocations and we therefore requested them to forego tv;o months* supplies of wheat from pool stocks at Basrah. The Political Agent, Bahrein, in reply, has now informed us that the Trucial C 0 ast»s wheat requirements are being re-examined and, for the present, their allocations for April and May need not be shipped. two months* supolies and, before we can offi cially cancel releases already effected, we are requesting further clarification. 3* In view of the foregoing, will you kindly suspend the shipment of their lay and June quotas (I .S.LI. Release Serials os .87 and 107) and not their April and May quotas as, in all obaility, the April quota has now been shipped or shipping arrangements may have already been’ concluded. 2* This statement, however, does no necessarily imply that they agree to forego This statement, however, docs not Copy to The Political Agent, Political Agency, ’ , ■ .IN . &lt;&gt;'GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, c£&gt; Defartmint, EXPRESS LETl'ER [«V. Ik —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition if it had been telegraphed. To sace time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. 1 i To BRITAGENT, SHARJAH. L &amp; 1 r tfa, 1964 - 29/22. Bahrain, the 22nd June 1946 Reference your memorandum No.511.1235 of May 1st, 1946. Wheat. 2. In view of the large stocks of wheat accumulated by the Trucial Coast from the surplus left over from past allocations the British Supply Mission (M.E.), Cairo, has requested that the Trucial Coast's wheat quota for May and June 1946 be cancelled. Accordingly I have agreed to the cancellation of wheat shipments amounting to 1640 tons only. POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised I// - Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. v ' KMS S. 6. MFi‘—4003&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.29/3 &amp; 29/22 4 a GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [iV. R ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sare telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime and formalities it is woraed and signed as if it had been so despatched,] FfcOM A To Political Resident, Persian Gulf, at Bahrain, y* Political Agent, Bahrain. No, c/311. Dated the 19th June 1946/30: Reference Residency telegram No. 1822 dated 22nd December 1945. \V? 2. Copy is enclosed of letter No.PG/1 dated 11th May 1946 from the British Ministry of Food (Middle East) Cairo, regarding the future procedure for distribution of the wheat quotas of the Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms. The wij'ingness of the Bahrain Government to purchase the Stated quota direct from the U.K.C.C. Basra (the predecessors of the Ministry of Frod fiddle East7) has already been expressed, vide your Express Letter No. 5 jL$ 6-29/1 dated 18th December 1945? and confirmation is requested thafy they agree to the procedure now proposed. 3 . Please comment on the possibility of extending the proposed procedure to the Trucial Coast, Sd. W.R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. Sd.J.Croning. for Secretary to the -Political Resident, Persian Gulf. t CO^ s a. MFP—400S&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.Reference PG/1. Date 11th May 194-6. The British Ministry of Food (Middle East) 14 Darih Saad, Cairo. The Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BH^hljie Supplies of wheat to Bahrain We have been asked by the British Supply Mission (ME) to release to Bahrain Government a total quantity of 2583 tons of wheat, additional to the 590 tons recently shipped from Bsra per s.s. 'Barjora'. This total quantify of 3173 tons will, it is estimated by the B.S.M., meet Bahrain requirements until approximately mid-June. The above release wi 1 be effected by direct discharge from the s.s.'Fort Finlay' expected at Bahrain about the end of this month. As you are aware, it was in the past the practice of UKCC to hold part of the Persian Gulf pool stock at Bahrain. It will be appreciated, however, that current supply conditions render it impossibelfor us to ioo^ in Bahrain stocks for several months in advance, and it is not our intention to ship to Bahrain quanitifeies the release of which cannot be afforded in present circumstances. Wheat stocks will not, therefore, be held at Bahrain henceforward as Ministry of Food property. 2. The pssibility has been studied of supplying Bahrain regularly by direct discharge of parcels, separately manifested and stowed, from incoming ocean carriers. However, practic ally all cargoes at present coming forward both to the Red Sea dn P.G. area are in vulk and therefore cannot be handled at Bahrain, and in any case shipowners, whose control over their own vessels is now absolute, are not prepared to accept the delays involved in discharge at Bahrain. In the case of the 'Fort Finlay' we were ablfc fortunately to arrange for the cargo to be bagged and consigned as a whole to Bahrai^, to meet both East Saudi A abian requirements as well as those of the Bahrain Sheikhdom, but do not anticipate being able to make any similar arrangement in the future. 3 We understand hov/ever that the feeder shipping posi tion in the Persian Gulf, difficulties in connection with which constituted the principal reason for the maintenance In the past, of a Bahrain pool stock and for the discharge at Bahrain, of ocean carriers, is now greatly improved and that the shipment of regualr supplies to Bahrain from pool stocks which we shall continue to maintain in Basra will be easy to arrange. This being so, there appears to be no reason why su riles for Bahrain should not be made on the basis of the sale of delivery orders on these Basra stocks, to Bab rain Government or its accredited qgent. 4 In the case of the delivery recently effected by us per ss.‘ 'Barjora', as was the case v/ith UKCC deliveries other than those from Bahrain pool stocks in the past, we were in effect employing an agent - Messrs. Gray Mackenzie - to take the wheat to Bahrain. It appears to us to be just as simple for Bahrain Government to employ an agent to take delivery of the wheat from Basra, paying 4n advance for delivery order and making the necessary arrangements for transport, and insurance if required, from the point of delivery ex store Basra. In acceptance wuch conditions the Government of Bah rain would merely be fa T ing into line with prodedure established elsewhere between ourselves and othe ^S°vern- ments receiving Ministry of Food supplies under BSM a. loca tions and, whilst the special difficulties of the Persian Gulf are fully appreciated, as is the fact that the supply /ofof foodstuffs from Basra at all instead of from India consti tutes a departure from the normal economy of the area, we nevertheless feel that ±± it should now be possible for the Governments in the Persian Gulf to employ agents to take delivery rather than expect us to continue indefinitely employing agents to effect delivery. 5. * We shall be grateful therefore if you will inform Bahr in Government that for deliveries subsequent to that shortly to be effected ex ss. 'Fort Finlay' we propose that the following procedure shll be adopted. 6. Our Basra Ofice will, on receipt of the BSM release through ourselves, inform Bahrain of the quntity of the release and its ex store value. Bahr- in will then be re quired to deposit the value of the parcel with our o Tice in Basra at the same time giving our Bsra 0 Tice the name of their representative who wi 1 take delivery ex store Basra. We do not of course wish to oblige the Bah^iAn Government’s representative to take delivery until an opportunity presents itself for shipment. What we do wish to establish is that, when such shipping opportunity does offer, responsibility for taking delivery ex store and arranging shipment will rest with the Bahrain Government's representative. 7. We trust that you will confirm to us as soon as possible the agreement of the Bahrain Government to this procedure for the future. Will you please inform us also Y/hether our channel of communication with BahrdAn Government should be through yourself or through the Political Agent in Bahrain. 8. We would appreciate your comments on the possibility of extending the above prodedure - i.e. of delivery against payment in Basra to receiver's agent in Basra - to the other releases we are at present making to Muscat and the Trucail Coast, and to any others we may be aalled upon to make. We shall be grateful for any assistance you can render us towards ensuring that our own activities in the Persian Gulf area should henceforward be limited to the maintenance of and delivery from Bsra pool stocks. 9. We would grateful if you would copy your reply to our Basra Office, the address of which is: c/o Frank Strick &amp; Co., Ltd., B$sra. Sd. P.D.MULHOLLAND Chief Executive Officer Middle East.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbpartmjint, EXPRESS LETTER [A . 7&gt;, This is cm OT\l(ilNAL M.T!SSAQT!^ sunt by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded aud signed as if it had been so despatched,] 2$11 - 29/22* Bahrain, rw&amp;s the 24th June 1946iXJC IkeAt supplies for Truclal Coast. A copy is enclosed of letter No.PG/1, dated the 11th May 1946 from the British Ministry of Food (Middle East), Cairo, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident. Please let me have your comments urgently on the possibility of extending the proposed procedure to the Trucial Coast. From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN BRITAGENT, SHARJAH. POLITICAL The Issue of the above has been authorised Assistapt Political Agent, BahrAln S. 6. MF1’—4003&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00.000.Ko • 673. • 1210 British Agency, ghferjah* Dsted 26th June, 1946. To, The political A£,ent, Bahrein. C 473.330 tons of v/i^et consignee in the na&amp;e of the Ruler of Bubei was lanaeci et Sharjah by S.&amp;. Barpeta on the 2nd of June 1946 and aelivered to the Sharjah Food Company. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.i agents of the British Supply Mission, Middle Best, have now submitted their bill of iis.202697. 1.0 representing cost of this consignment to the Ruler of Dubai for payment. As this consignment has been lended in Sharjah, the Sharjah Food Co. will have to pay its cost and they are prepared to do so. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie have therefore asked for authority from us to enable them to alter their bill in the name of the Ruler of Sharjah. 2. May the necessary authority be given?KMS y No. 2100 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 1st July 194-6. To The Political Officer, Trueial Coast, SHABJAH. MFMOPANDUM Reference your memorandum No.601.1210, dated the 25th June 1946. 2. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., may be authorised to alter the bill accordingly. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAINGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B ,— This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by jtosl to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, lo save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.'] Feom political, Sharjah political, in No No. 719.1215 Dated 5th July, 1946 jSX Subject*- wheat supplies for Trucial Coa&amp;t * Your Express letter Mo♦2oll i *29/22 Gated. 24th July, 1946. 2. I would prefer, if possible, not to have the present procedure of wheat shipments to the Trucial Coast changed, but do consider that the suggested procedure of delivery against payment in Basrah to our agent there, is quite possible. I have consulted the Food companies here on the subject, ana in the event of the new prodaure being adopted, we would appoint Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. as our agents at Basrah and are prepared to pay commission at the usual rates. 3 . X anticipate that our wheat supplies w/ould be less regular under the new procedure as compared with direct shipments from the British supply Kiission (kE)« / opV&amp;in political officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah.s&gt; GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, „ Depabtminx, LETTER [.V. P&gt;.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sarg telegraphic' expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From To Political Agent, Bahrain, The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. tfo, 2227 - 29/1. Bahrain, thued the 11th July 194033 Reference your express letter No. C/311 of June 19th, 1946. 2. It is confirmed that the Bahrain Government agree to the procedure proposed. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. at Basrah will be appointed as their pirrehasing and shipping agents for future supplies of wheat after the consignment ex f, Fort Finlay”. 3 . I consider the proposed procedure could be extended to the Trucial Coast and in that event Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie dc Co., Ltd., would be appointed as the agents at Basrah. = POLITIC AL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/- H.D.H.RANGE. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. t S. 6. MFi’— 400S&amp;P-(M-480)-26-7-34—2,00 UOO.I ■ VI GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS EETTER (AIR MAIL), &amp; t [S.B.—This ia an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR ifinTendld to be treated, expeditious than the ordinary mail and is eheape) than the J 1 j T save time and to obviate on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been f^Se^icated by ^ * » a formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is aiUhenhcatea oy , y responsible officer o f the Department^ ^ ^ p olitic? . 3 ROGld^nt, ?eT?\'n ^ ' , No. C/476 . To Repeated Camp, Bahrain, ^ the 1 6 th July 1946. 1Jaie xmo BMlfc* British Ministry of Food (Middle Fast), 19 14, Darih Saad, CAIRO, Briiyi^h Ministry of Food Office, V2/10 Mendi] Road, Ashar, Basra. - - ^ ■ X Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Agent, Musc-t. v ' 3 /T Reference vour letter Ho. PG/1 dated 11th May 1946 regarding supplies' of wheat to Persia- Gulf Shaikhdons. 2. Bahrain Governnent agree to introduction of Prosed procedure and wi 1 ! appoint Mes rs. Gray, t-aekenz^ ^ j’ Bas^a, as their purchasing and dipping agents for supp^.^o wheat a''ter the consignment ex s s. Po. * f^i^Ad-friser 'to the pn^-rpqnondenoe mav he conducted direct with the Aavl. Government of Bahrain. Questions of policy may, however, continue to be referred to me (with a copy to the Pol ' • - Agent, Bahrain, to ^aeili^ate reference. o Prnopduve could also be introduced in respect of 3 . iroceau^e couia ctj Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie suuPlles to Trucial Coast and Muscau,^ ; . v_ Tr , nr*la'i Rr Cn T 1 vi Basra, would he appointed as agents for the True. Const *also'£or this purpose. Muscat Government is already importinMits barleyMunnlies through agents in Basra and the ;',l e . „ e nts could handle the Ststels wheat quota. ^ ■ ; inttmarg when it is proposed to introduce new procedure in respect of these Sites'so that they can be asked to conclude tbeir arrangements, 4 It would be appreciated if a monthly return o^.ysueS from Basra, quoting price, could be sent to me and to the .oil Agents of the Shaikhdoms concerned. Sd. W.R.HAY, Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested . Sd. J.Croning. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. - (Sigmtui e) ( Designation) S. 14. gjFP—8J5S&amp;T—(M-1070) 14*9-34 10,0C0.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—Thit is an ORIGINAL messtge tint by AIR MAIL which provides a meant of communication mors expeditious than the ordinary mail and it cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to be treated, on receipt, with the tame expedition as if it hai been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a reapondible officer ojthe Department.]^ ^^ g of the Political Re S idCH t, PerS ian Gul No. C/534. Bahrain &gt; Dated the 24 th July To Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 29 46 . #«A A' &gt;1 Reference Paragraph 3 of my Kxpress Letter No.G/476, ^ dated the 16th July 1946. Wheat supplies to Persian Gulf ShaiJkhdoms. 2. Ministry of Pood are prepared to introduce new procedure immediately. Please ask State or States concerned to conclude ilixxx arrangements urgently and instruct their agents to confirm to Ministry of Pood Basra as soon as possible their readiness to purchase supplies ex; warehouse Basra. Sd. W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Sw Attested * for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL. P sh Ta ^n R6C6J Date S. 44. (Signature) (Designaiion) MGIPC——2385(S&amp;P)MFP—(M-1744)—3-12-40—20,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depabtmbnt, EXPRESS LETTER [N , B % —1 his is an ORIGINAL MJGSSAGN, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of doe wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] No. 243? - 29/22. Bahrain, Dated the 2?th July 194#» . o/ /If * Your express letter No. 719.1215 of July 5th, 1946. Wheat supplies to Trucial Coast. 2. Ministry of Food are prepared to introduce new procedure immediately. Please conclude arrangements urgently and instruct the Trucial Coasts agents to confirm to Ministry of Food, Basra, as soon as possible, their readiness to purchase supplies ex: warehouse Basra. Fbom POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To POLITICAL, SHARJAH. POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMS s. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820&gt;—23-7-36—300,000.-V - GOVERNalENT OF INDIA, DaPARIMRUT. EXPRESS LETTER [iV % B ,—This is an ORIGINAL MNSSAGN, sent by •post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To No. 2738 - 29/22. Bahrain, Dated 21st August 194-6. . Reference my express letter No. 2435-29/22 of July 27th, 1946. Wheat supplies to Trucial Coast. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &lt;5c Co., Ltd., regarding the arrange ments for shipment of wheat supplies to the Truc#ll Coast: Ministry of Food in Basra, jrou will write by air mail your requirements to Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Basra, with a copy to their Office in Bahrain, advising the Trucial Coast's requirements. Gray Mackenzie in Basra will approach the Ministry to ascertain the cost of the wheat required, to which they will add the estimated charges from warehouse Basra to C.I.F. Trucial Coast, and advise you of the G.I.F. cost. You will then arrange for payment Cc Cray Mackenzie in Basra through the Bank in Dubai. A (ii) Shipments are to be made in double bags and the weight wi'l be based on a percentage basis, particulars of which will be decided later on. Slack bags are to be weighed separately. It was suggested that 5% of the total shipment might be weighed. (iii) Shipments are not to be made by local craft but by steamships only. sare lime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To BRITAGENT, SHARJAH. (i) When you decide to purchase from the British (iv) S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.13 2 (iv) As shipments will be made in double bags, it is hoped that Gray Mackenzie in Basra * will be able to obtain a clean Bill of Lading from the ship, and therefore, the carriers will be responsible for any difference between the v/eight delivered on board at Basra and the weight delivered by the carriers at destination. (v) Buyers require complete cover by insurance. (vi) It has been agreed that Gray Mackenzie will receive remuneration at the rate of 1% of the C.I.F* va l u ® the shipments, i.e. 1% to Gray Mackenzi* Basra and 1.% to Gray Mackenzie agent at Dubai. 3* Please let me have your comments after discussing with the Food Company, urgently. POLITICAL r The issue of the above has been authorised &gt;V * Captain. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMSc fJS V ir^ No. 278? - 29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY| BAHRAIN. The 26th August 194-6. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. MEMORANDUM Reference my express letter No. 2238 - 29/°2, dated the 21st August 194-6. 2. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., have now informed me on the subject of Insurance. Their London office has agreed to quote cover as under ° Corn Trade F.P.A. clauses, including theft, pilferage, non-delivery, short-delivery, shortage including fresh water '. 3. The charges Gray Mackenzie quote for this cover are 6 sh. per £ 100/- plus 5 sh. 6 d. per £ 100/- Combined Marine Surcharge. The charge for the cover of war risks and S.B.C.C. (Strikes, Riots and Civil Commotions) will be 1 sh. per £ 100/-. 4. Will you please confirm that the above cover and rates are satisfactory to you, and also state if you require cover against Strikes, Riots and Civil Commotions (1 sh. per £ 100/-). 4 Captain, for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN KMSGOVERNsIENT OP INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [,V. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, bnl intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it hart aeon so despatched.] Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Political Agent* Bahrain , Political Agent« Muscjrt , (Middle East) Monthly Letter No.9. 2. Please report whether any reduction in the wheat Kuwait quota of Bahrain and Trucial Coast is possible during the Muscat x ^ period September - December 194-6, and if so to what extent. Attested . Sd. E.Thomas. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. /CO KMS S.6. Mjrp—1206 8&amp;P—&lt;M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000*. From at Bahrain To Political Agent. Kuwait C/750 Dated 25th August /531-6. Sd. W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian GulfExtract fron British Supply Mission (Middle East) Monthly Letter No.? for July 194f&gt;. FOOD SECTION . CEREALS . 1. ■ •' r hoat/FlQ iffi. As predicted In our June Monthly of wheat, which continues to come forward in ^he form flour, is beginning to become precarious. rfrulst tne supdII^ s now in stock and shipments already on the^ter'are 1 Relent to meet the consumption require- ments of all countries until the end ofSep^mber .th. e are signs that the period thereafter will be critical. Loadings during September may be a negligible ; It is for this reason that we once apatn find it necessary to request all countries to endeavour, in whatever way possible, to collect the maximum ouantity of wheat from their own harvests. The period between October to December inclusive is likely to be the climax o present world shortage in the k-isale East and ^ ^ - 1 be during this period that countries may have to rel unon their own resources for the largegr part of consumption requirements. In this co ec ^ n ^ ^ he of great help to ns if each coOTtry would review their requirements of imported wheat/ilour an ^ re P®^ at the earliest possible date any reductions they are able to accept in their monthly releases fe x p ol stocks for the months of September, October, November and December.y I I * * a 9 ,GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dkpartmint, EXPRESS LETTER [;V. B'—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expert se and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it had been telegraphed. To sace time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,} From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To ERITAGFNT, SHARJAH. N(^28AA - 29/22. Bahrain, the 1st September 13 Reference attached extract from the British Supply Mission (Middle East) Monthly letter No.9. 2. Please let me know whether any reduction in the wheat quota is possible during the period September/December 194-6, and if so to what extent. POLITICAL The Issue of the above has been authorised. •&lt; rtf. Captain. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. • / i ^ KKS S. 6. MFR— 400S&amp;P—lM-480)—26-7-34—2,00 000.I S3 &lt;S&gt; Telegram G.T.C. f From Britagent, Sharjah. To Political, Bahrain. ixl No. 890. /% Dated 1st and received 2nd Septeniher, 1946. Your Express letter No.2739-29/22 August 21st. Wheat supplies to the Trucial Coast. 2. I have discussed with Food Company and we are in full agreement with the agreements made. Britagent&lt; C.No. 2865 - 29/1. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 3rd September 1946. To Messrs* Gray, Mackenzie &lt;&amp; Co* 5 Ltd., Bahrain. / t Dear Sirs, Reference your letter 'o. BA.3/116, dated t&gt;ie 14th August 194-6. 2. The Bahr- in Government and the Truoial Coast Shaikhdoms have confirmed that they are in agreement with the suggested arrangements. 2. I should be grateful if you will let me know if you have now come to any del init.e arrange ments with your Basra Office aegarding wheat shipment to Bahrain and the Trucail Coast. Yours faithfully, Captain. for POLITICAL AGI-NT, BAHRAIN.—\y*&gt; c# POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. No. 2953 - 29/22. The 9th September 1946. To Dear Sirs, In continuation of my letter No.2909- 29/1, dated the 7th September 1946. 2 . The Trucial Coast Shaikhdoms also have confirmed that the cover and rates of the insurance are acceptable to them. They require cover agains Strikes, Riots and Civil Commotions. Yours faithfullyGray, Mac kenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. iC s&gt; (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAES OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET. LONDON.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUS R E H. AM ARAH. K UT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUN DAR-SHAH POU R BUSH I RE. RAS TAN UR A. E l_ KHOBAR. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. M U SCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no. ^65. Bahr-j The Political Agent, BAHREIN* Dear Sir, We thank you for your letter No•2909-29/1 of the 7th instant , qnri have passed on to our Basrah office the information contained v &gt; therein. ^ ^ We take this opportunity of enclosing herewith copy of a letter of the 2nd instant addressed to our Basrah office by the British Ministry of Food, Basrah, regarding certain parcels of wheat they have available in Basrah for shipment in fulfilment of August allocations. Our Basrah office have asked us to take the matter up with the Political Resident Persian Gulf and advise them what action is to be taken * You will recollect that in his letter of the 8th ultimo, the Secretary to the Political Resident informed us that our letter L /312 of the 5th idem on the subject of wheat shipments from Basrah had been forwarded to you for direct disposal* From this we understand that the Political Resident wishes us to deal with you in this matter and we shall be glad to have your instructions. In the event of the Sheikhdoms agreeing to accept delivery ex warehouse Basrah, our Basrah office would require to be put in funds in order to meet the accounts of the Ministry of Food and expenses incurred in shipping. We shall be glad to have your early advice in this regard. Yours faithfully. For GRAY, MACKENZIE Co-, Ltd. c.c. G.M.Co. Ltd., BASRAH. Manner.COPY* From;British Ministry of Food, Basra® To: Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Basra. \f* NO® C/2 2nd September, 1946® y^eat for Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms — ex Warehouse® With reference to your letter No® GEN/255 of the 20th ultimo, we would advise you that we hold the undemoted allocations for wheat to be delivered ex warehouse at Basrah to you for shipment to P.G. Sheikh doms in fulfilment of August allocations: AF.42 for 400 tons wheat to Muscat. AF.43 for 590 ' »» n Dubai® AF.44 for 180 tons wheat to Sharjah. \ We shall be grateful if you will kindly acquaint the PEPG with these figures and ask him if it is now possible for the stocks to be taken over n ex warehouse 1 ’® You might also be good enough to intimate to him that we are prepared, in the event of his local arrangements not having been completed, to assist by shipping the above mentioned allocations under the old terms, but that we are not prepared to cent in— 'ae these arrangements indefinitelly® sd/- J. E. Ardill MANAGER.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depabtimnt, EXPRESS LETTER t-V. B. — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition m if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From The Political Agent, Bahrain, I i To Btitagent, Sharjah, 2975 -29/22 uaudtYie 11th September The British Ministry of Food, Basra, hold the undernoted allocations for wheat to be delivered ex warehouse at Basra to Messrs, Gray Mackenzie &amp; company Limited, for shipment to Dubai and Sharjah in fulfilment of August allocations. AF.43 for 590 tons wheat to Dubai AF.44 for 180 tons wheat to Sharjah. 2. Payment may be made to Messrs Gray Mackenzie and Company Limited, in Basra through'the bank in Dubai on further communication from me. -POLITICAL— The issue of the above has been authorised. Captain. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. s. e. MFP—400S&amp;P—(M-4S0)—26-7-34—2,00.000.* No. 2978 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGFNCY, BATINA IN. The 11th September 194-6, To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahr:in. Dear Sirs, Reference your letter No.L/365&gt; dated the 9th September 194-6. 2. I confirm that as regards wheat shipments for Bahrain and Trucial Coast you should deal direct with me as per your para 2. 3. Reference your final para and enclosed letter from Basra please let me know the c.i.f. cost of wheat for Dubai and Sharjah. On receipt of this ififormation payment will be made to your Basra office through Bank in Dubai. Yours faithfully, for Captain. POLCTICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMS122. LEADEN HALL STREET. LON D 0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BU S R E H. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAH POUR BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. BUNDER-ABBAS. LING AH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. 1 / 369 . Bahrein, 113th September 1946 . A The Political Agent, BAHREIN. I' t 14 Dear Sir, Wheat Shipments to Bahrein &amp; Trucial Coast* We thank you for your letter No. 2953—29/22 of &amp; e 9th instant advising that the Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms have confirmed that the insurance cover and rates as mentioned in our letter L/339 of the 21st ultimo are acceptable to them. We note that they require covpr against Strikes, Riots &amp; Civil Commotion, but you do not state whether they require cover against War Risks. Please advise us on this point* Yours faithfully. d. /7/SGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department.] No* To 935.1215 Sharjah Dated the / 4 ' New Delhi political, £ahrain -7 . September 1946^ n V Reference ^ express letter ho .2844-29/22 Gated the 1st September 1946&gt; toe can bear* a reduction of 100 tons in the monthly v.heat quota during the period September/beccmber 1946, i*e. t, e monthly quota can be reaiicec from 820 to 720 tons.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, DhPARi mint, EXPRESS LETTER [*Y. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE y sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition jw if it had hem telegraphed. To sat e time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] No* 3034 • 29/22. Bahrain, Dated the 16th SeptemberJ33i-6. Reference my express letter 2910 - 29/1 of September 7th, 1946. 2. Trucial Coast can bear a monthly reduction of of wheat for the period from September to December 1946. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. 4 4* 1 Captain. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Hon 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. / 7 ^ KMS S. 6. MFP—400SifeP—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.No. 3035 - 29/22. (ig) POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 16th September 1946. To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. 1 t Dear Sirs, . Please refer to your letter No. L/ 369 , dated the 12th September 1946. 2. The Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms do not re quire cover against War Risks. Yours faithfully, V'- Captain, for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN, KMSGray, Mackknzie &amp; Co. I/ri) (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: 122. LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. EC.3. GRAY BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAH R Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BAI SHARJAH MUSCAT NO. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE L/382. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE Bahrein, 22nd September, jg 46# The Political Agents, BAHREIN. WHEAT SHIPMENTS TO BAHREIN AND TRUCIAL COAST SHEIKHDOMS. # Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No.2972-29/22 of the 14th instant and previous correspondence, we have to advise having today received the following telegram from our Basrah office: 'Ref. your telegram of 18th estimated cost GIF Bahrein &amp;35.12.6 per ton stop endeavour remit immediately cost 941 tons as shipping per 'Barala' Presumably they will require Dinars in Basrah and 941 tons at &amp;35.12.6 is equal to ID.33,523.125. As our Basrah office are shipping per 'Barala' will you kindly arrange for the above amount to be remitted to them as early as possible, advising us when the Remittance has gone forward. Yours faithfully. Manager.UBG^NT No. 3134 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGiSNCY, BAHIAIN. The 25th September 1946 To Messrs. Gray* Mackenzie &amp; Co.&gt; Ltd.| Bahrain. Dear Sirs f / Reference your letter No. 1/382, dated the 22 nd September 1946. 2. Although the wheat consignments are for Dubai and Sharjah, vide enclosure to your letter No.L/36o, dated the 9th September 1946, the price now quoted is for GIF Bahrain. Please clear up this point. Yours faithfully, POLITICAL AGiiiNT, BAH All*GOVERNMENT OF INDIA- Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a mcjins of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] Persian Gulf Residency! Nn. 7 93-S, To Dated Bahrain 9 the 26th September 2 , 9*6 •- NO ^'7 ? British Supply Mission (Middle iiast )9 Cairo. Reference paragraph 1 of Pood Section of your Monthly Letter . '4 / i No. 9 for July 1946. ^ Cf * jP V ^ / / 2 . Trucial Coast can accept reduction of 100 tons per month in its wheat quota over the period September to December 1946. 3. No reduction will be possible in the Bahrain wheat quota unless the State succeeds in securing any supplies of rice when corresponding reductions in the wheat quota will be recom.iended • 4. Information regarding Kumit and Muscat will be furnished later. Sd. W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. attested . Sd«. B. THOMAS. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. No. 794-S. Dated the 26th September 194 6. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to Bahrain Express Letter No .3034-29/22 dated the 16th September 1946. (Signature) S. 44 MFP—1450 S&amp;P—(M-2386)—28-3-40—15,000. (Designation)Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. &lt;3 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND* BRANCHES: HEAD OPriCE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. EC.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY COOES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAH R Ahwaz BUN DA R-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO. l/390 BAHREIN, 30th September, 1946, We have today received advice from our Busreh Office that the allocations for the month of September have now been advised to them by the Ministry of Food, Busreh, as under Sharjah Dubai Bahrein 180 tons 640 tons 780 tons L. (■ Our Busreh Office calculate that the c.i.f*&amp; c. cost of the above shipments will approximate to : A/c. Sharjah A/c. Dubai A/c. Bahrein - ID. 6118/200 @ 33e990 per ton - ID.21753/600 @ 33o990 per ton - ID.25467/- @ 32 0650 per ton The difference between the Bahrein and the Trucial Coast prices is due to the fact that insurance for Dubai and Sharjah includes S.R.&amp; C.C. which is not required by Bahrein, and also Dubai and Sharjah Landing charges which are collected at the port of shipment. We shall be obliged if you will kindly advise the parties concerned and ask them to arrange remittance to Busreh as soon as possible. --q ram fc cCC T 1 ****** So Yours faithfully, GRAY, MACKENZIE A Co., Ltd. Manager.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER JV. B .—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. - 29/22. Dated Bahrain, the 5th October 194 6. Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, of the allocation of wheat for September 194-6 as 180 tons for Sharjah and 640 tons for Dubai. C.I.F. cost @ 33.990 per ton will be approximately ID.6118/200 for Sharjah and ID. 21753/600 for Dubai. To BRITAGENT. SHARJAH I have been informed by Messrs. Gray, 2 Please arrange the remittance to Basrah A as early as possible. = POLITICAL = The issue of the abo’ e has been authorised Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain ^ 'XU MFP—841 S&amp;P—6768—(M-1943)—9.4-45—£00 KIwIS /wmmmmKmmm GOVERNMENT OF INDIA- Department. I C r X h T EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This i* an ORIGIN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provide* a meant of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] No. E58-S BAHRAIN, Dated n r jp &gt; October 1946 /w/ From Political Resident, Bahrain. f T ) t / To , \ 1 * Political ngent, Bahrain.—* \ Political Agent, Kuwait. ^ Political Agent, Muscat. i&lt;\ Bnfopenc8 -^ r Ccroy is forwarded of Savingram No.7 Coolie dated the September 1946 from the British Supply Lis (Liddle East). ssion z 2. An examination of the cereal consumption figures ior the Gulf States for the 11 months from October 1945 to August 1946 has led to the following conclusions. 3. ho alterations or amendments seem possible to the Bahrain and Muscat wheat quotas. 4. Kuwait's consumption of barley has been low throughout and a reduction in the wheat quota is prima facie possible, but in view of the expansion of the Kuwait Oil Company and the consequent influx of labour, it seems prefer able not to suggest any alteration at present. 5. In spite of a consistently low adulterant consump tion, the Trucial Coast have never consumed their full wheat quota, the average consumption over the 11 months having been ^only about 650 tons. A reduction of 100 tons per month during ^che last four months of the current year has already been accepted, and a permanent reduction in the wheat quota to the same extent seems feasible. 6. Please furnish your views *(by telegram) without consulting governments concerned. *To Kuwait and) Muscat only.) ATTESTED. 4 ^ ‘ i,. for SctTfetary to the I' * Political Resident, Persian Gulf. (Signature) NPG. (Designation) s. 44 MFP—1450 S&amp;P—(M-2386)—26*3-40—15,000. ( SGD •) A • C . GaLLOih AY • Political resident, PersianMulf.c To RLPGU BAHRAIN No.7 COOLIA SAVING From B.S.L. (K.E.) L. 26th September 1946 No greement nas yet been reached regarding the method to be adopted to programme supplies to the Lidele Last during 1947 of those essential commodities v/hich remain in critical supply and subject to International allocation by the I.L.F.C. these essential foodstuffs, London lias requested us to prepare an unofficial 1947 programme to cover certain basic items which, as far as can be juaged at present, will continue to be subject to International &lt;*l~Dcation in x9'±V. 3. It is stressed that the preparation of this programme is unofficial and should not be mentioned outside British Government circles. 4. The only item specifically programmed for the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms is 31,20C tons of wheat. Lithout any reference to any of the local sheikhdoms, we will be grateful for your views on any alterations or amendments to this figure which you anticipate for 1947. 5. A reply at the earliest possible date would be appreciated. To ensure continuity of supply ofGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, _ Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N, — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by fast to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. \ / To REPGU, BAIT IAIN. ^*•3357 - 29/22. Bahrain, Datti the 13th October J9SS . possible in the cereals quota for 194? for Bahrain. 3. As regards the Trucial Coast I agree that based on the present rate of consumption, and as far as one can foretell, the Trucial Coast will be able to accept a permanent reduction of 100 tons per month in 1947. 2 . Your express letter 858-S of October 8th, 1946. It is confirmed no alterations or amendments v/ill be POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised KMS ^ ^ ' Captain. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. s. 6. MFP—1206 SAP—(M-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000,7?//yJ&gt; 1*3 eP Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS’. GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE '-NTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSREH AMA RAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR A H WA Z BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO.. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Bahreinj, 9th October, |g 46. JUFFAIR. Dear Sir, We beg to refer to your letter c/619 dated 8th August last and previous correspondence and to advise that the represent ative of the British Ministry of Food, Basrah, has asked our office there if we could obtain for him a formal letter from the Political Resident confirming that the Ministry of Food’s proposals that the future wheat supplies to Bahrein and the Trucial Coast be delivered to us ex warehouse, Basrah, had been formally accepted and approved. If you will kindly let us have such a letter we shall be pleased to pass it on to him. Yours faithfully. No ,w ? Dats... S3- — l/v F&lt; to.. Ltd. !=&gt;’CY i | 8.110 [ ^ t&gt; No. 886-S Dated the 13th ctober, 1946 G \1LF &gt; f forwarded with compliments to - ^ J o Political Agent, y Y Bahrain for disposal.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA- Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). This in an ORIGIN A L message sent by AIR MAIL which provide a nuumt of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. Jt is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No- 909- 3 Bahrain Dated , the 22nd October, 2 !? 46 - To British Supply Mission, (Middle East), Cairo . J Reference-^ s ving telegram No. 7 Coolie dated 2©th Septmmber, ’46. Following are my views on Middle East 1947 programme as regards the ^ulf ^haikhdoms* (a) Bahrain. No altej^tion possible. (b) Trucial Coast. /lOO tons per month reduction aC' epted in my Express Letter No. 793-S dated 25th oeptember 1946 may be acted upon permanently. (c) Muscat. No alteration possible. (d) Kuwait. Further communication will follow. Sd/ A.C. GALLOWAY political Resident. Persian Gulf Thomas for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Persian Uulf Residency, Bahrain. 22nd October, 1946. Bahrain Receipt Copy forwarded with compliments to s- The Political Agent, Kuwait . The Political Agent, Bahrain % w' The Political Agent, Muscat . ZttLssm ir? ML. {Signature) / S. 41 MFP—1450 S&amp;P—(M-2386)—28-3-40—15,000. (Designation)Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. EC.3. GRAY BUSREH AMA RAH KUT KHORAMSHAH R A H W A Z BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Bahrein, 29 th October, jg 46 The Political Agent, BAHREIN Dear Sir, WHEAT FOR BAHREIN AND TRUCIAL COAST. -*-VV We thank you for your letter No.351' of yesterday^ date and note that it y.III be in order for us to correspond direct concerning wheat shipments from Basrah, sending copies of such letters Nos. L/439 and L/440- and for your records copies are attached hereto. As regards shipments to the Trucial Coast sheikhdoms, should v/e correspond direct with the Sheikh of Dubai and the Sheikh of Sharjah through our office there or do you wish all correspondence to be passed through you? with the Adviser to the Government of Bahrein in regard to all matters A to you for informatio * * ' ' ^ | ^ Actually w^ despatched two letters to the Adviser yesterday Yours faithfully alirain Receipt Manager. c.c. Basrah office.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No. 3676 - 29/22. The 11th November 1946. . - ' 'C • ° ^ To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. Bahrain. f . !■ • • A v o n n 18 9 R R U Dear Sirs, . Please refer to your letter No. L/441, dated the 29th October 1946. 2 . In future please correspond direct with the Shaikhs of Dubai and Sharjah, regarding shipments of wheat to the Trucial Coast. Copies of* communi cations however, should always be sent to ^he Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Yours faithfully, ii-Vn-/— POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.MFP—841 S&amp;P—6768—(M-1943)—9-4-45—600,000. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER N. B. —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. To 975-S Dated the nibe£94 6« \ (A Political A^snt, Bah.-ain. ' ’ 1 J Vr Gontinuation of my express letter No. 925-2 dated the 9th November 1946. 2. Please report whether Bahrain Gove -ninent or Tracial Coast ah&amp;i’-hs are 5 on re onsideration. willing to ae-eot any P.A. T.C. surnln.s flour. A.' Attested. Sd '. C V Political Resi - ent, P 3 rsian Gulf. 3d. 3.Thomas. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. COPYGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER rjtf, B. This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by pout to swe tekgrnphie expense and undue use of Ike wires, but intended to be tn &lt;iU'd, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hud been tdtgrapned, lo sare lime and formalities it is worded and signed as ij it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To BRITAGENT, SHARJAH. Vo. ^721 •• 29/22. Be*i&amp;rain, Dated the 14th November/ 9346 . Reference ny memorandum No. 3694-29/1 of November 12th, 1946, to the Director of Customs, Bahrain, copy endorsed to y . o Iran Command have declared a surplus of l60° tons of second grade flour which contains 6 o£ wheat flou- an. ar y flour. A sample of the flour is sent herewith. 3 . Owing to its high contont of barley ^ P ™ p °^ t to allocate it for the purpose of programing as 1120 tons o. wheat 4 . The price of the flour is £27.6.9 Per ton of 2240 lbs. net for Shaiba, excluding charges to I . f .B. ana .reig.. . •? The flour is held at the Command Supply Depot, Shaiba, and^will delivered by Military F.O.B. and price quoted above. x t+ rvrohable that there will be a shortage of wheat to the Persian Gulf i&gt;T the near future. Please explain eho P ^?t.lon to the Trueial Coast Shaikhs and let me know telegra- ph!ca?Si? they would accept this flour against Trucial Coast's monthly allocation in accordance with paragraph 3 above. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Ws 400S&amp;p /V — ► # — V ^Assistant Political Agent, (M 480 26-7^4 2/ 0.J00. Bahra in •*HHH G.T.C. B rit a £ ent, J harj^h. Politic 1, Bahrain. 1145 IWV cj9 Telegram From • To Mo. Dated the 16th November, 1946. Your Express Letter Mo.3255-29/22 October 5th. Remittance to Gray Mackenzie Babrah v/as made but no news yet of shipment o^ wheat quota ■for September. Grateful if Gray Mackenzie could be asked to expedite shipment. -POLITICAL EB. - I.R.Mo.639 IP/11/46. — L . — —Mvil —— --u-t&gt; No. 3786 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAilRAIN. The 19th Novamber 1946, Messrs. Gray* Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain* To Dear Sirs, Wheat for Trucial Coast . Please refer to your letter No. b/330, dated the 30th September 1946* 2 . I am informed that the remittance to ^ Me srs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Basrah, has been made, but that there is no news yet of the shipment of the wheat quota for Trucial Coast for September. 3 . I should be glad to know when shipment may be expected. Yours faithfully. KM3 . Xfor POLITICAL AGcNT, i3A.ff.AIN.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, DePARI'MBNT, v 5 $ EXPRESS LETTER [N, B ,—This is &lt;m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as \f it had been telegraphed, 1 o sace time and formalities it is worded ami signed as if it had beer* so despatched,] To politicalj Bahrain No, iih4*i2Xo Dated 16th November 19S 46 Reference your memorenoum No.3694-29/1 oaved the 12th of November 1946. Flour. Shaikhs enc. members of the Food C mpsni'^^ ^ f r0 m Bahrain. Tfey'tu faif thlf^e hour is unfit for human consumption ana therefore aeciaed to refuse i s. 6, WFP—501 Sfr.P—(M- 820)—23-7-36—300,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dkparimmnt, EXPRESS LETTER [N. n % —This is an ORIGINAL MESS AG T!, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Fkom POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To RJSPGU, BAHRAIN • N°- 3817 - 29/1. Dated 20th November -7346 • Your express letter No. 945-S of November 11th, 1946. P.A.I.C. surplus flour. 2. The Trucial Coast Shaikhs have refused, even on recon sideration, to accept this flour as they consider it unfit for human consumption. The Bahrain Government have also refused to take it for much the same reason, and I enclose a copy of their letter on the subject. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd. H.D.H.Ranee. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMS /COPY/ S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.Oray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS*. GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE A BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAH R Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Bahrein,. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO .L/467. 20th s!ovenber f 19 kb..* BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KO W E IT DU BA I SHARJAH MUSCAT The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We have to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.3786-29/22 of yesterday’s date and to advise that we have referred to our Basrah office and on receipt of their reply we will again communicate with you. Yours faithfully, Manager.MFP —841 S&amp;P— 6768 —(M- 1943 )— 9 - 4 - 45 — 600 , 000 . GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. &lt;3 Department. EXPRESS LETTER To ,n ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue le wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if been telegraphed. To save tune and formalities it is worded and signed as if it q so despatched. - 29/1. Dated Bahrain, the 27th Novembers* 6 . Your endorsement No. 1036-S of November 19th, 1946* approximately 15 to 20 thousand tons of grain could be stored in Bahrain, in Customs ware houses and merchants 1 private godowns. 3 * 10 thousand tons of grain could be stored An the Trucial Coast* The issue of the above has been authorised Set- Ijjb- !-} ■ Assistant Politi al Agent, Bahrain. 2 . The Director of Customs estimates that POLITICAL KMBGRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO. LTD. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES HEAD OFFICE: 122 LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E. C. 3 . TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE BLISREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. L/479. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR P,V r 7S'?6 ad * iipt The Political Agent, BAHREIN, Dear Sir, Bahrein, 30th November, 1Q 46, . Wheat for T ruclal Coast. IL With reference to your letter No, 3786-29/22 of the 19th instant, we have now heard from our Basrah office who write as follows: WJ OB 9 H* C+' cr lt Sharjah &amp; Dubai , We note the enquiry you have received from the Political Agent, Bahrein, regarding shipment of the September allocations for Sharjah and Dubai, and as you will know there has not been an opportunity for shipment to these ports since the receipt of funds, Wemre under the impression that we should have an opportunity for shipment by the 'Barjora 1 ’ about the end of this month, but we now learn that, according to present programme, this vessel will not be calling at Sharjah and Dubai, In any case we are awaiting news from you in reply to our letter GM/294 of the 18th instant, as to whether the Sharjah Dubai Governments would accept shipment in single bags or would prefer to wait until possible shipment in double bags can be effected. In this latter respect we would mention that the Ministry of Food apparently are still without information regarding the arrival of a fresh consignment of gunny bags*’ which we pass on for your information. As regards the question of double bags for the Dubai and Sharjah shipments, we wrote to our Dubai office on 23rd November and asked them to telegraph to Basrah whether they should hold over the September allocations until such time as they have sufficient gunny bags to pack wheat in double bags or whether they should effect shipment of these allocations by the first opportunity. We have no doubt our Dubai office will already have telegraphed this information to Basrah,No. 3970 - 29/22 A The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments tos The Residency Agent, Sharj ah, and has the honour to send him a copy of the under* .nti med document. Please confirm telegraphically that Gray Mackenzie, Dubai, have replied to Basra about the gunny bags. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 7th December 1946. — Reference to previous correspondences -i^ Sharjah telegram No.ll4o, dated the 16th .love .bor 1946. — 1 —: 77 Description of enclosure Subject. . Copy of letter No. 1/479, | dat d the 30th November jj 1946, from Messrs. Gray, 5 WHEAT P0R TP.JCIAL COST. Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, to the Political j| Agent, Bahrain. i — KiiSrn- (3&gt; Telegram, From, To* No, Dated the 10th GTC, Residency Agent, Sharjah* Political Agent, Bahrain* 1223 and received 11th December, 1946. My telegram No, 1145 November 16th. 2* Wheat quota for September not yet ship ped by Gray Mackenzie, Basrah. Cost of wheat quota for October has also been remitted but no news of shipment of this either. Trucial Coast wheat stock will be exhausted by the end of December, 1946. 3 * Grateful if arrangement could be made for the early shipment of wheat to Trucial Coast by first available steamer. I.R. No. 668 L. -BRITAGENT-No. 4051 - 29/22 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 11th December 1946 To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. , Bahrain. Dear Sirs s. ■&gt;u. j. j. u . i^eference your letter No. iy479, dated Wheat for Tracial Coast . the 30th November 1946 2 I am informed that the cost of wheat quota for October also has been remitted by the Tracial Coast Shaikhdons. I have'asked them to reply telegraphically whether shipment of wheat in single bags has been accepted, in the present circumstances. 3. It is requested that, meanwhile, arrange ments may please be made for the shipment of the wheat by first opportunity as stock of wheat on the Trucial Coast will be exhausted by the end of December 1946. Youi's faithfully, Sd. H.D.H. Ranee for POLITICAL aGENT, BAHRAIN Attested Superintendent KMS■■■■■■■■■I jmmmm Telegram G.T.C. From political, Bahrain. To Britagent, Sharjah. No.605. Dated the 11th of December, 1946. Your telegram No.1223, December 10th. Wheat. 2. please telegraph whether Trucial Coast have accepted shipment in single bags vide my printed Letter 3970, December 7th. -POLITICAL- NS.Telegram From To No. G.T.C. Residency Agent, Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain. 1231. Dated &amp; received 12th December 1946. 11 th.Wheat. Your telegram No. 606 dated December 2. Trucial Coast have accepted repeat accepted shipment in single bags and Gray Mackenzie, Basra have already been informed telegraphically to this effect. = BRITAGENT = I.R.671.BAS/217. Bahrein, 12th December, 46. S . O J 4 « ; WHEAT FOR TRUCIAL COAST. \ With reference to our letter l/ 479 of the 30th ultino, addressed to the Politioal Agent here, a copy of which was sent to you, we hare non received a letter from the Political Agent tinder yesterday's date in chich he writes as followss 'I am informed that the cost of wheat quota for October also has been remitted by the Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms. I have them to reply telegraphically whether shipment of wheat in single bags has been accepted, in the present circumstances. It is requested that, meanwhile, arrangements may please be made for the shipment of the wheat by first opportunity as Stocks of wheat on the Trucial Coast will be exahusted by the end of December, 1946' As regards the question of gunnybags for Trucial Coast shipments you would learn from Dubai's telegram of the 26th ultimo confirmed in their letter DO/FOOB/57 of the same date, that no empty gunny bags are available at Dubai or Sharjah and as the wheat is urgently required they ask you to ship in sound single gunnies by the first steamer. Please advise us if you will be able to arrange shipment by the 'Barpeta' expected to sail from yours towards the end of this month. For GRAY, MACK ~ Co., Ltd. No., j ? ix -:(-64 c.c. 1) Dubai. / 2) P, A .Bahrein, in acknowledgement ^ of his letter 4051-29/22 of 11th instant. Manager.GOVERNMENT OK INDIA, Dei-arimint, EXPRESS LETTER (A T . B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expei.se and undue use of the mres, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it had been telegraphed. To sace lime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Fkom POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To POLITICAL, SHARJAH. tfa, 256 - 29/22. Bahrain. tJaU&amp; the 21st January 134 7. Wheat for Trucial Coast . In spite of a consistantly low adulterant consumption, the Trucial Co^st have never consumed their full wheat quota, the average consumption for the last calendar year having been only about 650 tons per month. The Hon , ble the Political Resident has therefore recommended a permanent reduction of 100 tons per mouth in the wheat quota for Trucial Coast for 1947. = POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMS f S. 6. MFi’—4003&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00 000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbpabtmint, EXPRESS LETTER L\\ B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sace time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, ILIihAIN. REPGU, BAHRAIN. 265 - 29/1. Bahrain. uaitd 21st January ^ 1947. j &lt;r Reference your endorsement No. 92-S of January 14th, 1947. Wheat for Trucial Coast. 2. A permanent reduction of 100 tons per month has been recommended from the Trucial Coast's wheat quota for 1947 (your £ \5S \ endorsement No. 910-3, dated the 22nd October 1946 refers). As last year's quota was 9840 tons, please confirm that the estimate for 1947 and the programme suggested by the British Sunply Mission for Trucial Coast, in the endorsement referred to above, should be 8640 tons and not 9640 tons. = POLITICAL The Issue of the above has been authorised. \ Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. s. e. K 400S&amp;P—(M.-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.■r GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dkpartmint, PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN. EXPRESS LETTER [N.B.—This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, tent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wives, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as \f it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From REPGU BAHRAIN. BaV'&amp;i Bsceipt no...&gt;3 7 To POLITICAL BAHRAIN. CONFIDENTIAL Dated 25th January, 1947. No. 155-3. Reference your express letter No. 265 - 29/1, dated the 21st January, 1947. 2. It is confirmed that the estimate for 1947 is 8640 tons. = REPGU = The issue of the above has been authorised. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.1 $ No. 345 - 29/22. To POLITICiiL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 29th January 1947, MEMORANDUM The Political Officer, | ^ TSucial Coast, Sharjah&gt;—-—' vm \ Reference my express letter No. 2o6 -29/22, dated the 21st January 1947. 2. The British Supply Mission, Cairo, agrees that the programme of wheat supplies for 1947 for the Trucial Coast should be 8640 tons. k/i for POLITICAL ACLiNT, BAH; AIK. KMSGP/13. Bahrein, 26th January, 47* With reference to ^our letter Gp/l2 of the 23rd instant addressed to Basrah, copy of which \ras sent to you, we confirm having telegraphed you on the 24th instant requesting you to arrange telegraphic remittances to Basrah of ID # 29,911*200 on account of Dubai and ID.12,236*530 on account of Sharjah* for GRAX, rOCaiiSlS 4 CU. LTD. k. c.c* 1) Basrah office - in acknowledgement of their telegram of the 24 th Instant* 2) Political A^ent, Bahrein - the above remittances are in respect of 880 tons for Dubai and 360 tons for Sharjah which our Basrah office expect to ship per ss. 'Bamora* 1 shortly*■ M* 1%* Noc 352 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 30 th January 1947. To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited) Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Please refer to your letter No. BAS/217) dated the 12th December 1946. 2. Please confirm that the Trucial Coast wheat allocations for September and October 1946 were delivered by s.s. Barpeta. Yours faithfully, Ul for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMSGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADEN HALL STREET, LON D 0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE- BRANCHES: BUS R EH. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. M U SCAT. Bahrein, IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO. h/4-2* 2nd February, ^ 47. The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Wheat for Dub ai and Shariah. In reply to your letter No.352-29/22 of the 30th ultimo, we confirm that the September and October 1946 quotas for the Trucial Coast were duly shipped per ss. f, Barjora n v.339 which reached Dubai and Sharjah early last month. We understand from our Basrah cffice that they also expect to ship the November/December allocations for both these ports per ss. ,, Bamora n expected to sail from Basrah about 12 days hence. Yours faithfully. For GRAY, A (■d. l/JZQ, Mana*?; t. c.c. G.M.Co. Ltd., BASRAH.i mm No. 565 - 29/1. UsV POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN* The 22nd February 1947, Messrs. Gray* Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. To Dear Sirs, Please let me know urgently the quantity of cereals landed at Bahrain ex s.s. Sarainver, and the total amounts taken over respectively by the Bahrain Government and Trucial Coast Shakhdo is against outstandings for the period August to December 1946. Yours faithfully, Sd 1 H-D H- , for POLITICAL AGclIJT, BAHRAIN. KiiSKMS fy# No. 612 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 25th February 19 4 7. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. MEMORANDUM It has been proposed that ^eBrltishSupply Mission should be dissolved from March 31 st, 1947, but the present Director General will be renaining in Cairo until the end of June 1947. De i a J: 1 |. 0f „ f, J tU I5»t r r™lrn ments have not yet been decided but His Majesty s Gcv ern. ment will continue to be responsible for supplies of cereals for Gulf States* M for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.■ GRAY, MACK^NZIiS iiND COMPAITY, LIMITED. No. L/62. Bahrain, 23February 1947. With reference to your letter No. 565-29/1 of yesterday^ date v/e have to advise that the total amount of wheat outturned ex ss. ''Saminver' amounts to 8,tons. As re/ard^ deliveries we have to advise th&amp;t we have delivered to the Bahrain Government 3,900 tons from the 'Sarainver' stocks, representing their August to December quo'as. No deliveries ex the ''Baminver M wheat have been made to the Trucial SExscxh Sheikhdoms, but for your information, we would mention that both Dubai and Sharjah have already received their allocations up to and including the month of October, from Basrah, and according to advise we have from Basrah, dated 17th February, the November and December allocations for . Dubai and Sharjah amounting to 1240 tons will be shipped from Basrah per ss. ’'Barala' on this voyage. Yours faithfully, Sd. for Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. Manager. /COPY/ 0 ri;iaal on 20/1.No. 840 - 29/22. S? &gt;3 POLITICAL ACrKNCY, BAHRAIN* . The 16th March 1947. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah IvIKM0x\ANDUM Reference my memorandum No. 612-29/22, dated the 25th February 1947. 2 . It has now been decided to disband the British Supply Mission (Middle Bast) on the 31st of March 1947. Provision will be made, however, for supplies of wheat up to 30th June 1947. 3. Full details of the procedure to be adopted after the 31st March 1947 will be communicated at an early date. KMS 4 , ^ /for POLITICAL AGfciNT. BAHRAIN. P-mmamtarn GOVERNalENT OP INDIA. DbPAR'IMKSI', EXPRESS LETTER [A , B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE) sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From - political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, - Political Agent, To Bahrain, No. 280,1215 Dated 12 th March, 1947, 193 . Subject: Trucial Coast Wheat Quota, Peference your memorandum No.345-29/22 dated the 29th January, 1947, 2,* Imports of this year’s wheat crop from Persia into the Trucial Coast are expected in the near future at prices below the current cost of controlled wheat which will then remain unsold. It is| therefore* requested that the Trucial Coast wheat quota for the three months^ from January to March, 1947 may be reduced by half. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. S. 6. MET—601 S&amp; P—(M-S20)—23-7-36—300,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N. Ii % —This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use oj ike wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as \f it had been telegraphed, do sate time and formalities it is worded ami signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. No.946 - 29/22. Bahrain. Dated, the 24th March * • 1947. Reference your express letter No.280.l215 of March 12th, 1947. 2. Since the British Supply Mission is about to be disbanded, and wheat may now become more difficult to obtain I am averse to the total surrender of half the Trucial Coast wheat quota for the quarter ending 31st March 1947. 3. Please, therefore, arrange for the whole quota to be purcaased as usual, and for half of it to be consigned to Bahrain, where it will be transferred to the Bahrain Government. The latter will refund all expenses on receipt of the consignment. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 / S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-30—300,000. KMo- No. 1038 - 29/22. To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 1st April 1947. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah' MEMORANDUM Reference ray memorandum No. 840-29/22, dated the 16th March 1947. / 2. Trucial Coast 1 s wheat requirements after the 31st of March 1947, should be sent to me for transmission through the Secretary of State for India, London, to the Ministry of Food. KMS for POLITICAL AGENT, BAH.iAIN.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department, EXPRESS LETTER ^ ' * This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic txpeuse and mdue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa 1 c i.ime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] No. 1106 - 29/22. Bahrain. DcUed the 9th April Reference my express letter No. 946-29/22 of March 24th, 1947. Wheat. the Trucial Coast*s consumption requirements during the month of March and the remaining 420 towards the consumption require ments of April 1947. Cairo, to release 2,040 tons in all, as made up below: Mission, you should accept the release without delay and Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., should be instructed to secure shipping space as early as possible. The wheat should be consigned as directed in ray express letter referred to above. From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To POLITICAL, SHARJAH. 2. The British Supply Mission, Cairo, has decided to debit 820 tons, of the recent delivery of 1,240 tons against 3 The Mission has arranged with the Ministry of Food, April May June a further 400 tons 820 tons 820 tons. 4. In view of the closing down of the Britihh Supply POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised /«/ / Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. AfFP—1196 S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000. KMSINTO.418.1225 To, British Agency, Sharjah, Dated, 14th April, 1947 n The Political Agent, Bahrain. n. n T'enorendnm. Reference your memorandum No. 1058-29/ 22 dated the 1st April, 1947. 2. Trucial Coast’s wheat requirements after 51st Narch 1947 are 600 tons a month. k Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. VNo. 1426 - 29/22 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 26th April 1947 To The Political Officer, Tracial Coast. Sharjah. MKMOiiANDUM Reference your moniorandum No.418.1225, dated the 14th April 1947. 2. For^the reasons mentioned in my express letter No.946-29/22, dated the 24th March 1947, it is desired that the wheat releases up to 30th June 1947 which have already been arranged, vide my ex press letter No.1106-29/22, dated the 9th April 1947, be accepted. ^p m 3. A cut in the quota will be considered, if the stock position warrants it, at the end of this period. for POLITICAL AG HINT, BAHRAINNo. 1442 - 29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 27th April 1947 To The Political Officer 9 Trucial Coast, Sharjah. MKMOiiANDUM His Majesty*s Consul-General, Bushire, informs me that although the export of wheat, rice and barley from the main ports is still prohibited yhc by r Persian Government, small ports such as Dilam, Ganeikeh etc. are permitted to export small quanti ties against barter. Also, since there is a surplus of wheat and barley in the Fars and Bushire Consular Districts, it is likely that permission to export a stated quantity could be obtained from the Persian Government, if applied for by a reputable local mer chant. It is requested, therefore, that every effort be made, through private sources on the Persian side, to import as much cereals as possible. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHiAIN. KMSNo. 1518 - 29/22. To POLITICAL AGiSNCY, BAHRAIN. The 3rd May 1947., The Political Officer, Tfcucial Coast, Sharjah. MEMORANDUM p &gt;i^ Further to my memorandum No. 1442-29/22, dated the 27th April 1947, I am informed by His Majesty 1 s Consul, Kerman, that wheat and barley are also likely to be available at Bandar Abbas, and permission to export could probably be obtained from the Persian Government if applied for by re putable local merchants^to^x w • for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.Politic^ 1, Bahrain. No. 525-1215 Dated 12th ? Tap, 1947. ^ . Peference your express letter TTo.o/l53 dated the 51st January, 1945. Barley. 2 . Since the year 1945 the barley requirements of the Trucial Coast have been obtained by batter. Consumption during April ^ was 35 tons and the stock on the 1st May was 273 tons. This will be sufficient for approximately 5 months. The local authorities have represented to me that they shall not require barley when the present stock has been exhausted as the wh^eat quota sufficiently meets local requirement. There is little demand for barley locally and if we are allowed to dispense with it wo will be able'to save the barter sugar which^we normally ?ive away towards the importation of barley through private channels. The barter sugar could then be disposed of at the current market price and the difference between the^actual cost and the sole price could be used towards the subsidizing of wheat. Pleose let me know if action- can be taken as atCopy of endorsement No,I028-S dated 29th May 1947 from P.R. to the Political Agent Bahrain etc. Copy of India Office X.L. No. E/2289/4 dated the I?th May 194? forwarded with compliments. Or&gt;y of X.L. No. E/2289/47 dated I7th May 1947 from India Office London to P.R. fixxk Persian Gulf etc. Reference your express letter No. 733-S of 26th April. The Ministry of Food confirm that the necessary releases of cereals for the Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms from pool stocks will be made by the Ministryfs office at Basra and that no further action on your part will be necessary in this connection.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, British Agency, Dbpabtmikt, Sharjah EXPRESS LETTER lit 09? [N . B, —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time a»d formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Feom - Britagent, Sharjah. No ..3 3 ff ,o l/ h To - Political, Bahrain. 568.1215 31st May, 1947. the 12th May, 1947 on the subject of barley. 2 . I have explained the position to the local authorities and made it clear to them that it is not possible to dispense *ith barley at all. They have, however, requested that the proportion of barley to be consumed may, if possible, be reduced from one third to one eighth or one fourth if such reduction does not affect our wheat quota. 3. I shall be grateful for your instructions in the matter. Il, i if S. 6.- • • , - . - - - -No. To Jjv* ■' V: 29/22. Political Agency, Bahrain, v », I5th June 1947 \V\ The Residency Agent, Sharjaju. Ay Menorandiim . &lt; 0 ^ Your express letter No. 558 of 31st May 1947. Barley for the Trucial Coast. 2 * As already explained to you verbally the proportion of barley to wheat cannot be changed. ^ for Political Agent, Bahrain. ' ' £*# •S.\No. 936.1216 British Agency 9 Sharjah* Dated 2nd October, 1947. The Political Agent, Bahrain. j.'V $ • _*■ j &lt;^y) kemoranduia RefereiJ.ce correspondence enairig v^ith your memorandum No. 2030-29/22 dated the 15th June 1947. Barley for the Trucial Coast. 2* Efforts have been made to obtain barley through private channels, i*e., by barter, but during the whole of September only 36 tons were imported. This is due to the increased cost oi barley in Iraq and Persia (the two sources Irom which we normally get our barley), the restrictions imposed on its export from those countries and the little profit that would-be importers will derive from the barter sugar. In the circumstances, it is not expected that any substantial quantity of barley will be imported in the near future under these arrangements. 1 have discussed the matter with the Food Committee who strongly recommended that we should dispense with barley and open barker fci* rice, the need foe which is more essential. ^ shall be grateful for your approval of this proposalTo No. 3364-29/22 The Political Agency, Bahra: Df 2.3. k . ^2 , The Residency Agent Bharjah. / 2 nd October, 1947. 2. The principle has long been established that recipients of wheat and barley from His Majesty's Government sho Id distribute them in the proportion of 2/3 wheat and 1/3 barley. As a special case the Trucial Shaikhdoms were permitted to import their barley by barter and now receive only wheat from H.M.G. If the Trucial Shaikhdoms have imported no barley recently, the inference is that they have been living on wheat only, or have been securing imports of other cereals. 3. Imports of rice by private arrangement are to be set off against the total cereal requirements of the Trucial Coast, i.e., against 840 tons of wheat received from H.M.G plus' 280 tons barley intended to be imported privately. In other words, 2/3 tons wheat supplied by H.M.G. is to be surrendered for every ton of rice imported privately. 4. You should therefore continue your efforts to import barley upto half the amount of wheat received from H.M.G., and any imports of rice should be reported to me so that they can be off set against the total wheat and barley requirements at the rate of 2/3/wheat and 1/3 tons barley for every tonx office imported. Political Agent, Bahrain LTelegram GTC Fro ® Brit^gent Sh*rjf*h. To Political B^hr^in. No. 1006. Doted 20th received 21st October 194?. 1800 tons of wheot hove been oHotted to the Truciol Coost representing quoto for August «nd September for which imraediote poyment is required. Food Componies who hlreody Iho.ve stock for two months ond ore short of Funds request your permission to to^e over 1000 tons only ond surrender remoining 800 tons. If Bo hr o in Government wishes to hove these 800 tons they moy be o S ked to remit imraediotely Rs.444,000 to cover cost ond expenses. BritogentEXPRESS LETTER From To. n olitic-l, hr-'In. HEPG«J f Bn hr-in. No. 0-29/22. Dntod the 27th October, 1947 . 4 1 x 5./V- Reference correspondence resting with Residency endo^eraent No. 1028-S d-ted the 29th M-y s 1947 . .. 2 * 111 ’P^ll this year the Rolitlc-l Officer, True 1-1 Co-st^requested th-t the whe-t quot- for the Truci -1 Co-st be reduced to 600 tons - month -s from the 1 st 'pril because limited qu-ntlties of cere-ls could be imported through tr-de ch-nnels. j. The Polltlc-1 'gent ruled that the existing quot- of 840 tons should be t-ken over until the end of June, when the position would be reconsidered. .. Th * R®*Money «gent has nov; reported th-t the Dub -1 Food Comp-ny now h-ve two months’ stock of whe-t on h-nd unsold, -nd th-t 1800 tons of whe-t h-ve been -Hotted for the Truci -1 Co-st for *ugust -nd September. Incre-slng qu-ntlties of rice -re -Iso reported to be -v-il-ble from Persl-, -nd imports of rice -re to be set off -g-lnst the whe-t quot-. The Pood Comp-my do not require more th-n 1000 tons of whe-t for -ugust -nd September; nor h-'ve they the inoney to yv^y for more. 5. It Is therefore requested th-t the Ministry of Food be -sked to rele-se only 1000 tons of whe-t for the Truci -1 oh-ikhdoms new, -nd 600 tons per mensem in future. Copy to The Residency “gent, Sh^rj*h. YV-'/.T. ^7 £ AfO'/DoC&gt; ^olitic-l ^gent, B^hr-in.'■v 0 OJr J/, f \ \ u7 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bahrain. To H.M's Consul-General, Basra. Ko. 1 1104 Dated the 4th November, 1947. Following for Ministry of Food Representative, Basra. Begins : Political Agent Bahrain reports that Truclal Coast Sheikhdoms are unable to absorb and pay for the allocation of 1800 tons of wheat made for August &amp; September and has recommended that it be reduced to 1000 tons. Political Agent has also recommended that future allocations of wheat to the Trucial Coast be reduced to 600 tons per mensem v/ith effect from the allotment for October 1047. Grateful for action accordingly. Ends. = REPGU = f: 1 . ( / .—-.vi ; i. co;:fide..tial No. 1893-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, the 4th November, 1947. Copy forwarded,fcsi with compliments, to (i) H.M*s Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, LONDON, with reference to his Express Letter No.E.1789/47 dated the 18th April, 1947 ; (ii) The Political Agent, DAHnAIN . b . with reference to his Express Letter No.3390-29/22 dated the 27th October, 1947• CLS. 4 ,(' ! i ' ^ i * 1 'r a* 7 Vvgray, Mackenzie &amp; co. iid No. BAS/176 Bahrain 10th November 1947. The Hon’ble Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Juffair* Bear Sir, WHEAT ALLOCATIONS FOR DUBAI &amp; SHARJAH . For your information we attach hereto copy of a letter i/239 of the 17th ultimo addressed to us by our Basrah Office together with a copy of the enclosures referred to therein. We shall be glad to have your views on this matter in due course so that we may pass same on to our Basrah Office. Yours faithfully, for GRAY, MACKENZIE 8c CO. XTD. Sd. W.MEIKLE. ManagerGRAY, MACK ENZIE &amp; CO, LTD . No. M/2 39 Basrah, 17th Oct., 1947. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Lear Sirs, WHEAT ALLOCATIONS FOR LUBAl AND SHARJAH . In connection with the above we enclose here with copies of the undemoted communications* British Ministry of Food Representative’s letter to us dated the 15th October 1947 . Our letter of today’s date to Dubai. The failure of these Shaikhdoms to take up the quantities of wheat allocated to them by the Ministry of Food has given the impression at this end that per haps the Shaikhdoms d'o not require this wheat. This impression has been further strengthened by a recent report of the movement of 800 tons of wheat from Dubai. From the Ministry’s letter to us you will note that Dubai and Sharjah are due to receive 2520 tons of wheat and that the allocations for November and December are 720 tons per month. We shall therefore be obliged if you will discuss this matter with Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and let us have the benefot of his views on the size of the quotas for Dubai and Sharjah, as it would appear that it might be appropriate to reduce these. Yours faithfulJy, for gray Mackenzie &amp; co. ltd. Enc. 2.BRITISH MINIS TRY OF FOOD (M,E ») Basrah, 15th Oct. 1947. C/6. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. Basrah• Lear Sirs, WHEAT ALLOCATIONS FOR LUBA I AKD SHARJAH . 1. We have now been advised by our London Office of the following Wheat allocations for Trucial Coast October 1947 ... 720,000 M.T.G. November 1947 ••• 720.000 ' December 1947 ... 720.000 M 2. As notified you on the ’phone yesterday, August and September quotas for the above Shaikhdoms are still outstanding, the quantities being:- Lubai Shar.jah August ... 720.000 MTG 360.000 September ... 540.000 ' 180.000 Please take the necessary steps to clear the above at your soonest. 2. We confirm it is most essential that monthly quotas should be drawn not later than the 15th of the next month, to which the allocation refers. 4* As agreed on the ’phone yesterday, we shall be grateful if you will telegraphically take up this matter with your Principals, advising them that we shall have to recommend to our London Office cancellation of any month’s allocation which is not cleared within the time limit specified in para 3 above. Yours faithfully, Sd. J.E.ARDILL, Manager.GRAY JAaGKjSNZIS &amp; COMPANY IITD* No • V238. Basrah f 17th October 19 47* Messrs* Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co •» Ltd., Dubai * Dear Sirs, We confirm having telegraphed to you at Sharjah this morning as under: 'Wheat allocations outstanding August/September are Dubai 1260 Sharjah 540 tons stop Ministry Food insisting Shaikhdoms take immediate delivery warned us failure may cause cancellation atop strongly recommend you remit immediately funds covering 1800 tons at Dinars Thirty seven per ton Kfe&amp;ks anable us arrange shipment earliest' • J-n this connection we have to refer to previous correspondence in which we drew your attention to the necessity for the two Shaikhdoms concerned taking delivery of their monthly quotas of wheat promptly. ^e now enclose herewith copy of letter dated the 15th inst. which we have received from the Ministry of Food representative here, which is self- explanatory. We would draw your special attention to the fact that deliveries for August and September amounting to 1800 tons of wheat are now overdue, and with the October quota now due to be shipped the total is 2520 tons. The Ministry of Food have not unnaturally gained the impression that the Shaikhdoms probably do not require this wheat, and for this reason they have stipulated in para graph 3 of their letter that in future monthly quotas should be drawn not later than the 15th of the month af ter that to which the quota refers. You will also note that in para graph 4 the Ministry are considering the necessity for can celling quotas not drawn within the time limit specified in paragraph 3, and we think you should warn the Food Companies at Dubai and Sharjah immediately of the position. We may mention that we are sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Bahrain Branch, so that they may discuss with Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf the position that has arisen. In addition to the above we may mention again the difficulties which will be encountered at this date in obtain ing shipping space for the accumulation of wheat which will now have to go forward should the Food Companies concerned decide to take up the balance in arrears. We have only '’Barpeta' and 'Bamora' on the subsidiary Gulf service just now, and in these circumstances the despatch of 2520 tons of wheat to Dubai and Sharjah may present considerable difficulty. We trust that on receipt of our telegram you will arrange for the necessary funds to be remitted to us immed iately, so that we may proceed with our arrangements for the shipment of 1800 tons wheat. Yours fasithfully, £nc • for GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; COMPANY LTD s gdNo a 1962z5 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY , BAHRAIN , the 15th November, 1947 Messrs. Gray, Mackenaie &amp; Co. Ltd., BAHRAIN Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter No.BAS/176 dated the 10th November, 1947, I am directed to state that it has been agreed with the Ministry of Food Representative in Basrah to make the following reductions in the Trucial Coast wheat quota August and September 1947 allotment to be reduced from 1800 tons to 1000 tons Allotment from October 1947 onwards to be reduced to 600 tons per mensem. Yours faithfully, Sd/- J. Croning. 'LB* For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulfm GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbfabtmint, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic eoipense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time a»d formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] raoM political Officer, Trucial Cosat, Sharjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain* ' Vo - 119C.1215 Snb.iects viheat \n Reference correspoiitiorrtfe resting v^ith your express letter No. S39G-29/22 dated 27th October, 19^7, to Repgu, Bahrain, y copy endorsed to me. o ,v/ The Rii in is try of Food have nov, allocated 2160 tons of wheat to the Trucial Coast for October, November and December* The Residency A^ent asked in his telt^raiL No. 1006 of the 20th October that 800 of the 1800 tons oi wheat allocated to the Trucial Coast for August ana September should be surrendered and that the quota should be reduced to 600 tons a month for the future. The present allocation for October, November ana December amounts to 720 tons a month. ^ ♦ Since the Residency Agent * s telegram No. 1006 was sent, however, consumption of wheat on the Trucial Coast has fallen further; and the Food Companies now reouest that the allocations for October end S. 6. MFP—1515 S&amp;P—(M-20S9)—2-4-35—200,000.wmm ■■■■■■■■■■■■in - 2 - Kove^iber be c&amp;ncellea aria thet. the alloc^bion for becec.ber tnci for futui*e .months may be i*eaucea to oOO tons £ month* i'hey also request that the quota be allocated month by month because they have net sufficient capital to pay in auvance for two or three month's supply at a time. i&gt;. The fall in consumption of v/heat is reported to be due to (a) a decrease in the purchasing power of the poorer people owin^ to unemployment.; and (b) to a rise in the selling price of wheat. Hitherto the selling price of wheat has been kept down by subsidies from profits made out 01 exports oi barter su^ar to lersia; but the cost of the last consignment of su^ar foi* barter purposes leaves no room for profit from exports to Persia where su^ar is bein^ bought forward at lower prices. Iiistead of wheat anu barley the poorer people are eating more dates and fish. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah.Telegram GTC. From Political Officer Trucial Coast Political Agent t Bahrain. Sharjah. To Dated 1219 % VZ* t ' 14th and received the 15th December,1947. 2 . My Express Letter No.1190 December 8 th. Gray Mackenzie here have been informed that the Minsltry of f'eod Representative in Basrah is closing down his effice at the end of December. Gray Mackenzie have been asked to persuade Dubai and Sharjah Food Companies to take ever and pay for 2440 tons of wheat immediately. 3 ’ * s future suppljr is uncertain Companies are n os * ? _trylng to raise funds to pay for this quantity which should suffice till June 1948. POLITICAL. I.R.493GTC. bahrain, Political, bharjah. Telegram. Fromo To. No. 6 /&lt;p ' bated the 20th December, 1947. Tour telegram No.1219 dated the 14th December. Dlease confirm that if the Food Companies take over 2440 tons of wheat supplied by iiinistry of Food, basrah, you will only require an allocation of 500 tons per month after June, 1948; that until then no wheat will be required by you. Presumably if food companies take over 2440 tons of wheat it will not deterriorate in storage before it is all consumed. - POLITICAL1 n/* No. 2212-S The Hon^le the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Presents his compliments to:- The Political Agent, Muwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to them the undermentioned documents, for action on the lines proppsed if they see no objection. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN De scription of Enclosure s iameand Date British Ministry of Food (M.E.) Basra Sub-Office, letter No. C/1 dated 13th December, 1947 0 i i ({ 5 0 Subject Bagging of wheat consigned t® the Persian Gulf States.British Ministry of Food (M.B.) Basra Sub-office, Our Ref. C/1 Strick Building, &lt;fUver Front, Ashar, Basra. Dated the 13th December, 1947. Political Resident, Persian ^ulf, Bahrain. Sir, I am instructed to invite the attention of Shaikhdoms to the world shortage of grain bags and to inform them that the future wheat allocation ex Basra will be effected in this respect. In this connexion I have been advised by my London office that future wheat loaders will be from Australia and hot Canada and further that it will be shipped in bulk. This Ministry will have, with the addition of a small purchase, sufficient bags in Basrah to bag up the first Australian loader due to arrive here in February. You will appreciate, however, that subsequent loaders cannot be bagged by the Ministry as this would necessitate large purchases of bags on the local market, in which for obvious reasons the Ministry does not wish to be involved. It is suggested therefore, that with effect from March allocations consignees hand over, when taking delivery of wheat an equivalent number of new bags to be used by the Ministry for bagging up bulk cargoes. While regretting *the necessity for such a procedure it is felt that the scheme outlined is entirely in the intrests ©f the Shaikhdoms who can buy bags much more economically than the Ministry. I shall be pleased if you will communicate the contents of this letter to the Shaikhdoms. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, Sd/- J.&amp;. Ardill Manager. LRo. 18-29/22 -ir 25 //. 0?) The Political agency, Bahrain. Dated the 4th January, 1948. To. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Memorandum-J Bagging of wheat consigned to Shaikhdoras. I have b.en asked by the Representative of the Ministry of food, Basra to draw your attention to the world shortage of grain bags and to say that the future wheat allocation from Basra is likely to be affected in tnis respect. j-'he Ministry of Food in London have also advised their representative in Basra that future wheat loaders will be from Australia and not Canada and that the wheat will be shipped in bulk. 3* The Ministry of Food, Basra, have sufficient bags in Basra. to bag up to the first Australian loader due to arrive there in February. Subsequent loaders cannot be bagged by them as for them to do so would necessitate their making large purchases of bags in the local market, in which they do not wish to be involved© . ^} ie Ministry of Food, Basra, have therefore suggested that, with effect from March allocations, consignees should hand over, when taking delivery of wheat, a sufficient number of new bags to be used by the Ministry for bagging up subsequent bulk cargoes. ''-' This procedure, they feel, Is in the Interests of the consignees themselves, because they may be able to buy bags much more economical! than the Ministry© “ill you please confirm that the Charjah-Dubai Food Company will be able to supply their own bags to the Ministry of Food Basra. L. lUd/M Lr# • jA*Mvk&gt;OiI for Political agent, Bahrain.Tolegram. Fr#a. T«. N». 1300 Dated the 18th DeceMber, 1947 79/143 GTC. Pelitical Resident, Bahrain. Censul-General, Basrah Yeur telegraa Ne. Nil December loth. Bhaikhdems have ne legitimate dellars with which to pay fer wheat unless special alletments are made fer the purpese by H. G• If however specially favourable rates were fixed fer dellar payments it might be pessible fer Bahrain and Kuwait Gevernments te obtain dellars at black market rates threugh private merchants from Sadui Arabia. - HAY Ne. 2180-S Persian Gulf, Residency, Bahrain. Dated the 18th December, 1947. C-jpy, with cepy of telegram under reference, ferwarded with compliments tes- H.^ f s Secretary ef State fer Cemmenwealth Relations, Lenden. The Pelitical Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat.Ma Tel«gr-uii, GTC. Frflim. Consul-General, Basrah Te. Political Resident, Bahrain, Ne. Nil Dated the 15th and received 16th December, 1947. Wheat for Shaikhdems, Lenden wish to know whether future paynents can be made in dollars. BRITAIN&amp; Telegram Fren T# Ne. Dated 2. fund 4#fvl640 tons out of 2440 tens of wheat and wish to surrender the balance ef 800 tons. These 1640 tens and their present stocks will suffice till the end of May. Wheat will not deteriorate in storage till then. An alloca tion of 500 tons per mensem after May will be required and until then no wheat will be required. BRITAGENT. GTC. The Residency Agent, Sharjah. The Political Agent, Bahrain 1252 23rd and received the 24th Dece*ber, 1947 • /v/ / ^ • . e o . ( / Your telegram 610 December 2 1st. Food Companies have only been able to raise the I.R.) GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, DfiPAKIMHNT, EXPRESS LETTER [A 1 . B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue me of the wires, ImI intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and siy ned as if it had beets so despatched*) From Political, Bahrain, To KEPGJ, Bahrain. No. 10^' 29/22 bated 10th January, \ft ilL.KT for TRUCIAL COaB T Reference my Express letter Ko. 3390-29/^2 dated the 27th October, 1947. ^ (2*4*6) 2. 2240 tdhs of wheat have been allocated to the Trucial ^oast by the Ministry of Food and the Bharjah and Dubai Food Companies were asked to take immediate^delivery of the wheat on payment as their office in hasra was closing down at the end of December. 3. The Food Companies have been able to raise funds for only 1640 tons and wish to surrender the balance of 300 tons, ihese 1640 tons, together with their present stocks, are estimated to suffice till the end of -lay. 4. No further allocations of wheat will be required for the Trucial Coast until May; after that an allocation of 500 tons per mensem (not 600 tons as asked for oe^ . ope ) will be sufficient. It is requested that the Ministry of Food may be informed accordingly. 5. This further reduction of wheat requirements of the Trucial Coast is due to (a) decrease in the purchasing power of the poorer people due to unemployment and (b) to a rise in the selling price of wheat. 6. In place of wheat and barley, eating more dates and fish. the poorer people have taken to • POLITICAL — Issue of the above has been authorised.EXPiiSSS LlTT^R qB&gt; From Political, Bahrain To Bepgu, Bahrain No. (%/ -29/22. Bahrain, 18th January 1948 WHEAT FOB TRUCIAL COilST n Reference ray Express Letter No. 105-29/22, dated the 10th Juiuary 1948. 2. The wheat allocation for the Trucial Coast by the * Ministry of Food is 2440 tons and not 2240 as mentioned in para 2 of the Express Letter under reference. The necessary correction may kindly be made. POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised for Political Agent, BahrainJh m No.46 # 1215 British Agency, Sharjah Dated 14th January,1948 To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject: Bagging of wheat consigned to Persian Bulf Shaiicnaoms. ^BANDIT-. ^ris oi + Peference your memorandura No.18-29/22 dated the 4th January, 1948. 2. The Dubai and Sharjah Pood Companies will be able to supply their own bags to the Ministry of pood, Basrah, for wheat as from June 1948 quota; no wheat will be required until then. u £ !\&lt;&amp;V Agent, Sharjah,y No. 2VI-29/1 &amp; 29/22 The 'oliticul Bahrain Dated t'ue 20th January&gt; 1948 To. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, \ Per cion Gulf, , Bahrain. . S / J I ^ - / V • J Memorandum Reference your printed letter No. 2212-3 dated the 22nd December, 1943. 2. 1 confirm that the Bahrain Government and the Sharjah and Dubai Food Companies will be able to suoply their own bags to the Ministry of Food, Basra.—f G.T.C Political Resident, Bahrain* British Consul General, Basrah. Telegram From To No. A/62. Dated the 22nd January, 1948. Following for Ministry of food representative; begins s- r Political Agent, Bahrain, reports that the Trucial Coast sheikhdoms are ufcable to absorb 2440 tons wheat allocated to them. They are able to purchase 1640 tons and wish to surrender 800 tons. Amount ^ purchased will meet their requirements until end May. 2. From June onwards Trucial Coast requirements will be 500 tons per month. Please confirm that you will arrange t is. - Ends. = REPGU = NO.194-80/78.A. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated the 22nd January, 1948 Copy forwarded to 1. H.M*s Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London, with reference to KM express letter No. E.1789/47 dated the 18th April,*47. / 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his express letter No. 105-29/22 dated the 10th January*48. i\ i' \ \ i\ N for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.EXPRESS LEITKB . PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAiliiAlU From Political Rasiclant, Persian Gulf, Bahrain lo British Ministry of Food, Strlck Building Ashar, Basrah. Repeated CROSEC, LONDON. POLITICAL, BAHRaIN. No.208-80/78-A Bahrain, 27th January, 1948 // Continuation of my telegram No.A/62 January 2nd. WHEAT FOR THUCiAL COAST SHAIKHDOMS. -y 2* reduction of wheat requirements of the Truclal Coast is due (a) to a decrease in the purchasing power of the poorer people due to unemployment (b) to a rise in the selling price of wheat. 3, In place of wheat and barley, the poorer people have taken to eating more dates and fish. - REPGU The issue of the above has been authorised ^. ^r\ for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No. «2g) FROM GRAY, MACKENZIE 6c CO., LTD. TO The Political Agent, Bahrein, BAHREIN. s' \ ■+ 19-- 48. Dear Sir, V y Our Basrah branch advise ns that the local office of the - ^v^British Ministry of Food have written them as follows: 'In reply we would state that there appears to be a certain amount of misapprehsion on the part of Sharjah regarding future supplies. Will you therefore kindly inform them that the closing of this office will not any way affect their future allocations except that deliveries will be effected by Messrs. Frank C.Strick &amp; Co.(Basra)Ltd., acting as Ministry Agents. Their request for 100 tons wheat is not understood in view of a telegram which we have received from the Political Agent, Bahrein, and which we quote for your information: ^ 5-&gt; ^ ^ 2.1 'POLITICAL AGENT BAHREIN REPORTS THAT TRUCIAL SHEIKHDOMS ARE UNABLE TO ABSORB 2,440 TONS OF WHEAT ALLOCATED TO THEM THEY ARE ABLE TO PURCHASE 1,640 TONS AND WISH TO SURRENDER 800 TONS. AMOUNT PURCHASED WILL MEET THEIR REQUIREMENTS UNTIL THE END OF MAY. 2. ERCM JUNE ONWARD TRUCUL REQUIREMENTS WILL BE 500 TONS PER MONTH. PLEASE CONFIRM YOU WILL ARRANGE THIS' We have advised our London Office and Messrs. Frank C.Strick of the contents of this telegram and would suggest that if Sharjah wish to make any further alterations at this stage, they should take up the matter through Political Agent, Bahrein, for arrange ment with Ministry of Food, London, under advice to Stricks' As you doubtless know, the Basrah office of the British Ministry of Food is shortly to close down and if there is any action that you wish us to take, we should be glad to hear from you as early as possible. Yours faithfully, GRAY,M229 4 c EXPRESS LETTER From. Political, Bahrain. To. Political, Sharjah. No. GOI. -29/22 Dated the 21st February, 1948. Reference your telegrams Nos. 1219 and 1252 dated the Idth and 23rd December, 1947. WHEAT. ^ 2. I enclose a copy of a letter No. L/69 dated the 15th February, 1948 from Hessrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, which is self-explanatory. 3. I do not understand the reference to 100 tons of wheat in para 3 of enclosure, but it may mean something to you. 4. If you wish to make any alterations as regards wheat allocations at this stage would you please inform me urgently. - POLITICAL - The issue of the above has been authorised for Political Agent, Bahrain. LGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, ♦7 ' 7 . •British Agency Department. Sharjah EXPRESS LETTER [N, B, — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if il had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From - Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. To _ Politicel Agent, Bahrain. Maw 275.1215 Dated 24th March, 1948. J9$ Your express letter No.6bl-29/22 dated the 21st February, 1948. WHEAT. 2. Neither the Dubai nor the Sharjah Food Companies know anything about the reference to 100 tons of wheat and say that they have not asked for this amount. 3 , T do not wish to make any alterations as regards wheat allocations at this stage. You will observe from the enclosures to mv memorandum No.174.1235 dated the 2nd March, 1948, that wheat consumption on the Trucial Coast has dropped. Because of this the present stocks may last longer than was at first anticipated. The drop in consumption has occurred because many people have left the Trucial Coast and many of those who remain are too poor to pay the high price of wheat. Consumption is likely to drop further if any of the new wheat crop arrives from Persia. s. 6. M FP— 1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4^2-36—200,000.No. |o6-8 -29/22. (2J£ To V — Politic*! A^®acy, Bahrain# Th« 5th April 5 1948# ^«ssrs. Gray i4ack®nzi« &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. . V 0 Daar Sirs, - / Please refer to your letter No. L/69 dated the 15th February, 1948. P. Neither this office ncr the Political Officer, Trucial Coast to whom a refdrence was made, know v anything about the 100 tons of wheat mentioned in you letter under reference. * 3. No alteration at this ^tage regarding wheat allo&lt;jition is contemplated. Political Agent, Bahrain.4 v\ ^V.^aOo. Telegram - From - To - No. 383. Dated the 19th and received the 21st April, 1948. Political, Sharjahs Political, Bahrain. S&gt;' V Reference correspondence ending with my express letter No. 275, March 24th. Wheat. 2. British Ministry of Food, Basra,may kindly be asked to release Trucial Coast wheat quota of 500 tons, a month on June and thereafter. = POLITICAL =EXPRESS LETTER. From - To - No. 22nd January Political, Bahrain. Prodrome, Bahrain. -29/22 Dated the 'z^April, 1948 s. 1/ Reference your endorsement No. 194-80/78 A , 1948. Wheat for Trucial Coast. dated 2. Authorities concerned may kindly be asked to release Trucial Coast wheat quota of 500 tons a month on June and thereafter, cf. your endoresement 678-80/78 A dated 10th March, 1948. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, . Bahrain. [J^■u ■ \ SavIngram From To Zb Prodrome [Jaarain*, Prourome London# No. - (80/78-A) dated the 22nd January 1948 to the Cor monwealth Eelation» Office# Trucial Coast wheat requirements# 2# Grateful if Ministry of Food may be asked to arrange release of the Truciul Coast wheat quota of 500 tons per month from June 1048 onwards. Prodrome# The issue of the above has been authorised# Sd. A.L.A. Dredge. Secretary to the Political He silent Persiaii Gulf# Copy to: 1. Messrs Frank Strick and Co. ^ 2. Political Agent, Bahrain. htd. Basrah. / 9avIngram (ht From - To - No. 26 (80/78-A). Dated the Ist/3rd May, Prodrome, Bahrain, Prodrome, London. j.v^ oo j t Reference itojLjw-rilorsement 194-80/78-A dated I th r:c?ii na cosra.^f q iLS. , „f;r , ” ,,lth ofriL - “ot. b Vr 1 S 2 g„. per month from June 1948 onwards* = PRODROME = The issue of the above has been authorised. Copy to Sd./- A.L.A.Dredge. Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. 1. Messrs. Frank Strick and Co. Ltd.. 2 . ihe Political Agent, Bahrain. Basrah. No. 11 * 5 - 1 + -29/22. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 8 th ^ay, 1948. Copy forwarded to The Political Officer, , , Trucial Coast, Shariah, to his telegram No. 383 dated the 19th Apr!' / with reference 1948.Telegram From To No. 494. Dated G.T.C. Brita&lt;fent, Shrajam^v Political, Bahrain The 25th May, and received the 26th May, 1948. &lt;vO' My telegram 383 April 20th Paragraph 2. 2. Although price of 500 tons of Wheat for June quota has been remitted it appears that no shipment has been made by s.s. Bamoaa expected to arrive here May 20th. Grateful if arrangement could be made for shipment of quota by next down steamer. IR 168 = Britagent=GTC &gt; Telegram From! To No. Dated £ Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. 31st May, 1948. PELLY to JACKSON. LERMITTE writes to me that his JACKSON informs him that food situation on the Trucial Coast is at present very difficult and shows signs of becoming worse. Please let me have your comments on this report. = POLITICAL =l3XPEi£SS LflTIKR FROM: POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. TOi PhOLROAi, BAHRAIN. No•B * 91 -29/1 Dated the 3rd June 1943. n/ y We shall he faced wit}) a food crisis in Bahrain, and possibly on the Tracial Coast, if early steps are not ta’cen to meet the present situation* 2 , The oi’iginal ceroal quota for Bahrain was fixed at 900 tons (wheat 630 and barley 270)* In October 1943 on a representation by the Bahrain Government that this was not sufficient, it was increased to 1000 tons (wheat 670 and barley 330), In June 1945 the Bahrain Government said that its merchants could make private arrangements to import barley and the barley quota was then given up leaving the wheat quota at 670 tons. In February 1946 the wheat allotment was fixed at 710 tons oer month, the total quota being at 1020 tons per month (which included 310 tons of barley imported under private arrange wents). 3 # This quota did wall enough when the ration could be supplemented by local purchase in the free markot, but since the Persians have prohibited exports, this market no longer exists. Furtneriao ; 'e, tne quota was originally 1 ixod on the census figures of 1933 which gave the population for the purpose of rationing as 90,000 and ration cards were issued for this number in 1940. Now they are issued to 105,000 people. As a result the previous ration of 20 lbs. per head per month had in November 1047 to be reduced to 14 lbs. poi 1 head per month in the town and 13 lbs. per head per month in the villages. 4 . The present population made the figure of 710 tons inadequate to supply the country's needs even on the under standing that ration was supplemented by local purchases to the extent that the Government Itself had to purchase wheat to sup plement the .Ministry of Food quota and it issued an average of 954 tons of wheat per month in 1947. 5 . The Ministry of Food's wheat quotas for Bahrain for the months of April and Hay are in arrears. 6, To meet the situation the Bahrain Government's request are i that the arrears of the wheat quota for the months of April, May and June be delivered forthwith; and that the barley quota of 310 tons surrendered should be restored and, if possible, rice or wheat to that amount in that oraer of preference be deli vered. CD (2) : &gt;x7* I support these requests most strongly. Unless urgent action can be taken to raent the liuhiuin Government *8 requests, I would reiterate the reconnandation made in the Agency Memorandum tfo.R.56, dated the 15th imy, 1948, for foreign exchange for tho inport of rice from Uruguay on condition that the oroviso regarding the set-off cf rice against the wheat imports (vide Residency iixnress letter Ho.931-3 dated the loth November 1945) be not enforced as in view of the relative nutritive qualities of the two grains the Bahrain Government is not willing to surrender tvi*&gt; thirds of a ton of wheat for a ton of rice* 8* The Bahrain Government or its merchants v ill also be able to take advantage of an offer of 5000 tons of rice from Brazil provided Brazilian currency to the value of £305,000 is made available* Is this possible? 9. I am not able to give a full report on the situa tion on the Trucial Coast, but I am awaiting one. Although the price of 500 tons wheat for its June quota has been remitted, it appears that no shipment has been made so far. I would request that British Unistry of Food Agents at Basrah be asked to make the shipment by the next down steamer 10. Is there any possibility of importing cereals from Pakistan, e.g. Kangunl rice from Baluchistan (vide corres pondence ending with Pettigrew’s Demi-official latter No.1730-79/265 dated the 8th August, 1947)? t* POLITICAL'? The issue of the i;bove lias been authorised. For POLITICAL AGLNT, LAaKAiN.GOVERNMENT OF [INDIA. British Ageaey^ Sharjah, _ Department, EXPRESS LETTER (iV. B ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the, same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From To No. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, UX Political Agent, Bahrain. 523.12|&gt;5 Dated the 1st June 19t 48. Reference your telegram No.380 dated the 31st May, 1948. 2. Increase in price of dates in February — para: 22 of Trucial Coast News Report No.3 of 1948 — later led to unexpected increase in demand for wheat from persons who did not formerly buy their rations and for victualling pearling boats,and there was danger that wheat supplies would be exhausted before quota for June arrived. 3. Issues were therefore restricted strictly to the ration and there are now sufficient stocks of wheat to last till arrival of June quota reported being shipped by Barjora due here mid - June. Quota of 500 tons a month is due thereafter. 4. Only small quantities of Persian rice are available. Price of dates rema ir* high, bugar and tea are plentiful. 5. There is distress on the Trucial Coast because of unemployment and of high price of dates and rice. Provided monthly quotas are delivered promptly there should be no shortage of wheat, but there are no large stocks on which to fall back if shipment is delayed. Food Companies were urged to maintain stocks but would not raise funds to pay for them in advance. 6. We have no control over the price of dates or rice. Prices here depend on prices in Basrah and in Iran. S. 6. MFP—1196 S&amp;P-(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah.EXPRESS LETTER POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. From To No Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bahrain. Dated 5th June, 1948. • $.91+- ^fjxi Reference paragraph 9 of this Agency Express Letter No.R.91-29/1, dated the 3rd June, 1943. 2. Jackson now reports that M there are now suf- % ficient stocks of wheat to last till arrival of June quota reported being shipped by Barjora due here ftiid- June. Quota of 500 tons a month is due thereafter.” 3. Grateful for confirmation that June quota will arrive by Barjora mid-June and that 500 tons a month will be punctually delivered in future. (SGD) C.J. PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . d* Assistant rolitica^ Bahrsin. Agent,HEAD OFFICE: 122. uEAD EN HALL STREET, LON D0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. A 'z&amp;h Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND BUS R E H. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAH POUR BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR. BRANCHES: BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE ACS/48/668. No. Bahrain, 31st May, 1948. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Dear Sir, WHEAT, TRUCIAL COAST. We have tibday received the following telegram from our Basrah offices- 'MINISTEY FOOD ALLOCATED WHEAT TRUCIAL COAST FIVE HUHDHED TONS MONTHLY FOR SIX MONTHS STOP PROPOSED SHIP THIS FOUR HUNDRED DUBAI ONE HUNDRED SHARJAH CONSULT POLITICAL' and we should be glad if you will confirm, or otherwise, that the proposed allocation of 400tons to Dubai and lOOtons to Sharjah monthly for six months is agreeable to you. We should also be pleased to receive any further observations that you may wish to make. wjm/bdb ITelegram O.T.C. Fromm Political, Bahrain ’ olitie~l, r harjah No. 39P. Dated The 7th June,' 1948. Grays Basrah propose to ship the tons of wheat for the Trucial coast in following pcoportion :'iubwi 4ro tons Fharjah 100 tons. Please telegraph if this is ^ agr-eable. Have you any other- instructions regarding these shipments, = Political = ^ y?)4^ Telegram From To No. 558. Dated G.T.C. Political, 'harjch Political, Bahrain The 9th and received the 10th June, 1948. (frJU*- (Lclc** IR 184. Your telegram 392 June 7th. Suggestion agreeable. * • Q ' _ Grateful if July quota could be shinned as early in month as possible. ^ = Political =UhGKNT. No. ^33 -29/22. Political Agency, Bahrain Dated 13th June, 1948 The Manager, i4/S Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., R A H R A I N._ Dear Sir Please refer to your letter No. ACS/48/668, dated 31st May, 1948. 2 . The proposal to ship 400 tons of *&gt;rheat to Dubai and 100 tons to Sharjah monthly for six months is approved, and I should oe grateful j you would telegraph your Basra office according ly* 3 . it is also requested that the July quota be shipped as early in July as possible, as the cereal position on the Trucial .^oast is acute. Yours faithfully, or Political Agent, BahrainTelegram From To No. ' 3S S Dated GTC Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. 3rd June, 1948. PELLY to JACKSON. Unless you see any objection, please address letters to Trucial Shaikhs warning them that if they allow export of quota grain from their territories they need not expect fresh supplies. * POLITICALTelegram From To Repeated 3- l&amp;i En clair. Britain, Basra. Political Resident, Bahrain. Foreign Office, London (For Ministry of Food). No.12. Dated 14th, received 15th June 1948. Reference your 524 of 12th June addressed Strick subject WHEAT. Payment for April quota Bahrain just received. Shipping next steamer. Would remind that terms are cash before delivery. June quota Trucial Coast delivered to Agents end of May and understand shipped first week June. - BRITAIN - NPG. Copy to the Political Agent,Bahrain, for information and such action as he may consider necessary. l { &amp;- 0 No. 80/78 A. Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain dated 15th June 1948.Telegram From To No. Dated IjlG En clair Political Agent, Bahraii. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. 17th June, 1948. Following is extract from telegram from BRITAIN, BASRAH, begins June quota Trucial Coast delivered to Agents end of May and understand shipped first week June. Ends. = POLITICAL =POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No.2025-29/22 The 28th June 1948. The undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah for information with reference to his telegram No.383 dated the 19th April 1948. For Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy of letter No.E 7226/69/65 dated the 2nd June 1948 from Foreign Office, London received under Residency Endorsement No.1650- 80/78.A dated the 23rd June 1948. NNRD.O.No. K.127-29/21. My dear Dredge, \ Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated 20th June, 1948. V M l Please fe-Ter to your endorsement No. 1566-80/78-A, dated, the 15th June, 1948, with which a cony of telegram No.12, dated the 14th June, 1948, from Britain,Basrah, was forwarded to me. 2. The expression in the telegram % would remind that terms are eash before delivey' seems to imply that the Bahrain Government delayed the payment and that this was the reason for the dei^y in delivery. - If this implication is correct, there must be a misunderstanding and as the matter is vitally important, I should be glad if it could be cleared up. 3. The telegram seems to be from Stricks though I understand G2*ay Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Basrah, are tie shipping agents for the Bahrain Government. When they iut£jax inform the Bahrain Government through their Bahrain Office that the wheat quota is ready for shipment, the Bahrain Government remits cash to Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co.,Ltd-., Basrah telegraphica- -lly. As far as I know there has never been any delay about this. For example, on the 31st .;Iay,.the Bahrain Government were informed that 780 tons of ..heat for Bahrain and ^atar were ready and they were asked to remit I.D.30,000/-. This was done telegraphicalLly through the Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain, on the 2nd June. The Bahrain Government is ready, if necessary to avoid delay, to olace a deoosit with the Eastern Bank Ltd., Basrah, to pay for shipments. 4 Major A.L.A.Dredge, M.B.E. Secretary to his Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.4. I should be grateful if you could find out and let me knpw the reau. cause of delay in making the shipments and whether there is anything thath the Bahrain Government :can do to avoid it in future. Yours sincerely, Sd. C.J.Pelly.No. 315-29/1. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 2nd February, If 1 ^ Dear Agency, The question intinuing procurement of wheat for Colonial and other territories has recently been raised in connection with the pattern of the United Kingdom’s purchases from Australia. It may be decided that the best plan would be for the United Kingdom to procure Australian wheat throughout 1949 for the Trucial Coast States and to leave them to make their own arrangements for procurement from 1950 onwards. We should be grateful, therefq£, if you would would let us have your views on the suggestion that His liajesty’s Government should stop procuring wheat for the Trucial Coast at the end of 1949. Yours Ever, AGENCY. To The Agency, (ORIGINAL ! . ) -FILE INo*160-1 \ &gt;British Agency, 5 / /* Sharjah. 6} /. TOe 16th Feb 1949 Dear Agency, Z / With reference to your letter No. 316-29/1 dated the 2nd February 1949, we agree in principle with the suggested reversion to free procurement of wheat. finding difficulty in disposing of even the existing quota as wheat is in only moderate demand. 3. The wheat quota has, on the other hand, been of great advantage to the people of the Trucial Coast in the past, and before finally recommending its abolition we should like to be assured that: • (a) Wheat purchased independently would not be likely to be so expensive as to upset the whole local cost of living, (b) Independent local merchants would not 2 At present, the Dubai Food Company are find themselves at an unfair disadvant age when purchasing supplies in competi tion with such organizations as our own Ministry of Food. Yours ever, AGENCY To The Agency, BAHRAIN.c BRITISH AGENCY, SHARJAH• No.172.1215 THE 22nd FEBRUARY 1949. The Dubai Food Company report that owing to the decline in both population and income of the Trucial Coast since the war, the wheat quota is now too large and that they have an accumulated surplus of 800 tons which they are afraid may deteriorate. They request that the February quota be suspended and that they be allowed to sell the accumulated stocks before the March quota arrives. 2. In principle, we are against requesting the Ministry of Food to reduce their issues, as we may require their help in obtaining larger quotas in future, if and when a possible expansion in the Oil Company's work in the Trucial Coast produces an increased local- demand for food grains. However, as the merchants appear unable to deal with the existing supplies, we are bound to recommend that the February quota only be suspended. 3 # The merchants state that there is no chance of re-exporting the surplus as the price of wheat is generally low. BAHRAIN.No. K-| £&gt;(&gt;-29/22. / , - Dear Residency/ VJ/ ! OLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 3rd ^larch, 1949. &lt;4 c 6^ The Duba^Food. C^iipany report that pwing to the dec34rte in both population and income of the Trucial Coast since the war, the wheat quota is now too large and that they have an accumulated surplus of 890 tons, which they are afraidpay deteriorate. They request that the February quota be suspended and that they may be allowed to sell the accumulated stocks before the I4arch quota arrives. 2. In principle, we are against requesting the Ministry of Food to reduce their issues, as we may require their help in obtaining large quotas in future, if and when a possible expansion in the Oil CompanyVs‘work in the r :’rucial Coast produces an increased local demand for food grains. However, as the merchants appear unable to deil with the existing supelies, we are bound to recommend that the February 4uota only be suspended. 3. The merchants state that there is no chance of re-exporting the surplus as the price of wheat is generally low. To The Persian Gulf Residency, Jufai r* &amp; No. ^^-29/22y^ \ / &gt; / POLITICAL ACiliNCX, 3AK; AIN. The 3rd - 1 archj 1949. Dear British, Agencj^ 0- Please refer to your letter No. 172.1215 dated the 22nd February, 1949. 2. The merchants sell the accumulated March quota arrives, the Residency asking quota be suspended. should be allowed to stocks before the We have written to that the February Yours Ever* AGENCY. The British Agency, N Sharjah.c pa . /U-K' ?3 • £ TELE Eft CLAIR FROM P.R. BAHREIN TO STRICK LTD BASRA TEL NO fl#*, 12. Zur^u DATED 16/3/49 Important. £, T A . Fleas e witfthold February quota wheat for Dubai. Continue despatch quotas for March and following months. Hay.Poli tica&gt;3^^ah rain. Political, Sharjah The 24th J^arch, 1949 YOUR LETTER NO. 172.1215 DATED FEBRUARY 22ND 1949. 2. STRICKS BASRA REPORT THAT NEITHER FEBRUARY NOR EARCH Q.UOTA FOR TRUCIAL COAST YET APPLIED FOR. PLEASE CLARIFY POSITION.COPY L FROM FciANK C ST RICK &lt;&amp; CO. (BASRA) LTD., BASRA POST OFFICK BOX NO. 49, 23rd 21st March, 1949. Sir Rupert Hay, Political Resident, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We have to acknowledge receipt of your telegram of the 17th instant reading as follows:- M IMPORTANT. PLEASE WITHHOLD FEBRUARY QUOTA WHEAT FOR DUBAI •'CONTINUE DESPATCH QUOTAS FOR MARCH ON FOLLOWING MONTHS. HAY” and confirm our reply of today's date reading as follows •’DOES YOURS SEVENTEENTH REFER DUBAI ONLY OR WHOLE TRUCIAL 'COAST FOR WHICH NEITHER FEBRUARY NOR MARCH QUOTAS YET AP- ”PLIED FOR. STRICK COMPANY”. We enclose herewith in duplicate a letter which we addressed to the Political Agent at Sharjah on the 18th instant which is relevant to the telegrams exchanged, and trust that we will receive full advices regarding quotas in the near future. Yours faithfully. For FRANK C. STRICK &amp; CO (BASRA) LTD. (Signed) IllegibleFunk C. Strick &amp; Co , (Basra) Ltd. BASRAH. (COPY) 'c. ite ■ , 16th March, 194-9* The Political Apent, Shariah. Dear Sir, MINISTRY OF FOOD - ?/?IEAT o As you are no doubt aware, we are agents for the Ministry of Food in Basrah and attend to the deliveries of Wheat for the various Persian Gulf Shekhdoms. Messrs, Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co,, Ltd, normally take delivery about the beginning of each month of the quotas for Sharjah and Dubai of 100 and 400 tons respectively per month, payment being made into our B 3 rik account in Bahrein in advance. By the end of February payment not having been received from Sharjah or Dubai for the February quota, Gray Mackenzies telegraphed their Sharjah and Dubai offices and a reply was received from Sharjah reading as follows 'YOURTEL 26TH UNDERSTAND FEBRUARY QUOTA ALLOTTED ’’LAPSE THROUGH POLITICAL”. On receiving this adviee we wrote to the Ministry of Food, Cereals Division in Portman Court, and we have now had their reply stating that they have no knowledge of the cancellation of any quota and Messrs. Gray Mackenzie have not as yet had any further information in explanation of the telegram quoted above. As it is now half way througn March and no application has been made from Sharjah and Dubai for their March quotas, we shall be glad if you can advise us ox the position as soon as possible so that we may assess our stock position as there is now a total of 1000 tons of Wheat outstanding for your area not yet taken up. We are passing this letter through the R.A.F. as we understand that the ordinary mail services take anything up to six weeks between here and Sharjah and we shall be glad if you could have your reply passed back in the same way as we are anxious to have the information required as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, FOR FRANK C. STRICK &amp; CO. (BUSRA) LTD. (Sgd.) D.C. McGregor. MPBA M Cl I z Telegram G.T.C. ^ rom Political, bharjah.' • Political,Bahrain. No. . 322 Dated the 24th(received the 25th) March, 1949. Your letter No.498-29/22 of March 3rd. Wheat. i ^• F.C.Strick of Basrah have informed me they have not yet been instructed by Ministry of Food to cancel February quota. 3* Suggest Residency be asked to expedite instructions to Ministry of Food. Political5.6 .No. isd'^Tsxs Confidential. British Agency, Sharjah. The 27th March 1949. C y 2. I applied f quota in this Agency’s letter No. 172-1215 of 22nd please refe of 24th March 1949 re I applied f Pehruary 1949. At that tine, the mercnants v^ho consititute the Duhai Pood Company considered that they 'would he able to accept the March quota. many hags of mixed wheat and harley which will easily undersell the quota wheat. This grain will inevitably attract the poorer trade. Cheap Australian flour is also appearing on the market. On 26th March, a deputation of merchants came to the Agency and asked me, in view of these changed conditions, to cancel the March and April quotas also. I suggested free sale of the accumulated stocks, hut apparently the demand for wheat would not he great enough to affect these. With the probability of even more wheat arriving from Persia, they are unwilling to increase the present stocks of 800 tons and nothing will persuade them otherwise^particularly as the wheat is beginning to show signs of deterioration. I have personally inspected the godowns and can confirm that very large stocks are already in hand. 5 # x can, therefore, only »eeemmend that the merchants’ suggestion i.e., that the March and April quotas be cancelled, but that the May quota be accepted. 3 # Since that time, however, the smugglers returning from Persia have been bringing with them M. C C. Andrew, Esquire, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN . The 3rd April, 1949 Please refer to your C.S. No. (46/48/49) of 26th March, 1949. 2. We applied for cancellation of the February quota in this Agency’s letter No. R-106-29/22 of the 3rd March, 1949. At that time, the merchants, who constitute the Dubai Food Company, considered that they would be able to accept the March quota 3. Since that time, however, the smugglers returning from Persia have been bringing with them many bags of mixed wheat and barley, which will easily undersell the quota wheat. This grain will inevitably attract the poorer trade. Cheap Australian flour is also appearing in the market. On the 26th March, a deputation of merchants called on the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah and asked him to cancel the March and April quotas also, in view of the changed conditions. The latter suggested free sale of the accumulated stocks, but apparently the demand for wheat would not be great enough to affect these. With the possibility of even more wheat arriving from Persia, the merchants are un-willing to increase the present stocks of 800 ton* and nothing will persuade them otherwise, particularly, as the wheat is showing signs of deter18$:ion. The Political Officer, Trucial Coast confirms that very large stocks are already in hand. 4. We suggest therefore that Messrs. Strick &lt;£ Co., Ltd., Basra may be informed that the March and April quotas will not be applied for or taken up and may be treated as cancelled, but that normal quota will be applied for and resummed from May. Yours ever, Agency. The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.Copy of letter No. ACS/49/401 of the 19th March from Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &lt;&amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, to His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. WHEAT - DUBAI AND SHARJAH . We have received the following telegram from our Basrah Office: ' WHEAT QUOTAS IN ARREARS DUBAI FEBRUARY MARCH SHARJAH MARCH ONLY FEBRUARY QUOTA LAPSED STOP PLEASE ENQUIRE RESIDENT INFORM US ARE THESE QUOTAS REQUIRED STOP IF SO RECOMMEND DUBaI SHaRJAH MAKE IMMEDIATE PAYMENT ENABLE US ARRANGE SHIPMENT BARJCRA ABOUT SECOND APRIL'. In accoraance therewith, we should be glad to hear whether these quotas are required. If they are so required, kindly recommend that these Sheikhdoms make immediate payment, in the usual manner through our Dubai Office, in order that early shipment as above may be made.TELE EN CLAIR FROM P.R. BAHREIN TO F*0* TEL NO* 153* ' STRICKS BASRA U/N. BATED 7/4/49. Addressed to F.O. and to Stricks Basra* My telegram 142* Owing to accumulated stock 800 tons wheat and imports from outside sources quota for whole Trucial Coast Tor February March and April may please be cancelled* Normal quota will be applied for from May* Copy to P.A.BNo. 99$ -29/22. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 13th April, 1949. Dear British Will you please refer to your letter No. 330.1215 of 27th March, 1949. Wheat for the Trucial Coast. We enclose herewith a copy of telegram No. 153 of 7th April, 1949 from His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Foreign Office for your information. 3. The Residency have asked that the whole quota be revised in order to prevent any more last minute cancellation and we think this question might well be discussed during your next visit. To The British Agency, Sharjah. Yours ever, Agency.Telegram G.T.C. p rom To No. 432. Dated Political, Sha jah. Political, Bahrain. ceived here the 28th 9. FOR POLITICAL OF FIC ER, TRUCIAL COAS T. 3} Reference Bahrain Agency Letter No.998, dated the 13th April, 1949 - Wheat quota. 2. Du food company wish me cancel May quota. I recommedd request be granted. PoliticalTelegram From To No. 261 Dated G.T.C: Political, Bahrain. Political, Sharjah The 3.ath-April, 1949, T&gt;0 0 Yoram No.5 432 Wheat. Please give aporoximate' stock totals. Do you recommend cancellation of June 'Juota also? PoliticalTelegram From G.T.C r ' #■ To No. 444 Dated Political, Sharjah Political, Bahrain. n/ 2. Yrtel 261, april 30th. Wheat. Stock total 560 tons. 3. Yes. 4. Sharjah Food Company require May and June their quota 100 tons each. PoliticilTelegram ZilTJL&amp;M G.T.C From Political, Bahrain. To Political, Sharjah. No.281. Dated The 5th Hay, 1949. Your Telegram 444 of Hay 2nd. //heat. 2* Your telegram 432 of April 26th requests for the cancellation of May quota of Mieat for Dubai Food Company whereas y^ur 444 of ..lay 2nd requests for the supply of Hay and June ^uo&amp;a for Sharjah Food Company. Please Clarify. 3* Please also state whether the Dubai Food Company require to take their June quota. Political% No. R-^^29/22. Dear Residency, POLITICAL AGExNCi, BAHRAIN. The 23rd May, 1949. &amp; ... Please rofe^vto.the correspondence resting with your C.S. No. (46/57/49) of the 7th April, 1949, re^ariing wheat for the Srucial Coast. Ye enclose herewith copies of the •.ollowing telegrams for necessary action 1. Telegram No. 432 dated 26-4-49 from Political, Sharjah to Political, Bahrain. 2 . Telegram No. 261 dated 30-4-49 from Political, Bahrain to Political, Sharjah. 3. Telegram No. 444 dated 2-5-49 from Pailitlcal, fharjah to Political, Bahrain. 4. Telegram No. 281 dated 5-' -49 from Political, Bahrain to Political, Sharjah. 3. The Residency Agent, Sharjah, who is at present ir Bahrain, confirms that the Dubai r?°I?AA 0 * pany d ° not require ^ay and June quotas ' ons en&lt; 5h of wheat and that the Sharjah C°? paliy require their May and June quotas or 100 tons each. To 6\ The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. fours ever, Agency. 0 ^ i- r 'rfM. i-~Tcl • No- folo'x cll~. J &amp;L lb /^/?. / 5 c—/tM. 0 C KG1 • » U » U • Ojk • jj.r.ii. to Adviser submitted. Regarding T r ucici± Uoci^t pontica-L onicer may oe consulted. Rex. r.u.u. uo ... ; ' ' 4 Theoraticaily as there is no stocK of bariey it v;ii.l not Dt a sufficient excuse for xeSping down the adulterant &lt;i/d: tnat of Vkheat stocx or a minimum stocx oi 4 jjj tons oi Ddrxe^ a. montns required adurterant. Buu aauutertait is being lorceu upon^ us and they may insist upon adulterating vvneat kith barley or mixxet and not replace bariey d„ rice. Bahrain too would nave prefered pure wheat ana rice the choice is given us. But due to circumstances aciuiteiant will have to be Kept up. tons (a months requirement) oi cerears and rice. Rice may be necessary bariey which due to unrorseen circumstances they are unable to get it through private channels at present. au pa &amp; e and asu i.d. to inciuae even private innerts in the monthiy statements oi stocks. May issue teiegranf? n'.r .-a. jj. i/o wheat : Bariey. There ought to have a barley sto.cK oi i/d of \ 77 It may be T-Ci is able to replace rice ror bariey. 7* T.U. can insist upon a minimum requirement oi i&amp;dO set oil against cereais. But ii they are to Keep up the pro^ortia ox k/ o : i/o wheat : barley, U.h.u.u. will have to supply them the» ■yye will have to modify para 'd ox our letter to x.u. Submitted ror orders. l4t-b-iu4o.29^22 - Cereals for T.C. / locj UlU Mt lULtO It- r -UL !l Cereal quota for T.C. is 1230 tons per month. Figures for the last six months show£ that average consumption of cereals is 932 tons only. (A statement kept below). The balance suggested by B.S.M. If a reserve of wheat is to be formed on T.C. as suggested by the P.O.T.C. (please see page 99 and N/para 140) it may be done with the Hon ! ble the P.R.*s permission and the figures of the reserve so formed need not be informed to B.S.M. X Reply to P.U.C. may not be made direct and may be addressed to the Hbn*ble the P.R. at the end of each month -get accumulated to florin a big reserve of 2443 tons on the 1st of May 1946. A- It may be that we will have to agree to the re4uMrron I* Cw-'i v oAiu»xyx\ - /-/ c (m) rynrs &lt;j^&lt;t /Vo- HUl, C( , Reference A.P.A^s verbal orders regarding the fixation of cereal ' quota on the T.6 ; There were no fixed quotas of cereals for T.C. KxxixEK in the earlier periods of war and monthly total consumption of cereals for sometime until Febnnary 194-4 was taken as 1900 tons (PI, see t page 75 of 29/22i). By the time Mr. Eagleton, the then U.K.C.C. representative in Baghdad visited Sheikhdoms and after discussions, details of which are not available in this office, agreed to a * monthly quota of l3&gt;5o tons of cereals for the m .C. It is not \ known how the figure has been arrived at, but perhaps the at page 24 of the same file night have been helpful, and also kindly see pages 106 and 107, 'Monthly requirements' of the T.C. on file 29/22 i. Later oi\ 120 tons of' cereals, requirements of Qatar, w^re included in the Bahrain’s quota with corresponding decrease in the Trucial Coast’s. Added (102) Telegram No.Coolie 09712, dt. 13.6.46 from Menin, Cairo. On T.C. the rate of food consumption has never been constant and depended on the visits of outlying Shaikhs to collect requirements, and k± increased during the pearling season. The T.C. quota of 1230 tons of cer als represents average hkh± minimum monthly consumption throughout the year, but in view of the serious world shortage of cereals a review is being made to reduce the cereals quota on the T.C., if it can .be effected without causing hardships^ to the people. Our letter did notiagree to the cancellation of two months, supplies but just a deferment of 2 months shipments. A2fe i / 164 Express Letter No.719.1215 dated 5-7-46 from P.O.T.C., Sharjah. P.R. 's office has been reminding for a reply for their X.L. We did not receive a reply from the Bahrain Government. I have reminded the Secretary to the Adviser occasionally and he has phoned me up to tell that the reply is being sent to-day. However may we send reply regarding the Trucial Coast? A draft X.L. is kept below for approval please. Itd.KMS. 9/7. ltd. G.M.D. 9/7/46. (112) 165 Memorandum No. 1444-50 SF dated the 8th July, 1946 from the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. (a) The Advisees reply has just been received and confirms his willingness to the new procedure being adopted. (b) I do not see the force-bf P.0.T.C.*s argument. The Ministry of Food will remain responsible for accumulating stocks in Basrah, and Gray Mackenzie Sc Co. Ltd., will purchase Bahrain/ T.C. requirements from the Ministry of Food, Basrah, and arrange for their onward shipment to Bahrain/T.C. I do not see why wheat shipments should be any less regular under the new procedure than under the old, and therefore suggest that we agree to its being adopted for the T.C. as well as for Bahrain. p.k- Jbb &lt;7 ' wf' ,o h - i jy /W. 4. ~4'fc.u iiA~n v P f o—, 1 % F D• JiUc^c.'J 1 A ry 4 • « x ^7 6)V ; V - , , A v x i J » Memo. No. 418.1225, dt. 14.4.4? from the P.0. .C. Sharjah HjM V \ 220 • : Our letter (pa-ge',190) to P.O.T.C. was only for \ ' ' s’ information (plG,ase also aee page 101 of 29/1 linked), T*C # have volunteered for a reduction in their wheat quota by 220 tons per month* The P*U*C* has crossed our letter at page 191, where the arrangement for the release of wheat f^or T*C* up to June 30th Has already been made* 221 If this release of 2,040 tons is accepted by T.C* wheat should be sufficient for T.C* for a period up to July 31st 1947, at their present usual average consumption of 600 tons per month. This does not take into account the private wheat imports expected in the near future from » \ Persia.from this year , s wheat crop, vide page 188 and the wheat T.C. were asked to consign to Bahrain*(page 189). That is, at the present rate of supplies and consumption T.C. w-tll have a reserve sufficient for one month on 30th June 1947, excluding private imports. 222 We may ask P.O.T.C. to accept their fuJ.1 quota up to 30th June 1947, after which period a review may be made if the stock figures warrant a reduction in quota, at that time. !deTS - 21.4.1947. «T 3&gt;- ^ fu-wc fv* • /yi4 ahisV 1 *' 3 ^ /(l ' 7)’ O' orjC^O S -1 isn J&amp;f j.S-.-Vl r, £ d 1 • /* *I want full information as to the position regarding quotas of Sharjah. ;Vhat are the grain and cloth quotas and when were they last issued ? ltd. C.J.P. 14.8.48 I'll The following afe the particulars of grain and cloth quotas for the Trucial^Coast : £ Rice . : There is no fixed allotment of rice to any of t^ Gulf Shaikhdoms and arrangements are made by the rulers themselves to obtain their requirements. Usually rice is imported from Iran. , • - v-v'H Theat . : Please see S.2li and 243 of file No. 29/22. Trucial Coast has an allotment of 500 tons of wheat every month from Basra. She is getting her allotment from lst*June, 1948. The June quota ha-s* boc&gt;n» shipped in the first week of June last, vide S. 241 of the file. \9-v Sugar .: Though sugar is decontrolled there, the Trucial Coast isi obtaining her requirements on Quota basis from the United Kingdom at 185 tons per mensum, vide S.289 of F.29/17. The Foreign Office &amp;as. been informed that the T.C. may require .her allotment from the 1st July, 1948 onwards. 18^ 18 ^ Piecegoods . : A quota of 50 tons of piecegoods has been alloted to the T.C. by the Government of India for the period January to June, 1948. Please see S.165 of F.36/33. Vegetable Ghee . : An allotment of 8 tons has been made to the Trucial Coast, C.f. S.94 of F.36/37. /(251) Tel No. 12- (Saving to P.A.) from P.H. to Stride Ltd. in Does your 17th (46/36/49— copy to Agency) refer Dubai only or the whole Trucial Coast for which neither February nor March quota yet ^applied for ? Stricks to ..Residency. Above telegram (if legible) received from 1st Secretary Can we check if reference is to Dubai only or whole of Trucied Coast, please ? , , . ltd./- R.M.A. 23-3-49 So far we have not received any telegram of the 17th (46/36/49) from Residency. But we have just no*? received the one- placed below, S. 251- from P.R. to /trick Ltd., Basra on the quota of wheat for Dubai. The quota should be for the whole of Trucial Coast. ' In this comnection please see S. 248 and 249 of the file. ltd./- K.V.V. Me may endorse a copy of kii this telegram ta from P.R. to British Agency, ^harjah for information with reference to S. 248 t a ltd./- K.V.V. 23-3-49 * ' A.R. ' ft* Jt. 1 7 . C. Scoken to 1st Secretary. I?sue &gt; draft please. ltd./- R.M.A. 24-3-49 \ y l^V (252) Issued tel No. 181 dt. 24-3-49 to Rolitical, -+Sharjsh. . ^ &lt;(253) C.L. No. (46/48/49) dt. 24-3-49 from Residency. (254) Tel No. 322 dt. 24-3-49 from Political, Sharjah. S. 253 /fe are yet to receive a reply from Sharjah for our S. 252. Further the P.O.T.C. may be asked telegraphica^ -ly to comment on the letter of the 16th March from Strick &amp; Co. S.254 :- Ztk The Residency ma£ be asked to inform the X. # Ministry of Rood about this. In the meanwhile, we may get the reply from Sharjah for \ Our forI reply from Sharjah for our S. 192. ltd./- K.V.V. 26-3-49 S. 253- 254 :- to our 6. 192. ) j^ay pend reply ts from Sharjah ia&lt;-f ltd. A.R. 26-3-49. ' R.1..A. 27-3-49. •?-V v (255) D.O. NO. 330-1215 dt. 27-3-49 from P.O.T.C. ' -The contents_of this P.U.C. may be conveyed to Residency with reference to their S. 253. A.B-;A . iR iT. lb p. A • CT^' lib 1 /V^ (257) 4- ^ &gt;U ^Vv. C.S. No. (46/41/49) dt. 31-3-49 from Residency. Please see S. 255 from P.O.T.C., Sharjah, which is self -explanatory. It is clearly stated therein that Trucial Coasts March and April-quota of wheat should be cancelled. I don-not think that any- useful purpose will be served by • referring the matter to the P.O.T.C. again. We have already informed the Residency on the lines of 5. ,255.. In this connection, please see S. 256. Now the Residency may be asked quotas to inform Gray, Mack, that these wheat/are not required and that they amy be cancelled far. 1. i Wo ixcVjtv t n 'M-. /OX</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/782</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c9</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/782</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 29/22 II CEREALS FOR SHARJAH AND DUBAI’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-27T21:17:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (311 folios)</extent><extent>Files papers are arranged more or less chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 313; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-203; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence about supplies of wheat and barley for importation and local consumption in Dubai, Sharjah and the other Trucial Coast sheikhdoms, during and after the Second World War (1939-1945), when food grains and wheat in particular were in short supply worldwide and subject to Government of India export restrictions and import quota arrangements in all the Arab States of the Persian Gulf under British protection. The main correspondents are the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; the Political Officer for the Trucial Coast and the Residency Agent, both Sharjah; the Middle East Supply Centre (MESC), Cairo; the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation (Iraq) Limited (UKCC), Baghdad; Gray, Mackenzie and Company, Bahrain (acting as Crown purchase and shipping agent). The main topics discussed are MESC allotments and UKCC shipments of quota wheat and barley from Basra to the Trucial Coast ports of Dubai and Sharjah; the monitoring of stock levels of wheat, barley and rice in the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms and estimates of future requirements; the introduction of reductions to wheat quotas, against imports of rice from Persia (Iran) and elsewhere, in view of the difficult worldwide supply situation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Middle East Supply Centre</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Supply Mission (Middle East)</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Food</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>United Kingdom Commercial Corporation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Dubai</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Wheat</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food control</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rice</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c9#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>