<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ce_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:09:47.621Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SILVER BULLION TO BURMA BY LAND ROUTE: further particulars on the subject BRITISH CONSULATE-GENERAL Legation General No.32 ~ (and three copies) YUNNANFU Copies to Su^Legation, Nanking. BUx jia Tengyueh November 2nd, 1932 Sir, With reference to my despatch Legation General No.31 of the 1st instant, and to my despatch (same series),No.26 of the 7th ultimo on the subject of arms and ammunition required by the Yunnan Provincial Government, I have the honour to send herewith some further particulars on the general question of the silver bullion for Burma, which is coupled with the arms question. 2* Monsieur Malortigue came to see me today on the subject of the silver bullion, as he had been requested by the Manager of the Futien Bank, Li Hsi-p*ing, to intervene with me in order to obtain some softening of the present drastic action of the Indian Government in imposing an import duty - which was tantamount to a complete closure of the frontier to silver - without any previous notice. Malortigue said that, up to the present, he had never met, nor had anything to do with, Li Hsi-p'ing, and so he was all the more surprised that the man should seek him out. Li himself did not appear at the interview, but his representative began by suggesting that Malortigue f s contract for arms and ammunition might be preferred to that of de Lieu, since the former’s contract was for British material. Malortigue said that he did not understand, whereupon the representative became more explicit, saying that if M.could arrange that the embargo on the import of silver into Burma could be rescinded, the contract for tlhe arms and ammunition was his. M. replied that he was merely here representing the British house, Arnhold &amp; Co., and the E.M.B. Ingram,Esquire, O.B.E.j His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires, British Legation, Peiping. other/V ' other question was one which involved the interests of the Indian Government, hence there was no connection whatsoever between the two matters. The representative, however, pressed him to come and see me, and finally he agreed to do so, and to put the local people’s difficulties before me. 3. I told M. that I saw the difficulties of the situation, and I had already done the best that I could do, that is to say, I had pressed the fact that the duty had been imposed without notice upon the attention of the Burma Government. I had further asked, if the latter would not consider some extension of the time within which the new so tariff should come into force, A that a compromise might be agreed to, by which the merchants might be allowed to get out of their commitments without undue loss, but also without any profit. 4. As I suggested in my former despatch, Li Hsi-p’ing, manager of the official Futien Bank, was so very closely in touch with the Yunnan provincial government, I felt convinced that the government was concerned in the matter. From what M. told me, the first consignments of silver bullion to Burma were entirely in the hands of private merchants, and the business had been done in small parcels. Now thetrade was to be done on a large scale, and it was not a private enterprise in fact - of course the government’s name was to be kept out of the matter - but the government was employing Li Hsi-p’ing to make a profit for the authorities. From the profits of this silver deal, the arms contract was to befinanced, as the government had not enough money to carry the thing through, unless they obtained some extra funds from somewhere. No wonder the Special Deputy for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs was so taken up about the matterl5. For the moment the arms contract is definitely hung up, until the question is settled as to what is to he done with all the silver bullion which is on the road between here and Bhamo. What I said about the care that must be given to the scrutiny of the costs of transport in any possible arrangement which might be come to, is borne out by wtiat Malortigue told me. He has had it stated definitely that the cost of horse transport from here to Bhamo was Yunnan dollars six hundred and fifty, the amounts which the merchants gave when they saw me two days ago, added up to one thousand paper dollars. I am afraid that one must accept it as axiomatic, that all sorts of trickery and lying will be indulged in - should the Indian government agree to any negotiations for a compromise, -before one can arrive at a basis of settlement of the silver bullion question. If no compromise be arranged, then we must expect the relations between this province and Burma to be on a distinctly difficult footing for some time to come. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, (signed) H.F. Handley-Berry, Acting Consul-General.mmmtm Forwarded with the Compliments of the Comptroller-General. ll&gt; ^ V [re in weekly letter ! n&lt;3&gt;4£ 20 our. 1932 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET D EPT. INDIA OFFICE DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 18© . o z ’ • o 28605/193 2/2 /: 14th October, 1932. OentlcMti* I have to Inform you that a telegrass dated Yum; mfu 12th eteber has bean received from the Britiah Goneul-Oei.er&amp;l at that plttce request lag that the follow lag ^aaage be ddiTrered to you, with reference to m telegrm sent on the 3rd October:- ^All that la required at the present time is the prices at which Hotchkiss is prepared to sell the ama and aasauultloa quoted In the tele- grrm from haiighfil* ihe prices are required as soon as possible* ‘5ome delay in deliTery Is not of great importance* * The above telegram was communicated by telephone to S r* l ainer on the 14th inetant* It 1« understood that the reference Is to a telegram sent by your firm to ihangh&amp;i on the 3rd October* Youre faithfully. Mosers. Amhold a Oo* Ltd* for the Joaptrolle r-acncrul*Ovwseas TWO* ''%* (aA) ( and „~^K&gt;pi©8) Original Via ©iboria* Copy Via CtiUkiiSL. OFFICE OF II. M. COMMERCIAL COUHSELLOR, h l rr v.. Sir, SHANGHAI. let ifuly 1933# Tith rofonmco to your doopatoh 0, T t Ho# 71 of 6th May 193E regarding the enquiry of the Yunnan Go Vermont for tender© for the supply of eums and arajauaitiono, I have the honour to inform you that on tiie 00th May loot I reooirod a telegrasa from H* K# v)on©ul General at Yunnanfu stating that the Government of India h&amp;d eonaonted to the txwieport of suoh uaunitiona of war via Burma and enquiring vhen quotations from Hess re# Arnhold ^ do # mi^jht he expected. 3 , On the same day aeer*5# Amliold * Co# in- formed m that taro^^h their r.ondon House they had aseertainod from the Department of overseas trade that the Government of India had agreed to grant facilities for the transport of these arms through Burma sufcjeet to eondiUone which I now find enumerated in ir# Relton’s letter of 32nd April to Arahold A Co.’s London office (enclosurs to despatch Go* 71 under reference}* 3. Accordingly on the fist May I replied to tr. andley Derry at YUnnanfu by telegraph asking him whether he was aware of the conditions on which the Oovenraent of India’® consent ^*as based; if so, and tiiey could be met, the l&gt;epartment of ' vsree&amp;s Trade would ascertain toe cost of escort throu^ Burma and liesors* AmteM &amp; Oo* would then be able to quote* 4* on/ His Haiooty’e rinsipid Secmetasy of State for lorslgn Affair®, Department of Overseas Trade, LOHDQH.4. On $36 th I raeeivad a wply from H* l • Ooneui Oenapal stating that until the quo tatIona had been auteitted to them the local Authorities could decide nothing as the prices eonditlona mould be taken into confident ion ae ooi^pared with otltor souroeB of supply. I accordingly adrieed Jfteeera Amhold a Oo# to quote ae far as the rail head in Buttia» leading further detail a euboequently to he eonwid^red. b# In due oauree on IQth ^un© I received froa l?e»Br&amp;* Arnliold ao. the ©nolooed letter fron whicn It will be seen Umt the fire have quoted o.i.f. subject to tie oonditiona laid down by tlie (iovem^icnt of India for all the samltione required excepting field gune and emnmltlon and aeroplane® which are to be the eubject of furtlier corns i deration. I have the honour to be, with the hlgbeet r©cj&gt;eot, sir, i'otir moot obedient f h unable ervant, (Bgd#) Louis Beale. mmmms* oowmmjuM*X H. B» aandley Derry H* B. M* Coneixl iionoral* TUmiAHTO. Dear Sir: RQ8AX« 16th June 1932. On the 5rd :&gt;iaroh last, the Office of H# r-oDaercial Counsellor, Shanghai, advieed uo that they had received Informtion by telegraph from K* M. Oonoul General f Yunnanfu, to the effect that the (Zorwuor of Yunnan Province desire© to receive quotations from a British AmeMnt Firm for the following supplies* 1# 10*000 Infantry Hiflee, 7.9 oillinetx^eo, with 1,000 rounds of ammunition per rifle. 2$ 200 Light Machine Guns, each with 6,000 round©. 5. 40 Heavy Machine Gun© with 5,000 rounds per gun. 4. Light Field Oun, with 500 round© of eiamunition. 5. Fighting aeroplane equipped with machine guns and aumunltion. 6. Two observation plane©. Quotations are required c.i.f. Chinese frontier via Burma and a duly authenticated Central Government pex'ait would he provided. to were also advised that the above infomation wue reported by cable to the Department of Overseas Trade. Acting on this inlhmetion, we appxxxached t2xs Department of overseas Trade through our London House and they advised us that the Government of India had agreed to grant facilities for the transport of these am© thresh Bsma on the following condition®* (1) H* M. Consul at Tengyueh is satisfied that the Chineee Local Govenment i© in a position to and will actually make satisfactory arrangements to accept delivery of convoyu on the frontier ©o as to prevent the munitione from falling Into wrong hands. ( 2 ) The payment beforehand of the cost of escorting the conoignment through Burma.(3) ?he passing of the munitlone througli Burma In eucii order and In suoh quantities as may (4) it is recognised that the permission to allow the munitions to pass through Bums is granted a© a matter of oourteay and cannot be denanded a© a matter of right. If the above conditions can be met# the Department of Ovoriioae ?rude state that they will tafc© steps to ascertain what the approximate costs will be of escorting the consign ment through Buj^ia to the Chinese I’Tontier. e die cue sod the above point© with H« U. (Jo.mercial Counsellor, Mhan^chal# and were later advised by telegram that was received from Yunnan stating that nothing would be decided until the local authorities had received eructations from us# a© price© and conditions would be compared with those received from other sources of supply* Vq have now received quotations c*i.f* hoao subjoct to the above condition© laid down by the Government of India. These quotations exclude coot of escort to the Chinese frontier but should the Chinese Authorities agree '■ to the above conditions, we can obtain on a a ti ante for Umi cost* • e enelo e herev.lth list or qaotatl .n©# in duplloate# covering the equipment specified unuer the first three items of the original enquiry, ermunition being quoted * separately. The equipment offered is unused British Gurplus War • toohs and same can be supplied in the original *d03 w calibre, or converted to 7.92 m*m. calibre without extra cost. The *303 w ammunition is also of British manufacture, but we understand that the 7.92 ammunition, being the Continental standard, would be made in Europe* Ve would prefer of course that the Chlneee Autliorities accept the equipment In the original .303** calibre, but if they Insist we shall be pleased to have same converted to 7*92 m*m« without extra cost*peer f . . B «■» 3 ' a| * We also oncloae herewith two copies each of photo&amp;raph® Illustrating the rifles end machine guna quoted for» The photographs illustrating the British Lee Kafield Elfle shows three model a conTerted to imitate the long, medium and short Mauser type Rifles, prices helntg the same for either of tlie^e three mo del a* The origins! unconverted •3U3 ff rifle® would he similar to that illustrated under J odel A. As ie customary In China, w liave poted prices subject to a discount* The price© quoted in the attached list are subject to a discount of 10$ l*e« they can be reduced by 10$ If necessary* fe regret to advise that we have ot yet received prices for light field guna and ammunition. We arc looking into the question of aircraft as it may be possible to fly those machines direct from Hongkong or Canton to Yunnanfu, in which case we will quote c*i*f. Hongkong or Canton. •vo shall be much obliged if you will hand enclosed list and phonographs to the interested Authorities* Should it be absolutely necessary, our Eeprcsontative, Major Barker, could visit Yunnanfu. thanking you in advance for your kind assistance, fe have the honour to be, 3ir, Your obedient Servants, per pro Arnhold % Co, Ltd* .ncls* 1 quotation (in dsipllcete) 2 photographs.Forwarded with the Compliments of the Comptroller-General. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. (S) 18 .COPY SENT TO ^ VD 23672/27/3 COPY* 4 ; AHNHOLD «r CO. LTD. # Stone House 140, Blahopegate LOHDOK, K.C 14th July, 1932 The Department of Overseas Trade 33, Old ,&amp;een Street, S.f.l. Dear Sira Kef. 3. 643 - Arms for Yunnan Your Ref. 23672/27/S. We beg to thank you for your letter of 9th Instant, whioh reached us to-day, and very much appreciate all the trouble you have taken In securing the Information which It contains relating to the cost of transport of Arms through Burma to the Yunnan Frontier. &lt;¥# have heard nothing further from our friends in China relating to this enquiry, which we are inclined to think has had to be abandoned. Ae are, however, sending them a copy of your letter, and if they would like us to examine more closely the cost of transport etc. in Burma, we agree that the best way would be to have these points investigated on the spot as you suggest. Again expressing our thanks for the kind assistance you have rendered us In connection with this business. We remain, dear Sirs, Yours faithfully, COPY SENT BY AIR MAIL p or nmj on behalf of ARHKOLD A CO.LTD ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER No. *30 28JUL V32 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND secret dept CTI0E (Sgd) S. Rainer Tub-ManagerFwn* On 23672/27/3, .643* 9th July, 1932 Gentlemen &amp;ith reference to previous correspondence relative to arms for Yunnan concluding with the Department•s letter of the ^lat ultimo and to a telephone conversation with Mr. Kainer on the 8th instant, I have to inform you that a telegram lias been received from the Government ’The Government of Burma are unable to give a complete answer regarding the cost of the escort without knowing the route or the weight of the consignment. An escort will be necessary right up to the frontier* The weight of p ckages is limited by the necessities of mule transport in China, to probably 120 pounds in 2 packages to a iaule* On the assumption that the consignment is 2260 mule loads, a rough estimate of cost of escort via Bhamo or /yitkyina is itupees 10,000, or via L&amp;shio and motor lorry to the frontier, 3600. Transport is probably impossible during the monsoons, especially d.;, jushio route. The Bhamo route is probably most practicable”. of Burma to the following effect:- MHT*. rnhoia „ Thev-o 0 2. Tlio tias b6©n njiid® bh.at the tiiae hae arrived when sotne lirni established in Ikinaa oould act on your behalf for obtaining further information from the Government of Burma regarding the transit of the consignment through Burma and should the transaction materialise, ae forwarding agents, The firm should be able, on the one hand, to supply detailed information regarding the maximum weight for each package and on the other, to make suggestions regarding the most suitable route for the consignment to follow, Beference to a current directory has shewn that there is a firm styled Arnhold &amp; Co. Ltd,, established in Rangoon, but it iy not known whether they are connected with your firm. The name of the following firm has also been suggested as being possibly able to suit your re quirements in this connection. It is given, of course, subject to the usual disclaimer of guarantee or responsibility on the part of the Department essrs. Balthasar &amp;. fon Ltd,, Shipping and Forwarding Agents, 581, Merchant Street, Rangoon. London Office:- 73/76, King illiara street, 3.0.3 Yours faithfully. for the Co mptro ller-General.(COPY TO INDIA OPPICS AND P3KBTG. ) Telegram R. No. 1412., dated 17th June 1932. From i . . .Foreign,Simla. To ' Burma, Rangoon. ft Reference Secretary of State's telegram No.1639 dated June 15th. Arms for China. Please furnish the desired information to Secretary of State direct repeating to Government of India. (X.,P.S.v. &amp; 0.) F. A.fkb/rtj/dt. \ Z. I 1^74 :J v 1932 (45 groups) P.V DECYj^HER 0 P 3 S 75 tel egham 4&gt;. J5.0-T. 7)oT t^Ln k,A^.i^tb&gt; (COPIES Prom CIRCULATED) Government of Burma to Secretary of State for India* M- Dated Meymyo# 25th Junej 1932o Received 10*15 ftoffi*# 25th June, 1932* X f 0*158* Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India* Secretary of Statens 1638, June ISth* Burma Government unable to advise completely without knowing route or weight of consignment* Escort necessary right up to the frontier* Weight of packages limited by need of mule transport in China? probably 120 pounds to mule, in 2 packages* On the assumption that the consignment is 2250 mule loads, rough estimate of cost of escort via Bhamo or Myitkyina is Rupees 10,000, or via Lashio and motor lorry to the frontier, 3500* Transport probably impossible during the moncoone, especially by Lashio route and Bhamo route is probably most practicable*18 . Forwarded with the Compliments of the Comptroller-General. Ko ^ith reference to Mr. Donaldson's letter to Mr. Relton, P.Z.3559/32, of 17th June, 1932. aj^o 4 hr 21st June, 1932. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l.21st June, 1932. 2367a/ii7/S/l39 S.643. Gentlemen, With further reference to your letter of the 13th June regarding the enquiry for arms for Yunnan, X have to inform you that the India Office have now informed the Government of India hy telegraph that you wish to have an estimate of the cost of escorting a consignment of arms of approximately 4,500 cases through Burma. The Government of India have at the same time been asked whether an escort would be required from the port of entry to the frontier or only from Myitkina or Bharao, also what restrictions there would be on the maximum weight of each package. It will rest with the Government of Burma to determine the route by which the consignment is to pass through/ Messrs Arnhold &amp; Co., Ltdthrough their territory, if permission is given, though they will naturally take into oonsideration the convenience of the Chinese and the practicability of the provision of transport on the route selected. Yours faithfully. for the Comptroller-General.MN DEPARTMENT \OF OVERSEAS TRADE New Telephone No : WHITEHALL 9040. Telephone: Victoria 9040. Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.L 23672/137/27.S 16th June, 1932 Dear Donaldson, In continuation of ny letter of the 11th instant and a with compliments slip of the 14th instant, I enclose copies of further correspondence with Messrs. Arnhold and Company about the proposed consignment of arms for Yunnan from which you will see that they want to know the cost of the escort in Burma both via Bhamo and via Myitkyina. E.P. Donaldson, Esq., India Office.COPY , 23672/137/27S ARNHOLD &amp; CO, LTD, , Stone House 140, Eishopsgate, London. E.C.2 13th June, 1932. The Department of Overseas Trade 35, Old Queen Street, S.W.l. Dear Sirs, Ref. S. 643 - Arms for Yunnan. Your Ref, 23672/134/27, We beg to thank you for your letter of 11th inst., and believe that it will be found more convenient for us to quote for delivery of the goods in question at Bhamo, and are preparing calculations for transport to that point by river steamer from Rangoon. It is quite possible that it would also suit the convenience of the Chinese better than if we delivered at Myitkyina and we trust, therefore, that you will be able to give us the approximate cost of an escort from Rangoon to Bhamo, and also from Bhamo to the Burma-Yunnan frontier . With our thanks in anticipation, We remain, dear Sirs, Yours faithfully, For and on behalf of ARNHOLD &amp; CO.LTD.Lk Forwarded with the Compliments of the Comptroller-General. %vj. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l.CO r. 23672/2 7/;-. FHB/WW. 3 O / * CO. MO., , •', Stone Ilousse, iC 140, lUahopogate, LOrilKH, • C « 2 • 6th June, 1932. The Department of Overeea© Trade, 35, Old ueen Street, S. .1. Pear ira. _2 . 043 - -riru tor Yum&gt;an We would refer you to our letter of , rd inat., and as we think the individual weight a of the oaees cnentioned theroin, in which the above ^oode would be pae ed, mi ; ht be too heavy for easy handling by coolies, we ere suggestin^ to make the packagea lighter, and thus aeoeesitatin;. a larger number oi them, ao that we imagine that the complete shipment would ooiprise somethin like 12,250 oases. A further point ia that we think it would be most advisable to make t^o ship rents, i.e. the jiilee to be sent forward first, and the ammunition later. This should, we think, lessen the risk oi attao on either of the convoys, as without the Rifles the Ammunition would not bo so attractive, and vice versa. If this suggestion was carried out the Hiflee and ‘achine Guns would comprise about 1,300 and the Ammunition about 11,000 cases. Yours faithfully For and on behalf of Arnhold A qq, Ltd., (Signed) Sub-Managert J DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE New Telephone No : WHITEHALL 9040. Telephone s Victoria 9040. Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London. Ref. no....?3672/134/27 . 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.L ///^ June, 1932. t&lt;\n. With reference to our conversation over the telephone on the 8th June relative to arms for Yunnan, I enclose a copy of the letter which we have received from Arnhold &amp; Co. It says nothing about aeroplanes. A copy of our reply is also enclosed^ escort from Myitkyina to the frontier. We observe, however, that the wording of Government of India telegram No.987, of the 15th April last provides for the cost of escorting the consignment through Burma. That implies presumably an escort during the period of transit from the port of entry to the place of exit, including of course the stages from Myitkyina to the frontier, if Myitkyina is finally They ask for an estimate of the cost of an selected/ E.P. Donaldson, Esq.2 selected as the town from which the caravan part of the journey is to begin. enough to telegraph to the Government of India regarding an estimate of the cost of providing an escort, and also clearing up the point about the necessity of an escort while the consignment is in transit. may go through Bhamo and not Myitkyina, since I understand that the road from Bhamo to lengyueh is the easier of the two. and of our reply to His Majesty's Consular officers at Yunnanfu and Tengyueh and to the Commercial Counsellor at Shanghai. A copy of this letter and of its enclosures- has been sent to Bowker at the Foreign Office. We should be much obliged if you would be good It may eventually be found that the consignment We are sending copies of Arnhold r &amp; Co.'s letterE.I. COPY 23672/134/27. APNHOLD 8c CO. LID. Stone House, 140, Bishopsgate LONDON, E.C!2. The Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, S.W.l. 3rd June, 1932. Dear Sirs, S.643 - Arms etc. for Yunnan. Your Ref. 23672/27/S. With further reference to the correspondence we have exchanged in connection with the above enquiry, we have recently had one or two telegrams from our Shanghai Office asking us to telegraph prices for the Rifles, Machine Guns and Ammunition, covering delivery to the rail head, on the Burma Railways. As they have got before them a copy of your letter to us of 22nd April, which outlined the conditions with which we should have to comply before the goods could be shipped from this country, and as it seems to us that some of the conditions would be somewhat difficult to arrange we must say we have been rather surprised at hearing from them. We can only gather, therefore, that there are circumstances attached to the enquiry ot which we are not aware, and which our friends consider make it worth while to follow it up in this way. It seems to us, therefore, that we might be justified in asking you to look into the question of the cost of providing an escort for the goods from the terminal station on the Burma Railway to the nearest frontier point, as suggested in your letter referred to above, and if you can do this without too much trouble, we think perhaps it would be as well if preliminary steps were taken towards this end. We are quoting for delivery to Myitkyina, which is the railhead on the Burma Railv/ays, but have not the least idea how long it would take to convey the goods from that point to the Burma Yunnan frontier. All we can tell you is that if the order covers 10,000 Rifles, 10,000,000 rounds of Ammunition for same, 200 Light Machine/2 Machine Guns and 40 Heavy with about 1-^- million rounds of Ammunition, the total number of cases required would be something like 4,500, ranging in weight from 150 lbs to 315. A'e trust that this information will be sufficient for you to commence your enquiries, and with our thanks in anticipation for your kind assistance. We remain, dear Sirs, Yours faithfully, for and on behalf of ARHHOLD &amp; CO. LTD. (Sgd.) E.A. Earner Sub-Manager.23672/134/2?. 10th June, 1932. Gentlemen, Vith reference to /our letter of the ^rd instant, I have to inform you that steps are being taken to obtain from the Government of India an estimate of the cost of escorting through Burma the proposed consignment of arms for Yunnan. One of the conditions laid down in the Department’s letter to you of the 22nd April last was the payment of the cost of escorting the consignment through Burma. That would seem to imply that an escort will be necessary not only from Myitkyina but during the whole period during which the goods are in transit from Rangoon to the frontier. The Government of India will be asked to clear up that point. it/ Arnhold &amp; Co. Ltd■y^ &gt; . . ‘v t .■ tii ^ d ^ - X &lt; it »X; c. ’i .. . w .. '* i v j '^. - i . . , . - * j o *.&lt;- ■ . i v - .ii .;C -.o oJ -iaXai o*t .../.&gt;v .. v ;» iio\ x tni uy: a I 8 : .*fc l'.- v' .. il ^.i.. [0 0 to O 101 i 0. v ', 'li .:•. ...x; IXK •• iJTOo «. ' iigpVtd£ 3 j* .iL^iafo'OLi axlX ^al.; 'foo'.i© lo cr.. o o j.-.j .'.-.&gt; j'aacrc.^^ l.ijvv j-x.:.c 0 a..: uisitt . tliio#- MK .&lt;i«rll . sitGO^ eil^ xxoilw tei'i-dq, . 'it ijiuyil m&amp;.$ &amp;t . .&gt; v liiolt oi iioo; ..i • fn.’l'i ^i . &gt;'T : -YIC li i 3 ' Hi ? aital -O . . ., • . . .It io observed that you propose to quote for delivery to Myitkyina. It is understood that the ordinary caravan route for consignments to Yunnan starts from Bhamo and not Myitkyina. Goods by rail for Bhamo are transhipped at Katha and thence go forward to Bhamo by river. You may, however, have considered the possibility of sending the consignment from Rangoon to Bhamo all the way by steamer. It is understood from a telephone conversation between an oiiicer of this Department and Hr. Rainer of your iirm that you are reconsidering the question of the ma mum weight of eaoh package in the consignment, with a view to making it possible for the consignment to be carried by mule and coolie transport both of which may be nece sary. Yours faithfully. for the Comptroller-General.COPY, 23672/27/132. Enquiry S.643 35, Old Queen Street,- - t i if f Confide n tial LONDON, S.W.l ^■Tl 14th May, 1932. Gentlemen, In continuation of my letter of the 6th instant, I have to inform you that a letter has been received from the India Office expressing doubt regarding the practicability of flying aeroplanes across the Burma-Yunnan frontier, and pointing out the necessity for further information and details of the scheme before a proposition can be put before the Government of India. So far there is on record only the rather vague mention of fighting aeroplanes with machine guns and ammunition and two observation aeroplanes. It is not known whether the Yunnanfu Government have fitters capable of assembling the machines or pilots competent to fly them, or whether they would welcome this method of taking delivery. military, and no facilities exist there for the erection of aeroplanes. There is no organised air route in the north-east of Burma. A flight in that area would therefore be extremely hazardous without a preliminary survey by experienced pilots. The only flying which has been done in the interior of Burma has been by flying boats up the Irrawaddy River. consideration will be given to the matter. The approval and co-operation of the Government of Yunnan are of course essential. Copies of this correspondence are being sent to the Commercial Counsellor at Shanghai, and His Majesty’s Consular Officers/ There is no aerodrome at Myitkyina, either civil or If a cut and dried scheme can be put forward further Messrs. Arnhold &amp; Co. Ltd,Officers at Yunnanfu and Tengyueh in order that they may be acquainted with the situation in the event of your head office at Shanghai deciding to go further into this Question of supplying aeroplanes to the Yunnan Government, and apj^roaching them with a request for assistance. Yours faithfully, ( Sgd. ) C.C. FARRER. for the Comptroller-Generalyitkyia- , And no fnailitlea for th« or^ction of the aero &gt;Xnnoe t nnd there is oertsinXy no org^niood Air-route ki the nort&gt; -east of iuran, so that a fli^ihi in th^t or a would do extra ely hasardoua without « preliainary ^urroy by earperiencod pilots. X do not think, therefore, th^t there woul l bo any use our *»lcli«g for pr r?ni«sion •’t this ot?^e: l-'ter on, if n out-am?•dried wt-re put for ar&lt;t, with thy npcroral of the 'iunn^n ^owerneseat whose cooperat on would be oorential, we ehoul= be prepared to approach the autheritiee in India ^nd ^ma, but the ar^anre^efite ^ould h^re to be cor-pl ted locally, and it woul probably be better if local enquiries we * xsm :e flret ae to the feasibility of the ion. 1 h we sent a copy of this letter to oisrker at the V Drei^n uffiee. Since writing the above, I have spoken to Squadron Leader Kerby at the Air Ministry, who confirms that there is no civil or military aerodrome at l/iyilcyina - there may be a landing ground at Mandalay before long - but hitherto there has been practically no flying in the interior of Burma except by flying boats up the Irrawaddy. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) E.P.Donaldson.x wmM DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. New Telephone No : WHITEHALL 9040. Telephone: Victoria 9040. Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London. No 2.36.7.2/27/130/S . l-V 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.i 6th May, 1932. Upon the receipt of your letter of the 15th April enclosing copy of Government of India telegram Uo.987 regarding arms, munitions and aeroplanes, for the Governor of Yunnan, we wrote to Arnhold &amp; Go., and sent you a copy of the letter. I now enclose copy of their answer of the 25th April saying that they are referring the matter to their head office in Shanghai, and of a further letter, dated 2nd May, enquiring whether per mission could be granted for the aeroplanes to be erected by Chinese fitters in Myitkyina, if an aerodrome exists at that place, and for them to be flown by Chinese pilots to China. Is this a question that you could put to the Government of India? E.P.Donaldson, Esq. In2 . In the meantime we have sent an interim reply to Arnhold &amp; Co., a copy of which is also enclosed. We have sent to the Commercial Counsellor at Shanghai, the Consul General at Yunnanfu, and the Consul at Tengyueh, copies of our letters to Arnhold &amp; Co. of the 4th March and 22nd April and of their letter to us of the 25th April. I am sending to Bowler a copy of this letter and of its enclosures. HUH.BH. 2 ^ 72 / 129/27 8. COPY . AKk'HOU) i HD CO. LTD., i , / Btoue houc&gt;e f 140, Bibhopsg&amp;te, IiOKOON, K.0.2. • t * 25 th April,1^52. The Department of OverBeae Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, 8^.1. Dear Dire, hof. S. 64.3 - Your kef. 23672 / 27/8 Arms ana Munition© for Yunnan. Ve are obliged for your letter of 22nd inetant, giving ua details of the various points we will have to observe in dealing with the above enquiry, and before shipment could be effected. Ve are afraid that we are not in e poaition here to aay whether certain of the stipulations could be met, but are sending a copy of your letter to our Head Office in Shanghai, asking them to go carefully into the whole matter, ana will let you know whether they can promise that the various assurances would be forthcoming. On receipt of their favourable reply, we shall be pleased to approach you regarding the cost of escorting any consignment of arms through Burma to the Chinese Frontier, but until we hove heard from China, will not trouble you to take any steps in this direction. We are very much obliged, however, for your kind offer of assistance in this way, and would like to express our appre- elation of all the trouble your Department has taken in connec tion with this enquiry. Yours faithfully, FOH AMD ON BKHALF OF ARHHOLP AND CO. DTD. , (Signed) K.M.Rainer. Sub-Manager.ILL. COPY. 23672/27/130/S f —\ ARHHOLB &amp; CO. LTD.*, ] Stone House, 140, Bishopsgate, LONDON, E.C.2. 2nd May, 1932. The Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, S.W.l. Dear Sirs, re Enquiry S.643 - Your Ref. 23672/27/S. Arms and Ammunition for Yunnan. With further reference to this business, you will no doubt remember that the enquiry includes some Aeroplanes, and while the question of delivering the arms to the Chinese Frontier has been investigated, we have not been able to make very much progress with regard to the Aeroplanes. It seems to us that the only feasible way of getting these into the Yunnan province, and if delivery has to be made from the Burma side, is to take them by rail to the nearest Aero drome and have them erected there by fitters, which the Chinese Authorities would have to furnish, and then for Chinese pilots to fly the machines to China. It occurs to us that possibly this might be feasible if the Aeroplanes were de livered to Myitkyina, assuming there is an Aerodrome there, but, of course, our suggestion would be subject to the necessary permission being granted by the British Authorities. If you could give us any indication as to their views to such a proposal as we have outlined above, we should be very much obliged, and with our thanks in anticipation for your reply, which we should appreciate in duplicate. We beg to remain. Dear Sirs, Yours faithfully.AP.Z. 2564. Copy extract from Despatch No. 2 datec 18/2/32 from Acting British Consul-General, Yunnenfu, on Yunnan Political Situation. 4. On the 12th instant, Li Kuo-ch’ing, the interpreter at the Bureau of the Special Deputy of the Wai Chiao Pu, called at this Office and asked if there were any means by which a British firm cpuld get arms and munitions to Yunnan. He suggested that the route via Burma might be used, when the consignment could be transported either by mule train or by means of porters. I told him that, provided the local Government obtained huchao from the recognised Chixiese Government, I did not see that there would be any difficulty in putting the Yunnan Government in touch with a British armament firm. He said that he would have to go into the matter at length with the Governor and that he would then let me know. He came again yesterday, and left with me a list of the requirements of the local Government. This list I have communicated direct to the Commercial Secretary at Shanghai. X X X X- SJ672/27/S 21st .pril, 1932. Gentlemen, la continuation of the Departi :&gt;ent ’ s letter of the 4th ultimo and to a telephonic conversation with r. Ball on the 20th instant, relative to the requirements of the Government of Yunnan in the matter of ai e and munitions, 1 have to inform you that the Governuient of India have agreed, to grant facilities for the transport of these arms through Burma on the lollo’.vin^ conditions;,, namely that:- (1) Eis ajesty’s Consul at iengyueh is satisfied that the Chinese Local Government is in a position to and will actually make satisfactory arrangements to accept delivery of convoys on the frontier and for their protection from the frontier so as to prevent the munitions from J falling into wron 0 hands. (2) The payment beforehand of the cost of escorting the consi 0 nment through Burma. (3 ) • • • « • essrs. ,rnhold &amp; Co2 - (3) , The passing of the munitions tnrou'Th Burma in suoh order and in suoh quantities as may he oonyenient to the Grorernment of Burma. (4) It is reoognised that the permission to allow the munitions to pass through Burma is granted as a matter of courtesy and oannot be demanded as a matter of right. If you are still interested in the enquiry, you will, no doubt, be good enough to inform the Department whether jou are prepared to accept the above conditions. If so, steps will be taken to ascertain what the approximate cost of escorting the consignment through Burma to the Chinese frontier will be. Yours faithfully. for the Comptrolier-Ceneral.INDIA OFFICE, '-VHITEHALL, S. u 1. 15th .ipril. 1932. lith reference to correspondence endinf; with our official letter, ?•£• 1994/52, of the let April, about arms and munitions for the Governor of Yunnan, I enclose copy of a tele?ram which we have received from the Government of India to-day, in which they indicate the conditions on which they would be orepared to ^rant facilities for transport of these munitions through Burma. If Lessrs, amhold and Comoany are still interested in the enquiry, perhaps you would find out from them whether they are orennred to accept the conditions, and,if so, we -''Quid ascertain from Bur a approximately what the cost of escorting the consignment to the Chinese frontier would arount to. I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosure to Bowker at the Foreign Office. T... ielton, sn.,I:.B.h. , Department of Overseas Trade. (Sgd.) E.P. Donaldson.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL. 3.*V. 1. 15th April, 1932. »/ith reference to rry letter of t?ie 10th March, P.«. 1549/32, I enclose copy of a further letter I have sent to Reiton of the Department of Overseas Trade about the Governor of Yunnan's enquiry for anns to be delivered through Burma at the Chinese frontier, and a copy of the Government of Burra’s telegram of the 14th Larch, referred to in the correspondence. (Bgd.) E.P. Donaldson- R.J. Bowker, Esq. ^CREIGil OFFICE, S.W. 1. »C+, j (74 groups) DECK PHHR | - 2096 /U l 0 W TSLEGRaMc {COPIES From CIRCULATED) Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla* 15th April, 1932* Received 11*0 a&lt;&gt;mo, 15th April, 1932 X pr jCjOf* 7(3&lt;?. Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Burma, reference their telegram 161~B April 5tho Your telegram of the 9th ultimo, 767* Arms for v'hin&amp;o Please ee© Burma telegram 18, March 14th, forwarded with Foreign Secretary^ weekly/^letter of March 19th. Order* of 1919 to which they refer, were, as you fcnow, cancelled by abrogation in 1929 of previous agreement between Hie Majesty 7 &amp; Government and other powers* v?e consider Burma Government’s objections will b*&gt; met if Consul at Tsngyueh is satisfied that Chinese Locaj Government can and do make adequate arrangements to accept delivery of convoys on the frontier and for their protection from the frontier as far as Tesagyush so as to prevent munitiont from falling into wrong hands* We should also expect importers to pay beforehand the cost of escorting the consignment through Burma and require their previous consent to our passing of the munitions through in such order and in such quantities as may he convenient to Burmese Government* On these conditions, we egree to grant facilities for transit* We should like it to be/■Hi ^ . 2;;. ■ ba reoogniaed th^t we accede to this request only as matter of oourteey and In token of goodwill, and that it cannot he demanded as matter of righto gqte f Paragraph No.2 has not been telegraphed©following telegraii dated --arcxi 10 th received from Britain, Yunnan-x’di Begins# Yellowing message sent to Commercial Counsellor 3tiangi:iai. Begins. Secretary to Commissioner of Yoreign Affairs has come on Behalf of Yunnan Government to ask whether quotations from British armament firms may Be supplied as regards following:- 1. 10,000 Infantry rifles 79 millimetres with 1,000 rounds per rifle* 2 . 200 light machine guns with b,000 rounds per gun. 3 . 40 heavy machine guns with 5,000 rounds per gun. 4. 20 anti-aircraft guns with 5,000 rounds per gun. 5 . lighting aeroplanes with machine guns and ammunition. 6 . 2 Observation aeroplanes. Yhole would Be covered By proper authenticated Central Government Huchow. quotations should ce cost, insurance, freight Chinese frontier via Burma. Ends. Foreign Office London telegraph that above should Be repeated to Government of Burma for repetition to Government of India. Arnhold and Corroany propose to quote and have Been ini ormed that 1 consent of Government of India would Be required for transit of arms through Burma. Can this consent Be given. Xiarch 10 th. ^nds. Proposal appears to be Barred by orders in letter ^ Bo. 781 Police August 6 th 1919 from home Department ana Local I Government does not welcome idea of these arms Being delivered at Chinese frota.tier|, N Q L 0 8 U ft E ^ !: INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S | Letter No ^ 2 M. J j Dated 1 9 MAR. 1832 Receiver 31 MAR. 193?• • •FLEXED CB. s FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. $ &gt; 1 a: '! i -j : 3 ^ DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. Telephone : Victoria 9040. Telegrams: Advantage, Pari, London. Codes: Liebers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. 35, Old Queen Street. London, S.W.l. March, 1912. iw. No ...236.7.2/2.73/123. Many thanks for your letter of yesterday's date Bo. P.Z. 1434/32, regarding: arms and munitions for the Governor of Yunnan, and for informing the Government of India by air mail. ^We prefer your second alternative, and enclose a copy of the telegram which we have sent to the Consul-General, Yunnanfu. Would you now be so good as to telegraph to the Government of India for their views, as you suggest ? I am sending a copy of this letter to Bowker at the Foreign Office. ^r'vw-* E. P. Donaldson, Esq,VP 23673/27/3/1S3 COPY OP telegram. Code 'K' H#M*Consul-(Jenerel f Yunnanfu• Ho dietributlon* 1 ,4 Q l *T j; 8 liar oh, 1933. i Q X ^ i J c.. Please repeat to the Govern ment of Burma for repetition to Government of India your telegram to Comraoroial Counsellor at Shanghai on the subject of arms for Yunnan Government, adding that Arnhold and Company propose to quote and that they have been informed that the consent of Government of India for the transit of the arms through Burma would be required. Costs recoverable from: Arnhold &amp; Company.X* \ .. 1434/3^, 7th K: roh t With roferenc© to your letter 23672/^73/Xi4£ t of the 4th March rtgeruixift the C^cvernor of Yunnan's enquiry for anae, «an»nitlon and aeroplonee to be delivered via Burraa # X t?rite to say that we have sent a copy of your letter and the caisacsereial coansellor's telegram which you enclosed to the Goveimv nt of India by air mail* The papero will roach the Government of I ^ia in about ten clays and we could then t- le^re -h foor their vieT , s # &lt;.ill thia i^et the case? If you c ansi car It oeeirablc to obtain the Gov or assent of India'e viewa as to the poaoiMlity of tr»n©it through Bun a r*ore urge tly we suggest that you should telegraph to Yunnanfu re uestiag the Consul General to repeat his . ess a re to the Garemment of Innie and the G v^rma it of Burma and to add that Arnhol i Gv 4 Bpany # limited who pro &gt;oso to qaote .or the anus hare be n info mad that the consent of the Gorcrn&amp;ent of India for the transit of the arras through Bur a would be re mi red*/ T*i., Eel ton i:»q* Eepartirient of Overseas Traae.Q3 IHPOiiTABT DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE.' O'^ Telephone: Victoria 9040. Telegrams: Advantage, Pari, London. Codes: Liebers, A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.l. 4th March, 1932. 1 .236.7.2/27 / S /12 2 Dear Donaldson, p/ With reference to our telephone conversation this morning, I enclose a copy of the telegram from the Gommercial Counsellor at Shanghai on the subject of an enquiry for arms, ammunition, and aeroplanes, required by the Governor of the Province of Yunnan, in China. us on the subject is Arnhold &amp; Company, Limited, Merchants, Stone House, Bishopsgate, E.C.2. They have branch offices in different parts of China, and have, we understand, had previous experience of the supply of arms to China. m he firm in London who have approached A8 E. P, Donaldson, Esq r ■ .i....' ' . - / i .1 i-i.ii ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER No. zio 10 MAR. 1932 fROM SECRETARY, (*SL!TICAL AND -t, Lj SECRET E-EPT. !N0'.* P--T0E J- 2 - As arranged, we have told them that a Board of Trade export license will only be granted after the production of a permit signed by the Chinese Minister in London, and provided that no objection to the transport of arms through Burma is raised by the Government of India, with whom your Department is in communication. Yours sincerely.3712. I. 1354. 2000.—7/1908. * Register No. Minute Paper. Political Department. Letter from Dated Dec. Formally acknowledged 190 Date. To Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Council . Table. Initials. SUBJECT. Copy to Previous Papers:</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ce_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2179</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ce</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2179</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/10 'China (Yunnan): Export of arms to China via Burma'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:51:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (83 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 83; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding a request from the Governor of Yunnan Province to transport arms, ammunition and planes to China via Burma [Myanmar]. The materials consisted of British surplus war stock, and were supplied by Arnhold &amp; Company Limited. The correspondence is between Arnhold &amp; Company and the Board of Trade Department of Overseas Trade, regarding the route to be taken and arrangements for transport and an escort. There is also correspondence discussing the deal, and the import duty on silver bullion imposed by the Government of India, conducted between the following: the India Office Political Department; HM Consul-General at Yunnanfu (Henry Forster Handley-Derry); the Foreign Office; HM Commercial Councillor at Shanghai (Louis Beale); and the Government of India Foreign and Political Department.A list of the materials, including prices, can be found at folios 11-15.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Commercial Councillor</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul-General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arnhold &amp; Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Yunnan Province</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Department of Overseas Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Burma</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Weapons</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ce#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>