<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T16:43:09.911Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">File No. it&gt; I 0 R.-RI 5 Collection No.CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED Bahrain branch 7th February 1945 Bahrain Receipt No... 0. ...Date The following has been received from our Head Office London ' Cable communication between London and Brussels restored. Present position is that United Kingdom, Canadian, United States, French and Belgian Government telegrams and press for Brussels admitted”. Officer-in-Charge, Bahrain branch.- &lt;mamm s*\ Bahrain Receipt ^ oct. m 2 . &lt;«■«.«*■ No _ 5 fc;X.D a te U..-...?~'.k\ W-m. - CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) R ©f 2 NOaTXS/SS SERWCE mifiBMIc &gt;_ /TN 12 th February 1945. NOTICE- [/J TE^KrrhuPH CQ^URICATICIj yVlTIi FRiiNCK. 4 t service to civilian addresses restored with MbiURli. . Plain English 6 r French or following codes only ^ admitted. Bentleys Complete Phrase, Petersons Third and Acme Com and Phrase. Deferred (LcJ.and Night letter Telegrams (Nit) admitted. Telegrams of business nature must be restricted to those ascertaining facts or asking for information. Rates, VfM/ Full Rate Code Deferred Nit Government M Code Rs. ii M 1.14.0 1 . 2.0 0.15.0 0.10.0 0.15.0 0. 9.0 Offtter-iZct fri.h.A:mm Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) $ Telephone No. SOM Tajr MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO ' , , /( . ^ April 1946. No. v cv lL2JULiL&amp;. 1* Following Government telegrams are now admitted for Brussels in code or cypher or in any plain language* Governments of U*JU Canada | France | Nether land S| U.S.ii*, Belgium and Luxemburg* 2* In addition telegrams of diplomatic representatives of all Governments accredited to Belgian Government in Brussels may be exchanged between Brussels and their home Governments and with Government representatives of United or Neutral nations in any territory /'-n other than enemy or enemy occupied territory* These telegrams are accepted in plain language written in English, French, Spanish. Portuguese ^ * or national language of representative in question* 3* Only other telegrams allowed are Press telegrams. I j!C,Ct HN cACt 4 . t f Wiretess lM fkaki'/h' !Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM IN REPLY REFER TO No. BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 16.tli Ap.r±i. t 124.5 tea?'' Receipt r i; 0 1 c -XoMM \Z~J.Cxli TC GUH ./ireless service is now available to Lanila - Philippines and Guam, nil classes of telegrams are accepted at prewar rates Full rate Cone Deferred Gov: Gov: Code manila hs.^s.Fs. 3- 0-0. 1-13-0. 1- 8-0. 1 - 9 - 6 . 0-15-6. Guam hs.AS.Fs. 3-10-0. 2- 3-0. 1- 13-0. 2- 3-0. 1- 5-0. Officer -in- Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain Branch. *Printed in England. b Telephone No. SOM CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO Ne &lt; * 'H j-Vr ?tVMay, 1945. 3To£?8/3 ..I NOTICE TELEGRAPH SERVICE WITH ITALY Telegraph service is now open to all provinces south of and including provinces of Pesaro Arezzo Siena Grosseto and that part of Firenze province south of river Arno but including City of Florence^ All normal classes admitted but telegrams must be written in plain English and French for present. Existing service and rates for Government telegrams and Press telegrams remain unchanged. Prewar rates apply. Office* -in- Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited. AM Bahrain Branch.Printed in England. Private telegrams available to and from Cireece. Business telegrams limited.to those ascertaining facts ana exchanging information. Languages admitted are French and mnglish ana the same nine authorised codes as are admitted for telegrams with Great nritain. Chixi«i j nL ipLiu-LtD • rv Telegraphic communication resumea with Channel Islands, bame rates ana conditions as with ^ Great Britain. * .b inn Cm . Telegrams are now accepted for v/hole of i'rance except Departments of haut-Rhin and Bas-Rhin. T16/106. v- t * , iiPrinted in England. Sept. 1942. (4,100. pad,.) w CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENOLANO.) I/-16 8 The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— ix Letters and Number of Message. Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed In and Official instructions—if any. Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. © T ^JLx .1 uftH COiiaiu.ULXCi-l'XCl'i WITH 6c hO&amp;U&amp;Y Telegrams are now acceptable to Hernaark and Norway as follov/s le Government telegrams in coae cypher or plain English, French, Spanish or Portuguese. 2&lt;&gt; Press telegrams. 3. Commercial telegrams. 4. Private telegrams in iinglish or French only. 5. In addition Danish may also be used in Government telegrams to Denmark and Norwegian to Norway as well as national language of Government concernea. % T16/107. a ^ ' MARK YOUR REPLY SuCtZ %/7TWlC^li&lt;T\ ^ Officer-m-chargt Ctthh mnd Wlveiess Ltd Bahrain ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES. J' ' ' ' Following from our London offi^c:- 'As soon as possible restrictions on use of language ^odo and Cypher will be withdrawn for telejrams axchangsd between countries of British Commonwealth (excluding India and ceylon) and between British c 0fTimonV /ealth countries l excluding India and c a yi 0 n) and U.3.A. including Porto Kico ? 3t. Thomas, 3t. '*roix and Philippines (but relaxation does not apply to telegrams from Philippine 3 ). 2. Foregoing does not include ? alestine. 3. Any language permitted by International Regula tions and any 'Ode {.Public or Private) or Cypher may t be used and use of P'* and F^p also restroed in above relations. 4. Probable date is 7th September but will advise soonest. 5. For your information, notification through Berne won’t be made till end 'September.” pep - Postal notification of delivery (telegram with) Forwarded to the Political Agent, for information. No.IB/3b Bahrain, 6th deptember, Id45 3d. N .L. Penf o Id , Officer in charge, &amp; \‘J,CABLE &amp; WIRELESS LIMITED. No.IB/38 Bahrain, 9th September, 1945 The Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ Dear Sir, Further to our endorsement IB/38 dated 6th September, 1945, our London Office advise:- 1. 'Removal of restrictions is effective forthwith. 2. U.S.A. possessions also include Alaska, Guam, Hawaiian Islands and Midway'• Yours faithfully, Sd. N.L. Penfold, Officer in charge, C. &amp; W. LtdPrinted in England. 1G CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED i/Ve are advised that messages to all parts of the U.S.A. except NLWORKCITY, CASHINGTONDC and SANFRANCISCO may only be accepted subject indefinite delay. Officer -in- Charge 5 Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain Branch, (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO 9 th January, 194(5 NOT ICE• • . nsKp-i f \ ''-A \ / I &gt; - / /'« ft No. 145-33/6. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 12th January, 1946. The Officer in charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your Notice dated the 9th January, 1946. 2. I should be grateful if you would let me know the reason for the indefinite delay. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain.Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) Telephone No. SOM MANAMA, IN REPLY REFER TO N«.- Tlb/158 . BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 15th January,194o. Bahrain Receipt N o^ 5 • • D &amp; t e...»** .^» *** *^ •^'^ In reference to your letter No.145-38/6 dated 12th January 194b, para 2, the reason for the indefinite delay is due to the strike in IL6.A. by the employees of the western union Telegraph Company. Yours faithfully. Officer -in- Charge, Cable and wireless Limitea, Bahrain Branch. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, •Vnc-fc i rinted in England. Oct. 1942. (500 pads). o b 1-93.9. e &gt; CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) tXCCGIUII. NO.T16/16B, iL.JK. 'L iv» 17 th January 1946* &gt; ollowing from western Union Telegraph Company, London* 'Please cancel previous notices and substitute following :- U Only tlie following can be accepted i- 1. Govt telegrams to ftewyoric and wasliingtou only* 2* Press telegrams to i«ewyork ana ^slxingtOAi only* 3* All classes of telegrams aocressed to a registered adaress In ^ewyorkcity only* 4* LtL am VL1 telegrams to all U*b*^* for Biailing beyond ;&gt;»ewyork. 6* Personal boldier telegrams of any class to all U*c.a. for mailing beyonc Xviev/york except Washington where telegrams handled by wire* 3*7 j~/r Prinlyj in England. Sept. 1941. (300 pads). CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) _ BAHRAIN BRANCH. MEMORANDUM. *51 0 I - ^ JULY 1 946« The Political Department, Bahrain. The PoaUlster General Bombay advises to discontinue booking of all clashes of private telegrams to India. Only Government priority and urgent press telegrams will he accepted. 0 Bahrain. IN REPLY REFER TO Ns. T 1 IS/ 2 Q 9 .0 CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) b4ihr«xj.n Branch, IN REPLY REFER TO 26 th £ugu^t,I946* No. The Honourable the jroiitxc^i He^iuent in the rer^i^n Gulf^ BAHHAIJi. Dear iiir, fle have to aavi«e you that our cable between kuscat &amp; Bushire is interrupted. CoBu^unication with Buanire has been established by wireless-lin^ Bahrain-Bushire. ^our^# faithfully. Bahrain Receipt Mailer Co^y: J^oxitical ^ent,Baarain.England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO I6tn January,1947. No. ,.15/8 Ine. Honourable Tne Political Resident in tne Persian Gull, BAHRAIN* Bear Bir, We nave to advise you tnat our cable communication between FAQ and BaHhAIN was* restored on tne 15tn instant. Yours taitnrully. ^Manager Copy: Tne Political Agent, Banrain.CABLE AND WIRELESS LUITED BAHRAIN BRANCH, 21st May, 1948 The Iraq Administration advises that from 18th May 1948, all telegrams originating from and terminating at Iraq are ; subject to the following restrictions *- 1, Telegrams must be written in plain language, Arabic, English, French, Turkish or Persian. 2. Telegrams in cypher or code are not allowed. 3. The Christian name and Surname of the sender must appear at the end of the text. 4. Abbreviated addresses are neither allowed in the address nor in the signature. 5. These restrictions do not apply to State telegrams, v VT\CAL a MAY i948 r HRAlN-dd i ^ His Excellency the Political Retident, Persian Gulf # presents his compliments to:- @) The Political Agent, (B/1471 Bahrain* The Political Agent, (K/57) Kuwait, Tfee Political Agent, .(,¥/47J. Hus cat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. PERSIAH GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN , the 28til Hay, 1948, Reference to previous correspondence . Nil, f Description of Enclosure, Cable and Wireless Limited Bahrain Branch, notices dated 21st and 23rd Hay 1948, t/Sr ^ f/^r ’l&lt;r&gt;( r J / Telegrams tA Iraq and Syria.CABLE AND WIRELB3S LI M ITED BAHRAIN BRANCH, 21at May, 1948. N 0 T I C E The Iraq Administration advises that from 18th May 1948, all telegrams originating from and terminating at Iraq are subject to the following restrictions 1. Telegrams must be written in plain language, Arabic, English, French, Turkish or Persian* 2* Telegrams in cypher or code are not allowed. 3* The Christian name and Surname of the sender must appear at the end of the t ext. 4* Abbreviated address are neither allowed in the address nor in the signature* 5. These restrictions do not apply to State telegrams* HOT ICE BAHRAIN BRANCH 23rd May, 1948. . . . The same restrictions as for telegrams to Iraq apply to Syria* •• /rr i Printed in England CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD ' (Incorporated in England) MANAMA BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF Telephone joM 33 f L No. 15 / 14 - Reply to the Company quoting reference and date 30th November,194B A His Excellency The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, JUFAIR. 4 V Dear Sir, We have to advise you that our cable between Muscat and Karachi has been restored. Circulation of telegrams for Pakistan is now via Bahrain/Aden (wireless circuit) and Aden/Muscat/Karachi (cable). % Yours faithfully. Manager. ES. Copy to: The Political Agent, BAHRAINPrinted in England CABLE AND (2 WIRELESS (Incorporated in England) MANAMA BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF Telephone {oM LTD t’i 3 No.15/ 14 . Reply to the Company quoting reference and date 2 C til JbnU&amp;Tf, l Exceixeiicy Tho Political in the Peraiotn Gulf, JUFAIR. Hesiaent Dear Gir, have to advise comnrunication between Muscat taiat our cable •uiu Karachi is interrupted. Tel eg ranis to Pakistan are being routed via Lonaon/Xarechi tireless link and are subject to boley in event of adv r:e working conditions. This delay especially applies to letter telegrams. if ours faithfully. Maiiiagcr. c Agent, . . ^in England Telephone joM CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD Defer ^ir, t'urtaer to our letter of 28th January 1949, cable col; runic .tion between Muscat .Karachi has now been re-established. In consequence, telegrams to Pakistan are no longer subject to delay. (Incorporated in England) .ic. 15/14 MANAMA BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF Reply to the Company quoting reference and date 1 .. Ul ; TCh, J. &gt;^9 bis nicy The :‘oli tica^. Hoc 1 oent in the Persia] JUPAlfi. lours faithfully. er. Co^y to The i-'oiiticai ,.gent, x/aiirt-inNotice dated 7th February, 1945 from the Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain Seen by E.O. and C.O.. Filed by order. Notice No.T16/82 dated the 4th February, 1945 from do Filed by order. . © - Notice No.T16/82 dated the 12th February, 1945 from do © Notice dated 4th April, 1945 from the Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain. (D Notice dated 16th April, 1945 from do (D ^ Notice dated 9th May, 1945 from do S.Nos. 4,5 &amp; 6. Seen by E.O. and C.O. Filed by order^ © / Notice dated 18th May, 1945 from the Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain. Notice dated nil from the Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain. Seen by E.O. and C.O. Filed. 9] Endt. No.lB/38 dated the 6th September, 1945 from the Officer-in-Chaive Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. , Letter No.lB/38 dated the^9th September, 1945 from the Officer-in- Charge, C &amp; W. S.Nos. 9 and 10. Seeh by P.A. and A.P.A. Filed. (7T) ^ i 4^ ^ G^r- y (h. r</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1768</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1768</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 33/6 Notices from Cable &amp; Wireless Ld'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-20T18:22:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (46 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 42-44). Circled serial numbers written in red ink and crayon, which appear on some items of correspondence, refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 46; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and notices concerning telegraph services issued to the Political Agent, Bahrain by Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain. The correspondence and notices are mainly issued by the Officer-in-Charge (later Manager), Cable and Wireless, Bahrain.The papers cover: information on telegraph communication with parts of Europe and other countries all around the world; rates charged; interruptions to the service; and restrictions on the service.The date range gives the covering dates of all the correspondence and notes in the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd, Officer in Charge, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Wireless telegraphy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Telegrams</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>