<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000133_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T16:33:05.661Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Confidential. c- im Meinoranduin on possible Methods of Purchasing or Leas the Islands in the Persian Gulf. asing Sche m e I. — Purchase. 1. If it should be decided to purchase the full ownership and sovereignty ot the islands, and this cannot be acquired for less than 2,000,0002., the Government of India are prepared to share in the cost. (2,000,0002. down ' be equiVc ] len L a t 4 pe N r cent ’ com P° ut iti interest to an annuity of about . , a ^ ear ^°. r 99 years). But the (Government of India stipulate that I ersia s outstanding debts to the Imperial and Indian Governments should be set otr against the purchase price. Phese debts on 21st August 1914 were— To India - _ _ fwio oor; rn t * i ~ 04 : 0 ,oOO lo ImperiaJ Government - _ 246,851 790,186 790 186? price t0 be paid t0 Persia would be 2,000,000?. minus But since, of the outstanding claims on Persia, a sum of 296 478?. lepresents a loan {plus interest charges) made by India alone, the Treasury should pay half that sum (148,2392.) to us before the remainder of the purchase price is divided. r.P 1 ' 1 ' 6 r . ei ' laillder of purchase price for equal division between India Umce and J reasury would then be : — £ 1,209,814 m'u ms 148,239 1,061,575 of which India would pay half (530,7872. 10s.) Thus of the total purchase price of 1,209,8142. the shares would be ■— i i • £ s. d. Iudia ' - - 530,787 10 0 £ s. d. Treasury - - 530,787 10 0 148,239 0 0 ■ 679,026 10 0 Total 1,209,814 0 0 2. An alternative form of purchase would be as follows (1) England and India to pay down, between them, 300,0002. (2) Persia’s debts to India and England, amounting to about 790,0002. to be cancelled. l \°) England and India to pay Persia an annuity of x pounds sterling for 99 years,(t^hrst payment to take place 12 months after the payment (4) In view of the fact that about 296,5002. of the outstanding loans to Persia has been advanced by the Government of India alone, it would be necessary to make a special adjustment with the Foreign Office to equalise matters. This could be done either by the foreign Office paying practically the whole of the lump sum payment of 300,000?., or by the Foreign Office bearing a larger share than India of the annuity. 17574 . I. 1305 . —- -The annuity to he entered in (3) would depend on whether the purchase basis is 2,000,0001. gross or something less. If it were 2,000,000?. gross the net sum left after deduction of (1) and (2) would be 910,000?. This would represent an annuity for a term of 99 years of 37,150?., on a 4 per cent, basis. If the gross sum were less—for instance, 1,836,390?.—the annuity, on the same interest basis, would be approximately 30,480?. If it were 1,500,000?. the annuity would be approximately 16,7407. Scheme II.—Various forms of lease. 1. The Government of India are prepared to share in a lease for 99 years at an annual rental of 100,000?., cost to be equally divided between India Office and Treasury. Three years’ rent (300,000?.), would be advanced in equal shares by the Indian and Imperial Governments. The Government of India do not combine with this proposal any suggestion for the extinction of Persia’s existing debts to the Indian and Imperial Governments. But a calculation has since been made that if Persia’s existing debts were cancelled and an advance of 300,000?. made, a reduction of the rental from 100,000?. to about 55,450?. a year could be claimed in return for these concessions. Of this the Treasury would pay about 30,5007. and the India Office about 24,500?. But the Treasury might pay in some other way their share of India’s separate loan (296,478?.), which figures in the debts to be extinguished. 2. If a rental of 100,000?. is thought excessive, the Persian Government might be prepared to accept 50,000?. a year for a 99 years’ lease on condition of receiving an advance of six years’ rent (300,0007.). It would hardly be practicable to combine this with any proposal for the extinction of Persia’s debts, as the rental left to be paid after such concessions would be only about 5,4757. a year. 3. If this offer is thought too low, 75,0007. a year might be offered for -a 99 years’ lease, with advance of four years’ rent (300,000?.). The offer in a modified form might include the extinction of existing debt and an advance of 300,000?. A calculation has been made that in that case a rental of about 34,4707. would remain payable. The Treasury might adjust their share of India’s separate loan (296,4787.) either (a) by finding practically the whole of the advance of 300,0007., i.e., half the advance = 150,0007. + half the separate loan — 148,2397.; or (h) by bearing a larger share than India of the remaining rental of 30,0007.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000133_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C141</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000133</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C141</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on possible methods of Purchasing or Leasing the Islands in the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-30T23:13:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences and terminates at f 57, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the bottom right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the item also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The memorandum outlines two forms by which islands in the Persian Gulf may be purchased from Persia, and three possible methods by which the islands may be leased instead; each proposal includes an estimate of the cost. It does not specify which islands the British hope to acquire by the proposed schemes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Lease or buy decisions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Islands</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000133#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>