<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000216_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T09:45:57.532Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IHMMH % ■ - 3 Allotted to Prom To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Repeated to Secretary of State for India and Received 10*30 hours, 18th December 1946. 86984/OET. Prom Givaffairs Repatriation to Tripolitania Bartini family Amor Ben Ahmed SI Baruni granted permission to proceed Muscat to collect Baruni family and return Tripolitania. Will advise you -when Amor reaches Cairo. Please inform all concerned. Government of India, External Affairs Dept. Dated Cairo, 12.00 hours, l?th December 1946,INDEXED CONFIDENTIAL. N„. 498-3 of 1940. s-rv F ILE C OPY f T&gt; -T JL • / (. 4 d 25 ! / - (?) */ The Tlon’ble the Foliti(/il Ri^l4tQn thj Persian Gnlf presents ilirfieuts to l complirfieuts t&lt; A. H.M* s Secretary of State for India, India Office, London* 2* The Secretary to the Government of India, H&amp;temal Affaire Department, Simla* 3* Middle ISast Intelligence Centre, Cairo, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents {rf. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. ..I'?*®* Name and Date. Copy in translation of an extract from a letter dated the 21st May 1940 from Yusuf al Baruni, Muscat, to Q,asim Mohammad al Baruni, Taaloon Hoad, Atfit Annajar, Ho*4, Cairo, Sgypt* Subject. Deceased Suleiman Pasha al Baruni al Nafusi*Copy in translation of an^ly^c dated the 21st May 1940, from YuJ 'i|c \et fzjofB a letter J Muscat, to Qasim Mohanimau A1 Bar uni, Toaloon Road, Atfit Annajar, No. 4, Cairo, Egypt. M I hope that you have had an interview with Azzara Bek, and will have a chance of seeing him again. I have written to him about the deceased’s opinions. There is a good hope as soon as the Italian neutrality becomes clear. It Yvould take a long time to explain this but not all. what a man seeks he gets.”CONFIDENTIAL * From - The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India SUBJECT «- SULEI^^N ^L MRWl . Reference correspondence ending with your printed letter No* 150-G, dated the 11th npril 1940* 2. A copy of a report from the Intelligence Bureau (Home Department, Government of India; No, 140/Mn/23 dated 11th i^ay 1940, intimating the death of Suleiman al Baruni is enclosed for your information* A copy of this memorandum is being sent to the India Office. in the External Affairs Department. To The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* tfenumuidum No, F, 3S6-N/39* Dated Simla, the May 1940# Sd/- W. R. Hay, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.A copy of report No, 140/MA/23 dated the 11th May 1940) from the Intelligence Bureau, Home Department, Government of India, Information received from the Bombay rolice is to the effect that Suleiman A1 Baruni arrived in Bombay with H*H, the Sultan of Muscat by the S»3« 'Bcuikura' on the 26th April 1940. He had been suffering from blood-pressure for the past 1-1/2 years and it is reported that he was expressly brought out to Bombay by H.H. the Sultan bf Muscat for obtaining expert medical advice. He stopped with the jtxibbm a£ M^jX3guttx£gxx«btxin±Hgx:RXjagrtxaEHtigidt Sultan only for a day and as he took ill on the 27th April, he was removed, under medical advice, to a local Nursing Horae the same night. In spite of the best treatment he died on the night of the 30th April from Cerebral Hemorrhage and heart-failure.-4 INDEXED CONFIDENTIAL. FlLEJJOEY No. 150-S coiuplimcnts to r*' zob/ 1, His Mejesty’s Secretary of State for India* London. 2 ,/ The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla 3. Middle East Intelligence Centre, Cairo. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUS ill HE. Dated lltk April^1940 Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter lio.C/l94 of 5th March 1940. \ .a us Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter dated 20th March 1940 from Suleiman al Baruni, Muscat, to Syed Muhammad Ariqi , Tunis- Subject. Suleiman al Baruni RECd. POL. 0(EF*t. ? 4 APR 1940 INDIA OFFICELetter dated the 10th Safar 1359 (20th March 1940) from Suleiman Pasha al Baruni, Muscat, to Syed Muhammad Ariqi, President of the Association of Tripolian immisrrsrrts *in Tunis. tr. 'ij* \ After Compliments- ^ O I received your letter of the 18th MiharHSfci. iflT) an ^ opportune moment and was very glad to know of the activities of our countrymen in Tunis and of their future plan for the welfare of their country. I was still more pleased to learn that the responsibilities of presidentship have been placed on you. This I learnt from our brother Ahmed Zarim, clerk of the Association. May God bless and help you in your undertaking and may He grant us the opportunity of meeting in our dear native country which we had to leave. Surely it is not difficult to God. Since a long time I have been trying to get leave to go to Tunis for treatment and shortly I will leave for India. I hope to return soon and to see that the way of Tunis is open for me. Please let me know if anything new happens to you. As for news of Tunis and our dear country, mostly I hear it on the radio. I am very sorry to hear the latest news about scarcity of rain and famine. Everything is in the hand of God. I have received letters from our brothers in Syria and Egypt and I am glad to learn that they have formed an Association with Saiyid Adris al Sanausi as its President. It is desirable that both these Associations should remain in touch with one another to exchange their ideas and each should show its activities to the other so that they may shape a united thought and aim. As for a binding between the two Associations for work, I do not find it possible or fruitful as both of them are under the supervision of different and independent Governments. Hence it is necessary that each Association should act according to the guidance of the Government under which it is. In view of the distance between the two Associations’ headquarters and their separation, no correspondence will be possible without the know ledge of those Governments. As such common action and binding of the two Associations sire not possible. Moreover the war is bring ing in changes every hour, nay, every moment. It depends on thecondition of the country in which the Associai immigrants are living. As to the immigrants living in the east e.g. Hedjaz and Syria, their participation in the Association in Egypt will be advisable on account of nearness of places and facilities of communications, if they want to act for the same cause and if Tunis is not near from their places. I have given my opinion to the Association of E&amp;ypt. Please convey my respects to my brothers and to one and each of the members of the Association and particularly to my brother Ahmed Zarim, clerk of the Association. I have received his letter but for want of time for the mail I could not reply but God willing, I hope to write to him by the next mail. With my regards for all brothers who may meet you and hope of being kept informed of you all. Usual Ending.PILE COPY CONFIDENTIAL . No. &lt;yi94 of 1940. faCjS -^\ The Hon’ble the Pol com plim ents to VI. P.Z. I486 : v »o tical \ WO in t e Persian Gulf presents his J} His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London* 2* The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, new Delhi* 3* The Middle East Intelligence Centre, Cairo* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, Bahrain* Dated....1940. Reference to previous correspondence: 11th February 1940. Description of Enclosure. It'T'j 1 Name and Date. / Subject. 1 . 2 . Extract from a letter,dated the 13th December 1939, frbm Ahmad Xarim bin Khalifah bin Omar, Salambo, Tunis, to ■ Suleiman Pasha al Baruni, Muscat • Letter dated the 22nd November 1939 from the Committee of Tripolian Refugees, Alexandria, to Suleiman Pasha al Baruni Muscat, with enclosure. Suleiman al Baruni al Nafusi• mm No* 44 RECat.P9L.ucr 1 1MARI940 INMA OFFICE --- IM ; j\J ; letter HSCEIVSD . 1 - 3 -m JATS 04 •' ,, (Copy in translation). ¥ Copy of an extract from a letter dated the 13th (|h) '* i «« , *'» f December 1939, from Ahmad Zarim bin Khallfah bin Omar. Sal ambo. Tunis, to Suleiman Pasha al Baruni, Muscat. We have forn P.Z. 1486 ed Association of Tourists in Tunis. The object of this is lu ryiiiulll Tn touch with all those who fled from Tripoli. I fervently request you to let me know the date of the war in dear Tripoli. We are expecting to know what happens just like thirsty people expecting sweet water. I hope you will let us know of this and also the cause of difference between you and Amir Shakib.”.(Copy in translat To , 1940 j His Excellency Suleiman Pasha al Baruni and any one of our country-men whoever might be v/ith him. After Compliments. We inform you that on Thursday the 6th Ramadhan 1358 corresponding to 19th October, 1939, there was a gather ing at Alexandria of the Tripolian chiefs and Sheikhs who fled from their country. The object of the gathering was to consider the situation of our brothers, who fled to different countries of the East, at the present moment when the atmosphere is cloudy and all nations are busy in determining their own safe course in order to keep their boats steady from sinking and entering into the waters of false propaganda. circumstances it was unanimously decided, firstly, that the democratic front was worse for our brothers in the East and, secondly, that absolute faith by the signatories of this letter was to be put in Amir Syed Mohammad Idris al Sanusi to represent us all. All our brothers are to be informed of this. Our brothers in Egypt have put their confidence in His Highness who will speak on behalf of all when necessary. our brothers who fled from Tripoli to remain in touch with His Highness and not to forget their native country from which they fled not for any legal reason but by compulsion and force. Wien the enemies come out of their neutrality, face them for deliverance and vengence. We wish that nothing should be done without the information and concurance of all* God will guide us in the proper path. Usual Ending. Sd./ Husain Hasan Abdul Maleic. Sd./ All Ibrahim Alqan. After much discussion and in view of the existing In the circumstances we send our advice to all of / Sd./ Jamal, bzssirLzd xiA \.bt. 1 b bsmuarttM rslbbU IboisTj \,£&gt;8 . rfbbUB^ xIA \. 5 o 1 b bsMnsfiijK nifiai/H \»bo .iU^bH Ib iaBH Id llscX.bc .J-aqaBp ineldS aubdA ssIbc \.b8 .IiupA Ijs t xlssssA Ijz msIjBc; aitedA \.b&lt;i . eir^d’A Ib riolBc \.dL .ieBiBil Ib oeAi'isH a , ixj5bP \..t&gt;c .Is.aii li? AAUSi U±^AJ&gt; \*AA .Q&amp;Bli lB b&amp;8l&amp;c &amp;v'ociA x£&gt;aH IA \.5A IfUWB'UBH dalBv' r£BlIx/bdA\.5d .x'iuoA Ib f'XijdcfA Ib ^laeU lubdA \.bc .‘xiaBPI is XxJl£X» itiodA \ .bc .x-xx/pA Xb IIwbH rLilijjbdA v .*-b8(Copy in translation). True Copy . After praises to God and peace on His Messenger. A meeting of the Tripolian emigrants in Egypt was held in Alexandria to consider their situation in the present time and to select one person to represent them in all matters. His Highness Saiyid Muhammad Idris al Mahdi al Sanusi has been select ed for that purpose. His Highness will represent in true sense of the term what he thinks better according to his high position and influence. A committee has also been formed by election of members to represent the whole body. In case of sickness or absence of any member of the committee, the member should appoint an agent but it is at the option of the committee either to accept or reject the agent by a majority of votes. The chiefs of the Tripolian emigrants hereunder put their signatures. Ibrahim Ahmad Sharif al oanusi. Muhammad Tawfiq al Gharyani. Al Hadi Abdus Samad Abdus Salem al Tarhuni. Kazz ah. Ali Adjuda. Muhammad ail Isawi Bu Khanjar. Abdul Huwail al Ufuri. Husain Hasan Abdul Kalek al Masrati. 3aad Allah al Namr Ufuri. Manmuh Kanish al Mohammad Said Halfaf Harbawi. al Bar*asi. Muhammad Abdul Faqih Fadur Badiran al al Masrati. Barasi. Salem^ Abdus Salem al Masrati. Muhammad Jamal Uddin Bashagha. Yusuf Mustafa Lagha al Ufuri. Taher Ahmed Badr Rahim al Masrati. Abdul Hamid al f Abbar. Husain Muhammad Faqih Muhammad Zabu. Abdul Hamid Abu Matari. al Masrati. Muhammad al Gharyani Miftah al Manfi. Wahdama. Saif al Nasr Haduth al Barasi. Ahmad ali al Shoghafi al Masrati. Ali Ibrahim Alqan. Al Haj Muhammad al Kabti. Ahmad al Maridh Ali. Haro on Ibrahim. Salem al Munfi. Abdullah Muhammad Amer. Abu Bakar Abu Dabbus Muhammad bu Rajab Bu Saja. Ahmad Ishtiwi. Aw an Muhammad Soof. Mutakhattar Fadhah. Amer Abdul Jalil. Awadh Ahmad Wakil. Al Munfi al Sabaqi. Mahdi Mustafa. Saleh Abdullah. Hasan Muhammad al Abedi. Al Tawati Abdul Jalil. Fiwami al Munfi. / Badr bin(Rtctived under Muscat Printed letter ^o•G/82 of 1 st n.fter Compliiaente. I have at last received your letter. Letters are greatly delayed. 1 hope you are well. 1 have received a letter fi-oin ^gypt the puiport of which is that all the brothers have put their- faith in Ills Highness Ainir Muhamaad Irdis as-Ganausi to speak in their names so &gt; that they may withuraw fi*orn the democratic front as to support it is worse for their brothers. An advisory committee of 19 persons has been formed am 1 have received a copy of the agenda. Our brothers in Damascus support their brothers there. Prior to this I wrote to you giving details and hoped that you would be able to help us. I am expecting your reply. I assur &gt;thing will be done without asxin^ your- views. I believe that it will be the same with you as it is with Syed and that you both will be one person at present and in future as all depends upon you. I think the others will follow your decision. This is my opinion and God willing I will do my best. In Egypt and Syria all have agreed. This is what makes a good name other than the name of Syed Idrisi in that country. You had asked me of the reason that led me to engage your thoughts to that direction. I wish that you will enlighten me regarding Muscat in a clear way. Some of our brothers who attach importance to your kind personality want some thing from you in their history. They want knowledge of Muscat and also of Oman. Are they inde pendent ? How they are administered by the Governments? As for mhe people, do they go away or remain in towns and then regaruing the tribes there and cities. This Damascus, To k 1940 J His nxceilency Shaikh Sulaiman Pasha Al Haruni.ifc 'because we have no history or knowledge particular ly of that side where you ai'e living. If you have anything printed about that side kindly send it to us. If there Is not anything printed, please give us some details so that if we speak about that side, its Sultan, tribes, towns and administration etc., we may be aware of them beforehand. If you have a printed book or publications about that side, please let us Know and send them to us. If I had enough time I would have gone to ilgypt to know the condition of our brothers there and obtain all other informations and from there receive the reports from you ana keep some footsteps. But what is to be aone? The eye can see but the hand is short All the brothers are well and they send their compliments to you. .»e all hope that our enemies the Italians will come out of their false retirement and sham neutrality and there will ring the hour of deliverance. My compliments to all the family and children and please accept my profound sincerety and respect. I have been asked to remind remind you of Ustadh Abybakar gadura, professor of history, who is expect ing a photograph with your signature on it. It has not arrived but he is daily enquiring about it. Sd. Omar Faiq ShanibmmMraXvTIAL . Secret No. G/37 of 1940. 2. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. 3. The Middle East Intelligence Centre, Cairo, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...37.t£..££.n^.^..^?4p. Camp, Kuwait. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter No.C/888 of the 14th December 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.C/5 of 2nd January 1940 from the Political Agent, Muscat. Suleiman al Baruni • / R ec« 11 pot-, OEPt.Copy* Secret British Consulate and Political Agency, Muscat, January 2nd, 1940. D.0.h T o.C/5 ofnal940. Please refer to the correspondence ending with in}' Printed Letter ho.C/536 dated the 5th December 1939. 2. During the course of conversation recently the Sultan informed me that Baruni had given up his idea of leaving Muscat as there did not appear any likelihood of Italy entering the war on the German side • Yours sincerely, sd. T.Hickinbotham* The Hon’ble Lt.Col.C.G.Prior, C.I.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.fjL rr FILECOPV £O0tXl®*J«P4W®f. Secret. i&lt;37 3o. v&gt; 8082 I 3- JAN MG No. C/888 of 1939 • The Hon’ble tie Politic il Resident in tile Persian Gulf presents his compliments to J, His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London* 2* The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, ^ew Delhi* 3. The Middle East Intelligence Centre, Cairo, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Camp, Kuwait* Dated... 14 ^ il. .V.e 0 e “h e r, 1.9 39 . i?f a*!. ‘&gt;5 fU;F-£2 Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter No*C/6 60 of 5th November 1939*^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Copy in translation of letter dated the 29th September 1939 to Shaikh Suleiman al Baruni, Muscat, from Ahmad Zari Ar.Rihaibi, Tripoli* 2. Copy in translation of a letter dated the 28th Novem ber 1939 from Suleiman al Baruni, Muscat, to Saiyid Ahmad Zariro, Salambo, Tunis. REOo.POL.DEPt. 1939 INDIA OFFICE Subject. Suleiman al Baruni al Nafusi• -* sent under i .I. 0.516-3 of 29/10/36 Jonfldentisa itoe re8id«noy f D.C iiuahlr« 9 the 2i* th October 193S« My dear Metoalfe, I e idoee herewith a oo^y of a letter ..o*^/i46 d&amp;tcd i^th October with ebcloaure fro® ttfttta on the aubjeot of ^ certain ^ulecan al haruni al ufuai# 2 * briefly baruni ia a native of :rii.oli» and has worked both for aiJd ag&amp;lngt the Italiana by *hOR 3 he it not allowed to return to h!e native country. ‘ro® 1^24 - 1932 Baruai w&amp;a employed in Oman by the lisa© aa hi a ^inanoial ^dviaer, and wae at ot*e time on bad terrca with the present ul tan of ^uacat f who t however. hu&amp; now for give hira t and appointed hi© to a vost in the internal administration of hi a itate. In the eyee of the bultan. hiroeeIf on the sunny aide of thirty, daruni la a •broken old man of over eixty*t (vide para C iTaph 3 of %tta f letter) who only wishes to paea the rerauinder of hie daye in peace and quiet. However thia may be we have certaiiily nothing dei ini te enough against bar uni to fl ive us aiiy reason for Ukin a the extreme etep of aaking Hia Hi ( ^hne«a not to employ him. i met barunl tome years a^o aiid he seemed to me tc have intelligence and a pleasant personality. ♦ I am aeiiding copies of this letter to reel and &gt;*atta. Your a a i rice rely, 3d.T.O.FOWLS nir Aubrey Metcalfe, K • 2 m J 0 '» 9 i &lt;}* 3* X* p M» V *()0 Secretary to the Govtrtmtat of India in the External .iffair* Department, Simla.(Received under Muscat .Printed letter !To«CJ/496 of 24th iMOveiyber ; t , 2 1939) Copy in translation of le 2^th Soptembor 1939 f to r Shaikh Suleiman al Baruni Ar-Rihaibi, Tripoli. |ter dgitacutha !93y Ahmad Zari I received your letter of 14th Rajah on 12th Shaban. I was very pleased with it. I have come to know about your health as well as your service to your country. As rer&amp;rds the news you heard on the radio, it requires no explanation as the world at large knows everything. Nothing remained except the spark of fire to start. As regards your desire to know something about it all| what I can say to you is that we are combined together waiting to enter the battle again. Our country^ condition is very bad. All that the news-papers have issued is quite enough. We held a meeting on the 17th, 18th and 19th. In this meeting the following were present s- Sheikh ifohammad bin AlhaJ Hasan Al Mashai, Sheikh balia bin Abciur Nabi Axantani, Ali Pikeeni on behalf of his father, ^aiyid Mohammad Oraikeeb, Kaji Israail bin Salim bin Ismail,sheikh Tahar Al Baddl, Saiyid Mohammad bin Khaleefah, «Tabar Asswai, Mohammad Kffendi Gfhalib and many others. #e had. an interview with the French Government who are ready to help us. Ths name of the Society ha© been changed to United Society. The address of the society is as follows:- Nahj Athahab, No. 7, Mukarar. fou may correspond with if if you like. We have stopped issuing the newspaper. We often wrote to you requesting you to give your opinions and advices on this subject but you are careful. We rely on you much especially in this hard time. This is what I could write to you briefly and exnect your reply and all your opinions about us and our situations.(Received under Muscat Printed letter No.t.P/536 of 5th December &gt; . ' . Copy in translation of a letter dat *3 fitm fiCth OUU£. \ November 1939, from Suleiman al Baruni, Muicat to Saiyid Ahmad Zarim, Salambo, Tunis. I 93 y J I received your letter of the 15th Shawal after two months. I have been expecting it. I hope that you received my letter of the 5th Shaban. I am awaiting your reply to that. _ fl it was a gret pleasure to me to know about Sheikh Mohammad bin Haji Hasan because a year ago I had heard that he had died and also Abdu/ Nabi. I thank God that that was a false report. God to bless him and return him to his country. I am now awaiting replies to my letters which I sent to some places regarding facilities on the way to Tunis. Please convey my regards to the heroes of the country and to all the sheikhs there. Also to the members of the society. I trust that all of them will succeed. My compliments to my friends and Sayid Al-Jablani. If you do not know him Haji Ismail will be knowing him.No. C/660 External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. £% His Majesty^ Secretary of state for Indie, London. 3. His Majesty's Ambassador, Baghdad. 4. Middle East Intelligence Centre, Caivo. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). \ \ Reference to previous correspondence : \£\ £&gt; 8-7 f- ■ er ’-' Hesidency Bxprsss letter 50.616 dated the J22nd British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Camp, KUWAIT. 5th HoYember 1939 October 1939 Name and Date. Subject, Copy in translation of letter dated the 5th Ramadan 1358 (l9th October 1939) from Suleman al Baruni, Suleiman al Baruni al Muscat, to Shaikh Ahmed Beg al Baruni, Qadhi of Yafrin, Hsfusi Tripoli.Copy in transl&amp;'tion of lottor dated the 5th uamadan 1368 (19th October 1939) from Suleman al Baruni, Muacat to ^— Sheikh Ahmed Beg *1 Baruni, Qadhi of_Xafrin, Tripoli. (Arabic). i p. :z. i : 7329 After Coiflplii&amp;ents # My salams to the students jand &gt;giir 0 a rt^ . We are all in good health, thanks to God, and our attention is towards you* We hope that you are enjoying good health and that the European war is not effecting the rest there because Italy is neutral* Every effort to induce Ibrahim to Join has failed* May God lead him. I have been informed that the Italian legation in Baghdad mentioned that you had asked for permission for him for Tripoli, and that your request has been granted. I do not know whether you have written to him to come to you or not. Anyhow you have to write to him in the following way «- rt Ibrahim, as you are still remaining in Baghdad and so far you have not Joined the family in Muscat, I request you to visit us on the mountain, where we have been enjoying peace and happiness. Italy has not Joined in the war etcetera.' Do not mention to him his sickness or the change of air as this information will estrange him.jsk asi o&amp;tBt io mltalnsvi-ii ai ^qo3 t/fwwtt f£MOi«&lt;S M((*rt (6MSX itfCX) WS&amp;X a; ifijba^XJte Kh»p t ±iarxi3£ Ijb r,»fi xUlfrf® * eiji-lX'I^ f ' v O ‘VW^fcA esE^ toj aJ-aa^im adJ- oj sssttlrts x 2 ^ — 'xw ii'*» ■ i— ^ « si riciw rr*vd£ **^0 ^ L* * 5 v;C'Sv*' ^*15 b^4 5^454 ’TACirtO?^ wtir'i JaAJ #^OW 4l* “• ■» torsrr ftt yxafLj jss*! s*:^ afULw j sfli. sJt ^IWMi- )so^ s.sfit rrio^ *V J' - v # . '/ * j^ix^rx «»4i i •»x&lt;{ : ja*i *ic*'- «lr 'xo'x noi.-“ft 4‘-y fi»t; •xoTt GXii* odxso^^^lpl • TO ;,C.V £XT BfflOG •' i*Ov r- .. Vt* &gt;»ux'-oXJoi *03 xtk akd ** *J£t* oj svarf -&lt;r&lt; iroxiv^ ^tjs nX &amp;u£tiisrzrt lit** 4Tt 3* i'- ^ ! 4 r: &lt;£iWt i# $*&amp; ***&amp; &amp;*X ^ °« 9VT t J r l.*^Si 1 &amp;tiZ*TlfffWk 405' fSO Cl od *.** .ai tm T+§§* &amp;$i*&amp; lo e'-iiusdo ^ es^ffiDla Lixii of no&amp;'MO&amp;i ieu oG .rairi iSlw &gt;t4x^'' isrxo-ni cx*lf &amp;«» ticraJttMBfl ( 7427/95/91). r ^CRKT . X FOBS Ml OFF 1C?, C.B.l* 21 8 t November, 1959. Dear Chancery, Ve enclose copies of correspondence from the India Office on the subject of letters addressed by r uleiman al jaruni al Nafusi, a former ^ali of Tripoli and now in the employ of tne ultan of Muscat, to tne Trench Premier, the Minister of ar ana the Resident General in Tunis. 2. As Culeiman al jiaruni has asked that an^ reply to these letters should be sent through the British Consul at Muscat, we think it would be as well, provided the Ajibassador sees no objection, if you would let the French Ministry for Foreign Affairs know that we have been informed in confidence by the Multan of Muscat (whose opinion of the writer’s capabilities is not, incidentally, very high) that an approach in the sense indicated in tne Muscat/ The Chancery, ! ritieh Embassy, Paris.—. (B Muscat letter of the 19th September to the Political Realdent In the Persian Gulf has been made to the French Gcvsrniaent by ^uielaan al fcarunl and that thl® approach wae made without riloxi^ibotna« , a Joiowledge, 3 . The fact that have actually obtained the correspondence should be Kept secret. Youra ever*FILE COPY GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. i ISxt eraal Affai e Dep&amp;rtmfnt- 5 6876 EXPRESS LE TTER (A|R MAIL). . [N.B ~Thi* i 8 an ORIGINAL mttmgt etnl by AIR MAIL which froridcfi a weave of ccrrwvvicaiicTi were. expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the tchgrapih. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been iel&amp;.rajhed. To eate time and to tbiiais formalities it is drafted in. the form of a teh^rasn. It is authenticated by lie signature qf a responsible officer of the. Department.] NoF*356-N/39 Dfitod A ew fJttko &gt; the 26th October 1.9 39 i ( 3 &amp; l X To Secretary of State for India» London (Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire and His Majesty's Ambassador, Baghdad)* Subjects-* Suleman al Baruni al Nafusi* Reference Political Resident, Bushire's Express letter No* c/462, dated the 26th September 1939* 2. Although we are willing to iiake cognisance of French interests in Muscat when necessary (actually the French Consul at Bombay is in charge of these in terests) al Baruni , s action in the present case was taken entirely without the knowledge of the Political Agent* As suggested by the Political Resident the French Government &gt;ight perhaps be ; informed accordingly if His Maj6sty r s Government consider it desirable* The issue of the above has been authorised* * 1 1 Deputy Secretary to the Goveri t of India* id- 44 T&gt;CF P—6CMS&amp; P—&lt;G -0. iO&gt;—iA- l-Vj -30.000 {Sirpudurc) (Desitpialicai) -t RECb. POL. DEPt.... fILE COPY GOVeRNMENTOF iNmTtr Secret* $ j . .c De^^r'tpent. h EXPRESS LEiTTER (AIR MAIL). ny. |Q^t Lu. m [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR M AIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a retpon^bl. ojjicer of Department.] ^ ^ t 0 lt t lcel ti.Bideut in N 0# Persian Gulf, Capp, KUWAIT# ‘ C/618 of 1939 Dated the ootob.r, ' 39. ^ CXXXJUUC ’ the To Hepeated - Reference Tatjaxxjz 7 The Secretary to the Gorernment of India, internal Affaire Department, hew Delhi. Hie Majeety’e secretary of State for India, »/ London* V Hie Hajeety's Jtobaeeador, Bagdad* Middle East Intelligence Centre, Cairo. The Political Agent, Muscat. SubJeot i Suleiman al Baruni al Nafusi* In continuation of my Express Letter Eo#^ 4SS, dated the Both September 1939. A copy of letter 'Io.C/357, dated the 26th September 1939, from the Political Agent, Muscat, and of the translations of intercepted letters enclosed with It, is fori^aided herew.th. 2. Six of Baruni’s seren letters intercepted are also forwarded. It is suggested that they should be sent on by post to the addressees, Bombay, or preferably Karachi, being used as a posting centre* The envelope of the seventh (Ho .6 on the Muscat list) having been damaged, the letter has been destroyed. 3* The contents of letters Nos.l and 2 on the Muscat list, addressed to the French Premier and Minister for War respectively, have been found to be identical with those of No.4, addressed to the French Minister and Resident General in Tunis. {Signature) [Designation) S/.44. MFP—985 S&amp;P—(M-1597)—27-11.36-10,000. / RECd. POL.DEPt. -2NGV1939 INDIA OFFICE n-it■ML*. 4. A bri«f note thie letter sent to • 2* * IQ -v Q * W w ^ J on Baruni has Been attaobed to the copy of the Middle &amp;aet Intelligence Oentre, »d. 0 *G.Prior• Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested . i for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf./I / * / sr t 'i \ iLCLLl . Ho. C/367. IVOB To HolitUal ‘Jtnay A H.B.M'a Conoulato, Muscat, tho 26th Soptanbar 1939. 6875 ! [ !939 Captain T* Hicklnbothaai, 0«BoE. t ““ Political Agant dt Consul 9 ^useato Ths Hon 1 bis tbs Political Ksaidant in tbs Psraian Quit, Sir, Subject s~ Jj£ul« I have ths honour to rsfar to paragraph 8 of ay letter So. C/344 dated tho 13th September 1333 and to forward, herewithf intercepted correspondence from Suleiman Pasha al Bartini el Bafual to certain persons. 8 . Care has been taken that the fact of their with drawal from the nail shall not boeoao known to tho postal authorities here. X regret that the original envelope of enclosure ho. 6 has unfortunately been damaged. X have the honour to be, Sir | Your meet obedient eervent, '• HlCJci N 6 o‘T KAM Captain,X.A., Political Agent ft E.B.M'e Consul, Huecat.mi fli MBuaam* X* Unopemd R*gl 0 t«r*d Cover Ho. R.148 addressed ftp to the x French Premier. 2* Unopened Registered Cover ho* R.143 addressed to the French Isr Minister. 3* Opened Registered Cover Ko« 150 addressed to Syed Aimed Zerioi f Tunis together with a translation of the contents* 4. Opened Registered Cover ho* R. 142 addressed to the French Minister and Eeaident-Oeneral in Tunis together with a translation of the contents* 6 * Opened unregistered and unstamped cover addressed to the French Premier* The contents are Identical with those of enclosure Ho* 4 * 6 * Opened unregistered and unstamped cover addressed to Syed Omar Paiq Shunaib of Damascus together with a translation of the contents* 7* K second opened unregistered and unstamped letter in a dark envelope addressed to ByeCt Ahmed ZaarLax of Tunis with a translation of the short enclosure*Copy in translation of lottor datod tho 7th Simaban (i\o 1368 and its post script dated tho 9th Shasban 1368 fras Salsiasn ml Bmruni ml Nafusi, Muscat to Sytd Ahmad Zapi*, Smiambo^ AhwmJ, i j| Tunisf m rssidmnt of Tripoli* After Compliments. 6875 !939 I mm enclosing the copy you sent me and asked me to return in this letter. Please accept my apology for keeping it until today* I replied to you on the 14th Rajah* I hope it reached you# I am expecting a letter from you. The war has broken out and it is expected that it will be wide spread y the result of which Z hope will be the liberation of our door country from servitude. Sometime ago X wrote to some sources, and informed them that the correspondence between me and you la continuing. Perhaps you will be questioned about it t so be on your guard. X am patiently awaiting the answer to what X have written and yours am well. Svery night we hear the war news from Berlin, Rome, Paris and London stations which excite us. God grant prosperity and benefit for us and our country. 1 will explain my views to you in my next letter. God make the way easy for me to reach you. Uy regards to the brothers. i'Ui lHoB. If it is possible for you and other brothers to writs to me a letter asking me to come as quickly as possible, please do mo mnd mend it by air mail as soon as possible. I will use it me an excuse for travelling. Hie Highness the Sultan is delaying him permission for ay travelling. If he grants ms permission X shall not remain here end your letter will follow me SSElgt. 9th Shmmban 1368. Copy of what was written on the back of m lotter sent before this with the word “Registered* written on the cover, but the messenger found the Poet Office dosed. He wrote on it in / English2 6875 t'rm En^aiah and without affixing any ataapa an 1 hJ po ^jBkb fr ship*# box. This was whan aha was raady to sail. fha enclosure to that lattar was tba copy of the eonminicatiott you cent to tha French Minister. I hopa you have received it, and expect that you accepted it and paid the fine. # 1 X 1 you please enquire about Syod aX if Haul about whom X read acme time ago that he has been appointed as a raaaber of the Tunis Council. He married a Turkish lady from Istanbul* Plsass give him my regards. Ha is an old friend of mine. X met him in France after the world war. Inform him that I am endeavouring to coma to Tunis for treatment at 'Hansata Qirfcio' where I treated myself when X was a student at 'Ma'ahad as-Zaltooni“ and recsived grant benefit. Do not mention my coming to your side except him (Syod al &lt;Jllanl) until X get permission and X will inform you from Baghdad. Inshallah.’■&gt; / V / 4L / Copy in tronolotion of o lottor doted the 21et Septoabor IMdAjy from Suleiman al Baruni al Kafuaif iOiacat to the French Miniator and Resident-General at Tunis. 6875 ’ jovro ’ w vj&gt; After Coapllnenta. The declaration of war by France against Germany&gt; who la in alliance with Italy by the Axis pact, has very much pleased the Tripoliaa 'Birqa' inaigranta numbering about one hundred thousand who are diaperaed among the countries* Woet of thorn are at Tunis y Algiers, Egypt and Damascus. They believe that the French will make easy the way to their national unity and enable them to organise their military force to liberate their country. Tunis is the place on which they ere relying because of its proximity to their country* I have been in communication with the heads of the Tripoli community, who took refuge in Tunis whan Italy broke the peace pact,which we had agreed upon with her,end revoked the Trlpoll’e Fundamental Lav, the articles of which had been agreed upon by us with the Italian Delegation. It was approved by the House of Deputies and the Senate end seal ed by the signature of the present King of Italy. Since their departure the immigrants have been awaiting to seise a suitable opportunity* Waiting patiently for a World War, when they would be assisted by the enemies of Italy to organise their army* They look to ths Franca, the mother of liberty and the neighbour of Tripoli at Tunis and Algiers. They do not forget the help rendered by France end Tunis in their previous wars with Italy In 1911-1912-Id 13. The kind and friend ly treatment shown to the people of Tunis end Algiers, the follow ers of the French, by the Tripoli ana during the World War, in spite of the war then being waged between t Turkey and France, was due to gratitude for help previously rendered. On my / arrival ata arrival at Tripoli from latwabul in a aubaarina at tba coawinoa- mat of the World tf«r m* WaJLl and Goneral of Tripoli end ite dopondoncloe I at once ordered ell the French prieonorof who wore captured hy Sheikh Khallfah hin Acker el-Seweti in e battle with the French near «D^ihaibat ,, on the Tunia borders, to be act free. X sent them with an escort who delivered thee to e French Officer et the Tunis frontier without coapenaation. X have in ay posaesalon an official letter from this French Officer in which he acknowledges their safe arrival# Correspondence is proceeding between ae end the Tripolian notables now in Tunis through the aealoue and loyal Ahmad £eria, resident of Salaabo a place (section) in Tunis. He sent me a copy of what they have eutaitted to the French Minister at Tunis* We therefore believe strongly that France will give us the necessary help to organise the immigrants so as to be reedy to march when Italy declares her entry in the war on the German side* This time, with God*s will, the Tripolian revolt will be stronger than it wee during the old World War of 1914* Then our soldiers drove the Italians from the desert to the sea and captured many thousands of them. These prisoners remained in their hands until peace was concluded between us in 1919 based on the famous Tripolian Funflsamntal Law. They captured from the Italians many thousands of rifles as well as guns and Lewis guns* The doors of Tunis and Algiers were closed by the French end the doors of Kgypt were closed by the British because they were on the Italian side* Wow the doors of Tunis, Algiers end Egypt are epen for tba lomlgranta Vo go to thalr country if Italy goca to war against Britain and Franco. Come what may God is with the oppressed. X am, therefore, pmqpma prepared to come to Faria, / Damascus _~ 3 ~ Da&amp;/kBCVA or Toals to diocuoo with tho arroogonintoi and what la roquirod for our country If fift*l victory la won 'Inahallah' ao that wo will know tha reward of our fighting froa now. If you accept ay view ploaao aond your reply by air wall or by telegram through the Consul of y\&gt;ur ally the British at &amp;iaoat« God load the aucceaa. Bealdoa informing you of ay wish it la saceaaery for you to know that 1 m now Advisor to the Muscat Government and at rest with my family* A very pleasant life under the patron- age end respect of His Highness the Sultan. Hay God support M» t All this does not make mo forget ay birth place and the &gt; ^*m&gt; of ay fere-fathara who were well known there for more than a thousand yearst as la written In history• 1 lelt ay family at Istanbul y* - * left ay seat in the Ottoman House of Lords (Ao-Slnat) of which X was a member. 1 spent more than four years in Tripoli during the World War fighting the Italians until they sued for peace with ua* 1 think this is sufficient for you to understand the greatness of ay desire at this critical period* I was awarded, during the World Mr when X was on the Tripo li an battle field, the Ottoman Hedal, the Ottoman,Austrian, and German War itedals of the 2 nd Class and the rank of Pasha etcetera. Usual Lading* Sd./ Suleiman al Baruni al Tarahleai. aXHUMtoer of the Ottoman House of Lords (Aa-Slaat)* Wall af and Commandant of Tripoli and its deoendcncies during the «#orld War* Ifeaber andComandant of Um Trip*ll*a BopUbli* after InVeiiwt.lonal liof i- Copy of tbi. la soat to *• ( 1 ) Th. Hon'bl. the French Premier. ( 8 ) Hie highness the French Minister for War.Copy in translation of lattar datod tiw 4th ( 17 th Saptonbor 1939) from Suleiman al loruni al Kafuoif After Conpliaenta. ”— I have read in the Egyptian newspapers of the organ isation of the new army under the direction of Asia beg djau ± have seen no mention of Syed Idris. What is the meaning of this? Will you please let me know the troa truth in regard to lint of the Tripollans in Egypt. Please expedite your reply. I have already written to you about my intention to go to Baghdad* I have been delayed here until now. I still intend to go end hope to come to you from Baghdad. Italy’s entry in the war on one side or the other will not be long delayed in my opinion. Bor entry on the German aide will be pleasant and will make matter# easy for us* but if she has deceivod tbs Germans f as in the world war* and enter# on the British aide then the door of our home will be closed in our faces. to the brothers especially those known to me. 1 am awaiting an air letter from you which ia»^o I hope* on the way. Muscat to Syed Omar Paiq Shunaib, a notable Ae-Salhiyah * Damascus. «f Tripoli) 6875 It 1. U» will of Hod. Pray God that that which is good for our country and oursalv.s nay com. to pass. Hy regard.1368 (18th StptMfeftr 1938) Trot* Sul*loan *1 ika'uiiX-*l Bafual, I „ f**m* ■ my apology for ita dataatlon until to-day* X anawarad you in n lettar on 14th Rajah which X hop* haa arriwod. I an awaiting your reply, rfar haa broken out and it ia expected to h* very extanaiv*. Therefor* X hope our dear country will he delivered from aervituda. Sonetine ago I wrote to aone aoureea that X an in eoanunioatioa with you continually. In eaae you are queation- *d in this respect please be on your guard. London and other stations which excite us. Qod prosper the well- fare of our country. X an waiting with patience for your reply. Sven if X leave for Baghdad X shall receive it. X will try ay beet to reach you. If it la possible for you and sons other friends to write ne a lettar asking na to return please do ee without delay because Hie highness the Sultan haa been delaying the grant of permission for ns to cone to you and X will make your letter an excuse to leave. Usual Sliding* , % tfuscat to Syed Ahmad Zarim* Salanho (Tunis). C O *7 PI / gvary night we hear the war news fren Faria, Rons, Sd./ Suleiman Pasha al Barunl al Xacfusl. the Comnittee./ «•-111 Conlidcntial FILE COPY GOVERNMENT OF 1ND Department , ?0 / 30 13 1938 A.O^D J : ‘339 :j, EXPRESS I FTTER (AIR MAlL)._ j. 'Kf i .v$ [N.B.— TAis is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MA ^ than £ t ,i efrap h. It it intended to be treated, expeditious than the ordinary mail and ts cheap beeH telegraphed. To save time and to ohvtntt on receipt, with the same expedition »* x f 'f h * n Authenticated by the signaiure ef a formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram, it responsible officer of the Department.] No* c/48* Dated Ni the Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulfj^Ca»p Bahrein. 26th September 39 To Repeated The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department» Simla* His Majesty's Secretary of State for India# London. His Majesty's Ambassador# Bagdad* Political Agent# Muscat* Reference Subject ! Suleiman al Baruni el Mafusi * Reference correspondence ending with External Affairs Department letter Ho*I&gt;*4110 -m/ 38# dated the 7th December 1938 (copy not sent to Bagdad)# 1 enclose copy of a letter Ho*C/344, dated the 19th September 1939# from the political Agent# Muscat# Copy of Baruni 1 s letter to the French Government will be forwarded on receipt* 2 * With reference to the Political Agent 1 a paragraph 7# I suggest that if it is considered necessary to make any commun ication to the French Government# the fact that Barun^s action was taken without the knowledge of His Majesty's Representative at Muscat may be made clear* Sd. C.G* PRIOR Win k k* ^ U U i&gt;0luic81 in the ‘ S Ww rsro- VMntx. t '1 | fe U. 0,lv^ V/Wx ^ Ob ... \ for Secretary tc the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* S. 44. MFP—985 S&amp;P-{M-1597)—27 11-36—10,000. {Signature) RECo. POL ^EPt. o oci (Designation) ! OFFICEPaUtioal Agency * a.a.a'c Coneolate, (g) yoaeat, the Idth Sep Water id39. Ho. C/344 Fro* Captain T. Hickinbothasi, O.B.Z., Political Agent 4 H.B.M'a Conaul, Muiemt* To Tfco Hon 1 bio tbe Political Hoaidont in the Forsian Gulf, Bahrain* Subject i* Sir, X have the honour to state that at an interview i had with Hla Highneee the Saltan thie teaming Hie “ighneea raiaad the question of Suleiman al Barunl al Hafuai and tha latter'a proposed offer of assistance to the French Gove meant. 8 . It appears that Baruni haa informed His Highness that ha intends to leave Muscat ostensibly for medical treatment in Iraq, but in reality to try and get as near to Tripoli as be o«n so that in tho •vent of Italy antaring tha war ha will ba in a position to taka advantaga of such opportunitiaa aa saay oftmr with tha Idsa of avantually ragaining aoaa at laaat of hia old Influanea in Tripoli. 3 . Baruni haa addraaaad a lattar to tha Frsnch Poraign winiatar outlining hia own oaraar and nalrlng the oioat of hia pswsr to issfluonea avanta in Tripoli* ®a haa point ad out that there are aont 30,000 of hia old adharonta in Tunisia and haa suggested that ha should go to Tunis now so aa to bo ready to act should Italy boeoae involvod with Franco* ho haa aakad that tha | French Qoveraaent should aaaiat him in hia andaavoura, proauoably financially, and haa expressed hie willingness to go to Faria or Syria to discus* tha situation with them* Hie Highness haa /promised to lett . . « proaia«d to lot m havo a copy of Banal 1 * ilftttw* to. the Fr^ach to bo informed of hie propoood aoveaionto and aokod that I bo acquainted with the contonto of hio lottor to the French Govern ment in which I understand ho has aaked that their reply nay bo aldreeaed to him through mo. that there is little chance of the French Government acceding to hie request unless Italy actually dec idea to enter the war ae an ally of Germany. Bar uni has announced his intention of leaving his family in safety here and going to Iraq whatever reply the French Government give. It is doubtful if he will even wait for a reply. 6 . I explained the delicacy of the situation with regard to Italy at present and informed His Highness that I would communicate with you at once. X aaked the Sultan to make a particular point of keeping the matter secret and he promised to do so. ?• The French Government» I have no doubt* ere better able to estimate Baruni’s usefulness and the advialblllty of use of him then X am* It might be ae well, If you thought fit' to make it clear that hie reference to this Consulate does not in say way Indicate that X have been privy to hie plane until now or that they have the benediction of the British Representat ive hare. Barunl is too old for active work in the Sultan 1 e opinion and has deteriorated mentally during the laat year. Z have little personal knowledge of e# the men but X doubt whether he will be ef much value to the cause. Government end ae soon ae 1 receive it I will forward a copy to you. I understand from His Highness that Baruni wished iae Hie Highness the Sultan has told Barunl that he thinks Should the original ef hie letter to the French / Gov** &lt;v H OyT / •rrcmiMnt cows lato bands nhcn cenaor: forward it to you unopened for auch action 6253 o win you I hart the honour to he, Sir, Your aost obedient servant. 3d a / T.Hickiribotham. Captain, X* A«, Political Agent * H.Beg's Consul, Muscat*CONFIDENTIAL. ,iS? No. 740-^3 ! ^/io ,; i V b !C\ZZ r\ A' The Hoo’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. 2 . R.T. &gt;eel, Isquire, I'.C. The India Office, London. ITaj or ./.R. Hay, C.I.E. Jeputy secretary to the Government oi India in the External affaire department, Wev/ delhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSH [RE. Dated... .I?'}. Reference to previous correspondence: Government of India letter no.d.4110-1/38 of 7th december 1938. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Residency letter no.739-8 of l7th december 1938. iuleman al daruni. !\ * aent under P.I*.No.740-3 of 17/12/38 gonfidential fhe H«8idenoy» '^0.110.739-3 Buahire, th# 17th December 1938 Iu.y dear ./atts, fith reference to correa^ondence endifie with 3ir rrench^rd* a demi-official letter Ho .hl7 -3 |, df ted tne 29th October 1938 f to iir Aubrey Metcalfe on the eubject of Ouleraan al Baruni, 2 am desired to enclose herewith &amp; ooyy of Hay*a letter No.D.4110-H/^ of 7tjl December 1938. 2. It does not seem to 3ir ^renchttrd that ’Jaruni 18 likely to indulge in any anti-British intrigue, and if he tried to do so he is eure that the Sultan» with hie healthy suspicion of the Italians and their ways, would stop him immediately. However you might keep an unobatrucive eye &gt;n Baruni and let us £now in due course what you can of his activities. Incidentally the Arab press, a« you will doubtleee have noticed, have commented favourably on Baruni*s appointment. * A copy of this letter is being sent to Peel and Hay Youre sincerely tlajor R.P. Watte, I.A Political ^gent. Hueoat•^ -/•&lt;&gt;&gt; ci*.rfc 3 £* EXTaRNAL AFFAIRS DEPARIVENT d.Q. Ho. D.4110-N/2 I am desired to refer to your deioi-official letters Hoa. 515-S. and 517-3., dated tne 29tn October 1958, regarding Ouleman al Baruni al Hafusi, and to aay that ao far as the Government of India are concerned they agree that the Bultan should not at present be asked not to employ Baruni. It is however suggested that the Political Agent, Muscat, be asked to watch Baruni’s activities and to report if he shows any signs of anti-British intrigue. A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. Yours sincerely 3d/- W. R. Hay To The Hon’ble Lieutenant Colonel dir T. C. Fowle, KCIK., CBS., Political Resident in the Persian ;}ulf/ FILE No. 518-3 CONFIDENTIAL. 1333 J The Hon’ble the Politic! !Sl KesideurTn^the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 . R. T« Peel, ^sciuire, The India office, London. Z, Laj or R.P. v/atte, I. A. Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Residency letter i.o.5l7-tj of 29th October 1938. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...&amp;9.m.Ufi£ T.. AS,5ft Hesidency Printed Letter j.,o# 516-8 of 29/10/38, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. duleman al baruni al RufusiConfidential D.Q. 0,517-a Ulae Keeidency, Buehire, the a9th October 1938. ]bUf My dear Metcalfej Could you please refer to my demi-official letter i 0.515-3 of a9th October 1938 on the subject of a certain Baruni. 2. In paraisraph 5 of his letter enclosed with mine -atte sayet believe the Cultan^ real object in brin^n^ back al Baruni to his State is a part of an ambitious project on which 1 have for long suspected the Cultan has set hie heart* the expulsion of the imam aiid the eventual resumption by the J&amp;uscat Covernoent of control over the whole of its territory.* I think that ^atts is correct. When l last met the Cultan, in the course of conversation he informed me that he thou^it that he could regain control over the interior of his State, not by force of arms, lwhich was tried unsuccessfully by his predecessors from time to time), but by diplomacy*. His Highness is in his way yuits a shrewd diplomatist and I should say that he may, in time, succeed in his object. Provided that he continues to do this by peaceful means X do not see that it need concern us. Xij 1 ac t i; should be to our advantage as the more control he acquires over the interior the easier this will/ 3ir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.3.a.8.I.,l£.V.O. Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs department, Simla.will c.ake th« oparatlons of Petroleum aonoeealone Limited. Fro* another point of view too, the attitude of Oman in the event of a major war (see paragraph 26 (3) of encloaure to my letter 18th January 1938), the more influence the Sultan exercises in that area the better. I am sending a copy of this letter to Teel and xours sincerely, sd# TaC.Fowle* ♦sent under Printed letter *o*5i8e3 of 29th October 1938 •Confidential itoe fteaidency, » sent under F.L.I0.516-3 of 29/10/36 iiuahire, the 29th October 1936. D.O. o.515&gt;C My dear Metcalfe I enclose herewith a letter fo.C/i46 dated 19th October with enclosure from Watte on the aubjeot of a certain Juleman al haruni al iufuai. 2. .briefly haruni la a native of Tripoli, and has worked both for and against the Italians by whom he is not allowed to return to hi a native country. i'^oin 1924 - 1932 Baruni was employed in Oman by the Imam as hie given . him, and appointed him to a post in the internal administration of his State. In the eyes of the Sultan, himself on the sunny side of thirty, Baruni is a 'broken old man of over sixty'! tvide paragraph 3 of Watts’ letter) who only wishes to pass the remainder of his days in peace and tiuiet. However this may be we have certainly nothing definite enoutJa against Baruni to give us any reason for taking the extreme step of asking His Highness not to employ him. 1 met Baruni some years ago and he seemed to me to have intelligence and a pleasant personality. / financial -adviser, and was at one time on bad terms with the present Sultan of Muscat, who, however, has now for- # I am sending copies of this letter to Feel and 'Vatts lours sincerely 3d. T r% 3ir aubrey Metcalfe, Becretary to the Goveriiment of India in the External -iffairs department. Simla.mmm ■■ From V Confidential. Political Agency &amp; H.M's Consulate Itascat f October 19th, 1938. IvO. c/146. a m b « . J i Major n ip. vitfeggiL t Political Agent A H.M* s Consul, Muscat. The Hon’hi* the roiitical Hesident in the Persian Gulf, hush ire • oulenmn al haruni al MuTusi. Sir, I have the honour to refer to paragraph 6 of teuscat Diary Ko. 14 of 1938, in whicD it was mentioned that a certain verson named Suieman bin Abdulla al haruui ai hufusi liad arrived in Muscat. 2. Early in August the Sultan had requested me to advise the British Consular authorities in Iraq to issue a visa when aa*ed for by al Baruni whom he wisned to invite to Muscat on a visit. The Sultan said that he had mentioned this persons name to you in a conversation during your meeting at Karachi in July last and that you had stated that His Majesty^ Government had nothing against him. On the strength of the Sultans statement X issued the desired letter. Al Baruni arrived in Muscat on August 26th and shortly after, it was reported to me, had been appointed to a post in the employ of the Muscat Government. On my return fromreoess therefore I looked a the Agency files about this man and also had a talk about him with the Sultan, who has now written me a letter on th subject of which a copy is enclosed.3 . The records show that al Baruni is an adventurer of the '•notorious' type who for many years both before during and after the Great *ar was a well Known person in the Middle £ast» Tide enclosures to Bushire Hesldency Confidential letter Mo, 410-S of 14th August 1930, It will be seen therefrom that al Baruni has in the past h&amp;fl a considerable amount of dealings with the Italians^/both against and for them and was suspected at one time of being one of their Secret Service Agents vide copy of extract from S,I,S« Summary Mo, 091 of 23rd May 1922 which formed part of the abovementioned enclosures. The Sultan, however, informs me that al Baruni states he is not now allowed by the Italian Government to return to his Home in Tripoli which he is desirous of doing and that his arrival in Muscat and his appointment to a post under the Muscat Government was mentioned recent ly in the Aiabio broadcast from the Italian iiadio Station at Bari, Had he still beeen in their employ it is hardly lively that the Italians would have thus announced his movements. From 1924 to 1932 al Baruni was in the On&amp;n being employed by the imam as his Financial Adviser, He left the country of hie own accord. In 1934 the present Sultan wrote to the Politi cal Agent and asked that this individual should not be given a visa to return to Muscat, His Highness in his talk with me about the matter said that he had taken this action on account of an impertinent letter he had received from al Baruni when the latter was in the Omani he had now, he went on to say, decided to forgive him and had sumnoned him to Muscat with a view to giving him an appointment in the State as he considered that xor cortcain internal administrative work, in view of the iact that he belonged to the Ibadhl ^eot, he would be of considerable use. The bultan said that whatever political intriguesintrigues al Bar uni may have Been concerned with in the past he was now a broken old man of over sixty (which age in the Sultan* s eyes is very oldl) and was thankful for a haven in which to/ pass the remainder of his days since he was forbidden by the Italian Government from returning to his Home in Tripoli* 4 . It will be seen from the Sultan's letter that he is evidently anxious not to employ al B&amp;runi if His ^hjesty-j Government do not desire it and he is careful to zaention that nis worx will be confined to matters concerning the internal administration of the State. 1 can find nothing in the Agency records to show that this man was ever sus pected of anti British activities and 1 certainly do not think that he will ever become as objectionable as the present head of the btate Courts, hasasi, a lalestine Arab time who for some oon aider able/pa st has not troubled to conceal his violent antipathy to ail things British. 5. I believe the Sultan's real object in bringing back al Baruni to his State is ^ part of an ambitous pro ject on which I have for long suspected the Sultan has set his hearti the expulsion of the imam and the eventual resumption by the lots cat Government of control over the whole of its territory. As mentioned above this can is of the Ibadhi Sect to which practically the whole of the inhabitants of the Oman belong. It seems he is by way of being a holy man and is said to have had V considerable influence for reii- ' gous reasons over the Omanis during the period he spent there in the employ of the Imam. The Sultan's policy for sometime past has been to make overtures to Shaiichs and Leaders of the Oman in outlying parts of that district whom he has reasons to believebelieTc are diesatiafied with the liiam* e rule. The laR®’ s authority and control over tae tribei of the Imam ia very largely, if not entirely, bused on his position as a rexigous leader, i believe that the sultan has the idea that al Baroni’s presence in iiuacat will help towards undermining the luam'a religous influence and, it is, in xny opinion, with this object that he hue given him an official position in nia doverncjent. I have the honour to be, Bir, four most obedient servant, Sd. R.P. WATTS. M&amp;J or,X.A., Political Agent &amp; K.^ 1 u Consul,Muscat.£.i.i. Ji a •^5 *' ' * t £ Oosj in ««n.intion oi n A . you „. no doubt —r. uv^ =.t staved there for years. He nad Tieited Oman in V***’ ® w , 1 «nnB with our Honourabie predecessors ana we friendly relations with oui a hisi visit to Muscat and he is a good man. taiew him ever since hie vis Tbn,. «o »• •»&gt;“•* ' o.„.l„ .uoUibl. » di. in -dl* *» ^ ,0 u., nut it ... not conToni.nt tn.u to -«»■• ' “** request* 14 txma tnat we were if* need of one who Last year we realised that we oouia administer certain of our internal and religiose afiair. and found that he was the proper man for the purpose a. hi. experience and Knowledge of the principles of our ibadhi eeot would be of great use to us. As you are aware we require efficient and experienced men in order to perform some of our aovernm.nt affairs, so we „rote to suxaimun Pasha al Baruni reminding him of his past request for an appointment. He accepted the offer and arrive* at liuocat a few weeics ago and we appointed him as an Advis*d for our internal affairs and inspector over our sails, etc, and he agreed to this appointment. I hereby desire to inform you of tdiSe «e underetood from the Honourable the political neside in the course of a conversation in which a mention of the » man in question was made that our friend the Honourable Government had nettling against him because we do not desire \ to employ from outside in our Government any one who would i dleturb the sincerity of the firm unity and friendship existing between us and our friend the Government if proved tnere was something to cause disturbance in the sincerity in our unity and friend shiv* ••••••••</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000216_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2990</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000216</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2990</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/30 'Muscat: Employment of one Suleman al Baruni al Nufusi'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-14T22:01:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (63 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 65; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to the activities of Sheikh Sulaiman Pasha al Baruni (also written Suleiman) [Sulayman al-Barūnī al-Nufūsi], an exiled notable of Tripoli appointed to the Muscat State Government.The file includes correspondence between officials at the Political Agency in Muscat, Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Government of India (External Affairs Department), India Office and Foreign Office discussing the appointment of al Baruni as Adviser for Internal Affairs and Inspector of Walis and the suspected reasons behind it. Also contained within the file are translations of intercepted letters to and from al Baruni to various members of the exiled Tripolitanian community between 17 September 1939 and 20 March 1940. The correspondence discusses the situation in Tripolitania, the position of the Italians in the Second World War, the formation of committees and the elections of leaders, and the possibility of liberating their homeland. Correspondents include:Syed Ahmad Zarim (Salambo, Ahwaj, Tunis)The French Minister and Resident-General at TunisSyed Omar Faiq Shunaib, a notable of Tripoli (As-Salhiyah, Damascus)Sheikh Ahmed Beg al Baruni, Qadhi of Yafrin (Tripoli)Ahmad Zari Ar-Rihaibi (Tripoli)Omar Faiq Shanib (Damascus)Ahmad Zarim bin Khalifah bin Omar (Salambo, Tunis)Syed Muhammad Ariqi, President of the Association of Tripolian Immigrants in TunisPresent within the file are translated letters and statements with multiple signatures of the 'chiefs and sheikhs' of Tripoli residing in Egypt declaring their intention to form a committee and elect a president (folios 15-17).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Sulayman al-Baruni</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000216#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>