<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100049434208.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T14:07:36.586Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FOREIGN DEPARTMENT NOTES. ARMS TRAFFIC IN THE PERSIAN GULF. Letter from R. E. Holland, Esq., Political Agent, Maskat, No. 345, dated the 4th (received 13th) April 1909. Forwards a copy of a letter addressed to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf regarding the illicit traffic in arms. Letter from Major P. Z. Cox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 975, dated the 25th April (received 3rd May) 1909. Communicates his observations on the foregoing lottery regarding arms traffic. Endorsement from the Majiinb Department, No. 710 M., dated the 28th (received 31st) May 1909. Forwards a copy of a letter from the Naval Commander-In-Chief on the subject of the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf. Letter from Major P. Z. Cox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 1201, dated the 22nd (received 31st) May 1909. Reported grant by the Sultan of MasJcat to a Raluchi arms-dealer in Maskat of a document stating that the import of arms into Maskat was free and that the trader was at liberty to import for a period of three years. Memorandum showing the papers forwarded to the India Office with the Foreign Secretary's letter No. 26 M., dated the 24th June 1909. Telegram to the Director, Persian Gulf Section, Indo-European Telegraph Department, No. 1058 A, dated the 25th June 1909. Asks for a report for the year 190S-09 regarding arms traffic in the Persian Gulf.J''' In our despatch No. 24, dated the 21st February 1907, we drew the attention of His Majesty’s Government to the growing import- No. 904 in Secret E., May 1907, Nos. 86G-93G. ance ^ ^ arms traffic in the Persian Gulf and to the alarming increase in its extent since 1903. We pointed out the injurious effects the trade was already producing in Persian and Turkish territory and the difficulties which it must eventually raise for us on the North-Western Frontier of India, and we prophesied that the time would come in the next few years when every fighting tribesman in Afghanistan and on our frontier would possess a modern weapon. We expressed the opinion that, in view of the impossibility of effective action for its suppression ever being taken by the Persian authorities, the arms traffic would continue to flourish and increase until the agreement with the French which we had advocated in our despatch No. 112, dated the 30th July 1903, was concluded and a complete prohibition was No. 20 in Secret E., September 1903, x os. - . en f oroe d. against the importation of arms and ammunition into the territories of the Sultan of Maskat. If this effect could be obtained by negotiation, the necessity of resorting to other expensive makeshifts would be obviated. Inter alia, we suggested the advisability of adopting measures to suppress the arms trade at Koweit by revising the Maskat proclamation* * No. 90 in Secret E., July 1898, Nos. 17-32 . of 1898 so as to include exports, as well as imports, and we recommended that the Porte should be asked to extend to us the right to search vessels flying the Turkish flag. The Secretary of State replied on the 29th March 1907, suggesting that we should continue to collect information and statistics with a view No. 925 in Secret E., May 1907, Nos. 866-936. ^ bringing our recommendations before the Arms Conference which was to meet at Brussels in 1908. 2. The hopes which were expressed in our despatch of 1907, that the problem was to be solved by negotiations having as their ultimate result the closing of Maskat as a distributing centre, are now not likely to be realised. The negotiations with France have been suspended ° Sir E. Grey does not entertain any great hope that the French Government will make the concessions we desire, and he feels that any Convention which could be arranged would be practically valueless. Assuming therefore that, so far as the arms traffic is concerned, the Brussels Arms Conference has failed, it is imperative now to decide whether we are to permit the trade to continue unchecked, and if not, what measures to adopt for its suppression. 3. The experience of the past two years confirms the views and apprehensions expressed No. 904 in Secret E , May 1907, Nos. 866-936. iu our despatch of 1907. The naval forces at our disposal in the Gulf have been shown to be quite inadequate to patrol the Mekran Coast effectively, and the few captures which have been made have only sufficed to irritate the Afghans without appreciably checking the trade. In the years 1907, 1908, 1909 as the result of our operations only 1,950 rifles and 175,000 rounds of ammunition have been captured and 500 rifles and 50,000 rounds of ammunition jettisoned to avoid capture. As Mr. Holland says a the efforts hitherto made to^check the arms traffic by sea can only be described as unsystematic, half-hearted and ineffectual”. The influx of modern arms to Afghanistan and the North-West Frontier has steadily increased. In 1906-07 the value of arms and ammunition imported into Maskat amounted to Rs. 16,85,075. In 1907-08 the value had risen to Rs. 41,85,760. Figures for 190^-09 are not yet available. In the report on the administration of the borders of the North-West Frontier Province for the year 1908-09, Sir G. Roos-Keppel writes as follows It is com puted that in the last three years 90,000 rifles (viz., 15,000 in 1907, 35,000 in 1908 and 40 000 in 1909) have left the Gulf for Afghanistan, and it is safe to assume that the bulk of this import has found its way, or will do so, to the best market—the tribal territory of the North-West Frontier. Of these rifles the percentage of Martinis has dropped from 82% in 1907, to 75% in 1909, with a corresponding increase in the percentage of *303 and other small bore high velocity rifles.” So far there are no indications that the market is in any way glutted, and the question of our future policy must depend on a consideration of the ultimate effects which an unchecked supply of modern weapons may be expected to produce with reference to (a) Afghanistan, (b) the North-West Frontier, and (c) Internal India. As regards (a), we have abundant evidence that the trade receives direct encouragement from the Afghan Government with the apparent object of providing every tribesman with a modern rifle. In August 1908 it was reported that the Amir had granted general permission to Afghan traders to bring arms and ammunition from the Persian Gulf and had even authorised advances to respectable traders for the purpose. In October 1908 the British A^ent at Kabul reported that a circular letter had been issued to all local Hakims throughout Eastern Afghanistan, authorising them to grant a loan to any indigent Afghan subject who may wish to purchase a rifle; and more recently we have been told that Sardar Nasrulla Khan has been receiving our tribesmen at Jalalabad, making special arrange ments for the sale of rifles to Mohmands and Afridis, and telling them to proclaim far2 and wide that those who wish to buy good and cheap rifles should proceed to Jalala bad without delay. The question of addressing the Amir on this subject was discussed last September in connection with the suggestion contained in the Secretary of Statens , « oor. despatch No. 16 of the 14th August 1908, that, ’ if arms are required for arming the people of Afghanistan, with the Amir’s permission, some other means might be devised for obtaining them which would not involve the traffic through Persia with the tribes on our side of the line. On this subject Mr. Clarke’s notes of 2nd notes, pages 8 anu . September 1803 and 2nd October 1908 may be read. We decided that the time was not opportune to make any communication to the Amir on the subject, and in any case it may be doubted whether, so long as no attempt is made to stop the Persian Gulf source of supply, anything we might say to the Amir would have any effect in preventing the present wholesale arming of Afghanistan. 5. The effect which the arming of the frontier tribesmen with modern weapons is having, and will have in the future, on the problem of frontier defence, has recently been brought prominently to notice, and has found expression in requests for increases to the strength of the Frontier Militia Corps and in recommendations for their re-armament. It has been pointed out that the tribesmen are now better armed than the local forces which we maintain to control them, and that the Militia Corps have in consequence lost the superiority which better arms and discipline gave to them in the past and which enabled them to cope successfully with raiding bands of greater numerical strength. The raiders on the other hand have gained confidence. It must be admitted that recent events in Kurram, Zhob, and on the Waziristan frontier lend considerable support to this argument. Unless the objection from a military point of view to re-arming the Militia with ’SO-'i rifles are relaxed, the difficulties experienced by the Militia Corps must be enhanced in proportion as the number of modern weapons in the hands of the tribesmen increases. 6. So far as internal India is concerned, the danger is problematical. Hitherto illicit traffic in arms has been from British India to the border, but it seems to be a matter of legitimate speculation whether there may not come a time, assuming that the supply through Persia proceeds unchecked, when the North-West Frontier will become a possible source from which the forces of sedition in India will obtain a supply of weapons and ammunition. 7. It may be argued that it is too late for effective measures to be taken, that the evil is already done and the stock of rifles and ammunition already in Afghanistan and the North- West Frontier so large as to make any increase thereto a matter of comparatively small importance. It is difficult to estimate the exact value which attaches to this argument, but we may at any rate assume that at present the number of *303 rifles is proportionately small. Moreover, improvements in firearms are continually being made, and we may soon be discarding the '303 for a superior weapon. The importance of checking the influx of still more modern weapons and possibly of Q. F. guns (for a recent report shows that parts of such have lately been imported into Maskat), cannot be overestimated. When we addressed the Secretary of State on the subject in our telegram of the 6th • No. 232 in Secret E., February 1909, No«. 188-242. Ja ° uar y 1909,* there was still some hope of a satisfactory solution of the problem through negotiations, and in the circumstances we were not prepared to recommend a scheme of increased naval activity to which it was considered there were political as well as financial objections. 8. The position has now altered and, unless we are prepared to face the dangers which are likely to result from a laissez faire policy, we must adopt the course which all authorities agree to be the only one which offers any hope of success, viz., a naval blockade with the supplementary measures necessary to make it effective. 9. His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, in his letter of the 7th May, expresses the opinion that an effective blockade can be established if the following measures be taken : — (a) A force of either (1) four 2nd or 3rd class cruisers or (2) three 2nd or 3rd class cruisers in addition to two of the subsidised vessels with full complement white crews instead of lascars. (i) All these vessels to be fitted with wireless installations and in addition a wireless station to be established at Jask, The latter proposal we have already recom- mendedf to the Secretary of State f No. 719 in Secret E., October 1908, Nos. 718-721. and we have also expressed the opinion’!' that the subsidised vessels should be fitted with wireless installations on general grounds inde pendently of measures for the suppression of the arms traffic. The cost of these installations should not therefore be regarded as part of the cost of the naval blockade. (c) The guard at the telegraph station at Jask to be reinforced to a total strength of 102 rifles as was done in 1908 and 1909. {d) Arrangements for intelligence similar to those made in the past by Mr. New to be continued but to be in charge of a special intelligence officer. Whether the results, so far as the peace of the frontier is concerned, which the execution of this scheme may be expected to achieve, will be commensurate with the expenditure involved,© Nos. 207 and 214 in Secret E., 207-222. December 1907, Noe. must largely depend on military considerations, but we may at any rate hope that its success would obviate a portion of the additional increase to the forces of protection on the frontier which the further arming of the tribes may render necessary. 10. Other points which suggest themselves for consideration are— (a) Can these measures be advantageously supplemented by arrangements— (1) with the Sultan of Maskat or (2) with the Baluch Mirs as suggested by Mr. Holland? (&amp;) Would it be necessary to increase the Sultau's subsidy ? (c) Is it probable that the traders can defeat the blockade by having recourse to other centres of distribution or by other means ? 11. As to (a), Mr. Holland suggests that it might be desirable to purchase the Sultan's co-operation in the prohibition of exports to the Mekran Coast in accordance with his Procla- N&lt;*. 8y-90 In Secret B, Jul, 1898, No.. 17-325. ” ation a ' &lt; } Notification promulgated in 1898 by a monthly payment of Rs. 5,0U0, in return for which the Sultan would undertake to prevent all exports from Oman ports to the Mekran Coast. Major Cox' criticism appears to me effectually to dispose of this proposal, for, firstly, the Sultan obviously has no means of making the prohibition effective, and, secondly, His H ighness is precluded from prohibiting all export by sea by Article 11 of the French Treaty which runs as follows :—‘‘ Mo vessel sha’l be prohibited from importing into or exporting from the territories of the Sultan any kind of merchandise'. The proposal to purchase by subsidies the assistance of influential men in Persian Mekran was put forward by Captain McConaghey in 1907. The Governmeut of India agreed with the Agent to the Governor-General in Balu chistan that the proposal could not be a accepted, for as the Persian Sardars in most instances derived profit from the trade, no reliance could be placed on their co-operation in suppres sing the smuggling of arms in return for a subsidy. Major Cox expresses a similar opinion now, and with it we may agree. 12. As to (6). it is perhaps premature to discuss the desirability of compensating the Sultan in the event of the measures adopted by us resulting in the crippling of the trade and the consequent loss of the revenue the Sultan derives from the imports. Mr. Holland states that the Sultan would in the circumstances have no legitimate grounds of complaint at the disappearance of his ill-gotten gains. This is no doubt perfectly true, but the Sultan would hardly look at it in the same light, and the loss of a large proportion of his revenue, however legitimately effected, would not tend to make him favourably disposed to the power by whose action it had been brought about, and would certainly encourage other Powers to intrigue with the Sultan and not improbably lead the Sultan to look favourably on a commercial treaty with Germany if such were proposed. 13. As regards (c), we have received information which shows a tendency on the part of the arms runners to split up consignments and despatch them from time to time in small quantities when any danger of their being intercepted is apprehended. This procedure, if adopted to any greater extent, must raise the cost, and thereby depreciate considerably the profits, of the trade. Were the trade at Maskat checked, it is possible an attempt might be made to utilise Koweit or Bahrein. Bahrein could be dealt with without difficulty, and as regards Koweit we should presumably press again the recommendations made in our despatch of 21st February 19U7*. Neither of these ports offers, however. No. 901 in Seorot E., May 1907, No.. 866.936. the same a(lvantage3 a3 Maskat, and the trade in Koweit is not so dangerous from the point of view of our interests. 14. There is another p5int which may be urged in favour of the policy of a naval blockade. Assuming that the blockade is established and is effective with the result that the trade at Maskat receives a severe check, it may be possible to resume negotiations with France with better hopes of success, for, so soon as our operations render trade unprofitable, the trade cry which influences the French Government must lose most of its force. The French merchants will lose the profits bought by the trade, while the French Government will not have obtained the quid pro quo which we were prepared to give her in compensation therefor. A possible objection is that a sudden increase to our Naval strength in the Gulf might be misinterpreted. The validity of this objection will largely depend on the course which events take in Persia, and it is difficult at this stage to know how much weight to attach to it, but assuming that our intentions are published, such a consideration need not deter us from the execution of a policy which our interests demand. 15. If it is admitted that an attempt must be made to suppress the arms [traffic by a naval blockade, the first step should perhaps be to ascertain the approximate cost of the scheme proposed by His Excellency the Naval Commacder-in-Chief, after Army Department has been consulted. L. W. Reynolds, —29-6-09. Foreign Office Press —No. 396—29-6-09—20.5 h) Letter from H. Whitby Smith, Esq., Director, Persian Gulf Section, Indo-European Telegraph Department, No, 374 P.j dated the 29th June (received 2nd July) 1909. Forwards a report by Mr. New on the importation of arms and ammunition to the Mekran Coast for the period from the 1st June 1908 to the 31st December 1908. Enclosure to Sir R. Ritchie’s letter, dated the 1 *tb June 1909. (Received 4th July 1909.) ARMS TRAFFIC. [4th May.] * 2 3 4 5 CONFIDENTIAL. Section 3. [16822] Sir A. Haidinge to Sir Edward Grey. (No. 57. Africa. Confidential.) §j rj Brussels, 3rd May 1909. I have the honour to report that, agreeably to the instructions conveyed in your despatch No. 48, Confidential, of the 30th ultimo, I to-day informed M. Van der Elst, Secretary- General of the Brussels Foreign Office, that our efforts to arrive diplomatically at an under standing with the French Government as to certain matters discussed at the recent Arms Con ference had proved unsuccessful, and that the British Delegates would accordingly attend here on the 17th instant, the date to which the reassembling of the Conference had been adjourned. M. Van der Elst took note of this communication for the information of the Belgian Govern ment. 2. I subsequently had some conversation with M. Capelle, the President of the Con ference, who said that he would cause the various Governments interested to be notified, and then enquired whether we wished the notification to mention the failure of our negotiations with the French. I said that I was not instructed to suggest this, and that I thought it would be sufficient to state in the formal notification that His Majesty’s Government was prepared to take part in the Conference on the 17th and desired no fresh adjournment. I have mentioned to one or two colleagues who have questioned me privately on the subject that there seemed no prospect of our coming to an agreement with France. 3. M. Capelle observed to me, speaking personally, that Major Liebrechts, who last year represented the Congo Government at the Conference, would now take part in it as one of the Delegates for Belgium, and His Excellency seemed apprehensive that some question might be asked when he appeared in that capacity, not perhaps by us, but by the Representative of some minor Power, as to the recognition by all the Governments represented of the transfer of the Independent State to Belgium, which might occasion some possible embarrassment. I said that I had no instructions from you on this point, but that I did not think that it was your wish to raise at the Arms Conference in any form the question of the Belgian annexation of the Congo. The withholding of our recognition of t at annexation was in no respect due to any desire to embarrass Belgium, quite the contrary, but to the necessity of our securing guarantees which we still earnestly hoped would be forthcoming, and the fact that Major Liebrechts, a Belgian subject formerly employed by the Congo State, the disappearance of which as an independent Power was a matter of general notoriety, was now employed by the King of the Belgians as one of the Belgian Delegates, need not I thought occasion any discussion, nor our acquiescence in it be held to imply any departure from the position which Great Britain had taken up with regard to the Congo question. Even if we should deem it necessary, which I thought personally was doubtful, to make a reservation respecting Belgium’s right to represent at an international gathering the interests of the old Congo State, such a reservation could be made in a note to the Belgian Government, without forming the subject of a public declaration at the Conference table. I trust you will agree with this view; we want all the support we can get from the Belgians at the Conference, and have nothing to gain by raising at its meeting a delicate question as to which we are at present at issue with them. 4. The Dutch Minister has asked me if, on the one point as to which his Government takes exception to our proposals, *.&lt;?., tne increase without special ad hoc authority from the Powers of duties on arms in the Conventional Basin of the Congo, we are, as yet, in a position to give it the formal satisfaction which it has demanded, and he has renewed to me the expression of his hope that this matter may be settled before we reassemble. 5. The Italian Minister has also spoken to me about the “ Italian conciliatory formula” for meeting the German objections to his Government’s original proposal as to the search of suspected vessels on the high seas, which formed the subject of my despatch No. 46 of the 7th ultimo. He has reason to believe that the Report from the Governor of German East Africa, of whose contents Count Wallwitz declared himself, as reported by me in that despatch, to be ignorant, is adverse to the original Italian proposal preferred by Viscount Morley and yourself, so that if we are to secure German acquiescence in that portion6 of oar programme which deals with the power of searching suspected vessels, it will be neces sary to adopt the compromise, however, unsatisfactory in itself, embodied in the Italian “ conciliatory formula,” and his Government is therefore, he says, very anxious that we should support it, if only as a pis aller, at Berlin, and induce the German Delegates to do so. You are aware from my despatch No. 46 that 1 thinlt there is a good deal to be said for this contention. 6. The main question, however, which His Majesty’s Government will have to consider, and as to which you will doubtless now instruct me, is that of the general line to be adopted by us at the Conference, in presence of the failure of our Maskat negotiations with the Irench. 7. There are two obvious alternative courses. One is to take the line that the Irench refusal to make anv concessions to us in respect of the arms traffic at Maskat, or of the exten sion of the zone of prohibition to Asia, makes the rest of the programme so valueless that we see no utility in continuing to discuss it. The other is to sacrifice the Maskat part of the pro gramme, and in return for this sacrifice to get all the other concessions we can, including, if possible, the extension of the zone to the whole of the Arabian coast as far east as the southern limit of Oman, exclusive, of course, of the Persian Gulf. 8. There appears to me a good deal to be said for both these courses, and my Italian colleague, whose Government’s interests in the Red Sea and on the Somali Coast are greater and more immediate than they are in the Gulf of Oman, is, I can see, strongly in favour of the latter one. He believes that the proposed limitation of the tonnage of vessels engaged in the arms traffic would deal it a very substantial blow, and that we might possibly, in return for the abandonment of our demands respecting Maskat, obtain valuable concessions in regard to Jibuti. He also thinks that there is no prospect that the Powers less directly interested than ourselves will sign the draft Additional Act as it stands, so long as the French refuse to do so, as the Germans, who have now got their Forest Zone Agreement, which was what they were most bent on, will be glad of the opportunity of obliging the French at the expense of Great Britain and Italy, while the secondary States, as well as those more important ones who have no direct interests at stake in the Asiatic side of the question, will take the line that although they entertain no objections to our proposals in themselves, they see no reason why they sh-mld adopt them, and thus assume obligations which are not accepted by all the Powers. We shall therefore merely have the very barren and Pyrrhic satisfaction of having placed the French in a somewhat odious light, as preferring selfish objects of a peculiarly petty and sordid character to the wider interests of all civilized communities. 9. On the other hand, an acceptance by us of a mutilated Additional Act would deprive us for an indefir ite period of all freedom to take any steps of our own for dealing in a more drastic manner with the arms traffic in Arabia, by giving to the Sultan of Maskat, for example, an increased subsidy in return for his adoption (without violating the letter of his Treaty with the French) of such police measures as we might consider necessary for preventing the re-exportation of arms to the territories of any Power prohibiting their import, or for himself prohibiting their purchase, save under stringent guarantees, by persons subject to his jurisdiction. 10. An intermediate solution might, perhaps, consist in an effort at the Conference to see what concessions short of the stoppage of the traffic in Oman we could obtain from the French, and in only letting them break it up, and thus restore to us our freedom of action if we found that they refused to make any of sufficient value. 11. As King Leopold is giving a garden party at Laeken on the 17th, the first meeting of the Conference can only take place on the 18th instant. I have, &amp;c., Arthur H. Hardinge. Letter from R. E. Holland, Esq., Political Agent, Maseat, No. 2C04 K., dated the 5th (received 6th) July 1909. Format (Is a copy of a letter witch he has addressed to the Political Jlesident in the Petstan Gulf on the subject of the illicit traffic in arms. The case is well stated in Mr. Reynolds’ note, dated the 29th June. We had a conference at the Foreign Office on the 3rd July at which Sir G. Roos-Ktppel, Mr. Merk, Colonel Malleson and Mr. Holland (Political Agent at Maskat) were present Yesterday’s mail brought a despatch from Sir A. Hardinge to Sir E. Grey, dated 3rd May, which I place in the file. There was never, I think, any real prospect of an agreement with France, for the bulk of the arms trade is in the hands of Belgians and Belgian financiers rule at Paris. The alternative courses of action described by Sir A. Hardinge, viz., (a) to sulk and (b) to take the crumbs gladly, trying to extend the zone of prohibition along the Arabian coast as far as the South of Oman, need not be considered here.7 We are unanimously and strongly of opinion that, the Arms Conference having failed so far as India is concerned, vigorous action must be taken in order to cope with a political movement (for it is nothing else) which has already upset the balance of power on our frontier and is now a grave obstacle to the maintenance of peace. Mr. Merk thinks that, whereas hitherto the worse armed tribes have been afraid to co operate with the better armed tribes, there is now a danger of combination as a result ot uniform armament with good rifles. In Afghanistan a serious situation is growing up, tor the people are now armed and the revenues are not coming in. Fiscal pressure might well precipitate trouble. The exact number of rifles which are imported into Maskat and exported thence to the Mekran coast cann-.t be ascertained. The figures of the Intelligence Branch (the best available) show the following trade paying custom duties:— Exported to Year. Imported into Maskat. Mekran. Koweit. Elsewhere. 1906 40,000 3,175 13,500 1,200 1907 60,000 11,247 14,500 1908 78,825 25,600 (For six months only.) 5,350 150 Ammunition imported into Maskat. ... 9,300,000 ... 14,520,000 ... 19,198,900 A considerable business is done by the Sultan's officials sub rosa ; and the destination of the arms is often wrongly shown. The price of rifles has already fallen on our frontier more than 50%. Afghanistan and independent territory are now armed to the teeth. There is abundance of ammunition. At Kharlachi the other 'day an incessant musketry fire was kept up for two days. In the Tirah campaign the Afridis had not more than 10 or 15 rounds per man. It is no longer possible to disarm our tribesmen. But action might be taken— (a) At the Afghan end ; (b) At the Maskat end; (c) On the Mekran coast and in Persia. (a) Last year the Secretary of State suggested that we should regularise the supply of e 4 . rwrvko. iqcr Knc s 9 *, 230 arms to the Amir. It would be useless to at- Pro No. 230 in Secret F., October 1908, iNos. . mu a • • i • uu ^ j Pro. No. 452 in Secret F„ December 1907, Nos. 378- tempt this. The Amir is deep in the trade 484 . ’ himself. He considers that he is within his lights, and greatly resented our interference with the gun-runners at the Kacha Gorge. (b) Mr. Holland wishes us to come to some arrangement with the Sultan of Maskat now or shortly Major Cox gives weighty reasons against such action. I think Mr. Holland takes an altogether too sanguine view of the probability of the Sultan's working loyally with us throne is none to secure, and he cannot aSord to alienate powerful interests. An agreement with the Sultan at this stage would, I think, raise more difficulties than it would settle and would almost certainly involve trouble with the French, and it might be ineffectual. The trade could move from Maskat. Arms could be transhipped to dhows on the high seas I would certainly not advise any reliance on the Sultan, at any rate until we have shown that we can hinder the trade. We shall then be in a position to make terms with some reasonable prospect of permanence. (o) We can expect no help from the Persian authorities. Now that the Russians are a-arrisonino- Northern Persia, one of the objections to our operating with our troops in Southern “ . Pr „ K„ B 205 , 206 .Dd 219 in Secret E., FeW, 1’ers.a has boon removed. This was recom- loot) Nos 188-242. mended* last year by Sir H. McMahon and Maior Cox. But I do not think that His Majesty's Government would allow us to use troops on Persian soil at present, and it seems premature to c insider the question. For the next few weeks may' see fresh developments of the Persian muddle. The country is at present in a state of chaos and it is not yet clear how order is t &gt; be restored. Possibly in the means employed to restore order, we may have an instn ment which can be used against the Afghan gun-runners.s We agree that for the present we should confine ourselves to naval activity adopting the proposals of the Admiral [vide paragraph 9 of Mr. Reynolds* note) with one important modi fication, viz., that the blockade should be maintained for a full year. Arms are now sent over weekly and stored on the Mekran coast until the Afghan caravans come down. We also advise that an officer of the Intelligence Branch be attached to the detachment at Jask with a view to organise a regular system of intelligence ; and that Mr. Gregson of the North-West Frontier Police be put on special duty to work between the frontier and Karachi. He has special knowledge. He, of course, would be in close communication with the officer at Jask. Much can be done to make the trade more difficult and dangerous. Many of the men who own the caravans are financed by the bankers of Dera Ismail Khan district and come down through that place to Karachi. There is reason to hope that the gun-running business will languish if an effective blockade is kept up for a year. The business is sensitive and it is run with borrowed money. For this reason the more and the sooner we advertise that we are going to have a naval blockade the better. It can be considered later, in communication with the Minister at Tehran, whether a garrison should be placed again at Robat, and, if so, in what strength. Perhaps it will be sufficient to withdraw the telegraph officer from Dehaneh. The case may go, in the first instance, to the Army Department. The Foreign Depart ment and our two greatest frontier experts consider the position to be so grave, and to be full of so much danger in the future, that any expenditure incurred now to prevent the situation developing further will be in the nature of insurance against larger expenditure. We thinfc that there is still time to take effectual preventive action. Had we been able to come to terms with France such action could have been taken at a smaller cost. We waited in this hope. Action should no longer be delayed. It would seem desirable to address the Secretary of State by telegram. S. H. Butler, —5-7-09. Army Department (Confidential). Memorandum showing the papers forwarded to the India Office with the Foreign Secretary^ letter No. 28 M., dated the 8th July 1909. The Chief of Staff’s Division may see with reference to General Mullaly’s note, dated the 4th June 1909, in Marine Department B, July 19U9, Nos. 1263-1264. S. C. B.,—8-7-09. Secretary has seen. E. W. S. K. Maconchy,—8-7-09. Chief of the Staff's Division.'''T* I I have added to the file two pamphlets which give our latest information on the Masqat Arms Traffic. These should be read, as they throw considerable light on the methods and procedure of those engaged in the traffic. I think that, with one possible exception which I will refer to later, we may agree throughout with Mr. Butler's note of 5th July 1909, which summarises the opinion arrived at, after very full discussion, by the informal Committee on the subject which met at the Foreign Office last week. In his third paragraph, page 11 of the notes, the Foreign Secretary describes this question as “a political movement which has already upset the balance of power on the frontier and is now a grave obstacle to the maintenance of peace.” We may certainly endorse this view, but at the same time it is necessary to point out that this problem is something more than merely political. The arms traffic, as it has existed during the last five or six years, means simply this—that we are confronted on and beyond our North-West Frontier with a serious and threatening military situation which every month becomes more formidable ; which has already compelled us to reconsider certain strategical measures ; and which, if not shortly checked, may be expected to become so minatory a danger as to compel us still further to readjust much of the existing scheme of military policy and organisation. In any communication, therefore, which the Government of India may make to the Secretary of State on the subject I think great emphasis should be laid on the grave military risks which the continuance of the traffic involves. It seems desirable here briefly to place on record the nature and extent of those risks, lest it be said hereafter that we were blind to the dangers so quickly growing up around us. To take first the case of Afghanistan. The present Amir has, beyond doubt, deliberately reversed the policy of his father which, as he so constantly boasts, has been his guiding star in almost every other respect. Not only did Abdurrahman forcibly disarm large communities of his subjects, but he dis couraged the acquisition of modern arms by the remainder, and did not even issue efficient rifles to his regular troops, preferring to keep them stored in his arsenals. The present Amir, though he cannot fail to be aware of the serious risks he runs in pursuing such a policy, has not only rearmed with modern weapons his regular troops and khassadars, but deliberately encourages the arms traffic, even to the extent of financing it to large amounts. Moreover he causes it to be made known far and wide that arms are procurable at Kabul and elsewhere, that he wishes his subjects to acquire them, and that, if necessary, loans may be given to respectable persons in order to buy arms. The imports of arms, too, in a period of falling revenue and acute financial stringency, are allowed to come in free of duty. It is inconceivable that the Amir can deliberately have ignored the obvious dangers of this policy. Presumably, therefore, these were fully weighed and the policy only embarked on because the ends to be gained were, in the opinion of the Amir and his advisers, even greater than the undoubted risks run. What precisely was the motive which told so greatly with the Amir it is difficult to say. But it is at least significant that the direct official encouragement of the Afghan arms traffic seems to have synch ronised with the Anglo-Russian Convention regarding Afghanistan. We have had numerous reports regarding the distrust and suspicion with which that instru ment was looked upon in Afghanistan, and there seems to have been a pretty general opinion that the Convention was but the prelude to a division of the Amir’s dominions between Great Britain and Russia. It seems a fair inference, therefore, that the Amir, convinced that before long a life and death struggle with one or both of his powerful neighbours was inevitable, with premeditation set about the wholesale armament of his subjects on a plan which, from his point of view, was a very economical one, and trusted to the cry of which now-a- days is more extensively preached than ever throughout Afghanistan—to weld together against a common and infidel foe the many discordant elements over which he rules. What are the practical dangers which confront us owing to this deliberate change in Afghan policy ? In the first place l think we may put internal rebel lion, leading to anarchy, and thus necessitating our forcible intervention in Afghan affairs. There is at the present time the greatest discontent amongst vast2 communities In Afghanistan, and the possession of efficient weapons may at any time encourage them to rise in arms against the corrupt and incom petent officials who represent the Amir’s Government. Perhaps the one means the Amir would be able successfully to employ in order to extinguish a conflagration of this sort would be an order for general which, as already pointed &amp; out, is being assiduously preached by the mullas in almost all the provinces. Then, again, the possession of modern arms by Afghan subjects residing near our border has undoubtedly encouraged them to commit raids and outrages on a more formidable and frequent scale, and each one of such carries in it the germ of a possibly very strained situation with Afghanistan. As regards the country on our side of the Durand line the case has been well put by Sir George Roos-Keppel in his last Administration Report. A moment s reflection should suffice to impress us with * Redsh P- the very serious character of the danger by which we are confronted within our owm frontier. In 1897-98 we found it neces sary to mobilise close on 70,000 men. Yet to-day the tribes, in the Chief Commis sioner’s opinion, are perhaps ten times better armed than in those years, and have, moreover, an extremely abundant supply of ammunition. I may mention that the returns for this year giving the armament of our frontier tribes show an increase over last year’s returns of some 26,000 rifles, quite apart from the increase in Swat and Bajaur, the figures for which have not yet been received, though in February last Colonel Godfrey estimated that “ thousands ” of arms had come into that area in the previous twelve months.f Undoubtedly our means of correct ly ascertaining the real extent of the increase and improvement in armament of our frontier tribes are most inadequate. We depend entirely on political sources for this information, and political officers are the first to admit the very approximate accuracy of the information supplied. From the Masqat figures, however, it would appear quite possible that anything from 50,000 to 100,000 rifles have been absorbed on our North-West Frontier within the last three years. And now that the frontier tribes themselves have embarked directly in the trade—which is what all our most recent and reliable information shows—we may confidently expect that, unless the traffic is severely checked, the process of rearmament, with ever more modern and formidable weapons, will proceed apace. Undoubtedly, therefore, one may correctly summarise the case by saying that a grave military danger is growing up before our eyes ; that already it has attained to very serious proportions ; and that almost any reasonable measures and expenditure, having for their aim the suppression of this traffic, would, as being in the long run most economical, be amply justified. Accordingly I think this Division may strongly support the proposalsj of + c ,, , His Excellency the Naval Commander in J Flag “Z 1 below. • c 11 r-»i&gt; Chief, extended as in Mr. Butlers note. There remains the further point which I have alluded to in the beginning of the second paragraph of this note. In his sub-paragraph (c), page 14 of the notes, Mr. Butler has discussed the possibility of land action on Persian soil by British troops. This, of course, is mainly a political question. But it is for considera tion whether it might not be advisable to put it to the Secretary of State whether the recent action of Russia in Northern Persia would not justify our now sending troops to Persian Makran, not for purposes of permanent occupation, but solely with an eye to the suppression of the arms traffic. At any rate, whether the political objections to such a course may be adjudged insuperable or not, there can be no doubt whatever that from the point of view of sheer efficiency such land action is eminently desirable, and consequently is worthy of the most serious consideration. All our latest information is to the effect that throughout this summer arms have constantly been conveyed across to the Makran coast, where they are stored and taken charge of by the Baluch sardars interested in the traffic pending the arrival of the Afghan caravans in the cold weather. Obviously naval action, no matter on how extended a scale, t These figures have now been obtained from Major Rawlinson. They indicate an increase in arms in the Dir, Swat, and Bajaur, Agency of no less than 33 , 500 , of which 16,500 are said to be Martinis. This is probably the increase of more than 12 months, the returns hitherto sent us by Colonel Godfrey having been somewhat perfunc tory. The total reported increase this year is consequently about 60,000 rifles. W. Malleson,— je-y-og.G. C. fe.lt*., Simla.—No. C 5 $I. B.-j 6.7-09.-50.~E.A.D*S. 3 cannot touch these arms, which will probably number many thousands by the autumn. If we were to take land action before the arrival in any numbers of the Afghans we should probably be able to make so large a haul as seriously to crip ple the trade. Probably three small columns, equally divided along the length of coast between Gwatar and Minab, and making a simultaneous sweeping movement over a belt of territory extending to, say, twenty miles from the coast, would suffice for the purpose, and the opposition to be met with would, from what information we possess, almost certainly be very slight. But such a move ment, to be effective, should not be delayed later than the beginning of September, by which time, also, the naval blockade should be fully established and continue for a full year. We shall, of course, be prepared to undertake all the intelligence work on the Masqat and Makran side, and for this purpose I would suggest that Major Austin, C.M.G., D.S.O., be employed. W. Malleson,— 10-7-09. p. fb .Foreign Office Prow— No. 572-27.7*09—21. Gulf a naval blockade of the Mekran coast is impossible. The Admiral certainly does not think it so. Mr. Reynolds^ note, 29th June 1909, clearly explains the position, and Colonel Malleson indicates very truly and forcibly the military risks we run in the constantly increasing armanent of the warlike populations on our frontier. We are undoubtedly called upon to press our views again most seriously on His Majesty's Government: there is ample material for a despatch in Mr. Reynolds' and Colonel Malleson's notes. In the meantime, I should be glad to know what has become of the rumoured exchange with France of territory on the Gambia for advantages to be given to us at Maskat. I was under the impression that some such proposal was contingent on the result of the Brussels Conference. Also has anything further been heard of negotiations with France in respect to her “ logos ' in India. I had hoped that these questions might perhaps have favourably influenced, our relations with her in Maskat. The papers should be circulated and the drafting of a despatch commenced at once. M[into], —25-7-09.12 1 entirely agree with Mr. Butler's note of 5th July 1909, as regards the gravity of the situation, but I am not in entire accord with him as to the policy which we should adopt in order to meet it. If we are permanently to put a stop to the arms traffic, I believe that Maskat and Maskat alone is the point at which we must aim. I do not believe that the naval measures which are proposed, or even military measures on the Mekran coast (in the unlikely event of the latter being permitted), would have any permanent effect. A few dhows might be captured, a few caravans might be broken up—and more than this we cannot expect—but the profits of the trade are too large for this to do more than to diminish its volume temporarily. Before Zanzibar came under our protectorate, the Navy made great efforts to suppress slave running by hunting down and capturing the dhows engaged in that traffic. The results attained showed how little effect could be effected in that way. Once our protectorate was established all this was changed, and for practical purposes slave running came to an end. In my opinion, we shall never stop the arms traffic until Maskat and its Sultan are brought definitely under our sole control. India's vital interests—even her safety—are involved in the solution of the problem, and I think it will be much to our interest to buy up all French rights in Maskat. It should not be beyond the resources of diplomacy to ascertain what value France places on these rights, and it would be well worth India's while to purchase them at the cost of a cession of territory adjoining Pondicherry and thus gain freedom to take action at the head-quarters of the arms traffic—Maskat. I do not think that we need entertain any serious fears of the transfer of that head-quarters to any other part of the coast, or of the trans-shipping of arms to dhows on the high seas which is not an easy transaction or one which any ship-owners would willingly undertake. Should the policy I have indicated be considered seriously it might be advisable at the same time to take over the small French possessions which exist in various parts of India other than Pondicherry, ceding territory enough in that neighbourhood to compensate for them all. In this way less prominence would be given to the Maskat transaction. In view of the existence of the “ the present time would seem to be favourable for such diplomatic action. I am convinced that there is no other course open to us which gives any hope of a really satisfactory and permanent solution of this question. K[itchbner], —19-7-09. I am aware that the Americans have always had a certain historical interest in Maskat, but this could be easily discounted as it was at Zanzibar. K[itchenbr],— Army Department. B. Duff,— 19-7-09. R. Scallon,— 20-7-09. Foreign Department. As considerable expenditure is involved, Finance Department should see. But His Excellency the Viceroy should see at this stage. With reference to His Excellency the Commander-iu-Chief's note I may venture to agree that, if the French are to be bought out, India must pay. The Home Government will not be a party to compensation in territory as recent $pcret negotiations have shown. It is for consi deration whether compensation should be given by cession of British Indian territory before other methods have been tried and failed. The military authorities advocate the employment of land forces, if possible. It is the employment of Russian troops in Northern Persia which has made the Russians so unpopular in Persia and I doubt whether His Majesty's Government would a^ree to this. The cmrse might be recommended subject to the exigencies of the general political situation in Persia; but reliance should be placed perhaps on naval action. What the cost will be only the Admiralty can say. Finance Department may see and the case may then be circulated to Council ? S. H. Butler, —22-7-09. It is impossible to overrate the dangerous importance of the importation of arms into Afghanistan, and the tribal territory on our frontiers. I have repeatedly pressed it on the Secretary of State. No doubt as His Excellency the Commander-in-Chief maintains, the most efficient check to this arms traffic would be fuuud in our control of Maskat, but I doubt the possibility of our obtaining it, and even for the sake of doing so I should be opposed to any cession of territory to France in the neighbourhood of Pondicherry unless we received some quid pro quo in India such as the cession to us of Chandernagore. Also in view of Admiral Slade's report it appears to be far from certain that with an increased naval strength in theu The negotiations as to Gambia and the loges have fallen through. Papers should he • Now in General Branch. submitted* separately to His Excellency, t Draft despatch ia being prepared by Deputy Meanwhile circulate to Hon'ble Members and Secretary (F.). startf on preparation of a despatch. S. H. Butler, —29-7-09. Circulated,—3 0-7 -09. Kitchener], —31-7-09. H. A[damson], —31-7-09. • v ■ S. P. S[inha], —31-7-09. Seen. I understand that it is not proposed to land troops on the Makran Coast. J. O. M[iller], —31-7-09. I am afraid it is a case of ' shutting the stable door ” a bit late. G. F. W[ilson],— 31-7-09. Seen. “W. L. H[arvey], —31-7-09. Letter from H. Whitby Smith, Esq., Director, Persian Gulf Telegraphs, No. 431 P., DATED THE 19TH (RECEIVED 21st) JULY 1909. Forwards a report hy Mr. New on the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf for the period from the 1st January to the 30th June 1909. Telegram from His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, dated the 29th (received 30th) July 1909. Enquires whether the Government of India have any proposals to offer in connection with the suggestions of Major Cox and Admiral Slade regarding the suppression of the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf. Letter from Major P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 1775, dated the 25th July (received 2nd August) 1909. Communicates his views in regard to the proposal made by the Political Agent y 3Iaskat, to subsidise the Sultan of Maskat in order to obtain his co-operation in stopping the illicit traffic in arms. I put up a draft despatch for approval. When approved, a telegram summarising the despatch will be prepared in reply to the Secretary of State's telegram of 29th July. L. W. Reynolds, — 5-8-09. Please let me have clean proof of the draft and put up the letter referred to at the end. S. H. Butler,— 7-8-09. I have made a suggested addition as regards the establishment of a wireless station at Jask. The position as regards the scheme for the erection of wireless stations for strate gical purposes is, so far as I can make out, briefly that we recommended the establishment of a station at Hen jam or Jask in connection with the general scheme and pressed for its early erection. The Finance Department agree as to the desirability of the scheme, but say that it cannot be carried out until funds permit. They further suggest that We must therefore press for the Jask installation the internal scheme should take precedence of apart from the general scheme into which it will subse- the external scheme, an opinion in which I be- quentJy fit. lieve the Chief of the Staff concurs. L. W. Bkynoi-ds. I think there can be no question (unless there are technical reasons for preferring Henjam) that Jask is the more suitable position. We already have a telegraph station and a guard there, and it would not raise questions with Persia. L. W. Reynolds,— 9-8-09.15 (1) Please get clean proof and (2) put up the letter about the logex which I asked for before. I do not see it. (3) Send duplicates of proof to (a) Commerce and Industry Depart- ment, and (i) Chief of the Staff’s Division asking (a) if there is any objection to the remarks about Jask ; (i) if they have any modifications to suggest. S. H. Butleb,—10-8-09. Extract from a demi-official letter from Colonel Mallexon to Deputy Secretary (F.), dated the 12th August 1909. I am desired to ask that, should there be no objection, we may be supplied with the following (1) Three copies of the notes on the Maskat arms traffic, so far as they have been printed at present, and with three copies subsequently of the additional notes on the same subject, and of the despatch in its final form. ******** I am returning you herewith the draft despatch on the arms traffic. You will see that our view is that we should place before the Secretary of State the best means of crippling the trade and let him decide how much of it he will sanction. If this idea be accepted some slight alteration will be necessary in the wording at the beginning of your paragraph 15, but I have not thought it necessary to suggest anything in the notes as regards this. Division of the Chief of the Staff. I have made a trifling red ink addition on page 2 of the despatch. I think we may concur in the despatch, with the exception of paragraph 14, which }■ think should be modified. As it stands it practically dismisses the proposal put forward in this Division to endeavour to capture the arms now stored on the Makran Coast as being outsid 6 the pale of practical politics. I do not think this part of the scheme should be gratuitously condemned in advance. It would be preferable to put the advantages of such action before the Secretary of State and leave it to him to say whether it is feasible or not. Moreover, the draft despatch speaks of military operations on a large scale on the Persian Coast. This would certainly frighten the India and Foreign Offices, and quite unnecessarily, since, so far as our information goes, the operations in question need only be on a small scale. Accordingly, the following, or something to the same effect, is suggested for consider ation :— 14. “ The possible courses that remain are military action on the Persian Coast, a naval blockade, or a combination of the two. There can be no doubt in our opinion that, from the point of view of dealing a severe and perhaps final blow to the arms traffic, combined naval and military action is desirable. All our more recent information goes to prove that the tactics of the arms-dealers have changed during the current year in one very important respect. Formerly it was their custom to await the arrival in Maskat during the winter months of the Afghan and frontier purchasers. The busy gun-running season was thus the period from January to April, or thereabouts, mentioned in the despatch of His Excellency the Naval Commander-in- Chief. The more recent Maskat practice, however, is to ship arms across to the Makran Coast steadily week by week throughout the summer months. Such arms are then stored by the Baluch Sardars interested in the traffic on or near the coast pending the arrival of the Afghan caravans in the winter months. Obviously a future naval blockade, however vigorously enforced, cannot affect these arms, which by now may number several thousands. Our military advisers are of opinion that it should be possible, by a sweeping movement over a zone extending to perhaps 20 miles from the coast, to secure a large number of these stored weapons with but slight resistance on the part of the Baluch Sardars, and that for this purpose a small force should suffice. We need hardly point out that such action, if successful, would have a far-reaching effect on the traffic, which is one of a peculiarly sensitive character inas much as it is mainly carried on by poor men on borrowed capital. Heavy captures, occurring at the beginning of the winter arms season, might not improbably have the immediate result of seriously crippling the trade. We are aware, of course, of the possible political objections to the landing of Indian troops on the Persian littoral. Your Lordship will be able to say whether recent events in Northern Persia and the threatened security of our Consulates at Kerman and elsewhere may not materially have modified the position. In any case we feel it our duty to state that to ensure the most complete measure of success, some such land action seems desirable should the political objections to such a course not be insuperableFote^n Office Prua—No. 680«»14.8*0y—80, 16 In any case I think the delicate financial status of the arms traffic should be prominently brought to the notice of the Secretary of State, since an appreciation of this may convince him that a single year’s sustained effort might go far towards strangling the trade. W. Malleson, —12-8-09. H. Mullaly,— 12-8-09. B. Duff,— 12-8-09* Department of Commerce and Industry. The original file about the establishment of coast wireless stations has, it is understood, been passed on to Foreign Department. Finance Department has demurrred to the expend iture involved and suggested for first consideration the establishment of inland stations. This Department had agreed to the establishment of the coast stations recommended by Army and Foreign Departments, and has no objection to the present draft despatch. B. Robertson, —12-8-09. Foreign Department. (1) I see no objection to the substitntion of the parairraph proposed in Colonel Malleson’s I tl,»««,» .held to substituted, but am not note of 12th August 1909 for the present para- sure that it has been accepted. graph 14 of the despatch. S. H. Butlee. (2) I think we should perhaps lay a little more stress on the necessity for early action as 1 bare added a word or two. every month adds to the supply of arms. I S. H. Btttleb. would therefore say m paragraph i b iiine o) “ and that it is of the utmost importance that measures for its establishment should be taken with the least possible delay (3) As regards the wireless installation at Task in the case on the subject of the installa tion of wireless telegraphy for strategic purposes, the Finance Department and the Division of the Chief of the Staff have expressed the view that an internal scheme of communications should take precedence of the external. The installation at Jask, though it will eventually tall in with the general scheme, will, I imagine, be considered solely on its merits as a portion ot the present plan for a naval blockade. To omit it would jeopardise the success of the whole plan. I may point out that though the present ease has been circulated, it has not yet been seen in the Finance Department. L. W. Reynolds, —13-8-09. The despatch is now ready for His Excellency’s approval. It has been seen in the Chief of the Staff’s Division, and by Commerce and Industry Department. Before being circulated it may be sent to Finance Department marked ‘‘Immediate”. We have no idea what the cost will be, but the matter is one of high Imperial necessity. The substance of the despatch, as finally approved, may be telegraphed to the Secretary of State. .n o Ara S. H. Butler, —13-8-09.{Confidential.) MEMORANDUM. 1. The Secretary of State’s telegram, dated 17th May, appears to indicate that circum stances will not, in the near future, permit of the conclusion of a new Treaty with the Sultan of Maskat for the prevention of the import of arms into Oman. Should the matter seem likely to arise a«-ain, at any time, in a practical form* I should be glad of an opportunity for making suggestions, if they are wanted, as to the conditions which it would be desirable to try and get inserted in such a Treaty. 2. In default of measures for the prevention of import, His Majesty^ Government will now, perhaps, decide to take vigorous action, in accordance with the suggestions which have already been made, for the prevention of the export of arms from Maskat to the Mekran Coast. If so, it will become necessary to consider the probable effect of such action on our relations with His Highness the Sultan. 3. There can be no doubt that an abrupt stoppage of the export would have a prejudicial effect on those relations, since, in the first place, the Sultan would soon lose a large portion of the revenue which he now gets from the arms traffic and he would naturally feel a grievance against us on this account. In the second place, in order to retain our friendship, he would be compelled to incur the enmity of all the powerful private bodies interested in the arms traffic. If he failed to back up the claims of his own subjects, they would be exasperated at the idea that their rights were being sacrificed tamely by their ruler, and he would feel that his chances of assassination, of which he is always apprehensive, were gravely increased. Foreigners, like M. Goguyer, would call upon the Sultan who has been their sleeping partner for so long, to take an active part in the defence of the industry, and if he failed td comply, they would intrigue against him locally and would incite the Afghans to threaten him. 4-. In the third place, the Sultan would be exposed to diplomatic pressure from the foreign Powers interested in the arms traffic. The French Government having no longer so much inducement to remain neutral, would probably instruct their Consul to protect vigorously the interests of French arms merchants which would be injured by our aggressive action, and the Consul would, doubtless, renew con amore the tactics of past years by which our relations with His Highness have frequently been embarrassed. The German Government which would probably be appealed to by the Hamburg firms might conceivably regard the estrangement between the Sultan and ourselves as a favourable ^opportunity for securing His Highness's signature to a Commercial Treaty and his consent to the appointment of a German Consul at Maskat. Our important political interests in this part of the world might thus be seriously jeopardised in consequence of our efforts to suppress the arms trade. 5. Our position at Maskat is, however, very strong at present, and although the game would be somewhat risky, I think that we could probably contend, even with no other weapons than we now possess, against any adverse influences that could be brought to bear on us there. The chief object of the Sultan's policy is to remain on good terms with us at all costs, and rather than forfeit our friendship, he would submit to a heavy loss of revenue, would endure unpopularity among his own subjects and would reject alike the threats and offers of other Powers. His relations with the inland tribes render his throne somewhat shaky, and he holds fast to the belief that, so long as he acts squarely by the British Government in important matters, they will protect him from attack. His great desire now is for a quiet life, and he is anxious to avoid entanglements with foreign Powers, firstly, because they would lead to a quarrel with us, and, secondly, because he fears that foreign agents would intrigue against him with the inland tribes, if they once gained a footing in his country. 6. On the other hand, it is just possible that the Sultan, irritated by the loss of revenue and exposed to powerful pressure on all sides, might be driven into an attitude of hostility to us. If so, he might embroil us with the French, and possibly with the German Government, and a dangerous situation might be created. It is perhaps worth while considering whether, with a view to lessen this danger, we could now enter into any arrangement with the Sultan which would have the effect, on the one hand, of strengthening his position against internal and external intrigues, and on the other hand, of attaching him firmly to our interests in the matter. 7. The first expedient which suggests itself is the grant of substantial compensation to H is Highness for the loss of his revenue from the arms traffic. This would not only render him favourably disposed towards our measures, but would efiable him to placate pecuniarily those of bis own subjects who were most clamorous about their losses, and to combat internal intrigues. It is suggested in the Memorandum, dated 22nd July 1908, by the British Plenipoten tiaries to the Brussels Conference that the French might object, under the terms of the Joint Declaration of 1862, to any increase being made in the subsidy given by us to His Highness.^*T' 2 The Frencli Government were, however, probably not consulted when we guaranteed the payment of the subsidy to Saiyid Turki, in 1873, subject to certain conditions, and it will perhaps be considered that the grant of a further sum to Saiyid Feysal, as compensation f«&lt;r the loss of income of which we indirectly deprive him, would not be an infringement of his independence. In return for the increased subsidy, we should, in the first place, expect His Highness to give us such assistance as might be possible in enforcing the terms of his Notification and Proclamation of 1898, prohibiting the export of arms to India and Persia. The French Gov ernment did not object to the promulgation of these declarations, and they could hardly object to the Sultan taking some measures to enforce them. I am convinced that His Highness could give us considerable assistance in this mattei*, if it were made worth his while to do so. 8. In the second place, the possibility of German intrigue would be almost excluded, if we could get the Sultan, as part of the consideration for the increased subsidy, to undertake for himself and his successors, never to conclude a Treaty with any other Power than those with which he is now in treaty relations, and never to consent to the appointment of Consular or diplomatic officers at Maskat by such Powers. It would be difficult to deny that the conclusion of such an agreement with the Sultan would amount, technically, to an infringement of his independence, since it would limit his treaty-making power which is one of the rights of a sovereign ruler. As a matter of fact, however, we have always regarded the joint Declaration of 1862 as guaranteeing to the Sultan the right to administer his own country freely, and not as referring to his external relations with foreign Powers. So small and weak a State cannot possibly be independent as regards its external relations and must hang upon some great Power. By virtue of our paramount position in Maskat and the Persian Gulf we are compelled to exercise what is to all intents and purposes a Protectorate over Maskat, so far as the Sultanas relations with foreign Powers are concerned. As instances of this, it is only necessary to point to the Agreement of 1891, by which the Sultan undertook never to sell or cede any territory to a foreign Power other than the British Government, and to our intimation to His Highness in 1895, to the effect that His Majesty's Government would not, in future, permit any attack upon Maskat or Matrah. In both these cases it might have Wh contended by the French Government that the spirit of the Declara tion of 1862 had Peed infringed, but so far as I am aware, they did not do so. It will perhaps be thought that the arrangement now proposed would differ very little in character from that of 1891, and the Ireneh Government wmuld be the less lixely to object to it, since it would not, in any way, affe^fceir Treaty relations with the Sultan. Further, it is probable, in any case, that local frictpPwill arise at Maskat with the French authorities, after the failure of the Brussels negotiations, if we take steps to suppress the Mekran arms traffic, and a slight additional cause of annoyance would, perhaps, not matter much. 9. The Sultan would, I am sure, dislike making any arrangement with us as regards the arms traffic which did not cover the prohibition of import by the consent of the Powers concerned, and the provision of compensation for merchants. When, however, he found that we were taking effective measures to stop the Mekran traffic, I think he would see that it was to his advantage to accept our offer. In order to make the agreement more palatable . to His Highness, it would perhaps be worth while to reiterate formally in it the assurance given, in 1895, of our intention, for the future, to prevent attacks upon Maskat and Mutrah. This assurance goes a long way in the direction of a dynastic guarantee, which it is one of His Highness's ambitions to obtain from us. If it were possible to include in the agreement a declaration similar to that in the Koweit agreement, to the effect that we have no desire to interfere in the Sultan's internal adminis tration, I believe it would be very gratifying to him, and it might also be useful in subsequent discussions with the French Government as an evidence of our determination to resnect the Declaration of 1862, R. E. Holland,—27-6-09, * Foreign Office Press No. 395—29-6*09—-20. \</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100049434208.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/289/B</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100049434208.0x000002</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/289/B</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Foreign Department Notes. Arms Traffic in the Persian Gulf.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1909</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-03T10:04:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (11 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 11; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: this part also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Printed copies of correspondence and memoranda relating to the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf:a letter from Leonard William Reynolds of the Government of India, dated 29 June 1909 (ff 2-3)a confidential letter from the British Minister to Belgium, Arthur Henry Hardinge, to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Edward Grey, dated 3 May 1909 (f 4)a letter from the Political Agent at Maskat [Muscat], Robert Erskine Holland, dated 5 July 1909 (ff 4-5)a memorandum written by Wilfrid Malleson of the Intelligence Branch, Indian Army Headquarters, dated 10 July 1909, also signed by the Officiating Chief of Staff in India, Herbert Mullaly, and the Chief of Staff in India, Beauchamp Duff (ff 6-7)further copies of correspondence signed by Malleson, Mullaly, Duff, and others including the Commander-in-Chief in India, Horatio Herbert Kitchener, and the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Spencer Harcourt Butler (ff 8-10)a confidential memorandum written by Robert Erskine Holland, dated 27 June 1909 (f 11)</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Weapons</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade routes</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arms traffic</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100049434208.0x000002#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>