<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002b9_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T11:14:33.775Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ U ^o . PART I. - 0j2 ca.. CON Fl DEN '7? PERSIAN GULF GAZETTEER. Historical and Political Materials. MASKAT TERRITORY. PAGES. A.—Events in Oman ... ... ... 1 to 20 B.—Events in Gwadur ... 21 to 30 C.—Events in Dhofar 31 to 42 D.—Events in Zanzibar 43 to 52 E.—British Policy in Maskat 53 to 72 F.—Zanzibar Subsidy and British Loans to Maskat ... 73 to 82 G.—Protection of British subjects in Maskat 83 to 94 H.— British Extra-Territorial Jurisdiction in Maskat 95 to 104 I.— British Government Establishments and Property in Maskat lu5 to 112 J,— Trade and Customs in Maskat 113 to 124 K.—Sanitary Matters in Maskat 125 to 134 in the sentence which they follow. ' Resident ' means the British Resident iu the Persian Gulf, and ' Agent the British Political Age n t at Maskat.Lo. confidential: A—EVENTS IN OMAN. 1873. Sultan left Maskat on 4th February in his corvette ' Rahmani ' to escape Bakri Id expenses. Maawal tribe dealinEr with Ibrahim bin Kais at Sohar and inviting him to attack Burka. Dismissed Minister, Thoweynee, not yet re placed (8-2). Faisal bin Hamud of Rostak, favourite of religious party, re ceived his cousin Ibrahim, bin Kais, rebel, at Eostak, and concerted with him (8-3). Ibrahim visited El Hazam possession of Faisal bia Hamud. Sultan embarked on 4th July to attack Sohar. Body of Wahabi guard preceded him and Debai and Umm-ul-Kawain promised to help. S. Oman tranquil, but Harthi chief Salih bin Ali threatening to attack Maskat if Sultan went to Sohar. Uneasiness at Abdul Aziz's presence on Mekran coast (3 -7). Saiyid Salim bin Thoweynee and Abdul Aziz offered 300 dollars each monthly to reside in British territory and not interfere in Maskat affairs '6-7). Naim, marching to join Sultan before Sohar, plundered Saham in passing (10-7). Sohar surrendered (20-7). Tliovveynee bin Muhammad, ex-Minister, murdered on 13th August (15-8). Ihoweynee bin Muhammad killed by Seedee slave of Saiyid Nasir bin Ali, whose murder Thoweynee instigated. First instance of one of A1 Bu Saidi slain by slave or even member of another family (21-8). Saleh bin Ali, intending to attack Maskat, sent A1 ahibeh Bedouins who encampBd outside Matra ; but, on their passing* Semail, Nedabiyin Ghafiris closed Wadi Al Akk and Saliu could not get through. (Wadis Dheykah and Akk—2 of 3^ leading from Sharkiya to Semail and Maskat-ave held by Ghafiris : 3rd is TV adi Beni Uuwaybeh. AV adi Akk principal and most traversed ; it has narrow precipitous defi'o). Hinawi combination broke up and Salih returned disappoint ed to Ibra. Al Wahibeh took presents from Sultan and returned (22-8). Ibrahim bin Kais retired to Hibi village 20 miles from coast. Sultan for first time in full possesion of whole N. E. sea-board. 300 men and 2 guns sent to Gwadur which besieged by Abdul Aziz (28-8). Powerful Hinawi tribe of Heni Kuweyeh came in on favourable conditions (5-9). Bedouins made Sultan s marriage excuse to flock into M]askat and obtain large presents of food and money. Two Turkish men-of-war from Basra for Hodeida with 1,500 troops for army of Yemen called at Maskat (17-10). About 12th September Mockler captured Abdul Aziz on high seas near Sur. Arranged he should live at Karachi and receive $ 300 a month from Zanzibar subsidy; he had formerly declined 600 (15-li). Saiyid Salim escaped from Gwadur when called on by Assistant Political Agent to surrender. Sultan would inquire how fort at Gwadur so easily captured ^23-12). 1871. On false rumour of Sultan s denth Saleh bin Ali, TTarthi, arrived morning of 17th January at Rui village on way to attack Miskat, having failed to pass through Akk and traversed Kahza instead. Letters sent by him to Ibrahim fortunately intercepted by Wali of Burka. Sultan taken by surprise sent Badr bin Saif and Wahabis, but rebels defeated them, killing 76, mostly in retreat to Matra. Citadel and fort commanding Matra held^out.' Wahibeh, Haboos, Hejrieen, Ilarthi and few Beni Ruweyeh were with Saleh, in all 00.' Political Agent offered to honour Sultan's drafts up to Rs. 40,000 against subsidy. Khoja fort with British flag respected ; Banvans and Khoias elsewhere looted to extent $4,000. Government on 20th January ordered Resident to proceed Maskat and after inquiry into facts demand from rebels holding Maskat satisfaction for injury to British subjects; if refused, fort to be bombarded after 48 hours'notice. Operations not to be undertaken on shore, but Political Agent given full powers to helpTurki activelvup to rano-e of ships' guns and to protect British interests. On 20th further fighting at Matra, 8^rebels killed and 3 Baluchis; plundering continued; rice requisitioned from Khojas^ and all Seedees enslaved. Terms concluded on 21st with Hamud bin Said, Sheikh of Wahibeh, who came to Sultan at Maskat on 20th. Rebels to be pardoned and get $ 6,000 and 100 bags rice ; Hamud to persuade Salih to evacuate Matra or help Sultan to expel him. Salih grew ausious about2 Hamud and started towards Maskat with scaling ladders. Hamud who had gone Matra overtook him and called him off. Such attitude and absence of warship made compliance of Sultan inevitable. Turki to receive 100 barrels of powder from Government on payment. Eear of vengeance of Metowwaor priestly party kept people from joining Turki between 17th and 22nd January, day on which ' Nimble' arrived and rebels evacuated Matra. Resident arrived 26th Feb ruary when all over. Abdul Aziz wished to be reconciled to brother Turki (16-2). Turki to get 6 months' subsidy in advance (18-2). Government decided to hold Turki responsible for British losses as he had pardoned rebels (6-3). Ghafiris discontented at Sultan s promise to Salih bin Ali to confirm confiscations of Saiyid Azzan, especially in Senrul. In Nakhl and other places where Ghafiris strong they refused to make over plantations (6-3). Ibrahim on 5th March attacked Musnaah, port of llostak trading with Tersia, without success; sami night took town and besieged fort. He had with him 1,000 Yal Sad, far most numerous Hinawi tribe in Batina (7-3). Government ordered Ibrahim to be told it viewed his rebellious proceedings against its ally with displeasure and he would be held responsible for injury to British subjects. Political Ageni went Musnaah with ' Philomel.' lis 10,200 worth property British subjects taken on board ' Philomel' on 11th. Fort surrendered to rebels on 12th. Political Agent requested rebels not to occupy till Government orders received, and on their per&gt;istins had them shellod out. British claims $ 15,000. One Banyan killed accidentally (L4-3). Political Agent returned Maskat 15th. Muhammad bin Seleyim £1 Gharibee,Chief Metowwaor religious leader in Batina, real prime-mover in business, offered to mediate, fe'gning neutrality. Government ordered Ibrahim to be warned he would be treated as enemy of Gov ernment wherever found unless he gave full compensation to British subjects. No shore operations, but Miles should support Turki with ship's guns (14-3). Resident on 27th March required Ibrahim to h ave Musnaah fort and disman tled it as far as possible by fire of ships. Rebellion collapsed. Turki negotiating and warned not to pardon offenders till British claims settled (31-3). Resident gave Ibrabim ten days to consult Yal Sad Chiefs (held jointly responsible) about compensation and ordered him to refrain from attacking Sultan's ports (2-4). Ibrahim offered to pay half indemnity if Turki would pay half. Turki dis missed his negotiator Hamaid bin Khalifain and tribe to homes : serious burglary meanwhile at Sib attributed to Wahibeh, loss $ 600 (15-4). Turki wished Abdul Aziz to return and take part in administration if Govern ment would mediate : this to keep out Azzan family. Peace not concluded between Sultan and Ibrahim Ibrahim refused full indemnity (21-4). Gov ernment refused to accept part compensation (i7-4). Sultan's affairs being desperate and he having estranged all but few worthless favourites, Government allowed Abdul Aziz to return, after agreeing to Turki's terms of reconciliation : no guarantee given by Government (5-5). Ibrahim asked for some months* grace : refused (11-5). Yal Sad offered to restore Musnaah Fort if Sultan would stand between them and British claims and dismiss his energetic Governor of Soweik (16-6), Yal Sad attacked and plundered Soweik (5 6), drew off with loss of gun on demand of Political Agent (9-6). Govern ment of India authorised Resident to carry out such strong measures as might be needed, to the extent of enforcing any terms he might judge to be reasonable and necessary; but hoped he might find himself able to arrange for a fair indemnity without resort to extreme reprisals (13-6). Government of India informed Secretary of State and laid stress on re peated serious losses to British subjects, and on Turki's attachment to Government and co-operation in re slave trade, such as could not be expected from Ibrahim and priestly party (28-7). Ibrahim took possession of districts Awabi and Wadi Beni Khuroos. Ghafiriand Hinawi fighting over possession of fort Birket el Mouz. 30 Ghafiri Beni Rujam killed and fort takein Fighting continued at Nezwa, Ghafiris besieged at Ziki. Wahibeh Bedouin threw stone at Captain Garforth of ' Philomel ' ; chiefs apologised and tribe were removed from town (5-8). Difference between Sultan and his nephews Muhammad and Hamad amicably settled by Political Agent (7-b). Abdul Azz received $ 500 a month from Sultan (19-8). Sultan with 400 men started in per son on 28th August for Semail to adjust matters between Hinawis and Ghatiris.3 Feud in danger of becoming general. Beni Ghafir garrison at Semail refused to make way for Hinawi garrison. Political Agent advanced Sultan Rs. 21,600, Metowwa Muhammad El Gharibi making great efforts to collect Yal Saad indemnity. Ibrahim inclined to submit (20-8). Ibrahim to get $100 per month (28-8). Ghafiris submitted. Turkish corvette ' Moozuffur ' in harbour (10-9). Advance of $5,000 to Turki. Beni Riyam brought to terms by mediation of Al Wahibeh and other Sheikhs (17-9). Yal Saad brought $3,133 ; Abdul Aziz sent to Burka to collect rest (9-10). Abdul Aziz took hostages and collected $ 7,000. Truce between !Nezars and Hinawis broken by a Beni Ruweyeh who killed a Nezar of Ziki in revenge for brother's death. Ruler of Shahar's people trying to recruit at Maskat for fight with Makalla. 80 Wahabis slipped away from Sur to join in defiance of Sultan's prohibition (7-11). Metowwa move ment originating with mullas of Hijrieen in Sharkiyeh. Neither Salih nor Ibrahim joined and movement languished. Sultan dismissed Wahabi guard, once 400, and substituted Hinavvis. Serious conflict at Yenkul between Hinawis and Ghafiris. Latter assailants, but defeated and lost 90 (25-12j. 1875- Salim at Kishm ; Sultan dreaded his landing on Pirate Coast or at Sur in consequence of invitation from Ghafiri tribes of Jaalan. Resident reminded him that Salim liable to arrest (18-1). $ 400 Yal Saad indemnity remitted, rest paid up (22-1). Open war between Ghafiris and Hinawis in Semail valley. Wali of Semail helpless, and Walis of Burka and Sur sent to help him to mediate (29-1). Sultan's Walis only able to arrange two months' truce between Hinaw's and Ghafiris. Feud originated in breach of faith by Beni Ruweyeh, but Ghafiris cut down $ 5,000or 6,000 worth of Hinawi date-trees in Wady Semail ; mischief irreparable (6 2). Three months , subsidy advanced Turki. Government ordered Agent not to volunteer advice (26-2). Sultan in hands of worthless favourite Mesh and policy weak (26-2). Political Agent to dissuade Turki from abdication, but not io advise joint rulership with Abdul Aziz—so Resident (6 3). No progress in Semail affair (13 3). Government of India decidedly of opinion that Political Agent at Maskat would do well to avoid interference in dynastic and internal affairs of Oman (30-4-). Disturbances in Dhahira extended south to Dhank. Joasmi attack on Braimi expected. Ghafiris of Semail afraid Hinawis would cut off water from above and destroy date crop. Muhammad al Gharibee refused to decide their dispute by shara unless in meeting of Chiefs convened at Maskat (3-4). Turki abrupt with Eeni Bu Hassan tribe ; both guard and tribesmen visiting Maskat eventually made common cau«e and Turki took refuge on ship in harbour. Abdul Azeez empowered to arrange (11-5), Azeez pacified Bedouins by settling arrears of pay and granting all demands, viz., for better food and pay, quarterly relief of guard, half-yearly visits of Sheikhs with followers to Maskat to receive presents and political consultation with tribe in times of difficulty. On 25th May, Turki told Agent he would abdicate in favour Azeez and retire to Karachi by mail steamer next day. Agent dis suaded; Azeez faithful and also dissuaded (28-5). Semail difficulty satisfac- torily adjusted by mediation of El Yaakib (Ghafiris) of Obria : all claims on each side to be withdrawn. Hinawis suffered most 40 mm killed against 3. Difference between Aziz and Sultan (24-6). Aziz said that Mesh, three years before cane-seller in streets, had accumulated $ 40,000 and was plundering Turki and lurki always accepted his advice. Finally arranged that Mesh should leave Maskat and reconciliation between brothers took place (8»7). On night 5th July, Al Wahibeh, on report of estrangement between Turki and Aziz, occupied Matra. Turki negotiated for their departure (8-7). Sultan agreed to keep 50 each of Wahibeh, Peni Bu Hassan and Hejrieen as paid guard at Maskat and Matra; Wali of Semail to be dismissed and Baluchis sub stituted for Ghafiris in garrison; rest of Wahibeh guard in Maskat except 30 camel sowars to be dismissed ; Beni Hadher not to have charge of gates of Matra; 100 men to be kept at Maskat as escort for Abdul Aziz on journeys in interior. After some procrastination Sultan tried to carry out conditions, but Ghafiri garri son of Semail would not make over place. Distrust and fresh breach between Turki and Aziz (20-7). On 21st Resident visited Sultan with Miles and reported4 His Highne^s's frame of mind such from worry and anxiety that unable to consi der affairs with calmness or come to any firm decision ( 24-7). Aziz wiihdrew from affairs, Bedouins deserted Turki, and Turki resolved to retire to Gwadur : cause of estrangement, a dispute about Maskat fort guards, Baluchis, whom Aziz wished 10 dismiss, numbers being deficient and Bedouins de&gt;iring dismissal. Bedouins threatened to attack Turki and plunder town if fort guards not changed. Turki went on * Rahmanee ' and wrote appointing Aziz to act. Metowwas flocked in (21- &lt; 8). 600 or 700 Bedouins in town, all-powerful ; daily customs of about $120 bareiy supplied their rations. Suddenly raised to 1,200 by arrival of Salih, Harithi. Abdul Aziz endeavoured to reduce to original 150 (2-9). Turki reached Gwadur in ' Rifleman' on 23rd August. Des patch sent to Secretary of State reporting revolution (13-9). Country quiet, but signs of disturbance and opposition. Compact between Aziz and Salih. Aziz raised $4,000 or 5,000 and got rid of most of visitors who accepted from him of what they would have taken from Turki. Salih visited Agent to sound him. Aziz also requested Agent's advice. Ghafiris uneasy at adhesion of Salih to Aziz. Saiyid Badr bin Saif prepared to hold Sohar and enlisted Turki's dismissed Wahabis (16-9) Defence of Maskat confided to Bu Hassan : Wahibeh and Hejrieen dismissed. Zaid of Abu Dhabi visited Aziz 30th Sep tember to 24th October. Metowwas in ascendant at Maskat; dances and public women forbidden (1-10). Turki advance 1 $5,000 for personal expenses (6-10). Secretary of State informed (14-10). Salih left Maskat for Sharkiyeh on 5th October (15-10). Saiyid Salim deported to Karachi on ' Daphne' (21-10). Beni Rujam attacked Kimrood to punish their defection from Ghafiris previous year: Kimrood to remain Hinawis, but pay compensation for losses (26-11). Turki left Gwadur for Maskat on 8th December. Aziz brought financed straight by economy and left for Semail via Burka on 11th December (11-12). Turki arrived Mitra unexpectedly night 13th and occupied town and forts without opposition. Muhammad Azzan and 60 Bu Hassan refused 3 summons to surrender Maskat (18-12). On 19th Turki occupied towers and heights round Maskat and only postponed attack till night 20th at request Political Agent. Two days' firing and Turki entered town on 28th. No injury to British subjects. Turki arrived without warning his brother, and Aziz did not come in (28-12). 1876. Turki banished his nephews, sons of Thoweynee, except Nasr, to Kishm on account of suspected intrigues (20 7). Quarrel between Ibrahim bin Kais and Hamud bin Azzan bin Kais over El Hazam fort and successorship to late Imam Azzan bin Kais (17-b), Salih supported Turki against rebels H'imud bin Said, etc. A tii still refused to leave Oman (31-8). Aziz at Semed. Haraud bin Said, Wahibeh, (imprisoned and fined along with Rashid bin Jamia and Amir bin Salim, early iu 1876 and released in'July) after attempts at rebellion in Sharkiyeh and Jaalan started from Mana. Saiyid Ib r ahim refused to join. He marched down by Rostak to Wady Beni Ghafir and after looting at Jumma, town in Wady, reached Tareyf with 200 men, and just failed to cap ture there Turki's son Faisal and favourite Numesh. Looted Sib bazaar but Indians had removed valuables to Maskat (29-9). Looted Indian shops at Saham, but only got $2,500 as Bannias had removed or buried valuables, and beat Banyas Mesnaah Banias' valuables removed on ' Rifleman.' Saiyid Bedr misled by rumour had removed guard specially placed in Saham by Sultan's orders, flamud went to join Maawal who had risen against Sultan (13—10). Wahibeh at feud with Jenebeh, Bu Hassan, El Hishm, etc , and com bination could easily have been raised against them (27-10). Fighting, Nakhl and Semail against M^awal rebels and Hamud; Nakhlis worsted and lost 17 men (10-11). Party of 40 picked Maawalis cut off and killed, except 2 or 3, on return from mission to Beni jRuweyeh by Nakhl ambush {28-11). Nakhl- Maawal feud composed by mission from Sultan : each side to bear own losses and Hamud to be sent away. Turki's difficulty with Maawalis lay in obtaining restitution of lands confiscated by Azzan and bought by Maawalis at Jess than value (23-12).6 1877. Tuvlci allowed $150 a month to his nephews inKislitn (2-2). Muhammad bin Thowevnee bin 8aid died at Linga on 4th February. Government refused aid asked for by Turki on 2nd February to t^ke Soweik fort out of hands of 8aif bin Hamad who, it was feared, would deliver it over to Ibrahim bin Kais /30 ^ On 9-h June Agent received letter from Salih Jiarlhi informing him that discontented subjects would attack Maskat and warning Lim to arrange for protection of Biitish subjects. Agent replied S.lih^oald be responsible for oonsequenoes of rebellious action. ' ieazer had lelt on 8th. On 14th Indians of Matra with valuables, except Khojas, went on board sbips : same dav rebels under Salib occupied Matra and plundered and set fire to bazaar. A 717 did not ioin Salib. ' Teazer ' returned morning 15th. Maskat blockaded from land side and cut off from fresh water. Not a raid, but well organised coah- tion of Metowwas. Rebels 1,000 to 1,600, carrison 200. Ibrahim joined Salib on 17th Banvans went on board sbips and. after warning,' Teazer opened fire at sunset on rebels who appeared about to attack and again at midnight. On 18th ' Teazer ' dislodged rebels from houses adjoining ci adel at Maskat, embarked all Khoias and reiurned MasLat. 19th gatheiing began to break up. 2^ fiultan met Saleh at Fu'aj. Saleh demanded $.0,000 to retire but refused by Sultan. Bedouins at Matra and Sadab had massacred children and unarmed fipprlpps f21-6). On 21st Metowwa force at Fulaj broke up. Salih retired to ftAme l and Ibrahim to Rostak and Haboos, Harth, Bu Ua&gt;san, Hejrieen and Buweveh tr .bes to districts, but Hamud din Said occupied Bosher and demand- i2 600 otherwise he would raze houses and destroy date-trees fiom Burka to Maskat. Wabibeh most numerous in Salib's force. Demand m t from 1 Ivanoe of subsidy and Hamud withdrew. Defences of Maskat restored and inrrison there and at M atra increased, foreigners being re-introduced (6-7). Hindis ensaeed in raid on Maskat arranging to ejport through Sur in future instead of Ma'kat (18-7). Loss of Indian traders between $8,000 ftna in 000 (8-12). Heirieen, afraid their produce would be seized on coast, negotiated with Sultan; but obtained no assurances Resident recom- mtmded levy of indemnity from tribes and offering Sultan naval co-opera- tion if leijuired (14i-12). 1878. Saivid Bedr Bin Saif deported to Zanzibar after some months' imprison- ment iu Maskat following deprivation of government of bobar (7-o). 1879- fiiirid Abdul Aziz bin Tboweynee brought from Bnrka and confined in * ^ A orMT.i n-S) Garrison of Maskat 300 Hasawis and 300 ^jdis. FrictioJ between them and on oth October Abdul Rahman al Asbkar Chief of Fnctiorv, , , h Neidis (9-10). Sultan undertook to dismiss 80 or 100 '» f ■■'tr.of' 1 ' '■ 18,, ■ of India asked Kesident for fresh opinion (28-10). 1880. To-t of Bait-al-Ainam, captured by Saivid Azzan from Ghifiris under S^ B iVh BarXsb and made oyer to Beni Ghafir taken by stratagem by Balucbis ^ ^Jouno d tbcv held it for Sultan, on which Turki sent them ammum- ton (5 2) share of estate, $3,064, from Zanzibar for Aziz not to be paid m r\ i prvlifinnl A ppnt without concurrence of iurki and payment to be Oman by P . £ 9e(1 instalments (31-6). Turki requested the $3,064 for ffie paid at rate of'$100 per mensem till date season be^au ; the remainder in lump sum (7-6). 1881. Tnrki's character described. Bis position stronger than ever before but health precarious. Sons now governed Sohat (Muhammad),. ezwa (Faisal), and6 Burlsa. Their possible rivals, Thrahitn bin Kais, Haraud bin Azzan, and Abdul Aziz. Turki's raotlier Abyssinian, Mubammad's Negress, Faisal's Abyssinian (26-3). On Turki's deatb Government would not intervene actively, unless to prevent reunion of Maskat and Zanzibar. Succession must be settled by Chiefs and people of countrv and first, if not only, duty of Agent to protect British subjects (25-6). Beni bu Ali attacked Beni bu Hassan at JawaM el-Khoweyseh and defeated them in bloodiest affair remembered in Oman. Sixty Beni bu Ali and 75 Beni bu Hassan killed, besides wounded. Hina« i garrison of Ee-.ein made vigorous sally, broke up siege » 52 Nairn and Beni Kelban slain (11-7). Sheikh Suleman, el Khandaki, sent by Goyernor of Sohar to Dhahirah, murder ed by Beni Saad ; and servant, Saood, sent to Hibi, by Nairn : both political demonstrations against Sultan (25-7). Saiyid Faisal married his cousin Aleyya, daughter of Saiyid Thovveynee, on 6th August (16-b). 1882. Attack threatened by Salihand Aziz on Maskat and by Tbrabim on Burka : not executed (23-1). Faisal ruling in Turki's absence at Feley (7-3). 'lurki wired to Zanzibar asking help as Mesnaah taken (12-3). Ibrahim reported to have seized Mesnaah by surprise (14-3). Ibrahim protected British subjects in Mesnaah most carefully and wrote to Agent that he was doins; so: Banvans also wrote to same effect (^1-3). Barghash sent no help to Masqat (6-4). Turki bombarded Mesnaah on 9th and captured it by storm on jOth. *• Ready' brought 21 of worst cases back to Maskat hospital fll-4). Aziz and Hamud besieged Matra ; negotiations (27-6). All quiet at Maskat, Aziz having accepted $200 monthly from Sultan (5-7). Muhammad bin Turki asked ^for $12 ,000 a year besides revenues of Sohar and subsidy: refused and Badr bin Saif appointed governor but countermanded at last moment (6-9). Two Zanzibar steamers run at Barghash's expense started for Jeddah with pilgrims (20-9). Makabeel and Nairn driving cattle near Sobar: Muhammad cooped up within walls (17-10). Beni Hina garrison expelled Ibrahim's men from Hazam and corresponded with Turki (29-i 1). Ibrahim replaced Bern Hina in Bostak by Beni Buweyeh garrison (13-12). Leader of Beni Hina, Hilal bin Zahair, same who in 1880 on pretence of helping Faisal seized Nezwa lor self. Aiming at supersession of Al Bu Said family. Ibrahim proposed to Turki to act in concert (27-12). 1883. Ibrahim recovered Hazam by paying $1,500 to Commandant (10 -1). Skirmish between Harth and Mesakerah (17-1). Ibrahim accepted pension of $100 a month and promised to renounce hostile designs ( 0-3) Hamud el Jahafi advanced to Lizak; Turki confronted him at Falaj (21-6).. Nedabiyin Rided with Hamud, but latter withdrew to Sharkiyah (9-7). Salih invited Ibrahim to join Aziz and self in se:ting up Metovvwa regime. Ibrahim declined. Aziz catspaw: Salih really intended to put religious re3luse, Faisal bin Hamud, on throne. On 19th October Agent received intimation of approaching attack from Aziz with request to arrange protection British subjects. Turki showed surprising energy. Weak force in Matra; 500 in Maskat. Banvans ordered to ship valuables and bo prepared to go on board. Most of Khojas remained in fort. On 21st rebel vanguard reached Rui. At 1-30 morning 22nd, rebels dressed in black, with scaling ladders, surprised Maskat wall in three places, but were repulsed with heavy loss. Aziz in attack: Salih at Rui. •'Dar-us-Salam' arrived with 70 Jen'ebeh Acent visited Matra in evenins:, where small attack had been made and ' Philomel '• fired on rebels'position with T guns and returned Maskat. Night of 23rd-24th ' Philomel' threw occasional shells to deter rebels. * Morning 2Uh, rebels showed in strength at upper end of valley and on heights above Ealbu and maintained fusillade in direction of water-supply. In afternoon ' Philomel' shelled rebel position and prevented attack ex pected that nr T ht. On 25th friendly Sheikhs of Harth and Mesakerah arrived with 300 men. On 26th small fleet came in with 600 or 700 reinforcements and rebels broke up camp at Rui and retired. At least 70 rebels killed includ ing 3 or 4i Sheikhs, 3,000 Arabs now in town besides garrison. Turki never seeni to better advantage (30.10) Sultan sent Faisal in pursuit with 1,700 or 1,800 men. Moved out to Felej on 31st October, finally started on 3rd (T-ll). ' Reached Semail lOth where people submitted and offered to pay indemnity. Nedabiyin and Rehbiyin took refuge in Akk but filially came in. i3eni Ruvvayeh submitted and were fined ^5,000. Expedition on 25tii reached Bidbid en / oute to Wady Maawal (26-11). Faisal entered Maawal. In accidental atiray 14 Maawalis and 5 Ohatiris killed. Maawalis on this refused to negotiate ; but their Sheikh Nasir bin Muhammad, on promise of life, went to submit himself c to Turki at Maskat. Faisal returned Maskat 4th December. Nasir imprison ed and Maawalis fined $ 12,000. They had paid no taxes for 3 years and had reduced payments from $1,700 in 1871, to pOJ ia 1879. Fines on tribes brouglit iu $19,800. 1884. Maawali fine reduced to $10,000. Saood bin Siif of Ruwaheh, in charge Soweik, known to be disloyal (24-1). Nasir released on Maawalis paying $3 000 only and fine being reduced to $9,000 (22—2). haim of Dhalura raided villages of Sohar district (1-4). Nezwa and Soweik forts both out of possession of Sultan (28-4). Sheikh Muhammad bin Nasir of Bern Ruwayeh treacherously imprisoned at Maskat and promised to surrender Ziki fort. Balucrii garrison to be put in as guard and then transfer it to Awamir. Muhammad el Gharibi, Mutawwa, most learned and influential priest in Oman, died (25 5). Beni Ruwaheh refused to give up Ziki fort whatever might be done to their Sheikh (9-6). Surrender of Ziki fort arranged through Nakhlis (18-0). Saweik fort recoverel from Sheikh Saud bin Saif, nominally Wali but P l ' ac ti- cally independent for some years; this through Nakhlis on payment of v500. Muhammad disgusted Sohar pople by incompetence and arbitrary government (10-11). Surrender of Nezwa by Hilal arranged for $i,000 (7-12). Resident advanced one month's subsidy; Government ordered advances should be referred for their orders (15 12). Ras al Hadd Sheikh appointed by Saltan murdered. Expedition in ' Dar-us-Salam ' dispossessed usurper. 1885. Party sent to receive Nezwa fort returned unsuccessful (5-1). Aziz wiling to withdraw to India if debts paid and sufficient allowance given (15-2). Sultan only getting $2,000 a year from Sur Customs: at 5 per cent, should eet $20,000 or 25,000 (30 3). Turki willing to gire same allowance as before, but not to pay debts (8 4). Suleman bin Suwailim, Wali of Zikki, de eited by Hilal bin Zahir after ineffectual attempt to occupy latter s fortlet at Fark (10-5). Heirs of Yaarebeh dynasty with Ibriyin besieging Bahla fort: leading spirit Salim bin Badr: attempt unsuccessful (24-5). Negotiations between Lurki and Abdul Aziz came to an end (7-6). Turki. on advice of Agent, renounced sudden idea, inspired by Arab astrologer, of pilgrimage to Mecca (2 b). Beni Ghafir obtained supremacy in Wadi Sahtani over Ibriyin after battle in ^hich 70 killed (13-9). Wali of Karyat attacked by Beni Battash and one follower killed (9 11). Hamud bin Said got no countenance at Abu Dhabi (-4-11). About 60 or 70 men killed in fighting between Mesakerah and Htnawi tribes, Hejrieen, Harth, Rejeibi, and Wahibeh. Sharkiyeh and Jaaian disquieted and danger of big Hinawi-Ghafiri disturbance (7*12). 1886. 4'i All parties in Hinawi-Ghafiri quarrel looked to Sultan as mediator (1-3) Turki declined visit from Zaid of Abu Dhabi (14 3). Muhammad bin Shimas, new Sheikh of Beni Battash, seized at Matra and executed in Turki's presence without reference to Minister: not on account of attack on Wali, for which blood- money already partly paid (10-6). No disturbances consequent on execution (23-5). Wali of Sohar, reinstated after displace ment on complaints of Indian traders at Khabureh, coquetting with inhabit ants of Shamailiya (20-6). Turki about to be invested with K.G.C.S.I. (4-7). Turki promised to abstain from interference with Dibba, Klior iakan and Kalba (17-7). Aziz refused to come to Maskat for G.C.S.I, ceremony without guarantee of safety from Agent, which not given (17-7). Sultanstarted on -8th July on tour to Semnil and Wady Maawal (2-8). Turki returned M'isk'it 6th August and went to Kalbat on 6th Sepfemlier. fleet ing with 13eni l^attash failed to take place. On 14th they attacked Karyat but were repulsed with lo^s (19-9). Hinawi combination in srmpjithy with Beni Battash unsuccessful. On 5th October Tuiki sent 340 men in ' Dar-us-Salam' to Karyat (10-10). Aziz in Hajir and demanded interview with Ministers of Sultan. Next day, 14«ih, 700 men and 30 horses under Badr bin Saif started for Hajir. Abdul Aziz fled (19-10). Sultan collected 2,000 men at Karyat on 20th. Force destroyed Mizfah (25-10). Sultan stopped Ibrahim's $100 a month (22-11). 1887. Beni lliyam, treacherously admitted, took possession of Birkat-el-Mowz fort from Wali (6-6). Birkat-el-Mowz and Zikki in hands of Suleman bin Saif (2-7). Ibrahim occupied Soweik about 3rd July, Resident went there 10th and induced him to withdraw (15-7). Faisal and other Saiyids visited Khasab on State business (10-10). 1888. Sultan dismissed Wazir Saiyid Said bin Muhammad and appointed no one in bis place (15-5). Saiyid Turki died 4th June ; Faisal, 2nd son, succeeded peaceably and with good wishes of majority (17-6). Saiyid Said, ex-Wazir, returned without permission on 23rd J une ; expelled, and was to leave again for Bandar Abbas on 1st July. Quiet apparently due to uncertainty of tribes as to attitude of Government to new Sult n (1-7). b'aisal trying to detach Salih bin Ali from Abdul Aziz (15-7). On 23r(i Faisal sent Fahd, Saiyid Badr, etc , to compose fighting between Kumzar and Beni Bidiyah (^6-8). Awabi, thorn in side of Rostak, surrendered to llTrahim alter stout resistance. Faisal preparing for attack on Hostak. Kumzar and Beni Hidiyah prisoners brought to Maskat (9-9). Faisal collected 3,000 to 4,000 men with 3 guns and 50 horses (23-9). Caravan for Faisal raided between Mesnaah and Ros f ak by Yal Saad (7-10). Faisal in hands of writers and Banyas connected with Customs: late expedition made him laughing stock. Faisal said if Wahabis invaded Oman, only British could save it (4-11). On 17th October Faisal returned Maskat having slipped away by night, to avoid paying remains offeree, and having mide terms leaving Awabi with Ibrahim. He had not sounded Sheikhs of his army before starting and Beni Ghafir defected (24-1). 1889. On 29th July Abdul Aziz advanced from Samad. 600 men repulsed him at Kahza Pass and he returned Sainad (8-8). 1890. Hamud al Jahafi, with sons of Imam Azzan and small following, encamped at Gobra near Matra. Outsiders took refuge in Maskat (15-1). Night of 13th panic and continuous firing for J hour at imaginary enemy. After loth Hamud retreated a few miles to Hail Garrison of JVlaskat swelled to 2,000, but would not move against Hamud's 200. About 20th Aziz got through and joined Hamud. Aziz took up quarters at Sib. 450 Is aim and Beni Katab camel sowars collected by Wali of Sohar could not be sent as STal Saad held roads (26-1). Fahd advanced to Jama and Ibrahim and Aziz met at Bostak. Sohar Bedouins with Wali arrived Wadi Kasim (2-2). Kaim contin gent plundered Yal Saad and committed excesses at Sohar on return (28-2). Fahd returned Maskat l&amp;th March, leaving Aziz at Rostak (23-3). On 8th April Aziz at Felah to visit Chief of Abu Dhabi. Arrived Bushire 9th June route Bombay (27-6). Faisal invited Aziz's family to live under his protection at Maskat (29-6). Aziz wished to see Viceroy at Simla (3-8). Last week November larga caravan, chiefly Harth, looted near Semail on way from Maskat to Sharkiya by Beni Jabir followers of Suleman-bin-Saif, dis missed Wali of Mesnaah. Camels carried to Suleiman in Jow. Hindus threatened and assaulted at Sur (14-12). Faisal's envoy to Jow insulted and sent back.9 1891. Abdulla, son of Salih, in Maskat from 19th to 22nd January : on going awa lie dropped Hinawi gang which committed many murders in environs. In conse quence of these and of relations between Harth and Beni Jafir no caravans left Maskat for 3 months. No redress to Hindus at Sur and goods of a British merchant burned with Suri baghla. Great internal feud of Bu Ali, begun 1887, continuing. Muhammad bin Nasir, Howsinee, refused passage to Wali of Sohar through Khabura and asked Faisal to make it separate wilayat, which Faisal did (22-2). Sharkiyeh commercially independent of Maskat owing to port at Sur. Sultan apathetic and allowed tribes to take own line (22 2). Khabura bazaar burnt down (25»2). Fire was work of Howamid section of Howasin (at enmity with Sowalim section) who claimed half rent of shops ; Wali of Sohar said to have instigated fire. Loss $35,000 (21-3). Farhat Ullali, man of violent temper and anti-Briiish sentiments, returned Maskat. Faisal reticent, and annoyed at pood information of Agency, which he tried to mislead. No serious attempt by Sultan to pacify country or restore trade. Traders, besides not selling, found up-country debts uarealisable (19-4). llashid bin Aziz arranged matters with Salih. Beni Jabir to pay Salih $1,800 in full settlement. Trade reopened after 5 months (3-5). Sultan summoned Jenebah from Sur in connection with use of French flag : they came 200 strong and left their French papers at Sur. 21i runaway slaves living at Agency. Faisal promptly recovered one given freedom by British Consulate whom former owner carried off (31 •5). Faisal, Pahd and 150 men went on tour 8th (and returned 26th) September, by sea to Masnaah, thence by land to Nakhl, Khowdh and Semail : would have gone Zikki and Mana, but Beni Rijam would not let them pass Object to settle Hadharim dispute at Semail (4-10). Sultan left by land on 25th November for Batina with field gun, probably intending to recover Awabi, lost at beginn ing of his reign (29—-11). Frustrated by Ibrahim changing garrisons ; only ■visited Masnaah and Nakhl (13-12.) 1892. Salih friendly and loyal to Faisal: his power apparently on wane in Oman. Requested guarantee of liberty and safety from Government with view to Mecca pilgrimage (21.1). Given (11-3). Sultan by personal attention and payment of wound-money prevented road to Shark^'ya from being closed by fresh tribal feud (1-5). Sultan placed part of Khabura fine on Sowalim, but removed it on advice of Agent (Ll-7). Two routes from Maskat to Sharkiya ; that by Sur already closed by disturbances, and, on Haboos stealing 700 goats from llahabieen, Ghafiris of Semail combined to close Semail route also (4 -9). Koads from Sharkiya practically closed (16-10). 1893. Oman tranquil (29-4). Sultan went on tour 5th June. Fahd in charge Maskat. Sultan intending to take formal possession of Mansur, offered him by Beni Barras (11-6). Tour a failure, did not get Mausur and withdrew from Nakhl on approach of Suleman bin Saif with large body. Could not arrange differences between Yal Saad and Dhahira (24-6). 1894. Hamud al Jahafi lately returned from Zanzibar (30-8). Hilal bin Zahir at Nezwa murdered by Saif, son of dispossessed Wali, Hamad bin Saif, whose property he confiscated (7-9). 1895. At end January Silih sent son Abdullah to join freebooter, Hamud-al- Jahafi, at Nezwa. Ostensible object to reconcile factions there, and on 10th Feb ruary it was reported to Sultan that Abdulla had arranged 6 months' truce bet ween Badr bin Hilal, Sheikh of Nezwa, and Suleman bin Saif, Rujami, and was coming with Hamud to visit Sultan at Maskat about Nezwa affairs. Sultan hoped this favoured his designs on Nezwa. Oh 11th February the two Sheikhs with 140 followers reached Rui, 5 miles from Maskat. Abdulla with Mohsin bin Amir, Harthi, were hospitably received at Muskat with 40 followers. On 12th Feb-10 ruary in afternoon Sultan sent Sheikhs $ 1,200 and dismissal presents and they intended to leave that night or next morning. After dark many Bedouins straggled into town. At 4 a. m . on 13th February Ahdulla 's party in town rushed gates and admitted comrades from Rui. General Badr bin Saif's house surrounded. New palace entered and Sultan attacked in old palace. Sultan's wife and her sister in-law reached British Agency vid roofs of Banyas' houses; similarly Sultan and rest of palace people. Agent offered him and family protection, but preferred to go to Jalali. Saiyid Muhammad bin Turki in Merani, Agent, wrote to Abdulla warning him he would be held directly responsible for loss occasioned to British subjects in life and pioperty. Arrangements made for protection British subjects. Attempts to retake old palace, Fahad's house and customs house failed. Message received from rebels suggesting Agent should take protective measures in Matra, where Salih expected. Agent again warned Abdullah he would be held responsible for all damage to British subjects at both places. The three rebel leaders declared people of Oman were determined to have Sultan who would rule country, Hamud said he wished Abdul Aziz. Evening of 13th both forts, all outside towers and one tower on South-East wall held by Sultan and rebels in pos session of town. Number of rebels at first 250—SCO, well under control of leaders who said they had come to rule not to rob. Mail steamer came in on morning 14th February ; no one allowed to land. Bequest of Sultan to send her to Sur for reinforcements refused : neutrality necessary as rebels in posses sion of town. Rebels wrecked Sultan's palaces and auctioned effects. Abdulla wrote to Agent declaring all arrangements between British and Arabs still in force. Agent replied w r hat he desired was protection of British subjects and property. Early on 15th white Mutawwa Hag flown on palace. On 16th Agent objected to rebels approaching Consulate quarter to blockade Jalali; they abstained. On 17th first reinforcements for Sultan, Beni Jabir from Jow, arrived: rebels also received large addition to forces. Mohsin bin Amir visited Agent and said rising was general Hinawi movement to dethrone Sultan ; Agent maintained objection to rebel occupation of extreme east and of town. Sheikh profuse in protestation that tribes of Oman desired nothing but friendship and support of British Government^ In afternoon Agent saw Sultan who wished to know if A^ent would mediate and who would be res ponsible for damage if Saltan attempted recovery of town. Agent replied hardly time for mediation yet and that Government of a country responsible for public safety. Late same evening Abdulla announced arrival of Saiyid Saood bin Azzan and his assumption of leadership and approach of Salih with large force. Matra escaped occupalion owing to want of force by rebels. On 18th early Sultan's men attacked Bab Saghir unsuccessfully. ' Sphinx ' arrived. Agent insisted on truce and removed all British subjects to Makalla except Europeaus, who took refuge on ' Sphinx ' and in Agency. Resi dent arrived in afternoon. On 19th and 20th desultory fire kept up by Sultan s men. On 21st Sultan's men gained up to East gate of Customs House. On 22nd sepoy Agency guard wounded by stray bullet- Banyas complained of looting by Sultan's allies, chiefly Beni Bu Ali. Sheikhs warned their boats might be seized and destroyed 'unless followers restrained. On 23rd Hamud bin Azzan arrived at Rui, and first complaint of looting by rebels made. Agent warned Saood that British might have to take action if this not stopped. On 2 ; tth A^ent was informed Sultan was urging friendly Sheikhs to advance, but they would not. Reported that 3U0 to 400 Yal Wahibeh had joined Salih at Rui and that Salih had declared general war against all Ghafins in Sharkiya and Jaalan on account of assistance rendered by them to Sultan. On 26th February Sultan's forces took water-gate and tower half way between it and Bab Kabir, and on left Beni Bu Ali advanced barricades 50 yards. On 26th Sultan sent evasive reply to Resident about his plan of action. Br. Jaya- kar's boat fired at probably by mistake. In centre Sultan's people captured Banyas' temple. On 1st March Agency peon killed by stray shot. On 2nd March Wazir stated to Agent that friendly tribes men wished to prolong matters and would not make determined assault. Said bin Ali, Harth, was trying to negoti ate. Rebels in a fix. Beni Bu Ali Shaikh, had written to Ghafiris of Dhahira and Nairn. More complaints of looting and Resident demanded 3 days truce. Resi dent and Agent interviewed Sheikh Mohsin bin Amir, rebels agent and a LlarthSheikh. They said rebels wished a ruler on whom all agreed. All Hinawis coming to join movement and all already represented. Admitted that they had no lonper full control over iheir men. Said Salih was wealthy and would make good losses. Sultanate to be offered to Zanzibar, or, failing him, to a son of Azzanb iu Kais. They had acted on own account however, not ou behalf of Zanzi bar Faisal was not friend of Government, they had chosen Hamid bin Tboweyni because he was. Truce arranged till night of 6th. Goods removed during*two days under increasing friction with Bedouins. Third day panic, and British subjects retired to Makfdla. Sultan declined to extend truce. Rebels sternlv warned by Agent not to misunderstand British moderation and said they were ready to go if show of force used- Afternoon 7th Agent met Salib and communicated Government orders that union of Maskat and Zanzibar now impossible, and that active measures of protection would be taken if British property not respected. Salih promised full compensation for damage done by his people. Agent replied Salih not a ruler and engagement by him to give compensation could not be accepted as sufficient. To Sal'h's request that remaining property might be removed, Agent replied this physically impossible and British subjects no longer safe among rebels. Resident refused request of Sultan for active assistance. On eth further looting by tultan's allies. On 9th terms of peace settled. Rebels before leaving wantonly destroyed property and • set lire to town in four places. On 10th Saltan's allies overran town; general conflairration with difficulty averted by Agency fire-engines British subjects did &lt; not return for some days for fear of friendlies, nor bring back pronerty till 17th. Difficult to get rid of allies for want of money and boats. On 13th French cruiser 'Troude' arrived, having left Toulon 13th February ; got her orders at Obok. 1 Karvat looted by Kurta, kindred spirit to Hamud al Jahafi ; two British subjects lost'$1,000. Sultan had about 40 killed and 60 wounded; rebels about 80 and feO. Sultan believed to have conceded free pardon to rebels, with continuance of allow ances to leaders and Rustak family, also cash sum down of between $12,000 and $17,000. Rough estimate of British losses one lac of dollars. Causes of rebellion weakness of Faisal's rule, his non-interference in tribal quarrels, ambition of Salih and defence 1 essness of town. Causes of failure of rebellion were rapid rallying of Ghafiris to Sultan, non-adhesion of some Hinawis and dissensions among actual rebels. At end of insurrection there were 2,000 rebels at Maskat and u,000 or 4,000 friendlies. Sultan complained that British had not assisted him, declared that rebels should pay for damage and said connection of Zanzibar with out break unquestionable (18-3). In i895 Sultan's direct authority limited to Batina between Maskat and Masnaah and coast towns beyond, but extended in a measure to country round Nakhl, Tao, Wadi, Muawal and Semail. Last important, as passes into Sharkiya and Oman proper lead thence. Sultan alienated even Ghatiris by non-interference and referred disputes of Rahbiyin and Nidabiyin to Shekh Salih. Hence, perhaps, these 2 Ghafiri tribes held passes for Salih in 1895. Chief dissensions of Hinawis due to jealousy between Sheikh Salih and Sheikh Said bin Ali, latter of whom Sultan favoured, also to ill feeling between Hijriyin and Harth on account of larger presents received by latter. Hijrieen tending to revert to Ghafiris to whom originally belonged (10-4). Earth and their Bedouins, Haboos w ith such of Zakawina and Wurood as included among them, Awamir of Kureeteen, Beni Ruwayeh, Beni Batash, Rustakis, Rahabiyin, Shurooj, Rawashid, people of Khadra, Beni Naman, Fawaris, people of Mahriz, Upper Semail, Fanja, Khode, Saddi and Al Yaman and Al Bu Saidis of Sharkiya were concerned in rebellion (10-7). Seven guns (12-pr.) mounted on Merani Fort ; 6 being sent Jalali. Powder and M. H. cartridges ordered from England. Palace retainers armed with rifles. 40 African guards of Turki re engaged. Faisal remained in palace. Matra defences in lamentable state (18 4). Lull in rumours about Salih's designs against Semail Ghafiris. 3 Harthis imprisoned at Maskat: Salih negotiated for release. Jenebeh Sheikhs refused to close Sharkiya trade at Sur at Sultan's request (3 -5). 3 Harthis at Maskat released. Maskat defences still being improved (31-5). Abdullah, son of Salih, Harthi, died (14-6). Salib reconciled disputants at Ziki and returned Sharkiya (2-67). Saleh visited Samad, but failed to reconcile Beni Rawayeh and Zakawineh.12 Shekli Malik bin Hijji tried to obtain exemption of ITartb from new indemnity tax (6-9). Sohar threatened by Saood bin Azzan (27-12). 1896. Suleman bin Suwailim trying to get Nezwa for Sultan (7-2). Nezwa occupied in Sultan's name by Suleman Lost to Turki through machinations of Wazir, Saiyid Said (5-b). Ex-Isakib Makalla arrived and lived quietly at Maskat on Sultan's bounty (20-11). Sultan received from Zanzibar treason able letters Tvntten by his Wazir Saiyid Mahomed bin Azzan to late Salih bin Ali, etc. Wazir admitted offence, paid $ 20,000 fine and was ordered to go to Zanzibar and live there after disposing of property (10-12). 1898. On death of Ibrahim, Rostakis and fome of Sharkiya Hinawis favoured Saiyid Saood, son of late Imam Saiyid Azzan bin Kais, as successor at Rostak. Saiyid Said, son of Ibrahim, fled to Hazam and asked help of Sultan. Suleman bin Suwailim, ordered to help with provisions and money, thought chance good to seize Rostak for Sultan. Yal Saad declared for Saud (6-7). Jenebeh for some time agitating for removal of son of Suleiman bin Sovrailim from Sur, On 21st March Suleiman arrived at Sur from Dhofar, and on 26th informed Sheikhs of Jenebeh, in future he would not respect khadr system. Same day left Sur and son soon began building fort to command both water-supply of town and caravan roads into interior. The four Jakhaids or sections of Jenebeh combined and memorialised Sultan who took no notice and turned deaf ear to deputation who visited him on 4)th May. On represen tations of Abdulla bin Salim, Temimeh of Beni Bu Ali, Sultan stopped work on new fort. Jenebeh demanded removal of Suleiman's son. On 26th September, news received that Jenebeh had cut off supplies of garrison in old fort (30-9). On 4th October 600 Jenebeh, 150 Beni Rahsib and 200 Beni Bu Ali attacked old fort which surrendered on conditions alter three hours, garrison beintr sent Maskat. Works of new fort destroyed. Jenebeh offered to restore fort to any Governor sent except Suleiman or son (13-10). Jenebeh refused to admit new Governor, Hamad bin Saif, till British Government gave guarantee against re-appointment of Suleiman, and directed Customs farmer to withhold customs but not punitive tax from Sultan (22-10). sultan Muhammad bin Hamad, with 60 men, took peaceable possession of Sur fort on 25th November; fort found dismantled except bare walls (8-12). 1899. Letter from Hilal-bin-Amr (native of Jbrah, and important personage in own country) to various Harithis, dated 20th April, seen by Fagan. Hilal advised his correspondents to avoid joining French party ; better to join English Government, which strongest and farthest seeing (29-8). Sheikh of Beni Rashib on 2^th May interviewed Eagan and sounded him as to attitude of British Government in case of rising against Eaisal. Eagan referred to gua rantee of protection of Maskat and Matra but promised to refer to Govern ment (20-5). Government of India ordered Eagan to be warned he should not discuss with tribesmen possibilities or prospects of rebellion against sovereign to whose court he himself accredited (3-7). On 29th April Said-bin- Ibrahim, brother-in-law of Sultan, deprived of Rostak by Beni Ruwayeh after father's death in favour of Said-bin-Azzan, visited Maskat and went to Hazam with men given by Sultan. Beni Ghafiri garrison reduced on various pretexts and remainder then expelled. Beni Ghafiri incensed at loss of fort (29-5). 1900- Hilal bin Amr returned unexpectedly from Africa and landed at Sur on 10th May. Interviewed M. Ottavi and | addressed assembled Jenebeh elders saying chief enemies Faisal and Engli&gt;h ; only French could help ; all should take French fiags. Eaisal on this visited Sur, for first time in reign, on 'Sphinx' and bad impression partly removed (20-6). Government of India complained of Hilal 's return without warning and proposed to tell Sultan he might expel Irm (16-8).13 1903. Agent found Bu Ali of Haija on point of attacking Jennebeh, among whom holders of French flag; persuaded them to await Sultan who accordingly left Maskat on 13th August (lb-8). Beni Bu Ali visited him: Jenebeh would not come on board nor would Sultan go ashore. Received news Aysa bin Salih and brothers (sons of rebel of 1^95) trying to get Kostak fort, so took Taimur and retainers to Sib and returned Maskat 19th (22-8). Uazam in possession of Said bin Ibrahim bin Kais and Rostak in possession of Hamud bin Azzan bin Kais. Taimur not in time at Finjeh to prevent Aysa passing from Semail valley to Rostak. Sultan left in ' Nur al Bahr ' for Batina coast night of 23rd (24-8). Returned Maskat 29th and left again. Said declined to come to Mesnaah, but left Hazam and joined Aysa at Rostak. Beni Ruwayeh commandant refused to evacuate and prepared for siege probably in interest of own tribe not of Sultan. Suleman bin Suwailim with 150 riflemen sent to Awabi on Aysa's line of retreat and communications. Yal Saad doubtful allies of Sultan: if he got Rostak he could collect taxes from them (31-8) Rostak handed over to Said bin Ibrahim by Beni Ruwaheh, com. mandant remaining in it under Aysa's orders. Sultan's attack on Hazam frustrated by treachery of Yal Saad. Savage raid on Burka by Aysa's brother. Slaves manumitted by Agent to annoyance of Yal Saad (14-9). Aysas attempt to set up Said as Imam a failure (18-9). Abdulla bin Salim asked Agent to come and see him at Sur : Sultan desired Agent to do so and take down arrears of his subsidy, $800 (4rl0). Abdullah had only grievances of subsidy and treatment against Sultan. Said bin Ibrahim asked for renewal of his pension. Aysa still at Rostak (12-10).21 B.-EVENTS IN GWADTJR. 1873. Political Agent ordered to interfere as little as possible in local quarrel (17-3). Maskat subjects when injured by others retaliated, instead of reporting to Wali. Ma^kat subjects of Gvvadur, Komas, Meds, etc., held land and were ex empt from taxation on condition of armed service, yet refused to act against Fakir Muhammed (19-3). Abdul Aziz left Karachi and expected to attack Gwadur (4)-6). Aziz to be warned, should he return to British territory, that he could only receive asylum on condition of abstaining from intrigue and interference in Maskat affairs and that he would be liable to criminal penalty if he made warlike preparations, etc., while in British territory (13-6). Aziz arrived Urmara, loth (16 -6). Aziz in Kolanch unsuccessfully trying to raise force, 50 miles east of Gwadur. Gvvadur with Arab garrison of 40 loyal to Turki (9-7). Aziz arrived, Ibth July. About 600 men with him, including 300 Rinds : Wali retired to citadel. Most of Indians in sheltered place near Telegraph. Kalmatis with Bahram Kbanin fort, related to influential Tikris ; hence lukewarmness of attackers, who feared blood-feud. Khula Nabi Bakhsh, chief ally of Aziz, anxious to desert him. About Rs. 10,000 damage to British subjects so far. Partiesiastonished at British inaction but knew power; hence no loss of prestige (1-8). Of 139 shops bearing Agent's notices only 6 touched (T6-8). Aziz left Gwadur on 7th August with threat to return in 8 days. Salim wrote from Kolanch he would come and take Gwadur (16-8). Government of India ordered that if either Aziz or Salim returned and threatened, Gwadur Agent might call on tbem to withdraw and disperse their men, and make them prisoners in case of refusal (26-8). Aziz| in Bahu, Salim at Kej, disordering country and caus ing trouble with Persians (29-8). Aziz and Salim to be informed of Turki's terms and given 10 days to come in. If they threatened Gwadur or tried cross Gulf to be arrested, if possible (1-9). At 1 a. m ., 8th December, Salim and 15 followers, who had come 100 miles in two days, escaladed fort assisted probably by treachery of AVali (8-12). Ten of Aziz's companions were Georgis Persian subjects of Repug in Dastyari. On 11th H. M. S. ' Columbine ' and tug ' Manora ' with 62 armed police arrived. Agent placed cordon across isthmus and called on Salim to surrender. At 7-30 p. M. rebels broke through. Salim 's horse shot, but Salim escaped. 1874. Aziz, brother of Salim, left Maskat, 7th, surreptitiously with Dahu-bin- Muhammad, Sidi, in Bahraini kotia, probably for Mekran (10-4). They arrived at Bandar Fazzam in August. Salim then at Kishm (14-8). Din Muhammad Dastyari arrested Aziz and Dahu and promised to deport to Maskat (28-8). 1879- Rinds raided Nagar, Gwadur, etc., and detained Khoja woman for ransom. 12 Rinds made disturbance in town, 2 shot dead, 8 captured by Wali's Arabs, one of whom died. Serious disturbances expected (16-6). SubadarandSO men sent Gwadur from Jask (18-6). Rinds threatened Agent, stole his Munshi's horse, cut wire and flogged telegraph artificer (18-6). Rind prisoners liberated by Wali on executing bonds not to claim blood-money. Jask detachment sent back (15-7). 1883. Sultan visited Gwadur. Rinds captured telegraph jamadar, but soon releas ed him, threatening they would declare feud against Government if blood-money for 1879 not paid by Turki or British Government in two months. Turki's visit to Gwadur probably cause of outrages. Rinds could not separate Indian from Maskat Government (25-1). Attempts made to induce Rinds of Mand to profess allegiance to Persia (12- j ). Outrage on telegraph was robbery ; blood.feud mere excuse. No fear of blood-feud against Government employes. In 18&lt;6 Wali refused in consequence of treaty to give up slaves of Kiazie Rinds, pursued by owners along with people of Kalatak ; this caused soreness, and inaction of Government after threats, etc., by Rinds loss of prestige.22 Durand's list of outrages appended (8-3). K^ssid of Sultan looted and camels stolen (12-7). Rind Kafilas selling merchandise at Gwadur, then purchasing gunpowder and lead. Latter prohibited by Wali (9-7). 1884. Sandeman arrived Gwadur, 21st February (21-2). Resident in Gulf urged Maskat should be consulted and properly represented in Riud negotiations (22-2). Resident in Gulf deprecated Indian traders beiug told that if they traded beyond limits of Gwadur, it must be on own responsibility (22-2). Sandeman thought time insufficient to consult Maskat. Wali declined to negotiate without orders. Resident in Gulf suggested Mockler should represent Maskat (22-2). Sandeman before departure told traders to remove from Gvradur, and that telegraph station would be t?iken away. Resident in Gulf ordered Mockler to tell traders not to remove. Gunboat to be sent and garrison reinforced (24-2^. Government approved Resident's action (26-2). Resident ordered Miles to Gwadur. Sandeman wished Rind-Gwadur cases to be settled by Jirga, chiefly Baluch. Pressure was put on Wali to pay blood-money for 3 Rinds killed, 1879 (25-2). Sandeman only told Gwadur traders to avoid Mand (26-2). Arab claims against Rinds, lis. 12.460, British, Bs. 2,438. No Hindu and other, should be told not to trade beyond further Steps should be taken, UnleSS Owadur limit, except on own respou.ibility. ^ ^ made ^ ^ tlje Gulf T i ew (3—3). All action suspended by order of Government for Sandeman's and Ross's reports q q.v. (5-3). Fresh raid by Rinds (.6-4). Resident in Gulf authorised to give orders at Gwadur pending final arrangement as to political control (6-5). [Gwadur, a dependency of Maskat; History of Political Agency at Gwadur ; the Rinds; for Lee-Warner's notes on these and related subjects, see Proceed ings June, Nos. 451-581-A, Political E.] Government considered Sandeman's settlement unsatisfactory and ordered cases to be disposed of afresh by Court consisting of one European officer each from Gulf and Baluchistan Agencies, with three Assessors, one Kej, one Maskat and one Rind. Resident in Gulf would use influence to get Rind cases against Gwadur submitted to this Court. Court to assemble at Gwadur and take up any new cases it thought fit (16-6). Government of India finally decided Court of Inquiry should consist of Miles and an officer from Baluchistan. In telegraph cases Director, Gulf Telegraphs, should replace Miles. Indemnity not be recovered from Rinds, but to be advanced by Government and Rinds warned (16-10). Sultan agreed to blood-feud case of 1879 going before Court of Inquiry (12-11). Wali of Gwadur built fort at Pishkan (18-12). Further raids by Rinds (6-12). 1885. Realisation from Rinds to be left to discretion of Court of Inquiry (6-2). Inquiry limited to 12 years preceding (13-3). Inquiry completed-Rs. 5,216 decreed in favour Arab subjects and Rs. 1,744 in favour Indian traders against Rinds. No decrees in favour of Rinds. Inquiry made in blood-feud case (23-3). Rinds found still to owe Rs. 620 in telegraph cases, these and other decrees totalling Rs. 7,010 against Rinds approved by Government and claim of Rinds for blood-money in 1879 case rejected. Telegraph decrees to be paid out of Kej subsidy. Other decrees to be met by advance from Government and Rinds not to be called on to pay unless they misbehaved again (15-9). 1886. Sandeman suggested Government should take over Gwadur on quit-rent. In 1873 there was an idea of purchasing by Government. Khan of Kalat now would not buy, and Sultan averse to selling; could perhaps be had as gift from Sultan to British. Sandeman's proposal negatived. Order of 1884 as to control reaffirmed (1-2). 1888. Turki, practically on death-bed, wished to separate Gwadur from Oman and give it to eldest son, Muhammad (29-5).23 1891. Government of India declined to ask Faisal to sell Gwadur as he liad just signed agreement not to sell or cede dominions^ and Gwadur was no longer regarded as possessing high value for Baluchistan. [Goodnote here by Mockler on Faisal at beginning of his reign (20-5).] Manumitted slaves sent away from Gwadur within week. Only ones staying longer were slaves settled there since 30 or 100 years. Rinds claimed these and had extorted ransoms from some. Rinds truculent to Native Agent, who was accordingly supplied with fire-arms and told to live in fort (10-7). 1901. Rendition of Gwadur to Kalat to be taken up on recurrence of rupture with Maskat (19—3). 1902. Government of India suggested to Secretary of State in connection with arms-trade and foreign desigus on Gwadur that rendition of Gwadur to Kalat on payment might be arranged (calculations here of revenue of Gwadur) (4—9) Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed sale or lease would not be contrary to Anglo-French Declaration of 1862, but thought strong French opposition would be provoked. Lease of Customs to Kalat also objectionable as affording precedent for other powers, but might be considered (21-11). 1903. Government of India replied they did not at present propose to move in matter of lease (26-2).(l 31 C.—EVENTS IN DHOFAR. 1876. Letter dated 15th May received by Sultan of Maskat from Saiyld Eadlil-bin- Alavi, Moplali, styling himself Turkish Governor of Dhofar, recommending Awadh-bin-Abdulah. ' Turkish subject,' to Sultan of Maskat's good offices. Maskat claimed Dhofar himself (15-6). Saiyid Fadhl had been carrying on desultory warfare against Garah Bedouins of interior with help of Dhofar people and had extended influence westwards among Mahrah tribes. Within past 5 years Dhofar chiefs had been at Maskat to pay allegiance. Fadhl arrived in Dhofar with family from Mecca about August 1875 (22-6). [Eor previous history of Saiyid Fadhl see notes in Proceedings, Secret, September 1876, Nos. 1-5.] At instance of Government of India, British Ambassador at Constantinople was directed, without assuming that Saiyid Fadhl had acted with the knowledge or consent of the Turkish Government, or asserting in any way the claim of Maskat to Suzerainty over Dhofar, to remonstrate with the Porte against his proceedings and urge them to repudiate his acts (21-10). 1877. M^skat claim to Dhofar was based on two facts ; 1st, that, on death of Muhammad Akil in 1829 Saiyid Said sent a force to Dhofar which was shortly withdrawn ; and 2nd, that, on every accession of new ruler in Oman, Dhofari iSheikhs sent deputation to offer allegiance and obtain flag. Ruling Sheikh in 1871 was Hamad-bin-Salim-bin-Umar, A1 Marhuni. After withdrawal of Said's troops dissensions occurred and Garas plundered and oppressed people. For some years the ruling spirit was Abdullah Lorleyd, an American captured as a youngster, wtio combat ted ttie Garas with daring and success (18-5). Government of India considered Maskat claims to be of an indefinite character and did not desire to interfere on Sultan's behalf (25-6). 1878. Porte had, however, been addressed and reminded meanwhile (1-1). 1879. Revolution in Dhofar (for reasons see No. 635, Procpedings A, November 1879). Saiyid Fadhl, expelled from Dhofar in January by Arab Shaikhs, left Berbera for Constantinople on 7th March (7-3). Turki interesting himself in Makalla-Shahr dispute on side of Makalla. His Agent Salman-bin-Yakub stated that Maskat territory extended to Makalla (12-4). Saiyid Fadhl left Jedda for Constantinople on 26th April (26-4). Suleman-bin Sowailim on behalf of Sultan Masket landed at Bundar Hasik in March or April, assisted by Awadh-bin-Abdullah, Shanfari, and resiNted by Awadh-bin-Azzan, Kathiri. A1 Kathir mostly adverse to Sultan, but overawed. Suleman reduced customs from 5 per cent, to 4 per cent. (22-5). Makalla people making large consign ments to Dhofar (11-5). Kathiris attempted to raise Marbat people against Maskat (26-5). Dhofaris used Maskat flag before Fadhl's arrival and wrote to Maskat for assistance against him. Kaiti Jamadar of Shahr intriguing in Dhofar affairs. Aden Resident prohibited Jamadar from sending men to Dhofar [Here will be found description of Dhofar] (5-6). Turki dis« claimed jurisdiction up as Makalla (8-6). No interference necessary with Turki's attempts to obtain control of Dhofar, but he must not try to get assistance from In^in. (it was reported he had written to Hyderabad). Govern ment settling Makalla-Shahr dispute and Turki should not have interfered. Jamadar of Shahr forbidden to interfere in Dhofar affairs 25-8). Letter to Hyderabad was written by Saiyid Said without Turki's knowledge. Turki promised to suspend correspondence with Makalla till settlement of Shahr dispute. Dhofar in peaceful occupation of Sultan's officials (9-10). Awadh- bin-Abdullah sent to Maskat by Wali for wishing to keep Wali too much in hands of self and party. Awadh charged Wali with misgovernment and extra vagance (17-10). Dhofar affairs to be reported in future through Maskat, not Aden (7-11). Rumour reached Makalla from Constantinople p/a Jeddah that Fadhl about to be sent to Dhofar in man-of-war to re-establish authority of32 Porte there and at Makal.a (30-T1). Boundary between Arlen Residency and Maskat Agency fixed at Has Sajiror S: ir {(10-12). Sultan of Turkey was almost persuaded to give Fadhl troops and ships to conquer Hadhramaut and Maskat, but desisted on representation of brother of Grand Sharif of Mecca th it Fadhl was a mere adventurer, and that complications with England would ensue. Fadhl enjoyed some con&gt;ideration at palace. So Layard (13-12). 1880. Fadhl wished to take leave of British Ambassador at Constantinople. Turkish Prime Minister agreed with Layard Fadhl should not be allowed to go to Hejaz; Council too all against allowing Fadhl to go back, but Sultan of different opinion (7-4). Fadhl wrote to Turki he had been at Constantinople in connection w T ith reforms in Dhofar and was about to return. He was astonished at Turki's interference with an Ottoman province (J3-5). New Grand Sharif of Mecca wrote to Sultan that annexation of Dhofar by Mnskat would produce bad effect in Arabia and recommenfled r adhl being recognised and suppoited (15-5). According to Al Jawab, Arabic paper at Constan tinople, Fadhl received honorary title of ' Wazir ' from Sultan (issue of 18th August). Revolution at Dhofar by small section of inhabitants, headed by the Awadh who ousted Fadhl i.nd brought in Turki. Awadh on bad terms with Wali and was shabbily treated by Turki on visit to Ma^kat. Awadh seized fort by surprise and captured Wali. Only 30 men there and 30 sent a week before to relieve and reinforce. Sultan was now sending '* Bar-us-Sal am ' with 2 boats and 180 men. Fear was that Kayti jemadar of Shahr might seize Dhofar for self (20-12). Instructions to expedition were to abandon Dhofar if inhabitants did not desire Turki's rule; otherwise to reinstate Suleman as Wali if acceptable to people and if not, to appoint Saiyid Khamis-bin-Suleman. No force to be used except against Awadh and his adherents. Expedition left on 21st December. 1881. Four Al Kullum Dhafaris visited Omar-bin-Awadh at Hyderabad Deccan and got handsome presents (5-^.) ' Dar-us-Salam ' returned Maskat on 4th January. Inhabitants of Dhofar rose and reinstated acting Wali. Awadh on promise of life undertook to surrender self at Maskat, Chief Sheikh in counter revolution was an old supporter of Fadhl. Guns brought back to Maskat; troops left at Dhofar (7-2). 1883. Revolution in Dhofar, Dhofaris besieging Sultan's fort (5-2). On iTth February 70 men and 10-pr. gun despatched to Dhofar (19 2). Suleiman bin Suweilim, Governor, given ^400 to raise troops to recover Dhofar, where his son Ali holding out (2t)-5). Fadhl wrote to Turki from Constantinople on 11th March, saying he would never renounce claims to Dhofar and claim ing friendship of English. No action taken (7*6). In July, Grand Sharif of Mecca advised AJuskat to abandon claims to Dhofar in favour of Fadhl. Maskat declined courteously under advice from Political Agent, stating that Dhofar had belonged to Portuguese, then to Yaarab, then to Said and his ancestors but that Fadhl had no claim (9-7). Colonel Miles left for Dhofar on 7th November and returned 25th November. [Excellent report by Miles on geography, history, etc., of coast from Ghubbat llashish to Dhofar] (?—12}, 1884. Turkish Consul-General forwarded to Governor, Bombay, letter from Fadhl complaining of action of Maskat (2-4). Various articles appeared in '* Eetidal *' Arabic newspaper published at Constantinople on Maskat-Dhofar question (7-6). , 1885. Rebellion broke out suddenly on 11th May. Wali, Ali-bin-Suleman, and 40 Wahabis besieged in fort. Middle of July Al Omar tribe of Morbat media ted and removed garritpn to Morbat. At end of September Wali and garrisonreturned Maskat. Wali was unpopular, Dbofar financiany an encumbrance to Maskat. No ruler at Dbofar (2' -10). 1886 Govevnrment frustrated expedition of Muhammad-bin-Fadhl who was pro ceeding to Dhofar in British return pilgrim ship ' etapedii ' with 16 personal attendants and 100 disbanded Arab soldiers of Grand Sharif of Mecca. On 20th January vessel was searched and large quantity of arrns and ammuni tion including Martini-Henry rifles and carbines and revolvers seized under Arms Aet. Muhammad Pasha then elected to land and await orders (as he said) from Constantinople (20-1). Sultan's troops inactive at Morbat in Dhofar (20-2). Agent of S^iyid Muhammad-bin-Fadhl recently landed at side near Morbat with warlike stores, Turkish flag and documant purporting to be Turkish Commission, proceeded secretly to Salala and deposited stores including Turkish coin in house of a Kutheiri. Qprman crown, Indian rupee and pice, prevailing coins in Dhofar except during Fadhl's ascendancy. Force for Dhofar being raised at Maskat (1-3). Wali of Basra wrote to Sultan of Maskat on 2t)th April asking for an explanation as to aggressions on Dhofar: ignored (20-6). Saiyid Muhammad bin Suleman sent as governor to Dhofar with Saiyid Abdul Jalil as deputy, also 50 Arabs and 20 Baluchis ^20-12). 1887. Fadhl wrote to Kesident at Aden and to Viceroy complaining of the Aden incident (9-4) (19-12). 1888, Turki's Akil shut up in citadel. Dhofaris intended to resist reappointment of Suleman-bin-Suvveilim. On 13th Turki sent ' 8ultani' , to Dhofar with Faisal, Fahad, 1 gun and 200 men (15-1). Faisal, Fahd, and other notables v.ith 200 men who left for Dhofar in c&lt; Sultani ' on loth January not heard of; H M. S. 'Turquoise' went in search on 22nd February (25-2). Five disaffected Sheikhs of Dhofar who corresponvied with Saiyid Fadhl and Shahar brought in chains to Maskafc by Faisal. Suliman-bin-Suwailim left as AVali at Dhofar (11-3). 1891. ' Avoca ' carried 100 Waliabis for Dhofar garrison (15-11). 1894. Fadhl Pasha applied to British Ambassador, Constantinople, for permis sion to return to Dhofar with his sons and promised in return for British pro tection to maintain free trade with British possessions and aid to suppress trafiic in slaves (12-10). 1895, Sahl Pasha, son of Fadhl, guest of Khedive at Kubba Palace near Cairo. He saw Sbakur Beg and proposed to recover Dhofar with countenance of Eng land (3-3). Lord Cromer told it was undesirable he should enter into com munication with Sahl Pasha and that Dhofar had been under Maskat for 14 years (26-3). Fadhl had 4 sons-Sahl Pasha, Hassan Pasha, Muhammad Beg and Ahmad Beg; all got allowances from Turkey. Fadhl's presents from India diminishing, but he still could give Hassan Pasha Rs. 1,000 yearly from that source. Sahl Pasha returned Constantinople with Khedive in summer (11-4). Resident, Aden, ordered to look for Fadhl and party and report suspicious cir cumstances. Sultan Maskat to be advised to strengthen defences and garrison at Dhofar and send arms (29-7). Request made for watch to be kept at Cairo and Jeddah CoO 7). Fort in Dhofar captured by hill Kathiris from Kara country on 3rd November, and Ali, son, and Musaid, nephew of Wali, besides 11 of garrison slain. Proximate cause, imprisonment of a Kathiri defrauder of customs; general cause harshness of Wali, Suleman-bin-SuwaUim. News reached Maskat, 25th November, and immediate preparations made for expedi tion (28 11). Garrison retired to Morbat (27-11).1896- Expedition failed to recover Dhofar. Attempt to land at Dhofar repulsed, Shanatira joining Kathiris. Sultan had neglected advice of Government to strengthen the place. Sultan inactive (23-1). Political Agent at Dhofar, 8th to 12th March, Only 120 men faithful to Sultan at Marhat. A1 Umr neutral. Sultan's flag flying at Hafa, where 20 of Sultan's men practically prisoners. Turkish flag flying at Salala | mile distant. Shanafirah expressed loyalty ; but few in Hafa, and had formed compact of neutrality. Salim-hin- Hamad, Marhuni, and Ali-hin-Kutheiri ringleaders of rebellion, Salim saw Political Agent, behaved defiantly and said his father had been treacherously detained a year at Maskat. Turkish flag was one that had been in district 8 or 10 years. Rebels apparently appealed both to Shahr and to Fad hi. Whole province actively hostile except Morbat, Thaka and Hafa. Rebellion assigned to interference with women, exactions and forced labour ( 9-3). Sultan will ing to send reinforcements (20-3). Government of India proposed on certain conditions to support landing with guns of 'Brisk' (22-3). Secretary of State agreed; also that Turkish Government should be informed Moplah would not be allowed to go Dhofar nor foreign interference tolerated {N.B. This communication was not found necessary eventually); and French Govern ment that action did not imply intention to established protectorate over Maskat (28-3). Sultan making no preparations and would postpone action till after monsoon if left to self (27-1). Up to 9th April Faisal apparently pleased with prospect of British assistance and hoped to have troops ready in 15 days. On 10th he inquired what advice of Government would be, accept ance of which made condition of assistance. Political Agent replied, on 11th, advice would depend on circumstances On 13th Sultan professed himself unable to conciliate Kutheiris or remove Wali and expected in absence of foreign complications, to reduce Dhofar unassisted. In conversation took line that he could not agree to an uncertain condition. Influence of Ottavi and Abdul Aziz suspected. Faisal's attitude to British Government getting worse and worse (15-4). Fadhl Pasha wrote to British Ambassador, Constantinople, referring to recent revolt against tyrannical Maskat Governor and hoisting of red flag with crescent. Proposed to send own Envoy with instructions to fly ' national flag of Dhofar, green with a pentagonal centre,' to cause recent agreeable to people to be elected and to proclaim complete accord with British Govern ment and intention of latter to protect rights and independence of Dhofar principality (13-5). Saiyid Fadhl to be told he could not proceed to Dhofar nor could Envoy be recognised or assisted (17-6). Fadhl wrote again to Ambassador complaining of demand of British ship that his flag should be lowered and asked for letters of introduction for an Envoy (27-5). Former order repeated (19-6). Fadhl continued writing (22-8). 1897. Faisal requested assistance of man-of-war, but was determined to send old 'Wali back (19-1). Sanctioned by English Foreign Ofiice (10-2). Sultan ac cepted conditions of assistance including dismissal of Wali, if found unsuitable &gt; and no new imposts (19 -2). u Surprise,' French war vessel, came to Maskat about 1st March and offered services for Dhofar ; Sultan declined. H. M. S. ' Cossack ' arrived on 6th. Suleman in Batina. Sailed without him on 12th ; Hamad-bin-Nasir, W^ali of Matra, taking his place Saiyid Muhammad-bin Turki accompanied with 70 followers. Main force of 300 had preceded. Arrived Morbat on 35th Found Sultan's troops in Hafa. Salala and Murabim held by rebels. ' Cossack ' and ' Lawrence' anchored opposite on 16th. Turkish flags flying. On 17th, Beville saw Sheikhs. Sheikhs demanded Wali of own choice without Maskat troops or no Wali at all ; then claimed Turkish protec* tion; finally sought British protection. Beville promised only pardon for past and no new imposts. On 17th, Resident issued ultimatum for submission by 20th. At dawn on 20th, hostile flags struck and afterwards sent on board. Hamad-bin-Nazir left in authority. Resident returned Maskat on 24th ; found Suleman had started for Dhofar two days before (25 3). Not advisable to insist on removal of Suleman as situation ditficult and he a strong man [Memo randum on modern history of 1 hjfar by Beville] (30-3). All quiet at Dhofar35 on 9tli April (9—5). Suleman recalled from Dhofar in consequence of disturbance between ilafa and Salala. Saiyid Saif-bin-Yarab sent in his place (10 5). 1898. Sulaiman-bin-Suwailim reached Sur from Bhofar on 21st March. Sheikh Salim-bin-Hamad, Marhuni, seized on 20th March and sent Maskat, arriving 2nd Miy (16-5). Charged with inciting tribes to resist Wall subsequently to rebellion. Eagan pressed for inquiry, to which Faisal averse. Suspected that proceedings were instigated by Suleman in revenge for death of son and nephew (23-5). Umr-bin-Abdulla similarly arrested (25-6). Resident consi dered it not proved that Sultan had violated promises or that British officers had guaranteed those promises. Fagan should exercise good offices and avoid irritat ing demands (7-8). Government of India agreed and desired importance of conciliatory attitude and of gaining confidence of Sultan to be impressed on Fagan (18-10). Salim and Umr released (20-12). 1900. Fadhl dead; he had been living at Constantinople since 1896 at expense of Porte (4-11).43 D.—EVENTS IN ZANZIBAR. 1875. Abdul Aziz petitionod Government for assistance in recovering from his brother Bargbasb, Sultan of Zanzibar, produce of 8 plantations in Zanzibar for 6 years, also shares in estates of 7 deceased brothers, 1 sister and, 1 niece. Creditors in India and Gwadur pressing (22-1). Petition sent to Agent, Zanzibar, for exercise of good offices if deemed expedient (12-3). Aziz's behaviour to Bar^ash of late years not such as latter's extreme kindness to him when a boy merited (4-5). Necessary to proceed with caution ; similar demands put forward by Madam Renter, Sultan's sister, which German Government might use for political purposes. Public revenue and estate should be separated from private at Zanzibar to avoid complete division and consequent embarrassment of each new Sultan on accession (28-9). 1876. Papers examined. Aziz's claim grossly exaggerated. Present Sultan could not be liable for shares unpaid at his own succession or death of Majid (8-3). Government considered it inexpedient to move. Barghash stated inability to help Turki with money, and blamed him for releasing hostile Sheikhs. Indignant at license now allowed to Bedouins in Maskat and com mended example of Said and Thoweynee. $50 a day to son of KhaliQa wasted. A force should be maintained at Watteya (13-12). 1880. Negotiations between Turki and Barghash of Zanzibar ; Turki to get pen sion and Barghash to unite Oman and Zanzibar. Government of India advised Secretary of State against any overt step (8-6). $3,064| on account of claims sent by Barghash' for Aziz, who declined to receive by instalments as recommended by ^Barghash (7 -7). Government agreed to payment in lump sum when date-season well commenced (18-8). Money withheld at request of Turki lest Aziz should join in expressions of discontent which micrht be caused by exaction of indemnity from 4 tribes that plundered Matra in 1877 (14-9). Turki agreed to payment of $1,000 arrears and thereafter $200 a month. Aziz accepted (13-12). 1881. Yusnf bin Abdur Rahman, Zanzibar Envoy, visited Maskat and by end. of 1880 project of Turki's abdication in favour of Barghash well known. Turki telegraphed ollering visit to Zanzibar, thereafter matter dropped (6-3). 1883 Presents no greater in value than those sent by Turki received from Zanzi bar (14-5). Turki wrote Barghash long account of Oman disturbances and asked for pecuniary help and confiscation of property of Juma -bin-Said, whom he described as ringleader of disturbances (23-11). 1884. Barghash sent Turki Rs. 32,000 in specie, largest present from Zanzibar since ±872. Turki sent horses, etc., in return (9—1). Saiyid Saud -bin-llamad, late Wali of Lamu, left Maskat on 2Uh February for Zanzibar on invitation to return. Property formerly confiscated; estate now offered him in Pemba (1,5). Saiyid Barghash of Zanzibar offered only §10,000 to heirs of Saiyid Ali his Wazir's estate (7-7). 1889. Zanzibar presented 6,000 lbs. gunpowder and 200 rifles with ammunition to Maskat (3i-l). Believed at Zanzibar that Aziz intended to seize Pemba and bad promised to remit clove-tax (2G-2).1890. Sultan Zmzibar sent Aziz Rs. 5,000 and requested he might not he allowed to come Zanzibar promising to supply reasonable wants (27-6). Government decided to detain Aziz if necessary to prevent his goin^ Zanzibar (1-7). Aziz wanted to go Zanzibar to arrange to succeed his brother if he survived him and to see his own plantations. Pressed for interview with Viceroy (15-9). Zanzibar willing to allow Rs. 600 per mensen to Aziz if did not eorne Zanzibar or ask for more (8-10). Aziz wished to go to Zanzibar and declined allowance of Rs. 600 a month (29-10). 1891. Sultan of Zanzibar indignant at Aziz's demands. Aziz's debts due to his attempts to dispossess brother of Maskat. Aziz had no plantations left at Zanzi bar except one small garden which Sultan would purchase. JSultan of Zanzi bar guaranteed right by British Government to choose own successor. Sultan, Zanzibar, finally resolved not to let Aziz return Zanzibar (29-1) Government advised Aziz to accept allowance and refrain from disturbing Oman and Zanzibar (24.3). Fahd went in Zanzibar steamer ' Avoca' to marry late Barghash's 3rd daughter at Zanzibar (15.11). 1892. Government refused to give pension or pay debts, hut would assist A.ziz in obtaining Zanzibar allowance. Aziz in Bombay (25-5). Aziz accepted allow ance and claimed arrears from arrival in Bombay, 20th June 1890. Offered to sell Zanzibar garden for $20,000 (10-6). Maskat willing to add Rs. dOO a month on condition Aziz lived out of Oman with his family and Maskat not res ponsible for his debts (7-8). Sultan Zanzibar willing to pay allowance from 24th Augrst 1892 merely, and would only bid for shamba if auctioned (3-9). Aziz claimed succession to Zanzibar and declined Rs. 400 per mensem offered by Maskat (1-10). 1893. Maskat offer raised to Rs. 600 a month (6-1). Zanzibar Sultan in precarious healtn. Nomination by him of Aziz would not be approved. Aziz therefore not to be allowed to leave for Zanzibar (22-2). Aziz informed if he attempted to leave India before being permitted he would be detained as State prisoner (9-3). Hamad -bin-Thaweynee invested with Sultanate of Zanzibar in succession to Sayid Ali. Aziz protested against own detention in India (lb-3). Aziz to be informed he would do well to recognise Hamad (21-3). Aziz in memorial to Gladstone stated Said at death left direction that sons should succeed in order of birth. Ibis in accordance with Zanzibar custom and Aziz now only surviving son, Majid and Bargash, elder; Xhalila, next to Aziz, succeeded in his absence; then Ali, also in absence of Aziz (17-3). Maskat offered Aziz Rs. 600 if he remained in India (3-5). Pending final settlement Zanzibar agreed ti increase allowance of Aziz to Rs. 800 ( 5-b). Zanzibar willing to pay Rs. 800 till shamba sold and to buy shawba for .SG,0J0, or would pay Rs. 5,000 down to extinguish mortgage on shamba and thereafter Es. 600 monthly ^8-6). Aziz declined to accept Maskat allowance on condition of expatriation from Oman (28-7). Aziz not to be informed of proposal to pay Rs. 5,000 down but only of proposal to buy shamba, which lie should be counselled to accept (8-8). Bombay Government recommended Rs. 2,000 as necessary for Aziz (12-8). Aziz declined to sell shaniba for ^5,000 (28.8). 1S94 Government of India forwarded to Secretary of State memorial from Aziz, urging claims to Sultanate of Zanzibar and requesting that prohibition against proceeding Zanzibar or elsewhere be cancelled, and that pending final orders debts be paid and suitable allowance fixed for maintenance in India. Aziz had comported self with dignity in trying position. Home Government by whose orders Aziz detained should settle about allowance ; Indian revenues not in any degree liable (31-1). Home Government did nothing (6-3). Maskat Arabs coming Zanzibar in numbers (19-1). Tour leading Sheikhs from Maskatwith large following arrived Zanzibnr on 13tli Tebruary. Projects for bringing Oman under Zanzibar possibly on foot (14-2). Sultan warned to have nothing to do with intrigue (22-3). Among Maskat Arabs at Zanzibar M ere Abdullah bin-Saleh-bin-Ali and Ilamud-bin-Said-ul-Jahati. Zanzibar Sultan ardent on project of re-union (2 t-3). Faisal to be cautioned about proceedinss of rebels at Zanzibar (24-5). At Maskat it was expected the 4 Sheikhs would not intrigue at Zanzibar, but possibly with Aziz. Relations between Maskat and Zanzibar strained. Faisal welcomed intriguers banished from Zanzibar and Hamad gave 2 field-pieces and 200 barrels powder to Sheikh Abdullah-bin- Saleh and 1 field-piece and 100 barrels powder to Sheikh Amir-bin-Salim. Further, Fahad tried to divorce wife, daughter of Barghash, without just causes (20-6) and committed suicide on l^th June possibly because unable to repay dowry and so obtain divorce (30-G). Government of India asked Sultan of Zanzibar might be res-trained from presenting tield-pieces and ammu nition to visitors from Maskat (14-8.). Sultan, Zanzibar, gave necessary assu rance but reluctantly (21-10). On request from Faisal Hamad sent him 500lbs. gunpowder Zmzibar Sultan promised in future not to give Maskat visitors more than customa-y sw )rd or dagger and robe of honour unless re. quested by Faisal (2-11). Nasr b n-Jumia, Hassani, and Jiadr-bin-Hilal, Hejriyin, from Maskat met with cold reception (26-11). 1895. Good reception to Sheikhs from Sur without letters from Faisal (7-1) Possible connection of Sultan of Z anzibar with rebellion atM iskat (9-3). Sul tan of Zanzibar in debt and selling houses and furniture. Partly due to extra vagant gift^ to Maskat Sheikhs in pursuance of policy encouraged by Hilal- bin-Amr, Maskati, his chief native adviser (brother of Mohsin-bin-Amr and son-in-law of S ileh-bin Ali, two leading Maskat rebels). Nearly persuaded to buy land in Oman where coal said to have been found (13-3). Eebels in Oman used Sultan of Zanzibar's name. Hardinge saw Sultan. He disclaimed connection with rebellion but promised to receive no more Maskat Sheikhs. Hardinge declined to give permission to German merchant to export muzzle loaders from Zanzibar to Koweit apparently on ground that they might be in troduced into Oman (8-4). Money being collected in Zanzibar for Oman rebels to be sent through Indian firm. $4,.' 00 already despatched. Sultan, Zanzibar, secretly favoured conspiracy as told by Hilal that an Azzan-bin-Kais puppet would be set up who would give him tribute in return for support (29-5.) Emissary of Saleh returned from Zanzibar with money, gunpowder and gold mounted dagger (22-6). Sultan of Zanzibar considerably alarmed at suspicions of Government about his connection with Maskat rising (13-8). 1896. Hardinge authorised to deport Hilal to Maskat: action postponed (28-1). Government of India thought Liilal should rather be detained at Aden (13-2). Hilal arrested by orders of Sultan, Zanzibar, after resistance, on 20th June and brought Aden on 30th June. Lodged in jail (3-7). Coalition of tribes in Sharkiya broke up and idea of appointing an Imam dropped on news of depor tation of Hilal from Zanzibar (15-8). Surveillance sufficient (19-8). Hilal permitted at request of new Sultan of Zanzibar, Hamud,.to live at Mombassa, Lamu or Kismayu on undertaking not to leave place selected (17—10). Inter ned at Mombassa (19-10). 1897. Hilal appealed for French intervention (30-6). Undesirable that Hilal should be allowed to return Oman as proposed; Sultan of Maskat regarded him as real cause of last rebellion (19-10). Seven Arab Sheikhs, deported from Zanzibar for attempt to usurp Sultanate reached Maskat on 22nd June, 2 months before intimation to Agent, JVlaskat (5-12). llilal not permitted to leave Mombassa, Lord Salisbury approving (23-12). Government of India advised return of Hilal should not be allowed (80'12).1898. Timely notice of deportations, etc., would be sent from Zanzibar to Mas- kat or Bushire in future (Nos. 23.2). On feast of sacrifices Sultan of Zanzibar cancelled sentences of deportation to Kismayu and Maskat of subjects who sup ported Saiyid Khalid's usurpation. Cases of Abdul Aziz and Hilal-bin-Amr reserved for consideration. Former protected by French Consul an4 working against British interests in Oman. Gulf authorities anxious to get rid of him, but presence equally undesired at Zanzibar. If French protection not recognised could be allowed to return and punished as local subject in event of giving trouble. Hilal might be allowed back; his only influence derived from Sultan. So llardinge (4-5) Saiyid Ali-bin-Salim returned voluntarily from Dar-us- Salam on 10th June and submitted to Sultan, Zanzibar. Sent to Maskat and Political Agent, Maskat infcrmed (16-6). Lord Salisbury vetoed return of Abdul Aziz (22-6) Hilal and his brother Abdullah allowed to return Zanzibar without reference to India or Home Government (25-8). 1901. Hilal returned Sur unexpectedly on 19th May, foregathered with Ottavi and advised Jennebeh elders to take French papers and flags (20-6). Govern ment of India proposed Sultan, Maskat, niigbt be informed he was at liberty to expel Hilal (16-8). Approved (5-10). Threatening letter sent to Faisal by Isa-bin-Saleh, Harthi, (Saleh died 1S96) in connection with manumission of slaves. Hand of Hilal undoubtedly visible in this (18-10). Cases of Saiyid Ali-bin-Salim-bin-Thoweynee and Abdul Aziz-bin Huwahi, Dragoman of Irench Consul at Maskat: latter b-anished from Zanzibar in 1893 with Hilal. Agent at Maskat favoured return of both to Zanzibar (29-9). Cave declined to promote return of Ali bin-Salirn (6-12). No steps for removing Abdul Aziz from Maskat against his will seemed admissible, while he was Dragoman of French Consulate and therefore under French protection, unless proved guilty of serious offence that would necessitate dismissal from French employ ment. So Foreign Office to India Office, (10-12). 1901. Return of Aziz to Zanzibar undesirable while negotiations pending for aban donment by France of extra-territorial jurisdiction there (13-3;. 1903. Death of Sultan of Zanzibar, about 18tb July 1902, did not remove objee- • tion to return of Ali-bin-Salim (10-13).53 E —BRITISH POLICY IN MASKAT. 1872. Ibrahim claimed that all movements by sea should be prevented by Gov ernment as was done when Turki was fighting Azan-bin-Ghes : ' permission to M askat Government to reinforce garrison on coast by sea cannot be continued, now that a state of war exists in Maskat territory .... all military operations by sea must be prevented ' (telegram of 7th January 1871) (1-6). No need to notify views of Government of India about hostilities by sea, Government of India thought to do so would be direct encouragement to rebels to com mence hostilities by sea (31-10). 1873. Sir Bartle Frere and Colonel Pelly at Maskat on mission from Queen (19-4) • Every effort to be made to capture Abdul Aziz should he proceed to sea (20-8). Aglia Khan denied helping Aziz and said on contrary he had sent Turki Us. 5,000 (23'!S). Abdul Aziz left Gwetter night of 7th September (11-9). ' Riflemen' with Mockler captured Aziz near Sur with 11 armed men and arrived Maskat IHth September (-4-9). Aziz refused Turki's terms and even increased allowance of |500 (19-9). Aziz conveyed md Gwadur to Karachi and kept there in honorable surveillance under Regulation III of 1818 (24!'9). 1874. Turki requested Government to move Barghash of Zanzibar to release Khalifa, who might reside at Maskat, f^om imprisonment (29-6). Turki granted 2,00'^ shot for field-guns, on payment, from Bombay Arsenal (10-6). Inquiry made of Barghash about Khalita (30-7). Secretary of State approved of action of Government of India in supporting and actively assisting Turki by maritime operations, while prohibiting operations ashore; this in connection with Mesnaah and Soweik disturbances (17 9). Barghash willing to release Khalifa who had been in strict confinement since abortive rising about January 1872, if he would leave Africa. Khalifa appeared unwilling to go to Maskat (23 -9). Turki on learning facts dropped matter (15-12). • 1875. Turki requested assistance of Resident in obtaining Bandar Abbas on same terms as predecessors (2 -4). Resident replied he could not advance his interests : this in view of reforms introduced by Shah into provincial adminis tration and bis evident desire to improve country and strengthen position (15—5). Persian Government complained to British Minister at Teheran that Tuiki had seized and disposed of hereditary property of Haji Ahmed Khan, ex-Governor of Bandar Abbas, Persian subject; good offices of Minister requested. In case of failure Persian Government would retaliate on Maskatis in [Persia (29.-4). Haji Ahmad left Maskat in 18G8, subsequently removed all personal property. Turki's accession not till 2 years later. Haji Ahmad still owned 2 houses in Maskat and share, conjointly with brothers and sisters, in house at Maskat and landed property in Oman (8-7). Turki expressed hish satisfaction with Miles and Mockler and hoped he might be accommodated with money while at Gwadur (8-9). Salim after escape from Gwadur resided at Kishm. On 2nd October Abdul Aziz reported Salim had left Kishm for Oman coast- S;ilim captured by boat of ' Daphne ' about midnight, 10th October, near Sowadi Islands with 'd baghlas and 40 men. Salim was to have landed at Hail. Salim said he did not intend to oppose present rule, but only to see about private pension of $150, which had been discontinued during Turki's absence (12-10). Tnrki suggested ' the parricide ' Salim should be made over to him (20-10). Warrant for Salim's detention under III of 1818 issued (3-12). Claim of Rs 10,098 against Turki for ordnance stores to bo allowed to stand over (13-12). It was believed Salim assassinated his father in February iSCB at Soha^. Thereafter he ruled in his place at Maskat till deposed by Azzan-bin-Ghais. Salim then fled Bandar Abbas. He made several unsuccessful attempts to regain Maskat. In May 1870 he was a54 xranderar on Oman littoral without means of raising a party. In January 1871 Azzan was killed in battle and Salim thenceforth intrigued against Azzan's successor Turki, his own uncle. Harib captured with S dim was allow ed to go (12-4)}. 1876. Salim ''requested intercession of Turki for his release (3-1). On 23rd May, Miles at Palace handed over 2 field pieces and 2 rocket tubes to Turki as return gift from Government under salute from 'Vestal' (26-5). Expenses of arrest, etc., of Salim and allowance of $ 100 a month promised by Turki to be deducted from Zanzibar subsidy (16-6). Turki refused to increase Salim's allowance as he was supporting mother and family separately (18-6). Four boxes Hale's war rockets also to be supplied to Turki (26-10 , Salim died of small-pox on 7th December (9-12). 1879. Turki wished to have an agent at Bandar Abbas to protect Maskat subjects (30-1). Resident thought idea should be discourasred (23-2). Turki sent telegram through his VVazir, Saiyid Said, to Foreign Minister of Shah's Gor- ernment at Teheran soliciting lease of Bandar Abbas on same terms as actual lessee. Peshkash promised in case of success. Telegram sent after Agent had given him unfavourable opinion as to probable success (27-2). Turki to be informed admission of Maskat Agent at Bandar Abbas rested with Persian Gov ernment. In December 1871, when British Minister tried to arrange lease of Bandar Abbas to Maskat, Sadr Azam stated no agent of Maskat there would be officially recognised. 1880- Wazir, Saiyid Said, in fear of dismissal, imprisonment, etc. ; direct inter vention not considered advisable. 1882. Turki sent horse to Miles at Zanzibar (9—2). 1883. Government of India sanctioned purchase by Turki from Bombay Arsenal of 4,000 round shot, J 12-pr , ^ 18-pr. (2-5) Government of India authorised Resident to assist Sultan unofficially in obtaining 3 drill masters for his Sidi and Baluch retainers (9-5). 1884. Time to make a return present to Turki. Last was 100 muskets in 1879, Government of India asked Secretary of State to send a one-barrel Gardner machine fgun with 5,000 rounds (27-6). Harness for 2 brass 6-pr., field pieces, presented by Government, renewed (9 -10). G. ' 1885. [ For notes as to policy of support to Sultan of Maskat, see Pros. External A., March 1886, Nos. 142-152] Gatling gun arrived and was presented to Turki (1-3). Continued rumours of disaffection in Sharkiya. Saleh held council of war at Path on 2Uth July (28). Resident suggested that, in view of large British commercial interests at stake, general friendly relations between British Government and Turki and aetive support already on some occasions accorded. Government should adopt definite line of policy as regards attacks on Maskat and Matra ; and Abdul Aziz and other revolutionary leaders should be informed that, even in event of gaining possession of those towns temporarily, they would be driven out by British Government and Turki replaced in posses sion. Such an intimation would effectually stop frequent risings and scares (12-8). Government of India feared this change of policy might commit it to necessity of propping up by force of arms a ruler who had already by his55 failure proved incapacity to govern. Policy had been to support de facto ruler and assist hira in quelling tribal disturbances ; that proposed might involve support of a Sultan de jure who could not hold his own without it. Action advocated entailed serious responsibility in Turki's lifetime and might be very embarrassing after his death as children would claim similar aid (16-9). Re sident replied not so much a change of policy desired as a more definite, consist ed and effective carving out of present policy. In practice, responsibility conld not be greater than that already assumed in case of attacks on Maskat, and embarrassing situations would be avoided to greater extent. Policy meant to apply to Turki only, not to successors. Normal and permanent policy should be as heretofore non-interference in dynastic strugsrles and internal adminis tration and avoidance of employment of armed force. Armed intervention when resorted to should be thorough. Turki's case was exceptional: impossible with credit, and consequently with expediency, to refuse armed support when solicited by him. To refuse help to Turki now would be a policy of abandon ment. Prom the fu st Turki had relied wholly on British Government and carried out its advice implicitly to best of his power. His straight-forward co-operation in slave trade matters had given a handle to his enemies. If Turki were ousted it would be blow to British prestige in Oman. Leading men would by proposed poliey be deterred from advancing on Maskat at all. Turki would not rely too much on support and neglect defensive measures nor would he take advantage of it to practise oppression (7-10). Miles entirely concurred with Ross. If rebels occupied town in spite of fire of ships could they be allowed to remain there ? Even Said, alter 20 or 80 years rule, would more than once have been expelled but for Indian Navy. Turki a weak but not a bad ruler. Had conciliated people and followed Arab ideal of Sheikh of Sheikhs, primus inter pares. On Turki's death Arabs should be allowed to choose their own ruler. None of his sons by Arab mother (17-10). • 1886. Government of India reposing confidence in Colonel Ross's knowledge of situation and in soundness of his judgment decided to follow his recommenda tion. Resident authorised to announce promise to Sultan and to his rivals and enemies (9-2). Secretary of; State entertained grave doubts as to policy and regretted he had not been consulted before issue of orders. Support only to be continued while Sultan's administration not unsatisfactory to Government of India. Glad that Colonel Ross had been instructed to point out clearly to Sultan that the concession was personal (31-3). Announcement made by Mockler on 33th July in presenting insignia of K.G.C.S.I. (17-7). 36 rockets to be supplied to Turki on payment (10-11). 1887. Twelve cast-iron 12-pr. muzzle-loading guns, with usual proportion of am munition, to be supplied to Sultan free of charge (return present for gold- mounted swords, etc., presented by him) as armament for forts Merani and Jalali (2-8). 1888. Sultan died 3 p.m ., 4th June (6-6). Faisal assumed government and hoped friendship of Government might be continued to him and promised steadfastly to carry out orders. Solicited Government to grant protection and favour (6-6). During Turki's funeral ' Turquoise ' fired royal salute and-British and American flags were flown J mast high till 7th. Every thing quiet (20-6j. Resident reached Maskat on 11th (20-6). Ross advised Government not to recognise Eaisal, but to continue subsidy for purpose of carrying on de facto Government and maintaining order (18-6). Government of India recommended continuance of subsidies and trusted Her Majesty's Government would contribute share (1:9-6), Aziz claimed succession and asked intentions of Government (9-7). Government of India supported Ross's proposal to Secretary of State viz., to hear proposals of Aziz and perhaps thus bring about peaceful settlement. If not, Government of India could still avoid committing selves to any party in Oman State (11-7).56 1889. Chance of dynastic struggle terminated. Government of India recom mended recognition of Faisal to Secretary of State (22-1), Secretary of State sanctioned formal recognition of Faisal (8-3). Recognition postponed. Inti mate correspondence between Ibrahim and Aziz, llinawis restless, Faisal discontinued Turki's allowance to Ibrahim. Resident recommended modus vivendi with Ibrahim and acceptance of proposals from Aziz. Faisal pro mised to appoint Muhammad-bin-Azzan as confidential channel of communica tion with Agent (4-5). Secretary of State informed of postponement of recognition (l4!-6). 1890. On ri port of A^ent and Resident Government of India smctioned formal recognition of Faisal (27-3). Formal recognition was communicated by Resi dent at Maskat on 6th April with some ceremony. Faisal in Darbar expressed earnest desire to be guided in all important matters of policy by advice of British Government (7-4) Foreign Office asked India Office what ground f(!r con sidering Maskat to be under British protection, as inferred from an India Office letter relating to slave trade. In view of Viceroy's opinion as to undesirablity of Foreign Powers having treaty relations with loc i 1 Chiefs under British pro tection might it not be expedient to take precautions to prevent any other power from interfering with Maskat (9-7). India Office replied Sultan of Maskat had not entered into any formal treaty with Indian Govern ment by which his territory was placed under protectorate. Hut as treaties of friendship had been exchanged with Imams of Maskat since 1798 ; as pay ment of $ 40,000 per annum was made to Sultan by Government of India ; as recent rulers had sought and obtained formal recognition from that Govern ment, and as British influence had been predominant in Oman for years past, term ' protection ' was used to indicate that stability of administration of rulers of Maskat was largely due to moral and material support derived by them from their connection with Indian Government. Secretary of State for India, however considered time had arrived when existing relations might be further affirmed and defined by conclusion of Protectorate treaty on bases of those lately concluded with Chiefs of Arab tribes on littoral from Shnikh Sayid to Ras iSair. Opinion of Government of India would be asked first however (16-7). Correspondence forwarded to Government of India (18-7). Lord Salisbury thought in present state of French feeling any action contrary to convention of 1862 would be much resented and that therefore disadvantage of stirring question at this paiticular moment out-weighed any advantage likely to be gained from it by country (1-8). Government of India informed of Lord Salisbury's opinion (8-b). Government of India observed that an un derstanding with France was apparently a necessary preliminary to British Protectorate, but this was a matter for His M ijesly's Government. On gen eral grounds there were good reasons for asserting a virtual protectorate over Maskat and if British relations with country and rulers for more than a cen tury were taken into account, no power could with justice deny that Maskat fell Irgitimately within sphere of British influence. Instances, 1st, arbitration of Lord Canning and Zanzibar subsidy ; 2nd. since Said no Sultan had been able to establish himself vuthout recognition of British Government and nothing to show any other Government ever appl'ed to for recognition; 3rd, between 1866 and 1881 Government of India had several times interfered in dynastic ^ disputes and interned claimants or pretenders in India; 4th., in 1874 British fleet had shelled rebels out of AJesnaah and exacted indemnity for British subjects; 5th, in 1877 ' Teazer ' had caused rebels to retire from Ma^kat; t'th Dutch irenty with Maskat had been negotiated through British Resident and Agent; 7th, in 18S3 Phelomel ' shelled rebel's camps and prevented their en tering Maskat. British trade and number of subjects in Maskat far exceeded those of any other European or American country. Only British had telegraph interests on coast; and police of sea had for many years past been carried on by Her Majesty 's ships alone (8 9). Secretary of S ate for India recommended establishment of exclusive British protectorate over Maskat at earliest oppor tunity on which adhesion of France could be obtained \9-10). Lord Salisbury57 replied not practicahle at present moment; but, in any future negotiations with France, Indian view would be borne in mind (16-10). Secretary of State for India concurred in suggestion of Lord Salisbury tbat ratification of Commercial Treaty between Great Britain and Maskat would offer opportu nity to propose to Sultan a declaration in which His Highness should engage that neither be nor his heirs and successors should cede, mortgage or otherwise give for occupation any portion of his dominions save to Her Britannic Maj- estv's Government. This would not be a violation of declaration of 1862. Government of India should take steps accordingly on ratification ot new Commercifil Treaty being announced (71-1). 1891. Draft declaration as to non-cession of territory sent to Uesident (11-2). Declaration signed by Sultan and Ross on 20tli March 1891, Ratified by Viceroy on 23rd May 1891 (31-3). Copy sent to Secretary of State (2-6). Triplicate copy delivered to Sultan on 9th July (11-7). Original asked for by Secretary of State for transmission to Eoreign Oflice (10-7). 1892. 10,000 lbs. of gun-powder asked for by Sultan could not be spared, but Government of India promised to issue export lieense, His Highness buying privately in Bombay market (3-12). 1893. Actirg Resident, Hayes Sadler, t^ok up* case of African boatman whipped to death by Saiyid Fahad. Government of India desired no further action miaht be taken as British Government not concerned (26-7). Sultan omitted to salute Hayes Sadler proceeding on duty on 10th December to take up Residency. 1894. On remonstrance Sultan replied (falsely) that it had never been custom to salute officers at departure as well as on arrival. He wished matter referred to Government of India and would abide by their opinion (28-2). Govern ment of India ordered Sultan to be informed of previous practice and that diminution of customary ceremonial distinctions discourteous ; hint also to be dven of possible alteration in honours paid by Government to Sultan (24-5). Sultan undertook to salute on departure also (27-8). 1895. On report of Hayes Sadler and AVilson, following rebellion, Government of India placed three courses before Secretary of State : (1) to annex Maskat and Matra and pension Sultan; (2) to declare protectorate over Oman and (3) to intimate to leading Sheikhs of Oman that, whatever diljerences they might have with their Sultan, the Government of India would not permit attacks on Maskat and Matra. Government of India thought protectorate desirable, but that it might not be prudent to open negotiations with France. Object of warning to Sheikhs would be to safeguard lives and property of Indian subjects and British Indian trade. Disturbances were likely to recur so long as policy of strict non-intervention observed; a t nd unless steps were taken to define BrHish position, discussions with France as well as Sultan and tribes might arise. French interest in Persian Gulf had revived; French Vice-Consul had been appointed at Maskat and French cruiser sent Maskat in connection with recent disturbances. Warning to Sheikhs was only for protection of existing political interests and need not be objected to as constituting a practi cal step in advance towards protectorate in effect though not in name ; such a result, however, would only be to our advantage. Course merely a modification of Dufferin's policy which directly in Turki's reign, and indirectly until recent ly) gave Oman unparalleled rest from internal dissensions (9-7). On bihMarch ' Nadiri ' of B. &amp; P. S. N. Co. flying British colours came into Maskat harbour carrying 25 Harthis whom Jenebeh boatmen, from fear of Sultan, refused to land at Sur. Sultan demanded surrender on ground that they were his enemies: Political Agent refused (9-4). Sultan complained to Viceroy (12-4). Government of India approved Agent's action and Viceroy replied to Sultan (14-6). Faisal wrote to Viceroy reporting failure of rebellion and hoping for Viceroy's favour (11-4). Viceroy congratulated Faisal on retreat of enemies and restitution of order and security in Maskat (28-4). Saleh wrote thanking Agent, Maskat, for refusal to surrender Harthis (16-5). No answer sent (8-6). Secretary of State expressed satisfaction at observance by local officers in 1S95 of policy of non-interference in dynastic struggles or internal administration laid down in 1886, also at arrangements made for in- demnifyine: British Indian subjects (2-8). Foreign Offiee ordered inquiry to be made at Zanzibar into complicity, gravely suspected, of Zanzibar iSultan in Masqat rising ( 2-8 ). Secretary of State recommended that, in event of assent of France to British Protectorate over Maskat being unobt.iiaable. Her Majesty's Government should, in defence of existing commercial interests, undertake to protect Maskat and Matra from attacks of rebel Arab tribesmen (3 2-8). Lord Salisbury concurred that leading Sheikhs of Oman should be warned that, whatever differences they might have with their Sultan, Government of India would not permit attacks on Maskat and Matra : he also desired to be informed of exnct terms in w r hich warning might be conveyed (^2-8) Resident was authorised to communicate orders to Sultan for notideation to Sheikhs ; but Sultan must not consider himself absolved from taking proper measures for protection. Notification by Sultan to Sheikhs should be approved by Resident (8-10) Intimation not received by Sultan with the cordiality expected : he treated it as a matter of course. No opportunity driven Resident to warn Sheikhs, etc., personally (10-11). Sultan's notification duly issued to Sheikhs ( 15-12). 1896. Sultan wished to postpone assembling of Sheikhs to h^ar warning as it vrould cost $ 2,000 (31-1). Agent to be instructed merely to impress the warning on Sheikhs visiting Maskat (10-2). Secretary of State informed of the proceedings up to date (19-2). So far as could be ascertained all monies received from Zanzibar were for commercial purposes (28-4). Believed at Zanzibar attempt would be made to send guns for rebels by 'Avoca' under Zanzibar flag (28-4). Two 5^ inch mortars with beds and ammunition were presented to Sultan by Resident from Government of India on 29th May (24-6). Sultan of Maskat's attitude was very unsatisfactory, especially in regard to Dhofar. Indications of active French intrigues at Maskat and on Arab coast. Might Madagascar atfairs afford opportunity of securing French consent to British Protectorate over Maskat r— So Viceroy by telegram to Secretary of State ( 25-6 ). Secretary of State wired reply that Foreign Office appreciated importance of trying to secure protectorate, but considered measure could not be successfully accomplished at present time. 1898. On arrival of Resident and Agent in ^Lawrence' on 1st January, Sultan fired 31 guns, but did not hoist British flag : this not noticed at time and salute was assumed to be Empress's Resident subsequently informed that omission intentional and asked Sultan for explanation. Sultan replied New Year's Day salute to all Christian narions, not compliment to Queen-Em press. Resident replied stopping of customary compliment unfriendly and Sultan must fire salute at once and keep British flag flying all day. This done on 3rd January Sultan also expressed regret for omission in writing and promised observance of occasion in^ luture (5-1). Government of India approved action, but reminded Resident that Her Majesty's Government specially desired to maintain friendly relations with, as well as influence over. Sultan in view ol i rench activity. Resident should remind Sultan of assistance given him in financial matters and at Dhofar (8-1), On 2 H th January Kibrit, a Ghulam oi Sultan, assaulted Gunner Jennings of ' Cossack,' who was accompaniedhj Lieutenants Brandon and Sterling. Sabir-bin-Sowaid, an official of Sultan's household, took all three cffioers forcibly to Reiyam gate and detain- ed them th&lt; re. Tautik-bin-Ali, another Sultan's official, arrived ; and they were taken in custody to palace and there released. Poiitical Agent returned Maskat on 30th and succeeded in getting Kibrit publicly flogged on 5th Feb ruary, while other two were marched off in irons to jail (9-2J. Latter two were released on 10th April at Agent's request (11-4). 1899. Secretary of State informed Viceroy with reference to Jissa difTiculty, etc., that Declaration of jS()2 must be maintained and respected; subject to this any measure not requiring French concurrence, and likely to be effective would be approved (3-1). Political Agent directed to ask Sultan about lease of .lissa and warn him it would be contrary to engagement of 18^1, and could not be permitted by British Government. If Sultan admitted lease, Agent should protest and wire to Government of India for orders (11-1). On iCth January Political Agent called at Jissa and returned Maskat. Local Sheikh at Jissa said Irench V ice-Consul and Commander had taken photos and made rough plans in October 1898. Officer and boats's crew of ' Sphinx ' left at Jissa,* to hoist British flag if French man-of-war came in. Sultan postponed answer on 16th and on 17th admitted he had granted French (Gov ernment) a place to store coal, but locality not yet fixed. Fagan protested verbally, on ground of infringement of engagement of 1891. Sultan denied infringement and said promise given and he could not 'snatch ''place from French, British might ' snatch ' it if they liked. On 18th Fagan protested again in writin?. On 19th Sultan sent rejoinder drifted at French Vice- Consulate asserting English and French -equality, mentioning English coaling sheds and refusins: discussion. Russian spy pr.'srnt in Maskat, interviewing Sultan and Ottivi, and promising visit of Russian man-of-war and establish ment of Russian Consulate (*21 1;. Action reported by Government of India by telegram on 19th approved by Secretary of State, but hoisting of British flag at Jissa to mean not appropriation of territory but prevention and punish ment (if violation of 1891 agreement Subsidy to be withheld pending inquiry into French concession (20-1). 'Redbreast' to leave Bombay for' Maskat on J5th January (23-1). Secretary of State wired Sultan might be reminded, 1st, of his formal recognition by British Government notwithstanding claims of Abdul Aziz, who had hither o been prevented from leaving India; 2nd, that Zanzibar subsidy was conditional on Sultan continuing faithful in ful filling engagements and manifesting friendship towards British Government; 3rd, that British Government in 1895 warned Abdullah-bin-Saleh to cease from attacking Sultan and had repeatedly used their good offices to uphold his authority lie might be warned that, in event of unfriendly attitude on his part, diplomatic and military support would be withdrawn and might pos sibly take another direction. If anything else necessary, such as removal Abtlul Aziz, Government of India could demand it on authority of former telegram of 3rd January (25-1). On 22nd January Fagan wrote to Sultan that if he had only given French a cove in harbour for coaling, as to English, he could easily prove it. Subsidy ordered by Government to be withheld till satisfactory explanation forthcoming. On 25th Sultan replied no cove available in Maskat except Makalla and no difference between Maskat and other parts of his dominions. No greater rights had been given to French than to English. Friendly relations were earnestly desired by him. On 26th Fagan answered he did not mean that French could have a cove in Maskat. ^f the concession to French Government were not a contravention of 1891 agreement. Sultan should produce documents in proof. On 27th Fagan point ed out a cove separated irom Makalla by signal station as sutitable for a coaling place. On 2^th Sultan declined to produce documents as heing contrary to custom of independent States. On 2£&lt;th Sultan piotested against Agency flag-staff being placed on ground instead of roof ; on 26th Pagan explained reason was that weight was injurious to roof. None of Sultan's letters con tained reference to 1S91 agreement. Fagan frankly informed British Indians of Sultan's attitude to Government and of suspension of subsidy : he looked to ♦ N ote .—Good descript-on of JUsa at rroceedingg Secret E., February 1899, No 183.GO them to do nothing to assist Sultan in withstanding just demands of Govern ment O l India. Sultan on 27th complained that Fagan had forbidden British Indians to do business with him: Fagan on 28th replied he had merely in formed them of situation and perhaps they thought Sultan's security inadequate. Recall on 22nd of ' Sphinx's ' boat from Jissa taken as si^n of weakness ; so sent back there. Suitan in great financial difficulties. No particulars of Sultan's agreement with French Government ascertainable (28-1). On 29th January Fagan pointed out to Sultan that question was contravention of agreement of 1891, not merits or demerits of place granted to French. On 1st February Sultan reiterated that concession to French was same as that to English. Uouse said to be in preparation by Sultan for a Russian representative (4-2). Resi dent exchanged ceremonial visits with Sultan. Sultan appeared to be relying on French refusal to surrender concession. Resident asked leave to use naval force if necessary. If Sultan found impracticable claim of Muhammad-bin- Turki to succession might be considered (8 2)'. Secretary of State objected to addition by Meade of condition about cancellation of lease to French, but if demand had been already presented, authority to compel compliance might be given on condition, no collision took place with French. A demand for the forcible deportation of Abdul Aziz might be against Declaration of 1862 (9-2). Viceroy informed Secretary of State that demand for cancellation Jissa lease was added by his orders to present ultimatum; to omit chief ground of oflfence from it would be wrong. Was compulsion authorised to enforce all demands, or only to obtain cancellation of Jissa lease ? No intention of requiring depor tation Abdul Aziz (10-2). Secretary of State replied compulsion was sanc tioned for all demands including dismissal of Abdul Aziz.. Cancellation of lease was in excess of instructions, but enforcement thereof also agreed to. Condition, no personal collision with French. Discretion to be used in matter of indemnity to avoid raising hostile local feeling (11-2). Viceroy replied not whole indemnity, but only interest on unpaid portion (which Sultan had sometime before agreed to give) was being demanded (12-2). Situation com municated to Resident and he directed to consult Admiral Douglas, who left Bombay on 11th, throughout proceedings (12 2). On afternoon, 9th, Arabic translation of Memorandum read to Sultan and left with him. Demands were— 1. Permanent dismissal of Abdul Aziz from Maskat service. 2. Payment of 5 par cent, interest on balance of 1895 indemnity. '3. Cessation of levy from British subjects everywhere of taxes not levied from Maskat subjects. 4. Eeduction of all import duties to 5 per cent, ad valorem and of tax on dates from interior to 6 per cent. 5. Public cancellation of agreement with French or other power grant ing port, harbour or piece of land. Discussion refused and 48 hours given for reply. On 10th French Consul wrote to Sultan saying he could not recognise agreement of 1891, of which Sultan had sent him copy, and which was contrary to declaration of 1802. Agreement about coaling place voluntary and could not be can celled. Should difficulties arise, French Consul would have them removed in accordance with declaration of 1S62. On llth Sultan wrote to Resi dent that grant of coaling place was not cession of territory and therefore not contrary to agreement of 1891; he hoped for clemency and forwarded French Consul's letter of 10th. On 12c,h Resident replied returning M. Ottav^'s letter and denying his right to intervene in a matter relating to 1891 agreement. Heminded Sultan that period of grace had expired. On 13th Sultan sent written notice of revocation of gift of coaling place to French and requested British protection against French if necessary. On 14th Admiral Douglas arrived. On 15th Resident wrote to Sultan that he should announce cancellation in Darbar, and post up notification to same elfect, besides informing French Consul by letter and sending copy of letter to Resident. He should also signify compliance with other four demands. Sultan ought not to have sent copy of British agreement of 1891 to French Consul, but having done so he should61 supply Agent with copy of French agreement (15-2). No answer from Sultan, and Kesident placed matters in hands of Admiral who peremptorily summoned Sultan to come aboard flag-ship ' Eclipse ' at 2 p.m ., and caused ' Eclipse ' to be warped broadside on to the town and shipping to be cleared out of line of fire. Immediately after, letter arrived from Sultan with documents pur porting to be copies of public notification published in Maskat and Matra and of letter of cancellation (on ground of 1891 agreement) to French Consul and of agreement with French about coalinsr place (last dated 7th March 1898). &gt; Resfdent decided these were not sufficient and requested Admiral to obtain full compliance. No notice was taken of a letter from Sultan statin? a Darbar had been convened and seeking to avoid visit to flag-ship. Admiral refused . even to allow brother of Sultan on board at 1 p.m . Ultimately Sultan came on board before 2 pm . After prolonged discussion he placed himself un reservedly in bands of British Government and left ship under salute of 21 guns. On Itith French Consul protested in writing against cancellation of lease and Sultan wrote Jenebeh to return flags accepted by them from foreign powers. On 17th Sultan requested French Consul to use some person other than Abdul Aziz, Eeuwahi, as a medium of communication, on the ground that he could not be received into tbe Sultan's house in future. Same day Sultan informed French Vice-Consul that he did not recognise French jurisdiction over Maskat subjects on Maskat soil: French practice was contrary to decla ration of 1862. On 17th Admiral called on Sultan and in afternoon at general darbar, attended by all leading men of Maskat, Sultan announced renewal of amicable relations with British Government and cancellation of agreement with French for coaling-place, which had been entered into in forgetfulness of rights of British Government (18-1). Instructions not to insist on public cancellation of French agreement reached M^skat too late. Viceroy instructed Resident that Sultan might be assured of support, including protection against France if necessary if he continued to follow British advice. Subsidy might be paid to him, future continuance to be dependent on friendly behaviour. Sultan, on renewal of subsidy, should be invited to promise due regard in future to advice of British representative Secretary of State and Foreign Office considered public cancellation of lease a serious mistake (19-2)] (20-2). Secretary of State, with reference to these instructions, authorised assurance of effective support to Sultan if necessary ; but hoisting of British flag for that purpose would be unnecessary and indefensible. Continued presence of British Naval force at Mlaskat should be sufficient. Inquired particulars as to British coal depot at Maskat (21-2). French Ambassador complained to Salisbury of excessive action of British Admiral at Maskat, o£ publicity and of tone of press. Dissented from Salisbury's view that independence of Maskat seriously threatened if either signatory of 1862 declaration, acting as a Sovereign State, could lease Maskat territory. Denied designs of permanent^ occupation and objected to acquisition of coaling station in name of French^citizen. Suggest ed France should retain acquisition and formally disclaim inferences deroga tory to Maskat independence or suggesting establishment of French rights on littoral (24-2). Sultan of Maskat appealed to Constantinople for help in his differences with England. Porte not disposed to meddle in matter (24-2). Viceroy did not dispute of treaty rights of France, but regarding her policy as hostile protested against their exercise in unfriendly manner, where French interests were insignificant and British interests supreme. Strongest objection to revival of Jissa arrangement after compelling its cancellation, French in trigues at Maskat were designed solely to annoy Great Britian and assist Russian policy in Gulf. Parity of treaty-right, but no other parity (25-2). French Government accepted English reading of Treaty of 1862, that neither State might accept any cession or lease of Maskat territory, and they no longer pressed proposal that they should keep grant of Jissa under formal assurances excluding idea of territorial right. They wished coal dep6t on exactly same terms as English, viz., on sufferance (27-2). Secretary of btate directed Govern ment of India to write to Sultan expressing satisfaction at his acceding to the terms and binding himself to abide by advice of Agent. If hereafter French Government asked for coaling facilities British Government would not object if request were limited to shed or sheds and carried no territorial or political rights. Result of recent action combined with such procedure should be to establish for future,62 with tacit assent of Erencli Government, paramount position in Maskat of British Government, (28-2). Sultan still reoeiving Abdul Aziz by day and night Abdul Aziz in Sharkiya endeavouring to raise tribes against British (28-2). Viceroy suspended communication proposed by Secretary of State, informing the latter. Agent authorised to withhold subsidy if facts as stated about Abdul Aziz (1-3). Full despatch to Secretary of State (2 3). On 2Sth February Fagan visited Sultan and latter promised to carry out wishes of Government about Abdul Aziz, but on 1st March Sultan again received Abdul Aziz (13). Ottavi saw Fagan and tried unsuccessfully to get him to withdraw objections to Abdul Aziz dealing with Sultan (6-3). British Law Officers held (1) that declaration of 1862 did not require British Government to abstain from exer cising predominant influence iu Maskat, so long as that influence not exerted in way inconsistent with independence of Maskat. Subsidy, and terms on which payable, involved no breach of declaration. (2) British Government would be justified in punishing and even deposing a particular Sultan who broke engage ments with British Government. Consent of France not necessary. It would be breach of declaration if after deposition a Sultan were set up who was not independent. Sultan could not consistently with independence of Maskat be compelled to accept Ministers and advisers acceptable to British Government (8-3). Sultan was not required not to receive Abdul Aziz. Sultan apparently wrote spontaneously to M. Ottavi that he could not receive Abdul Aziz. Latter !had been regularly paid by Sultan from November 1895 to October ]898-thu3 Viceroy to Secretary of State (14-3). Tribes inflamed by Abdul Aziz wrote to Sultan offering their assistance against British (14-3). On 7th March French Consul informed Sultan that France and England had arrived at a settle ment ; that France had secured from England an assurance that the independ ence of Maskat would be respected and that no objection would now be raised by British Government to grant of coal-dep6t by Sultan to France. French Consul stated he would not press Sultan to receive Abdul Aziz. After this visit Sultan's attitude improved, but subsidy was still withheld (14-3). ^ Abdul Aziz was in Sultan's employ in 1893 before Ottavi arrived in 1894 from Zanzibar (17-3). On 12th March Sultan paid 1st friendly visit overpaid by him to Political Agent at Agency. His attitude was improving daily (16-3). Fagan informed Sultan no objection to French coaling shed in Maskat harbour similar to English, no political or territorial rights being involved, provided British Government consulted as to situation and conditions and assent given. Proposal from French Consul to be submitted to Fagan in writing (20-3). Ottavi, when challenged, pretended ignorance of dual employment of Abdul Aziz and Sultan pretended Abdul Aziz not in his permanent employ ment; both pretences false (21-3). Mirza Muhammad Mohsin Ali Khan, ordinary Moghal of Lucknow, was convicted by Sessions Court, Fyzabad, under Section 471, fndian Penal Code, of using a forged document as genuine and sentenced, on 23rd October 1897, to two years' rigorous imprisonment and Rs. 300 fine. Appeal was dismissed on 25th February 1898 and accused (who had been liberated on bail) absconded. On 8th July Sultan, Maskat, wrote, and on 11th telegraphed to Viceroy asking pardon for Mohsiu Ali who had taken refuge at Maskat. Sultan ordered on 8th December to be informed that Vice roy was unable to interfere in view of facts; inquiry made of Resident, with reference to telegram of Agent pronouncing Mohsin Ali mischievous character, whether warrant for his arrest in Maskat, legality of which doubtful, should be issued. Resident recommended matter should stand over as Ag:ent now reported title of ' Private Secretary' bestowed by Sultan on Mohsin Ali purely honour- ary, and man had brought over family and was giving no trouble (19-2). Agent was directed to bring necessity for distinctive Maskat flag to Sultan's notice (26 3). Sultan appeared to be under impression that recent action of Indian Government was about to be repudiated by Her Majesty's Government (28-3). Sultan inquired if similar advice about flag had been given to Zanzibar and said he would consult Jenebeh (5-4). Government of India pointed out tiiat Zanzibar was a British protectorate and that in recommendation of use of distinctive flag Sultan should see a recognition of his position, which in his own interests he would do well to accept (3-6). Grant of coaling-station to French was apparently arranged during visit of gun boat ' Gabtis' in February to March ,1898 (18-3). Muhammad-bin-Azzan,'VTazIr hostile to Sultan because of his former dismissal, fine and impri sonment, and would like to embroil Sultan with British. Moreover, he was a French nominee and was always writing to Abdul Aziz (20-S). Sultan might accept British official to superintend customs if he were given a loan on their security; indefinite stoppage of subsidy would destroy Sultan's remnants of power (20-3). Government of India did not propose at present to make future payments of subsidy contingent upon linaocial control, nor to reduce subsidy because of fall in exchange. Renewal would be favourably considered, when recommended on political grounds ; but cus toms question should be settled in advance, and Sultan's loyalty ascertained before reverting to status quo ante (14-4), Fagan thought it most impor tant to get control of customs, as being the only security Sultan could offer for loan from foreign power; also that Muhammad-bin-Azzan should be dismissed (16-4). Secretary of State approved of suggestion. English and French Gov ernments should agree beforehand as to procedure about coaling sheds and in struct representatives accordingly ; but objected to joint communication from two Agents to Sultan. Right of French to be restricted to oceupancy on sufferance, conferring no territorial or sovereign rights. Coal might be in- charge of Agent or subordinate ; but there should be no question of protective works or of flying French flag over sheds. Complete liberty of action should be reserved to Government of India and its Agent. British Agent should require Sultan to consult him on Application of French Agent (21-4) Atter consultation with Foreign Offic3, Secretary of State decided that no exception need be taken ^o intimation made by Sultan of Maskat to French Consul refusing to recognise right of France to exercise jurisdiction over Mas- kat subjects while residing in, or visiting, his dominions, provided Article IV of French Treaty of 1846 with Maskat not contravened (21-4). Foreign Office on complaint of French Ambassador animadverted severely on Fagan'a 'unauthorised' demand that proposals of French Consul should be submit ted by Sultan to him for approval of Government of India. On 2nd May Secretary of State replied Government of India was right to take measures to guard against repetition of misunderstanding, in view of results of French Consul's original action in obtaining lease (2-5). At desire of Secretary of State, Government of India directed Fagan to ascertain orally from Ottavi pre cise situation desired for French coal dep6t at Maskat, avoiding written com munications (6-5). Sultan declined to apply for British Customs official (9«5). Fagan replied situation not decided. When French man-of-war next visited Maskat, Captain would be asked to choose (18-5). Viceroy protested to Secretary of State against settlement of matter in London in general terms, particular application being left to Sultan (17-5). Government of India wired to Agent, Maskat, inquiring sites for French coaling shed least open to objection (23-5). • Government of India agreed no further formal demands need be made on Sultan at present and Resident might exercise discretion as to payment of subsidy. Probably pay might be recommenced if Sultan's atti tude had substantially improved or Sultan specifically applied to Agent for payment; or if there were a real risk of Sultan turning to French for pecu niary aid, or selling concession to foreign adventurer. Desirable, however, if possible, to settle customs question in advance (25-5). Fagan mentioned Gobatneel cove, Makalla, and Maskat town as sites for French coaling station; first, bad approach expensive to improve; third, dangerous to town; second, best and could be arranged by one out of three British sheds being sold to French (27-5). As result of correspondence between 17th April and 9th May, in which Fagan offered to move in renewal of subsidy, Sultan declined to do more than take into Consideration Agent's advice and that only when not likely to be injurious to himself or to cause trouble to his subjects. Resident recom mended continued withholding of subsidy which would probably cause Sultan's Government to collapse (29-5). Lord Salisbury declined to agree to selec tion of Bandar Jessa by French for coaling shed, as contrary to agreement between him and French Ambassador. Conditions would not be same as Eng lish (1-6). Fagan instructed on orders from Secretary of State to tell Sul tan that if French applied for site for coaling shed within Maskat harbour, on same conditions as English, without flag or fortification, British Government would not oppose ; but such concession elsewhere could not be acquiesced in.64 Fagan to maintain right to be consulted by Sultan, but to show every considera tion to French suceptibilities and meet French wishes as far as possible (3-6). Fagan reiterated condition about consulting Indian Government in announcement to Sultan about terms on which British Government approved grant of a place to French (8-6). Government of India pointed ont to Resident mistake of Fagan in substituting reference to Government of India for reference to himself on two occasions. Intention was that Fagan should not make difficulties and should inform Sultan beforehand of approval of British Government on cer tain conditions : he was nevertheless to let it be known that he expected to be informed of, and consulted about any proposition French Agent might make. Fagan to be informed for guidance in future conversation with Sultan (18-6). Foreign Office, London, acquitted Fagan of intentionally exceeding instructions and recognised difficulty and delicacy of his position in consequence of decla ration of 1862; but thought he had not recognised importance of avoiding lang uage inconsistent with Sultan's independence : '.g., his statement that he would forward French proposal to Government of India, through the usual channel, for approval. Foreign Office also commented on his asking Sultan for explanation why he received Abdul Aziz (4 -7). French Ambassador said room at Makalla not sufficient and suggested Eiyam (25-7). Fagan reported room at Makalla sufficient and Riyam unsuitable for coaling place. Riyam, an an chorage for Suri dhows, could easily be fortified and might become sort of French settlement. Ridge surrounding Riyam commanded entrance to Matra harbour, Maskat -Matra road and town of Maskat. Decision not to allow French site outside Maskat harbour was generally known and should be maintained (4-8). Viceroy deprecated withdrawal (6-8). Secretary of State left treat ment of subsidy to Government of India. Early resumption of payment pro bably advisable in interests of a good understanding (11-8). Government of India thought no essential difference between Riyam and Jissa (17-8). French Government informed, 10th August, that British Goverument could not agree to Rivam site. Offer of third store, Makalla cove, renewed (18-9). Ratansi Parshotam was friend of Ottavi, Agent of ' Messageries Maritimes ' in 1896, farmer of Maskat customs and creditor of Sultan whom he persuaded to resist reform of finances and customs (20-9). Fagan reported Faisal's bias in favour of French, due merely to fear of English designs. He was never favour able to English, was further alienated by failure to assist him in 189c and finally was imbued with distrust of English by Ottavi. His behaviour in quarantine affair proved his suspicions. Stoppage of subsidy failed to bring him in as he simply ceased to subsidise tbe tribes, who had lost all their promin ent leaders and were deterred from attacks on Maskat and Matra by British notification. Income from customs ($470 a day) and lately confiscated estate of a Baluch murdered at Sib worth $25,000 kept Sultan in funds. He had lately utilised Abdul Aziz to deal with Beni Ruwahah garrison at Rostak; he would never cease to cause anxiety to Governmeut of India and would never of own free will allow British influence again to predominate at his Court (28-9). Govern ment of India orderea that if Sultan received Captain Cox, new Agent, in friendly spirit and Cox and Resident favoured resumption of subsidy payments Govern ment of India would be inclined to acquiesce. Arrears of subsidy due since last payment for November 1898 should only be paid subject to deductions for loan of 1897 and to display by Sultan of sincere desire to resume friendly relations. Monthly payments should be resumed first. Balance of indemnity of 1895, should also,'if convenient, be liquidated from arrears (2-10). 1900. Sultan agreed to use Saiyid Said, ex -Wazir, as medium of communication with British ^Consulate (16-5). Double barrelled Lee-Metford rifle with 1,000 cartridges presented to Sultan in return for sword, etc., given by him to Naval Commander -in-Chief on 18th February 1899 (15-5). Promptitude and energy with which Rear-Admiral Douglas acted in 18y9 recognised by India Office (13-7) and by Fo reign Office (21-7). FiveKhabura boatsattacked in Socotra waters by Somalis of Italian territory, who killed three Omanis, looted boats and kept three men prisoners Communicated to British Consul Generalj Zan zibar (16 -7).65 1901. Gov ernment of India saw no reason to interfere with orders of Sultan forbi ddin e landing at. Maskat and Gwadnr except (1) of Maskat subjects and (2) of other d eck passengers in batches of not more than 50, these last having property with them worth Its. 5 in case of Gwadur and Rs. 10 in case of Maskat. Rs. o mvabla b y each class as quarantine fee. Collector of Karachi had been using Sur al dumpily-ground for indigent Mekranis (16-2) Jaimur eldest and highest born of Sultan's sons and only surviving child of his senior wife, Alaiveh daughter of Saiyid Thowaini, now 16 years of age, was recently received with salute of 13 guns, on following day visited Agent alone. Agent and Resident recommended he should be invited to make a tour in (21-10). 1902. Sultan intended, following precedent of his grandfather Said in 1838, to present Khig on Coronation with gold work worth £500 also instead of horses, two Beatrix g Antelope S (rare) and two Wild Goats of Oma- Cnever seen out ot Oman before) (22-3). Sultan of Maskat invited to attend Delhi Uarbar (20-5) London Foreign Office objected to Maskat gold present, which would necessitate costly return present. Viceroy recommended accep ance ; Secretary of State suggested suspension as sending of horses postponed C 1 ?- 6 )/ ^ of inconvenient alienations, sometimes of AVakt property to Indian usurers, etc., and more immediately of danger of site owned by a beino- alienated for Russian Consulate, Cox issued notification on 13th September 1902° that British and British protected subjects ^ were prohibited under penalty from alienating to, or acquirinj? from, any British, protected or non-British subiect any land or household property in Maskat dominions either by g^t' pnrchase. mortgage or other form of conveyance without due execution ofsTgnature and registration in British Consulate previous to transfer of the property (21-9). 1903- A-ent allowed to make use of Sultan's steamer ' Nur-al Bahr ' on condi tion that no pressure should be put on Sultan to lend vessel; that use not made of it when Ship of war available and that loan of steamer occasional, not fre- quent or habitual; also that value of coal be refunded (18-9).73 F.—ZANZIBAR SUBSIDY AND BRITISH LOANS TO MASKAT. 1873. Sultan applied for payment to him of arrears from time of last payment to Salim (17-5). $i0,000 to be paid as complete arrears of subsidy at expiration of half year in August and thereafter $20,000 to be paid each half year (12-8). Government of India authorised payment of any advance, not exceed ing amount of subsidy due ; this on request of Sultan for $15,000 to remit to Bombay (1-9). 1876. Government of India agreed to subsidy being; paid quarterly from April 1876 (28-2). Government of India approved action of Agent in declining to accede to proposal that he should acknowledge some accommodation bills, issued by Sultan against Zanzibar subsidy, by giving verbal assurance to holders that amounts would be paid by Government in event of anything happening to His Highness, to amount of such portion of subsidy as might remain due (6-9). 1877. [Home Government apparently under took half cost of Zanzibar Agency and half Maskat subsidy from 19th June 1872 (27-10).] 1879: Sultan's receipts for subsidy to be taken in triplicate in future, one copy for Secretary of State (2 6). Payment of subsidy made monthly (4-8). 1895. Sultan a«ikeil in writing for loan of $30,000, to be recovered by deduction of $1,000 per mensem from Zanzibar subsidy. Sultan verbally stated that, if not granted, he would have to apply for help elsewhere (22-8). Necessity for loan had not been properly stated (7-9). Government of India sanctioned loan of Rs. 60,0 0 with interest at 4^ per cent, repayable by monthly instalments of Rs. 2.000 deducted from Zanzibar subsidy; loan conditional on written assurances from Sultan that it would be devoted to meeting present difficulties, and that Sultan would not borrow from foreign power while loan unrepaid (29-10). Sultan accepted terms (28-11). 1896. Sultan determined to attack Beni Kuaheh against Beville's advice and asked loan of Rs. 20,000 in anticipation of sanction of Government. Beville refused (14-10). Sultan asked for Rs. 40,000 loan to punish tribes in interior and break down all opposition to rule (1-10). On 1st November Sultan asked for $20,000 down to pay off troops in anticipation of sanction. Beville refused (10-11). 1897. Government of India required, as condition of any loan, that Sultan should fully explain purpose for which loan required, manner in which it would be utilised and actual financial position (4-1). Sultan's response not cord'al or full. He estimated liabilties at $130,000 (19-1). Sultan pressing for reply (9-5). Government replied they were not ^illing to give assistance for expedition against Beni Kuaheh, but were willing to help Sultan if he would give explanations already asked for (18-5). Sultan's expenditure about $700 per mensem in excess of income. He intended to effect reduction of $2,000 per mensem. Customs sold for $^24,000 ; worth $150,000. laisal likeTurki had no extravagant tastes. This time he gave information unreservedly. $100,000, rebel lion loan without interest, due to Banyans and Arabs. $33,000 bore interest at74 2 per c^nt. pf r mensem: this last Saltan desired to pay off by means of lonn of Rs. 60,0 0. Wanted R.s^ 40,000 also to pay olT Arab creditors. Beville ad vanced Rs. 5,200 on own responsibility (2-6). Lorn of Ks. 60,000 sanctioned on same terms as previous loan, repayment to commenee when first loan dis- chariied. Sultan must undertake to show Political Agent that ordinary expenditure including refund instalments could and would be kept within ordinary income. Political Agent, if necessary, should take means to secure that loan was not diverted from declared object, viz., of paying debts which bore exorbitant interest (2S-6). If Saltan gave preof of resolve to place finances on sound basis, Government would consider a third advance ot Rs. 40,000 to pay off Arab creditors. Government would lend a suitable officer to reform customs if Sultan desired (21-47). Sultan gave necessaiy assurances as to extinction of debts bearins: exorbitant interest and balancing of revenue and expenditure (9-7). New loan paid to Sultan (6-8). 1898'. Resident thought Suit m would consent to make over control of customs for 10 years and requested authority to offer advance up to one year's income from customs if necessary (15-1). Referred to Secretary of State (21-1). Salisbury considered direct control would be infringement of 1862 declaration, but Secretary of State approved appointment of British official as Superinten dent of Sultan's customs and advance of money on security of customs (18-2) No gift or loan ever made (as onca reported) to Sultan by French Vice-Consul (18—2). Sultan's debts $190,500. Nearly half of last loan misapplied and Sultan, in spite of several reminders, had not sent in projects of reform. Sultan politely but distinctly refused to change customs manage- mei t (16-2). 1899. Zanzibar subsidy to Maskat fixed at Pts. 86,400 in 1873 when $100=Rs. 216. Now $.00= Hs. 125. Sultan broached renewal of subsidy to Cox (23-10). Cox calculated arrears of subsidy December 1898 to September 1899, both inclusive, at Rs. 72,000 : arrears of instalments due on account of some months for loans at Rs. 20,000; total balance of loans at Rs. 36,000; balance of in demnity at Rs. 34,000; deficit at Rs. 18,000 (24-10). Resident pointed out that if arrears of subsidy were applied to liquidate balance of indemnity, burden would be shifted from offending tribes to Sultan (2-12). Sultan, once more in funds, repaid advance of Ratansi Parshotam and cancelled his provisional contract for customs; then telegraphed to Bombay for two Muham- madans, said to have had practical experience in Bombay Customs, to enable him to manage customs for one year himself (12-12). 1900. Government of India considered arrears of subsidy had been forfeited by conduct of Sultan. Even application of arrears to discharge of Sultan's liabi lities was exceptional generosity of Government towards him. View of Government was that whole balance of loan of 1897 should be paid out of arrears and, as regards indemnity, quarterly instalments of balance for Sep tember and December 1899, if owing, should be deducted from arrears of subsidy, similarly interest at 6 per cent, on unpaid balance from February 1899; but balance of capital sum of indemnity, Ks. 84,000, might, for political reasons, continue to be paid off by instalments. Sultan might, however, possibly obtain mitigation of these orders by proper attitude to representative ami representations of British Government. Immediate liquidation of loan might be abandoned in return for substantial concession by Sultan in regard {e.g.) to management of customs; but monthly instalments must of course be paid from December 1898 till debt extinguished (2-1). Receipt from indemnity tax diminishing as collusion increasing and on account of Sultan taking tax into own hands instead of farming it (12-2). New customs arrangement apparently working well (14-2). Government of India accepted $4,564, paid by Sultan as proceeds of punitive-tax between June and December 1899, in75 j)ln(;e of full instalments for quarters ending September and December ; no deduction from subsidy arrears, therefore, to be n?ade on this account. Obli gatory deductions remaining were arrears of monthly repayments of loan (Rs. 20,000) and interest on unpaid balance of indemnity from February 1899 to date (about Rs. 2,16 ). This left about Rs. 49,835. Should this sum be devoted to extinction of loan, or of indemnity, or of both or of neither ? and should any return be exacted for these favours ? Any balance left in any case would be retained by Government unless Sultan made concession in matter of customs or Maskat flaor (21-5). Sultan had behaved well in the matters of partition of Makaila cove, restoration of ex-Wazir Saiyid Said, spirited action in re French, tlajr, request to have scurrilous Franco Arabic leaflets sup pressed and his offer to place quarantine arrangements in charge of Agency Surgeon. Cox, therefore, recommended only Rs. 20,000 arrears of monthly instalments for loan and Rs. 27,000 entire balance (with interest to September) of indemnity should be deducted from arrears of subsidy, and rest of arrears (Rs. !i5,000) should be handed to Sultan ; rest of loan (Rs. 17,000 odd on 2nd September) to be paid off by monthly instalments of Rs. 2,000 as formerly. Sultan agreed to continue punitive-tax for only one year more to pay Arab losses (28-8). Government of India ordered set-off of Rs. 20,000 and Rf. 27,000 and Rs 17,000 (balance of loan) and payment of Rs. 8,000 to Sultan, provided his loyal action had received no check (12-9). Balance of Rs. 9,034 paid to Sultan (9-10).G.—PROTECTION OF BRITISH SUBJECTS IN MASKAT. 1872. Pelly recovered $ 2,255 from Ibrahim bin Ghes as compensation to British Indians on Batina coast for 1871. 1873. Details of claims against ' Chief of Sohar ' amounting to $ 2,255 (15-5). Paid (26-11). 1874. Two British haghlas left Aden in December 1873 and touched at Helaniya (one of Kuria Muria Islands ceded to Britain by Maskat on 14th June 1854). One Nakhuda and two others seized (23-2) and held to ransom by Jaaferah of Ashakur (1-4). The Kachis released on payment of $ 250 ransom by passing vessel (6-5). $ 450, value of goods stolen from British subjects at Sib, recovered from Sultan (14-5). Sultan took upon self satisfaction of claims by Britisli subjects for losses caused by Saleh's proceedings at Matra (11-6), Loss in Helaniya case, $ 350 besides personal injury (11-6). Yal Saad intract able and avaricious. No expectation of their paying without display of force. They sent ultimatum to Sultan demanding he should pay whole indemnity, remove Wali of Soweik and give up Mtisnaah to Ibrahim. Turki offered to pay one-third indemnity and give Ibrahim $ 100 a mouth if he would restore Mesnaah and live at llostak (17-6). Mesnaah British traders at Maskat since March. In 6 months 4 serious depredations on British subjects and half a lakh rupees plundered (26-6). Sultan's ' Rahmani' and H. M. S. ^Philo mel ' and ' Magpie,' with May Frere,' latter carrying Resident and Political Agent, assembled Burka on 10th July after warnings sent to Ibrahim and Yal Saad. Aziz completed his force to 350. On 13th vessels moved to Mesnaah, fort of which partially repaired by Ibrahim and occupied by small garrison. Nego tiations with Yal Saad. On 19th Aziz landed with his men, after few shots at fort from ' Philomel,' supported by armed boats of ' Philomel,' 44 Nimble' and 'Magpie.' Garrison before evacuating blew up part of wall and Aziz then occupied. Cliiefs of Yal Saad agreed in document, written by Muhammad bin Suleyim, chief priest of Oman Ibadhis, to pay $ 10,000 in 70 days from 22nd July. Sultan to pay remaining $ 5,000. Aziz an ener getic and bold leader of troops. Ibrahim ignored in negotiations. Aziz undertook to satisfy British claims in three months (30-7). Government of India ordered assistance of Gulf Squadron to be offered Sultan for coercion of Jafferah (20-7), and informed Secretary of State (4-8). * On the 13th June 4 Aden camp followers and 11 pilgrims (Indians), arrived at Maskat whom a Suri Nakhuda? had embarked at Bombay, carried to Makala and then brought back to Sur, after promising to carry them to Aden and Jeddah, Nakhuda obliged to return passage money, and Sultan warned Nakhudas not to take Indian passengers except for ports to which they were bound (5-8). Political Agent went Ashkhara in ' Philomel' with Agent of Sultan and demanded reparation from Jaaferah for Helaniya outrage. Arabs unwilling to give up offenders, but paid § 600 and promised good behaviour (12-9). Balance of fine to be paid to Sultan (24-10). Rs. 630 paid to Junagarh State (13-11). Britisli Indian traders permitted to return to Mesnaah (24-11), 1875. $ 809 recovered from Jaaferah paid to Sultan, Maskat (6-3). $ 9,600 re ceived from Yal Saad and distributed. $ 5,000 still due from Turki (2-4). Government of India sanctioned reduction of balance due from Turki to such amount as after careful scrutiny appeared to afford fair compensation (8-6).84 1876. In June 1875 godowns of Banyan at Sur broken into by Jenebeh and $ 1,600 worth of stuff taken. Sultan promised to exert bis influence. On llth September 1875 Government of India prohibited British coerceive mea sures and directed Political Agent to look to Maskat Government. In August 1876 Sultan replied could not coerce Jenebeh. In reality he was unwilling to offend a Gbafiri tribe. Government of India repeated orders that matter pertained to Sultan (28-10). 1 1877. Government of India ordered Sur affair to be pressed on Sultan (8-2) * Done (2-3). Sultan requested presence of man-of -war at Sur (9-7). Poli tical Agent permitted to proceed in ' Teazer' (14-7). Robertson arrived Sur on 24)th with Saiyid Said as Sultan's representative. Gave Jenebeh till sunset 25th. Banyan fully compensated and fine of $ 2,000 paid (31-7). Fine after deduction of expenses of expedition to bo paid to feultan (J-10). 1878. Turki spontaneously recovered from Rostak, by correspondence with Ibrahim, an Indian woman and boy detained there as slaves since six months $ 3,144 recovered from Turki and paid to sufferers for losses at Mesnaah in 1874'(13-8). 1880. Government of India approved notification to Saleh, and Harth, Hijriyin and Habus tribes declaring them liable in followinsr proportions for losses of 1 877 Saleh $ 1 ,500, Harth $ 2,750, Hijriyin $ 3 ,750, Habus $ 1 ,000 and that Sultan authorised to demand and would act with support of Government. If not paid in one month demand would be increased (2i -l). Notifications sent out on 10th and llth February and replies received between 20th and 23rd (25-2). General impression was that Sultan had pardoned Hijiriyin with whom he bad since had friendly intercourse (26-4). Government of India thought Turki appeared unwilling to enforce demands and Government would have either to cause Sultan to make good the losses, which would impoverish him and give moral victory to tribes, or else take steps to enforce payment which would he interference iu internal affairs of Oman. Besident to give opinion ri7- 5). Doubtful answer from Resident (6-G). Effect must be given to notifica tion. Turki to be told to recover with British support or else pay himself. In first case presence only of a vess3l of war at Sur to be granted, in second deductions should be made from Zanzibar subsidy (G -7). On 16th September Political Agent reached Sur in Wood lark,' Badr bin Saif accompanying on Dar us Salam.'* Sultan's information incorrect; no produce of Hijriyin at Sur and trade at standstill as Beni Bu Hassan at war with Beni Bu Ali, Beni Rasib, Hishm and Jenebah. Suris told not to embark any Sharkiya produce, and Wali to prevent any baghlas putting to sea (23 9). Sultan distrained and sold $ 2,000 worth produce of Sharkiya tribes and imprisoned broker for remitting price of 350 camel loads Harth produce to owners (2-10). About 20th October Sultan approved indemnity tax, proposed by Hijriyin or by Mesakera always friendly to Turki, of $ 1 ex^ra per bahar of dates exported from Sharkiya. ' Hindu customs farmer at Sur instructed to levy accordingly from Sharkiya but not from Jaalan produce. Sultan told Miles none of Sharkiya tribes were unrepresented in rising of 1877, and that Saleh s share would have to be collected with rest (9-11). 1881. Indemnity tax collections retained by Banya customs farmers who had plaims against Turki. Political Agent refused to make them disgorge and held ^urki responsible for payment of amount collected (15 8). Customs Collectors85 withheld $ 1,000 collected at Maskat and Matra and $ 400 collected at Sur towards lb?7 indemnity between 10th October 1880 and April 1881. Arab appointed in their places on IDth April 1881 only collected $ 300 up to date (29.11). Turki paid § 1,100 out of Zanzibar subsidy. 1832. On 25th November 1881 Tejpal, Hindu, killed by unknown thieves who carried off box from his shop. Wahabi guards suspected. Pressure put on Turki to discover and punish offenders and recover stolen property valued at $3 121 (27-4). On night of L'th-lGth September, Hindu Fakir murdered atMeabin: no clue to'murderer (20-9). On night of 29th-30th September Banyan murdered at Matra : again no clue {3-i0). In open day some A\ ahabis took away milkgoat and stole gold bangle off arm of daughter of Ismail Isa, respectable Khoja merchant. Turki, then in bad health mentally, referred to Faisal who said nothing could be done. Eventually Shekh of Wahabi company to which robbers belonged suffered 10 days imprisonment and paid $ 13 fine (l-H). 1886. British Indian traders of Khabura complained against Saiyid Hamad bin Nasir, Wall of Sohar alleging that he demanded benevolence of 400, warned people of Dhahira not to trade with them and porters not to work for them, exacted illegal tax of 2 per cent, on dates and put. in irons at Sohar a Khoja British subject, well known as such, Ali bin Nasir (25-1). Ali bin Nasir released (31-1). Sultan disinclined to do more (1-2). Miles pressed for further action (13-2). Sultan decided to give $ 200 to Ali bin Nasir as compensation for imprisonment and $ 200 to traders for losses, to abolish tax of 2 per cent, and to establish separate W ali at Ivbabura. Meanwhile fiesh complaint received and Sultan dismissed Hamad from Government of Sohai (4-3). Hindu traders received $ 250 from Sultan for losses caused by raids of Beni Kattab, etc., (27-3). Compensation to Khabura people paid (2-7). On 24th July Aulad Kassib carried off a Banyan of Sur (20-7). 1887. Bu Ali Shaikhs procured release of Bania kidnapped by Aulad Kassim from Sur (14-S). 1891. Khabura bazaar burnt night of 24th February, partly in consequence of difference between Sowalim and Howamid sections of Howasinah, latter of whom claimed part of rent of shops and apparently threatened m Sultan s presence, or one occasion, to 'shut up' tue bazaar unless they got share. When Wali of Sohar refused admission to Khabura he ordered its Wall, Kahtan bin Yaarab, to go Sohar: when Faisal separated Sohar and Khabura Kahtan went back and fire immediately happened. About time of tire Bam Omar attacked Geizen, chief town of Howasin. Beni Omar sulTered seriously in ' subsequent retaliation. Faisal accepted assertions of Howamid and pretended to believe fire was accidental (19-4). Losses estimated at$ o6,000. Merchan s returned Khabura (10-5). Wali of Sohar, Hamad bin Nasir, again jealous ot power of Sheikh of Khabura and coveting certain revenues tried to widen breach between Howasinah sections and Sultan approved his policy. Certain Howamid set fire to bazaar. Attack by Beni Omir simultaneously with burn- in^ of bazaar was sanctioned and approved by Wali of Sohar (12-6). bovern- ment of India accepted view that fire was deliberately cance l and thit Sultan aware of fact. Ordered that Sultan should be pressed for compensation (l-w). Sultan accepted assessment of losses by panchayat at $ 12,7o9 and agreed to pay $ 1,000 a month from Zanzibar subsidy (9-11;.83 1892. Sultan imposed on Sowalim a fine equal to one-third indemnity. Boatg of Indians prevented from obtaining ciews by Howasinah (15-4). ' Matter of boats arranged by mission from Sultan. Sultan bad taken $ 5,370 from Howasinah (24-4). Unless fine unjustly collected from Sowalim was return ed no permanent settlement would be possible (11-0). 1893. Khabura account settled (13-5). 1895. Government of India approved proposal that indemnity for recent rebellion should be exacted from offending tribes in form of tax levied on their export trade. Sultan to be authorised to notify that demand made at instance of British Government, but to understand that his own responsibility was in no way lessened. Tax to be such as to produce amount required in 2 or at most 3 years (29-5). Sultan practically accepted proposal without condition. .British subjects to be compensated ; thereafter Maskat subjects might be compensated also, but tax to be repealed when compensation completed. American subject (Zwemer) and French subject (Algerian) to be treated as British subjects. Government could not agree to support Sultan if attacked on account of tax (30-8). Additional tax on dry and pressed dates, 10 per cent, calculated to produce $ 28.025 per,annum, or allowing for accidents, etc., $ 20,000 (1-8). Committee considered 224 claims of British and British-protected subjects amounting to $ 206,040 and Rs. 66,919, and found many fraudulent and exaggerated, Finally accepted $ 77,895 at Es. 183=§ 100 (25-11). 1896. Sultan obstinately clung to view that British subjects should have no precedence over Maskat subjects, and spoke of sum collected as ' common to four Governments' (9-1). Sultan to be told $ 77,894 must be paid quarterly by instalments within 3 years, minus rateable deduction for 1 American and 1 French claim, otherwise steps would be taken to recover from Zanzibar subsidy (27-3). Owing to collusion of Ghafiris, abuse of exemption of Hijriyin, absence of effective control at Sur and Sultan's own partiality in collection at Maskat, collections from indemnity tax only $ 9,054 from imposition of tax on 1st August 1895 to 14th March 1896, including $ 650 from Sur. Sultan believed to have spent proceeds as received. Sultan would impose extra 5 per cent, on Ghafiris aiso for connivance and on account of looting done by friendlies making Ghafiri taxes 10 per cent, and Hinawi 15 per cent, altogether (1-4). Government thought unnecessary to interfere with Sultan's discretion in taxing Ghafiris (22-5). Money col lected to be demanded from Sultan and he to be informed in unmistakeable terms that, failing payment of sum already collected, and the quarterly pay ment in future of the receipts from the special taxation, the amounts due would, without further notice, be recovered from the Zanzibar subsidy : also if at end of 3 years claims remained unliquidated balance would be recovered from subsidy in such manner as Government of India might decide (22—6). § 11,526 received from Sultan (22-7). Sultan withdrew tax on Ghafiris, not imposed till July, at advice of Agent on report of combination to resist (22-7). Award of compensation committee accepted as final by Government of India : appeal of Messrs. Lodhawala, Parsee merchants, rejected (18-9). Secretary of State informed Government of India that as French actively interesting selves in Maskat affairs, in such circumstances effect of levying unpopular tax on friendly subjects, as well as rebels (injurious to trade and with object of paying indemnity assessed on doubtful evidence) deserved careful consideration of Government of India. Extreme measure of deductions from subsidy should be avoided if possible (11 -9). Sultan sent $ 3,94^ for 1st quarter 1,313 (18-10).87 1897. Resident to tell Sultan that Government trusted it would be unnecessary to resort to sueli extreme measure as deduction from subsidy. Orders as to in demnity postponed till present position reported (1-1). Government of India informed Secretary of State no tax actually levied from Ghafiris. No deduc tion would be made from Zanzibar subsidy (27-1). Collections for first half of 1896-97 only $ 6,884. Paisal asked 6 years to pay off, but promised interest after 3rd year (23-1). Punitive tax farmed to Eatansi Parshotam for $ 15,000 a year (21-2). Instalments received from time to time (18-11). 1898. Up to date only $ 29,711 paid out of $ 77,894 (14-3). Indemnity tax farmed to Eatansi Parshotami for $ 18,000, though Damodar Daramsi offered $ 25,000 (10-8). (Payments continued to be regularly made). 1899. In June band of Sharkiya tribesmen, led by Ilamed bin Saleh, Harithi raided bazaar at Kurniyat, small port 30 miles south of Maskat, and carried off goods of four British Indian traders. Sultan paid them $ 1,193 out of own pocket, there being no prospect of recovery from tribes (20-12). 1903. Arrears of subsidy, Rs. 72,000, handed .to Sultan : from this Sultan paid Rs. 27,026, balance of 1895 indemnity: $972 unclaimed (28-2). To be refund ed to Sultan (3-0).95 H—BRITISH EXTRA-TERRITORIAL JURISDICTION IN MASKAT. 1873. Sultan gnve agreement on behalf of self, heirs and successors rendering subjects of Native States of India amenable to criminal jurisdiction of British Consul whenever Consul thought fit to exercise such jurisdiction. ' British subjects ' in all Maskat treaties to inclade subjects of Native Indian States [Jurisdiction of Consul in these cases was defective without express consent of Sultan] (1—7). 1875. Consular Commission received by Allies (11-2). Sessions cases against British subjects wtre tried at Bombay at this time, the witnesses being senffiom Maskat, ride case of Fadhl bin Turab Ali. (8-7). In connection with Fadhl bin Turab Ali's case Sultan appeared disposed to claim whole Khojah community as Arab subjects (16-1). In reply to questions of Government of India, Agent reported Khojas of Maskat did not combine with other communities. They lived in Khojah Fo-.t at JVJatra and intermarried only among themselves. A minority were followers of the Agha Klian ; the majority had adopted* the Mohamad an religion but preserved some of their old social habits. Khojahs whose ancestors had emigrated from Sind prior to British conquest, and such as had declared themselves Arab subjects, were undoubtedly subjects of Sultan. These last formed one and the same community along with British Khojahs and intermarried with them. Maskat Khojahs all'came from India, either from Sind or Kutch. No general consideration prevented Khojahs who preferred to do so from acquiring Arab nationality. Registration of persons under British protection was done with Sultan's cognisance, but notice not usually given him. Sultan had never formally objected to practice of registration, but had been fur nished on request with list of persons registered. Khojahs born at Maskat of Indian parents after coming of age wore registered if they made application. Kames were never entered in the register except at personal request of the persons and after investigation. It had always been the custom to treat adult Maskat-born descendents of Indian immigrants as protected subjects, provided original immigrants were British subjects or subjects of protected Indian States and provided the said descendents desired to be so treated (5-8). Omission to register name did not free British protected subjects from British jurisdiction. Government of India directed registration of British and British protected sub jects to be conducted methodically and copies of register to be furnished to Sul tan at convenient intervals (19-10). 1877. Government of India ruled that Abdul Wahab, Arab, born at Calcutta of parents who were Maskat subjects, and who was a possession of in passport entitling him to British Consular protection, could not claim to be considered a British subject whilst within the territories of Oman and that he was not entitled to be registered as such under Maskat Order in Council (23-7). 1879. ^ Government of India negatived proposal of Euan Smith that summons froth British Courts in India on British subjects should be sent to Sultan for service. Desirable that Agent should retain all authority over British Indian subjects at Maskat in his own ^ hands. Trocedure Ishould vary with circum stances (4-10). 1880. Government of India considered it essential to both British and Maskat interests that Sultan should accept and discharge all responsibilities96 where his own subjects were offenders. Agent slionld therefore decline a pro posal from Sultan to make over to him for trial and punishment the Sidi hure- lar of a Memon's place of business (15-1). Agent to submit draft rule under Maskat order in Council to prevent scandal from sale of liquor by British sub jects (8-5). Draft rule submitted. Grant disagreed with Euan Smith as to necessity for rules. Only 3 shops, quite respectable, in Maskat and Matra, kept by Goanese employes of an American mercantile firm. Government of India asked opinion ol' Resident (l*-9). Resident thought Agent's influence suffi cient and that proposed sale of licenses liable to be misunderstood (o0-9). 1882. Government of India accepted view that British Consular Court, Maskat, had no jurisdiction (dispute not being between British subjects) in case of boy whose guardianship was claimed by a British Indian, resident at Calcutta, as agent of his wife, daughter and sole executrix of the bo/s father • objectors were Maskat subjects. Matter was one for Maskat Courts (16-1).' Appeals from Consular Courts, Maskat, lie not to Government of India but to Hi^h Court of Bombay (13—9). Jeta Nand brought suit against Lalji, both being subject to jurisdiction of British Consular Court at Maskat, on ground that both con jointly lent Sultan a sum of money and that defendent fraudulently retained repayment instalments, exclusively for himself. Agent asked whether suit should be entertained. Government of India ordered thit private preliminary eoquiry should be held andresult reported to Government before suit was allowed to proceed. No inconvenience or annoyance to Sultan should be permitted nor information pressed for which Sultan was unwilling to give (15-7). 1884. On representation of Bombay merchant that Hish Court, Bombay, could not transmit its decrees for execution to Consular Court, Maskat, and that to sue at Maskat was in practice impossible, High Court recommended that sections of Civil Procedure Code concerning execution of decrees bevond juris diction of adjudicating Court might be declared in force in Maskat 'and Zanzi bar Consular Courts with respect to decrees transmitted from Courts of Presi dency Towns in India; but Consuls should have power of staying execution under section 239. By means of an order in Council subjects of'Indian Native States could be brought under operation (25-8). Government of India inquired views of His Majesty's Government on proposed Zanzibar order in Council, with which Indian Government no longer concerned, in order that they might proceed with draft order in Council for Persian Gulf (27 10). 1885. Brahmin boy went on board Sultan of Zanzibar's steamer 'Avoca' intend ing to visit Mecca and become Muhammadan. Hindu community much excited. Fellow pilgrims (well armed Afghan and Persians) refused to give boy up and then hid him. ' Hanger detained ' Avoca ' and boy given up and re nounced idea of becoming Muhammadan (13-9). Government of India declined to interfere on behalf of orthodox Khojas of Maskat (only 20 families) who had been dispossessed of original holy place. They were perhaps entitled to it under Bombay decision of 1864, but on other hand they could still worship in old building and had also a new building of their own and had not brought their claim for a long time (16-11). 1886. Complaint received by Bombay Government that Khojah women at Ma^kat were being ill-treated by husbands to make them join in secession from Shia Ismaili sect ot Khojahs and that husbands were supported bv Sultan of Maskat (27-1). Government of India ordered inquiry, but did not' anticipate much practical advantnge (25-6). Complaint found'to originate in case of one Khoja woman at Matra who was an Arab subject (31-7). Matter drop ped (2-9).97 1893. On 24th February, son of second mate of ' Humayoon Shah,' sailing vessel flying British colours, was murdered on hi^h seas and an Abyssinian was sus pected. Both were Arab subjects. Resident ruled, with approval of Govern ment of India that as ship was not owned by naturalised British subjects she was not British ship, and accused should be tried by Sultan of Maskat (15 7). In virtue of powers conferred by section 8 of ' Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1889 ' Governor-General in Council appointed by name Director of Persian Gulf Telegraphs to be Magistrate of 1st class within local limits of tele graph stations of Jask and Charbar and along alignment of telegraph between these two places and also to be Justice of the Peace (9—8). Secretary of State considered that as point doubtful such powers should be conferred on each new holder of Directorship by name, and not once for all on present and future holders, ex-o(Jicio (2-11). 1894. Civil case filed against Ali bin Juma, Baluch, in Consular Court. Man had obtained British certificate of naturalisation in 186S at Bombay on declaration that he meant to live in India, and name had been on Consular register since 1872. His mother was Arab, he himself was born at Masnaah and believed his father had been born at Maskat (,7-5). 1895. Government of India decided that, unless law of Maskit recognized naturalisation abroad as valid abnegation of former nationality, Ali bin Juma must ordinarily speaking be regarded, while» in Maskat, as subject of Sultan. At same time, as Consul could try cases between British subjects by birth or naturalisation. Government of India had no objection to Consul trying case so long as no objection made by Maskat authorities (2-3). 1897. At request of Sultan, Consul struck Ali bin Juma of Consular list. Ottav had quoted him and others in justification of his own action in matter of French flags given at Obok, etc., (25-11). 1898. Government approved (15-2). 1899. High Court, Bombay, dismissed application of Ratansi Parshotam for revision on ground that order in Council gave them no appellate jurisdiction over Court of British Consul, Maskat. Criminal Judgment No. 191 of 159^ in Imperatrix v. Ratansi Parshotam (6-12). 1900. In August 1899 French Consul at Maskat applied to British Consulate for extradition from British India of freed Negro slave, who absconded to British India with valuable property belonging to French Consular dragoman, in whose employment he was (20-1). Secretary of State and Foreign Office held that fugitive could not properly be surrendered as extradition treaties in force with France did not cover cases of offences committed in extra-territorial jurisdic tion (9-4). Inconsequence of punishment of Ratansi Parshotam for contempt of Court in refusing to produce a document called for, some Banyan traders of Maskat petitioned Government of Bombay for introduction of Indian Penal Code and Code of Criminal Procedure and for revocation, modification or amendment of Order in Council (12-7). Government of India considered change unnecessary (11-9). 1902. In notice under Order in Council requiring registration at Consulate of transfers of real property by or in favour of British subjects, etc., Foreign Office required substitution of word 'British protected persons ' for 'British pro tected subject' (4-12).105 I.—BRITISH GOVERNMENT ESTABLISHMENTS AND PROPERTY IN MASKAT. 1874. Agency building at Maskat held on yearly rent of $600. Originally very small and still insufficient in spite of successive additions at different periods. Owing to patchwork character, unsuitable and, inconvenient in many respects. Value of bouse consisted in its position ; it was, for coolness, best situated house in Maskat. Basement story occupied by offices and godowns, including treasury wdth no guard. No servants' quarters; peons and khalassis had to make own arrangements for lodging in distant part of town. Agent requested grant of Rs. 4,000 to build servants' houses on land offered by Sultan for so long as might be required (16-10). 1877. Government of India considered that Assistant Political Agent at Gwadur should be assistant for country between Gwetter and Jask to Resident in Gulf; for Gwadur territory, to Political Agent, Maskat; and for Khelat terri tory and subjects, to Agent Governor-General, Baluchistan. Government of India inquired of Government Bombay whether this Assistant might not therefore be transferred from control of Commissioner in Sind to Political Department of Government of India (1-3). 1879. ^ • Durand's report on Gwadur. No necessity for telegraph reasons to keep Political Agent at Gwadur, and any formerly existing political necessity removed by new arrangements in Baluchistan. Native news-writer or Agent would be enough. Political Agent without power to punishwas no deterrent from outrages (17-7). Resident in Gulf (Ross) thought so far as Residency or Maskat concerned no necessity for maintenance of Political Assistant at Gwadur. But undesirable that telegraph officers should be mixed up in political matters and most undesirable that Mekran Political Agency, now more important politically than at institution, should be abolished (25-7). Saudeman thought Gwadur could be managed by Native Agent under Political Assistant at Khelat (4-8). Government of India inclined to agree with S mdeman, (9-9) but asked whether Telegraph Officer at Gwadur could not be empowered to dispose of minor political work (9-10), Ross thought trouble with Rinds, etc., due not so much to impunity as to offence given by slave trade measures enforced by Maskat authorities at British instance. When Ross went Gwadur, as 1st European Political there, 6 unarmed men were a sufficient garrison, and relations with tribes were friendly. Suggested friendly rendition of Gwadur to Khelat by purchase (2-10). Ross thought minor and routine political duties should be conducted by Deputy Director Persian Gulf Telegraph on Rs. 150 allowance he had steamer and telegraph at disposal. Duties extended to whole coast; not confined to Gwadur. Stationary Agent useless. Native agency not desirable (27-10). 1880. Government of India fixed Ras Sajir or Sair as boundary between Aden and Maskat political jurisdiction (18-2). Sandeman agreed to appointment of Deputy Director for political work of Mekran Coast as temporary arrange ment (16-2). Government sanctioned (22-3). Sultan of Maskat thought things not going so well at Gwadur as formerly and that Native British Agent should be appointed (7-7). Miles asked leave to visit southern part of his beat (22 -11). Sanctioned by Government of India (30-12). 1884. Sandeman thought Gwadur should be managed by Native Assistant Political Agent reporting to Political Agent at Karachi and under Baluchistan106 (7-6). Qovermnent of India ordered Director, Persian Gulf Telegraphs, to be placed in charge as formerly (19-8). Director of Persian Gulf Telegraphs to be regarded as Assistant to Political Agent, Maskat, for Gwadur matters (7-10). 1900. Medical arrangements at Maskat consisted of A.geney Dispensary, establish ed for British employes and subjects, but also used largely by Arabs; Sultan's Dispensary, under retired Hospital, Assistant who also superintended quaran tine arrangements; Plague Hospital in charge of [another retired medical subordinate. Agency Surgeon had no connection with last two. Agency Dispensary premises consisted of house lent by Sultan who also kept it in repair. On average, 62 oit end 3 in-patients daily. Establishment inadequate (22-5). Government of India authorised Agent and Surgeon to endeavour to obtain Sultan's interest and support with view to improved arrangements (23-8). 1901. Por nearly 23 years, in 1900, Agency Surgeon had been residing at Matra and Agency Clerks had had to make own arrangements for houses. On 27th April 1901, Government sanctioned purchase from Ratansi Parshotam of block between British Consulate and Customs (except one slice, in bad repair and not utilisable by others) for Its. 60,000, ^0 provide site for Agency Sur geon's house, accommodation for clerical establishment, also Telegraph Ollice and quarters (1-8). 1902. Government of India sanctioned Compounder and 2 Pankha Coolies (last for 8 months per annum) in addition to existing establishment of Hospital Assistant, Peon, Night Watchman and Sweeper, from 1st April 1. 02 (16-1). Pay of Agency Arabic clerk and Interpreter at Maskat raised from Us. 50 to Rs. 100 per mensem (11-8). 1903. Political Agent authorised to build coal jetty at Makalla, as experiment, of as great length as oould be managed for Rs. 3,000 (28-1).113 J.—TRADE AND CUSTOMS IN MASKAT. 1875. Saltan, Turki, ^oing beyond rules established by Sultan Said in April 1846, agreed to forego customs on cargoes of distressed vessels putting into Maskat for repairs and landing cargo for purpose of repairs, even if cargo reshipped in other vessels (10-2). 1876. On 3rd October 1872 Sultan, to meet British demand for statistics, required every vessel leaving Maskat in cargo to take out manifest from Superinten dent of Customs House, specifying crew, passengers, cargo and destination; laden vessels entering harbour also required to report. Fee for each manifest $2. ^Graduated fee of Re. 1 per 50 tons now introduced: Residentdoubted com patibility ol this with Article IX of Commercial Treaty. Government thought exception need not be taken to new charge ; but, if raised. Agent should report and in any case explain to Sultan that infractions of Article IX should be avoided (2-11). 1877. Secretary of State approved (11-1). Weighment dues, instituted by Said early in reign, and wharfage dues, instituted by Turki in 1873, also found to exist but not excessive (13-9). 1878. [Weighment and wharfage papers lost (31-7)]. 1879. Weighment and wharfage charges could not under Treaty be compulsorily exacted ; Government of India thought, however, it would suffice if Sultan were moved to make weigbment optional (14-8). Sultan issued notice making weighment and wharfage dues optional to British Indian subjects (9-lof. Government of India held that Treaties of 1839 and 1840 were not applicable to tax levied by Sultan on country produce imported from interior by land into coast towns, British subjects therefore should pay it (S-ll). 1880. Sultan obtained $ 2,000 to 3,000 a year by sale of monopoly of dyeing silk for Arab market. Some banyas now objected as contrary to Article X of Treaty (5-2). Government of India thought this long standing system need not be interfered with (12-3). A British subject complained of levy from him of local tax of more than 5 per cent, on tobacco imported by him from Batina by sea to Maskat (27-9). Government of India approved Resident's view that unless the tobacco was intended for direct re-exportation to British port he must pay (8-11). 1881. s Octroi tax at Maskat and Matra on goods from interior for sale and expor tation raised from between IJ and 2^ per cent, (formerly included in customs contract) to 6 per cent, (now purchased by farmer as separate tax for $ 15 5b0) Did not consult British Agent. Likely to irritate Arabs and drive trade to Sur (11-7). 1885. Chief camel-breeders, Bedouins of Sharkiya, and after them tribes of Dbahira; 3,000 camels, possibly many more, could be collected in these districts in short time. Average price of really good animal $ 25 (26-4). 1886. Sultan imposed 5 per cent, duty on dates brought from interior to Mesnaah, Khabura, etc., payable there in case of direct exportation abroad,114 otherwise on arrival at Maskat. 'Arthi' tax of 2 per cent, at Khabura abolished (1-3). 1887. Ross sujrgested revision of Commercial treaty with Maskat in view of new Treaty with Zanzibar (1-9). Draft sent up modelled on new Zanzibar treaty. No material departure from spirit of existing treaty. Sultan not yet consulted (5-11). 1888. Article approved by Government of India to debar Sultan from prohibiting export or import of any article and from levying export duties without consent of British Government. No necessity for an article to exempt from duty goods re-exported by land. No objection to clause for enhanced taxation of alcohol. Restriction on importation on arms and ammunition might stand over (15-8). 1889. Masqat customs resold to Damodar &amp; Co., for $111,000 or $1,000 more than year before (13-12). 1890. Treaty signed by Faisal and Ross at Mastat on 18th April (4-9). Govern ment of India recommended ratification to Secretary of State in spite of mistake by Ross who acted without powers of plenipotentiary (8-9). Foreign Office desired fresh treaty with certain modifications, including condition as to duration (11-12). 1891. Fresh treaty signed by Faisal and Ross at Maskat on 19th March. After 12 years and on 12 months' notice by either party treaty to be subject to revision by plenipotentiaries appointed on both sides. Sent to Secretary of State (18-8). Ratified by Queen at Balmoral on 29th September. Treaty should be terminable, not revisable, after 12 years on 12 months' notice. Sec retary of State desired amendment to be made in this respect in protocol of exchange (lt)-10). 1892. Ratifications by Sultan and exchange carried out at Maskat on 20th Feb ruary (27-2). Natal desired to be included in, Cape of Good Hope to be excluded from, operation of new treaty (8-9). 1893. Canada acceded to Treaty (15-4). • • 1894. After closing of Indian mints to free coinage of silver, Austrian dollar at Maskat fell relatively to rupee and heavy export of rupees and pice set in. Dollar (before closing of mints-136 to 140 pice) fell on 20th March 1894 to 108 pice. Searcity of pice caused hardship to poorer classes at Maskat. Poli tical Agent discountenanced Saltan's idea of prohibiting export of pice. .On 22nd dollar rose to 118 pice (30-3). Copper coinage of Oman was of 3 sorts, Indian, Zanzibar and German East African: Indian pice slightly more value- able than others (4-5). Dollar alone was current in interior. All mercantile transactions in a practically fictitious coin, (Persian, long out of circulation) called ' Muhammadi,' , at 11| Muhammndis to dollar. Sultan's revenue in dollars except subsidy, which in rupees. Sultan powerless to influence rate of exchange, which was fixed by traders on advices from Aden and Bombay. Austrian mints had lately supplied 45,000 new dollars to Maskat. Indian rupees could not always purchase 64 Indian pice, sometimes only 68. Twelveyears previously nearly all copper coin English : now only j. Sultan preparing to mint pice at 140 to dollar. Double Indian rupee if coined, might oust dollar (24-8). Sultan lately closed scales at Matra except for weighment of iard dates. He and Turki had always looked on Matra with jealousy. In 1880, 1885 and 1889 attempts were made to force Matra dates to come to Maskat. Sultan pretended that arrangements for weighments at Matra were only temporary (this though weighment at Matra had been carried on for 24 years) and that original and only proper place of weighment was Maskat and that no loss was caused to British subjects by change (30-8). 1895. Correspondence arid interviews continued without effect. Explanation pro bably that Hindus in Maskat had prevailed on Sultan to favour them at expense at Khojahs of Matra. Fard dates went to America and arrangement therefore unduly favoured American trade. Decadence of Maskat due not to weighments at Matra, but to neglect to improve communications with interior and absence of fear of pirates, from which in former times convoys were made up at Maskat (20-1). Scales at Matra were opened again without official notice to Agent on 25th March (13-4), 1898. Messrs, A. and T. J. Malcolm proposed to obtain monopoly, concession and mining rights in connection with oxide of iron deposits said to exist at Abu Musa, Musandam, etc., and hoped for good offices of British Government Agents in furtherance of object (11-5). Government of India replied favour could not be shown to individuals, though legitimate trading enterprises would be viewed with pleasure. Resident m'ght offer advice, in order to protect Chiefs from unscrupulous traders (16-7). Practically whole export and import trade of Maskat in hands of British Indian traders who were also the only farmers of customs in country. No other had sufficient capital to act as Sultan's bankers, to honour Sultan's cheques on overdrawn account. Right to farm customs was sold by auction to highest bidders for period of 1 year. Contract not binding on Sultan. Purchase money paid in monthly instal ments and farmer must make considerable advances whenever required. Arrangements for collection were left to farmer. Sultan was generally in debt to farmer and could not offend him and was compelled to countenance illegal charges. Most British traders were ignorant of terms of treaty of 1891; rest were afraid to offend Sultan as they would afterwards have difficulty in recovering debts from Arabs, etc Both British and Arab traders had to pay 20 per cent, on Oman tobacco, 7J per cent, on mother-of-pearl, shark oil and fins, isinglass and dried fish, and 6 per cent, on arms and ammunition. Goods of British traders sent from one part of Oman to another were taxed at both places. Charges made for weighment were contrary to article VI of treaty. Chief in direct advantage to farmer was power acquired to hamper business of his rivals. Five times since 1881 Matra traders (except Messrs. Towell and Co.) had been obliged to bring dates to Muskat for weighment: this obstruction and delay contrary to Article Xof treaty of 1891. Sultan also often attempted to replenish treasury by means inconsistent with British treaty rights, e.g., by sudden impo sition of 5 per cent, extra tax on dates from Rostak and Wadi Maawal, which already bought up and paid for by British Indian traders : repeal obtained with difficulty. Customs farmer was not a servant of Sultan and it was wrong to look to Sultan for redress. Rules consequently framed by British Consul under Arti cle I ofMaskat Order in Council of 4th November 1867 making British subjects liable to Rs. 500 fine or 3 months imprisonment who (1) after entering directly or indirectly into customs contract failed or unreasonably delayed to furnish Consul with terms of contract, (2) collected, etc., taxes other than those authorised in Articles 6 and 7 of treaty of 1891 (3) collected, etc., taxes in a vexatious manner contrary to Article of treaty (19-11). Scales at Matra were not reopened till after end of date season i894-95 and since then scales at Matra closed except for Fard dates every date season (6 -12). lie ' export duty ' of 5 per cent, on dates brought from interior to coast, Fagan pointed out inequality of incidence.116 la Khabura, Howasinah paid neither import nor export tax ; British Indians? paid 5 per cent, both ways. Banians of Mesnah and Burka had to pay in full; but Yal Saad, dealing through Khadra and Wudam, where they allowed no In dian trader to reside, paid nothing. At Sur, Beni Bu Ali of Awaikah paid nothing while Jenebeh of Magraintain paid 1 per cent, export and 1^ per cent, import tax, and British Indians 2^ per cent, export and 5 per cent, import tax (5-12). Sultan imposed punitive date tax on Rostak and Wadi Maawal tribes on 24th July and persisted though whole crop already bought up by British Indians. On 30th September he was persuaded to remit, but notified intention of re-imposing it in following year (8-12). Political Agent signified intention to Government of India of preventing British Customs farmers from levying more than 5 per cent, import tax on any article from foreign port and suggested Government of India should direct export taxes (from interior or from one Oman p )rt to another) to be restricted to 5 per cent, and not to be paid twice, unless for local consumption regarding which no provision in treaty of 1891. 'Weighment charges also to be prevented (6-12). Maskat Customs leased to Damodar Dharmsi and others for year for $ 170,000, or $ 2',000 more than preceding year. Of this $ 16,000 to be kept in payment of claim against Sultan (7-12). 1899. Government of India did not accept assumption that the customs farmer was not a servant of Sultan. Rules defective, could be evaded and might throw customs into hands of foreigners. If not already enforced should be suspended (31-1). ^ 1900. Government of India suggested to Secretary of State that existing Karachi to Jask cable should be diverted to Maskat, or 2nd cable from Karachi should be laid via Maskat to Jask, and in either case one of existing cables between Jask and Bushire should be looped into Bandar Abbas or land line extended there from Jask. Government of India strongly urged necessity for cable to both places and hoped His Majesty's Government would undertake part of cost (3-5). Net revenue to Sultan after working customs direct for 1 year just under $ 190,000. Highest figure previously derived from sale of customs $ 170,000. Sultan disinclined to employ British official, partly after talk about Russians taking over Bandar Abbas customs and French reports echoed in Arabic papers that Maskat customs and with them State were about to come under British domination, and partly from fear of abolition of personal and tribal indulgences (5-12). Government of India considered that goods consigned from abroad to agents at Maskat, with discretion to dispose of them locally or to find another market in neighbourhood, must be held to have reached their ' destination ' by delivery to agents at Maskat, This the strict ly legal view Government of India thought however there should be no rule requiring that goods for transhipment or re-exportation from Maskat should be so declared in manifest of vessel or in bill of lading. If agents followed procedure laid down in 6 (1) of treaty real intent thereof would be secured. Destination of goods, for practical purposes, was destination stated by agents. If Sultan's contention admitted trade would decline (24-12). - 1901. •* Sultan accepted Government of India's view and explained reason of his original objection was absence of bonded warehouse and probable dishonesty of merchants, who were consequently allowed to keep the goods free of duty on their own premises pending re-exportation (6-2). Sultan agreed to examina tion of coal at Rufsheh by geological export (16-8). Examination took place on 22nd and 23rd May and Kraft reported quality satisfactory, but quantity uncertain. Government of India directed thorough and sustained examination and asked Political Agent whether, if coal sufficient, it should not be workedby Britisb Government or by British firm instead of by Sultan (9 -7). Treaty of 1891 expired on 19th March 190i, or one month and 12 years from ex change of ratifications. If notice given on 20th March 1903 Treaty would terminate or be open to revision on 19th March 1904 (25-9). 8ultan desir ous of imposing enhanced duty or sale restrictions on cheap alcohol in Maskat. Government of India would place no obstacle in Sultan's way ; but action proposed was contrary to French treaty of 1844) and American treaty of 1833, as well as British treaty, and French and American representatives should be ap proached by Sultan (6-12). On 80th October Sultan and Cox left Maskat for Khor Jerama on ' Perseus.' Sea bad and Cox did not land till 1st Novem ber. Anchorage entirely exposed and unpleasant to lie at with rocky steep coast as a close lee shore and a confused sea. 'Assaye' with Mr. Oldham, Gov ernment Geologist on board had already arrived (2-11). Party were out from 3rd to 16th November. Coal was found by Oldham to occur in tertiary rocks, newest rocks of the district, extending from 4 miles north of Migel to 3 miles south of Musweh, 10 miles in all. Seemed very limited, merely pockets in fact which reached good workable thickness in places, but rapidly thinned out. Exposures indicated an area of coal perhaps J mile square with thickness of 4 feet and more ; say 250,000 tons of workable coal. Conditions adverse. Khor Jerama to Musweh would require 30 and Sur to Musweh 35 miles of rail way. No local labour available, nor timber, nor firewood nor provisions; nor even water within 10 or 12 miles. No probability of other more continuous seams iu neighbourhood (3-12). 1902. Government of India not prepared'to proceed further in matter, but result should be explained to Sultan and he asked to promise first refusal of concession to Biitish Government (17-2). Sur coals of excellent quality, almost equal to best Assam coal (16-4). Information about Sur coal-field to be 'kept in confidential (3-5). Sultan gave required undertaking (31-5). 1903. Sultan was proposing to raise ' Zakat ' on dates, in origin a religious tax and always collected direct even when customs were farmed, from 1 per cent, to 2 per cent. British traders objected. British traders obtained dates from interior in 3 ways (1) by sending out local middlemen, with advances in off-season, (2) by purchase from agents of growers at Maskat, (3) by sending out represen tative in date-season to purchase on spot; this last was least frequent method. Only in 3rd case need ' Zakat' fall on British trader (22-6). Sultan informed under orders of Government of India that there being no difference between Zakat levied as proposed and enhancement of export duty he must arrange to recover Zakat in interior if at all (2.7). Government of India had no objec tion to prohibition of British subjects from selling spirits by the glass or at less than Re. 1, per quart, provided French and American Consuls took similar action at same time (29-6;. Report by Cox on Zakat, export duty and Arsa (octroi). At Sohar and in other part of that Wilayat, Zakat levied regularly, and at other ports irregularly, from Arab producers, besides the universal 5 per cent, export duty. This in spite of fact that correspondence of 1885 shows export tax was in lieu of Zakat. No Zakat at Sur; and Burka, Sib and Karyat treated as incorporate with Muskat for fiscal purposes (26-9).125 K.—SANITARY MATTERS IN MASKAT. 1875. Government of Bombay enquired of Political Agent, Maskat, whether any measures could be taken to prevent importation of plague from Mesapo- tamia to India through trade with Persian Gulf (41-8).^ Miles replied Sultan would no doubt arrange for inspection and detention of vessels if desired (1-9). 1899. Two cases of plaguo—one in Matra, one in Maskat. Sultan raised quaran tine from 6 to 10 days counting from arrival at Maskat and prohibited landing of deck passengers from India, G^vadur and Jask, except servants of superior class passengers. He also asked Government to take over quarantine arrangements. Agency Surgeon was prepared to do so if given two extra Hospital Assistants (13-4). Hospital Assistants arrange! for (25-4). Sultan declined to reduce quarantine to 10 days from infected port for vessels carrying no qualified doctor (8-5). Sultan professed inability to pay for Hospital Assistants (17 -5). Government of India ordered Hospital Assistants to remain at Maskat at Government expense (7-6). Sultan on advice of French Coosul refused Agency Surgeon's draft quarantine regulations and abolished quarantine at Maskat altogether (18-7). Hospital Assistants ordered to return to India (2-9). 1900. • Plague declared in Matra suburb (12-1). Disease still confined to Khoja Port (10'2). Sultan tried to get medical staff from Bombay but failed. He could pay Rs. 300 per mensem for men from India, but they should be under his orders (27-2). Sultan's own men arrived and he withdrew request (8-3). Plague inoculation flourishing in Maskat : Sultan asked for 400 doses for own use (28-4). Plague mortality slight and Maskat declared free on 30th May (30-5). Sultan disposed to give Agency Surgeon (Smith) Rs. 150 per mensem to superintend quarantine arrangements and attend serious cases in Sultan's own household (16-8). Sanctioned by Government of India (19-9). Agency Surgeon should besides give professional help and advice to Sultan in all sanitary and medical questions, besides attending all cases requiring his aid in Sultan's household ;(19-9). Arrangement came into force from 1st October. Extent of assistance given by Agency Surgeon would depend on Sultan. Sultan had placed his native doctor, Saiyid Magdum,^ under Smith's orders (13-10). Cholera imported probably from Karachi via Gwadur, broke out in Matra in September 1899 There had been epidemics in Oman in 1821 and 1865 ; both came from sea. Total attacks in Maskat and Matra about 1,339, of which 449 in Maskat. 274 deaths in Maskat and 462 in Matra. Chief Arab remedy, for this as for other maladies, actual cautery. Epidemic spread over whole interior: 470 persons out of 1,000 died at Surur, nearly 1,000 out of 5,000 at Semail and 450 or 15 per cent, at Nakhl. Total deaths in Oman about 12,331. This epidemic preceded by one of small-pox carrying off 6 ,000. Epidemic in Maskat was at its height at beginning of November and ceased at end of Jan uary 1900. At Matra it reached its height at middle of October, recrudesced end of November, continued December and finally declined middle of January 1900 (1-4). Small-pox always prevalent, but no severe epidemic in Oman for more than 30 years. All Oman subjects were against preventive measures, especially trading classes during date season (28-4). G. C. Press, Simla.—No. 1547 F. D,—22-8 o4.—20.—T. K.-----</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002b9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/723</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002b9</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/723</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Historical and Political Materials, Maskat [Muscat] territory, 1872-1903'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1903/1903</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-04T11:21:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (66 folios)</extent><extent>There is a list of contents on the front page of the item.</extent><extent>Pagination: the item has original pagination, which commences at 1A on the front cover, and continues through to 135 on the back cover. These numbers are printed, with additions in pencil, and can be found in the top centre of each page. Pagination anomalies: 1A, 1B.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of
                           Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Historical and Political Materials, Maskat Territory, 1872-1903(Simla: G C Press, 1903).The Gazetteer summarises events in Oman, Gwadur [Gwadar], Dhofar, and Zanzibar on a year-by-year basis, and has separate sections on Maskat [Muscat], again on a year-by-year basis, covering: British policy; Zanzibar subsidy and British loans; protection of British subjects; British extra-territorial jurisdiction; British Government establishments and property; trade and customs; and sanitary matters. The text contains references to original letters, telegrams, and other documents (not included), which are indicated by numbers in brackets.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abū-Shahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hormuz Isle</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Gazetteers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002b9#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>