<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002f7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:29:16.828Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">10 No • of 1903. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, J&amp; f June 1903. To The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, With reference to your letter No 118 dated 13th June 1903J have the honour to inform you that the two Abbas referred to therein have been received and placed in the Toshakhana of this Residency• Your suggestion regarding a suitable return present to His Excellency Seyyid Taleb Pasha has been noted. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, uapva in, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.* %J.. rife. No : 6ZZ of 1903, T-o ($ British Rtsidbncy and Consulate-General t Bus hi re July 1903, To The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, Si r, In r^ply to your letter No: 117, dated the 13ih June 1903, I am directed to forward herewith for your in forma- tion / and necessary action / as regards furnishing the in formation which the Resident now requires, copy of the mar~ T o :3-S, A, ,dated 8th July l903\ ginally noted letter to the Government of India, 2, I am to inform you that the Resident seos no objeotion to the Banias going to Katif at their own risk and sub ject to such assistance as we may be able to give them, which may not be great. He approves of your proceedings, but wishes you to hear carefully in mind that you have no Consular position in Turkey and must therefore be care- J*ul to avoid raising the suspicions of the Turkish authori ties at Busreh by entering into direct correspondence wi thI' I I with Turkish officials . 5. The Resident will of TekchandDwarmdass 's visit I hovt vht honour to be Your Tiiost oh^cLi^Tit sbrvcxiii 'aptain First Assistant to the Political Resident in lh&amp; PersiaTih iI &lt;3) Copy of a letttr No :S~S. A. , datod Shtraz the 8oh July 1903, from Lieut-Colonel C. A, Kemhall t C * I , Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to L. W. Dane, Esq*, Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Depart ment, Simla, I have the honour to submit for the information of the Government of India copy of a letter with enclosure addressed to me by the Ass is tanc Political Agent at Bahrein on the subject of the reopening of trade relations with Katif by the Bunniahs of Bahrein. It will be remembered that some demi-official corres pondence has already taken place on this subject and j beg to invite a reference to this correspondence ending with my demi-official letter to Major Daly dated 23rd May 1901. do not put much faith in the professions of the Mutassarif cj &amp;1 Mass a and I doubt if he has the power to support the Bunniahs againsu the oppression of their Mohammedan rivals at Katif. However this may be, I seejno objection to th* Bunniahs reopening trade thevr nsk and I an instructingI am also requesting him Co supply me with such information as he can regarding and the nature of the former traders at that place and I am also ashing him to furnish^f he can, mor* detailed information regard ing the disabilities under traders at Katif suffered and which led to their wi vhoLrawal from tht plact,. 1 may thtn bt in a posi tioTi to mo.kb suggestions on the subject of the oppoiiitrntnt of Q ConsulaT Agent at Katif*Copy of ad&amp;s^hch No 31 dated 19th October 1903, from F. E Crow Esq:, H.B.M's Consul, Bussorah, to Lieut-Coh C. A. Kemball, C. 7. E., H.B.M's Acting Consul-General^ Bush ire. I have communicated to the Vali the substance of your letter No 642 of the 9th instant in regard to the complaint against the farmer of the Customs at Katif. Under the Commercial agreement between this Country and Persia of the 5th September last the 12fo export duty on goods destined for Persia was abolished. i .ere is therefore no longer any reason for claiming the aeposit in the case of goods sent to India and else where, and I do not understand on what grounds the Customs . Authorities at Katif continue to demand it. No of 1903. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, t November 1903. Copy of the foregoing desp&gt;atch is forwarded to the Ass istantAssistant Political Agent, Bahrein, for information and necessary action in continuation of correspondence end ing with his letter No 186 dated 5th September 1903* By order:, Captain, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*p. t (X /f fa , ^ No. fid- OF 100^. Karachi Customs House, /??'*/// This is to certify that the undermentioned Goods, per cc ^ - £ Tindal Sa * , from have been duly landed at this Port, as per No.77^ — /J SI'S*' /'/S&gt; 3 . Import Entry Packages. Weight or Quantity. Description of Goods No. and Date of Manifest from R bmarks. Port of ibiupexi.-Z; /t/n Examiner Head Clerk. [136 - 500-6-190^]No: of 1904. British Residency and Bush ire,. &lt; March 1904:. From Lieut-Colonel C m A. Keuiball, C m I JZ Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; To The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No:70, dated the 19th March 1904 on the subject of the Customs at Katif. I forward for your information copy of a letter recently received from H.U's. Consul at Basra to whom I have sent a copy ply, informing him that no further complaints have been re ceived owing to the fact that th | ceased on the termination of the date export season and ashing him to again bring the matter to the Fall's notice^ t so that His Excellency may see that the complaints were well founded and may issue more stringent instructions to his subordinates at Katif. You may perahps be in a positio tois Copy of a letter No: 7. dated 15th March 1904. from F,E Crow Esquire, H.B.M's. Consul, fomoall.C J .E Offg: Political Gulf. I have receivea a reply from the Vali in regara to the complaint of the Bahrein the Katif Customs farmer in d 12% dutch. His Excellency says the only levies duty according to t excess. He asks for the names they have been overcharged m Your de spate n No of Oy, state that the 12% was actually paid out merely that it wa.^ claima arid if such is the case, authorities at Katif that Cutch is m India ana tne export duty Itfc^may be sufficient to check any jurther attempt to overcharge. I should be glad if you woula inform me whether yen have received any further complaints on tne subject a/ui whether any nvsrchant was actually In my reply to the Vali I Customs farmer should be instruct andTo No. 3fl of 1904 % British Residency and Consulate-General, d) ^ Bushire, QaL u April 1904. TJie Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein. Sir, I am directed to acknovoleoge the receipt of your letter No 88, dated 9th instant, and in reply to request that you will be so good as to report the names of the traders who have complained, the amount of dates purchased by them and the duty paid thereon. A reference is being made in the matter to HJA's to Consul at Bussorah and in the meantime I amjenclose for your information a copy of a letter No 9 dated 29th ultimo which has been received from him. I have the honour to be. Si r. Your most obedient servant 9 Captain, First Assistant to the Pulitical Resident in the / Persian Gulf^Copy of a letter No: 9, dated 29th March 1904, from F. E.Crow Esquire,H.B.M's, Consul Basra, to Lieut-Colonel C„ A, Kemball,CJ EOffg: Political Resident in the Persian 'ulf. In reply to your letter No: 280, of the 25th instant^ in regard to the excessive duty levied on exports from Katif to Cutch r I have the honour to inform you that I saw the Vali personally about the matter to-day and communicated the information contained in your letter. At his request I have again written to him and asked him to instruct the Idutessarif of Hassa to enquire further infc• the Customs farmer's operations and to endeavour to recover the excess. I have also asked His Excellency to give strin gent orders for the protection of trade against similar abuses in future % The Vali promises me that he will draw the serious attention of the Mutessarif to the matter^' qj idBTit ICil , No s// of 1904. British Residency and Consulate-General, Buslnire, J U L Y 1904, Bushire 3/^ To The Assistant Political Agent Bahre in, Sir, Referring to your letter No 166 dated 16th July, I have the honour to state that you are at liberty to inform the Hindoo trader Thawerdas J animal that in the absence of an official British representative at Kateef / the amount of personal protection that can be afforded is limited but so far as the Residency can accord its good offices through you as the nearest British official, they will be so ac corded . 2„ I may mention for your oiun information that a more effective arrangement is under consideration but has not at present received sanction, I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. /tec / * I'a J or, Offg Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.4( •Copy of a letter T To r4 dated 11th. November 1904. : a.B.M's Consul^i3usreh ; to the Political Resident in the Persian Crulf • With reference to your despatch No 103H of the 15th September last, and my reply 31 of 29th September, I have the honour to inform you that I have received the following instructions from ll.^i's Embassy at Constantinople under date 10th September 1904, 'You should endeavour, in concert 'with the Pesident's 'assistant at Bahrein to obtain and forv.ard to me 'particulars substantiating the complaints of the im position of extra and harassing export duties, and 'it 'would be well to advise the Bahrein merchants to 'keep records of undue Customs charges or illegitimate 'molestations which could be communicated to you as 'each occasion arises in which redress is called for' would ask you kindly to communicate with Bahrein. Yo /IfOf of 1904. British residency and Consul at e-rfeneral. Bushire November 1904. Copy forwarded to the Political .Agent Bahrein with re ference to this office endorsement No: 1165 d&amp;ted with aa reruest that if any further information regarcing past transactions is forthcoming, it shoula re fur,-.isr.e&amp; to this office; and ^the traders may be informec. tr.? . '= -- ^ have be^ taken to put a stop to the malpractices compla.ineQ of out^ in spite of this, should they be harassed^ snoiua .^eep a note of everything they T Tiay have to co^p-ai-- a-xQ famish facts when called upon to do so . -» .ain, First Assistant to the Political Resident ih the Persian r-ulf. { In charge current duties ),India Office, London, 23rd December 1904. Secret, No, 61. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. ]\1 Y TiOlll), In continuation of my Secret Despatch No. 33 of the 5th August last, as to British Indian Persian Gulf: British Indian • i , T7 - t • i • j , 4. ts * commercial interests at Katir, I commercial interests at Kattj. ' enclose, for your Excellency's information, copies of further correspondence* with the Forei^ Office. 2. It will be seen that orders have hfen issued to the Mutessarif of #i? tt' • rkrt&gt; ^ ^ r» El llassa forhiddinir for the future * brom foreign Oflice, dated 7111 Decern- » ber 1904, with enclosures. the levy by the Katif Customs To ditto, dated 20th December 1004. « ' e ' i tanner or the excess duty on dates shipped by British Indian traders, and directing the recovery of the amounts levied in excess in the past. I have infoimed the Foreign Office that, if practical effect is given to these orders, it will be unneces sary to press for the appointment of a Consular Agent at Katif. 3. I request that I may be furnished with a report showing whether effect has been given by the Customs officials at Katit' to the orders issued by the Turkish Government. I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship's most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) S t. J ohn B rodrick. S. 63. AENCLOSURES. Enclosure No. 1. Foreiga Office to India Office. Foreign Office. Si r j 7th December 1901. With reference to your letter of 2n(l June I am directed by the Marquess of Lansdowne to transmit to you, for the information of the Secretarv of State for India, copy of a Despatch from His Majesty's Charge d'Aft'aires at Constantinople relative to the treatment of Indian traders at Katif. I am to enquire whether Mr. Secretary Brodrick considers that the action taken by the Turkish Government, as reported by Mr. Monahan in his Despatch of 29th September, is satisfactory, and whether the measures discussed in the first three paragraphs of your letter of 2nd June may be deferred for the present. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State ^ E. Go est. for India. Annex. 1. Mr. Townley to the Marquess of Lansdowne. No. 890. Constantinople, My Lord, . 22nd November 1904. With reference to your Lordship's Despatch No. 217, of 21st June, respecting the unfair treatment of Indian traders by the Turkish Customs Authorities at Katif, I have the honour to transmit herewith copy of a letter from the Acting British Consul at Basrah to His Majesty's Acting Consul General at Bushire, from which it would appear that the Embassy representations reported in Sir N. R. O'Conor's No. 512 of the 28th June have had a good effect. I have, &amp;c.. The Marquess of Lansdowne, K.G., Walter Townley. &amp;c., &amp;C., &amp;c. Annex 2. Letter from the Acting British Consul at Basra to His Majesty's Acting Consul General, Bushire, No. 31, dated 29th September 1904. Sir, With reference to your Letter No. 1035 of the 15th instant, respecting the excess duty charged by the Katif Customs farmers on dates shipped by British Indian traders, I have the honour to inform you that representation was made to the local authorities, and the Acting Vali has addressed the Mutessarif of El Hassa directing the recovery of the amount levied in excess, and forbidding such a charge for the future. I have, &amp;c., J. H. Monaiian. S. 63.Enclosure No. 2. India Office to Foreign Office. India Office, 20tli December 1904. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt ot Sir E. Gorst' B letter of 7th December, or: the subject of the treatment of British Indian ^Iirrepl^T am to state, for the information of the Marquess of Lansdowne that Mr. Hroilrick considers tue actioii of the luiush Government in inning orders for the discontinunnce of the duties which formed the subject of our complaint and for the recovery ot the sums levied in excess is satisfactory, and renders it unnecessary to press for to appointment of a Consular Agent at Katd provided that practical eftect fs 'jven by the local Customs officials to the orders sent them. On this point the Government of India will he requested to furnish a report. . The Under Secretary of State, Eoreurn Office. I have, &amp;c„ A. G odlet. t Y 33^ Ui'-c ^ lA, fit w. ^ /X ,I ^No of 19 British Residency and Consulate-'leneral, lib Bushira, j fi 1 May 1905 % To The Political Agent, Bahrein Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your letter Ho 75, dated March the Katif Customs fanner of excess by British Indian Traders, I a you will he good enough to submi soon as you can as the G-ovemmnt a report on tlie subject % I have the honour to he. Si r. most obedient servant. First Asst % Resiaent % II/ (ft ITo: ^/5of 1005. m TO, British Residency and Consulate General Eushlre June 1905. Captain P. B. Prideaux, I. A., Political Agent BAHREIN. Sir, I have the honour to enclose for your information copy of a despatch from H .M. 's Consul Eusra, on the sub ject of British Indian Comnercial Interests at Katif. 2 In view of the fact that the Hindu traders must now be returning to Bahrein, it is hoped that the submiss ion of the report asked for in this office rTo:656 dated 16th May IPOS, will not be long delayed. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. MajorCopy of a letter TTo:23 dated 2nd June 1905, from H. B.M. 's/' Consul Busra to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. IVith reference to your endorsement 110:699 of May 24th last regarding the claims of Indian traders at Bahrein, I should be obliged if you would be good enough to inform me whether the claims referred to are the same as those stated by the Resident in his letter to me No:842 of October 9th 1903, for excess duty on dates exported from Katif to Cutch As some of the correspondence on this subject has been mis laid it is not clear to us whether the case is the same. If it is, I mau add that His Majesty's Ambassador at Con stantinople, in his despatch of September 10th 1904 to Mr. Monahan (transmitted to you, as I understand, in Mr.Mona- han's letter to you No:34 of November 11th 1904) asked for particulars substantiating the complaints of the impos ition of extra harassing export duties, in order to enable His Excellency to make fresh representations to the Sub- lime Porte. These particulars do^seem to have yet been furnisjied. I will, on receipt of your reply, request the Vali to instruct the Mutessarif of Hassa to communicate direct with Captain Prideaux on the subject, in order to facilitate a solution of the question, but as His Majesty's Embassy is already in correspondence with the Sublime ?orte on the subject and awaits further details before taking action, I fear my request will not be attended with any useful result and it would perhaps be preferable that the Political Agent at Bahrein should furnish me with the particulars.required ^or the information of His Majesty's Embassy.| Uo. Of 1906. Political Asency Bahrein 5th July 1905. To The Political Resident in the Persian (Mlf, Bashire # Sir, % I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter 'To# 81S dated the 15th June 1905 on the sub ject of Piritish Indiaji Coiameroial Interests at Katif # As yet only one of the 'iindu traders concerned has arrived in Bahrein and Tikchand Bawarkadaa ifiio acted as | Agent for all and holds the Katif Oustoios receipts is expect- [ed by every mil# The report called for will be subriitted with as little delay as possible# I have the honor to be Sir Your most obedient servant - 7 Captain, Political A^entf Bahrein#Cop ' r ith refer en despatch of September neral Jlonahan's renly S.P.Notice same year,7 transmit to 'To. 62?58 August 24, I have received from t 1905. representations made to the subject of the trea by the iatif Customs. The promemoria from in the Sublime Porte's ing of the note would was the specific total Traders for excess of e local customs,but that 190r that amount had be -ers under this head. T 1899,after a prolonged dent in the Persian rul refund of 5012 rupees o by British Indian subje^ The sum of 2821 rupc cation from the Sublime by the Indian .Merchants with the total of the c obtained in September ] Agent at Jahrein and foi han's above mentioned de Ilonahan reported that th he had instructed the Mu tnese sums and to abstai future. You will observe * the reason why these cla: -.ndian traders have not ' I the properly 1 in India provi delivered at a the production to our case as ice of the cla Hassa to'recov raised by the delaying payme It would,he the Assistant Indian traders the xiatif Cust excess duty de not having don formality,if p of monies undi;Copy. Therapia August 28,1905. E' T i'b.i veierence to .Ir• ey' s Conx iden'tial c .tiptjCiTi' 01' 10,1904 and 'bo ..Ir Acting Consul Gfe— 0 -g xic^dl J.i .'nc.^an' o reply r :&gt;,n' of 'tne Slst of October of 'the ---'~o''o' same ^ ear &gt; 7 transmit to you,herewith,copy of a 'Totice which 0. oo Aagast a.'J:, J , ,ci c i ecei /ed iroin tlie Silblime Poi^te in answer to the 1905 • 'reprc ^ cn ^a uiont) made to tnem cy i^is . majesty's embassy on ^ J c c o )x ^.^0 11 eatment ox tiie British Tndian traders by the Aatif Customs. The promemoria from the British Lmbassy referred to in the Sublime Porte's ?, ' T otice'did not state,as the word ing of the note would appear to imply,that the 25000 rupees v/ci,o -c speciiic total of tr.e sums due to British Indian traders for excess of export duty paid on deposit to the 1 .-Ocil cast.^ms, l at tjiat it was calculated that in the year 190r that amount had been extorted from British India trad- -ers under this head. The promemoria also said that in 1899,after a prolonged correspondence,the Political Resi dent in oj.c Persian - ulf had only succeeded in obtaining a icfiind .1 5012 rupees out of a sum of 15000 rupees claimed '\y -•■ritis..i Indian subjects who had appealed to him. 'Jhe sum of 2821 rupees cited in the enclosed coramuni- Cati.in j.rom the Sublime Porte as being the amount claimed 1 j. tj^e jndian .• jerchants themselves i. r ould appear to tally 1 .'it.a tne total of the claims the particulars of which were obtained in September 1904 by the Assistant Political A^cnt at .;,a..rein and farmed the 1st enclosure in .Ir .'lona- han's above mentioned despatch.You will observe that : Ir . .lona^an reported t.-at the Acting 'ali had assured him that ■ c had instructed the .'lutessarif of 11 hassa to recover tnese sums and to abstain from levying such charges in the future. You will observe that the Sublime Porte state that the reason why these claims have not been paid is that the Indian traders have not yet presented to the Custom houseB | the properly legalised certifica'tes )! u .1 als in India proving that the goods exported were really delivered at an Indian destinati -n.I c .ii idci o c the production ox these certificates is nov iriimaoci ial to our case as the^ r ali of Basra has adinit + ;ed tlie Just ice of the claims by instructing the J.Iutessarix of ^1 Hassa to recover the money,and the question is merely raised by the Ottoman Government as a pretext for further delaying payment. It would,however,be advisable to ascertain from the Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein whether the Indian traders have furnished these Certificates to the Aatif Customs when applying for the refund of the excess duty deposited by them or, in the event of their not having done so,then to advise them to fulfil this formality,if possible,in order to facilitate the return of monies unduly levied. I am etc Sgd: ~T. .0'Conor.No: /5'0 2of 1905. of 1305. British Residency and Consulate-General, u. Bushire, /E^'October 1905. ■r To The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No: 377 dated 13th October and to state in reply that the suggestion made by you in the concluding portion thereof will be submitted to the Resident on his return to head-quarters. In the meantime I would request that you will be good enough to expedite transmission of the report called for in this office No: 330 dated 7th March 1905. I have the honour to be Sir, for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.1)05. Political A^runcy .irtin 'th fi0V£7nbcrl9O) To ^.e Political 'Fteoi lunt in the Persia Gulf, Bushlro, Sir, with rt fercnce to the second pars^raph of No. 1C93 / dated the 97th October 1905,1 have the honor to pi/) report that the Oustons Pamcrs of Katlf have in .way relax- eel tlieir opposition to the British In'li ji traders doing business in that district in spite of the orders referred to in the -Totioe fron the Sublime Porte,'To. 62558 dated the 34th Awrust 19(&gt;i,to the address of His Majesty^ Mbassador at Oonst^ntinopIe,nor have any of the excess duties levied in the year 1903 been yet recovered, o# 'Hie e^rport trade of 3'atif is practically all in the h^jids of ttro local merchants, Man stir bin Juma'Pasha Mid Ali bin Paras. The latter in conjunction with some sub- oHinate partners has also famed the Customs of the Pro- ' .noe of Hasa for about the la-rt 1- years. There is bitter ri'^ir-r entity between these tvro Katif nercharts and ^enever tjhe Oustoas T1 armers are in favour vrith the cons- ^,.atl' ch^nrinrr governors of the Provftnot -and districts ■ pe ~ ; ' s ^ ady to levy illegal rat.es of duty froia Iiansur fro..i every other trader. At the sane tine both T T pjad Ali bin Faras are at one in their determination the &gt;toiniahs out of Katif,and as every successive Kfl.1 ' ' ia?I:es friends at once vrith one or the other 69*1 .'.-n 5 tG,thc. Hln&lt;tUS i/ill never receive jTair 'ol^y until ths 8 ^ 0l ' v ' er of T^hese two persons is reduced. If the Porte 0U H o. l.y be induced to see that a pre ate r revenue should 0 finable from the date-gardens as soon as the growers ^ ^ d\bed to sell their stocks to the hirhest bidders 11 open market,the present unsatisfactory state of affairsNo. 77 / ^ British Residency and Consulate~Creneral, - fo Sir, Bushire, November 2905 7 7 7ze Political Agent, BAHREIN I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of llo 377, dated 13th October 1905 your two letters margin- \ r o 410, dated 4th November 1905 J ally noted, on the subjec of the claims and treatment of British Indians at KatiJ\ 2 The absence of any patent practical result from their original representation and unabated extortion or opposi tion on the part of the Customs Farmers at Katif has possi ~ had the effect of wxiking the Hindus in question apathetic as to their claims and sceptical of ever recovering any thing You will realise however j that the claims of these r men have a much greater importance than is representee by the Rs 2000/-odd to which they collectively amount;for this reason that the non-set tlerrtent oj them and the con tinued difficulties experienced at Katif is undoul tealy causing their fellows to hold olooj from, a section oj rult trade which they former 1 y handled regularly ana nil ich represents several lakhs annually % 3 % The eagerness of the community generally to regain their position is evidenced by their ^epe^ttd offers to pay the expenses of a Native Agent's appointment riain It is venj undesirable therefore t'.at we should contempl |. dropping the present claims ^hich we ''Lave already pressed on the Porte, if there is sufficient reason to believe ,as there seems to be, that they were originally well ^ ounded % 4 1 With reference to paragraph 2 oj your letter ..c 377, dated 13th October, it seems to me immaterial to us at ^. g present stag ^whether Turkish Consuls in India will or will not I iQ t grant certificates oj importation into India ^ I have little doubt that it would serve the purpose ofHM's Embassy if duly authenticated extracts from the Customs Import Returns of the British Indian Ports to which the consignments in question had been sent, were furnished % 5 I think it would be well if you sent for the 5 merchant covcerned at once and instruc tathem to take steps to' obtain these certificates or to enable you to do so officially forthwith; and with regard to TekcharA / 1 see no objection to your addressing him a letter to the effect tJiat he has been repeatedly directed through his representatives ^ to produce his books in connection with his claims and that if he fails to comply by a certain date, it will be presumed that he has fraudulent reasons for refusing to do so and steps will be taken to compel his attendance 9 ! i 1 I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, P Z.&amp;o I a J or, Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf\ \LNo: of 1906. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, January 1906. To The Political Agent, BAHREIN . Sir, T have the honour to invite your attention to my letter No: 1716, dated 15th November last, regard ing the complaint of certain Hindu traders against the Customs Parmer at Katif and to request that you will be so good as to let me know the result ot uhe action baleen 'by you in the matter. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Resident, Persian Oulf.No. of 1906. British Residency and Consul at e~nenera2. Bush i re, March 1906. The Political Agent, Bahre in. I am directed to invite y No 56, dated 31st January 1906, cess Customs duty from certain Customs farmer at Katif, and to request that you will be so good as to expedite transmission of the requisite information. I have the honour to be. Sir, obedient servant, \a i n. First Asst. Resident % INo. of 190 Q. British Residency and Consulate-General: Bushire, ^ // [ ( '90 6 / To T he POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Sir, I have the honour correspondence ending with your letter Ho 261, dated 31st March last, and to enquire receive the promised information Tickchand has not yet put in an appearance at Bahrein or sent m the requisite details, you sho ants that if they cannot persuade him to return to Bahrein or submit what is required of him, they run the risk of losing their claims. I have the honour to he. Sir, iur most obedient servant, Ca pta in First Assistant Resident. ( In charge current duties.)Karachi, 22nd August 1906. tyCc. In reply to your demi- official dated the 11th instant I fn qui red from the 'Tukhtyarkar of Tatta who informs me that Tekchand Dwarkadas leaves for 'Bahrain hy the next mail and that he could not leave earlier owing to delay in the settlement of accounts of some firmer I am writing to th e ^ukhtyarkar to ^ report the date of his 1 saving ^ Tatta and shall inform you ahout^ it. &lt;7 ^ ^ ^ Yours 7 '^ s 1935—2,coo-3-o6 No. 0 f 190 3 . British Residency and Consulate-Genera Bus hire, , 9 o G. To T he POLITICAL AGENT, ^aebeha. Sir, i am directed 'bo invi'te a reference 'bo your letter 'To.345, dated 11th ultimo, and to request that you will be good enough to let me knovr^ for the in- ^formation of the Resident, when he may expect to re ceive your report in the matter. I have the honour to be. Sir, v our most obedient servant. j* First Assistant Resident ur*'o: if- of l'.)06 ir'oli'tlcal Arency baJaraln 19th OctoTier 1^06 &amp; II To -eolitical Resident in the I'eralpn (ulf, ^ishire. Sir, .♦it:! reiorence to your office let-car To:2^79 dated the ^7th Sep-oenber 1^06 I have the honour lo report that as the result cf nor correupondence with ^he Oollector of Karachi the latter wrote to lae under dpte of 10th Sep tember 1906 that Tekchand I/vfarkadaa had left Tatta for the I'eniiji ( ulf ^Jid Bahrain. I re gret to ba^' however that the mpn has not yet arrived in j &gt;a' rain, and I beliw^e that ne bro :e his journey at Ijabai. % I have addressed utie Reoi ienvy A ents, oiiarqa and iiinga i7ix,h requests that if Toichand lands at either of these ports ohey should press him uo sjaart for Bahrain by the first iiail opportunity. There is little do-bt that Tekjh^id inuends soon to visit ijahrain, as he has sub.oittf i to the director Per- las Vasand ] al of Labai, stating that he was r&gt;roceedinpr to Bahrain ioiiediatel' and that he would present his acco ^int si an (.Hilf Telegraphs a claim against a : tin in narned (-o^al books at *uhls A enc^ ^ jr inanecbion I have the honour to be Sir Your Rost obedient servant Capi^ain, Political A:ent, Bahrain..1 A// V o- 'V ' r o. i?7/^ of 190 5. / British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 21st ' r ovember 190 f 3. To The POLITICAL ACuTiT, Bahrein. Sir, I am directed to invite a reference to your letter iTo.454, dated 19th October 1906, re^ardin^ the excess Customs duty alleged to have been levied at \atif from certain Hindu traders, and to enquire when the Political Resident may expect to receive the promised report from you in the matter. I have the honour to be. Sir, '''our most obedient servant. First Assistant Resident. J #&gt;TTo. QSZTS-ot 1906. riritish Residency and Consulate-General f Busliire, )ecember 190G. Bushire To The Polit.ical A^ent, BA[iKr;r T . Sir, T it,h reference to your letter ' T o,-524, dated 25th November 1D06, I an directed to inform you that the best course to adopt under the circumstances would appear to be to invoke the help of the Commissioner of Police,Bombay,in obtaining the requisite information from Tj eke hand. I there- -fore request that will send this office the questions you wish to put to Tlekchand in order to obtain his replies ox extracts from his books. you I have the honour to be Sir, T^our most obedient servant. First Assistant Resident urn■ v m ' 7D fj ~ „ le-b-ber No. 223 darted the 27-bh January 190' ftom r W copy of a 1 iL •! , . on T-PKldent in the Persian Galf, Eushire to the the Polit lcai ^ e&amp;J - - ' Ooffiinissioner of Police, Bo rib ay. &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; - -&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; With reference to the Chief Presidency Magistrate's Ko. '2 6a ted 10th January 190V, a copy of which is forwarded herewith, T •nave the honour to explain 'that the statement in question is re- qairea in connection with certain Consular representations and not, as the Chief Presidency Magistrate appears to tnihk, in a judicia. proceeding, so that the issue of a commission is not feasible. It would however be desirable that the answers required should be made on solemn affirmation before an officer empowered to receive such statements and I should be obliged by your arranging tms, either in Bombay or Tat/ba as c ire -instances me.y reqair As regards the man's address in Bombay, I am asKing tne Political Agent, Bahrein, to send you the particulars 0: 1,0; Qlj- r f of 1907 • British I-esi^ency ano ^onsulate -General, ^Fani Bushire, &lt;^7? 1 anuary 1907. / ■ t ? o'n v p i ti for iinfoi ma Copy forwarded to the Political Agen , '^ion and necessary action, with reference to ..is ^ated. 16th December 1906, Ey order, First Asstt Fesidert: 0: i-t/ber No- P2 dated lOth January 1907 froin\Ag copy of a ,T. orristra -be and Eevenue Judge, Bombay to the ahief presiaency itlcal resident in the Persian Gulf, ^ ash Ire • &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; With reference to your letter No. 310P dated the 30th Ultimo I* addressed to the Commissioner of Police. Bombay, who has referred it to me for disposal, I have the honour to inform you that in the absence of a Commission under Section 504 Criminal Proceedure Code (Act V of 1898f I shall not be able to examine the said witness. PU X1 particulars with regard to his address in Bombay should also be famished.s IQIO-S 00 ^- 06 o. of I 90 |U+ '' . British Residency and Consulate-General: Bushire, the April 190 7. A copy of the accompanying letter is forwarded to tlie Political Agent, Bahrein, for information and necessary action, with re ference to correspondence ending with his letter No. 58 dated 8tii February 1907. i By order, First Assistant Resident. i^L Letter Ko. 2510/6 dated 22nd March 1907, from Commissioner of Police, Bombay, to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, .^usnire. •fiUi enclosure (in original). &gt;■ j \ ' i I f 1 i\\ i£ Copy of a letter No. 2516/. dated 22nd March 1907 Cominissioner oi Police, ^oialay , to the Political Reside n Persian Gulf, Bush ire Vith reference to yo^ur letter No. 223 dated the 27th Jan uary last, I have the honour to inform you that Tekchand Dwarlia- das returned to Bombay on the 8th instant and was taken before % the Fourth Presidency Magistrate here. I forward herewith the replies eiven by him or. solemn affirmation before the Magistrate to the questions put by you.*A / (y i^ No. of 1907. ^ I 3r i'bish Residency 0210. ^onsuls^'t 1 © - ' •'©neT^lj /)- . Bushire Ire, ol 2 July 1907. 12 To Sir, The Political Agent, B A H R -3 I N « I have the honour to invite a reference to my No. 752 dated '9th April last, regaromg the excess duty alleged to have heen levied at Katif from oertain Hindu traders, and to request that you will be gooa enough to expedite the suhmission of the required Information, which has been c ailed for by the Government of India. I have the honour to Sir, Your most obedient servant First Assistant Resident. (In charge current duties).'■&gt;o:/f.£Cof 1907 Political Agency B^irain, TOuh Au-TUst 1907. (S&gt; To ^lie Political '-teai lent in the Persian &lt; ulf, l^uahire. Sir, '^ith reference to correspondenoe eniing irith your office letter Ko:16n6 dated the 0 ,8th July 1907 on the subject of the excess Oustoms luty allefl^d to hB.ve been levied at Katif on boiled dates exported to India in 1903, I have the honour to report that Tekchand Iwr-Tkadas, the purchaser of the dates on his own and other merchants• behalf, arrived in Bahrain on the 10th Aupust 1907. I have exaiained this inlividual'a accoiint-books, md have causud him, Tekch^xd I&gt;varkadaa, to affirm their accuracy and renuineness on oath. 'Tie 4 Statements c-nolos^ plve the abstract of the iniormtion contained in the bookr as follovrs of Statement A. Li3t A l9 rebi ui-os of Katif, from a whom boiled dates were mirchastd, ^ivin^ the quantities rates ^aid. Statement B. '^Intries in t^he daily cash book Rnd stock book showing the amo'ints ^aid on various days by n e :chand iHmrkadas as Oustoi s duty on bailed dates,rice, piece goods &amp;c. Statement 0. List of merchants in Bahrain and In lia for v/hom dates were 'nurchased for despatch to India. r,1 he quantity and price in each case is piven. Statement D. Particulars of the sums ^aid in Qxoeaa hy the Bahrain and India merchants, ^rouph ^ekch^jid Dv/arkadas.J m 10 I T o. 2 Tics' of 1907. British Residency &amp; Consulate-Cteneral Shiraz 1 October 1907. The Political' Agent, B A H R E I r. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter I: T o. 460 dated ^Qth August f or . ^ . , 4th September warding certain details at length obtained from 1 ekchand T&gt;warxcaQas, regarding the excess duty levied by the Turkish Authorities from British Indian tra ders at Katif in 190??. 2* I cannot undertand the figures shown in the statements furnished by you and do not think the vro/ernment of India could deal with them in their present form. The following observations will explain to you what I mean. (a). i 7 o connection is indicated by you between the several statements A, E, C 9 (b). Apparently 0. should tally with A. in regard to weights. (c). Apparently the rupee figures in table o. repre sent not 'prices' paid as stated out 'duty' paid, and the total should tally with the rupee total in B. W. ^ r e should then have the following result, (xvly figures have been added up hurriedly and re quire checking). iuxcess 1 — — — —^— — — — — — ^28'6. 1B5040 j lQ2.Es. 1 Es. 40--8. j Es. 850. ! Es. ^SlsSO. The s'eThese figures do not quite correspond with. furnished by Mr. G -askin with his letter i T o. 205 d 4th September 1904 but probably those now obtainable o r e the more correct. to * I return^ou, addressed to you on leave, the duplicate copy of your letter and accompaniments under reply in case you may be able to find an oppor tunity of obtaining personally while in Karachi a rore complete list of the Customs receipts required. In any case please see what can be done to get your several statements of account to tally better and to evolve a further table on the lines of that in the preceding paragraph, which will furnish a plain exposition of the case^and on which the Govern ment of India may be able to take action. I have the honour to be Sir, Tour mosy obedient servant, ivlaj or. Political Resident in the Persian -ulf HQTL The above letter wa!? sent direct, being received t o late to reach you while on leave..I No;/f^Of 1907 Political Agency Bahrain, SOth August 1907 # TO The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Sir, With reference to correspondence ending with your office letter No:16S6 dated the 28th July lf&gt;07_ on the subject of the excess Customs duty alleged to have been levied at Katif on boiled dates exported to India in 1903, I have the honour to report that Telcchand T )warltadas, the s purchaser of the dates on his own and other merchants 1 behalf, arrived in Bahrain on the 10th August 1907. 2, I have examined this individual's account-books, and have caused him, Tekchand Dmrkadas, to affirm their accuracy ajid genuineness on oath. The 4 Statements enclose give the abstract of the information contained in the booj^ as follows:- Statement A. List'49 residents of Katif, from r* whom boiled dates were purchased, giving the quantities and rates paid. Statement 3. Entries in the daily cash book and stock book showing the amounts paid on various daj y Tekchand .Dwarkadas as Customs duty on bailed dates, rice, piece goods &amp;c. Statement C. List of merchants in Bahrain and India for whom dates were purchased for despatch to India. The quantity and price in each case is given. . Statement D. Partlmlwe of the Sim. p.W J» escess by the Bahrain and India merchants, thui.iah throng Tekchand Dvrarkadas.I regret that there is no means of obtaining L reliable corroboration of the correctness of these acdountr the customs receipts from India are incomplete. I believe, however, that they are genuine, and they tally with the accounts in the other merchants 1 books which fact proves that Tekchand convinced the latter that the sums were actually expended. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.1 } A r A Ai Ho. .2fL No. 0 f 1007. \ British Residency aJ^Consulate-aeneral^ Bushire , £ 1 Tec ecember 1007, Please rerer to your letter No. 564 dated l~th ^ay 1907. I suppose we may now assume that it is im- possiole to get amy further certiTicates from Custom Houses in India that the dates have been imported. The Turks will most certainly ask for them. 2. Please refer to the last paragraph of the Secretary of State's despatch No. 61 dated £Srd Fee ember 1904 forwarded with No. I5?0 dated 7th ■' ,T arch 1905. T 'e have not had the report call- ed for yet. kpt-ain F.B. Prideaux, Political A^ent, Bahrein. INo. A?2 of 1908. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, January 1908, / ijects- dutvlevie. M. A cop'/ of the undermentioned conanunlcation Is forwarded with compliments to the Pl®tlcal Agent, Bahrein, for Information, with reference to the correspondence ending with his letter No.564 dated 16th November 1907. By Order, Resident to aptain, Assistant Resident. *********************** /6 f . Foreign. Letter No. A// dated /^January 1908,No . (,0. or loos. J Bri-tisli Residency and Consulate-General. Bus aire, ^vo/Febraary 1008. I orwarceo^ with compliments, to the Political A^ent, Bah rein, for information anc favour of e^rly report. Captain, Fir^t Assistant Resident, 1. (In charge cui^rent duties' to Telegram No. S.IO'^ dated 17th I 'ebruary 1003, from loreigi the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Telegram I.o. 143, dated 10th February l o 03, from the First Assistant President, in charge current duties, to Foreign,Copy. Telegram. Prom Foreign, Calcutta, No. S.lOo, ■nn + ated 17,2.03 (P), Please see your letter No. 101, cated loth January on tiie subject of I^atif. Please, wire whether there is any evidence that excess duty has been levied 'by Customs farmer on cates shipped by British Incian tracers at i.atif since orders were issued by the Turkish Government to the Mutessarif. Is excess duty being levied now ? Foreign. ■oooooOOOooooo- 'elegram. Jo Foreign, Calcutta. Im 0 , 14' , rated, 10,2,09. (P). Please see your telegram dated l/th February L.o, 106 on the subject of the Customs at Katif, I L3ve ^ 110 definite information but beleive tust o.ie .Liiui^^i Inc ' traders have ceased to export from I^atif, I am requesting Sahrein to submit a report on the sULje^u, ini- iiowever ;v ill talre some time. Trevor, ■oOo- iy) To No.122 of 1908. Government of India. Foreign Department Secret /&lt;/ External. The Right Hon'ble VISCOUNT MORLEY of BLACKBURN, O.M., His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 2nd July 1908. My Lord, We have the honour to refer to Mr.Brodricl^s Secret despatch No.61, dated the 23rd December 1904, regarding the British Indian commercial interests at Katif, and to enclose a copy of further correspondence on the subject. 2. In the despatch cited it was intimated that orders had been issued by the Turkish Government to the Mutessarif of El Hassa forbidding, for the future, the levy by the Katif Cus toms farmer of the excess duty on dates shipped by British In- . dian traders, and directing the recovery of the amounts levied in excess in the past. It was anticipated that, if practical effect were given to these orders, it would be unnecessary to press for the appointment of a Consular Agent at Katif, a measure which had been recommended by Lord Curzon's Adminis tration, and the Government of India were asked to report * Despatch No.74(secret external)dated the 31st} vhether the or- March 1904. « ders proved effective. 3. As regards the levy of excess Customs duty, it will be observed^that the orders issued in 1904 have been evaded. The Customs farmers at Enclosure No.4 { Katif have in no way re . 1 laxed their opposition to the British Indian traders doing business in that district, the .I the export trade of wliich. ic almost entirely in the hands of two merchants who are determined to keep our traders out of m * Katif. In 1905, 1906 and Enclosure No#4 j 1907 the Hindus were altoge ther prohibited from dealing with the growers in Katif, and were compelled to purchase dates only from these two merchants at 'delivered on board rates'. This resulted in a loss to them of about R:20 per 100 Katif maunds, 4. The position as regards the recovery of the sums le- ✓ vied in excess in clearly explained in a letter dated the 16th — —•—— November 1907, from ' Enclosure of enclosure No.l { — the Political Agent Bahrein, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The total of excess duty levied is now reported to be 1^3,187-4-7 o as compared with R 0 2,821 quoted by Mr.Gaskin in September 1904 and communicated to the |*orte 0 Enclosure No.l J „ ^ at the time. No refund of the illegal exactions has been made, and it seems desirable that the Turkish Government should again be addressed on the Bub- ject. In order to avoid the introduction of a new element of diBoussion we would confine the claim to the sum (K2,82l) originally quoted. 5. The present may not be an appropriate time to press for the arrangements which we originally suggested, but Lordship will observe that the Turkish Authorities have failed entirely to do justice in the case and we trust that a strong representation may be made to the Turkish Government interests of the Indian traders. ^ hav . Q etc., (signed) Minto 0 Kitchener h .E.Richards E.N.Baker C.H.Scott H.Adamson j .O.Miller W.L.Harvey&lt; A v ' no. ^ y // of 1908. ; R0Eidenc y ^ Consulate-General. d , 1 ■^r r r;PT-^\ bushire » September 1908. A copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded, ivith compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for information, with reference to the correspondence ending Viith his letter Ko.lSQ, dated the 7th March 1908. Captain, First Assistant Resident, (In charge current duties) Letter foom the India Office to the Foreign Office, dated the 5th August 1908. (Received under Foreign department endorsement l\ T o.2879~E.B., dated 29th August 1908). fJjLcopy ) • 11.. (received on 24th August 1908 with Political Secretary letter, Wo,32, dated the 7th August 1908) INDIA OFFICE. 5th August 1908. Sir, V .ith reference to ray letter dated the 20th December 1904, as to the treatment of British Indian traders at Katif, I am directed by Viscount Morley toenclose, to be laid before Secretary Sir E. Grey, copy of a Secret letter from the Government of India reporting that the orders issued by the Turkish Government in 1904 to the Mutessarif of El Hassa for the refund of the excess^ duty levied Vide letter of Acting British Consul at Basra} on dates have not dated 29th September 1904, enclosed with F.| 0. letter to India Office, dated the 7th December 1904. « b9en complied with, and that the orders forbidding such a levy in future have been evaded by measures making it impossible fcr the Hin due to deal direct with the date growers in Katif and compelling them to purchase dates from two particular mer chants at 'delivered on board rates'. As regards the first point Lord Morley agrees with the Government of India that it is unnecessary to claim the full sum of *3,187-4-7, which is now reported to be thinks that a representation should the amount due, but he be addressed to the Ottoman Government insisting on the immediateimmediate payment of the sum of 6=2,821/- admitted to be due in the Porte-a 'Notice' enclosed with sir I. (honor's despatch or the 28th August 1905 to Mr. Crow. As regards the second point. Lord Morley recogni ses that it may prove impracticable to procure the fulfilment of the undertaking given in that Notice, to place no ree- triction on the trade of British subjects, unless steps are taken lor the appointment of the Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein as Vice-consul for El Eassa and the sta tioning of a Native Consular Agent at hat if, in accordance .V- 1 ^ ^ witil the proposals of the Government of India in 1904, to '^Vf -V &gt;V ! which they revert in their present letter. The objections to these proposals appear to Lord Llorley as strong now as they v/ere in 1904, when it was decided not to adopt them. S In the circumstances Lord Lorley would be glad to be favoured with Sir E.Grey f E views as to how i'ar it is de sirable to press the claims of the Indian traders uncer the second head, a matter on which E. i:. Ambassador at Constantinople might be consulted. It ruz „ ce .ir.-r mind that the grievance is a very serious cr.e as io is e stimated that these traders lose about &amp; ^0/- or. ev-^Py hundred Katif maunds of dates purchased. .h.i. lo^.. 1907 is stated to cr secretary of State, foreign AZtzzzz Office. amount toeome h 30,000/- (£^,000/-) I hav e etc., Sd/ A. Godley,No . S of 1910. British Residency and Consulate-General. Bushire January 1910. A copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for information with reference to the correspondence ending with this office No.2711, dated the 12th September 1909 Major, First Assistant Resident, (In charge of Residency). November From India Office to Foreign Office, dated 3rd BM.sKw 1989 (Received under Foreign Department endorsement Ko.1952. E .A., dated the 13th December 1909).(Copy) India Office, 3rd Novernber 1909, Sir, With reference to Sir A. Godley^ letter, dated the 5th August 1908, as to the treatment of British Indian traders at Katif, I arc directed 'by Viscount Morley to enquire whether it has been found practicable to make any representations to the Ottoman Government as to the immediate payment of the sum of Rs .2821 admitted hy the Porte to be due to the traders in respect of excess duty on dates. Lord Morley would be glad to be favoured with Sir E. Grey s views on the wider question, discussod in Sir A. Godley s letter mentioned above, of moving the Porte to give effect to -he un er taking, in their Notice' of 1905, to place no restrictions on f the trade of British euhjecte in Katif. But Lord Morley has no desire to press the point, should Sir E. Grey think it inexpe dient to raise the question at present. I have etc.. Sd/- R. Ritchie •he nder Secretary of State, Foreign Office.no. B i iy ' British Residency and ConBUlate-General. Bushire, O January 1910. m ■ l4 ,7* h i&amp;e // • ^ A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for information in continuation of this office endorsement No.53, dated the 6]bh January 1910. Major, First Assistant Resident, (In charge of Residency). Extract from letter from Sir S.Grey to Sir G. Lowther, No.347, dated the 25th August 1908. Extract from letter from Sir G. Lowther to Sir E. Grey, No.545, dated the 6th September 1908. Letter from Foreign Office to Mr. Marling, No.35^, dated the 12th November 1909. (Received on 7th January under Foreign Department endorsement no .2016-E.A.. dated 21st December 1909)—JC. U0.347. Sir E. Grey to Sir G. Lowther. Foreign Office, August ^5th 1908. Sir, Til© recent introduction of constitutional Government into the Ottoman Empire appears to offer a favourable opportunity to secure the settlement of the various outstanding claims against the Sublime Porte. It would therefore be advisable to prepare a list of British claims and hold them in readiness for a favourable opportunity of discussing them with the Turkish Government, which Your Ex cellency will use your discretion.in selecting, the I enclose copy of a letter from the India Office respecting treatment of British Indian traders at El ^atif and have to request that Your Excellency will include in the list ot claim., the payment of the sum of two thousand eight hundred and twenty- one rupees which the Sublime Porte admitted to be due in August 1905 and which the Kuteasarif was instructed to recover (see Sir N. O-Oonor-s despatch to Mr.Crow of 28th August of that year) With regard to the second point mentioned in the despatch of the Government of India I should be glad to be favoured with Excellency's opinion as to what action might usefully be your taken in the matter. YourYour Excellency should use the concesBiDn which file Ma jesty's Ucvernment are making in regard to the Abbot and Blosse Lynch claims, as an argument in favour of settling this and any other claims which you may include in the list for presentation to the Turkish government, but as 1 have indicated above, I leave the time for approaching the Porte entirely to Your Excellency^ discretion. I am etc..No.545. Sir G.Lowther to Sir E. Grey (Reed September 14). IV Therapia, September 6th, 1908. Sir, I have the honour to reply to your despatch No.347 of the S5th ultimo, in which you intimate that the recent in troduction of a constitutional regime into this country seems to offer a favourable opportunity for securing the settlement of outstanding claims against the Turkish Go vernment . The remainder of the British claims against the Turk ish Government ar© described on pages 5,6 and r7 of the An nual Report. Satisfactory progress is, on the wbftle, being made with Ko.3 (Red Sea piracy claim). I will not fail to take the earliest convenient op portunity for presenting the remaining outstanding claims including that for the refund of the exoeas duty levied on dates at the Katif Customa, to the Turkish Government, but it must be borne in mind that they are at present in the greatest straits for money to furnish the most necessary payments, such as salaries and arrears, a loan being offered them at thia very moment only upon arduous terms.No.353. iTi Foreign Office, November 12th, 1909, Sir, With reference to the last paragraph of Sir G. Lowther's despatch No.545 of the 6th September 1908, I transmit here with a copy of a further letter from the India Office res pecting the position of British Indian traders at Katif, and their claim for a refund of excess duty. I request that you will report whether any progress has been made with this claim, and also furnish me with your view I I II 1 as to the advisability of raising the wid^r question of the treatment of British Indian subjects in Katif, - a point raised in ray despatch to Sir G. Lowther, No.347 of August 1906, but not dealt with by His Excellency in his reply. I am etc., '• M, Marling, Esquire, C.M .G., etc•, etc . , 6^°•&gt;No. 1727, dated Bushire. the 26th June (received 4th July) igro. From-LIEUTJNANT-COLONEL P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C I.E., Political Resident in the To—The Hon sle Mr. S. H. Butler, c .S .I., c.i.e., Secretary to the Govern ment of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. Referring to the correspondence ending with Foreign Department Endorse ment No. 2016-E.A., dated 21st Dece mber 1909, regarding the claims and treat ment of British Indian Traders at Katif, I have the honour to submit, for the •No. 402, dated 8th June 1910. information of the Government of India, copy of a letter* received from the Political Agent, Bahrain, reporting that a Hindu trader from thaf port has proceeded to Katif to open a shop there. Copy of a letter No. 402, dated 8th June igio, from Captain C. F. Mackenzie, Political Agent, Bahrain, to Lieutenant-Colonel P. Z. Cox, C.SJ., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gult } Bushire. I have the honour to inform you that Seth Chatamal Tarachand, a member of the leading Hindu firm of Bahrain Messrs. Gangaram Tikamdas &amp; Co., is proceeding to Katif to open a shop there. 2, 1 have given him a letter of introduction to the Kaimmakam of Katif requesting the latter to render Chatamal assistance in starting business. I have warned him that he should be careful not to get himself into trouble as I can give him no promises of assistance. The same man went over to Katif last September to collect certain debts and received useful assistance in doing so from the then Kaimmakam of Katif, Abbas Effendi. He now wishes to set up there in general trade and I do not think there is any danger to be anticipated. G. C. B. P. Simla.— No. Ca22i F. D -t27 **o.-44 -H.C.S.L.No. 2364 (Confidential), dated Bushire, the 3rd (received 12th) September 1910. From—L ieutenant -C olonel P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In continuation of my letter No. 2113, dated 7th August 1910, I have the No. 599, dated 22ndAugust igio. honour to forward for the information of the (jovernment of India, a further com munication received from the Political Agent, Bahrain, reporting the return from Katif of the Hindu trader Chatamal owing to illness and giving some details of his dealings there. Enclosure. No. 599, dated 22nd August 1910. From — C aptain C. F. M ackenzie , I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain, To-— L ieutenant -C olonel P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C .I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. In continuation of my letter No. 538, dated the 29th July 191 o, I have the honour to inform you that Chatamal has returned from Katif on account of illness and has given me the following particulars about his business dealings there:— Value of goods taken to Katif Value of goods sold Outstandings ... ••• ••• ••• Advances made for dry dates to Katifis including Mansur bin Juma Pasha. Rs. 18,226 12,556 7)356 S 1 ^ 60 A. P. 0 0 Chatamal has hopes of doing very good business in Katif where he is pro ceeding shortly with more goods. The Kaimmakam has treated him with every consideration and has pro mised him every assistance on account of thejntroductory letter I gave im. I G. C. B. P, Simla.—No. 0-3613 F. d .-17-9-10.-44.-H.C.SL.(ri- 0 Political A,cr0ncy» Bahrain, 2Srd July 1915 i Soae little time ago shortly aftar Katlf wae taken over by Bin Saud, I was approaohsd by Seth Tekchand who asked whether there was any objection to hie reopening business there* I replied that as no Hindu firm had been trading there since he hiMelf left sone 10 years ago after having been attacked by Bedouin and losing an arm, the present time - Just when the town had been taken over by the Amir of Hejd 9 and the country was in a disturbed state* seemed hardly propitious for renewing his enterprise• Afterwards he said something about going to Katar* He has renewed his request about going to Katif several t times, and has asked me to ask you about ths matter# and I do so» though it hardly seems nscessary to trouble you with it* Personally I see no particular objection to his p»ing to Katar# but even there it would be better to wa. t a li. perhaps* Ths presence of a British Subject or two might be useful later* But Tekchand ssems to have set his heart on going to Katif again, and there seems to me no advantage in his golnr there at / Lt•Colonel Sir Percy Oox, K*0.I*E*, Political Resident in the Persian Oulf*Copy. Foreign Offi:e to In Ua Office. 33843/10 Foreign Office, October 13th 1910. Sir With reference to your letter of November 3rd 1909, 1 am directed by Secretary Sir E.Grrey to transmit to you, to be laid +&gt;,0 Qonr-a+ow r«-p Rfate for India, the accompanying copy of the view that it is inadvisable to raise at present the question of the treatment of britl^h Indian Bub^ects at Katif. Sir E. Grey proposes, if Lord Morley concurs, to approve ._&gt;ir G. Lowther* s view. 12th, from ^is Majesty's Ambassador at I am, etc.. (Sd) L. Mallet.Sir G. Lnvrther to Sir E. Grey. 2o No•646• Therapia, September 12th, 1910. Sir, i arc in receipt of your despatch No.248 (30178/10) of the 23rd ultimo, transmitting an extract from a letter of the Politi cal ngent at Bahrein in which he informs the Political Resident Ho Busnire of a British Indian Subject^ departure for Katif to open a shop and engage in trade there. In your despatch r.o.353 of November 12th 1909, to which you refar in ycur above-mentioned despatch, you ask me for my views as to the advisability of raising the question of the treatment of British Indian Subjects in Xatif. At that time, in the early days of the constitutional regime, it was still so uncertain what effect new conditions would have in the outlying parts of the Empire and what policy the new Government would adopt towards neighbour- ing ota -93 that I did not consider I could usefully give any answer to your question. Since then the Turkish Government have, especial! in the region about Mesopotamia and Persia and the Persian Gulf, displayed distinctly expansive tendencies; and it appears to me therefore inadvisable, for the present at any rate, to raise the question of Lhe treatment of British Indian Subjects at Katif, and more particularly so if, as appears from your last despatch, ^ritish Indiana are able to proceed to Katif and engage in fc rade and commerce thers with some assurance of safety ani of good will -''rom the authorities. I have etc., ^ad) Gerard Lowther.India Office 'L- 2 Novemher 1910. Sir In reply to your letter No,33,B43, dated the 13th October, 1910, regarding the treatment of British Indian Subjectn at Katif, 1 am directed to say that the Secretary to State for India concura in the proposal of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to approve the view of Hie Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople that it is inadvisable to raise this question at present. In continuation of correspondence communicated 18th August and 6th September last, I am now to enclose copy of a letter from the Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated the 3rd September, regard ing the dealings of the Hindu trader, Chatamal, Attention is also invited to the enclosed abstract from the Memorandum on Persian Affairs for August, 1910, reporting that the Turkish Government have abolished the system of farming out Hasa and Katif Customs. I have etc., (signed) R. Ritchie. The Under Secretary of State Foreign Affairs.Sir S. Grey to Sir G. Lowther. Foreign Office, November 10th, 1910. No.342. (39994/10). Sir, With refsrenoe to your despatch No.646 of September 12th respecting the treatment of British Indian subjecte at Katif, i 2nd I transmit to Your Bxoellenoy herewith copy of a letter on to., r 1910. subject fron the India Office. I concur in Your Exeellency's proposal, ae containei in y0 ur above -mentioned despatch, not to raise this question .1th the Turkish Government at present. I ara etc., (sd) E. Grey. a SJ</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002f7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/24</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002f7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/24</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. E/1. Hindu Merchants at Qatif'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1900/1913</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-03T00:02:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (211 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: This file has a foliation number in the top right hand corner. The number is enclosed by a circle, running from the first folio of text and ending at the back cover. Attached to folio 40 is an envelope which contains folios 40A to 40F. Foliation skips from 115 to 117.Condition: Folios 35 and 36 are damaged on the right hand margin with Arabic text missing.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the British Assistant Political Agent, and later the British Political Agent, at Bahrain and the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, as well as with British officials in Constantinople, Basra and India. There is also correspondence with Ottoman officials, including Sayyid Tālib Pasha, mutasarrıf of al-Ḥasā’, and various Hindu merchants, including Tekchand Dwarkadas, Thawerdas Janimal and Seth Chatamal Tarachand.The file concerns the status and mistreatment of Hindu merchants (
                           bunniahs) resident in and trading with al-Qaṭīf, dating back to 1900. In a letter dated 2 August 1903, John Calcott Gaskin, Assistant Political Agent at Bahrain, gives a detailed report concerning commercial operations between Bahrain and al-Qaṭīf and the status of Hindu merchants trading in dried dates with complaints being made against the customs farmer (folios 24-27). In a further piece of correspondence dated 9 April 1904, it is claimed that Hindu merchants are descriminated against and made to pay 12% duty by the customs farmer at al-Qaṭīf (folios 43-44).Similar incidents are reported in subsequent years. Also in 1904 there are enquiries by various Hindu merchants about opening businesses in al-Qatif and the possibility of British protection, including a petition by the principal Hindu merchants of Bahrain (folios 51-53). There is further correspondence in 1905 and 1906 with representations to Sayyid Tālib Pasha (folios 66-69), and the Sublime Porte to resolve the situation (folios 84-85).Also included within the file are copies of Tekchand Dwarkadas's accounts (folios 128-149); a report on the status of Hindu merchants trading with al-Qaṭīf (folios 178-180); a report concerning the absence of Hindu merchants in al-Hafūf, al-‘Uqayr, Najd, and Qatar (folios 182-183); the opening of a shop at al-Qaṭīf by Seth Chatamal Tarachand of Messrs Gangaram Tikamdas &amp; Co. in 1910 (folios 184-193); and the situation of Hindu merchants at al-Qaṭīf after Eastern Arabia had been taken by ‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd (Ibn Sa‘ūd) in 1912 (folios 194-195).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002f7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>