<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:43:13.680Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&amp; - t lOu'a August 1945 from Britain JTe^hed to Foreign Hew Delhi. SUBJECTCharge of + he post of Assistant to His Hajesty* s Vice-Consul at Zahul lieference your telegram Ho. 3795, dated the 2,4tiu April, 1945. 2, Dr. Fuzammal Hussain in addition to his own duties as Assistant surgeon, Zahul, took over the charge of the post of Assistant to His ilajesty r s Vice-Consul^at'Zabul with effect from the forenoon of IZth/jJssi’l f 1945. It is requested that an allowance of 3s. 100/- per mensem be- sanctioned for Dr. Auzammal Hussain to c.^ipensate him for the additional ch a r ge. 3. A similar allowance was recommended for Dr. Muzamiaal Hussain for the period he ofticiated as Assistant to His Itajesty 1 s Vice-Consul, zabul, during ;the absence on leave of Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy referred to in my memorandum ITo.706/Z/117 dated the 19th Kay, 1945.V c. vJ ^ ••.«».»»•»»»..«» Gopy of memorandum No.1091-7/66 ^dated the 5th ijugaat 1945 from H.B•M’s Consul General for Khorasan, MOahied toftne Secretary to the Grovainment of India in the External iffaira-iDepartment. Reference my memorandum No,5 CS dated the 4th September 1944 para 2 Busget estimates. 2© The menial staff of this Consulate General have several times in recent months threatened to walk out oaring to the ^ inadequacy of their pay and dearness allowances under present conditions of scarcity and^rising prices. The total emoluments of 48 menials at Meshed, Birjand. and Zabul average Rs.57/- per head a^inst the fts.lll/- per month drawn by menials in all Persian Government offices and the standard daily wage of unskilled labour fts.3/-. Matters came to a head on 2-5-1945 when the men, who are possibly affected by a general labour unrest /stimulated by the Russians, demanded either (1) Indian Army rations on payment plus cloth at Indian rates for selves and families, or (2; increase in their total emoluments to correspond with Persian Government rates. I told them that Indian Army rations were out of the question and that the Government of India had already refused facilities for export of cloth for menials vide your express letter NO.F.174-ME/44, dated the 8 th Januaiy 1945. 3* During a visit to Tehran in June I obtained from His Majesty’s Embassy the past and present rates of including cost of living bonuses enjoyed by (1) Embassy farrashes and other denials (2) Ahwaz Consulate General Escort sowars. I append a statement showing the rates in both cases. It will be seen that the Embassy meqials have had increases of 450 to 550 % in their pay and now enjoy an average of tomans 118 or, say Ss.120/- p.m. while the Ahwaz sowars get an average of tomans 86.2 or say fis. 88 /-. The cost of living at Meshed is at least as high as at the Capital and much higher than in Khuzistan. 4. It was advisable to do something for the men without further delay, %s a part from the danger of serious dislocation of the work of this Consulate General, discontent among the menial •staff was highly undesirable from the security point of view, cf. Sir John Dashwood’s remarks in his despatch ANl o.$9 of 11th September 1942 (copy forwarded to the Government of India under my endorsement No.45o dated the 21st September 1942). I therefore decided in anticipation of the sanction of the Government of India to raise the basis pay of our menials to an average of 33/- per head per mensem and to add a dearness allowance calculated at 225% of basic pay. This brings the total average emoluments up to, roughly, the Persian Government rates. As soon as there is any cnange in the pay of Persian menials the above rates will be modifiSa correspon- dingL*. • : ^ 5. The total increase in expenditure debitable to Office Allowance grant amounts to Rs.2412/- p.m., against which may be set off 8s.228/-, I am saving by reduction of three farrashes and one garden cooly. The total net cost of the revision will amount to 8s.18929/- during the current year, as the new rates have been brought into force with effect from 1st June 1945. If approved the increase will be included in our revised estimates for 1945-46•If From % The Under Secreitar m Government 'India in^the External ^epar^ri . nt. To I His Maje8ty f a Consul* GeneraT for Khorasan, Meshed, Memorandum No«F»23(5)-£/45« Dated Nee Delhi, the August 1945, Reference your memorandum No •706/&amp;/117 dated the 19th May 1945* 2. Sanction is accorded to the igrant of a Soecial Pay of fe.100/* P,M # to Dr. Lluzaamal Husain, Assistant Surgeon, Zabul, for the period he officiated as Indian Assistant to His Majesty 9 s Vice-Consul, Zabul, in addition to his o*n duties in the absence on leave of Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy. Sd/«* P.N« Krishnaswamy, Under Secretary to the Government of India,— &lt;&lt;* T»i%irsit No-120-S/OeuBp/44« Da tad siala* the 15th 3apt«ri»ar # 1944. Proa &gt; Koroign, Siala, To - - Britoanaul ( hashed. Tong letter Mo.900/7/66, of August. 2* Continuance of dearness allowanoe to your staff on aaae tense as hitherto sanctioned upto end of Nor sab ar 1944 or till the end of mar, shiohaTer la earlier oubjeot to your reporting if there takes place any uihetantial fall in the general cost of Using*■** '-'TC r, V l9t%( 59 ) va ^ Extract from letter No«1200/A/62, dated Meshed the 14th November, 1943, from His Britannic Majesty's Con sul-General for Khorasan to the Secretary to the Govt, of India in the External Affairs Department New Delhi. Subject:- Budget Estimates of the Khorasan Consulate- General (including the Zahidan Consulate)for the year 1944-45. * * * ; * * 8 * (iii) Offic e Al lowance. -The contract grant of Rs.30,000 has tcTprovide for ! 1) Menial establishments at Meshed,Birjand and 2) Fodder for Escort animals. (Zabul. 3) Line gear for Escort animals. 4) Liveries for 47 menials. 5) Repairs to buildings at Meshed,Birland and 6 ) Hot and Cold weather Charges. ' (Zabul. 7) Improvements to the Consulate buildings and gardens at all the three stations . ( 8 ) Medicines for 3 dispensaries (Meshed,Biriand h (9) Lighting. (Zahul) Expenditure under ^11 these items has consider ably and unavoidably risen owing ( 1 ) to the increase in the*'official and seci?l activities of the Consulate-Gene ral and subordinate pffiaassand to the re-opening of the Meshed and Birjand dispensaries(2) to the rise of 600- 900% in the cost of materials, services end doily labour (3) to the necessity of paying the 28 menials emoloved by _ the Meshed Consulate-General and 19 by the Zabul* - and Kain Vice-Consulate, dearness allowances' ranting from 150% on the my of single men to 300% on that or men with 7 large famililies. The rates p*iven in my telegrams No.986 • dated the 18th September 1943fcJ.v.) represent^tho minimum that it ha.s been round necessary to pay to menials in or der to keep them in service; it must be remembered that owing to war conditions employment is plentiful and and highly paid on the eastern as well as the western supply route to Russia.Oovarnraent of India, iiixtornal Affairs Department* iXPRi^d LuiTT^R. Foreign* Simla* Britconsul, Meshed* 5? V * g ' 65C3 ! Q4? i e O , No. 18(13)-ii/43. Dated Simla, the |»7A j. August 1943* jUfJdCTj* Increase in dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of the Consulate General for Khorasan* In confirmation of Foreign t elegr am No* 6441. dated 4th August 1943 sanction is accorded to an increase oi 50% in the rates of dearness allowance sanctioned in Govemnent of India External Affairs Department memorandum Mo. 18(13)-i^43, dated the 17th May 1943, to tne ministerial staff ( both gazattea , nd non* f azettea) and Asst. Surgeons of His Majesty^ Consulate General 9 r Khorasan. for a period of three months in the first instance with effect from 1st July 1943. The question of further conti nuance of the allowance will be taken up after receipt of sanction of the Secretary of State which is still av/aited* Mean while you may kindly keep the Government of India posted with the latest figures m regard to cost of living in last Iran* 2* A doubt haying arisen as to admissibilitv of the dearness allowance to a taxi drawing more than &amp;• 500/- p*m.* Government of India have decided that the allowance is ad missible on the first ft, 500/- of tne salaries of all ministerial and non-superior staff (gazetted as well as non-gazetted) referred to in paragraph 1 above, without exception no allowance &lt;being payable on portions of salaries exceeding ft. 500/-. \ —— THal ISStte OF TH&amp; ABOVd iiAS B£MN AUTHDRId^. Sd/* V*B. Arte* Under Secy, to the Govt, of India*4^^ 'y'Mffc ^ ^ JVuV. Proa - Tha Undar Secy, to ttie Govt, of India ^/'W&lt; q in the External Affai ra Dopf.ru.iant». TO - - Hie Ifejeety'e Consul General for Khorasea. 4 Uemorsndum Mo. 8(90)-ii/42. st Jl sj 7 Dated Simla, the Aufgost 1943. I n abject:- Continuance of the posts m of one Upper and one Louer Division clerks for Bis Majesty's Consulate General, Meshed. ^ Reference your Express letter Ho. V48, dated the 13th July 1943. 2. Sanction of the Governor-Generai-in-flounci1 is accorded to the continuance on existing terns of the posts of One Upper Division clerk and One Lo? er Division Clerk for the Cbnaulato-General, Meshed .till the end of February 1944 or for the duration of the ear whichever period is shorter. Sd/- V.B. Arte, Older Secy, to the Goveraunt of Indie. —— (p-T-.c./-.. - Ehf« FOREiG No. Of \ ^ rpjf/ v. »4' ' ■r- 'r+Fi _ , Copy oi‘ an Kzpross Lottor No, 748. da tod i^th July 1943 from the British Consulate** Genoral, Moshod to theForoign, Now Delhi. Creation of post a of One Upper and one Lower Division Clerk in Khorasan Consulate General for the duration of the war. •w* mk I * M * r '‘’• 8&lt; ® ) 2. The volume of office work which necessi tated an increase in the clerical staff of the Khorasan Consulate General has not abated since the framing of the recomnarelations made in m telegram Mo. 426 and 94b dated 26th March and 6th July 1942 respectively. In fact office work has since increased, taanKa m^arto the inception of Legation's ,^ e; - Supervision Scheme and great increase in the flow of supplies to Russia by this route. Both the Upper and Lower Division clerks remain fully occupied in dealing with the telegrams and typing work connected with these matters and other new responsi bilities placed on this Consulate-General sines Allied ^roops entered Iran. The existence of the posts after 31st August 1943 is therefore justified *uvJ it is earnestly Hoped that the Government of India will be pleased to sanction their continuance for at least another year.and address— 1 g; r» /t 7 i O' v# i Foreign O v ♦ t Foreign Office. ! S.¥.l. IM wJvdvCj .1.5^°H aethijQf'tober, 194S X-^ ¥ith reference to India Office ir^ter Ext 2970/43 of the 5th August,to Government of India tel egr am No* 6743, a copy of which wasforwarcLect xo this department under India Office reference Ext 4589/43 of the 16th August, and to India Office letter Ext 4589/43 of the 7th September, I am directed by Mr. Winston Churchill to inform you that sanction has been obtained for the charge to Imperial revenues of a moiety of the expenditure involved in the grant of a dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of his Majesty’s Consulate-General for Khorasan, in its continuance with an increase of 50?o for the period of three months from the 1st July, 1943 and in its further continuance at the existing rate after the 30th September, 1943 subject to there being no material in the cost of living. ■% - w — —rr ~ ■—^ ~ i - — i ( The Under-Secretary of I am, Sir, Your —- 1 - ^-“vant nder-becreta India OfficeimVAR D THLEGRAM 39979 Al lotted to E;:uem al I)ej)t-« ; ^ NFID 2 !BTIAIi CODE TSLIilGrRAM From Govt* of Xudtay External Affairs Dept. s To Socy. of state for India. Dated New Delhi* 21.15 hours* 22nd October, 1943. Reed. 01.00 hours* 25rd Oct.*1943. 9026. Foreign telegram No.6745 August 12th% ' ' ~~- Pending the; receipt of your sanction dearness allowance to Khorasan Staff being continued at the rate sanctioned already for further period (? up to) end of February 1944.mm wan c^) ( - o.a EXT.S832A3 DRAFT TKILGRAJ.’ Frans Secretary of State. To: Government of India, External Affairs Department 3/ (/. Mr .Harris on. v’ 4 '* I have spoken to Mr. Dalton, of the Consular Department, who agrees that as the G. of I. have been waiting so long, we may telegraph on the basis of the Treasury letters without waiting for the F*0. letter of agreement, which is now on its way. C7.0. % A ! JUS - hi‘ Your -air 1 -marl letter No. 18(13 )^e/43 of y l?th Maj/ an^ telegrams^ 6743^ ^ 12th August and^O^^of 22nd October. Dearness allowance^ to subordinate ^staff of Consul / / General, Khorasan. H.M.G. approve your qotien-and sanction/aontinuanoo of increased rates / ^ f 3** W '^ S “ ^ rates ^ . UHt A Ms- ^ ^ , ?{ji C^JL * 3 * ' ^ V ’ *3 ^/io o^- V 5'/to 4 7 ISOluioi 64/10163/ . , 234-. 6373/10. Sir, In reply to Mr. Hatcheon’s letter of the 22nd ultimo I em directed hy the Lorda Coni dasioners of His Majesty** Treasury to request you to inforra the Secretary of State for Foreign MTairs tlmt They sanction the charge to Imperial revenues of a moiety of the expenditure iirvolv^u. in the rant of a dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of H.M. Consulate General for at the existing rate - after the 30 th Septei^er m3* subject to there being no material decrease in the cost of living* : *. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, ?he Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. &lt;Sfd.) C. W. WI. WILCOX. \41)72 3000 7 .:-:o EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT. Eeoaomic^ajiKi Overseas. Notes. r\ Register No. K,., &amp;-Q-; Dated Ext, 4589/43. Received Formally acknowledged Under Secretary. ( vtr fiyC cc. C~u. ’ Committee Under Secretary.. Secretary of State. Council J&amp;rr Table’ Date. Initials. SUBJECT. kb Grant of dearness allowance zC to the subordinate staff of H.M. Consulate-General for ! 3 ( ArA Khorasan.* FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY Draft letter to the Foreign Office, proposing that the allowances at the increased rate sanctioned by the Government of India should be approved. V i r CfitC THE advisers concur 7- iEPi343 F7 SEP io-iMINUTE Please see the submission at Ext,2970/43. The Government of India have found it necessary, not only to prolong the dearness allowances which they had previously sanctioned up to the end of June (paragraph 3 of our letter to the Foreign Office of August 5th was intended to provide for this contingency); hut also to increase the amount of these allowances by 50%, We must therefore again go through the motions of consulting the Foreign Office, who in turn will presumably seek the approval of the Treasury. The Government of India ! s action in cutting down ohe scales of dearness allowance proposed by H.H. Consul-General (see paragraph 3 of their letter of May 17th), seems to have been most ill-advised. A draft letter to the Foreign Office is submitted. r Secretary, Financial Department. Do you concur**? 11033 J C/VvC44^|EkT- DRAFT LETTER To - The Under Secretary of St^te, Foreign Office. Sir, *Tj&gt;. ^ 2 SEP 1943 Copy to \ v-ir T, /-hv fat 1 - 1 THE ADVISERS CONCUR 7 - _i£P . 343 With reference to this Office letter No. Ext.2970/43 of August 5th last, regarding the grant of dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of H.M. Consulate-General for Khorasan, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward herewith a copy of a telegram from the Government of India stating that, owing to a further rise in the cost of living in Khorasan, they have sanctioned, in anticipation of the approval of H.M.G., the continued grant of dearness, allowayace with an increase '•'^f 50% in the rates sanctioned in their letter of May 17th last (copy enclosed with this Office letter under reference) * • / for a perioG|gf 3 months from July 1st, 1943. 2. Subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign /Affairs/o Affairs, and^the acceptance of a moiety of the expenditure involved as a charge upon Imperial Revenues, the Secretary of State for India proposes to approve the Government of India’s action and to authorise them to continue the allowances in question at the enhanced rate after the end of Of CfaJUL IWowhvJ* the period^for which they have i sanctioned^ ) ounleu i*\ tKL rr^o^Jj^. (bfiuf rtvfluGXiaJ cLlcajiaA*. ^ hok. CoVf* - . 3 . A copy of this letter 1 is being sent to H.M. Treasury. R. PEEU 3-&lt;? 0 IM. /'pj^■ . » jJl d i GOPV indexed ^ INWARD T^L33HA?^ . : 31251. Allotted to Kxterna! Department . CUNPI DBHTXAL CQDK Tii;L&gt;0IV Ai&gt;a. . j 45c:&lt;9 fo i fa From Government of India, External Affairs Gept. To Secretary of State for India. ^7* Dated New Delhi, 16.25 hours, 12th August, 1943. Read. 06.30 hours, 13th August, 1943. 6743. Government of India, External Affairs Deot. Letter No. 18(13)3/43 of May 17th. 2. Due to further rise in cost of’living in Khorasan Government of India have sanctioned in anticipation of your sanction, continued grant of dearness allowance with an increase of'50 per cent in the rates sanctioned in letter- referred to for period of three months from July 1st 1943. 3. Please telegraph your approval. Ttefci. f SL BEPr. 1 6? AUG *943 INDIA OFFICEH.M. Consul General for Khorasan, with the support of H.M. Minister at Tehran, recommended to the Government of India that the subordinate staff at the Consular posts in his charge should, in view of the very great increase in the cost of living owing to the war, he granted dearness allowance as from April 1st, 1942, on the scales shown in paragraph 2 of the Government of India*s letter below. 2. The expenditure in question is divisible equally between Imperial and Indian Revenues. As, however, H.M. Consul General had represented the matter to be very urgent, and as H.M.G. have sanctioned liberal rates of dearness allowance for their staff in Persia, the Government of India sanctioned, provisionally and pending approval by H.M.G., the grant of dearness allowance on the lower scales shown in paragraph 2 of their letter to H.M. Consul General of May 17th, for the period August 1st 1942 to June 30th 1943. They ask that the approval of H.M.G. to this action may be conveyed to them by telegram. They estimate the annual cost involved at about Rs.28,900 (about £2,170). 3. In a note, a copy of which will be found below the draft, the Financial Secretary advises to the effect that the Government of India’s proposals cannot properly be regarded as covered by the rule under which they may sanction, without reference to H.M.G., diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia and the Persian Gulf up to a limit of £1,000 at each post. Before the Secretary of State approves the Government of India’s action, therefore, it will be necessary to obtain the concurrence of the Foreign Office. A draft letter for this purpose is submitted, which makes it clear that we propose to authorise the Government of India to continue these allowances after the end of the period for which they have been sanctioned by the Government of India, and which has already expired. 4. Please see also the similar case of dearness allowances for the clerical establishment in the Persian Gulf, which is being submitted concurrently at Ext. 2969/43.To travel with 5xt. 2969/43 3xt. 2310/13 Financial Secretary, Please see the Government of India’s letter below and its enclosure, about the grant of dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of H. 1.1.0 onsul ate -General for Khorasan. 2, The Government of India have sanctioned, provisionally and pending approval by the grant of dearness allowance on the scales (lower than those recommended by the Consul-Genera] shown in paragraph 2 of their letter to him of May 17th, for the period August 1st 1942 to June 30th 1943* Tney ask tnat H.M.G-’s approval of their action may be conveyed to them by telegram* They estimate the additional cost involved at Rs. 28,900 (about £2,170) a year. 3. This expenditure is divisible between Imperial and Indian revenues. Since February 1942, however, the Government of India have had the power to sanction, without reference to H.M.G'^ diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia up to a limit of £1,000 (F. 1022*8/42). I believe that this limit refers to the amount which may be sanctioned at each individual post. The action they have taken in this case applies to four posts (Meshed, Zahidanj. Zabu! and Birjand) and it therefore appears that thq^would nave been justified in themselves according final sanction to the expenditure. If you agree that this interpretation of the £ule is correct, we might inform the Government of India accordingly, without referring the matter to the Foreign Office (though a copy of the correspondence would be sent to them). The Government of I n dia will then be able to arrange for the continuance of these allowances after the end of the sanctioned period, which has already expired. 2^. Please see also the similar case at Ext. 2969/43* which is travelling with these papers. i ^£ 5 /j (Copy overleaf)On the whole I think this should be regarded as one measure - the grant of dearness allowance - and that the cost cannot very well be treated as allocable to separate posts and sanctioned by the Government of India under their increased powers. I agree, of course, that there is no alternative to the grant and I assume the concurrence of the Foreign Office will be readily granted, especially as they appear to have sanctioned similar allowances for their ovm staff in Persia. (Sd.) F.E.GRIST 20/7.DRAFT LETTER To - The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. ExT- Ac|yo I+-1 / Copy to V -i. Treasury, «/ ^ Ic. tjj- J tfrn/j^. i^cy&lt;. £—|r[^-Ct46 ^ M' M sir, P 5 AUG 194$ I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward herewith ol copy of a letter from the Government of India regarding the grant of dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of H.M. Consulate General for Khorasan. 2. It will be seen that, in view of the urgency of the matter and of the fact that H.M.G. have sanctioned liberal rates of dearness allowance |cn- their staff in'Persia, the Government of India have sanctioned, provisionally and pending approval by H.M.G., the grant of dearness allowance on the scales shown in paragraph 2 of their letter to H.M. Consul General of May 17th last, for the period August 1st 1942' to June 30th 1943. They estimate that the additional cost involved will amount to some Rs.28,900 (£2,170V. -&gt;&gt; *3. Subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and to the acceptance of a moiety of the expenditure involved as a charge upon Imperial Revenues, the Secretary of State for India proposes to approve the Government of India's action and to authorise them to continue the allowances in question after the end of the period for which they have been sanctioned and which has already expired. 4. A copy of this letter is being sent to H.M. Treasury. R. PEEL TUK ADVI8ERS CONCUR 3 - AUGi943\ (ff) By Fast Air The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Bepirtment, %t\y&gt;c\. -7 The Under secretary of State for India, India Office, London&lt;. } Dated Simla, the / ^Zfy. Jiay J Subject:- Grant of dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of His Majesty r s Consulate General for Khorasan* Six, I am directed to address you on the subject of grant of dearnes^allowance to the subordinate staff of His Majesty 1 s ConsulaterSiQneral for Khorasan. 2. t Hia Ijlaje^w^g Consul General for Khorasan represented that the cost of li&gt;i^r in East Iran had increased enormously on account of the conartHmis created by the war h£ a daaxxxxxand the grant of relief, by w £yy&lt;if a dearness allowance, to the subordinate^staff was a matter^p urgent necessity as the pi of the staff was serious and all tT^-thera were living on savi and some were even selling personal Cost of living • ‘ ‘ ‘ raTr Consul index figure reported for April 1943 was _ recommended the grant of dearness allowance to tl question at the following scales with effect from 1st Apri; ,942- Emoluments. I (i) On the first 100 Tomans of a Govt, servants f s emoluments p.m. m (dd) On portion of emoluments over 100 tomans but not { exceeding 200 tomans p.m, B Ijldi) On rest of emoluments Station. Percentage of dearness allov:ance on total emoluments. iiahidan, Zabul and Birjand o © • • o o O C O L C O o 9 9 9 0 0 9 9 9 9 exceeding 200 tomans p.m. Meshed Zahidan, Zabul and Birjand. Meshed.. ..... Zahidan, Zabul and Birjand. 0 0 9 9 9 9 150 % (100 Tomans are roughly equal tO fee 100.) 75 % 56-t,a rilco co c \2 This proposal was strongly supported by His Majesty 1 s Minister, Tehran. 3. The Government of India* in view of the circumstances given above, and the fact that His Majesty's Government have sanctioned liberal rates of dearness allowances to their staff isary out they _ _ n as proposed by him have not been fully substantiated. Tney have, therefore, considering the urgency of*the matter, sanctioned provisionally the grant/of dearness allowance as detailed in taeir memorandum to the Consul General, Meshed, No. 18(13)-H/43, dated the nin rky 1943 (copy enclosod) with effect from 1st August 1942 (the date from which dearness allowance at revised rates has been sanctioned for low paid staff in India) till the end of June 1943, pending approval of His Majesty'.s Government, The annual cost involved in the above proposals will amount to about Ks. 28,900/-. Uf/ , z-7 —rYY'' * to '■ t/d s — SST 4 0 I am to request that approval of His Maiesty* s Government to tho dearness allowance sanctioned may be obtained and conveyed to the Government of* India by telefTrarru I have the honour to be, Sir ? Your most obedient servant, — ^ for Secretary to the Government of India*i 9 ^ i m From - The tinder Secretary to the Govt, ©f India in the External Affairs Department, To - - His Majesty*s Consul General for Khorasan, Meshed, Memorandum No, 18(13)-G/43, Dated Simla, the j^lh May 1943. Subject:- Grant of dearness allowance to the subordinate staff of the Consulate General for Khoraaan. Correspondence ending with the telegram from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department No.499-0* dated the 30th April 1943, 2. Sanction is accorded to the grent of dearness allowance with retrospective effect from the 1st August 1942 until the end of June 1943 to the clerical staff (both gazetted and non- gazetted) and the Assistant Surgeons 3 of His Majesty*s Consulate-General for Khorasan on the following scales:- Emoluments Station, Percentage of dearness allowance on total emolu ments with the exception of kmdqx customs compen satory allowance. CD (ii) (iii) On the first 100 Rupees of a Govt, servant's emoluments per mensem. On portion of emoluments ever Es. 100 /- but not exceeding Rs, 200 /- p,m. On rest of emoluments exceeding Rs, 200 /- up to t maximum of Rs, 500/- p„m. o«o oooo •ooo*« Meshed, Zahidan, Zabul and Birjand. Meshed, Zahidan, Zabul and Birjand, 0 0 0 # « c oooo* c o o e 000 oooo oooooo oooo Meshed. Zahidan, Zabul and Birjand 100 % 75 % 50 % 37 i% 25 % iQil 3. The above sanction is provisional and subject to confirmation by His Majesty's Government, 4. The Government of India will be glad if a statement of current prices of essential articles of consumption is prepared ana maintained up-to-date, A copy of it may be forwarded to them and appreciable variations in prices should also be intimated to them from time to time. This is proposed with a view to avoid delay in considering any revised proposals relating to dearness allowance and to avoid loss to the staff concerned, as the Government of India are opposed on principle to the grant of retrospective sanction, 3d/- V.B. Arte, J Under Secretary to the Government of India,•1 From Britoonsul, Meshed, 3 r * o. “^ N To Foreign, Mew Delhi, ^ Repeated Bush ire. . -Your telegram No.4^65 Japp tAth, J a gyee n . ^ *iia:o post of Consular Clerk at Blrmnd 00 frBa&amp;lxdf; abolished but reouest new post of Loy^eir Division Qlerk at Keshed be created instead* ^his oil ice is top heavy heving 4 gazetted officers, one . selection grade and 3 upper Djvjsion one of H)L. abolish^ boypott. Conditions^very di revival urgently necessary. Telegram No.584-E t dated the 2lat July 1C42* Troni Foreign, Mew Delhi. To .Britoonsul, .1 eshed, T L . v (Repeated Lntoonsui, Busture). # Your tel e gram Mfi .94o July_ 6 tn. One lower division clerK: at Eeshed sanctiohea to end of . February 1943 or end of war whichever is easier on terms admissible to Ipwer division izcmxx&amp;i clerks at Zabul aM Xahidan. ^xtra expenditure involved should be met if possible from sanctioned budget*. I &gt;-V\^ zx 'S) ^^‘siagram No. l-VCarap^datad Sirala^ tha 16th April From: Foreign, Simla, ^ ^ J[)i To: Britconsul, Mashed. (Repeated Britconsul, Bushire.) Your telegram No. 426 f«Iarch 25th. One upper division clerk sanctioned up to end of February 1943 or end of war which ever is earlier on emoluments as admissible to existing upper division clerks. Extra expenditure involved should be met if possible from sanctioned btiSget. From: Britconsul, Meshed, To: Foreign, New Delhi. No. 426. Dated 25th (received 26th.) March 1942. * * * By ch. of One upper division clerk extra war establish- one letter ment urgently required at Meshed. During the last few months work has considerably ^increased and present staff inadequate. %zrade and *allowance be same as for the *up i er division z clerks of permanent establisliment here. Understand %By ch. of that *such *e 3 tablishment*already sanctioned *for two lettemPorsian Gulf. *Post *will be filled in consult ation with Resident Bushire. Requesting early sanction. Addressed Foreign N ;w Delhi ^Repeated Resident Bushire. ENGLOSU .ci; I,:. ' ' DATE receive: 1 4r 7ON HIS MAJESTY’S SERVICE.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3680</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3680</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/103 'Khorasan: Meshed; clerical staff'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-28T14:45:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (40 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 42; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the HM Consulate at Khorasan, Meshed.The file covers:grant of dearness allowance to Consulate subordinate stafftemporary War Establishment at Meshedbudget estimates of the Consulate for the year 1944-45.The file is composed solely of internal correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the HM Legation at Tehran, the HM Consulate at Khorasan, the Foreign Office, the India Office, and the Government of India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consulate General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>