<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000116_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:34:03.713Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">i - PERSI G OFFIDEETIAL . (95/15/49) 5th Dear Furlonge, The following is a summary of Gulf during the month of December. GENERAL . The Residency . The drainage scheme proposed f been found to be inadequate and it devise a new one. As a result none likely to * E. tl/ss £.J. 1 liest. V: S: stayed and pa: Locust and fr&lt; days ij him up, ways C( at the' the on! Petrol* Grant ( to Boml came t( T( the fi] except and pai we met all the most oj Petrole and Ras' S R- With the compliments of the Under-Secretary of State 1 . ; for Foreign Affairs &amp; !^pies also sent to :— C Foreign Office, 7‘ ^ l9 ^o SB lb l On the 14th January I am expec official visit to Muscat. Relations with the LLSoA . During November and December, 1 States Commander Middle East Force ' Coast and Muscat in U.S.S. 'Valcour 1 ro4 to have passed off without any &lt; Hensel did complain mildly to the P&lt; Coast that he was surprised at beinj on the local Shaikhs whereas they c; Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, whose ; his own. He has not, however, take, the Senior Naval Officer or myself, he went on to Bombay in the 'Valcou: back for a few weeks. /Re. Furlonge, Esq., O.B.E., Foreign Office, London. G.W.igi • li 2T-. U) /^N \ CONFIDENTIAL . (95/15/49) Dear Furlonge, PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 5th January, 1950. ^ O H , ' '■ 'K# The^following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf during the month of December. GENERAL . The R e sidency . The drainage scheme proposed for the new bungalows has been found to be inadequate and it has been necessary to devise a new one 0 As a result none of the bungalows are likely to be ready for occupa-tion until February at the ear liest . Visitors . Sir Evan Jenkins, Deputy Chairman of the Eastern Bank, stayed with us^for a few days at the beginning of the month and paid a visit to Qatar. Stephenson, Head of the Desert Locust Survey, spent a few days in Bahrain on his way to and from the Trucial Coast. M. Georges Balay/spent three days in Bahrain during Christmas week. We offered to put him up, but he preferred to stay in the British Overseas Air ways Corporation Rest House as he was on holiday. He dined at the Residency and called on the Shaikh. He admitted that the only interest the French had here was their share in Petroleum Concessions Limited and its subsidiary companies. Grant of fylackinnon Mackenzie’s called at Bahrain on his way to Bombay to take charge of the company’s office there. He came to see me and discussed shipping matters. Tours. I toured the Trucial Coast with my wife and daughter in the first half of the month and visited all the Shaikhdoms except Kalba. We spent three nights in the Agency at Sharjah and parties were given there and in the R.A.F. Mess at which we met all the Dubai and Sharjah British community. I saw all the Trucial Coast Rulers and exchanged formal calls with most of them. On the 8th December we visited the camps of Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited at Khor Ghanadhah and Ras Sadr. On the 14th January I am expecting to leave on my annual official visit to Muscat. Relations with the U.S.A . During November and December, Captain Hensel, the United States Commander Middle East Force visited Qatar, the Trucial Coast and Muscat in U.S.S. 'Valcour”. All these visits appea rs to have passed off without any contretemps, but Captain Hensel did complain mildly to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast that he was surprised at being expected to call first on the local Shaikhs whereas they called first on the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, whose position was similar to his own. He has not, however, taken the matter up with either the Senior Naval Officer or myself. After visiting Muscat he went on to Bombay in the ’’Valcour” and is not expected back for a few weeks. / Relations with Saudi Arabi a. G.W. Furlonge, Esq., O.B.E., Foreign Office, London. 12 Relations wit h Saudi Ar abia„ The Saudi Arabian Government have erected a concrete plinth on Farsi Island with inlaid brass plates announcing 'that the island belongs to His Majesty King Ibn Saud. It will be remembered that at the end of 1948 the Persians erec ted a notice on the island to the effect that it belonged to them and that this notice was removed by one of H.M's ships t Subsequently the Shaikh of Kuwait put up a notice that the island belonged to him. Ibn Saud has written to the Shaikh of Kuwait making sugges tions for the future administration of the Neutral Zone. The Shaikh has replied that he considers the time has not yet come to take up the matter. The Political Agent has been asked to hold up this reply and it is not yet known whether it has actually been sent or not. Oil . I The position in the Bu Sa’afah area remains much as it was. The Shaikh of Bahrain has replied to the request that ! he should ask the Bahrain Petroleum Company to refrain from \ further operations in the area for the time being by saying ^ i that he will do this if the Arabian American Oil Company are I also restrained. The latter company have erected a survey tower on Bu Athama and so far as is known the Bahrain Petroleum Company are also still operating in the area. The question of starting negotiations with the Saudi Arabian Government for the delimitation of the sea-bed boundary between Bahrain and the mainland is under consideration. Under the Bahrain Petroleum Company’s concession the royalty payable by them to the Shaikh is due for revision in January 1950. The Bahrain Government have written to the company demanding an increase in the royalty from Rs.3/8 to Rs.10 per ton. The Shaikh of Bahrain has given notice to Petroleum Concessions Limited that they must cease to use their jetty at Sitrah^for shipping to and from Qatar unless they assist him in obtaining his so-called rights in Zubarah. He has given some speciousness to this preposterous demand by complaining that the use of the jetty by the company’s launches has led to many evasions of the customs and passport regulations. The Political Agent has taken up the matter with the Shaikh and asked for suspension of his demand pending further considera tion of the case. The first tanker called at the new terminal of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited at Umm Sa'id on the 29th December. Eight tankers are expected to call in January and the termi nal is to be formally opened on the 2nd February. Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited are pre paring to drill near Has Sadr which is in Abu Dhabi territory about halfway between Dubai and Abu Dhabi and are landing equipment at^Khor Ghanadhah. It is hoped that the erection of the rig will be completed by the middle of February. When I visited Abu Dhabi I spoke to the Ruler about his unreaso nable attitude towards Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. He replied that as they were claiming the sea-bed over^which they had no right and forcing him to go to arbi tration, he was also making claims from them which did not appear to be covered by the concession. He is actually hoping to obtain a loan from the company to cover the expenses of his dispute with them. Awhilei 3 Vvhile I was at Abu Dhabi a plane came roaring over the Shaikh's fort and dropped a letter announcing that a represen tative of the Superior Oil Company was coming to see him. The representative followed in due course, but Shaikh Shakh- but's demands are still so exhorbitant that the company can make no headway with him. Galloway himself visited the Shaikh of Dubai and obtained a favourable reply from him. Galloway stated that he was acting as an interpreter for the Superior Oil Company on the Trucial Coast and that the Central Mining Investment Corporation have no interest in any concession there. The first tanker berthed at the Kuwait Oil Company's wharf at Mina A1 Ahmadi on the 2 r} vd November and the wharf is now in regular use. It is to be formally opened on the 17th January and Southwell, the Managing Director, is pressing me to be present on the occasion. It is doubtful, however, whether I shall be able to attend because of the arrangements already made for my visit to Muscat. The American Independent Oil Company are drilling four wells in the Neutral Zone. By an arrangement arrived at with Western Pacific, who obtained the concession for Ibn Saud’s share in the Zone, they are solely responsible for the pre liminary operations. Civ il A viation . Negotiations for a new Civil Air Agreement with Sharjah are still pending as Shaikh Sultan, who is ill in Bombay, has not yet authorised his brother to negotiate on his behalf. When asked to furnish such authority all he did was to say that his brother might draw the increased pay which it is proposed to give the guards under the new agreement. Bahrai n. $ \J The^only meeting I have had with the Shaikh was at the races which took place on the 23rd December. He has continued to pester the Political Agent and others over his alleged rights in Zubarah. His latest proposal, which is not at first sight unreasonable is that the interpretation of the 1944 Agreement with the Ruler of Qatar should be referred to Judge ^Haines and that his decision should be final. He has also in the^course of correspondence about Bu Sa'afah re-asser ted his claim to the whole of the sea-bed between Bahrain and Qatar including even that underlying the Qatar territorial waters. H.M.G's decision about the sea-bed between Bahrain and Qatar was announced some two years ago, but the parties concerned were given an opportunity of raising objections and the decision has not yet been made final. We have now learnt that it is likely to be revised on the basis of certain ^ principles which have been recently enunciated. A Shaikh Muhammad bin Isa, the Ruler's uncle, who recently returned from Bombay where he had gone to have his eyes treated, has now left for Egypt for further treatment which it is feared is unlikely to be successful In my last summary I mentioned that a Pole, who is Chairman of a Palestinian committee in Bombay, had asked for a visa to enable him to visit Bahrain in order to get into touch with the local Jewish community. The Shaikh has asked that a visa should be refused as he fears that the Pole's visit may serve to stir up anti-Jewish feeling which is at present more or less dormant. Q ata r. The situation in Qatar remains much the same and the- 4 - Darwish family are still all-powerful. Saleh al Mana’s stock is low and he has been on a visit to the dentist at Bahrain. It is now appears unlikely that Deardon, who has been told horrible tales of the conditions prevailing at Doha, will accept the appointment of Adviser and we are looking for somebody else. Trucial Coast . I found all quiet on the Trucial Coast except for some minor squabbles at Has al Khaimah and no case of abduction into slavery has been reported for some months. There has been plenty of rain and supplies are adequate. The oil com pany's operations at Has Sadr and Khor Ghanadhah are provi ding a certain amount of employment for the local tribesmen. I took the Shaikh of Dubai severely to task for his refusal to provide a site for the construction of a new Agency in his territory and he eventually agreed to do this, but asked that a British Political Officer should always be in charge of it and that he should not be left to the mercies of an Arab agent. I also spoke to him about the 'Joker' case add although he claimed to be completely innocent he said he would pay a fine if ordered to do so. It will be remembered that some months ago reports were received that the 'Joker', which is a^motorised dhow, had taken a cargo of slave girls to Saudi Arabia, and that the vessel was seized at Bahrain on her return journey. Shaikh Sultan, the Ruler of Sharjah is still in hospital at Bombay and although his health is repor ted to have improved and I was shown photos of him in a standing position, his final recovery is very doubtful. Meanwhile, his brother Muhammad is carrying on in his place and the Political Officer is finding him more satisfactory to deal with than the pompous and excitable Sultan. Though Shaikh Saqr of Has al Khaimah is continually having trouble with his neighbours, who demand their shares of the comparatively small payments he receives from the oil company, he appears to be firmly^ seated in the saddle. The ex-Shaikh, Sultan bin Salim, is still in exile in Muscat territory but is due to return in April. The latest trouble has been the abduction of three women from Has al Khaimah by the Khawatir tribe. They have not been abducted into slavery but as hostages to extract_a contribution from Shaikh Saqr. The Shaikh ^f Umm al Qawain, who is a professional mediator on the Trucial Coast has been asked to endeavour to bring the parties into a settlement. The Regent of Kalba, Shaikh Khalid, called on me at Sharjah bringing with him his nephew Humaid. Khalid is now very old and doddery and Humaid manages affairs on his behalf. The latter is an opium addict and has asked Dr. McCaully, our Medical Officer on the Trucial Coast, to cure him of the habit. Though he looked to me rather a brigand, he appeared to have some commonsense and force of character. I asked the Regent whether it was not time that the real Shaikh, Hamad, who is now 19, was put in charge of affairs and he replied that it was the will of Government. The case will require careful consideration before any decision is reached as Hamad is reported to be a weak character and al ready debauched. The Residency Agent, Jasim bin Muhammad, has resigned on grounds of ill^health. It is proposed not to continue the appointment which is really an anachronism dating from the time when the Residency held direct charge of the Trucial Coast and there was no British Political Officer there and it is probable that instead an Arab officer of a lower grade will be appointed to assist the Political Officer. ^The Locust Party, which now includes four British officers are installed at Sharjah and are about to start exploration. Stephenson agreed that they should not attempt to go beyond /Buraimi5 Buraimi until told that it was safe for them to do so, and their objective during the present season will be to cover the triangle Abu Dhabi - Buraimi - Ras al Khaimah and they may proceed as far south as Liwa. They are to be joined in due course by a Pakistani contingent and the Government of India have asked us to purchase some trucks for them as their contribution to the operations. One member of the party, Dr. Lee Oldfield, has taken his wife to Sharjah. So far as is known she will be. the first European woman to reside on the Trucial Coast. She .s a trained nurse and is looking forward to assisting Dr. McCaully. Muscat. The Sultan returned to Muscat from his visits to India and Pakistan on the 16th December. He expressed himself very appreciative of all the arrangements made for him. I do not yet know if he discussed any political matters with the Govern ments of India and Pakistan. He has told the Political Agent that he does not intend to visit the United Kingdom during 1950 and it is believed that he intends to leave for Dhofar in the early spring. In my last summary I reported that the Imam was said to be on his periodical deathbed. It is now understood that he was suffering from jaundice and is well on the way to recovery. E CONOMIC SUPPLEMENT . All the banks are now refusing to accept the Pakistani rupee and its rate in the Bahrain bazaar has failed to rupees Pakistani 100 to rupees Indian 125. It is being purchased at this rate for export to Saudi Arabia. I was informed during my Trucial Coast tour that there is a big drainage of Indian rupees from the Trucial Coast to Saudi Arabia, parti cularly of Indian rupee coins which are almost unobtainable in the Dubai bazaar. The manager of the branch of the British Bank of Iran and the Middle East a'; Dubai told me that he was well satis fied with the business that is being done there. Owing to restrictions imposed in India and elsewhere nearly all the local merchants are now conducting their operations through the bank. The Eastern Bank have reached a satisfactory agreement with the Ruler of Qatar and expect to open a branch at Doha under a European manager on the 15th January. They have not asked for, nor been given any kind of monopoly. Two Americans, Rowe and Williamson, who were formerly employees of the Arabian American Oil Company are now in America purchasing equipment for a company to exploit the Gulf fisheries. It is to have its headquarters in Bahrain and is to be known as the 'Persian Gu.l ^ Aosociates' . Mr. Kendall of Messrs. Charles Kendall &amp; Partners expects to visit Muse t in February in order to negCoiate with the Sultan for the establishment of a company to exploit the Muscat fisheries. Grant of Mackinnon &amp; Mackenzies, whose visit to Bahrain I have already mentioned, told me that it is the intention of the British India Steam Navigation Company to withdraw their 'B M boats services, which are not paying, as soon as their fourth 'D” boat is ready, i.e. about June 1950. It is then proposed that the M D n boats should make two calls a month at Gwadur, three at Muscat and two at Dubai. As a quid pro quo for regular calls of 'D' boats at Muscat the company hope to /obtainf 5 /&gt;,) /v* /?. H 4 y # 6 obtain for Gray Mackenzies the contract for landing arrange ments which is at present held by a local merchant» The com pany propose to cut out altogether the calls at Sharjah as no traffic offers itself and Grant asked me whether there was any political objection to this. The calls at this port were started in the early 30's at the request of this Residency, it is believed as one of the inducements to the Ruler to allow us to establish an airport there, and the extent to which we are under an obligation to continue this is a matter which will have to be examined. Direct calls by cargo boats at Umm Sa'id in Qatar have ceased and Gray Mackenzies have now a monthly tug and barge service between Sitrah and Qatar. Cargo is unloaded direct from the steamer on to the barge. At present only freight for Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited is carried in this manner and we are examining the possibility of the service also being used for ordinary commercial cargo and mails. The Shaikh of Bahrain, owing to his feud with Qatar, charges full customs duties and not the ordinary transit dues for all goods consigned there, and it is very desirable that some means should be found for the shipment of cargo to Qatar without its having to pass through the Bahrain customs. Gray Mackenzies have now a British manager at Muscat and hope shortly to instal one at Dubai. Holloway Brothers have fenced off the site they have ob tained from the Ruler of Dubai and will presumably soon start building their premises there. Their representative, Lindsay, is installed at Dubai. He has suggested to the acting Ruler of Sharjah the construction of a jetty there for the protec tion of shipping which is at present very much exposed to the weather as the creek can only be entered at high tide. Sharjah, however, is a much impoverished State and it is doubt ful wheth r funds could be raised for such an expensive project. On my way to the Trucial Coast I visited Sir Bu Na'ir* island and met Pocock, who is working the red oxide deposits there and on Bu Musa on behalf of the Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide Company. He informed me that he hopes to ship 8,000 tons of red oxide during the current season and 5,000 tons a year during the remaining seven years of the company's con cession. He has visited all the islands in the area and reports that there are deposits of red oxide on Arzanah, but on no other except possibly Tanb which he has not yet visited. He has endeavoured to obtain a concession for Arzanah from the Ruler of Abu Dhabi, to whom it belongs, but the Ruler's demdnds are exhorbitant. He told me that two other firms, one a Kuwaiti and one an Indian, are also trying to obtain a red oxide concession from Abu Dhabi. Shaikh Shakhbut actually asked Pocock for 25% of the company's gross takings. When I saw the Shaikh I pointed out to him that this was quite unreasonable, but he seemed to think that if Pocock's company was not willing to agree to this the othors In the field would.2 Vi sitors With the onset of ’’directors r weather” we have had a host of visitors in Bahrain, many of whom stayed at the Residency, and I do not propose to mention them all. A party of officers of the Defence Services from the Canal Zone in Egypt led by Air Vice-Marshal Combe stayed here for one night and discussed a few local problems. Sir Herbert Todd, late of the Inaian Political Service and now concerned with industrial relations in the Iraq Petroleum Company, was here lor a few days and also visited Qatar. Mr. Gibson the Managing Director elect of the Iraq Petroleum Company was brought to call on us by Lermitte. Mr. Peter Holloway, a Director of Holloway Bros., who have expanding interests in the Gulf, was here for several days. We have also seen several members of the locust party who are assembling on the Trucial Coast. Thesiger stayed with us en route to the Trucial Coast whence he proposes to set out for further travels. Colonel Galloway, who served in the Gulf for many years and only left us last April, has returned to his old haunts to act in the late Sir Hugh Weightman’s place on behalf oi the Central Mining Investment Corporation. Mr. Smith, a Vice- President of the Corporation’s partner, the Superior Oil Company of America, joined him here. It is understood he is to be President of the new Company which.is to. be formed to operate the Qatar sea-bed concession. Tours. Early in the month I visited Dhahran with my wife and daughter and we spent three nights there as guests of Mr. Hart, tne United States Consul-General and his wife. We met all the leading lights of the Arabian American Oil Company and dined with the Amir Abdul Muhsin bin Jiluwi at Dammam. We visited the Abqaiq oil field which is said at present to be producing more oil than any other field in the world and were shown round by the manager, Mr. Bevin. We also visited the new causeway at Dammam which is expected to be completed in January. Towards the end of the month we spent two nights at Dukhan in Qatar where we were hospitably entertained by Mr. Langham the local Field Manager of Petroleum Develop ment (Qatar) and his wife. While out fishing we ran into a very heavy rain ana hail storm and at Dukhan camp three quarters of an inch of rain fell in a quarter of an hour, re lations with t h e U. S.A. During the month I exchanged calls with Captain Andersonof the U.S.S. 'Maury' which was on her way to the Kuwait coast to continue her last year’s survey. This year she has brough': with her a helicopter to make beach landings. I have asked the United States Naval authorities to be careful about making landings in remote areas where this strange aircraft may arouse the curiosity or cupidity of the local tribesmen. A bevy of United States Senators, concerned it is believed with United States defence expenditure in these parts, paid a brief visit to Bahrain and called at the residency. They were very affable though their Chairman, Mr. Ellender did not add to the gaeity of the occasion when he remarked to one of my officers that he thought the United Kingdom was finished and that 20 millions ol its innabitants •©■crt to migrate to South Africa, When I repeated this remark to some of the Americans here they replied by making scathing references to their Senators as a whole. /delations with'i' ECOMQldC SUPPLEM^ T. The Gulf States are now able to obtain their requirements of wheat without the assistance of the Ministry of Food and we have recommended that during 1951 only a small reserve should be maintained in Basrah for use in an emergency. The cost of living at Bahrain is still unaffect ed by the revaluation of sterling. Before revaluation the rate for the £ in the free market was x-is.12/8 but it has now hardened to xis. 13/5. The dollar rate is round about r(s.5/2. Some time ago Transcontinental &amp; Western Air Incorporated had a substantial rupee balance with the Eastern Bank which^they were trying to change into dollars at the official rate. They have now exhausted this balance by making payments to Gray Mackenzies on behalf of the Isthmian Line and have applied for an overdraft to meet further payments of this nature. The price of coffee has recently more than doubled in the Bahrain market. There has also been a substantial increase in the prices of pepper and card- omoms. Owing to the poor date crop the Shaikh of Bahrain has temporarily remitted all customs duty on im ported dates. ( trw A*-.*-* 31 ^ - PERSIAN GULF PESIDEN^Y, ' : ' bahraiL bJ94 7th Novemljj^Qg^g^ CONFIDENTIAL (95/13/49) Dear Burrows, r„if ^ he . fol i° win g is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf during the month of October. GENERAL . Staff . ... Stobart arrived in the first half of the month and has thf 30th Octn? S °V h ® T f uc ial Coast. Dredge arrived on Jakins^ wt t d ta - en ° Ver again as Flrst Secretary, akins has left to relieve Jackson at Kuwait and Gethin is temporarily performing the duties of Political Agent, Bahrain It is hoped that Pelly, who has returned to Jeddah after getting married, will be allowed to come back to Bahrain on the understanding that his services will be made availa- Pinhof ^L b ^ ry T n !f° ti S ti ? n ? at Jeddah when squired, nhiy, late of the Indian Political Service, is expected to arrive about the 20th November to take over the duties of Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. in tho PnfiNJ? r P ° rt t ^ at Wali A hm^d, the Head Clerk in the Political Agency, Kuwait, was killed during the month by an accidental fall from a roof. Tours c On the 1st of the month I visited Dukhan in Qatar and went round the oil field. I did not see the Shaikh, bu? me at .P uk £an and I had an opportunity of discus- oing the local situation with him. On the 8th I left to xt t XntJ+ C ° n * eren&lt; :t at h Aden ° 1 spent two days on the way at Kuwait and another two days at Cairo. At Kuwait I exchan- ged cans with tne Shaikh and received calls from a number relations. I discussed a number of cases with the T f al pgent and he very kindly arranged parties at which d ?? d l n ? me ^ ders ol the British and American communi ties. At Cairo I stayed with Troutbeck and had talks with A f n- blS ataff - Between Cairo and Aden I lunched with the Actmg Governor-General at Khartoum and spent a night with Drew, the Governor of Eritrea at Asmara. I spent A n e h aS the guest of the Governor and Lady Cham- plo iV l| he Con^rence was attended by Troutbeck and Trott ?p n ^ h ® t F 2 rei ?fJ 0ff i ce side, by Glendaye, the British Resi- dent at Zanzibar, Reece, the Governor of British Somaliland, br?ef e wp eS f nt u^ 1VeS f 2° m Kenya and Tanganika. Its object in -ho f f? t0 d l s ? uss the common interests of the Arabs of i-he Arabian and African coasts. It was found that these interests were somewhat limited and the discussions only lasted two lays. I could not get away from Aden until five days after the Conference ended and during the intervening things officials and amongst other vi^t to Mn f W n th ^ artley his plans fcr his forthcoming 0n the return journey I spent four days at f ers^and^opT i 1 discu ^ed the boundary question and other mat ers, and called on the King, who was in residence there. B .A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London. /I2 I returned to Bahrain on the 24th. During the journey across Arabia by Saudi Airlines I had to spend several hours at Kharj where American experts are busy with an agricultural development scheme. Relations wit h Persia . During the monti the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf visited the Tanb islands and removed the flagstaff which had been erected by the Persians on Little Tanb. He found that there was no truth in the report that the inhabitants of the main island had heard rumours that the Persians were proposing to establish a customs house there. Re l ations with Saudi Ar abia , Rumours were received during the month of further in cursions by ARAMCO into Abu Dhabi territory, but from aerial reconnaissances it appears they they are without foundation. /\ Oil. The refusal of the Pakistan Government to revalue their rupee has caused some embarrassment to the local oil compan ies. Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited offered to pay their Pakistani employees, who number abort 230, half their salary in Pakistan rupees. This offer was refused and the employees demanded repatriation. About 100 of them are being repatriated and it is believed that the remainder are 'illing to stay on. It is understood that the Kuwait Oil Company, who have about 2,000 Pakistani employees, have made a simi lar offer to their employees but it is not known whether it has been accepted or not. The General Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company has been authorised to make a similar offer to his company's Pakistani employees, who number 167, but only on the understanding that their contracts will be terminated as soon as possible. In these circumstances, he has not made the offc ? and he is of the opinion that most of the employees will prefer to continue to serve on their pre sent terms rather than lose their jobs. On the 19th October a party of Saudi Arabian coastguards visited Arabi island and took down details of the Bahrain Petroleum Company’s personnel and installations there. Acting under instructions fpom his principals the General Manager of the company a few days later withdrew the personnel, but he has left a launch In the vicinity to keep an eye on the installations. The company have drilled a 1000 ft. bore at Bu Saafah to test the geological structure and are proposing to drill another bore about S miles to the east. Information has been received that the Arabian American Oi' 1 Company in tend to erect pile structures with radar beacons on two shoals called Ashirah and Bu Athama, eastwards of Bu Saafah. Both companies apparently hope to establish claims to the sea-bed on behalf of the governments from whom they hold their con cessions and an early delimitation of the sea-bed boundary in this area is clearly called for. Mr. Witherspoon, Vice-President of the Bahrain Petroleum Company is again in Bahrain and expects to stay here for two or three months. Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited are making rapid progress and have now nine wells ready out of the ten contem plated in their initial drilling programme in the Dukhan area. Thef still plan to make their first shipment of oil at the beginning of 1950.We were all deeply grieved to hear of the deaths of Sir Hugh Weightman of the Central Mining Investment Corporation Limited and Mr,. Allen of the Superior Oil Company of America with their companions in an air crash when they were leaving London for the Gulf. It is believed they were coming here to mature plans for operations under the concession obtained for the Qatar sea-bed and to resume negotiations for the Abu Dhabi sea-bed. The tragedy cannot fail to result in a serious delay in the development of the companies f plans. I had a long talk with Mr. Jordan, General Manager of the Kuwait Oil Company, while I was at Kuwait. The company are not going ahead quite as fast as they were and they have some fears regarding the marketing of their oil which is not of very high quality. The causeway at Mina al Ahmedi will be completed in a month or two's time and arrangements are being made for the repatriation of several hundred Americans who have been employed by the Bechtel Organisation on its construction. Ba hrain . I paid a formal call on the Shaikh in uniform on the occasion of the Id al Dhuha, accompanied by other officers of the Residency and Agency. On the following day I called on the Shaikh's uncle, Shaikh Muhammad and Yusuf Fakhroo, the leading local merchant. The Ruler's other uncle. Shaikh Abdulla went on the pilgrimage to Mecca accompanied by an enormous tetinue and has since returned to Bahrain. Kuwait. While I was at Kuwait the Ruler paid his usual call on me at the Agency, during which nothing of particular interest was said. I immediately returned his call and as soon as we were seated he made what I was able to accept as a reasonable apology for his behaviour to me at Bahrain. I told him that I had been greatly offended by his behaviour, but that I would say nothing more on the subject. I noticed a marked improvement both in the outward appearance of the town and its general atmosphere. The new highway between the customs house and the main square has been completed and numerous traffic police cope fairly adequa tely with the incessant stream of motor vehicles. The British Chief Medical Officer, Dr. Parry, likes his work and is set tling down. The new hospital has been equipped and is now functioning and the Shaikh is obtaining the services of a British matron and two more British doctors. The three Bri tish police officers formerly employed in Palestine are used by the Shaikh purely for dealing with persons subject to the Order in Council, but it is hoped that in due course they may be given some say in the training of the police. The drinking water situation is still not very satisfactory as the two water tankers belonging to the Kuwait Government are mecha nically unsuitable. Nothing more has been heard about the distillation plant which the Shaikh is said to have ordered. The Kuwait Government have engaged the services of 54 male and 27 female teachers from Egypt and are paying them double their basic salary and double dearness allowance. The head of the Education Department informed me that it had been decided to recruit all foreign teachers from Egypt because it was easier for their Egyptian Director of Education and In spectors to cope with them than with Palestinians, Syrians or Lebanese. They have a new Director of Education, the pre vious one having been dismissed because of quarrels with Pales tinian and Syrian teachers previously employed. I was also told that it was not intended to send any more boys of secon dary school age to Cairo, but that younger boys were being / sent- 4 - sent to the Victoria College at Alexandria. A batch of nine such boys accompanied me when I left by flying-boat for Alexan dria on the 10th October. The Kuwait Government have obtained the services of three qadhis from Egypt to assist the local qadhis in the Shara courts. Q atar . The situation in Qatar is by no means satisfactory. The Ruler, Shaikh Ali 9 has fallen too much under the influence of the Darwish family and tries so far as possible to ignore the advice of the Political Officer. The Darwish family are trying to persuade Ali to employ Syrians in the administra- tion. Cochrane, the Police Officer is only allowed to fun ction in a very limited sphere. It is satisfying to learn, however, that he is receiving his pay, and the financial situa tion appears not to be so bad as had originally been feared, we now haye a candidate for the post of Adviser and the Poli tical Officer has been instructed to approach the Shaikh regarding the terms of his employment. Mu scat. The Sultan left for India on the 21st October. He appears to be adopting the attitude that there is no boundary dispute with Saudi Arabia so far as his territory is concerned and that he does not wish to be drawn into any dispute. He may be forced to change this attitude when he learns the Saudi Arabian Government’s latest proposals. ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT . In the early part of the month, the banks in the Gulf States were purchasing Pakistani rupees at the rate of Ps.141 to Is.100 Pakistani rupees. The Bahrain banks are now refu sing to accept any Pakistani rupees as the Pakistan State Bank has refused to give sterling in exchange for them. Reports are current that the value of the Indian rupee is likely to be enhanced against sterling. These may be based to some extent on a recent B.B.C. broadcast. The revaluation of sterling has not caused any rise in the cost of living in Bahrain up to date. Bahrain merchants are complaining that their sales of imported goods are falling off as they can be obtained cheaper at Kuwait. This is rather surprising, but it is possible that the Kuwait merchants may be trying to sell off their large stocks. Messrs, Eastern and African Limited have obtained per mission from the Shaikh to open a branch at Kuwait. Refrigerated vessels are now available for the trans port of ^ foodstuffs from Australia to the Persian Gulf and Gray Mackenzies have informed all the Gulf oil companies accordingly. Messrs. Holloway Bros, propose to keep a representative permanently at Dubai and are negotiating with the Shaikh of Dubai for a site for premises. At present the Shaikh will not grant a lease for more than 10 years. Messrs. Holloway Bros, have submitted to the Muscat Government the plans and estimates for the Sur water scheme. The estimate amounts to about £42,000 which the Muscat Government consider much too high.8B 37430 ( 16 ) of the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs ^ Foreign Office, ID Referei^e:— Copies also sent to :— 863/g 7 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, CONFIDENTIAL . (95/12/49) Dear Burrows, The following is Gulf during the month BAHRAIN. 6th October, 1949. 8633 ri INDEXEi a summary of events in the J^grsKi of September. GENER AL. Staff . Chauncy took over as Political Agent, Muscat on the 28th September. Andrew, whom he replaced, is going on leave. Stobart, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast is expected back from leave on the 9th October. We are still without any news of an Assistant Political Agent for Bahrain. Tours. I visited Doha (Qatar) on the 6th September to exchange calls with the new Shaikh and obtain first-hand knowledge of the local situation. Towards the end of the month I paid a brief visit to Muscat to see the Sultan before he leaves for India. I travelled there in H.M.S. •'Flamingo'* and returned by the fast mail steamer 'Dumra' which was di verted for me. Visitors . General Sir John Crocker, Commander-in-Chief, Middle Fast Land Forces with Lady Crocker and two officers of his staff stayed with us from the 29th September to the 2nd October. During this time General Crocker visited the oil installations in Bahrain and Qatar. He called on the Shaikh on the 30th September and was'received with a guard of honour. The following evening His Highness gave a dinner party in his honour and presented him with a sword. A number of other parties were arranged to enable him to meet the leading British and American residents. Relations with the U.S.A . The American Commander Middle Fast Force, Captain Hensel called on me formally during the month. I returned his call in the U.S t S. 'Greenwich Bay' and lunched with him on board. I was given my salute on leaving the ship. Hensel also brought an American Marine General called Wallace to lunch with us one day. The U.S.S. 'Greenwich Bay' has now been replaced by the U.S.S. 'Valcour', and a cocktail party was given by the officers of the former ship in the Jufair ward-room on the 30th September to enable some of us to meet the 'Valcour' officers. Hart the United States Consul-General at Dhahran and his wife lunched with us during the month. The Sultan has written to him asking him to correspond with him direct about Wendell Phillips' proposed archaeological expedition to Muscat territory. He is apparently somewhat annoyed that approach for permission for Wendell Phillips' visit to Muscat in August was made by us. Hart proposes to visit Muscat in the U.ScS. 'Valcour' in the middle of December but it is not /yet B.A.B. Burrows, Fsq., Foreign Office, London.yet certain that the Sultan will have returned from India then= Relations with P ersia . When the ’’Nearchus' visited Tanb island on the 23rd September the Captain was informed that according to a re port received from the local villagers the Persians had erected a flagstaff on Nabiyu or Little Tanb. Rumours were also current there that the Persians are proposing to es tablish a customs station on the main island. The Persian press have given publicity to the with drawal by the Pakistan Government of its invitation to Bah rain to send representatives to the forthcoming economic conference at Karachi. As reported in my last monthly let- . ter the invitation was not formally withdrawn as it was learnt that the Bahrain Government intended in any case to decline it. Relations with Iraq . In my letter for June I reported that Ahmad Fakhroo, a Bahrain merchant, had received a letter from a friend in Iraq enquiring whether he would be willing to perfoim the^ functions of Iraqi Consul in Bahrain in an honorary capacity. He has replied saying that he cannot give an answer one way or the other unless the matter is taken up officially by the Iraqi Government with H.M’s Embassy, Baghdad. He has informed the Shaikh as well as this Residency of the approach made to him. Rel atio n s with Saudi Ar abia. The Sultan of Muscat and the Shaikhs of Qatar and Abu Dhabi have been asked to send responsible persons to Jeddah for our representatives to consult as occasion arises during the boundary negotiations. The Sultan and the Shaikh of Qatar are unable to find anybody whom they can trust. The Shaikh of Abu Dhabi has sent his brother Shaikh Hazza. Relations with India . Mr. Chaudhri who was on his way to Baghdad to open an Indian Legation there in the capacity of First Secretary and Mr. Kidwai, who is to be the Legation’s Press Attach^ passed through Bahrain during the month and lunched at the Residency. I also received a call from Messrs&lt; Mehta and Abdullah', representatives of the Bombay Navigation and Ship ping Company. ‘ Re latio n s with Pakista n. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf very kindly^ arranged with the Flag Officer Commanding the Royal Pakistan Navy to despatch a consignment of gunpowder by the H.M.P.S. 'Jhelum' to Muscat. This gunpowder which was obtained for the Sultan through the Government of India before partition had been lying at Malir near Karachi for about three years and previous efforts to arrange for its despatch had been unsuccessful as no merchant ship would handle it„^ The ’’Jhelum” took the opportunity to pay a formal visit to Mus cat and the usual courtesies were exchanged. There were also parties and games ashore and the visit is reported to^ have passed off very successfully except that the Pakistanis were somewhat annoyed to find that their currency was not accepted in the shops. This was before sterling had been re-valued. Civil Aviation. The Manager of International Aeradio Limited re P^^| t3 that he had to deal with 548 movements at the Muharraq aero drome during the month and with nearly 700 aircraft over-flying. We are still awaiting instructions regarding the issue of new regulations for the use of this and other airfields in the Persian Gulf States. Slavery. No fresh cases of abduction into slavery have been re ported during the month, but this may be due to the absence of a representative on the Trucial Coast. On the other hand three cases of the restoration of kidnapped persons have been reported. The restoration of a Bahraini boy kidnapped from Dubai a year ago and sold as a slave with the Emir Saud was obtained through a Nedji merchant at Bahrain. The ac ting Ruler of Sharjah has obtained the release of a kidnap ped girl on payment of Ps. 16,000 and the Ruler of Abu Dhabi has succeeded in recovering a girl who had been carried from his territory to Qatar. Oil . The Bahrain Petroleum Company have established an elec tronic survey aid station on Arab! island without obtaining the formal permission of any authority. The Shaikh of Kuwait had however intimated that he had no objection to the estab lishment of the station. The Vice-President of the Arabian American Oil Company has objected strongly and it is probable that a protest will be received from the Saudi Arabian Government in due course. The Bahrain Petroleum Company have also started operations on a shoal called Bu Saafa about 50 miles north of Bahrain. They were given permission to drill there in 1941 on the understanding that they would withdraw if the Saudi Arabian Government objected. Such an objection will almost certainly be received as it is under stood that the Arabian American Oil Company had intended to start operations on this shoal in the near future them selves and it is likely to fall within Saudi Arabian limits when the lateral sea-bed boundary between Bahrain and Saudi Arabia is determined. The Manager of Petroleum Concessions Limited has repor ted that the Bahrain Petroleum Company are again carrying out seismic surveys on the Qatar side of the Bahrain-Qatar sea-bed boundary. No action has been taken on this as the Ruler of Qatar has not protested and no instructions have yet been received on a similar report made by Mr. Lermitte earlier in the year. Mr. Skinner, Vice-President of the Bahrain Petroleum Company has taken up his residence on the island and it is understood that he is to be in charge of the company's public relations and that a house is to be built for him on the site originally reserved for the residence of the com pany’s Chief Local Representative in Manama. I have informed the company’s Manager, Mr. Russell Brown that when he him self ceases to perform the functions of Chief Local Repres entative we shall almost certainly insist on the appoint ment of a British subject to the post as prescribed in the company’s Political Agreement. During the month I inspected the school which the company have started at Zellaq for the teaching of English to some of their local employees. The course is a very short and elementary one but it is something that the company have begun to realise their responsibilities in this direction. Funds have been sanctioned for the building of a large school for local employees either at Awali or in the refinery area at Sitrah and when this has been completed it is to be hoped /thatamrnmm \wxmmtin' Tr jj]—|. 4 . - 4 - that more substantial progress will be made. Sir Hugh Weightman has not appeared in these parts again during the month, but a British subject called Lee belonging to his company visited the coasts of Qatar in a launch. The Shaikh of Kuwait has granted a concession to the American Independent Oil Company for the islands of Kubbar, Qaru and Umm al Maradin. This concession will only be valid if the claim of the Kuwait Oil Company to these islands is not substantiated. The Shaikh of Kuwait has rejected the Kuwait Oil Company’s claims both to these islands and to the sea-bed in spite of the detailed legal arguments which the company have submitted to him, and both claims will presumably be referred in due course to arbitration. Bahrain. During the month I paid a friendly call on the Shaikh, He received me with a very glum look and as I expected as soon as possible launched upon his usual diatribe about Zubarah. His hopes have been raised by the changes in Qatar and when I visited Doha I pressed Shaikh Ali to come to some friendly settlement with Shaikh Salman. Ali, who is still entirely under the influence of his father and frightened to make up his mind about any subject, asked that the mat ter should be postponed for two or three months. I explained the situation to Shaikh Salman, but he would not be pacified. The Bahrain Government have advertised in the British Medical Journal for the services of a Medical Officer of Health. The terms they offer are not very attractive and so far no applications have been received. Qatar . I visited Doha on the 6th September and exchanged formal calls with Shaikh Ali. His father Shaikh Abdullah called on me and 1 was surprised to find him in such good health and spirits. I also took coffee with Shaikh Ali's factotum, Saleh bin Mana, and with Abdullah Darwish, one of the leading merchants. Although everything is peaceful the general^situa tion in Qatar is not in all respects satisfactory. Shaikh Abdullah has retained all the money and property he has accu mulated during his long rule and Ali has exhausted most of the advance he received from Petroleum Development Qatar Limi~ ted in paying off old debts and purchasing necessary equip ment. He has turned down several proposals made to him on the grounds that he has no funds. He sees his old father every day and the only result of the conflicting advice he receives from his father, the Political Officer, Saleh bin Mana and Abdullah Darwish is that he refuses to take posi tive action of any kind. Although his appearance is imposing he has a poor intellect and no mind of his own. Wilson reports that he is already tired of being Ruler and it re mains to be seen whether he will try to shuffle off the res ponsibility on to some other member of the family. At the time of my visit Cochrane, the Inspector of Police whose services have been lent by the Bahrain Government, had not yet been allowed to do anything and Ali wanted to send back 30 rifles lent by the Bahrain Government, which I had brought with me. I persuaded him to keep the rifles and Cochrane has since been allowed to recruit some police, but whether he and they will receive any pay is still a matter of uncer tainty. The oil company are willing to make a further loan to Ali on condition that the funds are administered by the Political Officer, and endeavours are being made to ascer tain exactly what All’s assets and liabilities are before /this5- k t ^this proposal is pursued. He at one time ordered Saleh bin Mana to prepare a budget but very soon countermanded the order after seeing his father. Wilton has an uphill task which could be greatly eased if only Shaikh Abdullah and Abdullah Darwish, who has great influence with the old Shaikh and is intriguing with him in his own interests, could be removed . from the scene. Trncial Coast . Little news is coming through from the Trucial Coast. There has been some trouble in Has al Khaimah between the Ruler, Saqr bin Muhammad and a son of the ex-ruler, Sultan bin Salim, and the minor Shaikh Hamad of Kalba, who is now about^19, has been endeavouring with the aid of the Shaikh of Fujairah to oust Humaid who is running Kalba affairs on behalf of his uncle the Regent Shaikh Khalid. These two petty Sheikhdoms are at present remote from the seer'', of any oil operations and it is not necessary to take their inter nal squabbles too seriously. Muscat. I had two long talks with the Sultan during my visit to Muscat, the principal matter discussed being oil explo ration in the Huqf area about which the Sultan showed a more forthcoming attitude than I had expected. He claims that the Imam has no influence in this area and in the course of the conversation remarked that he was on very cordial terms with the Imam and that he had recently sent one of hi* gover nors to treat him for cataract, which I understand he did by branding him on the forehead and cheekbone. The Sultan al§o said with reference to the boundary negotiations with Ibn Saud that he and the Imam were completely at one in all foreign matters. During discussions about Indian represen tation in Muscat the Sultan stated that he intended giving notice of the termination of the 1939 Treaty of Commerce and Navigation with His Majesty's Government and the Govern ment of India in February 1950 which means that it will automatically terminate on the 5th February 1951 and that a new treaty will have to be negotiated before that date. The Sultan seemed to think that it would be sufficient to nego tiate the new treaty with His Majesty's Government leaving it to India and Pakistan to accede to it as they wished, but I told him that it might be necessary for him to negotiate separate treaties direct with these two countries. The Sultan hopes to leave for India about the 20th Octo ber. He proposes to visit Karachi for a few days at the be ginning of December and expects to be back in Muscat about the middle of that month. While at Muscat I saw most of the members of the British and American communities there and some of the local merchants. As usual I found the local atmosphere most happy and r JL A iC. iy. The Suluan is how T ever apparently attempting to restrict intercourse between his relations and Europeans, possibly because he has heard that some of them used to take alcoholic refreshment at the Cable &amp; Wireless club. He is reported to be pursuing a policy of religious intolerance - it will be remembered that he insisted some time ago that the American Mission school be closed - in order to give the Imam and the tribes of the interior no grounds for saying that he is not a good Muslim. FCONOMIC _gIJJP£LEMF^T. The revaluation of the pound appears to have caused little stir in the Gulf States, but the failure of the /Pakistanw - 6 - 8633 Pakistan Government to co-operate has peJ’turbeBMHe Mu in be^ige Mu^pat merchants who informed me that both the Piirsvi 1 gv Daiili ti^ India; and the local branch of the British Bank of Iran and the Mid dle East were refusing to accept Pakistani rupees. The free market dollar rate at the time of revaluation was more favou rable to the rupee than the new official rate. The representatives of the Bombay Navigation and Ship ping Company who visited Bahrain during the month told me that the company hoped to put two new steamers with a speed of 18 knots on the Persian Gulf run before the end of the year. They appeared somewhat embarrassed when I asked them whether the steamers would run in competition or co-operation with the British India Steam Navigation Company's steamers. The Bahrain Government have now promised to give Gray Mackenzies a 99 years lease for the site for a shipyard on the west side of the Muharraq causeway bridge. No rent has yet been fixed. Rowe, the American promoter of 'Persian Gulf Associates', a company designed to supply fish for Bahrain, has gone to the U.S.A. to mature his plans and obtain materials. The Ruler of Qatar has given his written consent to the opening of a branch of the Eastern Bank in Qatar, though I do not yet know the exact terms in which this consent has been given. As already reported the British Bank of Iran and the Middle Fast are also showing an interest in Qatar and it is believed that their manager at Bahrain shortly intends to visit Doha. Gray Mackenzies have obtained a site for premises near the customs jetty at Doha and propose to send a representative there shortly. The customs revenue at Muscat is continuing to increase apparently because piecegoods and other articles are arriving from India for export to Pakistan. These goods are sent to Pasni on the Mekran coast where the customs duty is much lower than at Karachi. The date crop on the Batinah coast and Oman is reported to be good so far as quantity is concerned, but rather poor in quality. Most of the crop is exported to India where due to the inferior quality rather low prices were being offered for it. A local merchant informed me that these prices are now showing an upward tendency. The rice imported by the Muscat Government from Egypt is only being put on the market in small quantities as up to the present Persian rice, which is much preferred, has been available at very nearly the same price. With the re valuation of the pound it is probable that the price of the Persian rice will rise and that there will then be a greater demand for the Egyptian rice.rrw* / CONFIDENTIAL (95/11/49) PERSI/LN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 8th September, 1949. y ( 2 a)\ Dear Burrows, CONFfD^NTfAi The following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf during the months of July and August. Owing to my ab sence in the United Kingdom no separate summary was prepared for July. ; y ^ general Staff . U A f v ^ J | I left Bahrain on the 17th July to attend thief! Middle ^last Conference and returned on the 20th August. ITUrlrig my-ah^ence, Jakins, Political Agent, Bahrain acted in addition as Poli tical Resident. Stobart, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast and Ellison, the Political Agent, Muscat went on leave to the United Kingdom in July. Andrew, Second Secretary in the Resi dency is acting temporarily as Political Agent, Muscat. Wilton took over as Assistant Political Agent, Kuwait in July, but has since been transferred to the newly created appointment of Political Officer, Qatar. A B.4 officer has been posted to Kuwait. Pelly, the Political Agent, Bahrain, who was on leave in the United Kingdom, has gone to Jedda to assist in the frontier negotiations with Saudi Arabia. At present the posts of Second Secretary in the Residency, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain and Political Officer, Trucial Coast are vacant. Visitors . Visitors to the Residency have included Harrison, the Ministry of Transport's representative in India and Pakistan, Ritchie, a member of a firm of chartered accountants who came out to examine the Persian Gulf Lighting Service accounts, Lt. Commander Abram, commanding H.M.S. 'Derby Haven', M. Coste Floret, the French Colonial Minister with his wife and a Cambodian princess, who is a school mistress in real life, and Waters and Shepherd, Ministry of Works officers from Cairo. A party of Imperial Defence College students also paid a few hours visit to Bahrain during a tour of the Middle East. Relations with the U.S.A . Captain W.V. O’Regan, has been succeeded by Captain K.G. Hensel, who has assumed the title of Commander, Middle Fast Force. It is understood that he is at the top of the U.S. list of captains and it is possible, therefore, that he may soon be granted admiral’s rank. The only ship in his commajid is at present the U.S.S. 'Greenwich Bay'. Relations with Persia . H.M.S, 'Wren' visited Tanb, Abu Musa and Sir bu Na’ir in July and found no signs of any Persian interference. H.M.S. 'Derby Haven' spent a few days at Bahrain during July on her way to Khurramshahr to be handed over to the Persians. She had two Persian captains on board who were entertained to lunch at the Residency. The question of the Persian claim to /Bahrain B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London. 4Bahrain was fortunately not raised and no particular embarras sment was caused by their presence here. The Persians have notified the International Bureau of the Universal Postal Union, Geneva, that they cannot recognise the present Bahrain stamps and that letters bearing them which arrive in Persia will be treated as unstamped. This however is an old story. Iranian Airways planes have been continuing to visit Kuwait, and to encourage their use, the Persian authorities have let it be known that Kuwait Oil Company employees will be allowed to visit Tehran without visas provided they are in possession of passports. Relations with India . Independence Day on August 15th was celebrated by a party in the Awal Cinema which Shaikh Salman and British Political officers attended. Eg. la t i o^s _wjt h,.„ Pakistan. Independence Day was similarly celebrated by the local Pakistani community and the party was attended by the Shaikh and British officers. We have received a visit from Mr. Ahmed of the Pakistan State Bank, whom we found most friendly. Currency and other questions were discussed with him and are dealt with in the economic supplement. In my summary for June I mentioned the invitation from the Pakistan Government to the Gulf States to send unofficial representatives to an economic conference which is to be held at Karachi in the autumn. The Persian Government have refused to co-operate in this conference unless the invitation to Bah rain is withdrawn. The Pakistan Government have accordingly requested that the invitation should be withdrawn as tact fully as possible. The Bahrain Government in any case inten ded to decline it. Civil Aviation . The new Kuwait Civil Air Agreement was signed by the Shaikh and the Political Agent on 21st June. It is in much the same terms as the previous agreement and leaves the control of aerodromes and civil aviation in Kuwait in the hands of His Majesty’s Government acting on behalf of the Shaikh. A survey party from the Ministry of Civil Aviation visited Kuwait in July and an early decision'is expected about the construction of the new Kuwait airport. No progress has been made with negotiations for a new civil air agreemwnt with Sharjah as the Ruler is still absent in Bombay and no authority has been received from him for his brother to negotiate 6n his behalf. During my absence the acting Political Resident held a conference to consider the action to be taken to improve the present chaotic conditions at the Bahrain land airport. The main recommendation made was the appointment by His Majesty’s Government of a civil manager for the airport. This is urgently necessary not only for putting the existing organisation into proper shape but to prevent friction between the British Overseas Airways Corporation and International Aeradio Limited which is at present liable to occur. Most of the flying boat services have been suspended and the marine base at Bahrain will shortly be closed down. We shall miss the flying boats which are comfortable to travelV u - 3 - in and a delight to watch when landing and taking off. Quarantine &amp; Medical „ Moody, the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, returned from leave at the end of August and Grant, the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain has gone on leave to the United Kingdom. Fwing is expected to arrive in Kuwait at the beginning of September to take over the duties of Quarantine Medical Officer there and Matthews will then return to Muscat. Oil. On the 4th August a concession was granted by the Ruler of Qatar to Sir Hugh Weightman, representing the Central Mining &amp; Investment Corporation, and the Superior Oil Company of America for the exploitation of the sea-bed subject to his jurisdiction. The concession is conditional on the decision reached on the claim made by Petroleum Concessions Limited that the sea-bed is already covered by their concession. This claim is to be referred to arbitration and Petroleum Conces sions Limited have appointed Sir Walter Monckton as their arbitrator. The Ruler has appointed Mr. Fox Andrews on the advice of Weightman whose company has promised to pay his fees. Petroleum Concessions Limited have appointed the same arbitrator for the settlement of their dispute with the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi over a similar claim. In my last letter I repor ted that Abu Dhabi had appointed his arbitrator, but this was incorrect. The Ruler has in fact appointed no arbitrator and the company have called upon the Political Resident to appoint one on his behalf under the terms of their concession. Before any action is taken, the Ruler is being asked to agree in wri ting to pay the arbitrators fees which are likely to be very heavy especially as a man of Sir Walter Monckton f s calibre is appointed. The other Trucial Coast rulers have been asked by the Political Agent whether they consider that their exis- ting'concessions cover the sea-bed. Abu Dhabi and Ajman have replied in the negative and no definite reply has yet been received from the others. The Bahrain Petroleum Company have abandoned their pro posal to establish an electronic survey aid station in Qatar and instead are constructing one on the main Hawar island. The Shaikh of Kuwait has informed the Political Agent that he has no objection to the establishment by the company of a station on Arabi and the company has told us that they are undertaking this work immediately. The Shaikh of Kuwait has not as yet sent any reply to the representation made by the Kuwait Oil Company that all the Kuwait islands including Qaru, Kubbar and Umm al Maradim are covered by their concession, and meanwhile the American Inde pendent Oil Company are negotiating for the grant of a conces sion for these three islands. V Bahrain S I exchanged calls with Shaikh Salman on my return from the United Kingdom and found him in very good health and spirits He no doubt hopes that the turn events have taken in Qatar will enable him to attain his objects in Zubarah and has al ready taken up the matter with the Political Agent. Shaikh Ali of Qatar wrote him a very friendly letter on his accession and there is now a possibility of reaching an amicable settle ment of this long standing dispute. I also exchanged calls with Shaikh Salman’s two uncles; the elder, Shaikh Muhammad has recently returned from a visit to the Lebanon where he went /toto avoid the rigours of a hot weather Ramadhan, while the younger, Shaikh Abdullah, has been compelled to abandon his frako his whole” intention of p ^^-^ming the pilgrimage to Mecca this year as he proposed to take his whole family consisting of 60 or 70 persons with him, and could obtain neither sea nor air trans port for such a large party. Father Louis, the Administrator of the Roman Catholic Diocese of Aden, arrived in Bahrain in July and presented a photograph of His Holiness the Pope to Shaikh Salman, who, like his father, has always shown himself sympathetic to projects designed to promote the spiritual welfare of Chris tians in Bahrain. Kuwait . Shaikh Ahmed has as yet made no amends for his failure to call on me when he visited Bahrain in June. It was ten tatively suggested to him that he might meet me at the aerodrome on my way back from the United Kingdom, but he was not willing to do this. He has informed the Political Agent that he would be grateful if we would support his claims to the islands of Farsi, Arabi and Harqus and it has been learnt that on his voyage back from Bahrain in June he caused a notice to be erected on Farsi island to the effect that it was Kuwait te^i' tory. It will be remembered that a similar notice erected by the Persians was removed from the island by one of H.M f s ships earlier in the year. As mentioned elsewhere, he has given permission to the Bahrain Petroleum Company to erect an elec tronic survey aid station on Arabi and has not mentioned the question of rent. Doctor Parry, an ex-Indian Medical Service officer, has been appointed by the Shaikh as his Chief Medical Officer. He will have an uphill task, but there is good reason to hope that he will prove more successful than his predecessor Dr. Akopiantz. Three British police officers with previous service in Palestine, have also arrived in Kuwait for employ ment under the Shaikh's Government. The Shaikh is also trying to obtain the services of a British matron for his hospital. Qatar . Events have taken place in Qatar during the period under report which have completely changed the situation there and give good grounds for hoping that it will be possible to intro duce a proper administration in the state and thereby facili tate the development of its rich oilfield. In July a request was received from the local oil company for action to be taken to restrain the Shaikh of Wakrah from interfering in their operations. Wakrah is a small village on the coast south of Doha and its Shaikh, who is a member of the ruling family, had refused to allow the company to erect survey marks in his area. The Ruler, Shaikh Abdulla, expressed his inability to take any action, and at my request the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf sent H.M.S. ,, Flamingo M to visit Wakrah, and its Shaikh was personally warned by her Commanding Officer. This had the desired effect and the company have reported that the local Shaikh is now entirely amenable. When Gethin, the First Secretary to this Residency, visited Doha on the 4th August with Weightman to complete the negotiations for the grant of a concession to the Central Mining and Investment Corporatoon and the Superior Oil Company of America, he found old Shaikh Abdulla in a state of much agitation as his relations had recently threatened to cause a riot and he had been forced to appease them by promising them regular monthly allowances out of his oil revenues. He asked Gethin to arrange for the early /appointmentI \n\ 5 appointment of a British Political officer to Qatar. Subse quently he^sent urgent messages to Jakins, the Political asking him to visit him. Jakins went to Doha on the 16th August and Shaikh Abdulla, who claims to be 84 but is k e a hout 74, said he wished to abdicate in favour of his eldest son Shaikh Ali. He agreed to the immediate appointment of a British Political Officer. Under instruc tions from the Foreign Office Jakins went to Doha again on the 20th August and after obtaining from Shaikh Abdulla an agreement to the bringing into force of the articles of the 1916 Treaty relating to the appointment of a British Political Officer and other^matters, and from Shaikh Ali an undertaking to observe all existing treaties and engagements and a written request for the services of a British adviser, held a public ceremony in which the abdication of Shaikh Abdulla and the accession of Shaikh Ali were announced. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf^had previously sent H.M.S. 'Flamingo' to Doha and her Captain, officers and ship T s company rendered every possible assistance throughout the crisis. The Captain, Lt. Commander Godden attended the accession ceremony and pro vided a guard of honour and the ship fired a salute for the new Ruler. A landing party was sent ashore from the ship on the 20th August to act as a guard for the British Political Officer and^also^as a deterrent to any kind of demonstration. Gethin remained in Doha until the 24th August to keep an eye on the situation and Wilton arrived from Kuwait on the 23rd to take over charge as Political Officer. As there was no sign of any disturbance the Naval landing party was withdrawn on the 29th August. The new Ruler is between 55 and 60 years of age and possesses a fine presence. He has always been kept in the background by his father who favoured the second son, Hamad. The latter, who was very able and an arch intri guer , died last year and subsequent events have shown that his father has found himself unable to carry on without his support. It is hoped that if we can give Ali the material and moral assistance which he requires in sufficient time, he will be able to consolidate his position and introduce a reasonably efficient administration. Trucial Coast . In the absence of any responsible officer on the spot little news has been received from the Trucial Coast. One case of the abduction of a woman into slavery has been repor ted in which the son of the acting Ruler of Sharjah is believed to have been concerned. The matter is being taken up with the Ruler but there is no hope of recovering the woman. Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr of Sharjah is still in Bombay, and his health is reported to have much improved. It is not yet known when he intends to return. Muscat . The Sultan proposes to leave for Bombay about the middle of October on a six weeks visit to India, largely to consult his doctors in Bombay. He intends, however, to visit Delhi and it is possible that he may discuss with the authorities there his future relations with India. During August he received a visit from Mr. Wendell Phillips, the American who wishes to bring a large party for archaeological exploration in Southern Arabia. He is reported to have treated Mr. Phillips with great cordiality and has already given him permission to visit Dhofar with an indication that he may allow him to explore additional areas subsequently. / ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT.ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT. - 6 - The Pakistan Government have offered to supply 1945 tons of broken rice and Baluchistan rice for the Gulf States. This rice is of inferior quality, but is the staple food at Gwadur for which the Pakistan Government have been asked to supply 150 tons. Kuwait and Muscat do not require any of this rice and replies are awaited from the other states. The opportunity was taken of the visit of Harrison, the Ministry of Transport’s representative for India and Pakistan to discuss local shipping problems, especially the British India services to and from Muscat. These continue to be very unsatisfactory as the ’’B” boat services are very irregular and sometimes as much as a month elapses between calls. The Shaikh of Bahrain has refused to allow Gray Mackenzies to build a shipyard on the site they have asked for on the east side of the Muharraq causeway bridge, but has told them that he is willing to grant them an indefinite lease for a site on the west side of it. They are examining the possibili ties of this site. Mr. Ahmed, the representative of the State Bank of Pakis tan, whose visit has already been mentioned, was as we expected chiefly interested in the question of Pakistan currency. He had talks with the Bank Managers, who agreed that if the Pakis tan State Bank bore the cost of repatriation of Pakistani rupees they would accept them at par. If an agreement is final ly reached to this effect, Mr. Ahmed hopes that British Govern ment offices will be willing to accept Pakistani equally with Indian rupees. He also had discussions with local merchants, whom he found anxious to develop trade with Pakistan. He, therefore, intends to propose to his principals the opening of a branch of the Pakistan State Bank in Bahrain for the purposes of facilitating this trade. After leaving Bahrain he paid a visit to Kuwait. The new Ruler of Qatar has granted verbal permission to the Eastern Bank to open a branch in Doha. The bank are now endeavouring to obtain confirmation of this in writing. In their letter they have not asked for a monopoly, but have re ferred to an understanding with the Shaikh that no other bank will be permitted to open there for the time being. Meanwhile the manager of the British Bank of Iran and the Middle East has begun to shown an interest in Qatar. 9 Venezuelan pearls are reaching Bahrain via Kuwait and Shaikh Salman has written personally to Shaikh Ahmed asking ■ him to put a stop to this traffic. A few months ago an American ex-employee of ARAMCO stated a company known as the Mercury Boat Lines for the conveyance of passengers and freight by high speed launches between Bah rain and the mainland. The launches in question were not suited to local conditions and continually broke down. The company has gone into liquidation. Another American ex-employee of ARAMCO is proposing to start an organisation called the Persian Gulf Associates to develop fisheries. The matter is under the consideration of the Bahrain Government. Haji Backer’s fishmeal factory at Mattrah near Muscat is not yet operating again as some machinery is still awaited from the United Kingdom. Kj • Hl\ V.Dear Burrows CONFIDENTIAL . (95/8/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDEN BAHRAIN. 5th July, 1949. The following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf during the month of June. GENERAL . His Majesty*s Birthday . His Majesty’s Birthday was celebrated in the traditio nal^ style in this Residency and the Agencies. His Highness Shaikh Salman called on me with twenty two of his relations and asked me to convey his felicitations and an expression of his loyalty to His Majesty. I took the occasion to present the Badge of the C.B.E. to His Highness' uncle Shaikh Muhammad bin Isa. Pelly has proceeded on leave and Jakins has taken his place as Political Agent, Bahrain. Gethin arrived at the end of the month and has taken over as First Secretary of the Residency. Wilton was expected at Kuwait as Assistant Political Agent at the end of the month, but his arrival has so far not yet been reported. Stobart is due to go on leave in a few days’ time and Ellison, whose leave was can celled is pressing for re-consideration of this order on grounds of his ill-health. If his request is granted I shall require urgently at least one A grade and one B grade officer to enable the Residency and its subordinate offices to function efficiently. I am expecting to leave for the United Kingdom myself to attend the Middle East Conference on the 23rd July and to return here in the middle of August. Visitors . We have again had a large number of visitors at the Residency. Woods-Ballard, the Sultan of Muscat’s Minister of Foreign Affairs, who is spending a month’s recess in Bahrain stayed with us for some days. Wood, the Regional Security Officer, Middle East, stayed about a week with us and inspected the Residency and the Bahrain Agency offices. Group Captain Counsell, Commanding the R.A.F. Shaibah, paid a short visit with his wife. Mr. Parker T. Hart, who has just taken over as United States Consul at Dhahran came over with his bride to pay his calls and spent the night with us. The United States Consulate at Dhahran has not yet been officially raised to the status of a consulate- general, but Hart informed me that this would be done as soon as the new seal has been received. Hart' has previously served at Dhahran and was United States Consul there when I took over as Political Resident in 1946. Captain Skelton, the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, stayed with us for two days before leaving for Colombo on a visit to the C.-in- C. East Indies. Weightman also spent some days with us while his draft concession for the Qatar sea-bed was under consi deration. We were all very sorry to hear that Sir William Strang's proposed visit to Bahrain had to be cancelled on account of his illness. Staff . / Relations with Iraq . B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London.- 2 - Relations with Iraq . We have been informed that the Political Agents may no longer grant visas for Iraq and that travellers from the Persian Gulf will be granted emergency visas on arrival in the country. We have not yet heard whether this system is working satisfactorily or not. Meanwhile, a local merchant, Ahmed Fakhroo has received a letter from an Iraqi ex-cabinet minister enquiring whether he would be willing to accept the appointment of honorary Iraqi consul in Bahrain or if not, whether he could suggest anybody else for the appoint ment . Relation s with Persia . The Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf visited the is lands of Tamb and Abu Musa, which are claimed by Persia, in H.M.S. ,? ?lamingo n an found all well there. Shaikh Muhammad bin Saqr, who is acting as Regent of Sharjah while his bro ther Shaikh Sultan is undergoing medical treatment in Bombay, accompanied him to Abu Musa. Travellers from Persia arriving in Dubai are spreading rumours that the Persians are collec ting troops to occupy these two islands and also Sir bu Na’ir. Rel ations_with Pakistan„ Mr, S.M. Saddiq, who used to be the Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain, passed through Bahrain on his way to take over the appointment of Pakistan Charge d*Affaires at Baghdad. He called on me and his manners com pared very favourably with those of another Pakistani diplo mat who recently called here on his way to Jeddah. We re ceived a telegram from the Pakistan Government that a senior official of their State Bank would shortly visit us. When I replied that we would warmly welcome him I was informed that the visit had been cancelled. I have been asked by the Pakistan Government to invite the Gulf States to send unofficial representatives to an economic conference which is to be held in Karachi in a few months’ time. Civ il Avi ation. Final instructions have been received about the new Civil Air Agreements which are being negotiated with Kuwait and Sharjah. I asked the Political Agent at Kuwait to endea vour to complete the negotiations there before Ramadhan, but I do not yet know if he has been successful in doing this. Negotiations with Shr^jah have been held up owing to the prolon^e. ahS'-xice of she Ruler in Bombay on account of ill- hc .un. He is hp^g asked to authorise his brother who is acting as Regent to oceed with the negotiations in his place. Many foreign aircraft are using the Gulf airfields without any kind of prior notification or permission and I am taking up this question with His Majesty’s Government. I have also been asked by the International Civil Aviation Organisation representative in the Middle East to arrange for notams to issue describing the conditions under which the Gulf airfields may be used. The Shaikh of Kuwait without consulting us has given Iranian Airways permission to use the Kuwait airfield. Nothing is being said to him about this pending the completion of a new Civil Air Agreement as the old agreement has lapsed and we are not, therefore, on very good ground in making a protest. /TheIThe Kuwait Oil Company’s supply of fresh vegetables and fruit and other amenities was held up for some time owing to the refusal of the Lebanese authorities to allow the aircraft engaged by Spinneys conveying these articles to fly between the Lebanon and Kuwait. The matter has been taken up by Hi.M’s Minister, Beirut, with the Lebanese Government. Quarantine and Medical . Col. Moody, the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, has proceeded on leave and Major Grant, the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, is acting in his place. Dr. §uthrie, the Quarantine Medical Officer, Kuwait, has resigned after a month’s stay there and we have had to send Captain Matt hews from Muscat, where he can ill be spared, to Kuwait to take over his duties temporarily. Dr. McCaully, who has recently been appointed Medical Officer, Trucial Coast has been on a visit to Bahrain. He has an uphill task, starting practically from nothing, but appears to be making good progress. The Bahrain Government are co-operating fully in the local quarantine administration, responsibility for which they wish to take over in a year or two's time. Rulers of Bahrain, Kuwait, Qatar and the Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms (excluding Kalbah) have issued proclamations claiming jurisdiction over the sea-bed in the vicinity of their coasts. The Sultan of Muscat, to whom it was sugges ted that he should issue a proclamation regarding the sea bed lying off his territory within the Persian Gulf, has demurred probably because he does not wish to appear to be acting at our dictation. Petroleum Concessions Limited claim that their existing concessions cover the sea-bed of Qatar and the Trucial Coast Shaikhdoms. Qatar and Abu Dhabi have refused to accept this contention and Abu Dhabi has already appointed an arbitra tor for the settlement of the dispute with the company. The attitude of the other Trucial Coast Rulers is not yet known. Similarly, the Kuwait Oil Company claim that their concession covers the Kuwait sea-bed and certain islands which are not specifically mentioned in it, and they have forwarded to the Shaikh of Kuwait legal opinion in support of their claim. The Shaikh refuses to admit it and resort to arbitration appears probable. Weightman with an American colleague representing the Central Mining and Investment Corporation and the Superior Oil Company of America has been negotiating with the Rulers of Qatar and Abu Dhabi for sea-bed conces sions. The latter Ruler flourished in his face a copy of the concession obtained by Pacific (Western) for the Saudi share of the Kuwait - Saudi neutral zone and made such exhorbitant demands that he is leaving him alone for the time being. He has, however, persuaded the Ruler of Qatar to grant the two companies a concession on reasonable terms and the draft is at present under the consideration of His Majesty's Government. The Bahrain Petroleum Company are showing rather an aggressive attitude. Complaints were received from Petroleum Concessions Limited that they were carrying out seismic opera tions in Qatar territorial waters in the immediate vicinity of their own installations. The Bahrain Petroleum Company state that as the Shaikh of Bahrain has not accepted His Majesty's Government’s decision regarding the sea-bed boun dary between Bahrain and Qatar they are not bound b£ it and that as the Shaikh of Bahrain claims the whole of the waters including the Qatar territorial waters, they are at liberty to operate there. The Shaikh of Qatar probably for reasons /of4 of his own has not supported the complaint made by Petroleum Concessions Limited. The Bahrain Petroleum Company have also announced their intention of establishing an electronic survey aid station on Arabi island without seeking anybody's permis sion. It will be remembered that they were previously informed that there was no objection to their erecting a station on Farsi island provided they obtained the Shaikh of Kuwait's permission. Arabi is regarded by us as belonging to Kuwait. Now that a boundary between Abu Dhabi and Dubai has been fixed, Petroleum Concessions Limited hope to start drilling in ^the former's territory before the end of the year. A good deal of surprise has been caused by the resig nation of Mr. MacPherson, the Vice-President of the Arabian American Oil Company and his acceptance of employment with AMINCO, who hold the concession for the Kuwait Neutral Zone. He has been associated with the Arabian American Oil Company and its parent companies for some 30 years and for several years has been their Vice-President in charge of their opera tions in Saudi Arabia. He expects to arrive in Kuwait on the 31st July to take over charge of AMINCO's operations in the Neutral Zone. The General Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company has informed me that the price of a barrel of crude oil has fallen from #2.65 to #1.15 since October last. This fall in prices is naturally seriously affecting the oil companies who are already in production and must be causing serious alarm to the companies who have paid such a heavy price for concessions in the Kuwait - Saudi Neutral Zone. Bahrain . I called on the Shaikh with Waight on the 5th June when we spoke to him about the currency question, and I went to see him again with the Political Agent on the 13th June to discuss his request for an assurance against aggression and other matters. He is satisfied with the terms of the assurance which it is proposed to give him, but is unlikely to agree to give a promise always to employ a British Financial Adviser as a quid pro quo . He showed himself very strongly opposed to the appointment of the representative of any foreign coun try in Bahrain and said that he wished to have dealings with the British only. He took very unkindly to a suggestion I made that if any company were willing to build a large modern hotel here the sale of liquor should be permitted. He has recently questioned our right to exercise jurisdiction over the subjects of other Gulf States in Bahrain and demanded that the new Order-in-Council should be suspended. I told him that any demand of this nature was not likely to be well received but if he made a request for the concession to him of jurisdiction over subjects of other Gulf States in Bahrain I would be prepared to give it my sympathetic consideration c It is somewhat unreasonable that backward states like Kuwait and Qatar should enjoy this jurisdiction while it is denied to a comparatively well administered state like Bahrain. The Shaikh's letter to the Foreign Secretary about Zubarah is still under consideration at the Foreign Office. The Shaikh has appointed Ballantyne, the Bahrain Petroleum Company's representative in London to complete his case and has now asked that Belgrave, who is on leave in the United Kingdom should also be heard on the subject. I have been informed that the visit of the Shaikh's uncle, Shaikh Muhammad to America cost the Bahrain Petroleum Company about #50,000 and that his behaviour with the ladies there and on the journey left much to be desired. His son Shaikh /Hamad,Hamad, who is being educated at Stanford University, has let it be known that on his return to Bahrain he expects to be appointed Labour Relations Officer and that he proposes to give the Bahrain Petroleum Company hell* Kuwait . The Shaikh of Kuwait, who arrived at Bahrain in his yacht the ,, Ahmedy n on the 30th May and left on the 10th June failed to call on me and refused to comply with a polite request that he should come and see me on business. Since his return to Kuwait he has explained to the Political Agent that he expec ted me to call on him first as he was a visitor or at any rate to send an officer to him to arrange matters. While at Bahrain he caused much annoyance to the local authorities by taking with him everywhere 20 to 30 armed men and on his first arriving he even landed boxes of ammunition on the cus toms pier. He was lavishly entertained by the Shaikh and his relations and local merchants and put everybody to much trouble and expense. He spent much time in the cinemas and the bazaar. It is to be hoped that his sojourn in Bahrain may Induce him to take steps to improve the administration of his own state and it is significant that since his return he has agreed to employ three British police sergeants. Truclal Coast . The Air Officer Commanding R.A.F., Iraq, very kindly arranged for a number of Brigands to demonstrate over the Trucial Coast during the month. They flew along the whole coast up to the Khor al 'Odaid and also inland over Buraimi and Liwa. The Rulers of Dubai and Sharjah were both away but the son of the former and the brother of the latter, who are representing the Rulers, inspected the aircraft and showed considerable trepidation when invited to go for a ride in them. Reports are not yet to hand of the general effect the demonstration. Muscat . At the request of the Pakistan Government the Sultan has been asked whether he is willing to sell Gwadur to Pakis tan. He has refused to sell the place, but it appears possi ble that he may be willing to lease it. I referred in my last monthly letter to a riot which had taken place at Gwadur, and reported that the Senior Naval Officer Periian Gulf had kindly made H.M.S. 'Flamingo” avai lable to take Ellison and Woods Ballard there. The riot appears to have been caused by the fact that the British Agent kept the woman over whom the trouble had arisen in his own house instead of handing her over to the Wali for custody. As a result a crowd attacked the house and released the woman after causing a little damage to the building and small injuries to the British Agent. Ellison succeeded in arranging for the woman to be despatched to Karachi and for the amicable settlement of a pending case relation to the Jewelry which she was alleged to have stolen from her previous Hindu husband. On the 29th May a report was received that a British Officer attached to the Royal Pakistan Air Force with some jeeps had stuck in the sand in Gwadur territory while procee ding from Pasni to Jiwani. The Sultan some time ago took steps to close the road which the Pakistani authorities were trying to build along the coast here and forbade its use. The Wali was therefore somewhat indignant when he heard what had occurred. The officer concerned, however, satisfied him that he had not entered Gwadur territory with any ill intention and he was accordingly given every assistance and allowed to proceed. / ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT .6 ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT . Waight, the Treasury Representative in the Middle East, spent some time • in^Bahrain at the end of May and the beginning of June and also visited Kuwait. The question of the currency to be employed in the Gulf States was discussed with the Rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait and both agreed that it appeared desirable that the Indian rupee should be replaced by a curren cy under the control of His Majesty’s Government. They both, however, wished to consult their merchants before expressing a final opinion. It is possible that some opposition may be encountered from the merchants and the policy to be followed has not yet been decided upon. Waight also examined our present system of exchange control which he considdred to be working satisfactorily. The Bahrain Government, who have all their reserve in vested in securities in India have applied to the Reserve Bank of India for permission to sell half of them with a view to devoting the proceeds to development purposes. On the 7th June at the request of the local Manager of Cable &amp; Wireless I inaugurated the new radio telephone system by speaking^to the Managing Director of Cable &amp; Wireless in London and my wife in the country. The speech came through very clearly and this new service should be of great benefit to British residents and the mercantile community in Bahrain, It is hoped in due course to establish communications by radio telephone between Bahrain and New York, a prospect which the General Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company does not appreciate. It is reported, but not yet confirmed, that the Persian Government are now permitting the export of ric^ to tne Gulf States from Khurramshahr. Owing to the amount of rice that is now arriving and the import of comparatively cheap wheat smuggled from Persia most of the Gulf States have asked that their quotas of wheat from stocks maintained at Basra by His Majesty's Government should be suspended. This gives rise to rather a difficult problem as the Ministry of Food do not want to be left with a large quantity of wheat on their hands at Basra and on the other hand I feel it would be very dangerous if we were left without any reserve from which the Gulf States could be supplied, as there is no guarantee that imports of wheat from other sources will continue and we should be faced with a serious situation if anything in the nature of a famine were to occur especially in the States where oil companies are operating. It is reported that ?old is now being exported to Hong kong instead of India and Pakistan. It is paid for by the Gulf merchants in dollars and owing to the demand for it the local dollar rate which is usual! v a little over Rs.4 has now risen to Rs.5. Rupee notes to the value of rupees 519- lakhs representing mostly the proceeds of the sale of gold, were repatriated by the branches of the Imperial Bank of Iran at Kuwait and Bahrain to India and Pakistan between the 1st November, 1948 and the 1st May, 1949.(95/7/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 6th June, 1949, Dear Burrows, The following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf during the month of May, GENERAL . Staff . Mr. C.J. Ovenden, a Branch B officer of the Residency was accidently drowned in the Bahrain Gymkhana Club swimming pool on the 25th May. Dredge, the 1st Secretary of the Residency has had to take leave owing to ill health and left on the 19th May. Pelly, the Political Agent, Bahrain, is suffering from suspected amoebic dysentery and expects to leave for the United King dom on the 5th June. The posts of Assistant Political Agent. Bahrain and Kuwait have not been filled and we are at present extremely short-handed. Tours . I visited Sharjah and Muscat with you between the 8th and 12th May, but otherwise I have not left Bahrain. Besides yourself, we have accommodated at the Residency during the month Captain Porter, the late Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Captain Skelton, the new Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Scott-Fox, Counsellor, His Majesty’s Embassy, Jeddah, Barnard, the Civil Air AttachA, Baghdad, Weight, the Treasury Representative, Middle East, Popov of the Desert Lo cust Survey and Stobart, the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. Captain Skelton took over from Captain Porter as Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf on the 4th May. Mr. Childs, the United States Ambassador, Jeddah, paid a brief visit to Bahrain on the 12th May and lunched at the Residency. You and Scott-Fox were present at the time and the opportunity was taken to discuss with him the recent in cursions of Saudi Arabian officials and Arabian American Oil Company survey parties into Abu Dhabi territory and the boundary question in general together with the proposed Saudi Arabian proclamation about the continental shelf and other matters. The U.S.S. ’’Duxbury Bay” spent some days at the Jufair anchorage. I exchanged calls with the Captain and the ship's officers gave a cocktail party in the Jufair wardroom. It is understood that the facilities afforded by the Naval Base in Jufair are in future to be made available freely to the officers and men of the U.S. Navy. On the 28th May H.M.S. Flamingo visited Farsi island and /removed B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London.V • 2 — removed the plate bearing the inscription 'Persian territory' and obliterated other similar inscriptions on the beacon. The plate was found to be made not of brass but of tin pain ted b lack with the inscription on it in white. Relations with Saudi Arabia . So far as is known, the Arabian American Oil Company survey parties have completely withdrawn from Abu Dhabi terri tory leaving behind only the beacons and cairns they have erected. Negotiations regarding the boundary are now being considered. Ibn Saud’s Court Chamberlain, A1 Tubaishi visited Bahrain during the month and called on the Shaikh. Relations with India . The Bahrain Government have asked that no more visas should be granted to Indians and Pakistanis without reference to them owing to the very large numbers that have been coming to Bahrain during recent months. Nothing further has been said to the Shaikh of Bahrain about the appointment of an Indian Trade Agent pending a deci sion on his request for an assurance against aggression. Mean while, he has received an offer from a Muslim in Cochin to act as Bahrain Trade Agent in that part of India. He has re plied that no such appointment is under consideration. The Sultan of Muscat has raised the question whether India is entitled to consular representation under the 1939 Treaty now that she has announced her intention of declaring herself a republic. Relations with Pakistan . The Government of Pakistan still continue to accuse us of being biassed in favour of India. This is largely because of the decision to accept Indian currency only for official purposes, but we are also alleged to be employing Indians in preference to Pakistanis. Actually, the proportion of Pa kistanis to Indians employed in the Residency and the Politi cal Agencies is greater now than it was at the time of the separation of the two countries. Persian G ulf Lighting Service . The 'Nearchus' visited Ras al Hadd during the month to find a site for a lighthouse. The Sultan would not allow the survey of Ras al Hz Junaiz 8 or 9 miles south of Ras al Hadd, which offers the best site owing to his inability to afford protection there. Although Ras al Hadd itself is not such a good site, water and supplies are available there and it will probably be found necessary to adopt it. The matter will shortly be considered by the Persian Gulf Lighting Ser vice Advisory Committee. SlYlLAviation. On the 7th and 13th May an Alaskan Airlines aircraft lan ded at Bahrain with a number of Jews ostensibly from Hongkong. On each occasion the aircraft cleared for Nicosia but actually went to Lydda. On the second occasion the aircraft was de tained for a time and the pilot was warned not to land at Bahrain again without authorisation. It is believed that a number of foreign aircraft are using both the Bahrain and Sharjah aerodromes without any authorisation or prior notifi cation and the matter is being enquired into. / 241 -- 3 - Oil . Instructions have been received that the Gulf Rulers may grant conditional concessions for off-shore oil after the 4th June and the concession-hunters will presumably soon be getting busy again. The Saudi Arabian proclamation regarding jurisdiction over the sea-bed issued on the 29th May and the Gulf Rulers are now being advised to issue similar proclama tions. The Bahrain Petroleum Company have presented a detailed statement to the Bahrain Government offering only a very small increase in the royalties payable by them. Belgrave is proceeding on leave in a few days 1 time and it is unlikely that negotiations will be resumed until after his return at the end of the hot weather. During the month the Bahrain Petroleum Company were informed that there was no objection to their seeking permission from the Shaikh of Kuwait for the erection of an electronic aid survey station on Farsi island. They had been clamouring for this permission for several weeks but no sooner had they received it than they were told by their head office, presumably at the instance of the State Department, not to proceed with the proposal for the time being. The Sultan of Muscat is still annoyed at the lack of in terest shown by Petroleum Concessions Limited in Dhofar and is urging that the company should either start operations or abandon their concession. The Shaikh 1 s eldest son Isa was married during the month to a girl of the A1 Khalifah and the Shaikh dispensed much hospitality. Amongst other things he invited a number of Europeans and Americans to a dinner party which ended with an inspection of the bridal chamber. He also gave a dinner party on th* occasion of your visit. When I took you to see him he harped as usual on his grievances about Zubarah. He has engaged Ballantyne to make representations on his behalf to the Foreign Office in this case. He has written the Political Agent a letter refusing to accept His Majesty’s Government's decision about the division of the sea-bed between Bahrain and Qatar as final and challenging the authority of His Majesty's Government to make any such decision. He has issued a proclamation forbidding any of his subjects to visit Qatar without the permission of the Bahrain Government and pres« cribing a fine which may extendi to Ps.1,000 for disobedience. This proclamation has been the subject of much adverse criti cism. Other matters which are giving rise to discontent are the poor teaching of English in the schools, the antiquated methods of administering justice in the Bahrain courts and the harsh liquor laws. So far as is known, the discontent is confined to murmurings and Belgrave who is proceeding on leave at the beginning of June has given it As his opinion that the political horizon is unclouded and that no trouble is likely to occur ddring his absence. The Shaikh's rigidity over the liquor question has killed the proposal to open a lar ge modern hotel in Bahrain as he is not willing to grant a licence for the sale of liquor except to residents. Under the liquor laws any Bahrain subject found drinking liquor or in possession of liquor can be and usually is awarded six mon ths’ imprisonment. The Shaikh has recently had to deal with his first cousin 'Ali bin 'Abdullah who while drunk drove a car through the bazaar and amongst other things assaulted the Roman Catholic priest. He has been confined to his house in Muharraq for six months, fined Ps.4,000 and deprived of his /carf - 4 - car and driving licence. This punishment was well merited. The Shaikh’s uncle, Shaikh Muhammad bin Isa has returned from his visit to the U.S.A. and seems to have enjoyed his travels. He has recently been awarded an Honorary C.B.E. by His Majesty the King. In the early part of the month a boat which was badly overloaded was caught in a squall while crossing from the main island to one of the smaller islands and 43 women and children were drowned. The Shaikh of Kuwait arrived at Bahrain in his new yacht the 'Ahmadi' at the end of the month. Shaikh Saimaa was not at all looking forward to his visit owing to the expenditure involved and because Shaikh Ahmad is always poking fun at the A1 Khalifah on account of their fine clothes and pomposity. He will no doubt also enjoy making the A1 Khalifah green with envy over his yacht. Qatar. It was hoped to open negotiations with Shaikh Abdullah during the month for the bringing into force of the three Articles of the 1916 Treaty which are held in abeyance, but unfortunately Felly could not do this owing to his illness. It is now proposed that the negotiations should be postponed till after the hot weather. Shaikh Abdullah has agreed that his eldest son and heir apparent, Shaikh Ali should act as his deputy for the pur pose of paying calls on H.M’s ships and should receive the sal utes and honours to which he himself is entitled. THUSlal.Cqa. st . The Political Agent has issued orders fixing the boundary between Abu Dhabi and Dubai. The reactions of the Rulers to the order are not yet known. There is some trouble between the Shaikh of Has al Khai- mah and the Shaikh of the neighbouring village of Rams. The latter is claiming a share of the oil payments. In my last monthly letter I mentioned the 'Joker' slavery case. The 'Joker' is still detained at Bahrain and some evidence has been obtained regarding the identity of the girls trans ported in it to Saudi Arabia. The action to be taken against the Shaikh of Dubai is still under consideration. Popov spent most of the month dealing with locusts on the Trucial Coast and also visited Sohar on the Batinah coast. It appears that most of the swarms have now flown off in a westerly direction. The operations have been closed down and the two remaining Pakistanis have left. MU3£§t. The Sultan was very well when I saw him with you on the 9th May. He attributed the postponement of his visit to the United Kingdom to the internal situation but did not offer any more detailed explanation. He now intends to visit India for a month next September and hopes to visit the United King dom in May, 1960. There has been some kind of communal trouble at Gwadur. It appears that a Hindu married woman ran away from her hus band and sought conversion to Islam. A formal conversion ceremony was held in the presence of the Wali, and the British /Agent0 * Agent, who is an Anglo-Indian from Karachi called Domingo, tried to interfere, A riot followed and some damage was done to the British Agency. The Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf has kindly made H.M.S. Flamingo available to take Elli son and Woods-Ballard to Gwadur from Muscat to deal with the situation. ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT . Egyptian rice has now begun to arrive in Bahrain. This is being rationed by the Bahrain Government on the basis of 6 lbs. per person per month ( 8 lbs, in Ramadhan) and is being sold at 5i annas a lb. as against the previously prevailing rate of 8 annas a lb. Mr. Cove and Mr. Kurley of Messrs. John Howard &amp; Company who are constructing the causeway at Dammam on the mainland visited Bahrain during the month. They are preparing for the Bahrain Government a rough plan for a causeway from Hedd at the southern extremity of Muharraq island to deep water near the Sitrah anchorage. Muscat is receiving Abyssinian wheat via Aden, smuggled wheat from India and Pakistan and flour from Australia. Some smuggled rice is also arriving. As a result a request has been received for the Muscat wheat quota to be suspended for three months. Japanese piecegoods are reaching Muscat in considerable quantities from Aden and Colombo and as a result there is a substantial fall in the sale of Indian piecegoods. It is reported that there is a market available for good English material. The State has decontrolled piecegoods and released large stocks to the merchants, who owing to the fall in prices resulting from Japanese imports are incurring heavy losses. Prices are reported to be falling generally in Muscat and the customs revenue is suffering as a result. Complaints have been received Arom Muscat of the seizure of a large consignment of dried sarodnes en route to Genoa by the Egyptian authorities at Port Said. His Majesty’s Embassy, Cairo, have been addressed on the subject. The British India Steam Navigation Company services con tinue to cause grave dis-satisfaction. The ”B' boat sailings have got into such a muddle that a gap is liable to occur of over a month between arrivals at Muscat followed by two or three arrivals within one month.W) | | ' Aj* PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN* 6th May 1949. EXi 1226 194€? CONFID ENTIAL. (95/6/49) Dear Burrows, The following is a summary of events in the Persian ulf for the month of April. ' GENERAL . Tours . I left Bahrain on the 25th March in a Petroleum Con cessions Limited aircraft and spent the night at Sharjah. The following day I did a very interesting flight over Buraimi and the country west of the Hajar mountains to Ma- sirah island where I spent the night with the Royal Air Force. On the 27th March I flew to Aden in a A.A,F, air craft and landed at Salalah on the way where I had about an hour's talk with the Sultan. I stayed at Aden until the 1st April as the guest of His Excellency the Governor and had in teresting talks with the officials concerned about the Aden Protectorate Levies, fisheries, agriculture, postal matters, etc. I was also able to discuss with the A.O.C. Aden, the use of the Masirah and Salalah airfields by civil aircraft and the arrangements to be made for refuelling them. On the 1st April I left Aden for Jeddah by Aden Airways and spent one night on the way at Asmara. I stayed at Jeddah as the guest of His Majesty's Ambassador until the 5th April and was able to discuss a number of pending cases with him. I called on Mr. Childs, the American Ambassador and discussed the ques tions of off-shore oil and jurisdiction over American citizens in the Gulf States with him in general terms. Trott also ttSolf'/jne to call on the Minister of Finance, Abdullah Sulai- man and on Khair ud Din A1 Zuraiqli, the senior representa tive of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Jeddah. My daughter joined me in Jeddah and on the 5th April I flew with her in a U.S.A.A.F. aircraft to Riyadh where we spent one night as the guests of the King. I had a brief interview with him in his Majlis where he said nothing significant except that the Gulf Rulers were concerned only with the sea. He had been unwell earlier in the day and I found him very lethargic. A number of notables-were present in the Majlis ^ no*! 'd ohe Crown Prince and R^Shid.^Ali Gilani. I had longoi pi±vate talks with Fuad Hamza and^Thilby. My daughter and I were given the usual presents. The following day special arrangements were made for a Saudi -Arabian Line a aircraft to take us to Dhahran whore we spent the nigho as guests of the United States Consul, Mr. Mel Toy. We returned to Bahrain on the,7th April. Later in the month I paid a brief visit to Kuwait to discuss cases with Jackson who took over as Political Agent from Galloway on the 31st March. I exchanged calls with the Shaikh and also had about an hour's business talk with him. Visitors . Visitors at the Residency during the month have included Bertram Thomas, Ellison, the Political ( Agent at Muscat, who came up at my request to discuss a number of outstanding • cases, and Waterston, the locust expert from the-British Middle East Office, who came to investigate the locust outbreak on the Trucial Coast. / Rela ti ons with India . - B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London.- 2 - Relations with Indi a. The Government of India desire to appoint a Trade Agent at Bahrain and a non-career Vice-Consul at Muscat, and to arrange for their Consul at Basra to be in informal charge of Indian interests in Kuwait. The Shaikh of Bahrain wishes to obtain from His Majesty's Government an assurance of protection against aggression before he will agree to the appointment of an Indian Trade Agent and the Sultan of Muscat has stated his preference for a career Vice-Consul as he is unwilling to accept the only obvious candidate for the appointment of ^ on ' career Vice-Consul, viz. Rai Bahadur Gokuldas. The Shaikh f Kuwait has raised no objection to the arrangement proposed. Orders-in-Council . The new Orders-in-Council for all the Gulf States were brought into force on the 12th April. They embody changes made necessary by the transfer of the control of the Persian Gulf Residency from the Government of India to His Majesty s Government and contain little new matter* An experienced judge is shortly to be appointed as Legal Adviser and Judicial Assistant to the Political Resident to assist in the trial of cases and in dealing with numerous judicial and legal prob lems to which the expansion of the oil industry in the Gull has given rise. Oil . During the month survey parties of the Arabian American Oil Company accompanied by Saudi officials and guards have made serious incursions into Qatar and Abu Dhabi territory. They have penetrated Qatar territory as far north as 25 latitude. They have constructed a road from Salwa to the Khor al ’Odaid, have carried out survey operations in the vicinity of the Khor edh Dhuwaihin andRas as Sila and have established beacons and cairns in the islands nii* this P^ r t of the coast. Their vehicles have been seen in Abu Dhabi territory nearly as far east as Jabal Ali. Stobart, the Poli tical Officer, Trucial Coast accompanied by Shaikh Hazza, brother of the Ruler of Abu Dhabi visited their camps at Sila and south of the Khor edh Ehuwaihin on the 21st April, he found there a Saudi Amir, who said he was acting under the orders of the Amir of Hassa, and a number of armed guards who disarmed some of his men though the arms were subsequently returned through the intervention of some of surveyors. The leader of the survey party stated that the operations were being carried out at the request of the aud Arabian Government. Stobart gave him a letter stating that the camps were in Abu Dhabi territory and asking him to with draw them in order to avoid a collision with the Abu Dhabi tribesmen. A reply was subsequently received from Mr. Ohliger, Vice-President of the Arabian American Oil Company to the effect that the survey parties were acting under the authority of the Saudi Arabian Government, but that in view of the deli cacy of the situation he was arranging to withdraw them. Latest reports show that the camps have been almost comnletely evacuated. Shaikh Hazza has come to Bah-ain and - —ve re ceived written and verbal representations from him asking me that the boundary between Abu Dhabi and Saudi Arabia may be defined and steps be taken to prevent further aggression .from the latter country. The situation regarding off-shore oil off Qatar and Abu Dhabi is most complicated. Sir Hugh Weightman acting on behalf of Trinidad Leaseholds and the Superior Oil Company of America has paid several visits to both places. Although he was fully aware that instructions had been issued to the Rulers not to /commiti /Kuwait. commit themselves he endeavoured to persuade the Ruler of Abu Dhabi to sign an agreement giving his company the first refu sal of the off-shore oil concession on certain stated terms and would have succeeded in doing so but for the personal intervention first of Stobart and then of Felly. Petroleum Concessions Limited who previously had given us to believe that they were not interested in off-shore oil in this area now claim that it is covered by their existing concessions and Lermitte has been busy trying to persuade the Rulers of Abu Dhabi and Qatar to admit this. Abu Dhabi has refused to do so while Qatar has apparently expressed no definite opinion as yet. This state of confusion is largely due to the delay of the Saudi Arabian Government in issuing a proclamation de fining their rights in off-shore oil. It is proposed that after this has been issued the Gulf Rulers should issue simi lar proclamations and they have been instructed not to come to any agreement with any company with respect to off-shore oil until this has been done. In addition to Sir Hugh Weight- man, Bertram Thomas representing Shell has been in Qatar. He appears however to have been very scrupulous in refraining from any endeavour to persuade the Ruler to commit himself and has left for London to obtain instructions from his prin cipals. In view of the fall in the price of oil, the Kuwait Oil Company are gradually slowing down their efforts and reducing their pay-roll. They hope to have their small local refinery completed in July and their pier at Fahahil, which the Shaikh insists on calling Minat al Ahmadi, in September. They have allowed the Shaikh to establish his own police posts under the command of his son Jabir in their camps. This might per haps have been prevented had the company conducted their re lations with the Shaikh through the Political Agent in accor dance with their Political Agreement. The Bahrain Petroleum Company wish to establish electronic survey aid stations in Qatar and on Farsi Island to assist them in the survey of the islands, shoals and waters round Bahrain which are covered by their concession. The Ruler of Qatar is likely to grant permission for the proposed station in his territory but some difficulty arises over Farsi Island which although regarded by us as belonging to Kuwait has re cently been claimed by both Saudi Arabia and Persia. Bahrain . I saw the Shaikh when I took Ellison to call on him and have also met him two or three times at social functions. He is making enquiries about the basis of our jurisdiction in Bahrain over subjects of Qatar, Kuwait and the Trucial States, and will probably ask that this should be ceded to him. He has issued a proclamation forbidding the sale of movable property by Bahrain subjects to foreigners except by the permission in writing of the Bahrain Government. His uncle, Shaikh Muhammad is still in America and his relations consider it rather foolish for such an old man to spend so much time gadding about. We have had a number of social func tions. The Spring Races on the 26th April were attended by a record crowd and the tote paid 25 to 1 on one of the winners. A boxing tournament was arranged by the Arab Club at Muharraq and was attended by the Shaikh and a large audience. The judging and refereeing was done by Anglo-Indian members of my staff and the whole affair which was the first of its kind in Bahrain went off extremely well. At the end of the month the annual exhibition of needlework from the girls’ schools and of various kinds of work from the boys’ schools was held, and was as usual organised extremely efficiently by Mrs. Belgrave. It was visited by large numbers of all classes and many purchases were made.i /Kuwait. 3 commit themselves he endeavoured to persuade the Ruler of Abu Dhabi to sign an agreement giving his company the first refu sal of the off-shore oil concession on certain stated terms and would have succeeded in doing so but for the personal intervention first of Stobart and then of Felly. Petroleum _ Concessions Limited who previously had given us to believe that they were not interested in off-shore oil in this area now claim that it is covered by their existing concessions and Lermitte has been busy trying to persuade the Rulers of Abu Dhabi and Qatar to admit this. Abu Dhabi has refused to do so while Qatar has apparently expressed no definite opinion as yet. This state of confusion is largely due to the delay of the Saudi Arabian Government in issuing a proclamation de- » fining their rights in off-shore oil. It is proposed that after this has been issued the Gulf Rulers should issue simi lar proclamations and they have been instructed not to come to any agreement with any company with respect to off-shore oil until this has been done. In addition to Sir Hugh Weight- man, Bertram Thomas representing Shell has been in Qatar. He appears however to have been very scrupulous in refraining from any endeavour to persuade the Ruler to commit himself and has left for London to obtain instructions from his prin cipals . In view of the fall in the price of oil, the Kuwait Oil Company are gradually slowing down their efforts and reducing their pay-roll. They hope to have their small local refinery completed in July and their pier at Fahahil, which the Shaikh insists on calling Minat al Ahmadi, in September. They have allowed the Shaikh to establish his own police posts under the command of his son Jabir in their camps. This might per haps have been prevented had the company conducted their re lations with the Shaikh through the Political Agent in accor- x dance with their Political Agreement. The Bahrain Petroleum Company wish to establish electronic survey aid stations in Qatar and on Farsi Island to assist them in the survey of the islands, shoals and waters round Bahrain which are covered by their concession. The Ruler of Qatar is likely to grant permission for the proposed station in his territory but some difficulty arises over Farsi Island which although regarded by us as belonging to Kuwait has re cently been claimed by both Saudi Arabia and Persia. Bahrai n. I saw the Shaikh when I took Ellison to call on him and have also met him two or three times at social functions. He is making enquiries about the basis of our jurisdiction in Bahrain over subjects of Qatar, Kuwait and the Trucial States, and .will probably ask that this should be ceded to him. He has issued a proclamation forbidding the sale of movable property by Bahrain subjects to foreigners except by the permission in writing of the Bahrain Government. His uncle, Shaikh Muhammad is still in America and his relations consider it rather foolish for such an old man to spend so much time gadding about. We have had a number of social func tions. The Spring Races on the 26th April were attended by a record crowd and the tote paid 25 to 1 on one of the winners. A boxing tournament was arranged by the Arab Club at Muharraq and was attended by the Shaikh and a large audience. The judging and refereeing was done by Anglo-Indian members of my staff and the whole affair which was the first of its kind in Bahrain went off extremely well. At the end of the month the annual exhibition of needlework from the girls' schools and of various kinds of work from the boys' schools was held, and was as usual organised extremely efficiently by Mrs. BelgraveV It was visited by large numbers of all classes and many purchases were made.4 I thought the Shaikh appeared rather tired and not so jovial as usual when I saw him. He has, however, lost nothing of his astuteness. He is very proud of the new yacht, rather ineptly decorates,-with coronets, which has been presented to ^ him by the American Independent Oil Company. There is at present some small engine trouble but when this has been put right the Shaikh hopes to make a triumphal tour of the Gulf. The Subah case which has been causing much correspondence during the last two years still drags on. It will be remembered that^Subah was accused of murdering three Iraqi subjects in Kuwait territory. According to the Iraqi side of the case, at a meeting held at Basra -the Shaikh’s representatives y agreed that Subah should be exiled for five years. The agree ment was not put into writing and the Shaikh repudiated it saying that his representatives had no authority to make it. Subah is a member of his family and one of his personal adhe rents and he does not wish to loose his support. He now denies that Subah committed the murders and has produced witnesses to the effect that they were committed by two other Iraqis. He is however, willing to pay compensation for the victims provided he is not forced to admit Subah's guilt or alternati vely has offered to have the case settled according to Moham medan, Christian, Jewish or any other kind of law. A few months ago the Shaikh engaged as his chief medical officer an American citizen of Russian extraction recommended to him by the Secretary of the Dutch Reformed Church Mission. The doc tor in question was not a success and his services have been terminated by the Kuwait Government. The Shaikh is now trying to obtain the services of a British doctor through Kemp his representative in London under his oil agreements, but opinion in British circles is that there is so much graft and intrigue rampant that no British doctor would be able to stick it for longer than six months. No Assistant has yet been provided for the Political Agent who is very much overworked. Amongst other things, under the new Order-in-Council he has no less than 7,000 passports to register. The consular work is very heavy in deed and with the withdrawal of all the old hands by the Governments of India and Pakistan his staff is not fully com petent to deal with it. During the month, he has had amongst other things to try three American citizens for breaking into a bedroom and causing grievous hurt to another American citizen. Partly through the efforts of the American Consul from Basra , the case was compounded with the leave of the Court, but • Jordan, the Kuwait Oil Company's general manager and other Americans consider that sentences of imprisonmant should have been awarded. Jordan appears to be under the impression, which ‘I endeavoured to correct, that composition was allowed purely as an act of grace because the accu.So^ Trucial Coast . Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr of Sharjah who was seriously ill and went to Bombay last month for treatment, has been operated on and has telegraphed to me that his health is now good. Shaikh Sultan bin Salim, ex-Ruler of Ras al Khaimah, who shot his way out of the Agency at Sharjah in July, 1948, has made his submission to the Political Agent at Bahrain. He has undertaken to pay a fine and will spend a period of exile in Muscat. The slave traffic on the Trucial Coast still appears to be rampant. Thesiger during his travels saw over 40 persons being led away across the desert in the vicinity of Buraimi and /undergoing5 undergoing brutal treatment. A report has been received that 14 virgins valued at Rs. 10,000 each were recently taken from Dubai to El Khobar in the Shaikh of Dubai f s launch M Joker'. This story is public property but is supported by little tan gible evidence and no particulars of the identity of the abduc ted girls are available. The 'Joker' has been detained at Bah rain pending further enquiries. Shaikh Muhammad bin Saqr who is acting as Ruler of Sharjah in the absence of his brother Sultan, has been successful in releasing four abducted persons. Mr. Waterston, the Locust Expert of the British Middle East Office visited the Trucial Coast during the month and reports that the locust outbreak there is fairly serious. Steps are being taken to deal with it, but there is a certain amount of opposition from the locals who are averse to the destruction of what they regard as a delicacy. Amongst other things they are refusing to allow the use of poison bait which they say will come up next year, in the form of poisonous weeds and kill their camels. Waterston has returned to Cairo and Popov who was in charge of a locust party at Jeddah has now gone to the Trucial Coast to superintend operations. Musca t. The Sultan returned to Muscat from Salalah on the 5th Ap ril. I found him very fit when I saw him at Salalah at the end of March. He then expressed himself as delighted to accept His Majestyls Government's invitation to him to be their guest in the United Kingdom in June, but I have since received a telegram from him that he has found himself compelled to post pone his visit to India and the United Kingdom, and that he will explain the reason to me when I see him. He has re fused to accept a proposal that his son Saiyid Qabus should be educated in a school run by the Society of Friends in the Lebanon as one of the conditions was that the boy should attend the religious services, and has asked that if possible arrange ments should be made for him to be educated at the Victoria College, Alexandria. In a conversation with Ellison, he has said that he wishes to do away with all extra-territorial jurisdiction in Muscat when the present Treaty with His Majesty's Government and the Government of India expires in 1951. When I visited Masirah and Salalah airfields at the end of March I enquired into the extent to which they are used^by civil or foreign aircraft and found that .French military air craft had been using them regularly since December although we had been given to understand that they were only going to perform one flight by this route, and that Ethiopian Airlines use them for a scheduled service between Addis Ababa and Pakistan. Apart from this, they appear to be used almost exclusively by the R.A.F. The Immediate Transport Company at Aden have hitherto been arranging supplies of fuel for Ethiopian Airlines but the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company have now despatched supplies for all civil aircraft to Masirah and these will be issued by the Officer Commanding, R.A.F. there. I found the relations between the R.A.F. officers and the Sultan's officials at both places excellent. Thesiger has returned from his travels which took him from the Trucial Coast west of the Hajar mountains down to the coast opposite Masirah. He reports that south of Ibri ' there is a regular administration run by the Imam from Nizwa’ and that complete security prevails. North of Ibri the tribes acknowledge no overlord and nobody feels safe. Abductions into slavery are carried out even from tribal villages. / ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT .ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT. The situation as regards food grains is much easier and prices are falling. Substantial supplies of wheat illicitly exported from Persia are reaching the Trucial Coast and Qatar and the Shaikhdoms have asked for their supplies of quota wheat to be suspended. Some rice is also arriving from Perdia and the supplies allotted from Egypt are expected very shortly. Lord Inchcape, Chairman of Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Co. Ltd. visited Bahrain during the month. The company propose to establish a shipbuilding yard at Bahrain and are negotiating for a site adjoining the Muharraq causeway. If this project materialises it should prove of the greatest use and bring increased prosperity to Bahrain. The British India mail steamers are erratic as ever. We are accustomed to their arriving late and there is often a good excuse for this, but recently one of the fast mail stea mers dislocated many peoples' arrangements by arriving at and .leaving Bahrain four days ahead of schedule. Dollars are arriving in Bahrain in large quantities from the mainland and the rate is now about Ks.4/- to the dollar. It is reported that Americans from the Arabian Ameri can £»ki Oil Company are purchasing tickets for American airlines at Bahrain with rupees. They cash dollar cheques in the free market and pay for the tickets in rupees at the official rate thereby making a handsome profit. Export of gold via Kuwait to India continues unabated. It is estimated that over six million pounds worth of gold has passed through the place in the last nine months. Mr. Lindsay of Holloway Bros, who recently visited Muscat to investigate the Muscat and Sur water supply schemes has informed me that the latter scheme is entirely practicable and that estimates and plans for it can be prepared at once. He also considers the Muscat scheme practicable but is propo sing to his principals that some test wells should be sunk before further action is taken to make quite sure that the supply of v/ater is adequate. \ (Signed) W. K. HAY.A ^ '9 ft: co nfidential (95/2/49) Dear Burrows, Persian Gulf Residency, • Bahrain. 31st January, 1949. Woexe© p ^ follow ing is a summary of events Bull lor the month of January. ' GENERAL. The Residenc y. li / in the Pe^ian boo a IS 48 I rd Except for two brief visits to Qatar which did not entail On th ln f f W T 7 f ° r the night ’ 1 have spent the month at Bahrain. ls ^. Januar y? 1 held the usual formal New Year's Day re- nnrnhr r» n Wa ? a ! ;tended b Y His Highness the Shaikh with a number of his relatives together with over 250 European and local guests. The function was held in the Royal Navy's cine ma and the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf very kindly pro vided a guard of honour for the Shaikh. After coffee had been fpnpr d i r M Und 1 ma ^ e a short speech and presented Mr. Lermitte, Gener-l Manager of Petroleum Concessions Limited with the M B E which was awarded him in the King's Birthday Honours? “Iter L° S H! a p ter ., and inc ? nse had bee n passed round the party adjourned f R fh lden ° y where refreshments were served. As usual at this MnL£ f M^ he «/ ea ^ W ® h ? V ? £ ad nume rous visitors. These have in- Vmh d =c„ M ' ^ 0 ?f iS0 ?l lst Secretary Information to the Baghdad Cailo Fmh a ?=„ hlS M Wlf » e »’ a ' d Mr ‘ Audsle y&gt; Labour Counsellor to the Cairo Embassy. Mr. Morrison spent about a week here, giving us advice and assistance in our Public Relations work aAd^xatofn? R a h 7 &lt; ? 6 Pr l ° P ° S ? 1 /? r establishing a broadcasting station at B n? r e ln ' &lt; - Mr ‘ Audsle y arrived towards the end of the month several days studying conditions in the Bahrain Pet- S any ? C n mp at Awali and Petraeum Development (Qatar) Limited's Camp in Qatar. He expects to go on to Kuwait earlv struction^f th Clerk of .^°rks has arrived to supervise the con- materl?? h f h he new n Residency buildings and a small amount of yet ?c?iau| slalted! “ th6 SPOt bUt thS WOrk haS not Visit of Comman der-in-Chlef E^st Indies. in H M C -?- L : Wccdbouse, C.B., flying his flag In H.M.S. Norfolk arrived at Bahrain on the 6th January and oQcip^fnnpf Cal ^- S were exchanged and numerous dinner held durin g visit. The Shaikh gave a of nffn-S ty r ^ h iu honour &gt; which was also attended by a number f ^° m , the U * S * S * ,Ta rawa', but on account of ill-health wMrh n h er h d H C K 0r s orders was unable to attend a tea party to dav of h the a L b?en il nV:L ^ e ^ 0n b0ard the ’Norfolk’ on the last thot Admira i s visit. The Commander-in-Chief informed-me Gulf tn t : h f Pr ?^? ed withdraw H.M.S. 'Loch Quoich’ from the nnr f ei n th u middlQ of March so -that we shall be left with only H M thG 8n ^ ° f April when H.M.S. 'Wren* and Chief'q ^pected. No details of the Commander-in month prp^f/^f f° ^ UW 5 ib which took place towards the end of the January! 7 ^ t0 hand * HQ WaS dUQ t0 Vlsit Musoat on the 31st R elations, with the TT t S - q - T/iaif 4-^ T 5 e u U, ? ,S j, aircraft carrier ’Tarawa’ paid an operational ^Norfolk’ was a herf r ° m T the h th ^ January while H.M.S. .na u Wa3 1 ex changed calls with the Captain and he and a number of officers including Mr. Me.Uoy, the acting /united » B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London*■i 5 C^) t^L^ ee ? suggested to the Sultan for the appointment Adminis- ■:°f’ Gw 2“ ur a nd he has announced his intention of reaching a decision after Woods-Ballard-s arrival. There has been a good o nt o f ,..? orres P 0 udence with the Sultan about the request by a ?? ut the renewal of their authorisation to fly thp fc - e r rl - 0ry . and land at Masirah in an emergency, and V p he Sultan is trying to get his 'pound of flesh' out of the Company in the way of authorisation fees. , \ hfugtigg, when he visited Muscat (vide under J 0il' on 0 the R f J'? W 4 n Tr a 1 D ® ? av if and Raplde which landed and took off H\V ala V- d ^ ground without any great diffi- culty though the surface is reported to be not too good. The in^ t T a h 1 ’ Cra f t to use the landing ground was a Dakota in 1946 it d took a off! &gt;een t0ld that “ ° nly JUSt oleared the WHs when ECONOMIC SnPPT.KMKUT fi.ir ct- tons of Egyptian rice have been allocated to the Guif States excluding Kuwait for the first six months of 1949 sntiQf 1 ^^ 10 ” of . 2 »°P 0 tons of this to Bahrain has caused great pensive t Kuwa?)- r t« e f haS hf 0 f 1 f ng been scarce M d extremely S e x- pensive. Kuwait is to obtain her share from a large allocqtion made to a number of Middle East countries jointly fnd it is not yet known how much she will get. 13 noz ^ he Sultan of Muscat has agreed to Messrs. Holloway th t °u herS P ro PJ &gt; sals for a preliminary survey on the spot before Muscn^and^ur 18113 ^ estimates for water supply schemes at r • J 1 thj ; rci nBM bo ^t has now been put on the Gulf run pnd Lch directi on ^I'n^fntM 1 ' 6 Sh ° U ^ be a b0at ° alli ^ i« Muscat^n f a ,•} “ r f c tron in future roughly once every 17 days. I am also consider^furthpv ltlSh Ind i Q .Steam Navigation Company propose to o fast Lf? =f er a r ? q uest that arrangements should be made for time when thev h^vp hV' 11 at Mus f at &gt; ln three or f °ur months' crii? ^ W i Gn ^ he y^} lave hnd some experience of the working of the new month? 163 f ° r theSS b ° atS introd uced at the beginning of this (Signed) W. R. HAY.Persian G-ulf Residency, Bahrain. Confidential . 5th January, 19^9. (v/M) Jfi Jt 1 ‘'T 6200 Dear Burrows, The following is a summary of Gulf for the month of December. GENERA L■ Tours . I returned to Bahrain from Muscat on the ^th Decem ber and left in H.M.S. Wild Goose for Kuwait on the 12th De cember accompanied by my wife and daughter. I exchanged calls vith^ the Shaikh and had one long business talk with him and I received calls from the local notables and. leading British and American business men. We were taken round the Kuwait Oil Com pany's camp and port and the oil fields and my wife visited the American Mission Hospital. There was the usual round of parties including three Arab meals. We returned to Bahrain by air on the 18th December. On the 28th December I paid a visit to Hr. Max ihornburgh on the is],and of Umm as Saba* an which was presented to him by the late Shaikh Hamad. He has built hi. self quite a nice house there where he lives quite simply, and nothin the more than orien'eal splendour which the American journalists would, have one believe. His latest scheme is to tap artesian water in the shoals north of the main Bahrain is- -i-pnd, pump it up to the high ground at Rlfa.a and then distri bute it over certain large areas of fertile land which are at present uncultivated owing to lack of water. To obtain the funds for this measure, he proposes that the royalty payable by tne Bahrain Petroleum Company should be increased by 100 or 150 per cent which explains why he 1s not very popular with the Company. Gulf Islands . X The Persians after keeping silent for a number of years are taking interest again in certain of the Gulf islands, xhey have made an approach regarding Tamb, which we regard as belonging to Has al Khalmah, and Abu Musa, which we regard as belonging to Sharjah, through diplomatic channels, and have coyered the ^ right beacon on Farsi island, with the words x ersian soil 1 ' and put up a brass plate on the island with the same inscription. We have hitherto treated, this island as bel onging to Kuwait, but Saudi Arabia has also claimed it. So far as is known, the Persians have not previously claimed it in spite of its name. Civil Aviation . Instructions have been receved regarding the new v ir a £ reements which are to be negotiated with the naikhs of Kuwait and Sharjah. The existing Kuwait agreement nas actually lapsed, but the Shaikh has agreed that it should be regarded as remaining in force unofficially until a new agreement can be negotiated. He has been approached by Trans worlo. Air Lines for permission for their service from Cairo to Bombay to call at Kuweit instead of Basra, but has not commited himself. He is very anxious for improved air ccmmu- B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., -/nications with - w j x_j o M • j Foreign Office, LONDON.nioatione with Kuwait. At Bahrain, more thfin 400 aircraft a , month are now usin^ the Muharraq aerodrome. Indian G-oodwill Mission . ^ An Indian Goodwill Missior. consisting of Mr. C,S. Jha, J.d.E., I.C.S., and Professor Muhammad Habib, visited the Gulf at very short notice in the middle of the month. They were on their way back to India from Paris where they had been attending the meetings of the United Nations 1 Assembly. Thev daye 3ahrain end 3 days at Kuwait. I had a talk w„,.th them at the latter place, and they said that they had come primarily to study the conditions under which Indians were w 0 rKing in the o^l companies with a view to stotrolng emigration lf circumstances appeared to justify such a step. They informed me tnat they^were delighted to f 1 nd the situation much better jhan the Inolah Press had led them to believe, but even so mS d a &gt; 4 ni i mber of improvements to suggest d'epacially at Kuwait. ey/interviews with the Shaikhs at both places, and presented them with addresses, and the Shaikh of Bahrain delighted them by giving them swords and A^ab dresses though they thought it unlikely that the Government of Indie would let them keep these, ine Political Agents looked after them very well and I think bhey T^ere fully satisfied with the reception accorded, them. Oil. I u is reported that the American Independent Oil Oompany have been out-bid by another Company fgr the Saudi Arab share of the Neutral Zone. It appears that the Saudi Arab Government are now in no hurry to dispose of the conces- sion ±or their share of the Neutral Zone, and are taking a cer- o.'.n amount of malicious pleasure in observing the embarrass ment which this is causing to the Shaikh of Kuwait. The lat ter s efforts to let the American Independent Oil Company get away with a concession for three islands which are not mentio ned in the Kuwait Oil Compen's lease having failed, the Ameri- can ^independent Oil Company have little to do except watch the ohaikh enj-oy their dollars, and their survey ship the 'Badawi ,! is r yin p, -die. Or. Morris, the Company's representative in Kuwait, together with Mr. Brookes, who I understand played a prominent 'cc* the formation of the Company, came to see me while I was in Kuwait, but made no attempt to discuss business and confined themselves to polite platitudes. ^ Kuwait Oil Company have made great progress in their^construction programme during the last-few months. Ah mad! is expanding very rapidly, and many houses have now been completed. The wharf and topping plant at Fahahil are expec ted to be ready at the end of June. The Company then propose to dispense with the services of the Bechtel Corporation as they cannot afford the dollar payments involved. The cost of the wharf which was expected to be about 10 million dollars is working out at nearly 20 million dollars. 7 Mr - Bertram Thomas, who is now working for Shell, arrived in Bahrain during the month. His visit had to be post poned owing to illness, and he is still in poor health. He vi sited the Trucial Coast Shaikhs to renew his acquaintance with them, and is now at Kuwait, where it is believed, he is proposing to sound the Shaikh on the subject of the continen tal shelf. ^ ho P e which I expressed in my last summary that ' .Petroleum Concessions Limited would now be able to go ahead with their current season's programme' of exploration in- 3 - Bur^imi and the Dhahira.h, has been rudely shattered, as al most immediately after I left Muscat, the Sultan Tyrote to Bird askings that all work in the area should be suspended for a year. Apparently he had received an unsatisfactory letter from Shaikh Sa.qr bin Sultan of the Na * im. Bird hopes to go and see the Sultan during January, and if -oossible to take Saqr with him, and it remains to be seen whether the Sultan can be persuaded to change his mind. In any case exploration in the area is a yery tricky business as the Sultan has no real control over the tribes, and I have suggested to Bird, that he should ask the Sultan tentatively whether he would agree to the raising of some local guards. Persian G-ulf Ligh t ing Servioa . *flt is honed that from the beginning of 194° it will possible to arrange for the recovery of lighting ^uec from shipping which does not enter the Shatt-al-Arab. I tackled ^he Shaikh of Bahrain about his 'strong protest', on this sub- vOct and he first of all said that he was referring to s thing quite different. Eventually it transpired ti-iot no cme- uhat he was ight to the Persian G-ulf Lighting no unwilling to concede the _ Service to recover a 'tax' in his waters, but would have no objection if some other word were used. Steps are being taken to explain the situation tc the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait officially, and. obtain their concurrence in what is proposed. Bahrain . (D I had a long interview wit' the Shaikh shortly before Christmas, and in addition to the question of lighting dues, discussed with him his request for a guarantee of protection against aggression, and the proposal to appoint a British Principal of the Teachers 1 Training School at Bahrain. He had originally asked for a written assurance that we did not re cognise the Persian claim to Bahrain, but h^s now shifted his grounds and asked, for a general assurance, of protection, and also a Promise that we will safeguard the interests of his sub jects in foreign countries. The last assurance against aggres sion was given in 1861, and. his' request for its renewal is not unreasonable. It is not clear what is at the back of his mind with regard, to his second reouest, and it may be that he is thinking of the claims of Bahrain subjects in Qatar. The whole matter has been referred to The Shaikh noted down the name of the educational appointment and. I ther onthe subject shortly. His Majesty^ G-overnment. the candidate proposed for hope to hear from him fu*- 11 The Shaikh has been having trouble with his rela tions who have been demanding increased allowances in view of he constant rise in the cost of living, and the number of their dependents. After a certain amount of recrimination, he hag increased the Civil List by Rupees °^—i S 0 f rni t-tttT y Sir Evan Jenkins, Deputy Chairman of the Eastern Bank, visited Bahrain during the month and spent two nights in the Residency. He expressed himself well satisfied with -^0 progress being made by the- local branch of the bank. K uwait t „ . 1 saw p good deal of the Shaikh while I was at Kuwait. iG 18 d oin g too much work, and it is reported, that his blood pressure is showing a tendency to rise. He neany died of coronary thrombosis in 1Q42, and his life cannot be regarded as a good. one. If he were to die suddenly, it is quite possi ble th^t the succession would be disputed, and that there would /bebe some disorder, and I heve esked. the Political Agent to let me have an appreciation on the subject* ^ I discussed with‘the Shaikh the Question of the ap pointment of British Advisers, unfortunately just before I had received instructions from the Foreign Office on the sub- ject. He enquired rather peevishly, why I was always putting his matter up, and said that if we gave him an order he would of course obey it, but that he did not think the time was yet ~ ' 1; ^ 8 U8U£, 1 0 byle. He went on to say that he w«s doubling' the number of his police, and that he had obtained tnu service# of two British-trained police officers from Pales- tine. He also informed, me that he was opening a new passport office on the 1st January. ^be Kuwait Oil Comoanv credited the Shaikh’s account with royalty amounting to 40 lakhs in June. After a time t^is was transferred to the Finance Department, but up to cate they have onlv erent 10 l*khs out of it. A further Payment of royalty amounting to 60 or ?0 lakhs is expected in the very near future. The 7,875,000 dollars received from the American independent Oil Company have been credited to the Finance De partment . Up to dote only 5^5,000 dollars of this has been spent on 2,000 tons of rice ordered from Brazil. ^ -'be Shaikh has asked that verv earlv steps may be taken to demarcate his southern boundary. He is of the opin ion that Ibn Baud’s health is failing and fears that after his ^e^th he is Likely to find the Saudi Arab authorities less accomvodating. He ha.s also said that he would welcome a teer^i—‘ tonal division of the Neutral Zone. Qatar . ‘7 Shaikh Abdullah has nominated his eldest son, Shaikh All, as his heir-apparent in place o^ his second son, Shaikh a mac, who died last May and has obtained the approval of his relations and the leading notables in writing to this appoint- ment. He is also reported to have designated Kha.lifah, the third son of the late Ha.mad, as the next in succession, which can hardly be regarded as a verv wise move. Trucial Coast . ^ Air Commodore Towsey and a party of officers of the Middle East Command, visited the Trucial boast.during the month to examine the question of protection in that area. It is understood that their opinion was that it would net be neces sary to locate any kind of force there until oil is proved. ihe^present position is not satisfactory, and on two occasions .unng the month, the Beni Qitab have fired, shots in the direc- ^ . on of G-overnment officers or oil company personnel. These incidents need not be taken too seria sly, 'but give some indi- cation of the lawlessness which prevails, and it is almost cer tain that sooner or later we shall find ourselves compelled to locate a force in the area. Muscat . , -^be case of Hay a tun, who was believed to have commi tted some six or seven murders, some in Gwadur territory and some in Mekran, is still unsettled. It is being found difficult 0 n I’ing him to trial for the GSwadur murders, partly on pro cedural grounds and partly because the witnesses from Gwadur territory refuse to come to Muscat. The Pakistan authorities ^bat he should be tried at Gwadur for some of the Mekran murders by a. Council of Elders, and a reply has been sent to them that no provision has been made for this /procedureHMM © £t-s&gt; - 5 - procedure In the Muscat Order-in-Ccuncil. ECONOMIC. 1° Good rain has now fallen in all the Gulf States. M 18 E «°uld ensure adequate grazing, but it has come too late ^o produce the truffles which the Arabs are always so fOnd of talking about. , Bahrain Tare had a s-oell of unusually severe cold at the end of the month and the sea was full of dead fish, ^^-huch anxiety was caused by the refusal of the Iraqi Government to ipermit the release of wheat for the Gulf States from the udhO' 7 °V ooe ' 8 stocks at Basra. We have now heard from s najes y s Embassy, Baghdad, that the Iraqi Government have agreeo to stocks being released for another six months, but for some reason or other, it arrears that the Trucial Coast's quota is stiLl hold un. ^ Ri ce is now trickling into the Gulf States from Pakis- 1 1 ' . ^ c - u0U ^ Vl America, and a large consignment from Bra zil is shortly expected at Kuwait. As a.result/ the nrice has fallen somewhat. The Political Agent, Muscat, reports that rice and other commodities from hard currency countries are reaching Muscat from Aden. • Trr11 , ^ Whil 2 h^wait, I had a talk with Haji Ahmad, the poat builder who figures in Villier's book 'The ’ or J s p inead 1 . He said that trade by countrycraft is in a cr\ Y i-Z 8 '' is now building nothing. Practically ^±1 thu carrying trade is now being handled by steamers. Each jCcan going countrycraft requires a crew of from to 40 ^nd ine cost of feeding the men in these days is so great, that * W^\mr ?? in taking ^ henrt0 sea - Only lo or 12 booms + *rnr&lt; JX f l A hl8 s f ?son , cargoes of dates. They were dee- Bom **y '* hQ re they would sell some of the dates and buy AdPn h ona T,mre 4 . tllef5 i. fr0IT1 there tlney would So on to Mukalia, a on the Afr ‘ioan coast where they would sell more hn-' rX and thGy ' v ' rould finally sell the tiles at Zanzibar and tlat in gr X?f?° le ^ tG brin ^ b?ck t0 Gulf. It is understood cuifV 1 ^ ^ tl0n to ^? he rea8on s given by Haji Ahmad, the diffi- deelinp f n? b ^ a ' J '? 1 ^^? lber fr ° m India ie also heading to the oeoline of boat-building industry at Kuwait. y. n ,M The 1 f ck of l ? 00d hotel accommodetlon at Bahrein end rugby an tJi ° U t d ’’ PWDPck - At Bahrain, a hotel which waa n „ Ha O' l . n T , Indlar! ’ hpa recently been closed by the State doctor •dl° of r-v! y X r ' 0Un h • At Kuwait, there is one hotel in the mid-- n^sed tn h ' tow n yhich is run by a local merchant, and- is peiro- benter T-t- 0 ^ 1 a + n 4 . e H Gnt ‘-■uropeans for lack of anything o' U' , ' 18 stated that both in Bahrain and Kuwait, some of inA SH ° har - t3 pre oonsidering building a hotel on modern enterorlse g f” 0tS that milit stes against such an enborprxse is the existence of prohibition in both olaces. h? ' L * 11 T 1 a H do dn via' Kuwait has recently dwindled apparently owing to a shortage of supolies. The gold is iiiemb- mhe ydv®! lnt0 Xn *f? Pnd ' many ot the Kuwait merchants have ' which rd i g v pr H lts - “ appears that payment for the gold how made througridenf rCm Svltzerlf&gt;nd yip Lebanon, is some! ^There Kuwait ; because cently obtained fo be of little balloon tyres. little market for British cars in is at present the roads are too_ bad. Twelve trucks were re- from the - ord works at Dagenham', but were found use as the wheel rims were too narrow to take (W.R. HAY)Confidential. Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. 9th December, 1948. Dear Burrows, ' t t The following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf for the month of November. GENERAL . Royal Family . The birth of a son to Her Royal Highness Princess Elizabeth was welcomed with unfeigned delight throughout the Gulf States. The Shaikh of Bahrain immediately sent telegrams to His Majesty the King and Her Royal Highness, and called at the Residency to express his congratulations. His Majesty’s Ships which were present at Bahrain fired a royal salute. A large comet which appeared in the sky at the time of the Prince's birth was interpreted by many of the people as a happy augury for his future. A pair of drop pearl earrings has recently been forwar ded to Her Royal Highness Princess Elizabeth as a wedding‘present from the Gulf Rulers. The pearls-were obtained locally and were set with platinum and diamonds in London. A signed letter of thanks has been received from Her Royal 'Highness and its contents are being communicated to the Rulers. Persi an Gulf Li ghting Service . A meeting of the local Persian Gulf Lighting Service Com mittee was held at Bahrain on the 13th November. This was the 5th meeting of this committee to be held locally, but no orders have yet been received from the Ministry of Transport on the va rious recommendations that have been made. Tour s . (97/4/48) At the beginning of the month I paid a visit to Cairo where I stayed with Sir John and nady Troutbeck. I attended a Commander-in-Chief's conference at Fayyid in order to discuss the question of the despatch of military assistance to the Gulf States in an emergency. While in Cairo I had useful conversations with members of the British Middle East Office and His Majesty’s Embassy, and with the British Council representatives. Wakelin of the British Council took me to see the Kuwait hostel where 49 students are accommodated. I found a very good spirit pre vailing there, and I understand the boys keep themselves aloof from Egyptian politics. During my return journey I spent two nights at Habbaniyah as a guest of Air Vice Marshal J.N. Booth- man*, C.B., D.F.Cc, A.F.C. He very kindly arranged for me to visit Baghdad where I lunched with the Ambassador and Lady Mack and had useful talks with members of the Embassy staff. I was also given an opportunity of renewing my acquaintance with Saiyid Ali Hijazi, the Iraqi Director General of Police who was the officer in charge of the Gendarmerie at Arbil when I was Political Officer there in 1920. After leaving Habbaniyah, I spent one night in Kuwait where I discussed outstanding ques tions with the Political Agent and exchanged calls with the Ohaikh. /On B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London./ x Page 2. On the 21st November, I left for Muscat in the '•Nearchus' with my wife and daughter after having r been held up for two days by inclement weather. We spent from the 25th to the 28th November at Muscat, and the two following days on the Batinah coast. There was the customary round of parties at Mus cat. The Sultan entertained Ellison and myself to lunch, and '^himself dined at the Agency. We were given the usual heavy and sticky tea parties by Rai Bahadur Gokaldass, the leader of the Hindu community and Haji Bhacker, the leader of the Khoja commu nity, and were also entertained to tea and tennis at the Con sulate Club. On the Batinah coast we were entertained by the Sultan’s Walls at Khaburah, Sohar and Shinas, and I received deputations from the Kohja community at Khaburah. and the Hindu communities at Sohar and Shinas. At Sahara we paid a visit to Miss Hosman, a dissident from the Dutch Reformed Church Mission, who runs a female dispensary there with the assistance of an American nurse. There has been heavy rain recently on the Bati nah coast, and the country inland from the gardens, which is in many places quite thickly covered with trees, was delightfully green. During the course of our voyage in the 'Nearchus', we also, visited the Qais light vessel and the Quoin and Tamb light houses. The Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah's agent at Tamb island did not appear to think much of his new master, Saqr bin Muhammad, and complained that all the Jowasim Shaikhs suffered alike from avarice, though he admitted that Shaikh Saqr treated his sub jects somewhat better than his predecessor. Bahrain . The Shaikh has written rather a foolish letter to the Political Agent entering a strong protest against the proposal to levy light dues on ships in his ports without his consent. The proposal in question has not finally been approved by His Majesty's Government. He has also turned down a proposal which was supported by his Adviser, Belgrave. to appoint a British Principal of the local Teachers’ Training Centre, but I am hop ing to discuss this matter with him further. It is reported that Russian broadcasts in Arabic are being heard three times a day in Bahrain. They are violently anti-British and find a number of listeners. The Arabic is poor and it is suspected that the broadcaster is not an Arab. It is also said that 'Al Arab' a newspaper published by Yunis Bahari in Paris which is very anti-British in tone is obtaining a certain amount of circulation‘through a local book-seller. The Mission of the Dutch Reformed Church of America held its annual meeting at Bahrain and amongst those who atten ded it was Mr. John Van Ess from Basra. He is now 72 years old and expects to return to America for good next year. At his request I had two long talks with him. He said he wanted to ask me a number of questions but spent most of the time propounding his own theories, which in spite of his disclaiming as a missio nary any interest in politics, were all concerned with that subject. His opinion is that pan-Islam is a spent force poli tically, that the present wave of political nationalism in Mid dle East countries will soon be exhausted and that in due course their administration and development will be taken over by the oil companies much in the same way as the East India Company took over the government of India. His advice to the British was to be 'tough' in their dealings with Middle East poten tates and governments. Kuwait. When I exchanged calls with the Shaikh at Kuwait on the 11th November, I found him as usual in very good spirits.Page 3, I did not talk business to him beyond referring vaguely to the drinking water question 9 with regard to which the Shaikh, earlier in the year, had promised me that he would place an immediate order for a distillation plant. He has gone back on his word because, apparently, he still hopes ^ that the Oil Company will find an adequate supply of water for him at Dibdibah in the extreme west of his territory. I did not mention the question of advisers but hope to take up the subject with him once more when I pay a longer visit to Kuwait next month. A recent approach by the Political Agent was met with the usual excuses for inaction. The Iraqi Government are again taking an inte rest in Umm Qasr and I was told by His Majesty*s Embassy at Baghdad that they expect to receive a note on the sub ject shortly. The discovery of oil near Zubair has made its early development as a port a matter of importance and the Director General of Ports and Navigation, Basra, has informed me that he wishes to put up tide gauges in its approaches, whict lie largely within Kuwait limits, at an early date. The de marcation of the Kuwaiti-Iraqi frontier has now become a mat ter of urgency, and the Political Agent has been asked to as certain from the Shaikh whether he agrees that the Iraqi Go vernment should again be asked to accept the line proposed ho them in 1940. Sir Hugh Weightman, representing Trinidad Leaseholds and the Superior Oil Company, was staying at the Agency during my visit to Kuwait, waiting for permission to approach the Shaikh for an oil concession in his s' are of the sea-bed off the Neutral Zone. He had been told in Jeddah that if he was successful in obtaining the concession for the Kuwait share he would be favourably considered for the Saudi Arab share. Ho was subsequently allowed to approach the Shaikh after the lat ter had been informed that a further communication will be made to him about the whole subject of the sea-bed and asked to be non.-committal if^ie received any approach regarding it in the meanwhileThe Shaikh gave Weightman as favourable a reply as was possible in the circumstances. .ucan r Independent Oil Company have failed to obca: Ibn Saudis share of the Neutral Zone, and Amer :1 j s ion have come to some clandestine agreement with the the ccncc: appear to Shaikh to him but ui Kuwait Oi shin called the i! 3adawi' ;: which they are bringing out, original! with the wa oer s, i. &lt; surround: exploit J’ubbar and two other islands which belong to infer tunately are not shown in the map attached to the i Oenroanvs concession. They want to use a survey Intention of surveying the Neutr. 'or the purpose of surveying thes* .ngs. il Zone territoria Islands and their The great increase in the foreign population at Kuwait is giving rise to many problems. It is reckoned that by the end of the year, the Kuwait Oil Company will be employing over 1600 British European subjects, over 800 Americans and over 6,000 Indians and Pakistanis.- This involves the Political Agen cy in a mass of consular and routine work and an increase oi staff has become urgently necessary. Criminal cases which nave to be tried by the Political Agent under the Kuwait Order--in- Council are growing in number and one of the most pressing ques tions is the provision of suitable ac ^mmodation for prisoners. Recourse can scarcely be made to the Kuwait Government's prisons as their w^uhuds of dealing with criminals savour of the mid dle ages. vember The U.S.S. 'Maruy' carry out a survey arrived at Kuwait on the 3rd Po of the waters off the Kuwait coast / shePage 4 She is being assisted by a number of smaller vessels and by air craft. Qatar . Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited have now erected a jetty at the new port which they are developing at Umm Said. The first visit to this port by an ocean-going vessel - Messrs. Strick Scotts 1 'Reglstan' - was made in the middle of the month. Muscat. I found the Sultan in very good spirits when I visited Muscat and we both had a great deal to talk about. He hopes to visit Bombay in May to obtain medical advice and to go on from there to the United Kingdom. He has asked for assistance in ar ranging for the education of his only son, Saiyid Qabus, who is now 9 years old and lives in Dhofar, either in the Lebanon or Egypt. He has been much distressed by the reports of the severe damage caused to his property in Dhofar by a heavy storm which occurred there on the 24th October and wishes to visit that plac^ for a fortnight in the latter half of February to survey the damage and arrange for repairs. I asked him whether he still had plans for bringing the interior of Oman under his control and he replied that he was waiting for the Imam to die and that he was hopeful that the tri bes would then ask him to become their ruler. Meanwhile he has gone a considerable way in establishing his control over the Dhahirah, a tract at the northern end of Oman bordering on the Trucial Coast Shaikhdoms, and has opened up a road for cars through the Wadi al Jizzi. Bird of the Petroleum Concessions Li mited has recently visited him and made his peace with him. The Sultan was much annoyed with him for dealing direct with one of the Shaikhs in the Buraimi area contrary to a promise which he had given. It is hoped that Petroleum Concessions Limited will now be able to carry out their current season^ programme of ex ploration in Buraimi and the Dhahirah without trouble to them selves and without treading on the Sultan’s toes. The Imam, though he has often been reported to be at death’s door, unfor tunately still seems full of life and has gone off to visit Ja’alan in order to settle a dispute between the tribes there. The Sultan is developing a strong bias against Pakis tan, probably as a result of the rather aggressive attitude they have shown towards Gwadur, and is anxious that in his territory, Indian Muslims, Christians, or Hindus should be employed in pre ference to Pakistanis. So far as Gwadur is concerned, he con tinues to press for the early taking over of the Post and Tele graph office by Cable &amp; Wireless and, with regard to some land which the Pakistan Director General of Posts and Telegraphs appa rently wishes to acquire from him at Gwadur, he has said that, if necessary, he is willing to make it over to His Majesty’s Government, but that he will not let the Pakistan authorities have it. The Sultan has agreed that French military aircraft may use the Masirah and Salalah airfields for a period of three months but insists that some formal agreement should be reached with him if their use of these airfields is to be continued for a lor^e-r period. His main idea is to obtain some financial consideratioi The State is a poor one and he has to make the most of any oppor tunity that offers itself of making money. The failure of Pet roleum Cone essions- Limited’s survey party to discover any oil in Dhofar has come as a bitter blow to him, and he is pressing that the Company should abandon its concession there so that he may try his luclk elsewhere. / ECONOMIC .' ■ *‘41 WITH CONFIDENT! AS OF THE UNDER-SECRETARY OF STATE # FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS Foreign Office, FILE COPY 357371 ' ' t. C onfidential . (9 7/8/48 ). r l i i '.?V TC/i 3 ' t Persian Gulf Residency. . Bahrain, v ID 29th October, 1948. dear Burrows The following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf for the month of October. / v . G SNEKAL. ' I arrived in Bahrain on the 9th October and took over charge of Che Residency from Galloway who left the next day for •i .uwait in Ji.f.b. 'Wr^D.' . He took over charge as Political Agent hreru .from Andrew who has left for the Lebanon on a fortnight’s .l ocal leave. Moody the Residency Surgeon who visited England j or a few weeks- to discuss future quarantine and medical arrange- nits in the Gulf returned to Bahrain on the 30th October. Pelly, the Political Agent, Bahrain, took a fortnight’s local leave in fersi, during the month. Horner, the Assistant Resident Engineer, inis try of Works, has recently undergone an operation for append! c- ieis and is being granted two months leave in the United Kingdom to convalesce. ^On my return from leave 1 found little change in the guneral^situation in the Gull. In the Residency the conversion bo Foreign Gifice procedure is pursuing an orderly course and me have now adopted the Foreign Office filing system. fahrain, J 1 exchanged calls with His Highness Shaikh Salman on hjs return and also paid the usual call on the Id-ul Adha. I found him in very much better health am/ spirits than when I left in July. The only public matter which he took up with me in th, course of conversation was the shortage of rice. He did not mention Zubafat/and I understand from Polly that he has not done so ior a long time. He is presumably awaiting with high hopes the result of his representation to the Secretary of State, on the occasion of the Id 1 also called on His Highness’ two uncles ohaikh Muhammad and Shaikh Abdullah. The former is not in good health and is shortly leaving for Bombay where he hopes to benefit from the change of climate. His son Shaikh Khalifah*is lull of praise for the arrangements made for his visit to the United Kingdom made by the British Council and is enthusiastic aoout the efficiency of the British Police. He enjoyed his visit to Scotland more than any other feature of his tqur. Shaikh ibduilah, when I saw him, expressed great concern over the Palestine situation. This matter still causes grave concern to many local Arabs, but with the passage of time the feeling about it is probably not quite as strong as it was, and there has been no reflection in/ Bahrain of the persecution of Jews in Iraq. A committee with James Belgrave, the son of the Financial Adviser, as Secretary is at present busy collecting clothes for the Palestine * 4 rab refugees in Iraq. 4His Highness has been recently given to the Persian a statement of Hi order that he may somewhat perturbed by the publicity claim to Bahrain and has asked for Ma j e s ty’s Govc rnment’s attitude in writing ia use it to counteract local rumours and agitation ‘ • d-k • B. Burrows The-Foreign London. / Its 2 It hrs been docided to givQ hin only a verbal assurance as he might make embarrassing use of a v/rittun one. Meanwhile it has cone to his notice that his Shiah subjects when visiting the- boly pi 'Ces in Irad travel via Persia and obtain identity certificates and ’other travel documents there', as they find that for some reason or other this facilitates their 'movements in raa. he has accordingly issued a public notice forbidding this oractice. .. uwa j 1^. f On the 17th October, r widen end ■jr.it Oil. C omp a n y left Kuwait fo r Riy r bn S aud for a con rk /-&gt; CL ! o s ion for 1 his shar G Of -.noth ■jr roprose nta tiv e of the ■ Company, Dr. limse If in-Kuwa it a nd is busy m .king a rrang !.. i s hm on t of an off ice th .re. presentatIves of the ^merican adh to negotiate tl.;&gt; Neutral Morris ha ments for ; with hone. installed the ostab- L u Kmvaiti subject employed as Jornpany vehicle has complained that ' 1 e was stopped by an Iraqi armoured car territory and e a 1* Oiled after being warned not to driver of a Kuwait Oil irds the end of September well within Kuwait was eventually allowed to proceed )Cen brought to the notice oJ frucial Coast. mention His the incident. The matter has .j esty’s Embassy, Baghdad. and h- quiet 7 Sh ikh Sa’id of Dubai has been on a visit,to Bahrain been staying with Shaikh Salman. He reports that all is t present on the Trucial Coast. Shaikh Sultan bin Salim ex-ruler of Has -1 Khaim.ah, who in July last, refused to accompany Polly from Sharjah to Bahrain and shot his way out of the Political Officer’s house has Id eon in Muscat where he has requested the Sultan to intercede for him. The Sultan has asked ■hat he may be- given safw conduct to Bahrain in order to discuss rm s Case with, the Political .-Agent. The reply to be given to the Sultan is at present under consideration and meanwhile Shaikh Sultan has left Muscat and is believed to have returned to his lair near tha Wadi al Saur. Muscat. ^ ' fbe Sultan has agreed to appoint Mr. V/oods-Ballard, C.I.E., 0•e•E., late of the Indian Political Service as his.Minister of foreign affairs, and Woods-BaHeard has accepted the appointment, .1though a formal contract has not yet been signed. Woods-Ballard, ifter interviewing the Sultan has returned to the United Kingdom where it is proposed that he should study ^rabic for a few months '•nd then return to Muscat to take up his appointment. Meanwhile h,. has undertaken to perform a few chores for the Sultan in London ad in particular is being asked to interview certain firms with a view to the appointment of one of them as purchasing agents for Muscat and also to place an order for equipment for the Muscat infantry. ^ _ The Pakistan Government recently asked for the Sultan's permission to be obtained for the visit of a warship and of a military road reconnaissance party to Gwadur, the former at 24 hours notice. The Sultan sHd he had no objection to the warship visiting Gwadur territorial waters provided that no party went ashore but that he preferred that the reconnaissance party should not enter Gwadur territory. It is not yet known whether the warship actually * visited Gwadur or not. The Sultan appears to be alarmed by the in lorest shown by Pakistan in Gwadur and is now pressing strongly for Cable &amp; Wireless to take over the Gwadur Post Office which'isHe \-’.t present being Administered by the Phkistnn authorities. vn.3. formerly lukcwar.: about this prop os 1. ..ii u t j ' i D. /0 Th nths ago a nurnbe d so far .1 esty f S' t&gt; oiai.nJ.y - case of Hayatun who was arrested in Gwadur a few for two Hoarders and sent to Muscat is giving rise r o f a j. f f i c u .11 i e s, a s h j. s a B ritis h pr otect e d pars on as is {mown there is' no precedent for a trial by His Consul Muscat on a capital, charge* The difficulties th. .-'So of procedure as Hay a tun a ami ts thu murders. ECONO, D // Except for ric ; n t i a 1 c o m ■., j d i. t y i n ; there app &lt; th-, Gulf can- rsi to .be no shortage of any. th . shops in Bahrain are full -f coiisum.r goods. Prices 9 however, continue to rise. Ric,. in to past has mostly be,.n obtain, d from Persia whence its .xporc io; prohibited. More ffcctive prev.ontive measures by the Persi ms c jmoined with restrictions recently placed on the entry of Persians to Bahrain owing to the advertisement recently given to Persia’s island have resulted in a greatly diminished supply h;’ : .di prices. There is a shortage of rice in Muscat also* as s uggiing of rice out of Pakistan by country-craft via Gwadur not been possible during the monsoon. claim to th and IL The pdarling fleet 'thot put out from Bahrain this year vnas smaller than eva-r but the quality of the pearls 'obtained was e • d -no on., of the , has change:! hands for Rs. 25,000. On the Trucial Co st, ov/ing to the economic depression ,nd unemployment t' . pearling fleet h s been larger than usual but the catch is oortt /3 , r 1 Th,, aave been- rather ioamist n paper 'Dawn” has been giving much publici i,y t ' alleged banning -)f Pakist n currency by the Political ugent train, one the* Pakistan Government have taken up the matt •or e..I;-.daily . There- has be,,n no gener d. banning- of Pakistan current ! some ..o t . m n ilsre] r o t M D t ■ ' . G’onks in the Gulf have always dealt in Indian currency and if theg poor on■ to well, would have to double v. r.. to deal in Pakist-.n currency tbeir staff, alternatively, a change-over froom Indian to Pakistani currency would be very difficult to effect and would be inconvenient commercially as the'bulk of the Gulf's trade is with India as Op p OS' to a -o currency at r Si;It of th ikistan. BanKs therefore will only accept Pakistani small discount to cover repatriation charges, gy • attitude aGopted by the banks, and largely for tha s'■jne reasons, His Majesty’s'Government 1 s Offices in the Gulf including the post Offices, have b^een compelled to refuse to accept P akistani currency, though no notice has been published to this English cars are being re-exported from Bahrain to Pakistan and India in considerable numbers after a few month's use. Th-.y are ie great demand there owing to their low petrol consumption and a car which cost Rs. 5,000 landed in Bahrain can be sold there for Rs. 10,000. ^ Owing to a sudden drop in temperature which took place in the middle of the month, and the consequent reduction in load, the Bamrain Government Electricity Department is now able to give a Ed hours' supply, .x number of new gone rating sets are on order but the problem is still being tackled in a piece-meal fashion, and I have recommended to the Financial adviser that he should., seriously cans!dor erecting a modern plant on a new site and scrapping the present site which is congested and unsightly.^ ready market could be found elsewhere in the Gulf •existing sets. /m ' The merchants in Bahrain are still complaining of the unsatisfactory arrangements made by Llossrs Gray Mackenzies for unloading cargoes at Si trail. It still takes anything up to 3 weeks for cargoes to be transported by sea from Sitrah to Manamah r ; di s t anc e of ^ a f ow mi 1 e s and very extensive pi If er ing g o e s on during this time. proposal by Messrs Gray Mackenzie that their charges should be increased has been unanimously rejected by the •Shaikh and the local merchants.'Vcat' Ui-fc-oAJt^ K &lt;SLo^cr»^^ hs-fs/ ri With the Compliments of THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs 1 S- a 6 OCT Reef 8UMD&amp;X££ %o. •v, / PF~RSIAN GUL^ RE SIDFFCY PAffiUIF -r 7 , the 3Gth September, 194^ clv *■•- -—• QUv Dear Burrows, 9 The following is my monthly letter. The dreary hot weather has almost dragged itself to a close. According to the Bahrain Petroleum Company's figures this year has been on an average ten degrees hotter than last year. C ONFIDENTIA L X£7Z.?/48l Teft Bahrain for Kuwait on the 4th and returned on the 8th. Hudson returned from leave in Iraq on the 9th. Hoody left for the United Kingdom on on the 26th to attend conferences in London on quarantine arrangements in the Gulf. Logsdail arrived from Bombay on the 10th and assumed charge of the duties of Secretary, Persian Gulf Lighting Service. ^e was previously employed by the Government of India as Deputy Superint endent of Lighthouses, Bombay, and was ex officio Secretary. 5* ^ Admiral Conolly Commander-in-Chief United States Naval icrces -astern Atlantic and Mediterranean accompanied by 16 Staff Officers and representatives from the American Press arrived on the 3rd. Admiral Conolly and Vice-Admiral Wodlridge called on me and in return I gave a cocktail party to which I the officers of His Majesty's Ships 'Wilde-oose' and Lren together with^the leading British subjects of Manamah. Officer invited me to lunch on board the iVildgoose with the Admiral and one or two members of his staff and other U.S. Naval officers. The American Consul, Dhajiran, was also invited. 7 ^ ' . During the mon th the Persian claim to Bahrain has been lonoly voiced which has not been without effect on the Shaikh I The unique feature of this campaign is that Iraq has ioined in /'/ and taken up the cudgels on behalf of Bahrain. p' -'- r • Bait ye of Gray Dawes, London, who was once Gulf Manager of Gray, Mackenzie, visited me to ask the possibilities oc opening a. branen of Gray, Mackenzie in Qatar for shipping and other trade matters. I have now received an official application which is being examined. 9° ^ You wil1 recall our difficulties in inducing the Bahrain Government zo step up their electricity supply programme to meet, public needs. ^ Mr. M.C. Clear the Cairo representative of Bri'_isa Oil Engines (Export) Limited and Agents for Mirriees arrived in Bahrain in the middle of the month to make a report. He suates that the laerk of electricity in 1949 will be as bad as it has been this year and that to correct this a new 900 K.W. oe., ,s required. Pelly is pressing the State to act urgently in -che matter. Shaikh Khalifah bin Mohammed bin Isa, Superintendent of Police, returned from the United Kingdom where he enjoyed a brief visit under the auspices of the British Council. ’ His fatner gave a large dinner in honour of his safe return. During my visit to Kuwait T had several interviews w 1 11 the Shaikh who gave a dinner party for me and v/ho in return was entertained at the Agency. Commander Martin H.M.S.'Wren' m 1 ii l r' ter M airied ' t ^' e myself and Andrew to lunch aboard H.M.S. The Shaikh took us out in his new British launch of v/hicn he is very proud. I found the Shaikh in good health, affable and desirous of discussing many and various subjects. B.A.B. Burrows, Esquire, Foreign Office, ' ' LO NDON. S.W .l2 jK F K‘ - I 1 30 tne The ; - .• / ”S A**' and , „ 1 discussed the recent labour troubles with General Manager of the Kuwait Oil Company and Andrew, i General Manager informed me that he wished to terminate! tho no? W ^ m he considered to be malconWs not suitable Tbb work in Kuwait. It is honed that with the eparture of these men at the end of this month the^e will be no further trouble. Andrew is thanking Gray, Mackenzie t 0 r their cooperative attitude in providing at short notice sea passages in face of heavy bookings 0 i 0 ‘ , . The Company have been enquiring into the possibility of g J P r ?P? rtl °n of their labour from Aden and the Sudan. ie Aden authorities have stated that owing to a dearth o^ skill ed workers m Aden only unskilled labour is available. As the' international status of Sudanese is not clear to me the fomnanv have been asked to mark time pending enquiries. 110 . . _ The lack of water was ,appalling in Kuwait, and it is remarkable how any town can carry on its daily life with this spectre over its head. The price of water is actually controlled acuaas a gallon but the cost to the public generally is ^s 5 a 4 gallon drum including cost o^ transport. h 2 ' , , Shaikh of Sharjah has sent his brother Sultan bin ^ohammed to Bahrain to make his peace with Pelly over the Sultan affai r re P° rte ci in my last letter. Sultan bin Salim aoW in ;J uscat and 1 ho P e next stage in his journey will • -2 Lahr 1 a } n ' fie has wfitten to me giving his story of* the incident which, not unnaturally, does not tally with ours. ^During the month unv/arranted attacks on Pelly and on the Bahrain Administration have appeared in the newspaper 'Dawn M which is published in Karachi. This spitefulness is most unpleasant but I am pretty sure of its author. vV' 1 LB6. CONRDENTIjf ^ With the Compliments of THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs sK Foreign Office, m* .1 FILE COPY ^ 1598CO NFIDENTIAL ' (97/1/48) PERSIAN GULF FESI^NCY BAHRAIN » , ^ ; the 16th September 194^^ ’ Dear Burrows, The following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf for the period-24th July to 31st August. I arrived in Bahrain on the 24th July and took over charge of the Residency on the following day when Hay proceeded to the United Kingdom on leave. Ellison, Political’Agent designate, Muscat, arrived from the United Kingdom on the 7th and^left for Muscat on the 11th. Stobart, who had been acting at Muscat arrived on the 22nd, and has been temporarily posted as Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, vice Hudson, who proceeded on short leave to Shaklawa a small hill station in Iraq on the 19th. Grant, of the late Indian Medical Service arrived from the United Kingdom on the 25th July, and has taken over as Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. 3. There has been considerable American Naval activity in the Gulf during this period. Between July 19th and August' 7th ‘ the aircraft-carrier escort vessel “Greenwich Bay' visited Muscat, Khor Kuwai, Sharjah, Bahrain and Kuwait, and, between August 17th and 29th the destroyer “Poccono' and the aircraft- carrier “Siboney' visited Kuwait, the 'Carpellotti' a vessel similar to the “Greenwich Bay' and ’Siboney' Bahrain and the Carpellotti' Qatar. Ceremonial had to be cut down to the minimum for the visit of the “Greenwich Bay' owing to Ramadhan. ^ The Id al Fitr was celebrated in Bahrain by the Sunni on the 6th ’ and by the Shias the 7th. I called on the Shaikh informally on the 6th to convey to him my Id greetings. In the other Sheikhdoms and Muscat the Id was celebrated on the 6th with the usual festivities and exchange of calls. 5 * The Bahrain Government have selected a Mr. D. Rrammer of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited to be State ^n^ineer in succession to Group Captain Leigh, whose contract is due to expire in September. Mr. Brammer will loin his new appointment in November after a spell of leave in England. 6 * A Party of officers from the Imperial Defence College passed through Bahrain on the 19th. The first intimation I received of their visit was an invitation to an evening party from the Air Staff Liaison Officer. 7• The new automatic telephone system in Bahrain is still far from complete. Cable and Wireless state they are unable to make any^progress as the State cannot supply them’with electric power and the State have retorted that they can supply the power required but that the delay is due to the wiring not yet being completed. In the meantime local merchants are complaining that the rentals and some of the regulations bear too hardly on on subscribers and talk rather childishly of boycotting the new system. 8 * During the month the “water garden' was opened by th^ Shaikh of Bahrain to which British officials and Arabs were Pelly describes the ceremony pithyly in paragraph 195 (iii) of his Intelligence Summary No.14 of 1948. I only wish to remark that the money would have been better spent on slum clearance. 9. The Shaikh of... B.A.B. Burrows, Esquire, Eastern Department, Foreign Office, LONDON. S.W.l2 4 T1 ^ he Shaikh of Kuwait hris heard nothing further from ang Ibn Saud since he sent him a copy of his concession agree ment with the American Independent Oil Company for the ^eutral zone, and is beginning to get worried on this score. ■^P &lt;&gt; . Izzat Jaffar, the Shaikh of Kuwait*s Social Secretary, „ ^ leave, has been touring Europe and America. In the United States he is the guest of Phillips Petroleum Company/ by rV h \ Unite ? 4 StateS ^ he is bein ? It i/^e'orted c.t he h.s been giving talks on the economic prospects and future of Kuwait. Abdullah Mullah, the Shaikh of Kuwait’s Secretary, is building a cigarette factory in Kuwait. It is reported that he proposes manufacturing cigarettes for export only. Kuwait of course grows no tobacco but is not distant from Middle ^ast sources of supply. Possibly Abdullah Mullah may import irgmian tobacco on Independent dollars and manufacture gaspers. 12. The Shaikh of Kuwait is reported to be replacing the Egyptian and Syrian doctors in his Health Department by Indians, and several Indian doctors have already arrived. The reason given for this change is that Egyptian and Syrians are tempera ment illy unsuitable for dealing with the illiterate poor of Kuwait. 13. On the 14th August the Junior Staff consisting of Indians and Pakistanis, Arabs and Persians, of the Kuwait Oil ^ompany came out on a general strike as an indirect result of an incident in which a member of the Junior Staff was abused by an European employee of the Company’s food contractors, Messrs, opmneys. An apology was asked for and given but was not accepted and a public apology demanded. This was refused but Sprnney’s employee was dismissed. The situation was aggravated by the Company’s refusing to give the Indians and Pakistanis a holiday for the 15th August and a strike resulted. Various allegations and demands were put forward by the strikers and various promises were made by the Company with the result that the men came back to work on the 18th, since when an uneasy truce has prevailed. The General Manager informs me that oil production was not affected. 14. Sultan bin^Salim, ex-Shaikh of Has al Khaimah, has been ' ; ' jh n o e heral nuisance of himself by adopting a truculent attiflude towards his successor, Saqr bin Muhammad. As his activities were likely to result in permanent bickering and Political Agent, Bahrain, visited Shar.iah In the^third week of July. He summoned Sultan bin Salim and reminded him of the warning given by the Political Officer, Trucial Coast that he should behave himself. He informed Sultan that since had paid no heed to this warning he should proceed with him to Bahrain for a brief sojourn. Sultan thereupon made excuses that he intended no harm and asked for time to attend to his affairs. This was refused and on his wav to the car which was waiting to convey him and the Political Agent to the jetty, he made a get away after firing several shots wildly. He is reported to be now at Manai in the Wadi al Oaur on the Has Sv' //f 11 m h - Mu s c a t border. Immediately after his escape the Shaikh of Sharjah and other Trucial Shaikhs were asked to take steps to apprehend him but in spite of his being in Sharjah for S 0re 4 -/^ ajfl 24 hours nothing apparently was done to arrest him. tor this unco-operativeness I have decided to take certain measures against the Shaikh of Sharjah. • Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, the Muscat Minister for Home Alfairs, who had been deputed by the Sultan to organise the 2? eri oT 1 ^4. 0 ^ to motor traffic returned to Muscat on the 21st July accompanied by an impressive escort of 300 camelmen. His entry into Muscat was watched by large crowds and sailors from H.L.S. Wren and U.S.S.’’Greenwich Bay”, to whom the final camel race up to the Sultan’s palace mustnave provided an extraordinary spectacle. IVA A r. su*Kb CONFIDENTIAL ) /ND^XS0 No,121 (1^ /PQR) PERSIAF GULF PK^IDF^r BAHRAIF the 22nd July 1948 tlyl* L. y ; c. '4 n .to Ou 4 V ' t ; UV J 'l; v b oc .,, T _ I . am ex P ec ting to proceed on two months leave on the Zu \ Ju % ana am 'therefore forwarding a summary of events for the Persian Gulf, for the first three weeks of the month only. GENERAL combination of the height of the hot weather with the month of Ramadhan have produced a period of almost complete stagnation, and most of the Rulers of the Gulf States h^ve retired from public life for the time being. S lave Trade During my visit to Muscat at the beginning of the’ ? on S’ Sultan that I had heard that there was some traffic in slaves via the Batinah Coast to Buraimi. The Sultan said he^doubted the truth of this report, and promised to make enquiries. He did, however, inform me that Shaikh Rashid bin Hamad of the A1 Bu Shamis who is nominally one of his subjects had been authorised by Ibn Saud to grant certificates in respect of slaves sold for export to Saudi Arabia in the Buraimi market. These certificates are to the effect that the slaves concerned have been born in slavery and have not been kidnapped or abducted. I told the Sultan that it was well known tnat Shaikh Rashid had been issuing many false certificates, and the Sultan promised to send for him and warn him. T have also enquired from His Majesty’s Ambassador at Jeddah whether it is possible for him to arrapge for the authorisation granted to Shaikh Rashid to be withdrawn. BAHRAIN His Excellency Vice-Admiral C.H.L. Woodhouse, Commander-in-Chief, East Indies stayed in the Residency at Bahrain on the night of 17th/18th July, while returning by flying-boat from a conference in Egypt. Opportunity was taken to discuss local security problems with him. I hope to pay a farewell visit to Shaikh Salman before my departure. He has moved down to his Manama place, but is reported to be still suffering from boils, on which he refuses to allow the doctors to operate. KUWAIT 4 -,^ 4 . P n Saud has telegraphed to the Shaikh entering a mild protest about not being consulted before the Neutral Zone oil concession agreement was signed and asking for a copy to be forwarded to him. The Shaikh sent a copy at once by air to Riyadh. He is somewhat perturbed by the tone of Ibn Saud’s telegram. The Subah an Nasir case still .drags on, and' it is reported that the relations of the murdered Sa’adun are willing to accept the settlement offered by the As Subah family, provided they admit that Subah committed the murder. This they are not willing to do. Meanwhile interest in the case in Iraq appears to have evaporated. ' /Gable and w ireless... B.A.B. Burrows, Esquire, Foreign Office, Whitehall, LONDON. S„W,12 ft % Cable and tireless, who have a large building programme to carry out, are being met with extortionate demands by the Shaikh’s property agent. The Political Aeent has been asked to take the matter up with the Shaikh and will probably do so when the latter emerges from his Ramadhan seclusion. TRUCIAL COAST. Authority has been received from Pis Malesty’s Government to accord formal recognition to Shaikh Saqr’ bin Muhammad as Ruler of Has al Khaimah, and his brother Shaikh Humaid as ^Regent of Kalba. Meanwhile, the previous Regent Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmed has staged a come-back and forcibly re occupied Khor Fakkan which rebelled against him at the beginning of the year. There were some casualties, and heavy fines have been exacted from the leading men. In 'the circumstances, the grant of formal recognition to Shaikh Humaid bin Muhammad is being delayed until the situation becomes clearer. The ex-Shaikh of Has al Khaimah Sultan bin Salim has also been trying without much success to re-assert himself. , The Political Agent Bahrain has proceeded to Has al Khaimah to accord formal recognition to Shaikh Saqr bin Muhammad, and may arrange for Sultan bin Salim ? visit to Bahrain for the good of his health. The Shaikh of Dubai has written in to say that he has made his peace with the Manasir tribesmen who have recently been raiding his territor ies at great loss to themselves. Shaikh Hazza, brother of the Ruler of Abu Dhabi, has been on a visit to Bahrain where he has disserted at great length on his brother’s claim to TTmm Said, a place in the Qatar peninsula, where Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited hope to construct their port. Shaikh Hazza while at Bahrain stayed with Shaikh Salman, who no doubt was delighted at an opportunity of encouraging another territorial claim against Shaikh Abdullah al Thani. According to Lorimer, the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi was informed as long ago as 1895 that his claim to TTmm Said and the adjoining part of the Qatar peninsula could not be approved. He is being so informed again. MS CAT ' By the courtesy of the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, I visited Muscat in H.M.S.”Wild Goose', in the first week of the month before the beginning of Ramadhan. During the trip, visits were made to both the Malcolm and Flphinstone inlets, and some of us landed on the Telegraph island in the latter inlet where the Indo-European Telegraph Department used to have a Cable Station, until the suicide of successive officers-in-charge, forced them to abandon it. I found the Sultan in good health and had some satisfactory talks with him. On the day of the 'Wfid Goose s” departure, he came on board and had breakfast with the officers. He was then taken out to watch the bombardment of a small deserted island called Fahl, He returned to Muscat in his launch, and the Political Agent reports that he collapsed on the way back, owing to the excessive heat &amp;nd had to be brought round by ice-bags. He was wondering whan I saw him, how he would be able to face the Ramadhan fast which he has not had to undertake before in the worst of the Muscat heat. j ^ J . The chief ‘ matter I discussed with the Bui tan was the appointment of a Minister of Foreign Affairs. He refused to consider certain names which have recently been suggested to him and pressed for the appointment of Colonel Hickinbotham at presen' Chairman of the Port Trust at Aden, who is unlikely to accept the post. He finally agreed to accept a suitable ex-Indian Politica' Service officer who did not know Arabic, subject to a satisfector ; interview, and an undertaking to learn Arabic as soon as possible' after his appointment. The Sultan also discussed with me at some length, Mr. Bird s recent activities in the Buraimi area, where he has been entering into agreements with certain Shaikhs who are nominally the Sultan’s subjects, whereby they have agreed to «- 3 - jlfcw. • '»« i I R : &gt; 4 permit oil exploration in return for specified annual payments. Previous misunderstandings with Hr. Bird were cleared up'is * reported in ray Summary of Events for May, but unfortunately further disputes have arisen, and he and the Sultan each accuses the other of double crossine. Mr. Bird has now left T£ r a ^ United Kingdom and \vill not resume his negotiations till the Autumn. I have suggested to Mr. Lerraitte, the General -lanager of Petroleum Concessions Limited in Bahrain, that he should, m the meanwhile, if possible, see the Sultan in order t FT AZt*\l ome satisfactory m odus vivendi . The situation ■i-f a u 1 £ flc i 1 ^ one as Sultan has no control over the tribes though he will not admit this and the tribes rreatly enioy thf game of playing off the Oil Company against the Sultan and vice V G-. l S cl • / in ? 0W re P° rted about a hundred MukaUa subjects w ___* berritery, some on their way to India and some on their n^_ b 'S k , ? fter having^been refused permission to land at ^ 0 r-bay. fP'r of bhem are working as coolies, but are reported tn be Sult?n eSt Th d }£t y U an n their b resence is not welcome to the neet^the . Government have agreed to provide funds to ^.eet the maintenance and repatriation expenses of the original ^nved in Muscat^ after being refused permission to Ic.nd at Bombay as reported in my last summary. ECONOMIC SUPPLPMkPT Bahrain win- 5 r&gt;vi C ^ Plai u ts J aeainst M ? ssrs * Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. limited, hich c.re a hardy annual in Bahrain, are now more profuse than ever, and are not without justification, as the delay and ^^ er i ng M V/hlCh takes P lace in the transport of cargoes from Sitra to Manama are said to be phenomenal. In fact, the firm have got themselves a thoroughly bad name. They have practic ally the monopoly of the shipping business in Bahrain and some real competition would do them a great deal of good. At p conference between the firm and representatives of the Bahrain Government and the merchant community it was agreed that the 15/ cut made in landing charges last year should be restored. Kuwait . , ,_ The £^ a , ilc , h ^ reported to be banking the verv large sun of Coran^v r S rece £ vin P from the American Independent Oil p th th ? Com P an y , s own bank. Possibly he fears they MB. deposited with a British bank. • Be has allowed his ...B.C., Izzat Jaffar, a sum of over half a million dollars for the import of. rice from Brazil. lcn has ^ been formed with 50# Kuwaiti and 50# Iraqi from the °L aplpe line t0 briris fresb water detaBcMf^M Kuwalt - An application setting forth CMB t f tbe P r 0P°sal has been submitted to the Shaikh for hig the M h 2 S ffM a c °py of ft through his Secretary to the Political Agent with some rather vague comments. Bis previous attitude has_been that he will not approve any scheme guarante e ° th -a ssKisMajesty's Government are willing to interfere witJ Iraqi Gov ®rn- ,, ient will in no circumstances to give 3 guarantee whlch ft is elearlv impossible K.iwaiMnj? o aVe be ? n a n ^ nbe r of small strikes amongst the cUn^tic cPnd?t?o£l S enp i oy | es ’ P robab fy ^e in part to the severe clime tic conditions. The Furopsan and American employees nt +-h^ be r renjtriated :r if C th C! i ti0n ? are Particularly bad, have' asked to be repatriated if their grievances cannot be remedied. /Muscat...Muscat D Q cL ^ The Sultan has now signed the agreement with the fnpirial bank °r Iran for the opening of a Branch at MuscaTT^nd 'tr. 'Scott, who has hitherto been Manager of the Bank’s branch at Dubai, has arrived at Muscat to start the new branch there. Sul,fcan has signed an agreement with Cable and w ireless ior the operation of an automatic telephone system at Muscat and Matrah. ’LB’'mm-™-v ^ CONFIDENTIAL No.102 (13/298) Dear Burrows, The following is a summary Gulf for June. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN the 1 s t Jul f ~, ,1948^ iNDexen | IC :38 | ; , ' of events in^tne Pe^4lan ] If GENERAL His Majesty The Ki r ^s Birthday At Bahrain on the occasion of His Majesty's birthday, His Highness Shaikh Salman accompanied by. a number of his relatives paid a formal call at the Residency. In the evening I gave a cocktail party which was attended by about 200 guests. At Kuwait, the Political Agent held a reception at the Agency and calls were received from His Highness the Shaikh and members of his family, and representatives of the British, American, Indian and Pakistani communities. At Muscat, a guard of honour was provided at the Political Agency and a Royal Salute was fired from Mirani Fort. His Highness the Sultan accompanied by members of his staff and the Shaikh of Dubai who was on a visit to Muscat', paid a formal call on the Political Agent. During the course of the day, deputations from various local communities called on the Political Agent, and a dinner for the European community was given at the Political Agency in the evening. Under the Sultan's orders, the Union Jack flew over the Mirani Fort for the whole day. Weather ^ ' The north-west wind which should blow in the Persian Gulf throughout the month of June has been very fitful this year. There have been some violent storms and a great deal of dust haze. On.the 7th June, a particularly violent storm raged in the area between Gwadur and Muscat and much damage was done at Matrah and two villages on the Muscat coast. Many sailing craft were lost or driven ashore and the submarine cables were damaged. In another storm, the Bahrain Agency launch which was on a visit to the Trucial Coast became a total wreck, but its engines and fittings were saved. The dust haze has held up air traffic and led to accidents. One flying boat landed in the open sea east of Muharraq island, but fortunately little damage was caused and no passengers were injured. On the 16th June, a United States Army aircraft was unable to find a landing place and after it had circled round for several hours 18 of the passengers baled out. The aircraft with a crew of three which remained on board eventually crashed in the sea between Bahrain and Qatar. Two of the passengers who baled out were killed, as well as the three who remained in the aircraft. The latter are said to have had two parachutes between them but no two of them could be persuaded to use them and leave the third man to his fate. Persian Gulf Lig ht ing Service . ^ Responsibility for the Persian Gulf Lighting Service was transferred from the Government of India to His Majesty's Govern ment from the 1st June. The Service will in future be administ ered by this Residency under the orders of the Ministry of Trans port. The Residency is to be assisted by an Advisory Committee and it is also proposed to create an Advisory Board in the United Kingdom to assist the Ministry of Transport. The first meeting /of the... B.A.B. Burrows, Esquire, The Foreign Office, Whitehall, LONDO N. S.W.lI 2 r of the local Advisory Committee was held at Bahrain on the 25th j June and was attended by the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, the Director General of Ports and Navigation Basrah, and representatives of Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited. The Anglo- Iranian Oil Company, the Kuwait Oil Company and the Arabian American Oil Company were also invited to send representatives ' but unfortunately the notice given was too short for them to do so. The meeting was largely of a preliminary nature and the chief recommendation made was the continued employment for 3 years of Mr. Logsdail as Secretary of the Persian Gulf Lighting Service, a post which he has held under the Government of India for 18 years. According to a report received by the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf from Admiral Zelli, the Persian Government intend shortly to take up the question of the lighting J of their coast in the Persian Gulf. BAHRAIN I called on the Shaikh on the 12th June and found him much perturbed about the local wheat situation. He told me he was about to move down from Rifaa to his town palace at Manama as he usually does in the hot weather, but I understand that his departure has been delayed by a bad boil. He did not mention Zubarah but has since presented us with a formidable memorial to the Foreign Secretary on.the subject. His cousin Shaikh Khalifah bin Mohammed who is Superintendent of the State Police has been selected to visit the United Kingdom as a guest of the British Council and will leave as soon as an air passage can be arranged for him. S' Captain Steele of the late Indian Medical Department who has been Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain for 7 years has left on retirement. Lt.Col. Moody, Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, Persian Gulf, is performing the duties of the post in addition to his own until the arrival of Captain Grant late of the Indian Medical Service who is expected in the middle of July. 6 ' Mr, Hilaly, Deputy Foreign Secretary of the Pakistan Government accompanied by his wife, paid a brief visit to Bahrain early in the month. He was ostensibly on leave but spent his time discussing with local merchants the possibility of supplying rice from Sind for Bahrain. It is understood that he is making a tour of numerous other Middle East countries during his so- called leave. 7- Mr. Thesiger who, as I reported in my last summary, had returned to the Trucial Coast after pursuing local fauna in the Buraimi area came to Bahrain in the middle of the month and left for the United Kingdom. Unfortunately I did not meet him. It is understood that he proposes to visit Oman again next cold weather. Both the Sultan and the Petroleum Concessions Limited view his movements with suspicion and he will not be very welcome there. ' ' The Manama electricity supply has given further trouble and for several days the current was cut off for 12 hours out of the 24. The situation appears to be the result of both bad planning and bad management and is causing much discontent. The lack of power is seriously delaying the installation of the new automatic telephone exchange by Messrs. Cable and Wireless. KUWAIT °l' I paid 2 visits to Kuwait in the first half of the month in connection with the Neutral Zone Oil Concession. As previous ly reported, the Shaikh asked for final bids to be submitted by the 1st June. The highest bid was submitted by the American Independ ent Oil Company. At first the Shaikh suggested that he would give the other competitors an opportunity of improving on their bids and private enquiries were made from one or two of them.w 4 c&gt; ^ K J $ - 3 - The Canadian Eagle Oil Company whose representative arrived at Kuwait at the last moment without notice and was unable to obtain permission from the Shaikh to compete 5 eventually combined with the Gulf Oil Company to submit an higher bid. The Shaikh, however, refused to accept this saying that the race had been run and won by the American Independent Oil Company and that it could not be run again. A Political Agreement between His Majesty's Government and the American Independent Oil Company was negotiated in London and the Concession Agreement was signed by the Shaikh and Company's representatives at Kuwait on the 28thJune. The agreement provides, amongst other things, for the immediate payment of 7i million dollars, an annual payment of 625,000 dollars until ^&gt;il is found, a royalty of 2.5 dollars per ton, and the allotment to the Shaikh of 15 % of the shares of the subsidiary company which is to be formed to work the concession. The American Independent Oil Company will now have to reach some agreement with the Arabian American Oil .Cbmpany who hold the concession for Ibn Saud's share of the Neutral Zone, for the working of the concession and some arrange ment will have to be arrived at between Ibn Saud and the Shaikh f of Kuwait for the administration of the area. The Shaikh of Kuwait has reason to congratulate himself on the outcome of his auction, as even if no oil is found, he will be richer by a very large sum in dollars. He has throughout maintained that this money belongs to the State and not to himself personally, and for so long as he is alive, this accession of wealth is unlikely to lead to any lavish personal expenditure by himself or his relatives. ^ The case of Subah an Nasir who murdered a Sa'adun and two Muntafiq tribesmen some months ago, is still the subject of much correspondence. The deputation which is negotiating a settlement tween the Shaikh and the murdered Sa'adun's relatives has reached Basrah on its return with the reply to the Shaikh's latest offer, but has been unable to continue its journey to Kuwait on account of the enforcement of martial law at Basrah. It is believed that the murdered man's relatives are ready to effect a settlement but that Shaikh Abdullah bin Falih, the head of the Sa'adun family, is unwilling to endorse it unless Subah is expelled from Kuwait. QATAR I reported in my last summary the death of Shaikh Hamad the heir-apparent of Shaikh Abdullah. The family has suffered further loss by the death of Abdul Aziz the son of the late Shaikh Hamad while under medical treatment at Karachi. TRUCIAL COAST /ZMr. Jackson has proceeded on leave and the Residency Agent Mr. Jassim bin Mohammed is now in charge of the Sharjah Office., Before his departure, Mr. Jackson succeeded in obtaining a written agreement^pf Shaikh Shakhbut of Abu Dhabi to accept the award of Government Officers in the boundary dispute between Abu Dhabi and Dubai. The signature of Shaikh Sa'id to a similar agreement has not yet been obtained owing to his absence in Muscat. Shaikh Saqr bin Mohammed the new Ruler of Ras al Khaimah and his brother Shaikh Humaid, Regent designate of Kalba have signed the under takings required of them and I have asked His Majesty's Government for approval to accord them formal recognition. ' The Shaikh of Hamriyah who as I reported in my last summary stopped one of the Oil Company's cars to call attention to his 'rights' has succeed ed in extorting from the Shaikh of Sharjah a share of the latter's income under his oil agreement. M USCAT A gentleman called Hayatun who has committed at least 4 murders has been arrested in Gwadur territory. In 1943 he murdered two men in a village in territory which is disputed between Muscat and Mekran. The Kalat authorities arrested him, but he subsequently escaped. A few months ago he committed another 2 »- 4 - murders near Suntsar in Mekran territory. Arrangements are being made to bring him to Muscat as soon as possible as there is every likelihood of his escaping if he is left at Gwadur. His subsequent disposal is going to be a matter of some difficulty as there is no agreement under which his extradition from Muscat can be claimed. He is, it is believed, a British, protected person and it is very doubtful whether sufficient evidence will now be forthcoming to permit of his being tried by the Political Agent under the Indian Penal Code for the murders committed in, what may or may not be Muscat territory in 1943. ’H' Some thirty Mukalla subjects on their way to Hyderabad probably to join the Nizam's forces have been refused permission to land at Bombay and sent to Muscat without any notice to the local authorities. As they are pratically destitute and owing to the monsoon will be unable to continue their journey to Mukalla till October they are likely to prove a source of considerable embarrassment. - E CONOMIC S U PPLEMENT GENERAL 15 I have recommended that the Indian Rupee should be the only currency recognised for the purposes of His Majesty's Government's Offices in the Gulf States including the Post Offices and Cable and Wireless Offices. There are now some Pakistani Rupees in circulation but they are only accepted at a small discount by the local Banks. The Sultan of Muscat also wishes to adopt the Indian Rupee as opposed to the Pakistani one and the Shaikh of Bahrain is believed to hold similar views. Although the political sympathies of the Gulf States naturally lie more with Pakistan than with India 90 % or more of their trade is with the latter country. —— !(p- As from the 1st July the local banks which have up to date been observing the Reserve Bank of India's rules in exchange matters will be subject exclusively to British control. This Residency has authority to sanction the grant of exchange for imports but not, at present, for other purposes, and authority is being sought to sanction the grant of clean exchange in certain cases. /7 The shortage of rice throughout the Gulf States is still causing some concern. Applications have been received for exchange to cover the import of rice from Brazil and this matter has been referred to His Majesty's Government. No reply has been received to requests made to the Government of Pakistan for permission to purchase rice from Karachi. Meanwhile some Karachi rice is reaching the Gulf States, probably via Gwadur. Bahrain. % There is a shortage of wheal; in Bahrain which may become serious. This is because ( a ) the regular monthly supplies received from the Ministry of Food, via Basrah, are in arrears; (b) the population has increases since the present quota was fixed, and (c) owing to the shortage of rice, more wheat is being consumed. It is also probable^that owing to the very high price of wheat prevailing on the mainland-, a certain amount has been smuggled out of Bahrain. Action has been taken to expedite the despatch of wheat due from the Ministry of Food, and it is still hoped that it will be possible to obtain sufficient rice to make up the general deficiency in cereals. ^ ' The pearling fleet is not to sail until after the Ramadhan fast which finishes in early August. Owing to the slump in thepearl trade It is probable that few vessels will participate. Kuwait 1°' The Shaikh has at last been persuaded to place an order for a distillation plant for drinking water, but it is likely to be some two years before the necessary machinery can be obtained and installed. Meanwhile the drinking water situation remains serious. Muscat ^ The Sultan has decided to grant a concession for the opening of a bank in Muscat to the Imperial Bank of Iran. . A representative of the Bank is expected to arrive in Muscat shortly to open a branch. Negotiations for the installation of an automatic telephone exchange by Cable and Wireless in Muscat are proceeding satisfactorily. ll ' The Political Agent reports that there is much distress amongst the poorer classes in Muscat owing to the export of essential food stuffs to other Gulf States. The Sultan is not interfering in this export as he recovers export duty and also, it is rumoured, receives a share in the profits from the local merchants. ’LB 1 Yours sincerely, Sd/-W.R. HayCO NFIDENTIAL No ,81 (13/298 ) the 8th Tfuney 1948 Bear Bu for May. GENERAL /. American Relations . Captain Rodgers of the U.S. Navy visited Bahrain and Kuwait during the first half of the month to make preliminary arrangements for some surveys which being carried the eastern shores of the Gulf were photographed by aircraft from the carrier U.S.S.'•Rendova'. This ship accompanied by the destroyer ,, C.H„ Roan' visited Bahrain from the 19th to the 21st May for fuelling purposes. Formal calls were exchanged with the Commanding Officers and on the 21$t the Shaikh gave a large dinner party which was attended by fifty or sixty officers from the United States’ ships. 2* Palestine . Events in Palestine have had no serious repercussions in the Gulf States but a keen interest is being taken in the situation by the ruling classes and the merchants in Bahrain and Kuwait. At the former place only a very few out of sixty merchants invited to attend a reception on board the ’’Rendova” turned up, and the remainder sent a letter to the Captain regret ting their inability to be present owing to the attitude taken up by the U.S.A. over Palestine. The Shaikh of Kuwait is more interested in his own affairs than in Palestine and has informed me that he considers the Jews too strong for the Arabs and that partition is inevitable. ^ Pers i an Gulf Lighting Servic e. Major Dredge, the Secretary to the Political Resident, visited Bombay in the^ latter half of the month to study the details of the administration of this Service. It is hoped that responsibility for it will be transferred from the Government of India to His Majesty’s Government early in June. United States of America in the late summer owing to the feeling which that Country's attitude over Palestine has aroused amongst the Arabs. He also considers that in any case it would be unwise 4 for him to leave Bahrain until the Palestine situation becomes Dre settled. ' r ^ ’ On the 24th an H.A.F. Anson aircraft force-landed in the ’ sa in shallow water between Bahrain and Qatar. Fortunately :&gt;ne of the seven occupants were injured. They w r ere found by a -O.A.C. launch and brought back to Bahrain. Colonel Galloway who was expected to take over as Political Agent at the beginning of April is still delayed by illness and is not likely to arrive until the latter half of June. Meanwhile Mr. Andrew continues to hold charge of the post * I paid two visits to Kuwait during the month, the first to have a general look round and the second to be present at the closing stages of the Neutral Zone auction. The place is develop ing rapidly and in particular great progress has been made with out by the United States Navy. In the latter half of the month BAHRAIN The Shaikh has abandoned his intention of visiting the KUWAIT B.A.B. Burrows, Esquire, Foreign Office, LON DON. S.W.l /thethe Kuwait Oil Company’s new Camp at Ahmadi. The Shaikh is in good health and spirits and discusses with relish the situation in Iraq which he considers likely to become muph worse. He says that he has still some opposition to overcome before he can ask us to provide him with a Financial Adviser but that he hopes to be in a position to approach-us at an early date. Meanwhile he has taken no further action regarding the appointment of a British Police Officer owing to strong criticism of the proposal which has appeared in some Iraqi newspapers. I am informed that he has discussed the proposal to appoint British Advisers three times during the last year or two with his Consultative Committee. In fact this is the only matter about which the Committee, which rarely functions, has been consulted during the period in question. The case of Subah an Nasir who is believed to have murder ed three Iraqis including a member of the Sa'adun family remains unsettled. Subah has returned to Kuwait and the Shaikh has been warned that if he does not expel him again, the life of his son Muhammad, who lives in Basrah, will be in danger. The Shaikh for some reason or other is refusing to expel Nasir and at the same time is unwilling to recall Muhammad from Basrah where his presence is required for the litigation that is going on over the Shaikh’s date gardens in Iraq. The Shaikh is making a last attempt to effect a private settlement with the Sa’adun and has \ said that if this fails he will ask that the case should be taken up through diplomatic channels The Shaikh is engaging 15 Pakistanis, presumably ex-soldiers, as a personal guard largely for ceremonial purposes. I have been enquiring whether any Communist influences are at work in Kuwait. It is believed that four members of the Tudeh who have been expelled from Iran, have obtained employment with the Kuwait Oil Company under assumed names but they have not yet been identified. Two small and abortive strikes which have taken place may perhaps be attributed to them. Some of the Indian members of the Company receive a Communist paper called r BLITZ’ from Bombay and are reported to indulge in a certain amount of wild talk but up to date there is no sign of any serious subversive movement. / v ' Representatives of the Burmah Oil Company, the Gulf Oil Company, the American Independent Oil Company, Amerada and Canadian Eagle gathered in Kuwait at the end of the month for the auction of the Neutral Zone Oil Concession. The Shaikh has asked them to submit their final bids by the evening of the 1st June and it is understood that he intends to award the concession to the highest bidder regardless of bther considerations. He told me that he regarded himself as a trustee acting on behalf of the State as a whole and that he was therefor^ bound to disregard his personal preferences. QATAR /// ' Shaikh Hamad the second son and heir-apparent of Shaikh Abdullah died of diabetes on the 27th May. He was recognised as heir-apparent in 1935 and during recent years had been attend ing to most of the affairs of the State bn behalf of his father who is over eighty and also suffering from diabetes. The questi of the succession will novy have to be considered. / ^'«By the courtesy of Messrs. Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. I visited Dukhan as their guest early in the month. The y second of the wells drilled since operations started again after the war flowed just before my arrival and I witnessed the firing of the first oil. The Company's camp at Dukhan is a temporary one and they hope to start work on their permanent Camp further south shortly. Work has begun on the road to the port which is to be constructed on the east coast of the peninsula. Qatar must he one of the ugliest places in the world and there are no amenities except from those afforded by the sea. During my visi the place was scorched by a hot south wind. The CompanyI - 3 - employees have many difficulties to contend with but rapid progress is being made and it should not be long before they go into production. TR UCIAL COAST Mr, Jackson has postponed his leave in the hope that we may be able to settle the boundary and other disputes between Abu Dhabi and Dubai before his departure. He has made much progress as a result of endless discussions with the representatives of the parties. The notables of Kalba and Khor Fakkan have agreed to accept Shaikh Humaid of Ras al Khaimah as Regent in place of Shaikh Khalid, and Shaikh Humaid and his brother Shaikh Saqr have been asked to sign agreements prior to their final recog nition as Regent of Kalba and Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah respect ively. The Shaikh of Hamr^iah stopped one of the Oil Company's cars on the road recent^: and demanded a separate concession. Hamryjiah is^regarded as being covered by the terms of the Sharjah Oil Concession but its Shaikh has long regarded himself as independent of Sharjah and his claim is supported to a certain extent by a document which was given him without authority by a previous Residency Agent. The Oil Company do not wish to operate in Hamr^yah territory in the near future and the matter will be dealt with at leisure. Mr. Thesiger has returned to the coast after hunting wild asses and other fauna near Buraimi and is believed to be intend ing to travel to Bahrain by dhow. MUS CAT ^ The Sultan has issued a law enforcing liquor prohibition in his territories. Europeans are to be allowed to obtain a reasonable amount of liquor through the Political Agent. He is still exercising his mind over his position vis-a-vis India and Pakistan and has given^the Political Agent to understand that while he ^will allow things to remain as they are at present, when the Treaty comes up for revision in 1951 he will do his best to ensure that jurisdiction over Indian and Pakistani subjects is transferred to himself. Mr. Bird of Petroleum Concessions Ltd. has recently visited Muscat and^had discussions with the Sultan. The latter was inclined to object ot an agreement recently concluded by Mr. Bird with the Al bu Shamis tribe whereby the tribe will allow the Company to carry out explorations in their territory for three years in return for an annual payment, but it is reported that an amicable settlement was eventually reached. * EC GNOMIC SUPPLEMENT GENERAL ;7 There is a shortage of rice throughout the Gulf States owing to the steps taken in Persia to prevent export and the price of such rice as is available is very high indeed. Applications have been received for exchange to enable rice to be imported from Uruguay and Brazil. The Government of Pakistan has also been asked to make an allotment of rice from Sind. ^rreucy. Pakistan currency is now making its appearance and is not regarded with favour in all quarters. A proposal that the Indian rupee should be regarded as the only currency accept able for official purposes is under discussion with His Majesty's Government. — * ' Qpmmu nic ations, There is now one Skymaster service a week between the United Kingdom and Bahrain in place of the two flying boat services. All the- air service schedules have been put out of joint by the refusal of the Egyptian and Iraqi Governments to allow aircraft to fly over their territories at night. An outbreak of cholera at Karachi may lead to the imposition ofy - 4 - 5 quarantine restrictions by Middle East Governments and a further disorganisation of the air services. fo*Pearls. The Government of India have stated that pearls may now be imported to India freely» It is understood however that import licences are still required. Owing to purchases of dollars by Kuwaiti merchants the local black market rate rose as high as Rs.4/12 per dollar. It was last reported at Rs.4/6, Kuwait^ Money is flowing into Kuwait and wages and prices continue to rise - except in the case of sugar of which there is a glut. Wheat received from His Majesty’s Government is sold to the public at Rs.37/- a bag but the price in the open market is Rs.120/- per bag. The export of wheat to Saudi Arabia has recently constituted a drain on local resources and the Shaikh has been asked to prohibit it. Kuwait is now buying instead of selling dollars presumably owing to the large number required for the purchase of gold which is still being smuggled into India. It is stated 7 or 8 lakhs of rupees in notes arrive by every mail steamer mostly derived, it is believed, from the sale of gold in India. Dollars are being purchased not only in Bahrain but also in Iraq, Syria and South India. In addition payments in dollars are made in Kuwait by the Bechtel organisat ion which is employed on construction work at Fahahil and Ras Misha*ab and by the Arabian American Oil Company. The Kuwait Oil Company earn no dollars and make no dollar payments locally. ^ • The supply of drinking water at Kuwait continues to be most unsatisfactory and the cost of it to the public is about 8 annas a gallon. The Shaikh is endeavouring to obtain some water tankers through the Kuwait Oil Company for the transport of water from the ohatt-al-Arab but owing to the precariousness of this source of supply he is being urged to order a distillat ion plant as soon as possible. 5*1' The Shaikh has agreed to the extension of the existing Civil Air Agreement which expired on 23rd May 1948 for a period of six months provided he can be assured that this will not entail any delay in the construction of the proposed new aerodrome. An assurance has been given him on this point. 2 ^ ' Musca t?. Mr. Findlay of the Eastern Bank has made proposals to the Sultan for the opening of a branch of the Bank in Muscat. The Sultan has now received proposals from both this Bank and the Imperial Bank of Iran and is expected to announce his decision shortly. Yours sincerely, ’LB* 3d/- W.R. Hay.VI - CONFIDENTIAL No.48 (13/298) Dear Burrows, if' PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIB Dated the TtSdUayEx^fS '=tV &gt;6237 The following Is a summary of the events in the Persian Gulf for April. GENERAL ' , Ikeir Majesties' Silver Wedding. A holiday was observed in the Residency and its subordinate offices. H.M.S. 'Loch Quoich' which was at Bahrain fired a Royal Salute. The Residency With effect from the 1st April the Residency came under the Foreign Office and we are endeavouring to adapt our- selves to the new routine. Permission has been accorded to the Political Resident to use the title of'Excellency'. Postal *u * With eff,ect Prom the. 1st April the Post Offices in the Gulf States except that at Gwadur, came under the control General Post Office London, British stamps surcharged with Rupee values are now being used, including the Silver Wedding stamps. Gwadur Post Office is still administered by the Pakistan Government. Boyal Navy Captain L.E. Porter who succeeded Captain R.J.R. Dendy as Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf in November and has b m? n unav °idably detained at Colombo while his ship H.M.S. Wild Goose** was refitting, arrived in Bahrain in H.M.S. Loch Quoich' on the 25th April and exchanged calls with the Reside ^, the Political Agent and His Highness the Snalkh the following day. He visited Muscat on the way and exchanged calls with His Highness the Sultan and the Political - Agent. H.M.S. 'Wild Goose** has also now arrived at Bahrain. Persian Gulf Lightin g Service . n T The transfer of the administration of the Persian Gulf Lighting Service from the Government of India to this Residency has been agreed upon in principle and was to have taken place on the 1st April, but has now been postponed to the 1st Meanwhile it is hoped to arrange for a representative of this Residency to visit Bombay to discuss details of the transfer. The Service will be administered under the direction of H.M*s Ministry of Transport. YiaA fro?? . , Mr * Noonan J Petroleum Attache British Middle East Office. Cairo, visited Kuwait, Bahrain and Qatar during the month and met representatives of the Oil Companies and saw their camps and installatiins. He had hoped also to visit the Arabian American Oil Company*s camp at Dhahran but the local Suadi - B.A.B. Burrows, Esquire, The Foreign Office, Whitehall, L ONDON. S.W.l /Arabian...*- 3 - sea bed between Bahrain and Qatar. He came to see me and protested that the Company and the Shaikh had not been allowed to get together on the subject. Accordingly a meeting was arranged between the Shaikh and the Company at which the Political Resident was present but their united efforts produced no new objections of any substance to His Majesty’s Governments decision, Mr. BaHantyne left for the United Kingdom and returned again 'n &amp;t the end of the month with a further argument which, in his the whole matter, but - was able to inform him that it had already been fully considered. Mr. Russell Brown General Manager Bahrain Petroleum Company and their Chief Local Representative has proceeddd on leave to India. During his a °f e J} Ce ^ r * responsible for production and the refinery and Mr. Crow for other branches of the Company’s business including the functions of Chief Local Representative. KUWAIT ^ a 4 -u^ e Agent, Major Tandy, proceeded on leave during the month and his place has been taken temporarily by Mr. Andrew. It is hoped that Colonel Galloway who was to have taken over as Political Agent at the beginning of the month but was detained by ill health in the United Kingdom will arrive towards the end of May. last monthly summary I mentioned the disappearance Oi a Sadun and two other Muntafiq tribesmen and their suspected murder by Shaikh Subah an Nasir. The Shaikh’s family nave been negotiating with the Sadun for a settlement of this case and the latter have insisted as* a condition precedent that Subah should be expelled from Kuwait. It was accordingly proposed to deport him to Bahrain but he fled the State and sought refuge with Ibn baud who refused to receive him. , He is now reported to be in / the Kuwait neutral zone. Meanwhile negotiations for'a settle ment continue. Representations about this case have been made by the Iraqi Government and the facts have been reported to H.M’s Embassy Baghdad. The Political Agent Kuwait is empowered to giant visas for Iraq but has hitherto been required to make a prior reference in most cases to the* police authorities in Baghdad, which has led • interminable delays. The Iraqi Government have now agreed that he should grant single journey visas only without prior reference '*2u* )er ? ons ’ amon &amp;st others, who are not engaged in smuggling or otherwise objectionable to the Iraqi authorities. These terms might be held to include the whole indigenous population of Kuwait* QATAR / v The Shaikh of Qatar has asked to be supplied with a lar^e number of rifles and with 'armoured cars fitted will, machine ' guns and heavy guns M . Under the 1916 Treaty he is entitled to be supplied at his own expense with, arms _md ammunition and it is proposed to provide him at once with 500 rifles and 50,00'' --^ds of ammunition for them. The question of obtaining motor veh^. um light machine guns for him is under consideration, with the rapid expansion of the local Oil Company’s activities P eninsu l a it is desirable that he should be burnished with the means for protecting .them. (CRUCIAL COAST “l. c . ^ 4 th ® beginning of the month I visited Khor Fakkan in the bhumailiyah trace on the west coast of the Gulf of Oman, his place consists of a group of villages around a small bay and Is normally subject to the Shaikhdom of Kalba. The peoole hav^ however, recently turned out the Regent's guards. J was hospitably entertained by the leading man Ahmed bin Hassan and round the people contented and reasonably prosperous. There are some fine date gardens here and a good harbour on which a few ocean-going country craft are based. Essential supplies are received from Dubai on the Trucial Coast. »I mentioned in my last summary that Mr. Thesiger had arrived at Abu Dhabi after completing the journey across the Rub al Khali and that he was proposing to travel to Muscat via Buraimi. As Mr. Bird of Petroleum Trucial Coast Ltd. is at present engaged in negotiations with the tribes at Buraimi and as the Company feel that Mr. Thesiger 1 s presence in this area ^would complicate their already very difficult task, Mr. Thesiger has been asked not to proceed further than Buraimi. He is at present endeavouring to obtain specimens of the fauna in this area and it is understood that he now intends to return to the Trucial Coast and travel to Bahrain by dhow. Meanwhile Mr. Bird is not meeting with much success in his negotiations with the tribes though he is still optimistic. The main difficulty lies in the fact that the tribes are not subordinate to any superior authority and in many cases have no recognised paramount Shaikh, and every one therefore is demanding his share pf the filthy lucre. A satisfactory arrangement has been reached with the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi regarding his responsibility for the Manasir tribesmen who have been raiding Dubai and his quotas of wheat and sugar have been restored to him. The Political Officer Trucial Coast is now proceeding with negotiations for the delimit ation of the boundary between Abu Dhabi and Dubai. The Air Agreement with the Shaikh of Sharjah expires in July next. He has been given notice of His Majesty’s Governments desire to renew the Agreement unless a new one is negotiated in the meanwhile. The terms of the present agreement require revision in many respects and new one is under preparation. MUSCAT By the courtesy of the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf I was able to visit Muscat and Gwadur in H.M.S.’’wren” in the first half of the month. At Muscat I exchanged official calls with the Sultan who has recently returned after an absence of over a year in Dhofar, and had several conversations with him. I found him in good health, but he was looking a little older and grey has appeared in his beSrd. He is somewhat exercised in hsi mind over his future relations with India and Pakistan. He appears to consider himself bound by the 1939 Treaty so far as India is concerned, but was doubtful if it governed his relations with Pakistan in the absence of any formal accession by that Dominion. I gathered that he would raise no objection to the appointment of an Indian Consul or Vice Consul at Muscat and that he might wish to appoint his own Trade Agent in Bombay. He raised certain questions of local protocol which he considered should be adjusted on the basis of international practice. Under the Government of India, such matters were made to conform to a certain extent with those prevailing in the Indian States. I discussed with him the question of Gwadur, and his general,attitude is that although he would not greatly objebt to leasing or selling the place to His Majesty’s Government he does not like the idea of handing it over to Pakistan or India, He lunched on board H.M.S. Wren during the ship’s presence in the harbour and was accorded all the appropriate honours. A hockey match was played between the local team and the ship’s team, in which the former were victorious, I spent the inside of a day at Gwadur where I exchanged calls with the Wali, met the Agha Kbnnl an* H5n*n ^^^cha^t? and discussed the local situation „ith the dritisn /igenc ana -che Sultan’s Administrator. In company of the Political Agent and Commander Martin of H.M.S*’’Wren', I attended a large tea party given by the Agha Khani community. The Wali an Arab, is out of touch with the people who are Baluchis, and the Agha Khani and Hindu merchants are entirely concerned with their own profit. Prices are high, but the local people who live chiefly on fish and dates are reasonably contented and according to reports are much better off than their brethren in the adjoining parts of Mekran. Nothing further has been heard of the Khan of Kalat’s designs upon Gwadur and owing to the Pakistan Government’sof C Mfvr»n 0I \ ? f &lt; Na Uf b u Bal Kh f n Glchkl as the independent ruler himself rL^M. per ! lapS unl i kel y that the Khan will interest himself in Gwadu*, at any rate for some time to come. MISCELLANEOUS w . , |he Persian Government have forbidden the Cable and or to Bahrein 1011 l* Bushlr e to accept or transmit messages from bv r&gt;n&lt;jt a frnm n ih Bom ® mes sages for Bahrain have been forwarded for Bushfre P ? st 0f f^ e and “assages from Bahrain xor nusnire are now being transmitted via Kuwait. EC ON QMIC SUPPLEMENT General Tnnniai „ The .P rlc ® of wheat at Bahrain, Muscat and on the ner toi C thanVs e tn 1 *2 at a f? irl y reasonable level viz. £.35 nnLrn»!,,+ ank ? 4 . t £ the supplies arranged by His Majesty's hfl^h^n 111 ’^ ^ Kuwait, the population has increased and there has been a drain on local supplies to Saudi Arabia, and in consequence the price in the open market is reported to be nronosw hn 0 ? 1 £,0 °' a ton. His Majesty's Government are proposing to increase the Kuwait wheat quota to meet the needs of coLro? ^? a ! in £i P °? Ula 1 tl0n - The P rlce °f wheat on toe east coast of Saudi Arabia is also reported to be very high. with T.e ffa v^ d f rS are await ed regarding the policy to be followed 1 J c i lrr ?i lcy ; The Indian Rupee is the currency tribes^whoM^ th t w e Gul£ territories except among the Muscat mfit u’ Who us f J he Ma rta Theresa Dollar. The Pakistan Govern- the ordinarv W T^i :r0dUCed thelr own cur rency and announced that Pakista£ aftJ c 'ren C ywlll no longer be legal tender in September next. The Sultan of Muscat is anxious Maria Th^rp^n^i 1 !^ Ru P ee a f the only currency (other than the dollar) acceptable for State purposes, but is awaiting advice on the subject. p ’ is an nnoffin^ 110568 merchants of the Gulf were raised by an unofficial report that the Government of India were lifting tot ban on the import of pearls. No reply has been received fr^ Bahrain e aSd e Kuwai'i- I Shi a h t0 re P£ esell tations from the Shaikhs of nanrain and Kuwait which were forwarded to them but in renlv conaignmcn+ n hh wh f ch wa f made to them regarding a particular consignment they have stated that licenses for the import of pearls are now being granted freely. The Government of°India export or 6 imnort°nf 0Wln f a . system of issuing licenses for th e d without°st&gt;eM?v^n^ i-n 00 ^® fro ® or t °, the Gul f to Indian merchants r;^2^ Spec F yin f t0 whom or from whom the goods are to be exported or imported. As a reault of this, Indian merchants are imnoitQ 1 ? 2 ex P° r t® to the highest bidder and refusing to buy forced to fr0m Muscat &gt; unt tl the producers are 7 have been at a n uneconomic price. Representations have been made to the Government of India on the subject. In S0 J e ,5 ases the Government of India appear to be Pakistan anf'thi^hp. 6 ® f °ii. t !? e &lt; Gu i f States more freely than for ^aKistan, and this has resulted in trade in certain articles. e.g. matches from India to Pakistan being conducted via Dubai. 4 -^ -d boat services from the United Kins- of^ t0 -! Ba ? rain which called at Kuwait in both directions have^ resoect y of e hntb anCelle ^ thereb y ca ^sing much inconvenience in respect of both passengers and mails. It is understood that of the OU n Compantos. iS t0 ** substituted 11108 ^ toe benefit onotfl nf !!J!!! ert0 , the J uwait Su PP 1 y Department has imported the rat^onpH f eg 2u dS a ^? tted by the Government of India and tioned it to the public. Lately owing to the inferiorquality of the goods received and the availability of supplies from other sources, it has been unable to dispose of its stocks and has suffered heavy loss. It has accordingly decided to cease the rationing of piecegoods and to leave it to the local merchants to import the quota from India if they wish to avail themselves of it* MUSCAT A representative of the Imperial Bank of Iran is at present at Muscat and has made considerable progress in negot*- iations with the Sultan for opening a branch of the Bank there. Meanwhile the Eastern Bank who had sent a representative to Muscat to make preliminary enquiries in February have also decided to open a branch there provided they can be given a monopoly. The Sultan has agreed to give a hearing to their representative who is expected to arrive there on the 13th May, and&gt; in the meanwhile to defer signing an agreement with the Imperial Bank of Iran* Muscat has had 7 or 8 inches of rain after 3 years drought and good rain has fallen in the Oman hills. Consequently a number of Omanis who had left for other parts of the Gulf in search of employgient are returning to their homes. The Sultan has forwarded to the Political Agent a state ment of his Government 1 s accounts for the year 1947. The total State expenditure was Hs*1,241,826 and the total income Rupees 2,294,964. Dhofar is not covered by the Statement and there is a separate account for Gwadur showing expenditure of about’ i lakh and %n income of about 2£ lakhs which is alsmot entirely derived from Customs. I saw deputations from the various mercantile communit ies during my visit to Muscat and they repeated their demands for a bank at Muscat. They are exporting dried fish to Colombo and shark 1 s fins to Hong Kong but are unable to obtain remittances against the s^le of these articles. They also •complained about the tactics employed by the Indian merchants who have been given licenses for the import of dried dates, to which I have referred above. At present the Indian merchants are refusing to utilise their licenses until the impossibility of exporting dried dates by country craft owing to the monsoon and the repening of a new crop forces prices down. • I have already referred to general conditions at Gwadur in the main portion of this letter. The Sultan's Administrator who is an Indian from the Baluchistan Administration, is making valiant efforts to effect a fair distribution of the quotas of sugar, grain, piecegoods etc. in the teeth of the oppositon of the Wali, the Baluchi headmen and the merchants, who have in the past been # exporting these articles on their own account to Persian Mekran where very high prices are obtainable. I received complaints about the price of wheat which is more than double that prevailing at Karachi but is reasonable compared with prices current in the Middle'East generally. A fequest was made for the import from Karachi of broken rice which is one of the staple foods of the fisher-folk in this part of the world, and I have written to the Pakistan Government on the subject. Gwadur continues to be entrepot for illicit trade. Rice from' . Kuwait and liquor, probably from Goa, are being smuggled into Pakistan via Gidani a small fishing village close to the Sind border, while rice which is being smuggled in from Sind is being sent on to Persia and the* Gulf ports. A Municipal Committee has been formed at Gwadur but the sanitation is still extremely bad and the place is black with flies. A doctor and a sanitary inspector have been engaged and are expected to arrive shortly, Yours sincerely,) COMFIDEMTIAL No.675-S 'few. J&amp; r- OT f'*- r** I b b t o Dated the 29th March, X94&amp;-io ! i J M- 0 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN Dear Burrows, The following is a summary of events in the Persian Gulf for March. % G ENERAL Wither. The weather during the month has been except ional. There was much rain in the first ten days except in Kuwait and since then there has been a succession of strong winds causing a certain amount of loss to country craft and disorganising shipping schedules. The temperature has been abnormally low. Visitors. Visitors to the Residency during the month have included Mr. Troutbeck, the Head of the British Middle East Office in Cairo, Brigadier Clayton, his Political Adviser, Mr. Morrison, First Secretary (Information) H.M’s Embassy, Baghdad, and Mr. Charles of the B.I.S.M.E. All of these except Mr. Charles have also visited Kuwait. A preliminary note has been received from Mr. Morrison containing his suggestions for the future public relations organisation in the Persian Gulf. Government of Indian Consular Representation . The Government of India have intimated that they hope to station a whole-time Trade Agent in Bahrain who will perform a certain number of consular functions for Indian nationals and have enquired what arrangements can be made for his accommodation, iit Muscat they propose to appoint a non-career Vice-Consul who will be subordinate to the Trade Agent at Bahrain. When they appoint Consuls in Iraq they propose to arrange that one of them should be responsible for the interests of Indians in Kuwait. BAHRAIN % During the month the Shaikh forwarded to the Political Agent a list os his claims in Zubarah but it had to be returned to him owing to the incomplete nature of the information supplied. The Political Agent is about to tackle him once again on the old and thorny question of the A1 Khalifah allowances.which has hither to been paid from his personal share of the oil royalties should in future be defrayed from general revenues. The Shaikh showed great distress when Mr. Belgrave recently indicated to him that he might wish to retire when he reaches the age of 55 in December 1949 and offered to raise Mr. Belgrave’s salary. The Shaikh said that Mr. Belgrave and his Hindu secretary Mr, Narayan, were the only two persons in Bahrain in whom he could place any trust. • K UWAIT I visited Kuwait from the 12th to the 16th March and saw much of Shaikh Ahmed who was in good health and spirits in spite oT a recent attack of bronchitis. There is no sign yet hhat his head has been turned by the articles about his wealth which h-ve appeared recently in the British press and copies of which were forwarded to him by his friends or agents. him about the appointment of a British financial Adviser and he said that he was still anxious for this B.A.B, Burrows, Esquire, Foreign Office, Downing Street, LONDON t S.W.l but must,..\ A - page 2 - ii jTL ... I £T“ f* ^ jt* 5bo6 the proposal li^ but must prepare the ground and I understand that ,1s meeting with a certain amount of resistance frofci the leader of the opposition Shaikh Abdullah Salim. The Shajikhhd^^^ 6 ^ ^ the General Secretary of the Dutch Reformed Church ffllysforr —f find him an American doctor to take over responsibility for the medical administration of the State and coordinate the work of the numerous Egyptian and Syrian doctors employed by the State who are at present quarelling with one another over the question of seniority. The Shaikh informed me that up to date he only recognised four competitors for the Neutral Zone concession viz . the Iraq Petroleum Company, the Burma Oil Company, the Gulf Oil Corporation and the American Independent Oil Company and that he has asked all these Companies to send representatives to Kuwait in May when he hopes to terminate the auction. The highest bid received up to date is from the American Independent Oil Company. Work on the new road between the Customs pier and the m^in square is proceeding apace and many houses have been demolished. The new hospital is still without equipment and is likely to remain so for a long time* A bore has been made for water within the city walls to the depth of 2000 feet but nothing potable was found and the Shaikh has now asked the Kuwait Oil Company to try another bore at a place outside the walls. During the month a Sadun and two other Muntafiq tribesmen who had visited Kuwait territory for smuggling completely dis appeared. They are believed to have been murdered by Shaikh Subah an Nasir who is running a rival smuggling organisation, but their bodies have not yet been found. This gentleman is a notorious character who some years ago shot his brother who was sitting beside him in his car while driving through the town and threw the body out on to the road and deliberately ran over it. Under Shaikh Ahmed's orders he and his family have been brought in from Jahrah which they had made their headquarters and Shaikh Subah is now not allowed to leave Kuwait. It is probable that the As Subah family will offer to pay blood-money for the three men. Apart from this hostility between the Muntafiq tribesmen and the Mutair of Saudi Arabia is leading to a certain amount of insecurity within Kuwait borders and/special precautions are being taken for the safety of travellers on the Kuwait - Basrah road. TRUCIAL COAST Mr. Judd of the Ministry of Works Cairo visited Sharjah and Dubai to select a site for a residence for the Political Officer Trucial Coast. He agrees with local officers that a site proposed on the west bank of the Dubai creek is the best one. Mr. Thesiger has arrived at Abu Dhabi after completing a journey across the Rub al Khali from the Hadhramaut. He proposes now to travel to Muscat by camel via Buraimi and' the Jebel Akhdar. It is understood that Ibn Saud when t(e learnt of his arrival in Saudi Arabian limits on his way to Abu Dhabi ordered his arrest but that Mr. Philby interceded for him and obtained permission for him to proceed. Mr. Philby then went out a few days' journey from Riyadh and met him in the desert. The people of Kalba have agreed to accept Shaikh Hunaid bin Muhammad as Regent in place of Shaikh Khalid, and Shaikh Humaid, who has been approached informally has agreed to accept the regency if appointed. Recommendations are being made to His Majesty's Government accordingly. Shaikh Humaid is the eldest brother of Shaikh Saqr bin Muhammad who has recently seized the Sheikhdom of Ras al Khaimah, MUSCAT The Sultan returned to Muscat from Salalah on the 10th March in the 'British Baron' /which was kindly put at his disposal i by the • • •- page 3 - 4 a w ■ * n; JL“^ by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, The Political] Agent has discussed many subjects with him since and’ I am proposing to pay! him a visit at the beginning of April. He is un iwill ingT^ seli; Gwadur to the Khan of Kalat but the Political AgenTThThltA'tfiat he would not be sorry to part with the place if he could do so with honour. He is much concerned over the constitutional changes in India and would probably like to bring the Indian and Pakistani subjects living in his State under his own juris diction, but there is a possibility that he will allow matters to remain as they are until the present Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation with His Majesty 1 s Government and the Government of India expires in 1951. I referred in my last report to Major Bird's proposed expedition to Oman on behalf of Petroleum Concessions Limited. He only proceeded a short way beyond Buraimi when he was stopped by the A1 Bu Shamis a tribe nominally under the jurisdiction of the Sultan of Muscat who made exorbitant demands. He returned to Sharjah to obtain instructions. The Sultan who has been informed of his proposed journey has raised no objection up to the present but has intimated that he will do so later if anything is done which impinges upon his authority. It is understood that in particular he is likely to object if the Company enter into anything in the nature of a formal agreement with any of the tribes. The Company at present propose to obtain letters of invitation from the various Shaikhs in return for specified sums of money but will avoid giving anything to the Shaikhs in writing themselves. M ISCELLANEOU S I returned from Kuwait by a slow mail steamer which called at Bushire where we were delayed for more than 24 hours by bad weather. • Dr. Easey, the Vice-Consul, with -whom I had a few outstanding questions to discuss had to be lifted on board in a basket. At the invitation of the American Minister at Jedda I visited Ras Tanura on the 25th March to attend functions held on board the United States aircraft carrier 'Valley Forge 1 ’. His Royal Highness the Amir Sa'ud and a number of other Saudi Arabian notables were present. We steamed out to sea to witness a display of the aircraft but the programme unfortunately had to be cut short owing to bad visibility. In the evening I attended an enormous dinner party given by the Amir Sa’ud at Dammam when between 200 and 250 whole roasted sheep were arrayed on the table. Mr. Philby who was of the party accompanied me on my return to Bahrain the following morning and spent the day as my guest. G ENERAL ECONOMIC SUPPLEMENT It is reported that two representatives of the Chase National Bank of America have visited Ras MLsha'ab to examine the possibility of opening a branch there. If such a branch is opened dollar transactions by Kuwait and Bahrain merchants will be greatly facilitated. C OMMUNICATION S The B.O.A.C. flying-boat services from the United Kingdom to Bahrain have been reduced from three to two, and both these services are now calling at Kuwait instead of Basra. A new B.O.A.C.'flying-boat service calling at Bahrain and terminating at Kuwait has be'en instituted. The Iraqi Airways service, via Bahrain to Karachi which was instituted in the latter, half of February is now only going as far as Sharjah owing to the i quarantine restrictions imposed in Iraq on travellers from India, f The aircraft usually travel more than half empty. The Kuwait Oil Company have selected a site for a new airfield • • t •\ page 4 - 'i airfield at Kuwait. Budgetary allotment and probably His Majesty’s Government’s approval are awaited before work on it is started. B AHRAIN The supply of livestock from Persia is now satisfactory. Its expert from Persia is prohibited but owing to the corruption and inefficiency of the preventive staff can be effected with little difficulty. The Bahrain Petroleum Company had 6078 employees on its rolls on the 31st December 1947. The number of British European employees had risen from 433 to 497 and the number of American employees decreased from 165 to 92 since the 31st December 1946. K UWAIT At Kuwait there is a shortage of wheat and an abundance of other commodities especially sugar and tea. The report that wheat from Kuwait had been purchased by the Government of India which I mentioned in ny last letter was found to be incorrect. The purchase was made from Kut in Iraq tnd not Kuwait. Owing to the large stock of sugar the price fell as low as that prevailing in the United Kingdom but rose again when it was announced that restrictions had been placed on the export of sugar from the United Kingdom to the Gulf ports. Sugar, tea and motor vehicles are being exported to other Gulf ports. I am informed that the only articles which it is now profitable tc smuggle to Iraq are sugar and cement. The Kuwait Oil Company are now purchacing rupees for sterling from the local bank to the extent of £.350,000 a month and this sum represents local earnings. In spite of this the accounts^ of most of the local merchants are overdrawn as they prefer to put all their money into imports rather than deposit it in the bank or invest it in securities. I mentioned^in my last report that geld was being smuggled to India via Kuwait. Further information has been received tc the effect that this gold is mostly in the form of Mexican 50 pesa pieces. ilt is purchased by Kuwait merchants with dollars which they obtain mostly from Bahrain, and it is reported that 350,000 dollars have recently been imported to Kuwait from this source. The gold is smuggled into India by country craft via Cutch. The Kuwait merchants are now somewhat embarrassed because the rupees for which they sell the gold ip India are frozen in, that country and are now endeavouring the find goods m India which it will be profitable to import to Kuwait. \ MISCELLANEOUS When I travelled to Kuwait I flew close over Has Misha’ab where about 400 Americans are now encamped inside a wire fence 8 feet high. Much material has already been unloaded and the pipes are expected tc begin to arrive within the next 2 or 3 weeks. These are to be carried from an unloading base in the sea to the shore by a rope railway. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company have opened an office at the port. Yours sincerely, (SGD) W.R, Hay •LB’CONFIDENTIAL D.0.No.540-3 V' h * r - ■ . ^3 ' “ ® ^ l? - PERSIAN GULF RESljlE i S’ ^ BAHRAIN _ Dated the 8th March 1948 JNDEXED ^ HZyf _ The following is a summary of events in tn^yersian Gulf for February. ^ G ENERA L &lt;f.e. / ( / ^ . On the whole the month has been uneveniwdl and there have been few visitors. Suaraniine: Lt-Colonel W.J. Moody, late arrived at the beginning of the month and has taken over charge as Medical Adviser to the Political Resident and Chief Quarantine Medical Officer Persian Gulf. He has already submitted proposals for a quarantine organisation for the Bahrain Petroleum Company's port at Sitra. He visited Kuwait during the month and has now left for Muscat. SIay£_Trade; The three women reported by me last month to be detained in Buraimi have been released. The Shaikh of Fujairah has also succeeded in releasing at no small expense to himself a - 16 year old Persian girl who was abducted from near Kalba in December. The relatives of the girl first O/f all approached the Regent of Kalba and on hig failing to assist them applied to the Shaikh of Fujairah. BA HRAIN * During the month I gave the Shaikh a long hearing on the everlasting question of his rights in Zubarah. He had^' previously been warned that as long ago as 1876 His Majesty’s Government had stated that the Shaikh of Bahrain could not be permitted to interfere on the mainland, and that in 1945 he had been told in writing that the Political Resident could not support his claims to Zub^rah. He stated definitely that his claims were of a private nature and was asked to. prepare a detailed statement of them and of his evidence in support of them. On his being told that the matter would be one for friendly settlement with the Shaikh of Qatar and that it would not be possible to issue anything in the nature of an order on the subject he remarked that there was no hope of iieaching any decision. I • The official reactions of the Bahrain Petroleum i Company to Hi s Majesty’s Government's decision regarding the I division of the sea bed between Bahrain and Qatar are still awaited. Petroleum Concessions Ltd. have replied that they consider that the Dibal and Jaradeh reefs should have been assigned to Qatar as they are connected by shoals with the penin sula. * ' *7' As a result of Abdullah Zireh’s antics in the Majlis at Tehran the Shaikh is anxious to reduce the Persian population in Bahrain and has proposed that any Persian leaving Bahrain for his mother-country should not be allowed to return. Meanwhile Abdullah Zireh is writing articles in support of the Persian claim to Bahrain in the Persian Press. The Bahrain ’’Union of Youth” has sent a telegram to Reuters protesting against the Persian claim and repudiating Abdullah Zireh’s action. L letter has been received from the Government of India stating that they, have received complaints of the persecut ion of Indian nationals by Muslims and asking for particulars. F.A.K. Harrison, Esquire. Commonwealth Relations Office, /go far as LONDON. S.W.l2 7 7 4?. So far as I know there has been no trouble as between Pakistani Muslims and Hindus but the majority of the Sikhs against whom 3 as I reported last month 3 there have been some threats have now left Bahrain. KUWAIT As / . * Representatives of the Superior Oil Company of_America visited Kuwait early in the month to compete for the Kuwait Neutral Zone concession but were received coldly and did not make any offer as the Shaikh demanded that they should produc&lt;.. a banker's reference first. Another bid has been made by^the Burma Oil Company. It is understood that the only competitors with whom the Shaikh is at present satisfied are the Burma Oil Company, Petroleum Concessions I:tdo 9 the Gulf Oil Company (American) and the American Independent Oil Company. ^ At the request of the American Vice-Consul at Basra, the shaikh has been informed that the United States State Department is not supporting any particular American bidder for the Neutral Zone concession but that it approves of all reputable companies participating in the bidding. Mr. Jordan, an American, has been appointed Manager of the Kuwait Oil Company in the place of the late Mr, Patrick. QATAR 7’ The first flow of oil since Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. started drilling again after the plugging of their wells during the war took place during the month. It is custom ary to burn the first oil that issues from a well and^the Shaikh of Qatar asked that as much as possible should be ignited in order that the flames might be seen by the Shaikh of Bahrain. TRUCIAL COAST J I paid a visit to the Trucial Coast in the ,, Nearchus M at the end of the month. Our first halt was at Halul Island which belongs to Abu Dhabi but lies at some distance from the east coast of Qatar. The island which was a mass of verdure after the recent rains was surveyed by the Captain of the 'Nearchus' as it may be necessary to locate a .light there when oil shipments from Qatar begin. There is very good fishing round the island and there are reported to be some oil seepages in the sea close to it. We were next compelled by the weather to take refuge in the lee of Sir bu Na'air island which belongs to Sharjah. ^ This island is normally uninhabited but there at are at present about 150 men there working on the red oxide deposit. We sailed from there to Abu Dhabi where I exchanged calls with the Shaikh. We proceeded next to Sharjah where the 'Nearchus' anchored for three days. During this tine I exchanged calls with the Shaikhs of Sharjah, Dubai, Ajman and Umm al Qaiwain and also visited the Jiri valley under the Ruus el Jabaal mountains where I met the new and not yet recognised Shaikh of Ras al Khaimah. I visited the R.A.F. camp at Sharjah and inspected possible sites for a new residence for the Political Officer Trucial Coast at Sharjah and Dubai. f' The Shaikh of Abu Dhabi has promised to send his brother to Buraimi to try to persudde the Manasir to make their peace with the Shaikh of Dubai . The brother is to see the Political Officer at Sharjah and inform him of the results of his mission. The Shaikh is averse to giving authority to the Political Officer to fix the boundary between Abu Dhabi and Dubai until his quarrel with Government is settled. His quotas of wheat and sugar are still bewwithheld owing to his refusal to restrain the Manasir from hostile action against Dubai. In his conversation with me he referred somewhat vaguely to his claim to Umm Said where the Oil Company propose to construct their port on the east coast of Qatar. He has already been informed that h this claim cannot be entertained and it is understood that he is not likely to press it. It is doubtful if he knows where exactly Umm Said is and he called the place by a wrong name when3 he first wrote to the Political Agent about it. Hs- me that he had reached a friendly settlement with Mr. .Lermitte of Petroleum Concessions Ltd. about the annual payment due to him from the Company which, as I reported last month, he had refused to accept. 10 ' The Shaikh of Sharjah can produce a better Arab meal than any other Shaikh on the Trucial Coast but apart from this has little to commend him. He is unable to maintain order in his Sheikhdom and there have been numerous complaints of thefts from the R.A.F. camp. The guards supplied by the Shaikh himself are believed to be responsible and he is being informed that compensation for the losses will be recovered from the payments made to him for these guards. //' During the month, while the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah, Sultan bin Salim, was absent in Sharjah, his nephew Saqr bin Muhammad, seized his fort and imprisoned his relatives. There was no bloodshed or disturbance and the relatives were subsequent ly released. Shaikh Saqr came to see me with his old father, Shaikh Muhammad, who ruled for a time as Shaikh before Sultan, in the Jiri valley and promised that if he were recognised as Shaikh he would observe all the treaties and angagements entered into by his predecessors. Shaikh Sultan was a most unsatisfact ory ruler and spent much of his time in Sharjah and Dubai where he has acquired property. Shaikh Saqr, although one-eyed and by no means imposing in - appearance, is reported to have some strength of character and to be well liked by the people and it is probable that I shall recommend him for recognition by His Majesty’s Government. / L' There have been no further developments in Kalba affairs. The Political Agent, Bahrain is to visit Kalba early in March with a view to making recommendations regarding the future of the Regency. v ft Tribesmen under the nominal control of Muscat or Sharjah continue to raid caravans fin the Wadi el Qaur through which the road between the Trucial and Batinah coasts passes. Most of the road in this area is within the jurisdiction of the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah who up to the present has been unable to^protect it. If any depredation is committed on the subjects of the Shaikhs of Fxas al Khaimah or Sharjah or of the Sultan of Muscat on this route it goes unpunished and unavenged. - It is only when robbers loot the subjects of Dubai or Fujairah travelling by it that they are brought to book by the Shaikhs of Dubai and Fujai rah themselves avenging their subjects in Sharjah and Ras al Khaimah limits. The Muscat authorities recently recovered some looted property by paying more than it was worth. ^ ■ Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited are^ now carrying out exploratory operations near the coast 130 miles to the west of Abu Dhabi. Major Bird, date of the Indian Political Service, who is now employed by this company, has arrived on the Trucial Coast and is about to start on an expedit ion to Dhank, Ibri and beyond. He hopes to meet the Imam and to finish up by travelling up the Wadi Samail to Muscat in order to meet the Sultan. He is taking with him only two trucks and his object is to pave the way for a visit by a larger party to j\ this area next year. The Sultan is aware of the Company's ^ intentions and has neither approved nor objected. MUSCAT The Political Agent reports that there is a good deal of grumbling and discontent amongst all classes at Muscat and that this tends to focus itself on the Sultan. The causes are the economic depression and the corruption and inefficiency of the officials left in charge during the Sultan's prolonged absences I in Dhofar. The Sultan is under no delusions regarding his i ^ ♦ officials and has for some years now been asking us to find him ^ a British adviser to whom he can entrust the administration ofir Muscat while he is in Dhofar. Unfortunately as previously reported our efforts to find a suitable incumbent have so far been unsuccessful. i 0 ' An Anglo-Iranian Oil Company tanker is to pick up the Sultan at Salalah on the 9th March, Mr. Altounyan of Petroleum Development (Dhofar) Ltd. has now reached Dhofar with a survey party and was reported to be leaving for the interior on t e 23rd February. $ H There has been some trouble in Muscat over the grant of visas to an American missionary, Mr. Kapenga, and his wife without the prior consent of the Muscat Government. The Sultan s Secretary at one time intended to ask Mr. Kapenga to leave Muscat but the Political Agent succeeded in dissuading him from this course. The Political/Agent reports some deterioration m relations between the American Mission and the Muscat Government during the past few months and as I have previously reported an order was issued a few months ago for the Mission School to be closed. It is hoped that the situation will improve with the Sultan’s return. ECONOMIC I General: Good rain has fallen in all the Gulf States including Muscat”and as a result there is excellent grazing for camels and flocks. f' In past years the Gulf States have received their quotas of sugar from India. During the last few months some of the States have found it possible to import sugar without any restrictions from the United Kingdom. In future the supply oi sugar to the States is to 'be controlled by means of allocations to exporters in the United Kingdom. Kuwait: ^' The Kuwait authorities have asked for an increased wheat quota which at present stands at 600 tons^a month owing to large purchases by tribesmen from Saudi Arabia and an increase in the local population due to the Oil Company’s operations.^ Meanwhile a report which is being investigated has been received that wheat has actually been sold by Kuwait to the Government of India at an exorbitant price. 2i. The Political Agent reports that gold which apparent ly originates from France is being brought to Kuwait from Beirut and being sent from there to India. ^ The Kuwait Oil Company’s junior staff which consists . largely of Indians went on strike for two days during the month owing to the alleged poor quality of the food supplied to them. They returned to work on being promised better food. ^ Efforts still continue to provide Kuwait with a better drinking water supply. The Shaikh’s Secretary, Abdullah Mullah recently drilled on his own land to a depth of 700 feet without any success. The Kuwait Oil Company as a result of repeated requests by the Shaikh are now boring to a depth of 2000 feet within the town limits, but they have little hope of any better result. Meanwhile the supply of somewhat brackish, water from a well out in the desert, which was brought into the town by the Kuwait Oil Company when the Iraqi quarantine restrictions cut^ off the normal supply from the Shatt-al-Arab, is being piped into various tanks in the town and there mixed with Shatt-al-Arab wate for sale to the public*. At the request of a B.O.A.C. representative the_ Political Agent has arranged -with the Shaikh for an alighting area for flying-boats to be made available in the Kuwait Bay when required. It is understood that the B.O.A.C. will shortly start a flying-boat service va via Kuwait. /Trucial Coast.. .Trucial Coas t: The economic depression migration of many of the local population to vwirn ;| ^ g a ji. is leading to the find work in Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Bahrain and elsewhere and the Political Officer reports that he is receiving about 200 applications a day for travel documents. This is all to the good at present as labour is badly required by the oil companies. I visited the Dubai te bazaar during my recent tour. It is one of the most picturesque bazaars in the East and is still well stocked though it did not appear quite as busy as when I visited it last year. The, Manager of the branch of the Imperial Bank of Iran at Dubai reports that the merchants are using the bank more than they used to and he appears to be satisfied with the progress it is making. f) ( rC Mr. Pocock is working the red oxide deposits on the islands of Bu Musa and Sir Bu Na'air on behalf of the Golden Valley Ochre Company of Bristol. . The target for the current season is 3000 tons. From 150 to 200 coolies are employed on each island. It is understood that the deposits are likely to be worked out within a comparatively short period. 4 1 r Umm al Qaiwain the headquarters of one of the Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms which is situated on a sand spit is suffering owing to a steady deterioration in the quality of the drinking water obtainable from local wells. It is doubtful whether there is any remedy other tha,n distillation. Muscat ; 1% As on the Trucial Coast there is considerable economic distress at Muscat due to high prices, low wages, lack of employment and the stagnation of trade. Many Muscat subjects have left to seek employment at Kuwait and elsewhere. The Muscat Government has now placed a ban on the emigration of certain classes of artisans for fear of a shortage of skilled labour. Mr. Findlay of the Eastern Bank Ltd. visited Muscat during the month and has submitted' his report to his principals It is hoped that as a result the Bank may decide to send a more senior representative to enter into negotiations with the Sultan with a view to opening a branch at Muscat before the next date export season 'opens in July, Dr. Bertram has completed his examination of the fisheries in Muscat and Dhofar and is preparing a report for the Sultan. He considers that there is’ scope for very considerable ! development in the local fisheries and that a strong case could / be made out for the United Kingdom Overseas Food Corporation to | interest itself in Southern Arabian waters on a large scale. 11, * 0 ' t&amp;'&amp;l Maritim e. H.M.S.'Wren” joined th,e 'Nearchus 1 ' for part of my Trucial Coast tour and accompanied her to Abu Dhabi and Sharjah. The Shaikhs of Abu Dhabi, Sharjah and Dubai called on Commander J.C.G. Martin, R.N., the Command ing Officer H.M.S. ,, Wren M and received their salutes. H.M.S. Challenger” was at Halul Island, where she was establishin'g a small party to Observe the tides. During the last two or three months she has been continuing the survey of the waters off the east coast of Qatar which was begun last winter.CONFIDENTIAL D.O. No.350 -S ! « ™ o 120 '--lOa : 9 IN D EX ED PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN the 9th February, • The /following is a summary of events in the Persia Gulf for January, i At the request of the British Middle East Office I have included the economic information in a separates supplement. 1 ^ GENERAL New _Year f s Day . New Year ! s Day was celebrated with the usual functions at the Residency and Political Agencies. These celebrations are derived from the former observance of Proclam ation Day in India and are being continued as the heat renders His Majesty's Birthday in Jun unsuitable for celebrations on a large scale, I held a reception at Jufair which was attended by His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain with his relations and a number of local notables and by the leading British and American residents. The Royal Navy very kindly provided a Guard of Honour for the Shaikh. Visitors. His Excellency the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, Admiral Sir Arthur Palliser, K.C.B., D.S.C. visited Bahrain, Kuwait and Sharjah in H.M.S.'Norfolk' and numbrous functions were held at his ports of call. He also visited Ras Tanura where he was met by Mr. Trott, His Majesty's Ambassador at Jeddah. Mr. Trott took the opportunity of paying a brief visit to Bahrain and of discussing with me outstanding cases of mutual interest. &lt; The Rt. Honourable Mr. Anthony Eden, P.C., M.C., paid brief visits to Bahrain and Kuwait. The Shaikh of Bahrain greeted him with the greatest enthusiasm and provided a large Guard of Honour with a band, a sumptuous lunch, and an old Arab sword in a scabbard of gold set with pearls. The Shaikh of Kuwait entertained him to dinner. ^• Mr. Caccia, Sir Andrew Noble and Miss Ibson from the Foreign Office visited Bahrain and Kuwait in the latter half of the month and made-numerous enquiries and provided much useful advice preparatory to the taking over of the control of the Gulf Residency by the Foreign Office on the 1st April next. While the Foreign Office party were with us Mr. Douglas of the Ministry t of Works Cairo paid us a visit to discuss plans for the const- I ruction of a new Residency. With our increasing British staff and numerous visitors the question of accommodation at Bahrain is at present very acute. r £ps tal_A rrangements . Mr. Breach from the. G.P.O. arrived in Bahrain at the beginning of the month and has since visited Kuwait. He will assume charge as Superintendent of Post-Offices from the 1st April when His Majesty's Government are to take over responsibility for the Gulf post offices. / , MKh,Mn^_and_Buoyin£. I visited Basrah at the end of the monthto discuss with Colonel Johnson, the Director-General of Ports and Navigation, the transfer of responsibility for the buoying and lighting in the Gulf from the Government of India to His Majesty's Government. As far as can be foreseen there will be no difficulty in making this transfer effective as from the 1st April . ^ I Fade. ^ According to reports received from various sources there is a fairly regular though not very considerable traffic in slaves, mostly women and children, from the Mekran Coast to the Batmah Coast whence they are taken via Buraimi to Nejd. Women and children from the Trucial Coast are also being abduct-* ed and sold into slavery. Pressure is being brought to bear on .P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G.M|R - page 2 - /i the Shaikhs of Sharjah and Dubai to obtain the release of 3 women who are believed to be still detained in Buraimi and during the visit of the Commander-in-Chief East Indies L discuss ed with him the possibility of reviving previous instructions about the search of dhows for slaves by His Majesty's Ships particularly in the Gulf of Oman. BAHRAIN / His Highness the Shaikh is in gooci health but as ever is obsessed with the question of his rights in Zubarah. In addition to entertaining Mr. Eden to lunch he gave a dinner party for the Foreign Office party and on both occasions referr ed whenever possible to his 'huquq' (rights). He visited me with his uncles to make a formal representation regarding the ban on the import of pearls to India which as already reported is causing distress not only in Bahrain but in Qatar and on the Trucial Coast. I asked him to let me have a detailed represent ation on the matter to enable me to pursue it further with the / Government of India either direct or through His Majesty’s Government. With regard to the recent decision of His Majesty’s Government on the subject of the division of the sea bed between Bahrain and Qatar the Shaikh has protested that he has been deprived of a large area of the sea bed which was treated as appertaining to Bahrain in negotiations with an oil company 10 years ago and has asked for an assurance that private rights in property will not be affected by the decision. This assurance has been given him. ^ The Shaikh in asking for it referred specifically to fish traps but was also thinking of his ever lasting claim to Zubarah. When I visited Qatar early in the month I asked Shaikh Abdullah whether he would be willing to recognise any private rights of the A1 Khalifah in this place. He replied that so far as he was aware ail that the A1 Khalifah possessed there were graves and that if they liked they could dig these up and remove the contents to Bahrain. The outlook for some kind of compromise is not therefore at present very promising. The situation underground ’’Home Front’’ Mr. Eden’s visit at Bahrain has remained quiet but the is still active. Immediately after _ copy of a letter was said to have been delivered to him came to notice in which a demand was made for a legislative council, a trade union and the dismissal of Mr. Belgrave, and a threat was added that if these demands were not conceded an application would be made to the.Persian Govern ment to take over Bahrain. A week later a young Baharni (i.e. a^member of the_indigenous Shiah population) called Abdullah Zireh appeared in the Majlis at Tehran and asked the Persian Government to send a force to occupy Bahrain and then to hold an election for a deputy to_the Majlis. Much publicity was given to this incident in Persia and a brief Reuter’s message regarding it was announced from the Near East Broadcasting Station at Haifa The Shaikh was most indignant and requested that an announcement should be made that nobody entitled to represent Bahrain had gone to Tehran and that Bahrain was an independent Arab Shaikhdom in f treaty relations with Great Britain, but it is not known whether any announcement to ( this effect has actually been made. In Bahrain generally the incident appears to nave been taken very calmly and it is doubtful whether there are many in the Island who would really welcome a Persian occupation. The agitators are chiefly concerned to force the hand of the Shaikh and get rid of Mr. Belgrave. Jamal Hussain! Chairman of the Arab Higher Committee of Palestine arrived in Bahrain on the 24th and left the following morning for Riyadh. He spent the night with a Nejdi merchant in Manama. His presence in Bahrain gave rise to no demonstrations as little previous publicity had been given to it but the 'Home Front' is reported to have complained that Jamal Hussaini was not publicly welcomed by the Shaikh and to have suggested that his stay here on his return journey should be made the occasion of a drive for funds tojassist the Palestine Arabs. Fortunately he is belie\ed to have left Suadi Arabia- page 3 - by another way. /^■For the first time communal strife in India is being reflected in Bahrain. Notices have appeared in Manama threat ening the Sikhs, and the Muslim Indian employees of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. are reported to be arming themselves with knives in order to massacre the Company's Sikh employees. All the Sikhs in Manama and Qatar have accordingly made up their minds to return to India and are said to have booked their passages by a steamer sailing about the 22nd February. The B.O.A.C. at Manama and Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. will be severely handicapped by the loss of their Sikh artisans. The news of Mr. Gandhi's assasination caused genuine sorrow and Government offices and most of the shops in Manama were closed. / / 11 ' An Aeradio party of about 8 Europeans and 30 Indians under Mr. Hemelik has been established in the R.A.F. camp at Muharraq. It is not clear why such a large party is required but Mr. Hemelik has been very helpful in interpreting obscure correspondence about Notams and such matters which I have been receiving from the Regional Representative for the Middle East of the International Civil Aviation Organisation at Cairo. / Messrs. Price and Kimberly of the Rank Organisation have been visiting Bahrain and other oilfields in the Gulf. They explained to me that they were particularly anxious to illustrate the spanner in which the Oil Companies' activities had assisted in developing the Shaikhdoms on modern lines. I asked them not to forget that it was the work done in the past by the Royal Navy and British political officers serving under the Government of India which had - created the conditions which alone had made it possible for the oil companies to start operations. KUWAIT v Bidding for the Neutral Zone concession continues. Mr. Twitchell has put in a bid on behalf of the Sinclair interests and, it is understood, has proposed that 40$ of the oil produced should be the property of the Shaikh. The latter did not know that Mr. Twm.tchell had come to Kuwait to bid for the concession and has asked him to produce his credentials. A plane-load of Superior Oil Company magnates is expected at Kuwait at the beginning of February and they will no doubt help to keep the auction going. A representative of the Burma Oil Company is also expected at Kuwait in February. • Auart from this little of interest appears to have occurred locally during the month beyond the giving of parties to distinguished visitors, ihe only matter worth mentioning is the conclusion of an inform- al arrangement between the Kuwait and the Lebanon authorities through the intervention of Middle East Air Lines chat Kuwaitis / visiting the^Lebanon will be given visas on arrival. It is understood that a similar arrangement with the Syrian Government is likely to follow. Q ATaR ^' I Paid a short visit to Qatar at the beginning'of January and lunched with the aged Shaikh Abdullah. ' Although he near!y died recently and owing to his diabetes can only walk with difficulty I found him in very good spirits and talking about paying a v^it to Persia (for shooting) end India in the near future. lie sao.a that he accepted His Majesty's Govern- ment-s decision regarding the division of the saa bed between Bahrain and Qatar as an order which had to be complied with but that he could not of his free will surrender any Qatar territory. 1 have already recorded his remarks about Zubarah. He made a request for arms which will require consideration as the adminis tration of Qatar is of an extremely primitive character and it is desirable in view of the rapidly expanding activities of etroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. that the Shaikh should have some kind of police force at his disposal to assist him in -4 1 If %page 4 - &lt;~ 9 maintaining order. The Shaikh 1 s second son and heir-apparent spoke to me about the prohibition on the import of pearls to India and said that he personally had 5 lakhs of pearls for disposal. The Ath Thani family are more pearl merchants than tribal shaikns and are indeed lucky that the ungainly, barren peninsula which His Majesty's Government has recognised as being subject to their jurisdiction has been found to cover a vast v The 0Dly town in is the port of Dohah wh^re I found the bazaar well stocked, and inspected the American Mission s new dispensary - the first wave in the oncoming tide of civilisation. TRUCI AL COAST The Shaikh of Abu Dhabi is reported to be in a chastened frame of mind after the recent heavy defeat of the Manasir and the withholding of his wheat and sugar quotas is , In view °i &gt; the improvement in the situation the Shaikh of Dubai has demobilised his forces. 1 ■ The Shaikh of Abu Dhabi has refused to accept the annual payment due to him from Petroleum Development (Trucial boast; Ltd. under their prospecting concession. This is due to a disagreement regarding the interpretation of a clause in concession and is an annual move on the Shaikh's part. The Company s exploratory operations in Abu Dhabi territory are P eace n full y with results only known to themselves. Ihe Shaikh is able to control his tribesmen and maintain excell ent order within his Sheikhdom. - ,, T ^ e afi^irs of the Kalba Sheikhdom on the east coast oi the Musandam peninsula sre cuasing a certain amount of anxietv The Regent Shaikh Khalid is old and feeble and the minor Shaikh Hamad bin Said who is now about 18 years old is entirely useless qht£L neVer lively to be fit to be a ruler. The people of thf rdV f mi i r 2J ln f tc the sha i khd °m of Fujairah where better order is kept and the inhabitants of Khor Fakkan and two adioin- turned ou ^ Rsgent's representatives. The bnaiKh °f iujairah has never been recognised by His Majesty's Government as an independent Shaikh though he has sought such recognition in the past. MUSCAT ,, « ^ The ^ Sultan has asked for arrangements to be made with the Anglc-Iranian Oil Company for a tanker to pick him up at alalah^between the 4th^and 8th March and take him to Muscat. He has informed the Political Agent that on his return he is anxious to discuss amongst other things the effect on Muscat of in India. Efforts to find a British Minister of Foreign Affairs for Muscat still continue. Colonel Dowson who was recently interviewed by the Sultan at Salalah has ndw refused the appointment. /f* The Khan of Kalat has for some time been pressing for he rendition uo him of Gwadur. This is an enclave on the Mekran Coast which has been under the de facto sovereignty of T® 18th c ® ntur y- The Kh an recently approached li?, . J T Sl:y , 3 Government on the subject through one of his urninS 1 ^ 13 Wh ° aoave y ed a thinly vi£led threat that the place would be seized by force it it were not ceded. The matter has been b F oaahed with the Sultan. Meanwhile complaints have been received from Gwadur that the Khan's officials have Thp n «^no?f a r° ad in - 1 ? Pl ace that is claimed as Muscat territory, tU S bl0J ? f 3 cam P llca tod by the ambitions of Nawab Bai Khan Wh 5 ? lsbe ?.to set himself up as an independent ruler in and iS believed to h&amp;ve been intriguing with the Sultan's officials to obtain their support. s ; ■ ' W . 4 0 * Sri l' -vhpage 5 - / 3 f l r* . r ''i • f E CO N OM IC SOP P L E _ M E N ‘I 1 —£I^i=Ei^E ^ ^ Bshrain a.nd Km^o.i t continue to i Louristi thinks in part to the ready availability or black market dollars. ’ At the beginning of uhe month it was reported that the Arabian American Cil Company had expended a million dollars in thi^Bahrain bazaar on the purchase of rupees out this report is now iDel'i'e-ved- to be untrue or grossly exaggerated and I have been informed by the manager of the Eastern Bank that the Company are now purchasing their requirements of rupees which amount to 3 or 4 lakhs a month through him 9 and tho.t his bank* s transactions afford no evidence of any large-scale purchase of rupees in the ba'zaar. ' ^ahraln. The Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company has informed me that his Company's dollar expenditure is only 25% of its dollar earnings and that the latter areturrender^d to His Majesty's Treasury. All U.S. Navy tankers And ships flying the American and Norwegian flags are made to pay for their fuel’ in dollars 42. The Company are now experimenting with deep drilling in the Bahrain oil field. The present oil-bearing stratum lies at a depth of only about 3100 feet below the surface and it is hoped that a further stratum may be found at a greater depth. ^ 3 - . No less than 30,000 tons of goods are expected at Kuwait between the 19th January and the 29th February and owing to the poor landing facilities great difficulty is expected in dealing with this large amount of cargo, the bulk of which is consigned to the Kuwait Oil Company, ^4* A report has been received from Mr. Deeks Controller of Foreign Exchange in Iraq which alleges amongst other things * that Kuwait is the most notorious smuggling centre in the Middle East and^ that the economy of Iraq is being seriously affected by the Kuwaiti merchants' activities. A group of wealthy Kuwait merchants wish to float a 26 company with a capital of up to £.1,000.000 to construct a pipe line and pumping stations to bring fresh water from the Shatt- al-Arab to Kuwait. They maintain that they could obtain an undertaking from the Iraq Government not to interrupt the supply of water for any political or other reason. The Shaikh has informed the merchants that he will only sanction the project if His Majesty's Government guarantees the Iraq Government's under taking, well knowing that-such^guarantee will not be forthcoming. ^EBcial_£oast. There is serious distress on the Trucial Coast owing to the lack of employment, the poor pearling season and the ban on the import of pearls into India. Many of the people are unable to pay for wheat at its present price and a substant ial portion of the wheat quota has had to be surrendered. 27 / ’ Mu sca t. payment held in remains call at of the Eastern January but it in FebruarV* it will be* a The Reserve Bank of India has recently authorised the to local merchants of 3i lakhs from the large balances Muscat Treasury. Otherwise the economic situation there unchanged. Owing to the last-minute cancellation of a Muscat by a B.I.S.N. Company steamer, the representative Bank from Bahrain was unable to visit Muscat in is hoped that he will be able to go there early Even if the bank decides to open a branch there onsiderable time before it can be opened and mean while the trade of the place is likely tc suffer severely from existing restrictions. The B.I.S.No Company have refused to restore the fast mail service to Muscat but have now arranged for the slow mail steamers to call fortnightly in each direction. i •A</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000116_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3715B</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000116</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3715B</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/5(3) 'Bahrein [sic] Residency Monthly Letter - Summary of Events'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-28T18:41:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (125 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 127; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains copies of a monthly summary of events that was compiled by the Persian Gulf Residency in Bahrain (having moved there from Bushire in 1946).The diaries are separated into a number of different sections that vary slightly from month to month. In addition to reports concerning specific events or developments that took place during that particular month, most entries contain the following headings:the residencyvisitorstoursrelations with the USArelations with Saudi Arabiarelations with Persiarelations with Indiarelations with Iraqrelations with Pakistanoilcivil aviationBahrainMuscatTrucial Coasteconomic supplementquarantine and medicalslave tradeThe file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Annual reports</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bushire</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Political activities</topic></subject><subject><topic>Administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000116#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>