<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00020d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T20:05:39.465Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">lfo» r//^ 1926 Political Agency^ Bahrein Dated the 2nd July 1926 Prom Major C•K»Daly» I«A*» 0*I«E.&gt; Political Agent* Bahrein To The Accountant General# Central ReTenuee# Secretariat Buildings&gt; Raisina* Delki Sir, With reference to your letter No.T.A.253 dated the mn June 1926# I have the honour to state ttoat tMe usual forms for the preparation of the Annual Statements of Establishment as supplied heretofore, have not been received this year, which please expedite, when the statements will be completed and forwarded. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, C.I.E. Political Agent, Bahrein.A. G. c. R. No. 451. Office of the Accountant-General; Central Revenues. Telegraphic Address: Accottnts,'India. All communications to be addressed to the Accountant- General, Central Revenues. \w No. T.A.- Erom IMPERIAL SECRETARIAT BUILDINGS. Baisina (Delhi), the «•'* / . . **.*■*, Is 192 . T he ACCOUNTANT-GENEEAL, CENTRAL EEYENUES, To The Political.Agent, Bahrein. Persian Gul; No. of Enclosures, 3.' Sir, fith reference to your IIo. 648/138 o.ated 2nd July 1926, I have the honour to state that these itrM&amp;o are no longer suppliec. oy the Audit Office but should be obtained by heads of offices from the Qeputy Controller of Forms under the note at foot of page 30 of the Givil Account Code Yol. I. To expedite the preparation of the return for this office, I enclose herewith three copies of the forms, with the request that they may be completed and returned to this office at a very early date. n I kwe the honour io l&gt;e» Sir, Ytwr most Servmni Amt,Orders of competent authority creating the post. J, O^-Ltr. M . eLaJZcb 6 J-U/Z ^ Cr\yls'\ dj- ^aT&amp;oasHj $&gt; dZ^-E ci&lt;tZu^&gt; M^*5juc,j&lt;iZ4 Present nrcttmbent; Date op 11 P. -S o a&gt; s s s o &gt;&gt; M ci i-^fn Name of Section and post, •M&amp;C^O-CrOLstL j&lt;&gt;&amp;?t'cbrk Ik ser of appoint- ach class. 11 ® ft a § of in( near 1.3 a „ la Q ¥ JA jl, sM &amp;cbc cu (L cJucxyVsO - ^^-t^wOTOCbfi fyorijLt^£ Name of Incumbent. ^ &lt;%&gt; r X' . J\o, eA J\x3~*f~U^^ Pay of post. 1S| F ^ S 3 H r: C « - S IfO '5 a o o rQ ^ fg g«2 S -A a CL cS •sf &gt;&gt; 3 eS as PM /J'O Remarks (including note of efficiency bar where applicable). Compared with Service Books and found correct. ¥ r - At foot of the return should be detailed all items of establishment sanctioned, but not yet incurred. The personal pay should be stated separate line ; immediately below the pay of the officer who received it, the orders of competent authority sanctioning it being quoted in the first column. The rule about entry of orders of con ^ -i,:t authority may be stated generally thus ; the general order is to be entered once only, any other will be entered against every entry which it supjv^+s. In the case of establishments on time-sc } of pay, tl. %ies of all temporary men in service on the date to which the return relates should be included indictaing the vacf ( t ^ whether per Other instructions for filling up the for; are containexf in Article 62. SQPI—S18—2162DCFOont.—8-4-24. 17,000. » * U 1 If B« PoMtte*! ft'' e office. ent or temporary in which they are officiatin? -n To ho returned in original with reply noted in rijriit ^ ri fl 001™. 2^ Of! Ice of the Accountant General, Central Revenuesrbelni. No .T. A .H, m/S 64 Date:! the 11th October 10S6. To The Political Af;ent&gt; Bahrein, Information ia wanting relative to the items quoted overleaf of your Detailed Statement of Establishment on the let April last. Kindly supply the deficiency by entry on the margin of the required particulars, givinp* to the answer the same number that belongs to the items concerned. l,Date of appointment to present post are not correctly stated. 3,Date of promotion to present pay not correctly stated, 5,Name, date of appointment and uromotion to present pay and date of birth of the permanent incumbent fo^ whom the acting arrangement has been made, not stated, 16,From what office transferred or Y^ith what month's establishment bill the health certificate and certificate was f orwarde d no t s t a ted, 22,Name of incumbent shewn in last year's return but now omitted not entered in Form 4. Order, A, Attend in future, E, Furnish, 0. State, f D. Complete and return, K, Furnish a supplementary statement (1) Mr,V.B.Menezea and ■r,Suhder 3inKh Objection items Order B, (2) Mr ,M. J. Gaidar, Sr Vr ,D .S . Athanasius . Objection items 22, Order B, (3) Passport clerk need not be shown in the return as the post is a non-pensionable one. Sd,illegible Asatt,Accounts Officer, Ho, Sovb/l?&gt;Q of 1926 Dated&lt;5.K^($ovember 1926, Obj:(1),Mr,7.B.Menezes, 1, 20-11-25 3, 2^)-11-25 5, Mr.M.J.Gazdar,M.B.E Apptt; 25-3-24 Pro: 1-9-24 Birth: 5-1-1879 16.Mr.Sunder Singh, From Residency,Bushir©. Obj:(2) 22.Furnished, 0^j:(3) Noted. i Poli tical Agent,3 a hrein, ofe- BAHRAIN. L T^jssr' wafcnrarnrirr '- v ■ ■ '-a.:''-? : V- Forn No,4. Civil Account Cod©, Vol.1 Chap.5 Art.62 DETAILED STATEMENT OF NE*7 NAMES, LEAVE, ETC. Sew names of Ron Gazetted Officers. From what office ^ Naraes of IIon- on what date transferee! Gazetted Officers or with what bill which were in Forn 5 of previous year but are now omitted From what date Non^Gazetted ceased to be borne on the establishment and why. officers who have been on other than priw. or cl.leave or under susp. during the year. Desc:* period of leave or susp: from &amp; to what, date * Mr. V.B.Menezes Mr.Sunder j^ingh Rosidency Bushlre, on 16-11-1925 Mr.D.S•Athanasius On 12-1-1926 transferred to Political Agency, Kuwait. 17-12-24 transferred to Combined leave 15 Mr.M.J.Gazdar months from forenoon 1-10-1925 i.e.8 months average &amp; 7 months | averagF pay —D©— on 16-13-2^ Hn .Maqbul s&amp;us a in Kha* H.B.U'a Consulat. /jfin Bandar Abbas • a 2.^-4 Political Agent, Bahrein.r r Ho. I \ 6 hof 1926. 0-f/^b *£■ Political Agency and Consulate Muscat, October, 1926. To The Political Agent, 13 A H H E I H. Memorandum, Reference Bushire Residency memorandum jNo.940 dated the 19th May 1926 to your address v/ith copy to me. The Accountant General Central Revenues has m* Called for the date of 'birth of Mr. Shaikh Ali who is still shown on t he annual return of establishmen t as the permanent incf/mbent of the post of Second Clerk, muscat. Will you please intimate it to me as early as possible. Major, r tv Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, ^ Muscat. AN A.j, — / 10: [jl iT •^xA 1Ho 1 i /158 of 1926 The Political Agency* Bahrein. Dated the 6th Noyeober 1926 To The Political Agent h Consul Mu s cat. Menorandum . Reference your menorandum No.1165 dated the 25rd October 1926. The date of Mr.Shaikh Al^s birth la 14th July 1898. Political Agent,Bahrein 'isn'Ho. of 1927. H.B.M'a Political Agenc/., Bahrein,3rd May 1927. Prom Captain R.G.Alban^ Political Agent, Bahrein, To Tlie Accountant General, Central Revenues, Hew Delhi. Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith, in dup licate, the Annual Return of the Permanent ^ataMishment of this Agency, as it stood on the Ist April 1927. I have the honour to fee, Sir, Your most obeaient servant, Capualn Political Agent, Bahrein.13 Eo* 1435-64/78 of 1927 # British Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, the 27th June 1927 # To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference paragraph 2nd of your memorandum Ho. 481, dated the 6th June 1927, Shaikh Ali should not have been shown officially as trajisferred and his name should appear in the Annual Return of the Establishment of the Bahrain Agency. A correction should accordingly be sent to the Accountant Ggneral, Central Revenues. In this connection I invite a reference to this office demi-official letter No.389, dated the 19th February 1927, in which it is stated that Shaikh Ali will be continued to be borne on your establishment. Please also see this office telegram No.511, dated the 1st June 1927. By order. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. T.M.IT'f- Froa To Sir j No. 17 ^ Of 1927, H-B.M's Politioal Agency* Bahrein Dated the 10th August 1987. Oapta^n R.G*Alban» Political Agent# Bahrein. i i The Accountant General# Central Revenues# Secretariat Buildings# Raiaina# New Delhi. With reference to the Annual Return of Establishment as it stood on the lot April 1927# forwarded to you* with this office letter Ro.57S dated the 5rd May l??g7# I hzvetf the honour to subDit the following correction, in the place of the second clerk shown as vacant please substitute:- Go^ernnent orders creating post. Foreign &amp; Political ^epartme letter No.2^7/86 Est.dated 50-1-1922. Date of appointment to present post or of coonencenent on prient time-scale. Promotion to present pay. Name of section and r^ost. Date of incumbents birth ^as near as^ possible). Serial number of appointment. Name of incumbent. Pay of post; Minimum. Rate of periodical increment^ whether annual# biennial etc. Pay o# post : Maximum. Pay of present incumbent and total of each section. Special pay. House Rent. 50-12-19S4. 11-11-1926. Second Oeirk. 14-7-1P92 3 Mr.Shaikh Ati Rs .120/- Rs. 6 /- Rs .150/- Rs.lSO/- Rs .15/- w 50/- Cl iA ^ I have thej have the honour to be# Sir, Your most obedient servant# Captain# Political Agent# Bahrein.NO. Of 1927. Political Agency* Bahrein. Dated the J25rcl August 1927. Fron Cartain R.G.Alban# Political Agent# Bahrein. To The Accountant General» Centra 1 Revenueo# Secretariat BuilcHngsj New Delhi. Sir, T^ith reference to your objection statement IT o .TARM/S r6 flat el the 11th July 1^27, to the address of the Political Agent, lluscat an extract fron which has been forwarded to ne for disposal# i have the honour to state that Mr.Shaikh All has since resi gned. He was however, appointed First Munshl on 11-11-S1 at Rs.120 -6 -150 (Vide Annual Return sent under this office No.208/l^ dated the 22nd April IPSC)^ and Second Clerk on 50-1S-24 (Vide Annual Return sent under this office No.596/1?^ dated the S6th May lf&gt;25.) Both appointnents being in the Second aMXcla grade, he earned the annual increments with effect from the 11th November i«ei. v T have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrein. mCopy forwarded to the Political Agent» &amp; Consul Muscat with reference to his endorsement No.1007 dated the 14th August 19S7.No. of 1928. Tha Political Agency# Baiiroin Datod tl)« J^/CtUxxciB 1928. From Tlie Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Accountant General, Central Revenuee, Hew Delhi« I have the honour to forward herewith, in duplicate, the Annual Return of the Fn-Danont Eetablieh^ mont of this Agonoy, as It stood on tha let April 1928. Sir, I have the honour to be# Sir, Your most obodient eervant, Political Agent, BaliriinOffice of the Accountant General, Central Revenues, IMPERIAL SECRETARIAT BUILDINGS, New Delhi, the 6th July 1928. No. Cent/151-1 -27-28 /12, Circular. /%f • Ci - | e n Sit ^ Fr0ffi V.. .aU. . \ ^y v The Accountant General, Central Revenues. • ^4^ '^ To All Heads of Offices. Subject:- Duplicates of Annual Establishment Returns. Sir, In inviting a reference to Clause (3) of Art. 62 Civil Account Code Vol-I, I have the honour to state that no dupli cates of Annual Returns need be submitted to this office in future• I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, S. TAJ MOHAMMED, Deputy Accountant General. A/ '3^/ Bo. ^ L 1 of 1929• The Political Aganoy,Bahrain. Dat,3d the /i'/-April 1029. From Tlie Political Agont, Bahroin. To Thd Accountant Gansral, Contra! Rov«nu9fi # Haw Dolhi. Sir, I liava the honour to forward, herewith, the Annual Haturn of the Pernanent Establichment of this Agonoy, ae it etood on the lot April 1929. I liava the honour to be, Sir, Your nost obedient Bervant, fir* i Political Agent, Bahrein.-—. ...To 'be returned in original with reply note in right hand coluim, O.i.fice o. the Accountant G-eneral, O ntral Revenues, Delhi. :./ll4 ated the 22nd June 1929. To the Political Agent, Bahrein. (}Ar k ■ m, y Imormation is v/anting relative to Vae ijs^ms quoted overleaf of our etailed Statement of Estahlishment on tk€ 1st April last. Kindly ^ ie deficiency by entry on the margin of the required particulars, giving go one answer the same nuiher that helon s to the item ansv/ered. Sd - Illegible. fir- ♦ b j J Asstt. Accountant G-eneral. Items IT 7 .?' Reply !• Prom the anuual return, it appears that the post of II Clerk is vacant. According to letter lo.2214-64-117 dated 12.10.28 from Secretary to Pol. \/^fTJi Resident in Persian G-ulf, now I r.D.S. f\ Athansius iclds lien on che aloove post. inus the najiie of I t.Athansius should have been shown as the substantive incumbent of the post Hr. Abdul Latif as officiating. 2. li lay be stated hether It . Abdul laatif holds a permanent post at Muscat and if &lt; S9, the fact may be su ported by a certificate from Political Agent, I 'uscat to that effect as re aired under Art.6 (1)(g) C.A.G. Yol.I 3. ^ It is presiivaed bhat Ir.aohamed Waris Ali 11 Munshi has been permanently transferred to Gwadur. Please confirm. /Hr. fl'Z- ^ u* A—4. It is not clear why the names of Messrs J.lr .Periera and Oazdar have not been entered in Form 4: the name of the former appears in the lafet year T s return 'but has now 'been omitted wmle the latter should have been shown in the column n New names of non-gazetted oi l ioers fl • Phe date from which Sr.S.P. x en era ceased to be borne on the es tablishment may also be stated. ^ -i 1- S 5- It appears^from the # Health certificate of r. ♦A.Hafiz that his age is 27 years. Orders of the Head of the Department to admit him to the service of Government . fter the age of 25 years may kindly be furnished. A^ 1 c Uj e OH* H. B. M's. Polltlcnl Bahrain. ( No, tH* * Qe-Hxtu*' 2 f■UhNdNi No, of 1929. The Political Agency,Bahrein* Dated the July 1929. To The Political Agent, Muscat. Memoraadum . The Account £jit General, Central Reyenues, New Delhi, has asked me to support an entry in the Annual Retur of the Permanent Establishment of this Agency that Mr. Abdu Latif officiating 2nd Glerk of this Agency holds the permar post of 3rd Clerk in the Muscat Agency. I shall he obliged if you will kindly forward him the certificate sending me a copy for my records. Political A/^ent, Bahrein# Copy to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, for information, with reference to his Ko.T.A«K«i-/l dated the 22nd June 1929 •No. of 1929. The Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the £Lllt Julj 1929 m To The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bush ire, MeaKsraridm . The Accountant G-eneral # Central Revenues, has asked me to furnish orders of the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to admit Mr* Mohamed Abdul Hafiz 2nd Munsbi of this Agency to the service of G-oyemaen' after the age of 25 year# The age of Mr. Eafiz is 27 years# I shall be obliged if you will kindly furnish me with the necessary orders#2% Ho.A.B. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire the 10th August 1929 ' To The Political Agent, Bahrein Memorandum . Reference your memorandum Ho, 842 dated the 24th July 1929. The necessary sanction order in respect of the appointment of Mr.M.A.Hafiz is enclosed herewith. By order Captain Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian GulfSANCTION ORDER The Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf is pleased to appoint Mr, Moharamed Ahdul Hafiz as 2nd Munshi, Political Agency, Bahrain at an age over 25 years. By Order, Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 10th August 1929. 4T q \ \ -r. / Ho. Of 1929. political Agency and Consulate^ Muscat 31st July 1929* fhe Accountant-Genera1# Central Revenues# Imperial aecretariat Buildings# m:. DiiiHi» ^&gt;1 Sir Witli reference to Meiao#Bo#841 dated 24tii July i929 froffl the Political Agent,Bahrain,to zny address,copy to you f I have the honour to state that iar.Abdul Latif officiating 2nd cler]c,Poli. • tical Agency, Bahrain, he Id the permanent post of 3rd cleric in this Agency on l»t # April 1929 and to enclose herewith a certi- -fic&amp;te to that effect. I have the honour to be, Sir t Tour most obedient cervant. 11^ (sd) G.i'.Murphy , Major, Political Agent and H.B•^ } s Consul, Muscat. Copy with a aopy of the certificate forwarded to the Political Agent,Bahrain,reference his Memo. quoted above. IFUA -Ox, i 1 . v Maj o: Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul,Muscat. iSSd'Muscat 313 t July 1929♦ SBRTigiCATE, Certified that Mr.Abdul Latif,2^ officiating 2nd clerk, post political Agency, Bahrain, he Id the permanent/of 3rd cleric ^in the office of the rolitical Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat,on 1st April 1929 Maj or, Political Agent and H.B.IvPs Consul,Muscat.No. of 1930. ThP Political Agency, Bai^rain. Dated the //,'', April 1930. Protr Captain C.G.Prior, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To T fae Acc&lt;antant General, Central ReTenuea, Secretariat Buildings, Raisina, Hew Delhi. Sir, I t^re the honour to forward i^rewith tlti Annual Return of the Perrnanent Eatablis^ent of this Agency, as it stood on tie Ist April 1930. I have ttP honour to be. Sir, Your rrost obedient servant. , political Agent, Ba^ain# iEij Victoria Memorial Hospit; Bahrein,P.G. Uths April 1930. I hereby certify that I have examined Agha Mahomed El Sherif, a candidate for employment in the Political Eept: , and cannot find that he hao any disrase, conBtitutional weakness or bodily infirmity, exoeptloss of the sight of the right eye. I do not consider this a disqualification for taaployment in the office of Second Munshi, Political Depts. Agha Mahomed's age is according to own statement,40 years,and fcy appearance about 40 years# Asst- Surgeon# M.O.i/c V # M»Hospital. Bahrein.Medical Officer * I shall 'be glad if you Y /ill please examine t^e bearer A£ vuiaTr-rrad Siiarif a candidate for etrpl^yrrent in t^e Political Agency Bahrain and reporjL.®n his health- ! M '3 bC's. P. P.—L (in) 977—400-1-30—k. No. of 193 T he P olitical A gency, B ahrain, Dated the 14th April 193Q # m To T he S ecretary to the H on'ble the P olitical R esident in the P ersian G ulf, BUSHIRE. % MEMORANDUM Kindly furnish mo with the requisibe ^aaoilea order of the Eo&amp;'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to admit Agha Muhaiaraad Sharif Officiating Second Ifonshi of this Agmcy to the service of G-overmient at an ago over 25 years# This is required in connection with the submission of the annual return of the pensionable establishment of this Agency. n qjj Political Agent, Bahrain# M.39^ Nc • cf 1930. British Residency 8c Consul ate-G-eneral, Bushire, the ^T-pril 1930. To The Political Agent, BAHR E I N Memorandum* Reference your memorandum No.647 dated the 14th April 1930. As Agha Muhammad Sharif is only a temporary hand officiating in a leave vacancy sanction to his appointment at an age over 25 years is not necessary unless he is confirmed. By crder, MaJ or, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. L.P.No.571/1/11 of 1931. The Political Agency, Bahrain. Datea the j .' k J 1931. From Captain G.G-.Prior, I.A», Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Accountant-General, Central Revenues, Mew Delhi. Sir, I have the lion our to forwrrd, herewith, the Annual Return of the Permanent Establishment of this Agency, as it stood on the 1st of April 1931. I have the iionour to be. Sir, lour most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahrain. A.J.HO M 0 R u m. 4, Petail«d atatewemt of saew siamea et«. itew /i nares of ror ' i gazetted officers. 1 ij'row what office and oa what 4ate trail a ferret or with what bill health and age certificate was furnished. 13ai?6 of no*u gazetted ofiicers wlio were in form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. jfe'ro® what date ceased to be borne on the Sst^blish^ent and why. Hon. gazetted officers who have been on other than prior casual leave or under suspension during the year. Bescription and period of leare or suspension fros* and to what date. ¥r.L«C.DeSouzi H.B.M*s Consulate, Bunder Abbas. 1.4.30. ¥r«Abdul Jabbar Political Agency, Muscat. 1.4.30. Saiyid Abdur Hezzaq Mr • I). S . At hanas i us Mr. E.Thomas First appointment e 22. 1.31. (Health certificate attached), 14.3. 31 • Being proceeded on consbined leave for two years* 1.4.30. Having been appointed as Leave Reserve (Upper Division) Agha Muhawad oharif 10.11.30. Terminated. ¥r. L.C.BeSouza Mr.Abdul Jabbar Mr.Anwar Mukhlis An outsider. 14.3.31. (Temporary) • Leave on ledical Certificate frop 11th to 31st ¥ay 19 30 (dates of arrival at Karacl i). Combined leave. 4 months on average pay and 2 months on half average pay with, effect from 6th July 1930 to 5th January 1931. (dates of arrival at Karachi). Bahrain. The 14th April 1931. ft. 8, Ws. Political /\geni, Uutoruia. (Persian Oulf.j A.J.I do hereby certify that I have examined Mr. E.Thomas an employee in the Political Agency at Bahrain, and cannot discover that he has any disease, or bodily informity. Mr. E.Thomas f s age is according to his own statement years and, by appearance ^ years. J/No. A.B. 33 r of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Busiiire, the April 19 31. --fr l-fn: i / rf, . . ^ . r - T 4 To V J v'' / &gt; The Political Agent, Bahrein. H.B.M* s Consul, Bandar Abbas. Memorandum. To enable this office to complete the annual return of the permanent establishment as it stood on the 1st April 1931, will you please furnish as early as possible the certificate required under the Civil Account Code, Vol: » \ » \ . Mr. Rahia&amp;tull ah, I, Artie,, a 6&lt;c {1 ; igy, in respect of M&amp;i —Mohnriuroci—V/arin Ala, pe r man ent second Clerk Muwcjhi of your office. By Order, Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,— 43 C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—d. From The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. To T he S ecretary TO THE HON'BLE THE POLITICAL RESIDENT in the P ersian G ulf, BUSHIRE. No. Slf Memorandum. DatpH the 30th April 193 1.. Reference your Memorandum No:A.B/338 dated the 18th April 193L According to the Nominal Roll received in this office with the Revision Scheme Mr.Rahmatullah is shown as Treasury Clerk,Bushire,and Mr.Abdul Jabbar^the existing incumbent,as 2nd Clerk,Bahrain. In the circumstances it is not understood that certificate is re uired. for Political Agent, Bali rain.ITo. A.B. of 1931. 'ritish Residency &amp; Consulate-General, /&lt;r Bushire, the May 1931 To The Political Agent, B AH R I Fe Memorandurn, Reference your Memorandum Uo,514, dated the 30th April 1931. Please refer to the Office 0 r( i er forwarded with this office Circular Memorandum lTo.723 dated the 9th April 1931. As, according to the revised order, Mr.Rahmat- ullah has been appointed as permanent Second Clerk, Bahrein with effect from the 1st April 1930, Will you kindly furnish the certificate required under the Civil Account Code, Volume I. Article 62 (l) (g). By Order, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—d. From The Political Agent, BAHRAIN no. six. the 16th may 193 1. Memorandum * Reference your memorandum No.i.B.390 dated the 10th May 1931. I forward, herewith, the certificate required under the Civil Account Code, Volume I, Article 62 (1) (g). ^ . To T he S ecretary to the hon'ble the political resident in the P ersian G ulf, BUSHIRE.Political Agency, Bahrain, the luth May 1931. C E n T I F I C A T E . Certified that Mr. Rahmatullah, officiating Treasury Clerk, Political Residency, Bushire, held the permanent post of 2nd Clerk in the office of the H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, on the 1st April 1931. Ii.B.M T s Political Agent, BahrainJ'*?' Please state the, circumstances under which, the word 'available' has been introduced in the certify -cate of comparison of service books which is required to be un- -condit ional. 3^ ^ ^ is yv^yaAkvA; - Axk^- 1 (J 2. The names of Sayjad Abdur Razaq oc Mr. Abdul Hafiz should have been shown against the posts of Head Munshi and 2nd iKxEsmxS Munshi respectively in Form 3 thdy being the substantive incumbents of the posts. 3. 4. A■certificate of the Political Igent. Muscat as prescribed in ^rt. 62(i)(g) of G.A.G'.Vol.i to the efrecx that Mr.Abdul Jabbar holds lien on the post of 3rd Clerk, Muscat maj kindly be furnished. The name of Mr.Rahmatullah should have been shown as the substantive incumbent of the post of 2nd clerk. \ A 5. Please refer to Art.62(1)(f) of C.A.O. Vol .1 and note ihiri he name of a person officiating in an appointment need not be shown in the statement unless the additional pay for officiating counts for pension. The name of Mr. Anwar LIukhlis should not tki thus have been shown. MiUJhX Indian' Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain.C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-1-30- -h. From T he P olitical A gent, BAHRAIN. No I/O Dated the 31st August 193^ • Memorandum ♦ « . , ... ,. I shall be glad if you will kindly furnish me with the certificate required under the Civil Account Code, Vol: I, Article 62 (1) (g)&gt; ia respect of Mr# Abdul Jabbar permanent third clerk of your office. Indian Assistant to the RoUUcal Agent, Bahrain. To T he P olitical A gent, And TTIT M 's. C onsul, Musca t*n©. ^3 A/i. Political Agency &amp; H.E.M* s Consulate, Muscat, the ^ ^ Septeiaber 1931. To The Political Agent, ^ahrain» Memorandum. Reference your memorandum N©.1020, dated the 3ist August 1931. I enclose, herewith, the required certificate Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.l.HVs Consul, Muscat,I RIB COPY. Q E H x I g I G A TB. Certified that Mr. Abdul JaVbar, officiating 2nd Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain, held the permanent post of 3rd Clerk in the office of the Political Agent and H.B. Ill 's Consul, on the 1st April 1931. Sd/- R.G. Alb an Captain, Political Agent H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Muscat. 7th September 1931.rl Ho . ^ 21 - Political Agency, Bahrdn, the ^th Septem'oer 1931 # From The Tolitical /igent, Bahrain* To The Account aat-G-eneral, Central ReYenues, HEW DEL 11 I, Sir, With referonce to the item No.3 of ycur objection Ho # fAHM/l56 dated the 28th July 1931, I have the hon iir to forward, herewith, the certificate required mider Article 62(i) {g) of Civil Acoomt Code ¥ol # I in respect of Mrsibdul Jabbar- I have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant, Indian Assistant to the Political -Agent, Bahrein, A.J «r 5^2- TO 3E RETURNED IN ORIGINAL WITH REPLY NOTED I RIGHT HAND COLUMN. Offioe of the Accountant General. Reply Ko # /^7-3 New Delhi dated the i9th September* 31 Dated Bahrain the/^Noyember 1931. NO .TAiBif/ 250-. To The Political Agent, Bahrain* The period for which Mr. L.C.DeSouza took leave on medical certificate from 21.4.SO may kindly be stated after consulting his service book. To The Ac count ant-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, yCU-CX-O 0&gt; d? &lt;^crrvv/ ^ ' K^LX^ a.i.'+ ic. /fe to-s- m I#| 3Sbm^m ) . , ^ERSlSS 3 ^ SIGNAU ^KE: - Sd/- S.Ratir am Assistant Accountant General. /?. B. ia'&lt;rPolHlcal L JTO BE RETURNED IN ORIGINAL WITH HEPLY IlOTED IN RIGHT HAND COLIW1T. Office of the Accountant General, New Delhi dated the 19th September 1 31 NO.TAHM/248. Reply No # Dated Bahrain the^^ovember 1931* To The Political Agent» Bahrai n. To The Accountant-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi« Reference - Your reply No. 1019 of 1931 Bated/31/8/21. 900J; 1. Please state the follov/ins particulars about Ifessrs Rahmatullah ^ f^vo-oa-^J LivCc. tCL and S.Abdur Reszaq. (i) Dates of appointment.to prewent post and pay. (ii) Date of birth. (iii) Rate of pay. (iv) Date of next increment .lO' ; 'J' '*-j/ KSts~ H. B* M's. Political Agent, tebraiu. ( Persia a Quit} ^'&lt;*1 S^NATURS;- Sd/- S.Ratiram Asstt: Accountsint General.C's. P. P.—L (in) 977—400-1-30—k. No. /Ztf/ of 193/. T he P olitical A gency , B ahrain, Dated the 12th December i93l* To T he S ecretary to the H on'ble the P olitical R esident in the P ersian G ulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM The Accountaat General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, in his NOf , rAlM/248, has requested me to furnish him with the following information in respect of Messrs. S.Abdur Hezzaq and Hahmatullah:- 1 # Dates of appointment of present post and pay. 2* Date of birth. r ^ 3. Rate of paj, 4# Date of next increment. As their Service Books are with you I should be glad if you would furnish the Accountant General, direct, with the required particulars. Saiyid Abdur Bezzaq's grade pay is Rs.l50/~ Politkjal Agent, Bahrain.5T c 's. P.P.—L( iii ) noi— 500-11-3x. NO. ^ OF I93 g P olitical A gency, B ahrein, Dated the 30th April 193 2- From THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. To The icoountant-Crenerql, Central Revenues, N K ^ L E L H I Sir, 1 have the honour to forward, herewith, in duplicate, tne Annual Return of the Permanent Kstablishment of this Agencyj as it stood on the 1st of April 1932. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Agent, Bahrain. T A •o y 0 R M ISO. A. Detailed statement of new names etc. Hew names of non- gazetted officers From what office and on what date transferred or with whit bill, health and age certificate was furnished. Name of non-gazetted officers who were in form 3 of previoa-s year b't are now omitted. yrom what dat^Hon-gazetted ceased to be 'officers who borne on the Establishment and why. 'have ^een on 'other than 'prior casual 'leave or u-nder 'suspension 'during the year4 Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. Mr.Jasim bin Mohammad. An outsider. 6.7. 31. (Not confirmed)• S. Abd r Rezzaq Combined leave(8 months on average and 16 months on half average pay). Bahrain* The 30th April 1932. 'c H. B- M's. poUtlcal Bahraia . ( OuU.jJg 0 R M HQ, A. Detailed statement of new names etc. Mew names of non- gazetted officers yrom what office and on what date transferred or with whit bill, health and age certificate was fcirnished. Name of non-gazetted officers who were in form 3 of previoa-s year b't are now omitted. From what dat^Hon-gazetted ceased to be borne on the Ss t abli shment and why. 'officers who 'have Ween on 'other than 'prior casual 'leave or '-nder 'suspension 'during the yeari Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. Mr.Jasim bin Mohammad. An outsider. 6.7.31. (Not confirmed). mmtum* S. Abd r Hezzaq Combined leave(8 months on average and 16 months on half average pay).o Copy of letter Ho, 562/E/46 dated 22nd April 1932, xrom Major G.K.Daly, His Britannic Majesty»s Consul, distan and Kain, to pie Secretary to the Hon»ble the^Politica^ Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire© &gt;ir, I have the-honour to request that you will kindly | formrd a certificate required under Article 62 (1) (g) of the -ivil account Code Yol. I, in respect of Mr. Rahmat UllahJ who holds a substantive appointaient in the Persian Gulf cadre f in the Lower Division, on the 1st April 1952o j ITo. A.B. /S/l 0 £ 193a. Bushire, the 7th May 1932» Copy forwarded to the Political Agent Bahrein, for information with the request that the requisite certificate may please be forwarded to His Britannic Majesty's Consul Si£ &gt;^ and Kairl, aS Kr# HaJlmat U:LlaIi ho1 ^ a substantive post in office. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.n C's. P. P.—L (ill) hoi— 500-U-31. No. fT^X —OF 193 2 • P olitical A gency, B ahrein, Dated the 11th May *93 2* From To THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. His Britannic Majesty ! 3 Consul, Sistan and Kain^ Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.5b2/E/46 dated the 22nd April 1932 to the address of the Secretary to the Hon 1 hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire and forward, herewith, the certificate required under Article 62 (1) (g) of the Civil Account Code Vol. I in respect of Mr. Rahmatullah. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. /C H.B«iu f s Political Agent, Bahrain. I A • J •Political Agency, Bahrain, the 11th May 1932. CERTIFICATE. Certified that Mr# Rahmatullah, officiating 2nd Clerk, British Consulate, Sistan, held the permanent post of 2nd Clerk in the orfice of kk K.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, on the Ist April 1932. O H.B.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.No. of 1932. The Political Agency &amp; Consulate r Muscat the May 1952. To The Political Agent, Bahrein* iieinorandum . Reference your memorandum iTo.503 dated the 11th May 1932. L enclose, herewith, the required certificate* ^ Lt-Golonel, Political Agent &amp; H.B.K's Consul,Kuscat• A XCERTIFIED, that Mr. Abdul Jabbar, otTiciating 2nd Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain, held the permanent post of 3rd Cleric in the office of the Political Agent and H-B.M's Consul, Muscat on the 1st April 1932. Sd/- T.C. Powle Lt.Colonel, Political Agent,&amp; H.B-M's Consul, Muscat. • Musca t. 23rd May 1932.^3 C's. P. P.—L (m) iioi— 500 -11 -31. NO. of 193 a Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the 4th June *932 • From To THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. Tiie a CG o un ta.n 17 Gen e rai^ Cent ral Rev en ues, NEW DELHI. bir. In continuation ot* my letter No.462 dated the 30th April 1932, I liaye the honour to forward, herewith, the certificate required under Article 62 (i) (g) of the Oivil Account Code Volume I in respect of Mr.Abdul Jabbar. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Politic?.! /gent,- Bahrain. A.J.Ho. A.B. of 1932. Britisli Hesidency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 7ir ^uly 1932. To /2^-7-32__ The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrein, j/' The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Bandar Ahhas. His Britannic Majesty*s Consul, Kerman. His Britannic Majesty's Vice-Consul, Mohaiamerah. Memorandum. To enable this office to prepare a consolidated statement of Establishment as it stood on 1st April each year it is requested that in future a copy of your Annual Return of Establishment may be forwarded to this office as soon as possible after 1st April of each year. ♦ a By Order, Captain, Secretary to the BolltloaX aesident in the Persian Oulf. ■ V; -v vt. # „ syo &amp;J- ^ A ':\- Af.Mbhf V Cg^vC's, P. P. L (in) iioi 500 -11 -31, no of Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the 15th Aprll ,93 3 . From T@ THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. llie Account ant-General, Central Hevenues, B W DELHI Sir, I have the honour to forward, herewith, in duplicate, the Annual Return of the Permanent Establishmetit of the Political Agency, Bahrain, as it stood on the 1st. April 1933 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Indian Assistant, Bahrain# ^(In Charge Current Duties) ; A.J #A. 6 / C's P. P.—L (III) 129—500-4-31. NO. V ^ / of 1938 . The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the I93 3 To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Reference your memorandum Ho«A # B»695 dated the 7tli July 1932• I forward, herewith, a copy of the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, as it stood on the 1st ^pril 1933* BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. Indian Assistant, 'ahrain. (In Charge Current Duties)* A# J#^u. C's. p. P.—L (in) 980—300-1-30 -h. From To The Political Agent , and The Political Agent, H. B. M's. Consul, BAHRAIN. MUSCAT. / ^ Memorandum# Daled the _ 16th April 1933 • would you please furnish me with the certificate required under the Civil Account Code f Volume I, Article 62(1) (g), in respect of Mr♦Abdul Jabbar permanent third clerk of your office. Indian Assistant, Bahrain. In Charge Current Duties A# J &lt;.-ff- 5.^-7/ 5'5 6 of 1933. 7( The Political Agency ^ Consulate&gt; Muscat April x933» To The Political Agent,. Bahrein. Mem or an audi Reference your memorandum Fo.462 dated the 15-th April 1^33. 1 enclose, herewith, the required certificate. . Captain, Poli tical A&amp;en-t oc Consul, luscat«71 7^ C E R T I F I C A T CBRTIPIHD that Mr. Abdul Jabbar, officiating 2nd Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain, held the permanent post of 3rd Clerk in the ^office of the Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat on the 1st April 1933• Sd/- R.G. Alban Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Muscat. 22nd April 19335V-7^ C's. p. p.— L (in) .101 500-11-31. No OF 1933 . Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the 8th May 193 3. From T® THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. The Accountant-General&gt; Ce ntral Revenues f . v ^ 1X v TOW DELHI Sir L'l-HI. j \ In continuation of ^ letter No•460 date&lt;3 the 15th iipril 1933j I have the honour to forward, herewith 3 the certificate required under Article 62 (1) (g) of the Civil Account Code Volime I in respect of Mr#Atodul Jahbar* I have the honour to bei Sir, Your most obedient servant ; Indian Assistant In Charge Current Duties Bahrain.— - ■'' ^ m vvjuh v -,75 fW, A-s.^.73 Copy of letter Ho.TA 12-1 -526, dated the 18th July 1953 f from tue Acoountant-General, Central Revenues, Hew Delhi, to the Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ••■.•oOo---- I have the honour to state that annual establishment returns of the esta-blishment in the subordinate Consulates are submitted to this office by the Consular Officers concerned* As a consolidated Annual establishment return for the entire establishment of the Bushire Residency borne on an amalgamated cadre is forwarded by you, separate returns from the subordinate Consulates are f J^ t u i r,3Cl by this office, vide clause R to Art# 62 (1) of the Civil Account Code, Volume X* They may kindly be directed to submit separate returns to this office in future only in respect of the establishment which is not borne on an amalgamated cadre and in that case the names of the permanent (superior) establishment only, if any, may be shown therein. 2* The names of inferior establishment should not also be shown in the returns sent by the above officers. —oO o—— (C's. P. P.—L (m) 977—400-1-30—k. , //// No. &amp; 9cof 1934- The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 19th May 193^ To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM I enclose | in duplicate, the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, as it stood on the 1st April 1934# L/ Political Agent, Bahrain.JtJ&amp;l GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER fiV, 1&gt;, T/ m . s is an ORIGINAL MESSAGJE, sent, hy yost to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time aud formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] F rom Britconsul, Bushire, To Political, Bahrain, /^■wGonsul, Mandar Ab'oas. No * A.B.^t/s/l of 1934. Daiei May 303 4 . h P h. Please expedite the despatch of the 'Annual Esta&gt;iishment ' « / Return' vide my Giicular memoranda Nos. A.B. 695 and 707, dated the 7th July 1932 and 19th August 1933 respectively. ^ ciecrertary to the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. DCfP- 1866S&amp;P—(M.182l)~27-9-32—2 &gt; 60 &gt; 000.Telegraphic Address: Accounts, India. All communications should be addressed to the Accountant- General, Central Revenues. OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES •?£ -so Enclosures. Y No, TiilO-1-254 NEW DELHI. dated the 25 MAY 1934 From To THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, The Political ^gent, Bahrain. SlE. I have the honour to observe that the detailed statement of permanent establishment of your agency existing on 1st April 1934 has not yet been received as required under Article 62 of the Civil Account Code, Volume I, and request that the same may kindly De furnished to this office at a very early date. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. iissiAccounts Officerho. i&amp;yi-f/ / Political Agency, Bahraini the 28th June 1934. From The Political Agent, Bahrain# To Sir, The Accountant-General f Central Revenues, Hew Delhi# With reference to your letter Ho.TA.10-1-264 dated the 25th May 1934 I have the honour to refer to your letter No.TA#12-1-628 dated the 18th July 1933 to the address of the Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, in which you had stated that the separate return was not required by you as a consolidated Annual Establishment return on an amalga mated cadre is forwarded to you by the Residency Bushire. 2. As the Establishment of this Agency is borne on an amalgamated cadre of the Bushire Residency no separate return was sent to you. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. for Political Agent, Bahrain1» ' ' i C's P. P—L (III) 129—500-4-31. m r/1/11 of 1^3 . The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 6th April i ^ q . To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, \ BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. I enclose, in duplicate, the Annual Return of remanent Eetablishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, ae it stood on the Ist April 1935. ^ _ Captain, Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain. / JSIP .LOR M J!2: Detailed statement of New names etc. New narnce of non- gazetted offieert' Fro® what office and on what date tranaferred or with what bill,st health an&lt;fl age certificates were furnished. Name of non~gf;zct*&amp;d officers who were In Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted* From what date cea&amp;ed x.o be borne on the Establishment and why* Non-gazetted officers who have been on other than pri* or casual leave or under suspension during the year. Bescrlption and period of leave or suspension from and to what date* Mr. D.J. Stephens. British Re»iders .cy and Consulate- General, Bushire. On expiry of leave* Mr* Zafsir Islam 1st September (Eub protern) 1934. On transfer to Political Agency, Muscat* Bahrain* The 6th April 1935* Captain, Offg. Political Agent, Baliraln^- ■ ■ ■ ... I I rOPPICE OF THE ACCOUNTA1TT GENERAL ^35 Sd cs CENTRAL REVEMJES 0 1 C- KEW DELHI. W'o 4 C 13-13-4l6o dated the 4 To ALL HEADS OP OFFICES,, Subject g- Annual Returns of Establishment - not required for inferior servants, Sir» : ' It will be seen from Article 62 (l )(a )(3) of the Civil Account Code, Volume I that no Annual Returns of Establishment are required to be submitted to the Accountant General in respect of Government servants for whom no service books are maintained, I have the honour to request therefore that no annual returns showing the sanctioned strength and scales of pay of inferior Government servants need be furnished in future to this office c I have the honour to be ? Sir g Your most obedient servant, DEPUTY ACCOUNTANT GENERAL S.Bahadur SSo 89 35No . 116 ~ l/ll Political Agency, Bahrain, April 7, 1936. To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memor nnciiiTn I enclose, in duplicate, the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, % as it stood on the 1st April 1936. Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain.FORM NO. 4&gt; Detailed statement of New Haines etc New names of non- gazetted officers, From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill, health and age certificates were furnished. Hame of non-gazetted officers who were in Form 5 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the Establishment and why. Non-gazetted officers who have been on other than pri. or casual leave or under suspension during the year. Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. Agha Muhammad al Sharif. An outsider. From 12th November 19S6 to 11th January 1956. (Temporary). Mr. L.C.deSouza Died. Kxact date not known. Mr. Juha. mad Abdul Hafiz. Six months' combined leave (three months on average and three months on holf average pay) with effect from forenoon of lat July to after noon of 31st December 1955. Bahrain. The 7th April 1936, Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain.J '*. * ** • -etalied statement of Hew Names etc« ^Tev. names of non- gazetted officers. From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill, health and age certificates were furnished. Name of non-gazetted officers ^ho were in Form 5 of previous year but are now omitted. Prom what date ceased to be borne on the i Establishment and why. on-gazetted officers who have been on other then pri, or casual leave or under suspension during the year. Description and period of leave or tuspension from and to what date. r •f- .(!■ \ 1 *han 'ahib r aiyid /bdur ^ezzaq ^-5-1956. r ransferred to char.iah. r. J as im bin 'uhammad. 1 Five months' lea,ve on average pay (hx-India). ■ ! , for Political Agent, Bahrain, Bahrain, * nril 9, 1057.No. 439/S/9, British Gbnsulate-Oeneral f or Khorasan. lies bed, Iran. The 5 th tgrll 1937. Memorandum. Till you please forward the certificate required under Article 62(1} (g) of the Civil Account Oode, Volume I, to the effect that Mr. S. E. Thomas held substantively the post of Additional Olerk, Bahrain, on the 1st April 1937. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. His Britannic Majesty^ Consul-Oeneral for Khorasan.No. u ( -1/11. Political Agency, Bahrain, April 29, 1937. To V His Majeety f 6 Consul-General for Khorasan, Meshed, IRAN. f v&lt; c M emorandum Reference your memorandum No. 439/£/9 dated the 5th April 1957. 2. I forward, herewith, the certificate required under Article 62(l) (g) of the Civil Account Code, Volume I in respect of Mr. E.E. Thomas, Second Clerk, Bahrain. for Political Agent, Bahrain. A.Political Agency, Bahrain, April 29, 1937. CERTI PIGATE. CERTIFIED that Mr, E.E. Thomas, officiating Superintendent, British Consulate-General, Meshed, held the permanent post of Second Olerk, Political Agency, Bahrain, on the 1st April 1937. for Political Agent, Bahrain. A.N0.692-E/9. British Consulate-General for Khorasan, Meshed, the 27th May 1937. IvIeiaQrandum To Th§ Political Agent, Bahrain Av] 1/11. A Reference your memorandum Mo,992-1/11, dated the 29th April 1937. 2. According to my information Hr.E.Thomas holds substantively the post of Additional Clerk, Bahrain, a post 'borne in the Upper Division of the coinbined Persian- Gulf and Khorasan Consulate-General clerical cadre and not that of Second Clerk, Bahrain, which is included in the Lower Division. If this is correct a fresh certificate may kindly 'be sent. 3. If the designation of the post of Additional Clerk, Bahrain, has 'been changed to that of Second Clerk, Bahrain please forward copies of the orders of the Government of India and of the Political Resident so that necessary entries may he made in his service hook. His Majesty's Consul-General for Khorasan. &lt; t 412) No. 1293/E/9. British Cbnsulate-G-eneral for Khorasan Meshed. Iran. The 9th September 1937. The Political Agent, Bahrain. To A q v Memorandum , Beference correspondence ending with your memorandum No. 1444-1/11, dated the 26th June 1937. 2. I enclose a copy of Bushire Office Order Mo. 915, of August 1937 from which it will he seen that Mr. E. E. Thomas, held substantively the post of Confidential Glerk, Bahrain, on the 1st April 1937. 3. In the circumstances please send a fresh certificate required under Article 62(1)(g) of the Givil Account Oode, Volume I, for submission to the Accountant-Oeneral, Central Bevenues, New Delhi• His Britannic Majesty's Oonsul-Oeneral for Kborasan.British Consul at e-G-eneral Bushire * OPfiaE OEDEB No&gt; 915 &gt; Mr. E» Thomas) Additional Clerk, Bahrain, and officiating Superintendent, Meshed, has 'been appointed as Confidential Clerk, Bahrain, with effect from the 1st April, 1937, and will continue to officiate as Superintendent, Meshed. By Order, (Signed) a. 0. galloway. Secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian dulf. British Eesidency &amp; Consulate-General, 9 Bushire, the August 1937.No •&gt;&gt;T l/li. f' Political Agency, Bahrain, October 4, 193?. ir, v H V ith reference to your memorandum No. 1295/li/9 I I ,/ dated the 9th September 1957, I have the honour to enclose, herewith, a freaih certificate required under Article 62(l)(g) of the Civil Account Code, Volume I, in respect of Mr. E. Thomas Confidential Clerk, Bahrain. \ I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, /fi Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. His Majesty^ Consul-General for Khorasan, BrItith Consulate-General, MESHED.V nl No. - '^^ I I Political Agency, Bahrain, October 4, 1937, To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum Reference your memorandum No. 374-19/121 dated the 21st February 1937. 2. His Majesty's Consul-General, Meshed, has now forwarded to me a copy of your Office Order No. 915 of August 1937, from which it appears that Mr. £• Thomas, officiating Superintenuent, Meshed, has been appointed as Confidential Clerk, Bahrain, with effect from the Ist of April 1937, but this office was never informed of this -change Correspondence between this office and the British Consulate- General, Meshed, would have been avoided if a copy of the Office Order had been sent to this office. 3. I shall be glad to be informed who has been permanent appointed/3rd. Clerk, Bahrain, from the 1st of March 1937. 4 ^ A. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.Political Agency, Bahrain, No.y^f-l/ll. April 12, 1938. To The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• Memorandum * I enclose, in duplicate, the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, as it stood on the 1st April, 1938. The details in Form No .3 regarding Khan Sahib Mirza Ismail Barduli, Head Munshi Bahrain are not complete. They may kindly be completed and verified with the Khan Sahib's Service Book at Bushire. for Political Agent, Bahrain. trie-in FOBM ITO &gt;4 Detailed statement of New Hames etc Hew names of non-gazetted of leers* From what office and on what date transferred* or with what bill, health and age certificates were furnished* Name of non-gazetted officers who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted* From what date ceased to be borne on the Ks tabli shment and why* Non-gazetted officers who have been on other than privilege or casual leave or under suspension during the year* Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date* i *3* irza Ismail British Residency Sarduli* and Consulate- General, Bushire, 16-11-1937 • Hr*S.Thomas Confirmed as Superintendent, Meshed• /id- Bahrain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. April 12, 1938.'r .r E &lt; Mo. /e/1 • dated the Jt April, 1938. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum# \ Q \ ; Reference the annual return of permanent establish- men t of the Political Agency, Bahrain, as it stood on the 1st April, 1938, received with your memorandum Ho. 544/1/11, dated the 12th April, 1938, I am directed to point out that the following discrepancies have been noticed;- (a) The date of promotion to present pay of Mr. D.J. Stephens has been shown as 1-3-1938 with the next increment due on the 1st April, 1938, which is incorrect. Please reconcile the discrepancy* ib) Mr. R.£. Tancred has been shown as officiating Confidential clerk, Bahrain, whereas he should have been shown as the permanent incumbent of the post, having been confirmed in the appointment with effect from the 16th of February, 1938, vide this Residency office order Ho. 451 of the 5th March, 1938. Please ^ acA correct your office copy accordingly, and inform this ^ ' ; M f office of the grade pay Mr. Tancred was entitled to draw on the 1st April, 1938, as well as of the dates of his promotion to his present pay and of next increme nt. 2. Por completion of this office consolidated Return of permanent Establishment as it stood on the 1st April, 1938, please furnish the information required under the following heads/(bV -2- heads in respect of Messrs. G.H. Khan and F. Prince:- (a) Date of promotion to present pay ib) Date of next increment. ic) Grade pay they were entitled to dravt on the 1st of April, 1938. id) Dates of their birth. 3. Names of non-gazetted officers who have been on leave during the year ended the 31st March, 1938, and description and period of leave enjoyed by them have not been shown in columns 5 and 6 of the C.A^G. Form 4. Necessary particulars for completion of these columns should always be furnished. By order, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfNo. 676-1/11. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th May 1938 To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resiclent in the Persian Gulf, Buahire. Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No. 796/8/1 dated the 28th April, 1938. 2. The date of the next increment of Mr# 'D.J. Stephens is 1-3*«1939« My copy has been corrected accordingly. 3. Mr# R.E. Tancred was shown as Officiating Confidential Clerk, Bahrain, on the authority of Residency Office Order No. 614 dated the 31st March, 1938, which would appear to supersede Residency Office Order Ho. 461 dated the 5th March, 1938. He was entitled to draw as* 144/- as pay, Rs* 35/- as Gulf allowance and as* 16/- as Special Pay (as Confidential Clerk) on 1st April, 1938. The dates of his promotion to present pay and of his next increment are 12-3-1938 and 25-1-1939, respectively. 4. The dates of promotion to present pay, of next increment and of birth of Mr. Ghulam Haider Khan are 12-8-1937, 10-8-1938 and 16-1-1907, respectively, and of Mr. P.E. Prince, 19- .2-1938, 19-2-1939 and 8-3-1915, respectively. Mr. Ghulam Haider Khan was entitled to draw hs. 144/- as pay and R*. 36/- as special pay and Mr. P.E. Prince Bs. 112/- as pay and Hs. 25/- as special pay on 1st April, 1938. 6, The following non-gazetted officers were on leave during the year ended the 31st March, 1938. 1. Mr. Abdul Jabbar, Officiating Confidential Clerk. Bahrain/2 Bahrain, proceeded on 8 months 1 leave with effect from 7th July, 1937• 2* Mr« Hidayat Ullah, Officiating 3rd Clerk, Bahrain, proceeded on 4 months 1 leave on average pay with effect from Ist March, 1938. 3* Mr* Aijaz Ali Khan, 2nd Clerk, Bahrain, proceeded on 4 months 1 leave on average pay with effect from 20th March, 1938. For Political Agent,Bahrain C&gt;/&lt;Z- opHo. 1217-1/11• Political Agencyi Bahrain, the 9th August 1938. To The Secretary to the Hon 1 ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf Bushire• Ifcnpr^aiin} Reference paragraph 3 of my memorandusr ^o. 675-1/11 ted the 9th May 1933 ♦ 2m Would you please inform me whether Mr. H.E. Tancred should continue to be shown as officiating confidential clerk, Bahrain^ If officiating, his substantive post may kindly be stated. The information is required to enter ^ his Service Book. for Cfficia-tixig Political Agent Bahrain. / qUNo Political Agency- Bahrain, April llj, 1939. n To The Secretary to the Hon^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum . I enclose, in duplicate, the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, as it stood on the 1st April, 1939. for Political Agent, BahrainStatement ehowing names of non-gazetted officers who have been on leave during the year ended the Slat March 1939. Description and period of leave enjoyed. On leave on average pay from Ist February 1938 to 25th April 1938. On leave on average pay from 24th December 1938 for 3 months and 4 weeks. 1 day^ leave on average pay on 19th July 1938. Combined leave for 6 months (3 months and 19 days earned leave and leave on private affairs for 2 months and 11 days) from 8th July 1938. Bahrain, / April 11, 1939. f 0r political Agent, Bahrain. ir.D.J.Stephens FC.E.Mirza Ismail Barduli Mr.Ghulam Haider Khan Mr.P.£•PrinceDetailed Statement of New Hames etc. New names of non- gazetted officerfc From what office and on what date transferred, or with what bill, health and age certificates were furnished. Names of non-gazetted officers who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now om it ted. From what date ceased to be borne on the Istablishment and why. Non-gazetted officers who have been on other than privilege or casual leave or under suspension during the year. Description and period of leave or suspension from end to what date. r.Abdullah Jassim Boodai Political Agency, Kuwait. 20-12-1938. r.Aijaz Ali Khan r.Abdul Jabbar Transferred to Bushire on expiry of leave. Transferred to Kerman on expiry of leave. Bahrain, f 0T Political Agent, Bahrain, April 11, 1939.IThe Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident to the Persian Gnlf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, with the request that the document be sent direct to the A.G.G.R. with the reply noted in the right-hand column, and a copy thereof to this office, British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .. ft. .9.91 ob e r t 1939 . Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Extract of endorsement No, TA-H,M.-80 dated the 6th September, 1939, from the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, (in duplicate) Subject. Annual Return of Establishment for 1939.1951-1/11 IM Political Ag€ Bahrain, the Sth November 1939. To The Medical Officer-in-Charge, V.M. Hospital, Bahrain. Memorandum Will you please examine Mr. Abdulla Jasim Boodai, 3rd Munshi, Political Agency, Bahrain, .who has been instructed to report to you tomorrow morning and return the enclosed certificate of health and age duly completed. for Political Agent, Bahrain.EXTRACT HU rpr, ig^» r&gt;| TT^T^r) TTJ OPIGI?J ft ^ •ifTT' 11 'RE^LY ITOTET) TJT 'RIGH^-TTT-TriD ^CI Tr TT URGENT OFFICE CF TITF •'CCOTWTATTT GETTSHAL CWTmL HEVSTIUES? 1TE'/ DELHI. No. TA - H.M.-80 Dated 6th September 1939. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Information is wanting relative to the items quoted over leaf of your Detailed Statement of Establishment on the 1st April last. Kindly supply the deficiency by entry on the margin of the required particulars, giving to the answer the same number that belongs to the items answered. Signature ..., Designation - Asst. Accounts Officer, Items (e) Increment Certificate of Mr. Tancred showing the incremeh granted with effect from 25-1-3 in the post of Confidential Clerk, Bahrain, has not yet beefi furnished. His pay should therefore be shown as Rs. 144/- 1 on 25-1-39 and not Ss. 150/- as | shown in the Return. Please state the circumstances in which his increment has not beep granted. (1) The date of birth of Mr. Abdulla Jasim Boodai may also please be furnished. (m) Mr. Abdulla Jasim Boodai has been confirmed on 12-3-39, but his Health and Age Certi ficate does not appear to have been received in this office. Please furnish them now. Reply The increment of H p . Tancred which fell due on 25th January 193 has been withheld for one year* A copy of the office order withhold* ing the increment is enclosed. His pay has therefore been shown as Es. 144/- on 26-1-39 in the Annual Return of this Agency Establish ment forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf t Bushire, and not is. 160/- as stated by you. The date of birth of Mr. Abdulla bin Boodai Is 20-10-1907. The health and age certi ficate is enclosed herewith. f for Political Agent, Bahrai k Copy sent to the Secretary to P.R. under P.L.No. 1956 dated 11-11-39.if K Political Agency, Bahrain Office Order 'rP er A &gt;1^ In exercise of the powers delegated to me by the Government of India, Home Department, Notification No. P.9/18/32, dated the 18th August 1932, I hereby withhold the increment of Mr. R.E. Tancred, Confidential Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain, for a period of one year with effect from the 25th Januaiy 1939 (the date on which the increment fell due) on account of his unsatisfactory workt The withholding of this increment will have no effect of postponing his future increments. Political Agent, Bahrain Copy to The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for information.CERTIFICATE I hereby certify that I have examined Mr* Abdullah bin Jassim Boodai, 3rd Munshij Political Agency, Bahrain, and cannot discover that Mr. Abdullah bin Jassim has any disease, constitutional weakness or bodily infirmity except * I do not consider this a disqualification for employment in the office of - % Mr. Abdullah bin Jassim's age is, according to own statement, 3JI. years and by appearance about 3^ &lt; years#No. ? Political Agency, Bahrain, n April 1?#. ,1940, To, The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political ^eeident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum I enclose,^ duplicate, the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency,Bahrain,as it stood on the Ist April 1940• ; / A for Political Agent, Bahrain,117 •r* Statement showing namee of non-gazette d Officers who have been on leave during the year ended the Slat March 1939. Mr. D.J.Stephens On ccitbined leave for 6 months (gmonths on average pay and 4 months on half average pay) from 10th ^uly . The period from 25th June to 9th July 1939 treated aa time. Mr. R.E.Tancred Mr. Qhulam RaTsbani Mr. M.A.Rafiz ,2nd runshi Proceeded on 72 days earned leave on average pay from 4th November 1939. The period from 23rd October to 3rd November 1939 treated as joining time while going on leave. Proceeded on 6 days earned leave on average pay from 24-2-40. The period from 12-2-40 to 23-2-40 while going on leave and lat to 6th March 1940 while returning from leave is treated as joining time# Proceeded on combined leave for 6 months (4 months on average pay and 2 months on half average pay ) with effect from Rth June 1939. The period from 2l8t May to 4th June is treated as joining time. Bahrain, 24th April,1940. for Political Agent, Bahrain. A \I J MBB=S ' /• ' I ^ ( Detailed Statement of new names, leave, etc. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. /§ Mr. B•Thomas, Head Clerk ( 250-» 10-500 ) Mp. Safftr Islam, I'hird Clcrk t Bahrain. (100-4-120-5-200) ,/?roa Bpttlel: fconsulate- Gcneral, Mes!^ 'after the ex of leave froiji 25th June 19 Bahrain, The 24th April,1940 } From what office and on wbat date transferred or witli what bill the health and age certificates werf farnished. ed pir^y From ^clitic Agency, ^uwa after the ex leave fro© 22i|k Feb ♦1940. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. Mr. D.J.Stephens I&gt;9&lt; al It piry of d Mr. M.A.Hafiz From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the yeai. Proceeded on 6 months com bined leave 10th July 39 after which date tran^fe to British Consulate-^ Bushire. from rred cneral. Proceeded oiH combined leav for 6 monthe from 5th June 1959 after Yfhich transfe to Political Agency ,Mu6ca1 rred Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. (Note.'—ln cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) for Political Agent, /t Bahrain. 111 th. Government semmt ta. ZZtiamlerreO moro thao one ta tto preoediag year, tke aamo ol eaoU office (ami post) m wUoh he wa. employed durmg tte year should bo meutioued with dates. - :» l 'J JDetailed Statement of new names* leave, etc. New names of non-gazetted QoTernment servants. J From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age oertifioates were furnished. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. 1 j Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. (Note.' —In cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen- ■ sion.) J If th® Government servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates. MFP—961 Audit—(M-1796)—19-1-39—15,000.Ko. Political Agency, Kuwait. . 25th April, 1940. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. MaaasaMm- I forward, herewith, the certificate required under Article 62 (l) (g) of the Civil Account Code, Volume I, in respect of Messrs. Zafar Islam and Jasim bin Mohamad, 2nd clerk and Munshi, Kuwait respectively, now working in your office. Political Agent, Kuwait*Article 62 (l) («) C # A # C # I. Certified that Messrs. Zafar Islam and Jasim liin Mohamad now working in the Political Agency, Bahrain, held substantively the posts of 2nd clerk and Munshi, Kuwait respectively, on the 1st April, 1940. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agency, Kuwait. 25th April, 1940.No . /3SJ? -8/1. /I/ ( /its, The Secretary fco the Eon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, with the request that the document be sent direct to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, with the reply noted in the right-hand column, and a copy thereof to this Office British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .. 15th. Octpb er . 1940 . Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Extract of endorsement No. TAHM.78 dated the 22nd August 1940, from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, (in duplicate) P.L. No.2006-1/11 elated 24-10- P.R. Bushire enclosing a copy ■ C ■ R ■ y ^P-^I 11ni &gt; ' Subject. Annual Return of Estaclishment for 1940. 10 issued to the Secy: to f reply to abjection raised/ i-a- EXTRACl 4 To be returned in original with reply noted in right-hand column, To OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GrEIORAL, CSHTRAL RlTSSraSS. Ho. TAHM.78. Dated JTew Delhi, the 22nd August 1940, The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire. URGEST Information is wanting relatiye to the items quoted overleaf of your detailed statement of Bstablishment on the 1st April last. Kindly supply the deficiency by entry on the margin of the re uired particulars, giving to the answer the same number that belongs to the item answered. (Sd.) SUBHAMOKIAM (Designation) Assistant Account! Officer, Central Revenues. ItOfilS xxx xxx xxx xxx 4, The date of lest incre ment of pay of Mr.Haja- gopalan should be 15-10- 1939 and not lo-10-1939. 5. The increment certifi cates of the following persons raising their pay to the ©mounts noted against each have not been received in this office. Kindly furnish. Tipper Div. (English Sec.) (l) Mr.Has Masaud Rs. 180/- Reply /A ^2 J yt xxx xxx xxx xxxC. A. c. 10A. (Art. 69, C. A. C.) Periodical Increment Certificate. (1) Certified that the Government servants named below have earned the prescribed periodical increments from the date cited in column 6, having been the incumbent of the posts specified for not ]ess than.....OHC. ye&amp;ifrom the date in column 5, after deducting periods of suspension for misconduct and absence on leave without pay and, m the case of those holding the posts in officiating capacity, all other kinds of leaVe. (2) Certified that the Government servants named below have earned periodical increnients from the date cited, for reasons stated in the explanatory memo, attached hereto, &gt; Nam© of incumbent. i* U xi d U i) f—i o fd c® v W &lt;H o « o lO (M 1 1 O 4&gt; rH &gt; | •H o c TH at 1 •P CO 1 § 8 ca t H &amp; rfl .2 &amp; &gt;&gt; III H ! Ph . *g ® s a g fl 00 +5 CO S uspended foe miscon duct . From To Leave without pay and, in the ease of those hold ing the posts in officiating capacity, all other kinds of leave. From 10 To 11 N ote 1.—When the increment claimed is the first to carry an officer over an efficiency bar columns 5, 6 and 7 should be filled up in red. N ote 2.—The figure (1) or (2) should be placed against each name according as the reason (1) or (2) applies. The explanatory memo, should be submitted in any case in which reason (2) applies. MFP—1654 Audit—(M-2697)—9-5-40—35.000. ;L for Political Agent, Bahrain, Signature and Designation of Drawing Officer,m Q ^ py of P ar ^ 2 of the auditor Genorul of India D.O. Ko. . • T . WJ-^dmn/K .u .17 2-udjm ,11-39,, dated the 23rd Septenbor, 1940. , ' itUd:Ltor G^n-cri.l h-.s furthur considered the question whether the names of persons holding temporary and officiating appointments should be included in the annual Establishment Return and has reached the conclusion stated below,., Under + — lpla l^ 0 ' Civil Sorvi c© Regulations, service in a temporary post counts for' pension if the post eventually becomes permanent and- under -rticle -371, Civil Service Regulations a . • .TT*? vd ^ hout . ^ substantive ■ ppointment officiating in i - post , which is vacant or the permanent incumbent of which doe-s not 0f + the ? !iy ^ 00Unt —i- ^-y. ' h e is oonfirld lathout interruption m Ids service count his officiating service. iiS he ^nnu'l ist blishment Returns are intended primirily for ri«f» C +* 10 V f sorvicofor pension, the n^mes of ull temporary and officiating Government servants to whom the two 'articles mentioned above apply should be included in the return in order that their service for pension may bo verifiedo (ii) iflie case of esttiblishments on time-sct.les of p&amp;y. the Accountants General may, under Article 62(3) Civil Account Code, Volume..!, require the submission of a duplicate dopy of the annual 'Establishment return, cjid Note 1 to paragraph 122(5) of the ^udit i^.nual permits of the use of the duplicate copy as the fly leaf of the Jiistc-blishment iiudit Register, The annual establishment Return is accordingly also utilised for purposes of audit of pay bills of establishments on time scales of pay; and to achieve this end it is necessary that^it should include names of men holding temporary posts or officiating in permanent posts on the first ^pril of the year to which the return relates in order that the dates of accrual of their increments may be checked by the audit office. TRUjL copy. Superintendent, Wfice of the -accountant General, Central Revenues* ■ -No.5'?7 -l/ll Political Agency, Bahrain May ,1541. To The Secretary to the Hon'tole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. ^-emorandun . I enclose,in duplicate,the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain,as it stood on the 1st April 1P41. for Political Agent , Bahrain,■Orders of competent authority creating the post. - Pebsent incumbent ; Date op Name of Sefttion and post Date of incumbent's birth (as near as possible). Serial number of appoint ments in each class. Name of Incumbent. Pay o» post. Pay of present incumbent and total of each Section. Date of last increment. Remarks (including note of efficiency bar where applicable). Appointment to present post ot of oommenoement on present time-scale. Promotion to present pay. Minimum. Rate of periodical increment, whether annual, biennial, etc. Maximum. • l i* Compared with Service Books and found correct, &gt; (?. /v. At foot of the rotnm should be detailed all items of establishment sanctioned, bnt not yet incurred. m. f P a y 8 0 ' ^ seated on a separate lino immediately below the pay of the officer who received it, the orders of competent authority sanctioning it being quoted in the first column, xne rule aoout entry ot orders of competent authority may bo statod generally thus; the general order is to be entered once only, any other will be entered against every entry which it supports. m cue case ot establisUmenta on time-aoale of pay, tho name; all tempprary men ini!eryAq£ on the date to which the return relates should bp hjoluded indicating the yacanf » whether permanent or temporary in which they are officiating,- MFP—767 Audit—(M-1228)—13-9.39—20,000, kDetailed Statement of new names, leave, ett. C. A. C. 4. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. Mr. Fas MasaudjOffg. Head Clerk,Bwhrain (Special grade) Mr. Naeirul Haq, Second clerk,38bra in. ( Upper Division) J From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age certificates were turnished. eroa British &gt; emeu late- General, Boshlre trorA 10 th f\pril 1^40. From Britlfc&gt;- )ons^late- '&gt;enert*l, Bnshire- fr* : m 4th A s v i 1 40. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. sir. Zafar ^lam,proceeded on leave;,7 days earned leave with effect from let March 1941.The period from 16th February to 28 thj&amp; February 41 and froa Rth March to i4th M arch 1941, treated ae Joing time under £.K.g94-A. ^ /v. for Political Agent, Bahrain. Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. (iVofe.—In cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) \Sp J If the Government servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates.Detailed Statement of new names* leave, etc. * New names of non-gazetted Government servants. { From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age certificates were furnished. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. \ Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. {Note.- —In cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) - J If the Govemment servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates. MFP—768 Audit—(M-1229)—15-9-39—20,000.No./'' 8 -2/1, Political igency, Kuwait, 1st April, 1941. To The Political A^ent, ' Bahrain. Memo randum . I forward, herewith, the certificate required under Article 62(1) (g) of the Civil Account Code, Volume 1, in respect of Messrs Jasim bin Muhammad and Zafar Islam, Munshi and 2nd Clerk, Kuwait, respectively, now working in your office. Political Agency, Kuwait.I)' Article 62(1)(g) C.A.C.I / Certified that Messrs Jasim bin Muhammad and Zafar Islam now working in the Political Agency, Bahrain, held substantively the posts of Munshi and 2nd Clerk, Kuwait, respectively, on the 1st April,1941, Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agency, Kuwait, ist April,1941./ V «01 SSI /V/26 of 1941. Political Agency Consulate, Muscat, dated the lath April 1941* /ff/^ ' , To The Political iigent, B A H H A I N« memorandum. 1 forward herewith the Certficate required under Article 62 (l) Cg&gt; of the Civil Account Code, Volume i, in respect of Mrs HasiP -ul-Haq, 2nd: Clerk, Muscat, now working in your office Maoor, Political Agent ct M.B.M's Consul, Muscat*Certific ate under Art* 62 V,o.IlJ;.L~ Certified that Mr ; i ^asir-ul-^-aq, officiating 2nd^ Clerk Political Agency, Bahrain, held substantively the post of 2ndJ cleric, Political Agency and H«i3«M 1 s Consulate, Muscat, on the Ists April 194!• Major, Political Agent « Consul, Muscat. Political Agency &lt;* H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, dated the 12th April 1941. //1/fNo . 7/7 -1/11 Political Agency, / Bahrain, ,1941. if To The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum . i forward,herewith, the certificate required under Article 68(l)(t) o f the Civil Account Code,Volume I, in respect of Messrs Ghulam Haider Khan and R.E.Tancred, 2nd Clerk and Confidential Clerk, Bahrain respectively, now working in your office. i for Political Agent, Bahrain, kV Article S8(l) (g) of Civil Account Code Vol. I Certified that Messrs Ghulam Haider Khan and R.E. Tancred now working in the British Consulate- General, Bushire, held substantively the posts of 2nd Clerk and Confidential Clerk, Bahrain respectively, on the 1st April 1§41. for Political Agent, Bahrain, Bahrain, 12th May 1941.No.^ -l/ll Political Agency, Bahrain, May ,1941. 7/ To The Political Agent, Muscat, Memorandum * I forward herewith the certificate required under Article 62 (l)^g) of the ivil Account Code, Volume I, in respect of Mr. E.E.Thomas. 'H PI for Political Agent, Bahrain,Certificate under Art. 62 (l)(f) G.A.C.Vol, I. Certified that Mr. E.E.Thomas, Officiating Treasury Officer, Muscat, held substantively the post of Head Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain, on the 1st April 1§41. for Political Agent, Bahrain, Bahrain, 12th May 1§41,He. 1156/V/26. Political Agency .'l r.Bjv^s C Muscat the 11th June 1941, fiZ- i Political Age 1 us cat the ©nsulate L T® The Political Agent Bahrain. Memorandum Please refer to your meiuo rand urn Kc. 88S-1/11 dated the 13th May 1941. 2. As Mr. E.E. Thomas was on leave on the 1st A^ril 1941 no certificate under Article 62(1)(g) of the Civil Accounts Code, Volume I, is required 'by this Agency in respect of him. for Political A^ent .^c H.B.M's Consul Muscat iNo•1246-1/11 Political Agency, Bahrain* 1st July, 1941. To The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat* Memorsnduin * Reference your memorandum No• 1156 -V/26 dated the 11th June, 1941* 2* According to Bushire Office Order No*10 dated 10th February, 1941, on reversion, Mr. E.S* Thomas proceeded on one montli^s leave from 21st January 1941, and since no notice of the extension of his leave was received in this office, the certificate under Article 62 (1)(g) of C»A*C« Vol: I, ha.d necessarily to be forwarded to the post where he had to resume duty. f a for Political Agent, ^ahrain. i kUt OFFICE OF TEE ACCOUNTaNT &lt;3EN33AL CENTRAL REVENUES NEv/ DELHI No. TM4-7/207 Erom Ogtsd the To The Accountant Generalj \ 1 Central Revenues, All Hsads of Of fie 2- Subjects- Annual Itettf olishm , . t Return s. Sir, I) i v In continuation of thi 3 Office Circular letter s No .TM -7 (Cir .y -172 d.ted the - f a November 1940 on the subject of preparation of Anni c 1 ^ stablisbrne n t Return, i I have the honour to state th t the auditor General has since decided that the Return j i question should be ppe - pared in two parts ? one for pe ? aanent establishment including the permanent and oiElating incumbents of permanent posts and the other ccv^ring all temporary posts - in existence on the 1st Apr Lu. • y 2o The above instruction mg/ kindly be followed v^rhile submitting the Annual 3stablishraeir;&gt; Return to this office in future» . , I have the honour to be, Sir 9 Youi 5 most obedient servant (B.N.'Sek Gupta) ' Deputy Accountant General, LRK. Central Revenues. No.TM-7/208 Dated the Copy forwarded to all T.^.J. Sections and i^stablishmen Section of this Office for information!. LRK n r- j n rff ('I U-) (3.NoSer! Gupta) ' Deputy Accountant General, /j ^j£ C entr a 1 Re ve nue s . iCkI Printed in England. NOV. 1940. (500pads.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED, 5/-168 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 'k /2jr NR7 BUSH ICE 11 25 1630 RADIO V' POLITICAL BAHREIN PLEASE EXPEDITE DESPATCH ANNUAL ESTABL I SH^MEN T RETURN = BRITCONSUL A 402 - V YOUR REPLY NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.1 U- h No, 3/L -2/1, The Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agency, Kuwait. 4th April, 1942, -Z£L MF.MORANDUM. I forward, herewith, the certificate required under Article 62(1) (g) of the Civil Account Code, Volume 1, in respect of Mr. Jasim bin Mohamed Munshi, Kuwait, now working in your office. Major, Political Agent, Kuwait. m - / ■ / Wv -■&gt; ■ \ No. 7 Political Agency, BAHRAIN. The -- Mav. 1942. Vo The Secretary to the Hon^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oull, BUSHIRE. I enclose, in duplicate the Annual Return of Permanent Establishment of this Agency, as it stood on the let April, a942« 2. It will be seen that parti ulars of present pay, date of 'birth etc. in respect of Mr.Hidayatullah are not given in the Ctatfcjnent, as they are not available in this Office. 3. Particulars in regard to Mr.V.B.S.Manian, vho is borne on the Bushire Extra ' ar Establishment are gKksx* appended to this memorandum for reference in preparing the Return of your Extra War Establish ment. c for Political Agent, Bahrain. LDetailed Statement of new names* leave, etc- C. A. C. 4. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. J From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age oertifioates were furnished. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. {Note. —In cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) • % If the Government servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates. MFP—768 Audit—(M-1229)—15-9-39—20,000.1 No. i/ll. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 8th May,1942. To His Majesty's Vice-Consul, ZAHIDAN &gt; Iran. MKMORANDUM. I forward, herewith, the certificate required under C.A.C.Art.62(l)(g) in respect of Mr.Hiuayatullah, working in your Oflice as Head Clerk. /V , y for Political Agent, Bahrain. I HCert Ificfttf ,vide Art.eg' l)rg ) &gt; C,A &gt; C . Certified that Mr.Hidf ; yatullah, now working ae Officiating Head Clerk, Zahidan, held substantively the poet of Confidential Clerk, Bahrain on the 1st April,1942. 'olitical Agent, Bahrain Political Agency, Bahrain.^.v^ The 8th May, 1942,Telegram From To no .A/628 Dated 2nd August, 1942. v ^v GTC. Britconsul, Bushire. Political, Bahrain. CIRCULAR. Accountant General, Central Revenues, now also requires annual establishment temporary posts in existence on April 1st last. Please despatch return by first available opportunity vide Article 62 of Civil Account Code Volt i #\k&gt;^ ''l /ll Political Agency Bahrein, The 12th August 1942. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum Reference your circualr telegram No.A/528 of the 2nd August 1942• 2. I enclose,in duplicate,the statement of this Agency's temporary Establishment as it stood on the 1st April 1942.The post of Navicert Clerk referred to in your memorandum No.1310-79/63,dated 3rd December 1941,has not been included,as no suck post is paid for out of Bahrein estimates. For 'Political Agent,Bahrein,No.839-64/270 BRITISH CONSULATE GENERAL BUSHIRE• The 27th July 1942. To iL^he Political Agent, Muscat, Political Agent, Bahrain, 3) The Political Agent, Kuwait, 4) His Majesty 's Consul, Bandar Abbas, 5) His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, 6) His Lajesty* s Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr• M emorandum . Reference Civil Account Code Vol.1, article 62» To enable this office to submit the consolidated return oy the due date, .ill all sub-offices in future post their returns so as to reach Bushire by loth April as far as mails permit. By order Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf— I M ^ Mi' / Orders of competent authority creating the post. P bhshjstt inottmbltnt ; D atb of S-S g 8-' Name of Section and post. §S oi I 1 O O 11 o3 § 'g a Name of Incumbent. P at 0! post. 11^ Si ill R bmaekb (including note of efflciency bar where applicable). Compared with Service Books and found correct. Signature of the head of the office. At foot of the return should be detailed all items of establishment sanctioned, but not yet incurred. _ .,. 1 The personal pay should be stated on a separate line immediately below the pay of the officer who received it, the orders of competent authority sanctioning it being quoted in the nrst column. The rule about entry of orders of competent authority may be stated generally thus ; the general order is to be entered once only, any other will be entered against ev e ree ntry which it supports. ~ . In the case of establishments on time-scale of pay, the narri^pf all temporary men in service on the date to which the return relates should be included indicating the ^pncies whether permanent or temporary m whic ey are c tmg. MPP—914 Audit—(M-17X2&gt;^-20-12-38—15,000. all teiuporary nieii iu service 04 the date to wWch the return relates should be included indicating the ^^nc r* \*p — Politicel Agency, Behrein. Detailed Statement of new names, leave, etc. i .^. to4s , C. A. C. 4. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. 1« Vacant• Confidential Clerk, Bahr ain• 2 m Mr.Hamad bin All, 2nd Munshl, Pahrein. Hr.^hulam Sarwar, 4th Clerk, Pehraln« X From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age oertifioates were furnished. .British Consulate, Zebul* 20. £. 1943. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. Mr. Hide yatullah Age and healt|h Cr.Abdulla Jaseim Roodai cert ificate forwarded wiljh his paybill for cTan'y. 1943.' From 2.8.42. Mr.Ohulam Hebbani From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. 1.8.42. Appointed Dpper In. ler 28.7.42. Resigned. 1.1.1943. Appointed Confident ial Clerk, Bush ire ^, r. ah i dan. K.E.iirzs Ismail Barduli Head un&amp;hi. (8 4 i avi Mr. C.V.Raiagopalen, Confidential .teno. Period since last re for as follcWiD Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. (Note. —In cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) Combined leave for 1 year ijionths on Hverag&lt; ex-India and lonths on half ra^e pay) from .42. turn is accounted P.T.O . J If the Government servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates. MFP—768 Audit—(M-1229)—15-9-39—20,000. — i 1 G-i6eteiled-Stetemei*^-itpw-iiain«fcrje«tve ? -ctc5^- i:cMiect - Ql - L:ui;:t - lt - Qr C. A. C. 4. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. J From what office and on what date transferred or with what biil the health and age certificates were lurnished. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. (From pre-page) lA .42 to 51.7.4:2 Jo ( Left Lii he Les Jo (K ui D Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. Confidential St 1.4.42 to 10.4. Lien '' Actually »n duty- .ning time 3R 294—A)- 11.4.42 to 25.4 ive(earned)-26.4.42 to 31. 1 .f i f 42 to 51.12.42. ►n - Upper Division (earned)- 1.8.42 to 22. ve on iAP - 2?.8.42 to 29 ining time rachi to Buehire, S.R.294-A) 17.10.42 to iive i ider 30.9.4 iity 1»43 to 31.5.43« en - Confidential St en \jity a&amp; 0ffg.2nd Clerk,Bush lining time between Buthir (.&amp;R-.S9-4)transfer to subst • 9.1.43 to 13.1.43. Dtjrty in eubet.spptt. -14.1 Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. {Note. —In cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) enographer, Bs hra in. 42 .42. 7.42.(Leave cont.) Leave ReserveiBusiiii' 8.42. .9.42 2 to 16.10.42 31.12.42 o .Bahrain, ire-let to 8.1.43. e * Bahrain on antive appointment 4^3 to 51.3.43. t If the Government servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates.V Cert ificate.vlde Art &gt; G2(l)(g).0.A.C. Certified that Mr.Zafar Iblam, now attached to Political Agency, Muscat, held substantively the post of 3rd Clerk, Bahrain on the ist April, 1943. Bahrain,the 18th April,1943. Ho. SjJL-1/11. Political Agency, Bahrain. The JillApril, 1943. The foregoing certificate is forwarded, with compliments, to Political Agent, Muscat, in accordance with Art. 62( l) (g) ,C . A .C. Political Agency, Agent, Bahrain - n for Political Agent Bahrain. ISr'yM'y./ ll' / *7/ // Extract from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi 1 s Objection Memorandum No. TA/ER 1942/TA/HM-155 dated the 25th February 1943 to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Information is wanting relative to the items quoted overleaf of your Detailed Statement of Establishment on the 1st April last. Kindly supply the entry on the margin of the required particulars, giving to the answer the same number that belongs to the item answered. Kindly treat this as urgent. 6. The substantive pay of Mr. Abdur Rahman, in the Lower Division, may please be stated. The pay Rs.l4G/- shown by you appears to be his officiating pay as Head Clerk, Khorram- shahr. In No.A.B. iftrl British Consulate-General, Bushire, the \ i May 1943. The foregoing extract is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for favour of necessary action direct with a copy of his reply to this office for record. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.t—' 3 o / s/VJ / 7^ Extract from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi 1 s Objection Memorandum N o . TA / EH 1942/TA/mi~155 dated the 25th February 1943 to the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Information is wanting relative to the items quoted overleaf of your Detailed Statement of Establishment on the 1st April last. Kindly supply the entry on the margin of the required particulars, giving to the answer the same number that belongs to the item answered. Kindly treat this as urgent. 11. The following increment certificates may kindly be furnished; they do not appear to have been received in this office, * * * (ii) Mr.F.B, D f Souza, raising his pay to Rs.200/- (iii) Mr. K.V. Rajagopalan, raising his pay to Rs.150/- * * * * ^(ix) Mr. Jassim bin Mohd. (x) Mr. A.J. Boodai. No.A.B. British Consulate-General, Bushire, the Ifth May 1943. The foregoing extract is forwarded to the The Political Agent, Bahrain for favour of necessary action direct with a copy of his reply to this office for record. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.INLAND: Immediate Class for telegrams important Expresa Ordinary To be iirasd tua 1st Remi&amp;daf 2nd Remindef 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. r letter S J r.nTt 'Memorandum Telegram ' I FOREIGN ; | | Immediate ij Important ^ Ordin ary - | Without priority Dated JTilo No jjeriiil No 19 Issued on (Code word for telegrams. is sent herewith. J.Boodai. Mr.Boodai was drawing the minimum pay of his eubstantive post oi 2nd Munshi, Bahrain, before he resigned. The quebtion of an increment certificate therefore does not arise. I have the honour to be, Zir, Your most obedient servant, -1/11 Copy, v\ 1, The Secretary in the Persiar his endorsemer r - Q b&amp;Xr 4 ^ jrQ»4. ^'rebpect H.B.M's Vice-C request that b la qufciution me New. Delhi S. 5. MGIPC~S2—1916 (S &amp;P) MFP- ■(M.U99)—18.11-40-'-60.000 Pads for Polftri^ai Agent, Bahrain Dated ith compliments, to - a to the Hon'ble the Political Resident Gulf, Bush ire, with reference to t No.A.B.448, dated 17th May, 1943, onsul, Bandar Abbes, with the certified copy of the necessary y kindly be sent to the A.G.C.R.,(Art. 69, C. A. C.) . Periodical Increment Certificate. (1) Certified that the Government servants named below have earned the prescribed periodical increments from the date cited in column 6, having been the incumbent of the posts specified for not less fchan...O.Ufe year from the date in column 5, after deducting periods of suspension for misconduct and absence on leave without pay and, in the case of those holding the posts in officiating capacity, all other kinds of leave. (2) Certified that the Government servants named below have earned periodical increments from the date cited, for reasons stated in the explanatory memo, attached hereto. Nam© of imramboBt. Mr. Jagsim bin Uol Offg. Interpreter, Extra v;ar Estt. Q -P CQ • O +3 00 0) ^ &gt; ^ •H M ■P 03 fi ■P ^ CO 0) JO 0 B CO a ft IC CO ct2 it cd p. o a&gt; ft aT CO 2 I l O • CO 04 o (U c? I OJ CO pc; r |E $ Pi Tj CQ cS g o» I 10 CO ai 11 CO a. CD •H o a&gt; ft (0 I e- OJ ■0 CO sxjbpeitded fob msoon- From To Leave without pay and, in the case of those hold ing the posts in officiating, capacity, all other kinds of leave. From N otb 1.— When the increment claimed is the first to cany an officer over an efficiency bar columns 6, 6 and 7 should be filled up in red. N ote 2.' —The figure (1) or (2) should be placed against each name according as the reason (1) or (2) applies. The explanatory memo, should be submitted in any case in which reason (2) applies. MPP—797 Audit—(M-1557)—15-11-38—30,000. Political AfegU Signature and Drawing Officer.■Page 218— (17) In column 1 of the Statement under Part I {a) In the heading against Section A, after the words ' income arising- abroad ' insert the following :— ' excluding income accruing or arising in an Indian State '. (6) Under Section B— (i) For item 1, substitute the following :— ' 1. Out of income which accrued or arose during such previous year (give details)— (а) In an Indian State (б) Elsewhere (u) After item 2, add the following item :— '3. Out of income accruing or arising in an Indian State which has been, included* as part of the total income in any preceding assessment but not actually charged to tax. [Not to be included in the total at the foot of the page.] [G. B. R., Notfn. No. 21-1. T., dated 28th February 1942.]' Page 219— (18) Under Section C, for items (&amp;) and (c) substitute the following ' (&amp;j Persons resident and ordinarily resident should show here their income accruing or arising abroad other than that in an Indian State—(Give details). (c) Income accruing or arising in an Indian State from a business con trolled in or a profession or vocation set up in India inchiding Indian States. [Applicable to persons resident whether ordinarily resident or not.] (d) Income accruing or arising in an Indian State not included in (c) above. [Not applicable to persons resident but not ordinarily resident.] Notes .—For deduction of Rs. 4,500 under the third proviso to section 4 (i) (c), see Note 9. Income under (c) and (d) is to be included in ' total income ' but is exempt from tax for any assessment for 1942-43 and subsequent years.' [C. B. R , Notfn. No. 21-1. T., dated 28th February 1942.] (19) In the statement under Part II, after item 5, insert the following: item :— - ' 6. Income accruing or arising in an Indian State which is exempt. [Items (c) and {d) in Section C of Part I] '. [C. B. R., Notfn. No. §1-1. T-, dated 28th February 1942.] Page 224— (20) In the. declaration at the end of Part VI, for the word® ' ordinarily reside nt resident substitute the following not resident' ' resident and ordinarily resident resident but not ordinarily resident not resident' [C. B. R., Notfn. No. 21-1. T., dated 28th February 1942.]To The ^eeidency Agent Sharjah. POLITICAL AGENCY r BAHRAIN ! 1944o MEMORi-JTOUM , Will you please let me know at an early date the date of 'birth of Mr. Kamal Din . The information ie required in connection with the estahlishment return of this Agency. 'oryj^-it ical Agent,BahrainPOL IT !CAL AGHTC Y, BAHRAIN No. tlj2&gt;0 -1/11 May 1944. To The Secretary to the Hon^ble the _ Political Resident in the Persian Quit, 'Bushire# T-TF ^ORATTDUM. As required 'by Article of the Civil Account Code Volume I, I iorward herewith the Annual Ebtablieiuacnt returns oi I'he ' ermanent and. Temporary tetebliBlimcnU of this Agency m they fatooci on let April 1944. lor Political Agent, Bahrain.Orders of competent authority creating the post. Present incumbent ; Date o» a •*» ^ § a Ag 10 If Name of Section and post I ;i o o I I il 11 Name of Incarabent. Pat op post. '3 ® -2 .2 jcj ^ «- a 03 otzj -9x1 R emarks (mclnding note of efficiency bar where applicable). Compared with Service Books and found correot. Signature of the head of the office- At foot of the return should be detailed all items of establishment sanctioned, bnt not yet incurred. The personal pay should be stated on a separate line immediately below the pay of the officer who received it, the orders of competent authority sanctioning it being quoted in the first column. The rule about entry of orders of competent authority mav be stated generally thus ; the general order is to be entered bnoe only, any other will be entered agains' pry entry which it supports. „ . . In the case of establishments on time-soale of pay, the na' ) of all temporary men in service on the date tp which the return relates should be included indicating ■■ vacancies whether permanent or temporary in whipb they are officiating. *IFP- 492 Agdit—(M-791)—30-8-40—20,000.Detailed Statement of new names, leave, etc. 0. A. C. L 0&gt; New names of non-gazetted Government servants. .N.0 # J ohennes r. Mohd. As hro f• £aud Fozan r.Mohd. Xemail return J From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age certificates were tumished. I t anaferred froi 7 !' BuLhlre. Joined as Confidential 3lerk,Bahrain from 3-4-43. Transferred from Buthire. Appoint ed substantively 3rd clerk, Bahrain from c3—4—1943 but hosted as offf : Inner Divii ior -'lerj^hxtra Var Kstt, Transferred from Kuwait . Joined as Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. Mr. N,P. C-unther Mr.Zafar Islam Mr.Abdul iohsin atrook Mr, Ghula Ratjbani ^•S.Mirza Ismail Barduli .{r.K.V.Ra ■ agqpalan rom 29-5-43. Joined as }ffg.Censor 3lerk Bahrain m 31-7-43 on from leave. 3flg.erd v * Ma,/cook From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. l-lg-43J Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. [r.Abdur Rahman 3-4-43. Transj-Mr. V .B.S .Manian ferred to Muscat. 5-4-43.Lien transferred to post of 3rd clerk Muscat. 11-5-43. VrariS' ferred to Kuwait. 31-7-43. Trans ferred to Ker-an Consul Retired 1rom 1-8-1943. Transferred to But rdre from 25-9-43, Lien trans fer^ Iroiu 1-12-43. 25-10-43. transferred to ushire.-fcieil tiransf ei'i'fcd Hr.V.S.Sharma ate.^' I-'r. F.B.De^ouza ] 4 ed t If the Goveminent servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year shpuld be mentioned with dates. Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. {Note. —In bases of suspension state wliether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) i-arncd leave for 32 days from*29-4-43 to 30-5-43. LAP lor 4 months from 8-5-43 to 7-9- 43 and lerve On ■ 1 e dic al c ert if ic at e from 8-9-43 to 7-11-43 TJ I US L/fP from 8-11-43 to 22-12-43. Earned leave ior 9 days from 7th to 15th Oct.1943. LAP for 4 months . plus LilP for 2 monthfi' On joining time from 7-2-44.Late of comrafcncenTent of Itf-.ve not known.«v Detailed Statement of new names, leave, etc. ■0 (3. A. C. 4. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. Mr.V. Maycock Mr.G.K.Moorthy Mr. H .W .Dessa Mr. Abdul Latlf J From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age certificates were furnished. Joined as offi Upper Divibion Kxtra War Esti. clerk from 24-9-45. In traabit from Bombay to Bahrain i'rom 8th to 23rd September 43. Iraneferred f: B ub hire.Joint as offg.Confi enographer 25-9-43. Translerred :?rora Buehire.Joined as ITrvper Divis ion, Bxtra War Lett, cleyk from 20-10-43 Lien transferred to post of Confident ial, stenographer Bahrain from 1-12-43,though he did not join ihis office. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Mr.Abdur iv ahman Mr, bharmi om dent ial rom 23-12-43. Transferred to Muscat. 1-2-44. Tram ierred to Kuwait. Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. Mr. ii ohd. As hr? \ f Mr.H#W.Dessa Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. (Note.' —In oases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) Earned leave for 120 days plus leave on urgent private affairs for 2 months. On joining time from 7-3-44. Date of commenceraent of leave not known. Relieved on 20-2-44 D.m. and proceeded on leave and resigntd. % If the Government servant has been transferred more than once in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates MFP—493 Audit—(M-792)—22-8-40—20,000.5. A. C. 4. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. J From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age certificates were furnished. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Non-gazetted Government servants who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. (Note. —In oases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards pen sion.) Mr. M.A.Khire Mr.Ohulam Muhiyud din Mr.A.R.Butt Mr.M.Y.Siddiqi i Transferred f Kuwait.Joined 1-2-44. In tr from iSlst Jen to 31 at JanuD Joined on 7-2 as Ofl'g.Head Bahrain on tx of leave gran Khorramshahr. transferred t post of Confi rlerk Bahrain 1-12-43. Transferred f Khorramshahr. 0ffg.4th cler Division Extr from 1-3-44. Transferred foined as Offg 'Upner Divisio Bahrain from 7 rora on ansit uary ry 1944. -44 3lerk piry ted from Lien o the dent ial from pom Joined as Uoper a War Kstt.), from Busiiire. .2rd clerc n,£xtra War Lstt.) -2-44. Pc $ (L r Political Af 1 . [ent,Bahrain. • MFP—493 Audit—(M-792)—22-8-40—20,000./ v &gt; Detailed Statement of new names, leave, etc. C. A. C. 4.. New names of non-gazetted Government servants. c^s J From what office and on what date transferred or with what bill the health and age certificates were tumished. Names of non-gazetted Government servants who were in Form 3 of previous year but are now omitted. From what date ceased to be borne on the establishment, and why. Non-gazetted Govemnient servants Who have been on leave, or under suspension, during the year. Description and period of leave or suspension from and to what date. [Note. —In cases of suspension state whether the suspen sion period will count towards peii- sion.) % If the Government servant has been transferred more than onoe in the preceding year, the name of each office (and post) in which he was employed during the year should be mentioned with dates.{y \ i C No. 2240/41 CUSTCSM HOUSEl KARACHI. V 5.1944 r ^_ys Certified that Mrr^Bal«eubramanianvwho has been temporarily transferred to the office of the Political Agent., Bahrein, held a lien on a permanent post of Lower Division Clerk in this office on the Ist April ^944 # &lt;Av- Memo '■ Forwarded in duplicate to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum Jib i T358f-1/I1 dated 9th May 1944. COLLBCTOR— 7 Orders of competent authority creating the post. Present incumbent ; Date of ® 53 ^ o S b pu® .5 a S a g lis I M S c Ci. &lt;—&gt;. _ rs . Nftmo of Section and post w a $ S Q^' ii a S rs a Name of Incumbent. Pat of post. 11:1 5n fe C 3 O a V2 ■9 ja 2° *3 CU Remarks (including note of efficiency bar where applicable). Compared with Service Books and fonnd correct. Signature, of the head of the office- \ At foot of the return should be detailed all items of establishment sanctioned, but not yet incurred. The personal pay should be stated on a separate line immediately below the pay of the officer who received it, the orders of competent authority sanctioning it being quoted in the first column. The rule about entry of orders of competent authority may h ''atod generally thus; the general order is to be entered once only, any other will be entered against -■■jry entry which it supports. In the case of establishments on time-scale of pay, the name fill temporary men in service op the date to whioh the return relates ^hoT|ld be included indicating Vacancies whether permanent or temporary in which they are officiating. PFP- 492 Aijdit —(M -791)— 30 -8-40 —20,000. I Jgto^ Circular Memorandum ¥o. A.B.707/8/1 of Aug 33 from Bushire. Establishment Return. P. A. 68 &amp; 69 Please see last x return on pagesM in file l/ll. Thes^ returns were furnished under C.A.C. Vol.1 Art 62(1) and copy of this was sent this year to Bushire vide Secretary*s Memo. TTo. A.B. 695 of 7.7.32 at ^age 64 in the same file. The copy of C.A.C. Vol I in our office is very old and S} obsolete and the section particle in question is not given in it. I am submitting an indent for the books required separately. May the instructions contained therein be noted papers file^ please? CL^ vTA? jiv (U^J&lt; , /4&gt; (a*, if. k, - ^f' ■ ^1 ^2, ^' U -^ L ^ cf^uJut ) tr- L'- jrfT*l/ll Memorandum No. 692-E/9 dated 27-5-37 from Consul-General, Meshed. Mr. Thomas was appointed Second Clerk, Bahrain with 144 file 1/16 effect from the 1st March 1937 (see Bushire memorandum No. 374-19/21 dated the 21-2-37) D.F,A. submitted, please. XT, t Memorandum No. 1293/E/9 dated the 9th September 1937 from Consul-General, Meshed. page 144 file 1/16 In his memorandum No. 374-19/121 dated the 21st February 1937 the Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf informed us that the post of Confidential Clerk, Bahrain, was vacant but later on the Residency appointed Mr. Thomas as a substantive incumbent of the post but we were never informed of this change. It would have saved a considerable amount of unnecessary correspondence between this office and the Meshed Consulate-General if the Residency would have sent us a copy of their Office Order No. 915 of August 1937. 2. Up to now we do not know who is the permanent incumbent of the post of 3rd Clerk, Bahrain. Draft to Secretary submitted for approval and letter to Consul-General, Meshed for signature,please. 4 a Issued letter No. 2057 dated 4-10-37 to Consul-General, Meshed Issued memorandum No. 2079 dated 4-10-37 to Secretary, BushireAcct-LPlease see instructions on page 148. The temporary posts in respect of Mr.Manien and Mr. Jassim bin Mohamnied, have not been shown in the Establishment return. The Annual return of establishmiDent is to be prepared in two parts e .g. (1) showing permanent establishment only and (2) showing the temporary establish ment as stood on 1st April,but it appears that you have mixed two parts in one return only. The post of 2nd lerk,Bahrein,has not been shown in the return at all. What about Confidential Clerk &amp; the Stenographer? 13/5 /42. H.C. now Mr, Jassim 9 &amp; name has/been included in part II of the return. Mr.Manian is borne on the Bushire Extra War Establishment and his name will presumably be included by Bushire in the return of their Special War Estt. As regards the posts of 2nd Clerk, Stenographer and Confidential Clerk; The incumbents of all these posts are officials whose names are not found in the last year^ return. Their names have therefore been included in the separate statement in Form 4, as required by Art. 62(l)(i) / c^- The statement of temporary estt. is typed on the reverse of the main statement and clearly marked/k». Acctt . UL + h + + u Plea f e ree £ Art.62(1) (c) which resds tnat the return should show accuretely the |H sc f 1 ?u 0 f Pf rin ??fnt establishment and will include every post and that it will be prepared in Form 3.The sanctioned scale of the permanent establishment is as under Head Clerk Head Munshi 2nd Clerk Confidential Clerk 3rd Clerk. 2nd Munshi 3rd Munshi In addition to the above the following 2 posts heve been made permanent in October last;- s v ^ ' ov ' Stenographer(U.D.) 4th Clrrk (L.D.) . , ^ i3 evident therefore that there ere 9 posts in all of this Agency statement of the permanent establishment J aL^CC^ /CC ^ | 'I', CtJLo &lt;2^^^ ■ ^ o</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00020d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/998</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00020d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/998</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 1/11 I Annual Return of Establishment</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-03T00:14:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (197 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1A on the front cover, and continues through to 212 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1A, 1B; ff. 81A, 81B, 81C, 81D, 81E; ff. 112A, 112B. The following numbers are omitted from the sequence: 139-147. The following instances of pagination occur: 126-127, 153-154, 165-166, 184-185, 186-189, 190-191, 192-193, 197-198. The following folios need to be folded out to be read: 5, 12, 18, 34, 40, 56, 77, 84, 86, 100, 108, 116, 183, 186, 201.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file covers the submission of annual returns of the Permanent Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain (relating to the employment of Clerks, Munshis, and Medical Attendants) for the years ending 1 April 1926 to 1 April 1944 inclusive, and also to the Agency's Temporary Establishment from 1942.The returns give details of authority creating post; dates of appointment of incumbent; name of section and post; date of birth of incumbent; serial number of appointments in each class; name of incumbent; details of pay of post; and remarks. The returns were submitted to the Office of the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, and are accompanied by detailed statements of new names, leave etc. Supporting papers include covering letters; correspondence relating to appointments, requests for particulars of staff, sanction orders, medical reports and certificates of holders of appointments.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Agency, Temporary War Establishment</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Publicity Office, Persian Gulf, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00020d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>