<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000022_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:38:00.517Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">9 . 7 - I '^ ^ No. \ c m- • of 1363 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bshrsin. Dr ted, Msharnm 29, 1363 January, 25,1944 H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- A number of estates all of Bahrain subjects are under the administration of the Minors T Depart ment of the Bahrain Government. The persons who have an interest in these estates include women, minors, persons who are mentally unsound and cer tain persons who although of age are un'f’it to deal with their own affairs. These people draw allow- ances from the department which paid ^rom the in- come of their estates. It has recently been found that some of the persons whose affairs are administered by the depart ment have deliberately run up debts in foreign shops The Bahrain Government can prevent such transac subjects. The President and members of the Com mittee have approached me on the subject o^ foreign shopkeepers and traders. Does any rule exist by which a shopkeeper is restricted from supplying goods to a minor or credit and if so can you tell me the legal definition of and have purchased goods which they then sold at loss. tions between minors and tradesmen who are Bahrain a minor?phould publish a list with the names of the indi viduals who are unrter the administration o^ the department and also publish, as the event occurs, the names of minors when they take over the con trol o^ their property. I should be obliged if you would favour me with .your views as to what means can be adopted I* to prevent minors who are in receipt o^ allowances which they receive through the Minors’ Department incurring debts by means of credit in foreitrn shops. k . His Highness Shaikh Sulman was President of the Minors’ Department for many years and takes great personal interest in it. j= Adviser to the Government.No.244-6/80. Political Agency, Bahrain, 31st January 1944 To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No.194-24 of the 25th of January 1944. 2. According to the law of India every person domiciled in British India who has not completed the age of 18 years is a minor. In the case hov/ever of a person for whom or for whose property a guardian has been appointed (Court of Wards) the age of majority is deemed to have attained on the minor attaining the age of 21 years. 3. Shopkeepers are not restricted from supplying goods to minors on credit but minors are not liable in law for the debts thus incurred. Courts of Wards are however liable for their charges. Persons of unsound mind, so certified by a Court or otherwise according to the law in force, are not liable in law for debts incurred. 4. I suggest that the Court of Wards should publish a dis claimer of responsibility for the debts incurred by minors and persons who are mentally unsound and whose property is being administered by them. The personSshould be named in the dis claimer. With regard to persons who although of age are in your opinion unfit to deal with their affairs I regret I can give you no assistance, for, according to the law of India and England every adult is entitled to have full charge of his personal property provided he has not bten certified as insane or a Court Order recorded that he is mentally unsound. Political Agent, Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000022_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1299</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000022</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1299</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/80 Bahrain Estates, Minors' Department'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-31T18:06:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-6; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the following:Correspondence between Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, and Tom Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain, regarding the legal specifics surrounding those whose estates in Bahrain are administered by the government due to their age or mental state, including their liability for any debts incurred through use of credit;a public notice issued by the government listing all those whose estates are administered by the Minors Department who are not legally liable for their debts.Folio 7 is internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000022#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>