<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000187_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T10:24:01.605Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] FROM TUIFOjY O a n i a /L i rypne No. 121. Mr a 1 iorgan (i uigora). 14th June, 193 r ^w 5.47 '0 • m * 14th June, 1937. 9 • 30 a.m. 15th June, 1937. u tsn St tt It &lt;» ft ft ft St :t it U t! St it i it ,t it C ' * v J / Sir Po Lorsine f s telegram No. 11 (baling). Minister for Foreign Affairs leaves Angora on June Voth lor Bagdad, Tehran and Moscow. In conversation with me on June 12tn he added little to his remarks to His Majesty's inabassadoi cut Minister of National Economy wita him to Bagdad ana intenas t-o the question of direct supply to Turkey of oil from Iraqi oil fielos. In Tehran, though it is not the reason for his visit, he will endeavour to persuade Iranian Government to settle their frontier differences with Iraq (see Sir P. Loraine’s telegrams from Istanbul NoSo 25 and 30)„ Minister for Foreign .affairs said as regards nis sisit oo Moscow that he would endeavour to reassure the soviet Government ahou the increase of German penetration in Iran which I gather is causing them anxiety. Throughout his journey he will as he puts it 'act as a stout upholder of His Majesty’s G-cvernment » Addressed to Foreign Office He. 121, June 14th, repeated to Bagdad, Tehran and Moscow.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPER'] fY OF HIS ^RITANNl jc MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT - | • EASTERN (Iraq). January 29, 1932. ^CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [E 443/35/93] No. 1. Sir G. Clerk to Sir John Simon.—(Received January 29.) (No. 30. Confidential.) Si r . Angora, January 18, 1932. WITH reference to my telegram No. 1 , Saving, of the 11 th instant, regarding rlie signature of certain treaties between Turkey and Iraq, I have the honour to report that I have been confidentially informed by Nuri Pasha that the position of certain matters raised during the course of the treaty negotiations is as follows : — (a) The Turkish Government accepted his suggestions for the execution ol certain preliminary measures to put a stop to brigandage on the Turco-Iraqi frontier. It postponed the settlement of the question of allowing Iraqi flocks to enter Turkish pastures until Iraq entered the League of Nations. It agreed to instruct its officials to arrest the Sheikh of Barzan if found in Turkey, and to deliver him to the Iraqi Government. It also raised no objection to the settlement of Assyrians in the Baradost area. (/;) Letters were exchanged between Nuri Pasha and the Turkish authorities regarding a readaptation or reinterpretation of article 14 of the Anglo-Turco-Iraqi Treaty concluded at Angora on the 5th June. 1926. This article refers to the Turkish share of royalties received by the Iraqi Government from the (then) Turkish Petroleum Company. The letters exchanged provide that His Majesty's Government (in the United Kingdom) are to be consulted in respect of the negotiations which are shortly to take place with a view to amend article 14. in 2 . 1 am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty's High Commissioner Bagdad. I have. &amp;c. GEORGE R. CLERK. [354 ft—2]^ *, INDEXED ** . In any further communication on this subject, No. £ r/m :ss —not to any person by name, 1 and address —not to any person bf name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. ! THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign- Affaire presents his compliments to ^ ^CCore/dy £jf jl&amp;T —^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, O' transmits herewith copc^ of the under-mentioned paper. 7 '^ Foreign Office, t , 1932. . Reference to previous correspondence : Similar letter sent to C Q to krll'' AM* 14 — 59 °! ( 2 )[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and shou ld be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] \ n • 4 S- L- FROM TURKEY . Telegram (ejn cl at v / from Sir G. Cler^ (Angora) January 11th, 1931. R, 9.30 a.m. January 16th, 1932. No.l (Saving). /. /. Residence Convention and Treaties of Conmerce and extradition between Turkey and Iraq were signed at Angora yesterday. Press st.'tes that first two agreements are based on most-favoured treatment and that ratifications will be exchanged at Bagdad. Texts will be forwarded as soon as pos ; iblec Addressed to Foreign Office No.l (Saving) repeated to Bagdad No.l (Saving).-THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GO kernmeKI;* /-n EASTERN (Iraq). CONFIDENTIAL 781 1 Octobei l 0 Section 1. [E 5509/1932/931 No. 1. Si?‘ G. Clerk to Mr. A. Henderson.—(Received October 13.) (No. 387.) Constantinople, October 8 , 1930. ’ I HAVE the honour to report that Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Francis Humphrys, His Majesty’s High Commissioner for Iraq, arrived here on his way to Bagdad on the 4 th instant and left for his post this afternoon. i r. 2. Sir Francis Humphrys and I went to Angora on the oth October tor two days during which time he had interviews with the President of the Republic the Prime Minister, the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, and the Permanent Under secretary in the Ministry, and this morning before leaving he also had an interview here with the Minister for Foreign Affairs, who returned from Russia yesterday and leaves for Angora to-night. . 3. The High Commissioner will no doubt report m due course to the Colonial Office the substance of these interviews and it is unnecessary for me to describe tliem at any length. But I may be allowed to put on record the excellent impression which Sir Francis Humphrys made upon the authorities as well as my feeling that the visit has established a valuable personal contact, that it came at a most opportune moment, and that it will be of great use to the High Commissioner when discussing with the Iraq Government the policy of that country towards lurkey 4 The reception of the High Commissioner by the authorities at Angora felt nothing to be desired. Both at the luncheon given by the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs and at the return luncheon given by me, at which the Prime Minister, contrary to his almost invariable habit, was present, and at the audience with t e Gazi, the atmosphere was one of sincere friendship and cordiality. The Gazi was . at his best and kept us for nearly two and a half hours discussing the autochthonic ’ races of India and Mesopotamia, giving, with great frankness, his opinion oi ex-King Amanullah, and telling us confidential stories of his relations with Enver Pasha during the last phase of Enver’s career. 5 . In the more official interviews with other Turkish authorities the Kuidish problem as affecting Turkey and Iraq was discussed frankly but in the same friendly spirit: no direct complaint was made of the weakness of the Iraq Government, owing to which the Sheikh of Barzan had been able to support the Kurdish rebels m Turkey and indeed, due allowance seemed to be given to the fact that the Iraq Go\cnimen had'not yet been able to bring the Sheikh’s district into complete control. But the High Commissioner was asked to press upon the Iraq Government the necessity tor them to take effective measures in the interests of both countries, and It eel that Sir F Humphrys was able to convince the Turks that it was not goodwill so much as material force that was lacking in Bagdad, and his assurance that he would impress the facts upon the Iraq Government immediately on his return clearly gave confidence and satisfaction. . , ,, ^ . 6 Sir F Humphrys took the opportunity to point out that the Permanent Frontier Commission was designed for such matters, and that much could be done if the commission, and more especially the Turkish members, showed a more active sense of their powers and responsibilities. . . 7 The Hmh Commissioner’s visit happened also to coincide with the receipt of your telegram 0 No. 88 of the 3rd instant, relative to the possibility of the Turkish Government seeking permission for their troops to enter, or operate within. Iraq territory Happily! it had not to be raised either by the High Commissioner or myself since as I reported in my telegram No. Ill of to-day, the Permanent Under-Secretary, when describing the present situation of the Turkish troops on the frontier, spontaneously a°dded that there was no intention of asking for leave to cross the boundary and said that renewed instructions had been sent to the Turkish offieei in command to respect the integrity of Iraq territory. TJ . , n _ 8 . I have sent a copy of this despatch to His Majesty s High Commissionei in Bagdad. p 13 I have, &amp;c. GEORGE R. CLERK. J [247 n— 1]In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. ti-Uf li arid address —not to any person by namei but to— / 1 The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. ’‘I THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs nre compliments to fists y and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop tu, of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office. Reference to previous correspondence : 'jjo J Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. y 4W Kv J . O Subject. EMC’.OSURE IN \'EE’'LY LETTER I - 40 -2 OCT 1930 ! : iT 0 , 7 l 'o-Citi'l A..., t 0 -i i i-vAt. AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Similar letter sent to 14— 21388 B ( 2 ) ^ ^ l0 m Oy Oofaz”.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT, r 665 1 EASTERN (Iraq) Section' t 7 CONFIDENTIAL. [is 4976/1932/93] No. 1. Sir G. Clerk to Mr. A. Henderson.—{Received September 15.) Constantinople, September 4, 1930. l ttt? U NTnri Pasha. Prime Minister of but a member of my staff found him very pleased with his reception. 3 . Nuri Pasha said that three main questions had been discussed (1) Mosul Oilfields.—Nuri Pasha had said that he had seen the Turkish note handed in by the Ambassador in London and told the Turks frankly that it was quite unconvincing. He pointed out that Iraq s interest m the exploitation of the oilfields was nine times as great as the lurkisii one and that real efforts were being made to develop the oilfields as soon as possible. He knew that the question was still under consideration and thought that there was some question of making an early payment, but he hoped to know more definitely in a few T days. Nuri Pasha got the impression that the Turks did not care in the least about the trace ot the pipe-line, realising as they did that the French were pushing the northern, just as the British desired the southern. ( 2 ) Frontier .—The Turks had told him that they had been entirely satisfied about the Iraq Kurdish policy and general attitude on frontier questions since 1926. Nuri Pasha pointed out that the last thing the Iraq Government desired was trouble on the frontier, and ga've quite definite assurances that no Kurdish intrigues would be encouraged. The Turks havin 0, referred to the Barzan incident, Nuri Pasha pointed out that the Iraq Government had themselves decided to deal this year with the Sheikh of Barzan, had for three years raised the question at meetings of the Permanent Frontier Commission and had definite proof that the sheikh had received arms and supplies, if not from the Turkish Government, then from Turkish sources independent thereof. He, Nun Pasha, was only too anxious to put an end to the intrigues of the sheikh and had contemplated approaching the Turkish Government with a view to the latter holding the frontier on one side while the Iraq Government dealt with the sheikh on the other. It was now too late for action to be taken this year, but if the trouble continued, he would probably make proposals to the Turkish Government in this sense next spring. (3) Commercial Treaty .—The Turks were anxious to complete this as soon as possible. Nuri Pasha said that he was, too. Agreement would probably be reached, as regards the judicial convention, in the next month. The Turks had now proposed to him that the commercial treaty should also include residence clauses. He had replied that he was not competent to discuss this, but that they might make the proposal through the usual channels Nuri Pasha had asked the Turks what they thought of the new treatv. The reply was that the Labour Government had done two of the best things that had been done by the British Government since the war—the conclusion of the London'Naval Treaty and of the Anglo-Iraq Treaty The Turks were delighted about the latter, but efforts had been made by the French to make them critical. They told Nuri Pasha that the French had suggested that the Turkish press should criticise the treaty in the direction of showing that, for practical purposes, it would include Iraq in the British Empire. The Turks had replied that they [220 p-lj'I could not dream of doing this, because they considered the treaty to be an excellent thing, not only for Turkey, but for Iraq, and Tevfik Riistii Bey indicated that, at a suitable moment, he would have articles inserted in the Turkish press in a sense favourable to the treaty. Nuri Pasha much appreciated this indication, for a favourable attitude towards J^e treaty would be very valuable to him in Bagdad. The Turks had asked Nuri Pasha about Great Britain’s attitude towards Turkey. They realised that Britain was coldly friendly towards Turkey, but thought this did not get them very far. Nuri Pasha pointed out that it would, perhaps, be best for the Turks themselves to show real signs of friendship, for the British were not of a nature to curry favour. He gathered the impression that the Turks were still pretty well tied up with Russia. In his conversation, Nuri Pasha had also referred to the Lawrence reports and pointed out what absurd rubbish they were. He had himself seen and talked with Colonel Lawrence in London, and the latter had been most amused at hearing the reports. The Turks had replied that they did not believe in the least in the Lawrence reports, which, at the beginning, had emanated from French sources in the same way as the first reports of Lawrence intrigues in Afghanistan had done eighteen months ago. The Turks had a very definite impression that France was doing her utmost to prevent any further development of friendly relations between Turkey and Great Britain and Iraq. 4. When I saw the Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday he at once expressed his gratification at Nuri Pasha’s visit and said that he was quite satisfied as regards the frontier and the Iraqi attitude towards the Kurds. 5. With respect to the oil question, his Excellency was clearly much perturbed at the thought that the delay in exploiting the oil diminishes by so much the twenty-five years during which Turkey is to receive her 10 per cent, of the profits. Under the Treaty of Angora, it is, of course, the case that the twenty-five years start from the coming into force of the treaty, but Tevfik Riistii certainly expected exploitation to begin within a year or two of that date. I have had the advantage of reading in your despatch No. 536 of the 1 st instant the very complete reply returned to Ferit Bey, and I hope that it will soothe Tevfik Rustii’s fears, for I need not dwell on the political disadvantage to our relations with Turkey of our seeming to encourage Iraq in anything which the Turks will be all too ready to interpret as a deliberate intention to put off as long as possible the day on which payments to Turkey must start. The fact that, if the positions were reversed, this is just what the Turks would do themselves will not affect the Turkish point of view. I have, &amp;c. GEORGE R. CLERK. P.S.—I have sent a copy of this despatch to the acting High Commissioner at Bagdad. G. R. C.INDIA OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000187_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2849</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000187</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2849</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 17/5 'Iraq. Relations with Turkey'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-26T22:08:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (12 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the following reports submitted by HM Ambassador to Turkey, Sir George Russell Clerk:Report on the visit of the Prime Minister of Iraq (General Nuri Pasha) to Turkey, to discuss frontier delimitation, the Mosul Oilfields, the Iraqi policy towards the Kurds, French attempts at interference in Anglo-Turkish relations, and the completion of the Turco-Iraqi commercial treaty.Report on the visit of the High Commissioner for Iraq (Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Francis Humphrys) to Turkey, to discuss the Kurds, and the Permanent Frontier Commission.Report on the treaty negotiations between Turkey and Iraq, including discussions of means to prevent robberies on the Turco-Iraqi border, and the reinterpretation of Article 14 of the Anglo-Turco-Iraqi Treaty of 1926 regarding Turkish Petroleum Company royalties.The file also contains a telegram regarding a visit by the Turkish Minister for Foreign Affairs to Iraq to discuss the oil supply issue.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Prime Minister</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to the Republic of Turkey</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Borders</topic></subject><subject><topic>Kurds</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000187#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>