<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002d3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-12T16:25:46.612Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">S' — 2 r- y £ 0 FILE CO IV-&lt;4 &amp; -Ui'^iQe ybf tTn^. Politicsl Resident D»Q&gt;]£o»C/245 l in Jne 'Perfeiap Gulf? Camp Kuwait. V'' 51^ IV,^. ? rlfet^^thej 19th March 1940 I v.i i O [ 1940 J Would you please refer to your letter Ko. P#Z*513/40, dated the 2nd February 1940, on the subject of the recovery of the cost of wireless sets supplied to officers in the Persian Gulf. 2 * Apart from the Consular Fee Account we have no means of accounting for expenditure direct to the Foreign Office and have in fact now been in structed to recover the expenditure from His Maj esty’s Government through the Government of India and the India Office. * I am sending a copy of this letter to Caroe. R.T. Peel, Ksq. , C*B.H.,M.C. The India Office, London. * sent under P#L#No.0/246 of 19th March 1940. jMOmi&gt;oLecPi if ?9MAR 940 INDIA OFFICE -f Telephone No.: EUSton 5030. ' lfrv//ma FILE COPY MINISTKY OF INFORMATION, 3 '7 SE NATE HOUSE, LONDON UNIVERSITY BUILDING, MALET STREET, VV.C.l. p.z. T13 I94G 25th Januar^r, 1940. N_... Dear Feel, vjvV Secretan of the Foreign Office has drawn my attention to your No. F.Z. 165/40 forwarded to him under cover of your endorsement of 17.1.40, relating to the supply of wireless receiving sets to officers in the Persian Gulf. The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, in minuting to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, presumes that the expenditure on the five wireless sets will be accounted for by him direct to the Foreign Office. Actually it is the Ministry of Information which has assumed the financial responsibility for these sets. Yours sincerely. R.T. Peel, Esq. India Office. M MOkP*I-.DEPt. 26 JAN 940 INDIA OFFICE^y\ \ Prom • The z s j J7 JAN 1W0 fo M y to the Government of Indxa 194® W External Affaire Deparhuent, 165 Unaer cieore To - Ttie Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Memorandum ho.F.2o7-ft/39. hated New jelhi, the December 1939. SUBJ’CT:- Supply of wireless receiving sets to officers in the Persian Gulf* Reference Secretary of State's Impress letter No*F*Z.7317/39, dated the 23rd November 1939. 2. It is presumed that tne expenditure on the five wireless sets will be accounted for by you direct to the For e ign Off ice, London • Sd/- G.K.S. Sarma, Under Secretary to tne Government of India V• • ■Q-je ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S t^TTCR No. DATE f;±££iV£0 247 S3 12 -9-1*c O FILE COPY GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ■■■■■■17367 EXTERNAL AFFAIRS Department. ifl,. ,0^0 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR u Pf.B. 7 '*‘ f ^ m9S * a 9 e MM by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more th ™ ord '™*y mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, ? X ! h J h i e *F ,dxfion •* if it bad been telegraphed. To save lime and to obviate ‘'““'’S'™- 11 «'*«»/- Mo. F.257-N/39. ^ flotei November 7939. To Secretary of State for India, LONDON. Supply of wireless receiving: sets to officers in the Persian Gul?. '2 Reference our telegram No. 1247 dated 29th August 1939 2. The favour of an early rep ly^is^re^uestedj The issue of the above has been authorised. L C. Vk QJ3 Under Secretary to the Government of India. OfZo MFP—1613 B&amp;P—(M-2617)—21-4-37—15,000. (Signature) (Designation)ifrw/ecr ‘ Telephone No. : EUSton ttWr- 4321 r. p, jooifi , MINISTRY OF INFORMATION, pa ~-y- WiTUTS OP EDUCATION. ; ONDON UNIVERSITY BUILDING, 7317 1939 MALE! STREET, W.C.l. 20th November, 1939 Dear Peel, Thank you for your letter P.Z 6921/39 of the 8 th November regarding the incidence of the cost of Wireless Sets for Officials in the Persian Gulf Area. The Ministry of Information will be responsible for defraying the cost of these Sets, and there is no objection to your informing the Government of India accordingly. Yours sincerely, R. T.Peel, Esq., M. C. , India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l RECd. concept. ?\NQyA939 INDI A /OFFICEI— 1 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l P.Z.6921/39 etli HovemLer 1939. Dear Rush!)rook Williams, Thank you for your letter No.F.P.2009/1, of the 2nd November regarding the incidence of the cost of wireless sets for officials in the Persian Gulf area. The attitude of the Government of India is that the cost of these sets should be considered as an Imperial charge and be borne by His Majesty’s Government. May we now definitely inform them that His Majesty’s Government agree to bear the charge? As to arrangements for the supply of the sets we feel no doubt whatever that the sets which are purchasable in the Persian Gulf, were acquired locally without delay on receipt of the Government of India’s authority at the end of August. In the circumstances we think there is no need to call on the assistance of the Communications Department of the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely Pr^ r'e sor I.,F. Rushbro ok-Wi 11 i ams, (Sgd.) R, PEEL, C.B.3., Ministry of Information.LFRW/ML !LS^ ephone No.: EUSton-60.m^- 4321 f. H 2009/1 A FILE COPY K. 1 - h/ l lu, r*A, MINISTRY OF INFORMATION, L.?a •• JOUSE, )ON UNIVERSITY BUILDING, MALET STREET, W.C.l. 2nd November 1939, Dear I am sorry for the delay in replying to your No. F2 5310/39 of the 7th September regarding the cost of wireless sets for the Persian Gulf, and to your subseQuent reminder No. FZ 5493/39 of the 25 th October. The Ministry of Information favour the supply of wireless sets at Government expense : and if the India Office find themselves unable or unwilling to pay, the cost will presumably be borne by this Ministry. In practice, the arrangements for the supply of these sets have been undertaken by the Communications Dept, of the Foreign Office. Would it be convenient if that Department were to act on behalf of the India Office in this matter? XiAZoLTJ^ Yours , J.P.Gibson, Esq., India Office, Whitehall,PiLE COPY 3 s- S3(o. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ? . 3 7 \ External Affairs Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL), k a n -f w 1- 4J 1 I ^ !9a)9 1 HA fN B ,—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. F.257-N/39. To Dated Simla the 30th August 19 39. Political Resident in the Persian Crulf. (Repeated to Secretary of State for India, London).^ 4 1 Subject:- Supply of tireless receiving sets to Political Oificers in the Persian Gulf. In supersession of the orders contained in express letter from tho Government of India in the External Affairs Department, No. F.257-N/39, dated 31st July 1939, the Government of India are pleased, in view of the special circumstances prevailing, to sanction the purchase of wireless receiving sets for the following officers at a coat not exceeding the sum mentioned against each:- Rs.. (1) Political Agent, Kuwait.- rECoPOU.E^t. £L-; I INDIA OFFICE ( 2 ) (3) Bahrain. Muscat. (4) Residency Agent, Sharjah. (Signature) (5) Head Interpreter, Busiure, ... 400/-. ... 400/-. ... 400/-. ... 300/-. *'Total:' s 44 . MFP—1048 S&amp; P—( M-2042 )— 17-12-37 — 20, 000, (Designation)3 . - 2 - \ 2* The sets should be treated as special office equipment and the officers concerned will be responsible for their naintanance in good condition.. The cost of upkeep and running expenses should (a) in the case of the Political Agents, be met by them, and (b) in the case of the Residency Agent ana Head Interpreter, be charged to Residency contingencies. 3. A further communication regarding the incidence of the cost involved will be made later. The issue of the above has been authorised. Under Secretary to the G-ovemraent of India. L 'ZBZS&amp;zmMKmmmmmmmLmmmmmmmmmmmmrnm file copy lN D cxc - w ^7- S ^ Allotted to Political Depar Copies circulated SECR IUOU - (37 groups *) 3145, D E C T P H B R OP T E L E G K A tft. From Government of India, External Affairs Department 5 to Secretary of State for Indiao Simla, 21,11 hours, 29th August, 1939 0 Dated Received 18 e 30 hours, 29th August, 1939, XXX . 1247 v Addressed to Secretary of State for India No,1247, repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Your telegram No, 1460 dated 26th August® v — — Wireless sets for the Persian Gulf® 2® Sets for Political Agent, Roweit, Bahrein and Muscat, have also been sanctioned hy us under Middle East publicity arrangements® Presume cost of these will be borne by His Majesty’s GoverryaearUiNDE ' jLE COPY tyl- Cg) = 5(fr r,o S i &lt;W:' XI / ! 9 - ) y *o «o Allotted to Political (External) Department. Cox Sb_ Circulated. 52 groups. 5139. DE CYPHER OP TELEGRAM. Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India. Dated Reshire, 12.10 hours, 29th August, 1939. Received 14.45 hours, 29th August, 1939. 398. Addressed to India Office, repeated to Government of India. Your telegra m No.1 460 of August 26th. 2. Five sets in all required, one each at Bushire, Koweit, Bahrain, Shargah for Residency Agent, end Muscat. 3. Suitable sets can he purchased locally at Bahrain and Koweit. Cost per set for Arabic side up to Rs.400 and for Bushire, including Customs duty, Rs.500. Please sanction purchase. REQd. POL.DEPt. iOAUwma INDIA OFFICE — ~£3 HVrl/KC 38, Belgrave Square, London, S.Y/.L. August 23rd, 1939. Dear Joyce, Our Hear Eastern Section put in a claim for the supply of wireless receiving sets^ to^ suitable individuals in the countries with which they are concerned. Some of these countries are foreign, others Y/ithin the jurisdiction of the Colonial Office. I am writing to you with regard to Bahrain and Oman, for political relations v/ith which I understand the India Office and the Government of India are responsible. Our Hear Eastern experts have put down^tentative provision of five sets (ordinary all-wave receiving sets) for each of these territories. 1^ suggested that possibly these figures may be too high. For the moment, what I am anxious^to discover is the proper channel of approach on this matter and the authority v/ho should advise what provision, if any, should be made in Bahrain and Oman. Yours sincerely, 8B7 j k '939 J A. H. Joyce, Esr., India Office, Y/hitehall, S.Y/.l.•IDS*** Britconsul Bush ire, BSPBATSD;- Secretary of State for India, LONDON. No. F. 257-H/39. Dated the 31st July 1939 Supply of wireiegs receiving sets to Political Officers in the Persian Gulf. Reference your egress letters Nos. 0/213 and 759 dated the 23rd May and 3rd June 1939 respectively. 2. The general question of sup lying mrelesa receiving sets to officers serving in remote .Agencies and Consulates was carefully considered by the Government of India in 1936-37 and they came to the conclusion that except in places where conditions were exceptional, the supply of receiving sets at Government expense could not be justified. In this connection please see the letter from the Govern ment of India in the Foreign and Political Deparhaent No.F. 59-4, dated the 20th January 1937. The Government of India are still of the same opinion and ihey therefore regret their inability to sanction the purchase of wireless receiving; sets for the Political .feents at Bahrain, Muscat and Kuwait. They however recognise that there are special considerations in the case of the Head Interpreter at Bushire and the 'Residency Agent at Sharjah, and are plersed to sanction the supply of wireless sets to them at a total cost not exceeding Ds. 800/- which should be met by re-appropriation from within your budget grant. Umm ck!*! The.... its ^AhIjuo vJX t ok RECd. POL. DEPt. 8AUG1939 INDIA OFFICE4805 - 2 - Hie sets should be treated as special equipment tor the Ttesidency Office and the maintenance cost charged to Residency contingencies. — — — THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. - &amp; Under Secretary to the Government of India. ( a/7 GOVEENilENT OF INDIA, Department. / L, O \ ItfJUN 1959 ; sj't EXPRESS LETTER 1959 ^ ')/(&gt; 9u 7, A, [N. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, toith the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Brit consult 3ushir«, To foreign - Simla* / Rtpaated - India Offict - London. A r o. 75^1 Baled 3rd Junt, 193 9, SUBJECT: Supply of a wirtltss rt coiving sat to Buahira. In continuation of my Express Letter Bo.c/213 dated the 23rd May f 1939. 2. There is already a receiving set furnished Government in the Residency at Subzabad* where the Resident lives and works* which serves for the reception of news by the Resident. 3. Bow, however, that I have been requested by His Majesty^ Government to comment on the effect of foreign broadcasts in Arabic in so far as these concern the Persian Gulf I have instructed my Head Interpreter here to listen in to these broadcasts. My inter preter however* lives near the Residency Office in Bus hire Town, some seven miles from Subzabad. It is of course out of the question for him to travel 14 miles every night to Subzabad and back S. 6. MFP—1196 SAP—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000. /to2 to llston In. At prosont, as a tamp or ary ■oasuro* ho Is using tho oot of a friond in tho Toon, but this is obviously I s unsatisfactory aa a permanent arrangement. A second set Is therefore required for office use in the Town# and I would os grateful if the grant ashed for could be increased by ks. 500/- to ccrer the cost of this set# including Iranian customs duty. 4. Provided I am supplied with the above receiving set I can telegraph my comments# when necessary# to the India Office without waiting for telegraphic report from them on any item calling for comment# thus ensuring a saving in tims and in tele graphic charges. (Sd.) T.C.POVLS political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.t,CUs ^ .U k FILE COPY GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. ' X\ s.Cfoito ^ Stsjbki OonfldeiitiaX 3448 1939 / ^5 JUH b J&lt;4 EXPRESS LF.TTER (AIR MAIL). I S ' l- u. &lt; ^ tN.B.-™« &lt;»•?'«»'r!»iriirif?.^V^.c. *- •** forvtaltiie* ^ responsible officer of the Department.] !Ua-» ( No, 0/213 To Repeated Baled f&gt; Office of Uie -.oliile&amp;l resident uJ '- f r in the Persian Oulf ,70am*? Kuwait. ^ ^ 23rd May 39 u &lt;L sju. ^ teJ? i ^ The Secretary to the Ck)Terriffient of Tn&amp;ia 3 o- * &amp;-* in the Rxtemsl \ffairs Department, Simla. /c^ t ^ -f — €w^t^ c«. ^ ( His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London.V' Reference ^ b^AJt fc- d 4 —. K-‘Yv4&gt;, subject: iroTision of tireless receiving b\ t&lt;rjL. sets for j olitical Agencies on b/u u . the \rah Ooast. ' . Since the inception of the B.B.C. Arahic broadcasts Political Agents on the Lrab Coast, at the request of His Majesty’s Government, have been carrying out Important duties in connection with reporting ° n the quality of reception, effect on local public opinion, suitability of programmes etc. More recently these duties have been increased by ^he necessity for reporting on wireless propaganda from foreign stations* 2. Hp to now this work has been carried on by means of wireless sets privately enmed by j olitical Agents. while this has been adec-uate as a teni&gt;orary measure it is obviously unsatisfactory as a permanent arrangement e.g. at present the new . olitical gent, Kuwait, Galloway, does not own a receiving set. It is essential in my opinion that each agency should have an official set provided by Government. 3. In addition to the volitical Agents the Residency Agent Sharjah, should have a set so that, in addition to reporting on broadcasts, he should be a distributing centre to the Truoial Coast {Signature) Shaikhs RECd. POL. DEPt. -1 JUl\i1939 INDIA OFFICE {Designation) S. 44. MFP—985 S&amp;P—(M-1597)—27-11 -3&amp;—10,000.(Id) 2 . 3haiidis and. their suDjects of B.B.O. hroadoasts. This would form an important pert of his duties, especially in an emergency. 4* In regard to the cost of such receiving sets. Owing to the low customs duty in the irah States good sets can he purchased for about iJs.400. I recommend that &lt;U‘W* this sum he put at the disposal of Political Agents, Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat, for the purchase of sets, the type being left to their selection having regard to local receiving con ditions. The Residency Agent, Sharjah, where there is no local electricity supply, should have a battery set costing B»# 300. The total grant applied for is therefore Ps. 1500. i 3d. T.C.FOTLLi! Political Besident in the Persian Gulf Attested for Secretary to the Political resident in the Persian Gulf.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002d3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/4145</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002d3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/4145</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 35/37 'Persian Gulf: provision of wireless receiving sets for Political Agencies on Arab Coast and Political Resident'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-29T22:21:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (29 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 31; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns supply of wireless receiving sets for Political Agencies in the Persian Gulf.The file contains correspondence between the Government of India, HM Ministry of Information, the India Office, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Information</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002d3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>