<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003cb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:35:11.186Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Results of Examination after each Series of I TTy fyutvaiu/ jult ^ fifaJ. No. ofrounds Date Since last Total to examin- i date ation Present condition of Inn Powder ch- .iber and bore f W. H Breech filings ' Wedge t f Note the amount and position of scoring, if an;., • addition to defects not already noted on this Memo. $ Quote the number on the article. § Fill in here the date of any repair ordered. Extractor |Record of Rounds fired. Number of Rounds Fired Returned from Date Blank With projectile Remarks *v Reduced 'L- \ \ \ % * u In computing the number of equivalent full rounrls, 1 proof=2 full and four f, sixteen ^ and sixteen blank '^rges may be regarded as equal to one full charge, but in recording the rounds on the Memorandum of Examination §, ad blank rounds should be shown as such.”Ordnance Quick-firing, Hotchkiss, 3-Pr., 4-Cwt. Mark I. Scale, ^th. y V\\\\\V\\\'\\\\\\\\\W^TxVV^'A J ; - 53 . 35 ^— LENGTH OF RIFLING- 7 ^* 06 ^’ LENGTH OF BORE-— ■-' 30*63 TOTAL LENGTH ■ &gt;! •&gt;! The gun is composed of three parts, all of steel, viz. :—the A tube, over which is shrunk the jacket carrying the trunnions, and receiving the wedge, being locked to the A tube by a small hoop screwed on in front. The chamber has a conical front, and is slightly coned throughout its length. The gun is rifled on the polygroove system (plain section) with 20 grooves, which have an unifonn spiral of 1 turn in 25 calibres. After firing a shifting of the hoops may take place; if this is but slight, and does not increase, it may be disregarded ; if otherwise, the gun should be provisionally condemned. . A crack in the steel barrel is sufficient to warrant provisional condemnation, but care must be T taken to discriminate between a crack and a superficial stieak. This gun should be examined after each series of 1 50^ IS'fe&amp;etdes. The condition of the bore can be ascertained by taking impressions of it in gutta perchr instruments for this purpose are in charge, requisition should be made on the Ordnance Store Departn Full directions as to the examination of Ordnance are given in the Equipment Regulations, and Instructions for the Examination and Repair of Naval Ordnance.BHflaBBI a INSTRUCTIONS. fl This Memo, is intended to present a complete history of the gun from the date of its issue from- the Gun Inspection Department to its final return into Store. /'A- It is to be always kept with the gun and to accompany it when returned into btore. The number of rounds fired, including blank charges, to be entered by the Officer in chaige, at the conclusion of each day’s practice, so that an accurate record of the firing may always be kept up. &gt;. The results of any examination whilst on service, will be added by the Officer, or other Examiner, who performs the duty, and the rounds totalled up to such date. If at any time this Memorandum of Examination be lost or damaged, a duplicate can ^ obtained from the Inspector of Guns and Steel, by whom also inside sheets for continuation of the . r^-^d-of the rounds fired will be supplied on application. , %No. C 1? or 1016. Political A&amp;sncy, Kuwait. 17th March, 1016. 1 To O'U# Deputy political Resident, Bush!re. Memorandum:- Please refer to your Telegram No. 5c&gt; uated irtii March regarding ammunition supposed to be in Kuwait. It is of course possible that there are secret stocks in the town the existence of which is unknown to the Sheikh, but as I have had five persons enquiring se .arately and ail assure me that there are non^- remaining I cannot think It likely. The best cour e would seem to be to allow some of ties men you mention to come and buy and see what happens. A copy of this memorandum is being sent to Basrah. Lleut-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait.CONFIDENTIAL. A (b No. C. of 1916. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 24th May 1916. 7 To The Political Agent, K u w a i t. o your iIo*C~l , 7 dated l^th March, I enclose a copy of a Note written by Mr. Chick after his visit to Bandar Rig at the end of April, It appears to show that ammunition is available at Kuwait and is obtained from there. I regret that through an oversight this note was not sent to you before.$ 4 X Ammunition smuggled from Kuwait. About the end or April a certain Eushiri Nakhuda, Hus fain ? Ze.j.r Ahir.ad, wlic hfifl reaided in Kuwait for sono tin.a past arrived at Bandar Hig with a Kuwaiti 'bellun'. Haidar Kean’s men got to know of ammunition being on board, and were instructed to offer to buy it from the Nakhuda. He then produced 8,000 rounds of .303 ammunition, which Haidar than has kept. 2. Nakhuda Hussain Zair Ahmad stated that these had been obtained from Ha.jl Kuhammad All 1,'arafi (Behbehani; of Kuwait, and soma shopkeepers. The system adopted was for the boatmen to go to the merchants selling and shopkeepers, and take away IOC rounds or so at a time on their person. The ammunition thus arrives ii sacks, not in the original boxes. Roughly, Haidar Khan thought that some 20,000 rounds monthly came over to Hashur, Hindian etc. (From Dilam and Rudhilleh he and his brothers kept strick watch, so that ammunition % should not reach Borasjun through their ports). In Mashur, Haji Muhammad Ali Marafi has an agent. It is from this source that the Behbehanis, and Kuhgilu tribes have got their ammu nition of recent times. Besides Hajl Muhammad Ali Marafi (who is a notorious smuggler - his family are well known) Hali Nejef Kuwaiti’s nephew, the son of Haji Muhammad Ta'^i, named Abdul Hussain also has over ammunition, but his stock is now said to be exhausted, that there-are a number of shopkeepers. 3. Haidar Khanand I think that the Nakhuda named, under threat of punishment might be got to give information as to stocks. Hail an says that formerly the Shaikh used to take import duty on import , and export duty on export . For sore time past he has taken both duties on import , and Haidar Khan is inclined to think that the Shaikh, or his men, know that6*i&gt; the Kuwaitis sell small quantities, and ship them. han still thinks that the best method would be for joint represen s - ' tc inspect al dhows before leaving the port, and ■ -‘•her 'xl :..vay ininQdiatQ.y aft.©!* inspection* i tha hio was at li^anty to ti’y all could get fron Cuwait, as it would deplete stocks there. Sd/- H.5.Chiok.: T 0„ o' 1916. Britiah Residency and Consulate-General, • , Q ,: April 1916. J |L I'he Political Agent, X U ’V A I T. ilEMORANDUi:. yith reference to your liernorandum Nc.G-l? of the r?th iiarch suggesting that the-friendly Khans who have aprlied to me to purchase arna at Kuwait should be allowed to send repreaentativsa to Kuwait to eff&gt;ct their purchaaaa, Ahmad •Chan of Angali has now sent the bearer of this, Kubanrad All bin Karbalai Hascan Kuli Angali with 30 (or leas) old Kartir rifles. They desire to sell these in Kuwait and -purchase more modern weapons (Magazine rifles) and a small amount o** ammunition. A copy of this Memo is being sent to Basrah. .a Tor. Deputy Political Resident,''ef 3 $.&lt;v- —HO C 44 of 1016, To Political Agency, Kuwait. tiny 03rd 101C* The Deputy Political Resident, Buehlre, mmmm 4 Plw.m ref or to your Memo Ho 630 of 6th April informing me that an Angali raa coming over to Kuwait to replace old rifles by modem onec v?ith ammunition. The man preaentecl your Homo to n** on tth Huy, He mentioned that he was also supplied with six thousand rupees for the special purchase of ammunition. l^o euccess seems to have attended his efforts, and incessant enquiries by me have Invariably the same result. There is no Mauser ammunition in Kuwait now in any quantity, and the few thousand rounds *hich might be collected. In the couse of se veral weeks would not be purchased at leoe than 2Q rupees per t un&amp;rod round z , A copy of thlc* Memorandum ia being cent to Basrah. CM 1° Lt-Colon«l, Political Agent, Kuwait.The Residency, Bushire, 14th June 1916. £ V I enclose an extract from a letter addressed by Haidar Khan of Bandar Rig to Chick, regarding the doings of Zaij* Ali of Bilan:. Haidar Khan is genuierely/anxious to put a stop ‘to the smuggling of ammunition if he can. * Hussain Khan has just written to say that he had not and would not write to the Shaikh in favour of Zair Ali.■^iWguifg’n. ho iXtract fro-: a letter dated 8th Jure, 1916 frora Haidar Khan Burdai Rig, uo i-r. H.G*Chick, C.I.S., etc Bushire. x A certain Bair At! of Dilum went to Kuwait sone tine ago and bought p ,000 rounds of ammunition, but was arrested. He huo now arrived at Dilur. with the intention of obtaining a latter from Hussain Khan to the Shaikh 0 f Kuwait asking that the latter will return the ammunition. I have written a letter to Hussain Khan, telling him not to give any letter to zair Ali. I now request you, in case Hussain Khan writes or has written a 1 + ' v ' t ’ i10 Shaikh of :uwait, to inform Kuwait that the ammunition should not be returned to Zair All, so that in future people will not embark on such dealings. Hair Ali is originally from Das ti, and has resided in Lirawi for severa 1 years: he went to Dilur last year. ,-- .. *■ ' f ^ f ' ' •' - &gt;fyf Major Hamilton, I hav.e no time to reply to this as I intended to do this evening but; the replies a • (1) • Where is the ammunition ? Why didn't they send me a sample whelp in traoing it? (2) . Why didn't Haider Khan arrest the Nakhuda and sent him to me for disposal? (3) . Note Chick's rotten sentence at end of para 2 which we discussed. (4) . There are no stocks here but as I have explained already Bedouib bring in small quantities, e.g. of the specimens attached, and dispose of them. Thus a few thousands can be collected every now and then.- 20,000 a month is quite absurd. are Sd/- W.G.Orey 25-6-16 Lt—ColThe Residancy, Bu sh 1 re, 3 1 31 Au^li s t 1916. / Please refer to the corres-poiidence endinf? .vith rry letter dated /Vf* regarding the sale of arms -nd ammunition in Kuwait. Ahmad Khan Chief of An^ali has recently sent one argent named Rais Muhammad Hassan here on business and he is believed to be a reliable man. Rais Muhammad Hassan states positively for a. fact that a certain Tang is tan i Nabhuda Ha ? i 7 ' _ ^ 4 ^ bin Sarur' recently went over to Kuwait and bourht a Ip.rge quantity of ammunition which he is now selling in Borasjun ard neighbourhood at Krans 140 per 100 - a pretty lucrative busi ness at that price I should think! Do you think there can be any stores of Turkish ammuni-28 th September 1915 / Referring to previous correspondence on the export of subject of^arms at Kuwait, I write to say that I heard from a reliable source that 6000 rounds Mauser Tangistani boat for Zair Khidh&amp;r Khan the Tangistani I think the only way to find out if this traffic goes on and to stop it if it does would be for the Shaikh to search dhows leaving for Persian Ports. But of course it is very likely that the Shaikh does not like to take any drastic measures, as they would make him unpopular. I can quite see his point &lt;r of view, but on the other hand it is rather annoying for us here to get these frequent and reasonably au thenticated reports of ammunition coming over from Kuwait and going to the hostile Khans. ammunition were recently brought over from Kuwait in chief Major R.E.A.Hamilton, Political Agent, KUWAIT.With referercs to previous correspondence on the subject of the snuggling of Ammunition from Kuwait to Persia, I forward for your information a copy of a Kemo which I have sent to Bahrain with its enclosures, 2 reports from the Director of Customs here. You see the information regarding the import of ammunition is coming in from all sides (the General Officer Commanding here wrote to be about it the other day), and I think there is no doubt that it goes on. The number of rounds specified (30,000) is probably an exaggeration. I understand that it will not be possible to get the Shaikh to do much, and that he is not in a position to act very strongly d&gt;n the matter. But perhaps he could find cut who has and who sells the ammunition, and we could possibly buy it up, or something of that sort. I believe Sir P.Cox made a suggestion to this effect before. Major R.E.A.Hamilton, political Agent,British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, w./yry of 791 *. Brnkire, 18t)i October, 131*3 To The Political Agent, Bahrain. UeRorandmu I would inrite your close attention to the attached ri translation (fron the &gt;ench) of a letter from the Provincial Di rector of CustOEB at Buohire rog rding recent snuggling from Bah rain to Dilwar on the Tangistan coast. Simaltaneously,the direct^r reports the snuggling of 30.000 rounds of amimition,and 300 cheota of Tea from Kuwait into Dilwar. It my be,of course,that the Nakhudas exporting the goods men tioned from Bahrain have given the Customs in abrain a fylse de claration of destination: or that they have preferred to lose t: eir deposits rather than obtain a certificate of receipt from the Per sian Customs: or possibly the consignment may have been actually shipped from Qatar. As regards the import of sheep into Bahrain,perhaps it will be easy for you to trace the Nakhud; *fl name: we havojK not had any un derstanding with the Persian Customs hitherto regarding exports smuggled out of the Persian coast to : r brain. It seems hardly pos sible to insist on iakhudas producing their export passes before larding live stock &gt;tc In B*brain,ard nrobably inadvisable a- a - rain depends for food on these shipments. Perhaps you have some sur suggestions to offer on the subject. Deputy ResidentTranslation From: Prorincial Director of Customs Bushir© To: najor Hae,etc,Qtc, B'askire Dated 14tk October,1^16. I send you attacked a copy of a confidential report TTkick I hare received from Pais laidar,former head tufan^cki at Dil’var, wkom 1 have reenp^tgod as intelligence agent at Dil'jar,in jiiick ke informn mo of t-eo follo’.riiag smuggling:- Fron 3a3arain to Dilwar:- 131 ckests of Black Tea. 31 n of white tea (i.e. white tifis). 20 Bags of curry. 1'rori Dilwar to Bahrain. 200 Head of sheep. According to vrhat was arranged with Dr Chick (see his letters of the Iflth and 21st August 1916 and mine of the 17th and 31st of that month) all goods exported from Bahrain for the Persian coast are subject to the following rules,which I give word for word here with : - n tfakhudas at Bahrain to declare their cargo,^nd the port to 'which they are bound,and deposit approximately the amount of 'the Persian duty with the Customs in Bahrain on producing a 'certificate from the Persian Vudir of the sort,where the goods 'were landed(verified by the Customs Director at Bushire,Lingeh 'or Bandar Abbas) to the effect that d^ty has been paid,the r a- 'khwda will obtain the return of his deposit'• How it is a fact that so far I have been asked for no certifi cate of this kind to bear witness to the regular import into Dil- rar of goods exported from Bahrain. Consequently I should be glad to know if the system cited above is applied at present in Bahrain,and how it is possible for a Ha- khuda to have deposited a sufficient sun in cash at Bahrain,and yet not cone to claim this certificate from the Persian Customs anth rities in order to be able to release nis deposit at Bahrain.J British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, *7 &gt; - ^ lu^i Bushire, 7th November, 1917. fa &lt;Z.o^v ^ ^f/xLu^^jLLcis SS Will you please refer to Col. Trevor^ demi-official letter of 31st August regarding steps for the prevention of smuggling from Kuwait to Persia. You replied on 14th September and I see from a note Col. Trevor replied to your letter on 21st September, but these letters were unofficial and are probably not on your record. Will you please let me know if the steps indicated in the letter of 31st August could now be taken without difficulty. The Customs have raised the point again and I do not wish to let it wait for Col. Trevor's return. It would be advantageous if steps could be taken without difficulty, but Col. Trevor noted he did not wish to V press the proposals on an unwilling Shaikh. * dU^yO L/ Lt.Col. R. E. A. Hamilton, Political Agent, Kuwait•No. C/^/^Tof 1917. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, 19th November, 1917. A copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded with compliments to THE POLITICAL AGENT, KUWAIT, with the request that he will kindly ascertain if there is a person named Karbalai Abbas Quli bin Agha Ueshedi Haidar Jahrumi at Kuwait. If so, he is clearly a man to be cleared out, or denounced to the Shaikh. Letter No. 1138, dated the 7th November 191 7 , from Major, First Assistant Resident. the Political Agent, Bahrain, and enclosure.No, 1138. 32 POLITICAL AGENCY. Bahrain, the 7th November, 1017. To Pirat Assistant Resident, Bushire. NEHORANDUH . On September 21st I intercepted the attached letter addressed to Karbalai ’Abbas bin Aqa Mashhadi Kaidar Khabbaz b Jahrumi - in English at Bahrain , in Persian at Kuwait . The ' attached note gives translation of passages regarding arms which nay interest the Intelligence Officer in the Persian Gulf. Sd./ P.G.Loch, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. Translation of Extracts of Passages from three letters narked 1 to 3. 1. It is stated in No. 1 paragraph marked 'A' 'send me a ten-shot pistol with cartridges.' ■ • '- para 'B' it is stated 'regarding pistols you should not forget to bring as many as you can as it is very good, because in Jahrurn the price of 100 rounds is forty (40) Tomans. You should in any case buy some and any loss or risk is acceptable to me.' ^ para 'C' it is stated 'Please bring a few ten and seven shot pistols together with rifle, and pistol cartridges. Dye is very scarce here, so you might bring any quantity you may get.' ✓ A note by the Agency Interpreter dated November 3rd 1917. L : ^ rad ?- careful oonf id91lt ial enquiries as to where -.ar.alai Abbas cm Aqa Mashhad! Haidar lives at present: anl S ntW«°»t n R f ? r Gertair -&gt; 30Ee sa .V is at Kuwait ' and others at Basrah and so on; but possibly he may be now staying at either of these two places or at* ’Abadan. 1 • .REPORT by the RESIDENCY DRAOOPAN All bin Ahneci, Shnikli Htiasain Clmhkutahi 1 s ^an, and Ghulara Huaaain bin Abbas have arcain proceeded to Kuwait by one of the Tangiotani boats about R days ago for the purchase of arns arid annunition. They have embarked on board that boat at the port Dilv/ar. Sc./- ■uhj''p~ad Khalil. Datsci. the ? Rth Eehru f ry, 1918 • M No. g/ f/of 1918. British Residency Consulate-General, 3u 'lire, 1 3th T 'e 1 '»ru?-ry, 1 )L . Copy forwarded with compliments to ihe Deputy Civil Commissioner, Basrah, The Deputy Commissioner of Police, Basrah, The Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. By direction.1917 No. JHb of 1917. Political Agency and Consulate, Muscat. The 5th February 1917. % To The Political Agent, Kuweit. Memorandum. .1 have the honour to forward the acco v n/ing- statement with reference to two men who are proceeding to Kuweit to purchase arms with the request that I may be informed of cny information which you may obtain regarding their movements and actions in order to check the accuracy ***d the source from which | I have obtained the information. 0 Major, Political Agent and IT. B. M’s Consul, Muscat. 4/ /'O-zrkStatement of , By S* S. ' Burnra M that left Muscat on the 30' January 1917 two :aen najne^l Hasaim ( f *trier’s tutme not 'known ) end TIaji Jun^oo ( father’s name not known ) Zid^r-lis, took 21 'bundles of driead limes to Basra* They v.ill jo to Kuweit from Basra to purchase rifles to sell at Batinah, I know then ns arras dealers. Two months ago Kashira purchased two rifles from Kunarak and took then to Kekran and sold then there. Recorded on the 1st February 1917.? Telegram, Knolaii*. Prom, Bill Bushire. lo. Politioal Koweit. Ko, 398. Dat&lt;?A ?7th. received 28th. March, 1918. 3°). T^o young Seyyids from Kizerun reported to have gone to Koweit ten days ago to buy arms atop Please detain if found. Copy to Blockade Officer, Kuwait. Please let rae know if you hear anything of these. &lt;t Captain., Political Agent, Koweit.Ho. of 1918. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire^/^March 1918. / . v To /f/7 The Denuty C-ivil Coimrissioner, Basrah. Memorandun . It is c mmonly rep rted here that Gusbah is freely used for the purpose of loading, o * transhipping, arms and amnunition, intended for illicit import into Tan- ls + an. T have no apoci'ic evidence to support this, but Haider Khan of Bandar Rig, among others, has men tioned it to me as an undoubted fact, and several re- into rorts of such imports/** Tangistan were received about the end of 1916, though the source of these imports ?as never definitely traced. Gust&gt;ah is also frequent ly mentioned as the centre of a considerable trade in snuggled tea. As regards the arns, the idea appears to bo that the bargains are struck in Koweit and the goods sent secretly, probably by Koweit water-boats, to Gusbah, where they are transhipped to T ngistani dhows. I suggest, therefore, that although there is as yet no specific ground for proceeding against Raji Sultan of Gusbah, it is advisable that the Shaikh of ’ oha-narah should be asked to institute seme stricter control over tha trade of the place than appears to exist at present. I remember that he has always had some difficulty in controlling the Gusbah people,but I imigine that he *ould welcome an apportunity to establish his authority there on a firm basis, with our support if necessary.IT'S Report by the Residency Dragoraan. Zair All bin Zair Ryder, Kadkhuda of Ghahtal, reports that four Tanpistani^ dealers have proceeded to ait tqf buy annunition thro\iph Yusuf Kazerooni. Their ir^Hs follows: - Hassan son of Zair Khidhar, Zair Muhanmad son of Haji Hussein, Muhammad Ali (or Alee) Kanan, Zair Ghulan Hussein son of Abdul Reza. M.Khalil British Residency, Bushire, dated the Rnd Jay, 1918. No. c//f/? of 1918. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, 5th May, 1918. Copy is forwarded with compliments to The Deputy Civil Commissioner, Basrah, 'The Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. f 1 %■ Major, Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf.' ^ l- ' _yr ''Jr '4 Telegram. linclair. (Priority). From. Political Kuwait. * u ^o. Political Buehiro. No. 878/13/7. Dated June 24th, 1918. 6«“) ti Information from reliable source states two Bushiri ho£ts sailed with eight bundles arms and a?nmunition packed in pennies for Dilwar A.^A First sailed 5 days ago Nakhuda Husain Crambot after ^f boat painted green Aivii Becond 'three days ago Nakhuda Aiamad cousin of Husain AAA Both Nakhudas have prominent moustaches AAA People here have idea we are about to make house to house search so they are likely to try to get -rid of arms in this way# Political 878/13/7 ^ K' ■V o • /&amp; (- Political Agency, Kuwait, Bated July 14th, 1918. O.C. H.M’a. H.T. 'Zaida'. * ernoranduni . • % I heg to request that you will take the prisoner, Yuauf Kaaaruni, sent herewith to Basrcih and hand him over to the Lepresentative of the deputy Civil Commissioner, who has Been asked by tele; raph to send a guard for him. It would be advisable to keep him in chains. He may be accompanied by his womenfolk and children about which a separate telephone message will be sent to you. Please take the best measures possible to prevent the man escaping as he is wanted for ^uu-running. They have been supplied with food for 3 days. Captain., Political Agent, Kuwait., i Talegran. iSnolair. (Priority). '&amp;J iTOin. To, No. Datad Political Kuwait. political Buahire ropaatad Basrah. 101:3. July * 14th, 1918. 6v ^ Compliance your request am sending Tusuf Kazaruni with one wife one son aged about 16 and two small daughters in charge Captain Zaida to Basrah for onward transmission to you AAA They have their personal effects but shop goods are being confiscated AAA View of Shaikh's action trust you will ensure very ez^plary punishment your end AAA No arms found here AAA Addressed Eushire repeated Basrah for favour of sending guard to take over prisoner and family and arsanging onward passage in safe custody. Political. ■Copy of nano. , No. 5808 • ' Datod tno 22nd Jul^, 1018, Prom:- Deputy Conniagiorior of Polj.oo, Basra, To:- Deputy Political Resident, BUrhire. • C'b \ Reference Political Officer Kuwait• a telerrram No. 1015'dated 14th July 1918. I attach herewith a Nominal Roll of the 5 Prisonem mentioned therein. Kindly acknowledge receipt to ne aa well as to Political Officer, Kuwait. Nominal Roll of Prisoners icing sent tc Buahlro Sd./- W.3.Davis, Major, lice, Basra•N°. /OjY of 1918 * British Residency and Consulate-tfeneral Bushire y August To The political Agent, Ko ^eit. Memorandum . — / Haidar Khan, Q, Yo? Hayat Baud, who is generally &gt; habitually concerned in the arms trade between Koweit and Tangistan:- (1) Hussain s/o Muhammad Niru. Tangistani. (2) Khuda Karam s/o Kal Abbas. Bahraini by origin. Father lives in Shabankara, and son visits Koweit. Local information here confirms the fact that these two men regularly visit Koweit, wit^ cargoes of onions ^tc^-Jl/nave no confirmation of h he charge of armsj) smuggling age [ should be glad if you would make enqv tries into their character and conduct, and Heputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf.Telegram# i^ijolair# ^roro# Political Euahira. To. Political Kuwait. No. 116?. Dated August 26th, received 37th, 1016. l Kaasar. son of Zair K^i^dhar ^0 y«ara and Ahwaz won of Zair Abbas bald headed left Jilvar for Kuwait weefc a^o to buy ammunition with chief of Taneietana money please take usual action. Political. Passed to Asst.Political Agent, Kuwait . We spoke sbout this on phone and ls.100/- may he i given Tor eaoh man once he is arrested and handed over to us. V/hen found we must write to the Shaikh to have them arrectod. /I ■ ' KTiwait. ' dr' Oaptain., r Dated August 27th, 1918. Politioal Agent, Kuwait.4^ REPORT by the RESIDENCY DRAOOllAN . I hear that Yusuf Kazeruni has told one of his relations who is in Buahire that he had four houses at Kuwait and two of them were searched where no ammunition was found, but there is some ammunition in other two houses and that it seems no search was made in those two other houses, otherwise it would have become known by this time • Copy of the foregoing is forwarded with compli ments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. Sd./- Muhammad Khalil 25.8.18. No. C/355 of 1918. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, 28th August, 1918. By direction• ' i \ ' r Telegram. Prom Bill Bushire To Political Baghdad No 1579- Dated and reed 22nd November 1918 Holder of Passport 1109 of 20th October Yusuf Kazeruni Birect evidence has now been obtained of his implication in smug ling from Kuwait Is therefore undesirable and if he is al owed to remain in Mesopotamia suggest he be made to give guarantees ftegret evidence not forthcoming earlier Bill Bushire No 26226 Office of the Civil Commissioner,. Baghdad,the -dnd November 1918 P_0_ Basrah (6 c opie s) Copy for favour of disposal or report Sd/- A T Wilson Lt Col I A Offg Civil Commissioner Copy to P A Koweit for favour of any information as to this man and his present whereabouts Sd/- A S Meek Major P 0 BasrahNo. C/493 of 1918. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, 89th November, 1918. To The Political Agent, Kuwait. Memorandum. I am directed to forward to you herewith for information, with reference to Kuwait telegram No. 1489 dated 4th October 1918, the following extract of a letter dated the 88th instant from the Provincial Director of Customs, Bushire to the First Assistant Resident, Bushire Report from Dilvar (Tangistan). 80*11♦IB. Sailing boat, Nakhoda Abdullah and Reis Teimur landed 40 rifles and 50.000 cartridges from Kuwait. His Majesty^ Vice-Consul, Bushire.Telegram. Code. From. Polit,ioal Banrain. To. PolitLoal Kuwait. NO. 114. Dated January B8th received 29th, 1919. 17th December last 1226 Rashid bin Abdur Rahman al Dowish Najdi is the owner of wool and smuggled cartridges detained here propose sending him to Bushire with cartridges and corres- u pondence regarding for disposal by first steamer n Tillr Iw noted smuggler and case may lead to go d results Addressed Bushire repeated Kuwait.l Telegram. ^rom - Bill Bushire To - Political Baghdad No. 200 ' * \ Dated 7th and received 8th February 1919. A Nejdi subject of Bin Saud, Rashif by name, has been detained by Political Agent Bahrein in possession of smuggled cartridges . He is reported to be a noted smuggler. Political Agent Bahrein proposed to send him here for disposal but I see no advantage in landing him in Persia. Assuming case against him to be fully proved how do you consider he should be dealt with ? Bill Bushire . Telegram. ^rom - Political Baghdad To - Political Bushire No . 1668 Dated 8th February 1919. Your telegram of 7th February 200. Unless you or Bray see strong objection he should be handed over to Shaikh of Bahrain for punishment. Political Baghdad . No . P.A ICE OF THE CIVIL COMMISSIONER Baghdad , the 10th February 1919 . r Copies for information. Offg: Civil Commissioner. It .Col.,No. 866. r'b i politioal Agency, Kuwait. Dat^a. 2oth October,' 1919. To His Excellency Shaikh Saliit, C.S.I., Ruler of Kuwait. \ A.C . I have received the following report from the political Agent Bahrain;- 'A Kuwait boom na^huda Ahmad a l Qhadiri arrived here from Kuwait on 81st? September with a Kuwaiti named Abdullah bin Ali al Sharidah with some wo^en passengers. He had 40 rifles and 1200 c cartridges hidaen in beddings. He was au^empting to smuggle them into Bahrain late ao hight and was detected by the Customs special watchman. The arms were reported to and seized by His Excellency the ShaiKh wh^has confiscated them. The man as well as the naidiuda was off by the Shaikh and the Customs without any further enquiry or punishment.*' This shows without a snadow of doubt that arms are still being smuggled from Kuwait, and as the Nakhuda and Abdulla a « Excellency will give them exemplary gnstxaihmsHi punishment so that bin Ali al Sharidah have been caught red handed I hope Your it may act as a deterrent to others. Sd/~ L.M.D'Mello. H.C.V Telegram.' Code. prom. Deputy Resident-, Bushire . To. politioal Kuwait. No. 1043. Dated 20th received 21st May, 1920- jlo •)' /qie Have received report that two persons Haji Abbas 0-uraKi and Zair Haider bin Qaum Chahtahdii left for Kuwait some time ago to purchase ar^.s and ammunition and have been staying with merchant tia. ed Yusuf who has been arranging purchase of arms and ammunition for them it is said that they are shortly starting bacK for so/ne small port near here but I expect they i will have “left. Please mace confidential enquiries and wire me if any truth in report and if so whether they have left or not and in latter eventuality when they are likely to do so and if possible nature of craft in which they propose to sail and probable destination. Deputy Resident. • »! ) u /35 f ■ • . Telegram. Code n 1 politioal Busliire. individuals named in.your telegram 1043 are here since last who five months trying to recover Rs-30,000 iro^ fusuf was deported iddle of f ruly 1 j 13 Stop Latmer in turn clai sac it from bro thers -in-law of Ha.jri and Mul ah Saleh iactotum ana Secretary resi ectively of Shaikh on account of advances made to purchase arms will telegraph as soon as they leave. political. 411. / J- I/C political Agency.Kuwait - 25/5/20*\ No /~N • WW of 1920. Memorandum. The following is an extract from a report made to Consul, * i Bandar Abbas by the Deputy Governor of Minab: ^ One Seyed Yusuf a Persian who had got into trouble in Lingah escaped to Shargah and Dubai and from that time he has been residing there. M Now he is trading in fifles with some Arabs of Koweit. He imported.about 40 rifles and 18,000 cart ridges into Biyaban and gave them to Barkat as a present.” Will you kindly make enquiries about this man*8 doings and report.Political Agenoy, Kuwait. Dated the &lt;J7th July 192o. Noor 19-ao. To . The Deputy Politioal Resident, Bushire. Me m orandum . ^ePerenoe your memorandum No.113d dated the 11th July 19do. Can you itinaly inrorm me whether the said Seyed Yusur therein reierred to is 'trauing in riPles with some Arabs or Kuwait** by oorrespondenoe, or whether he is supposed to be now in Kuwait himseir. In the latter oase would it be possible to obtain any partioulsrs as to his personal appearanoe eto., which would help to identiry him.telegram Code. From Political, Kuwait. * To Political Bahrain. j no. . * : . v ' ■^ated 2{5th August 1920. ' ' i * \ Political,Bahrain. ' i Box of arms and ammunition detected heing embarked on Bamora by two passengers for Bharain. stop Ad box contains considerably more bolts than rifles they may have had confeder ates with other consignment. Political P.A/il lolitioal Agency, Kuwait. \ •^ated the 6th Se. teaber 1520. No. v/ ' 624 of 1520. To. His Excellency the Shaihh Saliin el—Mubarak Kuwait. I have the honour to send herewith the. box containing arms and ammunition which seized on the S.S.Bamora duly sealed by me. ‘ The arms and ammunition contains in it are;- ‘ 11. British rifles barrels of various kind. 12 £2c©strokes stocks. 29 Rifle bolts. 100 British rifled cartridges. ( 512 Turkish Mauser rifle cartridges 1 38 Pistol cartridges. Sd/- J.C.More Major, Political Agent, Kuwait / ✓ ' / M .A * S .Ui * 'r. No • 10 11 of 1920. - r , r British Agency &amp; Consulate^ Ay 6 /o Bandar Abhas, the 5th November 1920,.* ^ ^61 a s O v ^;* The Political Agent f Koweit. Memorandum . Reference your No.558 dated the 27th July 1920 to the address of the Deputy Political Resident, Bushire. I am making enquiries with regard to the particulars you require and on receipt of any information will communicate with you. \ 7 \1 &lt;• Ho. /O *1 7 of 1920. British Agency and Consulate, Bandar Abbas, the 18th November 1920, (io The Political Agent, Koweit. •il - TJHHrOHAITOTO . In continuation of ray memorandum No.1011 dated the 5th November 1920, I forward, herewith, for information and necessary action, a translation of a letter which I have received from the Deputy Governor, Minab. I.C.S*, Assistant Resident &amp; H.M*s Consul, tcJ. Bandar Abbas, O « ■Translation of the letter from the Deputy Governor, Minab to H.M’s Consul, Bandar Abbas. Received on 14th November 1920. After Compliments, I received your letter dated 9th November 1920 regarding the particulars about Sayed Yousif,! beg to say that Sayed Yousif is a well known person. In the year 1315 A.K. he occupied Lingah by force,but owing to the steps taken against him by the Government Authorities he was compelled to run away to the Arabian Coa^t. He now resides either at Dubai or Shargah. He communicates with the Axxi Arabs of Koweit,but I do not know them by their names. All I know is that they must not be well known persons^, as the reliable merchants never deal in such ill£gal and dangerous business, 3ayed Yousif had imported forty rifles and one thousand and eight hundred cartredges into Biyaban, which were presented to Mir Barakat on his behalf and, in exchange Barakat gave him three slaves ^two of them male and one female^ and also some money. A certain man named Sayed Yousif Tahirzai, who lives at Biyaban, is an agent of Sayed Yousif in question. He imports rifles an^cartredges in small lots into Biyaban, and sells them to the + Tahirzais. The good rifles and cartridges are always kept by Barakat for his own use and the rest sent to Bashkard and Roodbar for sale. There are i&amp;xxy a good many rifles and also a quantity of ammunition here similar to those of the Sarbazes.These are being used by the of Barakat whenever they come to Minab. Barakat had given 14 rifles and some ammunition of a similar kind to Abbas KhaiijWhich are now being used by his slaves. One Khaja Abdul Karim, Kalantar of Kahuristan(in Iks&amp;x the Lar districts) who has shops at Dubai and Shargah,had also imported 12 rifles and some ammunition into Biyaban, Barakat had given him a guide in order to enable him to go to Bashakard. Nephew of Barakat had purchased thirty rifles and some ammunition, from the Arabs,who have a part in Sayed Yousif*s business and has taken it to Biyaban, I was informed about the importation of the rifles after one month and immediately I reported the matter to the Consulate, 3 Cl Bandar Abbas, from where I received no reply in this connection, soso I did not effect further inquiries into the matter. According to the information# which I have received, they have brought another consignment into Biyahan. There are Coneul.ate representatives at Shargah and Dubaijwho can easily furnish particulars about Sayed lousif, moreover Hirza. Abbas, ilunshi of the Consulate, had been for a^long time in Ling ah and had many times visited both the places Shargah and Dubai, he must know him very well. I myself have never seen bayed Yousif personally.TRANSLATION. . politioal Agenoy, Kuwait. Lated the 30th^ November 1920. To . His Excellency Shaikh Sj.lim. Kuw ait A . 0 • , Reference your letter datea the 7$h Dil Q,a fi^-h 133d, re lative to one Saiyid Yusuf who according to information received from H.B.M’s Consul, Bander Aboas, was said to be clearly in arms in Kuwait. I asked the consul in question if he could obtain any far ther informat io-n regarding the man and he now sends me a copy o: a letter which he has received from the Deputy Government of MINAB of which I enclose a translation for your Excellency's information. prom this it appears that Saiyid Yusuf himseli has not been to Kuwait but it- is said to correspond with certain peoi le her here regarding this traffic. Sd/-. J.C. More., ■^ajor, Iolitical Agent, Kuwait.y Prom To Haidar Khan Hayat Daudi, c.I.E., Zabet of Hayat Daud t f c Kharg, Bandar Rig. Captain Shuldham, I.A., Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire. hated 8th Zi-hejjeh 1339 (=13th August 1921)Recd.14-8-21. A.C. I most humbly beg to state that a certain Haji Ebrahim bin Mazaf, a tawwash of Kuwait, who had gone from Kuwait to Jubail and those parts for buying pearls came to Kharg on his return so that he may buy pearls if he gets anything. The Customs Hudir of Kharg goes in4o his boat and takes 8 rifles which he has kept in his boat for protecting and guarding himself from the robbers of the sea and confiscate them. The tawwashes are those who proceed among the diving boats to the neighbourhood of Bahrain and other places for buying pearls and carry rifles to protect themselves from che robbers of the sea. Now Ha.ji Ebrahim the ” M tawwash M has pressed Karbelai Ahmad to recover his rifles from the Customs hudir as he wants to go to Kuwait and cannot wait. The Customs Mudir says he will inform the Director of Customs at Bushire and await instructions. The tawwash is pressing Karbelai Ahmad, Kadkhoda of Kharg, and the latter has reported the matter to me • I now bring the facts to your notice So that you may write me in any way you deem advisable. Since former times un to now I know and am aware that the boats of the 'tawwashes' who buy pearls take a few rifles in order to protect their lives and T)roT)erty. I do not know*whether this boat is guilty, that is, Ha.ji Ebrahim bin lia$af, tawwash of Kuwait, is guilty or not. The object of writing this letter is to inform you and also to get rid of the said Ha.ji Ebrahin tawwash.' m ) vo. of 19^1» British RasMency A Connulate-hrsreral, Bushire, r5th Aurust 1991. To Haidar Khan Ha$at Daudl, C.I.S., 7*bet of Hayat Dpud &lt;5: Kharp, Bandar A f' You had written to Captain Shuldham about Hali ^brahiir ben 'azaf tawwash of Kuwait. T have now returned to Bushire for a short tine as Secretary and the Resident has directed re to reply that Haji Rbrahiia should po to Kuwait and rake his complaint there to the Shaikh who if he thinks fit will represent it to the Resident through the Political A^ent. Ct£ Vajor f Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian ^-ulf*British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, 4th April 1922. To The Political Agent, KUWAIT. Memorandum . Please let me frnow when a reply may be expected to my endorsement No. 196 ; dated 3rd February 1922 / regarding the importation from Kuwait of ammunition by the people of Dilum• Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.No. 3/13/7. Political Agency, Kuwait Dated the 8th April 1922 To The Secretary to the Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U SHIRE. Menorandum Reference your znemorandun No. 546 dated the 4th April 1922. I replied to your endorsement No. 196, dated 3rd Pehruary 1922, in my confidential memorandum No.32-3 dated the 14th February 1922 to which reference was sub sequently made by the Under Secretary in his memorandum Mo. 167-8 dated the 25th February 1922. Maj or Political Agent, Kuwai 4. u •3h P.A. One Khamis ‘bin Sulainan, who nayb that he in a ' , ]^idawi' , of K.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, states that he xeke! received a letter from one Said bin Khalfan of Muscat, who is a confectioner here, informing him that his servant Ubaid bin Mabruk died last year and that he had left a box with him and asked him (i.e. Khamis bin Sulaiman) to come and take it over, Khamis bin Sulaiman states that he received the letter in the month of Shawwal, 1241 (June 1922) but that he arrived here to take over kixxxKrxxxtJ.xxkix the kit of the deceased Ubaid, about a month and 20 days ago. He has, how ever, no passport or any papers in his possesion to %how that he .has come from Muscat or that he is H.H. the Gultan of Muscat’s 'Fidawi'. On his arrival here he states he opened the box which he took over from* Said bin Khalfan and found that it contained four rifles and some, cartridges. As the deceased has his family at Mxxsxt el Hayal two days’ distance from ..Khabura, he wanted to take the box with its contents tc£: hand it over to them but that the Customs seized and conf is-*r all the cated XkExxxxkx^E things. He now requests that the things confiscated my be returned to him or that he may be given a letter to that effect. Submitted for orders please.Ill do tted the Oth Jan ua ry 1^23. To H.JI. Shaikh ahmfcci al“Jablr as-Subuh, C. I .ii., Ruler of Kuwait. A. C. a man named Khamis'Mm Sulaiman, who describee himself as a of H.H, the Sultan of Muscat has complained to me that in ,£hauw&amp;l last he received a letter from one Sa'ld bin Khalfan of Muscat, who is a confectioner here, saying that his servant 'Ubai bin Mabruk had died and left a box with him, and asking him. to come and take it over. He says that he arrived here about seven weeks ago and took over the box, which, on opening, he found contained four rifles and some cartridges — at least he says he only saw four rifles, but there may have been more as he did not unpack the box. As the deceased's family is at Hayil, near Khaburah, he wanted to take the box and its contents to hand it over to them, but that Y.K.'s Customs had seised it and confis cated it. He asked, me to request Y.E. to have them returned. He has no papers of any sort even to prove his identity, and when I asked him if he had asked i.E.'s permission to export the arms he said that he had not as he had not known that any permission was necessary. I told him that I could notaccept his statement or accede to his request, as I was not prepared to intercede for anyone who had contravened Y.K.’s orders prohibiting the export of arms. j. should be glad if X.E. could kindly let me know the true facts of the case, so that I can inform the P.A., Muscat.o. 24/13/7 IC2 Political Agency, Kuwait, Dated the, 11th January, The Political Agent 6c Il.B.h's Jonsul, l^useat. Smuggling of Arms fro ft Kuwait. jiljjS j^efnorri?.r:duR,. One Khania hin Sulaiinan, who deacrihes himnelf as a ’Pidawi* of Pits higiiiiess tne Sultan of Jus cat, hau coiaplained to Die that about seven iuontns &lt;xgo he recei-veii a le tfer froiii one Sa’id ‘bin Klralfan of j'ixariat who is a confectioner here saying that his servant 'tTbaicl tin Matruk had died r;nd left a box with hiD, and asking him to come and take it over. He accordingly oarce here about two months ago and took over the box, wnich on opening he four.d contained four rifles - at least he only saw four tut there may have teen more as he did not unpack tiie box - and , some ammunition. As the deceased’s family is at hail, near Khaturah, he wished to take the box and xi i^s contents to them, tut it was seized ty the local Customs and confiscated. Kg asked me to ^et it returned to him. The man had no papers of any sort to prove his identity and when asked if lie had applied for permission to export the arras he said that he had not and maintained that he did not know the export of arms was prohibited. I told Kim that I could not accept his statement and was not prepared to ask the hnai&gt; h to return the ra. I have subsequently asked the Khaikh about the matter and he telle me that when tne down mail came in one of his Customs Officials saw a porter carrying the box in question for embar kation and as be was suspicious of it, told him to put it down, the nan however again took it up ami tried to yen it on board so he took possession of it and on opening it it was found that it contained seven rifles.British Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat, the 7th February 1923* To The Political Agent, v Kuwait. Smugbling of Arms from Kuwait. *******************-** !v r FI. r QIuU.T-ULi- Your Memorandum 24/13/7 dated 11th January 1923* Nothing is known of Khamis bin Sulaiman here. The tern ■Fidav;i* is not used in Muscat. The word 'askar* is used to denote a soldier. MAJOR, Political Agent &amp; H. M*s Consul, j Muscat. A* J•deC• fDpX X Extract from Diarj of H.B.M’s Consulate, Knuzistan Ahv/az, for the month of August a93i. X XX XX X Sixty bags of sugar from Kuwait 'which were being smuggled by a Kuwaiti &amp;nd tY/o Persian merchants were caught and confiscated by the Customs at Hindijan* on inspection of the bags six rifles were xound. The three merchants have been arres ted and imprisoned pending trial. x X xc X X X No ^ 7 - S of j.931 Bxitish Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bus hire the ±5th September i93i T“ e foregoing extract is forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Please furnish for the information of the Hon'ble the Political Resident any further purr.lcu- l-ars ascertainable at Kuwait regardin- this attempt By Order, Secretary to the Political Resident. in the Persian Gulf.Letter prom - T.He politioal Agent, KUWAIT To H. E. Shaikh Sir Ahmad al-jabir as-Sabah, K.C.I.E.', C.S.I., Ruler of Kuwait, KUWAIT No Dated 13 th Ja aad Auwal 1350 . (26-9-31) 13 After compliments, I have the honour to enclose translation of an extract from Diary of H.M.S. Consul, Khuzistan, Ahwaz, for the month of August 1931, which has been forwarded to ob under the Secretary to the Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf’s No. 6 q 9 dated 15th September 1931, translation of which I also enclose. information that may be available regarding this matter for the information of the Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian G ulf, Bushire. Usual ending. I should be glad if Your Excellency could make full enquiries into the matter and let me have any further Lieub .-Col. politioal Agent, Kuwait.rrfcbnBl&amp;'tion or &amp; note dfekted 16td Jjatnad Aawekl 135^ i (29-9-31), Babaiitted to H. S. tde i^aler of Kaw&amp;it, by tde l&gt;irector of CaPtoaiB, Kuwait. Your Excellency, You dave orderd me to submit to Your BxcellQncy a state uent about the consignments of sugafc that have benn exported from Kuwait to Hindijan during the current ^ear. inforuation, that only one consignment was exported from Kuwait to Hindijan on the 28th Muharram 1350 (14-6-31) under i^nifest No.36. It was shipped on nakhuda Abdur Ridha bin Ghulums ship and belonged to him. I, therefore, beg to submit, for Your Excellency’s Usual ending.no* 7^6 Politloal Agency, Kuwait* Dated the 1st October 1931* To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Politloal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* ^morandum * Reference your memorandum No*609*3* dated 15th September and enclosure* 2* I am enclosing translation of a letter from His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait No*R/l08 dated the 16th Jamad Awal 1350 l29th September 1931) together with enclosed note from his Director of Customs in reply to a communication which I made to him on the subject* The Shaikh f s letter speaks for itself. 3* I have also had private enquiries made from Dhow owners etc* and can get no evidence to show that any sugar oon- signment ever left Kuwait. 4* Prom the Diary of His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz it is presumed that the merchants who were arrested were local Ittoi' shopkeepers doing business in the town of Hindijan, and^no particular Dhow was caught trying to dump a contraband cargo* 5* For your information dhows are not permitted to put to sea from Kuwait until after they have been searched for arms, and to insure a particular boat does not escape inspection the rudder is always kept unshipped on the land till permission is granted for it to put to sea* 6* It may also be of interest for the Hon’ble the Political Resident to know that any arms taken to sea in dhows for protection purposes are always registered in this Agency by the Captains under written authority from the Shaikh, and most strict orders in writing are given about showing all such arms to Customs authorities at ports of call* The certificate granted by this -tsl' Agency also issues strict*instructions about not allowing sailors to land with any lethal weapons in their possession. AT /) Lieut-Col*, Politic fxl emaatTranslation of a letter . 1^4 From His Exoeinenoy the R\xler of Kuwait* The Folitital Agent, Kuwait. To No.R/108 Dated the 16th Jamad Awal 1350 (29th September 1931). A fter compliments. the I have pleasure to acknowledge/receipt of your letter Ho.729 dated the 13th instant and to say that X have noted the translation of the extract from the Diary of His Majesty’s Consul, izistan, Ahwaz, forwarded to Your Excellency under the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Polities! Resident in the Persian Gulf f s letter No.609 regarding the 60 bags of sugar said to have bean seized by Customs at Hindi jan, who pretand that the goods originated from Kuwait and were the property of a certain Kuwaiti and two Persian merchants, also that on examination of the bags six rifles were found, and that the said merchants were thereupon arrested and imprisoned pending trial. enclose herewith a statement from our Custom Department showing all sugar shipped to Hindi jan during the current year. entirely prohibited, and a very thorough inspection is always made of every sailing ship which is leaving this port. It is therefore a matter of great surprise to us that they the Forsian Customs try and pretend that this sugar comes from Kuwait. as Kuwaiti subject must of course be entirely aware of the source of this sugar. Full enquiries have been made here as to the identi-t ty of this man but nobody has been able to throw any light on him at all. matter especially into the accusation about the firearms until we get to the bottom of the story. Should anything be discovered the darin ' smuggler will be put to severe punishment. Please be so good as to report same to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. A s reg rds the export of fire arms from Kuwait, this is Full enquiries have been made into the matter, and we The merchant whom they (the Persian Customs) describe In the meantime we will continue our enquiries into thisTransl tlon of a not© dated the 16th Jamad Awal I5d0 (29-9-31) submitted to His Exceltenoy the Ruler of Kuwait by the Director of Customs, Kuwait. Your Excellency, You have ordered me to submit to Your Excellency a statement about the consignments of sugar that have beon exporter from Kuwait to Hindi Jan during the current year* X, therefore, beg to submit for Your Excellency’s Information that only one consignment was exported from Kuwait to Hindi Jan on the 28th Muhar am 1350 (14-6-31) under Manifest No 36. It was shipped on Nakhuda Abdur Ridha bin Crhulum’s ship and belonged to him. Usual ending#</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003cb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/48</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003cb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/48</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 13/7 Illicit Trade of Arms and Ammunition'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1890/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-28T18:02:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (184 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 186; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-185; these numbers are also written in pencil, and are sometimes circled. Where previously circled this has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns incidents of arms and ammunition smuggling in Kuwait.The file contains general correspondence on arms smuggling; statements and memoranda; lists of arms and ammunition smuggled; lists of Persian firms exporting arms and ammunition; list of Persian merchants of importance in Kuwait.The principal correspondents are: the Rulers of Kuwait: Shaikh Jaber II Al-Mubarak Al-Sabah, Shaikh Salim bin Mubarak Al Sabah, and Ahmad Al-Jaber Al-Sabah; the Customs Department at Koweit [Kuwait]; the Director of Customs at Bushire; the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf; the Political Agency at Muscat and the Political Agent at Kuwait.The documents in the file date between 1916 and 1931; there is an earlier memorandum at the beginning of the file, dated 1890 but presenting results of guns examinations gathered in 1903 and 1904.There are numerous letters and statements in Arabic within the file, mostly correspondence with the Ruler of Kuwait, sometimes with English translation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs, Bushire</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Kuwait Sālim al-Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Kuwait Jābir II al-Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Smuggling</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003cb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>