<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000058_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T22:36:02.063Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Minute Paper. Letter from ? 0 . Under Secretary Secretary of £ptate Committee Under Secretary.. Secretary of State — iy a-^ A Secret Department. Dated ^ 19i/. Dec. SUBJECT. r? &lt; 4 / C'UAiA. ^TjCryunr * (*4&amp;uA,6ria4 . f hvy'a ^4, Copy to /Lit ^ /Ci ,, FOB INFOBMATION. Previous Papers :—— ' ' CONFIDENTIAL. * i5DECl9H d '%C7T Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received December 14, 1*50 p.m.) (No. 693.) R. US^ Tehrariy December 14, 1911, 1‘4 p.m. MY telegram No. 690 [ ]. Russian Minister made a communication yesterday to the Persian Government in the sense of the last two paragraphs of the Russian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs’ statement reported in Sir G. Buchanan’s telegram No. 332 [ ]. [973-986]( (No. 692.) Tehran, December 14, 1911, 2*30 p.m. MY telegram No. 686 [of 13th December]. I understand that the Cabinet, with a view to facilitating the acceptance of the Russian demands, are endeavouring to induce Moderate deputies to resign their seats. Resignation of some twenty of these, which I am told is assured, would leave the Medjliss without a quorum. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh and Government of India.):;x'j V CONFIDENTIAL 4 ?? (9 150EC1911 y/, WJ Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey. — (Received December 14.) (No. ^91.) Decode. Tehran, December 14, 1911. YOUR telegram No. 418 [of 5th December]. Stokes left this morning. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh and India.)a (ff/d CONFIDENTIAL. otlV£p&gt; 15 DEC1311 ] Sii* G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey. (Received December 14.) /N 338 ) &lt;Sfc. Petersburgh, December 14, 1911, 8'40 p.m. ^ ° I °SPOKE to Minister for Foreign Affairs this afternoon in sense of your telegram No. ^■ 8 g ^ xce ^ en i Q evidently much averse to M. Lecoffre remaining on for any time in Ministry of Finance, and all that I could induce him to concede was that he might do so for a fortnight or three weeks. He thought it ought not to be difficult to find him some post in our sphere.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Puchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 14, 8*30 p.m.) (No. 337.) Petersburgh, December 14, 1911, 7*30 p.m. IN a conversation which I have just had with the Minister for Foreign Affairs, I spoke of the serious preoccupation that the Persian question was causing you. His Excellency said that he hoped misapprehensions and suspicions entertained in some quarters in England as to Russia’s intentions had now been dissipated. We then discussed the three demands. As regards the first, Shusters dismissal must, his Excellency said, be an accomplished fact, and if he remained on for a little at Tehran it must be on the distinct understanding that he took no part either directly or indirectly in Government business. His Excellency next read me the text of the last formula proposed by the Persian Government respecting the engagement of foreign officials (see Sir G. Barclay s No. 686). His Excellency said he would accept it with substitution of words “ arrive at an understanding” for “enter on an exchange of views,” as the latter constituted no real engagement. After some discussion I suggested that text should run (R) “ to enter into an exchange of views for the purpose of arriving at an understanding with the two legations.” (End of R.) He finally said that some such words might do, but that before giving a definite answer he must submit them to the Emperor. As regards indemnity, he assured me that Russian Government would not be hard on Persia, and had no intention of extorting a large sum from her. I then asked whether he would not give the Persian Government a definite assurance that troops would be withdrawn when once three above demands were complied with. He replied that he would give us such an assurance, but that he would not give Persians any more assurances whatever, as they did not deserve them, and he would prefer that you should not do so either. I then told him of the aide-memoire given me by Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, adding that you would probably have communicated to Parliament to-day the assurance which it contained on this subject. His Excellency answered that he had no objection to your doing so, but that, of course, this assurance only applied to withdrawal of troops from Kazvin to some other point like Resht, and not to their definite recall ^ from Persian territory. I said that it was quite impossible to restrict this assurance in the sense which he had suggested. He then sent for Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, who at once confirmed my contention that it meant complete withdrawal of the expeditionary force from Persia. His Excellency said he was very glad to hear it, as now we seemed nearly in sight of a settlement. He added that I might assure you that he had not the least wish to occupy Tehran, and that he trusted that all necessity for such a step would be removed by speedy compliance of the Persian Government with the three demands.CONFIDENTIAL. S t r G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received December 4, 2T5 p.m.) (No. 649.) R. Tehran, December 4, 1911, 2 20 p.m. MY telegram No. 620 [ ]• In a private letter to me Stokes absolutely denies he has taken part at any meeting. COPY TO INDIA 8 DEC 1911 SECRETARY’S N2 49I CONFIDENTIAL. /f } 3 1 ) .o'.') Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). « (No. 411.) R. i J Foreign Office, December 4, 1911. YOUR telegram No. 638 [of 3rd December]. Journey expenses of Stokes will be paid as requested. I am in communication with India Office as to earlier date of leaving.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] [Bj PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [46091] [November 20.] Section 11 . Sir G. Bay'day to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 20.) (No. 204.) Tehran, October 27, 1911. WITH reference to my despatch No. 180 of the 1st instant, I have the honour to report that on receipt of your telegram No. 284 in which you asked for my view on the suggestion of the Russian Government that Major Stokes might be employed to organise a gendarmerie at or near Ispahan, I enquired of Mr. Shuster as to what he thought of the idea. I enclose a copy of his reply the substance of which I reported in my telegram No. 467. I acquainted my Russian colleague with Mr. Shuster’s answer, and on the 15th instant he informed Mr. Shuster, under instructions from his Government, that as it was unfortunately found impossible to restrict Major Stokes’s services to the south, the Russian Government must adhere to their protest against his engagement to organise a Treasury gendarmerie. As reported in my despatch No. 162 of the 4th September, Mr. Shuster had threatened to publish a statement of his case against the two Governments in the event of his being prevented from securing Major Stokes’s services, and on receipt of M. Poklewski’s communication of the 15th instant, he lost no time in communicating to Reuter’s correspondent a brief statement, which I understand duly appeared in the London press. He has since, I am told, posted a more detailed indictment, which will presumably appear in the London press in a few days, meanwhile Major Stokes stays on in Tehran, though I have urged him in a friendly manner to leave. He has been granted leave by the Government of India, pending a decision on the question of his resignation from the army which he had tendered on the 30th July. This grant of leave was conveyed to him by me on the 9th instant, and I have since been requested by the Government of India to inform him that he has been granted leave for twelve months. This message however, I have not yet conveyed to him, as I thought that when once he had been formally granted leave for a definite period, it would be more difficult to recall him to his regimental duties, which as far as I can see would be the most likely way of inducing him to leave Tehran. His continued presence here may prove very inconvenient as he is staying with Mr. Shuster, and it can hardly be doubted that he is assisting him in the organisation of the Treasury gendarmerie. As I have already reported I should not be surprised if at any moment you were approached by the Russian Government with the request that he may be recalled. I must confess to feeling some anxiety as to how, if this request is complied with, he will respond to his orders of recall. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Shuster to Sir G. Barclay. Dear Sir George, Tehran, October 5, 1911. REGARDING your note of the 3rd, to wdiich I was about to reply, let me say that the suggestion as to localising Stokes at Ispahan, is, of course, out of the question, both on principle and as a matter of practicability. I hope some day the British and Russian Foreign Offices will come to believe that when I said I wanted Stokes here in Tehran to assist me by his advice and peculiar knowledge in the formation of a Treasury gendarmerie, I meant just that and nothing more ; no arriere-pensee, no military expeditions, no intrigues, nothing but what I said. It seems impossible at times for one to gain any credence for a frank open [2253 w—11]statement of facts or intentions, but it is equally true that it was neither within the letter nor the spirit of my statement to go through the truly absurd performance of marooning him at Ispahan or anywhere else in order that he might advise and assist me here. Is it not about time, dear Sir George, that two big Governments stop playing a^. this matter, and state plainly whether they intend to continue to oppose the employment of Stokes along the lines which I have mentioned, or not ? With, &amp;c. W. MORGAN SHUSTER, Treasurer ■‘General of Persia.sia. [44100] No - '■ Question asked in ihe House of Commons, November 2 , 1011 . Mr. Dillon—To ask the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on what grounds the British Government supported the Russian Government in resisting the appoint- ! ment of Major Stokes by the Persian Government, and whether he can now lay upon the table all the correspondence which passed between the British and the Russian Governments and the British and the Persian Governments in reference to this proposed appointment. Answer. What we have done is to refuse to facilitate the appointment of Major Stokes by accepting his resignation. The ground for doing so is that it is not consistent with the spint of the Anglo-Russian agreement that we should directly or indirectly promote the employment of a British officer to control gendarmerie in the north of Persia. We might ourselves have taken objection if the Russian Government had promoted the employment of a Russian officer to control gendarmerie in the part of Persia next to the Indian frontier, and we are bound to act reciprocally. It is not proposed to lay separate papers on this point, but I will see if they can be included in the next Persian Blue Book. [2253 5 — 2 ]?&lt;rr9 11199 . 1 . 1352 . 10 , 000 .- 7 / 1911 . Departments are requested, if they suspect that there is any mistake in this telegram, to communicate immediately with the Private Secretary to the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State. COPY OF TELEGRAM. TaX A From Dated Received at London Office 9 \3 Sfy, lt 7 u tCONFIDENTIAL Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 418.) R. Foreign Office, December 5, 1911. YOUR telegram No. 637 [of 3rd December]. Following sent to India :— “ (Private.) “ My private telegram of 1st December : Stokes. “Sir E. Grey wishes him instructed, in reply to Barclay’s No. 638 [of 3rd December], to leave Tehran within a week at the latest. He should travel via Caucasus and London, and Foreign Office will pay his expenses from Tehran to London. He can get advance from Barclay, subject to adjustment. Instructions should be sent to him with least possible delay.” (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 771.) [973-820]47*j @ CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 3, 3 p.m.) (No. 638.) R. YOUR telegram No. 16 S.C. [ Tehran, December 3, 1911, 1 i’.M. ]• Following is message from Stokes :— “ I propose starting for India, in accordance with orders of commander*in-chief, as soon as my private affairs here are settled. I request instructions as to route I am to travel by, and the authority from whom I am to draw money for travelling expenses. With regard to route, via London would be quicker than Suez Canal and Bushire. If ordered to travel via London, wull Foreign Office pay for my journey to London as it would have done had I left Tehran at termination of my appointment as military- attache ?” (Addressed to India, No. 638.) [972—655]CONFIDENTIAL. 4 ^ &lt;-o4^-OaN V ' *\ 4 DEC191Vd \ r V - * O ’ ^%rrD^ Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received December 3, 3 p.m.) (No. 637.) Tehran, December 3, 1911, 1*45 p.m. MY telegram No. 635 [ ]. Major Stokes replies that he has communicated decision of His Majesty’s Govern ment, refusing his resignation, to Shuster, who, while deeply regretting the revocation by His Majesty’s Government of the permission previously granted to Stokes to accept his offer, has informed Stokes that he now feels compelled to release him from promise which he had made as the result of that permission. Stokes proposes to start for India at the “ earliest possible date consistent with the termination of purely personal affairs.” Notwithstanding this, I trust that peremptory order may be sent to him to leave at once. Reply to a message which I am sending to Government of India from Stokes might take this form. He told me on the 20th ultimo that in any case, for purely personal reasons and private business, he could not “ leave Tehran for a month at least.” In the present situation he should, I think, be made to leave at once. I believe that his private business consists chiefly in the disposal of furniture of Dr. Lindley, which he ought to be able to depute to others. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh.) COPY -MA 8 DEC 1911 SECRET AmY’S N2 49CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.-(Received December 3, 1L30 a.m.) (\o 635 ) R Tehran, December 3, 1911, 12'30 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 403 [ ]• I received telegram in the sense indicated from Government of India yesterday, and communicated it to Stokes. I fear, however, that he will need something more peremptory.CONFIDENTIAL. (No. 403.) Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). Foreign Office, December 2, 1911, 3‘30 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 591 of 21st November. Following telegram sent to Government of India, 22nd November :— “ Stokes having appealed for reconsideration of the decision of His Majesty’s Government, they will be glad if you will cause him to be informed as follows :— “ ‘ Reasons for which it was decided that his resignation cannot be accepted have been fully explained to him. As he is an officer in His Majesty’s service, it is clearly his first 'duty to obey the orders of His Majesty’s Government, which involve with drawal of his acceptance of appointment under Persian Government. This withdrawal is, in the view of His Majesty’s Government, necessary, and they take full responsibility for it.’ ” (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 754.)CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey .—(Received December 2, 1215 p.m.) (No. 625.) Tehran, December 2, 1911, 12 noon. YOUR telegram No. 401 [of 1st December], last sentence. My official letter conveying message to Stokes has elicited a mere acknowledgment,CONFIDENTIAL. y z .. c »'* 2DECl911j-' Sir Edward Grey to Sir (No. 401.) Foreign Office, December 1, 1911, 7 p.m. . YOUR telegram No. 620 [ j. I am asking Government of India to repeat order to Stokes to return to India. Meanwhile you should warn him that, being a British officer, he must take no part in complications that have now arisen. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, 752.) t*: A*’ COPY TO INDIA 8 DEC 1911 SECIIETAHY’S N2 49very of tl that the A troo of g situ with that dese 'Y a *A±d 6. 20 P.M. .A -Barclay ^ ; ^ Deer 1 .-trP.-RTr' 0 I Uilnk, in view of excitement in the town, it is very desirable to getjrtoke^s soon as possible . 1 cannot say positively that he has done anything to provoke breach of the peace, but Russian f.iinister *»*« on reliable authority that he is taking part in meetings at Shuster's house,where the situation and the possibility of resistance to Russian troops are discussed, Russian Minister asks mewhethwr there is no way of getting rid of him and thus relieving a fe very delicate i situation, where a British officer appears to be mixed up with the enemies of Russia. Cannot a telegram toe sent to him to tell him that unless he leaves forthwith he will toe considered a deserter,and could I,if he still stays on, deport him? (X 1 M r&gt;) A 8 DEC 19 11 SEUuc l N2 49In any further communication on this subject, please quote N . 0 . 46551/11. Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. November 22, 1911 immediate. Sir With reference to previous correspondence, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. drey to transmit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, the accompanying copy of a telegram, T o. 591, dated November 21, from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran respecting the departure of ^ajor Stokes. I am to suggest that, subject to the approval of the Marquis of Crewe, the telegram of which a draft is enclosed should be sent in reply, and I am to enquire whether, in His Lordship's opinion, the telegram had better be sent from the Viceroy or from this Department. The Under Secretary of State India Office.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 21, 3*5 p.m.) (No. 591.) * Tehran, November 21, 1911, 1‘30 p.m. 'YOUR telegrams Nos. 353 [of IGtli November] and 356 [of 18th November]. I delivered your message to Stokes, but I cannot induce him to make up his mind to leave. He says that when we informed Shuster that he must resign his commission before taking up the appointment he pledged himself to Shuster to accept the appointment. He therefore requests direct answer to the “question” addressed by him to the Secretary of State for India in my telegram No. 558 [of 12th November], such as would show*at least that if he broke his pledge he did so through force majeure.Draft telegram to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). Your telepram No. 591. Reasons for which it was decided that Major Stokes' resig nation cannot be accepted have been fully explained to him As he is an officer in H.M. service it is clearly his first duty to obey the orders of H.M.Gr. which involve withdrawal of his acceptance of appointment under Persian Government. This withdrawal is, in the view of H. T '.G., necessary and they take full responsibility for itCONFIDENTIAL. lAj£ V O^ Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 12, 7*30 p.m.) (No. 558.) Tehran, November 12, 1911, 8 p.m. FOLLOWING is a telegram which Stokes begs may be forwarded to Secretary of State for India :— (R.) “ Refusal of my resignation by Government of India has been communicated to me. It places me in a position of having to choose between disregarding orders of His Majesty’s Government and breaking my faith, pledged on conditions officially formulated by His Majesty’s Government themselves (see Foreign Office telegram .No. 213 of 21st July). I most respectfully and most earnestly request His Majesty’s Government to reconsider their decision and to permit me to resign. 1 have through out acted in entire good faith, and the difficulty of my position is not in any sense of my own making.” (End of R.) I informed Stokes officially on 5th November, at the request of the Government of India, that his resignation could not be accepted, as His Majesty’s Government were unable to advise the King to accept resignation of an officer who tendered it solely for the purpose of taking service under a foreign Power in circumstances which made his action in their judgment detrimental to British interests. I added that he was to join general staff branch at Simla as soon as possible. Since then I have not ceased to urge him to leave, but I doubt whether I have made any impression. Matter may prove very serious in view of St. Petersburgh telegram No. 271 [ ], which shows that, if Persian Government do not yield to Russian demands, Shuster’s gendarmes will be removed by force. An actual conflict between Russian Cossacks and Treasury gendarmes is therefore quite possible, and in this conflict Stokes, if he persists in his hesitation to obey our orders, would probably become involved. (Private.) At the same time I fear that peremptory order to join his new post at once would precipitate his signing his contract with Shuster.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 356.) v Foreign Office, November 18, 1911. YOUR telegram No. 579 [of 17th November]. I concur in your proposed modifications in communication to Major Stokes. 21H0V1911 COfV TO 'U t SEOHE '' ARY F l+ 7 ■yVT-D ^!\C- ' r^ v .v' Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 17, 1'30 p.m.) (No 579.) ^ (wUv Tehran, November 17, 1911, 1'30 p.m. G(?oJ YOUR telegram No. 353 [of 16th November] and my telegram No. 558 [of 12th November]. Before addressing Stokes as instructed, I venture to submit-that, as it contains no repetition of order to join his post at Simla, Stokes may interpret message as in nature of an encouragement to linger here. Moreover, the word “ now ” is somewhat ambiguous. It is true that it is doubtful whether order would be obeyed, but it would at least be more consistent with the attitude we have observed vis-a-vis to Russia than the message as it now stands. May I omit the word “now” and add words “he had therefore better comply with orders of Government of India without delay ” ? COPY TO IND’-'v | f SECRE TARY'S N° ../ ¥ ~;Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 353.) R. Foreign Office, November 16, 1911. YOlTR telegram No. 558 [of 13tli November]. You should tell Stokes that, as his appointment will clearly precipitate a conflict between Russia and Persia, and as we cannot consistently with the spirit of the Anglo- Russian Convention promote the employment of British subjects in the north of Persia, we cannot facilitate his appointment by accepting his resignation now./V/ V In any further conmmnication on this subject, please quote No. 44775/11. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Immediate. {. Foreign Office November I if 1911. Sir:- 14 NOV 1911) I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, copy of a telegram from Sir G. Barclay respecting the resignation of Major Stokes. Sir E. Grey would propose, if the Marquess of Crewe concurs, to reply to Sir G. Barclay in the terms of the telegram the draft of which is also herewith transmitted. I am. VJD T ’ V n Sir, Your most obedient. humble Servant, Under Secretary of State, India Office.r Telegram to Sir G. Barclay, dated Your telegram No.558 (of November 15th). You should tell Stokes that as his appointment will clearly precipitate a conflict between Fuesia and Persia, and as it is the essential part of a good under standing between Great Britain and Pussia that we should not promote the employment of British subjects in the North of Persia, we cannot facilitate his appointment by accepting his resignation now.CONICONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received November 12, 7*30 p.m.) (No. 558.) Tehran, November 12, 1911, 8 p.m. FOLLOWING is a telegram which Stokes begs may be forwarded to Secretary of State for India :— (R.) “ Refusal of my resignation by Government of India has been communicated to me. It places me in a position of having to choose between disregarding orders of His Majesty’s Government and breaking my faith, pledged on conditions officially formulated by His Majesty’s Government themselves (see Foreign Office telegram No. 213 of 21st July). I most respectfully and most earnestly request His Majesty’s Government to reconsider their decision and to permit me to resign. J have through out acted in entire good faith, and the difficulty of my position is not in any sense of my own making.” (End of R.) I informed Stokes officially on 5th November, at the request of the Government of India, that his resignation could not be accepted, as His Majesty’s Government were unable to advise the King to accept resignation of an officer w T ho tendered it solely for the purpose of taking service under a foreign Power in circumstances which made his action in their judgment detrimental to British interests. I added that he was to join general staff branch at Simla as soon as possible. Since then I have not ceased to urge him to leave, but I doubt whether I have made any impression. Matter may prove very serious in view of St. Petersburgh telegram No. 271 [ ], which shows that, if Persian Government do not yield to Russian demands, Shuster’s gendarmes will be removed by force. An actual conflict between Russian Cossacks and Treasury gendarmes is therefore quite possible, and in this conflict Stokes, if he persists in his hesitation to obey our orders, would probably become involved. (Private.) At the same time I fear that peremptory order to join his new post at once would precipitate his signing his contract with Shuster. 1972 —1(&gt;() -SSSH. 1. 1400. IUCKA—Ofiyiu.FOREIGN OFFICE October 23, 1911. immediate r Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. drey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of October 14th. respecting the resignation of Major Stokes, and to inform you, in reply, that he approves of the terms of the draft telegram to the Viceroy which was therewith transmitted. I am further to call your attention to paragraph 2 of Sir Gr. Barclay's telegram No. 505, copy of which is annexed for convenience of reference, and to suggest that, in these circumstances, it might be advisable, if the Secretary of State for India concurs, to offer Major Stakes some post in India or request him to rejoin his regiment, with a view to finding him employment out of Persia I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant tinder Secretary of State, India Office[ ,p' J Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—-(Received October 19, 9-30 a.m.) (N°. 505.) p Tehran, October 19, 1911, 10-45 a.m. llilL Government of India have granted Stokes leave pending decision of his application to resign. I have urged him privately to leave Tehran and take his leave in England, but he awaits answer to his application to resign, and to demand the reasons, if resignation is icfused, before deciding upon further action, which conceivably may be defiant. Meanwhile, he is living with Shuster, and is doubtless helping him with the gendarmerie. It is not impossible, therefore, that the Russian Government may approach you with a view to his recall to his regiment.(39056/11) The Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and is directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit herewith an amended letter respecting the position of Major Stokes, which he hegs may he substituted for the former Foreign Office letter of the same date. Foreign Office, October 18th, 1911. * a m. 19 OCT !9tJIn any further communication on this subject, please quote n„. 39056/11. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office October 11th, 1911 Led i ate. &lt;4 \ Sir ^:i9CCT1911 With reference to your letter P.4308 of October 2nd. transmitting copy of major Stokes' telegram of September 27th, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state, for the Information of the Secretary of State for India that he is of opinion that that officer's resignation of his commission in the Indian Army should not be accepted. Sir E. Grey, in his telegram No. 242 of August 18th instructed Sir G. Barclay to inform the Persian Government that Major Stokes' resignation could not be accepted, in view of the well-founded objections of the Russian Government to his appointment, and the Russian Government have expressed their thanks for this decision. His Majesty's Government are therefore committed to the refusal of Major Stokes' resignation. I am to transmit to you a copy of a telegram from Sir G. Barclay and of the reply which has been returned to him 16 Under Secretary of State, India Office.(59056/11) him on this subject. Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn on what grounds, in the opinion of the Larquess of Crewe, the refusal to accept the resignation of an officer in the Indian Army should be based in these circumstances. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edicard Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). (No. 242.) Foreign Office, August 18, 1911, 5*15 p.m. PROPOSAL of Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs is unacceptable to Russian Government. Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs should renew his protest to Persian Government. You will then repeat warning given to Persian Government by you already and urge appointment of some neutral, and say that we cannot accept Stokes’s resignation in view of well-founded Russian objections to his appointment. Stokes clearly cannot take up appointment till his resignation has been accepted, but to recall him summarily after he has offered resignation is a harsh step to take, and I am reluctant to ask Government of India to take it. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 450.)In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 39056/11. and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Office, London. [innediate Sir:- Foreign Office . c .. October 11th, 1911. With reference to your letter P.4308 of October 2nd tiansniitting copy of iiiojor Stokes' telegram of September 27th, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state, the information of the Secretary of State for India that he is of opinion that that officer's resignation f/ W of his commission in the Indian Army should not be accepted. Sir E. Grey, in his telegram No. 242 of /F f instructed Sir G. Barclay to inform the Persian Government that Major Stokes' resignation could not oe accepted, in view of the well-founded objections of the Russian Govermnent to his appointment, and the Russian Government have expressed their thanks for this decision. His majesty's Government are therefore committed to the refusal of kajor Stokes' resignation. - I am to transmit to you a copy of a telegram from Sir G. Barclay and of the reply which has been returned to him 5 Under Secretary of State, India Office. iif(39056/11). him on this subject. Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn on what grounds, in the opinion of the i.iarquess of Crewe, this refusal should be based. I arn, * ^ J \ Sir, Your moist obedient. hijimble Servant,LM)5 CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey- —(Deceived October 9, 6'58 a.m.) (No. 478.) Decode. ^ | I YOUR telegram No. 283 [ Tehran, October 9, 1911, 10 a.m. ]• In anticipation of your sanction I have allowed Stokes take two months’ leave from 12th August on termination of appointment as military attache.Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 5, 3 p.m.) (No. 467.) R. Tehran, October 5, 1911, 3 P.M. MR. O’BEIRNE’S telegram No. 228 [of 26th September]. What Shuster needs is advice and assistance of Stokes in capital, and he most emphatically rejects the idea of localising him at Ispahan as “ out of the question, of course, both on principle and as matter of practicability.” Shuster is most anxious for reply “ stating plainly whether two Governments intend to continue opposing appointment of Stokes on lines which he has mentioned or not.” (Repeated to St. Petersburgh.)U-32L. CONFIDENTIAL n G a nrTiQii Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 5.) Tehran, October 5, 1911. I AM not sure that we clearly understand your telegram No. 283 [ ], but I infer from it that Stokes may count upon two months’ leave as military attache from 24th July, when his appointment terminated, and that for leave subsequent to 24th September he must apply to India. [973—44] ii !CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received October 5, 3 i\m.) (Xo. 467.) R. Tehran, October 5, 1011, 3 p.m. MR. O’BEIRNE’S telegram No. 228 [of 26th September]. What Shuster needs is advice and assistance of Stokes in capital, and he most emphatically rejects the idea of localising him at Ispahan as “ out of the question, of course, both on principle and as matter of practicability.” Shuster is most anxious for reply “stating plainly whether two Governments intend to continue opposing appointment of Stokes on lines which he has mentioned or not.” (Repeated to St. Petersburgh.)CONFIDENTIAL. y Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 283.) Code. ^ Foreign Office, October 2, 1911. YOUR telegram No. 446 [of 28th September]. Stokes is entitled to two months’ leave annually, and had that period of leave in 1910. He has no claim to additional leave on the termination of appointment. Under agreement of 1903 with Indian Government Stokes must report himself in India at the expiration of leave. Date of grant of leave should be fixed accordingly.C &gt;N I'l DKNTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received September 29.) (No. 446.) Decode. Tehran, September 28, 1911. I BELIEVE that Stokes is, on termination of appointment, entitled to three months’ leave full pay as military attache. In order to send in his life certificate in this sense, he now applies lor three months’ leave from the 24th ’July. [731—699]CONi'lDENTIAL. Sir G. Buchanan lo Sir Edward Grey. — (Received September 26, 10*15 p.m.) (No. 228.) St. Petersburgh, September 26, 1911, 9*45 p.m. DURING conversation with Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs to-day he referred to Stokes question. Russian Government have insurmountable objections to Stokes organising any gendarmerie force whatever in Tehran, even if his appointment is limited to a short period, for they consider that he would then necessarily have a con siderable force temporarily under his command in Tehran itself. I gathered that if the scheme for the organisation of gendarmerie by Swedish officers falls through Russian Government might not object to Stokes organising a force at or near Ispahan, provided, of course, that any portion of it employed in Northern Persia would'be commanded by Persians or by officers of a neutral Power. I do not know how far this idea is practicable. (Sent to Tehran.)(psui. The INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH Go. (Limited). ^ Registered Offices :— 18 , Old Broad Street, London, E.C. enquiries respecting: this telegram must be accompanied by this Copy. eceived in London on the Telegrams may be handed in at the Company's Stations. . (18, Old Broad St., E.C. (Head Office: Always open). LONDON: 6 &amp; 8, Lime Street Square, E.C. | 10 &amp; 11, Mincing Lane, E.C. LIVERPOOL:—African House, 6, Water Street. \ MANCHESTER:—Duchy Chambers, corner of Clarence St. and Tib Lane, or at ANY POSTAL TELEGRAPH STATION in the United Kingdom. REPETITIONS should be obtained OFFICIALLY through the Office of Receipt. &lt;7 ivf/ at TELEGRAM from so. of y 7/ Q a/ No. of | legrarfT j J ft W ords j Date and Time handed j in at original Station 1 ortest and most Idirect route for Telegrams for p-TL (t * &amp; r Ce V f &amp;/&gt; T*\. UTH RUSSIA, TURKEY n Europe and Asia), irsia, Baluchistan, INDIA, urmah, Ceylon, nang, Singapore, JAVA, orneo, Sumatra, CHINA, Siam, Annam, Cochin-China, JAPAN, ormosa, Corea, i'ippine Islands, USTRALIA, Zealand, and East generally. T 'iff Books , y’ffij*, ,oms ' dc -' Post free 0n spoliation, / r&gt; TUr - r £ -me*? / V ( f 3^^ fT * rr s/ / t r \ CC '' Tff ^ Tjt (t OAO £-e P 'h\ 77\cr&lt; ^ irZMinute Paper. Register No. Uxb Secret Department. ^ Letter from dP- Date. Initials. Under Secretary Secretary of State IP Vm- Committee ../ Under Secretary Secretary of/State I\ujp C / 7 , IS I IS 191/ flee. \ &amp; SUBJECT. % CrsrcK Co Py to BiYhck Xp . t^K FOR INFORMATION.C0NKIDENT1AI 15SEP1911 Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey —(Received September 13, 11 p.m.) (No 206.) St. Petersburgh, September 13, 1911, 8*56 p.m ’ SIR* G. BARCLAY’S telegram No. 380 [ ] and your telegram No. 256 [ ] to him. I referred in the course of conversation with Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs this afternoon to the negotiations which had been proceeding between Shuster and the Russian Minister respecting the organisation of gendarmerie force, and asked what he thought of them. . . His Excellency replied that the question was a very difficult one, and that he was o-iving it his serious attention. He was most anxious to find a solution that would gi^c satisfaction to Shuster and which would at the same time be acceptable heie. feared that engagement of Major Stokes, even for a few months, would make a very bad impression here, as the gendarmerie to be organised was not to be used solely for fiscal purposes, but was to be an armed force for the maintenance of order throughout the country. , „ . , j j I observed that the organisation of such a force seemed to be urgently needed, but that His Majesty’s Government were taking no part in the negotiations as they would not support an arrangement to which Russia might take exception. Shuster, added, seemed still to believe that Major Stokes was the only man capable of doing the organising work. . ^ , i t ^ ^ His Excellency said he did not share this view, and that he thought that someone else might be found at Tehran; amongst others he mentioned an Austrian. I asked whether he would like to see command of such a force given to an Austrian, lie replied that Austrian in question was already in the Persian service. I fear that, even if Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs were to consent to the temporary employment of Major Stokes, we should again be exposed to attacks m the Russian press. The “ Novoe Vremya” quite recently publishefl a telegram from Tehran denouncing the idea of Major Stokes’s engagement, and emphasising Ins anti-Russian sentiments. (Sent to Tehran.)CONFIDENTIAL. L+Voh' Y Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward (Grey.—(Received September 10, 4T5 p.m.) (No. .180.) R. u Tehran, September 10, 1911, 2*35 p.m MY telegram No. 371 [ ]. following is substance of Shuster’s reply to Russian Government: — Purpose of Treasury gendarmerie is to collect taxes and to produce a feeling of public security and order without which in Persia collection of taxes becomes impossible. Eventually force will be Persian except for a few European or American superior officers. Force will eventually be from 12,000 to 15,000 strong, but will not reach that strength for eighteen months. Shuster states his view strongly that two gendarmerie forces will be unnecessary and uneconomical. He thinks “mere presence in most instances of a well-organised and disciplined force will be sufficient to main tain order, and such attempts at local disturbances as might arise from time to time could^ well be repressed by a force having general police powers, unless, indeed, disorders became serious enough to demand attention of a regular army.” COPY TO INDIA iai SECRETAHY’S N° A?-CONFIDENTIAL (No. 256.) Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). Foreign Office, September 8, 1911, 3'15 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 380 of 7th September [Major Stokes]. E have no doubt seconding of Stokes will be arranged if Russians agree to proposed \ arrangement. I desire to facilitate in interest of Shuster’s work whatever the Russians will agree to, but if I urge proposal at St. Petersburgh it may appear as if we had some reason of our own for getting Stokes appointed. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 502.)[This Document is the Property oi His Britannic Majesty's Government ] PERSIA [August 28.J CONFIDENTIAL. Section 14. v [33757] No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 28.) (No. 149. Confidential.) ^ r ’ T , Gulahek, August 9, 1911. 1 have the honour to transmit herein copy of a letter from Mr. Shuster, the substance of which I had the honour to communicate to you in my telegram No. 322 of this evening, lespecting his desire to appoint Major Stokes to organise the Treasury gendarmerie. I have. &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Shuster to Sir G. Barclay. (Purely Personal.) Dear Sir George, Tehran, August 8 , 1911. I BEG leave to address you, unofficially, on a subject of great importance to my work here. I have been intensely surprised to learn this evening that your Government has conveyed to the Persian Foreign Minister a note of warning or protest against my pioposed employment of Major Stokes in the Treasury gendarmerie. You are doubtless aware of the course of this matter up to the present. Need I say that, in view of the tone of the communication which your Government authorised you to address to me on the 22nd July last, in effect that Major Stokes could accept the position upon resigning from the Indian army, the apparent volte-face indicated by their note of to-day is [ almost incomprehensible. I recognise that I would have no right to say such things to you in an official communication, and nothing is further from my thoughts than to give offence to anyone, but does your Government quite realise the position in which it is placing me before the Persian people, and their Government is now suddenly joining with another Power to prevent the exercise of the most elemental act of sovereignty by this country whose independence and integrity both of those foreign Powers have solemnly pledged themselves jointly and severally to respect ? My personal feelings are of no importance, but the success or failure of my mission here is of moment both to Persia, which entrusted her financial affairs to my care, and to my countrymen, who are not unnaturally interested in the creditable accomplishment of my task. Before accepting this work I was given clearly to understand that neither of the two principal Powers having interests here offered any objection to my undertaking it, and surely such a statement was something more than an empty pledge. No one, 1 am assured, knows better than yourself that the choice of Major Stokes was actuated by no political motive in the faintest degree, and no thinking person could suspect me of any intention to engage in political jobbery here—a thing which would only make me ridiculous and spell absolute ruin for my work. What, then, am I to think when 1 see the first vital step which I undertake in the task of bringing order out of chaos here obstructed and relentlessly opposed by the very two nations who have time and again professed their sincere desire to see the progress and prosperity of the stricken country which I am seeking to serve ? Does your Foreign Office fully realise that in adopting its most recent attitude in this affair it is inevitably producing the impression on the Persian people that it is in reality opposed to the successful accomplishment of my work, in addition to forcing ine to assume that I can count on no friendly moral assistance from your Government in a vital matter of this kind ? If this were a normal place where well-trained, capable, and experienced men could be had in comparative abundance, the result (though not the principle of your Dovernment's objection) might not be so bad ; but here, where, as you know, good men [2141 ee —14]are extremely scarce, the attitude adopted amounts to a virtual veto of my efforts and a ''’^fwand^rarifsre'manner your Government may be brought to see the j^LrlS intemauKrtle 0 feancial'oJgankation O WhiC k I rsOTX d t ferso S stronglyon P the subject that I am forced to contemplate the of allm^experiei^s^n^his cmmecti^since^rrivtag^n Tehran ° r Needless to say, such ^antpearthte^ur pSIr dlcSslulhis 0 stCnge land, and the Stokes case happens, likewise, to be one of mine. ^ ’ W. MORGAN SHUSTER, Treasurer-General of Persia.Cf 1^0 ^ - Lf- [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [33764] a5v V/x,. SEP1911 i No. 1. [August 28.] Section 13. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey .—(Received August 28.) (No. 236.) Sir, St. Petersburgh, August 22, 1911. IN continuation of my despatch No. 228 of the 9th of this month, I have the honour to report that in a conversation which I had with the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs on the 10th instant, I informed his Excellency of the statement which you had made in the House of Commons two days previously, and explained that, pending the reply of the Persian Government to Sir George Barclay’s last communica tion, the question of Major Stokes’s appointment would remain in abeyance. I added that should the Persian Government, contrary to your expectation, decline to give way, His Majesty’s Government would support Russia were she to demand that the gendarmerie force in North Persia should be placed under the command of a Russian officer or of a subject of a minor Power, whom Russia might designate. As M. Neratof observed that I had omitted to say what His Majesty’s Government would do should Major Stokes’s appointment not be confined to the south, I pointed out that, if Russia obtained the control of the northern gendarmerie, it naturally followed that Major Stokes would be precluded from trespassing in the Russian zone. On my calling on M. Neratof two days later to communicate the reply which had just been received from the Persian Government, I found his Excellency in an unusually perturbed state of mind. He had already received a report on the subject from M. Poklewski, so that he had had time to reflect on the situation, while, as he had hut just returned from an audience with the Emperor at Peterhof, he was, it is to be presumed, fully acquainted with His Majesty’s personal views. After emphasising the serious character of the incident which had so unfortunately arisen, his Excellency ] proceeded to dwell on the prejudicial manner in which Major Stokes’s appointment would react on the effective working of the Anglo-Russian understanding. It would, he said, inevitably create the impression that, as that understanding had failed to stand the test in the present instance, its stability could not be depended on, and that it would fail to answer the calls that might be made on it in the future. What, he asked, would have been said in England had our respective positions been reversed and had it been a Russian officer who had accepted a post in the Persian Government which conferred on him the right to organise and control a gendarmerie force in South Persia ? I replied that his Excellency seemed to have forgotten the various statements which you had made in Parliament, in one of which you had touched on this veiy point as well as the promise which you had given to support Russia in the matter of the northern gendarmerie and the serious warningwhich you had addressed to the Persian Government. Major Stokes’s resignation, moreover, had not yet been accepted nor would it be accepted pending further developments. I did not therefore see what more you could do, nor did I believe that, after all that you had said and done, the Anglo- Russian understanding could in any way be impaired. M. Neratof, however, adhered to his views which he had already expressed, and said that Russia could do nothing to obtain satisfaction. She might, it was true, intervene by force, but to do so would be to create an entirely new situation, or she might present a demand for an appointment of an analogous nature to that of Major Stokes—such as chief of the staff—but he did not know whether His Majesty’s Govern ment would support such a demand. If, however, as was by no means impossible, the ex-Shah remounted the throne, public opinion would, after Major Stokes’s appointment, insist on the Russian Government presenting it. I pointed out that, were Mohammad Ali once more installed at Tehran, both Mr. Shuster and Major Stokes would in all probability disappear from the scene, and ns in that case the latter would not command the gendarmerie, Russia would have no reason to ask for a counterbalancing appointment. M. Neratof, however, declared that this would make no difference. It would be maintained, he contended, here that Major Stokes had obtained his appointment owing to the fact that, when an Anglophil Government was in power at Tehran, England seized the occasion to push her interests, [2141 es—13]2 and that Russia must likewise profit by the return of a Sovereign who was well disposed towards her to get a Russian officer appointed chief of the stalt. His Excellency concluded by saying that the question raised by Major btokes s appointment was such a serious one that he could not assume the responsibility o dealing with it by himself, and that he would have to submit it to the Council oi Hs Ministers. Before doing so, however, he would make a final appeal to you as, now that I had told| him that Major Stokes’s resignation had not yet been accepted he thought that it must be possible for His Majesty’s Government either to recall him temporarily to London or to give him some appointment m India. e earncs \ hoped that you would consider this, as it would be deplorable were the Anglo- Russian understanding to be impaired for the sake of gratifying the amour-propre As M. Neratof was too busy to receive me when I asked for an interview aftei the receipt of your telegram No. 441 of the 10th instant, I embodied the mam points oi that telegram in a private letter, of which I have the honour to enclose a copy. In a conversation which I had with him two days later I supplemented what 1 had said in it by once more impressing on him the fact that His Majesty s Government had had nothing whatever to do with Major Stokes’s appointment, and by lemmding kimoi the attitude which you had consistently adopted when unfavourable comments had been made in Parliament respecting the proceedings of Colonel Liakhon and the retention of the Russian garrison in Persia. I trusted, I said, that his Excellency would on his part exercise the same moderating influence on Russian public opinion whenevei, a* had recently been the case, the conduct of His Majesty s Government was suajectec to unreasonable criticisms. . His Excellency replied that we might count upon his doing so, as there was nothing that he desired more than that the two Governments should always work together, more especially at a moment like the present when affairs in leisia veie m such a critical state. He had already instructed M. Poklewski to addiess a communica tion to the Persian Government in the terms of the note which had been submitted to you by Count Benckendorff, and to associate himself with Sir George Barclay in urging that Government to entrust the organisation of the revenue gendarmerie to one of the Swedish officers. He would only ask me to convey to you his warmest thanks foi having instructed Sir George Barclay to state that His Majesty s Government cannot accept Major Stokes’s resignation. I nnvp /VP ’GEORGE W. BUCHANAN. Enclosure in No. 1. Sir G. Buchanan to M. Neratof. Mon cher M. Neratof, Saint-Petersbourg, le 4 (17) aout, 1911. JE viens de recevoir un long telegramme du Foreign Office, dont je vous donnerai lecture samedi. Mais, en attendant, je tiens a vous faire savoir que Sir Edward Grey trouve que le Gouvernement Imperial, ainsi que I’opinion publique en Russie, exagere un pen la portee de 1’incident Stokes et parait regarder la nomination de cet officier comme un fait accompli. Qa n’est pas du tout le cas ; et, en outre, le Gouvernement de Sa Majeste n’a rien fait pour justifier I’impression qu’il a voulu assurer la nomination du Major Stokes au poste de chef de la gendarmerie fiscale on qu il a consenti a cette nomination. Tout au contraire, le Ministre de Sa Majeste a Teheran a ete charge, a plusieurs reprises, de faire des representations au Gouvernement persan a ce sujet et de 1’avertir que, si ce dernier persistait a confier a Stokes la tache d’organiser une gendarmerie nationale pour toute la Perse, le Gouvernement de Sa Majeste reconnaitrait le droit de la Russie de pourvoir aux mesures qu’elle jugera necessaires pour sauvegarder ses interets. Sir Edward estime que la Russie ne doive plus tarder a adresser au Gouvernement persan une communication, congue dans le sens de la note dont le Comte Benckendorfr lui a tout recemment soumis le texte, car, a defaut d’une telle protestation de la paR de la Russie, le Gouvernement persan sera porte a croire que le Gouvernement de Sa Majeste soit plus royaliste que le Roi en ce qui concerne la defense des interets russes en Perse. Pour le cas ou le Gouvernement Imperial se decide a faire une telle demarche, Sir Edward Grey sera dispose a renouveler Tavertissement, qu’il a dejaT iih B Document is the Property ol His Britannic Majesty s Govermneiit.] [B] PERSIA. /*■&gt; CONFIDENTIAL. [33747] No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir BJdward Grey.—(Received Auqust 28.) (No. 139.) ^ r ’ r , Gulahek, August 5, 1911. \\ 11H reference to my despatch No. 122 A of the 15th ultimo, I have the honour to report that on receipt of your telegram No. 213 of the 21st ultimo I informed the Ireasurer-General that Major Stokes would have to resign his commission in the Indian army befoie accepting the appointment as commander of the Treasury gendarmerie. When informing Major Stokes in the same sense I strongly deprecated his resigning his commission, pointing out to him that his appointment to the post which had been offered to him, the duties of which were not confined to the south of Persia, would be sure to provoke the objections of Russia, and that these objections, which we might not be able to oppose, might lead to the cancelling of his contract, in which case he would he in a most unfortunate position. I found him, however, firmly resolved to resign, provided that satisfactory provision were made as regards a pension on the expiry or the cancelling of his engagement. No provision for a pension had been made by the Medjliss at the time that the Treasurer-General had been empowered by that body to engage Major Stokes, and further reference to the Medjliss was therefore necessary. There was some hesitation on the part of the Cabinet in taking this step. The Russian Minister had intimated to the Minister for Foreign Affairs that the proposed appointment of Major Stokes would be most unwelcome to Russia, a fact of which his Excellency must have been already aware, and his Excellency had felt it necessary to disclaim any responsibility for the appointment, which, he declared, had been proposed without the knowledge of the Cabinet. Mr. Shuster pressed the Cabinet to pass the pension arrangements through the Medjliss, but his insistance was of no avail until the advent to power of the new Democrat Cabinet. That Cabinet took office on the 25th ultimo, and provision for^ Major Stokes’s pension was voted on the 29th ultimo. As reported in my telegram No. 300, Major Stokes tendered his resignation from the Indian army on the following day. In obedience to your instructions I told the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the 29th ultimo that I had heard that if Major Stokes accepted the post which had been offered to him he might be employed in a military capacity against the ex-Shah, and I pointed out to his Excellency that if he were so employed it might afford an excuse for Russian officers to take an active part on the other side. On the 2nd instant, on receipt of your telegram No. 221, I delivered a more formal warning. I informed the Minister for Foreign Affairs—leaving an aide-memoire with his Excellency—that Major Stokes had been required to resign his commission before taking up his appointment under the Persian Government. I reminded his Excellency that the appointment had been made irrespective of His Majesty’s Government, who would have preferred to have been first consulted in the matter, and I warned his Excellency that the employment of Major Stokes in milita^ service in any active operations in the north of Persia might involve political considerations, and that His Majesty’s Government could not oppose any objections which might be taken to it. W hen I first informed my Russian colleague, on the 7th ultimo, of the offer which had been made to Major Stokes he took it with comparative complacency. Indeed, he gave me at the time the impression that he saw in the appointment a welcome opportunity for securing compensating appointments for Russian officers. However, a day or two later he told me that he had telegraphed to his Government and to Count Benckendorff urging the objections to the appointment, and that he had told the Persian Government that he would recommend his Government to demand some equivalent. This warning, while it sufficed, as reported above, to give pause to Sipahdar’s Cabinet, had no effect on the ultra-nationalists who succeeded it, anti by the bine M. Poklewski was authorised to say something definite from his Government the Medjliss had already voted the pension arrangements for Major Stokes. The vote [2141 ee—S] r ;FP1Q!1 \J L~1 • v/ » I [August 28.] Section 8.2 was passed on the morning of the 29th ultimo, and it was only that afternoon that M Poklewski told the Minister for Foreign Affairs that his Government would ask for compensation if Major Stokes were appointed. Judging from Major Stokes s demeanour when I saw him last this warning does not seem to have had much effect, for he seemed quite confident that his contract would be signed as soon as his resignation from the Indian army had been accepted. have &amp;c g! BARCLAY.Q, 'Vt) 3 ^ This Document is the Property of Hig Britannic Majesty’s Govegament.] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. y\\d » ‘ [33735] No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received August 28.) (No. 122 a.) SR, ^ Gulahek, July 15, 1911. I HAVE the honour to acknowledge receipt of your telegram No. 199 of the 13th instant. The proposal of the Russian Government that the command of the Treasury gendarmerie, which the Treasurer-General desires that Major Stokes should organise, should he split up so as to secure a Russian as well as a British officer, would not, I feel sure, he accepted by the Persian Governmeut except under compulsion, and if we insisted upon it, I have little doubt that the Treasurer-General would resign. As regards the alternative proposal that the command of the Treasury gendarmerie should be entrusted to a Swedish officer or to a subject of some other minor Power, I thought it well to consult Mr. Shuster, and I have now the honour to transmit a copy of his reply. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Shuster to Sir O. Barclay. Y* L Dear Sir George, Tehran, July 14, 1911. I AM in receipt of your note of to-day’s date in which you state that your Govern ment evidently think that the appointment of Major Stokes to organise the Treasury gendarmerie might cause some international jealousy. You ask me whether the appointment of a Swedish officer or of a subject of some other minor Power might not be a way out of the difficulty. In reply, I beg to state that the Medjliss having recently authorised me to appoint a suitable person to organise, under my direct supervision and control, a force of Treasury gendarmerie, I tendered the position to Major Stokes for the sole reason that I consider him to be the best fitted man for the work whom I could possibly obtain. I am personally aware of Major Stokes’s peculiar qualifications for this task, such as his military training, his four years’ sojourn in Persia, his knowledge of the country, of the Persian language and of French (which is widely spoken here), and, in general, of the high esteem in which he is held in this community as an officer and a man. I have no hesitancy in assuring you that in seeking the most efficient financial aide whom I could find for this particular branch of my work, the question of nationality played no part whatever in making up my opinion. Had this been o, it is but natural to presume, that the matter being left entirely to my discretion, I would have sought such an assistant from my own country. I may take this occasion to repeat that the work of financial reform here, which I have undertaken in the midst of many grave difficulties, and on which I have in a manner risked my professional reputation, is in no sense political in its character. No act of mine has been guided by political considerations, either local or international, and I naturally feel that I could not in any manner accept any suggestion which would cast upon my perfectly frank and disinterested tender of a post to Major Stokes the light of political bias. With all due respect to the subjects of minor Powers, and without any disrespect to several of my own countrymen whom 1 have appointed to serve with Major Stokes in the Treasury gendarmerie, I believe that Major Stokes is the best qualified to give efficient service to this country in connection with my own financial mission, and I would be unwilling, under any circumstances, to appoint anyone, from any Power whatsoever, for this or any other branch of my work unless I, personally, was aware of and satisfied with the appointee’s special qualifications. We know, of course, that one of the greatest handicaps from which any foreigner suffers here is, as in my own case, a lack of knowledge of the language, habits, ami [2141 ee—7] J2 J r , 1 1 . r Pprcjinn -npoDle This defect becomes even more serious in the “° S of 0 ^ at ?p n\rTe7dSy with a large number of such men as would go to make up an armed force. A Swedish officer, be he ever so competent, would have n ^end at least a year or more here before he could possibly be of any real assistance in this line of work, whereas the necessity of getting my gendarmerie force oigamsec In ^nclusffin, permit me to say that, as the fact of my tender of Ins post to Maior Stokes is now generally known here, any withdrawal of that offer by me could not fail to be interpreted as being dictated by purely political considerations, which I C0Ul( Trusting 1 that this statement will enable you to reassure your Government upon this subject, and that I may receive an early and favourable consideration bv &gt;o Government of Mr. Stokes s acceptance. 1 am, &amp;c. W. MORGAN SHUSTER.TroS CONFIDENTIAL. h ^ 8 SEP1911 Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 7, L45 p.m.) (No. 380.) R. ^ Tehran, September 7, 1911, 12*5 p.m. MY telegram No. 348 [of 21st August: Major Stokes]. Shuster finds it impossible to give an express undertaking in the sense of his proposals, as it would be regarded by Nationalists as a recognition of the spheres of interest. At a meeting yesterday at Russian Legation he proposed that a new contract should be prepared engaging Major Stokes for nine months, or, if that is impossible, for six months, to assist Treasurer-General in Tehran in organisation of Treasury gendarmerie. Question of any further employment of Major Stokes after expiration of this contract being left for subsequent consideration ; he might either rejoin Indian, army, or a new contract might be concluded in accordance with wishes of two Governments. Shuster begs Russian Government as a favour to consent to this arrangement, and he hopes that His Majesty’s Government will consent to second Major Stokes for period named. I ventured to tell Shuster that I thought that, if Russia consented to proposed arrangement, there would be no difficulty in seconding Major Stokes. Both Russian Minister and I agree that, if Major Stokes is to get this appointment, it would be better that he should retain his position in Indian army.LfllO CONFIDENTIAL. 5 5EP1S11 ^£aT d£?j£ © Sir g. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received September 2, 8 p.m.) (N °' MY telegram No. 3«[ j. ^ 2 - 1911 &gt; 8 ' 50 P - M - In reply to his telegram reporting Shuster’s proposals, Russian Government have numbera^ndduties! ^ ° btam ^ particuIars as to Treasury gendarmerie, its These instructions, although dated 23rd August, only reached Russian Minister yesterday, telegraph, having been cut by ex-Shah’s forces. I ill m m [730—369]4-'7 0 Document is the Piroperty of His Britannic Majesty's Government. ; [B] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [August II.] Section 3. [32105] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay. Foreign Office, August 11, 191] (No. 101.) Sir, ^ THE Persian Minister came to see me to-day. He made a series of complaints about the action of the Russian Government, including then objection to Major Stokes s appointment; and he stated that six Russian naval officers had accompanied the ex-Shah from Baku to Persian territory T asked him whence this latter statement came. He said that his Government heard it from their consuls and vice-consuls in Russian territory, of whom they had several. i Die Minister complained that all these actions were not in accord with neutrality between the Persian Government and the ex-Shah or with the Anglo-Russian agree ment, the principle of which was the independence of Persia. I explained to him our action in connection with Major Stokes in the same wav as 1 had already explained it in reply to questions in Parliament. I said that we desired to maintain the Anglo-Russian agreement, but any questions which arose with Russia in regal d to it must be discussed between Russia and ourselves: they could not be discussed with anyone else. The Persian Government should, therefore bring their complaints directly to the notice of the Russian Government or of ’the Russian Minister m lehran. The Minister said that this had already been done ; but it had no effect, I observed that, according to my information, there had been in the last few days more friendly conversations between M. Poklewski and the Persian Government in lehran. The Minister, who had a sheaf of documents, from which he read portions to me asked whether I would like to have the facts in writing. I said that he might send them to me in the form of a memorandum of this conversation. I am, &lt;&amp;c. E. GREY. [2141 1—3]m CONFIDENTIAL. ' /-■ - J G1911 Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received August 21, 4*55 p.m.) (No * 1 1 I • • Tehran, August 21, 1911, 4 p.m. i t • ^ as j 1 ?® whether, in view of my communication to Persian Government, 0 j ^ in i° rilie d him, he is to understand that his resignation is definitively refused and if so on what grounds? He points out that it is now three weeks since he tendered his resignation, and that he is still without a reply. Meanwhile he says that Shuster is most anxious for him to begin work.PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL [31858] No. 1. ™ oon x ^ Buckanan t0 Sir Edward G^y.-(Received August 14 .) (No. 230.) ' ' Sir ’ I HAVE the honour to report that the “ NovS'V^myS^oXf ^ pV' burgh newspapers continue to discuss with considerable warmth St ' Pete, .' s ' (ml in th, ,h, k of account contrary to its own expressed wish, of what value is the am'eement'of 190?“ If it be true, moreover, that Great Britain has expressed her i;f 100£ , , ' * V 0 ?' Russian protest at Tehran, what becomes of British prestiev ? I ‘it n t ' s,I PP ort ‘j 16 the Government of the British Empire in its st^X wdh i *v ' e “y for call in the help of the rulers of a small and impotent Asiatic'power/'V thV bt’so’ then m future when signing any agreement with England, we must make a mental’ reservation as to the consent of various Mulks, Dowlehs and Sultanehs Un the 8th August the same paper compares the powerlessness of the British Government to control one of its own subjects with the influence exercised bv the commander of the German cruiser at Agadir, who recently offered two British subjects Ins protection in a manner which showed that lie had power to prevent or nWthi agilemen te ^ wi th^Grea t ° f is ’ Paper continual, ta British subject m ° f 6 Vahd ’ m ’’ St be 00 “ cl ^ed with each In its issue of the 9th August the “ Novoe Vremya” bitterly criticises a Reuter Te l' a '\ ) lr ' Whl ° h ,t . ls P 011lted ou t. while there are Russian, German and Itahan officers in the Persian service, there is not one British officer, and inferring’that frl bt ?v S f a PP° lntmen t.merely restores the balance in favour of England It descnbes this telegram as an insult to Sir Arthur Nicolson, who, in Aucmst 1907 siened matir,-r iai i', agi ir men v b) , T ieh j of wliici ‘ ai1 cSic^mJ’rt; mam in force, while Russia binds herself not to interfere in the English sphere of influence, and England gives a similar bond with regard to the Russian sphere. beside :L artlCl, ;. COnCk l e8 : “ R eferellce to Russian, German, and Italian officers is stil ee -I 168 ® ? fficerS , 0CCU P! ed thelr P osts Previous to the agreement, and - &gt;■ th T. m vu ' ]‘ e 0 “ d 7V n defianCe 0f il ' Ma j° r Stokes has accepted is appointment to a political post m defiance of the direct and indisputable conditions l! “rl a . rtlc,e 3 . ° . the agreement. It seems to us that Sir Arthur Nicolson would artdl 1 c.r remmdm g B 't&gt;fh diplomatic circles in Tehran of the substance of ivith M [lolsky 8 ’' 66 ” 1611 *’ Wh ‘ ch he ’ 88 Britisl ‘ -Ambassador at St. Petersburgh, signed I have, &amp;c. GEORGE W. BUCHANAN. [2141 o—2] 1 rn[Tbis_I)ocament is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Govei~ t ] [BJ ^COxNPIDENTIAL. Section 1. [31856] No. ]. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received Auqust 14 ) (No. 228.) ' ' ,i X) • x .i i - 1 , —^ un buc neiu uy the iiussian press on the subject of the appointment of Major Stokes to command the gendarmerie which the Persian Government propose to organise for Treasury purposes. Even such an Anglophil journal as the u Novoe Vremya” has taken His Majesty’s Government severely to task for allowing a former military attache to resign his commission in order to assume the command of a force whose operations will extend over the northern zone, especially placed under Russian influence by the 1907 agreement or to take an active nart in an in+pmal +r,of ir, — ....— G . i atoresaid agreement, would, the “Novoe Yremya ” apprehends, seriously prejudice the harmonious working of the Anglo-Russian understanding. Other papers, representing ^ Z, ie ^ s reactionary and Germanophil circles, have openly declared that now that England has shown her cards Russia has acquired a free hand, and is at liberty to intervene by force m Northern Persia for the protection of her interests. In official circles the appointment has been no less strongly condemned on its merits, though it is perfectly understood that His Majesty’s Government are innocent of the Machiavellian designs imputed to them in other quarters of stealing a march on the Russian Government and gaining a foothold in the Russian sphere in Northern Persia. When Mr. Shuster early in July decided to entrust to Major Stokes the task of organising a treasury gendarmerie, whose operations would embrace the whole of Persia, I explained to M. Neratof the great benefits likely to be derived from the creation of such a force, as well as the special qualifications possessed by Major Stokes for organising and commanding it. M. Neratqf, in reply, expressed himself favourable to the idea of a gendarmerie of this description, but took exception to its being placed under the command of a British officer. He suggested that the command should either be split up and shared by a British and a Russian officer or that it should be entrusted to a subject of one of the minor Powers, such as Sweden. The fact, moreover, that the appointment was being offered to Major Stokes by Mr. Shuster, who had already incurred his serious displeasure by the attitude which he had taken up towards the customs administrator without previous consultation with the Russian and British Governments, did not predispose his Excellency in its favour. The unexpected turn which Persian affairs took in consequence of Mohammad Ali’s sudden return distracted M. Neratof’s attention for a time to other matters, and his Excellency was at first under the impression that the grave internal crisis with which the Persian Government was confronted would cause the two questions of the Mornard-Shuster dispute respecting the customs administration and of the projected Treasury gendarmerie to fall temporarily into abeyance. When, however, it became evident from the decision taken by the Medjliss respecting the salary to be allotted to Major Stokes on his appointment that the Persian Government were determined to avail themselves of his services in some orm or another, and that they would in all probability employ him to direct the military operations about to be taken against the ex-Shah in Northern Persia, his Excellency caused representations to be made on the subject to His Majesty’s Government through the Russian Ambassador in London. It was not, however, till the 2nd of this month that M. Neratof again referred to the matter in conversation with me. After enquiring if I could tell him how the question stood at that moment, his Excellency told me that the Russian Minister at lehran had already informed the Persian Government that, in the event of Major Stokes being entrusted with the organisation of the projected gendarmerie, Russia 'would demand something of an analogous nature for herself. Having received that [2141 o-l]2 morning your telegram No. 221 of the 1st instant to Sir George Barclay, I explained to M. N^ratof that Major Stokes’s appointment had been made irrespective of His Majesty’s Government, and that they would have preferred that the Persian Govern ment should have first consulted them in the matter. Sir George Barclay, I said, had now been instructed to inform the Persian Government that Major Stokes had been required to resign his commission before taking up his appointment, and to point out to ^ them that, as his employment in any active operations in Northern Persia might involve political considerations, His Majesty’s Government could not deprecate the objections that might be taken to it. I added that, when once Major Stokes had resigned his commission, His Majesty’s Government could exercise no control over his action. These explanations by no means satisfied M. N^ratof, who expressed himself in a manner which showed that he regarded Major Stokes’s appointment as most inopportune at the present moment. Referring to the possibility of that officer being employed in active operations against the ex-Shah, his Excellency drew my attention to the action taken by Russia last year in the case of the Persian prince, Darab Mirza, who was then serving in the Russian army, and commanding a sotnia of Cossacks at Kazvin. Having expressed a desire to resign his commission, and having subsequently attempted to raise a revolt against the present Government, Darab Mirza had been placed under arrest and sent to Russia; and his Excellency evidently wished to convey to me that the proper course for His Majesty’s Government to pursue in Major Stokes’s case was to refuse to accept his resignation and to recall him to England. After the publication of the article in the “ Novoe Vremya,” of which I had the honour to forward a translation in my despatch No. 225 of the 3rd instant, I again called on M. Neratof, and, in accordance with the instructions conveyed to me in your telegram No. 411 of the 3rd instant, explained that it was very difficult, if not impossible, for His Majesty’s Government to prevent Major Stokes taking service under the Persian Government if once he resigned his commission. You considered, however, that the Russian Government were entitled to object to his being employed in North Persia, and that, should they wish you to do so, you would instruct Sir George Barclay to inform the Persian Government that His Majesty’s Government could not take exception to such an objection, and that the Persian Government would do well to take it into account. While expressing his thanks for this communication, M. Neratof said that he feared that a protest of this kind on the part of the Russian Government would expose them to the retort that the Persian Government were in no way concerned with the 1 Anglo-Russian agreement, under which Persia had been divided into a British and a Russian sphere of influence. He would, however, think over the matter, and see whether it was possible to find a formula which would get over this difficulty and which would at the same time command the support of His Majesty’s Government. M. Neratof sent for me on the following day, and again spoke of the grave anxiety which this incident was causing him. He regretted it more especially because it would show to the world that a serious disagreement had arisen between the two Governments and because Russian public opinion would believe that His Majesty’s Government were supporting Major Stokes’s appointment out of interested motives. Such an appointment was, moreover, a contravention of the principle on which the two Governments had hitherto acted, namely, that no subject of a European Great Power should be allowed to occupy any important post in the Persian service. He pointed out that at a moment when the Persian Government were engaged in a struggle for their very existence they would not give a thought to the projected Treasury gendarmerie, and would employ Stokes and any other forces that he might organise to fight the ex-Shah in Northern Persia. This, he thought, ought to be prevented at all costs, and he repeated the suggestion which he had made to me on the previous day, that His Majesty’s Govern ment should recall Major Stokes temporarily to London. There must, he imagined, be some formalities to be gone through before Major Stokes could leave the army that would serve as a pretext for such a step. If, however, His Majesty’s Government were unable to act on this suggestion, it would be absolutely necessary that the two Governments should take some step that, while giving satisfaction to public opinion in this country, would demonstrate the solidarity of their interests in Persia. His Excellency then read to me the draft of the two accompanying notes, which he suggested that the British and Russian Ministers at Tehran should respectively address to the Persian Government. The Russian note would enter a protest against Major Stokes’s appointment and would state that Russia would regard it as an unfriendly act and would reserve to herself the right of taking such measures as she might deemnecessary to safeguard her interests in Persia. The British note would express entire concurrence in the terms of the Russian note and would recognise Russia’s rifrht to take the necessary steps to protect her interests. ^ ^ t to I pointed out that it might he difficult for His Majesty’s Government to express ^entire concurrence in a note which virtually threatened armed intervention P a nd uggested that the Russian Government might protest against the employment of Major Stokes in Northern Persia, and at the same time express their 'readiness to place at the disposal of the Persian Government the services of a Russian officer to organise a gendarmerie for the maintenance of order in those provinces. M Neratof however, adhered to the general tenor of his draft note, remarking that if Russian interests were threatened the Imperial Government would be obliged to intervene On the receipt of your telegram No. 419 of the 7th instant 1 informed M. Neratof that Sir George Barclay had been instructed to warn the Persian Government that they ought not to persist in engaging Major Stokes, except on the understanding that he was not to be employed in Northern Persia, and that, if they did so persist, His Majesty’s Government would recognise the right of Russia to take what steps she thinks necessary to safeguaid her interests. I added that, in view of the pressure which we had brought to bear on the Persian Government last year to organise a force under British officers for the purpose of protecting the southern trade routes, we could not deprecate the employment of Major Stokes in those provinces, but that you recognised that it would he contrary to the spirit of the Anglo-Russian Convention for His Majesty’s Government to support that officer’s employment in Northern Persia or to deprecate any obiections which Russia might take to it. In the course of the conversation which ensued, M. Neratof said that he feared that the Persian Government would insist on adhering to the terms of the original contract which they had made with Major Stokes. What, however, he was most anxious to obtain from His Majesty’s Government at the present moment was some statement that would give a moral satisfaction to Russian public opinion and that would counteract the very unfavourable impression which this incident had created. Supposing that the Persian Government did agree not to avail themselves of Major Stokes’s services outside the southern provinces, there was no guarantee that the gendarmerie which he was going to organise in those provinces might not eventually be dispatched on service to the north. Would His Majesty’s Government, he asked, make a state ment to the effect that this would not be allowed ? I said that they might possibly give an assurance that Major Stokes would not be employed in the north, but that they could not take any engagement as regarded the gendarmerie force which be might have organised. M. Neratof replied that this would not be sufficient, and that what he wanted was an assurance that the gendarmerie, which was a purely local force, should not be moved from the south to the north. I pointed out that it would be impossible for you to defend in Parliament an assurance that the Persian Government would not be allowed to dispose of the forces, of which it might dispose in the south, for service in the north, should the situation require it. His Excellency admitted that this would no doubt be difficult, and then suggested that, in the event of the command of the southern gendarmerie being entrusted to Major Stokes, you should declare your readiness to support Russia, should she eventually demand that the organisation of a northern gendarmerie should be given either to a Russian officer or to the subject of some minor Power, whom the Russian Government might put forward as a candidate. I said that I personally much preferred this suggestion to the one which his Excellency had previously made, but that 1 could not answer for His Majesty’s Government. M. Neratof then proceeded to say, cfchat should, as he expected, the Persian Government persist in placing Major Stokes in command of a national gendarmerie for the whole of Persia, he hoped that you would promise to support any eventual demand which Russia might put forward for some appointment of an analogous character being given to a Russian officer. I asked whether he had any particular appointment in his mind’s eye. His Excellency replied that the appointment of a Russian officer as chief of the staff might perhaps answer the purpose. I observed that I thought that there was but very little likelihood of the Persian Government complying with such a demand under the present circumstances. M. Neratof, therefore, explained that the Bussian Government had no intention of putting forward any such request at this moment. He was not just now thinking so much of the Persian Government as of His Majesty’s Government. What he desired was that you should, either by a statement in Parliament or by a communique in the press, make a declaration of the readiness of His Majesty’s Government to support any demand for compensation that the Russian Govern- /CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 21, 7 p.m.) (No. 348.) _ Tehran, August 21, 1911, 9 p.m. SCHUSTER visited the Russian Minister yesterday and again pressed him hard regarding appointment of Stokes. He said he was willing to undertake that Stokes should not be employed in the north except for organisation work in Tehran, that he should remain in the capital for only six months, and should be then sent to Shiraz. He held out hopes of arranging for a counterbalancing appointment of a Russian officer in the north. He promised, moreover, to exclude from certain negotiations for a loan which he had opened with Colonel Beddoes the conversion of Russian Bank’s loan, and to negotiate this conversion with the Russian Government. _ Russian Minister, while holding out no hope that his Government would change their attitude, promised to submit to them these proposals, and he has since told me that he is reporting by no means unsympathetically. After his conversation with Russian Minister Schuster induced “ Times ” correspondent to refrain from sending a report of an interview which he had given him which would have embittered matters. He also told Russian Minister and me that he would for the present withhold public statement which he was preparing. I gather this statement would be on the lines indicated in my telegram No. 322 [ ], penultimate paragraph.CONFIDENTIAL. r I &lt;- UG19U .■c^n y Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Greij.—(Received August 19, 9T5 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, August 19, 1911, 8’2 p.m. (No. 185.) d 51 MY telegram No. 182 [ ]. Acting Minister foi Foreign Affairs, whom I saw this afternoon, desired me to convey to you his warmest thanks for the instructions sent to Sir G. Barclay in your /telegram No. 242 [ ], more especially for your declaration that “His Majesty s Government cannot accept Stokes’s resignation. I reminded him of the attitude which you had always adopted in Parliament when Russian action in Persia had been unfavourably commented on in the past, and ex pressed hope that his Excellency would also use his influence to tranquillise Russian public opinion when our policy was subjected to unreasonable criticisms. His Excellency replied that we might count on his doing so, as he attached greatest im portance to the closest co-operation between the two. Governments, particularly at the present moment, when affairs in Persia were in such a critical state. Russian Minister at Tehran has been instructed to make a communication as you suggested. (Sent to Tehran.) [730—294]1+^4 CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G, Barclay (Tehran). (No. 240.) R. Foreign Office, August 18, 1911, 3*10 p.m. MY telegram No. 441 [of 16th August: Major Stokes] to Sir G. Buchanan. You should act accordingly as soon as your Russian colleague receives his instructions. (Repeated to St. Petershurgh, No. 448.)mmmmamm ('ONFIDENTIAL Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). (No. 242.) Foreign Office, August 18, 1911, 5*15 p.m. PROPOSAL of Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs is unacceptable to Russian Government. Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs should renew his protest to Persian Government. You will then repeat warning given to Persian Government by you already and urge appointment of some neutral, and say that we cannot accept Stokes’s resignation in view of well-founded Russian objections to his appointment. Stokes clearly cannot take up appointment till his resignation has been accepted, but to recall him summarily after he has offered resignation is a harsh step to take, and I am reluctant to ask Government of India to take it. (Repeated to St. Petersburgh, No. 450.)[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.! oi me minister oi innance s proposal to engage three more foreigners to work under the American treasurer-general. The first of these new men to be charged with the formation of a force of gendarmerie for the Treasury Department. The salary of this post is fixed at 5,000 dollars a-year, and the post has, as reported in my telegram No 234 boon offered by Mr. Shuster to Major Stokes. ’ ’ The precise functions of the other two posts are not stated. The salaries attached to them are respectively 3,000 dollars and 1,500 dollars. [July 31.] CONFIDENTIAL. Skction 15. [29944] No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey—(Received July 31 ) (No. 119.) - J J 1 IV Po 1 have. &amp;c. G. BARCLAY.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] r PERSIA. if CONFIDENTIAL. fLUy 31.] Section 1. [29933] No. 1. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 31.) (No. 107.) gi r&gt; Gulahek, June 28, 1911. I HAVE the honour to report that at the sitting of the Medjliss on the 24th instant the Minister of Finance proposed that four more Americans should be engaged to work under Mr. Morgan Shuster in the Financial Department on a three years’ contract as in the case of those already engaged. The Medjliss agreed to the proposal without debate, and practically unanimously. The salaries of the four new men are to be as follows:— An auditor to replace Mr. Flills, 4,000 dollars. An assistant to Mr. Shuster, 3,500 dollars. A clerk to Mr. Shuster, 1,800 dollars. A clerk to Mr. Shuster, 1,600 dollars. There are at present four American financial experts at Tehran, namely:— Mr. W. Morgan Shuster, the Treasurer-General, at 2,000h a-year. Mr. F. C. Cairns, the Director of Taxation, at 1,200h a-year. Mr. O. L. McCaskey, the Inspector of Provincial Revenue, at 1,000b a-year. Mr. B. G. Dickey, Inspector of Taxation, at 1,000b a-year. Mr. Hills, the accountant, arrived with his family, but owing to the illness of one of his children he decided at once to return to America, and has apparently thrown up his appointment altogether. A successor to him is therefore included among the four whose engagement has now been decided upon. I have, &amp;c. G. BARCLAY. [2105 hh —1][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] PERSIA. [August 8.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [31131] No. 1. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received Auqust 8 ) (No. 226.) Sir, St. Petershurgh, August 4, 1911. WITH reference to my immediately preceding despatch of yesterdays date, I have the honour to report that the “ Novoe Vremya ” publishes a further article on the subject of Major Stokes in its issue of to-day. The article begins by reminding its readers that in May last year the Persian prince, Sharukh Darab Mirza, who was in the Russian service and commanded a sotnia in a Cossack regiment, decided to enter the arena of Persian politics. He obtained leave of absence, left his sotnia at Kazvin, sent in his resignation, and raised the standard of revolt against the Tehran Govern ment. But the Russian Government, in pursuance of a policy of non-interference in Persian affairs, refused to accept his resignation, and even sent troops after him to compel him to return. Not until he was escorted into Russian territory (where he still is) was his resignation accepted. In this manner did Russia deal with an attempt by a Persian prince in her service to interfere in Persian party politics. But Major Stokes, ex-military attache at Tehran, is a British officer and not a Persian prince, and it is therefore much simpler and easier to know how to treat him. If the British Govern- ; ment regard the agreement of 1907 half so seriously as does the Russian Government, then the end of the major’s escapade could be accurately foretold. He would not be allowed to retire, and would be informed that he must not interfere in a matter which did not concern him. If, in spite of everything, he should desert, the Indian troops at the British Legation at Tehran should treat him as the Cossacks did the Persian prince. He would be arrested. But, of course, the matter would never go as far as this. One word from the British Minister would be enough to stop the officer from entering the Persian service in a capacity which would contravene the spirit and the letter of the Anglo-Russian convention. The “ Novoe Vremya ” expresses the hope that His Majesty’s Government will do all in its power to prevent this “ridiculous adventure.” The article concludes with the words : “ By the way, what will the British Government do if Mohamed Ali Shah takes Major Stokes prisoner and orders him to be impaled ? They would probably remember then that Major Stokes was a British subject. But would it not be better to remember this now ? ” I have, &amp;c. GEORGE G. BUCHANAN.PERSIA. UG1911 [August 8.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1, [31130] No. 1. (No. 225.) Sir, Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 8.) on tlie proposed appointment of Major Stokes to command the new Persian Treasury gendarmerie. The article is entitled “An undesirable complication.” The article begins by sketching Mr. Shusters proposal, and goes on to compare the position of the commander of the gendarmerie to that of Russian officers who have been in the service of the Persian Government. The “ Novoe Vremya ” considers that the adoption of Major Stokes of the role of commander of the forces being dispatched against the ex-Shah is incomparably more dangerous for the maintenance of good Anglo-Russian relations than was the participation of Russian officers in the events which took place at Tehran two years ago. The Russian officers were not specially invited to take the field against political opponents. The outbreak of trouble found them at posts which duty and honour forbade them to vacate apart from all considerations of party politics; but Major Stokes is being engaged specially for the purpose of leading the troops of one party against those of another. The part which he is playing is not one which should be played by a British officer, for he is acting like a “hired condottiere.” Moreover, the Russian officers’ activities were limited to a sphere placed by the Anglo-Russian agreement under Russian influence, while Major Stokes is acting outside the sphere assigned by that agreement to British influence. While the Anglo-Russian agreement of 1907 remains in force Russia would not permit herself to mix in events which were taking place in the British sphere. Equally it cannot be considered legal or tolerable that British officers should take part in military operations in northern Persia. Russia does not wish to prevent the Persian Government from taking into its service any roving adventurers ; but she does object to the participation, indirect though it may be, of a friendly Government in such an appointment. The “ Novoe Vremya” continues: “Major Stokes is not a ‘nobody.’ He is a British military attache in Tehran. He cannot leave British service unless he has received the assent of the British War Office to his retirement Thus, the entry of Major Stokes into the Persian service is without a doubt entirely dependent on the wishes of the British Government. If it does not approve of the decision of a military attache in its service to embark on adventures which threaten to cast a shadow on the good relations existing between England and Russia, then Major Stokes will withdraw his resignation. If, on the other hand, his resignation is accepted, the British Government will show that it interprets its obligation of political non-intervention in the Russian sphere in Persia very conditionally.” The article points out that it is only Major Stokes’s official position and the assent of the British Government to his new appointment to which Russia takes exception ; to the personal side of the question she is entirely indifferent. The “ Novoe Vremya ” concludes by emphasising the immense importance of the Anglo-Russian entente and the necessity of carrying out its provisions with especial scrupulousness. The last sentence of the article runs : “ The incident with Major Stokes may introduce into Anglo-Russian relations, as far as they are connected with the .1907 agreement, substantial limitations equally disadvantageous to both parties.” I have, &amp;c. GEORGE W. BUCHANAN. [2141 /i—l][ 30212 ] /xt oi/\ \ Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan. (No. 210.) T TOT T'&gt; 4 - Tf ^ ^ cc j . ^ i i Foreign Office, July 26, 1911. o Ar • . F }^ Count Benckendorff to-day that we could not interfere with the appointment i&gt; . a J or Stok cs m Persia, though we should insist that, if he entered the service of the 1 ersian Government, he resigned his commission in our army Count Benckendorff pressed me to do more, and to*intimate to the Persian Government or to Mr. Shuster the undesirability of making the appointment. 1 said that we could not do this. Mr. Shuster was acting without any political motive ; he was apparently a very good, businesslike man, and he might throw up his of Persi^impossible ’ ^ ^ ^ Government ¥ d made the regeneration I told Count Benckendorff, however, that inasmuch as Major Stokes when appointed would superintend certain Bungs in Persian territory even on the Russian frontier we could not raise any objection if Russia intimated to the Persian Government, should ajor Stokes be appointed, that Russia also must secure some appointment which would ensure that her interests in the region of her frontier were not overlooked. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. Ji [2105 cc-5]COX MDKXTIa I Sir Edward Ore.,) to Sir Q. Buchanan (St. Petersburqh). &lt;N °' YOUR telegram Xo. 181 [ 16, 1911, 015 p.m. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs speaks as if we had not only acquiesced in but secured appointment of Stokes, and as if it was a fait accompli Th s s n&lt; so lie oniv H w^ 3 that a PPOmtment of a neutral Z i n ^ d ^^mumuctuuii ui ms own to rersian (iovernment such as Count Benckendorff lias shown me. Jf this is done, I will repeat warning to leismn Government, and urge appointment of a neutral instead of Stokes amUell SnSon WG m ° f Well - f0Unded R “ objection, accent’ Stokel ^ cting ^ouster for Foreign Affairs must understand that the appointment of Stokes has been made entirely without us, and that Stokes has acted quite indepenclently. far as 1 am aware Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs has not lodged any objection at lehran, and I must at present appear to Persian Government as being more Russian than the Russians in the line I have taken about it. 1 flunk Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs and Russian opinion are more sensitive than need be about Stokes s appointment. I have never stipulated that Persian Cossacks trained at lehran by Russian officers should not be employed in the south, but 1 have admitted Russian objection and done all I could hitherto to prevent the appointment, because I attach great importance to maintenance of good understandino- and co-operat 1011 with Russia. It is disappointing that Acting Minister for Foreign /Hairs seems to realise this so little. If I had been equally exacting from Russian Government about action of Colonel Liakhoff in past years, and continued presence of uissian troops in Northern Persia, good understanding between the two countries would have been over long ago. I have more than once had to defend these matters and make public opinion here patient on these points, and Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs should do as much in the case of Stokes, and explain to his people that hitherto it is our action alone that has prevented appointment from being made. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 238.) ! J V UCONFIDENTIAL. - 17AUG1S11 Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey,—(Received August 16, 8*30 a.m.) ( No * , ,, r St. Petersburgh, August 15, 1911 8 pm 10 UR telegram No. 439 [of the 14th August: Major' Stokes 1 Affairs made ^ COminimication as in structed to-day to the Acting Minister for Foreign His Excellency said that he had already received a report on the subject from the Russian Minister at lehran, and he would not conceal from me the fact that he considered the matter a very unpromising one. He repeated that it was not so mdch what might be said or done at Tehran that was causing him preoccupation as the grave prejudice that might be caused to the working of the Anglo-Russian under standing should the engagement of Stokes be persisted in. i a ^ appointment would inevitably cause the impression that as that understanding had not stood the test m the present instance it could not be depended on in the luture. \ hat, he asked, would have been said in England had a Russian officer accepted a post which would comprise the south of Persia in the sphere of his activitv ? I reminded his Excellency of the statements which you had made in Parliament ot your promise to support any eventual demand which Russia might make respecting the gendarmerie in the north, and of the satisfaction which you had given her in warning the Persian Government that His Majesty’s Government would recognise her right to take steps to safeguard her interests. His Excellency replied that all that Russia could do would be to demand some analogous appointment for a Russian officer, such as Chief of the Staff, or to intervene by force. In the latter case an entirely new situation would he created, while in the lormer h3 did not know whether he could count upon the support of His Majesty’s Government. I observed that your promised support of a Russian demand for the control of the northern gendarmerie would preclude any interference on the part of btokes in the north. His Excellency then proceeded to say that, should, as was not impossible, the ex-Shah regain the throne, Russian public opinion would force the Government to obtain from the Shah appointment of Chief of the Staff for a Russian officer. I pointed out that if the ex-Shah gained the day it was probable that both Shuster and Stokes would disappear from the scene, and that consequently Russia would nave no reason to ask for compensation. His Excellency rejoined that this.,)vould make no differejige. Russian Government would be told that they must profit by the fact that a Russophil Government wns installed at Tehran to obtain appointments for their subjects, just as England had none in the case of Stokes when an Anglophil Government was in power. He added that the whole question was such a serious one that he could not take upon himself to necide it alone, and that he must submit it to the Council of Ministers. Before doing so, however, he would make a final appeal to you, as, since Stokes’s jesignation had not yet been accepted, he thought it must be possible either to recall him temporarily or to give him some appointment elsewhere. Tact that his Excellency had just had an audience with the Emperor before seeing i, me gives additional weight to what he said. (Sent to Tehran.) [731—356JBM— m* m ' ML] (^,0 © CONFIDENTIAL ♦ V ^ ' * Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh ). (No. 439.) Foreign Office, August 14, 1911, 10 p.m. SIR G. BARCLAY’S telegram rfo. 326 [ ]• You should give to Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs substance of Persian reply, including Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs’ suggestion in penultimate paragraph of telegram, but omitting antepenultimate and last paragraphs. You may say that 1 do not see what more I can do m the mattei except repeat to Persian Government warning given by my telegram No. 226 [ ] to Sir / G. Barclay. You may add that Major Stokes’s resignation has not been accepted and will not be, pending further developments.C0.NTIDENTIA1. Vsr/ &lt;y G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 13, 10 a.m.) (No. 325.) R. Tehran, August 1911, 9*30 a.m. .A 1 a dinner last night arranged for the purpose my Russian colleague and I had for the first time an opportunity of free discussion with Shuster. United States Minister was present. My Russian colleague and I urged upon Shuster the necessity of acting with due regard to the spirit and letter of the Anglo-Russian agreement. And we assured him of our full support on those lines. We endeavoured to persuade him that the appointment of Majoi Stokes to the command of a national fiscal gendarmerie was contrary to the spirit of the agreement, and reminded him of our warnings to the Persian Government as to the engagement of assistants from subjects of European Great Rowers. Shuster assured us that in offering post to Stokes he had had no idea that the appointment would be unwelcome. He gave us the most ample assurances as to working within the lines of the agreement, but pleaded with extreme persistence for the employment of Stokes without restriction of his duties to the south. He said he could assure us that he would not be actively employed in the north except for organisation in Tehran, and declared that his assistance for this work for a time in Tehran was indispensable. There was no one else immediately available for his purpose. Moreover, if he waived his demand for Stokes’s services, his position with the Medjliss, which he solemnly assured us should be used in the interests of smooth relations with the two Powers on the lines of the agreement, would be seriously shaken. He promised that while Stokes was under his orders the latter’s Russophobe proclivities would be completely controlled, and he pressed the Russian Minister repeatedly and earnestly to endeavour to overcome the Russian Government’s opposition. The Russian Minister tried in vain to convince Shuster that any such endeavour would be useless, and most courteously but firmly refused to advise his Government to I. change their attitude. Shuster made it evident that he was so dependent on Stokes that he would support any reasonable counter-demand from Russia, but Russian Minister pointed out the friction that would result from Russia’s pressing for a counter-demand would react in favour of Mahomet Ali. The most sensible course was therefore to abandon the appointment of Stokes. Our conversation, -while it was unsatisfactory in that it was inconclusive and left us in doubt as to what course Shuster would adopt in regard to Stokes’s appointment, served at least to put our relations with Shuster on a rational footing, and also some what to relieve the anxiety which his go-ahead methods had caused us.CONFIDENTIAL. Lf-cr^sl — r 2— 15 AUG1911 Sir O. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 12, 9-45 r.ji.) M P *'“' I Lirficiii Government cannot understand tlip attiturlo nf TTic i\t ■ a » in regard to the appointment of Major Stokes 0 ' [ ^fajesty s Government word could be found in it to S^ify tSnlen&amp;n 1 : °- 25 ° ° f ye3r) ’ n0t 0116 independence a'nd'Segrity of'persiajsupporbf the pS^fntT^ 31 temS order in S fcrte^ SZTTJZZ 1 diffilTt task taXeS ’ Wlth0Ut Which the ma &gt; nten ance of order would be fn anVcounS The Persian Government are confident that His Majesty’s Government will lend Ld^trhefmosSlTnil 8 qUeSti0U C ° UsisteiltI y with the dignity of Persia In handing me this communication, the Minister for Foreign Affairs asked u,v *? emerge from the present impasse without loss of face. I suggested that Majoi btokes s work might be confined not perhaps expressly to the south but to Furs but his Excellency said that Russia would inevitably demand an eqCaknt in the of influence 3 * eVeU SUCh aU arraugement would be tantamount to reception of spheres IlisExceHency then suggested that the appointment of Stokes might be limited onl&gt; to three years, with the stipulation that it was not to be a precedent. At the end 0 that period the Treasury gendarmerie would be entrusted to Persians or subjects 01 minor Powers. He said that if this did not satisfy Russia he thought that, if the G o,? y^'^ment replied favourably to his recent advances (see my telegram Lf1 L , A he migllt be able t0 declare that, provided the appointment oi Stokes was not made the pretext for any Russian demand, he would not be sent Tehran 0U 337 3CtlVe mlSS10u m the nortb as distinct from organisation work in 1 b , a 'l ddormed the Russian Minister of the above and he does not think the I proposal ol the Minister for Foreign Affairs worth telegraphing to his Government. I(’ 15 AUG 1911 Sii' Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran). Foreign Office, August 11, 1911, G'15 p.m. (No. 230.) YOUR telegram No. 322. You should tell Shuster that we appreciate his work and his single-minded motive and are sorry not to be able to do anything that he wishes. But we might ourselves have objected to appointment of a Russian officer to organise any administration on Indian frontier, and as soon as we found that appointment of Stokes would be objected to by Russia we could not deprecate her objection, and were bound to warn Persian Government of difficulties that would arise. For some time past there has been an understanding with Persian Government that only subjects of minor Powers should be selected, f he only exception to this was the United States, and to that Russia agreed influenced thereto by our opinion that the United States was beyond suspicion of any political motive in Persia. It is a pity that if a departure was to be made from this understanding the Russian Government were not sounded in advance. I fear only way out of difficulty that has now arisen will be appointment of some subject of a minor Power.CON'FIUKNTIAI . c^or/- Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey .—(Received August 11 , 5*5 p.m.) (No. 180.) ^ St. Petersburgh, August 11, 1911, 3‘1S p.m. I SPOKE to Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday in the terms of your telegram No. 427 [ ]. His Excellency remarked that support promised by His Majesty’s Government to Russian demand respecting northern gendarmerie met case of Major Stokes’s appoint ment being restricted to south, but said nothing of what would be done should that appointment not be so restricted. I said that support which you had promised to Russia virtually covered both cases, as it would render it impossible for Major Stokes to extend his operations to the north! His Excellency did not seem quite satisfied, and asked whether Major Stokes had been informed of the views of His Majesty’s Government on this question, as he could not understand why pressure could not be brought to bear on him to make him relinquish appointment. His Excellency begged me to let him know as soon as you had received a reply from the Persian Government, as he desired that the incident might be closed as soon as possible. I am postponing communicating to him the contents of Sir G. Barclay’s telegrams Nos. 318 [ ] and 319 [ ], as before seeing him again I should like to know what is result of communication which Sir G. Barclay was instructed to make to Stokes by your telegram No. 227 [ ] and also whether you have any further instructions for me.CONFIDENTIAL. 4-0 $ 7 - 7 . A U 15 AUG 1911 i)F r ' s - r ■ •Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan {St. Petersburrjh). ^ N °'rFOrV OWTMP ' ; r Foreign Office, August 9, 1911. 8th A ngust':—y Vfil P arharaentar y question by Earl of Ronaldshay, ‘ I uuderstand that, Major Stokes lias been offered an appointment by the Persian Government It cannot have the approval of His Majesty’s Government unless the condi tions of the appointment are consistent with the terms and the spirit of the A redo- Russian agreement of 1907. *L^D Tl- [Thiajjocumcat i 8 the Property of Hie Britannic Majeety 8 r—, PERSIA. [July 29.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1 [30211] No. 1. 2 . Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan. (No.-^) gi r&gt; Foreign Office, July 29, 1911. THE Russian Ambassador asked Sir A. Nicolson on the 25th instant whether Major Stokes’s appointment had been finally settled. Sir A. Nicolson replied that he did not know, but that His Majesty’s Government had informed Major Stokes that he would have to resign his commission in the army if he accepted the appointment. Count Benckendorff said that M. Neratof hoped that His Majesty’s Government would go a step further and tell the Persian Government that they had nothing to do with the appointment, and that, if the Russian Government asked for some appoint ment to counterbalance that of Major Stokes, we would support their requests. M. Neratof thought that perhaps two or three Russian “instructors” might be appointed under Major Stokes if necessary. Count Benckendorff said the Russians must obtain some compensation for an Englishman being appointed as head of the gendarmerie over the whole of Persia, the Russian sphere included. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. [2105/-l][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Govern™i PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. $ J O ^ [Jnly 28.] Section 6. [30228] No. I. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan. (No. 206.) COUNT TCFYON CNrinPi?!? i Fmeign ()f)ice, July 28, 1911. •1 Tf fi CK i;^ D Ill T sp ^ ke t0 me t0Hla y Wlth great anxiety about the possibility that Major Stokes might take part m military operations in Persia. If this happened, Russian officers might take part on the other side, and the result would be to give the appearance of a most unfortunate breach between England and Russia in their policy with regard to Persia. .i ^ telegram which I was sending to Sir George Barclay to-day. I gathered that Major Stokes had not yet actually received an appointment. I agreed that it was undesirable that he should take jiart in anv military operations in Persia or that any European officers should do so. But the officers who were in command of Peisian gendarmei le would no doubt take part in operations against the robbers on the southern roads, and it was a little difficult to know where to draw the line I would however, see what I could do. ’ ’ I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. [ 2105 ee—6]Lf-o r7— 1 — [This Document ia the Property of ffi s Britannic Majasty g Governmp nt ] PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [28641J No. 1. Foreign Office to Anglo-Persian Oil Company* Sir, Foreign Office, July 28, 1911. I AM directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 20th instant, relative to the proposed appointment of Major Stokes to organise a force of gendarmerie to assist in the collection of the revenue in Persia. I am to inform you, in reply, that His Majesty’s Government will not oppose this appointment should the officer in question desire to accept it, on the condition that he resigns the commission which he now holds in the Indian army. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET. Also to Imperial Bank of Persia, mvtatis mutandis. [2105 &lt;w—3][This Doeament is the Property of H 13 Britannic Majesty's Government.] PERSIA. [July 21.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 4. [28641] No - L r: 'T Anglo-Persian Oil Company to Foreign Office.—(Received July 21.) ('Confidential.) Winchester House, Old Broad Street, London, Sir, . Jul V 20, 1911. I BEG to enclose copy of a telegram which I have to-day received from our agent at Tehran, Mr. Brown, with reference to the proposed appointment of Major Stokes for the purpose of organising a force of gendarmerie. I have, &amp;c. C. GREEN WAY. Enclosure in No. 1. Telegram from Mr. Brown (Tehran) to Mr. Greenway (London). July 20, 1911. TREASURER-GENERAL estimates that total(s) inland revenue collected amounts to 19 000,000 tomans yearly, of which less than 3,000,000 reaches Central Treasury. Although’he will place capable officers in all important centres for the collection of revenue, these would be helpless unless backed (by) properly organised force(s) of Treasury Guard; this force will be also employed to maintain order throughout country ‘ Stokes has been selected to organise this force, and it is of the utmost importance his services should be lent by British Government. I telegraph you at the request of Treasurer-General. Appointment is not political, but based on qualification(s) of the man. [2105 x—4]C^o &lt; 57 - 2 ^ [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government 1 PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [28483] io ti a q 1911 No. 1. [July 20.] Section 4. The Imperial Bank of Persia to Foreign Office.—(Received July 20.) Sir, 25, Abchurch Lane, London, July 19, 1911. IN a telegram received yesterday from our chief manager in Tehran the hope is expressed that the Foreign Office will favour the appointment offered by the Treasurer- General to Major Stokes. Our manager adds that, in his opinion, the appointment would be greatly to the bank’s interest. I have, &amp;c. G. NEWELL, Manager. [2105 w-4]CONTI DKNT1AI 10 AUG1911 Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.— (Received August 10, 11-45 a.m.) Tehran, August 10, 191J, 11*15 a.m. Shuster, marked (No. 322. Urgent.) MY telegram No. 319 [of the 9th instant]. I have received strong but courteously-worded “ Purely personal.” lie expiesses surprise at the volte-face indicated in my communication of yesterday, as compared with your message in your telegram No. 213 [ ], and asks whether His Majesty’s Government quite realise position in which they are placing him by now suddenly joining with another Power to prevent exercise of most elemental act of sovereignty by Persia, whose independence and integrity both Powers have pledged themselves to respect. Before accepting his post he was given clearly to understand that two Powers offered no objection, u and surely such a statement was something more than an empty pledge,” yet his first vital step to bring order out of chaos is relentlessly opposed by two Powers, notwithstanding their repeated professions of their desire to see progress in Persia. Recent attitude of His Majesty’s Government must inevitably produce impression that they are really opposed to his success, and must force him to assume he can count upon no moral assistance from His Majesty’s Government in a vital matter of this kind. In Persia good men are so extremely scarce that attitude of His Majesty’s Government amounts to a virtual veto of his efforts. Letter goes on to speak of our attitude as bearing appearance of totally uncalled-for interference in purely routine and internal affairs of financial organisation, and say he feels “ so strongly on the subject that I am forced to contemplate necessity of setting right my own men at least with a formal public statement of all my experiences in this connection since arriving at Tehran. Needless to say, such a course would be much to my regret; but there is such a thing as just dealing even h between Governments and individuals, and certainly in this case I feel my own record/| is sufficiently clear to bear light of the most thorough inspection.” I would propose merely to reply that my warning to Persian Government was given in hope of saving them from an awkward situation, and as soon as we saw appointment of Major Stokes would raise serious political questions [? remainder of t degram omitted].confidential. LtOl^ r, 10 AUG 1911 Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 10, 11 a.m.) (No. 319.) ( ^ Tehran, August 9, 1911, 410 pm \ OUR telegram No. 226 [of 7th August]. } ni AIf • a C0 ?l? ll i?^ Ca Ji 0n as i nst [ ucte d, leaving aide-memoire with Minister for r ore^gn Anairs. His Excellency promised to send me written reply. I suggested to him that to confine appointment of Major Stokes to the south would be way out of the difficulty. He replied that this was quite inadmissible. -“U [ eason 18 evidently that this would be implicit recognition of division of of Persia into spheres of influence. [731—336]CONFIDENTIAL Foreign Office, August 9, 1911, 11 p.m. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 427.) / YOUR telegram No. 178 [ ]. Inform Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs of my statement in the House of Commons yesterday, and let him know that appointment is in suspense pending answer of Persian Government. You may add that probably after our last represen- tat ion at enian the Persian Grovernment will drop the appointment altogether but if not yon may tell Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs that we shall be ready to support a demand that gendarmerie employed in the north should be under a Russian officer or subject of a minor Power proposed by Russia. Best solution, however, would be appointment of a neutral for whole of revenue gendarmerie._ 10 AUG 1911 Sir O. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 9, 8'30 p.m.) (No. 318.) fi. YOUR telegram No. 221 [ ] J ehran, August 9, 1911. MiniLTft leavi 'g. with have now received excellency promised me a reply m writing, which I Reply states that Persian Government do not intend to emnlov Malm- &lt;st i military operations. employ ^lajoi btokes m any As regards my mention of “north of Persia ” renlv savs • “tww,- t . equally necessary in Northern and Southern Persia and m 1 ^ eS - 18 ll Government there is no difference between these two regions ” JeS ° f ^ PerS,ai1 iiconmi)i:n'i'iai. Lf-Ob^ Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 8, 9*30 p.m.) (N0 ‘ YOUR telegram No. 419 [ ^ August 8, 1911, 740 , Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, with whom I had a long conversation this afternooii, is still very occupied as to the consequences which the Stokes incident may ha\e unless some moial satisfaction can be given to Russian public opinion. He doubts whether the Persian Government will consent to modify Stokes’s original contract, m spite of the warning which Sir G. Barclay has been instructed to address to them. 1 told him that I did not see what more you could do at present and that we must now await the answer of the Persian Government. He replied that it was not so much Persian Government that he was thinking of as public opinion here. I then enquired whether he had any suggestion to make ? His Excellency thereupon said that, supposing the Persian Government did agree to confine Major Stokes’s command to the south, it would be difficult to prevent them from eventually employing the gendarmerie thus formed with or without their commander in the north, and he thought that His Majesty’s Government might tranquillise Russian public opinion by publicly stating that under no circumstances would this southern gendarmerie be utilised for service in the north. I observed that, though it might be possible for you to say that Major Stokes’s services would not be made use of in the north, it would be very difficult, in my opinion, to declare that Persian Government might not ever avail themselves of any forces of which they might dispose to put down disorders in some other part of the country should the situation require it. His Excellency then suggested that His Majesty’s Government might, in the event of Major Stokes being entrusted with the command of a southern gendarmerie, announce their readiness to support any eventual demand which the Russian Government might make that the organisation of a northern gendarmerie should be confided to either a Russian officer or to the subject of a minor Power whom Russia might propose. I said that I personally preferred this suggestion to the one which he had previously made, but that I could not answer for His Majesty’s Government. Reverting subsequently to the possibility of the Persian Government persisting in giving Major Stokes command of a national gendarmerie, his Excellency suggested that His Majesty’s Government might in that case declare that they would support Russia’s claim to some similar appointment, such as that of chief of the staff, being given to a Russian officer. In reply to my remark that 1 feared that the Persian Government would never consent to this, his Excellency said that Russia had no intention of putting it forward at present. It was only a possible eventuality, and all that he wanted at present was that you should, either in the House of Commons or in the press, make some statement that would calm public opinion in Russia. (Sent to Tehran.) [730—240]4oTl CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 419.) Foreign Office, August 7, 1911, 2’30 p.m. YOU should inform Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs of substance of my telegram No. 226 a [ ] to Sir G. Barclay. As we pressed Persian Government to organise a force under British officers to protect southern trade routes last winter, a fact of which I think Russian Government were aware and to which they made no objection, I cannot deprecate employment of Major Stokes by Persian Government in any part of Persia. But I agree that it would be a breach of the spirit of Anglo-Russian convention if we were in any way to support Stokes’s employment in north of Persia, or deprecate Russian objections to it. You may tell Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs that I am enquiring whether his suggestion in first paragraph of your telegram No. 176 q ] is feasible, and meanwhile we may await result of my telegram No. 226 a [ ] to Sir G. Barclay. (Repeated to Tehran, No. 22S.) [730—228]CONFIDENTIAL. ♦ 8 AUG 1911 \ t rp \ Foreign Office, August 7, 1911, 2-.30 p.m. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 227.) / MY telegram No. 226 [ j Ton should inform Major Stokes of what you are instructed to say to the Persian Government. Russian Government are as much within their right in protesting agams h.s employment to control gendarmerie in north as we should be in protesting against employment of Russians to control southern trade routes. It will bf impossible foi Peisian Government to uphold appointment against Russian inter- “ “1“ appointment I am enquiring of India Office whether there is any means of suspending acceptance of Major Stokes’s resignation. Unless you have already done sofdo njt make any communication of acceptance of resignation to him.4-^v CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 226.) \/ Foreign Office, August 7, 1911, 2’30 p.m. IN view of Sir Gr. Buchanans No. 1/6 [ repeated to you from St. Peteisburgh, it is clear that appointment of Major Stokes to control gendarmerie in north of Peisia will raise a serious political question. You should warn Persian Go\ ernment that, unless Major Stokes is not to he employed in north of Persia, they ought not to persist in the appointment, and, if they do persist, we shall recognise right of Russia to take what steps she thinks necessary to safeguard her interests in North Persia.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 7, 10 a.m.) (No. 315.) Tehran, August 7, 1911, 10'45 a.m. WHILE question of Major Stokes’s appointment and possible Russian intervention in Persia is under your consideration I venture to point out that, should ex-Shah come to Tehran, it would be probably with a following of Turkomans or other savage tribes, who would be a danger of a very different kind from the Bakhtiari at the time of the last revolution, and if in such eventuality Russians were to urge necessity for presence of their troops in Tehran it would be difficult to affirm that life and property would be secure without them, notwithstanding any gendarmerie force which might by that time have been organised.CON FI L ' - o (No. 176 MY Acti more he still be formal iti given to He ] between it here, two Gov Power si were on a that won solidarity Minister the foil o^ Rusi create a incompat unfriend' find nece Brit Persian Russian service v may jud^ I sai their con milder ai remarked intervene Hus: Excellem (Sen [7CONFIDENTIAL Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey .— (Lleceived August 6, 8 a.m. (No. 176. .Urgent.) J St. Petersburgh, August 5, 191J, 8'32 p.m. MY immediately preceding telegram [ ]. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs sent for me this afternoon and said that the more he reflected on Major Stokes’s appointment the more he trusted that you might still be able to recall that officer temporarily. There must, he thought, be some formalities to be gone through that might serve to prevent immediate effect being- given to his resignation. He regretted the incident because it showed to the world a serious disagreement between the two Governments, while a false interpretation would inevitably be put on it here. Appointment was, moreover, a contravention of the principle on which the two Governments had hitherto acted, namely, that no subject of a European Great Power should be allowed to occupy any important post in the Persian service. If you were unable to act on his suggestion it would be absolutely necessary to take some step that would give satisfaction to Russian public opinion and at the same time demonstrate solidarity existing between the two Governments in Persia. He suggests that Russian Minister at Tehran should be instructed to address note to the Persian Government in the following sense :— Russian Government protest against proposed appointment of Major Stokes to create a gendarmerie which will act in North Persia as well as elsewhere as being- incompatible with their interests. Appointment if made would be regarded as an unfriendly act, and the Russian Government reserve right to take measures which they find necessary to safeguard their interests in North Persia. British Minister, he further suggests, should at the same time address note to the Persian Government stating that His Majesty’s Government concur entirely in the Russian note, and that, while regretting that Major Stokes was invited to enter Persian service -without their knowledge, they recognise Russia’s right to take steps which she may judge necessary to safeguard her interests in North Persia. I said I thought that it might be difficult for His Majesty’s Government to express their concurrence in a note which virtually threatened intervention, and I suggested a milder and more conciliatory formula. 1 failed, however, to move his Excellency, who remarked that, if Russian interests were threatened, Government would be obliged to intervene. Russian Ambassador will be instructed to speak to you on Monday, and his Excellency is most anxious to have a reply before he sees the Emperor on Tucsday. (Sent to Tehran.) [730—220]CONI 0 ]mmmm LVOIT^ CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received August 4, 11 p.m.) (No. 175.) St. Petersburgh, August 4, 1911, 8’10 p.m. ACTING Minister for Foreign Affairs, to whom I spoke this afternoon in the sense of your telegram No. 411 [ ], said that Russia had already protested and had warned the Persian Government that they would require some sort of equivalent in the north. While obliged for your proffered support of any objections which Russia might make to the employment of Major Stokes in the north, he feared that protest of this kind might provoke retort that the Persian Government were not concerned with division of Persia into spheres of influence under the Anglo- Russian Agreement. He would, however, think over the matter and see if it was possible to find a formula that would get over this difficulty and that would, at the same time, have the support of His Majesty’s Government. His Excellency did not conceal embarrassment and preoccupation which the incident was causing him. He personally understands that His Majesty’s Government are not behind Major Stokes, but fears that Russian public opinion will place different interpretation on the matter. He said that at a moment when the Persian Government were fighting for their existence they would not trouble about the organisation of the Treasury gendarmerie and would employ Stokes to fight the ex-Shah. This ought to be prevented at all costs, and he asked whether His Majesty’s Government not recall Stokes temporarily to London on some service of the frontier. He cited the incident, incorrectly reported in my telegram No. .172 [ having occurred two years ago, of the recall last year of the Russian officer Mirza, who had wanted to take service against the Tehran Government. I told him that His Majesty’s Government could not control Stokes’s movements when once he had resigned his commission, but his Excellency begged me to try and see if something could not be done. Reactionary press welcomes what it terms [two groups undecypherable: ? violation of] Anglo-Russian Agreement, as Russia, it asserts, will now be free to interfere actively. I fear that it will be very difficult for the Russian Government to resist doing something should Stokes take part in any military operations against the ex-Shah. (Sent to Tehran.) could again ] as Darab4-0tr7 CONFIDENT! AI. Edward Grey to bir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburyh ). Foreign Office, August 3, 1911, 10 p.m. (No. 411.) / YOUR telegram No. 174 [ ]. It is difficult, if not impossible, for us to prevent Major Stokes from taking service under the I ersian Government if he resigns his commission. But I agree that Russian Government aie entitled to object to his being employed in northern sphere of Persia. cd d^ e y w ^sh to piesent objection to Persian Government against such employment, Sir G. Barclay will be instructed to inform Persian Government that objection is one to which we cannot take exception, and which Persian Government should take into account, as it is reasonable, and was to be expected. (Repeated to Tehran.)c^cny] CONFIDENTIAL. Cs 4 AUG 191 ] ^ Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey,—{Received August 3, 5’15 p.m.) (No 174- Urgent.) St. Petersburgh, August 3, 1911, 3'40 p.m. v 'YOUR telegram Ngn-300i } to T^ktan [? Sir G. Barclay’s telegram No. 300 [ ]•] . A M . q, i j “ Novoe Vremya ” of this morning enters a strong protest against Major btoKes s appointment to the Treasury gendarmerie if that force is to be employed outside British sphere. It contends, moreover, that the real intention of Persian Government is to employ him for the time being as commander of troops to be despatched against ex-Shah. It declares that so long as Anglo-Russian agreement remains in force it is not permissible for British officers to take active part in an internal struggle proceeding in the northern provinces or to assist in the organisation of any armed forces v hatever to be employed in those provinces. ^ n , . tt- at • . * It throws eventual responsibility of Major Stokes s appointment on ms Majesty s Government, as it is in their power to prevent it by refusing to accept bis resignation. Acceptance of his resignation will, it concludes, show that His Majesty s Crovernment place very narrow interpretation on their obligations under the agreement ol 1907 not to interfere in Russian sphere. . rv-i- i i Above article evidently represents the views held in official circles here, and I fear that unless Major Stokes’s appointment to the gendarmerie is made conditional on his not being employed outside British sphere bad impression will be created here. Situation will be much aggravated should lie be allowed to take held against the ex-Shah. (Sent to Tehran.)CONFIDENTIAL. LfCTVl Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey. —(Received August 2, 9T5 p.m.) (No. 172.) St, Petersburgh, August 2, 1911, 7*20 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 403 [ Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs asked me to-day what was happening with regard to Major Stokes, and said that the Russian Minister at Tehran had informed the Persian Government that, in the event of his employment in the Treasury, Russia would demand an equivalent in the north. I communicated to his Excellency the instructions sent to Sir G. Barclay, adding that, if once Major Stokes resigned his commission, His Majesty’s Government could no longer control his action. His Excellency evidently considers that his employment in any capacity in the Persian service at the present moment is inopportune. Speaking of the possibility of his taking part in active operations against the ex-Shah, his Excellency said that when two years ago a Russian officer had sent in his resignation, in order to take service with the Nationalists, the Russian Government had refused to accept it, and had recalled him to Russia. (Sent to Tehran )CONFIDENTIAL. / 3 AUG 1911c) Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (N ° YOTk telegram Noiw [ ^ ^ ^ 2 ’ 1911 &gt; 7 ‘ 15 P “- Major Stokes s resignation must be submitted to Government of India, to whom telegram has been sent with request that they will telegraph approval to you direct soon as possible, if they agree. There is no objection here. Application as legards pension should be made to Government of India (Repeated to St. Petersburg!!.) [73 - 202]CONFIDENTIAL. A Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 30, 9*50 p.m.) (NO ‘IoUR telegram No. 219 [ ]. ^ ^ 3 °’ 1911 ’ 10 ’ 10 i\Iajor Stokes has decided to resign his position in the Indian army, and hopes that in view of I reasurer-General’s urgent need of his services you will see your way to ask authorities concerned to dispense with usual formalities and to inform him bv telegraph of the acceptance of his resignation. He also asks that in view of his sixteen years’ service he may be granted such ieduced pension or gratuity as his services may be considered to deserve, but whatever may be decision on this point, he begs that there may be no delay in telegraphing acceptance of Ip.s resignation. ' eraCONFIDENTIAL. A Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay (Tehran). (No. 219.) Foreign Office, July 28, 1911. YOUR telegram No. 289 [ ]. Major Stokes should be given clearly to understand that he must resign his commission in the army before taking service or duties of any kind under the Persian Government. How are his proposed services under Treasurer-General compatible with his taking the field in a military capacity ? It might also be pointed out to Persian Government that if Stokes is employed by them in active military operations in Persia it may provide excuse for Russian officers taking active part on other side.Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey. — (Received July 28, 1 L a.m.) Tehran, July 28, 1911, 10-38 a.m. (No. 289.) YOUR telegram No. 217 [ ]. Proposed joint declaration is a rejection of Persian Government’s appeal to the two Powers (see my telegram No. 279 [ ]), and is virtually recognition of ex-Shah’s belligerency. I cannot see, therefore, how it would help Persian Government for the moment. In the long run, however, it would probably work out to their advantage, as it would serve as a restraint on over-zealous Russian agents, who, if no declaration were made at all, might consider their hands free. Logical course for the two Powers, one of wdiom has undertaken to take effective measures to prevent ex-Shah from intriguing, would be to refrain from using any phrase which might be construed as recognition of his belligerency, at any rate, st&gt; soon after he has left Russian asylum, and merely to declare that they will give him neither material nor moral support; but if we cannot hope to induce Russia to see matter in this light, we had better as a pis oiler make proposed declaration. Should Stokes get his appointment under the Persian Government, they might order him to the front. Russian Government were doubtless contemplating this contingency when they proposed so explicit a declaration of strict neutrality. I do not know how far proposed joint declaration would enable or compel us to prevent Major Stokes from active service against ex-Shah. Russian Government, who I understand have ruled that Russian officers to the Cossack brigade and other Russian subjects shall not be allowed to take part in conflict, would probably protest against his fight ing whether we made declaration or not. (Sent to India.)[ 73 ( CONFII (No. 280 YOl I iff Latt as to pen are neede he would Min Russia, ] amendnn Min will not ] I ha‘S/r G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 23, 3*30 p.m.) (No. 280.) / YOUR telegram No. 213 f ]• Tehran, July 23, 1911, 3*30 p.m. I -.group omitted : r' liave seeu ] rreasurer-Geueral and Major Stokes Latter is fully resolved to resign from the Indian army if satisfactory amendments as to pension are made in contract already authorised by Medjliss. These amendments are needed to make good to him the pension to which, if he remained in British service he would be entitled in two years. They must be approved by the Medjliss. Ministers, fearing that Stokes’s appointment will provoke counter-demands from Russia, hesitate to comply with Shuster’s insistence and to propose the necessary amendments to the Medjliss. J Minister for foreign Affairs has privately asked me for an assurance that Russia will not make such counter-demands. I have told his Excellency that I cannot give him this.CONFIDENTIAL.. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received July 21, 3T5 p.m.) (No. 273.) Tehran, July 21, 1911, 3’30 p.m. MY telegram No. 252 [of 14th July]. I have received letter from Shuster asking me to hasten your reply about appoint ment of Stokes. He says— (R.) “ Entire matter of Treasury gendarmerie is necessarily being held up pending settlement of this question, and I have no hesitation in saying that formation of this force is most urgent and vitally necessaiy to financial reorganisation of Persia. Without this gendarmerie I am practically helpless, and without Stokes I am at a loss where to turn for a man possessing anything like his qualifications.”(No. 251 YC Prc officer v comp uP On Shuster, Me&lt; under r position for the \ peculiar Persia, 1 genera] &lt; Iln aide (sic played n to presm an assist I ta undertak risked m mine has naturally frank am Wit] several &lt; undecypl efficient i would be whatever satisfied 1 We suffers he modes of case of o] to make i to spend assistance organised In ce Major Sto not fail to could by ] I tin Governme i -CONFIDENTIAL. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received 14, 2'30 i-.m.) Tehran, Julij 14, 1911, 3 p.m. (No. 252.) YOUR telegram No. 199 [ ]. Proposal that command should he split up so as to secure Russian and English otticer would not I am convinced, be accepted by Persian Government unless under compulsion, and if we insisted on it 1 have little doubt Shuster would resign. 4 11 j recei P t °/ y° lir telegram 1 wrote suggesting the other alternative to Shuster, and extract of his reply is as follows Med i lis s having recently authorised me to appoint suitable person to organise ^sitLT AT n ‘ eCt Q S f U f rv f 10n 1 and COntr 1 ° 1 f( 1 )rce of T^asury gendarmerie, I tendered f!?rt^on t0 ?^ aj P r Stokes for the reason that 1 consider him to be the best fitted man npr-nli! W ° rk rr ^ 1 C0ll } c] V0 ^ sihl y ? btain - 1 am personally aware of Major Stokes’s peculiar qualifications for this task—military training, his four vears’ sojourn in Peisia his knowledge of the country, of the Persian language and of French, and in general of the esteem in winch he is held in this communitv as an officer and a man U-\ e u 0 ltal ^ a you that in seeking the most efficient financial i V _*n I could find for this particular branch of my work question of nationality played no part whatever m making up my opinion. Had this been so, it is but natural to presume that matter being left entirely to my discretion I would have sought such an assistant from iny own countrv. I take this occasion to repeat that work of financial reform here which I have undertaken m the midst of many grave difficulties and on which I have in a manner naked my professional reputation, i s in no sense political in its character. No act of mine has been guided by political considerations which are local or international, and I naturally feel that 1 could not accept any suggestion which would cast on my perfectlv frank and disinterested tender of a post to Major Stokes the light of political bias. V\ 1 th all due respect to subjects of minor Powers, and without any disrespect to several of my own countrymen [? who could be] appointed to serve [group undecypherable] m Treasury gendarmerie, Major Stokes is the best qualified to give e cient service to this country in connection with my own financial mission, and I would be unwilling under any circumstances to appoint anvone from any Power whatever for this or any other branch of my work unless I personally was aware and satisfied with appointes special qualifications. We know, of course, one of the greatest handicaps from which any foreigner suffers here is, as in my own case lack of knowledge of the language, habits,'and modes of thought of the Persian people. This defect becomes even more serious in the case of one called to deal impartially with large number of such men as would &lt;r 0 to make up an armed force. A Swedish officer, be he ever so competent, would have to spend at least a year or more here before he could possibly be of any real assistance m this line of work, whereas necessity for getting my gendarmerie^ force organised and at work at once is urgent in the extreme. ,, . 1“ conclusion permit me to say that as the fact of my tender of this post to -Major btokes is now generally known here, any withdrawal of that offer by me could not lad to be interpreted as being dictated by pure political considerations, which I could by no means permit. p I trust I may receive early and favourable consideration [? and approval of] government of Major Stokes s acceptance. JMiniCONFIDENTIAL. (Received July 16, 5 p.m.) Tehran, July 10, 1911, 1*45 p.m. Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey. (No. 254.) / MY telegram No. 252 [ ]. 1 understand on enquiry that Shuster contemplates appointing three Americans who have considerable experience to assist in the formation of Treasury gendarmerie, fie has telegraphed his terms to two of them direct, and has applied for one through Leneral Edwards at Washington.CONI M, under positioi for the peculia Persia, genera] II aide (s? played to presi an assis It undertis risked i mine hj natural frank ai Wi several undecyj efficient would 1 whateve satisfied We suffers ] modes oi case of i to make to spenc assistanc organise In &lt; Major St not fail t could by I tr Governmw i-- 17JUL1911 Kir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey.— {Received July 14, 2'30 i\m.) (N °' YOUR telegram 199^ ]. My U ’ 1911 ’ 3 P M ' nffipprw^u 1 that command .should be split up so as to secure Russian and English —iZn “h’J am . c&lt;lnvl ^ d . ho accepted by Persian Government unless under compulsion, and if we insisted on it 1 have little doubt Shuster would resign. Shuster ' 1 ' 'hi’ 0 /,^ 0nr grant I wrote suggesting the other alternative to onuster, and extract of his reply is as follows :— unrW e n j 1 ^- ha 7 ing reCPnt!y al, J thorised me t0 a PP oi “t suitable person to organise ’ ZitLi to AfaW StT'TTi aDd C 0 Ut u 01 f V ree of Treasury gendarmerie, I tendered for the J t 1 J n St r kes m r the . l ; e 1 as01 ‘ that 1 consider him to be tile best fitted man 1 C0 'f f P t °v lbly ? btaln i. Ianl Personally aware of Major Stokes’s Persia hiftn 1 1° 118 ‘aah—'nrhtary training, his four years’ sojourn in «en^l of the ’I® C h I ^ rB,an lan g' a gc and of French, and in e eneral of the esteem in which he is held in this community as an officer and a man. aide f«vTwhTjT ltot w“&lt;: 1 “i a r SSU n“ gy&amp; “ tl ’ a \ in seeking the most efficient financial olaveH , T , i U ' fi - nd 0I i i hls particular branch of my work question of nationality F y d Part 'hatever in making up my opinion. Had this been so, it is but natural piesume that matter being left entirely to my discretion I would have sought such an assistant from my own country. T take this occasion to repeat that work of financial reform here which I have undertaken m the midst of many grave difficulties and on which 1 have in a manner ns ed my professional reputation,-s in no sense political in its character. No act of ZZT n e i n P’1 ed b y Pchbcal considerations which are local or international, and I flirts 11 ' 1 1 C °i U d j 0t aL ' oe P t au y ^riggestion which would cast on my perfectly fiank and disinterested tender of a post to Major Stokes the light of political bias. * , dh all due respect to subjects of minor Powers, and without anv disrespect to several of my own countrymen [? who could be] appointed to serve [group undecipherable] in Treasury gendarmerie, Major Stokes is the best qualified to &lt;dve efficient service to this country m connection with my own financial mission, and 1 would be unwilling under any circumstances to appoint anyone from any Power whatever for this or any other branch of my work unless I personally was aware and satisfied with appomtes special qualifications. We know, of course, one of the greatest handicaps from which any foreigner suffers here is, as m my own case, lack of knowledge of the language 'habits &amp; iud modes of thought of the Persian people. This defect becomes e ven nSrious in the case of one called to deal impartially with large number of such men as would ^o to make up an armed force. A Swedish officer, be he ever so competent, would have to spend at least a year or more here before he could possibly be of any real assistance in this line of work, whereas necessity for getting mv gendarmeri/force organised and at work at once is urgent in the extreme. M . n inclusion permit me to say that as the fact of my tender of this post to Major Stokes is now generally known here, any withdrawal of that offer by me could could'bynomeansTrmit . 38 g by ^ P ° litiCaI co “ sid &lt;™tions ) which I GoveLntLTfajor r StoL e s’s e actpT a te aV ° Urable &lt;&gt;01lsidei ' ati - and approval of] [ 730 - 107 ]■I i$SU- CONFIDENTIAL. .^oUHLc' teJULiaul 7“ /Cl Sir O. Buchanan to Sir Edward Grey .—{Received July 11, 10 p.m.) St. Petersburgh, Juhj 11, 1911, 2 p.m. (No. 148.) (3? YOUR telegram No. 327 [ ] pointed out that it might be difficult to secure the right man and tW seemed eminently qualified for thp -nncu TTn'a n^n ana tnat btokes difficult to get another Swedish officer Lxcel W «phed that it would not he (Sent to Tehran.) [730—65]COXI IDENTIAI. 5P3&lt;r Siv Edward Grey to Sir G. Buchanan (St. Petersburgh). (No. 327.) f 3 $ | Foreign Office, July 10, 1911. bill Cl. BARCLAY’S telegram No. 234 [ol 7th instant : Treasury gendarmerie]. Rxplain circumstance to Russian Government, and say that this is the first we have heard of the appointment, and ask their views. [731—79](No. 234.) TRE Medjliss Medjliss, 1 General tl Ids letter conditions language, indicated, give the n financial a would be 1 that if it applicatioi I have matter soo me if you Russian cc It woi expressly t convince ]V and 1 am i we shall ge I shou heard of t apparently,( ) Immediate and The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of IL telegram , as marked the margin.CONF] (No. 234 TR Medjliss Medjliss General Ids lettei conditioi language indicatec give the financial would be that if i applicatie I ha- matter sc me if you Russian c It wc expressly convince and I am we shall f 1 sho heard of apparentb</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000058_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/195</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000058</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/195</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 3819/1911 'Persia: Major Stokes'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1911/1911</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-14T21:12:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (193 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 193; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials concerning the desire of William Morgan Shuster, Treasurer-General of the Persian Government, to appoint Major Claude Bayfield Stokes of the Indian Army as a financial assistant responsible for the organisation of a Treasury Gendarmerie. This proposal was ultimately refused due to the resistance of the Russian and British governments for its perceived contravention of the Anglo-Russian Convention of 1907, which had divided Persia into Russian and British zones of influence.The majority of the correspondence in the file is between Sir Edward Grey, Foreign Secretary; Sir George Barclay, British Ambassador to Persia; and Sir George Buchanan, British Ambassador to Russia. The file contains a limited amount of correspondence in French, including drafts of letters to be sent from the British Government to the Government of Persia. Copies of correspondence between Shuster and Barclay are also enclosed in the file.The volume includes a divider which gives the year that the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained in it arranged by year. This divider is placed at the front of the volume.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Russia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Persia, Treasurer-General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Claude Bayfield Stokes</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Anglo-Russian Entente (1907)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000058#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>