<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-06T10:14:39.176Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">© 'I Extract fromletter fron Lieut-Col. H.R.P.Dickeon, C.I.E ## dated 5th September 19P-9. *In their preeent mood the AJchwan will never submit to Bin Saud. 'heir women and cattle will come across first in thousands and then the men, if beaten in fight, stngly, as fugitives who will join their feaniliee secretly. ** Extract SKrxjbRJtfutxxfciix fromletter from Political Agent, Kuwait, No. 54G, dated 19th September 19?9. am •» 3 . As I understand things here, and the Shaikh agrees with this view, the forces in rebellion against Bin Saud rill never send their women arid camels alone axross the border, and remain fighting themselves till the last. This might be expected in the case of civilised persons but not of Bedouins * * * * * if there is going to be any crossing of the border I am convinced that it will be by all the Akkwen forces together, either as the result of immediate severe pressure or as the result of a, decisive healing in the field.Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the September 1929 jQNP I DEij TIAL . NO. TO The political Agent, Bahrain. Mem orandum . By this down mail arrives Shaihh Trad Sattam bin shaalan of the ruling house of the Anaze,Syria. It might be of interest to watch hia movements It is thought he is proceeding to Hiath. I shall be obliged for any information of a useful nature that you may obtain about him. ui Lieut-Col., political Agent, KuwaitCONFIDENTIAL. © A No 5^^ Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated tiie 27tli septemter 1929* From To Lieutenant-Colonel H.H.P*DicKson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. TJie Hon*Die the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, X have the honour to refer you to your con fidential N0.411-S dated ?th September 1929 tn which you called for my remarks &lt;fcn (a) Letter from His Excellency the High Commissioner Baghdad No.S.0.1?42 dated 5th September 1929. (b) Letter from yourself to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Colonies No.55 dated ?th Sept. 1929 (c) Letter from yourself to the Government of India NO.410-S of ?th September 1929 with enclosure No. 409-S copies of which you sent me. 2. In view of my confidential No*51/ dated 5th September on the subject which must have reached Bushire after despatch of your letter under reference, I am not ^uite sure whether anything further by way of report is required from me. In case you desire a full report of the incident from the very commence ment of the affair to its close, I should be grateful if you could telegraph the word M Report tt . As a matter of fact your despatch No.409-S of ?th September 1929 to His Excellency the High Commissioner was, if I may say so, most admirably put, and entirely voices any opinion or remarks I0 ,0 I could liave wished to put forward. It goes with out saying of course that all of us are anxious to co-operate whole heartedly with the Royal Air Force at/t all times, and I in particular shall continue to do so to the test of my power. 4. The reconnaissance misunderstanding could as far as I can see have teen avoided, if His Excellency the Hi&amp;h Commissioner or the Air Officer Commanding &lt;«- had set a telegram proposing the reconnaissance the day before i.e. on 1 st September. Even if the reconnaissance had only been decided upon the morning of the 2nd September a 'clear line' telegram to that effect, should, I submit, have been sent me, to enable me, to stop it if necessary. As it was His Excellency 1 ! telegram informing you and me of the intended move only reached us after the reconnaissance had come and gone. This left me in entire ignorance from the very start of what Baghdad was thinking about or what the aeroplanes themselves intended doing. 5. A point which may be worth bringing out here is that news of the world reaches Kuwait very slowly. We have nothing in the nature of a Reuters Service, and news of the Palestine troubles had not reached us, still less any suggestion that the Royal Air Force Baghdad had been called upon to prepare to send reinforcements. Our little world in Kuwait consists almost entirely of Desert Hews and desert happenings. In this, 1 think, we are up to date and have a better A. knowledge of local situation than other people. 6 . The Air Officer commanding had made the sug gestion that it was his duty to find out for hi-aself exactly how the situation stood on 2nd September, as from my telegram of JOth August, quoted in part by himhim, lie was entitled to view tJie situation witli anxiety. He also has suggested that the presence of 5,000 Akhwan under Faisal al Duwiah within 5 to 4 days* march of Basrah, a vital port, entitled him to know what Duwish was actually doing. My reply to this point, if I may respectfully give it, is that Kuwait, a large town of 50,000 in- habitants,was much closer to the Akhwan than Basrah, in fact only a day’s march away, and had there been the slightest cause for anxiety as to al-Duwish’s intentions, I, as His Majesty’s Government 1 s repre sentative, would have made it my duty to have let him know with the utmost possible speed. But I purposely refrained from doing this. 7. From all my previous telegrams, and reports on the subject of the possible crossing of the Kuwait frontier by the Akhwan, I do not think I suggested anywhere that the Akhwan had any hostile intentions towards 'Iraq, or Kuwait. On the contrary, I think, I brought out that the whoje anxiety of the Akhwan leaders was to come to friendly terms with us, and be allowed to cross our frontiers as friends and new allies. Their assurances in this respect had been repeatedly made, and as often reported by me. 6. That Air Reconnaissances had been frequently made early last spring as stated by the Air Officer Commanding without previous reference to the local ' Political Agent may have been the case, but 'alarums and excursions' were the order of the day and a state of war may be said to have existed with the Akhwan. At that time they had not revolted against Bin Baud's authority. I however certainly understood from my predecessor, Lieutenant Colonel More, D.S.O., that he© in the form of an oversight. Their very generous sentiments of regret at the difficulty and anxiety caus ed, cannot tut be accepted in the same spirit. The principle one stands for however remains, it is that the Political Agent on the spot must in normal times be informed of any contemplated Air Beconnaissance before hand in order that both he and the Ruler should know what is happening and further that no air action and by this is meant bombing etc., should be taken in the area over which he has political control unless he himself and the Politic al Resident in the Persian Gulf asks for it. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., political Agent, KuwaitTelegram M. From. BritAgent Jeddah. To Zusacari Kuwait. No. 196. Dated and reed. 30/9/29, 1/10/29. Addressed to Foreign Office Telegram No. 144, repeated Kuwait Baghdad, Eushire 196. is a summary main points lengthy memorandum dated Sept, C ' cc r e ^ ^ ec'. ling to British Government with reference to assurances given by H.M.G. to prevent rebels enter- ing Mesopotamia or Kuwait territory. . h Baud is now ready attack them but before doing so wishes to eliminate any cause for misunderstandings with H.M.G. First of all though he feels bound, to pay unqualified tribute to efforts of British Officials in Iraq arid Kuwait to assist him. He then describes briefly 18 cases which have occurred during last three months in order to show that assistance and encouragement is being received by rebels from Kuwait and Iraq, ano. from King Faisal himself, and that constant communi cations pass between rebels and Court Baghdad; all this is contrary undertakings of British Governments, and happens no doubt without their consent. These incidents lead to friction and bad relations all round, but their chief Importance lies in their effect on harmony relations existing with H.M.G. King then refers to 6 occaisons during last three months when Kuwait frontier has been crossed by rebels for their own purposes. In spite of promise to H.M.G. they are still taking refuge there. What will be attitude of H.M.G. if they remain in Kuwait territory and King wishes to attack them?j ® ,l *- A 2 If H.M.G. objects to this what measures will they take themselves to expel them? As regards assistance recieved from Iraq the last proposal made to rebels by King Faisal is that they should move into Iraq territory and proceed thence to Syria, Ein Saud fears this may be done clandestinely. Till XJXKX5. H.M.Cx. object force being posted near Iraq frontier to Intercept rebels and to attack them wherever they may be ? If they manage to get through to Syria may Kings forces persue them over any territory over which K.M.G. exercise Influence? Bin Saud anticipates a rush for asylum to Kuwait or Into Iraq, and wishes to persue rebels wherever they may be found in order annihilate them. Bin Saud states he has addressed communication on the subject for th Ir infomation direct to High Commissioner in Mesopotamia and ?xiEXk±Kxxx Political Resident in Persian Gulf, full translation memorandum follows by ba 0 leaving tomorrow. ii /'1 iti* € I itTelegram (,0). From - Resident, Rushire. To - Secretary of State for Colonies; Uo.44. Repeated to Simla, Baghdad, Kuwait, Jeddaii. No.9bO. Dated and received ^Otli September 19 R 9 . Addressed to the Secretary of State for Colonies IIo.44, repeated to Simla, Baghdad,. Kuwait, Jeddah 960 . Ibn Saud has addressed to me a letter dated the / 12th September just received through -Bahrain. While commends efforts of British Officials in ’Iraq., Dickson and myself he makes complaint against Shaikh of Kuwait of entertaining rebels and giving them gifts. He mentions Akhwan irruption into Kuwait limits on ^ist August ( see my despatch Ho. 92 , ^rd September) in violation of agreeing with British Government and a breach of neutrality of Kuwait. He says he has made representations to Ris Uajesty’s Government asking if he may attack rebels even if they are within Kuwait territory and awaits their opinion just as he awaits measures they take about Kuwait. He also brings a series of charges against King of Iraq, of intrigues against him. Resident.Telegram. M, From . Re sIclent Bi 5 b} lire. To Political Kuwait. No. 969. Dated and reed. 30/9/29. Addressed Secy, of State for the Colonies 43, repeated Simla Baghdad, Ti-.it, Jeddah £'J9. My immediately preoeeding tele^am. I v T ill forrar 1 . translation::; letter by earliest opportunity, but in mean time with your permission I propose reply acknowledging letter and stating Dawish and party were expelled froi Kuwait with all speed as soon as their arrival was known ( end proposed ). At instance Sheikh Kuwait I have already asked High Commissioner Baghdad to refuse facilities for entry into Kuwait of 4 of King Faisals emissarys mentioned by Bin Baud.(b ' 1 x Telegram (G.) From Political ; Kuwait, To iiesident, Bushire, No. 5 ^ 4 . Dated the ^Oth 3e£tenter iy2y. Your personal letter dated 2&gt;th September re mass \ entry rebels. Please discard first opinion given my private letter of 5th September which was sent off on spur moment and before receipt your Demi Official Ho. 425 of 10 th September. My considered views arrived at as result discussion with Sheikh and other responsible Arabs are those given in my No. 54 ^ of 19 th September. Regret confusion caused. Political 554*Telegram (C). ?rom - political, Kuwait. To - £e si dent, Busiiire. Repeated Highcoma, Baghdad. Dated 1st October lykiy. UHGEUT 1 . Nafisi has received letter from Bin Saud dated yth August saying tnat he hoRied start for Awania south of lit a via Hafar Atz either about ZQth August or first v/eek September. Letter written in angry vein declares that every aimed man- in Ilajd whether owning camel or horse ordered march with him for grand chastisement rebel. Z. IIo news direction Awazim or Luv/is'd though there is faint rumour that clash has taken place. Shaikh has reliable men watching events who v/ill report anything of importance i mediately. Addressed to Bushire repeated Baghdad.Telegram (C). prom - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Busiiire. IJo.^o. Dated 1st October lyi^y. Your yoo. Sincerely trust Biu Baud’s improper request attack rebels in Kuwait territory will be turned down at once. Political.Telegram E.C. UIPOIiTAIIl. From Aviation, BaS^cl^ct Cantonment, To political, Kuwait, Ho. A-&gt;04 Fated and received the ^nd. October i^Ey. A__^04. B/lo• Reports from various spurces indicate Ibn Uashur recently defeated by Bin Sa'ud’s forces vicinity Uadjira and rebels retreating direction Kuwait AAA Can you confirm. Aviation. Telegram E.C* From Political, Kuwait, To Aviation, BaS^ a( ^ Cautt. no. Fated the End. October IVE^. 4 0 your A-j&gt;04. Ho such news in Kuwait. Political yy^*Confidential . Ho. 488-5. of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 30th September 1929. A copy of the under-mentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for favour of ea^lv report. By Order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subje^cts. Complaints against the Shaikh of Kuwait and King Paisal of Iraq. Despatch to H.M’s. Secretary of State for the Colonies London, Ho. 61 of «feven date, with enclosure.Confidential British tesidtmey and Coneulait-censral, Busiiire, 30tla 3ssmbsr 1929, }»o. 61 . 5 vir # X have the honour to forward for the info rotation of His Uajeaty^s Covamwont a translation of a letter addressed to me and dated 8 th Rabi Ath Than! 1J546 12th Ssptcsaber 1929J whida I received by the last aail from Ba^irain, in idiielj Bin Saud makes complaints against Kuwait £«r}G Iraq, « 2* In hir, letter Bin Caud has divided his com plaints against Kuwait into six and his sosjplaints against the King of Iraq into nine paragraphs* 1 will deal with these as far as possible seriatim * Corajlainat ag ai nst th e haihh ofjvi &lt;w u.i t. (1} This refers to the visit paid to Kuwait by ^arhan Ibn 1 a&amp;iiur at the beginning of .ay* The Shaikh of Kuwait visited him at Jahra but subsequently, at me instance of the ’olitioai Agent, ordered hixa to quit Kuwait territory* He complied on 14th May. 1 hfcve no inforciation as’to tiie «aiount purchased, but 1 will enquire from the Political Agent at uwait4 The last oom- raunication I sent to you on the subject was ©y despatch Ho* 24, dated Ute 28th May 1929. 4 (2J(S) I have no inforcmtion. (3) I haV« no infonaation* (4J Azaiyiz son of i^aisal bln J)awi 8 h accompanied by a hundred, men mounted on canc lB* arriv ed within ten miles of huwait about the but at the inetance of Colonel hickson the Shaikh refused the request* The meuoa^e was conveyed to Azaiyiz by Abdulla bin Jabir, Commander of the Kuwait forces. tzaiyiz and his Arabs left Kuwait territory on the 30th June. Before his departure Colonel Dickson had An interview with ^tisal bin nhibian, wiio was bin Dawish’a ri^it-liand man. The last eoMiiunication made you on this subject wafi my letter «o. 30 of the 2 nd July 1929. vicinity of Kuwait on Wednesday # the i7th July* but the Ohaijch refused t© allow them to enter the town. They were interviewed by Colonel lickson. who gave them clearly to understand His ‘ajesty*a Government could not treat with mn in rebellicku the orders that they were to receive no supplies from Kuwait. A copy of the ‘oliticol Agent at -uwait 1 s report on this subject was sent to you under my despatch bo. 39 of bth August 1929. ( 6 ) In thie connection please see Colonel Dickson's 2&lt; 7 th J. ne. He requested pe rmission for the rebels to encamp in Kuwait territory, (&amp;) i zam bin Hithlain and Al 'Juqua arrived in the against a friendly ruler, ana reiteratedMo. 466 of tie 12th August 1929, copy enclosed. The i^haikh of Kuwait appears to have received the ttiinouncenent of Faisal bin Danish's success in a note addresned to hiia by that individual him- self. I have already wired to you under my Mo• 40 of 8 th September 1929 to ash pcrmieaion to inform Bin fhaud that the insurgents who entered Kuwait territory on the 31st August were speedily compelled to leave • 3 e With regard to the truth of the allegations of intrigues against King Faisal, the High Commissioner at Baghdad is in a better position to judge; but 1 will taxe them seratim giving all the information on record in this lesideney. (1) In his telegram ho. 368 of 1st June, copy of which was sent 4»o you, the Political Agent at Kuwait reported the arrival of Ubaid. His movements appear to be as follows: Arrived in Kuwait on the 30th hay with le tiers from half al Hindi ibn Huraaid (his cousin and ex-Chief of tne Ataibah, who fled from najd about three years ago, and has since been living in Baghdad and working for King Faisal;, to Ibn Hashur and naif ibn Hithlain. He went to ^afrah, delivered the letters whieh were said to contain an offer from Half ibn Huuaaid to support the rebels against Ibn 3aud, am returned to Kuwait on 1st June with replies to naif ibn Huiaaid4 \ ( 2 ) (3) (4) Hu&amp;aid, and also a letter from Ibn Mae bur and Ibn Hlthlain to King i-'ai sal, requesting permlesion to enter Iraq territory if attaeJted by Ibn Baud. Ubald Ibn Humald arrived in Hasrah on 2nd June and proceeded to Baghdad by train the earie nijjlit. Ali abu fShuwairibat arrived in Kuwait from Baghdad on I at July and stayed with •Jiaikh Ahmad. on 2nd July he vioited aorce of the Ranhalyidah at Biiaaah (about tight miles south of Kuwait), returning to Kuwait the bsuit day, left Kuwait on the 6 th July and proceeded to afrah, returning on bth July. He left Kuwait for Baghdad on 17th July and it ie be lieved that his intention was to collect his family there and return to Kuwait an the nee proceed to join the rebels. He was reported to have gone to Baghdad at the end of August to invoke the High Commissioner 1 s assistance through the mediation of King ?aisal. It was uddet that hr possessed tfeieal bin Dawi 8 h*s new signet rifig. Muliammed al Khuahri arrived in Kuwait on Bth July. He aecumi^irded Ubaid bin Humaid on the 17th July. All abu Bhuwalribat left Kuwait for Ba^inad 17th July. (3) Shuaifan abu Hhajrah aecompanied by three Ajmanis arrived in Kuwait on 15th July company with Mutrak ibn Hajnah who had four companions from the Ataibah tribe. Both• 5 • \ Both Bhuaifari and Mu Irak are refugees from Ji&amp;jd niio iui'we been living in Baghdad for the past three /ears. It was suppossd that they intended to join the rebels but bcth were in Kuwait up to the Uhth July. rhe Shaikh of Kuwait has recently xequoated tiiat the High Comiaitttiioiier at Baghdad should deny Mutrak tin Hajnuh,jU.i abu nimwairibat, Id al Dahalnah arm 00 ae otlfiers all fac ilities to visit uwait 0 ae ht sas,&lt; ct b the» of intrigues. All ibn Khalid abu liiuwairibat 9 a dietani rel^ ive of Mi abu ^huwairibat, arrived in Kwwait on 15th July with two raen of the Braih-Kut«ir. He was in Kuwait up to 26th July# X have no in formation regarding Hurhan al Jabali and the other men mentioned, ano (7). At the end of August Colonel DicksoA reported his suspicion that King Faisal was intriguing with Khan Bahadur Mulla Saleh, Private Secretary to the Hhaikh of Kuwdit. *rhe go-between was said to be Abdulla al iUsfir. the High Com- ttlBBioner at Baghdad was inforaed under my Mm telegram Ho. 847 of 27th August. Abdulla al uisfir is known in Kuwo,^* as King ‘miftaitB Confidential Ataibah Secretary. He is in regular telegraphic communication with an agent named tt .iahoined bin Ibrahim' which Colonel ickson due treats is a pseudonym for rjwn Bahadur Kulla alek. In the middle of August the ShaihA •f Kuwait complained to Colonel Dicksow of6 of King F&amp;ieal’B intrigues. Abdul Rohimn H usaibi iu a pearl mcrabunt belonging to the well-known Bahrain family. lie Yi sited Kuwait by Imperial Airways aeroplane and eubeequent- ly continued his journey to Bahrain by naka motor dhow. ( 8 ) 1 have no information. (9) It is possible that interested messengero may give out stories of help expected from Great Britain. Canards of this sort are frequent in Arabia. the -tolitieal Agent at Kuwait for report as my informa not fail to write a further despatch setting out he facts in greater detail. Government of India, His K&gt; eeilency the Higii Commissionc for Iraq and the British Agent add Consul at Jeddah. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your moat obedient, humble servant, (Signed) C.C.J. Barrett. Polltiaal Resident in the i . 4 1 am sending a copy of Bin Baud's letter to tion ia incomplete. On receipt of hie reply 1 will A copy of this despatch is being sent to tiu0 T* Translation of a letter No. 3/147, dated 8 Katoi ath- -Ttaani 1348 ( 12th September 1929) from H.M. the King of the Hejaz and of Nejd to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian aulf. Verily, it must have reached you that the British Government undertook to us to prevent the criminals from taking refuge in Kuwait and Irag, and to! prevent their traffic and to prevent all sorts of ass- -istance reaching them from the neighbouring towns, and we do not doubt that the British Government ordered all its officers to stand guarding that undertaking. ;nd we mention with commendation your efforts specially and the efforts of Mr. Dickson, which are thanked in this respect, just as we mention with commendation the attitude of all British officials within Iraq boundar- -ies. But we have received some news of occurrences in Iraq and Kuwait which we aesire to mention to Your Honour and in them you will see that these actions were against what the British Government undertook to /'“N us. Here, below, is a brief summary of these news : - 1. In the end of Dhil Hajjeh and beginning of Moharram (June) riding parties of the Ajman and Ibn Mashur and those with them commenced to reach Kuwait and to put up as guests of Ibn Subah and they purchased all they could find in arms and cartridges and on the * same date Ibn iiubah wrote to their headmen ( sending ) presents of rice and dates, and gave thorn about 6,000 dollars. 2. on the same date Ibn Mashur and A1 \jiaan purchased 20 mares from Kuwait, 10 of which were pur- -chased from Subah A1 Nasir. Orders were given and they were sold to them. 3. In the beginning of Mohamram (June) a troop proceeded to Ibn subah by orders of sahman. It consisted2 consisted of 60 men and put up at Adailiyah. Abdullah 1 Jahir mrilet out to them, entertained their deputation and the party then returned to Wafrah. 4. In the middle of Moharram autxMiocxxfcrHHp Abdul Aziz ad-Dawish arrived at Malah and sent Ibn ohiblan, who was with him, to Kuwait, Ibn Subah sent to the son of Dawish a present of 1000 dollars. 5. In Safar, while Abdur Kahraan al Qusaibi was in Kuwait, he saw,after A*sar prayers, Half al Fakiiam with Milal at llutairi. ( /aid it is known that Kaif al fakham is the person who raided Kuwait during the Jiblah affair and robbed Kuwait subjects of property, and it is the same person whom the British Government had suspected of being the cause of the murder of a wireless official of a British aeroplane). 6 . In the middle of Habi al Awal (August) Ad- -Dawish, after raiding al ^aiyah, sent filial and Al ohahri to Kuwait to give the good news of what had 'tfT been accomplished by Ad Dawish at qaiyah. These two persons are Ibn Subah's men and they accompanied Ad Dawish in his depredations and so did some persons who left Ad Dawish with the intention of robbery and theft. They were sent to take the good news to Kuwait and all those who arrived at Kuwait were rewarded generously. These actions took place in Kuwait in the past, and as you see they are z.gdinst the agreement which the British Government mace, and also iBjekxxx against the rules between two friendly countries. And the severest breach of all that happened was the camping of the jman and the coming of 150 tents of them who camped from Shamiyah to al Kintas and Abu Halifah at Shuaibah to Araifjan, and others camped from Shamiyah to al Naq/arah to al Qasur and Al Suliaman, and the Al llashidah camped near Subaihiyah, and3 and the A.1 Safran oamped at Araifajan. On the 25th Rabix al Awal Ad Danish and those with him from the Rutair camped near Subaihiyah. The camping of these in the boundaries of Kuwait , as you see, is a vifclat- -ion of the agreement of the British Government, and a breach of the neutrality of Kuwait. And at this Juncture we find difficulties for us in leaving them to transgress the said limits and we therefore have represented to the British Government asking whether they had any objection to our attacking the rebels even if they be within the boundaries of Kuwait. ¥« e await the opinion of the British Govern: ent, just as we await the measures she will take about Kuwait in respect of this situation. In this connection we see it useful to relate to Your Honour what was done by the King of Iraq at this juncture, which increased trouble and forced us to put away some of those persons who were deceived by the promises of the King and had entered inside our country -A by trick, as we ordered complete annihilation of those who are* evil doers. Praise be to 6 od, verily the cleaning of the interior of the Nejd country has been completed. Here below is a brief account of what we verified from the news of the interference of King Faisal and of his deeds. 1. Cn the 5th Moharram 1343 (12th June) Obeid bin Faisal bin Humaid, deputed by King Faisal, left Baghdad for Kuwait. He stayed in Kuwait for some time in close touch with the rebels. He put up in their residences for several days and theji returned to Iraq, where he saw King Faisal and reported to him the result of his mission. On his return he carried letters from the rebels to the King. 2. In Safar (July) oteid bin Faisal bin Humaid returnedrtrjsi 4 returned from Baghdad, having received money from King Faisal. He arrived in Kuwait and purchased four camels and a tent to go out with it in company of al Dhainah. 3. On the 20th Moharram (27th July) after seeing King Faisal, All hu Shuwairahat and liuhammad al Khideri left Baghdad for Kuwait in order to meet ad-Dawish, Ibn Shahur and Ibn Hithlain. 4. On the 14th hafar (21st July) Ali Ahu Shuw- -airbat returned to Baghdad with letters for King Faisal and he reported that he reached Kuwait and accompanied Muhammad al Khidheri till he met ad Bawish. O’hen both returned to Kuwait and Khidheri purchased a she camel and returned with it to ad Dawish. Abu Shuwairibat however returned to Baghdad with letters for King Faisal and reported to him the result of his efforts. 5. In the end of Moharram, Shuaifan Abu Shajrah, Mutrak bin Hajnah, Burhan al Jabali, Ali bin Abdullah, laid Abu Ghuwairabat and Id al Masud al Dahainah left Baghdad for Kuwait. They interviewed Ad Dawish, Ibn Kashur and Ad Dahainah. These persons constantly move between Baghdad and Kuwait and the rebels and this is well known to all the people. 6 . on the-17th 3 afar (24th July) .uajaa Ibn 3 hahin left Baghdad for Kuwait and with him was Hamud al Kharaash, a relation of Abdullah bin lisfar (guests of King Faisal) and with them 6 mares, which they sent to the rebels. 7. While passing through Kuwait Abdul Rahman al , v usaibi learnt from reliable sourcos that B mares have arrived at Kuwait by the hand of a follower of Ahdullah al Misfar and these mares are intended for despatch to the rebels. And Al ^usaibi also learnet from trustworthy sources that formerly some other things were5 r% were sent from Iraq for the rebels. And al Qusaihi came to know from a reliable official source that Abu Shuwairabat and ibn Humaid were despatched by King Faisal, but Mr# Dickson did all possible to prevent them from carrying out their scheme. 8 . Shukhair Ibn Tuwalah, who stays at oafwan, is in constant communication with the rebels ana he carries their news to the Court at Baghdad and he acts as an ambassador between King Faisal and the rebels. He goes to Baghdad twice or thrice a month. 9. the messengers encouraged by King Faisal to ad Dawish and Ibn Fashur and al Ajman never cease com- -ing and going and they inform them that King Faisal says that the British Government will help them when it sees from them active war operations against Ibn Baud. v.e have related to you these news from Iraq so that Your Honour may know it, and what we await from Your Honour are decided and firm measures in Kuwait territory, and in the end accept our best respects. Sealed. ABDUL AZIZ. Translators note . All parentheses except the onw marked with an asterisk are His Majesty’s.61/14 eiegram acretary of Jtato lor /olonias, Loudon# To Political Keoldent# Bushira# atod 4ti» reed bth ctc er 192^# l ay-, ria nt, .ubjaot to your via^a and thooe of tuo Acting nigb OotTjffiissionor for Iraq, wfco is aloo being consulted, it is proposed to send to ?ritisB Agent Jeddah in reply to his baiegrnn Ho 144 of hepte^ber 50th telegi a.a in following terms, begins# {Lore insert text of my telegram limed lately foil -wing) ^nds. Please telegraph to me whetLor you concur, repeating to Acting High lomaisaianer imgitdad. I see no objection to y^ur returning to I’^n ,aud the interim reply suggested in yoi;r toiegraM Ho 46 of 30th 3eptember# Iveference is to my telegram of 2 na ctuber ecretary of 3tate for folmies# Copy by post to : The Political Agent at (Signed) C.C.J. .Barrett, political Resident in the Persian Culf Attested: for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. c (£ Bushire, J ^October 1929.** 1 ^ — v Telegram o ( / . / Fro^ ^ Secretary of ^tato for tkie Coiftniesy London +-f &lt;a,»Y**/'er &lt;rr T To UttniHittCRiii) 9ltf ni JnsfitEsfl I oWil-j'I Jated 4th (roccivea bthj dotober U£9 # #T Political Heoldeut iiuahlre »*v+eu.t^A lASPOKTAhT, Following ia text Referred to in ay immediately preceding telegram be^itie &gt; &gt; ot* ahottlcL inform lUn daucT in reply to • 1 j i'D Hi-: 13TO t J r f3DI3z5. nia memorandum of 14th September that hie da^eot^^ Gorermaeiit gladly agree to hi^poating a force near ♦iraqian frontier to intercept rebel*. They waila further 'i'-'t-kov ttsC. weicome any pfeeama# wlitoh he uh.y oe prepared to make for the establiehment of close liaison on the frontier ana suggest he should designate emissaries to keep local frontier authorities in *lraq ana Kuwait informed of tlie movements oi his troops a*a of rebels. His Majesty's Government regret, however, that they cannot reconoider their previous decision ^BSBSSVflRssewcrobsiiitj oi ei tner ir^i+tior . ^n &gt;oud'o forces. As Ibn daua has already been assured uiai, axl possible steps will be ta^en to prevent use of 'Jraq ^wait as a refuge lay Akhwan rebels aad local Military authorities have been authorised if necessary to taxe drastic action to achieve this object* ibn caud will however himself realise if reoeis should succeed in eitner crossing tne frontier's; with their woman siid children or in effecting JuneU-n with latter in Iraqian or Kuwait territory local military authorities may oe placed in t»ost era ar/hoei;^ pcoitiai, 1118 Government therefore hope Ibn ,nua va _ ^ able to ta^e elieetive measures to prevent ouch a contin gency arising.' ends.Confiden tial. © Ho. 502-3. of 1929. British Residency and. Consulate-fTeneral Bushire, the 10th October 1929. From - The Hon’hie the Political Resident Mem oran dun . T forward herewith a copy of a telegran from the Jligh Commissioner for Iraq to the Colonial Office, llo. 350, dated the 6 th October 1929, for your information. 2. King Paisal strongly resented Shaikh Ahmad’s references to his intrigues with the rebels, which he described verbally as an impertinence. In order to avoid possible recrimination between Kuwait and Iraq 1 agreed to the elimination of the Shaikh’s remarks from the official letter addressed to the Prime Minister of Iraq provided the action the Shaikh wanted is taken. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.or Fra«i :&gt;ov.rn*ent win be tole«jraph«i bj ne aa UQO n a8 : obtain It. The opinion of ling felsal, whleh la anarea oy Abdullah whoa i net at wan, and alao, 1 undaratand ftroa the lolitloal resident In the Persian Oulf b. the haUh of^oweit, Is that the authority of loaiaue is on point or oollapso. Xhe personal attitude of King Faisal la that, apart froi his own faallngs, this would in faot oeat suit the intareets of Irag. he argues that an effective cnJ &gt;n oi the fanatical tribes of central Arabia can only be MtataiMu by the pel lay oi' oonataiii, ahgrossl &gt;n agale nolgatjourlng states. If disunited, the tribe.; w .ulu expend tfcoir energies on local disputes and the frontier of Iraq, 04 by VS Hi Jfcaamr, «e&lt; King Faisal, in doforonoe to T;ia i-aucsty^s Oovemaant, la how over prepared to recall hie agents and to maintain a scrupulously o or eat atUtude in aoeorcanoe wlti. the policy of nta ^ajeaty'a Oovamwent t &gt; I bn baud. aefere-.-os Is to y.,ur talegraa *!o 23 .&gt; of 4 th ctoDur • HlgllQOMeW t +3 10. £47 timber ir, In n*y telegram ] o. 130 of the loth* instant I to ached briefly on the conditions in the hejaz, and I mentioned then that the political and financial situation was becoming steadily v/orse* £. In Yiew of recent and possible developements it may be of interest if 1 amplify the information contained in my telegram, and give a resume of the main features of the situation as it is to-day and as it appears to Jedda and Mecca opinion with whom 1 am in touch* 3 * £ver since ieisal ed howeiah threw off the %»il e* iJLm dOw*t£ttl allegiance and declared himself openly in rebelion against Ibn hand the Government has had to deal with a growing restiveness and lawlessness among the tribes, which has vented itself in incidents of major or minor importance and which has now brought the Government face to face with a critical situation resembling in many ways the position at the beginning of the Great #ar wnou tne liej** was menaced by the revival of tne militant Wahabi power to which it eventually succumbed* 4 * fheee is a general feeling abroad now in Jedoa and 4 keooa among the better informed classes, whether sym:&gt;athetlc or hostile to the present regime, that the fate of the Heiaa; and of irabia in general may at any time His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs*4* time within the next few months be staked upon the issue o. a deoisive battle between Xbn Saud and the rebel forces. 1‘here does in faot seem little doubt that the King »s position in rabia is shortly to be put to a searching test. Openly, every confidence is professed in the result. In private one observes an undercurrent of anxiety, an anxiety which, xed by the successive rumours of gossip mongers, sees its justification in the exceptional measures taken by ibn Saud to provide for the coming conflict, houbts are expressed as to his ability in certain eventualities to control the situation in the interior; and such eventualities might result for instance from a succession of ooups, possibly of snail importance in themselves, in which the xikhwan were victorious. Their prestige is such that, given a reasonably successful start, they are li ely to attract active sympathy and cooperation from all sides. ^ would be futile to attempt a comparison between the strength of the rival forces. vary almost from tray to day ana they would fluctuate in aocoruance with the varying or tunes of the campaign, recording to the local representative of the minister of I loanee, Ibn ^aud has strong detachments based on hail, Tebujc, me ina and itiyadh. ills position is a strong one. He has all the material, if not the moral advantages on his side, and above all he has relative fraedom o movement and time to prepare for a cam; aign. whatever the risks may be, therefore, his forces have every chance of success, provided that he himself survives, on the other side the rebels are also believed to be well armed but one may infer from the deputations and appeals to the oheixh of Koweit and their anxiety to avail themselves of the howeit grazing grounds that they are severely handicapped b„ la ox of supplies, i^ume. icaluy also theyJiey mast be at a great disadvantage* chief weakness of th® AJuag T s position lies in the ijuierior ,«iarai® of his arir^ as compared with the fa**atio enthosiasua and desperate courage of the Aihwan* and in the gtnexai uupwpuisrity of his role. *. s a reeait of the latter, it is generalxy beiieved that except in ,,©^4 proper the aa^ority of the tribes would rise at once if ther were any reasonable hope of throwing off his yoice. ^dded to this is the fact that he is unable to rely on a large number of troops who have been emailed in the south by attractive promises and by enforced levies, s m ‘ \ who have not their heart in the fight; they include for instance a number of «rabs of the i*t&amp;ib&amp;h tribe of which several sections are in open defection, ^any of these troop* have been sent to -adina and thence drafted to other bases, while some seven thousand are distributed at different posts between Taif and .iSnaiiya to provide against surprises. ■* ijl itself, to judge from the Eualu number of tribal ohisfs of importance who are reported to b© with him at ^iyadh, h© does not appear to have succeeded in rallying the tribes to his side and has had to fill his ranita largely with townsmen, 7. another w©axn«s* is the fact that the defection of the ihhwan has to a large extent ui©ore lied him among the more fanatical and influential elements of hie own following. People li*© ^bdulla bin Kasean, a deeoendant of ibdul »iahab, who wa« chiefly reaponeible for the recent dismissal of the imams at neeoa and Medina, *&gt;bdulla bin dial hid until last year Grand „adl of neooa, ^lohamuted bin xvli f furly who resigned the same post a few monthe ago, are oom ©iily believed to favour th© Ahhwan cause, while Abdul Latif f another descendant of ibdul V^ahab and one of the must influential Ulemas at Riyadh is reported to nave Riy*^ ® irUl ^^initei^ ever to ?eiaalW * 0 9 &amp; Doueish.* Dm Saud is bggiiiiiitt&amp; to Oe re^ardod by these tanatiOE as no Xon^or true to Vahabl tenets and as Dein&amp; himseif now no better then an infidel. Their support of him is in any case likely to be lukewarm only ae they theaieelyes would stand to lose by any diminution of the fanatical kkhwans Influence • 6 * Si^ns and incidents are not wanting to alarm the Inhabitants of Jedda and ^isoca. Following on the recent ecu* of Feisal ed Dowel eh at jay* oame the news l confirmed from various sources, of the i&amp;iir Saud T s narrow escape from capture on his way to Easa t ?/hen fourteen out of seventeen cars are said to have been taken and their occupants JdUUed. This was followed by the defection of the Beni Aau of the lejdi Harb 9 a fact which is symptomatic of the unhealthy condition of the regions around Me dim and Henakiya arid further north. The situation in the Northern Hejas has its repercussion in the south in i;he growing truculence of the Itaioah as shown by acts of agression which have lately been committed by them. X may refer again to the attacks on the two caravans on the Mecca- X*JLf road where perfect security was thought to exist, and X may mention the arrest of kbdulla bin Hassan whose great religious prestige was e peated to guarantee him a safe passage from - 10 oca to Riyadh whither he was being sent with gold and with arms and ammunition. He was apparently allowed by the Ataib&amp;h to proceed after giving the most solemn assurances that he would secure the release of their chief, Bin Bujad, but from all accountsaccount b the gold, anas and amanmitlon were retained by the At&amp;lbah. It is now praotioally established that the punitive expedition sent against them under the well known Wahabi leader Khalid bin lowai has been checked or defeated and Khalid himself is believed to have withdrawn to Khuroa, whither reinforcements have been sent, H* It will not be an easy task to bring the Maibah to heel, Naturally turbulent, connected by blood relationship with the lahraf and akin also to the recalcitrant 24utair, they have latterly become impatient over the continued detention of Sin Bujad in Riyadh, fhe task will be made no easier by the fact, if it proves to be 'true that the tribes around furaba and further south into lair, eg,, the Beni dhahran, have become disaffected. 12• In view of the state of affairs as described above, it is not to be wondered at that the morale of the local hejazl is shaken, Comrnmio&amp;tion with the north is difficult and takes considerable time, humours of defeats are exaggerated and good news, meagre as it is, is received with a scepticism born of many diappointments. The black side of things therefore looms large before his anxious eyes and he derives little comfort from a situation which, for all its brighter aspects, is wrapped in uncertainty. To add to his gloom the cost of all such commodities as are normally purchased from the interior, e,g,, mutton and butter, has risen considerably and is still rising. The cost of mutton for instance is doubled.ohannftls and i‘incus Its way into tkw pooi^ota o£ the hi^hax Goyecrnwant oiiioiaiB and ot tn* f^isal itaaif t Kdile tne sums that are saut to Hiyadh are from all aocoonta expended by the in true royal laakion* 1 for&amp; oi taxation has been ixetruducea among the tribes around faii by which eaoh tribe is called upon to supply a fixed number of men and camels for the arms, failing which a fine of eight pounds per camel and thirteen pounus for eaoh fighting man short Is of the number/inflicted# This tax is causing widespread diteOuntent# Fln^juiy there is a report from Mecca to the effecttthat 4 .uuCL 8 held on trust on account of deceased pei'sons* estates are, aesplt the injunctions of the Horan, being used by the Government for its own neeas# lb# Mae fact is that the Government cannot afford the maintenanoe of a large military establishment which oiroimstanoes have forced upon it; nor can it looic for relief until the present situation is liquioated, and what now forma a large standing army Judged by Arabian stanoarus, is effectively reduced# lb# i am senuing a copy of tills despatch to His Majesty T e High Commissioners for Mgypt, Ir&amp;&lt;p and Palestine, the Governor General of the Sudan, the Political Eesident, Aden, the Political Resident in the Pei'si an Gulf, the Political Agent at no welt and the Senior Haval Officer, Red Sea Sloops# I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Tour most obedient, huwole Servant, ISi’.h# uCni,#HIS Majesty’s presents his compliments £Lct L'L-&lt;z c. ^enti crzsts^c^s and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. Bri iish.. .&amp;0. .£ 19..^. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. t C- C- 7—i Telegram (C). prom - political, Kuwait. To - ^Resident, Busliire. Repeated Lo Highcoma, Baghdad; Special, Basrah.. No.^57. Dated 0th October 1^2^. Though situation i: i very obscure, following h;.s been brought in hy man considered reliable who left portion are at Injair,southern at IJaairiyeh, with latter are ning's troops under nohamed al Suhaili. Total strength ^ 000 . Ashwan with Braih at Hamudth ibn Hathlain with Ajman at Rakba 7 miles North East of Injair - Duwish with liutair at Bajsa 12 miles South ast of injair from where he has cut off all .communications between Northern and Southern Awazim. • forces at Hafar Atz. Cl?) No engagement of any sort has so far taken place between opposing forces. ( 6 ) !Iy view with which Shaikh agrees is that everything i)°ints to fact that Duwish is manoeuvering to force Awazim to surrender or retire South and is general- # ly carrying out plan outlined in my despatch dated 24th September No.24b. Duwish’s camp 2 Bays ago. (l) Awazim are devided into two forces northern (2) Disposition insurgents as follows - Ibn No member of Bing’s family with Awazim. [A-) No sign of any concentration Bin gaud's Addressed to Bnshire repeated to Baghdad and Special, Basrah. Political.Telegram C CJ. From - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Ilighcoma, Baghdad; special, Basrah. Ho. do nated 5tn October iy^y» m uy No. 55 */. A Rashidi who states he arrived this morning from Duwish 1 s camp reports that on Sunday Awazim from Naairiyeh affected junction with Awazim at Injair and were attacked, by insurgents. In action that resulted Llutair were successful and drove back Bin Saud’s regular troops as far as camp where they captured and drove off 1 ^ st cX LxC * 11 ^ pardEMr^iif-Hrly all Awazim - 00111013 . Ajman on other flank wehe repulsed by Awazim who pursued vigourously till driven back tjy victorious M u tair. Both sides then returned to respective camps which they now hold. Shaikh, who does not know man, considers news should be received with considerable caution prefers await report of his own messenger who he expects hourly. Addressed bo Bushire repeated to Baghdad and. Special Basrah. i ca -bTelegram. M. From Britagent Jeddah To. Zusacari Kuwait. No. 203 Dated 8/10/29 reed. 9/10/29. Addressed to Foreign Office 148 repeated Tufrait, Bushi- t, Oovt. of India, Jerue: .len, Baghdad 2 Cg. Cc pies by post to Cairo Aden. I understand as a result trouble with Ataibah more effective measures are being taken to project Mecca- Riadh road by concentrations at different points. Reasonable security now appears exist in day time for passage of convoys. King himself is reported to be at Shaara with a large force. From all accounts Khalid's defeat was more in nature of a check. Reinforcements were sent from Taif but no decisive action seems to have taken place. BritAgent 14808@ 'ft Telegram (c). From - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Ilighcoma, Baghdad, Special, ^asrah. 110 .^ 02 . Dated 9^ October ly^y. izy Wl. Story of 'battle given by Tlashidi yesterday con firmed by Shaikh’s messenger who ax-rived this morning as well as by Uutair courier who has just brought letter of congratulations from Duwish himself to Shaikh. From letter and messengers report battle took place at dawn Saturday !?th October and ended in signal victory for Akhwan. This was mainly due to a heavy and well sustained onslaught of the mutair from the north after Duwish’s plan had nearly been wrecked by the Ajman attacking prematurely from the Fast. The latter who had placed themselves on the Awazim’s sf-rite flank overnight attempted to rush their opponents at 4 . a.m. Though successful at first tiiey were driven back and pursued vigorously almost to their camp. The situation was saved by a charge of all the Ajman horsemen under Il^sam al Hathlain who shattered their counter attack and drove it back he himself being killed in the process. % It was at this moment that the main attack of the xlutair commenced which ended in the-Awazim main position and camp being occupied. Al Suhelli Bin Gaud’s commander was killed. All Av/azim camels were taken and Bin Gaud’s Hathar troops with their allies Bani Hajir and 3 aji hi ia i 4 id are stated to have been destroyed almost to a man. The messenger left as Duwish was preparing deal i with remnants Av/azim who were attempting to rally to the south. Losses Ajman and Awazim reported very heavy those of ilutair slight. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad and Gpe- Basrali. political.'ft Telegram (C). From - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. * Repeated to Higncoma, -Baghdad; NO. 564. hated 10th October 1 ^ 29 . Hy 5 t&gt; 2 . No further nev/s that can be called reliable received. Bedouin gossip has it that Awazim have rallied vicinity Injair and that another engagement is imminent. This I think probably true. Awazim have certainly lost heavily in camels but Akhwan have expended ammunition they cannot replace. Uohomed ai shx Suhalli reported killed by Ali Shuwairibat. Addressed to hushire repeated to Baghdad and Special Basrah. Special, Basrah. Political. 1&amp; w COafflELj'i’lAL. # political Agency, Kuwait. r / c Dated tiie loth October 1929 . Prom Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon*tie the Political Resident in the Persian flulf, Bushire. 6666666 BATTLE OP IHJAIR. Sir, In continuation of my telegrams K 0 . 557 , No. ST# and No.JbJLof 6 th and 10th October respectively, I have the honour to send you fuller details of the above engagement between the forces of Bin Saud under Mo- homed al Suhalli and the insurgents under Paisal al Duwish at Injair in North hassa. Details of the fight have been obtained from the following sources (a) Letter from al Duwish to Shaikh Ahmad. (b) The messenger of al-Duwish who though not allowed to enter Kuwait was interviewed by Shaikh Ahmad in person and is considered reliable. (c) A reliable AJ 21 * 111 Kuwait sent by Shaikh Ahmad to watch events. (d) A man of the Reshaida tribe who arrived at Jahra with some looted Awazim camels and gave an intelligent account of the action. No doubt fuller details will be fortcoming later, but I do not think they will affect the general story, though they may modify details.0 ) j 2* it would appear that on Jpriday 4th October the Awazim southern force, witn which were Bih Baud’s regular troops (Sarriya) and other■allies such as Bani Hajir and Bani Khalid under the comzaand of Mo- homed bin suhalli, moved up from Kaairiyeh and affected a junction with their advanced troops at Injair (pro nounced Ingair) 5 . Faisal al-Buwish who UP to then had been averse to risking everything on a battle, and was out rather to manoeuvre the Awazim into retiring, suddenly decided to attack. 4. Saturday at dawn was fixed for this and on Friday evening he moved the Ajman under Hzam al- Hithlain and Khalid al Mohomed close in on the right flank of the Awazim (see sketch map attached). The Hutair forces, including the Ilwa, the Braih under Ibn Ashwan, and detachments of Ibn Mashur and al— Bufudi, he concentrated immediately to the north of th&lt; Awazim camp. His orders were that as the sun rose the A. jman should commence the attack from the East, and when well engaged, he with the whole ^utair would deliver the main attack. The ^itair mounted troops and the Ajman ditto were to work round the enemy’s left flank and right rear respectively and charge home as they saw opportunity. 6 c At about 4 a.m. the Ajman against order precipitated matters by attempting to rush the enemy’s right wing, and ware at first entirely success ful, pushing in the darkness right into the heart of the Awazim camp and cutting up all who opposed them. Reinforcements of Awazim and Bani Khalid however coming up counter attacked and drove the Ajnian sackoack vfith. lossos and pursued tiiem right tack to their camp a 1000 jnsrds away where hand to hand fighting continued. 7. At the first streak of d^wn Hzam al Hathlain with the Adman mounted contingent relieved the situatio] by coming up and delivering wk a charge on the attack ing Awazim and 3ani Khalid, and forced them to retire in disorder. In this charge Shaikh Hzam was killed, his place being taken by Khalid al Mohomed (ZebShhman). 0. At this moment al-Duwish who had till then not moved, delivered his main onslaught with all his forces, on the Awazim left and centre,where were posted Bin Saud»s Hathar troops, the Bani Hajir and main body of the Awazim (ahl al Bayir as opposed to the ahl al Ghanam who were opposing Ajman). Al-Duwish's attack was immediately successful, and those opposed to him are reported to have been almost wiped out. huring this attack the Mutair mounted troops fell upon the Awazim rear where the tents and camels were inextri cably mixed Up and rounding up the latter drove them off the field. The fight ended by huwiah planting his standard in the heart of the Awazim camp in front of al-Suhall^s tent, the survivors of the Awazim retreating Southward to the camp of the Awazim ahl al Ghanam situate about 1500 yards South of their main camp. Here they reformed, and opened a long range fire on the Mutair and Ajman in occupation of their main camp. 9* At this stage, the whole of the Mutair and Ajman became scattered all over the place in search of loot, and it was a case of every man for himself. Duwish therefore finding he had no concentrated body to continue the fight and pursue the Awazim who werewere obviously rallying, decided to move back to liis camp. This apparently both his force and the Ajman did | leaving nothing in the main Awazim camp standing, seeing the day lost, is reported to have ridden away with 4 men, and al-Duwish is said to have remarked that he should be let alone so as to convey the news to his master. Ali al-shuaribat (recently of Baghdad) how ever pursued with a small body of horsemen and is said to nave caught him up and killed him with his own hand. 11. The probable strength of the forces engaged are as follows:- Awazim 2000 to 2500; Akhwan 2200. Losses of the ifutair 20 killed (reported by al-Duwish himself) while those of the Awazim including allies and the Ajman were probably much heavier. They could not have had less than 50 killed in each case. 12. It seems pretty clear that the Awazim lost practically all their camels numbering at least 2000 , but the Akhwan on the other hand expended much am munition which they cannot replace. 30 one may say that as far as gains and losses go the honours mre even unless the Akhw _ aunition in the camp they looted. This is a possibility as the Awazim are re ported to have had a very full supply of British .202 S. A* A. come in and one does not know how far the Awazim have been able to rally their forces, or whether al-Duwish has attacked them again or drawn off. Bedouin gossip or worth carrying off. 10. Mohomed al-suhalli Bin Saud’s commander At the moment of writing no further news has has it that the Awazim have rallied and tnat these will be another fight. I am personally inclined to think tnis is true but prefer to await further news.14. The honours obviously went with the Akhwan, but the Awazim as far ae i can see/! have not received by any means a 'knock out' blow. 15. Further news is bound to come in soon and will be telegraphed you. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Col., political A£ e nt, KuwaitTelegram (C) # From ___ Political, Agent, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire* No, - 567. Dated 12th October 1828, URGENT Reference my despatch 365 dated loth October, Please read 150 instead of 50 at end paragraph eleven* PoliticalTelegram (C). I?rom - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; Special, Basrah. No. Dated l^th October iy2y. IMMEDIATE. My No.i?b4 of 10 th October. Battle Ingair. Though there is mass of Contradictory rumour, from accounts five independent eyev/itnesses as well as from repoi*t of second of Shaikh’s special watchers, a reliable man, who present during battle greatly fear that Bih Saud’: Hassa force as represented by Awazim has suffered severe reverse. It clear however that portion Awazim were ab|e to rally vicinity Ingair. These have been surrounded and are still holding out. Duwish after battle sent force South in pursuit fugitives as well as to deal with Bani Hajir and Bani Khalid reinforcements reported Sarrar. Shaikh’s eyewitness states slaughter Awazim left and centre exceeded anything he saw at battles Jarrab Hadiya and Jahara. Mutair who blood enemies Awazim gave no quarter in spite strict orders Duwish and pursued hotly for seven miles. The Zaab, Malaaba and Sowabra sections together with Bin Saud‘s detachment who only numbered 1Q0 all told, were practically all wiped out. Those who rallied and are now surrounded consist of survivors together with Braichat and Haddadin sheep tribes who opposed to Ajman and are almost intact. Duwish himself took no part in battle but directed operations from distance.* Camels captured approximate 0000 also quantity British rifles and ammunition. Impossible ascertain any degree accuracy casualties either side though it clear that A^azim and Ajman suf-S' suffered very heavily indeed v;hile Mutair losses were insignif icant. Latest news Jednesday otli was tliat Awazim had refused Duwish’s demand that they should lay i down their arms and had dared him do his worst. fwo more ohaihh’s watchers hourly exj^ected with latest news.Telegram (C). ^ \0 « From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; Special, Basrah. ' Vo . £ 6 ^ express. Reference my 566 dated 13th October which posted Basrah owing breakdown telegraph line. Firstly . Third of Shaikh’s and my special watchers arrived last night from Duwish’s camp. He reports that remainder Awazim surrendered unconditionally Friday night 11th October. They included Braichat Had- dalin, fc'usahma sections under Mubarak al-Malaabi and Abdullah ibn Faishan, as well as other survivors. Awazim ‘ begged that they be allowed proceed Kuwait.and take shelter with their old ruler, alternative was to join Akhwan with all their families. Duwish acceded their request and allowed them temporarily to camp at Batchsa close to Akhwan. Awazim leaders may be expected here any moment to beg shelter and protection from Shaikh of Kuwait who has decided grant same. Above has been con firmed by letter from Duwish hiteelf dated 9th October and just received. Secondly . On Saturday 12th October Duwish leav ing Bandar his son in charge, moved South to round up Turki abu Ithaar who last reported Shabach South East of Nta with 112 men awaiting arrival Bani Khalid and Bani Hajir. As result battle latter have sent messengers to Duwish offering to submit. Thirdly . Duwish before leaving gave out that after Turki his objective was Ibn Jaloui’s camels in Habil region afterwards he will harry Hoffuf, ^atif and Jubail areas. Fourthly . A 1 Suhalli escaped with 5 men. Abdul lah al Subaii his second in command was killed.- 2 - l Fifthly * With destruction Bin Baud’s Hassa army Duwish is free move into Nejd where he will now certainly he joined by many other Nejd elements* Ajman will be able deal with anything in Hassa, where accord ing Duwish Bin Saud has nothing further to oppose them with* Sixthly * Report follows* Political.co.. - . ;..l . No.569. Political geticy, Kuwait. Dated the 15th October 1929. From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I. Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Battle of Injair (Ingair). Sir, In continuation of my despatch 565 dated loth October also my telegrams 566 and 568 of 13th and 14th respectively, I have the honour to report the following further details which may be found of interest. I might mention here that as far back as the 1 st October last when a clash between the opposing forces appeared imminent, I arranged with His Excellency Shaikh Innad for four of his most reliable Ajman and Mutair fidawis, elderly men who had served Shaikh Lubarak Shakespear and Hamilton to proceed to Faisal al-Duwish f s camp and sit there till something happened. Their ins tructions were to report immediately the various stages of any battle that took place coming in one by one to do 4o. -AL Duwish knew the men were from Shaikh .*hmad and myself and treated them well. S. Our second t? watcher n came in on 12 th October and brought very interesting details, but as he left before it was known definitely what had happened to the Awazim who were trying to rally, I was unable to give you definite news regarding the final stages of the battle. On the night of the 13th came our 3rd watcher, also a letter from al-Duwish himself to His Lxcellenoy Shaikh Elimad and from these two sources the 'fog' may be said to have lifted, and the cause of events made clear.-2- 0) ^ Much other corroborative news has also come in through Dhafir, Rashida and Awazlm sources to relations among the ”Hathar ,? of Kuwait. The full story is given below. 3. As was clear from my previous despatch, the Mutair broke the Awazim right and centre and carried all before them, on the 5th October. The Ajman on the other hand suffered a sharp reverse on the ^wazim right wing. The Mutair pursued wildly for a matter of 7 miles, their horsemen numbering some 550 causing much execution among fugitives. On giving up their imnediate pursuit of flee ing Awazim and loose camels, the Mutair returned to find Ajman still engaged with the Awazim and pressing them back. The latter had rallied in their subsidiary camp (see original plan sent) which was much closer to the main wells of Ingair than originally reported, and were put ting up a fine resistance. The Awazim had dug trenches everywhere and as daylight came on their fight became more severe. Both Mutair and Ajman from all sides then attacked and opened a tremendous fire into the camp of the Awazim vhich contained women and children, camels sheep etc etc closely inextricably mixed up. It was c this fire which caused so many casualties among the Awazim animals and women and children. 4 # ;BL-Duwish at noon called off the attack, mainly because his forces were out of hand and had scattered in their efforts to round up the Awazim camels. It might be mentioned that the Awazim women, when the Mutair attack was at its height, loosed nearly all their camels in the hope they would escape and be recovered later. These to the number of nearly 8000 were rounded up by the iJchwan. 5 . On Sunday 6th October all was quiet, though al-Duwish with his mounted men arranged that no one should come to or leave tlie Awasim camp. 6. On Monday 7th October the Awazim sent in a man of the Zaab to treat for surrender. As a prelimi- nary he asked al-Duwish if the Awazim could move camp to al-Batohsa, wells close to, and to the South Bast of-3- (^&gt; ^ Ingair, as the stench of dead men, camels and sheep was very great and the water was pointed. Al-Duwish agreed and likewise moved his own Ajman and Mutair camps to l&amp;i al Hz am, a place commanding Batohsa. The moves of both forces were completed by Thursday 10th October. 7. On the same dry i.e. Thursday the 10th Octo ber Duwish sent in and demanded that the --wazim leaders come to his camp and discuss terms of surrender• q # This was agreed to and on Friday 11th Octo ber al-Fucm with 3 men proceeded to the ^wazim camp and escorted Eubarak al Milaabi and Abdullah ibn Faishan the leading Shaikhd back to al-Duwish. 9 . Throughout Friday 10th the conference took place, and much speech making was indulged in on both sides, viiich it is unnecessary to try to repeat. Suffice to say al- r )u*fish blamed the ;.wazim for bringing so much trouble on their own heads and asked God to witness that he had sent 3 clear warnings to them to retire, as their continued presence, pinning him to Aorth Itassa w&lt;-iS very awkward. They the Awazun had. chosen to refuse and had preferred to obey Bin Baud’s commands, so he had had no alternative but to remove their threat by force. The Awazim on the other hand agreed that they deserved all they had got, and violently abuse i -&gt;in .aud for leading them on by continual promises that large reinforcements were coming to their aid. ..lone had ever put in an anpearance nor were any at all in the vicinity except very weak details (no more than 112) of 'Hathar' troops under Turk! bin Abdul Aziz abu Ithaar who was at dhabaoh South East of Nta: trying to get 3ani elements I halid camped at Hajira (East of Sa^ar/ and Bani Hajir camped at Nahaishiri (one day’s march South of Awaina; to join him. These on the approach of al-Duwish had f tney said ; positively refused to move north, the 3ani Hajir going so far as to return to ^mir Saud at Hof fuff all the that had been sent them, with a rifles and ammunition4- (% ^ message to the effect that they would do nothing unless either the King himself or he .amir Saud came and led them personally. 10 . On Friday night 11th, the Awazim surrendered; al-Duwish allowing them to retain their arras, property camels and sheep not actually taken in the battle. --I Duwish further offered thetf Awazim two alternatives (a) That they should retire North well away from his rear, and enter Kuwait territory if they could make their peace with the Shaikh of Kuwait. (b) With their fighting men join the Akhwan in their future operations, leaving their women and flocks with those of the -Ichwan The Awazim chose the former, and xkwd asked al-Duwish to write to the Shaikh of Kuwait and explain their case. The latter did this on the spot, and the Awazim Shaikhs armed with this letter are probably now en route to the Kuwait frontier to beg asylum from Shaikh idmaad. The Awazim asked for 20 days grace before txiey took tneir farailies North in order to bury dead, attend to wounded and collect fugitives. Al-Duwish who seems to have shown remarkable magnanimity all through, at once granted their request. . Ajfr dawn on Saturday 12th al-Duwish, al-i'uqm and al-Rufidi moved South to try and round up Turki abu Ithaar. A» a guard over their camp and to watch the Awazim, Bandar^ Duwish’s son, Ibn :Iashur ; and Naif al- Hathlain were left behind. 12 . Al-Duwish before starting gave out that he had not much hope of catching Turki but he intended rounding up Bani Khalid, Bani Hajir and then proceeding against Bin Jaloui’s camels in the Nabli region North of Hoffuff. -afterwards he would deal wi til —offuff, Qatif and Jubail, by which I think he meant 11 areas” not 'towns', for it is obvious he would only tie aim- self --5- himself up If he started besieging those places. 15. The Awazim who surrendered were the Braichat, Haddalin and Ausahma sections, as v/ell as a good many survivors of Malaaba, ^aab and Sowabra sections who had borne the brunt of the I utair attack. 14. In addition to Shaikh Hzam al-Hithlain, Shaikh Hamad bin fcusamah of the A.iman was killed. No ^utair Shaiichs fell, and of the Awazim only Mubarak bln Dralh and Hi.laan M raieh T&gt; Faharna , were wounded. 15. far as one can judge 42 Mutairi rank and file were killed. 35 Ajman ' ' ' ' 400 Awazim ?«»»♦*« « The Ajman had a great many wounded. The Awazim killed are reported from many quarters to^ exceed^900, but it is • so difficult to get true facts that I have preferred to put their killed down to the figure stated. This how ever must be taken as guess work only. 16. Mohomed al-Suhalli was not killed after all. He escaped with 5 survivors out of a total of 70 of Tin Baud’s raen who were with him. He presumably joined Turk! abu Ithaar. One Abdullah bln &gt;ubaii iiis second in command was the person slain by All al-Shuairebat. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Li eut-Col., Political Agent, KuwaitTelegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait# To - Resident, Bushire# Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; Special, Basrah# No#570. Dated the 15th October 1929. A Shammari, reliability unknown, has brought news that Ibn Msaad acting under orders, has retired from Ijibba to Hail, as there were indications Shammar unrest. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad and Special, Basrah. r'N Political. Telegram (C)# From - Political, Kuwait# To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; Special, Basrah# No# 571. Dated 15th October 1929. Man from Duwish f s camp reports that messenger from Artawiyeh arrived 3 days ago, declaring that open rebellion exists among all Ataiba. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad and Special, Basrah. Political.Telegram (C}. From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire* Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad; Special, Basrah. No. 572. Dated 15th October 1929. Twelve mares belinging Naif al Humaid Attaiba refugee Baghdad arrived Kuwait last week. Attendants have no passports. Shaikh who suspedts they are for Duwish would like orders - suggests they be returned Basrah. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad and Special Basrah. PoliticalT ELEG-RAM • M. From Britagent Jeddah. To Zueacari Kuwait. No.208 Dated 15/10/29 reed. 16/10/29. Addressed to Foreign Office 153 , repeated Kuwait, Bushire, Simla, Jerusalem, Baghdad 208. Copies by post to Cairo and Aden. Reply official communique is-published here to day to the effect that expeditions against the Ata i bah have been successful, and that no more trouble is expected from these tribes. I believe this is largely true. oc muni cue adds that rebels in north have also been defeated and Feisal ed Darishk hilled. Britagent 15315.•- Telegram M. From Pol it ical Kuwait. To (D Resident Bushire (2) Highcoma Baghdad No 573. Dated 16/10/29. Jeddah 3 T o 208. That Duwish is very much alive is proved by two letters from him dated i ; nd and 9th of October reed. here. Report his death traceable to Abdullah bin Turkl abu Ithaar, Bin Sauds General who wrote from Shabach, 50 miles from scene battle to Amirs Jubail, Qatif and Hassa claiming overwhwlming victory with deaths Duwish and 5 other principal Akhwan leaders by name. Copy this letter has eonie into my possession from Jubail is being posted, you. Addressed Bushlre, repeated Baghdad.COKFIDKI-rrL.L. (3) \ 0 &gt; No. 575. Political Agency, Kuwait, Dated the 17th October 1929. From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.i .Dickson. C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire. Comnlaints against the Shaikh of Kuwait iJid King Faisal of ’Iraq. Sir, I have tte honour to acknowledge your confi dential No.488-S dated 30th September to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, with copy of His Majesty the King of Hejaz and Nejd’s No.3/147 dated 12th September 1929; and submit my report below. 2 0 For clearness sake I propose taking your report No.61, and dealing with the complaints His Majesty the King of Nejd and Hejaz in so far as they ooncern Hi. Excellency the Shall* of Kuwait, correcting or adding to what you have already said in each case, paragraph by paragraph. r.nmnlalnt ( 1 ). I have nothing to add to your remarks which are correct in every detail, except to say that the Shaikh of Kuwait denies in to to that he ever gav# Ibn Mashur a present of any money, much lest Dollars 6,000/-. The Shaikh also denies that Ibn Mashur purchased any arms or ammunition in Kuwait. He on the other hand admits having sent out the following supplies for the men of Ibn Mashur numbor- ing 250 who were camped at Jahara with him. 25 bags of rice. 20 maunds (80/ Ibsj of dates. ' 1 bag of coffee.-2 ^ Vo 3 -■s the I 12 ihh. had denied them entry Into Kuwait, he con sidered It was up to him to send out some food, pending . ttfers of His Majesty's Government as to whether the party was to be allowed to remain in Kuwait or be ejected. i'he Shaikh when questioned about this, observed that/the time no 'rebellion” against the authority of Bin Baud had broken out, and .Lbn I.-ashur, who was out of favour only^ad in his possession a letter from Bin Saud offering him ootaplete forgiveness, and inviting him to return to Eiath. uch letter in the hands of Ibn Maahur and the latter's assurance that he was on his way to Bin Saud justified him, the ohaikh, in supposing there was no objection to giving him and his followers food for their journey back to Nejd. fhat Ibn Lashur in actual fact never did return to his allegiance does not according to the Shaikh, effect the issue. The treacherous seizure of Ibn Hathlain and the fear that he, Ibn Mashur, would lie treated likewise, ob viously decided him to change his mind. All this was after he had left Kuweit* PiSSPA*4.^21^ -(-%-) * Ibn Mashur purchasad 3 mares only whilst at Jahara* These were brought s from Zubair not from Kuwait# The story that 10 mares wore sold him by Subah bin Nasir of Kuwait is on the face of it an invention seeing that this personage was at the time undergoing a six months f sentence of im prisonment for the murder of his brother, and has only just recently been released. Subah T s mother did it seems sell 2 horses belonging to her son to a man of the -ijman about this time — but there is no rea son why should^she not have done this. The Ajman had not rebelled then. complaint (5) . Shaikh Ahmad says the complaint probably refers to the visit of Kfcalid bin Kohomed (Sab Sahman). This person arrived Zigara 22 miles away, accompanied by 7© mai* He sent in and asked for permission to visit his sister in the Tovm# As the rebels had been in the mean time forbidden to have dealings \ith Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad sent his commander of troops to him with orders to eject him* This was done. Complaint (4) . I have no remarks to make, Azaiyiz any money. Complaint (5) . There is a slight confusion of facts here. In your letter under refe rence you dealt with the visit of Hzam al Hathlain and al-Fuqm. Bin Saud curiously enough has not mentioned this visit. He does however refer to the 'secret' visit of Haif, al-Kuqm’s brother to Hi Hal al Mutairi’s house (vide my despatch No.450 dated 29th Julyj.iibdur Rahman al-^osaibi who was staying in Kuwait as His Excel- lency’s guest at the time, never saw Haif, but was told of the incident by the Shaikh himself. ‘The ejection of the sick man Haif from the Town without his dinner, as soon as he was discovered, has been care fully glossed over. Comclaint ( 6 ) . I have nothing to add to your remarks; except to say that in the portion where Bin Saud makes complaint about the crossing of the border by the .khwan and their camping round about Subahiyeh, he has got his facts very badly confused. No Akhwan ever camped anywhere near Fintas, Abu Halifah, Shuaibah lages above the sea coast. Nor are Bin Ba ud’s references to Naqasah and al-Syleim understood, these places are forty miles except that the Shaikh of Kuwait never sent or Araif jan, which rrea the ’Kiusur' vil-4- ioi\ \° b miles from where the -Jehwan carded* 3 . In conclusion I might mention that Bin baud's complaints have obviously been collected from hearsay evidenc forwarded by biased persons ignorant of facts, and certainly not acquinted with the Kuwait terrain* I do not think Bin Baud’s chief agent here Abdullah al Nafisi can be guilty of working up such a poor case for his master, as he is much to icnowledgable to have done such a thing* I wo Id say that Bin Baud’s two infor mants have been ^bdur Rahman al -ips^ibi and al-Ribai. fhe former stopped in Kuwait for 4 days some time and stayed with His iSxoellency the Ruler, and if ill behoves him to libel his host in the way he has done, seeing that Shaikh Ahmad took particular^ trouble to explain the efforts that were being made to prevent supplies going to the rebels dnd the strict measures that he the Shaikh had taken to prevent Kuwaitis from holding intercourse with their friends in the r bel camp; I myself went so far as to drive Abrur Rahman al Qosaibi in my car fcound the varous Bedouin’s ca.os near the city to satisfy him that the occupants were A*'- not rebels in disguise, who had come in to purchase supplies This story had been told him by certain pro Bin Saudites in the Town. 4 As regards Al Ribai. This person is a spy pure and simple, and his visit to Kuwait was duly reported to you. He is of the servant class and a man of no account though greatly trusted by Bin Saud. Both the Shaikh said I knew perfectly well that his visit to Kuwait would result in a crop of accusations being made against Kuw it. The men consorted with many disreputable Zubairi and Kuwait pro Bin Saudites elements whilst here with the result we see. I have said nothing about the accusations brought against King Faisal, as X presume these do not fall within my provinceTelegram (C) From Political^ Kuwait;; To Resident^ Bushire, Repeated Highcoma, Baghdad, No. 577. Dated the 18th October 1929. Special Basrah. My telegram No. 568 of 14th October and Despatch No. 569 of 15th October. Fourth watcher arrived. Confirms everything already reported. States (i) , Ajman death roll now 40, ^wazim now 250 also that ibn Msha , al andlabu Sufra minor Sheikhs of Mutair died of wounds. • (ii) A1 Dubaina with one rider arrived Duwish f s camp to see if news spread by Bin Sa f ud that Duwish killed true. A 1 Duhaina finding Duwish gone south followed. Before leaving he told watcher that ibn M f saad had returned Hail. (iii! Position Bin Sa’ud’s forces. Small party Sahool at Hafar Atz with detachment. Small party Sbei at Jooda, N # W # Hoffuf. Abu Ithaar at Jubail. Bin Sa’ud still at Riath. Khalid bin Mohomed at Shaara. (iv) Before watcher left news arrived that Duwish captured quantity supplies NTA. Addressed to Bushire^ repeated to Baghdad, Special Basrah. Political./''N H. C. F. 68 SECRETARIAT OF H. E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR ‘IRAQ. 11th, Oct. Baghdad th&lt;&gt;. *. /9 29. The Secretary to His Excellency the High Commissioner for ‘Iraq presents his compliments to and has the honour to transmit herewith^^ of the document (S^ mentioned below on the subject of thre ^llepaticns Ty King Ibn b aud. Reference :— Nil. ‘“‘emoranduir: No. S.O. ].953 dated the 11th. of October, 1929 to H.B.M’s Agent and Consul .Jeddah, with enclosure.Telegram (C)* From Pollti ca 1 , Kuwai t, To Resident, Bushire, Repeated to Highooma, Baghdad, Special, Basrah* No* 578. Dated the 19th October 1939. My 577 of 18th October* Sheikh thinks A 1 Dnhaina may have come as fugitive from Nejd though of course he did not say so. Neither he nor servant had rifles which suspicious* Addressed Bushire, repeated Baghdad and Special Basrah. Political.c 1c-eR- Uo. 504-S. of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 10th October 1929. 'The under-mentioned paper is forwarded to the Political A^ent at Kuv/ait for information, comment and return. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ■ - , || Extract from a letter from King Bin Baud to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad, Ruler of Bahrain, dated 16th Pabi Ath Thani 1348 - 19th September 1929.CONFIDENTIAL No* 591. Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 26th October 1929. From Lieutenant-Colonel D.R.P.Diokson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble 1iie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Sir I have the honour to acknowledge your no.504-3 dated 10th October forwarding copy of King Bin Baud's letter dated 16th Rabi Ath Thani 1348 (19th September 1929) to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad Ruler of Bahrain which as requested by you is returned herewith, to gether with my comments. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, Li exit -Ool., Political Agent, KuwaitCOMMENTS 1 # Faoimile copies of Bin Saud ? s letter to His Ex cellency Shaikh Hamad of Bahrain, were sent also to His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait, Shaikh Abdullah al- Salim of Kuwait, Shaikh Hamad al-Mubaraq of Kuwait and to at least ten of the leading citizens of this town. I understand also that many people in Basrah, Zubair and Baghdad (not to mention notables in the Hejaz) were also sent copies. 2. Bin Saud’s letter seems to me to be a n Defence Tf , or sort of ' justification ,, • He appears to be trying to Show the Arabian world that he is not only a much injured and misunderstood person, but that the reason of his strange inaction is not due to weakness, enemy pressure, or inability to punish the rebels, but on the contrary to his magnanimity and desire to avoid shedding blood. This f, appologia w unfortunately has had an entirely op posite effect at least as far as Kuwait is concerned, and on all sides one bears the opinion expressed, that Bin Saud is in dire straits, and that his round about methods of explanation merely bring out the factii that there is a big rebellion going on in Nejd, and that it is of such seriousness that it has forced him to adopt the defensive, or at least to face westward and neglect.the very serious situation that has arisen on his eastern flank of Hassa. 3. His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad’s view is summed up in the following sentences:- (a) Why does Bin Saud continually write screed after screed to all and sundry, saying what he is going to do and how terrible is going to be his vengeance. Why does he not keep quiet and get on with the work of putting down the rebellion? (b) His continued letter writing has of itself- 2 &lt; condeianed hi^k and proved to every thJLnking person that the situation in Nejd is serious, (o) Till he started defending himself like this the world only thought Faisal al-Duwish was the peril. Now every one knows* what was only guessed before, that western and central Nejd is in full ferment. That • (d) his frequent and regular statement* liie principal rebej. leaders like Duwish, Duhaina etc have been routed and slain, is terribly bad policy, for now nobody believes what he says. w 4 . Abdullah al-Nafisi (Bin Baud’s Agent) hitherto staunchly loyal, is dismayed by such tactics and does not know what to believe. t, Statement ,, after 'statement' has been received from his kaster in the last two months, for public consumption. But as fast as they sire issued by him, they turn out to be falsehoods. As he confided to me pathetically recently al-Nafisi *does not know what to say or believe'. 5. The insurgents in Hassa on the other hand effect to be in great glee. They hear of, or get copies of every one of Hin Baud’s 'statements', and their cry is^, did not we tell you you muslims, that our late master is no longer a true Mohomedan. He once feared to tell the smallest lie, but look at him now. He has left the straight path, and is now worse than any 'mushriq'. He started his policy of acting tig 'traitor ' to us his chosen Akhwan, and now finds he can do nothing without getting deeper and deeper into the mire of falsehood. His very lies prove that everything is going wrong for him ia and well for us'. 6 . (a) I personally hold the opinion that it is a lettie bit early to form definite conclusions as to how things are going to end, but that matters are pro- t grossing badly for Bin Baud is very clear now. Every thing depends on how staunch the rebel Ataiba keep up-3- their pressure from Ihe west# The rebels in Hassa are 'to full of enthusiasm and use a slang phrase ' haws their tails well up'. They however have as their leader the redoubtable Faisal al-Duwish, than whom no abler or more dangerous adversary can be found injtf the whole of Arabia# Have the Ataiba found such a versatile and strong leader to lead them? That is the question# (b) . That Bin Baud feels that he can possibly sow dissention aaong the latter more easily than among v al-Duwish’s following is proved the attention be is devoting to the west. That Duwish feels it is now time to turn his attention to Nejd proper, end give the Duhaina * s Ataiba encouragement is all significant# A1 recent arrival at al-Duyrish’s camp, was obviously to persuade him to initiate an attack on Riath itself from the North East/and prove to those of the Ataiba still hesitating, that, he was not only very much alive but that he had been completely successful in the Hassa province. It should not be forgotton that Bin Baud for the past few weeks has been engaged in disseminating intensive propaganda among the AtaOa to the effect that the Hassa rebellion had failed miserably, and that al- Duwish, Ibn Mashur, Ibn Hathlain and many other lesser leaders had been executed. (c) . The Ataiba,and Qassim will by now have heard of al Duwishls de^feat of the Awazimthe force with which Bin Baud was to have driven the rebels into the sea. If now al Duwish appears in person before Riath, Bin Baud will find himself between two fires and in difficult pridicaraent•/ (d) . The attitude of the great Qassim Towns has so far been correct, but just in the same way as they threw off Bin Raschid’s yoke and joined the successful Bin Baud, in the days when the latter rose to power, so they may any moment eject Bin Baud’s governors and come to terms with the rebels. The people of Q£ssim-4- of all people in Nejd depend on maintaining good rela- &lt;5L tions with the great 'B&amp;dia” tribes, who are in a posi- topm at all times to hurt them by destroying their gardem and cutting off supplies. They must always adbtsc attach themselves to tbe strongest party in power. For the moment they are loyal to Bin Saud, but are grumbling at his delay in putting down the rebellion. Should the Qiassim people decide Bin Saud’s star is definitely onthe wane, they vrlll act, and if they do, I think we may « assume it is all up with Bin Saud, This is how I read the Nejd situation. (e). That Faisal al-Duwish is making a final effort to get Shammar in on his side, with the bribe of Hail, before he moves into Nejd, is I believe what is delaying him in his present locality South West of Wafra. The most persistent rumours are in the air to this effect. ?/hen he does move, which will be soon I think, he will march via Hafar al Atz, not Artawiyeh now. The more one sees of al-Duwish’s moves the more one must come to the conclusion that he is working out a well thought out campaign. In this connection I would remind you of my talk with Hillal al Mutairi the millionaire merchant of Kuwait and Fao. S 6 e my confidential No.546 dated 24th September 192 9. 7. &amp;5y latest information from the Akhwan headquarters in Hassa is an follows, and I believe this to be a fairly correct summary of the situation^for whatever the Akhwan may be^ they have systematically gone in for say ing what they mean, and avoiding false propaganda. That I am able to get reliable men through to al Duwish’s camp from time to time and persuade that leader to re ceive and tell them part of his plans as well as other items of news, is I believe due to the fact that when I saw him at Wara, I was able to show him that I had no personal bias against him or any of his fellow insurgents. In other wards I was I think able to win his respect by-5- \ acting straight^oinwardly at an awkward moment. Position of Rebel Forces . (a) The Awazim are at Arak and are slowly moving up to Kuwait territory. (h) The Ajman are at Arak 'tia&amp;ea, their role being to look after Hassa and cut trade routes frcm the coast to the interior but not to attwppt to lay seige to Hoffuf or Qjatif • (c) The Mutair under el-Duwish are to move into Nejd and cooperate with the Ataiba in an attempt on Riath, incidentally causing Qaaim to declare for the rebels. (d) .Johjah al Humaid with a strong fbrce of the Ataiba is at Arwah ready to move when al Duwish appears in Nejd. (d) Sharraim ibn Assai (Ataiba) is working in the direction of Taif. ' (f) Al-Duhaina’s force is engaged raiding the Riathpi Hejaz road, their leader himself remaining for the present with Faisal al- Duv/ish (as sort of liason officer). Position of Bin Saud's forces . (a) Nil Hassa, except small garrisons of 'Hathar' at Hof fuf Qatif and Ainair^ supported by &amp; -£oa unreliable Bedouin. (b) A weak detachment of 150 men at Hafar a- Atz with a few Sahool and Subei tribesmen (num bers reliably reported to be quite insigni ficant) • (c) Ibn Msaad at Hail with a force of about 4000 maximum. It is not t^uite certain that he is definitely hack in Hail yet, but all reports say he is. (d) Ibn Rubaian and Ibn Haithal are at Shaarah . with an unknown force guarding the approaches to the capital from the west and mainly en gaged in trying to keep up communication witi-6- \V°\ the Hejaz. According to a direct report from al-Duwish received on 20th October, these two leaders have openly quarreled and their followers are fighting each other. Bin Gaud himself has procoeded to Shaarah to try and heal the breach, with what success is not known. This Shaarah force is presumably a strong one. (e) .The tpwns of Aared .and Qassim are in Bin Saud f s hands still, each having its garrison of Hathar levies. (f) Khalid bin Lonei appears to be defending the approaches to Taif from the east though with what strength or success is unknown in Kuwait. Lieutenant-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram Jj'rom To Repeated Code Political Heoiae/it BusJriire Secretary of State for Col Simla* Jiaghdad, Jerusalem* Bahrein No*i012. Dated i.7th October 19ii9, • London Do,46 Jeddah and * Political Agexit Kuwait reports that t;utuir and Ajman under Dawish inflicted crushing defeat on Awazim at Injair on October bth. Latter finally Burr.uder ed to Dawieh on October 8th and with his permission are aoout to approach Shaikh of Kuwait for shelter and proteo tion* Shaikh has decided to grant tnem protection. As result of victory Dani Haoir and haiii Khalid are reported to nave offered to eubmit to i^awish. Dawish reported to nave have moved towards south east of -•/ , Dta in pursuit of TurKi Abu ITHAAH. n e has given out f thf he then intends to march into Hoffuf, Siatif and Jubail Area and later into Hejd. Unconfirmed report received at Kuwait Uiat Ibn Musaad Joae retired to Hail owing to indications ol ohamtiiar unrest also tnat Ataibah are in open rebellion. - RESIDJSHT - *** Post copy for infornation to ' The Political Agent, Kuwait, ^he Political Agent, Muscat. Sd/- f. C. . T . Bar i' e 11 • Lieut-Col., Political Fesident in 1h e Persian fluff. Attested. ✓ # fox Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian fl-ilf.CONFIDENTIAL Political Agency, Kuwait* Dated the 18th October 1929 Wo.576* From I Lieutenant-Colonel H.R*P.Dickson, C.I.L., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Sir, In continuation of my telegram Wo.573 dated the 16th October 1989, I have the honour to forward translated copies of (1) A letter sent to His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait from a personal friend in Jubail whose name he does not wish to divulge dated 7th Jamad I, 1348 (10th October 1929) (2) A letter sent to His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait from Haji Shimlan bin All bin Saif (a prominent pearl merchant and Kuwait subject, now at Bahrain) dated 10th Jamad I, 1348 (13th October 1929). Both letters are interesting as showing that in the south, a totally different version of the Ingair battle is current, and the Akhwan are made out to have suffered a heavy defeat and al-Duwish, his son Bandar, Naif Abul Kilab (Ibn Hath- lain) and ibn Ashwan's two sons are reported to have been killed. will be seen is Abdullah bin Turki (Abu Ithaar) known tar short as Turki Abu Ithaar. This personage was 50 miles from the scene of battle, and the first news must have reached him by the fleeing Mohomed al Suhalli. That he knew a disaster to Bin Saud’s arms had taken place is of course clear but Arab like the news is forward by him in the form of a victory for his this 'Bashara' (good tidings) asmaster, though secretly no doubt he conveys the real nature of things to his superiors. Letter ( 2 ) is also interesting as showing how the news is allowed to reach Bahrain# I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, * Liout-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait#(«*) Translation of a letter received by His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait grom a personal friend in Jubail whose name is not dilrulged dated Jubail 7th Jamad 1348 (10th / October 1929) • oOo The messengers who brought the news of ad-Duwish , i slaughter by the Awazim arrived yesterday morning. They consisted of two persons sent by Abdullah bin Turki (Abu Ithaar) and they brought a letter copy of which is also below. Similar letters having been sent to iatif and Hassa, 11 We convey to you the happy tidings that the Awazim crushed the vile enemy on the 1 st Jamad I, (5th October 1929), and that their chief ad-Duwish, his son Bandar and Ibn Ashwan’s two sons were killed and that the defeated were followed up to Hamadh and were slaughtered in a killing so great as Yd 11 be handed down by the living to posterity. Five Bairaqs were captured from the enemy, and sent by us to Hassa. 2 . The messengers gave out that the day before the battle there were attacks on horses by hisxjfc both sides and that on the 1 st of Jamad (5th October 1929) Mutair heavily attacked the Awazim who consisted of four parties camped on the Nuqairiyah wells (Ingair). During the attack the most southernly party was defeated and Mutair reached the Awazim’s camp and seife up their Bairaqs in it. 3. As to Ibn Shuqair, he too^ Dhidan from the Awazim, but the latter then counter attacked and defeated and grate drove back the enemy to their camp. In the evening the Awazim again attacked the Mutair and fought with them with swords and daggers (hand to hand) and after^ a two hours struggle the Mutair were again defeated and followed to Hamadh. 4. Ibn Shuqair escaped in another direction to that of the defeated tribes, whose total casualties are esti mated to be 800 out of whom ad-Duwish is one (undoubtedly), and also Naif Abul Kulab (Shaikh of the Ajmon) Ibn ^shwan** sons and many others. ((Translation of a letter From - Shamlan bin Ali bin Saif, Bahrain. To - H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah,C.S.I. Ruler of Kuwait. ,C.I.E • » Dated the 10th Jamad I, 1340 (13th October 1929). After compliments. Before this I sent you a letter in which I informed you about our safe arrival, nothing occurred here besides the fight of ad-Duwish with the Awazim. The news which has reached us is that ad-Duwish has . been defeated but we are in doubt as to whether the news is true or not, but many stories have reached us from Hassa, Jubail and ^iatif all to the effect that the fight took place on the morning of Saturday and continued for six hours, ending with the defeat of ad-Duwish who was followed to Hamadh, and that ad-Duwish himself and his son Bandar had been killed. There is an addition to the above news, received from Jubail, it is that Ibn Shuqair during the fight took sane camels which belonged to Awazim and started to wards the West in another direction than that of the defeated tribes, we do not know whether he took these camels from Awazim during the fight or found them straying. This is a summary of the news which has reached us about the fight and the truth of course, will appear later. As to the Amir Saud, he has probably left Hassa today v proceeding to the Awazim with a force, he ordered the Qusaibis to arrange to send his requirements to Jubail, this was done together with 500 tins of petrol for his motor cars. It is said that Amir Saud has fifty motor oars and thot four aeroplanes will reach to him, God knows better if this be trueTftlttgran P. Ptom H .U'is• Hifib Coffl»i»sioner for Xr»q # MughtUul. To ^Xliioal 1 «olden i c isuohlre* Unnu»bered• T»ftted (and reoolved ) 18th uotober 1929. lU^iDlATB . Pollowlng la rapatltlon of telagruae fro« Hla lUgaat/ 9 a 3aaratary of fttata far tka aolonlee, no. 314, dated ilia 16th Catober 1929 begin# !- Ibn Baud has daaided to baaa at qmtlt kla air unit (a) on the *crnlun Gulf. Ha ima aaked Uiut four aero plane 8, which he la purehaning fro* at oak In Iraq, ahuuld be went to qptif. It la proponed alien balance of purehaae price iiaa been paid that the naohinea ahouid be flown fra* Iraq to t^atlf earrylng the Brltiah pilota, who are being engaged by Bin Baud. A wore unobtrualee Method of delivery would have been preferred by «* ae laae lih*ly to annoy King ^hiaal and the Iran Qovernnont; but I o» adviced that delivery by aea le rendered impracticable by the coapleta lack of landing faoilitiea at qatlf. Dclivcxy by aea would Moreover involve con aider able delay. It would pro bably also be necessary to despatch apeaial party to re- aesemble the aeroplanea at r^atiC, and their departure Might attract even more attention than the departure by air of the aeroplanea. In faet I doubt nhatber anything wouht be gained by attempting to conceal the real aeatinati on of the aero plane a which would doubtless leak out later. I an therefor inclined to think that the beat course would be to inform the Government of Iraq quite frankly of the sale of machines to King Bin Baud and of the arrangements contem plated for their delivery. If you agree you should infora the Iraq Government accordingly. if necessary you will, of course. Make use of the point that if Hie Uajesty's Government Had refused to sell. Bin Baud would undoubtedly haveCQCTIDaNTIilL No.587. Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 22 nd October 1929 From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Charges against Kuwait and ’Iraq formulated by Bin Saud in his No.147/9 dated 14th September 1929 forwarded to the Foreign Office by H.M’s Agent and Consul under his No.2069/1464/46 dated 30th September 1929. In reply to your telegram No.1032 dated 22 nd October 1929, asking me to comment on the letter mentioned at the head of this despatch, I have the honour to remark that if H.M. the King of the Hejaz and Nejd’s letter No. 147/9 dated 14th September 1929 be carefully examined, it will be seen that apart from a certain amount of fresh padding delivered in rather more verbose style than usual, all the charges Bin Saud brings against Kuwait on pages 4 and 5 of his letter, with the single exception of charge No.9 are identically the same both in form and wording, as those sent direct to you recently. These were dealt with by you in your despatch No.61 of 30th September to the addcess of H.M’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, as well as by me in rn^y No.575 of 17th October 1929 to your address. As for charge No.9. This is an incorrect statement of fact. The man who brought the first news was one of H.E. the Shaikh of Kuwait’s ’’watchers’*, vide my telegram No.478 of 16th August 1929, though perhaps this was not made quite as clear as it might have been by me. Further the supposed sender of the message, Mohomed al Athain, the actual destroyer of the motor convoy in the Dahanna himself brought the news to Kuwait accompany ing as he did, Farhan ibn Mashur on his last visit to Sir— - 2 - Kuwait. This was clearly brought out in my despatch No.500 of 26th August 1929 and paragraph 11. 2 . As regards Bin Baud’s charges Nos.10 to 18, these also are identical with those mentioned in the King’s letter to you: but as they concern King Faisal, I feel it is outside ray province to comment on them. 3 . As regards charges 1 to 6 ofil page 8 of Bin Baud’s letter, these are the same as were mentioned in the last part of paragraph 6 of Bin Baud’s letter to you, only they have been rearranged, no doubt v/ith a view to impress. Of these last charges Nos. 1 to 5 are fabrica tions altogether, and have been hopelessly mixed up with the AJchwan decent on Subaihiyeh under Faisal al Duwish on 30th August last. In this connection please also see my despatch No.757 of 17th October 1929 and last portion of paragraph 2 , 'reply to canplaint 6 '. I am afraid there can be little doubt that all these So called 'charges' on Bin Baud, against Kuwait and ’Iraq have been worked up from 'the collection' made by the arch-spy al—Ribai when that 'worthy' was in Kuwait recently. H.E. the Shaikh, of course, knew at the time what was in -the wind nnd, if you recollect, tried to prevent his leaving Bahrain, but he was to late the steamer having already left. 5 . That bin Baud should continue to prefer charges of this nature against those who do ndt see eye to eye with him instead of putting his vfriole energies into the war against his rebellious subjects seems a pity. It looks as if, in his desire to find excuses for his lack of success, he is trying the worn out trick of the 'red herring'. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, KuwaitTelegram (C)* From - Political, Kuwait# To - Resident, Bushire# Repeated to Highoorna, Baghdad; Special, Basrah# No. 583. Dated the 22 nd October 1929# My telegram dated 18th October No#577# 1 # Duwish has returned to Hamudh# He did not go further than Awaina as country entirely devoid grazing for horses further south# 2 # Before returning Duwish sent three camel parties under al-Fuqm, Mohomed al-Khalid and Mohomed al-Bandar to raid 0jair-Hoffuf-Riath road. 3. Al-Duhaina has left again for Qassim# 4. Sent reliable man to Hamudh on Saturday 19th to discover Duwish’s next move# Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad, Special Basrah# Political#Telegram (C)* V3 From Political, Kuwait* Resident, Bus hire. To No* 584. Dated the 22 nd October 1929. Have received two letters from Bin Saud both dated 27th September. Firstar thanks me for informing him of Sir Gilbert Clayton T s death, and expresses sorrow and concern at loss of such good friend and sympathetic administrator. Second^ letter expresses gratitude my sustained efforts prevent insurgents crossing border or purchasing supplies from Kuwait, begs me continue good work with redoubled energy. Hepfcs move against Duwish shortly and bring about his speedy defeat. Translations both letter being sent mail. Suggest I may be permitted send short non-committal reply, giving news of general interest only. Political.OOHFIDBHTIAL I'iT. \y* No. 585. Politioal Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 22nd October 1929. K : From Lieutenant-Colonel H.ReP.Dickson, C Political Agent, Kuwait, To The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, In continuation of my telegram No#584 dated the 22nd October 1929, I have the honour to forward trans lations of His Majecty King Abdul Aziz al-Baud’s two letters to me, both dated 27th September 1929, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col,, Political Agent, KuwaitTranslation of a private letter From - His Majesty King Abdul Aziz as-Saud f Riyadh. To - Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated the 24th of Rabi II, 134G (27th September 1929). # After compliments. With great regret and grief I have received the sad news vfoich you have related to us, regarding the death of our dear friend General Sir Gilbert Clayton. Your news was particularly distressing because of what we knew of the deceased’s true sayings and faithful actions. We feel we have lost a very great champion and faithful worker towards the good relations existing between us and the British Government. If there be any consolation, it is in our belief in the existence of wise and faithful men of the British Government who we believe will follow in the steps of the deceased and continue to carry out his acts and good work. Usual ending.\ Translation of a letter From - H.M.King Abdul Aziz as-3aud f Riyadh. To - The Political Agent, Kuwait. No. - 11/147. Dated the 24th Rabi II, 1348 (27th September 1929). After compliments. We have received your letter No.333 dated the 10 th Rabi II, 1348 and became veiy greatly delighted with the efforts which you have made and will continue to take in preventing the rebels from coming into Kuwait territories and from buying there provisions from Kuwait Town. We are sure of these your efforts and indeed have appreciated and appraised them in our letters to the British Government, the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and to His Majesty’s High Commis sioner for ’Iraq. We trust that you will redouble your energies to prevent the rebels from smuggling goods from or seeking shelter in Kuwait territories, absolutely and ccampletely in every way. No doubt you have heard of what happened to the rebels who raided under the chieftainship of Abdul Aziz ad-Duwish (Azaiyiz) and of the severe punishment which exhausted all their power. Shortly we shall, Good please, proceed to punish the rest of than in the vicinities of the Kuwait front- by iers, when that time comes we expect that/your efforts you will take the necessary action to prevent them absolutely from obtaining any benefit from Kuwait and its territories. Usual ending.Telegram. M. From Political Kuwait. To Resident Bushire. No. 586. Dated 23/9/29. Your endorsement of 19th October ^orwarding copies telegrams regarding proposal sell aeroplanes to Bin Saud. Matter was openly talked about in Kuwait week ago with this difference that Pilots were to be lent by x*ir Force. Bln Saud has obviously been propaganding above openly, as news first reached us from the Awazim, together with story tuat Juba 11 not Q,atif was to be base. I believe onp of Iraq papers also published details about week ago, though have not seen copy.Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire, Repeated Highooma, Baghdad, Special Basrah. No. 588. Dated the 24th October 1929. My telegram 583 of 22 nd October. Man whom I sent returned wihh following report:- (i) ’Ajman and f Awazim camped ARAK, (ii) Mutair in SHAQ south west Wafra, (ill) DAHAINA still with Dawish, his companion returned, (iv) No news from three strong parties raiding south, (v) Dawish with whom man had interview stated he was moving into Nejd at once and would attack Riath in co-operation with T Ataiba. This was reason Dahaina f s visit. ’Ajman would remain in control Hassa where there was no longer any opposition. Dawish added that Bin Sa’ud had gone Sha f arah where he was trying make peace between ibn Rubaian and AL HAITHAL who were fighting each other. JAHJAH al HUMAID was at ARWAH ready to co-operate with Dawish. Sharraim ibn Assai was working direction TAIF, ani DUHAINA’s force was astride Hejaz road. Addressed Bushire, repeated Baghdad and Special Basrah. Poli Healcomp^ri x. No. 589. Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated tte 24th October 1929. From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Diokson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in 'the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Nejd-Hassa In 1 ?elli£ehcQ. Sir, In continuation of my telegram No.588 of date, I have the honour to forward some additional news which I did ' not think worth while telegraphing but which may be found of interest. 2. His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad who as you know keeps himself infoimed of Nejd affairs through Bahrain by means of certain Kuwaiti merchants has received letters by last mail making the following reports:- (a) Abdur Rahnian al-niosaibi bas written confidentially from Hoffuff to his family that a caravan between Nejd and Hoffuf has been taken by the Ajmnn also another belonging to Bani Hajir near Hoffuf. (b) A KuY. r oit merchant from the interior confiims that Bin Saud has gone to Shaara 140 miles west of Riath. He adds that the Nejd-Hejaz road has been closed for some time. Also that the price ox a bag of rice in Riath is now Rials 60/-. Further that the Hoffuf treasury is empty and officials have not received pay for 2 months. That tte people fear a sudden attack and that four or five patrols in 'ford' cars move out of 11 the town daily and proceed towards the north T'Atu-pninff averv evening. (o) That a good deal of anti-Kuwait propaganda is(m?, \Mr 1 ' issuing from the C^osaihi’s house, special items being that tl© Shaikh of Kuwait’s cars leave regularly for the rebel camp with supplies of anas and ammunition, also that al-Duwish has got one of the Shaikh of Kuwait’s 'Bairaqs' with him, (d) That Bin Baud has written to the Ataiba Shaikhs saying that the heads of Duwish, Ibn / Mashur, Xbn Hathlain, Mohomed al-Khalid, and twenty three lesser rebels have been sent to Hoffuf, as. % wells as several captured 'Bairaqs' as a result b of the last crowning victory. Note . That 2 war flags were taken from the Ajman by the Awazim when they were driven back at the battle of Ingair is admitted by the Akhwan. These were t got through to Hoffuf before Duwish finally farced a surrender, and I believe have hung from the walls of the 'kut* ever since as emblems of the victory. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, k* Li out-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram (C) # From - Highcoma, Baghdad* To - Resident, Bushire* Repeated Political, Kuwait* No*302. Dated and received 25th October 1929. URGENT . « Addressed to Bushire repeated to Kuwait. Report received via Basrah, Nasiriyah and Safwan stating force of Harb and Dhafir under Muhsin al-Firm and Ajaimi al-Suwait is moving through Bashuk area towards Hafar with presumed intention of attacking rebels. One report gives their objective as Kuwait tribes,J which I consider improbable* Force due Hafar today* It is also reported that loyalists force of three Bedoui. Bairaqs and 1500 townsmen is concentrated at Hafar al Ats* Highc cma•CONFIDENTIAL (Kn) Wtt- 591. Politioal Agency, Kuwait* Dated the 26th October 1929* From Lieutenant-Colonel H.H*P.Dickson, C*I.E*, Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire Sir In continuation of my telegram No*586 dated the 23rd September 19 29, I have the honour to forward trans lation of an extract on the subject of aeroplanes for Bin Saud from the n Fatah al-Arab dated 29th September 1929 of Damascus, sent me by His Excellency the Shaikh* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Extract from Newspaper 'Fatah al-Arab” of Damascus, dated 29th September 1929. 0*0 KING OF THE HIJAZ IS HAVING BRITISH AVIATORS. London - The correspondent of the Daily Express has come to know from an Officer in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs that six ex Royal Air Force British officers will leave from England within the next fifteen days to start on the organization of the Air Force of Ibn Saud. The officers* names have been concealed until their agreements are signed and sealed. London - An article appeared in the Daily Mail in which it was stated that King Ibn Saud shortly intended establishing a great army, the purpose of which was not to contend with any European Gova'innait. That steamships had secretly discharged thousands of rifles and hundreds of thousands of cartridges and other amuntions, (which had been imported from Gemnany and India) at the ports of Jeddah and Bahrain. That Ibn Saud had bought some hundreds of Lewis guns and field guns and that the purohasement of aeroplanes was being discussed at the moment of writing, 1ek± his troops were to be trained by German officers, and the six ex Royal Air Force officers will leave from England within the next fifteen days to be as a commencement for the Air Force of Ibn Saud. In another number of Fata al-Arab, dated the 4th October 1929, appeared under ihe title of Petty News. The Daily Sketch writes that the King Ibn Saud reqyested for the British aeroplanes to assist him in reducing the rebellion of Faisal ad-Duwish.Telegram. From Resident Bushire. To Political Kuwait. * : c. 1043 Dated 26/10/29 Colonial Office have asked me to nominate Political Officer to accompany flying boat reconnaissance from Iraq to Qatif to select emergency landing ground. I have nominated Dickson • .•ill you please keep us 'both informed of arrangements for despatch of flying boat. Addressed Aviation, repeated Kuwait. Telegram M. To Resident Bushire. From Political Kuwait. No. 39? Dated 27/10/29. Your telegram No.1043 undecypherable, please repeat in another code •i Telegram M. To Resident Bushire. From Political Kuwait, No. 593. Dated 27/10/29. Your telegram No 1041 of 26th October. As I read situation, ^atif is at the mercy of the rebels any time they choose to a.ttack it. That they have not done so yet is because they wish to retain their field mobility and not deseimate their etrengh by attacks on towns: When Bin Bauds aeroplanes arrive they are sure to invite immediate attack, unless in the meantime situation radically changes or Bin Baud can send a strong force to protect them, for any aerodrome chosen will have to be on desert side of Palm belt some three miles from town and fort, and in vulnerable position. I think from Bin Bauds point of view Hoffuf would be more suitable, also much healthier. From personal knowledge there is a superb site for an aerodrome west of the town commanded by Qalat Khsam, in whole of above connection see eight maps of Hoffuf, Qatif and OJair areas made by me in your office. Regarding suggested reconnaissance only difficulty I can foresee is danger of landing Qatif Harbour at low water, where numerous shoals render operation difficult. Obviously arrival of flying boat will give warning of what is to follow, and for this reason suggest better plan is for reconnaissance proceed to Bahrain and visit Q,atif by sea from there. Meantime will you permit me to discuss question with Sheikh. PoliticalTelegram. M. From Resident Bushire. To Political Kuwait. No. 1041 rated 26/10/29. Colonial Office having asked me to nominate Political Officer to accompany flying boat reconnaissance which it is proposed to send from Iracj to Q,atif to reconnoitre site for emergency landing ground, and to arrange its marking out. I am nominating Dickson as Political Officer. Please report early if there is any danger to preliminary reconnoitering party, or aeroplanes to be delivered at Qatif falling into hands of rebels. Addressed Kuwait and Bahrain. ResidentTelegram* M. Prom Political Bahrain. To Political Kuwait, No. C 120 Dated and reed 28/10/29. Addressed Bushlre, repeated Kuwait. Your telegram no. 1041 of 26th of October. Qatlf is reported quiet, but Amir is thoroughly nervous, and garrison reported to be standing to. Outside town there is no security. Provided Bin Saud has authorized reconnaissance and a notification has been sent to the Amir, I anticipate no danger to party in Qatif itself. Political.ISM 'X A^&gt; - Telegram From To Jode Foil ti cal Ageut Baiirein Politic d nebiue.it Dusnire Vo•1285 Bated &lt;JOtn (received 21et) October 1929* Your telegram No*1012. Shei iUa Abdullali Bin Isa informed Adviber yesterday afternoon, Sunday txiat former wac goiii^ to ^ fetch or put away his camels for fear of Ajma.ii a*id Awa-eAia anticipated attach Wt on ^atif aiid Juoail. The quaaiois gave big feast to Al Nejais on 18th October in honour of the so called victory over Ajm&amp;n and Bawish being Killed* • political - for Post copy to the Politi cpl A^ent, Kuwait, for infoVnation. Sn/- C*C,J.Barrett• Lieut-Col., Political Pesident in the Perr-ian Gulf. At ties ted. Secretary to'the Political Hedent in the Persian f ?ulf. -DUtniie, 21 / 10 / 2 ^.@ \bo Telagraii P. Jecrotary of *&gt;tato for tho ’olonlesi London political lostaent, BUbhire. From To Unnumdoraa Dated 22nd roceived 25rd Gotoder 1929 « i Tho date of delivery of the aeroplanes at £ atif oannot yet de fo ecast. Air X f inis try are of opinion that before the flight is undertaken an Air loroe officer froa Iraq should inspect tha v aerodrome at present being prepared at xfcyantK Qatif ana that emergoney landing ground should be selected and marked out on the Has* Coast approximately midway between |atif and } uwait. The British gent at Jeddah is being instructed to inform the Hejaz Government of the arrangements proposed, omphas- -iaing the necessity for proper accommodation for pilots, and to request permission for an inspecting officer, accompanied by a political officer, to proceed from Iraq to ;atif in a flying boat, descending en rouue to reconm- -oitre site for an imergoncy landing ground &amp; to arrange for its marking out* J ir Officer Commanding, Baghdad, regarding the arrange- -ments for the despatch of the flying boat. To the point raised in the latter part of your telegram under reference I will reply separately. Reference your despatch No. 62 of 1st Cct- -obor and your telegram No. 46 of l?th October. If you consider that there is danger either of the preliminary reconnoitring paJrty or of the aeroplanes to be delivered cit % atif falling into the hands of the rebels you should report accordingly by telegraph. AurL Political Officer for this purpose should be nominated by you. You should keep in touch with the reference i.* to your telegram No. 4d of 16th October* aecretJiry of 3t ie for the Colonies. 0Telegram (C) # From - Resident, Buslrire. To - Political, Kuwait. No* 1036. Dated and received 24th October 1929. Your 584. In accordance with instructions of 3rd September please telegraph terms proposed reply. ResidentConfidential. wo. of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General Bush ire, 25 th October 1929 A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for information. By Order, Subject : Activities of ITajdi rebels in Kuwait territory. 1. Telegram from H.tT. Agent, Jeddah., to the Foreign Office, Wo. 140, dated 24th September 1929. 2. m elegram from the Foreign Office to H.M.’s Agent, Jeddah, ITo. 102, dated 26th September 1929. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Received under despatch dated 3rd October 1929 from the Colonial Office, London.)@ ' V ’ H Decode. British Agent, (Jeddah). 24th September, 1929. D. 11.05 a.m. 24th September , 1929. R. 6.55 p.m. 24th September, 1929. No. 140 (R). My despatch Mo.159 and your telegram to.100. Acting Linister for Foreign Affairs is under impression that ris Majesty’s Government have undertaken to attack Doweish on sight whenever he is found in Koweit territory and requests action should be taken accordingly. He does not regard Britisn undertaking as bearing solely on maintenance of neutrality of loweit and prevention of improper use of loweit territory.(E 4892/2322/91). NO DISTRIBUTION . \'o ' 5 Code telegram to Mr. Bond. (Jeddah). Foreign Office, 26th September, 1929. 6.15 p.m. No. 102. (R). Your telegram No.140 (of September 24th - activities of Nejdi rebels in Koweit). Fuad Hamza has misunderstood the position, which is that Lis Majesty's G-overnment have undertaken to prevent Nejdi rebels from using Koweit as a base for their activities against, or as refuge from Ibn Saud. With this object in view authority was given for Faisal-ed-Dawish to be attacked if this should be necessary in order to eject him from Foweiti territory. This authority was not an instruction to attack Faisal-ed-Dawish at sight, but was intended to enable British autnorities to take drastic action against him if and wnen necessary witnout reference to higher authority. Colonel Dickson, on the occasion to which my telegram 1 O.100 (of September 19th) refers, did in fact take steps which resulted in Faisal-ed-Dawish leaving Koweiti territory forthwith. Had these st4ps not been successful he would no doubt have had resort to more drastic action. No action such as that foreshadowed in liejaz Government's Note referred to in your telegram - T o.l31 (of September 11th) is covered by the undertaking given by His i ajesty’s Government.relegraa From P v 1 olivi nil Ke&amp;laenty r/jsliire. to eoretnry of for tho Colon!as t London. ho. 50* Datact 26tti Goto bar 1929. I have nominated Oolonal Diokson as polit- -ioal &lt; ffioer to accojupanjr the flying boat. The uale of aoroplanea to I bn Caud was openly diaouasad in Kuwait on 12th October but it was stated that tne pilots were to be supplied by the oyal ir Force. The news reached Kuwait from the Awazim, who alleged that the base was to be nt Juball. As the news of his purchase has obviously h been publised by Ibn Gaud I propose, with your permission to mention the matter in a letter regarding voy&amp;l Air force refuelling stations which 1 am writing to my Agent on the Truoial Coast. The foregoing refers to your telegram of 22 nd ctobar. sJIGSMT. lost copy to The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Politioal Agent# Bahrain. iid/- C. C. J. Barrett. . Lieut~Col. f Political Kesident in the Persian Chilf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Hesident in the Persian : ulf. Bushire, 26th Octodar 1929 .Telegram (C), From - Political, Kuwait# To - Resident, Bushlre# No# 598# Dated 30th October 1929, Tour 1058# One All bln Ibrahim merchant is spreading story that he has heard that Qosalbi has got Abdul Wahabi house at Qatif ready for flying officers, and that launch has been sent there for their use as well as quantity petrol. Also that Italian gunboat is arriving shortly with munitions for Bln Saud. Political.Telegram.M. From Resident Bushlre. To Political Kuwait. Fo• 1058 Dated end reed. P9/10/29. Your telegram No.593. Do not discuss v.^ith Eheikh at present. Telegram. M. From Resident Bushire. To Political Kuwait. No.1053. Dated 28/10/29 reed. 29/10/29. Baghdad endorsement S.O. 2013 October 23rd. Please telegraph your observations . Fact that Awazim have not yet applied for Sheikh of Kuwaits protection support belief Honours are not wholly with Dawish.( 3 ) 8GP8 v .621...1081...5,000 ..18 9 23. ^ Vi ■ ^ ' &lt;r H. C. F. 16. Confidential. SECRETARIAT OF H E. THE HIGH . P ^ COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ —o* o* — -^2— &amp; f {Baghdad, ^ October- 192 9, By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for ‘Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked below is forwarded with compliments to :— ?h$ 3*3eretary to the hoa , ble the Politic il .iecident in the Persia** ^ulf, Bushire* Xhe Political A#;ent, Kuwait* to H, E. The High Commissioner for ‘Iraq. r\ enclosures :— Confidential »eirior\ndu-.i lio.C/3491 dated the Slot of October, 1929, from the Adviser to the ministry of Interior, Baghdad, to the Secretary to h. .the High Commissioner for ‘Iraq, Baghdad, on the subject of the situation in Bajd.Telegram - wireless. Prom Buttolph Safwan. To Advisint Baghdad. No. B^eo. Dat ed 18-10-1929. - Reports of rebel victory over Ibn Sard’s Northern Hasa concentrated on 5 result of which Awazim Shaikhs have surrendered unconditionally and are seeking entry Kuwait for safety should be treated with reserve. They constitute insurgent propaganda and reflect enthusiasm for rebel cause by Ibn Subah. Reliable reports from numerous sources confirm that AJman who prematurely opened rebel attack au^ered severe reverse heavy casualties and fled. Mutair with Ibn Mashhur (Ruwalla) attempted to loot Awazim families and camels in rear but were counter-attacked by reinforcements Ibn Sa’ud^ regular Beni Haja and Beni Khalid and were forced to withdraw. Both sides sustained considerable casualties. The Akhwan who were routed lost Hizam ibn FotfUi, Ibn Hithlain killed Ali Abu Shumairban and Ali ibn Ashwan severely wounded (former reported died at Kuwait). Duwish and many rebel concentrations now camped Wafra and Kishasha area but some encampments reported moved Subaihiya. ! Ali Ashwan believed vicinity Araq. Since the action number of Ajman and Mutair families have been camped I immediately outside Kuwait town and others now appearing at Jahra and intermingling with Ibn Subah*s Ruwaishda tribe there. Some Mutair have also arrived innit - 2 - in Kuwait territory as far as Liyah (50 miles from •Iraq frontier). Northern Hasa force to he moved up to Badjsa is likely to he reinforced from Hasa shortly. Supplies S. reported delivered hy motor transport and further clash is imminent. Duwish and Ihn Hithlain have attempted trace negotiations with Awazim chi fs wA y^^ve informed them to accept n-utrality end «nt*r Kuwait for grazing, supplies and also security against any coming fighting. The indication was supported in writing hy Shaikh of Kuwait which will undoubtedly he viewed hy Ihn Sa’ud as a further act of hostility hy the Shaikh. Negotiations were referred to Muhammad al Suhaili (Suhai) Ihn Sard's leader who with Awazin chiefs is said to have agreed nothing could he consi dered unless Faisal al Duwish would present himself in person. Latter mistrusts and refused. Snail force of Suhai raided Dawi al Rashid (rebel Uutair) near M Shaqq looting about 300 camels on 13/10. Ihn usa’ad has visited Hail. Large percentage his tribal force at \jiba is now being replaced hy Hail townsmen and cultivators.(Horse). T.0.0.11.15/18. Confidential Ministry of the Interior, No.C/3491 Baghdad, the 21st October, 1929. 37/3.' The Secretary to His Excellency the High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad. Memorandum . Forwarded for information. Sd.G.C. Hitching, for Adviser, Ministry of Interior. 9 y U. I.Telegram M. From Political Kuwait. To Resident Bushlre. No.598. Dated 30/10/29. Your telegram No. 1053. It Is a pity Buttolph h&amp;s thought fit to enter the lists against Kuwait, s.n area for which I am responsible. His reference to the Sheikh in second para is bad taste, and I certainly object strongly to his statement that AJman and Mutair families after battle have come and camped immediately outside Kuwait, and others are mingling with Sheikhs people outside JahSf£§ , this is not only a delib erate falsehood and mischiveous statement, but shows lamentable ignorance of the movements of the Sheikhs “hathar'' bedouin, who are all on the move after recent rains: Nop indeed is such a statement flattering to my Intelligence, seeing that I now know personally occupants of every tent almost within a radious of 20 miles of Kuwait. As regards Awazlm, they are not due Kuwait territory till November 1st, see my despatch No.569 of October 15th: Actually they are now near Wafrah camped side by side with AJman and more or less prisoners. There are indications that Dawish after all may not allow them to enter Kuwait as the rebels view now is that in Kuwait they are capable mischief, and can correspond with Bin Saud, with them they are helpless. There is no question whatever that Awazlm suffered a heavy defeat at Ingair, and were forced to come to terms to save themselves. In this connection consider my reports more to be relied on than those emanating from Basrah or Safwan.Telegram (C) # From - Politleal, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushlre. No. 590. Dated 50th October 1929. Tour 1036. Propose replying to Bin Saud as follows:- Firstly gire him latest Afghan news. Secondly tell him about your coming departure and who will relieve you as Resident. . Thirdly that Awazim are now camped with Ajman near Wafra and that Duwlsh is in Shaq South West of Wafra. It is not known what Awazim Intend doing. Fourthly that shall continue efforts to keep Akhwan from entering Kuwait or obtaining supplies. Political.Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. No. 600. Dated 31st October 1929. IMMEDIATE . Duwish who reported camped in Shaq South of Manaqish sent letter to Shaikh last night asking for interview today or tomorrow at Jahara or Saada. Shaikh who suspects matter concerns Awazim is strongly in favour granting request and wishes me accompany him. I support Shaikh’s view as much can be learnt from talk. Request immediate instructions by telegraph. Political.Telegram (C) # From Resident, Bushire. Political, Kuwait. To No. 1066. Dated and received 51st October 1929. IMMEDIATE. As visit by Duwish to Kuwait means justifiable rrmt protest by Ibn Saud it is desirable that you and Shaikh Ahmad should meet him south of Manaqish not at Jahrah STV/V^A &gt; or ( . Can you arrange this? You should certainly^ accompany Shaikh Ahmad if he gObo. Manaqish is in Kuwait territory I presume Daw4»h is across frontier. Resident.Political. fi£&gt; I mmedlate. Telegram M From Political Kuwait To Resident Bushire. No. 602 Dated 31/10/29. My telegram No .600. Whilst I was with Sheikh this morning express messenger accompanied by Dawish's nephew arrived with news that Dawish impatient for reply was on his way to Kuwait and had reached point 6 miles from city. Sheikh and I at ance decided send Joint order to Dawish to proceed Jahara, and there await your reply. Order was sent out by Abdullah al Jabir by car. Sheikh very angry, told nephew exactly what he thought of Duwish* s action.Political Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire* No* 604* Dated 31st October 1929* ILIMEDT ATS. Tour 1066 just received prior its arrival Shaikh and I considering presence of Dawish too dangerous Jahara sent Abdullah al Jabir with orders eject Dawish from Kuwait territory tonight without fail and return well ffoutside Kuwait territory* Abdullah further ordered to get from Duwish verbally or in writing exeotly what he desires to say and to tell him it would be reported to His Majesty’s Government* If latter then thought it necessary send Shaikh and myself to interview him this would be done in his own camp not anywhere inside Kuwait territory* him to his camp which 10 miles South West Manaqish andTelegram (C) • From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire# Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad* No.601* Dated 31st October 1929, IMMEDIATE. Leading Awazim Shaikhs arrived last night with large following and formally asked protection of Ruler Kuwait with permission camp Jahara. They made it clear that they did not desire temporary protection but wanted to return their old allegiance, alternative they said was to throw in their lot with rebels, and fight Bin Saud* Latter course they wished to avoid as Bin Saud had treated them well in spite of the fact that he had failed them utterly when pitted against whole strength rebels lately* Shaikh agreed grant his protection, and ordered them to move up to Jahara area. Main body Awazim camped Hazaim west Wafra. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. Political. #Telegram (C). Prom - Resident, Bushire* To - Secretary of State for Colonies# Repeated to Baghdad, India, Jefldah &amp; Kuwait# No. 56. Dated 31st October received 1st November 1929# BIPORTANT. Kuwait No. 604 31st October begins ••••• ends# I approve Dickson’s action and will report result Abdullah’s interview with Dawish# Dickson’s 601 I see no objection to Kuwait granting protection to Awazim who are originally a Kuwait tribe please see my despatch dated 8 th August No. 40. It is more advantageous to Ibn Saud that they should remain neutral in Kuwait rather than be forced to fight on the' side of rebels# Addressed to Secretary of State for Colonies No.56 repeated to Baghdad, India, Jeddah and Kuwait. Resident.(.n, Telegram (C). From - Politioal t Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No* 605. Dated and received^ 1st November 1929* BWDXATB . My 604 31st October* Duwish left two hours before dawn, Abdullah’s report follows. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. Political.*Telegram (C) # From - Resident, Bushire* To - Political, Kuwait* No. 1072. Dated and received 1st November 1929* IMMEDIATE. Please ensure that Dawish Reaves Kuwait territory at once. Arrange to meet him in future on neutral and Kuwait boundary if such meetings are absolutely necessary which appear unlikely. Resident.Telegram (C) # From - High Commissioner for ’Iraq, Baghdad* To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated Political, Kuwait. No. 310. Addressed Bushire repeated to Kuwait. Recent reports from the desert state Mutair and Ajman encampments are now located in Kuwait territory or wbI close to Kuwait frontier. Bedouin opinion attack on rebel imminent and suggest rebel in Kuwait territory will be first objective. In order to gauge reliability such reports I should welcome information of present locations of rebel elements if these have changed since despatch of the Kuwait telegram No. 588 dated 24th October • Dated and received 1st November 1929. Highcoma.Telegram (C). Prom - Resident t Bushire* To - Political, Kuwait. No. 1073. Dated and received 1st November 1929. Do you propose now to amend terms of proposed reply mentioned in your telegram No.596. Resident. #» Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire, No. 607. Dated 2nd November 1929. Your 1073. Propose amending paragraph three and saying that Duwish appeared Jahara on 31st October and asked to see Shaikh and myself he was ejected without being granted interview, also that Awatim Shaikhs asked be allowed enter Kuwait as alternative to being forced join Duwish. Shaikh granted their request. PoliticalTelegram (C) . Prom - Political, Kuwait# To - Resident, Bushire# Repeated to Highcana, Baghdad. No# 608. Dated 2nd November 1929. Baghdad f s No. 310 of 1st November. Dm Rebels are camped along line Shaq depression from Kuwait border to Ahairish, llutair in North Ajman in South. Dawish himself suspiciously close to border not far from Manaqish hills. Owing to recent rain rebels are no % longer concentrated on water but are soattred in small groups over wide area guarding camels which grazing westward, some of latter who water once a week reliably reported, drinking Subaihiyeh and Tawil this engaging my close attention. Awazim are in Hazaim on coast. On 29th October party 600 raiders under al-Firm appeared al-G-ara area but retired hastily on learning from heardsman that Awazim had submitted and rebels were in front of th*m. Apart from this party story impending attack from west discredited. Care should be taken not confuse Kuwait 'hathar' Ajman and Mutair elements with their tribal cousins many of these after recent showers have moved from Kuwait and will be found vicinity Jahara especially to north east. Addressed to Bushire repeated Baghdad. Political.Telegram (C)* From - Resident, Bushire# To • Political, Kuwait, No, 1086, . Dated 2nd received 3rd November 1929, Will you please accompany flying boats leaving Basrah 9th November for Bahrain for reconnaissance of emergency landing ground aircraft will now be delivered at Darin instead of Qatif boats will reconnoitre D on 10th November and 11th November and ben return you to Kuwait, I have asked Aviation to inform you direct whether you should join boats at Basrah or Kuwait, \ Resident, / -Telegram (C) # Prom - Resident,’Bushire.• To - Aviation, Baghdad.• Repeated to Political, Kuwait &amp; Bahrain. No. 1098. Dated and received 3rd November 1929. As Colonial Office now wires that Ibn Baud (? will not) agree to reconnaissance of Hasa coast alleges danger from rebels in that area it is unnecessary for Dickson to accompany flying boats. Prior will accompany reconnaissance from Bahrain to Darin. Addressed to Aviation repeated to Kuwait, Bahrain. Resident.Telegram (C)• ]?rom - Resident, Bushire. To - Political, Kuwait. No. 1099. Dated 3rd received 4tli November 1929. Colonial Office have approved of my mentioning sale of aeroplanes to Ibn Saud but ask that method of not delivery and base should/be disclosed to them. Resident.SECRET, Reference :-l/BS/34, 4 0 * „~Si eSufir&amp;t £+***&gt;*&amp; . (v&gt; \U~^***'* /{ *^* ^ Special Service Officer. BASRAH. 26th October, 1929. Bear \ I ajn sending you a copy of ny last report, as far as it concerns the Southern Desert &amp; Rajd. This has been rather held up by my absence on tour in the Amarah Liwa, and also by the fact that I was anxious to get as many reports from as many sources as possible on the recent events south of the KUWAIT frontier, before rendering a report on the situation. As you will see, my information on the fight on 5/10 and by/ subsequent events differs from that received you in certain important respects. I received a- la,rge number of reports from varied sources, some of which I know to be usually reliable, and as a result I think that the account I have given in this report is a fair summary of the events. All the reports I received agreed that the AWAZIM &amp; Ibn SU*UD 1 s people got slightly the best of the show, although the AWAZBT undoubtedly received as severe casualties as the AJKAK. I an also inclined to place the rebel locations further north than you do, in fact, s,s you see from my ••Stop Press' news, latest reports are quite definite abou t ,r&lt;~w ^ • OP many of them being in KUWAIT territory, and some of the • ' AJMAU in the SKA}[IYAK. The latter has been consistently reported ever since the fight on 5/10. There are also numerous reports from everywhere about this concentration in BASHUK, and their move to HAEAR al BATIK. I wonder whether:.you have heard anything about it ? Yost of the news from that direction usually comes up to SAEWAN and STTLFAK, so perhaps you have no information on this*(2). It is curious how reports from BAHREIN tend to exaggerate news in favour og Ibn SU t UD, to an even greater extent tha.n the rebel protagonists in KUWAIT, and for that reason I am not inclined to put much faith in these vague reports of concentrations in the HASA district. But I have had many reports from aJ-l over the place of a large fore with StT’IIB ibn SH 1 UD at HASA, and also of a concentratic at HAFAR al f AJ, where they say that Ibn SUUJD himself ha.s arrived, although I doubt that myself* he ATAIBAH still seem to be causing a good dea.l of trouble, but pernaps this move to HAFAR al BATIN is an indication that Ibn SU’UD thinks that if he can finish off DAWISH, the rest will oe easy '• I was very glad to get all your telegrams, for \vhich very many thanks. I thought it as well to let you know the gist of the information I have received on these events, although I am afraid you will disagree with a good deal of iU Still, having regard to the variety of sources from which I obtained my reports, I could not very well put aby other construction on the events. I am enclosing a note for Krs. Dickson in answer to her 1 s about some stores from ASKAR, which have left by boat Lieut.Colonel H«R. Political Agent KUWAIT*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/33</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/33</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File [10/4] British relations with Ibn Sa`ud: Ibn Sa`ud's complaint about aid given to rebels by King Faisal and Shaikh Ahmad; fighting between rebel and loyal forces; Battle of Injair</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-07T22:29:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (201 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 203; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-201; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to the British Government's relationship with Ibn Sa'ud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd]. Specifically, the correspondence concerns hostilities between the forces of Ibn Sa'ud and the Ikhwan during the rebellion led by Faisal al-Duwaish [Faysal al-Duwaysh], the movement of Ikhwan members and their followers into Kuwaiti territory, tensions between Ibn Sa'ud and Kuwait, and reports of support for the rebellion coming from the Government of Iraq.Much of the correspondence in the file is between British officials at the Political Agency in Kuwait, the Political Residency in Bushire and the High Commission in Iraq, but the file also contains copies of letters, in Arabic with English translations, from Ibn Sa'ud (including a letter of condolence after the death of Sir Gilbert Clayton, folios 138-141) and Fuad Bey Hamza, a diplomatic representative of Ibn Sa'ud's.In addition to correspondence, the file also contains a number of accounts of the Battle of Injayr (also spelt Inqayr) that took place on 5 October 1929 (folios 83-7 &amp; 96-100) and a hand-drawn sketch map of the events of the battle (folio 88).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Battle of Injayr (1929)</topic></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Fayṣal bin Sulṭān al-Dawīsh</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Ikhwan revolt (1927-1930)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>