<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054362.0x000027_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T00:10:06.034Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054362.0x000027_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/30, ff 49-51</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054362.0x000027</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/30, ff 49-51</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No 24 of 1823 from John Macleod, Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushere [Bushire] to William Newnham, Chief Secretary to the Government, Political Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1823/1823</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-09T02:23:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is acknowledging the instructions of the Bombay Government, dated 25 March 1823 (No 329 and No 393). It reports on how the Resident intends to enforce the provisions of the General Maritime Treaty 1820; it outlines a relaxation on the enforcement of paper work to be carried by Arab vessels (in other words, the Registers and Port Clearance), and explains why their strict enforcement may be counterproductive. It also recommends that the restriction on building fortifications on the coast is lifted.It explains that the difference between maritime warfare and piracy is difficult to define to Arab chiefs, and will be difficult for British officers to distinguish. Therefore, it is noted that there is the potential for a great deal of disturbances to occur in the Persian Gulf without giving the British cause to intervene.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054362.0x000027#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>