<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000e0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T02:55:59.114Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">- — - —- - — - SCTt ■ —^ - —*&lt;- I f* _ ■ 111 GOl^TI^imAL . No:C/209-15/2* k ,v&gt; Ip &gt;v v 'c , c -r Political Agency, Balirain,the 18th June 1933, From:- To: - Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch,I,A., Political A^ent, Bahrain, The Hon'blc the Political 'Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Sir, I have the honour to inform you that during my recent tour H.M.S 'Powey* anchored off sir Bu Na f ir Island to shelter from the wind on the 9th June 1933• A large numher of dhows (over seventy) were there for the same purpose. 2. The Shaikh of Sharjah's flag was flying from a flagstaff and there was a small hut at the 'base of the flagstaff, No signs of other 'buildings were to 'be seen, 3 # On the 10th June the Shaikh of Abu Dha'b i said that he understood that 'buildings were 'being made at Sir Bu Na'ir and asked that the Shaikh of Sharjah should be prevented from 'building there. The matter had 'been the subject of a dispute during the time of Sir Percy Cox. 4, On the 11th June the Shaikh of Dibai made a similar protest. 5, The Residency Agent informed me that there had been trouble in the time of Sir Percy Cox and he had decided that in the interests of peace no buildings should be constructed. The matter had again come up in the time of (2) S S c^z&gt;Lieutenant-Colonel Trevor,who had said that Government had, ^ no objection to the 'buildings being constructed. On hearing this the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi had Y /ritten a threatening letter to the Shaikh of Sharjah,who then gave up the idea. There is no question about sovereignty,which admittedly rests with SharJ ah, 6, In accordance with recent general instructions the Shaikh of Sharjah hoisted his flag on Sir Bu TTa'ir Island, and has apparently made this an opportunity for reverting to the plan of building there and creating a re-victualling base for the pearling fleets, 7. In each case (Abu Dhabi and Dibai) I said that I had no information,that I had seen no buildings except the hut at the flagstaff,but that I would report the matter to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, 8, I took an opportunity of telling the Shaikh of Sharjah that I had heard that he was thinking of building and that I believed that the question had been raised in the time of Sir Percy Cox and Lieutenant-Colonel Trevor. He said that he was not building now,but that he might do so in the future. 9. I do not know what took place in the past and submit the matter for your orders. On the meagre information before me,I would suggest that the Residency Agent might be instructed to remind the Shaikh of Sharjah that the question of building on Sir Bu ITa'ir Island gave rise to unpleasantness in the past and to advise him not to do anything which would upset his relations with his neighbours. 10. I would only add that I think that the Shaikh of Sharjah is acquiring rather an higher opinion of himself than (3)V/i 3. hard facts would wwrent, and it ie not impossi 'ble that he may embroil lumself in some foolish course of action unless he is carefully watched, I have the honour to te Sir, Your most obedient servant LYtnlt-Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain, F/*&gt; /$io /Sjz /&lt;}02 fi. V • -/ ■ 3 7 fiu e -'r — '/ /0 1jh . \S Ho.2f-3Of 1933. British Keaidenoy &amp; Oonsulate-OeaeraJ Buahlre t 1^ July 1933. i To 'JCUe Kesidenoy Agent, Shargah. After Oompliments. Ihen Oolonel Looh was on tour at A'bu Dhal)! and Ciatar recently the Shallchs of those places mentioned ^the Island of Sir Bu Ha'air. You // / mentioned that the matter had 'bee V* disoussed 'both in the time of Sir ^ __ that they had heard that the Shaikh C r ^&gt; y J- Of Shargah was 'building houses on Peroy dqz and also of the late 4 t/O t? Oolonel Trevor* I request that you will inform me of the number Any and date of^letter whioh may have &gt;v&gt;\ ^ 'been sent to you on this subject from the i^olitioal Kesident or of \ r ^ i if Y'! any report i^iioh you may have sent \ »\lr ~ to the Hesidenoy. U. 1. * \ Secretary to thff^olitical Hesident in the Persian Gulf.:io. 441% Dated* 22nd August 1933 From. The Residency Agent*Jhargah. To# The oeoretary to the Poi^ticai Resident in the Persain Guir. Bushire * After Gfompliments* Tith reference to your letter No 243 of the 19th July 1933 on the subject of the statement made to the Hon 'hie CJolonel Loch when he last visited the irucia] Goast,hy the Trucial Shaikhs saying that they had heard that the Ruler of ihargah intended to do repairs to the jir-^t)u-Hai # r Island^And that the ^on* ole Colonel Loch desires to have infonuation on this subject uecause this uuestion was discussed in the time ox Jir Percy Cox and v^ also in the time of the late Oolonel Trevor % I have/the honour to state that on receipt of your letter No&gt;243 I made searches for old letters in the archives of the Residency Agency ,and I found a lettei written from this Agency under No,689 dated 30th .3eptemher 1921 to the Hon # ble Ooloen Trevor and sent to him under its cover a letter from .3haikh Khalid hin Ahmad the then Ruler of Jhargah on this subject•In reply a letter was received from the First Assistant to the Political Resident under No 396 dated 13th Catcher 1921 saying that the Hon*hie the Pox\Ltical RQsidcntha^- had no objection in this respect t 1°^ i I enclose copy or the correspondence nerewith and beg to state that besides these I have not been able to see any other papers in this Agency.. The Ruler of ohargah continues reminding me aboul this matter and I tell him in reply that it is not good to make haste in the matter#. U.E. , 18-10-33.01 ^rom - ^he lesidenoy Agent, Shargah T q - The Political Resident Persian Oulf, Bushire. No.689 JJated 30th 3eptem'ber 1921. A. v. I heg to forward herewith a letter reoeived 'by me from Shaikh Khaled 'bin -\hinad, Tnief of 3Uargah, stating that the respeota'ble merchants of his town who are engaged in diving 'business ask him to 'build a reservoir for tnem in the island of 3eer Bunair wiioh belongs to him to reserve water at the time of raining so tiiat r.is subjects take water in the next diving season from the island. The Jiiaikh requested me to ask you if you have any objection in this matter. In fact the merchants who deal with divers experience much trouble in carrying water and food such as dates, rice and firewood to tne divine 'hanks 'because some of them reach the divers and some of them spoil at sea on account of strong winds. Letter dated 20th Moharram 1340 (23-9-31) from Shaikh Khaled hin Ahmad, Jhief of ohargah, to the Residency Agent, Shargah. A.J. l 'beg to inform you that the respectable men of my town who deal witn divers came to me and stated that for the last three years they have suffered much loss because most of the tilings such as water, dates, etc. that they have sent to the divers at the diving banks got spoiled and asked me to construct a few wells or a reservoir in my island Seer ^unair, to be ready for water at the time of raining. 1 deem it necessary to enquire from His honour, Colonel Trevor, the Resident and Consul General, whether the (rovernment object to me or not. i hope you will not neglect a .i this action is only to avoid further trouble and losses on the divers my subj ects.XL ■ NO. 396 of 1921. British -Hesidency iz Consulate General, i^uahire, loth October 195^. \ ^ \ i - .^N To The Residency Agent, Shargah. A ^ A • j • '7ith reference to your letter Wo.689 dated 30th oeptem'ber 1921, 1 am directed to inform you that the Political Resident has no objection to the Shaikh of Shargah constructing a reservoir in the Island of 3ir Ahu JMa'air. Major, od. i ?*.Gr. J.Anson Secretary to the Political Resident. j■■CONFIDENTIAL. i; ' ^ ^ Ko G/201 of 1933. T&lt;^ b\ ✓ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-nlf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Clamp, Bahrain. Dated.. £61 tr 'N o v emt'er • 'Vtt 3. — Jy. /■ Reference to previous correspondence Bahrain letter No•0/209, dated the 18th Jfine 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter Ko.0/200 dated the 25th November 1933 to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. Intention of the Shaikh of Sharjah to 'btild on the Island of Sir Bu Ka'Jr.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000e0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/251</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000e0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/251</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'14/102 I Sir Abu Nu`air'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1902/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:15:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file. There are file notes at the back of the file explaining how the file is arranged.</extent><extent>Foliation. The foliation sequence starts on front cover and continues to back cover. It consists of uncircled numbers in the top right-hand corner.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence relating to the island of Sir Abu Nu'ayr[Şīr Bū Nu‘ayr],its use and ownership. It consists mainly of letters in Arabic with English translations. The main correspondents are Shaikh Za'id bin Khalifah, Chief of Abu Dhabi; Political Resident Persian Gulf; Residency Agent, Sharjah. Most of the correspondence is dated 1902 or 1933; there are also copies of letters from 1921 which discuss the building of a water supply for divers. Letters discuss how the Shaikh of Sharjah claimed the island and the concerns of Shaikh Za'id bin Khalifah of Abu Dhabi over this claim. Issues discussed are whether the islands have remained uninhabited and whether a settlement could be a threat to Abu Dhabi and lead to a breach of the maritime peace. One letter discusses how the sale of salt from the island supports the claim of Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Sir Abu Nu'air </geographic></subject><subject><topic>Territorial disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000e0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>