<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000170_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:33:13.544Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">i &lt;D No. Of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, IBth Rajab, 1366 May 31, 1947. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - Dr. Snow, the State Medical Officer, is going on leave to England this summer for four months, from July till October. 2. Would it be possible for Dr. Steele to take over the medical duties in the European ward of the Government Hospital during Dr. Snow’s absence? This duty would entail a morning and evening round of the European cases in this ward which rarely number more than 7 or 8, and the making up and sending of bills to Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie 8c Co. 3. It is suggested that an allowance of Rs.300/- per month should be paid to Dr. Steele for these duties. 4. In case of operative work Dr. Harrison would be called in and would receive remuneration at usual operation rates. Adviser to the Government. S.Z. Confidential. Bahrain receipt. N»...«7»7s~_ Dat e a. 6(ID No.C/653. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 3th of June, 1947. To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . mbmorandum . The Bahrain Government have informed me that Dr. Snow, the State Medical officer, is going to the United Kingdom on four months' leave this summer, from July to October. They enquire whether it would be possible for Dr. Steele to take over the medical duties in the European Ward of the Government Hospital during Dr. Snow’s absence. They would entail a morning and evening round of the ward, and the making up and sending of bills to Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Company. There are rarely more than 7 or 8 patients at a time in the European Ward. 2. They suggest that Dr. Steele should be paid an allowance of Rs.300/- a month for this work. Dr. Harrison would be called in for surgical cases, and would be paid the usual operation rates. 3. I should be grateful to know whether there is any objection to this arrangement. Sd./- C.J. PELLY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. J for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. NS.No.1529-54/2. To PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The 2nd July, 1947• The Political Agent, Bahrain. f - ,.. € MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No dated the 8th.June, 1947. 2. There is no objection to the arrangement proposed. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf N®. Confidential. BAHRAIN R^oetRT. Art. - ^ v , , &gt;&lt; vNo.C/775. / / i ( , ) POLITICAL AGENCY To w BAHRAIN. The 6th of July, 1947. The Acting Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bah rain,. MSLi ORAN DDK . Reference paragraphs 2 and 3 of your Memorandum No.1436-10, dated the 31st of May, 1947, on the subject of Dr. Steele's taking over the medical duties in the European Ward of the Bahrain Government Hospital during Dr. Snow's absence. 2. There is no objection to the arrangement proposed ATTESTED. Sd./- C.J. FELLY political Agent, Bahrain for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. f)e. Copy to Captain M.L.A. Steele, I.M.D., together with a copy of the memorandum under reference.of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Dulqaada £8, 1366 October 1£, 1947. H. B. M f s Political Agent Bahrain. Memorandum: - Please refer to paragraph 3 of your memorandum No* c/593 dated 19th May 1947. His Highness Shaikh Sulman wishes to offer a further four years* contract to Dr. R.H.B. Snow, the State Medical Officer. Before the matter is taken up with Dr. Snow, I should be grqteful if you would let me have the approval of Hon’ble the Political Resident to the extension. His present contract expires on 12th March 1948. Adviser to the Government IJ. 1AUJK711 U . Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ^ f nu u . /1:.'.. 1.•••«•*• M s.z 1)&amp;t,eD.O. Ho.C/1055. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 28th of October, 1947. Dear Sir Rupert, please refer to Agency Memorandum Ho. C/1134, dated the 30th July, 1944. 2. Belgrave has informed me that His Highness wishes to offer a further four years’ contract to Snow, who will complete his current contract on the 12th March, 1948. Snow will be 42 years of age when his current contract expires. 3. The Bahrain Government are, I feel, extremely fortunate to have a man like Snow, and I recommend that the extension suggested be approved. 4 . t am not sure whether it is customary for the political Agent to suggest amendments to these contracts but the provision for passages to India for the State ^ Medical Officer's annual leave appears to be^out of aa^e now. and perhaps it would be more suitable if passages for the Lebanon or even Southern Europe or Switzerland were allowed for instead. Your s sinc erely. The Hon'ble Lt-Col. Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. K.C.I.E., NS. 3 sc.(ORIGINAL ON FILS 32/22) Extract from demi-official letter No.1809-3, dated 20.10. f 47 from the Hon'ble Lt-Col. Sir Rupert Ray, K.C.I.E., C.3.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to G«'N. Jackson, Esq., M.B.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. XX XX jj % . XX 3. Reference paragraph 8 please inform the Bahrain Government that experience has shorn that it is not possible for the Quarantine Medical Officer to deputize as the Government’s Chief Medical Officer and perform his own functions properly at the same time and that we regret therefore that it is unlikely that we shall be able to consent to a similar arrangement being made on any future occasion.4/a-j (ORIGINAL ON FILE 32/22) Extract from demi-official letter No. C/1021 dated ch^ 15th of October, 1947, from G.N. Jackson^ Ssq. ^ M^3E. Political Agent, Bahrain,- to the Hon’ble Lt-Col. Sir Ruper o Hay, /.C.I.E.,. C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. xx xx xx xx ^^ i consider also that the Adviser should be warned now that it will not again be' possible to lend the ser vices of the Agency Surgeon to deputize for the Bahrain Government’s Chief Medical Officer, because the Agency • Surgeon already has more than enough work of his own .No. C/1064 political Agency, Bahrain. The 2nd of November, 1947 Memorandum To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, B a h r a i n. Reference correspondence ending with my memorandum No. C/775, dated the 6th of July, 1947. 2. Experience has shown that it is too much for one man to deputize, during the hot weather, for Dr. Snow when he goes on leave in addition to performing the duties of Quarantine Medical Officer and Agency Surgeon which are already onerous. 3. It is regretted, therefore, that it is unlikely that the arrangement made this summer will be permitted on any future occasion. Sd./- G.N. JACKSON Political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, [c. Bahrain. NS.S.O. Mo. 2318-54/2 . h (iC PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 3rd November, 1947. (VjLw s Please refer to youf^eml-official letter No. C/1055 dated 28th October, 1947, regarding Snow*s contract. 2. The extension suggested may be approved. 3. Reference paragraph 4 of your letter. In view of the saving clause which already exists vide''paragraph 3 of clause 8 of Dr. Snow’s contract, I doubt if any amendment is really necessary. If any officer^ wished to proceed to the Lebanon instead of India he would probably make his own arrangement with the Bahrain Government. If however you can devise a formula more in accordance with present conditions please do so and submit it to me for approval. G.N. Jackson, Esquire, M.B.E., The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Confidential. BAHRAIN REOETFT.C/1113 No. political Agency, Bahrain, The 17th of November, 1947. To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. MBMOBANJUM. ✓ Reference your Memorandum No.2385-10, dated the 12th October, 1947. rjj 2. The Hon’ble the political Resident has approved the extension of Dr. Snow’s contract for a further four years from the 13th March, 1948. ATTESTED. for Assistant Political Agent Bahrain. 3d./- G.N. JACKSON Political Agent, Bahrain. NS.£ I 7 11 A' /&lt;? of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 28th Dulhaj, 1366 November 10, 1947 With reference to your memorandum No. C/1064 dated End November 1947, the Bahrain Government is very grateful for your cooperation in allowing Dr. Steele to assist in the Government Hospital during the absence on leave of the State Medical Officer but I would like to point out that Dr. Steele did not deputize for Dr. Snow. All the admininstration of the Medical Department was undertaken during Dr. Snow * s absence by the Lady Medical Officer, Dr. Doeg. Dr. Steele 1 s work at the hospital was about an hour a day and Dr. Bhandarkar carried out the quarantine work on many of the ships which visited Bahrain during this period. I do not wish to give the impression that Dr. Steele’s services were not appreciated but I feel that it should be mentioned that Dr. Doeg had to bear the main brunt of the work. H. B. M’3 Political Agent Bahrain. Memor andum: - Adviser to the Government S.Z Confidential■ • No. C/271 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 16th March, 1948 The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: and has the honour to send him a copy of the under mentioned document with the remark that the arrange ment requested was sanctioned by the Political Agent in anticipation of the Hon'ble the political Resident’s approval. The Hon’Die the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain Reference to previous Qorrespondence: Description of Enclosure. NAME &amp; DATE SUBJECT Memorandum dated 12.3.48 from the State Medical Officer, Bahrain Govern ment, to the political Agent, Bahrain.From T EXPRESS L ETTE R Political Resident, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.649-S Dated, BAHRAIN, the 24th March, 1948. A Reference your Printed Letter ✓ ^ No.C/271 dated the 16th March, 1948. Permission granted for Dr. Steele to officiate in place of Dr. Snow. 2. In the circumstances I fully approve your action. Your attention is however called to paragraph 3 of my demi-official letter No.l8Q9-S dated the 20th October 1947 to Jackson. 3d/- W.R. Hay, 5 1 ATTESTED For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ConfidantiaL BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ..'..Date,&amp; No v /7V'/^-/'^ of 1367 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 25th Dulhaj, 1367 October 28, 1948. Reference your memorand , L113 dated 17th November 1947. Dr. R.H.B. Snow asked for an extension of his contract for two years only and not four years. His Highness approved of the extension. H. B. M’s Political Agent Bahrain. S . /D Memorandum: - Adviser to the Government $0 —S. 0. $0. C/R-218. Dear Sir Rupert, Will yon resting with your demi-official letter No. 2318-54/2, dated the Rrd November, 1947, to Jackson? 2. Belgrave has now informed me that Snow asked for an extension of his contract for two years only, and not four years, and that His Highness has approved of the extension for two years. Yours sincerely, His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE, GSI, Political Residert, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. © POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHMIE,© INDIA OFFICE RECORDS | MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000170_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/905</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000170</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/905</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 42/7 (6/37) Dr R.H.B. Snow, State Medical Officer, Bahrain Govt'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-13T21:12:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (21 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-12; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding the contract and leave arrangements of Dr Richard Henry Barter Snow, State Medical Officer for the Government of Bahrain. The majority of the correspondence is between Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; the Political Agency in Bahrain; and the Political Residency in Bushire (Bahrain after 1947).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Medical personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000170#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>