<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-09T10:50:21.080Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I 3® V a -•y Telegram. •^rom To Secretary of State for India. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Repeated to Political Agent, Muscat No 2987 Dated 21st September 1935 Received 21.9.1935 Cable reorganisation. Letter from Company giving details of operations at Muscat where Cable Ship is due to arrive about October 1st has been sent by Air Mail of September 20th to India Bushire and Muscat.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 738-S of 1935. POLiTiCAi- ril&gt; CON.FlI&gt;S^ T1 L RECORD ——* p i*«. ”4. iiCI. iJjo U-K. N-\ /?9 H. B, U’8 ^SUiA- 1 ’. v ' ;?c:T a The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat his com- and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 19th September 1935. Dated Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Political Resident’s telegram No.753 of 2nd September 1935. 2. Political Resident’s telegram No.757 of 4th September 1935. 3. Government of Bombay tele gram dated the 9th September 1935. 4. Political Resident’s telegram No.T/2C0 of 11th September 1935. Subject. Cable and wireless reorganization in the Persian Gulf.Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political, Muscat, 2To. 753. Dated the 2nd September 1935, Confidential. Dec ode yourself• Please communicate following: message to Sultan Q from me and telegraph Sultan’s reply begins: As part of reorganisation of cable communications in Persian Gulf to be introduced shortly it is proposed to link Muscat with cable system by cable running direct from Karachi to Muscat and thence to Bushire instead ol the present connection. I hope that Your Highness will see no objection to the small alteration in cable landings at Muscat involved by this improvement. I should be grateful for Your Highness’s reply which l have instructed the Agency office to telegraph to me• End s• -Britc onsul.0 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire. To The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political and Reforms Department,Bombay. No* 757• Bated the 4th September 1935. Import ant. Grateful if you would kindly communicate following to Sultan of Muscat due to arrive Bombay 5th September on s.s.Bamora and telegraph Sultan’s reply begins; »As part of reorganisation of cable communications in Persian Gulf to be introduced shortly it is proposed to link Muscat with cable system by cable running direct from Karachi to Muscat and thence to Buhhire instead of the present connection. I hope that Your Highness will see no objection to the small alteration in cable landings at Muscat involved by this improvement. I should be grateful for Your Highness’s reply which I have asked the Government of Bombay to telegraph to me. End s• -Resident•Telegram G.T.C. From Government of Bombay, Bombay. To Political Resident, Bushire. Unnumbered» Dated the 9th September 1935. (Relayed under Bushire telegram No.772 dated and received 10th September 1935). Your telegram 757 of September 4th regarding introduction of cable communications in Persian Gulf. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat has no objection to the proposed alteration being carried out immediately. He respectfully requests that letter informing him of details be sent him to which he will reply. - RestisTelegram xx From Political Resident, at Shiraz. &lt;p 0 Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Government of India, Simla. H.M.*8 Minister, Tehran. No.T/200. Dated the 11th September 1935. My telegram of 31st August T 198. Sultan of Muscat has no objection to proposed alteration in cable being carried out immediately. He asks for letter informing him of details. -Resident•By Air Mail. P.Z.foU'TS'' 19 m ii?» Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to bv Mail./I IS p.2,6475/35. OABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED, Electra House, Victoria Embankment, London, W.G, 2, JVgr/L/K. 13th September 1935. Dear Mr. Glauson, I have to thank you for your letters P.Z.6322 and 6433 of the 11th ana 12th instant regarding the Company's plans for reorganisation of the communications system in the Persian Gulf. My Company is pleased to note tjaat the sheikh of Bahrein welcomes the proposed cable connection between the Island and Bushire and the enlargement of the Company's wireless station. We do not anticipate that any more land will be required as that in present occupation of the Company should be more than sufficient to meet our requirements* It is noted from your letter of the 12th instant that the sultan of Muscat has no objection to the proposed alterations in regard to the cables landing at Muscat and I have pleasure in appending herewith a brief outline of the contemplated alterations at that place, for communication to the sultan. You will note from the tentative programme that the ship will call at Muscat first in order to pick up a letter containing the fullest instructions, which is being s^nt by air mail to-day, and in addition we will instruct the Commander of the ship to call on the Political Agont and explain to him in detail exactly what it is proposed to do after having examined the landing place and the lead in of the cables at Muscat. Regarding/t - a - Regarding tne withdrawal from Persian territory at Jask, Chartar ana Ren jam as covered in the enclosed programme, my Company woula he glad if His majesty' s Government could take any action which may facilitate the entrance and departure of the ship at these points and for the embarking of instruments, stores ana staff which it may be necessary to transport for use at muscat and Bahrein. It is noted tnat tne Persian Government have made enquiries regarding the purchase of the wireless installations at Henjam, Lingah and Bushire. my company has no claim on the material comprising the wireless installations at Henjam and Lingah, whicn are of spark transmission type and therefore not in a position to be used for wireless transmission. However, my company would be reluctant to see these stations pass into the hands of the Persian Government ana would prefer that they should be dismantled. As regards Bushire wireless station the apparatus at present in use has been manufactured locally by our own staff in order to enable communication to be carried on on a continuous wave since the spark apparatus became obsolete. As stipulated in your letter of the 13th June 1935, wireless communication at Bushire will be maintained until the reorganisation of the cable system has been completed, and it is possible that it might be found advantageous to continue using this station for a further period so long as the existing temporary apparatus continues to function with reasonable efficiency, but in any case my Company would be reluctant to see this station pass into the hands of the Persian Government or any other party, more//u © more especially as tne land, ana buildings comprising tiie wireless station are on the same site as the cable station• My I again refer to your letter of the 13th June in connection with the reference in the last paragraph to the disposal of the landline at present operated by my company in Persian territory, perhaps you would be sd good as to inform me whether this line is to be handed over to the Persian Government, subject to the restriction referred to in my letter of the 18th June* 1935. As regards the general programme of procedure, it is anticipated that the Cable ship 'Lady Denison-Pender' should arrive at Muscat on or about October 1st to pick up the letter of instructions wnich is being forwarded there by air mail. At the same time the ship will survey the landing place for the cables and the Commander will be instructed to get into touch with tne political Agent at Muscat. Operations at Muscat . A new cable shore-end to be landed on the beach at a position opposite the British Consulate building and in close proximity to the existijqg shore-end of the Muscat cable. The new shore-end will follow the route of the existing trench line from the beach to the Company*s Office at Muscat. No alteration will be necessary to the Muscat end of the cable now running to Jask but the line will be disconnected at Jask and joined through at sea making a direct connection with Bushire. When the alterations are completed Muscat will be :n direct telegraphic communication with Karachi on the one side and Bushire on the other side* wnich should prove/4 prove of consiaeralDle advantage to the Government and the coirirnercial comriunity at Muscat, fhe existing telegraph staff at Muscat will he reinforced hy prohahly three more telegraph operators. The general programme is set out in the enclosed statement. Yours sincerely, (3d. ) NOEL J.C. LAW SON» Manager. Cable and Wireless Limited. M«J. Clauson, Esq., B.A., India Office, Whitehall, 3. W. 1.Persian G-ull Reorganisation — programme. October 1st C.3.'Lady Denison-pender' due to arrive at Muscat to pick up letter of instructions and to survey landing place for shore-end of the Karachi cable. Commanding Officer will get in touch with political Agent at Muscat. October 2nd. Ship arrives at Jask to take on board staff, instruments ana stores and closes down the telegraph office. If local transport is possible the staff ana instruments from Charbar will also embark at Jask, otherwise the ship will proceed to Charbar and pick them up. October 2/3. Charbar telegraph station will be closed. October 4/5. Ship returns to Muscat to land additional operators, personal effects, instruments, etc. October 5th. ship proceeds on diversion of the Karachi cable into Muscat, which should be completed about October 9th or 10th. October 11th. ship arrives at a position off the coast at Jask and proceeds to pick up and join through the cables at sea to form a direct cable Muscat to Bushire. October 12/13.The above connection should be completed and th lines of communication Karachi-Muscat-Bushire should be available for traffic. October 15/16.ship arrives at Henjam, embarks local staff, instruments,, stores and materials and closes down Henjam telegraph station. Next proceeds to Bahrein Island to land tele graph operators and the necessary instruments for working the projected new cable section BeJarein-Bushire. October 19th. ship aue to arrive at Bahrein; surveys landing place for new cable, and October 20/21.should leave for Abadan to refuel. After refuelling ship will repair Fao-Bushire No.l cable. Next proceeds to a position off Henjam and conmences to pick up part of the nenjam- Bushire cable to a position well outside Persian territorial waters where tne cable will be diverted ana re-laid towards Bahrein Island. October 31st. It is anticipated that tne whole of the foregoing should be completed by this date, weather permitting. The ship will then proceed to pick up the remaining abandoned portions of the cables but will be instructed to avoid making contact with any of the ports on the Persian coast after withdrawal and closing down/down of the Branches at Jask, Charhar ana Henjam on tne respective dates given in the progruinme. The dates ^iven Cc.n only Pc considered as approximate as tney are dependent on weather conditions ana any unforeseen circumstances which may arise during the course of operations. (Intd.) N.J.C.L.F»Z.6475/35. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED, Electra House, Victoria Embankment, London, V/*C. 2. Ljgr/L/K. 13th September 1935. Dear Mr. Clauson, I have to thank you for your letters P.Z.6322 and 6433 of the 11th ana 12th instant regaraing the Company's plans for reorganisation of the communications system in the Persian Gulf. My Company is pleased to note that the sheikh of Bahrein welcomes the proposea cable connection between the Island and Bushire and the enlargement of the Company's wireless station. We do not anticipate that any more land will be required as that in present occupation of the Company shoula be more than sufficient to meet our requirements. It is noted from your letter of the 12th instant that the sultan of Mluscat has no objection to the proposed alterations in regard to the cables landing at Muscat and I have pleasure in appending herewith a brief outline of the contemplated alterations at that place, for communication to the sultan. You will note from the tentative programme that the ship will call at Muscat first in order to pick up a letter containing the fullest instructions, which is being s^nt by air mail to-day, and in addition we will instruct the Commander of the ship to call on the political Agent and explain to him in detail exactly what it is proposed to do after having examined the landing place ana the lead in of the cables at Muscat. Regarding/Ptegarciing tae withdrawal from Persian territory at Jask, Charhar ana henjsan as covered in the enclosed prograrime, my Company woula he glad if His Lajesty’s Government could take any action which may facilitate the entrance and departure of tne ship at these points and for the embarking of instruments, stores ana staff which it may he necessary to transport for use at Muscat and Bahrein. It is noted tnat tne Persian Government have made enquiries regarding the purchase of the wireless installations at Henjam, Lingah and Bushire. % Company has no claim on the material comprising the wireless installations at Henjam and Lingah, whicn are of spark transmission type and therefore not in a position to he used for wireless transmission. However, my company would he reluctant to see these stations pass into the hands of the Persian Government ana would prefer that they should he dismantled. As regards Bushire wireless station the apparatus at present in use has been manufactured locally by our own staff in order to enable communication to he carried on on a continuous wave since the spark apparatus became obsolete. As stipulated in your letter of the 13th June 1935, wireless communication at Bushire will he maintained until the reorganisation of the cable system has been completed, and it is possible that it might be found advantageous to continue using this station for a further period so long as the existing temporary apparatus continues to function with reasonable efficiency, but in any case my Company would be reluctant to see this station pass into the hands of the Persian Government or any otner party, more/3 more especially as tne iana ana buildings comprising the wireless station are on the same site as the cable station• May I again refer to your letter of the 13th June in connection with the reference in the last paragraph to the aisposal of the lanaline at present operated by my Company in Persian territory, perhaps you would be ao good as to inform me whether this line is to be handed over to the Persian Government, subject to the restriction referred to in my letter of the 18th June, 1935. As regaras the general programme of proceaure, it is anticipated that the Cable ship 'Lady Denison-Pender' shoula arrive at Muscat on or about October 1st to pick up the letter of instructions which is being forwarded there by air mail. At the same time the ship will survey the landing place for the cables and the Commander will be instructed to get into touch with tne political Agent at Muscat. Operations at Muscat . A new cable shore-end to ba landed on the beach at a position opposite the British Consulate buiiaing and in close proximity to the exisohqg shore-end of the Muscat cable. Jhe new shore-end will follow the route of the existing trench line from the beach to the Company's Office at Muscat. No alteration will be necessary to the Muscat end of the cable now running to Jask but the line will be disconnected at Jask and joined through at sea making a direct connection with Bushire. When the alterations are completed Muscat will be in direct telegraphic communication with Karachi on the one side and Bushire on the other side, wnich should prove/prove of considerable advantage to the Government and the commercial community at Muscat. The existing telegraph staff at Muscat will he reinforced by probably three more telegraph operators. The general programme is set out in the enclosed statement. Yours sincerely, (Sh. ) NOEL J.C. LAWSON. Manager. Gable and y/ireless Limited. M«J. Clauson, Esq., B.A., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1.Persian Gulf ReorRariisation — programme. October 1st C. 3.''Lady Denison-P8n(ier' , due to arrive at Muscat to pick up letter of instructions and to survey landing place for stiore-end of the Karachi cable 8 Commanding Officer will get in touch with political Agent at Muscat. October 2nd. Ship arrives at Jask to take on board staff, instruments ana stores and closes down the telegraph office. If local transport is possible the staff and instruments from Charbar will also embark at Jask, otherwise the ship will proceed to Charbar and pick them up. October 2/3. Charbar telegraph station will be closed. October 4/5. Ship returns to Muscat to land additional operators, personal effects, instruments, etc. October 5th. Ship proceeds on diversion of the Karachi cable into Muscat, which should be completed about October 9th or 10th. October 11th. ship arrives at a position off the coast at Jask ana proceeds to pick up and join through the cables at sea to form a direct cable Muscat to Bushire. October 12/13.The above connection should be completed and th lines of communication Kurachi-Muscat-Bushire should be available for traffic. October 15/16.ship arrives at Henjam, embarks local staff, instruments,, stores and materials and closes down Henjam telegraph station. Next proceeds to Bahrein Island to land tele graph operators and the necessary instruments for working the projected new cable section Bahrein-Bushire. October 19th. Ship due to arrive at Bahrein; surveys landing place for new cable, and October 20/21.should leave for Abadan to refuel. After refuelling ship will repair Fao-Bushire No.l cable* Next proceeds to a position off Henjam and commences to pick up part of the nenjsm- Bushire cable to a position well outside Persian territorial waters where the cable will be diverted ana re-laid towards Bahrein Island. October 31st. It is anticipated that tne whole of the foregoing should be completed by this date, weather permitting. The ship will then proceed to pick up the remaining abandoned portions of the cables but will be instructed to avoid making contact with any of the ports on the Persian coast after withdrawal and closing down/I 1 1 Ho. C/197 Political agency &amp; H.M’s consulate, Muscat, the 16th November 1936. \ To P.E. Bunker, isquire, Manager Persian Gulf section, Cable cc Wireless Limited. I have received a telegram from the Political Resident Bushire the substance of which as given below I have been instructed to communicate to you. 2. The Persian Government state (1) that they agree to Henjam station being closed, (2) The Company's offer to one or other of the overland lines from Jask to Charbar and Gwadur with V... and dependencies is accepted with thanks, (3) The Ministry of Posts and Telegraphs will try to insure within 2 years telegraphic communication with Jask; after however^the expiration of this period in the event of the land lines to Jask not having been completed, tair the Persian Government expects the Company to main** the Cable station until land lines are ready. 3. Instructions to permit exportation of surplus stores, accessories and apparatus have been sent. The export of arms, however, cannot be allowed until 'special permission has been obtained by Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Further information on this point is promised shortly.© Telegram. H* \ rrom - political, Bahrain. To - Political, Muscat. ^,0. - 160. uated l^th deceived loth ijovemoer Following from Political Resident November 12th i,o.948 begins, minister -telegraphs that reply now received from Persian vjov eminent states that they agree to closing of Henjam station. ‘g. They accept with thanks Company’s offer to one or other of the overland Lines fror^ask to Charbar and Gwadur with buildings and dependencies, d. ministry of msts and Telegraphs will try to ensure telegraphic communication with Cask within two years. If however after expiration of this period land lines to Jask have not been completed Persian Government! will expect that Company will maintain ^able otation until land lines are ready. 4. Instructions have been sent to permit exportation of surplus stores, accessories and apparatus, export of arms however cannot be allowed until ’’special permission”has been obtained by ministry of Foreign Affairs, further note is promised shortly on this point. Please communicate substance to Bunker. He should reach miscat on down slow mail November 14th. political.The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to ?ne Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- Reference to previous correspondence: Residency memorandum ^0,496-3 dated tne 2dtn tfune 1937, to tne Secretary to tne government or India, eternal Al'iairs lepartmefat, JNew Delni. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Sir T. ^owle* s Note dated tne 24tn September 1937, to Mr.M.J.Clauson. Kequest or Sultan or muscat for payment by Cable and •vireless limited ror telegrapn facilities at muscat.Request of the Sultan of Muscat for payment from Cable and Wireless for the use of his territory traversed by the Company^ cables Mr. Clauson* In view of the correspondence now before me I have somewhat revised the viev/s expressed in my memo randum No. 499-S of the 25th June, P.Z.4376/37. 2. I am still of opinion that the Sultan fey tech nically is due rent from the Company and that appears to be the general view of the other authorities concerned. On the other hand, as between His Majesty's Government and the Company, the question of rent would seem to put the former in a somewhat awkward position, vide paragraph 2 of the Secretary, E.&amp; 0. Department's note of the 17th September, P.Z. 6076/37 • The Imperial Communication's Advisory Committee refer to the same point, vide para graph 3 of their letter of the 14th September. 3. It is true that in certain cases (the Azores one quoted in G.P.O. letter of the lOfh September, P.Z.6046/ 37 and the annual royalty of Rs. 8,000 referred t o in paragraph 2 of E. &amp; 0. note of the 17th September) subs tantial payments have been made for the use of territory traversed by foreign cables. At the same time, the actual position in Muscat is that for all practical purposes our that State is under/protection and that the cable is largely used by the Political Agent there in the interest of the Sultan and his Government, both in this connection and in othe -s. During the last five years or so for instance we have come tc the assistance of the Sultan on two important occasions against rebellious Sheikhs in his territory. On one occasion we actually used armSjLforce(at Khassab) and on the other, mobilised sloops and aircraft (at Sur) the threat of which was sufficient* We would not have been able to do this unless there had been telegraphic communication with the outside world. I think this argument, together with the precedent of Rs. 10 rent paid by the Government of India to the Com pany for landing at Karachi ( vide paragraph 2 of E.&amp;.O. note of the 17th September) and any others of a similar nature which could be dug up, would carry weight with the Sultan and might induce him to be content with a nominal rent annually. This would presumably satisfy the Com pany, ( vide the last paragraph of Imperial Communication Advisory Committee^ letter of the 14th September). 4 . I suggest that the next step might be to infom the Company of the Sultan’s request and see what their reaction is, after which I shall be glad to discuss the matter with them as suggested by you in your note of the 11th September, P.Z. 6046/37. After that the matter might betaken up with the Sultan on the lines indicated in my paragraph 3 above. Sd/- T.C. Fowle. 24/9 Indi a Office, London.No. 108-S of 1938 CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his cem ents to The Political A^ent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (31). confidential record ll^l British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. H . B. I .]'8 fl'&amp;'bijtOf; MUSCAT Dated. 2 n&amp;. Utb a«y. .19.38.« Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter Ub.F.Z.7914/37 The Sultan of Muscats dated the 5th January 1938, request for an annual payment London, from India Office/to the in respect of the Gables Secretary to the Government landing in his territory, of India, External Affairs Department, -New Delhi ^ and enclosuresP.Z. 7914/37. I PD IA CD •ICE, By Air Mail. 5th January 1938. Sir, I am directed By the Secretary of State to refer to the Government of India’s Express Letter ITo.D. 2810-L T /37 of the 9th August, regarding the Sultan of Muscat’s request for an annual payment in respect of the Cables landing in his territory, and to forward, for the information of the / Government of India, copy of the marginally noted / correspondence on the subject. Letter to General Post Office, dated ) 28th August. ) A copy of a note dated 24th September by Sir Trenchard From General Post Office, dated ) 10th September. ) From Treasury, dated 16th September ) and enclosures. ) Fowle is also enclosed. To Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., dated 25th Sept ember. I am to request that, if From Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. dated 2nd ) December. ) the Government of India see no To Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., dated 5th ) January 1938. ) objection, the Political Resident may be instructed to discuss the matter with the Sultanate authorities, in the light of the views expressed in the letter dated 2nd December from Cable and Wireless Limited. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department. J. p, QfBSOh.7914/57. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.^.l. # 5tli JanuarjT- 1958. Dear Mr.Farmer, Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 2nd December (reference S.E.C/T/P.3.) about the Sultan of Muscat’s request for an annual payment in respect of the cables landing in his territory. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf will be instructed to discuss the matter with the Sultanate authorities, in the light of the views expressed in your letter, and a further communication on the subject will be addressed to you in due course. I should add, however, that the Sultan recently started on a world tour, and it is possible that the matter may have to be held in abeyance until he returns to Muscat about May 1958. As regards Fao, we suggest that you should take up this matter direct with the Foreign Office, to whom a copy of the correspondence is being sent. Yours sincerely, Farmer , Esq. , Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Electra House , Victoria Embankment, W.C . 2.J i P.Z.7914/37. ^ «, — - *1 sec/t/pb. Dear Mr .Gibs on , CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED, ELECTRA HOUSE, VICTORIA EMBANKMENT, LONDON, W.C.2. 2nd December 1937. PERSIAN GTILE LICEITCES. We would refer to Mr.Clauson’s letter to Captain Lawson of the 25th September last (Reference P.Z.6046/37) and to the conversation which he had with you and Sir Trenchard Fowle on the 21st October on the subject of the Sultan of Muscat’s request for an annual payment in respect of the cables landing in his territory. He has, I understand, already explained to you that the question of landing rights, etc., in the Gulf has recently been under consideration here; hence the delay in the present instance which, it is hoped, has caused you no inconvenience. It is quite probable that this request has arisen '-N as the result of the diversion of the Task end of the Karachi cable into Muscat in 1935, although His Highness's approval was previously sought and conveyed to us, it will be recalled, in Mr.Clausen's letter of the 12th September 1935. Por the right to land cables at other places throughout its system, the Company generally speaking pays only a nominal consideration, e.g. for those stations which fall within the control of the Colonial Office an annual fee of £1 per cable is charged, whilst, in the case of A.den, Bombay, Karachi and Madras, a licence fee of Rs.10 per annum is payable, irrespective of the number of cables. There/ J.P.Gibson, Esq. India Office.I There is also the question of Customs Cuties paid on the apparatus and stores used at the cable station. During the past year a considerable amount of apparatus has been imported into Muscat in order to improve the system and, as a result, we have, unlike our predecessors, the Indo-European Telegraph Department, been paying Customs Duties at that pla.ce. We are not prepared to dispute His Highness’s right to collect such dues on a reasonable basis although we consider that, in our position a,s successors to the Department, we should continue to be accorded the same privileges as were formerly enjoyed by the Department. This we feel, applies equally well to the licence question. However, if His Highness would be satisfied with a nominal fee, in the same way as is paid for similar rights in the , Dominions and Colonies, etc. , we would not object to such payment, nor to the payment of Customs Duties on a reasonable basis, but, in return, we should be glad if His Highness would grant a formal licence covering a period of 25 years. We would be pleased to prepare the draft of such a licence for submission to His Highness if this course is considered desirable. ■^e should like to take advantage of this opportunity also to mention the question of our position in Fao. This was one of the cable stations included in the Gulf assets transferred to the Company from the Indo Department, at the time, as you know, when Iraq was a Mandated Territory. Chiefly for this reason, the question of a licence in respect oi the cable was not pursued but, since this country has now become an Independent State, it occurs to us that, strictly speaking/speaking, our position there should 'be regularised. In the circumstances, we should, therefore, be obliged if, at your convenience, you would be good enough to favour us with your opinion a„s to what steps, if any, might now be taken in the matter of seeking a i orma3. licence for the cable landing in this territory. • Yours sincerely, S.G. FARMER./ ?. Z . 6046/37. IlvDIA OFFICE, ECU TEH ALL , S.W.l. 25th September 1S37. Fear Captain Lawson, I enclose a copy of a letter dated the 27th May from the Sultan of Muscat to the local Political Agent in which His Highness asks fcr the payment of an annual sum for the telegraph facilities which he provides in his territory. There is in existence an Agreement of 1864 which gives the Bri tish Government the right to construct and maintain telegraph stations and telegraph lines in Muscat territory; but in this.Agreement there is no mention of payment for the facilities provided and , so long as the cable in question was Government owned and operated, no question of payment arose. 2 . We do not know what has prompted His Highness to put forward his request, and in the first instance we should be glad of the views of your Company upon it. Yours sincerely, M.J. CLAUSCM. Captain M.J.C.Lawson, M.B.E., Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. , Slectra House, Victoria Embankment,4^ E. 23 672/0 69. LT AT r T^' : ?’ r 0 TREASURY CHAI REIT SHALL, S.W.l. 15tln September, 1937. /-v ^ \ Lear Claus on, With, reference to your P.Z. 54 72/37 about the request of the Sultan of Lius cat for payment by Caole and Wireless Limited for telegraph facilities at Muscat, I enclose herewith copy of a letter and enclosure which I have sent to Phillips at the Post Office. Bamford asks that in due course when you communicate with the Company you will be good enough to send him a copy of your letter. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) A.P.Waterfield. M.J.Clauson, Esq., India Office.TREASURY CHAMBERS E. 23 672/0 69. WI TEH ALL, S.W.l. 16th September, 1937. My dear Phillips, No doubt you have been considering the India Office papers about the request of the Sultan of Muscat for payment by Cable and Wireless Limited for telegraph facilities at Muscat, about which Clauson wrote to you on the 28th August. I wrote on the same subject to Bamford and I now enclose a copy of his reply to me. I agree with him that no action should be taken until the Company has had an opportunity of furnishing its observations on the position and I doubt if it is worth while for the Departments concerned to attempt to reach a decision on policy until we hear what the Company has to say. But of course I have no wish to deter you from advising the India Office of your views at this stage if you prefer to do so. I am sending a copy of this letter and the enclosure to Clauson. P. W. Phillips , 'Esq General Post n r n 9 W • i‘l/i • \JT • y Office. Yours sincerely,0 Y IFF3RIAL COmaJNICATIOHB AFVISCRY COI' r ; r ITTRS, ELECTPA HOUSE, VICTORIA WiBAHKMEMT, LORDOH , W.C.2. 14th Septemher, 1937. Hy dear Waterfield, I have your letter of the 9th September, Ho.S.23572/ 059, on the question of payment by Cable and Wireless Ltd. for telegraph facilities at Hus cat. The Company undertook to maintain cable and wireless communications in the Persian Oulf on the terr-ination ox the Cis-Indian Joint Purse, and there is no doubt that their business in this quarter is ot more importance on grounds of general British policy than anything else. It was hoped that the recent re-organisation would make the business bres^c even, but previously it was run at a loss. Taken fcy itself, I do not suppose that the Huscat station pays its way. There is, however, something to be said for the Sultan’s claim for payment. There are precedents xor a charge by Administrations for the landing of cables in their territory; for example, the case of Newfoundland. It is also common practice to charge a fee for the Licence under which telegraph Companies operate in a particular territory, though I think that, as in the case of the United Kingdom -Licence of Cable and Wireless Ltd., this fee is generally nominal. It is also usual for an Administration to impose a terminal tax on incoming and outgoing traffic, and such charges are imposed in some cases where there are no services rendered by the y of traffic.* - 2 . un the other hand, it is, no doubt, to the advantage of huso at to have the Company’s service, and it is doubtful v?n.b :,her we should put it in the Sultan’s power to make the o 'pany pay out any considerable sum for rendering this service. Moreover, the Company speak of themselves in the correspondence (for example, in their letter of the 18th -June, 135e, to the India Office) as being in the position of Agents to His Majesty’s Government in regard to communications in the Persian Gulf. They may consequently claim that either on grounds of law or equity they should, as far as possiole, be put in the same position as the o-overnment. was previously in operating the service; and it appears from the Resident’s memorandum of the 25th June, .l9c 7, that the Government has the right to operate the telegraph service in Muscat without payment. The terms of tne Permit under which the Company now operates in Muscat (reierred to in the Company’s letter quoted above) may have some bearing on this point. On the whole, therefore, I suggest that the Government should do what it can to protect the Company from making any Payments in Muscat; or, alternatively, to try to confine this payment to a nominal sum. I presume that, in any case, no action will be taken till the Company has had an opportunity of furnishing its observations on the position. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) E. St. J. BAMFORD.I Your Reference P. Z. 5472/37. v P. G.Reference 34563/37. TELYCCY; :'URIG A.TIOY3 DEPARmEITT, GEMEHAL POST OEEICS, ^ LOUPON, E.C.l. 10th September 1937. Dear Claus on, I am replying to your letter of the 28th of August to * ,T eston who retired a few months ago. In this country certain telegraph companies are licensed to land cables on the foreshore and the licences include a clause requiring the payment to the Board of Trade of a nominal rental for the landing facility. This is usually fixed ah £1 a year for each cable and the relative clause in the main licence to Cable and ’Tireless Ltd., which covers ten cables landed in Great Britain, rea.ds as follows: - ■*_ ’’The Company will during the term pay to the Assistant Secretary of the Finance Department of the Board of Trade in London or to such other person as the Board of Trade may direct on the 1st day of April in each year of the term the sum of £10 sterling in respect of the Cables free of all deductions on account of present or future landlords’ or tenants’ ^ taxes, rates or impositions.” The rental of 10 rupees paid to the Indian Government oy the Company in respect of telegraph cables to the Persian Gulf is a similar payment (your letter E. &lt;k 0.7154/30 of 20th September 1930). It is evidently not a payment of this type that the Sultan of Muscat has in mind. There are cases in which substantial charges are made -A to Telegraph Companies for the right to use territory as a landing point for cables. The Portuguese draw a considerable revenue of this kind from Telegraph Companies whose cables land in the Azores, those islands being well situated for repeater/ M.J.Clans on, Esq.repeater stations on the transatlantic cables and for the exchange of traffic between the various routes. We do not know the value of the telegraph traffic of Muscat; but it seems unlikely that a Telegraph Company would normally be willing to pay anything but a nominal fee for the right to land a cable there. You will remember that Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. took over the Persian Gulf cables as part of a bargahn which involved the payment of £450,000 by the Company to the Secretary of State for India. We are not familiar with the details of the negotiations but even if the Company were not promised support in retaining the landing rights existing at the time of the transfer, we should hesitate to accept the opinion of the Political Agent at Muscat that it is only reasonable that the Company should pay for the use of Muscat territory - unless a nominal fee is meant. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) H.G.G. Welch.P.Z.5472/37. I1TDIA OFFICE, FOII TEH ALL, S.W.l. 28tli August, 1937. Dear Weston, I enclose a copy of the marginally noted papers regarding the request of the Fran Pol.Resident, Persian Gulf, ) to Government of India, ) Sultan of Muscat for payment dated 25/6/37 and end. ) From Government of India to ) hy Cade and Wireless Limited Secretary of State for India,) dated 9th August 1937. ) for telegraph facilities at ) Muscat. Y\ 7 e are not aware of the general practice in regard to the payment of rentals for telegraph facilities and we should therefore he glad to receive your observations on the Sultan’s request before making any communication to the Company. Yours sincerely, M.J. CLAUSON. W.E. West on , Esq . , General Post Office, E.C.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Confident [iV, R. —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraplne expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is 'worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] Q£i iq* of tnm i-oiAticax Kes 4ae«t in Uie Persiau uulf* Am y* From _ .political Resident Bushire* at Muscat. To Secretary to tne aovernaent of o tne Government of |nd4a f — Ijcternal Aff&amp;ira OepwLm#t * c&gt; no Mew Tel hi. Repeated Secretary of State for India# The India Of*ice, Jjondon. ^Political Agent* liuecat, e&amp; tn cogy of tiovemment of Intin Ixpreaa letter under refer mice Dated 2lat ^efcrupry dv AX 5 / 9(5 0!r 1938. Suoj ect t Sultan of Muscat*s request for payment in respect of cables landing in nia territory. Reference your -ixpreaa letter fo.D-.13U-h/5d of tne 2&amp;tn January 1938. I nave discussed the matter with Political Agent. Muscat, fn.e Sultan* as you art aeare# is still absent fro??i his State and nas left no powers vita fcia Representative to discuss or decide any matters •k save tnoee of a routine luature. This being ao f the question will have to be postponed until an opportunity occurs of discuacing It witn the Sultan personally eitner by the Political Agent, Muscat* or by myself. sd. owle. Political Hesident in tne Persian GulfCrovernment of India* Sxtemal Affairs Departracnt. 3XPRJSS3 LaiTTiSR* From Foreign, iJew Delhi. To Britoonsul, Bus ire. Repeated Secretary of State for India* No. D. 130 -N/38 . Dated January 1938 NT India Office letter No*P*2*79i4/37# dated 5th J^oiuary 1938• Sultan of Muscat's request for payment in respect of the Cables landing in his territory. 2. The Government of India see no objection to your discussing matter with Sultanate authorities and would be glad if you would kindly take action as desired by the Secretary of State for India. *»*+*+ mm *m mm &lt;■»*■» mm The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/- Q.A.G.Savidge, Under Secretary to the Government of India5 th May? 1938 P.Z.3013/38 Dear Mr. Farmer, V/ould you please refer to my letter of the 5th January No. P.Z.7914/37 and connected correspondence about the Sultan of Muscat’s request for an annual payment in respect of the cables landing in his territory. The views set out in your letter of the 2nd December, 1937? were explained orally to the Sultan during his recent visit to London. His Highness did not express any objection to the suggestion for the payment of a nominal rent only, but he did not commit himself to any figure and the matter will be pursued with him on his return to Muscat. In the meantime we should be grateful 'if you would prepare a draft licence for submission to the Sultan and indicate hOY/ far your Company would be willing to go in the payment of rent. The maximum figure need not be offered to him at the outset, but we thin: that he should be offered a sum that is not obviously negligible. It/ G-. Farmer, Esq. , Cable and bireless Ltd. , Electra House, Victoria Embankment, 7.C.2.r 2 . It is possibie that when the question is again rais vath the Sultan he will want to hnow what payments are ‘tade by the Company in respect of cables landed in forei, countries, i.e. pi else ./here than m the cominions and Colonies. It V'ould in any nan. 6 . to mli , t&lt;) analogies in foreign oo„» trl e, ,, he „ E „ „„ iJUa ^ Company is a loo figure or even, as we belie™ is at present tb. ease in Iran a M irag, „et..,„ g at all. Perbaps you would kindly consider if » goi, letter of p„d p,e,„ b ,r eould be supplemented in this respect ? Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) a. P.P.Z.4188/38 IT ID IA OFPICjl), V/HITEKAL, j.VM. 21st LI, 1938 fS7 / / My dear Fowle? Would you kindly refer to your Express letter X’o.C/96 of the 21st February and our letter to Cable and ’Wreless Limiced To. P.Z.3013/38 of the 5th May (a copy of which was sent to India * Bushire and Muscat by Mail of 7 th Hay) about the oultan of Muscat's request for an annual payment in respect of the caoles landing in his territory. I now enclose a copy ',f the marginally noted correspond ence with Cable and Wireless Limited f om ’~ N &gt;mpany dated 2nd June, 1938, and enclosure. C 193G? y dated 9th June ’ ] fl ’ om which y° u Will note that in return 0,1 193Cp any dated 14th June U ror a lon 2 term licence, the Company _ are prepared to pay a nominal rent of £1 per annum for each cable landed at Muscat and we should be ^ &gt; glad if, provided that you see no objection, the matter may be pursued with the Sultan on this basis. Copies of this letter (and enclosure) are being sent to India and Muscat. ^ Yours sincerely, e Hon'ble Lt. Col. Sir T.C.W. Fowle, KCIE., CBS., H.B.M's Consulate General, Bushire.P.Z.3S95/38 SEC/T/PB CABLE APD WIRELESS LIMITED, ELECTRA HOUSE, VICTORIA LMBAHaiEHT, LOUD 01 7 , W. C. 2. , End J une, 1938 Dear Mr. GiLson, CABLES AT MUSCAT. I thank you for your letter of the 5 th ultimo (Reference P.Z.3013/38) concerning the Sultan of Muscat’s request for an annual payment in consideration of the landing in his territory of the Company’s cables, upon consideration of which I should like to make the following further observations. Firstly, I confirm that, with the exception of Newfoundland which is a special case at present receiving consideration and those instances cited in my let ;er of the 2nd December last concerning the cables landing in the Dominions and Colonies, no landing fees whatever are paid by the Company throughout the rest of its system. One point to which I should like to be allowed to draw particular attention in considering the present request is the fact that, leaving entirely out of account the heavy cost of maintenance of the cables involved, the expenses entailed in maintaining the Muscat branch are alone almost three times the estimated value to the Company of traffic emanating from this source. I mention this because, on referring to the Sultan’s letter of the 27th May last year to Major Watts, the British Consul, I see that he stated that ''it (the cable) now belongs to a Company who run it for profit'” . It may also be mentioned that in the early days cf submarine telegraphy it was the practice for the Company to receive a subsidy from tho places benefiting from telegraphic connection with the outside world rather than to pay a c onsideration/ J.P. Gibson Esq. , India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.2, consideration for so doing. Moreover, in taking over the Persian Gulf system from the British Government, the Company assumed that it would enjoy the rights and facilities afforded to the former owners, an^ since, as I understand, no jjayment was made hy the British Government in respect of the cable prior to its being taken over by my Company, it is hoped that the Government will give the Company its fullest support when the Sultan pursues the matter as, it is understood, he intends to do upon his return to Muscat. In the light of the above remarks, the annual deficit at this branch in particular, you will readily appreciate that the Company is averse to paying the Sultan anything for the light in question, although, as stated in previous correspondence, it would not object to a nominal amount as is P a i Q the case of the Dominions and Colonics. On the assumption that Kis Highness will be agreeable, upon consideration of all the circumstances of the case, to accept a consideration of say, £1 for each cable landed at this branch, I enclose a draft of a proposed form of licence to cover the landings for a term of fifty years from the oeginning of this year. As you will see the grantor has in this draft been termed the Government of the Sultanate of Oman but, prior to submitting it to the Sultan, you will no doubt be good enough to introduce any amendments you may consider desirable in the general wording of the document. Yours sincerely, Sd. S.G. Parmer/ P.Z.3895/38 BY THESE PRESENTS the Government of the Sultanate of Oman grants unto Cable and Wireless Limited a company incorporated in England and hereinafter referred to as n the Company ' 1 the exclusive licence and permission to land maintain and operate at or near Muscat any telegraph cable or cables the Company may desire for the purpose of communicating with any place’ or places comprised in the Company’s world-wide system of telegraphic communication I / Uc ^ ^ TO HLVE Ai'TE TO HOLD the said Licence for the term commencing on the 1st January 1938 and expiring on the 31st December 1987 YIELDII T 0 AltD PAYIITG therefor during the term or for such lesser period thereof as telegraphic communication is maintained the yearly rent of £1 for each cable landed as above to be paid to the Government of the Sultanate of Oman on the 1st January in each year GI VEIT under my hand and seal on-be half 4j*g_Gpyernmenir-erf 1 1 he—of GmarF^his**'’ day of hundred and thirty-eight. one thousand nine / M 1* ^WHITEKAL, P.Z.3895/38 L0iTD0I T ? 3 . Vi . 1. 9th June 5 1936 Dear Mr. Farmers Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 2nd June (3EC/T/PB) regarding the payment of landing fees to the Sultan of Muscat? There is a small point which we would like to clear up before carrying the matter further. You propose a form of licence to cover a period of fifty years. Your letter of 2nd Decembers however 9 mentioned a term of tv/enty-five years 9 and this was the figure tentatively mentioned to the Sultan in London. May we assume that 9 if the Sultan objects to the longer periods the Company would accept the shorter period of twenty-five years? I note from paragraph 2 of your letter that the Company pays no landing fees to any foreign country. The Sultan, who is sensitive in the matter of his country’s independence should be particularly impressed by this consideration. Yours sincerely, Sd. J.P. Gibson S.G. Farmer Esq., Cable and Wireless Ltd., Electra House, Victoria Embankment, W.C.2.P.2,4138/38 CABLE Ai'TD WIRELESS LIMITED ELECTRA HOUSE VICTORIA EMBAUKMEITT LOHDOITj W.C.2. SEC/T/P3 14th June, 1938 Dear Mr. Gihsorij On the question of the term of the proposed licence from the Sultan of Muscat; referred to in your letter of the 9th instant; as a period of twenty-five years has already Been tentatively mentioned to His Highness; I confirm that the Company would not object to this figure should His Highness not be willing to grant the longer period provided for in the draft licence submitted with my letter of the 2 nd instant. Yours sincerely Sd. S.G. Parmer J.P. Gibson Esq • 9 India Office; Whitehall; 3.V.1 ♦’ C~ v ’■ t I J : I :!l 1. K » * I Cgnfioential British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 23rd July 1938• The Political Agent, Muscat* mm W Subject: Sultan of Muscat 1 s reouest for an annual payment in respect of cables landed in his territory. Memorandum. Reference correspondence ending with India Office letter No.P.Z.4188/38, dated 21st May 1938, copy sent to you direct. 2. Please approach the Sultan accordingly, verbally of course in the first instance, showing him the draft agreement 3. The best argument to use, I think would be that in paragraph 2 of General Post Office, London, letter of 10th September 1937 to the India Office (copy forwarded to you under Residency Printed Letter N 0 .IO 8 -S, dated 2nd February 1938), i«e«, that the Board of Trade in England charge only a nominal rent of *; 1 for landing facilities. If the Sultan raises the question of the Company 1 s profits, you can point out that according to the Company the expenses of maintaining the Muscat branch are three times the estimated value of the traffic emanating from that Station. 4. If the Sultan concurs the agreement may be concluded / between 1lited in England. (Sept. 193fi.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. QOO »-r-r-rA • n . . . . _ . if* (Message Forms 5/-171). (INCORPORATED IN ENOl Awn&gt; mm . 2 s&amp; 6 hj i ^ ’- .‘•r r: .V o/ TTords &amp;0 Da^ Q —P C M Ug . Time -m. Remarks- V/L? your V/IB please convey ay regards anc thanks to P.A. for his Kind efforts stop appreciate natter involved with Company’s cable licence but suggestion toerect alternative means communication is solely for benefit of commercial EBBiKuuixfcjlfcxaH community whose business mace more difficult auring isolation Muscat by interruption — c ab l e s } : J -.4 ¥ \ MARK YOUR REPLY No enquiry respecting this Telegram can be attended to without the production of this Copy.yi r&gt; /-220. Printed in England. Sept. 1937. (1040) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) SERVICE TELEGRAM. From DMPG to OC/MUSC/ITT H/KF yr H/KF please thank P.A. for his kind efforts which are greatly appreciated stop I am hopeful H.H. will see advantage of a wireless installation to his subjects as curing isolation of Muscat RAF are not permitted to handle private telegramsReference: 7216/33/slga. tsy Lx AIR hsapouartbrs, BRITISH FORCT5S IH IRAQ, ROYAL AIR FORCE, H ABB AKITA* I RAO . Divisional ? Persian I Cab&gt;€ &amp; November, 1938. Division, tireless Limited, Karachi. /ic&gt;. / *-- j y IKSTALLATIOR CP L01T'1WSR TltAttS* 4 * TT CR * 2 RBClgVER - MUSCAT. Sir, I aia directed to refer to your letter 101 3, dated 29th October, 1938, and to state that the Royal Air Force in Iraq has no objection to the Short Wave low power Radio Station being established at use at, subject to there being no interference with Royal Air Force traffic. 2. Royal Air Force traffic is nomally carried out on frequencies between 13000 Kcs and 13500 Kcs by day and 6400 Kcs and 7000 Kcs by night. Routine periods for traffic as kept by Royal Air Force uscat, are at: 0415-0430 0615-0630 0715-0730 1030-1045 1300-1315 1415-1430 1848-1900 ) ) Cr.M.T ) ) 3* I am further to state that the Royal Air Force see no disadvantage to thenselves in your having an alternative other than cable communication with 'uscat and ccneider that such an alternative offers added protection against a breakdown of :uscat communications. Tours faithfully. Ur Yice arcshal. Command!ng, ritish Forces in Iraq. Copy to; The Political Agent, USCAT\ ^ 1 f GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. CO*. FI I. ^ i ' a i V. 2.. - «cf t . S '• ' s~e. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIU. : ^ I ^ ecpeditious ^han^fh * ent MAIL which provides a means of communication more on receZ S ,£ ^ a&gt;ld ^ ^aper than the telepraph. It is intended to be treated, forS^ it is drafted Z f ^ f Ao&lt;f Megraphed. To save time and to obviate Office of the Political rieaideut No ‘ C/20 Of 193». Dated New Delhi xxxxxx in the Persian Gulf, *jt, th:. Cami&gt;, kuaeai.. 19 6th February, 39. &amp;x From - To Political Resident, Buahire, at Muscat* His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Bepartment, Beliu, Reference — XXXXXXXXje^ Political Agent, Muscat*^ Telegraphic communication between Muscat and the outside world is (a) by cable (b) by local Royal Air Force wireless with whom Cable and lire less limit ad have a working arrangement* 2 . Communication under (a) is frequently interrupted owing to faulty cable as it is at present and Royal Air Force have been unable to despatch ny recent telegrams to you owing y to their own traffic. If DEPTFORD through whom I am now sending my telegrams had not been here X could not have communicated with you, at all events not without considered)le delay* 3* Situation is most unsatisfaclory and in the event of war when sloop most certainly would not be here might lead to serious consequences* I suggest that Cable and rireiess be approached with A (Signature) jm ( Pesiondit/isM.'i/ a view to their establishing their own wireless here. I understand that they would be prepared to do so. ad. T.C.Fowle. Political Resident in the Pero ian Gulf. Att eated. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No.Printed in England, Sept., 19S6. &lt;100 pads.) I M asy&lt;r/ (incorporated in England.) IN REPLY REFER TO ITus c at 16tii February 1939 W / f ... 13 J 70 i za, T ^e Political Agent, &amp; H. h . M* s Consul, Muscat• Pear Sir, Our Manager, Mr Humphrey •, pnre y» wl shes to thank you for your &amp;ina offices in moTine the ^ mg the sultan to agree to the installation Of a Wireless set. ^ , tt ^ 18 alS ° glad t0 learn that are hopeful of obtainir written permission which he consider* * considers is essential before we can proceed with the work. We shall be grateful if the Sultan’s permission in writing is obtained at an early date. n 1 ^ ^ n * ' v ' Yours faithfully. Muscat.V * Telegram Prom To No. Dated the 2nd March 1939. Political Resident, Political Agent, Muscat. T/41. N^P. I have received a letter from Divisional Manager Cable &amp; Wireless Karachi. Situation is that Cable &amp; wireless are quite wiliingjinstall wireless at Muscat and only awaiting written permission from Sultan. Please obtain this as soon as possible and wire me when you have done so.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C /39. The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents nis compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s). N Political Agency and British Consulate, M uscat. / / Dated 13th March 19 39.' Reference to previous correspondence : Reference telegram No. 37 from Political Agent, Muscat to Bntconsul, Bushire. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Co^y of letter Ho. 22 dated 17th Moharram (9th March 1^39) from His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman io Major R.P.V/atis, H.B.M* s Consu Muscat. V, Subject. Installation of a wireless set at Muscat by Gable and Wireless Limited. i&amp;HO &lt;f ^ \.. 4 f y&lt;p\ '\ CP' X CP tb v A Sc?'/ Translation of a letter Uo* 33, dated 21st Moharram 1358 (13.3.39) from H.H. Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman to Major R.P.Watts, H.B.IPS Consul, Muscat* After Compliments, I forward herewith a licence permitting the Cable and Wireless Limited to import into Muso.at the telegra-ohic cables and use them for communications#GABL-; Aim wmjxwss LTMITKI) TUB r.UI.TANAn OF OliAM and / 9Y Trnsn PHR3K3!5rTS the :?ultftn of Muscat and Oman grants unto Gable and Wireless Limited a company incorporated in ■England and hereinafter referred to as ^ the company* the exclusive licence and permission tc land maintain and operate a t_„or near Muscat any telegraph cable or cables the Company may desire for the purpose of communicating with any place or places comprised in the Company’s worldwide system of telegraphic communication* The Company’s office for despatch and receipt of telegrams shall be in Muscat town. TO TTATPil AKD TO HOLD the said licence for the term Nineteen thirty-nine commencing on the let January 1039/and expiring on the 31st December 1987. YXI5LDTNU AND PAYTNG therefore during the term or for such lesser period thereof as telegraphic communication is maintained the yearly rent of £ 1 for each cable landed ae above to be ps4d to the Hultan of Muscat and Oman on the let January in each year. (JXV IN under my own hand and seal on the ninth day of March of the year one thousand nine hundred and thirty nine corresponding to the seventeenth day of Muharran ofthe year one thousand three hundred and fifty eight. 3d/- Said bin TaimurGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. COUFIHEIUTIAL. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) [N.B. This an ORIGIN A L message sent bij AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate j ormahties it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a rpRnmisrhlp nthror nr the T)o/nnrttr*i 1 *9 j responsible officer of the Department.'] a means of communication more No. C /47 From Muscat ,the SIst March 19 39. Muscat To Political Resident Bush ire ( Subject Licence of Cable and Wireless Company at Muscat . Reference correspondence ending with your Memorandum No. 458-S, 2* The Sultan has at last signed the licence permitting Cable &amp; tireless Limited to land and operate their cables in Muscat territory for a period of fifty years and this licence signed and sealed by him is enclosed. It will be noticed that no mention is ; made in the licence of any wireless set, the installation for which VtOA ^ u ~ ^ , 1 _ _ ft l ft'. '■ a a . . ... has actually been sanctioned by the Sultan in his letter No. 22 , ^ dated the 9th March 1939, forwarded with my printed letter No. C /39 dateo the 13th March -l 939, but the Sultan informed me in a recent conversation that the licence would include the emergency wireless set also. Instead of redrafting the original licence which of course would have to be referred to you for confirmation and sanction I propose to have this point confirmed by exchange of letters copies of which will be forwarded to you in due course. Major, I.A,, Political Agent &amp; H.M's Consul, Muscat. S. 44. MFP—1534 S&amp; P—(M-2835)—24.5-38— 10,000. (Designaiim)England. Dear Sir, Pro-posed Wireless Telegraph at Muscat, The Officer—in—Charge at Muscat informs me you have expressed the opinion that the Company’s local applica tion for a licence to instal and work Wireless Telegraphy at Muscat is irregular and that the application must be referred to the India Office. I have to thank you for this advice and to inform you that I have asked my Company to follow the course you suggest. The Officer—in—Charge also states you have conveyed to him the wish of H.H. the Sultan to have the installation expedited as the merchants of Muscat are put to inconvenience and loss. The inconvenience caused to the public is indeed regretted and I trust you will convey to His Highness how greatly the delay in establishing a Wireless Telegraph is deplored but it will be appreciated that until my Company is in possession of an official licence the heavy expense of installation is not justified. Yours faithfully. Divisional Manager, Persian Gulf. P. A. D,V By Air Mail. P.Z. H og 19 p 3 1 LONDON, i i- If Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.73 i 'P.Z.1109/39 India Office ? ’Vnitehall ; 1 st March; 1959 Dear Captain Lawson, xon v/ill remeiu^er our conversation on tnc 2 Mth Mehruary about telegraph facilities at Muscat. I write to confirm that ohe Political iesident has v/ritten to us on the subject. He has drawn attention to the frequent interruption of cable communications at Muscat owing to the present faulty state of the Coiblc ana adds that it is not always possible to rely for prompt handling of telegrams on the local P.A.IM Y/ireless which may be fully occupied with its own traffic. He proposes thereiore that it might be suggested that your Company might erect their own wireless station at Muscat. I understand that actually your Company have already had this matter under consideration and are proposing to carry out two measures to improve facilities at Muscat, namely.. U) l 'h' relating, at considerable cost, the greater mart of tne faulty cable between Muscat and .Karachi, and ( 0 ) seeking permission to erect a small wireless station at Muscat. ?tu-n I!. JK C . Lawson, M.B. 1. , Cable and Mireless Ltd., Electra House, Victoria Embankment, V/. C. 2. Presumably/Presumably you will be writing to us in due course c-.bout the latter point. Yours sincerely; (Sgcq J. P. GIBSON4 V y\^ CONFIDENTIAL. 251-^ V. t The Hon’ble the Politi compliments to ij ' J the Persian Gulf presents his 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat s Depar* v and has the honour to transmit to hirq copy of the undermentioned documents (s). uEHTIM KCOiiD | If s' H. B. fHcWSULuTfei I v !■. ’• ■' /It British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dafced *--2&amp;th--March-*1959 Reference to previous correspondence : / L- India Office Printed Letter No.P.S.1109/39 of 3rd March 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. o 1. &amp; 2. only (1) Translation of letter No.22 of 9th March 1939 from Sultan of Muscat tc Political Agent, Muscat. (2) Residency letter No. 250- 3 of 25th March 1939. Installation of a wireless set at Muscat by Gable &amp; ireless Ltd.To - Hie Majesty** secretary of State for Iniia, load on* Copy to The Becretary to the 'tOToraraeiit of India# eternal Affaire Depar taent# H*w i&gt;elhi. The political Agent, Muscat, ✓ Subject ; License to Hahle &amp; tireless. Limited, for the landing of their cades at ^ueoet* Heaorandum* mjL fi /LU^ /L .1 Befer»noe corveepondence coding with India Office letter wo # ^ # s # 418S/33 t 4a&gt;;ed the ^lat ^ay 1938, X enclose copy of an express Letter 8o*3/47 § dated the Slat March 1939, from the Political Agent, Muscat, with its enclosure in orig iaal&lt; 2* The Sultan*s letter according the Company permission to install a wireless set at Muscat was forwarded under my U Printed Letter Ho.231*3, dated the 23th March 1939. Copy | of the proposed exchange of letters Uniting this permission y ^ ^ ***h *** license will bo forwarded in due course. j^A A&gt;^ 'OJ^ (i, ^ It will be noticed that the license runs for 49 years 1 &gt;•&gt;.: Y* ^3 and not for 30 years as suggested but 1 do not propose approaching the dultan to hare it amended to the latter period*X' fife : Bi-iSSriBS mm* / / / 7471 Wt 23481/P 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, 3^1 Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.P). This is an original message, sent by air mail to save*, telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same ex|&gt;^dition as* if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Political Agent, Muscat, and to Government of India, External Affairs Dep artment« PT T jM ^ Dated 29th March, 19 ?9. No. P.Z. 1856/39. I i f: 11 i cj^ruEdTiM i Vw-.- I Date /i Lf o; \\, B. M’S lutiuo - 7 V • idgatJ Please refer to your express letter of the 8 th February, no. C/20 of 1939, Telegraphic communications v/ith Muscat, A copy of correspondence with Cable and Wireless Limited is enclosed, from which it will be seen that the question of the installation of From Cable and Wireless Limited dated m ^ ^ 6 th March lo Cable and Wireless Limited dated 10th March From Cable and Wireless Limited dated 21st March a wireless station by the Company in Muscat is already under discussion with the Sultan. Please give any possible assistance in securing an arrangement satisfactory to the Company, having regard to tneir wishes as expressed in the enclosed correspondenc The issue of the above has been duly authorised. ttgd.) J- ** GIBSON/ - P.Z.1856/59. ELSCTRA HOUSE, sec/t/pb . VICTORIA EM3A1TKMEET, LOITBOE, w.C.2. 21st March, 1939. Sir, am requested to acknov/ledge with thanks your further letter of the 10th instant (Ref.P.Z.1430/39) on the subject of the permission being sought from the Sultan by this Company for the installation of Wireless at Muscat. In view of the possibility to which you refer in the second paragraph of your letter, my Company is quite prepared to allow the matter to be left to the discretion of the Political Agent as you suggest, the opportunity being taken at a later stage perhaps to embody the authority in the draft licence which, it will be recalled, has already been submitted to cover the landing rights of the cables. In conclusion I am to convey to you my Company’s appreciation and thanks for the kind interest you are taking in this matter on its behalf. I am, etc., (Sgd. ) s.G.Harm er, Secretary. The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.1.WHITEHALL, S.W.l. P.Z. 1450_/'3^ 10th March 1939. Dear Mr.Parmer, With reference to your official letter of the 6 th March (SEC/t/PB) about the Muscat wireless I should be grateiul ii you could let us have a draft or specimen licence which would show what your Company have in mind. It occurs to me that, while a letter from the Sultan merely giving authority to instal wireless would probably be in practice as satisfactory as a formal licence, to press for the latter might encourage the Sultan to stipulate payment of rent or fees as a condition of giving permission. Might we leave it to the discretion of the Political Agent not to press for an actual licence if he should apprehend that the result of doing so would be unfavourable to your Company ? Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) J.P.Gibson. S.G.Parmer , Esq., Cable &lt;k Wireless Limited.P.Z.1430/39. SSC/T/P3. VIC T OKI A m3 AIVCfXIT , V LOPPOV, ¥.0.2. 5th March, 1939. Sir, / I am requested to acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter of the 1st instant (Ref.P.Z.1109/39) on the subject of my Company’s recent proposal to instal wireless at Muscat. Prcm a letter addressed by the Manager of the Muscat Branch to the Company's Divisional Manager at Karachi, it is learned that the former has already been advised by the political Agent of the Sultan's verbal agreement to a Wireless Station being erected. It is also understood, however, that the Political Agent is endeavouring to obtain on the Company’s behalf a confirmatory letter from His Highness. Ix is not known whether the Sultan's intention is to issue merely a letter of authority to instal wireless or to put the matter on a more formal basis by the issue of an actual licence. It is considered that, of these alternatives, the latter would be preferable providing no undue restrictions or obligations were imposed on the Company thereby. Despite, however, steps which it appears are at present being taken locally in the matter, my Directors er Secretary of State, India Office, Whit..hall, S.W.l. would/* t 2 . would, nevertheless, be very grateful if, through the good offices of His Majesty’s Government, the granting of the necessary authority by the Sultan could be expedited. I am , etc. , (Sgd.) S.G.Farmer, Secretary. I1679a INDIA OFFICE, POLITIOaL( ^XT3RNAL) Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same el if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it wei^ so \ From Secretary of State. iphic\ as \ fc.) I Vi To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Repeated to Political Agent, Muscat, and to Government of India, External affairs Department. Dated 4th April, 1939- No. P.2.2060/39. ; i u u /r-^- K i it^ L /&lt;rr' / dated 30 th March. mAi! yj&gt; Iviy express letter of the 29th March, No. P. Z.I 856 / 39 . Telegraphic communications with Muscat. Copy of further letter from Cable &amp; tireless Limited is enclosed. It will be seen that in view of written permission now obtained from the Sultan the Company do not, at least for the present, wish to pursue further the question of obtaining a formal licence. ihe issue of the above has been authorised. J. P. QIMONP.2060/39* Cable and ./ireless Limited, Plectra House? Victoria ninbanbment, London? ?.C.2. SSC/T/MB. 30 th ^/larch? 1939. Sir? Referring to my letter of the 21st instant, I am requested to send you the attached copy of a telegram from the Company’s Divisional Manager at Karachi advising that the ^ Sultan’s written permission for the installation by the Company of Vireless at Muscat has been received by the Political Resident. It would appear that the form of permission is sufficient for the Company's purposes and? in the circumstances? it is considered that there is, at least at this juncture? no need to pursue the application for a formal licence. I am also requested to reiterate my Directors’ appreciation of the a^Lstance rendered to the Company in this matter. I am? Sir? Your obedient Servant? (3d.) ?.?. Parmer, Secretary. The Under Secretary of State? INDIA OPPICS? S.Y.1. Enclosure.P. 3. 2060/39- . a ! ! i AND TRIiLliJSS limited. TELEGR AM. Copy of telegram' received from the Company’s Divisional Manager at Karachi, dated 30th March, 1939* ’’PROM POLITICAL RESIDENT BEGINS SULTAN IvlUSCnT Hi.S ACCORDED PERMISSION IN VRITING FOR C-fBLB ,iND SIR ..LESS LIMITED. TO INSTIL TIRELESS SET IN THEIR PREMISES Al MUSCAT TO RECEIVE aND ISSUE PUBLICLY MESSAGES. NO STIPUL^iTIONS x,RE ii.TTji.CHED TO PERMISSION ENDS.”/ CONFIDENTIAL. The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. \ and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s). Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. Datedth e 28th April *^9. Reference to previous correspondence : Muscat letter No. C/47 of 2ist March 1939 paragraph 2. I if script ion of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of : (1) Letter No. C/50 of 28.3.39 from the Political A^ent, Muscat to H.H. the Suxtan of Muscat and Oman. (2) Letter No. 7i of 22nd Ai&gt;ri 1939 from H.H. the Buitan of Muscat and Oman to the Political Agent, Muscat. Installation of a wirele set at Muscat by the Cab &lt;&amp; tireless Ltd.Copy of &amp; letter No. C/50 dated the 23th March 1939 from the Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. With referenceour recent conversation and your letter No. 22 of the 17th Moharram 1358 (9th March 1939} in which you granted permission to Cable and Wireless Limited to install an emergency wireless set at Muscat, I understood Your Highness to say that the terms of the licence granted by Your Highnes^o the aforesaid Company to land and operate their Cables in Muscat, vide your letter No. 33 of 21st Moharram 1358 (13th March 1939) 0 , would Include the emergency wireless set also. I should be grateful if Your Highness would kindly confirm that I have understood you correctly.Copy of translation of letter Ho. 71 dated tne 1st Rabi Auwal 1358 (22n&amp; April 193d) from His Hignness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman to the Political Agent, Muscat. After Compliments, I hay« noted that the contents of your letter l-io. C/50 of 28th March 1939 is the result of the conversation we had with you. Usual Ending.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. A, Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR N &gt; [N.B. This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL inhich provides a means of communication more. expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department ] Bushire. No. 405 - 3 r, * ,, XI th Anrll. Dated m*m- the p * His Majesty** ^olbuI, Basrah* To iispeated My tele gram 3o # 4l4 of the 12th December 1936 (copy to Bahrain under Printed Letter 36*703-»3 of saoe date)* 2* 3able coxamunlcation between Bushlre and Muscat now restored, and telegrams between Bushlre and Bahrain will be relayed by Political A^ent, Muscat* Very many thanks for your assistance* ad* T • 'Z m Fowls* Political Resident in the Persian Ohlf* ATT^BTik). for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian 3ulf*o- tfSignature) Designation) s. 44.Ooafldentlal. ” GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAI [N.B. —This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To stve time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department^ No* To Dated Simla 406~S New Delhi Bu8hire f XXXJtXX , the 19 27th April* 39* Air Officer Coniaanding* British Forces in Iraq 9 Habbauiya. repeated Officer Joi3i3ai*ding k&gt; *84 (B) Squadron* r3haibahJ3a&gt;£$A* ™~*M*«** A ^ nt * Kuaaat - I! iEmWTi l ub r&gt; ^5 ) i . I l,. J. (Vi’j JiwULHit MUSCa i, • - - — * —— my i &gt; i t * XXUtXOJOC Correspondence ending with your tele^raci Xoa S«545 of the 3lst December 1936* 2* Cable communication between Bushire and Muscat restored* Many thanks for your assistance* 3d* ?• C* ? owle • Political iiesideat in the Persian Gulf ATlSCr^D. fior secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* {Signature) S. 44. MFP—1048 S&amp;P—(M-2042&gt;—17-12-37—20,000. (Designation)f )&gt; ^ By Air Mail. - ^ ifm b f\v\ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON At 'tr- if Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. in \ A copy has been sent to Li*. — (as\j^ by Mail. Tbp Fnrftixm Rppi-p.tnrv, OnvArnmAnt. of hpjja. The Political Uookient in the Persian Gulf. i lAlwv uUr 3681&gt; INDIA OFFICE, C4 P&gt; Z.S292/59. WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.U. 1 . 19th April, 1939, Gentlemen, With reference to Mr, Farmer’s letter dated 2nd June 1933 s£C/l/ftB, relative to the request of the Sultan of Muscat for an annual payment in respect of cables landed in his territory, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward in original the licence now granted to you by the Sultan on the lines of the draft enclosed with Mr, Farmer’s letter, 2 . it will be observed that the licence makes no reference to the use of wireless, written permission for which was recently given to you by the Sultan. His Highness recently informed the Political Agent orally that the licence would cover use of the wireless set also, and the Political Agent proposes to have the point confirmed by an exchange of letters with the Sultan. 3. requested that payment of the annual rental may be made by you to the Sultan direct. ' '-■■'■'x 'rjgtfttemen. Ksoeeseis***™*’'*®*' Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) R. PEEL.' Cable and Wireless Limited, Electra House, Victoria Embankment, S.V, 1 .Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to b ^ riIail - Xlie Foreip-n iSeeretnry, rtnvernmont of Ind ia. The Political llooidont in the l ) oioiaii'~0 uli ; . ^ fw- 3681^-3 y P&gt; 2* 2592/59 Gable and Wireless Limited sec/t/pb . Eleetra House, Victoria Bnbankment, London, W.C.2. 21st April, 1939. / Sir I am directed to acicnouledge wit'n tbanks receipt of your letter reference P.2.2292/39 of the 19th to the Company by the Sultan of Muscat in respect of the cables landed in his territory. His Highness’s oral intimation to the Political Agent that this licence would include the use of wireless, together with the proposal of the latter to have this point confirmed ,;y an exchange of letters, is noted, and payment of the annual rental will be made direct to the Sultan as requested. My Directors have learned with pleasure of tne contents of your letter and accordingly request me to express their thanks for the assistance rendered by you in the successful conclusion of this matter. I am, etc. (3d) Secretary. Under Secretary of State for India Political Department, India Office, London, 3 . 7 . 1 .confidential* ACRoylin i riuU'ji 1. T&gt; i\ &gt;?( n a( 0.472-3 of 1939. ideno/ &amp; Ooaeul&amp;te-Oeneral* Buenire# the lOtn a&amp;y 1939. • ■ l. i.njouA I yroa rk. to ais Copy to fhe v/The Hon v bla the political Heaident in the i*eraian Odlf. hajeaty'a ieoretary of state for India lend on. Secretary to the UoTerzkient of India, external Affairs ^emrtment, uinla. political Agent, ^U8C it. 9 ^ubJact s- Inetallation of a wireleea •et by Cable ^ fireleee Ltd., at Muecet. ''' x ^ '&lt; y P M am or and urn. p ' In continuation cf Hesidency xsemorandua )fo.23d-3 dated the 31st larch 1939, I encloae copy of letters exchanged between the political Agent and Hi® Highness the Sultan of Muscat linking the per mission granted to Cable &amp; Tireless, Limited, to iuutall a wireless set at Muscat with the license granted to them for tne landing of their cables at Muscat. Jd* T. 0. ?owle. political hesident in the Persian Gulf ATf J6tf20; for Secretary to the Pol it ical Resident in the Persian Gulf./ y M v&gt; .er secretary vo ”one uovernmenL o the External Affairs Departnsant, [(X) From - The Under Secretary to the Government of India in To - 1. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. The Political Agent. Muscat* A Memorandum No. F. 110-N/39. Dated Simla, the A May lv. U9?9. Th. B. 1 - 1 *' -r.- 2^^ v.u.uaT, Telegraph communication with Muscat. Two copies of a license granted to Cable and Wireless Limited for landing at Karachi and working a submarine telegraph cable connecting that port with Muscat are sent herewith for information and record. Under Secretary to vernment of India.LICENSE TO CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED FOR LANDING AT KARACHI AND WORKING SUBMARINE TELEGRAPH CABLE CONNECTING THAT PORT WITH MUSCAT, PERSIAN GULP. Whereas Cable and Wireless Limited (formerly known as Imperial and International Communications Limited, and hereinafter referred to as “the Company”) has applied to the Governor General of India in Council (hereinafter referred to as “the Government”) for a license to maintain and use a line of telegraphic cable, namely, Clifton-Muscat, upon the foreshore and bed of the sea at Clifton and to connect that terminus of such cable with the Central Government Telegraph Office building at Karachi, which office is to be treated as the terminus of the said cable within the British terri tories in India, and the Government have agreed to grant such license upon the terms and conditions hereinafter set out. 1. Now the Government by these presents grant unto the Company license and permission to maintain and renew and to use on and along the foreshore and bed of the sea at Clifton aforesaid in a seaward direction, the line of telegraphic cable hereinbefore mentioned to be carried direct to Muscat and to be there landed And Also license and permission to connect such cable with the Central Government Telegraph Office building at Karachi by means of a certain landline to be rented to the Company by the Government on terms already agreed but maintained by the Government throughout the continuance of this license And Also license and permission to use the said cable and such connection for the purpose of transmitting telegrams between Karachi and Muscat and places beyond in either direc tion, the said cable to be maintained and secured to the satisfaction of the Government and in such position and direction as may be directed by the Government or any person duly authorised in that behalf by the Govern ment. '2. This license shall be deemed to have been and shall remain in force from the 1st day of March 1931 until the 29th day of February 1956. The Company shall pay to the Government during the continuance of this license a yearly rent of Rs. 10 on the 1st day of March in each year commencing from the first day of March 1931. 3. (1) The Company will construct and maintain all junction boxes, cable huts, offices and other buildings, pipes, tubes and other apparatus necessary for the working of the said cable in such manner, and place the same and the said cable in such positions as the Government may direct or approve and will not make any alteration in any of the said works (other than in the said cable where outside British territory) without the consent in writing of the Government, and will from time to time comply with such stipulations and conditions as regards location and concealment of the said cable, buildings and apparatus where in British territory as the Government2 may from time to time make with a view to safeguard and protect the said cable, buildings and apparatus from accidental or malicious injury and from destruction by His Majesty’s enemies. (2) The Company will not, without the consent in writing of the (rO\- ernment first obtained, place any buildings, works or materials, or do am other act on the said foreshore and bed of the sea, which may, in the opinion of the Government, prejudice or obstruct, or tend to prejudice or obstruct, navigation or be or become injurious to the public interest. (3) It shall be lawful for the Government and any person or persons duly authorised by the Government at any time to remove from the said foreshore and bed of the sea all buildings, works and materials which may have been placed there by the Company without the consent or approval hereby required thereto, and to abate or put an end to any act done by the Company which may, in the opinion of the Government, prejudice or obstruct or tend to prejudice or obstruct, navigation or be or become injurious to the public interest, and to restore the said foreshore and bed of the sea to the former or proper condition thereof, and the Company will pay to the Gov ernment or such authorised person or persons as aforesaid all expenses in curred in or about the premises. (4) It shall also be lawful for the Government and any person or persons duly authorised as aforesaid, notwithstanding anything in this license contained, to erect or construct on the foreshore and bed of the sea any works which, in the opinion of the Government, may be required for the purpose of navigation or in the public interest. 4. The signalling officers, clerks and other employees from time to time employed by the Company in operating the said cable shall be accommo dated in the Government Central Telegraph Office Building at Karachi if the Government so desire but nevertheless all telegrams intended for trans mission or despatch from Karachi by the telegraph of the Company, and all telegrams received by or through such telegraph and intended for deli very in Karachi or elsewhere in India shall be received and delivered by or be made over for transmission to the officers, clerks or servants employed by the Government in the'said Government Central Telegraph Office at Karachi. It shall, however, be lawful for the Company to employ signal ling officers or clerks, and to use its own instruments, machines and appara tus m the said Government Central Telegraph Office building at Karachi. 5. (1) The Company shall with respect to the treatment over its whole system of telegraphs of 'telegrams originating in or destined for or passing in transit through British territories in India observe the provisions of the International Telecommunication Convention of Madrid of the 9th Decem ber 1932, and any provisions which may for the time being be in force in substitution therefor or amendment thereof and any Service Regulations thereunder which may for the time being be in force in relation to British territories in India under the said provisions, and the Company shall be deemed to be bound by the said Convention and Regulations as though it had been a party to the said Convention. (2) The Company shall, with respect to its whole system of submarine telegraph cables, observe the provisions contained in the Convention for the Protection of Submarine Cables signed at Paris on the 14th day of March 1884, and any provisions which may for the time being be in force in sub stitution therefor or amendment thereof, and the Company shall be deemed to be bound by the said Convention as though it had been a party thereto. 6 6. (1) The Company shall with respect to all GoA^ernment telegrams transmitted over its whole system of telegraphs give to the Government, to the Government of Great Britain and to the Governments of every British Possession and Protectorate every advantage in rates of charge for the transmission of telegrams and otherwise in the treatment of telegrams which it gives to any foreign Government for traffic over the same telegraphs.(2) In respect of telegrams transmitted on behalf of the Government, of the Government of Great Britain and of the Governments of every British Possession and Protectorate over the cable the subject of this license, or over any cable owned or effectively controlled by the Company, the Company shall charge rates not in excess of half the rates accruing to the Company for ordinary telegrams of the same category to which shall be added all the outpayments required by other Administrations and/or Telegraph Com panies for such telegrams. ( 3 ) With regard to the route by which Indian Government telegrams shall from time to time be transmitted, the Company shall with respect to its whole system of telegraphs conform to such directions whether special or general as may be given by the Government. 7 ; (1) I he Company will from time to time furnish to the Government at their icquest all such information as to the rates of charge of the Company oi telegrams transmitted to and from India over the cable the subiect of this license the extent and condition of its business, its income and expen- oituie and its financial position as the Government may from time to time reasonably require having regard to the ordinary staff' and administrative _.ipaut\ of the Company. Provided that such information shall (except ioi the purposes of this License) be treated as strictly private and shall re m no way published or publicly made use of (except as last aforesaid) with out the consent in writing of the Company. (2) During the existence of this license the Company shall not -it anv time during the continuance of the Agreement dated the 29th dav of Mav thf'L Llf ,, etweeR H ' s -Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and renre nf W' W r' mmi0nS be y o!1 d the Seas, Emperor of India, with the eoncur- r f A , f ! Governments in the Dominion of Canada, the Commonwealth nnAhi f •‘n T, ' e D ? mlnI01 \ of New Zealand, the Union of South Africa a ?!i th c ^' 1Sl l l ' ee state ari, -i of the Governor General of India in Council o an y w r!r (Riding) Limited-(under its the™ ks then name nTlmnf ° f the . se '- 0I1(l P a «. the Company (under the third Vm-t, tL P ’f ’''m f nternatloaal Communications Limited) of x&gt; , . pait, The Eastern Telegraph Company Limited The Eastern We t sTerTd^nnh S Co and ^ Company^LiS^The CompaL Llmkefof r P r y rf' lmit f d and Marc0Ili ’ s Wireless Telegraph y T .v d V he fo ' rth P art ’ or anv extension or renewal of such ment refen-cd oT D 6 °l the : Advisnr y Committee in that Agree ment referred to or thereafter without the consent in writing of the Govern- (i) make any new or directly or indirectly increase anv now existing of thif Hcenfe. ** Send,ng telf “' rams over the cable the subject (if) ^exlstence^ Cate§0ry ° f red '° ed rate mess *t*» which is now in (3) If the Company shall propose to the Advisorv Cnmmin^ , .i if - : service of India. sltllatlon bot h of the Company and of the telegraph 8. The Company will from time to time furnish tn th* their request all such particnEre nf f m 1 the (j0ve rnment at and originating in orTstfned to ot - DaS f ng 0Ver its telegraphs territories in India (includino- the HistriK f • ^ J n transit through British Of H. Company „ the 0 , Jparticulars shall (except as herein provided) be treated as strictly private and in no way published or publicly made use of, except when included with other general returns or with the consent in writing of the Company. 9. The Company shall with due regard to recognised differences between one class of telegrams and another transmit over the cable the subject of this license all private telegrams on equal terms without favour or prefer ence whether as regards rates of charge, order of transmission, or otherwise that is to say all telegrams which do not originate with the Government or with the Government of Great Britain or of any British Possession or Protectorate, or the Government of any foreign State and which are not service telegrams; nrovided that nothing in this license contained shall prevent the Company from providing for the delivery of telegrams at con venient hours according to the local time at the respective places by trans mitting the same in such order of priority as shall be reasonably adapted for that purpose having regard to the respective longitude of such places. 10. If at any time telegraphic communication by means of the cable the subject of this license is interrupted, the Company shall immediately give notice of such interruption to the Government, but such information shall be treated as strictly private and confidential. 11. (1) The Company will not, without the consent in writing of the Government first obtained, assign or dispose of this license or permission or any benefit arising therefrom or delegate any of the powers hereby con ferred . (2) Should any such assignment, disposition or delegation as last afore said be made with such consent as aforesaid the Company will cause a true copy of the Instrument effecting the same to be, within two calendar months of the date thereof, transmitted to the Government. 12. (1) On the occurrence of any public emergency, or in the interest of the public safety, the Government or any officer specially authorised in that behalf by the Government may (a) take temporary possession of the above mentioned cable; or (b) order that all telegrams or any telegram or class of telegrams to or from any person or class of persons, or relating to any particular subject, brought for transmission by or transmitted or received by the Company, shall not be transmitted or shall be intercepted or detained or disclosed to any officer mentioned in such order. If any doubt arises as to the existence of a public emergencv or whether any act done under this provision was in the interest of the public safety, a certi ficate signed by a Secretary to the Government, or other person as aforesaid, shall be conclusive proof on the point. (2) In any such case as aforesaid, if the Company shows that during the exercise of any of the powers aforesaid, its receipts from the telegraphs with respect to which the said powers have been exercised have been less than its receipts from the same source during a corresponding period on the average of the three years last preceding the exercise of such powers, there shall be paid to the Company as compensation for any loss of profit sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by the Government or other person as aforesaid of any of the powers hereby reserved such sum as may be settled by agreement or as in case of difference may be deter mined by the tribunal hereinafter mentioned. Provided always that no such compensation as aforesaid shall be paid, if and so far as the powers hereby reserved to the Government or other person as aforesaid are exercised for the purpose of preventing direct communication with any of His Majesty’s enemies, and save with the consent of the Government no such compensation shall be paid if and so far as the powers aforesaid are exercised for the purpose of preventing indirect or suspected communica tion with any of His Majesty’s enemies, or of protecting the interests of His Majesty under the apprehension of impending war. (3) In estimating such compensation as in the last sub-clause provided account shall be taken of all the circumstances of the case, including not only such loss as aforesaid, but also any additional profit accruing to the5 Company, whether from the use of the telegraphs so taken possession of or controlled or from any other telegraphs used by them from the emergency which gave rise to the exercise of the powers aforesaid. And as regards the telegraphs with respect to which the said powers have been exercised, the receipts of the Company on the average of the three years last preceding the exercise of the said powers during a period corresponding to that of the exercise of the said powers shall be deemed, to be the receipts which the Company would have taken during the period of the exercise of the said powers had the powers not been exercised. 13. The tribunal for the determination of any difference hereinbefore mentioned shall be an arbitrator appointed by the Government and an arbitrator appointed by the Company and such third arbitrator as the two arbitrators to be appointed as aforesaid shall by writing under their hands before proceeding with the reference appoint. The award and decision of the said three arbitrators or any two of them shall be final on the matter or matters in difference referred to them and the terms of the Indian Arbi tration Act for the time being in force shall apply to any reference to the said tribunal. 14. In any of the cases following, that is to say : (1) If before the 1st March 1956 the Company shall be dissolved or go into liquidation otherwise than for the purpose and in course of such a reconstruction of the Company as does not, -■s in the opinion of the Government, destroy the identity of the Company, or shall cease to carry on the business of transmit ting telegrams; or (2) If the said cable is not maintained throughout the whole length to the satisfaction of the Government, subject to the provision of clause 15 of this license; or (3) If the terminus outside India of the said cable is altered so as in the opinion of the Government to affect the objects for which the cable was laid; or (4) If the said cable is, without the permission of the Government, landed at or by means of any branch cable connected with any point intermediate between the points of departure and arrival specified in this license; or (5) If any act shall be done or suffered whereby, either wholly or partially, the license or permission hereby granted or any ^ benefit arising therefrom or any powers hereby conferred shall, without the assent of the Government first obtained, become vested in or delegated to any body or person other than the Company; or (6) If default shall be made in the observance or performance of any condition or provision herein contained and on the part of the Company to be observed and performed. Then, and in any such case, it shall be lawful for the Government to revoke and determine the license or permission hereby granted for the said &gt; cable as they shall in their absolute discretion think fit, and such license or permission shall thereupon cease and determine accordingly, but without prejudice to any remedy of the Government under any condition or provi sion herein contained and on the part of the Company to be observed and performed. 15. If the telegraphic communication by the said cable which is autho rised by these presents shall at any time cease to be duly maintained by the Company for a period of two years continuously (unless such maintenance shall be prevented by act of God or restraint of Princes) then the license or permission hereby granted shall cease and determine but without prejudice to any remedy of the Government as provided in the last preceding clause hereof.6 Signed by Secretary to the Gov ernment of India, in the Communications Department for and on behalf of His Excellency the Governor General of India in Council. Secretary to the Government of India, Communications Department. New Delhi; The 1939. GIPD—LI 6Telegraph—20-3-39—100.LICENSE TO CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED FOR LANDING AT KARACHI AND WORKING SUBMARINE TELEGRAPH CABLE CONNECTING THAT PORT WITH MUSCAT, PERSIAN GULF. Whereas Cable and Wireless Limited (formerly known as Imperial and International Communications Limited, and hereinafter referred to as “the Company”) has applied to the Governor General of India in Council (hereinafter referred to as “the Government”) for a license to maintain and use a line of telegraphic cable, namely, Clifton-Muscat, upon the foreshore and bed of the sea at Clifton and to connect that terminus of such cable with the Central Government Telegraph Office building at Karachi, which office is to be treated as the terminus of the said cable within the British terri tories in India, and the Government have agreed to grant such license upon the terms and conditions hereinafter set out. 1. Now the Government by these presents grant unto the Company license and permission to maintain and renew and to use on and along the foreshore and bed of the sea at Clifton aforesaid in a seaward direction, the line of telegraphic cable hereinbefore mentioned to be carried direct to Muscat and to be there landed And Also license and permission to connect such cable with the Central Government Telegraph Office building at Karachi by means of a certain landline to be rented to the Company by the Government on terms already agreed but maintained by the Government throughout the continuance of this license And Also license and permission to use the said cable and such connection for the purpose of transmitting telegrams between Karachi and Muscat arid places beyond in either direc tion, the said cable to be maintained and secured to the satisfaction of the Government and in such position and direction as may be directed by the Government or any person duly authorised in that behalf by the Govern ment. 2. This license shall be deemed to have been and shall remain in force from the 1st day of March 1931 until the 29th day of February 1956. The Company shall pay to the Government during the continuance of this license a yearly rent of Ks. 10 on the 1st day of March in each year commencing from the first day of March 1931. 3. (1) The Company will construct and maintain all junction boxes, cable huts, offices and other buildings, pipes, tubes and other apparatus necessary for the working of the said cable in such manner, and place the same and the said cable in such positions as the Government may direct or approve and will not make any alteration in any of the said works (other than in the said cable where outside British territory) without the consent in writing of the Government, and will from time to time comply with such stipulations and conditions as regards location and concealment of the said cable, buildings and apparatus where in British territory as the Governmentmay from time to time make with a view to safeguard and protect the said cable, buildings and apparatus from accidental or malicious injury and from destruction by His Majesty’s enemies. (2) The Company will not, without the consent in writing of the Gov ernment first obtained, place any buildings, works or materials, or do any other act on the said foreshore and bed of the sea, which may, in the opinion of the Government, prejudice or obstruct, or tend to prejudice or obstruct, navigation or be or become injurious to the public interest. (3) It shall lie lawful for the Government and any person or persons duly authorised by the Government at any time to remove from the said foreshore and bed of the sea all buildings, works and materials which may have been placed there by the Company without the consent or approval herebv required thereto, and to abate or put an end to any act done by the Company which may, in the opinion of the Government, prejudice or obstruct or tend to prejudice or obstruct, navigation or be or become injurious to the public interest, and to restore the said foreshore and bed of the sea to the former or proper condition thereof, and the Company will pay to the Gov ernment or such authorised person or persons as aforesaid all expenses in curred in or about the premises. (4) It shall also be lawful for the Government and any person or persons duly authorised as aforesaid, notwithstanding anything in this license contained, to erect or construct on the foreshore and bed of the sea any works which, in the opinion of the Government, may be required for the purpose of navigation or in the public interest. 4. The signalling officers, clerks and other employees from time to time employed by the Company in operating the said cable shall be accommo dated in the Government Central Telegraph Office Building at Karachi if the Government so desire but nevertheless all telegrams intended for trans mission or despatch from Karachi by the telegraph of the Company, and all telegrams received by or through such telegraph and intended for deli very in Karachi or elsewhere in India shall be received and delivered by or be made over for transmission to the officers, clerks or servants employed by the Government in the said Government Central Telegraph Office at Karachi. It shall, however, be lawful for the Company to employ signal ling officers or clerks, and to use its own instruments, machines and appara tus m the said Government Central Telegraph Office building at Karachi. 5. (1) The Company shall with respect to the treatment over its whole system of telegraphs of telegrams originating in or destined for or passing in transit through British territories in India observe the provisions of the International Telecommunication Convention of Madrid of the 9th Decem ber 1932, and any provisions which may for the time being be in force in substitution therefor or amendment thereof and any Service Regulations thereunder which may for the time being be in force in relation to British territories in India under the said provisions, and the Company shall be deemed to be bound by the said Convention and Regulations as though it had been a party to the said Convention. (2) The Company shall, with respect to its whole system of submarine telegraph cables, observe the provisions contained in the Convention for the Protection of Submarine Cables signed at Paris on the 14th day of March 1884, and any provisions which may for the time being be in force in sub stitution therefor or amendment thereof, and the Company shall be deemed to be bound by the said Convention as though it had been a party thereto. 6. (1) The Company shall with respect to all Government telegrams transmitted over its whole system of telegraphs give to the Government, to the Government of Great Britain and to the Governments of every British Possession and Protectorate every advantage in rates of charge for the transmission of telegrams and otherwise in the treatment of telegrams which it gives to any foreign Government for traffic over the same telegraphs.6 o, .ho Company „ rogard, 0 ) SfaS (2) In respect of telegrams transmitted on behalf of the Government, of the Government of Great Britain and of the Governments of every British Possession and Protectorate over the cable the subject of this license, or o\er any cable owned or effectively controlled by the Gompany, the Company shall charge rates not in excess of half the rates accruing to the Company for ordinary telegrams of the same category to which shall be added all the outpayments required by other Administrations and/or Telegraph Com panies for such telegrams. (3) With regard to the route by which Indian Government telegrams shall from time to time be transmitted, the Company shall with respect to its whole system of telegraphs conform to such directions whether special or general as may lie given by the Government. 7. (1) Ihe Company will from time to time furnish to the Government at their request all such information as to the rates of charge of the Company for telegrams transmitted to and from India over the cable the subject of t us license, the extent and condition of its business, its income and expen diture and its financial position as the Government may from time to time reasonably require having regard to the ordinary staff' and administrative capacity of the Company. Provided that such information shall (except tor the purposes of this License) be treated as strictly private and shall be m no way published or publicly made use of (except as last aforesaid) with out the consent m writing of the Company. (2) During the existence of this license the Company shall not at any time during the continuance of the Agreement dated the 29th day of Ma'v 1929 made between His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and rnt-e Of w- 1 p mim0ns bey0nd ^ he Seas&gt; Em P eror of India &gt; with the concur- rence of His Governments in the Dominion of Canada, the Commonwealth 1 , A . , ; Str T aha ,' ! ie Domlmo n of New Zealand, the Union of South Africa h fi ! rlSh F ' ee ,? tate and of the Governor General of India in Council of the first part Cable and Wireless (Holding) Limited (under its then name ° a ^ ' r'TI ° f the Se&lt;?011(l the Company ('nd' the thirrf nTrt Ti mr ^ ri f ^ J ntern f 10nal Communications Limited) of . d pait, The Eastern Telegraph Company Limited The Eastern ^tension Australasia and China Telegraph Company, Limited The Company i e mh.ed P f and Marc0m ’ s tireless Telegraph company Limited of the fourth part, or any extension or renewal of such Agreement without the consent of the Advisory Committee in that Aeree ment referred to or thereafter without the consent in writing of the Gofern (i) make any new or directly or indirectly increase any now existing of this license ^ Send ' ng tele £ rams over the cable the subject (U) ^'existence 117 CateS ° ry ° f rednced rate messages which is now in (3) If the Company shall propose to the Advisory Committee or to the srszss “i* “',7?, ^ r; r-» ‘'™' d ““*■ Of the represen atne Of He i Same Shal! be glven the careful consideration &lt;*• s s asrs a r arsstst tx^Jssr- “■ - ■ k ' vo„ P »,s„'rzJCpi; thei, 8 4!~3 p «*.S pinfs “7»' h ' , t and originating in or dmiinrt for o, pa.i,,) territories in India (mcludino- the distributinn nf .n.n m gh t Britlsh pany’s cables during any specified period of the day ^iehr^r the f/ 0m ~4 particulars shall (except as herein provided) be treated as strictly private and in no way published or publicly made use of, except when included with other general returns or with the consent in writing of the Company. 9. The Company shall with due regard to recognised differences between one class of telegrams and another transmit over the cable the subject of this license all private telegrams on equal terms without favour or prefer ence whether as regards rates of charge, order of transmission, or otherwise that is to say all telegrams which do not originate with the Government or with the Government of Great Britain or of any British Possession or Protectorate, or the Government of any foreign State and which are not service telegrams; provided that nothing in this license contained shall prevent the Company from providing for the delivery of telegrams at con venient hours according to the local time at the respective places by trans mitting the same in such order of priority as shall be reasonably adapted for that purpose having regard to the respective longitude of such places. 10. If at any time telegraphic communication by means of the cable the subject of this license is interrupted, the Company shall immediately give notice of such interruption to the Government, but such information shall be treated as strictly private and confidential. ( 11- (1) The Company will not, without the consent in writing of the Government first obtained, assign or dispose of this license or permission or any benefit arising therefrom or delegate anv of the powers herebv con ferred . (2) Should any such assignment, disposition or delegation as last afore said be made with such consent as aforesaid the Company will cause a true copy of the Instrument effecting the same to be, within two calendar months of the date thereof, transmitted to the Government. 12. (1) On the occurrence of any public emergency, or in the interest of the public safety, the Government or any officer specially authorised in that behalf by the Government may (a) take temporary possession of the above mentioned cable; or (b) order that all telegrams or any telegram or class of telegrams to or from any person or class of persons, or relating to any particular subject, brought for transmission bv or transmitted or received by the Company, shall not be transmitted or shall be intercepted or detained or disclosed to any officer mentioned in such order. If any ooubt arises as to the existence of a public emergencv or whether any act done under this provision was in the interest of the public safety, a certi- hcate signed by a Secretary to the Government, or other person as aforesaid, shall be conclusive proof on the point. (2) In any such case as aforesaid, if the Company shows that during the exercise of any of the powers aforesaid, its receipts from the telegraphs with respect to which the said powers have been exercised have been less than its receipts from the same source during a corresponding period on the average of the three years last preceding the exercise of such powers, there shall be paid to the Company as compensation for any loss of profit sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by the Government or other person as aforesaid of any of the powers hereby reserved such sum as may be settled by agreement or as in case of difference may be deter mined by the tribunal hereinafter mentioned. Provided always that no sileh compensation as aforesaid shall be paid, if and so far as the powers herebv reserved to the Government or other person as aforesaid are exercised for the purpose of preventing direct communication with any of His Majesty s enemies, and save with the consent of the Government no such compensation shall be paid if and so far as the powers aforesaid are exercised for the purpose of preventing indirect or suspected communica tion with any of His Majesty’s enemies, or of protecting the interests of His Majesty under the apprehension of impending war. (3) In estimating such compensation as in the last sub-clause provided account shall be taken of all the circumstances of the case, including not only such loss as aforesaid, but also any additional profit accruing to the x5 Company, whether trom the use of the telegraphs so taken possession of or controlled or from any other telegraphs used by them from the emergency which gave rise to the exercise of the powers aforesaid. And - as regards the telegraphs with respect to which the said powers have been exercised, the receipts of the Company on the average of the three years last preceding the exercise of the said powers during a period corresponding to that of the exercise of the said powers shall be deemed to be the receipts which the Company would have taken during the period of the exercise of the said powers had the powers not been exercised. 13. The tribunal for the determination of any difference hereinbefore mentioned shall be an arbitrator appointed by the Government and an arbitrator appointed by the Company and such third arbitrator as the two arbitrators to be appointed as aforesaid shall by writing under their hands before proceeding with the reference appoint. The award and decision of the said three arbitrators or any two of them shall be final on the matter or matters in difference referred to them and the terms of the Indian Arbi tration Act for the time being in force shall apply to any reference to the said tribunal. 14. In any of the cases following, that is to say :— (1) If before the 1st March 1956 the Company shall be dissolved or go into liquidation otherwise than for the purpose and in course of such a reconstruction of the Company as does not, in the opinion of the Government, destroy the identity of the Company, or shall cease to carry on the business of transmit ting telegrams; or (2) If the said cable is not maintained throughout the whole length to the satisfaction of the Government, subject to the provision of clause 15 of this license; or (3) If the terminus outside India of the said cable is altered so as in the opinion of the Government to affect the objects for which the cable was laid; or (4) If the said cable is, without the permission of the Government, landed at or by means of any branch cable connected with any point intermediate between the points of departure and arrival specified in this license; or (5) If any act shall be done or suffered whereby, either wholly or partially, the license or permission hereby granted or any benefit arising therefrom or any powers hereby conferred shall, without the assent of the Government first obtained, become vested in or delegated to any body or person other than the Company; or (6) If default shall be made in the observance or performance of any condition or provision herein contained and on the part of the Company to be observed and performed. Then, and in any such case, it shall be lawful for the Government to revoke and determine the license or permission hereby granted for the said cable as they shall in their absolute discretion think fit, and such license or permission shall thereupon cease and determine accordingly, but without prejudice to any remedy of the Government under any condition or provi sion herein contained and on the part of the Company to be observed and performed. 15. If the telegraphic communication by the said cable which is autho rised by these presents shall at any time cease to be duly maintained by the Company for a period of two years continuously (unless such maintenance shall be prevented by act of God or restraint of Princes) then the license or permission hereby granted shall cease and determine but without prejudice to any remedy of the Government as provided in the last precedino* clause hereof.Signed by Secretary to the Gov ernment of India, in the Communications Department for and on behalf of His Excellency the Governor General of India in Council. Secretary to the Government of India, Communications Department. New Delhi; The 1989. i i G IP D— L16Telegraph—20-3-39—100.(INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Muscat Sultan has agreed that the Cable Landing Licence, already given us, would also include the use of a wireless emergency set. We shall be grateful for an early reply, as we expect the wireless gear to arrive here by the beginning of August, Yours faithfully. Officer-in-Charge&gt; Gable &amp; Wireless Ltd, Mutmnt,I No. 1103/XII/B-l Political Agency &lt;Sc H.B.M's Consulate Muscat, the 29th June 1939. To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless, Limited, Muscat. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No. 13/77 dated the 28th June 1939, I have to confirm that His Highness the Sultan has agreed that the Cable Landing Licence would include the use of a Wireless Emergency Set by your office at Muscat. Yours faithfully, Captain, I.A. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, MuscatCONFIDENTIAL. his 1* Hie Secretary to the Government of India* External Affairs Department* Simla* 2* Hie Political Agent* Muscat. and has the honour to transm it to him a copy of the undermentioned documeDts (8) ' and II * T e. No •r?3? - AIuSOaT, British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Gamp, Shiraz, Dated... 2.hd.. AWLgtt a t. IS S9.t. Refe rence to previous correspondence: &lt;Z.\ ^ Residency memorandum Bo.472-S of 10th May 1939* '9 a \ vC Description of Enclosure. Residency dated 2nd Name and Date. telegram Eo.T/154 August 1939* Subject. Installation of a wireless set by Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd** at Muscat*Te le gram !?rom &gt;olltloal Heaident, Bushlre at ilhlraa* To Secretary of State for India, London* ^opy by poet to Government of India, Simla, * * * 11 Political Agent, Moecat. ifo#T/154 1 Bated 2nd August 1939, rreepoxidenoe ending with ay letter *o,4?2-S 10th May* Cable oomimiiiioation with Muscat is once more interrupted* Qrateful if instalment of wireless by Company at Muscat could be expedited. Company were informed as long ago as last March that Sultan had accorded permission see my irinted Letter lo.251-3 25th March*INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to 'V b y l V * r Mail. The FuiLi,i&gt;Jt g^bimury, Quveimnuib of Inthar The Political hooidcmt m the PoreOn Gulf &gt; 3681P.z.4731/39. 8th August 1939. Sir, With reference to correspondence resting with your letter No.Sec.T/P3 of 2nd June regarding the permission granted to your Company to instal a wireless set at Muscat, I am directed to inform you that the Political Resident has reported that cable communication with Muscat is once more interrupted. I am to enquire what the present position is in regard to the installation of the wireless set, and whether steps can be taken by your Company to have the matter expedited. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Secretary, Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Electra house, Victoria Embankment, S.W.l.IFDIA OFFICE. Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER fAIR MAIL). From Secretary of State To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated t Pol.Age nt, Mus cat , Govt, of India, Ext .Aff.Dept. Dated 24th August 1939. Ho. P.Z.5090/39. Your telegram of 2nd August, Ho.T.154. Instalment of wireless at Muscat. It will be seen from copy of letter from Cable and Wireless Ltd. forwarded herewith that wireless equipment is to be shipped in the very near future. if- 4 ! -S 4 ? h'lb The issue of the above has been duly authorised. (Sgd.) R. PEELiintcd i» Enfc'limd. Sept., 19.%. &lt;100 parts.) a//a /'ftteteM' ^ t//u (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat, With reference to our interview on the 11th November with regard to the erection of two masts of about l+O feet each on the roofs of both our Company’s quarters, and two additional masts of about 30 feet each at the edge of the pier in front of our own building, we beg to submit that as there appears to be no immediate liklihood of our Divisional Manager’s visit to Muscat, we be granted permission to proceed v/ith the above work. (!!?&gt; N ^ 2/-/26 \w* MuscatA 17 th November 1939 . We also propose to lay an 'Earth 11 in the soft sand on the beach in front of our office and trust you will have no objection to this being done. Thanking you. Yours faithfully. Offi 'XT-in-Oharye , Oahla &amp; Wireless Ltd, Muscat,I' TEL E G R A M. \V&gt; Telegram From To Repeated to No. Date - 'Q' - Political Agent, Muscat. - Britdonsul Bushire - Political Resident, Kuwait. - 476 - November the 19th, 1939. : - : Addressed Bushire repeated to Resident Kuwait. Cable and Wireless wireless installation. 2. The officer-in-charge has asked if there is any objection to Company erecting two receiving (height about 30 feet) and two sending masts on their premises. Before approaching Bultan in this connection I shall be gratpful to know if there is any technical objection from a constructional or electrical point of view. Officer-in-Charge states that there will be no interference with R.A.F.Station.'■! . ' •5 Telegram From To Repeated to No. Dated TEL E G R A M. - ”Q' - Secretary to P.R., Bushire. - Political Agent, Muscat. - Political Resident, - 507 - November the 2Gth, 1939. nt, % Your telegram 476 November 19th. Regret that I am not in a position to offer technical opinions on the subject. jfgjsSaaBggNo. C/492. \\ Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat the 23rd November 1939. The Officer In Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Muscat. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No. 13/84 dated the 17th November 1939. 2. There is no objection to your erecting the masts in question provided Messrs. Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., guarantee that no damage will be caused to Government property by reason of the erection of these masts. It should also be understood that the Company will be JiliiSlsy€iA responsible for any injury^ which may be caused by reason of the masts being erected on foundations of not sufficient strength to support their weight. Before the work actually commences I would like to see the exact position selected* I shall probably be absent from Muscat from Sunday next until the 4th of December 1939. Yours faithfully, %Y/, Captain, I.A., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat* ' '-^qipiniptnE L E G R A M. - Political Resident, Kuwait. - Political Agent, Muscat. - T/516 - November the 24th, 1939. Your telegram 476 November 19th Muscat Wireless. No objection provided no damage is done to GovernmentPrinted in England. Oct., 1985. (450 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO 12/81*. = ^L^/ ^ c \ (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) / , « \ •1 1 The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Dear Sir, Kindly refer to your letter No 1991 /XII dated 11th November. Ve beg to advise that our new wireless installation has been completed and commenced operating yesterday. . Referring to your letter Clj.12 dated 17 th October 1939* Mr Faithfuls transmitter and receiver are now available for Government purposes*CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/ 583. The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s). Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. Baud 22nd December ^ 39 * s correspondence : Your. Printed Letter No. C/292 dated the 2nd August 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. (l). Copy of letter No. 13/84, dated the 18th December 1939, from Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Muscat, fo *t^e Political Agent, Muscat. Wireless Installation.Dear Sir, Referring to our letter dated 1st August 1939&gt; advising you of total interruption of cable communication with Karachi and Bushire, we beg to report that the Muscat-Karachi cable was put through by our cable ship Lady Denison Pender yesterday. The ship^now steaming towards the fault in the Muscat-Bushire cable and hopes to tackle it tomorrow. , yours faithfully, Offixr-in-Chargz, Qubit &amp; Wireless Ltd.tinted in En*l»nd. Oct., im. il ? (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Muscat J£L^, D/ 15 . 1 . The Political Agent 4 H.B.M's Consul. MUSCAT . * * Dear Sir, With reference to our interview with you this morning, we beg to attach a telegram from Sir Edward Wilshaw K.C.M.G., Chairman, Cable and Wireless Limited, London, for kind favour of delivery to His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Thanking you. z 7 . /. JjLl A Yours faithfully. Offi&amp;r-in- Charge , Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. MuscatThe 15th January 1940 To Hie Highness Saiyid Said bin Tairaur Sultan of Muscat and Oman* Your Highness* Mr. J.A. Faithful the Officer-in-Charge of Ca^le ana //ireless Limited at Muscat has asked me to convey to you the attached telegram which he has received from Sir Edward Wilshaw, Chairman of the Company for delivery to Your Highness. Your Highness's sincere friend Captain, I. A., His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. No. C/42. Copy forwarded to Mr. J.A. Faithful, Officer- in-Charge of Cable and Wireless Ltd, Muscat with reference to his letter No. 38/6 dated the 15th January 1940. Captain, I.A., Political Agent &amp; H.3:M's Consul, Muscat.Mi CcMii iaen COVERNMi^NT OP ,2 EXPRESS tETTER [iV, 15 ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGN, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Prom kolitioal ieaident, Buauire. ••• J~2l ' i ■ r-. STSTT-* CiCT- '* ^ ' * No. His peaty’s ;ecr«tary of Stats for India, Lcmaon VJns secretary to the Governiaent of inaia in the 4ixteirnaX ffairs ^^e^urtiuenty hew helhi* political ^ent 9 aisoat. ^ Dated W^aq 12th January Instalment of wireless at tqacat« Heferanoe correspondenoe endin t ; witii India Office express setter 5090/59* dated tiie 24tii -vu^ust 1959* 2* officer in Oharget Gable and wireless Limited, muscat, has informed the Political Agent thiit new wireless installation has oeen completed and has eoimaanced operating* *d»G*l#® 4 HIGH i olitical Hesident in t^ie lersian Gulf* tteated -f for oeih*et&lt;Ary to tiie political Resident in the 2 ersian Uulf* U •’.X •Enc d in England, * m. 1934.) fMfef MEMORANDUM. Cable anfr *Mttreless ^imtteb, ^rma( aiib j)ii(mia(iuiial Cumnmmi’iiiuiib yimili'U, (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Muscat. BRANCH. ♦ Dear Sir, We attach herewith a copy of a telegram received from our Head Office in London regarding the acceptance of press telegrams to the Ministry of Information, London. v/ Yours faithfully. , (Station Forms 2/30. H.) , ^ 0 . ••/ \ (i?“J 21st January ^o. No 1 V 96 . , 19 to The Political Agent , _ —- &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Offizer-in-Ciic &gt;■&gt; Q&amp;h te-Winhs* im Muscat,England. Sept. 1938. (12339 Pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. — (incorporated in England) * * • 5/—168. ' ; S/MS messages In plain language conforming to rules for press | addressed to Miniform Ldn originating with Brit Govt representat ives should be accepted at press rates stop similar messages in reverse direction addressed to Political mus will be accepted in .Ldn as press telegrams. ik. 'Dui J7Tuie?iui£: MARK YOUR REPLY NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY J. J W2 I Printed in KneUmd. Sopt., 19 a 6 . (100 pjvU.) vl i' * IN REPLY REFER TO 1 5/80. No (OaY'/e anr/ /ftibe/eM Sm /Y t/ (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Muscat. r ^, / 21st January 1914 . 0 * » ♦ 1 • The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Dear Sir, We beg to advise that the Muscat-Bushire Cable was put through yesterday. The Office is now open for 2 I 4 . hours. ( Yours faithfully. OffivetYn-Charge, Cable &lt;# Wireless Ltd, Muscat.ladiaa. Pfiata_and_l'e l9graph8 Departme nt. The DiYisional Manager (Persian Gulf) t Cable and wireless Ltd., Karachi. No.P-461/39, dated New Delhi, the 6 th January 1940. Subjects- Call Sign for Muscat wireless Telegraph. With reference to your letter No.101/46 dated the 7th December 1939, I am directed to inform you that the Call Sign VTS is allotted to your station at Muscat for working a commercial Service with Bahrain. Necessary particulars for notification to Berne may kindly be forwarded I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. S. Banerji, Assistant Chief Engineer. U&amp;M1/2SL. Copy forwarded for information to the External Affairs Department and the Defence Department. Sd. 3, Banerji, Assistant Chief Engineer.TELE GR A M. Telegram From To No. Dated - XX Ministry of Information, Political Agent, Muscat. Circular No. 96. January the 24th, 1940. f Cable dc Wireless have agreed that messages containing news intended form basic messages for publication in this country may be handed in by the representatives of the Ministry I of Information at your post for despatch at press rates provided:- (1) . that paid service indication - PHESSE - is inserted at the beginning of address. (2) . that telegraph (seven) handeddin only at Cable 6c Wireless Company's office (for your Government only at Superior Wireless Telegraphing Office). (3) . that routing indication (for Aden,Cairo, Lisbon and Shanghai) 'VIA EASTERN' (for Bahrain , Buenos Ayres, Hong Kong, La Paz, Lima, Montevideo, Muscat, Rio De Janeiro and Santiago De Chile) 'VIA IMPERIAL' (in the case of Bogo only) 'VIA SUPERIOR' (in the case of Havana only) 'VIA INGLESA' (in the case of Tangier only) 'VIA TANGIER EASTERN' is inserted. VJi. ) 1 X' MUSCAT nuary the 27th 1940 I am sending you the draft-reply to Sir Edward Wilshaw and shall be grateful if you will let me know if it is adequate and suitable. I will then send it to you with an official letter and request that it may oe trans mitted to him. ^ —eS. 1^/^—* / Captain T.Hickinbotham, H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat./ &lt;, A V , ^ \ Xv v ' \\- :&gt; *x / / MUSCAT January the 28th 1940 Frpm Said Din Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Our Friend Captain T. Hickinbotham, Consul, Muscat. After Compliments, v ' e thank you for conveying to us the telegram of HU, Fir Edward Wilshaw, Chairman of,Cable and Wireless Company Ltd.London, and shall be grateful if you will please arrange for the transmission of our reply, attached herewith to Sir Edward Wilshaw. Your^ Sincere Friend, Sultan of Muscat and Oman.From Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. To Sir Edward i&gt;Vilshaw K.C.M.G. , Gable &amp;. Wireless Eimited, London. ./e shall be grateful if you will convey our cordial thanks to your Company for the kind message and our appreciation of their distinguished activity in installing a wireless station at Muscatj which, we are confident, will not only ensure facility of communication to our mutual benefit and help but will maintain and promote the existing relation of friendship and good will between us stop It is our wish indeed that the wireless station may develop and progress and we assure your company of our ready assistance in that respect stop Our grateful thanks to you for W6 uhc ^ood wishes which ure/sincerely reciDrocubeHo. C/72. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat, the 31st January 1940. To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless iiimitec;, Muscat. Dear Sir, IMufj. reference to uSie correoponcience enciin^^ with my endox'sement Ko. C/42 dateu the 15th January 1940, I forward, herewith, His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman's reply for transmission to the Chairman of Cable &amp; Wireless limited, London Yours faithfully, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M'S Consul, Muscat.V CONFIDENTIAL* D.O. No. C/32u. Muscat, the 8th May, lb&gt;4C. Faithful came ia this morning- to see me about a guard for the telegraph office; he says that in India all such offices have a guard, and that at night the operator is ^lone there. 2. I suggested, and he agreed, that in view of the close proximity to the Consulate, security would he adequately assured if one of the Consulate guard were to sleep at the Telegraph Office. If you see no objection, perhaps you would issue orders to the guard commanders about this. M&lt;i,jor A.O.C. Pettyfer, I.A., Military Adviser to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. u,/ y /APolitical Agency A H.B.M's Coneulate, Muscat the 15th of May 1940. ill you please refer to your letter of yesterday's date? 1 am referring the matter to Capt tin Howes 4nd will let you know the result on receipt of his reply, uCONFIDENTIAL. (|tg\ .. ,T £? te dated 14.5.40 from Major A.O.C. Pettyfer to K.S. M.H. Khan. -tr*::.;;:.: •.« h Before he left Captain Howes spoke to me about placing a guard over the Telegraph Office by night and I did so pending approval of Saiyid Shahab, whom I asked today. He is agreeable, but would like the request to be sent to him direct by you so, if you are authorized to do so, will you please write to him asking for this guard to be supplied. If not I will write to Captain Howes asking him to write. The guard is for the purpose’of protecting the instruments against sabotage when there is only one operator on duty. t'. j. c ^ a ^ e&lt; ^ 15.5.40 from K.S. M.H.Khan to Major A.O.C. Pettyfer. Will you please refe-to your letter o£ yesterdayfe date? I am referring the matter to Captain Howes and will let you know the result on receipt of his reply. P. A. Copies of above correspondence are submitted for orders pi. 2. As far as I remember I think you wanted a sepoy to sleep in the telegraph office at night and did not consider that a proper night guard be posted. Since the guard has been posted this subject is receiving attention of news makers in the local coffee shops. Some of them say it is due to the gap in the boundary wall, others say it is on account of the trouble in the Oman. Some of them also think that some sort of danger is apprehended in the close vicinity and connect this with the news of German submarines which they believe are operating not very far from Muscat. 3. Saiyid Shahab, I think wants to obtain ap-'roval of His Highness for posting of a guard at the telegraph office and for this purpose he wants a letter from us. . lh is _conn ec tion I, iaav ad d for vonr&gt; on ^- 2 - J hi i¥t] 1923 or thereabout when the Indian Army guard was withdrawn from the Consulate the Sultan had agreed to provide a guard from his Levy without any cost to us. It is however, doubtful that His Highness will like the idea of providing another guard and that also for the protection of the Cable and Wireless office without any cost. As the arrangement is only for the duration of the tfar for which period he will be receiving a Subsidy I do not think he can have any objection to this arrangement. IPolitical Agency &amp; E«B.Sf*s Coneulate, Muscat ti*€ 27th of May 1240. Mil you please refer to ay letter dated the 16 th of Cay 1240* 2* 1 have received tae following’ teleyrasi from 0a tain Howes;- ''Telegraph Office Guard* Letter for Jaiyid Shahab by claix• ,,Copy in translation. &gt; ) Quetta May 25th, 1940. To Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal, Representative of his Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. After compliments. I have heard from Khan Sahib Maqbool Hussain Khan thrit you wish to have from me a formal letter about the guard on the telegraph office. As you know, a guard is posted over such offices in India; and Mr. Faithful, the Officer in Charge, asked me just before I left Muscat whether this could be done there too, as the operator is alone at night, and if (God forbid) any agent of the Germans was to come upon him there, he could do serious damage to valuable instruments, and Muscat*s communication with the outside world would be completely cut off. I therefore consulted your Military Adviser, Major Pettyfer, on this subject. x no ^ think it is likely, thank God, that this vii^ happen; but Your Honour will not fail to realise that it was, xor instance, because Great Britain prepared carefully against air raids that the Germans have so far not dared to do any serious bombing on our towns. think therefore that we ought to take this precaution for the duration of the war, and I hope that you will agree. Usual Ending. Sd./ J.B. Howe s, H.B.M* s Consul, Muscat *vD.C. 110. C/437 Bated the 9th AUc'aet 134J* 'Hi th reference! to our conversation of yesterday morning. X hnve spoken to Kajor iettyfer aid he weicouied the idea of setting up wireless poles on the Bait &amp;i Falaj Building. He is prepared to for this wor&lt;c from his Military Budget and will be grateful if you wi!3 give him your technical advice on what is actually require-♦ If you will let ue rcnow the frequency and wave length which will be used by the emergency set I will get in toucn with Air headquarters and come tc some arrangement about the procedire to be followed in the event of an emergency occurring. J.A. Faithful, Esquire* kuuc&amp;uCONFIDENTIAL. No. -=«• S B C R B T. ) &gt; 576-S of 1340- r Ihe Tloo’ble the Political Resident in the Persian compliments to !• The Politics! Agent» Kuwait* 2* The Politicel Agent# Bahrain. The Political Agent# Ku^jat* y- and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated ”-&amp;th--A tf-uet '1940. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. — Name and Date. Subject. GoyernTnent of India’s letter Ifo.P.64-w/40, dated the 17th June 1940. with enclosure. TEMPORARY 31 StOCATI Off OF WIRE: STATIONS I IT THE 3YK3TT OF' IMPS: CAPTURE BY AS EIT3MY% S3CRBT. ffo.F. 64-W/40 From Tne Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Afiairs Department# To !• The Chief Secretaty to the Government of the Horth West Frontier Province* 2* The Hobble the Agent to the Governor General# Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan* 3* The Hobble the Political R e sident in the Persian Gulf. 4* The Resident in Kashmir (for Gilgit)* 5. The Political Officer in Sikkim. 6* His Majesty’s Consul General for Khorasan. 7. His Majesty’s Consul General# Kashgar. Dated Simla# the 17th June 1940 Temporary dislocation of wireless stations in the event of impending capture by an enemy. Sir# I am directed to forward a copy of memorandum from the Army Headquarters (General Staff Branch) Ho. 47930/1/^.0.2# dated the 8th June 1940# with enclosure# for XKfxxxxjdbra information (and guidance) Omit to Hos 5 &amp; 6 * 1 have the honour to be # Sir# Tour most obedient servant# Sf). Xllig&amp;fcle, Under Secretary to the Government of India.Ho.47 930/l/ii.0.2. ARMY HEAirUARTERS .INDIA , GENE RAX STAFF BRANCH, SIMXA, THE 8TH JUNE, 1940 SECRET. Tot HEADQUARTERS, NORTHERN COMMAND EASTERN COMMAND SOUTHERN COMMAND WESTERN (INDEPENDENT) DISTRICT Subjectt- TEMPORARY DISLOCATION OF WIRELESS STATIONS IN THEE VENT OF IMPENDING CAPTURE BY AN ENEMY 1* All personnel responsible for wireless stations must know h best to put their wireless station out of order in the event of its being in imminent danger of capture by an enemy. The responsibility for taking action in this event will lie with the officer orN.C.D* in charge f the wireless station at the time. 2* A copy of Appendix M A H to this letter will be distributed to all units supplied with wireless. Sd* G. Swones» Col.» for CHIEF OF THE GENERAL STATF. Copy toi- Headquareters* Peshawar District. Rawalpindi District. i* Together with sufficient copie for distributer to units c oncerned. Lahore District. Kohat District. N It Waziristan District. Meerut District. Presidency and Assam District. it n ) Lucknow District. Deccan District. Bombay District. Madras District. tt n Jubbalpore (independent) Area* n The Adjutant General in India. The Master General of the Ordanance in India. The Signal Officer in Chief* The Major General* Royal Artillery. S.D. 2. External Affairs Department (10) Political Department (lb) Military Adviser in Chief* Indian State Forces. (30).SBCKBT Appendix 'A 11 to A-rmy Headquarters letter No«47 930/l/l£.0 da tea'13't'h~June Action to be taken by personnel responsible for wireless static in the event of the wireless stati on f ailing temporarily into enemy han either as the result of operations against an organised enemy or of internal disturbances in India* It is imperative that such a wireless station be rendered at least temporarily' unusable ec that it cannot be employed by the enemy either to transmit messages tc or receive messages from another enemy station or to transmit false messages to cithers of our own stations* 1‘his can best be effected by removing from both the transmitte; and receiver some vital components such as valves* t ne components be in* smashed and care being taken that no spares or possible substitutes fo: tlie se components are left in the station. In choosing tue component to be d estroyed in an internal security wireless set it should be rem.mbej ed that certain spare parts are often available locally* It is also imperative that such documents as wireless diagrams lists of frequencies and lists of units and their locations which may be of use to the enemy be destroyed# If there is sufficient time this can best be done by burning* Officers in charge of wireless station s will ensure that the personnel concerned know how he st to put their station out of order in the event of impending capture by the enmey#/ / / &lt;JO • ^©AAUcal Agency ^ H.iJ.g 1 ® ConsaxaUf the 14th October 1^40« From lejor T* HlcjclnboUiem 9 C*B*K* f aoxIUcoI At.eni i H.&amp;.x'b Coneulf MuscbU TO Ijc*e Honourable the political Heeluent in the iersian Gulf* Bushire* sir* 1 have the honour to refer to your printed letter Ho* 576~s of 1940 dated the 8th August 1940* £. I hare arran^Wfor tne storage at Balt al Faiaj* the Headquarters of Ute Muscat Infantry* of all syare relres belonging to tne noyai Axr Force and Messrs* Cable and Irexsss hlmltsd’a virsless Installations* It sill thue be possible for both these sets to be renaered temporarily unserrlceable sh aid the necessity for such action arise* 3* I hero arranged for the Installation at Balt el P&amp;laj of an emergency wireless transmitter ana receiver* Teats on this set have axre^dy seen ct rrled out with Messrs* Cabxe and Irexess Iliul ted * s ./T c tatlon at Baiiraln* the Haval tireless station at Bahrain* end the Koyal Air Force station at Shalbah* These tests have proved entirely satisfactory* 1 have the honour to be* four most obedient servant &lt;* 7 Major*I.A. * political Agent * H.£*£t'e Consul* Muscat*D.O. No. C/609 of 1340 Muscat, the 8th November,1940 «y dear Friend, You mentioned the question of payments due by Cable &amp; Wireless to me the other day. I have made enquiries and find that they paid the annual rent on the 29th June 1939 ana again on the 21st February 1940. The vouchers have been sent to London with their accounts. Perhaps it was some other pay ment that you were referring to ? Your sincere friend, His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and OmanJ in England. OffivgrAn-Uharqt , (fable &amp; Wireless Ltd, Muscat, M v CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) V\ IN REPLY REFER TO 5/205. No ELECTRA HOUSE, MUSCAT, OMAN, PERSIAN GULF. 2nd December 1940. The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul. Muscat. # Dear Sir, we beg to advise that Mr F.W.Humphrey handed over charge of the Persian Gulf Section of Cable and Wireless Limited, to Mr F.L.Thornton on the 1st December 1940. Yours faithfully.m fb* .u England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED J (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) ELECTRA HOUSE, MUSCAT, OMAN, PERSIAN GULF. 16th December 1940. The Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat Dear Sir, The following is a copy of a Service Message received from our Divisional Manager, Persian Gulf Section, Karachi. ' Please say if it is possible to arrange with the Political Agent for an armed guard to protect the office against nossible acts of sabotage.' Yours faithfully. OfficerAn-Cfiarge, (fable &amp; Wireless Ltd, Muscat,Offl&amp; r-in-Gharge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. Muscat d in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) ELECTRA HOUSE, MUSCAT, OMAN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO No. 1V104 28th December 1940. The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul» Muscat. Dear Sir, We beg to advise that our submarine cable between Muscat and Bushire has become interrupted. Traffic to and from IraQ, Iran and Bahrain is being disposed of by Wireless. Yours faithfully,Qffizer-in-Gharge, Gable &amp; Wirdeu Ltd. Muscat* England. 4 '- CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) i‘l( in ELECTRA HOUSE, MUSCAT, OMAN, PERSIAN GULF. 11th January 1941* V* Dear Sir, Please refer to our letter No 38/22 dated 16th Decemher 1940. We shall be grateful if you will kindly let us know if it is possible to arrange for an armed guard to protect our office against possible acts of sabotage. The office is now closed from 0000 to 0600 local time, but a call circuit has been installed in the Supervisor’s quarters for the disposal of Urgent traffic. Yours faithfully. /?Printed inCABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) No 13/105. IN REPLY REFER TO ELECTRA HOUSE, i MUSCAT, OMAN, PERSIAN GULF. 11th January 1941* The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul 9 Muscat Dear Sir, Would you very kindly let us know whether it is legal, in Muscat, for the Officer in Charge, Cable and Wireless Ltd., Muscat, to inflict fines on the Menials of the Company as punishment for disregarding Company's rules and regulations. Yours faithfully Offiser-ln-(Sharge, (fable &lt;&amp; Wirdes* Ltd, Muscat.England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) ELECTRA HOUSE, v MUSCAT, OMAN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO l^th January 19 I 4.1 The Political Agent &amp; Consul Muscat* Dear Sir With reference to the following instructions contained in your letter No C /608 of I 9 I 4 .O, dated 8 th November 19 I 4 .O Important and Immediate telegrams should be delivered to myself or the Treasury Officer who ever can be found Quickest”, we have to advise that our ”Most lmmediate' r telegram No 180 dated 11th January 19^0, received at 1.25 A.M., was offered to the Treasury Officer for acceptance at 1.50 A.M. but the Officer would not take delivery of the Urgent message. Would you kindly let us know if your instructions have been revised. Yours fa : 5 Offizer-in-Charge, (fable &amp; Wireless Ltd, Muscat,Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate Muscat, the 13th January,1941. The Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless, Limited, Muscat. Dear Sir, Will you please refer to your letter No. 13/105, dated the 11th January, 1941? 2 * T be reply to your enquiry is in the negative. Yours faithfully, Maj or, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat../t&gt;Y Political Agency &amp; H.B. f’s Consulate Muscat, the 14th January, 1941 Consulate, y \ To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless, Limited Muscat. Dear Sir Reference your letter N 0 * 11/60, dated the 13th January, 1941 My instructions still stand. The message in question 2 was delivered to Khan Sahib Maqbpol Hussain Khan at 1-30 a.m. who asked the messenger to take^to me at the Consulate telling him that he was following him. The Khan Sahib followed the messenger to the Consulate and signed the receipt. The message was being decoded at 2 a.m. Your letter would appear to indicate that the message , was deliberately refused and had not been delivered at alx. I was present in the Consulate and am not aware that your messenger made any attempt to wake me or was prevented from doing so. Y 0 urs faithfully, Major, Political Agent Sc H.B.M’s Consul, MuscatC/66. Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat, the 14th January,1941. To The Manager, Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Muscat. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. 38/22, dated the 11th January 1941. 2. If you desire I will approach the Muscat Government in the matter. As the premises to be guarded are those of a commercial undertaking it is probable that your company will be required to pay for the cost of the guard. Am I to understand that your company are prepared to do this ? w Yours faithfully, Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* s Consul, Muscat. «Muscat. 14th January 1941. The Officer-in-Charge, Gable and Wireless Ltd., Muscat. Dear Sir, I beg to differ with the last paragraph of the Political Agent’s letter No. C/57 of even date. As the Khan Sahib would not take delivery of the telegram, and, as he requested me to deliver it to the Political Agent himself, I went to the Consulate and handed it to the night peon, with the request that it should be handed to the Political Agent immediately. After the lapse of a fefcr minutes the peon returned to say that he could not wake the Sahib. Soon after this the Khan Sahib arrived and took delivery of the message from the peon. Yours faithfully, Ho. 38/22, Dated 14th January 1941. Forwarded t.o the Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul .Muscat. Oft i-2tr'Zfi-‘(7harge t Gable &amp; Wireless Ltd, Muscat. atA. /2T A* ^ ^Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATJ AND) l 4 ^@) ELECTRA HOUSE, MUSCAT^qiviAN, Persian gulf. IN REPLY REFER TO no. 12/4. 20 th tTanuary 1941. \--'t ^ v v- - 'A- vj v ^ N y The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. Dear Sir, V-' ■ N ■ \ \ ..A 0 &amp; A v '•cr \ x \ '-y s \&gt; y We beg to advise that there is a possibility of our Cable Ship calling at Muscat. * The Engineers on board will probably land testing gear to localize the fault in the Muscat-Bushire Cable and take the set back when they return to the ship. The date and time of arrival of the Ship will be notified when this information is definitely known to us. Yours faithfully. OUivcMtirGharge, mi# &lt;&amp; Wireless Ltd, Muscat,Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) 'sf*, IN REPLY REFER TO No. 12/4 The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat, Dear Sir, Muscat and Bushire branches have received the following coded telegram from our Divisional Manager, Karachi, CJ/KC (DECODE) CONFIDENTIAL PLEASE ADVISE PA AND PR RESPECTIVELY THAT SHIP COMING SHORTLY REPAIR CABLES AND MAY POSSIBLY WISH COME ASHORE. DATE AT PRESENT UNKNOWN. r* j Yours faithfully, &amp;Printed in England. Aug. 1940. (250 pads.) 2/-50 IN REPLY REFER TO no. 1/145. MEMORANDUM. The Political Agent, Muscat. Dear Sir, CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED) (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) .... Ip . Muscat. BRANCH, 29th October1941, 2«f/o . Referring to our Memorandum dated 10th October 1941, we bee the a 27th e 0ctober e i94l! been ^ Wireless communication with Dhofar since We have arranged to work Dhofar once daily. /? Yours faithfully. Off/*** CHn*c,e Cm. Wirden&amp; Ltd, MuiGat</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/403</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/403</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 12/1 I CABLE &amp; WIRELESS LTD: September 1935 - Oct 1941.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-16T22:02:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (176 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. There are file notes on folios 170-175.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 178; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the operations of Cable and Wireless Limited at Muscat.The papers include: the introduction by the Company of a cable running direct from Karachi to Muscat, and from Muscat to Bushire, and the enlargement of the cable station at Muscat, 1935; the issuing of a licence to the Company to land their cables at Muscat, and to use a wireless set there, in exchange for an annual rental paid direct to the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, 1935-39; a copy of the licence issued to Cable and Wireless Limited by the Government of India for landing at Karachi and working a submarine cable connecting Karachi with Muscat (folios 103-105); interruptions to the cable service at Muscat; erection of masts at the station, 1939; the posting of a guard at the station, 1940; wartime security measures, including instructions issued by Army Headquarters, India, for the temporary disabling of wireless stations in the event of capture by an enemy, 1940; and general matters.The main correspondents are the Political Agent, Muscat, and Cable and Wireless Limited. The file also contains correspondence from Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat and Oman.The Arabic language content of the file consists of approximately seven folios of correspondence (with English translations) between the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Political Agent, Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Telegraph cables</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000b2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>