<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:21:11.199Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Confidential no. 554-3. of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-Beneml, Bnshire, 25th October 1929. 'From The Hon’ble Lt.-Col. C.C.J. ^ca*rett, C.S.I., C.T.'F., Pol it i cal Resident in t: e Persian Gulf, To The Pclitiwal A^ent, y-i^ai t. Sir, With reference to the correspond ence ending with mv telegram TTo. 881 of the 6 th 3 c pt ember last, I have the honour to forward for your information a -opy of a 'Vet+er from the Poi’ei^n Qm to the Coloni;al Office, London, TTo. E.4504/2322/91, dated the 13th September 1929, on th subject of the attitude o 4 ' + he Shaikh of Kuwait towards Kajdi rebels, and to state that 1 am very pleased to see that the t’orei^n Office in addition tb the Colonial Office have appreciated your tactful handing of the difficult ;und dangerous situation. T have the honour to be, Sir, ''''our most obedient servant, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.r L COPY. K. 4504/2322/91 Cor? f id. ent ial. POP!'IOil OPPICP, r, .w.i 13tY Septenber 1029 3ir, T am directed by Mr ftecfetary Henderson to s\ ac!mowledc&lt;* + lie r e v. ip t oi CQlor’'Li- Of*i ice letter o, 69006/285/29 of September 5tli v/i tli wliifth v/as enclosed a copy of a telegram from the acting Resident in the ^ernim Gulf reporting the final stages/)’ the evacuation by is a led!) aw ish of h i s n centra t ion. in Kin *-1 i t territory in accordance rith 'he undertaking uhic: he .-ave the Polite w al \gent, Kuwait, as a result of the latter’s visit to Wara; and I am to send to you, herewith, a copy of a telegram received from His Majesty’s Agent and Consul at Jeddah in tils connection and of the Poi' c i^n 0 ice reply. p. I am at the same time to express the Secretary of State’s appreciation of Colonel Pickson’s successful handling of a di+’+'T-ult and dangerous situation. T sm, Sir, ^our obedlent servant, SP/ G. W. PMHPMT..j&gt; 0 COPY * OOFY (B 4504/2322/91) HO PI 3 T HI BUT! Oil ■ Decode, British Agent (Jeddah)# 5th September, 1929, D, 4,00 p.m, 5th September, 1929. B. 6,30 p.m, 5th September, 1929, Ho. 128, (R) Your telegram Ho# 80 and your telegram Ho#87• Hote received from Acting dnister for foreign Affairs expresses warn appreciation of evident good will find desire to co-operate shewn ly His Majesty f s Government. Resolute course adopted by His llajesty^ Goverment is welcomed with thanlzs and sense of obli gation, I am requested to convey the thanks of the Hedjaa Governaent officially to His Majesty's Government, ilay I communicate to Acting Idnister for Sbreign Affairs when I see Mm the facts reported in Bushire telegrams to Colonial Office Hos, 33 to 36? /COPY. (B 4504/2322/91) HO DISTRIBUTIOH. Paraphrase telegram to Mr. Bond, (Jeddah), foreign Office, 7th September 1929. 2. 50 p.m. ho .94. You may act as suggested in last paragraph of your telegram of September 5th: No. 128 regarding the attitude of Sheikh of Koweit towards rebel Nejdi tribes. Any references to bombing, however, should be avoided and some phrase such as 'threat to expel by force' should be substituted.British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 2t&gt;th October 1929. ■ ) v Ho. 64. With reference to my despatch Ko. 61, dated the »}Oth September 1929, 1 have the honour to forward here with a copy of a report from the Political A^ent at Kuwait No. 57&amp;, dated th* 17th October 1929, together with a copy of hie desijatch No. 450, dated the 29th July 1929, refer red to in Colonel Dickson’e comment on the complaint from Ibn Saud numbered (5). 2 * Copies of this letter and of its enclosure are being sent to Die Government of India, Hie Ijcoeliency the High CoBniBeioner for Iraq and Hie Majesty's Agent and Consul at Jeddah. I have the honour to be, ?Hr, Your most obedient, hunblc servant. (Signed.) C.C.J. Barrett. Political Resident in the !, erBian Gulf. HIP MAJFRYY’S GKCRKTART 0? TOR f .'HK COLONIES, COLONIAL 07?PICE, LONDON. Copy forwarded to the Political A t ;ent for Secretary to the Polt Resdt :, Persian Gulf, Bushire, 25-10-1929. at KuwaitConfidential. l^o. 571-S of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bus hire, 28th October 1929. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for information, reference cecrespondence ending with his letter Bo. 549, dated the the 26th September 1929, regarding/situation in Rasa and Raj d. By Order, Secretary to the -Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter Secret B dated 21st October 1929 from the Ag. High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad, to Hvl r, s. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. (Received under endorsement Ho. S.O. 2012, dated 22nd October 1929 from R.E. the High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad.; /Secret. m he Residency, Baghdad, dated 21st October 1929. lEy Lord, I have the honour to refer to Your Lordahip’s telegram ITo. 313, dated the 16th of October, 1929, in which Your Lordship invited my observations on despatches Nos. 546 and. 549, dated the 24th and 26th of September, 192 9, respectively, from the Political Agent at Kuwait. 2. I have Already in my telegram No. 350 (No. 90/S to Bushire} dated the 5th Of October, 1929, given an indication of the attitude adopted by His Majesty King Yaisal in regard to the Najd rebellion. His Majesty makes no secret of his sympathy for the rebels, who, he thinlcs, are certain to succeed in overthrowing King Tbn baud’s rule in the near future. King Yalsal main tains that in his opinion His Britannic Majesty’s Govern ment are making a profound mistake in attempting to bolster up King Ibn Gaud’s tottering throne, not merely ■ because its collapse is inevitable, but because the con tinued rule of King Tbn Gaud over central Arabia based as it is on constant military aggression is contrary to the interests of Iraq, and '’’ransJordan and so to the interests of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. 3. In these circumstances it ^is impossible to eivpiect that a man of King Faisal’s character could refrain from taking more than an academic interest in the fortunes of the rebel Akhwan . There is no doubt in my mind that he has been sending agents to the rebels with messages of eniouragernent and in some cases wi Hi The Bight Fon’ble, Lord Hassfield, B.C., Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, London, S.W.L.with material assistance in the form of cash -- though such assistance is ostensibly provided, no doubt, by the refugees from the rebel tribes now in Iraq. I have no doubt moreover that one of the reasons for the visit of the Amir Abdullah to Baghdad was the desire of the two brothers to discuss how the fall of King Ibn Haud might be hastened and how it might be subsequently used to the best advantage. 4. As regards the report that arrangements have been made for a general move southwards of the Iraq Shammar with the object of recovering Hail for the Ibn Rashid family, it is a fact that the Iraq Shaminar are moving southward from the northern Jazirah into the Billah and Div/aniyah liwas . This southward move of the Shammar is however not unusual when gracing is scarce in the northern Jazirah. Similar migrations took place in 1923, 19 25 and 19 28. m he presence of the Shammar (more especially of the Shamar Abda who are refugees from TTajd) in the southern liwas has in former years a source of anxiety to the Iraq Government in view of possible disturbances on the .Najd frontier, and consequently measures have been taken to keep these southward migrations of the tribe under clofie control. TFc section, fef example, is permitted to cross the Euphrates into th^ Shamiyah. 1 consider it likely that this southward move of the Bhammar has been used for propaganda purposes by those who are seeking to encourage the rebels and had been represented as evidenc* of Iraq’s intention to assist them. 5. On the other hand if the rebels are successful and the armies of King Ibn Saud are routed, as King 'Faisal expects, it is certain that the Sharrun&amp;r Abda will throw in their lot with the rebels and return to Bajd to win what share they can of the spoils, not do I consider that it will be possible to prevent them. How far a definite agreement has been reached between Shaikh- 3 Shaikh Aqab ibn Ajil of the Shammar Abda and Faisal al Dav;ish, under the auspices of Kin. 4 ; Faisal, ~or Hail o be handed o^er to the Sharomar in the event of a rebel victory I cannot say. But knowing that such an eventuality would precisely coincide with King Faisal’s desires for the future, 1 should not be surprised if an agreement of this nature did e^ist. 6 , I may add that 1 have no evidence that the Amarat (the Iraq Anaizah) are in any way implicated in such an agreement and 1 consider that the report that they are implicated originated in the brain of some zealous propagandist* As to the Huwallah I am less qualified to give an opinion, but 1 do not attach much weight to the report of their complicity. 7 , Your Lordship will appreciate the difficulty of preventing King Haisal from giving encouragement and support are moral rather than material. 1 have as Your Lordship is aware forwarded to the Iraq Government a list of specific chargee made against King Faisal by King Ibn Saud; I understand that His Majesty is preparing a de t ai le d reply, and in the me an ti n e he ha s und e r take n to act with strict propriety in future, but, so long as His Majesty’s sympathies are known to be wholly with the Akhwan rebels, this will not materially affect the situ ation. 8 , While I do not share King Faisal’s belief in the imminent collapse of King Ibn Gaud, 1 am becoming increasingly impressed with the fact that his ultimate victory over thr rebels is uncertain^ The Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf in his telegram Ho. 101? d&amp;ted the 16th of October, 1929, forwarded a report of &amp; rebel victory, which if confirmed would seem to threaten King Ibn Gaud’s control of the whole of the Province of Hasa. 1 shkpuId add however that reports of this same battle received by way of Basrah represent4 represent it as having been a decisive victory for the loyalist forces. Where the atmosphere is still so clouded with propaganda that one cannot'clearly review the present situation, it seems idle to attempt to look into the future. 1 have the honour to be, with the highest respect, Your Lordship’s most obedient, humble servant. ST)/ • HUBTTR' YOUNG— D .0. The T *e s id e n cv , .ft' Bub hire, n o ve nib e r 1929 . / ^U.^ /k- Your telep-ram Mo^ 598 of the 30th October. The arrival of the Aw a aim chiefs lias now confirmed the truth of your account and the falsity of 'Buttolph’s. It appears that he and not you is the victim of skilful propaganda. At the same time I don’t think you can rightly object to his passing on any news he may get of what is haxipening in Kuwait. It is his job to pass on any news that he thinks may effect the issue of the civil war from whatever sphere it may emanate. It is for Baghdad to appreciate his news correctly so I have pointed out that you were correct about the \wazim and explained the true significance of the movements within Kuv/ait territory. You have clone extremely well at Kuwait and T am sure everyone appreciates your ?;ork and your knowledge of Arab mentality. Do not worry because a man, who has not half your experience, occasionally sends incorrect messages. I am writing a farewell letter to the fhaikh. T am sorry I am unable to get over to see him again before I leave. 1 hand Lieut.-Colonel Dickson, C.T.E., I.A., Do1itical Agent at Kuwait.0 - 2 - J hand over charge this day week and leave for England on the 10th via Bombay. (rood luck to you all. p-V'UU-7'61/14 &amp; 61 / 6 * @ Telegram From ♦ Political lieaident, Bushiro Political Agent, Bahrain. To No. 1076. Bated let November 1929 Beference your telegram No. 121~C. \ Berore arrival of the flying boat please make certain that there is sufficient depth of water for visit to the Amir will enable xm you to select a suitable sea between ^atif and Tarut dries out at low tide. There is no objection to your visiting ^atif as soon as the Amir replies. The Colonial office, who seem nervous of. me permission to mention to the Trucial Chiefs the sale of aeroplanes to Tin Caud so please be circumspect if the subject arises in conversation with the Amir. Cur reconnaissance has been sanctioned by Ibn B ; ud so before visiting Qatif in a flying boat no parley will be lost copy to the Political Agent, Kuwait. 6d/- C.C.J.Barrett. , ^ Liout-Ool., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. her to alight in a sheltered spot near &gt;atif. Your place. My information is that a large portion of the the reaction on King Faisal of Ira&lt;i, have not yet given Attested. Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 3rd November 1929.61/14 ax/6 2o Telegram F. From To No. loay. X/ated 2nd November 1929. lolltioal Hesident, Mushire. Political Agentf iiatirain. Air Headquarters, Baghdad, aro satisfied about the suitability of the nchorage so preliminary inspection is now not necessary. There is however no objection to your visiting Qatif as soon as you like. The sale of the aeroplanes may now be mentioned oponly. s 3in Baud h s agreed to the reconnaiss- -ance two flying boats will arrive at Jahrain on 9th November to reconnoitre Darin, which has now replaced ^atif as site for aerodrome. ( ne will bring Colonel Dickson| you may wish to trave£tcf Darin in the other. ' ne boat with Colonel Dickson will then return to Kuwait. Air Headquarters would like to send the other boat on a reconnaissance from Bahrain of Dohat as Balwa Bay and the coast line down to Abu Dhabi. Han you conveniently accompany this reconnaissance ? The foregoing refers to my telegrara of 1st November No. 1078. IVXJID’MT. ]ost oo^y to The Political Agent, Kuwait, Dd/- C.C.J.Barrett. T.ieut-Col., Political esident in the Persian Culf. Attested• for ecretar^ to the Political .esident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, Brd November 1929.61/14 ‘ .ft © P. .Secretary of State for*Colonies, London, lolitical Resident, Bushire. High Commissioner, Baghdad No 342. Bataa 2nd reed 3rd.Novemher \ li nm '.la te. . His Majesty's Government have now receive ttie final instalment in payment for the aircraft. The KeUjaz Gov9( nment have intimateu that arrangemenos have been completed for aeroarone and acconunoaation of personnel on Darin island instead of ^atif. They consider it highly t desirable that prior to arrival 0 f aeroplanes flying boats should reconnoitre Darin, but owing to danger from rebels ln th t area th ®y cannot agree to reconnaissance of Hasa coast. Air Officer Commanding is being instructs to arrange in consultation with you for reconnaissance of Mai Darin. Telegram From To Repeated reference your telegram No 4d and jO.. Ihere is no objection to your mentioning to your Agent or to Trucial chiefs the fact that Ibn Saud is purchasing aeroplanes. No mention should howeve. be made « of the mode of delivery or of the place where they will be based. Keferenoe my telegram of 28th October. As final instalment has been paid by Ibn 3aud presume you now hav. no objection to shipment of bombs on November 9th as proposed ? Please telegraph urgently in confirmation. Colonies. Secretary of State for thePost copy to The Political Agent, Kuwait,^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, 3d/- G.C.J.Barrett. Lt-Col,, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.61/5 4. Tel«grsuu From To Repeated High GomaiBBioner* i5a^dad # . ) Ho,, 1083.- w British'Aeent, Jeddah. ' f ' J ' Pa ted 2nd Boveaber 1929. Political ^esioent, Wuehire. Secretary of State for Colonies, London, Ho# &amp;8. Govermaent of India, hew Delhi) S?» _\ r&gt;p . ‘ ' Taisal ad Dawiah, who left Jahrak on 1st ftovenbe? two hours before dawn, Met a representative of the Shaikh of Kuwait* Dawish stated that he was moving into hejd at once. (1) He begged for an assurance from H.M's* Government that they would not permit Iraq or Kuwait v \ribes to molest the Mutair or Ajman families,whom he was leaving camped,in their pre- -sent location South of Kuwaitfrontier. He would warn them not _ . . . ';rf Tr 5VoH JbiC to cross the frontier. (2) He aeks would H.tf's* Oovernraent permit his women to take refuge at Jahrah in Kuwait territory in the event of their being raided in his absence by Win baud’s Bedouin ? (3) If he shot down the aeroplanes which he knows H.lPs. Government have sold to Bin Gaud or if they fell into his hands would H.M’s. Government hold him responsible ? He is anxious not to harm Englishmen or to take action which might set H.M f s. Government against him. r?1 he ohaikh of Kuwait does not now desire to meet Dawish but proposes to despatch a reply in ac cod ranee with the wishes of H.M’s* Government. I presume H.M’s. Government would not deny asylum to women and children but would exclude all Males capable of bear- -ing arms ? As the aeroplanes would be in Bin Gaud* a service ^^resuraably H.M’s. Government would not object to Dawish attempting to shoot them down, but would expect Dawish to treat with proper consideration any airmen that fell into his hands. I request orders as to the reply to be given to the Shaikh of Kuwait* 'the foregoing refers to My tleegram Ho. b6 of 31st October ( 10 71 to Baghdad etc.). RESIDEHT. y.^oo.61/14 Telegram From To Bepeated Dated 1st reed V. Secretary of State for Colonies, London. Political .Resident, Bushire. High Commissioner, Baghdad. No 340. 2nd November 1&gt;29. I agree that no ejection need be offeree to Sheikh's of Kuwait's affording shelter to romnan of /wazim tribe. Rererence is to your telegram of October 16th No 47. Secretary of State for Colonies. Po»t to yr The Political Agent, Kuwait. The PoiiticnJL Agent, Bahrain. ' V- 0 . 0 .J.Barrett. Liout-Col., Political Pepiaent in tne Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 3rd November XSr,s*, to the Political Peri dentTelegram From To Repeated P. K.M's. Secretary of State for the Colonies London. Political resident, Bushire. High Commissioner, Baghdad, No. 341. Dated 2nd received 3rd November 1929. I approve the action proposed for the ejection of Dawish from Kuwait territory. I also consider it highly undesirable that he should be given an interview by the Shaikh of Kuwait or by the Political Agent,if it can be avoided. The foregoing refers to your telegrams Nos. 53 and 56 of October 31. Secretary of State for the Colonies. Post copy to The Political Agent, Kuwait. Sd/- C.C.J.Barrett. Lieut-Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 3rd November 1929.61/14. 81/6. Telegram P. From Political Residentt Bushire Political Agent, Bahrein, To No 1097 Datea 3rd November 1929 For your inlormation If you visit /bu Bhaoi, jeoretary oi State for Colonies has today informeu me that although the sale oi aeroplanes may he mentioned they do not wish mentioned to Tru^ial Chiefs the method delivery or the place at which the, aeroplanes will be inference, your telegram No 12^ oi 2nd Novemher, sale has beon publicly discusaeu also at Kuwait and other places for long time hut till now has not be.m aoknowle&lt;gea by British Officials. s your- telegram No 122 of 3lst October- contained no reference to previous telegram it was b:l dBatooa retar to ^usalbls quarrel with Mespers. 1 *avo now telegraphed Colonial Offloo who will ship bombs by ' 00 ■ ^ a/ing London 9th November. The question of charges is one i or the decison oi the Bahrain Covornment but it woul( courtesy to neighbouring state to pass bombs through free. iQferenoQ is to ay telegram No 1089 of 2na November. Resident The Political A^ent, Kuwait. 3d/- C.C.J.Barrett. Lieut-Col., n olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. in the Persian Gulf.co\£ T~ • n No. 1929. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, • / //♦ Bushire, the - November i929. To The Political Agent, K U V/ A I T. Memoranaum. Reference your letter Ho.591, dated 24th October 1929. The translation oi ihn *&gt;aud*s letter mentioned as having been returned has not been received Pl ease return it early . By order, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. « / 4Telegram M From Britagent Jeddah. To Zusacarl Kuwait. No. 218. Dated 4/11/ reed 5/11/29 Addressed Foreign Office 162, repeated Kuwait, Bushlre 218. Bushires telegram No.58 to Colonial Office. I fear it would gravely offend. Bin Saud if Duwish were allowed count on grant asylum to his women and children in case of need, and that he would regard it as a distinct breach under takings given by H. M. G. The fact that Dawish is cramped in his movements by having to care for these non combatants, is an asset of considerable military value to Ibn Saud, and he Is probably counting on it. Britagent 16204Telegram (C)* f From - Resident, Bushire# To - Political, Kuwait* No# 1105# Dated the 4th November 1929# Bahrain telegram No# 1348 dated 11th November begins* Mudir of Ujair arrived this morning Sunday. He . says Ibn Saud is expected to arrive Jibail within 4 or 5 days and been met by Qusaibi Nejd forces stated to be collected at Hafm# Hnds. Resident# IV ' No. To Political Agency, Kuwait, Dated the 4th November 1929. H.E. Sheikh Ahmed al-Jabir as-Subah, C 3 I., CIE., Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the honour to inform your Excellency that I have been informed by the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf in his telegram No. 1084 of 2 nd. November 1929, that His Majesty T s Government see no objection to your Excellency affording shelter to the remnants of the T Awazim i tribe who have asked to enter Kuwait territory. Usual ending.4 ,, A V 8GJ?$...62l...l081...5,000...18 9 28. H. C. F. 16. No C Ol'tF ITHUtT IAL . SECRETARIAT OF H. E. THE HIGH Baghdad,. COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ iovemberj* 792 9 . Acting By direction of f^is Excellency thei'High Commissioner for ‘Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked mm below is forwarded with compliments to :— •fhe Bee rotary to the Fon* ble the Political Benident. in the Persian Cuif, liushire . The Political Agent, Kuwait, for Acting Couneellor to H. E. The High Commissioner for 'Iraq. Confidential moriorandu’n ho. C/3583 dated 3}*10*29 # from the »Iraq Uinintry of the Interior, Baghdad, with ita enclosure.Confidential . Ho. C/3583. Ministry of the Interior, Baghdad, the 31 bC. October, 1929 To, The Secretary to H.E. the High Commisaioner for ’Iraq, Baghdad (3 copies). Memorandum . x Copy of the undermentioned telegram is forwarded for your information. Sd/- ^ For Adviser Ministry of Interior, Telegram Ho. B/501 dated 31-10-29 from Buttolph Sulraan to Advisint Baghdad.f 32- Tele f;r am Ho. Dated Prom To - Wireless. - B/501. - 31-10-29. - Uuttolph Sulman. - Advisint Baghdad. Retainer mentioned my B/500 left Hail kil/lO states main move against rebels held up until sufficient rains fall in Dahana and Gumraan areas and Horth East aaa Principle concentration arranged take place vicinity Hafir al Ats aaa Ibn Saud intends command in person bringing force regulars from Riyadh backed by small number of recently acquired machine guns aaa Some 40 cars will be brought into use qs far as sandy country will allow aaa Other bairaqs waiting to join Royal standard include Abdul Rahman ibn Saud from Buraida with about 1500 townsmen (1/3 home) aaa Abdulla ibn Glaim from Azaiza with 2000 (1/4 Horse) Abdul Rahman al Bawad from Shqra with 1000 aaa Saud the King’s son (Abu Shuraim) expected to move up with force of townsmen unknown strength and join with Awazim aaa ITuhsin al Firm will attempt raiding, at present, expected to be reinforced by ilaro and other elements and either attempt cut off line of retreat or to join main attack according to orders received irom Imam aaa Ibn LIusaad and Hail force not expected take part at onset if at all aaa Jahud against rebels being carried out with great energy by Rajd Ulemas end informant alleges enthusiasts in the districts mentioned are willingly giving up l/3 of property to the cause aa.a Informant is sensible and information given is confirmed large extent from other sources aaa Do not consider any big move likely take place for some days yet33 The Residency, Bus hi re, the 4th IToveiiher 1929, ^ Ce^ ^ Please refer to your telegram TTo.599 dated the 30th October 1929. Colonel/Barrett has agreed to let you have another Rs.150/- oh account of Secret Service and I am accordingly forwarding that sum herewith in currency notes. Kindly acknowledge receipt. Lt .Colonel H.R.Dicks on,C.I.E., Political Agent, K U W A I T. \frx. «- ^ ■ vsCONFIDENT!;.L i6) No. 612. Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 5th November 1929 From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to refer you to HisBxcellency the High Commissioner’s No. 2013 dated 23rd October 1929 and my telegram No. 598 dated 30th October 1929. I am forwarding copy of Special Service Officer Basrah’s No. I/BS/34 dated 26th October 1929 with en closure for your information. You will notice that Captain Burton’s report follows so closely that of Captain Buttolph, though it is dated eight days later, that I would suggest that the same informant has supplied both officers with iden tically the same news. I would further suggest that the original in formation has been sent by al-Nafisi of this town, who is, as you know, Bin Saud’s agent, end highly interested in pushing his master’s propaganda in ’Iraq. I say'this as I have seen the original of one of al-Nafisi’s letter to a friend in Zubair (it was brought back to Kuwait &amp; shown to the Shaikh &amp; myself as an instance of the type of news that al-Nafisi was forwarding to Zubair) which contained almost word for word the same statements as have been made by Captain Buttolph ^d Captain Burton in particular where the presence of rebels has been reported inside Kuwait territory. 2. I do not wish it to be thought that I write in a carping or critical spirit but both officers apart from making several incorrect statements about the-2 battle of Ingair etc. which may be excused as being open to argument, have suggested or stated as facts the following:- * i 3. (a) . That I^any of the rebels, both Ajman and Mutair had camped close to Kuwait Town (under the walls in fact). (b) That other rebels had mixed with the Shaikhs Rashaida tribe at Jahara to escape notice. (Captain Buttolph’s statement). (c) That some of the rebels (Mutair) were camped at Arhaiyah 10 miles south of Jahara (Captain Burton’s statement). (d) That al-Duwish with his family had arrived at Tawil well in Kuwait territory and 10 miles North West of Subaihiyeh. (e) That part of the rebel Ajman, under their leader Naif al Hithlain (Abal Kilab) had camped at Shiaiba on the coast, and 20 miles inside Kuwait territory (Captain Burton’s statement)• (f) That the Jiblan section of the rebel Mutair had camped at Manaqish hills, 15 miles west of Subaihiyeh with the implication that they were across the border (Captain Burton’s statement)• (g) That the Shaikh of Kuwait had supported the rebel leaders in their negotiations with the Awazim with a letter pressing them to enter Kuwait territory and that this would undoubtedly be viewed by Bin Saud as a further act of the Shaikh of Kuwait’s hos tility (Captain Buttolph’s statement). In view of the expressly stated policy of His Majesty’s Government, that no rebels are to be allowed inside Kuwait territory, the serious nature of the above statements are obvious. i-nd I think it not onlydesirable , but fair in the interests of His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait not to mention my own ,that such statements be emphatically denied# The Shaikh of Kuwait’s position vis-a-vis Bin Saud is difficult enough as it is, without reports of such nature being sent in. 4. That the same stories have already been passed on to Bin Saud by al-Nafisi, there can be no doubt, and that I shall before long be asked to comment on them, is also certain :but while it is fairly easy to refute charges made by Bin Saud’s agents, it is highly undesirable to have to enter into a wordy discussion as to the merits or demerits of British officers’ reports. The point I think is obvious. 5. I have already protested in by telegram No#598 of 30th October on Captain Buttolph’s letter forwarded under His Excellency the High Commissioner’s No.2013 of 23rd October, I shall merely confine myself to Captain Burton’s report, my comments on which will be found attached. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political Agent KuwaitCOMMENTS ON ENCLOSURE TO SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER BASRAH’S SECRET DEMI-OFFICIAL LETTER NO. l/BS/34 DATED 26TH OCTO BER 1929. 0*0 SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER’S PARAGRAPH 1 . The battle took place at Ingair or Injair South of the twin hills of Khalilain. Special Service Officer’s NADGIRA is 10 to 15 miles North of this spot. Naif al Hathlain received a slight flesh wound in the forearm only. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER’S PARAGRAPH 2 . Mohomed al Suhalli only was actually present during the battle, Abdul Aziz abu Ithaar was 40 miles away, and never took part in the fight at all. See my various reports on the battle of Ingair. None of the three individuals mentioned in the last three lines were wounded at all. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER’S PARAGRAPH 3 . The Ajman and Mutair did not move north till eight days after the battle. Abdul Aziz abu Ithaar, never came near the Awazim but on 6th October he fled to Jubail, and then proceeded to Qatif. The Awazim were certainly not at Bajsa on the 26th October, the date of the report. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER’S PARAGRAPH 4 . There is not a word of truth in this statement, especially that there are rebels camped close to the town. I have made it my business during the last few months at least 3 times a week, to ride round among all tents any where near Kuwait and in particular to get to know the occupants. I therefore speak with authority. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER’S PARAGRAPH 5 . Fairly accurate statement though Saud's letter was not sent to Bajsa but further north. The letter was delivered by a Ford motor car which got through from Jubail a remarkable performance and hitherto unnoticed.Entirely incorrect that al Duwish was at Tawil SPECIAL S5RVTCE OFFICER*S PARAOI^IPH 6 , Bo comments* SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICERS PARAGRAPH 7 * No truth in this story* SPECIAL SEP'/ICE OFFICER'S PaBAGRAPH 8 * No truth whatever that al~Duwish moved to Subai- hiyeh on 21st October. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER^ PARAGRAPH 9* No truth whatever that many scattered tents of rebel Ajman inside Kuwait territory. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER'S PAiUGRAPH 10* The Jiblan did not camp at lianaqish hills but Faisal al Duwish did, but well South West of two hills in question. No rebel Mutair have ever camped at Arhaiyah near Jahara or within 35 miles of it at any tine. SPECIAL SERyiCE OFFICER’S PARAGRAPH 11 . Not correct. Itrn Sliuqair did not go, he Is still at Jarriyat al Ilya, sitting on the fance. His right hand man is always with al-Duwish probably others are with Bin Saud. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICERS PARAGRAPHS^ 12: 15: 14 . There has never been any evidence of such concen- traion in Kuwait. Al-Eirm, it is true, appeared in on 29th October in the vicinity of Shaq depression with 600 camel- men and 60 horses, but retired when he heard that Awazim had submitted and that the rebel strength was before them. That this party came from very far* away is proved by the fact that they left several exhausted camels behind them; see my telegram No. 608 of 2nd November. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICERS PARAGRAPH 15. My information is to the contrary. SPECIAL. SERVICE OFFICER'S PARAQRAPH 16 . No news of this in Kuwait. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICER'S PARAGRAPHS 17 &amp; 18 - Correctly stated. SPECIAL SERVICE OFFICERS PARAGRAPH 19.-3- on date reported or ever proceeded there Before or after that date. In paragraph 10 it was stated the Jiblan were at liinaqish, here they are stated to he at Tawaris 40 miles further South. The statement that part of/Ajman camped in the n Shamiyeh M , the group of wells immediately outside the Safaa gate of Kuwait, and that Naif al Hathlain the paramount Shaikh of the Ajman camped at Shiaiba on the coast, are totally incorrect as well as mischievous statements. the Lieut-Col., Political Agent, KuwaitCOPY SECRET. Reference l/BS/34:. Special Service Officer, Basrah. 26th October 1929. Dear Colonel Dickson, I am sending you a copy of my last report, as far cs it concerns the Southern Desert and Najd. This has been rather held up by my absence on tour in the Amarah Liwa, and also by the fact that I was anxious to get as many reports from as many sources as possible on the recent events south of the Kuwait frontier, before render ing a report on the situation. As you will see, my informction on the fight on 5/10 and subsequent events differs from that received by you in certain important respects. I received a large number of reports from varied sources, some of which I know to be usually reliable, and as a result I think that the account I have given in this report is a fair summary of the events. All the reports I received agreed that the Awazim &amp; Ibn Saud’s people got slightly the best of the show, although the Awazim undoubtedly received as severe casualties as the Ajman* I am also inclined to place the rebel locations further north than you do in fact, as you see from my 'Stop Press'- news, latest reports are quite definite about many of them being in Kuwait territory, and some of the Ajman in the Shamiyah. the latter has been consistently reported ever since the fight on 5/10. There are also numerous reports from everywhere about this concentration in Bashuk, and their move to Hafar al Batin. I wonder whether you have heard anything about it? Most of the news fran that Direction usually comes up to S&amp;fwan and Uilman, so perhaps you have no information on this. It is curious how reports from Bahrein tend to- 2 - exagarate news in favour of Ibn Saud f to an even greater extent than the rebel protagonists in Kuwait, and for that reason I am not inclined to put much faith in these vague reports of concentration i# the Hasa district.But I have had many reports frcm all over the place of a large force with Baud ibn Baud at Hasa f and also of a con centration at Hafar al Aj, where they say that Ibn Baud himself has arrived, although I doubt that myself. The Ataibah still seem to be causing a good deal of trouble, but perhaps this move to Hafar al Batin is an indication that Ibn Baud thinks that if he con finish off Dawish, th&lt; rest will be easyl I was very glad to get all your telegrams, for which very many thinks, I thought it as well to let you know the gist of the information I have received on these events, although I am afraid you will disagree v?ith a good deal of it! Still, having regard to the variety of sources from vyhich I obtained by reports, I could not very well put another construction on the events. I am enclosing a note to Mrs. Dickson in answer to hors about seme stores frcm Ashar, which have left by boat• With kind regards, Yours sincerely, SD/- H.M.Burton. To Lieutenant-Colonel H.H.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Pllitical Agent, Kuwait.PART V. SOUTHERN DESERT t:. NliUD (a), Bnoounter between Awazim &amp; Rebels , From a large number of reports received from va rious sources, it is considered that the following is a fairly accurate outline of the engagement between the rebels and Ibn Saud’s forces and the Awazim on 5th Oct:- 1. The Ajman attacked the Awazim camp in the vicinity of Nadjira at dawn on 5th October, After severe fighting, in which both sides suffered heavy casualties, and Ilazam ibn Foran ibn Hithlain (Ajman), was killed, the Awazim succeeded in driving off the Ajman. Naif ibn Hithlain was wounded in this encounter. 2 On hearing this Faisal ad-Dawish ordered Farhan ifoi Mashur and Ali ibn Ashwan, with a force of cavalry, to attack the Bani Khalid, Bani Hajir, end Ibn Saud f s regular troops under Muhammed as-Suhaili and Abdul Aziz ibn Turki Abu Dhaar, who were also in the neighbourhood of the Awazim camp. This attack met with success at first and it appears that the thxtair were about to gain a decissive victory, when reinforcements of the Awazim, under Mubarak ibn Drei, arrived, and succeeded in driving off the Mutair. The canualties in this latter fight were not so great, and the Mutair withdrew successfully, but apparently without any desire to renew the combat. Ali abu Shuwairbat and Ali ibn Ashwan of the rebels, and Muhammad as-Suhaili of Ibn Baud’s farces, were severely wounded. 3. Subsequent to these engagements, the remnants of the Ajman and Mutair retreated northwards and camped in the area Wafrah-Mishash-Shitaf, and the Awazim, Bani Khalid, and Bani Hajir, with Abdul Aziz ibn Turki Abu Dhaar, camped at al Badjsa. 'The latter later on withdrew to Jubail with his regular troops and sane of the Bani Khalid and Bani Hajir, leaving the Awazim at al-Badjsa, where they are now. 4. Numbers of Ajman and Mutair retreated into Kuwait .^_ e _ rr i_tpry and quite a number of scattered tents are sti 11reported to be In the immediate vicinity of Kuwait towiu 5. It now appears to be quite certain that the rebels \ have come to tormc vrith the Awazim at Bad^sa, and they have agreed not to interfere with one another’s movemaits. Messengers arrived from Baud ibn oaud (how at Hasa) , abo\± to 18th October with letters/the Awazim reproving them for making terms with rebels, and stating that he was sending them reinforcements* 6. Faisal ad-Dawish left Misharsh on 12th October with the object of attacking Abdul Aziz ibn Turk! Abu Dhaar, but failing to locate him, returned to Shitaf on 16th October, It is reported that he captured a supply column in the neighbourhood of Nts. 7. A report, considered fairly reliable, states that on 13th October fifty canelmen of Subai raided Dhawi Rashid, (Mutair), near Ash-Bh&amp;qq, looting 400 camels* (b) Rebel locations * 8* The following are given as the present locations of the rebel forces, and are believed to be fairly accurate Faisal ad-Dawish at Mishash abu Dhaar, (South East of Wafrah)* A report of unknown reliability received on 26th October, stated that he moved to Subaihiyeh on 21st October, but this is unconfirmed from other sources, and cannot be considered as more than a rumour at present. 9- Ajman at Shitaf, with many odd tents scattered about in Kuwait territory * 10- Jiblan, (mutair). at Mlnaqish . (15 miles West of Subaihiyeh). Some of the Mutair are at Arhaiyah . about 10 miles south of Jaharah. All ibn Ashwan with Braih is believed to be 11. It is said that Ibn Shuwair,(Mutair), and Ibn Mandil,(Bani Khalid), have proceeded via £ Jariyah al Ilya to join Ibn Baud’s forces. (c) Location of Ibn Baud’s forces . 12. News has been received from several sources of a concentration of Dhafir, Harb, and Bhammar in the Bashuk-12- area. The following loaders are said Id be with this force Muhsin al Fim, Harb. MiJab ibn Nahit, Harb. Mia she al ibn Tawal, Shammer. Grhadhban ibn Rimal, Shammar. AJaimi ibn Suwait, Dhafir. A man who arrived at Safwan on 24th October, ha ving left Bashuk on 19th October, states that this force moved from Bashuk to Hafar al Batin on the latter date. 15. According to a report Just received at the time of writihe, Ghadhban ibn Rimal and Mashaal Ibn Tawala (Sharamar) have arrived at Dulaimiyah, and Mushin al Firm and Ajaihi ibn suwait at Uqubbad. They all intend to move to Hafar al Batin, i:nd subsequently to Jahrah. Reliability of this report is unknown. 14. ibn Musaad himself is reported to be still at Hail, but intends to join the Bhammar and Harb in the near future. lo. There is no satisfactory evidence of any forces in northern Hasa, in spite of vague reports that they exist According to information received from several sources, however, there appears to be a considerable force with Gaud ibn Gaud at Hasa, and another large force at Hafar al Aj. 16# ** i8 reported from Bahrain that a consignment of 000 rifles, 100 cases of ammunition, and four Mahailahs loaded with rice and dates have recently been despatched from Bahrain to bjezirat abu ^-li for the Awazim. Id) Movements o f agents between Baghdad and Kuwait , 17. On 10th Cctober, one Gulaim^n ibn Muhammed abu Kulaib errived at Zubair from Kuwait, carrying letters frcm Faiael ad-i)awish, and left Basrah for Baghdad on 19th October. n -H© same day, a man named Taha ash-Ghibli arrived in Basrah from Kuwait, and left for Baghdad on the night ox ly/20th October. He describes himself as the editor of a newspaper in Damascus called rt Lisan al *jcfcx/''S ./Uirab 1 ’ and said that he had been down to Riyadh, and inter viewed Ibn Saud, and travelled all over Najd, with the idea of writing a book on Arabia* It was subsequently discovered that he had only been as far as Kasa via Bahrain* He had in his possession a document which he stated was the detail of the Bahrain Budget, and said that he intended to show up the bad administration of the British in that place* also gave the impression that he intended that his book should be very anti-British. On arrival in Basrhii, he immediately wired his arrival to the Palace and the Prime Minister* L aTBBT news . 19. News just received frcra a source usually reliable, states that Faisal ad-Bawish with his families has arrived at Tawil . (10 miles north west of Subaihiyeh), that the Jiblan (Mutair, with Jasir ibn Lami, (who is wounded), are at Tawarls, about 20 miles south of Kuwait territory in the neutral zone, that a part of the Adman a re caiaped in the Bhamiyah. .lust outside Kuwait town , an d a part, with Naif ibn Kithlain. at Bhlaiba . (about 50 m iles south eas t of Kuwait town* on the coast )• 3D/- H. M. Burton, Captain, Special Service Officer, R.A.F* Basrah. 26-10-29.Telegram (C)» From - Resident, Bushire. To - Political, Kuwait# No# 1114# Bated 5th received 6th November 1929# Aviation Baghdad A#421, 4th November begins# Your telegram No# 1098, 3rd November flying boats will go from Basrah to Bahrain (? 10th November) and will inspect Darin with Prior 11th November after which further reoonnaisance mentioned in (? your 837) 1st November will take place w Ends# Resident# ft /) iJ; LuM Kvi'fuv j (fe-f ^Telegram M. From Resident Bushire To Political Kuwait. Dated 6/11/29 tUsuL lf(f : ZQ . No.1 121. Your telegram No.606 of Nov.1st 1929. Colonial Office reply as follows, begins H.M.G. strongly deprecate contincus discussion with Faisal al Duwlsh in view reactions on Bin Baud, and of use to wMch such discussions may be turned to by Dawish himself. Sheikh of Kuwait should accordingly inform Dawish that his questions have been communicated to H.M.O. who have replied as follows:- begins: They do not feel called upon to Indicate attitude which they would adopt in the circumstances referred to by him, but as regards his point 2, assurances given to Bin Baud precludes grant refuge to Dawish's women in Kuwait or Iraq. As regards his point they would take very serious view of failure on his part to treat with full consideration any personnel that might fall into his hands* ends. In communicating above, it should be made clear H.M.G-ovt. are not prepared enter any further discussions wl$h Dawish, who should be warned that if he himself or any his emlsarys cross Kuwait frontier again, they will be liable arrest, or any other action that may be considered necessary, ends. Please take action accordingly.CQNglDLM'IAL . Political Agency, *Kuw%it. No. 613. Dated the 6th November 1929. From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dichson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Faisal al-Duwish’s request for interview. Sir, With reference to my telegram No.600 dated 31st October and subsequent telegrams, I have the honour to submit the following report:- 1. On the night of the 30th October at about 7.30 p.m. His Excellency the Shaikh sent round his Secretary to report to me that al-Duwish had written in asking for an interview at Jahrah or Saada the next or follow ing day, adding that he hoped I would meet him also. H© had certain questions to ask, he said, as well as certain important information to impart. The Secretary added that as His Excellency thought such interview would be useful especially as it was not known, if al- Duwish intended preventing the Awazim from entering Kuwait or not, he, the Shaikh, suggested that he should be allowed to see the Rebel Leader and that I should accompany him. I accordingly sent off my telegram No. 600 early on the morning of 31st October. 2. On the same day (31st October) at 10.30 a.m. I visited the Shaikh to discuss al-Duwish latest request, explaining at the same time that I had telegraphed you, and that we could do nothing till we received your reply. 3. Whilst with the Shaikh and at about 11 a.m. a messenger accompanied by al-Duwish’s nephew suddenly # brought the startling news that al-Duwish himself witha considerable retenue had followed up his letter in $ person and had reached a point 6 miles from the city. The Shaikh who was very angry indeed sent for the Duwish’s nephew, a mere boy, and to his face abused his uncle roundly for being a 'worthless and thick headed Bedouin who could not wait a few hours for a reply to an ordinary letter', fi1 he youth replied with spirit that no man could stop al-Duwish in anything, when once the latter’s mind was made up, nor would he the Shaikh be able to stop him from coming to Kuwait now he had got so far and the city itself was in sight. His Excellency much upset dismissed the youth and asked what my advice was, I suggested his being returned to his camp at once. But on the Shaikh pointing out that the Rebel Leader would certainly refuse to do this and would come straight on^ I came to the conclusion that the best means of 'turning' him was to send a joint order to al-Duwish to retrace his sfceps and then proceed half right to Jahrah, where he could await our reply. To insure his going back, zee a car was sent for him and he was invited by Abdullah bin Jabir the Commander of the Kuwait forces to proceed to Jahrah. The trick succeeded and at noon al-Duwish was successfully shephearded to Jahrah, but the situation was still difficult, and both His Excellency and I fully realized the danger of allowing al-Duwish to remain inside the Kuwait border. 4. After a further discussion with the Shaikh, it was decided that I should send for Abdullah al Jabir from Jahrah and give him a definite order from myself to al-Duwish to quit Jahrah that night, informing him at the same time that no meeting could be held at all with him till he recrossed the border. As stated in my telegram No. 604 Abdullah was further instructed to obtain from the Rebel Leader either verbally or in writing exactly what he deiired to say, and to tell him that ±± it would be reported to His Majesty’s Government and if the latter-3- thought necessary both His Excellency and I would be sent out to his camp to interview him, 5, It was Just about this time, and shortly after we had sent off Abdullah on his second mission, that your telegram i.o, loGG arrived impressing on me the necessity of meeting al-Duwish outside Kuwait territory in company with His Excellency the Shaikh. 6, Abdullah who was very late in reaching Jahrah owing to his car breaking down duly relivered my message and after an all night discussion successfully got Duwish out Cf Jahrah two hours before dawn, on 1st November 1929 and across the border about 2£ hours later. With al- Duwish were the following Rebel Shaikhs:- Talah jfibn Hanaiah. ) ) Dooshan Mohamed ibn Watban. ) ) Mutair. Mikhlif ibn Jarbuh. ) Muahi ibn Ashwan. ) ) Braih. Jazzah ibn Ashwan. ) also one hundred and twenty five retainers. 7. Abdullah bin Jabir returned to Kuwait at 10 a.m. on 1st November and reported to me verbally what he had done and delivered the message which al-Duwish desired (v* to conveyed to His Majesty’s G-overnment. ‘i’his I sent off to you under my telegram No. 606 of the same date. Abdullah also brought a personal end rather typical letter fran the Akhwan Leader, translation of which I append to this report. 8. Among other interesting statements made by Duwish to Abdullah the following is I think worth of record, ^-e stated that Din 8aud had spread the report among the Ataiba that he had received recently a letter from Hhaikh Ahmad of Kuwait to the effect that as he Bin Saud had now destroyed the Rebels in Hassa, he the Shaikh of Kuwait desired to be allowed to take over and protect the Mutair and Ajman women and children who had survived the King’s chastisement, and that he intended placingthem in the country on the worth side of the Bay of Kuwait. Bin Baud had added that he had granted the Shaikh of Kuwait his request as he was an old friend. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servait, \ ' , l Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Translation of a letter From - Faisal bin J^iltan ad-Duwish. To - The Political Agent, Kuwait, Dated the 29th Jamad I, 1348 (1st November 1929). By the Providence of G-cd I am victorious, insha’allah, and I have not now come to you from fear of Ibn Saud in the very least. I have only come to obtain a decision from you and to give you a decision also, I was not relying on the High Government when I first contended against Ibn Saud, but I was relying on God Almighty, I now only ask the Government for peace, and it need have no fear whatsoever as regards to its own tribes from me, I Faisal say so. My desire for a meeting with you was only to discuss what you have correctly anticipated, but since you returned me, I obey the Government’s order and I bear nothing in my heart against the Government.Telegram (C) From To Repeated No. Dated Political, Kuwait, Resident, Bushire, Political Bahrain and Highcoma Baghdad. 611 5th November 1929. Your No. 1105. Reports from Akhwan sources are that Bin Sa f ud still in Nejd and that nothing at Hafar Atz except few tribesmen At Hafar Batin there is also nothing. Raiders mentioned my 608 dated 2nd. November returned direction BASHUK. Hillal Mutairi states rebels only waiting for ’Awazim to finally enter Kuwait and for their lightly wounded to get better then they will move south. This should be in ten days. His information usually very good. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad and Bahrain. Political 611p Telegram From To Unnumbereu. secretary ol for Colonies, London* Jolitical Besident, Bushire. Bated vth reed dth ^ovemher 1929 , t the request ol the IlQdjaz Gk&gt;veminent arrangements are being made for delivery at Bari i^homos Ste * They wil1 not be oonaigned to the Political Agent, Bahrein as originally proposed. British Agent, .Jeddah, Has been instructeu to inform the Hedjas Government that reconnaissance will take place on November nth. H ® haB also bean instructed to suggest that any further questions of detail which may arise regarding the reconnaissance or delivex-y of aircraft etcetera sh ,uld be settled direct between Bin Gaud's gent at Darin and the British Political uthorities in the Persian Gulf. Reference is to y ur telegram Bo 59 of 3rd ' ovember. Secretary of State for Colonies. ONFIDBNTIAL. Post copy to the Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. 3d/- C.C.J.Barrett. Lieut-Col., Political Besident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, 8th TTovemher 19 29.Telegram (C) # From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoaa, Baghdad. No. 615. Dated 7th November 1929. Reference my telegram of 2nd November 608. Having proved to my satisfaction that rebel camels were drinking at Subaihiyeh and Tawil wells, I sent Hillal al Mutairi on 5th November to Duwish’s camp with / sharp warning that unless practice ceased immediately I would have camels bombed. I also requested Shaikh issue similar warning and post guards on wells in jS|U3stion to prevent recurrence incident. Hillal deli vered message and returned same day with following reportU) Duwish promised stop practice complained of. (1) He had news that Bin Saud had at any rate for moment satisfactorily dealt with Ataiba. (•) He was moving on 11th November with whole rebel force less Ajman to Wabra, Safa, and perhaps Hafar area. (4) From there his first attack would be on Ajibba and Bin Saud’s force there. (5) n e would hasten move of Awazim into Kuwait so as to release Ajman who at present watching them. Ends Have confirmed that Duwish*s camp just west of Manaqish hill in Shaq. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. PoliticalTelegram M. From Brltagent Jeddah, To Zjisacarl Kuwait. No.221. Dated 8/11/ and reed. (9/11/29.) Addressed to Foreign Office 165, repeated Kuwait, Bushire 221 Sheikh Hafiz W. leaves here today for Kuwait where he is going to discuss situation with Sheikh.Kuwait. He tells me unofficially that Hedjaz G-overnrcent wish him to investigate truth allegations made against Kuwait regarding assistance given rebels. He suggested incidentally that Awazim might now be used as intermediarys. His mission is possibly an excuse to get him away from Mecca. He expects to be in contact with and probably to visit King who will be encamped at Qaryah. BritAgent 16508.Important• Telegram R. From Resident Bushire. To Political Kuwait. No, 1022 Dated and reed 8/11/29. My telegram No1121 of 6th November, Please telegraph when message has been despatched to Dawlsh. M Immediate, Telegram R. From Political Kuwait To Resident Bushire. No.618. Dated 9/11/29. Your telegram No.1022. Message despatched and delivered Dawlsh yesterday noon, I was awaiting return of man who took It before informing you. Political.Telegram (C.) I’rom Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire, No* 616. Dated the 8th November 1929. j* Your 584-S., dated 4th November. Translation Bin Sa’ud^ letter under reference returned with my No. 591. Grateful if you would look through your papers again. Political 616.8th November 9 Thank you very much for the Ls 150/- you cent me with your demi-official letter of the 4th November 1929, which I have safely received. To Captain A. A. Russell, t'.C., Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political esident /\ in the Persian Gulf, BushireConfide ntial. Ho. 603-S of 1929. British Residency and Co nsu late-General, Bushire, 9th november 1929. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded t© the Political Agent at Kuwait for information. By Order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sub.je ct : -Actiyi ties of ITajdi rebels in Kuwait. 1. Telegram from the British Agent, Jeddah, to die Foreign Office, London, no. 138 of 18th September 1929. to Ditto from the £x* Foreign Office, no. 100, aated 20th September 1929. (ReceiTed under Colonial Office letter dated 12th October 1929.}Coda to Mr. Bond, (Jeddah). Foreign Office, 20th September, 1929. 7 p.m. Ko.100. (R). jctivitieB of Bejdi rebds inKcreit). Particulars of tin incident referred to in oy tele^an, Ko.94 (of Beptember 7) h^ve been coiii* luUnicaied to Htfix Wahbi- end v411 rto doubt becone known to Heja^i Govera^ent* You ishould therefore addresa e Koto to Hejax Minister for I^orei/pn Affairs recording the cir^mip st ncee of Faisal ed^DewiBh* ^ entry Into end with- th- Political k(*p nt at Ko^eit took action in this taking given by Hi* iiajaety f 8 Gorermert to prevent the improper use of Ko eiti territory by hojdi rebels - see nrj tele^rEai No.62 (of June 18tin). You should request Fuad Hamza to bring Colonel Dickson's action on tills occasion to tlui notice of You should make no reply to the Note from the Hejaxi Government referred to in your telegram No.l?l f Your telegram No.138 (of September 18th: drawl from Koweiti territory end pointing out that matter in strict ani loyal oompli noe with the under King Im Saud. nor refer to it in your Note luaaed on thie tole^e^p.Telegram (C.) From Politi ca 1 Kuwai t, To Resident, Bushire, No. 621. Dated the 11 th November 1929. PERSONAL.- In view late Resident *-s Demi-Official of 1 st. November perhaps you may consider it Yfiser not forward my No. 612 dated 5th November to Higher Authority even though Special Service Officer T s statements re presence rebels in -'uwait were quite untrue. My object is to try and safeguard Sheikh from insiduous propaganda continually emanating from the Pro Bin Sa f ud news factory at Zubair which has for its object the discrediting of Sheikh with us.Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushine, repeated Highcoma, Bagdad. No. 623. Dated the 12th November 1929. Reference my 615, dated 7th November. Dawish with whole of Mutair yesterday moved towards Hafar al Batin and district south east of it. Owing season of year Akhwan will of course not actually camp at wells indicated, but will spread over wide area guarding their camels whilst grazing, only sending in latter to water to Hafar and probably Safa once in seven days. As T Ajman have been instructed follow, Dawish appears to have abandoned idea of watching ’Awazim. Latter still in Hazaim though their caravans are daily in Kuwait purchasing supplies. Addressed Bushire repeated Bagdad. Political 623mam&lt;.*re being buto ^erod In ais pr o noe f aom of t ie more l«portfc*at oaptivea b* lag sent to the King ^nd, i-i ter &amp; nonainui trial by the haria Gourt, Hogged end put to death* Hatters mignt h*.ve Oeoostc moro serious but for ta© iact that tnm raiding pai'ties devoted ueu^l too muon attention to plunder and too little to taotloal oonaiderat ng # ivl 30 f nftd soswj or tne other Atalbah 1 sdjrrs suoh as iultun Abu el Ula t who had apparently been i avering* trirown in their lot with M Banalna t the dang r would have b on very MUOh greater* Sultan Abu cd Ula him ell is reported to have boon juraaon d by tho King and. to hav been sent to a distant region where he can do no harm* / t, # I an sending copies oi this despatch to His Majesty*a High Oomsisaloners for gypt 9 Ira and Tranajordan f the Government of India in t ie loroign and Polltioal l&gt;epartiaent f t.;e olitio-i ii aidont in the cruian Gull at Bushlrot the olitiou Besldent at Men and tue ] olltioai Agent at * owoit* 1 have the honour to be wit * th# high i t re pect* Sir t Your most obedientfTelegram (C)• From - Political, Kuwait, To - Resident, Bushire, Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad, No. 626. Dated 14th November 1929. The remainder of the Awazim Shaikhs came in yesterday to see Shaikh with caravan of 400 camels. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Highcommissioner Baghdad• Political.* ► I H M) COfUTDENTI AL • 7Z No. 651. Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated 14th November 1929. From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.K., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Polltioal Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Letter from Al-Duwish re aeroplanes. Sir, I have the honour to forward English Translation of a letter dated 6th Janad II, 1546 (8th November 1929) from Chaikh Faisal al-Duwish, the leader of the idchwan forces now in rebellion against H.M.King Bin Saud which is of interest. The letter reached me on 18th November 1929 the day after the writer led his forces away to Hafar al- Batin. 2. The wording of al-Duwish’s letter is merely another way of showing that he is still desperately anxious to be on friendly terms with H.M’s Government. This he has already intimated on several occasions in the past six months. His quaint request that our aero planes should not fly over his people’s heads in com pany with Bin baud’s machines (when the latter materia lize) seems reasonable from the Bedouin point of view. In this connection doubtless H.M’s Government will already have arranged with Bin Saud for the painting of the Nejd device underneath of the wings of his mechines, as apart from al-Duwish’s request it will bo desirable for everyone in these parts to know exactly J o\. lo differentiate between British aeroplanes and those of Bin Saud. I have not replied to Shaikh Faisal al-Duwish’s j l . 'W v.r 2- letter, nor do I consider a reply necessary as his letter after all is couched in the form of a Notice. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.73 Translation of a letter From - Faisal bin Multan ad-Duwish. To - The Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated 6th Jamadi II, 1348 (8th November 1929). After compliments, been We have/infonaed that Ibn Saud has bought some aeroplanes for himself, therefore we are anxious to make it clear to you that, should any aeroplanes come over us we must assume them to belong to Ibn Saud, and no doubt we shall be compelled to fire at them. But as we are most anxious not to make any mistakes and possibly innocently fire on a Government aeroplane ^ and as we are afraid that there may possibly be one or two Government aeroplanes amongst Bin Baud’s me- chines, we would ask that Government abstain frcm sending any of its own aeroplanes in company with those belonging to Ibn Baud. In this way we may be sure that any aeroplane^ that come to us are the enemy’s and not those of our friends. We, as you know well, are earnestly desirous that nothing should happen, that may give rise to the accusation that we are hostile to His Majesty’s Govern ment or are in any way desirous of being anything but friendly.TRANSLATION of a LETTER. From Faisal bin Sultan ad-Dawish, To The Political Agent, Kuwait, Dated 6th Jamadi-II, 1348 (8th November 1929). After Compliments, We have been informed that Ibn Sa’ud has bought some aeroplanes for himself, therefore we are anxious to make it clear to you that, should any aeroplanes come over us we must assume them to belong to Ibn Sa’ud, and no doubt we shall be compelled to fire at them. But as we are most anxious not to make any mistake and possibly innocently fire on a Government aeroplane^ and as we are afraid that there may possibly be one or two Government aeroplanes amongst Bin Sa f ud f s machines, we would ask that Government abstain from sending any of its own aeroplanes in company with those be longing to Ibn Sa’ud. In this way we may be sure that any aeroplane thaife come to us are the enemy’s and not those of our friends. We, as you know well, are earnestly desirous that nothing should happen, that may give rise to the accusation that we are hostile to His Majesty’s Government or are in any way desirous of being anything but friendly.7 H C OHF IDZilNTI AL &gt; From - The Political Agent, Kuwait. To - H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-3uhah, C.S.I.,C.I.E. Ruler of Kuwait. No. - 614. Dated the 6th November 1929. After compliments etc., I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that from very careful enquiries I have made it appears quite clear that the camels of al-Duwish and his Mutair followers have been drinking at the Subaihiyeh and Tawil wells, even though the various camps of the ^ikhwan are well outside the Kuwait boundary. The above fact has become known to His Majesty’s Government and they have received the news with concern and surprise. %s Majesty 1 s Government have now directed me to request your Excellency to issue immediate orders that the Akhwan camels should on no account be allowed to drink at these two places, for just in the same way as it is forbidden for the Akhwan to camp inside the Kuwait boundary so is it forbidden for them to send their camels to graze or drink across the border. I trust Y 0 ur Excellency will not only inform Faisal al- Duwish of the above order of His Majesty’s Government, but will send a party of fidawis to guard the wells and prevent them being used by the Akhwan until such time as the Akhwan move away from the border, which I undere stand will be done soon. 2. I have also to inform Your Excellency that in the course of my regular visits to the r ’Safa* tt and the Kuwait Bazaar during the last five or six days I have noticed that the number of Bedouins who have come into to city to buy and sell has increased ve ry much o f lat e and many of these I suspect are from the Akhwan camps across the border. Though I fully realize that^the^(iiwazim also wear white turbans like the Akhwan and also many of Your(3 it Excellency’s own Hathar tribesmen and Araibdar do likewise, this fact cannoT^account for the large number of white 7' turbaned strangers now in the Town. In the spirit of entire interest at heart, I would urge Your Excellency to look into the matter carefully, and if as I suspefit to be the guize of Ateizim or Araibdar Your Excellency will put a stop to this £xhbl form of trading and tighten up the orders which I know Your Excellency has issued to the guards at the city gates. Ibn Majid and the small son of the late Hazam al Hathlain recently entered the city. I have however not believed the story because I know Your Excellency would be the' first to let me know if there was any truth in such a report being aware as Your Excellency knows that I not only look upon myself as your first friend in this town but have often informed Your Excellency that if I am told everything that goes on, in the spirit of mutual trust, I shall be able to successfully defend Your Excellency and your people from false charges that may later be brought by your enemies,and Which eminate from people living in this Town in the first place. With the hand of true friendship I write this letter and I am sure Your Excellency will understand the reasons that have prompted me to say what I have said. Usual Ending. greatest friendliness, and as one having Your Excellency’s the case the Akhwan are buying supplies in your town under 3. Lastly it has been reported to me that al-Euqum, Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.CONFIDENTIAL. I &amp; Translation of a letter From m- H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah,C.S.I.,C.I.E,, Ruler of Kuwait. To - The Agent, Kuwait. Dated the 6th Jamad II, 1348 (8th November 1929). After compliments. With the hands of affection I have received your letter dated the 4th instant No. 614. I thank you very much for your statement regarding the news which you mentioned in connection with ad-Duwiih and his followers of Mutair,Cth&amp;t their camels, drink at the SubaMiiah and the Tawil that H.M’s Government by* received th£ news with concern and surprise. Your merle — v '|-vO statement has been well noted by your friend. tu deeply thank Your Excellency for -these ^ ■ de-tail-e- Y^ieh *11 -owing- te ^eur kin^nees, towards 1 your friend, and I also ttraaak 7 Your Excellency for all your Airectionscwhich concern us so closely as well as our country. Yes I say H.M f s Government is right to receive this news with concern^ and surprise^, because wishes ^ (a&lt;&gt;K ^ us and our country every progr^ss^eAd^eli^ai^LAAaA I _ ? cu&gt; ^ appreciate a favour and kindness from N^fc/upoa those who are true and faithful to His Majesty. As for news generally Your Excellency is well aw^re that reports always are doubled by the people with false and true and especially by enimies, but I am made happy by the fact of Your Excellency’s presence here and especially by your good intention towards us and I have full trust and consideration in Your Excel lency always. M As to ad-Duwish, as is well known to Your Excellency he ftftprnaphpfl to the Kuwait frontiers intending to med A. us with Your Excellency and because of the disapproval 1 nuu, of H.M’s Government we refused him and ordered him toentered into Kuwait, this only is a false rumour, because I have entirely forbidden their entry. My friend Who art dear to me be assured that I, by God, not accept anything which disagrees with H.M*s Government’s order, and believe me that I am doing my best to acquaire its satisfaction in every way. According to your desirelshall send some of our servants to guard the wells at Subaihiyeh and Tawil from the camels of ad-Duwish and his followers^and will forbid them drinking from them. Our servants will also eject any one that sot they may find from among ad-Duwish T s followers who may have crossed the A. frontiers of Kuwait in any way. Usual Ending.CONFIDENT! A Letter From - The Political Agent, Kuwait. To - H.E.Shaikh Ataad al-Jabir as-Subah, C.S.I.,C.I.E. Ruler of Kuwait. No. 617. Dated the 8th November 1929. After compliments etc etc. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the three questions which Faisal al-Duwish desired should be ■* conveyed to His Majesty’s Government were duly telegraphed to London on 1st November. i hey sue* if your Excellency recolle' as follows First question . In the event of Faisal al-Duwish going south and leaving their Akhwan women and children'-' near the Kuwait border, would His Majesty’s Government undertake not to attack them, or allow any of the ’Iraq tribes to do so. Second question . If, when Faisal al-Duwish was absent in Nejd, Bin Saud’s people were to raid the Akhwan families and camels from the west, would His Majesty’s Government allow them to take refuge at Jahrah. ' Third question If Bin Daud brought aeroplanes hired English-^-— civilian pilots to work them^would His Majesly’S Sovemment hold Faisal a(.-Duwish responsible if he captured or destroyed any of these aeroplanes, as he, al-Duwish was very anxious2* I have now to inform Your Excellency that yesterday the 7th November I received an answer from H.M’s Governmeiit through the Hon’ble the Political Resident to Faisal al- Duwish t s questions, and am directed by H.M f s Govemnment to ask you to convey their -Wai* reply to al-Duwish without delay* As regards his first question f H.M f s Government does not in any way feel bound to inform Faisal al-Duwish what attitude they would take up in the circumstances referrad to by him, nor do they consider it necessary to answer his question in any way at all* As regards his second questio n. H.M's Government has given their solemn promise to Bin Saud not to allow any of al-Duwish’s followers to cross the border into ’Iraq or Kuwait territory, and in no way can they agree to make an exception in the case of the Akhwan women and children. As regards his third question . H.M T s Government warns Faisal al-Duwish that should any English air pilots fall into his hands as prisoners, and he does not afford them good treatment, and full consideration as prisoners of war, then H.M’s Government will take most serious notice of the fact. In oommunication the above answers to Faisal al « Duwish, I am directed to request Your Excellency to make it quite clear that H.M’s Government is unable to enter into any further discussions with him,and to request Your Excellinoy to warn al Duwish that if he himself or any of his emissarys again cross the Kuwait frontier they will be liable to be arrested, or dealt with in such other way as may be considered best.by H.M’s Govemnmait. deepe st This is what had to be said and with the respect &amp; friendliness, I convey these directions to Your Excellency. I should be grateful for an early reply from Y. E« to the effect that the above message has been conveyed t Faisal al-Duwish so that I can inform H.M's Government. Usual ending. ^ US ^ - Lieut-Col., Political Agent,Kuwait.TRANSLATION of a LETTER From H # E.Sheikh Ahmed al-Jabir as-Subhah, CSI., CIE # , Ruler of Kuwait, To The Political Argent, Kuwait. Dated the 8th Jamadi-II, 1348. (10th November 1929). After Compliments, your letter No. With the hands of affection I have received 617 dated the 6th instant and understood the contents• Regarding the reference which your Excellency made to His Majesty’s Government of the three questions which Faisal ad-Datirish desired to be conveyed, and with reference also to His Majesty’s Government’s rpply to them, I told your Excel lency verbally that I had sent Hilal ibn Fajhan to Ad-Dawish, with orders to explain to him exactly what was necessary re garding His Majesty’s Government’s reply, as well as our own orders to him that neither he nor his emissaries should enter into Kuwait territory at all (under pains of arrest). I have now to add that Hilal met him (Ad-Dawish) and told him the manner of the order^and Hilal reports that he Faisal al Dawish stated that he would obey the order to the letter. Hilal, of course, has visited your Excellency and told you everything himself. We, for our part, as already decided, have arranged for a party (Siriyah) to go out the day after to-morrow to guard the wells of Subaihiyah etc., from the camels of Ad-Dawish and his followers. These will also patrol along the frontier and eject anybody they may find from Al Dawish’s people who may have entered the territory of Kuwait unwittingly. For the rest we desire to do everything in our power to * please His Majesty’s Government and carry out their orders. In return we only ask and hope for His Majesty’s Govern ment’s satisfaction and pleasure to-day and for all time. For our one aim is to carry out His Majesty’s Government’s wishes and desires with complete fidelity at all times.CONFIDENTIAL, No, 633, Political Agency,Kuwait, Dated the 15th November 192 From Lieutenant-Colonel H,R,P,Dickson,C,I,E,, Political Agent, Kuwait, To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, H,M f s Government’s reply to Faisal al-Duwishls three questions. Sir, iVith reference to your telegram No. 1121 dated 6th November (received 7th November) 1929 and my tele gram No, 618 dated 9th November 1929 to your address, I have the honour to forward for your information copies of the following correspondence on the above mentioned subject:- (a) Letter No. 617 from myself to H.E, the Shaikh dated 8th November 1929. (b) Translation of a letter from His Excellency to myself dated 8th Jamadi II (10th November 1929). 2. It will be seen that in conveying the reply of H.M f s Government to Faisal al-Duwish’s third question I have slightly enlarged on the actual wording of the message as conveyed under your telegram No, 1121 dated 6th November 1929, as I thought it better to leave no room for ambiguity. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.C0NFI13MTIAL. Letter From The Political Ageat, Kuwait. To H.K.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah,C.S.I., Ruler of Kuwait. No. 617. Dated the 8th November 1929. After Compliments. I have the honour to inform Your Kxcellency that the three questions which Faisal al-Duwish desired should be conveyed to His Majesty’s Government were duly tele graphed to London on 1st November. They were if Your Ex cellency recollects as follows:- First Question. In the event of Faisal al-Duwish going south and leaving their Akhwan women and children near the Bin Baud’s people were to raid the Akhwan families and camels, from the west, would His Majesty’s Govem-r ment allow them to take refuge at Jahrah. Third question. If Bin Saud bought aeroplanes and hired English civilian pilots to work them, would His Majesty’s Govern ment hold Faisal al-Duwish responsible if he cap tured or destroyed any of these aeroplanes, as he, al-Duwlsh was very anxious to keep on good terms with His Majesty’s Government and particularly desirous of doing nothing which might anger His Majesty’s Government against him. 2. I have now to inform Your Excellency that yesterday the 7th November I received an answer from H.M’s Govemmenl through the Hon’ble the Political Resudeht to Faisal al- Duwish’ s questions, and am directed by H.M’s Government to Kuwait border, would H.M’s Government undertake not to attack them, or allow any of the ’Iraq tribes to do so. Second Question . If, when Faisal al-Duwish was absent in Nejd,'Yr ask you to convey their reply to al—Duwish without delay. As regards his first question . II.M’s G-ovem- ment does not in any way feel bound to inform i'aisal al-Duwish what attitude they would take up in the circumstances referred to by him f nor do they con sider it necessary to answer his question in any way at all. ixs regards his second question. H • M * s Gov em inent has given its solemn promise to Bin Baud not to allow any of al-Duwish’s followers to cross the horde into ’Iraq or Kuwait territory, and in no way can the agree to make an exception in the case of the Akhwan women and children. As regards his third q uestion . H.M f s Govern ment warns Faisal al-Duwish that should any English air pilots fall into his hands as prisoners, and he does not afford them good treatment, and full con sideration as prisoners of war, then H.M’s Govern ment will take most serious notice of the fact. In communication the above ansv/ers to Faisal al-Duwish, I am difected to request Your Excellency to make it quite clear that H.M*s Government is unabl to enter into any further discussions with him,and to request Your Excellency to warn a^-Duwish that if he himself or any of his emissarys again cross the Kuwait frontier they will be liable to be arrested, or dealt with in such other way as may be considered best,by H.M’s Government. This is what had to be said and with the deepest respect and friendliness, I convey these dire ctions to Your Excellency. I should be grateful for an early reply from Your Excellency to the effect that the above message has been conveyed to Faisal al-Duwish so that I can inform H.M’s Government. Usual Ending. • Lieut-Col.,Translation of a letter From H.K.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah,C.S.I.,C.I.Lr Ruler of Kuwait. Dated the 8th Jamadi II, 1348 (10th November 1929). After Compliments. i/Vith the hands of affection I have received your letter No. 617 dated the 6th instant and under stood the contents. Regarding the reference which Your Excellency made to H.M’s dovernmont of the three questions which Faisal ad—Duwish desired to be conveyed, and with reference also to H.M’s Government’s reply to them, I told Your Excellency verbally that I had sent Hilal ibn Fajhan to ad-Duwish, with orders to explain to him exactly what was necessary regarding H.M’s Government’s reply, as well as our own orders to him that neither he nor his emissaries should enter into Kuwait territory at all (under pain£ of arrest). I have now to add that Hilal met him (ad-Duwish) and told him the manner of the order, and Hilal reports that he Faisal al-Duwish stated that he v/o^ld obey the order to the letter. Hilal, of* course, has visited your Excellency and told you everything himseii^ tfe, for our part, as already decided, have arrang ed for a party (Siriyah) to go out the day after to morrow to guard the wells of Eubaihiyah etc, from the camels of ad-Duwish and his followers. These will also patrol along the frontier and eject anybody they may find from al-Duwish’s people who may have entered the territory of Kuwait unwittingly. For the rest we desire to do everything in our power to please H.M’s Government and carry out their —~ orders. To The Political Agent, Kuwait In return we only ask and hope for H.M’s Govern-Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait, To - Resident, Bushire, No. 634. Dated 18th November 1929. Hafiz V/ahba arrives Kuwait tomorrow by Airways. \?7, 0 \\* Telegram (C) . From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 633. Dated 18th November 1929. My telegram 626 of 14th November. In speech made to gathering of all the Awazim Shaikhs Saturday Shaikh offered them country between Khabra Dalaiyil west of Jahrah down to Subaihiyeh to graze their camels in, and advised them move up from Hazaim without delay. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad, Political. n.-1.... iTelegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 635. Dated 19th November 1SB9. BuMEDIATE . My 623 of 12th Novenber. Ever since Duwish r s departure there have been persistent rumours that he had decided submit to Bin Baud partly as result collapse Ataib^,but chiefly because of H.M’s Governmait’s recent uncompromising reply to his three questions see your telegram 1121 of 6th November. Above has now been confirmed by reliable person sent by me to enquire truth of story from Duwish himself. Latter who apparently very despondent stated he had given up all hope receiving support from Kuwait or ’Iraq and had there fore decided open negotiations with Bin Baud while still strong and undefeated, especially also as Mutair were pressing this course. Suitable opportunity to do so had been offered him in shape letter received from Bin Saud week ago urging him take this sensible line. Duwish added he had replied asking exectly what terms Bin Saud was prepared offer he for his part stating he only desired beallowed adopt strictly nomad life and be left alone. Shaikh considers and I agree that Duwish has definitely decided on submission at early date. This is further confirmed by verbal message last night to Shaikh from Duwish enquiring if jftie would act as intermediary. Addressed Bushire repeated to Baghdad. Polit icala_. Telegram (E.C.) From To No. Aviation, Baghdad Gantt., Political, Kuwait, JS/l. Dated 18th (received 19th) November 19E 9. JS/l. 18/11 AAA Information received Dawish may move with perhaps 400 followers from neighbourhood of Ash- Shaqq. via Batin and Neutral area towards Syria AAA Reconnoitre to-morrow 19/11 down Batin towards Eastern corner of neutral area and thence to wells in Samah neighbourhood returning via Abu Khuwaimah and Chilawah AAA Air action will not be taken unless fired on AAA Aerofour to acknowledge. Aviation.Y ■ Telegram (C). From - Highcoma, Baghdad. To - Resident, Bushire# Repeated to Political, Kuwait# No. 321. Dated and received 19th November 1929. URqjlIT Addressed to Bushire repeated to Kuwait. According to many reports from Southern Desert Duwish recently informed Mutair Chiefs near Llinaqish that $ no help was to be expected from Kuwait and Mutair had no friend. He therefore proposed to make for Syria. Majority of Chiefs including Ibn Ashwan decided not to follow D(uwish) but to treat for peace with Ibn Saud. Haw Kuwait any confirmation? I should be grateful for immediate notification of any Westward move by D(uwish) in view of the possibility that he may attempt to cut across T Iraq territory to avoid Harb force reported at ^afar. » High Commissioner. Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 636. Dated 19th November 1929. IMMEDIATE. ‘ ' | — Reference High Commissioner’s No. 321, see my No.635 today’s date. I do not think Duwish will attempt any move towards Syria till he knows exactly what terms Bin Saud will offer. Should latter take generous line which I think he will seeing that Akhwan are x±± an unbroken force and still very strong submission of Duwish with whole rebel force may be expected soon. If on other hand Bin Saud demands unconditional surrender of Duwish as preliminary any discussion, latter may either decide try his luck in further resistance or i with small following attempt to make for Syria. In formerformer case he will I think make for neutral zone and try and gather Shammar round him for final struggle. Latter have for some time offered to join him provided he comes further west. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. PoliticalCopy of memorandum Tfo , 1406, dated 9th November 19139, from the Political Agent at Bahrain, to the Secretary to the Political Reaident in the Perui an Gulf, 75 u eh ire. I forward, herewith, for the information of the Hon * ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the latest Ifajd news received through the fresh arrivals from Has a. (according to some reports 700 men only) from the Harb tribe have camped at Hafr al Batin. Another force of Najd Hadhr and Shammar are reported to be at Hafar al Ach, Khalid bin Muhammad, nephew of Bin faud and Muhammad bin Abdul Aziz bin Saud, are reported to be with Saud bin Abdul Aziz is expected to leave Hasa shortly for Najd to take charge of the duties of hie father, who is reported to have left Riadh xto* on Hiursda.y the 31st October. Bin Saud is saio to have raised a loan of £ 8,000 from each province in Najd, and purchased all the of purchase. It is further reported tliat a raiding party under Ad-Pahir of the Ajman tribe attacked few Pawasir Hasa to-day the 9th November for Riadh to take up the duties of his father, there. LATEST NKJP NEWS. It is reported tliat a force of about 2,000 men the latter force. i Najd camels with the Hadhar people at ±0% interest. The cost being payable after a period of one year from the da£ camps and carried away a large number of camcis whicli^varc grazing between Riadh and Haoa. Saud bin Abdul Aziz is reported to be leaving/ y II • ■ (P Confidential. Mo. 617-S of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Buehire, 15th Movemher 1929. * A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for information, reference this office despatch Mo. 49 of the 27th August 1929 t# His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, an attest- ed copy of which was sent to him. By Order, SjJZ for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sub.je c£:- The Possibility of an influx of Refugees from Hejd into Kuwait. Despatch (Confidential) dated the 23rd October 1929 from the Colonial Office.PERSIAN GrULF iiowning Street, C (BglDiUNPIAL. October, 1929. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your Confidential despatch Ko. 49 of the 27th August regarding the possibility of an influx of refugees from Nejd into Loweit. 2. Since your despatch was written the situation which you apprehended has actually arisen and has been successfully dealt with. Insurgents accompanied by their women and children have in fact entered Koweit territory and have been prevailed upon to leave. In the event of a further influx of refugees into Koweit it must, in my opinion, rest with the local authorities, acting in the light of existing instructions, to take such steps as are practicable to expel them, obtaining the assistance of armoured cars should this be necessary. His Majesty^ Grovernment are not themselves in a position to devise special measures in advance to deal with such a situation. 3. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Acting High Commissioner for Iraq.. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, (Signed) PASSFI£LO. THE HON OUBABLE THE ACTING POLITICAL HESILTNT IN THE PERSIAN GULPC QNff IDKNTIAL No. 632. Political Agency, Kuv/ait, Dated the 15th November 192'' From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson,C.I.N., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Report that centrain aUchwan camels v/ere drinking within Kuwait territory. Sir In continuation of my telegram No. 615 date 7th November 1929 and first paragraph, I have the honour to forward for your information copji of a ^ ibject as well as a translation of His Hxcellenoy 1 iply. Laikh, though the latter, as will be seen, did no mtion the matter in his reply to me, he admitted subsequent conversation that I was right in my sur about certain Akhwan having entered the city, addi; that a few of the Ajman did in fact get into the t&lt; in company with a large caravan of Awazim who just about that time were commencing to send in their peop r to purchase supplies. As a result of my representatio. H.E. the Shaikh at once looked into the matter and as suggested by me tightened up matters at the Safaa Gat the only one available for caravans entering or leavi; the city. Eis Excellency further took steps to punish certain guards on this gate for neglect of fluty. I might here mention in passing^ that these Awazim, who were part of the force defeated by the - ^^ Akhwan at Ingair and who now enter the city at will, are all equally good Akhwan with the followers of al- Duwish, and look very much like them wearing as they'^'^^ letter which I addressed to H.E. the Shaikh on th?^ As regards paragraph 2 of my letter to the\ 0 c ( do the large white Turban adopted by the latter* To a person not v/ell up in tribal physithey can easily be mistaken for Ajraan or I utair rebels. I am glad to be able to report that, from further ir vestigations, I am ccmpletely satisfied that the in( viduals mentioned did not enter the city, and the report that had reached me that they had done so, was a 'canard' pure and simple. In his denial therefore, the Shaikh only stated what was the truth. 3. Regarding paragraph 3 of my letter to the Shaikh I have the honour to be Sir j Your most obedient servant Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait*CONFIDENTIAL From - The Political Agent, Kuwait* To - H.E.ohaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-^ubah, C.S.I.,C.I.E. Ruler of Kuwait* No. - 614. Dated the 6th November 1929. After compliments. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that from very careful enquiries I have made it appears quite clear that the camels of al-Duwish and his Nutair follow ers have been drinking at the Subaihiyeh and Tawil wells, even though the various camps of the Akhwan are well outside the Kuwait boundary. The above fact has beccme known to H.M f s Government and they have received the news with concern and surprise. H.M's Government have now directed me to request Your Excellency to issue immediate orders that the Akhwan camels should on no account be allowed to drink at these places, for just in the same way as it is forbidden for the Akhwan to camp inside the Kuwait boundary so it is forbidden for them to send their camels to graze or drink across the border. I trust Your Ex cellency will not only inform Faisal al-Duwish of the above order of H.M’s Government, but will send a party of fidawis to guard the wells end prevent them being used by the Akhwan until such time as the Akhwan move away from the border, which I understand will be done soon. __ 2. I have also to inform Your Excellency that in the course of my regular visits to the 'Safaa” and the Kuwait Bazaar during the last five or six days I have noticed that the number of Bedouins who have come into the city to buy and sell has increased very much of late and many of these I suspect are frem the Akhwan camps across the border. Though I fully realize that the recently eonquered&amp; Awazin also wear white turbans like tho , khwun and also many or 'iour -tcodloncy’s own Kathar tribosmon und. i raibdar or likewise, this fact oannot I think entirely account Cor the large number of white turbaned strangers now in the Town, In the spirit of greatest friendliness, and as one having Your Jxcollency^ entire interest at heart, I would urge Your iixcellency to look into the matter carefully, nd if as I suspect to be the case some of the -khwun are buying supplies in your town imder the uiijO of Awazim or ^raibd&lt; r lour .ol celloncy will put a stop to this form of trading and tighten up the orders / which I know Your bccollency has issued to the guards at the city gates, 3, Lastly it has been reported to me that al-Aiquna r Ibn hajid tmi the small son of the late ilazam al-Ilathl recently entered tho city, I have however not believed the story because I know Your bccellenoy would be the first to let me enow if there was any truth in such a ' report being aware as Your Lxcellonoy knows that I only look upon myself as your first friend in this U but have often informed Your jccollanoy that if I am tc everything that goes on, in the spirit of mutual trust, 1 be able to successfully defend Your iicellency and your people fraa false charges that may later be ^ brought by your enei ies, and which emirate from peopW* livin/^ in this Town in the first place, with the hand of true friendship I write this otter and I am our© Your otoellency will understand reasons that have prompted mo to say what I have said. Usual Lading, Hffjicks ^ 1 1 •i.-i eut-Ool, Political Agent, Kuwait,A CONFIDENTIAL Translation of a letter From - H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah,C,S.I.,C.I.E., Huler of Kuwait. To - The Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated the 6th Jamad II, 1348 (Qth November 1929). After compliments. With the hands of affection I have received your letter dated the 4th instant No. 614. I thank you very much for your statement regarding the news which you mentioned in connection with ad-Duwish and his followers of Mutair, namely that their camels, drink at the Subaihiyah and the Tawil, and that H.M’s Government has received the news with concern and surprise. Everything that you have said has been well noted by your friend. I further deeply thank Your Excellency for your interest in the matter and the advice you have given, which is solely due to your kind feeling towards your friend, and I also am grateful to Your Excellency for all your directions in matters which concern us so closely as well as our country. Yes, I cay, II. M’s Government is right to receive this news with concern and surprise, because I know His Majesty wishes for us and our country nothing but good. This fact I appreciate as being a favour and kindness from God Almighty upon those who are true and faithful to liis Majesty. As for news generally Your Excellency is well aware that reports always are doubled by the people with false and true and especially ygog by enemies, but I am made happy by the fact cf Your Excellency’s presence here ' and especially by your good intention towards us and I have full trust and consideration in Your Excellency always. As to ad-Duwlsh, as is v/ell known to Your Excellenthe recently crossed the Kuwait frontiers intending to meet us with Your lixcellency, and because of the dis approval of II.Ll’s Government we refused to see him, and ordered him to leave the frontiers as warly as possible. As regards the other Shaikhs who you stated were reported to have entered into Kuwait, this only is a false rumour, because I have entirely forbidden their entry. lly friend who art dear to me, be assured that I, by God, will not accept anything whfcch disagrees with H.M*s Government’s orders, and believe me that I am doing my best to acquire its satisfaction in every way. According to your desire I shall send some of our servants to guard the wells at Subaihiyeh and Tawil from the camels of ad-Duwish and his followers, and will forbic them drinking frcm them. Our servants v/ill also eject any one that they may find from among ad-Dawish’s follow ers who may have unknown to themselves crossed the front iers of Kuwait in any way. Usual ending.\ Confidential* no. 6^5-3. of 1929. British Residency and Comm late-General, Bush ire , 16th JioTeraber 1929. M k coDfiPf rand e r men ti one d paper is forwarded to the Political A^ent at Bahrain, for information, the Political Agent at fwuwait, '* By Order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subje ct : Channels of communication with Ring Pin Taud. Blue Print (Despatch Ho. 198 of 16th September 1929 from the Foreign Office to H.M’s. Agent and Consul at Jeddah (with enclosure;. (Received under Colonial Office despatch dated the 18th October 1929.;[Thii Do cament is the Prop erty of His Britannic Majesty’s Government^] EASTERN (Arabia). September 16, 1929. CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [Amended Copy.] [E 4133/323/91] No. 1. Foreign Office to Mr. Bond (Jeddah). (No. 198.) Sir, Foreign Office, September 16, 1929. WITH reference to Foreign Office despatch No. 71 of the 11th April last, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Henderson to transmit to you the accompanying copies of a revised memorandum on the question of the channels to be used for communications between His Majesty King Ibn Sand, or the Hejaz-Nejd Government, and the High Commissioners for Iraq, Palestine and Transjordan, and certain British officers in the Persian Gulf. The present memorandum should be substituted for that enclosed in the Foreign Office despatch referred to above. 2. You will observe that insertions have been made in paragraphs 5 and 6 of the original memorandum so as to cover the question of communications regarding Hejaz-Nejd affairs to and from posts in the Persian Gulf. I am, &amp;c. G. W. RENDEL. Enclosure in No. 1. Communications with Ibn Saud. UNTIL August 1928 communications intended for Ibn Saud were sent through His Majesty’s agent and consul at Jeddah when Ibn Saud was in the Hejaz, or through the Resident in the Persian Gulf (at Bushire) when Ibn Saud was in Nejd. 2. In August 1928, Ibn Saud requested that this arrangement should no longer be followed, but that in future all communications should be addressed to him through His Majesty’s agent and consul, even during his periods of residence in Nejd. It may, therefore, now be laid down as a general rule that all communications for Ibn Saud shall pass through His Majesty’s agency at Jeddah. 3. The High Commissioners at Bagdad and Jerusalem are authorised to correspond direct with Ibn Saud on matters of detail arising out of the Bahra and Hadda agreements, and such communications will ordinarily be sent through His Majesty’s agent at Jeddah, who will act merely as a channel of communication. In cases of extreme urgency, however, it will still be open to the High Commissioners to communicate with Ibn Saud through the quickest available channel, while sending a repetition or copy to His Majesty's agent and consul at Jeddah. Communications intended for Ibn Saud will ordinarily be addressed to His Majesty’s agent at Jeddah direct by the High Commissioners concerned, but copies in the case of despatches, and repetitions in the case of telegrams, should in every case be sent to the Colonial Office. 4. As a general rule, such communications, whether sent by telegram or despatch, will be transmitted textually by His Majesty’s agent at Jeddah, and they should be drafted on that understanding. His Majesty’s agent will, however, have discretion, more particularly in the case of telegrams, to introduce any minor modifications of style or wording which, in the light of his local knowledge, he may consider desirable. It will, further, be open to His Majesty s agent at Jeddah, in any case where he considers that the proposed communication raises issues of political importance, to refer to the Foreign Office for instruction. Information received from the Iraqi and Transjordan Governments respecting raids on their tribes by Nejdian tribesmen and other minor frontier incidents, or replies from those Govern ments to complaints by the Hejazi Government respecting raids on Hejazi or Nejdian tribesmen and other minor frontier incidents, should, subject to the proviso indicated above, be communicated by His Majesty s agent to the Hejazi Government, without awaiting the receipt of instructions from London. 5. Communications for Ibn Saud, or regarding Nejdian or Hejazi affairs, from Iraq, Transjordan, Palestine or the Persian Gulf posts, on all other questions, [903 q—1]2 should be addressed to the Colonial Office, but repeated, or copied, to Jeddah in every case. In such cases His Majesty’s agent at Jeddah will not take official action on the communication until specifically authorised to do so by the Foreign Office. He may, however, if the matter to be dealt with is in any way urgent, take such intormal action with the competent Hejazi authorities as he may think desirable. 6. Similarly, His Majesty’s agent at Jeddah may address the High Commissioners for Iraq, Transjordan and Palestine, the Political Resident at Bushire and the political agents at Koweit and Bahrein, direct on points of fact on matters of routine, or in reply to enquiries, sending a repetition, or copy, in each case to the Foreign Office, and in the case of Koweit and Bahrein to the Resident m the Persian Gulf also; while, on all other questions, he will address the Foreign Office direct, sending a repetition or copy to Bagdad or Jerusalem, when either is concerned, and reporting in each case in the body of the telegram or despatch that he has done so. Foreign Office, September 16, 1929. r kConfiden tial. Ho. 632-S of 1929. British Hesidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 16th November 1929. Memorandum . A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded herewith with reference to correspondence ending with the Political Resident’s despatch to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, Ho. 40 of the 8th August 1929 ( attested copy of which has been forwarded to you). 2. It is requested that the Political Resident rnay be furnished as soon as possible with your comments tiiereon by telegram. By Order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Foreign and Political Department letter Ho. F.375-H/29, dated the 5th November 1929, with enclosures.ooMffrpwri'g From To Bo.?.375-H/29. The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Dated Kew Delhi, the November 1929. Sir, Settlement of outstanding questions between the Shaikh of Koweit and King Bin Saud. I am directed to forward a copy of the communication cited in the margin and to request that the Government of India may be furnished urgently by telegram with your views on the various suggestions in the Colonial Office letter. Letter from the Colonial Office to the India Office No. 69155/29, dated the 4th October 1929. I have the honour to be, Sir,‘ Your most obedient servant, Sd. J.G.Acheson, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.r IZl) P* 6357 • Colonial Office to India Office, r » + + at* -from Oo ioni ai urnce lo inoia umce dated 4th October 1929. Ho.69155/29. Downing Street, 4th October 1929. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with the letter from this Department of the 30th July (Ho.69006/225/29) I am directed by Lord Fassfield to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for indie, a copy of a despatch and enclosures from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf communicating proposals for a comprehensive settlement of outstanding questions between the Shaikh of Koweit and King Ibn Baud. 2* Prom Shaikh Ahmad’s letter which accompanies the Resident’s despatch, Mr, Wedgwood henn will observe that the Shaikh has taken the opportunity to submit claims in respect of raids carried out by King Ibn Baud’s tribes into Koweit territory and to put forward other demands in addition to proposals for the settlement of the customs dispute which Lord Passfield had in mind when suggesting that the Shaikh should be informed that if he co-operated loyally with His Majesty’s Government at the present juncture, they would do what was possible to arrange a settlement with King Ibn Baud. 3. It might be arguod that as the Shaikh of Koweit, unlike the Iraq Government, is in a position to correspond direct with King Ibn would be preferable to leave him to settle claims for raids and kindred questions direct with that ruler. But, as the Shaikh himself points out, he has '‘complained to Bin baud on every single occasion when they (the raids) happened', but with no result what ever. His correspondenoe with King Ibn Baud has produced no compensation and has led to the restitution of none of the stolen property. There is some force in the view that, as His Majesty’s Government are to some extent responsible, owing to the frontier decision laid down at the Uqair Conference at which the Shaikh was not T* The Under Secretary of State, India Office.f II (/t not present for his present k inability to protect himself against Akhwan raids, some moral responsibility rests upon them to do what is possible to obtain compensation for the Shaikh and his subjects* In the circumstances it would seem that His Majesty 1 * aoverrment might properly support the Shaikh’s claims to the extent of inviting King Ibn Saud to agree to their examination by a special tribunal of the nature contemplated in Article 2 of the Bahra Agreement. Such a suggestion might well be productive of no result, but it is possible that King Ibn Saud, faced with the prospect of a special tribunal awarding heavy compensation against Kejd, might think it preferable to settle out of court and to make some payment in the nature of a compromise, ' I am accordingly to suggest that the lists of raids into Koweit territory now furnished by the Shaikh should be communicated to King Ibn Saud by His Majesty’s Government, with the suggestion that a tribunal similar to that provided for in Article 2 of the Bahra Agreement should be set up for the purpose of examining the claims for compensation arising therefrom* x 4* Turning now to the detailed proposals for a settlement contained in Statement 3 accompanying the Shaikh’s letter, it may be doubted whether the suggestion for the solution of the customs dispute, in the form suggested by the Shaikh, would / be acceptable to King Ibn Saud ir would operate satisfactorily in practice. There seems nothing inherently unreasonable, however, in the Shaikh’s projtisal that King Ibn Saud should d establish four customs postf at watering places within the / Koweit frontier* Presumably the places suggested are situated upon the ordinary caravan routes frcm Koweit town in the * interior. In its present form, however, the proposal would J be open to the objection that it would be to the interest of caravans to avoid these posts in order to evade the payment of customs duty to King Ibn Saud* And in order to overcome this objection it would olearly be necessary to eliminate this element of self-interest. 5. As Mr. Wedg&gt;7bod Benn is aware, in the case of Bahrein a transit due of 2 per cent is charged on goods entering7. 2. (fZS ViP entering the island and subsequently being re-exported to Nejd. It seems essential that the Shaikh of Koweit should be brought to accept in principle the imposition of a similar transit due ‘ in the case of goods exported from Koweit to Nejd. If it could be arranged that the import duty charged by l^ing Ibn Saud on goods entering his territories from Koweit were less than the import duty charged by the Shaikh of Koweit by at least the amount of the proposed transit due (for example, if the Koweit import due were a per cent, and the at Bejd import due 6 per cent, the difference representing the transit due) arrangements could, it is suggested, be made whereby the Shaikh would charge full import duty in the first instance upon all goods entering his territory, but would subsequently refund the balance over and above the transit due in respect of any consignment for which a caravan leader could produce evidence that he had paid import duty to a N^jdi customs post. By this means caravans into Nejd would have no interest in avoiding payment to King Ibn SauA^ customs posts, since they could subsequently recover the equivalent from the Shaikh of Koweit. Clearly, if the difference between the Koweiti and Nejdi import duties were greater than the transit due charged by the Shaikh of Koweit, there would be a definite incentive on the part of Nedji caravan leaders to pay Eejdi import duty. An alternative and possibly simpler arrangement would be for caravans leaders merely to nand over to the idedji customs posts their receipts for the Payment of Koweiti import duty and ior the Hejdi customs officials themselves subsequently to recover from the Koweiti Customs Administration the balance over and above the transit due. It seems probable that the absence of financial interest, coupled with the fear of condign punishment if caravan leaders were caught attempting to avoid King Ibn Baud’s customs posts would be sufficient to ensure the reasonably efficient working of the arrangement proposed. 6. The proposals in paragraphs 1, 4, 5, 6 and 7 of State ment 3 accompanying the Shaikh’s letter appear to be un exceptionable and such as might properly be supported by His Majesty’s Government.7. Mr, Wedgwood Benn will obeerve from Colonel Barrett’s despatch that the Shaikh has suggested a revision of the boundaries of Kowcit to coincide with those laiJ do»vn it., the Angio-Turkish Convention of 19J3, It Beams doubtful whether any useful purpose would bo served by re-opening at the present state the question of the Koweit-tfejd frontier, and it is not recommended that any suggestion to that effect should be made to King Ibn Saud, It is for consideration, however, whether the Resident’s suggestion that an attempt abould^e mado to induce King Ion Saud to return ^ Awasim tribe to the suzerainty cf the Shaikh of Koweit might not be adopted. While the TJqair Conference was in progress King Ibn Saud showed himself quite willing to do this, but at that time the Awazin them selves preferred to remain under k his protection. In view cf the inter-tribal conflict now prevailing in Nejd, it seems likely that the Awazim would be glad to transfer their alleg iance. The greater part of this tribe’s habitat is either within Koweit territory proper or with the neutral zone. They were, as Colonel Barrett points out, originally a Xoweiti tribe. They rank 3ow in the tribal heirarchy and consequently it is ualikely that King Ibn Saud would feel any strong objection to their lose. On the other hand, on occasion they have shown that they can fight reasonably well, and if supported by armoured cars, might be capable of protecting Koweit from Akhwan raids. 8. It is, moreover, of considerable importance to His Majesty's Government that the Shaikh of Koweit should be put in a position to defend himself without having to cull upon the British Air Force and armoured cars. It seems possible that when Iraq attains to full independence the present Imperial garrison in that country may have to be reduced. If so, the British commander might find it embarrassing if he were required at any time further to reduce the strength of his force by detaching contingents to assist in the defence of Koweit. As pointed out earlier in this letter, His Majesty’s Government WZSiG over fine ct can sx scarcely divest theme elves of all responsibility fox the present defenoelase etace of Kuweit, ajil i &lt;« Is s«i^^ww vSd tnat in common equity they should do what is possible to remedy the unsatisfactory position that exists in that territory today, 9. Lord Pasafield would oq glad to be furnished in due course with the observations of Mr, 'i'edgwood 3enn on the proposals new submitted by tns Shaikh, and upon the considera tions advanced in the present letter. If, however, i£r, v/odgwood Benn considers that it vrould be preferable that these questions ehculd In the first instance, be discussed orally between representatives of the Departments concerned, His Lordship would be happy to arrange for an interdepartmental conference to be held at the Colonial Office for that purpose, 10. A similar letter is being addressed to the foreign Office and a copy ol t:.ie correspondence is beir^* sent to the Air Ministry. I am, etc, , £d. G.Grindle.. ^ i tZQ Confidential. Ko. 635-S of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire, l^th Boyemher 1929. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for infonnation, reference telegram from His Majesty’s Agent and Consul at Jeddah to him. Ho. 196 of the 30th September 1929. By Order, for Secretary to the Political -KeBident in the Persian Gulf. Sub.je ct : Ibn Saud’s measures against the rebel AMhwan. Telegram from the Foreign Office, London, to H.M’s. Agent and Consul at Jeddah, Bo. 107, dated the 14th October 1929. (Received under despatch from the Colonial Office, London, dated the 24th October 192S )(E. 5239/23^2/91). To Arabia. (£7) \^( Goae telegram to Mr Bond. (Jeddah). Foreign Office. 14th October, 192.9. o.55.p.m, No. 107. (B). \ Your telegram No. 144 (of September 30th: Position ol Akhwan in regard to Iraqi and Koweiti frontiers). You should inform Ibn Saud in reply to his memorandum of September 14th, that His Majesty’s u-overnment gladly agree to his posting a force near the Iraqi frontier to intercept rebels. They would turthei welcome any proposals which he may be prepared to make for the establishment of close liaison of the frontier, and suggest that he should designate emissaries to keep the local frontier authorities in Iraq and Koweit informed of the movements of his troops and of the rebels. His Majesty’s Government regret* however, that ( they cannot reconsider their previous decision against any crossing of either frontier by Ibn Gaud's forces. As Ibn Saud has already been assured, all possible steps will be taken to prevent the use of Iraq and Koweit as a refuge by Akhwan rebels, and the local military authorities have been authorised if necessary to take drastic action to achieve this object. Ibn Saud will, however, himself realise that if rebels should succeed either in cFossing frontier with their women and children, or in effecting junction with latter in Iraqi or Koweit territory, local military authorities may be placed in most embarrassing position. His Majesty's Government therefore hope that Ibn Saua will be able to take effective measures to prevent such a contingency arising. YouYou should also explain to Thn 3aud that if* his own forces cross the Iraqi or Koweit frontier it may oe impossible from the air to distinguish them from rebels and thus there may be serious risk of their oeing bombed.Bushire, 18th November 1929. Telegram Code From Secretaiy of State for Coloniee, London* To Political Resident, Bushire No. Nil Bated 15tJa (received 16th) Novemuer x9ii9. it is proposed to communicate with Ihn Saud all the information contained in y^ur telegram of 8th Novemuer No.61 except that in (v). Bo you see any objection ? Please repeat your reply to Jeddah who is aware you are oein^ consulted. - SECKR ***** Post copy forwarded to the Political Agen at Kuwait, Bushire Residency telegram No. 61 referred to 615'? above repeated his telegram No. 16b of the 7th November 1929. By Order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram Code from To .Repeated Political Heciuent, Buoliire Secretary of State for the Colonies, London 3So*66« British Agent, Jeddah, No.1162 Hated 16th November 1929. Your telegram of November loth referring to telegram N 0 . 61 . Isee no objection. - HSSIDiiNT - *** Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait. Bushire Residency telegram No. 61 referred to 6^5 } above repeated his telegram Ho. 16b of Uie 7th November 1929. By Order, kftLu^ for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 18th November 1929.mamHi TelegrsLm C. URGENT. From HighComa Baghdad, To 2.Politleal Kuwait. 1. Resident Bushire No. 524 Dated and reed. 20/11/29# Addressed Bushire repeated Kuwait. Kuwaits 635. Gratefull if Kuwait could telegraph present whereabouts of Dawish and Keep me informed of his movements.Telegram (c.) From Political, Kuwait, To Re sident, Bushire, Repeated Highcoma, Baghdad, No. 639. Da te d the 23rd. November 19 29 My 638. The curious return of Akhwan to Shaqq after they had got half way to Hafar is probably connected with arrival Kuwait of Bin Sa’ud's Minister. See my telegram No. 623 of 12th November. Addressed Busliire repeated Baghdad. Political 639.Telegram (C) # From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad No. 640- Dated 23rd November 1929. My 638 last paragraph. Shaikh reports guards at Jahrah tried to keep Akhwan camels from drinking but latter’s escort threatened immediate reprisals from main body if interfered with. Similar story just in from patrols at Subaihiyeh and Tawil. As most of Shaikh’s forces now guarding Kuwait camels grazing in North West of State and it clearly impossible for small patrols camped on wells in question to prevent Akhwan drinking under .threat force, would request that sectior Armoured Cars be sent down to Jahrah for one week, and that two air reconnaisances be sent over Subaihiyeh next week duxxi during afternoon, time when camels likely drink. Above measures will show Akhwan leaders that we mean deny them only water available across border, and will probably result their moving farther South. Pol it ical.f Telegram (C). From - Resident, Bushire. To - Highcam, Baghdad. Repeated to Political, Kuwait. No. 1190. Dated and received 24th November.1929. IMPORTANT . Addressed to Baghdad repeated to Kuwait. Kuwait telegram No. 640, 23rd November. I support Political Agent’s request and am repeating gist of his telegram to Colonies. Resident.Telegram (C). From - Special, Basrah* To - Political, Kuwait. No. 1/234. Dated and received 24th November 1929. Have heard Duwish sent message to Hafidh Wahba want to meet him Kuwait and former replied that he would go to his camp. Please telegraph me if true and what are future movements of Hafidh Wahba. SpecialTelegram R. From Britagent Jeddah, To Zusacarl Kuwait, No.225 Dated and reed 24/11/29. Addressed to Foreign Office telegram No.170, repeated to Bushire and Kuwait Despatch No.225. I have recieved letter from King dated 17th November with reference to my letter to Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs of November 1st. Following is its gist. News regarding Awazim is incorrect; it is possibly trick of Doweish in order to have friends within Kuwait territory whom he can use. Even supposing it were a fact, is it lawfull for Sheikh of Kuwait in present critical Juncture to allow portion of Kings subjects to leave his country and settle in Sheikhs territory? King therefore protests strongly against action of Sheikh of Kuwait, as also against approval given it by British Govern ment, and requests all persons claiming to be Awazim or other subjects of His Majesty who may have taken refuge in Kuwait should be expelled at once, as this embarrasses his action against rebels. Telegram No.070 of the 24th. Agent•'31 Telegram (C). Prom - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No# 641. Dated 25th November 1929. HvlCODlATE. As I have just received news that whole Akhwan force is immediately moving South for line Hafar-Safa- Jariya al Sifli request that despatch armoured cars suggested my 640 be held up pending confirmation news air reconnaisance may continue but should not cross border. Addressed Bushire repeated to Baghdad. Political# atgxtrtKHt.It? &amp; Telegram (C) # 5*rom - Highcoma, Baghdad, To - Resident, Bushire* Repeated to Political, Kuwait, No# 329# Dated and received 25th November 1929, URGENT Addressed to Bushire repeated to Kuwait# Reference Kuwait’s 641 and your 1190 air recon naissance will be carried out as required starting tomosprow. Armoured cars standing by to proceed Jahrah if required. Highcoma.Telegram (C) * From - Political, Kuwait, To - Special, Basrah, No. 642, Bated 25th November 1929. Your 1/234. As far as I know no truth in report. Individual says he is awaiting his orders from Bin Saud. PoliticalTelegram M, From BritAgent Jeddah To Zusacari Kuwait. No.226 Dated and reed. 25/11/29. Addressed to Foreign Office 172, repeated Bushire and Kuwait 226. A messenger has arrived from Riyadh to Amir Feisal in Jeddah with report that Duwish has asked for pardon, hut that King has replied this can only be decided by Sharia, the report adds that King proposes attack at once in force. It is privateer stated that Bin Saud intends to attack Kuwait, as Sheikh of Kuwait is supporting rebels. It is significant in this connection in a conversation whivh I had with Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday, the latter restated his case against Kuwait somev/hat emphatically. He also handed me an aide-memoir which he stated represented only his own personal views, and which is in reality a tirade against the perfidlty of Kuwait, on line Kings memorandum enclosed in my Despatch No.225 of Sept . 30 th, though it also i states incidents have occured there which are difficult to explain, except on the grounds that His Majestys Government have gone back on their undertakings. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs also insistently demanded that any rebel entering Iraq or Kuwait should be arrested, tried and punished, and that in accordance with international law he should be disarmed. Here he says he also speaks for Hedjaz Government. He had not yet recieved news of Duwish's offer submission. The coincidence of Kings projected movement to the neighbour hood of Kuwait border, as foreshadowed by Hafiz Wahba ( see myr/i 2 . my telegram No.165 of November 8th ), the present attitude of Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs In spite of all past assurances, and the rumour referred to above, suggest possibility that Bln Saud may be tempted to use opportunity presence hie forces on Kuwait border, which His Majesty’s Government has so strongly recommended, to teach Kuwait a lesson. Present intention of acting politically may therefore be to forestall eventual protests in case of an action against Kuwait by Bln Saud. Brit Agent.Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwqit, To - Resident, Bushire # Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 644. Dated 25th November 1929. UROjUNT After despatch of my No.640, Shaikh addressed strong protest to Duwish and said he had asked for armoured cars and aeroplanes to deal with situation. Duwish in reply dated 24th November received this morning says protest appeared justified, and some of Mutair Camels had been guilty acts complained of, hopes there will be no need any violent measures as he moving South immediately with whole force his yfright wing consisting of Braih to Haffar^ the Jiblan in centre to Safa ; and his left consisting of himself and Ajman to the two Jerriyas. In special verbal message to Shaikh Duwish said that Ibn Shuqair by Bin Saud T s orders had written to say that he had been empowered to act as intermediary. That he Duwish had told Ibn Shu^air to inform King in writing that he was prepared to submit at once with his whole force on following conditions. First . That he be free to purchase supplies in any town he wished whether in ’Iraq, Kuwait or Nejd. Second . That he should not be required meet Bin Saud» Third. That he be allowed adopt Bedouin life in future, and not be ordered reside in any town. Duwish added that he knew positively that to test his loyalty Bin Saud would as soon as he surrendered order him to prosecute an unofficial war against Kuwait, this he Duwish assured Shaikh he would under no circumstances agree to do. Other items news from Duwish as follows. Bin Baud engaged in trying get Ajman treat separately. That force at Hafar al Atz consisted of only 350 hathar troops andand some tribal elements, that portion of Ibn Mussaiyis force near Artawiyeh had come over to him. That to strengthen his position in coming negotiations he had ^ ordered raids South to recommence at once. Political.Telegram (C) # From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire* Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad* Bo* 643* Dated 25th November 1929. Yesterday carried out motor reconnaisance of Southern border Kuwai t between Shaqq and Batin. After moving up Batin and visiting Kuwait tribal concentration Jest of Qraa al Murru I returned via Jahatah. No Akhwan camped inside border, saw few their camels near Saadah obviously making for Jahrah to water. Tour lasted 13 hours. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. Political.CONFID ITOAL &lt; ^ No. 645, Political Agency, Kuv;ait. Dated the 25th November 1929 0 From To Lieutenant-Colonel P.R.P#Diokson, C.I.E*, Political Igent, Kuwait, The Hon’ble the Political Resiaent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Faisal Duwish’s reply to His Excellency shaikh .Jiniad’s complaint re ^khwan camels watering at jahrah,Gubj^aihiyob and Tawil, Sir, In continuation of my texegram No, 644 of 25th_ Ncvaaber 1929, I have the honour to forward for your information translation of the actual letter which His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad received from Shaikh Faisal ad« Duwish this morning regarding the matter referred to at the head of this letter, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ ' Lieut-Col., Political Ag ent, Kuwai t• /Translation of a letter Frau - Faisal bin Sultan ad-Duwisli. To - H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, Ruler of Kuwait* C*S*I•,C.I•A•) Dated the 22nd Jamad II, 1548 (24th November 1929)* After Compliments, Your messenger Hillal has come and reported to us every thing you told him about our camels watering and that we should immediately cease from coming to Jahrah and Subaihiyeh for the purpose* You have right on your side and God willing we shall obey your order* Be at ease, for we are in process of marching south, our right wing will make for al-Hafar, our m centre will while march on al-Safa,/our left wing with ourselves and njnian will reach (a riah. The reason why we have been staying all this time on your borders is because we were expecjjjja/ and hoping that you would arrange tilings for us all th' time, for the sake of,God preserve you, the friendship formerly existing between us, otherwise we have no desV or inclimation to reside in this part of Arabia. Forjt' future, you can rest assured and believe^tha$ weJwl far CLfcd near will remain your friends, and that we Ido anything for you, except that which is not in ou ^to give* This we say, God helping us. ‘There remains now the fact that not every one our followers of the Ajman and Mutair have yet become aware of our decision to depart, and some of them may still come to these watering places (Subaihiyeh, Tawil and Jahrah) Please do not allow them to be bombed befc warning them that 1 have gone and they must fol This because they do not Iqiow*SECRET . No, 646. From 'at&gt;; To Political Agency, Kuv Dated the 25th Novf Lieutenant-Colonel H.R•P.Dickson,C.. Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Visit of the rebel leader shaikh Naif al Hathlain. Sir, I have the honour to report that on 19th No vember 1929 and unbeknown to me, Shaikh Naif al Hatlila^ paramount chief of the Ajman turned up secretly with one man on the outskirts of Jahrah, and sent in and ask if he could see His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait. The latter without referring to me in anyway, sent and told him to quit Kuwait territory without delay, as the British Government had forbidden all intercauree between rebel leaders and himself, and that if the Political Agent heard about his arrival he would have him arrested at once. Shaikh Naif hastily departed. I am sorry to say that His Excellency only told me the story on Saturday the 23rd ; and then only when I taxed him with having heard about the rebsl leader’s entry from another source. 2. . It is possible that His Excellency honestly thought I would have the rebel Shaikh seized^as H.M’s Government had in their recent reply to al-Duwish’s three questions, threatened that this would be done in the case of further visits of rebel leaders, so he quietly had him ejected, intending perhaps afterwards to inform me. As he said nothing I had to point out to His Excel lency that he had not played ’’straight^ by me. 3. I further pointed out to him that it was b: own efforts also, and not through him th^-that some of the rebel in the evening at Jahrah* And that only M V&gt; UUi od to him officially he proceeded to write and report fcy the fact to me as well as the Subaihiyeh and Tawil in cidents, mentioned in my telegrams Hos* 638 and 640 of 22nd and 23rd November respectively. 4. As already mentioned in the first of these telegrams I fancy His bccellency lost his head somewhat after the recent arrival of Bin Saud’s emisary Shaikh Hafidh Wahba. He did not know what the latter was going to report to me or what information I was going to to him impart/about rebels and Kuwait. He fancied that to keep silence was the best policy. I have now throughly rubbed in the fact to His Excellency that he has no better friend than myself here, and that he need fear the intrigues of no person, enemy or supposed friend, in his Town provided he confides in me always and above all trusts me. I think he has taken the lesson to heart. 6. In fairness to the Shaikh, I must add that he is surrounded by a great many rogues and traitors, who while flattering him always, are in many cases in con tant communica ion with Bin Saud. He knows this thou^ does not feel strong enough to take energetic action. 7. As regards the Ajman leader, Shaikh Ahmad ir~ connected by blood ties to both the Hathlain house as well as to that of Duwish^and this fact alone tends t make him favour and wish for the success of t&gt; It is after all only natural and I cannot blam I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, \ Lieut-Colo ; Political Agent, Kuwait.No* 647«, CONFIDENTIAL Political Agency ? Kuwait (@ Dated the 26th Novonber From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait* To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Intelligence Sir I have the honour to report that there is t unconfirmed rumour in the town to-day that Ali * Shaikh of the Braih section of the Rebels, hay4 a caravan of Harb at Samah in the Northern Neut Thirty men of the Harb are reported to have be- in the process. 2. It is also reported that Dhafir thie’w f Iraq have been responsible for the loss of mar by the Akhwan now camped along the Southern bo: Kuwait* A statement to this effect was actua” Faisal al-Duwish to Hillal, His Excellency’s who brought in the news this morning (25th Nov that the Akhwan were leaving for the South - set gram No* 644 of date. As Hillal is a reliable pers there may be sane truth in the story* liked badly to revenge himself on the Dhafir fo acts, but as they were under British protection hii. hands were tied* Duwish is reported to have said he woul&lt;? I have the honour to be Your most obedient Sir\b U Telegram M« From Political Kuwait To Resident Bushire No.650 Dated 26/11/29. Sheikh has asked me If I can explain presence Hafith Wahbas in Kuwait* Latter has neither produced credentials nor mentioned object his visit to Sheikh. Latter feels that Bln Saud has shown him scant courtesey in matter.Telegramf C) Fron - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. •Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 651. Dated 26th November 1929. Reference Jeddah’s No.226. It is difficult to see from where Bin Saud is going to produce force to make attack on rebels. His only proved concentrations of any strength are the Ajibba force and a new force recently collected at Hafar Atz. Role of both these appears to be to cover movements of J 1 numerous food caravans now working between Qasim Su^air and the coast via Hoffuf. Before everything Bin Saud must improve food situation Nejd where famine condifcions prevail. Situation is aggravated by lack transport. i To sum up Duwish does not aopear to be contem plating submission as result of military pressure but at dictates common sense. Though he immensely strong judging by Arabian standards, he feels that without friends or supplies he cannot hope for ultimate success. '.7ith Unimpaired forces he realizes that Bin Saud likely offer him generous terms now. Addressed Bush ire repeated Baghdad. PoliticalTelegram (C) . From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire* Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad* No. 652. Dated the 26th November 1929. My 644. Confirmed this morning that Duwish is on move South. He camped yesterday 20 miles South West Hamatiyat. His latest dispositions Braih and Jiblan for Hafar, himself with Ilwa for Safa, Ajman for Jariyah. Latter trying per suade Awazim accompany them. Split has occurred ranks Awazim, Ibn Juma head sheep sections has departed South, al Millaabi Shaikh atm stronger camel elements has moved closer Kuwait, waters Wafra and Grain. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. Political.Telegram (C) . From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire. No* 654. Dated 26th November 1929. S Your No. 63251 dated 16th November. Colonial Office letter opens up questions of % such vital importance that I feel I may do grievous injustice to Shaikh if I attempt submit my canments by telegram. Would it be possible to suggest to Govern ment of India that you would like discuss matter fully with Shaikh and myself before replying their No. 375 of 5th November. I should myself feel much happier if I could talk over matter with you first especially as several points raised in my No. 451 of 1st August seem to have been overlooked by Colonial Office. Political0 / / rv^ Telegram (M) . From - British Agent, Jeddah. To - Political, Kuwait. No. 228. Dated 27th received 28th November 1929. IMPORTANT. \&lt;3i Addressed to Foreign Office 174 repeated Bushire Kuwait, Baghdad 228. Following is gist letter received from King dated November 17th. The rebels have learnt Bin Saud f s imminent attack and have been advised from High quarter in neigh bouring countries to scatter if they cannot withstand him and to save themselves by mingling with Arabs of Kuwait and f Iraq. Paragraphs 4, 5 and 6 of my letter October 16th (vide my despatch No. 268)call he says for special attention. As to paragraph 4 he has not the least desire cross frontiers of ’Iraq and Kuwait, and requested permission do this as a precaution only to be acted upon when absolutely necessary, and in event of forces in Kuwait and ’Iraq being unable prevent insurgents from taking refuge there when pursued by him . tfhat does H.M’s Government expect him to do in such event? Is he to withdraw and leave mutineers safe in Kuwait territory free to create fresh trouble. As to paragra' ph 5. It is obvious that the intention to scatter among Arabs of Kuwait, and Mesopotamia when hard pressed is not known to British Government. As regards hope expressed in this paragraph he wishes that British Government would Have explained how he is to prevent rebels entering Kuwait and Mesopotamia terri tory when Government Kuwait has not prevented them, and they are still watering their animals within refugo of Kuwait territory, he himself being debarred from competing. The position as British Government must realize is difficult for him. As he has actually moved off and expects in a few J -adays to establish contact insurgents, and. as in desert warfare it is essential to seize first opportunity of attack, he suggests the following:- (a) That Kuwait Government should order their subjects to collect in an appointed localXity far from any likely scene of action and should cover them with an armed force* He should be informed of locality chosen* An adequate force should then be placed by Kuwait Government on frontier to repel rebels - he does n ot hink air force alone would suffice* British Government officials should be with two forces (presumably Bin Baud’s and Kuwait frontier force), frontier should push back insurgents as far as possible even operateing within Nejd itself* Any rebel who may succeed crossing frontier should be arrested and handed over. In this event he says there would be no need for him to cross it hiihseff • (b) If all this is impossible he suggests that subjects of Kuwait should be concentrated as in (a), that he should then be left free to pursue rebels anywhere. In this case he undertakes to protect subjects neighbouring countries from any aggression. He also promises not to leave a single soldier in those countries a moment after pursuit insurgents is over. Thus the rebels will be annihilated. This is in his opinion only way to deal with problem and exterminate mutineers. After all his efforts, trbuble and expense it will be impossible return without completely crushing them. * If British Government does not agree either suggestion the consequences will be regretable. He grieves for suffering which he is inflicting on part his subjects 9 and on their women and children when events originally obliged him to punish them owing fact that they had violated assurance (given by him to British Government) by attacking ’Iraq and Kuwait subjects. It was incumbent him to punish them most severely in order safeguard his pledges. If neighbouring countries really wish cassist him in his efforts secure their safety, and that of their .■ _ • • «own subjects, be does not wish his action to result in . a clash between his forces (particularly as he is command ing them in person) and those of the British Gobemment; this is situation which he is trying avoid and which please God cannot occur. If immediately foregoing presumption is correct he would have to abandon not only punitive measures undertaken, but also a plan for ensuring inter nal security. He will not then be responsible for any aggression against neighbouring countries. He would then be justified before himself and world, for he will have fought against his own people for sake of neighbours who shelter their own deadly enemys and help these against himself. He is now setting forth. If either of his suggestions is met, well and good. If not he will to his regret be compelled adopt last mentioned attitude and declining all responsibility will take no further measures prevent attacks against neighbouring countries. The res ponsibility will then lie with those countries themselves. British Agent.'/£+) V' Telegram (M) # Irom - British Agent, Jeddah. To - Political, Kuwait. No # 229. Dated 27th received 28th November 1929. Addressed to Foreign 175 repeated Baghdad, Bushire, Kuwait 229. \ Your telegram No. 128. • I am now infoimed there is a strong pro Bin Saud movement inside Kuwait, that considerable funds have already expended there by King to foster it, and that main object Shaikh Hafez Kahba’s mission to Kuwait is to gauge and if occasiqn should arise to take charge movement. I would normally regard my source information as fairly reliable. Rumour referred to in my telegram 172 is so far as I can discover cutiosity amongst a few higher officials and persons in contact them. It is based I think on a knowledge of contents of Kingls letter to me reported in my immediately preceeding telegram f but it is possible also that there may have been some direct communication from King of which I am unaware. I do not ascribe rumour to Bedouin origin. In view new information now received I attach greater credence to it than it surmised origin alone might perhaps warrant. British Agent.(/cry Telegram (C). From - Highcoma, Baghdad. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Kuwait &amp; Colonies. No. 334. Dated and received 27th November 1929. URGENT. Addressed to Bushire 334 repeated to Kuwait 334 Secretary of State for Colonies 421. Kuwait’s 640 and 641. Air reconnaissance 26th November shows numerous herds of camels still watering Jahrah wells. Exact location of Duwish and following and his future intentions especially after threat of his followers to Shaikh’s guards still remains uncertain. In view of our promise to Ibn Saud that His Majesty’s Government will prevent Kuwait and Iraq being used as refuge by rebels and that Military authorities will if necessary take drastic action to achieve their object Air Officer Commanding proposes two armoured car sactions with Special Service Officer and wireless communication proceed J(ahrah) as soon as possible from Basrah to deny J(ahrah) wells to rebels. Air reconnaissance will be carried out as required. He also suggests (i) D(uwish) might be warned that Air action will be taken unless his followers are removed altogether from Kuwait territory by 2nd December. (ii) In view of the difficulties of identifying the tribes from the air Shaikh be asked removal of all non rebel tribes North of J(ahrah) forthwith. (iii) That Shaikh be requested to send represent ative to join the armoured cars at J(ahrah). Please let me know as soon as possible whether you concur. High Commissioner for ’IraqTelegram (M) • Prom - High coma, Baghdad* To - Resident, Bushire, Repeated to Political, Kuwait and Colonies* No* 95-Sv Dated and received 27th November 1929. URGMT Addressed Bushire 95-S repeated Kuwait same number Secretary of State for the Colonies 422* My immediately proceeding telegram 334. I see no objection ate officer commanding*s proposal from f Iraq point of view* I understand that his object la not only to expel Dawish but also to be prepared for possible incursion by Bin Saud into Kuwait in violation article 6 of Anglo-Nejd treaty May 1927* See Jeddah telegcs m 326. ~ J Highccxna*Immediate Telegran.M From Political Kuwait To Resident Buehire. No,655• Dated 2?/l l/29» Baghdad's :ro.33 2 *'. and 95 S. Sincerely trust you will take no action till you recleve my comments which will reach you in morning. Political 655r ,r / Telegram (M) # From - High coma, Baghdad. To - Political, Kuwait. . No. 96—S. Dated 28th received 29th November 1929. IMPORTANT . Secretary of State for the Colonies 425 repeated Bushire, Kuwait, Jeddah 96-S. Reference Bushire telegram 1200 (71 to you) which was presumably sent before he had seen Jeddah wire 228. Air Officer Commanding now considers it essential to send two armoured car^ sections into Kuwait forth with. In view serious situation which would arise in ’Iraq if Bin Saud were for any reason occupy Kuwait I fully concur that such steps as Air Officer Command ing considers necessary preclude all possibility of this happening should be taken and support his proposal. Please reply urgently. Highcoma.\\Sv Immediate. Telegram M. From Political Kuwait, To Resident Bushire. No.656 Dated28/11/29. I visited Sheikh last night and showed hin-^ Baghdad * s No.33^ and 95S. Sheikh requested that following he sent you immediately^ Begins While thanking HighComa and Air Cffleer Commanding for so promptly wishing to assist him expel some rebel camels watering, when he asked for help, he now no longer requires assistance in shape of armoured cars at Jahra, as necessity for such has ceased to exist, and Duwlsh and all his people have definitely left frontier and are rapidly moving south. As regards camels seen by aeroplanes, these part of his own and Kuwait’s 20,000 animals which now all drinking at Jahra. As regards A.O.C’s other sugesstions there appears no necessity answer them as every thing now normal again. As regards threat from Bln Baud, at present such possibility very remote and certainly does not Justify immediate counter measures. Should threat materialize he will not only ask for but gratefully accept fullest assistance, ends. In view of my clearly worded telegrams Nos. 641,643,644 and 651 and 652 all which were repeated Baghdad, it is not clear how situation has been so misunderstood. I therefore strongly support Sheikhs request that armoured cars asked for and later countermanded be now definitely cancelled, and that no air reconnaissances beyond two asked for be sent. Political 656Telegram K.R Immediat e. From Political Kuwait, To Resident Eushire. No.657 Dated 28/11/29. Personal . A.O. C*s anxiety establish strong post of armoured cars in heart Kuwait, presumably for indefinite period is I fear cloak to getS.S.O. back here. Since Sheikh strongly objects proposal, and Akhwan have entirely dissapeared and. must now be nearing Hafar, I trust you will have no difficulty in quashing suggestion. Cannot Aviation be asked fly Officer dovm to consult me when in doubt, I am only 4 hours from Baghdad, and only too ready always help by placing my local knowledge their disposal. Political 657\v£ (rn) From Political, K\jy/ait, To Resident, Bush ire, No* 658. Dated the 28th Uovember 1929. PERSONAL. Did Colonel Barrett show you his Demi-Official No. 416-S., of 9th September and my Demi-Official No. 553 with enclosures before he left? Political 658. Telegram (C.) iTelegram (C). From • Political, Kuwait. To i Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 659. Dated 28th November 1929. Llan who left Duwish’s camp yesterday reports latter changed plans now proceeding with all Mutair and Ajman to Jariya and Safa, Hafar idea abandoned. Duwish himself in Garaa South West of Thallat Ramadi watering camels today Wafra. Addressed to Resident repeated to Baghdad. K|t 652. Political. JTelegram (II) • ffrom - Resident, Bushire. Tom - Political, Kuwait. No. 1200. Dated 28th November 1929. Addressed Baghdad repeated Colonial Office and Kuwait. Your telegrams 334 and 95—S (421 and 22 to Secretary of State)• Xn view Kuwait’s telegram 643 situation does not appear to be serious at present and I have every hope Political Agent will be able deal with it. Please defer action proposed till I have received further reports. Resident. . _ . 1il Telegram (M) . ^rom - Resident, Bushire* To - Political, Kuwait. No. 1204. Dated 28th November 1929. My telegram 1200. Do you think you will be able get rid of ^Uchwan camels? I am anxious to avoid calling in Royal Air Force if possible, but it will be difficult do so unless camels depart soon. Resident.Telegram (C) # % From - Political, Kuwait* To - Resident, Bushire* No. 661. Dated 29th November 1929. URGENT. Tour 1204. Please see first paragraph my 644 of 25th also my No. 657 and 659 # of 28th November. Shaikh’s protest to Duwish mentioned in first telegram which was sent at my suggestion had desired effect entirely. Only very few Akhwan camels drank on 26th. They ceased coming entirely on 27th and 28th all having followed Duwish on his move south. To make absolutely certain I visited all wells at Jahrah yesterday and examined personally the 2000 odd Kuwait camels which watered before and after sunset and did not come away were found, for your informawu till after dark. No ttfc Akhwan camels/w^fch^fer^ Jahrah ever came from people camped inside Kuwait territory. And those which came were attended by about 5 men only to every 100 camels. Political.Telegram (R) # From - British Agent, Jeddah* To - Political, Kuwait* No. 231. Dated 28th received 29th November 1929. * Addressed to Foreign Office telegram No. 177, Bushire, Kuwait telegram No. 231. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs tells me according reports published in Cairo press originating from press agency in Kuwait, Shaikh Kuwait has stated to His Majesty’s Political Agent that he does not regard himself as bound by any treaty obligations such as need prevent rebels from obtaining supplies from Kuwait. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs is loth to believe this statement, and if untrue would like denial circulated by local press agent. Telegram 077 of the 28th. Agent.Telegram (M) ♦ From - Resident, Bushire. To - Political, Kuwait. No. 1215. Dated and received 29th November 1929. Addressed Baghdad repeated Secretary of State for the Colonies 76 Kuwait your telegram No. 76-S. You will since have received my telegram No. 1206 (73 to Colonial Office) and in view facts therein stated no action would seem to be necessary at present. Resident.//?) Telegram (C) # From - Resident! Bushire# To - Political, Kuwait# No# 1203# Dated and received 28th November 1929# Following from Secretary of State for Colonies reference correspondence ending with your 607 2nd November begins# Your telegram dated 4th November 60 proposed reply to Ibn Saud# If word 'Afghan' in (i) should read 'Akhwan' I see no objection to course proposed, but if 'Afghan' is correct Political Agent should make no statement regarding Afghan out situation with/first submitting its terms to His Majesty’s Grovemment for approval as his info mat ion on the subject may well be out of date and his letter might be misleading# As regards (iii) it is undesirable that Political Agent should include in his letter anything more than passing reference to Dawish’s overtures and admission Awazim since British Agent at Jeddah has already been instructed to repcr t both incidents to Ibn Saud. In general it is undesirable that matter in which questions of policy are involved and on which British Agent at Jeddah has been instructed to communicate with the Hedjaz Government should be dealt with in personal corres ondence between Dickson and Ibn Saud which should remain of (ZOXEM) Mature. Complete absence of any mention of of these incidents might however arouse suspicion; but Dickson should \ say no more than that Ibn Saud will have learnt of them from British Agent at Jwddah. Subject to these comments I see no objection to proposed reply Ends# First paragraph of proposed reply should therefore be omitted. I have notified Ibn Saud on the assumption of office but no objection to your mentioning it third paragraph should be amended in accordance with the Se- cf State for Colonies instructions# Forth paragraph i J i ResidentTelegram (R) # From - Resident, Bushire# To - Political, Kuwait. No. 1206. Dated 28th received 29th November 1929. t PERSONAL. Your telegram No. 657.- fully sympathize with your desire not to have Special Service Officers back, but he seems inevitable accompaniment of any Air Force action. » I have telegraphed Shaikh r s message and cancelled armoured cars but have made no reference to further air reconnaissance as such seems hardly necessary. Resident.Telegram (M). From - Resident, Bushire, To - Political, Kuwait* No* 1211. * Dated and received 29th November 1929. Addressed Secretary of State for Colonies 74 repeated Jeddah, Kuwait 1211* My telegram No. 70 (1198 to Jeddah) November 27th. In view Shaikhls statement contained first paragraph Jeddah telegram 175 to Foreign Office I trust it will be possible make suitable representations regarding continued presence of Hafiz Wabha in Kuwait. Resident.Telegram C. From - Resident, Bushire. To - Political, Kuwait. No. 1213. Dated and received 29th November 1929. Your 660. If important telegraph gist Resident.m Telegram (C) # From - Political, Kuwait# To - Resident, Bushire# No# 662. Dated 29th November 1929. x N?T-v .S' Reference my No# 650 of 26th November. Have received fetter from Bin Baud today dated 13th November informing me that he was on that date leaving for Hafar al Atz to start operations against rebels; that he had sent Hafith Wahba to Kuwait to keep touch with Shaikh and myself and act as his intermediary in any . conversation. Political. y ( •— —*C ONTIDEITTIAL ILS^DIATE No. 663 From Political Agent,'-Balrrain, To H.E. Sheikh Ahmed al-Jahir as-Subah, CSI., CIE., Ruler of Kuwait. Dated the 29th November 1929 After Compliments, I have the honour to inform your Excellency that the aeroplanes which came over Jaharah yesterday also visited Umm Russ, Umm Anarat al-Shaqq., Umm Amarat Mahyne and then returned‘to Shaibah after landing at A3ATA and leaving Captain Howes with the Dhafir. The latter is said to be leaving a^in to-day. The aeroplanes say they saw among other things, many between Ash-Shaq.q and Umm Amarah, also a large collection of the first of these consist of Kuwait sheep tribes, and the second are the Kuwait 'hathar' tribes camped with your Excellency’s fiddwiyyeh which I saw myself last Sunday. In people really are, lest they form wrong conclusions about them, especially the first lot, I should be highly grateful if your Excellency could confirm what I say, and give me any | I should be highly obliged for a reply to-day, so that I can wire Baghdad. . Usual Ending. scattered tents, with camels and sheep grazing in the area 170jtents ten miles east of Abraj al-Fabari. I presume that other information that may be useful in this respect ik Lt. Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait.COEPIDMTIAL. II.2JCDIATS. From Politi cal Agent, Kuwait, To H.E. Sheikh Ahmed al-Jabir as-Subahm CSI., CIE., Ruler of Kuwait, Dated the 29th November 1929. After Compliments, ’ I h^ve pleasure in informing your Excellency that the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, has asked the Air Officer Commanding to cancel his proposed plan of sending eight armoured cars ^2 sections) a wireless set, and an Intelligence Officer to Jaharah as 7 /as contemplat ed, seeing that your Excellency’s v/ise and strongly worded message to Duwish of the 25th November had the prompt and desired effect of getting him to move the Akhwan^ away from the Kuwait frontier and withdraw those of his camels which had attempted to drink at Jaharah, Tawil and Subaihiyah against the express wishes of His Majesty’s Government and your Excellency’s orders issued in this connection. Usual ending. kT Lt. Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait.f r s % Telegram (c.) From Political, IZuwai t, To Aviation, Baghdad, Repeated Resident, Bushire. No. 666 • Dated the 29th November 1929 My 666. Received report air reconnaissance of 23th only® Addressed Aviation repeated Bushire. Political 666.Telegram R ytf f^) Prom Political Kuwait To Resident Bushire No.668 Dated 29/11/29. Jeddah^ No. 231. Story is an invention from start to finish. We have no press Agency here. Report obviously emanates from Hafith Wahba, and shows type propaganda campaign which Sheikh may expect for future. Political rTelegram R Immediate From Political Kuwait To Resident Sushire: No.669 Dated 29/11/29. Baghdad's telegram No.96 S. Fear I am unable understand arguments put forward• From all sources Sheikh*s information, which hithertoo been extremely good, nearest Bln Sauds proved concentrations apart from insignificant force near Artawlyeh, are at Aglbba and at Hafar Atz, each over 200 miles from Kuwait frontier across parched desert in which no rain has fallen this year. Whole rebel force which is greatly superior to anything Bin Saud can put in the field intervene, and are about to occupy line Jarriya, Wabra and Safar 90 miles from Kuwait frontier. Rebels are further contemplating sueing for peace, as such course now to their advantage. Should Bln Saud however foolishly drive them to extremes by imposing Impossible demands, which I do not for moment anti cipate, I have no doubt Bin Saud will go under if he risks pitched battle. It does not appear to have been appreciated that Bin Saud with his usual cleverness is trying to win his war by letter writing. No other interpretation can be put on wonderful statements and demands made in Jeddah*s 228, Acid test is that Sheikh of Kuwait fears nothing from Bin Saud at present though he certainly believes that in event Duwish*s submission latter will later be ordered to attack Kuwait unoflclally to prove his sincerity. This Duwish has already said he will be no party to, vide my telegram 644 of 25th November.Telegram M Immediate From Secry. of State for the Colonies, London, To Zusacari Kuwait. * No. 130 Dated 29/11/ reed 30/11/29. % Your telegram No.73 of November 28th, and Jeddah Telegrams No. 174- and 175 of November 27th to Foreign Office. In view of Importance give Bin Saud no Justification or excuse attempt invade Kuwait territory, or of allowing his tribes to resume raiding, Kie Majestys Cxovernment consider it essential that every possible measure should be taken to implicate more fully and effectively the pledges already given to Bin Saud, and thus place His Majesty's G-overnment in a position satisfy him that this has been done. Rebels have had clear warning of consequences of crossing frontier, and methods of persuasion must now ssasAx give place to measures of compulsion. Further more all communication with Dawish and his associates must definitely cease. In these circumstances, (1) Measures on general lines of those advocated in Baghdad telegrams No.421, and two of November 27th, and 425 of Nov.29th txymr*- should forthwith be taken. His M ajesty's Government attach particular Importance to removal of all Kuwait tribes and refugee Awazim from vicinity frontier or scene possible conflict. (2) You should immediately concert Air Officer Commanding Iraq necessary military measures for ejectment any of contending forces (whether those of rebels or of Bin Saud) that may enter Kuwait territory. Every effort should moreover be made to intercept isolated2 . / s isolated groups of rebels entering Kuwait for the purpose of mergeing with Kuwait tribes in manner suggested by Bin Baud, ( see Jeddah telegram 174 ) and secure their immediate ejection from Kuwait. Political Agent should at once approach Sheikh Kuwait to secure his concurrence and co-operation in these measures, which in considered opinion of His Majesty's Government are essential. Addressed Bushire, repeated Baghdad 376 Kuwait and Jeddah 130 SECER. /&gt;Telegram (C) # From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. No. 670. Dated 29th November 1929. Shaikh has receiver' friendly letter from Bin Saud via Bahrain dated Riath 13th November thanking him for his last letter and saying he proceeding Hafar Atz shortly Adds that Hafidh Wahba will act as Liaison officer to prevent misunderstanding. He trusts his dear brother will afford him wwery welcome. Political.Telegram (C.) From Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bush ire, Repeated Highcoma, Baghdad, No. 671. Dated the 30th November 1929 . IMPORTANT&lt; Have received second letter from Bin Sa T ud dated Riyadh 18th November informing me he leaving that day at head his forces. Similar letter sent to Sheikh. It will be noted that in previous letter Bin Sa T ud gave 13th November as date departure. Bin Sa T ud added that he had received accurate information that rebels were still camped in Kuwait territory^ and as this was against promise made by His Majesty’s Government he trusted I would have them ejected at once, so that no difficulty would arise wl 1 h Ruler of Kuwait or His Majesty’s Government result which could only be evil. My comments. Statement of course is incorrect and probably another instance Hafidh Wahba’s mischief making here • Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad. Poli ti cal 671; Telegram (B). From - British Agent, Jeddah* To - Political, Kuwait* No* 255* Dated and received 30th November 1929. Addressed to Foreign Office rapaatMt telegram No. 180 repeated to Baghdad, Bushire Kuwait No. 235. IXy telegram No. 175. I am info mod Fhilby telegra phed Daily Herald yesterday stating there is trouble on Kuroit frontier and that there is likely to be a clash between Bin Baud forces and those of Kuwait 100. Telegram No. 080 of 29th* British Agent. •!Telegram (C) . v • From - Political, Kuwait* # To - Resident, Bushire* • • No* 672. Dated 30th November 1929. In reply to communication sent by Shaikh to Bin • • Saud two months ago offering co-operation with all his forces in event rebels being driven on to frontier. Latter has sent confused reply dated Riath 18 November which Shaikh interprets to be one long threat against himself, gist being, that however much Shaikh may try and • * • please, Najd tribes are so angry that he Bin Saud will be unable to prevent them attacking Kuwait. Though there is no danger this happening at present. Shaikh has no doubt whatever that as soon as Akhwan problem is dealt with Bin Saud will start his old game and order his tribes to attack Kuwait, himself denying all knowledge to His Majesty’s Government. Shaikh gives it as his considered only opinion that x±jt satisfactory way stop Bin Saud will be to present him with ultimatum*threatening war on first act aggression, otherwise bjt attempting defend frontier by Air Force while at same time holding conversations, will only play into Bin Sand’s hands. Shaikh adds Bin Sand’s goings on are so strange today that he fears for his sanity. \ PoliticalTelegram (C)• From - Polltloal, Kuwait# To - Resident, Bushire# Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad# No. 673. Dated 1st December 1929# D-IME DIATS. Tour 1216. . If flying boat could be arranged Shaikh would very much like accompany me Basrah for conference pro vided you have no objection. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. Political. Telegram (0). From - Aviation, Baghdad. To - Political, Kuwait. Repeated to Resident, Bushire. No. A/509. Dated 1st received 2nd December 1929. BI MEDIilTB . With reference to No.673 1st December from the h Political Agent, Kuwait suggest Shaikh sbuld not be A present at the conference which will include matter of policy of His Majesty’s Government and ’Iraq. Further, Dickson is aware of Shaikh's views. Suggest Dickson proceed Basrah 2nd December if possible allow conference to start morning of 3rd December as weather forecasts are ( mutilation) • I have instructed boat squadron to (? stand by) for request from the Political Agent Kuwait if he requires to be flown to Basrah. Addressed to Kuwait repeated to Bushire. Aviation.Telegram A.D.2. Immediate, From Aviation Baghdad* To Political Kuwait No. Z.155 Dated t/11/ reed 2/11/29. The following reconnaissances are to be carried out Dec.2nd. (1) Jahrah- Umm Rue - Subaihiya, thence Ash Shaqq - Umm Amarat West, thence to encampment reported in last reconnaissance east Abraz al Hubari, thence Umm Ruwaisat* \ Report on encampment, types of herds and flocks and any surface water from recent rains. (2) Down the Batin to eastern Neutral area, thence to wells in neighbourhood Al Amariya - Al Uqubba - Samah, return ing via Al Abtiya and home along west of Batin. If you see Police cars in neighbourhood Al Tlya drop any information regarding location of encampment and flocks seen. Air craft will be armed. No action is to be taken unless fired on. Reconnaissance No.1 is more important, and most experienced Officers will go with this flight, dnform (Jlubb. Addressed Aerofour, repeated Special Basrah, careserve. Political Kuwait. AviationTelegramM To Resident Bushire From Political Kuwait. No.674 Dated 2/11/29. Personal . Baghdads 97 S. Should AC.C. suceed bring off H fait acompli” at Jahara which would be great pity and upset Sheikh very much. I anticipate latter will raise strong objection to second suggestion mentioned in HighConm^s No.334 of 27th Nov. as such course would seriously threaten Kuwait*s economic life, the inhabitants of the town, neighbouring villages, and tribes all being dependent on each other for milk rice, meat ,vegetables, firewood. Please see Bushires No.409 S. of 7th September to HighComa, and Kuwalts 552 of 27th Sept, to Bushire on similar occasion when R.A.F. tried take control out of Politicals Hands Political 674Telegram A.D.2 Immediate Prom Aviation Baghdad To Political Kuwait No.Z.156 Dated i/ll/ reed 2/11/29. With reference to cay telegram A.400 of November 30th. Two sections to proceed to Jahrah morning December 2nd. Establish wireless telegraphy communication there, and form defensive camp wherein you will await further instructions. Seven days rations will be taken. Howes will not accompany. Acknowledge and inform G-lubb, Addressed Careserve, repeated Special Basrah, Areofour, Political Kuwait. AviationTelegram M From Resident Bushire ( on Patrick Stewart ) To Political Kuwait No # T.2 Dated 1/11/ reed 2/11/29 # Armoured care are proceeding Jahara December 2nd ae a precautionary measure• Air force will fly you up , please arrange direct. Sheikh* s presence would seem hardly necessary unless you see special reason for it . I arrive Basrah 2nd evening* should like preliminary discussion that evening or early 3rd. Resident.s HIS Majesty’s^^*^ CsC&gt;C&lt;£+ presents his compliments to &lt;_^£ oS) (n^c^Y and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. y /■$■ //• tr-f 7 /, yf^Cs. 'UsCc^*. 3479 » 94 o 8 6/29 ( 2 )Telegram From To Repeated [zni ''QilQ, &gt; x Political Resident, Bushlre. Secretary of State for the Colonies, liondon, No* 69 Government of India, New Delhi,) No* 1194* B/ritieh Agent, Jeddah, ) Copy to High Commissioner, Baghdad, toy air mall of 27th November. Dated 26th November 1929* Following summarises reports from Kuwait* Shaikh has addressed protest to Dawish regarding presence of Akhftan camels in his territory* Dawish has replied admitting that protest was justified out states that he is moving South immediately to line H&amp;far, Safa, Jarriya-es-:&gt;ifla* &gt;&lt;* * ) . p v Ihn Shuqair has informod Dawish he has been authorised to act as intermediary. Dawish has replied saying he will submit with whole force on follow- -ing conditions (1) that he be free to purchase supplies in any town he wished in Nojd, Kowl)et or ’Iraqi. (ii) that he be nou required to meet I ton Gaud, and (iii) that he toe allowed to lead Beaouin life in future and not ordered to reside in any town. Dawish states that in order to test his loyalty he knew that Ibn 3aud would order him to attack Koweit , but under no circumstances would he agree, and in order to strengthen his hands in coming negotiations he had ordered raids to the South to toe commenced at once. political Kuwait has carried out personal reconnaissance on Southern border of Kuwait and reports no Aktevan camps inside border though a few of their camels making for Jahrah water. Air reconnaissance is being carried out today and armoured cars standing by to proceed if required Addressed H.k's. Secretary of Utate for the Colonies, London, repeated Government of India, New Delhi, and British Agent, Jeddah. Copy Baghdad by airmail of 27th. ~ rt-CONFIDENTIAL Tost copy for information to The Ganior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, J&amp;useat. By order, Capt•, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Drftgnt &amp; Confidential HO* »765. To 2- Soerotorlot of tho Council of Minlrtoro, i oirhd&amp;d, 12 th lioTCiator, 1929. The Aeting Counsellor to . . %)M i*Pi—I BBimm r r cr ’ :rao f BaRhdad• 1 . Koforonco your letter Ko. f.O/WC dated 4th ttoTenber, 1*29, regarding coaplainte aade by His Majesty King Ibn Sa'ud, 2, 1 rm directed to forward to you herewith copy - ^ of Hals of the Royal Diwan’s letter Vo. 2C7 dated 9/lOth October, 1929, containing the obeery&amp;tione of Hie 1 ajeety the King on these oo»plaints # The 3£ini»try of the Interior her replied stating that it has no knowledge of the chargee directed again Ft the *lrao hewernment. 3 , The •Irae Soreraaent agre* to all refugees in •Iraq from the rebel Akhwan tribe# being prohibited entry into the desert area. 4, The Ministry of the interior hat already issued orders for the prevention of rebele obtaining provisions - from * Iraq end has adoptsd ths necsssary arrangement for | , preventing, as fsr as poselbls, supplies from reaching 'j them. (Sd) •Abdul padir Rashid, Secretary to the Council of ministers.3 A It 7 of H.M. mini, l*n tio’ud. U»fortunfc tfily, however, it ftpp«%ro that the aeoiotanee which hae been aicorded end continueft to be accorded by ’Iraq hae not proved sufficient to dispel these doubts. It in undeniable that certain individuals have actually gone cut from 'Iraq to Kuwait and the borders o; i»ajd with the aimple object of aocertainini; thr situation. Such individual* were in touch with the civil end military intellifence deportments. We do not think that t is action, which all notion* reaort to a* a measure of precaution, i* ouch a* c^lla for any Euoplcion «&gt;e to ( oodwill. Bia liajeety Ibn Sa'ud himnelf Itaa •’eyea*' (or sj ie-*) rci tiered throughout the varinun parts of •Iraq, against the pxeaenee of whom it h^o never occurred to us to complain, ao Ion* as they kept aloof from Interference with the internal affairs of the country and avoided indulgence in intripue and evil activities, hotwitiiwtnridin^ the feregsir^, Ms* Majesty can see no objection The * Iraq Government have »o far adopted with the utmoet cautiouenes* a policy of strict non-interference with the affaire of hajd, and they had been and continue to be anxious to adhere to (or observe strictly) the tre tie* concluded between them and Kajd and to respect them to the utmost possible extent. It would appear to u» that the ♦Iraq has pursued thi* course and its desire for peace and amity with hejd further than is demanded by treaties, hvint, a® it has, promise# to expel the Dewiah from its teriitorie* in the event of his se^kin* refuge therein, and adopted stringent mo^sures in the restriction of 'Tnusabals* (trade in provisions) with the rebel triber of hajd notwithstanding the resultant harm to the country** trade, and has also, on numerous occ^ciono, deaonstrateii e r asonabiy perfect attitude of neutrality. These effective demonstrations should have left no place for doubt and suspicion in the mindobjection to an aoaurance toeing; *.iven that the • Irac Government &lt;io not countenance ^ctivitiee ruoh flop** conpletined o: by K # M # Ibn 3n*u£ an&lt;3 that they will not heeltate to take etepe to prevent, ee far ae poeeible, activitiee on the part of certain individuala who fco out to seek intercourse with the rebel Akhwan tribee with the object of inati* atin ; dieafection. There i» also no objection, in Hie Majesty* m opinion, to a renewal of the underteiiii; previously ^ iven by the • Iraq Government regarding the expulsion of the Dawiah in the event of hie seeking refuse in ’ Iracj territory. Ae regards the queation of preventiai the supply of provijione, thia mvolvee great h^na to Hh# trade of *irao. it alao appeare to Ilia Majesty that the control of the supply of provisions ia attended by great difficulty, o specially when we reali e the faot that tribes h?ive nowbecoi/iu split, iiito nuraerous sections of whom it's difficult to know which are loyal to Ibn Oa^ub and which are againet hira. In any caee. Hie ttajeety woul like to leave this and other points for decision by fl.a. the Prime Minister* In the meantime he would invite hio attention to th* treatment whicy* i« bei. rcorded by h.t ? . King Ibn Sa'tai in H-ijC territory to #ei tain * Iraqi nhaikhe (tribal leaders} and in particular to tiie Shaikh of the Hbafir - » treatiaent w ich is inconsistent with the obligationa laid down in the iialira reameut • and alao to the utterances which Ibn Sa’ud hae no unecrupulously rmdc even to certain chiefs of 1 Iraqi tribes during their visit (or pilgrimage) to the liija* • utterances which do not evince that mutual respect el ri*&gt;te and obligations which ia called for by the relations existing between the two pnrtioa.[Hi61/1 4 'i Telegram From To Repeated P. Political Pepident, Bushire. High CommiPBioner, Baghdad, No. 1?06. ♦Secretary of State for the CoJonjee, No. 73. Dateo 2fc&gt;th November 19P9. Reference my telegnui No. 1P00 (71 to Colonial Office). All Akhwan camels that were watering are now reported by Political Agert, Kuwait, to have left. Prltirh Agent Jeddah hap been informed of this. ^he Shaikh therefore, whiJe thanking High CommiRPioner and Air Officer Commanding for po promptly offer- -ing to expel rebelp* camels, no longer requiree appjptence. The camel p that were seen by the aeroplanes were hia own and Kuwait animals and these a.re now all drinking at JahraJa. The po hp ib.il ity of any threat from Bin Send appears remote and the Shaikh doef. not consider counter meastireR necessary at present, but should the threat mater- -ialise, he will not only ask for but gratefully accept fullest ciBHintance. In these circumstances ^xrpsfjc*fjw^joc the request for armoured cars may Ran be definitely cancelled as I now consiuer Fitu.at.ton normal. RPSmFNT. Post o py to the Political Agent, Kuwait, for iniormation. By order, Hi Capt., for Secretary to the Political ted. aent in the Persian Gulf• Bushire, 29th November 1929. # i61/18 Telegram Code ^ roin Political ^eaiaent, JJuahire For* Political Department, 24ew Dollii Bo*lS05 Dated 28th November i929 Your letter ho*F.375-h/29 of November bth. i will submit my views after discussion with 8heiiOi ana Political Agent on December 5th* • R^SIDiShT - #** Post copy to the Political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to his telegram Ho,tty , dated 27th November 192‘ 9. By order, CJapt. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 29th November 1929.TRANSLATION'OF A LETTIR. From - H.E. SheiLh Ahmed al-Jabir as-Subah, CSI., CIE., Ruler of KuvTait, To - The Political Agent, Kuwait, 27th Dated the 22x^. Jamadi-II, 1348 (29th Novaiber 1929). After Compliments, I have pleasure to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 663 of to-day’s date, and I have noted your statement re the aeroplanes which arrived at Jahrah yesterday. I thank you cordially for this information. * As regards the tents with the camels and sheep which the aeroplanes saw between the Shaq and Um Amarah, and the big party which was estimated to be of 170 tents at 10 miles east of Abraq. al-Fubari and which your Excellency presume I to be from the Kuwait tribes, we beg to infonn your Excel lency that Bedouins have no specified place, but always they j wander in the places where pastures for their animals to graze are available and therefore we are not sure whether they are Kuwait tribes. We have now ordered for the necessary enquiries to be done, and shall let your Excellency know the fact to-morrow morning. Usual Ending.E 5566/2322/91 NO Code telegram to Mr.Bond (Jeddah). Foreign Office 30th October,1929 3.10 p.au No.113 (R). Bushire telegrams Nos.46 and 47 to the Colonial Office of October 16 repeated to you. (Defeat of Awazlm by Faisal ed Dawish). To foi*Btall possible protest, please inform nejazi Government that in the circumstances described his Majesty's Government have acquiesced in decision of Sheikh of Koweit to allow the remnant of the Awazim tribe to take refuge in Koweiti territory. You may explain should this be necessary that Awazim, having surrendered to Feisal ed Dawish, can no longer be regarded as part of Ibn baud's forces, but that they equally cannot be regarded as insurgents,so that present attitude sf his Majesty's Government is not inconsistent either with their decision not to allow Ibn baud's forces to cross frontier, or with their undertaking not to allow the rebels to find refuge in Koweit. CONFIDENTIAL. No. u &gt;- -3. of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-Ceneral, Bushire, 30th November 1929. Dopy forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. By order, * Capt., for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.Telegram From To Secretary of ^tate for Colonies, London British Agent/Jeddah No.134 Repeated Political Resident, Bushire Political AgentKuwait Political Agent, Bahrein High Commissioner, Baghdad. Dated and received the 1st Lecemher 19291 Following is message referred to in my immediately proceeding telegram. His Majesty’s Government have learnt of contents of Your Majesty’s letter of November 17th to the British Agent at Jeddah with regret. They have never failed in undertakings which they have repeatedly given to Your Majesty to use all means in their power to prevent improper use of Kuwait and ’Iraq, territory hy Your Majesty’s rebellious subjects. Efforts which latter have made to take re fuge in Kuwait territory have indeed already been frustrated more than once and on Septem er 3rd Your Majesty’s Government recognised the sincerity and the efficiency with which the British authorities in Kuwait had carried out their undertakings by formally thanking them for their efforts. As Your Majesty is aware th^ His Majesty’s N Government were approached as recently as November 1st by Sheikh Faisal-ed-Dawish with requests for guarantees for his women and children. They are credibly informed that overtures for peace which Faisal Dawish is reporte^t- recently to have addressed Your Majesty were princi pally due to tht3 uncompromising attitude which His Majesty’s Government have taken up in reply to these requests. His Majesty’s Government have moreover given material proDf of their earnest desire to co— U ‘ ax) oo-operate with Your Majesty in suppression of rebellion in North east Nejd hy assisting Your Majesty to obtain from India arms which you urgently required and by arranging to supply in neal? future on specially favourable terms four aeroplanes of latest type with necessary BI2I British personnel. Further supplies for use with these aeroplanes are already on the way out to the Persian Gulf and should reach Darin early in December. His Majesty’s Government feel certain thatjthese explanations will dispel any misunderstand ing as to their attitude. Careful enquiries have convinced His Majesty’s Government that Your Majesty must have been misinformed as to assistance which the rebels have obtained from Kuwait and ’Iraq. His Majesty’s Government desire in this connection to place Your Majesty on your guard against accepting reports from untrust^^and unreliable sources. Turning now to specific requests contained in Your Majesty^ oommuniOation His Majesty•» Government in addition to strictjnstructions already given to their authorities in Kuwait and 'Iraq, of the nature of which Your Majesty has been informed.have taken following action. In their desire to meet Your Majesty’s wishes as far as possible and to show their readiness to co-operate whole heartediy with Your Majesty in re establishing peace and order in your dominions (i) they have now issued renewed instruc tions which should ensure that pledges already given to Your Majesty shall be fully implemented, (ii) Instructions have been given to secure the removal of all Kuwait tribes and of refugee Awazim from the vicinity of the frontier or from any soene^possible conflict, (iii) Instructions have been given con cerning necessary military measure-s for ejection of F3 © ^ or f iraq. territory and to intercept wherever possible isdated groups of rebels entering such territory for purpose of merging with the local 4 A* tri ;es in the^manner^ which Your Majesty suggests. With regwrd to communication addressed by Your Majesty^ Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs to the British Agent Jeddah suggesting that rebels may attempt to escape into Transjordanian territory in structions on similar lines have now been sent to the High Commissioner for Transjordfcnia which should effectively guard against tbfe danger. Your Majesty will seefrom the foregoing that His Majesty’s Government have gone to the furthest possible limit in their endeavour to co operate Your Majesty on the lines suggested by you? They regret ^however that they cannot in any cir cumstances modify their decision against allowing Your Majesty’s armed forces to enter Kuwait, ’Iraq aradt or Transjordgni am territory. Apart from the risk, of which Your Majesty has already been informed by the British Agent, Jeddah^that such forces might be mistaken for rebels, instructions issued to British local author! ties for ejection of any of the contending forces that may cross the frontier would inevitably result in your forces coming into conflict with those of His Britannic Majesty, a contingency which His Maj esty’s Govern ent and Your Majesty would equally depl&gt;re. In conclusion His Majesty’s Government would again point out that the task of their Military Authorities would be rendered less difficult if Your Majesty could designate an emi sary from Your Military forces to keop the local frontier authorities at Kuwait informed of the movements of Your Majesty’s troops o ri/l r\ -f* + a y* cs'H a 1 aTelegram M From Hlghcouia. Baghdad. To Political Kuwait. No. 97 S. Dated 1/13/29. Addressed Bushire, repeated Kuwait 97 S. See Secretary of State for the Colonies 429. Your telegram No.1216. I have asked Air Officer Commanding to reply direct. He tells me he is recommending that armoured cars should proceed forthwith to Jahra. HighcomaTelegram (R). From - British Agent, Jeddah. To - Political, Kuwait. No.236. Dated 1st Received 2nd December 1929, Addressed Baghdad repeated Bushire, Kuwait, telegram No. 236. Following is repetition my telegram No. 173 to Foreign Office repeated Jerusalem under 227 begins. Following is gist note just received from acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. In spite of optimism expressed in my note Sep tember 27th vide my despatch No. 251 it has been reported to him that tribes of Tremsjordania are making expeditions on large scale within Nejd boundaries along a line from Jade Sirhan to Red Sea. Several attacks have taken place involving inclaculable loss to life and property. Amongst these is raiding carried out by Transjordanian Arabs against Shararat nearest Jaul.^u3aAt*eirtfi and another against a caravan which had been left Maan Misheitiya and Halaj nearest Tewa seven men car were taken prisoners, one killed whole caravan looted. Several other attacks in force by Transjordanian raids have taken place near Tewa and much property captured including sheep and cattle Government and of Smir T. himself. A- Strong measures are required to fctop this and Hedjaz Government hope that His Majesty’s Government will co-operate usual protest follows. 3nds. BritagentTelegram (R). From - Britagent, Jeddah. To - Political, Kuwait. No. *ii' 137 Dated 1st received 2nd December 1929. Addressed Baghdad repeated Bushire, Kuwait, ^&gt;23^ Following is repeiition my telegram No. 178 to Foreign Office repeated Jerusalem under 232 begins. My telegram No. 174. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs is informed Duwish if pressed may also attempt escape into TransJordann territory with active co-operation Transjordanian border tribes. « Nmir Neshmi has therefore been ordered transfer his force from Tebuk to Jauf to deal such an eventuality and also to control situation as described in my telegram no. 173. Fnds.Telegram (C) # From - Political, Kuwait, To - Resident, Patrick Stewart, Basraradio, Repeated to Aviation , Baghdad, No, 676, Dated 2nd December 1929, IMMEDIATE. that Kuwait tribes possessing about 20000 camels and xxd several hundred thousand sheep are all out grazing at present in particular large numbers are concentrated west and north west Jahrah and stretch as far as Batin, These are changing ground daily. Also that number of cars may be seen along whole southern border of Kuwait containing hunting parties of prominent Kuwait families who daily go long distances in search of gazelle and to hawk bustard which plentiful and forms chief spofct this season. Above information given to prevent any regretable incidents. Needless to say there are no rebels at all in Kuwait territory. Addressed Aviation repeated Resident Patrick Stewart, Your Z 155, Hope your various reconnaissance flights realize Political.Telegram (C) # Prom - Political, Kuwait. To - Aviation, Baghdad. Repeated to Resident, Patrick Stewart, Basraradio. No. 677. Dated 2nd December 1929. URGENT Request that copies of reports all reconnaissance flights over Kuwait territory be telegraphed me. I have so far only received copy of report of reconnaissance of 28th. Addressed Aviation repeated Resident Patrick Stewart. PoliticalTdlegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait, To - ^Resident, Cable Ship Partick Stewart, Basraradio. No, 675. Dated 2nd Denember 1929 IMPO RTANT Hafidh Wahba has flooded town with seme seventy letters from Bin Saud dated Riath 18th November addressed to all members of al-Subah family as well as to leading merchants of town. He has also circulated hand bills to less important persons. Letters contain defence of Bin Baud’s policy and urge recipients to persuade Shaikh not allow rebels enter his territory and advise him use his influence with H.M’s Government not to allow rebels’ escape into ’Iraq. Latter in particular he fears will happen in spite H.M’s Government’s assurances. Comments. It will be notified Bin Saud to us says rebels inside Kuwait to Shaikh something quite different. Shaikh becoming increasingly anxious activities Hafidh tfahba. Political.[1 Telegram R, Fro Becretfiiry of State for the Colonies To Zusacari Kuwait No. -? Dated 2/12/reed 3/12/29. Addressed to Jeddah Telegram No.136 repeated Kuwait Bushlre. Your telegram No.181. Yes, but my message to Bin Saud in my telegram No.13^ should on no account be delayed. —c Telegram M. Important * Prom Resident, P atricfc Stewert, To P olltlcal Kuwait• Ko # T*8, Pated 3/12/ reed*4/12/29* Addressed Secretary of State for the Colonies, repeated Jeddah, Kuwait, Government of India # Your telegram of Nov« 29th• (37^ to Baghdad } Two sections armoured cars proceeded Jahrah on 2nd, and several air reconnaissances have been carried out* At conference held today between Air Officer Commanding and myself, which was attended by Political Agent Kuwait following arrangements were decided upon* 1. Kuwait tribes should not proceed south of a line &lt; ^' r ~ ' ^ /VC fyXw ii mm Amarat — Mahazul to Umm Rus®'— 2. The sector east of a line from Kuwait to north west corner of neutral area is occupied by Kuwait shepherds, wood cutters etc. It was not considered practicable clear this area, on which economic life of Kuwait town largely depends. 3. Awazim have not yet entered Kuwait, but are at present camped in neutral area, and are drawing supplies from Kuwait. If they migrate into Kuwait they will be ordered north line referred to in 1. 4. Armoured cars will carry out reconnaissance to frontier on December 5th, accompanied by Political Agent Kuwait. 5. Periodical air reconnaissances will be carried out as required* Resident.I ftW' Telegram R* Important From Resident, Patrick Stewart, To P olitical Kuwait. No.T.9. Dated 5/12/ reed 4/12/29. My immediately proceeding telegram. b^+jsre. Please communicate measures thorofor&lt;^ been decided *.pon to Sheikh, and inform him That I trust he will agree to them. I greatly regret if any inconvenience is caused to him or his subjects, but*have every hope that it will be of short duration. Resident.CONTI , I . Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 4th December 1929 tS) No • (a From Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I. Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour, in continuation of my telegram No. 671 dated the 30th November 1929, to forward trans lation of H.M. the King of Nejd’s letter referred to. As already stated by me, the statement made by the King in the body of his letter about rebels being A- inside Kuwait territory is entirely incorrect. 2. I might mention that His Excellency the Shaikh also received a letter from Riath dated the same date as mine in which II.M. the King after many compliments, stated that as he was about to drive the rebels against Kuwait boundary, he trusted that His Excellency would co-operate with his forces assisted by those of H.M*s Government, and attack the rebels in rear when they arrived. Many other letters in similar strain have also been received by mambers of the Shaikh’s family and the notables of Kuwait. 3. I mention the above as H.LI. the King appears to have one type of letter for H.M’s Government’s officials and another for His Excellency the Shaikh and his people. The real meaning behind such tactics would appear to be the King’s desire to whip H.M’s Government into activity, and if possible by direct and indirect means 'panic' us into taking an active part in his war, and attack the rebels on his behalf. I feel certain the King does not feel strong enough to 'take on' Duwish single handed, but by an intensive propaganda of 'falsehoods' such as (a) the rebels having hidden themselves insideinside Kuwait territory or (b) ijMsxxEtiBjbB his being about to make an immediate attack on them, and his requiring iramedaite co-operation from us, or (c) that the rebels, are camped right inside our territory etc., he hopes to sting us into committing ourselves, and bombing the rebels. He knows that such.action would bring the rebels to their knees at once. 4. I might add that in my considered opinion Bin Baud has not yet left Riath (i.e. on 4th December 1929) and this is the opinion held by His Sxcellency the Shaikh of Kuwait and other 'sound' persons. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., tolitical Agent, Kuwait.Translation of a letter From - H.M.King Ibn Saud, Riath. To - The Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 27/147. Dated the 16th Jamad II, 1348 (18th November I wish to let you know that on this date we have moved from Riath at the head of the force which we ordered to assemble for movement to the remnants of the rebels in the neighbourhood of Kuwait, whom, God willing, we shall reach soon. Vie have no doubt that Your Excellency will assist ms against them as best as you can, because the interest of- will be associated. The real and true news which we receive about them every day show that they are still themselves safe, and this, as you know, is against the promise of the British Government. We, therefore, request Your Excellency to do your best to drive them out, so that their stay my not raise difficulties between us, Kuwait and the British Government and which may have evil results. Usual Ending.Telegram R From Secretary of State for Colonies* To Political Kuwait, No. 177 ? Dated 4/12/recd 5/12/29. Addressed to Jeddah Telegram No.139 of Dec 3rd. repeated to Bushire, Kuwait. Your telegram No.177* Report in Cairo press as to Sheikh Kuwait attitude toward Nejd rebels, and Bushire telegram No.83 to Colonial Office. Inform Please Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs that / report Sheikhs statement is pure invention, and that no press Agency exists in Kuwait from which it could have emanated. SECER. iOffice of the Political Bealuent in the Persian Gulf. I.G.T.3.'Patrick Stewart' t 5th December 1929. From The Hon'tole the Political Boaldent in the Persian Gulf. Sir, I have the honour to forward a oo.py of a letter from the Political Agent, Kuwait No.631, dated the 14th Noveaber 1929, and of its enclosure. I a^ree with Colonel Dickson that it is very desinble that the aeroplanes sold to I bn Saud should be narked so as to be easily distinguished from those of the Hoyal Air Force. done ana furnish ne with a description of tho disting uishing features. To The Air Officer Commanding, •Iraq Command, Will you kindly Inform mo if this has been I have the honour to be Sir Tour most obedient servant (Signed) H.V. Biscoe. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested For Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copt to The Political Agent, Kuwait The Political Agent, Bahrein,0 \h« f» on tier* of Ktja in ownr to te* euro that they •U1 sot *ro*s the frontlora again. »aooof&gt;ao&lt;t la oesa,,inf into the interior of Kovelt o* ir*Q» b# should ho arrontod sad hawf&lt;*d to tra. In this o«so tioro would he no need for oar Korea to arose the Kovait frontiar. snhjaats of Koaalt shoald ha onSarad to oollaot in a aartala local ity of whiou «a ■ y he iofomod. Then v a ah old ho ir»&lt;&gt; to not against the rebels nd to yaaaas the* vhorosor they a y he ■,i• e• into Koweit) and* in this oa.ee, o a»8er» toko to # rotoot all the subjects of tho aelr hoarln* o aatrioi and to .yreaent the;:, being ta*: objiot of any agfrosales, to furtiior a«lort.aio not to la-»o a single soldier in thoao oonntriad laaadlataly Oar uaraait of the arlniaala has mm to as sad. la afelah oaao the rebels will ho totally annlhll ted by the ftr&amp;ee nd Power of ood, this is in Our oisioa the only solution of the yrohlea sod the only way of o*terminating the rehole. 1% la isdeo t inposslhle for »a to retire fter the tronhle ' e hate t ken and tfte great or eases va hare inenrrad t ad t .# exteneire «fforts *« her* heforo o rush lag tho last r&lt;s*nant of the rehels hy the loner of Ood., If tho British Sorer.nent do not agree to eitnor of the . boro saggestlons to nil! he eery sorry for tho aita ties that any a ueuueatly .rise. Be wish to t&gt;oaur# tne Britiah Ooreraneat that it ia act easy for 3a to sue a section of Our subjects suiierlog tho bitterness of such innismoot at our If it ha.pettad that eay of the rebels great or if all this ia Ifltvosalble *e suggest that the ■ ^ n|U vC . ,v?-' v HIS Majesty’s ^ presents his compliments te^£ \ y and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British. ..62fyCM&lt;cfr. ..fljTM s3/?.: , 19-^. Reference to previous correspondence: (^o&amp;y 0^1- Ju. J2l£ cty •//• Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. csoCot* &lt;Pc*s) ^ ^ ° c/Z&gt;C%^Xo / '1 &lt;Z~/ c*&gt;^U Jl ^^I4rt****f ~&lt;s*- \s\XO . ' c p^ 4 7 j o^jtsLrc* Sot 1——</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/34</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/34</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File [10/4] British relations with Ibn Sa`ud: aid given to rebels by King Faisal; removal of Al Duwish from Kuwait territory</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-07T22:30:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (278 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 280; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-278; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to the British Government's relationship with Ibn Sa'ud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd].Specifically, the correspondence concerns the evacuation of the Ikhwan leader, Faisal al-Duwaish [Faysal al-Duwaysh] and his followers from Kuwait, King Faisal of Iraq's support for the Ikhwan, the delivery of British planes and armaments to Ibn Sa'ud, the aftermath of the Battle of Injair (also spelt Inqayr) and a visit made to Kuwait by one of Ibn Sa'ud's representatives, Hafiz Wahba.Much of the correspondence in the file is between British officials at the Political Agency in Kuwait, the Political Residency in Bushire and the British Agency in Jeddah, but the file also contains copies of letters, in Arabic with English translations, from the following: Ibn Sa'ud; the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah; officials of the Government of Iraq and Faisal al-Duwaish.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Agent and Consul General, Jeddah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Fayṣal bin Sulṭān al-Dawīsh</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Ikhwan revolt (1927-1930)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>