<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003aa_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:55:10.187Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">S’ ^ Sfinfidential From The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India I am directed to forward the accompanying confidential request that you will sign and return the enclosed receipt and enter the report in the separate register for such works referred to in the circular letter from the Government of India in the Foreign Department, No. 141-P., datod the 20th January 1894, as modified by circular letter No. 2176-F., dated the 30th August 1900. in the Foreign and Political Department, To ?he Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated oimla, the April 1919. Sir, No. 26 • An^ 61 }. ^^-His^^tion Report on the Persian Gulf Political Residency for the year ending the 31st December 1917 copy of the report noted in the margin, and to I have the honour to be. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India■MS-/ . M of is^o. © Polioioal Agency, Kuwait. Dated 7th January,19^0. Captain D.V. McCoIIuji, Political Agent, Kuwait. The Co.a.aander, S. r . ,, Ban.dlura' , . Sir, I have tne honour to request th^t you will be oo good to ta*ce charge of the sealed p,Aw^et ^.ent herewith ..und aeliver it personally to Colonel Coraon W-^l.ter, Military Governor and Political Officer, Basrah or an. ofxicer vuthDriotd oy hiu in writing to ta^e delivery. 2- The contends „re strictly secret and I .oust request on.j.t you will oe so good as to consider yourself personally responsible for tne safe delivery of the pao-ce*, with sehLs intact, acwording to che directions noted above. 3. A receipt fori is attached which you will .cindly sign and return to the bearer of this letter and packet. Fron To , I have the honour to be, Sir, Your cost obeuient servant, j? Captain, political Agent, KuwaitDECEIVED from the Political Agent, Kuwait one sealed packet (with seals intact) for aelivery to the Political icer, Basrah or his duly authorised representative.vaaildeaU-4. ^rorn Xno Jeputy Secretaiy to the Government a* India in tue Forri ; ~n and Political Jepart&lt;ient t To The Political iigent, Kuwait. Dated Siel&amp;i, the^ '^ Larch 1920, 3ir f X am directed to forward the accompanying * » confidential copy of the report noted in the margin, 26. I and to request that Annual Administration Report on ! th^ Persian Gulf Political Residency I fo: the year ending the 31st December * you will sign and ISto. | return tae enclosed receipt and enter the report in the separate register for such works referred to in the circular letter from the Government of India in the Foreign Department, No*!!!-?., dated the 20th January 1G94, nr. m dialed by circular letter No.21?6~P. da.ted the 30th Augurt 1900. Deputy Decretary to the Government of India; / rv ^ ^ itfBsmSeC^ ——- «? Telegrams: - Arbur, Cairo. Telephone: 5552. N y Ref. No., ARAB BUREAU, 3 , SHARIA LAZOGHLI K ASR-EL-DO UB AR A, % CAIRO. 18th. ^pril 19^0. (g) Political Agent, Koweit. I am sending you by Registered Post one oopy of 'tfotes on the Middle East* Ua.3. 7 /ill you please acknowledge receipt on attached receipt form. 7^- 0 - O ^^ 2- z^ 7 ^ feTegrarnTT- ARBUR, e Cairo. Telephone: 5552. Ref. No Xi/3/-6A2P...„„ 'ARAB BUREAU, 3 , SHARIA LAZOGHLI KASR-EL-DOUBARA, * CAIRO. Political Agent, Koweit. 1.4.20. 7/^ On the 31st. December last I sent you one copy of 'Notes on the Middle East' No.l. Will you please let me know if you have received same. or Director Arab Bureaua) Telegrams: - ARBUR, ARAB BUREAU, 3 , SHARIA LAZOGHLI KASR-EL-DOUBARA, A Cairo. elephone: 5552. REF. No . 11/3/7^55* CAIRO. 14th June* 1920. On the 16th April last I sent to you by Registered Post one copy of the Arab Bureau Secret Publication 'Notes on the Middle Sast' U°*3. Will you please let me know if it has duly reached you. The Political Agent Koweit.RMBfe Yj SBC R B / Y (o Y\ Klil'iORiU-i -JHId 9 H8re',7lth a. pi as as under of Xiden to Salaries of Intelligence from Force 'D' Hoa. J24 to 334* Please acknowledge receipt. Ho of Copies . 1 . Seri al Hos . b3. To: - Polit foal Age nt f KU./AIT. Tine Arab Bureau (of the Residency) will be abolished aa from October let 1920. All outstanding claims should be sent so aa to reach the Bureau before September 25th 1920. After September 50th, communlcatioiis on 5 uih^e&lt;rta relat ing to toe He v iaz should be addi'essed to British Agent, Jeddah. ComEEnmioations connected with the cloeing of the Arab Bureau may be addressed, from October let 1920, until further notice, to:- Ifcajor H. Garland, The Raaldency, Bamleh, 6-9-20, z / t^amlah or Cairo) 7%^ lx ^ y ^SECKET. &gt;f 1920* Political Agency, Kuwait. The 26th October 1920. To The (reneral Staff, General Head Quarters, Mes. Ex.. Eorce. — Memorandum . I have to acknowledge receipt of a copy, serial No.63, of Index to Summaries of Intelligence from Eoroe 'D' Nos.324 to 334 forwarded with your memorandum HA.I-145(b)of 29/9/20. Major, / Political Agent, Kuwait. 7No. 103 -rs. of 1926. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 16th March 1926. To MEMORANDUM . The Kadda ( Nejd-Transjordan ) and Bahra ( Nejd- -Iraq ) Agreements recently negotiated by Sir Gilbert Clayton with the Sultan of Bfejd have been published in pamphlet form by His Majesty’s Government and can be purchased directly from H.M. Stationery Office, Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2., or through any bookseller in the United Kingdom. Price 3d. net. By order, Resident in the Persian Gulf.NO. Political Aganoy, Kuwait. Da tad tha 16th Auguat 192J. proa To Liautanant-coLonal H.R.p.Lio^on, C.X.B., Political Agent, Kuwait. Tha o-f^ioer in Cherga, Air Staff Intalliganoa, Air Headquarter*, Hineidi. Sir, In returning receipt* for S • of I• Ho* 26 dated 2dth June, 27 dated 6th July, 2d dated 12th July, 22 dated 12th July, SO 26th Juiy and SI dated 2nd AuguBt, I have the honour to draw your attention to the fact that all Fix publication* reached ae together, and on 16th August 1222 . Doubtlen* you will oa*e nece^aary enquiries ap to where the fault of the delay in transmitting such important documents l*y• To apaipt you in this x enclose three outer cover*, which prove that the letter* were not *ent by Registered po»t, but by hand, ap far a* I can oa.te out at thi* end, the three envelopes were handed over to the Captain of the B* I • S .f .’'Banrtura - on it* down voyage from Basrah on 2nd August 1222. The captain having forgotten to deliver them at iCuw«.it handed tneu over to the Captain Of tn# first 'up* ship that ne met (probably at Masoat) which happened to be the S.S .’•Bandra' and the Captain of th« latter pent them ashore by the hand of the Port Dootor, in moat oasual manner and without note of any sort. I might mention that a cypher oode sent by H£b Bxoel- lenoy the High Commi*»ioner for ‘Iraq which I was expect ing by the *a ae Phip on Srd AuguP^ Pinilarly got loPt, and after muoh telegraphing also arrived yesterday 16th August 1^22. x have the honour to be, Sir, four most obedient servant, L ^ Li«ut-Col., Ealitical Agent, Kuwait.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003aa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/15</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003aa</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/15</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. 6/3- Vol. II Confidential Books and Maps'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-16T18:03:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (48 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 48; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-47; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence and telegraphs consisting of requests for books, maps, memoranda, administration reports and military surveys of the Persian Gulf, particularly pertaining to Kuwait and Iraq. The file also includes requests and receipts for secret and confidential documents circulated via the Royal Navy and the Indian Army. The file also includes maps of Riyadh and Buraidah from 1919.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003aa#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>