<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ff_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-25T15:27:03.051Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">11, Birchin Lane, London, e.c.3. 29th September, 1938, Dear Symon, I learned yesterday that there are extant some photographs of the Dinner given to the Sultan of Muscat. Gan you tell me from whom I can get a copy as I would like to have one? When the present rush has abated a little, perhaps v/e can meet; there are one or two things I would like to speak about.' Office of the Political Residentjf (a i, in the Persian Gulf, \fil0 Gamp Karachi. F^l' Could you please refer to your letter No.P.Z.4586/38 dated the 2nd July 1938 on the subject of certain payments due from the Sultan of Muscat to the Government Hospitality Fund. 2. I mentioned the matter this morning to His Highness, who said that he had already made out a cheque in payment of these bills and was sending it off. I am sending a copy of this letter to Watts. ( ' C ~ / T—f n - 0 J /) . , . n ♦sent under P.L.No.C/439 of 7.7.'33.IU 6 ' ^ All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted Parl, London.' ‘elephone No.: Whitehall 1481. .ddress: “Hospitality, GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, Dear Symon, Do you think you might now take steps to remind ohe Sultan of Muscat that he still owes us some money which we paid on his behalf, namely - ? (1) Messrs. Kidner and Son, Limited . Hire of car during his unofficial visit ••• ••• ••• £33. 3. 3a. (2) Press photographs ordered at the Sultan’s request at a cost of ... ££• 3.10a. I wrote to Mr. Dull Chand, in Paris, on the 3rd May suggesting that he should pay these two amounts, hut have received no reply. Yours sincerely, A.C.B. Symon, Esq., India Office.Confidential D.o.uo.aea-s ! 4479 1 I 1 Bu shire. 1 \95 S The Residency, the 10tn June 19o8. My dear Metcall'e, Gould you please refer to Peel’s letter Ro. P.2. 8451/38 of 28th May to you, enclosing aymon’s Note on the visit of the Sultan of Muscat to London. 2. As, in connection with the Muscat Treaty, I was in London during the visit of the Sultan, and in close contact with him almost daily, I am in a position to confirm what is said in the Note, as to the visit being an unqual ified success. I know His Highness well, and could tell he was enjoying himself, quite apart from the fact that he told me more than once how mucn ne appreciated tne efforts made on his behalf by the India Office and tne Government Hospitality Department. Sven after the conclusion of His Hignness’s official visit, wnen ne returned from Paris to London in a private capacity to continue tne Treaty talks, Grankshaw and Symon were good enough to give much of their time to looking after him. ^ nls Jdosts made a fawnurable impression on the Sultan, the reverse was also the case. Everybody I met was mucn taken with nis engaging personality. Cranksnaw, who has had much experience of visiting Potentates, told me that His Hignness was one of the pleasantest he had .xet. I am sending copies of this letter to Peel and Watts. / Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, k:.c.i.e.,c.s.i. ,m.v.o. , Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. Simla. fours sincereiy, 3d.T.C.F07LE * sent under P.L.No.365-3 of 10/6/38© Dear th rington-oiaithf With reference to our conversation this afternoon, I enclose an extract from a letter dated 18th ay from the Sultan of Muscat, from which you will see that he joined the ship for Bocnfbay at Genoa on the 19th May. It looks as though His Highness aban oncd his intention of flying to Egypt. We have no ini' mat ion as to whether he visited Germany or Italy. Yours sincerely* i.i ./. i;‘dierington- raith, Msq., Foreign Office* S.w.i.r^. Copy of a letter D^A.Dis♦No.709-Cus.I/3S7 Hated Simla. the 14th May, 1938, from the First Secretary, Central Board of Revenue, to the Collector of Customs, Bombay. Ruling Chiefs - His Highness the Sultan of Muscat - Baggage - ?Jxemption from duty. •»».. j*X? 0 I am directed to refer to the Board’s endorsement R.Dis.No.622-Cus./25, dated the 29th September 1925, relating to the exemption fran duty of the baggage etc. of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, and to infora you that His Highness the Sultan is arriving at Bombay by the Lloyd Triestino steamer which leaves Naples on the 20th May 1938, His baggage is being brought in advance by his Aide-de-camp, Mr. Hilal Bin Badr who is expected to sail from Marseilles for Bombay on the 7th M^,1938 by the P.&amp; 0. as 'Maloja'.N0.D.1866-H/38. Prom The Under Secretary to the OoTernment of India in the ^eternal Affairs Department, To The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay Political and Services Department* Dated Simla* the Hay 1938. Return of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat from tour. Sir, I am directed to state thaton his return from tour in the United Kingdom and the continent. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat will be arriving at Bombay by the Lloyd Trieatino steamer which leaves Naples on the 20th Hay 1938. His Highness will probably stay in Bombay for about two weeks before proceeding to Muscat. 2. During his stay in Bombay His Highness will not be a State guest, but the Government of India would be glad if arrangements could be made for an officer of the Provincial Government to meet His Highness on arrival at Bombay and to afford him any reasonable facilities or assistance which he may require. 3. I am to add that the Collector of Customs, Bombay has been addressed separately regarding His Highness 1 baggage which has been shipped in advance by the P. &amp; 0 ms ’Maloja* leaving Marseilles for Bombay on the 7th May 1938. I have the honour to be Your most obedient servant. Sd/-. C.A.G. Savidge, Under Secretary to the Government of India.Hotel d»Angleterrc et tie la Grande Bretagne - nice /'-n Bice , 1q Dear Mr. Symon, Thank you very much for your letters for which I will write separate replies in due course. I am leaving for Genoa tomorrow morning and will sail from there in the afternoon. l ©hall he grateful if you could arrange to inform the Government of India about qy arrival in Bombay and to give the necoaoary facility on my arrival. I hope to arrive Bombay on the 30th instant. X X &gt;C /c ;c Tours very sincerely, (Sgd.) Said bin TairaurConfidential r. i ^ T- V*s^ ^ /Ay ^ *, A. J&gt;O.ITo*228«-3 Tne Kesidency, ctc#wx. ^YVrwfyu Could you please refer to India Office printed letter No.P.Z# 2806/58, dated 90tn April 1958, on me subject of tne Sultan’s visit to London. You will remember tnat I asiced you to let me nave a copy of tne report wnicn you are writing on tne sub ject or tne visit, and wnen I receive tnis I will add some comments ot my own# in tne meantime I snould lige to say tnat, in my opinion, tne visit was a great success, and I am grateful to tne India Office and to CranJcsnaw lor all tne trouble tney too* in tne matter. me success of tne visit snould certainly nelp us nere in our relations witn His Hignness. Yours sincerely, -p c.s/tU0**C , CrtsLtC /LU'4 is /ftftit' flTtv/kdiatJ ~ cu+/£ 4,^fJ You may lik^ to see Mr. note Cnu+fafaur!* ffirtn, y containing information which^rb is «l&gt;0osed to send to India about the Sultan of ^ Muscat’s visit and his second (unofficial) visit from 19th April to 1st May. During the latter period further progress was made in the business conversations about the commercial treaty and other matters with Sir T. Fowle and Mr. Gibson, and Mr. Symon gave a good deal of time to looking after the Sultan, as Major Crankshaw, having other duties to perform, was unable to pay much attention to him and Col. Dalyell was no longer available.Register No. P.Z / SECRET. ‘ZJf.51 rs*- POLITICAL DEPARTMENT /-V i-etter Telegram from Dated Rec. 19 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Cftmirman Under Secretary lb • f~ /W. Secretary of State.. Committee Under/Secretary HUSCfl T Nfa. nJUMA.(: i-Co'Jr £j-Minute Paper. political Department. Visit to England of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. The Sultan travelled from New York in the s.a. 'Queen Mary' which reached Southampton on 28th March . 2. He was welcomed at Southampton hy Major E.N. S. Crankshaw, Secretary of the Government Hospitality Fund, (on behalf of the Minister in Charge of Government Hospitality) and at Waterloo by Lord Stanley, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State (on behalf of His Majesty’s Government), Sir Trenchard Powle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, aad representatives of the India Office, Admiralty, War Office and Air Ministry^ oO ^ 3. During the period of official hospitality the Sultan and his suite were accommodated at the Dorchester Hotel. 4. Although the Sultan wore European clothes on arrival he wore his national costume for the remainder of the official visit and it is understood that he preferred to do so. 5. Press arrangements were handled by the Information Officer at the India Office. A flompr^hrnfflvr ntntrmrnt regarding the Sultan and his country which was issued on cn% i tv~«- the eve of the Sultan’s arrival j t- mT »y f cr His Highness; tn la ana « on - ^i g arri-v^ but, on the ove-of hio departure^ he issued a statement (which was released through the India Office) in the following terms 'On the eve of my departure from England at the end of my visit as the guest of His Britannic Majesty’s Government I am anxious to give expression to my sense of gratitude for the kindness and hospitality extended to me in so generous a measure by His Majesty’s Government, by official and non-official organisations 5319b 5000 10 30 and/2 . and by private individuals. I am indeed appreciative of the cordial welcome T have received. Jo effort has been spared to make every moment of my visit interesting and enjoyable, and I shall always preserve the happiest recollections of a country with which I and my people are linked in true friendship.” Partly owing to the elaborate programme of entertainment which was arranged for the Sultan during his visit to America the official programme of entertainment in this country was somewhat more elaborate than is usual in the case of visits of this nature suad it—ta aatiaficto^ -fro jf* t'W-'S****. fit ft' rafiorri that no instance—haa come i:o light of—any hlfca 0£SJArr1 ng 1 rv the arrangements made. There is not the slightest doubt that the Sultan enjoyed himself immensely and that the visit was an unqualified success. At all times the Sultan expressed himself as interested in what he was shown and appreciative of what was done for him. fct may -be-^pnrely coinoldcnce thaty 4s in the case of'^his A official visit to Delhi last November, the two eutotondlng events were the trips by air over London and the visit to the Agricultural College at Cambridge. If anything the programme was too full and on any future similar occasion it might be a good thing to leave a little more time for leisure and private affairs. It is true that on this occasion certain mornings and afternoons were left free for the purpose of official discussions with the Sultan. His Highness, so far from resenting this encroachment on the short period of his visit which was not filled with officiajl entertainments, welcomed the opportunity for talks on riatters and was most anxious to complete the Treatv discussions during Sir T. Fowls's presence in London. Per / y a future visit of a similar kind probably the best thing would be leave, say, ev?ry fourth or fifth day completely free/Minute Paper. Department. 3. 5319b 5000 10 3fi free and^leave it to, tTie p^ty euggenlr how these days' snouljz be filled. The Sultan did not seem particularly Interested in things mechanical; but he liked scenery, trees, flowers etc, and on the occasion of any future visit it might be a good thing to show him more of the country. During the period of official entertainment Hie Highness refused all 'private' invitations except that of Lord Cadman. The proposed visits to Broadcasting House and to the de Havilland Aircraft Factory were cancelled at the Sultan's request. His Highness declined the invitation to make a short broadcast in Arabic but did not give his reasons for doing so. The visits to the Tower of London and to Windsor Castle were arranged ru Ap+U at the Sultan's request. The informal dinner^ at which Sir Lancelot Oliphant acted as host was arranged in order to give the Sultan an opportunity of meeting representativesj of certain foreign missions i.e. Saudi-Arabian; Iraqi; Egyptian and French. 7. A copy of the speech delivered by the Sultan at the Government dinner on 29th March is attached. 8. A list of guests who accepted invitations to attend tne Reception held by the Sultan at Dorchester Hotel on 8th April is also attached. The Sult8n was neatly interested in the news films taken during his visit. Copies of the films (specially reduced to fit his cine-camera) were purchased by the Government Hospitality Fund and wer* presented to His Highness. 10. The Sultan was granted an interview by Lord Halifax, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, on 11th April. 11. Rai Sahib Dulichand, the Sultan's Accountant-General, arrived in England at the end of March and remained throughout/4. . tTVw- throughout the visit. He stayed at a different Hotel and at the Sultan’s request he was not included in the official party. 12. The Sultan left England for France at the end of the official visit on the evening of 12th April and at his request his departure was kept as quiet as possible. So anxious was His Highness to prevent his identity 'jx being discovered in France that the whole party travelled under assumed names. He v/as seen off by Sir Trenchard Fowle, Major Crankshaw and a representative of the India Office. 13. The Sultan returned to England by air, (in a purely private capacity) on 19th April and^using the name of Mr. Ozdi, occupied a suite of rooms at Queen Anne’s Mansions. He was accompanied by Mr. Dulichand and servant only, the remainder of his suite remaining in Paris. It is understood that His Highness preferred the privacy of Queen Anne’s Mansions; and on the occasion of any similar official visit in the future it might be better to engage accommodation at that place in preference to an Hotel. His Highness ended his private visit on 1st May and was seen off at Croydon Air port by Major Crankshaw and a representative of the India Office. During this private visit most of the day-time was occupied in official talks connected with the revision of the Muscat Treaty etc. , and with shopping excursions. His Highness accepted invitations to take tea with Lady Willingdon and Lady Linlithgow but otherwise refused to accept any ’’private” invitations*^ During this period the Sultan gave the impression that he was really enjoying the novelty of being separated from his suite - he stated that this was the first time/Minute Paper. Department. 5. time he had been alone since he was 14 years old - and it is thought that he would have liked to remain for a longer period; but as he had made arrangements to return to Muscat in July this was not possible.Speech delivered hy Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat and ’Oman at the Government Dinner on the 29th March, 1938. Lord Zetland, my Lords and Gentlemen.* I should like to thank Your Lordship for the kind words in which you have proposed my health, and you, Gentlemen, for honouring the Toast in this w*y. And I should like to say how much I appreciate the welcome that I have received. As you know, the Sultans of Muscat and ’Oman have 'been in treaty relations with the British Government for more than a century, and I welcome this opportunity of visiting Great Britain. I hope tomorrow to have the great pleasure of seeing His Majesty King George and to enter into a personal friendship which I trust will endure. As I said, the Governments of Great Britain and ’Oman have been long in treaty relations, hut I would claim more than treaty relations, relations of true friendship and real understanding. Your Lordship has referred to certain help which I have been able to give and I should like to assure you that I am very glad to have been of assistance to H.M’s Government. And T on my side am deeply appreciative of the help and assistance extended by His Majesty’s Government from time to time to the Sultans of Muscat and ’Oman which the Saudi dynasty will not forget. I hope that these happy relations will be further strengthened by the personal friendship which I now have the privilege of forming with you all. T have greatly enjoyed my journey and am sure that T shall enjoy my stay in this country. I do not think that you will wish for a long speech and I will close with renewed thanks and wish you all good health and happiness.(With the Compliments of the Information Officer, India Gxfice) U N 0 F F I C 1 A L NOTE ( As •previously announced IIis jirfhne ss the Saltan^o j^ Muscat and Oman v/i 11 arrive at South amp ton on honaay _^8th March, hy t he s. s. n Q ueen Mary 1 ^ His H ighnes^-^viH he the puest of H j s Ma,jest y T s Goverr.r nent foi'* a period of a -Lortni^nt from the date of ar rival) His Highness’ suite consists of the following:- Halal 'bin Badr (A.D.C.) Saiyid AWdulmmiim Zav/avd (Secretary) Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubaily (State Official) The party will 'be accommodated at the Dorchester Hotel. Major E.H.3. Cranhshaw, C.M.C-. , M.B.E. , Secretary to the Government Hospitality Fund, and Lieutenant-Colonel G. Dalyell of The Binns, C.I.E., an officer of the Indian Political Department who has had long experience in the Persian Gulf, will 'be attached to the party during the period of official hospitality. His Highness will he welcomed at Southampton hy Major Crankshaw on 'behalf of the Minister in Charge of Government Hospitality, and at Waterloo Station hy representatives of His Majesty’s Government. The Sultan will he received hy the Secretary of State for India at 12 noon on Tuesday, 29th March, and hy the King at Buckingham Palace at 11.30 a.m. on Wednesday, the 30th March. The Programme of official entertainment includes a Government Dinner to he held at Lancaster House on the 29th March. (Further details of the programme will he issued separately.) Last November th,e Sultan paid a State visit to India lasting ten days, during which time he was the guest of His Excellency the Viceroy for three days. On the terminationof this visit he proceeded on a world tour, including visits to Singapore, Japan (to see his father who now lives in that country) and to the United States of America* He arrived in America on the fOth February and during his visit was received by the President. An Unofficial Note regarding His Highness and the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman is attached.h&gt; s 4? &amp; Any further comm unication on thesubject of this letter should be addressed to:— THE COMMISSIONER OF POLICE OF THE METROPOLIS (SPECIAL BRANCH), NEW SCOTLAND YARD, S.W.I and the following No. quoted METROPOLITAN POLICE OFFICE (Special Branch) New Scotland Yard London, S.W.I TELEPHONE WHITEHALL 1212 V 3U5/RLT/224' Sir, Communications should not be addressed to individuals by name * * * POSTAGE MUST BE PREPAID 9th May, 1938. 4- S- I am directed hy the Commissioner of Police of the Metropolis to acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter of the 5th instant (P.Z. 3021/38) , and to inform you that the thanks of the Sultan of Muscat for the protection rendered him have heen conveyed to Detective Sergeant pocock. 3 I am. Sin&gt; ^ / t Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, S.VV. 1. . ate*. ; 10MAY1938 I INDiA OFfICE 4O [W* lrf v I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 16th April (345/R. L. T./224) intimating that an officer of the Special Branch would be placed at the disposal of the Sultan of Muscat during his recent private visit to this country. Tho MarquoQS' of'Zetland underotands that the Sultan particularly desires to have placed on record his high appreciation of the services rend^^d by Detective Sergeant Pocock^/ Lord 5 renders k^/ Lord Zetland desires me to take this opportunity of conveyfe^ to you his thanks for meeting the Sultan*s v/ishes in regard^; this matter. fa 7 ©fid.) R. PSEt v 4 fit, Li,5 L Draft Paper. P.Z.3021/38. Department. DRAFT LETTER. 3 MAY 1938 T.V. Brenan, Esq.., O.B.E., Foreign Office, S.W. 1. rj^r r090 Wt 41703/86 10,000 3.38 Dear Brenan, As I told you on the telephone on Saturday morning, the Sultan left for Paris hy air at 9 a.m. on the 1st May, travelling as Mr. Ozdi. He will remain incognito until he pays his visit to the French President which will take place shortly 'before his departure from France. He has def initely decided to travel to Bomhay 'by the Lloyd Triestino liner whi-eb leavoo Naples on the 20th May will join the—ship at Port Said on the 22nd May. In order to get to Egypt he will fly from Amsterdam 'by K.L.M. plane. He plans to remain in France for about a fortnight, during which time he will pay a short trip to Berlin. It seems doubtful now whether he will go to Italy, but if he does the visit will probably take place jual* before he leaves for Egypt. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) A. C. i3. SYMON.'PaJ* Vt ^ Many thanks for your letter of the 16th April 1938 (P.Z.2566/38)and for so kindly sending me the change of address of Shaikh ’Abdullah bin Hamad. I will write to him in due course. 2. Symon asked for comments on the Muscat visit. The visit went off,I think, very successfully and I am sure that His Highness appreciated all that was done for him,and was very interested in everything. Grankshaw’s arrangements were,as always, admirable. I would,however, suggest that on any future similar occasio the party should be given a little leisure,now and again, probably the best thing would he to leave ,say,every fortth or fifth day blank and ask them when the time comes if there is anything that they would liKe to see. And a little rest should be allowed - for the East does nottaKe Kindly to our habit of rushing round all day.* The party missed the debate in the Commons as the House rose before dinner was over on the evening of Butler's dinner. They are very anxious to hear a debate and I mentioned the point in an informal letter to Butler. I am sure that they would appreciate it if it could be arranged. Yours sincerely.p — f P • faphic Address : ' HospitalitV, Parl, London.*' ' r Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. j ^ 4 ri All communications should be‘ addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted G.H.F. 1886. Sir, M * s GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.I $ I am directed 'by the Minister in Charge, Government Hospitality, to thank you for your letter (P.Z.2806/38) of the 27th April, from which he is glad to learn that the Secretary of Staie for India is satisfied v/ith the arrange ments which were made by Government Hospitality for the encei tainment of : is Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman during the period of his official visit. I am, Sir, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office. 2 9 APR 1938 india orncrI4&amp;HL r / ^ M- The official visit of the Multan of Muscat to this country ended on the 12th April, and there is not the slightest doubt that His Highness enjoyed himself immensely and that the visit was an unqualified success. The programme of entertainment was somewhat more elaborate (and expensive) than is usual, and it is satisfactory to record that we have heard of no instance in which any hitch occurred in the arrangements made by the Government Hospitality ^und. Major Crankshaw has been indefatigable and did everything possible to maxe the Sultan’s visit pleasant and enjoyable. We are also indebted to Colonel Dalyell for lending his services during the Sultan’s visit. It is therefore suggested that we should send letters of appreciation to the Government Hospitality ^und and to Colonel Dalyell. Draft letters are suggested. toP.Z. 2806/38 Draft Paper. Department. Major E.N.S. Crankshaw, G.M.G., M.B.E., Govt. Hospitality Fund, S.W. 1. Copy to India Bi/shire iscat ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER HO. - M SECFaT^RY, POLITICAL AMD SECRET. L :?T. i;v: IA crriOE {ULuouan m Am MAIL Lt I I tr o. Ifr* &lt;*4 3 0 APR 1938 e-H SEC! t T-Lr, PC'ITICAL AK UOr Y SEN i lO 2 7 APR 1938 I am directed by the S. of S. for I. to refer to your letter of the 19th November, 1937, No. G.H.F.1886, and connected correspondence regarding the official visit to England of H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. The Marquess of Zetland has been much gratified to learn that the arrangements made for the Sultan were successful in every way, and in conveying to the Minister in Charge of Govt. Hospitality hisappreciation of the hospitality afforded to the Sultan, he desires to express his thanks to you and your Dept, for the special efforts which were made to ensure the success of H.H.'s visit. (Sgd.) R. PEEL m kDraft Paper. ^806 ' POLITICAL Department. draft Lieut.Colonel G.Dalyell of the Binns, C.I.E., The Binns, Linlithgow. Lette r, • 2 i APR i938 I am desired by the Marquess of Zetland to convey to you an expression of his thanks for the services which you were good enough to render during the recent visit of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Om anMETROPOLITAN POLICE OFFICE (Special Branch) New Scotland Yard London, S.W. I WHITEHALL 1212 TELEPHONE Anyfurther communicationon chesubject of this letter should be addressed to:— THE COMMISSIONER OF POUCE OF THE Communications should not be addressed to individuals by name * * * POSTAGE MUST BE PREPAID METROPOLIS (SPECIAL BRANCH), NEW SCOTLAND YARD, S.W. I and the following No. quoted ^U5/RLT/224 16th April, 1938 Sir I am directed by the Commissioner of Police of the Metropolis to refer to your letter of the 12th April, (P.Z.2602/1938), and to inform you that an officer of this Branch will he placed at the disposal of the Sultan of Muscat on his return to this country. I am Sir Your obedient Servant The Under Secretary of State for India, political Department, India Office, S.W. 1.1 li^' ■ T ^1- jt, ^ *4^ .., iii'*- Ao-you-are pyolaftbAy—aweyg^ the Sultan of Muscat is leaving for France on the evening of the 12th April on the termination of his official visit as the guest of H. M.G. / j ) It is prohahle that the Sultan A will return to England on or about the 19th April in a purely private capacity, and if this visit materialises His Highness would be glad if an officer of the Special B r anch could be placed at his disposal. Lord Zetland would be grateful if arrangements could be made to comply with His Highness’s wishes in this matter. A further communication will be addressed to you on receipt of detailed information regarding the Sultan’s movements. »'ll 6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IOP;,a». Joyce. The Sultan has approved the issue of the attached message on the eve of his de arture* His Highness leaves London for Paris this evening by the 10 o’clocc train, and is most anxious that his departure should be as private as possiole. l or this reason it is desirable to avoid ne . r s of his departure reaching the Press until the last possible moment. Y;ouid you kindly bear this in mind when making arrangements for publication ?V PROM HIS 171th the Compliments of the Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. JWO 3Lm, .SiWr -ft (For favour of publication.) ,; 0n the eve of my departure from England at the end of my visit as the guest of His Britannic Majesty*s Government I am anxious to give expression to my sense of gratitude for the kindness and hospitality extended to me in so generous a measure by His Majesty’s Govemmentf by official and non—official organisations and by private individuals* I am indeed appreciative of the cordial welcome I have received^ ITo effort has been spared to make every moment of my visit interesting and enjoyable, and I shall always preserve the happiest recollections of a country with which I and my people are linked in tiue friendship.On the eve of my departure from England at the end of my visit as the guest of His Majesty’s Government . ; 1 am anxious to give expression i&gt;o i:iy sense of gratitude for th.e kindness and hospitality extended to me in so generous a measure 'by His Majesty’s Government, 'by official and non-official organizations and 'by private individuals. I am indeed appreciative oi the cordial welcome I have received. j..o ef or u has 'been spared to make every moment of my visit interesting and enjoyable, and I shall always preserve the happiest recollections of a country with which I and my people are linked in friendship.on the eve of my departure froi i 1 ngland at the end of iay offioial visit as the guest of His Majesty’s Government I m anxious to give expression to my sense of gratitude for the kindness and hospitality extended to me in bo generous a measure *sy His Majesty 9 a Government, by official and non-official organisations and by private individuals* I am indeed appreciative of the cordial welcome I have received* to effort has been spared to make every moment of :vr visit interesting and enjoyable, and I shall always preserve the happiest recollections of a country with which I and r iy people are proud to be linked in friendship*’© With the Compliments of the Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. MESSAGE FROM HIS HIGHNESS THS SULTAN OF MUSCAT AND OMAN. K.C.I.E. (For favour of publication.) / d Hjl 6a l f U ^ ^ H 0n the eve of my departure from England I am anxious to give expression to my sense of gratitude for the kindness and hospitality extended to me in so generous a measure by His Majesty’s Government r by official and non official organizations and by private individuals. I am indeed appreciative of the cordial welcome I have received, om«3Ll« No effort has been spared to make every moment of my visit interesting and enjoyable, and I shall^take away, andj always preserve,, the happiest recollections of a country with which I and my people are proud to be linked in friendship. wDraft Paper. H.A. Caccia, Esq., FOREIGN OFFICE, S. W. 1. s. II Department. 11 APR\»i Dear Caccia, In case they may be useful I enclose copies of the following:- (1) A confidential Memorandum giving brief particulars regarding (a) the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman; and (b) H.H. the Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur, K.C.I.E. (2) An unofficial note regarding the above. (3) The programme of entertainment. Crankshaw will bring the Sultan to the side entrance at 5 minutes to 11 tomorrow morning and I will come over a few minutes before that time to go with you to meet His Highness at the door. The official visit ends tomorrow and His Highness leaves for Paris by the 10 p.m. train from Victoria. He wishes his departure to be strictly private. During the last two weeks we have had a number of informal conversations with the Sultan regarding the revision of the Anglo-Muscat Treaty and it is possible that the Sultanthat His Highness will return to France. He may also visit Germany and Italy. All these visits will be private, though it is understood that the Sultan is to have an interview with the French President.^Teltegraphic Address: 'Hospitality, Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted Cr.H.P.1886. r VERNMENI HOSPITALITY FUND. P. Z. J , Treasury Chambers, P: A( | k . Whitehall, Dear Symon, Thank you for your letter ( ZZ. 2486/38 ) of the 8th April v/ith which you enclosed a copy of a telegram from . . Ambassador at &amp;ahln bout the visit of the Sultan of Ifuscat and Oman to the United Staues of America. I fully appreciate that the fact that His Highness was so well treated in America as well as that his visit is being followed by visits to Prance, Germany and Italy has made it necessary to exceed the usual scale of entertainment in his case. The Dinner at the House of Commons was really arranged at his own request, and in view of the position of the Foreign Office in regard to the Sultan, I feel that Sir Lancelot Oliphant’s Dinner was also unavoidable. I therefore agree that the cost of these additional items to the program'e shall be borne by Government Hosoitality.P7 gLH-Zb S'- c ■ Draft Paper. POLITICAL Department. DRAFT LE Major E.N.S. Crankshaw, G.M.G. , M.B.E. , Government Hospitality Fund, Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1. ^‘7 i' , H '4'' MR I$j8 TTER. 6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IOP 3^- As I think you are aware, we atta ch considerable political importance to the visit of the Sultan of Muscat and are anxious that should he done to make the visit a complete success. As this is the Sultan f s first visit to England it is perhaps unfortunate that it was preceded by a visit to America, where His Highness was treated with great ceremony, particulrly during the short period of official hospitality, and that it is being followed by visits to France, Germany and Italy. It is on t^ig account that we have felt obliged to ask you to arrange a more elaborate and expensive programme of entertainment than might perhaps have been otherwise necessary. In particular I rof ev - tw' the dinner at the House of Commons, at which Mr. Butler acted as host, and ijcn. the dinner at the Savoy Hotel, at which Sir Lancelot Oliphant acted as host. In this connection you will see from the enclosed telegram from H.M* Ambassador at Washington that in addition to a lunch at the Wh .te House, dinners were given by the Secretary of State wereanu Under Secretary of State during the period of the Sultan^ official visit to Washington, and in such circumstances it was felt desirable that in addition td the Government dinner at Lancaster House &gt; Sultan 1 s programme should include one v* -4 “i -i _f (Sgd.) A. C*.B. SYMON,All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY Telegraphic Address : “ Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l and the following reference quoted G.H.P.1886 * 9th Anril, 1938. Dear Symon, Thank you for your letter of the 8th April (P.S.2486/38) about the Reception given by the Sultan of Muscat end Oman on the 8th. I agree that any expenditure on this Function in excess of £50 shall be uaid by this Department. Yours sincerely A.C.B. Symon Eso., India OfficeZ.gL/f^ ss-. Draft Paper. POLITICAL Department. 5 DRAFT LETTER. 1933 Major E.N. S. Crankshaw, C.M. G-. 9 M. B. E. 9 Government Hospitality Fund, S.W.l. V/hen the question of holding a Reception Before his departure from England was put to the Sultan of Muscat it was thought that the cost would he approximately £ 50 &gt; ^3. His Highness was informed accordingly. We now understand that owing to the number of acceptances the figure of £50 will he exceeded, and in order to avoid any difficulties with the Sultan we hope that it will he possible to accept any excess over £50 as a charge against the vote for Government hospitality. Ycfurs slncerafy* (Sgd.) A. C. C. SYMOM. 6471a Wt 22530/P 141 10,000 9.37 lopr Telegraphic Address: ** Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND I Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l and the following reference quoted :- F. 1886 9th April, 1938 Dear Symon, Thank you for your letter (P.Z.2486/38) of the 8th April. I quite agree that the charges for the reproduction of the nev/sreel films taken during the official visit of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman should he charged against this Department, and I have therefore written to the companies concerned asking them to have copies made to fit the Sultan’s projector. Yours sincerely A.C.B. Symon Esq. , India Office5^ Draft Paper. POLITICAL Department. 3 DRAFT Major E.N.S. Grankshaw, G.M.G* , M.B.E. , Government Hospitality Fund, Treasury ChamlDers, S.W. 1. LETTER. , 8 APR m (jvc* 3)0^ We understand that the Sultan of Muscat has expressed a wish to obtain a reproduction of the News Reel films taken during his official visit, to show to his own people on his return to Muscat. These films will have^/cer :ain propaganda value and if the charges can he accepted against the vote for Government hospitality we think that it would he a graceful gesture to present reproductions to His Highness. £ smrs sinceraiy*&gt;• p- T^gY’aphic Address : ' Hospitality, ^ Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. and the following reference quoted All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY (I.H.F. 1886 Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, 6th April, 1938. S.W.l ■2 0 . J Dear Symon, In connection with the visit of the Sultan of Muscat, I am accepting charges against the Vote for Government Hospitality that are to some extent without precedent. For instance - the reproduction of new s reel films of the Sultan at a cost of approximate ly £5; the cost of the Sultan*s Reception ove r and a bove the £t&gt;0 he is prepared to pay ; the Dinner given b y iir. imtler and there may he other small items. I have ART doubt that there are very good reasons why we should be as generous as possible to the Sultan during his stay, but to assist my Minister and myself in defending the expenditure to which I have referred, should any question arise on it hereafter, I should be grateful if you would give me something on paper in justification. I imagine that it is of the greatest political importance that the Sultan should be phased with his reception and should leave with the most friendly feelings towards this country? Yours sincerely. A.G.B. Symon, Esq., India Office.Greedy, Sir Herbert and Lady Dalyell of the Binns, Davidson, Mr* W.J* Davis, Mr* Richard C« de Margerie, Monsieur Lt*-Col* and Mrs. and Mrs* Edward C. and Madame Dennys, Colonel and Mrs. Dent, Paymaster Captain and Mrs. Duffer in and Ava, The Most Hon* the Marquess and Marchione Dunbar-Nasmith, Admiral Sir Martin Dunlop, Sir Robert and Lady Ede, Mr* and Mrs* Egyptian Charge d'Affaires and Madame Hakki Bey Etherington-Smith, Mr* R*C*A* -: 1 —Tr— 1 -,:. ' :c...,, lt r—• Ea.i.:[^huy Lir. -Culr;—3 tA. Paviell, Lt*~Col* and Mrs* \7« P* 0. Fowle, Sir Trenchard and Lady Frew, Wing Commander M.BG-ibson, Mr, and Mrs, J, P t Gordon-Lennox, The Lord and Lady Same Gossage, Air Vice-Marshal and Mrs. E*L. Hale, Mr, and Mrs. Hal land, 'Colonel and Mrs, Gal, IL Hancock, Mr, G,C. Healy, Mr, and Mrs, J c Hav/art, The Lord and Lady Hoare. The Rt, Hen. Sir Samuel and The Lady Maud JZ. //rri' o&amp;ds&amp;C;- India* The High Commissioner for and Lady Noon 1 ran i Mini ster, The Keif-Cohen, Mr. and Mrs, R, Kershaw, Sir Louis and Lady Kisch, Sir Cecil and LadyRimingtin, Lt.-Col* and Mrs* Ross. Sin Denison and Lady Rouse. Mr. S*F. Russell, Wing Commander and Mrs. H.B. St* Bar 'be, Mr, and Mrs, Said-Ruete, Mr. and Mrs. Seal, Mr. and Mrs. Starling, Mr. and Mrs. F.C Shelley, Captain and the Honourable Mrs. G.E, Stevenson, Group Captain D.F, and Mrs. Stevenson, Miss Studd, Group Captain T.Q Sykes, Brig.-General Sir Percy and Lady Symon, Mr, and Mrs, A.C.BTod, Captain CoF Tuke, Fit. -Lt* B.S. V/akely, Sir Leonard and Lady ualton. Mr, and Mrs. Wiidey, Mr. A e E. Wilkins, Mr. and Mrs, V.E, Williams, Mr. Kenneth Williamson, Sir Horace and Lady Willing&amp;on, The Most Hon, the Marouess and Marchioness Yates, Captain and Mrs. G.D. L a d a, M o n s i eu r&amp; umiA orFics, TOXTSHAtLf 7th April f 193H* jear Mr* sawawi. As you are getting hack tron Caj^ridge later tlmn I bought, and will then have to get ready for the dinner this evening# I am deferring my visit until to-uorr rv morning* I hope to be able to see you about a quarter to ten* Yours sincerely# (Sgd.) A. C. 3. SYMON. Maiyid Abu Inuni • awawi# Secretary to H*Ii* The ultan of Muscat and &gt;man 9 . orchester Hotel, Pork Lane# 1 .1. _I an directed to infora: you that the Snatan of Unseat and Oman will pay a vieit to the r, ower of London on Friday, 8th April, 1938, at 2.30 p.m. T n this connoction I an to roQueet that you will nake the neceopary arran^enentP for the Guard to turn sut and pay tho normal compliments to ills Highness. A Guard of Honour will not be furnished on this sccasion. 'he General Officer Co unending, London ^iRtrict, Horse OuardP, S.V/.l. V T am, Sir, Your obedien* Servant, Q- Ei* OaptflJn, director of Personal ervicee Copi s to:’- India Office. liecretary, GoYamment Hoapitality vund. he Constable, 'o v /er of London.Draft Paper. \&gt; _ POLITICAL DRAFT T.Y. Brenan, Esq-, O.B.E. , Foreign Office, S.W.l. k -if* . SJfc fowj/cX’’ ■ -i. t “A ^ 7 r ' *k. ENCLOSURE H A!R MAIL UlTtR NO. (l-f'- *6 APR 1938 , 8EC- E ‘ PERT. INDIA C.-fICE COPY SENT i.' /ry^-4 nr^: 2359 i 9 5 B j Department. LETTER. , 5 APR 1938 Dear Brenan, According to present information the Sultan of Muscat proposes to leave this country for France on the 12th April, i.e. immediately on termination of his official visit. In a conversation which I had with him the other day he said that he would prohahly stay in Paris for 3 or h days, and although the visit would he of a private nature he hoped to he received hy the President. From Paris he will go to Berlin for a few days and will then come hack to Paris. From Paris he goes direct to Italy, and proposes to spend a few days each at Rome, Naples and Venice. My impression is that the visits to Germary and Italy will also he of a private nature and the Sultan has told Sir Trenchard Fov/le that he does not tA+Ck**XLt*~ t wish W meet^Mussolini. K474A Wt 22530 /^?44 IOP At the end of the Italian visit the Sultan will fly to EgypW where he will spend a few days before joining a steamer at Port Said to take him U uuU to Bomhay # /fie ^nriijio otirj mm stay for ~ *4r ffln about a week . Bomha^ l&amp;i vz mtinm-httgi rjj rrr+-trr-trt ^-1 mji i Miiiilir7 ^ a-Tpee-te/ (Sgd.) A. C. B. SYMON,Telegrajjhu^cklress: ' Hospitality, Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. v* All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted ' government hospitality fund. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l G.H.P.1836. 29th March, 1938. Dear Symon, I asked the Sultan whether he would like to have Sir Trenchard Fowle and Lady Fowle and Mr. and Mrs. J.G. Walton to Dinner hefore the Central Asian Society Receotion on the 6th April, and he seemed to he aelighted with the idea. So will you let them know that this is all right? A.C.B. Symon Esq., India OiTice. REdo. POL. 6*7 r. 3 OMAR 1938 INDIA OFFICETelegraphic Address: 'Hospitality, Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and tli^fc 41 owing reference quoted :- G.n.P.1886. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 28th March, 1938. Dear Symon, On the way up from Southampton I diplomatically asked the Sultan what he thought of Said Reute, and he said that he did not mind seeing him perhaps once, and thought it quite proper that he should he invited to the Government Dinner, hut heyond that he did not particularly wish to have much to do with him. I duly received your letter of the 25th March, with which you enclosed the questionnaire for the Sultan to study before being faced by the B.B.C. microphones at Waterloo, and it may interest you to know what he thought about it. He did not like the idea at all and was distinctly relieved when he heard that the B.B.C. arrangements had broken dovm, and that he would not have to speak. He enlisted my aid in concocting answers to the first four questions, but for some reason he would not say how long he was in the United States. He would say nothing in reply to the fifth and sixth questions. He said that the fifth question (whether he had kept in touch with Muscat) was a silly one, as of course, with telegraphs and wireless, he could be in instant touch whenever he wished, and he said that he could not decide offhand whether he would broadcast in Arabic. Yours sincerely, A.C.B. Symon, Esq., India Office. jyy e» A; fenclosure inSultan of Muscat to Sir \ubrey Metcalfe* Secy, to the Jovern- ment of India in the External Affairs Department dated the 16th ^ February 1938. From Sgid Bin laimur, My dear friend, After due compliments I have the honour to state that t received your D.O. letter No. F.381-N/37, dated the 19th November 1937 when we were in New Delhi enjoying the happy invi tation from our great friend the Government of Great Britain and ag^in thank you very much for the hospitality extended to us at that time. 2. We have great pleasure to thaik H.M's Government from the core of our hearts for the grand invitation which has now be-?n extended to us and which is an emblem of Great Britain’s frienship and sincerity. Yes, before our departure from India we had informed Hie Majesty’s Consul at ' uscat that we would leave America on the 23rd March by 'Oueen Mary* and will reach Great Britain on the 23th instant. We again inform you through this letter of our date of departure, as we did before through the above official, yesterday we too informed His Majesty’s Government in London of this f*ct through His Majesty’s ftnxxx- Ambassador in Washington. 3 . We look forward with great pleasure at the pros pect of seeing His Majesty the King Bmperor of Great Britain on reaching London. — ^ In the end we again thank you very much for what you have done for us. This letter has been written at Los Angeles in &lt;.Nh|ted States of America. Dated 15 Zil-Hijja 1356. ^ S 5 (doith February 1933). Yours sincerely, Sd/- Said Bin Taimur Sultan of Muscat A Oman. Sir \ubrey Metcalfe, External Affairs Department, New Delhi.twujuwikE i ' FILE GOFV INDIA OFFICE!» / / WHITSHAIX, S.W.l. 25th ¥?rch 1938. Dear Crankahaw, lAT^ahould he grateful if you will sound the 3ult*n regarding the Arabic broadcast. The present arrangement is th^t the B.B.C. will send a sound recording track to aterloo Fnd t if His Highness is agreeable, make a record of a short conversation in Arabic on the lines of the enclosed statement. The Sultan would not be inconvenienced in any way as the microphone would be brought to him while he is sitting in his c^r. I believe that Calvert of the B.B.C. is getting into touc* with you direct. Yours sincerely. ^ ^ CT . .fi. Usj or JS.F. 3. Crankshaw , C11G., VBft. , Government Hospitality ^hind,- C ILE GOHV 3UGGF.STED QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS FOR RECORDED CONY 'RS AT I ON WXW IUII.THE SULTAN OP MUSCAT AND OMAN f ON HIS ARRIVAL AT WATERLOO STATION ON MONDAY, 23th March, 1933. A* A. A. 3* A- Q. A* a, A. V7e ore delighted to welcome Your Highneas to thio country. We hope you have had e pleasant voyage across the Atlantic and that you are In good health. We hope that you have had an interesting visit to the United States of America. How long were you there? I understand that Your Highness travelled in the n Queen Mary”. What do you think of her? How long do you propose to stay in England? I suppose that Your Highness will have kept touch with Muscat and Oman during your absence - we hope that you have good news of your country. e hope that you will be so good as to accept an invitation to broadcast in Arabic from London - our listeners will be delighted to hear you and in particular your own people will be very pleased to hear your voice and to know that you are in good health and enjoying your visit. I hope to be able to come to Broadcasting House (on Friday, the 8th April ^ (during tny stay In Kngland; ^ 1 look forward to speaking by means of the radio from London to ray people and friends in Arab lands.Telegraphic Address: “Hospitality, Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted G.H.P.1886. Dear Symon, GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Thank you Tor your letter (P.Z.2042/38) of the 25th March with which you enclosed, copies of correspondence between Mr. Said Reute and Mr. Bertram Thomas, as well as a copy of a letter from yourself to Mr. Said Reute regarding an invitation to the Government Dinner to the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Yours sincerely A.C.B. Symon Esq. , India Office.Since our conversation this morning the attached letter from Mr. Said-Ruete has reached me. The previous correspondence regarding him is flagged at ’'A” in the hound volume. Major Crankshaw has confirmed that Mr. Said-Ruete received an invitation (apparently at the instigation of the Colonial Office) to the Government Dinner which was held in honour of the Sultan of Zanzibar on the occasion of his official visit in 1929. I suggest a draft letter to Dr. Bertram Thomas and if you agree v/e might await his answer before replying to Mr. Said-Ruete.Dr. Bertram Thomas, O.B.E. , CLM ftjU fuM i tu^k 'V/// 1 ?^ ' 4u ^ £&lt;aX^ ^ti\. Laj t^t' 1 &amp; T/c-#v»e-4t&gt;0 * x 3^ .lif . 3 You may remember that during the visit of Sultan Saiyid Taimur in 1928 you had some dealings with Hr. Rudolph Said-Ruete, a relation * • by marriage of the Muscat Royal family. Said-Ruete has evidently got «474a Wt 2253&lt;VPl44 10,000 9.37 IOP wind of the forthcoming visit, since he Ip has sent us a letter in which he asks to be invited to the official arrangements which take place in connection v/ith the Sultan’s visit. In order to assist us in dealing with this request, I should be most grateful if you would let me know what sort of relations, if any, were established between the old Sultan and Said-Ruete, and whether you consider he is the kind of person who might be invited, without causing offence to the young Sultan, to the dinner which is to be held at Lancaster House next Tuesday. We have ascertained from Crankshaw that Said-Ruete received an invitation to the Government Dinner which was held on the occasion of the Sultan of Zanzibar’s visit to England in jH? 1929. Colonel Gordon Loch (who, by the way, has now changed his name to/to Dalyell of the Binns) has agreed to look after the Sultan on this occasion^ and if you can add anything which might be useful to him in dealing with Said-Ruete vis-a-vis the young Sultan it would be very much appreciated. I have now ascertained that the 'Queen Mary' is scheduled to reach Southampton at 11.30 a.m. on the 28th March. 'X c. ,■ -■j TT ■ . 'ti ' fi a V' - £ ’ I'li.a ~ rill 5^ Telegraphic Address: 'Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted :- ^G.H.F.1886. S 8&lt;*&gt; GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 22nd March, 1938. ■ Dear Symon, This is to confirm v/hat I think you have already ■been told hy telephone, namely, that the only Function that was attended by Said-Ruete during the visit of the Sultan of Zanzibar was the Dinner given by the Government at Lancaster House.is.;? It is with reference to the coming visit of - His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and 'Oman to this country that I take the liberty to submit the following for favourable consideration. The Sultan is a relative of mine from my mother's side: she having been the daughter of SAID BIN SULTAN the Ruler of 'Oman and Zanzibar. SAID BIN SULTAN L Thuwainy Turky Saline / / (Emily Ruete) / / / Karub Faisal R. Said-Ruete / / KHALIFA Taimur (Zanzibar) / SAID ('Oman) Said Bin Taimur is up to the present personally unknown to me. I met His Father frequently when He was on an official visit (192:8) in London. He invested me (1929) with the first class of the Order of A1 Sa'idi, the wearing of which was granted to me by His Majesty the King in 1935. I entertained close and friendly relations with the Sultan of Zanzibar when He was here in 1929 and for the Coronation last year. He confered upon me the second class of the Brilliant Star (1930) and the title of 'Seyyid' (1932), thus recognizing me as a Member of the Dynast# I have written the Biography of my Grandfather (London, 1929) and ?jmJ R. Said-Ruete / India Office 19.III.38 2. and read a paper atont^The Al-Bu-Said Itynasty in Arabia and East Africa” (published in the Journal C.A.S. Vol.XVI / Part IV 1929) before a ^oint meeting of the Royal Asiatic Society and the Central Asian Soc. in 1929 when the Sultan of Zanzibar was the distinguished guest. I read a similar paper before the Ligue Orientale in Cairo (1930) and the In ternational Congress of Orientalists at Leiden (1931). I enclose a reprint from the Journal C.A.S. (Vol.JCVIII / Part II, 1931) giving 'Dates and References of the History of the A1 Bu Said Dynasty” as compiled by myself. Under the circumstances as stated above I shall feel obliged if I should be invited to the official arrangements which will take place in connection with the Sultan’s visit. Through the midium of the Colonial Office - where I am known - I received invitation &lt;b| from the Government Hospitality Fund to arrangements made for the Sultan of Zanzibar. I may mention that I am seventy years of age, by birth a German, but naturalized in this country - where I live since 1910 - in 1934.P.3930/28, INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 1st September 1928. My dear Sir Percy Cox, I am sorry to have been so long in writing further to you about Ivlr.Said Ruete. I am now desired to say that we think that the best answer to give to him would be that which you yourself suggest, viz. that His Majesty’s Government see no prima facie reason to interest themselves. We will mention the question privately to Thomas. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) P.J.Patrick. Major General Sir Percy Cox, GCMG., GCIE., etc., Woodlands, Clapham, Beds.FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 30th August, 1928. SECRET. Dear Laithwaite, I return herewith the correspondence about Mr. Rudolf Said-Ruete, which you enclosed in your letter No. P.3930/28 of August 28. We do not appear to have had very many dealings with this man since the war, but I enclose a note giving such information as appears from our archives. You will see that it does not amount to much. Yours sincerely, (SD.) H.J.Seymour. J. G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office.In June 1918, while consorting in Switzerland with certain disaffected Germans Ruete got into touch with our Legation with a view to mediation. He also requested that a journey to England might be facilitated as he wished to send his son to Eton. Early in 1919 he published a volume of 'Politische Korrespondenzen” to which however no importance was attached either here or abroad. March 1919 he asked to be received by H.M. Minister at Berne ”to make certain statements which would be calculated to clear up the situation between Great Britain and Germany and thus safeguard the interests of both parties’ 1 . He was not encouraged. Prom 1919 we have no record of him until January 1926, when, v/riting from 36 Cheniston Gardens, Kensington he asked that he might be informed of the addresses of Sir Claud MacDonald and Sir Charles Euan-Smith, if they were still alive. There appears to be nothing more recent about RueteP.3930/28 Secret. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 28th August 1S28. Dear Seymour, I venture to trouble you about the correspondence which I enclose in original about Mr. Rudolf Said-Ruete. From the papers enclosed you will see that there is nothing very definite against Mr.Said-Ruete, but before we reply to Sir Percy Cox, I am desired to ask whether the Foreign Office have any information as to his recent activities. If they have not, our answer will probably be that His Majesty^ Government see no prima facie reason to interest themselves, but we shall, of course, take steps to put Thomas, the Sultan’s Wazir, an fait with the position. I should be very grateful if you could, without in convenience, let me have an early reply as Thomas is expected to call here at the beginning of next wee* and it would be a convenient opportunity to talk the case over with him. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) J.G.Laithwaite. H.J.Seymour, Esq., C.M.G., Foreign Office.Rudolf SAID-RUBTE. Before the war Said-Ruete who was then living in London was ?n active member of the Anglo-German 'B'riendsnip Committee, and in 1904 he became a Fellow of the Royal Asiatic Society. His name appeals frequently in the India Office records of negotiations with the German Government immediately preceding the war for the settlement of the outstanding questions in the Middle East - the Baghdad Railway, etc. Herr von Kuhlmann, in May, 1913, warned our Foreign Office against him, describing him as 'a perfectly honest if somewhat garrulous individual” who was in the habit of writing mischievous articles on Middle Eastern affairs in the German press. The Secretary of the Political Department, India Office, also recorded, in an official minute, his opinion that the r$le, in these negotiations, of SAID-RUETE, appeared to be that of a mischief maker. SAID-RUETE had previously obtained considerable knowledge of Middle Eastern affairs as Manager of the Cairo branch of the Deutsche Orient Bank, to which post he had been appointed by M.Gutmann, Manager of the Head Office in Berlin. In July, 1^14 , he and his wife went to Switzerland, where they appear to have remained until 1921. In November, 1915, Mrs.Said-Ruete received permission for a monthly allowance of £100 to be made to her out of her property in this country. In April, 1916, SAID-RUETE wrote to Sir William Slaughter urgently appealing that he (Slaughter) should discuss peace terms with official persons in the United Kingdom. He forwarded then, and on subsequent occasions, copies of the Swiss Magazine ”Wissen und Leben” to which he was in the habit of contributing pacific articles. Ruete was also a contributo: to a pro-German organ known as the 'New Zurich Journal”. In June, 1917, he was reported from Berne as Promoter of the British/■r% British Progressive Club in Zurich whose leader was a notorious Hungarian spy named Moskxwitz. The British Progressive Club was suspected by the British authorities in Switzerland of being used as a cover for smuggling into Anglo-Saxon countries the ideas held by the German pacifist party, i.e. an immediate peace accompanied by the abandonment by the Allies of the contention that Germany was responsible for the beginning of the war. On the 27th June, 1917, on the strength of representations made byM.1.5, the Secretary, Trading with the Snemy Branch of the Treasury, wrote stating that the authority previously given to Parr*s Bank to send Mrs.Said- Ruete £100 a month had been withdrawn. In June 1918 it was disclosed that Said-Ruete was working for a section of the British S.S. in Switzerland and the payments were resumed at their request. Some months later this Service reported his work not to be satisfactory, but the allowance was not disturbed. A Berne report on November 1918 stated that Ruete was in close relations with Erzberger. Erzberger was an avowed pacifist and the head of the Centre Catholic Party in the Reichstag whom he had met several times during the formers stay in Switzerland, and from whom he received certain instructions. Said-Ruete was also in constant touch with many of the most important political and financial personalities in Germany. It was moreover reported that on October 28th 1918 Ruete had written Erzberger a letter in which he laid special emphasis on the necessity - according to him the pressing necessity - of ccmpletely and rapidly reorganising German propaganda Service in German-Switzerland, and of substituting for other officials certain members of the German Diplomatic and Consular Staffs who had either compromised themselves or became antipathetic in their views, notably the German Minister/Minister Romberg and the German Consul at Zurich. He then suggested that it would be an excellent plan to increase and renew Germany^ prestige, if the charge of the Imperial Legation at Berne were entrusted to an entirely different man in whom Switzerland could have entire confidence, preferably Erzberger himself. Said-Ruete also suggested in this letter the discreet recall of other German functionaries in Berne, and ended cis communication by emphasising the great interest attached to the re-organisation - not only in Switzerland, out also in other foreign countries - of various diplomatic or consular positions and of the economic organisations which would be called to play a very important part in the post-bellum struggle -'these positions to be henceforward filled by personalities known to be entirely trustworthy and having the same political sentiments as the new Government.' The war ended shortly after this and nothing more was heard by us of Ruete until November, 1925, when we ascertained that he was on sufficiently intimate terms with Herr Albert Dufour-Eeronce, Councillor of the German 'Embassy, to introduce him to sn individual for whom he was anxious to obtain the post of Legal Adviser to the Embassy.WOODLANDS, 3930/28. CLAPHAM, BEDS. July 26th, 1928. My dear Patrick, Would you kindly advise me, after taking instructions from your Chief if necessary, in the following matter. There is living in England (36 Cheniston Gardens, London, W.8) one Rudolf Said-Ruete, a German subject by nationality, married to a niece of Lord Melchett. Curious to relate his mother was either the sister, or the daughter, I am not sure which, of Sultan Saiyid Saeed of Muscat, great grandfather of the present Sultan, who is Taimur-bin Faisal-bin Turki-bin Saeed. She was sent to Europe and married Said-Ruete, apparently a pure German, in Berlin, where she lived and died. The Said-Ruetes h.-:ve a son aged about 24 who is in America, and has taken American nationality, and a daughter about 20 who lives with them. Said-Ruete sought an introduction to me two or three years ago owing to my being familiar with Oman and the Sultan’s family; they are quite nice people and he is proud of his connection with the Muscat family, has a good library of works, in all languages, relating to Oman, and is at present engaged on a history of his family (the Muscat family). Now I come to the point. Now that the Sultan of Muscat, Saiyid Taimur, is about to visit England, Said-Ruete is anxious to pay his respects to him and get to know him, but fears that either H.M.Government might be suspicious of him as a German subject, with possible political designs to further, or that Saiyid Taimur might hesitate to hobnob with him, being a German subject, lest Government should disapprove. He accordingly asked me as a friend if I could sound the Powers That Be privately, and perhaps smooth the way for him. I like the man myself, and heve no reason at// . «£ at all to think that he has any other designs than to get to know his 'rcya-l' relative, but should be glad, if the India Office see no objection, to let him know that, for instance, he is welcome to cultivate his relative or, that H.M.*s Government see no prima facie reason to interest themselves. In point of fact I should say that Thomas, who will be bear-leading Saiyid Taimur, would be able to look after His Highness vis-a-vis his cousin. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) P.Z.Cox.TOASTS! / Speech delivered by His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and ‘Oman at the Government Dinner on the 29th March 1938. Lord Zetland,my Lords and Gentlemen l I should like to thank Your Lordship for the kind words in which you have proposed my health , and you,Gentlemen, for honouring the Toast in this way. And I should like to say how much X appreciate the welcome that X have received. As you Know, the Sultans of Muscat and ‘Oman have been in treaty relations with the British Government for more than a century , and I welcome this opportunity of visiting Great Britain. I hope tomorrow to have the great pleasure of seeing His Majesty King George and to enter into a personal friendship which I trust will endure. As I said, the Governments of Gfceat Britain and 'Oman have been long in treaty relations , but I would claim more than treaty relations,relations of true friendship and real understanding. Your Lordship has referred to certain help which I have been able to give and I should like to assure you that I am very glad to have been of assistance to H.M. s Government. And I on my side am deeply appreciative of the help and assistance extended by His Majesty's Government from time to time to the Sultans of Muscat and ‘Oman which the Saidi dynasty will not forget. I hope that these happy relations will be further strength ened by the personal friendship which I now have the privilege of forming with you all. t rrr»oo+iv mv iournev and am sure that I shall enjoy my stay in tms country. I will close with renewed thanks and wish you all good health and happiness. ■r-JMr . t n ■ y fl+4***~* ti. Ul t „JUu ut^J i ^ ™ ~U4 f*^r .’ J ‘'y./&gt;Lv^s _ U~j Kf . J The Private Secretary has asked for suggestions for the Secretary of State’s speech at the Government Dinner on Tuesday. I have not been able to discover any notes regarding the Bahrein Dinner speech. The following suggestions may be useful:- (1) A reference to the Sultan’s recent State visit to India (during November last) and to his subsequent tour^which included visits to Singapore, Japan and the United States of America). The Sultan has been to India before and in fact received part of his education in that country; but this is his first tour abroad and his first visit to England His father, who abdicated in his favour in 1932, paid an official visit to England in 1928. (2) Mention might be made (a) of the Sultan’s helpful^^generous attitude in regard to the request made by H.M.G. (in 1935) for facilities for r '-7 a naval rest base at Khor Kwai; (b) to the helpful co-operation of the Sultan in regard to the establishment of ^—Pqya.1 Air ^’orce landihg grounds i-n Muscat t er-r-Pt 0 ry.;— and „ (c) to the Sultan’s willing co-operation and assistance in connection with the establishment of the Empire Air Service to India. The Muscat enclave of Gwadur i 0. (A 7a*«^f&lt;lijgr^phic Address : ' Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. P / -» • X-.V i ,C4] 5 Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, 938 SW1 March, 1938. G.H.F.1886. x Dear Symon, .j.0 |(? I enclose proof of the menu and toast list for the Dinner to the Sultan of Muscat on the 29th March, and shall he glad to have your Secretary of Stated approval - or otherwise. We have not yet discussed the question of the toast list, and it may he that you do not wish to have formal toasts, in v/hich case perhaps you will let me know. Yours sincerely,P. Z. 2040/38 'S’V Secretary, Political Department (External), Our contract with Durrant T s Press Cutting Agency covers Press cuttings relating to Indian affairs only, and special arrangements are therefore necessary to obtain Press cuttings regarding the visit of the Sultan of Muscat. Two complete sets are required, one for permanent record after circulation to you, and another from which a selection can be made for His Highness. Durrant T s charges for the sets would be as follows:- Two guineas for 100 cuttings Pour u ' 250 ' Six ' ' 400 ' It is difficult to estimate what the total cost would be for the period of the Sultan’s visit, but I imagine that it would not exceed £6. I shall be glad to have authority, as soon as possible, to make tne necessary arrangements with Durrant’s. (Sd) A.H. JOYCE. 24th March, 1938. Mr. '.yalt on. May this be approved, please? (Sd) A. C.B. SYMON) 24.3. As proposed, J.C.W. 24.3. M r. Joyce, Proposal approved by Mr. V/alton (see above) (Sd) A. C.B. SYMON. 24. 3.Minute Paper. . z. ih-,, ~ Yt 1 ; Q t' jf , political Department. 2i- , S’ v Please see the telegran below from H.M.Ambassador at Washington regarding the Sultan of Muscat’s official visit to Washington. It will be observed that the ceremony on the Sultan’s arrival was the same as for the Sovernor-General of Canada (see Washington despatch Vo. 292 of IQ.?? - ^lag A). The Sultan was apparently met '?t the Union station by (among others) the American Secretary of State and was escorted to the White House by a war strength troop of cavalry. This is confirmed by the report from the New York Sun, flagged at B. 2. His Highness is travelling to England by the S. S. ”Q,ueen Mary” which is scheduled to reach Southampton at 11.3C a.m. on the 3&amp;th March, and he should reach London about 3 p.m. on that day. At Southampton he will be welcomed by Major Crankshaw, Secretary of the Government Hospitality Fund, on behalf of the Minister in Charge of Government Hospitality, and it is for consideration whether, having regard to the honours accorded to him on his arrival at Washington, a member of the Government (perhaps Lord Stanley if his engagements Pi 'k* fa CsdU fjbti* Jin** bHf&gt;dr^ U'~C * ^ /f****^~ *?■ //u ^*7 i/Aitf) %i \b :s!) :i 9 permit) should be at the station to meet him when he reaches London. In this connection it must be remembered that His Highness may visit Italy on his way back to ‘‘At y Muscat and it may perhaps be assumed that the Italian authorities will not lose the opportunity of feting /***+# ihe Sultan’s visit to Japan was private, and there was no ceremony. In the U.S.A, he was received with great ceremony at Washington, where he was the guest of 5000 7 35■* the U.S. Govt. Last January an enquiry was received from the Sultan while he was in Japan as to whether a Government representative would meet him at Southampton, He was informed in reply that he would be officially welcomed at Southampton by a Government representative, who would wait upon him at the ship, but that there would be no ceremony. As regards his reception at Y/aterloo, we cannot, of course, compete with the U.S. Govt., and it is to be hoped that the Sultan will not be expecting any elaborate ceremony. It was contemplated that he would be met by representatives of the Secretary of State and the India Office (not the Foreign Office, as it is not desired to emphasise the foreign status of the Sultan), by Colonel / Dalyell, and no doubt Sir T, Fowle, who will arrive in this country on 27th March; but in view of the comparison with Washington, where he was received by Mr. Hull, perhaps the suggestion at A above might be considered//-s UrulWJ / -t- h 0 jD i S i']ilBUl 1 IGi'-l. Decode. Sir R. Lirdsay (Washington; D. o r 4:6 p.tn. R e 10. DO a.mo Ro.104. (R). March 7th 1958. March 7th 1958. March 8th 1958. ^ i /our celegram j-iO. loo. Ceremony on Sultan’s arrival was the same as for Governor General of Canada (see my oesnatch i.o.292 of 1957). He stayed at a hotel. Lunch at the white House, dinners given hy Secretary of State and Under Secretary of State. These were attended in turn by some cabinet ministers, a few heads of missions. Chairman of Senate and House, Foreign affairs Committee, State Department and other officials. Visits were paid to Federal Bureau of Investigation (G men), Scotland Yard, Cavalry Headquarters where lunch was served and exhibition of drill performed, and Mount Vernon. I understand Sultan expressed himself as being interested in everything that was suggested to him. His journey through Southern States was quietly dropped owing to colour question. So far : I have no information on political and commercial aspects of the visit. Sultan is now in Hew iork.No. 898 SldBAatr/ Oovc-rnor-G^ neral of Cfctt&amp;d*, acco:a^unied by l^dy Tweedsazuir and his staff, Arrived in hlngton on an official visit to the resident on the 30th March. I enclose co lea of the programs* giving in detail the ar ang^ment® made : or Mia Excellency. The party was ;aet at the r*d Iway station by the Gt-n^dian Minister ana i^ady «urier, with the staff of his legation, and by jriyeelf accompanied by the Counsellor and the M&amp;val /ttfeche to this ijabuSc/ with their ladiea, &lt;-na by the First ecretary. The death fricotn Minister . nd Mro. Close were also present. n escort of a troop of oovelry and fo;r armoured cura accompanied the official party on the drive from the station to the -hite Ho ae. £• You will see that Included in the arrangeiaenta ect out in pragraMd® was a visit to both Mouses of Congress during the afternoon of the let pril. Extract, froa the Con.pes ional Record containing the speeches delivered by Lord Tweedamuir on this occasion are enclosed. 3. As/ The Hight honourable / nthony jiden, M«r #f i.3. As thJU was th# first occasion of a formal visit to this country of a Governor- Qoncral, it b« useful to re corn that His Bxc liency wore morning arose for his d&amp;ytims eng^gemrntB including hie arrival, except during ihe momlngs of the 31st \5v,rch and the l«t A;ril» when he wore uniform. Hie staff we^re, however, in full uniform for all these engagemeita* I ahoild add that I was invited to tiie o fici^l .uncheon end dinners given in His ^Uceli.ency , a h nour; also th t, availing myself of the authority conveyed to me in the letter of the S*4th nogusit, 1^54, (A 63^0/566/46&gt; I intimated to the State tepartnent that I was able to forego any claim to precedence over ix&gt;rd fweedsiauir for the occasion of his visit. 4# The visit a, je&amp;ro to h ve h^en a co^iete success, althojgh I thinh it was generally recognised that it w * of no i oeuiate political significance. 3* X am sending a copy of this despatch to the High CamutiB&amp;ioaer for the united Kingdom in Canada• I hfcve the honour to be with the highest respect Sir, Y &gt; »r moet obedient h imble servant, 8 . C. llftiitlAY/fZ(* 5:00 p.m. - 2 - Tuesday , 'llarch 50 Their Excellencies will reach the Capital at 5:00 p.m. They will he formally received at the Union Station by the Secretary of State and Mrs. Hull, the Canadian Minister and Lady ,,iarler and members of the staff of the Canadian Legation, the Chief of Staff, the Chief of Naval Operations, the Commandant of the Marine Corps, the Assistan Secretary of State, the Honorable Marvin H. McIntyre, the American Minister to Canada Mrs. Armour, the Chief and the Assistant Chief of the Division of Western European Affairs, the Commandant of the Washington Navy Yard, and the Commanding General of the Washington Provisiona Brigade. After the presentations and exchange of greetings on the platform, The Party will pass through a double line of marines and sailors formed from the train shed to the entrance to The President’s R e *' ception Room. After passing through The^ President s Reception Room, The Party will stop at the street entrance, where the Army Band will render the Na tional Anthems. Following the taking of photographs Their Excellen cies and Party will then enter motorcars provided by the White House and by the Department of State, and, escorted by a war-strength troop of cavalry, will drive by way of Constitution Avenue to the White House where they will be received by the President and Mrs. Roosevelt. An informal tea at the White House. Dinner at the White House. Wednesday T March 31 His Excellency and The Official Party will.leave the White House to visit Fort Myer and Arlington National Cemetery. 10:30 a.rn. His Excellency and The Official Party will arrive at Fort Myer where a squadron of cavalry will be waiting to act as escort. Salutes appropriate to IIis°Excellency 1 s rank will be fired. Imme diately after reviewing the cavalry, His Excellency will depart for Arlington Cemetery. 10:15 a.m. 11:00 a.m. a.m. His Excellency will arrive at the Tomb of the Un known Soldier where he will lay a wreath. Appro priate honors will bo rendered. His Excellency will lay a wreath at the Canadian Cross, where appropriate honors will be rendered. The Official Party will visit the Lee House at Arlington. The Party will return to the White House.~3~ A /^\ 1 ; 15 p.m. Their Excellencies will he the guests of the Sec retary of State and Mrs. Hull at a luncheon at the Sulgrave Club. '2:45 p.m. Their Excellencies will leave the Sulgraye Club to embark at Alexandria on the Presidential Yacht POTOMAC to visit Mt. Vernon 4:15 p.m. Their Excellencies will arrive at Mount Vernon. The President will greet them at the dock and will accompany them to the Tomb of G-eorge Washing ton where the Governor General will place a wreath. The President will accompany Their Excellencies to the house at Mount Vernon and upon the conclu sion of the visit will return to Washington with the Governor General by motor. 8:00 p.m. The President and Mrs. Roosevelt will entertain at a State Dinner in honor of Their Excellencies. Thursday, April 1 9:15 a.m. Their Excellencies will leave the White House by motor to visit the United States Naval Academy at Annapolis. 10:30 a.m. The Party will arrive at the Naval Academy, where His Excellency will be received by the Commandant of the Navy Academy and will receive a salute. Thereafter His Excellency will review the midship men and will deliver a brief address. 11:50 a.m. Leave Annapolis for the White House. 1;00 p.m. The Governor General will be the guest of honor at luncheon given by the British Ambassador at the British Embassy. 1:15 p.m. The Lady Tweedsrnuir and Mrs. Roosevelt will attend a luncheon given in their honor by the Secretary of Labor. 3;00 p.m. His Excellency will leave the British Embassy to visit Congress, where he will be received by the appropriate officials. 5:00 p.m. Tea at the White House. 8:15 p.m. The Governor General and the Lady Tweedsmuir will attend a dinner at the Canadian Legation given by the Canadian Minister. Shortly before leaving the White House for the Legation Their Excellencies will make their farewells to the Pre-sident and Mrs. Roosevelt. Following the dinner Their Excellencies will pro ceed directly from the Legation to the Union Station to begin their return journey.The Official Party will be accompanied to the Canadian frontier by the Honorable Richard Southgate, Chief of Protocol, Captain W* R. Purnell, American Naval Aide to the Governor General, and Lieutenant Colonel John A. Crane, American Military Aide to the Governor General,Congressional r?eoor^ Apr I, 193'/. VlSli. OF GOVERNOR GENERAL OF CANADA Tt TB^ 1 aNATE The VICE PRESIDENT. The Chair asks the indulgence if the Senate for a moment while he makes a statement. The Chair is advised by the State Department that His Er rillency the Grovernor General of Canada will probably Vi-..* the Senate end of the Capitol about 3:15 p. m. today and, if agreeable to the Senate, will probably desire to come to ’che Senate Chamber. It is the opinion of the Chair, in view of that situation, that it might be advisable to appoint a committee to arrange the matter. So, without objection, the Chair would like to appoint the Senator from Arkansas [Mr. Robinson], the Senator from Nevada [Mr. Pittman], and the Senator from Oregon [Mr. McNary] as the commit tee. Is there objection? The Chair hears none, and the committee is appointed.k k THE GOVERNOR GENERAL OF CANADA Mr. RAYBURN. Mr. Speaker, I ask unanimous consent to proceed for 1 minute. The SPEAKER. Is there objection to the request of the gentleman from Texas? There was no objection. Mr. RAYBURN. Mr. Speaker, there is in the city, as we all know, a distinguished citizen of a neighboring and a friendly country, the Governor General of Canada. I think it fitting and proper that the Members should have the privilege of meeting our distinguished guest. I therefore move that the House stand in recess subject to the call of the Chair. to meet the Members of the House of Representatives as they are presented by the gentleman from New York [Mr. Bloom 1. His Excellency the Governor General of Canada stood In the well of the House and was presented to the Members individually by Mr. Bloom. RECESS The motion was agreed to; accordingly (at 3 o’clock and 39 minutes p. m.) the House stood in recess subject to the call of the Chair. During the recess the following occurred: The SPEAKER. The gentleman from New York [Mr. Bloom] acting chairman of the Committee on Foreign Af fairs, and the gentleman from New York [Mr. Fish] will es cort our distinguished visitor to the rostrum. The Governor General of Canada was escorted to the Speaker’s rostrum by Mr. Bloom and Mr. Fish. The SPEAKER. I have the honor of presenting to the Members of the House our distinguished guest, His Excel lency the Governor General of Canada. [Applause.] His Excellency the Governor General of Canada. Mr. Speaker and Members of the House of Representatives, this is a great honor, for which I am most sincerely grateful. I have just had the privilege of being received by the Senate, the upper House. I belong now to the upper house at home, but I have been inside only once and am not very familiar with it as yet. I have come now to a House, in the British Isles the equivalent of which I sat for 8 happy years, and I feel very much at home. [Applause.] The Governor General, as you know, gentlemen, spends his time walking on very thin ice. It is very hard for him to express an opinion on any subject which is remotely con nected with politics, and as nearly everything is connected in some way or other with politics he is wise if he keeps silent. [Laughter and applause.] But there is one thing he can say freely and with a whole heart. He can express his gratitude to the American peo ple for the pleasure they have given him on this visit and his admiration and affection for your great country. I have known America now for many years. I have the privilege of the friendship of many Americans; in fact, I can say I have always regarded America as my second fatherland. This visit has been one of unalloyed pleasure. I have renewed many old friendships and made, I hope, some new ones. I have visited some of the famous places in your environs which I had not seen for many years, and I have renewed my acquaintance with your beautiful city, a city which I think will very soon be one of the noblest capi tals in the world. I have been favored with wonderful spring weather, I have no doubt, through the brilliant organ ization of your Postmaster General. [Laughter and ap plause.] I would like to say to you one thing, and one thing only: Your Nation and mine are today in a special sense the guardians of that great form of government which we call democracy, and of which I think the truest definition is a true mixture of law and liberty. Therefore, I regard my visit to you this afternoon as a culminating step in a most memorable experience, for I have been admitted into the very inner shrine, the focus, the center, the power-house of your great democracy, your great free Government. I am proud of the privilege, and I offer you my sincerest thanks. [Applause.] The SPEAKER. The Chair may say that His Excellency will stand in the well of the House and will be delighted 8• f 1937 CONGRESSIONAL RECORD—SENATE 3843 Mr. GUFFEY. Mr. President, the four amendments I have TT^Nd are clarifying amendments which have been suggested by the Treasury Department to make the bill easier of interpretation in connection with the tax provi sions. They are not offered on behalf of the committee, but entirely at the request of the Treasury Department. Mr. KING. The amendment just proposed does not change the obligation? Mr. QUFFEY. It does not change the obligation at all. Mr. BARKLEY. It is merely in connection with the tax. Mr. GUFFEY. Yes; it is in connection with the tax. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The question is on agree ing to the amendment offered by the Senator from Penn sylvania. The amendment was agreed to. / The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The next amendment of fered by the Senator from Pennsylvania will be stated. The Chief Qlerk. On page 40, line 14, it is proposed to strike out “secfton 600 of the Revenue Act of 1926” and in sert “title IV of the Revenue Act of 1932, as Amended.” The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The amendment offered by the Senator from Pennsylvania is to a committee amend ment which has heretofore been agreed to. Without ob jection, the vote whereby the amendment was agreed to will be reconsidered. Th,e Chair hears no objection. The ques tion is on the amendment offered by the Senator from Penn sylvania to the amendment reported by the committee. The amendment to the amendment was agreed to. The amendment as aipended was agreed to. The PRESIDENT pro. tempore. The clerk will state the next amendment offered by the Senator from Pennsylvania. The Chief Clerk. On page 52, after line 8, it is proposed to insert a new paragraph, as follows: (h) The term “United Stastes” when used in a geographical sense includes only the States, the Territories of Alaska, Hawaii, and the District of Columbia. and The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The question is on agree ing to the amendment offered by the Senator from Penn sylvania. The amendment was agreed to. Mr. GUFFEY. Mr. President, I offer another amendment in behalf of the senior Senator from Alabama LMr. Black] and the junior Senator from Alabama [Mr. Bankhead]. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The amendment will be stated. The Chief Clerk. At the end of section 5 (a), on page 33, after line 8, it is proposed to add the following: No producer shall by reason of his acceptance or reinstatement of membership become liable for breach of any contract the per formance of which may be invalidated as a result of such ac ceptance or reinstatement. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The question is on agree ing to the amendment offered by the Senator from Penn sylvania. Mr. BORAH. Mr. President, will the Senator from Penn sylvania explain, in a word, what the effect of that amend ment will be? Mr. GUFFEY. I was asked to offer the amendment by the two Senators from Alabama. I have not had time to consider the amendment carefully, but I think if it may he read again its effect will be understood. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The amendment will be again stated. The amendment was again stated. Mr. GUFFEY. The amendment, if adopted, will protect the producer from any action against him from the in validation of a contract. That is the object of the amend- J ment. 1 Mr. BARKLEY. And would protect him from the auto matic invalidation by reason of the acceptance of the terms of this act? Mr. MINTON. Mr..President, does not the Senator from Idaiho understand that that would be the law in any event, whether any such provision were inserted or not? Mr. BORAH. That would be my understanding, and so I did not see any necessity for the amendment. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. ^ The question is on agree ing to the amendment offered by the Senator from Penn sylvania. The amendment was agreed to. ~ RECEPTION OF THE GOVERNOR GENERAL OF CANADA Mr. ROBINSON (at 3 o’clock and 10 minutes p. m.). Mr. President, the Vice President, some hours ago, announced that a very distinguished visitor will call at the Senate this afternoon, the Governor General of Canada. In order that Senators may have an opportunity of meeting him infor mally, and that he may be permitted to express his appre ciation of the opportunity afforded him, I now move that the Senate take a recess until called to order by the Chair. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The question is on the motion of the Senator from Arkansas. The motion was unanimously agreed to; and the Senate took a recess subject to the call of the Presiding Officer. The Senate being in recess. His Excellency Lord Tweedsmuir, Governor General of Canada, escorted by the committee appointed by the Vice President, consisting of Mr. Robinson, Mr. Pittman, and Mr. McNary, entered the Senate Chamber, accompanied by the Honorable Sir Ronald Lindsay, the British Ambassador Ex traordinary and Plenipotentiary accredited to the United States; the Honorable Sir Herbert Marler, Canadian Minis ter accredited to the United States; Hon. Norman Armour, American Minister to Canada; Hon. Julius C. Holmes, As sistant Chief of Protocol, United States; Mr. Redfern, secre tary to the Governor General; Col. Willis O’Connor, aide to the Governor General, Captain Purnell, American naval aide; Colonel Crane, American military aide; Lieutenant Rivers- Smith, aide to the Governor General; Captain Campbell- Preston, aide to the Governor General; Mr. Richey, secretary to the Canadian Legation; and Mr. Spruks, of the State Department. The Governor General of Canada having been seated to the right of the Vice President and the distinguished visitors accompanying him having been escorted to places assigned them on the Senate floor on the left side of the Chamber, The VICE PRESIDENT said: Senators, I have the privi lege of presenting to you His Excellency the Governor Gen eral of Canada. [Prolonged applause, Senators rising.] The Governor General of Canada. Mr. Vice President and Senators, you have done me today a great kindness and a great honor for which I am deeply grateful. This is the culminating step in what has been a most memorable visit. I have had the opportunity, in a place I used to know well, of renewing many old friendships and making some new ones. I am told, Senators, that I am supposed to say something to you today. A Governor General is in a very curious posi tion. Once I was like you; I was a free and independent politician. [Laughter.] I could liberate my mind on any subject, anywhere, at any time, at any length I pleased. I had an official character, and, like you, I had also a private character. I need not remind you that a man’s official char acter does not do justice as a rule to the stalwart virtues which he possesses as a private citizen. [Laughter.] I remember in my own country on the Scottish border there was an old minister who once a month thought it his duty to deliver a sermon upon the terrors of hell, when he fairly dangled his congregation over the abyss; but, being a humane man, he liked to finish on a gentler note. He used to conclude thus: “Of course, my friends, ye understand that the Almighty is compelled to do things in his official .capacity that he would scorn to do as a private individual.” [Laughter.] Senators, I am in the unfortunate position now of having no private capacity, but only an official one. I am unable to express my views upon any public question of any real importance, at least not for publication. But there is one subject on which even a Governor General may express his views, and that is my gratitude for your kindness here and my admiration for your great country. I have known America for many years. I have had the privilege of the I ii 1\ A. Congress ional tL. / 3844 CONGRESSIONAL RECORD—SENATE April 1. friendship of many of your citizens. I have long been a lover of your history. I am quite sure that no American steeped in European history gets more of a thrill from Westminster Abbey than I get from Valley Forge and the Wilderness and the Shenandoah. I have always believed that the secret of the future of civilization lies in the hands of the English-speaking people. I want these great nations not only to speak the same lan guage but to think along the same lines, for that is the only true form of cooperation and friendship. I think that far too much is said about my country and yours being alike. It is much more important that they should be different. The strength of an alliance between two nations lies in the fact that they should be complementary to each other and each give the other something new. Therefore, I am always inclined to rejoice when I find great and real differences between your country and mine. But I think, when that has been said, that we have a wonder ful basis for keeping together, especially on two grounds. In the first place, we have the same definition of what constitutes greatness and goodness in human character. We admire the same qualities. We give our admiration and affection to the same type of leadership. Will anyone deny that your great men and our great men are singularly alike at bottom? In the second place, we and you have the same tasks before us. I am especially struck in Canada to discover that nearly all our problems are paralleled by yours. We have the same economic problems. We have the same problems in the drought areas in the West. We have very similar constitu tional problems and the task of harmonizing local interests and rights with national interests and duties. Senators, I cannot imagine a greater bond between two nations than that they should engage in the same tasks and for the same purposes. ' As I have said, I regard this afternoon as the culminating pleasure of a most delightful visit, and I offer you my sin- cerest thanks for your welcome today. [Prolonged applause, Senators rising.] Mr. ROBINSON. Mr. President, I suggest that the Gov ernor General of Canada stand in the area in front of the Vice President’s desk in order that Senators and others may have the opportunity of greeting him personally. The VICE PRESIDENT. If it is the pleasure of His Excel lency, we shall be very glad to have that done. The Governor General of Canada advanced to the area in front of the Vice President’s desk, accompanied by the com mittee of Senators and by the Secretary of the Senate, and greeted the Members of the Senate as they were introduced to him by Mr. Pittman. The Governor General of Canada and the distinguished visitors accompanying him were then escorted from the Chamber. The VICE PRESIDENT (at 3 o’clock and 33 minutes p. m.) called the Senate to order, and legislative session was resumed. Mr. ROBINSON. Mr. President, during the recess of the Senate the Governor General of Canada appeared in the Senate Chamber, greeted Senators and others, and made an interesting and illuminating statement. I ask unanimous consent that the proceedings relating to the visit of the Governor General to the Senate Chamber, particularly in cluding his remarks, be incorporated in the Record. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. Is there objection? The Chair hears none, and it is so ordered. REGtrtAflON OF BITUMINOUS-COAL INDUSTRY The Senate resumed consideration of the^Wll (H. R. 4985) to regulate interstate commerce in bttuminous coal, and for other purposes. Mr. AUSTIN.!!*!*.' President, I offer the amendment which I send tqJJar^esk. The'PRESIDENT pro tempore. The amendment will be The Chief Clerk. On page 31, after line 5, and before section 4-A, it is proposed to insert the following (m) Anything herein + o the contrary notwithstanding, no pro- » driver of bituminous coal shall be required to sell the coal pro duced by him at prices higher than will be sufficient to realize for suc^ producer the aggregate cost of production and sale of such coal/ M^ AUSTIN. Mr. President, briefly stated, this amend- ment^js designed to protect the consumer. Under, the bill the prices which each individual producer is required to chargeVor his coal are to be based not upon his own indi vidual opsts, but upon the average of the costs of all the other producers, including his own costs, in the minimum- price area*, N. R. A. statistics show that in the geographical area rouglUy corresponding to minimum price area no. 1 under the yinson bill, the weighted average cost was ap proximately $1.85 per ton, whereas the individual producers’ costs varied from approximately $1.52 to $3.18 per ton. This bill would require a producer whose cost was $1.52 to sell his coal on the $1.85 basis simply because other producers in his area have higher costs than he. Thus&lt; by this bill, the consumers of coal will be deprived of the benefit of low- cost production by the efficient producer, and wil be saddled with the higher costs of the inefficient producer. Much more could be said on the subject; but I realize that the time is short, and I therefore have cut the explana tion short. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The question is on agree ing to the amendment offered by the Senator from Vermont. The amendment was rejected. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The clerk will state the next amendment offered by the Senator from Vermont. The Chief Clerk. On page 34, after line 12, it is proposed to insert the following: The code shall be declared by the commission to be, and shall become, operative whenever acceptances for membership therein shall have been received from the producers of 66% percent of the _ aggregate tonnage of bituminous coal determined by the com mission to be subject to the provisions of this act. Mr. AUSTIN. Mr. President, briefly stated, the objective of this amendment is to introduce into the proposed act the . element of consent of the governed, which is, I believe, a fundamental principle of the Government of the United States, and which is excluded by the bill. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The question is on agree ing to the amendment. The amendment was rejected. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The clerk will state the next amendment offered by the Senator from Vermont. The Chief Clerk. On page 52, line 9, it is proposed to strike out the first sentence of section 18 and to insert the following: Section 3 of this act shall become effective on the first day of the second calendar month after the enactment of this act, unless the commission shall not at that time have declared the code to be operative, in which event section 3 of this act shall become effective from and after the date when the commission shall have declared the code to be operative, which date shall be promulgated by Executive order of the President of the United States. Mi’. AUSTIN. Mr. President, this amendment has for its objective the promulgation of an agreement instead of the imposition of a mandate. The PRESIDENT pro tempore. The question.is on agree ing to the amendment. The aihendment was rejected. The ^RESIDENT pro tempore. The clerk will , state the next amendment offered by the Senator from Vermont. ThqF Chief Clerk. On page 49, after line 24, 16 is pro-- posedr to insert the following: Ea£h producer shall file with the commission, on or befpre the 15thf day of each calendar month, pursuant to regulations* to be promulgated, and upon forms to be prescribed, by the Coftamis- . siqih, a statement showing for the previous calendar montltj (a) tije aggregate costs of production and sale of such producer;' (b) the tonnage of each kind and size of c5al shipped by such pro ducer, whether individually or through an association, from eaich fnine to each State, destination and use, and the free-on-board mines realization therefrom; (c) the average daily and monthly stated.Although the Sultan T s special car was shunted into the Union station at 6.55 a.m., official Washington did not hecome cognizant of his presence until 11 a.m. when the dictates of protocol decreed that he should be welcomed ofxicially by Mr. Hull and other high ranking officials. As Mr.Hull and the accompanying officials arrived at the sultanate's car, a little brown man dressed in flowing brown and white robes descended the steps of the car and made his t salaams to the American dignitaries. He was one of the aids to the Sultan. He was followed by the Sultan, also dressed in brown and white robes with gold facings and a multicolored, bejewelled turban. He shook hands formally with Mr.Hull and the other officials and the party passed back through the double line of marines and sailors to the President's reception room in the station. The Army band played the American and the Muscat and Oman national anthems. Following the ceremonies, the party paraded in automobiles escorted by the cavalry troop, to a downtown hotel.11 H F P.Z. 1794/38. British SnilDassy, Rome, 4th March, 1938. (121/4/38). My Lord, With reference to your despatch No.237 of the 22nd February, 1938, regarding the visit of the Prince of Yemen to Italy, I have the honour to inform you that, according to the Italian press. His Royal Highness, accompanied by the Grand Master of the Yemen University, arrived at Turin from Paris on March 2nd, being met ceremonially at the station by the leading local authorities. He visited the Fiat works and the 'Aeronautica d’Italia” and was entertained by the Podesta at lunch in the Palazzo Madama. 2. The Prince of Yemen then proceeded to Spezia where he was again received ceremonially. He then proceeded to Rome where he arrived yesterday evening. Amongst those present at the station to receive His Royal Highness were the Minister of Iraq., General Parian!, the Under Secretary of the Ministry of War, General Valle and several other generals, the Vice-Governor, Prefect and Quaestor of Rome, the Under-Secretary of State of the Foreign Office, Signor Bastianini, and other senior officials. Signor Mussolini and Count Ciano were absent from Rome attending the funeral of the late Signor D f Annunzio. The interior of the station was decorated with enormous Italian flags alternating with scarlet red flags bearinj inscriptions/ : The Rt. Honourable the Viscount Halifax, K. G. , G. C. S.I. , G. C. I.E. , etc. , etc., etc. Foreign Office. m • —V,_ ia ... Yn-r-rr inscriptions in white oriental characters with, in translation, such Moslem expressions as 'There is no God hut Allah, and Mahomet is his Prophet: the victory will he granted to him who trusts in God' etc. A detachment of Carabinieri and a military hand were drawn up on the platform, and as the Prince of Yemen stepped from the train the hand struck up the Yemen hymn, followed hy the 'Giovinezza', while the troops presented arms. His Royal Highness, who wore oriental clothes and turban, proceeded, after presentations had heen made, through a cordon of troops out of the station and was escorted to his hotel. 3* A problem, I understand, has arisen regarding the food which can he offered to His Royal Highness while visiting Rome. My Iraq colleague informed a member of the staff that he had heen approached in the matter and was rather in a quandary because the Prince of Yemen, being a strict Mahommedan, would only eat flesh killed in the Mahommedan manner, that is, hy the cutting of the throat. The Italian authorities had thought of employing Jewish kosher experts to solve the problem, hut t e Minister of Iraq pointed out that that would not do at all. Now he had borrowed the Egyptian Minister*s cook, who statedjthat while not expert in the matter he was prepared to advise. As it stands at present it does not seem therefore that the problem has yet heen appropriately solved. I have the honour, etc. (Sd) NOEL CHARLES.Telegraphic Address : ” Hospitality, Parl, London. Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers. All communications should he addressed to the SECRETARY Whitehall, S.W.l and the following reference quoted (T^.P. 1886. Dear Symon, Thank you for your letter (P.Z.2039/38) of the 24th March. 1. The programme of the Sultan’s visit has now gone to print. 2. I have excluded Dulichand and have worded the arrival in London as - Received hy Representatives of His Majesty's Government. 3. I have ordered a wreath from Messrs. Robert Green Limited, 27, Crawford Street, ¥.1. at a cost of £5., and presumably I shall be able to recover this from the Sultan. Yours sincerely A.C.3. Symon Esq., India OfficePROGRAMME. Morning Afternoon Monday, 28th March Arrive Southampton. Received by Major E. N. S. Crankshavv, C.M.G., M.B.E., representing the Minister in Charge, Government Hospitality Arrive Waterloo. Received by representatives of His Majesty’s Government Proceed to Dorchester Hotelad Morning 9.55 10.30 11.00 Thursday, 31st March Leave Dorchester Hotel Arrive Royal Air Force Aero drome, Hendon, and fly to Hornchurch in Air Council aeroplane D.H. 86b Arrive Royal Air Force Station, Hornchurch (No. 11 Fighter Group), Inspect Station Lounge Suits Leave Hornchurch by air for Royal Air Force Aerodrome, Hendon Royal Air Force Mess, Hendon, at the invitation of the officers Arrive Metropolitan Police Col lege. Received by Lieutenant- Colonel G. H. R. Holland, C.I.E., O.B.E., Commandant Evening Dress VFriday, 1st April Morning 10.00 Leave Dorchester Hotel 11.30 Arrive Aldershot for a demon stration by a mixed company of Light and Medium Tanks followed by detailed examina tion of Tanks Afternoon Lounge Suits Luncheon 1.00 The Aldershot Officers’Club, at the invitation of the officers 2.15 Return to London Dinner Dine privately11 Lounge Suits Morning 10.30 Sunday, 3rd April Leave Dorchester Hotel Lounge Suits Afternoon 1.00 Arrive Guilsborough Court, Northampton Luncheon 1.15 As guest of Colonel J. Lowther, D.S.O., M.C., and the Honble. Mrs. Lowther Arrive Cottesbrooke. Inspect livestock at farm of Captain R. N. Macdonald-Buchanan, M.C.. M.F.H., and the Buchanan Arrive Brixworth. Inspect hunters and foxhounds at the Pytchley KennelsTuesday, 5th April Morning 9.15 Leave Dorchester Hotel 12 noon Arrive Portsmouth. Firing of Salutes and inspection of H.M.S. “ Nelson ” Afternoon Luncheon 1.15 As guest of the Earl of Cork and Orrery, G.C.B., G.C.V.O., Commander - in - Chief, Portsmouth 2.30 Embark on H.M. Submarine and proceed to sea 4.00 Return to London 7.45 Leave Dorchester Hotel Dinner 8.00 At Houses of Parliament as guest of Parliamentary Under secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, subsequently listen ing to Debate in House of Commons Lounge Suits Evening DressHI 14 Wednesday, 6th April Morning Morning Dress Afternoon 12.50 Leave Dorchester Hotel Luncheon 1.15 At Mansion House as the guest of the Lord Mayor of London 3.00 Leave Mansion House 3.15 Embark on motor launches at Tower Pier for visit to Port of London. Received by the Lord Ritchie of Dundee, Chairman, Port of London Authority 5.30 Arrive Tower Pier Dinner « Dine privately 8.15 Leave Dorchester Hotel Evening Dress 8.30 Arrive at the Hall of the Royal Society, Burlington House. Received by Field-Marshal Sir Philip Chetwode, G.C.B., O.M., G.C.S.I., Chairman of the Council of the Royal Central Asian Society, and Lady Chetwode 'u LZQi&amp;i,Morning Afternoon Luncheon Dinner 15 Thursday, 7th April 9.30 Leave Dorchester Hotel Lounge Suits 12 noon Arrive School of Agriculture, Cambridge. Inspect Colleges 1.00 2.30 4.30 At the invitation of the Vice- Chancellor, Cambridge Uni versity. Received by the Master of St. John’s College, on behalf of the Vice- Chancellor, at the Master s Lodge Visit to the University Farm, Field Stations and Research Institutes Tea at the Institute of Animal Pathology 5.00 Return to London Dim* privately tufa lata - /&lt;- L - M&gt; U ^ L . ^ kd- - ? SouuJi-Montfng Afternoon Luncheon 16 Friday, 8th April At Dorchester Hotel 4.00 Leave Dorchester Hotel 4.15 Arrive Broadcasting House Tour of Broadcasting House Lounge Suits l/rtlfa Tcrurt*. Cl' Dine privately jy^A/^L YjLAJLfafc** DinnerMorning Afternoon Luncheon Dinner 17 Saturday, 9th April At Dorchester Hotel 2.00 Leave Dorchester Hotel Lounge Suit&gt; 3 00 Arrive Wembley Stadium to witness the International Association Football Match England versus Scotland, as guest of the Football Asso ciation Dine privately 8.00 Leave Dorchester Hotel Evening Dress 8.15 Arrive at the London Coliseum to witness 'St. MoritzMorning Afternoon Luncheon Dinner Monday, 11th April 10.30 Leave Dorchester Hotel Lounge Suits 11.30 Arrive Aircraft Factory of Messrs. de Havilland, Hatfield. Received by Mr. F. E. N. St. Barbe, on behalf of the Directors. Tour fac tory. 1.00 As the guest of the Directors of Messrs, de Havilland 2.30 Arrive Aircraft Factory of Messrs, de Havilland, Rdg- ware. Tour factory 4.00 Return to London (tlAAAA*\ fP**' 4 *^ ./ II* f* J &lt;U- Official Visit EndsMinute Paper 'V'Z. . 10 ^ PS political Department. 5cfl This is rather a full programme - hut then v/e have had so many excellent suggestions from the Resident. The following 'day' periods will be available for discussions: 30th March Afternoon 2nd April Before 11 a.m. 4th ' 6th ' Morning H II II 8th ' 9th ' ^ 'flu (****) , lJI*+* 4* ** &lt;*** * tL L ' U ~* 1^ %+f&gt;K ^ ^ ft / fL ^ ^ In addition there are a number of free evenings during which the Resident might perhaps visit the Sultan for informal talks. As regards ’A’ in Major Crankshaw’s letter, please see the Resident’s telegram of 14th March at P.Z,1747/38. As we have not heard anything from the Sultan regarding Dulichand we had better not include him in the official party. Part B is still under consideration. As regards ’O’, I had suggested to Major r Crankshaw that the visit to the Cenotaph might be omitted; but from his experience of other similar visits he is inclined to think that the Sultan will want to lay a v/reath, more especially as his father did so in 1928. In the circumstances we had better let Major Crankshaw get the wreath and take 1‘ money from the Sultan later. As regards ’D’, we have left Highness’s arrival before tackling Arabic broadcast. May I write to Major Cranksl K474B Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IGP the attached draft please?Draft Paper. T.'Z. ao^m /r J fi^ political Department. Ma S. Crankshaw, CMG., MBE., Government Hospitaljty Fund, Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1. 24 MAR 1938 Dear Crankshav;, Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 22nd March, G.H.F.1886, enclosing a proof of the programme for the Sultan 1 s visit. We have no suggestions to make^and-ohould like to tako-^his opportunity of congratulating you on the excellent programme which you have fixed upT' Sc fa. 2. As we have not Iseen asked hy the A Sultan to include Dulichand in the official A* ttu^ Sfyc party it would be best^to keep his name out of the programme. &amp; 4' 41m. £* €i*iAui 4 A* ' fajy J*, ur^ L+* kc 3. The question whether a member of the Government should meet the Sultan on his arrival in London is still under consideration, and I v/ill let you know as soon as a decision is reached. 4. In view of the time factor, it might be best if you order the wreath and obtain payment later. Ycmju £ sino&amp;i'&amp;ty fcC ..»wo«.Telegraphic Address: '• Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehajx:&gt;I481. „ g£ 4 All coqVftunications should be addressed \o*i\e SECRETARY and the following reference quoted P.1886. m VEKNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 22nd March, 1938. Dear Symon, I enclose proof of the programme, and shall he glad if you will let me know whether you consider that any altera tions should he made other than those which have already been marked on it. I should he glad if you would let me know in regard to the following points:- A- Page 3. Shall the Financial Assistant, Dulichand, he included in the list of the suite? B - Page 5. The name of the member of the Government who will receive the Sultan on arrival at Waterloo. Page 6. Shall I order a v/reath for the Sultan? The Sultan will presumably pay. J&gt; Page 16. As we have just agreed hy telephone, I am leaving out the broadcast speech. A.G.B. Symon Es^., India Office. LiflD. POL atPT. 2 ,MA 19: jHIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND VISIT OF HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF MUSC AT^ Cand OMAN~ 29th MARCH to Ith APRIL, 1938PROGRAMME. Monday, 28th March Morning .00 Afternoon .00 Arrive Southampton. Received by Major E. N. S. Crankshaw, C.M.G., M.B.E., representing the Minister in Charge, Government Hospitality Morning Dress Arrive Waterloo. Received by Lieutenant-Colonel W. G. Neale, C.I.E., representing the Secretary of State for India a { &amp;' 6 Tuesday, 29th March. r Morning 10.45 Leave Dorchester Hotel Morning Dress 10.55 Arrive Home Office 11.00 Lay Wreath at Cenotaph 12 noon Received by Secretary of State for India at India Office Afternoon Luncheon Dorchester Hotel 2.45 Leave Dorchester Hotel 3.00 Arrive Middlesex Hospital. Tour of Hospital Depart ments 8.15 Leave Dorchester Hotel Dinner 8.30 At Lancaster House. Given by His Majesty’s Government: State e spital. epart- Morning Dress Wednesday, 30th March Morning 11.20 Leave Dorchester Hotel 11.30 His Majesty The King will receive His Highness The Sultan in audience Morning Dress8 r Thursday, 31st March Morning 9.55 Leave Dorchester Hotel Lounge Suits Arrive Royal Air Force Aero drome, Hendon, and flv to * Hornchurch W/A’ir Touncil ^ aeroplane D.H. 86b 11.00 Arrive Royal A ir Force Station, Hornchurch,^Inspecti^ Sta- Afternoon 12.45 Luncheon 1.30 3.00 Leave Hornchurch by air for Royal Air Force Aerodrome Hendon Hendon /u * , , M n+'v***t* Arrive Metropolitan Police Col lege. Received by Lieutenant Colonel G. H. R. Holland C.I.E., O.B.E., Commandant tngparting Galiogf 4.30 Tea at College Dinner Dine privately 8.40 Leave Dorchester Hotel Arrive Royal Adelphi Theatre to witness “ Balalaika ” Me Mr L12 f Monday, 4th April ihLre (a_j /l&amp;XiC Leave Dorchester Hotel Morning Dress Arrive Westminster Abbey, West Cloister Door. Received * by*. ^ rU Arrive Houses of Parliament, Peers’ Entrance. Received by Lord Esme Gordon-Lennox, C.M.G., D.S.O., M.V.O., Secretary to the Lord Great Chamberlain Moi Aft&lt; Lur Dinner Dine privately 8.45 Leave Dorchester Hotel Evening Dress Din.*»a Morning ~MQ Arrive — :—Hall fUT -rofroohment- .00 Arrive Portsmouth. Inspectiaig H.M.S. “ Nelson ” Afternoon Luncheon .00 As guest of the Earl of Cork and Orrery, G.C.B., G.C.V.O., Commander - in - Chief, Portsmouth .00 Embark on H.M. Submarine and proceed to sea .00 Return to London Dinner14 C Wednesday, 6th April Morning Afternoon MS' Luncheon Leave Dorchester Hotel At Mansion House as the guest of the Lord Mayor of London 3 .00 Leave Mansion House 3j!S Embark at Tower Pier for visit to Port of London 5. co Dinner Dine privately Evening 8.15 Leave Dorchester Hotel Evening Dress 8.30 Arrive at the Hall of the Royal Society, Burlington House, to attend Lecture by Central Asian Soci ety. Received by i Sir Philip^cfnd Lady Chetwode (-i.Friday, 8th April At Dorchester Hotel Arrive Broadcasting House.Morning Afternoon Muuiing Drm,s Luncheon At Dorchester Hotel ^ X 2.30 Leave Dorchester Hotel Lounge Suit^ ^ 3.15 Arrive Wembley Stadium to witness the International Association Football Match— England versus Scotland ^ 3^7 Dinner Dine privately 8.00 Leave Dorchester Hotel Evening Dress-■JUS * Telegraphic Address : 'Hospitality, Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY ~ GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 24th March, 1938.List of * REFUSALS* for the Dinner in honour of His Hi^iness The Sultan of Muscat Mr, Barlow - Treasury Mr, E.JS.Bridges - Treasury The Hon, Sir Alexander Cadogan - F.O. Field-Marshal Sir Philip Ghetwode ^ The Earl of Cork and Orrery - Commander-in-Chief, Portsmouth The First Lord of the Admiralty x Vice-Admiral L.G.E, Crabbe 0 Mr, H.R, Dean - Vice-Chancellor of Cambridge Professor F, L* Engledow - Agricultural College, Cambridge ^/Lieut,-Col. J, A, Fairhurst - Newbury Mr, 7, Fraser ^ Admiral Sir Eric Fullerton r Air Vice Marshal Sir Philip Game - Metropolitan Police r Lord Esme Gordon-Lennox - Houses of Parliament Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs Sir Alexander Hardinge Lord Chief Justice Secretary of State for Home Affairs Secretary of State for War Lord Lloyd Lord Mayor of London Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs $ Captain R,N, Macdonald-Buchanan - Home Farm, Northampton Lord Chancellor — Brigadier E.L. Morris ^ Mr, W, Pickford - Football Association Sir John Reith — Mr, G.W. Rendel Sir Edward Denison Ross Wing Commander Russell Marshal of the Royal Air Force Sir John Salmond First Commissioner of Works Chancellor of the Exchequer The Speaker — Lord Stanley President of the Board of Trade —Sir Findlater Stewart Secretary of State for Air Sir Robert Vansittart The Marquess of Willingdon Lieut,-Col, Sir Arnold 7/ilson Earl Winterton ^ Other than on India Office list x Vice-Admiral Crabbe - on way home from China Admiral Sir Eric Fullerton - in BermudaTelegraphic Address: “ Hospitality, Paul, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. All communications should be Treasury Chambers, addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted Whitehall, S.W.l 1886. 23rd March, 1938 Dear Symon, Thank you for your letter of the 22nd March, with which you enclosed fifty copies of a note regarding Muscat and its present Ruler. I will distribute these to those people v/ho are entertaining the Sultan. Yours sincerely, A.G.B. Symon Esq • » India OfficeHIS HIGHTBCS S7LTAT RAIYir' SAID Bla TAI!,'ro The Sultan succeeded his father, Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal bin Turk!, K.C.I.S.,C.S.I., in 1932. He is 27 years of age and is unmarried. He has a pleasant personality, and though short in stature (about 5 , 2 U ), bears himself with considerable dignity and is endowed with a quiet sense of humour. He is shrewd and energetic, with a flair for finance. He speaks excellent English and received part of his education at the Chiefs* College, Ajmer. GENERAL The Sultanate is not a British Protectorate. In law it has independent sovereign status. Besides its Treaty relations v/ith His Majesty*s Government it has treaty relations with France and America, and before the Great War these Powers had Consuls stationed at Muscat. TERRITORY Oman in its geographical sense represents the South Eastern corner of the Arabian Peninsula from Abu Dhabi in the North to the borders of the Aden Protectorate. Politically speaking, the Sultanate consists of the littoral extending from Has Musandam at the entrance of the Persian Gulf along tne East and South coasts to Ras Fartak in Central South Arabia, a coast line of 1,100 miles, together with the overseas possession of Gwadur, an importsint Mekran port which handles the trade of much of Southern British Baluchistan and South Eastern Persia, and is situated on the Imperial Air Route to India.carried the trade 'between Babylonia rand India, and its seas were the cradle of navigation. Oman figures before the rise of Islam as an appanage of Persia, and in turn fell into the hands of the Abbasid Caliphs of Baghdad, but from the Middle Ages onwards secured independence under its own native rulers. The present dynasty rose in 1741. Napoleon, to further his Indian designs, regarded the Sultanate as of such importance as to seek an alliance, but the period of greatest prosperity came seventy years later under the Sultan Saiyid Sa f id, the great great grandfather of the present Sultan. He ruled from 1807 to 1856 and was perhaps one of the greatest Arab figures to appear since the Arab prophet. He extended his influence northwards and asserted his mastery over the entire Persian Gulf. He invaded and colonised Zanzibar and the adjacent East African territory. He presented a frigate to our Royal Navy and received a handsome yacht, the ,f Prince Regent”, in return. The Sultanate has since then diminished gradually in importance, largely as a result of the influence on Muscat trade of the development of steam navigation and the opening of the Sues Canal. PHYSICAL FEATURES The dominant physical features of Oman are (i) a lofty range of mountains running almost parallel with the coast, the great backbone of the country rising to a height of 10,000 feet in Jebel Akdhar, (ii) a coastal plain distinguished for a date grove one hundred and fifty miles long and from three to seven miles in depth, (iii) beyond the mountains, the immense spaces of Ruba al Khali, the Great Desert. The deep waters off the Oman coasts render navigation simple, and Muscat is a safe as well as a very beautiful harbour. CLIMATE Encircled by precipitous volcanic cliffs, the summer climate/climate of Muscat is intensely hot and there is sc difference between day and night temper attire. It that the Persian poet wrote 'And here the panting receives a foretaste of his future deetinjt’. The rainfall varies between three and six inches. arcely any was of Muscat sinner average POPULATION API) RELIT I Oil The total population of Oman has been estimated at 500,000 representing perhaps 15 per cent, of the entire population of the Arabian peninsula. 80 per cent, of these are tribal Arabs, there is a considerable pure - negro element generally in domestic service, and a less numerous foreign trading element which consists of British Indians, Persians and Baluchis. The majority of the inhabitants belong to the Ibadhi sect of Islam, which is elsewhere found in Morocco. PRODUCTS AND TRAPS The Overseas trade is largely with Bombay, Aden and Zanzibar, though America takes a considerable portion of Oman’s date crop. The fisheries, chiefly shark for export to the Par East, are of second importance to the date industry. The camel of Oman are famous throughout Arabia, but the country is too parched to allow the horse to flourish and very few are bred. Indigo dyeing, copper and brass work and cloth weaving are among other industries, and there is a crude but characteristic variety of gold and silver work, especially used for sheaths and mountings of daggers and swords.(With the Compliments of the Information Officer, India Office. ■His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, accompanied 'by three State officials, leaves New York to-day (22nd March) for England in the s. s. ’’Queen Mary” which is due to arrive at Southampton on the 28th March. His Highness will he. the guest of His Majesty’s G-overnment for a period of a fortnight from the date of arrival. He will he received in Audience hy the King and a programme has heen arranged which will enable him to see various aspects of our national life, including the daily work of the Fighting Services. 22nd March, 12i8.1 I.lr, Jovgo. He the fortlicomin^ visit of the Sultan of Muscat. It has been agreed with the Foreign Office that the publicity should be handled by this Office, and I understand that you are agreeable to this arrangement. The Sultan is leaving New York by the S.3. Queen Mary on 22nd March and is due to reach Southampton on the 28th March. He will be received by the Secretary of State for India at 12 noon on the 29th March and by the King at Buckingham Palace ao 11. oO a.in. on Wednesday, 30th March. The programme of official entertainment, covering a period of approximately two v/eekSf includes a Government Dinner to be held at Lancaster House on the 29th March. I will let you have full details of the pro grannie very shortly. As regards publicity, it is suggested that a short statement might be issued on or about 22nd March stating that the Sultan has left New York for England and is to be treated as a Government guest. Perhaps something on the following lines might do. 'His/the @&gt;@) 2 , Oman, accompanied by three State Officials, is learing New York for England on the 2Snd March in the S.S. oueen Marj r . His Highness is to] be received in Audience p Government for a period of afrnut tv/o ucekb from the date of arrival.'* ^ ju Something on the above lines might also be included in the Arabic broadcast about the same dfa^e? Further items will be passed on to you from time to time, and it is hoped that His Highness can be persuaded to make a short broadcast in Arabic describing his experiences in England towards the end of the official visit. I attach a Memorandum giving a brief description of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman and of His Highness the present Sultan. This document is not 'confidential* and the fullest use may be made of it in dealing with any enquiries which you may receive iron the press. If you require any further information please do not hesitate to let us knew. I yO J •$Colonel Neale&gt; I attach a Memorandum giving a brief description cf the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman and of Hie Highness the present Sultan. Part (b) of this Memorandum is confidential: Part (a) is not. I also attach a non-confidential note regarding the Sultan. His Highness is travelling from Nev/ York in the S.S. Queen Mary, which is due to reach Southampton on the 28th ; larch. He will be welcomed on board by Major Crankshaw on behalf of the Minister in Charge of Government Hospitality. It is too early yet to say what time the boat train will reach London, but I will pass the information on to you as soon as it is known. j4v V ti &lt;*ICk*J* fai, ?*****■ K'It (iM- av* So u fa'* (&amp;) ('b) HIS HIGHNESS SULTAN SAIYID SAID BIN TAIMUH The Sultan succeeded his father, Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal bin Turki, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., on the latter’s abdication in 1932. He is now 27 years old and isunmarried. He has a pleasant personality, and though short in stature (about 5 ! 2 ,r ), bears himself with considerable dignity and is endowed with a quiet sense of humour. He is shrewd and energetic, v/ith a ilair xor finance, and has a v/ill of his own. He speaks excellent English, which he learnt at the Chiefs* Colbge, Ajmer, where he received part of his education. The Sultanate is not a British Protectorate. In law it has independent sovereign status. Besides its ireaty relations with His Majesty’s Government it has treaty relations with Prance and America, and before the Great War these Powers had Consuls stationed at Muscat. Last November the Sultan paid a State visit to India lasting ten days, during which time he was the guest of His Excellency the Viceroy for three days. On the termination of this visit he proceeded on a world tour, including visits to Singapore, Japan (to see his father who now lives in that country) and to the United States of America. He arrived in America on the 10th February and is travelling to England from New York in ohe S.S. Queen Mary, which is due to arrive at Southampton on the 28th March. While in America he was treated as a guest of the American Government for a short P®**iod and was received by the President. On reaching England His Highness will be the guest of His Majesty’s Government for about a fortnight. During this time he will be received in Audience by the King. His/His suite consists of the following Halal bin Badr (A. D. C. ) Saiyid Abdulmunim Zav/awi (Secretary ) Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubaily (State Official) The party will be accommodated at the Dorchester Hotel. Major E.N.S. Crankshaw, C.M.G., M.B.E. , Secretary to the Government Hospitality Pund, and Lieutenant-Colonel G. Dalyell of The Binns, C.I.E., an officer of the Indian Political Department who has had long experience in the Persian Gulf, will be attached to the party during the period of official hospitality. His Highness will be welcomed at Southampton by Major Crankshaw on behalf of the Minister in Charge of Government Hospitality, and at the London station by Lieutenant-Colonel G. v. Neale, C. I.E., C./. 0. , Political A. D.C. to the Secretary of State for India.political Department. 18 MAfil938 (XjL^A/ f I enclose a rough idea of the official programme of the visit of the Sultan of Muscat. His Highness is n^-ow in America and intends to travel to England in the S.S.’’Queen Mary” which is due to reach Southampton on the 28th March. He will be welcomed on board the ship at Southampton by Major E.N.S.Crankshaw, on behalf of the Minister in Charge of Government Hospitality, and at the London station by Lieut.Cel.W.G. Heale, f!IE.-rCVP. &gt; the Political A.D.C. to | the Secretary of State for India. I am sure that His Highness would appreciate it very much if you could manage to meet him at Southampton, and we have told Crankshaw that you are thinking of doing so. As Crankshaw will have many things to attend to at Southampton^he would prefer to leave you to make your own arrangements for getting on the ship jmd as soon as wtr y receive information as to the time of arrival I will let you know. u. ^ ^ ^ i- ^ H /'V tt 'p H,h v . Yours sinoerefy. (Sd.) J. O. WAJLTU-N,Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 17th March, 1938. Thank you for your letter (P.Z.1798/38) of the As you say, Butler’s Dinner at the House of Commons on the 5th April is an excellent item, and I win include it in the programme. 1 am writing to Loxley saying that v/e v/ill pay the hill if he certifies it and sends it along. Yours sincerely, / A.C.B. Symon Esq., India Office.rt •. /. t ! 1 I ?8political Department. - M - r - GlbS ° n ’ 7 * (JJi, ^ Mr. Brenan te Is phoned last night to say that Mr. Butler is prepared to give a dinner to the Sultan • of Muscat at the House of Commons on the 5th April. After dinner it is proposed to show the Sultan something of the Parliament buildings and if time permits to look in at a debate. Mr. Brenan suggested that as the dinner would be of a semi-official nature the cost might be charged to the Government Hospitality Fund. I have discussed the matter with Major Crankshaw and understand that there will be no difficulty about paying for the dinner; but he would like something in writing. If you agree, I might write to him on the lines of the attached draft.1 6 MAH 1938 Dear Crankshaw, With reference to our telephonic conversation of yesterday^ date, I v/rite to confirm that Mr. Butler is prepared to act as host at a small semi-official dinner in honour of the Sultan of Muscat at the House of Commons on the 5th April at 8 p.m. The necessary arrangements will he made hy Mr. Butler’s Private Secretary, x Mr. P. N. Loefcsley. After dinner it is proposed to show Kis Highness round the Parliament buildings and, if time permits, to look in at a debate. This seems an excellent item to include in the official programme of entertainment and will fill an obvious gap in the second half of the programme. May we take it that the cost ^ of the dinner will be met from official funds? ($&amp;d‘) A. C. B. SYiv.uft,Department. T.V. Brenan, Esq., O.B E. , Foreign Office. 11 MAR 1938 Dear Brenan, V/ith reference to our conversation this morning, I attach a rough idea of the programme for the visit of the Sultan of Muscat. 2. As Watts will not he able to come to England to look after the Sultan, we have asked Loch (who, by the way, has now changed his name to Dalyell of The Binns) to take on the job, and he has agreed to do so. 3. The Government dinner will be held at Lancaster House and our Secretary of State will definitely preside. Yours sincerely, ^ A#- my Telegraphic Address: 'Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted P.1886. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 8th March, 1938. w?) Dear Symon, I attach a rough idea of the programme for the visit of the Sultan of Muscat. Yours sincerely, A.C.B. Symon Esq. , India Office.Telegraphic Address : “ Hospitality, Paul, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY Whitehall, and the following reference quoted : S.W.l P.1886. 14th March, 1938 Dear Symon, Thank you for your letter (P.Z.1658/38) of the 11th March, with which you returned the proof of the invitation card for the Muscat Dinner. I will now have the cards printed. Yours sincerelv. A.C.B. Symon Esq. , India Office.Telegraphic Address: 'Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted: GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.I 11th March, 1958. Dear Symon, I enclose proof of the invitation card for your Dinner to the Sultan of Muscat, and shall he glad to have this hack v/ith your approval or otherwise. A.C.B. Symon Esq., India Office.Military Branch. M. 982/38. 8th March, 1938. Dear Crankshaw, Your letter to Markham of 22nd February, 1938, No. G. H. F. 1886 re the Sultan of Muscat. 2. We are asking the Commander-in-Chief, Portsmouth if he can arrange for the Sultan to inspect a Capital Ship of the Home Fleet at Portsmouth and to take a trip in a submarine, if possible on Tuesday, 6th April, and will let you know when we get his answer. 3. As regards the salute, the position is that there is no saluting station at Southampton and it would be necessary to send a ship there specially for the purpose, or to get the War Office to move a saluting battery. we do not think there is any justification for doing this, but we propose to fire a 21 gun salute for the Sultan during his visit to Portsmouth, as was done on his visit there in 1928. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Gibson at the India Office and Baggallay at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely. '% k. SEAL. Major S.N.S. Crankshaw, C.M.G., M. B. E. , Government Hospitality Fund, Treasury Chambers, 3. W. 1.Telegraphic Address : “ Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted &gt;.H# F.1886. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 11th March, 1938. Dear Symon, Thank you for your letter (P.Z.1584/38) of the 10th March, with which was enclosed a list of guests to whom the Lord Mayor might send invitations to his Luncheon in honour of the Sultan of Muscat. Yours sincerely. A.G.B. Symon Esq., India Office.Thank you for your letter (P.Z.1313/38) of the 11th March, with v/hich you enclosed a list of guests to he invited to the Government dinner to the Sultan of Muscat on March 29th. I am glad to know that your Secretary of State will preside, and I will arrange for this Dinner to he held at Lancaster House. 2. I note that the King will receive the Sultan at Buckingham Palace at 11.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 30th March, and that the Secretary of State will receive him at 12 noon on the 29th March. A.C.3. Symon Esq., India Office.Draft Paper. ISisht- political Department. DRAFT LiilTTiiH. Major E.N.S. Crankahaw, CMG. , MBE. . 11 MAR 1938 Dear Crankshaw, I enclose a list of gueats whom we suggest might be invited to the Government Dinner on 29th v 'arch. Provided that numbers permit it is considered preferable that the dinner should be held at Lancaster House. Cur Secretary of State will definitely preside. Firm arrangements have now been made for the Sultan to be received by the King at Buckingham Palace at 11.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 30th March. Arrangements have also been made for the Sultan to be received by our Secretary of State at 12 noon on the 29th- March.Minute Paper, poli ti cal Departm ent. l°IZ &gt;N CM *■*•-». it /* H*\v+\ / (re c +* '*&gt;'*+/’ f J lJ\H Uce+A. la In pt*****} tL &lt;iL**rr***' *9 ft I* ( l * fu * *** llu- UtS* «l ri'JMU S* i. l&gt;/c-J&lt;*Ui ^ 7.Hi. Js* y , p. s % 1 ~J ? 'J. Major Crankshaw has suggested that the proposed 3 Government Dinner for the Sultan of Muscat should be held on the 29th March, the day after His Highness reaches England, and he would be glad to be informed as soon as possible whether he may make arrangements accordingly. It is understood that the suggested date will be convenient ttf^the Secretary of State. As regards place, the choice appears to lie between Lancaster House and the India Office. The latter would be quite convenient provided that the number of guests does more not exceed 45, and it would probably be /congenial than Lancaster House. The Foreign Office have been consulted informally and take the view that if the Secretary of State for India is to preside it would be quite logical to carry the ’’Indian” interest a step further by holding the Dinner at this Office. The point is, however, submitted for orders. A list of names is suggested for submission to the Government Hospitality Fund. A ce [/iA IM-*7 © H.H. The Sultan of Muscat Halal bin Badr (A.D.C.) Saiyid Abdulmuniin Zawawi (Secretary^ Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubaily (State Official) The Secretary of State for India The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs , ^ ( The Secretary of State foi^ Home The President of the Board of Trade . ^ 0 The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs V yi i ihe First Comissioner of Works ' Lord Stanley J 7 c &lt; '• Mr. Butler ,. . Lord Winterton 1 ^' ^'^ A jUr\ Lord Willingdon , , / Lord Lloyd ' ^he Lord Mayor is giving a private lunch for the Sultan on 6 April. The Lord Mayor of London Sir Hughe Knatchbull-Bugessen Sir Philip Chetwode ^ Sir Percy Sykes Sir Trenchard Fowle ^ Colonel Loch f Colonel Daly . Bertram Thomas r Denys Bray Sir E. Howell Sir Arnold Wilson Lord Cadman Sir J. Reith Sir E. Denison Ross Sir A. Cadogan Sir R. Vansittart Sir L. Oliphant Mr. Rendel Mr. C. Baxter Mr. Baggallay Mr. Brenan Mr. Etherington-Smith R h' Foreign Office Admiral Sir M. Dunbar Nasmyth Vice Admiral Crabbe Captain T.S.V. Phillips, R.N. Captain G.D. Yates, R.N. Mr. Seal Admiralty Brigadier E.L. Morris Colonel L.E. Denys f Major Mallaby War Office n n Air Vice Marshal R.E.C. Peirse Group Captain D.F. Stevenson Wing Commander H.B. Russell Air Ministry P.T.O.p&gt; 1 { fapi) NO NIS j.'RIBUiTON . Decode. Sir R. Lirds.y (.,L£hU . D. dr 46 p, m. R. 10. i&gt;0 e.. riu Ro. 14-4. (R), March 7th 1958. March 7th 1958. j'larch 8th 1958. Your telegran) ho, ceremony on Sultan's arrival was the same as for Governor General of Canada (see my despatch Mo.292 of 1957). He stayed ao a no tel. Lunch at the ,/hite House, dinners given by Secretary oi Soate and Under Secretary of State. These were attended in turn by some cabinet Ministers, a few heads of missions. Chairman Ox ^tTic .cq ano. House, foreign Affairs Conunittee, State Leoartinent and o Oier ofucials. Visits were paid to Federal jjureau of Investigation (G men), Scotland Yard, Cavalry Headquarters where lunch was served and exiii'bition of drill performed, end Mount j ernon. I understand ultan expressed himself as being interested in everything that was suggested to him. His journey thiough Southern States was quietly drooped owing to colour question. So far • : y have no information on political and commercial aspects of the visit. Multan is now in Mew fork.Ur' 'L'K Mr. B. A. B. Burrows Mr. O. C. Harvey Mr. H. A. F. Rumbold Muhammad Sarwar Khan Colonel H. L. Ismay Major-General R. C. Wilson Mr. Laurence Collier Sir Edward Denison Ross Juma Khan Siddiqi Dr. Rifki Bey Sir Richard Maconachie Sir Denys de S. Bray Sir Lancelot Oliphant Brigadier-General Sir Percy Sykes Lieutenant-General Sir Sidney Clive Ghund Mishar Muhammad Ihsan Khan Major-General Sir Percy Cox Colonel Sir Maurice Hankey Field-Marshal Sir Cyril Deverell Field-Marshal Sir William Birdwood The Rt. Hon. C. R. Attlee The Earl of Munster The Earl of Plymouth The Most Hon. the Marquess of Willingdon Ali Muhammad Khan The Rt. Hon. Anthony Eden The Most Hon. the Marquess of Zetland His Royal Highness Sardar Muhammad Hashim Khan The Rt. Hon. the Earl Winterton The Viscount Halifax The Lord Lloyd The Rt. Hon. Sir Archibald Sinclair Abdul Majid Khan Marshal of the Royal Air Force Sir Edward Ellington Sir Robert Vansittart Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Francis Humphrys Sir Findlater Stewart General Sir Kenneth Wigram Sir Herbert Creedy Sir Edward Crowe Lieutenant-General S. F. Muspratt Sir Robert Hodgson Sir Abdul Qadir Sir Leonard Wakely Mr. J. C. Walton Muhammad Ali Mr. S. D. Waley Mr. J. B. Monck Mr. F. H. Nixon Mr. W. D. Croft Mr. H. A. Caccia Major E. N. S. Crankshaw M | ENTRANCEI think you rang up to ask for a list of » , ii i nf 11 11 Naval Officers who might he asked to the Grovernment dinner for Muscat. The following names have been suggested:- Or ^ Name Admiral Sir Martin Dunhar- Nasmith, V.C., K.C.B. Second Sea Lord, Admiralty, — Vice-Admiral L.G-.E.Crabbe. (Due to arrive United Kingdom from China 25th March, address not yet known). Captain T.S.V.Phillips, C.B., R.N. , Admiralty till 19th April. Captain G.D.Yates, R,N., Admiralty. Captain E.C.Denison,M.V.0., R*N. , 42a, Hay’s Mews, Berkeley Square, W. 1. Appointment Commander-in-Chief, East Indies (1932 - 1934) Senior Naval Officer. Persian G-ulf. (1930 - 1933) Chief Staff Officer to Commander-in-Chief, East Indies (1932 - 1935) H.M,SHIPS FOLKESTONE &amp; FOWEY (1930 - 1933) H.M.8.B1DEF0RD, Persian Gulf. (1932 - 1934) Yours sincerely,BUCKINGHAM PALACE 4th. March, 1938 Dear Hood, Thank you for your letter of yesterday about the Sultan of Muscat. As he is going to ar ive on March 28th., it would be much more convenient for The King to receive him in London before going to Windsor for the month of April. His Majesty v/ishes me to say, therefore, that he will see him at Buckingham Palace at 11.30 a.m. on Wednesday, March 30th. Yours sincerely, The Viscount Hood India Office. 7and the following reference quoted : addressed to the Telegraphic Address: 'Hospitality, Parl, Londi Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. G.H.P.1886. All communications shout SECRETARY GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, 10th March, 1938. Whitehall, S.W.l Dear Symon Thank you for your letter (P.Z.1081/38) of the 8th March, with which you enclosed a revised version of Part B of the information contained in the memorandum about the Sultan of Muscat enclosed with your letter of the 4th March. I note that Part A of that memorandum and the revised Part B can be supplied to those who entertain the Sultan. Yours sincerely A.C.B. Symon Esq., India OfficeThank you for your letter (P. Z.1178/38) of the 4th March with which you enclosed a memorandum giving a ciescription of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman and of His Highness the Sultan. This will be most useful. I presume there will be no objection to supplying those who are to entertain the Sultan with the iniormation contained in the memorandum. Yours sincerely, A.O.B. Symon Esq., India Office. HRSCn. POL, ffiPrl ~ 8 MAR 1938 INDIA OFFICE!(*&gt;) ^ . : SULT^K SaIYI ,1 T V-.IMUR . The Sultan succeeded his father, Sultan Saiyid Tairaur bin Paisal bin Turlci, K.C.I.J2. ,0,S,I., on the latter’s abdication in 1932« He is now 27 years old and is unmarried* He has a pleasant personality, and though short in stature (about 5 9 2*)t bears himself with considerable di nity and is endowed with a quiet sense of humour* Ke is shrewd and energetic, with a flair for finance, and has a will of his own. He speaks excellent English, which he learnt at the Chiefs’ College, Ajraer, where he received part of his education*J The Sultanate is not a British Protectorate. In law it has independent sovereign status. Besides its Treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government it has treaty relations with Prance and America, and before the Great «ar these powers had consals stationed at uscat. /v a jAT -Last November the Sultan paid a State vialt to India lasting t jn days, during which time he was the guest of His excellency the Viceroy for three days# On the termination of this visit he proceeded on a world tour# including visits to Japan and the United States of America. He arrived in America on the 10th February and is travelling to England from New York in the s.s. 'Queen Mary”. While in America he wil i be treated as a State guest for a short period and will be received by the President.3rd March 1938 Dear Sir Alexander, Thank you bo much for your letter of the 3rd March. I will expect in due course to hear from you In regard to a definite date for the Sultan of Muscat's audience. The Sultan will be a Government guest for a fortnight, dating from the day of his arrival - March 28th. I understand that he is due back in Muscat some time in May and as he proposes to visit some European countries on the way home I doubt whether he will stay very much longer in England after the close of his official visit. Yours sincerely, H. The Rt.Hon.Sir Alexander Hardinge, GCVQ., KCB., MC2nd torch 1938. Dear Sir Alexander, Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 17th December about the Sultan of Muscat’s visit to England? We have recently received a message from the Sultan coni inning his intention of coming to this country &amp;y the 3.3. 'C^ueen Mary', and the Government Hospitality und have now been asked to prepare a suitable programme of entertainment commencing on the date of arrival, i.e. 28th March. A suitable date, so far as the Sultan is concerned, for Hie Highness to be received in audience by The King, would appear to be at the beginning of the week commencing 4th April, and we shall be grateful if you will consider whether this can be arranged. We note that it may be necessary for the Sultan to go to Windsor il His Majesty is in residence there during the period in question. I enclose a memorandum giving a brief description The Rt. Hon. Sir Alexander Hardinge, GCVO., KCB., MC.&lt;A ^ ^ J / i maiMPJM (a) The Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. (b) His Highness Sultan Saiyid Said bin The Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. His Highness Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur T^rg-ITOHY . Oman in its geographical sense represents the South Eastern corner of the Arabian Peninsula from Abu Dhabi in the North to the borders of the Aden Protectorate. Politically speaking, the Sultanate consists of the littoral extending from Has Musandam at the entrance of the Persian Gulf along the East and South coasts to Has Fartak in Central South Arabia, a coast line of 1,100 miles, together with the overseas possession of Gwadur, an important Mekran port which hanules the trade of much of Southern British Baluchistan and South Eastern Persia, anu is situated on the Imperial Air Route to India. HISTORICAL . This maritime Arab State is believed by some op to have been the original home of the Phoenicians. Its sailors carried the trade between Babylonia and India, and its seas were the cradle of navigation. 'Oman figures befoi* the rise of Islam as an appanage of Persia, ana in turn fell into the hands of the Abbasid Caliphs of Baghdad, but from the Middle Ages onwards secured independence under its own native rulers. The present dynasty rose in 1741. Napoleon, to further his Indian designs, regarded the Sultanate as of such importance as to seek an alliance, but 5 the period of greatest prosperity came seventy years later unuer the Sultan Salyid 3a'id, the greag great grandfather of the present Sultan. He ruled from 1807 to 18S6 and was perhaps one of the greatest Arab figures to appear since the Arab prophet. He extended his influence northwards and asserted his mastery over the entire Persian Gulf. He invaded and colonised Zanzibar and the adjacent East African territory. He presented a frigate to our Royal'll* Navy and received a handsome yacht, the “Prince itegent', in return. The Sultanate has »ince then diminished gradually in importance, largely as a result of the influence on Muscat trade of the development of steam navigation and the opening of the Sues Canal. Internal disaffection and rebellion have restricted the authority of the Sultan to the coastal districts. British policy has throughout this later period been chiefly concerned with suppressing (a) the Slave Trade and (b) the Arms Traffic. Both had their centre in Muscat, which derived from them great wealth. Muscat was the slave market for South East ..tabla and the armoury for European arms destined to be smuggled across the Persian Gulf for Afghanistan, Baluchistan and the North West Frontier. Both have disappeared largely through the activities of the Aoyal Navy and the collaboration of the Sultan under Treaty obligations. PHYSICAL ESaIUKKS . The dominant physical features of Gfiian are (I) a lofty range of mountains running almost parallel with the coast, the great backbone of the country rising toj a height of 10,000 feet in Jebel Akdhar, (II) a coastal plain distinguisned for a date grove one hunured and fifty miles long and from three to seven miles in depth, (III) beyond the mountains, the immense spaces of Kuba al Khali, the Great Desert. The deep waters off the Oman coasts render navigation simple, and Muscat is a safe as v;ell as a very beautiful, harbour. summer climate of Muscat is intensely hot and there is scarcely any difference between day and night temperature. It was of Muscat that the Persian poet wrote ’And herethe panting sinner receives a foretaste of his future destiny'. The average rainfall varies between three and six inches. POPULATION . The total population of Oman has been estimated at 500,000, representing perhaps 15% of the entire population of the Arabian peninsula. 80% of these are tribal Arabs, there is a considerable pure negro element generally in domestic service, and a less numerous foreign trading element which consists of British Indians, Persians and Baluchis. There is a large admixture of African blood in the population at large, as also in the Ruling Family. PRODUCTS rtND TRADE . The overseas trade is largely with Bombay, Aden and Zanzibar, though America takes a considerable portion of Oman's date crop for her own black population. The fisheries, chiefly shark for export to the! Par East, are of second importance to the date industry. The camels of Oman are famous throughout Arabia, but the country is too parchea to allow the horse to flourish and very few are bred. Indigo dyeing, copper and brass work and cloth weaving are among other industries, and there is a crude but characteristic variety of gold ana. silver work, especially used for sheaths ana mountings of daggers and swords. RELIGION . The majority of the inhabitants belong to the Ibadhi sect of Islam, which is elsewhere found in Morocco. Fiercely intolerant of other creeds, Oman has been traditionally hostile to foreign penetration, and the Sultan himself, disapproved of for his infidel associations, has never deemed it expedient to visit the interiormountains. The tenets of Ibadhism, in their puritanical narrowness, resemble the Wahabism oi Central Arabia# GQVIlRNiVI;NT . The Government of the Sultanate is patriarchal or feudal, and judged by western bureaucratic standards is without much system or efficiency, but it admirabiy suits the conditions and needs of the inhabitants. It was formerly a theocracy, but the Sultan now exercises only temporal functions. (b) HI3 HIGHNESS SULInN...MLY IS The Sultan succeeded his father, Sultan Salyid Taimur bln Faisal bin Turk!, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., on the latter's abdication In 1932. He Is now 27 yearn old and is unmarried. He has a pleasant personality, and though short in stature (about S'2'), boars himself with considerable dignity and Is j endowed with a quiet sense of humour. He Is shrewd and energetic, with a flair for finance, and has a will of his own. He speaks excellent English, which he learnt at the Chiefs' College, Ajmer, where he received part of his education. The Sultan was faced with a difficult task when he came to the throne. The State was practically bankrupt and there were also signs of tribal unrest in various parts of the Muscat territory. He had, in addition, a crowd of 'wicked uncles', one of whom, Salyid Hamad, was Governor of the outlying district, of Sohar, where he had practically 8et| up an independent regime. The young Sultan tackled his difficulties with considerable resolution. The first step he took was to proceed to Sohar in the State gunboat with a detachment of the Muscat Infantry and with a set of irons wnich he said he would place on his uncle if he proved recalcitrant. It was a bold move and successful. SaiyidHamad climbed down, was made Wall of IvAittra where he could be under the eye of the Sultan, and aince then the 'wicked unci sb” have been well under control. The Sultan also set about the reorganisation of the State finances with zeal and not a little skill, and with the assistance of the local British authorities was success ful in bringing the State off the rocks. It is now financially in a comparatively flourishing condition. The Sultan is duly grateful for this assistance. At the same time the fact that the State for some years previously was unavoidably run under British administration has made him sensitive in the matter of British control, and he has recently shown an increasing desire to assert his independence. The Sultanate is not a British Protectorate. In law it has independent sovereign status. Besides its Treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government it has treaty relations with Prance and America, and before the Great War these powers had consuls stationed at Muscat. In practice, however, British influence in the State is not challenged by any other nation. The Sultan has submitted proposals for the revision of his Treaty with Mis Majesty's Government, and it is probable that informal discussions will take place with him during his visit to England. Last November the Sultan paid a State visit to India lasting ten days, during which time he was the guest of His Excellency the Viceroy for three days. On the termination of this visit he proceeded on a world tour, including visits to Japan and the United States of America. He arrived in America on thelOth February and is travelling to England froc New York in the s.s. 'Queen Mary'. While in iUEerica he will be treated as a State guest for a short period and will be received by the President.Minute Paper. political Department, &lt;r. The Sulton has recently confirrred hie intention of proceeding to this country from America in the S.S.'Q,ueen Mary ', and the Government Hospitality Fund are now en^ap'ed in preparing a suitable prop'ramme of entertainment comnencina; from the date on which the party reach Sn^land, i.e. 28th March. Perhaps the most suitable moment for the Sultan to be received by the Kin^ will be towards the end of the v/eek ending the 2nd April. This will leave a few days for the Sultan to settle down and give us time to sound U&gt; him about the K.C.I K. In connection with the * s * programme arrangements it will be useful to have early information of the date on which the Sultan is to be received by the King and I accordingly suggest a draft letter to ^ir Alexander Hardinme on this point. At the same time we might send to the Palace a copy of the attached memorandum regarding (a) the Sultnrtffeof Muscat and Oman and (b) His Highness the present Sultan. In accordance with the Political Resident's suggestion part (a) has been based on the similar memorandum (Flag prepared at the time of the visit of the previous Sultan, while pa.rt (b) is based on the recent note (Flag B) regarding the Sultan submitted by Sir Trenchard ^owle. K474B Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IOPDraft Paper pcli t i c al Department 2^? DRA^T LETTER. V~*\ The Rt.Hon. Sir Alexander Hardin^e, G.C.V.O., K.C.B., M.C. Tould you kindly refer to your letter of the 17th Decemher 4ro- Hired about the Sultan of Muscat’s visit to England ? We' recently received a message from the Sultan confirming his intention of pperceed4*ng to this country by the S.S.”Q,ueen Mary”, and the Government Hospitality Fund have now been asked to prepare a suitable programme of entertainment commencing on the date of arrival, i.e. 28th March. pfifhnpg tinn m~nnt suitable momerrfc ^ cka 'flu SuAtam 'us CmctAruxi ^ for His Highness to be received in audience by the King wiJrl be towards—the &amp;fKi of the week ending 2fod April, and we shall be grateful if you will consider whether this can be arranged. We soe- rro oo r ^y the Sultan should not go to Windsor if His Majesty is in residence * 0 rt— th?rt^place during the period in question, r I enclose a memorandum giving a brief description of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman and of His Highness the present Sultan. 647 4a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IOPV (a) The Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. (b) His Highness Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur, TERRITORY . Oman in its geographical sense represents the South Eastern corner of the Arabian Peninsula from Abu Dhabi in the North to the borders of the Aden Protectorate. Politically speaking, the Sultanate consists of the littoral extending from Has Musandam at the entrance of the Persian Gulf along the East and South coasts to Ras Partak in Central South Arabia, a coast line of 1,100 miles, together with the overseas possession of Gwadur, an important Mekran port which handles the trade of much of Southern British Baluchistan and South Eastern Persia, and is situated on the Imperial Air Route to India. HISTORICAL . This maritime Arab State is believed by some to have been the original home of the Phoenicians. Its sailors carried the trade between Babylonia and India, and its seas were the cradle of navigation. Oman figures before the rise of Islam as an appanage of Persia, and in turn fell into the hands of the Abbasid Caliphs of Baghdad, but from the Middle Ages onwards secured independence under its own native rulers. The present dynasty rose in 1741. Napoleon, to further his Indian designs, regarded the Sultanate as of such importance as to seek an alliance, but the period of greatest prosperity came seventy years later under the Sultan Saiyid Sa’id, the great great grandfather of the present Sultan. He ruled from 1807 to 1856 and was perhaps one of the greatest Arab figures to appear since the Arab prophet. He extended his influence northwards and asserted his mastery over theentire Persian Gulf. He invaded and colonised Zanzibar and the adjacent East African territory. He presented a frigate to our Royal Navy and received a handsome yacht, the 'Prince Regent', in return. The Sultanate has since then diminished gradually in importance, largely as a result of the influence on Muscat trade of the development of steam navigation and the opening of the Suez Canal. Internal disaffection and rebellion have restricted the authority of the Sultan to the coastal districts. British policy has throughout this later period been chiefly concerned with suppressing (a) the Slave Trade and (b) the Arms Traffic. Both had their centre in Muscat, which derived from them great wealth. Muscat was the slave market for South East Arabia and the armoury for European arms destined to be smuggled across the Persian Gulf for Afghanistan, Baluchistan and the North West Frontier. Both have disappeared largely through the activities of the Royal Navy and the collaboration of the Sultan under Treaty obligations. PHYSICAL FEATURES . The dominant physical features of Oman are (I) a lofty range of mountains running almost parallel with the coast, the great backbone of the country rising to a height of 10,000 feet in Jebel Akdhar, (II) a coastal plain distinguished for a date grove one hundred and fifty miles long and from three to seven miles in depth, (III) beyond the mountains, the immense spaces of Ruba al Khali, the Great Desert. The deep waters off the Oman coasts render navigation simple, and Muscat is a safe as well as a very beautiful, harbour. CLIMATE . Encircled by precipitous volcanic cliffs, the summer climate of Muscat is intensely hot and there is scarcely/scarcely any difference between day and night temperature. It was of Muscat that the Persian poet wrote ’And here the panting sinner receives a foretaste of his future destiny’. The average rainfall varies between three and six inches. POPULATION . The total population of Oman has been estimated at 500,000, representing perhaps 15^&gt; of the entire population of the Arabian peninsula. 80 c /c? of these are tribal Arabs, there is a considerable pure negro element generally in domestic service, and a less numerous foreign trading element which consists of British Indians, Persians and Baluchis. There is a large admixture of African blood in the population at laxge, as also in the Ruling Family. PRODUCTS AND TRADE . The overseas trade is largely with Bombay, Aden and Zanzibar, though America takes a considerable portion of Oman’s date crop for her own black population. The fisheries, chiefly shark for export to the Far East, are of second importance to the date industry. The camels of Oman are famous throughout Arabia, but the country is too parched to allow the horse to flourish and very few are bred. Indigo dyeing, copper and brass work and cloth weaving are among other industries and there is a crude but characteristic variety of gold and silver work, especially used for sheaths and mountings of daggers and swords. RELIGION . The majority of the inhabitants belong to the Ibadhi sect of Islam, which is elsewhere found in Morocco. Fiercely intolerant of other creeds, Oman has been traditionally hostile to foreign penetration, and the Sultan himself, disapproved of for his infidel associations/4 (O-'l?' associations, has never deemed it expedient to visit the interior/lnountains. The tenets of Ibadhism, in their puritanical narrowness, resemble the Wahabism of Central Arabia. GOYlktlvilvIENT . The Government of the Sultanate is patriarchal or feudal, and judged by western bureaucratic standards is without much system or efficiency, but it admirably suits the conditions and needs of the inhabitants. It was formerly a theocracy, but the Sultan now exercises only temporal functions. (b) His Highness Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur . The Sultan succeeded his father, Siultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal bin Turki, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., on the latter 1 s abdication in 1932. He is now 27 years oldtf^ /s , He has a pleasant personality, and though short in stature (about 5 } 2'), bears himself with considerable dignity and is endowed with a quiet sense of humour. He is shrewd and energetic, with a flair for finance, and has a will of his own. He speaks excellent English, which he learnt at the Chiefs’ College, Ajmer, where he received part of his education. The Sultan was faced with a difficult task when he came to the throne. The State was practically bankrupt and there were also signs of tribal unrest in various parts of the Muscat territory. He had, in addition, a crowd of 'wicked uncles', one of whom, Saiyid Hamad, was Governor of the outlying district of Sohar, where he had practically set up an independent regime. The young Sultan tackled his difficulties with considerable resolution. The first step he took was to proceed to Sohar in the State gunboat with a detachment of the Muscat Infantry and with a set of irons/irons which he said he would place on his uncle il he proved recalcitrant. It was a hold move and successful. Saiyid Hamad climbed down, was made Y/ali ol Muttra where he could be under the eye of the Sultan, and since then the ’’wicked uncles' have been w ell under control. The Sultan also set about the reorganisation of the State finances with zeal and not a little skill, and with the assistance of the local British authorities was successful in bringing the State off the rocks. It is now financially in a comparatively flourishing condition. The Sultan is duly grateful for this assistance. At the same time the fact that the State for some years previously was unavoidably run under British administration has made him sensitive in the matter of British control, and he has recently shown an increasing desire to assert his independence. The Sultanate is not a British Protectorate. In law it has independent sovereign status. Besides its Treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government it has treaty relations with France and America, and before the Great War these powers had consuls stationed at Muscat. In practice, however, British influence in the State is not challenged by any other nation. The Sultan has submitted proposals for the revision of his Treaty with His Majesty’s Government, and it is probable that informal discussions will take place with him during his visit to England. Last November the Sultan paid a State visit to India lasting 10 days, during which time he was the guest of His Excellency the Yiceroy for 3 days. On the termination of thi s visit he proceeded on a world tour, including visits to Japan and the United States of America. He arrived in America/a S 6, America on the 10th February and is travelling to England from New York in the s.s. n Q,ueen Mary”. While in America ^ Unll kx frill 61 he treated as a State guest for a short period and received by the President.FILE COPY P Z. g r? ‘&gt;5 =. 1 : (36 groups 0 ) 778. DJ5 C Y P H EH OP TELEGRAM^ From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Received Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India 0 Muscat,20tL February,1938„ 4 e 45 Pom., 20th February, j.938 0 X T/40. Addressed to Secretary of State for India copy by post to Government of India ,copy given to Political Agent, Muscat. Paragraph No.3 of //e2^ your telegram No. 349 « 19th February 0 2 0 Sultan's letter is presumably his 'reply thereto' and will take considerable time to reach Muscat from America. Suggest Sultan might be asked to send you direct an advance copy 0 REOo. POL. DEPT. 2 1! FEB 1938 INDIA OFFICETAgtaphic Address : Hospitality, Parl, London.' ' Te^hone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted G.ll. P. 1886. 1 Government hospitality I L » Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 18th February, 1938. Dear Gibson, ,® .A* Visit of the Sultan of Muscat. , ' ^ Thank you for your letter (P.Z. 968/38) of the 16th February, with which you enclosed:- 1. A list of suggested entertainments, 2. Programme of the Indian visit and 3. Letter from the Foreign Office on the subject of salutes. From the information you have given me, it should not be difficult to draw up a programme for the fourteen days during v/hich the Sultan of Muscat will be the guest of the Government, in fact, the difficulty will be to find enough time for even the starred items. I have had considerable experience of these Arab gentlemen, and I know that their powers of endurance are not very great, and that if one arranges a really full programme they rapidly tire, lose interest and ask for the cancellation of many items. Tl «c The sad thing is that he is coming at the very v/orst time of year, as the v/eather is generally atrocious, making outdoor entertainments a misery, and such things as a trip by water to the Port of London out of the question. However, next v/eek I will get down to the details of the programme and feel sure that we shall be able to arrange something that will please the Sultan. I think the Government Dinner should be early in the programme, say Tuesday, the 29th March. I will see what the Admiralty, War Office and Air Ministry can arrange on the lines of your suggestions, but we shall^ shall probably have to make use of Imperial Airways for a flight over London. I will try to keep the mornings free as much as possible and arrange that two or three evenings in each week are filled up. This I think we can do quite easily, the Government Dinner, one Greyhound Racing, one Palladium, one Cinema, one Speedway Racing and a theatre. Should you decide that it would be a good thing for the Sultan to broadcast in Arabic, I can arrange that the visit to Broadcasting House takes place at the same time* 1 note that there is no change in the Muscat flag, which is a plain red square* I will ask the Admiralty if they can arrange for a salute to oe fired when the Sultan arrives at Southampton. I note the change in the duties of the officials accompanying the Sultan. Yours sincerely, P.S. The Grand National, alas, is run on the Friday before the Sultan arrives.NO DISTRIBUTION. Decode 0 Sir R. Lindsay (Washington). il6th February, 1958. D. 4-4 p.m. 16th February, 1S38. R. 10.40 p.m. 16th February, 1958. No.125. (R). xxxxxxxxxxx * Your telegram N o.108. Message was conveyed through Mis Majesty r s Consulate-General at San Francisco to the Sultan who has now replied as follows:- ’'According to request of His Majesty's Government in the 'United Kingdom for an informal discussion for revision of 'Treaty of 1891 between us and His Majesty's Government I shall 'be pleased to discuss the same while I am their guest in 'London. 'I myself did not suggest discussion of political agree- 'ment regarding Oman Oil Concession but I will discuss the 'nature of the letter I received from His Majesty's Consul, 'Muscat and explain my reply thereto which I am sending him from 'here. This matter was presented to me by His Majesty's 'Consul three days before I left India and without previous 'understanding or any sort of agreement. &lt;* &gt; *** t&gt; **— 1 'maim**+*■***■**)** i&amp;m:^,*,,*,*' ***|i 'Please inform His Majesty’s Government that I shall visit ’them next month when I shall have the pleasure of being their 'guest. I shall leave New York for London on March 23rd on 'the Queen Mary'. I have the Sultan's addresses should you wish to get into touch with him during his journey across the United States. He now expects to reach .ashington by March 3rd.7^5/195/91) NO DISTRIBUTION. Code telegram to Sir R. Lindsay (Lashington) 5 Foreign Office, 9th February, 1958. 4.45 p.m. No. 103. (R). My desnatch No. 12 [of January 4th: Sultan of Muscat]. * Please inform Sultan if possible through His injesty s Consul-G-eneral at San Francisco, that His Majesty's Government feel that it might be of mutual advantage if opportunity were taken for an informal discussion of his proposals for revision of 1891 treaty while he is the guest of His Majesty's Government or subsequently, if His Highness contemplates extending his visit. His Majesty's G vernment would therefore be glad to know His Highness’ wishes in order that, if he agrees, necessary preparations may be made. 2o Sultan has himseli suggested that another matter - the political agreement regarding the Muscat oil concession - should be discussed during his visit, and you may inform him at the same time that His Majesty's Government would welcome discussion of this and any other question which he may wish to raise.Minute Paper. POLITICAL Department. 6474b ^ 1 iv. /v *«— — li / ^ The Programme of Entertainment. Sir Trenchard Fowle has put forward a very good selection and the only suggestion which I have to make is that, as in the case of the Sultan’s father in 1928 and the Sheikh of Bahrein in 1936, the programme of entertainment might include a Government Dinner to consist of about 30 to 40 persons, A list of guests who were invited to the Muscat Dinner of 1928 and the table plan of the Bahrein Dinner of 1936 will be found below. We do not usually hold receptions for distinguished visitors from the Persian Gulf, but it is perhaps worth while considering whether one might be arranged on the present occasion. Apart from the fact that we are anxious, at the present juncture, to create a good impression on the Sultan, it has to be remembered that it is the declared intention of the Sultan to visit Frairee-y It^ly and Germany on his way back to Muscat. We may, of course, be able to dissuade him from doing so, but if we fail it may be assumed that the Italian Government, at any rate, will go out of their way to fete His Highness. Whilst we should not wish to compete with the Italians in this direction, we ought perhaps to do everything possible to create a favourable impression on the Sultan, and since I understand that a small reception could be held without much expense, I put forward the suggestion for consideration. 2,The suggested Arabic broadcast. If this suggestion is adopted and the Sultan sticks to his idea of going to Italy, the Italians may take the cue from us and attempt to persuade him to broadcast a talk from that country. They may, of Wt 22530/P 114 10,000 9.37 IOP course/t course, do so in any case and for that reason alone it seems desirable that, provided His Highness is agreeable, arrangements should be made for him to broadcast from this country. It has been ascertained from the B.B.C. that arrangements can be made at short notice and in such circumstances it seems unnecessary to trouble the Ambassador at Washington to ascertain His Highness’s wishes in advance. Sh Accommodation. Accommodation has been arranged for the Sultan and his party at the Dorchester Hotel and in para.4 of his letter of the 29th December at P.Z.8422/37 Major Crankshaw asked us to find out whether the Sultan desires that a member of his suite should occupy a bedroom next to his own. It was originally intended that unless the local Political authorities could confident^:ly say what the Sultan’s wishes are likely to be in the matter, we should consult His Highness through the Embassy at Washington. Major Crankshaw now tells me that the Dorchester is not likely to be full during the period of the Sultan's visit and he thinks that it 7 /ill meet the case if His Highness' wishes are ascertained when he reaches England. In the circumstances we need not take any further action in regard to this point. 4. Muscat Flag. The Political Agent has now confirmed (see P.Z.925/38) that there has been no change in the Muscat Flag and we can pass this on to Mejor Crankshaw. 5. Salutes. Please see Foreign Office letter of 9th February at P.Z. In view of their recommendation it/Minute Paper. Department. it is suggested that if the necessary arrangements can he made, a salute should he fired on the Sultanas arrival at Southampton. It will he noted (Major Crankshaw’s letter of 11th January at P.Z. 256/38)that the Government Hospitality Fund do not anticipate any difficulty and that they are prepared to approach the Admiralty. 6. Draft letters to Mr. Baggallay and to Major Grankshaw in the light of the foregoing are submitted* «471B Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 IOPDraft Paper. political Department. DRAFT LETTER. H. L. Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office. Copy to Ma.jor Cra p^shaw Govt, jiospitallty Fund. In my letter of the 5th February No. P. Z. 774/38 I promised a further communication on one or two other points arising out of the Political Residents letter No.6/26 of the 19th January about the Sultan of Muscat’s visit to England. 2- As regards the suggestion that His Highness might broadcast a talk in Arabic, it has occurred to us that if thirs— rm 1 r nfinptiOfl, nnri the Sultan sti&lt; to his idea of visiting Italy on his way back to Muscat, the Italians may take the cu-o from us awd attempt to persuade him to broadcast a talk in his own language from that country. They:_jnay, -of eber so V- iiV-any case and -for that reason alone we are inclined to think that it would be an excellent thing if, provided that His Highness is agreeable, arrangements could be made for him to broadcast a short speech from London. If therefore the Foreign Office agree we would propose , to make arrangements accordingly. We understand from the-D. D-^C. ' that the arrangements can be made at short notice and subject to your views we are inclined to wait until His Highness reaches England before putting the matter to him. l* - I enclose for your information a copy of a letter which we have addressed to i'WHtwintFe. , . /^Z . qbS'Zt- Draft Paper. political Department. DRAFT Major E.N.S.Crankshaw, GMG•,MBE., Government Hospitality Fund, Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1 iETTER. Copy to Mr, lay, F.Q« (If C/-~ AL r pwnn *u* } 6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 &lt;).37 lop i)ccu Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 29th December (No.G.H.F. 1886) about the Sultan of Muscat f s visit? I ^5 2 I now enclose a list of entertainments 0 and inspections v/hich the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf thinks would interest as well as amuse His Highness. Those which he considers more important are starred. You may also like to see V the enclosed programme of sight-seeing and demonstrations which was arranged for H.H. f s entertainment during his recent State visit to Delhi. We understand that all the events were genuinely enjoyed and appreciated by His Tiu f*/l, 1*06 t*oM Highness. , the object of the greatest interest to the Sultan was his visit to the Imperial Agricultural Institute and certainly the greatest thrill he experienced was the demonstration by the | Delhi Flying Club at the At Home given in his honour and his night flight over Delhi in a machine of India Airways. ^ me* i The fact that His Highness knows English quite well makes the task of keeping him interested during his stay in England somewhat easier than if he only knew his native tongue and we hope that with these suggestions/suggestions you will have no difficulty in arranging a suitable programme of entertainment. i, On our own account we would suggest that among the items of entertainment might be included a Government Dinner - perhaps something on the same lines as the Bahrein Dinner in 1936 - to consist of about 30 to 40 persons. We are starting to work out a list of names. ^, When arranging the programme the general idea might be^ to fill in His Highness f s afternoons and evenings with entertainments, etc., while keeping the mornings free for o££io4€el/discussions*'* In connection with the proposed visit to the B.B.G. headquarters, the suggestion has been made and is now under consideration that His Highness should be invited to broadcast a short speech in Arabic giving his impressions of. what he had seen in England during his visit. If the suggestion is put into practice it wil be desirable to arrange that the visit to Broadcasting House takes place tov/ards the end of his visit. In this connection I enclose for your information a copy of a letter which we have sent to the Foreign Office on the subject. We will advise you in due course when a decision is reached. With regard to para. 4 of your letter of the 29th December, the local Political Authorities are unable to say what/ * 1U+, kfru. tu. ,what His Highness’s wishes are likely to he in regard to the point raised. I understand^ however, that you consider that it will meet the case if His Highness’s wishes are obtained on his arrival in England, and we are therefore not taking any further steps /fW ^ A* 1 fiirvvii' tk*- It. + Htlzi 6474 a /t 22530/P 14 t . 10 , 00 a &lt;j.37 lOli , 4 , A ^ t T UL *’ in the matter. 7 We have obtained confirmation from the local Political Authorities that there has been no change in the Muscat flag, which is a plain red square. &lt;f- We consulted the Foreign Office regarding the question of Salutes and I now enclose a copy of a letter setting out their viev/s. On the whole we are inclined to think that, if the '‘necessary arrangements can be made without undue trouble, a salute should be fired on the Sultan’s arrival at Southampton, and we should be glad if you would approach the Admiralty accordingly. * 7% /c, I am sending a copy of this letter to Baggallay at the For^i-g ^Office and l Seal at the Admjj^lty. SlH-tcvnl y (Sgd.) J. p, QIBSONGOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Telegraphic Address: “ Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. Treasury Chambers, All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted :- Whitehall, S.W.l 2nd February, 1938, Dear Symon, I enclose a list of the persons suggested for the Dinner to the previous Sultan of LJuscat. The number attending was 24* Those on the list marked , x* attended; those indicated by an ’R* refused. Gonmodore Pearson seems to have been the only ‘’reserve” not invited. Table Plan of Dinner to the Sheikh of Bahrein also enclosed. Yours sincerely. A.C.B.Symon, Esq., India Office.HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT IN THE TED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND TABLE PLAN OF DINNER TO HIS EXCELLENCY THE SHEIKH OF BAHREIN LANCASTER HOUSE St. James’s The Most Hon. The Marquess of Zetland, G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E. In the Chair THURSDAY, the 18th JUNE, 1936List of Guests suggested for Dinner in honour of His Highness The Sultan of Muscat on 11th October, 1928 * S5r John Shuckburgh * Sir Percy Cox x Sir Gilbert Clayton Sir Sefton Brancker - Air Minister ’H* His Hi^iness The Aga Khan x General Sir H. Hudson ; Sir Henry Wheeler ) Political Commit tee of the India Council •H* Sir William Marris ) * Sir Malcolm Seton - Deputy Under Secretary of State * Mr, Lancelot Oliphant - Foreign Office * Lord Monteagle - Foreign Office ’H* Lieutenant-Colonel Prideaux last Resident of Persian Gulf * Lieutenant-Colonel A, P, Trevor - last but one - ditto - 'H* Lieutenant-Colonel Sir A # T. Wilson * Captain R, St, P, Parry - last Senior Naval Officer in Persian Gulf Coramodore J, L, Pearson - the above officers predecessor x Mr, L, D. Wakely - Political Secretary, India Office »R* Mr. P. J. Patrick - India Office * Mr. J. G. Laithvvaite - India Office x Lieutenant-Colonel S.B.A.Patterson - Political A.D.C. India Office x Mr. H.W.W.McAnally - Air Ministry x Group-Captain R.P. Ross - Air Ministry *H* Sir Ronald Lindsay - Foreign Office * Field-Marshal Sir Claud Jacob - India Office * Sir Muhammad Rafique - India Office x Captain G.H.Lang - Radio Communication Company x D,T. Monteath, Esq., - India Office and The Sultan’s party x H.H.The Suit an of Muscat x Saiyid Theeyab * Mr. Bertram Thomas * Mr. E.E.Beare Those marked * attended the Dinner Sir Sefton Brancker dropped out at the last moment ’R* indicated refusalEXTRACT from Muscat Intelligence Summary for the period from 1st October to 15th December 1937 SECRET. No. 14 of 1937* For the Sultan*s stay in Delhi the Government of India had arranged a varied and comprehensive programme of sight seeing and demonstrations of different sorts. These were all genuinely enjoyed and appreciated by His Highness. Perhaps the object of the greatest interest to the Sultan was his visit to the Imperial Agricultural Institute and certainly the greatest thrill he experienced was the demonstration by the Delhi Flying Club at an At Home given in his honour and his night flight over Delhi on a machine of India Airways.^ 1 EXTRACT PROM EXPRESS LETTER PROM POLITICAL RESIDENT, BUSHIRE, TO SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT, DATED 19TH JANUARY, 1938, ( a ) Hilitar y. (D X ( 2 ) (3) Inspection of a capital ship, with possibly a submarine trip added. Inspection of a military mecahanised unit at work. Inspection of an R. A •P• aerodrome and latest machines. ('b) Historical and General. X (l) House of Commons in session. Visit to Cenotaph to lay a wreath. Westminster Abbey. Mint. Tower of London. Windsor Castle. Port of London docks. London County Council Offices. Hendon Police School. National Portrait Gallery. X % X X Imperial War Museum or Royal United Service Institute. X (12) British Broadcasting Company^ headquarters. X (13) Visit to Court of Criminal Appeal in session. British Museum (with special reference to M.S.S. in Arabic section).(19) Car Factory. * (20) Visit to large London hospital. (c) Sntertainments. X (1) Visit to Grand National if possible, otherwise any other race meeting. (2) Greyhound and/or speed way racing (3) Boxing. X (4) Falconry meeting if available. (5) M adame Tus s aud 1 s (6) Ice Hockey. (?) Theatres (preferably Ballet or musical comedy). (8) Cinema (if possible to see a news film featuring himself). (9) Coliseum or Palladium 'non-stop variety'.^ His Highness Saiyid Said hin Saiyid Tairmir, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, will pay a State Visit to Delhi as the guest of ohe Government of India in 'ovemher 1937* The programme to he followed during His Highness’s stay in Delhi will he as follows:- His Highness the Sultan of Muscat’s programme. November 1937. 12th (Friday) Arrive New Delhi PUBLIC ARRIVAL. Dinner at Viceroy’s House. 13th (Saturday) 14th (Sunday) Stay at Viceroy’s House. 15th (Monday) Leave Viceroy’s House and proceed privately to Maiden’s Hotel where he will he met hy Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department (Afternoon) Visit hy Deputy Secretary, Government of India, External Affairs Dept., to His Highness. 16th (Tuesday) 11 a. m. (Afternoon) Visit to Council of State and Secretariat. Visitors. 7 - 8.30 p.m. Tea Party at Maiden’s Hotel. 17th (Wednesday) 11 a. m. Visit to Delhi Fort. 8.30 p.m. Official Dinner to he given hy Foreign Secretary at Imperial Hotel. 18th (Thursday) 11 a. m. Visit to the Imperial Agricultural Institute. (Afternoon) Visitors. 19th (Friday) Rest. 20th (Saturday) 11 a.m. Visit to Broadcasting Station.I * ^ *- r «•. ' V '■''*■* f) ' , ’ .PCREIGN 0PRICE, S.W.l. (E 65C/195/91). /■N i Q y 9th February, 1938. Dear Symon, I write with reference to our telephone conversation of the 3rd February about the question of a salute being fired on the occasion of the Sultan of Muscat’s arrival in this country in March. As I explained then, we feel that since the Sultan will not be coming as a guest of His Majesty, The King, but only as a guest of His Majesty’s Government, a salute is not necessary. On the other hand there are so far as we can see no objections of a ceremonial kind to the firing of a salute if any political advantage is to be derived therefrom. We understand that the Sultan will be visiting other European countries, including France and Italy, when he leaves England, and if he received salutes from them after failing to receive one here, he might draw conclusions/ A.C.B. Symon, Esq. FEB 1938 INDIA OFFICE *conclusions unfavourable to ourselves. The India Office are, however, in a better position than we are to judge what importance would have to be attached to his conclusions on such a subject. Taking it all in all, we should be inclined to recommend giving him a salute and having done with it unless we can clearly remain indifferent to his disappointment on such a point.THK/MMo (22 words c) 540 o DECODE OF T E LEGH A ) &amp;« From Political Agent, Muscat^ to Secretary of State for Xndiao Dated Muscat, 8th February, 1938« Received 8th February, 1938 e Addressed Secretary of State for India, repeated by post to Bushire* Reference to your PoZo 339/38 of January 15thc There has been no change in the Muscat flag* RE£«. POL KPT. 8 FEB 1938 INDIA OFFICEA v\ M- GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbpartmint, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From political Resident, Bushire. 51 &gt; ^lep Political Agent, Muscat* Repeated to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. No* 67-S of 1938. Dated 26th January 133 8 Subject : Sultan of Muscat’s visit to England. I enclose herewith copy of India Office letter No.p,z # 239/38 dated 15th January 1938* 2 . Please telegraph India Office whether there has been any change in the Muscat flag.' P. Z. ] GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ; O Department. L—,j EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). This xs an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 69-5 of 1938. Bushir e XJU 5 XXX r&gt; the 26th January W Prom To Political Resident, Eushire# 19 38., ecretary of State for India, India Office, London* Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi© Political Agent, Muscat, Subject s Tour of Sultan of Muscat, Reference my Express Letter No©7l9-S dated 19th October 1937. Sultan has telegraphed Political Agent, Muscat, as follows begins 1 wP /'L r\vr 4. ry _... * » ♦; Draft Paper. URGENT . H.L. Baggallay. Eso., F. 0. d/- 3Cth January and 1st February. / / / / H- ^ Department. . &gt;5 FEB 1 Q ^ lear Baggallay, I enclose, for ready reference, copies of telegrams from the G. of I. and. the Political Resident (copies have already been sent officially to the F.O.) dealing with the possibility of carrying the discussions relating to the new Treaty with Muscat a stage further during the Sultan’s visit to London. I also enclose a copy of the Political Resident’s express letter of the 19th January, para. 5 of which deals with this matter. It is desirable that we should know as early as ray be convenient whether the Sultan is himself willing to engage in treaty discussions while in London, since we need to give Fowle ample notice if his presence in London is required. We should be glad, therefore, if the Sultan might be approached, -through H.M.*s Ambassador at Washington and the Consul-General at San Francisco. It might be explained to T .H. that H.M.G. feel that it might be to the mutual advantage of both parties if the opportunity of the Sultan’s visit to England were taken for a quite informal discussion of his proposals for revision of the 1891 Treaty, either during the fortnight for i which he will be in receipt of the hospitality/' hospitality of H.M.G. or subsequently if H.H. contemplates extending his visit to England beyond that period. The Sultan has himself suggested that another matter - the political agreement with Petroleum Concessions Ltd. - might be discussed during his visit to London. From this it seems probable that H.H. might not be averse to taking the opportunity of his visit for the discussion of business matters of urgency and importance. In the matter of the Treaty (to which, as H.M.G. are aware, the Sultan, like themselves, attaches considerable importance)it is felt that such personal discussion, at any rate of a preliminary character, might be of matbrial assistance in helping to expedite the negotiations and to facilitate agreement would therefore be glad to know His Highness’s wishes in order that, if he agrees that it would be of advantage to have such a discussion, they may make the necessary preparations. I hope to write to you shortly on one or two other points arising out of the Resident’s letter, but as the above is urgent, I am dealing with it separately. Yours sincerely, (Sga.) J. P. GIBSON87 . Addressed to Secretary of State for .S India, repeated to Government of Indiao paragraph No*4 of Government of India’s telegram No o198, January 30tho Sultan arrives at San Prancisoo February 10th ( vide enclosure to your express letter P.Zo76, January 5th). To save time I suggest that Ambassador, Washington, should make preliminary enquiry from Sultan through Consul-General, San Francisco. RECd. POL KPT. 3. FLB1938 INDIA OFFICEI9B, Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Bushire. Bushire express letter No«C/26 dated I9th January, 19*58. Sultan of Muscat 1 a visit to England* g B Paragraphs 2 and 3. We agree and have no cormnentsc 3. Paragraph N 0 o 4 « Daly will probably not be available, as he may have be sent to Pondicherry to relieve Ryan* This would make it difficult to send Watts, and we think that some other officer e.g- Colonel Loch, already in England might be used for the purpose of looking after the Sultan* 4. Paragraph No.5. We agree that, if His Highness favours 4 discussion of treaty, it would be a good thing to tr.; and obtain decisions during his stay in London. In that event we consider Powle should go home on brief deputation as suggested by him* We agree with Powle that prelirainary enquiry should be ijiade from Sultan through Washington Embassy since, if Sultan declines tc discuss treaty in London, there would obviously be ny point in Fowie going to London. UiF-Sfl. P0L. ( StP* t JAN 1938 INDIA OFFICEGOVERNIM . INDIA. OOHHOS'lTI Ai.. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to be treated, on receipt, with the earns expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and to ohvintt formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a r„ r o»,M. officer, m.D'tartmeM.i of f t „ of ta&lt; Political K««laent vt . in the Pere lan (lulf, * V?6 of 1938. iiask.. the 0««p, Kuwait. 19 . dXXdkU*’ 19t« January, 38. Xx Proa - To Political Resident, Ruanire, at Kuwait* Secretary to tne u or eminent of India, External Affaire Department, New Delhi* your / Repeated Secretary of State for India, London* Political Agent, Huecat* 3ub.i ectt '.Sultan of Muscat 1 a vialt to England. 1^ } &lt;Ma/ Reference your telegram No.bS of tne Ihth January as icing for my rievs on India Office Express letter ao.P. £.7666/37 of tne ?. 2 nd Decern Per 1937* i 2* As regards paragraph 2 of aboTe«mentioned Express Letter. I hare selected below various entertainments and inspections which I thinic would interest as well as amuse nim* Those wnicn I consider more important are starred. The fact tnat rtis Hi miess Knows English quite well maxes tne tasK of Keeping nim interested during hl» stay In Knglnnd soraswnat aasler tnan If ne only Know nls native tongue. (a). Military* *U) Inspection of a capital snip, witn possibly a submarine trip added* *( 2 ) Inspection of a military mecnaniaed unit at work. *(3) Inspection of an R.A.p. aerodrome and latest - pf-'Fta , I S. 44. MFP—985 S&amp;P-(M-1597)—27-11-36—10,000. {Signature) {Designation)- 2 - latest njacnines. (b). Historical and General. # (1) House of Comnons in session. ♦ (2) Visit to Cenotapn to lay a wreatn. * (3) Veetminster Abb^y. ♦ (4) Mint. ♦ (5) Tower of London* ( 6 ) Vindsor Castle. * (7) Port of London docics. * ( 8 ) London County Council Offices. * (9) Hendon Police Scnooi. (10) National Portrait Uallery. (11) Imperial far Museum or Royal United 8 err ice Institute. * (12) Britisii Broadcasting Compares headquarters, (*ee^ x pRr*gfrapJt/3 below). * (13) Visit to Court of Criminal Appeal in seasi on. * (14) Britisn Museum (with special reference to M.3*3,ln Arabic section). (lb) Any Agricultural College. (16) Scotland Yard. (17) Inspection of Ciril Air Factory. (18) Inspection of yacnt building yard and suitable yacnta as His Highness is thinicing of buying ons of the latter. (19) Car Factory. * (20) Visit to large London hospital. (c)• Entertainments. * (1) Visit to flrand national if possible, otnerwise any otner race meeting. (2) Greyhound and/or speed way racing. (3) /(de Oaury infonas me tntt the late King All of tna^rtedjaa was very interefited in Service coxing, and it may also interest His highness)• (3&gt; Boxing. * (4) Falconry meeting if available. (5) Madame Tu 8 B&amp;ud f s ( 6 ) Ice Hockey# (7) Theatres (preferably Ballet or musical comedy). ( 8 ) Cinema (if possible to see a news film featuring himself)• (9) Coliseum or Palladium ’•non-stop variety 4 . The general idea might be to fill in His Highness* a afternoons and evenings with entertainments etc. while Keeping the mornings for discussions on tne treaty (see paragrapn b below)• I am entirely in favour of the a ingest ion that Hia Highness might broadcast a talk in Arabic. Possibly ne might give hia impressions of wn&amp;t he had seen in England during his visit. 4 Paragraph 3 of India Office letter. Attachment of British Officer. Since Hie Hignneea knows ^glisn tne task of hia temporary A#B.C. will be rendered aomevraat easier, though it would be an advantage for this officer to Know Arabic. I suggest that either Major tfatts, or Colonel Daly - wno is relieving tiaj or fatta at Muscat - would be suitable, wnicn of tnese two would be available would depend on tne date that Colonel Daly leaves England. Failing either of these sir.Bertram Thomas wo) Id be suitable, or Colonel Locn, or perm pa some other Department, e.g. the Colonial OfH ce, could provide some suitable officer.(0 ^ &lt;0&gt; -4- b. (1) Paragraph 4 of India Office letter, buggeetion for discussion of the revision of the ld91 treaty #itn tne Sultan. 1 thin* that such a discussion mlgnt prove very useful, and there is now sufficient material available (vide N correspondence ending Y/ith my TSxpreas letter *o.a27-3 of tne 14th December 1937) on which such a discussion could taice place. With Arab Rulers (as with other people) there is a psychological moment for approaching them, and I imagine that tne Sultan when in London should be in a receptive mood, rfe will be the guest of Government, ne will I understand oe received in audience by riis Majesty, and ne nay receive the honour of a K.C.I.2. It might be possible therefore to arrange during his visit an agreed draft of the new Treaty as between him and His Majesty's Government, leaving to a later date the formalities connected with tne confirmation of tne Treaty by the Dominions. (2) The Sultan himself is anxious to conclude tne / new Treaty as soon as possible, and I expect would welcome a discussion in London. I suggest, however, tnat tne proposal for this discussion might be made to him tnro^h tne Ambassador, Vashington, and his reaction reported. The message to His Highness might indicate the informal nature of tne discussions and pern&amp;ps be United with the proposal which rm himself has | made tn&amp;t the Political Agreement witn Petroleum Concessions ; Limited might be discussed during nis visit to Londoi, (vide sy Express letter No.865*»7 of the 20th December 1937} a in tills connection see also correspondence ending with my Express letter ao .O/lB of tfte latn January 1938. (3; T&amp;cre vould seem to oe obvious advantages in tne India Office suggestion taat a l-olitical Officer enould be avai lable /available to ta^e part in the (Uscuaeions. Such an ofiicer mi&amp;ht be (a) Major Watts or Colonel Daly or (b) myself on deputation. The advantage of (a) would be that one of tnese officers would be available in England. The advantage of ( b) would be that telegraphic references to me would be obviated, and I suppose that as Resident I would carry more weight vla-a-vls the Multan than a Political Agent. The Sultan and I have a mutual liking for each otner # (see paragraph 4 of my demi-official letter no. c/l 66 of the 16tn August 1937 to Parsons) ,and I daresay this might count for something, though Ido not rate this too nigh, as when it comes to business lea affaires s ont les affaires . If I were deputed it would necessitate my absence from the Gulf from three weeks to a month. For this period Mr. /eigntman could act for me without coming to Busnire, where current duties could oe carried on by Captain Galloway as Secretary and Consul. afl. T.C.Fowle. Political Resident intne Persian Gulf. Att est ed. for tne Political Reai _ Persian Gulf.&amp;r&lt;/ From (COPIES CIBCULATSD) Dated GoTernment of India? External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India. New Delhi, 20th January? 1938. fteceired 20th January? 1938? 12*15 pm* X Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Bushire• Political Resident's telegram from Koweit T-13, January 19th? 1938, Sultan of Muscat, 2„ Yfe agree with Tiev/s expressed in paragraph Bo,3, 3* Our obserTations on your letter P c Zo7666, December 12th, 1937, will follow on receipt of Fowle s views.PULE OOP X o £ — / | y3o G’;P/VH ;copiss■ CIRCUITED) (48 words. ) D SCOPE OF TSLEGB. aM From Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf to the Government ox India and repeated, by the former bo Secretary of State for India. Dated Received Knwait,19 th January,1933. 3 0 45 poEa c ,l- + jd January, 193 8 y, oi- t/15 o Addressed Government of India repeated Secretary of State for India, copy by mail to Muscat* Your telegram 51,16th January. 2 C My views on Secretary of State j express letter PZ.7666 ? 2£nd December, are being despatched to you by air mail leaving Basrah on 24th January 0 3 a Reference Secretary ox State's letter uo.P.b.76, 5th January. Ambeftsanor s? suggestion seems eminently suitable,jel^aphic Address : ' Hospitality, Parl, London.” ^•Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted G.H.F. 1886 1 - i^NT HOSPITALITY FUN Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, Sir, Jbu 10 ' l l h S.W.l 17th January, 1938• I am directed by the Minister in Chaise, Grovernnent Hospitality, to acknowledge receipt of your letter and enclosures (P # 2.l59/38j dated the 17th instant on the subject of the visit to this country of the Sultan of Muscat. I am. Sir, The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office. tQL DEPT. 18 JAN 1938 INDIA OFPK3E, :■ , ei 4k* I^Tflephone No, Address: “ Hospitality, Parl, London.’ Whitehall 1481. All communications should be^ » addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted G.Hv^.1886. GbVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND -J Dear Symon, RtAMtAldtSls (to. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 11th January, 1938. o/\ I have looked up precedents for the firing of salutes, and I find that when King Peisal came here as a Government Guest he had a salute of 21 guns from Dover Shore Batteries, and in addition was met hy Destroyers and v/as escorted across the Channel. Both these were arranged hy the Admiralty. When the Sultan of Muscat v/as here in 1928, he did not have a salute, hut this appears to have heen because he was in England privately before he became a Government Guest. The flag appears to be a plain red square. U* Perhaps you will let me know whether it is decided that he shall have a salute and I will ask the Admiralty to arrange. I do not expect it v/ill present any difficulties.' Mr, Gilpsony After consultation with Major Crankshaw and the Foreign Office I submit a draft reply to the Resident’s telegram of the 8th January,Draft Paper. politi cal P 2 -. / y f 7 Department . DRAFT TELEGRAM. Prom Secretary of State to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to the Political Agent, Muscat. l\lrui [v&amp;Lr 315 u.' 1938 Copy to P. 0. 7 Government Hospitality Fund (w/th copy of the irVard telpgram) India (hy ai]/mail). ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER NO. ^ 4 . IS.(At . I FRGM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AN&amp; ZFnofT DEPT. INDIA OfF^ Addressed to the Political Resident, repeated to Political Agent, Muscat, v \ \ Copy x&gt;y Air Mail to the Government of India.^ Your telegram No.32^of 8th January. / X Sultan’s visit to England. 7 n K x, 2. In accordance with usual \ &lt; &gt;v \ practice Sultan will he officially welcomed at Southampton by ^Government*'' V &lt; V K. representative who will wait Upon him at the ship; hut there will he no^ ceremony.\ v 3* If—oultan-eaila,—ag arranged, ^ 1 * hy the Queen Mary, there is no need for Iffim-te—tele graph-from New Yepk. (h* y tJUut ilu Como Hi) Hitjtmoo'' lotn+iU. ^JGrS/MMo FILE C.QP2 L . Z. RO \J -J . i9o8 (71 words^ DEC ODE 0Ji LXIlEjor^am, (COPIES CIRCULATED) From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India* Dated Riaher, 8th January, 1938. Received 2c30 pam*, 8th January, 1938* 32^ Addressed Secretary of State for India, repeated Political Agent, Muscat, copy by air mail to Government of UkU India* Muscat telegram T/10^ November 24th* Sultan's visit to Engl arid* Political Agent has received the following telegram from the Sultan* Begins, , Please telegraph whether Government representative will meet me at Southampton officially* ohall ] wire to London on deoarture from New York? Please reply to British Consul, Kobe, I am leaving Janan January 27th, Message ends* 2 * Presume answer to both questions is in the affirmative? Please confirm, repeating to Political Agent, Muscat, who should then telegraph accordingly to the Sultan,*’&lt;! ess: ' Hospitality, Parl, London.” Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted P&lt;r/ 5 . 'j 8422= OVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. \ /♦H* P.1886# &lt;r- H. £ Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 29th December, 1937. Dear Gibson, / 14 &lt;7 * Thank you for your letter (P.Z.7666/37) of the 24th December about the Sultan of Muscat’s visit. I note that the Sultan v/ill arrive at Southampton on the 28th March on the ’’Queen Mary”, and I therefore have noted the period for which he v/ill be the guest of the Government as from that date until Sunday, the 10th April. I am glad to know the names of the Sultan’s suite, and also that the Hyde Park Hotel will be suitable for the accommodation of the party. I v/ill book the rooms now. On previous visits of this sort the Potentate has desired that one of his suite should occupy a bedroom next to his own, and I shall be glad if you will find out v/hether the Sultan desires that, and if so, for v/hich member of his suite. Before doing anything about the programme, I will av/ait further word from you. Thank you for returning the programmes of the visits of the Sultan of Muscat in 1928 and the Sheikh of Bahrein in 1936. Yours sincerely, Ar J.P. Gibson Esq. , India Office. hfc fWi Credit^ ^ : 3'T- oJ.” f&amp;ADraft Paper. P.2. 7666/37 Department. DRAFT LETTER. Major E.N. S Crankshaw, G.M. G. , M. B. E. 9 Government Hospitality Fund, S. W. 1. 2 l™ /V'37. Would you kindly refer to your letter to Walton of the 1.9th Novemher (G. H. F.1886) about the forthcoming visit to England of the Sultan of Muscat* We have now heard that the Sultan has booked accommodation in the s.s. ’'Queen Mary', leaving New York on the 23rd March, and arriving at Southampton on the 28th March, and that it will l»&amp; meeting His Highness's wishes if the period of his entertainment as an official guest of His Majesty's Government commences on the date of his arrival in this country* The Sultan has also confirmed that his suite will consist of the following:- (1) Halal bin Badr, Secretary (2) Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubaily, State Official* (3) Saiyid Abdulmunim Zawawi, A.D.C* |f| The question whether, as was the case in 1928, a British officer should be attached to the Sultan during his visit, has been referred to the Government of India for consideration, and I will let you know more about this when we receive their views. We have also been informed that if the King's movements permit, His/His Majesty will 'be pleased to receive the Sultan after his arrival. As regards hotel accommodation, we agree that the Hyde Park Hotel would 'be quite suitable. V/e are consulting the Government of India and the local Political authorities d)out the programme of entertainment and will let you know when we receive their views. As requested, I return the programmej of the visit of the Sultan’s father in 1928j &lt;?* ^ u* Yfctirs « ''.rer+H* StP. cirsoifDepartment. ^4 BECuSt DRAFT EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Prom Secretary of State for India, To Government of India, Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Political Agent, Muscat. Copy F.O. yjks 'oty-t ^ ( ^ iaXk lUeLtMA. U\ *1' P^v^x******** tj, 'flu. 4A^v/* 1*10t\^Uu\a£o u* (Xui/nx. ^ui4 ^ O^W/- £ £ u^UCUU^ ^ IL 88 C. Please refer to the correspondence ending with Watts* telegram (addressed from Bombay) No. T/10 of the 24th November, regarding the Sultan of Muscat*s proposed visit to England. 2 .I enclose a statement containing particulars of the programme of entertainment which was arranged for the Sultan*s father in 1928 , and I should be glad to receive any suggestions which you may wish to offer in connection with the entertainment of Sultan Saiyid Said bin Tairaur. A visit to Broadcasting House be included in the programme and the suggestion has been made that the Sultan (or perhaps a member of his suite) might be invited to broadcast TcOK a short Bpoeah in Arabic, ^ I should i be glad to have your views on this suggestion. V A British officer (Mr. Bertram Thomas) was attached to the Sultan’s father during the 1928 visit, and consider that a similar appointment should be made on the present occasion I should be glad if you would recommend % ■ * - a suitable officer. 6030 Wt 9128—P 18 10,000 4.37 IOPPaper. Department. ^.Assuming that consideration of the Sultan’s proposals for revision of the 1891 Treaty will have proceeded sufficiently far, his oresence and entertainment in this country might give a good opportunity, if this is agreeable to the Sultan, for making further progress with the question by at any rate informal discussions with him. Atmosphere might be favourable for this and it might moreover save time in view of the delays inevitably involved in oti-a£3 net irons by telegraph rm aspects of the negotiations in which other n epts. of H.M.G. may tre concerned. For the purpose of such discussions or conversations, however, it would of course be desirable that we should have available here a political officer competent to conduct them, who might be either the officer attached to the Sultan for his visit or an officer deputed for the purpose of such treaty discussions. mi J. 0. WALTONVISIT 0? HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OP MUSCAT September - October 1928. ^ His H-j ghness 1 s Part y; - H.H. The Sultan of Muscat- and Oman (Sir Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal bin Turki, K. 0.1.E. , C. S. ... ) Saiyid Theeyab, Aide-de-Camp to His Highness Atta ched Br iti sh Of f icers : Mr. Bertram Thomas, 0. B.E. and Mr. Ernest E. Beare, C. B. E. Secretary; Government Hospitality, Treasury Chambers, S.X1,1. PBOGPAi IME Saturday, September 15th Afternoon 1.05 Arrive Xing’s Cross. Official Welcome by Representative of Secretary of State for India. Ceremonial Dress. Lunch 1.45 Hyde Park Hotel. Dinner. 7.00 Hyde Park Hotel Pull Evening Dress. Evening 8. 00 Leave Hotel 8.30 Duke of York’s Theatre, 'Many Happy Returns'. Sleep Hyde Park Hotel. Sunday, September 16th. Morning 9. 50 Leave Hotel Morning Dress 10.05 Arrive Westminster Abbey West Cloister door. Received by Canon in Residence. Lunch 1.00 Hyde Park Hotel Afternoon 2. 30 Kew Gardens, Richmond Park, etc. Lounge Suits &amp; Bowler Hats Dinner 8. 00 Claridge’s Hotel Pull Evening Dress Sleep Hyde Park Hotel. Monday, September 17th. Morning 10.40 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 11. 00 Lay Wreath on Cenotaph 11.10 Lay Wreath on Grave of the Unknown 'Warrior in We s tmins t e r Abb e y. 11.15/Lunch Afternoon Dinner Sleep Morning Lunch Afternoon Dinner Evening Sleep Morning Lunch Afternoon Monday, Sep tember 17th (cont. ) 11.15 Arrive Houses of Parliament. Received by Sir Thomas Butler, KCVO. , Secretary to Lord Great Chamberlain. 1.00 Hyde Park Hotel. 2.00 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 3.00 Arrive Windsor Castle by the Henry VIII Gateway and Visitors’ Entrance. Received by Inspector of the Castle. 7.00 Hyde Park Hotel Full Evening Dress 8. 00 Leave Hotel 8.15 London Pavilion 'This Year of Grace 1 '. Hyde Park Hotel. Tuesday, Sentember 18th. 11.30 Leave Hotel Lounge Suits &amp; Bowler Hats. 12.10 Arrive Kennington Oval. 'Champion County v. Rest of England' 1.45 The Oval At the Ova1 7.00 Hyde Park Hotel Full Evening Dress 8.00 Leave Hotel 8.10 Adelphi Theatre, 'Clowns in Clover.' Hyde Park Hotel. Wednesday. September 19th. 10,20 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 11.00 Arrive Royal Mint. Received by Sir Robert Johnson, KBE. , Deputy Controller. 12.15 Leave the Royal Mint 1.00 Hyde Park Hotel 2,30 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 3.00 Arrive British Museu m . Received by Sir Frederic Kenyon, QBE. &amp;c. , Director. Dinner/3 Dinner Evening Sleep Morning Lunch Afternoon Dinner Evening Sleep Morning Lunch Afternoon Dinner Evening Sleep T 7edne s day, Septen iber 19th (cont. ) 7.00 Hyde Park Hotel Pull Evening Dress 8.00 Leave Hotel 8.15 Arrive Winter Garden Theatre 3 ’’So This is Love” Hyde Park Hotel. Thursday. September 20th . 9.45 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 11.00 Arrive Croydon Aerodrome 12.45 Croydon Aerodrome Hotel. 2.00 Leave Aerodrome 3.00 Arrive Tower of London. Ceremonial Dress Received hy Col. Dan Burges* V. C. , D. S. 0. , Resident Governor. 6.00 Arrive Hyde Park Hotel 6.45 Leave Hyde Park Hotel 7.30 Crystal Palace Dinner Jackets 8.30 Pirework Display 9.15 Concert and Organ Recital Hyde Park Hotel. Frid ay . Sep te mber 21st . 9o 30 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 11.45 Arrive Portsmouth. Inspection of Ships. 12.45 With Admiral Superintendent at Admiralty House. 2. 00 Leave Portsmouth Toy subtna rine. 4.30 Arrive Southampton. Inspect S. S.'Aquitania”. Tea on hoard. 5.30 Leave Southampton hy car. 7.00 Arrive Branksome Tower Hotel, Bournemouth. 7.30 Branksome Tower Hotel Dinner Jackets Branksome Tower Hotel ' ' ' Saturday/Saturday, September 22nd. Morning 9.30 Leave Hotel Lunch 1. 00 Savemake Forest Hotel Dinner 7.00 Spread Eagle Hotel, Thame, Oxon. Sleep Mitre : Hotel, Oxford. Sunday, Sent ember 23 rd. Morning 9. oO Leave Mitre Hotel, Oxford. Lunch 1.00 Bull Hotel, Cambridge Dinner 7.00 George Hotel, Stamford Sleep !» tf tf Monday, Sentember 24th Morning 9.30 Leave George Hotel, Stamford Lunch 1. 00 ’'Ye Olde Bell’' Inn, Barnby Moor. Afternoon 6.30 Arrive Royal Station Hotel, York 7. 00 Civic Yelcome at Hotel by Lord Mayor Dinner 8.00 Royal Station Hotel, York. Sleep Royal Station Hotel, York. Tuesday, September 25th. Morning 9.30 Leave Royal Station Hotel, York. Lunch 1. 00 Spa Hotel, Ripon. Dinner 7.30 Royal County Hotel,Durham. Sleep Royal County Hotel, Durham. Wednesday. September 26th Morning 9. 30 Leave Royal County Hotel, Durham. Lunch 1.00 Abbey Hotel, Melrose Dinner 8. 00 City Chambe rs, Edinburgh, Guests of the Corporation. Sleep C' ledonian Hotel, Edinburgh. Thursday, September 27th. Morning Lunch 9.30 1.00 Leave Caledonian Hotel, Edinburgh Trossachs Hotel Dinner 7.00 Central Hotel, Glasgow Sleep Central Hotel, Glasgow. 4. Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Dinner Jackets. Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Dinner Jackets Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Ceremonial Dress. Dinner Jackets. Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Dinner Jackets. Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. 5\ill Evening Dress with Decorations Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Dinner Jackets Friday/Morning 9. 30 Lunch 1.00 Dinner 7.00 Sleep Old ] 1.00 Crown &amp; Mitre Hotel, Carlisle Morning Lunch Afternoon Dinner Sleep Morning Lunch Dinner Sleep Morning Lunch Afternoon Dinner Sleep Morning Windermere Dinner Jackets. Old England Lake Hotel, Windermere. Saturday, September 29th. 9.30 Leave Old England Lake Hotel, Lounge Suits and Windermere Bowler Hats. 1.00 Grosvenor H 0 tel, Chester In Chester 7.00 Grosvenor Hotel, Chester Grosvenor Hotel, Chester. Dinner Jackets. Sunday, Septemper 50th. 9.00 Leave Grosvenor Hotel, Chester. 1.00 Grand Hotel, Llandudno 7.00 Station Hotel, Holyhead Station Hotel, Holyhead. Mondayo, Oc tober 1st . 2.30 Leave Station Hotel, Holyhead fOr 2.55 Boat to Kingstown 5.50 Arrive Kingstown. 1.00 2.00 Leave Dublin 7.00 Royal George Hotel, Limerick Royal George Hotel, Limerick Tuesday. October 2nd. 9.30 Leave Royal George' Hotel, Limerick 1.00 Great Sourthern Hotel, Ki Harney 7.00 Great Southern Hotel, Ki Harney Great Southern Hotel, Ki Harney Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Dinner Jackets Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats Dinner Jackets Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Dinner JacketsWedn es day, October 3rd . Morning 9. 30 Leave Great Southern Hotel, Ki Harney Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Lunch 1. 00 Imperial Hotel, Cork. Dinner 7. 00 Grand Hotel, Tramore Dinner Jackets Sleep Grand Hotel, Tramore Thursday, October 4th. Morning 9.30 Leave Grand Hotel, Tramore Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Lunch 1. 00 Barry ’ s Hotel, Rathdrur/u Dinner 7. 00 Shelb ourne Hotel, Dub1in Lounge suits o to 00 Leave Hotel. Evening 8. 50 Boat to Holyhead 11.4-5 Arrive Holyhead Sleep Station Hotel, Holyhead. Frida y, October 5th . Morning 9.30 Leave Station Hotel, Holyhead Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Lunch 1.00 Hand Hotel, Llangollen Dinner 7.00 Raven Hotel, Shrewsbury Dinner Jackets Sleep Raven Hotel, Shrewsbury Satu rday-, October 6 th. Morning 9.30 Leave Raven Hotel, Shrewsbury, L 0 unge Suits and Bowler Hats. Lunch 1.00 Green Dragon Hotel, Hereford. Dinner. 7.00 Queen’s Hotel, Cheltenham. Dinner Jackets Sleep Queen’s Hotel, Cheltenham Morning 9.30 Leave Queen’s Hotel, Cheltenham Lounge Suits and , Bowler Hats.Sunday, October 7th (Cont,) Dinner 7. 00 Hyde Park Hotel Dinner Jackets Sleep Hyde Park Hotel Monday, October 8 th. Morning 10.30 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 11 . 00 by Arrive Guildhall. Received Lord Mayor Lunch 1.00 Hyde Park Hotel. Dinner 7.00 Carlton Hotel Pull Evening Dress. Evening 8.00 Leave Hotel 8 . 15 Carlton Theatre 'Good News' Sleep Hyde Park Hotel. Tue s day, October 9th. Morning 10.. 15 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 10.30 Embark on S. Y. 'St.Katherine' at Westminster Pier for Visit to Port of London. Lunch 12. 30 On Board S.Y. 'St.Katherine at Royal Albert Dock. Afternoon 4.30 Arrive at Westminster Pier and disembark. Dinner 7.00 Kettner’s Restaurant Pull Evening Dres Evening 8 . 00 Leave Restaurant 8.15 a London Hippodrome 'That T s . Good Girl' Sleep Hyde Park Hotel Wednesday, October 10th. Morning 10.50 Leave Hotel Lounge Suits and Bowler Hats. Lunch 1.00 Cambridge Afternoon 3.30 Leave 0ambridge Dinner 7.00 Hyde Park Hotel Dinner Jackets. Evening 8 . 00 Leave Hotel 8.15 Ma she lyne ’ s The a t re 'Magic &amp; Mystery' Sleep Hyde Park Hotel. Thursday/Thursday, OctQ' , oe r 11th , Morning Royal Air Force Display, Hendon. Ceremonial Dress Dinner 7.30 Sovrani’s Restaurant Full Evening Dre Evening 8.30 Leave Restaurant 8.45 Palladium Theatre, Variety. Sleep Hyde Park Hotel Friday, October 12th. Morning 10.45 Leave Hotel Ceremonial Dress 11.00 Arrive National Gallery, Received by Sir Charles Holmes, Director. 12.30 Leave National Gallery. Lunch 12.45 Cheshire Cheese Afternoon 2 . 00 Arrive Royal Courts of Justice. Witness Procession of Judges, &amp;c. Received by Lord Chief Justice. M u Dinner 7. 00 Hyde Park Hotel Dinner Jackets. Evening 8 . 00 Leave Hotel 8.15 Tivoli, Pictures. Sleep Hyde Park Hotel. Saturday, October 13th. Lunch 12.30 Hyde Park Hotel Ceremonial Dress Afternoon 1.15 Leave Hotel 2.00 Kempton Park Race Course: October Meeting. Dinner 6.30 Hyde Park Hotel Dinner Jackets. Evening 7.30 Leave Hotel 7.45 Coliseum or Cinema Theatre Sleep Hyde Park Hotel. Sunday, October 14th. Morning Leave for ContinentI have much pleasure in conveying to your at Uie request of Hia liajesty'a Ooverm^it an invitation from ids l&amp;jesty's Government to be their guest for a period of two from the tinse of Your Highness* arrival in Ingiand* It is understood that Your Highness proposes to reacfi ingland some time in March 1938* and 1 am requested to point out that it is essential tnat the exact date of four Highness* arrival in England should be known several seeks in advance in order that His Majesty’s Crovera ent my be able to arrange a suitable pro grams of enteriairiti.ont. It would be of great advantage if Your Hig/iness could coiiTiunicate to mo before you leave India a definite date on which Your Highness expects to reach upland. If, however, that is not possible, i am to request that you will communicate with colonel be&amp;ie, Political Aide-de-J&amp;mp to» Dear Hood, Thank you for your letter of yesterday about the Sultan of Muscat’s visit to England next year. The King will probably be at Windsor at the beginning of April, but there is no reason why he should not come down there to see His Majesty when the time comes. Yours sincerely, The Viscount Hood, Indai Office.16th December 1937. Dear Sir Alexander, Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 16th November to Clauson about the Sultan of MuscaVa visit to England next year? a passage in S.3. QUEEN MARY which is due to arrive in this country on March 28th. If The King will be pleased to receive the Sultan in audience the most suitable moment *ould therefore be some time at the beginnihg of April. I quite understand that it is impossible for His Majesty to enter into any definite commitments so far ahead, and the puipose of this letter is therefore only to ask you to be good enough to make a note of this alteration in the Sultan's plans. The Rt.Hon. Sir Alexander HardInge, GCVO., KGB., MC.FILE_£_QPV xzn IT/DI A. &lt;[4I-^roiip8) 5112, &amp;JS..C Y PiH B^R .Q TELEGRAM, (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom Dated Received 2299, frnment of India, External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India* New Delhi, 23rd November, 1937, 23rd November, 1937, 1-30 p.m. X Addressed to Secretary of State fdr r *1^33 India, repeated to Bushire, Your telegram N o,2758, November I7th 0 Invitation to Sultan has been conveyed as requested* 2 0 If possible, he will intimate date of arrival in England to us before he leaves Indian Otherwise, he will -inform Political Aide-de-Camp, India Office, as soon as possible* 3o Presumption (? s,omitted) regarding commencement of Sultanas treatment as official guest of His Majeslvy s Government and number of persons accompanying him are correct* ^1 P£Cg. POL, LTelegraphic Address : “ Hospitality, Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY and the following reference quoted 1886. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND. Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, S.W.l 19th Novemher, 1937. Dear Walton, I nave just written officially to say that my Minister has given sanction for the expenditure involved in the visit of the Sultan of Muscat next year, and we can now aeal with the detailed arrangements by semi-official correspondence. ihe first thing I should like to know is whether you ave any particular hotel in view for his accommodation. The last bultan of Muscat was accommodated at the Hyde Park Hotel during his visit in 1928, and I should like to take rooms at the same hotel on this occasion as they thoroughly understand how to look after this sort of people, and it is very conveniently situated. I will think out some sort of programme, but it , . will not be too easy as in March the v/eather conditions are no ^ very good lor outdoor events. But no doubt ,/ou will have ————- mar L ideas wnich I shall be glad to .have. I enclose programmes oi. the visit of the last ^Sultan of Muscat and also of the visit of the Sheikh of Bahrein which may 7 serve as a guide, and I make the following few suggestions:- Visit to Royal Military College, Camberley. Steeplechase Meeting. A Factory. The usual V/estminster Abbey, Houses of Parliament, British Museum etc., etc.^Telegraphic Address : “ Hospitality, Parl, London.' Telephone No.: Whitehall 1481. GOVERNMENT HOSPITALITY FUND Treasury Chambers, All communications should be addressed to the SECRETARY Whitehall, S.W.l and th e^jo llowing reference quoted: 9th November, 1937 G.H.F.1886 Sir rr I am directed by the Minister in Charge, Government Hospitality, to say in reply to your letter (P.Z.7247/37) of the 12th November, v/ith which you enclosed copy of a letter addressed to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that he approves the suggestion made by the Secretary of State for India that Kis Highness the Sultan of Muscat should be invited to be the guest of His Majesty’s Government for a period of tv/o weeks in 1938. 2. Sir Philip Sassoon notes that His Highness v/ill be accompanied by a Secretary, an Aide-de-Camp and one State Official, and suitable accommodation v/ill be arranged accordingly. 3. I am to say that the necessary details in connection v/ith the visit can be arranged by semi-official correspondence. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant The Under Secretary of State India Office.r / /C- 2 and address, not to any person by name, but to— Foreign Office. 1 “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. iS3 7 s.w.i Immediate — 18th November, 1937 Sir I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to request you to inform the Marquess of Zetland that he has had under consideration your letter PZ 7247/37 of the 12th November in regard to the proposal that during the forthcoming visit of the Sultan of Muscat to this country His Highness should be entertained as the guest of His Majesty’s Government. 2. Mr. Eden supports His Lordship’s recommendations as set out in your letter to the Secretary of the Government Hospitality Fund, to which a copy of this letter is being sent. I am Sir Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State India Office./) i) L*MDiM' ' 1 °*: T&lt;’i“,#^f' /n ? ' u ^. ^ (X BUCKINGHAM PALACE Wlum 16th. November, 1957. Jfafi tir£a-&gt;s- 'V&lt;i With reference to your letter of yesterday, as far as it is possible to foresee there should be no difficulty about The King receiving the Sultan of Muscat during the third week of March, 1958. At this distance of time it is, of course, impossible for His Majesty to be definitely committed, when his movements at that time of the year have not even been considered. M. J. Clauson Esq., India Office./• i* to th November 1937. / k Wt i/ur~ / 1 *' &lt;#'«'&lt; — The Secretary of State wishes me to write to you on a matter arising out of a proposed tour round the world which His Highness the Sultan of Muscat is about to undertake. The Sultan is an independent potentate, in special treaty relations with His Majesty's Government as well as with France and the United States of /uuerica. He is a young man under 30 years of age and succeeded his father on the latter's abdication in 1932. He is at the moment in Delhi, where he has been the guest of the Viceroy, and will shortly leave India to visit his father in Japan, and thereafter to visit the United States of America and Europe. He expects to reach England by the middle of March and is most anxious to be given an audience by Hid Majesty, as was his father when he visited England in 1928. He is very anxious to know, before he leaves India in a week's time, whether the period of his visit to England would be aconvenient time Rt.Hon. Sir Alexander Hardlnge, GCVO., KCB., MC.6 - for His Majesty to receive him, since If it were not he would wish to alter his plans to suit His Majesty’s convenience. Lord Zetland is seeking the concurrence of the Foreign Office and the Government Hospitality Fund in a proposal to treat the Sultan as an official guest of His Majesty’s Government for the first two weeks of his visit to England, and he would be glad to recommend that His Majesty might be graciously pleased to grant the Sultan the honour of an audience. It is, of course, premature to consider with any exactness the question of a date, but Lord Zetland would be glad to learn whether, if His Majesty were willing to receive the Sultan, you think that it might be possible to arrange the audience say about the third week of March. Yours sincerely,■ n PJM/MU. S006. (COPIES CIRCULATED) 1011 lllf-f D-g C...Y PHER OF TELEGRAM. From Goverment of India, internal Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 13th November, 1V37. Received 6.45 p.m., 13th November, 1937. - IMPORTANT. ^250, Addreesed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Bushire- Reference paragraphs 6 and ? of Bushire express letter of 28th September, 0*267/37 , and our telegram No .2210 , 5th November, Muscat Eurooean Lour. Sultan very anxious to know before leaving Delhi on 22nd November whether he will be received by H.lf. the Kirg if he visits London middle of March. If His Majesty is unable to receive him in March he will so arrar^e his tour as to arrive in Ergland some time when His Majesty can receive him. Please telegraph what reply should be given to the Sultan. m &amp; RESic. r i. . 15NOV1937 INDIA PICERegister No. P. z. 7247/37. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Lett&lt;!r Telegram from Dated Bee. 193 Formally acknowledged To Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of State ... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Date. Initials. SUBJECT. II ’ II /( % SULTAN OF MUSCAT. Proposed visit to this country. K Question of entertainment as an official guest of His Majesty’s Government. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letters to the Foreign Office and Government Hospitality Fund,consulting. ju NOV 1957contact with the Sultan after he has commenced his world tour it seems desirable that the proposed invitation should he conveyed to him before he leavesP.Z. 7247/37 Minute v :Ul s H, Paper. Department. Please see the submission at P.Z.5128/37 (flagged A) and Mr. Caroe^ Express Letter of 28th September at P.Z.7021/37 (flagged B), regarding the Sultan of Muscat^ proposed world tour. His Highness is now in India on a State visit to the Viceroy, and he plans to leave Bombay on the 30th November for Singapore, where he will remain for about a week before going on to Japan to pay a visit to his father. Prom Japan he will proceed to America and glNKi* thence to this country, where he is due about the middle of March. Thereafter he may visit other * European countries and hopes to return to Muscat early next May. His Highness has received an invitation to visit the President during his stay in America, and he has indicated a desire to be treated as a guest of His Majesty 1 s Government and to be accorded an audience by His Majesty during his visit to this country. The Sultan 1 s father was treated as an official .guest by His Majesty’s Government when he visit' England in 1928, and it seems desirable to accord similar treatment to the present ruler. Following precedent, the Sultan’s predecessor was treated as an official guest for one month , but since that time it has been the practice to restrict official guests to a fortnight, and it has been ascertained that the Treasury His would be most reluctant to consider a longer period in the present case. The Sheikh of Bahrein was treated as an official guest for 2 weeks last year, and after consultation with Sir Trenchard Powle and a the Government of India it is submitted that/similar 6474b Wt 22530/P 114 10,000 9.37 10P periodperiod of hospitality should he extended to the Sultan of Muscat. It is understood that neither the Foreign Office nor the Treasury are likely to raise any objection to this arrangement&gt; hut it will he necessary to obtain their formal concurrence before communicating with the Sultan. Draft letter is submitted accordingly.1 Draft Paper. P.Z. 7247/37 DRAFT LETTER. The Secretary, Government Hospitality Fund, S.W. 1. 6030 Wt 9128—P 18 10,000 4.37 I()P 1 2 NOV 1937 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, who is at present in India paying an official visit to the Viceroy, will leave Bombay on 30th November on an extended tour abroad, including visits to Japan, America and Europe. His Highness expects to reach England about the middle of March next, whoro he has indicated a desire to be treated as a guest of His Majesty^s Government and if possible to be accorded audience by His Majesty. His Highness will be accompanied by an A.D. C., a Secretary and one State official. The Sultan of Muscat is an independent potentate in treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government, and it will be recalled that his predecessor was treated as an official guest of His Majesty’s Government during his visit to England in 1928. The local political authorities, supported by the Government of India, consider it very desirable that similar hospitality should be extended to the present ruler and ? on the analogy of the Sheikh of Bahrein’sit I 2. Bahrein’s visit last year, they have recommended that His Highness should he entertained hy His Majesty’s Government for a period of 2 weeks. As will he seen from the enclosed copy of a letter which he has addressed to the Foreign Office, the Marquess of * Zetland supports this recommendation and he directs me to enquire whether Sir Philip Sassoon agrees that, subject to any views which Mr. Secretary Eden may have to offer, an invitation should he extended to the Sultan on behalf of His Majesty’s Government, arrangements for his accommodation and entertainment being made hy the Government Hospitality Fund, and charges in connection therewith being debited to His Majesty’s Government, ♦ in accordance with the standing arrangements in force. In view of the fact that it will he difficult to maintain official contact with the Sultan after he has started on his world tour, it is considered very desirable that the Viceroy should he ina position to communicate the proposed invitation to His Highness before he leaves Delhi on the 22nd November. I am, therefore, to ask for a very early reply to this letter. (S41 y n WATTOKDraft Paper. P. Z. 7247/37. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. DRAFT LETTER. Sir, 12 NOV 1933? / i d ! k 6030 VVt 9128—P 18 10,000 4.37 I()P I am directed 'by the Secretary of State for India to refer to Bushire Express Letter No. 0/26? of the 28th September (copy of which was sent to the Foreign Office with India Office printed letter No. P.Z.7021/37 of the 27th October) and connected correspondence ending with the Government of India’s telegram No.2210 of the 5th November (copy of which was sent to the Foreign Office with India Office printed letter No. P.Z.72U7/37 of the 6th November) on the subject of the Sultan of Muscat’s proposed tour abroad, and to enclose copy of a letter which Lord Zetland has caused to be addressed to the Secretary of the Government Hospitality Fund, regarding the desire of His Highness to be treated as the guest of His Majesty’s Government during his visit to England. I am to enquire whether Mr. Secretary Eden concurs in His Lordship's recommendations, or has any observations to offer. I am to request the favour of an early reply. A copy of this letter is being sent 'o the Secretary of the Government Hospitality Fund. (&amp;q J, U WALTON.le copy gch/vh, (53 groupso) 4921 (COPIES CIRCULATED) D-JBC Y P H E R OF T ELEC R A VT. From Government of India,External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Rev/ Delhi, 5th November, 1937, Received 3.45 p.m., 5th November,1937. e ‘ X ^ /fy. IMPCRTAN'T, 2210, Aadressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Bushire and Muscat. Your telegram No.2637, November lst 0 Sultan of Muscat''s tour. 2 C We agree with the recommendation in paragraph No .6 of Bushire express letter _C 0 267, September 28th, tad with the suggestion that period of government hospitality in the United Kingdom should oe limited to 2 weeks. We are treating the Sultan as a State guest here for 10 days, 3 of which he will spend in the Viceroy f s house. c N0V 1 .3 c/jP.Z. 7031/37. Draft Paper. Department. DRAFT TELEGRAM. From Secretary of State for India To Government of India, Important. External Affairs Dept. , '' Repeated to Pol.Resident in tne rersian /ulf, and Addressed to Government of India, repeated to Political Resident, Bushire, and Political Agent, Muscat. -— ^ s ' f f Bushire Express letter No.G/267 of Political Agent , Muscat £ Copy to F.O. 31 0 TIMS IfECD /' ' ///// OODL \ ' A DE&amp;PATC, f/jl t-lopl to. Of W0t, « V, ^i.-OL 28th September. Sultan of Muscat’s proposed tour abroad.'— 2. Fowle agrees with recommendation in para.6 and I should be glad to have your views. If you also agree I will take f* * ^ up question of treatment of Sultan as ^ ^ ^ ^ , s' State guest on his visit here next March.^ ^ S' S' ^ sS On analogy of Shaikh of Bahrain’s visit last year I suggest that period of &lt;•— Government hospitality should be limited *s y ' s' ^ S to two weeks. ' Do you agree ? Treasury would probably be most reluctant to ^ ^ ^ - consider a longer period.— 3. You will, no doubt, wish to be in a position to communicate H.M.G.’s L , ^ ^ ^ ^ invitation to Sultan before he leaves India and I should therefore be glad to receive your views as soon as possible. 4. I am considering other points dealt with in Resident’s letter. 5319c 5000 10.36Minute Paper. poiiticai(int.) Department. Sir T. Fowle. May v/e have your views on the various points dealt with in Mr. Garoe's letter please? Assuming a decision in favour of treating the Sultan as a State Guest the next point to he considered is the period of hospitality. Following precedent the Sultan*s predecessor was treated as a State Guest for one month during his visit in 1928 hut since that time it has become the practice to restrict State visits to 10 days or a fortnight. The Sheikh of Bahrein was treated as a State Guest for a fortnight during his 1936 visit and I think that the Government Hospitality Fund would he reluctant to do more for the Sultan. We should he glad to have your views on this point. On receipt of your views it is proposed to consult the Government of India (the Foreign Office are now thinking about the matter) and we ought, perhaps, to try and get a decision before the Sultan leaves India to start the tour. (Sd.) A.G.B.SYMON. 28/10. Mr. Symon. The Sultan 1 s reply is somewhat sticky, hut I think that our approach to him has done good. Though he states that he proposes only to consult H.M.G. in cases where it is to his own interest to do so, in -previously of his proposed tours in foreign countries, would/ n If Iwould be that through our Embassies and Legations facilities could be arranged for the Sultan with the Foreign Governments concerned. This was touched on in para, 2 of P.A., Muscat’s letter of 5th August to the Sultan. It is obvious, however, that the Sultan does not want to use this channel. As far as this point is concerned I think we should leave the Sultan to his own devices. The Foreign Office should, I think, inform the Tokyo and V/ashington Embassies of the Sultan’s tour and leave it at that. If he wants any assistance from them - the Embassies - he can ask for it, and should get it. If, by reason of his not wanting us to arrange for facilities in foreign countries he gets into difficulties, it will be a salutary lesson for him. I agree with Mr. Garoe’s views as expressed in para. 4 of his letter of 28th September (P.Z.7021). 4. I also agree with Mr. Caroe’s viev/s in his para. 6. In addition to the communication to the Sultan suggested by Mr. Caroe, I think|that it might be made clear that H.M.G. understand that H.H. does not desire that they should approach any foreign Government with a view to arranging facilities for him, and that therefore they are taking no steps in the matter. Naturally, however, facilities will be afforded him in British possessions. 5. It is satisfactory that the Sultan wants to visit England, and have an audition with His Majesty. I think that a fortnight as a State Guest would suffice. If necessary it could be explained to the Sultan verbally that, since his father’s time, the period for a State Guest is a fortnight not a month. 6. Re Mr. Caroe’s para. 7 (last part). See my para. 4 above. I don’t think we should go out of our way to press our services on the Sultan unless he asks for them - which he may after receipt of our letter.P&gt; Z.7142/57* COITFIDENTIAL. No.719-S of 1937. GO^/SRIH.CTT OP INDIA. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Dated Bushire, the 19th October, 1937. Prom - Political Resident, Bushire. To - Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Political Agent, Muscat. Subject: Tour of Sultan of Muscat. In continuation of my Express letter No.C/267, dated the 28th September 1937. 2. Sultan has furnished Political Agent with following details regarding his tour. ( a ) Party . 1. Saiyid Tariq bin Taimur, Sultan’s brother. 2. Halal bin Badr, Secretary. o. Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubaily, State Official. 4. Saiyid Abdulmunim Zav/awi, A.D.C. 5. Two servants. Nos. 1 and 5 will accompany Sultan only as far as Japan, (k) Itinerary . Sultan leaves Delhi November 22nd proceeding direct to Bombay. Leaves Bombay on iiovember 30th by Lloyd Triestino steamer for Singapore. Leaves Singapore about December 14th arrives Kobe about December 21st. Leaves Japan about end of January 1938 arrives San Francisco about middle ol Iebxdary. Thence via Washington to London, where he is xUe about the middle of March. Sultan intends to visit Prance and Italy on return journey, and hopes/hopes to return to Muscat early in May, ( c ) Permanent address on tour . Head Office of Messrs, Thomas Cook and Sons in each country visited, 3• I have asked Political Agent, Muscat, to ascertain before Sultan’s departure what arrangements latter proposes for the administration of his State during his absence, (Sd,) O.K.Caroe. Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Attested. (Sd.) J, Croning. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Extract from Express Letter (Air Mail) from Political Resident, Bushire, at Shiraz, to Secretary of State for India, London, dated 28th September, 1937. 5. For the rest Sultan sets out an indefinite programme for a round-the-world journey, starting from India after visit to Delhi, via Japan and U.S.A. to London, and thence back through France and possibly other European countries, only fixed date being arrival in London on March 15th 1938. Date proposed for his departure is likely to be inconvenient in that negotiations will still be afoot for revision of Muscat Commercial Treaty at express request of Sultan himself. Projected tour will take him through Japan and America in depth of winter and bring him to England at inclement time of year. Visit to the U.S.A. may possibly lead to some embarrassment, if question of tariff revision is under discussion as a result of negotiations for revision of his treaty with His Majesty’s Government. Finally owing to Sultan’s protracted recess in Dhofar we have had so little opportunity of maintaining touch with him that renewed absence at this juncture will certainly be ill-timed. Sultan is due to leave for Delhi on 7th November and, if he adheres to his programme, he will be unable to meet the Resident again until he returns from his world tour. Subject however to Fowle’s views I feel that little is 6 to be gained by placing these considerations before Sultan and endeavouring to prevail on him to postpone his tour. We may hope that treaty negotiations will be well on way before visit to Delhi, and it would probably be preferable to use some of these arguments as means to induce Sultan to agree to continuation of present Treaty until such time as new agreement can take shape. I therefore recommend that Sultan/Sultan be informed that His Majesty's Government are glad to hear of his projected visit and will welcome him as State Guest. His request to he received by His Majesty will no doubt receive consideration. 7. Sultan's father was treated as State Guest for one month when he visited England in 1928 and was received by His Majesty (see correspondence ending v/ith your telegram No.1864 of 5th July 1928). There are also recent precedents of visits of Shaikhs of Kuwait and Bahrain, and it will no doubt be thought desirable to accord similar treatment to Sultan. As regards projected visits to Prance and other European countries, when the time comes, it may be possible, despite attitude taken in his letter, to suggest to Sultan that His Majesty’s Government will be glad to communicate on his behalf with Governments concerned if he will inform them in more detail of his itinerary.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ff_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2968</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ff</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2968</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/14(3) 'Muscat: Sultan's visit to England, 1938'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-06T22:09:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (318 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 321; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and minutes concerning the arrangements for the visit of Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd], the Sultan of Muscat, to the United Kingdom in March-April 1938. The principal correspondents include officials at the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the Government of India (External Affairs Department), the India Office, the Foreign Office, Buckingham Palace, and the Sultan himself. Practical arrangements for the visit are discussed (party size, itinerary, table plans, guest lists, menus, toast lists, an audience with the King, etc.) as well as the question of whether to receive the Sultan as an official guest of the state. Also contained within the file:Information on previous visits by foreign dignitaries used as reference for the current visitCorrespondence with the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) regarding an interview with the Sultan for their BBC Arabic ProgrammeCorrespondence with Rudolph Said-Ruete, a third cousin of the Sultan’s who wishes to be involved in the visitNewspaper cuttings relating to the visitCorrespondence with the Metropolitan Police concerning arrangements for an officer to escort the Sultan when he returns from France in a private capacityMessages of thanks following the success of the visit</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Buckingham Palace</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>State visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ff#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>