<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003dd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:10:43.798Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">id****GOVERNMENT AD P ublic P epai!tmi:xt. HE Hon'ble the Governor in Council is pleaied to publifh for general informa tion the following Regulations adopted at this Prefidency relpccting Perfons in the Hon ble Company's Civil Service, who may be defirous of proceeding to Europe, and thefe Regulations are to be confidered as having effect from the period of pub lication; To prevent in future any Civil Servant o{ the Company from leaving this Country for Europe, until it (hall be certified by the proper Officer that his accounts with the Company have been fettled, and that no balance or j aft claim ftands ag.dnft him. The Hon'ble the Governor in Council is pleafed to order; ift. That every Civil Servant of the Company, in whatever Department, intend ing to proceed to Europe, ffiall notify his intention to the Secretary to Government three months previous to his actual refignation of his Office-, fo that the faid intent tion may be duly fignified to the Governor in Council and recorded; 3d. That every Civil Servant Of the Company, in whatever Department, fhall, up on quitting his Office, deliver ovei - the fame to his Senior Affiftant on the fpot, or to fuch Perfon as may be appointed hy Authory to receive charge of it; and to I'uch Affiftant or other Perfon fo appointed, the Records, Papers, and all other Official Documents whatever belonging to it, ffiall be delivered over by the Perfon refigning, with the balance, if there be any, of the Public Money in his hands; which delivery ffiall be duly and formally Certified in Writing, and in triplicate Cupies by the Per fon fucceeding to the duty of theftation; one Copy ffiall be lent to the Secretary to Government, another Copy to the Department of Audit, and the third may be re tained by the Perfon retiring from Office; Sd. The applications from the Civil Servants of the Company for leave to proceed to Europe ffiall. be preferred, from whatever Department, either through the Secre tary to Governrrtent, or immediately to the Governor in Council; whether the Peri fon be in, or out of employment; in the former cafe (provided the Civil Servant does not hold a Military Appointment) accompanied by a Certificate figned by the Ac countant General, and Civil Auditor, that the Company have no pecuniary claima on any account upon fuch Servants, or, that full and fatisfactory Security has been given for difcharging whatever amount may be declared by Government to be due from thefe Gentlemen to the Company; 4th. The Governor in Council has refolved that the period of application ffiall not on any account be lefs than three months, excepting only, in cafes of fevere illncfs, or feme other caufe of an urgent nature; all Perfons, coming within the above Re gulations, who may intend returning to England, are required accordingly to ftate their intention three months anterior to the period of their embarkation. The Secretary has been directed to be particularly careful that the above Regulations are ftnetly complied with, before any Orders ifiue from his Office, that ffiall grant to any Company's Servant permiffion to go to Europe, and affign to him accommo dation in any of the Company's ffiips. By Order of the Hmihle the Governor in Council, F. WARDEN, BOMBAY CASTLE Secretary to Gwernmentt 21/2 ■dugujl 1806.TABLE of BOOKS, S'. become due. BOO BOOKS, ANNUAL, ending the 30/ Journal and Ledger fn Ditto and ditto fr Ditto and ditto fr Ditto and ditto fr Ditto and ditto fr Ditto and ditto fr Ditto and ditto fr Books from the Cuftoi Books of Military Dif Appendix to the Mar Duplicate Journal an Ditto ditto , ai Ditto ditto ai: Ditto ditto ■ ai Ditto Books fro! STATEMENTS &amp;= MONTHLY, Treafury Cafh Accoi Statement of aelual Collectors of Bor Cuftom Ma ft ens a Surat and Camhj Ertimate of expefte Collectors of Bor Cuftom Mailers ; and Cambay, thi Account Current o i- uA. v^u that may have be QUARTERLY, Statements of Qulc Ditto ditt Ditto dittj Ditto dittj Return of Goods oil ment to be furnij at SnraL. C.nmVjTABLE of BOOKS, STATEMENTS &amp;c. required at the Accountant General's Office ith the periods at which they severally become due. OOK'S, ST^iTE-M E To be delivered in if at the Prefidency, or trans mitted if from Subordinates, fo as to arrive at the Prefidency, at the following fixed !• jrio&lt;is i BOOKS, ANNUAL, ending the 30th of April. Journal and Ledger from the Military Paymafter General, . Ditto and ditto from the Marine Paymafter and Store-keeper,.. Ditto and ditto from the Refident at Buflbrah, Ditto and ditto from the Refident at Bagdad,. . Ditto and ditto from the Refident at Bufliire, Ditto and ditto from the Military Auditor General, Ditto and ditto from all other Offices at the Prefidency and at Suhoi Books from the Cuftom Mafters at the Prefidency and at Subordinate Stat Books of Military Diftjurfcments, Accompaniments to the Military Pay ? General's Journal and Leaer,. . . . Appendix to the Marine Paymafter's and Store-keeper's Journal and Ledger, Duplicate Journal and Ledger from the Refident at Buflorah, !' Ditto ditto and ditto from the Refident at Bagdad, . . . , Ditto ditto and ditto . from the Refident at Buftiire, , and ditto - from -all other Offices-at Subordinate Stations,. Ditto Ditto ditto Books from the Cuftom Mafters at Subordinate Stations,. \\bthof July after the clofe of each year [ of account. Ditto ditto ditto. Ditto ditto ditto. Ditto ditto ditto. Ditto ditto ditto. 5 th of July after the clofe of each year of account. f 30/A of June after the clofe of each I year of account. Ditto ditto ditto. 31// of Auguft after the clofe of each year of account. Ditto ditto ditto. Ditto ditto ditto. Ditto ditto ditto. Ditto ditto ~~~ ditto, j 15th of Ajrgnfi after the clofe of eath | year of account. Ditto ditto ditto. STATEMENTS &amp;=• MONTHLY, Treafury Cafh Account from the Sub-Treafurer at the Prefidency, ... St-atement of actual Receipts and Difburfements from the Sub-Treafurer, Poll Mafter General, Civil Pay Mafter. Collectors ot Bombay, Sall'ette, Caranjah, Surat, Kairah, and Broach, Relidents at Baroda and F'tt Vidloria, Cuftom Mafters at Bombay, Salfette, Surat, and Broach, the Warehoufekeeper, and the Commercial Refidents at Surat and Cambay, — EHimate of expected Receipts and Difburfements, from the Sub-Treafurer, Poft Mafter General, Civil Pay Mafter. Collectors of Bombay, Salfette, Caranjah, Surat, Kairah and Broach, Refidents at Baroda and Lrt Victoria, Cuftom Mafters at Bombay, Salfette, Surat arid Broach, the Warehoutekeeper, the Commercial Refid^nts at Surat and Cambay, the Marine Pay Mafter and Storekeeper, and, the Military Pay Mafter General, — Account Current of Receipts, or advances and fupplies on account of the Prefidencies of Fort William, Fort St, Ccorgc, jPoi-L' iCbnTwHiViV, aria 1 the Gvmcciencai st GzyKia accompanied by Vouchers for the advance: and fupplies that may have been made, for tranfmiftio^ to thofe relpedlive Governments — QUARTERLY, Statements of Quick and Dead Stock to 31ft of July, — Ditto ditto •ditto to 31ft of October,. , . — Ditto ditto ditto to 31ft of January,. Ditto ditto ditto to 30th of April, — Return of Goods on hand and in courfe of proviiion accompanied by General Remarks on the ftate of the inveft ment to be furnifhed under the following dates, by the Warehoufekeeper at the Prefidency, Commercial Refident; at Surat, Cambay, Malabar and Anjengo, vizt. 31ft of March, 30th of June, - -- -- -- -- -- -- - |- - - — 30th of September, - - - -- -- ------- — 31ft of December, - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - — ANNUAL, Statement of Aitual'Receipts and Difburfements of the paft year from'the Mari J Paymafter and Store-keeper, and from the Military Paymafter General, .v. . — Statement of Actual Receipts and Difburfements of the paft year from all other Offices at the Prefidency and Su bordinate Stations, . . . . . . , . . . V •— Comparative Statement, flievving and accounting for the differences betweea the A6tual and Eftimated Receipts and Difburfements of the paft year, from the Marine Paymafter and Store ' ' r, and from the Military Paymafter General, . . . . Comparative Statement, fhewing and acconnt-Ing for the differences betv '&lt; Difburfements of the paft year, from all other Offices at tht. V -■ -lenc Eftimate of expected Receipts and Dilbarfini;ats of the current Year, fu and from the Military Pay Mafter General, Eftimate of expedtcd Receipts and Difburlements of the current Year, from .all other Offices at the Frefidency and Subordinate-Stations, - - - General Return of Stores imported from Europe'to the 30th of April, from ti )e Military, Medical, ^Tarine Boards, Return of Goods and Merchandize imported from Europe to the 30th of 4pril, from the Warehoufekeeper at the Prefidency, and from all Commercial Officers at Subordinate Stations, _ - . _ - - — General Return of Stores received and purchafed in India to the 30th of Apr]^ f r om the Military, Mescal and Ma rine Boards, BO^'v ^ CASTLE. 1 30 days after the clofe of each month. 1 jih of each fucceeding month. 1 jth of the month for which it is framed. 1 oth of each fucceeding month. 31 days after the clofe of the quarter. Ditto ditto ditto. Ditto ditto ditto. 5 th of June following. I 20 days after the clofe of the rcffcc- j' tive quarters. ? Actual and Eftimated Receipts and bordinate Stations, Marine Pay M ifterand Storekeeper, r30/A of June after the i year of account. \\5th of June after the | year of account. \ 5 th of July after the cloj, |' of account. (20th of June after the | year of account, f 1 Oth of July after the | year of account. {15th of June after the [ year of account. {\Jl of July after the clofe of account. clofe of each clofe of each e of each year clofe of each clofe of each clofe of each of each year Ditto Ditto ditto' ditto ACCOUNTANT GENERAL'S OFFICE, f \\th March ISO/. J. ELPHINSTON SanBioned by the Honorable the Governor in Council, Accountant General, F. WARDEN, Secretary to Government.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003dd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/9</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003dd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/9</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Vol 9 Bushire Diary</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1806/1807</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-20T09:10:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 volumes (241 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is in the form of a diary running in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. The correspondence sent is entered under the approximate date the letter was written; that received is entered under the date of receipt at Bushire. Notes of the arrival and departure of vessels are similarly recorded in diary form under the relevant date.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence, which runs through both volumes, commences at 1 on the first folio of correspondence and terminates at 235 on the inside back cover of the second volume. The numbers are written in pencil, are smaller than the pagination numbers, and appear near the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 116, 116A, 116B, 116C, 116D, 116E, 1116F. Folio 228 folds out beyond the edge of the volume. This is the system in use.Pagination: there is also an incomplete pagination sequence, which runs from 1-458 through both volumes. The numbers are written in pencil, are larger than the foliation numbers, and appear at the top centre or toward the top of the recto and verso pages.Condition: the volumes have suffered extensive damage at the beginning and end of the original (pre-conservation) volume (ff. 1-15 and 222-232), in the shape of damaged edges and holes in the folios, which has resulted in significant losses of text. There is also some damage to other folios, which occasionally causes loss of text.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume consists of chronological diary entries containing transcripts of correspondence sent and received, and notes on the arrival and departure of vessels at Bushire. The Residents during the period covered were William Bruce (acting) and (from May 1807) Nicholas Hankey Smith.The correspondence sent is entered under the date the letter was written; that received is entered under the date of receipt at Bushire. The correspondence is between the Resident and other East India Company officials: officials of the Government of Bombay (including correspondence in the Political, Military, Public, General and Commercial Departments, and correspondence with the Accountant General); the Resident at Bagdad [Baghdad] (Harford Jones, and later John Hine [Acting]); the Resident at Muscat (David Seton); and the Resident at Bussora [Basra] (Lieutenant William Eatwell [Acting], and later Samuel Manesty).The records of shipping consist of a note of the day of arrival and departure of ships of the Bombay Marine (the East India Company navy) and country ships (privately-owned merchant ships, which operated under licence from the East India Company), and information on their port of origin and destination. The term 'imported' is used to indicate the arrival of a vessel.General topics covered in the volume include:political developments in the Gulf;movements of ships;the transmission of packets of correspondence;piracy;the provision and sale of East India Company merchandise;accounting and financial matters;administrative matters;relations with the Court of Persia;relations with local rulers;the activities of the French in the region (including the activities of French privateers);reports of political and military developments in Europe.Specific topic include:dispatches from the Government of Bombay concerning the Persian Embassy to India (entry for 20 February 1806, folios 5-22), including a report of an assault by a sepoy sentry on a horse belonging to members of the suite of the Persian Ambassador, Mohumed Nebee Khan [Muhammad Nābī Khān];dispatches from the Government of Bombay concerning the Persian Embassy to India (entry for 27 February 1806, folios 22v-40v), including details of the garrison court martial of the sentry mentioned above, and financial claims of the Persian Ambassador;letter from Bruce to Francis Warden, Secretary to the Government of Bombay dated 3 March 1806, in response to the above dispatches (folio 41);letter from Bruce to Jonathan Duncan, President and Governor in Council, dated 12 March 1806 containing a report of the search for the wreck of the
                              Reliance(f. 42v);letter from Bruce to Jonathan Duncan, President and Governor in Council, dated 25 March 1806 containing a report of the presence of a French agent at Tabrize [Tabriz], who was on his way to Teheran [Tehran] (f. 44v);dispatches from the Government of Bombay concerning the Persian Embassy to India (entry for 13 April 1806, folios 40v-67v), including details of stores drawn and remaining to be drawn from the Honourable Company's stores, and bills to be paid on account of the
                              Rahimshaw(ff. 47-51), account of articles purchased by the Ambassador's people (ff. 56v-57), report of the sale of horses presented by the Persian Ambassador (f. 60), and list of articles purchased for the Persian Ambassador for use as presents (f. 62);dispatches from the Government of Bombay concerning the Persian Embassy to India (entry for 27 May 1806, ff.74v-138v), including the embarkation of the embassy for Calcutta;correspondence containing reports by Bruce of a French agent at the Court of Persia, (1-5 September 1806, ff. 160v-162);regulations issued by the Government of Bombay concerning persons in the East Company's service who wished to proceed to Europe (19 October 1806, ff. 170v-171);correspondence concerning an incident involving the Honourable Company's Schooner
                              Sylphat Bushire, which led to a serious loss of life amongst the
                              Sylph'screw (14 January - 14 February 1807, ff. 188-192);table of books, statements etc. required by the Accountant General's Office, Government of Bombay, issued 11 March 1807 (f. 228).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Ambassador to India</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sylph, schooner</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bombay, Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bombay, Accountant General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bombay</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Napoleonic Wars (1800-1815)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000159.0x0003dd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>