<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00015d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-14T10:24:42.724Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I do not think there is anything in the first draft of the White Paper on which the Political Department need at this stage make suggestions. The most important points with which we are directly concerned are: (a) Aden; (h) British Baluchistan; (c) The position of the Governor of the North West Frontier Province. (d) The position of the Department of External Affairs. (a) Aden , (paragraph 5). The Cabinet have agreed to the transfer and the Viceroy has been consulted as to whether the proposal can best first be made public in the White Paper and in the terms at present embodied therein, mere is nothing further to be done pending his reply. (b) British Baluchistan , (paragraphs 5 and 107 to * 109} of the draft circulafcto Heads of Departments). Paragraph 5, in the light of the Governnent of India’s comments and discussion with Mr. Dawson, has now been modified to run as follows:- Mn/•In the case of British Baluchistan special provision will he made whereby tne Governor-General will himself direct and control the aoministration of the province (see paragraphs 57 and 58). Expenditure required for British Baluchistan will not be subject to the vote of the Federal Legislature but will be open to discussion in both Chambers. H Paragraphs 57 and 58 represent The existing paragraphs 107, 108 and 109#*^&lt; £****. *+«~**%*^u.u + ' tdVf Unr «ulJl h ^ ' The point taken by the Goveriment of India in regard to the method of election to the Baluch seat has also been noted in connection with the White Paper (c) North West Frontier Province * The Governor is vested with the ordinary powers ana special responsibilities to be given to Governors of provinces under the new scheme, the special responsibilities inducing the '’securing of the execution of orders lawfully issued by the Governor- General'; but in addition is declared (as arranged consequent on the discussion with Sir Balph Griffith) to/to have a special responsibility in respect of tt any matter affecting the Governor*s responsibilities as Agent to the Governor-General in the tribal areas. H (a) Provision of supply for the Dei^rteignt, nf Externa l Affairs . The provision made ifetM-s-aaetrian puts the Governor-General in a position to secure the provision of such sums as are required for the aischarge of this particular special responsibility.Personal and Secret. Secretary, Political (External) Department - ^ T; &gt;ep^rrtrrp7?t Military Department S. &amp; D.^Department E^Js^. Department ppSnt ant OenCTcd' Sir-Saloolm Soto-n -Mr^.Takoly- 1. The Under Secretary of State has asked me to send you the accompanying incomplete and provisional drafts of the forthcoming fhite Paper on Reforms with the request that you will examine them, and let me know (i) whether you regard the provisions inserted in the Proposals which affect the business of your Department as satisfactory and, if not, in what respects you think they require alteration; and (ii) whether you consider that there are any omissions from the draft as it stands which ought to be made good before the White Paper is. published. 2. The general policy underlying the drafts is, of course, that indicated in the Reports of the threeSessions should c at prese 4. must be the Gcw comment! March 1Sessions of the Round Table Conference. 3. It is intended that the document when complete should contain proposals on the following heads, which at present are not included (i) Federal Finance. (ii) The Railway authority. (iii) The Secretary of State's Council. (iv) The Federal Court, the Supreme Court and the High Court. (v) Fundamental Rights. 4. You will, of course, understand that the document must be treated as very secret. Proofs are being sent to the Government of India weekly by air mail and their comments have been invited. Publication is intended on March 17. V .MESON, 24th February, 1933.MOST SECRET. PROPOSALS FOR INDIAN CONSTITUTIONAL REFORM. INTRODUCTION. The White Paper of December, 1981. 1. In December 1981 both Houses of Parliament adopted a motion expressing approval of the Indian policy of His Majesty’s Government, as announced to the Indian Round Table Conference and set out m Command Paper 3972. That policy, stated in the broadest terms, involved the prosecution of further inquiries and discussion with the object of finding a suitable basis for the conver sion of the present system of government in India into a responsibly T (-deration of States and Provinces, on the understanding that the responsible Government so established must be qualified by limitations in various directions, which limitatione have commonly been described by the compendious term “ safeguards.” 2 . Having pursued their further inquiries and discussions, including a third session of the Round Table Conference, His Majesty s Government are now in a position to indicate with greater precision and in fuller detail their proposals for an Indian Constitu tion; and it is their intention, as indicated by the Secretary of State for India to the House of Commons on the 27th June last' to invite both Houses of Parliament to set up a Joint Select Committee to consider these proposals in consultation with Indian representatives, and to report upon them. It will thereafter be the'duty of His Majesty’s Government to re-examine their proposals in the light of the Joint Select Committee’s report and to introduce a Bill embodying their own final plans. The form and purpose of the present document. 3. It should be made plain at the outset that although the proposals are set out below in the interests of clarity in the form of short paragraphs or clauses, the language used in so describing them must not in general be taken as representing the language which would actually be used if they were presented in statutory form. Nor must it be assumed that the present proposals are in all respects so complete and final that a Bill would contain nothing which is not covered by this White Paper, or omit nothing which is contained in it; nor, again, that a Bill would present without modification everything which here appears. At the same time it is hoped that although further examination may disclose the desirability of modifying in some respects in matters of detail the proposals here after set out, and although in other respects they require further elaboration in detail in order to achieve that degree of precision and completeness which would be requisite for statutory enactment, the clauses which follow, read in the light of the explanatory para graphs which precede them, will afford a full explanation of the governing principles by which His Majesty’s Government have been actuated, and indeed of the greater part of the detailed arrangements which those principles are designed to embody. 4. One further explanation of the scope of this document should be given. It is unnecessary for the present purpose to marshal and elaborate the general arguments in justification of proposals for the government of India of the character of those which follow. With such argumente His Majesty’s Government are, of course, prepared [8174—1]Introduction. to deal fully ii to explain as nature and intended effect of their proposals. The Federation of India. The processes involved in its formation. b. The conception of a Federation of States and 1 rovinces, and the legal and constitutional processes involved in its formation necessitate a complete reconstruction of the existing Indian Consti tution; these proposals are accordingly based on the assumption that the existing Government of India Act (which is a consola a ion of the series of statutes relating to the government of India, the earliest of which dates from the 18th century) will be repealed in toto, and will be replaced by the Act which will ultimately embody the decision of Parliament. ‘The problems presented by the legal and constitutional reconstruction are briefly these :— 6 . Federation elsewhere has usually resulted from a pact entered into by a number of political units, each possessed of sovereignty or at least of autonomy, and each agreeing to surrender to the new central organism which their pact creates an identical range of powers and jurisdiction, to be exercised by it on their behalf to the same extent for each one of them individually and for the Federa tion as a whole. India, however, has little in common with historical precedents of this kind. In the first place, British India is a unitary State, the administrative control of which is by law centred in the Secretary of State—-in some respects in a statutory corporation known as the Secretary of State in Council—in whom are vested powers of control over “all acts, operations and concerns which relate to the government or revenues of India ’ ’; and such powers as appertain to the central and provincial Governments in India are derived by a species of delegation from this central authority and are exercised subject to his control. It follows that the Provinces are to-day possessed of no sovereignty and no real autonomy : historically they are creations of the central administrative organism formed for (convenience to exercise delegated functions subject to its supervision and control; and accordingly they have no original or independent powers or authority to surrender. The States, on the other hand, though they are under the suzerainty of the King, form no part of His Majesty’s dominions. Their contact with British India has hitherto been maintained by the conduct of relations with their Rulers through the Governor-General in Council. Moreover, since Parliament cannot legislate directly for their territories, the range of authority to be conferred upon the Federal Government and Legisla- ture in relation to the States must be determined by agreement with their Rulers; and the States have made it nlain that tW ovo in relation to British India and 'with such powers3 Introduction. memb ofrepSeraS w l, ° t States as the States- and effect witMr Sir ton^it ” ^ *f! Pt “ , beillg of tul! £otc « qualifications as may be S ' bJeC, - t0 , SUch lim i‘^ione and Accession Pull hbertv will 3 Upon ' n their Instruments of f r-,»tart t&amp;sr» briefly md.cated above, it will be necessary at the“t (set paragraph 1 of the Proposals) to resume into the hands of the Crown all powers appertaining or incidental to the government of British n t 'l 1 ri Q f htS ’ ? Uth0rity and i uri8 diction exercisable in, or in 1 n ff’ fc f e ^. tates b y tr eaty, grant, usage, shft'eranee or otherwise bo much of this corpus of governmental powers, authority and jurisdiction as is requisite for the government of the Federation of India will be apportioned between the Governor-General the Governors, and other appropriate authorities to be established by the Constitution Act. The powers now exercisable by the Crown m relation to the States through the Governor-General of India in ( ouTied, except in so far as they are requisite for Federal purposes and the Eulers have assented to their transfer to the appropriate rederal authority for those purposes, will be exercised by the Crown’s representative in his capacity of Viceroy, and these powers will be outside the scope of the Federal Constitution. The office of Governor-General of the Federation will be consti tuted by Letters Patent, and that document will also serve as the means of conferring upon the Governor-General, in his capacity of Viceroy, the powers of the Crown in relation to the States, for which the Constitution Act, since these powers will be outside the federal sphere, will make no provision. Such prerogative powers, in so far as they are required for the government of the Federation (for instance, the power to pardon offenders), and in so far as they are not specifically delegated by the Constitution Act, will be delegated to the Governor-General by means of his Instrument of Instructions. There will thus be three Instruments from the Crown in relation to the office of Governor-General—Letters Patent constituting the office, an Instiument of Instructions and the Royal Warrant, whence individual holders of the office will derive their individual authority. The first two of these Instruments will be applicable to all holders of the office, the last will be personal to the holder for the time being; the same arrangements are contemplated in this respect for each Governor. 9. So far as British India is concerned, the first step requisite in the transfer from a unitary to a federal polity is to define with precision and with statutory effect the jurisdiction and competence of the Federal and Provincial authorities respectively—or, in other words, to create Provinces with an independence not dissimilar from that of the States, and to assign to them a defined and exclusive share of the activities of government. It is accordingly proposed to declare that the executive power and authority in each of the Governors’ Provinces is vested in the King and is exercisable by the Governor as Ihe King’s representative ; to constitute a Council of Ministers to aid and advise the Governor, and a Legislature of elected representatives of the provincial populations to whom the Ministers will be responsible; and to define the competence of this Legislature (and of the F’ederal Legislature) in terms of subjects, some of which will be exclusively assigned to the Federal and Provincial Legislatures respectively, while over others both Federal and Provincial Legisla tures will exercise a concurrent jurisdiction, with appropriation provisions for resolving conflicts of laws. The Date and Conditions for the Inauguration of Federation. 10. It will be apparent that the mere passing of the Constitution Act will not of itself suffice to bring the Federation into being. Apart from the preparatory processes required in British India, which cannot be effectively commenced until the Constitution Act is4 Introduction. until both Houses of Parliament have presented an Address to t i , Crown with &amp;. prayer for its promulgation. 11. Another prerequisite to the inauguration of responsible Federal Government of a financial character is dealt ^vith in paragraph 24. His Majesty’s Government are of _ opinion— that the arransrements for bringing the Constitution Act into opera tion shall not be such as to admit of the introduction of the new autonomous constitutions in the Provinces under conditions which will leave Federation as a mere contingency in the future. It may be that it will be found convenient, or even necessary, that the new Provincial governments shall be actually in being a little in advance of the inauguration of the changes in the Central Govern ment and the. actual participation in it of the States: but it is essential, in the view of His Majesty’s Government, that, in that event, the coming into being of the autonomous Provinces should be the initiation of a definitely prearranged constitutional process. The Federal Executive. 12 . The executive power and authority of the Federation will be vested in the King and will be exercised by the Governor- General as his representative, aided and advised by a Council of Ministers responsible to the Legislature and containing representatives both of British India and of the States. But whereas in the Provinces the Council of Ministers will be entitled, as will be seen from a later paragraph, to tender advice to the Governor on all matters which fail within the scope of provincial administration, other than the use of powers described by the Constitution Act as being exercisable by the Governor at his discretion, the transfer of responsibility at the Centre is not to be co-extensive with the range of the Federal Government’s activities. Certain subjects, namely, Defence, External Affairs and Ecclesiastical administration, are to be entrusted to the Governor- General personally, and these matters he will control in responsibility to His Majesty’s Government and Parliament. In the exercise, more over, of certain specific powers to be conferred by the Constitution on the Governor-General, and to be expressed as being exercisable at his discretion, the Governor-General will be entitled to act without seeking advice from his Ministers. On other matters. Ministers will tender advice to the Governor-General and the Governor-General will be guided by that advice, unless so to be guided would in his judgment be inconsistent with the fulfilment of any of the purposes for which he will be declared by the Constitution Act to be charged with a “ special responsibility,” in which case the Governor-General will act, notwith standing the advice tendered to him, in such manner as he deems requisite for the fulfilment of his “ special responsibilities.” For the purpose of assisting him in the administration of the Reserved Departments the Governor-General will be empowered to appoint at his discretion not more than three Counsellors whose salaries and conditions of service will be prescribed by His Majesty in Council.5 Introduction^ The Federal Legislature. 13. The Federal Legislature will be a bi-cameral organism, each of the Chambers of which will possess identical powers, except that Money Bills and Votes of Supply will be initiated in the Lower Chamber, and that the arrangements to be made for the voting of supply will be confined, in the case of the Upper Chamber, to such heads of the Estimates voted by the Lower Chamber as the Upper Chamber may select to be debated and voted upon by itself: such selected heads will be brought before a Joint Session of both Chambers [? submitted to a Committee containing an equal number of representatives of both Chambers] for final determination. Equality of powers necessitates arrangements made for the solution of deadlocks ; the arrangements proposed are set out in paragraph of the Proposals. The range of competence of the Federal Legislature is dealt with, together with that of the Provincial Legislatures, in paragraph 34 below. 14. The Lower Chamber of the Federal Legislature will consist of 375 members, of whom 125 will be appointed by the Eulers of States- members of the Federation, to which, either individually or in groups, the number of seats indicated in Appendix will be allocated. The remaining 250 members will be representatives of British India and their seats will be allocated to the Provinces and to the several communities and interests in each province in the manner indicated in the same Appendix. The British Indian members will be directly elected by constituencies in each Province containing qualified voters of each community. The Upper Chamber. 15. The Upper Chamber or “Council of State' will consist of a maximum of 260 members (apart from the Governor-General s Counsellors) of whom not more than 100 will be nominated by the States-members of the Federation, to whom, as in the case of the Lower Chamber, seats will be assigned either individually or in groups in the numbers shown in Appendix . The British Indian members, 150 in number, will, for the most part, be elected by the members of the Provincial Legislatures by the single transferable vote, thus rendering unnecessary any specific allocation of the seats on a communal basis, except in the case of those minorities (the Europeans, the Anglo-Indians and Indian Christians) whose repre sentatives in the Provincial Legislatures will be insufficient!) numerous to provide the necessary quota : in these cases, special all-India electorates will be provided and seats will be specifically allotted. In the case of the members representing the Chief Commissioners’ Provinces where there are no Legislatures, special electorates will be formed. In addition the Governor-General will be empowered to nominate not more than ten members and, in making his selection, he will be free to act on his own judgment. Special qualifications will be demanded of candidates for the Council oi State, and a higher age limit will be fixed than in the case of the Assembly. It is hoped by these means to secure a membership for the Upper Chamber which will represent elements in Indian public life of mature judgment and stable character. The franchise for the Federal Legislature. 16. The British Indian seats in the Upper Chamber of the Federal Legislature will, as indicated in Appendix . be filled by indirect election bv the Provincial Legislatures. No question ol franchise qualifications arises, though certain specific property or other qualifications will be required m members of the Upper House. The franchise for the Lower Chamber of the Federal Legislatm e will, for practical purposes, be the existing franchise for the present Provincial Legislatures. In Bihar and Orissa the qualifications vi be changed, but the character and numerical effect will be substantially as at present. In the Central Provinces, where the existing percentage of enfranchisement is unusually low. an alterna- [8174—I] Ci -.f /’in fl i n ort 1 uenerous scfii* five franchise of the same character ^ - existing has been worked out by the on property. In franchise in ah provinces is essen chamber of the Federal adopting it as the franchise , m-operty qualification Legislature it is proposed o su W’' e ‘‘‘ e ' J, men and won.eri, and. by an educational qualification 1 , . h as t&lt;) produce a where necessary, by a differential 8U ® ®. ( . en ' t . of the Depressed Class electorate of approxi province, except in Efrtd Orissa, S the^ P—e eaifranchi- aisri-— ^^Thed^taiSrfthefraneliise proposed are set ®' t ; I A, ' 1 „ al f^ tion I^oiRtration of claimants in respect of an educational qualification wilf. a t any rate for the first two elections, be on application by the * *' ^h^ effect ^f acceptance of the proposals in question would be to enfranchise between 2 and 3 per cent, of thetotai pope, at ion o British India. The gross total electorate would, so far as can be judged, amount to between 7 and 8 millions. The ‘ ‘ Safeguards . ’ The special responsibilities and powers of the Governor-General 17. At this point it is desirable to explain in detail the manner in which it is contemplated that the provisions of the C onstitution relating to the Governor-General’s special responsibilities and the special powers which are to flow from them will, in practice, work. As will be seen from paragraph 27 below, the general plan, subject to necessary variations, is the same for the Governor-General and the Governors, and taken in conjunction with the device already indicated of reserving certain Departments of State at the Centre for the exclusive control of the Governor-General, constitutes in effect the plan devised for the necessary limitations on responsible Government commonly described as “ safeguards.' The plan can best be described by considering the Governor-General’s relations with his Ministers on the one hand and with his Legislature on the other. Governor-General's relations with hu Ministers. 18. Although the Deserved Departments will be administered by the Governor-General on his sole responsibility, it would be impossible in practice for the Governor-General to conduct the affairs of these Departments in isolation from the other activities of his Government, and undesirable that he should attempt to do so, even if it were in fact possible. A prudent Governor-General would keep his Ministers and the advisers whom he has selected to assist him in the Reserved Depart ments in the closest contact; and, without blurring the line which will necessarily divide on the one hand his personal responsibility for the Reserved Departments, and, on the other hand, the responsibility of Ministers to the Legislature for the matters entrusted to their charge, he would so arrange the conduct of executive business that he himself, his Counsellors and his responsible Ministers, aic given the fullest opportunity of mutual consultation and discussion of all matters—and there will necessarily be many such— which call for co-ordination of policy. His Majesty’s Government intend to secure the embodiment of this principle in appropriate terms m the Governor-General’s Instrument of Instructions • but at the same time, the Instrument of Instructions will make it clear, without ambiguity, that whatever consultation between the Governor-General and his responsible Ministers may take place upon matters arising in tne Reserved Departments, the responsibility for the decisions taken is the Governor-General’s and the Governor-General’s alone.7 Introduction. iJ. A different problem presents itself in regard to the Governor- General s relations with his Ministers outside the ambit of the Reserved departments, ne., in the Departments which will be entrusted to the charge of Ministers responsible for the conduct of their administration Oi them to the Legislature. In this sphere Ministers, as aheadv explained, will have a constitutional right to tender advice, and the Governoi-General will, except to the extent and in the circumstances explained below, be guided by that advice. The problem is so to define the circumstances in which he will be entitled to act on his own exclusive responsibility. His Majesty's Government consider that the most satisfactory course will be o?) the enactment of provisions in the (’onstitution laying down that the Governor-General has a “ special responsibility,” not for spheres of administration, but for certain clearly indicated general purposes, and that for securing these purposes he is to exercise the powers conferred upon him by the (’onstitution Act in accordance with directions contained in his Instrument of Instructions; and (b) the insertion in the Instrument of Instructions inter alia of a direction to the effect that the Governor-General is to be guided by his Ministers’ advice unless so to be guided would, in his judgment, be inconsistent with a “special respon sibility ” imposed upon him by the Constitution Act, in which case he is to act, notwithstanding his Ministers' advice, in such manner as he judges requisite for the due fulfilment of his special responsibility. It will be apparent from this proposal that the Instrument of Instructions will assume a position of great importance as an ancillary to the Constitution Act, and His Majesty’s Government propose that appropriate arrangements shall be made to secure for this document, and for any subsequent amendments proposed to be made in it. the approval of both Houses of Parliament. 20. It remains to indicate the matters or purposes in respect of which the Governor-General should be declared, in accordance with the proposals in the preceding paragraph, to have a special responsibilitv in relation to the operations of the Federal Government. It is proposed that they should be the following :— (ii the prevention of grave menace to the peace or tranquillity of India or of any part thereof; (ii) the safeguarding of the financial stability and credit of the Federation; (iji) the safeguarding of the legitimate interests of minorities; (iv) the securing to the members of the Public Services of an} rights provided for them by the Constitution and the safeguarding of their legitimate interests; (v) the protection of the rights of any Indian State; (vi) the prevention of commercial discrimination; (vii) any matter which affects the administration of the Reserved Departments. 21 Before describing in detail the scope and purpose of the items’in this list, it is desirable to explain the precise effect which is contemplated as the result of imposing upon the Governor-Genera these “special responsibilities.” In the first place, it should be made clear that unless and until the Governoi-General feels’ called upon to differ from his Ministers m fulfilment oi a, “ special responsibility,” the responsibility of Ministers for the matters committed to their charge remains complete. Io take 'rete Since, it will clearly be the duty oi Mm.stere rattier than of the Governor-General himself, to ensure that the SmSis ration of their departments is so conducted that minorities are not suhfected to unfair or prejudicial treatment. The mtention of attributing to the Governor-General a special responsibilitv foi the nnrtection of minorities is to enable him, in any case where he regards the proposals of the Minister in charge of a department as likely to be „K or prejudicial to a particular minon^m the last resort to inform the Minister concerned (or the Ministers a bod},introduction* if they generally support uie proposals of ' h;m '' Nor iB it will be unable to accept tlie advice t « nd ““ l . ves t e d with contemplated that the Govemor-General, hasun b- . “ special responsibilities 'of the find it necessary, to be constantly - n,, proceed advice. The present proposals m genera - . ' • ] e by on the basic assumption that every endeavour *ill be ^ h those responsible for working the Constitution ^ a fP r ^f irit administrative problems which will presen 1 thei^eive^n the sp of partners in a common enterprise. In the bul - ' therefore in day-to-dav administration, where questioiib might ai s afiecting the Govemor‘-General’s “special responsibilities mutual consultation should result in agreement, so that no questaon wou arise of bringing the Governor-General s special responsibilities - play. 22. Reverting now to the list of ’ ‘ special responsibilities; ’ in para graph 20 , the necessity for the items numbered ( 1 ), (m) (l ^) » as a matter of course from previous statements of His Majesty . Government's policy. With regard to item (vn)^ h is appaL^^ that if, for example, the Governor-General were to be tree to folio his own judgment in relation to Defence pohcy only m regard to matters falling strictly within the ambit of the department of Defence, he might find that proposals made m another department m charge of a responsible Minister are in direct conflict with the line of policy he regards as essential for purposes connected with Defence, and consequently that the fulfilment of his responsibilities tor the department of Defence would be gravely impaired it he accepted the advice of the Minister responsible for the charge of the ottier department in question. If, therefore, such a situation is to be avoided, it is impossible to secure the object m view otherwise than by expressing the Governor-General s special responsibility ^ in some such terms as those indicated in item (vii). As regards item (v), it should be explained that this is not intended to give the Governor-General any special powers vis-a-vis the States m relation to matters arising in the Federal sphere proper; the necessary powers having been transferred by the States in their Instruments of Acces sion, such matters will be regulated in accordance with tue noimal provisions of the Constitution Act. Nor is it intended that the inclusion of this item should be regarded as having any bearing on the direct relations between the Crown and the States. These will be matters for which the Constitution will make no provision and which will fall to be dealt with by a Viceroy representing the Crown, who will be the Governor-General in a capacity independent of the Federal organisation. It may be, however, that measures are pioposed by the Federal Government, acting within its constitutional rights in relation to a Federal subject, or in relation to a Central subject not directly affecting the States at all, which, if pursued to a con clusion, would affect prejudicially rights of a State in relation to which that State had transferred no jurisdiction. Or, again, policies might be proposed or events arise in a Province which would tend to prejudice the rights of a neighbouring State. In such cases it is evident that it must be open to the Crown, through the Governor-General or the Governor, as the case may be, to ensure that the particular course of action is so modified as to maintain the integrity of rights secured to the State by Treaty or otherwise. 28. Item (vi) is intended to enable the Governor-General to deal with proposals for administrative action which he regards as likely to have discriminatory effects. As regards legislative discrimination His Majesty’s Government propose that the Constitution should impose a specific limitation on the powers of the Legislatures. Federal and Provincial, of two kinds. In the first place, they propose that legislation should be prohibited which makes religion, descent, caste, colour, place of birth, or any of them, the ground for any discriminatory treatment of any subject of His Majesty resident in the territory embraced by the Federation in respect of taxation, the holding of property, the carrying on of any profession, trade, business or occupation, or in respect of residence or travel. For the purpose of this provision, subjects of His Majesty yvill be defined as including (besides individuals) companies, partnerships orIntroduction, India Ug incor ! JOratec ' b .v or under the laws of British incorporated by or under the laws of the United Kinedom against he imposition of any disability or subjection to diSmnaZ Brit sW d 1 re ? rd t0 1 th ® exercise of certail “ specified rights within ntish India, if in the exercise m the United Kingdom of the corresponding right, an Indian subject of His Majesty oTa comnam incorporated under the laws of British India, would not be suWected H th 6 aT ‘ S °‘ the Umted Knl 8 dom to a disability or discrimination of the same or a similar, character. To this principle of reriprS treatment of Indian and Umted Kingdom “nationals' there'mus* X&lt; d pt;0n: u- n ? an agreement is reached, and for any time thereafter during which such an agreement is not subsisting, between he General Medical Council and an Indian Medical Council as to the mutual recognition ol medical degrees, medical practitioners duly qualified in the I mted Kingdom will be entitled to practise in India without the necessity of obtaining further qualifications The necessity lor such a provision in order to secure the attendance of British doctors upon the Army, Civil Servants and the European population generally needs no elaboration. Further, it is proimsed thaC m qualification of the generality of the prohibition against discrimination, an Act of the Federal, or of a Provincial, Legislature which, with a view to the encouragement of trade or industry, authorises the payment of bounties or subsidies out of public funds to ^tlading companies will not be held to be discriminatory by reason only of the fact that it is limited to persons resident or companies incorporated in India or that it imposes on companies entering the trade after the passing of the measure in question, as conditions of eligibility for such bounties or subsidies, the necessity of being- registered under the Indian Companies Act or of direction by a Board composed in a manner approved by the Governor-General or the provision of approved facilities for the training of Indians in the business of the company. The Governor-General and the Governors respeetivelv will be enjoined to reserve for the consideration of His Majesty any Bill passed by their respective Legislatures which, though not discriminatory in form, appears to them likely to lead to discrimination in practice. The effect of these provisions would be that any legislative measure. Federal or Provincial, which was inconsistent with them would be invalid, and could be challenged as such in the Courts; and that the Governor-General or the Governor, as the ease may be, would be entitled to act otherwise than in accordance with his Ministers’ advice, if he considered that such advice involved discriminatory action in the administrative sphere. 24. The second item in the list of special responsibilities deserves to be noticed at rather greater length since it involves the whole question of what have become known as “ financial safe guards.” Subject to the powers conferred upon the Governor-General by this responsibility, and subject to what is stated below as regards the “Reserve Bank.' it is intended that the Finance of the Federation should, like all other subjects, except those included in the Reserved Departments, be entrusted to the Ministry. Unless occasion arises for the exercise of the Governor-General’s special powers, it will therefore be for the Ministry, and the Ministry alone, to take decisions on all such matters as the means to be used for raising the necessary revenues, for allocating expenditure in the responsible field, and for the programme of external and internal borrowing. The appropriation of revenues for certain obligations* of the Federation, such, for example, the service of the debt, salaries and pensions of certain officers, as well as for the reserved departments, will, however, not require the vote of the Legislature, the treatment of these charges being roughly analogous to that of consolidated fund charges in this country. 18174—1! See Proposal 50 for full list. DIntroduction. 10 T1 , object of the Governor^Generars^Bpwial^rosponsjbilWy fer Fet%ta-Tt n oonfer on him powers to step in, if the need should f ederation is to ■ o{ hig Mimstry m respect,, foi or am oTthe obligations of the Federation, whether directly or indirectly through prejudicing India's credit m the 1 n 011 e.y- 111 a 1 l.ets d he world. The definition of this special responsibility ,s drawn hi somewhat wide terms not in order to diminish the field of responsi bility of the Ministry, but owing to the difficulty of giving a detai e specification of financial operations or measures which might occasion endanger stability and call for the use of the Governor- General’s powers. . j- i . In order that assistance may be available to him m the discharge of this special responsibility, the Governor-General will be empowered to appoint a Financial Adviser (without executive powers), whose services would also be available to the Ministi} . The proposals relating to responsibility for the Finance of the Federation are based on the assumption that there will be m existence and already successfully operating before the first Federal Ministry comes into being a Reserve Rank, fiee from political influence, which would be entrusted with the management of currency and exchange. His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India are taking every step in their power to facilitate and expedite the estab lishment of a Reserve Bank on sound principles. Some, however, of the conditions necessary for the successful establishment and operation of such a hank, depending as they do on world economic conditions, are not altogether within their control. If a situation should arise in which all other requirements for the inauguration of the Federation were satisfied, but it had so far proved impossible to start the Reserve Bank successfully, or financial and economic conditions were such as to foredoom to bankruptcy the new Federal and Provincial Governments at the outset of their careers, it would, inevitably, be necessary to reconsider the position and determine in the light of the then circumstances what course should be pursued. If, unfortunately, such reconsideration became necessary. His Majesty’s Government are pledged again to call into conference representatives of Indian opinion. ‘25. Apart from the Reserved Departments, and the specified ' special responsibilities of the Governor-General outside the sphere of those Departments, there is a third category of matters in which the Governor-General will be free to act on his own initiative and consequently will not be under any constitutional obligation to seek, or, having sought, to be guided by, ministerial advice. For this purpose certain specified powers will be conferred by the Constitution on the Governor-General and will be expressed as being exercisable at his discretion. In this category of discretionary powers,” the precise range of which it will be impossible exhaustively to foresee until the drafting of the Constitution has reached completion , 1B . Majesty’s Government anticipate that the following matters will be included :— A , ’ oumiuim tue ijegisiatur (b) 1 he power to assent to, or withhold assent from. Bills, or reserve them for the signification of His Majesty pleasure; J (c) The grant of previous sanction to the introduction of certa classes of legislative measures: (rfi The power to summon a joint Session of the Let-islature limi? ITT™ 7 ’ Wbere ob8e ™'« of the ordinary tin limit which, it was assumed, would be prescribed hv tl Constitution would produce serious consequences. It is also a necessary corollary of that the special powers to be conferred the purpose of enabling him to fulfil what has already been said on the Governor-General for his responsibilities must beIntroduction. similarly exercisable “at his discretion.” therefore, be added— To the foregoing mast. (e (/&gt; ■ he power to take action, notwithstanding an adverse vote in the Legislature—to be dealt with more fully below ■ I he power to arrest the course of discussion of measure; in the Legislature—also dealt with below: “ e I be power to make rules of legislative business in so far as these are required to provide for the due exercise of his own powers and responsibilities. Governor-General's Relations with the Legislatv re. wb. It is not sufficient, however, merely to regulate the Governor- General s relations with his responsible Ministers, i.e., to regulate matters arising m discussion amongst the members of the executive Government. It follows from previous declarations by His Majesty’s Government, upon which these Proposals are based, that the Governor-General must be given powers which will enable him effectively ^ to fulfil the responsibilities entrusted to him, whether for the Reserved Departments or the “special responsibilities” indicated above, if their fulfilment involves action normally lying within the functions of the Legislature to which the Legislature will not agree. The general scheme underlying the proposals is that, wherever the Governor-General’s responsibilities for the Reserved Departments, or his special responsibilities, are involved, he should be empowered not only to act without, or, as the case may be. contrary to, the advice of his Ministers, hut also to counteract an adverse vote of the Legislature whether such a vote relates to the passage of legislation or to the appropriation of funds. Bui it will clearly be of importance to the fostering of the, sense of responsibility in Ministers and Legislature alike that room should not be left for doubt whether in any given case the responsibility for the decision is, or is not. that of the Ministers or of the Legislature, ae the case may be—in other words, it is of importance that the special powers of the Governor-General should be so framed as to make it plain that the responsibility for the results of their exercise lies upon him. The necessity for the use of the Governor-GeneraTs legislative power may arise through the refusal of Ministers to be parties to a Bill, or to provisions in a Bill, which the Governor- General regards as essential to the discharge of his responsibilities, or where the Legislature rejects a Bill for which Ministers have accepted responsibility and which the Governor-General regards as essential, or the Legislature may alter the Bill to a form which would fail to secure the object which the Ministers and the Governor-General have in view. The essential point to be secured, in both contingencies, is, as already indicated, that when the Governor-General decides that the fulfilment of his responsibilities necessitates a course of action to which he is unable to obtain the consent either of his Ministers or of the Legislature-—or perhaps of neither—the resulting enactment should not purport to be an enact ment of the Legislature (as is the case with Acts which the Governor- General “certifies” under the existing Government of India Act), and further that its presentation to the Legislature should be brought about by the personal intervention of the Governor-General, that his responsibility for it should be manifest, and that Ministers should be in no way compromised by his action either with their supporters in the Legislature or their constituencies in the country. On the other hand, it would be undesirable to carry this principle to the logical extreme of placing all measures for which the Governor- General has himself to assume responsibility on the footing of Ordinances, the enactment of which involves no reference to the Legislature at all. The Governor-General’s powers in this regard should therefore be such as to enable him to test opinion in the Legislature; if he finds a majority there in support of his policy no question arises of using his special powers. If he finds only a minority in the Legislature in favour of his policy, he would at all events secure that measure of moral support, but he would carry out his policy on his own responsibility without compromising either the Ministers with their supporters in the Legislature, or the latter withIntroduction. their constituencies. It is l ir0 &gt; WS ^ euacted bv the Governor-General without the consent of *0 Leg ^ tore should be described as “ Governor-General s Acte, a special form of enacting words should be emp oj ^ them from lets ‘enacted by the Governor-General by and with consent of both Chambers of the Legislature. Governor- The nature of the corresponding power proposed for the &lt; General in the matter of supply, which is based upon the same principle, will be described in a later paragraph. •27. For the same purpose, namely, in order to enable the Governor-General effectively to fulfil his responsibilities for . Reserved Departments and his special responsibilities, ’ however! be necessary to arm him with a legislative power wh, h is capable of immediate employment m emergencies, either when the Legislature is not in session or if it is in 8 ®f ' 1 ‘ “ fo circumstances which necessitate immediate action. It is theretore. proposed to vest in him a power analogous to the existing Ordinance making power. Indeed, in addition to such a power to be placed at the disposal of the Governor-General at his discretion foi the express purpose of fulfilling his responsibilities ^ a Reserved Department, or for carrying out a special responsibility, 1 Majesty’s Government are of opinion that a similar power must necessarily be placed at the disposal of the Governor-General acting with his Ministers, i.e.. at the disposal of the Federal Govern ment, to meet cases of emergency when the Legislature is not in session, the Ordinances resulting therefrom being limited m duration to a specified period, and their continuation beyond that period being made dependent upon subsequent ratification by the Legislature. *28. Finally, it is proposed that the Constitution should contain provision requiring the previous sanction of the Governor-General acting in his discretion to the introduction of any Bill affecting a Reserved Department, or religion, or religious rites and usages, or any Bill repealing, amending, or affecting any Act or Ordinance of the Governor-General, enacted in discharge of his personal responsi bilities, and. in addition to this requirement, that the Governor- General should be empowered on the lines of the provisions of section 67 (2 A) of the existing Act, to prevent the discussion, or further discussion, of any measure the mere discussion of which, in his judgment, is liable to involve grave menace to peace and tranquillity. 29. It is perhaps desirable to summarise very briefly the essence and effect of these proposals. The intention is that the special powers of the Governor-General properly so described, namely, his power to obtain legislation and supply without the assent of the Legislature, will flow from the responsibilities specifically imposed upon him and be exercisable only for the purpose of enabling those responsibilities to be implemented. The responsibilities to be imposed on the Governor-General by the Constitution will be of two kinds—an exclusive responsibility for the administration of the Reserved Departments, and a “special responsibility” for certain defined purposes outside the range of the Reserved Departments. On the administration of the Reserved Departments, Ministers will have no constitutional right to tender advice, though, in practice, they will necessarily be consulted; nor wall they have any such right to tender advice on the exercise of any powers conferred upon the Governor- General for use “ in his discretion.” On all other matters Ministers will be constitutionally entitled to tender advice, and unless that advice is felt by the Governor-General to be in conflict with one of his special responsibilities he will be guided by it. If, in fulfilmeru of his responsibility for a Reserved Department, or of a special responsibility, the Governor-General decides that a legislative measure or a vote of supply to which the Legislature will not assent is essential, his special powers will enable him to secure the enactment of the measure of the provision of the supply in question, but Ministers will not have any constitutional responsibility for his decision.Introduction. 18 The Govebnors Provinces. The Executive. 30. The eleven provinces named in the margin will become autonomous units, the government of each being administered by a Governor representing the King, aided and advised by a Council of 5,1 msters responsible to the Legislature of the Province The u ' of „ Mlms ; e ''f be entitled to tender advice to the Governor on all matters which fall within the provincial sphere, other than the use of powers described by the Constitution Act as exercisable by the Governoi at his discretion, the nature of which will be explained more particularly later. The Governor will be guided by the advice tendered to him by Ministers, unless so to be guided would be in his judgment, inconsistent with the fulfilment of any of the purposes lor the fulfilment of which he will be declared by the Constitution Act to be charged with a “special responsibility”: in which case the Governor will be entitled, and indeed enjoined, to act, notwith- etanding the advice tendered to him. in such manner as he deems requisite for the fulfilment of his special responsibilities. M&amp;dra# ; Bombay, Bengal, The United Provinces, The Punjab, Bihar, The Central Provinces, Assam, The North- West Frontier Province, Sind, Orissa. (jovernors special powers and responsibilities. 31. As indicated above, the scheme for the Governor-General’s responsibilities and powers will be applicable in all respects to the Governor in relation to his Ministers and Legislature, with the following modifications : In the provinces there will be no category exactly corresponding to the Reserved Departments of the Governor- General, though analogous arrangements are intended in order to provide for the administration of those areas in certain Provinces which, from the primitive nature of their populations and their general characteristics, will have to be excluded from the normal operation of the Constitution. With this exception, the Governor’s special powers will flow from, and be expressed as being required in order to enable them to fulfil, his “ special responsibilities ” only. 32. As regards the “ special responsibilities ” of the Governors, these wdll be identical with those indicated in the case of the Governor-General, save that the first item on the list will, necessarily be confined in scope to the Province, or any part thereof, and not extend, as in the case of the Governor-General, to India as a whole, and that His Majesty’s Government do not consider it necessary to impose on the Governors a special responsibility for the financial stability of their Province. But in the case of the Governors, it will be necessary to add to the list of “ special responsibilities ” an item relating to the execution of orders passed by the Governor-General. If the Governor-General is to be charged, as will be explained later, with the general superintendence of the actions of Governors in exercise of their ” special responsibilities,” and if, as has already been proposed, he is liimself to have imposed upon him a “ special responsibility ” for the prevention of grave menace to peace and tranquillity throughout the country, it follows that he must be in a position to ensure that his instructions to a Governor are acted upon; and consequently that the Governor must be in a position to act otherwise than on his Ministers’ advice, if such advice conflicts with the Governor-General’s instructions. Finally, it will be necessary to impose upon the Governor a “special responsibility” for the administration of certain excluded areas, if, as seems probable, the arrangements for the administration of excluded areas involve their classification into two categories, one of which would be placed under the exclusive control of the Governor, while the other is made subject to Ministerial control, but with an over-riding power in the Governor obtained in the manner explained in earlier paragraphs through his “ special responsibility.’’ 33. The division of legislative powers between Centre and Provinces would no longer make appropriate the concentration in the hands of the Governor-General of the power to legislate in emergency by Ordinance on provincial matters and this power will now be con ferred on Governors also, for the double purpose indicated in paragraph 24^Introduction. 14 84. Finally, it shonM. General or a Governor is not . fhat he ghould be requirements of constitutional oeoi\ , Parliament for any responsible to His Majesty s io^n ^nd^l arlmme in t ^ 7. Governor the ehain of responsibility must necessarily include the Governor-General. 85 The proposals indicated above have no reference to situations where* a complete breakdown of the constitutional machinery has occurred It L the intention of His Majesty's Government that the Constitution should contain separate provision to meet such situatiomc should they unfortunately occur either in a Province oi m he Federation’as a whole, whereby the Governor-cenera or the Governor, as the case may be. will be given plenan authontv to assume all powers that he deems necessary for the purpose of carrying The Provincial Legislature. 86 . The Provincial Legislatures will be enlarged to the member ship first indicated in His Majesty’s Government s (ommunal Decision—(Cmd. 4147)—and now more exactly specified in Appendix to these proposals (or to a strength closely approximating to the figures there indicated) and seats will be apportioned to the various communities in the proportion shown in the same Appendix. The members will be in all cases elected, and no official will be eligible for election. In three Provinces the Legislature wil be bi-cameral : in the remainder it will consist of a single Chamber. Bui power will be given to each Provincial Legislature to abolish the Upper Chamber where such a Chamber exists or to create an Upper Chamber where it does not exist. The powers of provincial Upper Chambers will not be co-extensive with those of the Lower Chamber, but will extend only to revision and delay. The Provincial Franchise. 87. Details of the franchise proposed in the case of the various Provincial Legislatures are given in Appendix . The franchise in question is essentially based on property, supplemented by an educational qualification common to men and women alike; by a qualification for women in respect of property held by a husband by provision directed to secure a Depressed Class' electorate oi 1 () per cent, of the Depressed Class population in each province, except in Bihar and Orissa where the general percentage oi enfranchisement is in the neighbourhood of 9 per cent, only, and in the North West Frontier Province, where the numbers of the Depressed Classes are negligible; and by provision of a special electorate for the seats proposed to be reserved for the representatior °: Commerce, Labour and other special interests. Registration oi claimants m respect of an educational qualification or of a womar qualified in respect of her husband’s property will, at any rate foi the first two elections, be on application by the potentLl v'oter only A precise statement of the numerical effect of the electora qualifications proposed cannot be given pending the preparation a provisional electoral roll. So far as can be judged, however thes proposals, if accepted, would, in the typical case of Bengal enfranchise some 7* millions, or some ,5 per cem ouf o a total population of 50 millions. In the 'ease nl 'lin h the percentage to be enfranchised would nrobablv he Jv. ? A' than in Bengal; in Madras and the United Prmnncest ifn approximately the same- in all nthpr • 1(68 11 would hi substantially lower, the lowest figure heiim Ched • ' (1 * 0nld b&lt; Bihar and Orissa, with an electorate of some 7 ir’ tJle ca3 f 0 9 per cent, of the total population. The General efSJ 'T 0r ahou o the proposals in question for India 'as T whof ' a “ e P tan « electorate in the neighbourhood of H per '^1 T be ” population, or some 27 per cent of the sUif , ■ ° f the tote A separate franchise will be itt of Sind and Orissa. In the case of Sind thffc • new f’ rovin eei will Probably he substantially identical in generalWt®^tion. »rnor- nera] W be any this bility tions has t the iong. the the y to ying iber- unal ndix g to 'ions The rible ral : will iber lere not end tons Siise an F a nd; of ice, of ind the [jial ion of lan for iiy- iral of ese ;al, of &gt;ay ler be be of )Ut ice an tal $es on ?ct i ~ Introduction. allowance for certain differences in i-,- proposed for Bombay. The new nrovincc nf n ( : OIldltlon f] Wlth that consequence he necessary in this ‘age may in Powers of Federal and Provincial 1 jegisl atmres. oa. me conception of Federation and of that consequential c lange m provincial status commonly denoted by the expression I rovmcial autonomy ' will necessitate a complete departure from the existing system of concurrent jurisdictions—namelv, a statutory demarcation between the legislative competence of the Federal and Provincial Legislatures respectively, and the assignment to each of an exclusive field of competence which the other will not be permitted save to the extent indicated below, to invade. Following the practice of other Federal constitutions, the respective legislative fields of the Centre and of the Provinces will be defined in terms of subjects which will be scheduled to the Constitution Act. But while it will be possible to assign to the Federation and to the Provinces respectively a number of matters over which they can appropriately be charged with exclusive legislative jurisdiction, examination has shown that this method cannot without inconvenience he so employed as to exhaust the entire field of potential governmental activity and that there are some matters in respect of which, while some measure of uniformity of law may be necessary, variation of detail to meet the local conditions of the Provinces is no less necessary. It will consequently be necessary to schedule certain subjects whereon both Federal and Provincial Legislatures will enjoy concurrent powers, the exact nature and effects of which will be seen from paras. of these proposals. Illustrative lists of the exclusively Federal, exclusively Provincial and “ concurrent ” subjects, which do not purport to be complete or final, are appended. (Appendix B.i 39. It follows from the fact that the self-government to be conferred with the Federal Constitution is to be subject to limita tions, that these limitations must affect the powers of the Legislature; consequently neither the Federal Legislature nor the Provincial Legislatures, though possessed of plenary powers within their allotted spheres will be sovereign bodies. It is intended, however, that the limitations to be imposed upon their competence shall be strictly circumscribed, and shall, so far as possible, be elastic rather than rigid. Certain matters will be placed outside the competence altogether of both Federal and Provincial Legislatures, namely, legislation affecting the Sovereign or the Royal Family, the sovereignty or dominion of the Crown over any part of British India, the law of British nationality, and the Army Act, the Air Force Act and the Naval Discipline Act. Apart from a complete exclusion of jurisdiction in regard to these matters it is proposed that such potential limitations as it will be necessary to place upon the competence of the new Legislatures shall take the form familiarised by the provisions of the existing Act of requirements of the Governor- General’s—in some cases the Governor’s—previous sanction to the introduction of certain specified classes of measures. The proposed classification for this purpose will be found set out in paragraphs 121 and 122 of the Proposals. It will, of course, be made clear (para graph 123) that the grant by the Governor-General or by a Governoi of his prior consent to the introduction of a measure nndei this Proposal is not to be taken as fettering his judgment, when the time comes, if the measure is passed, for his decision as to the grant or withholding of his assent or the reservation of the measure or the signification of His Majesty’s pleasure. One further specific limitation on the powers of the Legislanre which has already been mentioned in paragraph 22 should be re 611 e ‘ to again in the present context, namely, the provisions proposed which will render ultra vires certain forms of discriminatory legislation.MOST SECRET. FOURTH PROOF. 24 Februanj, 19S8. Copy No. 27 THE PROPOSALS. THE FEDERATION. , General. 1. There will be first a declaration to the effect that all powers appertaining or incidental to the government of India and all rights, authority and jurisdiction possessed in that country— whether flowing from His Majesty’s sovereignty over the territories of British India, or derived from treaty, grant, usage, sufferance or otherwise in relation to other territories—are vested in the Crown and are exercisable by and in the name of the King Emperor. [See paragraph of Introduction.] 2. The Federation of India will be a union between the Governors’ Provinces and those Indian States whose Rulers signify their desire to accede to the Federation by a formal Instrument of Accession. By this Instrument the Ruler will transfer to the Crown for the purposes of the Federation his powers and jurisdiction in respect of those matters which he is willing to recognise as federal matters; and the powers and jurisdiction so transferred will thereafter be exercised on behalf of the Federation and in accordance with the provisions of the Constitution Act by the Governor-General, the Federal Legislature, the Federal Court (with an appeal therefrom to His Majesty in Council) and such other Federal organs as the Act may create. But in the case of every State which accedes, the powers and jurisdiction of the Federation in relation to that State and the subjects of its Ruler will be strictly co-terminous with the powers and jurisdiction transferred to the Crown by the Ruler himself and defined in his Instrument of Accession. 8 . Except to the extent to which a State has transferred powers and jurisdiction by its Instrument of Accession or has recognised thereby previous transfers—and, in the case of a State which has not acceded to the Federation, in all respects—its relations will be with the Crown represented by the Viceroy, and not with the Crown represented by the Governor-General as executive head of the Federal Government. Accordingly, all powers of the Crown in relation to the States which are at present exercised by the Governor-General in Council, other than those which fall within the Federal sphere, will after Federation be exercised by the Viceroy as the Crown’s representative. 4-. The Federation will be brought into existence by the issue of a Proclamation by His Majesty in Council declaring that on a date to be appointed in the Proclamation the existing nine Governors Provinces,” with Sind and Orissa (which will be constituted as new and separate Governors’ Provinces), are to be united in a Federation of India with such Indian States.as may accede to the federation; but the Proclamation will not be issued until (a) His Majestv has received intimation that the Rulers of States representing not less than half the aggregate population of the Indian States and entitled to not less than half the seats to be allotted to the States m the Federal Legislature, have signified their desire to accede to the Federation; and ajj (b) Both Houses of Parliament have presented an Add ™ 38 to His Majesty praying that such a 1 reclamation may, b ^ issued. [8174—2] ifProposals. ‘2 .jfoai .y +^~4 tmm*r «4| r;^ 5. The authority of tlie Federation will extend not only to tho Governors’ Provinces and the acceding States, but also to those areas in British India which are administered by Chief Commissionerg —namely the Provinces of Delhi, Ajmer-Merwara, Coorg, British Baluchistan and the Andaman and Nicobar Islands. These Provinces will be directly subject to the jurisdiction of the Federal Government and Legislature. In the case of British Baluchistan, however, special provision will be made whereby the adminiatration -of -frfatr Province wilLJ)e moreover, be given power to make Regulations for the peace of good government of the Province which will have the same force and effect as an Act of the Federal Legislature. No Act of the Federal Legislature wall apply to British Baluchistan unless the Governor- General in his discretion so directs and in giving any such direction he will be empowered to apply any such Act or any part thereof to the Province subject to such exceptions or modifications as he thinks fi£J Expenditure required for British Baluchistan will not be subject to the vote of the Federal Legislature, C&lt; 4 , At present the Settlement of Aden falls in this category. Proposals will, however, shortly be put forward for the administrative separation of this area from India. The Federal Executive. 8 . Gm executive authority of the Federation, including the supreme command of the Military, Naval and Air Forces in India will be exercisable on the King’s behalf by a Governor-General holding office during His Majesty’s pleasure, but His Majesty will be empowered to appoint a Commander-in-Chief to exercise in relation to those Forces such powers and functions as may be assigned to him. All executive acts will run in the name of the Governor- General. 7. The executive authority of the Federation will include in relation to a State only such powers and jurisdiction as the Ruler has by Ins Instrument of Accession expressly transferred to the Kin&lt;r for the purposes of the Federation. ' . • , exercise tne powers conferred upon h&gt;m by the Constitution Act a« executive head of the FederationTnd sucti powers of His Majesty (not being powers inconsistent will, the provisions of the Constitution Act) as His Majesty may be pleased bv Le ters Patent constituting the office of Governor-General to assign om. Li exercising all these powers the Governor-General will aM bl “r With 8,1 InStr ™ ent 0f T '“ns tobeS^hS The draft of any such Instructions (including the drafts of an* amendments thereto) will be laid heW WP it!? £ * ,. ot an J and opportunity will be provided for each S ^■^ent Instructions. ’ nission Irom, the tion Act and all other payments in respect of hifpersonal 1 allo 0, ‘ SHtU ' or of salaries and allowances of his nersnnai . a p onal allowances, be fixed by Order in Council none of T. ff etarial will th.s paragraph will be subject to the vot ofThe I “gTslIto'^ * “ 10 . The Governor-General may be , under conditions to be prescribed bv Order H n of ab8euo « is granted leave a substitute will be annoint iTl ' 101 ’ and when he Warrant under the Royal Sign Manual. ^ * to ^ for him b . T wm'be il p &gt;- whose favour a dormant commission has been flsued ’ by * Per80D in8 Proposals. The Working of the Federal Executive. administration orcertLn^enLtm' dlrect and 00ntl&lt; &gt; i ‘h* External Affairs and Eeclesiitica! Affairs tfl ^“ mely ’ De,eD&lt;&gt;e &gt; Govemor^ene'rarwmt'a^T/K th6 , Reserved ^tments, the who will be appointed hv rhf r n0t ^ 0re t * lan t * lree Counsellors, and eonditiorS^^^^r^ 1 ^ General in tlie^ever' 11 ^ 0H f ^ aiding and advising the Governor- the Government o/'fhe^^T^t-^^ 1 '^' 1 Up0n him b y the Act fo1 ' with the matteL f h f P ® &lt;1&lt; : ratlon &gt; other than powers connected law to Ids dte r™ I?' 6 * 1 m .,/ lara K ra P h 12, and matters left by Ministers will b ev' 0n ’ W1 be a Collncil of Ministers. The sworn as Tf b p h 06 .' f‘ d summoned b y Governor-General and pleasm-e i )j 1 t , mbers of the Gonncil and will hold office during his wHhin a stated ap P°’ nted Minist «™ mus t be, or be«&gt;me Federal r J egislatn P re n mem ^ ° f ° r 0thPr Chamber of the 15. In his Instrument of Instructions the Governor-General will be enjoined inter aim to use his best endeavours to select his Ministers m the following manner, that is, to commit to the person who, in his judgment is likely to command the largest following in the Legislature the selection of Ministers for the Governor-General’s approval, and m consultation with that person to appoint to the Councii of Ministers those persons (including so far as possible members ol important minority communities and representatives of the States members of the Federation) who will best be in a position collectively to command the confidence of the Legislature. 16. I lie number of Ministers and the amounts of their respec tive salaries will be regulated by Act of the Federal Legislature, but, until the Federal Legislature otherwise determines, their number and theii salaries will be such as the Governor-General determines, not, however, exceeding the numbers and amounts specified in Appendix The salary of a Minister will not be subject to variation during bis term of office. 17. The Governor-General will have the right to preside at his discretion at any meeting of his Council of Ministers. He will also be authorised, after consultation with his Ministers, to make at his discretion any rules which he regards as requisite to regulate the procedure and formalities to be observed in the conduct of Govern ment business, and for the transmission to himself and to his Counsellors in the Eeserved Departments, and to the Financial Adviser, of all such information as they may require. 18. The Governor-General will be empowered, at his discretion, but after consultation with his Ministers, to appoint a Finaricial Adviser to assist him in the discharge of his “ special responsibility ” for financial matters—see next paragraph—and also to advise Ministers on matters regarding which they may seek his advice. The Financial Adviser will be responsible to the Governor-General and will hold office during his pleasure; his salary will be fixed by the Governor-General and will not be subject to the vote of the Legislature. 19. Apart from his exclusive responsibility for the Reserved Departments (paragraph 12) the Governor-General in administering the Government of the Federation will be declared to have a ' ‘ special responsibility ” in respect of— (a) the prevention of any grave menace to the peace or tran quillity of India or any part thereof; (b) the safeguarding of the financial stability and credit of the Federation; , C ) the safeguarding of the legitimate interests of minorities;Proposals. (d) the securing to the members of the Public Services of any rights provided for them by the Constitution Act and the safeguarding of their legitimate, interests, (e) the prevention of commercial discrimination, ./) the protection of the rights of any Indian State; (a) anv matter which affects the administration of any Depart ment under the direction and control of the Governor- General. It will be for the Governor-General to determine whether any of. the “ special responsibilities” here described are involved by any given circumstances. 20. If in any case in which, in the opinion of the Governor- General, a special responsibility is imposed upon him it appears to him, after considering such advice as has been given him by his Ministers, that the due discharge of his responsibility lequires that he should himself take such action as he deems fit, he will have full discretion to exercise all such powers as are conferred upon him by the Act; so, however, that in the exercise thereof he is to be guided by any directions which may be contained in his Instrument of Instructions. 21. The Governor-General, in administering the Departments under his own direction and control, in taking action for the discharge of any special responsibility, and in exercising any discretion vested in him by the Act or by his Instrument of Instructions, will be required to give effect to such directions, if any, not being directions inconsistent with anything in his Instructions, as may be given to him by a principal Secretary of State. 22. The Governor-General’s Instrument of Instructions will contain inter alia provision on the following lines :•— “ In matters arising in the Departments which you direct and control on your own responsibility, or in matters the determination of which is by law committed to your discretion, it is Our will and pleasure that you should act in exercise of the powers by law conferred upon you in such manner as you may judge right and expedient for the good government of the Federation, subject, however, to such directions as you may from time to time receive from one of Our principal Secretaries of State. In matters arising out of the exercise of powers conferred upon you for the purposes of the government of the Federation other than those specified in the preceding paragraph it is Our will and pleasure that you should, in the exercise of the powers by law conferred upon you, be guided by the advice of your Ministers, unless so to be guided would, in yonr judgment, be inconsistent with the fulfilment of your special responsibility for any of the matters in respect of which a special responsibility is by law committed to you; in which case it is Our will and pleasure that you should, notwithstanding your Ministers’ advice, act in exercise of the powers by law conferred upon you in such manner as you judge requisite for the fulfilment of your special responsibilities, subject, however, to such directions as you may from time to time receive from one of Our principal Secretaries of State.” i The Federal Legislature. General. 23. The Federal Legislature will consist of His Majesty, represented by the Governor-General, and two Chambers, to be styled the Council of State and the House of Assembly, and will be summoned to meet for the first time not later than a date to be specified in the Proclamation establishing the Federation. Every Act of the Federal Legislature will be expressed as bavin e been enacted by the Governor-General, by and with the consent of of both Chambers. 24. Power to summon, and appoint places for the meeting of. the Chambers, to prorogue them, to dissolve them, either separately or simultaneously, and to address either Chamber separatelv or bothProposals. jointly, will be vested in the Governor-General at his discretion, subject to the requirement that they shall meet at least once in every year and that not more than twelve months shall intervene between the end of one session and the commencement of the next. G-'' 1 -• 23. Subject to dissolution, each Council of State will continue for seven years and each Assembly for five years. 26. A member of the Council of Ministers will have the right to speak, but not to vote, in the Chamber of which he is not a Member. A Counsellor will be ex officio an additional member of both Chambers for all purposes except the right of voting. The Composition of the Chambers. 27. The Council of State will consist, apart from the Governor- General’s Counsellors, of not more than 260 members, of whom 150 will be elected from Provinces in the manner indicated in Appendix , not more than 100 allocated in the manner indicated in the same Appendix, who will be appointed by the Eulers of States, and not more than ten (who shall not be officials) will be nominated by the Governor-General in his discretion. 28. A member of the Council of State shall be at least 30 years of age (this age limit not, however, being applicable to the Ruler of a State) and a British subject or a Euler or subject of an Indian State, and he shall possess either one of the property qualifications set out in Appendix , or have been at some previous date a member of the Indian Legislature or of the Federal Legislature, or possess qualifications to be prescribed by the Government of the State or Province which he represents with a view to conferring qualification upon persons who have rendered distinguished public service. 29. Casual vacancies in the Council of State will be filled, in the case of a British Indian elected representative, by election (so long as communal representation is retained as a feature of the Constitution) by those members of the body by which he was elected who are members of the community to which the vacating member belongs, and in the case of a nominated member, by a fresh nomination by the person by whom the vacating member was nominated. 30. The Assembly will consist, apart from the Governor- General’s Counsellors, of not more than 375 members, of whom 250 will be elected to represent constituencies in British India in the manner indicated in Appendix , and not more than 125 allocated in the manner indicated in the same Appendix, who will be appointed by the Rulers of States. 31. A member of the Assembly shall be not less than 25 years of age and a British subject or a subject of an Indian State. 32. Casual vacancies in the Assembly will be filled, in the case of an elected member, by the same method as that prescribed in Lie Appendix for the election of the vacating member, and, in the case of a nominated member, by a fresh nomination by the person by whom the vacating member was nominated. 33. Only the Ruler of a State who has acceded to the Federation will be entitled to appoint, or take part in appointing, a member ol either Chamber of the Federal Legislature, and any vacancies arising out of the operation of this restriction will for the time being remain unfilled. [8174—2] ; c6 Proposals* 34. Every member of either Chamber will be required to make and subscribe an oath or affirmation in the following form be In the ease of an appointed member :— Council, “ I, A.B., having been appointed a member of this AggemWVt do solemnly swear (or affirm) that, saving the faith and allegiance I owe to C.D., I will be faithful and bear true allegiance m my capacity as Member of this Aggem biv ^ a j es h' Emperor of India, His heirs and successors, and that 1 will fanh- fully discharge the duty upon which I am about to enter. I. A.B., having been In the case of an elected or nominated member :— elected , . Council, T a member of this . ,, nominated Assembly, do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will be faithful and bear true allegiance to His Majesty the King Emperor of India, His heirs and successors, and that I will faithfully discharge the duty upon which 1 am about to enter.” 35. Appropriate provision will be made- fa) for the election of a President and Deputy President of the Council of State and a Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the Assembly, and for the tenure of those offices; {(&gt;) for determining the quorum and for the determination of questions by majority vote; &lt;c) for prohibiting membership of both Chambers by the same individual and for determining in cases of double election of which Chamber he shall be a member; {d) for the resignation of a seat in either Chamber; and (e) for the vacation of a seat by reason of absence through incapacity or neglect. 36. The following disqualifications will be prescribed for membership of either Chamber :— in) in the case of elected members or of members nominated by the Governor-General, the holding of any office of profit under the Crown other than that of Minister: (b) a declaration of unsoundness of mind by a competent Court; (c) being an undischarged bankrupt; (d) conviction of the offence of corrupt practicee or other election offences: ) in the case of a legal practitioner, suspension from practice by order of a competent Court; but provision will be made that the last two disqualifica tions may be removed by order of the Governor-General at his discretion: (/) having an interest in any contract with the Federal Govern- ment; V^vided that the mere holding of shares in a company will not by itself involve this disqualification. ^ ua a luemoer ot either Chamber when he is not qualified for, or is disqualified from, membership will be made liable to a penalty of • , ? e«ch day on which he so sits or votes, to be recovered in 'the High he Prov ince or State which the person in respect of whom the complaint is made represents by suit instituted with the cousin of a 1 nncpal Law Officer of the Federation [?i„ the Federal Chir^fwm £^rei“^ri n „V°th e San a b eCtin8 f t Federal Legislature. No person wifi' bt l^blTt “f^i^7 Proposal*. by tt rea^n ,r of b 'anvtSi &gt; n, ° f ^ ? pe t oi '. 0r votc in 9ither Chamber, or y re ^° n ol anything contained in any official retvvrf proceedings in either Chamber. * ep0rt of ^ procure in .nT 118 matterB .^nected with elections and electoral procedure in so far as provision is not made by the Act will be regulated by Order in Council^ i a ) qualifications of electors; (b) The delimitation of constituencies; (0 The method of election of representatives of communal and other interests; (d) The filling of casual vacancies; and (e) Other matters ancillary to the above; vdh pionsion that Orders m Council framed for these purposes shall be laid in draft for a stated period before each House of Parliament. ror matters other than the above connected with the conduct of elections the Federal Legislature will be empowered to make provision by Act. But until the Federal Legislature otherwise determines, existing laws or rules, including the law or rules providing for the prohibition and punishment of corrupt practices or election offences and for determining the decision of disputed elections, will remain in force, subject, however, to such modifications or adaptations to be made by Order in Council as may be required in order to adapt their provisions to the requirements of the new Constitution. Legislative Procedure. 40. Bills (other than Money Bills, which will be initiated in the Assembly) will be introduced in either Chamber. 41. The Governor-General will be empowered at his discretion, hut subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act and to Instruc tions given him in that behalf, to assent in Ilis Majesty’s name to a Bill which has been passed by both Chambers, or to withhold his assent, or to reserve the Bill for the signification of the King’s pleasure. He will also be empowered, if he thinks fit, before taking any of these courses, to remit a Bill to the Chambers with a Message requesting its reconsideration in whole or in part, together with such amendments, if any, as he may recommend. No Bill will become law until it has been agreed to by both Chambers either without amendment or with such amendments only as are agreed to by both Chambers, and has been assented to by the Governor-General, or, in the case of a reserved Bill, until His Majesty in Council has signified his assent. 42. Any Bill assented to by the Governor-General will within twelve monthe be subject to disallowance by the King in Council. 43. In the case of disagreement between the Chambers, the Governor-General will be empowered, in any case in which a Bill passed by one Chamber has not, within three months thereafter, been passed by the other, either without amendments or with agreed amendments, to summon the two Chambers to meet in a joint sitting for the purpose of reaching a decision on the Bill. The members present at a Joint Session will deliberate and vote together upon the Bill in the form in which it finally left the Chamber in which it was introduced and upon amendments, if any, made therein by one Chamber and not agreed to by the other. Any such amendments which are affirmed by a majority of the total number of members voting at the Joint Session will be deemed to have been carried, and if the Bill, with the amendments, if any. so carried, is affirmed by a majority of the members voting at the Joint Session, it shall be taken to have been duly passed by both Chambers. In cases where a delusion on a Bill cannot, in the Governor- General’s opinion, be delayed without serious prejudice to the public interest, he will be empowered at his discretion to summon a Joint Session at any time without waiting for the expiry of the normal period of three months indicated above.8 Proposals. 44 ^ order so enable the Governor-Genera* io falhl res^itmines imposed upon him peraonaUv for ^ the Reserved Departments and his special reaponmbihties, he wiU be empowered at hia discretion— a ,o present, or cause to be presented a BiU to either Chanier. and to declare bv Message to both Uiambers that .t is essential, having regard to h» reepons.bdities for a Reserved IVrartment or. as the ease mav be, o any o his • special responsibilities.” that the Bill so presented , i. . ifiod m the Measage ; b to declare bv Message in respect of any Bill already introduced in either Chamber that it should for similar reasons become » 1 m 1 ■% r _ 1_ rv a £h ^a'WW /» A t A Bill which is the subject of such a Message will then be considered or reconsidered bv the Cnambers, as the case i ay require, and if. before the date specified, it is not passed by the two Cumbers, or is not passed by the two Chambers in the form specified, the Governor-General will be empowered at his discretion to enact it as a Governor-General s Act. either with or without any amendments made bv either Chamber after receipt of his Message. *A Governor-General's Act so enacted will have the same rorce and effect as an Act of the Legislature, and will be subject to disallowance in the same manner, but the Governor-General s competence to legislate under the provision will not extend beyond the competence of the Federal Legislature as defined by the Constitution. 45. Provision will also be made empowering the Governor- General. in anv case in which he considers that a Bill introduced, or proposed for introduction, or any clause thereoi, or any amendment to a Bill moved or proposed, would affect the discharge of his special reeponsibilirv ” for the prevention of any grave menace to the peace or tranquillity of India, to direct that the Bill, clause or amendment shall not be further proceeded with. Procedure with regard to Financial Proposals. 46. A recommendation of the Governor-General will be required for any proposal in either Chamber of the Federal Legislature for the imposition of taxation, for the appropriation of public revenues, or axv proposal affecting the public dehf. or affecting, or imposing anv charge upon, public revenues.t 47. The Governor-General will cause a statement of the estimated revenue and expenditure of the Federation, together with a s r a'ement of all proposals for the appropriation of those revenues, to be laid, in respect of every financial year, before both Chambers of the Legislature. The statement of proposals for appropriation will be so arranged as— a to distinguish between those proposals which will, and those which will not see paragraph 50' be submitted to the vote of the Legislature: and fh to specify separately those additional proposals (if any), whether under the votable or non-votable Heads, which the Governor-General regards as necessary for the discharge of any of his ' special responsibilities.” * It is proposed to make ft dear, through a distinction between the enacting words of a Governor-General's Act and the enacting words of an ordinary Act (see paragraph 23f. that Acts of the former description are enacted on the Governcr-Generai's own responsibility. + This paragraph represents the const ; tutional principle embodied in Standing Order 66 of the House of Commons, which finds a place in practically every Constitution Act throughout the British Empire: — “ This House will receive no petition for any sum relating to public service or proceed upon any motion for any grant or charge upon the public revenue, whether payable out of the consolidated fund or out of money to be provided by Parliament, unless recommended from the C^Gwn. ,,9 48. The proposals for the appropriation of revenues, other than proposals relating to the Heads of Expenditure enumerated in tiara' graph 50, and proposals (if any) made by the Governor-General in discharge of his special responsibilities, will be submitted in the form of Demands foi Grants to the vote of the Assemblv. The Assembly will be empowered to assent or refuse assent to any Demand or to reduce the amount specified therein, whether by wav of a general reduction of the total amount of the Demand or‘of the reduction or omission of any specific item or items included in it. 49. The Grants as voted by the Assembly will thereafter be laid before the Council of State which will be empowered to require that any Grant in relation to which it disagrees with the Assembly shall be brought before a Joint Session of both Chambers for final determination. 50. Proposals for appropriation of revenues, if they relate to the Heads of Expenditure enumerated in this paragraph, will not be submitted to the vote of either Chamber of the Legislature, but, except in the case of items (ii) and (v), will be open to discussion in both Chambers. The Heads of Expenditure referred to above are— (i) Expenditure required for the purposes of Defence,* External Affairs,* or Ecclesiastical Affairs, or for the salaries and allowances of the Financial Adviser and his staff; (ii) Expenditure required for the discharge of the functions of the Crown in, and arising out of, its relations with the Rulers of Indian States ; (iii) Expenditure required for the discharge of the duties imposed by the Constitution Act on a principal Secretary of State, in so far as such expenditure is not covered by item (i) and item (ii); (iv) Interest, Sinking Fund charges and other expenditure relating to the raising and service of loans; (v) The salary and allowances payable under the Act to the Governor-General; (vi) Sums payable on account of the Governor-General’s personal or secretarial staff, and the salary and allowances of his Counsellors and of Chief Commissioners; (vii) The salary and allowances payable under the Constitution Act to Ministers; (viii) The salaries and pensions payable under the Act to, or to the dependants of, Judges of the Federal Court or the Supreme Court or Judicial Commissioners or Additional Judicial Commissioners and expenditure certified by the Governor-General after consultation with his Ministers, as required for the expenses of their Courts; (ix) Expenditure authorised and fixed by any law, or required to satisfy a decree or order of any Court or an arbitral award; (x) Expenditure required for the discharge of the functions of the Crown in the administration of any areas which are, under the provisions of the Constitution Act, for the time being treated as Excluded Areas; (xi) Expenditure required for the administration of British Baluchistan; (xii) Salaries and pensions payable to, or to the dependants of:— (a) persons appointed by or with the approval of His Majesty or by the Secretary of State in Council before the commencement of the Constitution Act or by a Secretary of State thereafter; (b) persons appointed before the first day oi April, 1924, by the Governor-General in Council or by a Local Government to Services and posts classified as superior, (c) holders in a substantive capacity of posts borne on the cadre of the Indian Civil Service; (d) members of any Public Service Commission. * The Governor-General’s Instrument of Instructions will contain provisions requiring him to consult his Ministers on his proposals tor appropriations unfer these Heads before they are la.d before the Legislature.Proposal*. 10 i ^ n person wlio is, &lt;xi ii, Sums payable to. 01 to tbe in India under (xm ' or has been, in ^ “rln ni State it, Council, by any Order made by the y nven ior-General m Council, a Secretary of State , by the t appeal preferred to or by the'Governor-Geneml upw &gt; Conatitution him in pursuance of huies Act; and , • paragraph the expression For the purposes of the a8 including remuneration, “ salaries and pensions ^i w hether by way of interest or Allowances, gratuities, contnbi , Fdfci to a ny Provident otherwise, out of the revenues ^ her paym ents or emolu- Fund or Family Pension Fund, and any^ q{ hiB ffice . m&lt; ^Th^Governor-General will ^empowered ^T^ndUnro'dCKes not fail under any of the Heads o, Expenditure referred to in fide paragraph. 31. At the conclusion of the budget ^eto^toGovemor- &lt; 3 eneral will be required to certafy a Pp^P ^ ^ ^ jn eiM||g Rrirri', *• proposals for appropriation under ^ p e empowered in his anv such additional sums do not exceed me ags * ' (a) anv sums (if any) originally included in the statement «d ( 'proposed appropriations m respect of h,s special wMch° f a Demand for a Grant has been reduced by vote of the Legislature. Every certificate so given by the Governor-General will be laid before both Chambers of the Legislature, but will not he &lt;&gt;pe n .t° discussion by them and will be for all purges sufficient authority for the appropriation of the sums in question. 52 The provisions of paragraphs 48 to 51 inclusive will apply to proposals for the appropriation of revenues to meet expenditure not included in the Animal Estimates which it may become necessary to • ,1 v't ni n I -\7OQ Y* Procedure in the Federal Legislature. 53 . The procedure and conduct of business in each Chamber of the Legislature will be regulated by rules to be made, subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act, by each Chamber; but the Governor-General will be empowered at his discretion, after consultation with the President, or Speaker, as the case may be, to make rules— (a) regulating the procedure of, and the conduct of business in, the Chamber in relation to matters arising out of, or affecting, the administration of the Reserved Departments or any other special responsibilities with which he is charged; and (b) prohibiting, save with the prior consent of the Governor- General, the discussion of— ■ i) matters connected with any Indian State other than matters accepted by the Ruler of the State in his Instrument of Accession as being Federal subjects; or (ii) any action of the Governor-General in his relation ship with a Governor ; or (iii) any matter affecting relations between His Majesty or the Governor-General and any foreign Prince or State. In the event of conflict between a rule so made by the Governor- General and any rule made by the Chamber, the former will prevail and the latter will, to the extent of the inconsistency, be void.11 Proposals. 54. The provisions of the Constitution Act and of any rules made, with respect to the procedure of, and conduct of business in, the Council of State will apply to Joint Sessions of the Chambers a« it the members of the Assembly present at those sittings were for the time being additional members of the Council of State. Emergency Powers of the Governor-General in relation to Legislation. 55. 1 he Governor-General will be empowered at his discretion, if at any time he is satisfied that the requirements of the Reserved Departments, or any of the 'special responsibilities” with which he is charged by the Constitution Act render it necessary to make and promulgate such Ordinances as, in his opinion, the circumstances of the case require, containing such provisions as it would have been competent, under the provisions of the Constitution Act, for the Federal Legislature to enact. An Ordinance promulgated under the proposals contained in this paragraph will continue in operation for such period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified therein; the Governor-General will, however, have power to renew any Ordinance for a second period not exceeding six months, but in that event it will be laid before both Houses of Parliament. An Ordinance will have the same force and effect, whilst in operation, as an Act of the Federal Legislature; but every such Ordinance will be subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act relating to disallowance of Acts, and will be subject to withdrawal at any time by the Governor-General. 56. In addition to the powers to be conferred upon the Governor-General at his discretion in the preceding paragraph, the Governor-General will further be empowered, if his Ministers are satisfied, at a time when the Federal Legislature is not in session, that an emergency exists which renders such a course necessary, to make and promulgate any such Ordinances for the good government of British India, or any part thereof, as the circumstances of the case require, containing such provisions as, under the Constitution Act, it would have been competent for the Legislature to enact. An Ordinance promulgated under the proposals contained in this paragraph will have, while in operation, the same force and effect as an Act of the Federal Legislature, but every such Ordinance- la) will be required to be laid before the Federal Legislature and, unless previously approved by Resolutions of both Chambers, will cease to operate at the expiry of six months from its promulgation, or at the expiry of fourteen days from the reassembly of the Legislature, whichever date is the earlier; and (b) will be subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act relating to disallowance as if it were an Act of the Federal Legislature; it will also be subject to withdrawal at any time by the Governor-General. 57. The Governor-General will be empowered at his discretion, if at any time he is satisfied that a situation has arisen which renders it for the time being impossible for the government of the Federation to be carried on in accordance with the other provisions of the Constitution Act, by Proclamation to assume to himself all such powers vested by law in any Federal authority as appear to him to be necessary for the purpose of securing that the government o the Federation shall be carried on effectively. , . A Proclamation so issued will have to same force and effect ah an Act of Parliament; will be communicated forthwith to a Secretary of State and laid before Parliament; will cease to operate at the expiry of six months unless, before the expiry of that period, it has teen approved by Resolutions of both Houses of Parliament; and may at any time be revoked by Resolutions by both Houses oi Parliament.12 Proposals. THE PROVINCES. (i) The Governors' Provinces. The Provincial Executive. 88 ^ “Governor's Province” will be defined as meainng the Presidencies of Bengal. Madras and Bombay, and the Provinces known as the United Provinces, the Punjab, Bihar, the J, en ‘ ® Provinces, Assam, the North-West Frontier Province, Sind, and 59. In a Governor’s Province the executive authority will &gt; e exercisable on the King’s behalf by a Governor holding office during His Majesty’s pleasure. ? ^ All executive acts will run in the name ol the Governor. 60. The Governor will exercise the powers conferred upon him bv the Constitution Act as executive head of the Provincial Govern ment, and such powers of His Majesty (not being powers inconsistent with the provisions of the Act) as His Majesty may be pleased by Letters Patent constituting the office of Governor to assign to him. In exercising all these powers the Governor will act in accordance with an Instrument of Instructions to be issued to him by the King. The draft of any such Instructions (including the drafts of any amendments thereto) will be laid before both Houses of Parliament, and opportunity will be provided for each House of Parliament to make to His Majesty any representation which that House may desire for any amendment or addition to, or omission from, the Instructions. 61. The Governor’s salary will be fixed by the Constitution Act. and all other payments in respect of his personal allowances, or the salaries and allowances of his personal and secretarial staff, will be fixed by Order in Council; none of the expenditure referred to in this paragraph will be subject to the vote of the Legislature. 62. The Governor may be granted leave of absence under conditions to be prescribed by Order in Council, and when he is granted leave a substitute will be appointed to act for him by Warrant under the Royal Sign Manual. 63. In the case of death or incapacity the Governor's place will be taken, until the King’s pleasure is signified, by a person to be appointed by the Governor-General. Working of the Provincial Executive. 64. For the purpose of aiding and advising the Governor in the exercise of powers conferred on him by the Constitution Act for the government of the Province, except as regards matters left by law T to his discretion and the administration of Excluded Areas, there will be a Council of Ministers. The Ministers will be chosen and summoned by the Governor and sworn as Members of the Council, and will hold office during his pleasure. Persons appointed Ministers must be, or become within a stated period, members of the Provincial Legislature. 65. In his Instrument of Instructions the Governor will be enjoined inter alia to use his best endeavours to select his Ministers in the following manner, that is, to commit to the person who, in his judgment, is likely to command the largest following in the Legislature the selection of Ministers for the Governor’s approval, and in consultation with that person to appoint to the Council of Ministers those persons (including so far as possible members of important minority communities) who will best be in a position collectively to command the confidence of the Legislature. 66. The number of Ministers and the amounts of their respec tive salaries will be regulated by Act of the Provincial Legislature,18 Proposals. but until the Provincial Legislature otherwise determines their umber and salaries will be such as the Governor determines, not Appendix ““ Miedmg ““ m,mhere and amounts specified in The salary of a Minister will not he subject to variation during hte term of office. 5 87. The Governor will have the right to preside at his discretion at any meeting of his Council of Ministers. He will also be Authorised, after coneultation with his Ministers, to make at his discretion any rules which he regards as requisite to regulate the procedure and formalities to be observed in the conduct of Govern ment business, and for the transmission to himself of all such information as he may require. 88 . In the administration of the government of a Province the Governor will be declared to have a special responsibility in respect (a) the prevention of any grave menace to the peace or tran quillity of the Province or any part thereof; (b) the safeguarding of the legitimate interests of minorities; (c) the securing to the members of the Public Services of any rights provided for them by the Constitution and the safe guarding of their legitimate interests; (d) the prevention of commercial discrimination: (e) the protection of the rights of any Indian State; &lt;/) th e administration of areas declared., in accordance with provisions in that behalf, to be partially excluded areas; (g) securing the execution of orders lawfully issued by the Governor-General; and the Governors of the North-West Frontier Province and of Sind will in addition be respectively declared to have a special responsibility in respect of— (h) any matter affecting the Governor s responsibilities as Agent to the Governor-General in the Tribal Areas ; and (!) the administration of the Sukkur Barrage. It will be for the Governor to determine whether any of the 11 special responsibilities” here described are involved by any given circumstances. 69. If in any case in which, in the opinion of the Governor, a special responsibility is imposed upon him, it appears to him, after considering such advice as has been given to him by his Ministers, ihat the due discharge of his responsibility requires that he should himself take such action as he deems fit, he will have full discretion to exercise all such powers as are conferred upon him by the Constitution Act; so, however, that in the exercise thereof he is to be guided by any directions which may be contained in his Instru ment of Instructions or which may be given him by the Governor- General . 70. The Governor, in taking action for the discharge of any special responsibility or in the exercise of any discretion vested in him by the Constitution Act, will be required to give effect to such directions, if any, not being directions inconsistent with anything in his Instructions, as may be given to him by the Governor-General or by a principal Secretary of State. 71. The Governor’s Instrument of Instructions will contain inter alia provision on the following lines :— “In matters, the determination of which is by law committed to your discretion, and in matters relating to the administration of Excluded Areas, it is Our will and pleasure that you should act in exercise of the powers by law conferred upon you in such manner as you may judge right and expedient for the good government of the Province, subject, however, to such directions as you may from time to time receive from Our Governor- General or from one of Our principal Secretaries of State. [8174-2] sProposals* 14 In matters arising out of th « eIer ““ “ f “orince othw y ou for the p « e ° eXg wph ' ia Our ^ than those specified m the p - exercise of the powers by and pleasure that you 9hould , he advice 0 { your Ministers, law conferred upon you be gm ^ judgment, be inconeistent unless so to be guided would, ^ ’ {or a of the with the fulfilment o ^ by law matters m respect ol ' h 1 . is wil j aD d pleasure committed to yo«^® ^ Ministers’ advice, act in that you should, notwithstano g ^ guch ma „ n er toe to toe receive from Our Governor-General or from one of Our principal Secretaries of State. The Provincial Legislature. General. 72. For every Governor’s Province there will be a Provincial Legislature, consisting, except in the provinces of j u i-n , of His Majesty, represented by the Governor, and of one Chamber, to be known as the Legislative Assembly. . , ... • . * rr In the Provinces just named the Legislature will consist of His Majesty, represented by the Governor, and of two Chambers, to be known respectively as the Legislative Council and the Legislative Assembly. . But provision will be made enabling the Provincial Legislature at any time not less than ten years after the inauguration of the Constitution— (a) where the Legislature consists of two Chambers to provide by Act, which both Chambers separately have passed, that it shall consist of one Chamber instead of two Chambers; and, (b) where the Legislature consists of one Chamber, to present an Address to His Majesty in Council praying that the Legislature may be reconstituted with two Chambers, and that the composition of, and method of election to, the Upper Chamber may be determined by Order in Council. The Provincial Legislatures will be summoned to meet for the first time on dates to be specified in the Proclamation establishing the Federation. Every Act of a Provincial Legislature will be expressed as having been enacted by the Governor, by and with the consent of the Legislative Assembly, or, where there are two Chambers, of both Chambers of the Legislature. 73. Power to summon and appoint places for the meeting of the Provincial Legislature, to prorogue it, to dissolve it, and to address it will be vested in the Governor at his discretion, subject to the requirement that it shall meet at least once in every year, and that not more than twelve months shall intervene between the end of one session and the commencement of the next. Where the Legislature consists of two Chambers power to dissolve and to address the Chambers will be exercisable in relation to either Chamber separately or to both simultaneously. 74. Subject to dissolution, each Legislative Assembly will continue for five years , and each Legislative Council where so oh a Council exists, for seven years. „ 7 ®- In . of a Province having a Legislative Council a Member of the Council of Ministers will have the right to sneak but not to vote, in the Chamber of which he is not a member/u Proposal#* Tke Composition of the Provincial Legislature. 76. 1 he Legislative Assembly of each Governor’s Province will consist ol the number of members indicated against that Province in . ppendix , who will be elected in the manner indicated in the same Appendix. 11. A member of a Provincial Legislative Assembly shall be at least 25 years of age and a British subject or a subject 'of an Indian State. 78. The Legislative Councils of Governors’ Provinces will consist of the number of members indicated against that Province in Appendix , w T ho will be elected, or nominated by the Governor, as the case may be, in the manner indicated in the same Appendix. 79. A member of a Provincial Legislative Council shall be at least 80 years of age and a British subject or a subject of an Indian State, and shall possess either one of the property qualifications set out in Appendix 80. Appropriate provision will be made for the filling of vacancies in a Provincial Legislature on the lines proposed for tho Federal Legislature (see paragraphs 29 and 82). 8i. Every member of a Provincial Legislature will be required to make and subscribe an oath or affirmation in the following form before taking his seat:— “I, Council A.B., having been elected a member of this nominated ~ r 80 i emn iy 8W ear (or affirm) that I will be faithful Assembly * and bear true allegiance to His Majesty the King Emperor of India His heirs and successors, and that I will faithfully discharge the duty upon which I am about to enter.” 82. Appropriate provision will be made— (а) for the election of a President and Deputy President of the Legislative Council and a Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly, and for the tenure of those offices ; ( б ) for determining the quorum and for the determination of questions by majority vote; (O for prohibiting membership of both Chambers (where two Chambers exist) by the same individual, and for deter mining, in the case of double election, of which Chamber he shall be a member; (d) for the resignation of a seat in either Chamber; and (e) for the vacation of a seat by reason of absence through incapacity or neglect. But the provisions relating to the determination of questions by majority vote will be such as to require that until the Provincial Legislature otherwise determines by a decision in support of which at least three-fourths of the members have voted, no proposal for the reduction in any province (other than a reduction pro-rata with the general educational grant-in-aid) of the grants-in-aid from time to time admissible on account of the education of the Anglo-Indian and domiciled European community will be deemed to have received the consent of the Legislature unless at least three-fourths of the members have voted in favour of the proposal. 83. The following disqualifications will be prescribed for membership of a Provincial Legislature : (a) in the case of elected members, the holding of any office of profit under the Crown other than that of Minister, (b) a declaration of unsoundness of mind by a competent Court, (c) being an undischarged bankrupt; # . . (d) conviction of the offence of corrupt practice or other election offences;16 Proposals. (e) in the ease of a legal practitioner, suspension from practice by order of a competent Court; but provision will be made that this and the last preceding disqualification may be removed by older of the Governor of his discretion; (/) having an interest in any contract with the Provincial Govern ment ; provided that the mere holding of shares in a company will not by iteelf involve this disqualification. 84. A person sitting or voting as a member of the Provincial Legislature, when he is not qualified for, or is disqualified from, membership, will be made liable to a penalty of in respect of each day on which he so sits or votes, to be recovered in the High Court of the Province by suit initiated with the consent of a principal Law Officer of the Provincial Government. 85. Subject to the rules and Standing Orders of the Legislature there will be freedom of speech in the Provincial Legislature. No person will be liable to any proceedings in any Court by reason of his speech or vote, or by reaeon of anything contained in any official Report of the proceedings. 86 . In so far ae provision is not made by the Act itsell for the following matters connected with elections and electoral procedure, they will be prescribed by Order in Council under the Act:— (a) the qualifications of electors; (b) the delimitation of constituencies: (c) the method of election of representatives of communal and other interests; (d) the filling of casual vacancies; and (e) other matters ancillary to the above, with provision that Orders in Council framed for these purposes shall be laid in draft for a stated period before each House of Parliament. For matters connected with the conduct of elections for the provincial legislature other than the above each Provincial Legisla ture will be empowered to make provision by Act. But until the Provincial Legislature otherwise determines, existing laws or rules, including the law or rules providing for the prohibition and punish ment of corrupt practices or election offences and for determining the decision of disputed elections, will remain in force; subject, however, to such modifications or adaptations to be made by Order in Council as may be required in order to adapt their provisions to the require ments of the new Constitution. Legislative Procedure. Noth.— The following paragraphs relating to legislative procedure are, with the exception of paragraph 90, framed, for the sake of brevity, to apply to unicameral Provincial Legislatures. Suitable modification of these provisions, for the purpose of adapting them to Legislatures which are bicameral would, of course, be made. In particular, provision will be made on the lines of paragraph 54 making Joint Sessions of the two Chambers subject, so far as procedure and conduct of business is concerned, to rules framed by the Upper (Chamber for its own procedure; and providing that in a bicameral Legislature Bills (other than Money Bills, which will be initiated in the Legislative Assembly) will be introduced in either Chamber. 87. The Governor will be empowered at his discretion, but subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act and to Instructions given him in that behalf, to assent in His Majesty’s name to a Bill which has been passed by the Provincial Legislature, or to withhold his assent, or to reserve the Bill for the consideration of the Governor-General He will also be empowered, if he thinks fit, before taking any of those courses, to remit a Bill to the Legislature, with a Message requesting its reconsideration in whole or in part, together with such amend 6 ments, if any, as he may recommend.Hihin'illiiliiiril 17 Proposals. No Bill will become law unless it has been passed by the Legisla ture, with or without amendment, and has been assented to by the Governor, or m cases where the Constitution Act so provides, by the Governor-General; m the case of a Bill reserved for the consideration or the Governor-General, the Bill will not become law until the Governor-General (or, if the Governor-General reserves the Bill His Majesty in Council) has signified his assent. 88 . When a Bill is reserved by a Governor for the consideration oi the Governor-General, the Governor-General will be empowered at his discretion, but subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act and to Instructions given him in that behalf, to assent in His Majesty’s name to the Bill, or to withhold his assent, or to reserve the Bill for the signification of the King’s pleasure. He will also be empowered, if he thinks fit, before taking any of these courses, to return the Bill to the Governor with directions that it shall be remitted to the Legislature with a Message to the effect indicated in the preceding paragraph. The Legislature will then reconsider the Bill and if it is again passed with or without amendment it will be presented again to the Governor-General for his consideration. If at the end of six months from the date on which a Bill was presented to the Governor-General, the Governor-General neither assents to it nor reserves it for the signification of the King’s pleasure, nor returns it to the Governor, the Bill will lapse. 89. Any Bill assented to by the Governor or by the Governor- General will within twelve months be Subject to disallowance by the King in Council. 90. In the case of a Province having a Legislative Council, if a Bill, which has been passed by the Legislative Assembly, is rejected by the Legislative Council, or is passed by that Council with amendments to which the Legislative Assembly will not agree, and if the Bill is, after the expiry of two years from the date upon which it was last under consideration by the Legislative Council, re-introduced in the Legislative Assembly, and the Assembly again passes it in that form and the Legislative Council again refuses to pass it, or passes it only with amendments to which the Legislative Assembly will not agree, the Governor will be empowered to summon a Joint Session of both Chambers for the purpose of reaching a decision on the Bill. The members present at a Joint Session will deliberate and vote together upon the Bill in the form in which it finally left the Chamber in which it was introduced and upon amend ments, if any, made therein by one Chamber and not agreed to by the other. Any such amendments which are affirmed by a majority of the total number of the members voting at the Joint Session will be deemed to have been carried, and if the Bill, with the amendments, if any, so carried, is affirmed by a majority of the members voting at the Joint Session, it shall be taken to have been duly passed by both Chambers. In the case of a Money Bill, or in cases where, in the Governor’s opinion, a decision on the Bill cannot, consistently with the fulfilment of any of his “ special responsibilities,” be deferred, the Governor will be empowered at his discretion to summon a Joint Session forthwith. 91. In order to enable the Governor to discharge the ” special responsibilities” imposed upon him, he will be empowered at his discretion— (a) to present, or cause to be presented, a Bill to the Legisla ture, with a Message that it is essential, having regard to any of his “ special responsibilities ” that any Bill so initiated should become law before a date specified in the Message; and (b) to declare by Message in respect of any Bill already introduced in the Legislature that it should, for similar reasons, become law in a form specified in the Message before a stated date. If, before the date specified, a Bill which is the subject of such a Message is not passed, or is not passed in the form specified, as the case may be, the Governor will be empowered at his discretion to [8174—2] FProposals. 18 enact it as a Governor’s Act, either with or without any amendments made by the Chamber, or either of the Chambers, after receipt of his Message. , *A Governor s Act so enacted will have the same force and enec as an Act of the Provincial Legislature and will be subject to the same requirements in respect of the Governor-General s assent and to disallowance in the same manner as an Act of the Provincial Legislature, but the Governor’s competence to legislate under this provision will not extend beyond the competence of the Provincial Legislature as defined by the Constitution. 92. Provision will also be made empowering the Governor, in any case in which he considers that a Bill introduced or proposed for introduction, or any clause thereof, or any amendment to a Bill moved or proposed, would affect the discharge of his special responsibility ” for the prevention of any grave menace to the peace or tranquillity of the Province, to direct that the Bill, clause or amendment shall not be further proceeded with. Procedure with regard to Financial Proposals. 93. A recommendation of the Governor will be required for any proposal in the Provincial Legislature for the imposition of taxation, for the appropriation of public revenues, or any proposal affecting or imposing any charge upon public revenues.! 94-. The Governor will cause a statement of the estimated revenues and expenditure of the Province, together with a statement of proposals for the appropriation of those revenues, to be laid in respect of every financial year before the Provincial Legielature, and, where the Legislature consists of two Chambers, before both Chambers. The statement of proposals for appropriation will be so arranged as— (а) to distinguish between those proposals which will, and those which will not (see paragraph 96), be submitted to the vote of the Legislature; and ( б ) to specify separately those additional proposals (if any), whether under the votable or non-votable Heads, which the Governor regards as necessary for the fulfilment of any of his “ special responsibilities.” 93. The proposals for the appropriation of revenues, other than proposals relating to the Heads of Expenditure enumerated in paragraph 96 and proposals (if any) made by the Governor in discharge of his special responsibilities, will be submitted, in the form of Demands for Grants, to the vote of the Legislative Assembly. The Assembly will be empowered to assent, or refuse assent, to any Demand or to reduce the amount specified therein, whether bv wav of a general reduction of the total amount of the Demand or of the reduction or omission of any specific item or items included in it. , “ 6 * l / h f P^P^sals for appropriation of revenues, if they relate to the Heads of Expenditure enumerated in this paragraph will not be submitted to the vote of the Legislative Assembly, but will be open to discussion m the Assembly. The Heads of Expenditure referred to above are (i) Expenditure debitable to provincial revenues which ia required for the discharge of the duties imposed by the Act on a principal Secretary of State- F ^ (U) ^Act to'The Govmior * nCe8 Payable the (i,i) “ ° f ‘ he G ~ 9 or ( ' V) T Act toKersf 0 ™ 11068 PayaWe UDder the euacting WOTdTTa bet ' ,ee “ tie Aet (see paragraph 69), that Acts of the former • ? rd8 of an ordinary the Governor s own responsibility r descri PGon are enacted on t Compare paragraph 46 and the footnote thereto.Proposals. 19 &lt;V&gt; “S; PayaWe by the PrOTi ““ *&gt; the Federal &lt;V1) tol ” 8 ^ C , hargeS and other expenditure iviii Fxn! the raising and service of loans; ' ‘ to 8 Sfy C the Ut d 0n8ed and a 1Xed by any laW ’ 0r rei 5 uired arbitrator; h d ° r 0rder ° f any Court ' or of &lt;Tl,,) T 0 be to ' ° r to the dependants Judirial r f be - Hlgh CoUrt ’ or of the Chief Gourt or sioners ^“ mi8s ‘ oners or Additional Judicial Commis- oners, and such expenditure as is certified by the rennl^fi f with his Ministers, as being reqmred for the expenses of the High Court, Chief Court Tvf ' 11 ^° m nii 8 Sioner’s Court; 11 T !! 1 ^ 8 and P ension8 Payable to, or to the dependant# (a) persons appointed by or with the approval of His Majesty or by the Secretary of State in Council before the commencement of the Constitution Act or by a Secretary of State thereafter; y (b) persons appointed before the first day of April, 1924, by the Governor-General in Council or by a Local Govern ment to Services and posts classified as superior; (c) holders in a substantive capacity of posts borne on Ine cadre of the Indian Civil Service; i d members of any Public Service Commission. (x) Sums payable to, or to the dependants of, a person who is. or has been, in the service of the Crown in India under any Order made by the Secretary of State in Council, by a Secretary of State, by the Governor-General in Council, by the Governor-General, or by the Governor, upon an appeal preferred to him in pursuance of Rules made under the Constitution Act. * s ^ or . ^ ie P ur P° seB of the proposals in this paragraph the expression salaries and pensions ” includes remuneration, allowances, gratuities, contributions, whether by way of interest or otherwise, out of the revenues of the Province to any Provident Fund or Family Pension Fund, and any other payments or emoluments payable to, or on account of, any person in respect of his office. The Governor will be empowered to decide finally and con clusively for all purposes any question whether a particular item of expenditure does, or does not, fall under any of the Heads of Expenditure referred to in this paragraph. 97. At the conclusion of the budget proceedings the Governor will be required to certify all appropriations of revenue. The total amount so certified will be required to be not in excess of the sums voted by the Legislature, or included in the original proposals for appropriation under the non-voted Heads. But the Governor will nevertheless be empowered in his discretion to include in his certificate any additional amounts which, in his opinion, are required for expenditure essential to the discharge of any of his special responsibilities, provided that the amounts of any such additional sums do not exceed the aggregate of— (а) any sums (if any) originally included in the statement of proposed appropriations in respect of his special responsibilities; and of ( б ) the amounts by which a Demand for a Grant has been reduced by vote of the Legislature. Every certificate so given by the Governor will be laid before the Legislature, but will not be open to discussion and will be for all purposes sufficient authority for the appropriation of the sums m question. L The provisions of paragraphs 94 to 97 inclusive will apply Jposals for the appropriation of revenue to meet expenditure icluded in the Annual Estimates which it may become necessary nr dnriner the course of the financial year.Proposals. *&amp;* Pmexdtsre m the 99. Tl* poster* uxi **dua ol k, 1^1B*U:ot*: wfli i» regaiaMd bj '*» !&lt;&gt; r* r/.wk-, = ab/»s » ^ pfwrfeftOBs cd the CcesSitotk® A--t. by t e ^r»«si 5 *aiiorj with Sc,,™, iriD « bis &lt;b«-refor,, aI t.r c^ ! sm , ».^ w 1 th *t Presdeiii or fspeaker. i» she sat* ni»? I*, t® ma.* njl«s rt/uUtM« Iho pnx^ore the eood «1 of bMm«* ™.Jh® Cbj^SmT in reUskiB 10 dmUcts arising out of or agfcrtmg, aoj ^special r-ws|ior^sl&gt;ijiitT '* with wbkh he is charged by the C^stitetioo Act- , , . Ii, the event of cmsflict be^eec a rule so made by the Governor smd any rale made by a Chamber of the Legislature, the iormt-r win prevail aud the latter will, to the extent of the inconsistency, be Vm6 (n the ease of a Province having a Legislative Council, the pro^isicns of the Constitution Act and of any roles made with respect to the procedure dt.and conduct of business in, the Legislative (.ouncii will apply to Joint Sessions of the two Chamfers as if tie members erf the Legislative Assembly present at those sittings were, for the time being, additional members of the Council of State. Excluded Area*. 100.. His Majesty will be empowered to direct by Order in Council that any area within a Province is to be an Excluded Area *' or a “ Partially Excluded Area,” and by subsequent Orders in Council to revoke or vary any such Order. 101. In respect of Partially Excluded Areas the Governor will be declared to have a special responsibility gee paragraph 68 ). For the purposes of administration, any area in a Province for the time being declared to be an excluded Area will be placed under the direct and exclusive control of the Governor himself. 102. Legislation required, whether for Excluded Areas or Partially Excluded Areas? will be obtained in the following maimer:— No Act of the Federal Legislature or of the Provincial Legisla ture will apply to such an area unless the Governor in his discretion so directs, and in giving such a direction the Governor will be empowered to direct that the Act, in its application to the area, or to any specified part thereof, is to have effect subject to such exceptions or modifications as be thinks fit. The Governor will also be empowered at his discretion to make Regulations for the peace and good government of any area which is for the time being an Excluded Area or a Partially Excluded Area and will be competent by any Regulation so made to repeal or amend any Act of the Federal Legislature or erf the Provincial Legislature which is, for the time being, applicable to the area in question. Regulations made under this provision will be submitted forth with to the Governor-General and will not have effect until he has assented to them; but. when assented to by the Governor-General, will have the same force and effect as an Act of the Legislature made applicable to the area by direction of the Governor, and will be subject to disallowance in the same manner as a Provincial Act. but will not be subject to repeal or amendment bv anv Act of the Provincial or of the Federal Legislature. 103. Rules made by the Governor in connexion with legislative procedure will contain a provision prohibiting the discussion in the Provfficiti Legislature of an * matter arising out of the administration of an Excluded Area, and enabling the Governor, at his discretion to disallow any resolution or question regarding the administration of a Partially Excluded Area. Emergency Powers of the Governor in relation to Legislation 1 M. The Governor will be empowered at his discretion, if at any time he is satisfied that the requirements of anv of the “ Special responsibilities with which he is charged by the’ ConstitutionAetrender it necessary, to make and promulgate such Ordinances as, in hiis opinion, the circumstances of the case require, containing such provisions as it would have been competent, under the provisions of the Constitution Act, for the Provincial Legislature to enact. An Ordinance promulgated under the proposals contained in this paragraph will continue in operation for such period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified therein; the Governor will, however, have the power to renew any Ordinance for a second period not exceeding six months, but in that event it will be laid before both Houses of Parliament. An Ordinance will have the same force and effect, whilst in operation, as an Act of the Provincial Legislature ; but every such Ordinance will be subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act relating to disallowance of Acts and will be subject to withdrawal at any time by the Governor. 103. In addition to the powers to be conferred upon the Governor at his discretion in the preceding paragraph, the Governor will further be empowered, if his Ministers are satisfied, at any time when the Legislature is not in session, that an emergency exists which renders such a course necessary, to make and promulgate any such Ordinances for the good government of the Province or any part thereof as the circumstances of the case require, containing such provisions as, under the Constitution Act, it would have been competent for the Legislature to enact. An Ordinance promulgated under the proposals contained in this paragraph will have, while in operation, the same force and effect as an x\ct of the Provincial Legislature, but every such Ordinance— (a) will be required to be laid before the Provincial Legislature and, unless previously approved by Resolutions of the Legislature, or, as the case may be, of both Chambers thereof, will cease to operate at the expiry of six months from its promulgation, or at the expiry of fourteen days from the re-assembly of the Legislature, whichever date is the earlier; and lb) will be subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act relating to disallowance as if it were an Act of the Provincial Legislature; it will also be subject to with drawal at any time by the Governor. 106. The Governor will be empowered at his discretion, if at any time he is satisfied that a situation has arisen which renders it for the time being impossible for the government of the Province to be carried on in accordance with the other provisions of the Constitution Act, by Proclamation to assume to himself all such powers vested by law in any Provincial authority as appears to him to be necessary for the purpose of securing that the government of the Province shall be carried on effectively. A Proclamation so issued will have the same force and effect as an Act of Parliament; will be communicated forthwith to the Governor-General and to a Secretary of State and laid befoie Parliament; will cease to operate at the expiry of six months um/'ss before the expiry of that period it has been approved by Resolutione of both Houses of Parliament; and may at any time be revoked by Resolutions of both Houses of Parliament. (ii) Chief Commissioners’ Provinces. 107. The Provinces known as British Baluchistan, Delhi, Merwara, Coorg and the Andaman and Nicobar Islands will be administered, subject to the provisions of the Constitution Act, by a Chief Commissioner who will be appointed by the Governor-Genera in his discretion to hold office during his pleasure. The Governor- General will be empowered to grant leave to a Chief Commissioner and to appoint a person to act in his place during his absence. 108. Special provision will be made for British Baluchistan whereby the administration of that Province will be reserved lor [8174—2]Proposals. J 22 W- lA &lt;fe. f |- [Th&gt;ei requires amplification in order to cover the application of the Naval Discipline Act to Naval Forces raised by the Governor-General {cf. s. 66, Govern ment of India Act as amended) ] n Ft I n nd control, for all purposes, of the Governor- through the agency of the Chief C—one, 109. Legislation required for British Baluchistan will be obtained in the following manner No Act of the Federal Legislature will apply to Prov'Me unless the Governor-General in his discretion so to direct that a direction the Governor-General will be en po |U preo f i 8 to the \ct in its application to the Province, or an} part thereol, ^e efot sfbj^to such exceptions or modificat~ he thinks fiL The Governor-General will also be empowered at his discretion to make Regulations for the peace and' good government of British Baluchistan n and will be competent by any Regulations so made to fetal or amend any Act of the Federal Legislature which is for the time being applicable to the Province. Any such Regulation, on promulgation by the Governor-General in the official Gazette wi have the same force and effect in relation to British Baluchistan as an Act of the Federal Legislature, and will, like such Acts, be subject to disallowance by His Majesty m Council. HO. In the Chief Commissioners’ Provinces^-other than British Baluchistan, the Chief Commissioner will have all such executive power and authority as may be necessary for the administration of the Province, and in the exercise of these powers and authority he will 1 be under the superintendence, direction and control of the Federal Government. 111. The composition of the Coorg Legislative Council, as existing immediately before the establishment of the I ederation, will continue unchanged, and special provisions will be made with regard to its legislative powders. Powers of the Federal Legislature and of Provincial Legislatures. 112. It will be outside the competence of the Federal and of the Provincial Legislatures, to make any law affecting the Sovereign or the Royal Family, the sovereignty or dominion of the Crown over any part of British India, the law of British nationality, the Army Act, the Air Force Act and the Naval Discipline Act. 113. The Federal Legislature will have an exclusive power to make laws for the peace and good government of the Federation with respect to the matters set out in Appendix Laws so made will be operative throughout British India, but in the States which have acceded to the Federation, only in so far as the Ruler of the State has by his Instrument of Accession accepted the subject with which the law is concerned as a Federal subject. Federal laws will be applicable to British subjects and servants of the Crown within any part of India and to all Indian subjects of His Majesty outside India. The Federal Legislature will also be empowered to make laws regulating the discipline of His Majesty’s Indian Forces, in so far as they are not subject to the Army Act, the Air Force Act, or the Naval Discipline Act, which will be applicable to those Forces wherever they are serving. 114. A Provincial Legislature will have an exclusive power to make laws for the peace and good government of the Province with respect to the matters set out in Appendix 115. Nothing in paragraph UB or 114 will operate to debar the Federal Legislature, in legislating for an exclusively federal subject, from devolving upon a Provincial Government or upon any officer of that Government, the exercise on behalf of the Federal Government of any functions in relation to that subject.* 'Note.—A ny cost which tails in virtue of this provision on anv Provincial Government, and which that Government would not otherwise have incurred, will be borne by the Federal Government. In the event of disagreement as to the amount or incidence of any charges so involved the question will be reterred for decision (which will be final) of an arbitrator to be appointed by the Chief Justice of the Federal Court r tom ' 28 Proposals. 116 . The Federal Legislature and the Provincial Legislatures Insert else- will have concurrent powers to make laws with respect to the on P the matters set out in Appendix , but laws made by Provincial lines of, but Legislatures under these powers will be confined in their operation to 'V^ er ^ an ' 81 II® the territories of the Province. The intention of providing for this CommomSalth concurrent field is to secure, in respect of the subjects entered in the A &lt;*] Appendix referred to in this paragraph, the greatest measure of uniformity which may be found practicable without at the same time debarring Provincial Legislatures from making variations to meet local conditions. In the event of a conflict between a Federal law and a Provincial law in the concurrent field, the Federal law will prevail, unless the Provincial law was reserved for, and has received, the assent of the Governor-General. The Federal Legislature will have no power to repeal or amend a Provincial law to which the Governor-General has thus assented, save with the prior sanction of the Governor-General. 117. It is intended that the three lists of subjects referred to above shall be as exhaustive as is reasonably possible; but provision will be made enabling either the Federal Legislature or any Pro vincial Legislature to make a law with respect to a residual subject, if any, included in none of the three lists, by means of an Act to the introduction of which the previous sanction of the Governor-General, given at his discretion, has been obtained, and to which (in the case of a Provincial Act) the assent of the Governor-General has been declared. 118. The Federal Legislature will be empowered, at the request of two or more Provinces, to pass a law which will be operative in those Provinces and in any other Province which may subsequently adopt it on a subject which would otherwise fall within the legisla tive competence of a Province only. Such a Federal Act will be subject, as regards any Province to which it applies, to subsequent amendment or repeal by the Legislature of that Province. 119. If any provision of a law of a State is in conflict with an Act of the Federal Legislature regulating any subject which the Ruler of that State has by his Instrument of Accession accepted as a Federal subject, the Act of the Federal Legislature, whether passed before or after the making of the law of the State, will prevail. 120. In order to minimise uncertainty of law and opportunities for litigation as to the validity of Acts, provision will be made limiting to two years the period within which an Act may be called into question on the ground that exclusive powers to pass such legislation were vested in a Legislature in India other than that which enacted it. 121. The consent of the Governor-General, _ given at his discretion, will be required to the introduction in the hedera Legislature of legislation which repeals or amends or is repugnan, to any Act of Parliament extending to British India, or any Governor-General’s or Governor’s Act or Ordinance ^iga Regulation III of 1818, or Madras Regulation II of 1819, or Bomba} Re eolation XXV of 1827;] or which affects any Department reserved for^the control of the Governor-General, or Ae currency of the Federation or the powers and duties of the Federal Reserve Bank in relation to the management of currency or exchange or religion or 'b rites and Jages, or the procedure regulatrng enmrnal proceedings against European British subjects. • An alternative method of dealing with insert a separate provision, to p tinuance 0 f existing laws, to the probably be necessary in relation 1 1 fr 1818 or Madras Regulation II following effect: Bengal J^Mation 1 ^ continue in force unless of 1819, or Bombay Regulation XX Ppriprol Legislature, or, in relation and until repealed or amended by t^ Federal^sla^^^^ ^ ^ to a particular Province, by the l jC fii Legislature will require introduction of a Bill ‘ h J 8 G^rnor-Gcnerai, and a Provincial Bill t° thTpTrpoeewSTe rlrtd g?WvernorW.l'a asaent.24 Proposals* 122. The consent of the Governor-General given m his discretion will be required to the introduction in a Provincial Legidature of legislation on the matters enumerated in the preceding paragrap , with the exception of legislation affecting currency or the Reserve Bank (which will not be within the competence of a Provincial Legislature at all), or which repeals, amends or is repugnant to a Governor’s Act or Ordinance, or which affects religion or religious rites and usages. The introduction in the Provincial Legislature of legislation on these latter subjects will require the consent of the Governor of the Province. 123. The giving of consent by the Governor-General or any Governor to the introduction of a Bill will be without prejudice to his power of withholding his assent to, or of reserving, the Bill when passed; but an Act will not be invalid by reason only that prior consent to its introduction was not given, provided that it was duly assented to either by His Majesty, or by the Governor-General or Governor, as the case may be. 124. The Federal Legislature and the Provincial Legislatures will have no power to make laws subjecting any British subject, or any subject of a State being a member of the Fedeiatiou (including companies, partnerships or associations incorporated by or under any Federal, Provincial or State law), in respect of taxation,^ the holding of property, the carrying on of any profession, trade, business or occupation, or‘the employment of any servants or agents, or in respect of residence or travel within the boundaries of the Federation, to any disability or discrimination based upon his religion, descent, caste, colour or place of birth; but no law will be deemed to be discriminatory for this purpose on the ground only that it prohibits either absolutely or with exceptions the sale or mortgage of agricul tural land in any area to any person not belonging to some class recognised as being a class of persons engaged in, or connected with, agriculture in that area, or which recognises the existence of some right, privilege or disability attaching to the members of a comtounity by virtue of some privilege, law or custom having the force of law'. A Federal or Provincial law', however, which might otherwise be void on the ground of its discriminatory character will be valid if previously certified by the Governor-General or a Governor, as the case may be, at his discretion, to be necessary in the interests of the peace and tranquillity of the Federation or any part thereof or of the Province. 125. The Federal Legislature and the Provincial Legislatures will have no pow T er to make laws subjecting any British subject domiciled in the Fnited Kingdom (including companies and partner ships incorporated or constituted by or under the laws of the United Kingdom) to any disability or discrimination in the exercise of certain specified rights, if an Indian subject of His Majesty, or a company incorporated by or under a Federal, Provincial or State law', as the case may be, would not in the exercise in the United Kingdom of the corresponding right be subject in the United Kingdom to any disability or discrimination of the same or a similar character. The rights in question are the right to enter, travel and reside in any part of British India; to hold property of any kind; to carry on any trade or business in, or with the inhabitants of, British India; and to appoint and employ at discretion agents and servants for any of the above purposes. Provision will be made on the same lines for equal treatment on a reciprocal basis of ships registered respectively in British India and the United Kingdom. 126. An Act of the Federal or of a Provincial Legislature, however, which, with a view to the encouragement of trade or industry, authorises the payment of grants, bounties or subsidies out of public funds to trading companies will not be held to fall within the terms of the two preceding paragraphs by reason only of the fact that it is limited to persons or companies resident or incorporated in India, or that it imposes on companies not trading in India before the passing of the Constitution Act as a condition25 Proposals. of eligibility for any such grant, bounty or subsidy that a Company shall be incorporated by or under the laws of British India or that ho composition of the governing body shall be such or that the company shall give such facilities for training Indian subjects of His Majesty, as .he Governor-General may consider satisfactory. , 127 ; t l ; nle8S a , n agreement for the recognition on a reciprocal basis of Indian medical qualification is for the time being in existence under the Medical Act, 1886, medical practitioners duly qualified in the United Kingdom will be entitled to practise in India without the necessity of obtaining further qualifications. Administrative Relations between the Federal Government and the Units. Relations with the Provinces. 128. It will be the duty of a Provincial Government so to exercise its executive power and authority, in so far as it is necessary and applicable for the purpose, as to secure that due effect is given within the Province to every Act of the Federal Legislature which applies to that Province : and the authority of the Federal Govern ment will extend to the giving of directions to a Provincial Govern ment to that end. The authority of the Federal Government will also extend to the giving of directions to a Provincial Government as to the manner in which the latter’s executive power and authority shall be exercised in relation to any matter which affects the administration of a Federal subject. 129. The Governor-General will be empowered at his discretion to issue instructions to the Governor of any Province as to the manner in which the executive power and authority in that Province is to be exercised for the purpose of preventing any grave menace to the peace and tranquillity of India or any part thereof. Relations with the States-Members of the Federation. 130. It will be the duty of the Ruler of a State to secure that due effect is given within the territory of his State to every Act of the Federal Legislature which applies to that territory. 131. The Governor-General will be empowered and, if the terms of any State’s Instrument of Accession so provides, will be required to make agreements with the Ruler of any State for the carrying out in that State, through the agency of State authorities, of any Federal purpose. But it will be a condition of every such agreement that the Governor-General shall be entitled, by inspection or otherwise, to satisfy himself that an adequate standard of administration is maintained. 132. The Federal Government will be empowered to issue general instructions to the Government of any State-member of the Federation for the purpose of ensuring that the Federal obligations of that State are duly fulfilled. [8174—~2 ] H/ 2-1 i • i V 3/ o‘3i 3 J Cypher te...e[:raz iron Secretary ox State to Soveromert India, foreign £: Pciitical Department, da’ad loth February iSS3 0 IXX 11 . - ortant jjs t OF FOUF PAnTS&lt; (91 groups) 4 IE I have had under consideration question oi providing in net? constitution adequate means cf cont, cl by G-cvernor of l.db*F. Province of matters arising in his Province Ger^rel far tranr-tc rder tracts^ In view or close ^ interrelatiaa of districts a a encies it i: clear that he will in practice hssre to exercise more constant supervision, and very probably contm 1 9 over provincial aixairs than is contearpleted in other provinces© All G-cverncrs will have extensive powers including a special re^onsibility for the prevent!cn of any grave menace to the satety arc. tranqui-lity cf their provinces, and I recognise that f i *.: r nl f public opiniai in N.W.F.Province it is desirable to avoid any unnecessary dl fferentiation© Nevertheless it is obviously desirable to avoid any risk of the constitutional means of control at the disposal of the Gcv ernor of Province falling short of requirements© £na i-Ui. . -a 2o Hepart of Safc-Oominittee of 1st Osau^ry J-Jol reoojamendod much stronger safeguards fer W.V/.i'.ProTlnce tas.-. tkose i&amp;ioli were oonteaplated elsewhere, e. 5 , tna. ^ovs '. a sdould be tiie effective head of the adndnistra^wn and one of his kinisters itlght be noi&gt;-eleotsa. In vi ®' f ' -atet derelopments at Hound Table discussions I camiot regard my such marked differentiation in constitutional structure .fa N.W.P.Prorince as cohered with other Governors* provinces as prae ticaL/practical, politicso On the other hash failure i n some ^ to recognise and due provision for the peculiar conditions of the Frontier is likely to evoke strong opposition in Pari 1 .amento (126 groups) 3rd PABf, 3« I would accordingly propose provision in the Bill and consequently in the White Paper for an additional 'special responsibility” for the Governor of No :i P«Province , i.u respect of any matter affecting his responsibilities as the Governor General for oh o trails-bo ruer areas”® 4® This would be insarted in a sub-clause together with the additional 'special responsibility” which, it is agreed, is to be given to Governor of Sind in regard to Sukkur Barrage* 5* It may also be found possible so to frame provisions relating to Governors* special responsibilities as to make special responsibility for adnlnistrati on of partially excluded areas applicable to certain named provinces only* If so, such provision,, as well as that which is in any ease to be made for Sind^, would remove ground for assertion that it is only in respect of N.VIF* Province that a special responsibility additional to the standard list is being provided* (122 groups) 4th &amp; LAST PAHT, Oe I have consulted Griffith who pointed out the objection from the local point of view to any ostensible differentiation of N.W 9 F. Province® But tins objection is modified by the fact that provision proposed in paragraph 3 above would be accompanied by that to be made for Sind aid would of course be still further met if it is possible to arrange for the provision referred to in paragraph 5 aov * also to appear in the same clause®7 ;) I also propose after consultation with G-riffith to include tn Instru^jeat of Instructione of Sot© r nor p c Proviiie© provisi cns corresponding to those in the present Inst rune it relating to the tribal areas, together with an instruction to the affect that Governor should maice it his endeavour to preside at meetings of his Oounci'l cf ministers as frequently as possible* ( Tke Bill will provide for right of all Governors to preside at their discretion at these meetings) • B« Please telegrip h whether you agreeo</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00015d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/75</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00015d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/75</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 3941/33 'Reforms: position of Aden, British Baluchistan, NWFP [North-West Frontier Province] and Department of External Affairs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-20T08:35:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (30 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description (used for referencing) commences at f 5, and terminates at f 35, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers regarding proposed reforms to the administration of India, particularly in relation to Aden, British Baluchistan, the North-West Frontier Province and the Department of External Affairs. The file includes a draft of a White Paper detailing the proposed reforms (ff 12-32), which would become the basis for the Government of India Act, 1935. The primary correspondent is the India Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Aden</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Government of India Act (1935)</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>North-West Frontier Province</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Administrative reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00015d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>