<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T09:02:39.742Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IOR NEC -61/26. i Telegram From To Hepeated R. Political Resident, at Shiraz. Government of Inaia, Simla. Secy, of State for Inaia, Lonaon. R.M's. Minister, Jeddah. No. T-96. Dated 25th July 1930. Jeaaah telegram to Foreign Office No. 108 of loth July. Bahrain Government will permit use of 140 pound bags but regrets inability to remit transit dues. EESIpEM 1 . Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, By orcer, for Secretary to the Political Eesioent in the Persian Gulf. Camp, Shiraz, 25th July 1930. WW •PI6 61/26. Telegram P. -' rorn Political Resident, at Shlraz. To Political Agent, Bahrain. JMo. t -94. Dated 22nd. July 1930. Correct proceaure would seem to be that v/hich would be follo?;ed In case of Indian State, where Political Agent would address Durbar, who woula send official reply. It is primarily for Auviser to cons-w -suit Shaikh though there is, of course, no objection to your supporting him if necessary should Shaikh not follow his advice. In matter involving relations v/ith fellow ruler Shaikh cannot be entirely ignored. The foregoing refers to yorir telegram Please address reply to Shiraz. prrc Telegram P. - I cm Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, at Shiraz. No. 154. Dated 24th received 25th July 1950. y^A v / Your telegram No. T-94. Bahrain Government will allow consign- -ment of 140 pound bags but regret inability to remit transit dues. POL IT ICAL.61/- Telegrani y lt rrorr Political Rgent. Bahrein. r ^ 0 Political Pes i dent, Bus hire. No. 147. Dated and reed ISth July 1930. Request for permission to import short weight bags ( ? offlission 'tnrough'; Ousaibi, out no exemption from transit ouee, was received in 1926 and 1929. Peraiission grantee in each case though practice unpopular with local merchants. Feal obe.iect is to give short weignt bags to Hasa tribesiren who apparently oo not ( ? omission 'not ice' J decept ion. I would deprecate suggestion of direct tranship -merit on sea, as Bahrein Government ao not desire/to encourage this, and Ion Saud might bring pressure on B. i. to make habit of it. Latter dislike it owing to difficulties to check and delay of steamers and it has hitherto only been allowed in cases of arms etc I suggest that reply be given taat Bahrein Government will allow imports of one hunarea snd forty pounas bags, 'but cannot waive transit dues whicn iia^ve already oeen reduced. It is always open to them to feed army via Hedjaz ports. Pol it ical.1 61/. Telegram P. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrein. No. 704. Dated I6tli July 1930. Hed.jaz Government wish to import 32,000 sacks of rice from Karachi via Bahrein for army and government xrzic ± kkxxkx use employing services of Qusaibi and beginning in September. They ask for (a) exemption from transit auty at Bahrein (b) permission to use sacks of 140 lbs. as opposed to regulation weight oi IbO lbs. I propose replying that while Hed.jaz Government are st liberty to arrange direct transhipment at sea as has sometimes been done in past if they wish to avail themselves of facilities for storage etc at Bahrein they should pay transit dues. Is tnere any precedent for request. Please wire your comments. Fesident.J 61/- 61/18. Telegram P- From H. M 1 s. Minister, Jeddah. •po Secretary of State for Foreign Afiairs, London. Uo. 109. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, Simla. Dated 15th reed 16th July 1920. Uo. 157. \ I find no precedent here. I understand that similar transactions nave taken place previously but been arranged locally on Persian Gulf side. Request at (2) may be new. I took opportunity of re/ninaing Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs privately that proposal for general discussion of Persian Gulf questions, including customs relations with Bahrain and Kuwait, was in abeyance I gatnerea tnat hejaz Government would still welcome general settlement but would prefer ordinary diplomatic channels. The foregoing refers to my immediately preceding telegram. Ryan. Post copy forwaoded to the Political Agent, Bahrein. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire 16th July 1930. ■ lJ 61/ 61/18. Telegram R. 'From To H. M's. Minister, Jeddah. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. No.108. Repeated Political Resident, Buslaire. ) Government of India, Simla. i No. 156. Dated 15th reed 16th July 1930. Hedjaz Government wish to import 32,000 sacks of rice from Karachi via Banrein for army and government use, employing services of Qusaioi^and beginning in September. They ask officially for following facilitie.s (l) permission to export from India. (2) exemption from transit duty at Bahrein. (3] permission to use sacks of 140 lbs. as opposed to regulation weight of 180 lbs. I should be grateful/ lor an early reply Post copy forwarded to tae Political Agent, Banrein. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire 16th July 1930.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/601</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/601</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 61/26 I (D 84) Exemption from transit duty at Bahrain on foodstuffs, etc., imported by the Hejaz government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-02T11:55:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (14 folios)</extent><extent>Correspondence in the volume is arranged in chronological order, from the earliest piece at the front of the volume, to the latest at the end. There is a page of office notes after the correspondence (verso of folio 7), which mirrors the volume's chronological arrangement. Because the items in the volume have been bound upside down, the correspondence runs in reverse chronological order if moving through the volume from the front cover to back cover.</extent><extent>Orientation: The items in the volume have been bound upside down in relation to the file cover and title page.Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using circled numbers in the top-right corner of each recto . There is an earlier foliation system which uses uncircled numbers. Because of the manner in which the volume has been bound, the earlier foliation system appears upside down, in the bottom-left corner of verso pages.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The correspondence in the volume relates to a request by the Hejaz Government to import 32,000 sacks of rice from Karachi via Bahrain, for use by the Hejaz army and government. Most of the items in the volume are telegrams sent between the British minister in Jeddah, the Political Agent in Bahrain, and the Political Resident in Bushire. Permission is granted to allow the import of rice from Karachi to the Hejaz via Bahrain, but it is stipulated by the Bahrain Political Agent (after consultation with the Advisor to Government) that transit dues on the rice will have to be paid.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>