<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000140_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T03:35:52.278Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">From To No. 287 Dated Telegram En Clair Political Agent, Bahraini Archbishop of Delhi and Simla, New Delhi 27th June 194-7 (Reply paid 20 words) Immediat e Deeply regret Father Gabriel Fleming killed in motor car accident this morning. Please telegraph confirmation that you have informed his next of kin whose address is unknown here. = Pelly Political Agent =Telegraa- proa- To- Dated- iimclair. Political Agency, Bahrain. Catherine Fleiaing, 14 , Hollln Park, Mount, LeedsS. 27th June, 1947. Deeply regret infora you death of Father Gabriel Fleming in motor car accident this morning. KW - Political Agent--(Not to tie tolearraphod) P. T. O. TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING- in Kurnchi Foh. i!M? CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (Incorporated in England.) Charge OFFICE STAMP AND DATE Clerk’s Name. No. and Circuit and Time forwarded.. 3017 O VD C\J 27 / 6 /A 1 VSN92 Official Instructions “(Via tSmpe’lial” Nm. Words. ^ ■] Time 1800 I nstructions Signalled. B Q S Jp Name BISHOP OF ADEN A ddress ADEN 3 * DEEPLY REGRET INFORM YOU DEATH OF FATHER GABRIEL FLEMING IN MOTOR CAR ACCIDENT THIS MORN I IMG POLITICAL AGENT * COPY I request that the at Hive Telegram may be forwarded subject to the •oaditirma printed on back of this form by which I agree to be bound. Signature of Sender '... Telephone No. Address '1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary coarse of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose; but in such case the amount paid for transmission'will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration*, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic 'service Ik; forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the Inter national Telegraph Ilcgulaii mis and the provisions of such Regulat ions shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The a*bove mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE. — Code words used in the iert of telegram* „uisl not contain more than 5 letters The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By Interna tional Regulations, the sender of a telegram is ontiged to produce the rode from which the test or port of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, on used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging must not exceed one ha{f of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegram* may be obtained from any of the Company's Branches.Telegram- Enclair. From- Political, Bahrain. To- Bishop Tirinnanzi, Aden. No. 293. Dated- 29th June, 194-7. r m Your telegram 2&amp;th June. No objection landing Father Anselm Bahrain. I can probably accommodate him for a few days. KW. POLITICAL—0 0 Telegram- Enclair* From- Fleming, 13 Gartongrove, Leeds9# To- Political Agent, Bahrain* Dated 28th and received 29thJune, 1947e Cable received. Please telegraph fuller details at once. I.R. No. 210 FLEMING 13 GARTONGROVE LEEDS9\ (!) /*- Telegram From To Enclatr. Political Agent, Bahrain. Fleming, 13 Gartongrove, Leeds9. No.292. Dated the 29th of June, 1947. Your cable 28th June, understand Father Gabriel with seven others six of whom were also killed travelling between Dhahran and Has Tanura, Saudi Arabia, in station wagon when it was hit by 10-ton truck and that his death was instantaneous. Remains were brought here in coffin afternoon 27th June and he was buried from his own church in Bahrain cemetery at 10 O’ clock June 28th funeral being attended by his own congregation and a number of British and American community. Priest unfortunately not available, but I read Prayers for the Dead. Suggest you communicate with Mac'pherson, ARAMCO, Bahrain for further details. -POLITICAL- NS. \Telegram- Encleir. , From- Political, Bahrain. To Bishop Tirinnanzi, Aden. No. 296. Dated the 30th June, 1947. • Ml# t \i m \ All arrangements had been made including publication of BANNS in London, New York and Bahrain for marriage here by late Father Gabriel on 12th July of CHARLES p LATT, American and AGNES STRICKLAND, BRITISH. As they are most anxious to carry out original arrangement grateful if you would telegraph me when Father A nselm V— expects to arrive here ?&gt;nd whether he will marry them. KW. —POLITICAL—30.6. »47. Dear Miss Strickland, I enclose herewith the Baptismal Certificates of yourself and your fiance in the envelopes in which they were found and with the connected correspondence. They were recovered after some difficulty as Father Gab riel’s papers were in considerable disorder. I think it would be better if you keep them. 3. I have telegraphed today to the Bishop of Aden asking when Father- Anselm is expected to arrive here, and whether he will be able to marry you. I have mentioned that all the formali ties, including Banns, had already been complied with. I shall let you know as soon as I get a reply. yours sincerely C ']&lt;L (C.J. FELLY) Miss A.M.A. Strickland C/o Bapco, Awali.30.6. »47 Dear I!adara, I enclose a copy of my cable •To.292 dated the 29th of June in reply to yours of the 28th June asking for fuller details regarding Father Gabriel's death. I write now to say what a very great shock it was to us all here, of all communities and creeds to hear of his death. He was universally respected, and I can safely say that there are none who knew him who did not regard his unremitting devotion to his priestly duties, often in very difficult con ditions, as a great and exemplary triumph of the spirit. I myself, as a Catholic and a parishioner of Father Gabriel's, off and on for a matter of six years, feel his loss most keenly. I have no doubt, however, that he has gone to his eternal reward. Yours sincerely, Miss Flerniiig, 13, Gartongrove Leeds9.■HMMrtMWi' No. \A&gt; POLIT CaL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 3r “ July , 1947 . The Political Agent ? Bahrain prese’ ts hir compliments to: Miss Strickland c/o Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Await) Bahrain, her in original and has the honour to send of the undermentioned document. V. V previous cc.respondence: Description o5» end sure. Name &amp; date ^ Subject Telegram from Father John f| Stack, New Yor.c, to Father Gabrl«L, Bahrain^ 5 5 0 5 1 TP ;Enclair* Telegram- From- To- Political, Bahrain. Bishop of Aden, Aden. No. £6 146-16/74. Dated the 9th July, 1947* Please cable faculties for Father Canberry, R.A.F. chaplain, c/o Political, Bahrain, to reach here by J^ly 12 th. —POLITICAL/I A 0 Telegram - From - To - Enclair. Archbishop Mulligan, Simla, Pelly, Political Agent, Bushire, &amp;***£ Dated the 27th June and received here from Bushire on the 10th July, 194?&lt;» Received cable. Next of kin informed. Regret exceedingly. I.R. 229© ARCHBISHOP MULLIGANr &gt; Encl^ir. Damian, Aden. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated the 11th July, 194-7. V * - '* Telegram - From - To - 2 . Bishop. Y our 146. Perform ceremony informing =DAMIAN= KW. £ish American mission joahrain, Persian uulf July 17, 1947 13 . 1 understand from father oarbury that you and ne nave been closing the personal affairs of the late rather Gabriel rleming. Would you be kind enough to send to me the proper names and addresses of rather Gabriel's sisters in rngland? Several people, both here and in uhahran, want to write to them. rather Carbury also mentioned that a replacement for rather Gabriel’s post is now en route to nahrain. iie didn't know whether this ne ,,T man would be stationed here permanently or temnorarily. i wonder if you would be kind enough to notify me of the arrival of the new father so that i aay greet him nersonally and possibly help him make arrangements for regular trims to i&gt; ha hr an and kss Tenure. we would like to have a corny of the wurial certificate of rather Gabriel for our ceme'tery records, rlease send us a signed copy of the certificate. to complete your records, let me note that Jfether Gabriel was buried in i-Tot No. Y-f -7. Thank you for your assistance in these inatters. Sincerely yours, jsdwin m. nuidensMM 9 Telegram - Enclair. From - Esther Anselm, Karachi. To - Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated the 4th and received the pth August,1947. Arriving Thursday morning by FATHER ANSELM plane. KVV. IR .269</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000140_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1585</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000140</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1585</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File No. 16/74 Death of Father Gabriel Fleming in Motor Accident’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-15T22:10:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (28 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 26-29) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 30; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-20; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Telegraphic correspondence, letters and other papers relating to the death in a road accident in Bahrain, of the Catholic Priest Father Gabriel Fleming, in June 1947. The correspondence covers: the reporting of the death to Fleming’s sister in England; expressions of condolences; burial arrangements and registration; arrangements for the carrying out of religious ceremonies in Bahrain (including a marriage); and Father Anselm’s arrival in Bahrain to take over the late Father Fleming’s duties.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Gabriel Fleming</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sacred Heart Catholic Church</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Burials</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious ceremonies</topic></subject><subject><topic>Death</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000140#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>