<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000297_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-14T09:59:26.691Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">DRAFT. G.C. Daubeny, Esq., Solway Close, Claremont Gardens Marlow, Bucks. * 4 JI|N 1M? D e ar Sir, I write in reply to your letter of the 1st June to Mr. Gibson, which he has passed on to me,'to say that the only news v/e have of your son, Mr. R.G. Daubeny, is a reference in papers recently received to his arrival at Kabul Legation on the 27th February to take over the duties of Second Secretary. but we have no reason to believe that he is other than safe and well. If, however, you s-houla wioti to cable hi it*-at—any time on urgent ^imL4e-rs we v/onld have no nh jpr t i nrv t.r&gt; a—enh-le~~nTi .^'uai 1 Imhol^' irf you would be prepared to refund the cost. Yours truly. (Sgd.) R.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000297_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/718</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000297</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/718</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 2934/42 'Whereabouts of Mr R G Daubeny'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-10-31T09:28:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a letter sent by C C Daubeny asking about her son, R G Daubeny, and the response from the Government of India, External Department, informing her of his arrival at the Kabul Legation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Communication personnel</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000297#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>