<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:04:34.840Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">jy Officer and Establishment* Appointment, transfer etc. of the P.W.D- Supervisor attached to the Political Agency, Bahrain.TUe following transfers are orOMed among the Suliordiiiaiies in the interest of t&amp;e puTsiio service:• Mr. i*.Mul wahabf supervisor, on the expiry or his 4 months leave on average pay to report his arrival at Bahrain and relilre Mr. Mohd. Ishaa# SupervisoTf Bahrain. 2} Mr, Mohd ishaat Supervisor, on ^eing relieved of his duties l)y Mr. JkMul Waha'b f Bupervisor, should proceed to awsaur am take up the work of 'Constructing New Political Bungalow at Grwadur*. As the exigencies of pu*blic service requires it, the subordinates should avail of the minimam Joining time. Assistant jg^gineert Independent ^Persian aulf Sul)-Division. Busnire, Da tea the 17th December 1936. Mo. 3cj S85 Oopy r or warded for information to:- !• The Secretary to the Hon*Dle the Political Kesident in the Persian Guift Bushire. 2* K^The Political ^gent, Bahrain. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat. Mr. Mohd ishaq., Supervisor, Bahrain. Mr. A'bdul ^ahaD, p^r.B. Supervisor, (on leave; Bajaghiri Post, Tanjore District. 'h VA 2_ 1/ \ jo^. No.l of 1936. Bahrain datedt he 20 th January 1936 To The Assistant Engineer, Bafehate. Sir 9 Subject Arrival Report. In complienoe w ith your Office Order Ko.44 dated the 17th December 1935» I beg to report I r ached Bahrain on 18th instant at 8 P.l£,and have taken over the charge from Mr. Mohammed IshaqtSupervinor»this morning. I beg to remaint Sir, Your most obedient servant, Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Supervi 3or.* 2. A . ' No. 102 of 1936. Bahrain dated the 1st.June 1936. To The Political Agent, Sahrain. Sir, Subj ect Casual leave. I beg to request that casual leave for 8 days with permission to leave the station may kindly be granted to V %j/ me with effect from 15th rnjfeyai 1936. I understant that Mr.Fatah Ali Shailc,Assistant Engineer, Bushire has gone on leave,hence I apply to you for leave. I have no work in hand for the time being or atleast till your departure on recess. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant, jl' \(Q Supervisor. k) (? £r$i&gt; ^ 9 4// The Supervisor wants to go to Bushire o ^ ^Bahrain, Dated, the 3rd March 1937. ^3 To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Most Respected Sir Through The Political Agent, Bahrain. Most respectfully and humbly 1 beg to state that I have sent in my application on the 3rd December 1936, through the Assistant Engineer, Bushire, for consideration of my prom&amp;Jion as Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire, when Persian Gulf was good enough to recommend my name - in 1934 to the Government of India for an acting post, when Mr. Fat eh Ali Shaikh wanted to go on leave. The * copies of office orders are herewith submitted for your kind perusal. 3. As I am familiar with all the works and prevailing conditions of the Gulf, I assure you that I will spare no pains in carrying out my duties to the entire satisfaction of my superiors. I feel certain that I will receive the symathetic consideration of the Honourable the Political Resident under whom I served at Muscat, and I feel certain. Sir, that he ha_s always had good reports from my superior officers about me. Mr. Fateh Ali Shaikh retires, So far I have not had any reply. 2. The Honourable the Political Resident in the I beg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant (Lk* r Supervisor, P.W # D. BahrainTo The Honot?rable the Political Resident In the Per•ian O^fo through The Pol i t ical Agen1 9 Bahra in. Respected Sir, I most repmectfully 'beg to draw yonr honours kind attention towards my a'o-nlicatitan and remind that in the last Uovemher yonr honour directed me in the presence of Colonel Loci C#I.E,to submit my application through my immediate sur»erior wh&amp;ch was duly ccm^Hed with in December last.In my application I stated briefly all my circumstances and services during the great war «nd afterwardstand enclosed therewith all my testimoni als of appreciation,in originaliand with confidence in the historical sence of the English justice.I expected that my claim for promotion will receive the just and ilue consideration.Ey confidence was,wholly based on my belief that my techinical merits,and abilities and long experience of the Gulf will not fail to impress my right upon your honour. led to think that my application has failed to produce the expected re^s'Tt,my past experience have been overlooked and application along with the original certificates have been filed in the Residency. incompetent non technical points of views might be in the way of a due and favourable consideration of my request and herooe earnestly hope that a chance may very kihdly be granted to me to clear my position and establish my right to the promotion prayed for. With a deep sorrow and profound disappointment I am nov I fear that some kind of misrepresentation and Por this act of kindness I shall ever remain grateful. Dated the 10th April 37 Bahra in • I beg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant,&lt; No. 836~ 1/37 • The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN', Persian Gdlf. Dated...1937 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Application dated the 10th April 1937 from Mr. Abdul Wahab, bupervisor, Public Works Department, Bahrain. Subject. Appointment of Assistan Engineer, Bushire. i Xl'-IT, GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DBPARTMaNT, EXPRESS LETTER [N, B, — This is an ORIGINAL M ESS AG F, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wire#, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched^ Fsom Brit consul, Bushire T© Political, Bahrain. DaUi May, mi I'lease hand the attached charge sheet to Mr. Ahdul Wahab and let me laiov? v^ien you have done so. His reply should be forwarded through you. - msimwr ~ The issue of the above has been authorla-ed. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. j* c ? ' kr I . X' ^ gy S. 6. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000 hhTelegram G.T.C, Prom Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. Uo.200. Dated 25th May 1937. ■ ^ Jf Your Express Letter Fo. 946 21st fey. 2. Charge sheet handed to Abdul Wahab on the 24th May and receipt acknowledged. He has applied for copy of section 3 of the Civil Service Rules quoted in paragraph 2 of the Charge Sheet. As rules available here have no appendices kindly send copy urgently. Political.*0- 9^/53/21. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 'be Political Agent, brain• ^and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents/. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 2^ Dated...r:. JIay + ..19.S7.. Reference to previous correspondence our telegraFj &gt;T o, 200 of the 25tb l f ay, 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Extract from ApT)enciix T of tbe Civil Services ^ Appeal) P^les, '^irst V A and publisheo by 'RaiSab ^ c. ;ion X (Page 98) of the Oomp Classification, Control an&lt;3 ition (September 1954), compiled ib ^ara Oband, 'P.A,\ 0 Extract from Ap-nendix TX (Page 98) of the Compilation of the OiviT Services (Classification, Control and Anpeal) 'Rules, v irst Edition fSepteml&gt;er 1934), compiled and polished iDy 'Rai BahiD ''ara ^band, B.A. X X X X X X X X X X Discipline . 3. he following penalties may, for pood and suffi cient reason and as hereinafter provided, he imnosed upon members of Subordinate Services, namely:- (i) Censure. (ii Withholding of increments or promotion, inclu- r s ^ 0 PP a ^e st an efficiency 'bar. •. ii i)7leducti on to a lower post or time-scale, or to a lower stage in a time-scale, fivjRecovery from pay of the whole or part of any pecuniary loss caused to Government hy negli gence or breach of orders, fv) Suspension, (vi) 'Removal from the civil service of the Crown, which does not disqualify from future employment. (viijlHsnissal from the civil service of the Crown which ordinarily disqualifies from future employment. Explanation ;- 'he discharge - (a) of a person appointed on probation, during the period of probation, (b) of a person appointed, otherwise than under con tract to hold a temporary appointment, on the expiration of the period of the apnoint- ment, fc) of a person engaged under contract, in accor dance with the terms of his contract, does not amount to removal or dismissal within the meaning of this rule 1 *. X X X X X XG0VER3MENT OF INDIA, EXTERNAL AyjfAIRS D EPAEPMENT* EXPRESS LETTER [N, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGJH, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue me of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had heen telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had hem so despatched,] F rom •To Political Agent5 Bahrain# Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire N®* 1320-1/37 • Dated 6th June /&amp;} 7 ( Heferene4 the enclosure to your nrlnted letter \ No# 998/63/21 dated the 28th May 1937• 2 * It is observed that the extract from Appendix IX of the Compilation of the Civil Services (Glassificatlon, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1st Edition, is from a book compiled and published by Rai Sahib Tara Chand, B«A* Would you please inform me whether this publication is definitely recognised as official in the preferment of charges against the Subordinate Services, who, of course, cannot be charged under the Civil Services (Classifica ion Control and Appeal) Rules (as printed in the first few pages of Volume I of the Fundamental and Supplementary Rules second Edition (Revised) which merely lays down the procedure for the Superior Services. The foregoing is brought to your notice in order to s. 6. obviate MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000*.2 obviate the possibility of any error in procedure with regard to the charge (vide paragra-nh 3 of the Charge Sheet forwarded with your Express Ietter Ho.946 dated the 31st May 1937) or in the case of any appeal being lodged. 4» In the case of this publication being officially recognised, I will obtain one for this Agency immediately* for Political -gent, Bahrain*\ to Bahi'aln, \ b The Sth June 1937. ' The Honourable tlie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre * Tlirough The Political Agent, Bahrain. Heapected SIT, ^ Wit reference to the Cliarge Sheet of the 21st May 193? in connection with ray placing a woodon joist below the fireplace (about 4 inches) which is considered to be the cuase ot fire on the early morning of ?few Year I re pectfully beg to state that as the vooden joist was placed by rae in accor dance with the Sc*ncticned estimate given to me by my Superior, I do not think that the charge of gross negligence of duty against me is justfiable, as the construction of work v /aa to be carried out a&amp; per sancti ned estiriate, binding rae to discharge ray duties within the limits of the specifications given to me, I am inclined to defend my action as bein^ quite out of the area of gross negligence of duty. 2. As specifications laid ddr^f in the esti ;nate were defective 1 should not roa onsbly be held re.&gt; &gt;onaible for discharging uiy duties in accordance v^ith Die sanctioned estinate^ In this connection 1 beg to submit herewith an extract frora standard books, shoeing how estiiaatefi and specifications for flr*eplace are prepared. This may kindly be coopared with the sanctioned estimate. 3. In spite of defectiveness of specifications and sanctioned estimate, I have taken all the rains anr cares tliat a careful sub rdina te could possibly take to see the joist uninfIf nable } as far as human intellig cc and experience could guide em* In fact the joist was about four inches belov* the fire lace and not directly under it.!%• Klapm of 23 rumtha without mxy fiign of the joist bfting effected proves the feet that all nece s&amp;ry care and precaution were taken by me* 4* In conclusion i beg to point out that on He* Year's Hight due to long and overheating probably a crack occurred due to the difference of coeficcient of ©xpenaicn of glared tiles and ceiiaent mortar (the latter should be fire clay) or a sleepy servant carelessly in the late hours threw aoae heavy piece of firewood end by impact a crack had occurred and tlirough the crock heated ^ir was getting in and ignited shavings first and then the Joist* There is a limit for each aud everythirv; an excess of anything is ad. If the fire l*ad t- ken the very day on which the fireplace was heated there is a re son to believe that it was ^oss negligence of duty as th^ fire took place on the ew Year's norning by verheatin or some other fe* cause, after being used for t&amp;o se^aons I beg to defend myself th&amp;t I have not neglected my duty anc it can be proved fron r iy r?revloim r, Htement how carefully X Iiave taken pains to make the Joist mdlnflasaable• T e description of the construe lion from ay nemcry even after two full yearn is a ccnclusive nroof t^aat I have really teken all the uecovisary precautions and nevei m /jlected my duties. 5* Tlae fact that despite iny utter helples mess d e to defective estiiaate, want of proper specifications, written or verbal f and the lack of accurate drawings I have taken great pains conscientiously to discharge my duties to the best of my ability will not fail to obtain appeal to the eyea of justice. I beg to remain. Sir. Vo r most obedient servant, ae ^-^2* r specifications. Extract from Audela Carpenterg anu FMllder a Guide.T-*,-e 729. Build two chimneys as shown f same size and ebape For all exposed arts of outside chimney and tipping otet use Saye and riahers No# 47 faced gray pressed brick* Fireplaces in parlo ir dining and bed rooms to be faced with some brick t smooth inside of fireplace revesling Q' on aid and 34 &lt;t at top* Colour joints, straight arches on strong angle irons unexposed* Fire bricks backs* Spring triirier arche for hearths to be laid with same selected bricks* All flues to have tile lining proper chimney pots and clean outs, including two po a in bed roctiU 2* Extract from Bannister Fletcher ~ Quantities Pages 312,314 t 315* Flooring hearth and Fireplace* 24* best yellow deal floor in 4 inch widths with splayed heading joints* W x u** Deduct Chimney breast 5*3' x 1*2** n Hearth 4•3 ,l x 1*6^* K*0* floor for mitred mai^ln wide round heart}^. Fir fremes in joists 3* x 2* x H* 12 Mos* ♦ Add Trimming joists 8^ &amp; 3 rt x 11 f 2 Nos* Add trissaer 8 H x 3' x 7* 1 Ho* Deduct fir frames in joist hearth* 8' x 2' x 2*B** 4 Nos* 2* x 2' herring b ne strutting to 8** joist 16 f ♦ 2 n tooles yark back hearth and ditto 2*3* k l*2 n * ♦ Centring left to hearth and 4 n P*C concrete to ditto in small quantities and 3/4' P *C* scred for tiles 6*6' x 28'. Deduct all 1*6' x 1*2' 2 Kos* ♦ Deduct l^B (fireplace opening) and deduct F*R*3* and twice washable distemper 2*3 x 3 t *0'*2m |v) E*Om cm stoc f brickwork to 9'* rcaxgh relieving arch 4^ sofit to 2•3 ,l opening 1 Ko« Opening 2»3 (Saber bearing ^'x 9^ 2 Nos. Torn up and down 2 H x 4 n 2 Kcs# 3*6% ♦ 2* x cambered chlsmey bar split turned m and do^n 2 n at each end* ♦ Render beck of I'ire place in mor+ar 1* rarge and Core flue 1* Edwardian chimaey pot 2»6 ,f high including setting and flataKShing in cement 1 Ho. T^rovlde P%C* eun of £ 15* for a 'well 51 fireplace* Bowes patent and add for profit* ♦ Allow for saaterials and labour for setting came* Provide a F*G* sun of £ 10 for uarble curb and allow for profit* ♦ Allow for all labour and materials for setting same* Provide &amp; P*C* sum of £ 6-6-0 for hearth as selected an allow ^or r'ofit and layi { nnmr concrete bed end cenient screeding measured separately)* Provide P*C« sum of £*26 for oak chicmey piece and allovjf profit and fi&gt;;ing same* ♦ hc^t - ho viiy 1 j -i:.- ' 1.-txkatf:*— ■No 1364-1/37. The Political -Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—. The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gdlf. Dated.... .1%%.. . Jufle . 1937... Reference to previous correspondence : A la Bushire Express Letter No. 946 dated 21st May 1937• Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated 8th June 1937 from Mr# Abdul Wahab, Supervisor, Bahrain# Reply to Charge Sheet# T ft/iGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. D zpaetment, EXPRESS LETTER [N.B ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] f^vg ALA Feom Britccms'ol, Busbire. 8 15jun.ij3/ j 61- To Political, Bahrain. 'I No. loqS /5 ^ • T&gt;1 h^/W^ June, \v / Thank you for your Express letter No, 1320-1/37, dated Dated / 2 \ the 5th June, 1937. 2. The compilation of Civil Services (classification, control and Axmeal) Bules hy B.S, Tara Ohand is a non-offi cial publication which we use a lot for ready reference. The compilation was quoted in this Besidency Printed letter TTo. 998/53/21, dated the 2^th May, 1937, for ease of reference on ly. 3. The mention, however, of Appendix IX, it) paragraph 2 of the charge sheet is not correct. The relevant rules are contained in the Fome department Notifications Nos. P.9-19/30, dated the 27th February, 1932 and P.9/18/32, dated the 18th August, 1932 fcopies of which were sent to you under this s. 6. mit—1616 s&amp;p—(m-2089)—2-4-35—200,000. Besid ency /A v /V v. r a A ' 2 ' 'ResideDcy eTidorsemeDts Fos# 1?60, a&amp;ted tine 6th July, 1932, ar^d 3000, dated the 8th October, 1932, respectively) 4« A fresh charge sheet is, therefore, enclosed _ . which may please he handed over to Kr. Ahdul Wahah and jl ri ^ el ^ ^ the previous charge sheet taken hack from him and des troyed . - besidbnt The issue of the ahove has heen authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Crulf.Bahrain, The 26th June 1937. To the Hcnourable the Political Resident in the Persian Giilf| Bushire* Through The Political Accentj Bahrain Respected Sir, With reference to the Charge Sheet dated the 12th June 1937 I withdraw my previous statement of the 8th June 1S37, in accordance with the fresh Charge Sheet# below the fireplace (abcut 4 inches) which is considered to be the cause of the fire on the early norniix; of Hew Year i respectfully beg to state that as the wooden joist was placed by me in accor ance with the sanctioned estimate given to xe by my Superior, I do not think that the charge of gross negligence of duty against me seems to me reasonably fair, as the construction of work was to be carried out as er sanctioned estimate, bindin: me to discharge my duties within the limits of the specifications given to me I may be permitted to defend my action as being w quite out of the area of gross negligence of duty. 3* As specifications laid down in the estimate were defective I should not reasonably be held responsible for discharging my duties in accordance with the sanctioned estimate. In this connection I beg to submit herewith an extract from standard books showing how estimates and specifications for fireplaces are prepared. This may kindly be compared with the sanctioned estimate. 4. in spite of the defectiveness of s- ecifications and sanctioned estimate, I have taken all the pains tod cares that a careful subordinate could possibly take to see the joist uninflamable as far as human intelligence and experience could guide me* In fact the joist was about four inches below the fireplace and not directly under 2 In connection wit my placing a wooden joist it/I ^ it» Elapse of S3 months without any sign of the joist he being affected proves the fact that all necessary care and precaution were t^ken by me# In conclusion I beg to point out that on Hew Year* s night due to long and overheating probably a crack occurred due to the difference of coeficcient of expansion of glazed t iles and cement mortar (the latter should be fire clay) or a sleepy servant carelessly in the late hours threw some heavy piece of firewood and by impact a crack had occurred and through the cr?&gt;r&gt;k heated air was getting in and ignited shavings fir t anc the. the joist. There is a limit for each and everything, an excess of anything is bad. If the fire had taken the very day on which the fireplace was heated there is a reason to believe that it r/as gross negligence of luty as the fire took -lace on the Few Year*s morning by overh ating or some other cause, after being used for two seasons I beg to defend myself that I have not neglected my duty and it can be proved from my previous statement how carefully X have taken Trains to make the joist uninflamable. The description of the construction from ray memory even after tw full years is a conclusive prodf that I have really tr en all the necessar prevautions and never neglected my duties. ^h^ fart that despite my ut er helplessness due to defective estimate want of proper specifications written or verbal and the lack of accurate drawings I have taken great pains conscientlou-ly to discharge my duties to the best of my ability will not fail to obtain appeal to the eyes of justice. I beg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient s ervant,■ * .V ) No. 1448-1/37 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—- The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulp. Bushire Express Letter No. 1098 dated 12th June 1937. Dated 28th .June 1937. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated the 26th June 1937 from the Supervisor, Public Works Department, Bahrain. Reply to his charge sheet.^ i/r fK' 7 Ho. 13 ^ /53/21. ; rr ^ r ; ' ■' - ' dated the 9^ 1937 To The Political Agent, B ahraIn. ^ AL ^QtfV/ Rtgf jij 1NUL1937 Memorandum , The finding in the charge preferred against Mr« Ahdul Wahah is forwarded herewith with the request that it should he handed him. 2. Having handed him the finding will you please warn him that any work carried out hy him in future which is not considered to he satisfactory may engen der his dismissal? He should sign the warning to signify that he has understood it. By Order, 7 Secretary to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. ^7 |-- 4 ^X -C • Cs* ^4^-^ . '^7 6VT/53/21 # _ V dated the 7\ 1937. To Mr. A'bdtil Waha'b, Supervisor, P•¥.!)., Bahrain, Femoratiaui^ . I have considered point 'by point your reply to the charge preferred against yon. Ton state that the wooden Joist was placed 'by you in accordance with the sanctioned estimate. This statement is incorrect for no details of the construction of the fire-places are shown in the sanctioned plans. The plans do not show that a joist is to he placed underneath a fire-place. YoT3 state that no charge is preferable against you, as you carried out the work as per sanctioned esti mate. Tour statement is redundent. state that as the specifications on the estimate were defective you should not he held responsi ble for carrying out work in accordance with the estimate. As the plans are not defective this point cannot he considered as exonerating you from 'blame. Had you found the estimates faulty it was not your duty to work in your own fashion hut to point the matter out to your superior officer. In any case as no details are given in the plans this part of your defence falls to the ground. 4. Your extracts from standard hooks are not rele/-2- relevant. 5. As there were no details in the specifications, yon should have applied for further details in accordance with the general paragraph of the specifications for the Kuwait Agency work, where it lays down that you were to act under the Assistant Utagineer. 6. You say that the Joist was ahout four inches 'below the fire-place and not directly under it. This statement is not clear, 'but I have ascertained from examination of sketches of the scene of the fire that a joist was placed directly underneath the centre of the fire-place. 7. The fact that the fire did not actually 'break out until sometime later is no proof that your work is not defective. In fact it appears ft*om an examination made at the time of the discovery of the fire that smouldering had actually taken place previously, prohahly the winter 'before. 8- With reference to paragraph 5 of your reply to the charge, I consider that what you say has no direct 'bearing on the placing of a Joist 'beneath a fire-place. It is possible for tiles to crack, a servant to 'be sleepy and for heavy pieces of wood to 'be thrown on a fire, 'but it is against such ordinary occurances that precautions are taken during constructions. Your assertions only provide a further reason for not placing a wooden joist in an obviously dan gerous position. 9. It cannot 'be admitted that the estimate or specifica tions were defective and as your supervising officer was constantly at Kuwait you had every opportunity of free con sultation, so that you were not 'helpless* 1 , to use your own words. There was no lack of accurate drawings, copies of the plans were with you and, as pointed out ahove, any point of douht should have 'been referred to your superior officer. 10/the estimates. Tn paragraph 4 you state that the estimates were 'defective 'but that ycu did your hest. In paragraph 4 you state that you used your experience as a guide to make up ^or lack of estimates and in paragraph 6 you again aver that the papers at your disposal were insufficient for your needs, ^om this it is quite clear that you now are of the opinion that you needed more guidance in the way of plans, 'o construct a building of the size of the Kuwait house without sufficient plans only, in my opinion, adds to the offence with which you are now charged and in no way frees you from 'blame. 11. So much -^or your defence; now in the concluding para graph of the specifications attached to the estimate of .the Kuwait Agency 'buildings you were ordered to carry out the work strictly in accordance with the P.T.D Hand-Book and under the orders of the Assistant 'Engineer. 12. Fad you carried out the ahove instructions you would not have placed a joist four inches 'below a fire-place, for paragraph 21 the P.^.D Hand-Book, volume T Chapter II, Materials, wood-work, specification Fo. 1, strictly forhids the use of wood-work of any sort within two feet of a fire place or flue. 13. I consider that you,have not cleared yourself of the charge preferred against you and I direct that you pay the cost of work undertaken at Kuwait in connection with the reconstruction of the fire-places, which amounts to L. 490. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Culf.V Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 652 Dated and received 1st July 1937. Please instruct carpenter ABDUL AZIZ to proceed Bushire via Basra also arrange for a fresh passport if necessary and Iranian visa through His Majesty's Consul at Basra. Britconsul. 4c jje* p_ . 1 iAr? 11 ^ ^ - t) ■ f ■ ^ (5— ^ /Kx— ^1') aTo H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain Sir, I beg to state that I have 'been engaged as a Oarpeuter at Bushire iiesidenicy, and have beei. ordered to teport myself at Bushire via Basrah. I therefore request that I may kindly he granted aa Adva ce of its. 100/- recoverable from me at Bushi^e. lour most obedient servant, A.F.A pa Bahrain, b.7.1937. Abdulaziz Oa^pente^. fey sanction advance of T.A. here ^^ ask Poiiticai Bushire by telegra-m as to vjiietinei tl e of 100 applied for by Abdul Aziz may be sanctioned.If in the latter case 'ratt telegram submitted for favour 01 appioval i»l. ft ^ 5/7/37 /71 Telegram - G.T.C. From - Political Agent Bahrain To - Britconsul, Bushire No - 25S Dated - 5th July 1937* r A Reference your telegram 652 of July 1st. Abdul Aziz requests advance of Bs 100 travelling allowance recoverable at Bushire. May be advanced? - Political-V Telegram - G.T.C. From - Political Resident, Bushire 70 - Political Agent, Bahrain Tto. -710 Dated and received 8th July 1937 Your telegram 253*July 5th. Rupees 100/- may be paid to Abdul Aziz and debited to Bushire account. Britconsul- O f4t (&amp;r, ^7Ho. 1587 X»jV The Political Agency, Bahrain, the 20th July 1937. J to Sir f I have the honour to forward herewith an appli cation for® for a new passport together with 4 photographs of Abdul Azias son of Badar Din, carpenter* vho is ordered to proceed to Bushire via Basra and to report for duty in the office of H»B» Majesty 1 ^ Consul General Bushire • It is therefore requested that you will please issu&lt; him a duplicate passport and also arrange to obtain the Iranian Consult vise on the same with a view to enable him to proceed to Bushire# The Consular fee on the duplicate passport, if any as well as the Iranian Consult vise fee wlU be paid to you by Abdul Aziz who is advised to appear before you ill person* I have the honour to be f Sir, Your most obedient servant. (9^ for Political Agent, Bahrain* His Britannic Majesty^ Consul, Basra# v Copy by hand of Mr. Abdul Aziz in confirmation.'4^/53/97 ^ated the November, 1937. 5^ To The Political A^ent, Bahrain. T r em oraric! iTiTi . a Heferenee this Ties id en cy memoranclTJin No. l?Oo/53/21, dated the 9th July, 1937. 2. The enclosed papers are for your perusal and for favour of handing to Fr. Ahdul ITahah. 'By order, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram — G.T.C» From Politi — 'Political Kgent, Muscat -- Political Agent, Bahrain — 30 To Dated &amp; received 8th January 1938# Following for Pradhan Singh, Supervisor, begins If obtainable please despatch following by next ship. Paints Green 5 Red 10 White 5 Black 5 all gallons, Siscolin distemper cream 500 or others reliable brand first choice Buff 501 Second Choice 120 packets of 3-^ pounds or equivalent. Please telegraph when despatched.Bill to be sent to Political Agent, Muscat. My 1553 - Political -11 To No. 30/ ^ II / / . Bushire, 27th April 1938 Mr. Mohd lehaq, P .W.D. Supervisor, Bahrain. Subjects- Service Book - Memorandum. Your service book is sent herewith for getting your height re-attested by the Political Agent, Bahrain, on page 3 of the service book over his signature. Please sign in column No. 8 on page 6 of the service book at the places marked in lead pencil. Assistdiit Engineer, British ^Consulate-General. Ho. 30/ JyJ' Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information.m No. 14&lt;i3. Dated tiie2C J ul y &gt; 1938. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum ; It has been brought to Sir Trenchard Powle 1 s notice that 3iCr. Abdul Wahab, lately Supervisor, Bahrain, exceeded the sanctioned estimates, in circumstances which appear to be unjustifiable, for the building of the Indian Assistant's Court at Bahrain. 2. I am therefore directed by Sir Trenchard Fowle, the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, jS to request you, in your capacity as officiating political 4! Resident, to hold a full enquiry into the matter and to W - , N \ V charge Mr. Abdul Wahab as provided by Government of India ^ Home Department Notification No .P.9-1^/30, dated the ^7th February, 1932, and in the Home Department Notification No.F.9-18/3(U dated the i8th August, 1932. 3. I enclose herewith the following documents which are relevant to the case -- A to X (copies of records and a warning recently issued to Mr. Abdul Wahab). 4. Mr. Abdul Wahab is at present at Muscat where his presence is necessary at another investigation which is being held there by the political Agent, Muscat. Please -- get■get into toucii with tlie latter and arrange for Mi*. Abdul Wahab*s presence at Bahrain at any date which, is conveni ent to you. The Assistant Engineer, who is a witness in the case, will also visit Bahrain on hearing from you. He will bring with him the actual files. By order. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfSecretary, ■ Mr. Abdul Wahab was asked (Page 122 of File 4 for 1936-37) whether he would be able to carry out the work of the Indian Assistant r s Court at Bahrain within the sanction- ed estimate or not. He replied (Page 147 of File 4 for 1936-37) that the work can be completed within the estimate# W—-■ He was repeatedly warned against excess (Pages 412,426,448 and 469-A of File 4 for 1936-37). In his letter No. 81 dt. 27th March 1937 (Page 216 of File 4 for 1937-38) , Mr. ^bdulwahab reported that there would be no excess provided certain adjustments in booking the expenditure were carried out. The needful was done except the cost of articles of Tools and Plant. It may be mentioned that the work was completed in the begining of April, while on 27th March the Supervisor had assured,that there wo'nt be any excess. During April, when the final batch of bills was received, it was found that he had exceeded the estimate by Rs^796/6/-. The bills were returned to him unaccepted (Page 76 of File 4 for 1937-38^. 2. Mr. Abdulwahab was asked (Page 243 of File 4 for 1936-37) to send the Weekly Progress Report in a certain \ form. He refused to do so in his -importinont letter (Page 430 of File 4 for 1936-37). It was clearly explained to him how to fill in the prescribed form (Pages 290 and 373 of File 4 for 1936-37). This form is prescribed by the Government of India. If Hr. Abdulwahab had carried out the orders, this office would have watched the progress of the work against the expenditure incurred thereon, and would 1 have spotted the excess atonce. He would have been warned immediately about it. He purposely kept the office in dark right upto the end. 3. The following comparative statement would show that the rates provided for the work at Bahrain were higher and more liberal than those provided for similar v/orks at Muscat, in Sind and Delhi Provinces. It may Page. 2*. 2 . U() be mentioned that servants quarters were constructed at Muscat only two years back, at the rates given in the statement below and the work was completed within the estimated amount. The cost of cement per ton in Delhi is Rs» 60/-, in Sind Rs» 56/- while in the Gulf Es# 30/-# Bahrain. Muscat# : Delhi# Sind# 1# Filling in foundation with Bs. 60/- Rs. 50/- : cement concrete (1:3:6). % Oft. % Cft. : - Filling in foundation with : t cement concrete (1:3:6)# : - — : Bs. 50/— Rs# 60/- : % Cft# % Cft# 2. Cement concrete solid blocks , masonry in foundation in fis. 93/- Bs. 75/- cement mortar (1:5). % Cft. % Cft. - Cement concrete solid blocks s masonry in foundation in - - Rs# 70/- Rs# 72/- cement mortar (1:4). % Cft# % Cft. 3# Superstructure masonry of Rs#100/- j » Rs# 73/- Rs# 76/- cement concrete blocks in Bs# 75/- cement mortar (1:5). % Cft# % Cft# % Cft.# %&gt;Cft# 4. Fortunately tit*• Abdulwahab ^ gave out the woodwork estimated to cost Rs. 1622/- on contract# There was therefore no excess on this item* 5. Abdulwahab explains the excess in his letter (Page 434 of File 4 for 1936-37)# I will deal with this para by para# (Para 1)^ is foolish and needs no comment, except the concluding sentence# In India, if a work is carried out departmentally, it is expected that some savings must accrue for the following simple reasons, that the Contractor's profits, the interest on his investment and his supervision expenses do not appear# (Para 2)# Number of moulds is certainly in excess of the requirement, particularly when Mr# Abdulwahab had so much time at his disposal to complete the work (Page 448 of File 4 for 1936-37). Mr. Abdulwahab says that he spent Es. 800/- on these moulds (Page 466 of File 4 for 1936-37)# He does not give any details as to how the amount was spent# I have worked out the details, and find they should not have cost him more than Rs# 470/-1 If he had employed a Carpenter atRs# 3A or 3/8/- per day, as mentioned by my predecessor - (Page 413 of File 4 for 1936—37), the cost would have been , ' I- 3- considerably less* Rs* 283/- were provided for 'the moulds in the sanctioned estimate. If Kr. i&amp;dulwahab had excercised some commonsenae and economy, the sanctioned amount will have sufficed. (Para 6). In the sanctioned estimate Rs. 177/- were provided for curing the blocks. This amount is ample for the two tanks constructed by Mr. iibdulwahab.. The cost of 2 tanks 12 r X5 r X2 r will be about Rs. 120/-. Rs. 687/- were provided extra as Contingencies, for unforeseen works. This whole amount has been used by Hr. 'iibdulwhab. - Actual cost of cement was Rs. 2007/- against Rs. 1971/- provided in the estimate. Hence there was net excess of Rs. 36/- only. If new Joists had to be moulded it was Mr. Abdulwahab's mistake. Anyway the cost of these will be Rs. 370/- as per estimate. Damp proof course received from India cost Rs. 49/~ (Page 301 of File 4 for 1936—37) against provision of Rs. 88/-. Hence no excess. If Mr. Abdulwahab has done little extra work, he has done so from the savings. The last item was not necessary as the joists are of Reinforced cement concrete, which is already damp proof. Moreover in a place like Bahrain, there is very little rain. The cost of asbestos downtake pipes is Rs. 82/2/- (Cash Voucher No. 37 dt. 26-3-1937) against Rs. 84/— provided in the estimate. Hence no excess. (Para 6). The extra 3 K height does not really mean any extra work. Due to horizontal joints this height increases. (&gt;ara 7). Please see page 448(File 4 for 1936-37). 6. Mr. Abdulwahab reports (Page 468 of File 4 for 1936-37) that due to improper calculations he moulded wrong lengths. He had to mould new ones. He does not give number of such joists. As explained (Page 471 of Pile 4 for 1936-37) it was Mr. Abdulwahab 1 s fault. He should have checked the j size before moulding them. The estimate was checked in Chief Engineer's office. The cost of remoulding will be about Rjj. 370/-. Page. 4.4 - U 7. There was a saving of iis. 643/- (Page 424 of File 4 for 1936-37) on purchase of shingles. (6000 Oft being purchased against 7010 Oft.). This whole amount has been used by Mr. Abdulwahab too. 8. Mr. Abdulwahab reports (Page 416-B of File 4 for X937—38) that lie spent Bs. 183/2/— on purchase of articles of Tools and Plant, fis. 136/- were provided in the estimate for this purpose. I object to the purchase of two items, Masons trowels and masons levels costing Rs. 25/-. It was for the masons to pay for them, if their 1 s got out of working order. Ordinarily, rates include such small expenses. -Anyway the net excess is Rs. 22/6/-. 9. The following statement will show the extra amount at the disposal of Mr. ^bdulwahab and that spent by him. Item. Contingencies. Savings on shingles. Sunderies. Wateri Moulds. in hand. Spent, 587/- Moulds.470/- 643/- Tanks. 180/- 136/- Tools &amp; 177/- Plant. 158/- -2&amp;S/~ Joists. 370/- 1826/- Cement. 36/- 1214/- Balance 612/-. The above statement would show that Mr. Abdulwahab had still more than Rs. 600/— to spend, which he has done and on top of it incurred an excess of Rs. 796/6/-. There seems to be absolutely no justification for it. I agree with my predecessor (Page^f^of File 4 for 1936-37) that Mr. ^bdul Wahab is personally responsible for it. He may be allowed to take away moulds and articles of Tools and Plants thou^a in fact ; they are now Government property, as all these articles have been taken into account :Mr. -Abdulwahab will be paid Rs. 100/- recovered from the Contractor for the servants quarters towards the use of some of the articles. As the excess is more than 5%, I cannot sanction it. The matter will have to be referred to the Government of India, in case. Mr. Abdulwahab i s not responsible fo r it. i ,That you reported under your letter No. 131 dated the 27th July, 1936, in reply to the Assistant Engineer's letter No» 4/546 dated the 17th July, 1936, that the work of the Indian Assistant 1 s Court at Bahrain, l, can be comple ted within the estimate as per sanctioned drawings and specified estimate'. 2. That you were warned against exceeding the sanctioned estimate under Assistant Engineer's letter No. 4/150 dt. 14/2/1937, No. 4/177 dt. 1/3/1937, No. 4/208 dt. 6/3/1937 and No. 4/233 dt. 18/3/1937. 3. That lander your letter No. 81 dated the 27th March, 1937, you had reported that to be within the estimate all the articles of Tools and Plant purchased for the work may be charged to Tools and Plant, and 16 planks and 310 cement bags written back to other work© . 'By this the work will be completed within the sanctioned estimate.' 4. The needful was done, except the cost of Tools and Plant, which is Rs. 183/2/- vide your letter No. 2 dated the 1st January, 1938. 5. When the work was completed during the first fort night of April, 1937, it was found that you have exceeded the estimate by Es. 796/6/-. 6. That you haaie refused to send the Progress Report (vide your letter No. 137 dated the 10th February, 1937 in the prescribed form, as instructed by the Assistant Engineer, under his letter No. 4/837 dated the 18th October, 1936. If you had carried out the instructions, the Assistant Engineer 1 office would have watched your expenditure against the progr ess of the work, and spotted the excess.mm No. 646. Bushire, 17th July 1936. To Mr. Abdul Wahab, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain. Subject:- Indian Assistant's Court at Bahrain - Plans and estimate for - Memorandum. Reference your letter No. 121 dated the 2nd July 1936. The estimate under reference has been received duly sanctioned by the Chief Engineer, Central Public Works Department. A copy of which, with 2 blue prints, is sent herewith for information and guidance. This disposes of your letter No. 122 dated the 2nd July 1936. Please state by return post if you can carry out the work departmentally without exceeding the estimated amount. Sd. Fatahali Shaikh, Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Divn. D/ a. Estimate and plans.(0 *Y I 7 -rs I ) No. 131 of 1936. Bahrain dated the 27th July 1936. To The Assistant Engineer, ?• W. D. Bushire. Subject:- Constructing Indian Assistant 1 s Court at Bahrain. Sir, With reference to your No. 4/546 dated the 17th July 1936 I beg to state that the work can be completed within estimate as per sanctioned drawing, and specified estimate. I beg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. iibdulwahab Supervisor.British Govtt&gt; Specials G. T, C. ABDULWAHAB SUPERVISOR BAHRAIN TOP AO RDEZY KARAD ANPTS SKB:IT OBLTO TEHAI PULBO FERUV HZUUX OBLTO 12300 SGULR DYZFA HDLDS LBILG BTPED OBLTO TECIO ORPEU PKUAS BLLDK BGEYL DFINE ETLMC ASSTENGER Bushire, 18th February 1937. Translation: 'Your despatch 46. Total expenditure made against the work is Rupees 8000. The estimate id for Rs. 12300. Wire definitely how much of the balance Rupees 4300 should be surrendered as you are unable to complete the work during the present financial year. 11 t No. 4/150. Bushire, 19th February 1937. Copy forwarded to Mr. Abdul Wahab, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain, in confirmation. It should please be understood that as the expenditure is to be divided in moities between the Home and Indian Government no excess will be tolerated on this work. Every endeavour should therefore be mad^ to keep your expenditure Page. 2.Vr5 t/7 2» within the estimated amount. The Undersigned was simply surprised to know that the number of moulds made by you runs to more than 100 and the cost more than Rs# 800/-. This is where economy and efficiency comes in, which, you have absolutely disregarded* You had ample time to take the moulding in hand which you did not undertake to do until iibdulaziz Carpenter arrived from India sometime in September or October last* The Carpenter according to your letter No. 180 dated the 10th October 1936 was sent for to do doors and windows on contract, but, was instead employed on making moulds at a exhorAitant rate of Rs. 5/- per day, whereas, local Indian Carpenters were available on Rs. 3/- or 3/8/- per day and were fully capable of doing equally good work. If the work could afford to bear so much expenditure on moulds the Undersigned would have pjirchased a moulding machine. But a small work like this did not justify the purchase of one. Undersigned is, however, determined not to have any excess and it is very much regretted to note that you do not seem to have any regard to whatever you write. Please refer to your letter No. 131 dated the 27th July 1936 in which you have replied that the ' work can be completed within estimate as per sanctioned drawing and specified estimate'. At the same time please note that the dimensions are not to exceed or fall short of those given on the sanctioned plan and estimate. In this connection please explain what made you chane the dimensions of reinforced cement concrete joists. They are supposed to be 2' thick and actually they were found l/8th of an inch short. Such joists will not be accepted and the cost of those deficiently made will be debited to you. Sd. Fatahali Shaikh. Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Divn.p t( I No. 4/177• Bushire, 1st March 1937. To Mr. Abdul Wahab, P. W. D. Supervisor Bahrain. Subject:- Floor of Indian Assistants Court at Bahrain - Memorandum. With reference to para 1 and 2 of your letter No. 50 dated the 20th February 1937, it is observed that the trouble in Bahrain is only atmospheric. The instance you cite is due to gutch plaster over which the tiles have been laid. Gutch having great affinity for water has swelled and displaced the tiles. In the case of Indian Assistants Court it has been adequately safeguarded by dry stone filling and dry stone concrete well rammed over which the tiles are proposed to be laid. Please note that stones do not swell and no such thing will happen as anticipated by you. Flooring stone is very cheap in Bahrain and can easily be broken into concrete. All that is necessary to be seen is that it is not freshly extracted and has become dry in which state when broken, there will be hardly any salt left, moreover when washed all salt and rubbish will disappear. In this connection please note that water available for building purposes in Bahrain is not entirely salt free. 2. With reference to para 3 of your letter under reference you are requested to explain why you should require an extra sum of Rs. 500/-. What about all the savings on different materials. Shingle alone has been purchased at a saving of Rs. 6/- for every Page. 2.ifirf iM - 2 - hundred cubic feet which means some what Rs. 360/-; then there is a provision of 6% as Contingencies. Leaving alone the anticipated savings on labour the woodwork would have left an appreciable savings if this office order for doors and windows would not have been intercepted for the encouragement of Abdulaziz Carpenter, for whom full estimated rates have been proposed* 3* As would appear from para 2 above there are savings under certain items of work and as such I see no reason why you should ask for extra sums. 4. Para 4 of your letter is sufficiently clear that as you are not given your own way of doing things you are inclined to use wet stones moss adhered, you are warned against this. 5. The estimate has been sanctioned for a certain specified sum in which Imperial Government have a share and hence ho excess over the estimated cost would be accepted by any authority. This fact has been brought to your notice more than once and you are required to do your best and keep yourself withih the estimated amount. Sd. Fatahali Shaikh, assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Divn.f i No* 4/208. Bushire, 6th March 1937. To Mr. Abdul Wahab, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain. Subjects- Ejccess over estimate - Memorandum. Reference your letter No. 66 dated the 28th February 1937. because you will not admit that they are closely related. 44s for your making personal attacks on every body Undersigned v /ill not stoop low to contradict you in tantamount terms. The drawing and estimate were scrutini zed and passed by competent authorities without making any remark as to its defectiveness. 2. The number of moulds prepared by you is quite out of proportion to the magnitude of the work. What was really required was more pallets rather than the number of moulds and then moulds should have been prepared in such a simple way that each block could be freely removed more often than in the present case. The moulds prepared by you are so difficult to handle that they cannot be struck out without hammering and this appears to be the reason of making more moulds which is an expensive part. 3. Please note that it is as presumptions on your part to say that you could not undertake to attend to moulds while looking after the special repairs to the agency building as you think it is presumptions on the Undersigned^ part to say that you did not undertake the making of moulds until Abdulaziz Carpenter arrived from India. Simple things require simple operations. The points mentioned look irrelevant to you Page. 2.- 2 - ff On the contrary it was a great surprise to the Under signed to note such complicated moulds; that suffocating shed; added with which the damp climate of Bahrain KX no wonder you could not turn out the number of blocks necessary for the completion of work in due course# Had I been in your place I would have used more pallets and would have preferred open air* 4# From the Undersigned's point of view it is sheer esStravagance and waste of public money to employ a Carpenter on Rs» 6/- per day# Moreover just consider the responsibility of sending for a man from India and maintaining him whether the work justified such mainte nance or not. At the time of which Undersigned speaks there was that sikh Carpenter with two or three other men available at Bahrain# 5# Points mentioned in paragraph 6 of your letter under reference are exaggerated. If you sit down and calculate you will find that these items do not come to more than a few hundreds or so whereas you had contingencies to the extent of about Bs. 600/-. Moreover if you anticipated any excess it should have been in sufficient time and not at the 11th hour. 6. Please note that by reducing the width you have reduced the bearing capacity of the joists, the increase or decrease in the size of tiles has nothing to do with joists over which they are going to rest. According to your explanation it is the size of the tiles, which, if cut down slightly would not have mattered much because in that case they could be easily slipped and filled in between the joists, but this do not apply to joists which remains inexplicable and proves lack of forethought on your part. Page. 3.- 3 - Evidently what happened is that you undertook to mould tiles first and made no provision for easy insertion^ at a latter stage when you under-took to mould joists you thought of this and as a consequence cut down the bearing capacity of the joists• 7♦ The above facts establish that you deliberat ely disregarded the 1st cannon of financial propriety by not exercising vigilance and precision in spending public money# Any excess over the estimated cost would accordingly be taken as waste of public money for which you would be held responsible. Sd# Fatahali Shaikh, Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division#To No. 4/233• Bushire, 18th March 1937, \ \ Mr* i&amp;dul Wahab, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain# Subject:- Allotment - Memorandum. Reference your letter No. 53 dated the 20th February 1937. Sanction is accorded to the purchase of gutch and prepare the same for inside gutch and niru plaster. 2. Concluding paragraph of your letter referred to above. This eleventh hour notice cannot be accepted and you must remain within the estimated amount. Sd. Patahali Shaikh, ^assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Divn.No. 81 of 1937• Bushire dated the 27th March 1937 o To Ihe Assistant Engineer, P. W. D# Bushire# Subjects- Excess over estimate - Sir, I beg to state that inorder to be within the sanctioned estimate of Indian assistant Court at Bahrain, I beg to state that all the articles of tools and P|ant purchased for the work may be charged to tools and plant# 2 10 bags of cement and 16 planks were used for excavation at Bosateen, the cost of the same has been charged to Indian Assistant's Court# It may please be charged to work concern# Mid the cost of 300 bags of cement purchased in excess to requirement may as well be refunded to the work# By this the work can be completed v/ithin the sanctioned estimate# If necessary all the moulds as well may be sold in ajction# I beg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. Abdul V/ahab, Supervisor.Registered^ No* 4/356-A* Bushire, 21st May 1937. To I Mr. Abdulwahab, P. W. D. Supervisor Bahrain. Subject:- Construction of Indian Assistants Court at Bahrain - Memorandum. In returning herewith your temporary advance ^accounts Nos. 1, 2 and 3 received with your letters No. 83 dt. 12-4-1937, 91 dt. 18-4-1937 and 92 dt. 30-4-1937, unpassed with following remarks:- The total estimated cost of the above work as technically sanctioned by the Chief Engineer, Central P, W. D. is fe. 12300/- (Twelve thousand and three hundred only). .Against the above estimate an expenditure of Rs» 12,737/18/- (Twelve thousand seven hundred and thirty seven/13/- only) has been booked to end of March 1937. As against the estimate in question the cost of 300 cement bags costing Rs. 500/- (Five hundred only) had been debited in excess of its requirements, it will, after taking back from you the 300 bags of cement or its account, be written back thus reducing the total expenditure from Rs. 12737/13/- to Rs. 12237/-. 2. When the estimate of the work was sent to you for carrying it out, you, in your letter No. 131 dated the 27th July 1936 assured this office that it could be completed within the estimated cost and when toward the close of the work you intimated that there would be an excess over the estimated cost, you, were warned several times that it is to be completed within the estimated cost as the Home Government being involved in it, no Page. 276-A. - 2 - excess can be made thereon* In 'these circumstancesj therefore^ you were to complete the work after 3/37 within the balance i.e. Rs. 62/- (Sixty two only) whereas the expenditure shown to have been incurred by you on the work, in the 3 temporary advances accounts comes to Rs. 729/12/- (Seven hundred and twenty nine /12/-) ancjhence they are returned unpassed. The charges incurred in excess for which you are responsible are to be met by you as already intimated vide this office letters Nos. 4/208 and 4/233 dated the 6th and 18th April 1937j respectively# Sd•^ Fatahali Shaikh, Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub -Divisiono D« A. Tempy: Advance A/Cs Nos. 1, 2 and 3»To n 243. No. 4/837. Bushire, dated the 18th October 1936 Mr. Abdul V/ahab, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain. Memorandum. The attached specimen of Progress Report is forwarded for your infomation and guidance. In future the progress report of works done by you should be sent to the Undersigned in this form please. Sd. Fatahali Shaikh, Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Divn) ys 244 PROGRESS REPORT# Name of work» Period of Report* Sub-head. as per Estimate Quantity, s Rate.; Cost* as executed. Quantity. Rate. Probable cost of work remaining to be done. Explanation of excesses and Cost.; Quantity. &amp; F Rate.;Cost. ; savings. Dated signature of the Subordinate.To ifi Wa/ 430 • &gt; No. 37 of 1937. Bahrain dated the 10th February 1937. r » I The ikssistant Engineer, P. W. D. Bushire * Subject:- Progress Report# Sir, With reference to your No. 4/68 dated the 22nd January 1937, I beg to state that there is neither sence nor logic in that letter. What is the necessity of supposing brick work, preparation of bills, recording of measurement, and payment to Contractors. Where does all these come in with my work. My work is done departmentally, and as such the form sent to me is of no practical use, and I do not know how to fill it. This I have clearly explained to you in my different letterso If other subordinates do fill the form and send to you, it is no reason that I should follow the same. It may be their work quite different from that of mine, and my work and ways of doing are different. The estimates and the copies of different work progress which other Subordinates sent to you may, please be sent to me for my information, and this will be of some help to me, which I doubt very much. I beg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. iibdulwahab. Supervisor.No» 4/999• Bushire, 23rd December 1936• To \ Mr. Abdul Wahab, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrairu Subject:- Revised form of Progress Report - Memorandum# Reference your letter No. 188 dated the 10th November 1936. The form is self explanatory and hardly requires any elucidation. The fol^wbing instructions are n however given for your guidance. The 1st, 2nd, 3rd and 4th columns i.e. the sub-head, quantity, rate and cost as per estimate are to be filled in from the estimate. The 5th, 6th or 7th columns viz. quantity, rate and actual cost to date as executed, are to be filled in from the measurement book, muster rolls etc. In this connection it should be noted that only those quantities should be entered which have been actually done, measured and paid for. The 8th, 9th and 10th columns viz. approximate quantity, rate, probable cost, of the probable cost of work remaining to be done^ will be, unless an excess has been made or is anticipated, the difference between columns 2nd i.e. quantity as per estimate and column 5th viz. quantity as executed. In case an excess is made or is anticipated the requisite explanation for the excess Should be given in the 11th column. Sd. Patahali Shaikh, Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Divn. Copy to Supervisor ^ Qwadur. for information and Overseer, Muscat, guidance. Mi 73 - Fo. 4/68• Bushire, 22nd January 1937 o To Mr* Abdul Wahab, P. W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain. Subjects- Revised form of Progress Report Memorandum. \ Reference correspondence resting with your letter No. 233 dated the 31st December 1936. From para 2 of your above letter it appears that you have misunderstood the instructions contained in letter this office/fTo. 4/999 dated the 23rd December 1936. In columns 5, 6 and 7 viz. quantity, rate and actual cost to date, quantity of work actually done and paid for is to be shown whether the item of work is completed or not. Take for example the estimate of a certain building in which 20000 eft. of brick masonry has been provided to be executed. In a certain month the Subordinate Incharge execute 10000 eft of brick masonry, wnters the measurements in a measurement book, prepares the bill and the Head Office makes the payment. In this case therefore the Subordinate Incharge would show in column 5 (quantity) 10000 eft, in column 6 (rate) the rate per unit and in column 7 (actual cost to date) the cost as actually paid. The example will show that though the item of work viz. brick masonry, is not completed and still it can be shown in the progress report. It is hoped that the above instructions will remove your difficulty. The other subordinates are submitting progress report in the revised form since long and as you have not sent the progress of work under your charge since along time, it should be sent now in the revised form without further delay. Sd. Abdul Ghafur, For Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division.m A 434 • / No® 55 of 1937, Bahrain dated the 26th February 1937 • To The Assistant Engineer, P. W. D. Bushire• &lt; Subject:- Excess over estimate - Sir, With reference to your No. 4/160 dated the 19th instant, I 'beg to state that I am at a loss to find out what you are aiming at, while you are hitting so many irrevelant points, which has no bearing on the subject# It is suffice for me to say that estimates and drawings are prepared in head office, with no knowledge of work and work conditions, and the estimates are not compared and checked by competent r nan before sending to the Government of India for sanction# It is no wonder, when the work done departmentally adhering to the full specifications, aiming at doing the only best work, why the estimate should not exceed the sanctioned estimate# 2» ^s for number of wooden moulds made for the purpose, I beg to state that their number is not great with compared to the magnitude of work in hand# For your information the descriptive list of mould is herewith attached# 3# It is too presumptious to say that I could not make moulds without Mistry iibdulaziz# I was busy with special repairs to the agency, after its completion I took up the work of the Indian Assistant's Court, and further the old building was not completely dismantled, and there was no room for making my concrete yard, which with all the accessories, and curing tanks, was a mild surprise to you when you have not seen such things in Muscat or Gwadur, where similar buildings were constructed# Page# 2#436 • ~ 2 - 4» It» is true that I wanted badly a good carpenter whom I can trust, so I sent for i&amp;dulaziz who was of real help to me at Kuwait, and who understands my ways and standard of work* As he is a good carpenter, he expects good wages, and his getting a rupee more than average local 1st class carpenter, will compensate in the long run, in the efficiency and standard of workmanship# I shall be grateful if you kindly inform me the name of Indian carpenter who is as good as Mistry Abdulaziz, so that I will try him* 5# I assured you under this office No. 131 dated the 27th tTuly 1936, that the work can be completed without any excess# Then I relied on the contingencies for my making wooden moulds, concrete yard, and curing tanks* The contingencies has been taken away by costly cement, extra iron bars for joists, some wrong calculations in joists quantities, extra length of cement downtake pipes, instead of cost iron, as sanctioned, washing of sand and stone# Extra quantity of damp proofing under the parapet walls in order to protect the iron of joists, requires an extra amount# 6# As for the size of the building I beg to say that the length and breadth are as per sanctioned estimate and the height about 3 inches higher than what was sanctioned is expected# The height was necessary to give bare thin lintels necessary cambers, and raise the trellis work one inch above floor level, so as to allow water to run out, instead of collecting in the verandah. Further necessary slope for the verandah is essential. These are based on sound scientific principles. 7. As for reducing the size of cement joists, I beg to say that I have not become mad to do so# I am convinced that if I actually made 2' joists, these will become useless, because the tiles made of wooden moulds are liable to Page. 3#£&lt;-f - 3 - 436. variation in size due to the absence ^zinc lining, as such they will not properly fit in, when laid over cement joistso When it cannot be easily inserted there is no remedy for it. If it is wood or iron it can be plained or cut. Further too tightness will result in the fracture of either tile or Joists, due to thermal expansion. My action is sound and reasonable. Before placing 3 joists, they will be tested on a low platform, with 4 times the weight it has actually to carry and those that fail will be rejected. Extra cement has been added to make them strong. 8* As for the recovery of cost from me, I beg to say that it was I who explained to you on board the ship on 16th January while you were passing to Gwadur, that I have reduced the size, so that I may not find difficulties in inserting the tiles between them. Then you said nothing, on your return you measured them, then also you said nothing, and there is no meaning now in informing me on 19th February that the cost will be recovered from me, when I actually completed almost all the number except those of ends, which require little more attention, as to the exact size. If it comes to that I am prepared to pay, on the decision of an independent Judge, who will not only be impartial, and better technical authority. Here I mean the Chief Engineer, Central P. W. Do I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. i4bd,ulwahab, Supervisor.' ■ : w X ^ r Ko.53 of 1937. Bahrain, dated the 20th Feb, 1937. f f To The Assistant Engineer, * , Bushire, Sir, S ubject - Allotment. With reference to your telegram of 18th instant, I have replied to you on 19th as follows. Spend 4300 final account submitting 27 if 13 March 2500. Supervisor. I can spend Rs. 4300/- provided I am permitted to send n^y account of labour and Mistri Abdul Aziez bil by the mail of 27th March. In case you want me to send the account by the mail of 13th so as to reach you on 20th March as informed to me by your letter, I can spend Rs.2500. Ho where I have told you that I cannot spent the amount. I have explained to you my difficulty, and how I am short of moulds. I am going to make 4 more moulds for drip cornice, as I have only 2 at present, and the turn out daily is only 2,. 1 &gt;i;f I have 6 moulds, I will be able to make 6 moulds. V ' V,Brass fixtures have been received and the bill amountin '••p', to Rs. 250/- will be sent to you by the n«xt mail. About Rs,5^/ bill for Parliamentary hinges and varnish is expected. Sanction may please be granted to buy guth and prepare the same for inside gutch and niru plaster. No separate requisition is necessary I think# because I have to buy gutch from Baoat men, rate differing according to daily demand.C*} -2- Sanction may as well be granted to buy necessary fuel for burning gutch. As I have spent more than Rs.800/- on making moulds I am afraid, I will exceed my estimate. This I wish to bring to your kind notice. Though there is still to spend Rs.4300/- it does not mean that the work can be completed with in sanctioned estimate. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (Sd.) Abdulwahab Supervisor.P.301. « n imim storifis m&amp;artmm mill form Bill Uo. 3366, dated 20th October, 1936. Dr. to Messrs, Plummer Bros. &amp; Co., For articles supplied to Mr. Abdul Wahab, P,W.D.Supervisor, Care Political ^.gent, Bahrain. I. S.D. Ordetf No.BH-1185. dated 2-10-1936. Date of delivery of goods charged for Challan Ho.2854 Amount of freight paid - R g .6/4/- Address - Amarchand Building, Ballard Sstate, Bomba^j Against indent Ho, 4/766, dated 24-9-36. from Asstt. Engineer, Independent Persian S ulf Sub-Division, Bushire, Ghallan/receipt No, 19-10-36. Bill of Lading Ho,39, dated 13-10-36, Received paymai t, for PLUMEGR Bros, 8c CO., (signed) Contractor's name in full. Item Ho, from Order, Description of Stores. Humber, length or weight price H umbe r or quantity accepted Humber or quantl ty rejected Ra te per Amount Ruberoid Roofing 3 ply in rolls of 72 1 x 3' wide. Shipping expenses and steamer freight as per bills attached 2 Rolls 18/8/- roll Total Rs, As. Ps, 37-0-0. 6-4-0c 6-0-0. 4y-4-U, (in words) Rupees Forty-nine only) Hs* 49-0-0, Or*P. 468. No. 64 of 1937. Bahrain dated the 13th March 1937 • To % The Assistant Engineer, W. u. Bushire* Subject:- Completion of work within the financial year - Sir, I beg to state that all my hopes of completing the Indian Assistants Court within this financial year due to improper method of calculating the length of cement concrete Joists over the iron beams in verandah is shattered. My mind is so upset that I could not write in detail how the joists were not correctly claculated please see the length of joists, provided in the sanctioned estimate, and expect my detail information by the next boat# Had these joists were of wood these may be cut and adjusted, being of cement I have to make new ones and I could not make and fix them, without allowing them to mature. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. ^bdulwahab, Supervisor.T Ho.4/242. n 4&gt;i Bushire, 19th March, 1937. To I Mr. Abdul Wahab, P.W.D. Supervisor, Bahrain. Subject; Completion of work within the financial year. M emorandum ; Reference your letter 2T0.64, dated the 13th March, 1937. You were on the spot and could have easily verified the actual length before moulding of the Joists was undertaken. There is nothing easier than to find fault and blame others. A competent man in your place would have taken more pains and would have worked out actual lengths of these joists on site. This would have saved you the disappointment caused. Still you do not admit your fault. On the contrary, you are trying to shift responsibdQ. i 1y on the shoulders of others. (Signed) Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-DivisionNo.2 of 1938. Bahrain, dated the 1st January, 1938. t .f To The Assistant Engineer, P.W.D., Bushire. Sir, Subject - Excess over Indian Assistant's Court. With reference to your ^0.4/1056, dated 4th Decern., which unfortunately reached here on 27th December, 1937. 2. As desired the list of articles of tools and plant purchased but directly charged to work is herewith attached for your kind perusal. 3. The list of moulds of pacca teak wood is also attached for your information. The cost of these moulds amounts to about Rs»800/- or so, with compared to the amount - prov ided in the rate analysis. 4. The savings from stones was taken up for washing stones and sands, and these were washed twice, and the stones required cleaning with hand. Savings from other items was used up in the purchase of extra irons for reinforcement of joists. 6. The contingencies were spent on high cost of cement high wages of labour, and a retention of a store cooly through out the work lasted. 7. Prom the above it is clear to locate where the excess occured, and further changing of flooring specification, has taken certain amount which was spent on this understanding . that there is actually savings, please vide head office Ho.- 2 - 416—A* Contd 4 No. 4/252 dated the 27th March 1937# Therefore I beg to request that you would be so good as to entertain the actual expenditure and pass the account according to your own decision# For this I shall be thankful# I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd. Abdulwahab, Supervisor.P. 33 . 1299/53/21. dated the 9th July, 1937. Mr# Abdul Wahab, Supervisor, Bahrain* Memorandum ♦ I have considered point by point your reply to the charge preferred against you* !• You state that the wooden joist was placed by you in accordance with the sanctioned estimate. This statement is incorrect for no details of the construction of the fire-places are shown in the sanctioned plans* The plans do not show that a Joist is to be placed underneath a fire-place* 2* The state that no charge is preferable against you, as you carried out the work as per sanctioned estimate * Your statement is redundent. 3. You state that as the specifications on the estimate were defective you should not be held l»§sponsible for carrying out work in accordance with the estimate* As the plans are not defective this point cannot be considered as exonerating you from blame. Had you found the estimates faulty it was not your duty to work in your own fashion but to point the matter out to your superior officer* In any case as no details are given in the plans this part of your defence falls to the ground* Page. 2*- 2 - P. 34 4* Your extract from standard books are not relevant. 5. As there were no details in the specifiaations, you should have applied for further details in accordance with the general paragraph of the specifications for the Kuwait .agency work, where it lays down that you were to act under the Assistant Engineer. 6# You say that the joist was about four inches below the fire-place and not directly under it. This statement is not clear, but I have ascertained from examination of sketches of the scene of the fire that a joist was placed directly underneath the centre of the fire-place. 7. The fact that the fire did not actually break out until sometime later is no proof that your work is not defective© In fact it appears from an examination made at the time of the discovery of the fire that smouldering had actually taken place previously, probably the winter before. 8. With reference to paragraph 5 of your reply to the charge, I consider that what you say has no direct bearing on the placing of a joist beneath a fire-place. It is possible for tiles to crack, a servant to be sleepy and for heavy pieces of wood to be thrown on a fire, but it is against such ordinary occurances that precautions are taken during constructions. Your assertions only provide a further reason for not placing a wooden joist in an obviously dangerous position# 9» It cannot be admitted that the estimate or specifications were defective and as your supervising officer was constantly at Kuwait you had every opportunity of free consultation, so that you were not 'helpless', to use your own words. There was no lack of accurate drawings Page. 3.- i - 7? F* 36# copies of the plans were with you and, as pointed out above, any point of doubt should have been referred to your superior odfficer* 10. In paragraph 2 you state that you worked according to the estimates. In paragraph 4 you state that the estimates were defective but that you did your best. In paragraph 4 you state that you used your experience as a guide to make up for lack of estimates and in paragraph 6 you again aver that the papers at your disposal were insufficient for your needs. From this it is quite clear that you now are of the opinion that you needed more guidance in the way of plans. To construct a building of the size of the Kuwait house without sufficient plans only, in my opinion, adds to the offence with which you are now charged and in no way frees you from blame. 11. So much for your defence; now in the concluding paragraph of the specifications attached to the estimate of the Kuwait agency buildings you were ordered to carry out the work strictly in accordance with the P. W. D« Hand Book and under the orders of the Assistant Engineer# 12. Had you carried out the above instructions you not would/have placed a joist four inches below a fire-place, for paragraph 21 of the F. W. D. Hand Book, Volume I Chapter II, Materials, woodwork. Specification No. I, strictly forbids the use of woodwork of any sort within 2 feet of a fire-place or flue. 13. I consider that you have not clear yourself of the charge preferred against you and I direct that you pay the cost of work undertaken at Kuwait in connection with the construction of the fire-places, which amounts to Bs. 490/-. Sd. A. C. Galloway. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No. 1300/53/21. dated the 9th July 1937 • To The Political iigent, Bahrain* Memorandum. The finding in the charge preferred against Mr. Abdul Wahab is forwarded herewith with the request that it should be handed him. 2. Having handed him the finding will you please warn him that any work carried out by him in future which is not considered to be satisfactory may engender his dismissal? 3. He should sign the warning to signify that he has understood it. Sd. Secretary to the in the ly Order, A. C. Galloway# Political Resident Persian Gulf.D.C.No* 1181-1/37. The 4th Auguet 1938 • My dear fatts, I understand that you are at present holding an investigation on Mr# Abdul Wahab, lately Public Works Department Supervisor at Bahrain# another Investigation in Bahrain, which Welghtman has to conduct in the capacity of Resident. Weightman wishes to do this between September 20th and 30th, so I should be grateful if you would send Mr. Abdul Wahab so as to be here between those dates. 3 # Would you please let me know when he will be coming, so that I can make arrangements for witnesses and so forth? 2. When you can dispense with him, he has to attend Yours sincerely, Major R*P* Watts, I.A., Political Agent and His Britannl Majesty's Consul, MUSCAT.Dated the 17th August 1938• 9^ WiXl jp « u please refer to your demi-official letter No.1181-1/37 of August 4th? 2, I have completed my investigations and propose to despatch Abdul Wahab to Bahrain by the steamer leaving here 13th September unless you require him earlier in which case please let me know by telegram* Captain J«B»HoweSf Political Agent f Bahrain3! No. 1330/37/1. Political Agenc , Bahrain, 'the 3Cth August 1938. To The Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire• Memorandum. Reference memorandum No. 1423 dated the 28th July 1938 from the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to my address. 2 m You will be required here by the 20th September for the enquiry to be held on Mr. Abdul Wahab, lately Public Works Department Supervisor, Bahrain. for Officiating Political Agent,Bahrain Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.No-114-1/37. The Political Ageat, Bahrain, Presents his complimenis to:— The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 1.,, in original and has the honour to send him the undermentioned document ( s ) T he Agency, BAHKAIN, P ersian G ulf. Dated 19th January 1939. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, Petition No. 1C from Mr. Abdul Subject. dated the 10th January 1939 ahab, P-' T .D. Supervisor, Muscat.No. c/2 of 1939. 5 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf presents his compliments to r ' w. Tile Political Agent, , 'Bahrairi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documentsc^x Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Muscat. xM£S£icK&amp;E. Dated..3£&amp;. ta'.uar^\, Reference to previous correspondence : May 'Bahrain Printed letter Ho, 1141-1/37 of tne 19tn January 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date y— Ai Memorandum Nd.C/l of the 3rd February 1939 to Mr. Abdul Wahib, P.W.D.Super visor, 'Bahrain. Subject. 4*/ iu I Mr. Ab d ul .¥ahab ♦s petition No.10 dated tne lOtn January 1939.Ho. 0/1 of 1939 • Office of the political Hesldent la the Persian Oulf, Garap, Muscat. Bated the 3rd February, 1939. To Mr. Abdul 7afcab # P.^.B.Supeririaor, Bahrain. Maaorandam . Reference your petition Ho. 10 dated tiie lOtn .Tanuary 1939. I am desired fey tne mn* tie the Political Resident to inform you tnat as Mr. ?elghtiaan , s decision against whlcn you are appealing was given in his capacity of Officiating Political Resident, there is m appeal to tne Political Resident. You can, however, if you see fit appeal to tne Qovermerit of India tnrough txie Political Resident. Your appeal is returned herewith. sd. A#G.Gallov/ay. Secretary to the Political Hesident in tne Persian Gulf.To No. 30/56(b. Bushire, dajed t 28th. June 19391 Mr* Abdul $ahb f ?•»♦!)• Supervisor, M^iprandyp,, Reference your letter 245 dated 12«6*39 9 regarding grant of leave* You are granted leave for 4 months from the 15th • «r\ily 19391 or subsequent date of aerf#. In the meantime you should keep the following papers ready for handing over to your relief *• (1) Charge papers. (2) A statement showing (a) the nasoea of l^ti- -mate© sanctioned! (b) the names of work# completed, showing the mmmit spent thereon f (o) the names of works in p^ogreae showing the amount spent thereon up to date, &amp; (d) the name of works not started yet# A separate statement showing works proposed to be carried out during the year, but for which Estimates have not yet been submitted to this office for sanction, should also be prepared. 2. tour teiaporary Advance account Ho. 3. having been adiaitted for Its. 402/- only, the Mount of teraporary advance outstanding against you on 24-6-39, is R$. 2419/3/9 ( Two Thousand Pour Hundred &amp; Nineteen/3/9. The correct * 3 6. balance outstanding against you including the ajaount still due on account of excess over Indian Assistant*s Court, on the date of handing over charge should be handed over to the relieving subordinate, and his acknowledgement obtained which should be forwarded to this office before you leave for India. Please note this very carefully. J'age. 2.Page 2. . Assls Independent Persian Gulf, Sub-Mvialon. relieve Mto. Abdul Wahab, Supervisor, Muscat,, on or about the 15th. July 1939, You will be treated as on tour at Muscat, holding Hnni charge of the Bahrain &amp; Muscat beats. You should complete the remaining works at Muscat and Qawadar and carry out all other current duties of both the posti Copy forwarded, with corapliments, to the Leal Agent, bahrain Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the Political ^gent ? MTBCAT, Copy to * Ur. Mohd. Ishaq, Supervisor, for imformation# You should proceed to Muscat toFile 1/37 Telegram - GTC From - Political, Bahrain. To - Assistant Engineer, Bashire. No. - 119 Dated the 1st July 1939. Your 30/366 of 28th June. Request you to postpone Muscat arrangements until verandah and other urgent work finished here. It is only possible for verandah work to be finished while I am on recess from 16th July for 2 months. - POLITICAL -Cfo British Govtt. Special. G. T. C. (u - 1 'vS BALm BRITCOHSUL rauzx ISHAQ KSBOF NBAST KORlsrT BRITCONSUL E 30/a! 0 ) Bushire, dated 6 - 7 - 39» Confirmation copy, forwarded, by post. Translation# Your No. 119» Ishaq need not proceed Muscat. To Copy to Assis Independent Persian Gulf, Sub-Division. The Political Agent, Bahrain* Mr* Mohd. Ishaq, Supervisor, Bahrain* ( for information* l^lr* Abdul Wahab, Supervisor, Muscat, for information, in continuation of this office letter No* 30/366 dated 28-6-39. Other arrangements for his relief on ofc about the 15th. July are being made.■jiiiMTr Cj / Bahrain, 11th January 1940. To The Assistant Engineer, I.P.G. Sub Division, Bushire Through H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, As already intimated to you about the sudden attack on my eye-sight, I would further like to inform you that on Wednesday the 10th instant the Company r s Eye- Specialist examined my eyes and as he could not diagnose the disease he simply asked me to wait for one month more but it appears to me quite dangerous to linger on here when I feel my eye sight effected and I also fear it may not go from bad to worse. Under the circumstances as explained above I would request that I may kindly be granted one month leave on medical groud as early as possible to enable me to proceed to India to have my eyes examined by ah Eye- Specialist there. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- Mohd. I sha q, Supervisor. No . 66 Dated 11th January 1940. Forwarded. Though I doubt if he would obtain more effective treatment in India, it must be recognised that any man whose eye sight is failing is bound to suffer extreme anxiety. I think he should be allowed to go. There is no work on hand for him. Sd/- H. Weightman. ^iH.Bahrain. Memorandunu Reference your application dated the 11th January, 1940, received with Political agent, Bahrain^ endorsement No. 66 dated the 11th January^ 1940. Please note that one months leave on average pay is granted to you with effect from 12th February, 1940, as per copy of Sanction Order No. 9 dated the 31st January, 1940, attached herewith# ASSistaBrt Engineer*, Independent/Persian Gulf Sub-Division •r t No. 30/ I' Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information, with reference to his endorsement No. 66 dated the 11th January, 1940*SiiNCTION ORDER No» 9. The Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is pleased to grant one month^s leave on average pay to Mr* Mohd Ishaq, P* W. D. Supervisor, Bahrain, with effect from 12th February, 1940. On the expiry of his leave he will return to Bahrain. Sd. a . C. Stewart. For Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 31st January, 1940.J tr V PJ A.P.A, I beg to state that I am suffereing from a boil on my leg and I am unable to stir out. The Doctor says that it will take about 8 days for healing. Under the circumstances 1 beg to state that if my presence is required for any urgent work the intimation may kindly be sent to me at my house. Submitted Supe Bahrai*h. 4-7-40, Vy , fa ^ P fl * 7 \\ ^ jv* — 7^ [u! vw o \ t #4 A. P. A. N Mr; Mahomed Issaq is suffering from a 'boil on the inner _ * \ _ J ^ yA side of the right thigh.He will probably he unfit for work for J the next eight dajts. xf 2 Bahrain Of\L ' ^ 4.7.40. 'P- • ^Telegram GTC. Prom Political, Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bushire. No.203 Dated 28th August, 1941. Please inform Assistant Engineer that Mohammed Ishaq has been operated on for a septic hand, has been in hospital since August 2nd and will remain there at least for another month.o 7i Telegram GTC. From Political, Bahrain* 1*0 Britconsul, Bushire. No.239 Dated 23rd September, 1941. fa. My telegram No •203 of August 28th* Ishaq has had cerebral haemmorrhage and is not expected to live# He is in American Hospital#Telegram GTC* From Political, Bahrain* *^0 Political, Kuwait. No.238 Dated 23rd Septem-ber, 1941* For Ismail* Ishaq was admitted to Mission Hospital on August 2nd for a septic hand* He developed diabetes and has how had cerebral haemmorrhage. He is not expected to live*Telegram G.T.C. Prom Pot Britconsul Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. A/MS Dated 26th September 1941. 5- Your telegram 239 September 22nd Please inform next of kin. -Britconsul-II telegram . ..• •G.T.C. Prom •••••• ^aj or R.G.Alban, Karachi To •••••* o Political Bahrain. No T/34 f# 7 Dated the 27th September, 1941# Very sorry to hear the death please give condolence to widow and arrange repatriation of family. Alban./ H Bahrain. 3^th Septonber, 1941 j To Sir, The Political Agerrt, Bahrain. I beg to inform you that on receipt of the news of the serious illness of my father I applied for 15 days casual leave only and the Political Agent, Kuwait, was kind \ enough to sanction this. I proceeded to Basrah to catch either a boat or planfe for Bahrain. While I was still in Basrah I received news of the death of my father and I had no time to return to Kuwait for extension of my leave. I arrived here by air on the morning of 29th instant. 2# As there is no male member if age in the family to settle the affairs of my late father, and as it is imperative on me to wind up the estate of my late father before my return to Kuwait, I shall be most grateful if keeping in view the helpless conditions of our family and small children, you will kindly ask the Political Agent, Kuwait, to grant me on months earned leave. It would of course be a blessing on me and our family if I could be transferred to Bahrain in which case the question of leave would not arise. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant. H Pfr. ^ ' 1 (Mohamed Ismail) 2nd clerk. Political Agency, Kuwait, on leave.Telegram - GTC. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Political Agent, Kuwait. No. - 258. Dated the 4th October, 1941. Owing to his father's death Ismail applies for one months earned leave to settle the estate. As his presence is essential I recommend leave may be sanctioned. - POLITICAL «J I . - —Telegram From Addressed to Repeated to No.810 Dated 6th October, 1941 / /j&gt; G.T.C. Political Agent, Ma Kuwait. Britconsul, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. Addressed Bushire Repeated Bahrain. Mohammad Ismail was granted 16 days 1 casual leave by me on receipt of telegram from Political Agent, Bahrain that Mohammd Ishaq was dying. Ismail now asks for one month's extension which Political Agent, Bahrain,considers essential. I am already one clerk short and have no one capable of carrying on Ismail^ work. So I much regret I cannot agree to extension of leave unless you can find relief atonce. -Political-Telegram - GTC. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Consul-General, Bushire / 7 No. - 265. Dated the 8th October, 1941. // 0 ^ Kuwait telegram 810 of 6th October. Ismail requests reply as the next up boat is expected October 10th. Suggest he is posted here in the leave vacancy of Head clerk. He can then clear up his father^ affairs and also learn passport work to be available as relief for Rabbafti vide your telegram No .A/309 dated 23rd September L - POLITICAL -Telegram - GTC. From - Britconsul, Bushire. Addressed - Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated - Political Agent, Kuwait. No. - A/340. Bated and received the 10th October, 1941. IMPORTANT Your telegram 265 October 8th. I have no relief available for Political Agent, Kuwait who is already short handed. Unless therefore you are prepared to change with Zafar Islam Ismail should return to Kuwait as arranged. - BRITCONSUL -Telegram From To Repeated to No.268 Dated 13th October, 1941. GTC. Political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. Political, Kuwait. Your telegram No .A/340. Ismail will be returning to Kuwait by the next up mail.No. I* | (-1/37 Tha Political Agent, Bahrain, Preseats his compliraeats to s— Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf ^ub-Division, Bushire• in origina and has the hinour to send hir^^^py of the und^rrasntioned document ( s ) for favour of disposal. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated Ufa October 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Mame and Date. Subject Bill dated the 6th Octobor 1941, for (U. 166/- from the American Mission on account of Meclical tre IsaQt late P- Supervitor, Bahrain- Hospital, Bahrain , tment of Mr# MohdIto.JJM '1/37. Political Agency f Bahi^ in. Mated the 24th November 1941• To Br. P•W.Harrison, American Mission TToapital, Bahrain. Dear Sir, ij . fith reference to your reminder of 14th Hovember 1941 (addressed to T ir. Steele) for payment Of your bill of 6th October 1941 for the medical treatment of the late Mr.Mohammad Isha&lt;??, X beg to inform you that the Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf, Sub Division, Bush ire, under whom l T r. Ishaq was serving before his death has been requested to arrange payment of the bill and a reminder is being sent to him in this connection# Yours faitlyfully, ^. for Political Agent, Bahrain. //&gt;L 7*. If-fl' -1/37. Tha Political Ageat, I3atiraia f Praseals his complitneats to Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub Division, Bushire. and has the hioour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for favour of disposal. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated Kaference to previous correspondence : °24th 'November 1941 Bahrain printed letter,No. Description Name and Date. Bill dated the 14th November 1941 Mission Hospital, Bahrain, on accc Fr. Mohammad Ishaq, late ?. : .'O.Sui ^nctoiutt datGd the 2lQt October 1941. Subject for R3.I66/- from t^e American unt of medical treatment of ervisor, Bahrain.«o. o?3 ss/^iy Poilticai Agency, Bahrain, the 24th November 1941 To The Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, B U s a I B £ Memorandum A sum of % 510/- was advanced to the late Mr. Mohaiamad Isnaq against two Htser/e Bank of India drafts, Kos* 096G46 and 096617 issued by the Treasury Officer, Bushire, without endorsements by him l3 he was too ill at that oxme to do so# de suDsequentiy died witnout endorsxag these drafts. 2* I shall be grateful, therefore, if the sum of k 510/- can be reimbursed to me. x'he drafts are ^returned herewith for cancellation. /?-&lt;£, jiff*/* , ' Political Agent, Bahrain \ K ■(I D I visited Mr.Md, Ishaq^Superviser, P.W.D.) last night when he handed over to me the enclosed draft and asked me to request you that as he is unable to endorse the draft this may be retained in Treasury and payment made to me on his behalf. He will, however, sign it on his becoming v/ell. 18.8.1941. (UUl Mr. Md.Ishaq, Superviser of P # W.D # is now a bit better than yesterday, the last night having passed in the utmost anxiety. I am submitting draft for his pay and request, on his behalf of course, that payment may kindly be made to me. He will sign the draft on his becoming alright. Payment for his last month's pay was similarly obtained by the permission of Capt # Howes • 14.9.1941.No. 30/732. Bushire, 12th December, 1941• From - The Assistant Engineer, Ind. Persian Gulf Sub-Divn., Bushire. The Political Agent, Bahrain• Sir, With reference to your memorandum No. 2328/1/37 dated the 24th November, 1941, I have the honour to forward herewith Reserve Bank of India Remittance No. 099403/140 dated the 12th December, 1941, for Rs. 510/- drawn in your favour on the Bombay Treasury in recoupment of the 2 drafts sent with your memorandum referred to above which have been cancelled. Kindly acknowledge receipt. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Independent Persian uuir buo-Division. Eiiclosure: mziu — K/|. 'm*)0 ' sanction Order No. £ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is pleased to grant 2 months 1 leave on medical certificate to Mj %~ Abdul t /ahab, Supervisor• Muscat. On the^piry of the leave # he is to report at Bahrain ant obtain a medical certificate of fitness before joining duty vld« S. H. 258. Copy with coxoplimentB ; to the Political ngent Bahrain, for information, in continuation of ♦ Ko. 561 dated 26-5-42. Copy with compliments t to the Political ngent, Muscat, with reference to his telegraia No. 270 dated 12-6-42. The exact date on which &amp;Sr. /ibdul ^ahab is relieved asay kindly be intimated. For PDlitlcal Besldent in tiie Persia Gulf. AI aA To //! No. 3C/369. Bushi^i 19th August ? 1942. (6 Mr. ^bdul wL^, Supervisor Con leave), Raj^ghiri Post, Tanjore District. Memorandum. ^ j &gt; U In continuation of this office sanction order No. 62 dated tlie 21st June, 1942, Mr. .Abdul- Wahab is informed that he is to report to Muscat after the expiry cf his leave unless otherwise ordered. X. Secretary to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. No. 30/370. Copy forwai'ded, with corrrplinents, for infomation to:- The Political Agent, Bahrain. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat.No.1709-1/37 Political Agencyi Bahrain. 22nd September, Date 1943 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to : — The Secretary to the Hon , ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, BushIre• Jl 1 ' J ' 1 '' 'i 1 ' 1 in original and has the honour to transmit to hiq^ the undermentioned document tor* favour of disposal. Reference to previous correspondenoe k, r No. &amp; date of enclosure Application dated 10th September,1942, from Mr* Abdul Wahab, Supervisor, P.W.D. Subject Fund Genera1 Frovident/Advancenth ( ■ PJnLIr 1 ■ani - ^ Ho. 01355-S. //0 Dated, Hew Oalhi, the /y/A. March, 1943, Mirzu t'&amp;qBood Bag, haa been selected for appointment aa an ovsreear under the Hcm'ble the PolltiCfJ. Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre with iomdlftt* on the rates of my noted below j- M M MMMM ' PAY. PSMIAM001# HOUSE RSHT. TOTAL. AW Re.150/- In the B8 ,40/~, R8,21C/- scnle of lia ,130- 5 -150. PMa Prt and Second Claat rv.asagtt of Steaaer Karachi to Buohlrn Bill he arranged for Beg. 2. arse Maqaool Beg la directed to report for 4uty to the Political Agent, Bahrain, ?,C, t at a very early date. 3d/- Mohd 3ulaliaan. CKKP fciJGIii.EIi. Ho. 0i356-L. Dated, Hew Delhi| the March, 1943. Copy forwarded toi- 1. Kirza Vhqaood Beg, Overaewr, Sirohl P.W.D., Abu Road, for Informtlon, with reference to his Telegram dated the 9th March, 1943. The date on which he can leave hie place should be corEnunicated to thia office at a very early date, so that mjceooary Paaa Port easy be obtained for him. Travelling Allo.Yincc advance, if he needs any, to enable hiss to proceed to hin naw destina tion should also be intimated to thia offica. 2. The Accountant General, Central Bevenuea, New Delhi, for Infoi-matlon. n. 3.The Koa'ble the Political i^aident in the PBrciun-Culf, Buahlre, for information, inkontin latioi of this^ndoraa- raent Ho. 01355-a, dated the '22nd January, 1943. UT. Beg haa been selected vice Mr. Khan who has expressed his unwillingness to accept the post. The arrival report of w/wr. Bag may kindly be sent to this ofiicc in due course. 4.*rhe Political Agent, Baharsln, P.G. for inforasation in- con tinuati on of this office endoraaBent No.01355-„ / dated the g^id January, 1943. v v ', 3. The Secreataiy to the Government of India, Oepartoent of Labour, New Delhi, for informtion in continuation of I thia Office Endorsement Ho.Oi365-£. dated the 22nd Jan., 1943. ur. Beg has been selected vice Khan who has expressed his unwillingness to accept the ooat in - question. 6. The Secretary to the Gove maw nt of India, iixtemal - Affairs Department, Hew Delhi, for information In conti nuation of this Office Endorsement Ho. 01355-K, dated the 22nd January, 1943. Mr. Beg haa been selected vice Mr. Khan who has expressed his mwlllizumGse to accept th- post la qucistion. )1 / ' •W «TH. ■ I I-; : -iCi-.H.Copy,of N©• G3/5586, dated the 13th August 1943, from the executive Kn^ineor, Central Public 'forks Department, Karachi Aviation Division, teirachi, to the Political Agent, .Bahrain. .Last pay certificate and service Book of Mr. A.M. Quadr^., transferred to your off ice vide Chief Engineer, Delhi's No. 01366, dated 22,1.43 are sent herewith, receipt of which may please be acknowled- une advance copy of L-P.C. was made ever to Mr. '.^uadri to avoid delay in payment of his salary # Bahrain for want of the same. enclosures service book(2 parts) L.P.C. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 19th August 1943. A'^ith enclosures / Forwarded/to the Assistant Engineer, j-ndependent Persian (iulf Sub-Division, Bushire. Receipt may please bo acknowledged direct. slj-fiLPrCj' Political Agent Bahrain.f$) 1 ' Co■ • of memoi^nduia ITo.P. i*D.4-430 dc.tod tho 6th ?'Ove:-iiber 1944 from the ^xecutiv-; Engineer, Independent' Po:sia.n G-ulf onh-iJivn. , Bushire to tfle Political -.gent, Bahrain. dubjeCt: Constructing Offics Building for the Hon'ble the Political.Resident at Bahrain. . The bearer .,ir.;iohd ila.:an Overseer, has been ■ sent'to Bahrain to start -the preliminary work in connection with the . )ove noted vork. He has been instructed to start' the demolition of tie existing store building-and also :a^e enquiries for he collection of local raaterials such s stones, Se^nd , and c hand--1 s e t q . % 2. The senior Supervisor v .dll be coming to Bahraii by the end of November, 1944 vheori the construction, work • wilP be commenced,. 3, It is. requested that all possible assistance may be rendered to ■Ar.'iohd. xiasan when fejuired. (Original filed In ^ile lo.18/16), . Office Orf'er No; ^3 Bahr^a %\lAhiC' Mrs is posted to Bahrain for Construction of tn6 Hon4sbXe/PoiiticaJ. Besident's Office at Baiirain until further orders. He will also complete other repair works to Political Agency at Bahrain, P, # Mr: Mohd Hassan after haadixig over charge to Mr; A.M.Qiadri, will report back to this head Office by the first availstele boat. n Executive ^igineer^ Ind epenc^nt P* (r # Bit Diri s3 on. /W&gt;T Baohire, ^y- Bated 1%^ January 1946. Copy forwarded for information to tre:- (a) Secretary to P.H. u/tb) The Political ^gent,Bahrain.No. f i \ Political Agency, Bahrain, / ' ' 1 IV 1 fhft 4.th Peb-puarv. 1945. To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Will you please book one second class passage with food from Bahrain to Bushire to Mr. Mohammed Hasan, by the first opportunity, and debit the cost to the Bushire Residency? Yours faithfully,^ • ^ ■ &gt; n . ^ -j for Political Agent, Bahrain. c4tv^nFROM G ray, M ackenzie a Co., L td. Agents: B. I. S. N. Co., Ltd., TO H*B» political Agent, | BAHRAIN. BAHBAIN. I no . B 1 /3 •284 ( ^ J 25th APRIL. 1945 o Dear Sir, Our d/ N bl/29 of 25-2 -45 lis.54 -0-0 We shall be pleased to receive your remittance of our above oill at your early convenience® VGBtMDS Yours faithfully, GRAY, MACKENZi^C^^yrTLtG. nqB$ 6 7 f. INo»1871-1/37. Political Agency^ Bahrain, ^ The 3rd May, 1946, u To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandiiiq . I enclose herewith copy of debit note No. BI/29 dated the 26th Febi^uaiy^ 1946 received from Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain, claiiaing cost of passage with food granted to Mr. Mohawaed Hassan, Overseer in February, 1946. The amount may please be recovered from Mr. Hassan and paid to the Company 1 s agents there. 4^- ^ or Agent, Bahrain. No.1872. )y Copy forwarded to Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.5 Ltd,, Bahrain, with reference to their letter No.BI/S.284 dated the 25th April, 1945.No»2106» Political Agency, Bahrain, fhs 22ad May, 1945# To Messrs* Lawrence &amp; Mayo (India) Ltd., 274, iiornby Road, Fort f Bombayi Please sand per V.P»?, parcel by air mail one pair of spectacles of the size and number mentioned in the attached note. The frame should be of celluloid, with wire inside ear pieces, pento shape and golden colour. It is required for Mr, A »M* Quadrl, (P.W.D. Supervisor) who is an employee of this Agercy. Please treat this as ^irgent. Dear Sirs Xovts faithfully, // for Political Agent, Bahrain. No.aiO?. Copy forwarded to the Export Trade Controller, Bombay for informtion ndth the request that the export be allowed.To ITo. Dated |S0 0 Telegram En Clair. From Political Agent, Bahrain. Lawrence and Mayo, 274 Hornby Road Bombay. 412 12th June, 1946. r Refer my 2106 May twenty second and expedite despatch spectacles. =POLITICAI= AMO.Telegram En Clair, From Lawrence &amp; Mayo, Bombay. To Political Agent, Bahrain. ITo • Ifil. Dated 14th received 16th June, 194 Yours received Spectacles ready awaiting export license. /ill despatch immediately upon receipt . Lawrence Mayo. Bahrain Receipt ^mm* From The Political Agents Bahrain. The Export Trade Controller, Bombay, No»2513~l/37« Bahrain, dated the 17l*h June, 1946i ' 1 ^ Please refer this office letter lta.2106 of 22nd May, 1946, addressed to Messrs# Lawrence &amp; Mayo (India) Ltd*, Bombay and copy endorsed to you. 2» Grateful if necessary export permit is supplied to the firm without any further delay as the spectacles are required very urgently. for Political Agent, Bahrain. V Copy forwardM to Messrs. Lawrence &amp; Mayd (India) Ltd., Bombay, with reference to their telegram of 14th June, 1946.■i _i __ % No. 21827 _ V^r-F IN YOUR REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. QUALIFIED SIGHT-TESTING OPTICIANS AND SCIENTIFIC INSTRUMENT MAKERS zyA* H ornby R oad F ort. BOMBAY. air miL /33 TELEGRAMS FOR EASTERN BRANCHES 'LYNX' iRAMS \ ALL | On REGISTERED OFFICE: 11, Government Place East, CALCUTTA. 13th June 1945, The Political Agent, Political Agency, B ahrein. Dear Sir, W No We duly received your telegram of the 12th instant reading as follows: ' REFER MY 2106 mY TWENTYSECOND &amp; EXPEDITE DESPATCH SPECTACLES'. Your letter No.2106 was received here on the 30th ultimo and we trust you duly received our acknowledgement of that date. An application for an Export Licence was submitted to the Authorities on the same date but this has not yet come to hand. The Spectacles are completed but we are unable to despatch them to you until the necessary Licence comes to hand. follows: We have accordingly wired you today as 11 YOURS RECEIVED SPECTACLES READY AWAITING EXPORT LICENCE WILL DESPATCH IMMEDIATELY UPON RECEIPT. 11 You may rest assured that the Spectacles will be despatched to vou immediately upon receipt of the Export Licence. y ours faithfully&gt; For L awrence mayq(indl^)ltd. JHG:AN ■or L awrence ^mayocindl^ltd^ branch secretary.OIL COMMUNICATIOMS TO RF AOOftCfiSEO TO THE COMPANY f c! □ M. .J V'^' f' QUALIFIED SIGHT-TESTING OPTICIANS AND SCIENTIFIC INSTRUMENT MAKERS 274, HORNBY ROAD. FORT, BOMBAY. 30th May, 1945. The Political Agent, Political ^gencv, Bahrain, B A H R ^ IN. iabraii Dear Sir, m iieceipt . - / No^^jf^.Date / We duly received your letter of the 22nd instant and as desired, are proceeding with the making of a new pair of Imitation Shell Sutton Wine Quadra Frame fitted with White Meniscus Lenses in accordance with your prescription. The work is now in hand and the Spectacles will be despatched to you as quickly as possible when we trust they will reach you safely and prove to be quite satisfactory. Assuring you of our best ser vices at all times, Yours faithfully, For Lawrence &amp; mayocindia)ltd. jhg;an branch secretary.B-r CK ' Z' 1 ** EXPRESS LETTER 'i From The Export ^rade Controller. Of Catiraiii ^ No 'T^e^Eolitical Agent, Dato. Bahrein. *^0 ti ew us torn ^ouse, ^omBay 7 — I945. - Reference your letter No.25l5-l/57 of ? 17/6/45. ^ill you please send to this office a copy of letter No 2X06 of tl/5/45, addressed to M/s L aurence &amp; Mayo ( India) Ltd., the copy of whicT ^ndorsed to this office, as the .ame doe' not -ppeS to have been rs^eived in this office,. i I . have the honour to bf, ' Sir, Your most bedient servant, s FOR THE EXPORT TRADE CONTROLLER /lahro in. ' rtatod 20th. Anaust. 1945 13^ To The Political Agent Bahrain, ^. i • • Sir, I beg to state that sin^e May 1945 I am*having some trouble with my eyes and am also suffering from headache# I was examined by Dr. Storm who prescribed reading glasses whinh you were kind enough to get me from India. I am usin^ them sinoe about 2 months but still my vision is diminishing and the headache has become a ^hroni^ one. besides this something has developed in my nose and requires an operation. In support thereof I am enclosing herewith a Medical Certificate in original I therefore earnestly request that the Secretary to the H f ble. the&lt;Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire may kindly be approached telegraphically to sanction me one Month 1 g earned leave and arrange to send my relief by first available boat, so as to enable me to go to Karachi by the first opportunity and have expert medical treatment over there, as I am afraid that more delay might worsen matters. Thanking you in anticipation. v Your most obedient servant Enclosures:- One Medical Certificate dated 20-8-45. in originalTe^egra^ GTC Fram - Political Ageat, Bahraiii.. To - Britaia, Bushire. No, - 655 Dated the 5th September 1945. - ;s ; .... f QADRI P.W.D. Supervisor diagaosed by Dr. Storm as require^ operation for masal septum aad asks for one moath's leave which I recommead if relief available. - POLITICAL -1^. Telegram From Political Resident, Shirnz. , Political A^ent, Bahrain. T/498 12th and received 13th September 45 G.T.~ To Da t eu Addressed Bahrain repeated Bushire. Ref-eren-e your telegram Ho.655 September Sth.-^l 0 '^^ Please inform Oadri operation does not apnear to present any urgen-y and leave is not repeat not granted. 2. He should submit report on progress of OAT J 0 T f A vTelegram From To No. Dated G.T.C. / Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire 709 1st October, 1945. j&gt;. /3? Your telegram No.T/498 dated 12th September. Qadri now says his son in India has typhoid. Kindly telegraph whether I may grant him ten days leave No relief required. -POLITICAL^Telegram G#T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 733 0 Dated 10th October, 1S46. My telegram 709 October 1st. Qadri f s leave Grateful for reply. =POLITICAL^ AMO.Printed in England. Sej»t. 1942. (4,100. pads, j CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) The first line of this Telegram contains the foflowing particulars in the ©rdprVni Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time Official instructions—if any. , 5/- } ^ 16 8 Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. POC. 0755 M2 Bakjrain Rece'pt //, RV43/N BUSHIRE 21 1 0 1 700 POL IT 1 OA L BAHRA IN E/4.87 IMPORTANT YOUR TELEGRAM NUMBER OCTOBER SECOND QADR1 MAY HAVE TEN DAYS CASUAL LEAVE REPEAT CASUAL LEAVE BRITAIN MARK YOUR REPLY '2%a JmAeiiaZ' ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES.IW No.4296-1/37 Policlcal Agency, Balirain The 11th October, 1945. To The Station Manager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please Issue Mr. A.M. Qadri of this Agency with a return vouchor for his passage to Karachi. The passage amount will be paid by this Agency, Yours faithfully ? for Political Agent, Bahrain. G.58/4^- Telegram. From. To. No. 549 Dated the 14th October 1945. GTG. , /• Political, Bahrain, f Political Resident, Bushire Your telegram No. E/487 of October 10th. 2. Qadri left by air on October 12th. 3, Grateful if Government of India could be asked to arrange priority air passage Karachi to Bahrain October 22nd for A.M. Qadri, 3 HaJi Mohammed Ishaq BMlding, Ramsami quarters, Barness Street, Karachi. - POLITICAL LH.Copy of a telegram ( G.T.C) No:E/4.92,dated 17.10,^.5, from Britain, Bushire; to Foreign, New Delhi. Grateful if priority air passage karachi to Bahrain on 22nd repeat 22nd October be arrabged for Abdulmajid Qadri P.W.D. Supervisor who is urgently required for duty in Bahrain. His address is as followsi- 3 Haji Mohdishaq Building Raraswami Quarters,Barnes Street, Karachi, Office of the Executive Engineer, P.W.D., British Consulate General, Bushire, dated 17th October,4-5. Copy of the above, forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain/for information, reference his telegram No:549, dated Uth October 1945, addressed to Britain,Bushire. for Executive Engineer, (S A.G. Nom No .222-1/37. Political Agency, Bahraino 19th January,1946• The undermentioned paper^®pgx is forwarded to the Secretary to the Elon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. for Political Agent, &amp; Bahrain. Enclosure. Petition datecb the 4th December, 1946 from Mr. A.M. Quadri, P.W.D. Supervisor, Bahrain, addressed to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian lulf, Bushire. C.Telegram GTC From Executive Engineer, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. E/87 Dated 18th and received the 19th May, 1946. Following for Qadri. Your telegram 14th May. Your relief reaches Bahrain next ship from Bushire submit ? detailed plan of work done and pending. ^EXECUTIVE ENGINEER= I.E.402 ' . , ' AMO.Telegram From To No. Dated relief. GTC Political Agent, Bahrain. Executive Engineer, Bushire. 310 21st May, 1946. Your telegram E/87 . Please telegraph name of Qadri 1 =P0LITICAL= AMDTelegram From To No. rJ / GTC His Majesty^ Consul, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, E/100 Dated the 8th and received the 9th June 194 -6 Please pay Qadri Rs«1201/4/- only his pay for May and advance Travelling Allowance. I.R.439 AMO. =BRITAIN='I i ? /V3 Ci^BGS CSRI'lFICATE Certified that wo haye handed over and taken ♦ oves» charge of the P. D. Section at Bahrain with effect from the afternoon of the 12th # June, 1946. Kelieving Officer, Supervisor. Believed Officer. Sti^ervisor. Copy forwarded for information tos- 1, The Political Agent 5 Bahrain. 2. The Executive Engineer| Indep; Persian Gulf S-uL-Divisioiij Bushire, with reference to his Office Order Wo. 64 dated Bushire the 21st. May 1946. A copssr of the Handing Over Notes is also forw&amp;rded herewith. Bahrain ^ No-.... Ul^.On,Telegram GTC From Political Agent, Bahrain. To His Majesty^ Consul, Bushire. No. 353 Dated 20th June, 1946. Please expedite despatch of PoW*JH n *:• Supervisor^ permanent advance. He is now without funds and requires RSo2000/- to pay outstanding bills and establishments® =P0LITICAL= AMO. v./ r ■ ^ ■ •/ '/' ■ / Telegram GTC Prom Assistant Engineer, Bushire. To Political Agent f Bahrain. No» E/109 Dated 21st and received the 22nd June, 1946. ■Ai , • . . . . Following for Supervisor Begins, Please telegraph cost of surplus materials creditable to construct' ing Political Resident Office Bahrain ?supT&gt;lemcntary account held up. Matter is urgent, =ASSISTAKT EKGIKEER= I.R,460 No. V^O ' Political Agency,Bahrain. The 22nd June, 194 -6. AMO. Copy forwarded to the Supervisor, Bahrain. H ■ *&lt;j for-JPolitical Agent,Bahrain (a ,1 Telegram From To No. Dated GTC Political Agent, Bahrain. His Majesty 1 s Consul, Bushire 359 2Vth June,1^46. • # t • • IS11 owing for Assistant Engineer, Begins. Your telegram No.E/106 dated June l^th Contractor does not accept Rs .326 annas nine and insists for full payment 6f his claimo Supervisor. =POLITICAL= AMO.Telegram From To No. Dated GTC (E&gt; His Majesty^ Consul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. E/lll 1st and received the 2nd July, 194-6 (.UA Your telegram 353 June 20th, Please advance Bs.2000 repeat 2000 to the Supervisor. Will refund by Bank Draft next mail. =BRITAIN= I .R .471 AMO.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. D bpaetmikt, EXPRESS LETTER N. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MJESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intetided to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched^ F rom POLITICAL, MHHAIN. f© BRITAIN, BUSHInE, 2126 - 1/37. Bahrain, the 3rd July 1946i3Soc Reference your telegram E/lll of July 1st, 1946. 2. The Supervisor has been advanced only Rs.lOOO/- as the credit balance in the Bushire Residency account on 1st July 1946 was only Rs.1748/-, vide my telegram No. 370 of July 1st. - POLITICAL = The issue of the above^as been authorised. x l ■ L y Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMS s. e. mfl'—400s&amp;p—{m-480j' 26-7-34—2,00,000.Telegram GTC, From Assistant Engineer, Bushire, To Political Agent, Bahrain^ Ko.S E/116 Dated 6th and received the 7th July, 194-6 Following for the Supervisor Begins. Your telegram No.359 June 25th 1946. Rs.326/9/- sanctioned as recommended by you in your letter Ho. 1/133 dated April 9th 194-6. ^ =ASSISTAHT ENGINEER^ No e SXbs' f &gt; - Political Agency, w Bahrain. The 7th July, 194-6. Forwarded to the Supeiyrisor, P.W.D., Bahrain. Alio. S^fo^blltlcal |f;en ;enl*; Bahrain.No:4/_ 1 53J_ e Dated Bushire, the £jT Agust 1946. To From The /iseistant En ineer, British Consulate General, Bushire# Mr. Abdul Hamid, P.W .D.Uupervisor, Care of Political Agent, - Memoaandum # Bank Draft Kot ?*/ 5 dated ^ 1946, for / Hsj4,600/- is enclosed brewith together with supplier's bills passed for payment. A sum of Rs»2,000/- has been deposited with Political i^gent, Bahrain, to meet your requirements in emergencies# It is requested that you should telegraph your requirements atieast a fbrtnight ahead so that arrangements may be made to send the money to you# In case the draft is delayed due to late arrival of steamer you can utilize the money kept in reserve with the Politica -agent, Bahrain. But as soon as you receive the Imprest from here you should recoup the reserved amount# Bahfaii Secelpf ^• 3 ..^T.Date ^ s iissistant Engineer No: 4/33^ Copy forwarded to the Political ^ent,Bahrain, for Infoxmationi A Draft No i ^ ^-^ed ^ &amp; -1946, for Hs: 2,000/- is enclosed herev/ith# A#G. 3787 (I. lo**J • p&amp;Z D ^SSiStant i , British Consulate General# Co ti*. &gt; (r* J' 1 '*' \*ypi Ibl POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. —- mtfrnw No - 2426-1/37• 4 n '27th July, '46. The undermentioned paper|^^ forwarded to The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulfi Bushire, for favour of disposal Signature— Description — Poetical Agent, Bahrain. List of papers forwarded. papers Letter No. 174 dated the 24th ^' ^ July, 1946, from Mr. Abdul Hameed, P.W.D. Supertisor, Bahrain, to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, through the Political Agents Bahrain. S;8, MCrlPC—S6—1117 (Genl )MEP—(6770/M-679j— 26 -10 -41— 300,000.1A' Copy of telegram No*F/130 dated the 16th August, 1946, from the Assistant Engineer, P„W.D., Bushire, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Following for Supervisor, P.W.D. Begins - Please telegraph quantity of cement locally available with cost per ton also Malabar teak and Burma teak planks and iron bars with cost - ends. Ho. 2710. f Political Agency, Bahrain, The 19th August, 1946. Copy forwarded to the Supervisor, P.W.D. t Bahrain. C. I'- &gt; ' Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain.'hi. Telegram From To No. I | G.T.C. Assistant Engineer, Bashir© Political Agent, Bahrain, E/131 Dated 19th and received 20th August, 1946. Following for Abdul Hamld. Please telegraph tRia Immediately total requirements of cement, paint, distemper, timber etc. required for all Residency work to be done at Bahrain. 1.8.537 — ASSISTANT EKGINEER — No.2723 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. DATED 20TH AUGUST, 1946. Forwarded to the Supervisor, Publ: Department, Bahrain. SDN 4-- . ■ ■ ■© Wo 7/^. ^ ^ tt^JC j fi&lt;zM-&lt;U^y ' 9&gt; n oy ^ rx ^*M€M &lt;x4 /m/* /£&amp;'/ ^ Ca ^ 1 /3- a ^ Mh fcrevyt &amp;Arz^u^u . Aw, £* &amp; &amp; /W ? *9-0^ 'A ■vk ^^&lt;*-0 rVv-Sf ?/-'/, J S I have recently my eye -sight and therefore' as advised by Dr. Steele, I was examined by Dr. storm who has cconk-ndoa the use of spectacles specified in the attached note. I tried to obtain it locally but found that it is not available, Owing to Export restrictions it is difficult for ne to order from India but I understand there will be no objection if lt ^ ordoi , d by you&gt; 1 request you kindly to order it for n* anci j am prepared to bear all oxponsos. Draft submitted for approval. tJi do a^e^JUJ J @ M- -SLio (, oL^ L^u ^ Au^,. ^ ''j 1 /SefV.— /ydiagnosis and told no to ^omo a ; iln at 3.30 s.r:. a-on he .would ^he^k up my vision and ..glasses• Accordingly I vvent to him at that | time and he examined my vision and glasses. After this he told * ' ~ • | me that the operation and treatment oOuid be ■ done here and' if I am j desirous to - ^et it done in India, it is nothin; for him to say but » is upto my officers to give me leave for the same. Then I requested him to ive rne his ooinion in writing in reply to your D.O* letter | and he told me that he would like to'dis-uss the matter with you ; ; ■ personally and hand over all the papers to you. • ; I would like to mention that it is a question of my eyesight on whi-h my future life and service is greatly dependent and in view of some unsu^essful ^ases treated here I am afraid to meet the same fate, ^en-e it is requested that I may very kindly ^ranted -he leave applied for, for treatment in India where I ran have more expert advice and treatment. I would also add that at present x^oxxjcx^xkRxiKxstx^xsa the treatment may take less time and after a few months it might take some more • time. f ; oreov^r it is not in my interest alnne but is in the interest of Govt, service also to jot the-treatment as quick as possible scf as to enable me to attend to my duty more efficiently than I am doing now with my present troubles. As regards some uncompleted items of work mentioned in U.B's. note ( N.P. 26) I have to point out that-these are the items which ^ould not be carried out for want of materils su^h as lire Gauzev Vieling boards; and ^ielins fans etc, Orders for allthese things together with other materials v /ora placed in December 1944 but not a single article except ^ement could be had in time. Though every effort has been and is being made to obtain the above materils but cannot say when we will get them. Therefore the remaining items of work vill not be done for sometime. I-would also say that if some, Y/ood and fittings were not available locally the work should not have been done(upto its present stage. I c-n therefore ^ say that I have done my best with the resources at my disposal. Hen^e Irequest that the ^ase of my leave should not be delayed on this account but as suggested by K.ii. kr. /bdulwahab may be^cailed from Banarabbas to relieve mo. T understand that full instructions, renardinj these changes have been given to the Divisional Accountant 3o by the K.2 A .P . Submitted for consideration and early orders. zi.'y^hrjr a. i i X) ^^^/A-aIX^ / 6 &gt; A £&lt;y V^t-AAA V ' / 33 , ^ ^ yU^A*! o. c^f-j^ A:(s./tj ^ 111 CL &lt;1^J^ ' O/H^c I** S^^csfc^^t yA-^w*. ^ /4- A^-ol^-C . /\ Uii^jL' /^/i y ¥ , ^ ^ Cfy ^ K, ^ * sj^yi/u^ As A/A* Cis^oU l^^Ut^k C^f^j CC&amp;:&lt;jrrc&lt; (_S ~ tt) ^Sr /Li ht^t ; ; , ^7V&lt;-«'. h /e ^'i-' •* A6 • / , tf-J?rf' 9 ^- J ' ^t -cn^ Z 0 /?-, . 36 • m a. ^ ,'■ ^ '• '■ J /ST; ^ U^jLi 37. Report on the progress of the building is submitted, for favour of further disposal. 38 I would like to point out that in the original medical certificate given by Dr. George, it is mentioned that I am suffering from diminishied vision, chronic headache and also deviated nasal septum -gyw for which ho advised for operation. DK Storm in his report has expressed his opinion for the operation only and he has completely ignored the other facts, although he had examined'me for those* too. He has also not returned the certificate of Dr. George. . |I request that the same may please be asked for from him. 39. In case the operation is not considered a matter of urgency the other troubles are surely of.urgent nature. One whose eyesight is failing and has caused chronic headache is liable to suffer from extreme anxiety too. I am rather finding it difficult to pull on with the present drugs 'Aspro and Ephedror 1 which give momentry relief at present and later on might become effectless and harmful. 40. I therefore earnestly request that the leave applied for xa may kindlv be recofn^nded. /A\ c \o ^ Cs~&amp;*r* ' fr d.^ ' L^ L s L^ u.r2U-- ^ .-' v 1—0 rH • ^ nj^i ^~. HjJUst &lt;*~ ^ ^ Mr. Qadri's question of leave was put up to me in Bushire and as he was thinking tiil^rusff excuse so as to get away on leave his case did not receive very sympathetic consideration. For instance, he tried bad eyes, bad nose, his son and what else, _^je ^11# alone knows, to achieve his purpose. He could not possibly Ck**AX- » have been of great assistance to his son^ -it appeared that he had some really urgent matters to attend to in India. It was, therefore, decided that if they were so urgent he might proceed to India at his expense to attend to them. On return from leave he told me that he wanted to see his son before he was sent to England for educational purposes. Mr. Qadri returned from leave promptly .and because of this I am prepared to forward an application from him for favourable consideration, but first he should submit a fresh application giving the real grounds. r.'P.A. J / 7.11.1945. -13 Rcf . N/V 68 and 69 * I regret, very much 'the impress ion crca'tocl by my many applications but I should submit that in January 1945 I applied for reversion to India and am still awaiting decision onfthat. During the summer months of this year when most of my work was out of doors (, ie. constg. new office bldg.; I suffered from severe eye strain. I got my eyes examined and as recommended by Ur. 3term started using reading glasses but this has not given -^tho required * rel-iaf ^sod am. ^ti^ suffering from bad eye-sight and headache. Later on it has also been diaganosed that i have ***■*' ■ ■ —- got deviated nasal septum'too. Que to ^.bis i had applied forneave bui did not get it. As my bad luck could give me, it is a mere coincidence that'my youngor -^on was tgken seriously ill with typhoid and my elder son was being sent abroad for studies, which meant that there could be no male membGr left to look after my sick son and the family; my wife being already not keeping good health from a long time. This added much to my worries and on receipt of the telegram regarding my son's illness I was compelled to apply for leave on this account and 10 days' ' casual leave was sanctioned. 1 explained my circumstances^to the a .P.A . and availed of this leave. My present application is only in connection with the leave granted to me due to the illness of my son and the other reasons have no bearing on the case. However 1 am submitting a fresh application as desired and would feel very grateful if it is forwarded with strong recommendation. 7o ^^3. , -)n~ k LLL -l- ' US' /,^ o'y 1 A ^ u \ , i li i - ^ L , v . JiZLJi - I - &lt; ^ J2 ~ A ] 731% 76, 71^ In January 194-5, I applied for reversion to my parental department (Central P .7 /.D.) in India, and submitted several subsequent applications but regret to say that I am still waiting for the result. It therefore appears that nothing has so far materialized, although the time elapsed is more than normal during which one could expect a definite decision. I am loosing heavily in the way of promotion in grade due to my absence on deputation to this department. Not only have my Juniors but also those who have worked under me superseded* I am therefore very anxious to be reverted to India forthwith and shall feel very much indebted to you if you would very kindly enquire from Bushire telegraphically as to the present position of the case and would appreciate it if my relief is sent by the first boat. This will enable me to leave for India sometime in the third week of Aril 194 -6. I may add that there is no major work in hand at present and it is the beginning of the Financial Year when my successor will have no difficulty to take over, P.A. L V-TS^A^ tL, L o cSL&gt;\f IL Q-U, . ~ J ■u^JL KJ ^l/ 9 fj tx a A t 4 c&lt;D - 1^ Mr /l ^ Jp</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1028</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1028</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/37 Appointment, Transfer, etc. of the PWD Supervisor attached to the Political Agency, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-01T00:04:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (198 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 195 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1, 1A, 1B; ff. 2, 2A; ff. 93, 93A. The following number is omitted from the foliation sequence: 66. ff. 44-77 also bear an irregular sequence of 'page numbers' in the same position as the main foliation sequence. These either form part of the typescript of documents or have been added in pencil. Many of these numbers have been crossed out. The words 'p' or 'page', written in blue crayon, are often added to the numbers. A second foliation sequence, numbered 1-40, runs through the notes at the rear of the file, between ff. 169-194. This sequence is also written in pencil, and appears in the same position as the main sequence. Most of these numbers have been crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the appointment and service of holders of the post of Public Works Department Supervisor [generally referred to in the papers as PWD Supervisor] of the Political Agency, Bahrain.The papers consist of correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, and related papers.The following topics are covered: appointment and transfer; leave; request for promotion; papers concerning a charge of gross negligence against the Public Works Department Supervisor in the construction of the new Agency, Kuwait, which led to a fire causing 500 rupees' worth of damage, May to July 1937; travel arrangements, expenses, allowance; advances of pay; correspondence concerning service books and last pay certificates; papers concerning a charge against the Public Works Department Supervisor of exceeding sanctioned estimates in building the Indian Assistant's Court at Bahrain, July 1938 to February 1939, with supporting papers dated July 1936 to January 1938; papers relating to leave on medical and compassionate grounds; papers concerning reimbursement of a sum owed by a deceased Public Works Department Supervisor; pay and allowances; construction of buildings at Bahrain; supply of construction materials; provision of spectacles for the use of the Public Works Department Supervisor, May to June 1945; and handing over note listing books, registers, files, equipment, works done/in hand/outstanding, names of staff who formed the establishment of the Public Works Department Section at Bahrein [Bahrain] and related information, January 1947.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Public Works Department Supervisor</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00024b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>