<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000256_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T06:07:14.034Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher nr marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first b&lt; municated to persons outside British and United States &lt; Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked be in a One Time System. Outward Telegram from Commonwea FII-TANCS &amp; EOOHOMIC DEPARTMENT E. 13828/49 CYPHER(SIMPLEX } 'JO: U. K. HIGH COMMISSIONER RFID. TO: U. K. HIGH COMMISSION! -J» K# j KiiBl! (SENT: 19.50 hours, 2 IMMEDIATE No. 1373 . SECRET . Addressed to U.K. High Commission repeated to U. K. High Commissioner in India U. K. Ambassador, Kabul, r r You will have seen Kinsey f s teleg as X336 of 24th May and X392 of 25th June, , No* 344/3/49 of 14th May regarding air servb 2 * Following on X336 Dunnett telegra; to include Kabul in route schedules of agre&lt; negotiated with Indian and Pakistan Governrm it might be possible to fly a route which wc 4 prohibited by Pakistan Government, He has 1: take no action \ending further instructions, 5* We appreciate long-term balance of favours opening routes between Kabul India a that this did not let in the Czechs and prov commercially feasible to avoid prohibited ar Baluchistan. But we feel that it would be i to make an approach to the Pakistan Governme: airlines should open up the route to Kabul w.&lt; . { \ J This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message and unless it is marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if com municated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex orTypex must be in a One Time System. Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office FINANCE &amp; ECONOMIC DEPARTMENT E,13828/49 CYPHER(SIMPLEX) TO: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN RPTD, TO: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN INDIA U.K. AMBASSADOR, KABUL (SENT: 19.50 hours, 30th June, 1949). IMMEDIATE No.1373 . SECRET . Addressed to U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan No*13?3&gt; repeated to U.K. High Commissioner in India No.2047, and to U.K. Amhassador, Kahul, : f You will have seen Kinsey’s telegrams repeated to you as X336 of 24th May and X392 of 25th June, and also Kabul’s letter No. 344/3/49 of 14th May regarding air services to Kabul. 2. Following on X336 Dunnott telegrajjhed asking permission to include Kabul in route schedules of agreements now being negotiated with Indian and Pakistan Governments, suggesting that it might be possible to fly a route which would avoid areas / prohibited by Pakistan Government. He has been instructed to take no action pending further instructions. 3* We ap reciate long-term balance of political advantage favours opening routes between Kabul India and Pakistan provided that this did not let in the Czechs and provided that it were commercially feasible to avoid prohibited areas of N.W. F.P. and Baluchistan. But we feel that it would be impossible for you now to make an approach to the Pakistan Government suggesting that U.K. airlines should oj^en up the route to Kabul without creating suspicions, /howeverhowever unjustified, that your earlier request to the Pakistanis not to operate it themselves (our telegram 168 of 22nd January and your 250 of l?th February) was insincere and that we were using the anti-communism argument merely to preserve the route for ourselves. Such a suspicion on their part might well produce a less co-operative spirit in future measures against communism which would he disastrous. Moreover the present state of Pakistan- Afghan relations would in any case make the timing of an approach inopportune. if you agree with this assessment of position grateful if you will explain to Dunnett accordingly, giving him necessary background. Also please inform Kinsey (unless this can more conveniently be done by New Delhi who should in that case act accordingly) that he should not himself re-open question with Afghan ambassador, and that if latter raises it again he should reply that while previous views have been tonveyed to U.K. Government it would be best for Afghan Government to deal v/ith our Kabul Ambassador. 5 # A start at Kabul is not at present an urgent commercial requirement for B. O.A.G. If and when question becomes urgent there should be no great difficulty in securing addition of Kabul to schedules even though we might then have to make some small concession in return which could now be avoided. This disadvantage must however be accepted. Furthermore we should not wish by raising this question now to delay conclusion of Air Transport Agreement v/ith Pakistan. Copy to:- C. R. 0. Mr. Rumbold ' Sir W. Jenkin ' Mr, Gordon (3) M. C. A. Mr. G. S. Hill n Reg. Tels. (20) F. 0. Mr. James Murray Copy sent to Foreign Office Cypher Room (for re-transmission to Kabul)Uc Cvoovc tooV&lt;.4.*^ Th/s /s on unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message and unless it is a 4 ^'] v&lt;h~» V.£-u»- marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if commun- j icated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. ^ kA'i'Ul Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex must be in a One vl i v* f v£ ^ivy Time System. _ 0 ' PoCvw Ci Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ALLOTTED TO FINANCE &amp; ECONOMIC DEPAKTtlENT CYPHER (TYPKX) PROM: D: R: IMMEDIATE No. X'%2. • • is bv. £ U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN INDIA. Utf i WvvK NEW DELHI, 17*45 Hours, 24tH May, ie . 4 / 19t08 Hours, 24tH May, 1 949 .^--- — ^ Office h Following for Ministry of Civil Aviation from Dunnett. Kinsey is telegraphing about recent requests made to Him by Afghan Ambassador for a Brit.isH Air Service to Kabul. 2. Question of inclusion of Kabul in schedules to India and Pakistan Agreements) was discussed in London. At that time C.R.O. were of opinion that it would be better to omit Kabul in order tp avoid establishment of route via N.W. Frontier which might at a later date have to be conceded to Afghanistan and so permit possible infiltration by Russians. 3. We consider this danger might be avoided by arranging for service from Kabul to Delhi to be operated on a route avoiding N.W, Frontier. In view of Afghan Ambassador f s request mentioned above and of B.O.A.C. ! s desire to serve Kabul, we suggest Kabul might be included in the Schedules. We should explain to India that °B.O.A.C. would be unable to fly from Kabul to Delhi by the'most direct route. The deviation would • be entirely justifiable on the grounds that the detour would be necessary to avoid the N.W. Frontier. B.O.A.C. would, we understand, be able with Canadairs to fly Kabul to Delhi direct /eveneven with detour, but if necessary, e.g. if Hermes were used, stop could be made at Karachi* 4# Grateful-' if we could be informed urgently whether there is any objection on C*R.O. or other grounds to the above# Copies to:- C.R.O. tt it Sir V/* Jenkin Mr* Fowler* Mr. Belcher.y This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message and unless it is marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if commun icated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex must be in a One Time System. r\ s Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ALLOTTED TO FINANCE &amp; ECONOMIC DEPARTMENT CYPHER (TYPEX) PROM: A/U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN INDIA TO: COMMON WEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE REPTD TO : KABUL U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN D. New Delhi, 20,05 hours, 21+th May 1949 “ 00.45 hours, 26th May 1949 PRIORITY No. X964 Addressed to Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations N 0 .X 964 , repeated to Kabul No.X 14, U.K.High Commissioner in Pakistan No.X336. (C.R.O. please pass Kabul as routine). CIVATT/79 from Kinsey. Afghan Ambassador recently asked me to call on him. He emphasised the wish to the Afghan Government that B.O.A.C. should operate through Afghanistan connecting it in the West with Iran and in the East with India and Pakiotan. 2 # He also mentioned the formation of an Afghan Company with the aid of British capital (A) to provide air communications within Afghanistan (b) to link Afghanistan with Iran, Pakistan and India ^ (c) to develop the aerodromes at Kabul, Kandahar and Herat. 3 # x understood that Pan American Airways were interested in operating through Afghanistan from the Vest and bifurcations at Kabul and operating services Kabul - Delhi and Kabul - China. Najeb Ullah Khan (the present Ambassador in Delhi and then Education Minister) led the Afghan Deputation to the I.C.A.O. Regional Conference at Cairo in 1946 and handed in x actual imormation about the airports and meteorological services in Afghanistan* These /shouldshould he readily available (? for) the reijort of the fact-finding group, 5* The American Mission which visited Afghanistan in 1947 apparently recommended that Kandahar not Kabul should be the main airport used for international services, 6 , The Afghan Government appear anxious to develop the following air routes (l) Teheran - Kabul (2) Kabul - Delhi (3) Kabul - Peshawar - Lahore - Delhi (4) Kandahar - Parah - Herat - Meshed - Teheran (3) Parah - Persian Gulf (to join up with B,0,A.C,, C.W,A, P.A,A. and Air Prance), (6) Kabul - Kandahar - Quetta - Karachi (?) Kabul - Mazar - I - Sharif - Mainana - Herat, ?• The Russians have permission to operate a weekly service from Tashkent to Kabul but only operate fortnightly during the summer season and monthly during the winter. This service, although run by Aeroflot, is virtually a courier service for the Soviet Embassy and is occasionally used by Afghan Government officials and diplomats for visits to Moscow, etc. The Ambassador said that the Afghan Government preferred the Russians to come in by air rather than that they should by road, 8 , The German Lufthansa pre-war used to operate from the West to Kabul, 9# Applications have been received by the Indian Air Transport Licensing Board from Indian companies to operate the following air services, viz (A) Bombay - Ahmedabad - Delhi - Kabul (b) Delhi - Lahore - Kabul, Licences to operate these routes cannot bo granted under the terms of the present agreement with the Government of Pakistan relating to air services, 10* It is known that the Government of Pakistan do not favour any schedulod services flying over the new frontier province which is in fact the prohibited area. The Afghan Government however say that practically the whole of the Afghanistan - Pakistan border is a prohibited area defined by the Government of Pakistan and that (A) this is inconsistent with the spirit of Chicago, and (b) that they would apply to the Government of Pakistan for the privilege to fly /along1 ~ 3 ~ Ql°ng certain corridors to be defined by the Pakistan Government ^ * Ido not know if the Afghan Government has made any official approach in this matter to the British Ambassador at Kabul. Copies to : C.P.O. M.C.A. n Foreign Office Mr.Belcher Mr.Crook Brig.Barker Mr.Gordon Mr.G.S.Hill Beg.tels ( 20 ) Mr.James Murray S.PP.y ^ Q . Foreign Office Cypher Boom for retransmission to Kabul.hw. , fa ^ i cypher message and unless it is (T\ This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message and unless it is marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if com municated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex must be in a One Time System. Outwar d Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office Sm* T FINANCE &amp; ECONOMIC DEPARTMENT ] E', 10560/19^9 CYPHER(TYPEX ) are considering opening a scheduled air service to Kabul, We are not sure that they fully appreciate the consequences of such a course. Firstly, service must inevitably cross strategic territories, and under Chicago Convention Article 9 route would then be open to any other country that has signed the Convention, This would open the route to Czechs or other countries entirely under Russian control but which are parties to the Chicago Convention, Secondly, Pakistan would presumably have to negotiate bilateral agreement with Afghanistan and grant reciprocal rights over the route chosen. According to our information, Afghanistan at present has no civil air organisation, but she might at some • later date accept outside assistance in setting up a service into Pakistan. Russia at present runs a scheduled service into Kabul, and might well furnish aircraft and personnel to enable Afghanistan to take advantage of reciprocal rights granted by Pakistan, Russia would then in effect have a through service to Karachi while Pakistan could fly only into Kabul, 2 * Pakistan Government have already shewn themselves alive to the dangers of such a situation and we feel sure that they would not desire to facilitate a situation arising in which Russian pilots were able to gain experience in flying over strategic country of N.W.frontier, TO: U.K, HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN (SENT: 17*00 hours, 22nd January, 1949) IMMEDIATE No', 168 TOP SECRET We have heard from Kinsey that Pakistan Government We shall shortly be requesting you to ask Gover nt 3.2 of Pakistan to co-oporato in a policy agreed between U.3.A. Government and ourselves for the prevention of penetration by ■ Soviet and satellite airlinos. Similar approach is being mad^o all countries in Europe and Middle East by U.S.A. Government and ourselves jointly, and to Commonwealth countries by U.K. Government but possibility of Pakistan negotiations with Afghans seems to make immediate approach desirable, 4 * We ai&gt;e not sure h °w Kinsey got this information and cannot check with him at the moment. If you arc satisfied that we can disclose our knowledge of it and see no objection we should be glad if you would make a high level approach to the Government of Pakistan and urge them not to open scheduled service to Kabul or negotiations for an air agreement with Afghanistan using arguments in paragraphs 1 and 2 above. if these do not carry conviction you may inform them of impending approach referred to in paragraph 3 and urge thorn at least to abstain from any commitment until it has been received and fully considered. Even if our knowledge of proposed service cannot be referred to you could perhaps inform Pakistan of this impending approach in a way which would warn them of dangers. Copies to : C , R , 0 J (B) Mr.Walsh Atkins H Brig* Barker Mr. Tims Foreign Office Mr.James Murray M.C.A, Mr,I.Lawton Reg. Tels (20)Mr.Rumbold Reference paper 60. You will remember that early this year the Government of Pakistan considered opening a scheduled air service to Kabul. We dissuaded them from this course on the grounds that such action would open the route to signatories of the Chicago Convention, and thus to Russia, via one of the satellites (vide paper 45a)• Now the suggestion is that the B.O.A.C. might operate via Kabul using a route avoiding the North West Frontier Area v/hich is, under Pakistn law, a protected area for civil flying. This does not seem to avoid the danger from Russia, however, even if it were physically possible, or economically practicable. The Foreign Office are preparing a draft reply to 60 - it ties up with the general question of prevention of Russian infiltration along air routes, which is their responsibility. The draft reply will be referred to us for comments, in due course. Mi’. Crook Nos .60 and 58 are wrongly placed on this file which deals with quite different matters. Which Dept, of C.R.O. is handling this - F &amp; E or Defence ? I would be grateful if I could see their papers about it. sd. K. CROCK 8.6.49. Sd. H.A.F.R. 8.6.49. Spoke to Gordon again. F. 0. are still holding this up. Sd. K. CROOK B.U. in 7 days to Mr.Rumbold. \Acb Cv v '&amp;occ^t^.6 costas. 5^ Cto.'TCfe-v.v ^e^SVVc/VVo-vi -ov\2x, CCo\J &gt; 'woW\W V'o ^cWto Oa r'cVAtr ^ £*&lt;1 vMk) T-* imi I I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000256_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2060</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000256</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2060</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/91 ‘Civil Aviation in Afghanistan’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-20T23:27:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file. A set of file notes can be found at the back of the file on folio 7. Serial numbers in red ink, which occur throughout the file, refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a small number of telegrams – two addressed to the UK High Commission in Pakistan and two from the UK High Commission in India. They are concerned with tentative proposals for civil aviation services to Afghanistan, and in particular the necessity of avoiding flights over the North West Frontier of Pakistan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>North-West Frontier Province</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000256#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>