<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00022e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T08:38:03.327Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">kl Telegram Code •'roia Political Kuwait To Resident Bushire Repeated High Coiaraissioner for 'Iraq, Baghdad Basra and Glubb. Ho,318 Dated 2nd (receiTed 3rd)May 1929. Ibn Maahur of Ani&amp;ah who has 'been causing trouble in Jauf « Linah direction etc. wishes to oamp at Subaihiyah. The sheikh has replied that he Kiill not he welcomed. ne is said to have ahout 800 men. - POLITICAL - o 1 ^ h kjf y\ - 11 i j^elegraja Uode Resident isusliire To Political Bahrein Jiio.400 Dated 4th Ma^ r 1929. Kuwait reports execution of Dhaidan and consequent defeat and death of jfahad 'bin jrilluwi at Rudainiyah near £&gt;arar. Murrah have joined Ajman v&amp;io are talking of marching on nasa. Please verify and report x true situation as far as possible. 4 4 - RESIDENTleleKrag P. 3 From- Political Agent, Bahrain. To. Political Besident, Busbire. d) No. 66. Dated the 4th (reed 5th) May 1929. 1 It is reported that Dhaidam al Eithlain with Ajman Chiefs went to confer with 'bin Jiluwi thrown(?) into chains and were killed after 'being attacked 'by Ajman trihes. In this connection please refer to para 110 of Force Suminary No 16 dated the 19th April. Above repeated to High Oommissioner, Baghdad under No 329 dated the 5th May 1929(2) Telegram Code From Political Kuwait To Kesident isushire Repeated by wireless to High Commissioner for 'Iraq. Aviation, Administrative inspector and Special Basra, Howes Hasiriyah and Glubb. iro.sas Dated the 4th (received 5th) May 1929. By 3Jo»318. Hews has just reached here that I'bn Mashhur who had already reached Subaihayah has received safe conduct from I'bn Saud who has not yet left Hedjas. on condition that he comes in to him at once. He is said to be laaiag for Qasim via Jahraiu Ibn Saud* s messenger referred to above passed by Jaryah where news had Just arrived of a fight between AJman and Pahd bin Jiluwi at Rudainiyah 7 miles a .s«w, of Sarar which resulted in death of both J^ahd and Dhaidan* According to a man who was present in battle and is well known here Dhaidan fiirst visited jrahd and was received with honour and dismissed with suitable presents. Fahd then summoned him again and arrested him on his a, arrival. Dhaidan and said AJman would never tolerate his arrest and would certainly attack jahd if he did not release him but ffahd replied if they did he would have him executed at once* jtfaif al Hithlain Abdul id lab who was with Pahd sent wond to tribe of what had happened to Fahd and Ajman attacked jmhd' s camp that night, j-ahd kept his word and had Dhaidan killed but was killed almost immediately afterwards the Haaa was completely ^ .outed and over 1,000 are said to have heen killed, she ^ S 11378 j0ined ^ ^ talking of marching on Hasa but it is thought unlikely that tHey will. There was great excitement over news in Jaryah. POLITICALI'elegrgm Code 3?rom Political Kuwait To Hesident Bushire Ho* 523* Dated 4th (received Sth) May 1929. Repeated by wireless to Higlicoma, liaglidad, Aviation, Administrative inspector and special Basra Howes, JNasiriyah and Glubb* My No *32^ Ibn Mashiiur arriving Jahrah today* Sheildi thinks as they have now Ibn Saud^ safe conduct they will not cause any trouble but suggests in the interests of peg.ce it would as well as for ourselves that armoured cars and aeroplanes do not approach too close to them as they are very wild people and might misunderstand the object. Addressed as my .No*322* - POLITICAL - P/2 # *** 4 4 «fXelegranx Code fxom Political Kuwait Resident J3ushire Repeated by wireless to High Gomoiissioner for ^raq., Aviation JBaghdad, Admini strati Ye inspec tor and Special Basrah and Glubb. Ho* 324. Bated thr 5th (received 6th) May 1929* . My iio.322» *an of Hashaidah just arrived from Jaryah confirms news of battle but says took place Uwainah a mile further south# According to him Dhaidan went in to i'ahd with 8 horsemen and was well received and told he had nothing to fear. ne and his party then were having coffee with jrahd»s brother nasir and he was arrested on returning to JTahd 1 s tent. two of his party escaped and took word to tribe* rarty of 160 Ajman on 80 camels started off at once and attacked by night. jfahd had Dhaidan killed and was himself killed in fight. Hasa casualties heavy but with exceo- tion of a few isani Maji. were all amongst townsmen as all other Bedouin fled immediately. Abul Kilab and his party were camping some distance but Joined other Ajman afterwards and he has been recognised as paramount^Sheikh It is said letter from Ibn Saud was found on Jfahd's body ib t0 o^osed feCt that ** he had im P risoned leading ildnnan who had^hira and that he expected him to do the same with ibn Hithlain, ibn Shu^air, 1'uqm etc. Great excitement and indignation prevails among ikhwan and are planning big raid to south, - POLITICAL - p &lt;• M li? ^ rSectet 7 Uo. 152-S. of 1929. British Residency and ConsulaJfCTGenraal, Bushire, 6t)i May 1929. A ^opy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for info asm ti on« By Order, kfL. VMrX*.— Captain, for Secretary to the Political Kesident fL*. in the Persian Gulf. Extract from the Report of the Southern Desert Administration for the month of March 19 29. (Received with High Commissioner, Baghdad Ho. S.O, 909, dated 2'6fd April 1929).Confidentialc No. 153-3. of 1929. British Hesidency and Consulate-Generally Bushire, the 6th May 1929. A copy of the underraentioned paper is forwarded to the Politioal Agent at Kuwait for information and coMnents. By Order, Gapt. f for Secretary to the Political Resident List of Peper s. Extract from the Report of the Southern Desert Administration for the month of March, 1929, regarding relations ^fith Kuwait.61/14 882-7/5/29 'i'elegram code iJ'rom Political iuiwait To resident ±5ushire Hepeated nigh Coimnissioner for •Iraq. JBl O a, 3 &lt;. S Dated the 6th (reaeived 7th) May 1929♦ Reference telegram No. 158 from iiigh Commissioner for 'Iraq* The Sheikh certainly thinks Ibn mashhur has received safe conduct from ibn baud and it seems to be the general opinion that he has. In any case, as stated in my jsio .327, the bheikh has gone to oahrah to see him today, jionday, and has promised to let me laiow the result of the interview on his return. - POLITICAL -- /V- ^ 6i -/-i- 4 885-7/5/29 (2) I'elegram Code 5rom Political Kuwait Kesident iiushire Repeated by wireless to High Commissioner for 'Iraq and Aviation, Baghdad, Admiaistrative Inspector, i5asra and cilubb. Uo.327 Dated the 6th (received 7th) May 1929. My JSo.324. Ibn Baud's agent JMafisi has receiTed 2 messages from Abdullah bin Jiluv/i telegraphed on (date omitted) from Bahrein. First one dated 4th mey merely says Jahd has killed iJhaidan A1 hithlain. second dated 5th asks for information as to the whereabouts of Ajman and also of xbn Jiashhur adding that Ajman reported to have moved north. ^rnree Dhafir^ one v/ounded^of unknown reliability arrived Malh state they were with Jahd when Dnaidan was arrested but were dismissed immediately afterwards and camped for the night a short distance away. About sunset they heard volley of 5 rounds follow ed by 2 odd rounds which may have been uhaidan's execution. It was several hours after this that Ajman attacked tahd's camp. these men have not yet come to Kuwait. Ibn aashur still at Jahrah and it is not known when he moves on# sheikh is going out there this morning. - POLITICAL-TeiCfcTKE P . 61/14. ^'rois. Political Agent, Kuwait* To» Political Resident, Bushire, Ko, 330» Dated 6th (reed 7th) M%' 1929* Reliability or source or report 'whieh. he refers to has not 'been stated by High Commissioner but I presume report was from Glubb who,as you know,, is hardly unbiassed where Sheikh of Kuwait is concerned# Above refers to my immediateiy preceeding telegram • V */V^5* /v r / 6i /14 898-8/5/29 s/ v/ xelegram uode STom Political Kuwait To Resident Busiiire Repeated nigh Gornmlssioner for 'Iraq &gt; Basrah and Qlubb. Ho.331. Dated the 7tii (received Sth) may 1929. yt&gt; *' y f lyiy 329. The oheilch of Kuwait interviewed Ibn Mashhur at Jahrali yesterday Monday, ne assurred him that he had received safe conduct from Ibn baud and had sent messenger on ahead to learn as he had been told he could. fhe aheilch told him that in any ease he could not agree to his remaining and that he must go. He gave him until Wednesday and he is going to move then, ibn mashhur complained to him that nine of his camels hadat been stolen from there and that their track lead to 'Iraq tribe and asked him to try and re- coveritheni for him. the »heikh said, that all he could W do was to ask me to have matter brought to the notice C\, t of the 'Iraq, authorities, agreed to do this. : Iy W? A telegram Code ^ ora * oil tic al numi t Kesident Bushire Kepeated High Coinmissioner for 'iraq^. Aviation Administrative Inspector and special Basra and Glubb. ITo*332. Dated 7th (received 8th) May i929» A'' My 327. Man of AJman in SheiMi 1 s employ who h^d 'been to Sarar on private business has returned# He says he arrived there just after itfiaidan had left to visit BahcL bin Jilluwi who had given him safe conduct. Apparently he was Taell received at first and ^iven coffee etc., and not arrested until evening. Two of his party escaped and took news to tribe who had feared treachery all along, un their way they heard volley which they thought was Dliaidan*s execution but thi was not so. J'orce of 250 men plus 35 horsemen started off for Uwainah and attacked JUhd*s camp. This was apparently on the night of 30th April / 1st May. when I'ahd saw fight was lost he went with his personal follow ing to tent in which Dhaidan was^Lying and had hirr\ shot. Then as he was mounting his mare a boy of Ajman seized bridle and shot him. AJman lost 30 killed including Dhaidan and their opponents' killed were said to be 600. .Nearly all of the latter were townsmen as no Hedouins took part except Hani Hajir the next morning. Ajman at first thought of raiding to south but decided not to and are now moving north probably to Shadah in mjd- Kuwait neutral Zone or possibly to Bubaihayah. POLITICAL -Tele g ram je» /i From. Political Agent 4 To# Political Resident, i?ushire# «o» 71* Dated and reod 8th Hay 19 29* Execution of Bhaidan and Ms party 'by jfahad confir- med» When Ajmani tri'be were attacked 'by jrahad isBSBteato ^.is Ajnanii head.ed hy jsaif al Hithlain treacherously murdered him He was killed and his force suffered heavily* It is said that Ajman marched into Kuwait direct# if Abovdrefers to your telegrami lio 400 dated the |®th May 1929* Above repeated to Foliticiai Resident in Camp under No 421 dated the8th May 1929# ur6i/i4 Telegram Code Prom nigh Commissioner for 'Iraq, Baghdad Resident Bushire To Fo. Mil Dated and received th 9th May 1929. Zfe cC ctS IMPORTART* Acting Minister for foreign Affairs telephoned me this morfiiing from Mecca and said he had 'been charged to convey following message from Ihn £&gt;aud. Begins » We understand band of our subjects fleeing from our punitive expedition intend to move towards , iraq^ They have chosen as their base Sobahia and frontier zone north of nasa and near iiuwait territory moving northwards towards Kuwait. We understand moreover that they are will, ^.ng to commit hostile acts on •iraci and in frontier zone. They are being pursued by our punitive force and we are afraid they will eventually be compelled to commit in 'Iraq acts which we disapprove. We therefore request His Majesty's Crovernment to taice steps to resist them so that any atosxte further trouble on frontier may be avoided w JSnds. message did not mean to imply His Majesty gave his consent under article 6 Bahra Agreement to crossing of frontier. Minister of jore^gn Affairs stated he would confirm message in writing to reach me tomorrow. Minister of J'oreign Affairs said this HIGHCOMA - Repeated to Political Resident, Muscat under no.428 datea the 9th May 1929.From, Commissioner, Baghdad^ TTo. Secretary of State for Colonje s»Mo 182* Repeated to Political Resident j Bus hire, political A^ent, Kuwait and Jeddah JNo 46/S and reed Dated/9th May 1929. ♦ Important» Bin Saud has already 'been infoimed that the Government of Iraq intend to refuse asylum to Alchwan rehels # Recent developments which 1 have reported in my telegrams 163 and 181 indicate that Aldiwan rehel refugees are more likely to malce for Kuv/ait territory aa Bin Mashhur has done already# Action by Bojial Air Force here to expel them fmm Kuwait territoiy will of course not he taken except Persian Gulf# at SJteikh of Kuwait *3 re quest* approved hy the Resident/ Such request would he welcomed hy me as action in Kuwait territory could seem only possible ma ana of recovering any of Iraq loot which may still he in possession of Bin Mashhur and others# Foregoing refers 71(55 to F*0») which has he en repeated Resident Persian Gulf \ / Ye leg;r am P« FrGm» Po lit ic al Bushire lo. Political Resident (Muscat)» lTo» 426 ♦ Dated the 10th May 1929 - Following from High Gommissioner,Baghdad 46/s May 9t h Be£lns Bin Saud X X Kuwait 'Ends Political Kuwait has been instructed to telegrapgh his comments to you direct and to repe atsui here * PC owvATelegram High Commissioner^ Bgghdad^ To* Kilitical Resident J 15usiiire^ MO. 47/3. Dated and reed 8tli May 1929# For your infarmation 1 have repeated in my unnuiiaTDered code message of today text of Jeddah^s telegram Ko 5 ited 8th May to foreign Office* Above repeated to Political Resident in Camp under No 427,dated the 10th May 19 29*h K ^/ s /m Code Political Kuwait Resident iSusliire High Commissioner for •iraa, Baghdad Basrah and Glubb. Dated and received the 9th may 1929. A'' My no»33i. The Sheikh informs me at ibn Ifeshhur 1 request for permission to stay longer at Jahrah for the sake of being unfit to travel, he agreed to his remaining there until today, Thursday, but made it clear that he must go then. telegram From To Repeated Uo.336 - POLITICAL iiL. r *** y ' ^5 C^crCn^Telegra m JP» iPr um» Polit ical Agent, Kuwait» To» Political Resident, Bushire^ Ho* 337 # Dated 9tli (reed 10th) Ma^ 1929 # Above refers to my telegrams 294 and 332|. ua.*' Repeated to Political ReaMent in Can p under No 430 dated the 10th May 1929 ^ There are indications that Subaihiyeh Bin is objective of Ajmans and they will probably arrive there today if this is the case. It has definitely been stated by the Sheikh that he will order them to leave his territory if they de enter and will not allow^' them to purchase supplies in Kuwait on any account* If you could arrange for sloop to be kept ready to come here at short notice during next few days in case of necessity I think it might be we&amp;U 1 rc — ^t-%1 ^ ' CifCvUAAy — ' |Telegram F # From* Hic-h Commissioner, J5sg;Mg^ # To, Folitiical Hesident, J?usiiire # ITo» Hil # &amp; reou Dated/the 10th Mag* 1929 # Impo rt ant fc Secretary of Stat© telagrapha as fellows Begins 22£gJ^b ITol54^ I skall 'be glad to receive your observations at n early date on telegrams dated the v-i * 7th May Hos 52,53 and 54 from Jeddaii regpurding request of Ibn Saud for assistance against Ajmn t which telegraim Jeddah had been instructed to repeat to you* Please repeat to Bus hire (all ? ) telegrams from Jeddah. and request Resident to furnish me as soon as possible with his observation EndsTeJo-egr am P# From* High Cominiss ioner^ JBagMad# Resident, Bus hire To» Political Ag&amp;ntat. ^ ^ ^ No# Hil» Dat ed and read ICth May 1929# Mpert ant» 'Following is Foreign Office telegram 46 to Jeddaii repeated Baghdad and Govt, of India m 156 TV liA Begins Keference your tele grains wos Si3 and 54# Decision has not yet been reached 'but matter is under active and (separate ? ) eonsideration # British trocp^ ship cannot,in any case^ 'be made available# Sndeavour in the meanwhile to ascertain precise nature of arrangements «hich Ibn Saud proposes for taking de livery of the arms and ammunition* at Uqair* J^r small boats only anchorage there is accessible and there ©an be no question of landing arms or men at Bahrain® Would delivery of arms and ammunition at Jeddaii as an- alternative be in any way helpful or practicable. All telegrams on this subject should be repeated to Baghdad who in turn v/ill repeat to India and Bushire» f C, fa /I itJPI 'PYom* High Commissioner, Baghdad* To » Politi cal Resident, Bus hire # KP,* irii # and reed Dated/ the 10th May 19?. 9^ Important^ Following telegram 72 received from Jeddah* 'My telegram 5 2 j to foreign Office urgent is repeated as follows Be^inss ThiB morning Bin Saud arrived Jeddah. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs ' X XKX Habe^h meet His MaLjesty i on his return he saw me and stated that owing to Bin Hithlain^s death King anticipated trouble with Ajmanu He accordingXy wished to despatch immediately a force to Hasa hut v/as confron'ted with fact that he had. dispersed troppa recently assembled in JHejd and that he had transport difficulties♦ ^ c. ^ ^ ^ J A v - 4 &gt; sSeXeEraun H Prom* Hi^h Commissioner^ Baghdad♦ To, Political Residentj Busliire* Bo^ lfil» Bated and reed lOth May 1929n T^porta rst &gt; k Jeddah t s telegram: m 53 to foreign Office is as / follows Begins My telegram m 52* King desired to approcak Eis Majesty's Government with following requests Cl) that His Majesty's Government would place at his ,. _ ^ (imrne d iat elv ?) disposal a troopship in order to transport/lOQO men whom he had in Hedjaa from Jeddah to Uqaii^ and that the troop ship should he available for any further similar employme nt| (2) that its might he supplied vdth 3000 iee Knfield rifles (new if poesihle with rmgaines taking 10 rounds) also 3000 ■boxes ammunition ( 1000 rounds per hox). His Majesty oonsiderid that too much delay would he entailed were the Bhip^, arras and ammunition Ut he seit from England. He accordingly requested that they might he despatched from nearest available yn-rt place e.g. Iraq,, India or Aden. On arrival of men at Qqair the arms and araraunition should a. Iso he there. If it were not possible to make avalIMiienow all the arms and ammunition what amount could he have immediately and when could the consign ment he landed at Uqair ? When would balance arrive in that case#?Telegr am High Commissioner, J3a^hdadi. # To* Political Resident, Bushire nil # Dated and reed the ICth May 1929» Impo rta nti, Jed dak telegraphs as ^ollcavs to Foreign Office No 54 3egtoG_ mffister for Foreign Affairs was told fey me that 1 eonsidered it unlikely for a British troopship to he (available ?) in Jeddah vicinity, A numher of British pilgrim ships are of course lying idle in harbour, fhoy will not he required until after Haj and for the purpose in view they are suitable, minister for .foreign Affairs informed me that he quite understood that for services now desired payment was necessary, I gather however that they desire to keep cost as low as possihli and think that it would he cheaper to have a British troop ship, than a pilgrim ship, i was also inforiissd by Minister for Foreign Affairs that a reply at the earliest possible moment was desired by the King ; Minister pressed me to obtain a decision at van early date# U /Telflgraia F » 6/A- / From* High CoirnniEisionerj Baghdad » To # Polit ic al Ke s id ent j Busiiire » HOf. Wil» Bated and reed 10th May 1929* Import ant « following is Colonial Office tele^r^m Ho .'fv&gt; Segins Reference my telegram &lt;^o 154 dat ed May 9th# X^bn* Saud f s; request has 'been diseased her^Z. and unless you or the Govt# of India imi£tijis.Kx±ksxsL see iarano serious objection it is considered desirable it » Tkere is however ho question of supply to Ibn Saud of/arms or ammunition from Iraq and as will be observed from telegrams from Foreign Office to Jeddah which are being repeated to you supply of British troop ship has been ruled out also# Flease repeat for information of Mrtrkxxs. (Resident ?} Bushire this and any further telegrams on this subject from Jeddah# eitherTelegram High Conimiaaioner, Baghdad* To» Secretary of State for Colonies Ho ISB^rect ated Bushire, Jeddaii and India Ko 49/s Dated and Reed 10th May 1929 ^ 0 . Important# (offer ?) I have no ohjection/to Ibn Saud T s specific request* I agree that we shauldl,in principle, do everything possihle:^ to assist him to reassert his authority t and pacify frontier district*. In (response ?) to Ihn Saud t s request forces in Iraq are (ready ?) to cooperate 'by dealing with any rehel- lious Hejdi tribes who may seek to enter iraq^tn this connection please refer to my telegrams 182 May 9thj(46/s to JSushire and Jeddah/, Action so far in Kuwait is confined 5rc protection with Sheikh's specific permission of all tribes grassing in his territory# If a similar request is made by Ibn Sauci as regards Kuwait where Mashhur and some of Ajman rebels have taken refuge already with large quant it ie^f loot from Dahaimshah and other Iraq shepard tribes^ 1 con~ sider that we should comply by affording such assistae ce as may be desired by Sheikh of Kuwait with Political Resident♦s concurrence * I hope that a reminder as regards the large quantities of loot taken from Iraq tribes by his recalcitrant Chiefs which is due for restitution ssms. will accompany amy promise of assistance to Ibn Saud* /^Jbove fefers to your telegram dated'the 9th May Ho 157* I u V 0 &gt; ^ V| f ^ ^■ J (t'h p . ( (p&gt; Reference to previous correspondence Secretary of State's High Commissioner's Downing Street, 19 Sir, -J— I have the honour to transmit to you, the papers noted below on the subject of CC b . I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. I J The High Cvnimixoiomr «jc~ Date. Description. c . (Cj £La^~X*Ji, tfc JKyt CZx/**^* h &gt; \ (E2432) Wt 1756B/2045 5.000 5/28 11 &amp; SP Go IIS6i /i4 929-11/5/29 Telegram uode ^ 1rom Political Kuwait 'i' 0 Resident jaushire Bo.338 Dated iOth (received iith) Ma^ 1929. Message . no.hk /236 of 9th May begins '♦Caravan from shajiimar at jaashuk states A1 Jirm left Ajibba with force to meet Ibn Saud and Ibn musaad at isashuk before caravan Jieft on 2nd May. ibn Musaad w^s in vicinity of iJashuk with force when they left Dhafir fighting men from neutral area summoned to Ibn Saud's standard, ubjective believed ibn mashur and Ajman and force expected to move to Al Hafar. Local opinion consider attack probable anytime after 12th May 11 ends. - political - *** w 'SyrFrom. Political Agent, Kuwait, T 1 TO Political Resident (Henjaw) repsated Political Buahire• Ho, 340, Dated 10th (reed 11th) I&amp;y 19S9, «f 1H ' V v vV^' |V^v r^ \A/ V Mich as he would like to ; Sheikh says he cannot obtain restitution^ As raids were in l^ejd and Ibn Mashur has obtained or at an3? rafc e applied for safe conduct from Bin Saud he thinks he has % taken only action at which Bin Saud cannot com plain in ordering him to leave Kuwait territo2y # with what animals he has (a^though points are not mentioned by him,Bin Saudis claim to Hahamishah should be remembered)» Above refers to Baghdad^ telegram Mo 164, U'l P C t /iyisy^A.' &amp; y6i/i4 930-11/5/29 Telegram J 'rom To ■Repeated Code Political Kuwait •'•e si dent Busiiire nigh Commissi oner for f iraq, Baghdad Administrative Inspector, uasrah and CJlubb# Jio.341 Dated iOtii (received lith.) May 1929. Sheikh of Kuwait has received letter from Ibn Jilluwi via Bahrein telling him about the death of Dhaidan and rahd and asking him not to allow Ajman to purchase supplies in Kuwait. He has replied that he will not allow. Reported that qusaibiBahrein has re ceived telegram from ^usaib: madinah to the effect that ibn Saud has arrived zX in Hedjaz. - Political *** 7/ltK 9^ ^ • r ^ - 'A'TeXerrraip _3P ? . Political Asent,Kuwait A To# Political Resident (Hen To# Political Resident (Henjam} repeated Political. Bushite • Ko» 339* Dated 10th and reed 11th M%- 1929 ♦ If Ajman come to Kuwait territory and do not leave wken ordered to do so or if ibn Maslihur has not crossed the frontier 'by specified date (he should do so 'by 14th May) I think it is protatle that Sheikh will ask for joutaiitaiaB aesistance, I think we should agree if and when he does ask» Abovey refers to BaghdadTelegram P # ^ora. Political Eushire (yS) To« Political Resident^(Muscat;» No. 435* Dated the 11th May 1929, Imrned late » High Commissioner BeXow is a summary of several long telegrans whiciy' Baghdad repeated in Cypher not with you:- LiT) jp*^ (1) Telegrams-Z^S^SS and 54 from Jeddah to foreign Offiee# As a result of Bin Hithlain's death Bin Saud sinticipates that serious trouble will be created by Ajman at Hasa ; as he is confronted with transport difficulties and troops at Nejd have dispersed he asks whether British troopship for conveying 1000 men to Oqair could be made available* Pilgrim ships were suggested by Agent at Jedda}i„ Bin Saud also asks whether His Majesty's Government could supply at Oqair 3000 rifles and 1000 boxes of ammunition from nearest available port e*2» Iraq,India or Aden before arrival of men® What could he have at once if all were not available immediately and when could they be landed at Oqair* When could remainder be expected ? (2) Colohial Office telegram to High Commissi oner, Baghdad 154, High Commissioner has been requested by Colonic. Office to ask Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to furnish Colonial Office with his observations on te3e srams 52 &gt; 53 and 54 from Jeddah as soon as possible* (3) Colonial Office to High Commissi oner,Baghdad wo 156, Jeddah informed that troopship cannot be made available and that troops may not land at Bahrain• To ascertain further precise arrangements which Bin Saud is making for taking delivery jck fltpiJbcKiof arms and ammunition at Oqai' where anchorage is only accessible for small boats, and to suggest delivery at Jeddaiu 4, 3^ (4) Colonial Office to High Co mmi s s ioner, Baghdad no 157. His Majesty's Government desire to render assistance but it is out of the question to supply arms and ammunition fro »v Iraq. (5). High Goramissionet n to Colonial Uffice Ho That we must afford all assistance to Bin Saud is agreed to by Hi^h Goinmissioner who also says that Iraq is prepared to repel all recalcitrant tribes who attemtpt to enter Iraq* Figh Commissioner considera that if Sheikh of Kuwait desires our support and Political Resident agrees we should actively do so» Govt* of India (6) / In their telegram *lo 1647/3 to Political Resident Stim!MimEri.xj3uex2.ndxx # and with reference to telegraais above quoted r have aatoid for the comments of Political Resident by telegraph. I 1Bi/14 936-11/5/29 ^4 (3 Telegram Code J'rom Political Kuwait To 'e si dent iiushire Repeated nigh Oommissioner for , iraq &gt; , Baghdad Administrative inspector, uasra and ulubb Xio.342 liated and received the 11th *ay 1929. Zilfi men of unJaiown reliability who left Zilfi on 28th April report that ibn Saud was then at Buraidah. His son Saud with a large force was between Burai&amp;ah and Zilfi and his brother Abdullah with another force near Ghatghat. At Hafar on 7th may they met messenger sent by ibn MUsaad to ascertain whereabouts of Ibn Mashhur. - POLITICAL -6i/l4 949-12/5/29 Telegram Code Prom Political Kuwait To Ke si dent Bu shire JSo. 343 Dated and received the ilth Mbv 1929. Message .No.HK/242 dated 11th May from Serial ICiwait to Aviation etc 0 begins:- M Agent from JSieutral area reports heard Ibn Saud abandoned intention to proceed to Medjaa and returned from Majma to JBuraidoh on receipt of news by car from Ibn Musad of latter^ defeat ibn Mashur in Haziul. ibn Masud # s messenger reached Ibn Suwait at Uqubba on 4th May ordering Dhafir concentrate with Shammar and Harb at Bashuk. Agent heard ibn sand's intention was to move to A1 hafar'. Ends. - POLITICAL - 05 ^ fA / ' @Telegram P» (g) 'Prom. 'Po litieal Re s ide©t (Mus? cat) , To» High Cor-unissioner, Baghdad,repeated Secretsn'y of State for Colonies,.Political Ku^a it A^ent and Political Eusliire» ITo. B/ie» Dated 11th (reed 12th) Mefir 1929 # I agree that action hy R # A»F* to (expel ?} rebels from Kuwait territoiy should he taken if Sheikh applies for assistance which he prohahly will do should Ajman enter his territory and refuse to leave when ordered or if Ihn Mashur lias not crossed frontier hy specified date May 14th- Above is with reference to Baghdad*8 telegram Ho 4^ 182 to Secretary of State fox Colonies)* —O &gt;Telegram P. Prom Political Resident in Gamp, Henjam. To Government of India, foreign &amp; political Department, Simla. (H.M's, Secretary of State for the V Colonies, London, RepeatedV VH.M'B. High Commissioner for Iraq, ^ Baghdad. Ho. 3/22, Dated iEth May 1929. Reference Government of India telegram no. yf) b-30 i647-S| Colonial Office Hos. / i54, 156 and 157; and High Commissioner for Iraq/s Ho. 185. From point of view of Gulf, assistance to Bin Saud is very desirable. if the Government of mdaa will supply ammunition and arms and will send them to qusaibi at Bahrain there will be no difficulty in getting them to Hasa without infringing neutrality of Bahrain. British India mail steamers anchor about three miles from shore and we can arrange that qusaibi, who is Ibn baud T s agent, ta^es delivery outside territorial water/ and ships direct by dhow to Oqair, qatif or Ras Tanur«h as most ooiwanient without landing at Bahrain. This pricedure is already followed in case of Anglo- Persian oil Company's kerosene in order to avoid Bahrain Customs dues so it is not novel, Ras Tanurah has 'deep water close to shore. Goods can reach their destination quicker via Bahrain than by 3F§ddah. I concur with view that we should actively support Kuwait if Shaikh desires. At present I am visiting Trucial Coast but I will be m Bahrain on 14th may and Kuwait on 15th may andjFrom political Resident in Gamp, Henjam. To Political Agent, Kuwait, Mo. x/ZZ. Dated IZth may 1929. jl High COEMiasioner for Iraq considers we snould actively support Shaikh of Kuwait against .wejd rebels if shaikh so desires. i concur, but vail you please wire Shaikh's views direct to me at Henjam. I hope to come Kuwait very shortly to consult you and Shaikh, We are eleven te all told. Can you arrange accommodation for i5th May. - Resident.n Telegram p. prom political Resident in Ga|ip&gt; Men jam To Political Agent, Kuwait. Repeated High CommisBioner for iraq, jiaghdad. Ho. ji/24. Dated 15th May 1929. xy. Bin Saud has requested British assistance in ammunition and arms as he proposes action against Ajman. Colonial uffice think it clearly undesirable that refugees from Hejd should enter or remain in Kuwait territory. iou should therefore invite Shaikh to concur in use of military force of nature and extent which may he determined by us in consultation with Air officer Commanding in order to prevent this, please wire me result of your interviev/ with Shaiich repeating to Hign Commissioner# Has reference to ray telegram j^o - RESIDS1IT •5V Telegram F* * Prom, Commissioner, Baghdad To* ±t&gt;litical Kesident, Bus hire 3.0* Dafe ed and Kecd tlae. IStli May 19?29» Immediate » to my address ^«llo^ing from Colonial Officj^/tfo ±.M 165o Begi ns Reference your telegrams lios 181,182 dated 9tli Ma^/ sak£. and Se 185 of the 10th May* / In view of message contained in tele grain j»o '55/ from Jeddah( Bo 71 to 3/ou) it is clearly undesirable that Bejd refugees should be allov/ed to enter or remain in Kuwait territory# You should therefore approach sheikh of through JPolitical Resident anl invite hi* concurrence to use/ military force extent and nature of whichi should be de~ termined by Air Officer Commanding in consultation with Political Resident with a view to prevent thi&amp; # Ibn Saud should be informed by you through Jeddah as regards the measures that are being adopted to secure this obejet* Please repeat/ to JPolitical Kesident .»Snds (Immediate) Above repeated/to Political Resident in Camp^Ig^^ under Ho 442 datedthe 13th May 1929# pC su^J- \kNo, 344-3. Political-Agency, Kuwait 11 tli May 1 S Cs | fouflBBi lU Pi£0Oiiu3&lt; rp 0 The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Residexfe in the Persian Gulf, ~B U S K I R Em C omments on 'Report of the Sout hern Desert Administr ation' for March 1929*- MSMORAirDPM. ft' Reference your endorsement No.153-0 dated 6th May 1929. I have few comments to offer to the Extract from the Report of the Southern Desert Administration for the month of March 1929, regarding relations with Kuwait, beyond reminding you that the writer is Captain Glubb, and referrfng to my letter No.250-S dated the 29th March 1929* Captain G-lubb certainly has an extensive knowledge of Arabs and Arab customs, but I think he is misinformed in what he says about camels, etc., claimed by an original owner. According to my information the Bedouin Custom is not ! quite so simple as he implies, but depends on various points such as the friendship or otherwise of the tribes concerned, whether the animals were raided, stolen or strayed, et&lt;,etc» When I first heard of these cases from him, I made careful private inquiries from sources by no meand pro-Ibn Subah, and came to the conclusion that the Shaikh was perfectly in the right. Moreover it is hardly consistent with his charac ter that he should set up a law of his own in place of the ordinary custom, as to do so would at least presuppose con siderable strength of mind - and the Shaikh is, unfortunate^ lamentably weak. Q.C , ^ieut.-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait*QOHFIDSNTIAL&gt; No. 345-$. Political Agency, Kuwait. Ilth May 1929. To BUSHn ft- Wo. /y r ^ GGuHDEislTS.i The Secretary to the Hon f, ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R U. Special Service Officer. MEMORANDUM. Reference my memorandum No. 335-S dated 8th I enclose herewith copiers of messages, Noo \ 929 * ^ - and PIK/237 of 9th May, and of HK/242 and HK/24t oS \\$x Uoj, despatched by the Special Service Officer, Kuwait. Flight Lieutenant Howes is leaving Kuwait this ***» afternoon for Nasirfyah, and Captain H. M. Burton, The _ * % ^ - .... - * Norfolk Regiment attached R.A.F., Special Service Officer, Basrah, is going to take over the duties of Special Service Officer, Kuwait, in addition to his other duties. I under stand that he will spend part of his time in Basrah and part in Kuwait. Lieut.-Gdl., Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram En Clair ^rom Howes Kuwait To Aviation Baghdad Repeated GluVb, fecial Basrah and Woolley. !To.IIK/235 Dated the 9th May 19S9. I Ton Mashur ordered by Sheildb. to leave Kuwait territory stopping day at Tawi1 and day at Subaihiyah en route. Did not move yesterday owing difficulty arranging transport for wounded. Shaikh states he will not permit AJman camp in Kuwait territory not allow them trade. Ibn Musailim (Rashaidah) living with Mu air at Jariya brought lette from Ibn Shqair on 3rd May to Sliaikh Kuwait asking to camp in his territory. Sheikh replied would permit tr butrefused allow any Mutair camp in Kuwait territory. AJman and Ibn Mahhur will probably camp lYafrail. *** Telegram End air From Howes Kuwait To Aviation Baghdad Repeated Ulubb, Special. Basrah and Woolley. No.Hl^/237 Dated the 9th May 1929. Ibn Mashur left Jahrah today for TmvilLro C En Glair Howes Kuwait Aviation Baghdad Telegram ^rorn To Ho .HK/S02 Dated the 5th. May 1929, Report that Ihn Mashur and Ar Rufidi have receiyed safe conduct from Ihn Saud appears incorrect. *** En Glair Howes Kuwait Ay i a t i o n Baghdad Gluhb, Special Basrah and Wooley Telegram From To 'Repeated Ho.HK/206 Dated ITil Ihn Mashur's party at Jahrah number 197 men with about 400 looted camels. Fifteen severly wounded with them and thirty were killed in fi^ht with Ibn Shuraini near Bashuk. ITafisi received telegram from Ibn Jilluwi confirming death ibn Hithlain but no mention daath of Fahad Original report of Fahad's death from Ibn Lami (Mutair) who subsequently visited Ibn Subah outside wall of Kuwait• Defeat of Ibn Jilluwi * s force' not yet confirmed. Sheikh says Ibn Mashur got ss£fe conduct from Ibn Saud but this not certain. -*■&amp;* En Glair Howes Kuwait Aviation Baghdad Glubb, Special Basrah and Woolley Telegram From To Repeated Ko'.HK/SO? Undated JMafisi received further telegram from Ibn Jilluwi saying Ajman. fled westwards and asking for their latest location. Local opinion infers from this that Fahad killed otherwise he would be in touch with them and would not need to ask their location. Jilluwi's force said to have zucounter attacked and routec 1 Ajmar after 3.rst battljL, Em Clair Howes Tftkwait Aviation Baghdad GIuTdId , Special Basrah and Wcole^ Tele gram From To Repeated HO.HK/S12 Dated 6th Ma^' 19, r 39. Shaikh states Ihn Mashur despatched yesterday messengers to Ibn Baud ascertain terms of surrender. Meanwhile Sliaikh has ordered Ibn Mashur camp Subaihiyaii His messenger from Ajman confirms previous news of 'battle but states Ajman afraid of Ibn Saud and moving to camp at t W(| Subaihi^ah. En Clair Howes Kuwait Av i at i on Baghdad Glubb, Special Basrah and Woole^r Telegram From To Repeated llo.HV223 Dated the 7th May 1929. Reliable agent reports 70 Ajman and 90 townsmen killed in fight near Sarrar, Ajman expected camp at Subaihiyah about 9th May.u Telegram En Clair From Howes Kuwait To Aviation Baghdad Repeated Glubb, Special Basrah and Woolley Ho.Hk/228 Dated the 0th May 1929. Heport of unknown reliability that Ibn Munaikhir (Suf ran -Ajman) and Ibn Juma (Dha'an-Ajman) wiiose following numbers some 300 tents took no part in battle and are wither neutral or for Ibn Jilluwi. Ha'ga section AJman approximately 200 tents expected camp Wafrah or Subaihiyah 9th May,L iP~f Telegram C. J'rom political Agent, Kuwait. To jfolitical wesident, nenjam. Ho. 348. Dated land receiired ; 13th May 1929. f ^ j i lour telegram no. i5/23. ? See my immediately preceding telegram. Shaikh does not anticipate anything happening in the near future. Jtie does not Relieve the report that J5in Saud f s force is moving up from ^ asxhl , and does not think it possible for a large force to do so at this time of the year except 'by way of nAbA. ne thinks 11m kUSSAD is not at / haili. ajmao have not come notth yet as was feared they would. ne hopes that ilin UAbJliiuK will leave his territory without trouble. Kegarciing your visit to Kuwait, which x welcome --see my imraediately following telegram. - rULiTiCAl..4' Prom High Commissioner, Baghdad. To Political Agent, Bahrein. No. 50/S Dated I3th May, 1929.- Priority. Following for Resident. Reference to Colonial Office telegram repeated to you at Bushire. I suggest that you should discuss with Burnett and with Shaikh of Kuwait how Air Jorce can cooperate against Ibn I^IASHEHUR, if he has not left Kuwait territory by fourteenth or against Ajman should they take refuge in Kuwait. As Mesopotamia has account to settle itfith I (sic) Mashehur of 750 Mesopotamian camels looted and 15 Mesopotamian tribesmen killed, I suggest that action against him might directed if possible to force him to surrender rather than driving him across frontier. Mesopotamian camels could then be recovered and I M handed over to Ibn Saud.51/14 968-14/5/29 © Telegram S'rom To Repeated Ho.347 Dated jL3th (received 14th) May i929» Code Political KuY/ait Hesident Henjam Busiiire, i5aghdad, Basra and Glubb Mutair of unknown reliability who left Artwayah states Dawish now out of danger* Heard ibn Saud had removed his personal standard from Sirr and ca/w r ?) had left for Hedjaa by (word omitted) . Me had asked Dawish to affect ibn Mashhur»s submission and had given him 100 rifles on his pointing out that he was short. Dawish had sent messages to Ibn Mashhur advising him to submit. Mutair now all,^ quiet. With the excep tion of Xbn Rubaian's following the utaibah are still refractory and Xbn Humaid's brother has Joined forces with Abu Lalah in Hedjaz. irejd now quiet and iling's son, Saud, is in Riyadh. From another source Ajman and mairiyah (Rudaif) Yfiiioh may be true as they have/materialised near here so far. - Political - hi. / f/&gt;-xelecram 61/14 Jfroro to Repeated itlitg H.M 's, High Coraraissioner, Baghdad. Ho. 352. JJated (and reeeired / 14th May 1929. His iSxcellency readily agrews to our using military force to prevent najd trilieBiaen, who are in rebellion against ilin saud, froia entering or remaining in Kuwait territory. fie reserves to himself, howeyer, right to decide who are in rebellion; and does not agree to tribes, which have made their jseace with Mn aaud,-- such as the mutaik ) etc., -- teeing prevented from com ing to Kuwait to trade. At jresent he counts ajmat ^ as rebels, ^ut agrees that if iten HAismiUK (whom he IselieTes to lie negotiating with ilsn saud regarding surrender; should try to double back into Kuwait territory after leaving it to-day, it would indicate that he too is one. as a matter of fact the shaikh thinks most im#rol®al»le that there will ^e any develo]*- ments at present time of the year. Ateove refers to your telegram no. J5-24.Telegram (p). Prom Resident, Kuwait. To Hlghooma, Baghdad, Eo, 30-Be Dated 15th May 1929. / , / Important^ Please refer to your telegram No* 50-So The Shaikh does not expect the ^jman to oross his border&gt; but if they do so, he will at onoe inform the Political Agent and he has agreed to grant his f411 periaission to the Royal Air Force to take air action against then* The Shaikh has not yet heard whether Ibn Mashhdr has left Subaihfyah but he expects the return of his messenger at sunsets Shaikh has agreed that air action can be taken if Ibn Mashhdr has not mored by dawn to-morrow morning* I have consulted Air Oommadore who suggests that reconnaissance be sent out at that time, Ibn Mashhur is so close to border that it is impossible to take action to prerent his crossing it. Oommodore will be grateful if this telegram can be shown to the Air Officer Oommanding*(7£) 7i T elegram JP From^ High Gomissioner, Baghdad# To» Politi«al Resident^ Buslaire. TFo » 5 l/S • Bated 16tk (reed i7t]i) M^r 1929* Jeddah*s telegram to foreign Office 61 dated Ma^r IStii and repeated to Baghdad and India under iio 78 is as follows Begins l^r telegram no 60» This morning Ibn Saud sent Minister for Foreign Affairs to Jeddah to enquire as to the position regarding the arms and ammuni- their tion required; (if ?) ijiisxx:/arrival was delayed they would be of no use» The need for them was urgent♦ On lines of yaur telegrams Kos 45 and 46 I endeavoured to reassure Minister for foreign Affairs hut his anxiety couldnot he relieved entirely* Re said that even if 500 rifles machine guns available immediate steps (for despatch *&gt;) . i would be a great help# I was aked by Minister for Foreign I Affairs whether some further information for early •aamunication could not be obtained# (SD) A»A»Russell # 17 *5♦29 w (SD) C»C.J»Barrett« 17«.5*29 «r /&gt; c ,Ju^ /Z61/14 ^ 7 ' 981-18/5/29 © Telegram Code From Political Kuwait To Resident .oushlre Repeated High Commissioner for •Iraq, Baghdad, Basra, nasiriyaJi and Glubb. Jso»550 Dated i7th (received i8th ) May 1929. Kasiriyah message 1.480 of 16th May repeated to you in my . no »558» Advance of large force expected by way of Tusa is considered here to be increasingly improbable as summer advances. According to my information xbn Luwai was murdered and it was his murderer who was executed. - POLITICAL -61/14 982-18/5/29 Telegram Code Prom Political Kuwait To He si dent Busiiire ITo • 358 Dated i7th (received i8th) May i929 Message 1.480 of ISth Hay from Special Uasiriyali begins 'Agent who left umm Arrudliuinmah on 9th May reports Ibn M.uz.yyr then at Shuaibah but his messenger at Umm Arrudhummah and inubbah ordered to rejoin him at Bashuk where Dhafir and Shammar instructed to concentrate for rdding* States J'irm also moving isashuk with |12 standards and messenger said Saud Ibn Saud moving with force to Safah» ibn Muz.yyr despatched sipies to Kuwait to ascertain location of xbn Mashhur and Kufidu. Agent further states Ibn Mashhur killed 90 of ibn Muzyyr»s force in fia2a2i battle and 20 Shammar in battle between Bashuk and Thammee. Reports ibn Luwai publicly bridged sha- ara. ibn Humaid imprisoned at Eiyadh and Dawish still alive® Keport is of unknown reliability*' Ends. - POLITICAL -&amp;) Telegram Code JTom high Cormnissiorier^ Baghdad To resident isushire Repeated Kuwait* ^lo*i76 Dated i7th (received i8th) May 1929• Aeroplane reconnoitred, southern iluwait territory yesterday and reported Subaiyah, Jariyah Tawil and adjacent area deserted. HIGHCCMA -Tgle£ram P * Prom,. Politieal Resident^ Bushire To* Poreign^Siiala lio 454 Repeated Colonial Office 11 and High Commissioner, Baghdad* Dated the 18th May 1929^ Yifevrs contained in m^r telegrara So B/22 are confirmed* All facilities even to the extent of landing arms willingly and ammunition in his islands would/#? granted 'by Sheikh of Bahrain to Bin Sand# I aia strongly opposed however to grant of facilities other than transhipment of arms,ammunition and if necessary men in vicinity of islands 'but beyond territorial limits^ increase We should deprecate any IniStiiRSiss: of liejd influence♦ Any attempt 'by Hejd refugees to enter Sheikh of Kuwait's territory will he communicated at once by him to Political Age at, Kuwait | full permission for British authori ties to take air action against such refugees 1m s also he ecu agreed to hy the Sheikh of Kuwait*. Matter was discussedat meeting in Kuwait at which I and Air Commodore Iraq were present^ Ko appreciable reaction in Muscat or on the Crucial Coast from any aetion His MaJesty^s Government may decide^, to take is anticipated*v\V* [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government. 1 EASTERN (Arabia ). June 19, 1929. CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [E 3115/2322/91] No. 1. Mr. Jakins to Sir Austen Chamberlain.—(Received June 19 ) (No. 114.) 7 HIS Majesty's acting agent and consul at Jeddah presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit to him copy of a letter from the Hejaz Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, dated the 9th May, 1929, acknowledging the message from His Majesty's High Commissioner for Iraq. Jeddah, May 18, 1929. Enclosure in No. 1. Hejaz Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs to the Acting British Agent and Consul, Jeddah. 29.11.1347 (May 9, 1929). 1 HAVE the honour to inform your Excellency that His Majesty, my August Sovereign, has received through His Britannic Majesty's consul in Bahrein (Lieutenant- Colonel Barrett) a message of congratulation from His Britannic Majesty's High Commissioner for Iraq. 1 enclose herewith His Majesty's reply, which I beg you to transmit by the first opportunity to his Excellency :— 'We thank your Excellency for the sympathy expressed in your message, likewise for your wishes to the effect that our recent punitive actions may be the preface to the settlement of the dispute outstanding between us and Iraq in a manner which will guarantee the attainment of the end we have previously and repeatedly pointed out to your Excellency. ' We were particularly pleased with one point mentioned in your Excellency's message that the request of certain of our subjects to the administrative inspector of the southern Bedouins to protect them from our punishment has been rigorously refused, and we are accordingly grateful for such action. ' We have noted also that the Iraq Government will never afford asylum to our subjects who have committed crimes against certain Iraq tribes. But we wish to draw your Excellency's attention to the fact that it is difficult to distinguish between the criminal and the innocent in this matter, and we fear lest anything might happen to cause misunderstanding at the present time or in the future. We are therefore of opinion that the co-operation of the Iraq Government with us would be perfected by their taking measures to prevent the entrance and the stay in Iraq territory of refugees from among our subjects whoever they may be. ' We have informed the British agent at Jeddah of the movements of certain people who, it has been reported to us, may take refuge in Iraq, so that he may communicate with the BritL-h Government to prevent them from entering Iraq and staying there. We shall not fail to forward later any further information about refugees who may be going, in order that they may be watched in a special way.' With highest respects, FUAD HAMZA, Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. [819 t—Ij1 /1 4. 999-21/5/29 Telegram Prom To Repeated Code Political Kuwait Resident Bushire High. Commissioner for 'Iraq^ Baghdad and 'Basrali. No.364 Dated 20th (received 21st) May 19 29. Unconfirmed report has reached here that Ajman have attacked and defeated detachment of Ihn Jiluwi a little way to south of NTA, There is talk of their moving north to Waifra now^ where Ibn Mashhur is at present♦ - POLITICAL - **»■ J - Xo61/14 ?v Tftleisam P. From H.M's • High Coimnissioner for Iraq, Baghdadr i To Political Resident, JSushire. Repeated Political A^^ent, Kuwait. Bo. 56~S. Dated 21st (recei-ved 22nd ) May 5-929. 'Minister for Foreign Affairs has now sent in note objecting; to the presence in Kuwait of if'arhan 33X1:'j 'bin Mashhur and his followers together with some people from G-hatghat* He states that to allow these people, whom Bin Saud seeks to punish, to take refuge in Kuwait only serves to encourage them and others as well* He asks that effective steps will he taken to eject them. n The foregoing telegram dated the 17th May from Jeddah addressed to Foreign Office, Bo. 63, repeated Bgghdad Ho. 81, is repeated for information. Hi £?h Commj s s i one r.I I lyrhif Tele gran Jt 3 . From Political Agent, .Kuwait. To Political Resident, Busliire. Wo. 365. Dated (and received ) 22nd, May 1929. As you are aware, Ibn Maslihur told Sliai-ch. of | Kuwait that Bin Baud had ^iver him cafe conduct, which Ihn Lami had 'brought him. 'Flven so, the Shaikh would mot allow him to remain more than the limited- period and ordered him to he out of his territory 'by a specific date* He crossed the frontier (out of ) on that date (May 14 ) and Shaikh will certainly not allow him to return* People from Ghatghat referred to were with Ihn Mashhur. Foregoing refers to 'Baghdad telegram .No. 56-S, ( lvJ v-'r POLITICAL- Ha^ 1 '«»/ C OITPIBBET lAL . Ho. S.O. /03/ Secretariat of E.E, the High CouaniBsioner for ' Iraq, Baghdad, lb May, 1929, BUSH !P^ RES!DE'rvK 'y. ffsg. No. y ? ^ fate 5' vj . teFIB&amp;[]TML RECORDS. o vJ Sir, Vc (=» V ^ / ^ '3 / I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.l44/S dated the 1st of May, 1929, enclosing a copy of letter Ho # 250/S dated the 29th of March, 1929, from the Political Agent, Kuwait, which had inadvertently been omitted from your letter Eo # 103/S dated the 8th of April, 1929, 2. Before discussing the question of the attitude of the Shaikh of Kuwait in regard to the Akhwan, His Excellency the Acting High Commissioner desires me to refer to the remark made in the second paragraph of your letter dated the 8th of April, 1929, to the effect that the Political Resident would have appreciated being asked for his own views instead of those of one of his subordinate officers. Sir Gilbert Clayton had naturally no intention at any time of asking for the views of a subordinate officer upon any question of principle or fro ^ policy, and he fears that my letter Uo.S.O,673 dated the 21st of March, 1929, may have been misunderstood. The position was this. His Excellency had received from Captain Glubb a report which indicated that the Shaikh of Kuwait*s attitude in respect of the Kajd and 'Iraq tribes respectively was, to say the least of it, unsatisfactory. It appeared to him that if this report was accurate, it would be The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire- 2 - would be necessary to consider measures with s. view to inducing the Shaikh of Kuwait to alter his attitude. But before putting forward any suggestions or recoirrnienda*- tions for the consideration of His Majesty^s Government (subject, of course, to consultation with the Political Resident) he wished to ascertain how far Captain Glubb's account of the state of affairs was correct. He, therefore, asked that he might be furnished with the opinion of the Political Agent at Kuwait, not as to the policy which should be pursued in the matter, but merely as to whether the Shaikh of Kuwait could give a satis factory ansv/er to the accusations levelled at him by Captain Glubb, It appeared obvious that the Political Resident would accept the views of the Political Agent at Kuwait on this matter, and it did not, and still does not, appear to His Excellency that he was taking an unusual course in requesting that, in view of the comparative urgency of the matter, the Political Agent should be authorised to repeat his opinion to him direct. He regrets that this request of his should have given offence, but desires me to point out that had it been found possible to comply with it, he would have received Colonel More's interesting and valuable letter of the 29th March early in April, instead of only on the 8th May, 3. His Excellency, when forwarding Captain Glubb 1 s report, realised that Captain Glubb^s information came from biased sources, and for that very reason was anxious to submit it to the criticism of the Political Resident and the Political Officer Kuwait, He would, in fact, haverV ^P 31 f V^ have preferred not to have forwarded the report in original, but to have sent the gist of it to the Political Resident couched in more moderate language. The report was, however, received in his Secretariat on mail day and as the question was urgent, it was forwarded in original as received. 4. Sir Gilbert Clayton has read with interest Colonel More's letter of the 29th March which sets forth the Shaikh* s position very clearly. At the same time it does not offer a very satisfactory explanation of Ibn Sat uc 11 o attitude in regard to the raid on the Bani Malik, On the 1st of March, Colonel More telegraphed asking for an escort to enable the Bani Malik to rejoin . the 1 Iraq tribes in northern Kuwait territory and stating that, pending a reply, he had asked the Shaikh to let them remain at Kuwait and to make the best possible arrangements for their protection . In view of this request. His Excellency assumed that the Bani Malik would be safe from attack for a short time. It appears, V however, both from Captain GlubVs report and from i; * . ii 'L ^11 v r » Colonel More f s own account of the incident, that the Shaikh made no serious effort to protect the Bani Malik, who were massacred within a few yards of the walls of Kuwait without any attempt being made to render them assistance. The Bani Malik raid is, however, a thing of the past 'and recriminations levelled at the Shaikh of Kuwait are unlikely to lead to any useful result. The point that His Excellency wished to consider was, hov; far the policy which the Shaikh of Kuwait had adoptedadopted in his own interests was inimical to the interests, in 1 Iraq, of His Majesty's Government, ajid whether it was necessary to take steps to induce him to alter that policy. 5, The whole situation has now 'been changed 'by the defeat of the Akhwan by Ibn Sa'ud and by the fact that the Shaikh of Kuwait appears to be taking steps to adopt the policy suggested in the Political Resident's / C ~ telegram of March 26th azid to prevent recalcitrant ^Tajd 'K 1 - ■ \fA VW tribes from taking asylum in Kuwait territory. Y/hether the Shaikh of Kuwait is to be pressed, s,nd perhaps ^ &lt;, assisted by His Majesty's Govei'nment, to adopt a firmer line in his dealings v;ith the Akhwan appears to depend entirely upon the measure of success which attends the efforts, which he is now reported to be making, to keep them out of Kuwait territory. The report that Ibn Mashhur, while in possession of a large amount of loot taken from * Iraq and Hajd tribes, was allowed not only I ^ to encamp in Kuwait territory but actually to occupy \f &lt; (M A Xs c j the famous^Xort .at Jahrah, is disquieting and it appears ^ t u not improbable that the Shaikh's efforts to prevent the 'l ' Ajman from encamping in his territory will be unsuccessful Should Ibn Mashhur and the Ajman remain in Kuwait territory in spite of the reported efforts of Ibn Subah to dislodge them, it appears probable that further Z 14 ' steps will have to be taken, and it is not unlikely /y A * ± &gt;- /( ^ ^7*^ ' that a request for action of some sort may be received cA — from Ibn Sa'ud himself.A copy of this letter is being sent to the Government of India and to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Secretary to H ,E« the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, r t.c.■5 f r iS V * | '• ■ Telegram F. From (xovermnent of India, Foreign and j ^olitical Departroent, Simla. To Po 1 i ti cal Res id.en t., 'Bus}i 1 r Ho. 1727/S. Dated 22nd (received 2 3rd ) May 1929, 'In regard to ilajdi tribesmen taking refuse in Kuwait, 'I agree, reluctantly, to Shaikh's bein w asked to concur in mse of military force, if necessarv if His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies and the Air Ministry considered such a request was still essential on condition that nature and extent of such force should he determined by the Air Officer Commandinr Iraq, in consultation with the Resident in the Persian n -m i f 'British Agent at Jeddah telegraphed on 8th May message from Ihn Hamd requesting that steps should he taken to resist hands of rebels who intended to move towards Iraq. High Commissioner at Baghdad telegraphed view that refugees were more likely to make fr&gt; Kuwait territory. Colonial Office accordingly, with my Qomcnrrence,authorised High Commissioner, on the nth||| Kay, to approach the Shaikh through the Pes:?dent with a request in terms previously agreed upon. M The foregoing is H.M's. Secretary, of State for 11 India's telegram Sated the 18th May, Ho. 1600. - POTT^TGH. tv c + iopy to the P.A's at Bahrain, Kuwait and/ ? O' ^rom E.Mts. Hi^h Commis sioner, Ba^lidad* Po 1itical Resident,Bushire . Ho. 57-S Dated 22nd (received 23rd ) May 1929. Following is telegram Ho. 171, (fated 21st May 1929, from Kis Kajesty's Secretary ofState for the 'Bin Baud's request for assistance against the Aj man. ft Government of India have offered 3,000 rifles with necessary ammunition at total cost «t Port William of appro2:imately 4 -|r lacs of rupees* 2700 of the rifles are magazine Lee-infields available within a week; remainder require repair and would have to follow later. British Agent at Jeddah. has 'been instructed to communicate aea±kx offer to Ihn Saud and also to address latter ^ in the sense of last sentence of your telegram♦ 'Please repeat to Resident, Bushire. 'Has reference to your telegram .No. 185 of May 10th.' Ends. T^ost Copy to the Political Agents at ?^.hraan, Muscat and Kuwait for information.Telegram P » From. Agent, Jeddaii. To» foreign Office No 63,repeated High Ooaimissioner BagMad,Political Agent Kuwait &amp; Political Besident Busfeire* No» 66* Dated 25tli (reed 26tlx) May 1929^ Tkanks kas 'been expressed 'by Itm 3aud for action taken whicbt has led to departure fro® Kuwait of Farhan i'ba Mash.ur# Ito Saud states ttiat this chief is at Wa^ra now (ahout three miles south of Tawil) where he is awaiting some AjBaan^ They may then 'be expected to enter Mesopota mia or send into Kuwait territory or (?) Mesopotamia for supplies. He hopes they will 'be unsuccessful in either atoe^pt^ Ahove refers to ay telegram No 6^tll^, 't COHFIDEMTIAL ) / No, 3S3-S Political Agency, Kuwait, ISth May 1926, /tff ± ^ 1 To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. Heference my memorandum Ho.345-S dated ilth May 1929. Captain H, Burton arrived in Kuwait on the morning, of the i2th May, but left again for Basrah on the 16th. Air Headquarters, Baghdad, have decided that it is no longer necessary to have a Special Service Officer in Kuwait and have accordingly withdrawn the Wirelesa Station thift afternoon. S^e^iitX. Service Officer memorandum.1044. Telegram Code F r om political, Bahrain To Resident, Bushire Ho. 518 ^ Dated 27th. received 28tii May i92.9* Arrivals from Hasa yesterday reported that AJman raided all camels and horses in the vicinity of Hasa belonging to Bin jaluwi# They also reported that aJ- day and night watiahnen have been posted Hasa^and between Riyadh and »Hasa is not dafe # Ajman are still at Sarar. Pew dav s a^o 25 Ajman raiders encountered Bin saud«s Patrol eight of these raiders were killed remainder captured^ political. (L4 v .JL' £« / c. C.O.r 'k.k Confidential. k/t 1TO.D.2026-N. F DENCY. r Sl% tuuHiiuii i i 11L hiGORDS. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Hon^ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information, with reference to the correspondence ending with his telegram L T o.B/22, dated the 12th May 1929. { By order,etc., for Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, SIMLA; lit The May 1929. 1. Telegram from the Secretary of State for India, Ho. 1528, dated the 10th May 1929. 2. Telegram to -ditto- H0.I66I-S, dated the 13th May 1929. 3. Telegram to -ditto- Ho.l655-S, dated the 12th May 1929. 4. Telegram to the Secretary of State for India London, K0.1684-S, dated the 16th May 1929. With 1 spare copy. V : L U J /cu/y 1,1 1&gt;]Confidential flu. &gt;*\tH y - vy liO.F. 157-ii. (li M^rf'ry. R'~. No. Shf 2 erf &lt;7*^ L.uNOEMInL RECORDS. A copy of the undermentioned paper le forwarded to ( ) To the Political Resident ^nly. the Army Department (General Staff Branch ) tne Hon'ble the political Kesident in tne Persian Gulf ^ lor Information, in continuation of the endorsement fran the (Government of India in the) foreign and Political Department ao.D .ii0ii6-ii, dated the 17th May 19^9. By order, etc«, for Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign and Political Bepartnent, Simla| J The ^ May 19id9. Telegram to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India JI0 .1693 -S, dated the 17th May 1929. LTelegram Ptqm * British Agent, Jeddah » f©» Foreign Offtce^London No 69 repeated Govt» of India,Baghdad,Bahrain and Bushire No 88* Dated a8th(recd 30th) May 1929 # Letter Troia Minister for Foreign Affairs confirming order of S700 rifles and 3 million rounds of aMmunition to 'be landed at UQAIB has now heen received 'by me 6 He renews request to he informed as regards date of shipment and approzimate date of their arriTal# He has also enquired what is the total final sum which is due 'by the Hedjaz Governments This morning I was informed on the telephone 'by Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs that situation not now appear to wairrant despatch of troops to Hasa; this proposal,therefore,has 'been abandoned^ Ahove refers to my telegram No 67 repeated under 85* /P C -fa hTelegram IL Foreign, Simla. la Secretary ot State for India, Agent at Jeddati, Political Resident, Busfcire,Political Agent, Bahrain and Government of Boiabay# 1803/S Dated 29th. (reed 30th ) May 1929» Foil©wing telegram received from KEALEEL, Bombay,May S7tb. Begins My leddah Agent offers to charter on 'behalf of Hedjaz Government steamer w Ara^estan flying British flag to carry 1000 soldiers from Jeddah to Ulceir near Bahrain# Have you any ohjeotion t© my accepting charter Ends Following from Morrison*3 Bombay dated May E8tlu Begins Have received enquiry from Eedjaa Government through our Jeddah Agents for steamer for conveyance of armed soldiers from Jeddah to Ugair pomt Slhassa after Bahrain* Wire urgently whether Government has any ohjection our undertaking business Ends • We are sending following reply to both Begins Your telegram May 27th .Government have no objection to your supplying steamer for conveying soldiers from Jeddah to Uftair on presumption of course that this will not prevent discharge of your pilgrim obligations Ends From. To. No.c?-VV Telegram From uritish Agent, jeddah, to H.M T s• Seeretary of State for jforeign Affairs, London, jio » 70, Repeated GoTernment of india, foreign and rolitieal Department, Simla, jso * @2. H.M's• High Commissioner for J.raq, Baghdad, no. 92. Political Kesident, Bushire, no. 92. Political Agent, Bahrain, no* 92. Dated 31»t May ^reeeived 1st June ) 1929. 'Acting Minister for iforeign Affairs informed me this morning, 'by telephone, that situation did not now appear to warrant despatch of troops by sea to Hasa; this proposal has therefore 'been abandoned. ••A detachment is said to have been sent from Kiyadh by land.** JSnds. The foregoing is correction to last papa- graph of my telegram flo. 69, repeated tinder no. 88. #0 81 copy sent to the ir* a s s . at luiwait and Muscat and to the s.n.u. u .miaju u .61/14- Telegram P. From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Hesident, Bushire. No. 467. Dated 1st received 2nd June 1929. i The Shaikh of Kuwait says that he has already refused supplies and will continue doing so. This is in reply to your telegram of May 30th No. 495. POLITICAL.Telegram code ^ rom Political, Kuwait 'fo Resident, Bushire' No. Dated ^ es P a ^ c ^ ec: ^ 1st received 2nd June 1929 received. Ubaid Cousin of Sultan Bin Humaid believed to be employed in King yaisal»s household arrived from Baghdad three days ago and proceeded to Wafrah with a letter .Sxsas for Ikwan there - he returned this morning en route ^Baghdad. ^ Wafrah are concentrated Ajman under Uaif Bin Hithlain new Shaiidi of Ajman also ibn l»iashur and Mijad al Dhainah ol Utaibah^latter with one standard# political- c^. H. fid &amp; /3Qy£c/(*c0 KynC&amp;A, 2. zr..- ^ Pc jth- &lt;h *1 J.61/14. (g) ) f Telegram From To Repeated No. 1845-3 P* Grovernment of India, Simla. British Agent, Jeddah, Secretary of State for India, London. Higli Commissioner, Baghdad, Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain, Dated and received 2nd June 192.9. 2700 rifles, low velocity, Mark III and III asterisk and 3000 'boxes of small arms ammunition '305 Mark 71 were despatched on Eay 30th from Calcutta and will reach Bomhay on 4th June. Oil 'bottles and pull throughs arrive at Bombay on June End from Allahahad. It will he arranged for the whole consignment to he shipped from Bombay on 5th June 'by a G-ulf steamer. The statement of full costs and the date ot arrival at Bahrain will he telegraphed as soon as known. The foregoing is with reference to your telegram ITo. t&amp;t&amp;xSx 69 of 28th May. P0REIGN. P. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain, Telegram Prom To No. 504. Dated 2nd June 1929. Please arrange with British India Agents and Qusaihi to give and take delivery of consignment outside Bahrain territorial waters and to ship it to Ugair without landing at Bahrain. Reference is to Government of India telegrair i of June 2nd, No. 1845-S. RESIDENT. £ ./V; (D. f. C . a^At$ I — yConfidential . Iu t Mo. 191-S• of 1929. British Residency andConsulate^General, Bus hire, 2nd June 192 9. Sir, I am directed to aclcnowledge the receipt of / your letter m, B.a.1031, dated the 13th May 1929, and to state that the issued'no longer arise. 2. The Shaikh of Kuwait permitted Ihn mashhur to meet him at Jahrah as he helieved he was the poss essor of a safe conduct from ibn Saud. He subsequently directed him to leave Kuwait territory hy 14th May and Ibn Mashhur complied with this order. The Bhaikh has also denied his territory to refugees from Hajd and will refuse them supplies. He will, if necessary, request ihe Political Agent for armed assistance in enforcing his prohibitions against refugees too power ful for him to deal with unassisted. 3# Copies of this letter are being sent to His Majesty's secretary of State for the Colonies and to the Government of India. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, _ _ Secretary to the Poetical KeBident in the lo. IL rk-St^. If v-f.awif. /K*. H ^VvvwA ------ • Mus ca t, Attested Cop^jto the Political Agent at Kuwait for Bahrai n information only. ^ ts 0^, ^ F ^or Secretary to x^.K. , jf.g.. 1 I I . Confidential . (V 0 British neoidency and GonouXate-Cienerai, Wuahire, 2nd June 1929. Mo. 25. Sir, I have the honour to forward for the informa tion of His Majesty 's government a copy of letter, Uo. i9i-S. of to-cay's date» to Uie FoiitiUal Secretary to His Excellency the High Coramissioner for Iraq at Baghdad. I have the honour to be, Bir, your raost obedient, huable servant. cJl ^ Lieut t -Colonel, Political Keaicient in the Persian Gulf. M His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, Colonial Office, LOiNBOJEi.L£ I -V sgp ^,„621 ...1081...5,000...18 9 28. Confidential . No s.n. II 0^ . uv t-jt AdJ) [l/i 2 K W H. C. F. 16. 14 tX rT . f .M*,;--.- : .!roinr 13^ SECRETARIAT OF H. E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ {Baghdad, /? 1. /V0...5.. .. 2- ^ 1' ft May, /929. ft: .tiBOiTi;.'. B£(M8. lui—aaKg.*ii■ ..--s—' Ml ' 1 By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked low is forwarded with compliments to :— The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Oriental Secretary to hi, E, The High Commissioner for 'Iraq, Enclosures :— Confidential despatch dated the 26th of May, 1929, from H.l.the Acting High Commissioner for 'Iraq, Baghdad, to the Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, with enclosures, on the subject of the seduction of Dhafir tribes by Ibn SaW* M.I. 27. /I/'- 'W 'JJ-JL- L.8GPS...621...1081...5,000...18 9 23. Confidential * No. &lt; ^. 0 IIP ^ Oml c^, I i\A ILlj fU y Hi H. C. F. 16. SECRETARIAT OF H. E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ M 2- {Baghdad, -May., 7929 By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked low is forwarded with compliments to :— The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Eushire . A Oriental Secretary to hi, E, The High Commissioner for 'Iraq, 4 Enclosures :— Letter No.S.0.1104 dated the 27th of May, 1929, from the Oriental Secretary to H.3.the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, Baghdad, to His Britannic Majesty^ Agent and Consul, Jiddah, with enclosures, on the subject of *Iraq-Hajd relations. C M .I. 27./ 1 'onfidenti a. ho. S#Q&gt; UDLf Secretmri%t of /!• :♦ the High ^o-nmissionar for ' Ir^q, B&amp;gMmd, dated 2 '7 -^ay, 19S9# Sir, I am direct9d to request you to forward the enclosed letter® to King • \bdul \zi% al Sa 'ud, by the quickest means alraiia&amp;le* Bagliah translations of these letters, %nd of the letters received from Ei»g Ibn Sa'ad to which 29* th ^ r:ira ^re enclosed for your information. Copies of this letter -and enclosures %re being sent to the Secretary of State for the Colonies and to the Politic*! Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* I have the honour to be, Sir* tour most obedient servant, Oriental Secretary to * • the High Coi^nifj^ion^r for »Irao, His Iiritannic Majesty 1 s \gent and Consul, -Tiddvie g7.a ff&lt; Nw m.S.Q. lOQX tfee aealdeney, Baghd-^i, Msay, 1929. Your Majesty, X thank lour majesty vary sincerely for ' your kind letter Ho.42 dated the 24th of April, 1929, in which Tour ajeety send® congratulatioao to me on my appointment a« High Gonmiiasioner in 1 Irao. I welcome with deep gratitude Your Majesty's assurance of support and sympathy in the task of strengthening and confirming the good relations between lour Majesty ♦s Kiagdosi and the Governments of His Britannic Majesty and of 'Iraq# Tour Majesty 1 s sympathy and confidence has always been extended to me in full measure and 1 sincerely hope that the time will come when friendly discussion of matters of mutual interest will afford me the priirilege of once more meeting Your Majesty in person and of renewing the friend ship with wh|.ch Tour Majesty has honoured me* \ccept. Your Majesty, the assurance of my highest consideration i ind esteem. High Commissioner for 1 Iraq His Majesty 1 Abdul A*is bin 1 Abdul Hahaian al Faisal al oa'ud, G.C«I. % • King of the Hijas, Kajd and its dependencies.fhm i**0ideney, JBrngtidati, Med w, 1929. lour X hasten to mcknowl«dg« the raotipt of Your ...aj^aty 1 s letter Mo. 31 d^t^d th« 34th of priX t 1929, m copy of which I hart duly c^miaunieat^d to Hi® Britannic ^jesty*« Covcrnment. fhe info motion which I have gathered on the •pot ree^ r ^i»g the attack on ir» Cr-mo mad ki® pmrty leads a# to tno belief th&amp;t /our ^ajeety ha« 'been xaiainformed suad that the perpetrators were men from the force® of Ibn lUthlain, who was at that moment carrying out a raid in the im ediate ricinity. :fleTsrthele«s f it will serve no useful purpose now to continue discussion on this deplorable incident which is only one of the unfortunate effects of an unsatis factory situation which I hope may he remedied toy mutual confidence and understanding. 1 venture once more to submit my respectful congratulations on the signally successful manner in which tour Majesty ha® dealt with those who attempted to disobey your order®. ; hatever may have been the motives of those who dar^d to flout your authority their punishment has bean timely and well-deserved, the question of the post® is one on ^hich we were unable to reach agreement, and, as lour . MajestyI &amp; is -atrart, His Btitvmiz Govftmi'ieiit and the 1 lr %&lt;5 Q^rttrnzent hair« signif ltd ihelr will lug- n«ss to rabbit to tepartial ^Itrmtion tiJ« interpre tation of \rtiele 3 of th€ Hqumiar -rotocol. U til# iNtsi® tliso 1 w&amp;t 'bound to point out to lour Maiswty that the @xi»toac« of thf? posts during th« recent trouMous period, to nhieh ^our Majesty has now hazily put ^n end, has 'oa^n the msafts of sariiig mmo^/of lift and property. On no single occasion h^re raiders ▼antursa. to attack any post or to carry out raids in their insmsdiats vicinity. they Have invariably confined th^ir attacks to defenceless shepherds an# tribesmen who have moved far afield in eearch of graslng. in these circumst^ncae, it is not unnattral that considerable value should be attached to the posts by those who are responsible for the protection of 1 Iraf tribes fro^ unprovoked at task. Nevertheless, 1 m in a position once more to assure lour Majesty • with full knowledf.;# - that these posts are in no wiy designed to interfere with the free movementsof tribes, whether 1- Jdi or 'Xwmi, nor do they constitute any menace whatsoever, against lour Majesty's people and country. I have my sal f visited the posts and satisfied myself on this point by personal inspection, provided that the situation on the frontier rsmaias mtmml and peaceful there is no intention of making them anything more than police poets for the better control and administration of the desert areas of 1 tr-m.X hsT« also mym$lf hy tmwmfmt inrsBtig&amp;tioa *me} mquirj that th* author it i*9 in * Iraa hmrtf, sines our conv^rs ttlans in Ti4d®H, ^♦ea serupalou^ in ol&amp;aarTing th®ir trsaty obligations ^.nd haTs on no single ceoasion t&amp;k&amp;n motion which coul^ fee oonsftrued %s proToeatlY« t or OT«n incorrect* So patient %nd fort-taring luvre thoj boan that th«y har# T&amp;s^n tfea object of sharp criticise in mmj quarters -md hrnv® horn accused of failing adsrmately to protect tht interests of thair own subjects. The &amp;9Y *rmmmt of * Irmq has no hostile ©r *1grtrntiro intention agminst Your majesty or your ^oainions. ihsir own mi't is to devote tinemselTes to questions of refom -mnd reconstruction and to ensure the progress and deTelopraent of 1 irao lit an atmosphere of pease and mity with their neighbours. I woul^ her® speak particularly of the un warranted accusations levelled agaiast Captain clubb. I have made very careful enquiries and i aa in a position to affirm that they are entirely unfounded. Captain Clubb is an officer of high principle who discharges his duties unselfishly and conscientiously, and it is intolerable that he should be subjected to continual persecution not only in the *Umm el ura* but also in the anti- overmaent Press in Baghdad. If criticism is to be levelled let it be at those who- are responsible but 1 e®. confident that ^our Majesty's chivalrous and generous spirit will no longer tolerate these continual attacks on an individual officer// ^ ) ft. 6/ No. 3I « Kingdom of Najd and T5«?p®ndenc ieso Biwan of H«k« The King* From ; 1 \bdulaziflt bin ' Abdulrahman U-Faisal. To ; H.l.Sir Gilbert Clayton, High Commissioner for We have received your letter Ho.3.0/615 dated 14th March, 1929, and we regret, as you do, that the first communication from lour Excellency, after your assumption of the office of High Commissioner, should be on the subject of raiding incidents and attacks etc between Najd and 1 Iraq. I like that you should fesl certain in the first place that the attack on Mr. Craned car and the murder of the American missionary were not of the doing of the raiders referred to by you, since the enquiry which we made into this incident in particular has shown us that the raiding party in question had not reached the place reached by i^r. Crane's car, and that the party had not at all come across that car. As regards other than what relates to the Mr. Crane 1 s incident, we wish to acquaint Your Excellency as follows: You will no doubt recollect the verbal discussions which took place between us at Tiddah, when we emphasised to Your Excellency the fact that 1 Iraq 1 s continuance in the policy pursued by it would 1md to continuous disturbances along the frontier. You will also recollect that we told you that unless the fortifications erected were pulled down it would be impossible to prevail over the forces in the vici nity of the frontier, beoause the people of Ha Id as a whole were displeased with the conduct of the 'Iraq Government, their revokation of their pledge and their interpretation of-2- of the treaties between them ^nd us according to their own wish and desire, to which has been added (or which were aggravated by) the activities of certain British offioiais, and their creation of causes for wrong doing. 411 the foregoing has led to certain incidents to which you hare referred- In our opinion, those responsible for these incidents are those who have bean the cause of them, as we have already informed the British Government on more than one occasion, and is we also infonaed you at Jidriah. The incident of the action by aeroplanes and cars in Hajd territory, when you were in Tiddah negotiating with us for the solution of the problem*, is not far to recollect. This and what preceded it and what followed it and their persis tence in their intrigues have reduced the conditions on the frontier to the state which you described in your letter. We on our part, being anxious to prevent disputes between us and the British Government and in the hope that existing problems would be solved following the arrival of Your Sxeellency in 'Iraq, found it inevitable to take the hazardous step of stablizing conditions on the frontier. Accordingly, I set out in person at the head of thirty thousand of my troops, attacked the forces assembled in the vicinity of the frontier under the leadership of Sultan ibn Bujad and Faisal al Dawish, and dealt them a fatal blow in the course of which the Bawish was wounded and surrendered himself to us, whereupon we sent him back to A .rtawiyah temporarily until his wound is healed when he will come back to us. -\s regards ibn Bujad ymm we captured him together with those who were with him, beheading some of them and sending the others to jail. Thanks to these strong and harsh measures affairs on the frontier have calmed down completely.-3- coiQplet&lt;sly. Those of our subjects whov?' wo hav® thus fought had not complained of any injustice or oppression on our part, all were the subject of our sympathy, deference and justice. Their only complaint against us was that the ♦Iraq had transgressed upon us by the erection of those qasrs on the frontier and put our honour to contempt by violating our territory, while we did not retaliate the aggression. This is what had Induced them to march on the frontier, to disobey our orders and to be obstinate in their behaviour, and it w^is on account of this that we hare dealt them this e destructive and hard blow® This is what we hare done for the pacification of conditions on the frontier, and we wish to know the action taken and to be taken by His Excellency General Clayton on his part with a view to assisting us in thft removal from »Iraq of the causes of these disturbances. There are three matters which should receive the attention of the British Government, so long as they wish to insurs their interests and comfort in 'Iraq md also the interests and comfort of the people of 'Iraq, and so long also as they wish for the comfort of their friend {i.e. Ibn Sa*ud himself - Translator), These three matters, which should receive consideration and for which a definite settlement should be improvised and over which -agreement should be reached between us and the British Government, are; Firstly . The \shraf und their intrigues - both the Ashraf ruling in 'Iraq and Transjordania and those residing there. They are the cause of the disputes between Hajd and 'Iraq and Hajd and Trans jordania. Before they came there no such difference or disputes existed. They should either leave these neighbouring countries or have their hands bound leaving them no power or authority over matters outstanding between us and »Iraq and Trans jordania, or ^von- the frontiers of these two countries.Ir 0 -4- Secondly . \ '♦liquidation M of former treaties should be effected go obviate misinterpretation and alteration, the qasrs and ••recent innovations' being removed. With this accomplished the British Oovermaent will find us anxious to ward off any occurrence against * Iraq. Thirdly . British Officials in Iraq and Trans,jordania should be made the subject of any enquiry (Literally; should be considered) and the removal effected of those of them who have been the cause of instigation to evil, the others being prevented from persistence in their activities which are productive of trouble and mischief* The above three matters we place before the British Government and before His Excellency the General, for urgent examination with a view to subsequent agreement over a definite and conclusive solution, in order that neighbouring Arab countries might devote themselves to affairs of reform and reconstruction and to the ensuring of the happiness and pros perity of their peoples. We are confident of receiving, at an early date, from Your FiXcellency and from the British Government practical reply for proceeding with the settlement of these matters. Please accept etc., (Seal of Ibn Sa^ud). Dated 14th Bhul OJL'dat. 347. 54th \prii, l^Sy!Ho.42. Kingdom of Hajd ?ind Dependencies. Biwan of His Majesty the FCingo From : ♦ AMulazia bin 1 Abdulrahman 41-?aisal. To : Ho 3. General Sir Gilbert Clayton, High Commissioner for Iraq. I have received with pleasure Your Excellency's letter lo.SoO/614 dated 14th karch, 1929, informing me of your arrival in ♦Iraq and of your assumption of the duties of High Commissioner. 1 congratulate you on your safe arrival and on your assumption of the charge of affairs whioh have besn entrusted to you in the sister country of 'Iraq. What we have known in your person, oh Your Excellency, as to the truthfulness of word, the anxiety for the fulfilment of pledges, and the unmistaka ble desire for the strengthening of good relations betwe«n us and the British Government, renders us hopeful of a change in the present burdensome 8ituation(which has arisen between us and some of those in 'Iraq) as a result of the drastic and wise measure which we believe you will adopt with resolution and determination for t;he clearing up of the atmosphere and the removal of the unpleasant matters which have cl-uded it, would like Your Excellency to feel certain that you will have the support of myself and my Government in every endeavour which is calculated to strengthen the good relations betwean us and the British and 'Iraq Governments, in deference to your person and out of desire to strengthen the ties with the British Government and of confidence in the result of your endeavours. You shall, by the will of God, find us always up to your goodgood opinion of us, while we on our part are hopeful * * L' ■ «&gt; ♦ of finding you always up to our good opinion of you. Please accept etc., (Seal of l'bn Sa^d). Dated 14th Bhul Qi'dat. 347 . 24th April, 1929o m. iConfidential. C -8. of 1929. MO. Britinh Heoidency and ConeuXttte-GencriUL, Bueiliire , 4th June 1929. A copy of the undermen tioned paper is forwarded to the -Political Secretary to his Kxcellcncy the High Cotanisaioner for ^raq, Baghdad, for informtior; By Oipcier, &amp; i&amp;C- „ Captain, He ere tar: to the Political Keaicent in the .Peraian Gulf, Bushire telegraia Uo, 504, dated 2nd June 1929. U /i^X It/ Telegram Code From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire Repeated High Commissioner for iraq, Baghdad, Administrative inspector, Basrali, special Kasiriyalu Ho. 375 Da. ed the 4th received the 5th June 1929» Shaikh of Kuwait saw me this morning.. He complains that last night 5rd June 20 raiders of A1 Said section of Dhafir, Shailch Mohammed 100 camels property of Kuwait woodcutters near juwaihil well South of Jahrah Kuwait road - one of the raiders captured confessed that party mistook camels for those of Ajman and Ibn Mashuro Shaikh of Kuwait to avoid incident that camels be returned without delay, suggest that Dhafir be warned not to raid Ajman or ibn Mashur as retaliatory measures will result message ends# Will Baghdad kindly inform me where to send owners of stolen camels for arranging recovery* bin Khidr, disguised as ikhwan / raided and carried off has-^^G-^^*— Jahrah outpo^st from pursing raiders requests Political#■*s r ' : .o Telegram yrom To Fo. Code Political, Kuwait /(si in Resident, Bushlre (repeated to HighcoroinissictB er for iraq^, Baghdad, Administrative Inspector, Basrah, Special, Hasiriyah. 576 Dated the 4th received the 5th June 1929. yellowing from reliable source, ibn Saud is due to arrive at Nejd this week with the intention of attacking and dispersing Ajman and other rebel concentrat- xon about Wafra. ibn Saud's Agent here has received credit of 5s 30,000 by telegram for purchasing supplies. Strong punitive force only awaiting the arrival of King before moving. If rebels defeated Shaikh of lOiwait fears they may endeavour to make for Kuwait territory probably Jahrah. Political.Confidential. mo . -H. of 1929. British Kesidency and Consula ce-General, J3ushire, the 5th J me 1929. The undermentioned papers are forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for perusal and return. By Order, % Captain, Secretary to the FoliticalKesident in the -He, si an Gulf. 9 List of paprrs 1, Confiden tial aes^tach,dated Oie 26th Bay 1929, from H,K. ^he High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad, to H.M*s. Secretary of btate for the Colonies, London, with enclosures, regarding he sedition of Bhafir tribes by ibnJaud. Letter Ho. r &gt;.0. 1104, dated the 27th of May 1929, from the Oriental Secretary to il.K. the High Conmissioner for Iraq, Baghdad, to Agent and Consul, Jeddaji, with enclosures , regaruing Iraq-Najd relations. (Received under enefforsement wos. J'.u. 1107 and r.O. 1109, dated 27th May 1929, respectively, from the Oriental Secretary to Ji.E. the High Conmissioner for Iraq, Baghdad.)61/14 Telegram Code From Resident, Bushire To Political, jBafrrain Ho. 514 Dated the 5th June x929* &amp; Have you received any confirraation of Kuwait news that Bin Saud will arrive at Nejd this week with intention of attacking Ajman, is qusaibi purchasing or forwarding exceptional quantity of supplies. Residento Confidential. ( ) To Bushire only, r~\ n 7) / Ho. 157-H. busk;- :y -^ 5~20 - | Rig. No. I Bde- (? - V' tgOHFlOElfw. v^OMi A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Army Department (General ^taff Branch) the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information in continuation of the endorsement from the (Government of India in the) Foreign and Political Department Ho,157~N f dated the 22nd May 1929• By order, etc., ^Deputy Secretary to the Government of India# Foreign and Political Department, The Simla; May 1929. 1 Z' _7 To Army Depart ment only# Telegram from the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, No#454, dated the 18th May 1929 J 2. Telegram from the British Agent and Consul, Jeddah, Bo#83, dated the 21st May 1929# 3. Telegram from ditto No.1725-3, dated the 23rd May 1929# ?R (With I spare copU ) h61/14 Telegram JjToin The Government of India, foreign and jeolitical department, bimla. To British Agent and Consul, weddah. (Political Kesident, Bushire# Repeated( (Political Agent, Bahrain. Ho. 1881-S. Dated 6th (received 7th ) June 1929. IMPORTANT. Two thousand seven hundred rifles and 1583 boxes of S. A# aiomunition were despatched on 5th June from Bomha^ 'by subsidiary Gulf steamer which is due at Bahrain otk the 16th June# By first available steamer will follow 1417 boxes of ammunition un fortunately delayed in railway transit. Details of cost will be sent shortly# - Jb'OHE IGiS • H»M*s« High Commiss ionei J^ost copies sent to the S»xi.U.. for Iraq. Baghdad. A's. at Balirain &amp; ~ ' TRIAD w y Ba s rah . Mus cat.61/14 Tel«grsun 1?. From K•M*s« High CoimniBsioner f®r iraq, J3agh.dad# T© JPolitical nesident, isushire. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. !!©• 60-B. Dated 6th (received 7th ) June 1929, h* fn f,- i Xra(i polic® care have gone as far south as Rodhatain (ahout twentyfiTe miles mthin Kuwait territory) in connection with recent raids of few camels from Iraq, tribes south of Safwan* Ministry of Interior are acting on assumption that permission given 'by the Kuler of Kuwait for Iraq, police cars to visit Iraq tribes in his territory still holds good, and was not merely granted for the period of one month m* was permission for concentration of armoured cars of the Royal Air Jforce# I am al«o of the same im- presBion; but to obviate any possibility of misunder standing will you please confirm ? i i HIGH OOMMIB SI UMIH» Copy by post sent to the Goverriment, of India under endorsement No. d/ H S/S for Colonies, n Muscat and Bahrain. {iTp© ly Telegram Code Prom Political, JSa^rain To Kesident, Bushire Ho* 556 Dated the 6t}i received 7tli June 1929. /7-i Your telegram No* 514. There is (? rumour) at ujair Bin saud will arrive at Hasa in four or five days but no confirmation. . \ i It is further stated that a few days ago i3in Musaad of Hail despatched detachment of 400 men which was attacked by ikhwan who killed them all. isin jaluwi also sent out detachments headed by Mohammed Assahali the latter and the majority were killed* Ujair force lias been increased by 40 men Bin jaluwi also ordered that all forts should be supplied with food supplies enough for 80 men for the period of four months. Q l usaibi»s activities have been normal. C POLITICAL* Telegram Code From Resident, Bushire. To High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad Ho. 521 Dated the 8th June i929. Following from Bahrain 6th June, begins There is rumour xxxx xx normal ends. Q,usaibi is Bin Saud t s Agent, who would be busy arranging supplies if early operations were anticip ated. ResidentCiltrOl Telegram Jf. jfrem jeolitical Keeident, iiushire. T® jfolitical Agent, Kuwait, rn. 520. Dated 7th June 1929» Are Iraq, bribes still grazing in Kuwait territory ? I consider Tisits of Iraq police cars should 'be limited to miniEiuia while i do not object to uritish armoured cars visiting Kuwait where they are needed for protection#. / Please consider whether these visits cannot 'be confined to hot pursuit. Cannot Kuler now, when number of Iraq trihes- mon must he small, undertaJce responsibility of policing his own territory ? unwelcome prescriptive rights will, in time, 'be created by too much Iraq police interference. Above has reference to Jiigh Commissioner for Iraq's telegram i*©. 60-S. - HESIDEN1*»Tele£ram F* hi O * gr corrupt c &amp; From. British Agemt, Jeddati* To. Foreign Office,Lon(ion» ITo 79 Hepeated Government of India,Baghdad Bushire and Kuwait { Dated the 6th (reed 8th) June 19E9» , v x Note from Bin Saud has 'been haded me 'by Minister for Foreign Affairs in which King states that his recent punitive measures were undertaken not 'because of misconduct of his subjects in Nejd hut 'because of their acts against countries with which,'by ties of friendship and affection, he is 'bound. King adds that nothwithstanding their recent withdrawal into Nejd Ihn Kashur and his Qhut, and Ajman A. followers are still receiving assistance, encouragement food and other supplies from Kuwaiti It is stated 'by His Majesty that he intends to punish remaining offenders severely 'but that he cannot hegin until (1) His Majesty*s Government will intimate whether they are prepared to effectively militate against * expelled 'by force anxious to take refuge in Mesopotamia or Kuwait♦ Because he knows that his dear friend the Shaikh of Kuwait has not sufficient forces at his own disposal he makes this enquiry, (ii) that an assurance will 'be given him 'by His Majesty^s Government that they will take •effect ive measures 'by pppointing persons to control these matters in preventing leakage of supplies from Kuwait# This is requested 'because he fears that in spite of his friendship the economic position of his country ohliges She Sheikh to wink at smuggling. Moreover, adequate means for a serious land 'blockade to stop out-going supplies are not possessed 'by the Sheikh, (ill) 'that tee. lh £ o~ in order^to eradicate disaffection in whole of frontier zion0,His Majesty^ Government and the Sheikh will agree to his forces pursuing offenders across frontier of Kuwait and driving them out of th^t terrltor/. His Majestyrequests that a reply may he sent at the earliest possible date. ^ — /r.-TTt;v gr j mi tted. o Telegra m From, British Agent, Kedda]!. To. Foreign Office, London Ko 81. Repeated Govemment of India, Baghdad Kuwait and Bushire. Dated the 7th (reed 8th) June 1929. N o 104. Acting Foreign Minister for Foreign Affairs in presenting the note stated that he was instructed to add that His Majesty knew that appeal for assistance^ which had 'been fort coming, had 'been addressed to Sheikh K of Kuwait. Loot had 'been sent to him for disposal and money,arms and ammunition and supplies had 'been returned in exchange. In Kuwait itself plunder had 'been sold. Sheikh had knowledge of whatever had 'been done. Minil ^ser produced illiterate Bedouin letters from Trahih 'bin Shuaair which he nor I can completely understand 'but which in opinion of King is evidence of the complicity of the Sheikh. It was further stated 'by Minister for Foreign Affairs that if His Majesty^s Government wished to put an end to the difficulty a 'blockade should 'be instituted 'by them. On his side Ihn Saud could inflict no effective punishment if those under the influence of * did not do their share. Arabic copies of letters in question are 3s±Kg luwait &amp; 'being ^fiet to/Baghdad hy me for examination. I have had a translation prepared which follows,*Telegram P# r — — liO ^rom. Secretary ot State tor tlie Colonies ^London. To. High Commissioner, BagMad ,Ko 192,repeated Political llesident,Busiiire» June Dated 3tli (reed 9tli) May 1929• Please furnish as soon as possible your ob servations on telegram Ho 79 from Jeddah which was ^ repeated to you under No 102* \ Your reply should please 'be repeated to Baghdad Government of India and Jeddatu P ^ ^ ' J' ^ ^6l/i4 1127-10/6/29 Telegram Code from Political Bahrein To Kesident Busiiire Ho.574 Dated 9tii (received 10th.) June 1929. /^cy C/ On or about the 31st May Abdulaziz 'bin Turki arrived at Hasa from Hiadh. with a force of 600 men. One of the sheiMis of C^ahtan is reported to have left Riadh with a force of 1,500 men and arrived short distance from Hasa. The Kejd forces are said to 'be concentrating at Hasa and will shortly m^ke their headquarters at Aluwainah which is near Sarrar the Capital of Ajman* - POLITICAL - dL. b /C&gt;2 '7 ^ I, it/i p- c ^Telegram P. From, Political Agent, Kuwait. To. Political Resident, Bushire. No. 379. June Dated 9tli (reed 10th) Ka?: 1929. yiif Jeddah*s telegram 104 has not 'been decyphered. Can he not 'be asked to send in a simple cypher; unahle to keep pace with messages, Aho^e refers to your 5E4. » Telegram P • From. Political Resident, Bushire# To. Political Agent, Kuwait. No . 530 Dated the 10th June 1929 Greenway may 'be asked to assist j&lt;m. Lwt me have with all speed your comments on Jeddah f s 104 as it it is very urgent. ' ^ Ahove refers to your 379. VoAr^OJ./ J.'* Telegram j?. Frem nigh Commissioner for iraqm ±sagMad. H.M^. Secretary of state for the Coionies, London• Repeated-ifoliti cal Kesident, uushire* British Agent, Jeddah. GoTernment of India in the foreign and Political department, simla» No* 61-S. Dated 9th (receiyed 10th ) June 1929. 1 think ire are bound to meet Xbn Saud^ request either 'by allowing Ibn Saud to pursue orer the frontier or by keeping Mashhur and rebellious Ajxaan out of Kuwait. As they will surely be a source of trouble in future as were refugees of the Mutair and Sharamar in the past, it is also in our interest that Ictoi th«y should not be allowed refuge. .Presumably the Kuler of Jtluwait is unable to hold his frontier by force unless assisted by us, and it is also doubtful whether we could now prevent further leakage of supplies, which he has been furnishing during past few months to rebel AJthwan. Question is whether we should leare Huler to allow the King^ forces to pursue into Kuwait or hold his (Ruler's ) frontier for him. This raises the whole question of extending our commitments in regard to Kuwait. Situation has been discussed by me with the Air Officer Commanding: we see considerable difficulty in adeqaately protecting Iraq as well as frontier with forces at our disposal and at present time of year. We should be akwardly placed vis a. vis Bin saud if we fail to discharge the responsibility undertaken by us in full measure. On the whole it appears that the best course is to agree to Bin Saud's pursuing across Kuwait border if the Ruler og Kuwait is unable to keep out rebel tribesmen and to undertake only to prevent them from enter* ing Iraq. it is obviously undesirable^to agree to Bin Sms &amp; Xx Saud ♦ s- 2 - Suad's forces entering Iraq proper, but it might be permitted to both xoarties to pursue into neutral zone, which is likely pStace for refugees: this would con siderably lighten task of R.A.J?, but would require the consent of Iraq Goyei^nment. I suggest that Shaikh be urged and assisted also to form a force for the protection of his oaui own country both now and hereafter, although control of any jfojrgatOB leakage of supplies from Kuwait is first essential. one of His majesty's ships at Kuwait would gire feeling of security at present juncture and, of course, help from the Air j'orce at Shaibah would be quickly available in the event of serious menace to the town of Kuwait. Kntry of rebel tribesmen into her territory will be prevented by the Government of Iraq by all available measures, but His Majesty should be anc warned of difficulty of distinguishing them from His own forces and consequent necessity of latter not crossing ths ^ ^ ^ - HIGH COMMloSiOMKK. 7Telegram Prom. Political Agent, Kuwait. To. Political Resident, Bmshire, No. 380♦ Dated the 9th (reed 10th) June 1929 f Q I have discussed question at length with the Sheikh of Kuwait whose replj: Is 'below: ~ First# None of Mesopotamian trihes are in Kuwait territory now* Second. As regards car question his standpoint is that British armoured cars entering his territory when required for his protection will always he welcomed 'by him hut in all cases he would prefer their stay to he fixed beforehand if possible. Sheikh is definitely suspicious of Mesopotamian police cars and objects to their crossing his border at any time even in hot pursuit unless latter reciprocate. Third. Sheikh is ready and abl^ to police his own territory. Fourth . He is entirely of^opinion held by you that interference by police across the border is likely to CEeate dangerous prescriptive rights. Fifth. He expresses gratitude for lines you are adopting Foreigoing refers to your telegram of the 7th June No 520 Ij* /? b P £ /JsUaU* ^ *T elegram R From. Political Resident&gt; Bustiire. To. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 534 # Dated the XOth June 1929. Alt 61/14. nl Your 380» I am unable to follow allusion to hot pursuit. Does Sheikh wish to have right of hot pursuit into Iraq, territory ? T elegram R » From. Political Agent, Kuwait. . To. Political Resident, Bushire. No. 382. Bated llth(recd 12th) June 1929 Your telegram of the 11th June 534.No. He only means that if forced to concede right he should he allowed to claim similar concession .He h opes however that contingency will not arise.c]£) |r, mirnrn^i Prom# Political Reaident, Bxistiireo To. High. Oominis si oner,Baghdad, repeated Secretary of State for Colonies No 12,India and Kuwait No o 535* Dated the l£th June 1929• Political Agent has 'been informed hy Sheilch. of Kuwait that no Iraq, trihes are in his territory now ; he therefore considers it unnecessary for police cars to enter it. Entry of British armoured cars for protection will always 'be welcomed 'by the Sheilch hut he would like period of stay to 'be fixed in each case as it arises* He definitely dislikes Ira&lt;i police cars cross** fcng his frontier at any time., and states that he is ahle to police his own territory. Iraq. poliiTe interference in Kuwait territory should in my opinion 'be discouraged as likely to create undesirable precedents and unfortunate incidents. British Agency should take such action as may he necessaiy Foregoing refers to your 6®/S. Telegram P. From. Foreign, Simla. To« Secretary of State for Colonies&gt;repeated Bushire Baghdad and Kuwait. No. 1934/S. Dated the 11th (reed lEth) Jyne 1929. in telegram No 535 of the 10th » ^ (XaJL g June from Bushire Imb agreed to.Confidential. ^ 3 - Ho. 205-a. of1929. i3riti«h Keoidenpj^ and Coneuilate-Creneral, Bushire, 10 th June 1929. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait with a request that he will let the Hon'hie the *&gt;olitical Kesident have his views 'by telegram as early as possible. By Order, ^ v Captain, Secretary to the .Political Heoident in the Persian Gulf. Baghdad telegram No. 61-S. of the 9th June 192 9. _ i .-^) r ky /&amp; Telegram code i n roin Resident Bushire To nigh Commissioner for 'Iraq., .eaghdad Uo.536 Dated the iOth June i929. please repeat to Colonial Office A&gt;\^ your telegram Ho«60i-S of 6th June referred to in my telegram immediately preceding, - RESIDEET -Telegram Pn 61/14 / CL From. Political Agent,Kuwait. To* PolitifiaiX Resident&gt; Buahire# No 381. and reed Dated/the 10th June 1929# Argument of Bin Sa^id is specious 'but incorrect Eecent rebellion of course was 'biggest possible con certed effort yet seen to 'break his power# Heferetjce three requests of Bin Saud: First does not seem to 'be quite necessary as Sheikh has undertaken to expel rebels himself,failing 7 /hich he is prepared to ask Boyal Air Force for immediate help. The second request strikes one as very high-handed. Sheikh has gone out of his way to meet Bin Saud. Only yesterday he again categorically assured me that he had forhiCden rebels to the 'border much less could they send supplies/foodstuffs , moreover as only gate available is under strict guard / townspeople could not send out anything. Following possible source of leakage Is suggested by Sheikh - Bin Saud^ Awazim allies in Eassa and loyal Akhwan were by permission of Bin Saud able to purchase food and (oxen ?) in Kuwait and take these out by boat. Eventual destination of such supplies could not be guaranteed by Sheikh. As regards the third request this will be strongly resisted by Sheikh as infringement of soverign rights; he wants Royal Air Force and not Bin saud to do expelli ng if this is necessary. Ftoally Sheikh indignantly denie s accusation of complicity which*he described a s im pudent efforts of anti-Kuwait propaganda . He greatly regrets that such obviously prejudicial tales were so readily seixed upon by his old friend Bin Suad as proof # Above refers to your telegram No 524. and timdi■Ma J No (c 18- u Secretariat of H.E.tiie High Commissioner for ^raq, Baghdad, [ q June, 1929 Sir, I I am directed to enclose a copy of memorandum Ho.4038/28 dated the 29th May, 1929, from Air Headquarters, on the subject of the supply and cost, to the Shaikh of Kuwait, of Lewis Gun mountings. 2. A copy of this letter is 'being sent to the Political Agent, Kuwait, in order that he may he ahle to convey the required information to the Shailch, if it is considered desirable that he should do so. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. . ' /clv &gt;-W Counsellor to H.S.the High Commissioner for ^raq The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf BUSH IRS. '(id 4i| 8GPS..-621...1081...5,000...18 9 28. Confidential. H. C. F. 16. SECRETARIAT OF H. E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ No im f Bl IT - - ! 'Baghdad, Ma -y-. / 9 |% iT~——i rSifa I o By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked below is forwarded with compliments to :— The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire * \ 1 Oriental Secretary to H. E. The High Commissioner for 'Iraq, Enclosures :— Tetter Uo.S.0.1136 dated the 30th of May, 1929, from the Oriental Secretary to H. 15. the High Comaissioner for ,I ^' Baghdad to Hia Britannin Majesty's Agent and Consul, Jiddah, with Enclosures, on the subject of tehwan prisoners. M. I. 30.Hj.ia. Kingdom of Hljaz, KnJ d and Dopendenolee BiWRKB of His majesty the King. Froxa ; ^Abdulaziz 'bin • Abduli^ahmfsn A1 -Faial. To : H.E. General Sir Gilbert Clayton, E.B.M 1 ® High Comraissioner for 1 Iraq. It hae reached us that Mr. Glubb hae arretted and placed in jail certain subject® of oure, Including a man by the name of Rabbah ibn Saghir whom Captain Glubb put in jail together with others in Bhawwal (March - April). This action on the part of Mr. Glubb ip one of the caused which instigate trouble, and we believe that it will not please you. We, therefore, request that you will forthwith order the release of all those who have been arrested by Mr. Glubb and their despatch with honour via Kuwait. We also request that you will prevent the repetition of such provocative incidents, because their repetition induces those in Hajd to retaliate by the imprisonment of natives Of 1 Iraq who may come within their reach, which thing will be in the interest of only those who wish for dispute between the two countries, which pleases neither you nor us. Please accept etc. # (Seal of Ibn Sa^ud). Dated 14th Dhul Qi'dat, 347 . 24th April. 1929. JJ. 14.5Confidential a no. 20G-n. of 1989. Britiali Kenidency and Consulate-^enBaal, Bushire^ iOth June 1929. Sir, I am directed to forward for the infoririation of His Excellency the Hi£;h Coromisaioner a copy of telegram • qy no. 1881-3., dated the 6th of June 1929, frora the Government of India in the Foreign and -Political Depart irien t, I have the honour to be, Bir, Your moBt obedient servant. Captain, Secretary to the -Political Keaident in the Persian Gulf. The Political Secretary to Hia Foccellency the High Gonraissioner for Iraq» Baghdad.u - ——i*—i—II Telesram Ps /i / 7 STom^. Politic^al Besident, BuBhire# To» Secretary ot State Tor the OoLonies^ London No 13 f Repeated. Foreign,Simla, HigMonimissioner,Baghdad and Sribish Agent,Jeddah No 539» Dated the 11th June 1929® Allegation that Ihn Mashhur and others are still in receiving any form of supplies from Kuwait is indignant ly denied 'by the Sheikh of Kuwait who states (1) tliat if po^ssilDle he is prepared to expel rebels himself 'but if this is 'beyond his power he will ask Eoyal Air Porce to render the necessary assistance- (2) He has forbidden communication with rebels of Bin Saud and states that as only gate of Kuwait available for egress is under strict guard smuggling is impossihle* ' As possible source of leakage Sheikh suggests Bin Saud's Awazim allies in Hassa and the loyal Akhwan who,with permission of Bin Saud purchased food in Kuwait and removed it hy sea. Final destination of supplies cannot he jcaaxaat guaranteed hy Sheikh. Appointment of officials hy His majesty's Government to control leakage is objected to hy hinu (3) He protests strongly against proposal of Bin Saud to pursue rsiassi rebels acrofs his border:, this he says jcmci would be an infringement of his sovereign rights• ^ Royal lir Force and not Bin Saud would be asked for assis tance if necessary# Accusation of complicity which Sheikh describes as im pudent anti-Kuwait propaganda is indignatntly denied by the Sheikh* He regrets that his old friend Bin Saud has so readily accepted such obviously prejudicial tales# Although existence of is denied hy Sheikh 1 am informed hy the Political Agent that it is very simple to load up caravans ou^tside walls after dark»and to get it away without our knowledge* I do not at present recommend that we should force our ^aiiLi'ul *r rm ■■■■■»'&lt; i n uni. t I i--- — ■ y _ i r jhw m ^imi-v control of exports on ttie unwilling Stieildi 'but I am a^ietly d-irecting Political Agent to examine question * In spite of sweet words there is no doubt that the Sheikh of Kuwait dislikes Bin Saud whom he considers ungrateful MMigTfaiPBmi in days of his poverty and the emasculator of Kuwait 'by the suborning of all the trihes^whom the rulers formerly relied for protection* Timry I myself consider that it would 'be detrimental to our interests if we are compeired 'by force of circumstances to acquiesce in Bin Saud v s troops entering Kuwait territory for any reason whatever# and every effort should,1 think, 'be made for us to undertake the defence* ourselves# Bin seeking opportunities Saud is/either openly or secretly to interfere in the GrUlf principalities and the news that hen has itivaded Kuwait territory with the permission of His Majesty* s G-overnment iasgaxisisstxii 'because we were too weak to protect it would have extremely 'bad effect on our position throughout the Gulf. ¥e may 'be sure that Nejd propaganda would stress Bin Saudis strength and ^our weakness* Ahove refers to Jeddah # s telegrams ITos 102 and 104* / / ^ / / ? £unexpectedly delayed. (9) An-Nafisi gave it as ills opinion that Ibn Sa # ud will, on arrival &gt; Tirst of all, invite all AJioan who desire forgive ness to come in and surrender. He will guarantee their safety and lives 0 in this way he hopes to detaoh a number of wavering elements• After that he will fall upon the reoaloitrant remainder. An-Nafisi fears that Ajman fugitives may make for jahrah in Kuwait territory. Should this happen and should the Shaikh of Kuwait not expel them immediately by foroe, he is of opinion that Ibn Sa'ud will pursue and attack wherever found even up to the walls of Kuwait. (This last may be a bluff on an-Hafisi # s part with intent to alarm the Ruler of Kuwait into mobilizing his available forces at jahrah). ^ ^ Lieut-cdonel, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy to H.E. the High conimissioner pfor Iraq,Baghdad. * The Administrative Inspector, Basrah. * * The Special service o^ioer, Nasiriyah.sa ttaj? '({jAvi m &lt;VU-C^ • I ■Jr* i ^,11^ v/u^ t 6l/l 4 1148-12/6/29 i Telegram i'rom To Kepeated Ifo.383 Dated llth (received 12th) June 1929 Code Political Kuwait resident Busiiire Baghdad, Administrative Inspector, ±&gt;asra and Special -Wasiriyah, f my jmo.375 of 4th june^ 0 heikh of Kuwait enquires if any steps taken to recjEover camels, captured raiders state precise party^onsisted of 26 persons 14 under Molaaaed -bin Khidr camping: at .toiriyeh near 'uldiaimiyeh 7,under Mohained bin KhaaaM of (word of 4 letters omitted) Hussain camping at safwan and 5 under xiuhaif ibn ttunaazil camping at Arfiiyah. J^arty met at JJewfuf raiding from there. Sheikh claims that as uhafir is .Iraq tribe and as aamp of 2 of the parties definitely located in 'iraa territory and as starting point also in 'Iraq territory •irag Government should either arrangfrestitution of camels or compensate the omer. S heiih trusts that High Coxamissioner for .Iraq will take up matter energetically* - POLITICAL - Ii*lL Cenflden tlal . no. AoS'S of 1929. British Reaidency and Consulate-General, Buahire, June 1929. VI To The Political A^;ent, Kuwait. MEMOHAHDUM . i Please reply through me to letter Ho. (&gt;118, dated 6th June 1929, froa the Counsellor to U&amp;e High Commissioner for ^Iraq, a copy of which has been sent to you direct. Lieut-Col., Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf. /&lt;■No p Political Agency, Kuwait Dated tlie 6th June 192 9 # From Lieutenant-colonel H.H.P.Biclcson, CUI.E*, Political Agents Kuwai To The Secretary to GOKFIOEKTIAL RECGR08.. the Hon*hie the Politic 'R'SSid^rjir CUSHIRE RESIDENCY. Reg. No..... Bute / fV In the Persian GrUlf, lushlre. Sir, In continuation of my telegram No # 375 dated the 4th June 192 9, I have the honour to enclose herewith, for the Information of the Hon^Dle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, lushire, a translation of a letter received from His Excellency the Buler of Kuwait relative to the rohhery of one hundred camels from the subjects of Kuwait* A copy of this letter together with the enclosure is 'being forwarded to the Secretary to His Sxcellercy the High Gommissioner for 'Iraq., Baghdad, Administrative | Inspector, Basrah and Special Service Officer, Nasiriyah, I for their information and necessary action* I have the honour to 'be. Sir, | | Your most obedient servant, I# Jr Lieut-Col Political igent, Kuwait #( Translation of a letter dated the 2Qth ot Diiil Hujjaii 1347 (4tii jione 1929) from H.E. Sbailda Ahmad al-jabir as—Subaii, C •S.I.jC-I.E., Biler of Kuwait to the Political Agent, Kuwaite After compliments. It is not hidden from Your Exoellenoy that about one hundred oamels were robbed from certain woodcutters of Kuwait yesterday afternoon between the jahiliyah and the Tawil (south of the KUwait-jahrah road) and it was ascertained that the robbers were 'Iraq tribesmen, and thei: chief was Muhammad bin Khidhr of the Sa 8 id tribe, a section of the Dhafir. I, therefore, request you to kindly give the bearer 'Ali bin Shaidah a letter to whatever responsible officer you may consider is the proper person to send him to^ for the recovery of the said camels, as both sides are the same (i.e.both are friendly towards each other.9 th .Tune 102'; Zns V UL /V l^h Dear Russell I have Just received the following telegram en clair from Ordn&amp;nee Bombay. '• exp/l4/a twohundredfifteen chests rifles one five one • k nought boxes S A A five boxes appurtenances shipped Baroda sail- j |l ing/sixth arriving Bahrein sixteenth approximately addressed I resident Bahrein repeated British Agent Jeddah ^ - Ordnance - ' This means of course that every telegraph clerk who reads this wire from Bombay to Bahrein,can,'with the exercise X &lt; of very little intelligence realise that the arms are destined for Bin Saud. If you agree with me that this is most undesirable; and that the message should at least- have tjeen sent in Indian Word Code, perhaps you»would suggest to the P.R. that he should have him reprimanded for his stupidity. Otherwise please consign this to the w.p.b. Yours sincerely pLn-lS ^ - ll ^2 liTelegram p (&amp;&gt; To* Secretary of State for Colonies,110 2S£U Repeated Political Resident, Bushire,Toreign, Simla,Political Agent,Kuwait and British Agent, Jeddah, No 63/S» Dated and reed ttie lEth Jxme 19E9» There is mucli force in arguments contained in last.portion of Bushire telegram 539 (13 to you) and my telegram 61/S of June 9tli against allowing Bin Saud tat to pursue into Kuwait* It isrgreatly preferable that Sheikh should,with such assistance as His Majesty t s Government can gi^e,safeguard his own frontier* Important[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] July 3, 1929. S ection 2. [E 3373/3/91] No. 1. Mr. Jakins to Mr. A. Henderson.—{Received July 3*.) (No. 138.) HIS Majesty's acting agent and consul at Jeddah presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit to him a note to the Acting Hejaz Minister for Foreign Affairs respecting the interpretation of article 6 of the Bahra Agreement. Jeddah, June 9, 1929. (After compliments.) Your Excellency, Jeddah, June 9, 1929. WITH reference to the question of the interpretation placed by His Britannic Majesty's Government on article 6 of the Bahra Agreement, I am directed to confirm the statements made to your Excellency by Mr. Stonehewer-Bird on his return from leave in January last that the article in question contemplated raids and the pursuit of raiders across the frontier, and that it did not contemplate incursions on a vast scale amounting to armed attacks; that His Britannic Majesty's Government was not limiting the scope of article 6, but was providing against two eventualities which were not contemplated under that article :— (1.) An organised attack in force, which His Majesty was unwilling to prevent, i.e., an aggression amounting in fact to an act of war; and (2.) An incursion which His Majesty was unable to prevent, i.e., an aggression resulting in a revolt against His Majesty's authority; and that it was in these special circumstances only that His Britannic Majesty's Government reserved the right of pursuit over the border. 2. I am now to explain that the statement in the letter which, as your Excellency is aware. His Majesty was pleased to address to me on the 23rd January last to the effect that His Britannic Majesty's Government are now attempting to attach a condition to their undertaking to be bound by the article does not correctly represent the position. On the contrary. His Britannic Majesty's Government have assured the Hejaz Government that they intend to observe the provisions of that article, and they recognise that British forces in Iraq, as well as Iraqi forces, are covered by its terms. The position is, indeed, that His Britannic Majesty's Govern ment have every intention and desire to observe the provisions of the article, and will naturally continue to do so, so long as a normal situation exists. They have, however, thought it only fair to warn the Hejaz Government that in the event of a situation of grave danger to Iraq being brought about by the actual occurrence of a serious attack on a large scale against a township in Iraq, or of continuous raiding by Nejd tribes, which the Hejaz Government prove unable to prevent or punish. His Britannic Majesty's Government must reserve their liberty of action and their right to take the necessary measures against those guilty of the attack, if this should prove, in their opinion, the only means of defending the Iraq tribes, for whose safety they are responsible, from further aggression. If, however, the Hejaz Government would establish the same degree of control over their tribes as has recently been enforced by the Iraq Government, who have effectively restrained their tribes from raiding Nejd, there would be no occasion for British forces to cross the frontier in any circumstances, and thus no hesitation on the part of His Britannic Majesty's Govern ment in falling in with the wishes of the Hejaz Government in the matter of article 6 of the Bahra Agreement. (Respects.) Enclosure in No. 1. Mr. Jakins to the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mecca. H. G. JAKINS.Telegram P prom.^St 1 Commissioner, Baghdad /97 u sjf_ u ^ Too Political Kesident, Bmshire* repeated Political Agent ,Kuwalt,Foreign,Simla No 62/S and Colonial Office No 2Z7* In ife&amp;sxx telegram of the EBth Fe'bruary 1929 Political Agent Kuwait stated that the Sheikh did not object to police cars so I was unaware of his dislike to their presence in Kuwaiti I entirely agree however that unless Mesopotamian trihes are in Kuwait territory Mesopotamian police cars should never cross the frontier of Kuwait# I am informing Mesopotamian G-overnment accordingly* But presence of police cars seem necessary 'both for protection an^L control when Mesopotamian trihes are grazing in Kuwait territory in any numbers# Begarding protection,when Sheikh of Kuwait claims that he is ahle to police his own territory he appears to have forgotten many attacks on Mesopotamian tribesmen which would have 'been prevented when he failed to doiiso 'by presence of police cars# Cars have also been essential for control of Mesopotamian tribes when in Kuwait territory# Dated the 12th(recd i5th) June 1929 his P&amp;reigoing refers to your ^o 555 (12 to Secretary of State P-C UvJ £ ~ ttuMXAv ■ Telegram P . 61/14. yrom. Air Officer Commanding,Baghaad» To* Political Eesident, Bushire. No Z 915 » Dated the 12th (reed 13th June 1929. On Saturday June 15th I propose to visit Kuwait. In view of recent disturbances it has no^r he em suggested hy High Commissioner that I should talk to Sheikh regarding the defence of his frontier against Ihn Saudis refugees and possible cooperation 'by Boyal Air Force. Have you any objection to my doing this ? When I interview the Sheikh Political Agent,Kuwait would of course he present. f* c fa hs ft - SPii L *T elegram From* Political Hesldent^ Bushire. To. Aviation,Baghdad♦ No. 55a. Dated the 13tb June 1929. Your suggestion is wetcomed 'bit I should vsry much like to 'be present myself at interview. Could visit he postponed till ahout June 18th to enable me to reach Kuwait on slow mail o^ alternatively arrange that flying hoat should carry me over. If so, permiasion for flying hoat to visit Bushire should 'be applied for direct to Minister at Tehran giving date. I have telegraphed to Minister preparing him for your message. / Ahove refers to your Z -SJaa- 6 Telegram Bn clair Prom. Aviation Baghdad. To Political Resident Bushire. No T¥/U Dated 13th(recd 14th ) June 1929. your 558 June 13th. Agree you proceed slow mail. Regret flying 'boat nojs available. A.0.0. indisposed. Wing Commander Oliver deputw^sg will arrive Kuwait June 18th. ITelegram From. Political Resident&gt; Bushire To. Political Afent,Kuwait. No. 559. Dated the 13th ffune 1929- yO 61/14. 1 r v /r My telegram 539 is repeated as follows Begins X X Snds Please quietly examine and report on force which Sheikh can raise to protect his own frontiers and on question of smuggling. In order to consult with Sheikh regarding defences Air Officer Commanding proposes to visit 1a/ Kuait on June 15th . To enable me to he present I have suggested postponment till June 18th, \ »•Prom# Political Besident^ Bushire^ Too Hifeh Commissioner, Baghdad, repeated political Agent, Kuwait# Ko. 56^. Dated tlie 13th June 19S9o /pv- Yovir 5S./S. I propose visit Kuwait iSth. June to meet Air Officer Commanding and will discuss question raised with Sheikh, and Political Agent.Telegram R» 61/14• \ ITroiru Political Resident, Busliire# To» Senior Naval Cfficer,H.M.S•Triad, BushireradiOp No• Dated the 13th June 1929 # It has 'been suggested 'by High Oommissioner in course of discussion as to defence of Kuwait if invaded 'by Nejd rebels that one of Eis Majesty^s ships might anchor off town to give feeling of security. Foregoing for information only*- v Telegram 61/14 From* Political Besident, Bushire# To. His Majesty*3 Minister^Tehran- No. 76. Bated the 13th June 192.9 If Aviation Baghdad ask permission for flying hoat^ to visit Bushire to take me to Kuwait and hack trust it will he possible to put matter through very early^ Pti Confidential . /u /3A ( ) To Bushire r ■ ii copy of ttie undermentioned n/ fag. NO......&amp; 0 Bat; iy. (a'V| — ^ ^ti^raedjo the Army Department (General Staff Branch) , the Hon^ole the Political HeBident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire \ ' for information in continuation of the endorsement from the (Government of India in xhe) Foreign and Political Department *jO. dated 27th May 1929 # By order, etc., AEsistant Secretary to the Government of India Foreign and Politljcal Department# Simla; The /?/ June 1929, 1« Telegram from His Majesty^ Agent and Consul, Jeddah, 130.67 dated 25th May 1929. / o ( 2. Telegram to His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India, ( HO.1803-S, dated 29th May 1929. Omit to ( Bushire 3. Telegrsm from His Majesty^s Agent and Consul, Jeddah, Ho. 69 dated 28th May 1929. (With 1 s.c.)felegram Ho,67, Dated (&amp; reed) the 25th May 1929. From#,..,. British Agent, Jeddah. To........ Foreign Office, London. (Repeated to Foreign, Siifiia, Baghdad Bahrain ^0 .85). ' I was informed this morning hy Acting Minister for j?oreign Affttirs by telephone that the Hedjaz Ocvernment without awaiting further reply my telegram Bo. 83 to India (repeated to Foreign Office under jao.65.) wish to purchase 2,700 rifles and all ammunition referred to in Government of India's telegram Ho. 165-3 of May i2th to Secretary of State for India. The 300 repairable rifles they do not require. Bin Saud has instructed Governor of Kasa to send a delegate to Bahrein. He has also told Qusaibi to see Resident at Bahrein and to make all arrangements for landing in dhows outside territorial waters. Hotification is desired of date of despatch from India. It is hoped this will be immediate and that approximate date of arrival at Bahrein will be communicated. Minister for Foreign Affairs seemed anxious that charges should be kept as low as possible. I was promised by tomorrow written confirmation of this meseage•No. Foreign, Simla* British Agent,j0ddah, repeated to Political Besident,BusMre and Political Agent, Bahrain* 1960/S• Dated 13th (reed 14th) June 1929• i 1490 'boxes of aminunitiGn which were despatched on 12th June hy S.S.Barjora are expected to arrive at Bahrain on the 22nd June* Foregoing refers to my telegram of the 11th instant No 1937/S. i v P c6i/i4 23 1169-15/6/29 -i 9 Telegram JTom To Repeated Ho»S07 Dated ISth. (received 14th) June 1929. Code nigh Commissi oner for istaq^, Baghdad. Kesident Bushire Kuv/ai t Kuwait's telegram jNo.375 and 385. Acaordling to information of police at Safwan raid in question carried out by Moliammed bin Khidr and 20 men of al Said section Dhafir aii of Tiwiiom are followers of Ajaimi Al Suwait residing wit—h iiim in nejd for the last 4 years. i*iieir present location uqukba. Police asserts that raiders did not touch 'Iraq territory whilst Carrying out raid. Allegations against other individuals mentioned in Kuwait's no.383 will be investigated. / High Commissioner - cTelegram uode resident Bus hi re To -folitioal Kuwait ^0.568 Dated 14th June 1329. Arriving slow mail accompanied by Croning. Can Sheikh find us accomaaodation till steamer returns• - RESIDENT -Telegram Code Prom resident Bushire To political Kuwait no.572 uated 14th June 1929. Wirj# Goiiiinaiicier uliYer will arrive at Kuwait on June 18th instead of Air ufficer Commanding wiio is indisposed. - RESIDjshT -61/14 1172-15/6/29 Telegram Code ^rom Political Kuwait To Resident isushire Repeated Baghdad Eo»384 Dated 14th (received 15th) June 1929, Jfor information only. 3 'Iraq police cars arrived Jahrah Sunday and left again same day* - POLITICAL - 1 c ' s ji *** &amp;61/14 1173-15/6/29 Telegram j'rom To Kepeated Code political Kuwait He si dent Jiusiiire High Gommissioner for •xi^acL, Administrative Inspector, Basra and Special# No*585 Dated 14th (received 15th) June 1929 7 J'or the last 2 days there have been rumours tkacfc of a coming raid by AJman and Ibn ffiashhur# reliable information available reports raid on very iarge scale started yesterday morning Thursday* Destination of raiders unknown departure kept very secret* - POLITICAL - **•* Z 7 / ■ x ! /f/s ij6l/l4 1175-15/6/29 Telegram J'rom To Kepeated Code political Kuwait He si dent uu shire Baghdad, Administrative Inspector and special* 110*387 Dated 14 tlx (received 15th.) June 1929. Sheikk reports Faisal Dawish /A J filM I 7 recently summoned isqaimi Al Suwait and his following to Artawiyaii; as latter refused to attend mutair raided and carried off majority of his camels. a. ■ - - POLITICAl *** p C6i A* 1176-15/6/29 Telegram. uode ^ ro111 Political Kuwait iteaident J3ushire Ho.388 Bated 14th (received 15th) June 1929. tAAsvr JirY high Commissioner for 'Iraq's jno .203 f of 13tii June. Surely statement of man wlio actually took part in raid is of more value than evidence of •Iraq, police. - POLITICAL ***io C- '- - :3o' 7„D I Telegram P # 61/14 From Political Agent, Bahrain. ?©• Political Resident, Bushire* No. 79 o Dated tlie 15tli (reed 16th) June 1929t» Delegate has not yet arriyed.Bin Jilawi and Qusaishi receiyed telegraphic instructions from Jedd%tu It is stated 'by responsible JTinancial official from Hassa that there is not a piastre in the Treasury etnd that payments are na&gt;t ahle to he made 'by him- Ahove refers to your telegram No 566.q?el®CTam Tram. Political Resident, Bushire* T©» Secretary of State for the Oolnies^fto 15 Repeated Foreign, Simla, High Commissioner, Baghdad and British Agent, Jeddah No 579» Datedthe 16th June 1929^ «■* m* m* m*'*- Political Agent Bahrain has heart from responsible financial official from Hasa that treasury there is empty and that payments are unahle to 'be made 'by him# Ahofe is with reference to sale of arms tc Bin Saud*61/14 1194-16/6/29 1M 0 Telegram Prom To 110.623 Dated 16th (received i7th) June 1929, Code Political Bahrein Resident BusMre A Definite reports now place number at 25()• - POLITICAL - **■*8GPS...621...1081...5,000...18 9 28. n . s.o COITT'IDEMTIAL. i?/' _BUP'-::-^c RESIDENCY, f H. C. F. 16. SECRETARIAT OF H. E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ t n- h'Vj- 192 9. OCSflOEJ'TWL REC0RO8. By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked below is forwarded with compliments to :— The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . The Political Agent, Kuwait, Orientar Secretary- to H. E, The High Commissioner for 'Iraq, Enclosures :— Confidential memorandum Bo # S.O. ( dated 13 -6-29, from this Secretariat to the Ministry of the Interior, Baghdad t s t ^ VW|.i' gflj .i.-j,. t' 0 ' . ZeerBt-ii- | f| th4j Hig&gt;i Cofti-ui^sioiier for 1 Xrti&lt;| t I Tj , 1929 # To:- The Ministry of the Interior # BagMa^ (2 copies), ^©moroMm , the Shaikli of Kwmit hass intimated that as there are no Ioniser any f Iraq tribes in Kmrait, he considers it unnecessary for * Iraq polioo cara to enter his territory. His Maesellency the High Co mimM lonef con %t\in attitude rem @one^le« Police cars were only permitted to enter Kuwait for the purpose of pretecting 1 IraQ tribes ^rusing in Kuwait territory, ana it was never intended that they ahould oroso the frontier with nny other object, such a« # . for exaraple tlu^ o.r trying to recover loot tu.ken fro® tribes in * toM| t X am directad to express the hope that orders m«iy he issued for the strict ohserv^me of the principle ind ic r.te c abov e, Sd-JJj.J l Buu. ■ Counsellor -to K # B, the lli^h Comissioner for • Iraq, 'oplea (3) to:- Air ifeadqumrterB, liinsidi.Confidential* Mo. 219-H. of 1929. / Britieh Kesidenpy and Consulate-fieneral, Bushire, 17th June 1929. A copy of the unaer-noted paper is forwarded to # Political Agent at Kuwait for information only. By Order, hd 0^, /I ^ / Captain, Secretary to the Political Keaident in the Persian Gulf. tiie Goijfidential memorandum no. 5.0. 1219, dated l^th June 1929, from the Secretariat of H.JS. the High Commissioner for f Iraq, to the Ministry of the Interior, Baghdad. v (Heceived under endorsement iio. B.O. 1220, of 13th June 1929, from the Secretariat of H.-k. the High Commissioner for Iraq.)Confidential. Britifih Kesidency and Gonfmlttte-General, Bub hire, 17 th June 1929. Ne. 28. Sir, With reference to the corroBpondence ending with my despatch no. 27, dated the 11th June last, x have the ...... honour t© 1. Kuwait telegram Ho. 383 of 11-6-1929. 2. Kuwait telegrara No. 385 of 14-6-1929. 3. Kuwait telegram JHo. 387 of 14-6-i.929. 4. Baghdad telegram w 207 of 13-6-1929. 5. Bahrain telegram M 623 of 16-6-1929. fo rward for the in formation of His liajesty'a Oove rnment coiiies of tlie telegrams noted in the margin. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. CJ\ Lieut.-Colonel, Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. m HIS MAJESTY^ SECRI^TARY O? BTATK TOR THE COLONIES, COLONIAL OFFIGK, LONDON.Telegram C. J'roEi Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Kesident, uushire. JNo. 751. i3ated Jand receiYed 17th ) Junel92 9. immDikTK. . The Mesopotamia-Persia Corporation, Limited, inform me mail is expected here on the 20th June. Presume you willinform wing Commander uiaviSK of any change of date. - POLITICAL.Telegra m. RJL - {2S3) -vM 1 ^ T©^ BUitisti Agenti, Jeddah,No 6S» Repeated to Baghdad. No 198, Political Hesident BusMre aM. Political Agents Kwait* Dated tlie 18th (reed 19th) June 19E9* Your/ telegrams 79 and 81*. You should inf orm Bin Saud that Eis Majesty^s Government are concerting measures for co-operation British forces with those of Sheikh of Kuwait with a view to preventing improper use of Kuwait territory 'by any refugees from NejJcU As His Majesty has already 'been informed 'by Sir Gilhert Clayt ®n direct adeauate measures have 'been takento prevent such refugees from obtaining asylum in • •Iraq&gt; In tkese circumstances a^estion of Kejd forces crossing Kuwait does not arise» His Majesty will appreciate,however, that there would,in any case, have 'been serious political objections to such a course* As regards other points you should inform Bin Saud TP that Sheikh indignatly denies allegations and suggests that possible source of leakage of supplies are Bin Saud t s Awazim allies in Hasa and loyal Akhwan who purchase food in Kuwait with Bin Saud*s permission^ and remove (it ? ) 'by sea^ His Majesty*s Government are,however, examining the whole question with a view to establishing facts* f c-u-A-t jl &gt;r ^Telegram R» (z^J (ri/'U From* Searetary ot State for tlie Colonies, Lindoiu To. High Commissioner, Baghdad Ho 199, Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Kuwait and British Agent, Jeddalu Dated the 18th (reed 19th) June 1929. See Foreign Office telegram to Jeddah repeated to you 198. I presume that necessary steps are 'being talcen in consultation with Resident,Bushire, for assisting the Sheikh of Kuwait to expel Nejd refugees^ See in this connection my predecessors 163 May 11th and last paragraph of Bushire telegram May 18th repeated to you 45 4 f reference to your telegram Eune 9th^ Hts MajestyGovernment would prefer not to raise auestion^ Allowing forces to enter neutral zone unless or until either (l) I'bn Saud raises question hinself or (E) need for action in that area becomes urgent*«hh 61/'' 1213-19/6/29 Telegram Prom To No.753 Dated and received the 19th June 1929. Goae r oli tical Kumait Resident Bushire IMI v IBDIAT l S . yollowins f roin High Commissioner for ^raq, Baghdad, begins ,l Please inform Resident in the Persian Gulf that if he v/ould like to visit Baghdad after conference 1 shoula be delighted to see him and put him up and R.A.IT. will convey him here and oack.' ends. - POLITICAL -' (t *** mmT^le^raon EN Glair jProm Resident Sushire To Aviati on 15a^hdad RepeatedPolitical Kuwait No. Nil Dated the i9th June 1929, IMMEDIATE. Slow mail delayed Bahrein i cannot reach Kuwait till Saturday. - RESIDENT - ***-i 6i/i4 rnrnmaa ,2i6-i9/6/29 v' Telegram Prom To Ho.390 Dated ana received the i9th June i929. uode Political Kuwait Kesident i3usnire iiave reaeived tv/o telegrams from London dated 18th June in cypher which l am unable to decode and do not think i possess. Can you assist as presume they addressed you and repeated here, - POLITICAL - Telegram ■From To 110 .597 Datea the'igth June 1929 ***• Code Resident Bushire Political Kuwait Xour 390. Bringing you copies RSSIDE1TTr- k/i iv/c iijhf If) ,&lt; — ^ From - Tiie Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the ^Foreign and Political Department, The -ion'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To Ifemorandum ITo. 76-IT, Dated Simla, the § June 1929. ■ RSSIDEKCY. | ifj-v J Supply of a^rms and ammunition to the Shaikh of Kuwait. a P ? 1 our memorandum -fo • 03-3. » date a th.6 23rd February 1929. 2. The Government of India sanction the supply on payment to the Shaikh of Kuwait of the arms and ammunition etc., ) specified in the margin. 1. Cartridges, S.A. Sail, .303-in MK YII Ifo. 50,000 2. Belts, ammunition, -303-iii, 250-rds. Eyelets, Long ITo. 4,500 Short Ho. 4,500 Strips, Long ITo. 2,500 Short Ho. 2,560 Braces, pouch, Lewis Gun, web ITo. 18 Pouches, magazine, Lewis Gu n, web. : 0 . 36 . Arrangements for their despatch to Kuwait as desired are being made. 3. The total cost to be recovered will be intimated on the priced vouchers furnished by the Chief Ordnance Officer, ^uetta. In addition to the value of the scores at priced voucher rates, 5 % departmental charges, the actual packing and freight charges and any special packing nece.- ary, will be charged for. Sd. J.G.Acheson, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Attested. Superintendent, foreign and Political Department. Copy, wit-h a, copy of the le cter and enclosure^ replied ■go , foruarded to the Army Deoartment, for information, and suci furtier action as may be necessary.s Mo. 223-S. of 1929. British He s id en cy and Consulate-General, Bushlre , the 20 th June 1929. A copy of the under-noted pax^er is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for infonnation, reference correspondence ending with this office memorandum no. 53-B., dated the 25rd February 1929, a copy of which was sent to him. By Order, % UIUL- Captain, Secretary to the political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. Subject : Supply of aras and ammunition to tht Shaikh of Kuwait. List of tapers . Memorandum Mo F.76-M., dated the 8th June 1929, from the Deputy Secretary (Foreign) to the Gov eminent of India,Simla.Telegram FroBio. British Agen|;, Jeddalu .^ V b To- Foreign Ofi'ioe, London»90 Repeated to Politioal Agent, Kuwait,Political Resident Bnsliire and Government of India No 123* Datedtlie 19tli (reed EOth) June 49S9o. It has 'been 'brought to the notice of the Hedjaa aovernment that some days ago Feisal Daweish left Artawiya to join Ajman and I'bn Mashxar» He requests that oommunications 'betv/een rebels and Kuv/alt will he prevented 'by His Majesty*s Grovernment and that any one from Kuwait and Mesopotamia will he prevented 'by the Mesopotamian Government from Joining them* He add^s that for the present occasion pnly the Eedjaa (Jovemment agree to rebels within Nejd territory Itself 'being hombed 'by British aeroplanes if nessary# PSTe^gram P . ki/ti. ~ From. British Agent, JadOah, Te. ^eoeretary of State for Foreign Affairs,London /91 Repeated to:- Higli Oommissioner, Baghdad, Dated the 19th(raod SOth) June 19S9^ Minister for Foreign Affairs explained that if n© aetiTe measures were taken hy His Majesty Sort 'both loyaL iuhjects and rebels would think that His Majesty*3 G-overnment encourage the latter to resist Bin Saud with the prospect that they would subsequently he allowed to seek asylum in Kuwait or Iraa* IrrespeRtiTe therefore of whether His Majesty*s Bfovtornment agree to other points raised,Bin Saud wished^ for sake of the moral as well as the material effect&gt; timt that aeroplanes should homh rebels immediately even if this entailed Grossing into Nejd territory# A fanatical letter,purporting to hare heen addressed to Amir Saud of Riyadh hy Feisal Daweish urging raids on infidels was shown to me 'by Minister for Foreign Affairs&lt;. He stated that this proves that and active assistance from His Majesty^ Government is called for 'by the present position. Reference is to my telegram immediately proceeding* Boreign, Simla# Political Resident, Bushire , Political Agent, Kuwait Ko 1E4* resolute1220 -20 /6/29 @) Telegram Code yrom Political Kuwait To Kesldlent Busiiire Repeated nigli Gormnisaioner for •Iraq^ ±5ailidad5 Administrative Inspector, Basr&amp;h, Special Hasiriyali and Special msrah. Ero*39i Dated i9th (received 20tli) June 1929. 61/14 Reliable informant reports raisal al Dawish with, all bis following arrived Jaryab near Subaihlyah from Safah.#. This means that he has joined up with Ibn Shuq^air and will probably now definitely throw in his lot with rebel Ajman* Faisal's messenger with letter for the bheikh of Kuwait arrived this morning. - POLITICAL -Telegram P» iti From* Political Resident, Bushire* T@# Political Agent, Kuwait,repeated to Higli Commissioner, Baghdad^ H©o 598tt Bated the EOtti June 1929 # ImportaBce ofavoiding even suspicion of Kuwaitis joining Bin Daweisli should 'be impressed on Sheiktu Foregoing is with reference to Jeddah^s telegram Ho 1?^- X X X X X X- X ■X-X'X--X-X-X-X-X-)f-X-^'X-61/14 Telegram Code Prom Resident Busnire To Hi^h Goinmissioner for •Iraq, Baghdad No.599 Dated the 20tli June i929. ThanK you for invitation to Baghdad which 1 gladly accept if extreme unpunctuality of slow mail renders yisit feasible. Now expect arrive Kuwait dawn Saturday. - RESIDENT - *** «■ w 6i/l4 Telegram IFrom To Rex^eated Code Political Agent, Kuwait Political Resident Bushire nigh Commissioner for •Iraq, iSa^hdad Administrative Inspector, Jjasrah Special Service Officer, Basrah. No.393 Dated atid received the 20th June 1929. t fu c 'P im ST My telegram no.3^5 of yestarde-y. Immediate. Correct version of news as follows:- Dawish at Jaryah al llya 70 miles south west of Wafra not Jaryah near Jytbaihiyah, latter does not exist# Sheikh visited me last night; confirms above. States he received letter from Dawish reporting he had evacuated Artawiyah and was moving to north of Hasa via Jaryah-al-llya. He asked for permission to camp at Subaihiyah. if granted, he guaranteed to pre vent Akhwan from committing any future hostile acts against 'Iraq, or Kuwait and would personally come to Kuwait and ratify agreement on these lines. If permis sion not granted he asked Shaikh to assure him that British v/ould not interfere with his coming operations in Hasa. Shaikh replied forbidding Dawish to camp at Subaihiyah or anywhere inside.Kuwait border, to second query Shaikh replied that he thought His Majesty's Govern ment would, remain neutral. Shaikh added that Dawish»s open defection serious matter for ibn Saud. Shaikh of opinion that rebels intend moving south on Hoffuf, while Utofuly would co -operate with Hedjaz and keep Ibn Saud there. Shaikh aays Dawish is brain behind whole movement. /&gt;&lt;• W61/14-VIII Telegram !?• From H.M's. High Commissioner for Iraq, JBaghdad- To Political Kesident, iiushire. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. ITo* 64-3. Dated (and receiTed ) 20th June 1929. IMMEDIATE « At the instance of the Air Officer Commanding and in view of the apparent possibility of large in- cl/rsion of liejd rebels into Kuwait,! venture to suggest that you should ask for slopp to proceed to Kuwait for the present. This might help to stiffen attitude of the Shaikh against rebels. HIGH OOHMiBSaOJNER. o I Telegram H. From H.l^s. Political «esident, iiushire. To The Senior JNaval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. 'TRIAD', No. 603. Dated 20th June 1929. IMMEDIATE . If you can spare sloop for Kuwait, i request that you will kindly send one. Kequest is made at the instance of the Air Officer Commanding, who is dis? quieted at news of possibility of large incursion of Hejd rebels. I am going to Kuwait as soon as transport can be arranged. - HESIDEWT. &lt;r ^ $ J J - ' T &lt;ruc&lt; sisrnsmrnsMm 61/14 Telegrwn R. From H.M's. High CoiamiBsioner for iraqi^ uaghdad TO H.M* s. Minister, Tehran, no. 107. Repeated H.M 1 s. Political Kesident, -^ushire , 215. Dated ^and received) 20tli June 19 29. Resident at J3ush4re is proceeding to Kuwait for conference, 'but boat is three days late. in view of 41ciiwan situation, urgent that he reach Kuwait earliest possible. Can you obtain permission for flying boat to proceed at once to ^ushire and take him to Kuwait. .Please inform Bushire direct if permission is granted. High Commissioner. Telegram R. From H.M*s. jfolitical Kesident, .bushire. To H.M's. Minister, Tehran, no. 79. Repeated H.M's. High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad, no. 604w Dated 20th June 1929. IMMEDIATE. Baghdad^ 107 If flying boat d^es not arrive before 9 Friday morning, 1 shall have left by steamer. - RESIDMT. 171 Telegram P. From H. H.M's. High Gommissioner for Iraq, ^ ^ d. H.M's* Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, iio. 237. 61/14 To | ) 65-S. (The Political Agent, Kuwait, ) Dated (and received) 20th June 192 9. IMMEDIATE! . The political Agent at Kuwait now reports that Faisal al Dawish has arrived at JARI^AH near SUJ3AIAilAH in Kuwait territory ahout forty miles south of Kuwait. Royal Air Force are xsxk sending out reconnaissance this evening. They will not take action unless fired on in view of difficulty of distinguishing AKHWAW with / certainty from Kuwait tribesmen. If they can he definM itely localted X proposer-subject to the Political 'Resident's concurrence, and in view of telegram dated the 14th May (»o. 352) from Kuwait, in which the latter intimated that jdaaocRttJbfix consent of the Ruler to use of military force 'by us to prevent rebel najd tribesmen from entering or remaining in Kuwait territory,—to attack rebels at once and thus comply with Ibn aaud^ requests ~~ vide telegram no. 91 from Jeddah to the Foreign Office. To be effective, it will be obvious that these measures will probably entail pursuing rebels into Mejd. As His Majesty has asked for it I am presuming that there will be no obj ectionr—vidje + 1 o mr» a rn f*'!a.TnOtr ® « Repeated by the Political Resident to the Governmenl of India, Foreign and Political Department, under No. 606, dated the 20th June 1929. P C 4s Ac H.M's. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, mo* .16* (H.M 1 s• Hi^n Commissioner for Iraq, ( Baghdad, ( (Political Agent, Kuwait, ;JSlo Hepeated( (Government of India, Foreign and :605, ( Political Department, Simla, &lt; (British Agent, fl)eddah. Dated 20th June 1929. Immediate (to Colonies and Baghdadonly) Political Agent at Jiuwait has now corrected his telegram. It is to Jariyah al Ilya 70 miles south west of Wafra that Faisal has gone, so he is not likely to enter Kuwait territory immediately. If they enter Kuwait territory, I agree that the Air Force should attack rebels at once. Above has reference to High Commissioners telegram Bo. 237. - KESIDENT. Post copy sent to the Political Agfcnts 4t Bahrain and Muscat.:26-20/6/29 ^1''' Telegram Code Prom Aviation i^a^hdad To Resident Busnire Ho.A.833 Dated and received the 20th June 1929. 0 t ' Flying boat now available to fetch you where convenient 2ist June or later if you wish, if ¥*** so^wil/you approach Persian Government if necessary. Reported here that slow mail will not reach Kuwait till 24th June. o - Aviation *** CA ^ YI i 61/14 r Telegram .P. From Political Agent, ivuwait. To H.M 1 s. Political Hgeident, tiushlre* Repeated H.M's. High Commissioner, Baghdad. Ho. 395« Dated (and received ) 20th June 1929. IMMEDIATE . Would far prefer that man-of-war did not come at present juncture. 1 see no reason to take alarming view —see my telegram of even date, no. 393. Foregoing has reference to High Commissioner's telegram Bo. 64-B. ^ % POLITICAL. '/fUl Telegram P. From Political Agent, Kuwait, To H.M's. High Commissioner, Baghdad. Repeated HM's. Political Kesident, Bushire. Ho. 396. Dated (and received ) 20th June 1929. IMMEDIATE . Of course my telegram Ho. 393 entirely alters situation. Letter fodlows. ^A Has reference to telegram ho . 65-S. from Baghdad. - POLITICAL.bj Telegram R. Prom Political Resident, isushire. To The Senior xiaval ufficer, Persian Gulf Division, M.m.S. m tHIAD m , JJIO . 607• Dated 20 th June 1929. IMMEDIATE . ^(&gt;3 Unless you can easily spare sloop and would like to 'be represented at conference on Saturday, I suggest you consider my 603 as cancelled as latest news from Kuwait considerably modifies situation existing when Baghdad wired me. ' V ) ^ KESXDEJST61/14 nJUj Te legram From To Repeated 1/ \ P» 7 . High CommisBioner, Baghdad. Secy, of State for Colonies, lio» 238. Political Resident, Bushire. British Agent, Jeddah. Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated and received 20th June 1929. As I have now received telegram from Political Agent, Kuwait, correcting his previous report and stating that Faisal al Dawish is not in Kuwait territory but at Jariyah al Ilya, about 85 miles south of the Kuwait frontier, please cancel my telegram No. 237. High Commissioner.Teltgram ^ /A y 7 , Frora® High Comrais sioner, Baglidafio To Secretary o State for the Colonies,London jso 238» Repeated to Political Hesident,i3usliire # British Agent, Jeddab. and folitival Agent, Huwaito Dated the 20th (reed 20th| June 1929# ^ telegram Ho 237 should now he canoe lied# 1'elegraxa from Kuwait saying that previous report is not correct and that ifeisal al Daweish is nob in Kuwait territory but at Jariyah al Ilya about 85 mil; s south of Kuwait frontier,has now been received by me»61/14 Telegram Code 11,1,0111 Political jsesldent uushire ^' 0 Political A^ent JSahrein ^o.602 Dated aoth June 1929^ i Please wire me at Kuwait all Hasa news re^ardin^ movements of Dawish^including rumours^and send me daily mainland news report. 1 can sift true from false. / - Kesident - ***o Y'Q o ^ To'»~ Political,Kuwait. HDomJ'' Hlgjri Commissioner,Baghdad. No:n 243 # Datei** 21 0 &amp; w 2© # Addressed:- Sedretary State colonies,349,Aeptd.Bu8hire,jed&amp; Kuwait. My immediately preceding telegram also Jeddah's telegram No.S.&amp;O and ©I to Foreign Office. I am in favour i in principle of granting Ibn Saud*s request to attack rebe^ in Najd territory, provided it is made clear to Ibn saud that we cannot commit ourselves to continuous operations against his rebellious tribes in Najd, and that action against them can only be taken when definitely located within range of our aircraft. It would be dangerous to commit Ourselves to operations which might extend in scale and from which it would be difficult to withdraw without loss of prestige. A.O,C # concurs.^eXtigriga Senior SaTal Officer^ M«iu8&gt; iad« # Busliireradio» jeo litcal, Re sid cnt # Buahirc. NO* 1029, Dated and reed the 2lRt June 1929 important* Your telegram jfo 607* Senior Maval Officer will eitlier attend Conference or Bend an officer# Opinion ©f Senior itaTal Officer is that presence of man^of«*rar undoubtedly girea feeling of security to townspeople: and would probably frighten attacking force if ignorant and undi b cipllned # but land forces are proper defence Sxm for a town from an attack on landward side* 'Cyclamen* and 'Lupin 1 are clianging places# Latter will stay # until further notice,in northern section and will always be within a few hours call of Kuwait which Senior jiaval Officer con~ aiders better than stationing her there# She will risit Kuwait occasionally# Senior MaTal Officer will Tiait Kuwait in •Triad • about 28th June# Above repeated to iMUat Kuwait imder iio 610 dated the 22nd June 1929 with the reisairk f Ho action has beeai taken here 1 #- ;x , OgmBENTIAL. ot 1929. iiritiah iXeBidency &amp; Consulate General, i^usiilra, the He ^ June i929 # A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded, v/ith compliments, to the Political Secretary to His Excellency the Hijh Commissioner for 'Iraqp -ba^hdadp for information# By order. uapt Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* • % Subject:- Akhwan Situati on* l*ist of papers# 1. Bushire telegram flo,603 of 20th June 2. JJuahire telegram iro .607 of 20th June 1929.Vl/JL*. n o Telegram Code» ^Tom Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, at Kuwait. No. 644. Dated 21st received 22nd Jtine 1929. Eumoured from mainland that three days ago Nejd authorities at Qjatif, Juhail, Ujair and Darin stopped all 2Tejd navigation, especially divers who came to take shelter against shamal, from leaving those ports and ( ? omission*warned* ?) them to he ready for defence against Ajman, who were reported to fesxai have 'been march- -ing against Hasa. This morning ^Friday news from Qatif is that they were allowed to leave for 'bank this - morning. The inhabitants of Hasa and the Nejd ports are in a disturbed state. Jehad has 'been enforced for the third time and hundreds are going to ( mut. ? join) On account of non-payment of prices foodstufifs are very dear in Nejd. As roads from ports to Nejd is unsafe merchants have stopped exports to interior. Dawish is reported to he alive at Artawiyah. Shaikh Muhammad, brother of Ihn Saud who attempted against latter*s life last year and who was taken with him to Hejaz, is reported to have escaped and has joined the Utaihah. POLITICAL.Telegram (c). prom - Barrett, Kuwait. To - High commiBSipner, Baghdad. No. K/l. Dated 22nd Jane 1929. Your '.ww. Will be very pleased to come to Baghdad It R.A.P. will get me back to Kuwait by 5 p.m. Tuesday. Barrett.ITelegrani p. prom - Resident, Kuwait. To - Higli commissioner, Baghdad. No. K/2. Dated 22nd June 1929. i giiaikh of Kuwait has consented to 'Iraq police oars aooompanying Mesopotamian tribes to protect them and act as buffer between them and raiders. He objects however to 'iraq police reconnoitering far in advance of their proteges. H© asics that British cars conduct any reconnaissances as he can trust them to behave properly. He spoke in very bitter terms of the •Iraq patrols which he said took false reports to their officers and caused endless friction. The head police officer at Safwan is an ex-servant of the shaikh whom he distrusts. Resident.Dfeiegram C0&lt;ie. From - RbBident, Kuwait. To - Higb. Ctommisj3ioner, Baghdad. J V No. K/3. Dated 22nd june 1929. Bahrain reports irumours that divers who were pre vented from leaving Hasa port in order that they might defend them against Ajman were permitted to return to pearl banks on 21st June. Owing to insecurity of roads merchants have dis continued despatch of goods to interior. Unconfirmed rumours that ibn saud»s brother Mahamad has joined Ataibah. Rbsident.giblLegrain pi r- ■ proE - Resident at Kftwalt. 50 - secretary of'State for colonies, Repeated to Oovemment of Indlaj High commissioner for 'Iraq copy to political Agent, KJiwai'^. i jm NO-K/4. Dated 22nd June 1929. This morning the shaikh of jjiwait infoimed me that though he liked Bin Saud I personally, he hated his policy and would like to see him defeated. Arabia might then fall into anarchy, tribe against tribe, but their civilized neighbours would be left alone by the tribes. Hb is confident that Ajman Awazim^tair^and^whom he looks upon as fliwait tribes seduced by Bin Baud,would return to Kuwait alltgAance. ' He claims that in addition to aid granted to Bin Saud by the late Shaikh MUbarak,he himself loaned sixty thousand dollars and sent fifteen hundred bags of rice to assist Bin saud during the siege of Hail. She money has never been repaid and instead of showing gratitude f or favours received Bin Saud first rendered Kuwait defenceless by obtaining, with the help apparently of Sir Percy Cox, transfer of allegiance of its tribes, then blockaded the town and ruined its trade for the sake of a difference about customs which could have been adjusted without difficulty. He now calls on the State which he has bereft of its strength and ruined financially to repel from its frontiers its own subjects whom he first seduced from their allegiance and then ty his treachery goaded to rebellion. Shaikh, Ahmad considers that the attacks on Kuwait during 1927/28 were all made by direct order of Bin saud. Shaikh says that if left to his own devices he would not aSBist malcontents with ams but he would certainly not work against interests of his own merchants by forbidding export of food in exchange for money. While holding these sentiments Shaikh considers that he is bound in honour to cany out British policy,conse quently he has forbidden the rebels to enter his territory. _ i!-!.:'!!';:'!:' 11 r^s and lias proMbited trade witii them. I reoonmiend tliat i may be authorised to inform the Shaikh that if he acts in loyal co-operation with His Majesty's Government at the present Juncture they will make every et ort to secure for him an honourable settle- the ment with Bin Saud of kiac dispute, whereby the merchants of Kuwait may be enable to resume their former trade with northern Nejd. The chief stumbling block to a settlement i* in the Shaikh^ opinion, Qusaibi, who having taken the customs farm for the southern ports is preventing any rapprochement • Reference Baghdad's 242. As a concession to shaikh's sentiments I recommend that operations ac^ross NeJd-KUwait frontier should not be conducted from Kuwait territory except in case of hot pursuit. Resident, I -J. jPiwnTelegram I?rom To Repeated P* Secretary of State Tor Colonies, Lon High Commissioner, Baghdad. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait, British Agent, Jeddah. Ho. S00. Dated and received 22nd June 1929. A &amp; i As intimated in my telegram No. 299 (? 199) of 18th June and Foreign Officer' telegram to British Agent ^fjeddah, repeated to you under No. 198, His Majesty's Government recognise their ohligation to assist Ihn Saud hy co-operating with the Shaikh of Kuwait in preventing the improper use of the latter*s territory 'by Nejdi refugees. In discharging that obligation they are prepared to auth- -orise you in the event of Faisal ad Dawish's entry into • Kuwait territory, to take action a gainst him sis proposed / in your telegram No. 237. His Majesty's Government consider however that the frontier should not he crossed except in hot pursuit and unless contact has 'been maintain- -ed with the '£&amp;£&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;* They could not agree to aero- w _ -planes crossing the frontier merely to search for rebels or to initiate operations in Nejd,as appears to he con- 27/ — -templated in your telegram No. 242. In any event it appears very undesirable that ground forces should exist on the frontier. ^ From your telegram No. 239' I note that air action is not proposed unless either aircraft are fired upon or rebels are definitely located. I agree that these Qonditlons should be strictly observed and that every precaution should be taken to ensure against any possibility of air actionbeing taken against innocent tribesmen. To this I attach the greatest importance. You should request Air Officer Commandins to instruct officers concerned to exercise every precaution and in no circumstances to attack rebels unless they are defin- -itely identified as such. s ' of s * fQr Colonies -Confidential. Mo. Mr of 1929. British nesidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, Uie ^S^June 1929. A copy of the under-noted papers is forwarded, with compliments, Senior naval Officer, rersian Gulf Division, •TRIAD', Basrah, for information only. Cap tai n, for Political Kesident in the Persian (Julf. X, Telegram Wo. 5, dated the 19th June 1929, from H.M # s. Secretary of Btate for foreign Affairs, London, to H.MJs. Minister, reliran. 2. Bushire Reaidenqy telegr^im lio.78/600, dated Lhe 20th June 192 9.■ Telegram From To 61/14, Code, Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, at Kuwait, No. 652» Bated E2nd received E3rd June 1929 An arrival from Nejd yesterday evening, Friday, reported that the forces of Ihn Saud from ( ? omission} destroyed G-hatghat, capital of ITdu Humaid. He also said Faisal ad Dawish has moved from Artawiyah with the intention of camping at Attawal, near A1 Hafar, which is three days from Kuwait POLITICAL. a. -1 D 6i/i4 1^46-23/6/29 Telegram JTrom To Repeated Bo.217 Dated 22nd (received E3rd) June i9E9. uode nigh Commissioner for ♦Ira^, Baghdad political resident i3usliire Political A^ent Kuwait v^/ Kuwait telegram no.ssi lias been sent to Secretary of state for the Colonies arid Jeddah. - EIGHCOEA - *** nwnw -61/14 Telegram p. From aovernment ot India, Simla. To Secretary of State for India, London, Repeated political Resaident, B^siire, at K^alt. High Commissioner, Baghdad. HO. 2038-S. Dated and received 24th June 1929. '4- Though, at first sight Ibn Saud 1 s request for our cooperation appears attractive it has its obvious dangers. We trjtst it does not foreshadow any serious weakening of his authority. to afford our support to an Oriental Ruler against his tribesmen is exacts what Amanulla asked us to do and, in the case of a ruler who is also Ki&amp;g of the Hejaz there are added dangers. It seems very questionable therefore whether we should bomb his tribesmen in Nejd unless in hot pursuit or unless there are definite indications that they are out to raid in Iraq or Kuwait. The foregoing refers to correspondence ending with Bushire telegram No- K/4. POREI(B$ (f 7 /?. aJ- ^ ^ iiVw -f-SGPS...621...1081...5,000...18 9 28. SECRST. No.. S.o. /'^ 7 i**U £bV:- f s # SECRETARIAT OF H E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ 5T^ June, 192 9. By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked ' ^low is forwarded with compliments to :— The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Oriental Secretary to H. E. The High Commissioner for 'Iraq, Enclosures Despatch Secret dated /7-6-29 f to the Colonial Office, with its enclosure, regarding the losses inflicted on ♦Iraq tribes by Najdi raiders since May 1928. ✓ T.C, mmmsrklfid or in oashg and I eneloa® m copy ®f thU Xiot her«wiUu it 1m© feeert eheoked by Air E^iiqiiarterii and ©©i^mrad with information o&amp;tain#&lt;! from independent mov &amp;&amp;B® mUfi J that, in main, it,s figures are sni^ntaatiaiiir ^orrcfdl^ 4, Fro,:.; your telegram ^o. 1?1 dated th© 21 »t ©f Mmr# 1929, I understand that Hie CoT«m»«nt teTe air*?sidy inetrmted the British Agent sat Jiadah te profit fr©m the oppertunity afforded by the provision of fttm ana a«unitioii to the U&amp;jQ. Bm&amp;rmmm %u remind to of the imm quantities of Xeet t^ken from * Ira^i tribes by hio ineurgeltnt chieftains. ^ma I hope tlmt fe# my new ins true ted formlly to present to the Government in the name of Hie Britannia Majesty 1 &amp; Oevemment the claim which hae hmn put forward by the * IreQ Oevernjaent, 5 # ¥au will notice het the r^iie in the list., with the exoeption of the first, mil occurred out®Me * Ir&amp;e territory either in M&amp;J4 or Kuwait, mi it is poeeihle, thouij^# %• think, unlikely that the Hnjit Oeverm»erit my argue- that they are uncer no ohligatlen to reetere lm% t^kmn from 1 Irm^i tribe® while they are freeing in tho^e territories, * 6, It le true that in neither the mr the Bahra Agreeaent is there any jireeiee re.terenee•» 3 ^ i# th#- obligation ©f either §m®Twamn% to r^^tor# loot, no natter where it m-y be but I conBider that thmxm are rAdequ.»te %¥&amp;&amp;$&amp;&amp; for GmitGn&amp;in% that the mutual restitution ®f loot is inh*T®m% in the iipirlt, t if not th# lett@r # of 4rticsXe I of the? h^mmmnt &amp;nd Artiolee I and 2 of the Bafcra Agre^aamt* ?. Mor«oir«r claims for th# restitution of loot taken tuteia® the bordere of the claiming party have tJie emnction of Arab custom and Ihu &amp;m*W&amp; himself ha® frequently in pa®t year® made Ql&amp;tm for the restitution of loot UOcen from iiaj4i tribes or caravans while in 1 Xr^q territory. 8. I suggeett therefore, that the claim® should be presented in aeooNtance with the spirit of /\rtiole 2 of the Bahm Agreement, and 1 hope that it will be presented with the full m&amp; strong support ©f li® Britoioio .Majesty 4 ^ Government. 9, X mm mmitnti copies of this ^-eepatoh to His Majesty 1 *5 .^wt and Consul mt Jidd®h f together with tn Arebic translation of the * Imwi ©evera^ent 1 ® list of clateio # and to the i-olitio^l E#«i#ent in the Persian Oulf, Bushire, I have the honour to be t Sir^ Your »at obedient, humble servant, *?&amp;) Gilbert Clay to. ■ aioh m%: i xoum - *. » II^h. t,cNo.. 8GPS.. 621...1081...5,000...18 9 23. GONFirSIITIAL . s.M^Tz BU' f R: rjl Baghdad, H. C. F. 16. SECRETARIAT OF H. E. THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR IRAQ is 4 ' June, 192 S. By direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for iraq, a copy of correspondence as marked 'Now is forwarded with compliments to :— The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (Reference this Secretariat letter Ho. S.0.1107 dated 27-5-1929). / /j./ Orientja^T Secretary to H, E. The High Commissioner for 'Iraq. Enclosures :— Despatch Confidential dated M-6-29, to the Colonial Office, London, with its enclosure, regarding the inducements offered by Ibn Sa'ud to 'Iraqi tribes to settle in Uajd. T.C.conyw^miAL &amp; uac .:,v . iso. 692. 'Iraq Ministry for loreign Baghdad t 10th Juno, 1929. To;- The Secretary to H/E, the High Comission^r for 1 Ira^t Baghdade It hae reached ub that Ibn ha© recently presented 9 A i&amp;imi i1?n with a H bairaG w , the news of this presentation has caused some commotion among the JDhafir residing in 'Iraq, since, a® It not hid froQ Your Excellency, although a haIraq in itself is no important thing, its presentation to h Shaikh • besides being one of the greatest marko of distinction that Ibn 8a , ud is capable of granting - makes the recipient a iihalkh of standing; while the presentation is generally accompanied by fin adequate salary ana .a quantity of arm®, clothing and aupplies, to enable the recipient to maintain mn outward appearance befitting the dignity he ha® acquired as a ^general officer 5 ' (eic) of the Akhwun forces, Ibn 3a 1 ua. is said to haire declared that his present tion of the bairoq to 'Aj^imi ibn Kuwait wan a reward to the latter for the service® rendered by him at the S&amp;bla battle. fhm facts ox the ease, however, indicate that the Dhafir have rendered only trifling services at ^abla, having regard to their losses at that battle, which consisted of one mm. On the other hand a considerable number of the Bhmmx bedouin® were present at S&amp;bla, but there ie no talk 5otalk of them having been presented witb any fcairaq, Ib oase, it ia ditTioult to allay the feeliB® aroused fey the preoentation of the bairaq to 1 Ajaimi ibn Sttwait that lay doing Ifen Sa'ud wished, to pursue a policy of reinforcing the Akhwan nucleus with men from the Dhafir found on the frontier ssone, of winning over other 1 Iraqi tribes, and of allowing the Dimfir of 1 Iraq no opportunity to gain any influence or authority in the desert. As its not hid from you, tribe© and Shaikhs undergo periods of rising influence and authority ae well as periods of decline and aubmieeion, but the influence of tribes in dependent on the authority and power acquired by their leaders. Accordingly, with the Dawiah now fallen and ♦Ajaimi ibn Suwait iiven a bairaq, the Dhafir and the Harb of Muhein Al-Farm ^ill become (paramount) tulera in northern Should thie take place, it would furnish oauae for the winning over of many more of the other Ehafir to liajd. Beeidee the foregoing, the presentation of a bairaq to ♦Ajaimi ibn Kuwait by Xbn ^a'ud cannot be reconciled with Article 4 o the lahra Agreement, In view of the foregoing, we request that a protest should be made to Ibn Sa'ud in thin connection, since it appears that 1 Ajaimi Ibn Swwait i» likely to spend the euimer in the Neutral Sone, and the presence of an Akhwan bairaq in the said zone will give rise to eome suapicion ' : ?a to the attitude of the JDhatir* Sd/- tawfiq Al*Suvitidi 9 Minister for Foreign Affair#.CONFIDENTIAL. V| 10 NO.394. politioal Agenoy, Kuwait. Dated the 2otii jime 1929. From Lieutenant-colonel H.R.p.Diokson, C.I.E.) politioal Agent, Kuwaiti The Hon'bl© the Politioal Resident in the persian Q-ulf, B^-shire. Sir, Subjectintelligence. in continuation of my telegram No. 393 dated the 19th June 1929, I have the honour to report in detail the converBation which I had with ik His Excellency the ShaiKh of Kuwait on the subject of the communication which he received from Faisal al- Dawish, as I think it may be found of interest. 2. The Shaikh called on me yesterday evening at 5 p.m. (19th June 1929) and said he had some important information to give me. 3. He had received, he said, a letter from paisal al-Dawish written from es-safa (Oawah), and dated 17th June 1929 (English date) to the effect that he Faisal had evacuated Artwwiyeh with all his people, as he definitely could no longer trust Ibn Sa'ud or his promises. That he had arrived at es-Safa, and from there intended moving north into Hassa via wabra and jariya al-llya (7o miles south-south west of Wafrah). That at the latter place he would halt pending receipt of a reply from the Shaikh of Kuwait to his message. 4. Next followed the main portion of the letter, which His Excellency the Shaikh said was a request to himself to allow him to settle his whole tribe at Subaifciyeh immediatly in Kuwait territory, in return for such permission, he was pre pared to give a guarantee to His Majesty's Government that th© whole of the northern Akhwan under his control would at once and for the future desist from any hostile act against either- 3 - (teu) ♦jraq or Kuwait: he would, be prepared to oome into Kuwait and ratify in writing any agreement on these lines that His Majesty's Oovemment liked, and he requested the shaikh of Kuwait to act as '•wasta^ between himself and His Majesty's Qovernmerb. 5. should the Shaikh not see his way to grant his request, he paisal added that he would remain at jariya el*-Ilya and jariya el-Sif'fe (places olose together and commonly known as al~(^arraiyat) where the Fuqum and Ibn shugair were encamped, and await developments. 6. in the latter event he would still promise on behalf of the Mutair, Akhwan^that no raids or hostile acts against 'Iraq or Kuwait would take place, but he would like the assurances of the Shaikh of K^ wa i't on the following two points;- (a) If he waged open war against Ibn Sa^d in Hassa territory would tie, Shaikh Ahmad, promise that the British would not attack him with aeroplanes? (b) If he moved further south and attacked jubail, (^atif or Hoffuf would the British remain neutral? 7. His Excellency went on to say that as the messengers (5 rikaibs) requested an immediate reply, he had already sent reply to jiaisal al-Dawish definitely refusing him permission to &lt; camp at subaihiyeh, or in any other part of Kuwait territory. As regards S'aisal^ other two requests he had (by verbal message) given it as his opinion that His Majesty^ Government would not interfere or attack jaisal^s people so long as they confined their operations to Hassa and proper i.e. the territories of ibn Sa'ud, and that so long as they killed each other outside Kuwait or •iraq borders it was no concern of His Majesty's Q-overnment. 8« His Excellency the Shaikh thought that perhaps he ought to have consulted me first but said that that would, have meant delay and the messengers of iiaisal had demanded a reply by the evening of the 19th june 1929. There was some force in what His Excellency said. 9. His Excellency next gave it as his opinion that what he had been expecting for days had now happened* paisal al- Dawish had at last openly thrown in his lot with the Ajman,the Puqum, ibn shugair, ibn Mashur and other rebels and had evidently decided the time for action had oome. The demand to be allowed to settle his people at subaihiyeh was for a two fold purpose. (a) it was the most desirable spot in the whole of Kuwait from a grazing and water point of view. (b) in the event of things going wrong he hoped to have already made his peace with His Majesty 8 s Government and would have a safe refuge to retire to. 'Faisal was a kelb-ibn-lcelb with the brain of an astute Hathari' (the Shaikh # s words) rt and his was the brain of the whole move ment against Ibn sa'ud without doubt'. lo- His Excellency believed that things were about to take for a very serious turn^^xaaa ibn s^'ud, and that the objective of the Mutair cum Ajman would probably be Hoffuf itself, and that the Ataiba, who had sworn to co-operate, would probably attack the Hejaz and keep Ibn Sa'ud occupied, while ibn Jaloui was isolated and mopped up. 11. His Excellency added that the movement in his opinion was wide spread and extended to qasim where the Town of 'Anaiza' had secretly agreed to support 5iaisal , s rebellion provided that he paisal would guarantee that if he were successful he would gua rantee free movement of the people of (^asim to and from Kuwait, the denial of which post hast reduced them to the uttermost penury 12. Throughout our talk His Excellency, I could sec, was excited, and whether correctly or not, it was clear he not only believed that the day of Reckoning for Ibn sa'ud was not far tc, 0- C ' distant, but showed he was in sympathy with the rebels* aims. When I asked him how he had got hold of the details he had given me, he broke out into a '^tirade' against Ibn sa'ud. 'Though i ftm outwordly friendly', he said, 'and though I personally cannot resist liking t^s Abdul Aziz as a man, I hate his policy, his ingratitude and dishonesty. He has strangled Kuwait and killed us, and this in spite of all we have done for him. He even now owes me 60,000 Reals in cash apart from the cost of untold food supplies sent him by me for the capture of Hail. I am genuinely glad he is in difficulties, as perhaps a better day is d/'awningdawning for Kuwait, if I were not bound to His Majesty's Govern- ment toy treaties and was anxious to please toy every means in iny powers I should have already sent out my standard to Hassa and led the rebellion in person against the King. Iton sa'ud would isacsoe fare toadly if I were to throw in my weight on the other side He then added with a smile that what he had said were his private thoughts entirely^and trusted j would keep them to myself. I oould not help remarking that it was a lucky thing he was a sensible man and knew on whioh side 'his bread was touttered'. At this he smiled and left me. in oonolus ion I would like to say that the wells marked Variya' on our mapg as toeing slightly north of Subaihiyeh, do not exist at all. The Shaikh assured me most positively of this. The name is unknown he said. I would suggest that all oonoerned be informed. Copy to His Exoellenoy the High Qommissioner for # iraq, Baghdad, with compliments. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. \J ^ V/ / ] Lieut-Col., political Agent, Kuwait. * ■-r&gt; \ . • V luts C ONFIDMIIAL , % '&gt;/' L - No.389. 17tk June 1929 Political Agency, Kuwait. ^irV 1 /?o?) Prom To R [h I—- fit RtCQBO S^ | Lieutenant-G olonel H,E # P»I)ick£on,C •I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'TDle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, lushire. Subject:- Smuggling of supplies from Kuwait to Ajman, and Ihn Mashur's rebels at Wafrah. V 0 1 Sir, I have the honour to refer you to your telegram No.539 dated 13th June 1929 in which you reguested me to (a) examine and report on the question of smuggling r (h) submit a report on the force His Excellency the Buler could raise for the protection of his frontier, 2 # Smuggling (a). In dealing with this question, it should he realized from the start that in Kuwait, there are many Ajman, Mutairfe, Awazim as well as other tribal elements who have many years ago settled in the Town, and who are to-day registered and looked upon as 'Hathar' as opposed to their nomad brethren the 'ledu' Most of these earn their living by Pearl diving, and except for the old men, women and boys, all go out to the lanks by the middle of May and do not return till September. All are under the direct control of the Sheikh of Kuwait, 5. Those left behind, leave the precincts of the city and go into camp round the wells situated just outside the city walls, forming small settlement du ring the summer. They do this, (a) because it is cooler than in the Town (b) to avoid buying water which is costly inin summer, (c) in order to graze their sheep and goats within safe distance of the Town, {^) l t&gt; J -V-ZfwJ ^ ^ 4, Other settlements inhabited similarly hy 'Hathar' tribesmen exist in the shape of the villages scattered along the coast to the south of Kuwait^ 5, The next point to note is that the M Hathar' elements mentioned above as well as the richer mer chants and members of the Buler^s family, keep camels, Jrom May onwards (the Diving Season) these are sent out to Bedouin relatives, camped about Jahara, or more often further south to the Hassa border, 6, The point I wish to bring out here is that the tribal 'Hathari' sends out his camels to be looked after, each year, by his tribal brethrenJwho are paid hire for the purpose. It is impossible for the Buler to stop this old established custom, firstly because no men are left to look after the camels, and secondly the grazing in summer is far inland. Nor can the Buler stop the formation of the small camps outside the city walls as goats and sheep must graze, 7, It is a well known fact that the Sedouin tribes always keep in close touch with their 'Hathar' con nections of the Town and villages, and normally do their shopping through them, should there be an embargo against supplies leaving the Town. 8, The way it is usually done, is as follows, and both the Ajman and Awazim are experts at the game, A message comes in^say to an Ajman Hathari,camped outside the walls, or living in a neighbouring village, asking him to send out 50 bags of rice. The latter does not go into the city to buy, but simply passes the word round, and each tent supplies one or two bags. The whole is then sent out under cover of darkness into.the desert, No names are. (&amp;J &gt;' { are mentioned, no Ajmi is seen, and no A J man camels put in an appearance, a few donkeys or firewood camels do tke needful. The inmates of the various tents are not even paid, and they normally replace their supplies when they next enter the Town to sell their wool and ghi* They are entitled to have their own supplies - they must live I , 9* I have somrwhat at length described the common method hy which the Bedouin can get supplies if there 'be a strict 'blockade against him. And if there is any smuggling going on to-day, it is prohahly hy this means. The Sheikh of Kuwait, is I am firmly convinced faithfully keeping to his promise not to allow sup plies to go out to the 'Wafrah' rebels, hut leakage of the kind mentioned ahove is practically impossible to stoju He can and does control »pen buying in the market,.but he cannot be expected to besiege his own Town, call in his villages and force shepherds to bring their flocks into the town where they would starve. 10. As a matter of fact, I myself believe that little actual smuggling is going on now. From careful en quiries it would seem that all the supplies that the Ajman required, were taken out of the town long before the Euler was asked to prohibit the export of supplies, There is evidence also to show that when Ibn Mashur c ame to Jahara, it was not to take refuge but to secretly purchase all he required for his coming ^ struggle against Ibn Sa'ud. This he did. 11. The sympathies of the people of Kuwait are of^ course entirely with the Ajman to—day. They look upon this tribe as belonging to Kuwait. * And blood is thicker than water. This is a very important point when considering the stoppage of supplies. 12. One final point. Ibn Sa'ud in the last few years, has by force of arms maintained an extremely, 'S 0 extremely unpopular 'blockade against Kuwait(xiot 'because the Sheikii would not surrender a portion pr Customs) and has prevented the northern tribes of Nejd from visiting Kuwait 'by means of strong parties posted in the hinterland. Since the hattle of S.ihilla and the defeat and death of Pahad 'bin Jaloui every thing has changed. Ihn Sa^ut has largely lost control, and many of his loyal Akhwsn are pouring into the town in ever increasing numbers, some ikxx come with Ihn Dawisi^s permission, some such as Harh with Ihn Be 'ud* s sanction others come 'by no ones permission. To-day it is a case of 'go as you please', and one cannot 'blame the people of Kuwait from taking full advantage of the state of affairs. The Sheikh does not hinder these men coming in, 'but as he emphasized to me he cannot guarantee that the loyal Mutair, for instance, do not supply the ijman round the corner, as soon as they have crossed the 'border. 13, Kuwait JTorces (h) For the purpose of actually watching the frontier to-day, I am of opinion the Sheikh of Kuwait cannot muster more than 400 mounted men, of these some 2 00 (called fidawiyeh or Araihdar) are permanently kept at Jahara, If the pearl season were not on, he could possibly raise about 700 men but this is an out side estimate. These must not be confused with the lias force he could muster for the defence of the Town walls For this latter a 'levee en masse' would be enforced, and probably 8,000 indifferently armed men could be raised. These would be footmen only,ana would man the walls, nothing more. I have the honour to be, • Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy forwarded, with oompllmenta, to H .B.the High Commissioner for -Iraq. Baghdad for information.C ONI? I 'DENT IAL No.586 Political Agency, Kuwait, . . : Dated the 14th June 192 9, From Eieu^eriairt-u oioriei. H.E # P.I)iclcson,C ♦ I,E political Agent, Kuwait. To The Eon'hle the Political Besilent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Subjec t:- She ikh oT Kuwait♦s ohj ec t ions to f Iraq police cars within his 'borders^ Sir, With reference to your telegram No # ^§ dated the Sslk 10th June 1929, and His Excellency the High C om- f missioaer 's telegram ]\To»6£/S dated the 12th June 1929 in reply, copies of which were received here. I have the honour to inform you that I again had a long and careful discussion with His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait yesterday (theisth June 1929) on the subject, as I was anxious to leave no loophole open for misunderstanding or recrimination. The point I particularly gave attention to was His Excellency the High commissioner's view as expressed in his No,62/s namely that 'When Mesopotamian trihes were grazing in Kuwait in any numbers the presence of police Cars seemed necessary hoth for protection and control'. I of course did not quote the words: I found the Sheikh of Kuwait willing and anxious to discuss the matter,and the following is a summary of the various points he made (1) The whole Question was one which concerned Kuwait's national honourIt was galling in the ex treme to his sense of pride to hear that the * Iraq police claimed a sort of right to enter territory.when the ♦Iraq shepherd tribes made their annual 4migration into Kuwait, (2) Would, he asked, Persia or Syria tolerate such a thing in similar circumstances? He ventured to think not. Though Kuwait was a small state he felt just as strongly in the matter as would larger c ountries, (3) is the ruler of Kuwait it was a point of honour with him to himself protect trihes of a neigh bouring friendly state when within his territory 1 should he find it 'beyond his power to do so he would always ask His Majesty's Government, who were his natural protectors, to assist him hy despatching Armoured Jc Cars; 'but these must 'be British and British manned. In no case would he ever ask for nor did he want ) any ♦Iraq Army cars, or »Iraq Police cars^to come to his assistance, (4) On one condition only would he waive his objection to Police Cars coming* This was in the event of the off ic er~ in-charge of the British Ar moured cars considering he had not enough strength to cope with a particular situation, and desired to have a few ♦Iraq, Police cars to assist him. But in this case the Sheikh expected to he asked to agree 1 irst* He made the stipulation however that in such a contingency the ♦ Iraq Police cars 1 duties were to be merely passive, i.e. they should he under the orders of the British Armoured Car Officer, and remain strictly for the defence of tribal camps. In no case were they to be allowed to roam about the country, or engage in any sort of reconnaisance» This must be done by British cars and British persor^l only* (5), His Excellency added that always in + he past he had had good reports of British officers and men and his people and tribes had nothing but praisefor them. For this reason if for no other they were always weloome. His experience of 'Iraq police was quite different. Last year for instance there were several cases of beatings and rough treatment of his people which extended even to thrashing af Kuwait motor car drivers. 2?hese he had never reported for the sake of preserving peace. He could quote instances also of •iraq Police in charge of cars demanding and getting bribes from poor Bedouins camped off the beaten track, should the demand be refused, invariably some umpleasent charge was made against the tribe in question, such as being mixed up in a raid, or possessing stolen property, and what is more the charge was brought home. These and many other instances had made the •Iraq police personnel execrated every where in Kawait territory, and they were looked upon as mere '^abl al fiten** or mischief makers. , It have above quoted the Shaikh's words almost word for word to enable you to get an idea of what is at the bottom of his mind. I; do not myself feil in any way competent to pass any criticism on his statements especially those quoted in paragraph 4, as I feel I have not been long enough in these parts to venture an opinion. As regards his ability to police his country the shaikh emphasised that he would guarantee the safety of anyone within his borders today. Xjast year when the 'Iraq tribes were looked upon as fair game by the Akhwan, the matter was on an entirely different footing, today the situation had so vastly changed that he could say with certainty there was no danger at all from the Akhwan, these latter were, and would be busy for many months to come with Bin Sa'ud, against whom the feeling of■4- resentment was growing day 'by day* I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. ^ * Lieut-Col,, political Agent, Kuwait. copy to Eis Excellency the High Commissioner for ♦Iraq, Baghdad, for information.Telggram P p Prom® High Commissioner, Baghdad, To* Secretary of State for the Colonies,xio 244# Hepeated to:» Political Hesident # Busiiirepolitical Agent,Kuwait and British Agent, Jeddah Ho 70/S # Dated and reed the 24th June 1929« Imaediate With the exception of conditions which you lay down, am I to understand that request of Bin Saud for immediate air action against rebels in iJiejd territory has 'been definitely rejected. Foregoing is with reference to your telegram tfo 200^ ^rele^rasa From* Secretary of State for the Colonies, Yo# High Commissioner, Baghdad. Hepeated to Political Hesident, Bushire, Political Agent, Kuwait and British Agent,Jeddah# No • 203 • Dated the 24th (reed 25th) June 1929 # Imme d iate * Answer is in the affirmative* kV^ In fourth sentence of my telegram No 200* raiders* should read * rebels •* Above refers to your telegram Ho 244#/ 61/14 &amp; 14/201. Telegram Code. From political Agent, Bahrain. political Resident, Basiiire, at Kuwait. Ho. 673. Datgd 24tn received 25th June 1929. Dame has been sent for ostensibly to see Ibn jiluw^s family but all reports show that he himself is seriously ill. He apparently took most binding oath to proceed against the Ajman after pahd^ death but orders of Ibn Sa 11 ^ stopped him and and failing in oath weighed on his mind. rumours of Shailda of Diba^s assassination but R e sidency Agent told me nothing about it. On return from Trucial Coast found strong political Agent, Bahrain.61/14 * Telegram C ode. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resilent, at Kuwait From To No. 676. Hated am received 2 5th June 1929. i t is rumoured that Faisal ad 'nawish has camped at Wafrah with a few of his followers, leaving the remainder at Atawal. Awazim trihe are said to have heen foraed 'by recalcitrant tribes to join them. Nejdis who were coming from 'Riyadh to Hasa are said to have heen looted 'by Mutair raiders, Hasawis alone have 'been given permission 'by Ihn Jilawi to go and seek work» Sixty men from Hasa have arrived here yesterday Monday, Juhail is guarded day and night. Political. Repeated to Political Resident at Baghdad, 2 5/6/2 9. Copy to Political Agent, Kuwait.6X/IA l2oo-Ht)/6/2y '0 - Telegram Code Jrrom To v Repeated Ko.aai Dated the 25th (received 26th; June 1929^ High Coiamissioner for 'Iraq, joaghdad Political Agent Kuv/ait Political fiesident ^ushire muhamad ibn Khajial now entered ^iraq^ and Has been arrested, search for ^aif ibn mvuiazzil oontin- ues. 10 Camels believed to be looted from Jahrah recovered. Please ask Sheikh aend representative of owners to SafTiian to identify their animals. I - nigh commissi oner £ma^ i2U, ***/ Tib J 6i /- 14 1285/28/6/29 Telegram. Code ^ rQm Political Agent KMait Political Resident Bushire Repeated nigh Coimnissioner for 'Iraq,, Baghdad U'o .399 y Dated and received the 2^th June 1929, IMMEDIATE^ qusaibi has telegraphed Hafisi this morning that Awaaim have inflicted severe defeat on rebels, whose leader xbn MashJiur,Al Pughum and ^ibsahman killed, news not confirmed here. - POLITICAL - *■*-&amp; S^t, Auu '/■ ,!6l/H 1282-28/6/29 Telegram Prom To Repeated Code PoliticaX A^ent Kuwait Political Hesident JBusiiire High Gomtnissioner for »ira a , Baghdad and Admini strati Ye Inspector J^asraJi i^o •398 Dated 27tii (received 28th) June 1929, On the 25th evening party of Shammar raiders were followed and successfully rounded up by Kuwait forces in the Ttoinity of umdaira north side of bay. Haiders who lost several, killed including leaders were brou s ht into Kuwait last night. retails follow. - POLITICAL - ^ * tj-y}-. Sji Jyx .itJL fru.t^ \ u &gt; v 61/14 1277-29/5/29 (09 Telegram Code ^ ,roia Political Agent Kuwait Political Resident jsushire Repeated High Coramissioner for »iraq., Baghdad. NO.40Z Dated and received the 28th June 1929. IIiMSDIATB* Sheikh visited me this monning and report- ed that Azaiyiz son of Jaisal A1 Dawiah with 100 oanelmen had arrived point 10 miles from Kuwait and had sent in messenger with letter from Dawish. Latter contained another urgent request from uawish to he allowed to camp at Subaihiyah reiterating all promises and offers made previously and reported in my despatch of 20th June J!lo.394. Messenger also requested be allowed to enter city and deliver personally message to Sheikh and myselfjrom Dawish. Pending orders from you I advised Sheikh to send immediate reply to Azaiyi^ that he could not enter town and that he should return without delay to Dawxsh and make it clear once and for all that he could neither camp at Subaihiyah nor cross Kuwait frontier anywhere on pain of being bombed. sheikh who agreed to ray views entirely immediately sent Abdullah bin jabir who commands troops to Azaiyi z . s oamp to deliver message. As Aaaiyiz will no t i e ave before tomorrow could myself,if you approve, visit him by motor to insure that he exactly understands position and does not receive a watered down or ambiguous message. Pending return of A.aiyi. Bawish has intimated that he is moving to namudh south of wafra. - POLITICAL - fcc. VN 1- A 1 Sj.61/14 1278-29/6/29 Telegram Code ^ rom jfolitical Agent isahrein To political Resident uushire JNO.696 Dated 28th (received 29tli) June 1929. xt is reported that on Monday the 24th Ajman, Bin Mashhur and Al Jniqm camped at Ra&amp;eviah with the intention of attacking Awazdm and other 5 Has a tribes wiien ^.iSglng for water they were attacked suddenly 'by AwazluigAJman and their followers^h^avy loss having 600 Haif Abal iCLlab chief of Ajman, Bin Mashhur, Al JHqm and his son are said to have been killed in this fight Awaaim are said to have lost 15 men only this is uncon firmed and boot may be on the other foot. - PDUTICAl - **» /c- h-'T*.,, iuL {h cTelegram - Code - Immediate. - Resident, Bush ire at Baghdad. fo - Polltioal Agent, Kuwait. 5*0. - BA. Bated • 29th June, 1929. hVl Heference your telegram No. 402 dated 28th JUne, 1929. I approve your suggestion to yisit Assaiyiz 10 miles from Kuwait for purpose cientioned. Copy to High Commissioner, Baghdad.a1288 -30/6/29 Telegram Prom To Repeated Uo *404 Dated 29tii (received 30th) June 1929. Code Political Agent Kuwait Political Kesident Busnire Higii Commissi oner for 'Iraq,, Baghdad My telegram dated 27th June iJo»399. Ibn Jiluwi ¥/ired JMafisi last night repeating story of Awazim victory over Ajman though/ no news whatever has reached Kuwait yet* ibn Jiluwi states that 7 standards including that of Sheikh of Kuwait captured and sent to Riadh. The rather clumsxiy attempt on part of Amir of Hasa to embroil Sheikh of Kuwait is typical and we may next expect ibn Saud to 'bring all his invectives to bear on jfcks Sheikh Ahmad* * - POLITICAL - J* ■y ^,, * ! 6 1 I Telegram P. 61/14, From. Political Asent, Kuwaiju To. Political Besident, Bushirs. No. 405. ancL r©cd. Datea/the SOtli June 19E3. to you. Immediate Should I repeat Jeddali^s telegram of the 29th June Ko 1S6 wUich does Dot appear to have 'been sent .^Ar Telegram P . yrcan. Political Resident r Bushire. To. Political Agemt, Kuwait. No. 633. Dated the 2nd July 1929. Importan t* Please repeat Jedda^s telegram No 156 referred to in your telegram No 405. ms/s for Colonies telegram No. 203 (to Baghdad), C» Aioendation will 'be made. A. , Kuwait may 'be Requested to give Mr Croning copy of C.O. telegram, since we do not knous move- mento not Hie duration of his stay at Baghdad. it is not likely tb.at P.H. will, fly to i3usb.iie. Draft below. Usual distribution ? D.J.S.~25-6-29 t SKGHg . Yes. Issue telegram. Usual distribttion of post copies. A.A.R(ussell).-25-6-1929.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00022e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/585</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00022e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/585</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 61/14 IX (D 56) Relations between Nejd and Iraq'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-02T12:05:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (347 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is arranged chronologically. At the beginning of the volume (folios 3-4) is a subject index, arranged alphabetically. Numbers refer to folio numbers.</extent><extent>Foliation: the sequence starts on the first page and runs through to the inside back cover. The numbering is written in pencil, circled and positioned in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. There are the following irregularities: 2, 2A, and 2B. There is a second, inconsistent sequence. It is also written in pencil, but is not circled.Condition: folio 296 is cut in half lengthways; only the right half of the folio remains and is folded.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume consists of letters, telegrams, reports, and memoranda relating to affairs between Najd and Iraq. The majority of the correspondence is between the Political Residency in Bushire, James More (later Harold Dickson), Political Agent in Kuwait, Gilbert Clayton, High Commissioner in Baghdad, Cyril Barrett, Political Agent in Bahrain, John Glubb, Administrative Inspector in Iraq, the Colonial Office in London, the British Agency in Jeddah, the Foreign Department of the Government of India in Delhi, and Ibn Sa'ud himself.Most of the documents relate to the execution of rebel leader Dhaidan Ibn Hithlain and the subsequent rebellion by his tribe, the 'Ajman. Various issues are raised:the whereabouts of the rebels and there attempts to enter Kuwait;whether the Sheikh of Kuwait is harbouring rebels in his territory and/or supplying them with equipment and provisions;Ibn Sa'ud's request from the British Government for a troopship, guns and ammunition and whether to provide them for him;the presence of another rebel leader, Ibn Mashhur, in Kuwait, and reports of his defeat and death near the end of the volume;Faisal al-Dawish's recovery from serious injuries inflicted at the Battle of Sabila, and his alliance with the 'Ajman rebels;how the British should respond to the 'Ajman rebels should they (or should they not) enter Kuwaiti territory;al-Dawish's attempts at communicating with Sheikh Ahmed of Kuwait and the British Government.Other subjects that are raised within the volume are:which channels of communication are to be used for contact with Ibn Sa'ud;intelligence on the movements and activities of several other tribes and people, including the 'Anaze, Awazim, Dhafir, Harb, Mutair and Shammar;the whereabouts, thoughts, and expected actions of Ibn Sa'ud;Ibn Sa'ud's suspected seduction of the Dhafir tribe;the deployment of Iraq or British police cars to protect Iraqi shepherd tribes during their migration in Kuwait;Ibn Sa'ud's brother, Mohammed, escaping from custody and joining the 'Utaibah;pearl divers in Hasa being temporarily prevented from leaving port and accessing the pearl banks due to insecurity;the request from Iraq for compensation for their tribes for losses incurred in raids, including a detailed list of these (folios 296-7).Notable within the volume are the confidential memoranda by the newly-appointed Harold Dickson as the Political Agent in Kuwait. They cover three subjects: Sheikh Ahmed's personal thoughts and opinions of Ibn Sa'ud (folios 304-6); the smuggling of supplies to the rebels from Kuwait (folios 307-10); and the Sheikh's objection to Iraqi police cars entering Kuwaiti territory (folios 311-314).At the end of the volume (folios 331-40) are internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Kuwait Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Fayṣal bin Sulṭān al-Dawīsh</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight John Bagot Glubb</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Farḥān bin Mashhūr al-Sha'lān</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Ḍaydān bin Ḥithlayn</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Shammar (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>'Ajmān (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Muṭayr (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>'Awāzim (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Ḥarb (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>ʻUtaybah (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>'Aniza (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>al-Ẓafīr (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms sales</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00022e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>