<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:24:58.871Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">79/143 Telegram G.T.C. from Political Resident, Bushire. To H»M.Ambassador, Baghdad, for Copy to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1624. Bated 5th November 1945. X Ny telegram No. T/157 July 22nd. 2. Bahrain Government has imported 530 tons rice during September and October and oan accept monthly reduction of no tons in wheat &lt; 4 uota for November December and January. - PRIOR - No. 889*3• Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, the 5th November 1945. 1 | { i ’ ! - Copy forwarded, with compliments, ta The Political Agent, BAHRAIN, with reference to Bahrain Express Letter No.4488-29/21, dated the 28th October *45. ■i) &lt;no RHL. . 6^33 /9No.PA/C/.^Z. Political Agent, Bahrain* | \\J I , , 0 ? MEMORANDUM :- With further reference to my memorandum No.PA/C/48 of the 2?th October, 1945* Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported a further 900 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Governtoent, THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 14th November, 1945* ? The price is Rs95/~ per bag of 210 lbs, C.I.F. Bahrain. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN ; 'I Eak«ia Reri'n: Data..GOVERMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [2V. J5 ,—This is an ORIGINAL MNSSAGN, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political, Bahrain* Political Resident, Bushire. (^ Nn* 4796 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 21st November /$$5 In continuation of my Express Letter 4571 - 29/21 of November 1st, 1945. Rice. 2. Hajji Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported for the Bahrain Government a further 84 tons of Persian gerdeh rice at the same rate. POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised, 'y Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KM5 S.6. MFP-—1206 S&amp;P—(M-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000,.No. PA/C/ o THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 25th November, 1945.&gt; Political Agent, Bahrain® ^EMORANDU¥. :- s' 1 With further reference to my memorandum No, PA/C/58 of the 14th inst, Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported a further 1000 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Government, i The price is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 lbs, C.I,F. Bahrain. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, nr ' Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been bo despatched,] From Political, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire# tf#, 4915 - 29/21. Bahrain, 'DaU&amp; the 29th November/^5, .\0 In continuation of my Express Letter No. 4796 - 29/21 of November 21st, 1945. Rice. 2. Hajji Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported for the Bahrain Government a further 93 tons of Persian Gerdah rice at IriftMNriMMBC Rs. 1067/- per ton C.I.F. Bahrain. POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised. if, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. ms S. 6. MFP—1206 8&amp;P-(M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000*. fGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [xV. B ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue me of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as tf it had been so despatched,] From Political, Bahrain* Eo Political Resident, Bushire. 4945 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 2nd December ( - ■ ' V % Reference my Express Letter 4915 - 29/21 of November 29th, 1945* Rice* 2* Hajji Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported for the Bahrain Government a further 56 tons of Persian Gerdah rice at the same rate* = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised* Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain* KMS S.6. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000*.H0.11B4-.1S15 ^ 1 / % British Agency, Dated 2Snd November 1945 To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Bub t iect: - Imports of rice into Crucial C^o as T Memorandum . Deference your telegram Ho.485 dated the 5th of July 1045. 2 # 58,500 Lbs. of rice arrived at Shatjah on the 19th of ITovembe:v I Ilo.U86.r215 lU;, British Agency, Sliarjah. dated 24th November 3.945. To The Political Agent, - , * B p hr a in. ^ 0 Subject: - Ipiports of rice into Trucial Coast n Memorandum . 'Reference your telegram No.483 elated the 5th of July 1945. 2. 78 tons and 16 Cv/t. of rice arrived at Dubai during the week ending the 24th of November 1955No. 4990 - 29/21. POLITICAL AOiSHCY, BAHRAIN• The 5th December 1945 To The Political Officer, Xrueial Coast, Sharjah. MEMOriANDUiVi Subjects Imports of rice into Trucial Coast . In future, please state the country of origin, type of rice and price in your reports of imports by the Trucial Coast. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, .Department, EXPRESS LETTER [A T , B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGN, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is warded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] 4991 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 5th December &gt; xl /■ ' Your telegram 1121 of June 23rd, 1945. Feom Political, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. Rice. 2 . Rice imported to Trucial Coast during the month of November 1945 amounted to 113 tons. Details not yet available. POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain KHS 8 . 6 . MFP—1206 8&lt;feP—(M-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000*.Ho. PA/C/f? H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, UffiMOHAKDUM :- THE 8 th GUST01,IHOUSE: BAHRAIN: December, 194-5 •&gt; ■ &amp; u -3 ' V/ith further reference to my memorandum No 0 PA/C/70 of the 29th November, 194-5 &gt; Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehmsn Fakhroo has imported a further 1,100 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Government, A The price is Ks 100/- per bag of 210 lbs, C. I .F.Bahra in. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN.No.PA/C/ OOOOOOOOOO^O^O**** H.B.M f vS Political Agent, Bahrain* t-EKQRANDtlK :- 9 V THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 12th December, 19^-5» \ With further reference to my No.PA/C/2 of th£ 8th inst Haiy Yousuf Abdulrehmsn Fakhroo has imported a further 200 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Government* This consignment now completes the*1000 tons ordered by the Government. The nr ice is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 lbs. C.I.F. A DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN• Y' J e o /&gt;v Bahrain No 7{&gt;l0 Receipt Data. f 2 .—Telegram 78/143 n /.&gt; urcrn To Q. Political Resicent, at liUBoat* tforeigrit Sew i)elhi • So* T/715 Dated 11th December 1945. Correspondence ending with my telegram No.T/652 October 25th. Rice lor Shaikhdoms. that free export from Karachi of rice of considerably better quality is now being allowed and they have ordered 900 bags at Rupees 19 per bag* Muscat has already received 626 tons* will be exported to speculators in Iran and elsewhere and eventually reach Sheikhdoms at very much higher prices* Government of India are aware of importance of rice to Sheikhdoms and I request that I may be kept informed of supply position so that they may be enabled to secure their supplies direct na opportunities offer* 2* Kuwait Government have been informed It is probable that much of this rice Pri or Confidential Ho*C/412 Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Camp iiluscat. 11 th December 1945. Copy forwarded with compliments to* The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ The Political Agent, Muscat.-POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN* . No. 5213 - 29/21. The 23rd December 1945. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. MBhlQaANDUM Reference your memorandum No. PA/C/2, dated the 8th December 1945. 2. Please confirm that the Bahrain Government is now prepared to accept a reduction of 110 tons of wheat during each February, March and April 1946. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAINr^) m No# 5236 - 29/21. POLITICAL AGliNCY, BAHRAIN« The 24th December 1945. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. iVIKMOkANDUM I understand that Kuwait and Muscat are importing rice free export of which is allowed from Karachi at Ks. 19/- per bag and that the quality is not bad. Bahrain merchants may be interested in this information. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMSTelegram- G.T.C. Prom- Prior, Bushire. To- Political, Bahrain. No. 1836. Bated and received 27th Dec. 1945 Your Express letter 4945 December 2nd and 4991 December 5th. Rice. 2. Please telegraph recommendations with regard to reduction of Bahrain Trucial Coast wheat quotas. -Prior-Telegram From To No. 2 . wheat of 3. m of wheat 113 tons December G.T.C. / S -. Political, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 906. Dated the 30th December 1945. ! Your telegram No. 1836 of December 27th. Rice. Bahrain can accept reduction in quota of 110 tons during each February March April 1946. Trucial Coast can accept reduction in quota of 100 tons only during February 1946 against imported in November 1945 and rice imported in 1945 exact quantity of which not known as yet. POLITICALGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, / Department, EXPRESS LETTER ' / ' / ! - : [A T . B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if iX had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political, Bahrain, To Political, Sharjah. 36 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 5th January Your memoranda Nos. 1157» 1184 and 1186 of November 14th, 22nd and 24th respectively. Rice. 2 . I have recommended a reduction of wheat of 100 tons during February 1946 against 113 tons of rice imported in November 1945 and rice imported in December 1945 the exact quantity of which has not been reported by you. 3. Please confirm your acceptance. = POLITICAL The Issue of the above has been authorised. KMS Assistant £ / Political Agent, Bahrain. 8 . 6 . MFP—1200 S&amp;P--(M-1723)—4-2-36-200,000*.1 I % c? No. 37 - 29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 5th January 194-6, To The Director of Customs, Bahrain• / MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum Bo. PA/C/10, dated the 30th December 194-5* 2. I have recommended to the Hon’ble the Political Resident that 110 tons of wheat be reduced monthly from Bahrain’s quota for each February, March and April 194-6 against rice imports concluding with the 19 tons reported in your memorandum No. PA/C/5 of 12th December 194-5* MS i for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.G0VER1MENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [A 7 . 7&gt;,— This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalilies it is worded and signed as ij it had been so despaicheds] From The Political Agent, Bahrain, To The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 36 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 5th January In continuation of my Express Letter 4945 - 29/21 of December 21st, 1945. Rice. 2. Hajji Yousuf Abdulrehraan Fakhroo has imported for the Bahrain Government a further 122 tons of Persian Gerdah rice at the same rate. 3 . This consignment is included in the quantity of rice imported against which a reduction in the cereal quota was recommended in ny telegram No. 906 of December 30th, 1945. ^ p = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. J Asiistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMS S.6. MFP—1200 S&amp;P—(MM723)—4-2-36—200,000*.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [iV . B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formaltf ies it is worded and signed as if it had been bo despatched,] Feom The Political Agent, Bahrain. O ' to ^*• 39 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 5th January 1^6., - ■ • , V Your endorsement No. C/412 of December 11th. Rice. 2. The Bahrain Government informs me that the rice v/hich is being exported from Karachi is damaged. A recent consignment for Saudi Arabia was seen here and was found to be heavily weevil]ed, with a large percentage of broken grain. 3. The Bahrain Government would like confirmation that if this rice is imported it would not be set off against the cereal quota* \ * &lt; ■ ;V; ( , . The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised. J Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, KMS S. 6. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000*.Telegram Prom G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. To Britain, Bushire. No. 21. Dated the 8th January 1946. ■A / Y) l 7 Reference to your telegram No. T/504 (Circxolar) dated September 23rd, 1945. Rice. 2. I shall be grateful to know whether damaged red rice is still available for export from India. POLITICALFrom Telegram G.T.C. To Political Officer, Sharjah, Political Agent, Bahrain, 40. Dated the 13th January 3-946 &lt; No Reference to your Express Letter No. 36 , dated the 5th January. , Acceptance confirmed. 112 half 224 tons of rice imported in December“not previously reported as imported privately but-since requisticned, = POLITICAL KMS . . Bahrain Receipt hs tv. ■mt &gt; GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [y. J5 ,—This is aw ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue we of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain. \ rn i To The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. iV«,173 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 14th January t ^ h •IV' Reference my telegram No. 906 of December 30th, 1945. Rice. 2 . 112 tons of rice were imported under private arrange* ments by the Trucial Coast during December 194&gt; and subsequent]y requisitioned. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. J. assistant Political «.gent, Bahrain. KMS S.6. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2-30—200,000,./ 7S/143 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Government of India, New Delhi. No. 1847 Dated the 30th December, 1945. My Printed Letter No. 53-S 10th January 1945. During my visit to Delhi in February 1945, Supply Department promised to give Persian Gulf Shaikhaoms priority on Burma rice when supplies became available. Please remind them of promise and enquire when supplies are likely to be forthcoming. HJN. PRIOR - -0-O-O-O-O-O-O-O-O-O-O-0-0-0-0-o~o-o-o-o-o-O-O-O-O-0-0- Mx-J&amp;SZiS Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. 31st December, 1945. Pb-- h Receipt jipi Copy forwarded, with compliments, to 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait . 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain 3. The Political Agent, Muscat.7 9/143 Telegram 3.T.v3. YTom political Setident, Buehire. jo Government of India* Delhi# Ho# 52# Dated the 9th Januarjs 1946. jfP Gorreepondenoe ending with telegram Ho. T/652 October 25th. 2. Grateful if you would telegraph repeating to Bahrain whether damaged red rice ib a till available for export. Ho-' P)a,te*»»****** - PRIOR - ML. Pei elan Gulf Residency, Bus ire. 9 th Jaa uary f 1946. Copy forwarded with compilmcats to j- j The Political Agent, BARR AIK . \ * / ' with reference to Bahrain telegram Ko. 21 dated the 8th January, 1946. aoiiPiPiiKTiia Fo. 55 - S Bahrain &amp;h l79/143 Telegram GTC From U Political Rosident, Bushire. British Supply Mission (Middlo East) Cairo No.27 Dated 4th January 1946 My Express Letter 931-S November 15th 2. Bahrain Government have imported 413 tons rice during November and December 1945 and can accept monthly reduction of 110 half 220 tons in wheat quota during February March and April 1946. 3 . Trucial Coast has imported 113 tons rice in November and further quantity in December exact figure not yet known and can accept reduction of 100 half 200 tons wheat in February only. PRIOR Persian Gulf Residency, Np, 20-S Bushire, the 5th January 1946. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , W- with reference to Bahrain telegram No. 906 dated 30th December 1945. Bahrain Reef pt RHLTelegram From To Repeated No. G.T.Co Foreign, New Delhi. Britain, Bushire, Political, Bahrain. 199 ME 0 Dated the 24th &amp; reed. 25th JAN. ’46, Bushire telegram No. 52 January 9th. Damaged rice. 2 . To avoid delay suggest Bahrain Government instruct this (their?) agent Karachi to approach Director of Civil Supplies Karachi for information required. = FOREIGN KIi'IS Bahrain Receipt No — ,/Telegram From To No, Dated GTC Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. 126 26th received 27th January, 194-6 ‘ Government of India's telegram 199ME January 24th. Sind Rice. Please instruct Bahrain Government to act according. =PRIQR= AMO Bahrain Receipt No DateNo. 308 - 29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 27th January 1946. &amp; S h &lt; 8 / To . ■ / Hajji Salih Sulaiinan al Mana* Secretary to the Ruler of Qatar* Bahrain. 14 I MEMORANDUM Reference your conversation with the Political Agent* regarding the purchase of 2000 bags of damaged rice from Karachi. 2. To avoid delay please instruct your agent in Karachi to approach the Director of Civil Supplies, Karachi, for the information you require. Yours faithfully, n U for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMS £Confidential U0.1C7-S H)HSIAN GULB 1 RESIDHNCY BUS HIKE, 2ist January 1946. / To The political Agent Bahrain, Karachi Rice Bahrain Receipt No_ Date ./.Qj.hj.. Memorandum, Reference your memoraridum Ho,39-29/21 dated the 5th January 1946. 2* No assurance of the nature requested in your paragraph 3 can be given but generous allowance for lack of quality will be made in recommending quota reductions. For your informa tion, a quota reduction of 250 tons was recently recommended against an import into Muscat of 700 tons of the rice referred to. Sd. .GEOFFREY PRIOR Political Resident,Persian Gulf Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. JKGSECRET , AIR MAIL , External Affairs Department express letter. Government of India, Proms Poreign Rew Delhi To Britain Bushire. Repeated!- Political, Muscat, U0.D.16584-ME/45. Dated, the 7th January 1946, Your telegram No, T/715 December 11th, 1945. Rice. 2 . Report that better quality rice is being freely exported to Persian Gulf ia incorrect. 3. Sind Government is being requested to supply required information regarding supply position. Issue of the above has been author! sed. Sd. T• E.BRO\VNSDON • tinder Secretary to the Government of India. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, KUWAIT , The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , in continuation of Residency endorsement No. C/412, dated the 11 th Dec 45. Persian Gulf Residency, No. 120-S Bush ire, the 25th January 1946, RHL.No. 438 - 29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 12th February 194/&gt;. To The Director of Customs Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No. PA/C/9, dated the 30th December 1945# me that no assurance of the nature requested in your memorandum can be given but that a generous allowance for the lack of quality will be made in recommending quota reductions, e,g. a quota reduction of 250 tons was recently recommended against an import of 700 tons of this rice from Karachi. 2 . The Hon’ble the Political Resident has informed n for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN73/143 Telegram From British Supply Mission, Cairo. To Political Resident, Bushire. No.10 COOLIE. Dated 4th received 6th February 1J46. Your telegram No.138 COOLIE» We regret Persian Gulf Ghaikhdoms are not included in territories to which allocations / of Egyptian rice can be made available. C 2 &gt; 7&gt; 4 - Ei IN - RilL. 3sc. No. 196-5 . PERSIAN GUIF RESIDENCY, BUSH IRS. 7th February 1946. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to - N 0 n- 1 Rc ?// / ( ■ ■ 'U-157 \ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N, B, — This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be Lrtmled, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain. \ V To The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. No^ 680 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 2?th''February jg$6 In continuation of my express letter 173 - 29/21 of January 14th, 1946. Rice. 2. ?6 tons of Sadri and Rashti rice from Persia were imported by the Trucial Coast during February 1946 at the rate of Rs.5/- and Rs.6/- respectively per maund of 9 lbs. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMS s. e. M, P -400S&amp;P - (M-480)- 26-7-34 -2,CO,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [jV, B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESS A GF, sent hy post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare lime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To The Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. &amp; No, ?20 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 3rd March ]$f&gt; In continuation of my express letter No.680 - 29/21 of February 2?th, 1946. Rice, 2. A further quantity of 22 tons of Sadri rice has been imported by the Tfucial Coast during February 1946 at the rate of Rs.5/4/- per maund of 9 lbs. 3 . I will recommend reduction of cereal quota in due course. = POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMS S. 6. M/ P—400S&amp;P - (M-480)—26-7-34—2,CO,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N,B,—This is m ORIGINAL MFSSAGT?, scut by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. \ { \ £j&gt; j To POLITICAL, SHARJAH. V 721 - 29/21. Bahrain, DateaXhe 3rd March A Your memoranda Nos. 214.1215 and 226.1215 of February 21st and 24th respectively. Rice. 2. Please confirm that the Trucial Coast can accept a reduction of wheat of 110 tons during April 1946 against 173 tons of rice (75 tons imported in December 1945 and not set off and 98 tons imported during February 1946) imported by the Trucial Coast. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. KMS Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. ill!l S. 8. M t ■ P—400S&amp;P — (M -480)—26-7-34 —2 ,00,000-79/143* telegram U*T*C From Government of intiia* Delhi To hrit&amp;i n Buahlre* Ho. 499 MS. Dated 22nd received 24th February 1946. Your telegram Mo. 1847 December 30th 1945. RICiS. 2. Burma, rice expected this year is much less than India’s o*n requirements and general food position in India is such that Food Department regret they cannot contemplate relaxation of embargo on export of rice or other food grains to Gulf at present. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The ?o li t ical Agent, Kuwai t, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Muscat, in continuation of Residency Endorsement Ho. 1037-3, dated the 31st December 1945. FOREX GH RtiL. 380. Office of the ■No. C/3 . Political Resident, Persian Gulf L.T.'Mearchus, at sea, the 1st Ma^ch 1946.rUT) Y^' * -.y &lt;- Telegram G.T.C. From Political Officer, Sharjah. To • Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 0 S5 r 317. Dated the 19 th &amp; Reed.20th March. Heference your express letter No. 721 - 29/21 of March 3rd* 2 . Rice* Confirmed* POLITICAL KMS Bahrain Receipt to' 3 *No. PA/C/.^ THE CUSTOMHOUSES BAHRAIN; 23rd March, 1946., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM 2 - No J&amp;. Ds I have to advise that Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported three consignments of Persian rice, totalling 2,000 bags, for the Bahrain Government, as under:- 950 bags; 550 bags; -520 bags. f&lt;r? &gt;/ 3 r„ . , • Totals 2.000 bags . The price is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 lbs. C.I.F. AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OE INDIA, Depabtmsnt, EXPRESS LETTER [N , B, —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition asif ii had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. The Hon 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Not 1013 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 30th March 193-6. Reference your telegram No.1062 of June 11th, 1945. Rice. 2 . Bahrain and the Trucial Coast are able to import rice only thuough the private deal*of the various merchants and only country craft is used in the carrying of the rice to these places. In view of these facts I should be grateful to know if the instructions in the above quoted telegram should still be complied with. = POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. s. 6. MFP— 1190 S&amp;P-(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.GOVERNMENT OR INDIA, DlF ABTIiNNT, EXPRESS LETTER {N, JB ,—This is an ORIGIN AL MESSAQR, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the Wires, intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it fiau been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Fbgm POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. The Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. No. Dated 193 . 1014 - 29 / 21 . Bahrain. the 30 th March 46 In continuation of my express letter No .36 - 29/21 of January 5th, 1946. Rice. 2* Hajji Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported for the Bahrain fovernment 18? tons of Persian Gerdah rice at Rs. 1067/- per ton C.I.F. Bahrain. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. S. 6. MPP—1196 S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B—This is an ORIGINAL MUSS AGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Bushire . To ii ■ ^ Political olitical Kuwait . Bahrain. Political Muscat, N&lt;k 427-3. Bated 9th April 1946. ISS: / ^ w Reference Bahrain Express Letter Ho. 1013-29/21 dated 30th March 1946 (not to Kuwait and Muscat). Rice. 2 . It is presumed that rice imported privately is being taken over and distributed in accordant/ with the instructions contained in Residency telegram No. 1121, dated 23rd June 1945. Details of private imports need not be reported in future, but the total quantity taken over by the State during each month should be indicated in your monthly telegraphic statements of cereal Imports and stocks, and your recommendations for corresponding reductions in wheat quotas should be communicated on the same message if the quantities of rice acquired are sufficiently large to warrant it. ATTEofED . (yZ ^' for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Sd. 'GEOFFREY PRIOR. Political Resident,Persian Gulf. HDN. s. MFP— 1206 S&amp;P— (M-1723)— 4-2 36—200,000.No. PA/C/..?. : -'THE duSTOMIOUEE: y^AHRAINs $ Apr il, 1946., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, .£..'.... 1 . MEMORANDUM T ? n ' * ”• ” ^ f With further reference to my No,PA/C/58 of the 10th April, 1946, Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported a further 1000 bags of Persian rice for the Bahrain Government. The price is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 lbs, C,I,F. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.A- Ko.PA/C/.% H.B.Iu 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 22nd April, 1946., t .. .i Fo Mp3 M M With further reference to my No.PA/C/62 of the l/th April, 1946, Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Faiihroo has imported a further 792 bags of Persian rice for the Bahrain Government. \ ' \ 7 u t The price is as 100/- per bag of 210 lbs G.I.F. mL*— DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AUD PORT OK’ICER, BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [A 7 . B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] m*- From Political Agent, Bahrain* L. I To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain* 1545 - 29/21. Bahrain, Dated the 16th May /#. In continuation of my telegram No.282 of May 6th, 1946. 2. Bahrain can accept a reduction of 100 tons in its wheat quota for May and a further 100 tons in its quota for June 1946. Trucial Coast can accept a reduction of 50 tons In its wheat quota for May 1946. = POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised. tt2- Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. r ■ &gt; • KMS S. 6. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000,GOVERNMENT OF INDIA %q/J&lt;ll Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) WZ-ThUi'anOBialVALmum* ‘en, by A1B MAwbicb erwditimiA than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is mtenaea w oe ireaiea, e*U“°n a. if i, been formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature oj responsible officer of the Department.] ~ ‘ ““ ~ * No»544&gt;S Hated the 6 tfe May 1946 Persian Gulf Residency, Bush ire, ikxx* To Foreign New Delhi* r No -.Date...%..•••• l %|« Referenceparagraph 3 of Foreign Express Letter No*D*3371-M]ij/46 dated 15th April 1946. Availahility of rice for export from Karachi. 2. It is requested that the Director of Civil Supplies and Chief Controller of Prices, Sind, may he asked to communicate any such information to me and to the Political Agents, Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat hy telegram. H ATTESTED * Sd. J.Croning 3d. GEOFFREY PRIOR Political Resident, Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. No.545-S . Dated 6th May 1946. Copy, with copy of Government of India, External Affairs Department,Express letter No.D.3374-ME/46 dated 15th April 1946 (with enclosures), forwarded, with compliments, to - The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain,!^ The Political Agent, Muscat, with reference to Government of India,External Affairs Depart ment, Express Let ter No *B. 16584-ME/45 dated 7th January 1946. (Signature) /; (Designat s. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;P—(M-1870)—9-2-39—20,000.Government of India External Affaire Department. Express letter . Trom Eoreibg* New Delhi* 3. To Britain, Buehire. Ho. D.3374-10^46 • Dated 15th April 1946. i / 7 ^ t Your telegram No. T/715, December llth. Damaged red rice. 2. Copy is enclosed of letter from Sind Government to Government of India, Department of Food, No. 459/S, March 20th for information. 3. Director of Civil Supplies and Chief Controller of Prices, Sind, Karachi hae already been asked to keep you informed of supply position of rice available for export. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/ Illegible Deputy Secretax*y to the Government of India.BY Alii MAII G0VBH5TM ! ^T OF 3IKD. DEPAimfSKT OF FOOD AWD ClVII SUPPLIES Bunder Hoad, Karachi 20th March 1946 ho. 459/S To The Director General of Food, Department of Food, hew Delhi . Subject:- Diepoeal of damaged rice. Sheikhdoms. Reference:- Your letter Ho. P.C.130311)^45 dated 29th January 1946 to the Dy. Regional Food Commiesi oner, Karachi. 1 am directed to state that the actual quantities of damaged rice permitted for export on private account to Persian Gulf countries are 1825 tons onlp against 2250 tons agreed to by the Food Department, as no such further material was avall&amp;ble. 2. This department in letter of even nu her dated the 25th January 1946 has already furnished the details in respect of 1173 tons permitted against 1600 tons authorised by the Food Department in their express letter .208^21) dated 27.11.1945 followed by a telegram Ho.I.0.1303(1-^)/45 dated 28.11.1945 to Extracon Karachi. The particulars for 652 tons, to which sanction was accorded by the Food Department in their telegram bearing Ko.P.3.1303(1 )a/45 dated 13.10.45 (for 60C tons)* and 2.11.45 (for 52 tons) are as shown in the accompanying statement. 3. As regards comments in regard to the quantities permitted and the basis of which export permits wan issued, it may be stated that the Food Department is already aware that the material was old and damaged, being of 1943-44 crop, and included red rice spoiled by rains etc. which no body was prepared to lift in India. To get rid of such material as early as possible, this Department, irrespective of consideration whether the shippers were established exports or not, permitted the export to those who accepted the quantities in the ratio fixed viz 2 red to 1 white and paid the required rate. Sd/- for (n.K.lardi) Deputy Director of uivil Supplies SindNo.PA/C/^ZR Political Agent, Bahrain*, MEMQRANBUil: - THE CUSTOMHOUSE; BAHRAIN: With further reference to my No.PA/C/68 of tha 28th April, 194-6, Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported further 600 hags of Persian rice for the Bahrain Governmento The price is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 lbs, C.I.F. \ . % DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. —This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be rea e ^ on receipt y with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time ana o o via e formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature fij a re, r &lt;m,ihU ojjlctr of the Department.} 0 f ReS Idellt, i’eMian No, Q/143. Ompt Bahrain, / Dated the 23rd Bay w 46 . MXXJBM&amp;t To Repeated British Supply Mission (Kiddle Bast) Cairo* British Ministry of JTood Office, Basra* Political Agsnt, Kuwait* Bo lit leal Agent, Bahrain*^ In continuation of my telegram Bo. 27 dated 4th January 1946 (not to Basra end Kuwait}* 2* .Following reductions can be made in wheat quotas of Persian Gulf Sh&amp;ikhdomss Kuwaiti Reduction of 60 tons per month for next 3 months as contribution to starring oountries* Bahraini Reduction of 100 tons per month in Kay and June quotas against rice inserted* Truci&amp;l Coast i Reduction of 50 tons in quota for May against rice imported* 3d. V.R.HAY. follt leal Heaident, farsiaa Gulf. At tested* / /(Jvtr^ Secretary Bo lit leal Resident, to the Persimi Gulf* RHL. 4 4 {Signature) (Designation) s. 44. MFP—1048 S&amp;P—(M-2042)—17-12-37—20,000.No. 1705 - 29/21 POLITICAL A GENCY, BAHRAIN. The 29th May 194$ To The Director of Customs Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your endorsement No.PA/SF/27, dated the 1st May 1946. 2. A reduction of 100 tons of wheat per month in the Bahrain quota for May and June has been recommended by me against rice imported during April 1946. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN KMS4 No. 1706 - 29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 29th l^ay 1946. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. MEMORANDUM Reference your telegram No. 317, dated the 19th March 1946. 2. I have recommended a reduction of ?0 tons of wheat during Kay 1946 against the imports of rice. KMS for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.No THE CUSTOMHOUSE: n c. BAHRAIN: • PA/C/*4»/ 30th May, 1946., | © H.B,M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. / H o MEMORANDUM :- With further reference to my No.PA/C/72 of the 11th May, 1946, Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported further 750 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Government. The price is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 lbs, C.I.F. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFPEER, BAHRAIN. v &lt;* -c^QJLl Gcvermnent of India. External Affairs Department. AIR MAIL From Foreign, New Delhi To Britain, Bashire. / No. F•42(6)-ME/46• Dated New Delhi 3, the 6th June 1946. Your 544-3, ilay 6th. Rice from Karachi. not permit any exports of foodgrains and as such no occasion likely to arrive in near future of letting any rice or other foodgrains go to Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms. In the circumstances no useful purpose is likely to be served at present by issuing any further instructions to Sind Government as desired by you. If, however, any focdgrains are allowed to be exported to Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms in future, necessary instructions on the lines desired will be issued. The issue of the above has been authorised. in continuation of Residency endorsement No. 545-3, dated the 6th May 1946. 2 Present difficult food position in India does \ Sd. M. O'Meally. Under Secretary to the Government of India. No. C/268. Office of the Political Resident Persian Gulf, t&gt;JL.exn ujlA , Camp, Bahrain. Dated the 11th June 1946. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to !• The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat.— —No. PA/C/. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain,, MEM0RAND13H:- THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 23r^ June, 1946., V/ith further reference to my No.PA/C/79 of the 30th May, 1946, Hajy Yousuf Abaulrehman Fakhroo has importecl^further 1,000 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Government,, The price is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 Ibs.C.I.F* DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. Bahraia Receipt No,.:? ..Date is S’ 4 . •mmGOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). 3^ [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AM MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of ® officer oJ^Depa^^^ ^ politioal R e 3 id B «11 , P er B i an Slllf , No. C/462* Caffip 9 Bahrain Dct/tcd July 19 46. To British supply iSiosion iSiiddle Kast) , Cairo Repeated British Ministry of ij’ood Office* Basra* Political Agent, Bahrain. | ^ 1 1 my 4 ,1^ In continuation of my impress Letter So.C/143 dated the 23rd May 1946* 2. Bahrain Government can accept a monthly reduction of 100 tons in its wheat quotas for July and August 1946 against rice imports in June and July* 3d. ff.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested . for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL. ijanram Re: V7W Date / s , 7- (Signature) S. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;P—(M.18701—9-2-39—20,000. (DesignationNo. 2294 - 29/21. To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 16 th July 1946. The Director of Customs Bahrain. a\^ IvIEMORANDUM Reference your endorsement No. PA/SF/ 38 , dated the 1st July 1946. 2. A reduction of 100 tons of wheat per month in the Bahrain quota for July and August has been recommended by me against rice imported during June and July 1946. b/2. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.No.PA/C//f^.. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORAN DUM:- With further reference to my PA/C/90 of the 2^rd June, 1946, Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported further 1,350 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Crovernment. The price is Rs 100/- per bag of 210 lbs C.I.F. 4 n ^ a * 'fj ^ ug .11 JJ'JLZZ? DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.THE CUSTOMHOUSE BAHRAIN 30th September, HI, B» 'M’s Politics 1 Agent, Behr?in* No, P&amp;/C//&amp;2,. Memorandum:- With further reference to my PA./C/104 of 16th July, 1946 , He^i^Yousuf Abdulrehman Fskhroo has imported further 1,044 bags of Persian Rice for the Bahrain Government, , - - '' # The price is Rs o 100/- per beg of 210 lbs C, I» F, No l^fcram Rccsipt ° ^ —— DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN,^(JDL The folIovviJbrg is contained in a letter I have had from Prior; '■‘I find that Baluchistan exports considerable quantities of an inferior type of rice, and ix you are getting nothing from India it might be worth while attempting to get a quota from the basirabad supplies’ 1 . Nasirabad rice is of an inferior quality which I believe is known as Kangni, If you require any of this rice would you kindly address this Residency accordingly?No. 1681-29/21 Political Agency, Bahrain. The 10th May 1947• To: The Director of Customs, B a h r a i ru MEMORANDUM I am informed that Baluchistan exports considerable quantities of an inferior type oi rice known as knngni. If any Bahrain merchants are interested in the import of this rice an attempt will be made to obtain a quota of it from Nasirabad supplies. 2. I should be grateful for an early reply. MMAPolitical Agency, Bahrain. No. 1682-29/21 The 10th May '1947. Tos The Political Officer^ Trucial Coast, Sharjah. MEMORANDUM . I am informed that Baluchistan exports considerable quantities of an inferior type of rice known as kungni. If any Trucial Coast merchants are interested in the import of this rice an attempt will be made to obtain a quota of it from NasirabAd supplies. 2. ' I shall be grateful for an early reply. MMA for POLITICAL AGENT t BAHRAIN—W L\ From Telegram G#T.C Consul-General, Bushire To Political Resident, Bahrain Bo. 301. Bated 1st received 2nd Itay 1947. Para. 5 of my telegram Bo. 245 April 14th; 2. Rice to quantity of about 40 hags is available from Bushire monthly for export under local licence. in continuation of Residaacy endorsement No. 646-3 dated the 18th April 1947. t , , - BRITAIN No. 837-S Persian Gulf Residen Bahrain, the 6th May 1947. Copy forwarded, with complirrents,to The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Muscat, RHLNo. 1630-29/21 Political agency, Bahrain. The 12th May 1947 The Director of Customs Bahrain. vt MEMORANDUM Reference my memorandum No. 1441-29/1 dated the 27th April 1947. 2. His Britannic Majesty*s Consul General, Bushire, informs me that rice to the quantity of about 40 bags is available from Bushire monthly for export under local licence.THE CUSTOMHOUSE: Ho •PA-Q-^f. Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- Reference your Ho.1581-29/21 of 10th May, 1947, I enclose herewith a list showing the requirements of Baluchistan 'Kangni' rice. Haj. Abdulaziz Ali al Bassam, and Sh. Mostafa bin Abdullatiff are also interested in the import of 'Kangni' rice but in the absence of sample and further particulars such as rate etc, are not xvilling to place orders• v v '^ .A U V &gt; ^ V.''. 1 DIRECTOR OF CUSTQIiS Al© PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIH.POLITICAL ^G.AJCY, B,an ain* D.O* No. 1725-29/21 Dated the 21st I4ay 1947. O^cca cSl ■ H* ql '=7 • 1 s' Aill you pleas© refer to your demi-official ^ letter No. 1048-79/265, dated the 5th ^lay 1947. 2. I enclose a list giving the names(and requirements^of merchants in this Agency interested in the import of 'Kangni” rice from Nasirabad. 3. Other merchants are also Interested \ but are unwilling to place definite orders without receiving saraples of the rice and parti culars of the rates to be charged. Yours sincerely ArW&gt; o\c The Hon , ble Lieut-Colonel W.R.Hay, C.3.I., , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.1 m 11 No .MB# 1225 British Agency, Sharjah, Dated, the 26th May,1947. Reference^your memorandum No. 1582-29/21 dated the 10th May, 1947. 2 * No one here is interested in the import of kangni rice from Balachistan. y Agent, Sharjah.D.O.So.1730-79/265. H % PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The 8 th ‘August, 1947. \ | V 1 I am desired to refer to Felly' demi-official letter lo.1725-29/21 dated the 21st May, 1947, on the subject of Nasirabad rice and to say that it now appears that the chances of getting any of this rice are so small that Colonel Galloway does not propose to pursue the matter. £ Major H. 3. H. Ranee, Political Agent, Bahrain. 'w:No. ^io&lt;o&lt;o - 29/21 Political Agency, Bshrain, 20th August 1947. Yo The Director of Custons, Bahrain. &lt; a' Memoryndum. ' KanHni” Rice from Baluchistan. Your memorandum No. PA-Q-I? dated the I8th May 194?. I am nov/ informed that no rice will now be available from Baluchistan. for Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER L^« This is an ORIGINAL MRSSAGJR, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt,' with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From The Political Agent, Bahrain. To Persian Guir f Bahrain. A letter in original from the Director of Customs repoiting that Egyptian hie© has been offered to a merchant here at £.E 40 per ton c.i.f. Bahrain is enclosed. The amount of rice offered is 2000 tons. 2. Egypt is now outside the Sterling area and no allotment of Egyptian pounds has been made for Bahrain; nor have instructions about the sale of them been received. 3. I would enquire urgently whether the necessary foreign exchange amounting to £.E 30,000 could be made available for the purchase of this rice, which would be set off against the Bahrain Government’s wheat quota at the rate of 2/3 tons wheat for every ton ox rice imported - vide Residency Express Letter No. 931-S dated 15th November, 1945. \ , a ^ -ff Bahrain has hitherto imported its barley through tr^i &lt;^0 cha s • MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-l L. kj, Politicaji Agent, Bahrain,No.PA-C//^ Political Agent, Bahrain, Memorandums- THE CUSTOMHOUSE 2 ^ BAHRAIN : 5th November, 1947, I shall be grateful for an early re No.PA/C/134 of the 11th October, 1947 .' ply DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.79/143 Telegram R From Political Resident, Bahrain, To H.M 1 s Ambassador, Cairo, No, 1114 Dated the 6th November 1947, For British Middle East Office, Messrs Fakroo a Bahrain firm has been informed by the Egyptian Trading and Contracting Company that with a recommendation from the Bahrain Government 2000 tons of rice from Egypt would be available for Bahrain at £^40 per ton c.i.f. Bahrain. Grateful if you would comment on offer and state whether Egyptian Government would be likely to permit export. - HEPGU - I.C.H. jOjL 1907-S _ PEREIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated the 6th November 1947, Copy forwarded with compliments tos- The Political Agent, Bahrain, s ^ with reference to his Express Letter , 3425-29/21, dated the 29th October 1947. /Mo. 3594-29/21 The Political Agency f Bahrain. Dated the 15th November* 1947 The Director of Bahrain. toms ifemorandura reference your memorandum Mo. PA-C/145 dated the 5th November, 1947. 2. I have referred the matter to the Hon^le the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, and will let you knov* of any further developments as soon as I hear from him. I*. Political Agent, Bahrain.URGENT Noo 44-50SF of 1367 Office of the iidviset to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 6th Mnharram 1367 H.B M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum This morning His Highness presided at a meeting ol the Tood Committee to which several prominent importers ol foodstuffs had been summoned. His Highness, with the unanimous ^ meeting made the following decisions, a* MHAax* The Bahrain Governments applications for the sugar quota should be withdrawn. This was because ansurances were given by merchants who were present that they could and would import immediately suiiicient sugar to meet Bahrain*s requirements; the Bahrain Government were imable to give any guarantee that sugar irom the quota would be forthcoming. Vie were recently informed that 220 tons of quota sugar from India had been released, after paying for this quantity we were informed that it was not at present available * or ex P° r t* The present situation is that Government stocks of sugar will be exhausted at the end of this month. hAqs.* The meeting was informed by Messrs. Dhamanmal Isardas that he was in a position to obtain rice from Rangoon provided ! that he obtai ned a strong recommendation from the Bahrain Government. ] - His Highness informed the meeting that he would apply for this ! ^commendation from the Political Agent. May this please be given. c * The possibility of a rise in the price of wheat ' was indicated to the meeting. It faas thought that although small amounts of wheat might arrive from Gulf ports it would be impossible for us to obtain all our needs locally therefore we shall have to depend upon the quota. d. The meeting was informed by piecegoods importers that ^ Bombay was allowing the unrestricted expojbt of 25 $ over the quota of piece goods to new and old shippers of piece goods. / The merchantsJ Tl -2- The merchants asked that, if they succeeded in obtaining part of this surplus, it should be admitted into Bahrain free of controls. His Highness agreed to this and approved of a notice being issued immed iately stating that all commodities not under quota coiild be imported and exported freely. 2. All the merchants complained that the recent restriction on credits for foodstuffs in the Sterling Area was very strongly handicapping trade and asked His Highness to explain the reason 4*ol* the new regulation, which he was unable to do as he did not know the reason himself. They also compared commercial conditions in Bahrain with those prevailing in Kuwait, Dubai and elsewhere, . in greatly to the disadvantage of Bahrain. They referred is particular to the very large imports of sugar into Kuwait at a time when the import of sugar into Bahrain was restricted and implied that they were getting no help from the Bahrain Government. His Highness assured the meeting that he would personally do everything that he possibly could to improve trade conditions. •—“v* \ 3 d/- DALKYMPLK BHLtrAAVB adviser to the Government.&lt;s / r Uf * CONFIDENTIAL No 0 1998 -8 The HorDble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, presents his compliments tos- \ The Political Agent, BAHRAIN . f / I / T. and has the honeur to transmit to him a copy of the under- .mentioned document(s), with a request that the Food Controller, Bahrain Government may be informed accordingly. v PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN Dated the 21st November .1947 J. n , R EFERENCE TO PR EVIOUS CORRE SPC! 1 PENCE Residency Endorsement No. 1907-S dated the 6tlfNovember, 1947 Pescriptien ef Enclesure. Number and Date Memin Cairo telegram No.363 Misc.17/11 dated the 17th November, 1947. •LB’ LB Subject EXPORT OF EGYPTIAN RICE TO BAHRAIN A-ficn Telegram En Clair. From Memin, Cairo. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.363 MISC.17/11 » Dated and received 17th November, 1947. Your 1114. Egyptian Government Mil not repeat not pe'rmit export. •LB 1 - MEMIN - H—No. 3 £&lt;^-29/21 ^ho Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 25th November, 1.947. To. M&amp;mQXAn&lt;\m Reference your letter No. PA/C/134 &lt;^ated the 11th October, 1947. 2. The Egyptian Government have refused to permit export of this rice to Bahrain. n (L Political Agent, Bahrain. cNo. 3724-29/21 H.B.M's Political Ag_ Bahrain. Dated the 29th November, 1947 To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain Bahrain ijIEMQKaNDIM . Reference sub para Cb) of the first para of your memoranduin No.44-50SF dated 6th Muharram, 1367, Please inform me of any firm offers of Rangoon rice which merchants here may have receiver, together with details of the amounts of exchange required and the quantities of rice offered. Political Agent, Bahrain£ \ j^l j&gt;\ ji ju-j* « j\+£ TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, “BACTRiA” In reply please quote ^ ^ O ur Kef. A 1 0 ; L/ 59/ 32 9 • ^5 Ctl O k !h ^ H. B. M* s Political Agent, Btahrain. 2,(1) »K cj •H OJ iA rC 05 PQ fH CD 1 —! 1 —I O Fh •P -o P o c CD ' * o O &amp;H I 1 OJ 0^ O •H P *H r—I O PL, 03 e o p 03 3 13 O P P o TJ CD T5 Sh C6 Jh o &lt;H fn CD P P CD .P SP P^ O CD Sh •H Q 0 Xi P Dear Sir, CD Foodstuffs into the Persian Gulf: We herewith apply for a ‘No Objection'Certificate for the following goods on behalf of our customer Mohamed Rafi Karmustaji who wishes to open Letters of Credit in cover Goods;- 200 tons Persian Gerdali Rice. Amount:- £.14,000/-cfourteenthousandj , From:- Iran. To:- Bahrain. Beneficiary:- Rezayat Trading Co. Teheran. In connection with his application Mr. Karmustaji writes:- n We have been importing rice from Persia in very large quantities prior to the export restric tions prevailing there and we have a vast ex perience in this commodity. According to pre sent regulations, goods could be exported from Persia only against Letters of Credit. Conse quently, we request that this Credit should be granted to us.” Mr. Karmustaji also informs us that he has in the past sold rice to the Bahrain Government. (2) EXCHANGE CONTROL: In connection with the above application we also apply for a “Recommendation Certificate'* in accordance with exchange Regulations(Reserve Bank of India letter of 21st May Nb.FC By 3147/67“47J to enable us to open Letters of Credit. Yours faithfully, For The Imperi^i^Bank of Iran Co- Q &gt; Manager Form 120Letter forwarded to Political Agent through the Director of Customs and ij’ood Controller, Bahrain, 0 BAHRAIN ; ^?t&gt;h__ : w_qyember 47 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, “BACTR1A” In reply please quote Our Eef. No ;L/59/347. H, B. M* s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Dir, (1) Foodstuff s into the Persian Gulf; We herewith apply for a 'jmo Objection f Certificate for the following goods on behalf of our customer Mr. Yousuf Akbar Ali Reza who wishes to open Letters of credit in cover In connection with his application Mr. Yousuf Akbar Ali Reza writes ’’According to new regulations no rice can now be exported from Iran without first establishing a In connection with the above application we also apply for a M Re commendation Certif icate' 1 in accordance with exchange Regulations(Reserve Bank of India letter of 21st May HojBC By 3147/67-47^ enable us to open Letter of credit. We have seen a telegram from Mr. Yousuf Ali Akbar Reza’s suppliers in Teheran reading Goods:- 1000 tons Persian Champa Rice. Amount:- Rupees 10,00,000/-(ten lacs). From: - Iran. To:- Bahrain. Beneficiary:- Mohamedali Khabiri, Teheran. Letter of Credit.' (2) Exchange Control: 'Open Credit Imperial Bank Khabiri 1000 Rupees Ton for 1000 tons Champah Rice.' Yours faithfully Manager Form 120Copy of letter No.iiC By 126/67/-43 dated 5th January 1948 from the Central Office of the Reserve Bank of India, Bombay, Exchange Control Department, to the Manager, Imperial Ban., o Iran, Bahrain. we forward herewith a copy of our By Circular No.l of the 2nd January 1943 detailing the new arrangements for finance of imports into the Persian Gulf Ports. These regu lations have been drawn up with the concurrence or the Bank ox England and apply to all imports into the xersian Gulf Ports from outside the Scheduled Territories v/hether exchange is pur chased from India or locally from, banks situated in these ports. We shall be glad, therefore, if you will note them carefully and arrange to forward to us the original recommendation certi ficates of the Political Agent along with your dally returns after the sale has been effected* Cody of By Circular No.l dated 2nd January 1943 from the Exchange Control Department of the Reserve Bank of india^Bombay. (Enclosure to above letter to Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain; m authorised dealers in f oreign exchange. In further modification of the instructions contained in our By Circular No.4 dated the 21st May 1947 ? authorised dealers are informed that imports of all kinds into the Persian Gulf Ports (not only foodstuffs) from outside the scheduled Territories (Sterling Area Countries) are now subject to the recommendation of the appropriate Political Agent. In future, therefore, no letters of credit may be opened Or sales of exchange or transfer of sterling or rupees to non-residents b made against imports into these territories from countries out side the sterling area except on the recommendation of the Political Agent. The other instructions contained in the Circular remain unchanged and authorised dealers are requested to note them carefully and to forward to the nearest office of the lieser^e Bank of India the original recoimnendation certificate of £he Political A ,T ent after the sale has been effected, dum.^ endoised and aUached to the relative Form ’A; or ‘3 A. 1’, along with the D.l return, in the same manner as impoit licences.•V* : * Uo.PA-c/, 6 H.B.M’s Poliiical A^ent, Bahrain, Memorandum: - THE GUST CffHOUSE 3 BAHRAIN: 30th November, 194 ^ I permission to enclose for your perusal and return, two applications for open letters of credit for the purchase of Persian rice for Bahrain. I am not prepared to recommend these imports by this method, until a decision has been reached re the Adviser’s application to you for an import recommendation for rice from Rangoon. Secondly, in the past ; rice from Iran, has been imported into Bahrain without the formality of opening-letters of credit. I shall be grateful for your view's on this subject. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.dU 1 ^ ^ BAHRAIN, 11th Deceber^)47 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, “BACTRIA” In reply please quote Our Kef H. B. M* Bahrain. Dear Sir We refer to our application for import of rice of 22nd Wovember(L/59/329;. We now enclose a copy of a letter we have re ceived from Mr. Karmustaji. Yours faithfully, For The Imperial Bank of Iran Manager Letter forwarded to Political Agent through the Director of Customs and Food Controller, Bahrain. / Form 120telephone: 112 m GRAMS &amp; CABLES: KARMUSTAJ I - BAHRAI N codes: BENTLEY'S 8, PRIVATE GENERAL MERCHANTS DISTRIBUTORS ASSOCIATE OFFICES AND AGENCIES AT TEHERAN - I RAN PERSIAN GULF PORTS OMAN TRUCI AL COAST SOUTH OF SAUDI ARABIA BAHRAIN (PERSIAN GULF) OUR REF ; EK/KACr YOUR REF COPIED DATE Deer.10,47• The Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. Dear Sir: With further reference to our application dated •November 22, for opening Credit against import of rice which you were kind enough to forward to ii.B.M.Political Agent for his approval, we have not received any reply to our application up to now. Inasmuch as the local prices in iersia are daily increasing and we consider there is aocute scarcity of rice in Bahrain, we request you to forward this letter again to H.B.M.Political Agent for his consideration. Thanking you, ' &gt;Ho. f f Of 1367 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 1 ' /r ”' 0,r TDe( H. B. M*s Political Bahrain. Memorandum: - Reference your memorandum No.3724-29/21 dated 29th November 1947, no firm offers of rice have been made to Bahrain merchants, but the firm of Dhamanmal Isardas are informed by their Agents that it might be possible to obtain 3/4000 tons of rice if the Burma Government are approached by the Bahia in Government. Adviser to the Government 3.2.Ian \ ♦ • 4 ♦ « ♦ 4jU ^» ^ \ W-* J • ^ *44 telegraphic address, BAHMINjl5thDecember^_ 'BACTRIA” In reply please quote Our Eef, No ; L/59/371 H. B. M f s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir We give below, since we think they will interest -A you, extracts from a Government of Iran Ministry of fina nce notice published, in the Teheran Press on 22nd November 1947. This notice gave the conditions for the export of H Champa” quality rice. The notice said that Rice may be exported on these terms up till 20th March, 1948 . 1 . Exports of rice can only be made under letters of credit opened abroad and against the Mova- feghat-Nameh of the Ministry of Finance. 2 . importers of rice must, when applying for cus toms formalities, present to the Customs the Movafeghat-Nameh of the Ministry of Finance and a Bank certificate confirming that a docu mentary credit has been opened with them for the export in question. 3. Exports of rice shall be subject to usual cus toms formalities, undertaking to sell exchange etc. Yours faithfully. For The : f Iran Manager Copy to; - The Director of Customs and Food Controller, Bahrain. Form 120II would refer you to my memorandum No.PA/C/6 of 30th November, 1947, in connection with the import of Persian rice into Bahrain. As the position of rice is critical here at the moment, I shall be grateful for your early decisions DIRECTOR OB 1 CUSTOMS AND PORT OFB’ICRR, BAHRAIN.cJUiif.L I « jJ \ • • • • ♦ ♦ «^ ^11 1 ^ j Telegraphic Address: ’’BACTRIA” In reply please quote Our Ref. No:L/59/437. H. B. 1*3 Bahrain. Political Agent, Dear Sir, Poodstuff s rfnlo t he Persian Gul f: . y., HicQrgm.lrar l &gt;« &gt; We refer to our letters L/59/329 of 22nd November, and L/59/347 of 29 th November and various conversations bet ween our Manager and yourself on the subject. As mentioned in the conversation of yesterday we have received a letter from the Reserve Bank of India as follows:- 'Re;-lj 1000 Tons Persian ,, Champa ,, rice - Rps.10,00,000/- 2) 200 Tons Persian 'Gerdah” rice - £. 14,000/-. With reference to your letter No.P/59/351 of the 17 th instant, it will be in order for you to establish letters of credit covering the above imports from Iran. We also approve your transferring a sum of Rs:1,00,000/- to the Imperial Bank of India,Teheran in respect of the telegraphic bill drawn by Mohamed Ali Khabiri of Teheran on Yousuf Akbar Ali Reza of Bahrain. Revised instructions regarding sale or foreign e exchange against imports into the Persian Gulf Ports are under issue and you will be advised in the mat ter in due course, n with the business. The Director of Customs has signified his approval. As promised we enclose a copy of a circular ftom the Reserve Bank of India which arrived yesterday by air mail. ■v' and as confirmed in that conversation we are now going ahead Your^falthf ully, For The /Imperial Bank of Iran ManagerRSSHIRVE BANK OF INDIA CENTRAL OFFICE BOLSAY Noil No; EC By 126/67^4:8 5th January, 1948 The Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We forward herewith a copy of our By Circular No.l of the 2nd January 1948 detailing the new arrangements for finance of imports into the Persian Gulf Ports. These reg ulations have been drawn up with the concurrence of the Bank of England and apply to all imports into the Persian Gulf Ports from outside the Scheduled Territories whether exchange is purchased from India or locally from banks sit uated in these ports. We shall be glad, therefore, if you will note them carefully and arrange to forward to us the original recommendation certificates of the Political Agent along with your daily returns after the sale has been effected. Yours faithfully, sgd. p,Assistant Controller■* HESiiiRVJii UjP HMDIA exchange contkuh department BOMBAY, 1. By Circular No.l. 2nd January, 1948 . To All Authorised dealers in for e ign e xchan ge. Dear Sir, In further modification of the instructions contained in our By Circular No.4 dated the 21st May 1947 ? authorised dealers are informed that imports of all kinds into the Persian Gulf Ports (not only foodstuffs; from outside the scheduled Territories (Sterling Area Countries) are now subject to the re^mmendation of the appropriate Political Agent, in future, therefore, no letters of credit may be opened or sales of foreign exchange or transfer of sterling or rupees to non-residents be made against imports into these territories from countries outside the sterling area except on the recommendation of the Political Agent. The other instructions contained in the Circular remain unchanged and authorised dealers are requested to note them carefully and to forward to the nearest office of the Reserve Bank of India the original re commend, at ion certificate of the Political Agent after the sale has been effected, duly endorsed and attached to the relative Form ’A’ or ’E.A.l 1 , along with the D.l return, in the same manner as import licences. Yours faithfully, sgd. Assistant ControllerClNo. 2 or. -29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHKlIN 20th January 1948. To l‘t s ’ I enclose in original two letters, Nos. 1/59/329 and L/59/347, from the Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain, applying for a recommendation certificate for the import of Persian rice. The Imperial Bank of Iran referred the matter of opening letters of credit to cover these imports to the Reserve Bank of India, Bombay, ?/ho have now approved the transaction. I also enclose copy of the Reserve Bank of India * s letter to tho Imperial Bank of Iran in this regard for your information. 2 . The rice position in Bahrain is very critical and it is essential that rice is imported ffom Persia as from no other source can it be got sufficiently early. 3 . Import of rice is to be set off against all cereal requirements -- i.e., 2/3 tons of v/heat supolied by B.3.^.Basrah is to be surrendered for every ton of rice imported, vide Resi- , dency Express Letter No.931-S dated'jthe 15th November 1945. The Bahrain Government have no objection to the reduction in their wheat quota if they secure rice in its pl-ice. asked the Manager of the Imperial Bank of Iran to proceed with the opening of the letters of credit to facilitate early export of the rice from Persia. 4 . As the export of rice from Persia has to be completed before 20th March, I have, in anticipation of your approval. 0 i. or Political Agent, Bahrain.Copy of letter No.EC By 126/67/-48 dated 5th January 1948 from the* Central Office of the Reserve Bank of India, Bombay, Exchange Control Department, to the Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. We forward herewith a copy of our By Circular No.l of the 2nd January 1948 detailing the new arrangements for finance of imports into the Persian Gulf Ports. These regu lations have been drawn up with the concurrence of the Bank of England and apply to all imports into the Persian Gulf Ports from outside the Scheduled Territories whether exchange is pur chased from India or locally from banks situated in these ports, We shall be glad, therefore, if you will note them carefully and arrange to forward to us the original recommendation certi ficates of the Political Agent along with your daily returns after the sale has been effected. Copy of By Circular No.l dated 2nd January 1948 from the Exchange Control Department of the Reserve Bank of India,Bombay. (Enclosure to above letter to Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain) All authorised dealers in foreign exchange In further modification of the instructions contained in our By Circular No.4 dated the 21st May 1947, authorised dealers are informed that imports of all kinds into the Persian Gulf Ports (not only foodstuffs) from outside the Scheduled Territories (Sterling Area Countries) are now subject to the recommendation of the appropriate Political Agent* In future, therefore, no letters of credit may be opened dr sales of foreig exchange or transfer of sterling or rupees to non-residents be made against imports into these territories from countries out side the sterling area except on the recommendation of the Political Agent. The other instructions contained in the Circular remain unchanged and authorised dealers are requested to note them carefully and to forward to the nearest office of the Reserve Bank of India the original recommendation certificate of the Political Agent after the sale has been effected, duly endorsed and attached to the relative Form , A f or ^.A.l 1 , along with the D.l return, in the same manner as import licences.« -29/21 POLITICAL AGENCY BiiHRAIN 20 th January 1948 To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain* ^ % ME^OHAi^DaM „ s. Reference your moraorahhum No*197-508F dated the 7th December 1948. 11 2. Please let me know the name of Messrs. Dhamanmal * Issardas’s agent in Burma. for Political Agent, Bahrain,■ i ' O'J ^ •j'-i B AHRAIN . 17t h Ja nuary , /a 48 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, “BACTRIA” In reply please quote 0 ™ Kef No:L/ 59/452 . %!/{ ■lJ&gt;b%jl‘)-/ . H. B. M*s Political Agent, w, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Rice from Iran. ;/e herewith apply for a recommendation certificate ..or the following goods on behalf of our customer Mr. Ahmad Yousuf Fakhroo:- r Goods:- Amount:- From:- fo:- Favour: - 300 tons rice. Rs: 00,000 (Rupees three lacs); Iran. Bahrain. Mohamed Amin Khunji. ^2 s;^d In this connection present regulations in Iran do not allow the export of rice unless Letters of Credit are first opened. We would also mention(as is known to you; that the Reserve Bank of India recently approved two applications one tor £.14,000 and the other for Rps.10,00,000 for rice from Iran. This would appear to indicate willingness to see this type ot business. 4 Please send us a reply as soon as possible since the matter is urgent . Yours^. faithfully, ^ For The imperial Bank of Iran Jf-f £■ -N: Manager Letter forwarded to Political Agent through the Director of Customs and Food Controller, Bahrain. PO*T OFHCtR. BAhrasn Form 120No« ^0 2 -29/21. POLITICAL AGLIICY BAHRAIN 20 th January 1948&lt; To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 4L,iORrtNi)iM M %■ ol- I enclose in original letters Nos.L/59/451 aiid L/59/452 dated the 17th January 1948 from the ^onager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. 2. The import &lt;bf this rice into Bahrain is recommended. 3. The enclosures may kindly be returned as soon as possible for Political Agent, B&amp;hrai#.t U i S fa ^ &lt;j 1-4 j** 3AHRA1M, l&lt;?th January /&amp; 48 Telegraphic Address: ’’BACTRIA” In reply please quote Our Kef H. B.,M*s Bahrain. Dear sir, No:L/59/462. Political Agent, We herewith apply for two Recommendation Certificates for the following goods on behalf of our customers (1) Applicant:- Goods: - Amount: - From: - To: - Favour:- Mr. Abdali Alaiwat, Bahrain. 70 tons Rice. Rps.90,000(Rupees ninetythousand). Iran. Bahrain. Bayed Jabir Bayed Moosa Almoosawi, Khorramshahr. (2) Applicant:- Goods:- Amount:- From: - To:- Favour: - Kakoomal Valabdas Bros., Bahrain. 300 Tons Rice. Rs:3,00,000(Rupees three lacs J. Iran. Bahrain. Abdullah Ali Rashid Fakhroo or his Nominee at Khorramshahr. In this connection present regulations in Iran do not allow the export of rice unless letters of credit are first opened. • We would also mention(as is known to youj that the Reserve Bank of India recently approved two applications, one for £.14,000 and the other for Rs:10,00,000 for rice from Iran. This would appear to indicate willingness to see this type of business. Please send us a reply as soon as possible. 0 !WECTO* of l c Vw- A*/ **• TOM For Letter forwarded to Political Agent through the Director of Customs and Food Controller, Bahrain. r ('' r ~No. 5^^ 29/21 The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 26th January, l948r To. The Secretary to the Hon f ble thePolitical Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. I enclose in original a letter No. L/59/462 dated i the 19th January, 1948. 2 . The import of this rice is recommended. The enclosures may kindly be returned as soon as possible, for Political Agent, Bahrain. iALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS EASTERTIDE. (incorporated IN ENGLAND,) /24th Jany The Politicftl Agent, Bahrain * q Dear sir. We send you herewith applica tion for Foreign Exchange submitted to us by Yousuf Abdulrahman Fakhroo in terms of your notification No*1573/36-89 of 7th July 1947. Kindly advise fate In due NO. APPLICANT. CTIMRJSJCY. T “ ' r - 39/12 Yousuf Abdulraluaan Faldiroo ^6600/- Yours faithfully.3#' TELEGRAMS “FAKHROO’ DISTRIBUTOR DUNLOP PRODUCTS HERCULES CYCLES CROSLEy RADIOS WILLARD BATTERIES OWNER OF boring machines NATIVE CRAFTS EXPORTOR OF DRY AND WET DATES CODES BENTLEY'S ■ YOUSUF ABDULRAHMAN FAKHROO BAHRAIN. ARABIA TELEPHONE, 1 ©*M DEALER IN MACHINERIES AUTOPARTS AND ACCESSORIES MARIN ENGINES TIMBERS PIPES FITTINGS AND BUILDING MATERIAL COIR YARN OIL CONTRACTOR OF ARTESIAN WELLS BROKEN STONES (SHINGLE) 24th January 1948 The Eastern Sank Ltd, BAHRAIN• Dear Sir, This is t® state that we desire to impart 100 tans @f rice from Iran for which a Letter of Credit in pound sterling is required ta 'fee opened* The estimated Colof cost at £81/-“ sterling would w®rk ®ut to £8600/- as per the telegram enclosed herewith for y@ur perusal. As ®ur acceptance of the offer is required by immediate telegraphic credit, we shall thank you if you will approach the authorities for sanction without least delay^ Please return the telegram after pt-rusal * \ We expect to hear from you very soon. Yeurs faithfully, FOR YOUSUF ABDULRAHMAN Fi^JiROO, ^wr Enc. 1No . -29/21 The Political Agency, Bahrain, 27th January, 1948. To The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM . I enclose in original a letter No. Nil dated the 24th January, 1948. 2 . The import of this rice is recommended. 3 . The enclosures may kindly be returned. for Politrcal Agent, Bahrainum 1 ^ ‘-^ J * ®j TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, ®j_..24tto .,j anuary . ? .../'jp 48 “BACTRIA” In reply please quote Our Eef. No :L/59/473. Bahrain. H. B.^M*s Political Agent, TD d 'VK *1 v-\ 7 Dear sir, Rice from Iran. Ne herewith apply for a recommendation certificate lor the following goods on behalf of our customers Messrs.M. A. Cohen and sons, Bahrain. Goods:- 200 tons Rice. Amount:- Rs:2,00,000(Rupees two lacs). In this connection present regulations in Iran do not allow the export of rice unless Letters of Credit are first From:- Iran, To:- Bahrain. Favour:- Mr. Salim sbrahim Nonoo. opened. Please send us a reply as soon as xjossible Yours faithfully, 1 Iran, O^rCTOR OF CUSTOMS ^ NO p$:a f— - Manager u £| « \ ***** * &lt;,U j*t £ \ ^l^.l c*-^ *jL— TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, “BACTRIA” In reply please quote © ^ (^ymneUu- min m BAH RAIN t 24th January fQ 48 V'©J Please refer to our letter 59/452 of l/th January, being an application from Mr. Ahmad Yousuf Pakhroo for the import of 300 tons of rice. Please alter the currency required from Rs:3,00,000 to £.Sterling 25,000(twentyfive thousand;. Yours faithfully, 7 v. Letter forwarded to Political Agent through the Director of Customs and Pood Controller, Bahrain. Form 120No. 300-29/21 The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 28th January, 1948. To. The Secretary to the Ilon'ble the Politico,! Kesident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandums - 7 T ? I enclose in original a Letter No. L/59/473 dated the 24th January, 1948 from the Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. 2. The import of this Rice into Bahrain is recommended. 3. f i'he enclosures may kindly be returned when done with. ^ Political Agent, Bahrain. LNo 301-29/21 The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 23th January, 1948, To. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum:- Reference Letter No. 1/59/452 dited the 17th January, 1948, from the Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain, which formed enclosure to my memorandum No. 202 - 29/21 dated the ‘ c' Q qC- , 20 th Jarr xu iy, 1948. 2. Please alter the currency required from Rs. 3,00,000 to £.Sterling. 25,000/- ( twenty-five thousand ). * for Political Agent, Bahrain. Lj) I ejd , \ ♦ ♦ ♦ ♦ ♦ • &lt;iU j~i 1 ^ '-*? ° telegraphic address, “BACTRiA” In reply please quote Our Ref H O S li/ 59/488 . ^ n. B. m*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We herewith apply for a Recommendation Certifi cate for the following goods on behalf of our customer Mr. Mohamed Abdulranman Alinia, Bahrain. vxoodss- 100 tons Rice. Amount:- Rps.1,00,000(Rupees one lac), jfrom:- iihorramshahr(Iran). To:- Bahrain. jravour:- fibrahim Saeed Alinia, Ahorramshahr. ^ in this connection present regulations in Iran do not allow the export of rice unless Betters of Credit are first opened. Please send us a reply as soon as possible since the matter is urgent. lours faithfully, j**or The im Lai Bank of Iran Manager i. lA a. y ^PT Better forwarded to Political Agent through the Director of Customs and ij’ood Controller, Bahrain. Form 120No. 325-29/21 The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 1st February, 1948. To. The Secretary to the Non'ble the Po 1 i 11 cc. 1 I o s ident , Pe r s 1 an Gulf , Bahro. in. Memorandura: - * I enclose in original Letter No. L/59/433 dated the 28th January, 1943, from the Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, M ahrain. 2. The import of this rice into Bahrain is recommended. 3. The enclosure may kindly be returned as soon as possible. .a'' / &lt;***; j for Political Agent, BahrainNo. 0 f 1567 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 17th R/Awal, 1367 January 37, 1948 H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Reference your memorandum No.303-39/21 dated 20th January 1948, the name of Messrs. Dhamanmal Isardas’s agent in Burma is Hashim Premji &amp; Co. Rangoon. Memorandum: - Adviser to the GovernmentMMMM — T ITo.PA-c/, TIE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHHAII : 10 th FeUruriry, 19A?,, *s Political A^ent, Bahrain• ; iom orandunv: 1 RICE from Rangoon (Burma). Reference telephone conversation of this morning I am informed t r - e Representative of Messrs Dhamanmal Issardas, that the controlled price of rice in Rangoon is quoted at R$ 800/- per 100 baskets; that 2 l/s baskets are equivalent to a bag of 164 lbs net costing R§ 18.12,0 F.O.b/ Rangoon. ' The C.I.F. cost Bahrain would therefore be in the neighbourhood of r'3 8cg/o0 and after allowing a reasonable margin o.f profit the selling price here would not exceed Rs 32/35 per bag. This price is about l/3rd of the cost of Persian rice and it is estimated tvat up to n^OOO tons may be available if suitably recommended. -AHD PORT OFFICBR,BAHRAIN.^ $ ^±1 URGENT No. 464 Political Agency, Ballrkin, the 10th February 1948 To The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum I have been informed by the Adviser to the Bahrain Government that M ssrs. Dhamanmal Isardas is in a position to obtain up to 3000 tons of Rangoon rice provided his apolication is strongly recommended by the Bahrain Government. 2 . The Director of Customs, Bahrain, has further con firmed that Messrs. Dhamanmal Isardas h ve been informed by their agents in Rangoon, Messrs. Hushira Preraji &amp; Co., that the above mentioned quantity of rice may be available. 3. As the export of rice from Persia is to be completed before the 20th March, and it is unlikely that the quantity of Persian rice recommended will be imported into Bahrain before that period, I recommend that the Burma Government be asked to allow the export of Rangoon rice to Bahrain. 4. The Bahrain Government are anxious that this rice be imoorted, if possible, as it will be considerably cheaper than rice from Persia. 5. Far}.y action is requested. for Political ■'‘gent, BahrainThe Political Agency, Bahrain,, Dated the 12th February, 1948* MCCUDiKNDxJION CiiRTIFICATii Ho. -29/21 Certified that Messrs, .ioharaed Bafi Karmustaji, Bahrain, is permitted to import into Bahrain 200 tons Persian Gerdah Bice valued at £,14,000/- through Rezayat Trading Company, Tehran, *The Political Agency, Bahrain* Dated the 12th February, 1948. ' \ / ekco.; .j:mdatioh c^htificatk No. H-W -29/21 Certified that Mr* Yousuf Akbar All Reza is permitted to import into Bahrain 1000 tons Persian Champe Rice valued at Rs. 10,00,000/- through Messrs. Moharaedali Kliabiri, Teheran.Th« Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 12th February, 1943. 7 '' 'I v f * ^ &amp; % MCQXliiND-.TION CiultTIFICAT^ No. -29/21, Certified that Jr. Ahmad Yousuf Fakhroo, Bahrain, is permitted to import into Bahrain 300 tons Persian ^ice valued at £.25,000/- through Messrs. Mohamed Amin Khunji. LI illf n ,/f h ’ Political agency, Bahrain. Bated the 12th February, , 1948 . 1 | i^Cai.ffiWDATTOW CdHTIFTC,, ^ Mr ,. Certified that Messrs. J. A . Cohen &amp; Sons, Bahrain, is permitted to import into Bahrain 200 tons Persian Rice valued at Rs. 2,00,000/- through Mr. Salim iibrahim Nonoo, Khorrcimshahr. j—The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 12th February, 1948. RKCO.,L'IEKDaTIOW CaKTIFICATK No. j}?_ -29/21 Certified that Mr. Abdali Alaiwat, Bahrain is permitted to import into Bahrain 70 tons Persian Hie* valued at Rupees. 90,000/- through Messrs. Bayed Jabir Bayed Moosa The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 12th February, 1948. KBCCUaNDATION C^RTIFiC.Ja Ho. -29/21 Certified that Messrs. Kakoomal Valabdad Brothers, Bahrain, are permitted to import into Bahrain 300 tons Persian Rice valued at Rs. 3,00,000/- through Messrs. AbdullahNo. SOC, 29/21 The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 13th February, 1948. To. The Manager, Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. Memorandum:- Reference your letter dated the 24th January, 1948. 2 * I enclose herewith a recommendation certificate for Messrs. Yousuf Abdulrahman Fakhroo, Bahrain to import into Bahrain 100 tons Persian Rice wortih £.8600/- £ for Political Agent, Bahrain.I 'w 'A % * n The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 13th February, 1948. Racoima NDATiON certificate No. 5 ° 7 - - 29/21 Certified that Messrs. Yousuf Abdulrahraan Fakhroo, Bahrain is permitted to import into Bahrain 100 tons Persian Rice worth £.8600/-1 — ^ . (5a) Telegram From To No. A/120. Dated the 12th January, 1948 G. T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain, H. M*s Ambassador, Rangoon, Messrs. DHAIiiANiiAL ISSARDAS of Bahrain have been informed by their Rangoon Agents, Messrs. HASHIM PREMJI, that 3000 tons rice may be available for export here. 2. Rice required here. Most grateful if Burmese government could be asked to permit export. = REPGU = 80/78.A. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 12th February, 1948. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum No. 454, dated the 10th February, 1948 \ for Secretary to th§ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 1 biFEB 19481 o. _ ro sahrSA Ji! R^.J No. 533-80/78-A. / The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, ( . Bahrain&gt; i v » and is directed to transmit document(s) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. to him a copy of the undermentioned Dated 23rd February, 1948. -S' ’ Reference to previous Residency endorsement No.386--80/78-A, correspondence dated the 12th February, 1948. Description of enclosure. NAME AND DATE SUBJECT SI Telegram No.21 of 21-2-48 from Bowker, Rangoon, to Political Resident, Bahrain. Residency telegram No.A/143 of 23-2-48 to&gt; H.M's Consul- General, Basrah. RICE FOR BAHRAIN FROM BURMA. iCode, Telegram From Bowker, Rangoon, To Political Resident, Bahrain. Nd&gt;. 21. Dated the 21st and received the 22nd February, 1948. Your telegram A/120. Application for allocation of rice to Bahrain from Burma must be made to I.E.F.C through British Ministry of Food. BOWKERTelegram From To G. T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain* H. M's Consul General, Basrah No. A/143. Dated the 23rd February, 1948 Following for Ministry of Food Representative begins Dhamanmal Issardas of Bahrain have been informed by their Rangoon agents Hashim Premji that 3000 tons rice may be available for export here. 2. H.M's Ambassador, Rangoon, whom I oj approphed has telegraphed that application for allocation of rice to Bahrain from Burma must be made to I.E.F.C through British Ministry of Food. 3 . As rice is required here most grateful if authorities concerned could be asked to permit export of all or part of consignment. REPGU *PEKSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. No.676-80/78-A. Dated 10th March, 1948. A copy of the undermentioned document is forwarded to . with reference to Residency Printed Letter No.533 t 80/78-A, dated the 23rd February, 1948. i^u.unuii suzkj ^ u.c*ted the 27th February, 1948, from Ministry of Food, London, to H.M. Consul General, Basrah The Political Agent, / Bahrain, i By order etc 5* ^ V-Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfTelegram From To No. Dated Ministry of Food, London. H.M. Consul General, Basrah. GRUB X20. 27th February, 1948. &gt; Your telegram 26th February. Exportable surplus Burma rice 1948 purchased by Ministry Food on behalf recipients I.E.F.C. allocations STOP All available supplies period January - June allocated by I.E.F.C. mainly to destinations in S.E. Asia view of which regret export to Basra could not be approved STOP Allocations second half 1948 not yet made but owing continuity world shortage all available supplies will be required by deficit areas S.E. Asia./$IT) X No.g 1 */ -29/21. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 15th March 1948. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Sub r iset: -Rice r rom Rangoon'^ Memorandum 5 ' Reference correspondence resting with ycor memorandum No. PA-C/32 dated the 10th February 1948. 8. Enquiries reveal that all exportable surplus of Burma ricejava liable during the xtsi first ra If of 1943 has been purchased by the International Emergency Food Council and allocated mainly to destinations in South East Asia. Though allocution for the second half o r 1948 have not yet been made it is most unlikely that we will be able to obtain any rice for Bahrain', as all available supplies will be required by deficit areas in South East Asia.D.O. Wo. feSY-S* S-'*' Adviserate, March 21, 1948 His Highness has heard that the Shaikh of Kuwait and the Sultan of Muscat have been enabled to buy several thousand bags of rice from Pakistan through the assistance of their Political Agents. He has asked me to find out about this and to ascertain whether he may be enabled to buy two or three thousand bags for his own family. 2. Can you give me any information on the matter ? C.J. Felly, Esquire, O.B.E., I.C.S., H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain.^ 5.’ D.O.No. 949-29/17 Political Agercy, Bohrain The 23rd March 1948• ^ l / My dear Dredge, \ S I enclose herewith a copy of deaii-official letter No. 1064-50S.F. dated the 21st Maech 1948 from Belgrave and shall be grateful if you will give me any information on the matter. Yours sincerely Major A .L.A. Dredge, Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resinent in the | Persian Gulf, Bahrain, r ^D.C. No. Adviserate, April 20, 1948. rv&gt; I should be obliged if you would let me have a reply to my D.O. TTo, 1064-50/SF dated 21st March 1948, regarding rice forTHE IMPERIAL BANK OF IRAN BAHRAIN. 26th April, 1948 No .L/ 6 O /96 Bahrain. Dear Sir, We have received an application from our customers Sbrahim Alajaji &amp; Company to open a Letter of Credit as follows;- Amount;- £12, 000 /- Goods:- Brazilian Rice. From;- United States or Brazilian Port. To;- Bahrain 100 tons. Bahrain in transit 100 tons. The credit is to be established in favour of a firm in Egypt. Please inform us whether you can sanction this -import and if so please send us your Recommendation Certificate. Yours faithfully, rial Bank of Irant (n'b C.O. No. 1133-80/78,A. Pl'RSIflN ffiJJ.:' !tn:5XT!F*fC5t, BAHRAIN. 23 rd April, 1948 . % o '/ Please refer to your D* 0 # letter $o* 1 . 110 P- 0/48 dated the 2 nd April on the subject of rice* I am desired to say that have heard nothing officially about the Shaikh of Kuwait * s request .for the supply of rice through Seth ftfohd* Marsook* &lt; a have however received a request from the Shaikh of Bahrain that he may be permitted to buy 2000 or 3000 bags for his own family. Apart from this when the Political Fesiuent recently visited Owadur lie was asked to arrange if ^possible for the export fro© Karachi to that place of 200 tons of broken rice which is estimated to b© sufficient for local requirement* for 6 months* a •I sllar request was mad# to the Political Itesident at the end of 1946 and the 6 ind Crovernmeut then very kindly permitted the export of 150 tons of broken rice to Gwadur vide u telegram from Prices Karachi a copy of which 1 enclose. dir Hupert would be very grateful isimilar permission could be given, on this occasion^ n possible for 200 tons f ut&amp;i if he could be authorised to nominate an agent to Ha 3 ! it* It will be greatly up reclated 11 the aiattar can be dealt with urgently so tnat the Gw&amp;dux people can fetch the rice in country craft before the monsoon sets In if they uesire to import it in this manner* &gt;,ith # regard to the request receiveu from the shaikhs Of Kuv/ait and Bahrain for the import of rice from Pakistan I am to say that this commodity/ — Efajor M*G, Pixon, Deputy Secretary, Ministry of External Affairs &amp; Commonwealth Belations, h h h C * X.commodity is in very short supply at both places and c«*n only be obtained by illicit export from Persia, ^ir Bupert will therefore be very grateful for any rice that can be made available by the Pakistan Government for these two whaikudoms• to his D.O. No. 949-27/17 dated 23rd March, 1948 together with a copy of express letter No. C/269 dated 9th April, 1948 from the Political Agent, Kuwait with the request for confirmation that no rice has been supplied to Bahrain from Bind. The Political Agent, Kuwait reference correspondence ending with his express letter No. C/269 dated 9th April, 1948 together with a copy of letter No. D.1109-0/48 dated 2nd April, 1948 from Ministry of Foreign Affairs &amp; Commonwealth Relations, Karachi, with the request tnat the Shaikh of Kuwait may be asked whether it is a fact that he has asked the Pakistan Government to supply him with wheat through Mohd. Marzook. If necessary, and if he sees no objection, the Shaikh of Kuwait may be reminded that the Pakistan Government should have been approached in a matter of this nature through the Political authorities and not through a private agent in Karachi. Yours sincerely, Sd/- A.L.A, predge d. ; Copy tos 1 The Political Agent, Bahrain with reference 3 The Political Agent, Muscat for informationFrom Political, Kuwait Prodrome, Bahrain To No. C/269 Dated the 9th April, 1948. Reference your endorsement No. 922 dated the 30th March, 1948. Rice. 2. So for as Kuwait is concerned there is no truth in the report. 3* The Minister of Supply in the Sind Government Mr. Ghulam Ali Talpur, did, however, personally inform the Shaikh of Kuwait when the latter was in Karachi that Sind was supplying rice to Bahrain. Grateful for confirmation that this is correct. Sd/- M.P.O'C. Tandy. Major. Political Agent, Kuwait. COPYNo. 29/21. Political Agency, To The Director Af Customs, Bahrain• I forward herewith in original (return requested) an applicatlt -n dated the 24th April, 1948, from Messrs. Salman A. kaiksow, for foreign exchange for the import of rice from Brazil. of nearly 2,500 tons of rice from Iran. Import of rice from Brazil, a hard currency area, is to be discouraged as far as possible • I 2. I have so far issued recommendation certificates for the impor should therfore be grateful if to know : i. whekther rice in sufficient quantifies is forthcoming from ii. whether you consider the present position of rice in Bahrain warrants the import of rice from hard currency areas (I have been allotted a small quota of Brazilian Currency). for Political Agent, Bahrain.dated the 20th April, 1948 to Felly regarding rice for His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain^ ' 2. The Resident has requested the Pakistan Government to allow the export of rice from Sind to Bahrain and I shall let you know their reply in due course. Meanwhile would you please confirm that so far no rice has been supplied to Bahrain from Sind ? Apparently the Minister of Supply in the Sind Government, Mr. Ghulam Ali Talpur informed the Shaikh of Kuwait, when the latter was in Karachi that ' Sind ?/as supplying rice to Bahrain. I may add that the information that the Shaikh of Kuwait obtained several thousand bags of rice from Pakistan does not appear to be correct, as the Political Agent, Kuwait denies any knowledge of it. i C.D.Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. %No. 1376 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN /The 29th April, 1948 To The Director of Customs Bahrain. MEMORANDUM . The Qatar authorities report that a boom 'Hibbat Allah' master Mohd. Jassim of Dubai stopped at Bahrain on the way to Qatar with a cargo of 700 bags of rice (360 not manifested), all for that place^and that 350 bags were confiscated here by the Bahrain Government. I should be grateful if you would give me the facts of the case from your side of it. for Political Agent, BahrainCable Address.- KAIKSOWBAHRAIN Codes Used: BENTLEY’S COMPLETE Bankers: IMPERIAL BANK OF IRAN iJ&amp;oTiiiRw Bal'jK LTD. H. B. IPs Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF Zllhb- April Xa48 &amp; Sol *ie beg to inform you that we got an offer for i.50 tons, of Brazil Rice from our Agent in Bombay Mr,* Ahmed Abdulla Bassam. As we understand that there is shortage in Bahrain for rice and moreover we got this offer at a very reasonable price^ we are avery desirous of importing the same. &lt;*e shall be very much obliged if you will kindly issue a permit for opening a letter of credit for'£9600/- covering the ■value of this consignment.No.PA/- sz THE CUSTOMHOUSE s BAHRAIN: 2nd May, 1948•, Political Agent, Bahrain# M35 0RANDUM:- V H / » Reference your No.1368-29/21 of the 29th April, forwarding in original an application frcra. Messrs Salman A.Kaiksow, for foreign exchange for the import rice from Brazil, whilst there is a shortage of rice in Bahrain at present, supplies from Iran being very irregular, I cannot recommend hard currency being granted to .Kaiksow, as I understand this type of rice is being offered here, payment in sterling. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN, Enel—© No. 29/21, To Messrs* Salman A. Kaiksow, Bahrain. Political Agency, Bahrain. The (^'May, 1948. Sub : Foreign exchange for the import of rice from Brazil. S'v- &gt; , ' ^ Reference your application dated the 24th April, 1948, it is regretted that the exchange asked for cannot be granted. dk. for Political Agent, Bahrain. ic/'THE CUSTOMHOUSE: Reference your No # 1376 of the 29th April, 1948, I wish to advise that the Bahrain Government have not confiscated the rice in question* The facts of the case are as follows: Boom 'Hibbat Allah”, Nakhudha Mohamed Jassim arrived in this port from Iran, and surrendered to us a manifest covering 700 bags rice from Iran destination Oman ports. As is usual in the case of such dhows arriving here, the Nakhudha was requested to enter into Bahrain half the quantity - this he did through Yousuf Ibrahim Jaidah who sold seme in the open market. The remaining 350 bags were then overcarrid by the Nakhudha to Dubai , according to the documents lodged with us. Tims there is no evidence that this consignment was for Qatar, as surely the rice would have been properly manifested for that port, and is also evident from your letter that the Nakhudha has made a false declaration of destination to us. DIRECTOR OF CUSTCMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN,D.0. No. Reference your D.O. No.G-2/29-20 dated 1st May 1948, I thank you for your assistance in this matter and herewith confirm the fact that so far no rice has be^n supplied to Bahrain from Sind. Major H.E.H. Hifsclon Assistant Ba lira in. Political Agent,© Bo.^ • ^3 -29/20. To The Secretary to H.E. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 9th May, 1948 0 / $ Reference your demi-official letter No. 1133-80/78 A dated the 23rd April, 1948 to Major Dixon and copy endorsed to me regarding rice for Bahrain from Sind. 2. %t is confirmed that so far no rice has been supplied to Bahrain from Sind. ok 4 for Political Agent, Bahrain.Political Agency, Bahrain. The 8th M ay, 1948. &lt; The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandum . ^ y&gt; I forward herewith in original (return requested) an application dated the 6th May, 1948, from the Manage*, Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain, and shall be glad to know whether you recommend the import of rice from Belgian Cango. ^ &amp; for Political Agent, Bahrain. IGAtfo. 1513- 36/89 F. To The Adviser, Government of Bahrain, Bahrain* Political Agency Bahrain. The 15th May, 194 &gt; Memorandum . I forward herewith in original ^return requested) an application dated the 6th March, 1948,from the Manager, Eastern Bank L td., Bahrain, regarding foreign exchange for the import of rice from Belgian Cango by Mr. Yusuf Akbar Ali Reza. 2. The application was not recommended by the Director of Customs, presumably on the grounds that the import of goods from hard currency areas should be restricted to the minimum. But in view s £ or ^ age of rice at Bahrain and the recent report Cof which as yet I have had no definite confirmation) that Iran is not allowing the export to Bahrain, sha11 know whetter you wish to reconsider the decision of the Director of Customs and recommend the import from Belgian Cango. If the Government of Bahrain would undertake to take over the rice that may be exported from Belgian Cango, it is possible that the necessary exchange facilities may be afforded even though the currency involved is hard. A strong case could atleast be put up by this Agency. ! 0^3 for Political Agent, Bahrain.URGENT . No. R.56. ( 25b! To Political Agency, Bahrain. The 15th May, 1948. The Secretary to H.E. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum. I enclose in original (return requested) a letter dated the 12th %y, 1948 from M r. Yousuf Xhalil A1 Moayyed applying for foreign exchange for import of rice from Uruguay. \ ' ' 2. The offer from Uruguay is a firr^ ^r»e and the sample received is good. x he price also is compa ratively cheap, about Rs.23/- per maund. following reports that Iran has refused the export of rice to Bahrain, rice has now gone up to Rs.50/- per maund in the bazaar and unless rice can be imported from elsewhere the cost of living will riseappreciably. 3. There is an unspent balance of £12,500/- wofcth of South American Currency allotted to Bahrain last year, an$if you agree, I shall grant foreign exchange for £10,000/- out of this allotment to Yousuf Khalil A1 Moayyed for this import. • 4. For future guidance, I should be grateful to know whether imports of food, even from areas for which specific quotas of foreign exchange have been fixed, should be referred to you. The instructions are not quite clear on this point. tag for Political Agent, Bahrain.V (NEAR EAST) African and Lastern I ‘ !- 0 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) ASSOCIATED WITH THE UNITED AFRICA COMPANY LONDON, LIVERPOOL, MANCHESTER. ROTTERDAM. / ! IZV IELEGRAMS AND CABLES “ ETHIOPE, BAHRAIN.' M/t, B A H R A1N, 11th jay, ] gi48. A Dear Sir, We understand that the Board of Trade are at present negotiating the question of Sterling payments with Brazil. v«hen this is concluded, it is likely that Brazilian rice will be available for export. May therefore exchange authority be issued as follows 100 tons of Rice. Approx value £8000. Country of Origin - Brazil. / Destination - Bahrain. \ &gt; )&gt; y Yours faithfully, ' for the African &amp; Eastern (Near E^t) Ltd., /No. 1367 Office of tlo ArHri C!£&gt;T* t.n the G-overnme Dated, 11th May U 1 Reference your memorandum No.1513-36/89 F. dated 15th May 1948, can you inform me whether, if the Bahrain Government took over the rice in question, the quantity would be deducted from Bahrain’s wheat quota ? 2. I have reason to believe that rice in small quantities may be coming from Persia, Adviser to the Government.No.'btl TO Political Agency, Bahrain* The^^ fey# 1948. The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference your man orandum 2To. 1467-508.P. dated the 18th my 9 1948 regarding rice f, oxa Belgian Cango• f 2. I confirm that if the Bahrain Government takes over the rice in question, there will ae a reduction of 2/3rd ton in the wheat quota for every ton of rice imported* for Political Agent, Bahrain.(iri]e 3mk, (incorporated IN ENGLAND,) ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TELEORAPHIC ADDRESS EASTERTIDE. 48 political itgetit, ^ \ ' Bahrain Dear Sir, refer to our latter of eth Instant enclosing an application Ho*39/64 5ubnltte&lt;3. by Ifouauf A^bor Alireei for the import 6f Belgian Cong&lt;? Ripe and shall be glad to have your reply at an early date*! b Is this rice for consumption in Bahrain only ? How does the price compare with rice from Uruguay? ltd/- J.E.H. 12.5.48 t4?! as confirmed through the phone that the rice is for consumption in Bahrain and fiar not for reexport. The price of Uruguan ric-e is £78/- per ton C.I.F. and that of Belgian Cango rice is £96/- per tons C.I.F, Bahrain Bahrain (I Grade) and £58/- per ton C.I.F. Bahrain (IIGrade). ltd./- K.V.V513.5.48 ltd./- K.V ,R.13,5.48 Please draft to 'Adviser, informing him that the import of rice was originally refused by D of C, but that in view of the repoft that Persia is believed not to be exporting to Bahraii does he wish to reconsider D of C 1 s decision and ask for the import. If the Bahfain Government states they would take over the rice it is possible that the necessary exchange facilities would be granted , although the currency is hard. ltd./- J.E.H. 13.5.48 From N/Para. : D.f.a. to Adviser, ltd./- K.V.V. 15.5.48 Please issue. . ltd,/- K.Y.R. 15.5.48 ltd./- J.F,Uv315.5.48 (253) Issued memo. No, 1513 dt. 15,5.48 to Adviser, xssm. (254) Letter dated the 12th May, 1948 from Y^.K.Almoayyed. Je are left with an unspent allotment of £12,500/- for South American-Countries. Further the rice position in Bahrain is becoming more and more acute. In view of the above we may recommend a part of the import say upto the value of £10,000/- Itd./- K.V.V. 12.5.48 4k&gt;&amp; Tf we decide to grant exchange for import of rice from Ijard currency areas, I suggest that an equitable distribution should be made among all the leading merchants in Bahrain, who are the regular importers of rice into Bahrain, instead ofallotting all the -esehange to a single merchant. Most of the merchant? are not applying for such exchange, because they are undert the impression that foreign exchange for imports from hard currency areas' will not be granted. ltd.A K.V,R.12.5.48 Atould you please see 1.245 and N/Paras Mr. A1 Moayyad saw mw about hhis offer of rice yester day, and as he has a firm offer, and the sample received tbi itSr is good, rice, the price C.J.F. Bahrain .is comparatively cheap$ I recommend that we allot him £10,000/- out of * Es.23/- per maund approximately our unspent balance of £12500/-of South. American Currencies. mile agreeing with lupdt’s remarks in N/Para. as regards equitable distribution, I think this is a chance not to be missed, and that Mr. A1 Moayyad should be allotted ■ ^ currency, Rice has now gone upto Ik.50/- per maund in the bazaar on account of reports that IRAN has refused the export oi. rice to Bahrain, The banks have unofficially informed me of this also, and unless rice can be imported from else where the cost of living will rise appreciably. . . ltd./- J.E.H. Recommend, to P.R. for reasons quoted by you. ltd./- C&amp;P. 13.5.48 As this is a question of the import of food, I presume t.ii’s sanction is necessary, even for allotting exchange from our quota. Draft please on lines of N/Para. itd./- J.E.H.13.5.48 Please see S. 122 of File 36/89(Para. 2&amp;3), which states I 92 P.A. can issue R,C‘s for the grant of bar' 1 currency exchange within the quotas allotted to him with out reference to P.R. In view of the* above I do not. think that it is | 9 3 necessary to refer the matter to the Residency, but we can issue the R.C. direct. ikb no niV- nn &amp; The position is not unambiguously clear, please see , .49 para. 5(b) and S.42 and a reference to P.R. seems better. Da. ltd. K.V.R.15.5.48 Thanks. This should clear up the position. Please isa and mark 'Urgent'. ltd./- J.E.H. IS. 5.48 (255) Issued Memorandum Ho. R.56 dt. 15.5.48 to P.R. (256) Letter No. 394 dt. 11.5.48 from African &amp; Pastern Ltd. We have referred a simmilar application for rice to the Adviser. Please see ^ ltd./-K.V.V.17-5-48 This rice is from Brazil. Out of the total quota of £12560/- for imports from South American Countries, we have asked Residency's approval to the issue of R.C. for £10000/- t, Almoayyad for rice from u ruguay, so that we have no balance to meet this request. ltd./-K.V.R.17.5.48 It may be forwarded to the Residency with the remark j that we have only £2500/- balance left. Perhaps Residency can take up the matter with London. Draft please. Ifc ft?)- N/Para. D.f.a, 7 /- ltd./-J.H. 18,5.48 ltd./-K.V.V.19.5.48 ltd./- K.V.R.19.5.48 If rice exported from Brazil under exchange facilities ^ granted by us is to be set off against Bahrain wheat quota, it, then Bahrain may not wish to recommend. This application should pend clarification of the above question. ltd./- J.E.H. 20.5.48 (257) „ ^ . Memo. No. 1467-50? .Fl'of 1367 dt. 18.5.48 from Adviser. I The adviser is correct in his statement. For every ton of rice imported into Bahrain, $ tons of wheat is to be redugpd frofa wheat quota for Bahrain. Please see N/Para,99 of file 29/21 (Rice). The file 29/22 (Wheat) is under circulation. May this be informed to the Adviser? Please also see N/Para.92. Jtd.'/ K v , V Vi INDIA OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM&gt; \ Telegram ■ Cj.T.C. Political Agent, B^Iirain, -B-fit-ain; Bnoniirer- * Po-T.C . 404. Dated txde 10th June 1945. IMPORTAhl * ■ : i *',} x ,/; | v,: ‘f . . My tel. 391 June 6th. 2, To relieve critical wheat situation it may he necessary to reduce your quota against imports of rice. 3. A general reduction of quota would appear un desirable in view of irregularity of imports of rice but what tonnage of wheat if any can Truciai Coast forego against nest consignment. Fitom To No. POnlTICAi.COPY Telegram From To Wo. G • T • C # political Agent, Bahrain. P.O., T.C., Sharjah. 405. Dated the 10th June 1945. Unless particularly urgent work detains you please come here forthwith for consultation. You snouid bring reply to telegram No. 404 dated June 10th with you unless this involve its delay. ft'I P0LITICam xlkb (Original of the telegram on file 1/42)' URGiiilT Wo. 2377 - 28/21* PGidTlCiUu AGiiWCY BAdEAIli. The 10th June 1845. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. MnMQtlAhlXJM Tfte M. h.O.C. sa^ that ovdng to the critical wheat situation f the wheat quotas will have to be reduced against imports of rice. 2. please let me know urgently what reduction in tonnage of Bahrain* s quota of 660 tons of wheat per noonth can, in your opinion, be borne against the tonnage of rice imported which, in May 1845 for instance, amounted to 240 tons and in the 2 preceding months was 4 and 215 tons res pectively. I would suggest that a general reduction in the quota would not be advisable because of the irregularity of imports of rice, but it should be possible for Bahrain to forego a proportion at least of the next consignment of wheat from the d.K.C.C. 3. please also keep me informed of ai-1 consignments of rice imported into Bahrain as when they occur. I under stand Ibrahim Nonoo is importing 600 bags by f N&amp;khuda Ibn Howeh*. for POLIXICiU, AGENT, BAahAIN. KiteTelegram From To No. Dated G.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire. % Political Agent, Bahrain. 1060. and received 10th June 1045. Your tel. 300 June 6-th. 2. please ascertain ai^report (a) tonnage (b) price and furnish to me only similar information* in respect of rice stated by Middle East'Supply Centre to have been imported by ibranim Nonoo. = 0i-iijl0V\/AY =: KMS No Re to Date... f.P.. C (ri Jp J o AMC. f Te leg ram From To No. G.T.C. No.&lt; P.O.T.C. Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain. 647 4 Dated and received 11th June, 1946. Reference to your telegrams Nos. 391,404,405 dated 7th and 10th June. ^/I? V ^ ' ; 1 61 tons rice imported from April 1st from Persia at Rs.1120 per ton. Trucial Coast can forego whole Juno ? wheat quota still retaining 2 months reserve. Am arriving Bahrain twelfth by flying boat at about 1400 hours. -POLITICAL^^7 n Telegram From To - Repeated No. * Dated Paliram Jl...Dat 0 ^ s ,, . ^ l «A-*4 fire u.T.C. ^ Political ResidentBushire. Political Agent, Kuwait Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. Hallows. 1062 11th received 12th June, 1945, (Z) Addressed Kuwait Bahrain and Muscat repeated Hallows. Owing to the critical wheat situation please investigate and report by telegram possibi lity of reduction in your cereal quota for 3 months July to September. Ratio § wheat to i- adulterant Should be maintained. Any reduction I may be prepared to offer will be made conditional on ?their adhering to agreement ?that rice should be set off against total cereals vide ?Residen cy Endorsement ?913 S December 15th, 1944. } • =GALL0WAY= AMO. Ktltx) Cl flute /■i/v H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, MEMORANDUM: THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 12th June, 1945 „, *• 6 ^. iji.i Mo4!ftra...Da 6 » |p lit € 7/ith further reference to my memorandum No.PA/414 of the 5th inst, Yusuf Fakhroo has imported a further 201 bags of Persian rice. The price is not known. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOIvS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRA3N.Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Britain, Bushire. 419. / Dated the 14th June 1945. My tel. 410 of June 11th. Fakhroo has imported a further 20 half 40 tons of rice details of which ar£ as in my telegram referred to above. POiITICaLasm*. w 1 ‘ Telegram la.T.C. From To No. Political Agent, Bahrain, Britain, Bushire* 423. Dateo the 14th June 1945. Youi telegram No. 1044 dateo. June 5th. 2. 61 half 122 tons rice purchased from Persia by Trucial Coast since April 1st at ns. 1120 per ton. 3. I propose to report such purchases monthly beginning e&amp;Joh month. ^ = POLITICALC 11/tu*) Copy i ) JiRuiiiMT Wo. 1165-50SF. Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, June 14, 1945. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - Ml , ^ Reference your memorandum No. 2S77-2d/^l dated 10th June J-d45, regarding the reduction of wheat quota ggainst importo ol rice. The rice which has entered 'Bahrain is rice Vviiicn was smuggled out of Persia and bought by local merchants, in most cases it was brought in dhows as a speculation and sold J Wannuaas if the price was good. There are no shipping do cuments for this rice and none has been boght by the Bahrain Goveinment nor is its distribution or price controlred. It is not paxt of the ration and is owned mdstly by foreign merchants who bought it with a view to selling later at a profit when rice becomes scarce. nice is to be regarded by the U.h.d.C. as. part ol oui cereal quota then it must be acquired by the Government a^d di^tiibuted as a ration, in which case the equivalent quan- trty of wheat can be reduced from our wheat quota, but the ac- quioition of fice from private owners who have already done some local, buying and selling presents difficulties. I fear however tnat n the Government takes this action it will Kill the hen thac rays tiie golden egg. The Government allows profit to importers of such staple food as rice and this will not be suf- licient inducement for Nakhudas to bring rice to Bahrain and uiey Cud seil it more prolitabiy elsewhere, Katif has already bought more of this rice than Banrain. ' • .. 3;. The Bahrain Government is negociating to buy rice direct |Tf this rice materiaiizes it wi-ii be issued as a ration and the !equivalent of wheat can be reduced. 4. I do not. think the present cereal ration can be further reduced it is now BO lbs. per head per month including 5 lbs. oi bailey which in most cases the people cannot use. It is tde : f orm flour, half of the. population do not eat bread and our milling capacity is already strained to the utmost. The two oia mills wnich we commandeered have collapsed and only the two new ones are working, but a third new mill has been ordered from India. 5. If the Bahrain Government commandeers all rice in private nanuo cuid uiotrib&amp;ties it as a ration then the equivalent quantity oi wheat can be deducted irom our quota but if this quantity is deducted and^the privately owned rice is not commandeered then tne public will be worse oil than they are nov ? and only a small gx oup of merchant o win proiit. i am now taking steps to en deavour to purchase new shipments of rice that are brought here ioi Scale ana any rice which is obtained w T ill be accumulated for use as a ration. • bd/- U.BniGdiiVM. Aaviser to the Government.73 / 143 . Telegram R. Frcia To No.1006. PcUtloal Resident j Bushlre. H.M. i\r;bf-35a6or, Baghdad. Dated the 30th May, 19*16. *// ,v7&lt;o Following for 'idole last Supply Centre. % Fakhroo has recently Im^rted rice from Persia into Bahrain. Details are not available at present but will be rumisheci on receipt. Bahrain iloverniaant are endeavourl g to purchase B f 000 bags of rice fro-a Khorraioshahr through a local merchant♦ 3. Kuwait GovexniMent are also endeavouring to obtain 400 tons Persian rice direct. LB« - a.iLuovu'i - Persian Gulf Residency* na Dated the 30th !iay, Copy forwarded with, compliments to*- 1. The Political Agent, 2. The Political Agent, mmm,, ^ LB. Bahrain ReceiptNo. of 1364 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 4th Rajah, 1364 dune 14, 1945. E. B. M’s political Agent, Bahr ain. Reference your memorandum No. 2401-29/21 dated 11th dune 1945. Ibrahim Noono has imported 58 tons of rice from Persia. The price is not known. Adviser to the Goverament. Memorandum: - Babram Receipt No..Mn? &gt; A:.-' /Mm. An.•T Telegram From To Rep eated ITo.?!?. Inter* H.M.Ambaasaddr f Tehran. Foreigi office, London Ho.537. Political Resident, Push ire. MEMIH Ceiro for H.S.O.C. Gonsu 1-ifene ral, Basra for Kackenzi Dated 2nd received 4th June 1945. My telegram Ho.393. (?) The prices quoted by Persian Government are no longer firm and latter now consider theueelves free to dispose of rice elsewhere. it may however still be possible to persuade them to sell from whatever stocks are available. 1 should be glad therefore to know whether His Uaje&amp;ty's Government could guarantee such a transaction. Unless something can be arranged food situation in Gulf will V s oon be bad. Furthermore poreian Government will i not be“ encourage* to treat future requests from us for ' cereals seriously. 2. political Resident Persian Gulf who is now in London has doubtless ajsplained position. - H.K.AMBASSADOR - CCHFlD-ar tiai . II0 . 64 l«rS » Persian Gulf Residency, Bush ire, the 9th June 1945. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, KUWAIT , The Political Agent, Ths Political -vgent, MUSCaT, P in continuation c£ Residency Endorsement Ho. 536-S, dated the 19th May 1945. RHL, P 7 ( -/r ’ fc KM3 i t 1 1 Telegram From To m. 2. O • i # L/ • Political Aaent, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. Dated the 23rd June 1945.' r % tel. 425 June 17th. ( Bahrain Government have bought 300 half boo tons rice locally during June and can therefore accept reauction of 200 half 400 tons wheat and 100 half 200 tons barley from quota. . . Begret I am unable to predict purchases of rice by Bahrain Government and can only suggest ouota re nnet ions as and wh&amp;vthey occur. POnliTuaLI No. 2613 - 29/21. POiil'IICAii AGUSICY The 24th June 1345. To y, .Mrntia^DuM The political Officer, Trucial Coast, bhAttJAh. June 1345. Reference my telegram No. 531, dated the 6th 2. Mohamad Kaorif is believed to have importer. 550 bags of rice into Truciai Coast through an exporter Hussein . Moneia. please confirm the quantity price and country of origin and also keep me informed of ail consignments of rice imported into Truc^al Coast as and when they occur.V// of Telegram From To Repeated Code. Political Resident, Bushirff . 0 Political Agent, Kuwait. -do- Bahrain. Hallows. -do- Muscat. No. 1121, dated 23rd, received 24th June, 1945. RICE. 2. Information regarding transaction reported and all other transactions should be telegraphed me as soon as possible. 3. As M.E.S.C. insist on deductions from wheat/barley quota against all imports of rice immediate steps should be taken to ensure distribution of all rice imported privately. =GALLOWAY= NS.TQlegr a ra. From. To. No. 1122 Dated and received 23rd June 1945. Cypher. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. P.sVr:! Receipt ZtoM'H.Dxte ky Immediately preceding telegram refers to ..B.3.C., Baghdad telegram of Jane 20th No. 7(7) to me. GALLOwAY LR. I.R. 426LrivuJ-iO ^ Aj \ Telegram From To Repeated Ko. Dateu Code. * Political Rt. si dent, Bushire. Ambassaaork Baghdad. (for M.d.u».C) Political Agent, Balirain. -dol Muscat. -do- Kuwait. and -ao- care Sind Government, Karachi, 1126. 2oro and received ,24th June 1945 ♦ in view of critical wheat situation I have been investigating possibility of temporary reduction of quotas of Shaihndoms and of deductions againsc rice imports. 2* Following temporary reductions now possibles (a) Trucial Coasts Reduction of wheat quota Jjy hundred (half 200) tons per month for 3 months July, August, September. (b) Muscats Reduction for same period of months of quota to wheat 310 half 620 tons and barley 190 , , half 380 tons against 400 half 800 tons Persia rice recently imported the details of which are 320 half 640 tons SADRA at 120 half 240/*'* i ton and 80 half 160 tons CHMPA at ,3. 90 half 180 per ton f.o.b. Khorramshahr. 3. Further communication will be made regarding Kuwait and Bahrain after investigation of recent reports o: imports of rice. KMB(S) L No. 2657 - 29/21. POLITICaij AGMCY, BAHRAIN. The 25th June 1945. To M£M3HANDLJM The Adviser to the Bunrain Government, Bahrain. , ' i I id I l The Middle East Supply Centre insist on deductions from Banx-ain*s wheat/barley quota against ail imports of rice and immediate steps should be taken to ensure distribution of all rics imported privately. KM5 - for POLmCAjj aGKKT nr rom. To. -iepaatad Telegram. Q©de. Political Resident, Bushire. Ambassador, Baghdad (for Political agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political agent, muscat. No. H51 Bated and received 27th June 1945 . 'S lm Oxil^PT Paragraph Ko.2 (b) of my telegram ho. 1126 June 23rd. P±ices oi Persian Bice imported by Buscat are per bag repeat bag and not per ton. BALLOKAY LB. .Ji, Bahrain iltc 1 ’ ±i ‘ 1 N 0 --!A...Data..11...;..4* - Cypher. Political Resident, hnshire, Political Agent, Bahrain. Telegram. From. To. No. 1152 Dated and received 27th June 1945 /&gt; /?'ft- 0 a 9 Your telegram No. 445 June 23rd. I should like as accurate information as possible at least as regards quantities of all government or private imports of cereals in order to answer allegations by LI.J.C.^. of imports into Sheikhdoms. Sven‘as. regards source, agency and price it is difficult to contend that information ? cannot be obtained. In Gulf the onus is on us to see that imports and distribution are properly controlled. n A. I.iU 432 HoJftfO ... =GALLDA^Y=? ZIJ C.Q. lio • ry &lt;/ f £j%j * &gt;o / •' &lt;&amp;«#/ (S o-t POidilUa, /.GUSCl, BAHHaIH. Tiu 1st July 1945. My dear Beigrave, Reference our conversations this msrning I have reported to the Hon»ble the Political Rsside.it that in auuition to the SCO tons of rice reported by you in your jaemoraudua Mo. 1S05-50SF dated the gist June 1945, *40 tons .i-ve since been controlled by the Bahrain Government and that details regarding the source agency and (if possible) pr^ce will be reported later when recommendation for reduction in the quota against this quantity *111 also be made in the usual proportions. I shall be grateful for the details as soon as possible and as I know the Kiddle East Supply Centre wixi press the Political Resident to give them so that they can draw up a long range programme. «• I am glad you are able to indicate some hope that more barley will be consumed ana X trust that you will be successful in getting tnis donee Yours sincerely. Bexgrave, Esquire, Adviser to the Bahrain Govermsent, Bshrein. jUMtwn*)) Telegram. From. To. No. 391 Dated 2nd July 1945. (Cypher) Political ngent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bhshire. /« j n fi **' 2 . . a Gorresj ondence ending with your telegram No. 1152 June 27th Amounts of rice reported in r.y telegrams Nos. 390, 419 . and 452 dated the 6th, 14th and 26th June should please he regarded as part of 300 tons reported in my telegram No. 445 dated the 23rd June. ^0.4 3. Belgrave informs me in addition to this 300 tons 440 half 330 tons have been imported and are now under government control. Since transaction was spread over some time and rice sold and re-sold considerable difficulty experienced in achieving control and it will take a little time to get details, bill telegraph them when available and then recommend that this 440 tons be subtracted from quota in usual proportions. 4. Because of Bahrain Government's action in controlling rice Belgrave of opinion that imports will cease and rice if forth coming will go elsewhere e.g. Jatif and .^atar as some has done already. LA. +P0LITI0xiL+-V Telegram Prom To No. 1173. « Dated and received 29th June, 1945. Cypher. political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. ® 'Y , 1 ^ M.E.S.C. Baghdad telegram No. 7 to me of June 20th. Rice shipments. x 2 . 3. Figures are in bags repeat bags. Country origin believed to be Persian. =GALL0WAY= N3 * Bahrain Receipt I.H. N' f&lt;7 c •••Copy . ® ^ Telegram From To Repeated No. 2 . Q- Political Resident, Bushire. Ambassador, Baghdad (for M.h.o.C.'). Political Agent, Bahrain. 1176. Dated and received 29th June 1945, paragraph No. 3 of my telegram 1126 June 23rd. Bahrain Government has purchased 300 half 600 rice and can therefore accept reduction of 70 half 140 tons wheat 30 half 60 tons barley in quota for July August and September. GAiiJ-iOhiiY Kil/ll (jjv tav, r /n?) ,u Telegram From To No. June. G.T.C. political Agent, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 4B2. Dated the 5th July 1945. | D in continuation of my tel. 423 June 14th. No rice was imported by Trucial Coast during POLITICALTelegram From To No. 2 . they occur G.T.C. political A^ent, Bahrain, political Officer, Sharjah. 483 . Dated the 5th July 1945. fy ft*} My tel. 591 June 6th. please report all imports of rice as and when in future. POLITICALUrgent. No. /joy—of 1364 Office of the Adviser to the G-overnriB nt, Bahrain Dated, 25th Rajah, 1364 July 5, 1S45. H. B. Li’s- Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - I should be obliged if you \vou^d kindly issue a certificate to the effect that there is no objection to the import by Kaji Yusuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo of 200 tons rice from Persia. This quantity is being bought on behalf of the Bahrain Government . Yours faithfully, Adviser to the Government.V iiQ QbjbWIQti ChKIIFICAJL This is to certify that there is no local objection to the import by H&amp;jl Yusuf Abciulrehman pakroo ox 200 tons of rice from Persia, Forwarded to: The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, \vith reference to his memorandum No, 1SC4-5CSF, da 5 th July 1M5, K.M5 q ' for Political Agent, Bahrain Ho, 277 Political Agency, Bahrain, 7th July 1946•40 Telegram Prom To No. raia Recs'pt G.T.C. Political, Sharjah. Political, Bahrain. 752. r.rA Dated 7th and received 8th July, 1945. y P Reference your memorandum No.2613 dated June 24th. Import referred to not traced nor are Muhammad Kaorif and Hussein Monem known in Dubai and Sharjah. Kindly verify correctness of names and report where consignment was landed. Political. C/8-7Telegram From To Wo. G* i • C• Political Agent, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 493 . Dated the 8 th Jaly 1945. VI P Your telegrams Wos. 1121 and 1122 of June 2erd. 2. import to Sharjah referred to is not traced nor are Muhammad Kaorif and Hussein Monem known in Dubai or S&amp;arjah. Could you kindly verify correctness of names and report where consignment was landed. POr.IilCAi, KMSFrom To Political Agent, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. ho. 4o4. Dated the 9th July 1945. Your telegram ho. 1152 June 27th. 2. 580 half 1160 tons of rice transhipped to Saudi Arabia through Bahrain, a direct result of our insistanc that rice imported here be taken over by Bahrain Government. Grateful if M.h.b.C. courd be ashed whether these and similar consignments are being subtracted from Saudi Arabia 1 s quota and I be informed of result. . POuilloniiNo. 2834 - 29/21 POLITICAL AOL’VCY, QAIIHATN. The 11th July 1945 To The Director of Customs Bahrain. MKliQi-^NDTIM Reference your endorsement No. PA/SF/55/464, dated nil. 2* Imporos of rice reported by the Adviser and you total 148 tons only vide his memorandum No. 1136-50 SF dated the 14th June 1945 and your memoranda Nos. PA/ 414, PA/426 and PA/449, dated 5th, 12th and 27th June, of 350 tons of rice is shown as imported during June 1945 also let me know whether the 350 tons imported has been taton over by the Bahrain Government? respectively. 3 In your endorsement referred to above a total ^ill you please reconcile these figures andG.T.C. Tg log ran To Prom Political Officer, Sharjah Political Agent, Bahrain. 771.' Dated 10th and received 11th July 1945 Reference yo r telegram No* 496 dated July 9th Hitherto rice has only been shewn in regular £ dated Ju] monthly imports and exports statements and not- in monthly stock report as it is a commodity obtained by barter in the same way as dates. Furthermore details of rice stock not previously called for. Details of rice imported from July. 1944 to March 1945 sent with-my memorandum No. 754 dated July 8th. Rice is not completely controlled. POLITICAL ✓ /Telegram Prom To Repeated Q* Political Resident, Bushire, Ambassador, Baghdad (for M.E.S.C.) Political Agent, Kuwait. -do- Bahrain. -do- Muscat. lik No. 1272. i Bated 11th Received 12th of July, 1945. Rice shipments to Sheikhdoms. It has been impossible to obtain confirmation i i i i in regard to any of the shipments reported and it is unlikely , v that further details even if obtainable would be of any use. 2 . both Kuwait and Bahrain report that attempts to improve Government control on consignments arriving at these * have resulted in their divepcion 'I'o o+hpr* ■noTeo ports e.g, a consignment of 580 (half 1160) has been transhipped to Saudi Arabia via Bahrain. Presume M.E.S.C. is being kept informed of rice reaching Saudi Arabia and that deductions to wheat quota against rice imports are not confined to Sheikhdoms. as regards Kuwait purchases of rice, which are made from quanti ties arriving there in transit to other ports,are too small (120 bags per mensem) and too expensive for general distribution. ^ * In addition to quantities already reported following further consignments have been imported*- Bahrain, (a) 40 half 80 tons CHBMPA price Rs. 920/- c.i.f. Bahrain importer Yusuf Fakhroo (Paragraph No. 1 of my telegram No. 1006 May 30th to Baghdad only refers). &gt;7 V (b) 58 half 116 tons CHAMPA from Persia price is. 860/- half 1720 c.i.f. Bahrain importer Ibrahim Noonoo. L These form part of 300 tons reported in my telegram No. 1176 June 29th to Baghdad. (c) 50 tons rice from Khorramshahr through Muhammad A1 Ganim of Basrah price Rs. 980 half 1960 c.i.f. Bahrain importer Yusuf Fakhroo; Trueial CoastJ- 60 half 120 tons from Persia price Rs. 1,120 half 2240. =GALL0WAY= ns. Bahrain Receipt IR. 474/12.7.' ' TE.O . Telegram Code. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1274. Dated and Received 11th July, 1945. Surely Bahrain Government with their large financial resources and greater facilities of barter than private merchants could make more energetjb|t%\ efforts to import Persian rice on their own account than appears to have done? Please stir them up. If desired I will ask Consul Khorramshahr’s assistance. =GALLOWAY= NS. IR.473/12.7. Bahrain ReceiptTelegram From To No. 1275. Dated 11th My immediately preceding telegram refers to paragraph No. 3 of your telegram 3S1 July 2nd. =GALLOWAY= NS. % IR. .12/7. Cypher. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Received 12th July 1945.I 1 1 (SS) no, -sail Political Agency, Bahrain, The 14th July, 1945, My dear Belgrave, » , Will you kindly refer to your memorandum No.1165-50 S.F. dated June 14th in which you wrote that the Bahrain Government was negotiating to buy rice direct from Persia? The Political Resident has telegraphed to me inquiring whether the Govern ment lere, with its large financial resources and greater facilities for barter than private merchants could not make more energetic efforts to import Persian rice. Could you let me know what has been done so that I can reply? I myself am greatly afraid, that, after the usual time-lag (say in 4 or 5 months time) the demands for wheat in Europe will make themselves felt in drastic cuts of our quotas here and that it would be folly not to prepare for that possibi lity now. I am going to Sharjah to-morrow but hope to be back on the 17th. Yours sincerely, Sd. C.J. Pelly. a( C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.Telegram From To Ho. G.^.G. Political Agent, Bahrain., Political Officer, Sharjah. 509. Bated the 14th July 1945. Youi ’ tel • No. wfdatoc d 10th July You should warn Trucial liulers concerned tnat in their own interest they should control rice as 7«8 (half 1576) tons will now he set off against •dieat quota and future imports of wheat reduced accordingly in usual proportion barley-wheat. POLITICALv-^ * uU’ / .r ss) S-v l;o . 13^- ° f 1364 Office of the Adviser to the G-overnment, Bahrain Dated, 6th Shaahan, 1264 July 16, 1945. E. B. It's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- (U Reference your memorandum No. E834-29/S1 dated 11th July 1945, addressed to the Dir ectcr of Customs. The figure given 'by me included rice imported during March, April, May and June amounting to 809 tons Of this the Government bougnt 6b0 tons, ine Government also bought 90 tons during July from rrce . imported in July, this accounts for the j-igur^ of r r 740 tons. The 'balance between 650 tons and 809 tons was consumed locally so could not be taken over by the Government. The following is detail of imports:- March £15-tons April 4 ' May Slo ' June 550 ” 80S tons. q 7, 1&gt; • mi Adviser to the Government. , C/ p V 'Vi - iiTelegram From To No. Dated (3) Bahrain Receipt ^ So ML Dat. n.-2x^ G.T.C. Political Resident, Shiraz. Political Agent, Bahrain. T/137 18th received 19th July, 1945. A My telegram 510 July 14th. Could Bahrain ?Government not purchase ? part of Trucial Coast stock of rice? = GALLOWAY = /7 S t AMO.KMb Telegram From To No. G • T • C • Political Agent, Bahrain. Galloway, B&amp;gh Shaikh, Shiraz. 524. Dated the 19th July iG45. Bahrain Government can accept a further reauction in quota 500 half 600 tons wheat and 140 half 280 tons barley against 440 half 880 tons rice taken over locally in adaition to that reported in tel. 445 of 23rd June 1045. ^ $ POLITICAL0 0 Telegram From To No. My immediately preceding telegram refers to my telegram No. 3&amp;1 of 2nd July 1945. ''' v p = POijli'ICAjj G.l.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Galloway, Bagh Shaikh, Shiraz. 525. Dated the 19th July 1945. KM5@ s Telegram F^om To No. / f {r lb f ' ^ 1 I f | G • T • C • Political Agent, Bahrain. Galloway, Bagh Shaikh, Shiraz. 520 # Dated the 19th July 1945. ✓ P C'b Your telegram No. T/137 dated the lutu Julj• o ’ Trucial Coast’s consumption of cereals per « month is 1230 (half 2460) tons. As will be apparent from my telegram No. 51Q^dated the 14th July it had approximately two months supply on 1st July. Bahrain* s consumption is 1000 (halt 2000) tono D er month. To cereal stock figures in my telegram 498 ^ ^ 'W t. dated' 9th July please add 740 (half 1460) tons rice now taken over by Bahrain Government and 600 (half 1600) tons wheat received on 12th July from 6 .K.C.C. stocks and it wixl be apparent Bahrain has stock to last for two months and three weeks as from 1st July. Hegret therefore I see no repeat no good reason for taking rice from Tr u ^i al Coast. 5 # i should be glad if I coaid be informed amount of next consignment of wheat for Trucial Coast and when it will arrive. POnlilO/uj KM6■ ...Mt.H , Ai'J.i.SC Adviserate, -ini v 17 1 Q 45 . 7ith reference to your No.2864-29/21 dated 14th July 1945. f\i? amount of barter which is now available is sufficient only for use in buying livestock, ghee, firewood etc. from Persian ITakhudas. Were it used to encourage the import of rice there would either be a^shortage of meat etc, or the price of meat would increase very greatly. The barter value oi- sugar is now .s.320/- per bag, it used to be over Ir. 500/- per bag, the barter value of tea is Is. 7/12/- p ,r lb. Barter for meat is given at the rate of 50% sugar and 50% tea. The Bahrain Government has bought 740 tons of r ^- ce * ^ ^his is being sold to ration holders at 13 . 2 /- P ei&gt; Wheat is sold at -/ 12 /- per roba and barley at -/10/- per roba. The price of rice is now higher than before and would work out at about 2/10/- per roba ii/more were purchased for sale to the public. _l iio equivalent amount is to be deducted from our grain quota so unless rice was heavily subsidized it would be difficult for the general public to buy rice instead of grain. If however the price of rice in Persia decreases then the Bahrain Government will make more purchases. I fully appriciate the danger of future cuts in our quota but will it be to our advantage to buy more rice now, at high cost, knowing that the equivalent amount will be -deducted from our grain quota ? 0 . I. pelly, Bsquire, O.B.E., I.C.S., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.i T) Telegram. From. To. No. 422. Dated 21st July 1945. 29/21-11 Code. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. Your telegram No. 1274 dated 11th July, jp 2. Please refer to my telegram No. 526 dated 19th July for latest figure of rice taken over by Bahrain Government. 3. Wheat is sold here at three annas and Barley at two and a half annas per lb. Rice bought now from Persia would cost fourteen annas pei* lb. For this reason I do not think further l . purchases can be expected. POLITICAL LR.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 21st July 1945. No. 2962 - 29/21. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Govei Bahrain. ESMO : ANDUiki Reference your memorandum No* 134.0-60Sf of July 16th 1946. I have recommended to the Hon’ble the Political Resident that 300 tons of wheat and 140 tons of barley be reduced .from the Bahrain quota against Idee taken over locally. This is in addition to the 300 tons reduction already re commended by the Hon'ble the Political Resident vide my menoEandum No. 2708 - 29/1 o:£ 1st July and. referred to in my D» 0. No. 27 .st July 1946. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAINTeLsgram. Code, From. Political Resident, at Shiraz. To. Pplitical Agent, Bahrain. No. T/102 Circular (should read as T/152) Dated 21st and received 22nd July 1945. IMPORTANT Following is repetition of Oovernraent of India telegram No. 6427 dated July 20th. Begins: Rice for ShaUch&amp;cwats. 2. 5,000 to 7,000 tons of old crop JOSHI rice may become available very shortly for export from Sind. Though somewhat damaged by rain it is reported fit for human consumption cost estimated about Rs.9 - 8 annas per maund. 3 . Please wire urgently whether you would be willing to accept their rice or part of it provided shipping would be arranged. Ends. 2. Please telegraph urgently whether state would be willing to accept this/rice* Allocation between Shaikhdoms will be in proportion to existing cereal quotas. GALLOWAY. Lfi - • -.7 ' I.R. No. 501 rdirab ?.5cs*pi No-. . .£V7.. Data.Telegram From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Officer, Sharjah. No. 534. Dated the 22nd July 1945. Important Between 5000 and 7000 tons for Sheikhdoms of old crop Joshi rice may become available for export from Sind. It is somewhat damaged by rain but reported to bo fit for human consumption. Cost estimated at about Rs. 9/8/- per maund (presumably Indian). Please telegraph urgently how much you are prepard to accept if shipping can be arranged. POLITICAL K:' SURG^I POiilTICAu AGhJSCX, BAHRAIN. No. 2986 - 29/21. The 22nd July 1945. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. MiJIQHAhDUM I have been informed that there may possibly be an exportable surplus of 5000 to 7000 tons of old crop t Joshi f rice from Sind. It is somewhat damaged by rain but is said to be fit for human consumption. Cost is estimated at about ife. 9/8/- per maund (presumably Indian). 2. Please inform me very urgently whether the Bahrain Government are prepared to accept this rice and if so, up to how many tons provided shipping can be arranged. $ ^ for POLITICAi. AGiiliT, BAtiUAlJNNo Bahrain Receipt - &lt;? ^ y &lt; h3 ...Date Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Shiraz. To H. M 1 s Arnba s sad or, Bag hdad. ( for M.K.S.C•) Repeated political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/167 Dated 22nd received 23rd July, 1945 From Political Hosidont in the Persian CJulf addressed Baghdad for Piddle liast dapply Centre repeated Bahrain. y My telegram No.1176 ? June 29th . Bahrain Government has acquired a further 44u half 880 tons Persian rice and can therefore accept V_a ? further reduction of 300 half 600 tons wheat and 140 half 280 tons ? Barley ? spreading over the 3 months July to September. «GALJ.O//AY-No. of 1364 Office of the Adviser to the Go Dated, / Bahr u in T s Political Auent, ub Aer.oranduin: - Reference your memorandum No. 2986-29/21 dated 22nd duly 1945. The Bahrain Governmen t would be willing to purchase 2,000 tons of the rice. Adviser to the Government. — y (ofTelegram G.T.C. -from Residency Agent, Sharjah To Political Agent, .Bahrain h r o. 813 Dated 24th received 25th July, IMPORTANT. Your teiogram 534 dated July 22nd. V/o are prepared to accept 400 ^half 800) tons ox Joshi rice provided this quantity is not repeat not set off against Trucial Coast quote of U.K.O.C. wheat. -= BRITAGENT^Telegram From Q • i Political Resident at Shiraz. Government of India, New Delhi. Repeated to Political Agent, Kuwait. -do- Bahrain, -do- Muscat. No. T/177. Dated 25th Received 26th July, 1945. /o Your telegram No. 6427 July 20th. Rice for Sheikhdoms. i 2. Many thanks offer. ' Shaikhdoms will probably be able to accept total quantity available. Confirmation will follow. Kuwait and Muscat would be grateful if oppor tunity could be afforded to their agents to inspect rice. I should be grateful if this could be arranged. P.A. s should make it clear locally that inspection is merely for confirmation of condition and that no haggling over price will be permitted. 3 . Kuwait Agent is Mohammed Marzuk, Bori Road, Karachi. Will P.A.s Muscat (and P.A. Bahrain if Bahrain Government also desire inspection) telegraph name and address of one agent each to Government of India repeating to me? Please confirm that price is F.O.B. Karachi. NS. IR.511/26.7.45. i =GALL0WAY=@ &lt;*1 URdaHj . Ho. 3044 - 29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 27th July 1945, f To % The Adviser to the Bahrain (iovernment, Bahrain. A Reference your meriiOrandULi No* 1395-50 SF ? dated the 23rd July 1945. . 2. Do the Bahrain Government wish to appoint an agent to inspect the Joshi rice? If so please let me know the name and address of the agent as soon as possible when the Government of India will make arrangements for him to do so. 3 # It should be noted thai inspection would merely be for confirmation of condition and no haggling ever the price would be permitted. .jtf ms for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.Telegram From To No* 2 . rice is Coast* s whether G*T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Britagent, Sharjah. 566. Dated the 31st July 1946. Your tel. 813 July 24th. Only on condition that f quantity of Joshi set off against U.K.C.C. wheat quota can Trucial requirements be included. Please telegraph you accept this condition. POLITICAL(75 &gt; ? V 1 ^! ir Telegram. Inter 0. , /[8 From Political Resident 9 Bushire. To M.E.3.C. Cairo. Repeated S5.E.S.C. Baghdad. No. 1232. Dated 9th July 1945. Reference M.E.S.C. Cairo No.11 Saving June 11th. CEREALS. 2. Your paragraph 6. Trucial Coast. Please see paragraph 3 of my telegram No.974 May 23rd 3. Your paragraph 7. Muscat. Please see my telegram 1126 June 23rd to Baghdad (M.E.S.C. Baghdad please pass to Cairo). Rice has apparently not yet reached Muscat but I am enquiring position. 4. As reductions have already been given effect to in June shipments, request confirmation that adjustments will be made in July releases otherwise Muscat will be short. - GALLOWAY - ffO t CONFIDENTIAL^ Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, the 9th July 1945. Copy, with extract of paragraphs 3, 6 &amp; 7 of ifc.E.S.C. Cairo No. 11 Saving dated 11th June 1945, forwarded, with compliments, to:- The Political Agent, BffiMIN* v 0jH RHL. i apt -Extract from Saving Telegram dated 11th June 1945 from M.E.S.C. Cairo to M.W.T.London No.1599 repeated M.E.S.C. Baghdad No.252, Political Resident, Bashire No. 11 etc. ** ** ** ** 3. Forward commitments are estimated as follows Consumer See nara. June July August. Trucial Coast 6 180 820 820 Muscat 7 200 400 400 Kuwait • 600 600 600 Bahrain - 780 780 780 • • • • •• ** ** ** ** 6. Notes on Consumers. Trucial Coast . The Stock return from Dubai dated April 30th showed an increase of 726 wheat since March 31 although only 640 were delivered during April. It therefore appears either that Dubai is consuming less or that the territory is getting wheat or possibly rice from other sources. The P.R.P.G. has been requested to investigate, and in the meantime we propose to make no release to Dubai in June. 7. Muscat . We have been informed of the purchase by this territory of 325 Persian rice, part of which was shipped in May. We are releasing 200 wheat only in June, and when we receive full details of the delivery of rice we will make a final adjustment to the wheat quota.No. /yyyof 1364 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 23rd Shaaban 1364 August 2, 1945. H. B. LNs Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum;- Reference your memorandum No. 3044-29/21 dated 27th duly 1945. Messrs. Laichand Dhamanmal, Tikamdas Dhamanmal Building, 4th Floor, Bombay Bazaar, Karachi, will inspect the rice on behalf of the Bahrain Government. Adviser to the Government. Bahrain Receipt . Date.. a. ..z. k Telegram From To Repeated No. 2 . Dhamarimal POLITICAL 15 G.T.C. r. , J Political Agent, Bahrain. Government of India, New Delhi. Galloway, Ba&amp;h Shaikh, Shiraz. 574. Dated the 2nd August 1945. Political Resident’s telegram No. T/177 July 25th. / Joshi rice for Shaikhdoms. Bahrain agent Messrs Lalehand Dhamanmal, Tikamdas Building, 4th floor, Bombay Bazar, Karachi. ir : KMSTelegram From To No* 2 . condition G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Galloway, Bagh Shaikh, Shiraz. 581. Dated the 6th August 1945. IB V Your telegram No. T/199 July 30th. Trucial Coast does not require Joshi rice on referred to in your telegram above. POLITICALNo. 3324 - 29/21. To POLITICAL AGENCY| BAHRAIN. The 17th August 1945* MEMORANDUM The Adviser to the Bahra|n Government, Bahrain. Fiirther to my memorandum No. 2986 - 29/21, dated the 22nd July 1945, f of the quantity of Joshi rice if imported would be set off against Bahraini wheat quota. 2. Kindly confirm that this condition is acceptable. * for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. 979/143 Itl le legram From To No, Dated Q Political Resident at Shiraz. Government of India? New Delhi. T/200. 30th July, 1945. No \ Your Express Letter No. F.42(6)-MH»/45 June 18th. Persian rice has been reaching Shaikhdoms tnrough private channels and I have informed India Office that question of guarantee to Gray Mackenzie for proposed purchase from Persian Government need not be pursued. No rice has been purchased through Gray Mackenzie. 2. Estimate of rice required from Bengal Aush Crop will depend on decision regarding Joshi rice dealt with in your telegram No. 6427 July 20th and connected correspondence. 3, Can you give a rough estimate of cost per ton c.i.f. Persian Gulf posts ? p * GALLOWAY YG CONFIDENTIAL Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gqlf, Camp, Shiraz, w Dated the 30th July, 1945.[ \ f 1 Copies, with copies of letter under reference forwarded with compliments to 00 The Political Agent, Bahrain ^ The Political Agent, Kuwait . The Political Agent, muscat .?ro'f! To j-j GOVSHMISNT OF INDIA, xternal Affairs Department TP \r TD T3 T'P , “ 1 T rp rn rn TP T&gt; ijili X X iiiXl » Foreign, New Delhi, Britain, Bushire. No. F.42(6)-LE/45. Dated the 18th June, 1945. S'* Reference correspondence resting with Deeretary of State for Foroogn Affairs, London telegram to Ambassador, Tehran No. 976. dated 4th Nay, 1945, about rice from Persia for Gulf Ghaik’ doms. 2 . Please report whether there have been any further developments in this case, whether the question of indemnifying Lessrs*. Gray INackenzie has been settled, and whether any rice has yet actually been supplied. 3. There is- a very tentative possibility that India nay be able to spare a certain quantity of rice from the coming Bengal Aush crop. This ride would not be available until September, 1945 and might amount to a fair nized shipload, though any definite estimate of quantity at this stage is impossible. 4. Rail transport of the rice from Calcutta to a western Indian port e.g. Bombay or Karachi can be ruled out and it would have to be shipped from Calcutta. In order to arrange shipment frofti Calcutta it would be necessary to secure inclusion of this item in inis try of War Transport’s priority programme. There seems little prospect of arranging this unless the consignment were offered as replacement against some other proposed foodgrains shipment for the Gulf e.g, wheat. 5. The Government of India will be glad to have your comments and to know (a) how much rice you will be urgently in need of at that time, and (b) what would be the maximum amount', if available, that you would be prepared to take in replacement of other foodgrains. It should be emphasized that the whole question is *at present extremely nebulous and kiddle Bast Jupply Centre have not been consulted as yet. The issue of the above has been authorised. 3d/- 3.J.L. Giver Under Deeretary to the Government of India, YG® CCli. v '“N SAVINGRAM 28 copies ID 7 To ! M.W.T. LONDON Kept ' : M.E.O.C. BAGHDAD M.E.3.C. TEHRAN P.R.P.G. BUSHIRE From s M.E.S.C. CAIRO RICE FOR THE 3HEIKHDQMS ; No; 1830 Saving• 290 Saving 187 Saving 14 Saving D s 5th July, 1945, m Retreat .D,ta mM...; Reference our Savingram 1264 of the 9th May, repeated to . M.E.S.C. BAGHDAD as No. 192 Saving. M.E.S.C. TEHRAN as No. 125 „ P.R.P.G. BUSHIRE as No. 8 „ ]_ a The PRPG has now reconlinended that the question of a guarantee to Gray Mackenzie over the purchase of rice for the Sheikhdoms should be dropped, as Persian rice appears to be arriving in the Sheikhdoms through private trade. 2 # we, therefore, consider that the proposal may now be regarded as dead.. {V 3. For h.E.S.C.. Tehran, only . Reference your telegram 183 of the 30th June,Please apprise the Persian Government of the above decision with suitable expressions of regret that the deal has been found impracticable. YG Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, 'Camp, Shiraz, ^ Dated 9th August, 1945/ , f Copies forwarded with compliments to * The Political Agent, Kuwait . The Political Agent, Bahrain ^x^ The Political Agent, Muscat ** ♦reference Residency Printed Letter No. S-569, dated 28th May, 1945. \y&lt; ^ v * * CONFIDENTIAL No. C/156 .*. k Date. sTl . No. r v't/f 1364 Office or the -i-kiviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Ramadhan IB, 1364 August 20, 1943. H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memor andum: - This is to confirm that the mentioned in your memorandum No.3324-29/21 of 17th August 1945, is acceptable. Adviser to the GovernmeitNo. 1364 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Ram din n 20, 1364 August 28, 1945. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain Receipt Memorandum: - With reference to your memorandum No. 3324-29/23f* dated 17th August 1945 and my memorandum No. 1549 - 503B dated 20th August 1945. We have now received samples of the rice in question and I am sorry to have to inform you that after it was examined by His Highness Shaikh Sulman and various local merchants it was found that it would not be suitable for food. Under the circumstances the Bahrain Government is not willing to purchase this rice. Adviser to the Government. S r? « Wf « -q, -v?Telegram From To No. tt.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. 636. Dated the 29th August 1946 / it * My tel. 639 July 24th. Hoshi rice. Bahrain Government reports after examination the rice is unsuitable for consumption and is therefore not repeat not willing to purchase. 3. Please inform Political Agent, Bahrain. POLITICALTelegram, Code. From, Government of India, New De^hi. No, 797 Dated 12th and received 13th September 1945, To. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. Correspondence eresting with Bahrain telegram No. 574 dated August 2nd. Rice for Shaikhdoms. Reg^et quantity damaged JOSIII rice available for export from Sind now reported to be negligible. While Food Department are maxing further enquiries in the matter and exact position will be intimated later. i hey wish warning be conveyed that offer may not materialise. Owing to deficiency of rice ther^e is no possibility of any ABS rice available from Bengal. \ £«. /; ! FOREIGN LR. I.R. No. 601 Bahrain Receipt /£ • 7*No. 3753 - 29/21. POLITICAL AGENCY| BAHRAIN. The 15th September 1945 To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. MEMORAL'Diri/i I am inforrued that owing to the shortage of rice there is no possibility of any ABS rice being made available Bengal. for POLITICAL AGANI, BAHRAIN.® ’ Telegram. Code. From. Political Resident, at Shiraz. To. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/504 (Circular) Dated the 22nd and received 23rd September 1945. IMPORTANT Following is repetition of Government of India telegram No. 8210 September t8th. Begins Foreign telegram No. 7973' dated September 12th. Rice for Shaikhdoras. 2. Sind Government have about 1000 tons of damaged Red rice which can be made available for Gulf Shaikhdoras in part fulfilment of order of damaged JOSHI rice. Sample of Red rice offered show that it contains high per cent weevilled and broken grain. If however offer is accepitable quantity may be allotted among agents of Shaikhdoms who may be instructed to contact Sind Government for price procurement, et cetera. Ends. 2. Please telegraph if State would be willing to accept any of this rice and if so quantity. ©ALLOWAY LR. I.R. No. 616. Bahrain DateURGENT 29/21, POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN# The 23rd September 1945 No. 3932 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No. 1596 - 50 SF, dated the 28th August 1945. 2 . I have been informed that about 1000 tons of damaged red rice can be made available from Sind for export to Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms. It contains a high percentage of weevilled and broken grains. If it is acceptable a quantity will be allotted to your agent who may be instructed to contact the Sind Government for price procurement etc. 3* Please inform me what quantity, if any, can be accepted by you,^a) if and^?) if not debitable to Bahrain’s food quota. 0 i for POLITICAL AGfiNT, BAHRAIN. KMSTelegram From To No. (3) 1 Cr. T. . Political Agent, Bahiain. Residency Agent, Sharjah. 691. Dated .the 23rd September 1945, ..A Your tele 846 August 4th. 2. Sind Government have about 1000 tons of damaged exes red rice available for export to Gulf Sheikhdoms. It contains high per cent weevilled and broken grain. 3. Please telegraph whether it is acceptable (a) if debitable against food quota and (b) if not. luvxS POLITICALTelegram From To No. Dated and 2 . in any case AMO . Bahrain Mo . V / ^ n. G.T.C. Residency Agent, Sharjah. Political Agent, Bahrain. 979 received 25th September, 1945. Your telegram 691 September 23rd. This rice is not required repeat is not required -BRITAGENT^ Receipt ....?.r.: .45mmm No. fffX 1364 Office of tfie Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 17th Shawal, 1364 September 24, 1945. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain Receipt No_ ate. Reference your memorandum No .3932-29/21 dated 23rd September 1945. Memorandum The Bahrain Government is not interested in the purchase of damaged red rice. Ag. Adviser to the Government. S.Z.29/21 Telegram. From. To. Code. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. No. 521 Dated the 25th September 1945. Your Circular telegram No, T/504 dated September 22nd. Rice for Shaikhdoms. 2 . Bahrain Government not interested in purchase of damaged red rice from Sin§. 3 Trucial Coast also do not require this rice. POLITICAL LR79/143 \ Telegrara From Political Resident at Shiraz. To Government of India, New Delhi Mo. T/562. Dated 20th September, 1945. Paragraph 2 of your telegrac; Mo. / 797 September 12th. Joshi Rice. 2. Shalkhdoins are not repeat not willing to purchase as according to their agents 1 reports the rice is unfit for consumption. - GALLOWAY - GO FIDh VPIAL Ho. CA3G . Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz. Dated 20th September, If No- Bahrain Receipt Copy forwarded with compliments to * The Political Agent, Kuwait . ** The Political Agent, Bahrain .' *** The Political Agent, Muscat . with reference tos- ♦ Kuwait telegram No. 823 August 31st, 1945. ** Bahrain telegram Mo. 636 August 29th, 1945. *** Musca t telegram iMo. C/1241 September 15th, 1945. ARG •Telegram From To No* 0 ; * G.T,C. Political, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 719. Dated the 3rd October 1945. s' Bahrain Government has imported 240 half 480 tons of rice in September and I will recommend reduction in cereal quota on receipt of further 260 half 520 tons expected in near future. ! O POLITICAL KMSHo. 4172 - 29/21 POLITICAL AGENCY, ^ BAHRAIN. The 3rd October 1945 To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your letter No. PA/SF/15, dated the 1st October 1945 ) and your conversation with the Assistant Political Agent this morning. 2. I note that the Bahrain Government has imported 240 tons of rice (presumably from Persia) during September 1945 and that you expect a further 260 tons to be imported during October 1945. Kindly confirm that the Bahrain Government is prepared to accept a reduction of the cereal quoca in the usual proportions against the 500 tons oi rice when all received and, also, please note that imports of rice should be reported at once giving country of origin and price vide paragraph 3 of my memorandum No. 2377 - 29/21, dated the 10th June 1945, to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. C for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAINV No.PA/C/.-?.'?; THE CUSTOMHOUSES BAHRAIN: 6 th October, 194-5•&gt; Political Agent, Bahrain a miOKANDUM ;&gt;- N ' ^ Hef.your No.2064-29/21 of 19th May, 1945. I have to advise that on the 2nd inst, Hajy Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported 300 bags of Persian rice for the Bahrain Government. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN.No. PA/C/&amp;? THE CUSTOMHOUSE s BAHRAIN i ... 8th October, 1945., H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM 8- Ref.your No.2064-29/21 of 19th May, 1945. has advi se that to-day, Hajy Yohsuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported 400 bags of Persian rice for the Bahrain Government. The price is Rs95/- per bag of 210 lbs, C.I.F., Bahrain. Rtkriia Receipt to- /O'... 1 ! 5 ” DIRECTOR OF CUEOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN,THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 9th October, 1945*, ^ I ^o.PA/C/ Political Agent, Bahrain, MEMORANDUM:~ Reference yonr No,4172-29/21 of the 3rd inst. I confirm that the Bahrain Government is prepared to accept a reduction of the cereal quota in the usual proportions against the 500 tons of rice when all received# I shall advise you when full quantity arrives. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. ftakra in Rac*,’j»tNo.PA/C/^/ H.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain, ME MORANDU M:» THE CUSTOM OUSE: BAHRAIN: 9th October, 1945,, .. 0 .. . With further reference to my memorandum No.PA/C/35 of hen ln f t i Ha v y Yousu:f ’ Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported a further 650 bags of Persian rice for the Bahrain Government. lustier The price is Rs95/- per bag of 210 lbs, C.X.F., Bahrain. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER Bahrain Receipt No^.^Z^...Data /0 '!C c ' Telegram From To No. ■ 1 G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 741. Dated the 13th October 1945. My tel. 719 of October 3rd. Rice. 2. Hajji Yusuf Fakhroo has imported during last 10 days for Bahrain Government 126 tons of Persian rice in 3 consignments at the rate of Rupees 1013 per ton C.I.F. Bahrain. POLITICAL KMSTelegram From To No, G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 749 . Dated the 15th October 1945. My tel. 741 October 13th. Rice. 2 . Same importer has imported a further 9 tons Hasti at Ks. 1280 per ton and 85 tons Garden at Rs. 1013 per ton C.I.F. Bah--ain. 3&gt; Rice in my telegram referred to above was Gardeh. POLITICAL KMS1 GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER B—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by jwst to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,} From Political, Bahrain. To. Political Resident, Camp Bahrain. No t 4488 - 29/21. Bahrain, Gated the 28th October . In continuation of ray telegram No. 749 of October 15th, 1945. Rice. 2. Haj j i Yousuf Abdulrehman Fakhroo has imported a further 70 tons of Persian Gerdeh rice at Es. 1,013/- per ton C.I.F. Bahrain. 3. Bahrain Government can, therefore, accept a monthly reduction in their quota of 110 tons of wheat for each November, December 1945 and January 1946. (My telegram No. 719 of 3rd October 1945 refers). = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. ^ M' © ^ Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KMS S. 6. MFP—1196 S&amp;P-(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.No. 4511 - 29/21 POLITICAL AGNNCY, BAHRAIN. The 29th October 1945. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. M^viOKANDUM y Reference your memorandum No. PA/ 0/485 dated the 27th October 1945. 2 . I have recommended to the Hon’ble the Political Resident that 110 tons of wheat be reduced monthly from Bahrain’s quota for each Novemberj Decomber 1945 and January 1946, against 500 tons of rice imported and taken over by Bahrain Government. 3. Please inform me when the Bahrain Govern ment is prepared to accept any further reduction in the cereal, quota; I suggest when a further 500 tons of rice has been imported beginning with the consignments mentioned in your memorandum under reference and your memorandum No. PA/C/47, dated the 25th October 1945. \ * for POLITICAL AGiiNT, BAHRAIN. Copy to $ - The Adviser to the Bahrain Government* Bahrain. KMSGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, DEPABTUeNT, EXPRESS LETTER [2^, B ,—This is cm ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as {f it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political, Bahrain. To. Political Resident, Bushire. No, 4571 • 29/21# Bahrain, Dated the 1st November 7A£ . xP''“ ' My Express Letter 4488 - 29/21 of October 28th. Rice. 2. Same importer has imported for Bahrain Government ^ further 180 tons of Gerdeh rice from Persia at the same rate. 3. I will recommend reduction of cereal quota in due course. « POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Politidal Agent, Bahrain. KMS S. 6. MFP—1190 S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/778</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/778</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 29/21 vol ii FOOD SUPPLIES RICE’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-27T21:17:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (322 folios)</extent><extent>Files papers are arranged more or less chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present between ff 2-200; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.Pagination: the index section (ff 286-323) has been paginated using pencil; these numbers are located in the top outermost corners of each page.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence, mainly telegrams, about British efforts to obtain supplies of rice for local consumption in the Persian Gulf shaikhdoms, particularly Bahrain, Dubai and the other Trucial Coast shaikhdoms, also Qatar, at the end of the Second World War (1939-1945). Rice and wheat continued to be in acute short supply in India and the Persian Gulf countries and subject to Government of India quota arrangements and other export and import controls. British and Bahrain Government officials discuss mainly the public procurement of rice supplies from Persia (Iran), India, Egypt and elsewhere. They also discuss extensively the implementation of regular reductions to Government of India monthly wheat and barley quota imports for Bahrain and the Trucial Coast, equivalent to the total quantity of their rice imports, including private importations made by merchants and others, such as the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO), as food rations for its employees.The main correspondents are the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Political Officer for the Trucial Coast and the Residency Agent, both Sharjah; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain and the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain; the officials and representatives of the Middle East Supply Centre (later the British Supply Mission, Middle East) in Baghdad, Cairo and Tehran. A large proportion of their correspondence consists of regular reports to each other about the quantity and price of rice and wheat imports, existing stock levels, new shipments and the names of the exporters and importers involved. This information is discussed in relation to planning future cereal requirements and the purchase of new supplies, as well as for regulating the landing, onward distribution and pricing of these rationed food commodities at Bahrain and also the Trucial Coast ports of Dubai and Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Middle East Supply Centre</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Supply Mission (Middle East)</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Food resources</topic></subject><subject><topic>Wheat</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food statistics</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rice</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000c5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>