<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023876399.0x000012_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:32:13.884Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">TABLE OF THE QASIMI FAMILY FORMERLY RULING LINGEH. Chronological list of the successive Shaikhs of Lingeh he- longing io this-family. Khalifah, 1861—74. •Ali, 1874-78, Ynsuf, 1878-85, (see note 3.') Qadhib, 1885-87. (Various Persian Goyenrors, 1SS8- 87.) Muhammad, 1898—99. Notes.—(1) This family is closely related to the rnling QSsimi family of Sharjah : 'Gad'eef' (probably 'Qadhib,' but no't certainly identifiable with the first person in this table) was Shaikh of Lingeh in 1805, and was then said to be ' uncle ' to Shaikh Sultan-bin-^aqar of Sharjah. (2) One Muhammad-bin-Qadhib, perhaps a son of the above Qadhib, was Shaikh of Lin^eh m 1829, and mediated in that year between the Shaikhs of Sharjah and Abu Dbabi. (3) The table is probably incomplete. It was complied in 1907 frnm a statement by Muhammad-bin-Khalifah, ex- Shaikh of Lingeh. It should properly include Shaikh Yusuf who ruled Lingeh from 1878 to 1885 in which latter year he was murdered by his relatiye Shaikh Q idhlb', (vide ( age 2064 of Part II of the Persian Galf Gazetteer.) Qadhib, (Dead.) I 1 jJL, ^ &amp; i 1 aaj IL Rashid. /ov Khalifah. (Deail.) (Shaikh of Lmgeh in 1851, though then a minor j died} Octo ber 1874.) Mubammad. (Dead.) 1 Qadhib (Shaikh of Lingeh from 1885 to 1887 in which year he was taken prisoner by the Persians and de ported by them to Tehran, ' where he died.) r J- 'AIL (Shaikh ot Lingeh 1874 to 1878 in Nov ember of which year he was murdered,) Mubammad. (Seized Lingeh in 1398 and returned it till 1899 when he was expelled by the Persians; now a wanderer, sometimes in Qatar and sometimes oo the Trocial Coast.) &lt;uuIA Khalifah. (Dead.)</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023876399.0x000012_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/C91/3, f 9</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023876399.0x000012</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/C91/3, f 9</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Pocket No. 7: Enclosure to Part III of Volume I of the Persian Gulf Gazetteer: Genealogical Table of the Qasimi Family Formerly Ruling Lingeh'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-11-04T02:01:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 folio</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This item is a genealogical 'Table of the Qasimi Family Formerly Ruling Lingeh'. It contains 10 named individuals (in Arabic and English) of the Qāsimī family of Lingeh, some with birth and death dates, as well as brief biographical information.There is also a 'Chronological list of Shaikhs of Lingeh belonging to this family' with the periods of their reign, including: Khalīfah, ’Ali [‘Alī], Yusuf [Yūsuf], Qadhīb [Qaẓīb], various Persian Deputy-Governors, and Muhammad.In addition, a section of 'Notes' is given that provides information concerning their relation with the Āl Qāsimī ruling family of Sharjah; mediation between the Shaikhs of Sharjah and Abu Dhabi by Shaikh Muhammad-bin-Qadhīb [Muḥammad bin Qaẓīb]; the completeness of the table and its compilation in 1907 from a statement by Muhammad-bin-Khalīfah [Muḥammad bin Khalīfah], the former Shaikh of Lingah. A reference to the
                           Gazetteer(p. 2064 of Part II) is also given concerning the murder of Yūsuf, the Shaikh of Lingah, in 1885.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023876399.0x000012#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>