<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000292_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:54:22.075Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No 143-2/11 Dated the 10th January 1935 My dear Worth, Just a line to acknowledge with many thanks the donation of Rs*30/-, which you handed to Doctor Holmes for the Hospital* It v/as very kind of you to think of giv ing the Hospital this help in its work. &amp;U /orth, Hlsquire, I.C*S. f Assistant political Agent, Bahrain*No S44-2/11. Dated the 10th January 1935* Dear de Grenier, Just a line to acknowledge with many thanks the donation of fo.25/-, which you handed to Doctor Holmes for the Hospital* It was very kind of you to think of giving the Hospital this help in its work* / 4 ^ C*C*L* de Grenier t Esquire, Director of Customs and Port officer, Bahrain.Received from the Medical Officer in Charge Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain, the sum of RupeesC 800/-) Eight hundred only being the amount received from the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain towards the Victoria. Memorial Hospital, Bahrain, for the period from 1st July 1934 to 31st October 1935, @R S ,50/- per mensem* The 23rd October 1935 Ba lira in Bahraino Political Agent. Ref: my letter lTo:16 of 1935,P 8th: August 1935. The di spensayy is still without a fan. May I get a table fan from the State Engineer please? M.O. A»x »A» Last year M.O.askea for two fans. Only one was purchased and fixed in his messing rooii. The State Engineer stated that a table fan would rn«; fu-mroxiaatelv Rs.65/-. May the anount be sanctisnenPolitical Agency, No- 2829-2/6 ,f( Bahrain the 12th November 1936 To Dr.C.E. Hynes Victoria Memorial Hospital Bahrain# Dear Sir, I have received with mny thanks the sum of Ks.il/- being a percentage on t he collections as a donation towards the Victoria Memorial Hospital - in the Cable and Wireless Sweepstake on the Cambridge shire run. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain TD.O. No. 281-2/11 The 6th February 1937 Just a line to acknowledge with many thanks the donation of Rs.30/- which you handed to Doctor Holmes for the Hospital. It was very kind of you to think of giving the Hosoifal this heIn in its work. C.C.L. de Grenier, Esquire, Director of Customs and Port Officer.k q f “ W Bahrain, 9th: February 1937, The Asst-Politic&amp;l Agent, Bahrain. Memo • Under a recent Bahrain Government o^der motor drivers are no- charged three rupees for the eye test given them- Twenty-five drivers were examined this morning,and I forward y the sum of seventy-five rupees,received from them,for credit to the funds of the Victoria Memorial Hospital, fU^ a \ n.o.i/c. h C. F 'i '? II 7/ \JE* Herewith the sum of rupees seventy. to he credited to the Hospital funds•This amount has been collected from drivers undergoing eye test, this week. M.O.i/c.To. T-'i^ Asst: Political Agent, Bahrain. Forwarded the sum of rupees fifteen only,for credit to the funds of this hospital. Tiis money was paid by motor drivers who had their eyes tested on ?3rd: February 1957. —Bahrain, 2nd: fffHsruary 1937. To. Thp Assist*Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo • / Borwarded the sum of Rupees sixty,only,for credit to the funds of this hospital. The money has been paid by motor drivers up to have their eyes tested this morning M. 0. -/ n No: 5 E.E. \ V y Bahrain, 9th: Mar ch 1937. The Asst: Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo. I forward tho sum of rupees thirty,for credit to the funds of this hospital. Tis amount has Been recovered from motor drivers whose eyes were tested this morning# .O.i/c $11Political Agency, Bahrain, 'arch 15, 1957. P li G E I P T . Received from Or. R. Holme a the earn of Rupees (245-0-0) iwo hundred and forty five only being the part of the receipts for the Bapco Club Xmas Draw. Note. Rs. 2/- were bad coins A Rs. 243/- credited to H.C.P.■MMMK J T o;6 ?:.F. Bahrain, 16th: March 1937. To. The Asst: Political Agent, Tahrain. Memo. I forward the sum rupees forty,for credit to the funds of this hodpital. Eye teste. RslS/- Hospital fees obtained from Mespers for an Indian treated 72/- for twenty-two days. Total Ks40/ -Bahrain, 26th: April 1937 To* The A.?* A. Bahrain* Memo. I forward the following amounts,'being half fees for the eye tests carried out on to Va credited to the funds of this hospital.V ' No: IQ,118c12 E.E, Bahrain, 18th: jlay 1937, To. The Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. Memo. I forward the following amounts being half fees for the eye tests carried out on 4.5.37 11.5.37. 18.5.37. KslO/8. SslO/8. Js4/8.. Total. EsSS/S. to he credited to the funds of thid hospital M.O.i/® V.M.Hospital. P\S13&amp;14 Bahrain, 1st: June 1937# To. The Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. Memo. I forward the following amounts Being half fees for the eye tests carried out on 25th: May 1937. 1st: June 1937. Ss 19/8/- Ks 15/-/- to te credited to the funds of this hospital please. c O-'- ***' ■ ^ \(L M.O.l/c V.M.Hospital, Bahrain.COPIED all letters to be addressed to THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS EASTERTIDE. ✓ i ‘ The Medical Officer, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. Dear Sir, H.O.B.C.13792 ; Sight Bill Drawn on you by Down Brothers, Ltd., London, for £126.4.6d. Clean. We have once again to draw your attention to the above mentioned unpaid bill. As the bill has been remaining unpaid with us for the past several months, we shallbe pleased to know when we may expect to receive a remittance from you in payment. K j ManagerWbe Ccistmt pank.Wtmit^, A l-&gt;- LBTiteHS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. (incorporated in England.) / l «. L.B.G « A PH 1C A DDR B / EASTERTIDE. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS / 19 thMay, The Political /igent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, H.O.B.G*13792 on The Medical Officer, Bahrain, for &amp;126.4.6d. We have to acknov/ledge receipt of your letter No. 1193-2/9 of date, authorising us to debit the Bahrain Agency Un-Official Fund Account with the equivalent in rupees of £126.4.6d. in payment of the above bill, but we would point out that the bill is payable with interest at plus all charges. We enclose herewith a memo, good for payment upto 22nd May, 1937, shewing the amount in rupees due to us, ifchich includes in terest from the 21st of December, the date of the draft, to the date of the approximate arrival of the remittance in London, as well as our Head Office charges @ plus Westminster Bank Commission of 3/2d. We shall be glad if you will let us have your authority to debit the whole of this amount to the Bahrain Agency Un-Official Fund Account. l Manager.No. 1193-8/9. Political Agency, Bahrain, May 19, 1957. cJf- To The Eastern Bonk limited, BAHRAIN. Gent le'Tien, With reference to your letter dated the 9th &lt;ny 1957 to the address of the edical Officer, Victoria 'emorial Hospital, Bahrain, I authorize you to debit the equivalent in rupees of £. 126/4/6 (One hundred and twenty six pounds four shillings and six pence) to the Bahrain Agency Un-Official Fund Account with you. yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain. A U;. -j-trvvcA . Aj.•40 Ho; 15&amp; 16 E.H, Bahrain, l©th;June 1937. To. The assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo; I forward the following amounts,being the half fees for eye tests carried out on 8th; June 1937. 15th; June 1937. Ks 19/8/- Es 25/8/- 1(^0 • 'ti to be credited to the funds of this hospital please. W^C' A fes&amp;asaBahrai 29th: Jane 1937. To. Tile Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo • I forward the following amounts being the half fees for eye tests carried out on 22nd: June.37. Is 28/8/- 29th: June 37. F.s 22/8/- Total. Fs 51/-/- Bahrain. A No: 19 &amp; 20 E.S. ?i Sahrain. 13th: July 1937. To. The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo. I forward the following amounts for eye tests carried out on 6th: July 19.37. 13th: July 1937. Total IIBahrain* I forward the sum of seven Hundred rupees,being the amount received from the Bahraih Betroleum Go: for payment to the ¥# Victoria Memorial Hospim funds,for the period 1st: August'36 to 30th: September 1937, t/txxjh* M. 0. l/C V.M.Hospftal 9RJCEIPT JL Received from the Medical Officer, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Pahrain, the sura of Rupees (700-0-0) Seven hundred only being the amount received from The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, towards the Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain, for the period from 1st August 1956 to the 30th September 19 37 @ Rs. 50/- per mensem. Political Agent, Bahrain Bahrain October 27, 1937 i36 A No: . E.E. Bahiain, 21st: Lecem'ber 1937, \: To. Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo. I forward the following amounts being the haff fees for eye tests carried out on:-The Bahrein Masonic Club has great pleasure in sending you herewith the sum of Fifty Rupees, Being their contribution to the charitable work carried on at The Victoria Memorial Hospital, Manamah; and at the same time desire to express their admiration and sympathy for the good work done for the poor by the Medical Officer, and their best wishes for its continued success. Yours faithfully,7 / “ 2/11 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th January 1939 u Jl To The Honorary Secretary, The Bahrain Masonic Club, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I acknowledge with many thanks the cheque for &amp;« 50/- sent with your letter dated the 22nd December 1938 for the Victoria Memorial Hospital, and the kind expression of appreciation of the work of the Quarantine Medical Officer contained in your letter. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain., \° V ^ D. 0. No. 451 -10. C 0 F Y « «? Orovermient ol Batira m. v: Hi iJe a r Vv e i ghtma n, loi* many yeara we have been paying Re.2 00/- per month to the Political A£ ent on account ol druga need in die * ictoria Memorial Hoapital. As you know the Agency Medical Oiticer in the paat attended the State Police and all Bahrain Government atari who were entitled to tree medical attention and ado aupplieu druga etc. to them tree ol charge. V, e now have our own medical stall who are responsible lor the medical work ol the Bahrain Government and we are purchasing year ly large supplies ol druga etc. the Police and all persons who receive tree medical attention from the State, are dealt with by the Bahrain Government Medical Oil ice r, the small dispensary at Naim is being used as a temporary hospital. I believe the allowance ol Rs .200/- per month was intended to cover the cost ol drugs supplied to Police and Bahrain Government and as this expense is now born by the Bahrain Government I think it reasonable to suggest that payment should be discontinue d. Yours sincerely, Sd. C. halrymple Bel grave. H. Y/eightman, Bs q., I. C. S. , H.B.M’s Political Agent, Eahra in.Bear Sir Trenchard, /s things take so long to settle, I think it would be as well if we began to consider now what should be the future of the Victoria Manorial Hospital at Bahrain. 2. As you are aware, the Bahrain Government are engaged in building a lar-e hospital of their own, with wards for both male and female in-patients, and they already employ both an IBnglish Medical Officer and a Scotch lady doctor. a It will probably be the best part of the year before all their aospital arrangements are in full vvorkii^j order and meanwhile our own Agency hospital continues to perform a very valuable function. As the result of )r. Holmes* personal popularity and his long residence here the daily attendance at our hospital is still very high, even though the State Medical Officer is already running a small temporary dispensary near the Fort. Dr. Holmes however is due to finish his time in August 1940 and he informs me that he will be asking for leave from about the middle of June 1940. Whoever may be sent as nis relief will not hrve the same personal attraction foi* sickly Bahrainis, and I should anticipate that attendances will fall rapidly. Thus, in a little more than a year from now, we can contemplate that there will be no real need, from the point of view of public service, to keep the Victoria Memorial Hospital open. The alternatives than would be either (i) to close down entirely and to come to some arrangement with the Bahrain Government by which they will, possibly in return/- The Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire.return for a monthly contribution, undertake the medical care of the Agency personnel, or (ii) to retain the hospital under an Assistant Surgeon solely for Agency purposes. The question is of course affected to some extent by the possible transfer of the Residency to Bahrain since I am not quite sure what is to happen about the Residency Surgeon end his staff if and when that does occur* Of course you may consider the contingency so remote as to have little or no bearing on the present question, and in that event my personal preference would be to close down the Victoria Memorial Hospital entirely and to abolish the post of Agency Surgeon* There can be little doubt that the State could and would look after the Political Agent and his staff for a reasonably small contributory fee, and there is no real reason why they should not manage the Quarantine work also* 3. If this view is approved* I would definitely suggest the beginning of .Tune 1940 as the time for the closure of our medical commitments in Bahrain* Yours sincerely,3rd May, 1939. \^\M D.O. Ko.5'8’'] Please refe your demi-official letter lJo.678- 4/24, dated the 25th April, 1939, to Sir Trenchard on the subject of the future of the Victoria Memorial Hospital at Bahrain. 2. Sir Trenchard desires me to say that the question u is one which should ts more properly decided by his sue- A cessor. I am accordingly keeping the question pending and will let you 'have a reply in due course. H.^We ightman , Esq., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. , S/5i-rKtn—-'—. -^»—m HPKE - cc^JI THE BAHRAIN GOVERNMENT ELECTRIC SUPPLY DEPT. NO. GEL/7/58 BAHRAIN. 23rd March,1939 2nd Saffar,1358 0 The Medical Officer,in-Charge, Victoria Memorial Hosoital BAHRAIN. nospitai, Memorandum:- for fans - Victoria Memorial Hospital With reference to your order of 14th August, 1938, signed by Dr. I.Davenport Jones and the Political Agent, for five ceiling fans 56', and nine 16' table fans. The balance of the order, i.e. 9-16” table fans are being sent to you. Will you please indicate to our mistry the position in which you wish the 2 - 56' ceiling fans (now temporarily fixed) placed,and the 9 - 16' table fans. As you know, three of the 56' fans are already permanently installed. Jo~X i i *'**1 GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN BILL NO, SS/40/58 Dr. To BAHRAIN, DATED The Medical Officer-in-Charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. 14th R/Awal, 1358 4th May,1939 THE BAHRAIN. GOVT. ELECTRIC SUPPLY Dept. To: Supplying seven G.E.C.Osc.table fans I6 M complete with the necessary lengths of flexible wire and plugs, for the Hospital (Rupees' five hundred and four,only). fi State Engineer, Government of Bahrajin IM / Rs. 504*- 0- 02 / 11 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21at May 1939. To The State Engineer to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. . i i • Memorandum . A ' Reference your memorandum No. GL/7/58 dated the 23rd March 1939 to the Medical Officer—in—Charge*Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. 2. Will you please send in the order dated the 14th August 1938 as the Political Agent has no recollection of the matter? Assistant Political Agent,Bahrainc* COPY. % Bahrain. Dated:-I4th August,1938 The State Engineer, The Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Memorandum: - Please supply:- (1) 5 - 56” ceiling fans (2) 9 - 16” table fans Also please carry out the necessary wiring for fourteen fan points s/d. Ivan Davenport Jones Government Medical Officer Victoria Memorial Hospital Countersigned J. B. Howe s Offg. P.A. \Telepk one : 43M IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD. BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF Tel egrams : Airway rs, Baki 20tJa November, 1939* Would you be so good as to advise me whetner Dr. Holmes Is In a position to examine sample stools fully for traces of enteric fever. ? t Yours faithfully, Dor IMPERIAL AIRWAYS Lm, STATION SUPERINTENDENT. J SW: ARM16 * 2/11 The 4tli January 1940* Will you please refer to my demi-official letter r o* 678 dated the 26th April 1939 to air Trenchard Fowle, and to Rushton*s letter No. 687 dated the 3rd May 1939 on the subject of the future of the Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain? 2* X think it is new time that a decision were taken on this matter. I am more than ever convinced that we should, close down the Victoria memorial Hospital when Holmes goes, since by that time the Bahrain Government Hospital should be in full working order and there will be no justification for providing medical aid in Bahrain at the expense of the Indian treasury. Incidentally Holland has just been here and it has been arranged that he should corae to Bahrain as State Medical uffleer for six months on probation in April. I am fairly sure that the six months will be extended to cover the whole of the war and possibly a few months after. 3. If we close down the Victoria Memorial Hospital I think we should pay a contribution of say Hs* 200/- per mensem to the Bahrain Government for medical attendance on the Agency staff. 4# As for the quarantine work which Holmes now does that can easily be managed by the State’s Medical Department. Yours sincerely, * Hiik 0 ' 4 ' Vy l{. t oc - The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel C.G. Prior* CIE., Political Resident /D.O. No. /tt- -19/94. imu^u cau^Ciiiivii ra-iceu... l s&amp;Ui: iiV Li ^ i S3 Dated the 18th January 1940. i/-' 2S t v X/ f r jy ^ nr / «vouid you Kindly refer to your demi-official letter No.15-2/11 of the 4th January adareseed to Colonel Prior. 2 ' He desires me to say that the proposal to close down the Victoria Memorial Hospital does not commend itself to him. He considers that the large Indian community in Bahrain would prefer to use this hospital, and, situated where it is, it would still be attended by people at that end of the t own, j.t i- uruikely that Holmes will be relieved while the war continuea and he will certainly be given no leave before hie retirement. All leave, except casual leave and leave on medical certificate, has been stopped. H. //eightman Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. /* s .» .m t m ■*;. .BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION. BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF 'M I Telephone : 43M Teleg rams : Plying Bali ram Codes : Bentley’s &amp; I.A.T.A. BA3/1 /1475/s* 8 H.B.M* The Political Agent. BAHREIN ' 13th October, 1940. Dear Sir, ACCOMMODATION AT SHARJAH QUARANTINE MEDICAL OFFICER in £ 1 ^ instructed by our Principals in Baghdad that, i ?^ r ^ anc *v Wi th your re&lt; l ues t, we are prepared to cancel our in/oice for the accommodation at our Rest House in Shariah for ??? iP ders &lt;;and that the Station Superintendent wl i&gt; e forwarding a credit note for this purpose. g J atef Y 1 » therefore, if you would cancel the attached hill from Dr. Holmes. We should like to place on record, however, that the total number of the Corporation’s staff vaccinated by Dr. Holme® was nine, and that the remaining 141 shown on the invoice were largely Government of India Meteorological staff and their dependant®, and that a certain number were nothing whatever t© do with the Rest House or Government, but were allowed to come uo the Rest House for vaccination purely for Dr.Holmes’ convenience. ^ .hu-uhck3To«1955 Poll tj cr?3 Agenay, Bahrain. 16th October* 1940 To The British Ovarseae A ir t mye Corporation, Bahrain . * Dear Sira, Pleaco refer to ycur letter 'K&gt; .RAH/i/1475/S• 3 dated the 13th October 19^0. '3. The bill for £.15/- from Dr. B* Holmes, Quarantine Tbfinal officer for vaccination*at Sharjah is hereby cancelled. Y oar a fa Ithf»illy, for Political Agent, l^ahrain.GOVERNI'lENT 0? BAHRAIN. STATK ElTGINSEIi'S T )SPAHTP.TSNT. No. D.O. Bahrain. \ 25th January, 1941. HI 27th Dilhaj, 1359. Dear Doctor, \U I send hereunder particulars of the fans supplied to the Victoria Memorial Hospital in 1358:- Seven G.H.C.Oxs. Table Fans 16 a issued during the month of Jamada Thani, 1358.(July - August, 1939). Billing amount its.504/-. Yours sincerely, Sd/Illegible. Dr. Ralph Holmes, M.B.E., Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. To The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. The State Engineer wishes to know whether the bill for these fans has been paid. The record in his office appears to have been lost in a fire that occurred early in 1940. Bahrain. Sd/- R.Holmes. 29th January,1941. Q.M.O. No payment for the fans supplied to you during July-August, 1939 has been made by this office. 18th February, 1941 Sd/-G.N. Jackson. Asstt. Political Agent, BahrainV&gt;—'~ ^JW&gt;. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE-GENERAL, BUSHIRE. £ y . O, . a 5 BEMORAJ No The attached As forwarded for information and necessary action. Major Residency Sxirgeon, Bushire,l o. / Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 16th September,1948. To The Bahrain etroleum Co.Ltd. Awaii Dear Sirs Please refer to your letter No.PA-396 dated the 28th August, 1948 8 . From the entry made in our register it appears that tne payment of ILs. 1-10 on account of petroleum supplied for the V.M.Hospital during ^arch 1948 was made to you on 1st feay 1948. It is therefore possible that the amount in questic , fas received and credited by you in vour accounl booK sometime in May 1948. Yours faithfully, Politica gent,Bahrain,THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian r.m f PAt396 2Bth August 194B. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, The Political Agency, MANAMA, OUTSTANDING ACCOUNTS File:089*1 A7o* VICTORIA MEMORIAL HOSPITAL W Dear Sir, According to our books billing L-3-84 of 31st March 1948 for Rs:1-10-0 covering supply of Petroleum Products during March 1948, has remained outstanding for a considerable period against the account of Victoria Memorial Hospital. With the above exception we find that all payments up to end of July I 948 in respect of this account have been received and therefore presume that the invoice in question has escaped your at tention. A copy of this debit is attached and we would appreciate receiving settlement at your early convenience. Yours very truly, For R.M. BRO®/ CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attach: far (L , . pi/w ui. ttr*_ (iJZc ' (ClT (LjuX ' fi t ■ 7 V/ ,^ f*0 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A v a 1 i. Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. PA-^94 The Agency, BAHREIN* File No 5089*1 Dear Sir, &lt;7 S '1 In reply to your letter No:46551 dated the 16th September, 1948, we would advise that we have no trace of having received a payment of Rs:l/l0/- on 1st May, 1948, for account of the Victoria Memorial Hospital* However, we shall be pleased to make further investigations if you can furnish us with a reference of your cheque number and date* According to our records, the only payment we received from you during the month of May is for an amount of Rs:3/4/- per your cheque No 5336215 dated 13th Nay, 1948, forwarded under cover of your letter No 51549 Accts* of 16th l&amp;y, 1948. This payment was in settlement of our invoices L-3-83 and L-4-106 for Rs :l/l0/- and Rs:l/10/- respectively covering cost of petroleum products issued for account of H Launch”» Yours very truly. For R. M. BROW] CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED vl /No» -2/11, POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 7th October, 1948&lt; To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, BAHRAIN , Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No.PA-396 dated the 28th August, 1948. 2. A cheque for Es«l-10-0 (Rupee One and annas ten only) is enclosed herewith in full settlement of your bill. Yours faithfully, KYM.4/ \ I n- r Dr Byxies Bfcts aiixiaea to :ae cue saui ox ixu^ees eleven^(Rs* ll/-) being a collections ^towards the Victoria Memsbrial Hospital in the Cable and Wireless Sweepstake on the Cambridgeshire run. (The Arabian Mission Hospital received a as a donation like sunj/towards that institution^ M&amp;y the sum be credited to our Unoincial Fund - Hospital Charitable Fund - Ac count ? t h. s (_ncc dr. t Issued letter No.2829 dated the 12th November 1936 to Sr. Hynes,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000292_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1067</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000292</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1067</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/11 Victoria Memorial Hospital: funds and accounts'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-10T16:30:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (77 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 71-78. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 79; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-65; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the Victoria Memorial Hospital at Bahrain: request for electrical supplies; acknowledgements of donations; credit notes; receipts for treatments; requests for medical exams, vaccinations, and eye tests.The principal correspondents are the Medical Officer at the Victoria Memorial Hospital (Dr Ralph Holmes), Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO), Eastern Bank Limited, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the Political Agent at Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Medical Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Eastern Bank Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Hospitals</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000292#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>