<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002da_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:52:17.568Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">r Copy , l 1340 j No. 25 BRITISH EMBASSY, (28/3/40). VERY GONE IDE ITT IAL 17th January, 1940* BAGDAD. My Lord In certain reports, which are also submitted to Your Lordship, it was recently brought to my notice that there was evidence that Shakib Arslan, the Arab nationalist agitator, was assisting the German Government to plan and organise a general rising in Syria, Iraq, Palestine and Transjordan and that he was in correspondence with the Mufti on this subject. 2. These reports indicated that it was probable that the Mufti was:- v (1) discussing Shakib Arslan’s plans with a number of Palestinian leaders in Bagdad; (2) sending a representative to the Diwaniyah Liwa to establish contact with discontented tribal and religious elements with a view to fomenting insurrection in that area: (3) planning to assemble in Iraq as many Arab political refugees as possible in readiness for concerted action in Palestine and Syria when the time was ripeo 3o A number of facts corroborated this information. The Right Honourable The Viscount Halifax, K.G., GoCoS.Ic, G.C.I.E., etc., etc., etc. Shakib/t Shakib Arslan's liaison with the German Government had frequently been reported from many quarters and was not in doubt, the Mufti's intercourse in Bagdad with well- known Arab extremists seemed to be increasing and afforded him ample opportunity to discuss plans of the kind suggested if he wished to do so, and the steady flow towards Iraq of Arab political refugees suggested the possibility of some understanding with the Mufti or his lieutenants. Recently, moreover, reliable information from a very secret source had revealed that some of those leaving Palestine for Iraq had stated that they were on their way to Bagdad at the Mufti's request. Finally the news was received only a few days ago that the German Government were making strenuous efforts to send Dr.Grobba on a visit to Jedda. 4. Having ascertained that there was no objection to a discreet use of the information in the above-mentioned reports, I have the honour to inform Your Lordship that I thought it desirable to give a warning to the Prime Minister and I found an opportunity to do so when, without any other guests being present, he dined with me on January 13th. His Excellency admitted that there was no doubt that Shakib Arslan was in German service and working to stir up trouble among the Arabs but he maintained that the Mufti would never lend himself to Shakib's plans. I said that the danger lay in the concentration of so many desperate exiles in Bagdad, and observed that the Mufti might be forced to act even against his personal wishes:d/ unless they renainel alert the Iraqi rroyfirri^fir^t 1 prfi^hi: he. taken by surprisec I reminded General Nuri also of the report that the Mufti was seeking support in the Euphrates, saying that although my information here was less conclusive it was such as should not be ignored. There the government had many enemies; elements to which the idea of an insurrection against established Authority in the guise of a holy war for Palestine would be likely to make a strong aopealo 5 C Nuri Pasha was, I think, to some extent impressed and undertook to make careful enquiries into the movements of the Mufti’s associates and in particular to ascertain whether a man whose name I mentioned as that of a possible intermediary between him and the Euphrates tribes had in fact been visiting Diwaniyaho At the same time he maintained that whatever Shakib Arslan, the Mufti, or any of his followers might wish to do, they could achieve nothing do long as the Army remained soundo He was watching the Army very closelyo He knew, as no doubt I did too, that some of the younger officers had been criticising the government openly for their failure to give more active support to the Arab cause in Palesiine. These young men had received encouragement from General Amin al Umari, the General Officer Commanding the 1st Division, and the Prime Minister was, he stated, insisting that this General should be removed from the Army. He had also had three young officers arrested for their disloyal criticism of himself and his Cabinet* All the senior officers other than/than Amin al Umari were, he claimed, solidly behind the government and Amin’s intrigues were solely due to personal ambitions and to his relationship to Mustafa al Umari, the Minister of the Interior in the last Cabinet who was now in opposition* 6, Two days later the Prime Minister asked the Oriental Secretary to call on him. He said that he had been testing the information which I had communicated to him; the result was that he was satisfied that the individual whom I had mentioned as a possible intermediary between the Mufti and certain elements in the Euphrates had not recently left Bagdad, and was known to be at his post teaching at the time at which it had been suggested that he was visiting Diwaniyah. As regards the Mufti the Prime Minister stated that his enquiries had failed to reveal any evidence that the Mufti had discussed with his friends plans such as I had mentioned as having been put forward by Shakib Arslan and had strengthened his belief that the Mufti was opposed to all attempts to renew fighting in Palestine. At the same time the Prime Minister asked that his thanks should be conveyed to me for having taken him into my confidence and declared that he would continue to keep a close watch on the activities of the Palestinian and Syrian refugees in Iraq. He also asked that I should be told that in addition to arresting three junior officers in the Army he was arranging for five other officers, including General Amin al Umari, to be placed on pension. He seemed confident that this step would stop the spread in the Aimy of agitation about Palestine. It is inevitable, however, tha t/■I A P V. JL • •&gt; 11 25 . 194 0 j that if these measures against the Army ih’tf gg??'!e3'To a successful conclusion they will, desirable as they may be in themselves, add to the number of his enemies. 7. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Cairo, His Majesty's Minister ct Tehran, His Majesty's High Commissioner for Palestine and to the Combined Middle East Intelligence Centre, Cairo, I have the honour, etc., (Sgd.) Basil Newton*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002da_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/343</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002da</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/343</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 1125/40 'German propaganda in the Near East'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-30T22:44:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single document.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This document, written by Basil Cochrane Newton (the British Ambassador at Baghdad), outlines concerns that Shakib Arslan is assisting the German Government in planning and organising uprisings in Syria, Iraq, Transjordan and Palestine, and that he is in correspondence with the Grand Mufti of Jerusalem (Mohammed Amin al-Husseini) on the subject. The document is addressed to Viscount Halifax (Foreign Secretary).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shakib Arslan</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Muḥammad Amin al-Ḥusayni</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rebellions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002da#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>