<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000be_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T14:44:58.082Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/210. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian iGnR preseflt iBh is co pliments to c? Q + Q -pr.r* „ H.M.Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London,*^ The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermpnHonpfl docu ment (jl). ^j.o. Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf Camp, Bahrain, British Consulate^.GeneraJ, BUSKIBE. ‘Vt. D^tcd... the. 2nd..J un§.. 1946 Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letters dated 14th Lay 1946; No . C/7 0 t o India Office and Government of India, •ject. Extract from '*Al-Mussawar*’ Issue No.1128 dated 24th Lay Egyptian interest in affairs of Persian Gulf States*Extract from ”Al-Muss a war 11 Issue No.lff28 dated 24th May, 1946. 4080 The nett result Is that the foundatioii.rtf .the Arab League has been received with Joy and gratitude by the Arabs as a whole wherever and whenever they may be found. Likewise the nett result is that the League has achieved ifcany of the Arab^ great hopes, yet she has not achieved •all* that had been hoped of her. Are we to keep silent about the part that has not been achieved for the sake of that which has been achieved? Or is it our journalistic duty - in addition to national duty - which requires us to continue to urge her to labour in those fields where she is behind hand? Northern Africa and the Arab Emirates. The League takes a great interest in the future of Tripoli and Cyrenica for which we thank her. Yet this interest would invite more thanks if it would be extended beyond the boundaries of Tripoli and Cyrenica to include Tunis, Algeria and Morocco; those countries whose sons look tmx towards the Arab League and who place great faith in her. And what is said about Northern Africa may be said also about the small states such as Kuwait, Qatar, Muscat, Hadhramaut and Bahrain, etc. The hour has struck in which those States, as well as Northern Africa, should be repre sented at the Arab League by delegates, or at least obser vers - who may keep the League informed of happenings in their countries. Pilgrimagev.-k kile copy ! ^ ^ 32/80/46. ^ . V. 3 b 2 3 * ' ? ' 7 y Sir, v/ Wil Jh referenda to; British Embassy, Cairo, 23rd April 1946. ^/r your despatch No. D.0.331-3 of March 28th, 1946, I have the honour to enclose herewith an ** extract from a report of a conversation between Brigadier Clayton on the one hand and El Sayed Taufiq Suwaidi , the Ifaqi Prime Minister, and El Sayed Tahsin al-Askari, the Iraqi Minister in Cairo, on tne other, who suggested participation of the Gulf States in the Arab League. In forwarding this report to the Foreign Office I remarked that, even if it is difficult for His Majesty’s Government to impose a veto on any cultural and economic participation of the Gulf States in the Arab League, it would seem inadvisable to encourage anything like that for the time being. I pointed out that Ibn Saud’s interest in the Gulf States might well be incon veniently stimulated by any such development. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, 3d. RONALD CAMPBELL. The Honourable Sir Geoffrey Prior ,K. C.I.E. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. ** below. Extract. They then raised the question of the Gulf States and Muscat. They were afraid that the Persian claim to the former might, at Russian instigation, be pressed. Could tiie League not invite them to join? They thought they would be quite ready to do so but they wanted to know His Majesty’s Government’s view. If His Majesty’s Government had no objection they would like to start the ball rolling probably on a cultural and economic basis to begin with. They asked me if I could get the views of His Majesty’s Government on the subject. I said I would see if it were possible for His Majesty’s Government to be sounded.A ^ Please see the last paragraph of Cairo's Dispatch Ho. 463 of 4 -th April and paragraph 6 of Brigadier Clayton's note which 1 + encloses. I think we might give the Foreign Office our view on what the re a ions of the Persial Gulf Sheikhdoms should be to the Arab ague. You might care to look in this connection atarSir G. Pnor's letter of 26th January 1942 and to &gt;*01 af a »□ tLk'Cuflt^ letter of 9th February 1942 both of which I have flagged. ' j A draft is suggested*uRAFT LEl'T^R C-^. Baxter, Esq., C.M.G., M.C. , Ext. 3315A6. Foreign Office, s.;y.i. CCh^} 2 8 Mflr 194$ Dear Baxter, iVe were interested to see Cairo Dispatch Copy, with Cairo Dispatch of 4th April and enclosure to Political RealtJeYit in the persiSi Gulf and Government vA ' India. ^ a*' No. 4^3 of 4th April transmitting a memorandum by Brigadier Clayton on a conversation with the Prime Minister of Iraq and the Iraqi Minister in Cairo^in paragraph 6 of which reference was made to the possibility of the Persian Gulf States joining the Arab League. There have I think ; so far been no indications of a de sire on the part of any of the Arab States of the PersiaTTGul^ to join the Arab League and^as Sir Ronald Campbell suggests in tc his Despatch, it io certainly undesirable to do anything to encourage such a development. Our Imperial interests in these States, which include the security of the air route to the /EastConfidential -2 ; &gt;' ' I t) l \o 1 l yV 24 MAY 1946 l FILE COP^ I /If* , Hoceived under «^viruin - Printed/Letter Uo» 0/445 dated 28th y . Anril 1946. @ h~ «Al ..iari* issue mo. 5195 of April 14th, 1946. An extract from a talk by H»£»« Abdul .ajeed Ibrahim balih pasha, president of the Arab union, tfgypt, under the following title: THE ARAH WILL 1^EVEH AC C EPT HUMILIATION It should not be far away from our minds that our brothers in the Persian Gull States, and in the nils protectorates, need some of our attention•.••.• It is our duty to put an end to their abnormal position by amalgamating them in the main body of their Arabian Ration, and by delivering them of the errors of Protection and occupation. They may then be independent and free, and live in lull respect and honour. No. 555-S# Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, 6th May 1946. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to - Hie Majesty's Secretary of^btaj^e for India, India office, London, v/ The secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, new Delhi.i* 17 APR V o . D.O. No. C/244 EXT The Political Agency, Bahrain. The 5th of Parch, 1946. 2728 A. Please refer to the correspondence ending with Foreign telegram No. 634 dated the 21st January 2 On the 27th February the B.B.C. announced that the General Secretary of the Arab League, Abdul Rahman Azzam Pasha, talking to a news agency about the League f s aims, declared that the question of representing the small Arab amirates of the Persian Gulf in the League has not been looked into though 60 Egyptian teachers were sent th to educate the sons of Bahrain and Kuwait. 3. It appears that the Egyptians do not regard the deputation of a number of Egyptian teachers to Bahrain purely as an educational measure, but that they also regard the matter in a political light. Besides this it is interesting to see into what detail the General Secretary has gone in his probings. Yours sincerely, Sd. A.C. GALLOWAY. The Hon'ble Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf D.O. No. 331-3 Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. The 22th L arch 1946. Forwarded with compliments to: ^ E.P. Donaldson,Esquire, C.L.G., India Office, London. H. Weightman,Esquire, C.I.E., I.C.S., Secretary to the Government of India vcxj. j vav/v x iiiiidi -Liiu.~Lci 5 External Affairs Department, New Delhi. • His Excellence Sir Ronald CaTelephone Number : WELbeck 4420. Telegrams : MINIFORM, LONDON. In any further communication on this subject the following reference should be quote 1:— FJ? 89/3 Your reference : - N Dear Harrison, MINISTRY OF INFORMATION, MONTAGU MANSIONS, CRAWFORD STREET, LONDON, W.l. 28th January 1946 With reference to your Ext 417/46 of the 19th January, I am sorry to say that I have''clrawn a hiank. I am now trying some personal sources in Middle Bast in the rather remote hope that they will know something about this curious story, and if I can leani anything authentic I shall of course let you know. Yours sincerely, J.H. DRIBBdG I.UDDLh BAST DIVISION J.B.K. Harrison Esq,, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. REtiO. F2L t' &gt;T INDIA OFFlOEl90 &gt;- OP\ (Received under Bahrain Printed Letter dated 30th October 1945}. iio. C/1026, A translation of an axtr^t fippm ..»41 issue &gt;, 5 ? ^ -Qu f da e* 1304 aor^espoAding to v No, 3048 dated 16th Dul 22nd October, 1945. „ . --f' 6 ■ 6 Federation of the Arab Persian Gi^lf irat^ in the Jyyv*’ It is understood in Baghdad that the Amirs, Chiefs and Shaikhs of the Persian Gulf Emirates, who had met in Bahrain in the middle of March last to discuss the plan of establishing a political and economic federation of the- Emirates, will meet again soon in Bahrain to re-examine the questions discussed in their last meeting. The summary of the questions is as follows First : The establishment of a federation of the Emirates with Bahrain as its centre. jecond : The adoption of a foreign policy of these Emirates. \ Third : To guarantee the internal autonomy of the Emirates. Fourth: Abolishing passport restrictions between these Emirates. Fifth : The formation of a high council in Bahrain of the Chiefs and Shaikhs of the Emirates to supervise the organization of the area. Sixth : The High Council is to be represented by a member at the Arab League. : CONFIDENTIAL No. 388 - S. Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, 5th November 1945. Copies forwarded with compliments to e/&amp;&gt; , H .M‘s Secretary of State for India T mi i n Of f*i n* . ' jfflK '' OX, &lt;£{ ^ m a n mm India Office, London. joN The Secretary to the Government of India i in the External Affairs Department, J ^ // Nev; Delhi . ni with reference to Residency Express Letter No. c/365, dated 28th October 1945.0 w 4 ' v &amp; i. file copy NT OF INDIA Department. CONF IJi MIAL . PRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). ms [N.B.— Thi« is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if »&lt; had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] 0 ^ : i CG O l* t h© No. To C/365 . Dated x&amp;tmfo Nj&amp;tiDethi Political Resident, Persian Gulf, , the Camp, Bahrain. 28th October 20 45- Re peated His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India , \ The India Office, LONDON. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External affairs Department, NEW DEL H I. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. mr Reports alleging proposed meeting in Bahrain of Arab Rule rs. Reference correspondence ending with my telegram No. 1/439. dated the 3rd September 1945 (endorsement No.C/233, of even date, to Government of India). 2. Copy is enclosed of letter No. C/1013 , dated the 25th October 1945, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, reporting two recent Arabic broadcasts from Jaffa on the same subject. I should be grateful for any information ascertainable as to the source of these reports. Sd. A.C.GALLOWAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.POL IX, The 25tH of C• J• Felly^ Lscj* ^ 0«B« • j« 9 I political Agent ^ Bah^ q/1 ^ The Hon»ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bahrain# Reports alleging proposed meetly of Arab States in Bahrain. I have the honour to refer to your endorsement No. c/ 233 9 dated the 3rd September, 1945, and preceding correspondence on the subject noted above. 2# On the 4th of October, 1945, the Sharq El Adna (Jaffa) Arabic Broadcast stated that 'According to the Beirut Press, it is most probable that the Arab Kings and Amirs will hold a meeting in Bahrain following the • pilgrimage season'. My enquiry from the Acting Adviser to the Government of Bahrain elicited the reply that he had no information of any arrangements for such a meeting and that he would have known of them if they had been made. He was unable to give me any idea of the source of these reports - if they have a local source. 3. On the night of the 21st October the same station broadcast that a meeting of the 'representatives' of Persian Gulf States is likely to be held in Bahrain in order to (a) formulate plans for a Persian Gulf Federation which would send a repre sentative to the Arab League. (b) consider the economic problem. (c) concert measures to remove all passport restrictions between Gulf States. B I would request that the Government of Palestine be addressed and requested to state the source of these reports.Datea Received CQNiffPfflff lAL CODE TSLBGRA| t l Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.' Secretary of State for India, (copy by post to Government of India and Bahrain) Shiraz, nil hours, 3rd September 1945* 22*35 hours, 3rd September 1945. &gt;*. 5. Mo. T/439. Y our telegram 16557, August 20t h. Arab meeting at Bahrain. ,, . i ' rom local enquiries it would appear ^nau there is no foundation for press article* ic, is presumably 'inspired” and I think had this come from anywhere in the Gulf we should have heard something of it. RECO. POL DtPT -■5 SEP 1945 INDIA OFFICE(4502) Wt. 41647—P171 25in. 12/44 G.S.St. Gp. 620 No Addressed Political Resident; repeated Bahrein; copy to Government of India. Lebanon News Agency quoted by Al-Nahar of 1st August reports that a meeting will be held at Beihrein by the middle of next month to discuss the following points: 1. Formation of a Union of Arab Amirates of the Persian Gulf with Headquarters at Bahrein; 2. Unification of ^ the foreign policy of these Amirates; 3« Full internal independence within present borders; if. Removal of all passport restrictions; 5. Formation of a Supreme Council at Bahrein to supervise foreign relations and undertake the administration of the country; 6. Part icipation in the Arab League. '2, Have you any comments?JT^: TO: Mr. [Harrison, India Q’fice, MINISTRY OF INFORMATION, Q p i^aTet street, LONDON, W.C.1. August 19 5 East Div, Herewith the extract for which you asked , relative to the Persian Gulf states. I should be very obliged if you would let us know the result of your enquiries. ^ J.H. DRIBERG MIDMLE EAST DIVISION A*') MPm- tLEBANON AG-BNCY (quoted by AL-NAHAR of 1 st August) ’'A meeting will be held at Bahrein by the middle of next month to discuss the following points: 1. Formation of a Union of Arab Amirates of the Persian Gulf with Head Quarters at Bahrein; 2, Unification of the foreign Policy of these Amirates$ 3, Full internal independence within present borders; 4* Removal of all passport restrictions: 5.Formation of a Supreme Council at .Bahrein to supervise foreign relations and undertake the administration of the country; 6 C participation in the Arab League.' 1■</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000be_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1019</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000be</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1019</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 4045/45 'Formation of a Union of Arab Amirates of the Persian Gulf - with Headquarters at Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-20T22:13:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 26; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers regarding reported discussions among the rulers of Bahrain, Kuwait, Qatar and the Trucial States to form a federation and to gain entry into the Arab League. The primary correspondents are: Ministry of Information; India Office; Political Resident, Persian Gulf; Political Agency, Bahrain; British Middle East Office; British Embassy, Cairo.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Middle East Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Information</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy, Cairo</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arab League</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial States</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000be#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>