<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000e5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T09:27:08.510Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">W/iS ; Uf/t NOTE ON HR. IMT H/IFV, .ITH HIS liIWXi:33 . Burrows saw His Highness on the morning of Saturday the 14th May and after the usual exchange of greetings explained to His Highness that His Majesty’s Goveimirient had been for some months past particularly exercised to combat Communism, -^hey had found from their experience in other parts of the world that this could most effectively be done by action on parallel lines: by vigorous police action against agitators and other Comrunist agents, and by social reform designed to remove conditions of poverty, squalor, and inequality of opport unity in which Communism had been found to take root most easily He explained that Communism had already got a hold on other countries in the Middle East and he hoped that steps could be taken now to prevent Kuwait becoming another fertile field for building activity and many schemes of improvement of which he had heard and indeed seen something - in Kuwait, as well as by the large suns of money that had been placed at the disposal o: the various Departments of His Highness’ Government for the regards police action against Communism he had recently strength ened his Police Force by the employment of personnel from the its propagation Mr. Burrows continued th t he was impressed by the improvement of the administration. At this stage Kis Highness interrupted to say that as former...former Palestinian Police Forces, that he would welcome any advice or information against suspedted Communists, and that he would act on it to the extent of expelling any one that His Majesty’s Political authorities might consider undesirable. Mr. Burrows thanked His Highness for this and continued that, efficacious as action on these lines was, it was not in itself enough. Mr. Burrows then reverted to the subject of improve ments in the Administration designed to to raise the standards of living of the workers and suggested to His Highness that, while it was clear that large sums of money were being expended, it was not certain that His highness was getting results commen surate with the expenditure involved. He continued that it was the feeling in the Foreign Office that expenditure of capital and income should be planned over a number of years and reserves accumulated in such a way that, if the price of oil were to fall or any other circumstance arise to limit His Highness’ income, the standards of administration at that time attained could be maintained out of income from reserve funds. At this sta e His ^ighness intervened to ask whether we were discussing Communism or money. Mr. Burrows indicated that Communism and improvements in standards of admin istration were, in H.M.G’s experience, parts of the same problem. His Highness replied that all his life he had de voted his energies to improving the lot of his people, and, when one considered how small Kuwait was, how it lacked many material resources, and yet how prosperous it was, he thought that we shouldshould have to admit that he had not been wholly unsuccess ful. He continued that His Majesty^ Government had always protected him from interference from outside and had refraihed from interfering in his internal affairs; and that he hoped it was not His Majesty’s Government’s intention to change their policy. Mr. Burrows continued that „he presence of large sums of money in a small State li^ce Kuvaitin the midst of a world racked by poverty and insecurity would give rise to an increasing volume of criticism and jealousy fro Eis Highness’ neighbours .and others, unless it could be shown that Eis High ness was making exemplary use of his money on social and other services designed to better the lot of the ordinary man. His Majesty’s Government would always do their best to put the Kuwait case in the best light possible, but they could only successfully argue a case in which they themselves believed. At this point His Highness interrupted to say that he had in the past dealt with Nazism although in Kuwait it had been supported by powers outside his State; and, God willing, he v/ould, with His Majesty’s Government’s help and advice, deal equally ruthlessly with Communism by expelling its exponents. He had always received hel ) and advice from His Majesty’s Government in ample measure in dealing with his external relations, but he had always concucted his internal affairs himself. /hile internally he was Huler of Kuwait; he was, externally, not just a friend of His Majesty’s Government but, like all of us, an actual servant of His Majesty’s Government. Mr. BurrowsMr. Burrows than-ced him for his expression of loyalty, but continued that Communism was not quite the same thing as Nazism. That while Nazism had x&amp;p* relied on force of arms; Communism, in the present stage at any rate, relied on influencing the minds of men and that it was by influencing His Highness’ own subjects that Communism might gaina footing in Kuwait. His Highness then reiterated his assurances about police action and demanded what was behind &amp;&amp;&amp; all this talic of improving his administration. Hitherto he had been left to run it himself. He had been well looked a£ter by His Majesty’s Government abroad, but left alone at home. If His Majesty’s wanted his money they should say so. Otherwise, it arose from oil resources which belonged to Kuwait and was their own to dispose of. Mr. Burrows explained that this was not the intent ion of His Majesty’s Government at all; that they had no desire to criticise what had been done but rather jointly to tackle a common problem. His Bigness thanked Mr. Burrows and assured him that he would always be glad to have His Majesty’s Govern ment’s help, and that Ins would always turn to His Majesty’s Political Agent when he wanted it. If His Majesty’s Govern ment had any specific advice to offer they could always offer it through the Political Agent and he would be gald to consider it. Throughout the interview, while being quite forth coming and cooperative about police action against Communists, His HighnessHia highness did not or would not grasp the connection between standards of administration and the development of Communism in Kuwait. Whenever the expenditure of State funds was touched he was ready to draw a herring across the trail; and appeared to regard the connection between internal administration and Communism as a bogey introduced to persuade him to surrender some of his autonomy. In closing the interview Mr. Burrows asked His Bigness whether he had any points to refer to His Majesty’s Government, to which he replied that he had nothing to conceal and nothing to ask for. Be was absolute ly satisfied with the treatment he had received.THE BRITISH COUNC ► INCORPORATED BY ROYAL CHARTER • '-N rmroo: H.M. THE KING 3 HANOVER STREET, LONDON, W.l Telephone : MAYIair 8484 Ref: FG/600/2 9 th June, 1949. r f : r4 •&gt; O 0 Dear Burrows, * ~ * _ Thank you very much for sending me the very interesting note with your letter of 31 st May* 1949 e I am very ^ glad that you do attach great importance to the maintenance of close contact between the British Council, the local educational authorities and the local British officials, together with representatives of the oil companies. I attach such reflections as occur to me on reading the memorandum. Yours sincerely, £1 a.T: Director, Middle East Department. B.A.B. Burrows, Esq. The Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. »NOTE Oil :KMOHATIDUK Hi HK. rUKnU&gt;»o dale*L) ' EITTITLED 'EDUCATION IK THE PERSIAN W.ur 1 . The British Council is now proposinc to keep Height NOTE ON ? NOTE ON ?E ?IORAIIDUI! BY T.!R, BURROWS DATED ei;titlsd 11 education in the Persian otiur in Basra for at any rate another year and to raise the status of the post to Grade II. This reflects the importance attached by the Council both to the work he will be doing in the Persian Gulf and to his duties os institute Director in this rather isolated station. 2. Kuwait. The section on Kuwait'gives a very clear picture of 'tile present position. The school system seems to be going through the stage which one always finds in countries where general education is comparatively new. At this stage there are more jobs for 'soi-di8ant ,, black-coated workers than suitable applicants, with the result that half-educated boys are tempted to leave school to take jobs for which they are not really qualified, in the interests of the country, the pupils themselves, and potential employers, a careful study would seem to be advisable as to numbers in all grades of schools to ensure sufficient boys of adequate education for the posts available and for some of the more promising ones to proceed to further education, while allowing lor the wastage which always occurs for one reason or another in these countries, in regard to the girls, one may feel quite confident that, before long, educate^ young men will insist that a proportion of girls at any rate stay in school long enough to receive adequate education to become suitable wives for educated men. I think the Hostel in Cairo is doing very well. I have heard good accounts of it recently. Other possibilities for further education should be considered, however, in case the Government desires, at some time or another, to break the educational connection with Egypt. I feel sure that it would be of great advantage to * have one first-rate secondary school with two or thre« British teachers, who will know the standards required for entry to the universities, both in Beirut and in this country, and it would be useful if some of the students could, in aue course, come to Great Britain for university education with sufficiently souna grounding and knowledge of English to make a university career a success. Kuwait may not, hov/ever, be repaired for such a move at present. Even if there were some British teachers at Kuwait, the periodic visit of someone conversant with educational administration is very necessary as the English teachers in such a school would be unlikely to have much experience of educational administration in Great Britain or, what is even more important, the wdjslfc of adopting educational administra tion to countries suen^as these, in the meantime, height's visits.•..4 V I agree that the Oil Company would ao well to ° ... -i . • „ J 4- V 4-Vv o part of a c enera l scheme which in its entirety seemed to facilitate their work in the area. (or indeed td'Kuwait) but from corresponaence I have rather felt that Mr. Belgrave is over-optimistic in thinking that the appointment of a British teacher will solve a good many of his problems. in any case, the success ol the teacher would, depend largely on the suitability of the man appointed and the arrangements that could be made to guarantee that the position he held was such as to make it possible for him to contribute much to the character of the school. I discussed at the time with the then Bahreini Minister of Education, who was in this country, the matter of the students sent to Cairo. He was quite firm in his desire to withdraw them anil did not feel it right or sensible to try to shake his views on the matter. It is interesting to note that the Bahrein petroleum Company is now taking considerable interest and it seems to be a matter of prime importance to direct their enthusiasm into channels which will be of the greatest benefit both to themselves and to the country. As to Qatar and I uscat, it is difficult to comment, but the situation is indeea intriguing and certainly seems to merit investigation. Bahrein. Unfortunately I have never been to Bahrein• • * 3 . j 4-v, arrnr»r\ tn von v final section Iieoci*i*ijenti al &gt; t* n ,Tree tha^the youncer n.eubers of rulinc families should ■'otnehow or other obtain satisfactory education. !,^y sor.ienow oi oi-i 1cfln nolle^e at Damascus is that by°several conversations with Arabs of the rioaleKastw.o ole as secondary school with a staff largely British on the lines of the victoria College but in surroundings less urban ■Mion timsp in Alexandria ana Cairo ana wi uh a ^reatci Lias towards the religious ana cultural background or the countries from which the students com#: If such a school were establishea, it might be aavisable to give up the idea of stepping-up tne f xistin 5 , ^ secondary school at Kuwait, with the addition of two or three ■British staff, into a first-rate seconaary school, anu to convert it into an efficient junior seconaary with two streams one literary and one technical, the latter to work in association with the apprenticeship scheme at th ® K * the former to supply pupils for the full secoiK-ar. 1.1 or at some other site which m^tt be cnosen in the . ei tile Crescent. V . •;nr i ARAMCO SENDS ARAB STAFF TO COLLEGE Washington, Sunday. The Arabian-American Oil Company, is training 40 selected Arab employees as clerks and teachers in a special training class at the American Univer sity of Beirut. According to information receiv ed here from Dhahran, the Arabian students began their studies on July 4 and training will continue 10 weeks. Upon completion of their course of study they will return to Dha hran and will be re-assigned to their former positions. The overall cost of the project to Aramco is estimated at 25,000 dollars. Students for courses were sel ected cn the basis of their know ledge of English, their particular job with the Company, and tneii individual record while empoyed by Aramco. Students in training for clerical positions receive instructions in English, mathematcs, typing, office machine operation, office proce dure, and supervised evening study. Those in training for teaching positions supplement their study with courses in teaching methods.■sin</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000e5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/230</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000e5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/230</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/43 Internal Administration (Social Reforms)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-04T00:36:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (12 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 14; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of the following:Notes of a conversation that took place on 15 May 1949 between the Foreign Office official, B A B Burrows and the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah, concerning state reform and how to prevent a growth in popularity of communism in the country (folios 2-6).Notes by the British Council official, E R J Hussey written in response to a memorandum entitled 'Education in the Persian Gulf' written by B A B Burrows, 31 May 1949 (folios 9-11).An undated article from
                              Iraq Timestitled 'Aramco Sends Arab Staff to College' (folio 12).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Communism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000e5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>