<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:25:37.506Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">T” * 28/51 Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. Telegram Q From To No. 595 Dated tie 9th September, 1943 Your telegram T/670 September 6th. Requirements programmes. £) Civil Paragraph l . (a) Dr. Harrison now in India has^ ordered there a quantity of surgical equipment hospital supplies and drugs urgently required for Mission Hosi-iital but even approx imate gross weight of 'his orders is not known here. If further information available on his return I will wire you. No other medical equipment on order for Bahrain. (b) nha l. Apart from small quantities totalling not more than a hundredweight ordered by Cable and Wireless and B.O.A.C. I am aware of no orders placed on India from Bahrain for dhal. I was under the impression from Foreign telegram 2393 March 26th that it could not now be obtained from India. If it can Bahrain would be glad of these three tons. (c) Washing Soda . Extra half ton not for Bahrain. Paragraph 2 . Names of shippers have not been given in civil requirements programmes as Government of India telegram 5567 July lOtb did not ask for them, please see paragraph 4(7) of that NCJ - POLITICAL -No.C/1481 Political Agency, Bahrain, 1st November 1943 To MEMORANDUM The Director of Customs Bahrain. In regard to Civil Requirements for the present quarter, it is possible that 35 tons of ghee surrendered by Muscat, may become available. Please let me know urgently, how much, if any, is required by the Bahrain Government. 2. The Government of India intimate that six tons of washing soda have been included in the Civil Requirements Programme for this quarter. As this item is not covered by the Established Shippers Procedure, could you please furnish the name of the shipper to whom a licence should be issued? Political Agent, Bahrain p'L-28/31 S Telegram G.T.C./S From Political Agent, Bahrain* To Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. No. 744 Dated the 1st November, 1943. Ten tons cement included in Civil Bequire- ments Programme for present quarter. Established Shippers Procedure does not apply. Telegraph name of shipper to enable me issue license. NCJ - POLITICAL -List of Established Shippers of Washinp; Soda . ^ 1. Ilohamed Javad Mohamed Hassan Lari &amp; Co., Bombay. 2. Hajy Suleman Adham Kothari &amp; Co., Karachi. DIRECT OR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN.1* St - ! No,_C/ 1655 Political Aeency, Bahrain. Dated the 29th November, 1943. To 1. Messrs Yousuf Abdulrahman Fakhroo, Bahrain. 2. Messrs Haridas Janimal Bahrain. MEMORANDUM . Reference your letters dated the 23rd and 25th November 1943, respectively. The question of the revision of the allotment of Civil Requirements is at present under consideration. I hope to be able to communicate with you again in the near future. R H.B.iPs. Political Agent, Bahrain I NCJP.^'s. Note dated SO-11-43 on F.O. file 36/49. 8 «■ 9. I understand that the export of cement is totally prohibited. w e should telegraph an cmendment to the Civil Requirements Programme and also write to the P.F. copy to 0. of I. recommending the grant of an Export Permit. It Id. T.H. 30-11-434 E 0 36/lh9 ¥ ^ i!iAX J itLOO i*LjLl£j\ /£) From Political ^gent, Bahrain. To Political Fesident, at Bahrain. No. C/17^4 Dated the 12th December, 1943. Civil Requirements Programme for quarter January - March 1943. 2. Pahrain Government’s stock of cement has been entirely exhausted and premises are falling into a drngerous state of repair. Grateful if Government of India could be U-c&gt;o asked to ermit the export of ^0 tons cuarterly. Sd/- T. Hickinbotham. ( Political Agent, Pshrain. c— J j EO 1No.C/1776. ^l3f '' ,, (§) Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 19th December,194o. II To. The Director of Customs, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM . Reference your letter No. P.A./936 dated the Urd November, 1943. 2. The Government of India have not agreed to allow the import into Bahrain of the vegetable ghee surplus in Muscat. , r c ^ i olitical Agent, Bahrain. jk HWD.ifo Po- 5 f Lt r r.T.r, Government of India, New Delhi. Political Agent, Bahrain. Telegram From To * wu-^ux^cw. /'.gem,, Bahrain. No. 181 N A Dated 9th recoived 10 th February, 1944 . \&lt;j ^ Civil Requirements Programme for J„nuary-I« a rch includes ?_cement for Trucial Coast. Please telegraph (a) Fame of consignee. (b) Fame and address of exporter and shares allotted to each. - torfign -CONFIDENTIAL. No. 236-S. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Pevsian Gulf presents bis compliments to 1# The Politioal Agent, KUWAIT , 2. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , 3. The Political Agent, y 135 CAT , and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...th«.. March. 1944 &amp;S H\^ ^ Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Go v*raman t of Ind iu, Cozcmerce Department, mamorandun:. No.il 5• (ETC)/43, dated th e 23rd Regulation of e^porte of controlled commodities to Middle Bast territories December 1943 to Export Trade Controllers, Bombay, Madras, Calcutta and Karachi*A yr (/? ^ Copy of a memuranduixi No.U-J.S. (BTC)/43, dated the 23rd )e can her 1943 from the Joint Secretary to the Government of \ India, Department of Commerce, Camp, Bombay, to the Bxport Trade Controller, Bombay/Madras/Calcutta/Karachi . A note containing ins true tione for the regulation of exports of controlled commodities to the Middle Sast Terri tories is forwarded herewith for necessary action. These instructions will apply in regard to commodities licensed by you, vrtiether under instructions from the Food or the Commerce Dspartoent • Any exceptions to the procedure outlined here will be conmunicated to you by the Department cone erne d. id. AS stated in the note, Middle Bast Import Licences should not be insisted upon in regard to exports to Oil Companies, Hallways and other strategic and tele-communicatio: undertakings. It is not intended, however, that any relax ation of the other export control restrictions should ordinarily be granted by the Export Trade Controllers for these undertakings unless specially authorised in any parti cular case by Government. Procedure for co-ordination eff the Indian Export Licences with Middle Bast Import Licences. Egypt Ih le sti ne Trans j or dan Syria Cyprus Sudan Aden Sau di Arabia It is proposed to bring into force a scheme of coordina tion between Indian export licences with Middle Bast Import licences on the following line s (1) To licences for export of controlled goods will be issued unless the relative consignment is covered by an import licence granted in the country of destination; this condition will net be insisted upon in regard to exports to Oil Companies, Railways and other strategic and telecommuni cation undertakings. (2) The M.E.S.C. Cairo will send to Delhi periodical lists of import licences granted in the respective territor ies and graded by them A, B or X in accordance with the procedure summarised in tie Annexure. (3) It has been agreed that for oertain main com oditi es the Government of India will furnish each importing terri tory with a list of principal established ejqporters, showing approximately their respective shares of the trade to that territory in the particular commodity. This list is intend ed to serve as a rou^i guide to licensing authorities and may be adhered to as far as poseible in making allocations to various exporters. It is not, however, intended that the list ehouId be adhered to rigidly, but no licences should be issued to anyone who is not a listed exporter. The * territories will, in turn, furbish lists of their establish ed importers together with names of the exporters with ¥hom they normally do business. In this way it diouldbe possible to ensure that business at either aid is carried on only by established firms and in some relation to previous trade. The Export Trade Controllers have already taken up the preparation of these lists, and when the co - or dim ati or arrangements are in full operation, th«y will bring to the notice of Government any instances where the importing countries show undu e prefer ence to particular exporters, or snow consistent disregard of the claims of any class of i establishedyrench Somaliland Iraq Pe r-ai a. V jr /=*■&gt; 'T 0 % ,2 established ejqporters. (4) it is possible that importing licensing procedure in some of the countries may not cover imports by parcel post or by dhow, but from the point of view of the Government of India, it is necessary that all exports permitted by Export Trade Controllers should be covered by import lie ernes gianted at the other end* ’whether the e^qporter proposes to despatch the goods by parcel post or dhow or by steamer (or by the overland route to Persia)* This is necessary to ensure that the available export quota will be utilised to satisfy only demands approved by the Governments of importing t err itorie s. There be a few commodities which are not in short supply in India and which msy be allowed to be shipped by country craft (unregistered shipping) without insisting upon Middle Bast import licences* It is proposed however that no such exports should be permitted without the Govern ment of Indians specific concurrence* Export Trade Con trollers msy submit proposals as to the commodities which may thus be licensed* (5) It is proposed to deal at Headquarters with the priority gradings received from th e M*E.S* C. For this purpos applications received from snorters who claim to have obtained import licences at the ether end will havd to be referred by Export Trade Controllers to Delhi and for this purpose, tii e procedure indicated below m^ be brought into force from the 1st February 19 44 for conmodities other than cotton piecegoods* In regard to cotton piecegoods, •quota* licences on the existing basis of allotment m^ be granted at the beginning of Hie quarter, a condition being imposed that the licences will be confirmed only if evidence of grant of import licences at the other end is produced within a period of two months* (6) There will generally be a time-lag in the issue of Middle East Import licences against the quota orfbexx for a given period* Thus in issuing licences against our January-March export quota, the corresponding MESC priority gradings for import licences granted during January-March may not be received until June* Y/e may, therefore, in considering issue of licences against any quarter's export quota consider applications supported by import licences granted by the respective territory during that or the previous quarter* (7) The export Trade Controllers map Isluc a notice to all exporters on the following line s With effect from the 1st February 1944, no export licence will be granted for any conmodity to Middle East territories unless the applicant is able to produce evidence of an import licence having been granted in the countiy of destination* The number and, if possible, the month of issue of the import licence should be quoted in the applica tion. Exporters should note however that the mere fact that their consignments are covered by an import licence granted in the country of destination will not entitle then to receive export licences in India, as a matter of course* Applicati onsffor licences under this procedure should be submitted well in advance of the intended date of ship ment (at least six weeks) as i t may be necessary to make references to tax-other authorities before a decision as to thethe grant of licences can be reached. issue of licences will generally be confined to shippers estaolished in the trade before the 1st April 1942 and will ordinarily be for quantities proportionate to the level of exports by the shipper concerned during previous years. The Government of India reserve the ri^it to refuse licences for individual consignments without assigning any reasons. It is open to the shipper concerned to effect shipment either by steamer or by country craft as they choose - ani by parcel post in the case of small quantities specially authorised by the Export Trade Controller - but in no case will exports by country craft or by parcel post be exempted irom the obligation to obtain an import licence in the importing country • (8) Applications on the above basis may be called for from exporters and referred to this Department once a fort- V night in the form of a tabular statement in the ^closed form. Two copies of the statement ahouli be submitted to this Department with the Export Trade Controller’s recommaid- ations as to the quantities that may be licensed in the case of each applicant, with reference to the quota restrictions usually applicable to the commodity concenned. urgent cases may be referred to Government by special letter or telegram giving the relevant particulars. This Department will scrutinise the applications with reference to the corresponding impart licence particulars received from the M.3.S.C. Cairo, and allot quantities to each applicant, having regard to the priority grading recommended by the Centre. One copy of the statement with the orders of Government noted therein will be returned to the Export Trade Controller for necessary action. It is quite likely that in regard to several items, action hag to be kept in abeyance, and further enquiries made from Cairo or from the ports, but such references can be minimised after some experience is gained of the working of the scheme. The present procedure in respect of exports to Persia and Iraq will be replaced by the detailed procedure outlined above for all Middle East countries.AJTNBXIRE • Procedure for importB under M.E.S.C. aponeorship ia aa follows: Schedule a of all ea&amp;ential commodities, whose import is approved, are drawn up by M.E.S*C., and the appropriate loading area for each, as directed by London and Washington, indicated# For most of these commodities territorial quotas are allotted in agreement with loading areas and the territories concerned* who issue licences on this basis. in the case of certain ether coMBodities, for which it is not possible to fix quotas, each application to import is treated on its ovn merits as a H sp ecial cast D A# denotes goods whose supply and shipment is vital to the war effort. B. denotes less agential goods, the import of which is nevertheless considered j us tifieMie should opportunity arise for shipment without displacing «A rt category items. X. indicates goods the shipment of v/hich is not * recommended• Import Licences issued by the local territorial governments in accordance v.ith the aoove procedure are listed and die lists are passed to M.E.S.C. usually fortnightly for vetting and approval of shipping space mn ;&gt;roottr*ra*ut facilities. In the esse of Saudi Arabia alone Import licences as such are not leaned, but meroh^nt »s orders are passed to the local authorities #iere they are allotted a number aid passed to M.E.S.C. in the same manner as Import Licences. Granted lists are then forwax’ded to ihn appropriate loading areas, where export facilities are granted only against M.3.S.C. recoiwnend-. ation. Ministry of War Transport representatives in all areas have instruct! ons to load, only goods recommended by the Centre. The gradings used by this centre to indicate the priority to be accorded to any giv«n item are as follows: General. — The Import Licences may be issued for the denomina tions recognized by us, e.g. yards &amp;r cotton pieoegoods, weight for cotton blankets, value for glass and leather manufactures. RHL.'r\ k-Jf CONFIDENTIAL C/520. Political Agency, Bahrain, 22nd March, 1944. To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. MEMOHANDUM I enclose for your perusal and ret, urn a printed letter which I have received from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in tha Persian Gulf. 2. I shall be grateful for your comments on how the scheme will affect Bahrain's re-export trade with Saudi Arabia. Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential. - No. 6 ^ V ' 1363 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahia in Dated, 10th R/^'hani 1563 April 3, 1944. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memor andum:- oo ^ ~ aaT,ea 'cne 22nd March, 1944. From what I understand of the new arrangements referred to in your enclosure it does not appear that transit trade from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia will be affected, provided that the Saudi Trade Represen- ativc forwards to the appropriate quarters his list of established exporters and importers for Eastern ^audi^Arabia. The importers are established in Bahrain the chief of them being Haj Abdul Aziz Ali ^ essrs « Dhamanmal Isardas ana Haj Yusuf + Whose a Sents in India are, respec- i ely, Haj Saleh Abdulla al Bassam, Messrs. Dhaman mal isardas and Haj Ibrahim Yusuf Zainal Ali Reza? I assume that U.K.C.C. will continue to send t up £ 1 ?; es of I&gt;oodstufl ‘ s su ch as sugar, cereals etc. to Bahrain for reshipment to Saudi Arabia Adviser to the Government. 01 jffiri-nfnfwy9 mmmm 28/cl Political Resident, Bushire, Political Pgentj Bahrain. Telegram Q From To No 1357 Dated 9th and Received 10th June, 1944. „ iSiSt telegram No YcS'f June 9th. 2. Cement is not subject to Established Shippers Procedure, please telegraph particulars of Exporter and con- signees to Government of India to enable to issue licenses. ICH - BRITCONSUL - s u ° ic is2Z\ EXPRiLbb LKTILH From Political, Bahrain, To Political, Sharjah, No, C/909 Dated the 11th June, 1344. 11th June, 1344. t As cennnt does not come under the Established Shippers Procedure please telegraph particulars of consignors and consignees, so that licences may be issued. (V NCJ Political Agent, Bahrain.✓ 23/30 &amp; S3/S2 Te-i-e^ram From To Q Political Resident, Carn^ Siiiraz, political Agent, Kuvait. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. No- T/520 Dated 14th received 15th September, 1J44 External Affairs Department Express Letter F* al-ME/44 August 26th. Export Control in India. 2. Please take necessarj action. NCJ - PRIOR - -fi k 1^ &gt;30 -iECEIVKD UNDER OOVERN’JS'r OF INDIA E&gt; ! DOSSEMENT NO. dated 30th August,1944. F. 15(78)-W/44 GQVil iNMUjT OF INDIA COMMERCE DEPART MU. T. D*C # • 6?-C.iv(23)/43 D«it6d. 10/ / o / /44* cy&lt;°3^ -Or 0 My dear v C 2 ' ^ During tho recent discussions at Delhi with the M.E3.C Delegation from Cairo, it was mentioned that there was reason to believe that a good proportion of goods for which bills of ^ading are made out for “Suez in transit* 1 are rebooked to final destination other than those for which the goods were originally licensed in India, A suggestion was made that it would be easier to control such diversions if the Indian authorities could exercise a oercent- age check aft r shipment of the goods, to see that bills of lading were made out i the name of the ultimate consignee as given in the export licences. Shipping agents should be instructed not to issue bills of lading merely to “order** of an unnamed consignee. M Xn transit 'bills of lading should name the ultimate consignee in such terms as ** Please notify....** 2, Government of India would be glad of early report from you as to the exact practice now followed in such cases and the feasibility of adopting the suggestion referred to in the preceding paragraph after calling for bills of lading from shipping agents and mailing a percentage check of the consignee mentioned therein ag:inst the export lie nee and the *xport manifest. hu To All Export Trade Controllers. Yours sincerely, Sd. G. SWAMINATHAN. * GOVERNMENT OF INDIA ? ldi OFFICE OF THE CHIEF CONTROLLER OF EXPORTS. (COi.i .iARCjii DEPART No. 11-F.P. (8)/44 New Delhi, tne Oth August, 1944. To The Export Trade Controller, Bombay/Madras/Calcutta/Karachi. Reference (correspondence ending with Sim.nivasan , s D.O. letter No, 64-CW(62)/43 dated the 18th March 1944)^your letter No. 1-11052/43 dated the 1st February 19447regarding percentage check of bills of Lading and export manifests. 2. It has been hedided that a percentage eheck of the Bills of Lading with export licenses should be exercised after shipment of the goods, in the nanner suggested in Swarainathan *3 D.O. letter No. 67-CW(23)/43 dated 10th June 1983 if the system Las not already been introduced in your port. As the underlying object of this check is to prevent “trafficking in licences** it is considered that for the present , the check may be confined to exports to the following destinations only in respect of which complaints of “trafficking in licences** or diversion to unauthorised consignees have been noticed. (i) Arab Shaikhdoms in the Persian Gulf. (ii) Ceylon and British East Africa. (iii) The Middle East Countries including the British Territories in that area.and (iv) European neutral countries including Turkey. Any suggestion you may like to make in the light of your experience in recent months as to the desirability of adding any other territories to this list may be cohimunicated to this office in due course. -- 2 - 3. A notice may, accordingly, be issued to exporters in suitable terms conveying Government’s decision. It may be explained to then that although their legal responsibility to send the goods to the consignee named in the export licences applies equally to all destinations, the Government of India propose for th^prezent to confine detailed check through authorised dealers in foreign exchange only to certain destinations. Likewise, the shipping companies may also be advised that entry in the export manifest of the names of consignees need only be made in case of destinat ions specified in paragraph 2 above. The above instructions apply only to export of controlled goods. 4. As regards uncontrolled goods no check over Bills of Lading need be exercised as' the responsibility for ensuring that the goods are hot consigned to objectionable consignees e.g. those in the statutory list, falls on the Customs authorities. 5. A point has been raised that the Exchange Bank may not be able to distinguish between controlled and uncontrolled goods. In the case of uncontrolled goods, this difficulty can be got over by your issuing a certificate at the request of exporters that the goods in question do not require any licence for export. [jhis disposes of your endorsement No. 244/W dated 26th April, 1944 to Commerce DepartmentTJ . Sd. Illegible Assistant Chief Controller for Chief Controller of Exports. To ()E.T.C. Calcutta, Madras, Karachi. £to E.T.C. Bombay CONF IDENT IAL. No. C/278 Office of the Political Resident Persian Gulf, Camp Shiraz. the 14th September. 1944. Copy forv/arded with compliments to: The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Muscat. yRMB | / 4 ?/ . CONFIDENTIAL. No. 794-3 -V\ &lt; (E P'' .A\ ^Vv ' ‘ u / The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, BAiiltalN . The Iblitical Agent, ICJaAIT The Political Agent, MUSCAT and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). ^ „ , . v ^ for iniormation. — I , — . British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated, 15th October 1944 Reference to previous correspondence: ~ Receipt Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Bushire Express Letter No. 7S3-S dated 15th October 1944. * 2. Muscat letter No. C 1591 1708 dated 17th September Jr * To Bahrain and Kuwait only. 'Established Shippers' system. [944.£GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [AT. B .—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bagftlrf* To Foreirn, New Delhi, No. 793-a hated t c 16th October m 44 Reference pera 4 mph 189 of Muscat Intelligence Summary No, 14 of 1944# 2, Copy is enclosed of Muscat letter No# C. 169! dated 17th Gepter.ber 1944 in which the Political Agent has reported In detail, at ny request, on the difficulties experienced by importers under the Established 3hippers ,t systen# 3. It is hoped that n*ost of the difficulties will be removed as a result of your J&amp;xpree* Letter No# F# 91-.IS/44 dated the 2(^th August 1944, but the reoort is forwarded as it serves to siioT? ho« adversoly the existing systera has affected Gulf Ghaikhdoms• So 3d./- uDCFFRSY PRIOR Political Resident, Persian Oulf, A TWAtm Jd/- J. Croning. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. S. 6. MFP—SOI S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.Mi Ho. C. 16a1. 1708 . ' ^ Political Agency, Muscat, y y the 17th September 1944, ^ ( From To The Political Agent, Muscat , The HorMble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject :- Civil Requirements . Sir, I have the honour to refer to your telegra i No, T/418 dated the 1st September 1944 and to enclose herewith a statement showing (a) Muscat’s quota for the April - June quartet 1944 as recommended to the Government of India by the Hon*ble the Political Resident vide his telegram No. T/67 of the 18th April 1944. (b) Goods for which permits were issued as reported to the Political Agent by the Export Trade Controllers, Bombay and Karachi and which arrived at Muscat. No information of permits issued other than t lose has been received to date, and no other goods have been imported It will be seen th r t Muscat received a mere fraction of the quota recommended and only piecegoods from Bombay. 2. The specific complaints of merchants are as follows (a) Cotton oieceroods . As already reported vide my telegram No. 1201 dated the 15th July 1344, merchants cannot obtain cloth from the established shippers at controlled rates. In Bombay and Karachi the latter apparently ’‘auction' the cloth for which they have been given permits to the highest bidders through a third party. The lesser merchants therefore get no ^toare at all and this is borne out by import figures here. (b) Other :’oods . Merchants ask that permits should be issued to their nominated agents. Under the present system, and in the absence of the list of Bombay Established Shippers they cannot trace the holders of permits or are told that the full quota has been issued and no further quantity can be exported. (c) No spices were imported into Muscat during the April - June quarter and according to information received here no permit was issued for the 20 tons allotted from Karachi. One merchant applied to the Established Shippers, Jetliabhai Gokal and Lalji Lakamidas who said they had been to see the Assistant Export Trade Controller and were informed no permits were being issued. ) Further enquiries revealed that permits had been issued to some Sindi merchants, not established shippers appointed by the Government of India, and one Muscat merchant was able to obtain a small share txxxxx from them.A f t ; ie3fe T pewits has not been reported to the ^ lf3?lv » f a3C at a d in any case v»as contrar to tie estaolisned prccedure. vCk/ ’ J-ly “ heLLfc .Li^p r i.&gt;4 r h t .^ [ l)p to the Ibth August, tiie following established shippers Karachi had not received permits for the export of cotton picccioods. Jethabhai Gok^l. h r av inch and ar, i’Lndardas Valabdas. v i! P t0 ^ he J sa&gt;!!e d ate, the following established shippers haa received no permits for so a p f tillseed oil and spices. Dayalal Doulatram. Ca) Merchants say that permits for all goods in addition to ^P u3 are sold to the highest bidders as a result of wnich the saalisr traders stand little chance of obtaining a s nare. It is imposuible, of course, to check the accuracy or other wise 0 ^ all their complaints but telegrams referring to these under i nave bCQr ‘ seen by the Assistant Political Agent, and the iacus are presumably therefore correct unless the established shippers have misinformed the merchants here. tn complaints under paragraph 1 (b) above, no xist ol established shippers in Bombay has bean received in muscat und tiie j olitical Agent has asked to be supplied with this e ?f^n t f a T i ! 1 lfor ?? t v l0 ? VldQ hi3 telegram No. C/1427 of the ^lSw. August lw44, wnich has been forwarded to the Government of xndia under Bushire telegram Uo. T/356 of the 24th August, 1 - 344 . In the neanw lie t-'ie Political A^ent can only tell the merchants to try and find out for themselves in Bombay who the established shippers arc. It would be of interest to know whether permits for Muscat's J 11 ), a ox airon Bor^bay otner t-.a-i piecegoods were Issued ancx tfnora, ..ecause none of the articles wore received here. 5. Regarding the complaints that tlie established shippers procedure as also the procedure whereby permits issued by*the Export irac? Controllers are given to an; applicant, not necessarily one recom e n^ ea ^ nQ Political Agent concerned ( in practice app-rentiy never so ), it is felt that they ave every justification for dissatisfaction. . ^., lr } tbe established shippers procedure has been of benefit .o the exporters only, and has certainly not facilitated c h ,ao ^ a articles to t is importing country. It has resulted i urtnerrnore in profiteering of exnorters wiiich would not nave.een the case if per -its had been issued to arents nominated by the Political Agent. r the pri ary object was to provide supplies for the and achieve this aim as else to ensure a fair distribution .f tne quota ainongst local merchants, it would appear that the besv ana only procedure was fer permits to be issued on Political A-ent's recommendation.? &lt;i ‘ L As t.iings are, apparently any merchant can compete for Muscat’s 2^5® ?; articles for which permits are issued by the Exoort Trade Controllers, he may not necessarily have any connection*with thnt a i,« n f ?,“’??? awarewhether there is any cast - iron Guarantee tnat the g ods wij.1 be shipped to iluscot and nowhere else.From results it appears that there are loopholes for evading shipment here, but the result of enquiries as recomnended -under the last sub-para; raph of paragraph 4 should reveal the efficacy of present arrange merits. 6. Everything possible has been done this end to explain fciur to merchants exactly whom they should approach in India to obtain permits for their goods ( a detailed list item by item was pre pared recently at considerable trouble, compiled from all relevant correspondence and Commerce Department ’notifications). They remain sceptical however of successin whot they have come to consider an unequal struggle as in which they are somewhat naturally losing interest. 7. The following recommendations are forwarded for consideration (a) Permits should be issued to the agents of importers recorm ended by Political Agents and not to established shippers, PveK v/htfhvPolitical Agents have no control or influence. This would prevent profiteering and other malpractices because agents could be changed tt once. (b) Enquiries should be ix:5i±i;:&gt;Jtast instituted as to whether per mits for any articles other than piecegoods were issued for Muscat*s April - June quarter 1^44 from Bombay because none were received here. It may be noted that this position should never arise if the procedure recommended above were to be adopted. (c) It is requested that if the present M open marhet ** pro cedure for issue of permits must continue, Export Trade Controllers may telegraph to e names of exporters as and when permits are issued in view of the irregularity of mails to Muscat. In this connection please see ny telegra' No. C. 1614 of K th September 1244* (d) Export Trade Controllers apparently issue permits to persons other than the established shippers appointed by the Government of India. It is requested that they may be issued in accordance with the proper procedure. (e) On the expiry of the quarter, a certain number of articles remain for which permits have not been issued. may Export Trade Controllers telegraph details of balances Kxtxftlixtabixx outstanding asking for names of merchants to whom these should be allotted.? This will serve ns a check on issues of permits and also ensure that Muscat's balance, for instance, comes here and is not sent elsewhere. I have the honour to be, dir, Your most obedient servant, 3d. li. Bird. In the absence of Political Agent, 3 i Muscat.Gobindram P. Bhatia Telegram: GOBINDRAM BHATIA \* v &lt;^ Mif&amp;.xahaxLxtimrt. II .B «M V 3 Political A^ent Dated 7 tn October 1944. / j/ji Bahrain. Sir f Hef:» My quota for July/ September for Hoisery , Mac Haberdasher and Provisions. I have receibed a letter^from my shipper/which I enclose herein in original^or year honours kind attention^cnd be* to request your honout y to kindly recommend for the above quota to enable me to import the same into Bahrain. you For this act of kindness I shall remain grateful to Kindly retun the original letter of my shipper when dene with Thanking you in anticpation. I beg to remain, 3 ir, Yours most obedient servai Bahrain Receipt Date No( enclosure to above ) 44 ^ From Rewachand P, Babiani, B/5 Snikapuri Market, Karachi. To Messrs. Gobindram p. Biiatia, Bail rain. Dear Sir, ft Ref:- Ju^ Sept quarter quota for Hosiery and Haberaasiiery a n d Provisions. „ , ^ith reference to the above quota sent by you ve xorvvaraea the papers to the Foreign Import Trade Control er KcircCni ana were Baking enquiries every week, and at la t &gt; zoaaj we are inlormed verbally txiat tney have not received any recommendation letter from ttie Political Agent, Bahrain ana hence cney will not issue any quota for thl above quarter ana instead of this (as tae, have not received any Idvice from shippers?^ V ' lii ® iVe tuiS ^ U£rterfs quota oaxy to established V,e may request you to please see the Political A^ent £T?£ iy &lt; h llS respect and sead the telegraphically advice to the foreign Export Trade Controller, Karachi to issue us Sue quota for the above quarter. After doing the aoove neeaful please inform us al&lt;?o so as to enable us to see the Export Controller here? Treat this as most urgent. Yours faithfully, oh. Rewachund p. Babiani.COPY Bombay 17th August, 1044 The Export Trade Controller, Nevv Customs House Bombay Dear Sir, Re. Export of Black Pepper. We have received a letter from our customer Messrs Haridas Janimal and Sons of Bahrain, placing an order with us for three tons of black pepper. The said order form seems to have been sanctioned by the Food Controller of Bahrain as a grant of quota to the said merchant, under Licence Ho. 536/63 of 8th July 1644 entitling tne said merchant to import from Bombay tne said quantity of the said stuff and also it has been countersigned by tne Boxitical Agent of Bahrain. We are enclosing a copy of tne same for your Kind reference. The said merchant, in his letter, further says that in tne event of his not being able to import tne same from Bombay, tne Banrain authorities will not consider their name for future allotments of such quotas. Moreover, he emphasises that on the basis of such quota granted by the aufchotities of Bahrain to the merchants, ail others are getting the goods from Bombay, and. subsequently show his surprise as to why we i.e. Messrs Ramchand Metnaram &amp; Co. of Bombay, are not being allowed to snip sucn goods as mutualxy agreed to • by both the authorities concerned viz the Government of India and the authorities of Banrain. We therefore feel greatly perturbed as regards our position in tne eye of our consignees and have to request you to take the matter into consideration and do txie needful so as to enable us to ship tne above goods for wnicn we shall feei much obliged to you. Sd G.V, Amernani. Manager, for Ramchand Metnaram Jc Co. Returned. Under the existing orders export of Black Pepper is prohibited. Sd lilibie. Export Trade Controller, Bombay. 29/8tr l? 0 &amp; Its S' EXPRESS LETTER Prom To Political, Bahrain. Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Foreign, Nevt Delhi. No. c/jfJ Dataithe Sth November 1944 Subject! Bahrain quotas from India. Reference External Affairs Department Express Letter No. F.91-ME/44, dated the 26th August 1944. It is not understood what particular advantage v*ill bo derived from the system proposed in paragraph one of the Express Letter under reference. It has taken some time for the present system to aork moderately smoothcly (oven now the Export Trade Controllers do not seem to have fully gras ped the fact that quota goods for which license is issued ±m arc not prohibited from export) and it is feared that any change will only serve to put the clock back six months. 2. Bahrain already furnishes lists of importers and provided the Government of India can issue lists of estab lished shippers slightly before the beginning of a now quar ter there is no reason why any delay in obtaining quotas should occur. With the proposed system delay will be caused before agreement can bo reached between the Agencies and the export authorities in India over the nomination of shippers by virtue of their alia re in trade in 1941-42 as many impor ters in Bahrain have to bo catered for whose normal source r of supply of certain articles has boon closed by war condi tions and who are n&lt;w forced to obtain those articles in bulk from India for the first time. For this reason shares of quotas in Bahrain are allotod on the basis of trade over the three years preceding the war. 3. • It is felt that much time will bo wasted and much misunderstanding and delay will occur over the selection of- ^ 2 local ’•approvod oxportora' and tJio Govcmmcnt of India's 'approved exporter** and it is feared that whole quarters will slip by without the issue of licences and arrival of the goods* 4* Although the present system has its disadvantage in placing too much power in the hands of the exporters in India who have profiteered over invoice prices and who have been slow in shipping such quotas as are allotted to them, until such time ns the Government of India can permit the appointment of exporters in India by the political Agencies f if 4 who can thereby ensure the shipment from India of such quotas as arc granted, it is felt that no change is desirable* 5* I am answering the points raised in paragraph 3(b) of the Exprosn Letter under reference which deals exclusively with Sharjah in a separate memorandum* /C POLITICAL AGTTKfT, BAH^ IK* . \ . ■ I ’•No. PA/FC/ * H.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain 0 Memorandu m:- who OFFICE OF m THE FOOD CONTROLLER, BAHRAIN, 7th November, 194-4*, Reference attached quota for 5 tons Bran against July/Sentember quota, refused on the grounds that no further allotment was available for Bahrain, in the respective quarter, the facts of the case are as under, and I shall be grateful if these can be brought to the notice of the Export Trade^Controller Karachi, with a view to his reconsidering his decision granting the release of July/September quota. Ref. my FC/16/63 of 18th January 1944 - Hajy Abdul aziz^Ali al Bassam was given a quota of 45 tons Bran; which quantity was^shipped in August to Bahrain. Controller 45 tons for It is therefore apparent that the Export Trade considers this as fulfilling Bahrain's allotment of July/September, ref.your C/907 of 11th June, 1944.&gt; 4 r ■^StafeancAana &gt;Slatani. banker, pearl merchant &amp; commission agent. Head Office: Hiranand Versimal, Banker, pearl Merchant and commission Agent, KHOK1 GARDEN. KARACHI. Telegrams:- “ BABULAL BAHRAIN. 12th July 1944 ( P. GULF. ) To Messrs HiranaAd Versimal, | ; Karachi• Dear Sirs, We are alloted the under-noted quatas as per Pood Controller^ letter Mo* PC/538/63, dated the 8th July, 1944, for the quarter July / September 1944* We will be obliged if you kindly arrange tfu to ship the same at your earliest convenience* Thanking yo*, Yours faithfully iiattanchand Dipcitand ran 5 tons * CER j. II • lED v/-'. oil In quota- ‘July/Seotemberj—1944 f*ri ,'Tf iPPUCiTlOK FOR LICBSSE TO EXPORT A OONTROUED ARTICLE , 4 ? Name of applicant Postal Address ORIGINAL- /s -(To accompany shipment). ^ - wo/;,'- KaracU^ ....f.*^, r7 ■.....: Dated.... A S.?.yrr. A ie undersigned hereby makes application for.a hcerise to export the under- entioned goods ^PEl^he port 0 ^ ^ aiac ^.^in respect of which the information by port furnished herein is certified to be true and corrected:— (1) Nature and quantity of goods....t/ •. V m (2) Name and address of consignee* (3) Name'and address of ultimate purchaser (is other than consignee and if. known) as above (4) Name of ship (if known) (5) Port at which gds will be unloaded (if know 4 i)....r (6) Route which goods are to follow (if known and if not a continuous voyage) Direct i? To. T &gt; ^isnatlu Customs House, Karachi. ? / : i-_—.— atiU£,of Applicant (All the entries below this line to be left blank by applicant.) /'N LICENSE. License No .granted for export of goods as above. (State here amount to be exported) Date Export Trade Controllerii'XPabko jjbli'ijd, r From H.B.M* 3. Political A^tnt, Baarain. To The Export Trade Controj-xer, Karacai. No. C/1675 DS-ted the 2£ad November, 1^44. ftefarence ^oar express xetter No. C/t&gt;40/ETC dated the 14tn October, 1^44. 2. Please see flty express letter No. C/7bd dated the 15th May, la44. 5. The Government of India xiave informed me that under the revised procedure, detailed programmes need no longer be furnished b./ ma, and I have therefore discontinued sending them. 4. I v«ould be grateful if you couid let me have details of what quota surpluses are available so that I could arrange to furnish you with the names of the snippers and consignees who will handle tne amounts. ///• pjh ] \ H.B.M 1 5. Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. ® j'n AT. B. This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, a-nt bj post to snve telegraphic use of the wires, but iLtendod to be treated, oa receipt, with the si AJL, K,J r ^v vw I but iLtendod to be treated, oa receipt, with the same expedition a? if « i an s.1 J lif^rao if la Trrrirr^ r*» ] n rn i Alrmo i ftS if l! EXPRESS LETTER WESJAGE, «»nt by post to save Ulogrsphic expeosp nod ondne lio** i/1 l/Ue? W lv \s'&gt;9p va*» 9 4 •« * ,, • JJ J* ^ it. had beefc telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and sign had been so despatched. Reference External Affairs Department letter No. F. 3(101)-ME/44 dated the 13th of October 1944. 2. Grateful if the Ministry of Food can be asked to approve an annual quota of eighty tons of black pepper for Bahrain and twentyfour tons for the Trucial COdSt from India. Our pepper supplies are getting very low No. c/1682 To The Hon*ble the Political Resi in the Persian Gulff Bushire. Dated Bahrain and the situation Political Agent, Bahrain, MFP—82T&amp;&amp;P—Sr 1 **—&lt;ai-12f»9&gt;- ?Ho. C/1685 Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 23rd November, 1^44 From Major T. HiCKinbotham, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Foreign Trade Controller, Karachi. Sir, I have the honour to enclose for your information a copy of a letter whicn I have received from Gobindra* p. Bhatia with in Government of India External Affairs Department letter No. D.5058-N/44 dated the 22nd May ld44 detailed programmes were discontinued. I shall therefore be grateful*if you wlfl grant the quotas in accordance with the countersigned import permits with which the merchants have been furnished# instructions contained I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. % H.B.M 1 s. Political Agent, Bahrain NCJ pNo.C/1684 political Agency, Bahrain, 23rd November 1944. From Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E*, O.B*E., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Foreign Trade Controller, Karachi# Sir, I have the honour to bring/to your notice the enclosed correspondence regarding your refusal to permit the export of five tons of bran by Messrs. Hiranand Versimal to Messrs. Ratanchand Dipchand &amp; company of Bahrain on the grounds that no further allotment was available for Bahrain. I shall be grateful if export permits can be granted for the full quota for each quarter irrespective of whether or not it has been found practicable to export the quota during the quarter for which it was granted. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahrain.KEGIalEHED AIR MAIL lo. C. 640/EXC X« ^ - n %&gt; (oa ^ w Th# Political Agent, Bahrain Cuatoa House Karachi Dated 11. 11. 1244 Sir, v In coAtinuation of this office letter ef even No. dated 17,10.44 I have the honour to enclose a statement showing the surpluses available against the various commodities provided for in the Civil Requirement / Programme for export to Bahrain during the quarter July/ September 1244. As the distribution of these surpluses is long overdue, X woUld request you kindly to forward your recommendations at a very early date. The names of two evacuee firms vix. Messrs. Jethmal Parsram and Messrs, hilar am Shewaram may also be considered in your recommendation. \ \ , f I have the honour to be, Sir, four most obedient servant, No. C/1725. M.J. , c 'V:. ^ For Export Trade Controller. ^ P0LITI0Afe&lt;^fiENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated December 1944. copy forwarded to the Director of Customs, Bahrain, with the request that the information required may^furnished early.No. C/ /70t Political Agency, Bahrain, 29th November 1944 To The Foreign Trade Controller Karachi. MEMORANDUM Reference your letter No.52/8218 dated the 15th of November 1944 addressed to Messrs. Ravji Jhaverchand &amp; Company, Karachi. 2. A quota of 270 tons bran was allotted by the Government of India to Bahrain for the quarter October to December 1944. Messrs, Haridas Janimal &amp; Sons of Bahrain, for whom Messrs. Ravji Jhaverchand &amp; Company act as agents, were allotted a quota for the import of 50 tons. The application was duly countersigned by this Agency and I shall therefore be glad to know why you 3. Five tons of soap vrere allotted by the Government of India as the Bahrain quota for October to December 1944 and six tons for the Saudi Arabian quota via Bahrain for the same period. Messrs. Haridas Janimal dc Sons of Bahrain v/ere allotted one ton of the Bahrain qhota and one ton of the Saudi Arabian quota of the washing soap by me and I am Informed that his application was duly countersigned by this Agency. I shill be glad to know why you have refused to issue export permits. 4. The Government of India granted a quota of 14 tons of vege table oil for the last quarter of 1944 to Bahrain and Messrs. Haridas Janimal &amp; Sons were allotted 3 tons of this quota and duly made application to you for an export permit. I shall be glad to \ know on what grounds the export permit was refused. Copy for information to Messrs. Haridas Janimal &amp; Cons, Bahrain, with reference to their letter dated the 27th November 1944. have refused to issue an export permit \; \ Political Agent, BahrainNO, C/ /76r T Political Agency, Bahrain, 29th November 1944 To The Export Trade Controller New Custom House, Bombay* MEMORANDUM Reference your notice No.War 505 dated the 3rd November 1943 and your endorsement on an application for an export permit for turmeric and cardomoms dated the 6 th of November 1944 from Messrs. Ramchand Metharam &amp; Company, the agents of Messrs. Haridas Janimal and Sons of Bahrain. 2 . I shall be glad if you will inform me from what date the Government of India have prohibited the export of turmeiic and what spices may be exported provided shipping space has been allotted under the Civil Requirements programme and importers into Bahrain produce orders countersigned by this Agency. Copy for information to Messrs. Haridas Janimal &amp; Sons, Bahrain, with reference to their letter dated the 27th November 1944. Political Agent, Bahrain.Copy of letter f^’om the Assistant Foreign Trade Controller , Customs House Karachi, to M/s. Ha j i Jethabhai Gokal, Khori Garden ,Kara chi No*32/8221 dated 20.11.1944. Acknowledges receipt of your letter dated 7.11.1944 0 No licence for the export of vegetable oil to Bahrein can be granted to you. As regards export of Provision, your claim for the t grant of quota will be considered at the end of the quarter on receipt of recommendatIons from the Political Agent, Bahrein. sd/- Assistant Foreign Trade Controller,,W- TAYEB KHONJI &amp; SONS- ^ BAHRAIN 19th December 1944 H.D.^’s political Bahr^- in. iv; D^ar Sir: Refc 1st paragraph 'Llinute of the Merchants advisory lom^ittee ivieeting held at the ^g’-ncy n nday^ the 4th Dec^^ber 1944” and my verbal conversation with yo of the 18th instant. J H rr, pending you herewith the under mentioned quotas together with the letters of the shippers. F3/329/63 dated 2?nd May 1944 FC/538/63 ' 8th July l q/ M Shippers Haji Mohamed Tahir Khoonji says In his'letter herewith that he applied to the Bombay Controller and latern on returned the quotas to us saying that he cannot get licence. PC/719/63 dated 9th Oct. 1944 Shippers Ali Jamal Khonji says in his letter herewith advising us that he applied + o the controller who has returned the same to a* in turn he is returning the same to us. I beg to point out to you that the validity must be outstanding with the Foreign Trade Controller., Bombay, and therefore requesting you to kindly favour me with a fresh quota for all the above named quotas to be shipped during the first ouarter of 1945. of the above named quotas, has been expired and the tonnage Thanking you in anticipation y? *'7 t r /^ 4 ?IDear Sirs, This la to Infora you that y:u are allotted* tone of Piece Gooil« ai» your Quota for the QUArt^r Apr i±/wurie ,1^44, to be imported from Bombay through your Ag?nt POOD CONrHOLLKR*HAJI MOHAMED TAHIR H- MD. JAFAR KHUNJI MAHBOOB BUILDING- B- BLOCK- PALTON ROAD ROOM NO 5 fort. BOMBAY j 1199 : ^ t &lt;Jr*r vO‘ «JL K.~ j4~ J' Bombay 26th Sept* 1944 To, The Ifixport Trade Controller Bombay* V'? V Dear Sir, This to invite Your Honour kind and urgent attention towards the fatt that I am in receipt of a letter from my agent Mohamed Tayeb Khunji &amp; Sons, Bahrein stating that the Political Agent has fixed the quota of 10 ten tons of Vegetable Ghee from Bombay to Bahreijj. So I /beg before Your Honour to take this matter under consideration and favour me with the above said quota as early as possible* Hoping to be excused for the trouble thus given and a favourable reply is soon expected* Thanking Your Honour in an anticipation. NoB* The Political Agent letter is herewith attached, please return carefully after done with* Yours faithfully. , Cir-v &gt;4 - Ha ^ * ll0m0d f '•V 4? */&gt; ^^ ist i. &lt;rt ' C 'Letter cikteo 1st December l!d44, from Haji Janmi-i Khunji, Bombay, to Haji Mohammad Tayeb bin Haji Mohammad JafanKhunji, Bahrain. A.C. I wrote a letter to you on the 6th Inst(Arabic) and Ha&amp;taK*. note that it reache® you and you understood the contents of it. Your letter of the 3rd written from Bahrain reached here on the 7th. I am gla® to Know what you have mentioned in it. The letter of the 22nd Dhulgada has not reacned me yet. Hope it wixi arrive. A draft No.64 date® 22nd, Dhuigaca in the name of Haji Mohammed an® Abdullah Haji Yusuf Khuri for as. 7^01/6/^ has been receive®. As regards pearls, what you consi®er will be the least. The quota which was entered in the Control Office has been returned. The sai® quota is No. 71^/63 F.C. written on the 9th October, 3 944, an® 'it is herewith returned. Please acKnowledge re ceipt. 7 bales piece goods have been sent two days bacK to .the jetty for shipment to Dubai by a country craft. Tne boat is expecte® to sail soon. The market of piece goods has not improved. All goods that are wanted are not available U.C.* /'N Letter «Lite« 24tL Dlnuibaj, 1563 from H&amp;ji Mohamme# Taher bln Haji l(K&gt;haiiima«t Jafar Kbunji to Haji Bohamna* Tayeb bin Mobamma* Jafar Kbunji &amp; Sons, A.C. The thing I want to know from you is the news of your goo«i health. jf you enquire about us, the reply is that we are aoing well. The thing that counts is the separation.. Two ciays ago I wrote a letter to you anti hope it has reache* you by now. ' I explained everytning in that letter. Your letter of the 16th Dhuibaj reache* me on the 22nci. I am glaa to hear that you are quite well. As regards the account I have alrea*y sent them. After sending 26 bales, if /$ possible, I will sen® more. I have not foregotten... I hope it will reach you. please acKnowltage receipt. I will sen* the other gooes when I get them. Please remain content. My compliments to the members of the family. U-C.jATJlMiLu &amp; bOi'Jb BiiHRAlW. To H.B.M’s Poxiticsx Agent, Bahr* in. Respectei Sir, We beg to submit thkt tAe following commotlities kre -i-ying purchasea at Veraval (India) on our account and its export to Bahrain is not bemg allowed by the authorities there unless produce the import licence from your honor:- 1000 bags grounanuts 1000 tins grounanut oil * 100 cases matches. ' Under the circumstances we shall feel highly obliged if jew yiiur honour will be pleased to issue in our name the import licence of the above commodities to be imported into Bahrain from Veraval. For this act of kindness, we shaxi evex remain grateful. We beg to remain etc., Sa/- (*&lt;- ;? Vh bJo &lt;y/ e n'r f At H ti-'w _— p. 7&lt;tctR 3 “/HiSUiv Tele A d dr ess '—M A K L A I’ ! * L-i-yu qJ . y&lt; ls*' ABDUL GANI MAKLA ^oosuf ffiaii J^-asham J/ftaKiai. GBNBJRALi MKRCHANT &amp; COMMISSION AGENT. ^^’ agg ^ rg yp--.. 5l^.) Bahrein, dated, 24th 0eember (P. GULF.,) im H* *i}.ms^Political Agent Biii H/iIh. Sir i»e most humbly an^ respectfully beg'^'to state follow 5 ; — 1. That we applied to the Directer of Customs for Permit of 200 B/s Cotton fly from Veravai as per telegraphic request of our \/eraval office (the copy of the letter enclosed herewith) and we have received the verbal reply that there is already plenty of c#tt#n fly in Bahrain. 2. That we may drwf6 your kind attention that r^sr our trade in this line is very old in Bahrain and if others have got and Lve have nothing our old customers willbe displeased^ 3. That there are other light commodities whieh are to be shipped and this cotton is required special^yto give the weight to the boat» 1 1 4. my we request your honour to kindly allow us permit f'vr the above mentioned 200 Bals of cotton fly for import in Bahrain, * Thanking you Anticipation and beg to remain dear Sir r* Yours Obediently t (U.ju ' for H.M.H.H.Makly ## r&gt; A© &amp;&amp; No. C/1923. To MEMORANDUM. BAHRAIN. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 27th December 1944. Reference your letter dated 19th December 1944. 2. Mr. Haji Janmal Khunj^s -letter of the 1st December states that Import permit No. 719/63 F.C. has been returned from the Control Office. You should ask your correspondent to indicate clearly if the export of the goods was refused and if so on what grounds. The letter from Haji Mohammed Taher bin Haji Mohammad .Tafar Khunji makes no reference to the withholding of any permits rather it indicates that ex port permits are being issued. &gt; POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMS■^o • C/2U. PGiil'IIGliu 6 tn January 1J45. To Messrs. Hariuas Janimal &amp; Sons, SAhRAJil. Reference your letters aatect 18th December 1844. and 22nd 2. It is regretted that it is not possible for me to grant more than has already been axlotted by the Director of Customs, Bahrain. t\ P■§ -o'7- POijIi’iCAu 8AdttKli^.3Y WB MAI Ii« From, EXPRESS LETTER. The Export Trade Controller, Custom House, Karachi. To, No.S.2/8221 The Political Agent,. Bahrein. Custom House, Karachi, 26th December 1944. ^ r- l-l ■ Reference your Express letter No.C/1768 dAted I 4 .12.1944. 2 . A quota of 7 tons for export of Vegetable Oil to Bahrein was allotted by the Government of India for the quarter October/December 1944 . This quantity was distributed prorata among the two established shippers viz. Ravji Javerchand and Dharamdas Thawerdas, the former getting a share of 30 Cwts 13 lbs and, the latter the balance. As Haji Jethabhai Gokal are not established shippers for export of goods in question to Bahrein and as no surplus was avail- -able, no licence could be issued to them. KJK For Export Trade Controller.(JY* 9 ' I H.B.L^s Politicel. Agent, Bahrein* Memorandum (55 ) YHE CUSTOMHOUSE; BAHRAIN: 2nd January, 1945^., © .73 / With reference to my No*PA/15 of 20 th December. 1944. I enclose herewith twelve orders for surplus from Karachi for favour of your countersignature and return. DIREC TOR OF CUSTOMS nm PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN, Enclos—From To The Export Trade Controller, Bonbay. / ^Cj\ ^ The Political Agent, Bahrein. \ / New Custom House, S.Ho. 1-10925/44W v &lt;^ Bombay, j 194^7 Reference your memorandum No.C.1705/ dated 29.11.44 regarding export of turmeric and cardamoms by Messrs.Ramchand Metharam &amp; Co. The prohibition on export of turmeric came into force from 10.5.43. Export of the following varieties of spices only are permissiMd under the existing orders of the Government of India subject to quota restrictions. 1. Betelnuts. 2. Chillies. 3. Cardamoms. A ^ 7 ^ ^ L H.c- 5Export n . 1 rade Controller. ^ 7 \ 2 _ -POliIilCAjj No. C/57 lltn Jitnuary ly4o To Tne Export Tr&amp;ae Controller BO ME AY • Sir L\ Reference your letter No.b.No.1-I8d25/ 44W, dated tne 2na January 1 j45. 2. For Octo»er/Decem«er U44 a quota of one ton caruamoms was allotted to Messrs. Haridas Janimal &amp; Sons, for whom Messrs. Ramchand Metharam &amp; Co., act as agents. in the letter unaer reference you have stated that the export cardaaoms is permissible. I snail §e grateful if an export permit can toe issued for carnamoms only. I have tne honour to is Sir Your most obedient servant EO-uIIIOau AUhA'I BAtuvAlNBattrain J.l-1-45. Bear Bir ^ Poxitical Agent Bahrain Reference Civil Requiremente Progranmie quotas of tne ana 4th quarters of 1944, iron India, We had been aliotea in the aoovementioned programme quotas as ^er attacnea xetters, recei'w -ed by us from the Birector of Customs, wilx show. Accordingly, we placea our orders,with our respective shippers , alter duly certified by the Birector of Customs ana counter-signed by your ggodself. Our Karachi Agents inform us tnat they were told by tne Foreign export Tr&amp;ae Controlxex during a personal interview, tnat he haa not received the recpmmenaation from tne po-Litical Agent Bahrain, as he haa in all the other cases, on the merit of which the others were issued the requisite export licences. Hence, we shall feel highly obligee if you Ainaiy inform the Foreign export Trade Controller accordingly, in order to enable us 1 get the requisite export permits. Thanking you in anticipation^ Yours faithfully\ t a IbaMk 1 Bahrain 21-1-45. ■ The Political Agent,^ Bahrain, Dear dir, Hefereace the quotas ailoted to us as per enclosed papers, lor the quarter of October/December, 1944. The enclosed letter of the Assistant Export ?rade Controller, states that Messrs Vasdev Khubchand, are not established shippers. Hence we shall feel highly obliged if you kindly alter the abovementionea name from the attached quotas and insert the name of Messrs Motamal Pahelajrai, our old snippers* , instaad. Kindly also iniorm the Karachi Export Trade Control authorities, regarding this alteration in tne name of our shippers. Thanking you in anticipation, Yours obediently. /&gt; yn India Service Pest Card. iThis side reserved for address, with signature and official designation of sender ) Vi Save paper and help to win the war- Every scrap is needed for vital muni tions. H * \[ (\ fxXAiwryv \ . y3 ^15 / 0 BY AIRM AIL. No.S.2/3218 Custom House, Karachi, 22nd December 1944 © To The Political Agent, Political Agency Bahrein. letter No.C.1684 dated 23•11.1944 and Memorandum No.C.iVOS-'aated 29.11.1944. only be allowed if covered by permits issued by the Government of India, Department of Food, New Delhi. The quote of 270 tons Bran allotted for the quarter October/December 1944 was accordingly distributed to two shippers viz. Messrs.Laljee Lakhmidas and Messrs. Fahad Marzook, Karachi. Under specific instructions from that Depart- -ment. As no quotas for the goods in question were allotted to Messrs. Ravji Jhaverchand and Messrs.Hiranand Versimal, Karachi, no licences could be issued to them. \ 3. A quota of 4 tons (and not 5 tons as started by you) for export of soap to Bahrein has been allotted for the quarter ending December 1944* Messrs.Ravji Jhaverchand who are established shippers have been issued a licence for Cwts representing their quota for the above quarter. The question of allotting them some quota from the surplus if any v/ill be considered after the expiry of the current quarter when the surplus quantity will be communicated to you for your recommendation. 4. The quantity of 7 tons of Vegetable Oil (and not 14 tons as stated by you) allotted for export to Bahrein for the current quarter was distributed prorata among the two established shippers viz Messrs.Ravji Jhaverchand and Messrs.Dharamdas Thawerdas, the. former getting a share of 30 Cwts and 13 lbs and the latter the balance. 5 . The export of soap to Saudi Arabia is covered by the Middle East Co-ordination Scheme and the application from Messrs.Ravji Jhaver- -chand, Karachi, covered by a valid import licence issued by the , Middle East rhwill ^be referred to the Chief Con- -tro.ller of Exports, New Delhi, for orders. Export T^ade Controller. KJK© &amp; (f ft.*' No;FC/ S. MULJEE, a eo-a*«*ooer BAHRAHJe THE 8 th CUSTOMHOUSE; BAHRAIN July, 1944 d , Dear Sirs, This is to inform you that you are allotted the under-noted quotas for quarter July/September, 1944. Will you please note that in the event of your no importing the goods as per quota granted, your name will not be considered for further quotas, unless you can prove that it was through no fault of yourse CQLIIODITY QUANTITY IN TONS: CONSIGNOR PORT OF LOADING, Piece Goods Hosiery &amp; Haberdashery s Motamal Pahelajrai 2 do Karachi ULtkciot u; n' ’ ' X ui't 0 /, 1 n1 To Karachi, T8th January 1945* .. /fr^ 7 ^ eg) ' Political Agency, \ Bahrein. Reference your letter No. C.1683 dated 23«li«i944‘ 2 . A quota of 6 tons each for export to Bahrein of Hosiery and ^Provision was allotted under the Civil Requirement Programme for the quarter J ^ulyVSeptember 1944* As Messrs.Rewachand P.Bablani are not establi shed shippers for the exp ort of t':. x.s in question, their application Tdr licenceg cquldino L t De^- entertainec and-rro licences were therefore issued to then! 3 . The surplus quantities of 113 Cwts-54 ^ 1 ° s i n respect of Hosiery remaining after alloting the due quotas to the regular established shippers and 6 tons in respect of Provisions (as no quota has so far been established by any shipper at this port) were intimated to you for your recommendations vice this office letter No.C.640-ETC dated 11.11.1944- The licences as per details given below were issued to the parties concerned on receipt of your letter No.C.1913 dated 21.12.1944* Cwt Lbs. Hosiery. 1) Mesbrs.Yousafali Alibhoy Karimji &amp; Co,Karachi. » Visumal Pamanmal. 60 0 M \ Sind Sports Depot. 23—54 113—54 Provision. Messrs.Abdul Kayoon Lokmani. T ’ Haji Suleman Adam Kothari. 3 Tons 3 ' 6 Tons As the name of Messrs.Rewachand.P.Bablani was not recommended by you, no licence could be issued to them even against surplus quota. 4 . There appears to be some misunderstanding regarding the issue of licences to the shippers recommended by you. Such recommendations are of 2 kinds viz. (1) Recommendation to individual importer at your end 'entitling him to get the specified quantities exported by the shippers at this place and ( 2 )- General recommendations made by you for distribution of surpluses communicated t 6 “y.ou by this office at the close of each quarter. The practice sc far adopt- -ed by this office in respect of ( 1 ) above is to issue licences only if the shippers holding such recommendations are established shippers at this port; failing which no allotments are made against such recommendations. As for (2) the licences are issued in accordance with the recommendations made by you. You will doubtless agree that the issue of licences based on recommendations . in favour of individual shippers who either do not come in the category of established shippers or the quantity recommended for ’whom i^ greater than the 1 share to which they are entitled as established shippers would be undesirable I the following obvious reasons:- (i) If all the recommended shippers are given their full share straight- -away when established shippers do not apply sufficiently in advance, there may be no balance available for allotment to the latter. According to the existing oraers, established shippers can apply even up to the last day of the quarter. J (ii) Shippers recommended by you individually who may come first will be ! * first served i.e. they will get their full recommended quantities while the late-comers though recommended by you may not get the entire recommended quantity if the sanctioned quantity has been fully utilised already (either partly or fully) by established shippers or others shippers recommendech by you. ^ With a view to ensure equitable distribution of the available surpluses during a particular quarter to all shippers recommended by you and ? to avoid complaints of this nature, I suggest that a consolidated list of recommendations for the issue of licences may be forwarded to this Department', immediately on receipt by you of the statement of the'particulars of surpluses available forwarded by this Department after tne close of each quarter. l |JNo. C/Iod t'O-uli ICiuj BiihtthlN. 27tn January 1^45 To The Director of Customs, Banrain. It has seen srou^ht to my notice *y some of the merchants in Bahrain that they are not obtaining the quota of goods allotted to them, though they hold licences for the import of tne same into Bahrain. 2. The reason apparently is that merchants do not place their orders with estasrished shippers. They may »e instructed that they shoiiid contact Export Trade Controixers to discover who has seen granted export permits for tne particular commodity they are interested in and place orders accordingly. PQ-uITICju* aGENT, HahiUilN.I @ ' ® tit . No.C/140. Political Agency, Bahrain, 27th January 1945. To The ®tpoft Trad. Controllor, Karachi. MEMORANDUM It is our practice to divide quotas granted by the ' / /'V Government of India among the established shippers in Bahrain and to issue to each individual merchant certificates specifying the quantity of goods that has been allotted to him. I have recently received complaints to the effect that the established exporters appointed by you in Karachi have preferred not to deal with established importers approved by me here in Bahrain. In order to avoid mis understanding and to ensure that those with the clearest right to trade are not in any way impeded I suggest that I should send you a list of established importers in Bahrain for each commodity and that established exporters in Karachi should be required to export only to these persons. . c /% Political Agent, Bahrain. /&gt; !i r-'N 114 Wo. C/146. To Hr. S.. Muijee, Bahrain. a AW DU M. ^UiilTiCiiL Aiiih\iUx B^hruiiW. 2dth January 1^40. Reference your letter detect the 20th January 1^45. It# is regretted that no assistance can ®e given where export quotas have •een arxotted *y the Export Trade Comtroixer. Steps are teeing taAen to ensure that front 1045 more consideration wiAi tee shown to holders of Bahrain import permits. Ban tvAliM • iUlBNo. C/147 POxiillUai. iiiki UAIN • 30th January 1 j45 To Messrs Go»inuram P. Bhatia, Bahrain. Reference your letter dated the 7th October 1^44. 2 The Export Trace Controller, Karachi have now informed me that as Messrs Rewachana P.Ba»iani are not an established shippers for the export of the ^oocLs in Question and as no surplus was available no licence could be issued. in future, it would be adviseabae for you to contact Export Trade Controllers to discover who has been granted export permits for the pai*ticuxar commodity you are interested in ana to place your orders accordingly. ' POuITlCiuj aiihhTj BamuiIN.Heceived under Government of India Endorsement No.D. 12545 -vAT' W/44 dated 20th December, 1944. EXP,;ES5 bETTEK . T° ^ \ The Export Trade Controller, v ^ Madras/Bombay. No. L-360(49) New Delhi, the 14th/l6th December, 1944. Subjects- Export of cardamons. Government of India have decided that, in addition to the usual quota, an additional quota of 250 tons of cardamons should be permitted immediately for export by established shippers to all permissible destinations. Out of this quantity 150 tons will be shipped from Madras and 100 tons from Bombay. The quota need not be distributed pro rata to permissible destinations on the basis to established shippers only on the basis of the sales evidence produced by them, the object being to secure export of the whole quota before the end of March, 1945. 2. The quantity for which applications are received and the quantity actually licensed for export for each destination should be reported to this Department as soon as possible. Sd/- S.K. Sen, Assistant Secretary to the Govt .of India. CONFIDENTIA L 82-S British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire Dated the 19th January 1945 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, MUSCAT. i * PUtiGHJttT. No, C/151. BiiiitiAlN. 31st January 1^45 To MiJIOUiiNUJM. I The Director of Customs, Bahrain. I 1 ^ v 1 / I have been informeu tnat the' export of a certain quantity of cardamoms is »eing permitted from Bom*ay ana Madras, up to the ena of March 1^45, in adaition to the usual quota. Applications from merchants who may aesire to import cardamoms should be submitted to this Agency with alx aue expedition. / KMd PUaliiCiOj AUiaiM 1 ^ i&gt;Ad.t\AXB&lt;I Tele Add ’- ABDULREHMAN ALGOSAIBI Pearl Merchant Importer, Exporter &amp; Commission A^ent E AMIR AIM. Codes:- BENTLEY. Q lo. BAHRAIN DATED 19 ^5 H.is.M’s i’olltioal Agent. Jbahrain. near iiir: Ker* our attached countersigned order dated the 14th Octooer 1944, we regret to point out to you that Messrs Mulhim A1 Mulhin are not extaoiished shippers so we have now made out the same on Messrs Haji Saleh Audulla nassam &amp; (Jo., who are established shippers and requesting you to kindly contersign the order and return please. Thanking you in anticipation. lours faithfullyI Tele Add. Afeditnlrelhimsum H o \^-9&lt; ABDULREHMAN ALGOSAIBI Pearl Merchant Importer, Exporter &amp; Commission Agent BENTLEY. BAHR. AIM BAHRAIN 314. Ql DATED 14th Octo'be r 1944 Messrs Mulhim A1 Mulhin Bombay. Dear Sirs: We would request you to try your best to ship the under mentioned goocis as soon as you can and thanking you for the same, ORDER Ref. allottment of q^uota received . from Director of Customs, Bahrain, under his No.FC/719/63 attached herewith in original. TO BE SHIPPED TO SAUDI ARABI A Vi&lt;L 1 Ton Turmeric 1 Ton C&amp;rdemoms 1 Ton Black Pepper 1 Ton Twine 1 Ton Senna Leaves 1 Ton Leadore Mark '* A . R . Gr “ CERTIFIED within quota October/December, 1944 # BAHRAIN IN TRANSIT SAUDI ARABIA Youths +.hf*nl iy (i ; fi. B. M's. PtiKIcalAgent. BttfirtitH.( r.sM/ii »! SNo.1-18925/44W. *V 5 “ (13) New Custom House, _ Bombay, 3/5/' January 1945, From. To The Export Trade Controller, Bombay. The Political Agent, Bahrein. With reference to your letter No.C57 dated 11 .1.45, I have the honour to state that an export permit for 15 cwts. Cardamoms was already issued as a special case from the available balance quota to Messrs.Ramchand Metharam and Co. on 2.10.44. I may add for yourinformation that the exporter is not an established^jshipper of Spices for this destination and ordinarily aaaeT quota can be granted to him. F. 1 -&gt;Y |Export^ Trade Controller.I } (S) &lt;@&gt;@&gt; No. c/mi. To i3iul ttAl-U • 11 til February lij45 I ■ ■! p cf Messrs. Haridas Janimai &amp; Sons, Bahrain. MbMutUiauuM. Reference n^- memoranaum No. C/137, dated the 27th January ij45. 2. The Export Trace Controj-ier, Bcniway have now informed me that an export £&gt;ei*mit for 15 cwts. cardamoms has been issueu as a special case to Messrs. Ramchand Metharam &amp; Co., on 2-i0- f 44, in spite of the fact that tney are not established shippers of spices for Bahrain ana ordinarily no quota can be grantee to them.; ‘ ' ^Ko.PA//^/, THE CUSTOKHOUSE: B AHIiA IN: 12th February, 1945 •) H.B.IJ’s Political Agent, Bahrcin. I'emorandum V/ith reference to your No. C/151 of the 31st 1945? I enclose herewith a list of applications received • AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. January, fr om Copy of enclosure forwarded under P.L. No. C/£34, dated the 15th February 1^45, to trie Export Trade Controller, Bombay. I JV o.^ § ’Received under Government of India, New Delhi No, F• 15(166) W/45 dated 27th January, 1945. Endorsement Copy of an Express Letter No. L-360(49) dated the 19th/20th January ?945 from Government of India, Food Department to the Export Trade Controllers, Borabay/afodras/Calcutta/ Karachi. subject, Government of Ind;‘a have decided that an additional quota of 250 tons of cardamoms will be licensed for export by established shippers^ and other shippers, if necessary, to all permissible destinations during the Current month. Licenses will be issued on the oasis of sales evidence produced by shippers, the object being to secure export of the entire quota before the end of March 1945. 2. $Please expedite report called for in para. 2 of the Express Letter referred to above). (Please report Urgently maximum quantities you can license for export from your port). Cn receipt of your reply, distribution of the quota to ports will be made. in continuation of Residency Endorsement No . 32-S dated 19th January, 1945. SUBJECT . EXPORT CT CaRDaIIOMS . No. 1/360(49) dated 14lh December, 194^ c cn the above Reference this Department Express Letter 3d/- S.K.ShJJ Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. CONFIDENTIAL No» 249-S British Residency, Bushire, the 27th february,1945 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, KUWAIT. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN The Political Agent, MUSCAT.79/328 &lt;4 79/267 Xel^grem jPro:B Q Rrltocnsnl, Bushlra, Go v^rahwit c.f Indt?, i^ew tk^lhi Political Kuwait • 4S7 6uh aoreh, isH6* r^^oeated X.'o D^ted Kuwait Express letter • 302; February 20th, Civil requireaenta i'rom India, f' ’ 2* Please confirm (a) that ,1 i5iT)ort lic«no*5 w dens/idocl is raciui‘‘ed solely #&lt;? evidence that export has recoKManded by Poiiticel Afmt vide paragraph 1 of your ixDiess Letter Ho, ^F»9 jL(&amp;) Hj^/ 44 August 8th, 1&gt;44 and is only for coafloditlas not repeat not subject to established shippers procedure, and (b) that similsr evridance is not required for coinmoditles subject to established shippers procedure, 3. Please also inform Political Agents what co diaodities included under general head M spices ,, are not repeat not net subject to established shippers procedure. together with copy of Kuwait express Letter Ko.302 dated 20th February, 1945, for information. BHITCOKSUL Rtf* t British Residency, Bush!re, 6th Maroh, 1945. No_..(b.7{.. Date.. Copy forwarded with compllitents tot The Political Agent, BAHRAIN Th^ Policicax agent, MUbCAT.mm t From To Hepeated No ' Dated ,HTT-2H. Political, Kuwait• Political Resident, Fusl ire Govern ert of India, Nev/ Delhi 302 20th February, l a 45. Jlr-f rsTI b 1 Indian exporters of Frv/ait civil requirements of tamarind, groundnuts, and spices have notified Importers h.ere that trey cannot oet i22°V$ licenses v/ithout an imoort lic'^nse from la wait. 2. I have no instructions aboi t the issue of such ^import licenses other tha.. ti c instructions concerning recommendations in respect of goods not subject to the Established shippers procedure. I refer to the instructions contair ed in Foreign Excess Letter I&gt;. F. 91(1)- HE/14 dated the 8ti August, 19-i4 ab6' , 't v/hich I asl ed for furth er details n *n paragraph 4 of my Express letter Ho. 144 of the 22nd January, 1945. ^ * 3. ’To prevent delay in the shipment f. of Kuwait’s civil requirements during the*sailing a/?.! se&amp;s i ,ri 5 I shall now issue on application Import u / licenses on. y for such goods, and for such' im porters and exporters as have been incli ded in the Kuwait civil reqTmrements programmes. 4 . leany/hile, it is ^eop ested that the Government of India be loved to issue instruictions concerning these import licenses if they are - r eq red at a ^ . In viev/ o ' tl c complete details of exporters and importers that are now given in the Iu wait 1 s civil requireijents Programme, the icenses in addition would ay ear to be unnecessary. It may well be that Exoort Trade Controllers- are confusing Kuwait with' territories under the jurisdiction of the ’EE.E.’C. such as Iraq- where imports , re controlled by the issue of such licenses. ED/ GN. JACKEOF Political .igent, Kuwait. * ✓ \mW* I \ * EXPRESS LETTER / ^ .S.2/8218 8 4 ( 133 ,) | ! Custom House, ? y Karachi, 7th March 1945 ftabrak «(e: /. H. &gt;»&lt;«. / / * randum ho.C./I40 dated 27.iiH945 regarding Civil T he Political Agent, Bahrain. « i , • A. V Reference your easier Pequi^emefits f^r Persian Gui|’ 2. Unde' the existing orders, export licences in respect of commodities which a-e subject to quota a'e issued % oniy to established exporters on the basis of their past exports to the destination concerned during the basic period and it is open to them to ship the goods to any consignees irrespective of whether they had dealings with'them in the past. It will therefore not be possible for this. Department to compel the established shippers at this port t- ship the gqods to particular consignees nominated by you. The desired result would however be achieved to some extent if some steps a'e taken at\ you' end to allow imports only by established importers.Telegram From To No Dajted Government of India, New Delhi Britconsul, Bushire 2544 and received 15th March, 1945. Your telegram No. 55 January 8th. Black Pepper. 2. Ministry of food cannot allot quotas asked for by you at present as quantity so far available is not sufficient to meet service demands of United Kingdom, United Jtates of America and dominions. Bahrain Receipt Nojill i-M FOREIGN CONFIDENTIAL No. 266»S British Residency, Bushire, the 19th March, 1945. Copy forv/arded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Muscat. for information and with reference to Residency Endorsement No. 36-5 dated 8th January, 1945. tz( J ^ ( 0-V - v th' 1 h&lt; j DLG.■ I3S flo. 1402 - 2'd/3Q. To POuITlCilu AGlImOi, BJit. tuilft • The ath A^rli 1^45. Ml li^ti t;l f&amp;atar of Customer r.^rf.ir,. The Pciiitical Officex - , Trueial Coast, Sharjah. BXaclx Pepper Government of India have informed me now that the Ministry of Food has refused to allot quotas ask^d for by me at present as quantity so far available is not suffi cient to meet tue service demands of united Kingdom, l.nited States of America ana Dominions, KMo 5^1'or PO^iITICAu AGLATI, BAnHAXH. cA’ v AV’No. 14*15 - 2*1/30. To POiilTlC/iUi AGENCY, 5iH.KiOLN. The 11th Aorii 1045. The Director of Customs, , Bahrain. . Reference Merchants Meeting discussion on otn April 1045 regaling the countersigning of importers* orders for requirements from India. 2• It is.hex*eby confirmed that tnere is no necessity for Bahrain importers* orders to be countersigned ip, you or this Agency. 3. Tiie above uoes not apply to it‘.ms for whicn quotas have been fixed. for PO-uil’iCiuj AGiiX\lI # BiicLtvAXN. tiMc, %i ' i \ Telegram From To Q- # r 'L 0 \ Political Resident,; Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat. No. 669. Dated the 9th and received 10th April, 1945. \\D b n* My telegram No. 43? dated ivlarch 6th (indorsement No. 261-3 to Bahrain and Muscsj/t)* Oivil requirements from India. Following is repetition of Foreign telegram No. 3275 dated April 8th. Begins: 'Presumption (a) and (b) in your paragraph No. 2 confirmed. Your paragraph No. 3. All comiodities under head 'Spices' are subject to establishment of shipper 1 s procedure. 2. STCS instructed not repeat not to insist on 'import licenses' for tamarind, ground nuts and spices.' Bnds. v - PRIOR - R.M. I.R. 265. Bahrain Receipt • /o? v H ' i Bat’ N/tI SQuIl'iCsiU AGiLiNC'i, No. 1556 - 23/30. The 14tn April 1345. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain* ubUL' .Ud4 DU hi . &lt; Reference my memoranaam No. 1495 - 29/30 dated the l^th April 1945. 2. The Government of India inform me that my recommendations of merenants*orders for the fallowing items are required. Cement, Balnunoniac^ dry colour, hemp and wood. 3. please inform the merchants accordingly' and arrange that tneir orders are submitted through you with your recommendations, for countersignature^ . 4L j. for POulTlCidi iidiHT, jJahitAll'i • /&gt; • /vr KMijt From The Export Trade Controller, Bombay. To The Political Agent, Bahrein. C.NO.203D/44W Sir, Nev/ Cuatom Houae, Bombay, / 0I { April 194o ( I enclose a stateraent of total Quantities of balances for the four quarters beginning irora October/ December 1943 to July/September 1944 distributed among the shippers of standing as per Qivil Heauirements frograrrme issued by Government of India from time to time. Your most obedient servant. y Export Trade Controller. Commodities. Balances for the four quarters Oct/Dec. 1943 to Juiy/Sept J944 Cotton manufactures '3.99882/- ^ Leather manufactures '3.39847/- Soap 184 cwts Cpices 233 cwts Vegetable oils 286 cwts Cigarettes 906 lbs9° py of ietter C• flo.2035/44W dated the lutn April 1 j 45 from the Export Trade Controller, Bombay, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. . , . 1 enci ose a statement of total quantities ^ 4 - 0 ^ t ' Lai } ces ior ^ our quarters beginning from October/December 1^43 to July/September 1044 distri buted among tne shippers of standing as per Civil Requirements Programme issued by Government of India from time to time. among importers for tne surplus items available. Commodities Balances for the four quarters Oct/Dec,1043 to July/tJopt. Iu44. to July/Sept. Cotton manufactures Leather manufactures Soap . Spices Vegetable oils Cigarettes. *. 99882/- to. 39847/- 184 Cuts. £53 Cwts. 286 Cwts. 906 lbs. BAiiRAIiW. The 19th April 1945 POLITIC An AGMICY, No. 1621 - 29/30 Copy forwarded to;- The Director of Customs, Bahrain, with tne reque~« that allotments may be made early for POLITICAL AGENT, BArihAIN tAcAr KMbFrom To B.v Registered airmail Bak, The Export Trade Controller .Custom House, Karachi. The Political Agent, Bahrain EXPRESS / *4^*33 ' NO.C.712/ETC I Custom House. Karachi, 10* 4* 1945 No.C.712/ETC In continuation of this office letter/WRPSWW dated 20 . 3. 1945, I enclose a statement showing the surpluses available against the various commodities included in the Civil Requirement Prograrnrne for export. to Bahrain for the quarter Janu a ry-.March 1945. Xour recommendations for the distribution of surpluses may kindly be communicated at an early date. -v. u , vr'»r\■*»+: T’t*qH ft Onntroll*SAI ETT ABUDLH 'ilLSALEH BAHRAIN ISLAND IMPORTERS EXPORTERS B*niraclors # Eommission. Agents, Bated 55 ' _ lj»i jii TELEGRAM, ALSALEH (UKp ^ Me )f^&gt; \ j, JiliA H.M. Political gent, iiahaiin. Sir, On the 21st instant I approached the food oonrtoiier to permit me/export monthly 75 tons of fruits etc from India and he has be:n good enough to sanction same and informed me that he has relieved t .e matter to your go &gt;dself. I shall be greatful if you will kindly sanction a quota of 75 tons fruits etc. as under per month, jsarx 25 tons assorted fresh truits 25 tons Unions 25 ' Potatoes. My agent's name and addre% in ho mb ay is as follows: Sayed Abdul rlamid, Shustery Imumwala, 1st i'looi , r e m 0 nwada Rg ad, Bombay, y. 1 shall be obliged if you will please sanction same at youi convenience. T anking you in anticipation, Ycurs obedientlyTo No. Telegram En Clair. From Export Trade Controirer, Karachi. Political, Bahrain. C712/ETC. Dated 5th and Reed. 6th Mpy 1945 . . Reference tills office Express Letter of even No. da,ted 10th April la45 regarding distribution of surplus under Civil Requirement Programme. ' • Kindly forward your recommendations early. EXIRaCON KM5' 'V* * / I3ctXAJ. ClJ.Xi* NO'PA/S.... 15th May, 1§45., THE CUSTOMHOUSE: Bahrain Political Agent, Bahrain* Memorandu m:' ’ With reference to your No*1621-29/30 of the 19th April, 194-5, I enclose herewith a list showing the distribution of the surplus items available from Bombay. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN^ No / e IS~- r-- Telegraphic Address:- “KAZEROONI” BAHRAIN. B. ¥*5 Political A^ent, Bahrein, Sir, ^ (§) ABBAS KAZEROONI &amp; Co- 3S . 28tli., April /,945 U f £- 'ey. • t O-r / No^SS.Dat . We beg to inform your Honour that we got a letter from our agent in Karachi saying that we cannot get export permit for our quota No#FC/7I9/63 copy attached until the Custom of Karachi get the instruction from Goverment*! of India. We request your Honour to write the Goverment of India to advice the Karachi custom to issue the same. For which we shall thank you for ever. We beg to remain, Sir Your obedient servants, Abbas Kazeroflni &amp; Co. Enel. Our Agent 1 etter Copy of our quota.Telegraphic Address:- •KAZEROONI” BAHRAIN. ABBAS KAZEROONI &amp; CO- fessrs. Hcji Sul email Ar’am Kofbari &amp; Co. Karachi. Deer Sirs, We have obtained ouotes for 3 Tons Ground Nuts, through The Director of Custom's * Port O^icer, to import ^rom Karachi, and shall thank you to made necessary arrangement to ship them aftear rec eiving santtion -^rorn Dxport Controller. Quota No.FC/719/63 for ouarter October/December 1944 Yours Faithfully, Albas Kazerooni &lt;1 Co. CEFiTIFIED within quota October^ c 'RSIGNED n. b: M's: PoinicniAeent Bahrain, f P? mi an OttffJ7 8 6 ALL SUBJECT TO KARACHI JURISDICTION ^faii oSu/eman CODES USED: A. B. C. 5th &amp; 6th Edition &amp; Private. aji K^uieman ^siaam IMPORT. EXPORT MERCHANTS A COMMISSION AGENTS. Cftot/icm &amp; Go., Tele grams:- “UMEDWAR” phone No. 2434. TO, KHORI GARDEN, Karachi, 20th April iq^i 6 Messrs, y aOD ass Kaeerooni a 0o, Bahraln # V# ucsx are reoiept of you letter dated , 12th AprU 1946 , and noted the content with thanks # (around nutts. we heg to Inform you that ve hare already applied f nree f ons of ground nutts qpute which you haTe sent hy countersigning from the Political Agent to The Karabhl Oustom , hut regret uptill now have not recieved the licence for the same from Karachi Custom 9 Beoauf Karachi wustjm sa^s we will issue the lioenoe on reoieving the instruotior -s from The ^ovenasnt of India, To get licence sion please instruct to Agent to write a letter to The Government jgfxcf to advice Karachi (juetom to iswit’^ter if you kindly arrange to do so , and we hope if you win arrange we will get lioenoe aeon. T ._, , , on*,*, ’ ' l* Veget able QH, %e are trying to Sget more time ‘(pods in the Licences .heoauee we cant get the/same within the short time as the •re is much scarcity of product and of wagons, and for that we have already applied to .jae^iStt^ Secret©OoVermerfb of India New Daunt and to The ss'ssiapst sx*a'. w j SSV'SU'thtf'® 1 ’ A * W7,, * T eeua n#?2eT«ie ' i/W a* aril 1^/y ine com Fere custom is/qputa’s from hisitu recieving the the ^ol tm ■•ww ■nnttfciBj’iitaia yjn&amp; c &amp;viL.„ t of mu. #VSi° MM “tki'oouliVw 0 tlii' ! « will .pay •Q^X derTpse a# vr'y'nj Tio^uo^s •a^cfo^ lioye * y^j^overpwnt of India thruogh •‘•he Karachi Custom and on getting the licem •Obs a* ajU he wpt« ^c i'pb Gin&amp;k ^ &gt;cn • rtppon* %j P.t # o #The Director of Customs, Bahrain, with the request tnat ariotmeats may be made eariy among importers for the surpius items avaiiabrd, ’ '““‘N XPrinted in Engiand. Sept. 194Z ^4,100. pads .} Circuit. The first line of this Telegram contains the following particula Prefix Letters and Number of Message. Office of Origin. Number of Word: Official instructions—if any. Clerk’s Name. H&amp;t&gt; 1445 CABLE AND WIRELES2 Received. Time UNCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) QV134/T s KARACHI 37/36 19 1505 BGOVT FI POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN BGOVT FIL C712/ETC REFERENCE THIS OFFICE EXPRESS LETTER' OF EVEN NUMBER DATED TENTH APRIL AND TELEGRAPHIC REMINDER OF FIFTH 'MAY REGARDING DISTRIBUTION OF SURPLUS MA¥=R UNDER CIVIL REQUIREMENT PROGRAMME STOP KINDLY FORWARD YOUR RECOMMENDATIONS EARLY EXTRACON MARK YOUR REPLY Sm/ietuaL ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.I THE CUSTOMHOUSES „ BAHRAINs (I No. PA/J-. 23rd May 5 1945. 9 Political Agent. oj |Bahrain© Memorandum I send herev/ith 25 orders for surolus quotas from Bombay for favour of your counter-signature and re turn. ^ JL—S DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. 'Enclos—ooooo*«o No, PA/ • H.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain* Memorandum THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: - 23rd May, 1945., / Bahrain Rece!pt N,,, ^ , ^(S NoS f.p .7 Date I send herewith 14 orders for surplus quotas from Karachi for favour of your counter-signature and re turn. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN• Enc^c PSNo. PA/, U£ THE CUSTOMHOUSET^^V^ i ’ BAHRAIN: ,f*' H.B,M ! s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum 23rd May, 1945., PaV ,; ~ Ref.your No.1556 -29/30 ! &lt; of 14th April 1945. I send herewith five orders for favour of your counter-signature and return. ^ ^ DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAINVa( y\vi Advocate High Court. Vv iss H.P. Shamdasani , M.A.,LL.B. OS) 7 ^ank of India Buildinp*,^ /?/. 1st floor,Kalbadevi Road, l ' v ' Bombay, ITOIA. Date: 15th ? f ay 1945. The Political A.gent, B^harein, (Persia'n Dulf). Sir, __ , , Under instructions '‘rori my clients,? f essrs. • . oolchand Sons of Bombay I have to address vou as under That my clients are exporters. They have received an order tosupply 200 bales Rmpty Gunny Ba^rs,each bale containing 3G0 pieces,measuring 44/26^ each to their constituent at Behrein. They are informed by the Chief Controller of Exports, Uew' Delhi that if their export of the said .goods from Calcutta is recommended by your goodsel^, then only their -- application could be considered by the Export Trade Sontroll^r^Calcutta. 1 have, therefore, to request you to be kind enough to recommend this export of 200 bales of empty Gunny bags to the Expprt Trade Controller,Cal- cutta at your earliest and inform me accordingly,for which act of kindness,my clients shall, as in duty bound, ever pray. A T c&gt; lah Your most obedient servant, r v .vsr * P. Advocate. /;i-)o. 2274 - 2a/ 30. PO-iIi'ICAi, AOUJGX BAiiHAXM* The 2nd June 1 j45« To The Director of Customs, Bahrain, Reference attached copy of a letter from mss !•?, Sliaadusani, Advocate High Court, Bombay, 2, Can you let me knov; who tie consignee is i,e, whether merchant has ordered those gunny bags? J for rlhjIUCiui AGj^DJT,mo.vk/M/.f. THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN* , 9th June, 194? •5 / &lt; ( H.B.M*s Political Agent, Balira in* Bn!;- ‘ - ,r &gt; oce : ; iUs // MEMORANDUM:- \ -Sr 3as i) Reference your memorandum No.227 4 —29/30 of the 2nd inst V/e have no knov;ledge of who has applied for permission to import empty bags. There is a surplus of empty bags in Bahrain and at times they are being exported* DIRECTCR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAINTHE CUSTOMHOUSES No * PA/ ...••••••• BAHRAIN: 20th June, 194-5., H.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUMS- V/ith reference to your No.2095-29/39 tile 21st May, 1945, I enclose herewith a list showing the distribution of the surplus items available from^BomJpay. nrajfx DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS BaivraH i^o-.507- i&gt;^ector AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. Enel—4/-Government of India internal Affairs Uopartr EXPRESS LETTER, Eroff.: Foreign, New Delhi. io: Britain, Bushire. ^Repeated Political, Bahrtdn. No .i New Dftlni, the ibth Juria x 94 j. &lt;\t ierencti is in vi ted be tLi s Lep&amp;r tiic. at eipresa letter t\ ! o. F.9l-ME/44^Teted 26'Ll Augist, 1944. reKaramg oo-orU nabi on of export control in India with if no or t controls in the Persian ‘Golf States. 2. Lijfcs of importers =nd exporters on the lines lard down in that letter nave so far been received from ?. As., Knwai t an i L-uacat. i T ne Govenunant of India be glad to u.ow .dun they may bxp*&gt;ot to receive the lists from f.A., Bahrain. The ; t dsuo of the above Las b^en authorised. (S.. 1. Under Secretary to the Govemnant of India. /&gt; /fc3.I Me morandum I send herewith 23 orders for surplus auotas from Bombay for favour of your counter-signature and return. Enel— X3 DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.NO.C737/3TC K l l *) To By Registered ^ Aw (il 9 lit //? The Political Agent ah roin a Custom House, Karachi Dated 6th July 1945 Babram !R«:o’pt /' N o jll. 0. .?!}.&amp;. Da oe. Continuation this office letter of even number dated 5*7•3945* A statement shoiwing the surpluses available against the various commoditie,' included in the Civil Requirement Programme for export to .Bahrein — ~ ' ^ o:r quarter April/June 1945 is enclosed with a request that your reconmendations for distribution of these surpluses may kindly be communicated at an early date. A.Kai. ft-* Asstts Export 'jITm&amp;G Controller For Exp^iit^raae Controller i&gt; /S/GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. political AOKNCvDepartment. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Hmn&amp;tMat . the To Britain, Bushire. Repeated Foreign, Now Belhi. \^0 V V Reference ^ Foreign Express Letter D.7451-ME/45, dated the 15th June 1945* \ v the 5th November 1944 stated that no change was desii'able until such time as the Government of India can permit the appointment of exporters in In in by the Political Agencies, who would be able to ensure the shipment of quotas given them. the war would only servo to put the clock bafek six months and disrupt the present system which, with all its faults, is now working more or loss snoothely. add that, to the best of my knowledge, at least two of the three. Political 'Vgencies on the Arab Littoral wore pressing two years ago for the allocation of quotas to importers recommended by tt*^ and their a ents in India; a compromise arrangement at this would only complicate a procedure that is, in comparison with ^ very simple and efficient Import Assistance Recoct-ondations procedure in force for United Kingdom and U.55.A. requirements, already extremely difficult to understand unless one has been dealing with it for some time. 2. wy predecessor in his Express Letter C/1585 datec He also stated that any cliange at that stage of 3. In agreeing with these remarks, I should like to S. 44, POLITICAL AGgNT, BAHRAIN. (Designation) MFP—367 S&amp;P—(M-508)—15.7-35—10,000.I &amp; ^ Ho. 3065 - 29/30. P0 6 IT I Cal Al’.fcHCY, iUALLRAIii* The 29th July 1945. To Messrs. Kli&amp;ns^heb Atdulhusein &amp; Bros., Bahrain. MniiJciAdUJM your letter dated the 2dra July 1^45. 2. please ascertain from your agent on what grounds and by wnich * Government authorities* the export of tne goods was refused, to enable me to taice up tne matter ’with the Government of India. X for ^G-uilXOJj Adiiiil,No. 2972 -79/P56 ilS The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent f Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dat ed • fiPth • • J»ly y • lP4fi. ••• Reference to previous correspondence: Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum No* L-354(lf5) dated the 20th June 19415 from the Department of Food to the Export Trade Controller, Exeort of dry fruita in second hand tins. GSL1 No. L-354(15) New Delhi f the 30th June 1945. . T/ra'ONANTW - • Subject Export of dry fruits In second hand tins. r\ fni Reference your letter No. E.T.15-14/45 W dated the 25th l f ay, 1945 on the above subject. The Government of India haVe no objection to the export of dry fruits 5n second hand tins, without rrlor reference to this Department, if you are satisfied that metal containers are the*normal trade packinp for that commodity. Your action in permitting export of Msmis irl second-hand tins by W/3 Gulabchand Chantilal &amp; Co . approved. :an&gt;yfletter clt^d in nara 1 of leu ir^rly was issued by the Chief *t and not by this department ( a^l with regard to the export Vdrjtalners^fcrj/cnshow Vamels should now leased to the^ Chief Controller Delhi, and not to this depart*' [ment. Sd/- S.R.Maini. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Department of Food. ^ G£L /lo-fi— \ / I \ Telegram From To No. Dated the 4th 3.T.C. Britain Bushire. Foreign New Delhi. a/1159 August 1945. Your express letter Ko. J 7451-UB/45, -•&amp;.P 1^7 June 15th. 2. I support views contained in Bahrain express letter No. 3016-29/30, July 24th repeated to you anct recommend that no change be made. BRITAIN. No. -79/128 \/t}opy by pdst td the Political! Bahrain'. V, f j * y USYW^'' GSLGOVERNMENT OR INDIA. Political Agency, BahrainDepartmcnt. EXPRESS LETTER -V. B. This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. To 3366 29/30. Dated Bahrain, the 21st August 19 ^5 Britagent, Sharjah. Please telegraph your annual requirements if any of flue cure tobacco from India, with names of importers. KMS for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. ^-t&gt; n y S. h. MFP—1130 S&amp;P—6768—(M-2148)—27-1-42—000,000.mi no n (*&gt; No. 3367 - 29/30. To POLITICAL AGjfiNCY. BAHRAIN. The 21st August 1946. The Director of Customs, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM I have been informed that the export of a reasonable quantity of flue cure tobacco will be considered by Government of India. 2. Please let me know Bahrain's annual requirements if any and the names of importers. ^ KMS for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. / nrTo Ho. 92 - E.I(I)/45. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. OFFICE OF THE CHIEF CONTROLLER OF EXPORTS. (Commerce Department) New Delhi, the 16th July, 1945, EXPRESS LETTER . The Export Trade Controller, Madr a s/Bombay/Ca 1 cut ta/ Karachi/Quetta/Peshawar. It has been decided that export of Rexine cloth to all perraissib 1 © destinations should in future be allowed by estab- lished shippers only upto the level of their exports during the year 1941-42. 2. Articles made of Rexine such as hand bags, writing cases etc. may, however, be allowed to be exported by estab lished shippers and bona fide manufacturers upto their 1941-42 level or 10% of their production, whichever is higher. di *P? s e» of your letter No. W 1891/44 dated the 18th April, 1945). ( ) For Madras only. Sd. C. SRINIWASAN. Assistant Chief Controller, for Chief Controller of Exports. No. 92 - E.I(I)/45. Copy forwarded for information to Commerce Department with reference their U.O. No. 2651-CW/45 dated the 29th June 1945 and to the etc. etc. Sd. C. SRINIWASAN. Assistant Chief Controller, for Chief Controller of Exports. Copied G.A.M.Ifo.PA/Q/rf Political Agent, .Bahrain. BEI.’QHAKDUl:: THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN; 26 th August,1945., (Tt 5 ) 1*3. Bahrain Receipt i ,* 1 No ... / r* T.ith reference to your Ho.2877-29/30 of the 15th July, 1945 , 1 enclose herewith a list showing the distribution of the surplus items available from Karachi. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. Enel- ! \I tT No. 3520 - 3G/33. POLITICAL AGiii;CY, BAHRAIN. The 2nd Beptrader 1945. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. HEMORaMDUU u I hair 3 been informed that export of Kexine cloth ;e^iig allowed freely by esGaolisi eG shippers only upto tie level of their exports during the year 1941-42. c * Ai*tides made of Rexir e such as and bags, writ ing cas s etc# are, however, allowed to be exported by tL.uahlished jliippers and bona fife manufacturers upto theii 1941-42 leve l or 19^ of their pi*oduc :ion, whiciiever is higher. J POLiilk.Ali AaSHi, JjAiittalN.)45* B'i Telegram From To No. August. tobacco. G.T.C. Britagent, Sharjah. Political, Bahrain. 927. Dated the 6th September 1945. A m . Your Express Letter No. 3366, dated the 21st Trucial Coast does not require flue cure BRITaG^NT KMS Bahrain Receipt No —(&gt; 6 Date ....■■PSHiHBB Telegrara From To No. 671. Dated the 12th September 1945. 2. require Your telegram No. A/1223 August 19th. Bahrain and Trucial Coast do#not repeat/ not flue cure tobacco. KMS POLITICAL/ r - 5*.PA/Q/.X THE CUSTOMHOUSE* BAHRAIN* 20th September, 1945., Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM s- Ref. my No of the 26th August, 1945# . pa/q/3 I enclose herewith sixteen orders for surplus quotas from Karachi for favour of your counter-signature and return. Enel—)t / Lf DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. S'&gt;?/3 0 O CO mpire i(A rading Code Used: Bentley's A. 3 C. 5th Edition. Exporters, Importers AND Telegraphic Address: “PARROT” Manufocturers 9 Representatit&gt;es, RAMPART ROW. tank no. h. Ref No. Bahrain Receipt Karachi, 2 17 t h S ept -1 9 4 c 17th dep \ . - To, The Political Agent, Bahrain (PeGulf). Sir, Subject:- Export of goods to your side- Recommendations of:- We have the honour to state that we have been doing export &amp; import business with Iraa, Iran,Persian Gulf, &amp; Muscat TeT. Since a long time. We have many friends to your side tfio have been constantly requesting us to send to them the required goods. hxtWe therefore applied to the Government of India, New Delhi for the necessary export permits. The Government of India have been pleased to intimate to us that the necessary permits for the goods sought to be exported to Bahrain,would be granted only if the Political Agent, Bah rain recommends that the said articles are but necessary. In other words,we require a recommendatory letter from you to the effect that the goods in question mentioned herein below are required on your side. We are desirous of exporting the following goods to your side for the time being:- 1. Tamarind 2 Tons. 2. Cotton Manufactures 5 Tons. ■ 5 . Leather Manufactures 5 Tons. 4. Provisions 3 Tons. 5. Candles worth Rs.3000/-. 0 . Pickles &amp; Vinegar. 5 Tons. From the above list you will be pleased to see that the above articles axe of great necessity at Bahrain and you will therefore kindly do needful in the matter. \ We may however submit that with the cessation of hostilities with Japan, the trade is going to be normal in a very short time in India and at the same time by the exporl• • • v BM | r \r &gt; v 5 Oq&gt; tf t f o • 2. export of the goods referred to above, we believe India will not at all experience any shortage; at the r same time these goods will be greatly welcomed at Bahrain, We have therefore the honour to request that you will be so good as to grant us the necessary recommendations as requested above so as to enable us to apply to the Government of India to get the necessary permits to export the goods to your side. 'OMH* M *' Thanking you. .abrow isriSo w«&gt; &gt; We have the honour to be. Sir, Yolir most obedikit servants. For Ihe Indo Jitoire Trading Co. nem no. 1c rim .p.tto'2 ? . ,r-r r - * ~ • .anox r Tffel a ao*r ,aoe t ;ui r &gt;sen oh 8/10 . ® j^VOT ,V^ f t ©xr eeloi^is svoci^ erU’ sin Ists'I: ffxw no ;3479 14509 (4) HIS Majesty’s Qonsul presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents, with the request that information asked for may he supplied to the British . Re si dency. and office? 1 ^ ^ ^ ^ Consulate.. General 7 .. Bushire.. 23rd September^.. 1945*iSt&amp;x Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.&lt;3*r &lt;^j ' Copy of letter No. 2021, dated the 9th July, 1945 from the Indian Government Trade Commissioner (for the Near 8c Middle East), A1 Bassir Building 5, Hue Adib Bey Issac, Avenue De La Heine Nazli, P.O.Box 287, Alexandria, Egypt to the Political Resident, Bushire, Persian Gulf. In connection with an enquiry received by me from authorities in India, I have the honour to request you to kindly let me know if imports of senna, cardamons and groundnuts into the Gulf ports are freely allowed at present. If so, names of a few importers may kindly be supplied An early reply will be appreciated. • ••••••29/30. Political Agency, Bahrain. The ^^Septomber, 1945. To The Indo KX^ire Trading Company, Rampart Row, Tank No*6, KARACHI. Dear Sir^, Reference your l3tter No.1012/45, 17th September 1945. dated the Your best course in my opinion would be to contact an importer in Bahrain who could then apply for a share of Bahrain*s quota of each article and, if necessary, nave nis orders countersigned by me. Yours faithfjilly, kms POLITICAL AGaMT, BAHRAIN.No* 4105 - 29/30* The 30th September 1945* To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Please confirm that the import into Bahrain of senna, cardamons and groundnuts is not restricted in any way and furnish me with the names of a few importers* KMS POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.Wi if .fo. PA/P/ H.E.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, MEMORANDUM :- Reference your No.4105-29/30 of the 30th September 1945. I confirm that the import into Bahrain of senna, cardamoms and groundnuts is not restricted in any way. I enclose herewith a list showing the names of a few im porters of the above commodities as desired. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. Enel— \No. 4215 - 29/30. To POLITICAL AGiSNCY, BAHRAIN. The 6th October 1945. The Indian Government Trade Commissioner, Al Basslr Building, 5, Rue Adib Bey Issac, Avenue De La Rsine Nazli, P.O.Box 287, ALEXANDRIA. HEMORANDUM Reference your letter No. 2021, dated the 9th July 1945, to the Kon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 2. There are no restrictions on the import of senna, cardamoms and groundnuts into Bahrain. 3. A list showing the names of a few importers of the above commodities is enclosed herewith. for / Copy forwarded with POLITICAL AGENT, compliments to:- BAHBAIN. H.tf^s Consul, Bushire, with reference to his Printed Letter No. dated the 23rd September 1945. 3696 ' I 10/12,- ^xtract of Minutes the Merchants Advisory Co.jiittee Meeting held at the Agency on Monday, the 1st October 1945. / f i| H) i.ir. Edwards said he had been unable to obtain provisions from India. Agreed to find out exactly what the proper procedure is and why provisions had not been forthconing. KI4S \GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Export Trade Controller, Karachi's letter No«S.3/8218 of 18th January 1945*- “A quota of 6 tons each for export to Bahrain of Hosiery and Provision was allotted under the Civil Reauirement Programme for the quarter July/September 1944. As Messrs. Rewachand P.Bablani are not established shippers for the export of the goods in question, their application for licences could not be entertained and no licences were therefore issued t6 them.” to obtain provisons ffom India allotted in the quarterly prograiaaes and I shall be glad to know, therefore, who have been appointed as established shippers for provisions. The issue of the above has been authorised. [N.B .—This is an ORIGIN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate No.4374 - 29/20. Bahrain, Dated 15th October 2945. To Britain, Bushire. Repeated Foreign, New Delhi. Subject *- Provisions from India . 7 The following is an extract from the Merchants complain that they are unable POLITICAL Agent, Bahrain. KMS S. 44.&amp;u f?JL£.dU l^i X'~ ' No.C.757/ETC. Karachi, 17th Octr., 1945• To The Political Agent Bahrein No. Continuation this office endorsement of even number dated 15/10/1945. 2. A statement showing the surpluses available against the various commodities included in the Civil Requirement Programme for export to Bahrein and Coast for the quarter ending July/September 1945 is enclosed. Your recommendations for the distribution of these surpluses may kindly be communicated to me at an early date. Assistant Export^Tfade Controller, for Exp Trade Controller, K.Bt .*; POLITIC,A AGENCY, BAH RAIN. - The 25th October i945. No. 4455,6 - 29/30. Copy forwarded-to: /. ■ ....... The Director of Gnstoms, Bahrain, , ■* The Residency Agent, Sharjah*, with the request ‘that allotments may be made early among importers--for the surplus items available. r DA % -for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. X' ■ i KMS ft INo. 4466 - 29/30. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 25th October 1945« To Mr. MflORANDUU Khalil bin Ebrahim Kanoo Bahrain. Reference your letter dated the 24th October 1945. 2. No import licence is necessary. J for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHhAIN.4 Mr. Johannes. 29/30 - Civil Reqs. - general. . I have seen Mr. Smitn who is not in favouJ.. Please che-ck on points raised by P.A. in last sentences of his note. * V . * ' It Id. R.M.H. 24/10/44 fee:... Action will be take d rfa 'of file. itld NCJ&gt; 27/10/4^ » . * i f « f ' r Ref A.P.Me.. , aote .of 24/10 ^bove. —.— ;—*. - ■ &gt;• , May remote these papers fi^m the piece^ocda file as two separate^que^ti dhs'‘ a^se ^*oth G of'I. r. L. at p.30 ? 1) Co-rox’dination of export control fro... India with import control in the Gulf. 2) Ccpaiate quotas for Sharia. . and Dubai. vU Regarding 1) - The G of I have furnished lists of established exporters in respect of many but not all items i ■■ the civil requirements programme. The Agency has in the past furnished the names of 'established importers' in t. e form of a statement, when giving details as to how much of each article in the programme an ,s importer is to handle. G of I ordered disconti.- ance of this practice, vide p,133 of f.28/31 vol 2. Reason was that they found it more convenient to allot quotas 1^7 to established exporters who were expected to distribute their snares among importer, in each fhaikhdom. P.A. strongly deprecated this unsatisfactory&gt; system, vide p.29 of f.2j/27. PUC indicates that G v of I is now favouring Bhn»s method of suppling details of exporters importers &amp; amounts, but want all these particulars to be based on business in lo41 only. Bhn ! s calculations which are based on business for at least three years precee-ding the war gives* a more, complete picture. There are no separate lists of established ^ importers for Bhn or the T.C. Regarding 2) - please see P.A 1 u. note of the ^ 3th Oct, on f. 29/22 vol' 1. Itld P.C.J. 30/10 Seen by A.P.A. &amp; discussed by P.A. &amp; A.P.A. Drafts to be faired. A* . c //JhP^r p&amp;f ////u u U°- PA/fc/ 7 ?tUj ^ ? //Cf • Pfc. A AfPiAx . 3^ is7/ 111 1. Articles subect to Established snippers procedure:- a) Cigarettes. b) Cotton piecegoods: E.T.Cs send us fortnightly distribution lists. c) Cotton manufactures. d) Dhal e) Leather goods. f) Haberdashery g) Hosiery h) Matches. i) provisions. j) Spices. c k) Tamarind. l) Vegetable ghee. Ho lists of B &amp; hrain dmporters are required by Govt, of India for these items (page 116 of 2^/30). 2. For tne following items import licences ^are r equired by the Government of India. 11$ Bran. tf Cement. Dry colour. Hemp. Saiammoniac. (I Tea. Timber. This procedure is worKing ail right. 3. These items are not subject to tne Established Snippers procedure and import licences are not required from us. ... ' Merchants obtain export permits from E.T.Cs. * * Charcoal * Cotton Twist. Cotton Raw Dry colour iMails. Washing Soda. 0.2ii/50 • 6. 4. Surplus commodities available at tne ena of a quarter are notified by E-T.Cs to us, we axuot and countersign orders, [ ^• From tne above, it wiil be seen tnat over 50^ I (aiid aii. tne items of most urgency) are subject to tne Established snippers proceLuaiiie wnicn means that a) Quotas are distributed amongst Est. Shipjers in India. b) The iatter are at liberty to seo.i to whomso— i ever they, wish and we. can not nope to confine! their distribution to importers recommended bl/ Y us (see my note para 140 er seq). The answer to your queries 6* the 13th are: ^ a) E.T.Cs are as far as we know acting in accordance with their orders. b) I don»t think we should suggest the present orders be rescinded. ' What might be of iterest would be to obtain tne figures oi imports of air items in para (l) above between! 1st January 1044 and 31st December 1944 and compare tnem with oufr quotas. If you agree, i wiix ask Director* of Customs to give us the figures. o. I apologise for tne delay in putting up tnis note J^y and nave not flagged axl the orders Wxiich are on separate files for eacn item. 7. 4.S 4. i-jiSAji —© /O)2ii/30. The X.L. referred to was anirwered vide p.45 1^1 in which it was stated tnat no change at that juncture sebined desirable. Banrain specificairy recommended that the Govt, of India snoula accept list of importers sent in by us. This was recommended by Mis cat vine p. 152 of file 56/35 Voi. II but was turned down vine p.160 of the same file. The same recommendation was again made by Muscat vide p.37 fixe 2d/30 ana the 1 • tt. then said that he hoped that dii'iicuitiea would be removed by the procedure suggested; in the X. L. we are now trying to answer. Yhckaj Jart dux t* 1C /C4 111 /Ucuu Cn c/&gt;cLu%s&gt; Ls\iC ILL oCfyf\jL*v&gt; \xtc4j, u* *A /Va tvo , N 9 • 3c 3 7 * 7' &amp;? $ . MrctS I can find no letter on the file in which I am putting up a draft herewith. * a} X r L. # /Vj 3 c /l JLr » Xit * * Q $ f &amp; {iZ, ^ 2ligawd</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/790</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/790</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 29/30 Civil requirements: miscellaneous items from India (pepper, spices, etc)’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-27T21:17:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (240 folios)</extent><extent>Files papers are arranged more or less chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 242; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-217 and between ff 218-241; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence about the supply of various essential commodities from India, by sea from Bombay and Karachi to Bahrain and the Trucial Coast ports of Dubai and Sharjah for local consumption, during the Second World War (1939-1945). Several commodities are mentioned including spices, nuts, oils, cotton and leather goods, hosiery, soap, matches and cement. These goods were in short supply due to wartime conditions and subject to Government of India export restrictions and import quota arrangements in the Persian Gulf shaikhdoms under British protection. The main correspondents are the Political Agent for Bahrain, the Director of Customs and Port Officer for the Government of Bahrain, the Export Trade Controllers (also referred to as Foreign Trade Controllers) in Karachi and Bombay, as well as other Government of India officials, mainly in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. They discuss the allotment of Government of India surplus quota goods among merchants in Bahrain, Dubai and Sharjah and exchange distribution lists that contain the names of all approved importers (local merchants), together with the names of their Indian exporters or shippers in Bombay and Karachi, and the type and quantity of the controlled commodity allotted to them. In addition, there are detailed submissions from the Political Agents for Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, expressing concerns about new Government of India instructions for improving the coordination of export control procedures in India with import control procedures in the Persian Gulf shaikhdoms, in particular, that Export Trade Controllers in Indian ports only grant export licenses and permits to Indian exporters and shippers who appear on their established shippers lists. The file also contains merchants’ correspondence, from several importers in Bahrain and their nominated export agents or shippers in Karachi and Bombay, complaining to the Political Agent for Bahrain, about the refusal of the Export Trade Controllers in Indian ports to grant them export licences and permits.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Export Trade Controller</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Commodities</topic></subject><subject><topic>Manufactured goods</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Export Trade Controller, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Commerce Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Chief Controller of Exports</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Dubai</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>