<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023514894.0x000005_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T15:22:59.654Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023514894.0x000005_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/95, ff 26-27</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023514894.0x000005</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/95, ff 26-27</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from Damodhur Trinbuck Punt, late Private Secretary to His Highness Mulherao Maharaja, Breach Candy Road No.472, Bombay to Colonel Sir Lewis Pelly</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1880/1880</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-29T00:28:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent><extent>Binding: The letter has been tied together along the left hand edge of each folio with string, excepting the last folio (25) which has come apart from it.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter regarding circumstances that had arisen owing to his having taken part in the trial of His Highness the ex Gaekwad Mulherao Maharaja of Baroda and detailing the guarantee agreed between himself and Pelly for his testimony, in particular the allowance which he had been receiving from the Gaekwar and which was covered under the property section of the guarantee.The letter goes on to discuss the loss of his allowance, which he was only able to claim back part of as the documentary proof was lost when his house was plundered, but that he had recently discovered it amongst a relatives papers; and asking that Pelly support his application to Government to have the full allowance restored as the present Officers of Baroda State did not known him.The letter refers to a guarantee which was issued to him in 1875 by Sir Lewis Pelly and which can be found at folios two to three.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023514894.0x000005#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>