<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00031b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T06:47:35.020Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Anglo-Russian Relations. Persia. In the event of the Russian Government raising the question of an agreement relating to Persia on Sir A. Nicolson’s arrival in St. Petersburg, it would be advisable that he should lay down as a general basis, before entering upon any discussion, that His Majesty’s Government attach the highest importance in any negotiations that take place upon the recognition of the independence and integrity of Persia, and, with a view to securing tranquillity upon her frontiers, the recognition of the province of Seistan and the provinces coterminous with the British frontier in Baluchistan as entirely within the British sphere of influence and outside the zone of future Russian railway enterprise. The only indication which His Majesty’s Government have of recent years received from the Russian Government of their views as to a settlement of the Persian question has 'been their desire for a commercial outlet in the Persian Gulf. His Majesty’s Government would present no objection to the realisation of such a project, provided there was no question of the construction of the terminus of a future Russian railway at Bunder Abbas or at any point to the eastward. A commercial outlet for Russian trade in the Persian Gulf may possibly be found by the participation of Russia in the Bagdad Railway. Subject to these considerations His Majesty’s Government would be ready to discuss any proposals put forward by the Russian Government, whether based on the joint co-operation of the two countries for the development and amelioration of Persia, or on the division of spheres of influence by a line drawn vertically, horizontally, or diagonally from north east to south-west, or any other scheme that the Russian Government might prefer to suggest. Afghanistan. When the subject of Afghanistan is raised in the impending negotiations at St. Petersburg, Sir A. Nicolson is instructed to formulate the following points as bases of an agreement between Russia and Great Britain. Russia to recognize the territorial integrity of Afghanistan and to acknowledge Afghanistan as being outside the Russian sphere of influence, and under British guidance in all matters of external policy. Direct communication to be allowed between Russian officials and officials designated by the Ameer as to matters of purely local character and of non-political complexion. The creation of a Russo-Afgban Commission, similar to the permanent Russo-Persian Frontier Commission, for the settle ment of tribal and boundary disputes, might present a possible solution of this question. Query insert— Russia to abstain from sending Russia to discontinue giving bounties in subsidies to Russian trade into AgClliS into Afghanistan. Afghanistan. S. S. 24. A2 Great Britain to place no obstruction to Russian trade enjoying the same facilities in Afghanistan as British and British Indian traders now enjoy'. Great Britain and| Russia to agree not to extend their railways in the direction of the frontiers of Afghanistan during a period of ten years. Extract Private Letter from Lord Minto to Mr. Morley, dated 12th June 1906. Thibet .—Draft instructions to Sir A. Nicolson. These follow the general conditions of the Convention, and I need say nothing except that from all I hear there is a very friendly spirit towards us in Thibet, and, that putting aside the question of the policy which led up to Younghusband’s Expedition, I hope that no over punctiliousness on our part in respect to the suscepti bilities of other Powers may interfere with the continuance of existing good relations and the development of trade. Persia .—The stipulation contained in the tirst paragraph appears to me perfectly sound as regards the integrity of Persia, and the recognition of conditions affecting Seistan and our Baluchistan frontier. The second and third paragraphs, however, may be open to some doubt. You know from what I have written in former letters that I quite recognise the natural desire of Russia for an outlet in the Persian Gulf, but that outlet I should like to see (as suggested in the draft instructions) secured by the partici pation of Russia in the Baghdad Railway, in which case she might by a northern connection with that railway became a participator m the benefits of its seaport terminus at Bussorah. As regards the vertical, horizontal, or diagonal lines dividing a possible sphere of influence, I should be apprehensive as to our acceptance of the first; it would depend largely upon the point at which it would strike the Gulf,— presumably it would do so west of Bunder Abbas, but that would afford Russia a sea-board and possible seaport, entirely apart from the Baghdad Railway terminus,—and I should be afraid of the consequence of a purely Prussian port on the upper part of the Gulf,—even though in the first instance we had assurances of its purely commercial nature. I do not know in what directions it would be proposed to draw the horizontal or diagonal line, the first should I think be the most preferable for us, whilst the diagonal line might sufficiently guard our interests if it joined the Gulf at its head, probably from Meshed to Bussorah. Afghanistan.—^*, as you say, is a much thornier question. It is surrounded by weighty considerations as to which one cannot be too careful. Again I will take the instructions by paragraphs. («) Russia to recognise the territorial integrity of Afghanistan, taut she is outside the Russian sphere of influence, and under British guidance in her external policy. This is only asking Russia to confirm the present position which she has repeatedly accepted. (b) Direct communication between Russia and Afghan officials as to matters purely local and non-official. Personally, I dislike rules which it is impossible to enforce, and if the Amir chose to evade the rule which now exists forbidding such communications we could not prevent him. But atthe same time there are grave objections to allowing such communications in the first place it would be contrary to the Amir’s wish as expressed during the Dane Mission to Kabul. He refused to allow such free com munications with Russia, because he said it would be impossible for him to allow equally free communications between his subordinate officials and ourselves; he is particularly strict in forbidding such communications with us. At the present moment he behaves fairly well. There is no doubt a certain amount of irregular communication which he does not report, and of which we take no notice, but anything important he tells us of. I do not say that he would certainly not now agree to legalise communications with Russia, but if ther were allowed it would at once become impossible to know what is going on, and one could not guarantee their non-political complexion. Also, it is most important to remember that the present position has been agreed upon between the Amir and ourselves, and that we are not entitled to cancel it without his consent, whilst one must feel doubtful as to the effect on him of such a proposal made by us out of goodwill to Russia. In respect to a Russo-Afghan Frontier Commission, I should be very anxious as to its advisability unless we were strongly repre sented upon it. I am afraid the history of the Russo-Persian Frontier Commission is not encouraging as to what might happen; for I believe it is a fact that that Commission established itself some ten vears ago at a point 60 miles within the Persian frontier, and has remained there ever since notwithstanding Persian remonstrances, and one cannot foretell what results similar action on the northern frontier of Afghanistan might have. (o) Russia to abstain from sending agents into Afghanistan. This is simply a continuance of the present agreement. (dj and ((?) aie not, I think, of great moment, though the discontinuance of bounties to Russians might be useful. I do not know of the facilities given to British and Indian traders, but am sure we need not object to equal facilities to Russians. As fai as this in the instructions, it is proposed to maintain the present position, except that in respect to communications between the Amir and Russia we are to open a very dangerous door to intrigue, and to sacrifice the power which the Amir has agreed with us to exercise to check sucli intrigue. (/) I notv come to the railway question, “ Great Britain and Russia to “ agree not to extend their railways in the direction of the frontiers of “ Afghanistan during a period of ten yearsand I may say at once, with the greatest respect, that in my opinion we could not possibly be justified in considering such an agreement with a foreign Power. I can understand objections being taken to railway frontier policy, I admit the full right of anyone to hold opinions in favour of a policy of advance or of passive defence, but I cannot justify to myself a proposal which would not only grievously cripple the defence of our frontier, but would tend to delay for 10 years the prosperous development and better government of a large part of the north of British India. We must surely be masters in our own house. We surely cannot agree to sacrifice the security and internal improvement of a portion of our domains for the sake of our relations with a foreign Power. The frontier railway question is political as well as military, and it is not only political in its possible effect on foreign relations, but in respect to its4 influence on points directly connected with the welfare of the populations through which railways run. Political and military considerations are so closely involved that it is difficult to separate them, but leaving out the latter and considering for the moment the internal effects of the propose, agreement, we should, if it came into force, at once be precluded from bridnino- the Indus at Kushilgur, from connecting that point with Ivohat, from broadening our gauge from Kohat to Tiiull, from carrying a railway up the Knrram Valley, and from proceeding with the Kabul Kiver Railway. P ie Kurram Valley is now practically in British India, and pays revenue, and, thouo-h I admit the future strategical value of such a railway, the everyday value of its civilizing influence would, I feel sure, be even more patent to the ordiuarv observer. I cannot say how impressed I was by the evident results of the line from Nowshera to Dargai. After crossing our adminis trative frontier it passes through a flat country now rich m agricultural produce through a tribal administered district inhabited by the very people who were fighting against us in 1897, hut whose jirga met me at Dargai, their chief request in their address to me being for an improved railway service These people do not pay revenue, and as regards their own internal o-ovemment are practically independent. A railway to Kurram should give even better results than that, to Dargai, and it is in such means of civilization, in development of local resources, in. better intercourse with the people, and not in our old policy of everlasting punitive expeditions, that I believe the solution of our irontier difficulties will he found. Hie proposed agreement would prevent all attempts at such a solution. We should have to stand still for ten years, to give u P the hopes of closer relations with our tribes, and for the sake of our own safety to go on fichting them as we have done for generations. The prosperity resulting from our frontier railways is palpable to any one who sees or who enquires. . . At the present moment the frontier railway most en evidence is the Kabul River line, and since I have been at Simla I have had much conversation and correspondence with Kitchener about it, and am sending- you with this a letter of his in reply to questions of mine and as to strategical and political points we have discussed together. I entirely agree with what he lias written. I need therefore do no more than accentuate certain views, most of which he has dealt with. The proposed agreement is apparently based on the assumption that om frontier strategy is aimed only against a possible Russian advance. This was no doubt the case in the military policy of past years, hut I cannot say strongly enough how much conditions have altered and are altering, ouing to the growing strength, in the sense of military organisation and infinitely better armament, of Afghanistan and the frontier tribes. Putting the Amir aside, a frontier war now would he a very serious affair, the tribes are becoming better armed every day with breech-loading rifles, and a general rising on the frontier would far exceed in difficulty any such campaign as we have hitherto undertaken. War with the Amir would he more serious still. Speaking from memory, he is believed to have some 80,0JO legular troops, with a large reserve, and, in addition to this, the tribes might be expected generally to support him against us. Our success in such a war must depend largely on the turning positions we can occupy, i.e., on the command we have of the country in rear of the tribes, and the possibility ofD striking rapidly at Kabul, whilst the force required would under present conditions be so much greater than any force we have put into Afghanistan before, that the difficulties of supply would be enormously increased. AH this Kitchener explains very clearly, as does also Lord Roberts’ note which he quotes; and the proposed agreement with Russia would, in case of a tribal war, or a war with the Amir, forbid us to push on our railways to those very points of vantage which might be vital to us. Again, the agreement I suppose assumes that we are proposing a fair arrangement as regards ourselves in respect to the check that is to be put on any further advance of our railways for military purposes. Kitchener shows how far this is from being the case—by the Kabul River route we are still two and a half years from the Afghan frontier, whilst a railway connection between Charjui or Samarcand and the Afghan frontier is a matter of a few months. But more important than this is a point which Kitchener lias not dealt with. At the present moment, according to my information, the Russians have 12 steamers running on the Oxus above Charjni, each of which can carry 500 or 600 men, and which can run along the Afghan Oxus frontier as far as a place called Yangi Kila. The Russian military base is therefore already on the frontier of Afghanistan. There could he no difficulty in their increasing the number of their steamers, and the agreement does not propose to forbid water transport to the frontier. It is also believed that they have railway plant at Charjui ready for an immediate railway advance parallel to the Oxus, whilst I understand similar railway plant is stored at Kushk preparatory for an advance on Herat. I am not the least saying this in apprehension of any Russian advance, which may be a matter for a remote future, but only to show the position we occupy at present and the onesidedness in a military sense of the suggested agreement. We should have been on more even terms if we had bargained for no Russian advance by water or rail south of the frontier of Bokhara, a nominally independent State, I believe, but under Russian influence, much the same as Afghanistan is under our influence. I cannot but feel strongly opposed to any agreement with Russia in respect to railways. I should he inclined to let her do what she wants. She has practically, in respect to her propinquity to the Afghan frontier, got all she wants now, or can get it at very short notice. I earnestly hope it may be realised how such an agreement would tie our hands. We must remember, too, that even if the entente with Russia should last for ten years, at the end of that time Russia would still be in the same superior position as regards aggression in Afghanistan as Kitchener now shows her to he, whilst we should still be at the same disadvantage. To deal more distinctly with the Kabul River Railway, I have no doubt that besides its strategical importance its civilising influence will be of the greatest value to us. It will certainly, I should say, gain possession of the Khyber trade, and the tribes, as they have done elsewhere, will he ready enough to recognise its benefits. Any idea of giving up the railway would, I have no doubt, be misunderstood by the tribes as a sign of weakness, whilst it would lie a heavy loss to them in the subsidies they would receive in respect to its construction. The present Mahommedan movement would do its best to magnify our supposed weakness, and to impress it upon the Amir, whom we have encouraged to believe that in our railway construction he has some guarantee of our possible assistance if he is attacked from the S. S. 24. b6 north. I am sorry to say the Fan-Islamic agitation is much deeper rooted than I thought when you asked me as to the advisability of employing Mahommedan troops in Egypt. There is evidence that it is a wide spreading organisation, whose doings it is very difficult to follow, and its influence will certainly be brought to bear on the Amir, who would be encouraged to look with the gravest suspicion on any indication of our abandoning the railway. He would construe it to mean fear of Russia,—and possibly that our entente with her might mean his ultimate rum. The Afghan Envoy apprehends no opposition to the line. Resides all that I have said there is a somewhat more remote possible consequence of the agreement. What will Japan say ? In the face of our alliance with her, and her position in respect to Russia, are we justified in accepting an agreement with Russia which must seriously interfere with the value of our position on Russia’s flank should she and Russia again come to blows ? The Japanese are practically our allies in the defence of India, and we do not know what may come out of the present Russian chaos, or what effect it may have upon her future military policy. And we must bear in mind that the impression Japanese successes have produced on the Eastern mind has been disparaging to the military prestige of European forces. There is no doubt that the defeat of the Russian armies has encouraged the idea that, after all, the Western powers are not invincible. The Amir will rate the power of Russia much lower than he (has hitherto done, to say nothing of his opinion of ourselves, all of which will be again reflected in the opinion of the frontier tribes. His danger to us as a political factor has therefore to my mind increased, irrespective of the greater efficiency of his troops, in that he may not be disinclined to take a high-handed course in any dispute that may arise between Afghanistan and Russia, and to undervalue the strength of our own army in India. I cannot but think that primarily the Amir is a more dangerous neighbour to us than Russia, and therefore in respect to India a more necessary friend. He may easily get into hot water with Russia, and complicate us, or he may himself fall foul of us. To me it seems infinitely more important to keep on friendly and controlling terms with him than to enter into any bargain with Russia which might lessen our influence with him, or alienate him from us. I believe him to be sensitive, suspicious, and over confident in his own strength, but in my opinion it is vitally important to keep on good terms with him, and if he disappears, as he may do any day, to provide for the integrity of Afghanistan. if we are to enter upon an entente with Russia, let us bargain with her elsewhere than in Central Asia. There is a matter which, though not directly connected with railways, is a new consideration in respect to frontier defence which I may mention here. After the absorption of the old Erontier Eorce into the Indian Army, the frontier was largely protected by troops whose places have now been almost entirely taken by the Militia levies inaugurated by Curzon. There is much to be said for the system, but we must remember that these levies are raised entirely from the frontier tribes, from the very people who in a tribal rising would fight against us ; and though they are generally quite ready to fight their nearest family relations, we cannot ignore the fact that our regular troops have ceased to be responsible for the frontier, and that the Militia levies have now attained a strength of over 10,000 men. That is to say, wenow find ourselves in possession of 10,000 more armed Native troops than formerly, raised from a source as to the reliability of which we have no great experience. Again a fresh factor in respect to possible frontier difficulties. I have attempted only to deal broadly with the frontier railway question, but I hope L may say a few words on the actual alignment of the Kabul Elver Eailway, which was being much debated before I left England. After arriving at a point on the Kabul Elver known as “ mile 300,” there was a great difference of opinion whether the line should follow the Kabul Eiver, or turn to the left over high ground to a place called Shilman Ghakke, from which there was a very difficult descent in the direction of Ghakka. I knew before I left England that .Lord Koberts was stronglv in favour of the line following the river, whilst I found on my arrival here that Kitchener was as strongly in favour of the other line. I also found the India Office Despatch here, of 21st July 1905, pointing out, I thought very clearly, all the objections to the Shilman Ghakke route, and advocating the river alignment. I also found a draft despatch ready for transmission to the India Office in answer to the Despatch of 21st July, the arguments in Tvhich the Government of India refused to accept, they still supporting the Shilman Ghakke line, and condemning that by the Kabul Elver. The Government of India Despatch seemed to me most weak and faulty, and I accordingly withheld it till I had an opportunity myself of going into the question. The result has been a complete justification of Brodrick’s Despatch of 21st July, and undoubted proofs of the superiority of the river route, as to which Kitchener has entirely withdrawn his objections. This will, I am sure, interest those who have followed the discussion, especially Lord Koberts, should you mention it to him. The proposal for a large canton ment at a place called Torsuppa or elsewhere in tribal territory near Landi Khotal has also disappeared. I confess I am pleased at this, as it represents the opinion I have always held—in favour of the Kabul Eiver and against advanced positions. Of course I have only given you my own views in answer to your letter, but I certainly think that for reasons affecting the internal administration of India, independently of Imperial foreign policy, the Government of India should be fully consulted before the agreement suggested is entered into with Kussia. I am afraid I have written at great length, and hope that if I have expressed myself too strongly you will forgive me, for the Afghan question deeply interests me and is full of risks and doubts.Letter from Lord Kitchener to Lord Minto dated 23rd May 1906. My dear Viceroy, I have received your letter of the 19tli instant asking for my opinion on the question of the Frontier railways, and feel that you would like me to answer it at some length. I think that you will readily agree with me that the question of the alignment of the railway in the direction of Dakka is, comparatively speaking, one of minor importance. 1 he really important matter is the construction of the lines. Before attempting to express an opinion it seems desirable to review the situation as it stands at the present time. The inception of the Khyber railway was no scheme of my own. Naturally as an outside observer I had always recognised the strategic importance of improving our communications in that direction, and Lord Roberts had continually impressed upon me, both verbally, and by letter after my arrival in India, the immediate necessity of this railway in con nection with the defence of India. On mentioning the subject to Lord Curzon the already voluminous file dealing therewith was sent to me for perusal, and I was directed by Lord Curzon, when visiting that section of the frontier, to look out for an alternative line between the Khyber Pass and the Kabul River, neither of which routes was considered practicable. This I did on the actual ground, with experts, and [hence originated the Shilman Gakhe project which has since been so fully discussed. Of my views on the general question you are, I think, aware. They have been siven in numerous official and unofficial documents which you have doubtless seen. Before dealing, however, with such considerations, I propose to say a few r words concerning the past history of this Frontier railway question. As you aw T are, when the last Afghan war broke out there were no Russian railways of any sort or description in Central Asia ; and in India our railway in the direction of PeshaAvar terminated at Jhelum, and in the direction of Quetta, at Sukkur. I need not dilate on the enormous difficulties in the matter of supply and transport which were caused by these long drawn out lines of communication, since they are probably within your personal recollection. It will suffice to say that the most strenuous efforts were made to push on rail-head in the desired directions, with the result that, on the Northern line a temporary railway had been completed to Rawal Pindi by October 1880, too late, however, to be of any assistance for purposes of the war; whilst on the Southern line, rail-head had been pushed by May 1880 as far as Sibi. The original intention had been to push this line through to Quetta and Kandahar, but when it was decided to abandon this latter place, and to retire from Quetta, all further work on this line was stopped, the stores and plant sold or otherwise disposed of, and such portions of the permanent way as had already been laid down, removed. Meanwhile the Russians had embarked on an era of pronounced railway activity in Central Asia. The Central Asian, or as it was then called, the9 Ti a ns-Caspian, line was begun in 1880-81, and was completed to Kizil Arvat m 1882. 1 be construction of this line caused considerable alarm to the Indian and British Governments of the day, and as a consequence it was determined once more to resume the work so hurriedly abandoned two or three years previous!}, lime did not admit of the preparation of either estimates or detailed plans ; the work was to be pushed on at all costs, and a com mencement having been made in October 1883, the railway was eventually continued to Quetta in March 1887. Owing however, to the feverish haste with which the work had been carried out, haste, which had been greatly accentuated by the news, received in rapid succession, of the Panjdeh affair in March 1885, of the extension of the Russian railwav to Askabad in November 1885, and to Merv in July 1886, these hurried operations and temporary alignments resulted in the waste of vast sums of money, and it was not until many years after construction had been thus hurriedly resumed, that our railway communication with Quetta at last rested on a secure basis’. On our Northern line of communications the railway was completed to Peshawar in 1883, and here rail-head remained until the short and com paratively useless extension was pushed forward to Jamrud in 1901. I need not refer in detail to the various strategic lines in the Punjab which have been laid since Peshawar was reached. Some of these have been of considerable importance from a mobilisation point of view, but the only trans-Indus lines which have been constructed, if we except the short Peshawar-Warsak line now under construction, are, the toy tram-line running from Khushalgarh, through Kohat, to Thall—which from a military point of view is of extremely problematical value—and the Nowshera-Dargai line, \ery useful in the event of tribal disturbances, but of no service for the purpose of major operations in Afghanistan. ^ h ereas ] 't tllus t&gt; e seen that for a number of years we have been almost quiescent in the matter of Frontier railway construction, the Russians have during the same period successfully carried through an enormous railway programme, and practically all their lines have been made for purely strategical purposes and with but one ultimate view, the menacing of Afghanistan, Persia, and India. The railway which had reached Merv in July 1886 was completed to Samarkand in less than two more years In 1895 Samarkand was linked up with Tashkent and Andijan. The Merv- Khushk extension, which brought a Russian railway to the Afghan frontier withm some seventy miles of Herat, was begun in 1897 and formally opened in 1900. In the same year was commenced the construction of a still more important line, that between Orenburg and Tashkent, a railway which has more than doubled the power of Russia against Afghanistan. This was constructed at remarkable speed for a line more than a thousand miles in length, and was practically finished in September 1904, though the opening ceremony took place some months later. ° As has been repeatedly pointed out, the construction of all these Russian lines, only a few of which I have particularised, has completely changed the strategic conditions affecting the defence of India. Whereas in 1892, when the main line to Chaman was completed, the main danger threatened us on the line through Herat to Kandahar, we now have to face an equal, if not a greater, danger on the Oxus-KabuJ. line of advance. All authorities are, I think, now convinced that the line Kabul-Ghazni-Knndahar is the strategic front which we must be prepared to take up for the defence of India and S. S. 24. c10 that it is a line which we must on no account allow to be even seriously threatened. Our preparations should, I consider, be governed by these considerations. It was precisely on this account that we constructed the extension to Cbaman in the days when the Kandahar end of this strategic position was that most menaced. The railway which we are now considering was designed specially to meet the danger which now threatens the Kabul Hank of our strategic front. Its cost, though heavy, is a mere fraction of what we very rightly, though extravagantly, expended in Baluchistan, am in my opinion it is not only an absolutely essential measure of precaution, hut one the abandonment or postponement of which, at the present moment, will make it necessary for us to reconsider our whole defensive preparations. If in time of war we cannot seize and maintain our hold of the Kabul- Kandahar line—and without the railway under discussion it is problematical whether it would be in our power to do so-it would he necessary to consider what could be our alternative line of defence. I have personally inspected the whole length of our frontier from Nushki to the Pamirs, hut I am unable to indicate where, failing the Kabul- Kandahar nosition, we should be able, with advantage of terrain, and the support of the Afghans, to find such a line. Any power dominating Afghanistan at Kabul, and attracting to her sice the tribes on our frontier, would constitute so serious a menace to the Empire that I consider that, no matter how peaceful the immediate aspect of the international horizon may appear, we should lose neither time nor chance now, in time of peace, and with money available, to take the simple and obvious measures which alone can avert so dangerous a state of affairs. In making this line we should he hut attempting in modest fashion to restore the balance disturbed by Russia’s vast achievements in railway construction in Central Asia. If we abandon it we are m danger oi repeating our mistake of 1880. I attach to this letter a small sketch map which shows how the railway situation on each side stands at the present moment, and which marks in red the lines constructed since 1892, the time when our frontier railway policy came to a standstill. It will be seen from this how greatly Russian construction has progressed, and how little we have done on our side to maintain the balance. It may perhaps be argued that if, in some problematical^ rapprochement of the near future, Russia promises to refrain from completing her railway extension to the Oxus, we should well he able to afford to drop all ideas of making such frontier lines as that under discussion. This I consider to be a dangerous fallacy which cannot he too strongly controverted. The respective conditions are on an entirely different footing. M hereas in our case it admittedly takes considerably over two years of heavy work to bring our rail-head to the frontier, in the case of Russia the Oxus extension is a question of only a few months. Running for the most part, and, if necessary, entirely, along the level banks of the river, Russia, could begin such a line in a score of places at once, instead of working merely from rail-head, as we are compelled, by the nature of the country with which we should have to deal, to do. Moreover actual experience has shown that Russia could lay a railway of this sort in that particular region without our being very much the wiser. . I pass now to the consideration of the lapse of time which must necessarily take place before a railway towards Dakka would he of practical value to us for the purposes of a campaign. I have not overlooked the fact that11 C) this must lie oi considerable length, but at any rate if we construct such a line as far as we can now, we should have at least two years’ work to the -ood. Moreover, while it is doubtless the case that a line stopping short at the Afghan frontier whether at Shilman Gakhe, or at some other point on the river—could not reach the plain of Ningrahar at Loi Dakka for possiblv some time, yet, once it had reached that place construction could proceed at a rapid rate, and the line would at once become of the greatest possible assistance. I think that it will be admitted that a line such as is here contemplated would not only be of the greatest value in the critical phases, hut probably the saving factor, of any campaign in Afghanistan. It has been suggested that the recent improvements made in our com munications with Afghanistan by the doubling of the Khyber Pass track and the construction of the Mullagori road, have greatly improved our position. This is true as against the tribesmen, but al! these lead into the bottle neck of Landi Khana, and from that point onward things are no better, even it they are not worse, than was the case at the end of the last Afghan war. You will remember that at that time we had a graded road suitable for wheeled traffic all the way to Kabul. This has now fallen into the greatest disrepair, and in some of its most important sections,-notably the passage of the Jagdalak and Lataband Passes-has been completely neglected by the Afghans, who, using merely pack animals, prefer to follow the shorter, but infinitely more difficult, hill tracks. I do not think, there fore, that it is safe to assume that our communications towards Kabul, once the Afghan frontier is crossed, are anything but indifferent, if not bad/ The extent tc which confinement to tracks unworthy of the name of roads, and the difficulty of maintaining animal transport on the Peshawar-Kabul line, would limit our power of action, does not seem to he generally realised. In this connection 1 would draw attention to a note written by Lord Roberts, less than two years ago, on this very subject. He says: ‘Hn Lord Kitcheners Paper, ‘The Preparation of the Indian Army for TV ar, a very careful calculation is made of the number of transport animals that would he required to mobilise the Field Army, and stress is laid on the necessity for the railway system of India being extended to the limits of our frontier in the direction of Ghazni and Kabul, to enable the Field Army to be rapidly placed at the decisive strategical points, and be maintained there. “The last four words ‘and be maintained there' are what I desire to (Iran particular attention to, for I have no hesitation in sayinp that it would be impossible to maintain a force of anything like the size Contemplated in the Memoranda I have referred to without railway communication to the foot of the Pei war Kotal, and to our frontier in the direction of Jalalabad with detraining stations at both of these termini, and sufficient material stored at the latter to carry the line on to Kabul with the least possible delay.” After pointing out that, judging from his own experience in 1879-80, it would be difficult, if not impossible, to maintain at or beyond Kabul much more than one complete division of troops, were we compelled to rely on the roads and pack transport alone, whereas the situation would demand that^ four or five divisions should be placed in that area. Lord Roberts continues:— “ 1 have frequently pointed out during the last five-and-twenty years that u-e could not hope to maintain a large army in Afghanistan without having rail communication to Kabul or its immediate vicinity. With the12 Amir so hostile as he is at present, we cannot hope for this, until after war has broken out, but we can meanwhile extend our railway system to the limits oi our frontier, and I cannot too strongly urge upon the Defence Committee the supreme importance of taking this matter into their earnest and earliest consideration. “ The two extensions, one from Peshawar towards Dakka, on the road to Jalalabad and Kabul, should be commenced as soon as possible, as the section which lies between the Khyber Pass and the Kabul river runs through a very difficult country, and must inevitably take a long time to construct. It is also essential that there should be no delay in beginning the broad gauge line from Khushalgarh through Kohat and Kurram to the foot of the Pei war Kotal, for although the country is fairly easy, the distance (152 miles) is longer.” As regards the larger question of Russian aggression with which this frontier railway problem must be closely connected, I do not think that the bogey of a Russian invasion need affect its elucidation. I am one of those who maintain that though an invasion of India by Russia from her present bases is a possible, though lengthy, operation, it is nevertheless an extremely improbable one. In saying this, I have of course, borne fully in mind the changes in the general situation brought about by recent events. The Russians themselves now affect to scout the invasion theory, and I think with some honesty. I am perfectly prepared therefore to put on one side any possible danger of such an event occurring within a period of several a ears to come. I leei, too, that I need not enlarge here on the ever present possibility of European complications, capable of reacting on our position in the Middle East, since such contingencies will doubtless occur to von. There are, however, other dangers which we must take into most serious consideration. There can be little doubt, for instance, that the victories of Japan over Russia have brought about so great a diminution of the latter’s prestige throughout Asia as to constitute a potential menace to the continuance of peace, which it would be rash entirely to ignore. As a ease in point I may cite the undoubted change which has taken place in the attitude of the Amir and Afghans generally towards Russia, a change assuredly due to the diminished prestige of the latter Power, 'the over weening v anity of Habibullah and his entourage was sufficiently shown during the residence of the recent Mission in Kabul, and I think L danger that we must ever hear in mind is that the Amir may, and not improbably will, treat Prussia in the future with less consideration than hitherto. We can afford to, and do, put up with scant courtesy at times from Kabul, if only to keep the peace, but it is a matter for consideration, whether Russia, with her shaken prestige in Central Asia, could be relied on tamely to swallow the affronts to which we sometimes submit. Tiiere is, I think, always danger of an incident arising on the Russo- Afghan border which might lead to very awkward situations. If Russia were to quarrel with the Amir we should have either to support the Amir, in accordance with the terms of our Treaty, if he was right, or coerce him ourselves if he were wrong, assuming, of course, that the resources of diplomacy had tailed to effect a peaceable solution. This latter course of action might, and very possibly w^ould, lead to a state of anarchy in Afghanistan. In such circumstances much would depend on our general state of prepare 1 ness at the time, as a safeguard agaisnt further7 13 complications which might conceivably result in the partition of Afghanistan. If on the other hand, Russia, through motives of pure aggression, were to advance into Afghanistan, then I am decidedly of opinion that it would be necessary to treat such an advance as a casus belli. This would be essential both from the point of view of our treaty obligations and from that of our material interests. If we did not adopt such a course we should practically have renounced all further right to any special position in Afghanistan, the first and essential line of defence for India, and both Amir and people would hasten to make terms with what was obviously the stronger Power. I need hardly point out how, in sucli circumstances, our position in this country would be shaken. All these are points which I think are thoroughly appreciated by all those who have studied the subject, and I am sure that in writing to you it is unnecessary to enter into them at length. What is, however, less appreciated, is how impotent we are under existing conditions, either adequately to defend the Amir against Russia, or even to coerce him ourselves, should this necessary railway construction be abandoned. I am afraid I cannot follow the view that this reversal of a railway policy which we, in common with His Majesty’s Government, have been consistently following for the last few years, would tend to increase the friendship of either the Amir or the tribes towards us. On the contrary, I cannot help thinking that so hurried and remarkable a volte-face, however much it might be welcomed by our enemies, would be deplored by all those sections who are at present friendly to us. and would tend only to strengthen the disbelief in our power,—amounting almost to contempt,—now affected certainly by the Amir, and to a less extent possibly by the tribesmen. Ibis feeling I regard as one of the greatest dangers to the preservation of peace on and beyond our frontier, and anything which would tend, even remotely, to increase it, I should consider as much to be deplored. I think that, should we now abandon our railway policy, the immediate result would he that we should find the Amir more “ difficile ” than ever whilst the tribesmen would not improbably he emboldened by what they could only regard as an exhibition of extraordinary weakness on our part. I think that on most, if not all, these points, we are in substantial agreement, and that you appreciate, as I do, that the increased, and ever- increasing, efficiency of armament of the tribes is an argument in favour of the most complete preparedness on our part. I am, as you know, opposed on principle to aggressive measures against the tribes, but I recognise that^ however humble may be our attitude towards them, they will continue to constitute a serious and ever-present danger, against which we ought always to be thoroughly prepared ; and, apart from more Imperial considerations, I can conceive of no better guarantee of continued peace on the frontier than the making of two such railways as are now on our programme, which will enable us to dominate on three sides the most formidable and important section of the whole borderland, and will, at the same time, provide them with those increased facilities for trade which have hitherto invariably proved a great civilising factor amongst the Rathans. When, in addition to the more formidable power of the tribes, it is recollected that the Amir is now carrying out an enormous increase in his armaments, you will, l think, agree that a combination of tribesmen andn Afghans against us would constitute a very serious coalition, for against the former alone we found it necessary in 1S97 to mobilise the whole of the existing Field Army. The Amir through the Mullahs, and as his father did before him, never ceases to tell the tribes that a time for Jihad will assuredly come. Quite recently we have been warned by Lord Cromer that this is a weapon which the Sultan holds in reserve against us. We know too that the Pan-Islamic movement Avas never more active than at the present moment, and that emissaries arc even now passing to and fro between Sultan and Amir. We are aware that the Amir is about to import thousands of the most modern magazine rifles, and millions of cartridges for them ; that he proposes to develop his manufacture of artillery to a irreat extent. E\'en taking the most optimistic vieAvs of the chances of future rupture Avould it be statesmanlike or even prudent to neglect simple and obvious precautions within our own borders, and within also our power and means, with a view to meeting the possible risks with which we may some day be brought face to face ? I think not, and being convinced as I am, that the shortest, safest, and most economical method of dealing with the trouble, should it arise, would be the present construction of the railvrays to Avhich \\ r e stand committed, I ha\ r e no hesitation in saying that I should view with apprehension any proposal to reverse so deliberately thought out and adopted a policy. In this opinion 1 feel I am supported by all military, and I think all political, authorities in this country, and to these I would add Lord Curzon, who, writing on this subject just twelvemonths ago, said:—“It is not by “ tinkering here or there that the question of military advance and transport “ upon the Kabul line can be solved. It can only be by a broad and bold “ policy of roads and railways.” I am afraid that this letter lias run to excessive length, but the issues raised are so \ T ast, and so important, that I have considered it necessary to deal with them in some detail. The time has never been more suitable for making such a line as that under discussion. India is in a peaceful and prosperous condition, and the money can be made available ; whereas, if Ave delay, who knoAvs but that we may enter upon a period of famine and financial stringency, such as avc passed through a f«Av years since ? If we put it off now, when everything is in its favour, it will never be done until urgent necessity compels its immediate inception. It will then be too late Avhereas by constructing it now Ave should spare ourselves the hurry and waste, which must otherwise inevitablv occur. There only remains for consideration the question of the line to be taken by the Khyber Eailway. Naturally the river route would gNe us better gradients, and offer certain facilities of construction. But considerations of local politics must finally decide the two alternatives, and so long as the political officers concerned consider that adequate and permanent arrange ments for the safe-guarding of the river route can be made, doubtless the eventual decision Avill be in its favour. Yours very truly, Kitchenek.SECRET. &amp; AFGHANISTAN. When the subject of Afghanistan is raised in the impending negotiations at St. Petersburg, Sir A. Nicolson is instructed to formulate the following points as bases of an agreement between Russia and Great Britain. Russia to recognize the territorial integrity of Afghanistan and to acknowledge Afghanistan as being outside the Russian sphere of influence, and under British guidance in all matters of external policy. Direct communication to be allowed between Russian officials and officials designated by the Ameer as to matters of purely local character and of non-political complexion. The creation of a Russo-Afghan Commission, similar to the permanent Russo-Persian Frontier Commission, for the settle ment of tribal and boundary disputes might present a possible solution of this question. Query insert — Russia to discontinue giving bounties in subsidies to Russian trade into Af ghanistan. Russia to abstain from sending Agents into Afghanistan. Great Britain to place no obstruction to Russian trade enjoying the same facilities in Afghanistan as British and British Indian traders now enjoy. Great Britain and Russia to agree not to extend their railways in the direction of the frontiers of Afghanistan during a period of ten years. s.s. .SECRET. PERSIA In the event of the Russian Government raising the question of an agreement relating to Persia on Sir A. Nicolson’s arrival in St. Petersburg, it would be advisable that lie should lay down as a general basis, before entering upon any discussion, that His Majesty’s Government attach the highest importance in any negotiations that take place upon the recognition of the independence and integrity of Persia, and, with a view to securing tranquillity upon her frontiers, the recognition of the province of Seistan and the provinces coter minous with the British frontier in Baluchistan as entirely within the British sphere of influence and outside the zone of future Russian railwav enterprise. The only indication which His Majesty’s Go vernment have of recent years received from the Russian Government of their views as to a settle ment of the Persian question has been their desire for a commercial outlet in the Persian Gulf. His Majesty’s Government would present no objection to the realisation of such a project, provided there was no question of the construction of the terminus of a future Russian railway at Bunder Abbas or at any point to the eastward. A commercial outlet for Russian trade in the Persian Gulf may possibly be found by the participation of Russia in the Bagdad Railway. Subject to these considerations His Majesty’s Government would be ready to discuss any pro posals put forward by the Russian Government, whether based on the joint co-operation of the two countries for the development and amelioration of Persia, or on the division of spheres of influence by a line drawn vertically, horizontally, or diago nally from north-east to south-west, or any other scheme that the Russian Government might prefer to suggest. S. S.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00031b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/A169</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00031b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/A169</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Anglo-Russian Relations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1906/1906</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-05-21T00:36:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence in this file is not in chronological order. Following the draft instructions, the most recent letter, which is dated 12 June 1906, appears first, followed by an enclosed letter, which is dated 23 May 1906.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the first folio, and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file begins with draft instructions, under the heading 'Anglo-Russian Relations', apparently written by John Morley, Secretary of State for India, for Sir Arthur Nicolson, British Ambassador at St Petersburg, in advance of negotiations over an Anglo-Russian agreement.The instructions are divided into two sections, 'Persia' and 'Afghanistan', and they concern Britain's and Russia's respective interests in Persia and Afghanistan. The instructions outline important points on which Nicolson is expected to base any future agreement with Russia (of which a fundamental requirement is Russia's recognition both of the independence and integrity of Persia, and of the territorial integrity of Afghanistan). The remaining instructions relate to issues of trade in Persia and Afghanistan.The draft instructions are followed by an extract from a private letter from Lord Minto [Gilbert John Elliot Murray Kynynmound], Viceroy and Governor-General of India, to John Morley, dated 12 June 1906.In the letter, Lord Minto responds to Morley's draft instructions for Sir Arthur Nicolson. Minto gives his opinions on the wording and possible implications of each paragraph of the draft instructions. Most of Minto's letter details his opposition to the idea that Great Britain and Russia should agree not to extend their railways in the direction of the frontiers of Afghanistan for the next ten years, for which Minto offers a number of political and military considerations.Minto's letter is followed by a letter from Lord Kitchener [Horatio Herbert Kitchener] to Lord Minto, dated 23 May 1906, in which Kitchener responds to Minto's letter of 19 May 1906, which requested Kitchener's opinion on the question of the Frontier railways. In his letter, Kitchener argues that the possibility of extending the British railway system is not only of great strategic importance for the defence of British India, but is also important for maintaining friendly relations with the Amir [Emir] of Afghanistan [Habibullah Khan].Kitchener's letter is followed by two loose folios which repeat word for word the aforementioned draft instructions on Afghanistan and Persia (folios 8 and 9 respectively). Both sets of instructions have the heading 'Secret'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Afghanistan</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Russia</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander-in-Chief, India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Great Thibet</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Russian Empire</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Railway lines</topic></subject><subject><topic>Anglo-Russian Entente (1907)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x00031b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>