<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100054910168.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-29T11:07:17.403Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">tr i % . . &lt;§&gt; -.Q_£ ISLE G R A High Commiosioner Bag-dad to So of So for India„ j J Bated Basra 7„2„21 Rec ^ ^ R Davidson salary of 2„500 rupees,, rising by annual inoremer? of 100 rupees 0 free housirjg and lighting 0 ration allowance at present flxed at t20 rupees monthly„ pension contribution (? wij.i be) paid if Soudan Government agree 3 in this case., to arrangements outlined in your despatch Political No 3?n June 26th 1919 (? arrears of) Soudan salary bei% recovered and credited to this Governmento -Free passage to Basrah with pay on journey oui at either half Mesopotamian salary or Soudan salary which ever is greatero Full Mesopotamian salary on landing at Basrah 0 On three years contracts leave counts at rate of 2 months per annum once during currency of contract with voyage leave both ways in addition,, During total period of such absence, full Mesopotamian salary,, but absence does not count as active service under contract. No leave under Soudan Government rules eamable or admissible during period of contract unless earned prior to transfer are then only granted in special cases, and with prior consent of Soudan Government who will pay Soudan salary according to their rules for such additional leave. Question of more frequent leave on a 5 year contract under consideration, tut will cepend largely on exigencies of service,,A - rwV In any further commnnication on this subject, please quote No.E 16268/14/44. and address, not to any person by name, but to— ^ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.]. i r- y S -i », 8 'f ' r $bV&gt; U 1 * © J J Forei Foreign Office. S.W.l. 6th. January 1921 Sir:- 7 JAN 1921 ( - 7/ith reference to your letter No.P ^642 of the 29th./ Fecemher on the subject of the proposed appointffieht-^f^ Mr.Davidson as a successor to Sir E.Bonham Carter, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India that Mr. Davidson, vrho has been in the Sudan Government service for over ten years, has an excellent reputation for capacity» and energy and tact with the natives. 2. He would in His Lordship's opinion be an excellent choice, if the Sudan Government will agree to spare him. 3. His Lordship would be prepared, should Mr. Secretary Montagu so desire, to telegraph to His Majesty's High Commissioner, Cairo, regarding the possibility of arranging a transfer and the terms on which Mr.Davidson's services would be available. 4. It is however unlikely that appreciable progress can be made towards the completion of any such arrangement until some information can be given of the terms of the appointment, and His Lordship would accordingly be glad to receive some indication of the probable pay and duration of the appointment as early as possible. I am, ^ 'V Sv Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.X.JoDo/H.P OJLi-J HI I E L 3 G R A V. Prom High Commissionor Bagdad , to Secretary of State,, Dated 29 0 11 0 20 o Received 2. 12 0 209„ 9oa 0 m u ■&gt;2-^01920 B. 14419c Please see India Office letter .6159 23rd august to Foreign Office, reference successor to Bonham Carter,, We should not delay further in seeking suitable x successor* Especially in view of our responsibilities under Mandate* He must be a (? good) lawyer whose legal opinions will carry due weight (? with His Majesty’s Government) 0 I made private enquiries regarding Mr 0 ilmos of Egyptian Service, but he is not available,, It is suggested that Davidson of London Civil Service would be suitable. If you agree will you please enquire if his services are available 0 and on what terms? This fullstop was telegraphedof E.H./H.P Prom Civil Commissioner, to S. of S* Dated Bagdad, 26. 8 . 20. Beceived 27th, 4.p.m. X 10305. Your telegram Eo. 871, 24th August. There is no objection to question of successor being held up at present, so long as it is clearly understood that Sir Edgar Bonham Carter will not remain here after 1st April next 'v ^ vj Lo' ' C A nr ' 7 'V^PUT AWAY WITH Office of th.e.‘Civil Coitinissioner - —Baghdad,, the 15th July, 1920. *] '' i S39' i Q 2 O \V &lt;r J v ^ith. reference to iny telegrB^iii of the 24th June, 7677, I h&amp;ve the honour to*enclose for your information copy of a letter, dated 12th July, in which Sir Edgar Bonham Carter intimates his desire to retire not later than April next year. I have the-honour to he, Sir, Your obedient Servant, /l' -T 1 Lieut.-Colonel, I.A. Acting Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia. (15 u&lt;M The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office London, S.V/. 1* 1 i; / ^' s \ / ♦Copy of letter from Judicial Secretary, ref. retirement. G.L.Judicial Department, Baghdad* p, 12th July, 1920. Sir, I write to confirm previous conversations with you when I informed you that I wished to retire not later than April in next year. I may add that I should he glad to retire earlier if it is convenient to His Majesty’s Government or to Sir Pecy Cox that I should do so: but in view of the difficult legal and political questions which will have tc be settled during the next few months, I consider that I ought to stay on until April if required. Being now in my fifty-first^fear, no explanation of my desire to retire is necessary; but I may say that, but for the war, it was my intention to ^ave retired from Government service before this: that upon resignation of my appointment in the Sudan I came here for the period of the war only: and that since August 1914 I have had in all only one month’s leave and have had no laave of any sort since my arrival here in September, 1917. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, (Sgd*) E. Bcnham Carter, Judicial Secretary. To: The Civil Commissioner, Baghdad.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. E 7926/14/44 and address, not to any person by name, but to— (i The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 1 Foreign Office. S.W.l. August 16th. 1920. Sir:- I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to acknowledge the receipt of your letter l T o. 5048 of the 7th. ultimo, on the subject of a successor to Sir E. Bonham Carter, and to state for the information of Mr. Secretary Montagu that His Lordship regrets, after enquiry into the matter, that he'has no suitable candidate to recommend for the post of Judicial Secretary to the Civil Administration of Mesopotamia. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, &gt;FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. ^ /. UDc (Z^JAA Au/ U' h t CfyisvU' &amp; cf x ^AJUJb^(/\ U~ r 4 ^ Ml- L&lt;vi (rfu- 4? (qJJ^ Ur a faXl ^ / Ci&gt;v ^0 ofx^ywA. &lt;^Ci f Ic&amp;a^ , &gt;/£^o ^v dsu^ir £ fa4. &gt;s3^/Xn ^►^7 puiafcri h n AM^^^ i (KA^rM4r i / ^C/i &amp;)Ma)l£^ 4 i£$l\ £ j'O, hi /&lt;C^nc /Wu, CclcLiiy ft h (aQjl^JL tsfttf Cfrft/rvVJL (iftfaA l^jJbrrw*\fajj W^yAAMiA . /tfr ;U j o-j Latsv-s, . V^2 vV^t\ ' 3 • -•© w / A.. 1 / ^ Previous Papers IO 873—1 500 2/20Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, J and^le following Nr quoted 33565/1920 Downing Street, July 1920 Sir, I am directed by Viscount Vilner to acknowledge the receipt of your letter P/5048 of the 7th of July on the subject of the post of Judicial Secretary in Mesopotamia, and to request you to inform Mr. Secretary Montagu that he would be glad to learn what are the emoluments of the appointment, and whether j it is intended that the appointment should be permanent or temporary. I am, Sir, Your most obedient Servant,5'‘4-fc 3 In any further cornmnnication on this subject, please quote No- E 7926/14/44. and address, Foreign Office. S.y/.i July 15th. 1920. not to any person by name, but to— “ The Cnder-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, Lomion, S.W.l. Sir:- I am directed oy Bari Curzon or diedleston to acknowledge tne receipt oi' your letter Uo.P.5048 of the ‘ : ’ on the subject of a successor to Sir E. Bonham Carter K.C.M.G., C.I.E., the post of Judicial Secretary, Baghdad. nis Lordship would be glad to learn the amount oj. the salary and allowance which Sir B. Bonham Carter 1 successor will receive, and the arrangements proposed with regard to his pension. In the meanwhile His Lordship is causing preliminary enquiries to be made. I am, Sir Your most obedient humble Servant e Under Secretary of State India Office.T A (Received 26th June, 12.3G p.m.) tv ^&lt;1 V] R.7677. Sir Ed,r&lt;ar Bonham-Carter will have completed three years continuous service in Mesopotamia in September next. He 7;a.3 desirous of leave this summer ^out consented to remain for a further year in view of acute shortage i experienced officers. He is not willing to remain after April 1st next and his successor should, if possible come out in September next so as to work under him*' for six months before taking over. Hill His Majesty’s Govern ment be good enough to consider matter with a view to making a suitable selection.I cannot recommend Knox nor do I consider (■■? even if Pun]aub Government would spare him, would adequately fill post though he is doing good work in his present capacity and has a thorough knowledge of Arabic and enjoys excellent relations with the local people. Successor to Sir Edgar Bonham-Carter should have full professional legal cualif ications, thorough knowledge of Arabic and, if -pssdbie possible^ ^eiiougn^pj ac^ i experience of legal adviser system Ui (corrupt gr^up) thr 1 *) tal.e charge.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100054910168.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/517/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100054910168.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/517/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4097/1914 Pt 7 Mesopotamia: administration; personnel; proposed appointment of a successor to Sir E Bonham-Carter as Judicial Secretary</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1920/1921</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-10T15:44:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (28 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This item contains correspondence regarding the hiring of civilian staff in Baghdad following the British occupation of Iraq during the First World War.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100054910168.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>