<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000040_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T07:27:49.795Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MrTelegram 3 From Political Resident at Bahrain. To Air Officer Commanding, Habbaniyah. Uo.T/490. Bated the 27th October 1940. IMPORTANT. C.A.3.O.C. reported three aeroplanes over or near BHAHRAN night of 25/26 October. Can you confirm ? RjSSIBi£NT. C.V.A. Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain. \/CONFIDENTIAL. L 'x c No. G/398 of 1940. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Senior Naral Officer, Persian Gulf, 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, y and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s).- ., xx with a request that he will reassure oil Jompany* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... 28 th ■ October • 1940. Gamp, Bahrain Reference to previous correspondence : j. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. To !• l« Political Resident*., tele* only. gram So.1/490 of 27th October 1940. Planes reported over 2* Air Officer Commanding, DHAHRaR. Habba.*iya*&amp; telegram Ko• a/ 755 of 27th October 1940.Telegram Q,. 5 i rorn Air Officer Commanding, Habbaniya. T 0 Political Resident, at Bahrain No«A/755* Dated 27th received 28th October 1940. Important . Min Your T/490 of October 27th. Ko information available here • Confirmed no R.A.F.aircraft in area.Confidential No« C/846-l.a/43 Dated the 30th October 1940 Deixr Mr* Ohiiger, Vith reference to the report of three aeroplanes having been over or near Dhahran on the night of 05/*&lt;!6th October, enquiries from the Air Force Authorities in Iraq have elicited the reply that no information of the pres.nee of any such planes has been received by them, nor were there any Royal Air Force aircraft oper, ting in the vicinity. Yours sincerely, F. W. Ohiiger, Lsq., California Arabian Standard Oil Company, limited, iJhshran - Saudi Arabia.California Arabian Standard Oil Company © Dhahran, Saudi Arabia October 29, 1940 ( 7 Dear Mr. Hallowes: We refer to your letter D*0.No.C/808-1.a/43 of October 21, 1940: Immediately following the incident of October 19th we ceased regular operations and imposed a complete blackout in the Dhahran Camp and Field, and at the A1 Khobar Pier and loading terminal. With the full coop eration of the Saudi Arabian Government officials, the blackout was imposed on the neighboring villages and Bedouin camps. Automobile traffic at night has been dis couraged, and those automobiles which are used have been provided with dark blue headlights. Our present regulation is that lights must be kept to a minimum from dusk until 9:00 P. M. After 9:00 P. M. the blackout is complete, and is enforced by a special patrol. It will be understood that the present complete blackout is made possible by the cessation of Company operations. It is our intention to resume operations in the near future. We shall, of course, restrict the lighting required to the bare minimum necessary to assure reasonable safety in operating practices. It will be necessary to have occasional lights on two drilling rigs which will be operating. There will be dim lights in the Stabilizer plant area. It will be necessary to burn waste gas in a flfirerl We are designing a flare to burn with a dull blue flame to eliminate the beacon effect of our previous flares. The residential and industrial area will continue to be blacked out. We have forwarded to Mr. Rodstrom a box of assorted bomb fragments for delivery to you for your inspection. Vie shall keep you fulty informed of any movements of aircraft in this area. In this connection you may be interested in the aerial reports of aircraft movement wehave had to date. At about 4:00 A. M. on the morning of October 19th a watchman at the Abqaiq camp (60 kilo meters 3. 45 ° W. from Qhahran) reported that aircraft had passed over coming from the direction of Bahrein. A watchman at an outlying camp about 35 kilometers S. 45° W. from Abqaiq reported that airplanes had passed over a little after 4:00 A. M. The Customs official stationed at Manifa, a port about 190 kilometers north of here, reported that two planes passed over flying in a general westerly direction between 3:00 and 4:00 o 1 clock A. M. On the morning of October 20th at 2:55 A. M. the watchman at Abqaiq reported an aircraft overhead. The alarm was turned in by radio, and we had an air raid alert in camp. We neither saw nor heard a plane and gave the 'All clear' at 4:30 A. M. Two Americans and their native crew at work on one of our camp wells reported having seen a low flying airplane to the north east of the field at 5:50 A. M. This machine was flying towards Bahrein. Please be assurred of our keen desire to be of any possible assistance to you. Yours sincerely, CED :R R. T. Hallowes, Esq., The Agency, Bahrein.D Secret. X 'l (D No. C/411 of 1940. cS w ^ &amp; 0 IM The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Political Agent, Bahrain -air 2, The/Liaison Officer, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ($1 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. Camp, Bahrain• Dated 29th October 1940 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Political Resident * s tele gram No.T/503 of 29th October 1940. Subject. ■Plights by R.A.P aircraft over Saudi territory.Telegram From Inter 3 S~\1J \ / O 4 * To Repeated Copy given Political Resident, at Bahrain. H.M.Minister, Jedda. Secretary of State for India, London. Middle Last Intelligence Centre, Cairo, to Political Agent, Bahrain, and ^l(ir Liaison Officer, Bahrain. No.T/bO.3. Dated the 29th October 1940. w!4y telegram No.T/481 of October 24th. Air Officer Conuoanding states that R. A.i? • aircraft have standing orders not repeat not to fly over Saudi territory in any circumstances unless compelled to do so for forced landing. Information as to flights over Bahrain is not of any value to them since such flights do not touch their territory. RjSBIDjSHT. —</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000040_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/671</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000040</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/671</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/1 R Reports from C.A.S.O.C. A.R.P. etc.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-21T21:47:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-9; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file’s contents relate to an enquiry made by the California-Arabian Standard Oil Company (CASOC), dated 27 October 1940, to the Political Agency in Bahrain, asking if British aircraft were flown over the company’s refinery at Dhahran [al-Ẓahrān] in Saudi Arabia on the night of 25/26 October 1940. A telegram from the Political Resident, dated 29 October 1940, states that the Royal Air Force (RAF) have orders not to fly over Saudi territory. A letter from Floyd William Ohliger of CASOC to R T Hallowes at the Bahrain Political Agency, dated 29 October 1940 (ff 6-7) describes CASOC’s response to the bombing of the Dhahran refinery by Italian aircraft on 19 October 1940, with details of: air raid precautions (ARP) taken, including blackout measures; cessation of regular operations at the refinery; the intention to resume operations at the refinery with measures to restrict lighting; a description of the sighting of planes on 19 October 1940, with times, location and directions.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Dhahran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum refineries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air raid precautions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000040#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>