<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000076_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-26T10:39:23.540Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Secret &amp; Ifer&amp;on&amp;l, ?a /pea Jonaulate and Political Agency, u:r-n? . 31st :«roh, 1951 . X 7 y dear 3ir Rupert, V-' /oods-Ballard tells me that the Sultan has ^ust decided to make a grant for a five year plan separate from the normal administrative budget to Ifqplement Hartley’s report, The amount of the grant has not yet been given nor have I been told whether the plan will, after all, be put into effect around Sohar or nearer Muscat. 2, The Sultan also seems much more disj osed to see Bosworth making journeys here, and may agree to some weekly arrangement, 5m On the subject of lighterage, I gather Malcolm of Gray ^aokenzie*s met with no success (though a kindly reception) when he was granted an interview with the Sultan, The B.I«S,Xi, Have, I fear, weakened their case by reducing their calls at LUsoat and thereby indicating that the voluma of cargo 14 diminishing, 1 understand from Grant that he was against this, but it seems the revised sehedu le may even have been his device, I do not know. but I feel tl-wat they might have been franker with me of their intention (or rather decisions as it seems) for I was still plugging the case for compelling the contractor to Increase lighterage, or alternatively, let others in on the monopoly. 4, Am regards mails and passengers, only two calls a week ship should now Hi, ExoaUSnoy Sir Rupert U«y, K.C.I.K., O.S.I. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN,- 2 - sliip should now be allowed to take oargo, mail* or passengers from Muscat, whilst Bosworth’s visits will be additionally welcome, if th«y materialise; though I am not sure how locals will take to flying, which from here to Sharjah seems usually to be buin y. 5* Since he has been back the Sultan has been very accessible and gives long and friendly interviews to all, lie has told Woods- Ballard that he wishes him to stay on, in reply to his request to do so. I gather he is not quite happy about Wynne* a dealings with the Xaudas in Gwadur. The latter are awful scallywags, but ap/ ear to have a following, and it seems that Wynne (quite Justifiably) has been saae- what disparaging about them* o* The Sultan has taken, from the start, he says, a violent dislike ~co Sara bell, and seems that it is no good talking to lifca about it. iere is also some strong, though I am certain utterly unfounded, rumour about his having a boy friend. The latter is said to be his servant, who is a rascal giving himself great airs, and with &amp; habit of dressing up -to kill', and it seems that this my have given rise t the gossip, which, with knowledge that he is out of favour is easily encouraged. 7* At all events, according to Woods-ballard, the Sultan will not rest till he has got rid of Cai pbell, and the Subedar il sJor, nor will he take the smallest interest in the force, which is now very reduced, and inefficient. I believe the dislike started with a very strong report against the poor conditions pertaining in the infantry which Campbell submitted to the Sultan shortly after his Joining. In this he compared their salaries unfavourably with that of a coolie in the oilfle l aB * *** suggested that expert opinion should be taken about the troops diet, which includes no meat. 'Ihe Sultan mentioned this to me in an interview, and also hinted that he had others, unmentionable. reasons to bereasons to be dd.ssatisfi.ed. with hdjiu On this and on other occasions I have endeavoured to suggest that GampbeH is a good soldier with plenty of service and from a first class regiment. He has, however, a curious manner and seems disinterested in his own living conditions, which may give a false impression* 7* Woods-^allard also tells me that the Sultan has ^finitely decided to build a new school in Gwadur, which does not sound as if he will contemplate the sale or lease of that place. The Sultan has also decided to build a hospital in not suitable and from a brief look, I too thought this was poor. At all events it seems that the Sultan will not take any interest in our hospital. Yours sincerely. 3d/- F. 0. L. Chauncy.ocroromiAL. (^&gt;J ^g^CRT CK T r g: FOR \&amp; y GT^E8AL&gt; 1 * . adranoe towards the dwvelepsezxt of oil has boon •nywhoro in Sultanate territory inrou^hout the year, and the general public have begun to think that 'oil' will not ootre to Mueoat* In the North, the Sultan wants the haikha to be left alone ! untii th ®3 r *'®a4laa that they have no ohanoe of getting arching except through bin. In the HUqf area, despite hi* prordae to deviae apache t to enable the prospecting partiee to operate in saj ety,ha haa so far taken no steps te do so, and it now seen that 4 .v ^ ^ W not be in earnest. In Dhefar indicative are ococession .ill be given #iilst the rumour find of oil seepage in Gwadur appears to have died the death afloat niaours. arousing the interest of the Sultan least of all. 3. The Agricultural Survey of the ^atinah was oosgOeted by Mr. Hartley, the Director of Agriculture of the Aden Oovernsent, and his report, full of interest and helpful suggestions, is now before the Sultan. Se far, however, the only sign ©f ado-ting any of the suggestions is the importation by a Dubai agent of Tetter pump* and by . ray 'ackenzie’s of Pustcn &amp; Hornsby pumps for owners of date ■ardens to use on their wells. These have been encouraged by the Itaacat Government's allowing their import free of Customs duty. About thirty sxioh pumps have been imported durii* the year, and reports from the users, including the Shaikh of Wud&amp;am, are satisfactory, the consensus of opfinic:in being that they are cheaper to work than bullocks. 4# pi I»iofar the only agricultural development has been by the Sultan, and, aa expected, the Jrovinoe is not likely to yield more than a large farm. 5* o progress has been made ever the various water schemes for Sur, j’uacat and 2'atrah and it is thought that l&amp;lloway Brothers* soher ec v.* re too expensive, and have been dropped; and so far no alternative has been devised. tlL » oh « 8 ® to set up a power station at Vtym has also followed the now al! too familiar process of falling through and instead the pww r h oy, adjh K «r e rory p^r ^nrlae durinfi the mner # toe bMO au^e- ted by teo more engines. It is now hoped to mnrnly ell »?? V** 0 ?* f ° r ®^ e ? trlolty fro “ twu » exoept the Ooneuleteend ^aole &amp; Irelees. It is doubtful hoeever whether this will pro*, to be the oase. totrah remains power—less* . Vr ' C*»»rles Kendall, the Muaoat Cewmeent'e london pun^sing agent, visited Ifasoat early in the year to exasdno conditions for development of the fisheries. Before leaving he presented the * *&lt;*“* for •d’ertising and disposing of a monopoly, but es the Sultan has been under the ipreaaion that he ms gelMto w* ooncrasion niiaelf, and not merely dispose of it to a third party, understoo&lt;1 » homercr, that the matter K “ a * U ^ W ”***** luacat in the ft... . n ^ the Sultan's hopes ran high for a tine, as, after visits and surveys by sir qyrU fox, ha had hoped to Interest a ooripeny • • • in the lime deposits15. -2 in the line deposits there. Upon further examination these proved useless, and it seems that, ss in the ease of oil, the 3ultaa is doooed i° thif &gt;POi ? t er \* b** to find and exploit Mineral wealth in this part of his territory . *• ***• Kartley has eophasised with regard to Agriculture, there is unlikely to be any real progress in the Sultanate until detailed plans have been drawn up, and a tnm of money allooated for e aoh purpose outside the ordinary budget. Of this there is little siffn though at the close of the year the Sultan irtfioated to his Foreign minister that, pleased with his Custoas n^oeipta, he was now ready to consider some of the schemes for spending which they had in im. /fortunately only seeing has cone to be believing in the Sultanate, and people are apt to be sceptical of such pronounoenents. 10. Neither provincial nor townsfolk appear to take ouch interest xti rid afi airs, and the happenings in the Far ftast, even the Korean ar are seldom discussed by more than a handful of leading Merchants and officials outside the uropean residents. The Merchants' attention has been primarily focussed upon securing commodities likely to be In short supply, and at the moment most shops are heavily over-stocked. greement was reached between the Sultan and Cable d Wireless Ltd. over the installation of an automatic telephone exchange serving up to about ^00 numbers. The equipment has arrived, and the system is expected to be in use early in 1951# FINAMCh. ‘b 6 -&gt;ultanat^ rrvtnue has continued to increase on account of the two principal factors. Firstly the increased spending power of the population as a whole due to the rise in prices of dates and fish, which are the principal exports of the Sultanate, and which exceed . J ***** ai eve p the increased imports • vis total exports £ 2,282,780 total inports £ 2, 176,353. Secondly, the continued differences oe ^een todia and Pwkistan and the consequent trade barriers, which have resulted lti yiu tl / increased imports of ^oods, especially oloth, from india and a transit trade through Gwadur into J^fikistan. ^ ^ Sultan is no acre infoxwiativo about his finances, but it has been fairly reliably estimated that the Revenue now exceeds (£ 225 ^ 00) ^ that ^ expenditure is about reoerre ?' PrtTwto and State, if these can be diffv renti ated # oust have reached nearly *s 130 la)dis or £ 1,000,000. 14. ^ Sultanate can therefore be regarded as in a very sound financial position in spite of any possibility of a sharp drop iTthe £**TjV**£ ^ th * ±r to listen, and even with^t^il royalties, by wldch Gulf Principalities have now oome to set so much store^there 5 iT ? n * kittle thought and foresight, a oo^&gt;i4insive development plan, to include both beneficient and profit making under takings, should not be drawn up. But, as already stated therein no sign of any such over-all planning, and nothing but rather ineffective Piecemeal ideas ever seem to find favour. Sirwe the Sultan keeps his finances secret even from his ministers, it is difficult for tSo to hel uim ovem if he desired it. .4s it is he keeps a tight hold on the purse strings, doling out to each d,partBient(irr5taoible\llocaUons for the year. lyen the Customs department has )iad no replacement of its motor whaler, which was holed over a year ago, and lies uselea-, ^the foreshore, and the Director General has to borrow a motor car wnon He wishes to tour.21. -3- 6 15* In the towns of Misoat and *'atrah there has been a ©onsistent shortage of balsas. Oils is the nlakle ooln. fomerly e ghty to the rupee 9 which fores the chief ourrenpy of th« lower orders, and gerems the cost of day to day foodstuffs. The rate at V*™*/* 1, *** half of the yeer was sixty four In fesoat ajfld ort y •iiht in Matrah to a rupee, asking the oost of all fresh l ocxt very high. The primary cause Is believed te be that Hie land &gt;istomr. dues on preduoe ftnoa the Interior ere mostly paid in mi those hare eoemalated in the Treasury, and nothing is done te get them back into circulation. It is even suspected that the Sultan* s intention is to -like a substantial profit in due oourse. Pakistan currency, which started the year at Ss 144/* to Rs 100/- Indian, ended the year at about Ra 97/- te Ra 100/- Indian in the open aarket, though the local branch of the British Bank of Iran and the Middle Kaat deals only at the Official rate. TRIBAL. 17* The Sultanate continued to enjoy what nuat be, in ita turbulent hiatoiy, an almost unparallsd period of peace. The : iivea* at the age, it la believed, of about seventy two. The other two mentors of the Triunvirste, which virtually controls affairs in the interior of the Sultanate, saleh bin laaalHarthi and Sulainan bin Haeyar of the Jabal Ahkdar, Hlnawi and Ghsfiri faction Icadara, reept^ctively, continue to oomduod' affairs peacefully. Tht latter, however, has shown signs of late of an intention tostrike out far hxinself, and he has made apj.roaches in several directions, including Rls Majesty’s Government, for independent recognition, and rc . diz tet negotiation for ell oonoesaions in his territory, so far without success. 18* fhat will happen when the Imam dies continues to be a subject for popular conjecture, end aa many can be found who fancy the Sultan s ohanoee of gaining the support of the tribes who now follow the Iami,*s these who insist that there will be an eleeted «»oeseor. The absence of a preponderance for the latter is perhaps due to there being no obvious candidate in view, and to rivalry between the xnm/is end Ghafiris as to which faction should provide iim. The only name actually mentioned so far has been Yahya, the eldest sai of the previous Imam, whom, with his brother, the present Imam hrr, brou ht up, and has employed as one of his Walls. 19* The only disturbances have been petty quarrels. In February, what night have developed Into a serious feud between the £ th * — oh*otod by the Sulten', brotner, aiyid ajld, aa Wall of Masna’ah, intervening and effeotlxm at nice for seven months pending the Sultan’s return from Salalah, where he had gone for the ntoner. Though he had not returned by the end of the year, the truce appeared to be still holding. 2 P'* _ „ I A bo f d ? r *l*l»*e ooourr^d In July between the petty Shthuh haikh of Bekheh In the Ruae-al-Jibbal ravinoe of the iultanate —* 4 to. a KtolMh in Truoial a-n.Bvi.wna rTi* 4 ,lsr J h * aotion ^ lolitiaal Officer on the Trudal Coast and one of H.M'e ship, prooeeding to the aoene and securing undertakinga fran the partiea. Keporta of the liklihaed of a rt er c^itbreal: ,vert received later in the year, mad aa a general war “&gt;4 «—tal tribes^ waa feared, repreaentations ^e re wade te the Muacat G^raawnt to ««iat in tri iv i, c . rimJ. T!*.;* 111 Und#r th * i^tigation tte Mwoat ove rnnient at the oleee of the jeer.21 Apart frow the** inoidonta a number of kidnappings of , D ? OCO,ber ' •nri it to believed that they here boon OM^ltted &gt;y bedouins of nhshirsh, op thnt neighbourhood, euoourogod ^ thi ' ^^uriahing state of the slave market in the fiuniai area* 4ie qoa ^fJf5 r *ay» ho’wver, be the truth, and owing to the more Aiffloult oonA^txo^ prevailing for would-be slavers, prices have risen and kid- nappers are tempted to try further afield. ADIgTTX 8TRATI V&gt;J ~ GhKKRAL. ^ There have been no (ftangcs in the Sultanate Ministration durir^: the v e ar. The Political Agent oarried out tours of the coital region® of the Batinah and the Roue-el Jibbal, and also vioitedlur. 4;' ^ ^ ^ ^ dlir # and st^raitted detailed reports at the time. The standard of the «alis seemed surprisingly high for the poor salaries ^ poor conditlona i® they lire, ©lore was tie evidence of graft, or of any serious miscarriage of lust lee. in .®J adur » 1 * ere * f «' had to be brought to the notice of the ikscat Covernsent of the ill treatment of British subloota. Oh the Batinih a long standin oemplaint about the levy of land custoos on ^ocal produce was brought to the notice of the Political Agent by the ^j (British subjects). This was examined in detail and co °P era tion of the Director General of Customs, has If - ; er - -idbefore the Sultan for final decision. British subjects residing in the Sultanate are not backward in airing their greviances fuc t f absence* oi* any serious or wide spread complaints supoorts th* iniTjressioTis gained^ of the oonduot of the local officials. MtgCTCXPAlJTY. tL *?° rU * p ^* r to have been made to improve the sanitation and general appearaaoe of the towns ef unseat and %trsh / t f uric-L aJ.-j ties, which continue to bw run by the Sultan’s eldest - ^ f*** 3 ** n,ethod * T* •till primitive, anh funds a^t, ^ th * WDric ^ ^ T** ronA between ^atrah and Muscat has been receiving the most attention, but ss usual the Government will net spend the necessary sue on higher technical •••iatanoe, end everything has to be done by trial and error by timid subordinates. The result is that the extensive damage done to the road by the rterms in February has not yet been repaired, with the ” hunal* * NOr * “ «* ** certaiTiat nil withstand the storms when they do ocme. MEDICAL. 24* Government medical services are still non existent. Sultan is trying to obtain a personal physician, who will be nil owed to plw, md ali . 0 dootow for 3ur and Gmdur. (ban har. been receive* fre ^ , ' ,t mmlta his return firm aSaih! , Ip ® *° Auditors, for vtieo he hu also ufced and reolre* names from the Govemnent of Tndia . I»»cat ftoapital 1m etUl in the charge of the Consulate ^ oontiruea as uarantln. Uedioal officer, ns is assisted by the Assistant Consulate burgeon, and drugs and staff are y**W Oo-^nt. ftw jn*Uc aubsoription. rha «Uy contributlcrnTreaT the t «• 600 -““the mat eub^puon nwu ^ &gt; ^ P 1 * 0 h** 1-«n to hand the hoqdtal and the quarantine arranpnents over to the Sultan, he has hitherto shown a firm disinclination either to take the. over or to open Ms oan a edical ••••services* The Bern applies to Mstrsh f where he is equally content to allow the American Mission Hospital to try to cater for needs* This, the Mission have new arranged, will remain open all the year round in future. The woman's hospital, run by the Muscat branch of the mission, also plays an important role, and provides the only reliable Midwife. 26* There were no epldenios or serious diseases during the yesr* i copy of the Consulate Surgeon* s report is attached. 2 7. In Gw&amp;dur the Doctor and oonpounSer have left *a3 the anltary Inspector has taken leave and is not expected to return* Nor has it yet been possible to replace them, presumably because the te r &gt;s are too unattractive* The result was a couplete absence of spy medical facility for the greater part of the year. This, added to the lack of an adequate school or teachers, water supply, electricity or, in fact, of all amenities, is making the people complain that they get very little return for the oondiderable revenue to which they contribute &lt; through easterns dues (about £ 40,000 to £ 4,000 expended), a complaint now often*v,ard in other parts of the Sultanate, especially ’ usoat and , Hatrafeu EDUCATION. 28* Thanks to the efforts of the British Council and the mbasaiea in Cairo and Beirut, the Muscat Government have succeeded in recruiting four Palestinian Teachers for the Saidiyah School in Muscat, if they stay, this should be a considerable benefit, but owing to the continuance of the various religious taboos imposed in ruscat upon Govemnent officials aid their families, these teachers are not at all content. Though unaoouatoned to purdah, their wives have been compelled to adopt it here, and they are not allowed to accompany their husbands in public. It is true that such strictures are expected by certain old fashioned and still influential Shaikhs of the Interior to be inposed, especially upon teachers, but as soon y»s these men, wi c are displaced persons, without financial means, can hear of other posts or hare saved enough money, the Sultan ha - c to decide what he can beat afford to lose. 29. The only other schools are in Salaleh and Gwadur. The former seems adequate and to be fairly well run by the existing headmaster, but it is not yet completed especially the boarding part. The Gwadur school is over crowded and structurally quite unfit for the purpose. It is understood that improvements are contemplated, but realisation is always too slow. 30* Matrah is without a government school and the Khoja ccewunity run their own. 31* The Missions in both MUaoat and **atrah cater for only their own employees owing to the Sultan discouraging his subjects from attendance. But, Judging from the Christmas 'exercises'', they have noe succeeded in interesting a great many friends and neighbours, as their function was attended by quite two hundred men, women and oBildreac JUSTICE. 32. Frm enquiries received through the Consulate it seems that the I/tisoat Government are contemplating the introduction of codified laws. At present all the courts administer according to !•*, which | If It has no other attribute appears to be speedy • •• • and free from intricacy.and free fro® intricacy* Allowance for stating badly on oath what cannot be proved by evidence is, however, open to 'bonaiderable abuse. On the ef ole, though* few oonplaints are heard, and, provided appeals really reach the Sultan, ehloh la doubtful In some oases, a fair meaaure of Justice should be maintained* The worst feature le the benching of cases, and therefore the parties, between the central and provincial courts, aiti diplooatio assistance has several i ij^ea bean sought by British subjects suing iSisaatla who have despaired of otherwise achieving any result. :?epr mentation by the Consulate has usually brought satisfaction, and hi^ier quarters have generally shown thenselves co-operative and reasonable. 33. Sentences are carried cut in either the Jalali Fort in *4isoat or the ^atrah Fort. o. ditions are primitive, but not eevere for the normal type of prisoner, whose hone is frequently far worse. All prisoners are, however, shackled, and the sight of the® out for exercise is painful. The administration has a long way t to go before the enoaoeration of a uropean in a local Jail can be equably contemplated^ whatever his fault. If Jurisdiction over Ibrltiah subjects is to bo surrendered, as the Sultan hopes, it seems that besides sane guarantee of a fair trial in accordance with generally accepted rules of evidence, he must provide suitable places for detention and imprisonment. PQLICK . 34. The Felice force remai-ns insignificant has a singularly inept Inspector in charge. Higher control seens to be divided rather confusedly between the inis ter s for the Interior end the Oommandant of the Muscat Infantiy. The latter deals with the traffic regulations, and the former with security, in whioh he is also assisted by a msnber of unurdfonaed aakeris. The police constables themselves are intelligent and well trained in traffic duties. There is no Criminal Investigation or Public Prosecutor's Department. MILITARY. 35. %m*i absenteeism and desertion was ebident during the ar, culminating at the end of September in a mutiny, as a result of which ninety men had to be discharged. The trouble was primarily d e to the unreliable nature of the Baluch element which comprised more than half of the force, and it has now been decided to recruit no more of then;. A secondary and nearly as important a f actor is the low pay and poor conditions of service. In spite of this the men look smart on parade, and appear to be familiar with their duties. The fere# (full establishment J05 all ranks) is almost ridiculously over arrred for its size, and for the uses to whioh it is likely to be i*it. it possesses two 3*7' Mountain guns, four &gt; iokers Machine guns, one exin gun, six V.B. guns, three hundred andsixty two modern .303” magasine rifles, and twelve hundred and forty-nine eld and probably unserviceable rifles of Martini henry pattern. ” . . ^ i*. ** Seer - F ' to be the policy never to use the force outside atrah and yuscat, and their fighting ability has not been tested, idiilat they can have no knowledge of the country or its peo;ole. One cannot help feeling that at least half the foroe could pro fita bly be trained as a pioneer corps under a qualified cncxneer officer.7* K/ 37* Salyid Pahr, the Multan's youngest brother, who completed his military training in Pakistan and was appointed to duty with the Muscat Infantry, was suspected of corrplioity in the mtiry, He is thought to hare been jealous of the Stibedar ajor having been planed senior to hiau He was sent to India *on a visit to his father”, and it is thought he will not rejoin the force. 36. The Pakistan Government have been asked to loan the services of two new Junior Oonsdsaioned of floors ( s Jube&amp;ar end a Jemadar), and the oaee for improvement of the conditions of service of the unit is being examined. THE SULTAH. 3UYH) SAID HDf TAXMJR ( b. 13th August 1910 ) ( a* 10th l^bruary 1932) 39* His IH^neas cancelled his proposal to visit the United Kingdom, and spent the stsaner in his favourite province of Phofar. Thera He leads the life of a genial country squire in contrast to the royal and inaccessible attitude he adopts in Muscat. He is absorbed in the development of his gardens at Halalah, and enjoys the leisured esse and peace of the life in his attiwmtive Palace, which is called the Fort. There can be no doubt that his administr ation there is excellent and well suited to the people. If he would only apply the same thoroughness and affection to the rest of his territory, all would be well. He is able and experienced, but, it seems, selfish and inollnad to be laxy where his personal interests do not lie. However, he has now been in the^ seat of Governnent for eighteen years, and if his rule has not so far been spectacular it has been peaceful and the Sultan's writ runs further than in hie father's day, whilst from bankruptcy the Sultanate has risen to comparative affluence. If, as he says, his attention will now really be given to development $f the other parts of his kingdom, well and good. But, if he continues to neglect them, he will inevitably estrange even his present supporters, and of late there have been many tongues at work. THB HKIK AIPAfrllT. 40. The Sultan's only son, Qaboos, aged ten, lives permanently in Salalah. There he is kept in the women's quarter, and seldom meets anyone outside palace circles. Be is brought up rather unnaturally and strictly under constant supervision guard, and is not allowed to forget his exalted position to be. He is discour aged from being toe friendly or forthcoming. The Sultan appears to be undecided about his future schooling, but is now believed to be making enquiries in Cairo. RKLATICWS WITH FOREIGN GOT^gHTS. 41. Relations with His testy's Government were cordial, and the Sultan took several opportunities of affirmir^ his sentiments in this respeot. 42. He gave notice of his wish to terminate the existing Treaty •» from the 11th February 1951, on the completion of the twelve years for which it was designed to run in the first instance. 43* He signified his readiness to negotiate a fresh Treaty, but owing tom his protracted stay An Dhofar no such negotiations had taken place up to the olose of the year, and indications are that he will now wish to extend the existing Treaty for a while longer. Informal letters were exchanged with the Government of India signifying a desire to enter into negotiations for a separate treaty upon termination of the 1939 Treaty with His Majesty’s Government, to which Ii*la is party. 45*___ •' UP V5. The Sultan* • relation* with the united States Cweronant ware alno good, and the Capital was visited on two occasions by the United States Aircraft lenderaarri^ in the Arslan Gulf, and flvins the flag of their CoaiDander riddle Seat Forces. TO: consulate;. Major F. C.L* Ohaunpy held charge of the poet of I Us Britannic ^ajesty’a Consul and Political Agent throughout the year and Mr. D.P.H. Domingo % that of British Agent at Gwadur. 47. Separate reports have as usual been made on Trade, .’onKrnications, Shipping, and the working of the Consulate Courts, whilst notes on the Tribes and the financial position of the Sultanate have also been fomarded. 48. The following statistics for 1950 show the volume of routine Consular work in the Muscat and Cwadur Agencies. New paasports issued 1 % Renewals eld paasports 66 fcoergency Certificates 112 ~ Certificates of Identity 11 No Objection Certificates 252 Visas (mostly for Tsfr U a Pakistan &amp; Gulf Shaikhdou) e 5 f »'^7 Registration of Dooumanta 26 Registration of Bitths ) Marriagee) Nil Deaths 2. Registration of British subjects 956 ’Tasters* Notes of Protest 11 Slaves manumitted 12 t-f the British s\d&gt;jeots registered only 16 are Uhitad kingdom Citizens. KaiTICAL. ....POLITICAL, significant Political event of the year conEienoed with an announcement on the Pakistan Radio on the 25th April that Gwadur should be returned to *ekran. This was followed by an article in the akistan newspaper 'Dawn', and accompanied by a customs block ade of the land frontier, and posting of Mekran Levies at KarwaA, Suntsar, Thalang and on the Jiwani - Piskhin road. 3°. The blockade proved ineffective owing to the ease with which the pickets could be bribed, and the hardships inflicted upon Pakistan* s own nationals near the border. 51. After representations were made to the Pakistan Government, assurances were received that that Government had no intention of cemitting unconstitutiohal or unfriendly acts against Muscat, and following the lifting of the blockade, conditions quickly reverted , to normal* It seems, in fact, that Nawab Bai Khan of Mekran was personally responsible for these manoeuvres and the Pakistan Govern ment were not at all pleased with him* His action can certainly be calculated to have retarded any chance of the success of an early approach to the Sultan for the lease or sale of Gwadur which the Pakistan Government have been hoping to secure* POSTAL. 52. None of the Post office savings certificates issued prior to the transfer of the Muscat Post office to the British General Post office, can be cashed yet. Severe embarrassment has been caused lu th f s 9°^ Bulate and to thd Muscat Government on account of the funds they hold in such securities, on behalf of the Muscat hospital, the lliscat Infantry Men’s Saving Bank account and Estates of Minors. It •eems that until India and Pakistan can agree to the basis of financial liability for such holdings Biere is no hope of satisfaction* 53* In Gwadur the Pakistan Government’s Post office remains, like the proverbial cuckoo, without the consent of the owner. All ?^ 8 ^P U “ Cat P fi ' re »,nt Tia Karachi la aplt, of dir act sailings from Gwadur, and several complaints of pilfered postal packets were received. The telegraph land line was frequently out of order, but has been reinforced now by the installation of a wireless set, and a considerable improvement was achieved by the close of the year. 54. mh the introduction of the new B.I.S.N.Co’s 'D' service, consisting of the four new partially air-conditioned vessels 'ara, D^arka, Dumra and Daressa, travel in the Gulf is almost luxurious passengers, whilst mails are now received regularly every eight days in either direction, the ships almost invariably crossing at Jjhscat. he service to Gwadur is, however, only forthnightly, ard unable to compete with certain seasonal rushes of deck passengers, SHIPPING. _ Statistics have been reported in the Trade report and the only matter of local importance has been the working of the lighter age and landing, which has been given as a contract to the local Bhack ®. r , f ith the Ver y considerable increase in shipping in the Gull generally, twenty to twenty five ships are apt to call ^ ? MUSCat oaj ^°- ,rh ® landing contractors equipnent Pr ^ tive *** lasvttlolent to cope with such traffic, and afforta are being made to persuade the Sultan to break the monopoly and to alio, any agents who wish to serve their own ships. This would result in Gray Mackenzie A Cot bringing in up to date 1 steel barges•tmml barges and a proper tearing unit, but to the close of the year it was impossible to wee the Vusoat Gorernacnt to this end. Though reasons are not officially given, it is understood that the Sultan considers this an undertaking of which his own subjects should be capable, and he does not wish it to be possible for him to be aooused of giving every concession to foreigners. SMOCGLING. 56. Smuggling is practically confined to gold and reached very considerable proportions during the year. There is no prohibition of gold entering or leaving the Sultanate, and there is evidence of muty worth leaving Muscat and Gwadur (having come from up the Gulf) for Ibkistan and India* The only rrystery la where thia apparently inexhaustible supply cores from. The smuggling itself is almost open, and a rrTuple person carries as much as several lakh*. In Gwadur a man had three waistcoats lined with three lakhs of gold each, whilst in one launch about fifteen lakhs worth was carried, and, recently, in Torbay, a date baskefr was found to contain about three and a half lakhs MBTEOROLOGICAL. 57. The rainfall for 1950 in Muscat /otalled 1.27'. In Gwadur there vras no rainfall for about the fourth year in succession and the supply of drinking water there is precarious. The sunner in usaat and along the -^atinah was milder than usual, and as a result the date crop suffered slightly. In Gwadur the sixaaer was unpleasant and hotter than usual. In Muscat the maximum temperature was * minlimw • n * asriwgj humidity ” minimum ” 92 % 18 f m 59. Recordings are not made in Gwadur at present, though the T^kistsn Government have asked for and received permission to open s meteorological station there, as well as in Muscat. The &amp;isoat allowances from the Pakistan Gcvement station is actually worked by this Agency, two of the clerks receiving Sd/- F.C.L. Chaunoy. Muscat. 11th January 1951 H*®.K** Consul it Politioal Agent.(§) British Agency, 1 w a d u r . 2nd. January, 1951. Annual Administrative Report for the year 1950; British Agency, Gwadur . Staff. 1. The staff of this Agency remains the same as last year. In J \9l t 3 the salaries of the full time employees were raised considerably, but the salaries of the part time employees were not increased. In my opinion, even though they may be part time employees, their case might be reconsidered and a fair increase granted them. Tours. 2. I proceeded to Muscat in the s. s. 'Bamora” on the 28th February for Comnittal Proceedings in a case under section 302 of the Indian Penal Code. From Muscat I proceeded to Karachi on the 5th. March and returned with my wife and family to G-wadur. 3. His Excellency the Political Resident accompanied by H.B.M's Consul &amp; Political Agent, Muscat, visited Gwadur in the H.M.S. 'Wren' on the 17th. April. Commander T.Merchant was comanding the 'Wren”. Lt.Col. B.Woods- Ballard, Foreign Minister. Muscat, had already arrived a week prior to this. The visit of the Political Officers was informal and during their stay here they inspected the Gwadur Agency and the Political Rest House building. Various deputations were interviewed and their complaints heard and noted. The Resident, Consul, Foreign Minister, Administrator and Commander Merchant were invited to lunch with the British Agent; from there to a tea party with the Khoja community at their Jamathkhanna. The Commander invited us to dinner the same night. The above party returned to Muscat on the 18th. morning. 4. Cfri the 19th. April, under orders from the Consul, I proceeded on tour by truck in connexion with the case mentioned in paragraph 2 above, to ascertain whether a small village by the name of Gamarao, about 28 to 30 miles from Gwadur town, was within Sultanate territory. It was at this village where the murders of Meskan and Pirol were committed by Bayatun. The Consul left behind a map for me and, finding this village well within the boundary I marked it on this map and submitted ray report to Muscat. 5. Earlier in the year, about January, I accompanied the Administrator to Sur and met the headman responsible for all British Subjects there. Sur is a small fishing village about 12 miles North-East of Gwadur with a popu lation of about 350, of which roughly about 100 are British subjects. They were very pleased to see me. While there, I settled a case where both parti es were British subjects, and one party injured a camel belonging to the other party. I appointed a Panchayat and a decision was reached whereby the guilty party should pay the camel owner Rs. 15/- for damages. This was agreed upon and the money was paid. My subjects expressed their desire to see me more often at Sur, but I told them that this was not possible as I had other more important work to attend to, but that I would try and visit Sur at least twice a year. The Administrator is expecting a truck from Muscat shortly and he has very kindly offered to take me with him whenever he goes on tour. Brief summary of work done. 6 . (a\ Court Work. The daily average of cases received in this court remain the same as last year. The theft case referred to in paragraph ^(a^ of my report No. 21/1/50 dated the 23rd. February, 1950* ended with the plaintiff withdrawing his complaint. One case of assault came up between two Hindus. I was fortunately an eye witness to the scene, and found both parties guilty and they were imprisoned in the local Fort for one day. The most significant case of the year was registered under sections 380 and 411 of the Indian Penal Code. 'A' a Hindu boy robbed gold ortoaments from his father’s house worth Rs.10,000/- and gave them to 'B”, a Moslem, who tried to dispose of them secretly. Their statements were recorded, but as I had my suspicions of 'B' that his statement was not satisfactory, an exhaustive search of his house was carried out in the presence of several witnesses and the gold orna ments were eventually recovered from a hole dug in the ground in the house. The matter /The matter was then forwarded to the Consul at Muscat who suggested that it would he best to deport 'B' as there are no proper facilities to imprison a man locally. This was done. 'A' was set free as his father did not wish to prosecute, and the gold ornaments were handed back to the father. Cases sr debt are most common and still continue in the usual manner. Sane difficulty is experienced and great patience has to be used to bring both parties to a compromise. The debtor admits his debt but cries poverty and says he is prepared to pay back in small instalments to which the other party will not agree to. Persuasion has to be used then to make him see reason, eventually he agrees. A Panchayat is still a reliable method of deciding minor cases, and is still used. Leading merchants are generally appointed who take it in writing from both parties that they will agree to their decision; of course an appeal can always be made, but this is very seldom. When a point arises where one's word is as good as the other, and both parties are Moslems, they are sent to a Sharia court to swear in the presence of a Qazi. Punishment of any description is very difficult in this court, the reason being that whenever this is done a large deputation is received to plead for the accu sed and various promises are made. I have given the question of 'security' considerable thought but under the circumstances T do not think it will prove very successful. From the British subjects most cases come from the Hindu's, and if I was to take security each time, if thought necessary, no body would stand surety. I have tried this on a few occasions but not, as I say, with any impressive results. If on the other hand/is sentenced to one week's imprisonment, the result ends with the deputation coming Tip to appeal, as mentioned above. I think the only alternative would be is to impose small fines upon the accused according to the nature of the offence, and the number of times that particular individual commits an offence. This would have better results as I have learned that to merchants money is their 'God', and if they were to pay these fines it would be felt more than making him sit in the local Fort for a few days. 6 . (b). There has been less Certificates of Identity and Emergency Certifi cates issued this year as compared with last year. The reason for this is that the cost of these were less last year, whereas this year the cost has gone up to Rs. 7/8 for an Identity Certificate from Rs.1/2. Over three thousand visas have been issued during the year which remains Rs.1/2. The rate of exchange for this is Rs.15/- to £.1/-. The rush and lull in traffic remains unchanged i.e. from March to September there is hardly any traffic, but from October to February the rush for passports and visas begins. The issue of regular passports is done at the British Consulate, Muscat. Most of the traffic is between Gwadur and Karachi, a few to Bombay and fewer still to the Gulf ports. There were a few more sale deeds registered this year than last. Other than this very little notarial work is done. Political. 7. The main communities in Gwadur who claim British protection are the Khojas (followers of H.H.Sir Aga Khan^, the Hindus and a few local Baluchi's. Of the IQiojas, Mukhi Ahmedbhoy Allibhoy Reimtullah is their leader and Mukhi if the Ismailia Jamathkhannah. Hazur-Mukhi Kamrudin Abdul 1 has recently been appointed Honorary Secretary of their Council. Under the leadership of Ahmedbhoy the Khoja community are kept in strict dicipline, and he excereises entire control over them. Cases involving both members of this conmunity are settled before their Council. In February when the Aga Khan visited Karachi, the entire eommunity, rich and poor, proceeded to Karachi to meet His Highness and obtain his blessing. Unfortunately Ahmedbhqy's tennure of Mukhi terminates on the 31st. March, 1951, and it is hoped that someone as reliable as this man will be appointed in his place. He was given the Hon orary title of Rai by His Highness. On the 13th. November I inspected their Vernacular School and was surprised to see the interest taken by both the teachers and the students. I was shown a sample of sane needle-work, cro chet and knitting from the girls division which was very neatly done. A new headmaster was employed earlier in the year who is taking personal inter est in the school, and according to Ahmedbhoy he says he finds some improve ment. I suggested to them that it would be a good idea if the pupils could be encouraged in their needle-work etc. and an annual school exhibition should be held in the Jamathkhanna and all this work displayed and sold. This would encourage the students more. The suggestion was accepted. I asked the headmaster. /asked the headmaster if* he had any objection to my giving the children a holiday to which he said 'no”, and a holiday was granted them. Now for the Hindu's. Mukhi Tulsidas Gianchand is the leader of the Charbari Hindus and Mukhi Kishenchand Parsram leader of the Sindhi Hindus. The term 'Charbari Hindu' originated when the Iranian Government more or less asked all British subjects to quit the country, and they migrated to Gwa— dur a few years back. The Sindhi Hindus, of course, are from Sind (Pakis tan . The Charbari Hindus do not obey the^r leader who exercises no control over them whatever, and most cases are received from this commu nity. The Sindhi Hindus are more united and obey their leader and little or no trouble comes from them. The most significant Political event of the year was a radio announcement from Radio Pakistan on the 25th. A.pril suggesting that Gwadur should be returned to Kekran to whom it rightly belongs. The announce ment concluded with 'we shall get Gwadur as soon as possible.' This naturally caused some excitement in Gwadur but everything soon calmed down vdthin a few days. Soon after an article appeared in the 'Dawn' newspaper in Karachi sent in by one H.M.Baluch. The article was titled 'Gwadur- an intolerable anachronism', a copy of which I am enclosing. This din not have the same effect upon the public as did the radio announcement, in fact it had not effect whatever. Shortly sifter this Mekran Levies were posted along the boundary by the Pakistan Government at posts near Karwat, Sun tsar, Thalang and one or two between the Jiwani/Pishkan road. Their duty was to stop caravans from entering or coming from the Gwadur terri tory. This resulted in a scarcity of ghee, charcoal, firewood for cooking, goat hair, wool, dates etc. and little or no business could be done. Cara vans leaving Gwadur were turned back. This blockade was overcome by the caravan traders offering small bribes to the Levies who allowed them to pass. It is believed that some trouble arose on the other side of the boundary as their own trade was being jaggrargd impaired. In Dasht the people said 'either restore Gwadur to us or allow our goods to go through.' In Jiwani the people informed the Ruler of Mekran, Nawab Bhai Khan, that as their only source of fish export via Gwadur had been stopped, due to the barrier posted between, they would have to desert Jiwani and move to Pishkan which is in Sultanate territory. As there was complete chaos there the Nawab and Wazir of Mekran decided to visit Jiwani, but instead 3hia Omar s/o Bhai Khan was sent to make enquiries. He received the same replies so he returned promising to give them a reply within a week. The result was that the barriers were withdrawn to a certain extent and once again traffic continues as freely as before. ^• The Political set up in Pakistan on the Gwadur border at present is as follows:- P.A.Mastung, K.B.Sher Zaman Khan, Headquarters; A.P.A. XauK-twnx;, K. S.Ghulam Haider Khan, H.Q at Panjgur; Major Mohd Salim, O.C. Mekran Levies, H.Q.at Panjgur; other posts sire at Suntsar. Talar, Turbat, with lesser posts at Kuldan, Gabt, Kalatu and Boon, two other posts are’ believed to be at Dandao and Kabu. The A.P.A is also the Wazir of Mekran State. The Nawab is Bhai Khan. Wazir of Kalat State is K.B. Zazif Khan, andHabibullah Khan is the Nawab of Kharan State, all of whom come under the management of the Political Agent. 10. The Jiwani Air field which was taken over by the Royal Pakistan Air Force from the Royal Air Force last year, has now been taken over by the Ministry of Civil Aviation, Government of Pakistan. The change over took place on the 12th. October. This station will only be used, it is believed, for an emergency and for a point-to-point check for civil air lines passing over. Medical. 11. Gwadur is once again without a doctor. The privilege was short lived. In March Dr. G. Stevens proceeded on leave to Karachi from where he submitted his resignation to the Administrator. He is now employed in the Kalat Government Hospital at Mas tun g. The reason for his resig nation is not known but can only be surmised that he might have been in volved in some financial trouble* The Muscat Crovemment have once more advertised for /- if - © advertised for a doctor in the local papers in Karachi. Many applications have been received but no one has arrived yet. It is believed that the Government have accepted a man from Bombay. Soon after Dr. Stevens left the Compounder also resigned. The Sanitary Inspector proceeded to Lahore on leave in November and there is every likelihood, of his not returning either. However, the Administrator takes active interest in the Gwadur Municipality and the sanitation. It is hoped that a doctor will soon arrive in Cwadur as this is most essential here. Communications. 1 2. The local post office is still under the management of the Govern ment of Pakistan. In July a wireless was installed on a short term plan to ease the traffic kb on the telegraph land line which keeps constantly breaking down. This has proved no asset so far, because the wireless is seldom or ever in working order. The excuse is that the batteries are run down or that the changing machine is out of working order. There has been a slight improvement in both for the last two months. I find that during the summer months the land line keeps breaking down frequently, and dfuring the winter months it works well. The cause for this might be that in the summer we have very strong winds, and not so much of it in the winter. As compared with last year there has been no remarkable improvement at all, except for the installation of the wireless. Jith regard to the postal department, several complaints were received from Hindu merchants who correspond with Indian firms, some of whom are agents. The complaint was that ,, hundies M (or cheques' were sent to India under registered cover, but when they were received there the envelopes were said to contain only blank papers. The matter was taken up with the local Sub Postmaster who referred the matter to his head office at Karachi with a request to make enquiries. The reply received was that the letters in question were correctly despatched from Karachi for their onward destinations and that they did not hold themselves responsible. Further complaints were received but enquiries ended with the same result, so the matter was referred to the Consul, Muscat, who has taken the matter to higher authorities. Water Supply. 13» There is nothing much to be said about the drinking water in Gwadur, except that all the wells have dried up and new ones have had to be dug further North. Some water was caught in the catchment on the Koh-Batail due to a slight downpour of rain in March! which lasted for about half an hour. The public used to go up on the hill and fetch their water. This dried up in about two month’s time, but even before that people were unable to drink this water as others found it an inviting spot to swim in. The ,ali stopped it but too late, as the damage had already been done. The price of water here remains the same and also Pishkan, but the price of water in Sur went as far as Rs. 1/- per kerosene oil tin (4 gals). I am told that only a month or two ago the price came down to Rs.-/4/- per tin. The cause for this is the same as Gwadur, wells drying up, no rainfall for the past four years, and new wells to be dug. These wells a^dug and looked after by some local Baluchi, who in turn pays one or two men to help him clean them from time to time. As mentioned in my report of last year, the water supply here really relies on the rainfall which is very scarce. General. 14. Trade . Last year I reported that some Egyptian rice had been imported to Gwadur to be sold at a controlled price. This year Gwadur was allotted 60 tons of good quality sugar from the United Kingdom also to be sold at a controlled price but this turned out to be a farce. 30 tons were imported for the first half of 1950 and the price quoted was a few annas less than the current market price. Only one third of this was controlled at Rs.5/12 per local maund, and no control was exercised over the remaining two thirds which was allowed to be sold at the current market price of Rs. 7/8 per local maund. The matter was immediately reported to the Consul who referred it to the Resident at Bahrain. Smuggling in Gwadur, /omuggling in Gwadur continues on a large scale. The struggling of foodstuffs is negligible, but what fetches a good profit is cigarettes. This is purch- a.s&lt;ja in i^ahrain or i uwait and brought dov^n here. Prom here it is sent in to Karachi by dhows or fishing boats. In October a consignment of cigarettes worth Rs.30,000/- was caught by the Customs authorities at Karachi and the goods confiscated. The profit* made on each tin of fifty cigarettes is roughly Rs.1/4 per tin. Gold is another itsaox thing which is smuggled in large quantities from the Gulf to Gwadur and then on to Karachi either by launch or fishing vessels, but mostly by launch. As a matter of interest T made secret investigations as to how this is done, and the results were rather a surprise to me. At one stage I thought my little game was up but to ray surprise the individual showed me the gold bars which were neatly sewed into a so-called waist coat. He told me that each waist coat was worth 3'^' lakhs rupees - there were three such coats, and I was asked to try and put one coat on. I did, but after a great effort. I mentioned that the results of my enquiries were rather surprising, well they were in this respect that I discovered that one Hindu merchant, one Khauda and the Customs Amin are involved in this racket. They are agents for a syndicate operating at Dubai and Kuwait, and possibly Bahrain. Until September the price of gold in Kara chi was just over Rs.ID 0 */— per tola, but the price has since dropped to about Rs. 90/- per tola, whereas the price was between Rs. 65 /- to 75/- per tola in the Gulf. A launch is called up from Karachi which proceeds to Dubai, coll ects the ’haul’ and returns to Gwadur. The launch remains in port until such time as it appears the land is clear ahead, and then she leaves for Karachi. This is then landed at one of the two places called Boleji and Bungalow, where a quick transhipment is made into a waiting truck. As the price of gold has dropped in Karachi the local ’agents’ are trying to concen trate on India where the price fluctuates at about Rs.110/- per tola. As stated in my previous report, Gwadur is surely a ’’Smugglers Paradise” and as the State Government rather encourages this sort of thing for the sake of her revenue, it is not considered a crime, and nothing can be done about it. One or two examples appear in the article attached which can be fully belie ved. Trade, however, with Iran and Baluchistan continues. The biggest im porters and exporters are Haji Bhacker and Rhemtullah Bashir Bandali. Frankly no honest business is done here at all. Education. ^5* The local Saidiya School continues with about the same number of students as last year for the day school and night school. There has been no further advance made to build a new school. The plan and estimate, ore- pared by the Overseer, were sent to Muscat for approval but nothing further has been heard since. The present school is in an awful condition and, tho ugh minor repairs have been done, it is not a fit and healthy building for any school. The children appear to^cramped in. It is a pity that the Local Lrovemment takes no interest in this connexion. The school sports were run, as usual, and the prizes were distributed by the Wali. There has been no Kkai changes in the schools at Sur and Pishkan. In paragraph 7, page 2 of this report, I have already mentioned about the Khoja Vernacular School which need not be repeated, except that in my opinion their standard of education is higher than the local Saidiya School. Financial. 16 The devaluation of the Indian rupee and the non-devaluation of the Pakistan rupee last year has had rather a reverse reaction this year. Rs.100/ Pakistan will buy Rs.94/- Indian according to the current market and Gulf rate. Last year there was a clamour for Pakistan currency by the merchants and the local Customs, actually started by the Customs demanding that currency for duty, but this year things are different, the cry is for Indian currency/ The merchants realised that the Indian currency was the recognised currency* in Muscat and the other Gulf ports and, as they were trading with these ports, it was in their interest to keep to the official currency. Though this is sensible, only Pakistan currency circulates on the local market. 7/hatever Indian currency is available on the market is quickly bought up by the mer chants at the current rate of exchange and sent to the Gulf where Pakistan currency is purchased at the current market rate there. For example in Ku wait, Rs.23,000/- Indian currency will buy Rs.25,000/- Pakistan. This money is again /is again smuggled into Karachi to agents there who either bank the money or make use of it again in business transactions. Incidentally the Pakistan Government still have a ban on the export and import on their currency, and no passenger is allowed to bring in or take out more than Rs. 50 /-. A cer tain amount of chaos arose when the local B.I.Agent, M/S Hoodbhoy &amp; Bros., began demanding Indian currency for freight and passages. I managed to check this in time. Last year the company demanded Pakistan currency with the excuse that their head office was at Karachi, Pakistan. This year their excuse was tnat remittances had to be made to their principal agents at Bombay, M/s Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. I spoke to the local agent and advised him to accept whatever currency was offered, at par, but getting no satisfaction from him I reported this in my fortnightly diary. The Consul reported the matter to the Bombay agents, and orders were received from them in November that the local B.T.Agent should accept whatever currency is offered for freight and passages etc. The present position now stands that the local agent will pay the Commanders of the B.I.steamers in Pakistan currency and this will be treated as an advance for disbursements. This will then be exchanged with the Company’s Bankers at Bombay. Shipping. 17. Until March the 'B' boats were calling at Gwadur as usual. In January a Mr. G-rant and Capt. Bishop, representatives of the B.I.S.N.Co. Agents, Bombay, arrived here in the ’’Bamora' and came ashore for a few hours to inspect the local agents office etc. Many suggestions were made by the merchants asking for more ships and eventually it was decided that they would get more ships. However this finally resulted in the 'B' boats being taken off the run, as they were far too old, and they were replaced by the 'D' boats, the first of which to call here was the 'Dara' on the 13 th March. Fames of the ships which operated here this year are 'Barala', 'Bar- peta M , ’’Bamora”, ’’Vasna”, ”Dara”, ’’Dumra”, 'Dwarka” and a new ship which the fleet in August, the , Da^essa' , , Gwadur now receives a ship every eight days - one up, one down alternately. During the year ' there were 2i». inward and 2£ outward voyages. One ship, the 'Moorcot' cargo boat, was chartered by the B.I.S.N.Co, to ease the rush of cargo held up at Bombay. She made one inward and one outward voyage, thus making a grand total of 48 services during the year. According to the local agents figures over 4,500 passengers were received and booked during the ybar. The name of the local B.I.Agent’s firm was changed in September. Formerly they were known as Cursetji Hoodbhoy, but Cursetji presumably sold out his share, and the company is now known as Foodbhoy &amp; Brothers. 18. In addition to the steamship company operating here, the launch service known as the Muslim Navigation Company continues to operate also during the non-monsoon season. As already mentioned, considerable gold smuggling is done by this service. One can obviously gather when a consig- nement of gold is on board because, when there is, the launch captain will refuse to accept any passengers. Public Y/orks. 1 9. A lot was expected to be started this year in the line of const ruction etc, but only minor repairs have been carried out on the school at Sur, the Forts at Pishkan and Gwadur, and the old Cable and Wireless bunga low was renovated for the purpose of a doctor. A new fish godown has been built during the year. No Customs House, godown or school have been built as hoped. The merchants complain that their goods are damaged by the damp ness here as they are allowed to stay out in the open overnight. There is no Customs godown or shed in Gwadur. The Administrator hopes to see some construction work start in the new year. The Y/eather /The Weather, 20. Comparing this summer with last, it has been definitely hotter. The month of April was a pleasant one, though a bit dusty. Summer set in proper in the month of May . The monsoon season lasts from mid-May to the end of August. This year again there was no rainfall which makes a total of about four or five years that Gwadur has had no rain. Inspite of this, the weather in Gwadur is comparitively better than any (Gulf port. In the summer it does become rather uncomfortable when the breeze drops*for a few hours at night, and everything becomes damp. I have already given a fair description about the winter season m last year f s report, but I would like to add that the coldest months are January and February. This / jnainly due to the snow melting up at Quetta and we get the cold North wind^blowing with it all the dust from the desert land of the interior. No vegetation can be started in 'Gwadur on account of its poor rainfall. One Baluch tries his best and has succeeded in producing tomatoes, brinjals and dhania, but very small in size and very expensive. He personally goes around with his wife watering the area which takes up the full day. In the days gone by, I am told, there were a few vegetable gardens here and the vegetables were sold quite cheaply. There was plenty of drinking water, sweet, and the wells were nearer the town then than what they are now. Gwadur means 'the gate of breeze'. When rain clouds appear over head, and it looks like we’re in for a good downpour of rain, the breeze starts up known as the ’shamal’ and the clouds are driven away. On the whole, the weather here is very pleasant indeed. Conclusion. 21. My relations with the Tali, Administrator, Customs Amin, all other State (Government servants and the various Headmen of local communities are most cordial and friendly.May, 1950. The following is an extract f rom the 'Dawn' newspaper of Wednesday 3rd , GWADUR : an intolerable Ety H.M.Balnch, CONFRONT El) BT numerous urgent problems demanding immediate and undivided attention that arose in the wake of partition, Pakistan has so far paid little or no heed to several other issues which, though comparatively less important, have nevertheless to be tackled soon. One such problem relates to the future of Gwadur, a territory in the possession of the Arab Sultan of Muskat &amp; Oman situa ted on the Mekran Coast in South Baluchistan. Both from the point of view of iti geographical position and historical and cultural background, Gwadur is an inte gral and inseparable part of the State of Mekran. The word Gwadur is a combination of two Baluchi words 'Guad' and 'Dar' mean ing the 'Gate of Wind'. Situated between the Mekran ports of Pasni and Jiwani, the territory has no defined Tnanjer boundaries. The question of its boundaries had been a bone of contention between the Ruler of Kalat State and the Sultan of Muskat long before the pertition of the Indian sub-continent. But inspite of apparent efforts to find a solution, the question remained unsolved. Roughly the boundaries extend in north to an area of about 8 to 10 miles and ends in a place called Fhuleri. Having a total population of approximately 14»000 Gwadur comprises a sea town of that name, two other minor ports and a number of small villages scattered over an area is called Nagore. The southern part of Gwadur is a T shaped strip of land about five miles long and half to one mile wide projection from the main coast in the north into the Arabian Sea and ending in the south with a six to seven hundred feet high reef called 'Koh-Batail'. The reef which is about nine miles in length and half to one mile in width is responsible for the formation of the east and west bays. The top of the reef contains a catchment area with an ancient masonary flam supposed to have been constructed by the Portuguese. The dam is a fine example of ancient engineering and workmanship. The huge blocks of stone used in its construction are nicely carved in rectangular blocks, which dovetail together to make a firm wall. There is no evidence of cement or some other material having been used in its construction. NATURAL SEAPORT. The town of Gaadur with a total population of about 8,000 is a natural sea port situated on the bank of the east bay on a sandy but hard soil dotted by tall date-palm trees which present a picturesque sight. Most of the buildings are made of mud only. Yfells dug in the narrowest belt of the projected strip provide the only source of water supply to the town, which has a tenperate cli mate and is considered one of the healthiest spots among the coastal towns of the Persian Gulf and the Gulf of Muskat and Oman. The indigenous produce of fish, which is famous both for its quality and variety and the catching of which constitutes the main occupation of its inhab itants. After being salted and dried, the fish is exported mostly to Colombo and some to Hong Kong. The other two minor ports of Gwadur are small fishing villages called Sur ara and Pishukan having a population of about 1,500 to 2,500 respectively. While the former is situated on the mouth of the east bay about 15 miles from the town of Gwadur, the latter is in the west bay at a distance of 25 miles by land. The rest of the area called Nagore consists of small scattered villages. HISTORICAL BACKGROUND,HISTORICAL BACKGROUND. Gwadur was always a part of Mekran. About a century ago the then rulers of Mekran allowed one of the Arab Sheikhs to take refuge in the town because he was a holy man Syed, who are held in great esteem by Muslims. Since then it has remained in the possession of the Sultan of Muskat and Qnan, who until recently were paying a nominal royalty to the Ruler of Mekran. In later years, the Arabs are said to have extended their hold by gradual encroachments occupying some of the adjoining territory which was lying waste and unprotected. The bulk of the population of Gwadur is of pure Baluch origin and belong to the same stock as those living in the hinterland of Mekran. They speak the Baluchi language and call themselves Baluch. Their customs and habits as well as their mode of living are the same as those of the people of Baluchistan. There are no natural barriers restricting intercourse between Gwadur and Tehran. The economic and social life of the former is inseperably linked with that of the latter. The people of Gwadur own land and other property on the other side of the border and have k the closest relationship with the people of Mekran. ABMINISTRAT ION. The system of administration in Gwadur is of the worst and the most anti quated type. There is hardly an organisation for maintenance of law and order. A Wali or Governor appointed by the Sultan rules the place with an iron hand and exercises absolute civil and criminal powers. He is assisted in h the performance of his duties by a Qazi and about 30 Bedouins called 'Askaris' or policeman. Disputed between individuals are settled orally and in an arbitrary manner by h the Wali, who often passes sentences of flogging and confinement to dungeons. There is a British Agency in Gwadur staffed by an Agent working directly under the British Consul at Muskat. His main functions are to report events in Gwadur and the adjoining areas and also to look after the interests of the British subjects in that place. He also tries civil end criminal cases involving British subjects residing there. Gwadur lacks all modern amenities such as sanitation and medical aid. Edu cational facilities were completely non-existint. A.bout a year or so ago, a primary school housed in a single room, mud building was opened end is most in adequate to meet the local requirements. SOURCE OF REVENUE. The only source of revenue of Gwadur is the customs duty charged on goods imported via sea or land. In pre-war years the revenue from the customs was roughly Rs.30,000 but it has now risen upto Rs.5 lakhs. This abnormal increase is attributable not to any increase in the rates of duty but to the fact that duty is charged on the market value of the imported goods. The absence of any regulated and controlled market has led to a terrible amount of black marketing and smuggling. In 1947 the price of one bag of broken rice soared up to Rs. 200 while coarse cloth, which was very much in demand in Ealat, Iranian Mekran and parts of Baluchistan, was sold at Rs.4 per yard. SMUGGLING. Since the outbreak of the last world war all essential commodities re re supp lied on a quota basis by the Government of India to the various Arab Ports in the Persian Gulf. Due to scarcity of foodstuffs and other essential articles in the adjoining country in the Persian Gulf, most of the commodities inported for local consumption were smuggled into other countries yielding huge profits to the smugglers. Following the partition • • . . •/V ■ jr •• Following the partition of the Indo-Pakiatan sub-continent, however, the quota system was discontinued though the import of Indian cotton piece goods continued as before. There was an acute shortage of food in the Persian Gulf ports. Tempted by the desire to reap high profits, merchants of Gwadur, which has always served as a distributing centre for smuggled goods, offered tempting prices for these articles to traders in Mekran. Consequently large quantities of foodgrains supplied by the Pakistan Government to Mekran started pouring into Gwadur. Similarly rice from Karachi continued to be smuggled in large quantities in fishing boats. This illegal trade is not confined to fooggrains only but also ±m extends to a number of other commodities. Articles such as cloth, sugar, gold, matches and cigarettes imported into Gwadur and charged at a lower rate of duty are smuggled into Pakistan territory via Mekran as well as Karachi, thus depriving the Pakistan Government of a considerable amount of its customs revenue. In view of the unrestricted intercourse between Gwadur and± the bordering areas both by sea and by land and in the absence of any check on the boundaries it is pratically impossible to put an end to this illegal trade. In view of the facts mentioned above and in consideration of the vital strategic position occupied by Gwadur, the Government of Pakistan would be well advised to give its closest attention to this problem and take immediate steps to restore Gwadur to Mekran to which it rightly belongs. ■ jr ••</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000076_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/343</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000076</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/343</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 11/1 VI Muscat Administration Reports and related correspondence'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1951/1951</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-20T22:14:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 28; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of correspondence concerning the Annual Muscat Administration Annual Report for the year 1950-51 and contains a copy of the report.The file features the following principal correspondents: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000076#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>