<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023514790.0x00000b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T16:22:33.939Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023514790.0x00000b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>X463/18</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023514790.0x00000b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Visual Arts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>X463/18</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Das Reitkameel (Hèdjīn) des Scherīf Jaẖja, eines Sohnes des Scherīf Aẖmed, dessen Vater der berühmte 1886 verstorbene Grossscherīf Abd èl-Muṯṯálib (vergl. über diesen letzten König Mekka’s vom alten Schlage Mekka, Bd. I, S. 16ff., 174ff.), mit einer reich mit Silber gestickten Satteldecke (batāt). Den Zaum hält der Sklave Jaẖja’s; neben diesem steht Jaẖja selbst im Reiteranzug und links in langen Kleidern zwei Scherife niedrigen Ranges'. Photographer: al-Sayyid ʻAbd al-Ghaffār</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1886/1889</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-22T11:52:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 collotype print</extent><extent>Dimensions:185 x 241 mmFormat:Collotype print, pasted into volumeCondition:The print is in good condition with minor surface dirt and light abrasions throughout.Foliation:‘XVII’Process:Collotype</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Genre/Subject Matter:This photograph shows four men and a camel standing in a flat, stony area. Behind them tall hills rise. The title suggests that one of the men is Sharif Yahya, ‘a son of Sharif Ahmed, whose father was the famous Grand-Sharif Abdulmutalib [bin Ghalib (1880–82)], who died in 1886’.The camel’s reigns are held by Yahya’s slave; to his left, is Yahya himself, in his riding habit, while the two men on the far left are sharifs of a lower rank.The sharif on the left wears a white
                           thawbunderneath a dark-coloured outer robe. At his waist a scimitar or long
                           janbiya– the curved dagger that is traditionally worn at the waist in countries on the Arabian Peninsula – is held in place by a belt. The sharif second from left wears white trousers, a dark-coloured outer robe and striped shirt with a
                           janbiyaat his waist. Both men wear white keffiyehs held in place by dark-coloured agals and sandals. Each holds a stick in his right hand.Yahya and his slave both also wear keffiyehs held in place by dark-coloured agals but while Yahya’s is dark, his slave’s is white. Both men wear belts held up at the torso by decorated neck halters. Yahya holds a stick in his left hand; his slave holds a long-barrelled rifle upright by the upper barrel.The camel is shown bearing a ‘saddle cloth, richly embroidered with silver [thread], or
                           batāt’. Tassels hang from a decorative harness as well as from the saddle itself.The negative has had hand-work applied, causing it to take on a drawing-like quality in places.Inscriptions:Above image, on the right, in ink: ‘XVII’</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023514790.0x00000b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>