<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T17:27:51.487Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Medical Adviser, - Please see the Politi of 26th November about Qua Persian Gulf. The position regardinj responsibility for qu&amp;rant is given briefly in the mil held here on 15th July to i Colonel Moody has now acce; £0 1 -xti ■ to the Political Hi before he will be in a pos; for in Treasury letter No. (flagged B). Should it bi States in the Gulf (e.g. Bi direct responsibility for t that some time will also el to do this. Quarantine a Coast and Qatar where ther&lt; probably have to continue i In these circumstance) to try and find replacemenl for a period of one year al I should be grateful for y&lt; question, and in particulaj method of securing replace! necessary. Before taking any act3 to consult the Foreign OffjMedical Adviser 3 ^ Please see the Political Resident's letter No*2029-S of 26th November about Quarantine Medical Officers in bhe Persian Gulf. \ The position regarding His Majesty's Government's responsibility for quarantine control in the Persian Gulf is given briefly in the minutes of the meeting (flagged A) held here on 15th July to discuss quarantine arrangements. Colonel Moody has now accepted the appointment of Medical £0 ■ W&amp;bP&amp;c to the Political Resident, but it will be some time before he will be in a position to produce the report asked for in Treasury letter No. IP 140/04 B of 26th July (flagged B). Should it be decided that some of the Arab States in the Gulf (e.g. Bahrein and Koweit) should undertake direct responsibility for quarantine matters it is probable that some time will also elapse before they are in a position to do this. Quarantine arrangement^, at Muscat, the Trucial Coast and Qatar where there are no^State medical services will probably have to continue on their present basis. i /jqj In these circumstances it seems to me that we shall have to try and find replacements for Captain Steele and Dr. Hynes for a period of one year after the latter leave the Gulf. I should be grateful for your views and suggestions on this question, and in particular your suggestions as to the best method of securing replacements if you agree that this is necessary. Before taking any action it will of course be necessary to consult the Foreign Office. &gt;(&gt;mmm Ifx. Hallows I quite agree with the Political Resident ^ in the Persian Gulf* that the type of ofiicer renuired is the officer of the ex-I»t**D•» oL the kind who have, up to now, been employed in that area. I have two men in mind - hiajor Robert oampbel I, I.A.l ,0, (ex I.U.D.) and Major F.M.F* Forres^, I.A.MG. (ex I.II.D.) . Both hold British qualifications and both are likely to be available and their reactions are being ascertained unofficially without any coiimitmeii-/. Neither are young, their ages being 5° 5^ respectively but both are officers of considerable experience who would be of great value to the Resident and colonel I body. If Dr. Easey is willing to transfer from Bushire to the south side of the Gulf, (Of which I am doubtful, in view of the pickings in Bushirey it would appear that only one appointment would be necessary, in which event we should be in a position to select the most suitable of the two individuals mentioned, always assuming that they are interested. I further think that a copy of the Resident's letter and other indications of the action taken should be sent to Colonel Moody for his information to keep him in touch with the situation.migm ■ 3- Ji /U H. CU^-^s C^cd . I' ■ / J~lc^y^wj&lt;- lljl / i?. v/ L~rf xg ^v 1 Mr* Hallows I note that the post of one Surgeon, Bahrein Residency, has now been jiven to Colonel Moody at a salary of £2*500 a year, as against the £930 provided for in the Resident's get* therefore^ assume that the posts which are now under consideration are t tfJP^of one Assistant Surgeon enc-± at the Bahrein Residency and the ICoweit Agency, for v/nich remuneration has been provided at the rate of £615 and £^1*7 per annum respectively. These remunerations may have oeen adequate for members of the I*Ivi*D. when earning periodic increments in an established Service when domiciled in India,but do not st:-ike nie as generous when proposed foi* a period of contract service for medical men with British qualifications proceeding from England. it is noted that the Agency Surgeons remuneration has been up-graded in these circumstances by 2507a» and in my opinion it will be necessary materially to increase the remuneration proposed for Bahrein and howeit; and I would propose that the scale of pay should be £1,000 - £ 1,050 - £1,100 with generous Income Tax concessions. It is noted that ■ 'only 2/5ths of Colonel Lloody’s income is taxable and I would suggest a similar provision for these two commissioned officer^ proceeding on contract from England, especially in view of the fact that no provision for pension or superannuation is contemplated. 31.12.1947■ ^ ■ —- | - / / Mr, Donaldson V 26th Noveniber and 22nd December and noting of General Hance. The Treasury (Slliman’s letter of 18th September; have agreed to the retention of the present medical staff (which includes the 3 quarantine medical officers at Kuwait, Bahrein, and Luscat) until the 31st March on the present terms, it was the idea that Colonel Moody should recoaiinend what long term staff H.M. G. will need to continue to provide for the Persian Gulf to fulfill their international obligations. Until Colonel Moody's recommendations are received it is unlikely that the Treasury will be prepared to agree to contracts on any but a very short term basis. As regards Muscat Sir R. Hay has recommended the extension of Dr. Matthew's contract for 3 years terminable at 1 month's notice. If it is terminable at such short notice I do not see much point in making it for as long as 3 years. As regards Kuwait Dr. Hinds will be there until May when he goes on K months' leave, when Sir R.Hay recommends that his services should be dispensed with. At Bahrein Dr. Steele wishes to retire on the 31st March. It is possible ; though doubtful^that Easey will agree to come over from Bushire to, serve on under H.M.G. at Bahrein and Sir R. Hay ^pfes sound4«^ him. It may, however, be possible to devolve sur quarantine responsibility at Bahrein at an early date on the Bahrein Government who have quite an efficient set up. These problems are really for the Foreign Office to deal with, since the period after 31 st March is involved. I attach a draft to Gardener.staff is concerned* I should be grateful for your comments. Jrna**** 0 '' c I!r. Harrison : I entirely agree that a clear distinctioh is necessary betv/een temporary and stop-gap arrangements and the permanent set-up. Taking the former first. At this late stage I ■ can see no alternative to some arrangement such as that outlined in para 7 of your ininute immediately preceding. The reason is that while I think it may be possible to obtain recruits on terms approximating to those outlined by Colonel I.loody for a period of say, 3 years (with adequate provision for family passages), I think much more liberal terms would be necessary for a period of one year. It is to be remembered that the medical market position in this country is very fluid; and doctors would require inducement to absent themselves for so short a time with the attendant risk of 'missing the ’bus' until it clears. An extended period would at least attract the man who is drawn to foreign service if worth his while} but the shorter period offers him nothing but the prospect of being thrown in a year’s time on to a market from v/hich the cream has been skimmed. I should be reluctant even to approach ex-I.I'.S. officers on these conditions - and I do not think that advertisement in the medical journals would produce a marked response f at anyrate from a desirable type* Loreover, to obtain Treasury sanction and to get the man on the ground by the 1st May is practically impossible.r I think, therefore, 'that they must make local arrangements until we have Looeys considered and long-terr: proposals - anl Treasury sanction thereon - on which we can into the market. o On the Sitra proposal, I a^ree with the Resident and Colonel Moody. If ^/Transport agree it would appear that the cost of this necessary post v/ould largely be offset by port dues - though it appears he has not taken rent of quarters into account, which is essential failing an allowance in lieu. Regarding the proposed consultation of M/Health, I have no doubt you are right although the exact function of each of the 3 le w s of the stool - F.O. (Dr. Pridie), C.R.O. arid Id/llealth - is obscure to me. But Dr. Stock has great experience in quarantine matters; and if it can be expeditiously available , it would be of great help. Decisions, I take it, a^re for ? .0? 9.3. 1940 . *- 7‘ It would therefore seem possible bry bringing Dr. Easey to Bahrein on 1st April, transferring him to Koweit on 1st Key and bringing back Steele to Bahrein in July to provide stopg^ x *p arrangements of a sort until further doctors can be recruited at* &lt;H on a longer term basis. This would certainly not be a satisfac- awfr t * r 'I J tory arrangement but the Foreign Office are inclined to favour something on these lines until Colonel Moody’s overall proposals for the Gulf has a whole can be considered and financial sanction obtained for the engagement of the required type of personnel. ^ Meanwhile it will be helpful to have your views on the possibility of obtaining British doctors on the terms reconmended in the report by Colonel Moo^y enclosed in Sir R. Hay’s express letter of 17th February. 1 should be glad to have your views on the suitability of the terms proposed and the chances of recruiting suitable Britisn doctors^ and ti^ earliest dates by which this might be affected. $ ^ l*~uy X U £ &amp;**+**+ Kffyu. r r /(^y&gt; Cj The proposals for the appointment of a quarantine medical officer at Sitra forwarded with the Political Resident's express letter of 20th February may be considered separately. I have no doubt that the steps proposed are desirable but the financial angle needs to be considered and in this connection the proposal for the recovery of quarantine dues from ships is important, tie shall have to obtain the views of the Ministry of Transport as to the feasibility of this. I would propose to send them a copy of the relevant correspondence and request their views. /O, I think we should also send a copy of this correspondence to Dr. Stock at the Ministry of Health. The Foreign Office did tt/lMt not consult theM before writing to the Treasury on 12th February but agree that they be brought in. I suppose that properly speaking thef7ought to advise on the implementation of H.M.G.'s quarantine responsibilities in the Persian Gulf but the Foreign Office will no doubt wish to continue to refer to G.R.O. (i.e. yourself)insofar as the employment of I.M.S. or I.M.D. /staffsi h c™' m 'si j? a “ 1 w w • ^ ^ / Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office C? /o r ALLOTTED TO EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT (B) CONFIDENTIAL CODE mDay^ XT ks \y 7 FROM: POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN -&amp;ULF D. BAHREIN, 13.30 hours, 28th March 1948 R. 13.25 hours, 28th March 1948 No.282. M My telegram No.266 March 24 th. Medical officers. 2. Reference paragraph 8 . Furniture. I strongly recommend that free furniture should he provided. 3. Medical officers quarters at Muscat are furnished hut those at Bahrein and Koweit are not. Steele is willing to sell his furniture for about Rs.2,500 and Hynes for Rs.4,750. Figure for Hynes furniture is high hut price quoted will almost certainly he obtained locally. Hynes is anxious to know urgently whether Government will take his furniture over as otherwise he will sell locally. 4. Request that either competent Ministry of Works officer he sent to value and take over furniture at early date or that I may he authorised to buy it at prices not exceeding those quoted. . J.M.^a^her ( Copy to :- Foreign Office - Mr. (2) Min. of Health - Dr. P. G.-^S^feck. C.R.O. - General HancV.£ -? ’ ‘iU / Allotted to E::tornal Dcpartmont('B) 10&lt; ^ ^ Confidential Code ' ivsj n ^ ^ FROM : POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF Di Bahrein, 17.20 hours, 24th March 1948 R 23.55 hours, 24th March 1948 No.266 Your telegram No.57 1 1th Marc h. 2. Paragraphs Nos. 1 and 2. I agree that final arrangements must he deferred until full report has been considered. Proposals referred to in my express letter - n a gt.h Pn'h-pnn-ry were in nature of interim arrangements in view of imminent departure of Steele and Hyne s. 3 . Paragraph No.3 - (a) and (b). Matthews and Easey have agreed to terms, provided that so far as Easey is concerned there is no liability to income tax. (c) Motala has agreed to terms provided his services are not required by Pakistan to whom he has applied for permanent employment. 4. Paragraph No.5• Government of India will not allow Hynes to stay on deputation after 31st March and he will retire on 1st April. Sanction therefore requested to retain Hynes until 30th April 1948 on present rate of pay(rupees 1 ,000 per mensem) free of income toe: and with free quarters. . Easey should take over at Koweit on May 1st. I am strongly opposed to Hynes retention after that date, c.f. paragraph No. 3 of my demi official No.2029 - S dated November 11 th 1947. 5. Steele is unwilling to remain longer than middle of May. -Is unwilling to return after departure as is proceeding to Kenya. Age (57)? health and family reasons. Essential therefore to provide relief middle of May latest. Although /proposals 0 S4 Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office- 2 - proposals in m y 421 - S February 17th only temporary it is already clear eventual arrangements must include provision of certain number of British doctors. Suggest therefore that one British doctor be engaged forthwith' on three-year contract. ^ Terms for first year as proposed. Can be stated terms may be liable to revision after first year but will not be less favourable. Moody considers although salary not high, V state allowances and private practice should make appointment worth total £2,000 per annum. If still doubtful whether emoluments offered sufficient suggest as alternative £700 per annum taxable plus £ 1,000 per annum allowances free of tax. 6 . In the meantime Steele should be retained until May 15th on existing rate of pay(Rs. 1,005) per mensem free of income tax with free quarters plus state allowances. 7. Paragraph Kb.4. Subordinate Indian medical staff should be retained for further year subject to one month*s notice, on existing rates of pay, details of which are given in enclosure to my demi official No.921 - S dated May 15 th. 1947. Paragraph No. 6 . Free accommodation is already provided. I will deal separately with question of furniture. Copy to ; F. 0 .,(Mr,J.M.Fisher) ( 2 ) Ministry of Health, (Dr.P.G.Stock) , Gen.HanceEXTERNAL DF,P.ARTMEm’ (Wl EN from : POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULP. RPTD: TEHRAN. D. BAHREIN, 14.25 hours, 19th March, 1948. R. 15,55 hours, 19th March, 1948. No.241 . Addressed London, Tehran tel egram 29 15th March Sasey has accex^ted terms ofdpred and is willing to take over as . « QMO Bahrain or Kuwait when required*OUTWARD TELEGRAM Cypher/OTP x XS^/3^V^J Confidential -- fMW ^ ^ f '”4 *1 PERSOKKE aJ JLi PRC.. FOREIGN OPPICS TO TEHRRN No . 139 T?th iviaroh, 19X8. D. 10.30 a.m. 13th naroh, 19X8, Following from Personnel Department. Doctor Rasy will he required to take up post as Doctorin the Persian Gulf by th, end of ^arch. Confirmation of actual date will be telegraphed to you in a few days. ^s it will not be possible to arrange for the transfer of a Branch 'S'officer in time to take over from E sy, do you agree to temporary closure of post for say, approximately three months? We are becoming increasingly doubtful of the value of this post. Would you strongly object to its being closed down completely? F F F FNo. B-jPOKTiil^T Your letters 421-3 of 17th February and 446-S of 20th February‘^about medical arrangements in the Gulf raise a number of problems which will require full consideration here and this will t-duce .time. Moreover ^we would prefer^not to deal piecemeal with the medical organisation but to review the arrangements^as a wiiole when Moocty- has had time after a few months to make -aai a ccmprehensive^ report with reconmendations for the future. ' 2. Our imaediate concern must be to ensure * ^ ^ continuation of stop-gap arrangements more or less on present lines for about a year until alternative arrgLncemengs can be worked out in the light of Moody's considered report, necessary &gt;_ - ^ ^ «. financial sanction obtained and staff engaged. It would be more difficult to obtain suitable men on one year contract -^han 'on 3 year and more ' • — ^ - v liberal terms would iiave to be offered for a shorter^period. In aiy case it would be practical^ impossible to get anyone 'out''to Gulf iy 1st Mgy. ^ 3» *^e have already obtained sanction^for '' s' ^ employment for one year of following staff / A ^ ) Mathews — Medical i.iffioer, Muooat. Taxable salary £540 per annum plus foreign ''s' S' ^ allowance £400 plus any State allowance. '' Pay Rs .600 a month plus allowance as recommended^in paragraph 6 of your letter No.12?-S of 14 th January. ( c ) /Matala Easey'0 S' /''* (i.) MjitaJ.a - Pay Rs.350 a month plus allowance as ^ y recommended-in your letter No. 30 - 93/1 of 5th January, -ve have taken no steps in regard to'Steele but it appears essential that his contract be extended. ^ What terms'do * you recommend? 4. wliat do you recommend regarding continued en^loyment of subordinate Indian medical staff, ^compounders, etc? f ^ S s' s' 5* I appreciate that on basis of above staff it will be ' *. • ^ ^ difficult to fill gap ^ Steele is to be on leave'for 3 / S / s' S / _ s r or 4 months from 1st April and ifynes is to leave'Koweit on 1st May• Could Steels'be persuaded to cut ieave to say, r 2 months and i^ynes to postpone departure (intil Steele’s ^tum. Easey might act at Bahrein during bteele’s leave and then take over 'At Kov/eit. He can be''' made available ^from Bushire 'And if you agree 'will be instructed to proceed to Bahrei*f*forthwith. Bo your recommendations for officers referred to in paragraph 3 include free furnished rent.CONFIDENTIAL FILE COPY 2 A F R K T T E R SO » ^ Wo /• EXT 1&gt; U * From To Political Resident, Bahraita^- H.M's Secretary of State for Xommonwearth oeurtitary ui ouaue iui* ^ommojywtjaj. wii \ Relations, Bahrain. i.(%Hc^Jt No.446-S 1 ' Dated, BAHRAIN, the 20th February, f948 ‘JL %6 FEB : V . ^ Demi- official. Harrison from Hay. * sb Viu Reference my Express setter No.421-S dated 17th February 1948_on the subject of the appointment of Quarantine Medical Officers. 2. I support throughout Moody 1 s proposals contained in the enclosure to my Express Letter under reference. Negotiations with the States with a view to their taking over the quarantine administration are likely to be protracted and it is certainly desirable that we should put the administration on proper lines before we' hand it over. 3. The chief objection to Moody's proposals is likely to be that they involve us in additional expenditure. At Bahrain the salary proposed for the ^.M.O. totals £.1500 a year whereas the salary at present drawn by Captain Steele is Rs.1005 per month i.e. about £.900 a year. The additional expenditure will thus amount to about £.600 a year. I do not consider any dearness allowance necessary for the Q.M.O. Bahrain especially as he will be drawing an allowance from the State and probably from certain firms. 4. At Kuwait I consider it essential to add a dearness allowance of not less than £.200 a year to the salary pro posed by Moody as prices are higher, no allowance is paid by the State and there is little or no income from contract practice. The pay drawn by the present incumbent at Kuwait, Dr. Hynes, is Rs.990 a month or a little under £.900 a year as against £.1700 per annum proposed for the new Q.M.O. making a difference of £.800. 5* The new appointments are proposed for one year only and the extra expenditure is not excessive in view of the ad vantage to be gained from the appointment of fully qualified medical doctors. It may be possible to cover some or all of the expendit ure by the recovery of quarantine dues from shipping vide paragraph 7 below; and it should also be borne in mind that the pay of temp* orary incumbents must necessarily be higher than that for the present permanent staff as they earn no pension. Similarly a certain amount of the extra expenditure can be set off against the sum which His Majesty's Government are liable to contribute towards tne pensions of the present incumbents. 6* As promised in paragraph 3 of my Express Letter under reference I forward herewith a note prepared by Moody on quarantine and medical arrangements at Sitra. _l fully agree with the proposals it contains and would ask for early sanctton to the appointment of a Britisn q.M.O. on £.1500 a year and to the other staff and expenditure proposed. ^he main proposal calling for comment is that relating to the recovery of quarantine dues from vessels visiting Sitra. I have suggested before that dues should be recovered at Sitra to cover both lighting and buoying and quarantine vide parag raph 4 of^my_demi-official^lett er No .737-S dated the 10th September, 1946, In Moody's 'note the rate^oT quarantine dues suggested is * Rs.ES per vessel which I am informed is similar to that'charged at Basrah. This as-Moody shows should cover the greater part of our expenditure at Sitra. I see no reason why dues should not be recovered at the same rate at Manama, Kuwait and Fahahil (the Kuwait’^r -page 2 - Oil Company 1 s port) and set off against the extra expenditure pro posed at Bahrain and Kuwait vide paragraph 5 above. . x would suggest that shipping interests be consulted regarding this scheme and that if it is approved I should be asked to submit definite proposals for its implementation. If ^lightly higher rate could be reasonably A charged so much the better. I would note that I shall probably be 'ibmitting in due course proposals for the recovery of lighting dues * irom shipping at Sitra, Fahahil and elsewhere, but these will probably take a considerable time to formulate and I see no reason why we sheu- should not proceed with the recovery of quarantine dues at once. 8. ^ The question of legal cover for the recovery of such dues requires to be considered. I am not sure that ehueh such cover is necessary and I have been informed by the Port Director Basrah, that no legal cover exists 'for the recovery of lighting dues in the Shatt-al-Arab. If however it is considered desirable to provide legal cover this could be done either by a Regulation under Article 70(a) of the Bahrain Order-in-Council and the corresponding article of the Kuwait Order-in-Council or by the addition of the Indian Ports Act(XV) of 1908 to the enactments enumerated in Article 11(2) of the Bahrain Order-in-Council and the corresponding article in the Kuwait Order-in-Council. 9. I should be grateful for early orders regarding (a) the appointment of a Quarantine Medical Officer at Sitra with the necessary staff etc. (b) the recovery of quarantine dues from ships visiting the ports in the Bahrain and Kuwait Shaikhdoms.m . f- s X I P A quarantine and Medical Arrangements From a study of the files and correspondence and from discussions with the Q.M.O* Bahrain and with representatives of Messrs• Gray, Mackenzie and the Bahrain Petroleum Company it is clear that there is need of a full time Quarantine Medical Officer at ditra. 2e The present arrangements are briefly as follows: (a) Ships bound for Sitra radio ahead to Bahrain (1) The nane of the last port of call (2) Whether they received a clean bill of health from that pert or not, and (3) Whether they have any sickness on board ©r not. If they are not coming frcm an infected port and if tie y have a clean bill of health and no sickness, the Bahrain gives the ship pratique through the Agents. There is therefore no inspection of the ship and no check of the information received via the Ship's radio. (b) Only if the ship is infected or'‘suspected' or notifies cases of sickness on board does the Q.M.O. from Bahrain board the ship. If he is not immediately available there is considerable delay to the ship in berthing and loading and/or unloading. (c) The ships themselves being almost entirely tankers or freighters have no medical officer on board and any medical attention required has also to be obtained from the Q.M.O. Bahrain, again with inevitable delay. 3. Shipping traffic through Sitra has increased steadily since the war and about 70 ships a month are now using the port. Between 8Q£ and 90£ of these are tankers and freighters connected with BAPCO affairs. Sitra is about 17 miles by road from Manama, the Headquarters of the Q.M.O. Bahrain, and it is quite impracticable for him to attend at Sitra other than as described in paragraph 2. This arrangement is inadequate and unsatisfactory. 4. BAPCO have constructed the wharf at Sitra and for all practical purposes control all matters there. Whatever quarantine arrangements we may wish to make will therefore of necessity have to be done with the cooperation of BAPCO. 5* I have visited Sitra and Awali snd entered into a fairly thorough discussion with Mr. Russol Brown, Chief Local Representative of BAPCO. He stated, that apart from quarantine measures, his chief concern was the provision of medical attention for the crews of oil tankers and freighters at Sitra, where as many as 10 ships at a time are anchored or berthed. For this purpose BAPCO had been considering establishing a Dispensary with a Medical Officer at Sitra, and Mr. Russel Brown suggested that this Medical Officer could in addition undertake the work of Quarantine Medical Officer. 6. I do not think this suggestion of Mr. Russel Brown's satisfactory for various reasons. The Quarantine Medical Officer would be an employee of BAPCO in whose interests he would be chiefly concerned. He would not oe under the control of the Political Resident nor of the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer. 7. Mr. Russel Brown however was quite agreeable to our appoint ing a Q.M.O. who would undertake to give medical attention to ships at Sitra wharf and anchorage in addition to his other duties. The proposals which I then discussed with Mr. Russel Brown and which are now for the consideration of the P.P. follow! in the/12 Elfl&amp;ncia]. Implications .... in the succeeding paragraphs. 9. There should be a full time Quarantine Medical Officer Sltra with an office and Dispensary in the vicinity of the wharf and residence at Awali. Kis duties would bes- (1) to board all vessels arriving at Sltra and give them pratiqu4 or otherwise. He would also give then a clean bill of health on departure. This service would be a 24 hour one. (BAPCO Intend installing lighting and other facilities for day and night berthing)• (2) to be responsible for health and sanitation measures in the port itself (e.g. anti-rat, etc.). (3) to provide medical attention to crews of ships at tne Dispensary or on board the ship if necessary. To arrange for the landing arid hospitalisation ef cases requiring such measures. (4) Item (3) being outside the duties of the Q.M.O. as such, the Q.M.O. would receive fees for these services. These fees would be fixed $ suggested rates are: (a) Rs.10 for attendance during day time at Dispensary or ship betthed alongside wharf (b) Rs.16 for ship anchored outside (c) Rs.20 for night visit or attendance. I would propose that the Q.M.O. should retain 70$ of such fees, 30$ being credited to Government. 10 (a) Office . BAPCO would construct a suitable building, appropriately furnished, on the causeway pierhead at Sltra. Mccommedation would include a combined Medical Inspection room and Dispensary, an office, and bathroom facilities. Furniture, fans, lighting, water etc. included. BAPCO would pay the initial cost but would expect us to pay a rent. (b) Residence . BAPCO would allot fully furnished air- conditioned accommodation at Awall. Their scale for bachelor quarters including full messing, is Rs.76C p.m. Married accommodation would be a furnished air conditioned house including light ana water etc. for which their rate is Rs.500 p.m. excluding messing. Amenities would include membership of their club, use of the commissary and educational facilities for children (up to 14 years of age). TRAWSPORT 11* (a) Sea . The BAPCO launch which takes off the pilot for 011 tankers and freighters would also take the Q.U.O. This would entail no cost to Government. (b) BAPCO have an arrangement for higing a car at an inclusive cost of fcs.760 p.m. which 1 covers repairs, maintenance, petrol, oil etc. This however is too expensive but a car is essential as Awali is 6 miles from Sitra. As the Q.M.O. will be on a short term contract he can hardly be expected tf provide his own car and I suggest that/the best solution a Government car (small Hillman or Austin) provided for the use of the Q.v; # 0., the latter to be responsible for running costs (petrol, oil, servicing etc.).- page 3 - yiMAKCUL I ^UUXlQfL 12 . A. fexpendltare (i) British Q.M.O. (1 year contradt reftewahle/ Basic salary plus £• 600 p.a. taxable £. 900 p.a. non-taxable £•1600 p.a. (ii) Clerk - lecal rates approximately Ks.160 p.m. Farash - lecal rates approximately Fs. 60 p.aa. above rates equivalent te £.170 per annum. Initial cost of car or calculated on a basis of a five year life (in) yrtnafeftrJ; £.400 (approx.) £• 80 p.a. Civ) Medical Stores Estimate not exceeding £.100 p.a. (v) Rent of Dlaccnsary Estimate not exceeding £.160 (cost of building and furniture £.15000) Total estimated annual expenditure b. Fcygnag £.200Q ap pgoz (i) 30% g.M.O^ fees (para.9(4) estimated (ii) Proposed port dues at Rs.25/- per ship estimated Total NOTE a With the increasing traffic at Sitra the estimates under havenue are conservative and may well cover expenditure. 1*. If the above proposals are approved and sanctioned Mr. Russel brown indicated that he could provide the facilities specified at 3 months notice subject to his firm’s approval. £• 200 p.a. £.1600 p.a. £.1800 p.a. appro:CONFIDENTIAL ( -’ ' • !*• ♦&gt; _ \«y, V- 1*5 k 'WZy « 6 ?t KOO^ I EXPRESS LETTER • r , Fr®a Political Resident, Bahrain T© H.M’s Secretary @f State for Commonwealth Relatiens, Lenden &lt; V©*421-8 Dated BAHRAIN, the 17th February, 1948 , ■ ■' ^il/v Demi-official. Donaldson from Hay* k .. Reference correspondence ending with my uVa. telegram No* 149 dated th e 15th February, 1948. _ 2. I enclose a copy of a report I have received from Moody on the subject ©f reliefs for the present Quarantime Medical Officers at Bahrain and Kuwait. 3. I hope to comment on Moody's proposals in more detail by the next bag, and to forward a supplementary report received Erom him regarding quarantine arrangements at Sitra. Meanwhile it is urgently necessary to obtain a relief for Steele, Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain who is due t© go on leave ©n the 1st April. Although he has volunteered to return as Q.M.O. Bahrain after 3 ©r 4 months leave and has dene good work in the past he is well past the age of retirement and Moody considers, and I agree, that it is desirable to replace him with a British, doctor who is better qualified and more up to date. 4. The employment of a fully qualified British doctor will cost more and I will examine the financial implications when I comment in detail. Meanwhile I would suggest that Hance be asked to be on the l©ok out for one or two doctors of the type recommended by M©ody. 5* Incidentally Moody informs me that of the two I.M.D. doctors recommended by Hance ©ne is understood to have obtained employment elsewhere and the ©ther was inter viewed by him and considered unsuitable. Sd/- W.R. Hay. Political Resident, Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL QUARANTINE ORGANISATION - PRELI MINARY SURV V tUt pa Bahrai4 r- . It is clear that existing quarantine arrangement i are inadequate and reorganisation with an increase inr-eg-tw&amp;Listoodnt is required. Of immediate urgency is the provision of reliefs for the present Quarantine Medical Officers at Bahrain and Kuwait. 2. Even if it is the intention to hand over quarantine arrange ments eventually to the States concerned, I note from a perusal of the files that this presents many difficulties and in any case will take a considerable time to complete. 3. I think also that before handing over we should organise adequate and satisfactory quarantine arrangements where necessary, and hand over in each case a ’’going concern”. This would at least set the States a standard of Quarantine Service which it would be up t© them to maintain. 4. In the meantime I would propose setting up&amp; small cadre of Quarantine Medical Officers (Persian Gulf) on a uniform basis and on similar terms and conditions of service subject to local conditions, under the control of the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer. 5. I do not think we should confine recruitment t© members of the late India* Medical Department (British Cadre), solely on financial grounds. In the first place they will eoasx cost more than before since they would in future be employed on a non-pensionable contract basis: secondly it will be increasingly difficult t© contact and select suitable candidates from that source; there are many argu ments, (professional, social etc) in favour of a younger better qualified British doctor, certainly in Bahrain. 6. There has not yet been time t© give full and proper considerat ion t© all details of terms and conditions of service in (fihe differ ent appointments in the Gulf, but taking conditions at Bahrain as * a basis I would suggest contracts on the following lines: , 1. Period . One year in the first place - renewable. Salary . £.600 p.a. (taxable) + £.900 p.a. (non-taxable) 3. Accommodation . Free furnished quarters. Note (a) in certain localities there appears t© be strong case for dearness allowance. (b) Transport is essential. If the doctor has his own car he should bring it and be given a conveyance allowance. Otherwise transport must be provided. i (c) Private practice should normally be restricted to: (1) Medical attendances on‘passengers and crews of ships and planes passing through. (2) Contracts or allowances from local governments. (3) Approved contract practices with certain firms (e.g. those directly or indirectly connected with Government work shch as shipping agents, Air lines, Cable &amp; Wireless etc.) (4) Consultations requested by local doctors. (d) Residency and Agency staffs and families should be entitled to free medical attendance from the Quarantine Medical staff. 7. Required in the immediate future are reliefs for (i) Captain Steele as Q.M.O. Bahrain (1st April 1948) and (ii) Assistant Surgeon Hynes as Q.M.O. Kuwait (1st May 1948). Even though details ©f these proposals require further consideration I would urge accept ance in principle so that reliefs for these two officers may be re cruited without delay. 8. Foreign Office may then be asked to take up urgently the engagement of two Quarantine Medical Officers and I suggest selectioi in consultation with General Hance.- page 2 - 9. I recommend as qualifications a British doctor ^ with seme experience in practice. Previous service in India or Middle East would be a definite advantage. Seme knowledge of ^ Public and/or Port Health is of course a distinct advantage but special qualifications (e.g. D.P.H.) not essential. • ■ i' Sd/- W.J. Moody, Lt.Col.With Mr. J.D.K. Beighton's compliments Ik H 'xa\a/ IP.33VW 7o€ INDEXED Daar \' wi^v ^ % 0 &lt;r: i n 1 _/ ^ lSDRY GIlnivIBERS, S. W. 1. r ^7th **toru*ry f !%&amp;• I9 Th&amp;nk you fbr your lot tor of the 12th itebiuaiy about BMdloel arrsneomento in the ereian Gulf« l«e note that there hes been u avoidU^ble aelay In the • peint^ent of a , edioal Offioer to iwiee the ioeition ani dnw up &amp; oorcprehenaive report on the future medioel organisation in the lerslon Gulf, It is neoessaxy therefore to oontinue existing arnan aaente for another year and I oonfirsi Treaeuxy authority/ orally given for the propoaals set out in your latter* It la not altogether dear whether Hayes’ proposals inoluds free fUxhiehed rent* You art going; to dear up tte oint aaft we agree that Auniaried rent ^iould be paid if Hayes* reoerameoiatione hare been put forward an that baals oa a^eors to be probable, i^e also agree to the provision of drugs er* the line® set out in oaoolA’t letter to ae of the 2tt^i January. I so sealing a copy of this letter to Donaldson* lours slnderBly f Gardener^ Eaq, # 0*B.E., Foreign Office, 8, Carlton House Terrace, S*W*1* JtDbK* BelgNten.Xsiif-fa+W+i) With the Compliments of THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs JNdzxep rixf Foreign Office, K&gt;&lt;4l , 194 ?. a. K.o$ \ ✓ -S Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ^LLOTTED TO IKTURNAL DEPARTl.'IIilNT (B) &gt; ? 0 1 j .. ^ ^ i oi I i ^JLD CODE* 1NDSXED FROM : POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF * D. Bahrain 12*15 hrs. y 15th Fohruary, 1948. £«i August question of offer of contract to him may he dropped* fctfi i/A' 3. My demi-official letter No. 2222-S 27th December. : After discussion with Cac«ia and Moody it has been decided that Msfcfchcws t services are only required for one year in the first place. I am enquiring whether it is possible f©r him to continue to servo on deputation Government of India for this period. I will telegraph further, meanwhile question of his term(s) may pend. No distribution.With i&lt;ir. Gardener^ compliments (xsio/; Zoaedy ;xfao/jte(V4S) FI R mam , To t oi 11 / 91 POKEIOW OFPICK , — i 8, CARLTON K0031 KU- RACS, 12th February f 194^* v iri \. ,. 1 . fylf ?0/l Dear Beighton, You will rernei.ibcr in yoiir letter to Donaldson I.i?.li| &gt;/04B of 26th July you s xictlonod the appointment of a ioedieal officer vO the j 02 *©ian Gulf to draw up &amp; co tproheosive ronort on the ruture of the . tedicfil organisation required to aerry out the responsibilities of His 2 ilajesty , 0 Oovorniaent in that area* There has been on inert table delay in this ap; ointdent and the of^ idtir selected, Ideutenant-colonel .j, : ,/OOdy* is only now tfiLiin^j up his post* / In his letter to Harrison of the Ooi^riouwealth ^elationa office, I*F*333/01 of 12th deptedber last iiJllimf^n tyare sanction for the retention of the present uisdical staff until 31st ^areh. 1942 f on their present terms. It wua hoped that by the 31st larch the newly appointed htedical advisor would have some ideas on the lo»ig tena isedical staff needed in this area* Unfortunately the delay in the appointment of Colonel M^xxly moans that ho will iiardly bo in a position to maiie any accurate pronounoement on the medical staff required by that date f and, oven if he could, it would not be possible to consider and irmleuent his recoramendat 1 one in time to put ttea into rorce by 1st April# V/o iamt therefore consider what action to take to prolong the present arran, ©monto until we are in a osltlon to implerriant hi© eventual recomi.iendations. m© you knov/ # the medical staff in the Gulf have two functions: i) to Q&amp;ri*y out our responsibilities for the quarantine arraj^gements under an international agree lent; and 2} to provide u^edical facilities for our staffs in those areas* &lt; The three main posts concerned are those of uarantine u»edioal oi floor at iiowait* Bunrain tuid u cut* fheue posts ai*o ^ rst present occupied by ex-I. V3. officers, tfr* Hynes f Captain tcele, and Captain Fiathewa respectively* Hynes wis icg for long leave in Hay» 1943 and the Political neoident rcooLiienda (foz reaa^*io into which he Joes not wish to go) that he be not employed after that date* Matiiewe is willing to stay on for a further period with H*2t»0* and Gtocle is wiiiin to return to Bahrain in July after he has had 3 ifionthe^ leave* The * oil tied kesident propooes, however&gt; to consult Dr* ioody on the subject of Steele's returii# Unloae # thorefoi'e* wc take eai*ly step© \.o retain the present ©taiT or to sco^rr© replacuoants for them we shall be in an awkward position by 31st karcli* obviously we oaonot risk failing between two stools* I asked th© Inspectors to look into this problem aiid wdle this letter wco in draft X received a letter from Oaocia (copy oncloaed) in which, you sec he has reached the same oonolueions after discueslon on the spot* I should therefore be moot gx^teful for ^ our early sanction for the engagement of the following 3 officers on the terns stated. Mathwwa/ J*D#K* :3eighton # ;.v»q* 9 Treasury*lt\ thewa Medical officerj* Musiont* Sie present totals 6^0 rupees a r&lt;ioiith. in addition he received dollar e^ehange co .perviati* n allowance which is roMiit to taice the .pls»c« of « deamess fldlowanoe and geiisr&amp;lly spttrlng varies between 1JJ&gt; rupees '&amp;n&amp; rupee© a iaenth* aoaex'ding to the I (iris Theresa .x&gt;lImyRupee exchange rate. In addition he receives from the Lueeat Governioent a quarantine allowance of 130 rupees per mensem and an alio anco, 33 medical offioer, Muscat lafentry # of th«* ssar^ ar«imt* tlsj r^coutu^'ivd^ (in hio letter of 22ml oocember to- the O.H.C* to which Chccia refers) that he be offered &amp; oonirHct r on a bsaic pay nluo foreicn allo-v fxnce which will bring iiim in r pc 00 a ^ntu nei # and that he be allowed t o .jraw In 'Edition any allovanee pel a by the 3tate in which he is employed# therofore ^co.imad for him a taxable salary of d&gt;4o plui' a foreign allowance of i|^00 p#a. to bring his xset pa v roughly up to the ^530 p*ft* rcootfauendedt plus any allowance paid to him by the State in which he is employed* UMBL At present he ia bioo v ino the Ereneh B 3 post at Buohire and hie salary ia :3 (tax free} plus 4 0 foreign allowance. He has oifered to sexnre at Bahrain, Rowelt or Muscat aa required* Ray r-coiiiendB (in hie.lctter to the TaIUO* of - 14th- Jnuuoxy to which Caccia refers) that he be o fered a contract on coneolidated pay of 600 rupees a wntt, plus deamcee ftllo^mee on tnis at the rote in force for the poet to which he may be appointed, togethex* with free accocifjociition* If ids post ia at Bahrain he steroid be permitted to draw the a low' me at present paid by uhc state* The dearness allowance at Bahrain is at present 30 . on 600 rupees and 120 et Kowalt. To are not quite certain Whether Kaaey should be on a sterling rate ox^ not: if a sterling rate seme prefer able we would propose for him a ta; able salary of £$k0 p«ra. pl^is a personal ello ancs of .^100 p*a* (i*o* 600 rupees a saonth) together with tVic different allowances liay rescmamsls* Vo can, I think, leave the px*eoiBe form of his pay until we icaow at which post he will serve. The important point ia that it should equal 600 rupees a *,ton:h nat and the‘appropriate dsarnesa allow ance* Kaasiu .br tx:a a Sub-Assistant »u 2 *geon at ueeat. Hd is well theu^^ht of and it will be eapoci:*lly nocesaary to retain him at daocut if Mathews ie transferred to Bahrain to replace steclo. But he has opted for Tar. i at an and the Political Resident is therefore anxious to offer him terms before the CK&gt;vemaent of : aide ten apr.ly for hie services* Dr. Ho tala has been 'drawing fixed pay of 200 ripeee a month eincc 19+3* addition he Jinn been receiving dollar exchange co pens at ion allowance at varyiiig rates averaging about 100 rupees a month. Kay recommends that he be offered a net 350 rupees a iionth and we ogres. We &amp;ee no reason why his salary should not remain In rupees and agree with Hay that if he is granted an alio once by the State in whioh he is serving he should be allowed to receive it without abating hi a pay from K*M*0* The'Tile above tiiree appointments would be for one year only in the firet imtonce and on the trict undora tandiiig that the new scheme produced aa a result of ioody's report will be brought into force at the earliest possible date. We also ask you for transport expenses to the Q-ulf and return either to India or to this country for both Mathews and Baeey with their wivea and faidLlies at the end of their year’s appointment. At the end of the pear they would be entitled to 60 days* leave including travelling time. These tenae are in px*oportion with the terms approved by you for the other officers in the Gulf serving 3 year appointments. For totals. Hay recoimaends one month '0 leave or pay in lieu and one free 2 nd class passage for himself and Ills family to India on termination of his year's service: we agree to this, and should like your sanction. Wo presume (but are not quite clear' on this point) that free furnished rent would also be a condition of the appointment of these 3 officers. Vie also presume that Hay is awa ting Moody's import before making recommendations about the 2 posts of compounder at Bahrain and . harjah (see the enclosure to Harrison's letter to yo u Ixt.1821/47 of 3y d September last ). You will also see Caccia asks for early sanction for supplies of drugs to the dispensaries for next year and I should therefore be grateful for your sanction for the items listed by him at the end of his letter enc.oaed, as well aa for the other proposals about staffing dealt with in this letter. I am sending a copy of this letter to Donaldson and should be glnd if you could consider these proposals urgently and let me have your reply soon. (A.J. Gardener)(XS10/34k(1A8) Ofrice of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, (Bahrain). 24th January, 1948* My dear John, We discussed with the Political Resident the attached papers about the Quarantine Service and these are our agreed conclusions. First the Resident is fully conscious of the Treasury’s desire that the Quarantine Service should be put on a self- supporting basis at the earliest possible moment. At the same time he points out that some means must be devised to keep the Service going until a new self-supporting scheme had been worked out, approved and put into operation. Dr, Moody has not yet arrived and it is now unfortunately out of the question that he will be able to put in a scheme and get it going with sanction from at home by the 31st March. Apart from anything else a visit to Muscat and back can take up to a month. Our Joint proposal is that financial provision should be made for the continuation of the medical service on present lines for the next financial year on the strict understanding that the new scheme will be brought into force at the earliest possible date within that period. Secondly a general question of policy will have to be decided, namely whether the Quarantine Service shall be run throughout by us or whether it should be taken over by the Shaikhdoios wherever they can be considered competent to run such a Service. At present this would be in Bahrain and possibly in Kowait but not on the Trucial Coast or at Muscat. If on investigation it looks preferable that in Bahrain at least the local authorities should run the (Quarantine Service an agreement will have to be negotiated with the local authorities and once a ain this will take time. Thirdly you will know that the Quarantine Officers have up till now run local dispensaries. These dispensaries have been financed from public funds and a great deal of medical work has been done free amongst the poorer part of the local population. In Bahrain it may be possible to shut the dispensary without great disadvantage. But at some of the other posts we should not close down the dispensaries which have high value for public relations and which are in any case necessary to provide some reliable medical service for our staff. Supplies for these dispensaries can not naturally be charged against any new self- supporting Quarantine Service. Pending Dr. Moody’s considered report we therefore recommend that the terms proposed for the Quarantine Medical Officers in the Resident’s communications of the 22nd December and the 14th January to the Commonwealth Relations Office should be sanctioned at once. We have been through these terns with the Resident and have no comment to make on them other than that it may be better to restrict the period of contract to one year in the first place pending a decision about the new scheme. It is also necessary that the provisions made in the Resident’s Budget for next year for supplies of drugs to the dispensaries should also be sanctioned before the n xt financial year. For your convenience the following are the items in next year’s Budget for this purpose A.J. Gardener, Esq*» C-B.E. Residency/Y\ Hll \| COKFIDi.NTIAL Sr 9- 'bVuJ • oS&gt; indexed EXPRESS LETTS From To Political Resident, bahfain^ H.M f s Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London. No.127-S Dated, BAHRAIN, the 14th January, 1948. December. Your telegram Nc.14733 date d 23rd Quarantine Medical Officers. 2. Easey is provisionally willing to accept contract for one year as Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain but naturally is anxious to know exact terms before reaching a final decision. He,is also willing to serve at Kuwait or Muscat if required. 3. Hynes at Kuwait has now applied for leave pending retirement from May 1st but Steele has stated that he is willing to return to Bahrain as quarantine Medical Officer after taking three months leave from April 1st. I am leaving it to Moody to decide whither Steele should be asked to return or not. 4. Easey's present emoluments are: (i) Pay Rs.400 (ii) Special Pay Rs.150 (iii) Customs Allowance Rs. 50 (iv) House Rent R s. 60 (v) Dearness Allowance 65% or Rs.227/8 5. The allowances attached to the post of Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain are: (i) Special Fay (ii) Compensatory Allowance (iii) Dearness Allowance 50$ Rs.130 Rs. 50 and to the post of quarantine Medical Officer, Kuwait are: (i) Special Pay (ii) Compensatory Allowance (iii) Dearness Allowance 180$ Rs.150 Rs. 30 The quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain receives an additional allowance of Rs.150 per month from the State. 6. I suggest Easey should be offered a contract for one year on consolidated pay of Rs.600 per month plus dearness allowance on this at the rate in force for the post to which he may be appointed, together with free accommodation. If his post is at Bahrain he should .be permitted to draw the allowance at present paid by the State. 7. Request early sanction of terms in order tji&amp;t I may ascertain whether Easey is willing to accept them. ATTESTED 4^ , Sd/- W.R. Hay. Political Resident, Persian Gulf For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf LBEXPRESS LETTER. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, ' pDOT 3.SP ndexed No. 30-93/1. REPGU, Bahrain. CROSEC, London. • Bahrain 5th January, 1948. I consider it desirable to retain the services of Mr. Kassim Ebrahim Motala, Sub Assistant Surgeon at Muscat for at least one year from the 1st April 1948. He is well reported on and it will be especially necessary to retain . him at Muscat if Mathews is transferred to Bahrain to replace Steele. Some particulars of him are given in the enclosure to Residency Express Letter No. 2369-93/1 dated the 6Jbh Nov ember 1947. He is a temporary employee but he has opted for Pakistan and it is desirable to offer him terms before the Pakistan Government apply for his services. 2. Dr. Motala has been drawing fixed pay of Rs. 200 a month since 1943. In addition he has been receiving dollar exchange compensation allowance at varying rates averaging about Rs. 100 a month. I suggest that a pay be fixed for.him which will bring him in Rs. 350 per month net after deduction of income tax. He receives no allowance from the Muscat Government but would presumably do so if he were to act as Quarantine Medical Officer and Medical Officer Muscat Infantry c.f. para 2 of my d.o. letter No. 2222-S dated the 22nd December, 1947. __ 3. The contract should be year in the first place and should allow for one^nonth's leave or pay in lieu and one free second class passage for himself and his family to India on the termination his contract, A ” Early orders request^. = R E P G U =iJOwning street, i^ondoo, ■&lt;(. 1 • 7th January 9 I9if8* / I onclose *erewitii copies of lei;tors from ii^r dated 26 th November and 22nd ^Member on trie subject of t/ie posts of Quartintine . edical Officer at Bahret?»^J.'w«it and 1 ascot* 2. To. rill re, e. iber that toe ^nerai line iu regard to l iedical and qUiirantiftte arrongaaeats in tl*a iiaralan Oulf was discussed at our '..meeting on 15th Jd*” and that tentative conclusions Here reaoiied* oinoe then we iare fixed up the appointment of lieutenant-0olonel ( .J* .oo^r htd.) as ledic&amp;l Adviser to tiie Xolitioal heal dent but hewill not be able to get out to Bahrein before the end of January* The Treoeury (Klliman* s letter of 18th September) iiaare agreed to the retention of the present .iedianl staif in tlie Gulf (i*e* additional t j ti» Medical Ad/iser) intil 31 st l iarch, 1948 on ^ resent tenos* 3. As regards the posts of quarantine he&amp;ujal officers at .oweit, Bahrein and unoat ** it e position is fill rigiit until 3^ fit arch wiien the re arsons ibi— lity of tiiis OiTioe ceases, but atepe will iiave to be taken before that * date for the cotitinued filling of these posts j.f ti»y are to be retained* Je liave referred the papers to General lance and he has occrientea on lar'a letter of 26 th iiover.ibe r as follows:- *1 quite agree with the Political Kesident that the type of officer required is the officer of tic of tlie kind who hr»ve up to now been employed in that area* * * ^ rrj0n in ialaa * U&lt; ^ or AObert Vimpbell, (ex-X.H.D.) • vidi ifn^or P*H*K. Forrest, I.-uIhG* (ex-X.,.. &gt;*) Both hold British qualificationa and both fire likeOy to be available and their reactions are 001 [*8 obtained unofficially witnout ony com.it.icnta. i.eithsr is roung, tneir ages being 30 and 53 respectively but both are officers of oonaideraHe experience wiio would be of great value ta tiia Kesident and Golonel Mjoody. If Dp* jua^ay is willing to transfer fraa hushire to the south side of tiie uulf, of wale r X an doubtful', \vte iuwe asked Hoy to make enquiries /from uJ. Gardener, isq., G.B*il., Foreign ;ffioc.t. VJ ‘ *“ iwj iCT'. Ol from ISase * aa auggeated In paragr&amp;p^i 4&gt; of ilia latter of '?6th lioveiaoerj ’it xiQald ajjpear that on^ one appoint*^ent would be rv?oessary # H On t.j« subject of prv for Quarantine edioal CiYioers (provision of rcjciuneration at tne rate of *6‘\5 and £17 })er annuca in res ect^^f the posts at Bahrein and ;vO\«it rea actively were included in Resir^no/ budget for 1947 /General iiaice noa noted furtiier « follows. 'These miuneratioas rosy iMare been adequate for ne^ioera of ti^ae wtien euming i^riodic inoreiaonta in an eatabliahed aervioo vaiea domiciljd in India but do not strike me as ganarous when proposed for a period of •ontraot senrioe for medical men with iiritiaa qualifications proceeding from .ngicuid.... .In opinion it will be necessary materially to increase the renuneratioas proposed for liahrsin and howsit and 1 would propose that taie scale stolid be £ 1 f 000 - 1 * 050 - 1,100 with generous incorao-tax conoessions. It is tioted that only ^5ths of Colonel Lloody’s inoane is taxable and I would suggest a similar provision for these two conriissioned , officers .wroooeding on contract from kvglana especially in view of tiie fact that no provision for pension or superannuation is eonteoplated** 5# rerhaps you would give these aatters your ooryaideration and let us know v«iat 3te ; &gt;;i you .w&gt;uld like us to take in the Immediate l\xture end what reply v« should seat to H*y. it aeana to im doubtful whether the treasury will be prepared to camit thewselves at this stage to trio retention for anj considerable period of these uar&amp;ntine .edioal Officers at expense and before agreeing will ’want to know what .oody*s recctijeni kit ions are. On tne ot^r hand we cannot let present arrange* asats corae to on end before alteroative arrange^Aonts have been made. 6* ■ e have mentioned the problem to iloody and ho thinks iie might be in a position to /aak® preliminary recoRnendations within a month or so of arriving at Bahrein, but «isy will want to knew if you are content to await his report#DRAiT LETTER Ext. 3006/47 A.J. Gardener, Esq., C.B.E. Foreign Office, London, S.W.1. ; Jfij) -IS48 I enclose aer^with 'Copiep^of letters froia Hsy dated 26 th Lov®ab^»^and 22nd December on the subject of the posts of.^&amp;aranlxine 4aft4^dical Officer at Bahrein, Koweit eind Muscat. 2. You will remember that the general line in regard to medical and quarantine arrangements in the Persian Gulf was discussed at our meeting on 13th July and that tentative conclusions were iAj* . . . reached, ^wnraquant ly we have fixqd/ the appointment (rntfO)^ to &lt;L?.K. of^Colonel ^.J. Moo^'as Medical Adviser/but he will not be able to get out to Bahrein i*»t-4r-l the end . of January. The Treasury (Elliman* s letter of 18th September; have agreed to/ retention of the present ft medical staff in the Gulf (i.e. apart from the Medical Adviser) until 31st March, 1948 on present^ ■ 31st March when aar responsibility ceases but steps will have to be taken before that date for the continued filling of these posts if they are to be retained. We have referred the papers to G-eneral Hance and he has commented on Hay* s letter of 26th November as follows ”1 quite agree with the Political Resident that the type of officer required is the officer of the ex-I.^.D. of the kind who have up to now been employed in that area. I have two men in mind, Major Robert Campbell, M I.A.M.C. (ex-I.M.D.) and Major P.X-P. Forrest, I.A.M.C (ex-I.M.D.) Both hold British qualifications and both are likely to be available and their reactions are , being obtained unofficially without any ccxnmitments. Neither isoyoung, their ages being 5Q f and 53 respectively but both are officers of considerable experience who would be of great value to the Resident and Colonel Moody. If Dr. Rasey is willing to transfer from /Bus hi reI I © Bushire to the south side of the G-ul f.//we have suggested in paragraph 4 of his letter of 26 th at the rate of . ‘615 and £ 5'17 per afvnuni in respect of the posts at Bahrein and .^owei^were included in the Residency budget for 1947 / 4 ^ General Hance has noted further as follows:- » ('These remunerations may have been adequate for members of the I.ThD. vrfien earning periodic increments in an established service when^/in India but do not strike me as generous when proposed for^period of contract service for medical men with British qualifications proceeding from iinwEa. •• • »In my opinion it will be necessary materially to increase the remunerations proposed for Bahrein and K owe it and I would propose that the scale should be £ 1 , 000 - 1050 - 1,100 with November/ it would appear that only one appoint- ment would be necessary.' / On the subject of pay. /generousgenerous income-tax concessions. It is noted that only 2^5ths of Colonel Moody* s income is taxable and I would suggest a similar provision for these two commissioned officers proceeding on contract from England especially in view of the fact that no provision for pension or superar^uation is contemplated. , * jr Perhaps you would give these matters your consideration and let us know what steps you would like us to take in the immediate future and what *// XlH+to £ h**' d' reply we should send to Hay ( TuL rt v Ir rftrW z&lt; i Wx h** fc. e tv*' h'^“~ ^ ! ~tL ' c~ WV. : &lt;rr s.fcw^ ^ (Sgd) E. P. D'ONAUJSCN°/i y&lt; CONFIDENT D.O. No.2222-3 EXT XI 6 f*~ '9rir 3 ii Afc- v?EK5IAN GULF r!ESIDH?:CY . U W V/ BaHP^IK . TT\ the 22nd December, 1947 cV: f. &gt; r\ (V«— jwJt*C\ IM Please refer to my demi-official letter No.2029-S_ v^TjL n dated the 26th November 1947 in which I suggested amongst I dT,h«r things that Mathews'~alTNTresent Nedical Officer Muse other things that Mathews~at~pTesent Medical Officer Muscat should be given a contract for three years. 2 . Mathews* pay is at present as follows: Pay Special Gulf Allowance Compensatory Allowance Total Rs.600 per mensem Rs.100 -do- Rs . 50 -do- 650 In addition he received dollar exchange compensation allowance which is meani to take the place of a dearness allowance and generally speaking varies between Rs.175 and Rs.275 a month according to the Maria Theresa Dollar/Rupee exchange rate. In addition he receives from the Muscat Government a quarantine allowance of Rs.150 p.m. and an allowance as Medical Officer, Muscat Infantry of the same amount. 3. I suggest that he be offered a contract for three years on a basic pay plus foreign service allowance which will bring him in Rs.950 per month net and that he be allowed to draw in addition any allowance paid by the State in which he is employed. He should be allowed 180 days leave during his period of employment and a free return passage for himself and his family to the United Kingdom or India for leave purposes and a free passage for himself and his family to the United Kingdom or India on the termination of his contract. 4. Mathews is an iinglo-Indian but some years ago applied for European domicile and believes that he was accepted as his son on the basis of his application was enlisted into the British &gt;irmy and sent to England. I understand that he will definitely wish to retire in the United Kingdom on the termination of his contract and he has referred me to a notice published in the Indian papers that members of the Anglo-Indian community who can prove European parentage would be permitted to leave India for England, Australia or Africa and granted a free passage. 5. Mathews* record at Muscat has been good and Stewart has strongly recommended his rentention. I have no record confidential or otherwise of his past service and Kance may perhaps if necessary be able to obtain this from India. He is 52 years of age. I think we would be wise to make sure of obtaining 6 . Mathews* services without waiting for Moody*s arrival. It will! be some time in any case before Moody has had an opportunity of forming an opinion about him and we can if necessary insert a clause in Mathews* conditions of service making his service &gt; V clause in Mathews* conditions of service making b r'jb' / terminable by either party on one month’s notice. ^ I y E.P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., t Commonwealth Relations Office, of ^ ‘i' LB Downing Street, LONDON. S.w.lE.P. {N DEXED COUTFIPENTI D*0.No*2029-3. ~Co? 2^ . - N -n i- 7 ' I ' \ * ► I C/oJ The Residency, Bahrain, the 26th November 1947 ^ tfWuX^\ e. ^ 1 a Mi i^-'- ycaai vaair ^lug^ fl I was proposing to leave it to the new Residency Surgeon or Health Officer to take up the question of the con tinuance in service or the replacement of our present Quarantine Medical Officers but as it appears that Moody is not arriving till the end of January vide your telegram No. 14207 dated th e 10th November , I feel compelled to broach the subject myself. 2. The posts of Quarantine Medical Officer are at present filled as follows: Bahrain: Captain M.L.a. Steele (tfio is also acting as Residency Surgeon) Kuwait: Dr. C.E. Hynes« Muscat: Captain A*Cr.T. Mathews. I regret that in my Express Letter No.2369-93/1 d ated the 6th November, Hynes and Mathews have wrongly been designated as 'Agency Surgeons. No such appointment exists in the Gulf. 3. Of the above Steele is long past the age of retirement and definitely wishes to leave the Gulf after 31st March 1948. ^ Hynes wishes to go on 4 months* leave in May 1948 and I recommend, for reasons into which it is not necessary for me to enter here, that if any replacement can be found he should not be «nployed by H.M.G. after that date. Mathews is willing to serve on after the 1st April 1948 and should X recommend be given a contract if possible for three years. 4. It will be seen from the above that we require replacements for Steele at the beginning of April and for Hynes some time in May. Easey, who is at present acting as Vice- Consul, Bushire, is willing to serve on under H.M.G., but might not be ready to serve on this side of the Gulf as he would lose the lucrative practice which he has in Bushire. I do not know it it is the intention of H.M.G. to replace him with a career Vice-Consul but if it is I suggest that he should be asked whether he is willing to serve under H.M.G. as Q.M.O. Bahrain for one year in the first place. 5. I should be grateful if you would let me know whether Hance has any suggestions to make regarding a relief for Hynes, and for Steele if Easey is not available. The species of I.M.D. officer we have eiqployed in the Gulf is I believe almost extinct but perhaps Hance may know of one or two survivors who might be willing to serve. I consider that we should if possible avoid employing Indians other than a good type of Anglo-Indian as they are likely to encounter difficulties in dealing with Masters of ships. Donaldson Esquire, C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office, King Charles Street, Whitehall, S.W.u RHL./5. uedical and Ouar^Jitiac ■.i.rrLaigeliicnto in the Persian G-ulf Notes of a Liceting held in the Indio. Office on 15th July, 19-4-7 Present Mr. E.P, Donaldson (India Office) in the Chair Sir Rupert Hay Hr. A. J. Gardener) Hr. L.P.L. Pyrnan ) Hiss C. Jatcrlow ) Dr. P.G. Stock ) Hiss K.V. Green ) Haj Dr-Gene ral J.B. Hance) Hr. N.A.K. Hcjrrison ) Hr. A. H. Reed ) Political Resident, Persian Gulf Foreign Office Ministry of Health India Office The meeting had before them Dr. Pridic's report on his recent visit to the Persian Gulf, together v/ith noting on inis by Sir A. Hey and the Medical Adviser, India Office. 2. It v/as felt that the matter might most conveniently be considered under heads: (a) H.M.G. *s internetional responsibilities, (b) the provision of medical facilities for H.H.G. ’ s own represent at ives in the Gulf, and (o) the political importance of H.^.G. undertaking medical commitments in the area in excess of their minimum intemational responsibilities. 3. As regards (a) Internat ioncl res-eonsibilit ies . it was explained that these ^rab States (except for Muscat) had no international status, and that their international commitments were devolved upon H.H.G. by treaties and agreements. In addition, under article 90 ^f the International Sanitary Convention of 1926 H.H.G. undertook a. special responsibility for quarantine control in the Persian Gulf, though the precise meaning of this wt iclc wajs far from clear. It was open to H.H.G. to persua.de the various Rulers to assist by the provision of quarantine and other health measures from their own resources, and to arrange fJr the levying of quarantine fees from the shipping and air companies which used the Gulf ports and airfields. Sir R. Hay mentioned that Bahrein and Muscat already paid a contribution towards the cost of British quarantine officers in these States. Among the measures necessary would be the regular provision and dissemination of epidemiological reports. A. Provision of medical facilities for H.ii.G, *s oam representatives in the Gulf . This had hitherto been a responsibility of the Residency Surgeon, and the surgeons attached to the Agency staffs. Sir R. Hay stated that at Bahrein it would bo possible as an alternative for such facilities to be provided by the Bahrein State Hospital on payment of a. contribution by H.H.G., and at Muscat/ by the .jncrican Mission. .^-Bimi-f-’r , li iMtigement- . 1 . 0 ,In M+ rinin rfikf. n, .n,,. Tf m rn i + f 1 ^ n -f;, q n.omp3iQlrf»4.5* Politi ccJ. dQsirr.bility of undcrtoicing extended nodical c3i?j.:itnonts in the Persien Gulf Shciklidxis It v;r,s that it aas generally in accordance with H.-uG.'s policy in this ore a to do v.hat wrs possible to encourage the provision Ox proper nodical facilities for the local inhabit arts, ^t Bclircin the local Government already had a reasonably efficient nodical organisation tnough this at present v;as nainly concerned v/ith curative ro.thcr than preventive measures. It was desirable to encourage other States, such ns Koweit rnd Oo.tor, ■'./hicii had the necessory financio.1 resources, to do likewise. The Trucial States however wore very poor and backward, end it \rcs considered that hero there was o. strong ease for the provision °y H.ii.G. of SDtiQ direct ncdico.l fr.cilities such on the cste.blishnent of o, dispensary. Sinilorly the continued maintenance of the dispensary r.t -iusco.t should, if possible, be arranged. Prom the politicos point of vie'.. r these steps would be likely to have a beneficent effect. 6. It was in the light of the o.bovc considerations, the meeting felt, tho.t the main recommendation of Dr. Pridic‘s report, nowely the c.ppoint ment of o. Health ,..divser to the Politicos. Resident r.t a soJLary of about rG2,500 a year, could best be considered. The recommendation './rn that this appointment should be made additional to the existing staff. Tne Foreign Office pointed out that this would be subject to Treasury approval, -t m :.;:r^e . however that a good cenc could be made out for the appointment of such an officer for a period of 15 months, during which time he would be expected to draw up a report making recommendations for the future medical set-up in the Gulf. ,1 suitable officer for such an appointment might be found from the Indian medical Service, but since that service was being disbanded on 15th ^ugust it would oe desirable to take steps to this end as soon as possible, salary of the range of ,G2,000 - £ 2,500 per annum would in any case be accessary, meanwhile the existing establishment should be maintained, the Indian medical staff being retained on deputation terms subject to tne agreement of the Government of India. It was agreed that a letter to the Treasury should accordingly be drafted by the India Office in consultation v/ith the Foreign Office./U b '^ 7 ^? R eport of Sr«Fridie» Aledical Adviaer to the Briti-h Saat Office on Medical, oanltary and qu arantine cirruiita^opts In the ota.t^o« A* !• present position In addition there la a amall staff consisting of a dispenser, clerks, quarantine guards, etc* at Ba.hreiri* 2 # j.m.D* Officer at Bahrein is responsible i’or informing the p.R* of the work done by all quarantine stations in the Gulf and together with the other 3 M*0«s has the task of carrying out quarantine duties in the area for which H.ftUG. has a special responsibility under Article 90 of the International Sanitary Convention (1926;, Vhese M*0'a also provide normal Medical services for Resideacy and Agency staffs* 3* At present the Medical Staff is below establishnent but even were it increased it would be unable to handle the additional quarantine work caused by the large number of tankers visiting Kuwait and Bahrein* consequently present quarantine arrangements deal almost entirely with passenger ships from India and Basra. There is no inspection of passengers arriving by land or air and the examination of tankers is inadequate. , 4. Recomuendation . The appointment of a capable British Health rixpert (at about £2,500 p.a.) to be 'Chief Quarantine k.O. and Health Adviser to the political Resident'(p* 1 contract^ possibly ex-I. . 0 This officer should spend six months touring the Gulf and then produce a detailed plan of action. Dr.Pridie says that he is unable to make any concrete recommendations other than the above The Medical Officer! of the P.R’s staff are distributed: Bahrein 1 I.M.D. Officer acting as (a) Chief quarantine Officer, P« Gulf (b) Residency Surgeon, Bahrein (c) Agency Surgeon, Bahrein Kuweit 1 M#0* Muscat 1 M* 0* Sharjah 1 M* 0* but he offers the following suggestions.Suggest (a) Abolition of tte artificial distinction between quarantine an prove it ine servioea. (b) ttevelopiaent of tlie various States* xiedical Services which should be made responsible for quarantine control (c) Oil Companies* iiedical Sorvioos to deal with the quarantine of tankers on behalf of the Sheikhdoms concerned. (dJ At present the Quarantine control is dependent on weekly telegrams sent fraa Singapore (whioh should be \ more widely distributed!. But as the problems of quarantine adainistration all deal with the Uiddle East the Gulf Administration should be connected with the Regional Bureau at Alexandria which could send its telegrams and intelligence reports to all Agenqy Surgeons. (e) Article 90 of the International Sanitary Convention of 1926 should be deleted. (f\ An adequate quarantine staff should be provided* (g) Expansion of British Medical Staff:- Bahrein 2 h.Os. auv/ait 1 M.G. iuscat 1 , L.0* iruci.ai Co'^t 1 M.O. Reliefs 2 M.Os. Subsequently, with the development of tho Stages* Medical Services this establisiiaent might be reduced and arrangements mode for the Oil Company* a doctors to treat members of hie Aesihency and Agency staffs. Those M.Os. should be c^u^efully chosen (about 1,7 O p.a. on contract) and should be given good leave accommodation and would assist tiie Sheikiidoms to form their own medical services.(h) l^sx^naarios at Kuwait 5 Bahrain and loiacnt siiould Gnly Be maintained if they can Be run efficiently* Ultimately they could be taken over ty tiie respective State liedical Services But in the meantime a sc^ of drugs, system of indenting a schedule of charges for sale of drugs to ships should Be established* Conditions of storage at Kuwait are Bad. (1) Piped water supply, sanitation and rat killing should Be introduced as precautions against cholera* In Kuwait and Bahrein smallpox and typhus could Be isolated on entry without exceptional precautions nor is it oert&lt;oin that special precautions are necessary any\^iere oxccp»t in ccses of passengers in ships from infected ports. B* BiJire in * 1, T ero are tv^&gt; hosp^it.ls of I K) beds eaoli, one a erican Ilission and one Govermont, Both efficiently run and together with the Agency surgeon's dispensary providing sufficient accommodation for a long time to come* 2* x'reventive health services are deficient and it is essential that till such questions as housing, nutrition, water supply, fly control, qui^rantinc etc* should be dealt with ty the local health authority. 3* Therefore it is recommended that a British Medical Officer of Health and a British Chief i.uBlic Health Inspector should Be appointed at once to organise &amp; health service, .^tcr they will each require on assistant k.O. These two latter officers could \ Be Arabic speaking (? natives} fr aa .th e M*K. if necoss^uy. Tliose preventive services would cost thojl&amp;overaaent less than the hospitals required for the curative services. C. Kuweit . ( 1* There is a prejudice against British doctors and the Chainan of the Health Comittee asked Or. l 5 ridie to^ lielp him recruit 2 male and 2 fe trJLe U.Os frua Syria, Egypt or Palestine. \- if - 2, There is a siaall Aiaerican Itission. Hospital and biie C-ovemoent is building a now 1.'30 bod hosiAtal* dcsi^Tned locally find not ex x x3cted to bo satisfactory. Working conditions for doctors are bad but the only solution is for Kuwait to sot up a It ate Medical Service, which it can afford to do, with • #H* and a British lublio Health Inspector. In the meant hoe doctors should be recruited from Hgypt * fc0 wor ^ in the new hospital. /</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3833</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3833</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/108(2) 'Quarantine Medical Officers at Bahrain, Koweit and Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-01T22:55:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (45 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 47; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the appointment, and terms and conditions of Quarantine Medical Officers at Bahrain, Koweit [Kuwait] and Muscat.The papers include a 'Report of Dr Pridie, Medical Adviser to the British Middle East Office on Medical, Sanitary and Quarantine arrangements in the Gulf States' (folios 42-45); a report by Lieutenant-Colonel William Joseph Moody (Medical Adviser to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) concerning reliefs for the Quarantine Medical Officers at Bahrain and Kuwait (folios 24-25); and a report on quarantine and medical arrangements at Sitra, which advocated the need for a full-time Quarantine Medical Officer there (folios 20-22).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Koweit</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Quarantine</topic></subject><subject><topic>Medical personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000191#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>