<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00013e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T05:22:45.538Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Confidential No. 1 1 C/148 lLU- 1 Q The Political Ageat, Bahrain, Praseats his complitneats to :— The Fonourable the Political Resident in the Persian n rulf, Bushire, ) 3^° iJJxjV-l' r.Q.ir^ ■ and has the hwio ir to aenl him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for information. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated Kaference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject T r ote by the /dviser . !'uh^rra: the night o to the Bahrain Government i disturbances on the 26th January 1^42. - ■w During the first ten days of the month of Muharrcoa tke ohias in Bal-irain who constitute over half of the population hold readings in their Matems every evening. In Mnnamah there are about a dozen large matems capable of holding several hundred men A and smaller matoms exist in every village. A maten is a building which resembles a church hall in an English village. It is partly a religious build ing and is maintained by religious endov/ments but it is used on secular occasions and eating and smoking is pemitted inside it, Separate matems exist for women and for children* The matems are managed by one or more of the leading men of the neighbourhood frequently by members of the man who originally built and endowed the mutom, Each matem has its own patrons who fre quent it in the same way as members frequent a club. There has always been, in Manamah, a certain amount of rivalry between the matems. During the first seven days of Muharram all the Shias congregate in the matems at night listening to the preacher* who usually succeed in stirring their audiences into a state of great excitement and emotion^ On the eighth and ninth nights of Muharram the men from each matem after the reading go out into the town in procession, each matem having its own procession. They carry banners, torches, effigies and many hundreds of them beat their chests, others flog themselves with chains and on the last night they brandish the swords which they use on the tenth in the day time procession wiien they cut their heads open® Tne largest matem is the Persian matem which V. I - 1 k ™r Mm H1 i i # i -2- If which produces the most elaborate procession. Each procession carries out a kind of ,T foilow my leader' visiting all the other matejis in turn. The men enter the mat em and circle round several times and then pour out into the street. This practice seerns to have existed for about 25 years, before then processions ware not allowed by the Khalifah Shaikhs either at night or by day # His Highness Shaikh Hamad, although a Sunni, is very broadminded and averse to interfering in any way with the religious liberty of his people. 15very year h3 lend? 5 some of his horses and camels to take part in the procession. The band of the State Tolice has taken part in the procession for several years. Although many of the incidents and the figures repre sented in the procession must be objectionable to the 8unnis no complaint has been mede on their grounds any many of the leeding ^rebs look on at the proces sions which they regard merely as a spectacle. During the ten days as roany police as are avail able are on duty in the Bahama (Shia) quarter of Manamah where the mateins ore situated. On the last two nights when processions take place and on the 10th during the final day time procession the police accojn- pany and direct the processions and organise them through the heads of the matems, so that no procession comes in contact with the other. This part of the town consists for the most part of narrow streets and lanes which are not lit, some of the matems are close together. In the last 20 years no serious incidents have taken place during the night processions. . ——-3- On tha eightii niglit of Muharram, this month, th© usual proceesions started out Troxa the matems acooiitpanied by the police most or whom wars armed with latnis. A reserve party of police with rifles ware stationed in a lorry on tha adga of the matem neighbourhood. It appears, though there is as yet no definite proof of this, th'it t*ihe hoadmen of ^matem bin Rojab' were on bad terms with one of the leaders of the Persian metern. The police had no knowledge of this at the time# At the time when the disturbance took place the Bin Rejab procepsion was accompanied by Sub- Inspector .Abdulkarim, himself a Shia. Fearing that the Bin Re^ab procession would enter one of the lanes where the Persian procession was still passing Sub Inspector Abdulkarim diverted the head of the procession in another direction. This annoyed the Bahama and they tried to force their way down ^ a narrow alley to the lane where the Persians were marching# A number of them succeeded in doing this, , Abdulkarim and one or two policemen were caught be tween the two processions, who began fighting with each other and were roughly handled. Sub Inspector Abdulkarim fired a shot in the air in order to summon more men. More police arrived and eventually sepa rated the Persians and the Bahama each party retiring to its own matem with the police following them. Persians in the neighbourhood of the Persian mat MS. flung stones, chairs and cooking pots onto the crowd below indiscri minately injuring some of the police and some of the men in the processions. A Persian, by name Kawesh, appears to have incited the Persians by shouting to ll u-4- f? to them that Mahmood bin Abdulnabi had been killed by the Bin Rejab people. During the fighting the torches and lamps were hurled to the ground, oil spilt and caught fire and this added to the general confusion. The whole incident however only lasted a few minutes and when I arrived, at midnight, every- \ thing was quiet but the two metem^ were full of men who had shut themselves in. They were told to go back to their homes quietly which they did. - i About 20 arrests were made and the case is now / being dealt with by the Bahrain Court. Three men are in hospital with broken heads and a number of people are said to have received superficial injuries. Several of the police were injured but none seriously. There are no grounds whatever for supposing that the quarrel was a political one^ between Persians and Bahama. These communities, in Manamah, are on good terms. The headman of the Bin Re jab matem is the ffavher-in—law Ox Mahmooa bin Abdulnabi, one ol the leaders of the Persian matem find many of the members oi the tvvo watems are related tu each other. On the following morning 1 reported the matter to His iiit ^hness tihaikh Hamad and asked his permission to forbid any procuscionc&gt; on tne lasv night ol the ten days 'Leilat Ashur'. liU i^Lghness, wlUi consi- cleriible reluctance, a^eed to my surest ion. The. heads of autems whofce mcLibers usually take part in the proco^. ions weru Juafonaeu thi-t no night processions woul&lt;? be permitted. At the same time they were told that the day time procession on tho morning of the 10th would be allowed provided that the heads of each matem gave personal guarantees that they would obey \ \ I K V 1 \■ -5- iU obey all dlroctions givon to them by the police, that tney vrould bo rosponaiDis if any trouble took plRC&lt;9 and that no weapons would be carried. Three of the Dahama matanc abroad to thaao conditions and appeared on the 10th as usual. The heads of the Pereian matera and the Bin Rejfib mat ems refused the conditions and too^ no part in the procea«ion, proceedir-s ajprajnst 19 persons, T la&gt;irain rubjects, are now proceeding in the Bahrain Coxirt but the case is difficult to deal with as owing to the darloiess and the general confusion it was difficult et the time for the police to recoj^nise the men who were most aggressive. Fevoral people seem to have taken the opportunity to get their own back on others with whom they were or: bad tanas and the evidence is diffi cult to disentangle. Shailchs Mohomed Abdullah and Sulnan have discussed the matter with me anfl they vould like to' persuade His Hl&amp;hnesp to obtain a 'fatwah' from the Shla Ulema in Iraq as to the undesirability of Muharram procos- sions. Amed with this they would forbid all such processions in future. The leading Bahama however are seriously disturbed at the prospect of the Sunni government interfering in what they regard as a reli- gioue rite. It is being suggested that the whole affair was staged in order to give the government an opportunity of curtailing the activities of the Shias, this is of course entirely untrue. . I consider personally that processions at night through the narrow lanes and alleys in tho middle of the town are liable to load to trouble but that the day time procassion under supervision is not liable to *to causu a disturbance. In the day tiiae people who laisbwiiave can bo reco^riiciud but at ni^t tiiici is diTficait and the cover of darloxea^ pro vides a gooa opportunity Tor people who wish to cau^e uiscnief.if/ibo Conl iaentiai &gt; Persian Gulf rtesldency, Bushl ret olst January 1946. M- When I get to Bahrain in February I am anxious to examine the question of Bahrain development and to formulate, with your assistance, some definite plan for future action. The matter really stands at present with the Government of India letter Mo.D*9600-M£/45 dated 22nd August 1945, which was to have been implemented by you on your visit to Bahrain, but which, owing to the absence of Belgrave, could not be effectively handled at the time. 2. The problem seems to me to fall under the following heads and the approach to it to be necessary in the following order viz, (ij Reforms in the existing administration (ii) formulation of a financial policy, (iii) Increased or more efficient staff to strengthen the existing adminis tration, and to enable it to carry out (iv) new schemes. 5. *ith regard to (i) the pre-occupationsof the war years seems largely to have prevented Political Agents from being able to do more than notice the defects with out being able to offer practical suggestions for their remedy. Several have commented on the Adviser's lack of administrative ability, his inability to decentralise any powers and the concentration of all control in his own hands. As early as 1939 confirmation of this came from an unofficial source; Davenport Jones in his letter of resignation (copy forwarded to Bahrain with Residency Printed Letter No.C/667 dated 6th November 1939) complain ed of lack of co-operation from Belgrave 'who by allotting to himself control of public works, funds, staff and other State affairs is able to interfere %t will in ail matters affecting the medical and other State departments.* You are, of course, aware of these general complaints but I shall like to have more details and proposals for remedies. In fact, what (if any) powers regarding (a) finance (b) staff has the Adviser delegated to the Director of Customs, the State Engineer, the Educational Adviser (when present), and the Medical Officer ? Does he fulfil any other direct administrative functions as well as that of Commandant of Police ? Does he sit in Court ? It occurs to me that the thorny question of flelgrave's direct control of the police might once again be broached by suggesting the training of the British policeman in charge for a specified period, it being understood that he took over as Superin tendent at the end of that period — Shaikh Khalifa remain ing nominal head. Again, I have been wondering what arrangements are for the actual prosecution in Court of criminal cases especially against British subjects and Americans. 4. Under Education and Public Health the State should adopt a much less half-hearted policy. On these subjects the Annual Report of the Bahrain Government makes sorry /reading. Lt.Col. A.C. Galloway, O.B.^., Political Agent, B A IIR AIK .reading. A State with nearly a million pounds in the flank is unable to keep teachers and nurses owing to in adequate salaries and is content to accept scholarships from a foreign power! (Pages 26 and 54 of the report j • Perhaps, after consultation with Belgrave and, on the Medical side,.with Drs. Snow and Boeg you will be able to obtain decisions to remedy this state of affairs and to formulate proposals for such future improvements as are practicable and shown by the reports to be necessary. Belgrave, I suppose, justifies his conservative finance in the terms of the phrase in his General Review (page 4 of the report) —•The fortunate financial position of the State was to a ^reat extent due to war conditions'* (the underlining is mine). ^e are presumably meant to infer that the larger Customs receipts are a windfall of the war besides which the Oil Royalty is hardly worth considering. When the latter forms half of the whole revenue (page 6) the inference is, of course, baseless. The Government of India letter I have quoted, though drafted in a somewhat doctrinaire spirit, does in paragraph 5 give valuable advice on the approach to the financial aspect of the case; and I should be glad if you could take up with Belgrave the question of putting it into effect. This brings me to discuss staff and new schemes but it is obvious that until a financial policy is formulated, proposals must be, in some cases, tentative. 6. In the first place is the State capable even of administering its finance ? I see that Pelly mentioned the matter of accounts to Belgrave and was told that all was well (the enclosure to his demi-official letter No. P.0 dated 19th August 1945 to you). I shall be glad to know whether you agree with Belgrave or whether you think that an Accounts Officer for the State is necessary. If the need is there I do not think it can be met by audit ing by an outside firm as, I understand, is occasionally undertaken. And an outside firm cannot formulate and supervise the execution of a financial policy. Ho further examination of Bahrain finances is, however, needed to enable us to decide that an efficient electric and pumped water supply, and better roads and streets are items on which expenditure is now justified. The present Bahrain engineering staff is inadequate for the execution and maintenance of these projects and I suggest that what Is required is an engineer, of the class and status of a Superintending Engineer in India, with full control of all public works and buildings, and adeouate staff, some of whom would probably be European, and powers. I should be glad of your views. The book value of the existing buildings would be relevant. / I should- 3 - I should also lik« to know whether any progress has been made in obtaining an h^ucational AdTiser, and also in the codification of the decrees and regulations which I first suggested nearly fifteen years ago# ?• Lastly — to consider new projects. Your memorandum No.C/1152 dated 29th December 194b states that three generating sets in the present power house are obsolescent* * It seems to me that we should press for the removal of the power house to a new centrally situated site to be fitted with new generators* #hen is the punned water supply system likely to be installed ? If the Adviser does not now do so he should at least be able to get and give you estimates for the completion of such schemes* Has the Bahrain Government any plans for repair ing the roads and streets ? It seems to me to be continually relying on the Oil Company to lend it machinery t such as graders, for this work; and to be time that the Government thought of buying some for itself* It also seems that a town plan is for Manama — and a real effort to carry it cutting off of a few comers here and there of complete haphazardness in this respect* badly needed out* The is evidence Something might ad so be done to encourage the building of cement houses when cement again becomes cheap* also be The possibilities considered* of a brlquettlng plant might I hope you will be able to give attention to these matters before I reach Bahrain so that we can make some progress when I do get there* 'C JKGu Will you please refer to the correspondence resting with Hickinbo tham 1 s telegram No .30 of the 10th January, 1945, regarding the Manamah Municipality Bye-laws ? 0 2. I am not certain that the Municipal Regulations forwarded under this Agency Printed Letter No.G/947 ol 20th June, 1944, are compiled in the best form and should be grateful if a copy of some good Municipal Regulations could be obtained from the Government of India to serve as a model for the redrafting of ours here. 3. One fresh problem that is about to face the Bahrain Government is that of Town Planning and, to my way of thinking, some system of control of building is essential now that the day is not far off when building materials will be available once more. 4. An exan?)le which emphasises the point is the proposal regarding a piece of land owned by the R.A.^. in Ghudhaibiya between the British Overseas Airways Corporation Transit Camp and the Assistant Political Agents house concerning which the R.A.F, are, 1 under stand unofficially, proposing (or may, indeed, have already done so) to sub-let to the A. I.O.C. for the construction of Indian Staff quarters. 5. As you know, Ghudhaibiya is predominantly the residential quarter of the Al Khalifa family and, being comparatively speaking unbuilt over, could with some thought be preserved from the evils of unplanned construe tion. 6. I propose sounding His Highness in the near future on the question of tae introduction of a Town Planning Scheme and, with the example I have Just quoted before him, I feel certain he will welcome the proposal. At the same time I should like advice as to the best method to incorporate rules regarding Town Planning under the present regulations in force. Ity idea was that they could best be included with the Bye-laws of the Municipalities, and if you agree I propose to ask the Bahrain Government (presuming that His Hi^aness agrees to the suggestion) to draw up the rules which I would submit to you for approval in accordance with King^ Regulation No.2 of 1936. - Political - The issue of the aoove has been authorised. Sd • R.iii.R. Bird Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.Will you please refer to your Demi-official letter No.l69-S of the 31st January, 1946, on the subject of development in Bahrain and improvement in the general administration? I am answering the various points as far as I am able to now so that you will be able to consider some oi them on your arrival in Bahrain on tour. 2. I thinK there is one point which should not be lost sight of, and that is the very close atten tion the Shaikh himself gives to the administration and expenditure of funds. He is, I know, anxious that his State should be efficiently ruled and indeed he tells me with pride that his State is the best governed in the Gulf. That, however, will not preclude his accepting sound advice for further improvement. 3. The most convenient method of replying to the points you raise is to deal with them separately oy departments. They are: (a) Public Health, (b) Engineering, (c) Education, (d) Customs, (e) Judicial, (f) Police, and (g) Finance. « 4. As regards (a) Health; This department already absorbs roughly one-tenth of the annual expenditure and is on the same level as Education but falls a long way behind the allotment to the Ruling Family and only half of what is inaccurately termed 'Defence and Pro tection'. Prima facie the people of Bahrain are entitled to a larger proportion than this, and I agree with you that increased salaries must be paid if neces sary to keep the local dispensaries open and to push ahead with health improvements. 5. The State has made great strides in anti-malarial work, and at the present time the State authorities are conferring with the Bahrain Petroleum Company in initiating a drive in an endeavour to stamp it out. Exactly what this will emsail I cannot yet say. 6. On the subject of staff, Belgrave informs me that, certainly so far as British medical staff is concerned. /it is The Hobble Sir Geoffrey prior, K.C .I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Lf -ft, shiPeV v ) ' 7* A/i/.** -rr''Ivi 1,1 -2- ^reply it is lack of actual trained people willing to come to Bahrain which is the trouble, rather than a low- ness in the scales of pay. He has succeeded in engaging a new matron. Incidentally the provision of an air-cooled operating theatre for the Manamah Hospital is under consideration. 7. i think that the expenditure on Health should be stepped up with particular attention to the urgent needs of the poorer people and the best course .would be to ask Snow for his views. I have already made the suggestion to Belgrave, and doubt less he will aLxic/in due course. The provision of the necessary funds will come under paragraphs on financial review. 8. Engineering: This department seems to have gone through the blackest period and to be on the up grade. As regards staff: Th^ Department as a whole is under the control of Leigh whose powers in major works and finance are centralized through Belgrave to the Sheikh and the Agency. 9. i do not think that there is anything calling for remedy in this except the actual control of the State Engineer's budget. At the present time all ex penditure is controlled by Belgrave. This seems to me to be a needless call on his time and a source of both annoyance and delay in the Engineering Department. Belgrave tells me that he is willing to delegate the control of the expenditure under the Engineering budget to the State Engineer in the same way as he has done with the Health Budget. That is to say that the State Engineer will be authorized to control the funds provided up to the limit of his budget allotment by drawing upon an account in the Eastern Bank. ^ x 6* s , leflxn 10. ' As regards engineering personnel, an Assistant 9 Engineer has been engaged by Belgrave, vide my Demi- TyA*- • Official letter No.C/258, dated the 6th of March, 1946. It is to be hoped that he will fill the bill but as he was engaged without our knowledge and has been on his way out for some weeks nothing can be done now but to wait and see how he turns out. He will come under the superintendence of the State Engineer and his main duties will be Public Works and Roads. Furthermore the ser vices of an oil-gauger are being acquired, see my Demi- official letter ^o.c/196 dated the 19th of February, 1946, and if this person is eventually engaged he will be available for the water supply side of the Islands' ' engineering problems. Two more Indian electricians are being engaged to strengthen the power-House staff to the required standard. 11. As regards equipment, generators, power plants, etc.: To replace the old generators which are worn out and which can only be considered as a very inadequate reserve, the State have the new plant No.4 - vide para graphs 2(b) and 2(c) of my memorandum No .c /1152 dated the /29th29th December, 1945. All the component parts have now been received and the set should be in operation fairly soon. A further generating set has been offered in England and has been accepted. This may be expected by the end of the year. Also there is a fair chance of acquiring two further new generating sets - vide Bushire telegram No.348 dated the 25th February, 1946. . 5. S'S There is talk that the Royal Air Force are considering closing down to a maintenance basis and may consider offering the State the present Muharraq generating sets. All this is as good as we can hope for at the moment. 12. As regards.road making material. One scarifier, or grader, together with a supply of spares and an oil sprinkler and the necessary equipment to go with it will be ordered as soon as the specifica tion has been received from London. This is daily ^ expected. One grader should meet the State's present ♦ needs, and I feel that at this stage we cannot ask them to purchase another. 13. As regards the present state of road repairs. A great deal is being done to tidy up the roads and oiling is going ahead as fast as transport permits. ^ The bottle-neck is that the Baladiyehs have only three ' lorries between them of 8 oil-barrel capacity and there is a lift of 30 miles. This naturally slows down progress, especially as the lorries are required for other work as well. 14. As regards transport, the State has placed an order through the East Anglian Engineering Company, Limited - see my Express Letter No.c/145 dated the 9th February, 1946 - \ MO CNt* C-* r) 6 number saloon cars 6 Station Wagons 6 Pick-ups 6 Lorries This is satisfactory. There is also on order a number of lathes, drills, saws and other equipment for the establishment of an efficient work-shop. This is satisfactory. 15. As regards the water supply, the plant is firmly on order and Messrs. Holloway's representative is expected in Bahrain very soon to draw up final details. There is doubt as to what type of piping should be used, until the submission of his report nothing further can be done. 16. As regards the removal of the Power-House to a more central position (your paragraph 7), I agree ohat irom certain aspects it would be desirable but I believe there are certain technical difficulties. These are noL insurmountable, but would cost a considerable /sumII -4- sum to overcome. I have asked Belgrave if he can let me have an estimate and after its receipt the desirability of removal to a new site can be balanced with the financial outlay, and the question finally settled. l) 0 Vw ^ 17, As regards Education. There are two points for consideration, one of which is the provision of a Director of Education in which connection please see my telegram No.52 dated the 7th February, 1946. Since its despatch the picture has altered in that the man the Bahrain Government had in mind is no longer available. The question now, therefore, is one of principle whether the Bahrain Government is to continue to depend on the British Council for a Director or whether the Director should be a State employee. You will see from the enclosure to India Office Express Letter No. Ext.1043/46 dated the 14th February, 1946, that the British council are suggesting that the ^ Bahrain Government should employ an Englishman as Head-master in the secondary school. The case might be resolved by the British council's finding the Head master and the Bahrain Government the Director both of whose services could be made available to Kuwait for necessary periods. 18. A further point for discussion is that the Sheikh is very doubtful if he is receiving any good return for the expenditure on education in Egypt. He is not at all sure that the boys do not absorb ideas of a trend which may be harmful to the State. He is toying with the possibility of sending them to Beirut to the American University. That would not be desirable; neither is it really practicable to send them to the Sudan. Each boy costs the State Rs.5,000 a year, and I wonder if it would not be a more paying proposition to reduce the number of students sent abroad, spend more on each individual and send them to England. 19. As regards technical education, the situation is that the school is now being run under the super vision of a local teacher. This is not satisfactory and consequently I have approached the Bahrain Petro leum Company. That Company inform me that a certain sum of dollars, 50,000 I believe is the figure, has been allotted for technical education, supply of machinery, necessary tools, etc., and that the proposal was to train youths in BAPCO shops utilizing the part time services of the company's skilled employees. I, therefore, proposed to the General Management that they should combine their scheme with the Bahrain Technical School and run th,e latter for the Bahrain Government. Ward Anderson favoured the idea and details of the scheme on the above lines will be worked out here and sent to the New York Board of Directors for comments. ■ The Bahrain Government is in favour of the proposal in * general, and I shall keep you informed of developments. 20. As regards Customs. .Expenditure in this Department is controlled by the Adviser in the same way as in the Engineer's Office. Belgrave is agreeable. /however-5- however, to making similar administrative adjustments outlined in paragraph 9. 21. As regards the judicial Department and your query in paragraph 6. Belgrave tells me that con siderable progress has been made in codifying the diving and water rights and the laws and regulations governing land ownership♦ Quite to what extent the progress goes I am unable to say at present but will get some further details in due course. 22. Belgrave himself actually attends, on the Sheikh's invitation, the senior Bahrein Court on the bench of which he sits weekly with two other magis trates. He also listens to appeals from other Courts in company with Shaikh Abdullah. This work takes up most of his Monday mornings and while I think it would be more correct for the Adviser not to take an active part in the Courts, the Island is so small and the Khalifah family's tentlcles so deeply spread that his guiding influence is of benefit to the State judi cial system. I would not recommend a change. 23. The last sentence of your paragraph 3 might conveniently be answered here. The British police Detachment now investigate and prosecute cases in which Britons and Americans are concerned. This is a new departure and is satisfactory. 24. as regards the police, this is indeed a thorny question and one which needs attention. You will see in the Annual Report that 8 lakhs a year are spent. By no stretch of imaginacion can it be thought that the State gets full value for that money. 26. . I think revision is required at the very root of the Force, and that the needs of Bahrain in this respect should be very briefly reviewed. 26. The Police problem of Bahrain is very rapidly changing. This is due to the increasing number of European residents, and also to the large number of American visitors the Island receives from the mainland. They come over in large numbers from Dhahran and Ras T^nura .and when here occasionally get into trouble. They cannot be dealt with by the Bahrain native policemen. Another cause is that the native police cannot effectively handle the crews of ships which now tie up at Sitra pier. At present the crews of ships are told that they cannot land at Sitra, but unfortunately the crews are not always inclined to obey. Come ashore they do, and as many of the men are toughs from the U.S.A., Sweden and Greece and Heaven knows what other country, axfii the Bahrain policeman is incompetent to deal with them when they become obstreperous. I do not wish to represent that the problem is serious at present but the presence of Sitra Pier does add to the policing difficulties. 27. I have spoken to Belgrave about increased use of the British police Detachment and he told me .that he was re-organizing the distribution of duties. He has not yet let me know what his proposals are. /28. I also-6- 28. I also spoke to him about his giving up the Commandant-ship to which he replied that he would rather not do that. For one reason he thought that if he did, Sheikh Khalifah would resign, it would be a pity if he were to resign since he works quite hard, but it is no good Belgrave's holding a pistol at our heads. Not only does Belgrave not wish to give up the work but I think the shaikh also would be disturbed if.a new officer were put in charge of his guards, and Belgrave would, of course, lose a very great deal of face. This would not be to our advantage, and I do not think that the resulting efficiency in the police Force would compensate the above two considerations. But that something has to be done to re-organize the force is clear and i think the best course is to push Belgrave into really putting his mind to the problem. I have already set the ball rolling, vide paragraph 27 above. If he fails then the question of a new Commandant can be taken up in full detail. S 1+1 29. As regards finance. On the g^n^rfal question- I am awaiting Belgrave's reply to joy^ietter based on Government of India letter No.D.9680-ME/45 dated the 9 22nd August, 1945. In the meantime you ask me my • opinion as to whether the State is capable of adminis tering its own finances. On the general question I think the answer is in the affirmative. The Sheikh takes very close interest in all financial matters and thinks very carefully before authorising new expenditure. Belgrave also is very conservative as you know, and I think he can be relied upon to move cautiously. This, combined with our control which counter-balances the general conservativeness of the State side, should, I think, be sufficient on main issues- Against this, however, I am quite in the dark as to the actual state of the State's finances and I do not think that Belgrave can be fully conver sant with the details of the various departments. I am not at all satisfied that the Budget as published gives us a true picture. I think it is absolutely essential that the State's accounts should be submitted . for audit annually. If that is done we should know actually where we are. This, in my opinion, is a necessary safeguard on our as well as the State's side. With your approval I should like to make the proposal to the Sheikh. 30. With regard to the Town Planning Belgrave tells me that there is a plan and he has promised to send it to me, or a copy. I have not received it as yet. When it does come it will be interesting to see if the proposal for the building of new Government offices on the site where the post office is situated and the removal of the Customs shed in the main bazaar street, about which I have asked Belgrave for more details, is included in the plan. The removal of the Customs shed to make way for new Government offices is a typical example of the piece-meal method of expenditure, it would, of course, be nice to have a new building at the port gate, but against chat it would cost, I suppose, many lakhs of /rupees&gt;1 ^ -7- rupees and it is surely a question as to whether the State of Bahrain will benefit materially by the expenditure or whether, for instance, it would not be better to put the money into some more use ful public service - say an hotel. 31. As regards a Briquecting plant, I have gone into the details with the Bahrain Petroleum Company to the extent of their knowledge. The relevant points seem to be that they have sold the coke dump, with the exception of a reserve for local needs, to a carbon company in the united States. The coke is only suitable for domestic fuel and possibly boiler-firing. This is due to its high sulphur content which amounts to 6 per cent and makes it unsuitable for blacksmiths' work, it is difficult to move in the raw owing to its brittle nature and a bag of coke not made into briquettes would arrive at - say Shiraz - pulverised. Another point for considera tion is that for converting the coke into briquettes a binding material of either asphalt or tar must be used. Neither of these articles is at present available in Bahrain, and they would have to be imported now, though an asphalt plant is to be built in Bahrain in the near future. It will probably be ready in about one year's time. As to the plant itself, a briquetting plant requires special power, pulverisers, magnets, mixing with the binding material at high degrees of temperature produced by steam under pressure. Then, of course, there is the'actual press. No one seems to be able to estimate the cost, but it would be high and to warrant this expenditure a steady market is essential, it is clearly not present in the Gulf, 32. Efforts were made by the Bahrain Petroleum Company to rectify the brittle quality of the coke. Success was achieved with coke straight from the retorts but they could not succeed with coke from the dump. 33. It may possibly be practicable to use some form of small hand-press but even for that it would be necessary to import binding material. The project does not seem practicable at the present time. NS.1^ ^-en / HOTS ON DISCU3. : iI0ii3 TH kR. BEIflRAVK AT BAHRAIN OB 16TK MARCH 1946. I began by pointing out that the actuals for 1362, 1363 and 1364 bore little connection with tne facts and showed that the budget was almost worthless as an accurate guide to the financial events in the State. -es The surplus/o wing to under expenditure and under-estimated revenue were over 7 lakhs in 1362, over 19 lakhs in 1363 and although the actuals of expenditure were not given for 1364 it is clear that there must have been a saving of over 13 lakhs owing to the greatly enhanced rsvenue received. i&gt;.-r* Belgrave said that this was due to the excess receipts of customs revalue and stated that it was difficult to estimate this accurately in advance* I inquired why he had estimated for a drop in 1364 when it was quite obvious that the war would be going on for some time and that there was little chance of a drop in prices. I could not follow Mr. Belgrave^ reply to this, I pointed out that the original plan oi saving 14 - 15 lakhs a year was now obsolete as the life of the oilfield was obviously secure for some time to come since the Oil Company were spending a great deal of money in installing fresh plant. I added that so far as I was aware, the life of the field was estimated at between, at the minimum, another 15 years, and possibly as much as 50 years. Mr. Belgrave did not appear to be aware of this. I drew his attention to the fact that the remark in his report two years ago that people were dying of starvation in villages read oddly when one reflected that the State had at that time over half a million pounds in the bank. Mr. -^elgrave said that this was really due to the fact that these people were upset by the change of diet necessitated by the cessation of rice supplies. I drew his attention to the fact that tne word he had used f was 'starvation'. Mr. Belferave volunteered the statement / that^ L i - 2 - that when the capital sunk in food supplies was realised the actual 'balance of the State would be over a million pounds. I said that this gave point to my view that some capital expenditure in the State was justified and added that I felt certain he would have to face rising opposition from the public if nothing was done in the very pear f uture. 2. HEALTH . I drew Mr. Belgrave's attention to the remark in his report that the staff had besn leaving for India owing to inadequate pay • Mr. Belgrave agreed that the State as could ad. well afford to pay/good wages as the Government of India&gt; and said that the position was now quite satis factory as the staff were contented with their present terms. I inquired the State Medical Officer 's financial powers, and Mr. ^elgrave said that he was allowed to spend any amounts in his budget. Mr. Belgrave mentioned that there was a 9-bed hospital for women in Muharraq with a Lady Doctor which was always full, and added that there was a men f s out-patient hospital there as well. iie agreed that Dr. onow should be asked for his views as to future medical policy in the State. 3. mGiumnim . I inquired the State Engineer's financial powers and degree, jf control over the other engineers and the Oil Gauger. The Adviser said that the State Engineer could spend any sum in his budget, but I was not very clear regarding the degree of his control over the other engineers and the proposed Oil Gauger. Mr. Belgrave seemed to take the view that the Oil Gauger^ appointment would be completely separate, but I pointed out that it was essentially an engineering job and that in the past the State had had to use the State .Engineer for this duty, and that they would almost certainly have to do so again. /1- 3 - I gave it as my view that what the State required was an able and hi^ily qualified engineer who wouid control all the engineering works in the State as Chief Engineer. I remarked on the difficulty that was always experienced in comhindng electrical atfid mechanical work with building and roads, but said that a single engineering department was obviously desirable. I was not very clear what the qualifications of the new engineer were but understood Mr. ^elgrave to say that his work would be more on the lines of roads and buildings. I drew attention to the fact that he had been engaged without reference to us, a point which is being dealt with later on in this note. I suggested that some standardisation of the electrical plant might be possible so that spares would be inter changeable, and ^r. Belgrave described the existing plant and said that the point -would be borne in mind in the future. I mentioned that the condition of the roads was disgraceful and that so wealthy a State could and should improve them. Mr. Belgrave agreed with this and said that he hoped something would now be done. He men tioned that new motor vehicles had been ordered and said that they were awaiting the arrival of the consulting engineers to conclude the water supply agreement. I drew i his attention to the agreement with their supply agents in Ulngland, which I observed had been concluded without reference to us, and drew attention to the serious defects in it. 4. EDUCATION . I pointed out the advantages of getting a man from the British Council to run education in Bahrain and said I would make a final attempt to get one from them. If this failed then the Bahrain Government would have to make their own arrangements. In any case there was little / objectobject in anyone coming out now as the school term had. not much longer to run. The disadvantage of a large number of boys being educated in ilgypt was discussed and this point is still under consideration. I said that it was essential that the technical school must be run by BA^GC and urged that an early opportunity be taicen to include this obligation in the Concession. Colonel Galloway said tnat this matter was before the Directors of the Company and it was agreed that they should be pressed to undertake this function. 5. CUSTOM 3 . I inquired the financial powers of the Director and Mr. Belgrave explained that he was empowered to spend any sums included in his budget. I inquired whether there was any plan of reorganisation of the pier or the possibility of having a bonded warehouse. Mr. Belgrave replied that there was a proposal to fill in the dock between the existing pier and the Kanoo Building but said that the question of having bonded warehouse had not been considered. I drew attention to the fact that Ras Tanura was now being put on the slow mail run and said that I feared this would divert a good deal of trade from Bahrain which could probatoly be retained if a bonded warehouse system was introduced as merchants would then be able to make this a centre for the whole Gulf and have a much wider scope open to them. Mr. Belgrave inquired whether they would not be wiser to take the money while they could get it. I pointed out that the State did not require the money and that the time to prevent Ras Tanura developing was now as once trade links were forged they were very persistent. It was agreed that the position would be investigated. 6. JUDICI a'L . , I inquired from Mr. Belgrave what progress he was making in codifying the regulations and publi&amp;ing thereof, a task I suggested should be undertaken 15 years / ago7U 7/ - 5 - ago when I was Political Agent, Bail rain. He replied that the work was proceeding but that its conclusion was problem atic. He is considering the appointment of Shaikh Salman bin Hsonad bin Isa to devil f or him, a duty which will give him an opportunity to discover how much legal knowledge this young Shaikh has acquired in Palestine. Mr. Belgrave confirmed that there was no compilation of State laws and rules in existence, and that the Sudan Penal Code, though relied on, had not been formally introduced. Apparently .lis ilighness did not care about having the courts bound by set rules for punishments. The Sudan Civil Code is not apparently in force. 7 • ^-OUCii; . I began by sayitig that the police in Bahrain were costly and inefficient and drew attention to some highly discreditable instances that had occurred recently namely the theft of ammunition from Jidda Island where it transpired that nearly half a million rounds had not been properly handed over and were in charge of a Lance-Naik. Mr. Belgrave could give no adequate explanation of this, or indeed ol the fact that an important prisoner in this case had been allowed to escape by the police and I stated frankly that i thought the whole matter was highly discreditable and reflected seriously upon him. I inquired the functions ox the new British lolice officers. These are apparently making themselves useful and it is intended that they should prosecute cases in court in which Europeans and Americans are concerned. They are mounted on motor bicycles, kr. Belgrave said that they were popular with His Highness, which is very fortunate. I inquired the suitability of having an Iraqi officer in the Police and 1 r. Belgrave replied that he was an excellent man and most useful. I expressed surprise that in 15 years it had not been found possible to train up a team of highly reliable local men. / I vIr - /^//76 . ( v: 6 9 /' J*.** i n/i . - 6 - I inquired Mr. Belgrave's plans for tae future and under stood that tie is reviewing the whole matter of the police force and will let us have his conclusions shortly. 3. gitutiga . I observed that 11 r. Belgrave was approaching the end of his term in Baarain, and that it was essential tuat there should 'be someone who should 'be fully equipped to ta^e over from him. I inquired -whether he ' klbx did not consider there was a case for reverting to the old position whereby there were three executive officers in the otate and having an Assistant Adviser now, Kr. Belgrave con sidered that there was a good case for such an appointment. I inquired about the auditing of the State accounts. This is still conducted by a firm domiciled in Basra ;^io have enough work in the Island to keep their personnel here for some five months in the year. They are able to audit accounts in Arabic and Mr. Belgrave expressed himself thoroughly satisfied.with their efforts. I asked Mr. Belgrave to be good enough to arrange for his budgeting in future to have a closer connection with realities, and understood that he hoped to do this. 9. TOW11 ^AMIKG. Apparently little has been done in the way of toWn planning beyond a proposal to turn the present import yard into a bazaar when the customs sheds are moved out to the dock that is to'be filled in. I drew attention to the extremely unsightly and completely unorganised rabbit warren of a bazaar and stated that what was wanted was a defimite plan for the centre of the town by which proper roads would be introduced so that decent shops could be erected. Mr. Belgrave said tnat the land was in various ownerships but I replied that there was no reason why a plan should not be worked out and the various obstacles overcone. mr. -beigrave undertook to consider this. 10. jiKCEURAGi&amp;a^T OP I NDUSTRY. i said that, to my regret, i had been unable to — i i HI3^ - 7 - to find any industry that could bejef f ect ively encouraged In Bahrain with the possiole exception of a briquet ting plant which apparently involved difficulties, it appears that the coke xs. has a high sulphur content which makes it unsuitable for blacksmithing, but if the coke could 'be briquet ted and exported to Persia it would be a very valuable counter in producing supplies in return, so the matter is not samply one for the Oil Company but one in #iich Bahrain generally has a vital stake. The great drawback in locating any industries in 'iahrain is the high cost of laoour as compared witn mdia, and the fact that they would not 'be sheltered behind a high tariff wall as in Persia. 11. i inquired what progress had been made in agri culture and Mr. Belgrave said that it was proposed to engage an Egyptian who was shortly leaving the Saudi Arabian service. i pointed out the drawbacks of engaging men in this haphazard way and said it would be much better for Mr# Belgrave, if he wanted Egyptian agriculturists, to fly to Cairo and go into the matter there where a much larger selection would be available for him. 12. i drew Mr. -celgrave's attention to recent instances of the engagement of European personnel without reference to us and reminded him that he had been warned about this on earlier occasions. He replied that the case had been discussed with the mdia Office and that he imagined that this had been sufficient. i said that the matter would be taken up with the mdia office who would be asked to see in future that such action was not taken without reference to us and reminded him again of the position for his guidance in the future«» 13. 'IKE BRIDGE . I inquired whether the swing bridge had paid for its cost or not. Mr. -oelgrave replied that it had not yet paid for its initial cost but that this position would shortly be reached. The intention then was to / maJtemake the bridge free of all tolls, which i said I was glad to hear. 25th j^arch 1946. RK.L. ry OS c #ifjn^ J GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN From No. of 1365 Pt- rtt. &lt;V 2 7^ Office of the Adviser to fikr- the OovernxiiGnt, Bahrain —. Dated, 3rd R/Thanl, 1365 March 7, 1946. C« Dalrymple Belgrave, iisquire, C.B .S., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf, His Britannio Majesty's Political Bahrain. ent. To Sir, I have the honour to enclose herewith four copies of the State Budget for 1365 which has now been approved by His Highness. Owing to my absence in Sngland the budget was late in being prepared. RimMUJS. The actual revenue last year was 64 lakhs; in the budget for 1365 I have anticipated a revenue of Rb. 55,45,000. Last year the oil royalty amounted to 30^ lakhs and customs revenue amounted to 24-^ lakhs. In the new budget I have assumed that the output of oil will be the same as in 1364 and that the customs will produce 20 lakhs. The lesser sources of revenue appear to require little explanation. The interest from the Reserve Fund is shown at about half what it should normally produce, the reason is that only one half-year's dividend will be received during 1365, the dividend for the second half of 1946 is not due until a few days after the end of the Arabic year 1365. 2/— r rMadloul raoeipta are 193a owing to the closing of tb8 aarvloo warda In the Goverumant Hospital, the large ward la now uaed for Suropaan civilian patients. Court faaa and finaa are decraaaing because there la iaaa amuggling and fewer caaas under tna price control regulations, thia la due to mora plentiful auppliea of ^ooda entering Bahrain and the haighbouring States. Bridge tolls are expected to fall with the reduction in the number of military vehiclaa. SXPBMDITUHa . The aurplua of revenue over expenditure la eatimated at 10 lalcha. Apart from the Blectric acheme, which la ahown separately, almost the whole of thia expenditure la recurrent expenditure upon the Civil Llat, Administ ration and Public Service a. A aum of 2 and l/3rd lalcha has been allowed for new public worka and two latha has beon allocated to new tranaport. The Civil Liat ramaina stationary, as it has for many yoars, the proportion of the oil royalty which is paid to the Ruler is 10 lalcha. a conaidarable portion of this sum la expanded by Hia Hlghneaa in paying coat of living allowances and additional allowancea to the numerous Khalifah relatione who depend entirely upon him for support. Thu expenditura on State Departments is higher than laat year as the allotment Cor' the cuatoma includea provlaion for the purchaae of new tarpaullna covering cargo on the pier. Judicial Dapartmanta ahow a small increase due to the appointment of a third shia Kadi and additional staff, 3/- 3 - JJduoation has risen from 4^ lakhs to lakhs. The sum of 1 lakh has been ai Located for the cost of the Bahrain boys who are studying in Cairo and provision has been made for some expansion in the existing schools. Expenditure on public health has increased from 4^ lakhs to 5 lakhs. Public Protection now costs the State almost 8 lakhs of which half a lakh is the estimated cost of the new British Police. The Special Police were disbanded but a number of them were enlisted in the State Police which is now over strength. During the year a certain pro portion of the Police will come to the end of the period for which they enlisted and it was therefore desirable to take on men from the Special Police some of whom will take the place of retiring State Police. No provision has been made for the Manama town water supply scheme. The tender for this work has not yet been received and it is improbable that payment would be made during 1365 though it is hoped that the work will commence during the second half of the year. The Government is endeavouring to obtain a quantity of building materials and P.W .D. requirements from England, in some cases the dates of delivery and the prices are not known but I lakh out of the E and l/3rd lakhs allocated under P.W.D. new works and stores are intended to cover the payment for the goods which arrive during the current year. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Crovernment. I v- iSncl,... \/f IIq \ 1 D«0. No.C/564. 3U The 30th of May, 1946^ ^(ni please refer to the extract from thel.New Yorker sent me under Residency printed Letter No .c/59 dated the 12th May, 1946. 2. I sent Belgrave a copy of this extract and enclose a copy of his reply together with a note from Smith on the application of the 'free port' system to Bahrain. 3. Belgrave has asked whether it would be possible for us to obtain details of the working of the bonded system at Aden, and I should be grateful if this could be done. 4. I am suggesting that the Bahrain Government should introduce the extended transit period forthwith. It is a pity that the Shaikh does not accept the Customs Director's advice and should pare the change down to an ^added 20 days, but I do not propose to press the point ^at this stage. / _xe Hon'ble Lt-Col. W .R. Hay, C .S .I., C.I.E., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, (Camp) Bahrain.Copy of Demi-official letter No.1124-3 dated the 25th I'ay, 1946, from C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. With reference to your D.O. No .c /495 dated 14th May, 1946, I understand from His Highness that Sir Geoffrey prior discussed this matter with him during his last visit here. 2. I enclose a note on the subject from Smith which ^have shown to His Highness. His Highness is willing to consider making some changes in the present arrangement but he is not in favour of intro ducing the Bond system now. He would be prepared to begin by increasing the period in which RE cargo can be transhipped from 20 days to 40 days, later he would be willing to extend this period and to reduce the duty on Transit cargo. Lt-Col. A.C. Galloway, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. I believe that Aden is a free port and more similar to Bahrain than any of the ports mentioned in the article which you enclosed, would it be possible for you to obtain for us any report or regulations from Aden which would explain in some detail how the system is worked? such information would be of much interest and would enable us to consider the matter more fully. a A*1 D.O. No.9. The Custom House, Bahrain. 21st May, 1946. Reference attached, to which T have j^ven careful considera tion, I am of the oninion that it would not be advantageous to the Government to attempt institute a Free port System here at Bahrain. Firstly I do not think the quantity of goods imported under this system would ever reach sufficient volume, to warrant the ore- going of Transit duty on this type of cargo. Secondly it would be necessary to erect a number of large new warehouses for this purpose. It is undoubtedly my wish, and I think yours too, to endeavour devise suitable means of encouraging and inducing trade to Bahrain, to the best possible advantage of all concerned, I of course am primarily concerned in the upkeep of Customs revenues, but fully realise the importance of making concessions to traders to encourage them increase their business and to centre same here. I have, as you are already aware, been considering the possibilities of introducing a 'Bond' system, but in the absence of stamp duties, etc., this system also does not appear to be feasible. As you are aware, there is a system in force at present where by cargo if marked R.E.and transhipped rcxit within 20 days of arrival in Bahrain to certain mainland ports of Eastern Saudi Arabia only, pays only 2^ duty and import Yard charges. If transhipped direct from steamer or craft to these ports, the cargo if over 100 packages pays If^ duty only, and duty only if under 100 packages. This system does not give merchar\ts very much time to explore the markets and confines their activities^ to the needs of Eastern Saudi Arabia, which are not great, and in'this connection, sight must not be lost of the possible opening up of the port of Ras Tanura as a commercial cargo port. I would, therefore, recommend for your consideration that the above system be abolished and. the following substituted;- 'All cargo marked Bahrain in Transit, if landed, • ma^'be re-shipped within 90 days to any destination whatever, against payment of duty and import Yard charges only. If transhipped direct from steamer or craft to any destination', this cargo will pay It transhipment duty only.' # This should give merchants sufficient time and scope to find suitable markets for their wares. Should the above be agreed to, it could come into force, after the erection of the new shed on the pier. Yours sincerely, Sd./- G.W.R. SMITH C- Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., G.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.THE AGENCY BAHRAIN D.O. No.C/576. Dated the 4th of June, 1946 0 l^ n Will you please refer to/the correspondence ending with your printed Letter No.417-3 dated the 6th of April, 1946, on the subject, ^of the Bahrain finances? 2. Criticisms on Belgrave r s work as Finance Officer have already been made this year - vide my demi-official letter No .g/259 dated the 6th Tarch, 1946, to Sir Geoffrey prior and the enclosures to Residency printed Letter no .410-S dated the 5th April, 1946 - and progress in the various S ^ ] matters is being reported separately. Severe criticisms are made most years - vide Hickinbotham*s letter No.C/393 dated the 21st March, 1945, and pelly's demi-official letter No.c/961 dated the 3rd October, 1945, to me - but now that the figures of actual expenditure have been provided further comments are called for. 3. The attached tables of estimates and actuals for 1364 show clearly that the Financial Adviser has once again greatly over-estimated expenditure and under-estimated revenue, and for half the heacls of; revenue the actual receipts range between half and half as much again as the estimates. This travesties the drawing up of a budget and defeats the purpose implicit in it, the apportioning of an accurately estimated income to considered purposes. I do not propose to discuss here the effect of this on the Bahrain public, but to confine the subject matter of this letter to the preparation and maintenance of the Bahrain accounts. 4. The State has spent less than the sums estimated on Defence, Kunicipalities, Oil Gauging, poor Relief, and Public Health measures (for which, due to prevalent condi tions, there may be some justification) and has wound up the year with an allocation of Rs.l8,84,54S. r7 .0 towards the Reserve Fund, an excess of Rs.8,84,548.7.0 over the estimated fi~ure and over and above the sum paid into the reserve fund from oil royalties. There seems no good reason why these 'savings' should not be re-allocated in the next budget instead of being lost to the public by being swallowed up in the general reserve fund. It is true that capital from the reserve has been used to finance major public services such as the bridge and the elctricity supply, but those services are run on a strictly economic basis. 5. It may not be possible to make a separate reserve fund for all the major heads of expenditure, but I am of the opinion that separate reserve funds should be started for public Health and Public V^orks. The State Medical Officer has recently inaugurated a campaign to advance the /general Hon'ble Lt-Col. W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, (Camp) Bahrain. T clt ■ : '~Y v5 -(&gt; .fykTHE AGENCY BAHRAIN general conditions of health and hygiene in Bahrain and the money for this campaign, and for a project such as the new water supply system, should not be provided from current income nor even from the General Reserve Fund, but from funds built up for such special purposes. The balance in any year where the actual expenditure on Public Health or public rr orks is less than the sum budgeted for might be credited to these separate heads. Thus a true account of expenditure on public services would be maintained and general allocation to the Reserve, the use of which is - and should be - closely watched, avoided. The Financial Adviser has promised to adopt the proposals recommended in paragraphs 5 and 6 of Government of India letter No.D. 9680-ME/45 dated the 22nd August, 1945, in his next budget, and w^ must hope that this will help to create the separate reservKfunda^ suggested above. I enclose a copy of his letter. 6. The amounts by which the Financial Adviser's 1365 estimates are greater or less than his 1364 estimates are as follows:- REVENUE. Increase in 1365. Decrease in 1365. Oil Royalty t 3,00 Customs 4,00. Land Revenue 9 Education 1 Passport Receipts 5 Bridge Tolls 70 Oil Gauging Fees 15 Miscellaneous 5 Increase in 1365 Rs. interest from Reserve 1,30,000 Medical Receipts Judicial Receipts Electric Supply Department 27,000 4,500 71,000 EXPENDITURE. Decr ease in 1365 . State Protection Municipalities Agriculture Rs. 20,000 9,000 6.000 Rs. Allowances to Ruling Family 1,00,000 State Departments 68,500 Judicial Dept. 15,000 Education 1,95,500 Public Health 30,000 public Works 2,15,000 Oil Gauging 2,000 The Financial Adviser has estimated that there will be a drop in bridge tolls, and I think this reasonable in view of the departure of Service personnel from Bahrain. Similarly the evacuation of the R .A.F. wards in the Bahrain Government Hos pital will mean a decrease in hospital receipts and the gradual abandonment of war time regulations may cause a decrease of receipts in the Law Courts. But his estimate that he will receive only Rs. 15,500 in judicial fees as against Rs.33,231.15.0 in 1364 seems somev/hat Utopian. His figures for land revenue also appear unduly moderate, particularly when it is remembered that both in 1363 and 1364 his actual receipts for this item were much in excess of his estimates, vide paragraph 3 of this /Agency ■-w | THE AGENCY BAHRAIN -3- S 3H- Agency letter No.C/393 dated the 21st March, 1945. 7. The Financial Adviser has budgeted for an increased expenditure on public health and public works of Rs. 1,95,500 and Rs.2,15,000 respectively over his 1364 estimates. He has also budgeted for an expenditure of Rs.2,00,000 on motor vehicles. To offset this his estimates for State protection, Kunicipalities and Agriculture have been reduced by Rs.20,000, Rs.9,000 and Rs.6,000 respectively compared with last year's estimates. The disbandment of the Special Police will account for some of the drop in expenditure estimates on State protection. He has also abandoned Poor Relief, but the^ subsidising of foodstuffs will continue. S 8. Further points for consideration are that the yearly statements received from the Financial Adviser, which in themselves as already pointed out give an unbalanced picture, are not signed. Neither do we know that the auditor has actually passed them. The accounts are audited annually, paragraph 29 of my demi-official letter NO.C/S59 dated the 6th March, 1946, to Sir Geoffrey Prior is, I regret to say, wrong, and presumably the auditor does sign the statements. For us to accept an unsigned statement forwarded under cover of a demi-official letter (I notice that in the past he has signed them) from the Financial Adviser is open to criticism. I enclose copies of this year's statement, and the covering letter. It is valueless to speculate as to why the Financial Adviser does not take this single precaution himself, but he does not and I suggest that I should tell him that we require to see the final yearly statement of accounts as passed and signed by the auditors. g 2&gt;\ 9. As regards accountancy staff, there has been consider able controversy concerning the late incumbent of the important post of accountant, and now that Mr. Braganza, on whom the Financial Adviser pinned his faith - vide paragraph 3 of the enclosure to pelly's demi-official letter No. p.8 dated the 19th August, 1945, and in which connection Sir Qlaf Caroe's note enclosed with * f r. Croning's demi-official letter No.635-S of the 24th August, 1937, is of interest on this and the general question dealt with in this letter - has gone (this I learnt through an application for a liquor permit and not through any act of co-operation on Belgrave's part) is the time to consider the adequate filling of the post. To my query regarding his replacement and the ability of the new incumbent efficiently to perform the duties of accountant, Belgrave has replied as follows:- P I 1 Vivi. C.-?/ 'I propose appointing syed Mahrnood Alawi to the post of Accountant which has become vacant ov/ing to Mr. Braganza f s retirement subject to His High ness 1 approval. Syed Mahmood has been in the service of the Bahrain Government for about 17 years, he has held the post of Accountant and also that of Head Clerk and after discussing the matter with our Auditor I am satis fied that he is suitable and capable of carrying out the duties which were undertaken by Mr. Braganza.' /10. Itm THE AGENCY BAHRAIN -4- 10. It is impossible sitting in my chair to hazard more than a guess about the reliability of Belgrave's opinion of Mr. Alawi. Personally I do not like the sound of it at all. and do not hesitate to express my opinion that a properly trained man of much higher calibre is required. The chief auditor himself told me that yearly he submitted some 40 pages of audit objections, and I think we should find that a properly trained accountant is required. To enable me more accurately to estimate the position J propose to discuss the matter with the Financial Adviser. '. r e need not go so closely into the State's internal workings by calling for a copy of the audit objections, but I should like to see one of his reports and propose to ask the Financial Adviser \to shoi'wrca** : ' 11. T '. T hile on the subject of finance I should like to point out that the State, acting on/Residency advice vide Residency demi-official letter ; To.275~S dated the 1st May, 1941, has a sum of 113 lakhs invested in Government of India stock. I think we should assure ourselves of the safety of this money, and the position of its availability for re investing elsewhere, now or later on, as may be thought necessary in view of the impending change of government in India. 7 ihCopy of Demi-official letter No.501-21 dated the 6th March, 1946,. from C-D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to theBahrain Government, to the political Agent, Bahrain. Reference your D.O. No .c /210 dated 25th February, 1946, -the budget fdr the present 37'ear has already been made and approved by His Highness and it would be difficult at this stage to recast it on the lines suggested in your note. I am sorry that I did not receive this note before, in time to adopt the method which is laid down in ^t. The life of the oil field was estimated in 1937 at 15 years. It would be interesting now to know what is its expectation of life in the opinion of the Company. oul ! it be possible to ask the Bahrain Petroleum company whether we could be given a very rough 'without prejudice' idea of how long the present output may last? The basis of the scheme appears to rest on this factor. 3. Apart ^rom the electric scheme there is at present no important government undertaking which produces' revenue and the budget on the expenditure side consists almost entirely of expenditure on public services and administration. His Highness has in mind a building scheme in Manama which includes the construction of a line of large shops which would be productive scheme but this was not included in the 1365 Budget as the material for the buildings is not likely to be available for some time. 4. 1 will prepare the next budget on the*lines of your note and I hope by then that there will be certainuw D.O. No.665-21. Adviserate, March 26, 1946. Dear Galloway, Reference your D-O. No. c/295 dated 21st March 1946 2. I enclose herewith four copies of the Statement of revenue and expenditure for the year 1364. Yours sincerely, Sd./- C. DALRYMPLS BELGRAVE Lt -Col. A.C. Galloway, O.B.E-, H.B.M.'s political Agent, Bahrain ./ 19/169 &amp; 19/176 GOm-iaOTlAU office of the Political Reaidantp Persian Gulf. jj 0 p / pao Bahrain, ' C /^ Q « the 6th June 1946. 'ill you please refer to your d,o. letter 1 *0. C/576 dated tUe 4th June 1946. 2. There are two polnte of outetanding Importance raisou ii^ your letter and its enclosure which I wish to take uj, at once. Tbe first is contained in para«raph 11 of your letter. tould you kindly let me know in exactly what OoTernaant of India stook the sua of 115 — ij invested in order that I may consult «eightnan about its safety, -o ^ o. .He second point is that raised in Belgrarefe demi-official letter So. 601-21 of the 6th of iiaroh about the life of the oilfielt. In order to obtain a true picture of Bahrain finances U is es.entxal that we ehoulUi know roughly how long the income from the oilfield is likely to remain at its present figure and when and oy what stages it io likely to decrease. if you see no objection I should be grateful if you would endeavour to obtain information from the Bahrain Petroleum Company on this subject and let me know the result. .Colonel A.C.Galloway» O.Beij;., \ Political Agent» (JJ f BAHHAia o f«L.s 19/169 &amp; 19/17 6. COHFIDKHTIAL . X) &gt; 0 &gt;1; o» C/253 &gt; Office of the Politios^ Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, the 8th June 1946* US) S-V Please refer to your demi-official letter So.C/576 dated the 4th June 1946» 2 0 I thoroughly agree with your criticisms but would note that my predecessor has recently spoken to Belgrave Yery plainly about his poor budgetting and the laok of progress that is being made in the State and that what is required now is steady pressure to bring about an improTement. Hith this end in view 1 agree to the action proposed in paragraphs 8 and 10 of your letter* 3* rtith reference to paragraph 5 of your letter X am Inclined to think it will be better to adopt the headings suggested by the Government of India in their letter to which you refer especially as the Financial Adviser has already been advised to a4opt these headings. There are few productive schemes and the bulk of the savings should therefore be set aside for capital expenditure on unproductive schemes* Steps should then be taken to ensure that the money so set aside is spent for the benefit of the State and the public on public works, public health etc* 4* 1 have been particularly impressed since 1 came to Bahrain by the extremely bad state of the roads which causes loss both to the State and the public owing to the unnecessary wear and tear on motor transport* 1 would ask that the Financial Adviser should be pressed to iiqprove the state of the roads as soon as possible* 5* 1 observe from paragraph 13 of the note recorded by my predecessor on his discussions witk^ Belgrave vide enclosure to Residency Printed Letter No* 410-3 dated the 6th April 1946 that Belgrave stated that the Muharraq swing bridge had not yet paid for its initial cost but that this position would shortly be reached and that it was then proposed to make the bridge free of all tolls* If you see no objection would you kindly ascertain when this position is likely to be reached* It appears to roe that in view of its satisfactory financial position the atate could well afford to forego these tolls at once* If it does not do this it should at least put the road across the causev^ay into a proper condition* Its present state is disgraceful. 6. I see from paragraph 6 of your letter that revenue from interest on the Reserve is expected to drop to the extent of Rs* 1,30,000 during 1365* This appears odd especially in view of the big increase in the Reserve and I should be grateful for an explanation* ■ I i Mt I Lt* -Colonel A*C*Galloway, U.B.ii., Political Agent, bahrain D RHL.s\ \ CONFIDENTIAL D.0. No. C/674 Dated the 25th June, 1946 v ' Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No. 0/240 dated the 6th June, 1946. S 1U- 2. • I have now received a statement of the Government of India stock held by the Bahrain Government and attach a copy herewith. 3._ As regards the life of the oil field, the Chief Local Representative informed me yesterday that the estimated content of the reservoir was 500 million barrels This colossal amount is sufficient to provide the Company with oil for a period much exceeding their concession, and does not take into account any possible reserves in the Additional Area. It seems unlikely in view of the above figures,and at roughly the present' rate of off-draw, that the Bahrain Government's income will drop for at least another 50 years. The Kon'ble Lieut. Colonel W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I. J)., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain . JANCI** — . ■ShalJtU Salman oame to soe me on the 2nd September Wb a result of a letter nhioh I wrote to him to the effect that I was not willing to enter into dieouseions about Zubarah until after Colonel Galloway's return from- leave but that there were other matters of a more urgent nature about which I vlehed to speak to him after Ramadhaiu 2. In spite of my letter as soon as formalities were over the Shaikh started off at once on the subject of Zubarah and resisted all my attempts to stop him* *vhan 1 eventualiy did get him to talk about other subjects he kept on breaking off and returning to Zubarah. He said he had brought papers with him which he wished to show me but X refused to see them. He talked at great length about 'my rights' and ''my land' and so on and complained that it was two years and two months since he nad signed the agreement and nothing had been done to implement it. fie complained of the further delay caused by my refusal to discuss the matter until Colonel Galloway's return and said that no doubt the matter would be further postponed owing to my departure on leave. He said he was oecoming a laughing stock of all the Arabs because in spite of his friendship with the British he was unable to obtain nis rights. He did not refer at all to the tower in tne course of the conversation but mentioned chiefly the restrictions the Shaikh of ^atar was placing on Bahrain subjects entering and leaving Zubarah. If I understood him rightly he stated that he did not claim sovereignty over i^ubarah but only wanted his grass and water. dThen I remarked that there was no profit for him in ^ubarah he replied that it was not a matter of profit as he knew that there was nothing of value in Zubarah but one of prestige. He said that Zubarah was of more importance to him than anything else in the world and th^t so long as the present position existed he would continue to remain in a state of anguish. He finally said that he could not bear the present uncertainty and wanted a decision one way or the other even though it was unfavourable, I replied that I could not possibly give a decision until I nad heard what the Shaikh of Q 4 atar had to say on the subject and suggested that I might even have to inspect the spot. 5. as soon as 1 was able I brought the conversation round to the subject that I wished to talk to the Shaikh about. I said that now that the life of the oilfield and the income from it was assured for 50 years I thought that more ought to be spent on improving conditions in Manama and Muharraq. I referred to the lack of any development plan, the bad state of the roads, to the need for a hotel, town planning etc. X also mentioned the difficulty that Colonel Blood worth had experienced in obtaining land for an automatic exchange at Muharraq and to the unsatisfactory position that had bean created by the faot that although Mr. Tunnicliffe is nominally Group Captain Leigh's assistant he has not been placed in subordin ation to him. Shaikh Salman first said that he could not do anything until the Zubarah question hsA been settled, at which I showed obvious signs of annoyance. He then said that Bahrain was greatly in advance of the other Gulf States so far its administration was concerned, and that he could not be blamed for being conservative in expenditure when the oil refinery could be completely destroyed by one bomb. I did not argue matters at great length but contented myself on this occasion by giving the Shaikh my views. I think ne had probably been informed beforehand the subject regarding which i wished to speak to him and briefed by My. Belgrave. RHL ./r •; l}*&gt; D.O. No.c/1172. POLITICAL AGENCY'' BAHRAIN• The 17th October, 1946. s please refer tp^ correspondence resting with your printed Letter No.772-S dated the 24th September, 1946, on the subject of a Bonded Warehouse System for Bahrain. f VvS f 2. &lt; I enclose copies of my demi-official letter No. G/1078 dated the 28th September, 1946, to Belgrave and of his reply which I have just received. I am informed that it is the universal custom at all Free ports to refund 7/8 of the import duty when goods are re-exported elsewhere, and in view of this it is difficult to refute the argument put forward by Belgrave in paragraph 3 of his letter. I understand that it will be at least six months before the new customs sheds are ready, but I propose, if you have no objection, to urge Belgrave to press on now with the preliminary steps necessary for introducing the facilities suggested by him in paragraph 4 of his letter. ia^rs Trie Hon'ble Lt-Col. A.C. -Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. NS.D.0. No.2166-3. Adviserate, October 12, 1946, Dear Ranee, f ^ Reference your D.O. No.C/1078 dated 28th September, 1946, I thank you for sending the Aden Tobacco ordinance. 2. Referring to your para 5, the period for reshipment of RE cargo is 20 days. 3. I have discussed this matter with Smith and he has examined the possibilities of a Bonded T ,varehouse System for Bahrain. If a Bonded System were adopted the customs would receive 1/8 of the duty from RS cargo instead of 2^ of its advalorem value. Sixteen times the present quantity of RS cargo would have to be imported into Bahrain, under the Bonded System, to produce the revenue which the State is now collecting by the RE system, a change in the system would also entail increased expenditure on additional staff and capital outlay on new buildings. Apart from imports through Bahrain into Qatar there does not at present appear to be any immediate prospect of any big increase in the RE trade. 4. instead of considering the introduction of the bonded warehouse system, at present, I am in favour of extending the facilities under the existing RE system. These facilities apply only to certain specified ports on the coast of Saudi Arabia, the arrangement is not a general one but is an under taking between the State of Bahrain and the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. I think it would be desirable and advantageous to extend the present system to RE imports from all Gulf ports and also to extend considerably the period allowed for reshipment. I think His Highness would be willing to put this suggestion into practice except in the case of Qatar. We have considered in the past the possibility of using the offer to grant to Qatar similar RE facilities as are enjoyed by Saudi Arabia as a bargaining basis in any negotiations which may take place between Bahrain and Qatar so it is not likely that His Highness would grant a concession to Qatar which might some day be granted in return for concessions from Qatar. Yours sincerely, Sd./- C. DALRYMPLE BELGRAVE Captain H.D.H. Ranee, H.B.M. t s Political Agent, 19 d 7 Bahrain. NS.Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrein, the 2nd November, 1946 Will you please refer to your demi- official letter No ,C /1172 dated the 17th October, 19467 2, I am unable to follow the argument at paragraph 3 of Belgrave's letter because the calculation of M i of the duty 1 ' depends upon the rate at and basis on which duty is charged. I should be grateful if you would get the matter elucidated. 3. In passing I should like to note that if Bahrain is made a free port it will be impossible to exclude one state from the benefits of the port. However, that need not be gone into yet but it is interesting to note how the Qatar phobia invades Bahrain development projects. Captain H.D.H. Ranee, Political Agent, B^hyaMt NPG/? mr D.O. No.c/204. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 15th February, 1947. S . o ' ' Will you please refer to your demi-official letter N0.1167-S of the 18th December, 1946? , ^.15 2. As regards paragraph 8 of my demi-official letter No.c/576 dated the 4th June, 1946, I pointed the irregularity out to Belgrave with the result that he has said that he would, in future, sign the statements and send them to me under cover of an official document. The summary of revenue and expendi ture as at the end of Jamad al Thani, 1365, (1st May, 1946), together with statements of revenue and expenditure for the same period has since been received signed. ^ 3. As regards paragraph 10 of my letter quoted above, I have seen a copy of the auditor's report, but was unable to learn anything from it. in fact, it was not a report written on the lines familiar to me, and so far as I could see no objections in the accounts were raised at all. The document consisted of a sheaf of papers on each page of which was an initial. There was no signature nor stamp nor } date and a more ingenuous document I never saw, for it seemed to me to convey nothing but a tacit expression of satisfaction. I propose to take the matter up with the Chief Auditor, Mr. Madams, when he pays his next yearly visit to Bahrain. 4. With reference to paragraph 4 of my letter No.g/269 of the 6th March. A great deal of progress has been made under this heading. Firstly a lady doctor has been engaged for a period of two years and another nurse has also been engaged, but with the resignation of Mrs. Godden the situation as regards nurses is the same. It is, however, quite satis factory. 5. Generally, a Public Health Committee has been formed which meets monthly and deals with the various subjects which we have decided are the most urgent, a great deal of work has been done. The Municipalities and the Health Department are progressing. Themost evident sign of advancement is the new women's hospital in Muharraq which is due to be opened shortly. The next step the Bahrain Government is trying to achieve is the appointment of permanent school doctors, and Belgrave is endeavouring to enlist more Indians, male and female, for this work. As regards 6 and 7, relevant remarks are in paragraph 4 above. Air conditioners have been installed in the hospital. 6. As regards paragraph 9. The State Engineer now controls his budget as I suggested he should do. i. /7. As regards.. The Hon'ble Lt-Gol. W.R. Hay, C .S .I., C .I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bah rain . fpFRSlAN GULF L, j NO | DATE-.nJMs i 1 '■ cO'Sf'OENTIAU ' Lf s^)-2- /for altera tions in 7. As regards paragraph 10. The Assistant State Engineer works solely in the Public Works Department and as such I have left him under the superintendence of the Adviser. The State Engineer has his hands full enough with new electrical instal lations and on second thoughts I considered it advisable not to press/the State arrangements in this respect. It might be advisable to make a change later after the arrival of the new State Engineer. The power House is now short of only one electrician and efforts are being made to fill the job. A new oil gauger has been recruited and is working in Awali. 8. As regards 12 and 13. A considerable amount of equip ment has arrived including a scarifier. You will yourself have seen that repairs to the roads- are being undertaken. 9. As regards 16. This project has been dropped for various reasons. One is the impossibility of maintaining the supply of current while the engines were being transferred. Duplication of the power house and engines is quite out of the question. Another difficulty was that the main cables would mostly have to be re-laid. 10. As regards 19. The Technical School has progressed to the extent of acquiring a 300 amp. gasoline engine driven generator and a 200 amp. electric powered welding generator, an electric holder, 2 welding helmets complete with lens and cover glasses, 2 pairs of welding gloves and 25 pounds each of 5/32' and 3/32' welding electrodes. An oxygen acetylene welding and cutting equipment was available, but not installed owing to the element of danger in their operation. A truck in poor working condition was given by BAPC0 for dis-assembly and re-assembly work. BAPC0 took up two scholarships in the Technical School and paid some Rs.2,000/- for these. 11. As regards 20. The Director of customs has been given control of his own budget. 12. As regards 21. shaikh Salman bin Muhammad bin Jsa on his return from judicial training in Palestine has been put on to this work. r . 1 0 13. As regards 24-28. The matter is under active con sideration as you will see from the correspondence resting with my printed Letter No.C/194 dated the 13th February, 1947. I am awaiting a further communication from the Adviser. 14. As regards 29. Relevant remarks are in paragraph 3 above. I have nothing to add at the moment except that I should like to point out that to make a non-financially minded man appreciative of financial values is next to impossible. Belgrave may have excellent qualities as an Adviser, but as financial adviser he has only one idea which he shares with the Shaikh, and that is to spend as little as possible and that little only when driven to it. 15. As regards 30. The new customs sheds are going up fast. A matter which I now propose to take up is that of drainage. /The place is,rr - - ■ IThe place is filthy enough as it is, but with the installa tion of a piped water-supply the problem may take on grave proportions. 16. The Adviser has been provided with new sample municipal improvement trusts and plans to enable him to draw up a proper town planning, public health and building code \</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00013e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/345</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00013e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/345</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/169 IV Bahrain reforms'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (60 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>Formerly a bound correspondence file, its sheets have been unbound and are now loose. Foliation starts on the file cover and continues to last page. Foliation in pencil numbers in top right corner of recto. Additional inconsistent foliation, also in pencil, starts with 9 on f.2. There is also occasional inconsistent pagination in blue crayon.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The majority of the documents contained in this file date from 1946 and 1947. The information contained in them relates to the state of Bahrain's economy and infrastructure post-World War Two. The documents contain discussions between the Agency in Bahrain and Charles Belgrave (the adviser to the Bahrain Government) concerning reforms in state finances, public health, engineering, education, customs, the judiciary and the police force. The file also contains financial records related to the Government of Bahrain's revenue and expenditure.Folios 2-8 contain an unrelated report (written by Charles Belgrave) that discusses disturbances in Bahrain that took place during Muharram festivities in January 1942.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Education</topic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00013e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>