<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001c8_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T15:37:57.883Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">V, ARM HEADQUARTERS, INDIA i i QUAUTEHMASTER CENEUAL'S BRANCH MESOPOTAMIA EXPEDITIONARY FORCE SUMMARY OF PAPERS RELATING TO SHIPPING AND CONGESTION OF STORES AT BASRAH l.- . SIMLA GOYEKNMKNT CENTRAL BRANCH PRESS 1916. SHIPPING AND CONGESTION OF .STORESHIPS AT BASRAHSHIPPING. Para. Barges. Transhipment of Troops into—— ... ... 2 Serial No. in appen dix. Director, R. I. M. Impressment ol ships by—— .,. 3 Draught of ships able to cross Fao Bar 2 i . Europe. Troops from 2 and 3 Egypt m n ••• ••• ••• ••• 2 and 3 Fao Bar. Crossing of— ••• ••• 2 / „ „ Transhipment at— ... ... ••• 2 Inspector-General, Communications, Basrah. Request re arrival of ships 5 i» 3.5. Koweit. Transhipment at— ... ... ... ••• 2 Limitations in choice of ships ... ••• ••• 1 Reinforcements. Normal despatch of— ... ... ... 4 River steamers. Transhipment of Troops into—... ... 2 Sailings arranged by D. R. I. M. ... ... ... 6 Ships. No difficulty in obtaining— 1 „ Arrival of—at Basrah ... ... ... 5 3. 5- „ Choice of—, limitations in— ... ••• ... a Storeships. Conditions to be fulfilled by— ... ... 2 Troops. Transhipment of»— ... ... ... ... 2 Units. Despatch of- ■ ... ... ... — 4 War Office. Ships arranged by— ... ... ... 3 CONGESTION OF STORESHIPS AT BASRAH. • Congestion increasing at docks ... ... lO 19, 20. n might be caused at Indian ports 6 I 4- „ relieved ... ... ... ... 4 23- „ Storeships first brought to notice ... — 1 6. Despatch of Storeships. Difficulty in regularizing— ... ... 5 12. Fao Bar. Suggestion ships should lie there ... m* 6 12. Floating warehouse. Suggestion of—— not concurred in by W.O. 6 12, 13- Gulf ports. Stores for and unloading at S 12. Loading. Suggestions by I. G. C. ... ... ... ... 3 and 5 9, 12. Port facilities. Lack of ... ••. ••• 1 6. River craft. Storeships used to tow — ... ... ... 5 12. Sailings. Difficulty in arranging programme of 2 7, 8- Stores. Monthly tonnage to be shipped ... *♦. 3 and 12 9. IO, 21- Stores. Monthly tonnage to be shipped increased ... ... 12 21. Storeships. Congestion of—first brought to notice ... ... 1 6. „ Interval of 5 days between departure of' ... ... „ Detailed by D. R. I M. ,, Limitation in selection of' ... ... •.« „ Numbers Basrah can cope with at one time, ... „ Release of suggested by W. O. •„ Sailing of » ••. . — „ Suggestions as to despatch from India ... „ To be despatched at regular intervals ... *•* . Troops transports. Space to be used for urgent stores and supplies Warehouse. Floating suggested M „ not concurred in by W. 0. ... ... War Office. Orders from regarding loading n „ „ „ floating warehouse ... ... Wharfage facilities. Lack of— „ ... ... «•. 2 12 6 3 and 14 rt 10 and 14 4 and 5 1 7 and 11 6 6 6 6 1 7,8. 23- 12. 9. 34. 25. 1 ?. 19, 20. 23. 11, 13. 6. 16. '2. '3. «3 l 3 6. 162GQ M % ^ •0 SHIPPING. 1. Since the outbreak of hostilities in Mesopotamia in 1914, no difficulty has been ex perienced in obtaining ships for troops or stores. 2. Choice of ships is limited by their capability to cross the bar at Fao, only ships of 18 ft. draught and under can do this. Storeships must therefore fulfil this condition. When troops arrive in ships drawing over this draught, they have to be transhipped at Fao or Koweit into ships of shallower draught or river steamers and barges. This has been the case with some of the troops from Europe and Egypt. 3. The Diiector, Royal Indian Marine^ has been able to impress all ships necessary, and no difficulty is anticipated in the future. Ships for troops and stores from India have been arranged by the Director, Royal Indian Marine, and from Europe and Egypt by the War Office, though in December 1915, India supplied 19 fitted ships to bring troops 7rom Europe and Egypt to Basrah. 4. Normally reinforcement ships for Mesopotamia are despatched from Bombay or Karachi twice monthly from each part, but units are despatched whenever required. 5. In July 1916, Inspector General of Communications, Basrah, requested that, owina to Serial Nos. 1,2. ^ the inadequate facilities for disembarking troops and animals there, arrangements should be 3,4,5, made that ships carrying them should arrive there at not less than 2 days intervals. 6. The Director, Royal Indian Marine, is now consequently arranging the sailings from Bombay and Karachi to meet this request. CONGESTION OF STORESHIPn AT BASRAH. 1. The question of congestion of storeships at Basrah was first broucrht to notice in April 1916, when the General Officer Commanding, Force ' D, ' wired that owing to inade quate port and wharfage facilities great difficulty was being experienced in dealing with a number of storesh.ps at one time. He states that while 16 ships arrived between 3 .st Serial No. 6. March and 9th April only 5 arrived betwen 15th March and 24th March and therefore asked that storeships should be despatched at more regular intervals to enable him to handle cargo more expeditiously and avoid delay in returning ships to India. 2. The difficulty of arranging a regular programme of sailings was pointed out by the Director, Royal Indian Marine, owing to the uncertaintv of the dates of return of shios Serial Nes. 7,8. from Basrah and other contingencies He would however, trv to keep intervals of s davs between the departure of each storeship. ' * 3. The General Officer Commanding, Force ' D, ' then gave approximate tonnage of stores required to be snipped monthly by each department to Basrah and suggestions as to Se io ial N01 ' 9 ' loading the ships with regard to urgency and facilities for unloading. He stated there should not be more than 10 ships at Basrah, 4 at the wharves, and 6 in the stream. . 4- In May, General Officer Commanding! ' D,' reported that there were 14 shinsIvincr m the river at Basrah, and only 10 could be dealt with at a time. He therefore LJam cs^.i urn ,n ted that any in excess of that number shnuld not leave India until their turn came insfeaH ' of lying in the stream at Basrah. e&gt; ,nstead 5 General Officer Commandirg, ' D, ' was then informed that his proposals as re- gards loading and despatch of ships were being carried out as far as practicable but' that several contingencies made it impossible completely to regularize despatch. A contingencv Serial No. 11. which upsets any programme is that frequently storeships are used for towing river rrfft anc are thus delayed and stores have to be unloaded at Gulf Ports, the result of which is that dates of arrival at Basrah could net be foreseen. It was considered H . loaded ships should wait at Basrah, or the Fao Bar rather than Bombav or Karachi hlr! General Officer Connmanding Force ' D.' knowing what on each' ship cou d uXd in the order he wished, and-berths at Indian ports would not be occupied bv fullv loaded ships, a matter which would cause congestion there. The suggestion was made that a ship should be retained as a floating warehouse into which ships could discharge their carVo and thus accelerate their return to India. &amp; car^o 6. This, however, was not concurred in by the Secretarv War .1 nf 31st directed that ships should not be loaded at Bombay or Karachi ' until' theV Serial No -» 3 - can be despatched so as to arrive at Basrah on a date they can be duchamed SeriaI NO - and thus some storeships might be released Dirertnr R ^oi r a - Jf ? '' pointed cut «h„t difficulties this would entail! sucl' as ierv tel ' Mar,ne ' the docks, both of stores on shore and shipping in the stream ' and that &lt; :°' g ':® t ' on at specially selected fortheir length and draught it' would be' impossible^ replace them Jt short notice, and that shipping companies would hp mnoKi ■ venienced and strongly object to ships being discharged and re-impressed continually;Serial No. 15. Serial No. 16. Serial No. 17. Serial No. 18. Serial Nos.19- 20. Serial No. 21. Serial No. 22. Serial No. 23. Serial No. 24. Serial No. 25. when they are committed for other cargoes. This wis referred to the Secretary, War Office, who then empowered the Commander-in-Chief to deal with the matter himself being cognizant of the local situation. 7 Orders were issued in June that all space on troop transports was to be fully utilised for supplies. 8. General Officer Commanding, Force ' D,' was then asked to give fourteen days' notice to India previous to date stores could be discharged at Basrah. g. On June 13th, 1916, Director* Roval Indian Marine, wired that ii a few days there would be several ships lying idle in Bombay, and should he discharge them, He stated also that the congestion at docks was increasing and asked if supplies could be stopped arriving there. 10. The Inspector General of Communications, Basrah, on June 18th wired that ships • on that date loading at Bombay should be loaded and desp itched—'bat that after those, in order to relieve the congestion there, no storeship was to sail until he gave notice and he would give 2# days clear notice of any more beini^ required. Then he hoped the port would be normal and hi would be able to work on the following lines:—12 storeships (other than colliers and railway material ships) should be ample to carry the normal monthly requirements of the Force. Nine would suffice and three added for a margin. 11. Troop ships should be used for stores which have been asked for urgently. 12. The Director, Royal Indian Marine, then detailed the 12 ships for monthly stores and released those not required. 13. On 2lst June, Inspector General of Communications, Basrah, gave ton nage of stores to be allotted in ships monthly to each department and this was increased on June 27th owing to arrival of Cavalry Brigade. 14- On July loth, Inspector-General of Communications stated the arrival of storeships at the rate of two or three weekly should commence about Augu.si 5th, and on July 25th a proposed programme of the sailings of storeships for August was sent to Inspector -General Communications, Basrah, who approved of it, and stated on 29th July I9I6 tkat conges tion had been relieved. 15, The Inspector General of Communications, has since stated, in reply to a reference from India, that the 9 storeships are sufficient, and that more aie not needed, even though the round trip between India and Basrah takes more than one month.1 0 3 APPENDIX. 1 Telegram P., No. 8J8-30 -L C, dated 16th July 1916. (Despatched 2-I0 P.M., received 8 A.M., 17th July 1916.) From—The Inspector General of Communications, Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. The routine of this port would be much improved if the transport could arrive at regular intervals instead of in two bunches as at present. When two ships arrive together one cannot be unfoaded and in stream the damp heat at temperature of 116 0 is deadly. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M S.C., A.D. (Marine). 2 Telegram P,, No. 66882, dated 21st July 1916. Serial No. 1. {Despatched 6-45 -P.M.) From—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. To—The Inspector General, Communications, Basrah. Your 818-30-L.C. of 16th. Waste of tonnage will often occur if reinforcements are sent in more than two batches each month. Following arrangement is suggested. Please wire if suitable. Reinforcements to be despatched In two groups but dates of sailing to be so arranged that on any one day only one troop transport arrives. Arrival of 1st group between 15th and 20th of month and of second group between 31st or 1 st, and 4th or 5th. If this is accepted as suitable it is presumed that on any day on which a troopship arrives no storeships should arrive. Record copy to Q.M.G. « . • Copy to M.S.C , A.G., G.S. (M.O. 1). 3 Telegram P., No. 818-34 -L.O., dated 23rd July 1916. Serial No. 2. (Despatched I P.M., received 9 P.M., 23rd July 1916.) From—The Inspector General, Communications, Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. Your (16882 of July 21st. If transports could arrive at intervals of two days it would suffice to ensure the prompt clearing of actual troops. Transports and storeships need have no connection with each other, and the former do not clash at all with the latter. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C , G.S. (M .O. 1), A.G.4 4 Seri»l No. 3^ SocifttHO. 4, Telegram P., No. 67497. dated a4th July 1916. (Despatched 10-30 P.M.) From—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. To—The Inspector General of Communications, Basrah. Your 8 i 8-34-L.C. of July 23rd. The arrival of transports, with normal monthly reinforcements will be so arranged that they reach Basrah at 2 days' interval. Kindly telegraph whether vessels, carrying such units as 13th and 14th Lancers and animal transports, must also arrive at intervals of 2 days from ah other troop ships. Record copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., A.G., G.S, (M.O. 1). 5 Telegram No. 818-36-L.C,, dated 25th July 1916. (Despatched 7-15 P .M., 25th July, received 4.30 A.M., 26th July 1916.) From—The Inspector General, Communications, Basrah, To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. Your 67497 of 24th. Yes please, if you can possibly arrange. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., G.S. (M.O. 1). 6 Telegram No. I557-2-Q-, dated 14th April I916. (Despatched 10-30 P.M., received 5-40 P.M., 15th April I9I6,) From—The General Officer Commanding, Force ' D,' Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff. Owinc to inadequate port and wharfage facilities and shortage of labour great difficulty experienced in dealing with number of supply ships arnvm'g here at one time. During the period 31st March last to 9th April sixteen supply ships arrived Basrah of which three left Bombay on one day namely 2 &lt;th March and three left Karachi on 1st April. During similar period 15th March to 24th March, only five ships arrived here. Please arrange despatch at more regular intervals otherwise impossible handle cargo expeditiously or avoid delay in return of ships to India. I am shortly addressing you by tele- gram on the general subject of loading of supply ships m special manner to admit of more expeditious unloading here. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., A.D. (Marine), G.S. (M .O. 1, M .O. 2).5 Telegram No. Q.-1447, dated l8tb April 191(5. From—The Director, Marine, Bombay. To—The Quartermaster-General in India. Your 338-109-W. S.* of seventeenth. I am in consultation with Embarka- ,, J tion Bombay and Karachi regarding ' ot uce • t ^ e possibility of despatching the store- ships at more regular intervals and I will attempt as much as possible to prevent storeships sailing on the same or consecutive dates. It is extremely difficult to arrange a programme with dates owing to impossibility of foretelling when ships will return from 'jD.' I will wire again on this subject after having consulted Embarkation. The three vessels that sailed on the twenty-fifth March however were one ship with remounts and two with reinforcements namely the ' Torilla/' ' Bankura ' and ''Arankola'; this programme was arranged by you. 8 Telegram No, Q.-1542, dated 28th April [916, From—The Director, Marine, Bombay. To— The Quartermaster-General in India. Your 338-114-W. S.f of date not understood but probably mutilated it refers to your 338 -112-W. S.f of twenty- t No rej.ioduceii. sixth which concurs in the proposal in sending a storesh ; p via Linga ' mentioned in my Q.-lSiy. If you refer to your 33 8 - icg-W. S.f ot seventeenth regarding fixing dates of sailing of supply ships we did endeavour to keep to the dates mentioned but it was found imposiible to adhere to them because ships could not returnfrom ' D ' at the time. Karachi wires they adhere to dates as far as possible but this depends on following conditions. First date of arrival of storeships from ' D ' second if storeships are towing barges third one storeship must call at all Gulf Ports. I concur with views expressed from Karachi and in consultation with Embarkation Supply here consider it impossible to adhere strictly to dates for the same reasons and also because ships are often delayed for more urgent stores than it was at first decided to send for urgent explosives also because they are often urgently required to call at ports en route. I consider it is best to load them as they become empty and as Basrah knows exactly what is required and exactly what is on board each they should discharge them as necessary ; they need not however block other vessels but lie in river below Basrah till required. I do not consider we should get vessels back quicker by despatching them on fixed dates but I will endeavour as far as possible to keep an interval of five days departure between each vessel but this merely means delaying the vessels here instead of Basrah. 9 Telegram No. 1152-28-Q., dated 24th Apnl 1916. (Despatched 10-20 P M.. received 11 A.M., 25th April I9I6.) From—The General Officer Commanding, Force ' D, ' Basrah. To —The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. In continuation of my previous telegram Scril1 No 6 - No. I557-2-Q.. of April 14th. Para. i. The tonnage of the more cr less constant monthly demancs of the different departments approximate to the following amounts. Supply and Transport Directorate Supplies 21,000 tons. Clothing 1 ,300. Work Directorate 3 000. Ordnance Services 1 ,500. Army Signals aoo. Total 26,900 tons.6 Para. 2. It is proposed that Directors should intimate to you detailed list of above monthly requirements and that arrangements be made to despatch these supplies every month without further reference to me. (?; Para. 3. This will enable you to gauge the approximate tonnage of shipping required to meet our constant demands. Over and above these de mands there will be of course demands for unforeseen and unfor'-eeable require ments. It is proposed to intimate to you those demands as they arise and to ask you to despatch them in a certain order of urgency as accommodation in a certain number of spare supply ships kept in reserve to meet such special re quirements becomes available. Para. 4. In cases in which the tonnage of such requirements is consider able and the demand may without detriment be met by the despatch in succes sive consignments at stated intervals, the quantities to be so des-patched will also be intimated. Para. 5. This will obviate large masses of supplies sent in compliance with any particular demand being despatched in one ship and causing without any compensating advantage congestion at the wharves of any particular department here. Para. 6. To expedite unloading here material which is of great weight or difficult to handle such as planks should be distributed among all the holds of a {word or words apparently omitted} otherwise if such material is all placed in one hold the contents of other holds will be much more rapidly unloaded and the unloading of this one hold will seriously .delay the departure of the vessel as the number of men working on this hold cannot be increased beyond a certain limit and no advantage will be gained working night shifts on all holds. Para. 7. At present only ration supplies are being unloaded at Magill wharves. Clothing and supplies and stores for all other departments are being unloaded from the stream at Basrah. Para. 8. Experience shows that not more than six vessels in stream and four vessels brought alongside the wharves can be unloaded at one time. Para. 9. GdneraMy jspeaking therefore arrangements should be ^made so that not more than ten ships should be in this port at one and the same time. Para. 10 Ships should as far as possible be loaded on the following principles : (a) Men's rations should not if it can be avoided be loaded in the same ship as grain and fodder as otherwise ration supplies discharged from a vessel berthed at the wharf nearest the grain and fodder yard will have to be of man handled form considerably and vice versa, {b) various departments should be allotted to space in vessels pro rata to their monthly requirements in different holds or other stores separately stored in between decks, (c) material which is heavy and difficult to handle referred to in paragraph 6 requires special treatment and to facilitate tally no ship should carry material of this class for more than one department, {d) ration supplies should if possible be loaded at the bottom of the hold and stores of other departments on the top. To facilitate matters I could, if considered necessary, advise you one or two days in advance of the probable despatch of ships from here and this should assist the Embarkation authorities in despatching from India to maintain a constant stream of ships aniving here at suitable intervals without the number of ships actually here in port much exceeding the number of ten ships which can be dealt with here. Para. 12. Should the method of loading and despatch of ships above Indicated be adopted I anticipate with confidence the number of ships taken up for supplying this force will admit of substantial reduction without in any way impeding the necessary constant stream of regular supplies or causing any more delay in the despatch and receipt here of any urgent requirement than is inevitable with the present arrangements. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M .S.C., D.G.O., D.G.M.W , G.S. (S.D. 3).10 Telegram P., No. 1152-32-Q., dated 15th May 1916. (Despatched g -30 A.M., received 2 P.M., 16th May 1916.) From—The General Officer Commanding, Force 0 Dj ' Basrah. To—The Commander-in-Chief in India, Simla. At present there are 14 storeships in port of which 3 left India on April 13th and 2 on April 10th. About 600 (60,000 ?j tons are represented by these ships and the daily rate of unloading is only about 2,000 tons. At one time only 10 of these ships can be dealt with vide my telegram of 23rd April # Intelligence 52-'28-Q. (11-52-28-Q. ?). The unloading of 7 of these ships will not, it is calculated, be completed until towards the end of this month. No useful purpose is served by ships lying in the river here for days until they can be dealt with and, therefore, since such ships simply cause congestion, I would suggest that, if chartering, loading and despatching ships from India, so that not more than ten are in port here at one time, is impracticable, then those in excess of that number should not leave India until their turn comes instead of being sent here without due regard being paid to our means of dealing with them. In my I152-28-Q. of 23rd April* a full explanation of this was given. Addressed India, repeated London. • Nnf r#&gt;nrnmirf»n- 1 Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., G.S. (M.O. 1, M.O. 2). 11 Telegram No. 55073, dated 20th May 1916. (Despatched 11 P.M.) From—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. To—The General Officer Commanding, Force ' D, ' Basrah. Your 1152-28-Q. of 24th Apriif and 1152-32-0.f of 15th Instant, regard- . „ . . kt ine^ shipment of stores. As regards the t Serial Noj. 9-10. 1 1 r 1 i* method ot loading stores and supplies every endeavour will be made to comply with your wishes as far as practicable. Reference paragraph 1 of your 1152-28-Q., the total tonnage of stores for the S. and T. Department during the last month was 35,000 tons or an increase of 14,000 on amount given by you and this meant three extra storeships, and you will thus understand it is difficult to determine any definite programme for sailing of supply ships. The question of congestion of supply ships in Basrah resolves itself into one as to whether it is more convenient to have ships waiting at Basrah or Bombay and Karachi. The difficulty in despatching them so as to prevent their arriving at Basrah in a bunch is that these ships are very often used for towing river craft and a certain number call at Gulf Ports to discharge stores and consequence is dates of their arrival at destination cannot be foreseen. It is considered preferable to despatch ships from Bombay and Karachi when loaded and let them wait in the stream below Basrah or at the Bar until they can conveniently be unloaded as nearly every storeship carries some stores which are urgently required and by this arrangement you would have the ships in the river and you could unload those most urgently required as details of such stores on board are always cabled to you by the Embarkation Commandants at the ports from which the ships sail. Another suggestion put forward is the retention of a floating warehouse at Basrah of the ** Queda ' class which with 16 to 18 derricks along her decks could stow 12,000 tons, and transports could go alongside her and rapidly discharge themselves.8 It is thought that this would reduce the number of supply ships running between India and Basrah, by reducing their detention at the latter place. Please wire your views. If concurred in, Director, Marine will be asked to make a suitable ship available for this purpose. Record copy to Q .M G. Copy to M.S.C., M.S.V., G.S. (M .O.i.M.O. 2 ). 12 Telegram No. 1I52-40-Q., dated 10th June 1916. From—The General Officer Commanding, Fonce ' D, ' Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. Reference your telegram of 20th May Serial No. 11. No. 55073. Paragraph /. On enquiry I find that 31,125 not 35,000 tons were actually sent from India as S. &amp; T. supplies, during the month of April. Further the increase of 10,125 tons, t. e., the difference between the 21,000 tons gjven in my telegram of 25th April No. 1152-28-Q. and 31,125 tons was chiefly abnormal and accounted for as follows. Stores amounting to 1,761 tons for other departments and private in dividuals were consigned to S.&amp;.T. and the balance of 8,364 tons consisting of ordinary stores and supplies was due to the additional amount required to provide a reserve of 2 months' supplies for the whole Mesopotamian Force. Paragraph 2. Seeing that monsoon is now beginning the matter of store ships towing river craft was thought hardly applicable for the next few months. Paragraph J. The suggestion that a floating warehouse of the u Queda ' class should be located at Basrah is not concurred in. In reality such a ware house would afford little or no relief, as, with the number of store and other ships being sent here monthly, it would be quickly filled up. Paragraph 4. The present congestion of port owing to the number of ships sent is complicated further by the following. At present I have at Basrah large accumulations of the whole Force's 60 days' reserve. 30 days' reserve ought to be en route to or at the outposts and advanced bases. I am unable to distribute it on the above lines owing to the insufficiency of river craft. With the object of meeting this difficulty and of preventing further congestion my D. S. &amp;. T. has departmentally requested you to decrease by 16,320 tons the June consignments. Paragraph 5. Under the supervision of Buchanan, Browne is taking over the port traffic and the former wishes your attention to be drawn to the follow ing points. Store ships should all be loaded to arrive at the Fao bar with a mean draught of 18 feet. All available space in reinforcement ships be utilised for stores. Many reinforcement and store ships are at present arriving totally empty or only partially loaded. There should be no difficulty in getting some of the store ships off charter if space and draught are full) utilised. All steamer Commanders should again be instructed to furnish two copies of manifest and copies of stowage on arrival at Basrah. These should give full particulars and names of departments to whom goods are consigned. For prompt discharge this is absolutely essential. 13 Telegram P., No. 17332-Cipher-Q.M.G.-2, dated 30th May 1916 {Despatched 3-50 P.M., received 1 -30 A.M., jlst May 1916.) From—The Secretary, War Office, London. To—The Commander-in-Chief in India, Simla. • K* Your 55339. May 23rd.*9 Until it has been ascertained that they can be dealt with promptly in the Persian Gulf, Egypt has been instructed that ships are not to be allowed to load. We do not concur in the allotment of a vessel for warehouse purposes as we consider that a warehouse on shore would be more economical than a float' ing warehouse. At Bombay and Karachi ships shall not be kept loaded, and they will not be loaded until such time as will enable them to reach Basrah on a date when they can be discharged. It may be possible, if this course is followed, to release some of the Force ' D ' store transports. To economise ships, every effort should be made. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M S.C,, M.S.V., G.S. (M.O. i, M.O. 2). 14 Telegram No. 59i57, dated 13th June I916. (Despatched 3-20 P.M.) From—The Commander-in-Chief in India, Simla. To —The Chief of the Imperial General Staff, London. Please refer to our telegram 55339 of 22nd May* and telegram No. 17332- ^ Cipher QM.G.-2, dated 30th May from * ' . . Secretary, War Office.f VVe issued orders to carry out the instructions conveyed in the latter and have received the fol lowing telegram, dated 9th June from the Director, Royal Indian Marine. Begins. No. Q.-1942. Your i262-2-V\ .S. received. In making proposals for vessels to act as floating warehouse I took into consideration that Basrah had no ware - houses on shore and that they could not be built in reasonable time. I also had opinion of leading shipping companies at Basrah and Bombay and also Com mander Hamilton who agreed that proposal was very sound and would result in enormous saving of labour and barges which I understood were urgently required and must expedite return of store ships thus enabling me to discharge some. Every endeavour will be made to carry out War Office wishes but following points require elucidation. ^ Am 1 to understand that only one ship is to load at Bombay or Karachi at one time and this only when orders are received from Basrah. If this is the case will supplies from all departments be regulated accordingly frojn Headquarters otherwise congestion at docks will be far worse than ever at present and utmost difficulty is experienced as it is with limited accommodation. Please note that ships at Bombay never lie idle but commence loading immediately they are available and by doing so it has only just been possible to keep up with demands from ' D ' with store ships at present in use and prevent congestion. At present moment stores for two ships are arriving at docks or are there at pre sent and ' Warturn ' and ' Windsor Hall ' commence loading at once all depart ments have been warned and shipping orders issued. Am I to stop this and await orders from Basrah? Weather conditions during monsoon absolutely prohibit work on bhoosa and bags of rice etcetera except spasmodically and fortnight's notice is not sufficient to ensure vessels getting away and being at Basrah in that time. Vessels for Force ' D ' have to be specially selected for their length and draught and if it is intended that ships are to be discharged except those actually loading fear it will be impossible to replace them whenever required con ditions being quite different to home ports. At present not a single ship in Bombay that could possibly replace ships for ' D.' Shipping companies would be much inconvenienced and strongly object to ships being discharged and reim- pressed when they are committed for other cargoes. If on the other hand it is required to load six or seven ships at same time until they are loaded they must be idle m stream and the congestion at the docks would be more than could be dealt with unless entire Alexandra Docks are taken over with consequent increase m cost for warehousing and also for extra staff to superintend this would also dislocate all arrangement of ships embarking and disembarking and hospital ships arriving and leaving to say nothing of railway ships loading as berths are notio always available. Definite orders are requested as to whether if same amount stores are to be shipped monthly you wish attempt made to discharge all but vessels actually loading or under fourteen days' notice to load and an endeavour to be made to replace them as required or if not whether vessels are to be in port idle and merely not load until orders are received this will cause great congestion at docks. Please also wire whether ' Windsor HaU'* and 'Warturm' are to proceed with loading or not. Presumably you wish Embarkation to inform Basrah amount of stores ready for loading and 1 am only to provide vessels, /fnds. It would appear that the War Office orders cannot be carried out without the greatest inconvenience and delay in despatch of stores and I should be glad if these orders can be reconsidered in the light of the proposals given in my 55339, with a view to their being cancelled. Record copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., M.S V., A.D. (Marine), G.S. (M.O, i, M.O. 2). 15 Telegram P., No. ijgoo-Cipher-Q, M. G ,-2, dated 15th June 1916. (Despatched 6-55 p. m., received 6 a.m., 16th June 1916.) From—The Secretary, War Office, London, To—The Commander-in-Chief in India, Simla. • Serial No. 14. Your59i57of 13th June.* Whilst impressing on you the necessity for economizing shipping in every way you are hereby empowered to deal with the situation yourself and this because you are cognizant of the local situation. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., M.S.V., A. D. (Marine), G.S. (M.O. 1, M. O. 2). 16 Telegram P., No. 59270, dated 13th June I9I6. (Despatched 11-50 p.m.) From—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. To—The General Officer Commanding, Force ' D, ' Basrah. Your H53-40-Q. of 10th June. Reference para. 2. —That the floating warehouse of ' Queda ' type should be used to warehouse stores until they were required for issue was not the intention. The intention was that it should be used to rapidly unload store ships and subsequently to discharge the stores on to land, both operations being facilitated by the derricks on such ship. However, no action will be .taken on this subject in view of your telegram under reference. Reference para. 5.—We note mean draught for store ships. We have issued orders to the effect that all space on troop transports is to be fully utilised for supplies but in accordance with your 965»8-Q. of February 9th that bhoosa, hay and fuel should not be sent on these troop transports : please inform me if this latter view is still held by you. Shall be pleased if you will uote names of ships arriving only partially loaded or totally empty with their ates of arrival. Record copy to Q .M.G. ' Copy to M.S.C., M.S.V., G .S, (M.O. i, M .O. 2).11 Telegram P., No. 58419, dated 8th June 1916. (Despatched 9-45 p.m.) From—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. To—The G. O. C., Force ' D ' Basrah. Continuation my 57007 of 31st May.» So that War Office instructions * Not reproduced. may be earned out Bombay and Kara- . . c hi will have to be kept informed bv vou to the dates you can receive and discharge storeships. General details of ores awaiting shipment will be telegraphed you frequently by Embarkation Bombay and Kiaman and so that ships can commence loading and sail to reach you on the date requ.red, you must give at least .4 days' warning to either port Ld nrnK M 0 - them to telegraph at once what ships are now partly 10^' and probable date of completion of loading. Acknowledge receipt. Record copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M .S.C. is Copyof a telegram No, Q.- I 9 7 i . dated 13th June i 9 t6. From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. To—The Quartermaster-general in India, Simla. Your 1282-3-W.S. of I2tht noted. Please note ' Ooloharia ' is lying idle in 1 Not reproduced. Bombay pending decision and ' Chind- !.'o, .rfi.it -T3.''-S;■ ,|11 1* 1=. at thr Hnol,. • y: a . ( 13 be ' n g he,d in reserve for remounts. Concestion *uppHe» arriving -'-ore ships are to be loaded. Can yo'u^p 19 Telegram No. 828.2 (818-2? L.C.), dated 18th June tgid. (Despatched 6 p.m., received 8 A.M., 19th June 1916.) From— The Inspector General of Communications, Basrah. To—The Commander-in-Chief, Simla. i Not reproduced. ^ our 59^*9 16th June! and your 59454 of 14th June. | po£: hay, bho'jsa or w^d'^^wtlhipM 1;^fufth^ ntL^'^h 1^ m ^ e Clogged with nearly three months' supplies of these c'mmoditil lrT ,S you 21 days'clear notice of any more ships being requed wJ u' Fv ,Ve port normal and shall be able to work on lines indfcateTL m of date and reduce the number of ships on the run to economical numbers My 818 -3 \) gives you total number of storeships required. Buchanan and § Serial No. 30. Browne consider ' Queda' would not help us at all and I concur after experience*2 at Lemnos. As soon port is normal ships can load at Bombay and Kiamari with tonnage for each Directorate in sequence of original orders. Addressed C. G. S., repeated General Kirkpatrick. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., M.S.V., G.S. (M.O. i, M.O .2), A.D. (Marine). 20 Telegram No. 8I8-3 -L.C., dated 18th June 1916. (Despatched 11 P.M., received 8-I5 A.M., 19th June 19I6.) From—The Inspector General of Communications, Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. Reference my 818-2.* The need of this force other than colliers and railway material will be amply supplied * serial No. 19. -j twe | ve s toreships per month oi aver age dead weight 3,000 tons of 18 ft. draught are taken up for the run. Total maintenance of force is 27,000 tons and assuming 30 days round trip nine ships would suffice and I have added three for a margin. If we do not get more than nine ships per month we can clear ships much faster. You are best judge of the number of transports required for troops and some can bring 800 to 1,000 tons cargo also and should be specially used for stores which have been asked for urgently if this can be done without lowering draught beyond 18 ft. When the port is normal as referred to in my 818-2 ^ 1 will ask you to commence shipping in the monthly quantities detailed m this tele gram. It should be understood that there is no objection here to ships lying unworked, we have plenty of room in harbour but no more dry land behind piers and no more coolies and no more lighters and the waste of shipping is very serious when stores are sent too fast while the amount of bhoosa and wood sent is paralysing everything. Addressed C. G. S., repeated General Kirkpatrick in view of his visit to Bombay. Working copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., M.S.V., A.D. (Marine), G.S. (M.O. 1, M. O. 2). 21 Copy of a telegram No. Q .-2044, dated 20th June I9I6. F rom The Director of the Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. To The Quartermaster -general in India, Simla. Your 1262 -9 -W.S.t No more hay bhoosa or wood will be shipped until fur ther notice. The two storeships now t Not reproduced. loading are ''Windsor Hall ' and ' War- turm ' and will sail on 20th and 24th. Twelve ships will be required for military Ctnrpc; for Force ' D ' ignoring all railway ships nine working and three reserve V \T ' Chanda,' ' Itaura, * |' Moora. ' ' Nizam, ' ' Ozarda.' - Sofala,' ' Varzin,' ' Braunfels,' ' Windsor Hall,' ' Warturm, ' ' Havildar,' ' Grac chus.' Of these ships seven are now detailed at 41 D.' Ships to be released ' Oolobaria ' and ' Umballa ' in Bombay and on their return 'Chindwara' due to-morrow 41 City of Glasgow' ' Islarda,' ' Itinda,' ' Orissa ' and ^ Clan Ogilvy.' Do you concur? Please inform me relative amount of tonnage required in future programme at Bombay and Karachi in order that ships may be correctly distributed.&gt;3 22 Copy of a telegram P., No. 864 -1-L. C., dated 27th June 1916. From-»-The Inspector General, Communications, Force ' D ' Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla, Following increase to tonnage for monthly maintenance will be necessitated by thearrivalof new Cavalry Brigade. Supplies 1,200 Ordnance stores, 50 Military Works, Total number of bottoms demanded should not be increased by above. _« . . This refers to my telegram 818-L. C # Not reproduced. r t t * j of 21 st June.* 23 Telegram No. 8i8-4i -L. C., dated 29th July 1916. (Despatched 9 A.M., received 5-45 A .M., 29th July 1916.) From—The Inspector General, Communications, Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. To enable us to get rid of your hired transports as promptly as possible strongly recommend that they should be reserved for small or urgent stores. Much time has been lost unloading engineer stores ' ^-Bankura ' as troopships unload midstream not go alongside wharves for supply ships. Another instance ' Muttra ' recently arrived with cargo, 330 tons previously reported actually had 600 tons petty stores. Congestion has been relieved, system which would be of great assistance is you should keep stores and supplies for supply ships with exception of stores urgently required and consignments intended for Mesopotamia and individuals. Transports will thus be manageable ; we will discharge into lighters or craft ana return as soon as possible. We shall then get stores urgently required ordered by telegraph after the word Mondharp ' as arranged in my 818.35-L. C. of 24th July and transports will not be delayed here. Working copy to Q .M .G. Copy to M .S.C. 24 Telegram P., No. 75853, dated 1st September I916. (Despatched 7-45 P.M.) From—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. To—The Inspector General, Communications, Basrah. t Not reproduced. Your 818 of August 30th.f Carrying coal for Railways is the use to which ' Isle of Mull ' is now being put. With regard to store ship programme corrections to my 72474, of 17th August for August sailings are as follows:— Sailed 34th from Kprachi ... ... ... *' Hartington.' „ „ „ Bombay ... ... ... ' Subedar.' „ 26th „ Karachi , Due to sail now from Bombay ' Warturm.' ' Braunfels.'&gt;4 Following sailings for September are proposed by D. R. I. M — From Karachi.'— ' jeddah ' to sail and Itinda ' „ „ ' lothcallingal Gulf Ports. aoth ' Sofala' „ „ '.Nizam' „ „ From Bombay :— ' Varzin' to sail ' Okhara ' ,• „ ' Moora ' „ „ ' Ozarda ' » » 24th T4th 18th 33nd 26th Owing to delay in departure of vessels from Basrah programme previously arrAnfed bv D R. I- M. had to be revised and present sailings are later than those previously arranged. It is also pointed out by D. R. 1. M. that unless ships ire discharged quicker at Basrah, sh.ps will have to be .mpressed m order to despatch o shfps in September and 10 or 11 in October, vide your 818 .10 -816, • Not reproduced. of 20th August. Please inform if there is any possibility ot discharge of vessels being speeded up and if not are the numbers of ships you ask for to be sent irres pective of those still being discharged at Basrah. Record copy to Q.M.G. Copy to M.S.C., G.S. (M.O. I, M.O.s). 25 Telegram No. 818, dated 5th September 1916. (Despatched u midnight, received 6 P.M., 6th September 1916 ) From— The Inspector General, Communications, Basrah. To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. • Serial No. m . Your 75853 September ist.t Will suffice if the same nine ships are kept on run and are returned filled bv vou as soon as we send them and more ships need not be taken up even ,f round trip takes more than one month. D. R. I. M. however should put on one extra ship in October making ten in all on the run. Am endeavouring to spec up unloading but you do not send my Porter Corps and 1 am struck (stuc ) up for labour. Working copy to Q. M. G. Copy to M.S.C., M.S.V., G.S. (M.O. i), A.D. Marine. / i6oJQMG»fio—13-g-i6-«GCBP Simla</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001c8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/132</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001c8</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/132</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Shipping and congestion of stores at Basrah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-09T00:13:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (13 folios)</extent><extent>The booklet has an index of contents (f 4), followed by the main sections on shipping and congestion of storeships at Basrah (f 5), then appendices of telegrams, numbered 1-25 (ff 6-11).</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: The volume also contains an original typed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to details of shipping and congestion of storeships at Basrah for the Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force, published by the Quarter Master General, Simlah, in 1916. The information is divided into two sections: shipping and congestion of storeships at Basrah and is annotated with relevant 'serial numbers'.An appendix includes twenty five telegrams relating to the logistics of moving troops and supplies (such as hay, bhoosa, wood, rice, fuel) from India to Basrah under different weather conditions. The correspondents in these telegrams include: the Inspector General of Communications, Basrah; Quartermaster-General in India, Simla; Chief of the General Staff, Simla.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Quarter-Master General in India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Basra</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><subject><topic>Supplies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x0001c8#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>