<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00005c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-07T13:12:17.703Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">M 0 V £• riubjecti Iranian rigiita or inspection and searcn of Arab cthowo* Iranian rU»it« of inspection and *e«ren under tne Arm* rraffio Cr,nT«it ion of 1SE5, the Mueeat Eroclsnat ion of 1898, and the Bruaeale Aot of 189C, ere *a»n»rl,ea in para graphs 4 - 7 of India office letter Bo.P.^.2430/33, dated tne 37tn April 1933, to tne Admiralty. briefly, they are that eo long as tne Arab principalities of tne ao not tnemaelTea accede or autnorise Hie »Jeety*e (lo»eri»ent to accede on tneir behalf to an inetruaait such as tne Arms Traffic Convention of 192&amp;, and ao long rs tr.etr vessels fly a flag which is not the flag of a High Contract ower, Iran appeare to nave no legal rights of inspection of suon vessels under the Convention, that it is possible tnat the aay retain uome rights of inspection under tne Sruesels (Slavery) Act of 1830, though the India Office doubt this, and tnat one nas (though stte nas shown no sign oi re- ■ is this) under tne Auseat Arms Proclawaticn of 1893, rights &gt;£ search of Auscat vessels on the High Seas. 3. The 3a nr a in and Kuwait Proolamat i.'ne of 30tn April 1393 an« 24ta May iOuO respectively (vile m letter ho.341-3, 'lated the «th April 1933) accord to Persian vessels tn# right of search in respect of the vessels of the notifying ^uler in Persian waters, Indian waters and the Kuler's o sn waters, not on the High Meae. fhes# Troolapiatioris are not liicely to oause any difficulty even if the Iranians realised that tnay taese ri^uta* 3. f ftave i*d t^o caa«» recently (ride correep^oUnce conriected /coimeotad #Uh B^y Printed letters 193-3 of tne 12tn Ketruery 1937, and No.252-1 of the 24th February 1937) of Interference with Dubai dhowe and a Kuwaiti dnow respectirely, on the high Seas. 4. there was no Jhroclaiaatian siwilar to tne above issued by Uubai or any other truoiai co&amp;et bnaiicns, and tne Kuwait proclamation was restricted to search in Kuwait, Indian and Iranian waters. The fact however that the Iranians mve a right of search of Muscat dnows on tne High Seas may g ire tne Iranians some excuse to bo&amp;ri vessels under tae cover of verify ing whether tne dhow is not a Muscati one. 5. I think therefore th&amp;s, subject to the vi^ws of tne Government of India, we should now ask tne Sultan of Muscat to cancel the Proclamation of 1&amp;38 and substitute for it an authority confined to His ?%jesty*s Ships, and, to round matters up, ask the Shaikhs of Kuwait and Bahrain to do likewise in respect of their Pro cl actions referred to in paragraph 2 above. sd. f.C.Powle. Buehlre. 36th February 1937CONFIDENTIAL. No ' C/70 of 1337. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the (JoYernment of India, hew Delhi. 3. The Senior haYal Officer, Persian Saif. 4. the Political Agent, Bahrain, y t&gt;. The Political Agent, haacat. y and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document /• v /Vy Office of the Political Readdent in the Persian Oulf, C&amp;aip, Bahrain. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, 12th KptlXt 1937. Reference to previous correspondence: Tehran telegram ho. 29 of 30th March 1937. Search of Dibai iho a b Iranian sloop.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 4fc4-S of 1367 • The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, Tne Political Agent, Bahrain* The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s), ov I yi. Mi 1 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated ,4th. t. Reference to previous correspondence: hesiaency Printed Letter No. £63-£, dated £4th March 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ! Subject. India Office Letter Iranian rignts of inspection No. P•E#£970/1937, aatec and search of Arab dhows* 11th May 1937 to Foreign Office.P.Z.^70/ 57. INDIA OFFICE*. Whitehall. llth May, 1^57. My aear Baggallay, Woula you Kinaly rtiler to Colonel Fowled letter to tne Government of Invia oaten the E4th Marcii, and Major Hay f s reply aated tne 14th April (copies of which were sent officially to the Foreign Office on the &amp;5ra April No. P.Z.EdOE/57 ana tne 6th May No. P.Z.2970/57) about tne Persian Governments rights of inspection ana search of Arab Dhows. You will have seen tnat the Resident suggests, ana tne Government of India agree, tnat tne Sultan of Muscat and tne Shaikhs of Bahrain ana Kuwait snould cancel tne existing proclamations which give Persian vessels rignts of search outside Persian territorial waters. If this suggestion, which seems prima facie sound, is adopted, I presume tnat tne repeal of the proclamations would have to be notified officially to tne Persian Govern ment - or at any rate tnat it would somenow come to tneir notice (tnere would not be mucn point in doing it otnerwise)^ You may therefore wish to inform Seymour of the proposal at tnis stage, in case he has any observations to offer. I am sending a copy of tnis letter to Seal. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) M.J. CLAUSON. H.L. BAGGALLAY, ESQ., FOREIGN OFFICE.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 521-S of 1937. y The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to (1) Tiae political Ag°nt, Muscat. ^ (2) Tue Political A^ent, Bahrain. (3) Tne Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). ^‘CY and i ICONFiDLO rj 1. RECORD X l'j JU. io 3 / &gt;a. No j H, B, W’S CONSUL a U; MUSCAT, British Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. Dated.tne..8tn.... J.uly. X937 Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter No.424-8 of tne 4tn June, 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Foreign Office Letter No.£04 Persian Governments rights (E &amp;747/1359/91) of tne ord of inspection ana search June, 1937, to His Majesty f s of Arab anows. Minister, Tehran.I transmit to you nerewitii copies of recent official ana semi official correspondence concerning a proposal made by tne Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf tnat His Majesty’s Government snoula invite tne rulers of Muscat, Koweit and Banrain to witnaraw tne Proclamations of 1898 anu 1900 whereby certain rights of search over the vessels of tne Ruler concerned are conferred on tne Persian Government ana publish in their stead proclamations confining tnese rigxits to his Majesty’s snips atone. The advisability of securxng tne cancellation of tne Muscat Proclamation was considered in 1988, ana it was then decided tixat there was little to oe gained by such action so long as tne Persian Government snowed no signs of being aware of tue rights accorded to them unuer tnat instrument. The position in tnis respect nas remained unaltered since 1^38 and I am inciineu to tninh tnat tne considerations wnich were ap licaoie then may be regarded as oeing applicable toaay, namely that as so n as tne Persian Government become aware of tne proclamations and appeal to them as justifying tneir nayy»s interference witn Muscati, Banraini ana noweiti anows, tnere would be gooa reason for cancelling them, out that until that happens there is nothing to ue gained by doing so, especially as His Majesty’s Government enjoy all tne rights they tnemselves require under tne Proclamations. Moreover a gratuitous notification to the effect tnat tne proclamations hau been cancelled might merely ieau to a st£riie controversy as to the/tne rignts of tue two parties in regard to tne arms traffic in tne Persian Gulf. Finally tnere is the point, to wnich tne Admiralty nave drawn attention tnat tne cancellation of tne Proclamations would, probably result in tile cancellation of tne Persian 'Firman” of 1897, oy which His Majesty 1 s Government were accorded rignts which might as '/.ell be Kept in reserve, even though tne possibility of tneir being aole to exercise t^em may be small. 6. I shall be glad to receive any observations you may nave to offer on Colonel Fowle’s proposal, and the present despatch. I am, with great truth and regard. Sir, Your most obedient Servant, Sd G.W.Rendel. (For tne Secretary of State)CONFIDENTIAL. 6i) No. b 05 -S of The Hon’ble the P&lt; litical Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 . Tilt Political. A^ent, Kuwait, ic. The Poiiti.c..l Aiciit, Baiirain, o. Tne Political A^ent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned Ref&lt; rence to previous correspondence : Foreign Office L'esp .ten No.£04 of tnc 5rd Juno, 1j67, to nis Majesty*s Minister, Tehran. (Busnire Printea Letter No.521-S dated tne 8th July 1037) Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. LcupciuCn No.is.oo oicitec. t*io oj st July 1 j 37, from nis Majesty's Ministei Tenran to Foreign Office. Subject. Iranian Government*s rights of inspection and search of AraD anows.V CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/248. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1# The Senior Ifeivai Officer, Persian Gulf, 2* The Political Agent, Bahrain* J 3. The Political Agent, Muscat* 4* The Political Agent, Kuv^eit* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). &gt;biTlCAV Cl nO D { loONFIDENTUL reOORD j { 1 1 11 IL-e. - l ? i'rr Nt Office of the Political Resident H, B, !'8 naNSU^ 1 •: ^ ' 1 in the Persian Gulf, t l ' 1 ' ' ~~ Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Foreign Office despatch No.3 968/162/91, dated 30th Mfrroh 1938 to the Admiralty, with Foreign Office despatch No.5 of Gth January 1938 to Subject. Persian interference with Arab dhov/s « Tehran.E 968/162/91 OITriCTS, 3 .W# 1* 30th March 1938, Sir, 71th reference to your letter ^*03427/37 of the 1th September 1937, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit to you, to be laid before the lord Commisioners of the Admiralty, the accompanying copies of correspondence with His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, in the course of which Mr. Seymour mrkes certain observations regarding the attitude to be adopted by the Commanding Officers of His Majesty's ships in case of Persian interference with Arab dhows. 2. As Their lordships will see from paragraph 3 of Mr. Seymours despatch, he considers that any incident involving one of Hi a Majesty’s ships and an Iranian vessel, in waters which, although beyond the three mile limit, are claimed by the Iranian Government as territorial, would give rise to great bitterness, and that it is therefore preferable to avoid tiic risk of any such incident occuring. * 3. lord Halifax is aware that interference by a Persian ship with an Arab dhow is more likely to take place in waters near the Persian coast and an oral assurance has, moreover, already been given by the Persian Government that Persian warships will not molest Arab vessels in Arab territorial waters or on the high seas. At tne same time, while fully conscious of the ill-feeling which would result if one of His Majesty’s ships were to take measures involving a Persian /vessel The Secretary. of the Admiraltyvessel within the six mile limit, His Lordship realises that the effect produced on the Rulers of the Arab coast if one of His Majesty’s ships failed to protect a dhow in waters which, as the Arab Rulers Jcnow perfectly well, His Majesty’s Government do not regard aa Persian territorial waters, might be equally unfortunate. It is, moreover, probable that Persian susceptibilities would be outraged in whatever waters the incident occurred. 4. Lord Halifax is therefore of the opinion that the balance of advantage lies in including waters outside the but within the six mile limit, three mile limit,^in the scope of the proposed Admiralty instructions. 5. His Lordship is, however, anxious that, in the issue of these instructions the following points should be emphas ised: (a) That the instructions must be carried out (as he has no doubt Their Lordships intend) with utmost tact and discretion, and force be used only in the very last resort. (b) Thit in all cases, and not only in arms cases, His Majesty’s ships shall inform the Persian vessel that they are themselves prepared to verify the flag and the papers of the dhow in question, to see, if the circumstances warrant it, that it proceeds to its alleged destination, and, if there is any prima facie reason to suspect thkt an offence has been committed, to ensure that the offence is duly investigated and punished. /66 * Lord Halifax io,however, most anxious that every effort should be made, compatible with the proper performance of their duties by His Majesty’s ships, to avoid an incidence in any ;vaters of the Persian Gulf, more especially in the present time of unsettled international relations and having regard to the importance of the oil supplies derived from Persian territory, 7. His Lordship therefore urges that the instructions issued to the Commanding Officers of His Majesty’s ships should make this point abundantly clear and that the general Admiralty instructions should be accompanied by further (possibly secret) instructions to the effect that His Majesty’s Government are anxious to avoid an incident within six miles of the Persian coast even more thun elsewhere on the high seas, and that although the same action must, if the necessity inevitably arises, be taken within those limits as in the rest of the Gmlf, commanders of ships should, if possible, contrive to avoid situations arising in which their ships are likely to be upon the scene when a dhow is stopped by a Persian vessel within the six mile limit. The simplest way of avoiding such aituationsls not to enter the six mile limit, and it is presumably usually possible for His Majesty’s ships, except in one or two places where the main sea routes may pass near Persian islands, not to do so at all except when going to ot from Persian ports. t oP.&lt;i.2268/1958 No. D* PCR 75 ISN 0 ??I 3 S' 'J.'t.l. I f \ 6 th January 1938. (3 7391/1339/91) 3ir, i y . / 1 .!*/ X/ /V 39 /i | \ i ' 1 J : A i I \ yith referenoe to your despatch No. 295 (543/2/37) of the 51st July last regarding Persian interference with Arab dhows, I transmit for your information the accompanying copies of correspondence with the \dniiralty as to the attitude to be adopted in the event of such incidents recurring. The India Office concur in the views expressed by the Admiralty. 2. In view of the oral assuranceugiven to you by the Persian Ministry for Foreign Affairs that Persian warships have been instructed not to molest Arab vessels in future either in Ai* b territorial waters or bn the high seas, I agree that the question of a forma 1 warning to be addressed to the Persian Government may be left in abeyance, to be re considered if a further incidence should occur. This does not, however, affect the main question of the principle arising out of your despatch No. 147 of the Slat April last, namely how far one of His Majesty’s ships ought, in fact, 1 0 go in order to protect an Arab dhow from interference. 3 . as you will see, the admiralty consider it important that in the Persian Gulf, as elsewhere, His ^jesty’s ships should have clear authority to use force if this is necessary in order to prevent interference with any British or British protected vessel, not only as regards Arab territorial waters, y . / /v 39 /;; 1) 1 ' I J : A j I \ /but also H.J. Beymour F.sq., C.M.G etc.» etc. 9 etc. 9 Tehran.I but also aa regards the high aers and waters claimed by/Persia as Persian territorial waters, but not admitted ns such by'\ His I^jeaty’s Government; and they suggest the issue of ne* instructions to this effect, with the addition of certain provisions to cover the possibility that a Persian warship might attempt to justify its action by alleging that an Arab dhow vtfio engaged in the prms traffic. 4# Subject to your further observations, I am disposed to consider that the Admiralty view of this problem is the correct one and to concur in the issue of instructions on the lines which the Admiralty propose, on the following conditions:- (a) Thu$ it shall be emphasised (as it .nay be srfely assumed that the Admiralty intend) that the instruct ions must be carried out with the utmost tfct and discretions and force used only in the very last res ort« (b) That in all cases, and not only in arms cages, His Majesty’s ships shell inform the Persian vessel that they are themselves prepared to verify the flag and the papers of the dhow in question, to see, if the circumstances varrant it, that it proceeds to its alleged destinrtion, and if there is sny prima facie reason to suspect that an offence has been committed, to ensure that the offence is duly investigated and pun iahed. 5. With regard to the particular point about the action to be taKen in waters claimed by the Persian Government as territorial waters, but not admitted as such by His Majesty’s Government, I am advised that in legal proceedings regarding a /cl*ira t o*'''*•'* clBi« to territorial rights over waters more than t^iree miles \ from the Persian coast it would in all probability be found that s (1) If His Majesty’s Government were plaintiffs before an international tribunal asking for judgment to the effect that Persia is not entitled to axcereiee territorial right in waters more than three miles from the Persian coast. His Majesty’s Government would lose their case, (2) If the Persian Government were plaintiffs asking for judgment to the effect that His Majesty's Govern ment must recognise a Persian claim to the excercise of territorial rights in waters more than three miles A. from the Persian coast, the Persian Government would lose their case. . \ The law is in fact uncertain and it is likely that the litigant who had to prove his case would fail. In any proceedings arising out of the action of one of His Majesty’s ships in preventing Persian vessels from operating against Arab vessels in ^waters lying between three and six miles f^ora the Perbian \ coast, Persia would be the plaintiff and Hie Majesty's Government could probably regard the outcome of the proceedings with equanimity, V 6 . The Admiralty and the India Office agree, in the light of the information contained in the despatch No.295 of the 31at July, and especially in view of the fact that the Persian Government seem to be unaware of the provisions of the Muscat proclamation of 1898, that it would be inadvisable openly to cancel the proclamations of the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait and the Sultan of Muscat, I am, with great truth and regard, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Sd, lacy Baggallay. (For Nevdlle Chamberlain)</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00005c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/317</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00005c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/317</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/20 Naval and Shipping: Infringement of Muscat territorial waters by Persian Navy'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-23T22:08:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (23 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order, from the front to the rear.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 25, these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the question of Iranian rights to search foreign vessels outside their territorial waters. The papers cover the report of such an incident involving dhows from Dubai and the interdepartmental discussion of what rights the Iranians have and what action should be taken should such a thing occur again. Correspondence comes from officials at the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the British Legation in Tehran, the India Office, and the Foreign Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Territorial waters</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00005c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>