<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00039d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:42:51.458Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">To. &amp;s 4 - Of 1003. 'f) (16 British Residency and Consulate-General. ,rftiT Busnire, 1 / March 1003. 4 ^ v T^t Please refer to youi' No.73 dated 2nd March (re ceived 11th) regarding Mr.Ardeshir*s resignation. The Resident wired to Foreign on 12th March 1003, sug gesting that as he is quite unsuitable for the post lis resignation may be accepted. Your letter under reference was forwarded to Fo- h e reign under cover of our A 342 dated 15th March 1003, and we will let you Imow result at once for informa tion of Mr. Ardeshir. Major S.G.Knox, I.A., Political Agent, \ P. T. O.Since writing above we have received a telegram from Foreign saying that they are looking oat for a successoi' for Mr. Ardeshir. It seems that his right to give only a month*s notice is not admitted^at any rate pending receipt of our letter forwarding his application. In any case he should not be allowed to leave pending the arrival of his successor, aid if necessary you can retain his pay for March to keep a hold.;.over him. ^ *0 &lt; k ^ JM la F- 4 -fl T—(For Approval). Political IlLonyr.rirrT, Pi.mihtiM Guim . iCcTHj-txA? Dated _ 2-0 (nU~ \goCJ. U chute 2 °ta Oot«ib«r J^ist &amp; line to *ak wnat is tna rdtarn of ^erwanjl Gaadar my aoootmtani aotln^ baareln • vlrsa ^naain tells mo that lie nears Lobe £ruy to iahraln h # 0* is or h^o applied for an extra three $ A one .as leave and If It Is not granted will be returning to Bahrain in about proposod abo H*G. at tne real three weeks whloh I snprose will mean Gaidar ooming baok here about the 16th November and ^irza nnsain going back to ^ashire* I have not spoken to ray H*0. Fernandes about i 1 ; , bat would t not be a good opportrnlty to fix up the cringe eon«er. latod lx months ago , viz D f Mello the bandar Abbas accountant ooming re , Gaidar going to 1 andatnAbbas , and ina nnflialn return* »lng to hushlre* Personally I don’t maoh oare which of taem somos here 9 but I think D’liello would be the b3st it ho a*3 not oaang'd his mind about it , as my olerks live In eaon other pookets in the quarters here and I don’t think Fernandes and aidar love eaoh othar particularly • Mina nuaain also ae a rothor of ^iria *anonod the late !• Agent would bo better out of the plaeo • You might let me know as Mlrsa ^usaln s ya if as Is to o back soon to i^shlre he would like to make arrangements in vanoe for a house to live in there when he arrivs* sorry to worry but it takes timed to fix things up in these parts without a telegraph# ad■■ P.A I have been given to understand that Mr Sequelra will be retiring earl^ next jear and Ghandj will pro bably wiWA succeed him. I therefore respectfully beg to ts v/ 'lcasxt* request that you will kindly write a D.O.^on m w behalf reccomending me for Mr Ghand., *s place. I# understand the post will not be offered to ar\, one in the iiesidencj office. I have now put in over 5 years* service at Koweit and I am desirous of getting a transfer mainly on account of m^ wife's ill-health and other private affairs.I shall be ver^ grateful if ..ou would do all ^ou can for me for which act of kindness I shall ever remain grateful. I put up m^ testimonials for favour of perusal. vczaT You will see from them I was one of the onl u two candidates * for the Head Clerk's post at Muscat when that post fell vacant permanently now 4T ear/ ago. I was recommended by the Resident for the post without m., applying for it and I lost the chance owing to Major Knox's absence for over a month in camp and application remained in the office. If Major Knox were in Koweit I feel sure I would have got that place as Major Gre^ had once before writ-oen to the Resident about me Major Knox was in England on A sick leave*-I could not be spared. Besides this Both the Resident and Major Trevor were good enough to offer me the Bushire Treasury Accountantship twice but as that appoint ment did not give me any promotion I refused the offer so kindly made to me. Moreover Major Knox advised me to stick to this post and said that I would have betuer chances of promotion later and he would see to it. That officer is now away and my only support is w our kindself in whom I look for /all my future prospects.This is the only chance^that will give me an^ propomotion in Gulf and I therefore humb^ re- -quest ^ ou to kindly help me •Political Agency, Koweit. The 11th December 1909 • H&gt; dear Trevor, Fernandez, Head Clerk, tells me that he understands Mr Sequeira will be retiring early next year, his post being filled up by Mr Ghandy, thus leav- -ing the Residency Office Superindentship to be tilled up. I don’t know how far this is correct but Fernandez wants to be a candidate for uhe post as it is one of the few which would give him any solid promotion. fou know his service and the man, so I don’t send his tes- -timonials, which are very good and I should like to recommend him strongly 7 for the billet as I think he would make an admirable Superintendent, being tactful, quick, very careful and painstaking, reliable, and with a good memory. I stand to lose by recommending him -self, but I should not like to stand in his wa„ and he has missed one chance of promotion already, besides which his work shows him to be of the t^pe of thoroughly reliable clerk who is worth promoting. He has also ta&amp;en the trouble to get naturalized as a British subject which is I uhink a point in his favour. there I am to look for an Head Clerk if ^ou think of taking Fernandez I don’t know ^et, out ^ou ma^ have some suggestions. I enjoyed my time in the desert A.l. Yours sincerely, sd/- Y. H. I. S hake spear. To Major A.?.Trevor, I.A., First Assistant Resident, (In charge Residency) Bushire.10 9 . 1910 37 Lt tijar Birdwood, Re our conversation about moving clerks It was rather hurried but I gathered you wanted my 2nd Clerk D'Mello to act as H«C. at Mohammerah, sending me in his place the junior clerk at Maskat. I think I told you I didn’t care about Mirza Husain coming here for several reasons smd that I was not keen about letting D'Mali) go unless it would improve his chances of being found a billet when the reductions took effect. My H.C. tolls me the junior msui at Mas- -kat is one D*Costa, and if so that will sili t ve ly we 11 he re, as- m^ c 1 e rks ' quarte rs necessitate theie living in each other's opo- -ckets and so no Mohamedan pardah families are suitable. M^ second clerk D'Mello is quite wil- -ling to go to. Mohamme rah if it will improve his chances of evading reduction but not otherwise. He has acted H.C. at Bandar Abbas twice for 6 months each time I believe so should suit ViIson. i Yours sincerely , Ed/- Y, H. I. SHAKESPEARBritish Residency and^onsulate-renera 1 . . rr • .^Bushire, Jjfi September 1P10. '» Na 'A / ; ) VJ ' 3$ 5 ( r r Please see your demi-official letter of September 1Cth regarding The man re are sending you is nob B’Costa i.'Ut cur acLing 2nd Treasury Clerk recently returned from Muscat. I thought you understood that when the proposal ’./as made. I:is name is Syed Ghularc Kussein. He is married but is not taking his family with him. He is due for re duction at the end of the financial year. De Mello’s going to ohammerah rill certainly improve his (De Mello f s) chances of evading reduction though he must of course understand that no guarantee can be given. 0 Is U-uCS • ‘■5 H [uuL lAjcal’ ? dOf a kuw-A-- [/fZi UsA**.\|0 *x&gt; British K*aldonoy, auahlro, Q 3 -Saptar.bar 1910• 'Gce^r me . esidant dlracta me to raquaat that you ffill ba good enough to forward rapll OB to the yarloua quarlaa detailed on the accompanying liata. Separate forma shoulcl be submitted for each cleric and i.irza in office, the word -nil- being placed opposite such question# txa do not concern you# 1 ““ alB0 to **• quest that in future all oorre- apondence regarding cleric, and Hirzaa, such a. the diaouaaion of their merit., appointment, transfer and relief etc, should be marled confidential and addresaed in double cover, to the tfirst Assistant Hesident by name. Mo correspondence of the above nature should on any account be allowed to go into the general office. Captain W•H.I. Shakespear, I.A., Political Agent, Koweit.Confidential* 1* Ai&amp;ma 2, Age 3* Nationality &amp; place of origin* 4* Date of first entry into Crovernment service. 5* Date of first employment under Residency* 6* Designation of previous appoint ments if any under Residency* 7. Designation of present ap pointment • 8. Pay of present appointment. (Maximum and ninlMnn) 9* Pay actually drawn. 10. House rent allowance* 11. State if free quarters allowed. 12* Telegraph allowance* Id* Meteorological allowance* 14* River gauge allowance. 15* Shroff allowance* 16. Amount of exchange compensation. 17. Local allowance. 18* Any other allowance or emolument not shown above.Oonfld3ntial» !• iknowladg# of typowriting. (a) Speed. (b) Accuracy. 8« Knowledge of linglialx. (a) Reading. (b) Writing. (c) Colloquial. (d) Capacity for putting up a good office note. (a) capacity for drafting. 3* xuiowledge of Persian. (a) Reading. (b) Writing. (o) Colloquial. 4. xoiowledge of Arabia. (a) Reading. (b) Writing. (c) Colloquial. 5. Knowledge of any other language. (j. Aptitude and anount of experience in Accounta work.Yours of 4 J oh insfanu regarding reappropriauion sua’oenenus. Ivliau happened was uhis. Sequeira when checking your figures hhoughh uhere was a mistake and made some correchions. Afherwards, he however, a found your ligures were right, so ha,d the statements re-typed in the Treasury Gifice. The despatching clerk who was not aware oi this noticed when sending the letters off that there was no sig nature and made the pencil remark to which you rightly take objection. A B.O. letter of explanation to ought of course A have been sent you at the time. Sequeira meant to do so but forgot about it. 1 am glad you brought the matter to my notice. / Captain W.H.I. Shakespear, I.A., Political Agent, KOTCEIT(g&gt; xi &lt;y British Residency and Consulate-General. Bushire, October 1910. C‘ Your demi-official letter of October ISth. I understand that Syed Ghulam Husein did not go down by boat to Fao as the 'Lewis Belly' was not expected to be there the day he was at Mohammerah, it being the week the slow mail went direct to j£g.xxKh± Koweit. He was not able to get a boat to take him to Koweit. Syed Ghulam Husein has not been provided with a service book as he does not as yet hold a permanent appoint ment under the Residency. Captain V/.H.I .Shakespear, Political Agent, K o w e i t.DR APT—(For Approval). ABj^ncy, Political Kn^^i t No. -J9o Dofni-Official CONPIPENTIAL Dated My d&lt;j*r Birdwood, ..i^r ^ T I had a lottor from my lato 2nd Olork , D’Niollo, f rom Mrhaimraorah with a moan abont being ^rednedd^ when the time came • He ayo Wiloon made him onqniro rom Seqneira if he intended coming back for gcod to Mohammearah or if he he wao going in for an ont ide job. I t aopearo that Seqniera in going to retnrn to Mchammearah a t th^ end of hi l.avc and ac h. hao i//46/ 10 Pensionable ervice he i not likely to chnck Go I guppogo O f Mollo will then revert to hi pe ye are vt employ, rnanent P’oot here of 2nd Clerk, nnleoa yon have got Gone other permanent job for him from which he won’t be^rodnood' in April. If h^ doe come back to mo here I hope yon will keep hto in mind for retention if poaelble-- he ie worth abont 5 of the P.roian Goolio I have now or my friend Mirz^ lla ain. I rhonld lx very glad to have him back bnt I chonld prefer the boy getting settled for good and o if yen have got oome decent Permanent billet for him I don’t mind bearing no ith the representative of Persian 5?ayido whom I have now!! | Yonr? finoeroly. w. H. T. ^?hake pearCONFIDENTIAL. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, fde a± Bushire,24th January 1911, '&lt;&amp; RECEIPT c&gt; .^vy I am desired by Captain Birdwood K (who is sick at present) to reply to your demi-official letter of the 17th instant, about the Second Clerks* The safest arrangement will be to show Mr.D^ello in your books from the date on v/hich he was relieved by Se^ira at Mohammerah, the Residency squaring up Ghulam Hussein’s pay from the 1st to the 12th instant inclus ive. A copy of this reply is being sent to Captain Haworth for information. \n&gt; v fPl'L'VJ S^LAA U A ’ * 'yjt Captain I.Shakespear, I.A., V lit I Pd^itical Agent, \ K O W E I T.14 My dear Haworth, I enclose herewith an application by ny 3nd Clerh, Mr, D'Mello, for a billet in the Imperial Bank at Mohammerah, He is good at his work and accurate, but there does not seem to be any chance of his being kept on anywhere in the Gulf offices when the reductions come into force on the 1st April, You will know more than I do about the new billet in ^ our office as 2nd Clerh, but Mr, D'Mello does not seem keen.about it if it is not pensionable, in which I do not blame him ! V.ould. you please hand on the application to the Manager with any recommendation ^ ou can add, For my part I have known Mr, D'Mello for the last 5 years and had him working ’under me off and on a good bit of that and can recommend him as hard working, attentive and accurate in his work and of good character. Yours smcrrely, bh/- f.A H. I. Shake spear.P„A, I have just* heard (h, lash siovr mail) hhah the Head Clerkship of the Llaskat Agency will fall vacant owing to the present incumbent (Mr Mukerji) going elsehwere on transfer. I have also heard that Major Trevor has written t j the Resident consulting him as to Mr Mukerji*s successor,, I should be ver^ grateful, Sir, if you would very kindly write a D,0/. to Col. Cox and also to Major Knox who will shortly releive Major Trevor at Maskat about me. You are aware,Sir, that I w T as one of the onl^ 2 candidates recommended by the Resident for that post when it fell vacant in 1908 but just at that time Major Knox happened to be absent on tour m the desert and my application re- -mained in the Office and in the meantime Mr. Sequaira pushed on Mr Mukerji although he is my junior. I was then offered the Mushire T reasury Ac c ountantship (Mr Mukerj i * s post? Major Trevor^as that post did not give me any promotion Major Knox advised me to stick to Kuwait and told me that I would have better opportunities for promotion later on if I re- -mained here. In the whole of Persian Gulf offices. Sir, there are only 2 appointments which carr^y any promotion viz: Maskat ana Bushire Residency Superintendent ship. The latter post , as y ou are aware / is comin^unaer reduction now and there will remain^only one post to which one can aspire for promotion and that is the Head Clerkship of the Maskat Agencym I have explained to you my case once before and y ou were good enough to 'recommend, me to Major Trevor^then the P.A^for the Supdt's post m Bushire office. I send you copies of these papers in case you may wish toXT cr\ refer to them, I also send ^ ou a cop w of Maj Trevor's D«,0,to Major Knox offering me the Bushire Treasury Accountantship and my appli- - cation for Mas hat post in 1908 which was too ,0,1 3 late to be sent in as you will see from Major Knox's remarks thereon. This time too when I hear the same post is again going to fall vacant you are miles awa^ and I fear that if I am late this time too I ma w have the mis fortune of losing a Bnd chance and that will be perhaps for man^ years to come* Entreating you^bir^ for your kind support and re c omme n dawions.&lt;@ 1 ° * Kis Mrjesty ? b Consulate for Arabistan, Mohanmerah, 4th, Haroh 1911 ,&gt; 4&gt; My dear Sha'^estjear, / I enclose a copy of Mr. Dalton’s letter to ne stating he is willing to tr&gt;e on Mr. D'Hello on Rs. ISO a month if he joined at once. Will you kindly therefore let me know if Mr. D'Hello is willing to join the Bank on that salary. Yours sincerely, To Captain W. H. I. Shake spear, I. .1. Political Agent,The Imperial Bfir.k of Persia, Mohr me rah, 4th. J^arch 1911. My dear Haworth, i'lany thanks for your letter of H4th. February encloc- ing an application from Mr. L.11.D*Hello in .luwait for a post in the Banh here. He is mistaken in the remuneration I an pre pared to offer him but I could tafe him on Rs. 120 per mensem if he can come along at once. Would you be so hind as to advise Captain Shahespear to that effect and as': him to ar range for Hr. D'Hello’s transfer here as soon as possible. Yours sincerely. True Copy, Head Clerh. H.M.’s Consulate, Mohammerah.KXXKZX Bushlre. 14th Maroh IS11 . ^SylzJZ^ s^ One of our clerks io shortly going on 6 months leave and ire are looking out for someono to replaoe him during that period It has occurred to us to offer the appointment to your 2nd clerk De Hello instead of breaking newjf ground with another « Both yourself and Wilson have spoken well of him and we should be glad to keep him on in the Gulf if it is possible* If ^Ke reduction scheme is given effect to 4R* will be thrown out of employment either from the beginning of the financial year or from such date as the new soheme comes into force* n***' /tjc It is suggested therefore that i&amp;^ttB&amp;iko should come over here as soon as our clerk goes on leave but to show hiny until the new scheme comes into forc^ on the Koweit establishment in the same way as was done when he went to Mahomerah *« After the reduotion scheme comes into force^ he would be shewn^ until the permanent incumbant returned X from leave^ on our books as holding an acting appointment thus giving him a slightly longer period in Govt: employ and more time to look around him for a new billet* I am to enquire ^whether you see any objection to the above proposals . They would of course^prejudice De Hello’s chancas as regards Mahomerah in the event of a second clerk being eventually sanctioned fnb that post*DRAFT—(For Approval). Accnoy, Political Kuwait Gonficdntial To, No D/0 Dated V Z 1 from the First Asst Resdt, BU^HTRE. My dear Birdwood , In contimiation of my hasty D/c desert abozit yoTir taking on D'Mello in a leave vacancy in the Residency Office • I fc,ot back here on Saturday and find that *Mcllo has come to the conclusion that the Mohammcrah Bark billet has more chance of permanency abo^it it and has decided to take it . T am lotting him have leave for the purpose and sun osc rn'iist carry on with one clerk myself in cor sequence. He t;ets Rs 120/- a month from the Bank so I don’t think T can exactly blame him for freezing on to something solid while it is a;oin£ # In haste Yrs sincerely. W,H,'I, shakespearNo.3389 of 1910. British Residency 5? Consul ate-General. /?0 Bushire 27th December 1910. Do The Political .Agent, - L £ i I jir, T'.'ith reference t,o ^our letter No.673» ated the 5th December 1910, reporting the departure n t.he afternoon of the 2nd instant, of Assistant Surgeon Nur Mohamad Rahim-ut-ullah on 3 mont.hs tnd 17 da u s privilege leave, I am dir-cted to 'orm ■ ou that he will not be entitled to an„ reave allowance uirless he is confined in Govenment service. His engagement was temporal subject to termination b^ six months notice on either side, fie thus comes under the category of a-i off serving under contract and leave allowance is therefore inadmissible under Article 196(1) of the C.b. Regulation.. If, however, the Assistant Surgeon wishes to continue in Government service and to ce confirm- _ e d, his best course will be to submit an appli- -cation to jou in that sense, which „ ou might recommend to the Resident if you consider that . . v,-- served satisfactorily and that the applicant haa se^veu ha confirmed. I have etc., sc/- L.Birdwood, Captain, First Assistant Resident. 5No. o Kuwait, lOtii I larcti 1911. To The Political Agent, Kuwait. Sir, 1 beg moat huiubly ani respectfully to 1 ^y before you the follovirlng few lines for your kind consideration and favour of forwarding to tne tro- -ner authorities 1 was appointed in the luonth of July, 1908, as JvTe lical Officer to the Political Agent, Kuwait, on the stae terms and the same scale of pay as As- -sistant Surgeons in Government service in Iniia with only this difference that there was a proviso in my letier of appointment that my r service was tenr* -poriiy and sublect to termination by six months* notice on either siie. After having served in that ■ ost for nearly ?4‘ years 1 applied for privilege leave to go to In- -dia to see my ? family ani it was graciouslj^ granted to me. 1 thought that the privilege leave of 3 months ant 17 days thus sanctioned to me woul i be con site red as such and that 1 would get full leave allowance for the period I wts on leave. It was only unter this impression that 1 availed myself of the privilege leave sanctioned to me. 1 have been, however, informed to my' surprise by the Political Resident that my service comes under the category of an officer serving unxer a contract ant that, therefore, I am not entitled to any leave allowance unless 1 am confirmed in Government service. If this be so I beg most respectfully to request the favourfavour of iour ooixfinuing me in (iovemJiien^ ijervice from Uiie of appoinWent* 1 beg to add unVu uhe trovammeno rta.3 no u bean pm, 'oo an^ axorv expeniiuure for gauxing a lo- -ouiu uenana in luy rlaoe for une uiiiie i «rag abaam on leave 30 » the &lt;K&gt;vemiueni will lose nothing 05 granting me mjr leave allowance. I beg furtner to ait that almost all trivate iniivi tuala or com’n aniea who eng age men for being sent out to foreign countrie 3 for long periods -to grant/, their servants leave with goo i allowanoes to go hume ani see tneir families at certain fixed in- -tervals. oovarnmem treats its iervmts witn more iniulgence ant kinlness than 'private comhariiee; so, 1 do not see why 1 should be so harshly iealt with as not to get any leave allowance. Trusting that you will oe ^ind enough to take all these facts into your consideration ant s anction the &lt; rant of leave allowance to me oy con- -fiming me in my uoat. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd/- ci.M. rielimatullah, L.M &amp; S., Assistant Surgeon to tne Political Agent, huwait./~N DRAFT—(For Approval). ly Political /Wi/sIAKj// No a -13 (j?ONPIDRNTlAL n 1 Dated »th A; ril IP It r9o of the 27 th Deoember 1910 , from your Piist Ass ny address rclatinc, to Assistant-^^rfc on Ji6fi6^/N?:r RahmatTillah f s leave allowances* 2. ir. ■Political ■‘''‘esidmt, BU^HIRE. I have the honour to invite a reference to lotltcr ^o istant to Mahomed After the AS8i8tant-Snrs;con had left Kuwait it J&amp;V/ ^jecame apparent that he would probably not be entitled to any MUtitiUHU leavc-allowances under the terms of his agree ment with Government * in which there is no clause knent ^// leave * and on the fact being communicated to him he *c joined ^fter availing himself of 2 months 6 davs leave. of which x have t *1. He has since submitted an a^T lication to* W enclose a copy * to be confirmed in Government service fro-^m allowance c i&lt; ! ; he date of his appointment and so secure his leave xje f r ospc o tive ly. * Art 196 (l) Civil Service Regulations notes see m^ to ap ly (to ^^.e re Acept in the final note ^ In cases in which the cn is not terminated leave may be granted for a period U* / with its sent case, gage me nt not e accc % :■ pay 11 * for ding siA months and on allowances not /cccding hal the Asst-Surgcon did not proceed on sick leave • £ • With regard to his application for permanent employ -rcent T would observe that ijshould not feel justified in rc- u- r T ' s 638 “— IfcCa -commending on 'he ground ofyhavin/g ' DAhibi ted any special ability T, # Presumably his/qualificatiomc^ 12 , 000 - 7-08 A——— Confidential No. fib# of 191 British Residency anq^Consulate General^ Bushire, the O 191/( * A copy of the accompanying letter is forwarded, with compli ments, to the Political Agent, Koweit, for information with reference to his letter No 13 C dated 4th April 1911. From the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Se cretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department No /lU-lo .. dated 30th April 1911. S 2300 — i,ooO' 4 -icS ' (/ No ro huh of 1911. British Residency and Consulate-General, Buehire, ^^April 1911. 8 Lieut-Colonel P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C.I.3., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The Honourable Lieut-Colonel Sir Henry McMahon,K.C.I.K.,C.5.1., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Sir, 1 have the honour to refer to my letters Nos 2994 of 6 th November and 3372 dated 23th December 1910 re garding the grant of privilege leave to Nur Muhammad Rahiffi-ut-ullah Merchant, Assistant Surgeon attached to the Koweit Agency. On being informed that his engagement being of a temporary nature leave allowance was therefore inadmiss ible to him under Article 196 (i) of the Civil Service Regulations, he out short his leave and rejoined on 9th February . He now submits an application of which I en close a copy requesting that Government will be pleased to confirm him in his present appointmentaand sanction the payment to him of his allowances for the period of his absence. The Political Agent was absent in the interior at the time the Assistant Surgeon made his application and was unable to deal with it until his return, and I discussed the Assistant Curgeon’s case with him on ray recent visit to Koweit. The Government of India are aware that the Pahrein American ■American Mission have recently obtained the concurrence of Sheikh Mubarek and ourselves to the location of Dr Bennett or other Medical Missionary at Koweit, and Captain Shakespear informs me that, probably owing to Dr Bennett’s presence, little use has been made of late of our dispensary by the inhabitants of Koweit. The political advantage of attaching an Assistant Surgeon to our Agency thus disappears and we only have to consider the needs of our Agency and the question of quarantine. In the former regard, I think the needs of our Agent and his establishment right conveniently be looked after by Dr Ben nett or his successor and in this Captain Shakespear concurs, but as to quarantine, it seems hardly expedient, ©non if he were willing to undertake them, that the duties such as they are should be performed by the doctor of the Mission. On the whole seeing that from the political point of view the Assistant Surgeon has ceased *o be of much value and from the quarantine point of view the future status of Koweit is a matter of some uncertainty, I am of opinion that it would be better not to confirm the Assistant Surgeon in his appointment for the present. On the other hand, I think fctesfc it would be a hardship to deprive him of his allowances for the period of his absence, and I trust that the Government of India will be pleased to sanction the disbursement o* them especially as ho substitute was employed. I have etc, (£d) P. Z. Cox, Lt-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf»no ^ r • v 'copy of A Derci-Off icial letter dated the 30th Anf;MBt I9li from the Political Resdt Persian Gnlf to Capt W # H.I. Shakes -pear , P*A* K--await. Mjr dear Shake spear. Please see the accompanying papers in original, regarding ^r Gazdar* I believe yovi do not approve of him and wo'ald not w elcoroe him at Ka^ait , b'at we do not seem to have any r ecord of yonr views, and it is possible I am mistaken* Will yon kindly send me a memorandum regarding him, m entioning if possible snch *f yonr vie-ws as yon wovild be p repared to father officially, Yonrs sincerely, P# ^# 00 x.# P .S, Kindly retnm this as I have kept no copy. Accompaniments, Application from Mr Gazdar for Head-clerkship o f Rnwait dated Karachi 25th Jnly 1911, Demi-Official fro Capt Biscoe to Capt Birdwood recommends - ing the application »OFFICE. NOTE. /ww ul i Mr Gazdar oar^e t~ Kuwait fan the Political Agency /~N beine; firbt eQtablnshed^ \/w*k as Second Clerk ft Copy- -ist . He reiriindd nntil the end of May ^909 when /Vcuvi^* v*ul he mBiwin/ to Bahrain* Dnrinfc; his tire in Kuwait his work was satisfactory C*sC(l Cu^ClA. i\ /W as ry predeces or'recordhis f;ood opinion in ©rders^ and I had no failt to f^ind d-arine; the ronth that he worked 'ander rce^ However, I do not think it will be altogether an adf -vantage that he shonld ret-arn to Kawait and for the ; following: reasons. (a) In Jlecerber 1905 a complaint was preferred a- -e;ainst him for harbonrinf: a slave g;irl in his quarters. It is almost certain that the complaint was false an^d ^&lt;n+Z{jLl£ io 'tUitf Csu^diiAscinx sltch investif?:ation as was possible )n*i' ' ~ft^T CL tlvtzuZCy (rt. Cl (b) Mr Gazdar is a Parsee faith wonld class m. him amongst Kuwaitis as an infidel • In my opinion i^. (ffylcrvn u*Y/ S will be a distinct disadvantage to the P.A. who has / Subtil A. only one/clerk to have that clerk looked down ipon^ as iiskiTi**^ l^/Tta Cut * /^evArid tho ^ t£Lc —*/ D-iring; the P.A f s absences on tour etc the Head-clerk has to be left in charge and it is most desirable that the ran shonld be s v ich. that the pe&lt;9 — » ke 4 -pie having; bnsiness with the Ag;ency shonld not 1 treat A him with contempt* Knwait is still somewhat big;ftted bt£&lt;n~e in matters of religion and V (l/y-C i Vi not vvft* of the ff ahl-al-kitab ?f 1 {jxx^K. tux . I have no fatlt to find with Mr Gazdar’s q-aalifi- i -cations bnt from the point of view of the Agency’s work in which I inclnde the H.C»s relations with mer- j -chants and others I do not think his retnrn to Kuwait CkX-cuIl liAVs/oe sir able • A 15th ^ept 1911. ' / , Capt S 741 — 11,000-1 ‘-o^DRAFT—(For Approval). •u.eriGY. Political R^smENcy, Persian Gulf/ Kuwait No., D/Q nONPIDENTTAL Dated— .i.Qt.h Octot^g 19 1 ! • ■big F.A. R. t BU^HIRE. dear Birdwood, a line before I leave, a word a -fice affairs • I aro leaving; D T Mello in chart; written instructions about all current work anfc ordinary contingencies , and 1 think he will carry on ouite all rig;ht. My confidential cupbt) be sealed pp , and his orders are to carry r n and report anything; of a Confidential nature, present H.C. sub jxo tern and I should like to that until I return , when, if he has carried -factorily as T think he will, I should like t * pukka'* H.C. Dont roy of- with ful 1 most ke on ep him at satis- make him •s or p er- o ) a young; en aboiish- Anyway, rlease don’t plant me with any Gazdar -eiras during; ^v absence! To keep him company I am getting; (or try in -ster as second clerk, as the billet has not be -ed yet. You needn’t worry about this as the 3foung;ster w ill g;o al^ once on orders coming; for abolition -ranging; on that basis and in case the orders c my absence he will g;o at once. I write to let that \is pay may not be held up when his name in an establishment pay bill. Yours sincerely. c me 3 ou19 DRAFT—(For Approval). At 6 T C r , Political Residency* Persian Gulf. Kviwait Nr. P/0 Dated. CONFIDENTIAL To, Political Resident, BMCHIRE. My dear Colonel, 2811 . ,F£ L r:i 191 2 V I dor f t Trant to b^r a r'titjarce b»it with reference to F. A. R f 8 endopyeinert No ?837 of the 31yt Octoter 1911 abo-at a rew Aywiatart ^nrt:eor fop Kawait , woaldrH it be ay well to remind Foreign that the jreyert mar’y six month® r' .ice (which iy all he hay to £;ive ander hiy contract) ex« ta£;e if ril and the the new -pipes on -he 12th Airil and it woiild be an advan hiy sacces^or coaid arrive before that date* There iy a down mail dae here on the 12th Ap A/S will probably want to leave by it r yo roan on^ht to arrive on the 4th , which roeany he Uoald have to leave Bombay by Fast Mail on the 28th March a|t lateyt. Yoa may have already wired to Foreign , ay with qaarantine running now it woaldn*t do to interree;nam with no qaarantine Doctor. yoary sincerely, W. H. I. SHAHECPeIr 9,000-3-10 bat I writ have anDRAFT—(For Approval). ere:/. Political Residency, Persian Gulf*/ Kuwait No O/CL CONFIDENTIAL Dated. ill ^.xil 191 ^ and Political Resident, BUCKIRE* My dear Or lone 1 , My as istant-Cnr^eon kec-ys aakint; about I have told hiir I have written to yo^i already hear very soon* Have Foreign managed to ^et a van yet, as w ^o bad in Bushire my present man ovi&amp;;ht notto 6 ;o he is relieved* I think 1 can make him stay on without mTich fiss, bTit I wish F^reitcn wonld hnrr^r stumps a little* Yonrs sincerely, W, H. I. Chakespeat. lis relief- hope to ith 1 la&amp;ne tntil bit their1 © 92 , OFFICE NOTE. A* i y Ay ynn knr»w T have beer vc ry bnyy the la^ t few days and have 'not been able to £0 into your afpjJ of the 14th April in detail* Since your notice asking to be relieved was cation sent V in I have written several times to endeavour to lave yon relieved before the expiry of yonr six months 1 notice * Government have apparently had some difficnl- -ty in finding a suitable man 9 brat on the Residents arrival I asked him when I might expect a man to relieve yon* He tells me that an Asyistant-Srargeon has Ijeen I s selected ( I do rot remember his name , and have no | official papers aborat him yet) f and he hoped that in j a mail or two I should receive the official letter 1 telling me of his appointment and probable date of arri- -val * More than this I do not know and therefore | cannot enlighten yora* / With plagrae as bad as it is now at Brashire 9 it would be most inconvenient if yora had to leave at once and if yora have not actually got an appointment elsewhere and can manage to stay on rantil the arrival 0 :!“ yorar relief I shall be very glad , and trrast that it will not be many weeks * Yorar expenses in regard to the quarantine service I presume have arisen from the change in the pcsijion of the Q.raarantine station * If yora wish me to take the mat- -ter rap f kindly let me have a separate application on the srabject with mope details * I have taken no action on yorar application official- randerstood ^*// Tr *’ wanted none if Resident coraid giv&lt; | ras any news of yorar relief* I merely showed yorao* S 1918 - 5 , 000 - 3-06 a]plication to the Resident and he made no comment* let me have this note back 9 as have no copy*Kuwait, 15th October 1312. My dear Birdwood, At the risk of being importunate I am reminding you about my Head-Clerk, Mr. L. M. D'Mello. He took over the office as acting H.C. on the 4th May 1911 and I asked for him to be confirmed when/f' came back from leave in Ja- -nuary, as also several times since, the last being when I was over in Bushire. Would you mind confirming him officially from the Residency or let me know if I can do so by an office order here. Yours sincerely, Sd/- Wf H. I. Shakespear.A @) British E©sidency Eushiro, 5th Kovernber 1912. Please see your deni-official letter dated October 15th regarding D’^ello. I am sorry we have been so long in replying on the subject of your clerPs, but the question has been hung up by ^ ref erence to Government regarding the interpretation of certain clauses of their letter bo. 2085-hst.A. dated 6 th July 1912. The latter is, however, still under correspondence and Sir Percy asks me to say that under the circumstances there is no objection to DM.IqIIo being confirmed as Head Clerk by an Office Order at Itoweit, but he would like the ap- pcirtrent of 2 nd Clerk still kept open, i.e. the present incumbent distinctly informed that he will bo liable at any time to transfer to an appointment paid from the Office Allowance here at Buahire or elsewhere. fINDIAN SUBOKDINATE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Assistant Surgeon Branch ^ I. A. F. 11122. Gratis. SteB-AOPlUTAHT lUTTRUDQM Additions to Record of Service for the year ending 3lst Decembei 19/2. Departmental Xo. (Snb-Asstt. Surgeons only) Rank Name /laud: fyrzl I.—Promoted to Ztidl C/jfroa , // * /&lt;? 06. , vide Gazette of India Notn. No. — of 19 - . II.—Nature of employment during the year. Intjian Govkbnment. Imperial Government. (Out of India.) Military or Civil. From To Nature of employment. From To Military ^ ^ . Civ^ (Department at Province to be stated.) &lt;Zu /&amp;iAca/ dfyiuCt/. ^stDtUr /9 //lay/A &gt;/£. \ HI. — Departmental and Language Examinations passed and medical qualifications obtained during the year. [Subject of examination. Degree of proficiency obtain ed or qualified for promotion. Where. On what date. Quote authority. _ Ji- IV .— War Services during year. Campaign. . . . . ,, .. . „ If wounded, Battle, siege or Dab* Appointment held on Name of officer in 8 t a te nature of action. the occasion. chief command. wound Medals and clasp received during year. - V.—Special Services in peace or war during the year. Instances in which the has distinguished himself by gallant or skilful conduct; or of special duties on which he may have been employed ; when, where and on what on as:on, und whether noticed or thanked in orders, or otl erw ise. (Attach copy of letters received. San? it, /9 ^ JtU,. £~*/**~ ^ 4 ' ^ H&gt;-a. j.f. zs.2 VI— Whether married or single. (Assistant Surgeons only.) If married, state WlTE. Children. Name in full. Date of Date of xt • * , • • Name in full. birth- marriage. Sox. Date of birth. -^ ek/uv /# ‘Z -/903 /- J /9 £&gt; 4 . VII.—Kindred Roll. (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only.) ‘Nearest relations in the established line of succession. Name. SODH Wife Daughters Father Mother Others Supposed a of. *» a o S Class and tribe. 1 Vocation and other particulars tending to identifica tion. Village or Town. Pargun- nah. District. Name, address and relationship of heir; and in the event of the latter being a minor, of the guar dian to whon^the estate is to VIII.—Occurrences affecting character. Station and date of assembly and by whose orders. Courts-Martial or Courts of Inquiry. Cliarges. Result. Reference to Order or Letter. _ Not*. —Not required in cases of trial which have resulted in acquittal or courts of inquiry which have exonerated him from blame. In all other cases a brief abstract is to be given. IX.—Statement of all Furlough and Leave (except privilege leave, and in the case of Sub-Assistant Sur geons leave on full pay) taken during the year. a Nature of leave, whether on medical certificate, or private affairs, and under what Furlough Rules. Authority, quoting the No. and date of order. Period actually taken. From To Months. Days. In cases of leave out of In dia give precise date of embarkation and of dis embarkation in India on return. X.—Name and address of nearest relative, stating 1 / A f relationship—for reference in case of emergency. &gt; (Assistant Surgeons only.) ) .jlfi// I hereby declare that to the best of my knowledge and belief this statement is correct and true. j .'JL^/cCaL Station Datcd 1st January 19'J. Sinnature of ***»* .jS'ifh. J msfawj .Surrfvvm.COPY of a letter fr^ra Officer Commanding 'Patrick Stewart' to the Director , Persian Gmlf Telegraphs dated the 22nd February 19i.2# No 19 • Forwarded to the Director, Persian Gulf for necessary action • In recommending Mr Kelly I would refer you to 3iy letter No 217 to yrur address dated the 25th Sept , your No u.405 dated the 2nd October ^909 , and the P,M.0 of India his letter No 8864 dated 29th Sept 1909 , relating to diag- -ncsis and t te interest he took in the cases of Beri-Beri which after increasing at the rate of 300 per cent before he joined us yielded entirely to his treatment and disappear -ed« Mr Kelly’s treatment of all other cases has been co n -listen! with the above throughout his service under me, not only in any particular case itself , but where possible in tracing the cause and taking steps to eradicate it. His general conduct and behaviour to all on board has given me the greatest satisfaction and I consider him a very able and deserving medical officer. True copy 22.2.^2 (sd) N,A. TINDALL Capt, Coromdg H. M’s I, T, S, 'Patrick Stewart' Certified above is a true copy. Kuwait ...January I9i3 Captain, Political Agent Kuwait3 INDIAN SUBORDINATE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Assistant Sueoeon Branch. Sub ■Assistant Surgeon Annual Confidential Report for the year 19 ' Questions 1 . Rank and name 2. Nature of his duties ? 3. How long has he served under you ? 4. State your opinion as to his intelligence and efficiency ? Answers. ^tuL'CAl Ci /f/z — 7 d f^dMlc'c^a /u IsdtUlcc&amp;d^ tcirrf- Ivxvi&amp;u^ t Uaryv-u^ k 9- tco^ x/ - 5 Does he from age, infirmity, or any other physical or mental disqualification, appear to be unfit for his duties during peace or war ? (A T . B .—In reporting on a first class Assistant Surgeon or Sub-Assistant Surgeon it must be definitely stated whether he is physically fit for promotion to the commis sioned rank, and to perform the duties of such rank on field service.) 6 . What are his habits ? 7. State what you know of the manner in which he has maintained order and discipline in the hospital, and performed his duties generally ? ~/Yo ^ ‘IxrvY*^'- 9- (Urt UL4 *i^CpU4 . hl'i~ e^cbr-CLA &lt;f- ( Ut Iua tiusL^s 8 . Docs he maintain his acquaintance wit the regulations governing Military Hospitals (N. B .—Tlie reporting officer must give a definite reply to this important question whether the subordinate is in civil or military employment.) 9. Is he well educated and does he write with facility and clearness ? (Assistant Sur geons only.) 10 . Is he in all respects fit for an independent charge ? (Assistant Surgeons only.) it ^i LljUZ&gt;s rv€/^£eirvi '££. Ctnlz 9 '(• !/&lt;rC l/J_ da U^r-INDIAN SUBORDINATE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Assistant Surgeon BkancH- H&gt;4LB-A£6 tST A TtiTT SUB GpF.QN Additions to Record of Service for the year ending 31st December lO/j, Departmental No, (Sub-Asslt. Surgeons only) Rank Name. Claude, Cy iii ICiUi/ I*—Promoted to ^ , vide Gazette of India Notn. No. — of 19 ^ , II.—Nature of employment during the year. Indian Government. Imperial Government. (Out of ladia.) Military or CiviL From To Nature of employment. From Military ♦ Civil {Department or Province to be stated). t Jh hredoe*/' • /fCuay / /SU . IH.—Departmental and Lang uage Examinations passed and medical qualifications obtained during the year. Subject of examination Dogreo of proficiency obtain, od or qualified for promotion- Where. On what date. Quote authority. — hd- IV.—War Services during year. Campaign. Battle, siege or action. Date. Appointment held on the occasion. Name of officer in chief command. If wounded, state nature of wound. Medals and clasp received during year. __ hd- V.—Special Services in peace or war during the xjear. Instances in which the hag distinguished himself by gallant or skilful conduct; or of special duties on which ho may have been employed; when, whore and on what occasion, and whether noticed or thanked in orders, or otherwise, (Attach coj'y of letters received.)yi % —'Whether married or single. (Assistant Surgeons only.) If married, state X/-* Wive. Children. Name in full. Date of birth. Date of marriage. Name in full. Sex. Date of birth. / X .*/ 2 '/ 86 t : /- y/foz AS £ A ' /• 3/^^. Y1I.—Kindred Roll. (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only.) ^Nearest relations in the established line ol succession. Supposed i age. Supposed height. Vocation and other , particulars tending to identifica tion. Residence. Name, address and relationship of heir; Name. Years. Montlis. Class and tribe. Feet. Inches. Village or Town. Pargun- nah. District. and in the event of the latter being a minor, of the guard ian to whom the estate is to be^tid. Sons ... | Wife ... ! ( Daughters ... { is' Father ... | Mother — | Others ... | I VIII.—Occurrences affecting character. Station and date of assembly and by whose orders. Courts-Martial or Courts of Inquiry. Charges. Result. Reference to Order or Letter. - M- Note.—N ot required in eases of trial which have resulted in acquittal or courts of inquiry which have exonerated him from blame. In all other cases a brief abstract is to bo given. IX.— Statement of all Furlough and Leave (except privilege leave, and in the case of Sub- Assistant Sur geons leave on full pay) taken during the year. ^ Nature of leave, whether on medical certificate, or private affairs, and under what Furlough Rules. Authority, quoting the No. and date of order. Period actually taken. j In cases of leave out of India give precise date of embarkation and of dis embarkation in India on return. From To Months. Days. hit - X.—Name and address of nearest relative, stating') n / / t/ ' - / ' relationship—for reference in case of emergency. [ 'V.V'. /iMj . (Assistant Surgeons only.) ) T ' I hereby declare that to the best of my knowledge and belief this statement is correct and true. Station^ /%0 lAst*. Bated 1st January 19/j 7 Signature of + * 1/ Assistant Surgeon.3 Date of birth. tit /• 3./^^. Name, address and elationship of heir; and in the event of the latter being a ninor, of the guard ian to whom the estate is to be ^tid. INDIAN SUBORDINATE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Assistant Surgeon ^ Sub-Assistant Surokon ijRANCH ' Annual Confidential Report for the year 19 Questions. Answers. 1 . Rank and name 2 .Nature of his duties ? 3. How long has he served under you ? 4 . State your opinion as to his intelligence and efficiency ? CL AOEE C ‘T? rlCL Oe J-Urv^ /*f /y (tf- bCtE f J3L AJLjk/j 5. Does he from age, infirmity, or any other physical or mental disqualification, appear 'ifY* to be unfit for his duties during peace &gt;rence to Order or Letter. iim from blame. -Assistant Sur- as of leave out of five precise date of cation and of dis- &lt;ation in India on return. istant Surgeon. or war ? (N. B .—In reporting on a first class Assistant Surgeon or Sub-Assistant Surgeon it must be definitely stated whether he is physically fit for promotion to the commis sioned rank, and to perform the duties of such rank on field service.) 6 . What are his habits ? 7. State what you know of the manner in which he has maintained order and discipline in the hospital, and performed his duties generally ? r&gt; 8 . Does he maintain his acquaintance with the regulations governing Military Hospitals ? ' (N. B .—The reporting officer must give a definite reply to this important question whether the subordinate is in civil or military employment.) 9. Is he well educated and does he write with facility and clearness ? (Assistant Sur geons only.) 10. Is he in all respects fit for an independent charge ? (Assistant Surgeons only.) t&amp;'VQuestions. [ (i) Is ho familiar with the use of the medical and surgical equipment provided in military hospitals ? 11 •&lt;{(»:) Have you any further observations to officer, especially as regards his attain ments, professional knowledge, charac- ter, and bearing ? 12. Is he competent or desirous for special work in connection with (a) a Laboratory, {b) Venereal disease, (c) ^ Surgical cases and Operative Surgery, (d) Midwifery and diseases of women and children, or (e) X-ray apparatus ? “ 13. Is his retention in the service desirable and likely to bo advantageous to the State ? {N. B. —This question should be answered in the case of all Assistant Surgeons and Sub-Assistant Surgeons of less than three years’ service.)” 14. Is hcf^desirous.of Civil employment ? Station^ Date- ^ — 2- . 19/S , Answers, A- //+-j J i~/i UsxJL /JL* hi'Medical Charter / z. . REMARKS BY BRIGADE OR DIVISIONAL D. OR A. D. M. S. Xote .—When a Military Assistant suigoon been unfavourably eported on, the Brigade or Divisional D. orA. Sub-Ass-stant Surgeon D, M, S, will note that the unfavourable remarks have been communicated to him. mLieutienant-Colonel VJ. Q. Grey, I.A. , Polioioal Agent, Kuwait. No. of 1915. Politio -1 Agency, Kuwait. Lieutenant-Colonel ^ir P.%. Cox, K.C.I.E., Political resident in the Persian Gulf, Baerah. Dated Kuwait, the 3th February 1915. Sir, I have the honour to submit for the favour of your support and transmission to higher authority a strong reoommen- -dation in x’avour of Assistant Surgeon Kelly, I.S.M.D. , who has been in medical charge of this Agency and Civil Dispensary for nearly three years. 2l. It would be difficult to over estimate the value and im- -portanoe of Mr Kelly's work in Kuwait; I consider that he has conoributed very largely to the satisfactory political conditionJ which prevail. The ShaiKh has the utmost confluence in his me- -dioal skill; so much so, that when a question of his transfer arose some months ago I was obliged to deprecate the suggestion on this round al^ne, and was supported in my view by Dr, Mylrea of the American Mission who went so far ao to say that, in his opinion, the Shaikh's recovery from his very serio-x illness in May 1916 was largely due to His Excellency's confidence in Mr. Kelly. The value to HiB majesty's Government of Shaikh Mubarax; 1 ^ presence in Kuwait during the pa^t few months need not be points out. 5. Mr. Kelly is always accessible, ohaerful and tactful in his dealingsmmdealings with the ^eo^le, ana indefatth.;able in hi of^orvc to relieve Gur/ej:!!!^ and diet-eGS, and tho fhaiKh's re^ara Tor and oon-Tidtnoe in hin io obviously 'hareu by the Kuwait oonuunity in general. It may be mentioned that in aooox-danoe with i^liti- -oal oonsideration ?3 1JU'. Kelly hitherto attended the fThaiish hi hou ,ehola f and tomii and launoh e^tabli-haent?,without re- -oeiving any re:auneration^ fro a Hi^ Rxoellenoy. 4 . I believe that ^ro.aotion to ooiaaisoioned raru: in the I.3.M.D in aade by c-eleotion and in my opinion it would be hard to f.nd a uore thoroughly deserving oase for ppeoial oonric^erat Ion than tiiait of hr. ^elly. I beg ttrongly to reooaaend that he may be granted syeoial pro action frou his present grade to that of 3e- -nior Assistant 'urgeon with the Honorary ranit of Lieutenant in view of the eminently aeritorious ce^vioe whioh he ha.- rendered in Kuwait at a uorst important time . 5. A oo^y of tills letter if? oeing sent to bushire for reoora. L I I have the hon &gt;ur to be, r* i r ► | Your aost obedient servant, Lisut-Colonel, Pol tioal Agent, Kuwait,Prom Lt: Ool: Sir P.Z Cox,K.C.I.E,C.S.I, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department Delhi. Dated,Basrah,the I9th February 1915. Sir I have the honour to submit,for favour of consideration,a copy of a letter from the Political No. G-5,dated the 8th February 1 Agent Kuwait drawing 1915 to the Political Resident Persian Gttlf. i attention to the services of Assistant Surgeon Keljy,Indian Subordinate ..'edical Department,and recomnending him for special promotion with the Honourary rank of Lieutenant. 1 liave no 't the record here but I remember that Assistant Surgeon Kelly was very highly reported on when serving at Shiraz,and I have sufficient personal acquaintance with his merits and his work to be able to endorse Colonel Grey’s opinion as to his fitness for special promotion. 3 * 1 trust the Foreign Department will feel able to make a recoramendatien in his favour to the Director Indian Medical Service. I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servantBushire, I4/2/I5. Major J. McPherson, I.M.S., Residency Surgeon in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Lieut.Col. W. G. Grey, X.A. Political Agent, Kuweit. Sir, I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of the Annual Confidential Report on Assistant Surgeon C. C. Kelly I*S.M.D., for the year 1914. I have the honor to be. Sir, your obedient servant. Major I.M.S., Residency Surgeon in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.INDIAN SUBORDINATE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT, I. A. F. Ill22. Urutis. Assistant Sur geon ^UB-AS 8 ttTAMT-Sunai!iON Additions to Record of Service for the year ending 31st December 19/^7' Depirlmental No. {Sub-A sslt. Surgeons only) Rank /2 m ft Name^7'// I.—Promoted to /it CAis vide Gazette of India Notn. No. — of 19//, II.—Nature of employment during the year. Indian Government. i Imperial Government. (Out of India.) Military or CiviL From To Nature of employment. From Military Civil (Department or Province to be stated). /&amp;' ///Z - HI.—Departmental and Lang uage Examinations passed and medical qualifications obtained during the year. Subject of examination Degree of proficiency obtain ed or qualified for promotion Where. On what date. Quote authority., IV.—War Services during year. Campaign. Battle, siege or action. Date. Appointment held on the occasion. Name of officer in chief command. If wounded, state nature of wound. Medals and clasp received during year. .fc/- F .—Special Services in peace or war during the year. Instances in which the has distinguished himself by gallant or skilful conduct; or of special duties on which ho may have boon employed; when, where and on what occasion, and whether noticed or thaukod in orders, or otherwise, (Attach copy of letters received.)2 f,- Yl % Whether married or single. (Assistant Surgeons only.) WlTE. Obuldren. Name in fulL Date of birth. Date of marriage. Name in full. Sex. Date of birth. /- f- 02, If. £ /f#*, YU.—Kindred Roll. (Sub-Assistant Surgeons only.) Nearest relations in the established line oi succession. Name. Sons Wife « Daughters Father Mother Others VIII.—Occurrences affecting character. Station and date of assembly and by whose orders. Courts-Martial or Courts of Inquiry. Charges. Result. Reference to Order or Letter. l V In all other cases a brief abstract is to bo given. IX.—Statement of all Furlough and Leave (except privilege have, and in the case of Sub-Assistant Sur geons leave on full pay) taken during the year. * Nature of leave, whether on medical certificate, or private affairs, and under what Furlough Rules. Authority, quoting the No. and date of order. Period actually taken. In cases of leave out of India give precise date of embarkation and of dis- embarkation in India on return. From To Months. Days. - M- - V . • relationship—for reference in case (Assistant Surgeons only.) I hereby declare that to the best of my knowledge and belief this statement is correct and true. lativey stating') ///&gt;/’// / * /? ' of emergency. [ ^ ^ Signature of Atsistant Surgeon. &amp;ub- Aesioiant ftnrperm,. 1 . ] 1 Supposed j AGE. Class and tribe. Supposed HEIGHT. Vocation and other particulars tending to identifica tion. Residence. ^ Name, address and relationship of heir; and in the event of the latter being a minor, of the guard- « ian to whom the **• estate is to be pai^^ Years. Months. 1 1 * i A O A Village or Town. Pargun- nah. District. 4. 5. or whe' sion field 6 . Y 7. 8 . (i repl is in 9.Sex. Date of birth. if. i •/?#$ y* 3 ’/&lt;?#//* Name, address and relationship of heir; and in the event of the latter being a minor, of the guard- ian to whom the estate is to be pai^ INDIAN SUBORDINATE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Assistant Surquon r Sub-Assis»aw Surgkon ^ ranch * Annual Confidential Report for the year 19 . Questions. 1 . Rank and name 2 .Nature of his duties P 3. How long has he served under you ? Answsvs. C. LA UTie C ^^7 /( t ^ ^ A-lc, /j/S — 4 . State your opinion as to his intelligence and efficiency ? , / . Reference to Order or Letter. ed him from blame, ^ub-Assistant Sur- 4 cases of leave out of iia give precise date of ibarkation and of dis- ibarkation in India on return. *2/•/Lm? XJ A/?€#/. Assistant Surgeon, tb- AsH^iant Surgeon. 5 . Does he from age, infirmity, or any other physical or mental disqualification, appear to be unfit for his duties during peace or war ? {N'B. In reporting on a first class Assistant Surgeon or Sub-Assistant Surgeon it must be definitely stated whether he is physically fit for promotion to the commis sioned rank, and to perform the duties of such rank on field service.) 6 . What are his habits ? 7 . State what you know of the manner in which he has maintained order and discipline in the hospital, and performed his duties generally ? pO _ - A/ /-ru t*-- — ^ I . 1 ^4- - .. _ ^ / i ^ *P-&gt; -LsisdZsui, &lt;3 . (a*%+ regulations governing Military ^ ^ —A^rv4L»_-. 8 . Does he maintain his acquaintance with the Hospitals ? (N. B .—The reporting officer must give a definite reply to this important question whether the subordinate is in civil or military employment.) 9 . Is he well educated and does he write with facility and clearness ? (Assistant Sur geons only.) 10. Is he in all respects fit for an independent charge ? (Assistant Surgeons only.) / eTelegram.R. From ^oixLical Kuwait To Political Basrah No . 39 C Dated 28.4.18 (19. CO) I should, be glad if you could recall Lieutenant Conoliy as Blockade can now be carried on by one Onicer; he knows no Arabic and in any case I do not consider him a suitaole ofiicer for political work such as this.Enolair. Telegram. From. To. No. Dated 1st Political Basrdn. political Kuwait. 2545. . received 2nd. May, 1918. Your .39/0 Please Of icer, Basrah. tell Conol y report here for duty as Blockade Telegram. Enclai r. From. Political Kuwait. To. Political Basrah. No. Dated May 2nd. 1918. Your 2545 AAA Conolly left In Kalika Political.Telegram.R t From Political Kuwait ‘ r ° PolitiSai iusliipg copy by oost Basrah No. 70 C Da-oect 8.6.13 (11.30) If D Hello not, returning here aftex* leave I request new Hccu Clerk. Present man helpless and inaccurate and. does not know Arabic or ways oi Gulf. If no more experienced man available would like De Souza who was at Bahrain* CantainConfidential. He.80 oflflO Politic'! Agency, Kuwait June 35th,IB. /r7 Te Beputy Political Resident, Buahire. Memor&amp;nduaie My telegram Ho.70 C of June Qth,l&amp;lft. D*Hello telegrar^n fh t he de-» rot expect Vw- 1»?Tore the end of October and I hear unofficially that he 5£ ticking for an e^uenaion of leare till then on medical certificate. 1 can leare nothing to the present Head Clerk and cannot trust the Office te do properly the work which ordinarily falls to the* in the Chilf, so I hope you will he able te let me nave tae services of sot^e man who knows the Oulf and a little Arabic,ii' possible, till Duello*s return. If there is ne one with Gulf experience , I would like any e*er£4tic clerk, bui. u%i i.UJt be a a &gt;&amp;n. I a* sorry te worry you but thr Kuwait Ofiio# iu chaos. captain, dgenti , Kuwait. Copy to D.C.C.Basr&amp;h.service. Telegram X. Prom - Political, Bagdad, To - Foreign Simla. No. 6239. Dated 29th July 1918. Health of Aset. Surgeon C.C.Kelly. Quarantine I'edical Officer. Koweit, has suffered from long residence at Kuwait and in Gulf and « my opinion he is no longer in a fit state of health to perform his duties there. He is very deaf and unfit for active military \ I recommend that he be recalled and posted to some good station in India preferablyi„ the hills. There is no immediate^necessity for his re- placement. Political, Baghdad. Telegram X. From - Foreign Simla. / To - Political, Baghdad. No. 990-S Bated 18th reed. 19th August 1918. Your telegram of the 29th July 6239. It has been decided to post Kelly to India. Please arrange his return and direct him to report arrival by telegram to Birector General of Indian I'edical Services who will arrange posting. No substitute is at present available. Foreign, Simla. No. /£, OFFICF OF THE CIVIL COiailSSIONER. B.ighoaa, the 19th August 1918. P»A. Koweit. v&gt;opy fo i information and necessary action. Copy to:- D.P.R. Bushi re. D*C.C. Basrah. / As** ‘ Offg. Civil Commissioner! ^ • J • G .Political Agency,Kuwait. Dfcted January ? 4 th 19 U. The Civil Corainissioner, Baghdad. MEiORANDiJ: The attached application from Mr.D’Eello,Head Clerk of this Agency, is forv trued and. the Increased rate of pay asked for,i.e. Rs.?? 5 /- )er mensem,is strongly re- commended. 'r. D'lCello is an exceptionally capable clerk and well deserving of this advancement. He has worked as Head Clerk and accountant fro i 5 th May I 'll. The maximum rite of pay sanctioned for the post of Head Clerk of this Agency is Rs. 150 /- per mensem. This was the rate sanctioned whei^ the Agency was first opened % in 1 904 and,due to the very Increased cost of living sin ce then,it is now quite Inadequate. I request that the Increase may be sanctioned with effect from the 13 th November lUB - the date of his rejoining‘from leave. Captain, Political A^entjKuwalt...■CP**Kuwait.. 17th January, 1919. The Political Agent, KUwa it. Sir, I beg to submit this roy application for your favourable consideration and transmission to the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad with your support and recommendation. I count already over 13 years* Government service in the Persian Gulf during which period I served at Bundar Abbas, Moham- merah and Kuwait, at the latter place as Head Cler* now for neaxly . 8 years. I held charge of the current duties of this office for 3j months in 1911-12 during the political Agent's absence on privilege leave and on several occasions since during his absence on tours, etc. The successive political Agents have appreciated my work: and recommended me for promotion as will be seen from the office notes , ' left by them on the files. * About April 1916 Colonel Grey, then political Agent, Kuwait, casually told me one day that Captain (now Lieut.-Colonel) A.T. Wilson, under whom I served before as Head Clerk at Mohammerah, had enquired from him at Basrah whether I would come there on promotion’ and that he had replied there and then that I would not. in 1917 the Chief Political Officer enquired - vide his telegram No. 806 dated 2nd February 1917 whether I could be spared for 6 months to relieve the Mohammerah Head Clerk who was promoted | to be Treasury Officer at Bushire. The political Agent, -olonel Hamilton, replied that I should be left here at least til± one close of tne financial year 1917-13 and I also declined the offer ' firstly because I was not gaining much financially by going there and secondly because I wanted to go on leave having had none for some 8 years. Since the outbreak of the war the work of this office has • increased enormously and I performed it singly up to tne begin ning’ of February 1918 without any clerical help whatever nor increase of pay to meet the advanced cost of living while the civil postal clerics in the next room were given revised rates of | and all field privileges with Rs- 2 /- per da^ as ration money pay in'V - 2 - in add it on to their iooal and other allow-inoes. ^olonei Hamilton in hi3 memo Ho«-il dated 15th January, 1913 to the 9ivil Commissioner, Baghdad, recommended that the arduous wor*t performed by me single-handed all throughout might be recongnised in sand form, and that I might be given promotion ' * ' * on my return from ie-j.ve. I rejoined the office on the 13th November 1913 and have so far not received any addition to my pay which is the same as was sanctioned some 15 years ago, A compari son of this rate witn tnose of other cier^s will snow that I am getting onl^ as much as tne unuer exerts of one ana two years' standing who are actually wording under me. I therefore respect- fully beg that you will nindly recommend me ^o be given at least tne same rate of pay, viz Rs.225/- per mensem, as was given to the late Head Clerh (Muferred Shah) of the Blockade Establishment. If the pay of the psot of Head Clerh of this office cannot be raised then I solicit go ^avourably consider my early transfer elsewnere either in the Basrah or Baghdad Willayats on improved pay. I beg to remain, Sir, four most obedient servant,No. 15/C. Political Agency,Kuwait Dated January DO th,t o 1 9 The ^Irst Assistant Resident, Bushire. Reference corresponlence ending with y 6 iifc No. 0^1 of Dist July 1013. On iccount of his a^e^han Bahadur Munshi Nulla 'Abdullah is no longer capable of iolnj sufficient work to Justify hie retention in Government service and I therefore recommend that no further extension yiven to him. For reasons of economy I ;ould prefer t.^at he should retire at once. . Captain, Political A^en t , Ku : Y.a i t. . . .Politioal Agency, Kuwait, 2nd February 1320. © Tne Oivil CooimisPioner, Baghdad. ^■eiuo random« Before leaving Kuwait I would li.ce to recommend the Hesd Cleric, Mr. Louis Miohael D’Mello, for an honour - the M.3.E. would, I thimc, be a suitable one and so I recommend thic for tc- him. He has, I consider, well merited some such recognition of his services. He always worjcs very hard, is very conscientious about his duties anu. is besides a most capable and trustworthy officer. Besides the honour I recommenci a personal allowance of Rs. 50/- per mensem for him for reasons given below. He is at tne maximum of his grade pay i.e. Rs„15o/- p.m. The pay of the other two clerks in the office is also Rs,15o/~ and it seems unfair to have the Head Cleric, who is far superior to ethher of these in qualifications and who has 16 years' Go vernment serviie as against 2 ^ and 2 years respectively of theirs, on the same pay. If Kuwait eventually comes under the Civil Administration s of 'Iraq perhaps it would then be possible to raise the Head Clerk's grade pay when the personal allowance could be disconti- —nued but until tnis can be done I strongly recommend the per sonal allowance for him. The cost of living is now very high in comparison to what i was when this grade pay was fixe^ for him 16 years ago and he finds it very difficult to support himself anu his family on his present income. captain, Political Agent, Kuwait.Confidential. No. S/. Office of the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, the 24 th July, 1920 . To P.O.s in-charge of Divisions and Heads of Departments. Memorandum. • • Please furnish a confidential report in the attached form on Gazetted Officers, Part I serving under your orders. Copies herewith ^ ne C °^ 0n ^ re&lt; l u ^ re&lt;: ^ an&lt; ^ be retained in this office. One copy should be retained by you for the information of your successor. A blank form for the reporting officer himself should be added and submitted. Sd. A. T. WILSON, Lieut.-Col., I.A., j 4 g. Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia.Surname Christian Names Rank and, or permanent Government Service if any ... Department and name of post or posts in which em-- ployed during the war. 1 1 . Is he in all respects physically lit to perform the duties required of him in his present post (if • untit a medical certificate should accompany the report.) 2 . Has he during the period under report performed his duties satisfactorily. 3 . Is he so decided by above or below the average in any respect as to call for special notice. If so, specify his particular merits or demerits. 4 . Do you consider that he is likely to prove tit for promotion in the ordinary course in the Depart ment in which he at present belongs. 5 . How long has he served under you 6 . What is your opinion as to his general capacity and ability. Major. Political Agent, Kuwait. Signature of Head of Department Kuwait • 27.8.1920 . or P. O. ijc Division. Station Date .political Agency. Kuwait, 'abed Uie &lt;37th August IdgO. of 1320. Bie civil COuaissXonQrt Baghdad. Memorandum . Referenoe your circular memorandum dated 24th Jiily 1320. I have no aaaettcci Officers serving under my orders. A blank, form is returned herewith. Major,;, , Pclitical Agent, Kuwait. Fnclo: One. M.A.3 Itelegram Code,, From - Trevor, D.P.R., Bushire. To - Political , Kuwait• No. 1923. Dated 24th (reed.25th) October 1920. Your despatch dated 18th August 615 item (7). Presume you will require reappintment of Assistant Surgeon for quarantine and general duty when Dr. Mylrea goes on leave query. * Would you prefer Military Assistant Surgeon of type of Kelly or Muhammadan civil Assistant Surgeon of type of man at Bahrain. w N • / Trevor. Telegram (P). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Political, Bushire. No.151-C. Dated 26th October 19 20 * Reference your telegram No. 1923. I consider Military Assistant Surgeon preferable. !D.O. No.l4tt-C. 7fp KUWAIT. 8th 3*pt*mb«r IOSA. Xou »«r* spying the oth«r &lt;U.y oo th« 'Lawrence' that you would probably b« changing ay h«ad dark »oon, owing to ■oa* swnlor onwa bwing rwturnwd frou Mwaopotamla which would naan a ganarai shuffla round. Is this llkaly to ba sot My nrasant nan, Bashir Ahmad, is vary hard working and Tary willing, and I hava no complaint with his work at an, axespt as regards his keeping of accounts at which ha is appallingly bad. Ha is constantly making silly careless mistakes, which, as I aw awfully bad at figures myself, are Just the sort I find it hardest to spot, and, as you hare seen, I have let uyself in m:i® than onea already. X hare had a regular field day as a result of your memorandum on the subject, and hare discovered tv;o more mistakes which had escaped me, both equally silly oima one of them running into three months - which I have corrected by telegram. I f c* course, r^rilise that X am entirely responsible, and -v nn L ara checking them - which would many men only about ten minutes, and it makes htti it sc much harder with a bad clerk. I am not blaming Bashir Ahmad in any way, as I am sure it is M3 nlsfortuns and not his fault, and h# f«#la it v»ry muchCopy of endora^piant rto. ai-iiat., dated 5th January 19211$ from the Under Secretary to the Uovemraent of India, i’oreign A Political department, Uelhi, to the ]lon # ble the Politioal Kesident in the Persia:! Oulf, iushiro, etc. copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded for neo 253 . 3 ary ajtion. It requested that the names of any aiitable officers rray be forwarded direct to the ro/emment of India Array Department. 3 . If spare conies of the form are required, they should he obtained from tne dovemment of India, Array henartnent, direct. setter from the Government of India Array Uenartment, ifc.8890-il.0» 3(c. i.s. ), dated /:?th uotober 1921, (with enclo sure) •ARMY DEPARTMENT. No, 8890-M. 0.-3 (0. G. S.). GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of MADRAS. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of BOMBAY. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of BENGAL. The CHIEF SE0RETARY to the GOVERNMENT of the UNITED PROVINCES. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of the PUNJAB. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of BURMA. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of BIHAR and ORISSA. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of the CENTRAL PROVINCES. The CHIEF SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of ASSAM. THE HON’BLE the RESIDENT at HYDERABAD. The HON’BLE the CHIEF COMMISSIONER and AGENT NORTH'-WEST FRONTIER PROVINCE. The HON’BLE the AGENT to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL and CHIEF COMMISSIONER, BALUCHISTAN. The HON’BLE the AGENT to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL in CENTRAL INDIA. The HON’BLE the AGENT to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL in RAJPUTANA and CHIEF COMMISSIONER of AJMERE-MERWARA. The HON’BLE the RESIDENT in MYSORE and ' CHIEF COMMISSIONER of COORG. The CHIEF COMMISSIONER of DELHI. jieatims make them suitable for employment on intelligence duties. 2. I am therefore to request that, with the permission of the to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL, Simla, the 27th October Subject.— Submission, of names of ciril officers and non-officials whose special qitalu I am directed to state that it is considered desirable to keep on record the names of civil officers and non-officials, whose services might be made available for intelligence duties, or whose local knowledge could be placed at the disposal of the General Staff, in the event of mobilization. names, of suitable civil officers of the several services and of other civilians whave special qualifications or knowledge that would prove useful in the perfor mance of intelligence duties, and whose services or local knowledge could be placed at the disposal of the military authorities on mobilization, may be forwarded to the Government of India for record. It is not intended that the recording of a name shall entail or imply any obligation to serve. 3. A knowledge of the following countries or of their languages would be valuable use for intelligence purposes :— * North-West Frontier. Mesopotamia. Afghanistan. Persia. North-East Frontier. ~ Turkey in Asia. Russian Tufkistan. 4. Only the names of those civil officers of the; several services and other civilians whose experience in, or local knowledge of, the countries in question is sufficiently wide to be of definite value should be submitted. The qualifications should be filled in on the enclosed form. &gt;* , 5. I am also to request that the names of any civil officers or non-officials who were employed on censorship duties during the great war and whose services might again be made available on mobilization may be forwarded to the Government of India. I am, *• Sir, Your most obedient Servant, (Sd.) H. R. PATE, % OJJg. Depity Secretary to the Government of India. No. 8890-M. 0.-3 (C.G.S.). J Copy of the above forwarded to :— The Home Department. •The Foreign and Political Department. » (Sd.) E. A. DANIEL, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. ■» % V \ G. M Prese, Simla—No. 28 A.D.—- 26 - 10 - 21 — 668 —P.B.B.PAKTICULiAHS OF IniJlVIDUALS WHOfcJII SPEOIAIj aUALIFICA'i’IOHS MAKE L 'i'HEM Slil'iABIiE FOE EiiPLiOXHEHT III IlfTBLIOEilCE DU'i'IEb. IHSTHUOTIOKS. (a) 'Late Corpa'. - In the case of those who have belonged to nore than one Corpa, the Corps should be entered in the order in rfhioh the individual joined then. Eg*-lftth Bttn.London liegiMent. iiiliated 6 th August 1914. / Uoyal Fusiliers. J omnia si one d. lat July 1915. Intelligence Corps. Appointed Srd Aeptenber 19IP. (B). 'Foreign Laui.guagea'. - The degree of proficiency in a laniniage raay be indicated by the uae of letters as under, instead of 'Very dood', M dood', ’*Fair M , ^dli'^ht”, i'tc. A.A. lhorou;3i knowledge, combined wiUi the accent of the Lative^ COl A. Thorough knowledge. A. B. Cood working knowledge. B. A. Fair working knowledge. B. slight knowledge. C. Jo practical value. The form after completion should be submitted through the Local Government concerned to the (F^vemment of India.El L E CONFIDENT IAT. , Politiodl Agency 9 Kuwait. 4 th Fsfjiru&amp;ry Tiie 3aoratary to the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, B U S R I r jj. MBTfORANDliW,, Reference your memorandum No. t» 0j dated 23rd January \ 9 Z&gt;. I submit herewith the name of one norson.whom I consider might prove useful for Intelligence worh. Major, Political Agent, Kuwait* * v(A). Name (Surname). Saiyid 'Abdur Razzaq bin daiyid Mahmud. (Christian names) Late Corps (if any) : Nil. Permanent Address : Kuwait. Date of Birth. 12th June 1900 . (B).Foreign Languages: Cpeak. Read. rtrits. Arabic (his language) A. A. A. A.B. English A.B. A.B. B.A. (C). Intelligence Appointments Held: Ih(country). From. To Detail of Intelligence appointments. (date) (date) Nil (D). Profession or Occupation in Civil Life: ’’MunshiS, i.d. Vernacular Clerk, Political Agency, Kuwait. . Other Qualifications - Business^Literary,Technical, etc. Can ride. (F). Special knowledge of any foreign Country, Colony, etc. Knows the country round Kuwait and the Lower Euphrates. (H) This space is for .the continuation of any remarks for which there is not sufficient room overleaf. &lt; He served as Interpreter to the Assistant Political Officer, S&amp;mawah, Euphrates, from May' lot 8 till January tod, and did very useful work of an Intelligence nature during'the rebellion of ^9^0, when he remained in the town of Samawah, after the Asststant Politi cal Officer had been obliged' to evacuate it, and continued to supply information under conditions of considerable danger and difficulty.Copy of memorandum No.£ 3 /C dated the 28th July 1921 from the Political Agent,Bahrain to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. You will remember that when you were laet here I mentioned that the contents of the confidential files of this office seemed to be commonly known amongst persons of importance and that several persons have informed me that they received their information from Bashir Ahmad who was, In Major Dickson’s time, in charge of the confidential work* Prom time to time since I have had occasion to refer to the files to verify records, which I was assured were available, with regard to certain 'Black List' Characters, I have invari ably found that there are no papers of a disparaging nature and I have reluctantly come to the conclusion that incriminating documents or adverse reports on individuals have been removed from the files. As an/ example, I learnt that Major Diokson had at one time ordered Muhammad Roshan Akhtar to leave Bahrain, and that the order had been given in writing and was on record. Also that he had written to Messrs.Mesopotamia Corporation asking them not to employ this individual as he was an undesir able. There was nothing whatever on this individual’s file except of a laudatory nature. The history of Muhammad Roshan Akhtar is known to you. His most intimate friend in Bahrain was Bashir Ahmad and for a time these two dragged in Siddiq Hassan and the trio acted conjointly in all matters official or otherwise. When I took over Bashir Ahmad was away on deputation. Siddiq Hassan put up to me the second portion of his report on the Rajd trip which I forwarded to you under Ifo. C. He made no report that anythin* was wrong. Bashir Ahmad returned, and Just before he left Siddiq Hassan reported that a copy of the actual report(issued under this office No.449/C) had been mielai* and that as Bashir Ahmad had been the confidential Clerk he had asked him to find it. He said that he had given Bashir10 Ahmad a certain number of copies for 'register an# deapatch* an# for filea an# on £oin* through the files foun# there waa one short. Bashir Ahraa# atate# he ha# *iven them to the Hea# Clerk for some reason. The latter emphatically #enie# this. It ha# been allowe# to stan# over so Ion* by Si##iq Haaaan an# I ha# only Just taken over and #1# not know the etaff, aoj^ that beyond orderin* a strict search nothing appeared feasible. The document consisting of 60 foolscap pages was entirely missing. I think Siddiq Haasan only reported matter because I was going very carefully into the whole office organisation and filea and because Bashir Ahmad was leaving and he himself going on leave / and Akhtar rapidly falling into ill favour and jfoe feared that the affair might some out. The sequel is that the report has been discovered among the effects of Muhammad Hoshan Akhtar after his deportation when his goods were about to be auctioned. The report was written by Siddiq Hassan and he was expecting much 'Kudos' for it and would be unlikely to run the risk of giving a copy to Akhtar. It therefore points obviously to Bashir Ahmad having conveyed this report to Akhtar, doubtless with a view to its translation for the benefit of tkm Bin Sau# , s Agent. There is every likelihood that Bin Saud has at any rate had the gist of the whole report, though I do not think there is anything of great importance in it. I report the matter at length as I feel that Bashir Ahmad is quite unfit to hold a responsible position ot indeed to hold any position in a Political Office. I hear he has been writing a lot of rot to people here about his influential position in Kuwait and that he is the Sheikh’s greatest friend and that he has much in common with Major More since they are both of literary tastes etc. His past history does not chow that he has ever had a responsible post, he having been employed as S &amp; T tally clerk etc. I should be glad to hear whether you wish any action taken in the matter. Would it be any use to call on Akhtar to J xplain how he came into possession of the doeumentT Personally think not, and that the solution is the silent removal of Bashir Ahmad. \CONFIDENTIAL. b.o. *o. xxxxx KUWAIT 24th Bov either ^»22 I am aorry I have not been able to axifiver your D.G. of the loth November about Baehlr Ahmad sooner, but it arrived by the boat by which I went to Basrah. I never had any cause of complaint against Bashir Ahmad myself, except as regards his weakness at accounts and his health, but for these two reasons alone I would sooner not have him back here if it can be avoided. I always found him very hard working and willing, and I have more than once sent him away as not fit to work when he himself wanted to stick it out - he is an awful crock, and the B.O. thinks he has got T.B. He has never had anything to do with any confidential work here, or seen any of my confidential files, so never had any chance of going wrong in that line if he wanted to while with me. Daly’s report about him certainly does not make nice reading. I am Just on shore from the 'Barala' on ny way to ’Ujair and will look you up in Bushlre to-morrow if we stop long enough to go ashore, though I rather doubt if we will. -“ajor G. F. W. Anson, O.B.Ef ■ Hu 3 : ' ^ D.O. NO. ■WHWMM ? /^5 /&lt;■'» t r^o/ v f &gt; w xxxxx KUWAIT* Vth February iv&gt;«»3. I think It will Interest you to kno* that I had a letter from Bashir ivhmnd by last mail, In which I think I can »•« th« fruits of the letter which you said you were &amp;oin£ to write t&lt; him about hi* Bahrain exploits. He says he haa been ill a^ain since he got home and fears that he will never be able to serve in the Gulf climate again. He nays he ie going to try t get a Job in India, and asks me to give him a letter of intro ductlon and a private letter of strong recommendation to anyone I may know in the G. of I. Secretariate which I am naturally not doing) or, if he cannot get employment in India, to ask you to ost him to an office outside the Gulf. L4y new man, Muhammad Shafi Wuralshl, seems to be shaping very well indeed. He tPlks Arabic fluently which is a distinct advantage for Kuwait, where other languages are so little know and gives him a pull over be Bouza, who knew none, but for that,he too was entirely satisfactory, being &lt;\ good clerk and very willing. Xhe. lion *ble Mleut. Col. A. ?• Trevor, C.u.I., C.I.E., Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, b U G H I K £•D.C. Ko 15-o xxxxxx KUWAIT. xOta January i.v 2 ^ # I am aoncUng Mr. Stephens off by to-days boat, whether the 'Bamora 1 * comes in or not, and I know you would not have asked me to do this if It could have been avoided as It naturally ie meet inconvenient. I am still hoping, however, that the 'Bawora' msy come to-day, although Meepere have hewd nothing - but that quite poaeibly may mean that the Buohlre Meppers have not bothered to let them know. I do not know whether you are sending Ur. Kenezee as permanent Head Clerk, or merely as another stop-gap, nut if the latter, I trust it will rot be neceam ry to change him again until after th?e Conference is over. I am extremely sorry to lose #»r. Stephens, as I was Just congratulating myself on having such a good man, and I hope he is only being tit ken away temporarily. H. D. G. Lfiw, Esq., Secretary to the P.R.,2&lt;md October 1925 . In reply to your undated letter which reached me lait mall I regret that I am unable to help you In the matter, a* all matters relating to the Clerical Staff of the various Political Agencies, etc., in the Persian Gulf are in the hands of the Hon’ble the Political Resident. I am however forwarding your letter to the Secretary, Bushire, who has a record of your work at Bahrain as well as at Kuwait, and you on address him on the subject if you think it worth while. I much fear however that he will not be in a position to help you. Mr. Bashir Ahmad, Court Road, No.2, LAHORE.D.O, No* 203-S. October 19^5. I enoloee herewith in original a lon^ letter, undated, which I have received from one Bashir Ahmad, a former Head Clerk of mine. I have replied to him that I cannot do anything and that he had better address you if he thinke it worth whil^ though I fear you will not be able to help him either. He c me to the Gulf from the Punjab Educational Establieh- aent, and went to Bahrain when Dickson was P.A.. Diokeon apparently thought no end of him, and trusted him implicitly • a great deal too much, in fact, as it subsequently appeared • but when Daly went there he found out a lot of unpleasant things about him, as detailed in his memorandum Ho. 63/C of ^8th July * 921 . From Bahrain he came here, but I never had any cause of complaint agalndt him, except as regards his weakness at accounts and his health - both of which were very bad, but he isver saw any confidential files here, and never had a chance of going wrong In that line if he had wanted to. Captain B. Stuart Homer, Secretary to the Political Resident, B u 8 h 1 r e. iThe British Bushire, the fu- Renidency - December y refer to your Demi-official letter No .20'?-s, dated the S2nd October 1925^ Colonel Prideaux is not prepared to do anythinir for Bashir Ahmad, whose letter to yon T am returninp; herewith. * Please9.0. No. 153-3. XX XXX KUWAIT. 26th June 1926 . I aa writing to you about ay clerical staff Hr. 'Abdur R&amp;zaaq, niy Vernacular Cleric, or 'aunahl' to give him his official title, aa you no doubt remember asked for leave last year, and I was told that he could only have it if I could replace him locally - which I could not. tfell, this year he has cg&amp;in applied: he nts to go to Persia to study the language, which he has been working at here for some time. This asens a very worthy object, nd one which will improve his value ta Government very considerably, eo I thin* you will agree it should be encouraged if pofcsibie. He is of course entitled to leave, ad I think he badly needs it, as he has been ill this summer. As a matter of fact I am not forwarding his implica tion for leave, as I want to take him to Shir&amp;s with me when I go on recess. This is partly to help him, -a he/ will then be able to draw T.A., nd partly for ay own convenience - and I am of course entitled to take a clerk on recess with ae. Khan Sahib Ihtlahaa ud-Daul&amp;h Khan is due in Kar chi on the 4th July (I am writing from memory, &amp;nd may be a day out) and should be here about the 16 th. He will be acting for ae here while I am away on recess, but one can hardly ask him to do all the work alone. I see no prospect of oeing able recruit a temporary Vernacular Clerk here to do *Abdur Ra&amp;aaq’s work *hile he is away and I do not suppose you can spare one now any more than ya you could Iwst year. As a matter of fact the Khan hib knows Arabic about as v?©n c® he does 'ngilsh, so could easily do the vernacular part of the work himself, if he be given help in other ways - in f ct I think this would probably be better for him. Do you thlak you could spare me the services of a Second Clerk while I am on recess? I spoke to the Resident about this when he hub here but he naturally could not promise me anything then. I hope however that it will be possible. I do not necessarily suggest Mr. Athanasius, who is acting as my Her.d Clerk now, as he is a good man and probably too valuable, but anyone would do, though preferably a man with out his family with him. Captain 3 . Stuart Horner,Telegram (C). From rolitical, Kuwait. To Secretary, Bushire No. 1 6 ( • Dsted 13th July I 926 . Your demi-official letter of loth July. Thanks for the arrangement regarding clerical staff which meets require ments. As stated m my demi-official letter No.151-3, i wish to take 'Abdur Razzaq with me to Shiraz on duty instead of his taking leave, i presume there is no objection?D.O. No. H9-S. aONFID^jTlAi.. 25 th Noveaber \ r ^7 X was hopins to hear froa you by yesterday’s nail about Mr. Naris ’All, but nothing cace. I spoie to Colonel Haworth about him when he was over here the other day, and he e^id he would go Into the question with you, but no doubt he had not time to do so on his way through Bushire. The faot of the natter Is that WarIs ’All, although he knows a fair amount of Arabic for &amp; foreigner, Is definitely not up to the job of veraacul olerk la an Arabic speaking place. 1 have a strong aversion to putting ay signature to letters in a sort of 'pidgin' Arabic, which Is really all that his are,ae his idioms are mostly foreign, and the use of the definite article is a sealed book to him - the latter is a thing which many Persians and Indians seem to find difficult, probably because there is none in their own languages. The result is that I have to write my own Arabic letters {which Is what I usually do now) or else correct his out of all recognition. This Is hardly good enough, partioularly as I know that my Arabic, though certainly better than his, is not always quite what an Arab would write. I hope therefore you will go into the matter as eoon as you can, and try and find some other field for teris ’All's energies. I have no grouse against him in himself at all, but I think more is being asked of him than one has a right to expect. Unless you have got a real Arab available, I would very much prefer to be allowed to taxe on someone locally. Even then I would prefer a local man, as it is a very great advantage to have someone on my staff in &amp; responsible position lixe that with an intimate know ledge of local people and local conditions. I feel the lose of such a person very particularly at a time like Captain C. G. Prior, Secretary to the P.R., BushlreTelegram (C). From Secretary, Bushlre. To Resident in the Persian Gulf; repeated to Kuwait, No, 1276. Dated 5th December 1927. More finds that though Waris 'Ali's Arabic is good it is insufficient for correspondence and he wants an Arab. We cannot spare such a man and (? best) course appears for him to engage a local man he knows, Waris ’Ali to go to Bahrain as Second Munshi, 'Abdul Latif becoming Second Clerk and Ghulam Haidar reverting to Bushire. ’Abdul Latif is by origin a non-Muslim and cannot remain permanently on the Vernacular Cadre, and his reversion to Second Clerk will meet Political Bahrain's wish to retain him. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. ^ To Resident, ss Chakdara, Hinjam Radio; repd. Bushire. No. 225. Dated 11th December 1927. Secretary's telegram No. 1276. I trust that it will soon be possible to sanction the proposal that I engage a local man, as I am seriously handicapped in my work at present.Telegram (Code). From Political, Bushire, To Political, Kuwait; repeated to Bahrain, No. 1300 . Dated 12th December 1927. Please engage a. local man .ice Warls ’All and send th. Utter to Bahrain. On arrival at Bahrain will the Political A^ent please send Ghulara Haidar to Bushire, Abdul Latif t-Kln, is place as second cleric.Telegram (C) Prom Political, Bahrain To Political, Kuwait. No. 1013. Dated 1®th December 192? f Abdul ’Aziz Salih an Arab lately acting Passport Clerk here who Is strongly recommended by Alban applies for appointment of Munshi, Kuwait. Do you wish to consider his application. Saiyid 'Abdur Razzaq says that he is a good man and would meet the requirements. Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Political, Bahrain. No. 224. Dated 11th December 192?. Your telegram of 10th December No. 1013. Thanks. Other things being equal I would prefer a Kuwait man, but will be grateful if you will post particulars as to 'Abdul ’Aziz's age, birth place, qualifications and appearance.To i'tie J^oretary to th* Hon'ble th« Polltloal R#fl&lt; 3 *nt In the Perelin Gulf, BUSHIRE. r. Vf.-.fia 'All. »,Ki.;oaAhcug. x ds-te from fir. wan* 'All on the euojeot of his servloe. •h he is already under orders to leave nusait, the question of his grading is outside ay province, but perhaps ' ly 0 f ilr - l0n of nuallflcations .nay oe of assistance to you. As I have already told laptain Prior deml-omcial- ly, I consider hi® definitely unfit for the poet of 'munshl' in this Agency, or anywhere else where he would oe required to translate into Arabic or draft letters in that language, .aptain Prior apparently sae.aed to have heard that he had a Tuita reaarkable knowledge'of Arabic, This is not the case at all: 0 f nis idioais are foreign, and his t ratnaar is by no 0 * ans * ubt.;es, . iie I. .B a good / useful working anowleu t e for s .^rei^ner, and that is nii. But that is not enough for a 'au.-ishi': there should oe no fear of the language of a latter issuing from a Political Agency exciting ridicule, out that is just what a letter written by hi®, or by m, or by almost -vsr.y foreigner, might do. I think you will agree that one could tell from the language of it that the attached letter was not written by an Ungllshaan - yet his Rnglish la iriuan better thrm his Arabic. I *ibh to oak* it perfectly clear that, although I say r * e ie for the poet of 'raunshi H , I thiai he mi^ht oe ^st useful if othere!ee employed, xte has an extremely c ,ood Knowledge of Sn^lleh and an excellent hand#ritixi&amp;, and ie in opinion a very promising clera. A knowledge of Arabic hu an ne ae poeeensee is ueefui to anyone ojv this aide of wne dulf, and would be ^ulte eufficient to be very usefulIf Kuwait, 17 December 1927. De&amp;r Major More:-* I should like to recommend the bearer of this note for the position you have open. His name is Jaeim Bin Muhammad. He has been a student in our school for over a year and knows considerable English. His good points are that he has a close mouth and is, I think, entirely trustworthy and truthful. He is a very good student and study is his favorite occupation. He is not forward, perhaps not enough so, but when he has a thing to do he undertakes it readily. He has about ^ as good a knowledge of Arabic as the Arab schools here ^ive, and I bel^ve he hag taken specj. ^1 lessen s r j* of the leading mullas. His hand writing in Arabici8so A- gdoc[ 'thatwe^employ him for our language students for that subject, A and we would like to continue to have him for an nour a week. His English hand is also good. The points against him are his youth, although he is very likely as old as abdulra^-aaq was when he first entered government employ. His youth means that he is teachable, and I think he can be trained quite readily. He has not completed his English course, but I have no doubt he will soon learn the special vocabulary his position requires, and I am sure he will continue to study. If you decide to take him on and can give him permission to attend our school in the afternoon thi'ee, four or five days a week I will be willing to have him continue his study with me. * He is eager and he says his father is glad to have him enter govern meat employ. I 'would like him to stay a year of more in our school, but such a good opening may not be disregarded, and as I think he has the qualifications required for the office except enough English I am reco-muending him in the expectation that in aix months or a year’s time he will be found to be entirely satisfactory. Yours sincerely,I Tho Political A Dated the f A December 1927. Please see your telegram No.224. Abdul Aziz biii Hamad bin Saleh is a little man about aiight the size as Syed Abdul Hazza(i» and has a very/limp due to a fall in childhood. He has not got much of a 'presence* but is quite presentable and has been v/ell turned out whenever i have seen him. He does not enunciate his words very clearly but seems to have a fair command of English. He is 23 years age and was born in Zubair of a Kuwait father and Zubair mother. He lived in Kuwait for 3 years, in Bombay for 2| years and has been in Bahrein for about 2 years. He studied English in Bombay under a nan named Aimed Farid of Mangalore and went to the Revd.Mordyk»s school at Kuwait for one year. A.t Bahrein no worked for 1 year and 5 months wi th Abdulla Aujan &amp; Brothers and for 6 months at the Agency, Major J.0.MORE, D-S.Q, POLITICAL AGENT, KUWAIT. g &lt; &lt;». /i9^ British Resideney &amp; Csnsulats- General, [ZJZi Bushire. 30 th Ipril 1 ^ 6 , Mr« Norton orficiatin^ 2 nd Cierx here nae dot imfiieatea in an affair with a rersian weaa* in jmahire. The roliee teex up the ease tout thants te the Gererner's d°od offices we hare settled the natter so far as they are concerned* Sone rersians were also concerned in the natter and the case against them has oeen referred to w- Idlieh who it is thought azter May iztn may en- deavour to drag in Borton once more* Under these circumstances the Hen* Sle the Resident has decided that Rorten should fce got out of rersla as soon as possisie and since xoweit is the only place suitasie to which to post him he is seing sent off accordingly to you* bo case was proved against him and he is not in any sense Being sent away in disgrace* He is quite an able olerx and can worx well if Xept up to the marx* He Lt-Col* J.c. More, D.S.u., •roUUoM. A**nt, JCUnEIT. « II forward in original lettflr No- TA.Bush-11-28-29-545 dated 7th August 1928 from the A.G.O.R.-, New jelhi, to^etherr with its enclosure, regarding travelling allowance drawn by Norton for his family. *'»ill you kindly obtain and forward me his explanation? Kindly return the papers with your reply. i /u tjtrrsi sI Gopy of &amp; letter, No^TA.Bush-1 1-28-29'“54^ of 7th August 1928 fro® the A• G• G.R, to the Vice-Consul, Muhaafiarah.!- I have the honour to enclose a letter dated the 90 th &gt;- !a y 19^Q i roa one Mr. S.D«&gt; Pereira regarding an alleged fraudulent drawal of travelling allowance by Mr. A.S.Norton, a clerk in your office, for inforaation and action if anr considered necessary. Copy of a letter, dated Bushire 90th May 1928 froa one M S.D. Pereira” to the Asst. A.G.C.R., New Delhi;- I have just learnt that one Mr. A.S.Norton, a clerk in the British Residency at Bushire, has fraudulently drawn the sua of Ra99«*-8-0 in a travelling allowance bill for his wife and one and a half fare for three children froa Mohaaaerah to Karachi on the cash account of the Mohamaer&amp;h office for for Septaaber 1927 (I believe you will find it under voueher o of payaents for the Mohaaaer&amp;h for September 1927 ). * can say that ?£r. Norton went down on the leave in March and left his wife and children in Goa (Portuguese laalt mdia) and that he returned alone ,hen he .ae urlenUy re^ called. Hi» wife did not return to Mohaeraa and she ie s ti‘i in Goa (a. Police reports -ill prove) and thaTshe did not ^ e t Pl ?°! (Goa) after her 60la 6 there in “arch or , ; rIi have seen her there myself and I recentlv *«»r leAvin 6 for Gulf. I therefore say that she is o .a and-that she did not accoapany her husband when he returned to Muhaaaerah and ast neither has she joined hla after he is transferred to Sushire. If she is with hi» -h. when^rantfer?' f ° r ^ allowanoe f 1 ’ 08 “ohaaaerah to Bushlr. Even if you did not trust this .y word, you aav write oO the British Consul there and find out on oath whether Mrs -.orton did coae back to Mohaaaerah as per travelling allow- I therefore say that the allowance was drawn in fraud to the 8 e!!eni e orEs!392r8-0 Gd and h “ fraUdln6 Gov «a.ent PerslL^uirf^iSf^SitlL ^ 18 t0 th6 ResideUt in This man is a bad man and he should be punished. Hie wife has not left Goa from about March or April 1927 and is a^ 1 \ th ^ re wi ! ,h 4 h f r fa ther in law (after Norton took her to^ Goa she has not joined him again in the Persian Gulf I can testifv t.o t.Vii. .+ 0 + vjuxi . x cant.c. «... Political £ U » A 1 t. i4th i^oveaber I 9 id. : ^lth rafei'enoa to your D # 0* lettar of pth lnat #&gt; I return herewith the A.O.O.H'e letter ^o.TA,Bueh-H-aS-^p* ^4^ of ?th Au^uet *928 snd It* eaeloeur* jnd nttaoh Vr. ^ertoa v e explanation. ?r, Norton tell* *t verbally that it wee beaaue* cf hie wife'e ill- health thHt he took leave -at the tiae in &lt;lU£ftioa «o to be able to take her to India, and that, &amp;s you were attending her at the tiae, you will no doubt re- aeaber thie. / Dr. CJ. H. ^inooln, U.B.l!., viee-Coneul, Duhaaaarah. Copy of letter dated 14th Nov e '23 froa lir. A.ScNorton, to P.A., Kuwait I I am greatly surprised to see HoB.M's Vice-Consul, Muhaaaarah's letter dated 9 th November * 928 ,and in reply I ^ beg to explain that the Journey in question was actually ( performed and that the whole charge made in 'SoDoPereira's' letter to the A.G.C.R. is absolutely false and is a uUtK malicious attempt to ruin t3iS prospects and future career in this department. It is unknown to me who this '3.D.Pereira' is as neither there was or is a man of such a name In Bushire or in the Persian Gulf Residency or in offices subordinate to it # during recent years.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00039d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00039d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘I/10. Confidential papers re Agency staff.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1928</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-27T22:42:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (215 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The first two sets of correspondence in the file (each relating to a single member of Agency staff) are preceded by a title sheet (f 3, f 12). A contents page at the front of the file (f 2) lists these two cases, giving the individual’s name and post held.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 217; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-216; these numbers are also written in pencil but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and papers, including confidential notes, relating to staff at the Political Agency in Kuwait (including the News Agent, Assistant Surgeon, and Head Clerk). Many of the papers relate to the recruitment, departure, and transfer of staff between British offices in the Persian Gulf, and are indicative of a general opinion amongst British officers that reliable and able staff are in short supply in the region. Many papers also discuss the pay of staff, and assessments of staff performance, skills (typewriting, proficiency in English, Persian and Arabic) and general demeanour. The file’s principal correspondents are: the Political Agent at Kuwait (most notably, Captain Stuart George Knox and Captain William Henry Irvine Shakespear); the First Assistant Resident in the Persian Gulf (Captain L Birdwood).Much of the file’s correspondence relates to the sixteen-year career of Head Clerk Louis Michael D’Mello, and his movements between different British offices in the Gulf, including Kuwait, Mohammerah [Khorramshahr], and Bushire.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Political Agency, Head Clerk</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Confidentiality (personal data)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency, First Assistant Resident</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Political Agency, Assistant Surgeon</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Government personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00039d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>