<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000354_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-08-01T16:25:38.849Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">© PILE NO: 5/14 APRIL &amp; MAY, 1947 n ! lots n; 'a/ ■ 0 BRITISH CONSULATE MUSCAT PILE NO: 5/14 NAME OP PILE: SCHEME FOR FOREIGN ALLOWANCES (MISSION FUND, CONSULAR CUSTOMS, REBATE, ETC:)[ XS 019 (23/47) ] Circular No. 37 Confidential Foreign Office. S.W. 1 21s£ April, 1947 New Scheme for Foreign Allowances: 1. Mission Fund 2. Consular Customs Rebate Consul, My dear 1 enclose for your information two memoranda, the first on the administration of the fund for extraordinary entertainment to be created at each Mission as part of the new scheme for foreign allowances, and the second on the application of the concession to Foreign Service officers occupying Consular posts where Customs Duties aie payable. 2 Both memoranda are self-explanatory and will only come into force at any post as from the date on which the new allowances take effect at that post. Posts not yet visited by the Inspectors should take no action on these instructions. We are pressing forward as quickly as possible with applying the new scheme to all countries but posts not yet visited will have to continue to manage on the present ad hoc arrange- . o ments for pay and allowances for the time being. Notification of the amount allocated for each Mission Fund is made to the post concerned iL as soon as possible after the return of the Inspectors to this country. 3 I should explain that the whole new scheme of foreign allow- 1 ’ ances and the details of its working are confidential to the Foreign Service (including temporary officers filling Foreign Service posts on a ‘ 1 fully-paid basis) and should not be communicated to any persons, official or otherwise, outside the Service, e.g., Service Attaches, Passport Control Officers, British Council staff, &amp;c. , . 4 A memorandum setting out a medical scheme tor the roreign Service and showing how it will be administered will be circulated as soon as it is ready. 5. I am sending a similar circular Representatives (as No. 077). letter to His Majesty’s Yours sincerely, H. A. CACCIA. His Majesty’s Superintending Consular Officers 14005 33405—33Memorandum &lt; NEW SCHEME FOR FOREIGN ALLOWANCES : MISSION FUND Part of the new scheme for foreign allowances which formed the subject of Mr. Caccia’s circular letter No. 0150 of 26th October, 1946, is the provision of a mission fund for extraordinary entertainment. The following general principles will govern the allocation and administra tion of these funds. Purpose of the Fund (1) The purpose of the fund is to cover extraordinary and unpre dictable items of entertainment which, owing to the irregularity of their incidence, cannot be provided for in normal foreign allowances, or in the case of information officers, from any provision which may be made for entertainment in their current budgets, e.g., visits of special missions or important persons for whom special entertainment has to be provided. The question of Naval visits is dealt with in the annex to this memo randum. It is not intended that the fund shall cover small items of day-to-day entertaining such as a lunch or dinner-party of normal size and style for an important visitor, unless it is in the public interest that such a party should be on a much larger scale than a lunch or dinner party customary at the post. Nor is it intended that the fund shall be drawn upon by officers for large-scale entertainment of a regular nature (e.g.. King's birthday celebrations) since provision will have been made for these items in normal foreign allowances, or information budgets. Administration of the Fund The administration of the fund and allocations from it will be left to the discretion of the Head of the Mission. To assist him. it is suggested that the fund should normally be administered at each Mission by a committee consisting of the heads of the different sections, Political, Commercial, Consular and Information, and presided over by His Majesty's Representative or his Deputy. Each application for an allo cation from the fund must be considered by the committee. When an allocation has been decided upon, the amount will be drawn from the Mission’s current account and paid to the Officer making the application, who will be required to render a statement, supported where possible by vouchers, to the Committee after spending the money, showing how it has been spent and returning any surplus over expenditure. It will be the responsibility of the Head of Mission to ensure that the fund is properly accounted for. A statement in triplicate should accompany the quarterly accounts showing the amount of the annual fund allocated to the Mission, the names and posts of Officers who have drawn upon the 14005a 33405—33a B^ fund during the quarter together with an account of the purpose of each allocation and the circumstances necessitating it. The statement should end with a certificate signed by the Head of Mission in the followino- form :— &amp; “ I hereby certify that .... pounds have been expended as shown in the above statement from this year’s Mission Fund of £ ... . under my administration during the quarter ended upon extraordinary expenditure on entertainment not otherwise provided for, that I have examined the subsequent accounts sub mitted to me by these Officers, and that I am satisfied that the money has been spent for the purpose for which it was allocated.” Vouchers submitted to His Majesty’s Representatives by the Officers should be kept at the Mission for a minimum period of two years, and until they have been seen by an Inspector, should he desire to examine them. They may then, with his authority, be destroyed. The only vouchers which should accompany the statement are receipts from individual Officers for moneys allocated to them. Officers Entitled to Draw on the Fund Heads of Mission and Charge d’Affaires will not be entitled to draw on the Mission Fund. Normally the only Officers entitled to draw will be established Officers of Branch' A of the Service, and Branch B Officers, whether established or temporary, in charge of consular posts (honorary officers being excluded). When the committee is in doubt about any particular allocation Heads of Mission should refer to the Foreign Office for instructions. Consular Officers residing outside the metropolitan territory of the Government to which their superintending Mission is accredited and independent officers who have no superintending Mission will be able to draw on a fund kept in the Foreign Office for this purpose. The pro cedure will be substantially the same and these officers will apply to the Foreign Office and account to the Foreign Office in the same way as officers in metropolitan territory apply to and account to their Mission. Independent Officers and Officers outside metropolitan territory should forward their account for this money annually to the Foreign Office under cover of a separate despatch supported fully by vouchers whenever possible, and should not include expenditure under this heading in their quarterly accounts. A separate schedule should be inserted in their quarterly accounts giving the reference to the despatch reporting such expenditure. Foreign Office, 1st March, 1947.f each ;hould 3 win' ed as nd of Twise ; sub- 1 1 the d.” t the P two iesire •oyed. 3eipts draw r will icers. Drary ' an y Office f the and )le to pro- o the ly as ision. lould Dffice lever their their such /'N 3 ANNEX Naval Visits We fully realise that it is neither possible or desirable to lay down rigid rules for dealing with naval visits which are now starting again. Circumstances vary widely; for instance, whether the visit is a Fleet visit with a Flag Officer or a visit of a single small ship, whether the visit is to a capital or provincial town, whether the local British community is large or small, &amp;c. Nevertheless, after discussion with the Admiralty, we think that the following general guidance may be useful, particularly in considering calls on the Mission Fund. Since the cost of entertaining by Foreign Service Officers by public funds fall on the British taxpayer, the scope of entertainment during the naval visits should be to further the purpose of these visits; that is to show the unity of purpose behind all of His Majesty’s Services and impress upon foreign governments and people the power and efficiency of the Royal Navy and the quality of the Officers and men. With this in mind, it is desirable that the Senior Naval Officers should meet the appropriate local authorities at luncheon or dinner and that a cock tail party or similar gathering should be arranged for wider contacts with the local community and British subjects. In a capital the Head of Mission will, no doubt, wish to take the major part in these entertain ments in all the more important naval visits, and the cost for enter- ment by a Head of Mission will fall on his frais and not on the Mission Fund. Apart from this the appropriate official entertaining will be done by the Consular Officer. As visits become regular, the Foreign Service Officer concerned will, no doubt, normally try to arrange his ordinary entertainment of local officials to fit in with these occasions. His Foreign Service allowance should therefore ordinarily cover the cost in most cases. But if the visit is at short notice or of particular importance, the Foreign Service Officer will have a case for a grant from the Mission Fund to help him to meet part or the whole of the extra cost. Whether in a capital or elsewhere it will ordinarily fall to the Consular Officer as the head of the British community to co-ordinate the arrangements for providing recreation on shore. The greatest importance is attached to looking after the ship’s company and every thing possible should be done to ensure the success of these arrangements. But any costs should, if possible, be borne by the local British com munity rather than the United Kingdom taxpayer. Where the local British community cannot do this, the costs may fall on the Consular Officer. In such circumstances the costs should be kept small and should be for recreation, such as football and cricket and not for free beer. 33405—33a b 24 Confidential NEW SCHEME FOR FOREIGN ALLOWANCES: CUSTOMS REBATE FOR FOREIGN SERVICE OFFICERS OCCUPYING CONSULAR POSTS During the course of their recent investigations to determine the rate at which Foreign allowances shall be fixed (Mr. Caccia’s circular letter, No. 0150, of 26th October, 1946), the Inspectors have drawn attention to the circumstance that Poreign Service Officers serving in a Consular Section at a Mission or at an independent consular post do not always enjoy certain customs privileges accorded to their colleagues serving in a diplomatic capacity. In some countries it has been the practice for the Head of the Mission to allow Consular Officers the privilege of importing articles under diplomatic cover thus avoiding the payment of local customs duties. This practice is, however, by no means universal, and it is only logical that, in order to secure uniformity of treatment to members of the Service who may in future be required to fill either a consular or a diplomatic post, this discrepancy should be removed. It has therefore been decided that, as from the date of the intro duction of the new allowances, Consular Officers who have not been able to obtain remission of local customs duties, either as a courtesy on the part of the local authorities or as a privilege from the Head of the Mission, may charge to public funds the amount of the import duties on goods brought into their country for their personal use. It will be the responsibility of Heads of Mission to administer this scheme for Consular Officers residing in the metropolitan territory of the Government to which the Mission is accredited. Such officers will pay duties in the first instance from their private funds and will then forward a claim to the Head of the Mission supported by the necessary customs vouchers. The claim will be examined at the Mission and pro vided no objection is seen the money may be refunded to the Consular Officer from the Mission current account. The Mission should include in their quarterly accounts with the Foreign Office a statement in triplicate showing the names of Consular Officers who have benefited under this scheme during the previous quarter, together with the amounts paid and a brief description of the goods in respect of which payments have been made. This statement should be supported by the Officers’ receipts for money paid to them from the Mission. The vouchers forwarded by the Consular Officer in respect of his claim should be retained at the Mission for a minimum of two years and destroyed with the approval of an inspector. The same concession will be allowed in respect of motor cars imported by Consular Officers for their personal5 w/mgBmm m use. These facilities will apply only to such goods as are exempt from customs charges when imported by Diplomatic Officers. Consular Officers who have no superintending Mission or who reside outside the metropolitan territory of the Government to which their superintending Mission is accredited, may charge direct in their quarterly accounts with the Foreign Office payments made by them in respect of import duties into their country of residence. Consulates superintended by another post should, however, obtain the authority of their superintending Consular Officer before doing so, and send copy of that authority to the Foreign Office when reporting the expenditure. Officers covered by this paragraph should report by separate despatch to the Foreign Office at the end of each quarter the amount of duty claimed and forward the receipts of the customs authority for inspection. They should not include these vouchers in their quarterly accounts, where a separate schedule should be inserted giving the reference number of the despatch reporting the disbursements. It is not proposed to restrict this concession only to articles bought in the United Kingdom since many Officers import goods to their posts from other countries both within and, subject to exchange control regulations, without the Empire. The concession cannot, however, be applied to goods not imported by the Officer himself, but bought locally and upon which import or excise duty has already been paid by the merchant who imported or retailed such goods. The cost of these articles will have already been taken into consideration by the Inspectors during their investigations when determining the new Foreign allowances. Only established Officers of Branch A of the Service not enjoying diplomatic status are entitled to benefit under this scheme. It is not the ^intention that the scheme should replace any existing arrangements whereby the Consular Officers have not been liable to pay customs duties either through local courtesy or through facilities made available by the Head of the Mission; on the contrary, such arrangements should be maintained wherever possible. It has been decided that a similar concession with respect to pur chases of petrol by Consular Officers, although desirable in order to bring them into line with their diplomatic colleagues, is not administratively practicable. In conclusion it is emphasised that Consular Officers should make the most of any privileges which the local authorities may extend on the occasion of a premiere installation and they should be prepared to take the maximum quantities of dutiable goods with them on taking up their first appointment. Foreign Office, ls£ March, 1947Confidential My dear Consular Officer, I ENCLOSE a memorandum on the machinery for varying the new foreign allowances in accordance with changes in the cost of living. It is no exaggeration to say that the success or failure of these allow ances depends in no small degree on obtaining an agreed cost-of-living figure for each post. The response to the Inspectors request for cost-of-living index figures made when visiting posts has not been uniformly satisfactory. I should therefore be grateful if careful study could be given to this memorandum and to the preparation of the figures required from Missions which have not yet sent in cost-of-living indices or whose proposals have not yet been agreed. 2. We do not wish to burden posts unnecessarily with producing these figures and for this reason we have agreed that the system of sending in the half-yearly returns for which this memorandum calls should not come into force until 1st January, 1948. We rely on Missions already visited to report any changes in the cost of living meanwhile if a complete 10 per cent, up or down is registered. 3. A similar circular is being sent direct to Superintending Consular Officers who have no superintending Mission and to Officers in charge of posts outside the metropolitan territory of the Government to which you are accredited, and the references above to Missions apply to them mutatis mutandis. Extra copies are enclosed for sending to Consular Officers within your metropolitan territory, but we shall not need reports from these officers as your figures should be applicable to them. Yours sincerely, H. CACCIA. Foreign Office, \5th May, 1947CONFIDENTIAL Memorandum VARIABILITY OF THE NEW FOREIGN ALLOWANCES 1. Mr. Caccia’s circular letter No. 0150 of 26th October. 1946, outlined the system on which we are calculating the new foreign Allowances. If this system is to work we must vary the allowances to •'“ N meet changes in the cost of living. In calculating allowances we take -v account of three elements— (A) Allocation for expenditure in the United Kingdom as agreed with the Treasury. (B) Local expenditure to cover personal and private household expenses. (C) Local expenditure on representation. 2. United Kingdom allocation^ —When the Ministry of Labour cost-of-living index and variations in income tax, taken together, show an alteration from the date of last adjustment of a complete 10 per cent, up or down, we shall adjust the United Kingdom allocation, excluding the portion earmarked for insurance. These figures will be reviewed in this department at six-monthly intervals in time for adjustments to be made from 1st April and 1st October in each case. 3. Local expenditure. —When the local cost-of-living figures and the rate of exchange, taken together, show a variation of a complete 10 per cent, up or down, the (B) and (C) elements will be adjusted accordingly; that is to say, the percentage variation will be applied ^not to the foreign allowance but to the total local expenditure as approved by the Inspectors. These adjustments will be made half-yearly as from 1st April and 1st October. If, however, the local cost-of-living index and the rate of exchange, taken together, show a change of over 20 per cent, the adjustment will be made immediately from the date when the change occurred. 4. Definition of percentage variations. —^By a variation of a complete 10 per cent, we mean that there must have been an effective change of 10 per cent, or more as the result of the various factors outlined above on the figure used for the last adjustment of allowances; that is to say, if the index figure used at the date of the last adjustment was 200 there must be a rise or a fall of 20 points before we will adjust the allowance. Similarly a major change of 20 per cent, means a variation of 20 per cent, on the index figure used for the last adjustment. 14045—1 33521—17a2 5. Cost-of-living indices .—In order to apply this system, we must have, at the earliest possible date after the visit of the Inspectors to any post, figures agreed between the post and the Foreign Office on which to work. We shall need two agreed index figures to show the cost of living at the post at the date of the Inspectors’ visit : (#) including rent. (b) excluding rent. 6. Naturally, we shall want to use the official cost-of-living figures whenever possible. There will, however, be cases in which the official figures do not effectively show variations in the cost of living or where ^ no official figures are published. In such cases we shall have to supple ment or replace the official figures by others from some reliable source, e.g., a British Bank, a British Chamber of Commerce, a firm of Chartered Accountants or any responsible British or foreign firm. At posts where there are neither adequate official figures nor reliable figures produced by any local body we may have to try and calculate our own figures. In the last-mentioned case it may be necessary for posts to submit complete lists of prices of the commodities going to make up a normal cost-of- living index, giving the appropriate “weighting” to the various commodities, and to work out from this a local cost-of-living index. Once the basis for such a special cost-of-living index had been agreed with us, it would be for the post concerned to do the calculations and to submit &gt; the result, with the necessary supporting statistics, to us at the appropriate intervals. 7. It is important that, whatever system is finally decided upon for each post, the method of applying the system should be made clear to and agreed with the Foreign Office as soon as possible. It is equally important that proposals to change the method of presenting an index figure or to correct it should not be made lightly once it has been agreed with this department; whenever possible, figures from the same source should be used continuously and processed in the same way each time. 8. Some of the Missions already visited by Inspectors have sent in to this department the two cost-of-living figures, i.e., including rent and excluding rent, referred to above, and have secured our agreement to them. Other Missions that have not already submitted these figures should do so as soon as possible. Missions that have not yet been visited by the Inspectors should go carefully into the question in order to be in a position to discuss with the Inspectors what figures can best be used and to be able to make recommendations to this department on this point as soon as the Inspectors have finished their investigation. 9. Periodic Reports .—Beginning on 1st January, 1948, every Mission and every Consular post having no Superintending Mission or situated outside the metropolitan territory of the Government to whichthe Superintending Mission is accredited should forward to this depart ment at six-monthly intervals the two cost-of-living figures showing respectively the position at 31st December and 30th June immediately preceding. These half-yearly returns should be made as soon as possible after the dates in question and should in no case reach this department later than the end of March and the end of the September quarters respectively. These returns are to be made whether or not there has been any change in the cost of living. They should take the form of a certificate signed by the Head of the post to the effect that, according to the method of calculation agreed with this department in correspondence ending with letter of , the cost-of-living index stood at the figure of including rent, and excluding rent as on (30th June or 31st Decem ber) The report should be accompanied by a banker’s certificate showing the rate of exchange for the purchase of local currency on that date and the average rate of exchange during the preceding six months, i.e., the rate of exchange at which the staffs concerned have been able to purchase local currency. At posts where officers have been authorised to cash their sterling at an unofficial rate of exchange, the report should also include a certificate signed by the Head of the post and stating the average unofficial rate of exchange for the past six months and the rate on the date of the report. 10. If an examination of these figures here shows that the cost of living and the average rate of exchange, taken together, have produced a variation of a complete 10 per cent, up or down since the allowances were last fixed, the (B) and (C) elements in the allowances will be adjusted accordingly with effect from 1st April or 1st October k respectively. 11. Special Reports .—Apart from these regular six-monthly reports, the only case in which a Mission should report a variation in the cost of living will be when the cost-of-living index and the rate of exchange, taken together, produce a variation of a complete 20 per cent, from the index at the time when the allowances were last adjusted. If this happens the Mission or Consular post having no Superintending • Mission or situated outside the metropolitan territory of the Government to which the Superintending Mission is accredited should immediately forward a report in the same form as laid down for the half-yearlv reports. The (B) and (C) elements in the allowances will then be adjusted with effect from the date of the change. ©</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000354_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/140</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000354</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/140</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/14 SCHEME FOR FOREIGN ALLOWANCES (MISSION FUND, CONSULAR CUSTOMS, REBATE, ETC.)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-14T22:00:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. There are file notes on folio 9.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the following Foreign Office memoranda (with covering circulars) concerning revised foreign allowances: (1) Mission Fund and Consular Customs Rebate, March 1947; (2) Variability of the New Foreign Allowances, May 1947.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Subsistence allowances</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Grants</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000354#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>