<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000146_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T14:07:17.498Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">K&lt;' © / EXPRESS LEV^EB From To Mo.C/9 Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Prodrome, London. * CAMP, MUSCAT, the 3rd April 1948. Reference Commonwealth Relations Office express letter No.E xt.631/48 dated 17th March 194 Saluting Stations in Muscat and Oman. 2. Sultan has confirmed that the only batteries capable of returning salutes in his terri tories are the Mirani fort batteries at Muscat. ATTESTED. (SGD.) N* P.GUNTHER. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. (SGD.) W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf NPGmi , 9000. iiiXt • Any further communicat should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, L.P.—No. 8 ..10426 quoting '.M99/48 . .$ Admiralty, S.W.l. (a) Sir UNP-^XED I am commanded “by My Lords Commissioner^ Atwiralty to acquaint you that a list of Salut Stations in ports throughout the world has been promulgated recently as an Admiralty Fleet Order. The list, however, is not complete and the only information available in certain cases is that for July 19^9 when the previous issue of an Admiralty Fleet Order on this subject was made. 2. It was known at that time that in MUSCAT and OMAN a saluting battery existed in Muscat and I am to request that you obtain an up to date list of Saluting Stations in Muscat and Oman and the position of the batteries w'hich will return salutes in order that this information can be promulgated as an amendment to the latest Admiralty Fleet Order. 1 ^ I am, Sir, four obedient Servant, Y* The Under Secretary of State, Commonwealth Relations Off3 Downing Street, S .vv. 1 • ■i RWB/PJF/C.C.B. 'CtAAAAsW sous™* /» AAj+svUsfesl * ^ 0“,', tlAA/ts I ^(j , wx «ik ^ 1 4 - m 1348 p. ZW/ttA WITH %Draft Letter .© Lieutenant Colonel Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., The Residency, Bahrain. Ext. /in \ Ju*&lt; My dear Hay, 6 1349 cu~i ' s- (t&amp;No. j. i lc D* a^r^^ u f\ r r-o- ^ ^ / 5 Would you please refer to your printed letter No* 1745 - S of -the 9th Octobei/about the flying of flags by hvbs.ct»J r M B..3L..S. and vessels visiting Stiarjah and 4” Bubal? . L We have/gone into the/question herq sn^d- r. position seems to be that a ship always Of v flies lat its stem \the flag of cipher the State where it is registered or/the State of which its crew are nationals- /-ilnnay ^ftMT r als o) sometimesrf ly the flag of th^- ooujufrry j /a O^A which ibs charterers belong/ As a&lt;t Matter / k%Q*f U» cJsfihr*&gt;i of courtesy a ship *©a«r7fly at the foremast the flag of the country of destination when ~tU U(L*4,9 jioiag^into one of ports or anchorages. This &gt; ^understands is often done as a gesture of courtesy to the local Sovereign or Ruler, /andEXT vs\' )ENi * PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY , BAHRAIN , the 6 th December, 1947 So INDEXED )+o- rw. Please refer to correspondence ending with your ,y r &amp; Ky&amp;P p /too. telegram No.10978 dated the 24th August 1947 in which you stated tnat nis Majesty's Government agreed with Galloway regarding the undesirability of the Shaikh of Kuwait's suggestion that ships should be requested to fly the Kuwait flag within the limits of Kuwait.Bay. the Shaikh was pursuing this matter further and had asked Gray, Mackenzie to have Kuwait flags made for B.I. boats to fly when they visit the port. Quite apart from this Gray, Mackenzie apparently on their own initiative have suggested that B.I. boats should fly the national flags when visiting Bahrain, Dubai and Sharjah; they have been asked not to v pursue this proposal. in this matter and would request that it may be further examined. According to Oppenheim vide Section 187(4) at page 387 of Vol.I 'A littoral State may make laws and regulat ions regarding maritime ceremonials to be observed by such foreign merchantmen as enter its territorial maritime belt.' The Gulf Shaikhdoms are in name in any case independent and fly their own flags ashore and I see no reason therefore why they should not ask foreign merchantmen to fly their flags in their territorial waters. It has been our policy to preserve the independence of these States as against Saudi Arabia, Iraq and Persia and I am doubtful whether the flying of Kuwait flags by merchantmen in the Kuwait Bay will really detract from His Majesty's Government's position in the Gulf. 4. If as a result of further examination of the question from the legal aspect it is found that there is no objection from the point of view of Kuwait's limited sovereignty to the national flag being flown by steamers entering Kuwait Bay I recommend that we should tell Gray, Mackenzie that if the Shaikh of Kuwait asks them to fly Kuwait flags in Kuwait Bay they may do so but that they should refer to us if they receive a similar request from any of the other Gulf Shaikhdoms, and not take any initiative in the matter themselves. 5. I have not had an opportunity of consulting the S.N.O.P.G. but I do not think the Royal Navy will be affected. I understand they do not fly national flags in foreign ports. In the Gulf Shaikhdoms and Muscat they usually hoist the local flag when the Ruler comes aboard and while his salute is being fired. ^— 6 . I am sending a copy of this letter to the S.N.O.P.G. 2. During my recent visit to Kuwait I learnt that 3. I do not altogether agree with Galloway's views E.P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G wiictjLvao wiij # ivi♦ vj • 2 Commonwealth Relations Office DOWNING STREET, LONDON. S.W.l 'LB'M.01813/47 My dear Harrison, fi /O Military Branch, Admiralty, 3* W* 1* I Oja % 9th November, 1947 k w w b With reference to Donaldson 1 s letter of the 7th November (Nxt. 1820/47} to General Money and pyman f s letter to you of the 13 th November, I write to say that we agree with the Foreign Office’s views about the flying of Arab Flags by vessels visiting Sharjah and Dubai* We should like to point out, however, that the gesture of flying foreign flags is purely one of courtesy and that there will be occasions when some merchantship concerned will not actually be carrying the actual flag 'of the country visited* Yours sincerely. F.A*K« Harrison, iSsq* , Commonwealth Relations Office, 3 &lt; //»1 • GCBD/NMBTelegrams: (Shipping) “Shipmikder, Telex, London.” (Inland Transport) “Transminrt, Telex, London.” Telephone— Abbey 7711 Extn. ^ 4 ' '^3 fcra Our Reference 3579/11&gt; Your Reference / r/ T: T* v MINISTRY OF TRANSPORT , 1 Berkeley Square House, © London, W.l. ' November&gt; 1947. Dear Urau/s. Mol mV* 1 j if L - Ci - * i* i CaCA^ 19 INDEXED I refer to my iv.ttTri 1 tu Drjfialdson of 8 th November and to Pyman’s letter E.9786/66/91, of 13th November, about the flying of flags by B.l. vessels visiting Sharjah and Dubai. lie entirely agree with Pyman’s remarks and think there would be no harm in vessels flying the national flags of the states in question. It should be made clear that it would be purely an act of courtesy. I am copying this letter to Dodds and Pyamn. Yours Aeti \ t' v/ |w 7 fa: ^ (A*; MaJ .Gen. R.C. Money, tv-* 1 V , k P.A.K. Harrison, Esq. , f Commonwealth Relations Office, JjyM' l\ * Downing Street, S.W.l.“X2MM' (E 9780 / 66 / 91 ) Mtc\ i C C onf xdenulsl : * V/ill you please refer to Bahrain letter No. G/995 cf the 4th October and Hay’s reply which you copied to us under No. NXT 2244, about the flying of flags by B.I. vessels visiting Sharjah and Dubai. The present proposal has presumably now been shelved as a result of Hay's action, but since similar questions may arise in future, possibly in connexion with foreign ships, we have thought it as well to look into the question. (Incidentally we note that the request did not come from the Sheikhs nor even from the British India Steam Navigation Company itself but only from the Bombay Agents of Messrs. Cray, Mackenzie and Company and we find it difficult to see what standing they could have for expressing any desires on the subject at all). Subject to anything which the Ministry of Transport may say, the position seems to be that a ship always flies e.g. at the stern its own flag i.e. the flag of the state where it is registered or that cf the state of which its crew are nationals and may sometimes also fly that of the state of which the charterers are nationals. The only question is therefore whether a ship should additionally fly at the foremast the flag of the country cf destination on coming into one of its /ports F.A.K. Harrison, Nsq., Commonwealth Relations Cxiicc*f A i t' j 'ports or anchorages. That we believe is very oi uen done as a gesture of courtesy to the local sovereign or ruler and tne oheihiis are undououedly in that position locally. ^he 'gesture is not one that has any particular inte r nat ional implication. In the case of Dubai, Sharjah similar status we do not think that be any objection to the local xlags at the foremast by incoming ships a courtesy and certainly do not think would prejudice our international r the Sheikhdoms concerned, though we would be better for this to be done are approaching and entering ports and not territorial waters as such. I am sending a copy of this letter to Major General Money of the Ministry of Transport with reference to your letter No. EXT 1820/47 of the 7th November to him, nd to Dodds a l, die Admiralty. and places of there would being flown s an act of that this ight to protect think that it only when ships or anchorages O'*** (L.F.L. Pyman)Telegrams: (Shipping) “Shipmindkr, Tblhx. Lokdok.” (Inland Transport) “TRANsmifRY, Tklbx, Lobdok.” Telephone—A bbky 7711 Exrir. Any further covivmnication should be addressed to :— THE SECRETARY and the following reference quoted Your reference- INDEXED lit uear rpe'^lr^ MINISTRY OF TRA^SPORT^ Berkeley-Square House/j^ London,- W.l. 8 th V. QjVemb e r, ^ 9 4 7 / &lt; ?o3 /gio 11 l\c~ H f* Thank you for your'lstter, 1820/47, of the 7th November, ffe ;ill look into the problem of flag in Persian Gulf territorial waters and let you have a reply as soon as pgssible. Our first reaction is to support Colonel Hay. C.P.Donaldson,Csq., Commonwealth Relations Downing Street, b.A.l.ar -V'irr tiv “I Mr&gt;Donal^gon Please see Political Agent Bah.oeia.'s letter No.C/995 of the 4th October, and Political Resident’s letter No.1743-3 of the 7th October in reply about the flying of the Ruler's flags by B.I.S.N. Company's vessels entering the ports of Dubai and Sharjah.CONFIDENTIAL Draft Ext •1820/47 ® I &amp; i a &lt; 7 NOV 1947 To: Major General R.C.Money, C.B., M.C., Shipping Relations, ^Foreign Division) Ministry of Transport. We have recently been examining the question thr fljing nf tfe flags of the Rulers of the Arab Sheikhdoms f A lu~ in the Persian Gulf and the Sultan of Muscat^by British /tviovci— ilwT vessels entering th^ir/ports• The question arose over a rcmiest f-jpom the Sheikh of Koweit that^in order to -arrii'iD. his sovereignty over the waters of the Koweit Bay, all ships Ci. Qs entering the Bay should^fly his flag. After consultation with the Aclmiralty and the Foreign Office it was agreed that it was undesirable to accept the Sheikh's request on the ground that to do so would be likely to lead to similar requests from other Persian Gulf Rulers and might result in awkward international complicationsj 2. ^ The Politid&amp;l Resident in the Persian Gulf has now informed us that the Agents for the British India Steam Navigation Company have sought approval for ships of this Company to fly the flags of the Sheikhs of Dubai and Sharjah during visits to these ports as an act of courtesy to the Rulers concerned. I enclose for your ^^information a copy of letter No.C/995 of the 4th October from the Political Agent, Bahrein (who is in local charge of H.M.G's relations with the Trucial Sheikhdoms of Dubai arid Sharjah) to the Political Resident on this subject and a copy of the Political Resident'/^/letter No.1743/5 ^ y /$42&gt; of the 9th October in reply. You will see from this j' —r'Vv £ I correspondence that from the political aspect-, it wets ’A- considered inadvisable to accede to the request of the /» B.I.S.N. Company's Agents. 3 # Internationally the Arab States of the Persian Gulf do not enjoy independent status. They are under r+ r t Y 4a—W 1 nna under the protection of H.M.G* with whom they have speoiart A / I-'Y P^uU l* ls\. treaty relations. Muscat is aoni«wh«rt diff■rent .r, /^crrmMr-tt^ though subject to our influence, tluw It rlie is, ^ /-/a, ^ tnohninr^ljn nt nny rntnj free to conduct rbs own foreign relations mii hns As you may know, the ^ Persian Govemment^heec in the past claimed sovereignty over the islands of Bahrein, and (though in a somewhat shadowy form) over other territory on the Arab side of the Gulf. &lt;Ve are most anxious to avoid any revival of these claims and agree with the view expressed in para.5 of the Political Agents letter ^Sexwii-te that there might be seme danger of this were the flying of the Rulers’ flags by British/-^--* vessels to be taken as a form of recognition of thai^full sovereignty over their coastal waters. 'S[' fo '3 /7- 3 /u,' ^IcS-U C ^-0 ^ 4« It seems to us to be desirable to obtain a general ruling on this matter aad having regard to the special position of the Arab States in the Gulf and the Sultanate of Muscat^and recognised international practice. I should therefore be grateful if you would inform me of the international procedure covering the flying of national flags by vessels entering foreign ports and for your iuZ *7 views on the application of this procedure to.jports in th* Arab tn the Prr-iinn finlf nnd-ftfmfri?+n I am sending a copy of this letter to tke ^ Admiraltyj (Wi'.DaCLla) and to^b^oreigg^Off ice) (Wg-ifymirH) ^Sgd) E p DO M MDSOWX; o i i 1 coapipamAL . f./nEXED *•&gt; * So. 1745- S. / J W fKi \ C&lt;\^yh&gt;. ( H '' 1 ^ r /V s . The Hon* hie the t_olit_ical Resident, Persian Gulf, • . presents his compliments to His Majesty 1 s Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, King Charles Street, WHITEHALL, LONDON. S.W.1 ~ and has the honour to transmit to him % cony of the undermentioned doaument(s). PERSIAN GUIP RESIDENCY, 3 AH R A Hi, the 9th Octob erj 19 47 . Reference tc previous correspondence. Number and Date Description of enc lo sure, 3ubj ect 1. D.O, letter No.C/995 dated 4th October, 1947 from G.M. Jackson, Esq., MBE., Political Agent, Bahrain to Lt-Col.A.C. Galloway, CIE., OBE.. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 2. D.O.letter No.l743-S dated 9th October, 1947 from Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, to G.N.Jackson, Esq., MBE., Political Agent, Bahrain. 1 LB* FLYING OF FLAGS By B.__I. S. &amp; N. VESSET.fi VISITING SHARJAH AND DUBAI. . . The 4th of October, 1947. Dear Colonel Calloway, essrs. Cray ? ae^enzie 4- Company’s representative in Dubai has stated that it Is the desire of their Bombay Agents that the British India Steam Navigation Company’s vessels should fly the flags of the ohaiKhs of ubai and Sharjah at tne foremast during their ships’ stay in the ihaL-iha’ ports, as aii act of courtesy to the Chaikhs. S. Che rtesi iency Agent has enquired whether tliere is any political objection to their being supplied with . specimen flags. 3. It appears to mo that to concede the flying of the ihalXhs* flags by British ships in their terri torial waters is to admit their full sovereignty over these waters, '%n©reas their acceptance of our protection from attack by sea constitutes in itself a delegation of their sovereignty in our favour, although not in favour of any other power. protection appears to have been offered to the Crucial shaikhs and to the bhaikh of Bahrain in Article 10 of Treaty No. XIX of 1330 in , t r r In ol. XI of Aitchison's Treaties; and again to the Jhaikh of Bahrain and to the ohaiith of { atar in Article 3 of Croat/ No. £ of 1361 and in Article 11 of Treaty Ho. XXXIII of 1916 in the same part of the same volume. 4. The divisibility of sovereignty was a principle well established in Bis Majesty’s government’s relations witn the Indian .caters; and, similarly, sovereignty in ^ I these territorial waters appears to be divided between ' * I the shaikhs a no Bis aiesty 1 s Novfvrnraent. % I V f 5. Whether this view is accepted or not, I feel that, if we start to advertise the sovereignty of the Nhalkhs in these waters by flying their flags, it is possible that Persia - or any other power that may lay dale to these ports - might try to contest this recognition by instructing their vessels to fly their own national flags in these raters. 6. This is a : atter that affects all the Rulers In relations with the Persian Gulf residency - with the possible exception of Muscat and I shoul i bo grateful for instructions. Yours sincerely, Sd./- G.N.JACKSON The don’ble Lc-Col political A.C. Gallov/ay, T' T T 1 n p p Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. NS.f- COMFIDESTIAL D»Q. Wo.l 743 rS EXT 2244 19 PERSIAN GULF mSXWHQl * BABBAIit the 9th October 1947 My dear Jackson, Please refer to your demi-official letter No.C/995 dated the 4th October, 1947, regarding flying of flags by B.I. vessels visiting Sharjah and Dubai. 2. I concur in your views and if you see no objection please Inform Meikle of the proposal and ask him to do his best to ensure that it is dropped as it is likely to create awkward complications if it is proceeded with. Yours sincerely, Sd. W.R. Hay. N H G.N. Jackson, Esquire, M.B.E., Political Agent, B A iffiA i B(T 16703/1001/3807 Dear Donaldson, With reference to your letter No. Ext. 1678/47 of the 11th August to Dunbar (who is away for a few days) regarding the status of Koweit Bay, we entirely agree as to the undesirability of adopting the Sheikh’s suggestion of making foreign vessels fly the Koweit flag. We doubt moreover whether it would be effective. However, the Sheikh seems to have caught, the idea, and he may hit upon some more practical expedient e.g. some form of quarantine control, or other police measure commonly imposed in national waters. Yours sincerely. Cox) E.P. Donaldson, Esq., C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office. King Charles Street.You sent Dodds a copy of your letter of the 11th August addressed to Dunbar about a suggestion .made by the Sheikh of Kuwait that he should request all ships to fly the Kuwait flag within the limits of the bay* We agree with you and Golonel Galloway that acceptance of the Sheikh’s suggestion might result in awkward complications and that the request should be refused, notwithstanding that this may be difficult. I am sending a copy of this letter to Dunbar* Yours sincerely, • y 3.P* Donaldson, Esq India Office, S.W. 1» C» M • G&lt;(11178) Wt.21321/P.248 6,000 (2 sorts) 7/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. WM. P. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.WA.(11178) Wt.21321/P.248 6,000 (2 sorts) 7/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 It ts requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under -mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.WM. P. .4* - INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.JF.L—Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. From - Repgu Bahrain. To - Retaxandum london. Ho. 1425-3. Bated the 31st July 1947 . (L jbujJL ^ Your letter No. iSxt. 1304/47_June 18th. Status of Kuviait Bay* 2. Shailch has suggested that he should also write to shipping agents requesting all ships to fly Kuwait flag within limits of Bay as defined. He points out that all ships entering Iraqi territorial waters at Fao hoist the Iraqi flag. 3. The suggestion appears, on the face of it, a good one for affirming the national status of the hay hut possible objections are (1) Kuwait is not an independent State as Iraq is and our approval may encourage the Shaikh in ideas of independence to the detriment of the position of H.M.G* (ii) if approval were given as regards Kuwait a similar request would undoubtedly follow from Bahrain, and possibly other Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms . These it would he difficult to refuse, while acceptance might result in awknard complications. On balance I am averse to its adoption. Please telegraph whether you agree. • Sd. A. C.GAUOV&lt;AY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. for S Po lit i cal sretary to Resident, the Persian Gulf RHL. I 'V i■■■MMDraft Letter Form B. P.Z. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State in Council to enclose, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of a letter from the Foreign Office regarding the appointment of as for at 2. I am to enquire whether any objection is seen to this appointment and am to request that, if there is no objection, it may be recognised by the Government of India. 3. If it is considered that there may be any objection to the appointment, the Secretary of State would be glad to be informed by telegraph at the earliest possible date.■ixl.iilt,}]'' &lt; ^( 7 kL\ Draft Paper. KXSKRl'JAi Department. C.W. Baxter, Bsq.., G.1I.G-., li*C., Foreign Office, London, S.W.1. 5 jou m COljFILEIli’LiL The Political Resident has sent home for consideration a note on various ceremonial matters which require to be settled as a administration from the Government of India to H.II.G. Except for the question of the flags to remain as they are until the Foreign Office take over from trie India Office in April of next year. You may, however, like to have our views on the points raised in Hay’s note and I set them down for convenience in this letter. (A) Designation of Officers •,/e agree with the Political Resident that there is no necessity to change the designation of any of the officers which have been in use for a long time and are well understood in the area. The Political Agent at I.Zuscat is already II.i,. Consul as well but we see no necessity foi a change in the description of the political Agents at Bahrein and Rowe it. (B) Precedence It seems only necessary to regulate the comparative precedence the Political Off icers and Officers in His Majesty* s fighting services, ^s the Political Resident result of the transfer of the control of the be flown no immediate decision seems to be required and you may feel that things at present ranks senior to all Flag, General / and (10337) Wt.U054/P.l&lt;H 10,000 5/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 (11764) Wt.26696/P.282 10,000 9/39■fri ' ■fri ' \ and Air Officers, it seems appropriate, that, v/ithin his charge, he should continue to enjoy this precedence and that the Political agents should rank with, but after. Captains, i.iT. , Colonels and Croup Captains in the and that the Junior officers should rank with, but after, Lieutenant-Comrr.anders, Ilajors and 3 qu adr on-Le ade r s. (C) Salutes I am inclined to think that the best solution is to leave the number of guns as they are at present^ and in ary case not to reduce the Salutes accorded to the Political Agents below the 11 guns which they now enjoy. (D) It seems clearly desirable that the Political Resident should no longer fly the 'Union Viceroy' (which is, I believe, a Union flag with tne Star of India in the centre) but should in future fly the Union flag with the Royal Arms in the centre ana uhe Political Agents the Union flag with the fudor Crown. (S) i'he Political Residents title of'lio^ble . I expect you will feel that the time has now come to drop this and we should not object if you so decide, but the point about the use of the honorific in Arabic correspondence should be borne in mindj*hsugii this /perhaps be treated as a local usage ha- left undisturbed. (F) Uniform The Political Resident's suggestions seeia to be sensible^ and we think tha^funtil new incumbents / are M *CONFIDENTIAL 1 ' 1 ' 1 '' D.O. No. 905 - thefl^-th Ma77^*±947. BAHRAIN. INDEXED h'lf HU I forward herewith a J regarding the designation, status, salutes, etc. of officers in the Gulf. I should be grateful for an early decision on the question of flags, but apart from this if you do not agree with any of my sugges tions you might perhaps leave them for discussion until I come home on the assumption that I get my leave. On the other hand if you consider them sound you may perhaps think it worth while to pass them on to the Foreign Office for consideration now. E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., India Office, LONDON. G • ' 2 3MAY 1947 J*jI n at present held by officers of the Indian Political Service in the Gulf : - 1. Political Resident. 2. Political Agent (at Bahrain, Kuwait &lt;1 Muscat). 3. Secretary to the Political resident’. 4. Under Secretary to the Political Resident. 5. Political Officer (Trucial Coast). 6. Assistant Political Agent (at present only at Bahrain;. At uscat the Political Agent is also Kis Britannic Majesty's Consul and is alvi/ays referred to as Consul by the Sultan. 2. These designations have been in use for a long time and I would suggest that there is no necessity to change them. I should have preferred that the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, were termed the Assistant Political Agent but as it will almost certainly be necessary to raise the status of this officer to that of a Political Agent in the near future I do not think the matter worth pursuing. I do not think it appropriate to designate the Political Agents at Bahrain and Kuwait Consuls as this would tend to lower their position in the eyes of the Shaikhs. They have consi derably more executive and administrative powers than are nominally enjoyed by a Consul. I had thought of suggesting the omission of 'Political' from the designation 'Political Resident' but see no real necessity for this change. If any change is to be made in the designation of any of the officers in the Gulf a decision should be reached on the point quickly as it will be necessary to use the new designations in the revised Orders in Council which will have to be enacted at an early date. B. PnnC-jDBKCB. ; arrant of Precedence. The Political Resident within his charge ranks senior to a full General and the Political Agents within their charges and the Secretary to the Political Resident rank senior to Lieutenant Colonels. I would suggest that in future the Political Resident should rank as a minister, the Political Agents and the Secretary to the Political Resident as Consuls, and the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Under Secretary and Assistant Political Agents as Vice-Consuls. C. SAnUTBS. of thirteen guns and the Political Agents of 11 guns. If the proposals about the ranking of officers are accepted, the Political Resident would appear to become entitled to a salute of seventeen or fifteen guns according to whether he is regarded as a inister Plenipotentiary or a ; inister Resident and the Political Agents to salutes of 7 guns. It does not much matter whether the Political Resident's salute is increa sed or not but I am opposed to the reduction in the salutes of the Political Agents which cannot fail to lower their status in the eyes of the local Shaikhs especially as the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait enjoy salutes of 11 guns. Precedence is at present governed by the Indian At present the Political Resident enjoys a salute D. FLAGS. /D. FLAGS. s&gt;® —p&amp;g-e-Sv 1 I $ h the case of the Political resident but he should continue to scs -f* q t* t&gt; o rs o c? ' * . 1 0 IvVi o rr, q +' ** ' 'i c H Kion 1 •' ^ 'in t-t T* O T H The flag at present flown bb' the'Political Resident and the Political Agents is tirie Union Viceroy. In future I consider that the Political Resident shquld fly the Union v/ith the Royal Arms as is prescribed for His Majesty's Diplomatic Servants, Ministers Plenipotentiary, etc. and the Political Agents the flags prescribed for His ajesty's Consular Officers. E. PUi.JTIOi-.ij ...IcIiJiiir-L ' 1 ^ Ari-^Li^Tlu] Of 'Rwf 0 U- . This appellation is prescribed by the Government of India for Members of Council and First-Class Residents. I think I am right in saying that no such appellation is allowed for under Foreign Office rules though I think it is enjoyed by some high officials in the Colonies. i do not think any harm will be done if the appellation is dropped in \ ^ J- be referred to as correspondence. Fakhamat' = 'His Honour' in Arabic F. IFC U . At present the Political Resident wears Class III diplomatic uniform, the Political Agents Class IV and others Class V. I would suggest that officers of the Indian Political Service who continue to serve in the Gulf and already possess the civil uniforms prescribed should be^ allowed to continue to wear them. If the Political Resident is given the status of Minister he could be permitted at his discretion to put up the additional gold braid. Of the matters discussed above the only one on which a more or less immediate decision is required is that of flags, as I do not think the Union Viceroy should continue to be flown after 1st April, 1948, and steps ought to be taken now to obtain the new type of flag which has to be flown in its place. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. the 10th May, 1947. G.A.immmmm Dress Regulations for OfiQ.cers of the Indian Political Service. I*—These regulations apply only to officers of the Indian Political Service. II-—For the purposes of these regulations officers are divided into three classes :— Class I .—The Secretaries in the External Affairs and Political Departments, Agent to the Governor General in Baluchistan, and Residents of the 1st and 2nd class and officers of the Indian Political Service of 23 years’ civil service and upwards. Class II .—Officers of the Indian Political Ser vice of 10 years’ civil service and upwards. Class III .—Officers of the Indian Political Ser vice of less than 10 years’ civil service. III.—FULL DRESS AND LEVEE DRESS • UNIFORM. The Full Dress uniform prescribed for all three classes is as given below : the only difference between the classes is in the pattern of the embroidery on the collar of the coat. Coatee.— Dark blue cloth, single-breasted, stand collar. The collar and gauntlet cuffs are of black velvet, and pocket flaps of blue cloth. Nine buttons up the front (to button), two at the waist behind and two at the bottom of the back skirts. Black silk lining. A white collar may be worn inside the coat. Class I .—Embroidered in gold according to the pattern of 3rd class English Civil Levee uniform. Class II .—Embroidered in gold according to the pattern of 4th class English Civil Levee uniform.7 A 14 2 Class III. —Embroidered in gold according to the pattern of 5th class English Civil Levee uniform. Buttons. —Gilt, mounted, the Royal Arms with supporters. Nom—Wherever the words “gilt buttons’’ occur hereafter, it is to be understood that this pattern of button, in three sizes, is referred to, and no other. Head-dress. —Black beaver cocked hat, black silk cockade, with plaited gold bullion loop and black ostrich feather border. No tassels. Breeches. —White kerseymere with three covered buttons and gilt buckles at the knees. Hose. —White silk. Shoes. —Black patent leather with gilt buckles. Sword. —English pattern with black scabbard and gilt mountings. Sword-knot. —Gold lace strap with bullion tassel. Sword-belt. —White web, with white cloth frog. Gloves. —White kid. Levee Dress will be the same as that prescribed for Full Dress with the following exceptions :— (i) Trousers. —Dark blue cloth, with gold oak- leaf lace on the side seams If inches wide, with straps. {ii) Boots .—Patent leather, Wellington (m) Sword-belt. —White web, with blue cloth frog. Note 1.—The helmet prescribed for use with the “Undress Uniform” should be worn with “Levee Dress” in the day time, and not the beaver cocked hat referred to above. Note 2.— Full Dress is usually worn at Investitures, State Balls, con certs and drawing rooms and at State ceremonies in the evening. Levee Dress is worn at Levees and official visits, official arrivals and departures. At State ceremonies at which Full Dress (with trousers) or Levee Dress is prescribed, an officer on mounted duties will wear the undress uniform prescribed below for mounted duties. Note 3. —In lieu of full or levee head-dress, Indian gentlemen may, if they so desire, wear a white puggri with £ inch gold French braid.3 IV.—UNDRESS UNIFORM. For, all classes. Frock coat. —Blue cloth, double-breasted, roll collar, trimmed with ^ inch black mohair braid on edges and collar, and five loops of the same braid on each side of the breast, fastening with netted cap buttons. Back-pleat edged with black mohair braid, forming a crow’s foot at top, two cap buttons at waist. Sleeves ornamented with \ inch black mohair braid, forming a crow’s foot six inches from bottom of cuff. Shoulder straps of twisted gold cord, fastening with a small gilt button. False vest. —White cloth, no collar, V-shape open ing, about inches, to show the knot of a black silk scarf, edged with gold Russia braid, fasten ing with hooks and eyes. Forage cap. —As for staff officers in army with gold embroidered Lion and Crown badge, with following exceptions :— Classes II and III .—Peak black patent leather, with a row of gold embroidery with usual twisted purl edging \ inch total width. Class /.—Same as for Classes II and III, but the embroidery on peak to be | inch wide. The band for each class to be of white cloth. The Forage cap to be fitted with a removable white 'pique cover and a similar khaki drill covei foi use as circumstances require. Great coat and cape. —Dark blue cloth, double- breasted. Two rows of gilt buttons down front, six buttons in each row and 6 inches apart across. Stand and fall collar of black velvet. Loose round cuffs, 6 inches deep. Pockets at sides with flaps. The coat to reach within a foot of the ground, with an opening behind about 26 inches long, and a gusset extending to the bottom with a tab and button to close it when worn on foot. Blue cloth back strap with gilt} J X O { .) ‘1 '' C X ;» d ^ i\ d JbJ Di.uoria no e. J .31 ’ &lt;j S n j-drioo ‘ v '' ; v In &gt; 4 buckle two inches wide to confine the coat at waist. Two openings at side seams, with pointed flaps 11 inches long and three gilt buttons. Sword slit on left side. The coat to be lined with scarlet Italian or Rattinet. Cape of blue cloth to reach to the knuckles. Lined black. Four medium gilt buttons down front to button through, and a gilt hook and chain at the neck. The cape should button on to the collar of the coat; but the coat and cape may be worn together or separately. Helmet.— White Wolseley regulation, gilt spike and floral base. Puggri white muslin, with J inch gold French braid showing ^ inch from top edge of puggri. Chin-strap of light metal gilt on white leather. Chin-strap to be worn looped up except on mounted duties. Overalls. —Blue cloth, with gold oak-leaf lace, one inch wide, with straps. Boots. —Wellington. Spurs. —Box, brass, swan-necked. Sword. —Mameluke pattern, brass scabbard. Sword-belt.— Gold oak-leaf lace, 1^ inch wide, with slings one inch wide, on white Morocco leather. Waist plate round gilt clasp. Royal coat-of- arms on centre-piece, universal ends. Gloves. —White dog-skin. (For mounted duties.) Breeches. —Blue cloth, with gold oak-leaf lace, one inch wide. Boots. —Black leather knee boots, military pattern. Spurs. —Brass, swan necked, with chains and straps. Saddlery.— Plain hunting saddle and bridle. Note 1.— In lieu of a helmet, Indian gentlemen may, if they so desire, wear a white puggri with ^ inch gold French braid. Note 2.— Medal ribbons will be worn with undress uniform.5 V.—EVENING DRESS. For all classes. Coat. —Blue cloth evening coat, white silk facings one inch from edge of lapel, white silk lining, black velvet collar and cufls, gilt buttons, four small gilt buttons on cuffs. Waist-coat. —White marcella, single breasted, with three or four small gilt buttons. Trousers. —Plain black cloth. Shoes. —Black Oxford. Tie.—W hite. VI.—HOT WEATHER UNIFORM. For Class III. Coat. —White cotton drill patrol coat. Stand and fall collar. Five medium gilt buttons down front. Two patch breast pockets with box pleat and pointed flap, each buttoned with a small gilt button. On shoulders a double line of white round cord (not twisted) with a small gilt button at top. Sleeves trimmed with a chevron of white cotton one inch braid traced above and below, and finishing in a knot, both above and below the chevron point. For Classes I and II. As for Class III with following additions :— Collar to be edged with white cotton one inch braid with a row of tracing braid inside, forming an eye in each corner, and back to have white cotton one inch braid down side body seams with a row of tracing braid on each side, forming three eyes at top at .angles formed by braid. Shoulder straps of gold twisted cord. Trousers. —White cotton drill, with black leather foot-straps. Forage cap. —Same as for undress uniform.O Si v c nxjncK / . 6 Helmet, boots, spurs, sword and sword-belt.— Same as prescribed for Undress Uniform. Beit to be worn under the coat. Gloves. —Gloves are not worn with the Hot Weather Uniform. Note.— This uniform-will be worn during the hot weather months in substitution either for the Full Dress or Undress Uniform prescribed above. When the uniform is worn as Full Dress, medals and decorations will be worn. When it is worn as Undress, ribbons only to be worn. VII.—HOT WEATHER EVENING DRESS UNIFORM. For all classes. White drill mess jacket, roll collar, sleeves plain with pointed cuffs 5 inches high at point and 2^ inches behind. Three small gilt buttons on cuffs. Shoulder cords as for hot weather uniform. White waist-coat as for ordinary evening dress uniform; or a plain white kamarband may be worn if preferred. White drill overalls, with black leather foot straps, or trousers without foot-straps, as directed for any particular station. Tie.—B lack. Note. Spurs should be worn when overalls are worn. VIII.—SERVICE DRESS. For all classes. Coat.— Plain khaki, open at the throat, with two breast and two side pockets, without shoulder straps or badges of rank but with white cloth tabs sewn on to the reverse of collar, 2^ inches long x 1^ inches wide, pointed at the outer end, a loop of gold Russia braid in centre of tab, with a gilt stud at the end near the point. Medium leather covered buttons in front and small on pockets. Shirt.— Khaki. Tie.—K haki.7 Breeches.— Khaki, or drab Bedford cord. Helmet. Regulation khaki, without a spike or chain, leather chin-strap. Sword.— Regulation cavalry pattern, with wooden scabbard, covered with brown leather. Belt.— Brown leather, Sam Browne pattern. Boots.— Brown, field boots, or brown laced ankle boots with brown gaiters or puttees. Spurs.— Jack, nickel-plated. hAP. Same as for Undress Uniform. Gloves.— Brown, regulation. Dress 0 ™ L ~ 0n SerViCe ’ ^ ° rdinary Undress Uniform wil l be used as Full th N °™ 2 - When 011 act,lve service with troops Political Officers mav if a j p , o wuh p xrwV g L te o7s y a r r“v rurdt 1 '. klMt ' ahoui ' d “ de„&gt;e, T wL 'khaki 0 pug6?i haki helnlet ' IndUn Se'&gt;U™en may, if the, so IX.—Officers now in possession of the uniform previously prescribed may continue to wear it until such time as their present uniform requires renewal. It should however be observed that the old pattern umtorm can be converted in accordance with the present Regulations with little difficulty or expense. •.?'cT 0fficerS are not obli ged to provide themselves with Service dress until ordered on service. XU Military officers may wear their militarv uniform, if preferred, until such time as they are permanently brought on to the graded list of the Indian Political Service. Military officers who hold an ex-officio political appointment conjoined with a military appointment, such as the Commandant of the Mewar Bhil Corps, etc., will wear their militarv uniform. ' 7 XII. —The possession of the hot weather evening dress uniform is optional. XIII. —Officers of the Indian Political Service when on leave in England, or otherwise present there during their service, will be permitted to wear their uniform at the Court of His Majesty the King- Emperor.XIV. —Retired officers who, when last on duty in India, were entitled to wear uniform, will be per mitted to wear their uniform at the Court of His Majesty the King-Emperor; and, when living in India, at Government Houses and on any occasion on which before their retirement they would have worn it. XV. —Officers whose retirement is due to mis conduct will not enjoy the privilege conferred by rule XIV. GIPD—L 31f Pol]. Dept.—4-1-38—350../ &lt;Lt. HyOPt IP- Goby^of m«mors.ndum .9oat*?d the 17th November 1945 from the Horrble the Political Resident, Persian Subject i- Gun salutes and 1 ceremonials ir the) “7 QQ Persian Gulf* | I ; li I x$/ u Ref^reace India Office Express Letts dated 25th Niarch 1937 1 and connected cor mi/£L~ nee* ' ^ hi C^b h / 2* Some doubt has arisen in re^ird to the correct# procedure to be adopted in regard to the exchange,.of ^ 'Ly.. j ceremonial calls at Muscat between the Political Resident, /)/} Persian Gulf, end the official deputy of H*H. the Sultan 7 of Muscat, in the latter’s absence* «hen the Gouncil of Ministers was in existence the Gouncil^as a whole was accorded a salute of 17 guns, and the Political Resident, whose salute is 13 guns, apparently paid the first call on the Gouncil* The Gouncil of Ministers wag disolved by the present sonixixtK Sultan in 1932. and in 1937 the Table or Salutes wag amended to provide for a salute of 13 guns for the 3ultan s official deputy if a member of the ruling family, and 9 guns if not a member of the ruling family* 3. In recent years only three visits by FoliMjal Residents have been made to Muscat in the lultan s absence, the first in 1938 by 3ir Trenchard ^owle t the second m 1941 bv ^t*Gol.Hay‘, and the third in this y^ar by myself* On all these occasions the Politisal Resident paid^the first call on the Sultan s official deputy, Saiyid Ghahab, a member of the ruling family. 1* arr doubtful, however, whether Ite the procedure that has been followed in these instances is correct. *here is an obvious difference in status between the Council of Ministers as a whole and a single individual, and I am of opinion that as the a salute accorded to the latter i^ not higher than that of the Political Resident, the first call should be paid by the Gultan s deputy. I should be glad faf a decision by Government on this point. 4. The Sultan hag recently dismissed Gaiyid Snahab and proposes to appoint an Idviser and ^orei^p Minister. ATTESTED. SD: illegible; for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf . FOREIGN SEC^TARY’S letter No DATE RECEIVED IB 5- 3 l£-3-1946 tV i Jr l V Bu shire. Subject i- Gun saluteg and ceremonials in the Persian Gulf • ^ Ijtefer^ge your memorandum No•934-S,dat^d the 17th® ® 2* '^he of India that, if n is ^ighnogg the Multan of ^usoat appoints his Adviser to 09 his deputy in his absence, the Deputy should pay the first call on the Political Resident* They do not, however, at^present propose to reach a decision on the point raisejd in # para 3 01 your ‘nemorandum under reply, since the situation described in it seems unlikel7 # to arise m the near future in view of the dismissal of ^iyid ShahaJh Oopy of a memorandum No*1027-3,/dated the 23th December 1945 from the Hon’ble the ^oli+ical Resident, Persian lulf, Bushire, to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, copy to the Political Agent, Muscat, with copy ox memorandum under reference* Dun Dalutes and Dereioonials in the Persian Pr^rc^L . Reference correspond 0 nee ending with External Affairs Department memorandum No*D.15625-MB/45 dated the 11th December 1945. 2. During ray rscent visit to Muscat Ris Richness the Sultan hgave me to understand that although he^had 'exsused' Saiyid 3hahab from his duties, na still proposed to retain himf in Muscat as a figure head for ceremonial purpose during his absence* I would be glad therefore if the point raised could be considered further* attested 3d/- Illegible for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Dulf r : » 27/2/46.*- . ^ / aiOHBT AIR MAIL From To The Hon 1 bio the Political nAfl'iHArrh in i ai on (ri The Under Secretary to the ^oTernment of India in the External Affaire Department, Heeldent in the Persian ^ulf* MmmUM NO .D.670-^/46. / j / DATED m DELHI,the Mmmf f 46. Subject Gun ealutee and ceremonials in the Persian Gulf • 2* The Government of India feel that there are no strong grounds for departing from the procedure hitherto followed and consider that the present practice might be allowed to continue* Sd/- T .E • Brown sdon • Under Secretary to the Government of India* #4th August, 1942* Dear Herding©, I T vrlte to soy that the new Sheildi of I&gt;ahrein to wiiom the grant of a l&gt;e-'3oml salute of 11 guns was recently approved by The King, has requested that his thanks nay be expressed to His -ajesty* Yours sincerely. (Sd) W.G. NEALEo The Rt#Hon# ir vlexanier Hardings, #C#V# 0 #, ■ • 0 «B* ,son? Cr Allotted to External Dg-pt . DECYFHER O P T li) L 2 O R A M» From Political Resident in Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India. Bated Bushina* I 80 OG hours* S9.7.42 a Reed. 15.00 houfa* 50th July* 1942. 24«3. 1462. Addressed to Secretary of Stats-for India repeated to Government o f'India. Your telegram 1286 4 (7 goth July). Salute for Sheikh of Bahrain. Sheikh has Been informed arid asks that his thanks may he conveyed. RECd. POL.DEPt. -1 auG‘942 INDIA OFFICEMr. Amery presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that the present Sheilth ol Bahrein may be granted a personal salute oi 11 guns. His Highness Sheikh Salman of Bahrein recently succeeded to the Sheikhdom on the death of his father, the late Sheikh Hamad, for whom a personal salute of 11 guns, was approved in 1933. The Government of India and local political authorities have represented that it is desir able to grant to the present Sheikh the personal salute enjoyed by his father, in recognition not only of his loyalty to the British connection both before and since his accession, but also of the increased political importance of Bahrein. The present proposal has the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty.15th July 1942 fofh 'U^JL *JT&lt;J ivKCA AaS (ktOLlMcrn &lt;*J*o llr. Amery presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that the present Sheikh of Bahrein may be granted a personal salute of 11 guns# HlghruSS His Ijliioallcucy Sheikh Salman of Bahrein lately succeeded to the Sheikhdom on the death of his father, the late Sheikh Hamad, for whom a personal salute of 11 guns was approved by .Xour Majgsty in 1933* The Government of India and local political authorities have represented that it is desirable to grant to the present Sheikh the personal salute enjoyed by his father, both in aKprooqio.i cr? rpp^^ ^^ his loyalty to the British connection ■and » rern flnaticH% /c iruporLoLYicc i mx iiV, ‘ , V' i ' i, ' l ‘ ,rf - of Bahrein# of the increased political The present proposal has the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Lords Commissioners of the i^niralty# Signed L. S. AM HR ^ *■J tL , / • - H dmm Register No. tBE • Ext* ffwfrm/' 32(33/42. EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT. Letter r Telegram fr ° m Dated 193 . Rec. Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairman Under Secretary . Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary . Secretary of State VI (( Salutes in the Persian Gulf* Proposal to grant a personal salute of 11 guns to H*H. Sheikh Salman bin Hamad al Khalifa, Ruler of Bahrein# Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft submission t o H.M# trr*' ’M? Previous papers 4136a 1000 10.35 'VMUTE. Please see the previous submission at Ext.2573/42. The Foreign Office and the Admiralty have now concurred. A draft submission is attached accordingly for approval *h.^ d. Any further communication should be addressed to— Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l. ,,„ S ..U, 0 R 06 ^ on the outsi e of the^rrj^lopa: he text. ^/Idmiralt)), S.W.l. 194 2 3 G0Ijto)EI^TI/iX . In replv to-your letter of the ^th J une/ITT.25?3Z !x2^ I am ccamaanded My^Tords Commissioners of the Admiralty to infom you that they concur in the proposal that H.H.Sheikh Salman bin Hamad al Khalifah should be granted a personal salute of eleven guns. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l. ~ ' ■&gt; ^In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. T 6193/491/377 and address^^k not to any Person by name but to-f Jnder-Secn 2.5 is. -Secretary of Stat Foreign Office ' London, 3.W.I. A ■oh oreign Office. S.V.l. 7:/ r o J O J ,7&gt; ' 26th June,1942 I. witn reference to your let ter EXT.2573 /42 of the 13th June I am directed hy Mr .’Secretary Eden to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India that he concurs in Mr.Amery’s proposal to submit for The King’s approval the recommendation of the Government of India that a personal salute of eleven guns be accorded to His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain. I am, . Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.mmm MINUTE. Please see previous submissions at P.Z.838/33, i. 2.1696/33 and P.2.1944/33. The Sheikha of Bahrain receive^ a permanent salute of seven guns fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit. Both the late Sheikh Hamad and his father, Sheikh’isa,enjoyed personal salutes of eleven guns. The Political agent at Bahrain recomuends that a similar personal salute should be granted to Sheikh Salman bin Hamad al Khalifah, who succeeded, on the death of his father, in February last. The Government of India and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf endorse this recommendation. Sheikh Salman is forty-seven, he has been associated with the administration of the State for more than ten years, and has been consistently loyal and friendly to the British. On the other nand it might be considered advisable to withhold the increased salute to be granted later, for services rendered. There is also a danger that the grant of personal salutes to both bheikh Hamad and oheikn Salnic«.n, on succession, may be held to establish precedent. In his note at Ext.2161/42, the Political Agent discusses these and other points and gives as his opinion that the 'advantages of granting a personal salute of eleven guns to Sheikh Salman far outweigh the disadvantages '. In view of these recommendations, and of the increased political importance of Bahrain, it is submitted that the proposal may be approved and laid before the King. A draft letter to the Foreign Office and the Admiralty is submitted accordingly. ft. „ Vl q. t/i. + Jus d iS^b t Ajl P-ftCx/)*.loi(s c/r\ fa- ^XC^r^L fWoJ~ ^x&gt;fK ‘KouK. /o ciij^jLCieA a£ cl. ^tCUiL a.jc &lt;f k4!K(AaJT . (At SdyJ A I U. L~*. ^ Ux/tC (~ / i. ) /U-3./ ■■■■■■■■■■ mammmmm letter To:- Under Secretary of State F.O. v\ Secretary, Atdmiralty. Sir, - 13 JUN 1942 X am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs copy of a Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty letter from the Government of India supporting the recommendation made by the Hon’ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf in his letter of 1.0. No. £xt.2161/42 on 9th, that H.H. Sheikh Salman bin Hamad al Khalifah, who recently succeeded his father as Fuler of Bahrain, should be granted a personal salute of eleven guns. State agrees with the Government of India in accepting their proposal, and subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Fo; Lords Commissioners of th Affairs Admiralty he proposes to submit it for His Majesty*s approval. Dated 10th April. March 15th, a copy of which was sent to you under 2 In the light of the considerations adduced- ...A JR MAIL. From To £j&gt;-E COhYss No.F.163-N/42. U C\f The Secretary to the Government of Indi^ v^) in the External Affairs Department. His Majesty's Under Secretary of State for India, External Department, India Office, Lgn4aiu Dated New Delhi, the /ft* April 1942. Subject:- Proposed grant of a personal salute to ills Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain. 'MU Q T T* * I am directed to refer to the letter from, the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian AY .942 I have the honour to be. Your most obedient servant. INDIA office Secretary to the Government of India# G.S. ((^11 $ Li Vi L&gt;-coxy idkatial , JNo.G/ 136 of 1942. Office of t’ue Political Resident in the Persian Guli» Camp* Bahrain. Dated the 15tli March, 1942. Prom - The Ron*ble Lieut ••Colonel .R.Hay, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Tp - The Beeretary to the Government of India, External Affaire Departmerit, ha\t Delhi. 1 have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a note prepared toy Mr.Wakefield recommending tt*e fc rant of a personal salute of 11 guns to his Highness bhaifch Salman whose recogni tion as Shaikh of Bahrain in succesBion to his father the late Shaikh Hamad Vies recently toeen aocorced. 2. X strongly support Mr.Wakefield *b recom iendation for tv*© reas^vis ^iven in Viis note. SViaikVi Salman is oi mature age he is 47 - and itae long to eon associated in the administration of the Principality. As Mr.W^efielb♦ s note shows his father Shaikh haioad was also granted a personal salute oi 11 ^uns immediate!/ after his accession. 3. A do not think the grant of tfeis privilege to two successive Rulers of Bahrain Immediately ai ter their acces sion will necessarily conetitute a precedert from which it will be difficult to depart in future, as both have succeeded to tneir dignities at a mature age and without any dispute. X am in any case inclined to favour the grant oi cynastio salutes of 11 guns to the BViaikhs of both Bahrain and Kuwait in spite of the argument contained In paragraph b of the llate Sir Trenchard Fowle’s letter Bo.939-5, dated the £&gt; th Sir, / Decemberijecemtoer 1956, tout i do not px*opooe to pursue this xsatter further at present. » 4. 1 am sending a copy of this let er to His U; jeety’s Secretary of State for India, Colonel JPrior and the Aoli' ical /\gent # Bahrain. X have the honour to toe, Sir, four Boat, obedient servant, sc.• W. H. Kay. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. * sent under Printed hetter Ho.0/157 of 16tii Karen, 194a.hi V \ Confidential » Ca XV 5 T- ^T- 1 shaikh 'Isa bin Ali al Xhalifah, Ruler of Bahrain, died on ^Sh December 1932. On the 17th December 1932 , in his letter Wo. 2656, the Political Resident recommended to the Government of I^dia that Shaikh Hamad should eeceive a personal salute of 11 guns. Ajsimilar increase in the personal salute of Shaikh Ahmad of Kuwait was recommended at the same time. The recommendatio were accepted by His Majesty's Government. The dynastic salute of the 'Ruler of Bahrain remains at 7 guns. 2. in March 1937 the dynastic title of 'His Highness' was conferred on the Rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait. 3. In April 1937 the Deputies of the Rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait, whenever such were appointed to act for them in their absence, became entitled to a salute of 7 guns. 4. It is now for consideration whether Shaikh Salman should be granted a personal salute of 11 guns. 5. In favour of the suggestion are the following points (1) ^socia^^^ at least ten years. (ii) Hehas been consistently loyal and friendly to British connection. friendship”• (iv) Th^following anomalies would be removed (a) The Ruler of Kuwait being entitled to more ( guns than the Ruler of Bahrain. i(b) The use of the title 'His Highness' by a Ruler with a salute of only 7 guns. (o) ir &lt;v) lrr..p.cti™ of .n “Jtifi.. • Against the suggestion are the following points (i) The advisability of retaining the enhancedjalute K.*vt *Ai — l/vi- &lt;-1 u 6 . $ Letter No.304-3 d: 26 . 3.37 from Political Resident to India R ie^erVo7c/30 d:^?^ 6 ^ P ° lltlCal 11 —^/ - 2 - as a reward for services still to be rendered* (ii) The disadvantage of establishing the custom of giving the Kuler of Bahrain a personal salute soon after his accession. 7. In my opinion the advantages of granting a personal salute of 11 guns to Shaikh Salman far outweigh the dis advantages. And, if this opinion is accepted, 'bis dat qui cito dat'. sd. E.B.Wakefield. 1st !!arck,1942. «P.Z.1695/1936 Extract from letter from The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, to The Under Secretary of State for India, No.D.456-N/36, dated New Delhi, the 20th February, 1936. * &gt; * * * 2. In support of this recommendation I am to refer to the circular letter to Local Governments on the subject of the use of the title of His Highness by Ruling Princes and others in India transmitted to you under cover of the Political Secretary’s letter No.76-M, dated the 24th September, 1925. It was then decided with the approval of His Majesty’s Government that the use of the style of ’His Highness’ would in future be restricted to Indian Ruling Princes and Chiefs enjoying salutes (dynastic, personal or local) of 11 guns and over. The Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait are both entitled to dynastic salutes of 7 guns and to a personal salute of 11 guns, and it follows that there is nothing under the orders of 1925 to debar the use of this style in addressing the present Rulers of both these Arab principalities. * + * *CONFIDENTIAL Extract from letter from The Hor^ble Lieut-Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi, No.959-S of 1935, dated Bushire, 5th December, 1935. * * * * 5. I appreciate the point raised by Colonel Loch in his paragraph 5, but I think it would be advisable to keep the dynastic salute at 7 guns to enable the guns for the new Ruler to be raised to 11 if his conduct proved satisfactory.Draft Paper. 466 ^ v ; v &gt; Political ^ Department. DRAFT LETTER. Si Major W.R.Hay, C.I.E., Government of India External Affairs Dept. Hi ^ % Deer Hay, VrnnTri.-ynp plp^Rr: reffr- t cl. 7 correspondence resting with the memorandum of the Political Resident of the Persian Gulf, N 0 .C. 8 C of 1937, dated 12th April 1937, a copy of which was sent to the India Office and to the Government of India^on the subject of gun salutes and ceremonial in the Persian Gulf? It would seem from this correspondence that a proposal to amend the Table of Salutes so that the official- / deputies of the Sheikhs of Bahrein and / Koweit w'ou^d receive a salute of 7 and not 5 guns received His Majesty’s approval (vide India Office express / letter to the Government of India, p.2. 577/37 dated 25th March 1937) and .that the Political Agents were instructed to inform the Rulers of Bahrein and 1 Koweit that this approval had been •g-U.ii! led (vide the n umj 1 WTHituu) • . c - 'Tu^ a.. h In. ^ A ««-»*JU U* V, lm ^QGc££iriLL_ t* the Half-Yearly List ocr. d ufKC&lt;X. of the Indian Political Service, however, the salute to be given to the official deputies of the Sheikhs of Bahrein and io y- Koweit rarn 0 ir w -g;—yaluto of 5 guns. sJUX* (******** 4 7 4 . SoujKj-^rou—thr Jvr any J &gt;-fiVit -en this c*fiA*o uta* ^ iu, zS^ty***** / / 73? / ^ W77/&gt;;- h i o —ond i f--it i-e-'a4 tributnbl e^to a-f*— ft. ftutUi 7090 Wt 41703/86 10,000 3.38INDIA OFFICE EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MIL) POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. From-: Secretary of State for India To: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Dated 22nd January, 1938. No. P.Z. 345/38 Addressed to Political Resident repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department, and Political Agent, Bahrain. Your Express Letter No.C-378 of 6th December. Kalha salutes. Effect of submission approved by His Majesty is that both Shaikhs are eligible for salute if they visit sloops officially at the same time but two salutes should be fired only if they leave sloop by separate boats. Copy of correspondence with Admiralty is enclosed for your information. The issue of the above has been duly authorised (TSd.) G. E. CROMBIE.(La blest) ON HIS MAJESTY’S SERVE FASTEN Envelope by gumminj? ' Label across FL OPEN by cutting Label instoy^I bearing Envelope]wmmm mm ■■■■■■■I 1st December 1937. Lord Zetland presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your majesty may be pleased to approve that Sheikh Hamad bln Said ol Kalba, in the region of the Persian Gulf, may be granted a personal salute of 3 guns, and that a similar salute may be granted to Sheikh Khalld bln Ahmad while acting as rtegent of Kalba during the minority of Sheikh Hamad bln Said. Kalba is an Independent Sheikhdom on the eastern coast of Truclal Oman, situated about half way between Bahrein and Gwadur on the main air route to India. Considerable Importance Is attached to Its use as an emergency landing site, and facilities for this purpose were granted by the late Sheikh Said bln Hamad, who died last May. Sheikh Hamad bln Said is a minor and the only son of the late Sheikh Said bln Hamad, who had been granted a personal salute of 3 guns, sheikh Khalld bln Ahmad Is a relative by marriage of the late Sheikh, and with the consent of the people of Kalba Your Majesty's Government/ mmummm mm uti 'mi■ i - 2 - have decided to recognise him as hegent of Kalbe during the minority of the young Shellch. The proposals have the support of the Government of India, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty. z.Confidential » ■ IH^i /30 : Government of India* . v- ! ^ ‘/ External Affairs Department, EXPRESS LETTER , (Air Mail.) Prom Foreign, New Delhi* To Britconsul, Bushire, Repeated Secretary of State for India, Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait, No,F.710-N/36. Dated New Delhi, theApril 1937. Secretary of State Express letter No.P,Z.677/37, dated the 25th March 1937* Gun salutes and ceremonials in the Persian Gulf. 2, Provided you see no objection, Government of India will be glad if you will kindly inform the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait of the decision reached. The issue of the above has been authorised.i ^ Mm l—B mmmmm tMKriJ'STXAL. Offio« of tfto Political Hesidont in the Persian ^ulf, Caapt BaJarain. Bated tfce l2tH Ajril, 1937. To The Political Agent, Bahrsdn. The Political Agent, Kuwait. j Copy to Hie ^ajeety*® Secretary of state for India, London.' Reference India Office sprees Letter Ro,P.2.677/37, dated the 33th March 1&amp;7, 2. Please inform Rule? of ^hrain that His Majesty has Ku’tfai t ’ been graciously pleased t&gt; approve that when an official Deputy is appointed by His Highness to act f or him in his absence, the Deputy should be granted a salute of 7 guns. 5. If the Ruler, in Inc case of a short absence for Instance, does not appoiit an official Deputy, or appoints an official Deputy but iitimatee that - for various reasons - he does not wish a salute to be fired, no salute will be given. 4. Men ever the Rulir proposes to leave his at ate you should ascertain his withes in this connection and report to The Foreign Secretary to the Uoveminent of India, dew Delhi The Senior $aval Officer, Persian hulf t with copy of the India office Express letter referred to. ^he Political Ag«it, Muscat. Subject* tiun salutes and ceremonial in the Pers ian oulf. Memorandum . me /^arnmtdesammmmmm Draft Paper. A /A^ - P.Z.677/37. fA- i { W~) POLITICAL Department. DRAFT 3XPRESS LETTER. Fran Secretary of State To Government of India, F. &amp; P. Department, repeated to Pol.Res. in the Persian Gulf and Political Agents at Bahrein, Koweit and Muscat. 5a&gt; r H 6 % * 7/ m ZSMARba/ \/ \V Your express letter NO.D.6945-R/ 36, dated 5th November 1936. Gun salutes and ceremonials in the Persian Gulf. 2. Enclosed is a copy of a letter addressed to the Admiralty on the subject, from which you will observe that the King has approved the proposal that when an fiffi cial deputy is appointed by the Sheikh of Bahrein or the Sheikh of Koweit to act for him in his absence the Jfeputy may be granted a salute of seven guns. / vwu tfctdr 3. Lf y-eu m? object ion please jjisixujc4: Political Res Sheikhs accordingly. uUi if ident t -6 inform^ (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON 5667 5000 2.37Register No. P.Z. 677/37 % SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Ir — - from I eiegram Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairman. Under Secretary Secretary of State.., Committed Under Secretary.... Secretary of State... 3. PROPOSED ALTERATION IN THE TABLE OF I GUN SALUTES IN THE PERSIAN GULF. — / Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft submission to the King. Previous Papers :— 1742b 500 3.33mmm Minute Paper. p.z.677/37 Department. Attention is invited to Admiralty letter of 26th September, 1936, (flag A), concerning gun salutes in the Persian Gulf. The important amendment is the proposal that when an official deputy is appointed hy the Sheikh of Bahrein M h-is or the Sheikh of Koweit to act^ during absence tn 1 j the deputy should be granted a salute of 7 guns. At present the eldest son of either Sheikh if appointed to act as official deputy for his father is granted a salute of 5 guns, but when the official deputy is not the eldest son no salute is granted. The local Political Authorities consider, however, that the official deputy, even when not the eldest son, ought properly to receive a salute, and it seems logical to fix this salute at 7 guns, which is the dynastic salute of the Rulers concerned. The amendment requires the King ! s approval, and a draft submission is therefore suggested.India Office, / Whitehall. 9th March 1957. Lord Zetland presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that when an Official Deputy is appointed by the Sheikh of Bahrain or the Sheikh of Koweit to act for him in his absence, the Deputy may be granted a salute of 7 guns. acting as his father’s representative, is granted a salute of 5 guns, but when the representative is not the eldest son, no salute is granted. The Local Political Authorities consider, however, that the Official Deputy, even when not the eldest son, ought properly to receive a salute, and they have recommended that the salute should be fixed at 7 guns which is the dynastic salute of the Rulers concerned. of India, the Secretary of State for Poreign Affairs and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty. At present the eldest son of either Sheikh, v/hen The proposal has the support of the Government9th March 1937. Lord Zetland presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that when an Official Deputy Is appointed by the Sheikh of Bahrain or the Sheikh of Kowelt to act for him In his absence, the Deputy may be granted a salute of 7 guns. At present the eldest son of either Sheikh, when acting as his father’s representative, Is granted a salute of 5 guns, but when the representative is not the eldest son, no salute Is granted. The Local Political Authorities consider, however, that the Official Deputy, even when not the eldest son, ought properly to receive a salute, and they have recommended that the salute should be fixed at 7 guns which is the dynastic salute of the Kulers concerned. The proposal hes the support of the Government of India, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Lords Commissioners of the jdmiralty.DHAFT SUBMISSION. Lord Zetland presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that when an Official Deputy is appointed by the Sheikh of Bahrain or the Sheikh of Koweit to act for him in his absence, the Deputy may be granted a salute of 7 guns. At present the eldest son of either Oheikh, when acting as his father’s representative, is granted a salute of 5 guns, but when the representative is not the eldest son, no salute is granted. The Local Political Authorities consider, however, that the Official Deputy, even when not the eldest son, ought properly to receive a salute, and they have recommended that the salute should be fixed at 7 guns which is the dynastic salute of the Rulers concerned. The proposal has the support of the Government of India, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty.FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l (T 259/220/577) !937 27th January, 1937. Dear Symon V/ith reference to your letter to Brenan No.P.Z.9216/36 of the 5th January regarding the revision of the Table of Salutes in the Persian Gulf, I am writing to say that we have no observations to offer on the proposals made by the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies t Station concerning the increase in the number of guns to be accorded to the sons of the Sheikhs of Koweit and 7 Bahrein when acting as their fathers’ representatives, and the alteration in the salute to the Ministers of Muscat. Yours sincerely A.G.B. Symon, Esq. P.EGq. POL. PtPT. 2 9 JAN1937. IND a OFFICEP.Z.461/37 AJXtlHALTY M. 03586/36 LOUDON, S.W.l. 19th January, 1937 Sir With reference to India Office letter Ho.P.Z,101/37 of the 11th January, and previous correspondence, on the subject of air facilities at Kalba, I am commanded by Mr Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit herewith for che information of the Secretary of State for India in Council an extract from a report by the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, on the visit of SHOESHAM to Kalba on the 28th November last. A similar letter has been addressed to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Air Council I am etc (Sd.) R.H.A. CAHTltE The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S. W. 1.P.Z.461/37 Confidential From: The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. SHOREHAM, at Kuwait. Date: 30th November, 1936. No.: 295/453 To: The Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. Air Facilities - Kal ba. X x x XX 2. First salute and visit to Sheikh of Kalba was carried out by H.M.S. SHOREHAM on 28th November 1936. Residency Agent was present and visit passed off satisfactorily. A three gun salute was fired as authorised by Admiralty Message 1820, 9th November, 1936, to Commander-in-Chief, East Indies. 3. Work will start mid-January, 1937. (sd.) Captain Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Stp . Commander-in-Chief. 13 December 1936. East Indies.wmammatt i % cXc**. ^ e^^rrv Please refer to your letter No. P.2.8077/ 36 dated the 28th November 1936 on the subject of the revision of the Table of Salutes in the Persian Gulf. 2. Under the present rule, the son of the Shaikh of Bahrain or Kuwait, if he calls as his father’s representative, gets 5 guns, and where the representative is not the eldest son, he receive® no salute. It seemed desirable, however, that the representative even when not the eldest son, (as is often the case nowadays), should receive a salute. It seemed logical to fix this salute at 7 guns, the Shaikh’s dynastic salute. I am sending a cop? of this letter to Hay. M.J.Clauson Esquire, g The India Office, ^ h ^ ^ London. * sent under printed letter . No.895-3 of 14th December 1936. rv ' I/ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. | Qfj J Foreign and Foil'ticnlDepartment. ;V / EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). exveditin rne!i!ta ^ e sen * ty AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more on receipt 7* ordtnar H m&lt;111 and ** cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, formalities iti^rili t '*P ed J tton a J V U had telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate ^ u ' *y *•&gt;-&gt;'- »/ « No. D .6945-N/36. To Dated the November Secretary of State for India, London, Repeated Britconsul, Bushire, 1936. ., iaJ V . X9f i Wo p % Your express letter of I3tli October 1936. No. P.Z.6945/36. Gun salutes and ceremonials in the Persian Gulf. 2. The reason for note (iv) to the table of salutes is given in the attached copy of a telegram from Bushire. Apart from this we have no observations to make on Admiralty letter of 26th September 1936. The issue of the above has been authorised. 14 NOV 1936 {Signature) {Designatim)Telegram R. No 773. Doted ( L reed) 31st Octooer 1936. rroei. .Britconsul 3is j^ex’ .Forei^ti r. ev/ Deliii. Your telegram No 25C9 Cctoter 30th. (a) of Admiralty letter. No comaient. (b) reasons for note (4) which is based, on original suggestion of mine is that when Ruler appoints representative he will inform me whether he v/ishes salute to be accorded to representative ( which he may not always desire) end I will inform Senior Naval Officer. ( N. ?.S. D.ScF.)c&gt; *&lt; * Any further communication should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.I Sir, b D V^ j- mr Admiralty, SW.1\ j j / V •! o rv H-r- .S..e.p.t.emb.er.^.. 193&amp; . quoting ‘M.* 4071/36,' 0 4 0 | ' &gt; ■■■■I Q ^ « J I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit herewith, for the information of Secretary of State for India in Council, a copy of a submission with enclosure from the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, concerning gun salutes and local ceremonial in the Persian Gulf. A copy of the present Section ’B*, Article 55, of East Indies Station Orders is also enclosed. So far as they are concerned. My Lords have no objection to the changes proposed by the Commender-in- Chief, and they would be glad to learn as soon as possible what reply should be sent to him. With reference to the notes to the Table, My Lords propose: point out to the Commander-in-Chief that the amended definition of India waters (K.R.2/35) requires the addition of Saudi Arabia to the list of countries whose territorial waters are excluded in Note (i). ask him what is the reason for the insertion of the words 'and whether he is entitled to receive the salute and honours' in note (iv). As all The Under Secretary of India Office, S .W . 1. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER ! State, 0 - 3OCT 1936 • FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL ATD SECR ET DEPT. INDIA OtTi. . QQj , CiiNT Tc—rry the sloops will have copies of the table, this seems superfluous, unless it is intended either that an official deputy should only receive the salute and honours when the sheikh, in appointing him has expressly said that he may receive them, or that the political authorities in the Gulf should decide on each occasion whether the deputy is to have the salute, etc. If this is the case My Lords are inclined to the view that the _ note should he given greater prominence than at present. r A copy of this letter has been sent to the Foreign Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,From ... The Commander-in-Chief, Fast Indies Station. At Colombo. Date .. 11th August, 1936. No. 1079/E.1.1202 . To The Secretary of the Admiralty. Copy to:- Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. SALUTES IN PERSIAN GULF . Be pleased to lay before Their Lordships the enclosed table of Gun Salutes and Local Ceremonial in the Persian Gu , which sets out in detail the procedure agreed upon oy the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, and the Senior Naval Gffi , Persian Gulf, and which is shortly to he issued in the revised East Indies Station Order Book as Appendix V, Section 1. 2 . Section B, The following alterations to the former Article 55, have been made:- Bahrein ) The salute of 5 guns to the eldest son when Snd ) acting as deputy has been altered to 7 guns Kuwait. ) to the official deputy. Muscat. The salute to ministers has been altered, the^ Council of Ministers, which acted as Regent for the former Sultan having been dissolved by the present Sultan. 3 . It is requested that these changes may be communicated to the India Office, and that approval may be forthcoming by signal, in view of my impending visit to the Persian Gulf in October next. (Sd.) A.R.M. RAMSAY. Vice Admiral. Enclosures: (in duplicate) Appendix V, Section 1, East Indies Station Order Book- Gun Salutes and Local Ceremonial - Persian Gulf (The Trucial Coast, Muscat and Gwadar.)(To be substitutf&gt;&lt;/ fur 1!&gt; undated) *«.; is East Indies Station Order Book ^ m Salutes and Ceremonies. 55. Salutes— Section “B n —Salutes in Arabian waters and Aden. Arabian waters are defined to mean ihe territorial waters of all the coasts and islands of Arabia on the East In li.-s Station, not being Indian, Persian or Iraq waters. 2. In Arabian waters, salutes are to l&gt;e fired on the same occasions and tmng the same number of guns, as in Indian waters. 3. The Political Resident (11.M. Consul General) is entitled to a salute of 13 guns, with the Viceroy’s flag at the fore, within the limits of his juris diction, and is received by a Subaltern’s guard (see K.R. &amp; A.I., Art. t&gt;t&gt;. IXa.'I 4. When the Political Resident, ora Political Agent, is on board within the limits of his jurisdiction, or on duty elsewhere, the Viceroy’s Hag is to be hoisted at the fore (K.R. &amp; A.I., Art. 65 a.) 5. Personal salutes and local information are shown in the following table:— Area in which Salute is fired l Authority Occasion No, of guns Honours Flags (a) Abu Dhabi 1. Shaikh Shakht bin Sultan (present Shaikh of Abu Dhabi) Conclusion of 1st visit to H.M. ship during each stay in port 5 Alert Zanzibar at fore 2. Successor to preseu t Shaikh 3 ’* ” (b) Aden Protectorate Chief Commissionei K R. &amp; A I. Art. 66 13 Subaltern’s G uard Red Ensign at fore, »»t own Hag Note.—Owing to the proximity of the hospital to the moorings, salutes are to be fired from off-shore guns when H.M. Ships are in the Inner Harbour at Aden. (c) Ajman Shaikh of Ajman Conclusion of 1st visit to H.M, ship during each stay in port 3 A lert Zanzibar at fore (d) Bahrein 1. H.E. The Shaikh of Bahrein 2. Eldest son of the Shaikh when acting as Deputy of the Shaikh 11 Sergeant’s Guard None Bahrein State at fore tl 3. Political Agent of Bahrein K.R &amp; A 1 Art. 66. IXB n • None Viceroy* at fore (e) Dehai Shaikh of Debai Conclusion of 1st visit to H.M. ship during each stay in port .»&gt; Alert Zanzibar at fore |f) Kuweit. 1. H.E. The Shaikh of Kuweit 2. Eldest Son of the Shaikh when acting as Deputy of the Shaikh n ft Sergeant’s Guard None Kuweit at fore ^ 3. Political Agent at Kuweit K.K. &amp; A.I. *rt. 66 IXB n None Viceroy’s at fore [200 31-12-34]. . iTo be xu tituted for page 16 undated) East Indies Station Ora r Book. Salutes and Ceremonies. 55. Salutes — conti n ued. Section ** B Salutes in Arabian waters and \&amp;en—continutd. .A re a in which rtalnte is fired 1 Authority Occasion No. of guns Honours Flags Muscat 1. Salute on arrival First arrival in each 21 Guard and Muscat at year, and after re- Band main commissioning 2, H.H. the Sultan of Official visit, on 21 Captain's Dress Muscat and Oman H.H. departure Guard and overall. from H.M. Ship Band Muscat at main for • salute Informal visit Nil Alert None 3. Council of Ministers i Conclusion of each 17 Subaltern’s Muscat at as a whole visit to H.M. Ship Guard fore 4. President of Council 13 1 (if a member of the liuling Family) 5. President of Council ;i i Sergeant’s (if not a member of j Guard the Huling Family) j 6. Individual members 5 None of Council 7. Political Agent and K.R.&amp; A.I., Art. fib 11 None Viceroy’s H.M. (VmKiiI at IX R at fore Muscat 1 Note. —Salutes are not normally to be fired on Friday, the Moslem equivalent of Sunday ; but salutes fired by foreign warships on this day are to be returned, an explanation being made to the Sultan later. (h) Qatar Shaikh of Qatar Conclusion of 1st visit to H.M. ship during each stay in port 7 Sergeant’s Guard Zanzibar at fore (i) Has al- Khaimah (j) Sharjah (k) Umm-al- Qaiwain Shaikh of Has-al - Khaimah Shaikh of Sharjah Shaikh of Umm-al- Qaiwain Conclusion of 1st visit to H.M. Ship during each stay in port 3 Alert [200—31-12-:*4]Enclosureto East Indies letter IJc. 1079 /E.!• 1202 cf7|h T Ancust, 1933. 9 APPENDIX V. % GUN SALUTES AND LOCAL CEREMONIAL. (See A rticle 18.) SECTION L—PERSIAN GULF [THE TRUCIAL COAST, MUSCAT AND GWADAR]. (For notes applicable to items in this Table, see back of page.) Area in which I I . No. of T t Salute Authority 1 Occasion Honours Flags la t i red I __l i (a) Abu Dliabi 1 Shaikh Shakbut bin Sultan Conclusion of first visit to H.M. 5* Alert Zanzibar i (the present Shaikh of Abu ship during stay in jiort j fore Dhabi) -I a i 2 Successor to present Shaikh or —do.— 3 —do.— do. his official deputy during his absence (b) Ajman | Shaikh of Ajman or his offic- —do.— 3 —do.— 7 ial deputy during his absence (c) Bahrein 1 1 H.E. Shaikh Sir Hamad bin —do.— 11* Sergeant's Bahrein (d) Debai (e) Kuweit (f) Muscat and Gwadar Note—Salutes are not normally to be fired on Fri day, the Moslem equivalent of Sunday; but sal utes fired by foreign warships to British flags are to be returned according to the custom of the Service, and ex planation made to the Sultan later. (g) Qatar (h) Ras-al- Khaimah (i) Sharjah (j) Umm-al- Qaivvain Authority Occasion No. of Guns Honours 1 Shaikh Shakbut bin Sultan Conclusion of first visit to H.M. 5 # Alert (the present Shaikh of Abu ship during stay in port Dhabi) 2 Successor to present Shaikh or —do.— 3 —do.— his official deputy during his absence Shaikh of Ajman or his offic- —do.— 3 —do.— ial deputy during his absence 1 H.E. Shaikh Sir Hamad bin —do.— 11* Sergeant's Isa al Khalifah. k.c.s.i. (the Guard present Shaikh of Bahrein) 2 Successor to present Shaikh or —do.— 7 —do.— his official deputy during his ' absence . l 3 Political Agent K.R. &amp; A.I. 11 Alert 1 Shaikh of Debai or his official Conclusion of first visit to H.M. 5 —do.— deputy during his absence ship during stay in port 2 Shaikh Juma —do.— 1* — 1 H.E. Shaikh Sir Ahmed al Conclusion of first visit to H.M. 11* Sergeant's Jabir as Sabah, k.c.i.e., c.s.i. ship during stay in port Guard (present Shaikh of Kuweit) j 2 Successor to present Shaikh or —do.— 7 —do.— his official deputy during his absence 3 Political Agent K.R. &amp; A.I. 11 Alert 1 Salute on arrival First arrival in each. year, and 21 Guard and after recommissioning Band i 2 H.H. The Sultan of Muscat Official visit, on the departure of 21 Officer s and Oman H.H. from H.M. ship Guard and Band Informal visit Nil Alert 3 H.H. The Sultan's official dep- Conclusion of first visit to H.M. uty in his absence :— ship during stay in port If a member of the Ruling Family 13 Sergeant s If not a member of the Ruling Guard Family 9 —do.— 4 Political Agent &amp; H.M. Consul K.R. k A.I. 11 Alert Shaikh of Qatar or his official Conclusion of first visit to H.M. 7 Sergeant's deputy during his absence ship during stay in port Guard Shaikh of Ras-al-Khaimah or —do.— 3 Alert his official deputy during his absence 1 Shaikh Sultan bin Suggar (the —do.— 5* —do.— present Shaikh of Sharjah) 2 Successor to present Shaikh or —do.— 3 —do.— his official deputy during his absence Shaikh of Umm-al-Qaiwain or —do.— 3 —do.— his official deputy during his absence fore —do.— —do.— —do.— e-c. [170—1-2-3GJ Personal Salute.Gun Salutes and Local Ceremonial. Notes.—(0 The territorial waters of the Persian Gulf (other fhan the territorial waters of Iraq and Iran) are Indian waters, and salutes are to be fired on the same occasions and usinjr the same number of guns as for Indian waters. (ii) The Political Resident, Persian Gulf (II.M. Consul General) is entitled to a salute of 13 sruns. with the Viceroy’s fla;' at the fore, within the limits of his jurisdiction, and is received with the Alert. Guard and band are not to be paraded. I (iii) When the Political Resident or a Political Afrent is on board one of H.M. ships within the limits of his jurisdiction, or on duty elsewhere, the Viceroy’s fiatr is to be hoisted at the fore (K.R. k A.I., Art. 65a). (iv) The Senior Naval Officer. Persian Gulf, is to inform all naval authorities in the Persian Gulf when an official deputy to any of the rulers included in the Table is appointed, and whether he is entitled to receive the salute and honours. Ships are not to fire salutes or accord honours to deputies alsmt whom official information has not been received from the S.N.O.P.G.PY OF FRC : Secretary of State for India, TO: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Repeated to Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department; Political Agent, Bahrein and Political Agent, Muscat. DATED: 14th November 1936. No.P.Z. 7725/36. Please refer to the correspondence ending with my telegram No.3176, dated 6th November, on the subject of air facilities at Kalba. agreement itself and (b) the exchange of letters with the Shaikh of Kalba; and desire to associate myself with the views regarding the services of Captain Hickinbotham, Commander Harvey and Squadron-Leader Fogarty, which are expressed in paragraph 6 of Colonel Loch’s letter of the 21st September, No.704-3 of 1936. Copies of letters which have I approve the action taken in regard to (a) the (without been addressed to the Air Ministry and Admiralty are enclosed. As indicated in my telegram of the 6th November, the salute granted to the Shaikh of Kalba is personal, and I should be glad to receive, in due course, your views regarding the question of making the salute dynastic- The issue of the above has been authorised. (Sgd.) M. J. OLAUSONINDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.¥. 1- P.Z. 7725/36. 12th Novemher 1936. Sir, I am directed, hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to the letter from the offl elating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (with its enclosures) of the 21st September, copy of which was forwarded with India Office printed letter of the 8th October, No.P.E.0109/36, on the subject of air facilities at Kalba, from which it will be seen that the officiating Agent at Bahrein has now been successful in obtaining the required facilities on the minimum authorised terms. In this connection I am to forward a copy of an Express Letter which has been sent to the (without Political Resident in the Persian Gulf conveying approval of enclosures). the action taken in regard to (a) the agreement itself, and (b) the exchange of letters relative to the recognition of Shaikh Sa’id bin Hamad as an independent .ruler. Lord Zetland desires to associate himself with the views expressed by Colonel Loch and Captain Hickinbotham regarding the assistance rendered by Squadron—Leader Fogarty and (without Commander Harvey, and I am to forward a copy of a letter to enclosures). the Admiralty in regard to the latter. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) M. a. CLAUSON The Secretary, Air Ministry, W.C. 2.INDIA OFFICE, P.Z. 7725/36* WHITEHALL, 3.V. 1. 12th November 1936. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the letter from the officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (with its enclosures) of the 21st September, a copy of which was forwarded with India Office printed letter of the 8th October, No.P.Z.7109/36, on the subject of air facilities at Kalba, and to state, for the information of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, that Lord Zetland desires to associate himself with the views expressed by Colonel Loch and Captain Hickinbotham regarding the services rendered by Commander Harvey. without A copy of a letter which has been addressed to the Air enclosures. Ministry is enclosed, together with a copy of an Express without Letter sent to the doYornmont— of India, enclosures# A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, wjmmm The Secretary to the Admiraltyumbh nan 7725/36. (29+29+30 words) CYPHxjR TELEGRAM FRQIA SECi.ST.iHY OP S T.ATE TO POLITICAL REST LENT IN THE PERSIAN GULP, RATED 6th NOVEIvIBER 1936. ■y 3176. Addressed to Resident repeated to Government oi India and Political A^ent&gt; Bahrein. Your uelegram dated 28th October No. 754. ICALB^. Per sonal Salute oi three guns has been approved by King and you may now act in accordance with paragraph 5 oi Loch’s letter oi 21st September.» 3rd November 1936. Lord Zetland presents his humble duty to Your tojesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that the Sheikh of Kalba, in the region of the Persian Gulf, may be granted a personal salute of three guns. Kalba is situated on the Eastern coast of Trucial Oman and is about half way between Bahrein and Gwadar on the direct air route to India; considerable importance is attached to the establishment of an emergency landing site at that place. As a result of recent negotiations the Sheikh of Kalba has consented to provide facilities for this purpose and in consideration of the recognition of his independence he has undertaken to observe the terms and conditions prescribed in the Treaties and agreements at present binding upon other Sheikhs of Trucial Oman. In consequence the local political authorities have represented that the dheikh should be granted a personal salute of three guns both as an expression of appreciation of his attitude in regard to the establishment of the landing ground and as a formal recognition of his independence.■I The proposal has the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty,ECF/CWP/DIA. 4r2iXo 1936 ^(93 groups) DECY PHER OP T E U E G R A m« *M.zMVMt 2 ou*nm*,*vtr,aB^\in tK-mm*’m imv mm iiiw&lt; cn^rwitciu^n ■m m ■mramummmmnm '■ • 1 *•* ** Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Received Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary’ of State for India* Risner^ 21st September$&gt; 1936 0 21st September^ 1936,. 3-45 pom© 66I 0 Addressed to Secretary of State for India^ i^epeated to Government of India*. telegram No»113~’T* ftPlLlSfl August 29th*. air facilitieso Sheikh of Shargah and Has- al^Khaimah may be trying to make difficulties* and I have sent suitable verbal warning© 2 C X am arranging with Air Officer Commanding to carry out work on landing ground as soon as possiblec 3« Pragraph No,3 (sic).Sheikh objected strongly to gun salute not being included in the agreement pointing out that salute is outward sign of independence* I think that* as we have got agreement* it would be well to grant personal salute of three guns and to fire it for him as soon as possible in order to show local world that we have in fact recognised him* This should put a stop to any mischief- making© Please consult Fowle* Question of making salute dynastic can be considered later* as there are '/arious local considerations which must be taken into account*?indexed Xith the compliment Secretary of the Admiralty. Admiralty. 29th Jan u ary &lt; 19 36* &amp;GPY SENT TO ENCLOSU RE IN WEEKLY L ETTte Mo. 6 6FEB1936 FRO 1 CRRRr. , i . (CAL AMD SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Admiralty Ref.Ho. M »69/36 Your Ref.Ho. The Under Secretary of State) INDIA OFFICE, S.W. 1. P. “•.VM.69/36. / • o 98 ( 5- ^5r~ lO* m 29th January! 6 Sir : With refere ice to your letter No* £*15209/82/377 of the 3rd January, concerning the exchange of gun salutes in Iraq, I co.'imanaed by Ky Lords Co,.misaioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for ttie infornuition of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs * that they observe from Bagdad despatch Ho* 650 that the iabasay, in corncam^ the naval scale of salutes to the Iraqi Ministry of oreign Affairs, stated, without qualification, that the salute for a Captain is 7 guns* 2* As the Secretary of State will be aware from the table appended to Article 66 of King*8 Regulations and Admiralty Instructions, only return salutes ore given to Captains* This is an important distinction regarding which, My Lords consider, the Iraqi Authorities should not be left in any doubt. They suggest therefore that the liabassy at Bagdad should be informed accordingly in order that a a itable opportunity may be taken to make the distinction clear to the Iraqi Government if this has not been done already# 3* A copy of this letter has been sent to the t India Office* 1 an, oir, Your obedient lerva ?’t, *3* The Under feerotary of State, FOHHICd OFFIGK, S# &lt;• 1* T.rr j j 82 u 193:6 lo9- 650 . (9/38/86) British .teTjasay, 16th Deo^ '-ber, 1956. Sir, ^ith raeferenoe to yo\:r despatch Ifo. b r ro (t 3075/ 82/577) of August l^th last, X have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of the note which hr. Batman sent to the Iraqi hint ally of Foreign Affairs concerning the scale of ceremonial salutes to be accorded on the occasion of British navra visits to Basra, together with a transla tion of the Iraqi 0owmment , s reply. £. It will he observed that the Iraqi Gioverment otill express diceatisfaction with the salute to be accorded to the Mutssawtf. But since the decision not to increase this salute was only reached after protracted discussion with the departments of His Majesty* s Qoro&amp;mmt concerned, I have authorised n nsmber of isy otaff to sxplsin once more to the Ministry of ‘orei ipn Affairs tho rcauona for the present salute of 7 sms, and to inform Xhmi that in ay opinion no purpose would be served by referring the matter bacx to you for i*cconeiueration. I trust, therefore, that the Iraqi Covemient will now lot tho matter drop*(o* Enclosure in Bagdad despatch No* 650 dated 16.12.35. No. 447 His Majesty^ Embassy present their compliments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and have the honour to in vite attention to the Ministry’s note No. 8646 of November 14th last, in which it was suggested that: (a) British warships visiting Basra should fire a salute of eleven guns when receiving a call from the Mutasarrif, and (b) The scale of salutes to be fired from the saluting base at Basra should be 17 guns for an Admiral of the Fleet 15 guns for an Admiral 13 guns for a Vice-Admiral or Rear-Admiral 11 guns for a Commodore. The Ministry also suggested that, as the minimum salute in the Royal Naval Scale was that laid down for a Commodore of the Royal Navy, and as it was considered that the rank of Mutasarrif was equivalent to that of a Commodore, the Mutasarrif at Basra should receive a salute of eleven guns. 2. His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom have given their most careful consideration to these suggestions and His Majesty’s Embassy are now instructed to make the following observations thereon. 3. The Royal Naval Scale of salutes is as follows : 19 guns for an Admiral of the Fleet 17 guns for an Admiral 15 guns for a Vice-Admiral 13 guns for a Rear-Admiral 11 guns for a Commodore (no senior Captain being present) 7 guns for a Captain. /This2 This scale is entirely in accordance with international practice. 4. His Majesty’s Embassy assume that the Iraqi Govern ment desire that the practice at Basra should be in conform ity with that at other ports the world over and they there fore suggest, for the Ministry’s consideration, that the Royal Naval Scale should be substituted for that set out at (b) above. 5. As regards the suggestions at (a) above, the Ministry will observe that the last phrase of paragraph 1 of their note under reference appears to have been based on a misapprehension. In any case His Majesty’s Govern ment consider that it is undesirable to endeavour to grade provincial Governors with officers of the Royal Navy. 6. In their view a more suitable relationship would ■ i be that between the Mutasarrif of Basra and similar author ities and independent rulers in the Persian Gulf. In the latter cases, the permanent salute is seven guns. Por this reason His Majesty’s Government feel bound to adhere to the existing salute to the Mutasarrif at Basra, 7. His Majesty’s Embassy trust that the Ministry will share the views of His Ivlajesty’s Government on this subject. His Majesty’s Embassy avail themselves of this opportunity to renew the expression of their highest con sideration. / / / ^ ; British Embassy, Bagdad. 9th September, 1935.Enclosure in Bagdad despatch No. 650 dated 16.12.35. 8 2 © i y 3 (&gt; ■ ? As No. 10112. Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Bagdad, 21st November, 1935. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty’s Embassy, Bagdad, and, with reference to the correspondence ending with the Embassy’s note No. 447 dated 9th September, 1935, have the honour to inform the esteemed Embassy that the arrangement stated in paragraph 3 of the above mentioned note has been agreed to, subject to the con dition that it should include the firing, for a Mutasarrif, of a salute of an equal number of shots as is fired for a Brigadier (Amir Liwa). The Ministry hope that the esteemed Embassy will share their view that the grade of a Mutasarrif, in view of his important position in the administration of State affairs and of his being representative of the Government in his post, is not, in this respect, less important than that of an Amir Liwa. In awaiting a reply the Ministry avail them selves of this opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. His Britannic Majesty’s Embassy, Bagdad.I 7 {Z V ^ ,f A ^ r 1: f %) © o o ] A. / v ifc' /a-r (b) Sharjah. The Honourable the Political Resident arrived at Sharjah on the evening of the 6th October. When the Shaikn came off to call on the Honourable the Political Resident the 7th October he was informed that His Majesty s Governmen had been pleased to grant him an extra 2 guns as a personal salute.i; t\\ P.Z.181/36. CONFIDENTIAL. EXTRACT PROM LETTER OP PROCEEDINGS lst-15th OCTOBER 1935 (N 0 . 6 /A) PROM THE COMMANDING OPPICER, H.M.S. LUPIN, DATED 16th OCTOBER 1935. $ ■ SHARJAH - 5th-7th October. 8 . Colonel Loch had sent a message to the Shaikh of Sharjah that he was bringing good news for him and when he came off to call the following morning he was told that his personal salute had been increased from 3 to 5 guns, which were fired when he left the ship. I told the Shaikh that the Senior Naval Officer was unavoidably detained at Bahrain and at the same time gave him the Senior Naval Officerk congratulatory message. The Shaikh did not appear to register much pleasure when he heard of this honour and outside observers thought the interview had fallen a little flat; certainly the dignity of the proceedings was interrupted by the Shaikh’s four year old son, who found that two glasses of sherbet were straining his capacity. f Ammmmmtmtmmmmmmrn *7 Hi NO. C/3l4 of 1935. Office of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, t+s &lt; H•:t. S.Lupin, At Sea. prom ~ Tthe Hon 1 ble Li eut.•Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I*S.» To * The ^oreiejn Secretary to the Government of India, I have the honour to refer to your tele gram No .2591 dated the 23rd September 1935, in which sanction was conveyed to the increase of the personal salute of Shaikh Sultan bin sa^ar. Ruler of Sharjah, from three to five gun s. 2. On the 6th October 1935 shaikh sultan bin baqar came to P®y his call upon me on board H»IT. S.Lupin. I had warned him beforehand by telegram that I had good newe to communicate to him and he brought with him a number of his family and his leading men. I received him on the quarter deck of H.M. S*Lupin which had been suitably j decorated by order of the Commanding officer (Comroander T.H.Back). After the usual courtesies and coffee I informed the shaikh that His majesty Xhe King had been pleased to increase his personal salute from three to guns, and offered him appropriate congratulations. The Goramanding Officer, H.M.3.Lupin, then gave to the Shaikh a message of congratulation from the senior aval Officer, Persian Gulf, who added that he would have liked to have been present in H.M. S. Shorehan himself Officiating Political h^gident in the Persian Gulf, Simla Sir,to fire the firet salute with the increased number of guns* but that pressing affairs had rendered it impossible for him to do ao# 3. The shaikh expressed his deep gratitude to ilia Majesty fche King for the honour which had been bestowed upon him. 4. The first salute of five guns was fired when Shaikh sultan bin saqarleft H.M.S.Lupin at the end of his call* 5. i am sending a copy of this letter to the senior Naval officer# Persian Gulf. I have# etc.# Sd./ G* Loch Lieut.-Colonel Officiating political Resident in the Persian Gulf. r.t in the / t■■■■■■■■■ s&gt; IT/DIA. ul- COPY (56 groi &lt;£) groups) 5011. £L£_£JL£.H.E_£_J)_E TJLLJUUeL&amp;JL Prom Political Resident In the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India, Dated Rlsher, 19th September, 1935. Received 19th September, 1935, 10-30 a.m. X ^ 795^ Loch to Claueom Salute ShelJch of Sharjah^ Senior Naval Officer has received telegraphic sanction to increase® Unless Powle would rather it await his next tour* I should like to accord it for first time on tour of Tiucial Coast beginning October* as it might help over Kalba® Please telegraph reply® ft£Co. POL. OEPt. it 9 SEP 1935 INDIA OFFICE14 —6130 11686 (2) In any further communication on this subjedyplease quote o any person by name, wit to— / / /*■ ! r~ Q o p 0 b D //?- @) ^iind address—wo^ to ‘The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign # Office, London, S.W. 1. fj) - THE Under-Secretary of State for ‘Foreign -Affairs presents his compliments to an( ^’ by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, V/IQBj'T % Reference to previous correspondence : r ’ T)p,scrrrttrnr\, of Frtrlnsurp ^ — '' Description of Entclosure. Name and Date. Subject.(T 8073/82/377) - '•rrz, - -* 9 » r on p • OO..D w I !9 : r ' NO DISTRIBUTION. Code telegram to Mr* ataman ( agdad). Foreign Oifioe. 2nd August, 19«35* 6*30 p.m# No* 186. My telegram No* 4 of Janua y 2 d, last jiaragra h* India Office have raised strong objections to increase or Mutasarrii^s salute above 7 guns owing to probable repercussions amongst other notables in Persian Gulf, fe do not feel dispobed to contest their view* Despatch follows*V ? wo. 673. i RR°6 ! pomiat* cotioi, pn7^/nj/s77) l i . &gt; * ■ r ■* { \ ^ v l^th ni^ust, 1^36, *iir 9 ■ 1th referenoe to ay telavras N o»lQ6 of the 2nd 4u,uRt f T hsve to Inform you th t hb the result of e protracted discussion with the departments concerned re andln * the ceremonial salute to be accorded to the utaearrlf of arra, it has been decided that such salute shall not be increased beyond the seven ^uns at present ^iven. 2* 'he /tew taken by the Secret©ry of State for India, in which the Lords 'osamissionerr of the Admiralty concur, is thst any ectior which ai^ht encoura ;e demands for a general Increase in the scale of salutes in the ersian Half should be avoided and that it is undesirable to ^recle ovemore with T aval of'ice^e in these matters, and ho hi s accordingly oonsldered the question in its relation to the salutes accorded to the local nheikhs end Governors. r’he rarquens of Zetland obBervee that, although personal salutes of 11 guns have been . ranted to th&lt; f heikhs of ah^eln nnd ^owelt, the permanent hereditary eialute accorded to these Sheikhs Is 7 ^ms and he considers thet it would be moot undesirable to accord a larger aal ite to the utasarrif than to these independent rulers. He fearn moreover that an increeie la the salute of the Kutasar if would lead to a demand for/ H. Bateman, Haq# , •• 0 * f etc., etc., eto. , Ba ;dad.for &lt; 50 Pr®»i&gt;ondin^ increasum ©Ise^hcre, »nd feeling that the vovamors &lt;*t Bunder Abbue, ohaa «rah and Abadan aho Id be regarded as on the aaifte footln c , aa the tutaaar If, he c^nsidern that any requeatn froea the* for a el&amp;ll&amp;r inorease to that of the Hutaaarylf would aooordin ly be difficult to refuse, 3 , T request therefore* the- you will ooaimuniaate to the Iraqi ovemaent the oyal w aval ncale of salutes enoloaed in if ^ohn 'icon’s deapateh no.TO3 of the 15th november last, with a Bug* eatlen that this scale, which la in aooordance with international practice, should he substituted for the proposed Iraqi ?*eale. You should at the turn time explain that the decision to adhere to the axis tin, oalute for the Mutaser if of Basra is based on the scale of salutea accorded to similar authorities in th ersian ulf. I s &lt;, with 0 reat truth, Mr, Y ur obedient ervant, (For the B oretBry of tate) ,' 40 . ^Sd.) kMfc,v»t-M.3417/35. 2nd 5 Sir fiitfc refereneo to your letter of the 14th January, Ko.T .82/02/377, on the subject of the exohunn® of rvn Siilutee in IrA ,, I ab oom..mle&lt;l by ny Loris Oorasionionort! of the iteirulty to ac iUaint you, for the infomution of the : ocret-ry of 3tute for ibrei n .Ji -ire, that in the li iit of the oonsideritiono put forward in India Cfi'ioe letter of the let July, So.i.i..340fi/35, Iheir bozdships are die,osod to a ree with the ..eoret-ry of at-to for India that the beat oourie would be to adhere to a salute of 7 nms for the Ihitasurif of Bueru, and 1’hey aufj^jst that this should be justified on the ■ round th.it it is in uooordanoe with the soide of salute aooorded to similar uutherities in the . orsian Oulf. .n regards i&gt;-ra;rraih 3 of the letter iron the Iru ; i Ministry of .•'ore l n fairs dated 14 th 1 orenber, 1934, (a copy of which was forwarded with your letter under reference), % lords would he glad, provided the .secretary of State sees no objection, if the Hoyd i;avul no.de of nblutes could be aommlcated to the Ira ii Governwmt with a autogestion that this mj.de, which is in .ocord-nco with intern..tiond jacuetiec, should be substituted for the proponed Ira,i scale. oopy of this letter has been sent to the India Office. I as, ir Tour obedient bervunt The Under eornt.ry of dtato i'orei'^ fi'fice.12-4 © P.Z.3406/35 Minute Paper. political Department. The note from the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs requesting that the salute of the Mutasarif at Basra be that it is politically desirable to make some concession to the Iraqi Government and propose that the salute of the Mutasarif should be increased to 9 guns. The Admiralty raise no objection but have asked for our views. As the Iraqi Government asked for an increase to 11 guns they may not be particularly grateful when it is only increased to 9 guns. It seems therefore that jtrcl ecA. if tfc*. the advantages/7ef t&amp;e Foreign Office propnrrftl are dj'awbackLr: Firstly, the permanent salute of the Sheikhs of Q,atr, Bahrein and Koweit is 7 guns. The Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein have been granted personal salutes of 11 guns, but the hereditary salute has remained 7. It is clearly undesirable that a larger permanent salute should be granted to the Mutasarif than to these independent Rulers. Secondly, an increase in the salute of the Mutasarif might lead to a general demand for increases in the scale 'fy*.; of salutes, wkiah should, if possible, be avoided. In particular, the Persian Governors of Abadan, Mohammerah and Bunder Abbas might rightly contend that they ought to be treated on the same footing as the Mutasarif. Thus their demands for an increase would be difficult to refuse. It is submitted, therefore, that the proposal to increase the salute of the Mutasarif should be increased to 11 guns will be found at Flag *■- • The Foreign Office (see their letter at Flag £ ) consider doubtful; Jkvr-I+J 'itz oijcJ-^ k ihz c ©'’• tc- s-et against thio- there- are 1 other definite 2956 6000 7/?4P.Z.3406/35. Draft Paper. political Department. DRAFT LETTER n • 1 JUl The Secretary of the Admiralty Sir, I an directed by the s/s for I. to refer to Admiralty letter of the 17th May, No• M.225/35, regarding a proposal to increase the salute of the Mutasarif Basra from 7 to 9 guns. The S/S agrees with the view taken by Their Lordships that any action which might encourage demands for a general increase in the scale of salutes in the Persian Gulf should be avoided and that it is undesirable to grade Governors with Naval officers in these matters. He has accordingly considered this proposal in its relation to the salutes accorded to the local Sheikhs and Governors. He observes that, although personal salutes of 11 guns have been granted to the Sheikhs of Bahrein and Koweit, the permanent hereditary salute accorded to ♦ these Sheikhs is 7 guns and he considers the salute of the Mutasarif would lead to a demand for corresponding increases elsewhere. He feels that the Governors of Bunder Abbas, Mohammerah and Abadan should be regarded on the same footing as the Mutasarif. and that th^ii' demands for/ SURE \H WEEKLY LETTER 28 11 JUL 1935 * v SECRETARY, POLITICAL and that it would be most undesirable to accord a larger salute to the Mutasarif than to these independent Rulers moreover, that an increase in v^ORET DRPT. INDIA OFFICE - - | | WHIIH |l COPY SENT TO_ 343(»A 5000 1.35for a similar increase to that of the Mutasarif would be difficult to refuse. /A ^ fyd Hs-lms therefore come to—tire that he cannot(/asawft to thre proposal and he hopes that Their Lordships, in view of the considerations set out above, will concur inlhis view. A C« iL-\ i 0^ t. * ^°. (Sd.) \T. C. 'WALTON. V' APPROVED POLITICAL COMMITTEUtAny further communication should be addressed to:— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l. quoting ' M * Sir, 1 - a ”'T T7 Admiralty, S.W.l. l.Tth.May., /.9J5 . • £ '*? ^ 2°/t ^ '* I am commanded 'by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, a copy of a letter from the Foreign Office, with enclosures, on the subject of the exchange of gun salutes in Iraq. 2. With regard to the gun salute to he given to the Mutasarrif of Basra, Their Lordships appreciate that this question involves political considerations with which They are not primarily concerned. From the naval point of view, however, They would deprecate any action which might encourage demands for a general increase in the scale of salutes in the Persian Gulf and They consider therefore that the argument in paragraph 2 of the letter of the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs dated the 14th November last is not one to he encouraged. In their view it is undesirable to attempt to grade Governors with Naval Officers for this purpose, and cases must he decided in their relation to the salutes given to local Sheikhs and otner Governors. 3. Having regard to the present scale of salutes in the Persian Gulf, shown in the enclosed statement ’A’ , My Lords would have no objection to an increase of the number of guns at present accorded to the Mutasarrif to nine, which is the number recommended by the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies. 4. As regards paragraph 3 of the letter from the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs, My Lords propose to ask the Foreign Office to communicate the Royal Naval scale of salutes to the Iraqi Government and to suggest that this scale, which is in accordance with international practice, should be substituted for the proposed r Iraqi scale. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,HO.T 82/82/377. /. * Foreign Office, •&gt;: s.w.i. v i-j v J S J 14th January, 1935. Sir, f . V • '-W* I am directed toy Secretary Sir John Simon to enclose, for the information of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, a copy of a telegram on the subject of the excnange of gun salutes and official calls at Basra which was received from His Majesty’s Ambassador at Bagdad while your letter (M*4480/34) of the 8th December last was under consideration, together with a copy of the reply which has been sent to Sir Francis Humphrys after informal consultation with your department by telephone. I am also to ^ enclose a copy of the letter of the 17th November from the Chancery of His Majesty’s Embassy to which reference is made in the telegram sent to the Ambassador, covering a copy of a note from the Iraqi Government, dated the 14th November. 2. As regards the request of the Iraqi Government that the Mutasarrif of Basra should in future be saluted with eleven guns instead of with seven as at present, Sir John Simon feels it to be politically desirable to make some concession in the direction of meeting these wishes. If possible, he would prefer to comply with them in full, but he fully realizes that in view of relations with other officials and authorities on the Arab side of the Persian Q. u lf ? the re may be serious difficulties in the way of doing so. In any case ne hopes that it may at least be possible for Their Lordships to agree to a salute of nine guns being given to the Mutasarrif. 3. Sir John Simon presumes that the Lords Commissioners will consult with His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in the matter in so far as may be considered necessary. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) Patrick Roberts. The Secretary of the Admiralty.• 'i -. &gt;- . • J. ' 1 .Vv , . ■ .• L J t s. ’ 1 . V ’1 ^ x ' i*iC' .u U- r -c; •. 'iv i ' • ' ' ■ ' w - ' ' ; v ; ai. io i '.is. no . ..... •. ‘i .. - . • - o . ..... s. - • v .. o*- . -i . • -i ' . '.i» •• . - r. . , C. . - O! * - ~ J. i .. 3 &gt; ‘x. v w . ivfy: - o t ,t . t -A ... . .f '.. :• . J • . • J i 1 a . SJ . , . vl s r s . iS.y 1 ni .v f ■ i .[ . rv 0 ^ : ■ J -. jr • o . o . ;... .. a .. . A) A . •I V.: . -A 'a • . liA &gt; J' :.CJ . A U ••I V Sit ; ' - a -i •&gt;. ‘ . 1 i. 'V:. on a lo % .. . ' i A A^ .•x •' ■ ■ /o a ■ ..a . -i vc . : - ' . •: .. ■ • o • 1 ... ■ J C 2 &gt;•:•. i XI -_ xi. , ■ «. ..O ,,‘X -U XCi.' ' -U ' ... CA.. U .' ., .... •- O .. ..1 •. .. f J u ; ,scr*i ^1 ‘a jCOPY /a? T 14418/409/377) i? ^ 2 3 ^ i * ^ NO DISTRIBUTION. Decode. Sir F. Hiimphrys (Bagdad), 27th December, 1934 12.15 p.m. 27tn December, 1934 1.00 p.m. 27th December, 1934 No. 289. (R). Your telegram No. 200. When may I expect your definite instructions? As Commander-in-Chief East Indies arrives at Basrah shortly may I instruct Consul to advise him to make the first call on Mutessarif?COPY /a 6 ! (T_l3787/409/377) Code telegram to Sir P. Humphrys (Bagdad). Foreign Office. 2nd January 1935. 7.30 p.m. No. 4. (R) H tt »» tt It It It tt tt It It It It tt It It tt It It It It Your telegram No. 289 (of 27tn December: Salutes and visits at Basra). Question of national salutes raised 'by Ministry for Foreign Affairs in tneir note of August 14tn nas 'been adequately dealt witn Py Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, see Consul’s despatcn No. 30 of September 15tn. As regards excnange of visits witn Mutasarrif, custom is as stated in paragrapn 3 of Ministry’s note, and Mutasarrif should pay first call to tne Admiral. On visiting one ©f His Majesty’s Snips ne would he received Dy a guard and would he accorded a personal salute of seven guns on leaving tne snip. Question of increase from seven guns (see Cnancery’s letter of November 17th) is receiving sympathetic consideration but involves certain complications which are under discussion with other authorities concerned. For this occasion therefore a 7.gun salute will again he given and a decision on the general question will he communicated to you later.( 2,0 COPY * (T 13409/409/377) (277/18/34) British Embassy^ Bagdad. 17th November, 1934 Dear Department, Our letter No. 277/8/34 of August 22nd last about naval salutes in this country. We enclose a translation of a further note from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, from which you will see that they consider a salute of seven guns too few for a Mutasarrif. There was no mention of this number in their previous note and, pending your reply to our letter quoted above, we have not written to them on the matter. Their further information comes, no doubt, from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, vie the Mutasarrif of Basra (cf. Acting-Consul Hendry’s despatches No.29 of September 5th and No.30 of the same date, and No.34 of September 15th, especially the enclosure in No.30). We shall be glad to be furnished in due course with the material for a reply to the Ministry. Yours, &amp;c., CHANCERY. Treaty Department, Foreign Office.Urgent . No. 8646. The Ministry for Foreign Affairs present their compliment to His Britannic Majesty’s Embassy, Bagdad, and, in continuation of their note No.6046 dated 14th August, 1934, regarding salute firing by warships calling at the Port, have the honour to state that the British Naval Command have sanctioned the firing of only seven rounds in salute to the Governors of Abadan, Muhammerah or Bundar Abbas and the same number in the case of the Mutasarrif of Basrah, whereas the minimum number of salute rounds, as provided for in British 'second' (?standing) orders, is eleven. 2. As the Iraqi tjovernment consider the rank of a Mutasarrif to be equivalent to that of Commodore, they consider that British warships should, when receiving a call from the Mutasarrif, Basrah Liwa, at the Port of Basrah, fire a salute of eleven rounds instead of seven. 3. The Ministry suggest the following arrangement for salute firing : 17 rounds in the case of an Admiral of the Fleet. 15 ' '» ” ' ' an Admiral 13 »» »» »» »» ' a Vice-Admiral or Rear-Admiral. H ^ ^ ' a Commodore. 4. The Ministry request the esteemed Embassy to be so good as to approach the quarters concerned and secure their consent to this arrangement in order that it may be agreed upon, and that firing instructions may be laid down accordingly and the necessary orders issued on the subject. The Ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. Ministry for Foreign Affairs, Bagdad. 14th November, 1934.COPY (T 82/82/377) y\ Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to enclose, for the information of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, a copy of a telegram on the subject of the exchange of gun salutes and official calls at Basra which was received from His Majesty’s Ambassador at Bagdad while your letter (M 4480/34) of the 8th December last was under consideration, together with a copy of the reply which has been sent to Sir Francis Humphrys after informal consultation with your department by telephone* I am also to enclose a copy of the letter of the 17th November from the Chancery of His Majesty’s Embassy to which reference is made in the telegram sent to the Ambassador, covering a copy of a note from the Iraqi Government, dated the 14th November* 2, As regards the request of the Iraqi Government that the Mutassarrif of Basra should in future be saluted with eleven guns instead of with seven as at present, Sir John Simon feels it to be politically desirable to make some concession in the direction of meeting these wishes. If possible, he would refer to comply with them in full, but he fully realizes that in view of relations with other officials and authorities on the Arab side of the Persian Gulf, there may be serious difficulties in the way of doing so. In any case he hopes that it may at least be possible for I3&gt; f~ ? &gt; . A - ’ (V) i !523 I i ( r t 1 1/ * s FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. 14th January, 1935. The Secretary of the Admiralty.to a salute of nine guns for Their Lordships to agree being given to the Mutasarrif. 3. Sir John Simon presumes that the Lords Commissioners *111 consult with His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India in the matter in so far as may he considered necessary* I am, etc. (Sgd. ) Patrick 'Roberts.r t V I r~ r ^ ~y — w &lt;1 HQ. JISTB IBUTTOH (T 13787/409/377). Code telegram to Sir F. Humphrys (Bagdad.). Foreign Office. 2nd. January 1935. 7.30 p„m. No. 4. (R). n ;i n ii ii it n n u it ii H u K H ii || || || || || „ „ || ,| „ ,| „ „ , f ( j |( tl J( Your telegram No. 289 (of 27th December: Salutes and visits at Basra). Question of national salutes raised oy Ministry for foreign Aflairs in their note of Aivyast 14th has been adequately dealt with by Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, see Consul's desnatch No, 30 of September 15th. As regards exchange of visits with Mutasarrif, custom is as stated in paragraph 3 of Ministry’s note, and Muta sarrif should pay first call to the Admiral. On visiting one of His Majesty's ships he would be received by a guard and would be accorded a personal salute of seven guns on leaving the ship. Question of increase from seven guns (see Chancery's letter of November 17th) is receiving sympathetic con sideration but involves certain complications which are under discussion with other authorities concerned. For this occasion therefore a 7.gun salute will again be given and a decision on the you later. general question will be communicated toCOPY ( 277/l8/34 ) BRITI SB. EMBASSY• (T ^3409/409/377) BAGDAD. 17th November, 1934. Dear Department, Our letter No. 277/8/34 of August 22nd last about naval salutes in this country. We enclose a translation of a further note from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, from which you will see that they consider a salute of seven guns too few for a Mutasarrif. There was no mention of this number in their previous note and, pending your reply to our letter quoted above, we have not written to them on the matter. Their further information comes, no doubt, from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, via the Mutasarrif of Basra (cf. Acting-Consul Hendry’s despatches No. 29 of September 5th and No. 30 of the same date, and No. 34 of September 15th, especially the enclosure in No. 30). We shall be glad to be furnished in due course with the material for a reply to the Ministry. Yours ever, CHANCERY. Treaty Department, Foreign Office✓ Urgent No. 8646 Ministry for Foreign Affairs, Bagdad 14th November, 1934. The Ministry for Foreign Affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty 1 s Embassy, Bagdad, and, in continuation of their note No. 6046 dated 14th August, 1934, regarding salute firing by warships calling at the Port, have the honour to state that the British Naval Command have sanctioned the firing of only seven rounds in salute to the Governors of Abadan, Muhammerah or Bandar Abbas and the same number in the case of the Mutasarrif of Basrah, whereas the minimum number of salute rounds, as provided for in British ”second' (? standing) orders, is eleven. 2. As the ’Iraqi Government consider the rank of a Mutasarrif to be equivalent to that of Commodore, they consider that British warships should, when receiving a call from the Mutasarrif, Basrah Liwa, at the Port of Basrah, fire a salute of eleven rounds instead of seven. 3. The Ministry suggest the following arrangement for salute firing : 17 rounds in the case of an Admiral of the Fleet. 15 ' ' ' ' ' an Admiral. 13 ” ' ' ' ” a Vice-Admiral or Pear- Admiral . 11 ' ' ' ' ' a Commodore. 4. The Ministry request the esteemed Embassy to be so good as to approach the quarters concerned and secure their consent to this arrangement in order that/that it may he agreed upon, and that firing instructions may he laid down accordingly and the necessary orders issued on the subject. The Ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. His Britannic Majesty’s Embassy. Bagdad7 A 'hI a&lt;. Register No. H . P. z. SECRET. 4719/35• POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. //|2- H Letter Telegram from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged; 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chajj^rmn Under Secretary.. Secretary'of State Committfee Under /Secretary.. Secretary of State. 13! Uf. Salutes in the Persian Gulf. Approval hy His Majesty of the grant of an increased personal salute to the Sheikh of Sharjah. - ^ O'/V Copy of FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. l* 'l/c Previous Papers :— 1140 1000 8.32The previous submissions are at P.Z. 4441/35 and 3143/35. His Majesty has now approved the proposal, and we can inform the Government of India accordingly. A draft Despatch is submitted for the approval of the Secretary of State.Salute to 'be accorded to the present Sheikh of Sharjah. To His Excellency The Rt.Hon^le the Governor-General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to the letter from the Y&lt;rvJ\ Foreign Secretary to H4e- Excellency’s Government, No.D. 1742,j^^5&gt; of the 29th April, 1935&gt; on the subject of the salute to he accorded to the present Sheikh of Sharjah, I am to inform Your Excellency that His Imperial Majesty pleased to approve the grant to the present Sheikh of Sharjah of the:tu'i India Office, Whitehall. 6th August 1935. Lord Zetland presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty would be graciously pleased to approve that the Sheikh of Sharjah on the Trucial Coast of the Persian Gulf may be granted a personal salute of 5 guns. A salute of 3 guns for the Sheikh of Sharjah was included in the list of salutes to be fired by Your Majesty's ships in the Persian Gulf which was approved by Your Majesty in 1931* The Government of India and the local political authorities have now represented that it is desirable to increase the personal salute of the present Sheikh of Sharjah both as an expression of appreciation of the friendly attitude which he has adopted in connection with the organisation of the air route to India along the Arab coast of the Persian Gulf, and as a formal recognition of the importance of his position on the Trucial Coast. The present proposal has the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary ofState for the Colonies and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty.6th August 1935* Lord Tetland presents hie hu ble duty to Tour Kajesty and has the honour to submit that Tour ajesty would be graciously pleased to approve that the Sheikh of Sharjah on the Trueial Coast of the Persian Gulf may be granted a personal salute of 5 guns. A salute of 3 guns for the Sheikh of Sharjah was included in the list of salutes to be fired by Your Fajesty’s ships in the Persian Gulf which was approved by Your ’ajesty in 1931* The (Government of India and the loc^l political authorities have now represented that it is desirable to increase the personal salute of the present Sheikh of Sharjah both as an expression of eopreeistion of the friendly attitude which he has adopted in connection ®ith the organisation of the air route to India along the Arab coast of the Persian Gulf f and as a formal recognition of the importance of his position on the Trucial Coast. The present proposal has the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary ofState for the Colonies end the Lords Ceramistloners of the Admiralty.►- Minute Paper. P.Z. 4441/35 Department. r\ °n.L u The previous submission will be found at P.Z. 3143/35. The Foreign Office and the Admiralty have new concurred by letter and the Colonial Office by telephone. A draft submission is accordingly attached for the approval of the Secretary of State. ‘Y? ^ &lt;s-wj dt X»-r ^ ~n 2956 6000 7/34Draft Paper. /CO Department. DlriAPT SUBMISSION. The Marquess of'Zetland presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty would be graciously pleased to 'appTOTg' that 'thF SHeikh of Sharjahjmay be granted a personal salute of 5 guns, I A salute of 3 guns for the Sheikh of Sharjah was included in the list of salutes to be fired by Your Majesty T s ships in the Persian Gulf which was approved by Your Majesty in 1931. The Government of India and the local political authorities have now represented that it is desirable to increase the personal salute of the present Sheikh of Sharjah both as an expression of gncutHmd^ tAmir fur the friendly attitude which he has adopted in connection w^ith thej aTr route[and &amp;s- -) /J #/ v ^ •Lcfc. (f+xk aa of his oupe-riority o-vcr lire-other Ghcikho of tho Tpue^al Joaot ^. ^ La&gt; * &lt;fw&gt;7ZL The present proposal has the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of State for the Colonies and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty. S 3761 5000 5.35 iThe Under Secretary of State, Communications on this subject should be addressed to— Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. ') Downing Street. 8 July,1935. and the following Number quoted: 79015/35 Si: I am directed oy Mr. Secretary MacDonald to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. P.Z. 3143/35 of the 6th June forwarding a copy of a letter from the Government of India with enclosures, in which it is recommended that the salute of the Sheikh of Sharjah should he increased from three to five guns (personal to the present Sheikh), and to request you to inform the Secretary of State for India that he has no objection to the proposal. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant, THE UNDER SEGREThHY OF STATE,Any further communication should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l quoting 02751/35. 4 41 L.P.— No. 8. i^ Admiralty, S.W.l. 27.th.June, 5 -3P- Sir, With reference to your letter of the 6th June, No.P.2.3143/35, I am commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, that They concur in the prooosal to increase the salute of the Sheikh of Sharjah from 3 to 5 guns (personal to the present Sheikh). I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l. DM.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No i- 7081/82/377 I :T2 and address, ‘a v :ot to any person by name, Foreign Office. but to— S.W.l. “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. 22nd June, 1935. Sir, With reference to your letter No. P.Z.3143/35 of 35 of the 6th June ; I am directed hy Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India that he concurs in the Marquess of Zetland’s proposal to submit for The King’s approval that the gun salute accorded to the Sheikh of Sharjah he increased from 3 to 5 guns (personal to the present sheikh). I am. Sir Your obedient Servant The under-secretary of State India OfficeWKBrnkcmamrmumma h'? t i &lt; 'A Copy of a letter Ho. c/66 o t 4.935* dated Camp Bahrain, the 2nd April 1935, from the Hon* ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the foreign Secretary to the Govern ment of India, Hew Delhi. Subject*- Salute to Shaikh of Sharjah. I have the honour to enclose herewith a copy of letter Ho. C/l71-1.a/8, dated the 13th Karch 1935, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, suggesting that the salute to the Shaikh of Sharjah be increased from 3 to 5 guns as a personal one, and to say that this proposal has my approval* I discussed the matter with you on my recent visit to Delhi and understood that the Government of India would be prepared to consider this proposal favourably. The Shaikh of Abu Dhabi has a personal salute of 5 guns so there is a precedent on the Trucial Coast for raising the Shaikh of Sharj ah*s salute to the same number. I am giving a copy of Ihis letter to the political Agent, BahrainCOKgIDEK TIAL /il No.c/171-1.a/8. Political Agency, Bahrain, tlie 13th March 1935 Proms- Lieutenant Colonel Gordon Loch, I• A* , Political .A^ent, Bahrain. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Salute to Shaikh of Sharjah. Sir, I have the honour to recommend that the salute accorded to Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar of Sharjah be increased from three ^uns to five guns as a personal salute and that this honour should be granted to him on the occasion of the King«s Birthday and Silver Jubilee Celebrations in 1935. 2. You -will remember that we spoke of the possibility of increasing Shaikh Sultan , s salute on one or two occasions Out decided that the time was not then ripe for such a mark of honour. 3. shaikh sultan was the first of the Rulers on the Trucial Coast to give us facilities in connection with the air route, and had he not done so the position of Imperial Airways would have been very difficult in view of the attitude of the Persian Government. In doing so, he undoubtedly took a considerable risk of being murdered and incurred much odium, since that time he has stood by his agreement and has placed no difficulties in our way. 4. Shaikh Sultan is the senior of the ^awasim Shaikhs and, as such, it is to our interests to do anything we can, short of internal interference in his State, to consolidate hisIts* -2^ his position and to mark his superiority over the Shaikh of Has al Khaimah and o ther Shaikhs of the Qawasim, 5. Mhen the Air route -was first opened up. Shaikh Sultan was ignorant and inclined to be boorish, but he has much improved of late both in manners and intelligence and would, I think, be truly appreciative of, and not spoilt by, this proposed honour, were it to be granted to him. I have etc., sd. a. LOOK. Lieutenant Colonel, Political Agent, BahrainBUCKINGHAM PALACE 27th. June, 1953. My dear Oroft, I have laid before tne King the copies of the letters you enclosed from the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrain. His Majesty is glad that that the grant of personal salutes of 11 instead of 7 guns has given them both so much satisfaction. Yours sincerely W.D. Croft Esq, India Office 1 FR 0 M SECRETARY, f ■ SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Enclosure IN w v No. 26 29 JL'N'.iBJj FROM SECRETARY, P . '.Ml)ear Sir Clive, You may term ber that on the 30th March the Kin approved a proposal made by Sir Samoa! lioare thc^t the Sheikhs of Koweii and Bahrain should be granted personal salutes of 11 guns, in the place of 7-gun salutes* Colonel Fowls, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, has now informed the Sheikhs that His ivSajeety has been pleased to increase their personal salutes and the Sheikhs have asked that their dutiful xprecsions of gratitude for the honour which His Majesty has been pleased to bestow upon them may be laid before His Majesty. Cir Samuel Hoare wishes me, therefore, to send you the enclosed copies of the letters which the Resident has received from the uheikhs, for His Majesty’s perusal. colonel the HUHon. Sir Clive wigram, GCB*, GCVO., CSI. Yours sincerely.sammmmmmmm in INDEXED Copy of letter No.946 of l93'6f Sjted tbe 11th '' J ^ J in the Persian Gulf, to the Fo-r^igB Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Depa, With reference to the correspondence ending with If your telegram ho. 869 dated the 3rd aprii l93o, I have the honour to state, for the information of the Government of India, that the Hon*hie Lt. Colonel T.C.Fowle directed the Political Agents to inform the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait that His Pajesty the King had been pleased to increase their personal salutes from seven to eleven guns and at the same time wrote to the Shaikhs himself. 2. I enclose a translation of the replies that have been received from the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait and request that, if there is no objection, their dutiful expressions of gratitude for the honour, wdiich His Majesty has been pleased to bestow upon them may be laid before His Majesty the King. ment, Simla. Subject:-Increased Salutes to the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Kuwait. l-cttor * • [8 S - IS M^.1333Oopy in translation of a letoer dated the 17th Zi hejjah 1551 z 13th April 1933, from His Excellency Shaikh Hamad hin Isa al-Khalifah, Euler of Bahrain, to the Hon’hle Lt. Colonel T.C.Bowie, Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. After Compliments• I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your esteemed letter No. 96 dated the 9th Zihejjah 1351 corresponding the 5th April 1933-and understood the contents namely your sincere friendship and congratula tions to me for His FaJesty’s having been pleased to raise the number or salute to me from seven to eleven, 2. I have the honour to offer with due deference to His Majesty my heartfelt thanks and sincere gratitide for His f&amp;ndness and splendid disposition towards me. And I continue thanking Your Honour from the hot tom of my heart for your excellent ifiendship especially for your conveying such a gladdening news. I wish you the best of happiness and prosperity. In conclusion please accept my highest esteem and respec ts. \ \© Copy in translation of a letter 110.1^/2/912 dated the 17th SiheJjah 1351 corresponding 12th April 1933 from His Excellency &lt;oir Shaikh Ahmad hin Jahir al-Salsrah, E.C.I.S., C.S.I., Ruler of Kuwait, to the Hon’hle Lieut. Colonel T. C.Rowle, C.B.E. , Political Resident in the Peisian Gulf, Bushire. After Compliments. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter /No. 95 dated the 6th .April 1S33 and read it with pleasure and offer my thanks to His Majesty the King Emperor for his having 'been pleased to raise the number of salute to me from seven to eleven. 2. I receive this kindness with many thanks and gratitude while praying for His Majesty's long life. I hope I shall always he regarded with favours by you and to secure the complete satisfaction and considera tion of His Majesty. Usual Ending. iit.: Register No. f~A^ O0f t P.Z. mi /. Political Department. Letter Telegram from Dated Rec. Eormally acknowledged 192 Date. Initials. To / Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee a M Under Secretary Secretary of State... Council U.?S,3Z Tsi Table SUBJECT. SJ~TLs ''m /lyyLS .fas yxc^t erf / A AXcr ^°^ T&lt;r MLcuJCfs / r'i Copy to / O^AvC, FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY 'V\ c K ^t -fe- 7^4 /tCXD^cyy, c^iy \ .n APPROVED(Signed) Samuel Hoake. Political, No. 1. India Office, London, 20tb April 1933. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to the letter from the Foreign Secretary to Your Salutes to be accorded to the Excellency’s Government, No. D. 5334— present Shaikhs of Koiveit and Bahrain. N/32 of 25th January 1933, on the subject F\Z. 1944/33. 0 f sa l u tes to be accorded to the present Shaikhs of Kovveit and Bahrain, and in confirmation of my telegram No. 850 of 1st April 1933, I have to inform Your Excellency that His Imperial Majesty the King-Emperor has been graciously pleased to approve the grant to the present Shaikhs of Koweit and Bahrain of personal salutes of 11 guns. 1 have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant,Draft Paper. Department. DRAFT DESPATCH. Political Ho. /. My Lord , With, reference to the letter from the Foreign Secretary to Your Excellency’s Government, No.L.5334-N/32 of 25th January 1933, on the subject of the salutes to he accorded to the present Shaikhs of Koweit and Bahrain, a.nd in confirmation of my telegram No.85C of 1st April 1933, I have l.hu hmiU'iii to inform Your Excellency that I duly -H-r.d _ f -Mna r pp-roAr n 1 HiS Majesty the King/the pi upugnlb uoit-fe-aaneri ^5rn---triTe' G^evernmont—eP-~Indla^s lelter^and thrrt fiio Mo.jest-y has been graciously pleased to approve the4 the present Shaikhs of ''f Koweit and Bahrain may—be granted personal salutes of 11 guns. APPROVED POLITICAL COMMITTEE. 1401 5000 11.32&lt;£ r JHL/MJ FILE COPY ^~WZ~ 1944 195^o ^gj’oupa) SECRET 2072 BBCYPHER OP tBLESRA M. Prom (COPIES CIRCUITS!)). GoYernment of India, Foreign emd Political Department, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram addressed to Political Resident. Dated Hew Delhi, 3rd April, 1933. Received 4.45 pom^, 3rd April, 1933. XXX IMP0RT4OT. S69. Addressed to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Secretary of State for India. Secretary of Stated telegram 851, 1st April 0 Personal salutes for present Sheikh of Bahrein and Sheikh of Koweit. Please take action accordingly.IV India Office, Whitehall. 30 th Larch 1933* * Sir Samuel Hoare presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that the present Sheikhs of Eoweit and Bahrein may be granted personal salutes of 11 guns. Bahrein were included in the list of salutes to be fired by Your Majesty’s ships in the Persian Gulf which was approved by Your Majesty in 1931&gt; but the Government of India and the local political authorities have represented that it is desirable for political reasons that the status of the present Sheikhs should be distinguished from that of the local governors of neighbouring Iraqi and Persian ports to whom also a salute of 7 guns is accorded. His jBxcellency Sheikh Hamad of Bahrein lately succeeded to the Sheikhdom on the death of his father, the late Sheikh Isa, for whom a The present proposals have the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of Salutes of 7 guns for the Sheikhs of Howe it and personal salute of 11 guns was approved by Your Majesty in 1931.5 j 6^3-^“- (h of State for the Colonies, and the Lords Commissioners of the admiralty.30th Uirch 1933 » Eir oaniuel lioare presents his hunble duty to Tour Majesty and has the honour to sub lit that Your Majesty raay be graciously pleased to approve that the present Gheikhs of I oweit and Bahrein may be granted personal salutes of 11 guns* G a lutes of 7 guns ^ or Gheikhs of I owe it and Bahrein were included in the list of salutes to be fired by Your 'ajesiy'e ships in the ^ergian Gulf which was approved by Tour ajesty in 1931» but the Government of India and the local political authorities have represented that it is desirable for political reasons that the status of the present : heikhs should be distinguished from that of the local governors of neighbouring Iraqi and Persian ports to whom also a salute of 7 guns is accorded. His excellency * heikh Hamad of Bahrein lately succeeded to the Gheikhriom on the deata oi his father* the late dheikh Isa* for whom a personal salute of 11 guns was approved by Your Majesty in 1931 . The present proposals have the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary ofof State for the Colonies, and the Lords Conn is s loners of the Admiralty.n&lt; © SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. i-^tter c Telegram r01 ' Dated Rec. 19 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Ohairn/aTi. 3. 4 -1% Salutes in the Persian Gulf. Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Proposal to grant increased personal salutes to the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft Submission to His Majesty. . 'T Previous Papers :— 1140 1000 8.32Hi■■■■■■■■■I ILCjl* p.z.ife^/ 33 . © Minute Paper. political Depar tm en t. ,&lt;r^ 'JdiuLS&amp;iA Please see the previous submission at P.Z.535/33* The F.^., C.0. and Admiralty have all * intimated by telephone that letters concurring in the proposals are now issuing from their departments, and in view of the Pol. Residents telegram of 20th March (P.Z. 1620/33 below) suggesting that immediate action in the matter might have a favourable effect on the Sheikh in relation to Koweit Oil, it is desirable to proceed at once with submitting the salutes for H.M. T s approval. A draft submission is attached for the approvalm- Draft Paper. f ? 2 3 Department. 1401 5000 11.32 Sir Samuel Hoare presents his humble duty to Your Majesty and has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve that the present Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein may be granted personal salutes of 11 guns. Salutes of 7 guns for the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein were included in the list of salutes to be fired by Your Majesty’s ships in the Persian Gulf which was approved by Your Majesty in 1931# hut the Govt. of India and the local political authorities have represented that it is desirable for political reasons that the status of the present Sheikhs should be distinguished from that of the local governors of neighbouring ’Iraqi and Persian ports to whom also a salute of 7 guns is accorded. H.E. Sheikh Hamad of Bahrein lately succeeded to the Sheikhdom on the death of his father, the late Sheikh Isa for whom a s personal salute of 11 guns was approved by Your Majesty in 193!• The present proposals have the support of the s/ S for F.A., the s/s for the C, and the L.C. of the Admiralty. rAny further communication should be addressed to— A dmiralty, S. W. 1. The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l.^. ,23rd. larch, mZ . quoting “ Sir, With reference tcKy-Our litters of the 9th March, No, P.Z. 838/33 and the 20th March, P.Z. 1620/33, concerning an increase in the gun salutes of the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, that they concur in the proposal of the Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf to increase the salutes of the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein from 7 to 11 guns, the increased salutes to be personal to the present Sheikhs. A copy of this letter has been sent to the Poreign Office and Colonial Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of Stn-3, India Office, S. W. 1.1 ny iurthcr couununication on this su .^ct, please quote *&lt;£ 2799/174/577 and address, not to any person by name. but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, ' London, S.W. I. Sir, rr i- -*« mtfr* I Foreign Office. S.W. 1. 22nd March, 1933. With reference to your letter P.Z. 838 /33 of the 9th instant, regarding the recommendation of the Government of India that the salutes of the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein should he increased from seven to eleven guns and that the increased salutes should he personal in each case to the present Sheikhs, I am directed hy Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that he concurs in the proposal of Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to submit the recommendations for The King* s approval. 2. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office and the Admiralty. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, India OfficeCommunications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. • Downing Sire March , 1937&gt; . and the following 0.0^^ l r i r i Number quoted : / 00 * Sir I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister to acknowledge the receipt of your letters ilos.P.Z. 838/33 of the 9th March and P.Z.1620/33 of the 20th March, and to request you to inform Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare that he concurs in the proposal to submit for His Majesty's approval the proposal that the Salutes of the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein should be increased from 7 to 11 guns, these increased salutes being regarded as personal in each case to the present Sheikhs, I am Sir Your most obedient servant THE UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE Inclos V-. '* IsU i INDIA 0PFIC1\t&gt; SECRET PON/EM n hi n Y P H E R From . 1620 (2fe groups) fete 1729 Political Resident In the Persian Gulf to Foreign Secretary, Government of India, Foreign and ^uriES Political Department, and repeated CIRCULATED) by former to Secretary or ota^e P ^ Tmr! 1 c Bated Bushire, 20th March, 1933« Received 20th March, 1933, 11.45 a.mc XXX 188, Demi-off icialo Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Secretary of.State for India, 11 increase in the salute fos' the Sheilch oi Koweit f vide your letter dated 25th January to the India Office, could be granted quickly it might have favourable effect on the Sheikh in the matter of Koweit oil.■■■ t J Ho. D.53S4-H/32. 1£55 j Prom The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* I am directed to forward a copy of letter from the Hon , ‘ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Ro* 2656 of 1932* dated the 17th December 1932* and to say that In the circumstances explained the Government of India support the Political Residents proposal to increase the salutes of the Sheikhs of Kuwait and Bahrain from 7 to 11 guns. They also agree with the Political Resident that the increased salutes should in each case be personal to the present Sheittis. To The Uhder Secretary of State for India Political Department* India Office* London. Sir, I have the honour to be. Sir* Your most obedient servant Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. (with two spare copies)Copy of a letter Ho. *656 of 1932, dated Bushire, the 17th December 1932, from the Hon # ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. SAHTTES TO nK I3FS IN THE FSRSIAH GULF. I have the honour to invite a reference to Foreign and Political Department endorsement No. F*72-N/32, dated the 8th June 1931, with which was forwarded a copy of a despatch from the secretary of State for India, No. 1, dated the 28tn April 1931, giving the list of salutes to Chiefs and Foreign officials in the Persian Gulf approved by His Imperial Majesty the King Emperor. 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait, reported some time ago that His Excellency the ShaiMi of Kuwait made a special point of calling on him and representing that his (the Shahih*s) receiving a salute equal injnumber of guns (7) to that of the Persian Governors of Abadan and Mohammer&amp;h and the Mutassarif of Basrah, would be taken by ‘Iraqis in general and the people of Basrah in particular, as placing him on an equal status with the officials named. 3. The question of salutes, especially as it applies almost entirely to visits of His Majesty«s Ships, is rated very high among the Arabs, and the impression which the above equality in salutes creates in the Arab mind cannot be very favourable to His Excellency. During my recent visit to Kuwait also His Excellency raised the question personally with me. 4. i fully appreciate the Shaikh of Kuwait's feelings in this matter and conceive that while we are endeavouring to •mphaslse the importance and independence of both Bahrain and Kuwait vis a vis Persia, 'Iraq, and Nejd, it seems incongruous to allow the local world to think that we place thethe Rulers of these States on a par with the local Gover nors of the neighbouring ports of Basrah, Abadan, Mohammerah, and Bandar Abbas# I therefore strongly recommend that the salute of the present Shaikh of Kuwait be raised to 11 guns, but that it should be made personal to him# I suggest this rather than that the Kuwait State should be raised to anjf 11 - gun State on the grounds that while - as far as Shaikh Ahmad is concerned - the increased personal salute will meet his complaint on the subject, from our point of view it may well be advisable to have something to offer his successor, whoever be may r be, in the shape of an increased salute should his behavio^ merit it# Shaikh Ahmad is persona grata with us, and in my opinion fully merits the increased personal salute suggested. It does not, however, in any way follow that his successor will be equally deserving of it. 5# With regard to Shaikh Hamad of Bahrain I recommend that as Ruler, following the recent death of Shaikh Isa,he should receive a salute of 11 guns, made personal to him for the same reasons as I have adduced in the case of the Shaikh of Kuwait# 6. In this connection I would invite a reference to correspondence ending with Government of India, Foreign and political Department, letter Ho. 1216-E.A., dated the 26th July 1909, from which it will be seen that the present suggestion for raising these States in the matter of salutes, is not a new one# In fact the grounds for the present proposal are more cogent in view of the increased economical and political importance of the States#2 M.20/32. 13tli January, c '' . i Sir, With reference to your letter of the 3l8t December last, Do.T.15909/59/377 concerning the appropriate gun salute for the Governor-General of Pars, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that They have issued the necessary directions for the Governor-General of Pars to receive a salute of 15 guns, as a matter of courtesy, in the event of his paying a visit to H.M.Ships in a private capacity. A copy of this letter has been sent to the India Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Secretary of State, POKLIGN QFFICL.ft 4 % 1 P 7 L • /.« • In any further communication on this subject, pleaat quote no. O^QOQj^CfU n and address —not to any person ny name, bbt fo— * / “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W i. i q i &gt;% 0 ^ ^ (m) THE Under-Sec ret ary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ££T ■y^dActca. j and, by directio^/of ^Ke Secretary of State, transmits herewith copL&amp;&gt; of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, In- , 193J . rjrtj oy\cLu*. Reference to previous correspondence (Qfoz. te- tJ*. 2. I 3 ' i Description of Enclosure. / OJ’J Name and Date.T 159fc9/69/*77 jmc , 31 e t iiecember, 1931. Sir &gt; Witu rvf&amp;rencv to til© lfc;tt&lt; 2 r from tni® d^perta^nt T 12255/69/577 of October 9th last, regarding tne aiilutefc to be accorded to Chiefs in th-.. i ^rtian Gulf, X am directed b' secretary tir John Ciiaon to tr narait to you Herewith, for the information of the Lorde Coaitiiaeion^ra of tu* Admiralty, a copy of a letter from the India Qifiee from which it will be observed that they concur in tue view of the Governuent of India that a aalutis of fil'teen guns might appro riately be accorded to the Governor-G^nen 1 of lera a&amp; a matter of courtesy in the event of ills paying a visit to hie *• jeety e bhipa in a private capacit . 2. hir Joan Gimon r&lt;~kium*&amp; that the horde Cominiasionura will nov autnoriaa tne nece&amp;sary steps to be taken to ensure the Goveinor-Gen^ral receiving such a salute in the event of the contingency arising, providing that th^y e oc no objection to such a course, I am, * ir. Your obedient b^rvant, the secretary of the Admiralty,■ mr******fv-r ' f&amp;XBSrj, swpnB »^P r/.. 76S1 ilo.5‘.72-i!i/29. -V I r '- . 'i &gt; ^rom To The foreign Secretary to the Goremment of India, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, * Dated isiew Delhi the % November 1931, Salute for Governor General of Pars. Sir, f\^ X Qt S j In reply to Mr. Walton’s letter No.P.Z.6077/31, dated the 1st October 1931, I am directed to forward a copy of letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf No.2296 of 1931 dated the 8th November 1931, and to say that the Government of India are in agreement with the views cf the Resident. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. . U&gt;jL for Poreign Secretary to the Government of India. f \ -A * hi (With 2 s.cs.)Copy of a letter Bo.2296 of 1531 dated Bushire the 6th Bovember 1931 from the Hon , ble the Political Resident injthe Persian Gulf to the foreign Secretary to the Government of India# New Delhi. Salute for Governor General of Pars. With reference to Foreign and Political Department letter Bo.F.72-b/29 of the 14th October, 1931, I have the honour to state that the question of a salute for the Governor- General of Pars is really more or less an academic one. This Official, seldom if ever, visits Bushire and if he did it is improbable that his visit would synchronise with that of the rare visits of war-ships to that this port. However, it is possible that some formal ceremonial occasion might arise for which the Governor General of Pars might come down and at which British war-ships would be present, and I therefore agree that it is desirable to come to some decision now on the salute to be accorded to the Governor General. 2. He must obviously have a higher salute than the Governor of Bushire, or than the so called Governor-General of Khuzistan, who is only granted this appellation by courtesy, and I there fore agree that a salute of 15 guns would be suitable. 3. The Government of India have expressed the view in the past that it is undesirable nowadays to give a Provincial Governor a higher salute than is accorded to their own Resident, a viewxwfcx with which in principle I agree. But in the present instance it is unavoidable, since, the four Governor Generals of Khorasan Azerbaijan, Pars and Kerman have a higher status in the official hierarchy than other Governors, being known as SWalis 'instead of' Hukumats* and the Governor of the Gulf 1 I Ports has for long been accorded the same salute as the Resident - and actually the likelihood of the salute ever being fired is remoteFrom The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Simla, the 2 ^ September 1931. Salute for Governor General of Fars. V/ith reference to Mr. Walton 1 s letter No.P.Z.5078/31, dated the 27th August 1931, I am directed to inform you that the Government of India propose to consult uolonel Biscoe in the matter on his return to Bushire, and that their observations will be communicated to you when his viev/s have been ascertained. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Sir Your most obedient servant for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (with 2 spare copies)14—5901 ( 2 ) INDEXED In any further com niunjf ation on this subject, pleasp quote no.Ti^U* S3JW1 and address —not to any person by \/awi,|but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. /** u : 4 b 6 INDIA DIRECT rt ^ J i % f v ^ l __ V . 'lllr THE Under-Seoretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his^ r° and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ts. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. W-rvs Jwi h ijo. o| lol^- ^A&gt; f) % ' / ^ Simitar letter sent toNo.497 (T 12253/59/377) British Legation, Tehran, September 12th, 1931. His Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Salutes. Reference:- Tehran despatch No.462 dated the 25th August, 1931. From the Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.134/1862 of the 5th Sept. 1931.igHmMMnwMnHBHHBBHHBBMIiHMIl 'X&amp;o ' Copy No.134/1862 of 1931. BritiBh Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, the 5th September, 1931. Sir I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your endorsement No.158 of 25th August, 1931, with enclosures. 8. With reference to paragraph 2 of your letter No.462 of 25th August to the Foreign Office. The salute of the Governor of the Gulf Ports has - as I understand it - already been authorised at 13 guns. 3. As you point out the question of the salute for the Governor-General of Pars no longer arises, since he cannot in future visit H.M.Ships in an official capacity. I agree that should he do so in a private capacity he might receive 15 guns as a matter of courtesy. of the enclosures received under your endorsement quoted above to the Government of India. I have the honour to be, etc., (Sgd) T.C.W.Fowle, M? jor, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and H.B.M.’s Consul-General for Fare, Etc. I am sending a copy of this letter with copies H.B.M's Charge d*Affaires, British Legation, Tehran.2,oS In any further communication S', on this subject, please quote No. T 11191/59/377 and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of S^ate,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. f '7, r- ..L r if ... t/ * Karr 1 / / V r V, // /» /C 4&lt;j t j, ^ ^ 8 w , Foreign Office, S.W.l. 22nd September, 1931. Sir, With reference to your letter P.Z.5078/31 of the 26th ultimo, regarding the salutes to he accorded to Chiefs and foreign officials in the Persian Gulf, I am directed by the Marquess of Reading to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Tehran indicating that the post of Governor of the Persian Gulf Ports has again become an independent one held by an official responsible only to the Persian Government, and that the Governor-General of Pars has therefore no longer any official connexion with the Persian Gulf. 2. In the circumstances Lord Reading shares Mr. Dodd’s view that a salute of thirteen guns should be given to the Governor of the Gulf Ports and that, in the event of the Governor- General of Pars paying a visit to His Majesty’s Ships in a private capacity in future, a salute of fifteen guns might be given as a matter of courtesy, in view of his importance in the Persian official hierarchy. 3. I am to add that a copy of Mr. Dodd’s despatch No.440 of the 18th ultimo referred to by him was enclosed in the letter from this Department K.10401/874/234 of the 17th instant. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State India Office. ■ wwiuhi^i ENCLOSURE !N WEEKLY LETTER NO. 3*140 ^ OCT. 1851 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE r.npv mt xn ^V ^.OH Ho. 468. i flulhek, / i E5 th Atigue t, 1931. v With r*£®renoe to your deapatoh So* 449 ( T 9E59/59/377) of Au^uat lEth, on the eulijeot of ib.% ealutee to be accorded to chief8 and foreign officials in the Persian Sulf, I have the honour to bring to your notice that as stated in my deapatch Ho* 440 of August 18th regarding the reorganisation of consular district* in South Persia, the Governorate of the Gulf Perta has once more been placed under the direct control of the Central Government, and the Governor- General of Fare hae therefore no longer any official connexion with the Gulf. 2. In these altered circumstances I venture to submit that the Governor of the Gulf ports should receive a salute of thirteen guns, this being, I understand, the normal salute accorded to foreign officials of his standing* Phe question of the ealute to be accorded to the Cover nor-General of Fare no longer arises, since he cannot in future visit Els Majesty’s Ships in an official capacity, but should he ever do so In a private capacity I presume that he would as a matter of oourtesy receive fifteen guns in view of his importance in the Perelal official hierarchy. 3* I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Officiating Political Kesldent at Bushire, who will doubtless furnish fhe Eight Honourable Arthur Henderson, M.P., fhe Foreign Office*Register No. P.Z. 5073/31. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT ^0(a V Letter Telegram from Dated Hec. Formally acknowledged m To Chairman / Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Initials. SUBJECT. / l ^ id. S' SALUTES IK THE PERSIAN GULF Proposed increase of the salute of the Gov error-General of Pars from 13 to 15 £uns. Copy to ,43^ FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letter to Foreign Office deprecating consideration of this matter at ux± 0 pr c* s 0 ti o &gt; &lt; r time • 2 p v'5,1931 Previous Papers : 27 AUG 1951mmsmmmmmmmmmm Minute Paper, Department. ^s/t5 i* ^vUOu* The Acting Political Resident at Bushire ha suggested that the Governor-General of ^ars should now be given a salute of 15 guns in view of the change which has been made in his status. Formerly, when the Governor-General had no jurisdiction over Bushire, he would have no occasion to visit British warships officially, and it is suggested that his position would be awkward if no salute was fixed for him in his capacity as Governor-General. On the other hand, a table of salutes for Chiefs and officials in the Persian Gulf has only recently received His majesty’s approval, and it seems most unnecessary to make a further submission to the Palace so soon after a comprehensive table has been w approved. Moreover, it has been decided on papers . 2587^below io defer^ urther consideration of the r» 7 . u question of the rearrangement of Consular districts in Persia consequent on the new arrangements made by the Persian Government for the controj^by thr Governor -General of Pars ^^Bushlr&gt; y—It^seems , therefore, desirable that this question should be postponed, at any rate for the present, and a draft letter to the Foreign Office pointing out the undesirability of considering this matter at the present time is put up. ^ .. 2l.YTtY'3'It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the rejily addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, 8. VV. 1. i J- ' Z. 6078/31. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALE, LONDON, S.W. 1. 27ta August 1931* Sir, I son direotea by tins Secretary of State for India to refer to the despetoh froja His sty’s Charge d* ^iffairt at Tehran, Ho* 362, dated 10th July 1931 eopy of mi oh was sent to you direet, and the letter from the Forei^ Office of 7th August, copy of which was enclosed with lay weekly letter Ho*2 33, under Ho.1^,5073, regarding the suggestion of the Acting Folitiot^l hoaident in the Persian Gulf,that the Governor General of Fare should be given a salute of 15 guns* The Secretary of State would be glad to receive tne views of the Government of India cm Ma^or Fowle’a suggestion in due course* Copy is enclosed of an interim reply addressed to the Foreign Office on the sublet* Copy of the Foreign Office letter of 34th April 1931 which is referred to, was enclosed under $0*1*2*2587, in the weakly letter of 30 April 1931 Ho*2*18. I am,Sir, Your obedient servant. The Foreign Secretary to the Gov eminent of India*51° Draft Paper. The Undersecretary of State, ^spuic-r cFFitr, S.7/. 1. p ~2 sa)^/ Department. ze m i93i ^1 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter, No. T 9259/59/377, dated 7th August, regarding the suggestion of the Acting Political Resident, Bushire, : that, in view of the increased importance of the position of the Governor-General of Pars, he should now be given a salute of 15 guns. / r. ~ IJ// v. J T1 7hiliLJ. f r. Sfi^-rGtrrr) ; Btrnn v^uld y lQ consider this matter m d'cte o&amp;ure-e, on receiving the views 35h of the Government of India y upon 7 sjtzU) U / ( * 3^Hr^^ln!cTIhed, ^as at present advised, to deprecate'^immediate porsi rlerei ion oj^tho quoc^rioiT rrf h..' increase of the Governer-General’s HrCLoe-Hs? j^r I/O salute in view of the/dec is ion to postpone consideration of the Rtt question of the extent ^of the jurisdiction of the^Gonsulate-General announced in Foreign Office letter, K 3660/874/234, dated 24th Ajoril.qir ^J.C'.VALTrtW *1 Ilr. Benn iis , moreover, reluctant to approach His Majesty again so soon a^ter having obtained Royal approval tA the table of salutes^ copy of \vh 4 ch was sent to thV/ 3000 5.31INDEXED. In any further communication on lis subject, please quote No.T 9259/59/377. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. !Nr' Cm EOT i Foreign Office. . '• * *- S.w.l. 7th August, 1931. Sir, With reference to your letter P.Z.2330/31 of April 24th last, regarding the salutes to he accorded to Chiefs and foreign officials in the Persian G-ulf, I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Henderson to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Charge d*Affaires at Tehran forwarding a copy of a despatch which he has received from the Acting Political Resident at Bushire suggesting that, in view of the increased importance of the position of the Governor-General of Pars he should now he given a salute of fifteen guns. 2. It will he observed that Mr.Dodd concurs in Major Powle’s suggestion, and I am to inform you that Mr.Henderson also shares Mr.Dodd’s view that it is desirable to provide for the Governor-General receiving a salute of fifteen guns in future. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.British Legation, Gulhek July 10th, 1931 Sir I With reference to your despatch No.244 (T 5401/59/377) of April 30th concerning the salutes to 'be given to chiefs in the Persian Gulf, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a despatch which I have received from the Acting Political Resident at Bushire on the subject of the altered position of the Governor-General of Pars. 2. It will he recalled that in his despatch No.P.72 N/29 of July 30th 1930 the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India informed His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India that his Government thought it undesirable to give a Persian Provincial Governor a higher salute than that accorded to their own Resident, and that they there fore recommended that the Governor-General of Khuzistan, who was not really a Governor-General, but merely a Governor of a similar status in the Persian hierarchy to the Governor of Bushire, should be given a salute of thirteen guns instead of fifteen. Prom recent corres pondence, ending with Sir R. Olive’s despatch No.101 of the 9th March last, on the subject of Lieutenant-Colonel Biscoe’s Royal Commission and Exequatur, you will have seen that the exact status of the Governor-General of Pars in his dealings with Bushire has not been satisfactorily defined The Right Honourable Arthur Henderson, M.P., The Foreign Office. rdefined; such lack of definition is, however, nothing uncommon in the Persian official hierarchy, and I doubt very much whether the Ministry for Foreign Affairs would be able to furnish an intelligible ruling on the point if requested to do so. As far as my information goes, it appears that the Governor General of Pars is at the same time Governor of Bushire, and that consequently in his official relations with His Majesty’s Ships he should strictly speaking be treated as a Governor rather than as a Governor General, receiving presumably, a salute of thirteen guns only, like the so-called Governor-General of Khuzistan. Nevertheless I consider that such an interpretation of the position would be unnecessarily rigid, and that in view of the great importance of the official in question in his other capacity (namely as Governor General of Pars) he should, as Major Fowle suggests, receive a salute of fifteen guns. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and to the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have, etc., (Signed) CHARLES DODD.No.89/1376 of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-Genersl , Bushire, the 22nd July, 1931. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 43, dated the 4th April, 1930, regarding the salutes to be given to certain Persian officials in the Persian Gulf. 2. The salutes for the following Persian officials have been finally approved by His Majesty as follows: Khuzistan . Guns His Excellency the Governor of 13 Mohammerah . The Governor of (at the termination of an official visit)... ... 7 Bushire . His Excellency the Governor of (at the termination of an official visit) 13 Abadan . The Governor of .. . Bandar Abbas . The Governor of ... 3. The case of the Governor-General of Ears has, however, not been provided for. When the question of salutes was considered, Bushire was separate from Pars, and the Governor-General of the latter would have no occasion to visit British war-ships officially. Owing to the recent change however, made by the Persian Government, Bushire, ♦ which His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, British Legation, Tehran.which has under it Bandar Abbas, Jask and Lingah, has been put under Pars. It might easily happen, therefore, that the Governor-General would visit a British war-ship which called at a port under his jurisdiction. In fact, I understand that the Governor-General is supposed to visit Bushire once a month to keep him in touch with the local Governor and local affairs. It would appear therefore advisable that some salute should be fixed for him. As a Governor-General I presume this would be 15 guns? 4. It may be noted that the present holder of the post of Governor, Bushire, is in an anomalous position, and has not been given the title of ’’Governor' at all. I hear, however, that he is going to be given that of 'Acting Governor' shortly. I have, etc., (Signed) T. C. W# FOWLE. Major, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and H.B.M.*s Consul-General for Pars Etc.e/ 6nimunications on this subject should he addressed to— /^The Under Secretary of State, CoLokiAti Office, London, S.W.l. &gt;^,nd the following •;umber quoted: 481^1/1930 2r2 ff—rr W: n- Downing Street, July , i9s\\ 9 ^ Sir, L_-^—^ Kith reference to your letter I' .Z.2330/31 of the 24th April, I'am directed.by lord Passfield to transmit to you, for the observations of Mr. Wedgwood Berm, copies of correspondence with the High. CoRimissioner for Iraq regarding the revised Table of Salutes to certain Rulers and Officials in the Persian Gulf. y 2. Subject to the views of the Lords ^ Commissioners of ^the Admiralty and the*-Secretary of State for India, it is proposed- to inform the High \ Commissioner in reply to his' despatch of the 19th June, that the proposed amendment of the definition . * — * of Indian Waters will not involve'any modification in / &gt; the scale of Saluteb'which has been approved for the * V. THH UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE! * -J 1 Rulers / ^ . ' ! i i ‘B ,11)1 i • ) \. +\ ■v \.Rulers and Officials referred to, and that it is not considered necessary to take any- steps with a view to increasing the number of guns already authorised for the salute to the Kutasarrif of Basrah. 3.- A similar letter has been addressed to the Admiralty. I am, , Sir, * • YiOur most obedient servant.[ h sy Copy. ' B A Q., lIISCijlLLAKiSOUa . 3'S Downing otreet, 29th May, 1931. p VUL, ?z 2yyo[$t Sir, I have the honour to transmit to you, ,ior your information, a copy of a despatch from the Secretary of State for India to the Governor - General of India in Council,' enclosing a copy of a revised Table of Salutes to certain. Rulers and Official^ in the Persian Gulf, which has'been approved by His 4 \ Majesty the King. &gt; v 2. I have also to -inforr^ you that the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty have under consideration * / the question of amending the definition of 'Indian Waters' for the purpose* of salutes, in Article 61 of Kings Regulations and Admiralty Instructions, so as to exclude the Persian Gulf and the South and Hast Coasts / *4 of Arabia, with the exception of Aden, fronRthe definition of that term. This amendment is considered desirable in view of the possibility of friction being caused by the firing of salutes on the Indian Scale by His Majesty ! s Ships in the Persian Gulf. Should it be decided to make this amendment, it. is proposed that further modifications should be made in the King T s Begulations and Admiralty Instructions so as to v ' admit \ ' HIGH COMMISSI OMR LIEUTENANT COLONEL SIR P.H.HUMPHRIS, G.C.Y.O., K.S.^.G., K.B.H., C.I.E., . etc., etc., etc. I • • L f -'Xl* admit of the flag of the Indian Political Resident being flown by His Majesty's ships in the iersian Gulf, when the Political Resident is on board and of the continuation of the existing salutes to him and to the Indian Political Agents. I have, etc., (Signed) PASSFIi&amp;D.I Copy. 0.0.1642. g)l The Residency, Baghdad. 19th June, 1931. My Lord, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Your Lordship T s despatch Miscellaneous 1 dated the 29th May, 1931, regarding the salutes accorded to certain Rulers and Officials in the Persian Gulfv 2. I should be interested to learn in due course to what extent the salutes shown in the enclosure to Your Lordship T s despatch will be modified as a result of the proposed amendment of the definition of 'Indian Waters'. At present the salute of seven guns to the Mutasarrif of Basrah, authorised in Mr. Amery f s despatch Miscellaneous 1 dated - the 7th'February, 1929, compares unfavourably with the salute of 13 guns accorded to the Governors of Khuzistan and Bushire, who would appear to be of similar status. I have, etc., (Signed) J5.R.LODLOW HSWiSTT. . Ag.High Cojaraissioner for 'Iraq. 'IQ Please see previous submission on P.Z.892/31 below. Draft Despatch informing the Government of India of His Majesty’s approval to the Revised Table of Salutes is submitted. The Government of India’s recommendations were a &amp; submitted in Secretary’s letter, and^reply would normally be sent in the same form. Having regard, however, to the fact that the reply covers a list of salutes which has been approved by the King Emperor, it may be thought more suitable that it should take the form of a despatch, and a draft is accordingly submitted (4 ’ IC'WXI —JIndia Office, London 23rd April 1931. Political, No. 1. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to the letter from the Foreign Secretary to Your Excellency’s Government, No. F. 72/N. 29 Salutes m the Persian Gulf. r oni.-u t i -mon .i u- ^ ^ xu J ot outh July 19o0, on the subject of the P.Z. 2330131. salutes to be accorded to Chiefs and foreign officials in the Persian Gulf, I forward for your information a copy of the list of the salutes in question, in the form that has now been approved by His Imperial Majesty the King- Emperor. 2. Your Excellency will observe that in accordance with the recommendation of the Government of India, a salute of 13 guns only instead of 15 has been approved in the case of the Governor-General of Khuzistan. It was decided, after mature consideration, that having regard to the alteration which has taken place in the position of the Sheikh of Mohammerah of recent years, it would be preferable to omit from the Revised Tables the salutes hitherto shown as applicable in the case of the Sheikh and his son, and the King has been pleased to accept a recommendation to this effect. His Majesty has also approved the discontinuance of the local personal salute of five guns hitherto admissible to the Governor of Lingah. I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Wedgwood Benn. I) 12 90 4.31 [ENCLOSUREENCLOSURE. Table of Salutes to certain Rulers and Officials in the Persian Gulf. Muscat. Number of Guns. / 'V 1. His Highness the Sultan of - - - - - 21 2. Council of Ministers (as a whole) of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat --------17 3. President of the Council if a member of the Ruling Family - 13 1. President of the Council if not a member of the Ruling Family - 9 5. Individual Members of the Council - - - - 5 Bahrein. 6. His Excellency the Sheikh of (hred by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit) - - 7 7. His Excellency the Sheikh of (personal to His Excellency Sheikh Sir Isa ibn Ali al Khalifa, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, for his lifetime; fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by the Chief) - - - 11 (personal) S. Eldest son of the Sheikh of (fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father’s representative) - - 5 Koweit. 9. His Excellency the Sheikh of - - - - - 7 10. Eldest son of the Sheikh of (fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father’s representative) - -5 Qatar. ' 11. Sheikh of - - - - - - - - 7 Khuzistan. 12. His Excellency the Governor of - - - - - 13 Mohammerah. 13. The Governor of (at the termination of an official visit) - - 7 Bushire. 14. His Excellency the Governor of (at the termination of an official visit) ----__--13 Abadan. 15. The Governor of- - - - - - - 7 Bundar Abbas. 1G. The Governor of (at the termination of an official visit) Abu Dhabi. 17. The Sheikh of - IS. The Sheikh of - Debai. 19. The Sheikh of rr ( 3 5 (personal to the present Sheikh) o Shargah. 20. The Sheikh of A] man. 21. The Sheikh of U mm -EJ-Kuwain. 22. The Sheikh of 3 3 3 Ras-El-Khaimoh. 23. The Sheikh of - - - - - - - 3 Salutes 17-23 in the above list are fired by His Majesty’s ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by the Chief concerned.Draft Paper. 2330 19 3! POLITICAL /s aa ( Department. 0 mm&gt;&amp;§ POLiTieAt 2oars DRAFT!DESPATCH. My Lord, With reference to the letter frcm the Foreign Secretary to Your Excellency^ Government, NO.F.72/N.29 of 30th July 1930, on the subject of im j 4 the salutes to be accorded to Chiefs (Jy and foreign officials in the Persian Gulf, I forward for your information a copy of the listCinthe form that has now been approved by His Imperial Majesty, the King Emperor. J2 Your Excellency will observe that in accordance with the recommendation of the Government of ' India a salute of 13 guns only . 11 instead of 15 has been approved in 'the case of the Governor General of Khuzistan. It was decided, after mature consideration, that having regard to the alteration which has taken place in the position of the Sheikh of Mohammerah of recent years, tA - Ir*- Cltb omit from the Revised Tables the salutes hitherto shown as applicable in the case of the Sheildcand his son* and the King has been pleased to accept a recommendation to this effect. His Majesty has also approved the discontinuance of the local personal salute of five guns hitherto admissible to the Governor of Lingah. V (pO 4.^1CA WA. 'fctc. fc*Sl~L A-xa. fy u+»JriA. MUSCAT. 1. His Highness the Sultan of 2. Council of Ministers (as a whole) of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. 3. President of the Council if a member of the Ruling Family. 4. President of the Council if not a member of the Ruling Family 5. Individual Members of the Council. BAHREIN. 6. His Excellency the Sheikh of (Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit). 7. His Excellency the Sheikh of (personal to His Excellency Sheikh Sir Isa ibn Ali al Khalifa, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., for his lifetime^ fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by the Chief). S. Eldest son of the Sheikh of (Fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father’s representative). 7 guin f 11 guns (personal) 5 guns KQ 7/E IT. 9. His Excellency the Shei3dof 10. Eldest son of the Sheikh of (Fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father’s representative). 7 guns 5 guns ^ATAR. 11. Sheikh of 7 guns KHUZISTAIM 12. His Excellency the Governor of M0HAIyg-/[ERAH. 13. The Governor of (at the termination of an official visit). 13 guns 7 guns■■Kas&amp;z&amp;ai tammsmmH %oS J p -z. /y India Office, 14th April 1931* Whitehall. The Secretary of State for India with his humble duty to Your Majesty has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously pleased to approve the accompanying list of salutes to be fired by Your Majesty s ships in the Persian Gulf, including certain modifications as indicated in the list approved by Your Majesty in l^lo. The modifications submitted tor Your Majesty’s approval are necessitated by the alteration in the position of the various States in the Persian Gulf, anc. the cnanges in the administrative arrangements of the Persian Government on the Persian littoral of the Gult, and of tne Government of His Highness the Sultan oi Muscat, wnich nave taken place since 1913. They have oeen drawn up axter careful examination by the Government ot India and tne local political authorities, and have the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of State for the Colonies, and the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty.iUSCAT . 1. His Highness the Sultan of Salutes aanction ed by TIITMajesty toe TCina: m 19 lo . 21 guns Salutes naw proposed « 21 guns 2. Council of Ministers (as a whole) of His Highiess the Sultan of Muscat. 3. President of the Council if ^ a member of the Ruling Family. 4. President of the Council if not a member of the Ruling Family. 5. Individual Members of the Council. 17 guns 13 guns 9 guns 5 guns 3AHREM . 6. His Excellency the Sheikh of (Fired by British ships of war in tne Persian G-ulf at the termination of an official visit). 7. His Excellency the Sheikh of (oersonal to His Excellency Sheikh Sir Isa ibn Ali al Khalifa, KCIS.. CSI.,.for his o guns 7 guns ships of war in the Persian Gull at the termination of an official visit by the Chief.) 11 guns (personal) 11 guns (personal) 8. Eldest son of the Sheikh of (Fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father’s representative.) 3 guns (personal) 5 guns kqisii. 9. His Excellency the Sheikh of 5 guns 7 guns 10. Eldest son of the Sheikh of (Fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father's representative.) 5 guns (personal) 5 guns x sheikh Sir Tsa, who succeeded to the Sheikdcxn in 1869 ,relinquished control of the administration of Bahrein in 1923, his eldest surviving QVuai Uamad CSI whose right of succession had been publicly recifSediSToi, taking over tie responsibility for the aSmim strati on as t^ fully empowered Aget\t of his fattier, in that year./ QATAR . 11. Sheikh of ^.qlntes sanc tioned. by His Haiestv phe in 1715 . 12. His Excellency the Governor of 13. The Governor of (at the . termination ox an onicial visit). 5 guns (personal) BIJSHffiE. 14. His Excellency the Governor of (at the termination ox an official visit). 13 guns_ (personal) ABADM . 15. The Governor of - BytlpAR AB3AS. 16. The Governor of (at the . termination of an oincial visit). 5 guns (personal) ABU DHABI . 17. The Sheikh of ^ ^ un3 18. The Sheikh of P&amp;baI- 19. The Sheikh of bhargah . 20. The Sheikh of 3 guns 3 guns Salutes nov: proposed. 7 guns 13 guns 7 guns 13 guns 7 guns 7 guns 3 guns 5 guns (personal to the present Sheakh.) 5 guns 3 gunst Salutes sane- lioned o Maiestv the King m 1TC3. Lutes now gr Q-poseci M2M- 21. The Sheikh of 3 guns 3 guns Uill-SL-KUWAIIL 22. The Sheikh of 3 guns 3 guns TUS-SL-KHAmAE. 23. The Sheikh of 3 guns 3 guns N ote^ . (1) The salute of His Highness the Sultan of Huscat is a permanent salute; tne o^her salutes sanctioned in 1913 or now proposes are local salutes. ( 2 ) Salutes 17 - 23 in the above list are fired by British ships of War in the Persian Gruit at the termination of an official visit oy tne Chiefs concerned. (3) It is orooosed to discontinue the tollowing local'”personal salutes sanctionea in 19In:- Sheikh of Mo hammer ah 12 guns Eldest son of Sheikh of Mohammerah o guns The Grovemor of Lingah 5 guns7$% Ik' 01 1 {a^ l i^ 1 . The Secretary of State for India with his humble duty to Your Majesty has the honour to submit that lour Majesty may be graciously d 1eased to aporove the accompanying list of salutes to he fired by Your Majesty's ships in the Persian Gulf, including certain modifications cs indicated in the list approved by Your lajesty in 1915. The modifications submitted for Your Majesty*a approval are necessitated by the alteration in the oosition of the various States in the Persian Gulf, and the changes in the administrative arrangements of the Persian Government on the Persian littoral of the Gulf, and of the Government of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, which have taken place since 1915* They have been drawn up after careful examination by the Government of India and the local political authorities, and have the support of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of State for the Colonies, and the Lords Comissioners of the Admiralty*V 2^^ Draft Paper. Department. Draft submission to His Majesty the King. The Secretary of State for India with his humble duty to Your Majesty has the honour to submit that Your Majesty may be graciously ' pleased to approve the accompanying modifications in-t'he list of salutes to be fired by Your Majesty’s ships in the Persian . Gulf which wffn approved by Your Majesty in. 1913. The modifications submitted / for Your Majesty’s approval are necessitated by the alteration in the position of the various States in the Persian Gulf, and the changes in the administrative arrangements of the Persian Government on the Persian littoral of the Gulf, and of the Government of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, which have taken place since 1913. They have been drawn up after careful examination by the GovernmentsSalutes nov; proposed. ^~ir Salutes sanctioned by H^M^wthe King in 1913? Mu^at 1. H.H, the Sultan of 2 Council of Ministers (as a whole) of H.H. the Sultan of Muscat. 21 guns 21 guns (permanent)^ 17 guns. 3. President of the Council if a member of the Ruling -- I 3 guns Family. 4. President of the Council if not a member of the -- 9 guns. Ruling Family. 5. Individual Members of -- 5 guns the Council. Bahrein 6. H.E. the Shaikh of (Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit)• 5 guns 7 guns 7. H.E. the Shaikh of (Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by the Chief.) 11 guns (personal) - 11 guns (personal to H.E. Shaikh Sir Isa ibn Ali al Khalifa, KCIE.,CSI., for his lifetime X)* 8. Eldest son of the Shaikh of (Fired on occasion when he visits one of H.M. Ships as his Father’s representative.) - 3 guns (personal)• 5 guns. Kttwtfit. 9. H.E. the Shaikh of 5 guns 7 guns 10. Eldest son of the Shaikh of (Fired on occasions when he visits one of H.M.Ships as his father’s representa tive . Qatar. 11.Sheikh of 5 guns (personal). 5 guns. 7 guns. Khuzistan 12. H.E. the Governor of -- 13 guns. x. Sheikh Sir Isa, who succeeded to the Sheikhdom in 1869,^ relinguished control of the administration of Bahrein in 19^,3, his eldest surviving son, Sheikh Hamad, C.S.I., whose right 0 f succession had been publicly recognised in 1901, taking over the responsibility for the administration as the fully empowered Agent of his father, in that year.1 V IMMKflMHI / r I m ci &amp;&gt; my further communication ub'this subject, please quote No- T 1654/59/377. and address— r not to any per non by name, j but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Sir, 13th February, 1931. With reference to the letter from this department T 59/59/377 of the 15th ultimo, regarding the recommendations which have 'been made 'by the Government of India in the matter of salutes for Chiefs and other authorities in the Persian Gulf, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Henderson to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India a copy of a despatch which has been received from His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Tehran on the subject. 2. I am to add that in view of the terms of Mr. Parr’s despatch, Mr. Henderson concurs in the proposed list of salutes indicated in your letter P.5411 of December 5th last, being submitted to The King for His Majesty’s approval. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office. 1 r 9*^COPY Ho• 51. (T 1654/59/377) British Legation, Tehran, January 28th, 1931. Sir, In reply to your despatch Ho. 21 (T 59/59/377) ox January 13th regarding the salutes recommended hy the Government of 4 India for Chiefs and otner autnorities in the Persian Gulf, I have the honour to inform you that I have no observations to make concerning the proposals in question. I have &amp;c., (Signed) R.C. PARR. The Right Honourable Arthur Henderson, M.P., The Foreign Office./—\ In any further communication on this subject, please quot&lt; no. -Tscti s-qj iq'f. and address —not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S. V. I !&gt; Z. I 329 ! Under-Secretary of State 'for foreign Affairs presents his ^ ^ compliments to jjx c^C Q t . a nd, by direction of th&lt;TSecretary of State, transmits herewith copi^j of the under-mentioned paper. !93f Foreign Office, 1 d ^ * Reference to previous correspondence : 14 —22065 (2)INDEXED 2.MM- Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under ISecretary of State, Downing Street, Colonial Office, London, S.VV.l. anuary , 198 1. and the following Number quoted Sir In reply to your letter P.5411 of the 5th of Decemher regarding the proposed revision of the table of Salutes for Chiefs and other authorities in the Persian Gulf, I am directed by Lord Passfield to request you to inform Mr. Secretary Wedgwood Benn that he does not wish to offer any observations on the Government of India’s rec ommendations. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant, THE UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE, I1TDIA OFFICE. SECKET DCrr. 1 M.A OfFlCE r \ jAny further communication should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l, quoting “_M.: . 4941/30 -, P.Z. 1 L.P.—No. 8. ) h+ffa I Admiralty, S. H . /. I 31 sl. J.eaemk..er* / 930 . r/ Sir, With reference to your letter of the 5th December (P.5411), I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, that They concur in the recommendations of the G-overnment of India on salutes for Chiefs and other authorities in the Persian Gulf. 2. I am to request that six copies of the list of salutes as finally approved may be supplied to this department for distribution to naval authorities. 3. Copies of this letter have been sent to the Foreign Office and Colonial Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l. ENCLCSL.. w NO. '2 2 FROM £ OR. 1 ’ V 1 c c ^ : f O * . Y LETTER JAN. 1931 Hl, fit- r~510a It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under -mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. IT. 1. W, INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. X. 5th December 1930. Uated 30th July 1930. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward, for the consideration of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affaire, a copy of a letter from the Goremment of India proposing for permanent sanction a list of salutes for the x'^rsian Gulf. A copy of the Secretary of State*s telegram of 14th June 1929 and of the papers referred to in the second paragraph of the Gorernment of India’s letter is also enclosed. i nf« to enquire whether the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs has any obserwations to offer on the GoYsrmaent of India’s proposals. Subject to his conctirrence hr. Benn proposes to submit the list of salutes for His Majesty’s approval. A similar latter is being addressed to the Gelonial Office and the Admiralty. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, J'C*W&amp;lton» The Under Secretary of State, FOREIGN OFFICE-From To His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla, the July 1930* Sir, Salutes for Chiefs in the Persian Gulf* With reference to the telegram from the Secretary of State for India, Ho *1899, dated the 14th June 1929, I sun directed to forward a copy of a letter from the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Ho.2087, dated the 11th September 1929. A list is also attached showing salutes as sanctioned by His Majesty the Ring in 1913, those pro visionally sanctioned by the Government of India in 1922 and salutes now. proposed for permanent sanction. 2. The Government of India support the Resident* s . » recommendations except that they think it Undesirable to give a Persian provincial Governor a higher salute than that accorded to their own Resident. They, therefore recommend that the Governor General of Khuzistan, who is not really a Governor General, but merely a Governor oT a similar status in the Persian hierarchy to the Governor of Bushire, should be given a salute of thirteen guns instead of fifteen. It is understood that Lieutenant Colonel Biscoe and His Majesty* s Minister Tehran agree with this view (vide papers sent with Foreign Secretary’s weekly letter Hodated 3/' July 1930*)3 I am to request that, if His Majesty* s Secretary of State sees no objection, sanction may be accorded to the revision of the table of salutes in the Persian Gulf accordingly* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* (With 2 spare copies).75V L T o. 2087 of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General. Bushire, the llth September 1929. From The Ho n r ole Lt-Col: C.C.J. Barrett, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla• Salutes for Chiefs in the Persian Gulf* Sir, With reference to Foreign and Political Department letter Bo. F.72-H/ / 29, dated the 2nd July 19^.9, I have the honour to submit my recommendations for a revision of the ‘table of salutes in the Persian Gulf as follows PFRMAKSM 1 SALUTES. 21 Guns. i — — Bus cat - The Sultan of ICCAL SALUTES . 17 Guns . Council of Ministers(as a whole) of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. ^ 15 Guns . Mohammerah - His Excellency the Governor Geneial of Khuzistan. 13 Guns. Bushire - His Excellency the Governor of The President of the Council of Ministers of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, when a member of the ruling family. 9 Guns . The President of the Council of Ministers of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, when not a member of the Ruling family. 7 Gunz^ n 7 Guns. Bahrein Kuwait qatr Bandar Abbas- Mohammerah - Abadan The Sheikh of The Sheikh of The Sheikh of The Governor of The Governor of The Governor of 5 Gu ns . Bahrein - Eldest son of the Sheikh of - or other member of the ruling family. Fired when acting a s a d ePiity. 9^ the Chie f o f Ba hreiri Kuwait - Eldest son of the Sheikh of - or ^ other member of the ruling family ■Fired when acting as a deputy of the Chief of Kuwait. Muscat - Individual members of the Council of Ministers of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. Abu Dhabi - The Sheikh of • (This is personal to the present Sheikh Shakbut; his successor will receive 3 guns) Dibai The Sheikh of 3 Guns. Ajman Has-al-Khaima- Shargah Umm-ul-QawaL n- The Sheikh of The Sheikh of The'Sheikh of The Sheikh of 2. Mo provision has, hitherto, been made for Kis Excellency the Governor General of Khuzistan whose Head quarters are at Ahwaz in close proximity to Mohammerah and who might have occasion to pay an official visit to a British warship. With the concurrence of His Britannic Majesty’s Minister at Tehran I have recommended a salute of 15 guns for him which would thus place him in the same category as a Lieut-Governor of Kis Majesty’s Colonies. 3. His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran suggested that the Governors at Abadan and Hohammerah should either receive a salute of 7 guns each which is the number sS to which a Consul is entitled or none at all. The Senior Baval Officer recommends a salute of 7 guns and states this would place them on a level with the Mutesarrif of Basra who receives the same number of guns. I have accordingly recommended this number for these officials andand also for the Governor of Bandar A’ohas who is of higher stetus than them* 4. As a Consular Agent is no longer maintained at Lingah, which is a dying port I recommend that the GoYernor of Lingah should he left out of the list* I have forwarded a copy of this letter to His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran* I have, etc*, Sd. C*C*J*Barrett. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.rs T^v^jiU xs^^- ^ -V ^^~&lt;i^XkC.a Table of local salutes, (Persian Gulf)* 't P-fit-4-/', 0 y\r-^(r&lt; '^- &amp; Salutes sanc tioned by His Majesty the King in 1913* Salutes pro visionally sanctioned in 1922* Salutes now proposed* MUSCAT. 1. His Highness the Sultan of - 21 guns. - 21 guns. ^ (Permanent). On arrival at or departure from, a military station, or when attending a State ceremony. 2. Council of Ministers as a whole. - 17 guns. 17 guns. 3. President of the Council if a member of the ruling family. - 13 guns. 13 guns. 4* President of the Council if not a member of the ruling family. - 9 guns* 9 guns. 5. Individual members of the Council. 5 guns. 5 guns. BAHRAIN * 6. The Shailh of - 5 guns. 7 guns* 7 guns* Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit* 7. Eldest son of the ShaiWi 3 guns. 5 guns* 5 guns, of - (Personal) ( Fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father's representative* 8* The Shailh of - 11 guns. (Personal) Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by this Chief. 11 guns* (Personal to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Isa ibn Ali al Kbalifs for his life time and will be continued till his death). Q.atarSalutes sane- Salutes pro- Ho* tioned by His visionally Salutes now Majesty the sanctioned proposed. King in 1913. in 1922. Q.ATAR . 9 . -3^1 ShaiMi of - - 7 guns. 7 guns. (Sanctioned provisional ly in 1920). KUWAIT . 10. The Shailii of - 5 guns. 7 guns. 7 guns. Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by this Chief. 11. Eldest son of the Shai&amp;i of - 5 guns. 5 guns. 5 guns. (Personal) Fired on occasions vfoen he visits one of His Majesty^ ships as his fathers representative. 12. The Shailfo of - Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by this Chief. 12 guns. (Personal to Shaihh Mubarak who died in 1915.) ABADAff . &gt; 13. The Governor of - 14. The Shaikh, of - Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by the Chief. 12 guns. 13 guns. (Personal to Shaikh Sir Khazal who is detained by the Persian Government at Tehran)» 7 guns. 15. Eldest son of the Shaikh of - 5 guns. (Personal)• Fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s ships as his father* s representative. Khuzistanis l* Ho* Salutes sanc tioned by His Majesty the King in 1913* Salutes pro visionally sane tioned in 1922* Salutes now proposed* ^ KHUZISTAH. 16* His Excellency the Governor of - - 13 guns* HOHAHKE RAH. 17* The Governor of - At the termination of an official visit* 5 guns* (Personal)* BUSHIKE * 18* His Excellency the Governor of - 13 guns* (Personal)• At the termination of an official visit. LIHGAH * 19* The Governor of - At the termination of an official vist. BALKAR ABBAS * 20* The Governor of - At the termination of an official visit* ABU EKABI . 21* The Shaiih of - 5 guns* DEBAI» 22* The Shailch of 5 guns* (Personal)• 5 guns* (Personal) * 4 SHARGA H* 23* The Shaiiii of 3 guns* 7 guns. N 13 guns* To he left out of the list* 7 guns* 5 guns* Personal to present Shaikh* His successor will receive 3 guns* V 5 guns* (Provisionally sanctioned in 1928 with the concurrence of Secretary of State for India) 3 guns* AJKAH*UMN[-EL-KOTAI N» 25. The ShaiMi of - RAS-BL-ra ABEAH. 26. The Shailh of - 21-26. Fired hy British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit hy these Chiefs. 3 guns, 3 guns. 3 guns, 3 guns, ID.0.So.i'.72-2l/29. ■MBmA TO Foreign arid Sl4ti4a2 Department, New Delhlj thfe^ Fe bruary 1930. L r-r 0 £) Dear Colonel Biscoe, v — Please refer to Colonel Barretos letter Bo. 2087, dated the 11th September 1929* It will he seen that he recommended, with the concurrence of His Majesty's Minister, Tehran, a salute of 15 guns for the Governor-General of Khuaistan. It seems unnecessary and undesirable especially now-a-days to give a Persian Provincial Governor a higher salute than we accord to our own Resident. I am desired, therefore, to request you to re-examine the proposal in this light and let the Government of India have your views* It is also noticed that in the list of salutes recommend ed, no mention has been made of the Local (personal) salute of 11 guns for His Excellency ShaiFh Sir Isa bin Ali-al-Khalifa of Bahrain or of that of 12 guns for the Shaikh of Kuwait. The local personal salute for Shaikh Isa has probably been omitted because the Shaikh having been deposed can no longer be officially visited* Shaikh Mubarak of Kuwait's local personal salute of 12 guns presumably goes out because of his death* We should like to know however that our presumption regarding Shaikh Isa's salute is correct* Yours sincerely, i Sd. F.V. Wylie* r The Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel H.Y. Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* ENCLOSURE IN INDIA i: 0REiGN SECRETARY’S No 9 1J M. Recc.fcu 1 d AUG. 1930The Residency, 2 S r \ Rushii'e, 30 th June 1930# Dear Wylie, Will you please refer to your D.0,Ro.P.72/N/29 of 10th February 1930, regarding salutes in the Persian Gulf. I agree with the view therein expressed that it is unnecessary nowadays to give the Persian Provincial Governor a higher salute than is accorded to the Resident* Further the Governor-General of ihuzistan is not really a Governor-General at all, but merely a Governor of a similar status in the Persian hierarchy to the Governor of Bushire. I have pointed this out to the minister and he agrees with the view that the Governor of Rhuzistan should be given a salute of thirteen guns instead of fifteen* The local personal salute for SneiFh Isa was omitted by Barrett because he now never visits ships thou$i he does visit the Resident who returns his call, but he only iPh Hamad has visited him and the visits may be regarded visits him after/as unofficial* Shaikh Mubarak of Kuwait’s personal salute has been abolished because of his death. I think it is a pity that the BhaiPh of Abu Dhabi receives five guns. This principality has a particularly bad record for fratricide and advantage might have been taken of it on previous successions to reduce the salute to three guns like the other i Trucial Shaildis with the exception of Dibai. However, it has now been decided (vide Foreign and Political Department letter No.F.72-N-29, dated 12th February 1929, to the India Office) that the salute will be reduced to three guns on the next succession. I do not think it politic at the present time to reduce the salute of the present ruler. Yours sincerely, Sd. K.V. Biscoe. F.V. Wylie, Esquire, C.I.E., Deputy Secretary (Foreign) to the Government of India, Simla.PUT AWAY WITH 27 v Telegram R.No.21Q3-S., dated 29th June 1929 From To Political, Bushire Foreign, Simla 485^ ■ \Vc' 0 ‘fc- Your telegram 434 of 28th Kay, Salute of 5 guns for Dubai sanctioned provisionally. Copy of a letter No.F.72-N/29, dated Simla, the 2nd July 1929, from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with the letter from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department No.2993/718-G., dated the 3rd October 1922, and to request that you should now examine afresh the situation as regards salutes in the Gulf generally and furnish the Government of India at an early date with your 4 * recommendations for a permanent revision of the old table for submission to His Majesty’s Government. Salutes for Chiefs in the Persian Gulf I am directed to refer to the correspondence ending 1 -■' 1 ni 1 1 ENCLOSURE IN INBiA FOREieN SECRETARY'S | Letter No. 5 / Ml^p~ 4174 PUT AWAY WITH / 6 Telegram H.Ho .484, dated iand reed.) 28th Liay 1929. From - Resident, Bushire. To - Foreign, Simla. Your 1620-S. I recommend Sheikh of Dubai*s salute should be raised to five guns, as early as possible, as his position is sufficiently secure. Senior Naval Officer would like to fire increased salute when we visit coast together about one month hence. v i W t ** \ I enclosure in INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S | Lelter No. f 4 4 W- | Dat,d ;3( MAY. 1329 Received 17JU|j.i 32 g j %Minute Paper. Department. The CxovernnBnt of India proposed on 12th February (P .1917/29) to alter the salutes of the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dabai. The concurrence of the Admiralty, Foreign Office and Colonial Office was secured but meanwhile trouble at Dabai made it |seen possible that the Sheikh, whose salute it was proposed to raise from 3 urns to 5 mipht be replaced by his cousin. Hence a telegram was sent to the G-overnment of India inquiring whether the position of Sheikh Said was sufficiently secure to justify submission of the question of his salute to the King (P.3079/29). The Government of India, in answer to our inquiry, consider that the nosition of Sheik 1 Said of Dabai is now sufficiently secure and we proceed t submit the question of raising his salute to the ling. A- dr a 1 1—su 1 ^ r: i s s i-on to— IT is'':h/5sb 1 '—bs rPpenc.'Gcl,—r ? web-1 no a note e-xo la inring the roaoon-s -h&gt;r-the proceed ^Ihoratiens. T 1 ^ere is some obscurity about the origin of of the Persian Gulf . these salutes riven to t^e Sheikhs/ In 1901 (9th hay) the Government of India reported that they 'appear to have 1 een fiked without reference to Her L ate liajesty T s Government and the autbrity for them is the Standing-Order of the Haval Cbm i rider- m-Chief of 2nd April 1879, which, so f r as can be traced from information before us, was issued without the authority of Her Late -4&gt;w'estv T s Government or of the*'Government of India*'. The Government of India therefore requested that formal sanction mi this was accorded, -H he given to these salutes, and apparently without reference to 'ing Edward, on 12th Ju&gt; 1901. The Crucial Chiefs 2871 5000 (i.28 hence\\ l •r hence appeared in the Table of Local Salutes in the India Office List for the first time in 1903 - the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi with five fp.ns and one ouvers, iucluc.iii^ the Sheikh of Dabai, with three. In their letter of 9th May 1901 the Government of India said that correspondence in 1881 showed that His Majesty’s Government were aware of the existence of these salutes. A reference to tnat correspondence yives no evidence that t'hs Office knew of them, but suggests that the Admiralty was acquainted with the practice which had grown up. In 1913 a complete list of the salutes given within the jurisdiction of the Government of India was submitted to TT is Mayesty for approval as it was found that many of these salutes rested upon an irregular basis. The approval of the Kin-was communicated to the Government of India in the Secretary of State’s Despatch of 20th June 1913. A precedent for the reduction of the salute of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi for no special reason, apart from that given by t^e general decline in influence of his state, mav be found in the alteration made in the salute of the Sheikh of Koweit in Hefore that date the Sheika had a local salute of 5 guns and a personal local salute of 12 runs. The latter was abolished on the accession of a new S 1 eikh and the local salute was raised provisionally to seven. These alterations do not appear to have been approved by the Secretary of State or submitted to the King. The tocal . . former^salute of the Sheikh of Koweit had an origin similar to that of the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dabai. A. Y\u.rvOo^ ^ ^ ^ , '•oJr’^oujc jvi)■NMMPMflHl vs/m. i 3764 10 29 j (23 groups) Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) _COPY of telegram' Yicsroy, Foreign &amp; Political Department, to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla, 30th May. 1929. Received 1 p e m., 30th May, 1929, 1810-S* Your telegram of May 4th, 1467. 3156. Dubai salute. Political Resident considers that Sheikh Said’s (sio^Sheikh’s) position now sufficiently secure and submission to the King need not be postponed. Senior Naval Officer wopld like to fire the increased salute when he visits with the Resident in about a month’s time.POT AWAY WITH &amp; Register No. p. z i 3 0 ^ Political Department. V Letter „ rr , from lelegram Dated Bee. Formally acknowledged 192 Cj. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairii^K Under Secretary | i - /■ Secretary of Stat^.. Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... Council Tyble 7 Proposed increase in the salute of the Sheikh of Dubai, (Zu. Copy to i. FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY Draft telegram to G.of I. enquiring whether^ in view of recent movement^ against the Sheikh by some of his subjects, they consider submission to the King should be postponed for a time. a'*CHytW (17 groups) 2431 SJLILX OF TEL KG RAM Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Government of India, (COPIES Foreign and Political Department, Dated Bushire 0 17th April, IS29. Received 1.20 p.nu, 17th April, 1929. 272. Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Secretary of State for India. My telegram of today, 270. Senior Naval Officer s telegram 2024 quoted is not of importance. and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India. XXXFCN/HL 2430 . ( 8 ? groups) OOPY GF TELEGfiAM From Poltt-lccl Eesident in the Par sine. - Gulf to Secret*r^ of State tor (COFj ; India (?repeating telegram to a CIPCULATEB) destination not indicated). Dated Bushire, 17th April 0 1929. Received 1.10 p.m., 17th April. 1929. XXX S?l. Yovtr telegram 1005. Although policy of Govenauent io one of non-interference in internal affairs of Trucial Chiefs a they would not be prepared to recognise new Sheikh coming foiiverd in circumstances so unsatisfactory as those detailed in your telegram. You may, therefore,, Inform tfajlis that change (?of„ emitted) this nature cannot be recognisedi, unless and until effected by the will of the people, and that very serious view will be taken of any disturbance affecting British subjects. if shaikh really has majority behind him, he should be able to reassert his position. if he has not* it is against policy to attempt bolster Mra up*(176 £X&lt; COPY OF T. F L F G P prom ' Poltt.ical Feel dent iii tbe Peroian Gulf, to Secretary of State for India, and repeat*!* telegram Senior Naval officer in the Persian Gulf,-. Dated Bush ire, 17tb April,, ]S2»» Received 3 p,». s 17tb Aprils ie?9* XXX ! oj Reference ton, 3t24, Avfil 13th. a i Dabaij, consisting of a&gt;erch«B &lt; s and cousins of Sheikh,, recently held private conference and (?pr®clai&amp;usd} &amp; cousin of sheikh Be led ae Sheikii. this isan w&gt;'ot« to the Residency Agent that he was Sheikh, and that Sheikh saied l ac recigned,, Have aecertained Sheikh salad ie still (?aduiniste! ing)(, and asks ter support cf Brit-isb Gaveratent it&gt; order to avoid trouble c St is tel iered that reaeone for attempt to eject him are his enforcement of payment of debts an d general subndBaian - to wishes of British Government. it is b»*li' ved. ti e* She »h f - as ed) has suprojt o. n ajcrity of population Bedouins,, in view ol number of persons an&gt;i property in Dabai entitled to Brltlcl support, consistent with policy, be afforded (?him, and) that commanding Office* b&lt; authoriaed to inform IloJUb through Residency Agent that ejectment of ruling Sheikh r» would incur strong disapproval of His Majesty's Govenw-en\ with consequent eerioua effects on trade of pabai. Peregoicg is from Perior Naval officer, 1005 ,, 16th April. I have replied as in my telegram inaediately following. Addressed to Foreigr and repeated t-e* Secretary c State fca India,Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following , Number quoted : 47146/29 . Sir 'X*'* * ^ April , 192 9. 7 r ith reference to your letter P.1917 ol the 5th of April, on the subject of salutes to be accorded to the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dabai, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Amery to request you to inform Viscount Peel that he has no observations to offer on the arrangements suggested by the Government of India. 2. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office and Admiralty. x I am. to A lima 2 MAY 1929 THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE. Sir, Your most obedient servant ~h c .-Uur With reference to your letter of the 5th April, (P.1917) on the subject of the salutes accorded to the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dabai, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, that i'hey will be prepared to accept his decision in this matter. A copy of this letter has been sent to the Foreign Office and Colonial Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant The Under Secretary of State India Office, S.W.l.‘t’ In any further communication on this subject, please quote ^ No. and address, T 3941/331/377 not to any person by name. but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. rs 1• 13th April, 1S29. s lr . ^ lr1 A 77 ith reference to your letter P 1917 of the 5th instant, regarding the question of the salutes to be accorded to the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dabai, I am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to inform you that he sees no objection to the arrangements suggested by the Government of India, 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Colonial office and Admiralty. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,I I iJ. V 32122 b 5000 11.28 Tup Draft Paper. POLITlbAL Department. Sir, (1) The Under Secretary of State, FOREIGN OFFICE,, S.7/. 1. I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to Affairs . Colynies . copy of a letter from the Admiralty, Government of India dated 12th February, with enclosure, on the question of the salutes of the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dabai. Viscount Peel, as at present advised, is in agreement with the views of the Government of India; but I am to say that, to enable him to reach a decision, he would be glad to be favoured with any observations which Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain A ngry m Commissioners of the Admiralty 1 care to offer on them. A similar letter has been addressed to the Colonial Office (2) The Under Secretary of State, nder Secretary o COLONIAL OFFICE, S.W. 1. forward, for the information of (3) The Secretary, ADMIRALTY, S.W. 1. nr. Secretary tne Lords the Fore i^ti Office the foreign ftYTice and the Admiralty . and the Admiralw . and the Soionial Office.f Confidential Prom | Q O O The Foreign Secretary to the ^oyernnient of India j To The Under Secretary of State for India India Office, London Dated hew Delhi, the February 19^9 Salutes for theShaikhs of Abu Dhabi and Dubai Sir I am directed to forward a copy of a letter from the lion’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, ho.2483, dated the 22nd December 1928, together with a copy of the correspondence referred to therein, and to say that the Government of India support the Political Resident’s proposals and propose, v/ith the concurrence of the Secretary of State for India, to authorise the Political Resident firstly to inform the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi that, while his own salute will remain at 5 guns, his successor will receive a salute of only three guns like other Trucial Chiefs, and secondly to raise from three to five guns trie salute of the Shaikh of Dubai. Apart from the reasons given by the Resident it would seem politic to accord to the latter some consolation for the strain on his loyalty when feeling was running high on the Trucial Coast lately over events in Henjam I have the honour to be, Sir Your most obedient servant Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (With 2 Sjjare copies).3 f Copy of a letter l'jo.^483 of 1928, dated Bushire, the 22nd December 1928, from the Hon’ble the Political Resident &gt; in the Persian Gulf, to the loreig h Sec retary to tne Government . . “ T/—^ oi Inaia, Revv Delhi, 19)7 Salutes to the Shaildhs of Abu Dhatii and Dubai. V' ^ ^ I have the honour to invite a reference to corre spondence ending with Government of India in the Foreign v , . De Partment letter Do.2521-E.A., dated the 26th Hovember 1910 and to state that the reconsideration of the question of continuing to the .idler oi Abu Dhabi the salute of 5 guns was apparently over looked at the time the present ruler succeeded his father. 2. His Majesty’s Ships following the old custom have been giving a salute of 5 guns to the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi, and it would appear to be difficult to uiahe any change now, 1 would therefore recommend that tne salute for this Chief oe retained at 5 and that he be informed that alter him his successor will receive only 3 like other Trucial Chiefs. 3. Today, by far the most important Chief is the Shaikh of Dubai and Sir Lionel Haworth, I understand, when he last saw tne Shaikh promised to recommend to the Government of India that his salute be raised to 5, and this appears to be thoroughly justified in view of his importance. I, therefore^ recommend that the salute oi the Shaikh of Dubai be raised to 5 guns. 4. In tne event of the recommendations above being sanctioned I request that the necessary corrections should be inserted in the Foreign and Political Department Quarterly list as on 1st January 1929.Cora iaential Ho .2936, dated xJusnire, the 30tn October ^received oth 1 have the honour to refer to the corx’espondence ending with Foreign Department letter lio . 1533-2 • A* , dated 28th September 1909, on the subject of the salute of the new Shaikh of Abu Thabi• /ears been ver/ intractaole in business matters general!/; parti/ 1 think, because his faculties were gradual!/ iaiiing and parti/ because he nursed one or two supposed grievances against us, for instance, in connection with tne Taona murder case and the colonisation ol Zora. ihis circumstance and the tact that the port of Abu Thabi tucked awa/ as it is in the most inaccessible part of the Gulf littoral and cut off from all civilising influences, has remained more backward than the other more favoured Trucial Coast Ports, inclined me to tne view, indicated in my letter of 4th Jul/ 1909, that it was hard!/ necessar/ to continue to the present Shaikh the five gun salute granted to his father. 3. Since then two or three visits have been paid to Abu Thabi d/ my Assistants or m/self, but the present Shaikh has unfortunatel/ almost entirel/ lost tne use oi both his legs, and the great discomfort to him which a journe/ out to one of His majest/’s ships entails, has aiioraea the best ol grounds for his not being required to come on board. Conse quently, as far as he is concerned, the position is as it Hovember) 1910 Prom - Lieutenant-Colonel P.Z. Cox, C.S.I.,C.I*E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Secretar/ to the Government of India in the Foreign Department The late Shaikh, Zaeed bin Hhaliiah, had in recent was on his lather’s death. 4. In the meanwhile, however, in business intercourse with^33 the Residency, Shaihh Tahnoon has shuv/n himself much more amenable than his father; he treats our Indian tiauers oetter and has given me nis coojjeration in one or two matters in respect of which his father withheld it. Under these circumstances, I do not think it would be worth the risk ot alienating his goodwill by reducing his salute. His “life’' must be a bad one, and it may be tnat occasion will never arise for him to receive nis live guns; but whether that be the case or not, I would ask permission on the grounds above explained to withdraw my suggestion of July 1909 and leave tne salute question where out anything specific as to the grounds on which Abu Thabi’s salute was originally raised. I can only suppose that it was desired to create a doyen among the Shaikhs of the Trucial Coast, and that the Abu Thabi principality possessing the greatest extent of territory, its ruler was selected for the distinction. it is I have been uable to trace on the record or find* V l'*o .2521-E.A,, aated Fort William, the 26th November 1910 (Confidential). From - The Deputy' Secretary to the Government of Inaia in the Foreign Department, To - Lieutenant-Colonel P.Z. Cox, C.S.I.,C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Busnire• I am directed to acknowledge the leceipt of your letter No.2936 (Confidential), dated the 30th October 1910, on the subject of trie salute of the new Shaikh oi Abu Thabi. 2. I am to state that your proposal to make no change in the salute is approved. $ W VRG 553 [1-274] 9568/P777 20m 6 / 10 , 42 G&amp;S 110 v M.404/29. It is requested that in further communication on subject, th* above letters numbers may be quoted, and the Letter addressed as follows: — “ The Secretary of the Admiralty, “ Whitehall, '\ “ London, S.W. 1.” 4th February^ 29 ^ Form T am commanded by j\fy fjords Commissioners of the Admiralty to / transmit herewith, for your inform ation, a mi* \j f r idrt / drstribrrtiwr;* COT&gt;y of a letter of even date and xmiriber which has been addressed to the Under secretary of State, C 0 I£NIAL OFFICE. / am, Sir, Your obedient Serrant, The Under-Secretary of State.i pr-* 1044 M.404/29. ,029 i 4th February, 9 Sir With reference to your letter of the 24th January (47455/28), I am coraraaaded by % Lords Coiardssioners of the A^ndralty to acquaint you, for the information of Mr. Secretary iOnexy, that They are prepared to authorise a salute of seren (7) guns to the Mutasarrif of Basrah on occasions of visits to I.K.Ships. 2* The Cosoander-ia-Chief, j$ast Indies, and the Senior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf, have been instructed accordingly. 3. Copies of this letter have been sent to the Foreign Office and India Office. I am. Sir lour obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State COLONIAL OFFICE.12 ^ Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted:— rr l ! ft Reference to 'previous correspondence: Letter J° __ the Colonial Office of the 2/st ■ Mj r -i n Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the : Oopj to Indur ^ / 8 1 v4/V 4 - Colonial Office, Downing Street, 192 '/ 1I m directed by r. Secretary ornery to trsn^sit to you, to bo iaiu before Uae ^oros Coatsiecionere of Ute dmiraity, cjo.iee of the corras cmdenee noted in the margin relative to a surest ion by the Iraq ^oremaent that trie Mutasarrif of Basrah should be accorded a salute when fiBiting one of Hie Majesty’s ships* 2* the Secretary of state i# disposed to with the wiew that a salute of seven guns would be appropriate on the occasions in question but would not be able to agree to a salute of more f&gt;uns being accorded to the ] utasarrif than to the pheikn of k owe it. i &lt;m accordingly to enquire whether iheir ^ordsaips concur. if so I a© to request that tm necessary instructions in the momtm, mwAln.PUT AWAY WITH I Register No. it 3 ! f: y^yfvj . Political Department. Dated '• Letter- from f 0 . Q . 192 ^ . Pee. 1 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To ■ y Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of Stydte... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... • i Box / Council Ta J e PBRSIilN GULF : f —r, Question of salute, to be prescribed for the Mutasaivif of Basra. //. ^ ik Copy to CUC LajCCm. , 4 r y ^ {.* ** * / 6 ^ 2 4 JAN 1323 FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letter to Colonial Office supporting Sir H. Dobbs’s view that 7 guns would be adequate. / yj\ r Previous Papers 464o 1000 6.252871 5000 0.28 knowledge/ 2 S Minute Paper political Department. r - / s Please see Colonial Office letters of 8 th and 15th January below. urgency. It is of little interest to the Government of India, save as a possible cause of jealousy in the Gulf, and I submit that in the circumstances we may take action without reference to them. 2. The principal Gulf salutes are at present as follows:- (a) 15 ^uns . 1. President of Muscat Council, when of the ruling family. 2. Persian Governor of Bushire and the Gulf Ports. (b) 11 g;un s. Sheikh of Mohammerah. (c) 9 ^uns . President of Muscat Council when not of ruling family. (d) 7 £uns . (e) 5 guns . Persian Governor of Bunder Abbas, Lingah, Muharunerah. Eldest sons of Bahrein and Koweit when deputising for the Sheikh. Individual members of the Muscat Council. 3. The Persian Governor of Bushire is a high functionary, and his 13 guns are hardly an argument loA+r &amp;rx*. IL LdU L*. fix Ixur* j* for the grant of 11 to the HutasamTZ For that official the 7 recommended by Sir H. Dobbs (with full This question is apparently now of some Sheikh of Bahrein f /IwWV // f J Koweit, El Katr.knowledge of the Gulf salute table, and of the relative importance of the Mutasanif) seem adequate. They will sufficiently mark his superiority to the Persian Governors at Lingah, Muhanmerah and Bunder Abbas, and will place him on the same level as Koweit, Bahrein, and El Katr. I submit therefore that we may support Sir H. Dobbs’s proposal (which the Foreign Office I understand also consider sufficient) to the Colonial Office.Draft Paper. political Department. - The Under Secretary of State, COLONIAL OFFICE, S.W. 1. 21 JAN 1929 r k, Co In 2 4 JAN ^ 29 sir, * 5 ^ JJQ2ff In reply to Mr. Fiddian's letter No. 47455/28, dated 15th January, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that, while he has no strong feeling on the matter, he is inclined to think that, in view of general practice in the Gulf, the MutasaxJ[if of Basra should be accorded a salute when visiting one of H.M. Ships, and that, in view of the considered opinion expressed by Sir H. Dobbs, and of the fact that the Sheikhs of Koweit, Bahrein and El Katr are entitled to 7 guns only, a salute of 7 guns would be adequate. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. &lt;Sd.) J. C. WALT0&amp; . AI t c . Communications on this subject shoultr be addressed to— 363 Downing street, January, 19 C S Th£ Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following URGMT. quoted : 4 74 55^/28 . r f Sir, Department of the 8th of January, respecting the question of according a salute to the Mutasarrif of Basrah when visiting His Majesty’s Ships, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Amery to request you to inform Viscount Peel that a telegram has 'been received from the High Commissioner for Iraq stating that the Senior Naval Officer is pressing for a decision and has unofficially suggested eleven guns as being an appropriate salute for the Mutasarrif. instructions in the matter at an early date, the Secretary of State would be glad to receive a reply to the letter of the 8th of January as soon as possible. In view of the desirability of the issue of A THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE 2 4 JAN 1929Y' h- 2 A similar letter is being addressed to the Foreign Office. I am, Si r Your most obedient servant, f . ddL'.‘JF 4&amp; Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. ^nd the following /tap, /oo ^Synber quoted : 47 45 5/2O ^ rv r* Downing Street, . January . 1929 * Sir, ^0 OKU® I am directed by Mr. Secretary Amery to transmit to you, to be laid before Viscount Peel, a copy of a despatch from the Hi^i Commissioner for Iraq relative to a suggestion made by the Iraq Government that the Mutasarrif of Basrah, who is the Governor of one of the fourteen Liwas or provinces into which Iraq is divided, should be accorded a salute when visiting one of His Majesty’s Ships. 2. Before approaching the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty in the matter Mr. Amery would be glad to be favoured with any observations which Viscount Peel may have to make upon the suggestion and as to the number of guns which should be fired if a salute be accorded. 3. ■3. A similar letter has been addressed to the Foreign Office. I am. Sir, Your most obedient servant,No. C.0.1310 The Residency, Baghdad, the36’:h November,1928. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that the Iraq Government have recently been considering matters of procedure and ceremonial connected with the visits of foreign naval vessel s to the Port of Basrah, Doing desirous that the Lutasarrif of Basrah should participate therein in a manner appropriate to the chief local representative of the Iraq Government. 2. Arrangements have, for example, been made that, when a British naval vessel visits the Port, official calls shall be exchanged between the Officer Commanding the ship and the Lutasarrif, and the Iraq Government have suggested that when the liutasarrix visits the ship on such occasions he should be received with a salute. I consider that the suggestion is reasonable and that it should be adopted. As to the number of guns that should be fired, I observe that the Governors of Bunder Abbas, Lingah and Nluhammarah are accorded salutes of five guns. The tiutasarrif of Basrah, being the Governor of a Liwa or province, would seem to be of somewhat superior status and I suggest that a salut of seven guns woulu be appropriate. 3 . If you agree, you will no doubt consult the Departments concerned with a view necessary instructions being issued. I have, etc. (Signed) H.Bobbs'.' HIGH CGLuTSSIuNER FOR IRAQ. The Risht Hon’ble L. C.M. S. Amery, P.C. , M.P., Secretarv of Stats for the Colonies, Downing Street, London, S.W.lIWfHUl HHHPPiiMi INDIA OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000146_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3760</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000146</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3760</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/46 'Persian Gulf, Salutes in'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-19T23:36:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (302 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 304; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to matters of protocol in the Persian Gulf including gun salutes, flags and uniforms. The majority of the correspondence in the file is between British officials at the Admiralty, the Ministry of Transport, the Foreign Office and the Political Residency. It also includes copies of correspondence from the rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait thanking the Political Resident after their gun salutes were raised from 7 to 11 in 1933 (folios 169-170).In addition to correspondence, the file contains the following documents:'Future Status of British Officers in the Gulf', 1947 (folios 35-36)'Dress Regulations for Officers of the Indian Political Service. 1937' (folios 37-42).The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Uniforms</topic></subject><subject><topic>Flags</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000146#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>