<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T05:49:28.418Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">C’s P. P.—L (111)606 —10,0009-23. I. E. Form, Jnfro-Ghtrapcan CEclegrapfi f'rpacfmnt!. To The political Aper No. Bahrein 3ir, I ha^e the honor to forward a letter o^ date ^rom one \Mul Sattar who wishes to shi^t one o^ the posts carrying your telephone line a few ^eet outside his plot. I could undertake the work with your permission ani provided he is willinp to pay the cost labour and one chandal which will he required to take the strain the increased span and so prevent the line wires i'rom contact with huts etc. I have the honor to he Your m ''rant Sir. % n ler v in Charge Bahrein.i &lt;• A No/ 1 / of 1926. Political Agency, Bahrein. Bated the 4th May 1926. To The Clerk in Charge, Radio Office, Bahrein. Memorandum. 'itli reference* to your letter dated the 4th instant on the subject of shifting one of the posts carrying the * \ telephone line. Please arrange accordingly. Major,C.I.E., political Agent, Bahrein. &amp;/e iM. j© C*s. P. P—L (ni ; 517—5,000-10-23. Jitbo-Oruropean CEcU'^rapli apartment, p p*ulf SECTION. from The Clerk in Hhare'e Bahrein I, E. Foim. 1 . E. P. 3. To. K 'B M*s Political A.^ent NDEX NO OF 19 -19 Abstract. Precis. 3ir, The Wireless Staff have jointly requested me to write anl ash you to hindly tahe some action against hlastin^ sea-stone opposite to, anfl sc close to the 'Tireless quarters. The reason heinp that showers 0 ^ crushed stone, lihe shrapnel, is thrown into the compound at every blast, an 1 occasionally lar-e 8 ' boulders, which is a source o^ positive danger to the sta^f and their families. Plastin^ has been ^oin^ on ^or some months, but we refrained from complaining as the work was bein^ ^one much ^urther off. Now that the men are working only about 15 ^eet ^rom our compund, I trust that you will be Food enough to order blasting some distance away where equally pood stone is procurable. I beF to remain fir,Copy of* a let tor datod the 4th June, 1927, from the 'lerk i/c nadio, to the Political Agent, ahrain. The WireleBE Staff* have jointly requested me to write and ask you to kindly take eone action against blasting sea stone opposite to, and so close to the Wireless quarters. he reason being that showers of* crushed stone, like sharynel, is thrown into the conpound at every blast, and occasio ally lar r* 8' boulders, which is a source of* positive danger to the staff* and their families. Blasting has been going on for some months, but we refrained from complaining as the work was being done much further off. ^ow that the men are working only about 15 feet from our* conpound, I trust that you will be good enough to order blasting some distance away where equally good stone is procurable. -JLXX No. /f/7 Of 1927 Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the June 1927. To The Adviser, iahrain ^tate, Bahrain. Copy forwarded for information, wth the reouest that t ~ou will be good enough to take steps to have the blasting operations removed to a safer distance. Political A -ent, Captain, Bahrain.dated 6th June 1927. I write to inform you that steps have been taken to remove the 'blasting operations to a safer dist o noe from C/sct Adviser, ''-N / V SMX. Bahrein Government.■Bahrein “Radio 11th April 1923. Dear Major Darrett, ' I have just received your letter encloeinr the notice fron the 'Bahrein Authorities. I should he very sorry indeed to think that any of my little staff *ras responsible for causing offence to His 'Excellency or any other member the Arab ooimnunity. I have warned them that very chaotic action will be taken against any cns cf them found ruilty ^f such a ij&amp;lx 'breach and I can assure A that I shall,in the future as in the pc.t, do everythinr in my power to promote the rood **eelin* at present existing between the two communities.BAHRAIN. ITth w V The Political Agent. thtough The Financial Adviser. BAHRAIN. Bear Sir. ^ . I have brought to Bahrain with me a small trirelees reteiving set f which has been detained by the Customs. I understand that the regulations witlr regard to these imports are not quite clear, and staall be glad to know if there is any objection to my using this set for my, own private use. I am in possesstion of an English, Indian, and West African licence to use this' set. ^ r ~ 1 Ycurs faithfully. ■ ■■ ' ' ■■■■ K.I.5.Z. ENGIKEBR-IK-CHMGE of BAHRAIN EIZCTRIFICATIN /• ffavt 4 /a.v.J-9. •^' a ' TLi.trPA.-^^A. 4 ; p/c iProm political, Laxirein* Captain Lrior, Bristol,Hotel Karachi, ^esicient, Bush ire. Ho.1127 Bated 19th September 1929. Jordan Bnjineer Bahrein electrification has 'brought wireless receiving set which has been detained at Customs. Adviser enquires if there is any objection to his usii ’ it. Jr. Hol ies was forbidden use of his set In 1926 and r. Bienem ield in 1927 by Captain x-HLban after consult ing Resident, please instruct addressed Karachi repeated Bushire. No. 27 Bated and received 20th September 1929. Bahrein 1127 I see no objection. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Bahrein.No# of 1929 • The Political Agency, Bahrein# Dated th 1929# To The Olerk in Charge, Bahrein Radio, Bahrein# M m v m &amp;m* I find that the delivery of the telegrams addressed to this Agency i*$ much delayed# In some instances they are detained for some hours after the 1 -/ receipt while in others they are delivered ij^next morning, Owing to such delays much inconvencince is caused# I would point out that telegram ( monthly ) No#507 from Captain Prior Political Agent, Bahrein now on recess at Karachi was received by you at 12.45 Gr#M#T# ( 4#03 p#m# local time) whereas it was only delivered to me at my house after office hours at 6#10 p#m# The Political Agent wanted some urgent papers to be sent to him# Had this telegram been received in time I would have arranged to despatch them by yesterday 1 s mail and much trouble and inconvencience would have bean saved* in future official telegrams are sent as soon as possible to avoid such inconvenience and delay# I shall be glad if you will please see that Indian Assistant In the absence of the ^Political Agent,Bahrein#INBO-EUR OPT? AN TELEGRAPH UEPARTWENT. Mymj * t (Persian Oulf Section) &lt; /To ) Brom The Clerk-in-Charge, Bahrein Badio. UtL To The Indian Assistant, Political Agency, Bahrein. r Memorand um. No.lm/ 93 Dated September 20th 1929. I have to acknowledge receipt of your Memorandum Mo.1128 of 1929 1 and to inform you that?- - much as I reerret any incon venience that may have been caused hy the delay to your offic ial correspondence of which you complain - the delay itsel^ i? invariably unavoidable. I have only t 7 fO delivery peons, who are engaged throughout the day, and are frequently sent out together or within a few minutes of one another. The present is our busy season, and as each batch of telegrams is sent ou for delivery as soon as it is received, it often happens that we have no peon available to deliver even treble-rated urgent traffic that chances to come in half an hour or so after a batch of •ordinary* or •deferred* has been disposed of, and - having taken perhaps ten minutes in transit between London agy* Bahrein - has perforce to be held up in our office for an hour or more for want of a messenger, in the case of Telegram No. 507, however, the delay was due to the fact that although re ception was timed 12.45 the message was not correctly receiv ed till nearly 2 £ hours later owing to •atmospherics* and the consequent necessity for repetitions etc. it is unfortunate that in this instance my operator omitted to amend the time of reception; had this been done the cause of delay would have been immediately apparent, in future cases of this de scription, should such arise, a note of flelay will be made on the message. 2. All telegrams, official or otherwise, are delivered with the least possible delay, and are sent out by the ^irst avail able messenger. If however, you wish to secure that tele grans for the Agency are handed to you immediately on receipt in this office, I would suggest that you attach one o^ your or derlies to the Badio Office to take your Telegrams over when ever we have no peon available. This was done by uaj. Daly in similar circumstances, the arrangement proving most satis factory to all concerned. jX' 31 erK 'i n -CharRe, Bahrein Radio.The Political Agency f Bahrein* Dated the^ ^September 1929 To The Adviser Bahrein Government Bahrein. Reference your memorandum No* Nil dated the 19th September 1929. The Eon r ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, has no objection to Mr* Jordan, Engineer, Bahrein Electrification using his wireless set provided Eis Excellency Shaikh Hamad sanctions the import. &lt; 7 »- Indian Assistant. % ■&gt;0 . % C’s. P. P.—L (m) 979—200-12-29 —l. No. OF 193 . Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the let Jttio 1930» $ 93 :. To The Adviser, Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. I v/ould bo glc-d if you uoidd kindly accord saaction to the use of the Electric Li^t poles to convey a telephone line fron the Agency to the terminal pole outside the west gate of the Telegraph conpoimd. Tlie line will be put up by Liessrs. Callenders £ Company at the expense of the Indo-European Telegraph Department. I v/ould be glad if your reply could be sent in duplicate. , x'oliticrJ. Afent, Balarc.in.MI No. Office i &lt;3 of 1349 Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated. 6th Muharam, 1349 II. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. With reference to your memorandum No. 912 dated 1st June, 1930. The Bahrain Government has no objection to your using the posts in question for your telephone line, but at the same I would point out that we take no responsibility for anything that may possibly occur through wires touching. / 4' &gt; - Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.' - C’s.-P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29— e. % . «r From To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. The Adviser, Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. No._ tap, Dated 2nd June 1930* rac • Jfaamaatott* I thank you for your Memorandum.No*39/l8 dated 6th Huliaram 1349 and the permission to use the electric light poles for our telephonic wire. The Electrical Department will, no doubt, take the usual precautions to avoid accidents. &amp; Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram- Enclair. From - D.P.G-. Karachi. To - Political, Bahrain. No. 833/367 Date. 8th July 1930. Existing telephone line to wireless erected at I.E.T.D cost ssxi in 1921. ^e have maintained line and phones without charge of rent, willing continue this but unable provide funds for new telephone line for which OallentLers cpiote Rs.615. if phone still required will you please arrange for re-building of line.Telegram- Enclair. Froy- Political, Bahrain, To - D.P.G. Karachi. No. 1086 Date. 12th July 1930, Your 833/357. Regret cannot find 615/- Could not present wire he re-erected. No. 1087 of 1930. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th July 1930. Copy to the Clerk-in-Charge, Bahrain Radio, Bahrain, for information with the request that he would say whether he considers it feasible to re-erect the present line. Political Agent, BahrainTelegram - Enclair From - D.P.G-. Karachi To. - Political, Bahrain No. 833/351 Dated- 30th July 1930. Your telegram 20/24 Callenders now quote Rs.401 (Four hundred and one ) erection single wire telephone line please wire if you could pay this amount as regret we unable do so. Telegram - Enclair From - Political, Bahrain To - D.P.C.Karachi No. 1178 Date. 31st July 1930. Your 833/351. Regrei unable find funds. Will discuss matter with you.&lt;C' rK f ^ al iSluirir, ^ n-o* ** /i•£ &lt;%q r t . HEHS,AN ISa{)fr^iu t ^^rsian l^th October, 19^0., H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, I hear that in Iraq, India, and Egypt, the Stu?©p©ftn Indo-European Telegraph Department offer special facilities at cheap rates for 'Christmas Greetings' telegrams. x' - '- rtoula it be possible, please, to enquire from the Superintendent at Karachi, if such facilities could be put into operation in the Persian Gulf. I think they would be greatly appreciated. I am, dear Sir, Yours faithfully,INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPH 'DEPARTMENT . (peraian Gulf section). Bahrein RaAio Deer. 12th 1930. NOTICE. C hristmas and New Year Greetings '▼!* INDQ '. Christmas and New Year Greeting Telegrams at special re duced rates will he accepted for Great Britain and Northern Ireland durin* the period 15th December 1930 to 5th January 1931, both dates inclusive. These telegrams will be classed XLT, and will be charged for at Six Annas per word with a minimum charge of Rs.3-12-0 for Ten words including the indication XLT. As there is sure to be a rush of this class of traffic it is advisable to BOOK EARLY. \No. Political Agency, Balirain. Dated the bth. iiarcii, 1931. The Superintendent, Bahrain Radio, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Will you please appear at the Agency to~nicrro*r morning the 7th instant,at 10 O 1 clock,in connection with the alleged theft of 1.3.T.Dept. Records and hiring with you all witnesses as also any parson or persons connected therewith. Yours faithfullyBY AIR MAIL. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 7th March 1931. No: From:- Captain C.G.Prior I.A*, Political Agent,Bah rain. To:- The Director,Indo-European Telegraphs, Persian Gulf Section,Karachi. Sir, With reference to your telegram No:1885/155 dated the 5th March 1931,1 have the honour to forward for your information copies of the statements made at an enquiry held by me regarding the theft of records from the gouown in the Radio Office,Bahrain. 2. It will be seen that the documents had been sorted on the 1st March and that some had been packed and that others had been left open in the verandah: at the close of the day’s work the lids of the boxes were not nailed Gown and the remainder of the records were left lying on the verandah floor and they were left in this condition all night. This was the north verandah of the goaown in the north-west comer of the compound some 20 yards from the boundary fence and within full view of the sea shore. 3. On the evening of the 2nd Mr.Edwards brought a man to the Agency and told me that he had been caught stealing papers from their godown. I had the man sent to the Police Station and went into the case the next day. The man said he had only been doing what many others had done and that he had no dishonest intentions as he thought the papers were not repaired; in fact the documents caught on him appeared2 . appeared to be of little value to anyone- I asked him what to sell them for one or two annas. As he was a first offender and the value of the stolen property was negligible I discharged him with a warning and his statement therefore does not appear among those which I enclose. 4. It is clear that the records could have been tampered with at any time during the 24 hours preceeding the theft and since they were found strewn about the compound there is little doubt that many persons had been at them. It is strange that the pillaging of the records attracted no attention and I can only account for it by the pre-occupatioi of Messrs Edwards and Mafalan with their immediate departure and handing over. Had the godown been kept locked the theft could not have occurred. 5. I am afraid that it is hardly possible to take any useful action after this delay,but I shall be glad to take any further steps you consider necessary. he proposed to do with them and he said that he had intended I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent, Bahrain.'r .T.A .Faithfull states On the 2nd of F&amp;rch durin ( ; the lunch hour a man was noticed going p st the quarters taking some old papers with him. I ersonally dtd not see the man as all this was dealt with by T e Edwards but I heard a bout it later* I saw the place where the papers were taken from that si me afternoon, and fo ind the peers all strewn about on the verandah. T.e boxes were open but the god owns were closed. The boxes were lying in the verandah and the paers were strewn about the com,ound. A P I dfcd not see any body there. I had all the paers collated and had them put back in the godown. I had nothing to do p with the paers before and did not take then over as it was sole ly a departmental affair, and they were all to be taxen to .Ka rachi by r Edwards. I believe he had started packing them the morning previoas to the thefts, but I did not see it. The driver and one of the two frrasxhes were doing the work, and Mr Edwards was not there himself.37 T hagwan 3ingh driver of the ireless Power plant, states. The day before the theft I had received intirtructions to pacic some paers. Some were for iuirachi and sbobk Mr Mafalan had sorted them out. V/hen they were in their boxes I said to ?r r Pdwards that they were ready to be nailed up but he did not come. They remained the night in the verandah, and the box lids were not fastened down but were just placed on. when the farash Ghulam Hussain came with a man he had caught, and said that he had found him stealing papers. I looked at the books and recognised them and said f Yes they are ours ’ and sent the man to Hr Edwards. He saw him and tnen said send him T ext day in the evening I was orking in the engine room and the books to the Agency. He was sent to the Agency. 7Gh’lam Hae^an t farash of the Radio states I was waiting to tf'll Hr Rdwards when the P.A.’s motor xxx had arrived and was on the lookout for it when I saw a man coming from the godo' n and crossing behind the building towrds the ro c. He had some papers under his arm. I called to him and asked wh n t he had and saw it was some books. I asked him 'Stax* he had. taken them from • nd he said that he had taken them from th-: god own, and that there were many children helping them elves from the pile. I to^k him to the Sikh engine dr ver, and he told me to take him to the Sr-hib { Hr Edwards ). ijtold the sahib -nd he came himself and he told me to take the man to the Agency. Has'-an Eakhuda r tempor ry hand in the Radio.States. The day before the theft I was working with the Sikh and r Hafalan in packing books and papers for hipment to Karachi. ‘11 those that were to go to Karachi were put in boxes and all those that were to stay behind were left on the verandah. That evening when we left off work the boxes had the lids put on but they were not nailed down, and the remaining papers were left on the fia&gt;or of the godown berandah. The xexzK god own doors were locked. \n the engineer s id that he would go and tell the sahib that the work was finished, but I dont know if he did or I was in the enfineroom when the patawala Ghulam Hussain brought a man in and said he had be^n stealing books. They sent for th*' chief sahib and he came and said hat he should be taken to the ‘gency and he was t v* 1 ' liwere T took him there notKo. /^^5/3 of 1349 Office of tne Adviser to With reference to the transfer of the wireless station by Indo- European telegraphs to a public commercial comuany. The conces sion of freedom from customs dues granted to the Indo-European Telegraphs was owing to its being a department of the Government of India, therefore the new company will be treated in a similar way to any other commercial concern in respect of Customs dues. ■ 6 U &lt;•/ i?/i ' Adviser to the government.Bahrain,the 10th March 1931 To, The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memor andum. Reference your Memorandum No:1295/3 dated the 20th Shawwal 1349. The contents have been noted. Political Agent, ( £^ Bahrain.''Copy of ^emo. No.1295/3 of 1349 dated 20th Shawwal 1349 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Covernment, Bahrain to H*B*M f s Political Agent, Bahrain . With reference to the transfer of the wireless station by Indo-European telegraphs to a public commercial company. The concession of freedom from customs dues grantee to the Indo-European Telegraphs was owing to its being a department of the Government of India, therefore the new company will be treated in a similar way to any other commercial concern in respect of Customs dues. Copy of Memo. No.329 dated the 10th March 1931 from tne Political Agent, Bahrain to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Reference your memorandum No. 1295/3 dated the 20th Shawwal 1349. The contents have been noted. No. Wo of 1931. The Political Agency, Bahrain Dated the 11th March 1931. The foregoing copy is forwarded to the Superintendent- In^Charge, Radio Office, Bahrain, for information. Political Agent, Bahrain.Ik TELEGRAM From Manager, Karachi Q.C. Bahrain. To Dated ana received 17th March 1931. Please inform Captain Prior sufficient copper wire for line will cost approximately rupees one hundred ana twelve plus freight to Bahrain aaa There is no scrap wire available but this is at half value aaa May I purchase from Govt. Store Dept.l Ji /'W. Ho. i, 3 ts l ,b Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 19th tlarch, 1931. Messrs. Callenders Cable &amp; Construction Co.,Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I shall be glad if you will let me know the cost of installing a telephone line from the Radio Office to this Agency if the necessary wire is provided by me end the brackets and insulators are supplied by you. An early reply will much oblige. Yours faithfully, ciiirain.C's. P. P.—L (m) 980—300-1-30—j. URGENT REMINDER. From To 1 essrs. Callenders Cable &amp; THE POLITICAL AGENT, Construction Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Bahrain. No. MEMORANDUM. r V Bahrain, dated the 2ord March m 1 I have to draw your early attention to this office letter No. 3o0/lo/^ . J ... tms Vr enc dated tae i ! nrch 193 1 , regarding a telephone line from Raaio t^ n( ^ to request that its reply may be expedited. Political Agent, Bahrain.L.Q.No:J^y 7 . Political Agency, Bahrain, tne 24th March 1921. The estimate for putting up the telephone line from the Radio office to the n^ency is so exorbitant tnat I am afraid jre will not be able to nave it. you tell me what would be the additional cosi over and above the Ro.lL//- for the wire for one or two additional poles and insulators in place of these that are broken and also whether you can find the necessary labour (linesmen &amp;c.,) withafft^~ the extra charge. If the line can be put into working oraer for a small charge over that your mentioned for the copper wire 1 would be prepared to pay for it. ication Coy, Bahrain. .Faithful Esu.. Superintendent ' 9 : I CommonCallender’s cable &amp; construction company, limited. Head office for India Forbes Building. Home Street, fort, bombay. B/2002 Engineers, Cable' Manufacturers &amp; Contractors. resident Engineer’s office. B A H R A I H. 23rd March 1931 VNe 1# n , 'A Ua t?2.V-5- 3 /. H.B.M’s POLITICAL AGENT. BAHRAIN. Bear Sir. Vvith reference to your TTo. 380/1^/2 dated 19th inst., vre have pleasure in quoting you for the Installing of a Telephone line from the Radio Orfice to the Agency. This line will he fixed to the existing 31ectidc li^it poles on suitable angle Iron cross airriSjand will he complete with, pin and shackle insulators where . required. Our estimate also includes the necessary lead in*-to both buildings, but does not include an extra pole that will be required in the compound at the Radio Station. We are prepared to carry out the above work complete, but you to supply the necessary wire, for the sum of Rs.50 5/*-. (PITS HUTTDHSD &amp; PITH . HIRERS.) Trusting to be favoured with your valued order which will receive our immediate attention. Yours faithfully for CALLJiiimiiiRS CABL±i &amp; CONSTHJCTIOH CO .LTD. _ * « - Resident Engineer.CALLENDER’S CABLE &amp; CONSTRUCTION COMPANY, LIMITED. With reference to our B/2002 dated 25rd nitimo, and our snibse&lt;nient conversation, I find that our original estimate for this work was Rs. 615 /- (Hs.515/- plus Rs.lOO/- for the leads into the Tmildings.) This amount was subsequently reduced insulators for same, and only half of the lead in wires. The estimate you now require without wire will require the original number of insulators, and the double lead in at both ends. In order however to meet you in this matter we are prepared to carry out the work complete tor the sum of Rs.4-7 5/-, which v/e trust will enable you to place the Head office for India Forbes Building. Home Street. Fort, Bombay. Engineers, Cable Manufacturers &amp; Contractors. RESIDENT ENGINEER’S OFFICE. B A H B A I IT B/2004- H.BJTs POLITICAL AGENT B A H B A I F Bear Sir to Bs. 4P1/- if only one wire was run, the reduction being,the cost of the wire order Yours faithfully for CALLENBEBS CABLE &amp; COFSTHJCTION Co.Ltd, Besident Engineer.@ D.Q.No: ty#? . Political Agency, Bahrain,the 24th ^rch 1931. V Please refer to your letter No:B/2002 dated the 23rd March 1931. I notice your estimate now amounts to Hs.5u5/~ and 1 feel sure there must be a mistake somewhere. You will remember that before you gave us an estimate for some Rs.uOQ/- but .yh&amp;k' i t was suggested that it should be a single lide\connection the estimate was reaucea to sqm^Bs.300/-,but now,however, that we undertake to si^p^Jy the copper wire your estimate has increased. Are the figures correct? F.V.Jordan Esquire, Bahrain.C.O.No: 4 ^? . Political agency, Bahrain,the 24th ^rch Uhl. Lear Jordan, [lease refer to your letter ^o:B/20U2 dated the 23ra larch 1931. 1 notice your estimate now amounts to Rs.5u5/- and i ieel sure tnere must be a mistake somewhere. ^ou will remember that before you gave us an estimate for some as.^uOZ-yhirt hen it was suggested that it should be a single line connection the 1 i.3jQ/-,but now,nowever, 1 „ ,e figures correct? copper wire your Yours Sincerely ordan Ls.;uire, Bahrain.The Agency, Bahrain. Bated 29th [larch, 1931 Bear Mr, Faithful, Please refer to your letter of the 28th instant in regard to the telephone. The old poles seem to me to be strong enough. Could they be made to do? Yours sincerely, J. H. Faithful Eseuire, Bahrain(g) Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the fod April 1931* Dear Mr. Faithful, nould . ou please have the work of the tele phone iine^ to the igeney taken in itand as early as possible? Please replace such of the existing poles as you consider absolutely necessary. lours sincerely, J. R. Faithful, Esquire, Bahrain.Q.f'o: Political Agenc/, Baiirain,tLe 4th April 1931 uoUj-d you piesse depute four prisoners daily lor vvota on the telephone line wnich is to be corfltructea between this Agency and the Bahrain Incio Station. if it is possible 1 shall be glad if you will instruct them to report to tne Superintendent ol tne Bahrain Itadio who is erecting tnis tele none. Captain i.C.farke., Co.aRiandant, tate Police, iianniin.0, f %\J ■ ' olitical n rency, ;&gt;-jhn i i i, tne 7tn April IjjI. . lease ref^r to your letter oi the ^ra j.pril 1.. 31. As no convict labour is available,! suggest you en age 4 coolies to no the work rna also arrange the purchase Ox six poles anc one cozen insulators, i will arrange payment of the bills on hearing from you. JFaithful hsquire, Bahrain Radio, Bahrain.Imperial and international Communications Ltd., (Persian Culf cables). No l/ 3003 Bahrain 30th Marcft, 1931. ?he political A^ent Bahrain. Dear sir, With reference to your note of yesterday evening '~Trewith repetition of Residents No 223. *he Bushire-Radio office says that the 13th and 28th 5 ext s are doubtful* 13th EfPVYBWYRC or EJP^TYBlfYRC. S8th OABOXKKYS^ur OABUXKKYSU We were unahle to pass your message last ni?ht as Bushire'Radio clo at 1630 CMf, every nisrht and we were unahle raise Henjam-Radio ^rom 8.50 pm to 1116 pm local, “'he clerk responsible for the reception of Residents No 223 has been warned to write more legibly in future. Yours faithfully r « Of freer in Charge Bahrain-RadioNo: Political Agency, Bai 1 rain,the 7th April 1931- To, The Jilicer-in-Charge, Imperial fc International Communications Ltd, Bah i Ji • inemoranaum . You are probably avrare that before your present Company took over from the Inao-Lurcpean Telegraphs an arrangement was in force whereby the latter billed this office monthly for all telegrams emanating from it instead of paying for ea- telegram sent. your Company to arrange to bill us monthly .ith &gt;ut any undue inconvenience. I write to enquire if it is possible for Indian Assistant, Itehrain.IMPERIAL AND INTERNATIONAL OOMMTJNICJA'TTONS L^N),, (Persian DuIf Cables), l/ 8 04 Bahrain dafjed Bth April 1931. 7*0 ?«he Indian Assistant political Agency Bahrain, Dear sir, With reference to your Memorandum no 446 dated 7th instant, we have to inform you that the arrangement which was in force before, will be followed by this office in future Officer in Charge Bahrain-padioTELEGRAL S.G From Manager Persian Gulf, Karachi. Officer in Charge, Bahrain Radio To No. 22 Dated 1st May 1931. 13/26 for Political Agent Begins - My letter No.13/26 dated 11th April Rs.3/l/6 has been spent account cartage to'Kimari for two cases containing wire kindly remit this amount. fEMGRAK From Manager Persian Gulf, Karachi. To Political, Bahrain. Dated and received 1st May 1931. In our SG/22/35/lst please read word after 13/26 as D/llth not H/llth.yi^ . Political ii,;ency, Baiirain, the 4th Llay 1^31- Dear Mr Faithful, Yes: the copper wire came in the Barpeta with me and 1 have asked :.:r.D T Souza to deliver it to you. Please engage such coolies as are required for the work. I passed along the line this morning and it seemed to me tnat at certain places it will be necessary to anchor the poles to take the strain. If this is necessary no doubt you will see it is done. I am giving the Manager’s packet to your man ana am instructing him to carry it carefully. Yours Sincerely, J.A.Faithfull Kscpii Bahrain Radio. ^squire,No: J73 . Political A^ r ;ency, Bahrain, the 10th May 1931. The Officer-in-Charge, Bahrain Radio. Rear Sir, Please refer to your letter of the 24th April 1931 to my Assistant regarding permission to take delivery of a gun .from the Customs. arms into Bahrain is prohibited by Treaty and it is difficult to make exceptions in favour of anyone. As a special case,however,1 am prepared to sanction the import of your rifle,provided that you undertake to send it to India as soon as possible. here,since His Excellency preserves it strictly for himself and members of the Ruling family. As you are probably aware the import of I may add that there is no game available Yours faithfully, ‘-Political Agent og, Bahrain.The Imperial International Communications Ltd: : ^ Bahrein * /y/*'/*//p*' Co b Pol it ical ;ciioy, Bahrain. Bated the 17th ! ay 3 1P31. Dear Mr, Faithful, Please refer to your letter of even date enquiring whether it would bo possible to issue a Supply Bill in favour of I r. PunG-avin. I a:: afraid I a r i unable, at present, to icsue a bill lor the aucuiit you require but could however issue one for say 's.3000/- now end for the balance on the 1st proxiiao. Yours sincerely, ao J. . Faithful isquire, Bahrain Radio*w o:^ Political r^Qucrj , Bahrain,the 17Lh ay IS31. Dear Mr.Faithful, I have ashed I espors if they can arrange to send the two telephones down to arachi as a favour parcel and if they can arrcj^e this I will ask you to send a chit to Ir.Lungavin announcing their arrival. i J. .Faithful ^sguire, Bahrain iadio. ^ j K Y - Al/U ^ ^ ■tmmmmmsrn i *■ Political /i^cncy, Bahrain,the 17th Hay Dear Russell, 1 have two telephones which origimuly belonged to the I.P.T,D,which ai'e not functioning properly and require overhaul. I \;ould much like to send then to Lungavin in Karachi for urgent overhaul and return hut l:)a shipping charges on so snail a package would tactically anount to their value. ould it he possihlc to send thorn dam as a favour parcel and if so could you arrange for then to he delivered to hi i at Karachi? Yours Sincerely, J. Ihissoil .scpiire, Pesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd, Bahrain.4 Telegraphic Address!- “mespers? s/iatasc- ( INCORPOrXtED yf^tNGLAND ) BAHREIN, 17th May /£ 31, Yes, I can send the telephones down as a favour parcel. Please send them to me in time to catch the down - mail arriving here on or about 2$th instant. To, Capt.C. G. Prior, Political Agent, BAHREIN. yjummgm ■ m- The Imperial and International Communications Limited. ?6 Wo. 13/26 . Karachi. Dated 11th April 1931 . To The Political Agent, ^ y RCDEi - •' ^ / ' ■ - inO /^ (O/ -/« BAHREIN. W oat*. ' Dear Sir, I send herewith in duplicate issue note No.5 dated 7 th April 19d1 received ftfom the Officer-in-Charge, Indian Telegraph Store Depot, Karachi on account of 225 Ihs of wire bronze 150 lbs per mile and two packing cases supplied to you and request the favour of your kindly return ing one copy of the same duly signed to the Officer-in-Charge Indian Telegraph Store Depot, Karachi direct. The bill for the articles when received will be forwarded for payment. (M Yours /faithfully, \. Manager. ty-The Imperial and International Communications Limited. (2,23J (h 4 CORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) K v Karachi 5^m P r j Yp 6 **\,Jx£f f’Oth June /9 4:*1 15/26 b 7 &gt; / Dear Sir, With reference to this office letter No.15/26 dated 11th April 1951* ^ send herewith in triplicate a bill for Rs 152/- received from the Officer-in-Charge, Indian Telegraph Store Department, Karachi on account of 225 Lbs of wire bronze, 150 lbs per mile supplied to you and request the favour of an early settlement of the same* Yours faithfully, ^^Manager. To The Political Agent, Bahrein. (Ckf ftBill No. 4 3W # dated 25-5-1931. The Political Agent. Bahrien. Persian Gulf. Dr. To Indian Telegraph Department. Total. Indent or Jferticulars. Authority. Rs. A* p. Kr S/v No: 5 225 lbs Wire, bronze. 150 lbs p.m. d/ 7•4-31* l/2 value. 90 0 0 2 P.C*nedlum. 6 0 0 56 0 0 Store keeping 25£ 24 0 9 120 0 0 Surcharge 10£ 12 0 0 Total;- 132 0 0 Sd/- illegible* Accounts Officer. Telephone Revenue. Stores &amp; Workshops. Storeyard.. Alipore. V.B.K.16-6.No: $12/ # Political Agency, Bahrain, the 5th July 1931. To, The Manager, Imperial &amp; International Communications Ltd. Karachi. Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No:13/26 dated the 20th June 1931. I enclose herewith Supply Bill No:2943/4 for Rs.132/-,(Rupees one hundred and thirty-two) only, in full settlement of your Debit Note No:4/SW dated 25th May 1931,for 225 lbs of bronze wire supplied. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, H Bahrain. Political Agent,y The Imperial and International Communications Ltd. (2/23,1 63 s't; 17th Jfily y/ 31. 13/26 Dear Sir, .vy-- -7-$/ Re. su _of 225 lbs bronze wire 150 Tbi per miTeV With reference to your letter No.812 dated 5 th instant, I send herewith a receipt No.12 Book No.55 dated 15th July for Rs 152/- received from the Officer-in-Charge, Indian Telegraph Stores Depot, Karachi. To The Political Agent, BAHREIN.T)e ar Capt ain pr ior, Wheeler has applied to me for permission to allow him to erect an aerial for hie wireless set arriving shortly, presume yoa have no object ion? yours sincerely, ^ ^ ^W'- A pi D.O.Ho: 8/6. rolitical , gency, Bahrain, the 18th July 1931. Please refer to your letter of even date, fhere will he no object ion tovUheeler in^orting a wireless set. k/ wB^SL ’i-n* @ ' Badio’*, Bahrein, Sfetyh July *31. . / f Mr Mungavin suggests that; the S,N.O, keep a deposit with you tc enable us to recover ' cost of Navy messages, due to this station 'through you at- Bahrein, instead of through Treasury Officer Bushire. I have wirelesseo to the SrN.O, and if he has no objection, I h4&gt;pe you wont * It would be much more convenient for us in this way. I wondered if you could possibly arrange with Aerotwo, when next over this way, to take a closeup snap of the Radio? I would pay the cost and also pass your message as a chit -£7 D.Q.No: ^? . Political Agency, Bahrain,the 26th July 1931 / Lear Ur.Lait^ful, Please refer to your letter rejardin^ the deposit of money to pay for Navy messages at Bahrain instead of payment bein£ made through Bushire# It will mean a little more work but there is no objection if you would prefer this method and you may tell the S.N.O that I have said so. I enclose a chit message to Aerotwo asking them to take the close up you asked for. J.A.Faithful Esquire, Bahrain Radio, Bahrain.- w i I i Neither the Director, f^^rsian Gulf Section, nor any Telegraph Company or Foreign Government, by whom this telegram is or would, in the ordinary course of the Telegraphic Service, be forwarded; shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission, or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay, or error, or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-trans mission, non-delivery, delay, error or omission shall have occurred. Applications regarding reiund of the cost of this telegram, and complaints respecting u, should be addressed to the Superintendent, Traffic Office, Indo-Furopean telegraph Department. Karachi within five months of the date of the telegram. 1 he receipt granted for the telegram should be enclosed. 'iH Radio House' ^ Bajirein. ^ C; i 2l3t Au^r. 1931. Dear Mr ATdIuI Haiy, I think, as a result of the interview, the man I sent to you yesterday, came to me this mor ning and expressed his willingness to work for Hs25/- p.m. and I have taken him on. ’’hanks so much for the trouhf taken in securing a man for us. I pro' -pose sending the attached telegram to the Manager Persian ^ulf, and sha ll he obliged if you would kindly countersign it. With best wishes, Yours sincerely,Bahrein, 3rd June 1931. The Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Sir, I have to bring to your notice that the total cost of coolie hire for erecting the telephone line is Rs.36/-., i.e., 4 coolies at Re.l/- per day for 9 days. I have only received Rs.20/- from the Officer in Charge to pay the coolies. The amount does not cover their wages for the above mentioned period. I humbly beg you will kindly grant me the balance i.e., Rs.16/- for which I shall always be grateful. I beg to remain, Sir, Tour most humble servant^ GHOLAM HUSSAItf KHTTDADAI) (&amp; ■'Radio House * Bahrein. 22/8/31. Bear Mr Abdul Haiy, I attach herewith telegram from our Manager at Kar achi in connection with expenses incurred on two telephones sent to Karachi for repairs on your behalf. I am slad to inform you that the telephonesbet ween the Agency and this office are now in good working order. Yours sincerely,C s. P . P .—L (m) 831 1,000-1-29 I M PORT. WHARFAGE ENTRY UNDER THE ' KARACHI PORT TRUST ACT, VI OF 1886.” (Amendment Acts II of 1902, II of 1909, and I of 1914.) To The Director of Traffic, Karachi Port Trust. . / Sir—P lease permit to be landed at the&lt;3 D.0.I]o:/3£\3, Political /igency, -al:irain,tlie 12th December 1931. Dear Faithful, Please refer to your letter of the 12th December 1931. I v/rote privately to hr.! un,;avin about taking Pitcher to Basra but in case you think it better to send a chit message regarding this, I enclose one The Permit you asked for is also enclosed. When Mr.Wilson comes here next month I will certainly do what I can about the A.O power scheme if you let me know exactly what it is. I suppose it consists of selling your power plant and attaching yourself to the Bahrain Government supply? J.A.Faithful isquire, Bahrain ladio.,Political Agent, Bahrain. No-./'W, Political Agency, Bahrain,the 30th December 1931. To, The Officer-in-Charge, Imperial &amp; International Communications Ltd, Bahrain. Dear Sir, On the 19th December 1931 I sent a telegram in code addressed to Aerotwo,Basra. The addressee informs me that this telegram was not received by him. I would be glad,therefore,if you would please arrange to refund its cost to this Agency. Yours faithfully,Political Agent, Bahrain. C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—3001-30—j. URGENT REMINDER. &lt;S) From THE POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrain. To The Officer-in-Qh arge, Biiirain ladio , BAHrlvIL* No. ML Bahrain, dated.. Ui'J Al-til Loor iu . r y 193 B . MEMORANDUM. I have to draw your early attention to this office letter No. l4«.5 , dated t il0 901b ’jjcentber l 93L &gt; regarding of the cost 01 loie^ram and to request that its reply may be expedited.Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No 1435, dated 30th December 1931, we attach herewith correspondence for your kind perusal and return. Yours faithfully, Of&amp;e€r -ck urge, I &amp; I Communications; Ltd: BAHREIN.E.Q.No. l ±!O m . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th April 1932. Dear Welsh Just a note to tell you that I have returneu to Brhrain and hope that you will be coming this way sometime in tne near future. Do you remember that when I was in Basra the wire announcing my arrival ana that of the team was said not to have been received anu Aerotwo had no definite news of our coming. On my return I took up tne matter with tne Telegraphs and asked tnem to ascertain what nad happened to it. They have now replied attaching a certificate which shows that they delivered it alright so it must hrve been overlooked in the pre-Xmas rush. The signatures are hard to make out, one lojks like 'S.Mantle' and tne other like X.Kliah”. Yours sincerely, Group Captain W.L.Telsh, D.F.C., a.F.C., Commanding 203(F.B.) Squadron, R.a.F.,£No iJiH Political igency, Bahrain, tiie 20th April 1032 , i /e&gt;? To, 'ihe Officer-in-Charge, Imperial &amp; International Communications Lta, Bahrain. Lear Sir, I return herewith the enclosures to your letter No:R/^A dated the 18th April 1932. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, 0 Bahrain. INo. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 25th June 1952 To The Gificer-in-Char'e, imperial ana International Consmunications Limited, BiJIHAlN. Lear Sir, Please refer to your letter No.Y/7N dated the 22nd June 1932# I forward, herewith, a receipt for m..78/7/~ as desired therein# Yours faithfully, , Bahrein-Nc. /^7 cf 19 32. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, theAugust 1^32. To The Political Agent Bahrain . I forward for your information a copy cf letter Nc.4/9, dated the 1st July 1932 received from the Manager Imperial and International Communications Limited Karachi and shall he glad if you will kindly furnish a report regarding the land and building in the occupation cf the Telegraphs in Bahrain, stating whether there are any title deeds on deeds cf gift deposited in the Bahrain Agency in respect cf the property in question. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. By Order, VSS. , JW4 &gt;(IU Copy cf letter Nc.4/9, dated tlie 1st July 1932 from the Manager, The Imperial and International Ccmmu- nicaticns Limited, Karachi to the Hcn # hle the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. Te shall be obliged if you will kindly inform us whether Title Deeds in respect cf the late Indo- European Telegraph Departments buildings at Jask, Charbar, Henjam, Bahrein and Bushire are available in your office. If so, we shall be glad ifyou will kindly forward these to us in order to enable us to determine cur proprietary rights in respect cf these buildings and land,. No trace of acy title deeds can oe found here and it is said that they are either deposited in the Bushire Residency or with the Legation at Teheran. It may be possible that the deeds have been registered in the Consulate General at Bushire and possibly as far back as the sixties. V3S.C’s P. P.—L (III) 129—500-4-31. t/1 ML To No.__3JL*£_of 1932 * The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the„i&amp;tll A^USt 193 ^ . The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. Re j: ere nee your memorandum No.1657 dated the 13th August 1933. The title deed of the land belonging to the Imperial and International Gommunications Limited in fehrain is in fta ^:enoy file, and can be given to the Company, if they desire it, on my return from India. It consists of a single sheet of paper signed by His Excellency ShaiJch Isa gifting the land, the measurements given 'being 700 x 500 feet. I suggest that the Imperial and International Comiiunications Limited sliculd take advantage of the creation of the Land Department and obtain registration of this title deed# I presume the Government of India will waive their claims to the property. a r Political Agent, Bahrain. .No. 57. /e'tefi/i'OnC' NO. 273. ■ Jftjnftel&amp;ci'/ anc/fain a /’’o n a / &gt;orrirrittricca,'foon(i- ^JL&amp;mtyfec/. fiH 0 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 1?th September /J?J 2 , J£. k/9 The Political Agent, . Bahrein. -S iii4 , feracM. Dear Sir, We are forwarding an extract from letter No. 1819 dated 10th September 1952 from Hon ! ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire and beg to reouest that you will be good enough to arrange the Registration of the Title deed in the name of the Imperial and Interna- tional Communications Limited. The Officer in Charge Bahrein will act as re presentative of the Company, should it be necessary to have one for the purpose of signing the Registration deed etc. The expenses, if any, for effecting the regis. tration will be paid by the Officer in Charge,Bahrein.Copy of an extract from letter No.1819 dated 10th September 1952 from the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to the Manager, Imperial &amp; International Communications Ltd, Karachi, X X X XXXXXXX The title deeds of the land at Bahrein is in the records of the Political igency there and can be sent to yon if XKpciradt desired. It consists of a single sheet of paper signed by His Excellency Shaikh Isa gifting the land, the measurements given being 700 x 500 feet, The Political Agent suggests that in view of the creation of the Land -Department in Bahrein you should arrange for the registration of the title deed in question.L.O.No: Political Agency, Bahrain,the 15th November 1932. -ear i’aithfuli, I think the air mail is going to cut into your telegraph traffic very considerably ana I snould be interested to hear whether you agree. Now that the first month has been completed,perhaps you could let me know whether your figures show any falling off or not. Pome of the nindus seem to have already tumbled to the idea that they can send their letters by air mail to Karachi and have the contents telegraphed from there at iland rates! Yours Sincerely, J.A.Paithfull Es*i., Officer-in-Cnarge, Bahrain Radio.Radi# House, Bahrein. 15th fteYenber, 1932, Kinaly reter to your d/ 0 ho 1226 of date. The following figures speak for themselres. August 1932, Rs 4250/- beptember ' ' 4605/- Ooxooer M ' 4656/- This includes everything - viz Traffic booked at the counter. Political, Meteorological and Ships messages.//« © ' D.O.No: # POLITICAL AOENC'/f BAHRAINj the 17th NOVEMBER 193?. Dear Faithful, Hilary thanks for your letter of the 15th November 193?. I am glad the situation is as good as it seasonal rise of traffic in October as that yould nullify the impression given by your figures. Yours Sincerely, J.A.Faithful Esquire, Officer-in-Charge, Bahrain Radio.4 n h Radi# House, Bahrein, I9th NsTe*her 1932* Kindly refer ts ytur D/0 sf I7th instant* There is generally a rise of Traffic in October, on account of the termination of the date and pearling seasons. The Petroleum Company, also helped to swell our receipts for this month, I shall let you know our takings for NoTember which I think is a better month to work on*/- Bahrein Branch 0/*P. I5tk January The Pelitieal Agent 3~/ Bahrein. Dear Sir 9 We attach herewith eerrespendenee fer your kind perusal and request that yeu will kindly arrange fer the Registratien ef the Title deed in questien. Please return the attached papers when ne lenger required. Thanking yeu. Yeurs faithfully f Ene:-3. I Jb I Communication*; JM: BAHREIN.Copj of a letter No.4/3 dated t] e 14tl December a332 from the Manager, Imperial and International Communications ^ Limited, Karachi to the Cfficer-in-Charhe 9 Bahrain. Please let us know whether an^ action has been tumen A u-i our ^ T o.4/l dc-G^d 17th Septes.her 1C22 addressed to Political Vent, PSxirain copy to you. # $( i7 y DEPT. branch: Section. Heading. Pros. File No. Serial No. NOTES. 19 Nos. Subject. Letter No*0/;VF dated 15th January 1933 from the officer in charge 1 &amp; I Communications Ltd. , Bahrain. Ke Title needs of land belonging to the Telegraph oept. Notes and Orders. F.A. PP submitted flagged at page 114. The title deeds are with you upstairs please end capt. Prior intended handing them over to the Officer in charge, I &amp; I Commu nications on his return off Hecess. way hand the document to the local Representative of the Company and ask him to have it registered in the Land Department, Bahrain oovt t or perhaps it would be best if we forward the document to the Adviser asking him to register the title deed in the name of the imperial &amp; International communications Ltd., since the original deed has: may have been made out in the name of the Indo-European Telegraph jjept. IvWl c. Document is upstairs in a box please. M 21-1-33 S. 1. DCFP —093S&amp; P— (G-8bl)—4-12-30—8.00,000.O' With reference to our letter K® (/.YF, dated I5th ultimo, we would be very grateful if the matter c®ild be expedited. Thankimg you in anticipation. Yours fathfully, I AT Cpmw-; cat ions,• jj§4t JVHREIN.No Political Agency f Bahrain, the let March 1933* To The Officer-in-Charge, Imperial and International Communications Ltd*, Bahrain* Dear Sir, * \ With reference to our conversation on the 27th February 1933 and your letter No* 0 / /F dated the 15th January 1933, I write to say that I have referred the matter to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* &lt;• • In the meantime the papers, noted in the margin, — f Letter. f[o*4/9 dated 17th September !932g which were attached to your from the Manager, I*&amp;I.C* Ltd*, Karachijf to the Political Agent, Bahrain* j letter are returned* Copy of an extract from letter No*1319 jj dated 10th September 1932 from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the g Persian Gulf, Bushire, to the Manager, j I*&amp;*I*C*Ltd*, Karachi* g Letter No*4/9 dated 14th December 1932 fi from the Manager, I.&amp;*I.C*Ltd*, KarachiI to the Of ficer-in-Charge, Bahrain* 5 Yours faithfully, Lieut-Colonel, Political .Agent, Bahrain* % A* J*The Political Agent, Bahrein^ Dear Sir, ^ ...... With reference to the attached telegrams, we would inform you that owing to adverse atmospheric conditions we have been out of communication with Bushire and ships since the 31st ultimo. We there fore regret your messages to Djedda, Bushire, Aerotwo, and Bideford, reporting the arrival of the HANNO, were unavoidably delayed here till this morning.The atmospherics have now subsided and communica tion is being carried on as usual. Yours faithfully.N0 *_l2iL* Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th April 1933• To The Officer-in-charge, Imperial and International Communications Ltd*, Bahrain* Sir, . . \ I have the honour to refer to your letter No*C/KA dated the 3rd April 1933 regarding my message to Jeddah, Bushire, Aerotwo and H*M.S.•Bideford*, reporting the arrival of the *Hanno *• 2* My message was handed in on the 1st April 1933, i s ;ortly after mid-day, and I supposed that it had been despatched until the receipt of your letter on the 3rd April* I should be obliged if in future you would let me know immediately, should you be unable to despatch a message, as the knowledge that it w?s not possible to transmit a message might, in some cases, make it necessary.for me to take other action* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain# A* J/ No: ^ Political Agency, Bahrain,the 7th April iyhJ. To, The Ofiicer in Charge, Imperial International Communications Limiteo, laemo random . I see that the enclosed telegrams irom Warship Bideford were despatched at 13.00 and 16.uO nours on tne 5th April iy33 but were not delivered to me till the morning of the vth April iy33. It is requested tnat you will Kindly inform me of the reason lor the delay in delivering them. Bahrain. Lieut Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain.Bahrein Wireless, 8th April I933 # yg The Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, t ^2.-/0. ft-il-i y With reference to your letter No 396 dated 6th April 1933, we would inform you that we have noted paragraph 2, for future guidance.Bahrein Wireless H/q. 8th April 1933. ^ The Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir, With reference to your Memorandum No 398, dated 7th April 1933, we are informed by the Warship Bideford that she was unable to effect direct contact with our station and consequently transmit ted the mesaages to the Warship Ormonde who passed them to us on the morning of the 7th April 1933. The telegrams are herewith returned. Yours faithfully Officer-in- chrirge, I &amp; I Communication*; Ltd* BAHREIN.1 From 1. and 1. C. Ltd. : STATION. SERVICE TELEGRAM. Nr. Clerk’s Name Clerk’s Name /y BAHREIN j- TlME &amp; IMTE HECK1VEJ&gt; TIME 4 DATE FORWARDED — Mi gi Ar-al'^6 ^ Nr. — W. Sl S. Lul. (lip (Station Formii 5 ,-12a-151.) To &amp; BRANCH '9's y ^ Dear Khan Bahadur, My successor wishes to bring up his dog to Bahrein. Idont suppose there would be any objection to this. Would you very reply urgently and oblige. Thanking you. Yours sincerely,15 th Sep t ember The Political Agent Bahrein. Bear Sir, I attach herewith for your information a copy of a letter addressed to the Commandant of Police, Bahrein, regarding an attempted robbery at our Quarters last night. Yours faithfully, \ / / * / * * (officer-in -eft arye, l &amp; ICo minun i c ations; Ltd: BAHREIN. /?&gt;v 'C fish &lt;&gt;J fr' P.A. It was on the 14th..The Commandant of Police B a h r e i n. ^ Pear 3ir, 1 have to report that last^ight at about 9.30pm. when everybody was out, theives entered the Telegraph Quarters. r othing was removed as the alarm was raised by my servant soon after their entry. The facts of the case as stated by him are as follows:- Shdrtly after about 9pm., all the servants left the quarters which were then in total darkness. !y servant,who lives in our compound went to his room. About fifteen or twenty minutes later he heard footsteps outside and on looking out saw a man dressed in black walking towards the Quarters. He thought it might have been one of the other servants but his suspicions were roused when he shortly afterwards saw the light in my dining room come on. lie knew I had’nt returned. Shortly after the light was switched on he heard a shrill whistle which was repeated at short intervals. e then saw about four other men rapidly approach our piarters. He suspected that 0 they were theives and being single-handed lie ran for assistance to some huts just outside our compound, where tne other servants livea. They nad also heard the whistling and were running towards the quarters making as much noise as they could apparently. The theives on hearing that an alarm had been raised ich put out the light and dashing down the siairs ran out of the compound by the gate which opens on to the sea front. ky servant then went up to my rooms to see whether anything had been stolen. He found that a teapoy had heen upset in the sitting room but that nothing had been removed. Is it is seldom that all of us are out at the same time, it would appear that this gang of theives were in some manner acq?iainted with our movements on this accasion. our;; faithfully. V)Political Agoncy, Bahrain, the 22nd FohAmny’SS. Dear Faithful ? Many thanks for your letter of Yesterday’s date* In view of tne proclamation issued by the Director of Customs on j&amp;fe February 1933 prohibiting import of dogs into these Islands, I am afraid it could not be possible for your successor to bring his dog with him* ¥oure sincerely. 4^ J*A* £ aiLthful, , Bahrain Radio* 'iPolitical Agency| Behrain. Dated the 22nd April 1933. Dear Mr. Faithful, Perhaps you are aware that the telephone line between P.A*s office and that of yours has been dis connected/^ somewhere. I shall be grateful if you will kindly arrange for its repair. I am very sorry to give you this trouble but trust you won*t mind it knowing that the line serves a very useful purpose at the time of need. Thanking you. Yours sincerely, a.5c J.A. Faithful, Esquire Bahrain Radio.Political Agency, Bdirain Dated the 22nd April 1933 Dear Mr, Faithful, Perhaps you are aware that the telephone line between P.A's office and that of yours has been dis connected^ somewhere, I shall be grateful if you will kindly arrange for its repair. I am very sorry to give 4 you this trouble but trust you won’t mind.it knowing that the line serves a very useful purpose at the time of need. Thanking you. Yours sincerely, Dear lir Maqbul Hossein, I understand the disconnection is in . ^ . the immediate vicinity of the Agency* J.A. Faithful, esquire. jjy effect a temporary repair pro tem. Bahrain Radio Yours sincerely,Imperial &amp; International Communieationa Ltd,, BAHRAIN. i okristmas « New Year Greeting telegrams tt the United Kingdom will he aacepted at thi* Branch from 14th. December 1933 to 6th. January 1934. Charges for the abore telegrams will be Ten Annas per word, the minimum charge for any such telegram being for ten words, i.e. Es 6/4. i &amp; X Vo ' * cations; Ltd: REIN.No. I ^7 The Political -^gcnoy. Bah rain, dated the i&gt;th NoveiZiUer 19o3. To The Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, in H.M.S.FO'jTEY. f ! I Sir, I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter No.20/12, dated the 7th November 1953, received from Ihe Officer-in-charge,Imperial and International Coununications Limited, Bahrain, and request that you will kindly place me in a position to reply it. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant Lieut.Colonel, Political -‘•gent, Bahrain.jjH ^ D»Q» MQ.198 . Sir, H.M.S. “SHO REHAM' at Henjam. 7th December, 1933. in reply to your letter of the 9th November, 1933, (No. 1357) I have the honour to request that you will be gooi enough to reply to the Officer-in-Charge, Bahrain wireless Station, in the following terms /- in H.M.Navy, 'Short Wave' is reserve! for long iistance communications ani its use over moaerate aistances is aiscouragel owing to the interference which may be caused over a wile area. Short Wave communications between H.M. Ships in the Persian Gulf ana Bahrain, would not, therefore, be in Keeping with the principles of Naval Wireless organisation except in emergency - moreover, a shore station using the 'Short Wave' frequencies in use by H.M.Ships in the Gulf would be bound to interfere with the Commander-In-Chief's lines of communication on the station. Your Head Office in London should be advised to approach the Admiralty regarding any contemplated use of short wave with H.M.Ships when they will be given every assistance. Some of the TanKers frequenting the Gulf are fitted with 'Short Wave' and are understood to use a frequency of 8330 Kc/s. 2. For your own information it may be noted that the use of Short Wave between the I.C.C. Stations in the Gulf has already caused some interference to Naval communications and it may be necessary to draw attention to this later on. I have the honour to be, Sir, kNo. i- 1? The Political iigency, Btihrain.dated the//^^ecembcr 1955. w To The Officer-in-ciuirgc, Imperial and International Commimications Ltd., Bahrain. Lear Sir, rrith reference to your letter Bo.20/12,dated the 7th Bovemher 1953, I beg to inform you that I have received the following information from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf:- 'In H.M.Kavy,'Short Wave' is reserved for long distance comiuunications and its use over moderate distances is discouraged o^ing to the interference which may be caused over a wide area. Snort wave communicatione between H.M.bhioe in the Persian Gulf and Bahrain,would not, there fore, be m Jteeping with the principles of Naval «Virelefi 3 Organization except in emergency.horeover a shore station using the 'Short Wave' frequencies in use by R.M.Ships in the Gulf woulu be bound to interfere with the Commander-in-Chiefs lines of coinrriunic tion on the station. Some of the Tankers frequenting the Gulf are fitted with 'Short Wave* and are understood to use a frequency of 8530 Kc/£ . M ^ 2. The Senior Naval Officer suggests t*iat your London Office should be a.dvised to approach the ^Uimirality regarding any contemplated use of Short Wave into II.M.Ships. Yours faithfully, Lieut.Colonel, Pori tic ax ;».gtnt, Bahrain.No. 2-6 tf) I he Secretary to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to ihe Pci it leal -Agent, 10 Bahrain. J^AliTpyt^' and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. Dated.. ember .1933Telegram Enclair* From Mr Bottomley, c/o Manager, Persian Gulf, Karachi. To Political Resident, Buahire. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. Ho 11/475. Dated and received the 20th December J1G33. Handed orer charge Persian Gulf Section to Mr P.E. Bunker to-day. Should like to thank you and Secretary also Political Agents, Bahrain and Muscat, for all your kind support and assistance. * -BOTTOMLEY-Enclair i Telegram From To Ho 1157. Political Resident, Buskire. Itr Bottomlejr, c/o Manager, Persian Gulf, Karachi• Dated the 22nd December 1933. I appreciate your telegram ana we are ▼ery glad to haTe been of assistance. -RESIDENT- /Dear Sir, Our Manager, Mr* P.E.Bunker is expected to visit Bahrain tomorrow the 5th. inst., arriving by the Gulf Mail from Karachi and will be pleased to call on you if convenient in the forenoon* He will be leaving Bahrain by the same boat probably the same evening. Yours faithfully, l £ J CominuniffaH^M; Lid: BAHREIN.B a hr a In 12th. A p r i l The Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, We beg to draw you r attention to the registration of the address ' POLITICAL ' Bahrain, which has not been effected for the year ending 31st. December 1934. D'e shall be obliged if you would kindly arrange to have this carried out at your early convenience. The Registration fee is Rs 20/- per annum. Youra faithfully, Ofre*r-in-charg*, f f * ow+nunication#; IA4. BAHREIN. y* pn /i'i- TELEGRAM G.T.CODE. No. 94. Dated 13th May 1934. From Political, Bahrain. To Resident Steamship VASNA Important * Grateful if you would telegraph hour you wish me to come on board as soon as known. Worth will accompany me. - POLITICAL - V *No# na-ikj-L. Political Agency* Bahrain, the 14th Kay 1934* To The Officer-in-Charge, Imperial and International Conmunications Limited BAHRAIN# Dear Six*, On the morning of the 13th May about 09#15 hours a telegram No*94 addressed to 'Resident Steamship Vasna' and marked important was sent to your Office for despatch* The peon book was signed by f, Ii!*R*F • ,1 2* The telegram had not been received by the S*S*Vasna up to about 11#00 hours on the 14th May, when enquiries were made on board# 3* It ic requested ohat you will kindly make enquiries and inform me of what has happened to this message* Yours faithfully, Lieut-Colonel Political Agent, Bahrain*The Political Agent Bahrain. Bear Sir, With reference to your letter No. 821-16/2 dated 14th. inst., we have to inform you that the message in question was forwarded to Bushireradio as we were not in touch with the S.3. Vasna at the time. Bushireradio states that the message was forwarded by him to the ss /asna at 13.40 hours Local time on the 13th. inst., and acknowledgement of receipt received. Yours faithfully, Officer-in-eharge, I £ I Communications; Ltd: BAHREIN.y So. tSe-fi/i: ^A»8.|S &amp; \ Dated, the 20th May 1934v Dear Colonel Fowle, I enclose a copy of a telegram No. 94 dated the 13th May 1' 4 34 which I sent to the S.S.Vasna for you, and the marginally Letter Lo#321-16/2 dated the 14th riay 193411 noted letters on the from the i olitical Agent. Bahrain, to the 5 Officer-in-Charge, Imperial and Inter- I subject, national Conriunications Limited, Bahrain. | O if' l &gt; I 2 . I should be grateful Letter dated the 16th Ma ; 1934 from the £ Gfficer-in-charge, Imperial and Inter- I if enquiries could be made national Oommunications Limited, Bahrain, 5 to the iolitical Agent, Bahrain. I about this telegram, because, although in this 4 case it concemad only a matter of convenience (over launch and other arrangements), it might easily have been of political Importance. Yours sincerely, A ' ' The Honourable Lieutenant Colonel T.C.y.Fowle,C.B.D., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, a udfib } ^ (&amp;) Bahrain. 2nd June 1934. The Captain H.M.S. Bideford Bahrain. Through: » The Political Agent Bahrain. • Dear Sir, In order to calibrate our Direction-Finding apparatus satisfactorily it is essential that we know accurately the angle made by the plane of one of the aerial loops with the direction of true North. As we have no means at our disposal of obtaining this information we shall be extremely obliged if you would be so kind as to assist us in this matter, if possible before H.M.S.Bideford sails from Bahrain. Thanking you. Yours faithfully, Sd/- W.E.P.Lowe Officer-in-Charge, Imperial and International Commanications Limited. Bahrain.4+u • NO* Political Agency* Bahrain, the 2 nd June 1934# ■“Forwarded to the Officer Commanding, H,M* 3# Bide ford, Off Bahrain with the request that help may kindly be accorded to the In^erial and International Communications Limited* Lieut-Colonel, Political .Agent, Bahrain. 7 ♦Letter dated the 2 nd June 1934 from the Officer-in-Charge, Imperial and International Communications Limited, Bahrain./W» i£f? © i). 0.No. 465-S of 1934 Bushire, 26th May 1934 The Residency Your demi-official letter No.850-16/2 dated the 20th May 1934. The only individual who can pursue the matter further is the one who holds the receipt for the telegram sent i.e. yourself. Lt.-Col.Gordon Loch,I.A., Political Agent Bahrain 'l 1 L -To The Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, We beg to advise you that by a special resolution passed by an Extraordinary General Meeting held on the 23rd. May 1934, the name of this Company has been changed from T Imperial &amp; International Communications Limited 1 to * Cables &amp; tireless Limited.* We would request that all correspondence in future should be addressed to the Officer in Charge, Cables &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain. Yours faithfully, Officer-in-charge, BAHREIN.0 T I c The Public are hereby informed that Daily Letter Telegrams (DLT) to Breat Britain, the Irish Pree State and Forth America will be accepted at the Telegraph Office with immediate effect* ^LT 1 telegrams are charged for at one-third the Pull rate and are subject to a minimum charge for 25 words. The Paid Service indication ’DLL’ must be written before the address. The text of ’DLT’ telegrams must be expressed in Plain language. Figures, commercial marks and abbreviated expressions are allowed but must not exceed one-third the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. after the day of handing in (calculated by calender date in both cases). ’DLT’ telegrams are delivered on the second morningReference No: 8941/34/Sigs. f AIR HEADQUARTERS, BRITISH FORGES IN IRAQ, HINAIDI. /v /' DECEMBER, 1934. Subject:- W/T STATION : BAHREIN. I have to inform you that the Imperial and. International Communications Company’s Station at Bahrein is about to take over the wireless traffic with aircraft flving in the Persian Crulf, and for communication v/ith Shaibah and Sharjah. Airways is being closed down and the wireless apparatus taken into the R.A.F. Rest House. In consequence of this change, messages sent through the Bahrein W/T Station to this Headquarters will be charged for by the wireless company, ana the free service which has been carried out by the Imperial Airways Station will no longer exist. The present station manned by the Imperial /^Air Vice Marshal, w Commanding, British Forces in Iraq. The Political Agen£, BAHREIN.F'' \ ' &gt; ’ ''^UK..’' From the Agent# IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED. tmoxaniittm Imperial Airw#je Ltd T' “ ~ ■ - f ' i H - Wireless Operator IA/56 J54th January 1935* IDi accordance with inatructionf'received from the Manager, 'ear East jea, Cairo as contained his letter to us No. BCHC/JLD/ 527b• 9 and in accordance vr. fi is of your* engagement as set out in the Company's leti.fr . ££65,of the,8th Kovember, 1932, and amended by the Company's XettJ are hereby given one no^cfiff the terminating of your employ- ^47X3 of the 29th August 1933, you nl % ment with the Company* ..'Ti, 4 '§ f On the expiry of yoar notd^you will be repstriated to Basra at the Company's expense any time within two months from the date of this letter after which period any claim in thfc yespect will not be enter tained by the Company, and, in view of the'J»,at during the period of your engagement you have received no leave, ypu will receive a cash payment in lieu of leave at the rate of X4 days per annum* Your House Allowance also terminates one month from the date of th^is letter ang, any property of jj he Company in your possession must be returned after this date* The Company regrets the necessity for dispensing wi and will be pleased to answer any enquiries from pros IV, cc The^Manager, Near East Area, Cairo. The Mhhager, Indian Area, Karachi. i JL f^UZUf fyJ Y AgentsV* INDIAN POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS NOTICE. X’mas and New Year Greeting telegrams. \ From the 14th December 1934 to the 6th January 1935, X’mas and New? Year Greeting telegrams will be accepted at reduced rates with a minimum* charge of ten words per telegram. In such telegrams the indication XLT should be inserted before the address. 2. For X’mas and New Year Greeting teDrrams addressed to Great Britain and Northern Ireland, Gibraltar-and M alta via IRC the charge will be Rs. -£-#• &lt;5'.4'•&lt;* atrt«r»-for ten words or less (including the indication XLT) and four*annas for each additional word. 3. In the case of X’mas and New Year Greeting telegrams addressed to other countries with which the Daily Letter Telegram service is in force except Russia and Irish Free State for which XLT service will not be accepted the rate per word will be the same as for Daily Letter Telegrams subject to a minimum; charge for ten words per telegram including the indication XLT. 4. Xb nvs a n d N^w \Wr4Irwtinu; Inhyi'ams wili—he aeecpted~fof Philippine IfflnHi via T PG — Madras -afr rates which might he ascertained fnnn ■tdcgiaph offices. I. New Delhi, ^ G. V. BEWOOR, fijic 15th November 1934.) Director-General of Posts awl Telegraphs* HGIFPAh.— 2195—10-11-34—1 ( ’,0C0, '(M) DEPARTMENT.BAHREIN. OjU / c y s/Ys^r/s -'/s/, O ' 1 J V ! v 20/7 8th May, yr/ 35, The Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We have received the following telegram from our Manager at Karachi, and shall he very grateful for your kind recommendations in this matter. 'Please make thorough enquiries as to whether if_ 'necessary an Operator with a good knowledge of 'arahic can he engaged locally stop If not are 'there any suitable youths with this knowledge 'you could train as Operators. Yours faithfully, ^3 Q£frfer-in-Charge, Gable &amp; Wireless Ltd. Bahrein. jf- 9 4/e- lie Kia^uu- i I - f!; ? © Ho. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21et May 1955, To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN . Memorandum . I have received a communication from Cable and Wireless Limited requiring information as to whether or not operators with a good knowledge of Arabic are obtainable in Bahrain, or if not whether there are suitable local youths who could be trained as operators. For Lieu tenant | Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain..-V *0. S~S~i^/(rfv . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st May 1935. To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, \ ^ \ ^ .'V St ' .V v. In reply to your letter No.20/7 of the 8th May V 1935 necessary enquiries are being made, and I hope to supoly you with the necessary information shortly. Yours faithfully. tk For Lieutenant,’/ Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain.PRINTED IN ENGLAND. OCT. 1934. •47 ® (2/23-16). €, /r/yrr ///'/'/'//-y-y . (incorporated in England) URGENT. The hearer of this letter, Nasir Ihn Ahmed, our water-man for many years, reports that he has been forbidden to supply us with water from Ruffa, with immediate effect. As this particular water has been utilised by the members of our Staff and their families solely for drinking purposes for the past 15 years or so, we feel this sudden stoppage a great inconvenience to all of us* We therefore beg you will kindly continue to allow us the privilege we have enjoyed for so many years of procuring our drinking water from Ruffa. Thanking you* Yours faithfully, Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd, Bahrein.Respected Sir, With profound honour , 1 beg, hurnbl^ to inform „ o- ! ;}aa'; it is understood from the manager of Witeless 2c Cables Ltd. that ^our honourable person should certify that I hnow Arabic ans English to accept me as a e- •mri as a candidate for Arabic wireless cp- ^ ration in ;h ir o' ice. I am attaching hereto n: application addressed to the manager for pour hind perusal, and to e offered wits, the cer tificate to th- Wireiess office. Appologizing humbly , I beg to remain, respected Sir , Add ress: c/^ KanooNo. IXkl^ of 1354 Office of the '“■dviser to the Ooverment, Bahrain hated, ^&gt;afar May 29, 25. 1354 1935. Reference your memorandum No.(334-16/2 dated 21st 'ay 1935. enquiring about a Y9ung man to v/ork at the tireless -atation. n ill you please inform me wh t would be the conditions of service, pay and pros pects etc. adviser to the Government. VTOGMT. ■anir»w/ No|946-16/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 30th May 1936, To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable and wireless Limited, Bagrain . m Dear Bir, l ^ith reference to your letter No 1 20/7 dat.ed the 8th May 1936, will you please supply the follow ing details for the information of the Bahrain Government i- 1. What would be the conditions of service? 2. what would be the pey, that is, the minimum and maximum? 3. would there be any contract of terms of service? 4. whet would be the prospects of a suitable candidate? fours faithfully. Lieutenant, for Officiating Political Agent,Bahrain. mJ © No 1949-16/2. political Agency^ Bahraini the 30th May 1936. To The officer-in-Charge| Cable aid wireless Limited, Bahrain. Dear sir, /p With reference to your letter No*20/10 dated 26th May 1936, I beg to inform you that it is in accordance with the orders of the Bahrain Government that the supply of r _ ' water from Huffa has been limited to certain persons. There is, however, another well or spring la the vicinity of Huffa, and you should mace your bv/n arrangements to obtain your supply from there if you wish to do so. Yours faithfully. A Lieutenant, for Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain.Koi1027-16/1 political Agency, Bahrain, the 8th June 1935* The Officer-in-Charge, Cable and wireless Limited, Bahrain. Dear air with reference to the correspondence ending with my letter xfo#946-16/2 dated the 30th May 1936, I beg to inform you thao 1 nave as&amp;ed the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to produce suitable youths for training, and this }k is doing, that is, youths who know both Arabic and English. A 2# I forward also the application of Jamil Aziz Raphael# He knows both mglish and A rabic# His suitability for the work should be ascertained from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government# Yours faithfully, /LAb^ Lieutenant, for officiating political Agent, BahrainWith Reference to your letters No 946-16/2 dated 30th May 1935 and No T027-I6/I dated 8th June 1935, the Bahrein Government may kindly he informed that the suitable candidate for training would receive Rs 40/- per mensem on engagement as Probationer until he is able to operate at a speed of 15 words per minute. He will then receive Rs 70/- per mensem with annual increments of Rs 10/- per month subject to his work and conduct being satisfactory. Before he is promoted beyond Rs 100/- per mensem, he must pass a general efficiency test in operating at 25 words per minute, necessary adjustments of apparatus used in Bahrein Wireless Station, a good knowledge of International and Company’s regulations and elementary knowledge of electricity. On passing this examination, the Operator will be promoted to Rs 105/- per mensem, with yearly increments of Rs 5/- per mensem up to Rs 180/- subject to work and conduct continuing satisfactory in every way. We shall recommended so as now be pleased to interview the candidates to enable us to select the most suitable youth. Yours faithfully, a? 9^* Offitier-i n-Charge, Cable Wireless Ltd. Bahrein.UBCT5NT» Not 1149-16/2 political Agency, Bahrain, the 4th July 1935* Bie Adviser to the Bahrain Government Bahrain* 1 Memorandum* Reference your memorandum Hoi224/23 dated the 29th May 1936* fhe officer-in-Charge, Cable and wireless Limited, states that the candidate selected for training will receive fe*40/- a month on engagement as probationer until he is able to operate at a speed of 16 words a minute* He will then receive Rs*70/- a month with annual increments of Rs*10/- a month subject to his work and conduct being satisfactory* Before he is promoted beyond Rs*100/- a month he will have to pass a general efficiency test in operating at 25 words a minute, necessary adjustments of apparatus used in the Cable and wireless office at Bahrain, a good knowledge of International and company !s regulations and an elementary knowledge of electricity, cn passing this examination, the (Jperato: will be promoted to Rs*106/- a month, v/ith annual increments of Ps.6/* ^ a month up to Rs*180/-, subject to his work and conduct continuing t* be satisfactory in every way* 3* fhe Officer-in-Charge, Cable and wireless Limited, will be pleased to interview the candidates recornended by you to enable him to select the most suitable youths* Lieutenant, for Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain.Noi1150/16/2 Political Agenfcy, Bahrain, the 4th July 1935* rhe officer-in-Charge, Cable and wireless Limited, Bahrain Dear air, I forward an application dated the 3rd July 1935 from Lzra Hiskeil ;£eloof» His suitability for the work should be ascertained ffrom the Adviser to the Bahrain Government# Yours faithfully Lieutenant for Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain#PRINTED IN ENGLAND. OCT. 1034. (2/23-16). /' s//ru m (incorporated in England) BAHRAIN November I5th Dear Please excuse me troubling you so soon * but the attached appears to be a case of excessive charging of visitors to Bahrein* I admit this Office should have made better arrangements, which I hope to do in the future. Would you please be so kind as to let me know • i&lt;ff Rs 374 is a fair charge for the number of trips made the owner Ali Bin Hal Alla states he is due Rs 385. Thanking you, Tours sincerely l-K. it.CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD (Incorporated in England). NOTICE X^AS AND NE/v YE4R GREETINGS T.-X^GR^Mo# Fron the ll|th December 195§ to 6th January 19 ? 6 * X’mas and New Year Greetings telegrams \irill be accepted at reduced rates Via IRC for Great Britain and Northern Ireland, Irish Free State and Germany at Rs 0-10-0 per word with a minimum charge of ton words per telegram* In such telegrams, the indication XLT should be inserted before the address which /ill ba charged for. In the case of X f ma8 and New Year Greetings telegrams addressed to Other Countries with which the Daily Letter Telegram service is in force, such as United States of America, Canada, Central America, West Indies etc., the rate oar word will be the same as for Daily Letter Telegrams subject to a minimum charge for ten words per telegram* These Greetings telegrams will be sent out for delivery in pictorial forms and envelopes* ^ &lt;dlavjJ C | t Bahrein, Of f i c er- in-Claar ge * The 12th December 19^5*D.o/io.^ib/a 30th January 1^36• ith r^fururiCG to your convurbation with me on the 14th January 1^3t&gt; arising out oi the uiiiiculty over the delivery ox a telegram reporting the arrival oi the Vincents at Ohaibaix on the 13th Hovember 1933 1 Colonel Loch understands that your ruxes permit oi the delivery ox telegrame to a ierash, but that you are willing to have teie 0 n£m8 &gt; which are to be delivered out oi O^iice hours ( i.e* between 01*30 hours one day and 06*00 hours the next) entered in a peon book, which will be handed with the teiegmm by your peon to the xerush to whom he gives the telegrams i’he Agency ferash will thumb mark or sign your receipt and ret uni it to your peon* The peon book will be initialed by the Agency Clerk on receipt oi the telegram from the Agency iorash and the book will them be returned to you. I m sending two peon books. »• Colonel Loch asks me to thank you lor yo’ur help in making this arrangement, which will obviate your peon having to search ior someone to ^hom to hond the telegram and also prevent delays in the passing ox telegrams to an Agency Clerk by the Agency ferash. Yours sincerely,Printed in England. Oct., 1985. (450 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) NO. URGENT. BAHRAIN. July 1st 1936. To:- The rolitical Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Will you please obtain a permit for my Company to continue drawing drinking v;ater for the otaff from nuPPA wells. Ahmed who resides at tiuffa refuses to allow him to draw drinking v/ater from there although we have been doing so for over fifteen years. him to kindly allow the Waterman Nasir bin Ahmed to draw one donkey load or 5 skins daily. The waterman states he received no written reply but was told the well belonged to ohaikh Hamad and we must get his permission first. the children of the otaff and now Mr Faithful hage been ill with dysentery, and v/e have traced the probable cause to our waterman getting water from another v/ell after the oheihk at Kuffa refused to allow him to draw v/ater from nuffa. Could this matter please be treated as urgent &amp; a permit obtained as soon as possible. Our Waterman states that oheikh Khalifah bin I v/rote to Jheikh bin Ahmed yesterday asking May I be allowed to point out that some of Thanking you. xours faithfully. Officer in Charge, Bahrain Branch.No. 1724-16/2. Political Agency, Bahrain the 2nd July 1936 vis V*? To The Officer in Charge, Cable and Wireless Liicited, Bahrain. m Dear 3ir, In reply to your letter No. 20/3 dated the 1st July 1936, I enclose a copy of this Agency letter No. 9*19-16/2 dated the 30th ?. r ay 1936* ' f''' Yours faithfully, ; Captain, Officiating Political Agent, \ Bahrain. ’b' _cNo.2862-16/2. Political Agency, Bahrain the 18th November 1936 To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to draw your attention to the inconvenience that is being caused by what is, I understand, a practice of your company, namely the telephoning through of long wireless messages to the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. This has often caused minor delays, and on the present occasion this Agency was prevented between the hours of 12 noon and 1 p.m. from making an urgent enquiry about Flying Boat K 4684 (vide telegram No. 1002 dated the 14th November 1936 from Ges 7 ), as messages were being telephoned through to the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. 2. However important the Company may deem these messages to be, they are in fact on no preferential footing to that of other subscribers on the exchange; end I would request that if messages are to be telephoned to them during normal office hours, they should be only short ones. 3 . I would direct your attention to the fact that the Company have a continual service of motor vehicles between Manamah and their camp. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain.Printed in England. Oct., 1086. (460 pads.) a/-/afi IN REPLY REFER no 20/14 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) BAHRAIN. November 20th 1936 • To:- The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter 28)52-16/2 dated 18th November 1936. We regret you were unable to get through on the telephone to the Telegraph Office the other day to make an enquiry of an Urgent nature due to our being engaged with the Bahrain Petroleum Company. To avoid such delays in future we have asked the State Engineer to inform the Telephone Exchange Operators, when we are engaged and the Agency require us Urgently, he should cut in and inform us to this effect. We hope this will avoid a recurrence in future. Yours faithfully. Officer in Charge, Bahrain Branch.No. 2878-16/2. folltioal Agency, Bahrain the 21st November 1936. To The Officer- in-Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain# Dear L^r, V ■ / Reference your letter No# 20/14 of November 20th, 1936. I am greatly obliged to you for making this arrangement with the State Engineer, and will endeavour to use the privilege of cutting in as sparingly as possible. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain. A l ; v /■ &lt; a--;Printed in England. Oet., 1985. (400 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO no 10/ 43. P'2-0 • tt/ (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Bahrain^ &lt; oV&lt;uA^ l\ \jju ****tfc' »7/*. 5 ©nt, , r\\ March 16 th 1937. I To:- The Political Agent, Bahrain. \ Dear Sir, On account of^your telegrams being sent without prepayment, we are unable to give Cash Receipts for each message; but give instead a receipt which is crossed with the words M Not for Cash n • 2. We understand the above receipt does not give you a clearance for your accounts as your telegram Bill is split up on receipt into different sections of accounts. 3. We can help, if you desire by giving you separate receipts for the totals of each section of your accounts. 4 . Our Head Office instructions are explicit and must be followed, so we very much regret our inability to give you seperate Cash receipts for your telegrams unless (Bash is tendered at the time of sending your telegrams. Yours faithfully. Officer in Charge, Bahrain Branch*for Political Agent, Bahrain No. 701-16/2 Politics! Agency, Bahrain, the 27th T arch 1937 To he Cfficer In Charge Cable rmd 'irclens I ini tec Bahrsin letter No. 10/43 dated the 16th arch 1937, would you rlease grant separate receipts for the total sun: of each section, that is to say one for Government and the other for non-Government accounts. Yours faithfullyPrinted in England. Oct.. 1985. (450 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO NO /■ 2/-/Qfi (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) ■y§?s7*?rd, March. 25th 1937 • Bahrain, I have receivea the attached telegram from Mr Humphrey in Karachi* My family are due to leave Bahrain on the 5th April when I see no reason why the Penfolds cannot move into my house on the 6 th* Would you he so very kind as to allow the Pendolds to stay with you until that date* Yojirs sihcerely, fO I w ^ fa ij. H *. o^oD.O.Ko. 1504 %• I Di ted the 6 th July 1537* Dear Penfold, I do not vy&amp;nt to make an official complaint but X have neard from the Officer Comm: nding H•)!«£« Deptford that he had a certain aniount of difficulty in passing messages aduressed to myself and to the Resident in the Persian Gulf on the evening of Saturday, the 3rd July* I gather that your operators were not anxious to continue to work and were anxious to know whether the messages from the Officer Commanding Deptford were of extreme importance, and also stated that they wanted to knock off for their supper* The messages that were being passed were of great import, nee and I should be iratefui to know if it would be possible for arrangements to be a de to take imp ortant political messages at any time*Printed in England. Oct., 1986. (460 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO NO S* (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Hie normal hours of 'this station are Sam to Spm daily and we are only staffed for this period* If requested, however&gt; arrangements are made to perform extra services* In this case the operator received a request to remain open ten minutes before closing time and informed me immediately but there was not time to arrange for reliefs. He admits only having told the Deptford 'Will to^lhis effect my ° #C# *° arrange to keep open ' or words The operators on at closing time have already performed seven hours continuous duty so that in the event of extra services it is desirable that reliefs should be provided. With our present system of working a minimum of two operators have to be found; one for the Receivers at the new station and the other to attend transmitters at the old station* For this reason I should appreciate it if you could give as much notice as possible on these occasions* I cannot trace any other difficulty or delay in handling the messages in question; I gather that our operator was waiting until they were ready for transmission and was only too glad to get clear* I trust that this is only a case of unnecessary remakks by our operator against which practice the man in question has been warned. If there is anything more serious I shall be only too glad to go further into this complaint•D.O. No. 1526 The 8th July 1937. \&lt;Z Your letter 7th July. Whenever possible notice will be given but it is difficult ( a) to remember th#t a wireless station closes at 8 p.m* and (b) to foretell a crisis. Thank you for the action that you have taken in this matter. I expect that it was as you suggest a matter of unnecessary talk. I do not wish any further action to be taken. Yours sincerely, • / ^ • ••• .'■ Printed in England. Oct., 1985. (450 pads.) 2 /-/ IN REPLY REFER TO (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 201 Bahrain 22nd November 1957 To The Political Agent Bahrain• Dear Sir, We beg to advise you that our Bushire Radio Station (VTP) has been closed from this date. yours faithfully. Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd; Bahrain•BAHRAIN &lt;o 25 th November* 1957 To Tbe Political Agent l Bahrain. Sir, We beg to bring to your notice±hsti that yesterday morning whilst trying to come ashore from the S S Varela, we were held up at the gangway by the local police who in a rude way and by laying hands on us, demanded our passes. Mr Jalaluddin had already left the ship ; and we were in a quandary as to what to dc^ when fortunately another policeman came who seemed a sensible fellow and allowed us to leave. As helk passes are to be surrendered on the gangway at the time of boarding a ship, we fail to understand why we were subjected to this rudeness and annoyance by the police demanding passes when none can, or axpastad are expected to be produced. to the launch but was prevented from doing so by the policeman on the gangway. He (Mr Coutinho) approached Mr Jalaluddin, the passport officer, who sent one of his assistants to inform the poilceman that all was in order. Despite this, it appears very strange that this same policeman was one of those that held Previous to this Mr Coutinho had occasion to go down&lt;s&gt; l2 &gt; V »1 us up. We appeal y to you Sir, to give this matter your kind consideration and approach the police authorities to take necessary action against those concerned for harassing us. Thanking you We beg to remain Sir, your most obedient Servants E.R.Franco J.Coutinho Gable &amp; Wireless Ltd; Bahrain.(S The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to ; — The Adviser to the Bahrain Government Bahrain ami lias the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document {*) for information nn^ snc v potion as may be desirabje. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 3 0 (u /\/crv • Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Copy of letter from I essrs E.R. ranco &amp; J. Coutinho of Cable &amp; iireles • to the Political Agent,Bahrain^ Subject. Alleged rudeness of Bahrain Police.No. / f (, of 1356 Office of the adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 9th Shawwal, 1356 Deer. 12, 1937. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Memorandum. k t’c ( 4 ) y Reference your ho. 2414-16/2 dated 30th November 1937. I have enquired into the complaint from Messrs. Branco and Covtinho both from the Police and the Passport Officer and I can find no ground for complaint. Ship passes of passengers are ins pected on embarking by the Police and steamer passes are taken at the gangway by the Police. The two men in question were not recognised by the Police as being local residents and were asKed on leaving whether they had surrendered their passes. Bahrain. adviser to tne Government. R.Z.1 ao4&gt; CABLE AND V/IRELESS LTD (Incorporatsd in England) NOTICE XMAS AND NS^ YEAR GREETINGS TSLSGRAMS Prom The December 1957 to the 6th January 1958* Xmaa and New Year Greetings Telegrams will be accepted at reduced rates with a minimum charge of TEN words per telegram* In such telegrams the indication XLT should be inserted before the address, which will be charged for* 2* For Xmas and New Year Greetings Telegrams addressed to Great Britain and Northern Ireland and Irish Free State and Germany, via IRC, the charge will be Rs 6~i|-0 for ten words or less and ten annas for each additional word. 5* The rates for Xlts to U.S.A. are from Rs 8-12-0 to Rs 1 O- 5 -O per ten words or less according to zone siixtxihainlitafcx of Destination. [(.« In the case of Xmas and New Year Greetings telegrams addressed to wtta-ttfc other countries with which the Daily Letter telegrams service is in force, the rate per word will be the same as for Daily Letter Telegrams, subject to a minimum charge for ten words per telegram. Bahrain The 15 th December 1957* Off icer-inrCharge, Bahrain branch.TTl © GAB L?E. AND r-A I ri .•X (incorporated in enqland) / 15 ’i. JUh ?eb.'-.;ary YJ? 33... of our Head Office, if there is any Workmen’s Act in force in Bahrain. the information Oomoens ition Yours faithfully. Officer -in -Charge, Bahrain Branch.Ho. / / o^'/JTl5/i6i; Political Agency, Batirain, Uic ii^ra Pcbi*uc;ry f To The Offi cc r-in-Charge , Cable and Wire lees Limited, Bahrain. Bear Sir, With reference to your letter Ho.2/154 dated the 7th February 1^33 I am to inform you that no Worionen’s Compensation Act is formally in force in Bahrain. fours faithfully for Political Agent, BahrainPrinted in England. Oct., 198-5. (460 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO NO 1.7/12 . (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Bahrain. 2/-/ac. I have to advise that the Jask Branch of this Company is now closed. Traffic for Jask will circulate via Bushire and thence by Iranian Radio. ✓ Yours faithfully. n 01 . ' A ' r l c^o wv Officer-in-Charge, Bahrain Branch .mam Printed in England. Oct., 1985. (450 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO no 15/5*9. The Political A^ent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Bahrain 22 nd October 1953• \)* %Z\U) Telegram No. GBS 25 dated 1 (p. / 10.1938 /t- From Oenstaff India to Political Bahrain ) r \ h.iv' Farther to our letter No. 13/38 of 16th instant^ nbovementioned telegram, copy attached, was also received via RAF Shaibah Radio. Will you please advise us if this was on Aero nautical Service. 'V Yours faithfully, V' / oC' l (JtJ.deNo. lU^ -33/3. « r.' Pclitical Agency, Bahrain, the 24th October 1938• To The Office r~in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Bahrain. r Dear Sir, M 4 /ff f Reference your letters Nes. 13/38 and 13/39 dated the 16th and 22nd October 1938 respectively; the reply to the former is in the affirmative and to the latter in the negative. 2 . I request, however, that in future the originators of such telegrams may be approached for information of this nature. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain. f'PRINTED IN ENGLAND. OCT. 1034. X-4 / vXfy) *^2/23-16). V/VW' ////&lt;, /jY'f/'.JJ (incorporated in England) Bahrain W/. / O 58. The Political Agent, Bahrain* Dear Sir, Farther to our letter No* 15/59 o; ^ 22nd instant, telegram* No«. 0E3 25/1 and 3E3 2 of 18th October and Ko. 3E3 3 of 20tb October, copies attached, were also received via RAF Shaibah Radio. Will you please advise us if these were on Aeronautical Service. Yours faithfully. cerAn-Charg** si i tcIpsk L ■■ £» (skffiU &amp;No. 1711-33/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st November 1938 To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Bahrain. / fS V V Bear Sir, ? s r t 0 With reference to your letter No. 13/40 dated the 31st October 1938, would you please refer to paragraph 2 of my letter No. 1662-33/3 dated the 24th October 1938? 2. The enclosures are returned herewith. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.Printed in nd. Jan., 1936. (80 pads.) * ^ ^ (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Bahrain MEMORANDUM. The Politics! Agent, Bahrain• If 21 st .April 1939* llll* We beg to advise that Buscat Kar achi Cable has been restored and traffic can be accepted for Muscat via Aden- ihi •/'-V Bombay-Karachi. The restoration of Bu shire-Muscat Cable is expected shortly. 2/-50CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED Great Britain, Eire and Germany has been instituted in place of the DLT Service now in force. Night Letter Telegrams are subject to the following conditions:- Rates* Annas ten per word. Plain language, according to rules for Deferred jt± telegrams but with a minimum of 25 words. Delivery. On the morning after the day of booking. This comes in force from 4 st May 1539* Yours faithfully, J (T%m ’ m , Call* &amp; ,&gt;i E*&lt;i.Printed in England. Jan., 1986. (80 pads.) IN REPLY REFER TO 2 / //ebeJeJA (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) MEMORANDU The Political Bahrain• t/et/ Bahrain. 'Zi&lt;b April 19.59 • // CM Further to our Memorandum dated 2Tjv, instant, we beg to advise that Bushire-Muscat Gable has been restored aic traffic for Muscat will circulate by the normal route. lA'' A LA/' Ua If U- / e Pit ju . S //1 OTf\&lt;xr-™-(Jha'rQ*- &lt;l„hU &lt;fe Wirdess Ltd . Hahrnr&gt; th. • r v&gt;7«Printed in England. Jan., 19S6. (80 pods.) IN REPLY REFER TO No MEMORANDUM. Political Agent, Bahrain. We beg to advise that from this date charge of the Bahrain Branch, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd, has been transferred from Mr. N.L. Penfold to Mr. C. E. Gahan.Telegram:- G.T.C 7 a 6 xS) From:- To:- Ko: Britconsul Shiraz. Britconsul Bushire. Political Bahrain. 1309. Dated and received 1st August 1939. Cable and Wireless report complete interruption between Muscat and Karachi and Bushire. Umportant messages will be sent by R.A.F Wireless. - Political - % &amp; ' »/«r/^Copy of telegram from Political Agent, Muscat to the Political Agent, Bahrain. / 0-' 'Request Bahrain radio be asked expedite official telegrams for me'• No. 1559. Political Agency, Bahrain the 4th September 1939. Copy forwarded to the Of fleer-in-Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain, for favour of compliance. L ^for Political Agent, Bahrain. %No* 1685*»33/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th September 1939* 0 t LS-J All private radio telegrams to ships at sea from the Bahrain Wireless Station are prohibited. a for Political Agent,Bahrain* Copy forwarded toi- 1* Messrs* Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd*, Bahrain. 2* The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain* 3* Messrs* Gray, Mackenzie A Co* Ltd*, Bahrain* 4* Messrs* Petroleum Concessions Ltd*, Bahrain* 5* The Eastern Bank Ltd*, Bahrain* 6. The California Arabian Standard Oil Co., Bahrain. 7* The President, Bahrain Merchants Association, Bahrain.n^\ is / Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, LONDON, E.C. 3. TELEGRAPH IC ADDRESS. GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSRE H. AM AR AH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (fob. BANOAR-Sr,,, , u siTT^e~x BUNDER-ABBAS. LI NG AH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO. Dear u«&gt;e» ^ [ *1 -7 StP* ^ V J . eigiil^ri.an, Bahr-e in, 26th Sept ember ,193 9 . @&gt; I give below context of a letter we have received from the Commander of the SS.'BhRPETA' now in port, together with a list showing the calls made by the Bahrein Radio to the 'BARPETA' s ”1 wish to bring to your notice the fact that the Bahrein Radio Station has been constantly calling this steamer by her international call sign since last Thursday. This is entirely wrong and lets both other steamers and wireless stations know that this vessel is in the vicinity. I would be obliged if you would take this matter up with the authorities concerned.^ I have asked Gahan of Cable and Wireless Ltd., if he will enquire into this and let me know, but in the meantime, I consider it advisable that you should be au fait with what has BAHREIN.Printed in England. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Bahrain / viam. , 7th November 1 939• The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, A telegram wqs tendered by the Warship 'Indus' on the Uth instant which was undercharged by Rs 5/15/-. this amount and would be thankful if you could arrange to settle the undercharge. As the ship has left, we are unable to collect Bahrain Branch.No. 1971-33/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 15th November 193S To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, ^ Please refer to your letter No. T 16/14 dated the 7th November 1939. 2. I suggest you ask the Clerk-in-Charge of the Naval Base at Jufair to arrange to collect the amount. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.UKTelegram - GTC From - Political, Bahrai] To - Political, Muscat No. _ 260 Dated the 12th November 1939. Your telegram No. 2000 of 11th November. Regret impossible. Suggest Indian Government be asked for special facilities. I shall probably do so for Bahrain soon. - POLITICAL -II // M N 0 TICE. It is notified for ite information of the general Public that, in accordance with the British Administration^ notice, we regret that XLT and GTQ telegrams to and from Great Britain cannot be accepted during the forthcoming Christmas and New Year greetings period. Copies The The The The The The The The The Officer-in-charge, Bahrain Branch. forwarded to:- ?olit!cal Agent, Bahrain. Adviser, Government of Bahrain. Station Superintendent, N.A.C.Service. Resident manager, Bahrain Petroleum Co. Ltd. Resident Manager, California Arabian Std. oil Co. Manager, Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. Manager, Petroleum Concessions Ltd. Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. Manager, Eastern Bank Ltd. II IV t By j ^'a53 Prom the December I 939 to the 6 th January 19^0, Christmas and New Year greetings telegrams will be accepted / to all countffes admitting Letter telegrams except the United Kingdom of GBeat Britain and Northern Ireland, The rates for these greetings telegrams will be at one third of full rate per word with a minimum charge for ten words per telegram. The prefix XLT should be inserted before the address and will be charged for* The minimum charges for these greetings telegrams to the United States of America will be from Rs 8/12 to Rs I 0/5 per telegram according to the zone of destination. Offioer-in-Charge, Bahrain Branch* dCABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED Telegrams originating in or destined for Bahrain or N 0 T I C 1 i.' IS*' Muaeat will only be accepted for transmission or delivered to addressees if they are written in plain English, French or Spanish. Telegrams in code or cipher will not be accepted. Code addresses or signatures are also inadmissible. This does not apply to British Government State telegrams. Officer-in-charge, Bahrain Branch.ihbhhhhhhhbihhmhhbu^hhi Printed in England. Jan., 1936. (80 rads.) IN REPLY REFER TO No. 2/-50 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Bahrain MEMORANDUM. 1st P* ce^ib#»r 1939 3? T From of Pe comber tolegrains between Sfc/udi Arabia and Bahrain are allowed in Arabic Language. P-A. tx CLf.i K Of f i ce r-in -Glvirge, ’a nrn in Pranch.Printed in England. Sept. 1939. (222 pads). IN REPL~^^FER TO No. MEMORANDUM. 2/-50 2- CABLE AND WIRE LESS-LIMITED.- (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) .mmmt branch, 26th May 1940 G I B C U L A B UNTIL FURTHER NOTICE NO TELEGRAMS FOB BELGIUM OR IIOLL/aO OR LU&gt;Li.l3JBG WILL BE ACCEPTED. THE a\HRAlN PETROLEUM Go. THE POLITICAL AGENT Tir; c.*Li:vO:ari,\ std. oil go. OlAClcer-ln-Charge, Bahrain Branch. GRAY M/»OKT!TZIE &amp; CoPrinted in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO 4th November 1940* no 15/15 • r rhe Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, The Bahrain-Bushire Cahle having been restored today all Government Traffic will now be forwarded 'this route. Yours faithfully Office f^in-Gharge, Bahrain Branch.CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD i. &gt; CIHQUIAR Refce 15/24 » The Political Agent# The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf# The Air Liaison Officer# The British Overseas Airways Corpn. Bahrain 27th December 1940# We hereby inform you that the Gable between Bushire and Muscat is interrupted and that traffic for India will now circulate by the Wifeless link with Muscat# Offi ce r-in-Cha rge, Bahrain Branch# /•vPRINTED IN ENGLAND C.\ 8 L,E/nd VVIREL (MID-EAST) Ltd? (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) Karachi &gt;4 IN REPLY REFER TO 152/1 2 8 th .L5ril 1941. The Political Agent, Bahrain* 8 ear 3 ir, ;j 0 have to advise you 'by Gahle and Wireless Li ;i ued in K carried on 'by Gable and Wireless that the 'business conducted arachi will he, in future, Lid-last) Li ;ii ted* The branches in the Gulf viz Muscat, Bahrain, bill’s ^riilfbe under^he^ administrative control of Karachi ac heretofore. 4 in future therefore all connamioatlona.ohouia be addreoaed to the Hvioional Manager, *• * and (irelesa (Kid-.iast) Limited Karach,. C Yours faithfully, I)ivi - ional Manage , ■ ian Gulf,Printed in England. 1- 2-7 Telephone No. SOM IN REPLY REFER TO No. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, he have to advise you that, owing to an interruption in the Karachi Muscat cable, telegrams^ from Bahrain can only he disposed of via Aden/Bahrain Wireless, except telegrams for Iraq and those intended for Iran, which will follow the normal cable route* Yours faithfully, Off i ce r- in~t;ha rge, Bahrain Branch.Printed in iingland. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 13th. September., 1941 The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, Oua? Divisional Manager in Karachi has wired me the accompanying Service Message for our office in Bushire, with the request that you should deliver it by Mail in your Official Bag. Will you kindly let me know if this is possible in order that I might reply to Karachi that it has been disposed of via Official Channels. Yours faithfully, Telephone No. SOM IN REPLY REFER TO No. IJ6/Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED V (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Telephone No. SOM IN REPLY REFER TO No MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 17 th# Septeiaher 1941 The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, We wish to thank you for forwarding our Message NB4. from our Divisional Manager in Karachi to Bushire. Two further messages have arrived from Karachi requesting you to forward them 'by the same route in your Official Bag. I attach these and v/o^uld he greatly obliged if you could have them delivered to our Office in Bushire. Yours faithfully, Officer in Charge.V No. I$( c f / Th« Political Agent. Bahrain, Presents his compliments to The Secretary to the Hoi^ble the Political Itesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. for favour ’of' doliv*^ to^ G^ie de ^a tl ^&amp; r t^. ) t Bushire.Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. in reply refer to 28‘tJi# September* 1941 fU- No : The Political Agent, BAHRAIN# Dear Sir, I enclose two Service Messages with the request from our Divisional Manager in Karachi that you would be kind enough to forward them to our Branch in Bushire in your Offical Agency Postbag. With anticipated thanks. Yours faithfully, ^ Officer in Charge.No.' 1981-33/3 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to •phe Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident i^ the Persian Gulf, lushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) * for favour of delivery to the Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bushire The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated ^I^raber, 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : This Agency Printed Letter No.1819 dated 18th September, 1941. Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject Copies of Cable &amp; /ireleas | service Tessages, service messages - a BHN BUS 22 and HB15/BS A IXI/KS of 28th September, 1941. Copy to the C'ficer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; 7/ ire less Ltd •, &amp;ahra in, f r information, with reference to his letter dated 28-9-1941.Printed in England. ) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) ^/3 MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN. PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO No The political Agent, Bahrain D#*** sir, r« b«g to inf or® you that 'Xllf* Christcaas and flow Yo*r ai^^tingo TWlOgram* will bo »coopted frm today. words 1 » ton at KLT rata, including tbo prefix *XUf* § which aiust be inserted ns the first word of the address. ire loss JJjnlted, anticipating a heavy volume of messages during the eo&amp;lng Christmas and flew Year season and taking into account tbs nations! needs as In each ease the minimum number of 0 xirgeuble Sued Telegrams will be accepted fort mmicik mnwavA TAfl lAlfYIKA CANADA The other countries do not admit this class of Sir Edward Wilshaw K.C.Y.O, chairman of Cable{ 2 ) rog^rcis fc®jp^dlo ®®ks for XJtw co &gt; jo ^ ui &gt;n of the public by bending in greeting saeeeagee early and If gMcible not la tor then the fifth of BMCMbor* It is nocoessr^ to fix tbio relatively e^rly filing date so «s to ensure so fsr as possible that all telegram# are delivered by obristoae or the He* 'ear aa the ease way be. mm would appreciate your co-operation in tide connection# Yours faithfully# Off ic«r-in-Charge # nr &amp; in firnch#Printed in England. Sept, if** (4,399 pads;. ABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. V-228 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) SERVICE TELEGRAM. YOU MAY KEEP THEM FOR FUTURE REFERENCES. %Uc lU(. c &amp; w.E F M TELEGRAMS It is proposed to introduce a special class of telegrams; E F M; between Bahrain on one side and Empirecountries, Egypt and Sudan on the other for telegrams between His Majestys Army and air Force ( including Nurses ) and their families and rela tives, from Naval personnel to fcheir relatives in overseas Empire countries or from personnel of Merchant Navy to their families in the bOKteward side only. The conditions are as follows;- 1, Indicater E F M before address, 2, If addressed to members of his *ajesty«s forces, address must include:• A. Army or Air Force number if any, B. Hank of addressee, C. Name. D. Squadren, Battery, Company or other section of the Unit, E. Army or Air Force Unit (including the words ,f R A F u in the latter case). The words n British Expeditionery force n or the place or country of destination if not serving with the Expeditionery force, J. Registered abbreviated addresses are not permitted as address or signature , i|.. The text should be in plain English Language* No code words are allowed, 5 , The name of the sender must be his surname, 6, no special classes such as Urgent, Deferred etc are admitted, 7, No special facilities such as Rp, Tms, are allowed, 8, these telegrams will be subject to censorship as usual. Standard texts will be used for all countries except India who do not admit them. A list of standard Texts and Copy of Head Office Service Message t/k February * lj.1 containing the instructions were forwarded with our letter No 166/7 of 23 ,6,^1 as instructed in T/k, the sender will be allowed to use maximam of three numbered texts in any one telegran, RATES The rates will be as follows*- 1, India, not admitting standard texts, annas per word minimum six words . the address and the indicator E F M are not charged for, 2, Other Countries. Admitting Standard texts, Rs 1.11 per telegram which include charge for the Indicator E F M, the address, numbered texts (maximum three) and the signature wtich should be his surname, for purpose of accounts and abstracts each such message will be considered equivalent of six words at EFF rate, in transmission the chargeable and the actual words of the message should be shewn in fehe preamble with a stroke between them e,g, A message contains six words in address including the indicator E F M , three numbered texts of standard ps. and one signature, the words should be shewn as A message contains six words in address including the indicator E F , seven words plain in the text ( for Messages to India ) and one signature, the number of words should be shewn as Q/1 k*A. CORRESPONDENCE LETTER RECEIVED MAXT THINKS. LETTERS RECEIVED MA.NY THANKS. TELEGRAMS RECEIVED MANY THANKS. PARCEL RECEIVED MANY THANKS. PARCELS RECEIVED MANY THANKS. LETTERS AND PARCELS RECEIVED MANY THANKS. LETTER AND TELEGRAM RECEIVED MANY THANKS. TELEGRAM AND PARCELS RECEIVED MANY THANKS. LETTERS SENT. PARCELS SENT. LETTERS AND FARCE 13 SENT. MANY THANKS FOR LETTER. MANY THANKS FOR PARCEL. MANY THANKS FOR TELEGRAM. NO NEWS OP YOU FOR SOME TIME. WRITING. URGENT. PLEASE WRITE OR TELEGRAPH. PLEASE WRITE. PLEASE TELEGRAPH. PLEASE REPLY WORRIED. GREETIGS. LOVING GREETINGS. FONDEST GREETINGS. LOVE. DARLING. ALL MY LOVE. ALL MY LOVE DEAREST. ALL OUR LOVE. FONDEST LOVE. FONDEST LOVE DARLING. BEST WISHED. GREETI OS FROM US ALL. LOVING GREETINGS FROM ALL OF US. BEST WISHES FROM ALL OF US. FONDEST WISHES FROM ALL OF US. BEST WISHES AND GOOD HEALTH. KISSES. LOVE AND KISSES. FONDEST LOVE AND KISSES. WELL. ALL WELL AT HOME. BEST WISHES FOR CHRISTMAS. BEST WISHES FOR CHRISTMAS AND NEW YEAR. LOVING WISHES FOR CHRIST AS. LOVING WISHES FOR CHRIST AS AND NEW YEAR. LOVING CHRISTMAS THOUGHTS. HAPPY CHRISTMAS. HAPPY CHRISTMAS AND NEW YEAR. GOOD LUCK. KEEP SMILING. MY THOUGHTS ARE WITH YOU. MANY HAPPY RETURNS. BIRTHDAY GREETINGS. LOVING BIRTHDAY GREETINGS. HAPPY ANNIVERSARY. YOU ARE MORE THAN EVER IN MY THOUGHTS AT THIS TIME. BEST WISHES FOR A SPEEDY RETURN. GOOD SHOW KEEP IT UP. BEST WISHES FOR NEW YEAR. FAMILY ALL WELL. ALL WELL CHILDREN EVACUATED.PAGE 2 70o ALL WELL CHILDREN RETURNED HOME. ?1. ALL WELL AND SAFE. 72. ARE YOU ALL RIGHT. 73. ARE YOU ALL RIGHT WORRIED ABO T T YOU. 74. PLEASE DONT ' ORRY. 75. HOPS YOU ARE IMPROVING. 76. PLEASE TELEGRAP l TH . T YOU ARE VELL. 77. ARE you ill. 78 . HAVE YOU BEEN ILL. 79o ILLNESS IS NOT SERIOUS. 80. ILLNESS IS SERIOUS. 81. I HAVE LEFT HOSPITAL. 82. IN BAD HEALTH. 85. HEALTH IMPROVING. 84 . HEALTH FULLY RESTORED. 85. SON BORN. 86 . DHUUHTER BORN. 87. 88 * 8$. 90. 91. 92. D. PROMOTION. C ONGRATULiTI ON T S OR ’Y OU R PROM OTI ON . VERY PLEASED TO HEAR OF YOUR PROMOTION. DELIGHTED HEAR ABO T YOUR PROMOTION. E. MONEY. PLEASE SEND MR £ ) PLEASE SEND ME S ) HAVE SENT YOU £ ) HAVE SENT YOU S ) CAN YOU SEND ME ANY MONEY. GLAD IF YOU COULD SEND SOME MONEY. HAVE RECEIVED MONEY. HAVE YOU RECEIVED MONEY. HAVE YOU SENT MONEY. THANKS FOR MONEY RECEIVED. HAVE NOT RECEIVED MONEY. UNABLE TO SEND MONEY. SORRY ANNOT SEND MONEY. NOTE THE ACTUAL AMOUNT IN WORDS TO BE INSERTED AND TRANSMITTED IMMEDIATELY FOLLO ING THE TEXT NUMBER. S REFERS TO DOLLARS NOT SHILLINGS. Q UN UKA TU Ijh x I Oih o . 115. congraWLM6M (8n Anniversary best wishes. 116. CONGRATULATIONS LASTING HAPPINESSTO YOU BOTH. 11?. GLAD AND PROUD TO HEAR OF YOUR DECORATION EVERYBODY THRILLED 118. LOVING GREETINGS AMD CONGRATULATIONS. 119. GOOD LUCK KEEP IT UP. 120. I V ISH WE WERE TOGE HER OR THIS SPECIAL OCCASION ALL MY BEST WISHES FOR A SPEEDY REUNION. 121 . 122 . 1255 124* G. WAR D v] AGE# *2§* INJURED A ID IS HOSPITAL. ( NOTE THE NAME TO BE INSERTED AND TRANSMITTED IMMEDIATELY AFTER THE TEXT NUMBER). 126. INJURED AND IN HOSPITAL. 127. SORRY TO HEAR OF DAMAGE HOPE ALL WELL. 128. SORRY TO HEAR OF INJURY AND HOPE NOT SERIOUS. 129. SORRY TO HEAR OF INJURY AND HOPE PROGRESS FAVOURABLE. IJO# sorry to Lear of injury and hope soon be better.FAGS 5 151 . 152 . 153. 13k 135. 136r 1M. 1142 . H. MISCELLANEOUS. VERY HAPPY TO HEAR YOU DEAREST AM PIT AND (YELL. HEARING YOUR VOICE ON THE WIRELESS GAVE ME A WONDERFUL THRILL. I. BEREAVEMENT . SORRY TO TELL YOU DIED. ) NOTE THE NAME TO BE INSER- SORRY TO HEAR ...... DIED. ) IED AND TRANSMITTED. 200. MY ADDRESS IS ( COMPLETED BY ADDRESS AND/OR CERTAIN CODE WDS IN CASE OP LATTER MILITARY AUTHORITIES MUST DECODE). THIS TEXT IS ONLY AVAILABLE FOR DIDEAST FORCE.GTC Britconsul Bushire Political Bahrein Dated 9th March a 1942* This is trial nesage by Persian wireless. Tf received plea s e send acknowledgment by direct wireless to Bushire. Telegram From To No.A/190 33Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO (uk* .2.7.th...Ho.Y.emb.er. 5 ....19.42.* Mo °C/l9 . U.R6-E N'T. The Pollticr l A^ent 3 Bahrain# Dear Sir^ In vc.ew of the scarcity of steamers between Karachi and Bushire, we are finding it difficult to effect Staff transfers, a matter which is of extreme importance to communications• and Bushire, but I cannot ^et any definite information about these launches* fiyhtin' servi.ces, I vrould be most prateful if you could five me ergr information and assistance in this matter, which is most urgent* I am to3.d that launches occasionally run between Bahrain Owinn; to the vital importance of communications to the Yours faithfully. Bahrain Branch*Printed in England. Sept. 1941. (30 / )0 pads). IN REPtY REFt.. .O c . - .. k«.T5/75. MEMORANDUM. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 2/-50 BRANCH, 5Qih...N.'?Y.?mber, 1.942_* The Polite A^ent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir^ \'Ie acknowledge,mth thanks,yonr letter No .2115—33/3 of the 29th instant, and enclose a cheque for Rs6/- , bein^ the refund on a telegram booked by Captain R.D.Metcalfe o^ the °0th September, 1941*afl aaoc KiATSif-.r fo\ota stdmtr re cz , ?&amp; : . , vx&gt;c ) si smmaA tm .(r-o^naa TF-tra csirn-ORTtw yratuik hettaj ao esao ki sow .edpoe tp.a£cic froa sisaiiava yjko si txho 21 ht - w -« £&gt;lr C..BL1 UiW u ^Dth Dec ember, i!»42 i © . CIKCUUa. x ^ — ■ — #• have to advise you that the E # F 9 M Service has been intreduced with the United. States Of America, with immediate ef eet « Special texts will apply upto the 27th December,1942* The sender can choose ore standard taxt^only, from the follo-dnr six standard texts ' A* A Merry Xmas and a happy iNewYear all well* . Love : oest wishes for Xaas anc the ew^ear all well. C« Love &amp; beat wishes for Xiaas and the NewYear to all at howe all well * D* Love A best wishes for Xaas and the hewYear from all at home all well * E* Love A best wishes for a happy ftawYear all well* F# Every ^ood wish for the Newlear * ' p. Ine Charges per tclepra is 'M/ll/* * wtm i. r. . tele rams are admit tec), be tween Dab rain on one side # and British' Empire counties, l).S*A* Egypt, Sudan, Muscat, Ice land, and throe Islands, on the other* e &gt;- o 1 .111 r s a re ' r: ; ■&lt; L1.o- 3 1* Indicator before tiie a dress* 2* If addressed to members of His Majesty’S and U.O.a. Forces, address must include * (a ’ 'i :, or ir i orce number,if ai.y* (b) Hank of acdressee. (c) i'iaaae * d) Squ&amp;dren, battery Company or other section of the Unit * e) Ar y or nir orce nit . f) The words*'British Kxoeditionery Foree” or the place or country* of destination,if not serving with the Expeditionary Force * • 1 5 , . si mature* ' ' * The nanua of the ender must be * A;- . ecA such, ^pent^ect ar&lt; # * s ecisl facilities, sac hs, reply pai&lt; , Aaltirle addresses ect are a Howe* * larname* Hates:- Indi&gt; not admitting standard texts,4i annas per word. Minimus six words* The adress and the indicator SFM are not charred for* other British Empire Countries * which acu&amp;it standard texts, Jfeil/ll/* per telerram, which includes charge for the indicator EFM, the address, text ' - ■ 4 d:-' ■ ’ p&gt;A:are * Icelanti anri ’aroe islands , adudt stanoard texts, ^2/*per telerra * United St atma at ' , Rd/ll/= per telegram* ' • ’’ i&lt;.B« His Majesty’s and the U*S*A*, Army Airforce,Nurses, Navy A Merchant )avy personnel, are cal ^rivil ed to send anti receive F tele rra is to a. 'ro, tfeir rc la lives fatal lies# Information,regarding the continuation of the EFM service with the United States of America, after 27.12*42,will be advised later* / ip \\ ■V'Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) MANAMA, IN REPLY REFER TO ■ Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 21stJanuary, 1943* no 15/50 The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, We have to inform you that Cable communication between Fao and Bushire is interrupted. Government telegrams for Iran will be forwarded via, the Iranian controlled, wireless station Bushire EPS* Yours faithfully, Office r* tn-Charge Bahrain Branch.CIRCULAR. BAHRAIN. Jo/f&gt;. Ja.r)uajcy ' «e have to advise you that, as from today, Mr N.L.Penfold has taken over the duties of Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain Branch, from Mr C.E.Gahan. The Political Agent. er-in-charge, C • * . c/tss Ltd. Bahrain.Printed in England. -C/g CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED O' INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.! Coaaunication between Bahrain and Fao is interrupted. Government Telegrams for Iraq will now be despatched via Bahrain/Muscat/Aden (Cable link) and Aden/Cairo/Baghdad by Wireless. lo • 1 '3 MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO 9th. February 19434 No.15/52. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, We have to advise you that Cable Yours faithfully. Cable and Wireless Ltd. Bahrain Branch . Officer In Charge,Printed in England. / / J6o CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED Dear Sir, With reference to our letter No. 15/52 of the 9th. instant, we have to inform you that cable communication between Bahrain and Fao has now been restored. 2 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO 23rd. February 1943. no No. 15/52* CONFIDENTIAL. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Government telegrams for Iraq will be despatched via the normal cable route. Yours faithfully. , \ Officer-In-Charge, Cable and Wireless Ltd., Bahrain.Printed in England. /. &amp;.iuL- 3-43 CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) M'3 Telephone No. SOM IN REPLY REFER TO noNo. 15/53* The Political Agent, Bahrain. MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 27th,February 1943. Dear Sir, With reference to our letter No, 15/50 dated 21st. January *43, we have to advise you that cable communication between Fao and Bushire has been restored. Government telegrams for Iran will now be forwarded via 'Fil” (Cable Route). Yours faithfully. Officer-In-Charge, Cable And Wireless Ltd., BAHRAIN.BAHRAIN, 27TH MARCH, 194-3. THE AGENCY, BAHRAIN. DEAR SIR, WILL YOU PLEASE DISTINGUISH CLEARLY YOUR MESSAGES WHICH SHOULD BE CHARGED TO POLITICAL OR RESIDENT'S ACCOUNT YOUR MESSAGES NO.24-1 TO 246 BEAR SIGNATURES RESIDENT BUT SIGNED FOR POLITICAL. YOURS FAITHFULLYCABLE ASD IRE LESS LIMITED, 24th April,W43. u at'*' LEM TELEGRAMS TO IRDIA. From the 1st May,1943, the Indian Administration has decided to introduce standard texts for EFM telegrams as applied to other British smpire Countries. The present 'charge* of 4&amp; annas per text A'ord will be discontinued from the above lentione. date. CM* zherga. sor Officer. Bimmah. n/ m r/ vj 3 -.‘j CABLE ARD AIRKLES3 UVITj.D CIRCULAR ^ith rsference to our Circular dated 24.4.43, the Indian Administration advises that owing to delay in the distribution of pamphlets,regarding EFM Standard Texts, to all* offices in India,the use of Standard Texts is postponed and the previous charge of 4 4 annas per word, « address free,will exist for the present. The Censor Officer, Manamah. Officer-h-cha’g*, Cable find Wireless Ltd.INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, External Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to The F—A—Dnpt Govftmmpnf nf India Thr FnJitiral Knirlrnt irr tlir Pi r inn C^ilf ^ P*-£Uc±*J&amp; (22554) Wt.30365/P.153 2,000 10/42 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685Kxt.1476/43 v ith the compliments of the Under- Secj etery of Utete for Foreign Affairs - 20th Ma^h 1943 F No. 52 ( 476 / 1 / 43 ) presents hie compliments to of S. for F.«., London, and has the honour to trsnsnit to him the under mentioned documents. British Nrobessy, Bagdad. reference: Foi^eign Office despatch letter from Office of the Director oenersl of Posts Telegraphs Cable is Majesty*s ^^assador at Bagdad 15th February 1943 No. 213 ( .13147/155/301) of October 8th # 1942 to Bagdad. Name Date •tektesa dated 15th December, Traffic 1942 to the Divisional Manager Cables, Karachi» the/ xt. 1476/43 BO. i5T10/4/84876 ■ Office of the Director General of xoats &amp; Telegraphs, Iravu Bsgdadt 15 th /ecenber, 1942 To 5 The Divisional Manager Gablea, Karachi* Sir, I have the honour to nform you that since Bahrein Telegraph Office became the Kxohsng© Office for cable traffic to and from Iraq the &gt;egdad *• *0* hoe experienced groat difficulties and inconveniences resulting from the lack of attention paid by Bahrein to numerous Bei^vlcos issued by Bagdad colling for missing messages, for correcting number of messages received in duplicate and to messages received bearing the c.t*f* indication and other corrections. For your information i append herewith.statement giving full particulars of the different Irregularities observed lately by Bagdad G.T*0* in state telegrams received from iiahrein from which it will clearly be observed that Bahrein Office does not or lo not in a X^osition as an exchan ;e office to deal promptly with missing numbers that telegrams bear-n • VB are left without supplying the required corrections and lastly corrections called for are not attended to until after the elapse of considerable time and the issuing of a reminder to most cases. You wi 11, no doubt, readi ly eppreci £ te the t in the present world situation, delays, omissions and obliterations particularly in state telegrams may cause and hoe in feet caused great inconvenience end bitter complaints by the British Bmbeasy and the British Military authorities in Bagdad and in some cases hove rendered state code telegrams undecipherable* Under the above circumstances, it is requested that immediate steps to be taken by your 1 office to remedy the position either by making .arachi T.Q. asD.O. No • /^V- 3,5/j Political Agency, Bahrain, the June 1943. You asked the other day how often clerks in the Persian Gulf Cadre are normally given leave to India and how often they are normally transferred from one station to another. The answer to both these questions is normally three yearsj but clerks are sometimes transferred from one station to another more frequently than that. 2. e have now received official sanction to the grant of dearness allowance to our clerks with retrospective effect from the*lst of August 1942—40# on the first js 200 of total emolu ments (which include pay. Gulf Pay and house rent allowance) and 20% on the portion of emoluments exceeding 200/- up €o a maximum of us 500/- p.m. Yours sincerely. N. L. P 1/3 TP G z* 0 ui)ear uir, / &lt;ith reference to ^ fetter 3.13/981 dated 24th June, I have to inform you that I returned from leave and resumed duty on the 7tn instant. lours faitnlully, Divisi ual Manager,Persian Gulf* b K. 7 icable and tireless limited. BAHRAIN 14th September,1943. My dear Dixon, I enclose a report by Mr Harding concerning the difficulty we have in delivering telegrams to your office on holidays. With this procedure there is a definite risk that important state communicat - ions may be lost or misdelivered. I should be grateful if you could arrange for one individual,known to our Messengers,to take charge of your messages when your office is closed. Yours Sincerely,/ Cable and ire]e s s Ltd., Bahrain 28.10•1942 EPM telegrams are submitted, between Bahrain on one side and Empire Countries, Egypt, Sudan. Muscat, Iceland and Faroe Islands on the other , between His Majesty* s Army and Air Force (including Nurses) and their families and relatives, also from Naval personn el to their relatives in Overseas Empire Countries or from personnel of Merchant Navy to their families. The Conditions are as follows:- 1. indicator EFM before address. 2. If addressed to members of Hin Majesty's Forces, address must include (a) Army or Air Force number, if any. (b) Bari of addressee. (c) Name. (d) Squadron, Battery Company or other section of the tinit. (e) Anny or Air Force Unit (including the worda*'R.A .F.'in the latter case. (f) ^Phe words 41 British Expeditionary Force' or the place or country of destination, if not serving with the Expeditionery Forces. 3. Registered abbreviated addresses are not permitted, as address or signature. 4. The text should be in plain English language.No code words are allowed. 5. The name of the sender must bo his surname. 6. No special classes such as Urgent, Def,etc are admitted. 7. No special facilities,such as Reply Paid,Multiple addresses etc are allowed. RATES:- 1* ilindia, not admitting standard texts, 4$ annas per word, Minimum six words. The address and the indicator EFM are not charged for. , ,, 2. Other British Empire Countries, admitting standard texfs, its.1/11/- per telegra i which include charge for the Indicator E.F.M, the address, numbered texts(mo.ximum three groups) and the signature, which should be surname. 3. Iceland and Faroe Islands admitting standard texts,it.2/- psr telegram.“ / we are in receipt of the following communication,through our head Office,from the lost-i aster General,London: n Owing to Xmas rush service will be suspended from 6th to 2£th December,1943 . both dates inclusive. w In view of the above-mentioned communication,we have to advise that we will not be able to accept E.F.M. • telegrams during the period mentioned. However telegrams tendered prior to the sus ension period will continue to be transudtted. The Laval ufficer-in-uharre, The air Liaison Ufficer,R.n.T. olitical *nent. ublic relations Officer. TW Defence Officer. Officer-iu-Charge, Gable and wireless Ltd., uahrain branch.CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Telephone No. SOM / MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. N. T16/51. IN REPLY REFER TO 14 th J anuary 1944 * The Political Agent, Bahrain . Bear Sir i/Ve were an vised by our Bushire Branch that a plane, not known to ns, would send a message to R.A.F. Moharraq which will be handed over to us for despatch to Bushire* R.A.F. Moharraq on the 12th instant, it was despatched to Bushire for immediate delivery to Britconsul Bushire. message has been booked and forwarded to Bushire yesterday for official delivery through normal course, a copy of which is attached. Would you kindly advise if we may debit the cost of this message to your account. On receipt of the message by telephone from On receipt of further advice from Bushire, the Yours faithfully Officer-in-Charge, Cable and wireless Ltd., Bahrain •'— CONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such, case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. ' 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever: NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches.D.O. No. POLITICAL AGKNCY, PAHHAIN. Th^T April 1944. Considerable inconvenience is felt by the general public by your present arrangement for receiving telegrams for despatch only at your sending station which is some little distance from the town. 2. /ould it be possible for you to consider opening a reception office for telegrams in the main 3uk or in the neighbourhood of the Post Office? Only one room would be Required. N.L• Penfold, Esquire, Offieor-in-Charge, Cable &amp; /ireless, Ltd., Bahrain? / 2 7f Printed in England. 40} 70 Telephone No. SOM xs ^ ' / IN REPLY REFER TO no 535/13. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) / a • y / MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 25th April,1944. Thanks for your D.O.ho.4181-33/3. I raised this matter in 1937 but there was no response. I should be glad to represent it again but would have to quote terms etc if a suitable place were available. Perhaps you could suggest something. There are other reasons I could put forward to justify another office such as congestion here and the desirability to find alternative working space for our increasing clerical establishment. 'tTlIsOONo. f2£o-33/3 J Political Agency, Bahrain, 3rst I4ay 19^Ar To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Bahrain. //K S' i U vpMQBmm Reference your letter No.535/13 dated the 25th April 1944. 2. I understand that Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited have already sublet two office rooms to the Anglo-Iranisn Oil Company and I suggest that you enquire whether they will be willing to sublet one to you. An alternative is to take over the upstairs of a building belonging to the Bahrain Government almost immediately behind the present Post Office. I gather certain repairs v/ill have to be done but as a temporary measure you might find the accommodation adequate. I suggest you get in touch with the owners concerned yourself and endeavour to come to terms if the accommodation is suitable. Political Agent, Bahrain&amp; NO. 1900-33/3 POLITICAL AGKNCY, BAH'fcIN. The 4th July 1944. No. 1260-33/3, dated 'ay 2nd. 2. I hope to be in Karachi shortly and propose to discuss the question with Thornton. I shall therefore be glad to know what progress, if any, has been made. N.L. Penfold, Esquire, Officer-in-Charge, Cable and «f ire less Ltd., BahrainBRITISH HESIIENCY AND CONSUIATH GENERAL, No. 1768-13/271.1 ^ Dated the 1st August, 1944. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to 1) The Political Agent, Bahrain.!^ 2) The Political Agent, Muscat. 3J The Political Agent, Kuwiat. 4) His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Ahhas 5) His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman. 6) His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr for information. D.O. Letter from Mr. J. Gordon, India Office, London, to M.O’Meally, Esquire, Government of India, External Affairs Department, dated the 1st June 1944. (Received under External Affairs Department D.O. letter No. 3406-G/44, dated the 3rd July. 1944). By order .1 for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Enclosure .- HBY FAST AIR ^ ' Copy of D.O. Letter from Mr* J. Cordon, India Office, London, to M.O^eally, Esquire, Government of India, External Affairs Department, dated the 1st June, 1944. You should perhaps know that a new system is being introduced in this country whereby the priority over commercial traffic which has hitherto been given by the Cable Companies to all Government telegrams will s in future be given only to those telegrams for which thi priority is specifically claimed. Thus in future there will be a class of Government telegram, 'without priority', which will take its turn with the ordinary commercial traffic provided that its transmission is not thereby delayed for more than 24 hours after receipt by the Cable Company. If however the delay exceeds this per -iod the Cable Companies undertake thereafter to restore its priority so that it will then be sent before the commercial traffic in hand, but after Government messages with higher priority markings. This practice does not, of course, affect the present priorities of 'Most Immediate','Immediate' and 'Important' f Telegrams sent 'with priority' will not bear any additional marking indicating their classi fication. but I understand that these sent 'without priority' will bear this indication (probably abbreviated to 'NOT PTY”) in the Cable Company's preamble. The above will not apply to telegrams sent from your end, and I am worrying youwith these details only for your information and so that, you will know why in certain cases the transmission period of those coming from here may appear to be unduly long. Will you please pass on the information at your —-discretion to posts In your jurisdiction likely to be interested ?7 'f '• Bahrain Reas : nt Ho. U3/44j&gt;.t. No ..Date lb f.UU (7$) ^75 L.T.Nearchufc;. 4th August, 1944. 'Zp. / / i \ The Political Agent, Bahrein, Rahrain Receipt f V. '••••••••••••TGi..,..* -^ir, I have the honour to inform you that Messrs Cable &amp; Wireless (M.E. ) Ltd,, Government Telegraph Buildings, MoLeaod Road, Karachi, have requested the Chief Accountant, Port Directorate, Basra, to pay a sum of 10,08 francs $ 887 fils in respect of two messages exchanged between us on the 22nd and 23rd July 1943 regard!*^ passages to Basra to certain officers,in L.T.Nearchus. As the sender of messages to me was indicated'as M P,R, Bahrein' the bills were &lt; ( rendered in the first instance to His Majesty* s Consul-General, Bushire, In reply H.M.Consul-General Bushire states that on the dates mentioned in the bills he was in Bushire and thinks the bills in question have been sent to him in error, I enclose herein the correspondence on the subject in original (return requested) and should be glad if you would arrange to settle the bill in the manner suggested under advice to the Director-General of Ports &amp; Navigation, Basra and the Officer-in- Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless, Fao, Basra, to whom a copy of this letter is being sent, I have tgj^honour to be, Your obedient servant, fLelh. Qo y to Inspect ghts. of Ports &amp; Navigation, Basra. The Ofiioer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless, Ltd., Fao.No vW -33/3 Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated/^f'Soptember, 1944 To Gable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrain. /^\ © Memorand um On Sunday September 10th at 8.10 P.M. your peon brought three telegrams to the Agency. They were delivered to and signed for by me. The telegrams were No.454 received at 0630 GMT-, No.462 received at 1525 GMT*, and No.463 received at 1630 GMT. The times of receipt of No.454 and 463 are interesting. 2. This is not the first occasion recently that I have found it necessary to complain of delay in the delivery of telegramSnnd should I have cause again to complain I shall do so direct to your Karachi Office with, j. trust, more satisfactory results. Political Agent, Bahrainao.^pfy -33/3 ^olitic^l Agency, Bahmin, Dated //frSeptember, 1944 To ifteasra. Cable and Wireless Ltd., Dabrain. ¥emo random . I am enclosing you letter No. NS/44/2b dated the 4th August 1944 with its enclosures which I have received from the Commander of L. T. Nearchus. 2. Will you please let me know if there is any reason why these messages should be charged to this. Agency. / Political Agent, Bahrain.Printed in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) /&lt;!0. r -n&lt;*u . Telephone No. SOM IN REPLY REFER TO 7/48 JijM-v** 1 • 7 ''' MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 13th September 1944 No. H. B. la's Political Agent Bahrain• Dear Sir, t&gt;pi ivery of Telegrafaa was so badly delayed. T-ho Tnattpr is be'ine investigated thoroughly and those immediately KSoneXlJ’SfAe »»!«*«&gt; to di.eipllm.ry aetiem. At the same time instructions have been issued which we trust will prevent any repetition of such delay. We should be most grateful if you would be kind enough to bring to our notice immediately any further instance of th nature. Yours faithfully, Officer-in-Charge, Bahrain branch. ERFPrinted in England. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED Telephone No. SOM REPLY REFER TO T16/79. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) Hahrain Receipt : ' 7 MANAMA. BAHRAIN. PERSIAN GULF. 14 th September 1944. H. B« s Political Agent, Bahrain. Please refer to your 2598^-33/3 dat ed 11th September. We understand that the staff of His Majesty^ Consul-General Bushire were in Bahrain during July 1943, and that the telegrams in question may be concerning their business. We see no reason why these messages should be charged to the Political Agency Bahrain and suggest that the matter might be referred to H. M*s Consul-General Bushire again for favour of verification that the telegrams concerned his staff. We should be most grateful if you would be good enough so to do. Yours faithfully,The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushir o. and has the honour to send him £he undermenticnod document for for favour of reverification and disposal* Political Agency, Bahrain. flatod The Soptembe r y 1944• Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Bnclosure* Name and Date* Subject* Copy of Letter N o *T16/79 *datod 14th September, 1944 with ends. from the Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain. Correspondence Cable and Wireless. t JCABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) n.o.M's roiiTicai ageriL, Present. J2c/c&gt; MANAMA, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. 23rd September, 1944. faWaS'-';!* . Telegrams for Paris We beg to advise you that we may now accept the following classes of telegrams for transmission to Paris to pass over the London-Paris wireless circuit. 1) . British and United States Government Telegrams in coded, cipher or plain language, 2) . Government Telegrams of USSR, China, Czechoslovakia, Netherlands, France, Norway, Poland, Belgium, in code or cipher provided they are duly authenticated*. 3) . Government Telegrams of other countries in plain English or French only. 4) . No other Telegrams (except Press) are permissible for the present. Yours faithfully, 4No. 3/ZC .33/3. Political Agency, Bahrain, 31st October 1944. To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; wireless Limited, Bahrain. , MEMORANDUM V Reference correspondence ending with ray demi-official letter No.1131-33/3 dated the 25th April 1944 and the conver sations which we have held earlier in the month. I understand that a shop which will probably be very suitable as a town receiving office for your company is to let in the Hllal building the owner of which is Badr as-Sayer. This shop is in the same row as Messrs. Jashanmals and to judge by the one you saw last week is remarkably large enough for &gt;our purpose. 2. I am quite aware that you wish to build or hire a large town office for part of your present establishment but as I have already pointed out to you personally it is most unlikely that any suitable building can be acquired or constructed for some time to come. -That is required is immediate alleviation of the present hardship which is fait by the general public in that they have to travel a distance of approximately two miles in order to despatch telegrams from your receiving office. I find the reluctance of Messrs, cable &amp; Wireless Limited to consider the convenience of the general public very peculiar. H.B.M‘s Political Agent, Bahrain Copy tos The Divisional Manager, Persian Gulf / JL v x o _L IVlCI.ll.Glg j. * Jr 4. O XCl.il vjTtX-Lx ^ Messrs. Cable A Wireless (Mid-East) Ltd., Karachi.o .No. Jfaf-33/3 PoliticalAgency Bahrain, 31st Oct.l^ n i My dear Thornton, I am enclosing a copy of a letter which I have just addressed to Penfold # / F* L. Thornuon, Esq., Divisional Manager, Messrs. Cable Sc Wireless Ltd. Karachi. *No A.B. //70-62/43-I rf The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gull presents his compliments to and is directed to transmit to him the undermentioned documents. The telegrams In question were not received ty the Fondle the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rushire. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bahrain printed letter No. 2692/35/3 dated the 23rd September 1944. The Political Agent Bahrain Bahrain Receipt in original BUSHIRE. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of letter NO.T16/79 dated 14th September 1944 with enclosures from the Correspondence Cable and Wireless Chble and Wireless Limited ThhrainV- &amp; No. 3/Vf. -33/3. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. THE 4th NOVEMBER 1944, To The Officer in Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, BAHRAIN. sYh *) /fp / H Dear Sir, / V With reference to the correspondence resting with your letter No. T16/79, dated the 14th of September 1944, I have been informed by the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Re sident In the Persian Gulf that tne telegrans, in question, were not despatched by the Political Resident. Yours faithfully,. 'it V/' POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN,Printed in England. Sept. 1941. (300 pads). IN REPLY REFER TO n*. T16/79. i 303) 2/-5»Afc iT&gt; CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) * \ V ^ MEMORANDUM. Bahrain BRANCH, The Political Agent, Bahrain. -17thNovember,1944. Biliraift n Q . Dear Sir, 0 '&lt; with reference to paragraph two (2) of letter No.NS/44/26 of 4.8.44 from L.T. Nearchus, we attach hereto correspondence in original to be returned to the Commander. Yours faithfully. Enel: 4. Officer-in-charge, Cable and Wireless Ltd. Bahrain.2Jo. &lt;34#9-33/3* Political Agency, Bahrain, The 22nd November, 1944• Sir, x ' 1 P I have the honour to refer to your letter Ko* KS/44/26 dated the 4th August 1944 and to inform you that the two messages in question were neither sent by the Hon f ble the Political Resident nor by ma* I return heravrith the correspondence forwarded with your letter under reference* I am sending a copy of this letter to the Director-General of Ports and Navigation, Basra and to the Officer-in-charge. Cable and Wireless Ltd., Fao. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your uost obeaieat servant, Political Agent, Bahrain. The inspector of Gulf Lights, L.T. Nearchus. Copy to: The Director-Gener’al of Ports and Navigation, Basra. The Officer-in-charge, Cable &amp; wireless Ltd., Pao.A/»- dUfy ■ Political Agency, Bahrain, The 22nd November, 1944. CKRTIFICATiS. This is to certify that Mr. T.C. Freshwater has been employed by Cable and Wireless in Bahrain and has been transferred by air to England. I understand that his trunk which is being despatched to United Kingdom via Basra contains only his personal effects. “i® Political Agent, BahrainCABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) MANAMA, Telephone No. SOM BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. IN REPLY REFER TO 5th December 1944 K. B. ll’s Political Agent Bahrain. .■Data... With reference to your letter No 3179-o3/3 dated 4th November last and connecting correspondence, ive have been instructed to enquire from you whether it is possible to determine from the texts of the messages, copies enclosed, as to the party on whose behalf the telegrams in question were It would appear fromjbhe Inspector of Gulf Lights f letter to the Political AgenOliat^e messages were concerning passages to Basra for certain officers in L.T.Nearchus*^From this information perhaps it would be possible to determine the party who should be debited with the cost of messages* sent Yours faithfully. Officer-in-Charge Bahrain branch. Fncls:~ 2Printed in England. Sept. 1942. (4,100. pads.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in enoland.) The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— Prefix Letters and Number of Message. Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Clerk’s Time Circuit. Name. Received. WPP 0705 GMT 5/-16 8 SS 9 X2X BAHRAIN DE NEARCHUS COE 16/15 PR BAHRAIN CDE11 CTUM RXZL VClYS LVHP ECYC T2YB SZQ.Y XOKQ, WQHS XYET HLJN. === 230655 GMT === ERF MARK YOUR REPLY Jm/iebiaC ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.Printed in England. Sept. 1941 (4,100. pads. | CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENOLANO.) 5/-16 8 OF The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— Prefix Letters and Number of Message. Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. 914 BAHIUIK Circuit. Clerk's Name. Time Received. l 22-7-1943 \ JPDS 1950 \ BRANCH J SS 8 BAHRAIN DE NEARCHUS CDE 12/11 NAVYCHARGE BAHRAIN CDE7 ULP VRZN GGCR RRKK CBKF NACR CtOfl). === 221920GMT === MARK YOUR REPLY Jnuie?ua£ ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES.No. 33/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, The'9th December, 1944. To The Officer in charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltdr, Bahrain. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No.T16/79 dated the 5th December 1944, I have to inform you that it is not possible to determine from - the texts of the telegrams in question on v/hose behalf they were sent. The fact that the time of origin G.I£. T. is included seems to indicate a service, possibly R.A.source. Yours faithfully,m No.20/12, dated the 7th November 1953, from I .&amp; I .Commncs .Bahrain Re. Short wave band. Put up to me when S.N.O. comes off this afternbon on / ' . / 16 hours into my hands. G.L. 8/11. X Submitted with reference to the above note. — P.U.G. said to have been removed by the P.A.and note returned to office.without initials. Urgent * Letter received back with the remarks 'Copy to go to S.N.O.with the request that he will kindly place me in a position to reply.' S.L. 8/11. Draft for approval placed below reference above note. ■^xi. No. 1357,dated the 9th November 1933 to the S.N.O.x.0. L, ( 1 *3 y No.3,98,da.tea 7-12-1935, from S.N.O jSh or eham. ( c, (It t ) A A The information may be passed to the Imp. Airways,Bahrain. Draft plaaed below for approval. z. \rr^~ ^ C ' f ^ p ‘ 'H- i£- n-- mj, 0- 4* ■163. Letter dated 25th Lay 1335 from Jemil Bahrain. LL may register this applicant’s name zusji; but please see pages 42 and 51 of file 23/j-IIl, in view of wnich '.«e perhaps shouId.^/make no rec/ommendation to the G-sie and tireless t as requested by the applicant. Incidentally, the applicant is ^rauic tutor to and A.P.A. Added; 164. Hemorandum Ho. 224/23 dated 23th May 1935 from tne adviser. Draft submitted to the C and //. Limited. Iki- P hI I* ■ w A 'Hi, Issued letter 1:0.946 dated the 30th ‘lay 1335 to the Office: in-charge, Cable and /ireless, Bahrain. / issued letter No.949 dated the 30th May 1935 to do JlUA*' to'. /e7y *{L -tZLetter dated the 15th November 1955 Irorn Mr. G. j^ottomiey* Officer in Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, hanram, to Lieutenant-Colone1 Gordon Loch, C.I.E., Political Ageat, Bahrain. I understand tix^t Mr. i^un^er toxd Mr. ju,ithiul to maKe all arrangements i or a launcxi during tue stay. ^nat did tne xi.A.ij. ^ay ana we a or our Louut Salwa reconnaissance• G.L.-15-11-19ob. The usual rates paid for launches plying oetween the CustODis Pier and the Navy and B.I* anchorages are:- Small Larg e, L a un c h,c • Navy Anchorage Rs. ' 4 5 to 6 B.I. Anchorage Rs. 8 10. A large launch was engaged by Mr. Jjaitniui. The 'Lady Denison Pender' useo tne i\ic*vy aucnor, which incidentally is less than hail tne distance to tne B.I. anchorage. The B.A.F. pay Rs. 2/- for a trip Prom tne R.A-F. jetty to the Muharraq pier. For the Dohat Salwa reconnaissance we ^«id at a contract rate of Rs. 40 a day when the launch was m use and at Rs. 20 a day when not in use or for delays. He nuv no information what the R.A.F. paid. I understand that tne launch used oy tne 'Lady Denison Pender' was hard worxced: each trip ( to the shi±&gt; and oacxCy would to be reasonable charge. * ns. 6/ - E3LKR ior uixereiore &lt;A i j t &gt;eo.L' U Issued d.o.No.2031-16/2 dated the 24th November 1935 to C. Bottomley, hsquire. Notice irom Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain. Seen by P.A., Mrs. Loch ana A.P.A. May be filed pi. ^ ''XThe 0,C. Gable and Wireless tells ne that there v/a:■ sone difficulty yesterday evening (November i2th) over a telegram reporting the arrival of the Vincents at Shai’bah. It was apparently brought to the Agecy where there was no one on duty to taKe it (please find out where the ferash was). The peon then went on to the house of the H.C.,who was at the by H.C. Telegraph Station . The peon too^ it there , but was then told/ to bring the Agency peon, as he w ould nto taxce delivery there. Mr Bottomley maKes no complaint , but does want to have some definite arrangement about the delivery of messages which were coming through. Mr. faithful used to send a note to or phone Mr. Thomas that these would reach us about a certain time, and I think still does. bate uode and cypher telegrams not marked •Important• or * Immediate• were sent down to the Agency the following morning. Please let uie nave lile re- uelivcry oi telegrams* I nave to reply to Mr. Bottomley. arrive after office hours What is the best arrangement ? /\ A.P.A _^K5.12.35 in my opinion the best arrangement is to have a duty clerk by the week in the b*0* to whom all telegrams should be taken out of office hours. if the telegram is c.T.C. he can deal with it, and if for C.O. send it on to Mr. Thomas, after having signed for it. •The telegraph office always helped us in the hot weather by letting us know ahead when code and cypher telegrams H.C G.Li ■■ P-A. Reference your note dated the 17th iJove^oer On the evening of the 12th November I was over at Mr. Faithful * s place. A telegraph peon brought a telegram to me. I asked him if he had tajcen it to tne Agency for delivery to the Agency peon. He said no. I tnereupon told him to telephone (from the G. and W. Oliice) lor an A^enc./ Ferrash (since it was aircraft movement report) or to give it to one. 11-« #/'Z , 7 Iiiscussed onthe 20th December 19o5. D.F.A. below. I, Please fiaice fair draft. Then will A.P.A. ta^e some opportunity of showing it to Mr Bottomley and finding out whether the suggested proaddure will suit him. If so the draft shd issue so that the matter wsll be on record in out? respective offices. dU+t*' Ux4n *“^ i ' h ft*- . L 5.1.36 '' ' L k * • 1 \ Jr. 14 4 Vj UIa P- (U 4Mq: ^ | M c*^- '|&gt; -L. “b £ 9 _ ' — / L- J.. 1^ /HU- /ffo &amp;&gt;. £-£ * * Liur&lt; h a ^ bJtr &lt;^ui n '*7* K^WiL ^ The Indian Worknifin’s Compensation Act is not appli cable to Bahrain as it is not included in the schedule of Indian Acts applied to Bahrain (marked A). A list of the English Acts applied to Bahrain is not available as those Acts are described in the First shE schedule to Foreign Jurisdiction Act 1890 (Article 12 B.O.CJ and we are not in possession of a copy of Froeign Jurisdiction Act. But it will be seen from a letter of Captain Prior (page 100 B.O.C. file) suggesting the extension of the Indian Workman’s Compensation Act to Bahrain and P.R's disapproval thereof (page 103 - 105) that no Workman’s Compensation Act has * ever been applied zo Bahrain. The subsequent correspondence between Captain Prior and the P.R. on the subject, which, adxh although irrelevant here,is of general interest appears on A pages 106 - 111 and culminated in Bapco’s agreement ” to dispose of claims for accident^ compensation on the linesof the Indian Workman’s Compensation Act ( p.109) and P.A’s satisfaction tiierewith (p.lll). But it docs not follow that the iict is, strictly speaking, applicable to Bahrain. Draft submitted for approval. n n i- -Wi j. -v/</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1765</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1765</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 33/3 [16/2] Correspondence with the Wireless Station etc.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-18T18:19:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (331 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 310-332). There are also some notes within the body of the file, e.g. folios 127-128.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 333; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional mixed foliation/pagination sequences are also present in parallel between ff 311-327; these numbers are written in a combination of pencil and blue crayon, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence concerning the radio (referred to earlier in the file as the wireless) station, Bahrain. The station was initially run by the Indo-European Telegraph Department (a department of the Government of India), but from 1931 responsibility passed to a public company, Imperial and International Communications Limited (from 1934 known as Cable and Wireless Limited). The main correspondents are the Political Agent, Bahrain, and the Officer-in-Charge of the radio station. There is also some correspondence from the Government of Bahrain.The papers cover issues such as: interruptions to wireless traffic; complaints about the service; the ownership of wireless sets by individuals; installation of telephone lines; maintenance of the telegraph system; the title deeds for the land on which the radio station was built; the provision of drinking water for employees at the station; recruitment of staff; notices and circulars; arrangements for Christmas and New Year greetings telegrams; and special arrangements caused by the Second World War (1939-45).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd, Officer in Charge, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indo-European Telegraph Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Wireless telegraphy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001f4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>