<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0003dd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T06:48:58.214Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ass,. |y Confidential. Persian Gulf. Turkish Jurisdiction along the Arabian Coast. (Part III.) Secret Letter from India, No. 145, dated the SOth October 1881. Secret, No. 127, dated 22nd May 1879. f ; f Memo., Part II., p. 61. Home, No. 677 of 1879. § Memo., Part L, pp. 7 to'22. Memo., Part II., pp. 50 to 66, The previous history of this question, with all the material facts bearing upon it, will be found stated at length in a Memorandum, in two parts, dated the 1st September 1879. That paper was prepared in view to consideration by the Secretary of State (Lord Cranbrook) of cer tain proposals made by the Government of India,* for a comprehensive arrangement with the Turkish. Government in reference to its territorial pretensions along the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf, and to the police of the seas in those parts, some decided measures having been rendered absolutely necessary by a succession of piratical acts on the part of the Arabs occupying the El Katr (or Guttur) coast, where the Turkish Government claimed jurisdiction without exercising any real authority. The nature of these proposals, and the view taken by the Secretary of State on the different questions involved, after consideration of the whole subject, and of an alternative proposition made by the Poreign Office,! will be clearly understood from the letter addressed to that Office on the 17th September 1879, of which the material paragraphs were as follows ;—{■ ' 3. There can, in Lord Cranbrook's opinion, be little doubt that the present disturbed state of the Arab coast and the seas adjacent is, in a great measure a consequence (1) of the obstacles to direct action on the part of the British authorities in the Gulf, which are interposed by the position assumed on the Arab coast by the Turkish Government since the Nejd expedition of 1871-72 ;§ (2) of the un certain nature of that position; and (3) of the practical inability of the Ottoman officials to main tain order even along that part of the coast where Turkish influence is strongest. '4. This being so, it appears to Lord Cranbroc-V to be important to determine, as speedily as possiH with whom shall rest responsibility for order alcT the coast, whether with the Government of I; alone, or with the Porte alone, or with the Governments conjointly. ' 5. His Lordship has considered with atten the views of Lord Lytton's Government on u point, expressed in their Despatch, No. 127, late*, the 22nd May last, |1 and also those of Xord 6364. 1. 2806. A **»Mi W2 Salisbury, as set forth in Sir J. Pauncefote's letter of the 23rd August. ' 6. The Government of India recommend that from Bussorah to Ojair the authority of the Porte should be recognized as established on land, but that at sea the British Government should continue to exercise some concurrent protectorate, pursuing pirates, if necessary, into Turkish waters, and dealing with them wherever found, whether at sea or on shore, within certain limits, through the Resident in the Gulf; that, south or east of Ojair, Turkish authority should not be recognized except at El Bidaa, on the Guttur peninsula; and that the Porte should be required (a) to stipulate not to interfere, either on the coast or inland, with the Trucial Chiefs between Odeid and Ras-el-Khymah ; (5) to recognize the territories of the Sheikh of Bahrein as under the protection of Great Britain, and (d?) in case of piracies from within its juris diction, to enforce restitution of plundered pro perty and payment of compensation. ' 7. Her Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs observes, with reference to these proposals, that, m the absence of inducements, the Porte is not likely to assent to the suggested limitations of its sovereignty or jurisdiction, or to independent S x a ? ot i, er Power in territory or waters admitted to be Turkish. Lord Salisbury, therefore suggests that it would be more practical, and more m, accordance with usage, that, having settled for ourselves the limits within which Turkish iuris- diction may be exercised, and beyond which it would be rejected or opposed, we should, as a general rule, look to the Turkish authorities to exercise a proper police in those limits, only 6 f ti0n 0f Britisl1 cruis ers in Turkish waters under special circumstances, when oblS l0eal authOTities has been '5' , T1 , le P™ ci P al objectlQn to the course recom mended by the Government of India appeSL To- Lord Cranbrook to be that it involves a P Sous understanding with the Porte which His LorS w i th ,, :L ? r(1 Salisbury in thinking scarcelv an exclusive British protectorate over .aSed experience, be a the part of the Turkish Government' to'eS 'i J lik 13 * Memo., Part II., p. 35. t Memo., Part II., p. 68. from third parties restoration of plundered property and payment of compensation would be operative in practice. On this point, the complete absence of result from the representations made at Con stantinople in 1876 and 1S77, in reference to the cases of the British Indian subjects Cheyla and Eama,* and the attack on an Aboothabee boat in the harbour of El Bidaa, are significant. ' I^ord Granbrook, on the other hand, fears that the course suggested in Sir J. Paimcefote's letter of the 23rd August, while it would probably be little less distasteful to the Porte than that proposed by the Government of India, would fail to attain the object in view. II. If adopted, the authority and responsibility of the Turkish Government would be recognized as complete within certain territorial limits to be fixed by ourselves, and would be wholly disallowed beyond those limits. '12. The limit of Ottoman jurisdiction along the coast, if it is to be defined at all, could scarcely be fixed at any point north of Ojair, which is opposite the southern extremity of the island of Bahrein; but it is precisely between that spot and Kateef that, since the settlement of the Beni Yas at Odeid was broken up in 1878, the operations of the piratical tribes have been carried on with almost complete impunity. Upon this point Lord Cran- brook would invite Lord Salisbury's attention to Colonel Boss's letter of the 8th May,j* enclosed in Government of India Despatch, No. 91, of the 28th July last, which was communicated to the Foreign Office on the 6th instant. ' 13. His Lordship apprehends that the effect of formally recognizing any particular part of the Arab coast and the waters adjacent as Turkish, and as, in consequence, closed against British cruisers, so far as action against piratical craft is concerned, would be the formation of an asylum which would betaken advantage of by marauders* in general, whom the local Ottoman authorities would be unable to control without a considerable and per manent increase to the Turkish naval force in the Gulf, which the Porte has declared itself precluded from making by considerations of expense, and which would be open to many objections on political grounds. '14. The conclusion, therefore, to which Lord Cranbrook is led is that negotiation or discussion with the Porte on the territorial question should be avoided; but that, in order that the obligations Contracted by the Government of India towards the Sheikh of Bahrein and the parties to the maritime truce may be efficiently fulfilled, the Besident in the Persian Gulf should be authorized to adopt all necessary measures for the preservation of the peace of the seas, without regard either to Turkish pretensions to sovereignty over the whole Arab coast, or to the recognition of Ottoman supremacy by individual Chiefs such as the Sheikh of El Bidaa,4 or to the presence of Turkish officials at isolated ^ It seems to Lord Cranbrook that Her Majesty's Government have a right to regard the fact of particular ports being used as bases for piratical attacks, and certain tribes being engaged In those attacks, as prima facie evidence that such ports and such tribes are not under the effective control of the Ottoman Government, and that they would be justified in issuing instructions to their officers in accordance with this view. ' 16. Lord Cranbrook is further of opinion that, laving regard to the repeated assurances given by the Turkish Government in 1871-72, at the time of the operations in Nejd, that no interference with the littoral tribes was intended, and to the often repeated declaration of the British Government that it would object to any disturbance of the status quo as regards those tribes. Her Majesty's Government might, if it were deemed expedient, legitimately decline to recognize any part of the coast south of Koweit as subject to Turkey, even if Ottoman authority were established there much more firmly than is really the case. ' 17. Provided, however, that no obstacles be in terposed to any operations which may be' necessary to preserve the peace of the seas and to punish marauders, and that no interference is attempted either with Bahrein, or the Trucial Chiefs from Odeid to Ras-el-Khymah, or with Muscat, Lord Cranbrook does not consider that exception need be taken to the proceedings of the Turks at any point of the coast north of Odeid. ' 18. In expressing this opinion, his Lordship does not forget that the Government of India would restrain the Porte from extending its influence beyond Ojair; but, subject to the conditions above stated, Lord Cranbrook does not see any sufficient reason for objecting to the establishment of such relations between the Turkish authorities in El Hassa and the tribes of the Guttur peninsula to the north of Odeid as may be agreeable to the parties con cerned. '19. It will have been gathered from the fore going remarks that, in Lord Cranbrook's opinion, it is essential to the restoration and maintenance of order in the Persian Gulf that no merely nominal extension of Turkish authority should be permitted to hamper the action of the officers of the British Government, and that His Lordship would desire a return, as far as possible, to the system followed until within the last few years, under which the Hesident at Bushire, and the British Naval autho rities acting under his orders, dealt directly with the Arab tribes along the entire littoral, captured piratical craft wherever they might be found, and exacted from the local Sheikhs redress for outrages committed by their people. '20. Under instructions which were issued by the Admiralty in the month of May last,* the Com- • Memo., Part IL, p. 48.1 5 manders of Her Majesty's ships in the Gulf are prohibited from hostile action within Turkish terri tory or its waters without the consent or co-opera tion of the Turkish authorities. Lord Cranbrook would suggest that these instructions should be modified, and that naval officers should be autho rized, when so directed by the Resident in the Gulf, to act in any particular case in such wise as may be necessary for the capture and punishment of marauders, collision with Turkish cruisers or troops being, of course, scrupulously avoided. ' 21. If, upon further consideration. Lord Salis bury should be prepared to acquiesce in the policy above suggested, it might, Lord Cranbrook thinks, be left to the discretion of Her Majesty's Ambas sador at Constantinople either to intimate to the Porte at once the determination of Her Majesty's Government, or to await a remonstrance against the action of the British authorities in some par ticular case. '22. The pretensions, however, which Abdullah Pasha, the Governor General of Bussorah, has lately asserted to regard all ports in southern and eastern Arabia, including Bahrein and Muscat, as Turkish, should, in Lord Cranbrook's opinion, be distinctly negatived, and the opportunity might, perhaps, be taken of intimating plainly to the Porte that, so far as eastern Arabia is concerned, to whatever extent Turkish supremacy may eventually be admitted by the littoral tribes north of Odeid, Her Majesty's Government will not recognize its ex tension over either the Trucial Chiefs, or the Sultan of Muscat. '23. I am, in conclusion, directed to state that Lord Cranbrook concurs in the view which Lord Salisbury takes of the proposal for a revision of treaty relations between the British Government and the Sheikh of Bahrein, the Trucial Chiefs, and the Buler of Muscat, which, is contained in the India letter of 22nd May last.* ' 24. It does not seem to Lord Cranbrook that closer connection with those Arab potentates is necessary or expedient in British interests, or that any object, which cannot otherwise be obtained, would be gained by exacting from them tribute or any other formal recognition of British supremacy. The policy of the Indian Government has always been to abstain from interference in the disputes and conflicts of the Arab tribes on land, and a departure from that policy, to which closer rela tions might very well lead, would almost certainly result in embarrassment.' The essence of the foregoing letter is in the 14th and 19th paragraphs, which amounted to a re commendation that the officers of the Indian Go vernment in 'me Gulf should be allowed the same liberty of action in respect to the littoral tribes as they 'had exercised unquestioned up to the year 1871 or thereabouts. While the matter was under consideration at the Foreign Office, various papers were received from 6364. B6 the Government of India, which put m a strong light the improbability of any effective action being taken by the Turkish authorities against- pirates the secret motives by which those authorities were likely to be animated, and the expediency of the course suggested from this Office. Or, fhp ifith Julv * Colonel Ross, the Resident * India, Political, No. 102, dated 1st Sep- in the Gulf reported to plunder of a Bahrein .emberl879. pearl vessel, one man being killed, and three wounded. The perpetrators were members of the TuSish^juri8&lt;nc^&gt;n;^I)Lit Uie' p^ple^of^a^ilh^etf ^Khor Shuj^ej, 20 .niles north of EI regarded by us as independent, were suspected of being concerned, and the act was committed at the north -eastern point of the Guttur promontory, which the Government of India were not prepared to recognize as within Turkish limits. Colonel Ross communicated with Mr. Robertson, the Political Agent at Bussorah, in view to the conduct of the Beni Hajir being represented to the Turkish authorities, but he had small hopes of any result. Writing to the Government of India, he observed:— ' 3. The names and haunts of the pirate leaders, and the special acts; of piracy committed by each, have been pointed out to the Turkish authorities, but it seems that, as a rule, the latter reserve their action for matters which they consider affect Turkish interests. Those who, as the Beni Hajir, attack only Bahrein or other vessels escape un punished, and it may be even suspected that the annoyance to Bahrein commerce is not wholly dis pleasing to officials who hope eventually to see British influence and authority displaced by Turkish in those coveted islands.' And Mr. Robertson was as little sanguine. Re porting to Colonel Miles, Political Agent at Baghdad, the representation he had made on the subject to Abdullah Pasha, the Governor General of Bussorah, and the merely dilatory reply of that functionary, he wrote (17th July 1879):— '3. I do not think that Abdullah Pasha can or will take any effectual measures to suppress piracy by the Bedouins of the Nejd coast. Here at Busrah he makes no effort to put a stop to the robberies and murders, which occur almost nightly, and in the remoter parts of the province he has no autho rity whatever. He was probably never a man of much capacity, and age and fanaticism have now reduced him to utter imbecility. His hatred of Englishmen is a disease, and he professes to regard the piracies on the Nejd coast as the results of English artifice and intrigue. They and other annoyances will, I have no doubt, continue and increase until a competent and fairly enlightened Governor is appointed to Busrah.' # Writing again on the 1st August^ Mr. Robertson J India, Political, No. 119, &lt;W«d 16lh ' conhrmed Colonel Ross's view, that designs upon October 1879. Bahrein might have something to do with Turkish inaction. He remarked - \, dated 1st Sep- es north of El * India, Political, No. October 1879. 122, dated 23rd 119, dated 16th i ' The real cause of the disturbed condition of the Nejd coast is the incomplefce and ineffectual Turkish occupation of the El Hassa district and the littoral, which, without apparently benefiting them in any way, occasions them a considerable loss annually in men and money, while it affords an asylum and practical stronghold to the refuse of the maritime population, who seem to hare elected Zaid bin Mahomed El Hajiry their Chief. As long as the Turks hope to obtain possession, of Bahrein and the pearl fisheries they are not likely to be persuaded to abandon the valueless mainland opposite, but they might be induced to nominate a Governor in some degree competent to maintain order.'- Colonel Miles, an officer of long experience in the Gulf, was of the same opinion. In a Despatch, dated the 5th August,* to Her Majesty's Ambas sador at Constantinople, he detailed at length the outrages by which the past year had been signalized, and the complete failure of the Turkish authorities either to punish the offenders, or afford redress to the sufferers, ' chiefly the peaceful and well-to-do natives of Bahrein.' This failure he attributed to lack of inclination rather than to want of means, and observed upon this point:— ' Mr. Hobertson, who appears to be well ac quainted with Abdullah Pasha's character, states that His Excellency regards the piracies in Turkish waters as none of our business, and expresses himself freely in private regarding English inter ference. ' He also believes that His Excellency does not put down the pirates because he is afraid lest it should be said he was acting under English dicta tion. It may be .so. But I confess my belief is that there are other motives of action not so ap parent perhaps, but which have had at least equal influence in determining the conduct of the Turks, and I think their procedure should be considered in connection with their well known desi— — Bahrein. They are probably far from chagrined at these disorders and outrages, and in no hurry to suppress them. ' They would, in fact, prefer their continuance in order that they may with more colour put forth the pretext that Bahrein is the cause of them, and that they cannot put them down until Bahrein is in their hands. They are seeking, in short, for a on being are cause ot quarrel and a pretext to interfere and conquer. ' I need not remind Your Excellency that it has been for many years past the cherished project of successive Pashas of Turkish Arabia to add this island to the Sultan's dominions. Their intrigues, claims, and pretensions to it have been unceas ing, and it may reasonably be doubted whether they would have ever troubled to conquer if they had not also expected to £ Bahrein. Hasa therewith 6' Anotlier string to the Pasha's bow is theJiope that the Sheikh and people of Bahrein, finding the British Resident no longer able to protect their ships at sea as heretofore, and unable to ensure them redress and reparation for losses at the hands of Turkish pirates, will turn at last to him and accept the soyereignty of the Sultan as the price of future peace and security, ' Under this light the otherwise incomprehen sible behaviour of the Wali Abdullah Pasha becomes immediately significant, and the impenetrable armour of passive resistance to remonstance put on by His Excellency no longer difficult to account f01 ' We then understand why it is that he pro crastinates to gain time under the pretext of making inquiry, and why it is that these promised inquiries have no results, and his orders fail to draw any action or response from his subordinates. ' If these surmises as to the causes of Turkish inactivity in repressing maritime disorders in the Gulf be correct, it is obviously of no use continuing to appeal to the Pasha for redress.' Colonel Miles concluded:— 'We stand in a false position, and I trust re spectfully Your Excellency will be able to support my opinion that the remedy in such a state of affairs can only lie at head-quarters at Constan tinople. ' There can be no question that the present posi tion of affairs is highly detrimental to British interests and prestige in the Gulf. ' When the Arabs on the formerly so-called pirate coast, whom we have transformed for the past half century into peaceful traders and fishers, see what their brethren in Turkish territory are allowed to do with impunity, and that, the protests and remonstrances of the Resident, the only human authority they acknowledge, are disregarded and set at nought by the Turks, it is impossible but that it may go far to unsettle their minds and seduce them to forsake the cause of order. The effect on the inhabitants of the Persian coast is equally pernicious. ' Every action, every step we take in those parts is closely scrutinized by those around us, and is of significance to them. I would humbly and re spectfully express the opinion that the time has come when it is no longer advisable for our supremacy, in the Persian Gulf to remain in question.' Upon receipt of Colonel Miles' Despatch, whose views were concurred in by the Government of India,* Sir H. Layard (September 1879), of his own motion, called the attention of the Turkish Govern ment to the matter.f The Porte, he wrote, was no doubt aware that the British Government, at a great sacrifice of life and treasure, succeeded, after many years, in put ting an end to piracy in the waters of the Persian * India, Political, October 1879. No. 122, dated 23rd f From Foreign Office, 1879, No. 717. 22ud September9 Gulf. Her Majesty's Government could never permit that British interests and commerce should suffer by its revival in consequence of their recog nition of Turkish jurisdiction over certain parts of the Arabian coast, and, if the state of things described by Colonel Miles was allowed to continue, they would be compelled to take such measures as might be necessary for the protection of British subjects and shipping in the Persian Gulf. After com menting on the misconduct of Abdullah Pasha, and the importance of appointing a competent successor to Ahmed Bey, the lately deceased Commander of the Turkish squadron in the Euphrates and the Persian Gulf, Sir H. Layard concluded:— ' Should, however, the tribes on the Arabian coast, over which the Porte claims jurisdiction, re vert to those piratical habits from which they were deterred by the action of the British authorities, and should the safety of British shipping and British subjects be again endangered by such piratical attacks as are described in the accompany ing documents, the Porte must alone be responsible for the consequences.' Shortly afterwards, Abdullah Pasha was re moved from his post, Zabet Pasha being appointed ♦ India, Political, No. 119, dated I6tli in his place,* but no other result followed beyond October 1879. an assurance from the Porte that the local authori ties had been enjoined to vigilance, and that the Turkish squadron would be reinforced by two t Fi om Foreign Office, 11th October, 1879, additional ships.f No. 822. On the 16th November 1879, consequent on a telegram from Colonel Miles, reporting that a British vessel, from Karachi, had been attacked and plundered fifteen miles below Bussorah, one man being killed, and two wounded. Sir H. Layard again informed the Porte ' that the neglect or in- ' ability of the Ottoman authorities to maintain tc the police of their own waters in, the Persian ' Gulf may lead to results which it is greatly in the ' interest of the Porte to avoid.' Meanwhile, the whole of the papers bearing on the question, together with this Office letter of the 17tli September 1879, had been referred by the Foreign Office to the Law Officers of the Crown, with a request that they would state whether, in their opinion, ' under the circumstances detailed in the ' correspondence, and in view of the unwillingness ' or inability of the Turkish Government to pre- ' vent outrages , on British subjects and British ' commerce in the Persian Gulf by piratical bands, ' organized in, and emanating from, territories ' under their authority and jurisdiction, the case ' was one in which Her, Majesty s Government ' would be justified in holding that the right of ' self-preservation was paramount to that of terri- ' torial inviolability, and might, consistently with ' the doctrines of international law on the subject, ' authorize the commanders of Her Majesty's ships ' to pursue the pirates and marauders in question ' in Turkish waters, and to destroy their strong- J From Foreign Office, 13th December ' holds on the Turkish mainland. + J879, No. 961. 6 3 64 c .1 ' .110 To the question, thus stated, the Law Officers* (2nd December 1879) replied with a simple negative, without giving reasons. With reference to it, the Foreign Office wrote to us on the 22nd December 1879 :—t ' The question is no doubt one of degree, de pending upon the magnitude and continuance of the evil, and the extent to which it is tolerated or neglected by the Turkish Government and officials; but, for the present, Lord Salisbury would be very unwilling that any action should l)e taken as to the legitimacy of which such grave doubt must be held to exist. Moreover, though Lord Salisbury does not deny the importance of putting a speedy check to these disturbances of the peaceful com merce of the Persian Gulf, there are, in His Lord ship's opinion, other and larger considerations of Imperial policy which render it inexpedient to adopt a course in the matter which might be re garded by the Porte as unfriendly and aggressive, or might be pointed out by other Powers as showing ait intention of subverting or weakening the Sultans authority in a portion of his Asiatic dominions.' For these reasons Lord Salisbury thought it decidedly preferable, in the first instance, to en deavour to come to some arrangement, explicit or tacit, with the Porte, by which the inconvenience resulting from the undefined nature of Turkish authority on the El Hassa coast, and from the remissness and inefficiency of the Ottoman officials in keeping the police of their waters, might as far as possible be obviated. With this expression of Lord Salisbury's views, the drafts of two Despatches on the subject to Sir H. Layard were referred for Lord C ran brook's con currence. The first draft forwarded the correspondence and papers bearing on the matter, drew attention to the material documents, noticed the action which had already been taken at Constantinople, and the absence of any mult from it in the shape either of punishment of offenders or compensation to the sutterers, and then went on : ' 'L It ,i s cle , ar ' hat a state of thiugs should of the-^rkTsh C COntmue ' eithCT ' m &gt;he interests other countries interested' I, tlle' ^mLe'L 1 of the the surrounding waters am? Uw? commerco ment are con4^Lt tKM, co-operate in anv nlm , e readily adapted to preyeut surf. 7 ' a - V seem we U irritating claims and questionsTo ''f fail to give rise.' wnich it cannot '7. They would propose for this purpose that 1 • Sir J. llolker. Sir H. Giffard. Mr. J. P. Doaite. f Horn®, No. 984. 41111 the commanders of Her Majesty's ships charged with the duty of keeping the police of the Persian Gulf, while they would he instructed to pursue their operations, as far as possible, outside the terri torial waters of the Arabian coast, between Koweit and Odeid, should also have authority to pursue and capture piratical bands within the three mile limit on that part of the coast, whenever this course of proceeding might seem indispensable to the attainment of their object. ' 8. It would be understood that in case of any Turkish vessel of war being within reach the British cruiser would not act without inviting the co-operation of its commander, and leaving to him, if he desired it, the principal share in the operations, and further that, whenever practicable, the previous consent of any Turkish Governor or similar official on the mainland immediately adjacent would be solicited. '9. In either case, any prizes made within recognized Turkish limits would be dealt with according to the wishes of the Turkish authorities. ' 10. Her Majesty's Government desire that your Excellency will endeavour to ascertain whether an arrangement of the nature described above would be accepted by the Sultan's Ministers. Its tendency would be rather to establish, than in any way to derogate from, His Majesty's authority in the districts concerned. It might be recorded in a Memorandum, or by an exchange of Notes, or in any other less formal manner best fitted to avoid raising the susceptibilities of the Porte, the prin cipal object being to obtain free scope for the measures necessary for the security of commerce, while avoiding the complaints and questions re specting territorial limits to which such measures might otherwise give rise.' This draft, it will be seen, dealt solely with the question of maritime procedure within ' recog nized ' Turkish limits, the coast from Koweit to Odeid being apparently so regarded, notwith standing that, along the greater portion of it, Turkish authority was neither asserted in any practical way, nor had been formally admitted by the British Government. The reason for this course, with the views of Her Majesty's Government on other points of Gult policy, was explained in the second (' very con fidential') Despatch to Sir H. Layard, of which the draft was as follows :— ' In the arrangement proposed in my Despatch of this day's date, for the repression of piracy in the Persian Gulf, no attempt is made at an explicit settlement of the question, how far Turkish autho rity shall be recognized to exist along the Arabian * It is to be noted, however, that, hud the coast.* Bearing in mind the exaggerated claims Porte accepted the arrangement, the very of traditional sovereignty which the Porte is always stringent conditions attached to the action of p ronei to advance, and its indisposition to abandon Sif iSh the smallest particle of the Sultans nominal juris- would, in consequence, have been practically diction, it does not seem probable that any agree* recognized as Turkish.—A. W. M.12 ment could be effected on this point, and the discussion might seriously interfere with the con clusion of any arrangement whatever. '2. The views of Her Majesty s Government upon the matter are, however, decided. Wherever the Turkish' authority is at the present time actually and firmly established upon the coast they are ready to recognize it, and would giaclly see it accompanied by a regular and civilized administration. ' 3, On the other hand, they see no advantage to the Porte, and only detriment to other countries, in vague claims of jurisdiction which have no practical enforcement, and serve merely as a pro tection for lawlessness and aggression on the part of the inhabitants of the territories so claimed. The Porte must not be surprised to find such claims ignored or contested, if the necessity should arise, and if it be found that asserted territorial rights are not justified and proved by a per formance of the corresponding duty of control. '4. Further, as regards Muscat, Bahrein, and the possessions of the Trucial Chiefs on the coast between Odeid and Ras-El-Khymah, Her Majesty s Government, while they think it unnecessary to seek for any formal declaration from the Porte, renouncing all claims of sovereignty over those territories^ are in no way disposed to recede from their repeated denial of those claims, and they con sider themselves bound by their treaty engage ments with the several Chiefs to resist any attempt, whether direct or indirect, to give them practical effect. '5. It may be desirable that, in discussing the proposals contained in my Despatch above referred to with the Turkish Ministers, you should give ex pression to those considerations, in order to show how far the arrangement is intended to extend, and what may be the possible consequence of refusing it. ' 6. It may, however, appear to you to be ad visable to abstain from any attempt at an arrange ment with the Porte of the kind mentioned, and that it would be better simply to leave to Her Majesty's naval officers a certain discretion as to visiting the waters of the El Hassa coast for police purposes, obtaining the previous consent of the local authorities, whenever possible, and taking the risk of remonstrance in other cases. This method of procedure has some recommendation on account of the known disposition of the Porte tacitly to con cede in practice much to which its official consent would never be given. But it is open to serious ob jection on other grounds. An act of indiscretion, or a distorted report from a Turkish official, might at any time be made use of to create illwill and to embarrass the course of an important negotiation upon other subjects. ' 7. Still, if your Excellency should think it ex pedient to suspend action upon the instructions contained in my Despatch, you are at liberty to do13 so. In that case I should bo glad to learn from you what alternative course you would propose to put an end to a condition of affairs for which some remedy is urgently needed.' When these drafts came under consideration, here, it was felt that, however preferable from our point of view might be the adoption of the more decided policy advocated in Sir L. Mallets letter of the 17th September, the decision as to the course to be pursued must rest with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Accordingly Lord Cranbrook's general concurrence in the tenour of the drafts was intimated to the Foreign Office in a letter dated 29th December * Home, No. 984. 1879.* It was, however, at the same time suggested that, in order that there might be no doubt as to the absolute freedom of action of the commanders of Her Majesty's ships within the territorial waters of the island of Bahrein, and to avoid any risk of misconception as to the view taken by Her Majesty's Government in regard to the status of Odeid as part of the possessions of the Sheikh of Aboothabee, one of the Trucial Chiefs, the sentence in para. 7 f ' Outside the territorial waters of the of the first draft, marginally quoted,f should run:— Arabian coast between Koweit and Odeid.' .. Outside the territorial waters of the Arabian ' mainland, north of Odeid j' } and, similarly that in the fourth paragraph of the second draft, the word ' inclusive ' should be inserted after ' Odeid ' in the sentence ' the possessions of the Trucial Chiefs on ' the coast between Odeid and B/as-el-Khymah.' There were two other points, moreover, to which it was thought necessary to draw attention; (1) the probability of evasion on the part of the Turkish Government; and (2) our obligations in the matter towards the Trucial Chiefs and Bahrein, as to which Sir H. Layard, in his communications to the Porte, referring exclusively to ' British ships' and 'British commerce' (which, in fact, had not been materially interfered with), seemed scarcely suf ficiently alive. It was accordingly observed :— ' While Lord Cranbrook is willing to hope that the arrangement proposed will be accepted by the Sultan's Ministers, and that it may prove effective in practice to restore and maintain order along the El Hassa and Guttur coasts, he cannot conceal from himself that there is, at least, a probability that the overtures of Her Majesty's Government may be met at the Porte by delay and evasion, and that, meanwhile, the evil which it is desired to suppress will continue unabated. ' His Lordship trusts that Her Majesty's Ambas sador at Constantinople may be empowered, if need be, to make clear to the Turkish Government that Her Majesty's Government will beunable to acquiesce in such a result. ' It is essential to bear in mind that the piratical outrages which form the subject of complaint have been perpetrated, not so much on British subjects 6364. D16 having followed the communication to the Porte, demi-officially, of a memorandum on the subject. The question was one of several to which Lord Granville, on assuming the office of Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, called the special atten tion of Mr. Goschen, as requiring a speedy settle ment with the Ottoman Government. Accordingly, as a renewal of piratical acts on the Guttu coast was reported, and as Abedine Pasha expressed a desire to be furnished with the views of Her Majesty's Government in writing, Mr. Goschen, on the 7tli July, addressed to the Porte a formal Note embodying the proposal con tained in Lord Salisbury's Despatch, No. 12 of 1880, of which paragraphs 6, 7, 8, and 9 were • Mr. Goschen to Earl Granville, No. 136, textually reproduced.* dat Home, t No^fiOQ. 880 Mr. Plowden, the newly appointed Political Agent of the Government of India in Turkish Arabia, being at this time in Constantinople on his way to his post, Mr. Goschen discussed the subject with him, and was furnished by him with a memorandum which was, in effect, an argument against any recognition of Turkish authority along the Arabian coast, or, at least, in favour of restrict ing such recognition within the narrowest possible limits. This view was, as Mr. Goschen observed to Lord Granville, that which had always been strongly held in the Indian Foreign Office, where Mr. Plowden had for some years been Under Secretary, but was not that indicated in Lord Salisbury's Despatch. 'The point, therefore,' he wrote, 'if I rightly ' interpret the Despatch, is not indisposition to re- ' cognize Turkish authority, north of Odeid, on ' account of political reasons adverse to the esta- ' blishment of Turkish rule on that particular part ' of the coast, but an indisposition to allow a state ' of anarchy, hostile to the interests of commerce, ' to continue Unless I hear from ' your Lordship to the contrary, I shall pursue the ' policy conveyed in Lord Salisbury's Despatch, ' No. 12, of the 5th January, and endeavour to t A8 above - « arrange with the Sublime Porte accordingly, 't The views of the Secretary of State for India (Lord Hartington) having been asked for by the x From Foreign Office, 14th August 1880. Foreign Office, J were given in a letter from Sir L. Home, 599. Mallet, dated the 30th August 1880, which, after noticing briefly the previous correspondence, and the considerations which had led Lord Cranbrook to acquiesce in the course of procedure preferred by Lord Salisbury, continued:— 'As regards Mr. PlOwden's objections, I am directed to state that his memorandum, as Mr. Goschen observes, reproduces the views of the Indian Foreign Office, which were fully considered when the correspondence of last year was in pro gress. With respect to the territorial limits within which Ottoman jurisdiction might be recognized, it was then deliberately decided that, while inter ference either at Odeid, or with Bahrein, or with16 having followed the communication to the Porte, demi-officially, of a memorandum on the subject. The question was one of several to which Lord Granville, on assuming the office of Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, called the special atten tion of Mr. Goschen, as requiring a speedy settle ment with the Ottoman Government. Accordingly, as a renewal of piratical acts on the Guttu coast was reported, and as Abedine Pasha expressed a desire to be furnished with the views of Her Majesty's Government in writing, Mr. Goschen, on the 7tli July, addressed to the Porte a formal Note embodying the proposal con tained in Lord Salisbury's Despatch, No. 12 of 1880, of which paragraphs 6, 7, 8, and 9 were • Mr. Goschen to Earl Granville, No. 136, textually reproduced.* dat Home, t No^fiOQ. 880 Mr. Plowden, the newly appointed Political Agent of the Government of India in Turkish Arabia, being at this time in Constantinople on his way to his post, Mr. Goschen discussed the subject with him, and was furnished by him with a memorandum which was, in effect, an argument against any recognition of Turkish authority along the Arabian coast, or, at least, in favour of restrict ing such recognition within the narrowest possible limits. This view was, as Mr. Goschen observed to Lord Granville, that which had always been strongly held in the Indian Foreign Office, where Mr. Plowden had for some years been Under Secretary, but was not that indicated in Lord Salisbury's Despatch. 'The point, therefore,' he wrote, 'if I rightly ' interpret the Despatch, is not indisposition to re- ' cognize Turkish authority, north of Odeid, on ' account of political reasons adverse to the esta- ' blishment of Turkish rule on that particular part ' of the coast, but an indisposition to allow a state ' of anarchy, hostile to the interests of commerce, ' to continue Unless I hear from ' your Lordship to the contrary, I shall pursue the ' policy conveyed in Lord Salisbury's Despatch, ' No. 12, of the 5th January, and endeavour to t A8 above - « arrange with the Sublime Porte accordingly, 't The views of the Secretary of State for India (Lord Hartington) having been asked for by the x From Foreign Office, 14th August 1880. Foreign Office, J were given in a letter from Sir L. Home, 599. Mallet, dated the 30th August 1880, which, after noticing briefly the previous correspondence, and the considerations which had led Lord Cranbrook to acquiesce in the course of procedure preferred by Lord Salisbury, continued:— 'As regards Mr. PlOwden's objections, I am directed to state that his memorandum, as Mr. Goschen observes, reproduces the views of the Indian Foreign Office, which were fully considered when the correspondence of last year was in pro gress. With respect to the territorial limits within which Ottoman jurisdiction might be recognized, it was then deliberately decided that, while inter ference either at Odeid, or with Bahrein, or with16 arwat is ss isssis hpfween the Turkish authorities m hi Hassa ana the tribes to the north of Odeid as might be agree- able to the parties concerned. _ „ ^ +w ' Lord Hartington is of opimou, therefoie, that Mr. Gosehen's proceedings should tc a Pproved. TTi« Lordship wonld, however, snggest that the mrtionlar attention of His Bxeelleney should be drawn to para. 4 of Lord Salisbury's 'very con- fldential' Despatch, No. 13, of the 6th January fast, which refers to possible Turkish pretensions over Muscat, Bahrein, and the possessions of the Trucial Chiefs, and re-affirms the often declared policy of Her Majesty's Government m respect to ^Balso appears to Lord Hartington fo' be very desirable that Mr. Goschen should not permit him self to be entangled in any discussion with the Porte on the territorial question, but that, in tne event of the reply to his Note being either long delaved, or evasive, or otherwise unsatisfactory in tenour, the negotiation at Constantinople should be dropped. It would then be for consideration whether the policy suggested m my letter ot the 17th September 1879 should not be reverted to. A copy of the foregoing letter was sent by Lord Granville to Mr. Goschen for his guidance.'' in termediately a further Despatch from the Am- haasador (17th August 1880, No. 254) reported a conversation he had held on the subject 'with Kaari Pasha, the Prime Minister (?), who had himselt been in the regions in question, and was more acquainted with them than the Minister for Foreign Affairs. Referring to the proposal which had been made to the Turkish Government, Mr. Goschen pointed out that the question had been mooted many months previously; that he could get no answer from the Porte: that the matter could not be allowed to drift indefinitely, as the prevalence of piracy in the Persian Gulf was inflicting constant injury on general commerce ; and that our men-of-war would be obliged to act in a somewhat high-handed manner if the Porte delayed coming to some arrangement. Kadri Pasha admitted the existence of the evil, ' but was not very precise in his promises to take ' any action,,' Mr. Goschen informed Lord Granville that he should continue to press the question, but suggested that, in the event of his being unable to obtain any satisfactory offer of an arrangement, the com manders of Her Majesty's ships of war in the Persian Gulf should be instructed 'not to allow &lt;' themselves to be too much hampered by the three-mile limit in pursuing and capturing ' pirates,' especially as the Turkish authority on * From Foreign Office, 1880. Home, No. 728. 25tli September17 * From Foreign Office, 25th September 1880. Home, No. 728. t Sir J. Holker, Sir. H. Giffard. Mr. J. P. Deane. t P. 9. § From Foreign Office, 26th October 1880. Home, No. 791. From Foreign Office, 9th March 1881. Home, No. 178. the coast was, at so many points, of a very shadowy description. Consequent upon this suggestion, the Foreign Office forwarded here* an opinion which had been given by the Law Officers of the Crownf in January 1880 (in continuation of their report of the 2nd De cember 1879) J as to the circumstances under which a resort to reprisals would be justifiable. Lord Granville, it was stated, would be inclined to call upon the Porte to reply to Mr. Goschen's note of the 7th July, and, in the event of their not agreeing to the proposals therein made, to adopt some such course as was suggested by the Ambassador; but, before deciding what instructions should be sent, His Lordship desired to be favoured with Lord Hartington's opinion on the matter. The Law Officers' opinion above referred to was as follows :— ' Should the Porte neglect to take any measures for the security of British trade in the Persian Gulf, Her Majesty's Government may, consistently with international law, endeavour to obtain from the Porte permission to act in Turkish waters against pirates and marauders, and, should this permission be refused, and the Porte continue to allow piracy in its waters. Her Majesty's Government might not improperly make such negligence a ground for reprisals. Whether either of these courses would be worth the expenses and trouble abroad, and possibly at home, we cannot form an opinion.' ' Another, and less objectionable measure, though probably not attended with any success in the present state of Turkey, would be to demand compensation in any case where British subjects or British property may have been injured in Turkish waters.' In reply to the request for Lord Hartington's opinion, the Foreign Office were informed (8th October 1880) that His Lordship agreed with Lord Granville in thinking that the Porte should be called upon for a reply to Mr. Goschen's Note. It was added that, should that reply be delayed, or be un satisfactory in tenour. Lord Hartington considered that, as previously suggested, ' the commanders of ' Her Majesty's ships engaged in the suppression of ' piracy in the Gulf should be instructed not to ' permit their operations to be hampered by con- ' siderations connected with Ottoman claims to ' jurisdiction along the coast.' Mr. Goschen was accordingly instructed § to press for a reply to his Note of the 7th July, and did so, on the 13th November 1880, in a second Note ad dressed to Assim Pasha, who contented himself by replying, on the 6th December, that his pre decessor had communicated with the Governor General of the vilayet of Baghdad on the subject; that he himself had done the same; and that he would not fail to inform the Ambassador of the result of the correspondence. H 6364. E18 Commenting on this unsatisfactory answer, Mr. Gosclien wrote to Lord Granville (6th December 1880, No. 643)* . ' Sir A. Sandison, who has had the question in his hands for two years, told me to-day that he had quite come to the conclusion that the Turkish Government did not intend to meet our wishes in this matter, and that the dilatory action they have thus far pursued they will continue to follow systematically. I have myself formed the decided opinion that it is useless to press the subject any further, and that our officers in the Persian Gulf should receive instructions based on the view that it is hopeless to expect authority from the Porte to follow the pirates within Turkish territorial waters. ' Your Lordship is aware that the Turks are at this moment unusually sensitive as to any proposals which may involve any question of sovereignty, or the introduction of European influence or action within the sphere of their own authority.' The definitive reply of the Porte was not given till the 8th February 1881,f when Assim Pasha addressed a short note to the Embassy, to the effect that, according to the information received from the local authorities, no such thing as piracy existed in the Persian Gulf; that, nevertheless, a vessel of war had been sent to the Nejd coast, as a measure of precaution; and that, under these circumstances, there was no occasion for the arrangement proposed in Mr. Goschen's Notes of the 7th July and 13th November 1880. Upon receipt of this refusal of the Turkish Government to accede to the very moderate and carefully guarded proposal which had been made to it, Lord Granville (9th March 1881) requested to be informed what were Lord Hartington's views as to the action which should be taken by Her Majesty's Government, bearing in mind, on the one hand, the opinions w r hich had been given by the Law Officers, and, on the other, Kadri Pasha's admission to Mr. Goschen that the evil complained of did exist.| The Foreign Office were informed (24th March 1881) § that, the contingency contemplated in pre vious communications from this Office having arisen, there appeared to Lord Hartington to re main no alternative but to adopt such measures as might be requisite to suppress piracy in the Persian Guit without reference to the claims asserted by the iurlash Government to sovereignty over the part of the coast particularly in question. This course H^ Lordship gathered, was in accordance with the views of Her Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople, and seemed to him to be necessary, both m the general interests of commerce and laving regard to the obligations of the British ^ Slleikl1 oi: Bahreil1 the liucial Chiefs of the Arab coast. With Lord (jranville s concurrence, therefore, His Lordship From Foreign Office, 9th March 1881. Home, No. 178. f As above. } P. 16. § Home ; No. 178.19 Memo., Part L, p. 3. f From Foreign Office, 27th May 1879. Home, No. 393. J From Foreign Office, 5th June 1879. Home, No. 415. § To India. Secret, No. 24, dated 26th June 1879. 1| India, Political, No. 95, dated 11th August 1879. f India, Political, No. 44, dated 27th April 1880. proposed to instruct the Grovernmeat of India to inform the Resident in the Gulf that the com manders of Royal Navy vessels in those waters were at liberty to act along the Arab coast in such wise as might be necessary for the capture and punishment of marauders, collision with Turkish cruisers or troops being, of course, scrupulously avoided. The issue by the Admiralty of corre sponding instructions to the Admiral Commanding in Chief on the East India Station was suggested. No immediate action was, however, taken at the Poreign Office in the matter, which meanwhile assumed a more urgent character, in consequence of threatened aggression from the mainland on the island of Bahrein. Reference has already been made to the Turkish pretensions to sovereignty over Bahrein, and their uniform rejection by the British Government.* But they have never been waived by the Porte, and the local Ottoman authorities are credited with per sistent designs to give them practical effect, and to obtain a footing in the island. In 1879 these designs took the form of a proposal to establish a coal depot there. Mr. Robertson, the Assistant Political Agent at Bussorah, was informed of the project by the Turkish Governor General himself, and he was also told by a trustworthy person that the intention was to place in charge of the depdt an agent who would be virtually a Political Agent, and whose work would be to excite among the people discontent, and a desire for annexation to Turkey .f The result of correspondence with the Foreign Office at this time was that, on the one hand, Her Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople was in structed to urge the Turkish Government to dis avow the project attributed to Abdullah Pasha, and to issue directions to the provincial authorities that it should not be carried into execution and, on the other hand, the Government of India were desired to ensure, through the Resident in the Gulf, that the Sheikh of Bahrein should refuse his assent to the establishment of the depdt, in the event of proposals being made to him.§ These instructions had, in fact, been anticipated by the Resident, who, in June 1879, obtained a promise from the Sheikh that he would take no steps in the matter without reference to him, and would act upon his advice. [J In March 1880, a Turkish ship of, war arrived at Bahrein, and her commander, acting, as he said, on the part of his Government and not merely on that of the Governor of El Hassa, preferred a formal request to have a warehouse placed at his disposal for storing coals. The Sheikh gave an evasive answer, and, when reminded by the British Resident of the assurance he had given, promised to abide by it. The Government of India,^ considering it of material importance that the depot should not beestablished, recommended that the Turkish Go vernment should he again pressed to cheek the proceedings of the local authorities; and Lord ilart- ino:ton's concurrence in this view was communi cated to the Foreign Office,* where the matter had already attracted Lord Granville's attention con sequent on a naval report forwarded by the Admi- Nothing more was heard of this specific project, hut the reports furnished from time to time by the British news agent at Bahrein indicated that attempts were being made to extend Turkish in fluence in the island. Accordingly, the Resident, Colonel Boss, proceeded to Bahrein, and, on the 22nd December 1880, concluded the following agreement with the Sheikh :—t ' I, Esau bin Ali A1 Khalifah, Chief of Bahrein, hereby bind myself, my heirs, and successors in the Government of Bahrein, to the British _ Govern ment to abstain from entering into negotiations or making treaties of any sort with any State or Go vernment other than the British without the con sent of the said British Government, and to refuse permission to any other Government than the British to establish diplomatic or consular agencies or coaling depots in our territory unless with the consent of the British Government. ' This engagement does not apply to or affect the customary friendly correspondence with^ the local authorities of neighbouring States on business of minor importance. ' The above agreement is subject to the approval and acceptance of His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor General of India in Council.' In reporting his proceedings to the Government of India (24th December 1880), Colonel Boss thus explained the considerations by which he had been actuated:— ' There has, as you are aware, been recently some reason to suppose that the authorities of the Turkish Government desired to obtain a certain influence in Bahrein by establishing an agency, which should at first and ostensibly be under the form of a coal depot. It has been the settled policy of the Government of India, in maintenance of the political relations subsisting with Bahrein, to exclude the interference of other foreign Powers in the affairs of these islands, and the Chief of Bahrein has been desired to avoid direct communication on political matters with the Turkish Government, and to decline to give permission for the establish ment at Bahrein of a coal depot by that Power. '2. It is further the case that the attention of other Powers has been, to some extent, directed to the trade, &amp;c., of the Persian Gulf. Erench, American, and Japanese vessels have been sent into these waters on special missions by the respective Governments, and other Powers have representatives in the neighbourhood. * To Foreign Office, 18th June 1880. Home, No. 374. f India, Political, February 1881. No. 19, dated 14tb21 * India, Political, No. 19, dated 14th February 1881. f To Foreign Office, 18th March 1881. Home, No. 190. J From Foreign Office, 30th March 1881. Home, No. 224. § India, Secret, No. 14, dated 8th April 1881. |1 Home, No. 224 of 1881. ^ India, Secret, No. 83, dated 27th May 1881. Enclosure 11. Memo., Part II., pp. 31, 35, 36, 38. ' 3. It is somewhat embarrassing for a ruler, situated like the Chief of Bahrein, to decline to allow the establishment of agencies or coal dep6ts without being able to point to some formal engage ment preventing. ' 4s. It has appeared to me, therefore, that to formalize the actually existing understanding with the Chief of Bahrein, by obtaining a distinct agree ment from him, would not only be a proper pre caution for the adoption of which the time has come, but would also be convenient and advan tageous to the Chief himself by furnishing him with a reason for declining the overtures of other foreign Powers which would be unanswerable and need give no offence.' Under the circumstances, it appeared to the Government of India to be desirable that the agreement thus concluded should be accepted and ratified. It did not, in their opinion, materially increase or alter the existing responsibilities of the British Government in regard to Bahrein, while its rejection might be misunderstood.* Lord Hartington, seeing no reason to dissent from this view,t and Lord Granville concurring,J the Government of India were authorized to ratify the agreement,§ which was also communicated to Her Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople for his information in case the Porte should make any further attempt to establish a footing in'the island, j] That this would be done directly was improbable, but various circumstances which occurred early in the current year indicated that the Turkish autho rities were disposed to use for their purposes Nasir- bin-Mubarik, a Bahrein refugee on the Guttur coast, and Jasim-bin-Thani, Chief of El Bidaa. Nasir, who is a relative of Mahomed-bin-Khalifa, sometime ruler of Bahrein, deposed in 1868, and since then a State prisoner in India, has long been a promoter of disturbances in the neighbourhood of the island. He receives an allowance of sixty dollars monthly from the Turkish Government.^J The Chief of El Bidaa is his fatW'-in-law, and of late years has hoisted the Turkish flag and admitted a Turkish garrison into his fort.** In December 1880, the movements of Nasir on the Guttur coast opposite Bahrein created alarm there. The local Sheikhs were warned by Colonel Ross against aiding and abetting him, and the Political Agent at Baghdad called upon the Turkish Governor General to prevent him from disturbing the maritime peace of the Gulf. That functionary, after an interval of two months, replied, as usual, that perfect tranquillity prevailed in the Gulf, and that the people of Bahrein had no cause for alarm. In fact, whether from inability to obtain boats, or from other causes, Nasir's movement at this time came to nothing, and he returned to El Bidaa. Thence he and his father-in-law carried on a correspondence with the British Hesident, with reference to certain pecuniary claims of Nasir 6364. f22 against the Slieikh. of Bahrein, concession of which, he attempted to make a condition of future good behaviour. In ^February last, Nasir-bin-Mubarik wrote a letter to Jasim-bin-Thani, stating that, unless his claims were satisfied, he would certainly attack Bahrein from Guttur, and do as much damage as possible. This letter was intended to be, and was, communicated to Colonel Boss by Jasim, who, on his part, repudiated all responsibility for Nasir's proceedings. But Colonel Boss had no doubt that the two were really acting in collusion. He therefore (26th Eebruary 1881) recommended to the Govern ment of India that the Turkish authorities should again be desired to watch Nasir, and that, instead of the Bidaa Chief's disavowal of responsibility being admitted, ' he should be specially and dis- tinctly warned that any hostile attempts headed Xi by Nasir against Bahrein would be attributed to 4 ' him.' Meanwhile, he was at once told that, should Nasir find means to disturb the peace from his neighbourhood, the consequences would be dis astrous to him. The report of a confidential agent sent by Colonel Boss to communicate with Jasim and Nasir con firmed the Besident's opinion that the former was insincere in his professions of inability to control Nasir, while the latter asserted plainly that, in addition to receiving an allowance from the Turkish Government, he was encouraged by it in his designs against Bahrein by promises of support in the event of his succeeding in gaining a footing there.* Mr. Plowden, the Political 'Agent at Baghdad, was not in favour of the further reference to the Turkish authorities suggested by Colonel Boss. He wrote to the Government of India (10th March 1881) f ' I think that past experience justifies my belief that no practical result would be likely to follow from any such communication, and it is therefore not worth while making it. If Jasim-bin-Mu- hammad and Nasir-bin-Mubarik disregard the warning conveyed in Colonel Boss's letter to the former, dated 23rd February last, I would advise that they should be dealt with under the orders of the Besident in the Persian Gulf in such manner as the circumstances of the case may seem to require. The effect of this procedure would not only be decisive as regards the two individuals named, but would greatly simplify our future course of action in the Gulf. And, although the proceedings of the Besident would probably elicit from the Turkish Government a demand for ex planation, it would not, I conceive, be very difficult to prepare an adequate answer to any reclamations which might be put forward.' of India were alive to the difficulty m dealing with the case created by the * India, Secret, No. 1881. Enclosure 11. dated 27th May, f As above. Enclosure 13. . AZ -23 P. il. f India, Secret, No. [83, 1881. J As above. Enclosure 14. § As above. Enclosure 15. As above. Enclosure 17. As above. ** Home, No. 477 of 1881. If Memo., Part I., p. 3. Turkish claim to jurisdiction at El Bidaa and other points of the Guttur coast, and to the possibility that direct dealings on their part with the Bidaa Sheikh might bring about a remonstrance from the Ottoman authorities. But the result of careful consideration was to convince them that, having regard to the necessity of defending Bahrein, which is under British protection, and to the views of Her Majesty's Government regarding the recogni tion of Turkish jurisdiction on these coasts, as announced in Lord Salisbury's Despatch to Sir H. Layard of the 5th January 1880,* they would, in the event of an expedition against the island being undertaken from the neighbourhood, not be justified in allowing vague claims of territorial rights—if unsupported by any practical attempt to discharge the correlative duties which such rights necessarily imply—to prevent them from taking measures to coerce both Nasir-bin- Mubarik and the Bidaa Chief . At the same time it seemed to them proper that every opportunity should be afforded to the Turks of using whatever authority they might possess, and might be willing to exert, upon the dated 27th May part of the coast in question.f Accordingly, the following instructions were sent by telegraph on the 7th May to the Resident in the Gulf:— ' You are authorized to warn Jasim-bin-Mu- hammad Thani that, if he is in any manner ac cessory to an attack upon Bahrein Island, he will be held directly responsible. If the attack is made, you will report again before acting against El Bidaa ; meanwhile ascertain and report whether there is any Turkish force or sign of Turkish autho rity at El Bidaa.' J Simultaneously, the Political Agent at Baghdad was desired to intimate to the Turkish authorities that, unless they could undertake to prevent and punish any attack on Bahrein Island from that part of the coast over which they claimed jurisdiction, the Government of India might be compelled, in the event of measures becoming necessary to pro tect Bahrein, or to redress injuries, to take the matter into their own hands. § Colonel Ross, on the 10th May, reported, as directed, that there was a Turkish guard, about 130 strong, at El Bidaa, and that the Turkish flag was hoisted on the fort, where the guard was stationed.]] These proceedings having been reported home to the Secretary of State,][ were referred to the Foreign Office on the 7th July last, with the following re marks :—** ' Under Articles 2 and 3 of the Treaty of 31st May 1861,ff the British Government is under an absolute obligation to protect the Sheikh of Bahrein from aggression by the neighbouring tribes, and to exact redress for injuries that may be in flicted upon the island and its dependencies. &lt;e It is obviously impossible, therefore, to tolerate24. the use, under shelter of the Turkish flag, of El Bidaa and other ports of the Arab coast as bases for piratical expeditions against Bahrein, whether such expeditions are, or are not, undertaken with the secret connivance of the Turkish authorities, from whom, as from the Porte, experience has shown it to be useless to look for redress. ' Lord Hartington accordingly proposes, if Lord Granville concurs, to approve the orders which have been issued by the Government of India, which appear to His Lordship to be judicious and proper under the circumstances. ' It may then be for the consideration of Lord Granville whether the papers should not be com municated to Her Majesty's Ambassador at Con stantinople, with authority, at his discretion, to intimate in distinct terms to the Turkish Govern ment the course which Her Majesty's Go vernment have decided to adopt in the event of aggression upon Bahrein from El Bidaa or else where.' The opportunity was at the same time taken to call attention to this Office letter of the 24!th March, relative to the instructions proposed to be sent to India on the general question of the repression of piracy in the Gulf. It was observed: — ' The papers now under notice seem to Lord Hartington to furnish strong evidence in support of the course proposed, while it appears to His Lord ship to be most undesirable that Her Majesty's Political and Naval officers in the Gulf should longer b^-left without specific instructions for their guidance in circumstances which may occur at any moment, and be attended with consequences very detrimental to British interests and credit.' Lord Grantille concurred with Lord Hartington in approving the proceedings of the Government of India in the matter of the threatened aggression on Bahrein, and that Government was informed ac cordingly on the 26ih August.* Her Majesty 's * Secret, No. 31. Ambassador at Constantinople was also authorized to intimate at his discretion to the Turkish Govern ment the purport of the orders which had been issued with the approval of Her Majesty's Govern- nie T Ilt ;t . . . t From Foreign Office, 18th August 1881. intermediately a decision was at last taken on Home, No. 595. the question of maritime procedure. On the 11th July the Admiralty were requested by the Eoreign Office, after further reference to the Law Officers of the Crown, 'to modify the in- t Memo Part II n 48 ' structions issued in May 1879,J by which the *' ' naval officers in the Gulf were prohibited, under 'certain conditions, from taking hostile action ' within Turkish territory, or its waters, and to ' instruct them not to allow themselves for the ' future to be too much hampered by the three 'mile limit in pursuing and capturing pirates' ' especially as the Turkish authority on the coast is 'at many points, of a very shadowy description.' It ^was added, ' they will scrupulously avoid any m25 ' collision with Turkish cruisers, and they will hand tc over to the Turkish officials all offenders captured ' in Turkish jurisdiction. They will report all cases ' where operations have been undertaken within ' the three mile-limit to Her Majesty's Consul ' General at Baghdad, for communication to Her * From Foreign Office, 25th July 1881. ' Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople.'* ome, No. 527. It will be observed that in these instructions no attempt is made to define the limits of e&lt; Turkish jurisdiction,' captures within which are to be handed over to the Ottoman officials, that question being apparently left to the judgment of the naval officers concerned. The orders which had been issued were com municated to Her Majesty's Ambassador at Con stantinople in a Despatch from Lord Granville (No. 515, dated 22nd July 1881), which, after noticing briefly the past history of the question, continued;—' As it is evident that the Porte is ' wanting either in the power or the will to protect ' British and general commerce in the Persian ' Gulf, and the constant representations of Her ' Majesty's Government, protesting against the ' continuance of unrestrained and unpunished ' piracy, have produced no result, it becomes in- ' cumbent on them, in the absence of the main- ' tenance of authority by the Power on which that ' duty would more naturally devolve, themselves ' to take measures for the protection of the life and ' property of the subjects of the Queen. Her ' Majesty's Government have therefore determined ' to modify the instructions issued in May 1879 to ' British naval officers in the Persian Gulf, whereby ' they were prohibited under certain conditions ' from taking hostile action within Turkish territory ' or waters. They will in future be authorized, ' when necessary, to take such measures as they ' may think Jit for the 'protection of British com- ' merce and shipping, without reference to the claims ' of the Sultan to territorial jurisdiction in those ' waters. I have to instruct your Excellency to ' make a communication to that effect to the ' Porte.' It is, perhaps, worth remarking, (1) that the passage italicized indicates a course of action con siderably beyond what has been actually authorized by the very carefully guarded instructions that have been issued; and, (2) that the reference to 'British tc commerce and shipping' might seem to imply the exclusion of the commerce and shipping of Bahrein and the Trucial Chiefs from the benefits of our direct action, which, however, can scarcely be intended. The Admiralty having instructed the Com mander-in-Chief on the East India station, in ac- % cordance with the terms of the Foreign Office letter f From Foreign Office, 26th July 1881. of the 11th July,t the papers were forwarded to Home, No, 529. the Government of India, with a request that they would issue such instructions to the Resident in the Persian Gulf as might be requisite, and apprise him of the nature of the orders which had been 6364. Gissued to the commanders of Her Majesty's vessels in those waters .J . . Before proceeding to notice the question raised by the GoTernment of India in their present letter (No. 145, dated 30th October 1881), it will be con- yenient to state shortly the practical outcome of the correspondence and discussions of the last two years. Pirst. A certain liberty of action has been given to British cruisers along the Guttur coast, subject to a proviso that captures made in Turkish juris diction are to be made over to the Turkish authori ties ; but it has been left doubtful how far along the coast Turkish jurisdiction is to be recognized as extending. Second. The Porte has been, or will be, informed that British naval officers in the Persian Gulf will be authorized to take such measures as they may think fit for the protection of British commerce and shipping, including, it is presumed, that of Bahrein and the Trucial Chiefs, without reference to the claims of the Sultan to territorial jurisdiction in those waters; but no such wide license has, in fact, been given. Third. The connection between the British Go vernment and the Sheikh of Bahrein has been made more close, by the Agreement concluded on the 22nd December 1880, by which the Sheikh binds himself to abstain from political relations with other foreign Powers. Fourth. The Resident in the Gulf has been authorized to deal directly with the Sheikh of El Bidaa, notwithstanding his relations with the Turks, in the event of his being in any manner accessory to an attack upon Bahrein; and the Sheikh has been so informed. Fifth. Formal intimation has been given to the Turkish authorities at Baghdad that, failing measures on their part to prevent and punish any attack on Bahrein from that part of the coast over which they claim jurisdiction, the Government of India will take the matter into its own hands. As to what at this date is the actual position of the Turks along the El Hassa and Guttur coasts there is little definite information. At Kateef and Ojair there are understood to be garrisons and re sponsible officials. Nevertheless, from near Kateef the notorious Beni Haji robber, Zaid-bin Mahomed, lately put to sea on a piratical cruise,* and plun dered a Bahrein boat, an occurrence which has drawn from the Sheikh of Bahrein an urgent ap peal to the Hesident in the Gulf ' to devise some ' plan for the protection of the lives and properties ' of his subjects.'! A t El Bidaa there is a Turkish garrison, and the Chief flies the Turkish flag; yet he is now threaten ing hostilities against a'tribe in the immediate neighbourhood of Kateef, in Turkish territory. That the authority of the Turks along the coast is extremely unstable, and liable to be overturned by any serious combination of the Arab tribes, there is little doubt. In April last, the Eesident in the X To India, August 1881. Secret, No, 28, dated 5th From Foreign Office, 31st October 1881, Home, No. 783. f Letter from 1881, No. 59. Resident, 3rd November27 * Nejd. This term has been rather loosely applied to the coast districts of El Hassa and Kateef, as -well as to that portion of Central Arabia to which alone it strictly belongs. See Memo, by Mr. W. Blunt, in Foreign Office letter of 2nd July 1880 (Home, No. 484), according to whom Nejd, properly so called, is independent, in all but name, of the Porte.—A. W. M. t Political, No. 67, dated 27tb May 1881. J Aitchison, ^ol. VII., p. 70. § For a Note by Sir C. Aitchison, when Foreign Secretary, which has a bearing on this question, and takes a different view, see this Memo., Part I,, pp. 16 and 17.—A. W. M. || Secret, No. 83, dated 27th May 1881. Enclosure ,12. ^ See Memo., Part II., pp. 39, 42, 50. l * Political, No. 79, dated 24th June 1881. ft Secret, No. 145, dated 30th October 1881. Enclosure 3. Gulf was informed that a person had arrived at Bussorah, bearing a message from Abdallah-bin- Feysal, Amir of Itiadh,* to the effect that although all the Nejd tribes had allied themselves with him, and were ready to attack El Hassa and El Kateef, he had restrained them, proposing that those places should be farmed by him from the Turkish Govern ment, and adding that on the answer to this pro posal depended the action of the tribes.f Nothing however, seems to have come of this. On the whole, it is perhaps not going too far to say that, as between us and the Turkish Govern ment, the territorial question has been shelved, not solved, and that our attitude towards the petty Chiefs and tribes on the Guttur coast still remains to be determined. The Government of India now formally refer for the orders of Her Majesty's Government the question what that attitude is to be as regards Jasim-bin- Thani, Chief of El Bidaa. His position towards the Turks has been already stated, more than once. As will have been ob served, he is in constant communication with the British Resident in the Gulf, and his father in 1868 concluded a formal agreement! with the then Resident (Colonel Pelly), by which he bound him self, amongst other things, ' on no pretence what- ' soever at any time to put to sea with hostile ' intention, and, in the event of disputes or mis- ' understanding arising, invariably to refer to the ' Resident.' The Government of India remark that this agreement had something of a personal character, and that its force may be held to have been weakened if not annulled by the Turkish assumption of authority over El Bidaa. § Nevertheless, it is to be observed that a letter from Jasim to Colonel Ross, dated 9th March 1881, contained a distinct reference to it as a ' Treaty. '|| In May last Jasim wrote to the Resident to the effect that he proposed to settle some of his people at Odeid, a place which has been ruled to belong to the Chief of Abuthabi, one of the Trucial Chiefs, and therefore beyond the limit of anv possible Turkish jurisdiction direct^f &lt; indirect: . The fact was. Colonel Ross wrote to the Govern ment of India, Jasim was uneasy about his position both with the Turkish Government and the Bedouin tribes, and would gladly, if he saw his way, come again under the protection of Government, and wished to prepare a place beyond Turkish limits to which he would have recourse himself in emergency. His proposal was, however, inadmissible, and he was so informed.** In reply, Jasim wrote (3rd May) that the Chief of Abuthabi had nothing to do with Odeid, which was part of Guttur, which belonged to the Wahabis, and was therefore Turkish, so far as the mainland was concerned, adding, ' the seas and what is ' connected with it are under the British Govern- 6364.28 Colonel Eoss declined discussion, but repeated that the proposal was inadmissible. At the end of July Jasirn addressed three further letters to the Hesident. Of these, one intimated his abandon ment of the Odeid project; another announced 'that he was about to proceed by sea to the neigh bourhood of Kateef, in order to attack the Ajman tribe, against which he had a grievance; while the third declared his intention of seizing in the terri tory of the Beni Yas (Abuthabi) a certain Sheikh, Bhataye-bin-Khadim, head of the Gubeysat tribe formerly of Odeid, who owed him money, and had broken an engagement. Writing to the Government of India on the ■subiect of these communications (16th August),* * Secret No. 145, dated 30th October i -i 1881. Enclosure 4. Oolonel Eoss observed :— « A movement from El Bidaa to the Kateef coast 'by sea of the sort Sheikh Jasim contemplates, or affects to contemplate, would have a disturbing -effect, and probably be the signal for the renewal of piracies and disorders in those waters, and I am therefore requesting the Sheikh to refrain from the proceeding. I do not feel sure, however, whether I would be in a position to interfere actively- to prevent the proposed expedition under existing relations. The father of Sheikh Jasim certainly engaged in 1868 not to make war by sea, but, since then, the political status of the Sheikhs of El Bidaa has been changed by the acceptance by them in 1871 of the Turkish flag and a Turkish garrison, and I doubt whether it would be deemed advisable to remind Jasim of the agreement referred to. The whole question of the political jurisdiction over that part of the Arabian coast has been so fully discussed that it is unnecessary to go into it again now. ' With regard to Sheikh Jasim's announcement of his intention to seize Sheikh Bataye, as the latter resides in the Beni Yas territory, it is to be inferred that Jasim means to threaten a hostile incursion into Beni Yas waters, in which the mari time peace is maintained under British auspices. Such action it would be impossible to permit with ^due regard to British rights and obligations, but, unless actively assisted by the Turkish Government, Jasim is not likely to venture to attack the more powerful Beni Yas.' To Jasim, Colonel Boss wrote (16th August) two letters, one requesting him to refrain from any movement to the Kateef coast by sea, as it would lead to general disturbance, another warning hi ™ -that he would not be permitted to make any hostile maritime expedition on waters where the maritime truce was in force. The Besident s report of his proceedings was replied to by the Government of India (4th October) 'l T1 'Frvl 1 /'VtiTl v» m 4 '/'v-*-»wr* r* • »L yA i. „ 1-.^» in the following terms :—f f Secret, No. 145, dated 30th October ' 3. The Governor General in Council has con sidered your proposals, and they have his approval. The preservation of the maritime truce is a matter 1881. Enclosure 5.Mi 1 30th October * Secret, No. 145, *&lt;881. Enclosure 9. ed 30th October dated 30th October 29 of importance, and the Sheikh was rightly given to understand that he would not be permitted to disturb it. The question of the Sheikh's projected expedition to the Kateef coast stands on a somewhat different footing, and the Governor General in Council considers that you acted with prudence in not authoritatively forbidding it. This point will be referred for the orders of Her Majesty's Govern ment in connection with the general question of Turkish jurisdiction on the Arabian coast of the Gulf. Meanwhile the Sheikh's proposed expedition to El Kateef should not be prevented by force. ' 4. I am, however, to, add that, if the proposed expedition should lead to any act of piracy, you will be able to deal with it under the instructions recently issued by the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty regarding the pursuit of pirate craft beyond the three-mile limit.' Intermediately, the Chief of El Bidaa (9th Sep tember) replied to Colonel Ross's letter of the 16th August, to the effect that it was not his intention to undertake maritime expeditions without the Resident's permission. Upon learning this the Government of India (26th October) sent the following further instruc tions to Colonel Ross * 44 2. The question of the Sheikh's projected ex pedition to the Kateef coast has already been referred for the orders of Her Majesty's Government, and, in the meantime, with reference to the connection between Jasim-bin-Muhammad and the Turks, you have been instructed not to prevent it by force. Erom the enclosure to your letter, it now appears possible that, notwithstanding this connection, the Sheikh may be willing to admit as binding on hi m the engagement made by his father in 1868. Should this be the case, the result may be to con tribute materially to the security of Bahrein and the neighbouring seas, and I am therefore to request that the point may be borne in mind, and that, if a suitable opportunity should occur, you will endeavour to ascertain whether the engagement can still be treated as in force.' In reporting to the Secretary of State the cor respondence and the foregoing orders, and requesting instructions with respect to the general question of the future relations of the Chief of El Bidaa with the British Government, the Government of India observe:— '4. Your Lordship is aware that the Sheikh is nominally under Turkish jurisdiction, a fact which greatly complicates our dealings with him in all cases, and, in the present instance, his proposal is of such a nature that there is some reason to doubt whether the British Government would be justified in actively interfering against him. The Kateef coast is in such close proximity to Bahrein that any expedition to this neighbourhood may easily have the effect of disturbing the security of the island, while it would also, in all probability, lead30 to the renewal of piracies and disorder m the adioininff waters. On the other hand, there is no definite ground for regarding, the expedition as directed against our feudatory, so that we haTe some hesitation in treating it as a matter to which your Lordship's orders of the 26th August would apply; and further, until piracies actually result from the despatch of the-force, it appears to us that our cruisers cannot act against the Sheikh s boats under the instructions conveyed in your Lordship's Despatch, No. 28, of the 5th August, by which we were informed that Her Majesty's vessels need not be too much hampered by the three-mile limit in pursuing pirate craft into Turkish waters. Under these circumstances, Colonel Ross has not thought it proper to interfere authoritatively in order to prevent the expedition, and we have expressed con currence in, and approval of, his views. The question as to our relations with the Chief of El Bidaa seems rather to have settled itself, at all events for the present. He has professed his intention to abstain from maritime war without permission of the British Resident, and, so long as he acts up to this profession, we may be satisfied, and need not concern ourselves with the nice point how far his deference to Colonel Ross's counsels and warnings is consistent with his acceptance, voluntary or the reverse, of Turkish jurisdiction. In the event, on the other hand, of his putting to sea, the course to be followed must depend upon circumstances. We are certainly not bound to protect Turkish territory against attack by a Turkish feudatory. But it is our declared policy to maintain the peace of the seas, which the Turks cannot or will not do. That must be understood to be the meaning of the instructions lately issued to the commanders of British vessels in Gulf waters, which may reasonably be read in the light of Lord Granville's explanatory Despatch* to Her * P- Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople, and ought not to be construed in the somewhat pedantic fashion adopted by the Government of India. A. W. M. Political and Secret Department, 2nd December 1881.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0003dd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B19/3</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0003dd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B19/3</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persian Gulf - Turkish jurisdiction along the Arabian coast (Part III)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1881/1881</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-06T15:59:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation for this description commences at folio 4 and terminates at folio 18, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 4-197; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the bottom right corner of each folio.Pagination: the document also has an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A printed memorandum written and compiled by Adolphus Warburton Moore for the Political and Secret Department of the India Office, and dated 2 December 1881.The document is a continuation of 'Persian Gulf - Turkish jurisdiction along the Arabian coast (Part II)' (IOR/L/PS/18/B19/2) and broadly addresses the same issues, namely, how to respond toTurkish claims to sovereignty along the southern coast of the Gulf that could potentially impinge on Britain's commitments with local rulers (in Bahrain and the Trucial Coast) and their security responsibilities at sea (the suppression of piracy).The document summarises correspondence from the previous two years (1879-1881) that had dealt with the matter, beginning with an outline of the opinions of officials from the main departments and institutions involved: the Foreign Office, the Government of India, and the India Office (whose opinion Warburton represents). Other correspondents include officials from the Residencies and Agencies in both the Persian Gulf and Turkish Arabia, as well as the Ambassador at Constantinople.The documents cover several topics, including:The threat to Bahrain from the Beni Hajir tribe and Ottoman ambitions to extend their sovereignty to the island, including the Turkish plan to build a coal depot on the island as a pretext to further political involvement;Questions of how to police the waters under Turkish authority;How Britain should deal with Shaikh Jasim [Jāsim bin Muḥammad Āl Thāni] of El Bidaa [Doha];Turkish claims to parts of the coast of Guttur [Qatar].The document concludes with the perceived outcomes of the discussions, including closer ties with the ruler of Bahrain, who, in December 1880, agreed not to open relations with any foreign power other than Britain.The author quotes extensively from the correspondence and other sources, notes on which are to be found in the margin throughout.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Assistant Secretary to the Political and Secret Department,</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of the Ottoman Empire</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Emir of Qatar Jāsim bin Muḥammad Āl Thānī</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Banī Hājir (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>El Bidaa</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Piracy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sovereignty</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imperialism</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0003dd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>