<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ad_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:42:12.668Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">( 2 ) Notes. Register No. P. z. SECRET. Minute Paper. 9318/35. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT . ^ V/ r Dated Rec. 193 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State.., Committee Under Secretary.... Secretary of State... /C A ARABIA . Foreign Office Memorandum entitled 'Tire Seven Independent Arabian States” (Yemen, Asir, the Hejaz, Nejd, Koweit, Jebel Shammar, and Jauf),/'giving an outline of these States at the time of the Arab rising of June 1916.’ Copy of India/ to Bushfre q |' Bahrein £o4eit. ZAs&gt; FOR INFORMATION. This memorandum provides a concise and convenient background for the study of more recent events in Arabia, and should prove a useful document for reference purposes. l/ol Previous papers V t /icr /j V/tt/u uwcl tM/U iruh** ^ ' C. f.P. oJmU- '4pao, ^ . /1A iL ^ (KCtuth ^ ^ H~LfoJhuwuJx (/j . (# iA lmmmmm m ^ &gt;; j *\ ' In any further communication on this subject please quote No.L 2958/2958/405 and address— not to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 27th December, 1935. Sir, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to transmit to you herewith to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, six copies of a Foreign Office memorandum of May, 1935, entitled 'The Seven Independent Arabian States', giving a brief outline of each of the seven States at the time of the Arab rising against the Turks in June 1916. 2. I am to request that, if no objection is seen, copies of the memorandum may be communicated to the Government of India, His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire and the Political Agents at Bahrain and Koweit, the remaining copies being for retention in the India Office. 1 am, Sir, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETT* NO. 2 9 JAN 1936 FROM SIOR 'ARY, POLITICAL AMD SEaRrr DEPT. INDIA OFFICE tSOPY SENT TO-jhu/yy^o ^ ■ THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT r p 7 “ CONFIDENTIAL. (14706) j 9318 | • 1955 J THE SEVEN INDEPENDENT ARABIAN STATES.('j THE purpose of this paper is to give a brief outline of each of the seven independent Arabian States at the time of the Arab rising against the Turks in June 1916. As the part played by the rulers of these States depended largely on the physical character and economic resources, the manner and life of the people and the form of faith held by them, it has been necessary to touch upon these factors. The regions of South-Eastern Arabia, including the Aden Protectorate, the Hadramaut, the Sultanate of Oman, the Trucial Coast and Qatar, which are in effect cut off from the remainder of the peninsula by the Great Desert, and therefore played little part in the ambitions of the greater Arab rulers and the consequent political and military issues, are excluded. The seven autonomous areas referred to are :— (1) The Imamate of the Yemen ruled by the Imam Yahya. (2) The Principate of Asir ruled by the Idrisi. (3) The Emirate of Mecca (or the Hejaz) ruled by Husein, Emir and Sherif of Mecca. (4) The Emirate of Nejd, ruled by Ibn Saud, Emir of Riyadh. (5) The Sheikhdom of Koweit, ruled by the Sheikh of Koweit. (6) The Emirate of Jebel Shammar, ruled by Ibn Rashid, Emir of Hail. (7) The vague territory containing the Oasis of Jauf, and various outlying oases, in possession of Nuri Bey esh Shalan, Paramount Chief of the Ruwalla. At the time of the outbreak of war in 1914 these seven States were more or less autonomous areas. Each area was vaguely defined, each peopled by a group of loosely united tribes, and each governed by a personal ruler who received the varying degrees of allegiance, which the self-interest of the tribes prompted and which the ruler found possible or politic to enforce.( 2 ) Each area, except those of Jebel Shammar, Koweit and Jauf, had a distinct political history extending back for more than a century, and, in the case of Mecca, for many centuries. Each had political aspirations prompted, not only by the ambitions of its rulers, but by obvious considerations of advantages for the tribal group, and each had its own particular and traditional enemies and allies. In differing degree, too, these embryonic States were subjected to exterior influence, exerted chiefly by the Ottoman Empire and Great Britain. I .—The Imamate of the Yemen. Though chiefly a mountainous country, the Yemen is the most fertile and closely settled area in Arabia, and in 1916 contained a population of about a million. The capital is Sana. The inhabitants of the highland Yemen, a race of hardy and warlike cultivators, hold the Zeid creed, a schismatic form of Shiahism judiciously modified in the direction of Sunnism. The lowland popula tion, on the other hand, are chiefly Orthodox Sunnis. In theory the position of the ruling Imam is that of an elective spiritual leader, but in practice the office has tended to become hereditary. Turkish administration regarded the Yemen as part of the Turkish vilayet of the name. The whole vilayet comprised the three sanjaks of Sana, Hodeida and Taiz in the mediatised province of the Yemen; the fourth, Asir, formed part ( 1 ) This memorandum was prepared by the late Mr. W. J. Childs and found among his papers. A few modifications and additions have been made to bring it up to date. May 1935. ( 2 ) Complications existed in consequence of a custom well recognised in Arabia by which tribes occupying land within one autonomous area would sometimes prefer to give theoretical allegiance to the ruler of another autonomous area, as being more distant and therefore less likely to exercise an unwelcome authority. 8056 [11932] B2 of the autonomous territory ruled by the Idrisi of Asir. for reasons, not altogether obvious, the Turks from the first made greater efforts to maintain their hoid over the Yemen and the adjoining territory of Asir than any other part ol Arabia. Complete Turkish occupation was effected at the close oi the 16th century. Since then the history of the Yemen has been one of intermittent rebellion and Turkish suppression, attended by wide variations of fortune. 9 Notwithstanding remoteness from the sources of Turkish power and the difficult nature of the country for campaigning, the Yemen was the part of Arabia where Turkish occupation and influence were most effective at the outbreak ot war in 1914. It was then a mediatised province subject to Turkish suzerainty and garrisoned by Turkish troops. The ruler, the Imam Yahya, though opposed to the Turks, nevertheless found advantage in supporting Turkish power during the war. The upshot was that the Yemeni Turks were strong enough to invade the Aden Protectorate, defeat a British force at Loheiya m July 1915, and penetrate to the suburbs of Aden itself. Though ejected thence they were able to maintain themselves at Loheiya until the conclusion of the war. The Imam was more or less friendly towards the Emir of Mecca, but a standing enmity existed between him and the Idrisi of Asir. In the rivalry between Hejaz' Nejd and Jebel Shammar, the Yemen, chiefly owing to its geographical situation, had little part. II. — The Princi'pate of Asir ruled by the Idrisi. The boundaries of Asir as it existed as a separate State were indeterminate in the north and east, and the name was vaguely applied to a much greater area than that of the original district. Nor did the authority of the Idrisi run over the eastern part of the territory, which was later included in the name. In 1914 Asir, according to Turkish theory, was the northern sanjaik of the Ottoman vilayet of the Yemen. This claim, however, was little more than a theory. The port of Qunfideh and the inland towns of Mohail and Abha were precariously held by Turkish garrisons, whose hold extended, sometimes more, sometimes less, over the roads connecting these places. The tribes east of the central mountains recognised the authority of the Sherif of Mecca rather than that of the Turks or the Idrisi. The remainder of the country, a strip about 350 miles in length extending along the Red Sea from a point a little north of Loheiya, on the borders of the Yemen, to Lith on the borders of the Hejaz, and reaching inland for a depth of about 80 miles to the crest of the central mountains, was either administered by the Idrisi or had been brought into federation with him. The chief town was Sabia in the district of Abu Arish, the southernmost province of Asir. With a population, which shortly after the war was estimated roughly at li millions, the area under either the rule or influence of the Idrisi was the most populous of all the autonomous regions in Arabia. Owing to favourable conditions of fertility and precipitation of moisture, it also contains the largest proportion of cultivators settled on the land. In physical configuration Asir comprises long belts of lowland lying east and west of central highlands, which form a northward continuation of the Yemeni mountains. The inhabitants are chiefly of the Sunni belief, with a small proportion of Zeidis and Wahabis. Asir was nominally a part of the Vilayet of Yemen, but although the Turks made repeated attempts ever since the 17th century to conquer the district, they were never completely successful. An Egyptian expedition which invaded the country in 1834 was destroyed. It was not until 1869, after the opening of the Suez Canal had enabled the Turks to transport their troops by water, that their operations against Asir and the Yemen were resumed in earnest. In 1871 the Turkish occupation of Asir reached its greatest limits. It continued thus until 1910 when the Idrisi succeeded in confining Turkish garrisons to the insignificant area they held in 1914. The southern province of Asir has a long tradition of independence against all comers, whether Zeidi tribes of the Yemen, Sunni tribes of the Asir central highlands, Turks or Egyptians. It was in this province of Abu Arish that the family of the Idrisi rose to power. About 1833, a native of Fez named Seyyid Ahmed-el-Idnsi, the venerated head of a religious school whose tenets he had preached at Mecca for more than3 thirty years, bought land in Sabia, the capital of Abu Arish. There he settled and died in 1837, leaving a reputation of sanctity. As an incident ot keyyia Ahmed’s career, he had been the teacher of the original Senussi, who took tne covenant in his tariqah at Mecca in 1823. This accident had a consi era e bearing upon the subsequent fortunes of the Idrisi family, which increased in wealth and influence, and, in 1841, supplanted the sherifial family ol Abu Ansn after Asir had been renounced by the Egyptians. The Idrisi house mtermarrie with the Senussi house, which was now settled in Cyrenaica, m Egypt and m tne Sudan. But the chief expansion of Idrisi power was achieved by feeyyid Mohammed, the Idrisi who ruled in Abu Arish during the Great ^Var, the grea grandson of that Seyyid Ahmed who had taught at Mecca. . Seyyid Mohammed was born at Sabia in 1876, and educated partly a A1 Azhar, Cairo, and by the Senussi at Kufra. He returned to Sabia about 1900 cherishing the ambition of making Asir independent. By 1910 he had succeeded in reducing Turkish occupation to Ibha, Muhail and Qunfideh, but t( J capture Ibha owing to effective assistance given to the Turks by the Sherit ot Mecca. During the Italian war with Turkey he was assisted by the Italians with arms and supplies and made his position in southern Asir secure, though at t e time the Sherif of Mecca managed to suborn a large number of his tribal supporters whose territories lay outside Abu Arish. During the Balkan war o 1912-13, however, the Idrisi recovered his influence with these tribes. In 1914 he sought to obtain recognition of his position in Abu from the Government of the Young Turks. He failed, and in consequence declared against them when they carried Turkey into the war. In May 1915 he signed an anti- Ottoman treaty with the Resident; Asir was supplied by His Majesty s Govern ment with arms and munitions and took the field in the following June with a force of 12,000 men. His purpose was to capture Loheiya, but being unsuccessful in the attempt he withdrew to his own territory at the end of the year, made a truce with the Imam Yahya, and ceased operations against the Turks until the Heiaz rising began in June 1916. After the fall of Jedda in the same month he promised co-operation with the Sherif of Mecca, and offered to subordinate his own interests to the needs of the common cause, but did not abate his claim to the whole of Asir. * . , , . When Qunfideh surrendered in July 1916 the town was occupied on his behalf by the sheikhs of Birk, who hoisted the Idrisi’s flag. This step affronted the Sherif of Mecca, who despatched a force against the town, but the Idrisi refused to withdraw his garrison and threatened to go over to the Turks whom he was blockading in Muhail and Ibha. In August, however, he evacuated the place, but at the same time raised his blockade of the Turkish garrisons, and his subsequent attitude towards His Majesty’s Government was one of discontent, if not of active disloyalty. „ , * i • u -la r This Idrisi was a man of almost negroid type, tall and powerful m build, of great energy and decidedly intelligent. In pursuit of his ambitions he was seriously handicapped by absence of noble lineage; among Arab rulers, in fact, he was regarded as yobvvBuu. For him the Turks had an implacable enmity and the Imam of the Yemen was little less hostile. The Sherif of Mecca despised him. “ He was,” the sherif once said, “ a man whom no one recognises to be anything, having made himself sheikh, and landed in some place which was not ruled by anyone.” The sherif’s own interests, however, eventually compelled him to keep on friendly terms, and he endeavoured to mediate between the Idrisi and the Imam. The only Arabian ruler really friendly with the Idrisi was Ibn Baud, ruler of Nejd. XU. The Emirate of Mecca (or the Hejaz) ruled by Husein, Emir and Sherif of Mecca. According to pre-war Turkish administrative theory, the Hejaz was an Ottoman vilayet extending northward from Qunfideh on the borders of Asir to the head of the Gulf of Akaba, sometimes including the town of Akaba, some times losing it to the Vilayet of Syria. Its eastern boundary was indeterminate, but included the oasis of Khaibar. In native opinion at this time, however, and also in the practical administration of the Hejaz, the northern boundary lay much farther south than Akaba. In practice the northern limit adopted was a line drawn inland from the coast a little north of Wejh so as to include the oasis [11932] b 24 of Khaibar. This boundary was accepted by the Ottoman Government and supported by the demands of religious prejudice, which forbade Christians to use the Heiaz Railway farther south than Medain Saleh, just outside the ower boundary in question, unless for special official reasons. The Hejaz, so dehned, had a length from north to south exceeding 600 miles, and a depth inland, including Khaibar, of about 200 miles. The vilayet was divided into tour kazas : Yambo, Rabigh, Jedda and Lith. * Physically, this western littoral of Arabia comprised, m a broad view, a Deit of coastal lowland, a parallel belt of mountain and highland, and then a parallel belt of falling country which merges into the interior plateau ot Arabia, ine principal surface characteristic of the Hejaz is a general barrenness due to lack of moisture. Oases are few and small; the largest the one in which Medina stands. The total population in 1916 was estimated as less than 1 million. .Only one-sixth of the inhabitants are settled in towns and on the land; the remainder are Bedouins, partly or wholly nomadic. . . Various circumstances combined to place the Hejaz in a position by itsell among the autonomous areas of Arabia. It is the Holy Land of Islam, and its two holy cities of Mecca and Medina, respectively the birthplace and burial place ot Mahomet, are the chief shrines of pilgrimage for the great Sunni sections of Prophet’s followers. This accidental endowment has determined the whole subsequent course of the country’s history. The annual pilgrimage of scores of thousands directly or indirectly provided the means of existence for a large proportion of the population^ 1 ) The attraction of the Holy Places for Moslems led to the construction of the Hejaz Railway to Medina in 1908, and though nominally an act of piety, this extension from Damascus, as part of the Turkish railway system, had far-reaching political and military aims, for it made Hejaz more accessible to Turkish arms than any other portion of Arabia. lurther, the importance of the Holy Places in the world of Islam conferred upon the holder of the Emirate and Sherifate of Mecca, which included the Hejaz, a standing and influence vastly greater than that of a merely local Arabian ruler. The position of the Emir and Sherif(‘) of Mecca, indeed, combined both temporal and religious power. For the “ reigning head of the dominant sherifial family is ex officio Chief of the Prophets’ tribe, the Qoreish, and Hereditary Keeper of the Holy Places.” It should be noted, however, that the religious bases of sherifial power lay not in any divine attribution, but in reverence for descent from Mahomet and respect for the sherif as an individual who had been entrusted with such lofty duties as were his by right. The Emirate of Mecca dates from the 10th century and was an outcome ot disintegration which overtook the early caliphial rule of the Moslem world. From that period until the close of the 18th century the Emirate was always the de facto power in the Hejaz. The Ottoman effort to exercise suzerainty, which began in 1538, was effective only while the high fighting prestige of Turkish arms continued; with the decline of that prestige at the end of the 17th century Turkish power in the Hejaz also declined, until, in 1783, it was represented by a single garrison precariously holding the port of Jedda. But from this time the Emirate was confronted by dangers more serious than any heretofore. The pilgrims of the Haj were first attacked by Wahabi raiders from Nejd in 1783, an outrage many times repeated in subsequent years, despite the Emir of Mecca. In 1803 a Wahabi expedition took and sacked Mecca itself, and, as an incident of the raid, beheaded twenty sherifs. In 1804 another expedition assaulted and took Medina. At this stage the great pilgrim caravans from all parts of the Mahometan world ceased. In 1810 the Wahabi Emir again entered the Holy Cities, plundered the Tomb of Mahomet at Medina, which he caused to be opened, and broke the Kaaba (the Black Stone) at Mecca in pieces. Spoliation of the Faithful on pilgrimage, complete interruption of the Haj, outrage upon the sacred shrines of Islam, at last moved the Ottoman Sultan to action. As Protector of all Moslems he did what in him lay and Turkish forces being unavailable, he sent his Mahomet Ali from Egypt against the Wahabis, an adventure which the latter, with an alert eye to his own ambitions for independence, gladly undertook. The ( 3 ) In normal pre-war times the pilgrimage accounted for an annual influx of nearly half a million persons into Hejaz. ( 4 ) “Grand Sherif of Mecca” was a European form of title. Arabs called the ruler of Mecca Emir, and addressed him as Seyyidna (our Lord).Egyptian conquest of Nejd, completed in 1817, led the way to Egyptian rule being established in the Hejaz until 1840. During this period the Emirate of was reduced to a form of authority more shadowy and unreal than any it had known before. In 1840, however, the Porte resumed control. Turkish Government began firmly, and being favoured by dissension among the tribes, prevented an ^ immediate recovery by the Emirate of its old status. Natural forces, making for a return to the autonomous condition, were, however, at work in the country. Progress was definite, if slow. Notwithstanding the consolidation of 1 urkish power in the Hejaz by Ottoman Pasha during 1886, the Emir of that time, Aun-er-Rafiq, not only retained but improved the privileged position he had recovered. The truth was that Emirs of Mecca were able to do what Turkish authority in the Hejaz never could achieve; they were able to call out Bedouin levies, with which, if so minded, they could give the Turks invaluable military support in the Arabian provinces. Emirs of Mecca, therefore, were recognised as chiefs with whom it paid the Turks, even at the cost of large concessions, to be on good terms. In this situation the power of the Emirs could hardly fail to increase with any decline of Ottoman power. And such, in fact, was what happened. At this point it becomes necessary to give closer attention to the Emirate and the affairs of the Hejaz in the years which immediately preceded the war. The E'mirate was never, in theory, hereditary or restricted, except by pre scription, to any of the Ashraf clans( 5 ) or families. For at least a century past the Emirs were appointed by the Power occupying the Hejaz, but the Ottoman Government kept to the Abadilah house after 1827, with the exception of the periods 1851-6 and 1880-2, when it chose Emirs from the rival house of Dhawi Zeid. The Emir always stood at the great disadvantage that members of other Ashraf clans, or of the Emir’s own house, considered themselves equally or better entitled to the Emirate. Mecca always contained a strong element in opposition to the ruling house, and an Emir seldom avoided having foes within his own household; in fact, one son was as likely to claim the succession as another. Husein Ibn Ali, who took the title of King of the Hejaz in 1916 and died in 1925, was a grandson of the first Abadilah Emir (who died in 1857) and was nominated to the Emirate by Kiamil Pasha, the Anglophil Turkish Grand Vizier, in 1908. In 1908 Husein had then been long resident in Constantinople. His uncle, Abadilah, had been nominated to the position before him, but died when on the way to Mecca to assume office. Husein’s cousin, Ali, the previous Emir, had been banished with all his family, and his other cousins, the children of Aun-er-Rafiq, Emir from 1882 to 1905, were also debarred by the Porte. In this way the choice fell eventually upon Husein. It should be recorded, as throwing light on certain aspects of King Husein’s character, that his mother was a Circassian. He was appointed to the Emirate, when approaching 60 years of age, as a man of pacific character who would serve the Turkish Government’s aims and keep on good terms with Great Britain. At first he seemed to fulfil the Porte’s intentions well. In 1910 he called out his tribes in support of the Turks against the Idrisi’s revolt in Asir, relieved a Turkish garrison besieged in Abha, and reduced the Idrisi’s power. In the same year he sent an expedition to Qasim to assert the rights of the great Hejazi tribe of the Ateibah, and though, owing to defection by Ibn Rashid, Eimir of Hail, his force had to retire without any considerable military achievement, he was able to make an arrangement with Ibn Saud, Emir of Nejd, whereby the Ateibah tribe remained free of that Emir’s taxation. At the same time he enforced the right of the Meccan Treasury to contributions from Qasim. Husein’s influence was thus extended to Central Arabia. Soon afterwards he gave his protection to fugitive rebels from Ibn Saud, who, having been given refuge by the Ateibah, drew upon that tribe the reprisal of a raid by the Emir of Nejd. This incident notwithstanding, the Meccan Emir’s relations with Ibn Sand remained outwardly peaceable. Meanwhile, Husein’s pro-Turkish attitude was undergoing a change. Prompted apparently by his second son, Abdullah, credited with being his father’s ( fi ) The Ashraf (sherifial clansmen) were the descendants of Hassan, grandson of the Prophet. There are some twenty-one clans of this descent in Arabia, fifteen of which live in or near to Mecca. In numbers the clans are small. Theoretically, Emirs of Mecca might be chosen from any Ashraf clan; but for many centuries practice confined the succession to the Abadilah, Dhawi Zeid, Dhawi Barakat and Dhawi Surur, with a great preponderance of Abadilah Emirs since 1827, when Mahomet Ali of Egypt put aside the Dhawi Zeid.successor designate, he began to cherish the design of freeing the Emirate from dependence on Turkey, and though professing himself to have no ambition towards the Caliphate, the same could not be said for Abdullah, either as his father s adviser or, perhaps, when considering his own future interests. Husein, in fact, had made effective use of his earlier expeditions in support of the Ottoman Power to organise and train a Bedouin force, which he intended to employ for his own ^ purposes if need or opportunity should arise. In 1913 he was able to follow a policy definitely in opposition to Turkish aims. He openly opposed the extension of the Hejaz railway southward to Mecca and supported his Harb tribesmen in their vehement hostility to this and other Turkish designs. When war broke out in 1914 he refused his assistance to the Turks in raising troops from the Hejaz, but he continued to organise the tribesmen for insurrection when the moment should come. He reconciled himself with the Idrisi and endeavoured to unite that prince and the Imam of the Yemen with himself in following a common anti- Ottoman policy. In 1915 he sent Abdullah to Central Arabia to make peace between Ibn Rashid of Hail and Ibn Baud, and to obtain again payments to Mecca from Qasim and Sedeir in northern Nejd. The strength of the Emir’s position before the Arab rising began may be judged by the consideration shown to him by the Turks. He received a large annual subsidy from the Ottoman Treasury. He was styled “ Highness.” He had his own force of Arab regulars, paid by himself, and his own police, who exercised authority as far south as eastern Asir. He was chief executive officer in Mecca itself. He alone could call up Hejazis for military service, who were thus exempt from Turkish conscription, and he alone could levy and collect taxes in Mecca and Medina; he could also levy contributions from funds belonging to the Ottoman authorities in the Hejaz. In addition, as has been seen, he could, for the benefit of Mecca, lay Qasim and Sedeir under tribute. ‘ The Ottoman side of the bargain compelled the Emir to admit Turkish garrisons in all Hejazi towns as the Turks might require, to accept a Turkish Governor-General, or Y^ali, in Mecca or Taif according to season, and sub- Governors and administrative officials in five other centres. The Turkish garrison at the beginning of 1916 was about 12,000 men, stationed at Mecca, Medina, Taif, Jedda and other ports, and along the Hejaz railway. At this time Husein had become the de facto power in the Hejaz, with wide influence extending southward to eastern Asir, northward to the southern Aneiza tribes, and eastward to Central Arabia. He had, in fact, confined Turkish authority to the areas held by Turkish garrisons. Behind these outward manifestations of growing influence and power, the moment was fast approaching for Husein to attempt the execution of his ambitions, which had, indeed, greatly widened since Turkey entered the war, as had also his prospects. From the 30th October, 1914, he had, in fact, become a prince whose goodwill, influence and active assistance would be exceedingly valuable to Great Britain. This is not the place in which to detail the history of how the Emir of Mecca came to co-operate with Great Britain in a war against the Ottoman Empire, ruled by a Sultan who was Khalifa of Islam. That intricate story belongs to the history of the Arab rising. Suffice it to say now that in September 1914 the Emir of Mecca’s son, Abdullah, was cautiously approached by Lord Kitchener, who knew him personally, and that between this opening enquiry and the end of 1915 an exchange of letters between His Majesty’s Government’s representative in Cairo and the Emir (a correspondence which did not cover the whole ground and was not always explicit upon the points sought to be defined) committed both parties to courses at the time highly acceptable to both. These negotiations revealed the vast extent to which the ambitions of Husein had now grown. The independence of the Hejaz had become merely the nucleus for a design which took a part of south-eastern Asia Minor, Syria and Mesopotamia, and almost the whole of Arabia for its field. Calling these regions the “Arab Countries,” he aspired to see them freed from Turkish rule, where it was then established, and united under one sovereignty, or, as several independent States, into a confederation acknowledging an Arab suzerain. Though sometimes professing indifference as to who the Sovereign or Suzerain should be, provided unification were attained, Husein had himself or his immediate successor in view. Behind these aspirations for the enlargement of his temporal authority remained the delicate question of an Arab Caliphate.7 At an early stage in the negotiations with Great Britain, Husein had received vague encouragement both from Lord Kitchener and Sir H. McMahon, the British High Commissioner at Cairo, to make assumption of the Caliphate one of his purposes. He was careful, however, to avoid adopting any open policy in this direction; he always spoke of the Caliphate as being an office to be filled only by /^the choice of Islam, but there can be no question that it was a position which not only he himself secretly desired but his ambitious son, Abdullah, avowedly sought it for him. After the tentative prompting to Husein to seek the Caliphate given by Lord Kitchener and Sir H. McMahon in the message of the 31st October, 1914,( 6 ) His Majesty’s Government left no doubt that they regarded the question of the Caliphate as one for Moslems alone. They restated this traditional British policy explicitly in a telegram to Sir H. McMahon on the 14th April, 1915. On the 17th November, 1915, they warned him to avoid “ all possibility of being involved in any question concerning the Caliphate.” The subject was accordingly ignored by Sir H. McMahon in subsequent negotiations. In the agreement which Great Britain eventually reached with the Emir, his territorial demands were conceded with certain limitations and reservations. The British protectorate of Aden, the British-protected island sheikhdom of Bahrein and the south-eastern part of Asia Minor were excluded, limitations to which the Emir agreed. Great Britain also specifically excluded Western Syria and made reservations regarding the Vilayets of Bagdad and Basra in Mesopotamia, but on these points the Emir temporised, and though the validity of the British reservations is not open to doubt, the agreement did not contain the Emir’s full acceptance of the reservations. Another important British limitation, that nothing in the agreement should prejudice the rights of other Arab rulers then in treaty or about to execute treaties with Great Britain, was also left in a somewhat similar position. Several old treaties between His Majesty’s Government and Arab States on the Indian Ocean and Persian Gulf were already in force. A treaty had also been signed with the Idrisi of Asir on the 30th April, 1915, and another, with Ibn Saud of Nejd, was concluded on the 26th December of the same year. The Emir’s letters nowhere show an unequivocal acceptance of the limitations imposed on him in regard to these treaties. This matter becomes of particular interest in considering subsequent relations between Husein and other Arab rulers. The reservation, in fact, struck deeply at the Emir’s ambition to unite the various Arab States, for, as far as those in treaty with Great Britain were concerned, compulsion was ruled out, and unity of the Arab race could be achieved only by friendly consent. Subject to these limitations and reservations, Great Britain in effect under took to recognise and support Arab independence in the territories proposed by the Emir of Mecca and to aid him with money, arms and munitions. For his part the Emir undertook to spare no efforts to attach all Arab peoples to the cause of the Allies and to give military assistance to the best of his ability. He also under took not to make peace without the agreement of Great Britain. These broad terms having been arranged, and money, arms and munitions supplied by Great Britain, Husein and his four sons raised the Hejazi tribes in insurrection against Turkish rule on 5th June, 1916. Two days later the Emir issued a proclamation denouncing the Turkish Government as dominated by the Committee of Union and Progress and proclaiming the independence of the Hejaz. IV .—Emirate of Nejd ruled by Ibn Saud, Emir of Riyadh. Of all the autonomous Arab areas with which this paper deals, the Emirate of Nejd came least under Turkish influence and power. It was too remote, too inaccessible, too poor, to offer permanent attraction for Turkish conquest and occupation. Nevertheless, it did not altogether escape. The hostile acts of its own rulers courted Ottoman intervention, and in 1817 an Egyptian army, on behalf of the Ottoman Sultan, took and destroyed the capital and ensured Egyptian occupation of a kind for a generation.* But thereafter Egyptian and Ottoman influence ceased. Upon this vicarious occupation rested the chief Ottoman claim to sovereignty in Central Arabia. Later, Turkish attempts to establish effective occupation were indeed made, but with little more than verbal pretension to success, as when, in 1871, Midhat Pasha occupied Hasa, the Persian Gulf, the province of Nejd, and on the strength of that achievement ( e ) For this correspondence, see Confidential 13778.8 was styled “victor of Nejd,” and when Feivzi Pasha, in 1906, operating in support of the Emir of Hail, hoisted the Ottoman flag in Qasim, the north-western province of Neid, but did not keep it flying for more than a few months. In 1913, too, the Turkish Government, still clinging to the theory that Nejd was an Ottoman province, and confronted with hostile action in Hasa by the Emu o ^ Neid, sought escape from an embarrassing situation by giving the Emir the title of “ Vali of Nejd,” and condoning his aggression. The Emir attached no value to the honour, which he seems to have accepted as marking Turkish acquiescence in his opportune and profitable conquest of Hasa and Qatif. ^ Territorially, at the time of the Arab rising, the boundaries of Nejd, except upon the Persian Gulf and towards Koweit, were indeterminate. From east to west it extended from the Persian Gulf to those doubtful regions where the authority of the ruler of Nejd was m rivalry with that of the lulei of the Hejaz. In the south it bordered on the Great Desert and the southern continuation of the debatable lands claimed also by the Hejaz. In the north-east it reached the boundaries of Koweit and found a north-western limitation between Qasim and the territory of the Shammar tribes, who gave allegiance to the Emir of Hail. The central portion of Nejd, the area from which the State derived the main part of its strength, comprises a long chain of oases scattered from north to south either upon the plateau of Jabal Tuwaiq or its eastward flank. Here is the district called Aridh, in which stands Riyadh, the capital of Nejd. The chain of oases, with separating intervals of steppe—which is something better than desert—covers an area of about 10,000 square miles. Dependent on this main group, but outside the area in which they lie, are other and smaller groups of oases to the south and west. In a comprehensive sense Nejd occupies a part of the great plateau of Arabia which falls gradually from west to east, with higher masses and hills imposed upon its surface. The long and extensive tract of sometimes very broken country known as Jabal Tuwaiq, which forms the backbone of Nejd, and by the precipita tion it ensures accounts for the great group of oases, is the chief of these uplifted masses. The eastern portion of Nejd, the lately regained province of Hasa, continues the general fall from the interior to a low-lying coastal plain upon the Persian Gulf, but also contains tracts of high ground and hills. This province possesses a water supply exceptional for Arabia, Indeed, in the great oases of Hasa and Qatif, springs and streams abound and make these districts the richest in Nejd. Any approximate estimate of the total population of Nejd is impossible. The central 10,000 square miles of oasis country, at the period under review, certainly did not contain more than 250,000 souls, almost entirely settled on the land. The province of Hasa had 150,000, two-thirds of whom were settled, and one-third nomadic. The population of Nejd, exclusive of Hasa, where Shiahs predominate, hold the Sunni belief of Islam. But they are Sunnis with a difference. Nejd is the home of Wahabism, “ an ascetic revivalist movement among Moslems who sympathise with the strict but orthodox Hanbali school of Sunnism.”( 7 ) Wahabis are, in fact, the militant Puritans of Islam, to whom the sword is the appointed means of argument, conversion, or purification against Moslems who will not voluntarily accept the Wahabi teachings. Upon this primary motive for armed aggression, a motive at first strictly religious, were easily grafted the secular ambitions of Wahabi rulers, and, on the part of the people, a sense of unity, born of geographical isolation and success in arms, which had in it something of a national consciousness. The circumstances attending human existence in the central oasis group of Nejd contributed the ample basis upon which Wahabism flourished and won its successes. Here was a population of cultivators and herdsmen, isolated, self- supporting, but poor, devoid of commercial interests and entirely unaffected by the cautious and sobering influences exerted by the presence of a trading class, even in a primitive state of society. It was a population by nature hardy, bellicose in spirit, men of their hands who supported their religious convictions with vehemence. It was, further, a population centrally placed with regard to other communities, but prevented by distance and intervening desert from ready inter course with neighbours who differed from them in large details of spiritual belief. ( T ) D. G. Hogarth, Handbook of Arabia, volume I.■'irgr* ■ °y 9 Qasim, the north-west border province of Nejd, and for fifty years the subject of almost continuous hostilities between the Emirates of Nejd and Jebel bhammar, has physical and economic characteristics meriting special notice. The nortnern part, or Upper Qasim, is pastoral and carries only a sparse population, but Eower Qasim, which has been described as “ a land of green villages in a winding s ^of sand,” is a stretch of fertile oases 100 miles in length, strung out along the Wadi er Rumma, and separated from each other by intervals of steppe. he settled population of the whole province was not less than 50,000. From the geographical fact that the province stands midway upon the trans- peninsular route between Mesopotamia and Mecca, it is a trading district by tradition; indeed, it was estimated that one-third of the population were cameleers or otherwise engaged in transportation. The people are warlike and independent, and stout supporters of Wahabism. Nevertheless, they have a wider outlook and better acquaintance with extra-Arabian civilisation than any other inland region of the peninsula. The two chief towns, Boreidah, lo,UUU inhabitants, and Aneiza 10,000, ranked as the largest and most commercial in Central Arabia. As the home of many prosperous and widely-travelled merchants they were comparatively civilised and wealthy; they were, further sell-governmg democracies, jealous of their rights and privileges, accepting only the overlordship of the Emir of Nejd and the payment of an annual tribute. Such are the elements, each supplementing the others, which have produced the history alike of Nejd and of Wahabism. The two form a subject inseparable. In combination they present the story of a primitive State, which, far more than any other in Arabia, possessed the spirit and tradition of conquest and expansion and the native human means of giving effect to these promptings. About 1750 an ascetic revivalist and Haji, by name Mohammed Abd-ei- Wahab, who preached a return to the pure and simple form of faith taught by the Prophet, took refuge at Deraiya, in Nejd, from the incensed people ot Haraimala, his native town. The Sheikh of Deraiya, Mohammed Ibn baud, was the first important convert made by Abd-el-Wahab. This early Ibn Saud c e n ~ cerned himself chiefly with that teaching of the reformer which declared that upon all true believers lay the unescapable duty of war against false believers, who were to be treated on the same footing as unbelievers and idolaters In fifteen years of such war Mohammed Ibn Saud completely conqueied am converted the inhabitants of the central oasis-group in Nejd as well as the adjoining territory of Hasa. auj i a • u- a a In 1765 Mohammed Ibn Saud was succeeded by a son, Abdul Aziz-bm-baud who inherited alike his father’s enlarged territory, power, ambitions and spiritual convictions. He ruled till assassinated in 1803. During these thirty-eight years he extended Wahabi conquest far beyond the borders of Central Nejd and Hasa. Fie issued ultimatums to his intended adversaries in the terms of conversion, submission or death. Under his rule, Wahabi forces carried out the most dinicult and dangerous expeditions, in complete contempt of death, with unfailing success, and spread the fame of Wahabism throughout the whole Mahometan world. ’ Pilgrim caravans of the Haj were first attacked by Wahabis in 1/83, an outrage many times repeated. o. j * ^ Early in 1801 Abdul Aziz sent an expedition under his son, baud, to the holy Shiah City of Karbala on the Euphrates. There, on the Feast of Bairam, 1801, the Wahabis destroyed the sacred relics in Meshed Husem and slew the temple guards and priests, with such unconsidered haste that no one remained alive who could reveal to the raiders where the priceless treasures of the shrine ^Y 0 j &gt;0 stored. The Wahabi force which m 1803 attacked and captuied Mhcca spared the Holy Places, but sacked the city and beheaded twenty sheikhs by way of ex ^P^ October, 1803, Abdul Aziz-bin-Saud was assassinated in the mosque at Deraiya by a shiah, in revenge for the attack on Meshed Husein at Karbala. His son Saud, who succeeded, was another ambitious, fanatical and competent ruler and soldier. He held power from 1803 to 1814. In ISOATie- captured Medina, and carried away the accumulated treasures from the tomb of Mahomet. In 1806 and 1807 he completely stripped the Haj caravans. In 1810 he raided Medina and Mecca again, caused the tomb of Mahomet to be opened and sent to Deraiya a great booty of jewels and other captured treasure. North ward his raiders carried their operations almost to Damascus. At this stage the pilgrim caravans ceased; not only those sent officially from Turkey and Egypt, [11932]10 but those in which the Faithful from Persia and the Yemen and other Mahometan countries usually reached the Holy Cities. r . , But fifty years of uninterrupted military success, conquest and spoliation naa produced results in Nejd strangely at variance with the austere teachings of the founder of Wahabism. Treasure torn Horn shrines as the forbidden offerings of idolatry, or from individuals as proof of wanton depravity had hlled Kiyadn^ with an accumulation of riches hitherto unimagined m Central Arabia. Display* that had been corrupting sin, to be punished by death in Orthodox Moslems, ceased to be sin and became merit when adopted in the capital of Aejd, where, at the beginning of the 19th century, luxury, ostentation, pride and favouritism prevailed On oppression being exerted on the tribes, discontent arose and som 6 of them emigrated. The Wahabi movement, the mainspring of Nejdi power and success, had, in fact, fallen into decay at a time when the Mahometan world was most stirred against it. , TT , We have seen how the plundering of the Holy I laces, the \iOi&lt;ition o Mahomet’s tomb, the slaughter and spoliation of believers and the Loss of provinces at last prompted the Ottoman Sultan, as nominal 1 rotector oi all Moslems, to take forcible action. For sufficient reasons it was impossible to send a Turkish expedition to Nejd. To Mahomet Ali of Egypt, later to become Viceroy, was therefore deputed the duty of punishing Wahabi outrages upon the body of Islam. Mahomet Ali entered on the project gladly. The campaign would enable him to build up and train an army in actual warfare, a force almost indispensable to his secret plans in other directions. An Egyptian army, mam v composed of Albanian and negro mercenaries, with a certain number of fellahm, was landed at Yenbo in October 1811, but got no further that year, being almost destroyed by disease. In 1812, however, experience so bought, combined with laro-e reinforcements, enabled progress to be made. Medina, Jedda, Mecca and Hanakiya near Khaibar, were occupied—Hanakiya being on the route from Medina to Qasim, which had been chosen for reaching the Wahabi capital. The year following Mahomet Ali himself went to the front with fuithei reinforcements. , , , , . Early in 1814, Saud, the Wahabi ruler, died, and was succeeded by his son, Abdullah-bin-Saud. On the 10th January, 1815, Mahomet Ali defeated a Wahabi force at Bessel, and thus opened the way for an advance into the interior. But the tribes upon the route remained hostile, and combined with the tremendous natural difficulties of the country, rendered further Egyptian progress in this direction exceedingly hazardous. Mahomet Ali therefore tried with great success the effect of gold upon the tribesmen. Abdullah made proposals for peace at this stao-e but his overtures were rejected by the Egyptian leader as being too late. ° Mahomet Ali returned to Cairo in 1815, and left in command his son Ibrahim, who had already given proof of possessing a native capacity for military leadership. Ibrahim, later famous to Europe as Ibrahim Pasha, corrupted his Arab opponents with gold where he could; those who were proof against gold felt the power of his army, which he directed with vigour. During 1816-17 the war was continued with ferocity on both sides. Ibrahim’s army appeared before Deraiya, some ten miles north-west of the present capital Riyadh, early in April 1817, and began a bombardment on the 14th of the same month. In spite of disease, incredible difficulties of supply and an obstinate defence, Ibrahim captured the town and received the surrender of Abdullah on the 17th September, 1817. Riyadh he completely destroyed. Abdullah was sent as prisoner to Cairo, and thence to Stamboul, where he was executed in 1819. With this remarkable conquest of the interior of Arabia—a conquest which eventually included the Province of Hasa on the Persian Gulf—Egyptian rule began, and was continued for some thirty years. But decline started almost from the outset. Even so, its continuance over this period was rendered possible by the presence of powerful Turco-Egyptian forces in the Southern Hejaz, Asir and the Yemen during the years 182T-27 and 1833-36. By 1849 not only was the evacuation of Nejd 'and Hasa by Egypt complete, but Egyptian influence had completely disappeared, and though Nejd, as a Wahabi State, had greatly shrunk in territory, power and influence, Wahabism, purified by tribulation, had returned to its earlier austerities. The inner tribes, with the Emir Feisal-bin-Saud, established in a new capital at Riyadh, had come together in a common hatred of Egyptians and Tutfks.11 HPNPM ;r\ The return of Nejd to power was, however, not attained solely by the pleasant road of uninterrupted progress. While the Wahabi State was st A ^. u ^? r , . e domination of hLgypt, a rival Emirate had arisen at Hail under Abciullan-3in Rashid; it soon grew strong enough to detach Jebel Shammar from Nejd am o dispute the control of Qasim. . . „ * In 1869 Abdullah, successor to Feisal, reasserted Nejdi authority m Hasa on the Persian Gulf. In 1871, however, the district was occupied by a lurkish force despatched by Midhat Pasha. More serious still were the reverses suliere in the long struggle between Nejd and Hail. In 1886 Riyadh was captured b) Mohammed-bin-Rashid, Emir of Hail, and again in 1891. Then followed a period of ten years during which the various districts of Nejd were m charge ot Governors appointed by the Emir of Hail, representatives of ^ the ^ud f ami &gt; were reduced to puppets, and Nejd, in effect, became a vassal State oi Hail. The history of Nejd now reaches the period from which emerged the latest strong ruler of the House of Saud, Abdul Aziz-bin-Saud, the present King o Saudi Arabia. Abdul Aziz, born in 1875, son of Abd-er-Rahman-bm-Saud, was in exile with his father at Koweit when his uncle, the nominal Emir of Neid was murdered by order of Ibn Rashid in 1902. With only forty men, Abdul Aziz entered the'Sedeir district of Nejd, secured support there, marched on Riyadh, which welcomed him, and ended the Rashidi domination the same year. Recognising the energy and outstanding qualifications for leadership shown b\ Abdul Aziz^ his father, Abd-er-Rahman, renounced his own claims to the Emirate accepted his son as Emir and, assuming the title of “ Imam,' took the direction of religious affairs in Riyadh. By 1904 the Emir was master of all Southern Aejd. He marched on Qasim in that year, but was compelled to retire by a Turkish force co-operating with the Emir of Hail. In 1906, however, he made another attempt, and this time succeeded in imposing partial subjection and payment of tribute upon Qasim, both of which he maintained at the cost of recui rent fighting with the Emir of Hail. In 1910 danger threatened the Emir both from within and without. Certain grandsons of his late uncle, Saud. claimed the Emirate for their own branch, and sought to raise the southern provinces, Kharj and Hariq, in rebellion. At the same time, Abdullah, second son of the Emir of Mecca, entered Qasim with a Hejazi force to support the rights of the Ateibah tribe said to have been infringed by the Emir of Nejd. This Emir’s younger brother, who was his representative in Qasim, was made prisoner. ibn Rashid, Emir of Hail, had promised co-operation with Abdullah in this movement, but failed to take action. The Hejazi force, therefore, retired, but not before Abdullah had exacted an under taking from the Qasim towns to pay £4,000 annual tribute to Mecca in place of the “Peter’s pence” hitherto subscribed voluntarily. On his part, Abdullah conceded that the towns should elect their own Governors. To these terms Ibn Saud assented, and also to an arrangement whereby the Ateibah tribe within the borders of Nej d should be free of his taxation. Meanwhile, the rebel operations in Southern Nejd having failed, the leaders took refuge with the Ateibah on Nejd territory. In 1911 Ibn Saud inflicted severe punishment on this tribe for harbouring his enemies. By so doing he again fell foul of the Emir of Mecca, who professed to regard the attack as a violation of the agreement made the previous year. The Meccan Emir gave asylum in the Hejaz to Ibn Saud’s traitorous kinsmen, but took no further notice of the attack on the Ateibah, though he appears to have carried to account—as did Ibn Saud—the countenance shown his enemies. Both Emirs had ambitions to fulfil; both Emirates were increasing in power; rivalry between them accordingly grew apace. .... But Ibn Saud had the greater geographical opportunities for expanding his territory with advantage. Being an inland region, it could be extended in almost every direction; he had, too, the helpful tradition of a Nejd much more extensive than it was at that time. The Province of Hasa had been snatched from his Emirate in 1871 by a Turkish force sent by Midhat Pasha, Vali of Basra, and was now known to Turkish Administration by the comprehensive name of the “Sanjak of Nejd.” Hasa was the only relatively wealthy province within the borders of earlier Nejd, or within the territory that was open to conquest by Ibn Saud; its recovery would greatly increase the meagre resources of his State; further a most important consideration—it would give him access to the sea. [11932] c 212 ■fc Without success he had endeavoured to enlist the support of the Indian Govern ment by offering a renewal of the declaration made in 1866 by his uncle, the Emir Abdullah, to His Majesty’s Government regarding British interests m the Persian Gulf.O But he was soon to have his opportunity for conquest. At a time when Turkey had her hands full with the Balkan War, and the Emirate of Hail was enfeebled by the dissensions of the Rashid family, some ol^ Ibn Baud’s rebellious relatives were enjoying friendly refuge m Hasa territory. They were said, moreover, to be preparing an attack against him. Here were both opportunity and reasonable excuse for prompt action by the Emir oi ^ e .l • Early in 1913 he marched into Hasa, captured Hofuf on the 5th May, and on the 15th May compelled the Turkish garrison of Qatif, the chief seaport, to surrender. The Governor and garrison he allowed to return to Ottoman territory by way oi Oqair and Qatar. . At the same time His Majesty’s Government were negotiating a convention with the Ottoman Government regarding the Persian Gulf and adjacent terri tories Little was known about the inland Emirate of Nejd, which had had no direct contact with the Gulf and British officials for many years. That it was an Emirate capable of over-running and permanently holding a Turkish province, and that its ruler was really a figure of outstanding importance in Arabian politics were facts still to be recognised. In negotiating the convention, there fore, His Majesty’s Government attached very little importance to Nejd and its Emir. The convention was signed on the 29th July, 1913. The eleventh article of this instrument defined the “ Ottoman Sanjak of Nejd m such a wav that it was made to include not only the coast-line and Province of Hasa, bu Central Nejd as well. It thus implied that the Emir was an Ottoman subject and his action against the Turks nothing but rebellion. Having comnutted themselves to these views, His Majesty’s Government were placed in a difficult position when the Emir, unrecognised by the Turks, maintained himselt as de facto ruler of Hasa and 300 miles of the Gulf coast-line and made overtures to the Indian Government. Whatever his status in theory, His Majesty s Government could not avoid having direct relations with a ruler of this weight, who held so much of the Gulf coast. . . Acting under instructions from the British Resident m the I ersian Gult (Sir Percy Cox) the British Political Agents at Koweit and Bahrein, the former being Captain W. H. I. Shakespear, I.A., went to Oqair, where they conferred with Ibn Saud on the 15th and 16th December, 1913, He showed much fnendh- iigss invited His IVI&amp;jesty s Government to keep the pe&amp;ce on the const nnd revealed the terms the'Turks were endeavouring to impose on him. These terms included the readmission of Turkish garrisons; that all communications from foreign Powers or their agents should be handed over to and dealt with by the Turks; the exclusion of foreigners and their agents from the province, and no concessions to foreigners for railways or motor-car services. In effect, Ibn Saud now desired British mediation. In a memorandum of the 9th March, 1914, His Majesty s Government explained their difficulties in regard to Ibn Saud to the Turkish Government, entered a protest against the last three of the Turkish conditions above cited and defined what they themselves required of Ibn Saud. Their requirements included no interference with other Arab principalities in the Gulf; co-operation in main taining the maritime truce in the Gulf for the suppression of piracy; co-operation in suppressing arms traffic; free admission of British traders to Qatif. Meanwhile negotiations between the Turks and Ibn Saud continued, and on the 15th May, 1914, the Emir signed a treaty with the Vali of Basra. It placed the “ Vilayet of Nejd ” in charge of Ibn Saud for life, with succession to his descendants by Imperial firman; it readmitted Turkish troops to the seaports of Hasa; it provided for the Turkish flag being flown and forbade the Emir to take part in foreign affairs or to grant concessions to foreigners. It also required the Emir to aid Turkey in war when requested by the Imperial Government. In June the Emir accepted'the title of “Vali of Nejd and Hasa,” but is said not to have regarded it seriously. From the signing of the Anglo-Turkish convention on the 29th July, 1913, to the outbreak of war between the signatories on the 31st October, 1914, His Majesty’s Government discouraged the advances which Ibn Saud made to them. ( 8 ) See Aitchison, volume XI, p. 206.During the same period the Turks attempted to reconcile Ibn Saud and Ibn Kashid and to obtain promises of their military co-operation with the Ottoman These overtures the Emir of Nejd put aside. In October 1914 the Sheikh oi Koweit, on his own initiative, wrote to Ibn Saud stating that he intended to stand by His Majesty’s Government if war broke out and that he advised Ibn Saud to do the same. The latter replied that, in the event of war with lurkey, he would stand by the sheikh “ and the British Government.” Early in October His Majesty’s Government resolved to send Captain Shakespear, formerly British Resident at Koweit, on a special mission to Ibn Saud; negotiations were begun before he arrived by His Majesty’s Goveinment asking the Emir in November to co-operate with the Allies in the war and offering in return to guarantee him against Turkish attack, to recognise him as indepen dent ruler of Nejd and Hasa, and to enter into treaty relations with him. These proposals became the basis of subsequent negotiations. Captain Shakespear reached Ibn Saud’s camp on the 31st December, 1914, and discussed with him the political situation. It appeared that Ibn Saud was resolved to remain neutral until he could secure a binding treaty with the British Government, and that what he sought was a solid guarantee of his position under what would be, in effect, British suzerainty. On the 4th January, 1915, Captain Shakespear was able to send Sir P. Cox a translation of Ibn Saud’s rough draft of the treaty he proposed. When forwarding this document, Captain Shakespear added some observations of his own :— “ I venture to submit,” he wrote, “ that Ibn Saud in effect asks (in his rough draft of a treaty) for little more than what has been already conveyed in the Acting Resident’s assurances (the proposals of a British guarantee, already mentioned) if these were meant to apply to the future and were not limited to the present crisis, and if they are interpreted liberally and generously. In exchange Ibn Saud offers to make himself a British vassal for good ” At this stage Ibn Saud was able to render valuable assistance to His Majesty’s Government by the attitude he took and the advice he gave to the Emir of Mecca when that ruler hovered in doubt as to the policy he should adopt. On the night of the 17th January, 1915, a letter from Abdullah, the Emir of Mecca’s second son, reached Ibn Saud, who was then in camp with his army not far from Majmaa, in Sedeir. It stated that the Turks were urgently pressing his father to proclaim the jihad and call up the tribes; but that he was temporising until he could learn what Ibn Saud’s own attitude was towards the Turks and British. Ibn Saud read the letter aloud to Captain Shakespear and asked what reply would be most advantageous to Great Britain. The story, as told in a letter from that officer dated the 19th January, 1915,( 9 ) is too long to be repeated here; suffice it to say that Ibn Saud advised the Emir to temporise further, pleading fear of a British attack on Jedda and other Hejazi seaports. He explained that he saw no advantage in siding with the Turks. He added that he himself had just returned a temporising reply to a deputation sent him by the Porte, alleging his pending operations against Ibn Rashid, and fear of a British attack on Qatif. With this letter to Abdullah he promised to enclose copies of British proclamations regarding Turkey and the war, and British undertakings regarding the Holy Places. At this time (January 1915) Turkish preparations for the attack on the Suez Canal and Egypt were in progress. Rumours and expectations filled Syria, where all believed that the attack would succeed and be followed by momentous results for Islam. The jihad had been proclaimed in Constantinople on the 14th November, 1914, and though the full response was still uncertain, signs were not wanting that it might set Arabia ablaze and greatly increase British difficulties. Arabs were looking anxiously towards Mecca in expectation of what the Ulema of that city and the Emir, who was direct descendant of the Prophet, Chief of the Prophet’s Tribe, and Hereditary Keeper of the Holy Places, would do in this crisis of Islam. Nor, so far, had much progress been made in the negotiations between Great Britain and that Emir. In fact, nothing had been received from Mecca beyond expressions of goodwill towards Great Britain and the statement that the Emir could not break with the Turks at present. This response Abdullah, on the 10th December, 1914, had conveyed on behalf of his father in reply to Lord ( 9 ) Given in volume I, Arab Bulletin, p. 336.14 Kitchener’s message of the 31st October, 1914. It was an encouraging response, but it was no more. Indeed, at the beginning of January 1915, the Emir of Mecca Was uncertain on which side he could range himself with the greater prospect of advantage. His inclinations and judgment impelled him to support Great Britain, but Turkish garrisons were on his land, holding all his chief cities; the war had not begun well for the Allies; he had everything to lose by taking part in unsuccessful hostilities against the Turk. While thus in doubt he received I bn Saud’s reply to Abdullah’s letter. That the Emir of Nejd’s advice carried weight in the councils of Mecca is not open to question. Thus encouraged to withstand Turkish pressure, the Chief of the Prophet’s Tribe continued to temporise; sixteen months were to elapse before he actually rose in arms against the Turks. Meanwhile, he made no move, and those who looked to Mecca for a lead saw no sign, drew their own conclusions, and the jihad became merely Turkish in its authority and left Arabia unstirred. Nor was Mecca’s silence at this critical time without its influence in the wider Islam. But to return to events in Nejd. Ibn Saud had on the 19th January already begun operations against Ibn Rashid, who, with his pro-Turkish confederation of tribes, had entered Northern Nejd The two forces, in great strength for Arabia, encountered at Jerab, near Majmaa, on the 24th January. The battle resulted in a draw, a result more favourable for Ibn Saud than for Ibn Rashid. Hostilities were tacitly suspended, but Ibn Rashid was put out of action; he could not join the Turks as he had intended and could not take part in the early campaign in Mesopotamia, when his appearance might have added considerably to His Majesty’s Government’s difficulties. A formal peace was signed by the rival Emirs on the 10th June, 1915. In this treaty Ibn Rashid recognised all Ibn Saud’s claims except that of over-lordship and confined his own jurisdiction to Hail, its villages, and the Shammar tribes. It is clear too that he renounced all pretensions to Qasim. But the treaty did not have permanent results, and relations between the two Emirs remained a condition of armed neutrality varied by actual hostilities. Later in 1915 Ibn Saud had to deal with a serious rising in Northern Hasa by the Ajman tribe. He suppressed the movement, but lost his brother in the fighting and was wounded himself. He then had trouble in Southern Hasa with the A1 Murrah tribe, whom he attacked because it had sided with Ibn Rashid. His difficulties with these tribes arose from the strictness of his rule compared with that of the Turks. During these struggles the British Government assisted the despatch of arms and ammunitions from Bahrein to Ibn Saud and in October presented him with 1,000 rifles and made him a loan of £20,000. In November 1915 the Sherif of Mecca seized the opportunity presented by Ibn Saud’s embarrassments to send Abdullah with a considerable force into Western Nejd. Nominally, the purpose of this singularly ill-timed incursion was to collect taxes from the Ateibah tribe, but subsequent information shows that the real object was political and that it was to support the Sherif’s interests or pretensions in Southern Qasim, a district claimed by the Ateibah. The force got within 70 miles of Riyadh, on the Mecca-Riyadh road, before it retired. As might have been expected, the movement excited Ibn Saud’s violent indigna tion and caused him to protest to His Majesty’s Government that, if they could not keep the Sherif’s activities within bounds, he would have to do so himself. No untoward results ensued, however, except the creation of further illwill on the part of the Emir of Nejd. Meanwhile, Ibn Saud followed a pro-British and anti-Turkish policy, and negotiations for a treaty with His Majesty’s Government were continued; the reasons making such a treaty desirable from the British point of view are stated in a communication from the India Office to the Foreign Office, dated the 30th January, 1915 :— “ The desirability of concluding a treaty with Emir Abdul Aziz (Ibn Saud) follows not merely from the exigencies of the moment, which made it necessary to pay an immediate price for his friendship, but also from the general situation that will be created in the Persian Gulf in the event, as the result of the present war, of the disappearance of Turkish rule from Basra, to which His Majesty's Government are pledged. It may be anticipated that the Emir of Nejd will be left master not only of Central Arabia, but of a15 long strip of the coast, and in the interest of peace and order it will be essential for the Power that controls the Gulf to have a working agreement with him. The extent, therefore, to which his claims must be met must be measured not only by the immediate services, which he may be expected to render, but also by the potential powers for mischief which, in the event of success, he will possess, and if permanently estranged will doubtless exercise ” Negotiations for the treaty were protracted, but the instrument was eventually signed at Qatif by Sir P. Cox and the Emir on the 26th December, 1915.( l0 ) Ratification by the Viceroy and Governor-General of India tolloy/ed on the 18th July, 1916.' By this treaty His Majesty’s Government recognised Ibn Saud as independent ruler of Nejd, Hasa, Qatif and Jubail, and engaged to support him against aggression by any foreign Power to such extent and in such a manner as the British Government, after consulting Ibn Saud, may consider most effective for protecting his interests and countries. For his part Ibn Saud covenanted to have no relations with any foreign Power, and absolutely not to cede, sell, mortgage, lease or dispose of any part of his territories to any foreign Power or the subjects of a foreign Power without the consent of His Majesty’s Government. . . . Three other points in particular may be noticed regarding the provisions ot the treaty :— (a) That article I, after defining the several ‘‘countries' recognised by His Majesty’s Government as being under the independent rule of Ibn Saud, added the words “ and their dependencies and territories, which will be discussed and determined hereafter . . . . .” These words appear to have committed His Majesty’s Government to arbitrate in any territorial disputes that might arise between Ibn Saud and his neighbours—King Husein, for instance—and, by implication, might have taken them even further. (5) That the India Office, soon after the treaty was ratified,' laid down the important decision that ‘ ‘ we cannot admit that article II (promising His Majesty’s Government’s support against aggression by any foreign Power) is binding on us against other Arabs.” (c) That article VII engaged His Majesty’s Government and Ibn Saud to conclude a “ further detailed treaty ” We must now consider the relations which existed between Ibn Saud and the Emir of Mecca from the outbreak of war in 1914 to the beginning of the Arab rising in June 1916. This period covers the secret negotiations between His Majesty’s Government and the Emir. Of these negotiations Ibn Saud was unaware, though the ultimate success or failure of the action contemplated in the negotiations could not leave him unaffected. Both Emirs feared the Turks (Husein, once pro-Turkish, having adopted a hostile policy since 1913), and would have been glad to see them ejected from Arabia; but each was jealous of the other as an Arab ruler and rival chief, whose large ambitions could only be satisfied at the other’s expense. Moreover, fertile sources of discord lay in the uncertainty of the claims and obligations of each in the absence of boundaries, and in the fluctuating allegiance of nomad tribes, who passed from one region to another with slight concern for questions of sovereignty. Such matters notwithstanding, the two Emirs had been drawn together immediately before the war by their common dread of the Turks, and were in amicable correspondence in the spring of 1914. In January 1915 Ibn Saud, in conversation with Captain Shakespear, declared it as his view that the Caliphate would revert to the family of the Prophet, of which Emir Husein was the representative, if it dropped from the hand of the Sultan of Turkey. This expression of opinion can hardly be taken as indicating unfriendliness towards Husein on the part of the speaker. Towards the close of 1915 a definite change appeared in the relations of the two Emirs. The expedition despatched to Qasim and Sedeir by the Emir of Mecca, under his son Abdullah in 1910, has already been noticed. In November 1915 Abdullah again appeared in Nejd with a Hejazi force, this time on the direct route from Mecca to Riyadh, for the ostensible purpose of collecting dues from the Ateibah tribe, over whom the Emir of Mecca claimed sovereignty. To ( l0 ) Printed as appendix to P.O. 11820*.16 Ibn Saud, just emerging from a dangerous rebellion in Hasa, which had severely strained his resources, the visit was not only inopportune, but highly suspicious. His misgivings were reflected in his conversation with Sir Percy Cox in December 1915, when he reminded the Chief Political Officer that Wahabis recognised no Caliph after the first four, and added that, if the Emir of Mecca should assume the title, it would make no difference to his status among other ^ Arab rulers. Ibn Saud would appear, in fact, to have scented the wider political ambitions to which the war had given rise in Husein, and was now on his guard. V.— The Sheikhdom of Koiveit ruled by the Sheikh of Koweit. At the time of the Arab rising in 1916,.Koweit was of small importance in wider Arabian politics, and its interests pertained as much to the Basra Vilayet as to the peninsula. British influence was paramount. The sheikhdom was generally in rivalry with the Emirs of Hail, but had always been friendly with Ibn Saud. It therefore requires some mention here. Koweit had a coastline to the Persian Gulf of 200 miles, an undefined maximum breadth of 150 miles, and an area of about 20,000 square miles. Its surface is chiefly desert, so much so that of the settled population of about 37,000 at the period under review, all but 2,000 resided in the town of Koweit, and the nomad population was estimated at only 13,000. The sheikhdom had, in fact, no political power, nor the prospect of attaining any. It owed its position as an autonomous sheikhdom to British support, given because the harbour of Koweit was the best in the northern part of the Persian Gulf coast and became the prospective terminal point of the Constantinople-Bagdad Railway. . . Until the last years of the 19th century Koweit was only an insignificant sheikhdom, with a jurisdiction extending little beyond the town. In 1871, when Midhat Pasha began a policy of Ottoman expansion in Arabia, the Sheikh of Koweit declared himself an Ottoman subject, accepted the rank of kai'makam, and his territory was nominally incorporated in the Vilayet of Basra. But the Indian Government never accepted this arrangement; they were therefore able to insist on dealing directly with the sheikh, Mobarak-us-Suba, when in 1899 the question of a Persian Gulf terminus for the extension of the Constantinople- Bao’dad Railway began to loom above the horizon. On the 23rd January of that year the sheikh signed a treaty( n ) with Great Britain, which secured British predominance. In 1904 he accepted the appointment of a British Political Agent at his Court. In return Mobarak was given a subsidy. The Turks made repeated efforts to coerce him by means of Ibn Rashid, from whose forces he was saved in 1905 only by a British landing-party. In 1907 the British Government made a more specific agreement with Mobarak by which they secured a perpetual base on the foreshore of the Bandar Shuweikh Basin in Koweit harbour, and the right of pre-empting all or any part of his territory which he might propose to alienate. In return they promised that £ ‘ the town of Koweit and its boundaries belong to Sheikh Mobarak-us-Suba and his heirs after him.” ^ ^ ^ In the Anglo-Turkish Convention^ 1 ) of the 29th July, 1913, the territory of Koweit was recognised as an “autonomous kaza of the Ottoman Empire,” and the sheikh therefore acknowledged the suzerainty of the Turkish Sultan. His territorial boundaries were defined, practical autonomy was conceded to him, and the validity of his agreements with His Majesty’s Government, including the base of land and His Majesty’s Government’s right to give him support, was admitted by the Porte. On the outbreak of the war Mobarak formally repudiated all connexion with the Ottoman Empire, and in November 1914, His Majesty’s Government promised, in return for help against the Turks, that Koweit shall be recognised as an independent principality undei British protection. The sheikh died at the close of 1915. YX. The Emirate of Jebel Shammar (or Hail) rtded by the Emir of Hail. The portion of Northern Central Arabia known geographically as Jebel Shammar, the territory of the great Shammar tribe, formed another of the independent Arabian States at the time of the Arab rising. Geographically, this ( ll ) F.O. 10515.area is an expanse of upland, traversed from south-west to north-east by the two parallel mountain ranges of Jebel Afa and Jebel Selmah, standing some 2o mi es apart. Jebel Afa covers an area of 100 miles by 20. Jebel Selmah 80 long, and is considerably smaller in extent. The greatest altitude of each is less than 5,600 feet above sea-level. The general surface of the Arabian plateau, which falls gradually from south-west to north-east, has hereabouts an elevation of about 2,300 feet. The visible height of these Shammar mountains is, thereiore, correspondingly diminished, and, except for peaks, does not average more than 1,000 feet above the level of the surrounding country. Jebel Afa has a westward continuation in the form of crags and isolated hills of no great height foi 100 miles; Jebel Selmah has a similar continuation southward for about hail that distance. All this broken country is included under the comprehensive name of Jebel Shammar. Precipitation caused by these mountain ranges has made Jebel bhammai an area favourable for Arab life. Springs abound, though making no streams, underground water is plentiful and easily reached; there are man}/ oases, ^d the rainfall is sufficient to ensure pasturage, not only in the upland country, but, in spring, even on the adjoining sands of the Nefud desert. Upon this geographical Jebel Shammar as a centre, a political Jebel Shammar arose, whose confines varied from time to time with the fluctuating fortunes of its Emirs in conflict with their neighbours. In 1914 the Emirate included an area measuring about 300 miles from west to east, and 150 from north to south. Its territorial limits, however, were entirely indeterminate and can only be indicated broadly. On the west it was bounded by Heiaz and included the oasis of Teima; on the south by the Province of Qasim under the suzerainty of the Emir of Nejd; on the east it extended vaguely towards the Euphrates and the territory of Koweit; on the north it had another vague limitation in the Nefud desert. In fact, the important oasis of Jauf-el-Amir, 250 miles to the north, had only been lost to Jebel Shammar four years earlier. The settled population of the Emirate was estimated at 20,000; the nomad population which yielded allegiance to the Emir, about the same. Ihe cultivators and nomads belonging to the Shammar tribe, who comprised the great bulk of the population, formed a solid nucleus closely bound together by loyalty to the Emir, by tribal relations and by a national pride in Shammar achievements during the past fifty years. The unity and fighting capacity of the tribe have been remarked by various European travellers and are attested by recent history. The capita* and chief town was Hail, which stands in the area between the two mountain ranges of Jebel Afa and Jebel Selmah. The population of the Emirate were Sunnis of the Wahabi belief. In practice the townsmen and cultivators were fanatical supporters of the creed, the nomads much less so; but the influence of W ahabism extended into the desert far north towards Damascus. The earlier history of the Emirate goes back only to the close of the 18th century and may be dismissed with a few words. Until the last decade of that century Jebel Shammar represented nothing more, politically, than the territory in which the Shammar Arabs wandered, found opportunities for cultivation, and enjoyed a tribal independence. During the last years of the century the region was brought under the domination of the Emirs of Nejd as the result of Wahabi conquest and conversion. With the overthrow of Wahabi power by the Egyptians in 1817, the Jebel Shammar country became subject to Egyptian control, but with the gradual decline of this alien power and influence, the Emirate of Nejd resumed its authority. In 1835, Emir Feisal appointed Abdullah-bin-Rashid, representing the leading Shammar family, as his Governor in Hail. Abdullah shrewdly used the position to increase his own power and influence, a course rendered the more easy by the detention of Feisal in Cairo for a period of five years. Abdullah did not, however, throw off his allegiance, but on his death in 1847 he left his successor, Talal, virtually free of the authority of ^ Jebel shammar Emirate thus established, great days came with the Emir Mohammed, who seized power in 1875 and proved himself the strongest native ruler seen in Arabia during the 19th century. He not only consolidated his principality and maintained complete independence, but formed the most powerful confederacy of Arab tribes ever effected. At the head of their combined forces in 1891 he brought the Emir of Nejd to battle, the greatest in Arabian history since the coming of Islam, defeated him and occupied Riyadh. Hail now [11932] D18 became the capital of Central Arabia, from Jauf-el-Amir, on the edge of the Syrian desert, to the Great Desert of the south, and Mohammed ruled as sole Emir until his death in 1897. How Nejd, under Abdul Aziz-bm-Saud, the present King of Saudi Arabia and Sultan of Nejd, recovered its independence m 1902, has already been related. ^ • i r Towards the close of his reign Mohammed adopted a pro-Turkish policy, which was followed consistently by his successors in return for Turkish support. Explanation of this policy may be found partly in the comparative ease with which Turkish support or Turkish pressure could be directed upon Hail from Samawa on the Euphrates, and later from the Hejaz Railway. Support, there fore became an alternative the Emirs of Jebel Shammar found preferable to coercion. On various occasions, especially in 1904 and 1905, Ottoman forces assisted the Emirate in its struggle against Ibn Saud and the Sheikh of Koweit. Moreover an aim of Turkish policy at this time was to use Jebel Shammar against supposed British ambitions in Arabia, particularly in the Persian Gulf where, in the Turkish view, His Majesty’s Government had secured the Sheikh of Koweit as a dependent, and, through him, were promoting their interests to the disadvantage of those of the Ottoman Empire. To this end Ibn Rashid was pushed by the Turks into attacking the town of Koweit m 1905, a movement which was countered by His Majesty’s Government landing a naval force m support of the sheikh. After the death of Mohammed no ruler had the strength and personality necessary to hold the widespread Emirate of Jebel Shammar together. Indeed, durin t, ‘ these years, the House of Rashid was divided against itself, and was infamous throughout Arabia for repeated resort to murder as a convenient means of raining the succession. In 1906 the ruling Emir, Abd-el-Aziz, was killed in battle with the forces of Ibn Saud and the Mutair tribe in alliance with him. In 1908 a boy of ten, Saud-bin-Rashid, became Emir and was supported m the position until able to direct affairs himself. He ruled Jebel Shammar during the period of the war. Notwithstanding the fact that the innate solidity and loyalty of the Shammar tribe was never better exhibited than under this Emir, his reign witnessed further curtailment of the Emirate. Hostilities with Nejd were almost continuous In 1910 Ibn Saud compelled Jebel Shammar to surrender the Province of Qasim to his suzerainty. In 1912 Jauf-el-Amir was seized by the Ruwalla sheikh, Nuri-esh-Shalan, who successfully maintained himself against determined Shammar attacks particularly in 1914. ^ . When Turkev entered the war in October 1914, Emir Ibn Rashid, then a featherbrained youth of sixteen, already noted for irresponsible violence, worked hand in hand with the Turks. He supplied them with camels, was actively hostile to the Sheikh of Koweit and the Euphrates tribes who were friendly towards the Allies, and received presents of money, motor cars, rifles, ammunition and even a few machine guns from the Turkish Government. It seems that he undertook to operate against the Allied flank in Mesopotamia, Probably he would have caused trouble in this quarter but for the campaign started against him in January 1915 by the Emir of Nejd. The battle of Jerrab, near Majmaa, which resulted on the 24th January, may have been indecisive, but it put Ibn Rashid’s force out of action for a time and produced a treaty of peace in which the advantage lay with Ibn Saud. By this treaty, signed on the 10th June, 1915, Ibn Rashid’s authority was confined to the narrower Jebel Shammar He withdrew his pretensions to Qasim, and acknowledged Ibn Saud s suzerainty over certain tribes, a matter hitherto in question, and rejected only the Emir of Nejd’s claim to the overlordship of Jebel Shammar. But the peace which followed had no reality and Ibn Rashid merely awaited his opportunity. VII.— Jauf-el-A mir. The part of Northern Arabia lying around Jauf-el-Amir, which in 1910 came under the independent government of Nuri-esh-Shalan, Paramount Chief of the Ruwalla, cannot be regarded as having been one of the chief autonomous areas of \rabia * It was too limited in resources and could not have direct relations with the outer world in a way possible to a State owning a seaboard. The Yemen, Asir Nejd, and, in less degree, Jebel Shammar, all had their bases in large settled populations of cultivators; the Hejaz, in the accident that it was the Holy Land of Islam. Jauf, however, had no such permanent foundations. Jauf, as an19 independent area, rested upon a confederation of purely nomad tribes, who, while ranging over desert and steppe larger in extent than Great Britain, made the Jauf group of oases their rallying point and centre of supplies. Further, tribal confederation and the capture of Jauf alike, were due to the personality of the Paramount Chief, Nuri-esh-Shalan, whom Colonel T. E. Lawrence described as ^the best Arab sheikh he ever met. It always seemed that the natural condition *of Jauf would be one of dependency either upon a powerful Jebel Shammar or on a greater central Arabian State, which included Jebel Shammar, or, again, upon a power seated in the north, such as, for instance, an independent Syria. To either of such dominant neighbours, south or north, Jauf would have been a valuable possession, as controlling the one route across the desert which separated Central Arabia from Syria. By this route Jauf is about 260 miles from Hail, in Jebel Shammar, and 350 miles from Damascus. Jauf had also a further strategical importance which made itself felt. In the event of the construction of a railway from the north into Central Arabia, the route to be followed would lie from the Hejaz Railway at Jizah in Transjordan and thence up the W adi Sirhan to Jauf. As far as is known no other route is practicable. Jauf-el-Amir (so called to distinguish it from other Jaufs) is merely an oasis a few miles in length, in a depression at the head of the Great W adi Sirhan. To the north-east are several smaller oases. The group stands in the midst of desert and derives its chief importance from that fact. Jauf was subject to the Emirate of Nejd during the period of Wahabi conquests, and later to the Emirate of Jebel Shammar. In 1910 Nuri-esh-Shalan, a nomad chieftain whose authority extended over a confederacy of Aneiza tribes, seized the group of oases and with stood all the efforts of the Emir of Jebel Shammar to eject him. In 1916 the population of the oasis group of Jauf did not exceed 11,000, but the tribal confederacy of nomads recognising Nuri, a confederacy whose ranging- grounds extended from Jauf in the south to Damascus in the north, and to what is now Transjordan in the west, may have numbered as many as 20.000 souls. Upon this wandering and widely-dispersed population alone rested Nuri-esh- Shalan's ability to maintain himself in Jauf. The northern portion of the confederacy came within the reach of Turkish authority. Nuri and his House therefore took a lively interest in Turkish affairs as matters closely concerning their own future In 1911 the Paramount Chief was invited to Damascus by the Vali, Sami Pasha, and was there imprisoned for a year. This indignity alienated him from the Turkish cause. In 1913 the Turkish Government proposed to carry a branch of the Hejaz Railway from Jizah to Qaf in the Wadi Sirhan, for the purpose of extending Turkish authority over the desert tribes. The scheme was violently opposed by Nun and had to be abandoned in consequence. When war broke out in 1914 he refused to collect camels for the Ottoman Government and removed his tribes to their eastern pastures beyond reach of the Turks. His tribes, among the greatest camel- breeders in Arabia, possessed vast numbers of animals, and the withholding of these supplies greatly increased Turkish difficulties during the attack on the Suez Canal. Nuri’s son, Nawwaf, who governed Jauf on behalf of his lather, was a strong supporter of the pan-Arab movement. Indeed, Nuri-esh-Shalan and his confederacy were accounted by the Emir of Mecca as among his firmest and most important supporters during the Arab rising. Foreign Office, May 1935. o</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ad_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2147</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ad</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2147</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/74 'Foreign Office memorandum entitled "The Seven Independent Arabian States." (Yemen, Asir, the Hejaz, Nejd, Kowait, Jebel Shammar, and Jauf.)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-22T11:30:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (12 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 14; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the centre top of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a memorandum received by the India Office from the Foreign Office. The memorandum, produced by the Foreign Office in May 1935, is entitled 'The Seven Independent Arabian States' (identified as Yemen, Asir, the Hejaz, Nejd, Kowait, Jebel Shammar, and Jauf) and aims to provide a brief outline of each of the seven states at the time of the Arab rising against the Turks in June 1916.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ad#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>