<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000098_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T01:55:52.048Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN ; v&gt;. 77 No. Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Batedrp 7th Shabhan, 1346 ft5/I a of 1346 To The H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, The people of Muharrak have complained that there is neither a post boxKor any arrangement for distribution of the incoming mails in Maharrak. They say that every person who receives letters sends a servant to Manama on mail day. Could some arrange ment be made with the approval of the postal authoritie whereby a Government servant or Policeman could take say, from the Police Station in Laharak. Also it would be of great convenience if a pillar box could be set up in the Police Station and some one authorised to sell stamps. such arrangement the Bahrain Government could supply a reliable man to do the work. The Municipal Council have asked me to refer . the matter to you. If the Postal Authorities would sanction some 1 have the honour to be, Sir Your Obedient Servant, BAHREIN ST A T E.i4*o • oi* 19 &lt;6. The Politioal Agency# Bahrein. Bated the £/k February 19Jd8 . To The Adviser# Bahrein Stats# Bahrei n. Reference your letter JNo.575/9a dated the 7th Shabhan 1340. The Bub-Bostoaster Bahrein, has been asked to refer to his Department in order to obtain the required f acili ties. Political Agent, Bahrein.Political Agent# Bahrein MO III /i.4/1 of io r ^a The Political Agency, iJul’reiri. Hated the February 19• F r on! The Political Agent, Bahrein. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind &amp; Persian Sulf Division, Karachi. Sir, I have the honour to invite a reference to this office letter Wo.765/i4/l» dated the leth September 19&amp;7, to and/enquire what is being done about the matter. The uystem olT door to door delivery would be much appreciated by the inhabitants of the Manama Municipality. I have the honour to be, oir, Your moot obedient servant a—*o Dated nhe 31st March 1928 i?' roin Hie Political A&amp;ont Bahrein* To The superintendent of Pont Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, r&gt; Karachi. I have the honomvto refer to the correspondence ending with tly Wo.lll/14/l of 22nd February 1928 and to enquire whether the system of door to door delivery of letters within the limits of Manana Municipality is likely to be adopted at an early date, 2. The Bahrein State have enquired whether it would be permissible for a Bahrein Government servant to tak* over iron the Post office all letters received by the incoming mails, and to take them to Muharraq for delivery. Tills would be a great convenience to the people of the separate i sland of Huiiarraq. Insy further request that a pillar box be erected at Liuharruq Police station and an official vendor of stamps appointed. j recommend that tho desires of the Muharr&amp;q poople oe met as far as feasible, jt would be preferable to appoint a Post Office official to take the nails for that island. I have the honour to be. 3ir, Your most obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrein* Copy to Bub-Postmaster, Bahrein♦ Telegram From Superintendent of Posts* Karachi, To Sub-Postmaster, Bahrein, Dated and received 10th April 1928. A Your telegram 4th, Par at cost of Bahrein Government is required to convey mail bag between Panama Poharrak. Branch Postmaster Uoharraq will be paid some allowance f rom the Departnent. t /OtNo. of 19Q0. The Political Agency# Bahrein. Dated the 11th April 1988. r ’ / ^\TN The Adviear# Bahrein State# Ba^irein. x ^emorandun . The Sub Postmaster, Bahrein infoms me that hie Superintendent is in favour of opening an extra Depart mental Branch Post Office at iiuharraq and for this purpose he has been asked to furnish a return for a fortnight# showing the number of articles received and desptached by the people of Muharraq. The Sub Post* aster requests that all people of that island nay be notified that, during a fortnight# they should hand in all their postal articles at the Manama Post Office# instead of posting them in letter boxes. The Postal Superintendent also enquires whether the Bahrein Government would be prepared to appoint# at their own cost# a trustworthy official for conveying mail bags between Manama and Muharraq. ' Political Agent# Bahrein.From ♦ H Q/ogf c** 4 . v, v»$• v v ♦ \ J* \ No,~., rt , 13^ ^9 ^fft§TAT&lt; ' 1 V Thb turn, of post om^t, ^^iimodPta8i«6U(..-TT To /' Number of enclosures The.. Political -a^ent, Bahrein. Dated Karachi t 4/4/28 /$? Subject: Outdoor delivery at Bahrein. Sir, * O With reference to your letter x,o: 111/14/1 dated the 22/2/28, I have the honour to say that the Sub Postmaster Bahrain has been directed to suomit required statements in this connection, with a view to enable me to see whether the outdoor delivery can be effected by the existing delivery staff or whether an additional Postman will be required for the purpose. l 1 he sub Postmaster contends that the present delivery staff is insufficient to cope with the work of door to door delivery, fhe sub Postmaster Bahrein has been expedited and on receipt of statements from him action will be taken and door to door delivery will be ordered. I have etc, 1 E.B.V Superintendent “ - oi P. Os, Uf.^wer^in^ad P. - *vn: 4 \. t h © * '*1. 1 — ■i &gt;1 No. $ 3 of 1346 Office of /he Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 14th April, &gt;n'.0CAL The K. B. M*? Political Agent, Memorandum ’ x ^ '-4£9?s/an Ref. your 219/ of 1928 of 11-4-28. I will make arrangements with Maharaq Baladya for posting of Muharaq letters in Manama. The Bahrain Government would certainly be prepared to appoint an official for conveying the Mails.Ho. of 1928&gt; Th« Political Ag«ncy Bahrtin, April 1928. To Th« Sub Postmaster, Bahrein. Memorandum. Reference your letter Ho.4 dated the 1st April 1928. The Bahrein Government ie prepared to appoint an official for conveying mail bags between Manama and Muharraq. your Department, arrangements have been made with the Muharraq kunicipality for posting all articles in the Manama Post Office. V.ith regard to the Return required by Political Agent.Bahrein./ UAJL ) P rogs.— 26 . r~r Al! (ommunications ulieald fee addressed to— Tha Siperintendoai, 'DiTieloa, (by title NOT by nam&amp;. Number of enclosures n * *x - 4r AN. anb A *^P Ko/^.s. To 277 /tT'S'-i? —1^ia.]—ugenti- Bahrein Dated Karachi tbe. /$/^U t*,l Sib, Opening tn extra Departmental B.o. at iiuharrak. ■ in continuation of this office endorsement No - A 184 dated, the 26/4/28, I have the honour to say that you will pfr hi# let me know definetily If Bahrein Government is prepared to arrange to appoint a nail carri toe tween iiuharrak and Bahrein i'.O. and. vice jersa^ at theii own cost if an extra Departmental Branch/Office is opened at Muharrak for the convenience of the puoiio. fhe adviser to the Government Bahrein has already t .0 you Vide his letter no: 57 6/&amp;ia, of l.Vlo 1! dated the 7th 3 haatoan,a copy of which,was fonvarded * to me toy the sut Postmaster Bahreln^that he would appoint a Government servant oE X&amp;XXHsiX to take over the iiuharrak post from the Bahrein i .0, on mail days. x'his man appointed toy the Bahrein Government may serve as a mail carrier who will exchange sealed mail Dag x* tho - ronoqed Branch Office at liuharrak wl tli^the , from the. ^roppsea «ran .. ^ Rfahl , ein .- ovt Bahrein P.0, and vice versa, fhe Official author!sed^as Bxtra departmental Branchpostmaster will selx Suampx. and perform all P.0, work except Divings Bank, Issue and Payment of Koney Orders, issue and delivery -oi Insured letters and Issue of Foreign parcels. *Lib official will toe paid some allowance from tnis Depurtimen^ suy uDout ha. 10/- h.^. / Superin 'Dendeni, of P .Os, Lower Sind uhd P. 0 Divn; Axio. Ol* 19Z&amp;. Tho Political Afionoy» 3ahrc3in. Dated the//'/^ May 19£8. To The Superintendent of Foot Offices# Lower Sind and Persian Gulf# Karachi• Dl vi aion# Meporandun • The Bahrein Goverr^nent is prepared to appoint a Mail carrier at their own cost to perform tho duties set forth in your No.Ale* ol* 5th May 192b. /0 Poli tical u Agent# Bahrein.No. 1057/9A of Office of tile Adv^F^r to Govornnont Bahrain. Daibod, 17t.?i 1&gt;j1 Ha j 1^4^. To Tlia Director of CuGtonu- Ivlsrao Rof. attached corrospondence vdiich oloaro return. I think that, the kest official to act ac Hlxtra D opart-rental Branch poet naete'r will bo the Cue tore Clerk at Muharraq; it will aleo bo very convenient as the Police Station is adjoining the Customs Office* Will you ploaee let no know it* you have any objection to thie arrangement from a Cue tone point of view. Sd. L.S.Parke Adv i e e r, Balir e 1 n S t a t eCUEtO^B Houe®, Bahrein. No.81/183/288. 9th Juno 1988 Slot Dhul Haj 1346. The Adyieer, The Government of Bahrein. h)b Sir, I liaye tlie honour to acknowledge the receipt of your No.1057/9 A., of 17th Dhul HaJ 1548, which enquires if the Customs Officer, stationed at the Maharaq Custom House, may hare added to his duties those of Extra Departmental postmaster, on pavmnt of an allowance of Hs.lO/- per month. I hare carefully perused your copy of No.A.184 from the Superintendent of P.O’o Lower Sind and Persian Gulf, which I return herewith, and, by way of comment I would remark!- 1. 'Hie official ••• will sell stamps and perform all P.0, work except.....' It would bo well if it were stated more clearly khat work is expected of this official, so that one may Judge whether or not the remuneration of Rs.10/- p.m. ic adequate or otherwise. 2. Calculating duty pro rata to salary, it seems that the pro posed Hs.io/- p.m. suggests less than an half hour’s work each day. IS this likely to be the case? 5. Customs work must not be delayed on account of postal work, as the former is of considerable importance} and the official will be on duty during the usual Customs hours of duty. 4 . The officer at Maharaq is not allowed to handle money, or take any responsibility therefor. Consequently for the custody and sale of stamps, he should please be provided with a safe. 5. To whom is this official expected to report, for his postal duties, please? I raise these points in order to avoid future misunderstand ings in working; and I trust I may be favoured with definite we- plies, so that I may decide whether or not the officer at Maharaq may be entrusted with these suggested duties. I return the correspondence herewith. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. C.C.L.deGronier Director of Customs. No. 3/’S of 1928. Tlie Political Agency, Bahrein. Dated tlie /X June 1928. Forwarded to the Sub Postmaster, Bahrein, for his views on para 1, as to the hours of work and provision fff safe. sion dlf safe. . cl Political AflatrtTjHahrsln.///y of 1346 e Aaviser to The H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain Memorandum Reference attached correspondence which please return. to undertake the duties of Extra Departmental Post Master will be the Customs Clerk at Muharaq. connection, but I agree that it would be better if certain points were cleared up before he takes over his duties. As regards para 1 of Director of Customs letter I do not think any action is necessary and naturally Customs work cannot be allowed to suffer and I cannot see any reason wipjr^ it should. The clerk will draw an allowance and will have to expect to work longer hours at times. the Post Master at Manama for all postal duties. I shall be sEe+i grateful if these small matters could be cleared up. In my opinion the most suitable official I do not anticipate any trouble in this an allowance of Ks. 10/- or so wiM, appear ample Para 3, as regards the hours of work; Para 4. Possibly the Postal authorities will supply a safe or suitable box. Para 5. I take it that he will be under Adviser to the Government, Bahrain' [ui^. C. ►W jt.vU. ^ W lu. Ux~ ^ ' rA N*. ^f2S /l4/lf 1928. Th# Political Agency, Balirein* Dated the 7July 1928, @ i ?• Tlie Adyiaer, Balirein State, Bahrein. Memorandum . Reference yeur nemerandum No.l974/9A, the 23rd Dul Haj 1346. The Superintendent ef Poet Offices in Sindh has now made a new proposal that the Portal Department should keep a regular letter box in Muharraq and should •u extra postman to clear the box regularly cell stamps and postcards and to make deliveries in Muharraq town. Will this arrangement suit you better than the appointment of the Customs clerk Muharraq as an extra departmental hand. J If you prefer the appointment of the Customs clerk the hours ef work would be arranged to suit his convenience as far as possible. cl Political Agent, Bahrein. - / tie-pAy (J* ^( AV Eo. y^/ JA of 1347 Office of/the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 27th Maharam 1347 The H. h. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. \ -y~ Memorandum Reference correspondence ending with your Bo. 423/14/1 of 1928 dated, 7th July 1928 I consider that the last proposal must be most satisfactory as it will do away with any question of division of duties and the Postal department will be entirely separate. /?; wkT. H 1 ^ 14 ^ ^ ^ ~ r , 11 ^ j ^ a 4 , ^ / wh xHo. Sn of 1928 folitical Agency,S A H H A I H. Bated August 1928. To The bub Pootniaater f B A H H A I I?# Memorandm a. Referenoe the correspoiideaco on the uuoject of a subordinate Post Office at Muharraq. The Bahrain Goyernaerit prefer the proposal of of the buperintendent of Poet Offices in Sindh that the Postal Department should keep a re^uidlr letter box in iiuharraq anu should ex^u^e an extra postman, to to clear the box regularly, sell stamps f aiid make deliveries in Muiiarraq town. ue put into force early. The correspondence on this simple matter has now oeen in progress without result for six months. Copy is forwarued to the Superintendent of Post Offices lower bina ana Persian Gulf, Division, Karachi. I recommend that these new proposals should Political Agent, Bahrain.^F. From To : Qv: 4 umb^r of enclosures ( post Office. Ho ^ —- fv •V - Postmaster r Bahrain.— Tkk ^PoUtioal Agent, # Bahrain^ - D^eSfBhrain ^’thr AttgtteV^ • Sin, In oomplianee with your no, £44 dated the 8tA.. Augost 1928 # I hare the honour to inform you that the Superintendent of Post Offioes, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Bn,, Karachi HA*4 has been duly referred to and requested to take necessary action to sanotion an extra Postman for making delirery in Hoharraq. Town. N, * He is also requested to supply me with a Letter- Box to be put up there at an early date. YU ft* . I Hare the honour to be ; Sir Your Most Obedient Servant, b-Postmaster. * % -7 Sr (fty. 11 n a uvft-v^- ^ . ixf ^ ^ $&gt;No of 1928 fb3 The Political Agency# Bahrein* Dated the 22'&gt;wA AugU3fc 19 r£ # To The Postmaster# Bahrein. kenorandup . Reference attached telogr-an of 22nd August fran tlie Superintendent# Post Office a, Karachi to your address. The Hoad peon of tills Agency who draws Ro.50/-p.n. Hospital conpcmnder who draws Rs.fiS/- p.n. arid other menial £ b? of this Agenoy are not in receipt of local or compensatory o/ allowance special pay. Indian Assistant# in the absence of the Political Agent# Bahrein.Telegram From Enolair. Superintendent# Post Offices# Karachi Post Bahrein. Te Dated the 15th September 19^8 • Ascertain and wire whether Bahrein Garemnent will undertake to transport additional postman if sanctioned to and from i^uharraq free of charge. &lt;ur» N©. U V ' 0 i* iggQ 0 The Political Agency# Bahrein. Dated the kgnd September 19^8• Cepy forwarded to the Adviser Bahrein State for information with a request that views of the Bahrein Government on the subject may please be communicated at an early date. v _ intlian Assistant, in the absence of the Political Agent# Bahrein.• A* ^ ^ -^'* u ho. 93/9A ° f 1347 Office of/The*A(iviBe^ to the G-overrix'nent , Bahrain, Dated, 9th E'T^any, 1347 Ref. your letter 600 of 22nd Septr 1928. This Government ^undertake to trans port the additional postman to and from Maharak free whenever he likes, and Before I reply to the question, I should like to know exactly what the wire means. I would he most grateful if this information can he obtained when a definite answer will he given. I presume the cost of his trans port would he at the usual charges i.e. t The H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum ■*. \J V/ V-4_ U Ks Ut XX. ^ KA. Kj JL. W i-i-CU. X ^ W kO p two annas hy launch and one anna hy Joli boat. Captain, Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Adv/N.3 °) 7-7 (36 C Ho. V v ~ of 19S0 # Th© Political Agency# Bahrein. Dated the Jb4th September 1920 • To The Adviser# Bahrein State# Bahrein. Memorandum• V (, Reference your memorandum Ho.293/9A# dated the 9 th R * TJiany &gt; 1347. The Superintendent of Poet Offices, Karachi# wants to knov/ whether the Bahrein Government will under take to transport to and from huharraq free of charge the additional postman for Muharraq if sanctioned. Will you therefore please reply at an early date whether the Bahrein Government would undertake to transport the postman free of charge. cy^ Indian Assistant# in the absence of the Political Agent# Bahrein.fc.r'- No. dot)/ f/f of 1347 Office of/the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 12th R/Thany 1347 The H. B. M f s Political Agent Bahrain. * * z&gt; ^ S ^ ^ ' * 2.7 * ^ ^ ^ Memorandum ^7 Ref. 'correspondence ending with your No. 606 of 1928 dated 24/9/28. I have the honour to refer you again to my No. 293/9A of 1347. If the cost of transport does not exceed that mentioned in the last sentence of my letter, say twice a week, this Govt, will be prepared to pay, but in order that there may be no questions raised in the future as to the liability of this Government having to hire special launches and joliboats I would request that a definite ruling may be given. Captain, Adviser to the Government, Bahr in. Ia, fix *• - • /%&lt;7 M, Adv/N i d,‘Si' tikaA f-fov of 19 £8 Wo. //f Th» Political Aganay# Bahrain. Dated tha Octobar 1920. To Tha Sub-Poatmaatar, Bahrain. |,V*&gt; Mamorandun. Rafaronca Suparintandant Poat Officea Karachi * a talagran of 15th September 1920 to your address. Tha Bahrain Stata ia willing to pay tha coat of a aeat in a launch or boat between Manana and Muharraq twiee a weak. I trust that tha neeessary steps for establishing a regular letter box in Muharraq will be taken at an early data • ' a Political Agent, Bahrein.t 4 ) 31 . 77 ^ Ho. L l ^/l4/4 Of lOfcS. The Politioal Agency# Bahrein. Dated the November 19!# . To The Adviaer# Bahrein State# Bahrein. i&lt;x eaorandun . Pleaae refer to the oorreapondonce ending with your No.300/9A of 12th Rabi n 1347. The sub Postmaster# Bahrein has now boon authorised to engage an add!tonal Postaan for the Buharraq area. The sub Postmaster proposes to send this man to Muharraq# after the arrival of each mail# to mako deliveries# clear the letter box and sell stamps. Will you kindly arrange for the transport of the Postman and also arrange to inform the inhabitants of the additional convenience now offered them. /f - n /i ^ Poll ti cal agent # Bahroji .■MM'lio. 3S3 Of 1929. Tli« Politioal Agency, 2'ljk Bahrein 4 / April 1929. Copy forwarded to the Adviser, Bahrein Government, Bahrein, for information and favour of opinion* « Political Agent, Bahrein* \No# So / of 1S29. The ioliticcl A^^ency, Bahrein# Bated the I:ay 192&amp;# The Adviser, Bahrein State, Bahi’ein# I invite a i’eierenoe to my endorsement ho383 dated the 27th April 1929 raid request that the reply thereto may please he expedited# Cffit Captain, Political A^-ent, Bahrein#To No. / S' Of 1347 Office of/the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 14th Dil Haj 1347 H. B. It's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum / S * . ■ ^/i 5 /L ^ V ;atc Ref. your No. 50l of 23rd Mty 1929. ■ -'V. -•' ^ I referred the question to the Muharrak Municipality who have not yet replied. As the suggestion was made by one man onlylsee fio reason for altering the present arrangement whicn^m^de in agreement with the Municipality. 9 Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. y A s•&gt; No. 0 f 1929. \ The Political Agency, Bahrein. Dated the May '1929{' Copy forwarded to the Postmaster,' Bahrein, - for information, with reference to his letter No.67, dated the 24th April 1929. 0- i Captain, Political Agent, Bahrein.To Office of y!ie Ad no. /£'&amp;9/9/l' Office of yiie Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 27th Dil Kaj 1347 iof 1347 K. 13. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum * With further reference to your 501 of 23rd May 1929, The Muharak Municipality do not consider it necessary to alter the present postal arrangements but suggest that the Postman might stay for two hours in Muharak when he goes over to enable people to buy stamps etc. This I consider is a reasonable suggestion. Copy forwarded to the Postmaster, ahrein, for information in continuation of this office endorsement No.517 dated the 26th May 1929. Adviserto the Government, Bahrain. t he Go ve r nm e nt, PU. UJ. X J CjJ . The Political Agency, Bahrein. Dated the Q rf June 1929. ioP' Woi'l929 Political Agent, Bahrein. Captain,Li / —tf-r-' ' v '' 'U, &gt; a T^Wr / GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. SOf of 1348 Office of/the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Bated, 12th R/Thany 1348 Memorandum The Manama Municipality have asked me to request that a branch telegraph office of the 'ireless should be opened in the Bazaar, from which the public can send telegrams. If the authorities were disposed to make such an arrangement, it would be greatly appreciated by the general public. Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. (A -i. ix ' L ^ Adv/N. &gt;A /lGQViiiRIG&amp;jfiNT OF B^JRAIH. HO. 50X/8 Of 1348 Off loo of tho Adviser to the Gov eminent, Bahrain. Bated 12th R/Thany 1348. To E. B. M»s Political Agent, Bahrain. Hemeorandum. The Manamah Eunicipality hare asked me to r^uost that a hratoch telegraph Office of tho Wireless should he opene in the Bazaar, from which the public can send telegrams. If the authorities were disposed to make such an arrangement, it would hegreatly appreciated by the general pub lie. Sd/ 0. Bairanple Balegrare Adviser to the Government,Bahraina©. x.Jf of 1929 * Office of the Political Agent 9 Bahrain Bated Karcahi 2?th S«petmher,1929. To the Bireotor, Xndo-European Telegraph Bepartment Persian Oulft Karachi* I©g^.9, y A ^ Uf A copy of Adviser to the Bahrain Government letter B©.50|/8 dated 12th H/Phany 13^8 is forwarded to the B^rector of Telgraphs Persian Gulf* It would he of great benefit to the public if the desired arr&amp;ngi&amp;ent could be made and several representations were A ^ade to me regarding it before I left for Karachi. olitleal Agent, BahrainIf o A, No. of 1351 Office of tne Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 24th J/Thany 1351 24th Octr. 1932. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum I have been asked by the Municipal Council of Manamah to enquire whether it would be possible for the Post Office to establish a branch in the Bazaar aatj the distance to the Post Office from the Bazaar is, in the opinion of the Council, a great inconvenience to the public. A similar request has been made in respect of the Wireless Office which is a longer dis tance from the Bazaar than the Post Office. 4 *-, /A ' rA€'•. P. P.—L (hi) 1101—500-11-31. From No. H&amp;S OF 193 ^-* Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the stlx November 193 E. THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN. To / hi Sir, The Manager^ Imper ial L Interna tional-Gommunications Limitea, KaracUi. I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter from the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain ana my forwaruin^ letter &amp;o the hi rector of the inao European Telegraph Department uatea the 22na September 1929. i feel that it is unlikely in view of the present financial stringency that your Company will be able to meet the wishes of the Bahrain public but since the matter has again been raisea,! am sending, you a co£y of the papers whicn were formerly sent to the Indo European Telegraph Leparuuent to which no reply has apparently been received. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obeuient Servant, n oiitical Agent, ^ Bahrain.C’s. P. P.—L (in) 979—400-12-29 —l. NO. J OF 1932^^ Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the—^Ttl Movember l 93Z. To The Adviser, Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. Please refer to your letter No:642/8 uatea the 24th October 1902 regarainf; the establishrient of a branch Post of lice and a branch ireless office in the lanama bazaar- I fear at the present moment it will be useless to approach the Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs,find ana Baluch istan Circle,with a request for a sub-office in the anama Bazaar,as the Post Office bucket has been the subject of most ruthless cuts ana any auaitional expense which was not absolutely essential for the running of the oepartment will str.nd no hope of being sanctioned at the present moment. 1 fear the same also applies to the opening of a branch Aireleas oflice.since this wou]d need extra staff to sena messages by land line from the bazaar to the wireless office, Sven if only a sub-office was opened with a clerk to take traffic aixd senu il by messenger to the wireless office, considerable expense would be incurred ana now that the Bahrain Radio is being run on a purely commercial basis,the Imperial an^ international hoifimunications him!ten are most unlikely to embark on fresh expenditure al a time when they are obliged to pay reaucea aiviaends. 1 find,however,that the question has been raised about the telegraph office before without any result being obtained ana I am senaing them a reminuer. Political Agent,Bahrain. 0Vj: No POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN,the 22nd JANUARY 1933. TO, The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. xV.emorandum. Your memorandum wot642/8 dated the 24th October 1932 and my predecessor^ reply hotll86 dated the 9th wovember 1932. The manager,Persian Gulf Section,Imperial and International Communications Limited,Karachi, informs roe that as the amount of traffic booked does not warrant the expenditure that would be involved, he regrets that it is not possible to undertake to open an office in the bazaar. aeut Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain. ■i i——D.O.No. / Adviaerate, December 27, 1944. (3 I enquired from Shaikh Abdulla bin Isa about his building in Muharraq which is let to the Muharraq Municipality. It appears that the whole building is used by the Municipality, the ground floor for a ration ticket office. I suggest that the Postmaster should ask the Secretary of the Muharraq Municipality whether he knows of a suitable house. Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.3., O.B.3., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. RaWm Rece ^. ( Noi ^- Da ‘ 9 *Corr.- 60 . IWPIAH POSTS AMO TBLECrRAPHa PgPARTMS’-WT' EXPRESS LETTER. Kf . A.Moharrak. n . } nyderabad 5ind X6th,Feb. 45. XHO. Dal f t . the, iqj. Sir., I ha/© the honour to stat® that in order to give postal feciliti e s to the residents of Moharrak locality at Bahrain, it has b*=en decided to open a non delivery fcrcsH xxk aXXxksl Town oib uffice at ii.oharr^ and for this purpo a suitable building will be required. • for a suitable building and intimate the rent at which tne same is secured together with details of the accommo dation to enable me to obtain the ijirector of i^o sts and xe legr aph s? sin d and ^alu chi stan v^i rcie ^ar achi 1 s san ct ion for renting the building. « To The nis British majesty's political Agent B A H it A I if. **** ** * *-? 4 « **** Subject:- upening of a Host oft ice at mohrrakt,Bahrain) . 1 therefore request you would kindly arrange I have etc,, sup sr in tendent of Host offices, - nc^er *ind 6c Bersitn uaif jjiv.D.O.No.y&amp;J- 14/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 28th February, 1945. My dear Belgrave,- I understand that two shops in Muharra'q Nos.21 and 22 would be suitable for the proposed Post Office there, and the Secretary of the Municipality has told the Sub Postmaster that both shops are likely to be vacant by the end of this month. Will you kindly let me know whether His Highness (to whom I understand they belong) will be willing to rent them to the Post Office and if so at what rate? Yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Ksq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.No. v Y83- 14/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 28th February, 1945* To The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain. © Memorandum . Please let me have details of the accommodation available in shops Nos.21 and 22 in Muharraq as this information will be required by the Superintendent of Post Offices, if they are subsequently rented from His Highness Shaikh Salman. Political Agent, Bahrain• ■w • j.\* 0 Adviserate, March 6, 1945. Bahrain Receipt Reference your D.O.No.782-14/4 dated 28th February 1945. His Highness is willing to rent the two shops in Muharraq. fora post office. The rent is Rs.7/- per shop, is. 14/- for both. I am writing to the present occupants of the shops to vacate them at the end of the month. If the post office wishes any alterations or additions to be made they will have to do such work at their own expense. J . Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.F., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.£*Om ^?^XV4. &amp; Political Agancy, Bahrain, The 12th March, 1945* To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.A. Moharrak dated the 16th February 1945 £ and to inform you that His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain is prepared to give on rent two shops in Muharraq for the Post Office. The monthly rent is Es.7/- per shop l«e«, Es.14/- for both shops. They will be available at the end of this month. Any alterations or additions to be made should be carried out by you at your own expense. 2. The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain reports that these shops are quite suitable for the Post Office The size of each shop is 22 feet by 12^ feet. Copy to the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain, for information. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, V No. for Political Agent, Bahrain-—' •' No.1522-14/4 1 / * [' I i,r* Political Agency, Bahrain, The 11th April, 1945. To © The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad. Sir, I have the honour to refer to my letter No.974-14/4 dated the 12th March 1945 and to inform you that the shops in question are now vacant. I have the honour to be, Sir, Yd»ur most obedient servant, •L for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain, for information.V v i ■a DtpJA’K P08T3 AND TELEQBAPITa DDFARTSflNT, VV ^ • s^n!L DF J m PFFlutli ' ^'D fcBSMN GULF GN. A .13 5( a ) . The political Agent? BAHRAIN, ******** Hyderabad ttind, 24 th^pr # , 1945 OPENING OP A POST OFh'IO AT MOtlAHRAK# ]P * J * Sir 09 With reference to your letter no # 152S-14/4 dated tha 4,4.45, i have the honour to state that the following additions and alterations are required in the two shops to make them suitable the post office pu ipo se and request y&gt;u kindly to intimat© tihe ^pproxioiat© cost which will be required for the purpose, 1, Flooring. , _ 2, An outsit© communicating door between the two shops, 3, A running counter. An eariy return is requested, I have etc,, Chaang/-.No,-1874-14/4. Pol' 5 ft cal Agency, Bahrain, ww The 2nd Hay, IK5. Copy forwarded to'the Sub. Postmaster, Bahrain for potion. ,for Political ..gent, Bah: y iTI.rouoi av No•2062-14/4* To Political Agency f Bahrain, The 19th May, 1945. The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain* Memorandum * Will you please refer to my endorsement No. 1874-14/4 dated the 3rd April, 1946 on the subject of an estimate for repairs etc* to the proposed Muharraq Post Office building, and let me have an immediate reply as the Superintendent of Post Offices, Hyderabad has sent a telegraphic reminder. y.'j ^ for Political Agent, Bahrain. £ 'Telegram From To No. Dated $41 Bn Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Superintendent Post Hyderabad Sind. 345 22nd May, 1945 .© s , S Your telegram A-135 (A). Estimated cost &amp;.540 excluding 15 bags cement also required. =POLITICALf AP40. ...© u No.2656-14/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 26th June, 1945. To The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain. Reference your Express Letter No.260 dated the 21st June, 1945. 2. The Agency P.W.D. Supervisor is not able to undertake the work of furnishing an estimate for the repairs to the Muharrak Post Office, but he will be glad to give you any advice you may require. It is suggested that you may get the estimate prepared through a local contractor. for Political Agent, Bahrain6 &gt; 4 '- Political Agency, Bahrain, The 6th August, 1946. Ro.3177-14/5. 1 ^ My dear/Belgrave, Kindly refer to your deini-official letter No.5?3~9 A dated the 6th March, 1945, / concerning the Post Office in Muharraq* 2. The Superintendent of Post Offices, Sind, now writes to say that the two shops offered by His Highness are net suitable for the proposed Post Office. I shall be glad, therefore, if you would inform His Highness and also apologise for any inconvenience that may have been caused. Yours sincerely, lA ^ ^ A C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. C.No.3247-14/4. Political Agency 9 Bahrain f The 12th August, 1345. To The Superintondent of Post Offices, Lorer Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind. Kindly refer to your letter No.A. 135 (a) dated the C 1 * 30th July, 1943. ■ t t 2. The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain in his letter No.944 dated the 26th February, 1945 informed me that he had inspected the two shops in Muharraq in company with you and that they were considered suitable. 3. His Highness the Kuler very kindly had them vacated and placed at your disposal and you were informed to this effect ^ vide my letter No. 1522-14/4 dated the 11th April, 1946#^ p.5 4. In your letter No.A.135 (a) dated the 30th July, 1945, you stated that the two shops in question were not in a ^ \ * habitable condition and were therefore no longer required. This opinion appears to be in complete contradiction to that expressed by the Superintendent of Post Offices himself when he visited the shops in February this year# 5# Wood is expensive and in short supply in Bahrain and labour rates are high. I am therefore of the opinion that the cost of repairs amounting to about Hs.550/- is reasonable and it is extremely improbable that a house could be obtained in which repairs for a less amount ware necessary. 6. I would therefore ask you to reconsider your decision about the two shops in Muharraq, to sanction their lease on the terms in my letter No.974-14/4 of 12th March, 1945, and also to sanction the cost of the necessary alterations up to R3.550/- when X would approach His Highness the Ruler once more. Copy to the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain, with reference to his endorsement No.400 dated the 8th August, 1945. for Political Agent, Bahrain.&amp; (,/ No. 3264-14/4. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 13th August, 1945* Dear Mr. Belgrave, 4r Kindly refer to my letter No*3177-14/4 dated the 6th August, 1945* ^ f 2. I am enclosing herewith a copy of my letter No*3247-14/4 of the 12th August, 1946, to the Superintendent of Post Offices, which is self explanatory. Could you consider my statement that the two shops were not now required as not final until I receive a reply to this letter? I will of course let you know as soon as possible, but I thought it worth while to try and persuade the Post Office authorities to reconsider their decision* C* Dalrymple Bolgrave, Esq., C*3.E*, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Yours sincerely, C^ - @lr l ) \TAkl FQST&amp;'AKO FjbOX i? v ! SUPOT. OF POST OFHUtii '-' 9t lOWDI SIND A,\U PLSBIAN GULF D» No xhe political A^nt, B AHjttA Iim # ^ A.135(a). isiedat Hyde rata &lt;3 *d W 2iaid.August., 1945. %Kr*jr*Ft* / i-ve ference. your letter i\o # 3247-14/4 dated the 12t h*Aug., 1945 . regarding propo ^-d po st offi ce building at MUharraq. ••uou.• »ihen the •superintendent of i^o st offices visited the piemi^s the shops \\ere lying vacant and the secretary of the Muharraq ^inicipality knew about thewy being vacant* x am surpiri^d to learn now the the shops uere g&gt;t vacated at our-instance # rhe flooring of the shops was incomplete and tnere was no communicating door in tet^veen tlie two shops. *vs the vadth of the shops was only about ^0 to 12 feet it was suggested to open an intercommunicating door between the shops, xher.e was ro provision for v^iter and lavatory and it was suggested to provide both these things in the premises as it was not possible for the sub postmaster to leave the office during the working hours, xhe oiiib postmaster was asked -'o see if these things and the counter and sheifs could be provided, it was intimated that n.is highness tne Kuler was not agreeable to do any repairs and wanted the posts and -.eiegraphs Department to occupy the building in the present condition as pointec out at the very outset* xhe building could no t be utilized for the pu ]po ^ of po st office without additions and alter at ions whi ch the nEpartment was asked to .carry out and which tins department is not in a position to qpend such a lar^ amount at the very outset for opening a pott office which will be for the benefit of the public.if any other building vhich is is a habitable condition and where vje can start the work by putting up counters which x hope the landlord fitould do, we will have no objection to the opening of another office at iviOharraqjbut as thin s stand we camx&gt;t .afford to spend such a large amount over a building not belonging to us. Oon ssq.uently the question of o pening a po dt office at Luharr gq has been kept in abeyance.14/4, Political Agency, Bahrain, The 004 .U Amnia*. 1945. 28th Ai 2 gust 9 The Political Agent, Bahrain presents his compliments tos tha t the tw o s hops a?-e not r eqtiij oct nay now bi cvAisidaed as iinal Demi-official letter No*3264-14/4 dated the 13th August, 1945* ( Letter No*A.136 (a) dated the) 22nd August, 1945 from the ) Post Office at Muharraq* Superintendent of Post Office^ Lower Sind and Persian ^ The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document. the remark that under the circumstances my statement document. D escription of enclosure . Name and date. Sub.iect. Division, Hyderabad* CA r Datj. f e ^°.29 dated the i3-i-4o # TO, The Super!n + crii(.ii^ P.Gs, Hyderubud Sind. SuDject :0jt&gt;enin^ ol a post oliice at Moh^raqUb. The Political Agent Bahrain, in the course a recent interview ,laf^ emphasis over the question oi opening oi pe^t oliice at ilohara^ue. The Director P st the time ol his last visit to Bahriin also recorded note to this efiect ,in the oider boojt. ^ccordindy , I looked into the question. I have selected one flat.Its fto. is '19. It is near the Municipal office and Police station.Mr.Ibrahim bin oalam'Tsthe landlord.At present it is rented up to Mr.Iorahim i&gt;in ii-jee.It is lying vacant f presently .The rent of the flat *ith the aftach godown i s 35 0/1. per an nun. The go-down will no t Oe required lor the post ofiice. The latter will oe locate in the flat itsell.The rent in any case will not \2G/» per mensem .The Political Agent is being lor its requisition and lixation oi rent. ox exceed pproi che It is requested that the establisiiment consisting of i oua postmaster and 1 postman (lor ^ effecting the deliveryof articles ,in the town)may kindly be arranged to be sanctioned on rates analogous as at Manamah(3ahrain).It will be rather difficult,I m^y observe, to spare the necessary st^ff from Bahrain P.G., for the reason that in view oi the switch over from »^ar t? Peace, the postal traffic is steadily on the increase. Pixed contingent charges ^.3/- and allowance to sweeper at therate ox ^.10/- per mensem,may also please be sanctioned. The under-noted articles of furniture will be re^iiired;for the proposed post office 1 sorting case- 1 almiralul xorms ract-two tables-two chairs -one stool safe and 1 wooden counter Q'x3\ The last equipment will oe rendered necessary as the landlord concerad is rafher disinclinedto 3 ix tf ct ^ny additions or aerations to the building. It is requested that an ;arly -ction may kindly be taken in the matter. Inspector Post offices, Persian uuli - section. / Copy submitted to p^liticalj^nt,i)ahmin, jr f* IX i ec^rp^S^^TsiTn aul^t.r n*&lt;!T r ihe cal ^gent bah r ain K T o 135(a) Hyderabad Sind Det^d. the 3#2#46* ^abject: - Op«iiitg a post office at Mohaera^ue* Sir Date Kindly refar the Inspector of Past Offiaea, parsi«i Gulf letter 2^ dated the I3*1.4to addressed to me end copy supplied to you and intimate if the flat referred to by the Inspector o^ Posts would be available on a rant &amp; 20/- p«r Meager and if yes frnr.! what date ? On receipt of your renly I will adresa the Director of Posts ^Tid Telegr^jhs Karacni for sanotiooiithe required e st M b li shu an t • Sup « r intarfl eat • I have etc.,No.632-14/4 Political Agency, Bahrain The 24th February, 1946. To The Superintendent of Post-offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division Hyderabad, Sind. Sir Subject: Opening a Post-office at MolaarraQ . With reference to your letter No. A-135 (a) dated the 2nd February, 1946, the flat mentioned will be available at Es.20/- per mensem with effect from the 25th November, 1946. If you wish to take it over earlier, it may perhaps be possible to arrange this. y I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant for Political Agent, Bahrain CNo. 856-14/4 Political Agency, Bahrain The 14th March, 1946. To The Superintendent of Post-offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, dated the 25th February, 1946, I have the honour to inform you that the landlord agrees to provide the wooden counter required and to accept the proposed monthly rent of Rs.25/-. In this con nection please see my letter No.633- the 24th February, 1946. Sind Sir, With reference to your letti No.A-135 (a) I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant for Politica &gt;nt, Bahrain.Telegram From To No. Dated En Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Superintendent, Post Offices, Hyderabad. 254 24th April, 1946. &lt;?.n * Your telegram A/f35 (A). Work will be completed by May 1st. =POLITICAL= AMO.Telegram En Clair. From To No. Dated Political /gent, Bahrain. Superintendent Post Offices, Hyderabad. 293 9th May, 1946. on&lt;\ Your A l^f (A). Work was completed on 4th May 1946. =P0LITICAL=T' (&amp; No. 1535-14/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 16th May, 1946. To The Adviser to the Govemiaent of Bahrain, The Superintendent of Post-offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Karachi, has informed me that sanction has been accorded, with effect from 1st June, 1946, to the esta blishment on an experimental basis of a town sub Post-office at Moharraq. 2. This office will remain open from 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. and from 3 p.m. to 5 p.m. on week days and from 9 a.m. to 10 a.m. on Sundays and holidays, and will conduct every sort of postal work. All mails to and from Moharraq will pass through the Bahrain sub Post-office, which will work as a sorting office. 3. The actual date on which this office will start working, will be notified later on, by the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain. Copy forwarded to the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain, for information. Bahrain. Memorandum for Political Agent, Bahrain. C.It is notified for the general information of the public that the new Post Office at Moharra^ (near Municipal Office Bin MattaV Building) will be opened on 1st June, 1946 and all Postal work will be performed. The Working hours are as under: Summer | ( 8 to 12 I 15 to 16 Friday closed Winter l 9 to 13 15 to 16 Friday closed -CO.Telegram From To No. Dated En Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Superintendent Posts Hyderabad, Sind. 377 6th July 1946. Your A/!*?. Moharrak is n separate municipality outside municipal limits of Bahrain. =POLITICAL=</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000098_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1417</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000098</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1417</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 14/4 Post Office at Moharraq'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-21T10:52:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (95 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are notes at the end of the file, on folios 89-96. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give brief description of the correspondence with a reference number.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 97; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-88; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and telegrams regarding the need for facilities to convey mail at Moharraq (Muharraq, Bahrain) and the subsequent arrangements for the opening of a Post Office, staffed with a postman sent from Manama via boat twice a week to make deliveries, clean the letterbox and sell stamps. A sketch of the building rented to host the Post Office at Muharraq is on folio 77.The file also discusses the proposal to open a branch telegraph Office of the Wireless in the Bazaar at Manama, which is refused by the Imperial and International Communications Limited.The correspondents are: the Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, at Karachi; Imperial and International Communications Limited, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; the Sub-Postmaster at Bahrain; and the Political Agent at Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and the Persian Gulf, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Moharraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Postal services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000098#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>