<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000db_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:43:04.983Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">16th November, 1938* 'S' tylS * Dear Gibson, India Office letter of the 9th June 1937 ( P»Z•3675/37) accepted as a charge on Indian revenue half of the cost of a new wireless set for His Majesty*s Legation at Tehran and suggested that, if possible, the existing wireless set should be sold, in which case the proceeds would have been divided equally between His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India. V/e have now heard from the Legation that all their efforts to sell this set which is twelve years old have failed and they propose that it should be handed over to Mr. Hewitt, a member of the clerical staff who has helped to maintain it and who may be able to use some of the components for experimental work. We are not really surprised to learn that the old set J.P. Gibson, Esq 1 flak, pol rSD 17: NOV 1933 | INDIA OFFICE I(£) set which was obtained free of cos 1 S^««U£iajSLJjido-European Telegraph Company many years ago has no sale value, and we are disposed to accept the suggestion from Tehran that it should be scrapped, Mr. Hewitt being given the opportunity of using the components. It appears that Mr* Hewitt recently lent a charging panel which was accidentally burnt out on the new set which he installed for nothing; and these are additional reasons why our people at Tehran would like him to have the old set. We should be glad to know if, for your part, you are ready to agree to this. Yours ever, X. {. • •Minute Paper. P.Z. 119/38. pgli ti c al Department. In connection with the letter oelow from the Foreign Office please see the submission at P.Z.8944/36 (Flag A) and the Government of India’s letter of the IQth May 1937 at P.Z. 3 673/37 (Flag B). The original quotation for the wireless set in parts was for £306:13:3, but by the time the order was placed with Marconi’s the price had been advanced by £20. To this must be added the charges in respect of transport and insurance, making a total of £363:11:9, Thus India’s liability becomes £181:15:10, instead of'tjL-sum of £153:5:7 which was actually accepted by the Government of India, and in order to regularise the position authority is now sought for the payment of the increased amount. The Foreign Office ask for payment forthwith, but after consultation with the Accountant-General’s Department it is proposed to ask that adjustment should be made in the normal manner through the Accounts for diplomatic and consular expenditure in Iran. Al draft letter to the foreign Office is submitted accordingly. financial Secretary. for the favour of any remarks. Further reference to India seems hardly necessary.Draft Paper. P. 2 . u ^ \(i \U- j political Department. DPA^T TT.S. of S. T.O. Copy to India - /with, copy of letter yrom F.0. ^CLOSURE IN wrr^Ly [ujyc { -4 2 7 JAIVJ 1938 J VI E-ICRET;.POLI. CAL AliO SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE THE ADVISERS cohour 20 JAN 1938 LI5TT3R • Sir, In reply to your letter ITo.X 9495 / 1C05/5C1 of the 5th January, regarding the provision of a new wireless set for H.M.Legation at Tehran, I ajn directed by the Secretary of State for India to state for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that he is prepared to accept as a charge against Indian Revenues the sum of £181:15:10 •t, representing one-half of the total expenditure incurred. 2. I am, however, to suggest with reference to para.2 of your letter thnt the charge should he adjusted in the normal way through the Accounts for Diplomatic and Consular Expenditure in Iran. J. p i/ k. 't i fciiU / n m\\- approved joint political * SPE0IAL M'j&amp;'f “ ,TTEE - 6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 lopK In any further communication on this subject, please quote No JWS 4:95/1006/501 Iress— ' r iwt to anu person by vawe but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Foreign Office, o. 1. 5th January, 1955. Sir, LETTF,. 7 JAN 1938 &gt;AL AMD ..ID1A OfFK)£ ^ V/ith reference to your letter No. 1 J . 5.^o675/57 of the 9th June last, regarding the provision of a new wireless set for Kis Majesty ! s Legation at Tehran, I am directed Mr. Neville Chamberlain to request you to inform the Secretary of State for India that Marconi’s tireless Telegrapl Company Limited intimated to this department on the 28th May that owing to the increase in the prices of materials which had taken place since their quotation for the wireless equipment was given in September, 1936, the original estimate of £250 for a Marconi Receiver, Type R.G. 25, complete with working valves and headphones, £55 for a Marconi short wave adaptor, type 627, and £1.13.3 for a spare set of valves, making a total of £306.13.3, was subject to an additional charge of £20. The Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury having agreed that the share of the cost payaole from Imperial Funds should be increased by £10, the order for the wireless equipment was placed in July last, ana the set was despatched to Tehran on the 17th November. 2. I am to enclose the duplicate copy of t ie Company’s invoice for £326.13.3 for the cost oi tne equipment, toguner with the duplicate copy of an invoice for £56.18.6 in respect of transport and insurance, and to request that, if there is no objection, instructions may be issued to His Majesty’s Paymaster-General to transfer to the Vote for Diplomatic and Consular Services the sum of £.l81.15.10, represenoing naif of/ The Under Secretary of State, India Office. m®, m. DE?T. 3 &lt;JAN &lt; INDIA OFFICEof the total expenditure incurred. 3. With regard to the second paragraph of your letter under reference, I am to state that His Majesty^ Minister at Tehran has been instructed to endeavour, when the new set is in working order, to dispose of the old set at the best price obtainable, but it is feared that there will be little, if any, demand for an eleven years’ old wireless set of this kind. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,/A / MARCONI’S WIRELESS TELEGRAPH CO., LTD. Telephone Numbers: Head Office: TEMple bar 4321. (Private Branch Exchange) WcX'“ CHELMSFORD 3141. MARCONI OFFICES, electra house, VICTORIA EMBANKMENT, LONDON, W.C.2. Date 21st December, 1937- Finance Officer, H.M. Foreign Office, S.W.l. Telegraphic Addresses : Inland Telegrams : “EXPANSE ESTRAND LONDON” Cablegrams: “EXPANSE LONDON” Works: “ EXPANSE CHELMSFORD ” Codes Used : Marconi International ABC (4th and 5th Editions) Western Union Bentley’s Works : CHELMSFORD, ESSEX. 3066 . REF. Cl. 683 .Cr. To Freight and Shipping Charges. £34.17. 0 Insurance. 2. 1. 6 £ 36 . 18 . 6 On good* despatched to Teheran per Simplon Orient Express on 15 th November, 1937• Order P. 2478 /I 03 / 150 . Varies:- THE BRITISH LEGATION TEHERAN VIA PARIS. Nos.24777/8v&gt; A ^ /iu S No.i\270-^/37. « . s j * ? V&gt; / i From To The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, political Department, India Office, London. Dated Simla, the May 1937. Subject:- Supply of a new wireless receiving set to the Tehran Legation. 4 , Sir, I , J y if X ^ With reference to your letter No.P.Z. 8944/36, dated the 14th January 1937, I am directed to say that the Government of India agree to accept as a charge on Indian He venues a moiety of the sum of £306-13-3 to be expended on the purchase of a new wireless receiving set for the Tehran Legation. 2 . I am to suggest that the existing wireless set be sold if possible and the sale proceeds divided between His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India in equal proportions. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ! - REfiO. POL 85 Pt. /JUN1937 IMO: . ? fc-f » )FHB/MA 5634 f %iyjt D E G Y P H ER OP TELEGR A'lf* 2806. From Government of India, External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India# Dated Simla* 3rd J u ne, 1937. Received 3rd June, 1937, 3-16 p»nio X QfV'f 1339. Your telegram No.1661, June 2nd. Tehran Wireless set. Reply accepting proposal was sent by mail of May 20th.47‘-'5 5000 5.36 Minute Paper, 2-* political Department. / j 6 700 1936 The letter from the Foreign Office dated 15th December deals with a proposal that the present wireless receiving set at the Tehran Legation should be replaced by a new set at a cost of about £300, which appears to be regarded by the experts as a reasonable charge in the circumstances. It is open to no doubt that a new set is required as the existing set was apparently taken over from the I.E.T.D. and has been in commission for a very long period. The question is whether, if the Treasury accept half the expenditure^the other half should be accepted as a charge upon Indian Revenues. It appears to be clear that this kind of expenditure is not capital expenditure, and the arrangement of course is that all recurring diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia is divided. Moreover there are actual precedent for the division of expenditure on new wireless sets, e.g. at Meshed (see P.^2371/28) and Bushire (see P.Z.4822/32). Draft letter to the Government of India consulting them is submitted. Secretary, Financial Department, Do you concur ?ZI- P. Z.8944/36. Draft Paper. political Department. DPAFT The Secretary to the Government of India, F. &amp; P. Department. L / V approved joint political. SPECIAL FINANCE COMMITTEE LETTER. 14 JAN 1957 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to forward for the information of the Government of India a copy of a the letter from^Foreign Office regarding a proposal to supply the Tehran Legation with a new wireless receiving set at a total cost of £306:13:3. I am to enquire whether in the event of the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury accepting as a charge upon Imperial Revenues half the expenditure incurred tfU* /fevh ttu&gt; the Government of India w-PPl bo—prepared t-o—accept trhre other ha 1T/L*~ The Government of India will recollect that similar charges have been divided between Imperial and Indian Revenues, for instance in the case of the wireless set for the Consulate-General at Meshed, for v/hich approval was given in India Office letter of the 7th June 1928, No.P.2371/28, and in the case of the Bushire set Pri regard to which refcrerrcc io invitod-t-o the Government of India’s express letter of the 28th July 1932, No.F. 232-N/32 / u/caox/, (SG.) J. C. W/ “In any further communication on this subject, please quote P 4308/206/150 ^ No. and address— not to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, Loudon, S.W.l. ' 7 /. . o n Foreign Office. S.W.l, 15th December, 1936, O vy 14.1 j r r 1S36 Sir, I am directed by Mr, Secretary p]den to request you to lay before the Secretary of State for India the accompanying copy of a letter, with its enclosures, which has been addressed to the Treasury, regarding the reproduction and distribution of 'British News' in Iran. 2. I am to enquire whether the Marquess of Zetland is agreeable to the proposal that a moiety of the expenditure referred to in paragraph 6 of the letter should be chargeable to Indian Revenues. I am, Sir, &gt; Your obedient Servant, % The Under-Secretary of State, India Office, t-rmzz R 4SjQa/20^1£La i ; i hOI^ S O w 4” H- i 9 o ..^ X -.itediate. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.V.l. 15th December, 1936, J ir, t ith reference to your letter K* 29476 of the 29th July last, and previoue correenondence regarding the reproduction and distribution of 'British News’* in Iran, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Kden to request you to lay before the Lords Commissioners of His itejesty’s Treasury the accompanying copies of despatches dated the 9th July and -he 1st October from His [ajesty’s Qhargtf d’Affaires at Tehran on this subject. 2 . It v-ill be seen that there now appears to be little likelihood of a revival of the attempt to impose further restrictions on the distribution of 'British News’*. A list of the existing recipients of the ’'News’*, with the subscriptions paid, and also a statement of r. George's expenditure, accompanies the despatch of the 9th July, in paragraph 8 of which it is stated that Mr. Butler does not regard the remuneration as excessive, though he thinks it is adequate. 3. Unfortunately, an expert examination of the wireless set which is at present used for receiving the British Official Vireless messages has revealed that it is badly worn and is nearing the end of its life. Mr. Eden strongly supports the view that Hie Majesty's Legation at/ The secretary to the Treasuryat (Tehran should possess an efficient ratio-telegraphic receiving set. He is advised that the instrument recommended in the despatch of the 9th July is well suited for the reception of signals on wave lengths from 200 to 22,o &gt;0 metres. The long wave transmission from Rugby Vireless Teegraph station would therefore be within its range. ! uch a set, unless equipped with a snort wave adaptor, would not, however, be suitable for picking up signals on GIA 16.276 metres, GIM 26.13 metres and QIC 34*72 metres, the short waves which are also used in connexion with the transmissions of the B ritlahOfficial vireless Bulletins. A further consideration which must be borne in mind is that there is a marked tendency for foreign stations to employ low wave lengths from, say, 16 to 20 metres. In view of the possibility timt it may at some future date be considered &lt; esirable that Tehran should be able to intercept short wave signals whether from British or foreign stations, it is advisable that any new instrument supplied to that post should be a receiver of greater wave range than that suggested in paragraph 6 of the despatch. It is accordingly proposed to purchase a iarconi long wave receiver type R.Gr. 25 with working valves and headphones (£ 260 ), and one Marconi short wave adaptor type 627fe 55 ), to ether vith a spare set of valves (£1. 15. 3), at a total cost of £306. 15. 3 net. it is learntc that the Post Office have tested this receiver, and are satisfied with it s performance. The equipment recommended would permit of reception/(ii) reception on all wave lengths fro??i 16 me tree to 22,000 metres, and is the cheapest obtainable to atet the requirements adequately* 4. Befofc ai^proaching Their Lordships on this matter, it was thought advisable to obtain an assurance tnat permission to import and install a new set would be granted, ano a telegram has now been received from His Majesty’s Minister stating that the Iranian Government have no objection, subject to what Mr* Seymour regards as a formal proviso that their consent is dependent upon any modification of their views on general questions relating to the possession of such sets. 5* Further, it has become nece* sary to replace the very old and badly worn typewriter used for copying the 'British News'* In this connexion, I am to invite reference to paragraph 13 of the despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran which was enclosed in Foreign Office letter of the 4th September, 1933, and your letter K* 29476 of the 30th December, 1933* The temporary arrangement by which i 4 r. George was able to use a reserve typewriter on the charge of His Majesty’s Legation has proved at times to be inconvenient, and Mr. George has consequently had to revert to using the machine supplied to him by Reuters. 6 . in these circumstances, I am to request that Their Lordships may be raoved to sanction ( 1 ) the continuance of the present arrangements for the reproduction and distribution of the 'British News”,(ii) the purchase of the wireless equipwent proposed in the third paragraph of this letter, and (iii) the supply of a new typewriter to His Majesty’s Legation on the understanding that one-half of the total expenditure involved will be recoverable from Indian evenues* It is proposed that His Majesty’s Government’s share of the oost of ohe wireless equipment should be met from Subhead K (News ] epartment 1 xpeneee) of the Vote for I iplo atie and Consular \ ervices* !? * Copies of tais letter and its enclosures are being sent to the India Office, whose concurrence in the course proposed will be awaited before any action is taicen. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,( 166 / 77 / 36 ) 9th July, 1936. Sir, 2 hate the honour to acknowladge the receipt of your despatch ho.270 (? 1406/206/150) of June the 24th last,and to Inform you that no further attempts hare oeen made by the Ministry of Foreign Affaire to Induce the iagatlon to cease distributing the British hews to outside subscribers. On the contrary they hare shewn some desire to receive extracts from the hews giving the speeches of British Cabinet Ministers on important International Issues and a recent incident'described below,has even led to a request that the text of such speeches should regularly be furnished by the legation in future to the tfara agency. 2 . as stated in the fourth paragraph of toy letter to Mr. hash of May 16th last, the practice of the -legation since lfc34 has been t not to send the news regularly to the Bars agency,but to oomcmriloate cocaslonal extracts unofficially to the Ministry of Foreign affairs. fhe Ministry has then usually caused these extracts to be trans lated and reproduced in the Persian press. * few wee.cs ago the Undersecretary for Foreign Affairs,in replying to a letter from me sending an account of a speech which you,Sir, had recently delivered,even expressed his warm thanks for my letter and requested that 1 should always send him such reports in future. a hen about a fortnight ago there incident mentioned in paragraph 1 above. ; publish'd The Bight Honourable , ^nthony Aden M.U # f e tc . , e to •, e to •, ^he Foreign u fflee.^pttbii&amp;nad a report of a speech aellTereo by tna Ural J-ora of the A flmiralty to the &amp;oyaI ^iaplre Society aaa Quoted Sir Samuel hoar# as saying that 'war is inevitable? fortunately the British kess also gave an account of this speech which showed that Sir Samuel had actually said that it was criminal folly to assume that war was inevitable. As the -Pare report had been reproduoea with sensational headlines in all the papers ,1 at once wrote to the ministry of foreign Affairs giving the true version of the speech and as/vi-ig that a correction should be made as soon as possible. X also statea that 1 should be happy to allow the Director of the ifcrs ^&gt;^0^0; in future to oheojc any reports which he might receive from ■London with the British hews. ^oreover.as aii this hapoentd on a Friday,ana ms practically no papers are published here on Saturdays,! also ffelt it as well to issue the necessary correction without delay to ail my colleagues. ihe rars -agency duly inserted a correction in their oulletin two ohye later,though they disregarded tne wording which 1 had given them and instead quoted ??ir Samuel as saying M 11 n*y a pas lieu de consid^rer Is guerre comae inlvltable”, iiore import ant was the receipt of a very conciliatory letter from Monsieur hoheily of which 1 have the honour to enclose a oooy herein. l would remaric in parenthesis that the supposed earlier correction of Sir aamuel*s speech was in fact no such thing ,but a fur ther .report of the speech which omitted entirely the passage in gweetiofi. in aocoroance with Monsieur Schelly 1 s suggest!on,1 sent the iters *geuey on iluly 2nd a sumaary of your speech before the Assembly of the league of ballons on the previous day,which they duly puolishea in ftxkflnqp tut follo^ihg morrlng. 4 . 1 venture to thinx that the above incident points to two conclusions. ihe first is that there now seems to me / butbut little liizelihooct of the Ministry reytving their campaign against the hritiah iewB,though admittedly readiness on the part of the ^ars *zQuoy to publish extracts therefrom does not preclude their objecting to the aireot dissemination of the news by the -negation to outs ioe aabsorlbers* ihe second Is that it is obviously of the greatest wlue to the hegetion to possess a wireless receiving set .and more than ever now that the official news agency of the country is willing to ma/ce use of the British hews. 5. ihere is,however, a flaw In what would otherwise seem to be a not unsatisfactory situation. iovi department will be aware that in my despatch ho. 15 ^ of ^aroh hbth last 1 requested that certain spare values might be supplied for the legation receiving set,as the stocx here has been exhausted, -these valves were duly procured,but the Gonamuaioations depart ment in their letter 335/835/450) of A pril 16 th state that they ware of efc obsolete v ; -pe ana that it was doubtful if any more oould be procured. In these circumstances,! thought It well to have the set examined by m expert in order to find out what the position would be when the present valves were worn out. ihis service Ur* driffiths^arconi* s representative here.has now jcinaly performed and 1 have tne honour to enclose a copy of a letter from him furnishing hie report on the set. Ur. Griffiths has since called at the legation and has confirmed that not only will the set become completely useless when the few remaining valves are burnt out,unless by any chance mere can be obtained,but also that other components are badly worn and that the set In general is nearing the end of its life. ihe set is in fact eleve* years ola.naving been in use for six years with the Indo-European leiagraph department and for five years in His Majesty's negation. Unless new valves can be obtained,**?. Griffiths does not /considerconsider that the set can last for more than another two years and he things that it Is by no means unlikely that it will give ottt earlier and possibly in only a few wee&lt;cs time. he accordingly reoo&amp;jtenas the purchase of a new set and he nas suggested a Maroon! &amp;. 3 . 25 . which he estimates will cost with all the necessary components,be tween three and four hundred pounds. in order to save unnecessary correspondence v he has been ae^ed to request his firm to suomit a detailed quotation direct to your department. 6. 1 fully realise that the expenditure involved in this proposal cannot be lightly under taxen .and 1 therefore feel considerable diffidence in requesting sanction for it. Nevertheless ^ cannot but thinX that the possession of a good receiving set by his Majesty's Segation,l^not an absolute necessity,is a t any rate a first class asset. *»• are faced here not only with unreliable posts,which now taxe anything up to a fortnight to arrive .so that news in the English papers when they reach here is quite out of date .but with a atate* controlled monopoly news agency which,as tne above-mentioned incident will show.is grossly unreliable and whioh.lf left to itself, taxes neiucl^ all its new^ from uavas. borne of its news it taxes from neuters but not much,ana its other sources in London,the nature of which it has been impossible to ascer tain, supply it primarily with sensational gossip from papers such as Reynold's which it duly reproduces in all seriousness. Now ,however,we have the assurance of the Ministry of foreign Affairs,that the agency will be gled to receive items of serious news from the British he we, and it would seem the greatest pity that this desirable arrangement should now be allowed to lapse through any breakdown of the negation receiving set. 7 . but If the prime factor in the situation would nowm seem to b© the readinee* of the *utb +renoy to rtTMrocmce ocoeeionai extracts from the British fcews, it should not b© forgotten thet there are other recipients of the Keee who read it a&amp;ily ana An exte t ao . in the first place there are the members of BLia ^a^eety’s -negation and certain of His Majesty* s ^onsuiB in the prorinoea; they are thus well- informed tnemseives t and are often ir a position to mu&amp;e use of infer station in the I*ews to correct misconeeptione in oonversa tion with foreigners. Secondly there are various British interests of varying importance who suosoribe, ranging from the ^nglo-iran i*n ^il Company ana the Imperial ban* of Iran at the top,to the haw,era and de Haviliana taeohaniOB under oontrect with the Iranian Air force at the bottom. thirdly there are the Japanese ,£oumanian and Egyptian legations; ana lastly there are mixed interests represented by the Tehran ^iub ,and the English iureing Home, where the news is reaa by Europeans of many nationalities, and one purely foreign non diplomatic subscriber, the Aether lands Harbour Worse Company. I would add that the circle of subscribers ie tending to wiaen; the monthly sub scription was reduced early this year with satisfactory resulte and i am not without hope that it may or ore possible at some future date, with out depriving l«r. Ceorge of hie existing remuneru tion, to a ttraot still more subscribers by a further reduction. imoortance of the exiating sub scribers,as 1 have said,naturally varies,but in a place where wireless telephony receiving sets is still unreliable and is on the whole uneatisfactory t l regard it as of no . mall importance that important interests British ana f or sign, should be able to count on the absolutely reliable daily service of the British news. laxlng all the circumstances into account and not least the particular importance in the present /troubled3,) - 6 - troublod Btate of Jeiui world politios of the aoourate dlssemliia* tlou of the British ctwnapolnt*! have no healtatlon In be lie ring that it is most desirable that uhe legation shouia renmln provlaea with a reliable wireless receiving set. 6. In aoo or dance with the in struct lo us in your despatch under reply, 1 have the honour to enclose a full list of the existing recipients of the news (other than his majesty's legation and Consulates*, with the subscription paid by each, and also a statement of ^r. George's expenditure* I under stand from Mr* George that the worx of eai ting .reproducing end despatching the hews taies him approximately two hours a day; 1 therefore do not regard his remuneration as in any way excessive .though 1 thin&gt;c it is adequate. ihe livelihood of the distribution of the hews being confineu to die Majesty's legation and Consulates has now greatly receded; but 1 would state that in that event 1 would still regard Mr* Ceorge’s services as essential. *ith a staff of only two typists in Mis Majesty's ^gatlon.lt would be quite impossible to spare the services of one of them for so long a period each oay. 1 consider that Mr. Ceorge should under no circumstances receive less than £&amp;&lt;-&gt; per annum for his labours* 9 . Ihere remains a farther point,if a new set is to be supplied, namely the question of obtaining from the Iranian Government permission for its importation and installation, in the note from the ministry of foreign Affairs,of which a copy was encloses in ilr B # h. hoars's despatch h 0.276 of august 11 th 1*34. it was stated that foreign missions might only possess wireless receiving sets with the permission of the Iranian Government and on condition of reciprocity. In point of fkot Sir h.h, hoars never sought this permission in set terms but iu his note,of whioh a oopy was forwarded to your department in his despatch Ko. 4 fe 9 of November 14th lfr&amp; 4 , /hehe explained the position in London and then went on to say that he trusted that he was correct in assuming that the -Persian Government were prepared to act In a reciorocal manner as regards the receiving apparatus of his Majesty* e -negation. i*o reply was received to that note but,when the 4uestion was raised again by the Ministry of foreign Affnirs early this year, Monsieur Motamedy informed ^r. iirott^s reported in the sixth paragraph of ay despatch ho .144 of March 2let last,that it was an understood thing that his Majesty's -legation could possess a receiving set since the Iranian legation would be permitted to instal one in honaon. 10. inhere are obviously considerably more possibilities of snags in obtaining permission to import a new set than in securing permission to operate a set already installed; and, though 1 do not believe that the Iranian Government would with hold this permission for u new set, they might sieoe the oppor tunity to Undeavour to extract a cromise from us to restrict the distribution of the hews. Should this contingercy arise,it might prove necessary to agree to discontinue sending the hews say to the Tehran Club,ana the Netherlands harbour *orxs Company. 1 do not Uiinx that the ministry of foreign affairs would now press us to stop sending it to British Subjeots,suoh *h® Managers of the Anglo-lranian Oil Company and Imperial Manx of lran t and I believe that we could successfully press for the right to send it to foreign diplomatic missions. -Thus,with the £ars Agency, the most important recipients would, 1 thinx, always remain. haver the less it is obviously out of the question to run any risxs and,if sanction oan be obtained for a new set, I would propose that, be fore the order is actually placed, 1 should explain the position to Monsieur Boheily and asm for an assurance that permission would be granted to ua to laoort and instal a new set. Cur subsequent line of action would then /havehu ve tu depend on Mb reply* 1 snotua be gr&amp;fceftoi,if 1 aignt be informed *a soon mb possible whether sanation o*n be wbtMinea for m new reoeiTing set and,if so .whether you approve the course suggested in the preceding paragraph. I nave the honour °ir, lour most huabi* &lt; Signedi her lie butler. to be with the h&amp;g&amp;eet respect, obedient, Servant,r\ Translation of a Letter from the Director-General of the UiniBtry of Foreign Affaire (Pars Agency) to Hie Majesty^ Charge d f Affaires* 7th Tir f 1315 (£ 8 th June, 1936)* Wo* 69. -rv : IMIuigDI ATS m My dear Friend, Your letter &amp;f 5th Tir (£ 6 th June, 1936) regarding Sir Samuel Hoare^ speech which was published by the 'Pars” Agency was duly received. According to enquiries made, a mistake was made in getting the telegram containing the ppeooh in question and have that the w Pars' Agency/oorreoted this news in their Bulletin Ho. 160 of £5th June in the evening, nevertheless with a view to having the mistake corrected in a more authoritative manner the correction will appear again in to-day’s Bulletin in the afternoon. The ’’pars ’ 1 gsnoy have, in the meantime, been warned that (in future) they should take their utmost care in such matters and that with a view to enabling the 'Pare” Agency to publish with care the important and official speeches of British statemsn * shall be grateful if you would be so good as to cause a copy of the English text of such speeches reaching the Legation to be sent to the 'Pars” Agenoy. But such information should reach the 11 Pare” Agency very soon so that they (the ’’Pars” Agenoy) may be able to use them in time. Yours sincerely, (Signed) A. Soheily*Kef. British Legation, Amplifier nG.ii (PS 444/tl), ©to# July 6 th f 1936* o/o Pension iSobatan, Khiaban Shah, Ho. 5, Teheran. My dear Lesley, Your letter 166/67/36 of the 1st inst. to hand. I called at the Legation this afternoon and had a look at the reoelver there. Some of the components of this receiver are in a bad condition and the valves it employe are obsolete^ The future life of this receiver is the life of the few valves you have in stock. When these burn out you will be unable to replace them and then yo*^ set is unworkable. Your existing stock of valves is far too small to hazard any guess at the probable life of them and an accident will leave you in a very difficult position. They may last a couple of years and they may last a couple of weeks. It is useless to consider reconditioning this set as firstly the cost would be prohibitive and secondly it would have to be done in lUngland. The only course open to you is to buy a new receiver and X suggest a Marconi R Gr £5. Uhis receiver will also give your operator the possibility of taking nows from India which is almost impossible with the present set, I am enclosing for your information a copy of our official leaflet Ho. 1217/E. (Signed) Sincerely yours, G. 2 J.A. Griffiths.1» List of Heolpiente of the Britieh Wewe p other than members of Hie Majesty^ Legation and Consulates* (a) Without charge* German Legation* Tehran nursing Association nursing ^me* (b) subscribing Recipients* Subscription Imperial Bank of Iran. (two copies) per month Rials* 100 Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, (two copies) 100 Japanese Legation. 60 Roumanian Legation, 60 Egyptian Legation* 60 Tehran Club* 60 Motherlands Harbours Works Co* 60 Mr. Taylor (de Havilland Co .) so Total 660 2 * Statement of Mr* C.M. George's eaqjenses per month* 1* Wages of ferash* Rials per month 60 2* Clothing of ferash* (Rials 360 per annum) 30 Total 90 Ur* George thus receives Rials 460 per month at present, or f*4^- IS - 0*I have the honour to Inform you that shortly after I wrote my uesoatch -To. 196 of the loth ' &gt;ril t regarding the distribution of the British ireless lewe» arm / &lt;merits were made for the supply to hie Majesty’s Legation of the bulletino hf tne Age era* toneieur Kntezam f then direc or of the Agence ar 3 f kindly agreed to allow iiie 'ajeety’G begaticwi to receive the bulletins without charge, for a time at least* The bulletins have since been regularly received, and though much of what they contain subsequently appear in the 'journal d© ?£h 6 mn 4 , nevertheless I am satisfied that it is useful and desirable that they should ue received in future* '• Some weeks a ;o I wrs some; text our prised to receive a bill for the subscription to the bulletins from the date on which ' hey were first supplied to the deyr.lion. I an happy, however, to say that ao soon as the riental iecretary reminded the present director of the Vgenc© nrs, 'onaieur iciiaioany, of Monsieur intesan’a proiiiso tiiat no charge would be made for the bulletins, at least for a tine, Monsieur Schaibony not only readily agreed to au_&gt; ly the bulletins permanently for nothing, ut also actually said that he would be very glad to receive every day a copy of the British i©we in return* fhe I3riilsii Jews is accordingly now bein sent to him every Homing* /3. The Right Honourable An thony den, ' T * d *, M. p *, etc*, etc*, etc*, The ’ore ign fflce* - • m- ■rnrnmm 0 HMM?ao 3 . This happy denouement, which reflects *jreat, crev it on rr. Trott’e handling of the natter, of co roe involves a complete change from the attitude adapted by the Iranian Government in 1934 (see „ir Reginald hoare’s despatches :fos. 373 and 364 of the 11th and -dind AU£-ust, 1934 respectively). This change of attitude is much to be welcomed, and should add greatly to the value of the reception of the British lews in Tehran, I will watch carefully to oee how far the British -Tev/o is used in preparation of the Agence i are bulle tins, and I will not fail to report further in due course on this subject, Meanwhile I would venture to su* rest that the fact that the British Hew© is now ta^en by the Agenoe pars provides a further argument for the replacement of the Legation wireless set and the maintenance of the present system of reception and distribution, as recommended in my despatches r os. 39 and M 3 of the 6 th ebruary and the 7th —— ■ ■ ■ - July respectively, Bor is it irrelevant to mention in this connection that ao irregular have posts from tlje United Kingdom now became that the original of your despatch Bo, 331 of the 27th August, posted in London on August 27th, did^not^arrive here till the 23rd Teotember, a whole week after a copy of it sent by bag, I greatly hope tnat in all the circumstances it will be possible to secure approval of the proposals set out in my despatches under reference, I have the honour to be with the highest respect tfir. Your most obedient, humble servant. (dignod) Hevile Butler,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000db_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3657</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000db</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3657</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/81 'Tehran Legation: supply of wireless set'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T10:50:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (44 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 46; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the supply of a new wireless receiving set for the British Legation at Tehran, and the Foreign Office's request that Indian Revenues share the expenses.The file is composed of correspondence between the British Legation at Tehran, the Foreign Office, the India Office, and the Office of Works.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Communication equipment</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Office of Works, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000db#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>