<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000349_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T13:32:21.276Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No.631 5548/327 the msimm MMM October I5th # 1924. ( Sir 5 With reference to despatch Mo*605 of 26th SepteMber, I have the honour to infom jon that further inquiries have '00 en mad® cone ami Mullah Haxis ? motemants throu^i a person who i^ acquainted with him, but that bo trace of him can be found in u-airo« X have §to. with the highest respect (Sgd) A •K.Clark Kerr ACTIMG HIGH CO - JSSIOHSB, The Eight Honourable J&amp;M0S Ramsay uaoDonald 1 h*P • stc* etc« etc.Kuwait t0 wh®a it was 3 «nt in t® his iu«r.7 • c &gt; t&amp; v h«th«r Tlafldh might c®m« h« r« • ^ c s m« ham &amp; without doubt, tsg#th«r r - it': Abdul » nab r '«yaini t st^rt«d th® agitation which culc »imt«d during 1 your recent visit here • -&gt;h ^ik bdulla admitted in your prssenc© th -t h« h d lad bis sax; Ma hemed astray.i think th- t is highly probable.but cannot f sel con vincethat ^bdulla was ignorant of what was happenning.In fact I think his visit her# was fer tho sale purpose of ^uch intrigues &amp; he went off with a letter to the ihaik of r atar from 3haik .jlasa.f sking he former to Join in a joint oompalint to Government about Bahrain affairs stated that Bin iaud had £ Iso been appe? led to .This information wa s given e by 3haik ^bdulla bin Thani f s private 3eorotary 3aleh bin Mana' i N® doubt he carried a similar letter tm lor Bin iaud ' Affeer visiting Qatar ha apparently returned to Kuwait &amp; from thero w«nt to Bin 3aud some time in November.I think Bin 3aud must have given 3haik Sasa some assurances of support but was taken aback by the recant strong line t ken here &amp; backed out f but has without doubt b en persuaded by H*'fidh to ' ppoint him to the Kuwait Conference,partly under th® guise that he knov - the vileg of the British,.^ p ! rtly wjth the object • of ondo.-'-Touring to ru / -n the app-^ ranee of a Joint 'r^b complaint about recent a 'fairs 't the Cinference. I suspect he has made t good thin;* fiaascially out of tho intrigues ' s a 1st of m^noy was colloct- ed ho re fro 'i th o K.-^khudas .ior tho purpose &amp; 3haik Abdulla certainly p^id his shore • I imagine the document bw-dcastod byAbdulla's son . was the handiwork of Ha,:idh.Y©u have already seen the copy sent to India &amp; I enclose for your informstion two letters re ently received from H # M f a Consul ' t Damascus. About last June an article appeared • in 'Ai Aichbar* with regard to tha oil concessions in the Gulf in i which the ^nglo-Per ian Oil company was attacked &amp; -ho whole article was vislentlv anti-British o t ccu.a d us of pushing the A.i.O.C i purely v ith Political ends ^ warning Bin 3aud that he would be ■ dvisf t t-o grant a concession to an American Company ^ keep th© oritisn out.A good deal of detail { presumably local Bazaar t^lkl was given about what had happened t Kuwait in the matter &amp; X strongly suspect that Mulls Hafidh w-s again the writer. He is an adventurer ,of .ransrior educ' tion &amp; cunning to the local arabs &amp; piH^-s on t-fie,ii natural tendAncios for intrigue,to enrich himself under the ^uiseCani'lf qntia l randi' M ulla Hfc fid h, In continuation of lay telegram C. When I met ihaik Eamad this kerning h« at once as iced me if I was aware of the arrival of Mull a Hafidh &amp; asked nse what would be tha attitude of Grovem - w&lt;ent towards him. I replied that I did not know what view would be !■ t-tken.Hamad said ha felt convinced that -^or- . n would not agree to his occupying a position which would give him great importance in the eyes ef local arabs,after what \ as universally known as te his p^stwhaik Hamad added that ha thought that if he • ere accept® • it would encourage hid anti-British influence grettly &amp; after 3 recognising hira in such a eapac^ity he weuldi be in a position to el im same sort of protection from Bin 3aad &amp; be difficult to deal i with. Hamad also said that he had every reason to believe that he was sent for by Bin land in connection with &gt;haik Maga f s appeal to t:i6 former for assistance with % that his inclusion in tha depiitation is at-b the object of bringing up Bahrain affairs at th i conf ^r^nce % ho thirds th -iy saay try to influence other delegates to t^k#- up the matter i s if it were one of importance to them all .-in laud ho thinks,intended to interfere himself but wa^ frightened o f by the line taken in the recent agitation hero, A fact that lends colour to the above is that 'haik HaTsad yesterday sent someone to 3hRik ~*v&gt; sa to advise him not to continue t© rofuso to take his «.tllow^-nce 1 to . ■ ri-s Bank, out fco start drawing on it» 3haik i3*'isa replied th tfe he stu.-.! lisd on^ hope of inducing to agree to ttB having at least 3s 50000 r &gt;er monsom &amp; that he preferred to wait &amp; see what happened ^ if it failed he would then consider taking the money from the I^n£. I need hsrdly emphasise that 1 f '3in Saui either directly , « or indirectly,by putting others up to spe* k, t&gt;nc- Id even he «• ul^ ^ ' The ?olitica1A fe ncy Bahrdto, 8X2/23 - // /o nrMcrmr cokf;.:. . — /y;, u • -o.litic.a.l ii£ency , Kuwait, ^Bth, June ia. *3 , 5 /&gt;V The Political i^ent B A H R A I jn ^ulla Haflclh, -M .QRAMDUL . Heference your ifiemorandum No,5^/0 dated ^2nd April 1^25 n ^ulla Hafidh has just 'been to see me, to say that he is thinking of going out to the Pearling Fleet as a tau^ash . and to ask what sort of reception he will be given in Bahrain in the event of his being compelled to out in there, either to take shelter froir. had weather, or to take on stores or water. He says that he has no ■•vish to go there and that he will not do so fron. choice, but that he may be compelled to and wishes to }cnow how he will stand if he %t „ I have told hin that I will answer his question after reference to you . V *v! ' y / ' ^ ajor. Political Agent, Kuwa it.Canfl'iGntlal Bo &amp;/ C. The Apx*r)i.rj i Bahraia,per8iaai Gulf 22 /4/23, y /I lha nOB f bI.#3 tho Political Hesiilorit in ths Persian Gu3f Meaoraiaduia Bu^hire Artleles in 9 A1 Akhbarf • Please refer to /our letter No 213/3 of 1922 to the Foreign Seeretary your I-fo214/3 to tha Political Agent Hawalt. I forward herewith for your infomation^in ease it ehouia not have coae to jour notice # aaother article in 'Al Aichb&amp;r* of doubt the ^ork of ^uila Safid.h,no-j of Kuwait, His attae£ on witb tho r^ferenoe to ileportatlon of righteous rsoriS3 f o*- ing to no oth ;r offence than Imtlon^liuK » mm iioubtleas due to his serene as at the result of hie \ eMJ dooortaxion trom Bahrain® V'hen ho w?«8 engaged in propagarida on behalf of Shaak Ah dull a bin 9 he invariably took pains to its sure hi » r- adera that he r uj an ardent adMiror of British rule and lorelj objected tci me ) raonally.The present artiole s&gt;ie^B hi i; his true :ii ? ht.lt is ^s Anti4 Bnlt• sh as it well radc eoald be ^ calculated to embitter oar relations with the :.lultan of llajd* Hull? Ilafidh has long been recognised as tho eorresponden &amp; agent of S AI Akhbar in the Gulf* Kkmi not attacking the British he iiaaices a living out of blackball Ing tlv« various arab Kulers# While her# ,he frequently told people that he had f :/e-.rs ago,served a ter« of iiaprlsomaent in ^gypt 'or sedition I believe he ^as deported froit Ira? in the early stages of the • tT ar« His scurrilous attacks have now worn sostev.-hat thin ■: re treated ratkiir as humourous reading in B' hrsiii # but I ina^ine nis articles are capable of doinir a go id deal of ham in jd &amp; other places * 8th r 3haaban f .This article like the previous ones,is vithout Copy,with compliiaeats^ta th Political Agent,?!uy.a 11•'t from Arabic* newsrm-nor, oallod A1 AkIVb '-r, o» 578 datied loth January 1038, printed at Cairo• *m ttm fev .,r» ««, ««R »*t ^ Kews fror the 1' ^st« Kuwait, We thought that BTioi'kh Ahj^ad would thinl- of the future of his territory .nd would engage honest and experienced persons, but he roTused to tread the path of justice and reformat1on, and restricted the enloynent of M b authority to the private enjoyments in the harem, and 13ft na 11 ere to de 31ir.y« He ha a read what we rrote and we hear that ho was angry about it, and complained to the Ocnsul supporting hib complaint by such proofs as he could produce# v ut we ask him in all respect, about the thin? s which our artiolo described, whether they are correct or not# V/e cannot understand that a Government having control over all ronouross of revenue should refuse the expenditure of as small a sum as one pie for the defence of the town, and without doubt Bhelkh Ahmad*s conduct confirms one of the meanings of the statement made by Colonel Knox who has held the post of a consul in the Persian Oulf# He we tinder stand from several sources, *The Arab G' r-rnmont??. are corrupted to the bone and chaos reign everywhere# The Arab Sheikhs have not on several occasions shown any compotenco in the administration of their country# The Government of H#K#the King have no political object# in the Gulf, and do not desire to interfere in the internal affairs of the Arab territories, but the horrible rule which that Government see and the surprising chaos which reign throughout the lands show us that those people toll, us w capture our towns, capture our towns* and we say f *No, no, our burden is already heavy 5 let your towns be for yourself#* We have heard something wonderful I We hear that the Sheikh has issued an order to certain youths which enjoins the following*- !• they must stop reading newspapers andana writing ,c the^ mist not criticise ih'.t happons, S» they nust be nilont alvout v?hat takes place in the town ana shou.t I net discus8 local affairs^ etc« which recaj,la to us the de«rV.est a honed sonotb^nr good fron this youth, but our hopt 0 bave bem disappointea5 may rod lead him to what is good to Mr; and his town. Vo have been informed by arrival r r'ror^ Kuwait that the Shelfch was told about a letter sent to the Consulate con- plaining about the condition of thetown and its disturbed Btute f and drawing the attention of the Consul, to the advlsere wmo o»used the trouble and misunderstanding, o^eilch Ahnad becane angry and '.•as displeased, and uttered threatening words* rut natters are in the sare condition end to change has taken ^laoe» •■'he Bheikh forgot that the letter was possibly arranged by 00me of his entourage w'.tl: via: obioct of frlghtenin^ him and widening the field o f 11 .^agreorient * Hut n God will not change a people unless they aro changed by thenselves', and W when God's revenge overt kes a land O'' oppression, vf is revenge will bo severed B A H H A I Nq T'atters in Bahrain are still in a troubled condition in -spit': of all t&gt;n '^forts made for the restoration of ^ood ixrderstandeng between the local nheikha and the « or : -.&gt;.1, and there ire many rumours some of which report • aeport.^tior oa.eiy of the notables who are said to h e- ■ been signatories of the letter of complaint sent to the r-ov rnment # j u .t all of these ere not proved, ba ^anee to make complaints is legitimate among all nations* We hear that, the sheikh of Bahrain has sanctionef an annual donate- or to his free school« Let us hope that other Chiefs will foilos his example, because nothing will i»rrove their condition and safeguard their independence except Vnowledge Basrah, 15th December»Tolagram Ho 108 da ted I4/1/2?. From Travor Last sentence of your lo/C* Perh&amp;oa it would help matters if Y.K. and others could do soma propaganda ori behalf of Bahrain public in Egyptian and Indian napers ae well as Mesopotamia Times•Go py oi letter Ho 6/C. ad dreased to Hesi Jent P•G» on 9/1/22* Original (Office eopy} in file 4/5. He 1 ere nee to the attached documer. t which w^s fo rwarde.^- for my ptruoal uncer voar secretar's o 1987 of 8th Dec. The* signature to this doe amentia document in Persian airuils r to one in Arabic which wi 3 sent to the Editor ia^ra Times,making yunrirga various slanderous ai; egations against the Political Agent) is a faise one.^he documentbis almost an exact transalotion of into Persian of dhatwhich was recently sent in Arabic to the Editor of the Time3 of Mesopotamia &amp; wjjich he forwarded to mo for comments &amp; which was forwarded to you .This le J terwas given to Abdur Rahman Bastaki (Qachawi) who is 1 schoolmaster under the Egyptian rullc Hafia v/ho was responsible for the original,to tranaaltae for him into Persian.The bro ther of Mm la Abdar Hahm^ii ga^a this information to the T !unshi of 'han Bahadur Muhammad Sharif .When the latter heard of it he told them that he had been veiy unwi e to mix himself up in such propaganda. Knlla Abdur Rahman b his brother who gave the information, are sons of Sh&amp;ik Abdul ''ahid (nicknamed Mulla Sindia) gainst whom the Dtpy (Jovr. of Xing eh has recently been complaining regarding his attacks on him in the press. He was recently warned oy mo to refraia^ fromsuch attacks while under British protection in Bahrain*It now transpires-that these three gantlemem have suddenly left Bahrain without even resigning their positions in the school. It may b.j that after having been carried toy me regarding his attacks on the Oovr • of ling eh and discovering that the com- olicity of the son in 3haik Abdulla f s propaganda had been found out the trio took fright and thought it wiser to leave,or it is not imp os lb la that they have left on a farther mission on Shaik ,Vbdalla*s behalf.The latter continues to spend money lavishly on this sort of thing. ^ , Mulla Hafis,the Egyptian who has been ais rignt mna man in spreading &amp; writing reports,recently left hurriedly lor Towait• I sxather that he was tol^ there that he was nou vented, nc then ent to B- sr- e it is not known for wla&amp;t purpose, yesterday evening I -as surprised to receive a letter from Shaiiw ^asa aay- in^r that this individual was s. id to be returning t^anrain the mail from Basra arriving to-lay &amp; asking me to forbid him to land in 3ahrain - 3haik Basa has been in state of nerv j usne 0 s si..ie he heard of the com plaints n. • de to you by nis subjects and his failure during my absence to abstract a document J'rom them favourable to hi isalf .It ia possibls therefore that this 18 a b.- lated attaapt to ,mt a stop to the woric vhlch Us son --baalla undo'bte ilv start-do v :.ar iiiaik 3asa ? s cognisance. ' Since it ould have a bad affect for Mulla Hftfiz,whose rn^deads are universally known hare to ba allowed to roturn ana d-f ss to 1. -.-i hwwwMtoixjta has been accedea to. ue nas no pro ae tzj ^ T? iwiihinfi otherwise than his post in uhe school nor meand -j , x ^lami^sed ^ so under no necessity to come from which ne tea boeu diamx^e. ^ so tUKen by me in as-iOsfeB!; «=-»~ f ' «»♦-Telegram R» Ho Il6/C« To Political Zowait. One Maila Hafls late headmaster of schaol her© laaving for Plow it this mall- This ondividual deported from Iraq in the war is an Egyptian and very anti-British® Has recently been writing libellols articles in the Egyptian press and we were contemplating his deortetion .Shaik; of Komlt I told imows his antecedents and might like w rning of his corning. Political.o . / so, - s of jcjas. British Ros5.^ ^noT.'--!« Bushlre^ Snd January 1922* To Tile Editor of the ?.!0 so not aril a tine;--, B i 3 r a ii s Dear Sir^ Hof erring to the letter dated 16 th -lovewbor frorr the Political Agent, Bahrain, I an writing to you on the subject of the letter sent to you for publication which you kindly oent to l ajor Daly. From the contents and style of the letter it is practical If certain that a certain Egyptian agitator who was then achoolnaoter in Bahrain but who Haa recently left, either wrote or Inspired the letter# In regard to the ailegattons made in hie letter^ I would observe that conpl«int was made to m© about the first, and I made enquiries# It was shown that the man only received a few strokeo according to the metbod of whipping prescribed in Inrii i and was at work (as a cocly) for two or three days b'-fore he was taken ill with pneumonia which unfortunately carried him off« A b regards the second oeee the -ian was stcmcned in the ordinary way through the Sheikh 9 b ^toir* * and the first the Political Agent hoard of the nan being ill was when he arrived at the Agency# Ho wan then sent to Hospital at once* Ordinarily when a summon is sent and a man is sick the fact is noted on the sxmnons, cut on this occasion owing to the stupidity (or willfulness) of the Amir's a fldawis h this procedure was not adopted# If you desire accurate news from Bahrain I think it would be better to appoint eome respectable person as correspondent who could send periodical news letters, 'ajor Daly would no doubt be glad to put you in communication with a suitablesuitable man If ycu sk Mn* Yours fal Uifiii 1 y # , v | N '^-- Liout-Coi Political Hesldsnt in the Persian P.S. i regret that owing to press of work and my absence on tour this letter has been much delayed,. Copy to Bahrain reference his memo No. 107-0 dated 17th' November 1921•i?cu • of 10^1, Brit.1 an ueBide*/O;,* -tiKi •'. ^isulat©— isn.1 Busl xr -3, 2 6th i'iovenber 19ij 1 , To The Political Agent, Bahrain. IiamoranduTii . four memorandum Ko.l09»S. dated 17th November 1921. I am coneidering how best to deal with the letter from the Editor of the Mesopotamia Times, which is a new departure® I expect a brief resume of the cases will be beet, and I will suggest to him the advisability of either sending a representative to Bahrain to study conditions^ or to ask n. some Bahrain! of standing to be M special correspondent** and suggest that if he does not know any one himself he might obtain the name of one from you. // Political Resident,Persian GulfCOHFID' ''T; al . tl^) ¥c m - •, Of Britlsli Re-Jl-xo ; T Oongv.l .-CrOiiiral, / ill»olii ro , 13th ;aroh 19; : ,Z * To The Po1iti cal Agen t, Kuwait® Herjorandar: „ your memorandum 34-S dated 15th February 1922 re garding Mull a Haf 'idh# Please inform Mulla Hafidh that the matter of his not being allowed to land at Bahrain was reported to me, and that having regard to all the circumstances oi Jie case and to the fact that zhe Ruler did not desire his return for sufficient reasons I approve of the action ta.^en. Will you also kindly texl him that I received his petition of 14th January and that I had already enquired into the cases mentioned and see no reason to do so again or to intervener# As regards the Gheifch of Kuwait desiring to get rid of ! ulla Hafidh, I have no desire to force an undesirable ptrfson on him, so that if he gets rid of tho nan, I shall not interfere. At the same time as long as he does not. give trouble in 'uwait this la a better place of rsaldPnoe for hln than many others in this part of tho world from our point of viow. It would he a very good thing if he would return to hie own country hut I suppoao there is no chance of this. ' f Political RealdB-nt'in tiie Persian Gulf. Copy to P. A. Bahrain.f #■ , @) Translation of a let,tor, dated th# 1 iU- February —, froa Kulla Hafldh to the Hon'bid the Polltlaal Haaident In tht» f rcsiin Oulf« fl»p -» «fc Wfr Sir, God know^ the love arhioh is in my he&amp;rt to^^rda the Qovarruaent of Great Britain, «hlch spreads trie banner of justiae, protects the vreak, and assists those who ire on^reased^ this love la in our blood and we learnt It In the beginning from our teachers. X l-^ my a ^se before you In the hone that you *111 £ive It your careful oonsldera- tion , not merely because it a case of Injustice done to * sub ^s-^v tinder your protection, but because it is one of those cases *hlcn I fear may affect the relations between the 4rabs and Gre ^t Britain ana lead to ^launderstanding as to the good Intentions of Governments Getitlenesa and perspicacity are necessary to win over the arab people, but severity and force and dolns what self-interested people want will never produce satisfactory results• Government has sean the results of gentleness In 4 Iraq thanks to the good policy of th^t wise man Sir Percy 0ox« I aiMB« to Bahrain from %ypt In Ootobmr '9^0 »t tho roquast of the founders of th* Sduaatlonal Dap&amp;rtmar.t thmrm and of ths Jhal«s anS maa appoints Direotor of Musatlon »lth tha approval of Major Dlikaon. I ontarad upon ay duties In a way that I oonatdarad suited to the mental and natural oonditiona of the to#n, folding every- : thins.' that might oauae malloe and aantentloa ISgiMol I oarae to Kuwait In ths latter part of November '9^, navlng obtained leave of abaanae from the aahool, for the benefit of my wife's health *ho had just been confined. 1 roturned to Bahrain OS tha expiration of ay leave by 3.3. 'Barjora', -hloh arrived at Bahrain on the 9th January '9^-. Before I oouid i\o«sver, Shaikh S&amp;laan bin Hamad and Khan Bahadur Muhaaaad Sharif amn to aa and told -ta that Shaikh 'lea did not consider the present tlae suitable for me to oome to Bahrain, and that the Falltleal Agent agreed. I not only ask for oompmasatlon for the Injury done to me by this prohibition, out I also ask that minute investigation ba aade of the case, .hlah is the sork of self interested people luring my absence. I »ant you to aeic Shaikh 'Isa^and get him to state on oath shat he !mo« about ee. and who asked him to prohibit s y Jiih^n t»h^ innotmncXnp, /ny strt-* ¥6d« I am BxirprUGft that th« Political should hav® a$»«d to a demand of this sort s as he raised strong objection^ th^y wished to axpel th^ prostitutes # A® X a greater taor^x dan-^r than th# •prostitutes? Or have thsry a better right to b# protested than Iv Why did not they take aotlon «h^n i waa actually there? And why did not tfuy Inform me at Kuwait? *%en oh^lkh * I ^a himself *rote to the Folltlsal Agenoy reoommendlng that I should be slven a passport, he knew that I was ^ol ^ig on leave to aeooapany my f ^ally. There are aeorets aonneoted with this and nther aaaes »hlah happen In Bahrain ff and # If you permit me, I win either write thsa c?&gt; Com£ &amp;&gt; 3$iSSA}7**£ and tell you »hat has taken plaae during my stay there, and I aanget IC notables and shaikhs of Bahrain^bear out everythlrig my hand writes or ny tongue say® ^ if once the witnesses are promised your protection, for dwellsh means are employed there to aoouse innocent people and get them punished® In aonaluslon I should like to Invite your attention to the cases of all individuals who have been deported from Bahrain this year* Tou will then become aware of ®any truths, and *111 know whose hands make sport of the people 's pea-oa* The state of affairs In Bahrain now is like what it ^as in Basrah lurlns the unjuat rule of the Turks { and people ;aake use of the government ^nd Its power to further their cwa evil ends* God la my witness that I writ# what I do in the first convict ion th &amp;t I am rendering the greatest pos- alble service to lovernaent, 1 have the honour to be, eto, (ilgnedjl Hafldh ^ahbaii^ Director of Education, Bahrain,The ■gency # Ba h nin» Confidential. 12/2/22* No. 33 /G of 1922. Tha Hontble the Political Resident, Bushire. Memorandum. You will remember that after the individaal Ma 11a Hafidh,left hers ha v ent to Kuwait and from thence for a time to Basra. I attach an article in the Egyptian Paper f Al Akhbar 1 obv'ously written oy this individual when hs was in Basra. It is a long tirad against the 3haik of ICowa it .There is also a short articla in his usual style ,on Bahrain. It is quite clear.I think, that this individual 13 out ', mslce mischief wherever ho goes. His ob act is douhtloas uo mail the Hulor of Kowait to pay him to keep quiet. The paper ' A1 Ikhbar' as you will hove noticed frat. nrevioua editions, is »■ most scurrilous organ.It is violently auti- British and apparently willing to print fnythirfe and everything as long is it is &amp;gainst the British. It is being increasingly road all along the Talf coast,and many co -ios no« go regularly to Qatar r .atlf etc. I think it can do nothing but harm to these ignorant people,who when they see such matter in print arc quite inctpable of forming a reasoned ostimate of its value.There is littlo or no educated c^s in these S ulf ports.whose oomraon sense might bo relioa on to refute the statements of such a papor.and consequently it is liable to make groat headway. I am informed that it used to print i-rticlas .gainst Major DioK3on,&amp; some u.mo oa - article in it written against Bin Ifiud. Uajor I.A ? Political Afent Bahrain.COHFIDI -NTIAL. No. • S Of 1922« I r British Residency and Consulate-General Bushire, 24th January 1922* \% r N To The political Agent, Bahrain« Memoranduiru I enclose in original for perusal and return twc letters which were recently sent to Editors of vernacular newspapers In Baghdad for publication, but which were handed to sir p.sCox who hopes he has prevented publication. As regards the first complaint jou have made a report; please let me have any further informations you may have regarding the case and these complaints and return the petition referred to in Residency memorandum No® 1987 dated 8th De-ceraber 1921* Please let me have a report of the facts of the Snd case, which I notice iS the one referred to in Abdullah bin Makommed's pe ti ti on « I gether from the Snd paper, the open letter to the British authorities dated 16th October, that Rafia Wahbah master of the school intended to come out in the open and make charges under his own name* Both letters appear to be written in the same handwriting* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confid ent : el , i*he aisahr j -tin• 2211122. Eon'blo the Political : ?onid n^^Bu^hlrQ« Memo ran dim • I beg to for^-rd ,% or your information n co.y of lette receieved from the Politiotl Agent Kowait,together vlth the reply I h« ve nent* To explain the situation folly It would bn necessary to go rualy Into th- Politios of thie pl-^oe to explain why the individoa is in the pay of Hhalk Abdalla nd takes up the • ttituae he does. ^Ince he left hew a good de^l mor^- h&amp;u transpired.Fir? I loa.m from Bhaik -.telaman thr t ^haik 'asa sud'l-nl./ took the decision ask for his r^moTal v; it ho at consulting Abdalla, who h a .ant for him t come bac£#t!o appears to have dons this,partly beoauj« he »as doubtlas aware of how the man is employed by abdulla,^nd h- recently become nerrous of the results of such a !)olioy t and partly because the yadhi advised him strongly to do so - ? the individual was starring up troui between his sons and doing bis best m create ill-feeling bet^e^n th€ nahrf in (Jovt • m the Agency, abdulla was greatly perturbed as soon ' he heard or the result 'nd has been trying ^ver ^ince to per'ir de :&gt;hf :asa that he mate a mistake. There is no doubt that 'lulla Hafidh flee from yahrain fearing results of hie scurrilous writings on Abdall f s hal f in the yress.For a time t hey lay low t out rhen after my return : JBushire nothing h^i ):;eB8d 9 t.'m3r^&amp;sixs^cm^ai:x^x£o^cr whereas everybody e■=: ectlng Government to take some ^ ctio n to out a stop to the state of affairs here, '\bdu' ! la h^ 1 him ftgi= in sent for. Mulla Zindiq, he oersm refersd to in my has di^coversd hers^Only his sons had left for u a tar. He went to A he v.»adh: ' asked him to interdade t'r. he had himself done nothing,but admitted that his sons had oe m foolish f md hr-d mixed themselves up in transa: articles in the press tor Mulla Eafis who was their Bttperior in the : school and of whom they rwe frightened, li^fidh has throughout be«s &lt; oho ugh not to put his own name to anything, and knows tnis and backed Abdull'^s cash will doubtless continue his operations as long as hi patron la h??re rnd considers that he has something to g-- in by it. It would seem to me th-1 the best lino for the p.A.Xowalt to ttiKQ ,lf -Jhaik V-mpA Fishos to turn th.U; pnrson oat roo-c! © - f &amp; 'ihailc Ahmad ;:nown that he h*^3 b«^n foand unaoal -sblo in n- hrain, s na aov^rnnient knowing thnt it i« the general opinion that he is mischief raeker ws no re a 3011 to oblige the ^halic to retain 'n his dominions b person from who^e activities ha has - rosinrt 5 for anticipating trouolc^ As frr as Bahrain Is concsmsd v the ihallt ;-omId not have him continue in service and he had no other reason whatsoewr for r mining here* I expeot he T, oald like to force an accas' tion of having written the articles in the press, Decause he loiows that it wou-d be most difficalt to prove n ' he has covered his tracks.He has only written in Egyptian and ersian p pars which will print ^ny anonymous eontribut ! on for a payment♦ His attempt in the Times of Mesopotamia failed as you k:r 'fhe simplest pft-in would have been to have deported him to tfgypt under the Bahrain Order in coonoftl.Plenty of evidence was availabl but I v.as anxious not to have to ne oontinua' ly deporting people,especl^ since f 3 'ion^ t &amp; Abdalla remains here rni has money to spend he will get someone else to do his worlc« I enolo^e for your information sone anonymous lattrrs xs received b Police and Municipal Officials. These things ^r© always im possible to 'ring home,but anyone conversant with the intrigues o thi plnce at once realises th t they can only originate from &gt;shai c Abdolla.f there is noone else who has any oo/ect in such actions. Major Political Agent.IIU * * ' , twi 4 -I -■ -} . ox - - » -^anciT J Ku'A'att^ v &lt; ih. r ..&gt;. .•'tV.a :'■• •■ I c:2^. To . I The Political A ^ent B A H R A I H, MElfOaANDm !. Reference your telegram No.116-0 dated 24th November , Otj. w-si'3 5'-'h &gt; fis udi.fiu '- cp . Hai Idh. bt'.i ^aJiaba appXted. to 313 ''o ~ an andorsoment to his Qerttfloata of I (Bahrain 158^ of 22nd Fovember I oat) for return to Bahrain, end, aa you had deson- oed 1' 1on it a a com! .1.3 hare ' for 'visit 1 -ad made it available ror a joar Instead of for the voyage only, I ^turned that there waa r» objection to his raturning and gave him the endorsement, .e le.. u nere by o, 3»'Bar '• ^ ora *■ on the 7 th instant, but return ad ^3 r the 'Ahmed! ?f yesterday afternoon. /.v. states tha&gt; on 1I.3 ax^rival at Bahrain, ^haiich Salman bin ^■ca :a-u al- Tsa and ''.nan Bahadur huhamsiad 3harif :;-oarded th3 vessel ci^u t ■ '.a . tnat The 3nai : c.b. of Bahrain axd not ^ish hi21 to remain In Bahrain, and that you agreed with Lim in this decision. He (4 'Ccor^:.i i^l y 'I'ansf c'l'red -o the 'Ahmedi'' } -vhich was then in harbour, and returned to Kuwait -.Yithout landing* He has now come to me as the oppressed British protected person an l a-. to be told for -rhat reason this decision has been '. :i v, 1 ■■ nj a . s 'i&gt;•.• : :sval 'fi 11!'? tnis tyne of nerson he professes the profo;..- d love and admiration for everything British, He says that there was certainly no question of his not being allowed to return when he left Ba-rain In November, and, in support of his statement ! produces a paper granting him leave of absence from the school• He maintains that he can think of absolutely no reason for Shaikh *1 sas decision , He hints that r ou parsonally have had your mind poisoned against him by lying reports, vihich he fears you ha ire believed, that he has been speaking against you regarding the case of a Persian who died a few days after having, been up before you on the charge of having stolen a ring, T spoke to Shaikh Ahmad about him when I received your telegram under reference, and he appeared to know all his history, I am sure</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000349_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/106</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000349</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/106</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/14 Mulla Hafiz'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1921/1924</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-03-19T00:13:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">heb</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (81 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of each folio. It would appear that this file has been foliated and then at a later date conserved and rebound in a different order to the foliation sequence. The foliation sequence appears to reflect the original order of the items, so the reasons behind the rearrangement of the folios are unclear. The folios in the file now run in the following manner: ff.1-48; ff.77-79; ff.65-76; ff.49-64.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the British Political Agents at Bahrain and Kuwait; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire; the Acting British High Commissioner at Cairo; the Secretary of State for the Colonies; Shaikh ‘Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah; Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah; the editors of the
                           Mesopotamia Timesand
                           al-Akhbārnewspapers.These correspondence concern the personality and activities of Ḥāfiẓ Wahbah, known as Mulla Hafiz, formerly an Egyptian schoolmaster operating in Bahrain and an associate of Shaikh ‘Abdullāh bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah. Within these correspondence are details about Ḥāfīẓ Wahbah's expulsion from Bahrain, his contacts with various newspapers including the Cairo-based
                           al-Akhbārand the
                           Mesopotamia Times, and his activities as the agent of Ibn Sa‘ūd at the Kuwait Conference.Included within these correspondence are the following newspaper extracts in Arabic from
                           al-Akhbār:'Ḥūdāth [sic.] al-baḥrayn' (Events in Bahrain) in issue 680, 17 May 1922 / 20 Ramaḍān 1340 ( f. 40);'Akhbār al-bilād al-‘arabiyyah: akhbār al-baḥrayn' (News from the Arabian Peninsula: Bahrain News) in issue 461, 31 August 1921 / 27 Dhū al-Ḥijjah 1339 (f. 42);'Anbā’ al-sharq: al-ḥūwādith al-kahṭīrah fī al-baḥrayn' (News from the East: Incidents in Bahrain) in issue 576, 12 January 1922 / 14 Jamādī al-Awwal 1340 (f. 43);'Anbā’ al-sharq: al-ḥālah fī al-kūwayt' (News from the East: the Situation in Bahrain) in issue 478, 20 September 1921 / 17 Muḥarram 1340 (f. 44).Folios 2-6 contain signatures in Hebrew script and have been misplaced and relate to 'File 5/13 Sayegah Khadori' (IOR/R/15/2/105).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>al-Akhbār, newspaper, Egypt</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Ḥāfiẓ Wahbah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Bahrain 'Īsá bin 'Alī Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Ḥamad bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah, Hakim of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh 'Abdullāh bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000349#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>