<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002e3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T12:18:50.007Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM-N@ . Lfjif British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, //~ May 1904. To The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein. Si r, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No 89, dated 9th ultimo &gt; and enclosure, and to re - quest that you will he so good as to inform Sheikh Naser bin Mubarek that the Resident has no communication to make to him on the subject of his letter* He is perfectly aware what the views and policy of the British Government are in the matter and these views and j)olicy are unchanged. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant 9 First Assistant to the Political Res i den t in th eK- //U ^ TTo: of l c 1Q05, British Residency and Consul at e-Greneral Bushire / J ^ June 1905. To, Sir, Captain F. B. Prideaux I. A., Political Agent BAHREIN. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No:189 of 1st June enclosing translation of a letter from Fasir bin Mubarak to your address. 2. We can only regard Kasir bin Mubarak as a subject of Shaikh Esa in rebellion and I think the proper course is to ignor§ the letter and refuse to hold any communication with the writer except through Shaikh Esa. In fact I think it would be worth while your telling Shaikh Esa now that you have had a letter from Kasir expressing a desire to communicate with you, and are ignor ing it, and adding that you mention the fact to him in case he can suggest any reason for the rebel writing to you now. PresumablyrGsumably Shaikh Esa knows his movsniGnbs. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Ma J or Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.V. i - • No^rfof 1905 folitic^l Agency Bahrein* Bated the %%rd of Deoeraber• T90-5 To .j*6! iQiitXCSll ii; thfc? GuiXx Bushirfcu Sir, €n&lt;Linq iiitdi rmtwrnxom to oorraiaiponclaxias^i^U snow letter i .To 80^ datad the I3t ■ of June 1905 on the subject of ITasir bin Mubamk I have the honour to enclose' copy of the lette A ^ | iihlch I at once a Wreased to Sheikh 13a In aooordanot vrilt- j r o-.ii' instructiona t and. a trap.slation of the Chief's peoly thereto. '* uae circumstances*I w&gt;,s jituoh eiabarrasaect last month at unexpectedly iaeeting Sheikh Kasir in his father- in-law Sheikh Jasiia hin 'Vh'mi'a camp at Bu Hasa,as re fusal to listen to hlia would have certainly annoyed re host. decided therefore to give Sheikh ifasir soae good advice,and I am glad to be able now to forward a transla tion of a letter dated the 6th 3hawwalI333 ( the 3rd of December 1905 ) which the refugee has sent to tie on the lines I suggested to hiu. I told ITasir distinctly that tJiere was little chance of Oovemaent's pressiru?- Sheikh i3sa to allow hia to return to Bahrein,but that they would undoubtedly be glad to hear of the reconciliation if it could be effected,and that aubmiasion on his part would at any rate perhaps benefit his descendants after Sheikh ■sa's lecease . Sheikh Hasir .-aet. Sheikh Haraad in Doha aX 4 *.tc fH. ' ^ tew weeks previous to this A though I ara not certain whether .interview waa pre—arrrUijRscl # Sheikh Hasir is exactly the same age as Sheikh but looks ranch stronger and younger.lt has been onr iliv,.,, ali, \.'is X/Osupport Shellch '-Ssa against Sheikh HasirTranslation of •, Ibtter tvon 3hel -h Waalr bin Mubapl' .to ■/aptaln ■ ! .B»i^rl'leux»jr'olltical Arr«»nt,iiahrtln. i at r itht 6tjh 0f Shtvmnxl 1333 H 3rd of i^oember&gt; 1906 After Ooiapliinerts I bog to that I aia anxious to ho rvoonolled to the Chief of Bahrein to he allowed to live In the co'mtry of ay anoeatora. I have ah-«.tone;l nil hopes of recovering the heritage of ay w^afather,^ ! I anh-nit, to the. decision nf the British Cioverment and of the People of Herein that there should he only one of th. A1 Khalifa as ruler of Bahrein. I wish only to reside in Bahrein as a subject of the (Thief like the other aembera Ot tie -a rj\alita,lf the British Oovernment will aediat© Jid effect a reconciliation hetvreen S* «uu| n7 couain r ' in A11 ^ XTi11 ******* the Utt«r to b^tow mtlUbte allowances upon ne and . A v brethren of the A1 Abdullah aec tion, I strictly bind itself to abandon all such w^ 3 as W rt-ault in uiacMef. I « not rMpO^lbl. for th. Hhich under God's will oooured in the nast.as I w. a y,^ ^d iignorant and a follower of Sheikh Muham^d bin Abdal- lah. T hope to God that a reconciliv-ion will he effected between the A1 Abdallah ^d K A1 Belmnn ^ that thi 3 a ° V !,e ''■ Ch - teVto&lt;t Vhrov*the effort^# the British Oovem- ■aent. The order la yours etc jljP;/'-^V I British Residency and Consulate-general. Bush ire, ' March 1906. To The Political Agent, Bahre in. Sir, I have the honour to invite a reference to your letter No 456, dated 23rd December 1905, on the subject of a representation made by Sheikh Esa's outlawed cousin , Sheikh Has ir bin IMbarak, begging that the Government of India may intervene in order to effect a reconciliation between himself and Sheikh Esa, 2 m In reply to his petition you should inform Sheikh Nas ir bin Ihibarak, that, in view of the past, the Govern ment of India do not consider that they have sufficient grounds for intervening in order to press a reconciliation upon Sheikh Esa, but that in saying this they wish in no way to discourage him from making such friendly efforts on his own behalf to arrive at a reconciliation y as may seem good to him. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.IitBush ire. / fL ^ Please see your DoG' of 24th November regarding the case of Nasir Mubarak. I will await your further report , but in the event of your coining into contact with him again you must be careful to say nothing which will unnecessarily raise his hopes or make it difficult to avoid ; subsequent afc -tion in his behalf ? £0r ?/e cannot presume that the Government of India will be inclined to give him any countenance • i Fifa /( m■Q) /68-S of 1908. BMtiish Resicl§ncy and Consulate-General, BusMre, ^ May 1903. A copy of tlie undermentioned communication is forwarded, with, compliments, to tiie Political Agent, Bahrein, for information and any observations iie may wisii to make. By order. First Assistant Resident. Tiie Political Agent, Koweit to tiie Political Resi dent, Persian Gulf, No. 237, dated loth. May 1903 and enclosure.OONFIDENTIAI' 1908. Office of the Political Agent,Aoweit, Aoweit 13th. Ma^ 1908, Major S.G.Knox, I .A*, Political Agent, Aoweit, MaJ op P. Z• Cox, C. 1.E., Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, jjushire. Sir, I have the honour to solicit a refer ence to ^our letter No.955, dated the 24th Jlarch 1908 on the subject of the Nasir Mobarak branch of the family of the Sheikhs of uahrein. 2 9 Hearing that '^asir bin Mobarak was in Aoweit, I thought, it a favourable opportvmit^ to acquaint the family with the repl„ which „ou were good enough to authorise me to give to their appli- cation. I accordingly instructed Moolla Abdulla bin Abdul Ilahi to inform Nasir bin Mobarak that, as he was no doubt aware, Ali bin Hamad had visit ed me a month or two ago and recuested me to write to the Resident on behalf of the famil.,that I had received a repl„ and would be glad to infom him of it,if he would visit me. 4 . On the 12th Ma., Sheikh ^Tasir bin Moba- rlk came to see me and, in the course of conver sation showed me a letter that he had received from Captain Prideauz couched in precisely ^the terms that I had been instructed to conve„.I tola the Sheikh that this letter simplified matters for me a good deal,as it was exactly the answer which I was instructed to give him. From To5. I further informed Ixim that it had come to m^ knowledge during the visit of Ali bin Hamad and I had reported to Government that there was good reason to believe that the notorious outlaw, Ahmed bin Sulaimaji, was living in the tents of the Sheikh and that I had been instructed to tell him that he could not give a better proof of the sincerity of his professions of lo^alK and attach ment to the British Grovemment than b^ handing over to them this well known offender, 6 1 Sheikh Nasir bin Mobarak made no attempt to den^ that he was in touch with Ahmed bin Sulaiman but declared that, situated as he was, he had no power whatever to do such a thing.He stated that, owing to his negotiations with the British authorities, the allowances that he and his family had been receiving for some w ears from the Turks had been cut off.,that it was with the greatest, difficult, that he was able to keep back his own more immediate adherents from making an effort to get back their own or perish in the attempt, as he had nothing to induce them to sta. .1th him? that, however,he felt confident that,if the British Government would step in between him self and Sheikh Isa and give him something even a small portion of the revenues out of which he had been kept for 39 .ears,he was confident that he could control them and others and keep them out of mischeif. 7&gt; As regards the possibility of a re- conciliation .!«. Shoifci loa.M .a' «&gt;at be tod tried to set both Bbeitt HobaraK of Koweit and Sheikh Jasim bin Thani of Aatar to mterv totb bad replied tbat tne, could do '»bbin g .de ^id tbat be did not .ant to live in .abrern but would live wherever he was directed to do so. m w8 « l-'he conversation at the visit of Sheikh. Aha^al and Sheikh Mobarak to the Agenc^ v • v v.ri„i X on the 13th Ma^ turned on the affairs of TTasir bin Mobarak and I ask§d them if it was not possible Ll • u ' &gt;, ; i ' for them to persuade Sheikh Isa to put an end to the scandal of his cousins practically begging from door to door.The„ replied that while the„ regretted his behaviour. Sheikh Mobarak indeed expressed himself ver^ strongl., on the subject, the., saw no wa^ of intervening effectively as, if Sheikh Isa did not listen to them,the., never, for a moment, expected that he would, the., would according to Arab ideas of honour have no option but to enforce his compliance with the sword, a course of action which was impracticable in ever., wa^ .At the same time. Sheikh Mobarak warned me that Tasir bin Mobarak had asked him to tell me that he had wandered from Consul to Consul getting no satisfaction from them, that the affairs of the Xl Abdulla were in a desperate state,that he would wait a couple of months to see if anything came of his present written application which I have the honour to enclose herewith, and then make 9, desp^erate attempt to recover what he considers his own b^ force or die.I replied that then of course he would die and Sheikh Ahazal who appears to have a more correct notion of relative strengths than Sheikh Mobarak,echoed m^ words. 9 # Sheikh Mobarak then abruptly changed the conversation and,as I considered that I had already rather overstepped the limits of friendly advice in a matter that had little or no concern with m. office, I made no effort to return to the subject.Translation of a letter elated, lltli Rabi n,1326 (= 12th. May 1908.) from Naser bin Mubarek al Ktialifah to ' iajor P. Z. Cox, O.I.S. 9 Political Resident in tiie Persian G-ulf. After conveying copious salutations and due honour and respect,(I beg to state that) I adhere to the relations of friendship and. cordiality. According to the conversation which took place, recently, between me and you and to the further communi cation which was made by me and the Political Agent, Bahrein, I have constantly been waiting, as promised by both parties (i.e. by both of us), for the result of that communication. I, however, believe that an affair in which you take measures will le settled, if uod pleases, in such a satisfactory manner as is expected from the sense of honour and Justice of the British Government and from your highmindedness and the good offices whffihh you afford. But,as it is not hidden from you. the exigencies of time require that result, should be obtained by conuaunications being exchanged tetween both parties. Still I do not think that this is the case always, because our old and new relations are inspired with absolute cordiality ( and suffice for settlement of an affair). It now became necessary for me to remind you; that the affair will be settled by such an and I hope that the anai early contrivance a s « lea. te emetneee ™ ^ ing (te eeerthat your high epinion eeem. nt. - rate, your opinion is high.• confidential; £v) To; 34,^ Of 1908. Political _ Atrtmoy Bahrain, 2/ 'jtme 1908. '•'ron. Major ^.B.Prideans, Poli-tical Agnnt. Bahi-ain, To, Major P.Z.Oox, C.I.I?,, Political Reaident. in the Persian Gtilf, 4, BUSH1RFJ, Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of yoxxr office -Inloraejaont TTo:1686 datnd the 3na J\me 1908 with enclosures, on the auhjeot of Shaikh ITasir bin Mubarak, the Bahrain Pretender. I had hopes at one tine that this Shaikh night possess a one quanttm of administrative capacity, and that with the assistance and noral support of his fatb er -in-1 'm Shaikh Jasliii bin 7hanl # ho jftdght h© able to v settle himaelf on the 'Torth-eaBt coast of K«.tar&gt; about /hioh Shaikh Esa I think would have nade no objection, and to ftra tually iniuce the mritliate tribal oettlemants in his vicinity to acaept his suzerainty forming a aoistpaot little state, which eventually could have entered into formal treaty £ relations with the 0o¥iTj'ie-nt of Irr.lia. I threw out a bint once ■o his t .fot to both Shaikh Jasim an;l Shaikh JTasir, ^ho said that they -rould consider it seriously* Later on, I found that there waa no likelihood of the enterprise being attenptod, nnd I have since come t^D the conclusion that it i d rht possibly have involved us in difficulties rith the -'''urks, as it is well-kno^m that Shaikh ITasir was once given by them a date-garden in Hasa for bis maintonanoe# I aa vt ...ry sceptical about tiiis ^ar len havingbeen re suae &lt;1 for uhe reason aeirtioned by ITasir, *xi&lt;X am endeavouring to get definite inforria/uion on the point. 4. It is quit© certain that Shaikh Ksa will never be reaonciled to his cousin, nor make him any allowance voluntarily froxa the Bahrain revenues, as he professes to regard him ?,s one of the actual murderers of his father Shaikh Ali* 5, When Shaikh Hsa and Shaikh Hasir die,however, i think there will be little difficulty about persuading the new Chief of Bahrain to 'nerxait the return of the other laeiabers of the A1 Abdallah branch, yfho u^un now are probably only voluntarily shairinc the exile of their senior representative, and perhaps to grant them small / allowances, siriilar to those which certain menbers of are the A1 Abdallah e^en now mm* en/joying. A. 6 # The present year undoubtedly is favourable for the adoption of piratical enterprises on a larger scale than usual, as many of the Be louin vfho have fallen into the practice of engaging themselves as pearl-divers during the hot- weather nonihs, will probably find them selves without legitimate employment this sunner owing to the restricted number of ^oats now working. 7. i can think however that, Sh ikh ITasir will definitely adopt a joiirae of life at his age, which will make hiia an ontlaw un ter Turkish nile, and will render his future visits to Kowait, Haskat and Lusail difficult if not inpossible. 8, i think that a reply nicrht be qi' r en to him definitely row that Shaikh '-Isa bin Mi refuses absolutely to be reconciled to him, and he should therefore live luietly for the rest of his life as a Turkish subject, enjoying the pension -which the Sultan has bestowed upon him. His followers amongst the A1 Ahda 1 lah can still apply to me for gnod offices with a iiew to becoiaing reconciled to Shaikh Ksa, =ind the disabilities fhich they and Shaikh Hasir will incur, as detailed in paragraph 7, in the event of their resorting to rebellions orNo . 0-30J of 1908. British Residency and Consulate-General, ^ushire, ^S &gt;July 1908. Copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded^ with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for 1 information. First Assistant Resident. (In charge current duties). Prom the First Assistant Resident, In charge Cur rent duties, to the Political Agent, Koweit, No. 2308 dated the 28th July 1908..230^ V^»sw2l» . ^o*elc&gt;U b 0 f 29Q3 British Realdonoy am Conoulate -Ganoral ■. iK.lJ.re, July 1CC8 # TO Tlae political Agent, ^ o w e i t. Sir, V/Ith refarenoe to correspondoaoa ending with your letter Bo.287, dated the istb ay ZOO8, regarding Haser Din Mubarak, I have the honour to tofona you that the Eeeldont direote that if you have an opportunity you should tell Baser tiiat Sheiih Xsa la not silling to be reconciled to him and that the Reoidant regrets he doee not see his way to nove further In the natter: Major 1 Cox's advice to hln is to live quietly for the rest of his -ifo and he : would be vary ill advised to embarlc on rebellious or piratical course, the evil consequences of wiiich ®ould Inevitably recoil on his osm head and that oi bXt iaailly, as long as they continue to conduct themselves circumspectly his followers of the A1 Abdulla branch can continue to apply to the Political Agent, Eah- reln x or 1- xc-od of ricee In pre-iotlng a reconciliation Vrf 4 n, ~ J* W X fci* t.'** &gt;O «&gt;I f.if I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, iif J f Captain, First Assistant Eeeident* (In cixarge ou. rent duties).Ho. 5'^ of 1900, / , v folitioal A Tenoy, 4l r f %K'' Bahrein,t-t-h Au^iat, 1909. From i o Captain 0. Maok^nziu, I # A*, jpoli-tioal A?enti, Bahrein, Tha Political Heui lont in 'th^ x^eriiian (nilf, B u a h i r e* Sir, 1/ith referenoe 'to corra^pondunae en'lin r UHi^i your ^ndoro-aarrt To. tated tha 0 .8th July 1909, I have the honour to forward, herewith, a translation of a letter recently received iron BheiMi Ilasir bin Mubarak, together with a oopy of the reply I propoae to &amp;vr &lt;L hi . tilth your approval. Another alternative appears to be to ^end him a severe letter to the affect that no further rep ra mentation a on thia subject will be attended to. There is little use in allowing the cjorre^pondenoe to proceed, now that it ha^ been settled that nothing is to be done for Mru I believe I co^lld obtain ~2i allowance for hia from She Ik} i ^aa In a friendly way, but at the aaiae time thia course would certainly be very di a tastefuldiatasteful to the Ohlef, and there la no auffijient 'aalr. I atippoae there ia no likelihood that Oovamiaon-^' would a ana t ion a pension for hira of aowo ia: 3,000/- per 'nnnra on oondition that he ahould officially disclaim all pretenaiona to bein r a Turkish subject. At present he ia merely axxpported by the charity of J'—**- f**/* . raaaon 'to upsset# for the banAflt» or 3huikh X have the honour to be. Sir, Your moat, obedient servant^ Captain, Political A.Tent, Bahreinatiliat# 'time iJh® British ha't not r^oo^nisad W ^ol:* 0 -3 Hor had offerad kind probation to -Uie Bahrein lalands. Than the British (^ovenuaent, xorf&amp;ve. It, tar jav© the lar an t the near after vTomiiifj adi/toz'.itjion• Bahrein ^itereti binder the protection of the British • ■otrem/aent. We withheld ouraelves and br- « the aworlsj^aidin: «#- strife and otir tho-a rhts were absorbed in how we shoixld tain the ]Jrltiah pleasnAt and ^ow we should en-ter into aonnecjtion with it ?uid % tinder its protootion. We should not be disappointed in Tettin- onr ri thta and deprived of ita Jnatioe w^iah extends to thoae helon^inT to it aa well aa to others. Pease Was eatabliahed by the Uovemraent and a atop wn,a put to raiaahlevoua iaattera. I then wrote a latter to you and aent it bj t.he hand of iqy nan Siilainan Junaid hopin? thao it •fill prodnoa t,he effeat that I / hoped froia yon I reoeivo i reply that you were sorry at t-he displeasure of jay Uncle's son Sheikh laa and that I should remain in thla aoadition dnrinT ray life tiros and that I shotild not ranks any disttu-banoes Perhaps afx^er iWdeath peace may be nale between the yotrn - taembers of lay faraily and the Chief of iahrein. I wondered at it. If I am left excluded dnrinr ray life tliiia froii tht- Justice of the Britiah (wrernraent and am deprived of ay eatabliahed rights over old andJy Ho. ^2?A of 1909, Brioisii Besidency a^cT^onsulaoe General, Bushire, August, 190P. -' V 8EP.WM ''&gt;sSM Pa f: -jyir TO The Political Agent, Balrrein. Sir, With, reference to your letter No. 505, dated 6th August 1909, I have the honour to say that-I think, it will 'be pre ferable if you refer Sheildi I\ T aser bin Mubarek to the communica tion made to him by the Political Agent, Koweit, on 11th March 1909 at Koweit on ir^y behalf ( the same as that contained in 9 the Enclosure to Residency endorsement No. 2S0^, dated 28th July 1908 to your ad-dress ), and say that you regret that you are not in a position to give him any other answer than that. I have the honour to be. iir, : r our most obedient servant. ^ Major, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002e3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/4</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002e3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/4</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File A/6 Nasir bin Mubarak's claim to Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1903/1909</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-12-20T10:55:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (73 folios)</extent><extent>The contents of the volume are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest items at the front to the latest at the rear.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using circled pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. The following foliation anomalies occur: 1a-1f, 7a, 16a, 36a. The following folios are fold-outs: 2, 12, 17, 20, 22, 23, 28, 31, 37, 39, 43, 44, 46, 56, 58, 59, 68-70.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence relating to Shaikh Nāṣir bin Mubarak Āl Khalīfah's claim on Bahrain, and his subsequent attempts at reconciliation with the Bahrain ruler Shaikh ‘Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah. The principal correspondents in the file are Captain Francis Prideaux, Political Agent at Bahrain from 1904 to 1909, Major Percy Cox, Political Resident from 1904 to 1909, and Shaikh Nāṣir bin Mubarak Āl Khalīfah.In letters sent to the Bahrain Political Agent in 1903 and 1904, Shaikh Nāṣir, who was the grandson of the deposed Shaikh ‘Abdullāh of Bahrain, asserted his right to land on the islands formerly owned by his grandfather; a right that he had maintained since the 1890s. In May 1905 he threatened to give up his land rights to the Turkish Government if the British Government continued to ignore his claims (folios 7-7a). A chance meeting between Prideaux and Shaikh Nāṣir, at Shaikh Jāsim bin Thānī’s camp at Bu Hasa in December 1905, prompted a change in tone, as a result of Prideaux recommending to Shaikh Nāṣir that the British would be more prepared to support a reconciliation between himself and Shaikh ‘Īsá (folios 15-16). Numerous letters sent by Shaikh Nāṣir to Shaikh ‘Īsá throughout 1906 were, however, ignored, leading to Shaikh Nāṣir sending numerous letters to Prideaux, asking for his help. However, the official British line, obtained by Cox from the Government of India in May 1906, was that there were insufficient grounds for British intervention in seeking a reconciliation between Shaikh Nāṣir and Shaikh ‘Īsá (folio 19). Subsequent British attempts to settle Shaikh Nāṣir at Fuwairat on the Qatar coast, with the support of his father-in-law Shaikh Jāsim bin Thānī, were likewise unsuccessful (folio 35). In a letter to Cox, dated 26 June 1908, Prideaux suggested that Shaikh Nāṣir should resign himself to never being reconciled to Shaikh ‘Īsá, and that he should live out the rest of his life quietly as a Turkish subject, without recourse to “rebellions or piratical activity”. (folios 51-53).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002e3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>