<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000178_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T16:09:29.201Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">R E C E P T. 1 Received from the Political Agent, Bahrain, the sum of Rupees(100/-) One hundred only being the rent of the building used as Indian Assistant’s Court for the period from 1st April 1935 to 30th September 1935 according to the lease made. Bahrain. The 19th May 1935. L.T.I. of Yusuf bin Abdullah Shatar. *■flSHH s/ 'gj - T ^ &lt;D xhe Addl. Deputy secretary to the Government of india in the Foreign and Political Department, The HonJble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum no. F#159-a/34. Dated yimla, the 3rd July 1935, Renting of a house for the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, and a Court room for the Indian Assistant, Bahrain. / \ Reference correspondence ending with your letter No. 2238/19/74, dated the 6th October 1934. 2. in view of the fact that suitable houses are very few in number and there is much competition for suitable accomodation, the Government of India are pleased to confirm your action in leasing a house for the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain at an annual rental of jxs. 1,620/- Vrupees one thousand six hundred and twenty) from 1934-35 on the understanding that the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain will not be entitled to any house rent allowance. 3. The Government of India are also pleased to santion the renting of a building at an annual rent of Rs.200/- Crupees two hundred; for the Court of the Indian Assistant, Bahrain. 4. The expenditure involved on the above account shoul be met from the budget provision of ^s. 1,800/- in the Bahrain Agency budget estimates for 1935-36 under the head »29- political Account l-A*- Other Agencies and Residencies A.6.- Contingencies’• sd. V.Narahari Rao, Addl. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Received with tnishire Printed letter wo. 1435/19/174 dated the 15th duly ‘35. see rile 18/8.REG E I P T. Received from the Political Agent, Bahrain, the sum of Rupees(100/-) One hundred only being the rent of the building used as Indian Assistant’s Court for the period frcm 1st October 1935 to 31st March 1936 according to the lease made. Bahrain. The 6th November 1935. Abdullah Shatar.S' SPi © / 3' D.O. No. 1428/9-A. Adviser’s Office, Manamah, March 15, 1936. Dear Colonel Loch, With reference to the previous corres pondence on the subject of the building temporarily used as the Indian Assistant’s Court. When you consulted His Excellency Shaikh Hamad on the suitability of the building for a court he acceded to your suggestion that it should be occupied for a short time until a suitable place could be £ound although both he and the other shaikhs very definitely disapproved of it as a permanent arrangement. The court has now occupied the building for about a year and I now write to enquire when this court is to be moved to a permanent and suitable building. Yours sincerely, Lieut. Colonel G. Loch, C.I.E., H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.IRECEIPT. Received from the Political Agent, Bahrein the eura of RUpeefe (lOO-O-O)One hundred only being the rent of the building used a b\ Indian Ae&amp;ietant’b Court for the jberiod from let April 1956 to 50th September 1936.RECEIPT. Received from the Political Agent, Bahrain the aim of Rupees (50-0-0) Fifty only being the rent of the building ueed ab Indian Absibtant 1 b Court for the period from let October 1936 to 31bt December 1936. L.T.I. of Yueuf bin Abdullah bhctar. Behraio, January lc, 1937.%/ ^ ,// 5 This is the plan and elevation of the Mew Court. The site will be marked out on the ground. I have also arranged for the A.E. to ThanKs. I wo ,ld li.-ce to see the exact position in which it is proposed to place the building, pegged out. 09.00 hours on 16.4.36. 14.4.36 0, f9Ud^//,7/ v 18/10. Issued L.O.No.819 u. 25-o-8G to Adviser, Bslirsin. a.p.a/p.a. I undtratand fr«n the -aaaistant iingineer that it will take 6 mtnths tr s# te cempalete the building #f I.A’s ceurt and ae the rent 100/- fer the half year ending 30th September 1936 be paid te the owner of the court. Submitted for approval. - 4 hf 16/4/36 I see no reason to withhold this payment but think that we should inform the Adviser that work on the new court will be started as soon as the plans have been passed and that money has been allotted by the Government of India. 2. I do not see any need to await technical sanction to the plans before starting to clear the site. I suggest that the Adviser be asked to assist us in \ obtaining a purchaser for the old Barrack. The contractor carrying out the reclamation might be prepared to purchase the material, or remove the building in return for the material. ^ ^ /?/&gt;• ^ Oa 18-4-1936. fa // /WI/ fattUs ■ / l , ^ ^ V’-K'A .i 3 . a/P.A 18/10 * Th« owner of the I.^’s court ie due rent from 1st October 1956 onward. The Supervisor tells ms that the new court will not be ready till the end of March. In the circumstances may pay the rent ior the 6 » months ending 31st March 1937 i.e., As 100/-? vPc 13/ 1/37 ?&lt;w^ The landlord of the I.A'e court is due rent from 1st January 1937. May rent (^.50/-) for the period from 1st January to 31st '•arch 1937 be paid please? The landlord of the I.A f s Old Court is due rent from the 1st April 1937 to 30th June 1937. The rent of the building is ° c . 200/- per annum. May ^ 50/- be paid for the quarter, please? I-A. shifted to the new court on the 9th of June 1937. (&amp;7</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000178_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1641</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000178</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1641</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 18/10 Buildings: Accommodation for I.A’s Court.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-24T22:34:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are also present in parallel between ff 1-12, and ff 14-20; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers relating to the Indian Assistant’s Court of the Bahrain Political Agency. It includes receipts from the Political Agent, Bahrain, for rent for the building used as the Indian Assistant’s Court, and correspondence between: the Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and between the Political Agent, Bahrain, and Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain.The file includes two documents in Arabic: a lease for the Court of the Indian Assistant for one year with effect from 1 April 1934 (folio 2), and a letter from Yusuf bin Abdullah ash-Shatur to the Political Agent, Bahrain, regarding payment of rent for the building occupied by the Court of the Indian Assistant (folio 3).Detailed file notes are found on folios 13 to 20.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Assistant's Court, Indian Assistant, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000178#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>