<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001f7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T19:37:48.500Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM \0(l A)6Ca /3341elegram; XX/ Iiri P ortant • No:- 853• Dated:- 5th October 1933. Fron&gt;:~ Resident Bushire. To:- Political Bahrain. ^ ^ ; ( © S./io'.JZ Following from Secretary of State for India,October 3rd, begins: 'Addressed BHSHIRbi,copy sent by Air Ma.il to Government of India• Have you,or can you discreetly obtain,a.ny light on intentions of Bahrain Petroleum Company as regards refining ^ R 6o l/x^rtU). oil won. HOLMES * letter of May 5th 1928 to the Political Agent rather suggests (that) Eastern &amp; General Syndicate had intended refining locally,which is most desirable from our standpoint as if this is also intention (of the) Bahrain Petroleum Company.We do not,of course,wish to raise question specifically with them. PRIOR stated at inter-depa.rtmental ^ P. to liUcjJoH&gt;). meeting of May 3rd last (Paragraph 26 of record) that Shaikh was interested. Can you confirm this and should we be justified in indicating informally to Company if opportunity offers in connection with our Mining Lease desideratum that SHAIKH has been enquiring as to arrangements proposed and is anxious (for) local refining. Alternatively,would you see any objection to asking SHAIKH formally whether if question arises we can assume that this is his view.V ^ . /le; 2- Telegram:- XX/lMPORTAMT, No:- 854. Dated:- 5th October 1933• From:- Resident Bushire. To:- Political Bahrain. ^ C nc:! My iimnediately preceeding telegram. S. Slo'. W I have heard things in conversation which give me impression that Company propose to refine at any rate proportion of thiir output locally (with a view to compete in Eastern market) # Secondly . Please telegraph if you can confirm that they propose to refine locally,if necessary after making discreet enquiries• Thirdly . (should this?) information point to their not, repeat not,intending to refine locally please consult HELGRAYE as to SHAIKHS proba/ble attitude in this matter. In reporting this state whether you see any objection to formal enquiry from SHAIKH in the last sentence of the Secretary of State's telegram. 4. Please show these telegrams informally to the Senior Naval Officer, A3 £. SU?: 5 Note re: REFINERY on BAHRAIN ISLAND . Mr. BELGRAVE sajs he and SHAIKH were told by Messrs JANSON and LOMBARDI in March 1933 that they couldn't possibly say whether they would refine locally or not. They might have a plant for local consumption (in oil fields?). 2. Major HOLMES told Mr.BELGRAVE a few months ago that it might soon be possible for the BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY to sell crude oil to the BAHRAIN POWER HOUSE^ Mr.BELGRAVE hasn't asked for any as Mr.STEELE says DIESEL engines need specially rfined oil. 3. Mr.BELGRAVE knows SHAIKH wants a local refinery (on a large scale). Rerl . Mr.BELGRAVE never heard of any idea of competition in Eastern market and considers it is much too premature for the BAHRAIN PETROEEUM COMPANY to think of such markets. Re;2 . Mr.BELGRAVE will sound Mr.STEELE on latest talk and Mr.STEELE ws well up with the engineering side of the BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY 'S works and plans. Ret3 . The SHAIKH always hopes for Refinery to bring lots of work for local people . Mr.BELGRAVE says though SHAIKH has not been enquiring lately it is always in his mind and is his desire. 4. I will endeavour to find a suitable occasion for an enquiry from Mr.SKINNER./ g) S./L01S. BAHRAIN OIL . In conversation and in reply to my leads Mr. SKINNER said on the evening of the 11th October 1933:- (!)• No:3 Well was still giving water. They intended reboring and recementing. He was pessimistic as to the extent/capacity of field. (2). Re Refining . For local use only % small 'topping plant' was coming out. Re: real Refinery . He did not there would be enough oil to justify one. His Principals had no intention of trying to compete with A.P.O.C in local market,which is not large enough for two Companies. Probably they would ship oil to their (much larger than ABADAN) refineries in AMERICA. (3). He added his ARMERICAN Principals were very worried at the 'misunderstanding' which resulted in Major HOLMES 1 resignation as they pride themselves on their adhesion to their contracts. (4). Says Major HOLMES had perhaps remained on after his work was completed and that once prospecting was under way there was no need for that type of negotiator. (5). He (Mr.SKINNER) felt he could say ill that was necessary to the Political Agent and SHAIKH and without misunderstandings and heartburnings. (6). As for the 'remaining area',the B.P.C. naturally did not want others on their heels. He considered Major HOLMES f offer (of cash) very very generous at the time,and when later water came at No:3,telt that no increase/further cash offers should (2)L © 2. be made as prospects were not at all bright for oil. He informed his AMERICAN PRINCIPALS of his views. O1 @ $. fto: (&gt;, Telegram:- XX. No:- 467. Dated:- Ibtk October 1933. From:- Political Batirain. V S /to' J2S - To:- Britconsul Bushire. ^ S. fyioi 2. Your telegram ol' bth Instant,No:8b4. (1). Regret Naval visit delayed enquiry from SKINNER,who tells me:- (a) he does not think Company would try to compete in local market which is too small lor two Companies, (b) he feels sure oil,if found in any commercial quantity,would be shippeu to their large AHERICAll refineries. He spoke pessimistically as to prospects of a large oil field. (2). Adviser says SHAIKH has always looked forward to a large refinery in Bahrain to give employment to his people. (3). Ruler would readily confirm this and I see no objection to formal enquiry.% S. /Ic 7 Note on letter No: - dated ^Ist March 193E from the Chief Local Representative,The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,to the Political Agent,Bahrain. (Pages 1 and 33 of File No:10/l Volume I). Interview with Mr.Belgrave * Question:- What did Bahrain Petroleum Company do? Answer:- Mr.Belgrave says that all the Bahrain Petroleum Company ascertained was that the Land Department would lend a Surveyor for SITRA and the main coast still unsurveyed,should they wish to examine that area. Nothing followed this. lb-10-1933/O Trp-nslntlon of the sioeech rend by Mohnmripd Snleh on 'be^nlf of Shnllfh Abaullr» bin lsf» t ^resident, M-ahnrrno Munlclpollty, on the oooasion of a fare well party in honour of ^ajor ^rank Holmes. On behalf of the President and raembers of the Muharraa Municipality, I take this opporunity of * this fnrewell party arranged by the Government of Brhrnin, in honour of Major Frank Holmes, on his departure from Bahrain, which has benifited by his vnrious scemes, at the instance of the Government of Bnhrain and the assistance of the Political A^rent, viz., artesian wells of MuharraQ, Manama, etc., the Mprinmn Sen Eon^ and the Oil, which will be of ^reat importpnee to the country. I offer to M n ior Holmes may thanks, and we annreci^te his nro.^ects, his conduct and his be- hnviors towards the nublic, nnd we offer a suitable farewell and we hope thnt he will cn.^oy a happy voyage and meet with success every where. lastly, I offer the ^uhnrrao Municipality's thanks to the Bahrain Government for helding of this fnre^ell party, to His Srcellency Shaikh Homed Buler of Bahrain for his becoming the ^resident in this farewell oarty and for his appreciation of great men, and to the Manama Municipality, as the farewell has been held in its beautiful garden. Salaams' I ♦ I£ no: f D.0.No:C/472-10/l.V . Political Agency, Bahrain,the 17th October 1933 Dear Colonel, 1 enclose for your information Ehglish translations of speeches delivered by the Secretaries of the Manamah and Muharraq Munciipalities at the farewell party hiid in the Manamah Municipal Gardens on the 19th September 1933. in honour of Major HOLMES. I have only just been able to get hold of the Muharraq Municipal speech. Yours sincerely, fo he Honourable Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1316-3 of 1933. IV /io i /0 ,\ ) ; A sgr The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf presents his com pliments to 'Tie Political Apent, 'Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). for information. Weape confirm the accuracy of T r r. '^allantyne T s state ment, reported in paragraph 12 of Tr .La ithwalte ' a note of 21st September 1933. t British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. &lt;A \ ' /,-s . m ^ ze T* . - Dated 13th October 1933. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Letter dated the 15th September 1933 from the 'Bahrain Petroleum Gorrman^London, to the India Of fi ce. 2. India Office letter No .P. 5^. 6015/33 dated the 21st Sept em 'he 1933 to the Bahrain Petroleum Gomnany, London. 3. India Office letter lTo # P»Z. 6020/33 dated the 31st September 1933 to the ^etroleum ^enartmert Kines 'Oenartment , with enclosure. 4. Letter dated the 22nd Septembei' 1933 from the Bahrain ^'etroleurji Com-Danv,Iondon , to the India Office'. Bahrain Oil. —| ^ lb ^, ss £ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd., 19, Moorgate, London,S.C,2. 15th September,1933. Dear Sir, I confirm rny telephone message to you this norning to the effect that this Company has received this morning from Major Frank Holmes, a cable dated yesterday in which he says H he is writing' to the Political %ent at Bahrein and to the Sheikh of Bahrein yesterday announcing his resif^nation; and that r .wA.Skinner and he visit the Sheikh of Bahrein to-day to inform His Excellency. I', ajor Holmes concludes with the request that I should advise the India Office of the foregoing. I have learned also that Major Holmes 1 intention is to leave Bahrein by the 'plane on Thursday the 21st instant. This Company is cabling bo-day to r.Skinner informing him of Major Holmes 7 resignation yesterday and instructing him to act as Chief Local Representative of the Company in Bahrein with effect as from the date of Major ^olmes* resignation. 'r.Skinner is also being instructed that his appointment, which has the approval of His Majesty's Government, is temporary, the question of the ultimate successor has yet to be determined by the Company and, of course approved by i is Majesty's Government. Mr• Skinner is requested to keep the temporary nature of his appointment as a secret upon the assumption that the Political Agent and Major Holmes will co-operate. I am &amp;c., (Sd.) H .R.Ballantyne. J.C.Walton Esq., India Office, Whitehall,S.W.I./lo'.fo INDIA OFFICE, I'liHIIEHALL, S.W. 1. P.Z.6015/33. 21st September 1933. Dear Mr. Ballantyne, In tlie course of our talk this morn lug you asked whether, should the Company desire to adopt this course. It would he possible for a meeting to be arranged between uie Petroleum Department and a technical representative of the Company to discuss the technical aspects of the question whether by December next the Bahrein Petroleum Company would have had enough time and done enough work to make it possible for them to choose the area to imich they are entitled for the purpose of the mining lease. 1 n ow write to say that the Petroleum Department will be very glad to see a technical representative of the Company and discuss the matter with him if the Company so desire. They point out, however,(and we should like to associate ourselves with this) that the ^ matter, as you will appreciate, is one of much urgency and that it would be desirable that any discussion should, ii pOoslble, take place in the immediate future. .Ballantyne, Esq., Ban re in Petroleum Company, 19, toorgate, iii • C» •s - 2 - 15 3. Perhaps you would be so goou as to let me know the wishes of the Company in the matter. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAIIE. ft, ♦Gonl'idential* P.Z.6020/33. INDIA OFFICE, LONDuK f S.W.I. iaist September 1953. / My dear Starling# I enclose a note of my discussion with Ballantyne this morning, the gist of which I have already given you by telephone* Consequent on our decision I informed him that the Petroleum Department will be glad to discuss the technical aspects of this question (and those only) with a technical expert on behalf of the Company, if the Company desire this; but that the atter is one of great urgency and that we hope there will be no delay in ohe arrival of their representative if they wish to take advantage of this offer• 2» Could we have a meeting say on Monday to discuss the amendments in the mining lease? There is, I t-hiiifc, much force in what Ballantyne says, and the sooner we can get a complete list of our desiderata in to him the stronger our position will be. The most controversial are, of course, those which the Admiralty have in mind* I am sending copies of this letter to Rendel at the Foreign Office and to Moore at the Admiralty* Yours, Ac*, (Sgd.) J.G. LAITHWAITS# it tarling Esq., oleum Department, nes Department, Dean Stanley Street, J 3.1».l.Swij j+ (i S. /loTTo aantlal . £..2.6020/05. NOT-''' OP AN INTERVIEW ON 21st SEPTEMBER WITH lit H.R. BALUNTYNE OF THE BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY. Mr. Ballantyne had asked Tor an Interview In order to discuss the question ol the extension of tiie Bahrein Petroleuffi CoiTipany's prospecting licence. 2. The position oi' i 'via .'ior K o I iuqs * At the outset Mr. Ballantyne conl'irmed that Ivajor Holmes had nov/ handed over and was leaving Bahrein to-day. He rWas anxious to know whether H.M.G. wished to persist in their charges against hinu I saia that I thought we should ce quite satisfied to let this matter drop in view of subsequent developments. Mr. Baliantyne expressed satisfaction and added that in the interest of preventing any future misunderstanding he was anxious to make it clear that Major Holmes had now ceased to have any connection with the Bahrein Petroleum Company and was no longer their Chief Local Representative; that at the same time he understood that he was still in the employment of the standard Oil Company, and the Bahrein Company were also under the impression, as the result of statements by him, that he had been and might still be engaged on private business by various Sheikhs in the Gulf, including the Sheikh of Bahrein. It was possible in these circumstances that he might at some time in the future find himself again in Bahrein and possibly using the name of the Standard Oil Company. Mr. Ballantyne hoped on behalf of the Bahrein Petroleum Company that we would not misinterpret any such visits by Major Holmes ana would accept the Bahrein Company's assurance that so far as they were concerned his responsibilities in Bahrein were at an end f I said we appreciated the position. 3. Extension of the prospecting licence . Mr. Ballantyne then raised the question of the extension of/ T?)I % ' ^ - 2 - of the prospecting licence. The Company remained of opinion thcit tiiey were entitled, uo a mrther extent ion and felt that such an oc tens ion vvoula ids necessary before they could 'be entirely satisfied as to the oil position in Banrein. There was nothing in the Hheikh's reply to show why the extension haa heen refused. The Compmy were in a position of some difficulty: they did not wish to ask the sheikh (through Mr. skinner) for his reasons, for fear of receiving a snuh, and equally they tnought that a request for those reasons submitted through the India Office might offend the Sheikh's amour -propre . 4. I said that I saw no reason why I should not frankly inform Mr. Ballantyne of the position. The information supplied by the Company had been very carefully considered by the technical advisers of H.K.G., who in the light of their investigations had advised that by December next the Company would have had enough time and done enough work to enable them to choose the area to which they were entitled for the purpose of the mining lease. On a point to which Mr. Ballantyne haa referred, I understood that there was nothing unusual in striking water in operations such as they were at present carrying on, ana in the view of tne Petroleum Department the Company were indeed lucky to have struck oil in all their bore-holes. He would not, moreover, overlook that the Company and their predecessors had now had 8 years from 1925 in which to make the necessary investigations in Bahrein. 5. There was a aifferent aspect of tne matter, viz. the financial aspect,of the grant of a further extension by the Sheikh. The Sheikh, as Mr. Ballantyne was probably aware, was very short of money and financial considerations must weigh very considerably with him. To grant a further extension/■ .....,.'1 @ extension (for which, on the advice summarised, in the preceding paragraph,there was no justification) would mean a further postponement of the receipt Toy him of increased royalties, etc. under the mining lease. Further, as Mr. Ballantyne v/as no doubt aware, the A.P.O.G. had now applied for a concession in respect of the halance of the islands. The Sheikh obviously could not proceed with this application until he knew what area was available and that he would not know until the B .P .C. had taken out their mining lease. The grant of a further extension to them would therefore not merely have the effect of postponing his increased receipts unaer the B.P.C.'s mining lease, hut also of postponing any receipts (whether from the B .P.C. if they were interested in the area, or from the A.P.O.C.) in respect of the remaining area of the islands. 6. On the question of the right of the Company to fins IT an extension, we were advised on the highest legal authority that they were not so entitled, and the Sheikh., in acting as he had acted, was acting within his legal rights. 7. Mr. Ballantyne expressed appreciation of this explanation of the position ana said that he would inform his Principals in S^n Francisco without delay. He wished to remind me that at an earlier stage this summer he and Mr. Lomhardi had informed the Colonial Office ttettha Company regarded the extension as one to which tney were entitled and were not prepared to make any additional payment in order to secure it. He recognisea at the same time the Sheikh 1 s financial difficulties and the force of the financial arguments. Moreover, if the A.P.O.C. were interested in the 'balance of the islands, it was clearly no longer possible, as the Company had at one time intended, to deal with the extension of the licence and the extension of/1*3 - 4 - if the area simultaneously ^nd sweeten the Sheikh hy giving lirn a lump sum to he repaid from royalties. His Company light, he thought, in the altered circumstances he prepared jo reconsider the question of some payment in return for a Concession, hut he could not, of course, comuit them on this. Speaking personally, he would prefer in the circumstances to ihandon the idea of a further extension and take out the aining lease next December. The Company had already made arrangements (in case they should he forced to take out the ulning lease) to stake out areas and coula prohahly take out :ho mining lease without delay. It looked now as though Bahrein was likely to he a less profitable proposition from the oil standpoint then haa at one time heen anticipated, and ipart from that there was little doubt that the Company were m the right siae of the oil bearing structure. 3. After some further discussion Mr. Ballantyne enquired whether we would see any objection to allowing (if bhe Company desired this) a technical expert representing them to aiscuss with the Petroleum Department the technical aspects of the question with a view possibly to convincing )ur technical advisers that there was some technical basis Company's cor the / claim for a further extension. He mentioned in this connection that under 'western practice' the Company 2onsidered that they could not reasonably be required to take out a mining lease until they were more satisfied than they were at present as to the position of the Bahrein oil structure. I said I would consult the Petroleum Department on this. Mr. Ballantyne was not quite sure whom the Company would nominate for the purpose. ]Vir. Hamilton would be a posdi^ility; alternatively they might send a man specially from America. I impressed on him the importance of urgency, which he appreciates. (I have since consulted Mr. Starling and/and with his concurrence have informed kr. Bailantyne that the Petroleum Department will oe glaa to discuss tne matter, hut that as it is one oi now great urgency any discussion should he in the immediate future). 9. Amendments in the mining lease * The conversation aid not justify a suggestion 'being made to Mr* Bailantyne that the acceptance of our mining lease amendments might form part of a Muia pro quo for the extension of the prospecting licence, but a casual remark on his part made it possible to raise the question generally. Arising out of it I mentioned that, as he was aware, we had a number of amendments to propose in the mining lease, one of which was not unlikely to be some modification of the arrangement under which the minimum royalty of Hs.30,000 might not become payable for a minimum of 5 years. Mr. Bailantyne said that he desired again to make the position of the Company in this matter clear. They regarded their hands as quite free as regards the mining lease. Any alterations must he the subject of negotiation. 1 said we appreciated this. On the other hand we felt that we had treated trie Company with considerable generosity in the past and had met them on a variety of points. We expected that they would be accommodating on their side in the matter of these amendments. The amendments were of two types - the first those which had for practical purposes already been Agreed with the Company, viz. the consequential amendment about oil production following on the amendment on that point made in the prospecting licence, and the amendments in regard to the maintenance of a Chief Local Representative, etc. which arose from the assignment of the Astern and General byndicate 1 s concession on 12th June 1930. The second category were rather diiferent in character. I could not give him full/- 6 - ull particulars of them at the moment. The majority were, thought, directed to bringing the mining lease into closer onformity with ordinary oil field practice, but there would robably be some of rather greater importance. ^ JWr• 3-llantyne said that clearly there was no if lie ulty abouo the first category. As regards the second, e had asked the Colonial Office so long ago as February for complete list of the amendments we desired in the mining ease, so that it could be considered without delay, whether r not a further extension was granted by trie Sheikh. They had ever received uny such list and he wished to make it clear hat the Company -would not be prepared to be jumped into flendments about which they were not satisfied. There would 3 uiought necessarily be a long period of bargaining on this abjecu which might run into many months. It was only common- tnat the Company should endeavour to get the best ^naxtions tney could in return for any concessions they made ) us. If they decided or were obliged to take out the Lning lease in December, thq/would, he thought, insist on iking it out on the basis of the mining least as at present .atea. Their position was quite firm In law. Any amendments i the lease could form the subject of negotiation at a later ^ate. I said J- thought The best thing would be that I tould without delay send hisa a full list of the amendments ' dss;Lre ^ secure and ask him to start on them at once; .trtlcularli H there was no extension it was most important ■ get the ground cleared before the mining lease period ■arted. He asked that we should give him the fullest possible formation as to the modifications we wished and that we ould, if all possible, proauce a comprehensive list to which/7 which no subsequent addition would oe made. I said that we voula hear this in mind. L2. British Drillers. I asked what the present position was Ln this matter. IvIr.Ballantyne said he thought there were now I or 8 British drillers or engineers in Bahrein. The Company ,vere fully alive to their obligations on this point. I expressed satisfaction. L3. B ahrein Govemiient' s claim for import auty on certain articles importea 'b.^ ^ for u^e of its emoloveefi . .Bushire despatch N o . jlxxu - o u ± ^th Auguso 1933). I hi^iefly explained the position of this matter to Mr. Ballantyne, (who seemed Q u i l e Lina v/ar e that any ciispute iio-d arisen,) and said jhat 'pr lnia, xacie the Bahrein Governments contention was ieaso liable. Ivlr. ballantyne seemed disposed to agree that this vas the case and said that in any case he quite realised ihat the 3iieikh v s financial position was poor and that •ustoms were very important. He thought it unlikely that they foul a wish to quarrel over a few rupees. I saia I would write o him on the subject. J.G. LAITHWAITS. INDIA OFFICE, 21st September 1933. &amp;. P.Z. f pp /, q I.. U ' r v.J !933 V , r —. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, 19, Moorgate, London, E.G.2. 22nd September, 1933. Dear Mr»Laithwaite, Thank you for your letter of yesterday 1 b date, I find there is available on forty-eight hours 1 notice, one of the Standard Oil Company of California^ Geologists with world-wide experience, who could discuss the conclusions arrived at by Hie Majesty's Petroleum Department with an Expert of that Department. The Company is of the opinion that such a discussion, based as it would be on the data in the possession of His Majesty's Petroleum Department, might well serve the useful purpose of convincing His Majesty's Government and the Company of the fairness of the views held by the other of them; therefore, I am to endeavour to arrange an appointment for Monday next. Any hour would suit if I could know by telephone during the course of to-day, Yours &amp;c., (Sd) H.R^Ballantyne. r.L althwalt e, Esq., India Office, Whitehall. S.W.I. Jeference P.Z.6015/33).No. 1317 -f? of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to Hie Majesty's Secretary of State for Indln, London. 2. The 'Forelpr Secretary to the Government of India, New I^elhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (fyy British Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRE. f ,a \— Dated... m j| $/ Reference to previous correspondence : ^ S u M V I Residency Printed letter Ho«lS75-n of 3rd October 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. /to;78 Letter No.C/455-10/l(IV) datL the 4th October 1933 from th? Political \^ent 9 Bahrain, with evicl&amp;aure8« Vt) Copy, with compliment a, Political Vent, Bahrain Subject. Bahrair Oil forwarded to the - for information.Note on visit to Oil Fielus on 2Qth October 1933. 1. The Bahrain Petroleum Company are erecting a new Rig No:6 between No :2 and No:2. Work started three weeks ago and will require another two weeks before drilling (non-rotary) starts. 2. Work will then be begun on the erection of another Rig (No:7) at a point near and to the north of No:2. 3. No more work is being done on No:5 (near Rifa^) where drilling had not been begun consequent on the find of water in No:3. 4. The plugging up with cement of No:3 progresses slowly. A fortnight is required for cement to dry before next test. Last test showed 15^ water,but the quantity of oil is disappointing and less than expectation.(2) 'V? /to/ /v File Nq :1 Q /1&gt; Y * Note * 2Qtii October 1933 * During the Agency At Home Mr.SKIMER asJced tor a lew minutes of my time. 2. He informed me he had received a long cable from Mr.BALLANTYNE (London) that morning. 3. He went on to say that the BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY were most anxious to have more time for prospecting. He (Mr.SKINNER) felt that they were entitled to another year under the Prospecting License. 4. In London there had been a Technical Conference which had,however,wandered from technical matters to the SHAIKH f s lack of money. b. His London Principals had asked him to try to find out what offer would induce the SHAIKH to grant an extension of the Prospecting License. They wanted 13 months from iind December 1933,i.e.,to end of December 1934. 6. They thought of offering:- (i) Rs.^5,000 as a cash present to the SHAIKH (non-recoveraole), (ii) Rs.7b,000 cash advance against future Royalties. V. The rent at Rs.10,000 per arirniin would continue during the 13 months,if extended. b. Mr .SKINNER went on to say that the Company were doing more than the stipulated amount of work for they would have three instead oi two ^strings' working until oil 'declared' (see Article X of the Mining Lease). 9. He said that the Oil Field would not be a commercial proposition until at least 1,000 Tons were extracted daily. 1,000 Tons § Rs.3/d per ton would give Rs.3,b00/- daily and2 say Rs.l^,y'/,bOO amiually as Royalty to the SHAIKH. 10. He reiterated his previous assertion that the oil would not compete with the ANCxLO-FERSIAN OIL C0MPANY t s markets in the GULF. It would be sent to AMERICA. There was no room for a second marketting concern in this small area# 11. I asked Mr.SKIMER to let me have this request for negotiation in writing and I explained that I would then at once inform the RESIDENT,who would instruct me in due course as to action to be taken vis-a-vis the SHAIKH. his 'offer' to writing,but I explained that he could word his letter in the way he had already put the matter to me. Without any 'offer' the SHAIKH would have nothing to 'consider'. The mention of reference to the RESIDENT and perhaps LONDON made him fear loss of valuable time. I reassured him and he understood the reason for my request belore leaving and agreed to send in a letter. 12. Mr.BELGrRAVE was then (20.00 hours) informed of the position and that I would not delay in referring the matter to BUSHIRE. Mr.SKINNER appeareu. to hesitate at committing 21/10/3o .A .M.Telegram:- R/27. No:- 476. Datea:- 21st October 1933. From:- Political Bahrain. To:- Resident Businre. ^ S./Lo'-M Last night SKINNER int'ormed me verbally that BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY consider an extension ol' their current Prospecting License essential. (2). LONLON Principals have re uestea him to 1'ind out what they can offer to induce SHAIKH to grant an extension of thirteen months (to ena of ti&amp;G). (3). In view of his need of money they suggcst:- (i) Rs.2b,000/- non-recoverable cask present to SHAIKH and, (ii) 75,000/- advance against future royalties. Recovery by arrangement. (4). Rental at Rs.10,000/- per annum would continue. (5). SKINNER was asked to submit in writing. (6). ADVISER informed orally. (7). Company most anxious to avoid delay and solicit early consideration by SHAIKH.S. ho; w-v THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. R. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrein. October Dear Sir: S. MO; . I have received telegraphic instructions from the London Office of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, to request you to advise His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrein that this company wishes to make the following tentative offer: In return for an extension of the Prospecting License for 13 months from December 2, 1933, to January 2, 1935, the Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited:- (1) will pay for the private purse of the Shaikh of Bahrein Rs 2 5,000 not recoverable, payment to be made in lump sum or in installments whichever is preferred by the Bahrein Government; (2) will advance to the public purse Rs 75,000 in 13 equal monthly installments beginning December 2, 1933, and to be recoverable from one fourth of any of the future annual royalties in excess of Rs 60,000; (3) should the company not apply for a Mining Lease by December 2, 1934, the Shaikh of Bahrein will have the right to a proportionate part of the regular annual rental of Rsl0,000, to cover the period from December 2, 1934 to January 2, 1935. The short time remaining before the expiration of the Prospecting License (December 2, 1933) necessitates prompt action on this offer. For this reason we are making the offer as simple as possible and in tentative form so that it may be discussed with the Shaikh of Bahrein and the interested offices of His Britannic Majesty's Government. If the offer is acceptable to all concerned it will be presented to you in a formal application. Yours very truly, r7,v&gt;/ Local Representative: Ti:^ BAHREiN PETROLEUM COMl-A.W LI Mil EL,S'./u-.d Telegram;- R/27. No:- 479. Dated:- 21st October 1933. From:- Political Bahrain. To:- Resident Bushire. My telegram of today,No:476. Letter containing 'tentative' offer receivea 11.45 hours. 2. Extension to be to 2nd January 1935. 3. Rs.75,000 to be paid in 13 equal monthly instalments beginning 2nd December 1933. 4. If offer acceptable to Shaikh and His Majesty's Government it will be presented in a formal application. 5. Copy of letter by Slow Mail.a-;, S. /Zo; /£ GOVERNMBXT OF INDIA. D epaetment. EXPRESS LETTER [N.B.—TMs is an ORIGINAL MESS A GE&gt; sent by post to save tele graphic expense and undue use of the wires&gt; hut intended to be treated, cyn receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and jormaUties it is icorded and signed as if it had been so despatched.'] 10X. • &lt;2^ Political, &lt;&gt; Bahrain. Bntconsul, BusHire. ^ 0/478-10/1.V* Qatea Xlst October \ I saw tiiree Water lower During visit to oil fields yesterday (20th October 1933)v . woric on erection of new rig No:6 (between 2 and 3). Work b^gan weeks ago and will take two to finish before drilling starts. 2. Rig No:7 will then be erected near and north of No:2. \ 3. Work on No:5 abandoned. 4. Cementing up of lower portions of No:3 progresses slowly, content improved to 15^ on last test but total quantity of oil than expectation. Political Agent, Bahrain. \ 1 . 6. 0!P0~?1, -573CCSP)DCF—(&lt;3 115) -7-5 C0 -4,00,000.3U v^' C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. No. C/480-10/1.V. •&gt; . /Zo ; f(^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Hoil T 'ble Persian Gulf,Bushire, the Political Resident in the/^nd has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. The Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 21st Octoher Reference to previous correspondence^ ^ Bahrain Telegrams Nos:476 and 479 of 21-10-1933. 1 9$ • • Description of Enclosure, 1. Name and date. I5SK of Note datea 21-10-33 on interview with Mr.SKINNER on 20-10-33. J, Copy of Letter dated 21^0-33 from the Chief Local ReoresentQ ative,Bahrain ^etroleum Company Limited. Subject. Bahrain Oil. Bahrain Oil.Telegram:- XX. No:- 3b8b. Received under Busnire No: Nil dated 21st October 1933. /i.io No: Dated:- 20th October 1933. Octo From:- Secretary of State for India, To:- Resident,Bushire. —^ S. Wo; *7 LT.oX. fS'£o). BAHRAIN OIL. Company yesterday instructed SKINNER to offer SHAIKH loan in return (for) 13 months extension (of) Prospecting License. Details so far as known with comment by tomorrow*s air mail. We assume SHAIKH will ask for our advice and will not commit himself until he has received it. Pending request for advice and information as to his reactions to offer (details of which please telegraph) we postpone fuller comment. 2. Company wish matter handled exclusively by SKINNER and no previous intimation of their intentions to reach SHAIKH through us. 3. LOCH might take opportunity of discussion with SKINNER discreetly to explore Company's intentions regarding refining further.S T /Lo i D.0.No:C/481-10/l.V. Political Agencj, Bahrain,the 23rd October 1933 Dear Skinner, I would be grateful if jou could see /our way to letting me have five spare copies on thin paper of all letters you write to me in your capacity of Chief Local Representative of The Bahrain Fetroleum Company Limited. Tou see copies have to be sent to 3USEIEE and LONDON and if they are submitted with the original letter much valuable time can be saved* USkinner Esquire, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Yours sincerely,No:C/482-10/l.V. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 23rd October 1933 Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge ^ J. /to /(* receipt of your letter dated the 21st October 1933,and to say that the matters raised therein are receiving attention. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant 4 nli* Political Agent, Bahrain. hief Lcpcal Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. 'CONFIDENTIAL. S. /Lo;j 3^ No. 1326-^ of 1953 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The I'orei^n Secretary to the Oovemnent of India, New 'Oelhi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment W/ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. v Dated... Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date., Political Resident's tele^rraw No.988 dated thr l^th Octoher 1933 to His MfijeBty'ii 55ecret|ary of State for India. Ow^ Subject. ^AlTRAllf OIL, Copy, vjith copy of encl-osure, forwarded, with corroliTnerts, to the '^oli^dcal Agerf, Bahrain, for information. \* k ^.^714: Telegram ^ ijyoTO 'Political Resident, Buehlre. ''q H.M. , b Secretary of State for India, London • Cow bv poet to the foreign Secretary to the Oovexnaient of India, »eif Delhi. No. 928. Dated the 17th October, 1933- S. SLo \ t * Tour telegrara of 3rd October, S45B. Before leaving Bahrain I had gained luiprei- slon, though not on any solid grounds, that Company pro posed to refine at any rate proportion of their output locally In order to compete for l^astern rnarlcet. 2. Gastrell on the other hand gathers from ^ S /to; b, recent conversation with Skinner that if found in any quantity oil nould be shipped to their large American refineries. Skinner spoke pessimistically as to prospect of large oil field. /n , V- 3* Adviser says that Shaikh has always looked forward to large refinery in Bahrain giving employment to his people. Shaikh would it Is thought readily confirm this. He has not actually made enquiries on the subject recently, but he no doubt would do so if he thought the matter likely to be under discussion. There is no objection to making formal enquiry from hlra on the subject. - RBSIBKRT \CONFIDENTIAL. No. 135P)-r5 of 1933. 4o 5*. /io: fUj. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to Political After?t , ^^bhralrr, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment/^ ^or In^omatl or), prHv. v IM British Consulate-G-eneral, (\ BUSHIRE. Dated, 20th October,1933, Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Ir^ia Office letter No. 6219/1933 dated the P9th Sent either 1933 to the Adni rait v. Subject. Hafepniards for lamlirp prronnds etc. in Bahrain.i \ A INDIA OFFICE, VrHITEHALL, S.W. 1- 60i u 1933 29th SeptemlDer 1933, Uty dear Seal, 7/ith reference to our discussion yesterday afternoon, I write to say that I have now gone through the previous correspondence with the Eastern and General Syndicate, or the Bahrein Petroleum Company, in regard to ¥ safeguards for landing grounds etc. in Bahrein. 2. The point appears to have heen raised in Air Ministry letter to the Colonial Office of the 13th May 1929 No. 3.28333/3.6. On the 24th Miy 1929 (No• 69035/29) the Colonial Office replied enquiring whether the Air Council had obtained possession of the site of the landing ground, hy lease or otherwise, or if not, in v/hose possession it at present was. They hinted that since the concession already granted to the Eastern and General Syndicate contained no clause prohibiting the erection of obstructions in the vicinity of the landing ground it might he difficult, if not impossible, at this stage adequately to safeguard the position. A. Seal, Esq., Admiralty, S.W. 1.1. The note of a discussion between the Colonial Office md ilr. Janson and I&amp;jor Holmes of the Eastern and General Syndicate on 19th July 1929 in connection with the desire of ihe syndicate to assign their rights to United States Interests (copy sent to India Office, Admiralty, etc. under Colonial Office letter of 3rd August 1929, No.69035/29) :ontains the following statement:- 'In the course of the liscusslon it was mentioned to the Syndicate's representatives jhat H.M.G. would require an assurance from the Syndicate ihat no steps would be taken which would prejudice the )osition of the proposed site for the landing ground and sea- )lane station, the precise location of which would be ;onimunicated to them in the near future. The Syndicate's 'epresentatives said that they did not anticipate any lifficulty with their American associates on this score and ihey promised to mention the natter to the latter at an Jarly date. It was agreed that in any letter sent to the syndicate setting out the conditions governing the fssignment of the concession a clause to the above effect should 'be inserted.' , . ^ P. The letter sent as a result of interdepartmental iiscussion to the Syndicate on 16th September 1929 by the , Colonial Office (No.69035/29, copy sent to Admiralty) remarked:' '3/I - 3 - '(3) H.M.G. also desire to receive an assurance from the Syndicate that neither the Syndicate nor the Company to which it is proposed that the rights of the Syndicate should be assigned, will take any steps which would prejudice the position of the proposed sites for a landing ground and sea plane station in Bahrein, the precise location of which will be communicated to the syndicate as soon as possible.' 4. The syndicate replied on 3 4th September (copy sent to Admiralty on 5th October by Colonial Office);- 'I note the contents of your letter of the 20th instant in reference to the site or sites for the landing ground In Bahrein and await your x urther letter on tftis subject as promised.' o. A letter of £4th October from the Eastern Gulf Oil Company to the Eastern and General Syndicate remarked that subject to certain exceptions which aid not affect the position of the landing ground 'the Colonial Office letter of r. x/xj) September 16th, 1929 is satisfactory.' 6. The Colonial Office letter of 3ra January 1930, No.6903b/29 (copy sent to Admiralty) finally stated that H.iv^Gr, noted 'that the Eastern Gulf Oil Company are prepared oo accept, save in ^ a s the specific points referred to -n their letter of 24th October are concerned, the conditions set out In colonial Office letter^/ 1 16th September last.' 7/, @) 4 - 7. In the light of this correspondence it seems, I think, fairly clear that we can claim that we have already secured certain undertakings from the Company in respect of landing ground and seaplane accommodation. On the other hand, as was mentioned yesterday afternoon, it is, I think, most desirable that, even if we mke a reference in general terms only to the area concerned in any communication made in the immediate future to the Company, we should be in a position, if they point out that it is now four years since we first promised an early communication as to the exact location of the areas in question and that it is unreasonable to expect them to wait longer, to make an immediate statement to them. 8» I am sending copies of this letter to Colonel • Turner at the Air Ministry, k Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAIIE.fa / U S. Ao; Js* P.Z. 6049/33# THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19, MOORGATE, LONDON, E. 0. 2» 23rd September 1933. Dear Mr.Laithwaite, I have to acknowledge receipt or your letter ^ S' &amp; S.AotSo- of yesterday's date, contents ox which I note. discussion. In the circumstances I shall not attend the Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) H.R. BALLANTYNE. Ga Laithwaite Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I,@) ^ ^ ,*S, /Zc' L49/33. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM C CMP ANT LIMITED. 19, Moorgate, V London, E.G.2. 25th September, 1933. Dear Mr. Laithwaite, Mr. Butterworth saw Mr. Starling and two Df his Colleagues this afternoon, but from what Mr.Butterworth bells me, the discussion was not confined, at any rate on the part af the Petroleum Department's side, to geology. The one important thing v/hich appears to lave emerged from the discussion, is that Mr.Starling and lis Colleagues did not deny it was impossible to select Intelligently 100,000 acres of oil lands on the basis of the Information so far obtained by the Company from its exploration and prospecting work. Therefore, I think it night be said that the result of the geological discussion vas definitely against the conclusions arrived at by the Petroleum Department and on which they gave their advice for the Shaikh of Bahrain to refuse the further extension of the Prospecting Licence. A further point, however, emerges from Mr. Butterworth's discussion, nemely, Mr.Starling with a manifest desire to be helpful, attempted to broaden the discussion so that it embraced matters which could not be said to be geological. For example, it appears from what Mr. Butterworth says that Mr.Starling enunciated the preposition that having regard to the time which had elapsed since the Agreement was first entered into, the Shaikh of Bahrain had not received the '^return' which he might reasonably have expected to receive. This does demonstrate, of course, that ther ie discussion was not purely technical In the sense of • t letter to me of the 22nd Instant end, with respect, It seras to me there was a 'calling-In aid' by His Majesty's itroleum Department of something outside geology to justify geological finding. There was a further remark by Mr.Starling which is been recorded, namely, that the selection should leave smething of a remainder for others: that statement covers principle which is definitely outside the scope of the real aestion which isjt Is the Company justified in its request )r an extension? Yours &amp;c., (Sd) H. R. BALLANTYNE. (t- .Laithwaite, Esq.. India Office, Whit ehell, S.W.I.P»Z«6149/ oo» r.OKrp 1 1DE NT IAL . Mntp nf a conversation with ]Vir. B &amp;llantyne of the Bahrein petroleub Ctompany at the India Office on 26th September. Mr. Ballantyne asked for an interview arising out of the discussions between Mr. 3utterv*/orth, the technical expert representing the Bahrein Petroleum Company, and Mr. Starling on the ^ouii bepteiiihur. 2 # On arrival he saia that in the light of Mr* Butterworth's representation of those discussions the letter which he now handed me (circulated separately) had heen written hy the Company. He had been anxious to present it personally so as to remove any feeling on our part that it was unauly argumentative or hostile in character. 3. After reading the letter I informed Mr.Ballantyne that I could not reconcile the statements in it with the report given me by Mr. Starling of his interview with Mr. Butterworth, ana indicated that the reply to the letter would take the general line subsequently/ adopted in my official letter to him, No.P.Z.6149/33 of 26th September, (copy attached). 4. After a brief further discussion arising out of this statement, I understood Mr. Ballantyne to indicate that the Company were not anxious to pursue further the question of the discussion with the petroleum Department or its results, ana that he now contemplated communicating further with San Francisco on the natter of the prospectarg licence. On this point he said that (in the light of the discussions which had taken place with the Petroleum Department) it seemed clear to him now that if the 'company wanted an extension of the prospecting licence they would nave to pay for it. Two forms of payment were pcooiole - a lump sum down or a loan to be refunded xiOx.. ioyaltius. The Company had always been extremely averse/- 2 - averse from the payment of a lump sura and he thought they were likely to remain so. They might he more favourably disposed towards a loan to he repaid from royalties. That was, of course, in the event of their wishing to proceed with a request for a further extension, as to which he could not commit thern in any way. I made no comment. 5. In the course of conversation I said that we were working on the amendments to he proposed in the mining lease. He said that on this subject we should find the Company 'nice hut as obstinate as mules.' They were sure of their ground in regard to the existing mining lease and if forced to take out that mining lease in December would certainly insist on taking it out on the basis of the existing lease. INDIA OFFICE. J.G. L^ITHWAITE. 27th September 1933.*P,Z .6192/33. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19, Msorgate, London, E.C.2. 21th September 1933. Dear Mr. Laithwalte, I have to acknowledge receipt of your letter (P.Z.6149/33) of yesterday's date, contents of which I note. I am forwarding your letter hy this evening's mil to San Francisco. Uie Company will no doubt let me have, in due course, instructions concerning tbe application for an extension of the Prospecting Licence. Yours sincerely, (3d.) H.R. BALLANTYNE. Laithwaite, Esq., J. '-JIX UV/ f • f India Office,' Whitehall, S.W. 1.p. z.6211/33. nnNFIDENTIAL Final. fififitiTi:?; Held at Qf-fTCfi Qn ^ j d ft r 6 amen Agent's . h-y ; 'r^i ' n petroleimi Hn^n^r^y ^ Tmm.n? le.asa. m There were present;- Mr. J .Gr. Laithwaite (India Office) in the Chair Captain H.E. Moore, DJ d. O., B.K., Admiralty; Mr A . EeA. Seal, Aomiralty; Mr. F.O. Starling, Petroleum uerHrtment; L/Ir. K.E. Johnstone, Foreign Office; and Mr. G-.Hi. Crombie, India Office. Hr. Laithwaite said that the meeting had been called to consider the amendments to be proposed to the Bahrein Petroleum Company in their mining lease. me views of the Petroleum Department were contained in their 'memorandum circulated to the interested Departments on the 2nd May, on which comments had subsequently been received from the Colonial Office, Admiralty and Inaia Officec Many of the amendments that had been proposed were apparently purely technical in character, and designed to cover points for which provision is usually made in oil mining leases. There were, however, certain others of major importance.•' In considering the action to be recommended it would not be overlooked that recent interviews with Mr. Ballantyne had shown that (particularly in view of the refusal of a further extension gratis of the prospecting licence) the Company were likely(g) 2. to stand rigidly on their legal position and to yield nothing of importance save in return for a qui d pro quo * Our legal position in the matter was weak, and, while having regard to the way in which we had met the Company on various points in the past we could reasonably ask for their co-operation, v/e could not in the last resort insist on having our way in any particular. While, therefore, we should of course aim at obtaining all possible concessions from them, it might prove desirable to concentrate on the points ,/hicn we regarded as of real importance, and to avoid overweighting our list v/here v/e felt on weak ground. Mr. Laithwaite added that the meeting would appreciate first that the question was one of urgency, and that, whatever might happen as regards an application by the Company for a further extension of their prospecting licenoe, it was desirable to let them know our desiderata without delay: secondly, that as Mr. Ballantyne had recently requested, v/e should submit a single comprehensive list to which no subsequent additions would be made. 2, Mr. starling mentioned that we had not meruly(ST) 3. extra given the Company an/extension by one year of their exploration licence and had agreec. to a revision of the clause in the prospecting license which v/ould have required them to take in respect of the area cone erne out a mining lease/as -soon as they had produced 100 tons of oil from a single bore hole, together with permission to use oil in the field operations. We had in addition decided not to press them fas we should have been entitled to) to mark out selected areas under their prospecting license. We might make play with this further point in any communication to them. 3&lt; The meeting proceeded to consider the amendments in the articles of the Mining Lease appended as the third Schedule to the Agreement of 2nd December, 1925 which had been suggested by the interested Departments. The text of the amendments proposed is given below under the respective articles. iiETIQLE T . Propocod amena^Tit. 4. After the words 'juch right, however, shall not include the exclusive right to sell such products within the leased area 1 ', insert the following:- 'ihe Lessees shall at their own expense forthwith erect and at all times maintain and keep in repair substantial boundary marks at the corners of the leased area according to the demarcation shown in the plan hereto annexed so that the boundaries of the leased area may at all times be clearly defined. n ■--r* ^tfurlmg. said that the amendment proposed was common form and that it was improbable that itsaocGptanoe would involve the Company lajmuoh expenditure. It was agreed that the amendment should be put for consideration to the Company. ARTICLE II . (last paragraph). Pro posed iiauendraent n 6, After the words 'At the expiry of the Agreement the ground and all immovable property left by the Company shall be handed back to the Sheikh'' add 'all productive wells and borings shall be handed over in good order and repair and fit for further working.' 7 # Mr. Starling stated that the amendment suggested by the Petroleum Department represented common practice and it was agreed that it should be put for consideration to the Company. aeticlk HI . Proposed AiuendmGnt . 8. After the words ,; In commercially exploitable quantities' add 'in addition to the amounts referred to in the preceding part of this Article the Company shall pay a royalty at the rate per ton provided in Article VIII on all net crude oil won and saved (i.e., alter deductmg water and foreign substances and oil required as fuel for drilling purpos.es in the Sheikh^ territories and for pumping to field storage)'. This follows the amendment recently made in Article IX of the Second Schedule to the agreement. ME j —Laithwaite said that it was not quite clear that we could assume that because an amendment on the lines proposed had been accepted by the Company in Article 9 of the Secorid Schedule to their Agreement, they would equally be prepared to accept it in the case of the mining lease since it apparently involved acceptance of an(S) 5. additional financial Durden over a longer period. 10. After discussion it was agreed that the aznendment might at any rate he put to the Company ana their reaction awaited. Articles III ana IX . Petroleum Department 'proposal . 11. 'It shoula he noted that the annual dead rent payable hy the Company remains at Hs. 10,000 per annum ior five years, or until the Company declares that oil has heen found in conmercially exploitable quantities, after which the dead rent becomes Rs.30,000. In view of the extensions which have 'been granted to the Company and the fact that oil has already heen proved m two wells, it is perhaps worth consiaering whether they could not he asked, in return for the further extension of the prospecting licence which they are now demanding, to make an annual payment of Rs.30,000 at an earlier date than that provided in the form of lease. as at present provided the Company need not make trie declaration until five years from the date of the mining lease.' 12. Considerable discussion took place as to the aesiraDility of suggesting to the Company the moaification proposed. Lr. Starling saia that since putting forward this suggestion he had given further consideration to the matter. Under suo-paragraph 2 of Article IX of the mining lease it was open to the shaikh, on the advice of the Political ^usiaent, to take the Company to arbitration over the ■-iUesuion oi commercial exploitation, and this action might 00 J u sti±iea after the mining lease had been in force for a ^oiupdralively short period. It was not of course desirable to throw any doubt on the rights of the Shaikh in this connection. .»ith the object of avoiding such a dispute it mi glit/6. might be put to the Company that some alteration of Article I a should be made. This, if it could be secured, might avoid the necessity for any alteration of Article III (See paragraphs 8-10 above). After considerable discussion the general sense of the meeting was that it would probably be desira.ole to indicate to the Company in general terms that while the Shaikh was of course entitled in certain circumstances to appeal to arbitration if dissatisfied, seme modification might make for smoother working without materially affecting the financial interests of the Company. It was generally felt that the proposal was not one that should be pressed if the Company manifested opposition to it; and that the terms in which it should be put to the Company (if it were decided to mention it in a written canmunication)would require careful consideration* Article V. 13. The Petroleum Department had pointed out that the meaning of the paragraph beginning 'If the Ccmpany's work is delayed by such events as are mentioned in this Article' did not seem very olear. It appeared as if the word 'of' has been omitted after the word 'expiration'. The Colonial Office had suggested that the Petroleum Department might suggest a revised wording which could be submitted to the C anpany. 14. it was agreed that it would suffice to suggest the insertion of the word 'of' after the word 'expiration'. Article VIII. Proposed amendments. 15. After words 'Rs.10,000 provided for in Article III' add (i) instead of 'for the customary operations of the Company's installations', say 'oil required as fuel for drilling purposes in the Shaikh's territories and for pumping to/(ii)/ @ 7. to field storage'. (ii) 'A royalty of 4 annas per 1,000 cubic reet of natural gas sold 'by the lessees and calculated at an absolute pressure of one atmosphere and at a temperature of 60 o P.' (iii) 'A royalty of 1 anna per gallon in respect of all casing head gasoline recovered and sold by the Lessees'. Note: - The form of mining lease does not contain any provision for royalty on natural gas sold or for royalty on casing head gasoline, which is usually charged Tor at a higher rate of royalty than in the case or crude oil. It may be that no sales of natural gas will take place in the case of Bahrein Island but as the Lease will run for a period of 55 years, it is desirable that it should include such a provision. (iv) Add to this Article provision for measuring cruae oil won for purposes of royalty assessment and for the keeping of accounts by the Company#- 16. (i) On the first amendment suggested in this article by the Petroleum Department Mr.Starling remarked that the point was one or some little importance which had caused considerable difficulty in Trinidad. It was desirable to make clear to what extent the Company weie at liberty to use, without payment, oil won in Bahrein. The amendment, which was being adopted in Trinidad, and was also in operation in a number of other countries would have the effect of restricting them to its use in connection with their technical operations and would dispose of any question as to their liberty to use it for the benefit of employees, etc. The meeting agreed that the amendment might be put to the Company.-8» (ii) On the second amendment it was pointed out that in the event of natural gas being found the provision in question would involve the Company in additional payments to the Shaikh. It would be better therefore to make sure of our ground before putting the amendment to them. The Petroleum Department stated that a provision of this nature appeared in both the Iraq oil concessions and that it represented nomal modern practice, although it was of fairly recent developnent. It was impossible to judge to what extent there was likely to be any output of natural gas now or later. The meeting agreed that the point should be put to the C cm pan y. {iii) On the third amendment Mr.Starling stated that while an amendment of this nature would admittedly involve the Ccmpany in some expenditure it represented normal modern practice, and might he thought reasonably be put to them. He recognised the probability that there might have to be bargaining with the Company both on this and on the preceding suggestion. The meeting agreed that it might be put to the Company. (iv) On the fourth amendment it was agreed that the the Company should be invited to add to/article provisions for these purposes. The provisions could be the same as those already included in clause 3 of the Agreement of 15th February X933 between the Shaikh and the Bahrein Petroleum Company, in connection with oil won under the prospecting license. The Company had been willing to agree to the insertion of corresponding provisionsin the mining lease at the time and had desisted from doing so only because K .M .G. had suggested that all mining lease amendments could 'best be dealt with together. Difficulty need not therefore probably be anticipated in connection with this amendment, which it was agreed should be put to the Company. Article 10. ■ Proposed amendment. 17. At end of Article add 'If the operations for winning crude oil shall be abandoned or discontinued for 12 months (except on account of force majeure or the causes specified in Article V) the Shaikh may thereupon give the Lessees notice in writing of such abandonment or discontinuance and call upon them to resume operations, and in the event of such operations not being resumed to the satisfaction of the Sh ikh within two calendar months from the date of such notice, the Shaikh may thereupon cancel and determine this Lease.' 18. It was pointed out that here again the effect of the amendment proposed by the Petroleum Department would be further to pin down the Company and that some difficulty might therefore be expected with them in connection with it. It was however agreed that it should be put to them. The customary and was amendment was/not in itself unreasonable, though the Company might of course not unnaturally prefer to retain its present freedom of action. Article 12. Proposed amendment. 19. At end of this Article add 'The Lessees undertake at all times during the continuance of this Lease to carry on all operations for winning and working crude oil and natural gas in a skilful and woriananlike manner in accordance with modern approved methods and to maintain all productive wells in good repair, working order and condition. The Lessees undertake that when any well is being drilled adeqiste means shall be taken to prevent any uncontrolled flow of cdl'.1 1Q, 20. It ms agreed that this amaiinent shoaldbe put to the Company.,. Arlaitional provisions. A. British Control etc * 21. The Company are hound under the terms of paragraph 3 of the Indenture of l^th June 1930, governing the assignment to them of the interest in the Bahrein Petroleum concession of tne Eastern and Genera- Syndicate to insert in the mining lease if ana when taken out the provisions set out in trie S^heaule to the Assignment in regard to the British character of the Company, the Chief Local representative, etc. No difficulty should therefore arise over this, though it would of course he desirable to draw the Company's attention to the point. Pro'posed aqqition . 22. Correct geological plans ana records should he kept, which should he open to inspection hy the Sheikh or his representative at all reasonable times. 23. It was agreed that this suggestion should he put to the Company. C. Pro'oosed addition . 24. The Company should at its own cost furnish an annual report of their operations, together with a plan showing the location of all wells drilled. They should also keep accurate records of the drilling logs of all wells, showing all casing inserted and any water horizons passed through. 25. Mr. starling stated that this suggestion represented common practice and it was agreea that it should he put to the Company. D. Proposea aaaition . -S. The Sheikh or his duly authorised representative snail tie at liberty at all reasonable times during the continuance of this lease to inspect and examine all11. vvorks carrisd. on oy 'thB Lssssss* Tii6 Lgss^ss sliall afford to the .sheikh all information which he may reasonably reQUire in connecoion vvitn aiiy such inspdCoion. 27. This suggestion also representeci coiiiiion pracoicc and it was agreed to put it to the Company* wiuii tna ^ri j1 tin n CJ' T in o •• r ri ■ ''' nr n 'i - 1 ^ulv onuiioriuoa roprc ocntiM 11 '—wit or tho aora—' oQ0 ikh 1 '—trid n^ct linet E. Proposed Audition . 28. Minerals, other than petroleum and cognate products, should he reserved to the Sheikh, who should retain the right to lease them to other parties, provided that the operations of the Company are not thereby obstructed. 29. Mr. Laithwaite pointed out that the substances for which the Company were at liberty to search were enumerated in Article 1 of the mining lease and suggested that there might be some danger that an amendment in the sense proposed would be restrictive. It was agreed after discussion that the amendment should be dropped. P. Proposea Addition . 30. The Company should undertake to offer no unnecessary or reasonably avoidable obstruction or interruption to the development and working of any minerals (other than petroleum or cognate products) including water and to afford to trie sheikh and to the holders of prospecting licences or mining leases in respect of other minerals reasonable means of access to such minerals for the purpose of working and carrying away the same. ol. it was agreed that tills amendment was reasonable and that it should be put to the Company. If accepted by them it would dispose of the point which the amendment discussed in paragraphs 28 ana 29 had been designed to cover.12. Gr. Landlnr Groun d. proiooded aa ^ition. 32. provision should be nictds in regard to keeping clear a landing ground ior aeroplanes on the northern extremity of Bahrein Island opposite to Luharraq Island near the W/T station. (See Air Ministry letter of 15th May 1929). The Air Ministry now intimate that it is desired to retain tl e landing grounds 'both at L-.uharraQ and ii^nama. The area required is not stated. 35. Considerable discussion took place on this question. Ihe India Cilice undertook to check the references which had been made in discussions with the Company or Iviajor Holmes in regard to landing grounds for aeroplanes and seaplanes ana the nature of any existing under standing with the Company on this subject; and also to ascertain what references had been made by the Company or by Ivajor Holmes to the intentions of the Company as regards the a re doing oi Khor Kali ya • It was agreed tnat tne admiralty should at once get in touch with the Air Ministry with a view to ascertaining what, if any, developments there had Occn in connection with the leasing of land for Government purposes in Bahrein; that the India Office should informally consult Colonel Fowle as to tne desirability ana practicability of ootaming from the Sheikh on a short lease the tip of land at Ras aiJasra. but that any reference to the Company on the subject of the mining lease amenaments should for the moment avoid specifying the Precise area we had in mind (since this was still uncertain) ,and should be on general lines and consist of a re£exe nce to the existing understanding as regards landing grounds and a statement that it was for sideraoion whether this slioula not be included in trie ana tnat we should in any case in due course inform ohv o0ITi ^ny of the precise areas affected.13. 34. Ths meeting took note of the fact tnat it was now u.esir^Q- t'O rcudin tx^e IciT],Qin&lt;^ ^-xouncis ootn at Iviuiiarrao and a t i'-i^nai/ia* H. x^-^iinin c 01: o il in Bahrain or British territory . 35» It appeared, that there was no inforaation at present available as to the intentions of the Company in regard to refining. It was possible that they might intend to refine at Bahrein, in which case it would 'be unnecessary to raise the point with them. On this / kr. otarlin^ stated that the usual practice of oil Companies was to locate their refineries as near the oil wells concerned as possible. Ivir. Johnstone pointed out that the Standard Oil Company of California might estaolish a refinery in Hasa which the Bahrein Petroleum Company might wish to use. He also referred to the fact the.o Captain Prior had mentioned at the meetinp: of 3rd I.iay Diiao the sheikn was inijerested in the Question of the location of the refinery (which would of course affect nis State as regards employment and otherwise). On the question of requiring the Company to agree to produce oil ^p oO A^iuiialuy specification, Lr.Starling stated tixat our evidence was to the effect that the oil suitabl^'f t TOm ? ne . BahTeln wells was good in Quality ouioabie for producing fu^l m'l i ^ 'oriQ/Qi tne right kfiid ior Admiralty use. On this assumption there should be no question of the oil i^rodu^d xailing to reach Admiralty specification axid it might Da tetter not to raise the point with the o-peuiy. The. meeting accepted Mr.Starling's view. Lie meeting agreed tnat while we were not In a itlon oo press sucu a demand if the Company refused 36.(6^ 14. it, particularly if, as sesmed possible, insistence on a refinery clause would involve the Conpany in considerable extra expenditure, it was of great importance if at all oossible to secure that the oil should be refined in Bahrein but that it was clearly undesirable to raise the point with the Company if they interded in any event refining locally. It was desirable moreover in any action we took to shelter behind the Shaikh. They decided to recommend in these circumstances that the India Office should at once telegraph to the Acting Resident to ascertain whether from his local knowledge of Bahrein he could throw any light on the intentions of the Company as regards refining, or whether any suitable opportunity could be taken of ascertaining discreetly how the land lay. The telegram should also state that we were anxious in informing the Company of our mining lease desiderata to say that the Shaikh had been enquiring as to the arrangements proposed and was anxious that the oil should be refined in Bahrein and that if he saw no objection he should endeavour to obtain the Shaikh's authority for a statement to this effect. I. Ri-^ht of pre-emption in time of war. 37. This subject was exhaustively discussed. The main considerations were that we had no legal claim to demand such a modification of the lease from the Company (the position was different in the case of Koweit where there was as yet no lease in existence and where we were free to negotiate terms of such a lease); that the Company were prima facie very unlikely in the circumstances to oe willing to accede to such a request; that there was15. the further danger that 'by raising the point at this stage in a case in which we were on weak ground, we might show cur hand prematurely, with unfortunate reactions on the position in Koweit, and possibly on British oil interests in other parts #f the world. On the other hand it clearly was of great importance that in the event of war we should be assured of control of Bahrein oil operations. On the assumption that the Shaikh was a sovereign and could in the event of a war in which he was our ally (a natural assumption) pass an ordinance on similar lines to those which would 'be passed in British territory taking over control (subject to compensation - which would of course have to be met by H.M.G. , and not by the Shaikh - to the lessee or other interested party) for the period of emergency over the oil output, etc., it appeared on the whole that the balance of advantage lay with trusting to the power and readiness of the Shaikh (advised by H.M.G.) to take action on these lines if and when the time came, and that it would on the whole on this assumption be unnecessary and undesirable, having regard to the considerations already mentioned, to raise the point specifically with the Company. 38. It was agreed in conclusion that the points discussed above appeared to c^ver all the points of importance to us and that it should be possible to present !the Company without delay with a comprehensive and iinal list of the amendments which we desired in the mining lease. I India Office, 3rd October 1933.?.d. 21, Part 5. Petroleum Department, (Mines Jepertment), Dean Stanley Street, Millbank, Westminster, LONiJON. J.wa. 4th October, 193b. Dear Laithwaite, I enclose, for your information, copy of a note of my interview with Mr. Butterworth on I have also sent a copy to Yours sincerely, (Sgd). P.C. STARLING. September 25th. Warner and Moore.7 4r s. fu -.zs HOTK 0'-' INTER? 1 KV.' 'VI 'JH HlTTTtRVVQTiTH. Mr. Butterworth, a technical expert of the standard Oil Company, of California, had an interview with Mr. Starling on Ceptember 25th, 1933. Mr. J.L. Jeffery and Mr. H.P.W. Biffard were also present. IjfTy. Ptarlin^ explained that this meeting had been arranged at Mr. Ballantyne's request in order that the technical aspects of the application nade by the Bahrein Petroleum Company for an extension of the prospecting licence for a further period of one year froa December next might be discussed with the Petroleum apartment by a technical representative of the Company. Mr, Butterworth said that was his understanding of the position. In reply to a question by Mr. Starling he explained that he had no direct knowledge of Bahrein. He brought no documents with him, and he did not appear to have been furnished with any of the Company^ geological reports or details of the well records. ife said the position had been broadly indicated to him, and he understood that he would be allowed to see copies of the documents which the Company had supplied to H .M. Government, tifi tarllfl^ accordingly briefly explained the position in regard to the Agreement which the Company had with the Sheikh, and Ir. But terworth was shown a copy of the Company's report ana a map of Bahrein indicating the position of the wells. After looking at the data submitted to him Butterworth said that, although the results obtained in the first two wells might be regarded as encouraging, a good deal of further and perhaps deeper drilling would, in his view, be necessary in order to define the extent ol the field and to enable the Company to make an advantageous selection of areas. For this he con. idered that a further extension of the prospecting licence woulu be rece sary. For instance, he thought it would be desirable/desirable to ascertain how far the oil zone extended in more than one direction. The results of further test drilling might for example, disclose whether it would be advisable for the Company to select ar part of their area one of the outside islands. He could only deal with the matter on general technical grounds in the absence of detailed information. Mr, .tarlingr pointed out that eight years had elapsed since the concession was first granted, five years of which had been occupied in geological exploration and three years under prospecting licence. This was certainly much longer than was allowed in other countries according to information available to the Petroleum jepartment, and Mr. Starling said he would be glad to hear 'r. Butterworth's views on that point and what the practice was in the United States. Mr, Butterworth replied that the periods differed as between one country and another, but it was not unusual to grant longer periods in the case of territories where oil prospect in : had not previously been carried out. He had not been in the United States for several years, and he could not state the present position there. He knew that some fairly long periods had been allowed in places like Alaska. He then asked what was our understanding o the kind of work which was expected to be carried out under an exploration licence and prospecting licence, respectively. —tarhnz explained that under an exploration licence the /oi c wa generally limited to a surface geological survey with shallow excavations (say to a depth of 20 feet) - this was the oasis of the present agreement. The object of the prospect in;- perlou -vap to enable such drilling to be carried out, to test whether the structures discovered by the geological survey \ vere in fact productive, as could be accomplished in the time available. In his view the prospecting period was not intended lo provide for an exhaustive drilling programe, and it was quite usual to lind that, after a mining lease had been taken out/out, further test drilling was necessary to determine the plan of commercial development. Ihe Petroleum department considered that, in view of the time which had been available both for the geological survey and the prospecting work, and in view of the amount of work which had been done when the Company furnished the information and which might be done between then and the end of December, the Company should be in a position to make a reasonable selection of its area of 100,O'X) acres without a further extension of time. y.r- Bntlerwor th said that it must necessarily take some time to correlate the sub-surface geology, as ascertained by borings, with the surface geology. In California, however, he knew of a case where three quite good structures had been mapped which were close together in the same field but of these two only proved to be productive. ihus, we could not place reliance on the results obtained by one or two test borings. He thought it was important in the interests of the Bheikh that the island should be developeu as a unit by one responsible company in order to avoid the evils of competitive drilling, a situation which might arise if the Company selected an area on the lain island and other areas on the adjacent islands. Starling.said that, judging by the plan of drilling indicated on the mrp, it would appear that the Company had reached some fairly firm conclusions as to the general run of the structure. Bahrein had more than once been suggested as a likely oil producing territory, and 20 years ago a report was aade which gave considerable details of the geology of the island and of the anticlinal structure tfhich was believed to exist there. This report could be found in the Geological Burvey Memoirs of India. !A: thanked r. Butterworth for coming, and said v. that he was glad to have had an o iportunity of exchanging views with him. (AINDIA OFFICE x 4&gt; S'■/lotus. Political Department ^ ' secretary of state Political Resident, Busblre. 6th October 1933. . . :.6020/S3. repeated Govemcient of Inal rel^i and Political Depurtii.snt. Bahrein oil. Paragraph Z oX recoru ol uiecuaeion with Ballantyne at inala Cilice on 21st Jepteaher, copy to you ana Croveiment ol inaia by air mail oX 23rd joptemher. we have no inlonuation here as to any private dealings between Holaes and 3heitch ol Bahrein or other jheikhs&gt; Fowle suggests however that political Agents concerned might be instructeo, now that iolmea no longer has olllcial positioi unaer Bahrein Petrolewa Cotopany, to convey tactfully to aheikhs ttiat, having regard to their coiurtitiBents to us, we expect them to inlom the Political Agent at once 11 uolmes Efakes any approach to them on any matter covered by their Agreements with us ana to avoid couBittlng themselves in uny way on such matters. It M ioeW I aii) avid The Issue ol the above has been authorised. (bd.1 J. C. V/ALT*-' I*THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 0. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 24, 1933. Captain E. Gastrell, H.B.M T s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Captain Gastrell; Reference your D.O.letter No J October 23rd. As you request, I shall be pleased to forward you five spare copies of all letters written you in my capacity of Chief Local Pepresentative of The Bahrein Petroleum C ompany,Limi ted. Yours sincerely,•X - ' — u y. /&amp;! *1. Telegram:- XX. No:- 968. Dated:- 27th October 1933. T.0.0:- 1521. T.O.R:- 1730. From:- Resident BusMre. To:- Political Bahrain. / a4&gt;'. /? v Your letter C/480. Please see Secretary of State's telegram repeated to you under my telegram of the 12th jnstant, No:941. ^ £. p J qi fC Your should communicate SKINNER's tentative offiner to SHAIKH and remind latter that His Majesty's G-overnment^nim to seek their advice and that he will not commit himself until he has received it.C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. No. C/493-10/1.V. /Lo Jl'j The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Hon'ble the Persian Gulf, the Political Resident in / and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. The Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 29tk October 193 3. Reference to previous correspondence. Residents telegram No:968 of 27th October 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and date. Subject. S,sic:ZS Letter ItoTc /490-10/l.V dated 28th October 1933 to H.E Shaikh Hamad bin 'Isa Al Khalifah,C .S .I. , Ruler of Bahrain. BAHRAIN OIL.u,c .it? (3 Air Mall. F.Z. 6727/33 My dear Fowl-, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I 21 OCT 1953 I enclose notes of conversations with '/ Bellantyne of the Bahrein Petroleum Company on 17th ' and 19th October, which are self explanatory. 2. In the Secretary of State's telegram of 20th October, No.2585 we promised to send you with these our preliminary cements. But on further consideration we think it better to postpone troubling you with any observations until we have heard the Sheikh's reactions to the American offer, and the precise nature of that offer, and have been able to consider with the other interested Departments here whether the Sheikh should be advised to grant the extension and if so, whether on the teiros suggested by the Americans or only in return for some improvement on those terms. N Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel T.C.W.Fowle, C.B.E., 3. The Residency, Bushire.i 3. A copy of this letter and of its enclosures Is being sent to the Government of India by today's air mail. J. G. LAITHWAfTE. '11 I - 'H 1Si nonfident ial. .Z ,6658/33. Note^ of a conversation with Mr. Ballantyne of the Bahrein Petroleum Company at the India Office on 17th October, 1933, Mr. Ballantyne had asked for an interview in connection with the Bahrein Petroleum Company's desire to secure an extension of their prospecting licence. 2. He said that he had. now received instructions from San Francisco which were to the effect that the Company was not prepared to make an out and out payment to the Sheikh of Bahrein in return for an extension of their prospecting licence. They regarded that extension as their right. At the same time they recognised that the Sheikh might be in some financial difficulty and I'r. Ballantyne's instructions were in these circumstances that they would be prepared (though not specifically in return for the grant of the desired extension) to assist him by making a loan, recoverable from Royalties. The amount of the loan was for consideration by the figure suggested by San Francisco was Rs.50,000. This Mr. Ballantyne thought too low to be likely to attract the Sheikh and, subject to the course of our conversation, he would be prepared to recoianend an increase to either Rs.l lakh or Rs. 150,000. There would be no objection to the amount in question being made partly payable to the private purse of the Sheikh and partly to the Government of Bahrein. 3. I said that as Mr. Ballantvne was aware we did/- 2 - did not recognise that the Company had any riglit to a further extension and that while it was no doubt important to save their face on this point in any understanding which might be reached in the matter, His Majesty 1 s Government saw no reason for modifying their view as to the right of the Company to the extension in question. Any arrangement reached between us must take account of this and there could be no question of our recognising in any way that the Company had any right in the matter. As regards the figure suggested, I agreed that Rs.50,000 would be unlikely to attract the Sheikh - Rs.150,000 might be more likely. As regards the private purse I thought there was much to be said in any payment made for allotting (as in the previous proposals put forward by Major Holmes) a proportion of the total to the Sheikh 1 s private purse. The proportion in the previous offers had been 50% but the position was different now as the Company were not offering a lump sum but a loan, recoverable from Royalties. Mr. Ballantyne would not overlook in this connection that a loan to the Sheikh 1 s private purse would be much less attractive to His Excellency that a gift and that there might also be difficulty later about securing its repayment. The Company might be well advised from their own point of view to so word their offer that any loan made to the Sheikh's private purse would be a loan in name only and would not in fact be repayable. 4. Mr. Ballantyne said that he would be quite willing to suggest a figure of Rs. 150,000 to the Company/- 3 - Company, two-thirds to be a loan to the State repayable from royalties, one-third to be for the private purse of the Sheikh without expectation of repayment. After considerable discussion on the question of the right of the Company to an extension he suggested as a compromise that the Company should ask for an extension of thirteen months. This would save the face of all parties. The Company were admittedly not entitled to an extension of 13 months (as distinct from 12).', and if they wished for it must therefore be prepared to pay for it, I said I thought that this was the best way out of the difficulty, 5, Mr, Ball ant yne said that the Company regarded it as important that the negotiation should be handled through the Chief Local Representative. I said we agreed entirely as to this. We had no desire to short-circuit the Chief Local Representative in any way. At the same time we should be grateful if the Company wouH keep us in close touch at this end with any developments in Bahrein or any instructiona sent by them to the Chief Local Representative, This might assist to smooth matters and avoid mi sunderstand- U. ings. Mr. Ball ant yne said he very glad to do so. He remarked in conclusion that the Company were anxious that the Sheikh should not receive prior information of the possible intentions of the Company and that his first information should come from the Chief Local Representative, o J.G.LAITIWAITE. India Office, '17th October 1933,$s P.Z. 6727/33. CC1I12M1ML office Note of conversation with Mr.Ballantyne of the Bahrein Petroleum Ccmpany at the India Office on Thursday, 19th Cctoter. I I \r i * i h; -i J Mr.Ballantyne asked for an interview consequent on the receipt of instructions from his principals in San Francisco in regard to the extension of the Bahrein Petroleum Ccmpany's prospecting license. 2. Ke said that as a result of his interview of 17th October he had telegraphed to San Francisco suggesting that an offer might be made to the Shaikh of Rs.150,000 in return for a 13 month extension of the prospecting license, one-third of the amount in question to be for the Shaikh's private purse without expectation of repayment and the balance a loan to the State recoverable frcm royalties. San r rancisco had, however, instructed him in reply that they did not wish to go beyond Rs. 1 lakh. The Company had further thought it well with a view to reaching a decision as to the offer to be made, to endeavour to ascertain from Major Holmes the approximate present private indebtedness of the Shaikh. Major Holmes had informed them that he estimated this at about Rs.10,000, that in his opinion a present of Rs.12,500 to the Shaikh would take him out of his difficulties; and that a gift so large as Rs.25,000 would best be \ paid in instalments if excessive expectations were not to be aroused in the Shaikh's mind. 3. The London representatives of the Company, after consideration of the matter, in the light of their instructions from San Francisco and of the information received/ / 11 ' III 1 ( fill2. received from Major Holmes, had now decided to instruct Mr. Skinner by telegraph to submit to the Shaikh an offer of a loan of Rs.l lakh in return for an extension by 13 months of the Company's prospecting license. Es.75,000 of this amount would be a loan to the Bahrein Government, recoverable from royalties, the balance of Rs.25,000 would be for the private purse of the Shaikh and would not in practice be recoverable. Mr. Skinner would, however, be given discretion to suggest to the Shaikh in what manner the loan to his private purse should be paid whether e.g. in tue form of a lump sum of Rs.10,000 down and the remainder by a series of'monthly instalments. 4. Mr. Ballantyne said that the Company had consulted Major Holmes, as explained above, in view of his knowledge of local conditions. They had not, of course, given him any information as to their relations with the India Office, which they thought it undesirable that he should know anything about. 5. I said that the Company's offer was of course one for tiie Shaikh to consider. It was only fair to point out to Mr. Ballantyne at the same time that the Shaikh was being asked to give a very valuable consideration in return for the sum now suggested by the Company. It was obvious that if the Company, as the result of this further extension of their prospecting license, were able to satisfy themselves, e.g. that they could cover within the 100,000 acres to be taken up by them under their mining lease all the material oil-bearing portions of Bahrein/3. Ealirein, not only would they probably have no interest in the 'balance of the island 'but there would be nothing left which would be likely to interest the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. On the other hand, if they were required to take out a mining lease at the moment it would be open to the Shaikh to negotiate both with them and with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in respect of a concession over the remaining area of Bahrein, Farther, the grant of an extension to the Company would of course postpone the increased royalties which would become payable to the Shaikh under the mining lease. These must all be factors in any decision reached; so far as we were called upon to advise the Shaikh it would of course be necessary for us to bear in mind all factors relevant to the safeguarding of his interests. 6. Mr. Ballantyne said the Company wanted to avoid bargaining in Bahrein. After all there was probably not much doubt now how the oil-bearing structure lay. In any case, they remained of opinion that they were entitled as of right to an extension of a: year. I said that vie had already made the position clear to the Company as regards the refusal of a further extension, and that in our view the Shaikh in refusing it had acted entirely within his rights. On the matter of bargaining the earlier sum named by him had seemed to me to be one more likely to appeal to the Sheikh and so reduce the prospect of bargaining. But the matter was one for the Shaikh to consider. feVE ice , (Sd.) J.G. LAITH17AITE. ^ Jctooer 1933.On the Srd November 1933 Mr.SKINNER callea by arrangement and discussed the question of the extension of the Prospecting License: and asked me to do what I coula to get an answer irom the SHAIKH as soon as possible. 2. He considered that the Company were making a good oiler ior this thirteen months 1 extension,because,he said, they were certain that the balance of the area aiter they had taken their 100,000 acres would be pretty well valueless and he did not think the Company would make any higher offer. / ^ c+wic* IL**- lr fe aslTea wnel ^nerlt^^^ssTole fI t^ / rriTe^t^ome arrangement whereby one could in verbal discussion arrive at a settlement of some sort agreeable to all parties before the matter was put into writing and ne particularly emphasised that matters siiould be initiated in Bahrain# I said that I thought that tne intention was that matters should be initiated in Bahrain and that the only reason tor London taking action direct between the Company and the India Office was due to the trouble over Major HOLMES. I said that the diiiiculty about coming to a verbal agreement tirst was that I had to put any offer that the Company made to the SHAIKH,who was obliged to obtain the advice of His Majesty's Government,technical or otherwise, beiore coming to a final decision,and it was hardly possible in the circumstances to do things by word of mouth. He appreciated that the 13 months' arrangement is a kind of face saving right round, but lie said that tne Company still regarded themselves as f entitled' to the further extension. I said that I would do what I could to get an early answer. llJ 4-11-1933. : : \CONFIDENTIAL. Noi7ft4-S of 1933. # r The Hon hie the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf presents his com pliments to Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch^I^A., -Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment m British Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRE. Dated ?. .. F 0 1^33. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Berni-off 1 cial letter No. 3 7P?..S dated the Slet Octobe]' 1933 to J.^.Lalthwalte IRsquii'e, 'Hie India Office, London. 1 Subject. BAHTUET OIL.CONFIDENTIAL. No.of 1^33. Ihe Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to '! 4 i ^he i&gt; olitical Apent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment W:\ -C ; - ' NO&gt; M -, XOV. 1933 British Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRE. Dated. 31pt October,1933 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. y H Name and Date. T Pdia Office letter dated the mfe October 1933 to the '^etroleun '^e-Dartment. Subject. 'Bahrain Oil.(Recel-vcd under Indift Office Printed letter flo.-P.Z. liiDIA OFFICE f WHITEHALL, S.*. 1. 17th October 19 t 53« ived Ire. My dear Starling, * I encloae a note of ay interview with Mr*Pallantyne this morning about the extension of the prospecting licence which, I thinlt, is sell-explanatory. 2* On the whole the arguments for agreeing to a further extension on the terms indicated are rather evenly balanced, but I think that if the Company put forward a proposition such as Ballantyne suggests we could reasonably advise the Sheikh to accept it* It is, of coarse, arguable that tne extension in question, to which the Company obviously attach great importance, may enable them to select for inclusion in the 100,000 acres to be taken up under their mining lease all the areas in Bahrein which are of value from the oil standpoint. II this is so the SMkh will, of course, be a loser since he would get no offer i for the remainder of his dominions either from the Bahrein Petroleum Company or from the A«P*0«C* But on tue whole the risk is perhapa one which may be taKen« This is mo e particularly the case aa firstly we know that local gossip in Bahrein, \ehich must have a certain effect on the 3heikh, has ratner suggested that our policy is directed to lavouring the interests of the A.P. ).G. rather than thobe of the Uheikh and his i amily and, secondly, we are quite in the dark as to wha i offer the A.P.O.C. might make in respect of the balance oi the area* Starling JSsq,, !l i'oleum Department, \3* From a dirierent standpoint there la the advantage in securing this extension that it will give us tiiae to negotiate with the Company the amendments we wish to secure in the mining lease* We might consider in this connection as you suggested this morning# whether we should not try to : et the Sheikh, if* and when the Company put up a proposition to him on the lines indicated by Ballantyne, to mention that he attaches importance to certain modiricatlons in the .aining lease which had been or would be communicated to the Company and that he would like an understanding thai the Company would be prepared to consider them Tavo iratoly# 4« I should he gratelul ror any comments you may have to make in general* 5* I am sending copies of this le ter to Warner of the Foreign Office and Moore at the Admiralty. If either you or they think it desirable to have a meeting to discuss the situation, we would airange that without delay* Youra# &amp;c* f (3gd. ) J.a. XtAlTiTSfAITS*1 &gt; f ; ' Telegram From To ^ NO. 2747. XX ru.c ^ H.k.'s Secretary of State for India. Po1 ui0 ^i... A8ent ' BahraiD ^f^L ag1% he'' f Datefl 7th I reoeived 8th ) Novemher, imesmst. 8 i^OV. 1933 :4 on behalf Ky telegram of Sra instant 2707. BAHixAlli OIL. Ballantyne to-day made signed representation of Company over delay in replying to thoir offer ^ i n*-.!(, (i/*v) communicated in writi ng tj^rough Jkinner on p .lst Lcto'cfr - to Political Agent, and hinted that failing decision hy November 15th offer may hava to he reconsidered. Please telegraph present position and Shaikh's reactions urgent- ^ 5* n*: 'to C v ) ly. As stated in my telegram of 20th Octooer, 2kBo, we wish Shaikh to ask for our advice, interdepartmental dis cussion will he necessary before this can he given, time is now very short. 2. As you will appreciate, it is desirable that I should be kept informed as early as possinle of course of events as otherwise my position vis a vis the Company is apt to be soxtewaat embarrassing. Please tberelore ke^p me in close touch by telegram with all developments. To save time, if you agree, Political Agent, Bahrrin, might be authorised in future to repeat direct by air mail, for information only, copies of correspond- [ ence with Chief Local representative or of his rep orts to you on Company's activities. -SSCKKTABY Or STATS FOR INDIA- . ;From Memad bin l£ :a ijjy P « • V r To r\ H.B.lTs Poli Bahrs After compliments. With referenc today regarding ti Bahrain Petroleum sion of the Exploi Your Excellency tl which is very impc we require informj the oil concessioi financial profit \ small amount of Ks until the Company found oil in comme quantities. Thei a Royalty of us 2&gt;/i ^rent of Ks 30,000/- 2. We ask i exploitable quanti have now drilled i well they found/oj that the oil whin! i'jFrom Hamad bin Isa al-Khalifah. To a Political Agent, Bahrain* fJ, After compliments. P,3tf f' &amp; * ^ With reference to our letter written today regarding the application of the Bahrain Petroleum Company for an exten sion of the Exploration License, we inform Your Excellency that there is one matter which is very important to us and on which we require information. According to the oil concession we do not receive any financial profit from the oil, except the small amount of Ks 10,000/- per annum, until the Company declare that they have found oil in commercially exploitable quantities. Then they pay to us a Royalty of its 3/8 per ton or a fixed ^rent of Ks 30,000/- per annum. 2. We ask what is commercially exploitable quantities. The Company have now drilled three wells and in each well they found/oil. It is possible that the oil which the Company has now found is a commercially exploitable quantity. Perhaps we might consider that the oil which they have found is a com- / u u j' - • ' X. ' » W ^ • • 9 &amp; • l/^»e&gt;j * | ^ »• • VsiLS.'jl &lt;AAy siS ' ' ' ' ' mercially exploitable quantity and the U ' l S ^ i ^ * ' Company might consider otherwise. We I i ✓ y* ^ LJs]^y request that the British Government will give us a definition of rt commercially exploitable quantity' : we enquire howhow many tons per da for this quantity, of great importance t we request His Britan government to conside to inform us on the s the Company will say, but we have no market that when a sufficien is found, then we sho benefit which we are Usual ending.-2- a, how many tons per day will be required for this quantity. This matter is one of great importance to our revenues and we request His Britannic Majesty's government to consider the matter and to inform us on the subject• Perhaps the Company will say, ^we have the oil but we have no marketbut we consider that when a sufficient quantity of oil is found, then we should receive the benefit which we are entitled to. Usual ending. Hamad bin Isa al-Khalifah. a Bahrain, Dated, ISth Raiab, 1352. 2nd November 1533. ^ cJ f ' oa^ f A*** ^ i ' \ ' uftjJdb ii/j • UlJ li AAthj UA) Z*JS\ \JjA&gt; I A&gt; ' ' ✓ | j'/uii f ^ 9 • — j &lt;j^ hitfijUjaSj ) £ gr m0 I ' • * 0 eft*** if A? SS&amp;x woc sJj&gt; c 903 C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. No - 501/10/1-V. ^3 &gt; fl/fy U** The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to ^0 Hon^ble the Persian Gull*. Political Resident in the / an ^ ^ as the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. T he A gency, B ahrain, P ersian G ulf. 9th November Reference to previous correspondence. D escription of E nclosure. Name and date. Subject. Letter No:C/500-10 /l.V dated 9th November 1933 to the Chief Local Representative,The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limitea. Bahrain Oil.COPY OF LTLTTER OTIGH WILL BI] DELIVERED TODAY. From Ham eel bin Isa A1 Kiialifah. 0^ To. K.B.M's Political Ajent, Bahrain• A-^ter compliments. \f ^r ff^ ojr pa- ^ ft Vitu reieruiice uo our letter written yesterday in which we Irequestou. a deii/iition of ' Gorjnercially exploitable quantity' we should be obliged if we could recieve a reply as soon as possible regarding the number of tons in one year needed for ' Commercially exploitable quantity '. Before we know this it is difficult for us to make up our mind regarding the extensioj of o;.e exploration licence. If the Company requires a larje number of tons for ' commercially exploitable quantity ' perliaps the Company will aay tiiat they cannot declare ' commercially exploitable quantity ' for a lon^j time. This time iixi^ht oe five years o.lthough it is possible that t^^ey -iuavc r3i i icent oil in t.heir wells before tixey declare. Usual ending. Hamed bin Isa A1 Klialifah. Bahrain, 14th Rajab, 1352 3rd November 1933.D.0.No:C/502-10/l.V Political Agency, Bahrain,the 10th November 1933. itiould you kindly send across as soon as you can the letter about oil of which we spoke yesterday,as we should like to telegraph to London about it today. balrymple Belgrave ^w juire. Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.From Hamad bin To H. B. M's I Balu After complimeni 7/ith refere written yesterde requested a defi exploitable quan obliged if we cc soon as is possi number of tons i Before we know for us to make u the extension of License. If th a large number o exploitable quan pany will say th mercially exploi a long time. T years although iFrom Hamad bin Isa al -Khalifah, To r H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. r- After compliments. With reference to our letter written yesterday in which we requested a definition of 'Commercially exploitable quantity tt we should be obliged if we could receive a reply as soon as is possible regarding the number of tons in one year needed for * oj 'commercially exploitablequantity'. Before we know this it is difficult for us to make up our mind regarding the extension of the License. If the Company requires a large number of tons for commercially exploitable quantity, perhaps the C mi ~ pany will say they cannot declare 'Gem-' mercially exploitable quantity for a long time. This time might be five years although it is possible that they will have sufficient oil in their wells before they declare. Usual ending. Hamad bin Isa al-Khalifah. Bahrain, 14th Rajab, 1352 3rd November 1933. * - v ^ j ul: &lt;^ui&gt; '-ii ^ j4j ' » ' * objk'ajd ' ** * f ^ ** ibti o/kiOj ^ L# i/ • 'u^- )-A '* ¥ ' • k' KH &lt;CONFIDENTIAL. I No. 0/124 Of 1933 foZ j The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Office of the Political Besident, in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, The Political Agei ,11th Novemher 1933. Dated' Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Telegram No.2707 dated the 3rd November 1933 from Secretary of State for India Bahrain Oil 'iii\Telegram XX Pro in H.M.'s Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Eesident, Bushire. Godv sent 'bv Air Mail to Gov eminent of India, New Delhi. No.2707. Dated 3rd (received 4th) November 1933. IMPORTANT. Your telegram of 21st October, 944. Bahrain Oil. Has Company's offer 'been communicated to Shaikh and if so with what result? - Secretary of State for India- i ij. -f'11 ■ CONFIDENTIAL.* No. 0/125 of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Foreign Secretary to the Oovern ment of India# New Delhi. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the- undermentioned docu ment W Office of the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, 1 a te cl -i -i -t h • ^ o v em* 3. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Political Resident's tele gram Ko.T/99 dated the 10th November 1933 to Secretary of ^tate for India. Subject. BAHRAIN OIL. L 1} 0 i; ;■[ r(9, L telegram iX Fr ok . Political Beslderit, at Bahrain, To oecretiiry of '&gt;tat« for inciai lonaon, Copy by Air Hall to Oovomaent of Znaia» Hav Delhi. Ho« T/99. Dateu the 10th KoveiaBsr 1933. P.f? lour telegran 2747* BAHHAIN C1L» * il) Sallantyne's representation ana threat re; ffoTMhw 15th would aeeja to iDdicato that Ca»^apy are try log to rush ua. That tiae is ah^rt la la ely due to Compaay v 6 delay in putting in an ofier 9 ano I venture to aug(;eat that this he brought to Ballantyne^ notice. Cospatv ahould rea^ber ttiat they are dealing not with a huaineaa concern hut with an Arab Shaikh who requires ample tine for cogitation# (2) If negotiations aatiaractory to che ihaikh are not concluded hy 2nd Dco^mber latter could jreauaaDly extend period of prospeotm&amp;lioence as a favour to the Jo&amp;pany for further short period say one month to that agre ^neut Aieht l &gt;e reached. j) ^ 7 id iitAlkb's repl/ has just Dean reoelvad. .-.'a a a da not wish to acospt Company* a offer oontt .neo In ^ ^vcv nu&amp;+. l aihi ■jr talagram 943 of 2l»t October, hut 1b willing to - i canal'.ar It If the ;.a.75,000/- for Batj-aln Oovarnment 1 *8 well aa Hs.23, COO/- for hlseelf is a gift ant not a 1# '' J (4) JUaikh also ralaea qu«tion of ^oosu eroialiy exploitable Quantities* and asks for a definition of this from His Majesty's aovernaent# He states that 1e finds difficulty/CONFIDENTIAL. - ^ N) ' 0/126 of 1933 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Mon'ble Major A.K.Fraser-Tytler, M .C., Ofticiating Foreign Secretary to the Gov em men t of India, New Delhi. 2. Lieut.-Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Office of the irolitical Ee^ident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp. Bahrain, Dated . 11 .t h. Jla aa X)UX.. Reference to previous correspondence : ^Political ^sident's Printed letter to. ' 0/125 dated the 11th Novem ber 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Telegram No.T/100 dated the ICth November 1933 to J.G. faithwaite Esquire, the India Office, London. Subject. Bahrain Oil. $v /inthe Bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 12, 1933. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: I acknowledge with thanks your letter No. C/500-10/l,V., in which you advise that you have received the views of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad Bin Isa Al Khalifah, regarding the Bahrein Petroleum Company's offer for an extension of the Prospecting License for 13 months frcm 2nd December, 1933, and that the advice of His Majesty's Government is being sought by telegram. Owing to the short time remaining before the expiration of the Prospecting License, it is obvious that the Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, cannot keep this offer open for many more days. I shall appreciate any information you can give me regarding the present status of the matter. Yours very truly, E. A. SKINNER, (jl,. ' f. nepresenta'S''?* TUB QAHRl •' PBT&amp;CtL&amp;U¥ COMfA: Y ball' CONFIDENTIAL. No. , V133 Of 1933. I ho Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1* His Majesty's oeoret^ry of State for India, London. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Govemaie t cf India, New Delhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). Office of the Political .Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain* British Consulate-General, xxmxxxxixxx*^ fttre XXXXXXXX Dated.... mii ■ mwaii ■681* • • rsrss. Reference to previous correspondence : P4o ir 'Io(l) Political i &lt;esiQent*s telegram i &lt;c .T /99 BB/ aateci iOth Novemwr 35, ^ To(2) ^ 'Printed let er Ko*C/l2o Description of Uth NoVemoar 15S3. Name and Date. 1. Letter dated the 2Qd Novemher 1933 from the Shaikh cf 3abra r -, to the Political Agent,^ahraip. 2. Letter dated tt&gt;e 2no Kovember 1933 from the Shaikh of Bahra s. irom the shaikh or iJaora Ln to tae iolitical Agent,Bahrain. Bahrain Subject. - -etter Ho. O/MO-lO/l. v f dated 9th November 1933 from the Political Agent ,Balirain, to 3hfcef Local itepresentative, ^ahrQin Petroleum (Jompany, Bahr; in. the t ae dll. Copy, with compliments, forwarded to Agent, Bahrain, for information. the Political yC's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. No. C/507-10/1.V. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the HoUOUrabl , Persian Gulf. til© Political lies id en t in the /and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. T he A gency, B ahrain, P ersian G ulf. 14 tli itoTemherL Reference to previous correspondence. D escription of E nclosure. Name and date. Subject. Letter dated the 3rd November 1933 from Eis Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin 'Isa Al Khalifah, C.S.I. Bahrain Oil.j C % C's. P. P.—L (m) 980—300-12-29—c. N0 .0/508/10/1-V. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments tothe Honourable Persian Gulf, the Political ruesident in thej^ and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. T he A gency, B ahrain, P ersian G ulf. 14th NoTemher. Reference to previous correspondence. '33 Bahrain Printed Letter No:C/501 dated 9-11-1933. D escription of E nclosure. Name and date. Letter dated the 12th November 1933 from the Chief Local Represent ative. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd. Subject. bahrain oil. |l 11 m{Jo:C/509-10/l.V. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 15th November 1933. To, The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Lear Sir, In continuation of my letter No:C/500-10/l.V dated the 9th November 1933 I beg to inform you that I have been instructed to communicate to you His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin T Isa Al Khalifah ? s reply to your Company r s proposal as set forth in your letter dated the 21st October 1933. I enclose,therefore,the letters noted in the margin 1. Letter of 2-11-193^ from H.E Shaiich Hamad bin T Isa Al Khalifah. 2. Letter of 2-11-1933 from H.E.Shaikh Hamad bin r Isa Al Khalifah. 3. Letter of 3-11-1933 from H.E Shaikh Hamad bin T Isa Al Khalifah. and shall be glad to have your Company's views in due course. Yours faithfully, Ijt '~^ 00000 Lieut-Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. November 15, 1933. Els Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: ^ . to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. 0/509^10 /1.7. of 15th of November, 1933, with #iich were enclosed three letters from His Excellency shaikh Hamad bin ^ba al Khalifah, in reply to my Company's r proposal which was set forth in my letter dated the Slsf^J. to'/o of October, 1933. I appreciate very much your sending these letters to the camp by a special messenger. Yours very truly, xu. -rt. • SxLL* ~Benresen7' S. Ndvember 15th 1933 (16,45 hrs) I Dear Mr Skinner, ^3 Very many thanks for your letter of the 15th Nov ember 1933 (16*00 hra). As time is short t I am not awaiting your formal confirmation , but write to say that, with regard to the time factor toft which your Company emphasize , the Adviser to the Bahrain Government informs me that His Excellency Shaikh Hamad ,who nas already considered the possibility of the negotiations being prolonged , is prepared to allow an extension of the Prospecting Licence for one month from the 2nd December 1933 » without prejudice , so that the negotiations may be completed without undue haste# I should be grateful if you would telegraph this to your Company as soon as possible. Yours trulyt 1A— Lieut, Colonel Political Agent , Bahrain. P«3. I presume that you have commtoicated to your Company the reply of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad , which was sent to you with my letter No»C/509-10/l»V of the 15th November 1933CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/140 of 1933. j. ^o /xr. 1 he Hon bio the Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and lias the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). for information. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Camp, Bahrain, Utaittab: € ao&amp;ia kitOr G encr ad, mmmsm Dated. ASM. 33. Reference to previous correspondence ; Political Resident's Printed letter N o. G/133 i UV • .4/ November 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. !• Telegram Wo.2810 dated the 13th November 1933 from Secretary of State for India. 2. Telegram No.2815 dated the 14th November 1933 from Secretary of State for India. 3. Telegram No .T /104 dated the 15th November 1933 to Secretary of State for India^ Subject. Bahrain Oil,1? 12^ -3- Ballantyne intimated that there would be at once coiniQunloated for consideration to i&gt;an Francisco. 6. tie should like to raise with Company question of what arrangements they propose with regard to refining. Do you see any ohjeotlon to this or would you think it better for Loch to raise it on Shaikh's 'behalf with Skinner? 7. Your demi-official of October 31st, 1782-3 paragraph 2 construction (a) is correct. i- n - Secretary of State for Inula - &lt; r3./ Telegram Jrom 86/2 XX. H.lPs Secretary of otate for India, London, To Political resident, at Bahrain. Copy t)y air Government of India, 'oreign &amp; Political No. 2810 Department, Hew Delhi. Dated 13th received 14th November 19S3. P- L 0 Yovr telegram of the 10th ilovemher, I o. T/99. Bahrain Oil. Communication suggested in your paragraph 1 was made orally to-day to Ballantyne who was informed that we should however he prepared to recommend to Shaikh to grant, subject to any legal formalities f an extension [ to form part of any extension which might subsequently be granted of prospecting lioenee ) not beyond the end Ol/ of the present calender year for purposes of negotiati- -atlons only should this be necessary and Company apply for it. Ballantyne was also informed that Shaikh regarded Gompany^s offer as financially unsatisfactory but that we could not give him details, which would be oommunicated direct to skinner and that His ^Kcellency ^ad also raised question of commercially exploitable quantities. Points of interest to him in this connec- -tion were presumably (a) definition of phrase occur ring six times in mining lease (b) modification in lease to secure that payment at rate of Bs. 30,000/- fell due within leeeer minimum period than five years i e.g. two years )3. Ballantyne said that San Franclsoo would have to he consulted on all points. He thought it likely they would apply to take out Mining Lease on Decemher 2nd (this may of course he hluff). Speaking personally, he thought request for advancement of date from which Kb. 30,000/- would 'be payable was not unreasonable and that Company would prohahly at proper time,i.e. in connec tion with amendments to Mining Lease, be preparec to consider it. He douhted if they would regard it as a fair demand as part consideration for extension of Prospecting License. 4. He was informed that it was for Compfiny to decide whether or not to take out Mining Lease on December 2nd and that you would he requested immediately to arrange for communication to Skinner of Shaikh's reaction to Company's proposals I? in the sense) of paragraph 5 of your telegram of 10th November. Please take necessary action. Company in this connection have in the past been reluctant to agree to lump sum payment and Shaikh migbt as alternative ask for increase of loan to State by, say, Rs.26,000/- or even i:vS.50,000/- and might perhaps stipulate that amount not to be recovered should be increased to, say, half of total amount Uncludirg gift of Ks.25,000/- to Shaikh) to be advanced by Compfcny. 5. Amendments in Mining Lease set out in enclosur|j to draft letter to Ballantyne sent by air mail of November 10th were communicated to Company on 11th with otiission of proposed alteration in Article X and with verbal modifi cations in last paragraph of I mut.) letter. i i Ballantyne/no 11 C* Telegram From XX Secretary of State for Inaia, London* To Political Besideotf at Jdahraln. No. 2315. Dated and recelTed the 14th November, 1933* mmm Uj telegram of 14tti Instant, 2810* Ballantyne states that Jan Francisco have replied they will give any assurance as regards Intro duction of ii8«30 f 000/- royalty after two years (though not in terms of in return for an extension of prospect- ing License) hut are not prepared to increase financial offer in any way, Skinner is ieing so informed to day. I&amp;iling acceptance hy Shaikh they will apply for fining Lease on HovemDer 18th. Telegram giving advice of Petroleum Department as to line to be adopted hy ohaikh follows immediately. - Secretary of State for Incia -ft! 1 CONFIDENTIAL. No C/143 of 1933. s*. to-.ZC, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to 1* The foreign 3«oretary to the Crover^m nt oi towns* 'sifti. 2* iiis kajesty*s secretary of 'tata for IncLxa 9 London* and 1ms the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). *5 Dffice of the lolltical Resident in the Jeraian Uulf, British Consnlate a m*af? ahr!iin ' XXIXIXXIXIIXX^gjjjg xxxxxxxx Dated lath. ^av^u.tea:,. 1 ^Political Resident # s Printed letter *»c. C/X53 of 12th November 1933. Description of Enclosure. : r*/ fivj Reference to previous correspondence : Name and Date. Subject. U letter dated the 3rd Ilovexaher [ 1333 from the Shaikh of Bahrain* 2. Letter dated 12th November 1932 irom tLe Chief Local ^epres.enta- tivQjiiahrain iretroleum Company, K m 0 Political Agent,.Bahrain. Xeiegram Ko.2dl5 dated the I4tt &gt; | November 1933 from ills Majesty's ♦ wecretary of otate for India/ lalegram i;o.T/l04 dated the 15tih Sovemher 1933 to His Majesty's secretary of 3tate for India. Bahrain Oil (1) only* L u! n Copy, with compliments, forwarded to the / Political Agent, Bahrain, for information.^The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 15, 1933. . V His Britannic I'aiesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: Confirmins my letter of the 15th of November, 1933 (6 r. &gt;T .) I have been instructed to notify His Excellency Shaikh Hamad Bin Isa Al Khalifah that The Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, because of the time factor involved, finds it necessary to withdraw its offer for an extension of the prospecting license dated October 21, 1933, if the offer is not accepted by llovember 18, 1933. Eovrever, if the offer is accepted, the company will be willing to f^ive assurance that beginning at the end of the second year of the life of the !:ining Lease His Excellency Shaikh Hamad will receive at least 30,000 rupees per annunu./ It should be noted that the above does not'alter the provisions of the second sentence of Article X of the Tiining Lease. The above is The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited*s answer to the reply of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad, vhich was sent to me with your letter No. C/509-10/1.Y. of the 15th of November, 1933. Yours very truly. E. a. SKINNER B ( /.. f Lncfil Reiresentativs: : / aurzli peiroleum comta:\y limited.The Bahrein iu&lt;i Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. November 16, 1933 Lieut-Colonel a. Loch, H. B. Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Colonel Loch: /pi'* Many thanks for your letter of November 15, 1933 (13.45 hours) in which you advise that His Excellency Shaikh ^amad having already considered the possibility of the negotiations being prolonged, is prepared to allow an extension of the Prospecting License for one month from December , 1933, without prejudice, so that the negotiations may be concluded without undue haste. This information is being passed on to The Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, by telegram. Yours very truly, E. A. siain^a, 1 cat Bepresentat. ■ 'c.TRGLLc.vi CuA B11 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 17,'1933. His Britannic ?'ajesty f s Political i^ent, Bahrein. Dear Sir; (jW I acknOTled^e with thanks receipt of your letter No,0/511-10/1.v. Please bp/Tnformed that His Excellency Shaikh Kamad Bin Jsa Al Khalifah's^answer to our offer which was enclosed with your letter No. C/5CS&lt;10/l.v. dated the 15th of ITovember, 1933, was telegraphed to my Company immediately after receipt on the morning of 15th of November, 1933. the short time orr-lind -'CTolohe 1 -1 owl e I am sorry that His Excellency is displease! b given him to decide on our offerv* ine'g^t^N , ^ _ ^ £ yesterday, the necessity for has^^t l^r^inad only by the fact that the Prospecting License will expire on the 2nd of December, 1933. The Company must have a few days in which to present the application for the Mining Lease, if our offer is not accepted. ^ill you please advise His Excellency Shaikh Hamad that I have telegraphed all details of the matter to both our San Francisco and London Offices, and in order to allow time for their answer to His Excellency's offer to extend the Prospecting License for one month to January 2, 1934, we will hold our offer open until the 21st of November, 1933, instead of the 18th of November, 1933, as was advised in my letter of November 16, 1933. Yours very truly. -il) . At SILIIvijER, Ckt# l*vcnl THE mAHkETN PE TRCk jltMUCPM/MAY Ji )S The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Hon'tie the 10 r.-l-t- T r •• * ers i ai:1 G u ll'» Political hesident in the/ and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. T he A gency, B ahrain, P ersian G ulf. C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. Nr. No. C/514-10/1.V. 18th NnvemtiRr [ 933.. Reference to previous correspondence. )rrespoudent .... Bahrain Printed Letter No:C/508-10/l.V of 14-11-1933. D escription of E nclosure. Name and date. Subject. 1. Letter dated 15-11-1933 from the Chief Local ,eBresentative,The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd. 2 .D.0 letter dated 15-11-33 from Colonel Loch., 3.Letter dated 15-11-1933 from the Chief Local Representative. 4.Letter dated 16-11-33 from the Chief Local Representative. b.Letter No:C/511 of lu-11-33 from the Political Agent.Bahrain. 5.Letter dated 17-11-1933 from Chief Local Representative. '/.Letter No:C/512 of 17-11-1933 to the Advi Bahrain Government Bahrain Oil. -do- - do ll | 1 ' i I. rio The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, BETiDIATE November 18, 1933. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: ■?ith reference to our offer for an extension of the Prospecting License to January 2, 1935, as set forth in my letter to you of October 21, 1933:- I am no77 instructed to inform His Excellency Shaikh Hamad Bin Isa Al Khalifah that The Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, will, in addition to the 25,000 rupee non-recoverable payment to his private purse, also make 25,000 rupees of the advance to the public purse non-recoverable. Furthermore, if the offer for the extension of the Prospecting License to January 2, 1935 is acceptedjthe Company is willing to give assurance that beginning with the year 1934, His Excellency Shaikh Hamad will receive at least 30,000 rupees per annum, but it should be thoroughly understood that the guarantee of such minimum payment does not constitute minimum guaranteed royalty under the Mining Lease, or a declaration of oil in commercial quantities within the meaning of Articles IX and X of the Hhird Schedule to the Concession Agreement of December 2, 1925. 1 The offer for the extension of the Prospecting License to the 2nd of January, 1935, as set forth in my letter of October 21, 1933, and altered by subsequent letters, can only be held open until 6 p # M. November 21, 1933. Yours very truly, iii • A» Si'drHIER, Ch 'cf T joccl I liepvcsp.'ntciti'Vfi • THE LAliRZIN PElROLSJJki b(jo- ' The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 13, 1933. Lieut-Colonel g. Loch, w . B. M's Political Agen Bahrein. le are making preliminary plans for shipping oil through a submarine line which will run from a base on sitra Island to the deep water just outside the entrance to Khor Kaliya. We plan to have ships enter this deep water anchorage by approaching the north-east corner of the Island of Muharraq, and from there passing down the deep water channel on the eastern side of I'uharraq, a certain number of buoys will be necessary to mark the channel; also detailed soundings will be needed to make certain there are no shoals or sand banks. (') Recently, H. M. S. 'Ormonde** did some very detailed work in this particular area, and T am wondering if it would be possible for us to obtain the full detail of their work without waiting for it to appear in print on the regular Admiralty chart forms. A 1 so do you think the s.s. ^learchus'-would consider making a marine survey for us, if this is necessary in addition to the information from F.M.S, ^Ormonde' ? Would they consider setting the channel buoys ? Could you advise me what permits, both from Fis Majesty's Government and fro^ the Local Authorities, would be required before we could undertake such a survey and install the necessary marine facilities ? I have some maps and charts partially covering this entire matter, and also considerable data which we have already worked up, and would be pleased to discuss all of this with you at any time. Yours sincerely,CONFIDENTIAL. N o .G /147 of 1933# The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s ).for information. a 11 S! /£&lt;&gt;? 6&lt;? Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, Dated i^th Novemher 19 33 Reference to previous correspondence : « w 1*,' Polit&gt;&lt;Sal Hesident's Printed' letter No. if/ 0/142 of 15th November 1933. ^ &gt;3' Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. J )1. Telegram No.£824 dated the 14th November 1933 from Secretary of State for India 2. Telegram dated 15th November 1933 to Secretary of State for India, 3. Telegram No•2330 dated the 15th November 1933 from Secretary of State for India 4. Telegram No.2832 dated 15th November 1933 from Secretary of State for India. 5. Telegram No.T/l05 dated 16th November 19 33 to Secretary of State for India. Telegram NooT/106 dated Idth November 1933 to Secretary o State for India. •* Telegram Nc«T/l07 dated 17th November 1933 to Secretary o State for Indiao Subject. Bahrain Oil- C fn Telegram XX From H.M.•s 3eoretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, at Bahrain. Copy T oy Air Mail to Crovernment of India, Kew Delhi. No.2324. mm . ■ \ &gt; v [if i y Bated i4th { received 15th ) Nov amber 1933. , 1 a Jo^) / ,... /&gt;■ (^ My telegram of 14th November, 2812.) BAHRAIN OIL. Ballantyne has now officially confirmad offer of undertaking ahout minimum royalty. He emphasis ed that undertaking ia) is not to be treated as part compensation ior extansion aau to be dealt with as an agreed modification of form of leaiie; it)) will not in any way affeot existing provisions in Mining Lease about ^commercially explottaDla guantities'* save to extent that payments at increased rate of xvs.30,000/- will 'begin at end of second year of fining Lease. Shaikh's remedy if dissatisfied witu delay in declara tion of commercially exploitable production would, as at present, lie in appealing to arbitration. 2. In favour of acceptance of Uompany's revised offer are facts that ia) shaikh unaer it will secure what we understand is of importance to him - lump sum down; ih) he will secure non-repayable .^3.60,000/- ibeing difference over a three-year period between Bfi. 10,000/- and xvs. 30,000/-) if declaration of commer cial produotion is delayed for full period of five years in addition to Hs.100,000/- already offered; ioj extension will give more time and may produce better/ II I-2- 'better ataosphere for bai 'gaining for remaining fining Lease amendments, including in particular important amendment regarding royalty in Article III. 3. Arguments against acceptance are (a) if extension is now given Petroleum Department are of opinion on such evidence as is available that Company on information to he secured during period of extension are likely to he ahle to reach definite decision as to ar a and, so far as can he Judged, to include within 100|000 acres all oil areas of substantial value at present time; this would of course mean (h) that neither Bahrain Petroleum Company nor any other Oil Jompany would, at any rate, for some considerable time be likely to interest themselves in balance of islands, and that Shaikh's receipts would therefore be confined to amounts now offered by Bahrain Petroleum Company and those to which he is entitled under kining Lease; (c) if extension is refused, while latest indications are that we cannot be sure that Anglo Persian Oil gompany would make early wove in respect of balance of islands, successiul operations by Bahrain Petroleum Company under fining ^ease would aiford best guarantee of subsequent application in respect of remainder of islands either trom Anglo Persian Oil Company or from Bahrain 3etroleum ompany,although this might not of course happen for some years. 4. Petroleum Department state that precise Qerinition of 'commercially exploitable quantitles' 1 (paragraph 4 of your telegram of 10th November, r/99) Presents difficulty. Usual criteria are (a) a specified test/test of wells on accepted leasts to yield a miniinuBi output ('b) a dead rental of such ainjuat as to make It desirable from Company's own standpoint to declare commercial production* Neither point is unfortunatel covered in present Mining Lease and to raise question at present stage with Oompany seems almost bounc to faL1 Petroleum Department thinK f however, that Shaikh would probably oe able later f if necessaryi to take question ol interpretation to arbitration relying on arbitration for equitaole construction. 5. Petroleum Department statethat had we completely frea hand f and were Shaikh in no hurry to secure immediate financial advantage, they would definitely recominend that he should refuse further extension of irospecting License and require Oompany to ta* e out instrument of kining Lease, Un the other hand, Shaikh is understood to want money; offer now put forward by Company deimitely to represent tiieli jlo^ l wordj anu attitude which they have adopted suggests that tuey feel tairly confident that they can at once select essential areas. 6. Decision is essentially one for Shaikh in the light oi our advice. Case for grant of exten- sion is, in our view, on the merits, in view of advance taaue by Company in regard to minimuBi royalty anc faot U^at there appears to be no prospect of their raising their bid, a good one. For your confidential info mation His Majesty's Covemaient so far as their own interests^ are concerned would be well pleased if extension were fciven because of vital importance of their leaaining in/•4- (3) in a position to aoguire laT)d for naval purposes at l?Bahrain) whioh is now under consideration and fact that we might find it embarrassing from this standpoint were Oompany in applying fbr Mining Lease wttk in the immediate future to indicate that they wish to include within it the Eas al Jasra area* -oecretary ot fttate for Incia •IO ts /SJ Telegram xx From Political Resident, at Bahrain. To H.M.•s Secretary of State for India, London. Unnuinbered. Dated the 15tU November 1933. Hi llDiSDl ATS . Your telegram 2824 referred to your telegram of 14tti November 2812. Presume this is error for 2815. \ -Besident- Telegram xx From E.M. # s Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, at -Bahrain. No.2830. Dated the 15th (received 16th)Novemher 1933. i i kpobjatit . 6 lour telegram of 15th November. Please re-number telegram of 14th November sent as 2815 as number 2812. Cyphering error regretted. 8-v\ - Secretary of State for India- ■ 'j i/03 Telegram from To xx H.M,* s secretary of State for India, London• Political Resident, at Bahrain, Go-py 'by Air Mail to G-overnment of India, New Delhi ♦ No. 2852. Dated 15th (received 16th)Novem'ber, 1933. Your telegram of 15th instant, T/104. As yo^^ill see from paragraph 4 of my telegram No.2824, Shaikh's position is un fortunately weak whether extension is granted or not, though grant of extension would give us more time to take point up with Company, -^e might, however, in any event, indicate in reply to Skinner is dissatisfied with absence of clearer defini tion and has asked us to raise point with Company r amendments desire part in g Leas Secretary of State for Indian r i (iik iTelegram xx To From Political Besident, at Bahrain, Secretary of State for Inclia, London. Oopy Air Mail to Grovermnent of India, New Delhi. No•T/105. Dated the 16th Novemoer 1933. immsdiate . 1. Considerations set out in your telegram 2824 with the exception of last paragraph for my confidential information have 'been communicated to Financial Adviser for information of Shaikh. yesterday morning of Shaikh's counter offer and last nigtt pn receipt of communication from him re; Company* ultimatum of 18th was further informed on authority of Financial Adviser that Shaikh was willing if necess ary to give the Company another month from December 2nd for conclusion of negotiations. in apparently ignoring possibility of extension of time for negotiations and attempting to rush the Shai&gt;h 'by their ultimatum as unfriendly. It is possible that Shaikh though easy-going may take the same view and if Company (whatever may he the immediate result of their present tactics) have in the future to deal with a hostile instead of a friendly ruler they will only have themselves to 'blame. 1 suggest that these considerations he put immediately before Ballantyne. 2. Chief Local Representative was informed 3. Personally I consider Company's action -Resident-loi lelegram FroiD To xx Political Keaident, at Jdahrain* H«M # 9 s secretary of ^tat© for Indiaf London. so - dv bv Air &gt;ali to CioremmevX of Inaia,N0w Delhi. Ho. T/107. Dated the 17th Koveciber, 1933. My telegram of 16th November, T/106. Financial Mviser has discussed matter with Shaikh who has made no decision hut who is dis pleased at Company rushing him. I have informed \ Obi at Local Bepresentative of this and I suggest that Ballantyne he also told* i i - Eesiaent - iCONFIDENTIAL. No. C/15S 1933 !0 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to com- The Political Agent, Bahrai and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment (s ).:or in formation • Office of the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, ^amp, Bahrain. 2Baitisii xfioaieKktexSaMeiiiai, Dnfpri i'v'th November 1935 cilcq •#♦•###••#••« 1 Reference to previous correspondence : li Ureal '147 dat Political Residents Printed letter No. , a C/147 dated the 17th Novemher 1933. / ill/ ' x Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. 1 ^Telegram November of State 2.Telegram Novemher of State S.Telegram November of State No.2841 dated 16th 1933 from Secretary for India, No.2350 dated 16th 1933 from Secretary for India. NooT/110 dated 17t|i 1933 to Secretary for India. Bahrain Oil. m i 'i [ ' :'i | 1 j r--kt Xelagram xx From B«or«tary of State for India, London. To Political Kesidant, at Bahrain. Jony tox Air Kail to aovamment of India. Delhi. Ke.SMl* I*tad 16th ( reoalved 17th ; Hovaaber 1933. / fo Your tel^ram of IdtU Novaaber, T/106. Petroleutt Lapartaent # fi adtloe follows Iffij&amp;ediately• Meanwhile as result of further aisouesion Coapany have agreed la) to inorease non-recoverable portion of advance of one lakh to rupees 50,000/-, i*b to our informing you that we have strongly presseci on the^n deairaDlllty of amending Mining Lease to cover definition of ooafoerdaily exploitable quantity, that they are prepared to consider very seriously such an amendment r with the other amend«ents already proposed to them 'but that this will take soxae little time as iiaiBedlate decision is iapractlcable; that Ooapany fully appreciate imut. ) that it is in their interests as well as those of His Majesty's Government that relations with Shaikh should be cordial, that they have no desire to stand on the strict letter of the law and that they trust that statement of this nature will reassure iihaikh. 2e skinner is being inforaed as above to-daye l -Secretary of i»taie for Inula-i M Telegram J'rom (j^2) XX H.M.'s «ecretary of Stat* for India. London. To PoliUoaX Kasluent, at Bahrain. Sns ^?T ftly ffiftU to OoTemiaent of India, «ew X.«lhl. *0.8830. ijated 16th treoelvod mhJHoTaabor 1932. m^UKi 0^ Your telegram of 16th Novaaoer, T /106. i etroleun Xiepartment advise (copy of letter oy sii ail of ivth ) that unrter Articles IJi and X of Mining Lease Joapany Is required to make declaration that oil Us teen t ound In oosunarotally exploitable quantity. Xhere Is no reference as to ability to dispose- of it. a .=sumption would therefore seem to be Uaou^h petroleum Department cannot express a definite opinion on the point) that on finding oil in quantities that would aormally be ooaiaerolally eiploi table Company would be bouna to make deolaratlon irrespective of market ocnditlons prevailing at the uioaieiite 2* On a itjvi'i* vi uu© si tuaulon ad a wliolQ, in the light of further adv ^noe by Company, reportea m my telagrae of 16th Bovember 2841, we aro now of opinion, *Uar consulting • etrolaum Departraent, that Shaikh woulo on the whole do best to face such risks as are Involved ^ granting extension of Irospeoting License. , 3 wo. la then press Company, who seem not Indisposed to behave 'Manably, to accept aux amendment to ilnlng ^ea ^o on the «««3tion of •commercially exploitable quantities' in Waition to the amendments already suggeste^to thei.. -Secretary of State for India-/i0 A i Telegram From To Oopy lay air XX. Political Kesident, at Batovain. H .M's Secretary of at»aie for inaia, London Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, ^ew Delhi. No. T/110 Dated 17th Norainljer 1933. Ky telegram of 16th NovomDer, No. X/105. Chief Local Bepresentative has informed Political Agent that Company have extended their time for Shaikh's reply until 21st November. Resident.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/154 of 1933. /// S*. 1*'. Jf 1 he Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, com- and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of ment (s). for information. ed docn- Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, CJamp,Ba'nrain, bidlflatb. tio k^ciiat Dated A.atn, Noy.sK.pe.r .1953. Reference to previous correspondence ; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. India Office letter No. P«Z.5321/33 dated the 7th Novemher 1933 to the PetrotLeum department(Mines Departmen b)• 2. India Office letter No. P*Z,7189/33 dated the 3th Hovemher 1933 to the Petroleum Department (Mines Department), with enclosures. Letter dated 7th Novemlier 1933 from the Bahrain Petroleum Oompany Limited,, London, to the India Officje, with enclosure. Subject. BAHRAIN OIL. ItI 5 . ^ INDIA OFFICE, 'WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. F.Z.6821/33. 7th November 1933. ly dear Starling, 7/e sent you on 6th November, under the above number, copies of the Political Resident's despatch No.1375-3 of 3rd October 1933, covering inter alia a letter aated 6th September 1933 from Holmes to Ballantyne, being his defence in respect of the various incidents to which exception was taken in the Colonial Office letter of 28th July last, No.18135/33. 2. To take first a minor point. Holmes's letter and its enclosures certainly seem to make it clear that there was what we should, I think, now regard as an undesirable / degree of direct dealing 'oetween the Financial Adviser, Bahrein and Holmes in the early part of this year. As you will remember, however, the Resident was instructed, (in the Secretary of State's telegram of 31st July, No. 1898, c opy sent to you and the other interested Departments under our printed letter No. p.Z.4656/33 of 1st August) Starling, Esq., that/ ^etroleuiii Department, kines Department, Dean Stanley Street, 3.W. 1.in - 2 - that it was, in our viev;, desirable to interpret Conciition 'G 1 scheduled to the Indenture of 12th June 1930 as strictly as possible, and that we should be glad It both the oheikh and Belgrave could be 'tactfully dissuaded from having any discussion, oral or other, with Holmes on oil questions, which we are anxious should be dealt with solely through the political Agent.' The Acting Political resident, in his telegram of 4th August, No.638, replied that the Sheikh entirely agreed to a strict interpretation of Condition 1 G ! and continued that it would in his (Colonel loch's) view be advisable for the A.P.CUC. also Ho conduct negotiations, written and oral, entirely through the Political Agent, as it will be contrary to their interests and ours if the Bahrein Petroleum Company were placed in a position to complain that we were favouring the A.P .O.C. by allowing their emissaries direct access to the sheikh when the Chief Local Representative was debarred from it.' Consequent on this suggestion the A.P.O.C. undertook to deal with oil Questions solely through the Political Agent. I do not 'toink, in these circumstances, that there is any need to •say anything further to the Resident as to the importance of/oi securing ci,il coiniiiUniC6iuionsj v/iiGljh.er or8,l or written, are made through the Political Agent, hut a copy oi this letter will, of course, go to Bushire and to the Government of India. 3• I now turn to the Question oi' territorial waters. You will rernemher that we have had a good deal of correspondence on the Question whether or not the territorial waters of Bahrein are included under the Concession of 2nd December 1925 (see in particular paragraphs 4 and 5 of my letter to you of 2nd August, No. P.Z.4660/33; my letter to you of 9th August, P.Z.4857/33; paragraph 11 of the minutes of the meeting held at the Inaia Office on 10th August; paragraph 2(d) of our telegram to the Resident No.2000 of 11th August; ^•nd paragraph 2 of the itesiaent's reply of 15th August, No.683). paragraph 3 of Holmes's letter of 6th September 1933 seems, however, to me to establish fairly definitely that the existing Concession is not regarded ty the Company as extending to territorial waters, and you will notice that the Sheikh appears to have made it Quite clear to Holmes that he was under the impression that the Concession embraced dry land only. Do you a bree as to this interpretation? If so, the ground will be/be clear in case the question becomes a live one at a later stage. 4. I am sending copies oi this letter to Warner at the Foreign Office and to Moore at the ivdmiraity, and copies will go by this week's air mail to the Political itesident and to the Government of India. Yours sincerely, j•g• laiihwaiti*//£ t INDIA OFFICli:, Inrnea lat a. p.Z.7189/33, WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. 8th November 1933. ivin^ apartment, Department, Dean Stanley Street, W dear starling, You will remember that consequent on the meeting held here on 27th September, general agreement was reached as to the amendments to he suggested to the Bahrein Petioleum Company in their mining lease. We had, as you know, oeen very anxious to make a corrmunication to the COixApcun,) on this subject, but thought it better on the vvhole oo postpone doing so until the position as regards ohe possible acQuisition of land at Bahrein ior naval purposes and the requirements of the Air Ministry was clearer, so that we could if necessary inform Baliantyne v/itiiout delay, in the event of his raising the point, of uiie ai^as whicn we wished set aside, in accordance with the unaertaking given by the Company in connection with the assignment of the Concession in 1930, for landing ground and seaplane sites. We are not yet in a position to dispose of this point, but I am inclined to tnink that U would be preferable to send in our mining lease amendments now without further delay and risk an enquiry irorn the Company on the question of the landing ground and seaplane sites. If we should feel bound for any reason 00 aavise Sheikh to reject the application which has how Deen by the Company for an extension of their respecting licence the point would of course be of ininedjate importance, since the longer notice we give the Company the more chance we have of securing early ^ndments in the mining lease which they would in that event/ S.W. 1in -2- event take out on 2nd December next. But even 11 the Sheikh is to accept their present application it would, I think, be well to let Ball ant yne know without delay what modifications we want, so that v/e can if necessary advise the Sheikh to ask the Company for an understanding that they will be sympathetically considered as part of the consideration for the grant by him of the further extension. 2. 1 now attach a draft letter to Ballantyne, covering a draft schedule of the amendments and additions which we suggest. Will you be so kind as to let me know whether you concur in the draft end in the schedule or have eny observations to offer on either ? As you will see, I have suggested that he end I should talk over the possible modification of Article IX. On this point the letter to him is, I think, generally consistent with the line agreed at our meeting on 27th September as set out in paragraph 12 of the record. 3. The list of amendments to be suggested to the Company contains no reference to the right of preemption in time of war. This is as agreed/I!f 0 -3- agreed at our meeting on 27th September (record, paragraph 37). Neither does it contain any reference to the refining of oil in Bahrein or in British territory, and I shall be glad of your viev/s on this point. At the meeting of 27th September the suggestion was put forward that we might, when informing the Company of our mining lease desiderata say that the Sheikh had been enquiring as to the arrangements proposed and was anxious that the oil should be refined in Bahrein. We referred the matter to the Political Resident in our telegram No.2438 of 3rd October. Colonel Loch's reply (telegram No.928 of 17th October) stated that he had himself formed the impression that the Company proposed to refine at any rate a proportion of their output locally and made it clear that the Sheikh had always looked forv/ard to a large refinery in Bahrein which would give employment to his people. He added however that Gastrell now seemed less certain about this. The general position in regard to refining is examined in detail in your subsequent letter to me, P.D.21, of 30th October, of which copies were sent to India and Bushire/— ma //f n d -4- Bushire by the Air Mail of Srd November, In the light 01 that detailed examination the probability that the Company will refine a material proportion of their output locally seems a strong one. Subject to your views and those of the other Departments, I am on the whole therefore inclined to say nothing on this point to Ballantyne at the present stage (unless of course in the course of conversation an opening offers itself). We have already suggested that Loch should take the opportunity of the Company's present request for an extension to make further soundings discreetly, and if he finds this possible the position may be clearer. If the result of such soundings or of any other information was to make it clear that the Company do not intend to refine in Bahrein, it would I think be quite possible lor us to say to Ballantyne that we had always assumed that, in accordance with the normal practice of oil companies, the Company proposed to refine locally; that this had been the consistent assumption of the Sheikh, who attached great importance to it; that we had regarded it as so much a matter of course tnat we had not included it in our list of requirements; but that now that there seemed some uncertainty on the point we thought it better to put it beyond question? On a last point, as explained above, we are not in a position yet to let the Company know the precise a ^eas we want for the landing ground and seaplane sites.Avo 5- sites. I do not think It Is really vital that this should be covered In the mining lease itself so long as we get an exchange of letters which will bind the Company. 5. I am sending a copy of this letter to Warner at the Foreign Office and Moore at the Admiralty for their consideration. We might,! think,aim at getting the letter off to Ballantyne if possible on Friday. As you know, the Company now hint that failing a decision on their application for a further extension by 15th November they may have to reconsider their position, and it would, I think be well to get our amendments in without delay. Yours sincerely, J.G.LAITHWAITS./&gt;! ( n' H, Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Go • Lt^Q • y 19, Utoorgate, iii • c • 3 1 / draft letter . Dear Mr. Ballantyne, You will remember that during our conversation on 21st September v/e aiscussed the question of the amendments desired in the Bahrein^^ Petroleum Company's Mining Lease^ I promised to let you have details of these amendments at a very early date. I am sorry tnat there has been so much delay and tnat I am only now in a position to write to you on the subject. i enclose herewith a schedule of the amendments in question. For convenience I have divided them into three heads. The first head covers the amendments which are for practical purposes already agreed with the Company, viz. an amendment to give effect to the provisions of the assignment of the Eastern and General Syndicate's concession on 12th June 1930 in so far as the Mining Lease is concerned, and an amendment making provision for measuring crude oil won lor purposes of royalty assessment, and for the keeping of accounts by the Company, following on the amendments on that point made by agreement between us in the prospecting licence early this year. You will remember that at that/that time the Company were willing iiEtnediately to make the corresponding amendment in tne Mining Lease, but that we thought it better to leave all the iviining Lease amendments to be dealt with c omp reh en s i ve ly. 3. The second head covers proposed mod Hi cat ions in specific articles of the Mning Lease, and the third certain additions which we should like to see made to tne lease. As you will see, the modifications and additions in question are for the most part airected to ^ringing the Mining Lease into closer conformity with ordinary oilfield practice; and we trust that the Company will find no difficulty in agreeing to their acceptance, me precise drafting of the various amendments, including in particular those contained in the first category above, might form the subject of discussion oetween us. Perhaps the simplest course woulo be that the Company should propose a draft which coula be considered here? In addition to the amendments set out in the schedule there is one other point which we might if you agree perhaps more conveniently in the first instance discuss orally, and that is the desirability of some moaification of Article IX, bearing on the date from which/3. which the annual payment of Rs.30,000 shall become payable to the Sheikh. We have no desire to press the Company unduly on this ana the Sheikh has of course the right in certain circumstances to appeal to arbitration if he is dissatisfiea. But we are of opinion that some modification of the Article as it stands, to he reached by agreement between us, might make for smoother working without materially affecting the financial interests of the Company, and if you agree we might talk this over.0.* Schedule of amendments etc. sneikh General osed In trie i^nin£_Leaoe appended as P SG fe'i]Tft , III to the ' ' the On Concession granted dv the ui Janrein to trie Eastern and 3:/naicate ~Qn ^n'T^Jecemper lyp.h. A, (1) Amendment under terms oi: Indenture oi 12th June 1930 for the purpose of inserting the conditions set out in the Schedule thereto in the Mining Lease. (2) Provision for measuring crude oil won -i-or purposes ol royalty assessment, and for the keeping of accounts by the Company, (ihe provisions might, as originally contemplated hy the Company, oe identical with those already included in Clause 3 of the Agreement of loth February 1933 between the Sheikh and the Bahrein Petroleum Company as new Articles IXA and IXB in Schedule II to the Agreement of 2nd December 1925). B. ivli sc e 11 aneo u s amendrnent r m inaiviQuai ArticlesT ' Article I&gt; After the words 'such right however shall not include the exclusive right to sell such products within the leased area' it is desired to insert the following amendment 'The lessees shall at their own expense forthwith erect and at all times maintain and keep in repair substantial boundary marks at the corners oi the leased area, according to the demarcation shown in the plan hereto annexed/(9 2. annexed, so that the 'boundaries of the -Leased area may at all tinies he clearly defined.' article . li . Penultimate paragraph. After the words 'at the expiry of the agreement the ground and all immovable property l^it jy the Company shall be handed 'back to the Sheikh' add 'All productive wells and borings shall oe nanded over in good order and repair and fit for further working.' Article III. After the words 'in commercially exploitable quantities' add 'In adaition to the amounts referred to in the preceding part of this Article the Company shall pay a royalty at the rate per ton provided in Article VIII on- all net crude oil won and saved (i.e. after deducting water and foreign substances and oil required as fuel for drilling purposes in the Sheikh's territories ana for pumping to field storage)'. This follows the amendment recently made in Article IX of the Second Schedule to the Agreement of 1925. Article V. Second paragraph: (a) The word 'of' appears to have been omitted af te r the wo rd ' e xp irat ion'. Article VIII/3. Article VIII. (a) For the v ;orcis 'for the customary operations of the Company's installations' substitute 'oil required as fuel for drilling purposes in tiie Sheikh 's territories and for pumping to field storage' and add '; a royalty of 4 annas per thousand cubic feet of natural gas sold by the lessees and calculated at an absolute pressure of one atmosphere and at a temperature of 60 degrees Fahrenheit; and a royalty of one anna per gallon in respect of casing head gasolene recovered ana sold by the lessees.' Article X* At the end of Article add 'If the operations for winning crude oil shall be abandoned or discontinued for 12 months (except on account of force majeure or tne causes speci-Lied in Article V) the sheikh shall thereupon give the lessees notice in writing of such abandonment or discontinuance and call upon them to resume operations, and in the event of such operations not being resumed to the satisfaction of the Sheikh within two calendar months from the date of such notice'the sheikh may thereupon cancel and determine this ' lease.' Article XII/3/ 1-1 (S) 4. Arilcle Xil, At end. of Article add; 'Ttie lessees undertake at all times during the continuance of this lease to carry on all operations for winning and working crude oil and natural gas in a skiliul and workixianiike manner in accorciance with moaem improved methods ana to maintain all productive wells in good repair, working order and condition. The lessees undertake that when any well is being drilled adequate means shall he taken to prevent any uncontrollea flow of oil.' In addition to trie amendments of particular Articles suggested above, the following add itions to the provisions of the Mning Lease are desired; (1) Provision tnat correct geological plans and records, wnich shall he open to inspection hy the Sheikh or his representative at all reasonable times, shall he kept hy the Company. (2.) The Company at their own cost to furnish an annual report of their operations, together with a plan showing the location of all wells drilled. The Company also to keep current records of the drilling logs of all wells, showing all casing inserted and any water horizons passed through.■■ -■■■ —— —— ^ (3 5. (5) His Shaikh or his duly authorised representative to be at liberty at all reasonable times during the continuarce oi the kining Lease to inspect and examine all works carried on by the lessees, trie lessees to aiiord 'Co the Sheikh all information which he may reasonably require in connection with any such inspection. (4) The Company to undertake to offer no unnecessary or reasonably avoidable obstruction or interruption to the development ana working of any minerals (other than petroleum or cognate products), including water, ard to ail ore. to the Sheikh and to the holders oi prospecting licences or mining leases in respect of other minerals reasonable means of access to such minerals for the purpose of working and carrying away the same.U 7^fi/33 . THE BAHBEIN PETBOLEUM OOmM LIMITED, IS, Mo orgate, i lonuon» 7 th N -j v cmbe r, 1933. Dear Mr. Laithwaite, As arranged v;hen I oailea upon you this afternoon, I send vou herev/ith a copy of Llx . Skinner's letter to His Britannic Majesty ? c Political A^eno, Bahrein, dated the 21st October. In his covering letter to me, Mr. Skinner explains that the suggested offer was discussed in some detail with the Political Ageno, Bahrein ana the Financial Adviser to the Bahrein (xuvernment. He was informed, apparently, that while the Financial Adviser, and the Political Agent could discuss the offer with the SneiKli ol Baijrein, tiiey were not at liberty to advise Mr. Skinner whether or not it v/as acceptable until the terms had been made Known to the Political Eeoident at Bu^hire, and probably to other Officials of the India Office. ALio, that neither the Political A^ent nor the Financial Auviser felt that they could open the subject with the Political hehiuent without having some sort of written offer irom iue Bahrein Petroleum Go. Liu. Accordingly, Mr. Skinner made what he calls an informal tentative offer' inwricing to the Political A ^ent, which was to be followed by ll a formal legal offer', if acceptable, for the reason that neither the Political Agent nor the Pinancic.! Autficer could take any action on a verbal offer. The news received by cable from Mr. Skinner to-day was to the effect that the offer was passed on to the Sheikh of Bahrein on the 28th October and the Sheikh of Bahrein had not made anv answer up to the time 01 cabling. I have cabled to Mr. Skinner this afternoon informing him//3o (J him that I understand the Political A^ent v/ill receive an enquiry from Lcnaon as to the position, and asking him to consider making a request for a definite answer before the 15th instant. Yours sincerely, (S-a). H.B. BiiLLAl T TYKE. . laithwaite, Eiiq., Inuia Office, Lunuon, S.W.TIIE BAHREIN PETROLEUM ccmpamy ; LTD. October 21st, 1933 .M.'s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I have received telegraphic instructions from the London Office of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, to request you to advise His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrein that this company wishes to make the following tentative offer: In return for an extension of the Prospecting License for 13 months from December 2, 1933, to January 2, 1935, the Bahrein Petroleum Conpany, Limited:- (1) will pay for the private purse of the Shaikh of Bahrein Rs. 25,000 not recoverable, payment to be made in lump sum or in instalments whichever is preferred by the Bahrein Government; (2) will advance to the public purse Rs.75,000 in 13 equal monthly instalments beginning December 2, 1933, and to be recoverable from one fourth of any of the future annual royalties in excess of Rs.60,000; (3) should the company not apply for a Mining Lease by December 2, 1934, the Shaikh of Bahrein will have the right to a proportionate part of the regular annual rental of Rs-10,000, to cover the period from December 2, 1934, to January 2, 1935. The short time remaining before the expiration of the Prospecting License (December 2, 1933) necessitates prompt action on this offer. For this reason we are making the offer as simple as possible and in tentative form so that it may be discussed with the Shaikh of Bahrein and the interested offices of His Britannic Majesty's G-overnment. If the offer is acceptable to all concerned it will be presented to you in a formal application. Yours very truly, S.A. SKINNER. Chief Local Representative: The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited.THE BAfiRAiW PETROLEUM COMPANY LBIITED Bahrain Island, Persian Gulf. No.vr 17, 1933. Mr. G. Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to Government, Bahrain. Dear Mr. Belgrave, T Ve are naking preliminary plans for shipping oil through a submarine line which will run from tne east side of Sitra Island to the deep water beyond the entrance of Khor Kaliya. It'will be necessary to bridge the channel between Sitra and the mainland, crossing over the small island near Malamir. IVould it be possible for us to close this channel comDletely'r If not ? could we completely close it on one side of the island and partially close the other side, leaving an opening approxi- mately 15 to 20 feet wide over which will be placed a draw bridge to allow small ships to pass? I assume there would be no objection to our putting in a road between the end of our No. 5 road and Sitra Island, bridging any canals crossed. I would very much appreciate an early reply. Cogy forwarded to H.B.M T s Political ^igent for information. Yours sincerely, 3d/ E. ii. Skinner.Io:Cjf522-10/l.V. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 19th November 1933. Lear iilr.Skinner, ptjif- 1 enclose a copy ol' your letter dated the 13th November 1933 Tor which you asked as you had written it in haste. Yours sincerely, t' v. Skinner Es % uire, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd, Bahrain.i ' f./ui?'. ^ C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. .y nq./523-io/i.v. \v The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments tothe Adviser to tiie Bahrain Government, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. T he A gency, B ahrain , P ersian G ulf. 19th November 193. . Reference to previous correspondence. D escription of E nclosure. Name and date. Subject. f, Letter dated-the 19th November 1933^0:0/521, 1'rom the Political Agent to H.E Shaikh Hamad bin T Isa Al Khalifah,C .S .I., Ruler of Bahrain. Bahrain Oil./31 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited j? /U: 77 (W) Bahrein Island, Persian Gulp. November 19, 1933. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear ^ir: Confirming my letter of 18#r of November, 1933, which was in answer to your letter No. C/Slo-lO/l.V;- Although your understanding of the terms of our offor an extension of the Prospecting License by 13 months' ; wss substantially correct, the method and time of payments is slightly different than you stated. T am enclosing a proposed Supplementary Agreement covering the entire matter in detail, which Agreement we would expect to be signed if His Excellency Shaikh Hamad Bin Isa Al Khalifah accepts our offer. It is my understanding that the payments in installments, as specified, will be more satisfactory to the Financial Adviser to the Bahrein Government than the payments in a lump sum, and my instructions are that the payments shall be in such installments. &gt;.-7^ T am further instructed to inform 3''ou^pat the Company is not in favor of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad*s of^er to extend the Prospecting license for one month, because if no result is reached within that time it would lead to disappointment, and that such extension is not good in principle. They have asked me to explain to everyone concerned that friendliest co-operation is desired and hasty discussion on one definition apart from consequential and other alterations which might be proposed to the T'ining Lease, is impracticable and likely to lead to embarrassment of everyone. For this reason, they do not wish at this time to discuss the definition of rt oil in commercially exploitable quantities'. Although willing to consider alterations mentioned above, the Company is not bound in principle to accept or make any alterations, but our idea is to embrace practical politics rather than to stand on the strict letter of the law. 'Te now consider that we have made a very handsome offer, and such offer can only be held open until 6 P.M. November El, 1933. Yours very truly, B J2i, -tv. SKTNI.-iJri, C/ kf Local Representative^, THE DAHREf/* PEJf*UJtUM COMHA^YA* 7f C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c, C)^ o N o C/524-10/1.V. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Hon»ble the Persian Gulf Political Resident in the / and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned document %ith reference to conversations on the 18th and 20th November 1933. The Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 20th NoYemher 193. . Reference to previous correspondence. Description of Enclosure. Name and date. Subject. 1. Demi-official letter dated 18-11-1933 from E.A.Skinner Esquire, Chief Local Represent ative,Bahrain ^etroleum Company Limited. 2.Lemi-of*ic8i letter No:C/516 of 18-11-33 to E.A.Skinner Esquire. Lighting and Buoying of Khor Kaliyah. -do-fQ-U /lo: No;C/525-10/l.V. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 20th November 1933. Dear Mr.Skinner, I should be grateful if you would let me have the further two copies of the Supplementary Agreement as soon as possible so that i may get the Arabic put in. 2. I return three of the four copies which you sent to me (one has been kept for translating purposes) as in the heading the title T G.C.S.I T has been entered though His Excellency Shaikh Hajnad bin ? Isa Al Khalifah as a ^.S.I 1 . 1 think that it will be necessary to have the page done again,as clearly it would be inappropriate to have a correction of that sort in the Agreement. Perhaps you would kindly send them back by the bearer. Yours sincerely. ^Skinner Esquire, Local representative r ihe Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd, Bahrain. epresentativehu flo'. fi Political ii^ency, Bahrain,the 20th iNoveabtr 1933. Lear air.Skinner, T Aith reference to the third paragraph of my letter ^o:C/52o-10/l.Y of today ? s date,perhaps we can arrange a time suitable to you at the Hams' f At Home T this evening. lours sincerely./'-■ f S.d*: $3 No:C/527-10/l.V* Political Agency, Bahrain,the 20th November 1933. From:- To:- Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Sir. In continuation of my letter No:C/512-10/l.V dated the 17th November 1933 and with reference to our conversation on the morning of the 20th November 1933, I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter dated \ the 13th November 1933 from the Chief Local Represent ative,The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,enclosing a Supplementary Agreement covering the proposed extension of the Company T s Prospecting License. 2. The Supplementary Agreement is being translated into Arabic and a copy will be sent to you in due course. 1 have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain... : m C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. v\ No. C/528-10/1.V. a) , y/c; &gt; if The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to til6 Hon' bit the Persian Gulf, the Political resident in / and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. T he A gency, B ahrain , P ersian G ulf. 20th Nove mber l93 3.. i Reference to previous correspondence. Bahrain Printed Letter No:C/514 dated 18th November 1933. D escription of E nclosure. Jta Name and date. Subject. •Letter dated 18-11-1933 from the Chief Local Representative,The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd. Uetter No:C/515 of 18-11-1933 to p the Cniet Local Eep resent at ive. 3.Letter datea 18-11-1333 from ftaM- A.Skinner Esquire, better No:C/52r of 19-11-1933 to P,*&gt;3 H.S Shaikh rlamad bin Isa al Khali f ah. Letter dated 19-11-1933 from the fP Chiel Local Representative. ^ter dated 19-11-1933 from t ,„ 0 H.E Shaikh Hamad bin 'Isa Al $ uo palifah. k ett er No^/SSo of 20-11-1933 to tne Chiel Local Representative. Bahrain Oil -do- -QO- -do- -do- -do- -do-m S, Ao'te 2 v C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c, v /ix) Na C/529-10/1.V The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to the Hon'ble Persian Gull\ tiie foil tical nesiaent in tJie/^nd has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. T he A gency, B ahrain , P ersian G ulf. 20 th Noyattber 193 3.. Reference to previous correspondence. Bahrain P.L.No:C/5d8 dated the 14-11-1933, D escription of E nclosure. Name and date. - - -- ... ,) f Subject. Letter No:C/509 dated 15-11-1933 to the Chiel* Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. Bahrain Oil.&lt;b''' '' Nz The Bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. November 20, 1933. . i His Britannic Majesty's Political ^gent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: /&gt;. /43 I beg to acknowledge receipt of your letter 'o # c/526 -10/l.v. c November the 20th, 1933, stating that His Excellency shaikh Dxii Isa al knalifah has accepted the offer of my Company for an extension of the Prospecting License to January 2, 1935, on terms set forth in my letters dated the 18th and 19th of November. 1933. \ \ The draft Agreement enclosed has been partially translated and typewritten already, and the part completed is in the pOose.s&gt;Gxon of J-usam v at9em» Tn case this will save you any timo in completing the translation, T am having Husain Yateem forward to you at once the work he has already finished. ^ shdll arrange to be in Manama any time you designate during the forenoon of the 21st of November, 1933 to sign the Supplementary Agreement. Yours very truly, E. A. SKUCTB, Locn I Reprtttmialii*: THE ti4HRElM PETRQ^tUM COAltA. W LIMIT 1 f r * ||j r if if! 11I The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited if? Jte'S Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, November 20, 1933. Dear Colonel Loch: 1$^ Please accept^'thanks for your Demi-official letter TT o. 0/52^-10/1.7 of November 19, 1933, enclosing a type^Arritten copy of my letter to you of the ISth of November, 1933. Yours sincerely. il. il. ox.xnitxjr. Lieut-Colonel 3. Loch, His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein, liv Uaso T he B ahrein petroleum C ompany L imited | S. Ac: ft Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, November 20, 1933. , p. /av Reference your letter No. (5/525-10/1,7, dated Nov. 20, 1933 Dear Colonel Loch: T ain f orwarding you 9 copies of the supplementary Agreement, 6 for your own use, and 3 for my use, which should be properly executed. I would appreciate your having the Arabic entered on all 9 copies, and wil] be pleased to reimburse you for any expense attached. t i, i ■ xM Yours sincerely. E. A. SKINNER, Chief Loral Representative: THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM CO HA h ANY LIMI.ZX Lieut-Colonel a. Loch, His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. B t n 1- ■ v i;f./u.s T he B ahrein P etroleum C ompany L imited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, November 20, 1933. Dear Colonel Loch T shall be at the HaIns , T At Home* this evening, and we can undoubtedly arrange a suitable time for signing the ^pplementary Agreement, at that time, as suggested in your personal letter of November 20, 1933. Yours sincerely. Lieut-Colonel a. Loch, His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein, I/-0 4 '/iv Aoi c fo Bahrain, Novr. Dear Colonel Loch, H. E. Shaikh Hamad informs me that he wishes to call on you tomorrow morning at 9-45. {^ Yours sincerely, Lt. Col. C. Loch, H.B.M T s Political Agent, Bahrain.-S*, Mot ( 7n No:C/533-10-l.V. m Political Agency, t Bahrain,the 21st November 1933. From:- To:- Lieut-Colonel Oordon Loch,I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sir, I have the honour to enclose two copies, ^ r duly signed and sealed,of the Supplementary Agreement dated the 21st November 1933 between His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin f Isa Al Khalifah,G.S.l., and The Bahrain Petroleum Gompany Limited. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, . 1 i Lieut-Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain. ir I'£/• T he B ahrein P etroleum C ompany L imited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, November El, 1933. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir; tvt r Vf ' clai0 ^ le ^g9 receipt of your letter . o, C o^C^lu/ .Y. of the Cist of ITovember, 1933, with w^ich were enclosed three executed copies of the Supplementary Agreement which was sisned today ^ (November 21st). ' Yours very truly, E. A. SKIISER, Chief Local Representative, Tli BAIIRSn. PEIECLZoi: COLIPAI^r,LI.II^EI&gt; 4 2Jjl*lk (1^ PETIOLiSUM disfastlffint, (Mines Department), P.D.21. Dean Stanley street, Mlllbanlc, Westminster, London, s .W. 1. 30th October 1933. Dear Lalthwalte With reference to Powle's telegram, 928, of the 17th October regarding the refining of Bahrein oil. It Is difficult for me to believe that the Company woula ship the crude half round the world to the refineries belonging to the standard Oil Company of California, which are all situated In California (except a small one in Texas) where tne Company already has a production of 5,000,000 tons of oil. The distance from Bahrein to California, going Kast via Singapore and the Pacific, is approximately 10,970 miles. Die other route, going West via the tealtarranean and the Atlantic, would be about 12,700 miles, but this would involve the transit of both the aue^ and Panama Canals and involve the payment of heavy cues. .Moreover, there is a high tariff in the united States which elfectively abuts out crude oil from much nearer sources than Bahrein. In fact it is possibly due In some iiieasure to this tariff that the Stanaard Oil Company oi California is looking for sources of oil nearer the markets in i *hich it can be sold. Existing refineries actually nearest to Bahrein ^re at Abadan, Suez and Rangoon. The distances are approximately 400, 3200 and 3500 miles respectively. Apart from/-MJtm 'LiS - 2 - from a small refinery belonging to the Egyptian Government at Suez ana two small refineries at Rangoon belonging to independent companies, all the refining capacity «»t the places mentionea is in the hands of the ^nglo-Persian, Burmah and Shell Groups, which would not he likely to help the standard Oil Company of California with the disposal of Bahrein oil. One obvious market for Bahrein oil is India, with its large native demand for kerosene and growing requirements of petrol and fuel oil occasioned by rapid road and industrial development. But this is a ntirket for rel'ined oils and the usual practice is to build a refinery on or near the oilfield. The standard Oil Company of California sent substantial quantities of crude oil to Japan in 1931. This was probably for refining in Japan for the Japanese Navy, and although regarded as somewhat of an unusual transaction, we know that Japan is very anxious to secure other sources of supply of crude oil. Xhe distance from Bahrein to Japan would be about 7,000 miles as compared with only 4,500 from Sao Francisco. If the Company find oil in Hasa, they will need a refinery also for that oil. All this serves to show that we are on quite strong ground in pressing for refining in Bahrein. It is up to them to say how such a proposal would inflict hardship on them. I am sending copies of this letter to itoore and Warner. Yours sincerely, (3d.) P f C. STARLING. r «•[iaii- CONFIDENTIAL. rt No. 0/171 of 1933. / Ia The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf presents his com- pliments to !• The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New .belhi. 2* The Political Agent f y* Bahrain, y and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment (s). ,ov hey v o L, i\iOV. I ^ Office of the Political Eesident^^ A,N in the Persian Gulf, Jaiap, ahrain. Reference to previous correspondence: g, : ToU) Political Resident's Printed letter No .C/146 ( v of 17th Novemher 1933, ,7^0(2} Political resident's Printed, letter No.C /153 \ ('to'] Name and Date. £ ^ 1. Telegram No.T.114 dated th&lt; liJth Hovember 193S to His Majesty's Secretary of Stat for India. 2. Telegram No.I.116 dated the 20th November 1933 to His Majesty's Secretary of otat for Inaia. Subject. e e Bahrain Oil nlU Xelegraia Prom To xx Political resident 9 at Bahrain* iUM, Jeoretary of Jtate for India# London• Bepeated Comiuander-in-Chief f ast Indies. Copy l)y Air kail to aoTernjaent of India, Neif JPelhi, tax xktflmcttem* Ho. T/114. Dated the 18th Noveniher B33. /or info ration* Bahrain I etroleuui Gofitpany have just inlonaed Bal^rain Government ttiat they are making preliminary plane for shipping oil through a suo-marine line to run from iiaatlside of aitra Island l to deep water 'beyond entranoe of Khor Khaliya. - Resident -ipnuai. / J . GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL)- [■SB.-This is an ()liIG1 NAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a mtans of communication more expeditions than thr ordinary mait and is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended tb he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and to obviate formalities it is dru/ted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] 'I* y No. J /172 or l*ZZj)at€d Sim49Ct%M ot tbe political eaiaeot N«w~MeUi u To lice the Persian lJ Caaap, BafaLratn f 20tb lio\ moer 19ZZ. From - To Reference my aaslaara, at ^ahrall Forelgn, N tm •taxandus, London* Havycoa. iUM^o.^Hawkins 11 , ast Indies Senior Naval Ofric0r &gt; i ersian Gulf* loliticalf Bahrain* ^'reference Agency Printed Letter No, C/b24, aatea tne 20tin November 1923« L |f .gi 1 enclose herawith copy of a let er dated t,txe idth Sovtaaber X9$Z from 2 r^klnnor, Chief Local riepredentative. The pahrain petroleum ^cmpany Limited, and would be glad to be inforoied by telegram as to whether MrsBkimer's requests can be granted* (3d.) T.a*Fowl0 f I«1 e 11 * • Solon el 9 Political Hesident in the Persian CrQlf, for Secretary to the Iclitioal Kesident in the ^ersian Gulf* (Signature) h.h I 7 S. 44. DCl! , p_i 1 24S&amp;r—(M-13H)-4-8-32-12,000. (Designation)No. CONFIDENTIAL. C/173 of 1933. j /lo: fz ic&gt; The Hon hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com* pliments to 1. Tbe Foreign Sccrctaay to the Government of Inoia, Hew Delhi, 2, Hie Majesty's Secretary of State for Ir;(&gt; ia, Lono on• and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). Office of the Political kcefc ^ent In thfe Persian aulf, Caaip, Bahrain. DatpH^lf t November 1933 Reference to previous correspondence: *»% Description of Enclosure. As pei 8checul2 attached. Bahrain an. Copy forwarded, with compl Agent, Bhhrain, for iments, to the Politicaly information. A i t Ano List or enolosurea S .u 1. Letter No.G/509-10/1 .V dated the lotti Hove ber 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Chief Local Kepres0n|jaU.ve f Bahrain Petroleum Co.Lc. 2. Letter dated the 15th November 1963 from the ^hief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Co .Ltd. to the Political Agent,Bahrain. ^ p- 3. Demi-official letter dated the 15th November 1933 from the rolitical Agent, 3aurain, to the 0- ief Local Bepresentative, Bahrain x-etroleuia Co.Ltu. i 4. Letter dated the 16th November 1933 from the Chief Local Hepresentative, Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd. to the Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ P* s ^ 5. Demi-official letter dated the 16th November 1933 from the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd., to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 6. Letter No.C/511-10/1.V dated the 16th November 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Chief Local Bepresentative, Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd. 7. Letter dated the 17th November 1933 from the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd., to the Political iUent, Bahrain. ^ vtvi 3. Letter No.C/512-10/1.V dated the 17th November 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. ^ i 9. Letter dated the IBth November 1933 from the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd.,to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 10. Letter No.C/515-10/1 .V dated the 13th Noveiaber 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Chief Local iiepresentative^ Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd. 11. Demi-oflicial letter dVted the 18th November 1933 from the Chief Local Representative,Bahrain Petroleum Co.Ltd., to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 12. Letter No.C/521^. io /l.V dated the 19th November 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Shaikh of Bahrain. ^ ^ 13. Letter dated the 19th November 1933 from the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Go.Ltd. to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 14. Letter dated the 19th November 1933 from the Shaikh of Bahrain to the Political Agent,Bahrain. /(r 15. Letter No.0/526.10/1.V dated the 20th November 1933 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum o o. L td. ■CONFIDENTIAL. (all No. a/175 Of 1933. r, no &amp; The Hon hie tlie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The foreign Secretary to tbe GovernmsTit of India, New Delhi. 2* The Political Agent, y Bahrain. / and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- men f ] British Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRE. Dated a t • • •&lt; o^0r &gt; 5 • ii Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Telegram No.T/ll? datea tae 21st Hovemher 1933 to His Majesty's Secretary of 3tat|e for India. Subject. Bahrain Oil V?i cgp GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D epartment. EXPRESS LETTER [ N . Tj , Tins i* an ORIGIN AL MJiSSAG ff, sent by post to save teleqravTiic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time ami formalities it is worded and siyned as if it had been so despatched,] F eom Besldent, at Bahrain. To - Betaxanduia 9 London* repeated - iorelgn, Nev Delhi* iolitioalf Bahrain, y/ To ''•0/176 of 1933. 2l3t Movtjwtoer i:&lt;ZZ* I -eferenoe my telegram ot 21st tiovm o ^r, No. '1/117. I enclose herewith copy of the Agreement in questior} ^•tween the Shaikh and the Bahrain ^etroleuni Company# Briefly U will he seen that the Cospany pay: ia) k sum of &amp;•25,000/- to Shaikh's private purse oon-recoverable, paid in instalments. I Vide clause 2 (a) Agreementi. lb) k sua of R b .75, 000/- to Bahrain Government f also ^ Instalments, of which ns. 25,000/- is non-reooverahle and ^•^0,000/- is recoverable from Uoyalties. ivide clause 2 lb) 01 Agreement). lc) A guaranteed minimum rental of ns.30 ,000/- per of which &gt;Aa. 10,000/- is paid on the 2nd December 19^3 ^ 20,000/- at the end of 1934, and similar payments on 1m5s&amp; p—(m-1821)—27-9-32—240,000. &gt;1 a siuiilai'/ri -2- - 0 l similar payments on similar datos in future years, (vicie clau»« 5 of Agreement). There is also a provision for the payiaent lay the Company to the 3ha kh of one morith*a rental at tbe end of 1954 if the Company should before then deoide not to take up the Mining Lease, ivide clause 4 of Agree ment) • these terms are fair and on the balance of advantages I think the 3baikh was wise to grant the extension aakeft for hy the Company. noo 2. The Shaikh 9 as indicated in my telegram Ko. T/iOVf dated the 17th Hovemher 1933, was upset and annoyed at what he rightly considered the hustling taotios of the Oompany. He is, however, correspondingly &lt; grateful for the successful efforts made in l^ondon and in Bahrain to seoure him more time for cogitation, (the Company^ ultimatum having heen extended from the 13th .4 to the aist November), and distinctly better terms than these originally offered hy the Gom]jany. In this k connection I cannot help pointing out that, while the . ■i|f Company have at various times deprecated any desire to bargain, in this instance their final terms were only ohtainea 'by the actual process of bargaining. I imagine also that, while of coiarse it is necessary for us to keep on good terms with the Company, (my own relations here, as those of Loch, with Skinner, are very frienaiy) in any difference of opinion that crops up in future we shall only obtain good terms for the Shaikh hy a similar/r uxu GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Ca5 i- 16TJ t i al • Department^ EXPRESS LETTER [N.B % 1 Ins is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hy 'post to save telegraphic expense and nndac use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and siy ned as if it had been so despatched^ S}/&gt;\ f 1 '. ipeated Kasldentf at Bahrain* Hataxaodua, London* Foreign, Heu Deltil* I-olltical, Bahrain* v/ viao of 1933. Dated m. z: 22nd hovtaeher jp.i^ liefer nee oorrespoodaoce ending with paragraph 5 of »ia Of fice latter Mo.i .ii. 7189/33, dated tUe ath Kovember 1933, ietroleua Departaeot. Refining of Oil In Bahrain or Brltlsk •rrltoiy. As it Is difficult bo ascertain reliable Infozmatlon otUei iceaos I suggest tbat Sbalklx should address Company «*«l:y asklhg for oonflnaatlon of his assuaptlon tbat Oompany U refine locally, and adding that, owing to need of provld- '5 sniployoant for tils subjecto, It Is a point to which he holies particular iBportance. Shaikh's coa^unication 'to, as usual, pass through Polltloal Agent, but latter •tt* only sp ear as forwarding authority. llease telegraph reply/ f«. v- k rcfp -'lb65saf—(11-1821)—27 9-32—2,40,000. I 1^ / 7 1)m -2- reply repeating Political Agenti Bahrain# atl^st id i (sd. } I.C.i 'owle, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in tbe Persian Gulf. for Secretary to tbe Political Resident in tbe Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No.CJ/133 Of 1953. i* /oh C / The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, BaiiraT and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s ).for information. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Camp, Bahrain. brkifek Dated? NoveiI1 ' oer -933 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. India Office letter No^P.Z. 7169/33 dated the 11th Novemlter 1933 to the Bahrain Petroleu Company Ltd.,Lendon, with enclosure. Z, Letter dated the 14th Novemhdr 1933 from the Bahrain Petroleum 'Jo.Ltd. ,LQndon, to the Tnaia Office,v.i.th enclosure. 3. India Office Note aated 15th Movemher of telephone conversa tion wita Mr.H.R.Ballantyne on 15th Novemher 1933, 4. Inaia Office letter No.P.Z.7±35/ 33 dated the 16th November 1^33 to the PetrcOeum Department, with enclosure. 5. Petroleum Department letter dated 16th November 1933 to the Inaia Office. Subject. B a hr a 1 n oil, k ' vl^ i r / M IP. Z. 7189/33 • WEI TEKA.iL, S.W. 1 11th November, 1933. dear ^si 1&gt; / vv You will remejber that during our conversation on 21st September we discussed the question of the amendments desired in the Bahrein Petroleum Company's Mining Lease, when I promised to let you have details of these amendments at a very early date. I am sorry that there has been so mu.ch delay and thrt I am only now in a position to write to you on the subject. 2. I enclose herewith s schedule of the amendments in question. For convenience I have divided them into three heads. The first head covers the amendments which are for practical purposes already agreed with the Company, viz. an amendment to give effect to the provisions of the assignment of the Eastern and General Syndicate's concession on 12th June 1930 in so far as the Mining Lease is concerned, and an amendment making provision for measuring crude oil won for purposes of royalty assessment, siid icr the keeping of accounts by the Company, following on the amendments on that point made by agreement between 'jBallantyne. Esq., us/ -'■fein Petroleum Co. ,Ltd.., 19, Lloorgate, E.G.2 j- 2 - us in the prospecting licence early this year. iou will • remember that at that time the Coi.Tpany were willing immediately to make the corresponding amendment in the '/ining Lease, but that we though it better to leai r e all the Mining Lease amendments to be dealt with comprehensively, 3. The second head covers proposed modifications in specific articles of the Mining Lease, and the third certain additions which we should like to see made to the lease. As you will see, the modifications and additions in question are for the most part directed to bringing the Mining Lease into closer conformity with ordinary oilfield practice; and we trust that the Company will find no difficulty in agreeing to their acceptance. The precise drafting of the various amendments, including in particular those contained in the first category above, might form the subject of discussion between us. Perhaps the simplest course would be that the Company should propose a draft which could be considered here? 4. In addition to the amendments set out in the schedule the Sheikh has raised in connection with your Company's application for an extension of their prospecting licence/I ^ ^ - 3 - licence the question of 'commercial exploitable quantities' in Article IX, and ve shall have to discuss this further. Yours sincerely, J.Gr. LAITHIAITE.It 5 • (z6i&gt; Schedule of amendments etc. proposed in tne iviining Lease appendea as Scneaule ill to t he Cil^Qcncesoion granted by the oheikn ol BaiTre in to tlie Eastern and General Syndicate on 2nd December 1925 . ' A. (1) rUnenament under terms ot Indenture of 12th June 1930 for the purpose of inserting the conditions set out in the Schedule thereto in the Mining Lease. (2) Provision for measuring crude oil won for purposes of royalty assessment, and for the keeping of accounts hy the Company. (The provisions might, as originally contemplated hy the Company, he identical with those alreaay included in Clause 3 of the Agreement of 15th February 1933 between the Sheikh and the Ban re in iretroleum Company as new Articles IXA and IXB in Schedule II to the Agreement of 2nd December 1925). fi. Miscellaneous amendments m inaiviaual Articles 7' Article I . After the words 'such right however shall not include the exclusive right to sell such products within the leased area' it is desired to insert the following amendment 'The lessees shall at their own expense forthwith erect and at all times maintain and keep in repair substantial boundary marks at the corners oi the leased area, according to the demarcation shown in the plan hereto annexed/2. annexed, so that the 'boundaries of the leased area may at all times oe clearly defined.' ar ticle II . penultimate paragraph. After the Vvords 11 at the expiry of the agreement tne ground ana all iiiimo vab 1 e property left by the Company shall be handed back to trie Sheikh' add 'All productive wells and borings shall be handed over in good order and repair and fit for further working.' Article III . Aft^r the vvords 'In commercially exploitable quantities' add 'In addition to the amounts referred to in the preceding part of this Article the Company shall pay a royalty at the rate per ton provided in Article VIII on all net crude oil won ana saved (i.e. after deducting water and foreign substances and oil required as fuel for drilling purposes in the sheikh's territories ana for pumping to field storage)'# This follows the amendment recently irade in Article IX of the Second Schedule to the Agreement of 1925. Article V * Second paragraph: (a) The word 'of' appears to have been omitted after the word 'expiration'. Article VIII/Article VIII . (a) For the words 'for the customary operations oi the Company 1 s installations' substitute 'oil required as fuel for drilling purposes in the sheikh*s territories and for pumping to field storage' and add a royalty of 4 annas per thousand cubic feet of natural gas sold hy the lessees ana calculated at an absolute pressure of one atmosphere and at a temperature of 60 degrees Fahrenheit; and a royalty of one anna per gallon in respect of casing head gasolene recovered and sola by the lessees.' Article XII . At end of Article add; 'The lessees undertake at all times auring the continuance of this lease to carry on all operations for winning and working crude oil ana natural gas in a skilful and workmanlike manner in accordance with modern improved methods ana to maintain all productive wells in good repair, working order and condition. The lessees undertake that when any well is being drilled adequate means shall be taken to prevent any uncontrolled flow of oil.' c/ 11wmm ii(&gt; In addition to the amendments of particular Articles suggested above, the following additions to the provisions of the Lining Lease are desired; (1) provision tnat correct geological plans ana records, which shall he open to inspection oy the srieikh or his representative at all reasonable times, shall he kept hy the Company. (2) Tne Company at their own cost to furnish an annual report of their operations, together witn a plan showing the location of all wells drilled. The Company also to keep accurate records of the drilling logs of all wells, showing all casing inserted and any water horizons passed through. (3) The sheikh or nis auly authorised representative to he at liberty at all reasonable times during the continuance of the Lining Lease to inspect and examine all works carried on by the lessees, the lessees to afford to the Sheikh all information wnich he may reasonably require in connection with any such inspection. (4) Uie Company to undertake to offer no unnecessary or reasonably avoidable obstruction/' Itl obstruction or interruption to the aevelopment ana v/orking of any minerals (other than petroleum or cognate products), inciuaing water, and to aflord to the sheikh ana to the holders of prospecting licences or Lining leases in respect of other minerals reasonable means of access to such minerals for the purpose of working and carrying away the same.iU p. Z. 7385/53. THE BAHREIN PETROLEIM COLIPMY LILITED. 19 UOORGATE, LONDON, E.G.2 14th November 1933. Dear Mr. ^aitbvaite. I have to acknowledge re of your letter of the 11th instant (Reference P.Z.7189/33) and its aocompanying enclosure, both of which are being forwarded to San Francisco by this evening's mail. confirm what I told you over the telephone this morning, namely:- I have this morning received instructions from the Company to inform you that if it will help matters the Company will give the Sheikh of Bahrein such assurances as he may be advised to accept, that the minimum royalty of Rs»30,000 would commence at the expiration of two years after the commencement of the Mining Lease. This is not to be treated as a part of the compensation for the extension of the Prospecting Licence and is to be dealt with as an agreed modification of the form of Lease, is any alteration in the period during which the Company ks at liberty to declare whether or not oil has been found in 'conmercially exploitable quantities'. Sheikh of Bahrein wants to have the assurance that he will have a minimum income commencing in, say roughly, three years' time and this is the assurance which the To deal with Clause 4 of your letter, I have to It does not follow from the foregoing that there As the Company understands the position, the ^.Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I Company/- 2 - Company is prepared to give. If the Lease is not taken up, or if it is abandoned prior to the arrival of the time of the payment of the minimum royalty, then, naturally, the Sheikh receives no portion of the minimum royalty of Rs.30,000. Mr. Skinner is receiving cabled instructions today to make this further concession by the Company clear to the Sheikh of Bahrein and to lodge his application for the Lease on the 18th instant if he has not received by then the asked for acceptance of the Company's application for the thirteen months' extension of the Prospecting Licence. The Company trusts that the Sheikh of Bahrein and his Advisers will not assume from the foregoing that they are being rushed into a decision without having had an opportunity for due consideration; a.s the Company sees the position, it is that the offer for cash it has made cannot be increased. The Company has accepted the desire of the Sheikh of Bahrein to have the assurance of a fixed royalty within a specified time and therefore it is only left now for the Sheikh of Bahrein to decide whether or not he will accept the cash offer, an offer which has been before him now for three weeks. Yours sincerely, (SD.) H.R.BALLANTYNE. r ip.Z.7365/33. woni^ x.tiij • li'v jj .l i y t L jui ♦ . U-' IK ON i3th NQV^IvSER WITH ii OF TH^ BAHREIN P^THOL^lJT^l CCL^ANY ai imil ir , jia ox^ : ig:' . i3 '— Extens ion of the Comaa iiv's Prospecting Licence and ainencmients to be liiaae in thdrAjiniriK Lease . Alter consultation with the interested Departments in the light o± tne views expressed in Colonel Fowle's telegram oi 10th November, T.99, I explained the position in regard to the extension oi trie prospecting licence Drielly by telephone to ivir. Ballantyne this morning, when he asked if he coula come to discuss tne position further this afternoon. ArnendmeD-ts in Mining Lease . 2. Mr. Ballantyne on arrival said that he had received the Inaia Office letter of 11tn November, No.P.z.7189/33, covering a schedule of the amendments desired in the Bahrein Petroleum Company's mining lease, and stating that the .Sheikh nad raised the question of 'commercial exploitable Quantities' in Article IX of the mining lease in connection with the extension of the prospecting licence. The proposed amendments in the mining lease must of course be communicated for consideration to 3an Francisco. This would be done at once. I said we appreciated that reference to San Francisco would be necessary. Extension of Prospecting Licence . 3. we then turned to the question of the sheikh's reaction to the Company's proposals in regard to the extension of the prospecting licence. I said in the -irst place that, as I had already explained to him by telephone/- 2 - telephone, the Heaident had impressed upon us that tiie Company must hear in mind that they were dealing not with a business concern hut with an Arab Sheikh, who required ample time for consultation. We could confirm the Importance of avoiuiiib any appearance of trying to rush matters from our own experience in questions of a different character with rulers such as the Sheikh of Bahrein. Mr. Ballantyne said that he quite understood that the Sheikh uiu not wish to be rushea ana that the Company would understana it also. On the other hand they regarded themselves as having a gooa record in this matter. The question of the extension of the prospecting licence haci been under consideration for quite a long time ana they aia not think that it was their fault (though he aamittea that there were certain extraneous circumstances which might have had some weight in the natter) if the time was now as short as it was before December &lt;;na. I saia that we coula not accept that view. Had it not been for the unfortunate inciaents which had arisen in connection with Ivjajor Holmes' negotiations in the spring, this matter could have been settled at a much earlier date. At the same time, Just as it was unuesirable to enaeavour to rush the sheikh into any premature decision, so there was no aesire so far as we were concerned in the matter to be unreasonable. The Company haa until the 2na December to make up their minds. If they thought that a short further period would ease matters we shoula be quite ready to recommend to the Sheikh an extension of the period of the prospecting licence, perhaps for a fortnight, but at any rate not beyond the end of the present calendar year, for the purpose of negotiation only. An extension to the end of the/(0\ v - 3 - tha present calendar year would he an extension for practical purposes ot &amp; month. Any such extension would, of course, be subject to whatever legal formalities were necessary, and also to the understanding that it would form part of any extension of the prospecting licence which might be granted as the result of negotiation. Mr. Ballantyne said that no difficulty should arise on the question of legal formalities and that he would bear in mina our readiness to meet the Company on this point and would inform San Francisco accordingly. 4. I then saia that, as already explained to him by telephone, we understood that the sheikh regarded the financial offer put forward by tne Company as unsatisfactory. He (Mr. Ballantyne) had previously been warned that in our juagment the reduced offer of Rs.l lakh which had been made to the sheikh was less likely to prove acceptable to him than the figure of Rs.1,50,000 which had originally been mentioned. I was not at liberty to give him details of the financial terms on which the oheikh was prepared to consider the Company's proposals. These would be communicated direct through the Political .Agent to kr. skinner. 5. Mr. Ballantyne saia that he would await the details promised on this point. He was more concerned immediately on the question of 'commercial exploitable quantities' and would be glaa to know what the Sheikh's point was on this. I saia that I wished first to explain that in ny latter of 11th November, P.Z.7139/33, I had referred to the sheikh as having raised this question in connection with Article IX of the mining lease. We had not actually yet had the text of the Sheikh's letter and did not know wnat phrase he had used. But the Resident's telegram had not/- 4 - not in fact referred to the sheikh as raising the question in connection with c^ny particular article ol the mining lease, ani the pnrase occurred six times altogether in the mining lease. On the other hand, Article IX (with which possibly Article a ought to he hracketea) was, as I thought Lr. Ballantyne would agree, the material article of the mining lease and it was f~ • this reason that reference haa been made to it in my letter. Mr. Ballantyne said that he understood the position. Secondly, we were not quite clear as to what was in the Sheikh's mind, out so far as we could juage on the information available to us he was interested in two points: (a) a definition of the phrase; (h) the question of the earliest date at which the royalty of Rs.30,000 would 'become payable. 6. I vj* • Ballantyne would appreciate that under the mining lease as it stood the Sheikh, unless there was a declaration of production in commercially exploitable quantities at an earlier period than 5 years, coula not hope until that 5 years had elapsed for larger royalties than Rs.10,000 per annum. That might have been a reasonable figure and a reasonable understanding at the time when the agreement was first drafted in 1925. But matters had advanced since then and it was quite clear that the prospects of finding oil in Bahrein were probably substantially more important now than they had been at that aate. It was only natural in these circumstances that the sheikh, before wishing to conniit himself on the matter of the further extension, snould want to know where he stood on this question. He had, of course, the right in certain circumstances to appeal to /8/ - o - If* to arbitration ii he v/as dissatislied, but we thought his spontaneous raising of trie point was ui'iderstandable, and haa ourselves quite inaependentiy formed the opinion that some moaiiication of the provisions of the lease on this point might make for smoother working without very materially affecting the financial interests of the Company, we could give him technical advice on the question of definition: but if the Company were disposed to meet him, e.g. by agreeing that the minimum perioa unaer Article IX should be reduced to say 2 years, the question of definition might be less important to the Sheikh. 7. Mr. Ballantyne said that he had thought this was v^hat the Sheikh haa in nan a, ana was not surprised that the point should nave been raiseu. Speaking personally, he felt little doubt that the Company woula be prepared to give full weight to any view expressed by us in the matter, and that some arrangement might be possible of a nature satisfactory to all parties. But he thought, ana felt that the Company woula think the same, that the point v/as one which ought properly to be raised in connection with the amendments in the mining lease and not as a condition of an extension of the prospecting licence. He felt himself, in the light of the sheikh's reaction, that the Company would probably not be prepared to improve their offer and woula wish to take out their mining lease on 2nd December. They were in a position to ao so if necessary, but he must of course take their instructions and he would cable San Francisco this afternoon on the position generally in the light of our conversation.- 6 - 8. I said that it was entireiy ior the Company to aecide whether or not to take out the mining lease on 2nd December, and tnat he would no douht let us know once he ha.a been able to take their instructions. He was now aware of our attitude in regard to a possible short extension for the purpose of negotiation, but if the Company decided to take out the mining lease without further delay we, of course, coula raise no objection to their doing so. 9. Mr. Ballantyne then turned to my earlier statement that we were asking the Resident to authorise the communication of the sheikh 1 s comments to Mr. Skinner, and saia that he hoped we would tnink it unnecessary to raise the question of commercial exploitable quantities in any communiCcition on behalf of the sheikh to Mr. skinner. He thought Mr. skinner naa been rather hardly used in being required to put forward in writing an offer (even though a tentative one) on behalf of the Company and he was averse himself from making this question of commercial exploitable quantity the subject of a formal communication. 10. I said we coula not agree as to this. It would have been quite impossible for the Political A^ent to make himself responsible for passing on an oral offer to the sheikh in a matter of such Importance as the present ana he was clearly entirely right in requiring Lr* skinner to put his proposals in writing. The form in which those proposals had been put forward seemed to me a quite reasonable compromise from tne point of view of the Company. Equally it woula be impossible for us to agree that the Sheikh's reaction to their offer should not be communicated to Mr. Skinner. Hie offer had been made/made tnrough the Chief Local Representative, and the Sheikh 1 s reply to It must he made through him. We had uo consider not merely the Sheikh's position In the matter, hut also our own. It would clearly he most unsatisfactory from our point of view, as well as from uhat 01 the Sheikh, If the Company were, as Mr. Ballantyne had rather hinted was possible, not to withdraw an offer made In writing through Jvir. Skinner in Bahrein and decide to take out their mining lease on and December on the strength of conversations in London as to the oheikn 1 s reaction uo the offer made by Mr. Skinner and without any formal direct reply to Mr. skinner on behalf of tne Sheikh. While tne sheikh had asked for our advice, and we had taken advantage of this to give Mr. Ballantyne an outline of his views, we had no intention ox dispensing with a formal reply to Mr. skinner which we would to-day advise the Sheikh to send. 11. After some lurther discussion Mr. Ballantyne (who for some reason which was not clear appeared to attach importance to avoiding any written communication, at any rate as regards commercial exploitable quantity, from the Sheikh) abandoned his point. 13th November 1933. J.G. LAITHWAITE.r P.Z.7421/33. confident^ .. NOTE C? T.^T.KiPH QNE GQNVERHATION WITH H.ff . QM 15til NQVrCMBER 1933 . Ivlr. Baliantyna rang up to say that he had received a cahle dated 15th November from Ivir. skinner to the effect that he had received from the Political Ag6nt, Bahrein (either to-day or last night) three letters addressed hy the Sheikh to the Political Agent on the subject of the Company's application for an extension of their prospecting licence. The first, dated £ia November, stated that he would, be prepared to consider the extension ii the wnole sum of Rs#l lakh was non-recoverable. This was tne only stipulation. The second, dated 2na November, saia that he had asked the British Government for a definition of commercially exploitable Quantities. The third, dated 3rd November, stated that before considering the extension of the prospecting licence he wished to be clear on the point raised in the second letter. No mention was made in any of the letters of the rate of minimum royalty. ^ Mr. Bailantyne said he founa himself in a position oi some embarrassment. He had already instructed Mr. skinner that the Company would mke no further financial advance and that they were, on the other hand, prepared to meet the Sheikh over tne matter of the minimum royalty. He was now faced with this demand for an /extA? 75,000 rupees Injcasn/and was frankly at a loss to know what reply to send to hx. skinner. He did not suggest that we haa any knowleoge of tne existence of these letters, hut It would have been a great help to the Company If they had known, so long as a fortnight ago, what/ i- 2 . what the Sheikh's reactions were. 1 sa-id that his news was news to us, but that I unought the situation was as follows:- I had told him at our Interview on Ivlonaay that we should ask the Political Resident to Instruct the Political .vent at once to coiununlcate the Sheikh's reactions to the Company's offer to iwr. skinner. That presumably accounted lor the letter of 15th November. I had also told him that we were unable to give him details of the ohclidi o fliidnclal criticisms, but I coula now tell him thctt they hc»d liicluaed the recjuest that the whole sum of Bs.l lakh should be non-recoverable. There nad since been certain further developments in tnis matter with which i need not trouble him. Pmally, on the question ol tne coninierdaily exploitable quantities, I had explained to him that m did not quite know what was in -ne oiieikh's mind; that he had asked us for a definition ox 'commercially exploitable quantity' and that we uiought that he was Interested in this matter from two points of view: (a) dexinition, since the phrase occurred some six times in the mining iease; (b) the effect of the phrase in the lease on the coiniricncement oi his royalties at the rate of Ss.30,000. I had added that while we did not know what was in his mina it was conceivable that if tne Company were to meet aim over tne question of royalty, say by reducing the period -o two years, the question of definition might assume less importance from his point of view. i ' ile Company had subsequently intinated that r --iey were not prepared to make any further financial concession/m r v&gt;° - 3 - concessitn, 'but; had oifsred to pay the Hs.30,000 royalty as irtm the end tf the second year of the mining lease. Mr. skinner would presunBhly hy now have so informed the Sheikh, hut we had no information as to what the .Sheikh's reaction to this modification of the terms might he. a telegram which hud since heen received, however, haa made it clear to us that the question of commercial aeiinition was one to which he might attach great importance and that it would not he altogether disposed oi uy a modification in respect of royalties. So far as I coula understand without a technical knowledge of these matters, the Sheikh was disturbed because of the absence in the mining lease of any clauses governing the date of the declaration of commercial productivity, ana was no doubt disturbed lest the Company should postpone the declaration for a considerable period of time to his detriment. I understood that it was usual in oil concessions such as the present to cover this point, either by provision for a testTor by the provision of a dead rent so heavy as to make it in the Company's interest to declare commercial production at an early date. The iwining Lease contained at present no reference to a test, while Mr. Ballantyne would agree that the dead rent of ^s.30,000 was far too low to make a delay in the declaration of commercial production of much concern to the Company. The Sheikh's interest in the question of definition was therefore not unnatural. 5. Mr. Ballantyne said that discussion of the amendment of the mining lease to meet the Sheikh's difficulty as regards definition might lead us down a path lengthy and difficult/and would certainly take time, /' He/2 - 4 - did not, it may 'be added, rule out the possibility of discussion of it later, and before the conversation ended I again emphasised its great importance from the standpoint of the Sheikh. The wording of paragraph 4 of the India Office letter of 11th November, P.Z.7189/33, to Mr- Ballantyne affords a peg on which to hang a proposal to the Company for a provision in the Mining Lease to cover definition?. 6. He finally stated that he would telegraph again to Mr. Skinner tonight and see what developments there had been, and that we might discuss the natter further tomorrow. I emphasised that if he coula authorise Mr. Skinner to reassure the Sheikh as to the definition of commercial production, which it was clear was a point to which he attached real weight, it might facilitate a decision in the Company's favour as regards the extension of the procpecting licence. INDIA OFFICE. Ibth November 1933. J.G. LAITHWAITE.lo/ INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1. P.Z.7436/33. 16th November 1953. Ky dear Starling, In confirmation of our conversation this morning I enclose a copy of a note of a further telephone conversation to-aay with Ballantyne which is, I think, self-explanatory. He subsequently rang up, as arranged, to say that after further consideration of the representations which had been made to him the Company would be prepared; - (a) as a final financial concession to agree to increase the non- recoverable portion of the loan of 1 lakh to be made to the Sheikh to Ks.50,000, the extra Rs-M),000 to he allotted either to the State or to the Sheikh's private purse, as might think desirable. He suggested that if it was allotted to the Sheikh's private purse it might be preferable that it should be paid over a certain period in instalments; (b) to agree to the Political-Resident being informed that the desirability of an amendment in the mining lease on the question of the definition of commercially/ • Starling, Esq., Petroleum Department, Mines Department, Dean Stanley Street, S.Y/. 1.3/ ' - 2 - commercially exploitable quantities had been strongly pressed upon tnem; that they were prepared to consider very seriously an amendment to this effect, together with the other amendments in the mining lease which had already been put to them; that it was at the same time in their view quite impracticable to dispose of amendments oi this nature at such short notice, that they appreciated at the same time that it was to the interests as little of the Company as H.M.G, that relations with the Sheikh should not be cordial; that the Company had no intention of standing on the strict letter of the law; ana that they trusted that a statement on these lines would reassure the sheikh. Sallantyne aaded that he would to-day send instructions as above en clair to Mr, skinner and said that he sincerely hoped that the advance represented by this latest action of the Company would have the desired eifect. He strongly emphasised in conversation that the Company would be very reluctant to enter on their mining- lease leaving in the minds of H.M.G. and/or the Sheikh a ieeling that they had taken an unfair advantage or were behaving unreasonably,7o3&gt; - 3 - •i. We have telegraphed to Powle to let him know these further advances. Copies oX the telegram will be aistnbuted in the orainary way. we have promised to iollow up our telegram with a further telegram giving the gist of your advice on the point raised in his telegram T* 106 oi' 16th November and we propose (unless any unexpected development takes places) to ada to our telegram that having regara to the further advance made by the Company we think the sheikh can reasonably be recommended to agree to the extension for thirteen months desired by them, 4 - I am sending copies of this letter to Warner of the Foreign office and seal of the Admiralty. Yours sincerely, j.g. laiihwaits.3/ I {v£/ Ojr^ 30I-IFID£IvriAI, . P.Z. 7^/33. r NOTE OF A TELEPHONE CONVERSATION WITH MR. BALLANTY14E ON IHE 16th NOVEMBER. Consequent on the receipt of Colonel Fowls's telegram No.T. 106 ol 16th November I rang up iVir.Ballantyne and said that we had had this morning a further telegram from the political Resident which emphasised the importance attached by the sheikh of Bahrein to the oiuestion of the definition of commercial exploitable quantities. I did not know whether he haa been able to think of any method of reassuring the sheikh on this. It was quite clear that it might be a real stumbling block in the way of any extension. Mr. Ballantyne said that he did not find it easy to appreciate tne Sheikh's difficulty on the point. He had thought that the step actually taken in regard to the royalties payable under the mining lease should have reassured him. I would agree that the question of making an amendment to cover the present point in the mining lease in the short time now available would be almost out of the question. The amendments we had already suggested had been communicated to the Company: he would not guarantee that the Company would accept all or any of them ana they might, of course, have counter amendments of their own to suggest. The amendments in the mining lease ought to be aealt with comprehensively and he thought it almost impossible that any guarantee could be got from the Company to accept an amendment of the type we now had in mind at such short notice./' ( 'v^ ) lo\ - 2 - ^ • I said that ws dici not agree that the amendment was of academic importance only and repeated the explanation I had given him on this point, as recorded in the note of my conversation with him on the 15th Novernher, No. P..Z.7421/33, paragraph 4. Secondly, on the Question of time it was only fair to let him know that my authorities were inclined to think that we were being unfairly rushed by the Company over matters oi considerable importance. The sheikh was not unlikely to feel the same. The Company would no doubt bear in mind that if the sheikh felt that he was being unreasonably pressed it might have very awkward reactions on the position of the Company's whole concession ana agreement. I did not wish to develop that point, however. He would remember that we had indicated our readiness to recommend the sheikh to grant a short further extension of the prospecting licence for the purpose of negotiation onL&gt; Would it not really be better for the Company to consider this suggestion further? 4. Mr. Ballantyne said that it would certainly take more than a month to deal with the amendments which were now before the Company and that this question ought really to be considered with them. He did not think that an extension such as we suggested would be of any real value. He wished to say that the Company had no desire to aaopt an unreasonable attitude ana he thought that we had not found them unreasonable or disposed to quibble. It might well be, of course, that they would declare commercial production within twelve months. On the other nand the declaration might have to be delayed much longer. He was fully alive to the undesirability of doing anything which/toi ( - 3 - mlch would proauce an unsatisfactory impression on the Sielkh. At the same time he was still inclinea to think ohe point in issue not one of real substance and found it difficult to consider in what manner the Sheikh could he reassured. There would tie no point, for instance, in leading the Sheikh to entertain hopes which it might prove impossihle to realise on any point in connection with the amendments in the mining lease. I repeated that, whether rightly or wrongly, the Sheikh was obviously very suspicious on this particular point and that it was of importance from the Company's point of view to reassure him# I suggested that Mr. Ballantyne should think over the natter further and let me know in the course of the morning whether he could make any suggestion tp which we could refer in replying to the Political Resident. He replied that he saw great difficulty in the way, but would consider the matter further^ He then hinted at the possibility of some advance (by way of soothing the Sheikh) to meet H.E.'s request for a more generous finaneial coneession. I did not enter into this, but said we trusted he might find it possible to put forward a proposal which would advance matters. INDIA OFFICE. J.G, LAITHWAITE. 16th November 1953.2.0*7 t447a933. pstholajm dipahtmiajt, (MINiCS DSPAKTMENT), DSAtl 3TAI4LiS5f STESSI', MILLBANK, S.W.I. 1 Ifith Novarnbor, 1933. Dear Lalthwalta, With referanco to Fowle's tolsgram of 16th Novaribar (X.106) tha basis oX ixticlas IX and X la that at soma period not more than five yaare after tha grant of the mining lease the Company is required to make a declaration that oil has been fftium in 'coramarclally exploitable Quantities''. Nothing is said about ability to dispose of the oil. As the draft lease stands the declaration determines the time when the minimum payment to be made by the Company shall be increased from Rs.10,000 to Hs.30,000 and this pranuraably is the main reason for the provision. There is no apaciflc provision that having made the declaration the Company shfJLl produce oil on a coranercial scale. It is conceivable that an Arbitrator asked to consider this question might read into the first two lines of Article X. that when the declaration has been made the Company can reasonable be expected to start and to continue commercial production. What should constitute cocnercial production it would be difficult to say. Apart from the question of the general state of the world demand for oil, which Colonel Fowl a raises, the question of how and share the oil could be disposed of would arise. The Conpany might claim that they must ship the crude oil as there is no eubstantial local market and it would not pay then to erect a refinery. i-'or this they would have to make suitable shipping facilities. Or they mi ^it state that the only practicable method would be to build a refinery and to sell the refined products. To build a refinery would require time and the Company might argue that it would not pay them| TH ( thara to build a roflnery ualese they had an assured production ol a certain amount. on this the Petroleum Department could produce evidence based on other concessions whore a provision had been made that a refinery inust be erected when the production over a period of, say, si* months reached en annual rate of 100,000 tons. Two or three decent oil wells could nulte easily produce that Quantity. It would obviously be Very difficult to insert a provision in an oil lease to the effect that the lessee rihRll produce a specified minimum quantity of oil, even if it could be proved that that quantity of oil was readily available. On the other hand it may be nrgued that a lessee having acquired a concession and proved oil In coranorcially exploitable quantities cannot in equity retain the concession and decline to proceed to cortrnorclal production. If conditions are such that the lessee does not consider it profitable to work the oil he should either give up the concession or pay a reasonable mount to the lessor. in the draft lease the rninimum rant of Rs.30,000 payable after the declaration was presumably accepted by the 3hslkh as the consideration he ahould get if cormerclal production did not take place, and it seams not unlikely that an Arbitrator would so decide. But generally the minimum royalty Is of such dimensions as to afford an incentive to the lassee to proceed to commercial reduction. Clearly in this case it is not. It would be possible to test the real intentions of the Company by sug gesting a larger miniraum royalty. The ahelkh, while he doubtless would prefer to have oil produced, with all that its production Implies in additional employment, etc., would presumably not wish to be unreasonable if there were in fact a surfeit of oil in the world markets, and would be eatisfled if he secured a minimum royalty of araaeonabla amount* Whether such a point con be ralBQd hot or left until we discuss the emenclnentB to the mining lease, 1 must leave to you. tl Z am sending copies of this letter to Warner and Moore. Yours .'x., ( id) . ..ST. L j . ce f Qi&amp;rles street, London, Q.n.l.CONFIDENTIAL. No. G/id4 of 1933. ik' ,• The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to com- Lieut.^Colonel Gordon Looh, I.A., Political Agent, BaUrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s).^Ox irifcr atloii. Office of the Political Residen in the Persian G-ulf, Gamp, Bahrain. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 24th Novanher i933 Reference to previous correspondence ; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. !• India Office letter No. P.2;.7467/35 dated the r 'th Noveiiiher 1933. BAHRAIN OIL. 2. India Office letter No. Novemher 53 dated 1935. the 1 thIll Copy. Bj- Air Kali. No.i'.Z.7467/32. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL,3.¥. 1. 17tti Noveiiiber 1933. My dear Fowle, P. HI Many thanks,.your confidential d.o. ot 31st Qctoher N o .17 &lt;3£- S , aldout -Bahrain Oil, 2. As regards paragraph 2, I am sorry that tie record at the interview with Ballantyne did not make the position clear. As explained in paragraph 7 ot the i 1 Secretary of State's telegram No.2810 of 12th Kovemoer, || construction (a) is, of course, correct. We attach the greatest importance to maintaining the Political Agent as the sole channel for any communications, whether written or oral, oetween the Shaikh ana/ or Liis representatives and the Bahrain Petroleum Company, ana woula see very strong objection to any direct dealings with the Chief Local Hepresentative. 3. T need not deal with the remaining paragraphs of your letter as they are covered hy the official telegraphic correspondence which has since passed; though I may add, with reference to your telegrams T/lOo of 16th November and T.107 of 17th November, which we have just received, that, as you ^vill see from M the papers sent you by this week's air mail, the opportunity of a telephone conversation with Ballantynell ^ (f.tol on ihe lot:, Ncvealjer (l-.Z.'436/33) was taken to impress ] upon him that the Company's whole position in regard to this concession might be prejudically affected if the Shaikh felt that he was being unreasonably pressed as regards the extension. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe. ^'We Lt.Col. ;/0 yif &gt;C.B,E., L - s Political Agent,Bahfcaip. - Yours sincerely, ( sd» )J•0,Lax thwaite. -BY A.TR MAIL INi)IA om cs, WHITEHALL. P.Z. 7473/33. My dear Fowle, Ylould you kindly refer to paragraph 1 of the note of my conversation with Ballantyne on the 15th November, of which coDies are sent by this week f s air mail under our No. P.Z. 7421/33? We have of course so far only Ballantyneaccount as therein recorded of the method in which the Sheikh^ views were communicated to the Chief Local Representative and it is possible that there may be some misunderstanding, particularly as it appears to be based merely on a telegram from Skinner• But by way of settling a procedure in future cases of this nature we should be glad if you would consider the following suggestions and let us know whether you see any objection to them. 2. Vie hu^'gest that the simplest course would, if you agree, be that the Sheikh should in the first place in asking for our advice, indicate his own reaction to the/ Hon f ble Lt.Col. T.GJL Fowle, C^B.E., c/o Political A^ent, Bahrein. 17th November, 1933.2-13 W) the proposition before him; that on the receipt ol our advice he should further consider the position and should then (unless he wishes to refer further on any point to Hi^ Majesty ! s Government or the Resident.) embody his final views in a comprehensive letter to the Political Agent. The Political Agent would not pass on that letter in original to the Chief Local Representative, but would embody its substance (with any modifications that might be thought desirable - in the case of modifications of importance only, of course, with the Sheikh's concurrence) in a letter under his own signature to the Representative stating that the Sheikhviews were as followed. This was the course which was adopted in August in connection with the Sheikh of Bahrein ! &amp; refusal to grant a further extension of the prospecting licence (compare G&amp;&amp;trell f s letter of 21st August, No. 0.355, of which copies were sent under Bushire despatch of 29th iiugust, No,.ll29-S). It of course, the obvious advantage that it leaves the Gompany in the dark as to the original reaction of the Sheikh and the nature of any advice which may subsequently have been tendered to him by His Majesty^ 'Government/Government, and that it enables us if necessary to modify any of phrase in letters written by His Excellency or the Financial Adviser which might give rise to misunderstanding or expose surface. (It might well have been slightly eebarrassing in the present case had the suggestions in paragraph 4 of the Secretary of State's telegram i ?o.2810 dated 13th November been communicated to the './heiih ana had Hie Excellency then followed up his letters of «id and 3rd Novender by a further letter embodying them and communicated to the Company by the Political Agent, since it would probably have been fairly clear to the Company that those suggestions were suggestions put forward by His Majesty's Government). As you Icnow, the Foreign Office are most anxious to avoid any risk of trouble with the United States Government over these Gulf oil concessions, and we feel sur^ you will agree that while maintaining as effective a control as possibl the more we can keep the degree and nature of our interference/interference or of the advice which wc tender entirely under cover the better. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe. yours iiiuuarsly, J. G. LAITHWAITE. iAIR KAIL. i....Ho.o/£07 of 1933. &gt;'1 Office of th.3 iolUlofl Hesldent in the Persian Gulf 9 Oaaap, Bahrain* 2dth November 1953. D Please refer to your clealrofflclal letier Ko.i. u.7473/33, dated the IVth Novamber 1933, reiaraing the procedure to be followed in oomnivinicating the Shaikh of Bahrain*3 Yiews on any subject to the Chief Local Bepresentatiye! Bahrain Petroleum Company limited* ilm 2. In the particular instance referred to (Looh*© letter cf 15th to Skinner) Looh and 1 hjfe as a matter of fact discussed the relative advantages of sending a sumiuary from ourselves f or copies 31 the Shaikh's letters, and decided in favour of the latter* 3* 1 Quite appreciate, honever, the very natural desire of the Foreign Office to avoid any risk of trouble with the United ^tatoa* Crovemment over Oulf Oil Concessions, and I agree with the procedure suggest ed in paragraph 2 of your latter, up to the stage of the iolitical Agent's communication to the Chief Local Representative of the ahaikh's final views. This, I think, should not embody the substance ox the ataikh's communioation, hut should forward a copy of the Lhaikh v s actual letter in order to ensure that both the Jcmpany and the Chaikh should be quite certain that the latter's views have gone to the former as actually pennea by tb«/ ®. Lalthsalte The India Offioe, Lonaon*Translation of letter dated the 4th Sha'ban 1352(22.11.33) from His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin ^sa al Khalifah,c*S,I., Huler of Bahrain to Colonel Loch, Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, l have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.532 dated the 3rd Shaman 1352(equivalent to 21st November 1933) enclosing a copy of the Agreement which was entered into between me and the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, copy of which v/as sent to the Adviser of ray Government, for which i thank you very heartily usual ending.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001f7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/392</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001f7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/392</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/1 (Vol V) Oils and Minerals. Bahrain Oil Concession.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (294 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the volume are arranged in chronological order. There is an index at the end of the volume (folios 272-282). The index is arranged chronologically and refers to documents within the volume; it gives brief description of the correspondence with a reference number in ink crayon or pencil, which refers back to that correspondence in the volume.</extent><extent>The main foliation is written in pencil, encircled and can be found in the top right of the recto of each folio. The numbering starts at the first page of writing, then 69, 70a, 70b, and carries on until 282, which is the last number given on the last page of writing (6th folio from the back of the volume). There is also another foliation system, which is inconsistent.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume mainly contains correspondence and telegrams between the Political Agent at Bahrain, the Political Resident at Bushire, the Secretary of State for India, the Adviser to the Government in Bahrain, Charles Darlymple Belgrave, and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) on the Bahrain Oil Concession, on a refinery to be built on Bahrain Island, and on the affairs of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. The volume also contains correspondence on the resignation of Major Frank Holmes from Chief Local Representative of BAPCO, who was replaced by E. A. Skinner. There are also letters in Arabic to and from the Sheikh of Bahrain, Hamad Bin Issa Al-Khalifah. There is an index at the end of the volume (folios 272-282).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Ḥamad bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah, Hakim of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Bahrain Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia Sa'ūd bin 'Abd al-'Azīz Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001f7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>