<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:13:28.990Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">for enclosure. Political Resident’s despatch No.1090-3 dated the 24th August 1933 to the foreign Secretary to the Government Inc- la. Kuv;ai+ of a Persian suhjec 4 - Saiyid Abdul Aziz Behbahani.I II is requested that in any farther commu/ni- ! ration on this subject the under.mentioned letter and number may be quoted, aryl the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. W. 1. P. g&gt; 4731/5; INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, 8.W. 1. 50*11 1933 • With ref«r*ii&lt; 3 * to ?or«lgii Off io# lottor i&lt;o. T*8117/633/371 of 3rd A.ugu«t X 955 regarding o request toy the i erei«u OoTemment that a certified oopy of a judgment given toy the Court of V{.eal of Kjiusietan and Kerman may toe served upon a certain Abdullah Safar in Ke«eit # X am directed toy the Secretary of State for India to eay that in the 0 i ro mas tone ee explained he ooneure in the proposal of the Secretary of state for foreign Affaire to treat the caee # in the eame way ae the previous oaee, referred to in your letter* I aft 9 Sir* four obedient Servant* Sd.) J. C. WALTON..‘••-'. V.-■&gt;. 4 T HIR directed fey 9 f?cr&lt; 3 tary ‘ Ip «&gt; r fekn Simon to tPanamlt to you bapfc^lth, to fe« laid before Secretary Sir Saak*! i.oar«t a copy of a deapatch from hia ^jeaty'a Charge d’Affairaa at Tehran on the subject of a re quest from the . eraian Ooeemiat.nt that atepa should fee taken for the axtradition from Koweit of one lieyed jVf&gt;dul-A«U Behbahani, believed to fee a %raian subject. 2« The case appear# to have «uch in common with recent requests froa the eraiin Oovemaumt for aaaiatanci** in securing the service of eraian writs upon residents in r.oweit, i nd Sir John Simon proposes, aufejeot to the concurrence of Sir i^muel Hoare, to instruct *r. Millet to inform the eraian Ooveromunt in r« ily that as the relations between R©w&lt;&amp;lt and i arala have not yet feeen regularised he is unable to afford any assistance in the matter* I am#u CONFIDENTIAL. Q ' L /L • U No. ibxo-S of 1953 . ^ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to me political A^ont, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...oer 1955.V 4th November, 1933. No. 667. Monsieur le Mlnietre, with reference to his Highness Mirza Manomeu Ali Khan Feroughi’s note No. 16762 of Tir 26th (July 16th, 1933), I have the honour to inform Your Excellency, under instructions from His Majesty's Principal secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that as the relations between Kowelt and Persia have not yet been regularised it is not possible for His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom to afford any assistance in the matter of the extradition from Kowelt of Seyed Abdul- Aziz Behbehanl. 2. The documents enclosed in the note-verbale of Your Excellency's department No. 24166 of Shahrivar 28th, 1312, (September 19th, 1933), relating to the request for extradition are returned herewith. X avail myself of this opport unity to renew to Your Excellency the assurance of my highest consideration. (Signed) V.A.L. Mallet.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/299</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/299</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 7/2 II Service of Summonses, Documents, etc, in Kuwait Vol. 2’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-18T18:14:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, the exceptions being enclosures which are often of an earlier date than their covering letters.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 3-19; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file is concerned with two extradition requests from the Persian Government for two individuals believed to be residing in Kuwait: Saiyid Abdul Aziz Behbahani and Abdulla Safar. The principal correspondents being the Kuwait Political Agent, the Persian Gulf Political Resident (Gordon Loch), the British Chargé d'Affaires at Tehran (Alexander Louis Mallet), and officials of the India Office and the Foreign Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Deportation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00014e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>