<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00005c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:07:54.848Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FILE COPY Personal* CONFIDENTIAL . XX 2544 19 4 lj The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to R.T.Peel Esquire, The India Office, London, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document British Consulate-General, BUSHIBE. Dated 5th April, 1941* Name and Date. Subject. Personal letter dated the 5th April 1941 to the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, with enclosure* Impressions of Iraq* RECd. ROL. DEPt. i 6 'i AY 941 INDIA OFFICE-tv r rer e onal « Confidential* P '7 ^ % © 2644 194 1 Office of the Political eaident in the lergi&amp;n Gulf, Camp, bbthrui n • Dated the 5th April, 1941* Dear Caroe, I am sending you a copy of a personal letter that I have received from Galloway which explains itself* ijiyerything that 1 saw on my recent flying visit to Ira&lt;i confirmed Galloway's impressions* ^s I crossed the frontier from Kuwait the gu«rd who checked cars (Bedouin from Hail and evidently bin x^ashid's men) on finding out who 1 was immediately begged me 'to honour them by having coffee with them** It is a tragedy that eo much good will should have been frittered away* 1 am sending a copy to ^cel for his information* 0*K.Caroe Asstulre, 0*&amp;*X•§0• X*Jb*,I• *b, secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Kew Delhi*Tb«y war# obviously frlwodXy ot wa should not here bean l»vtted and X gathered that th#y weru «ma ihey mac ao bones of saying that they thought their own Govermont corrupt, end ranch preferrea the order we had enforced* -t# The ~&gt;h&amp;lithe were even store friendly, and did all in their power to saoke the day** ehc-otins over their Inndfl a euccoea* ^&gt;o far a a I could make out they were not in contact with any drltlah Offieittl but were outapoken encugh to c*e, and cid not try to hide their contact of their own local officials whose peculation* in all aiattera connected with their land and crops disgusted ther,* end whom they looked upon *e a plague of locusts* They were pretty oontwaptuoue of the mtiah, too, for huving gained so mmb at such great cost and for having given it t*mx/ to a handful of Iraqi famiiie©. There wee a lot or rainy weather on these trips ©o we had plenty of ti^e to talk* 5. Beyond taa Governor of /aaarat the only local official X met was a folio# Commissioner, and one or two of hi© underling® hut the/ too were friendly a&amp;ci tno of a uot of o&amp;rtrid^es ©nd an invitation to join a £d;u)t started a train of friendly relations* ii0 * us t before star ting; my last trip the return of Corawulii® a© -oabasyador had been announced, and there was ^ueh tal* of hiti. He is, of eourae, wall knon § apparently liked and eotjewhet feared, as* the Shaikh a wanted to he in Baghdad to meet him* One eon w&amp;© particularly anxious to get his word in first for Cornwallis had apparently taken a lot of merest In bim an* the rice /growla*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00005c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/510</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00005c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/510</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 2544/41 'Galloway's "Impressions of Iraq".'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-06T22:14:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a personal letter written by Captain Arnold Crawshaw Galloway, Political Agent, Kuwait, providing impressions he formed of British/Iraqi relations after meeting Iraqi Government Officials, local Shaikhs and others informally while on shooting trips.The letter is forwarded, with comments, by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, and to the India Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Arnold Crawshaw Galloway</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Bilateral relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00005c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>