<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002a5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T10:55:52.196Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE &lt;™St l ) limited Mk w. FHASBR. C.B.E.. C. 8. GUU8NKIAN (FORMERLY ARMENIAN) *’ (rnTioii). H. &lt;3 seiovL Wr»,A.&gt;. r. w. Sellers. J. Skliros R-cU MorJuUfi*' 6th March, 1946. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Through H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. I* SHARJAH OIL AGREEMENT 1937 AMENDMENT TO PARA B OF SCHEDULE N6.1 (Drilling Qhligationr We have the honour to forward herewith a signed copy of the Amendment dated the 26th February 1946 to Sharjah Oil Agreement dated the 17th September 1937, which extends the period within which drilling should commence from nine to fifteen years. 2. We shall be pleased if you will acknowledge receipt in due course. 3. The Ruler of Sharjah has a signed copy and we have also sent a similar signed copy to our Managing Director, London. 4. As far as we are concerned, this brings the matter to a satisfactory conclusion. We have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servants, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED. Enel. 1 , MANAGERGOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL), smimim [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message tent by AIR MAIL which provide* a Tn . eana / . 0 / expeditious than the ordinary mail and it cheaper than the tekgraph. It xt xn ended to be ire^ed, on receipt, with the same expedition at if it had been telegraphed To save tune ^ to o6ma/« formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 321-i Dated -rf §ii i¥r: iersisji Gulf K&lt;**ld6ncy f Budhlr# • iq the 27th Inarch 1946, To i India Gfflc#, Loidoru i*epe«ited Gcvermsront of India, New Delhi* v' Political agent, Bahrain. ^ / TvpfftrpnPA yoar raierenc fi* taiegraa No. 2903 dated 9th Pebruary 1946. 2. Copy is enclosed of letter No. T3A. 16/4166 dated 6th iiarch 1946 froa the i^nager, Petroleua Jevelopaent (Trucial Co&amp;at) Limited, Bahrain, without its ©rxlosure. 3. As no spare copies of the rrac3csure have been received, I shall be grateful if, while obtaining a copy for your records from the Company’s Head Office in LoivJon, three spare copies could be Obtained and forwarded to the Government of India, the Political Agont, Bahrain and this Residency. sd. GKorouar prior Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Ip l / for Secretary to Political Resident, Persian Gulf. (Signature) (Designation, S. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;P—(M-1870/—9-2-39—20,000.Copy of Demi-Official letter No.C352.0205 dated 28.3.1946 from Captain R.C. Murphy, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, to the political Agent, Bahrain. Will you kindly refer to para 28(iii) of my News Report No.4 of 1946. 2. I enclose a copy with translation of the agreement concluded between the Shaikh of Sharjah and Shaikh Muhammad bin Ali bin Huwaidin and Ali bin Abdullah bin Huwaidin, Chiefs of the Beni Qitab, regarding the income derived from the oil concession. 3. The Shaikh of Sharjah has paid Muhammad bin Ali and other members of his family their share for 6 months of the annual payment received from the P.C.L. It remains, however, to be seen if he will continue to fulfil his undertaking if and when oil is extracted in commercial quantities. 4. This agreement, which is the first of its kind on the Trucial Coast, will probably have repercussions on other tribes resulting in demands for similar agreements from their respective Shaikhs. Shaikh Ali bin Rashid as-Saman, Chief of a sub-section of the Beni Qitab named al-Massa»id, has already made such a demand which has, of course, been rejected by the Shaikh of Sharjah. ENCLOSURE . In the name of God, the Compassionate and the Merciful. Be it known to whoever may see this document that, having a desire to help my friends, the Beni Qitab, I have granted (agreed with) shaikh Muhammad bin Ali that when, if God is willing, oil etc. come out to our mutual advantage, I shall not deprive him of any income and to give him one- third of the yield after expenses. This is in return for their compl^iance with my special orders and their protection of the Company's interests. They should be obedient to me whenever any necessity arises as has been the case since the time of our ancestors. God is the best witness. ^igned and Sealed. Thumb impression of Sultan bin Saqr. Muhammad bin Ali bin Huwaidin. Seal of Muhd. bin Saqr. Thumb impression of Seal of Saqr al-aasim. Ali bin Abdullah bin Huwaidin. Witnessed by:- Said bin Abdullah, 'Amir bin Salih, Ma'dhad bin Ali bin Abdullah, Said bin Huwaidin, and Muhammad Hadi Awadhi. No.C/367 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 7th of April, 1946 Forwarded with compliments to: i The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002a5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/703</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002a5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/703</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Confdl. 86/49-(i). Sharjah Oil.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-09T12:07:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-6; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises of a letter from Ernerst Vincent Packer, Manager for Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Charles Geoffrey Prior) enclosing a copy of an amendment to the Sharjah Oil Concession agreement agreed with Sheikh Shaikh Sulṭān bin Saqr Āl Qasimī. The amendment is in Arabic and English.Also enclosed is a letter from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast (Raymond Clive Murphy) to which includes details of an agreement reached between the Shaikh of Sharjah and the Chiefs of the Beni Qitab, which would grant Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited permission to operate in Beni Qitab territory in return for a share of the income derived from the oil concession agreement.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Abu Dhabi Company for Onshore Oil Operations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Beni Qitab (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Sharjah</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002a5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>