<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:23:34.328Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■mb;- * VNOTES. (1) The leading authorities on eaeh sub-section are given in a note at tie beginning of the sub-section. (2) The spelling in this precis is not unifor n. The names are spelt as found in the various authorities, who of course follow different systems of trans literation. In the Gazetteer the spelling will be made uniform, and to facilitate this it is hoped that investigating officers will gi^e the equivalent in Arabic characters of every name. (3) Population is a point which requires special attention. Some authori ties give total number of inhabitants ; some (able-bodied ?) “ men ” (=^ to f of total population); others only fighting strength. (4) It will greatly facilitate compilation of the Gazetteer if investigating officers frame their reports according to the following numbered syllabus, which has been adopted where possible in the present precis :— Tracts (1) Boundaries. (2) Subdivisions. (3) Physical geography. (i) Climate and seasons. (5) Communications, vit.— {a) Routes. (b) Distances. [c) Stages. [d) Supplies. (e) Transport. (6) Trade, viz .— (а) Products. (б) Internal trade. (c) Imports. (d) Exports. (e) Commercial centres. (/) Coinage. G) Weights. (A) Measures. Mountains, (1) Position. (6) (2) General direction and configuration. (7) (3) Elevation. (S) (4-) Height and names of peaks. (9) (5) Snow-line. (10) (11) Valleys. (1) Position. G) (2) Extent and direction. (5) (3) Slope, surface and general character. (0) (7) Districts. (7) Population, viz .— (а) Number. (б) Races and tribes. (c) Chai’acter. (d) Religion. (e) Mode of life. (/) Occupations. (g) Language. {h) Customs. 0) Fighting strength. (;) Arms. (8) Administration— (a) Police and army. (£) Criminal justice. (c) Civil justice. (&lt;/) Land revenue. (&lt;?) Taxes. {/) Officials. (g) Relations oi civil and religious authorities. (/5) Genealogy and personal details of ruling or leading families. Spurs and offshoots. Geology. Vegetation and animals. Population. Routes and passes. Valleys and lines of drainsgo, Climate. Tributary valleys. Resources. Population,Inhabited Places. (1) Position geographically and politically. (2) Character of site and general description of place. (3) Defences. (4) Number of population. (5) Tribes, religions and occupations. (1) Position. (2) Shape and extent. (3) Surface and general character. (4) Resources. ( 6 ) Industries, markets and trade. (7) Resources in water, food, forage and transport. (8) Local shrines. (9) Religious, charitable and educational institutions. (10) Administration and government. (11) Historical facts. Islands. (5) Population. (6) Mainland to which belonging (where doubtful). (7) Administration. (1) Origin and political faction. (2) Subdivisions. (3) Numbers and habitat. (4) Character andjippearance. (5) Religion. (6) Mode of life. Simla ; 24th November 1904. Tribes. (7) Occupations. (8) Language. (9) Customs. (10) Fighting strength. (11) Arms. (12) Government and political matters. J. G. LOEIMER.A— TRUCIAL CHIEFS’ TERRITORY. The principal charts and maps for this subsection are (i) Admiralty Charts Nos. 2373-2837 0 , and 2374-2837 6, Persian Gulf, published 1862 and corrected to 1903. (ii) Admiralty Chart No. 2375-753, Entranoe of the Persian Gulf, published 1872 and corrected to 1898. (iii) Map of Parts of Arabia and Persia, in 2 sheets, 12th July 1883. (iv) Ross's Map of Oman, showing distribution of the Principal Tribes, No. 1, 815*1.&gt; 1901. (v) George Philip and Son's Map of Arabia, the Red Sea and the valley of the Nile. The principal authorities are (1) Niebuhr's u Description de I'Arabie,” 1774, pages 283-284. (2) Buckingham's “ Travels in Assyria, Media and Persia,” 1829, pages 476-504. (3) Whitelock’s Account of the Arabs who inhabit the Coast between Ras-el-Khaima and Abuthabee in the Gulf of Persia, generally called the Pirate Coast,' in the transactions of the Bombay Geographical Society, 1836-38, pages 32-45, followed by his “ Description of the Arabian Coast,” pages 46-49. (4) Whitelock’s “ Sketch of the Islands and Coast situated at the Entrance of the Persian Gulf ' in the Journal of the Royal Geographical Society, 1838, pages 182-184. (5) Wellsted's “ Travels in Arabia,' 1838, Volume I, pages 236-269. (6) Mignan's “ Winter Journey,' 1839, Volume II, pages 213-229. (7) Wellsted's “ Travels to the City of the Caliphs,' 1840, Volume I, pages 93-126. (8) Bombay Records, Selection XXIV, 1856, pages 13-17 and 456-458. (9) Binning's c ‘Journal of Two Years' Travel in Persia, Ceylon, etc.,' 1857, Volume I, pages 133-136. (10) Palgrave's “ Narrative of a Year's Journey in Central and Eastern Arabia,' 1865, Volume II, pages 257, 297-318 and 322-326. (11) Goldsmid's “ Telegraph and Travel,' 1874, pages 134-151. (12) Miles’“ Note on Pliny's Geography, etc,,' in the Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society, 1878, pages 157-172. (18) Curzon's (t Persia,' 1892, Volume II, pages 446-452. (14) Douglas’s “Journey from India to the Mediterranean,' 1897, page 8. (15) The Persian Gulf Pilot, 1898, pages 66-114. (16) Zwemer's “ Arabia,' 1900, pages 82-83. (17) Zwemer's “ Three Journeys in Northern Oman ' in the Geographical Journal, January, 1902, pages 54-64. (18) Cox’s letter No. 290 of the 2nd July 1902, included in the Government of India's Political Proceedings Secret E. for November 1902, Nos. 7-21. (19) Kemball's notes on the Trucial Chiefs.forwarded to Foreign Secretary with his demi- oihcial letter of 30th October 1903. (20) Cox's notes on his journey from Abu Thabi to Muskat, forming part of No. 101 of Government of India's Political Pros. Ext. B , for December 1903. (21) Government of India's Political Records, Persian Gulf Administration Reports and Gulf Residency Diaries. [It is known that Lieutenant Chester, I.N., traversed the route from Sharga to Bereymi in both directions in 1855 and that Lieu ten ant-Colonel Disbrowe and Lieutenant Powell, I.N., made a journey fiom Dibba to Ras-al-Khaima in 1865, a sketch map of their route being afterwards lithographed in Bombay. The reports of these officers and the sketch map have not yet been traced.] r (C912FD)mhmmbmh 2 AJMAN.—Town. (1) On Pirate Coast 12 miles 8. 8. W. from Umm«ul- Kawain; independent. (2) On south side of entrance to creek, most accessible on coast, having bar of sand instead of rock with 5 feet at low water. Anchor age at sea off Ajman had. (3) Small high fort with towers. (4) 1,500 inhabi tants in pearling season, 4 bunnias. (5) Naim, Mahami section, many of whom migrate to Bereymi in date season. (6) Sends 60 boats to pearl-fishery. (7) water bad; wells 1 mile south-west of town. (8)—(10) Not clear whether there is any district or subject village belonging to Ajman. AKABAH —Village. (1) At north-west corner of bay of same name on east side of Ruus-el-Jebel promontory, connected with Lima by short land path. (2) (3) (4) Population 80 or 90. (6)—(11), AKLET-EN-NAKHLET.—Halting place on route from Bereymi to Hasa, one stage West of Sil. There is sweet water. Place lies among sand-hills and belongs to Manasir and A1 Morrah. ALI (AL BU).—Tribe at Umm-ul-Kawain. ALI (JEBEL).—Only landmark on Pirate Coast. Elat-topped hill, 220 feet high, 4 miles from sea, about 20 miles south-west of Dabai. ANKEH.—Hamlet of Beni Kattab in Beinoona District, with date-trees and cultivation and good water in shallow pits. Second stage on western route from Bereymi to Hasa. AWAMIR.—Tribe said to be subject to Sharga. Are these the same Awamir as in Oman ? AWEYNEH.—Third stage on western route from Bereymi to Hasa, two days from the sea. Water is plentiful but brackish and wells deep. There are acacias and camel-fodder. BADI (or BADIYA V).—Village. (1) On Shameiliya coast about 5 miles north of Khor Eakan in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) — (10). BAINNON.—Village near Leewa, attacked by Shekh of Katar in 1888. BAIZA (KHOR-AL).—Village. (1) On Pirate Coast, 3f miles north-east from Umm-ul-Kawain, in territory of Umm-ul-Kawain. (2) On seaward side of an island separated from main by Khor-al-Baiza creek. Date-grove to west of village. (3) Small fort. (5) —(10). Note. —It is not clear that village is called Baiza. BAKHA.—Village. (1) Five miles south of Ras-ah Jadi on west coast of Ruus-al-Jabal promontory in Ras-ul-Khaima district of Sharga. (2) In shallow sandy bay open to northward. Behind village is plain with cultivation and date groves, and there are dates between Bakha and Jadi. (3) Square fort on hillock £ mile east of town, and one on west point of bay visible 9 or 10 miles, third fort in ruins. (4) (5) Shihiyyin and Tannagi. (6) Chiefly fishing. ( 7 )—( 10 ). BATHNA.—Fort (or village ?) in hills commanding land route from Sharga to Fujaira. BEIAH.—Or Baiya. Frequently referred to as a Shihiyyin village assist ing headman of Fujaira against Chief of Sharga. It is same as Badlor Badiya. If so, what is correct form ? BUNEYYAN.—Place wdth water between Katar and Oman where Ejman and allied tribes were defeated in 1884 by Al Morrah and Manasir. BEINOONA.—District on route from Bereymi to Nejd, adjoining Oman district of Jow. In it is situated Ankeh. BEREYMAN.—Place 3 hours* distance south of Ojair. CHUTUB (BENI).—Tribe which in 1875 sought protection of Chief of Dabai against raids by Manasir and Beni. Hajir. Buckingham speaks of Beni Chittib.DAAFIS.—Grassy, watered vale ia Dhafreh district, two days from the sea, visited in season for pasture by Manasir, Awamir, Beni Yas, Beni Kattah, Mizariyeh (?) and Ghafileh nomads. There is brackish water in deep wells. Ground is low with acacias, scrub and grass. DABAI.—Town. (1) Last southwards on Pirate Coast about 7 miles south of Sharga ; independent. (2) A little back from shore and higher than most towns on this coast, being 20 feet above sea; date-grove behind town extends 1 mile to south of it. Sheikh’s house is high square castle with tall round tower at south-west corner. Reef stretches from Dabai some distance towards Abu Hail. Creek with shallow and difficult entrance passes town and extends for miles to south-east. Palgrave described Dabai as unfortified, strangling village with gardens, wells, and many boats. (3) Sheikh’s tower and 8 or 9 smaller towers in town and suburbs. (4) Population with Deira suburb 5,000 to 6,000 (Gulf Pilot, 1898), 3,000 to 4,000 (Kemball, 1903), with 50 or €0 Hindus and Khojas. Zwemer says population is now 15,000 at least. He calls it a growing town and the real metropolis of North Oman. (5) Abu Felasa section of Beni Yas, belonging to Maliki sect. (6) Sends 160 boats to pearl fleet which employed on other fisheries in winter. Present Chief intelligent, and town increasing. Curzon says dried fish, pearls and dates are exported. Steamers of Bombay and Persia *Steam Navigation Co. call regularly and port is supplanting Linga as entrep&amp;t for Arab Coast. (7) Presh water in wells behind town; cattle and poultry procurable. (8)—10). Uncertain what are boundaries of Chiefs authority. Kemball says it only extends inland short way, but that Chief could command services of some Bedouins of interior. p ? —Small village with date trees sprung up few years since, 4 miles south-west of Dabai—see Gulf Pilot, 1898, page 94. DALMA.—(1) South point 24° 27' N. 52° 19' E. Lies almost on line from Abu Dhabi to Khor-al-Odaid twice as far from former as from latter. (2) Elliptical with long axis north and south and narrow projection at south end; length 5, breadth 2£, miles. (3) Hilly with very low, narrow plain at south end, highest point 2U feet. (4) Plenty of brackish water in wells, many goats. Red oxide said to exist. (5) 15 families located in little village and tower on west coast of plain Bazaar and large temporary population in summer, as pearlers resort here for water. Great centre for pearl boats and one of princi pal pearl markets in Gulf. (6) Trucial Chiefs* Territory. (7) Abu Dhabi. DEIRA.—(1) Suburb of Dabai town (q.v ). (2) Stands opposite main town on east bank of entrance to Dabai Creek. All mat huts. (3) Few towers on north side. (4) Population 400. (5) Suidan refugees who left Sharga in 1826. (6)—(10). DHABI (ABU) —Town. (1) 24° 29' N. 54° 21i' E. At western base of Oman promontory, independent town, capital of principality extending to Khor- al-Odaid. (2) On a low shore, all white sand, without vegetation except few stunted date trees one mile inland of town. Town extends two miles along shore; huts of matting with several conspicuous stone buildings. ^ Laffan creek and Abu Dhabi creek, three miles west of town, unite and make island of land on which town stands: one ford, called Maktaa, to mainland at low water. Abu Dhabi creek, three miles wide at entrance, unexplored, reaches perhaps 20 miles into interior. Large vessels anchor 2 to 2| miles out. lor anchorage see plan on chart No. 2837A. (3) Small fort with six towers close together and small tower on beach. (4) Population 4,000 fluctuating (Kemball, 190o) ; not over 10,000 (Zwemer, 1902) ; 20,000 (Gulf Pilot, 1898) ; also 50 Hindu traders, or (according to Zwemer) a dozen Banyans from Sind. (5) Beni Yas (6) Sends 600 boats to pearl fishery and at other seasons Abu Dhabi fishing boats found everywhere to Khor-al-Odaid. Pearl-fishing, date-growing, and camel- transport are chief means of livelihood. (7) Water brackish, good water brought for sale from Dabai. Cattle obtainable. (8)—(19)* DHABI (ABU).—Principality. (1) Limits are on west. Khor-al-Odaid ; east, Berevmi; N, ? S. ? (2) (3). Between Dabai and Abu Dhabi shore is low and uni form in appearance with tufts of grass growing on sand-hillocks, intersected by creeks and in parts bj extensive swamps. No tree larger than mangrove bush. Nommmmmmmmmmrn WWBBIHggH—— 4 settled inhabitants, but prowling Bedouins from interior. From Abu Dhabi to Wakra (coast line of 250 miles) no fixed inhabitants nor single house. Coast low and sandy or stony with here and there rocky hills, or sandhills, of moderate height. Water scarce and indifferent. Beni Y as, Beni Hajir, and Manasir occasionally visit coast. (4) — (8) Kemball says about 5,000 Bedouins acknow ledge Abu Dhabi, but pay no tribute. DHAFREH.—District beyond Beinoona on route from Bereymi to Hasa. Contains vale of Daafis and is inhabited chiefly by Manasir. DHAID or THEYD,—Place inland from Sharga. Apparently uncle of present Chief of Sharga has date-groves there. DHARIJ.—Town belonging to Sheikh of Naim, attacked by Manasir and Beni Hajar in 1875. DHOAN (KHOR).—Inlet on coast immediately south of Odaid. Supposed mouth of Wadi Sohba. D HUN HA.—See Ross’s Map of Oman, near Dibba. DIBBA.—Town. (1) On Shameiliya coast, northernmost place in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) Stands on west shore of sandy bay five miles in breadth, open from N. N. E. to E. Extensive date plantations in valley south of town. (3) Fort called Jilla Hirshi. (4) Population 2,000. (5) South portion, Nakbiyyin section of Sharkiyyin ; north portion, Shihiyyin. (6) Supplies Bedouins of inte rior with grain. (7) Water good, cattle excellent, vegetables ^ fair. (8)—(10). Sharkiyyin portion is fief of relation of Sharga Chief; Shihiyyin portion is under a Sheikh appointed by the tribe to control motley and fluctuating population. DUBEYKHAH.—Abu Dhabi Chief’s advanced base in 1889 for his attack on Katar. ELAYILEH.—Section of Sharkiyyin detached by Chief of Sharga from headman of Fujaira. FAIYARIN (UMM-EL).—Rocky islet off east side of Oman promontory, 360 feet high and ^ mile long, about 3| miles from nearest mainland (entrance of Ghubbat Shabus). FA.KAN (KHOR).—Village. (1) Fifteen miles south of Ras Dibba in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) Stands on south shore of sandy bay, with per fectly sheltered boat-harbour and large date-grove. (3) (4) Population 150. (5) (6) (7) Excellent water obtainable, also fish, cattle, poultry, and vege tables. (8)—(10) Joasmi flag flew here in 1902 and there was representative of cousin of Chief of Sharga. Mote. Admiralty chart 2837 A. contains plan of harbour. What are the seven small Sharkiyyin villages between Khor Fakan and Ras Dibba to which Cox in one place alludes ? Only 5, Zubara, Badi, Karam, Zadna and Ruwul Zadna are shown in maps. FALAH (AL BU).—One of the tribes that suffered in massacre commit ted by Chief of Katar during his raid on Abu Dhabi in 1888—9. FALEYN (or FATE YAH ?).—See Ross’s Map of Oman and Map of Parts of Arabia and Persia, near Ras-ai-Khaima. FANAKHA.—Small village, with good water, at bottom of cove a mile deep just inside entrance of Khor-ash-Shem (Ruus-el-Jebel promontory) on west side. FASHT.—Village (1) On Pirate Coast, 3 miles south-west from Ajman and 2 north-east from Sharga, dependency of Sharga, (2) On shore with date plantations behind. (3) Small square fort. (4) (5) (6) Sends 15 boats to pearl fishery. (7)—(10). FELASA (BENI BU ?).—Section of Beni Yas tribe. FI LAM.—Village at bottom of outer cove on north side of Ghubbat Ghazira (Malcolm Inlet) in Ruus-el-Jebel peninsula. FUDAR.—Or Fuda or Fazghah. Hamlet. (1) Between Bakha and Ghamtha on west coast of Ruus-al-Jebel promontry in Ras-ul-Khaima districtHHHHHHHBMMMmHNi 5 of Sharga. (2) On sandy beach, with few date trees, deep water close-to. (3) (5) (6) Fishing. (7)-(10). FUJAIRA.—Town. (1) miles from coast in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) Consists of huts surrounding a fort in midst of extensive date-groves. Land ing place Gherefa; distance days by land from Sharga. (3) Arab fort, small but apparently well defended. (4) Population 500. (5) (6) (7) Sup plies obtainable and plenty of fresh water. (8) (9) (10) Head-quarters of well-known Hamid-bin-Abdulla, who since 1901 has been attempting to assert independence of tract between Khor Kalba and Dibba against Sheikh of Sharga. GHADIR-EL-LALL.—Seventh stage on western route from Bereymi to Hasa. Water sweet but w ells deep. Scanty scrub ; road level but winding among sand-hills. Separated from Bir el Metoww^a by the Sabkheh. GHAFILEH.—Tribe which more than once assisted Sheikh of Abu Dhabi against Sheikh of Katar. Its nomads frequent Daafis in the season. GHALAT KALBA.—Village. (1) Half-way between Fujaira and Khor Kalba on Shameiliya coast in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) (3) Dilapidated Arab fort. (4) Population 200 to 300. (7)—(9) (10) Seat of Governor on behalf of Sharga Chief. GHALEELA.—Mentioned by Cox as Shihiyyin village between Shuam and Rams. Is this same as Kalila below ? GHAMTHA.—Hamlet. (1) Between Fudar and Tibba on west coast of Runs el Jebel promontory in Eas ul Khaima district of Sharga. (2) On sandy beach with few date trees. (3)—(5) (6) Fishing. (7)—(10). GHANAM (JAZIRAT-AL).—Island on west side of tip of Oman promon tory with cliffs nearly all round. Low at north but rises to 600 feet in south. Length 2£ miles, nortli and south ; breadth f mile. Barren without water or inhabitants but goats of Kumzar people are kept here. Separated from mainland by Khor Kawi. GHARUM.—There is village (what name?) in little cove of this name, £ mile deep, on mainland of Ruus el Jebel promontory opposite south point of Ghanam Island. Village consists of huts upon hills with date plantations below. GHASSA.—Settlement on western side of Musandam Peninsula. See Goldsmid, page 143. Is this same as Hassa below ? GHAZIRA (GHUBBAT).—Or Malcolm Inlet. Arm of sea on east side of Oman promontory, 2| miles wide at entrance and 8 miles lon«* in a west- north-west direction. Separated from Khor ash Shem on west°by narrow isthmus of Maklab. There are two large coves on north side, each 3 miles deep; and two coves, not so large, on south side. Villages are Habalain, Mukaka, Filam, and another hamlet (what name ?) GHEREPA — Village. (1) (2) Landing-place of Pujaira. (3) (4) Con sists of large stone house and few huts. (5)-(10). Joasmi flag flew, and there was a representative of cousin of Chief of Sharga here in 1902. Is this same as Gnereytah, described as Sharkiyym village near Dibba ? ... GHU B ALI.—Small village on sandy beach, at bottom of Khor Ghub Ah on west side of Musandam promontory; has a few date and other trees and good water. GIIUREEF.—Old ruined fort in thick babool jungle with several wells o good water. Belonged to Shuamis ( Showamis ? ) of Bereymi who were driven out by Bern Kaab about 1790. Occupied in 1840 by Beni Kattab fof from BMeymi?' 3 ^ 6 ^ ° amelS “ ' Vinter 16i hours f^m Sharga and , HABALEIN—Village at westernmost end of Ghubbat Ghazira (Mal colm Inlet. ) Alternative settlement of inhabitants of Mukaka. HADIYEH (BENI). Section of Skikiyyin among whom Zahooriveen are included when in permanent quarters. onyeen HAFFA. Village in cove of same name, a few miles north nf THKhQ on east side of Ruus el Jebel promontory. Vlbha (C912FD) * B6 HAFFA (DUHAT).-“Cove on east side of Oman promontory, short distance north of Dibba Bay. It runs in parallel to coast for 2^ miles with width of from £ to £ mile. Soundings are regular, 7 to 8 fathoms. Penin sula masks cove from seaward and makes of it land*locked harbour. HAIL (ABU).—Town. (1) On Pirate Coast about 2| miles south-west of Sharga, in Sharga district. (2) On south side of small inlet separating it from Khan (g. t?.). Mostly mat huts. Bad anchorage. From here to Dabai no date trees, and shore pure white sand. (3) Four towers. (4) 2,000 inhabitants. (5) Matarish. (6) Sends 40 boats to pearl-fleet. (7)—(10). HAIRA.—Village. (1) On Pirate Coast, 3 miles south-west from Ajman and 2 north-east from Sharga, dependency of Sharga. (2) On shore, date plan tations behind village. (3) Two detached towers. (4) (5) (6) Sends 15 boats to pearl-fishery. (7)—(10). HAJAR (BENI).—Tribe who attacked Naim in 1875. Are these identi cal with Beni Hajir in subsection B ? HAMRA (JAZIRAT-AL).—Town. (1) On Pirate Coast in Ras ulKhaima district of Sharga, about half-way between Ras ul Khaima and Umm-al-Ka- wain. (2) On a small low sandy island, south-west end of which at low water is nearly connected with main. Creek between island and coast is shallow. No date trees. Red sandhills behind town. (3) Fort and various towers, also bastions in commanding positions. (4) 400 houses. (5) Zaab or Zaal tribe. (6) (10). HAM RITA.—Town. (1) On Pirate Coast about half-way between Umm- ul-Kawain and Ajman : independent. (2) To north of small creek, no trees. (3) Square fort on shore with 5 towers in cluster, also two detached towers near creek. (4) Population 400. (5) Naim. (6) Sends 50 boats to pearl- fishery ; people very poor. (7)—(10). HAN A.— Small village, with fine date-grove and well of good water 300 yards from beach, situated on Hana cove 1J miles from Ras Shekh Masud on its east side. HARAF.—Village with about 100 inhabitants, chiefly fishermen, on hills above Ras Shekh Masud. Boats kept in Aida cove 1 mile south-west of the Ras, where there is a well of excellent water. HARF.—Place where Shekh of Katar halted in 1888-9 on his raid into Abu Dhabi territory. HARIM (JEBEL).—See Ruus el Jebel. HASS A.—Hamlet on sandy beach in largest bay on western face of Oman peninsula between Khor Ghub Ali and Khor ash Shem. HAWAMIL (AL). Tribe who in 1880 committed a raid for which Chief of Katar held Chief of Abu Dhabi accountable. HAWEIDHAH (UMM-EL).—Place south of Ojair. Head quarters in 1887 of 2 pirate boats. HEBE AH (BENI).—No particulars. HEYL.—See Ross’s Map of Oman near Ras al Khaima. HO WAR AH.—Place passed by Palgrave on Pirate Coast, apparently between Umm-uLKawain and Ras al Khaima. HOWEIL.—Wells 26| hours from Abu Dhabi on way to Bereymi. HOWTAH.—Village seen by Palgrave, apparently a few miles inland from Sharga. HUATIAL FAAL.—Village near Ras al Khaima; see Bombay Records XXIV, 1856, page 542. HUBHUB.—See Ross’s Map of Oman, between Ras al Khaima and Dibba. HURMULLIOH,—Beautiful valley of Beni Kaab where wheat grows, about 4 hours north of Bereymi.wmmmrn MPiH 7 JAAEOOK.—A district enclosed by the Dkafreh, Katar and Hasa districts, JABRIN (WADI).—Pertile and well watered valley situated in the desert south of Yemaraah and 3 days from Hasa. Date groves are said to extend several miles. Formerly large and flourishing, but deserted by permanent inhabitants before 1876 on account of malaria. A1 Morrah and Dowasir tribes collect dates in summer and sell them in Nejd and Hasa. Nomads also frequent Jabrin for its luxuriant pasture. JADI.—Village. (1) Three miles south of Ras al Jadi on west coast of Runs el Jebel promontory in Ras ul Khaima district of Sharga. (2)—(5) Shihiyyin. (6) Pishing village. (7) Some wells of good water near beach. JALAJILA.—Marauding tribe behind Pujaira whom Pujaira headman wanted Chief of Sharga to restrain. JERASH (BEDA).—Sixth stage on eastern route from Bereymi to Hasa. JIBUREE.—Port in Hurmullioh. JIRL—Village. (1) miles south of Ras al Jadi on west coast of Ruus el Jebel promontory in Ras ul Khaima district of Sharga. (2) Under the hills on a beach which extends as far as Bakha. (3) (1) (5) Shihiyyin ( 6 )-( 10 ). JOASMIS.—No particulars available of this most important tribe. Palgrave says that the Joasmis form a singular colony of unmixed Nejdean descent and of comparatively recent establishment extending from Ajman to Shuam. Accord ing to the same authority they trace their ancestral stem to Meteyr and their settlement was formed within the last 240 years: they are Wahabis of the Wahabis, fierce by nature and fanatical by religion. JOHUR.—Half a day from Bereymi on western route to Hasa. Belongs to Dhowahir. Has wells of good water and acacia jungle but no cultivation. JOWA.—Place, also called Zafrah (?), 4 marches west of Abu Dhabi. Great massacre was committed here in 1888-9 by Katar raiders. IBLIS (HISN).—Or Narsaila. Landmark 9^ hours journey from Abu Dhabi on route to Bereymi consisting of an outcrop of limestone rock, in fantastic shape, above the sand. KAAB (BENI).—See Section I, Maskat. KABAL.—In valley at head of Duhat Kabal, a cove teeming with fish between Lima and Malcolm Inlet. Consists of a few scattered single huts containing 4 or 5 families of herdsmen. In west branch of valley are ruins of extensive village having walls built of large slabs of stone without mor tar. Here staff of life is a shellfish of strombus family which abounds in shallows of cove. KABBA.—Little village at head of a bight in Musandam promontory on west side, opposite south-east corner of Ghanam Island. KADA.—Small village with large date-grove at bottom of a little cove between Khasab and Ras Shekh Masud. KALB A (KHOR).—Village. (1) Nineteen miles north of Shinas on Shameiliya coast in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) On creek which boats can enter at high water. (3) Port. (4) 200 inhabitants. (5) (6) Some trade with interior. (7) Cattle and poultry obtainable. (8) (9) (10) Joasmi flag flew herein 1902, and there was representative of cousin of chief of Sharga. KALILA.—See Pelly’s ' Report on the Tribes, etc., of the Persian Gulf ”, 1874, page 2, margin. Place seems to be near Shuam. KANA.—Small village in sandy bight, on south side of Elphinstone Inlet and immediately west of Maklab Bay. KARAH.—Scene of first engagement between Abu Dhabi and Katar forces in 1889. KARAM.—Village. (1) Half-way between Khor Pakan and Ras Dibba on Shameiliya coast in Sharki district of Sharga. (2)—(10).r- - Himm 8 KARSIIA.—Place in Bibba Bay. See Admiralty Chart No. 753 ; one mile north of Dibba; has 120 inhabitants. KATAN.—Marked in Philip’s Map of Arabia some distance inland, half way between Abu Dhabi and Katar. KATTAB (BENI).—Is this same tribe as in Oman ? KAWA (JEBEL).— See Runs el Jebel. K AW AIN (UMM-UL).—Town. (1) On Pirate Coast about half-way between Ras ul Khaima and Sharga : independent town. (2) Tolerably clean and well-built. On a peninsula which runs nearly east and west between sea on north and creek on south. Creek is 6 to 8 fathoms deep at town, but entrance is 2 miles distant to N.-N.-E. and carries only 2 feet at low water : nor can depth of 5 fathoms be found on seaward side nearer to town than 1 mile. (3) Wall across isthmus, with 3 towers, also other towers. (4) Popu lation 800 to 1,000—more in pearling season—including few Banyans. (5) A1 Bu Ali tribe. (6) Sends large number of boats to pearl fishery. Trade carried on mostly by Banyans. (7)—(10). Note. —It is not clear whether any district is attached to town, nor whether there are subject villages. Bombay Records, XXIV, 1856, mentions “ four villages”. KAWI (KHOR).—Strait between Ghanam Island and mainland 2 miles long, 3 cables wide at north and south entrances and 5 cables wide at mid dle. Soundings are 15 to 19 fathoms, sand and gravel without hard rock. A well-sheltered, safe and commodious anchorage, defensible, and well sui ted for naval flying-base. KHABAL.—Place belonging to the Naim, burnt by the Beni Yas in 1875. KHABB.—Is this same as Kabba ? Village visited by Palgrave, in a retired bay of Oman promontory. KHAIMA (RAS-AL).—Town. (1) On Pirate Coast in 25° IS' N. 55° 67' E., chief town of Ras al Khaima district of Sharga. (2) Houses chiefly stone. Square buildings higher than rest belong to Sheikhs of Ras al Khaima. Town occupies two miles (?), beginning from tip of sandy spit, about 5£ miles in length, which points north-east. There is long narrow bay between promontory and mainland, connected with sea also by back- water about 4 miles long beginning 1| miles south of Rams. Plain between town and hills, about 6 miles broad, but increases in width very rapidly to south ward. One mile south-west of Ras al Khaima begin high reddish sandhills which extend past Hamra. Country in vicinity is flat and sandy. Bay between town and mainland forms harbour for native boats ; only 2 feet of water on entrance at low water, but 9 after passing it. Opposite town com mences dense date grove extending far inland and continuing along coast to Rams. Anchorage for vessels of size is 2| to 3 miles north-west of town. (3) Town is protected on land side by wall with 2 square towers across isthmus, and there is detached tower near commencement of red sandhills. (4) Popu lation 4,000 to 5,000 (Gulf Pilot, 1898); 1,500 (Kemball 1903). (5) Joasmis, Shihiyyin, Zaal, and Mutarish, and 9 or 10 Hyderabadis. (6) Many boats and baghalas belong to this port, and about 20 go to pearl-fishery. (7) Water uncertain ; cattle, vegetables and fruit obtainable. (8)—(10). KHAIMA (RAS AL).—District. (1) Boundaries, north Ras Shaikh Masud (?); west the sea ; E ? S ? (2) Sub-divisions, natural or administra tive ? Principal towns are Ras al Khaima, Hamra, Rams, and Shuam; villages, Zai, Tibba, Ghamtha, Pudar, Bakha, Jadi, and Jiri. (3) Consists of a moun tainous portion, part of the Ruus el .Tebel, which on west side runs almost north and south, till at Shuam the coast begins to trend south-west, leaving between the sea and the mountains a wedge-shaped plain with its point to the north and its broad base in the neighbourhood of Ras al Khaima town. (4) (6) (75) Shihiyyin and Joasmi. (8/) Governed by a deputy of Sheikh of Sharga. KHAN.—Town. (1) On Pirate coast, about 2| miles south-west of Sharga, in Sharga district. (2) On north side of small inlet, one branch of which runs north-east and joins Sharga back-water, while other turns south9 behind Abu Hail village ; mostly mat huts. Land inshore of town for some miles is low and swampy. (3) hive detached towers. (4) (5) (6) Sends 25 boats to pearl fishery. (7) — (10)* KHANUR.—Fort in Dhafreh, taken in 1888-89 by Chief of Katar. KHASAB.—Town on coast of Runs el Jebel promontory, to east of entrance to Khor ash Shem (Elphinstone Inlet). (2) On sandy beach nearly a mile long. Surrounded by date groves which extend up wide valley. At back of groves valley is well cultivated with corn and vegetables. (3) Two towers on beach, fort containing Sheikh’s house near centre of groves and small square tower on western rocky point overlooking bay. (4) Population 600. (5) (6) A cloth for wearing apparel, much used by Arabs, is exported. (7) Mood, cattle and vegetables obtainable. Fresh water in good wells plentiful, and is used to irri gate plantations, (9), (10) Sheikh is aTFaliof Sultan of IMaskat who gets an annual revenue of $; 00 to 600 from place with which he pays his own salary ; but he makes no remittances to Maskat and receives none thence. His functipns are mostly consular connected with floating population : he has little or nothing to do with permanent Shihiyyin. (11). [What is name of small village men tioned in Persian Gulf Pilot, 1898, as having wells of good water and lying in a little bight between Khasab and Ras Shahath ?]. KHEREYBAN (AL BU).—'A section of Naim tribe. KHOTEM.—Second stage on eastern route from Bereymi to Hasa. KHUT.—See Ross’s Map of Oman between Ras ul Khaima and Dibba. Possibly the same as a village Khatt, which Miles says exists on the Pirate Coast. KHUM 7 EIR.—Mentioned by Cox as Shihiyyin village between Shuam and Rams. KILHAT.—Povah’s Gazetteer of Arabia gives this name to coast on east of Ruus el .1 ebel promontory of which chief town is Dibba : is it correct ? Pal- grave calls it Kalhat or Kalhoot and says it extends from Lima to the Batinah and that Dibba is its chief town. KOHEEL.—Fort in Harmullioh. KUBAISAT.—Section of Beni Yas who broke off temporarily from Abu Dhabi and settled at Odaid. KUMAZIREH.— Mentioned by Ross as one of two main branches of Shihiyyin. Cox regards them as originally a distinct tribe but now merged in the Shihiyyin. KUMZAR.—Town, at bottom of cove in north face of Musandam pen insula, built in a gloomy valley or gorge in the hills. Population 600, fisher men. Salt-fish and shark-fins are exported to Kishm with which place there is much intercourse. No cultivation. There are 40 or 50 small craft and 3 or 4 dhows which ply to Linga and Batinah with dried fish for sale. None of dhows go to pearl fishery, but some individuals go on Sharga andDabai vessels. People profess allegiance to Maskat, but pay no taxes there. All but 200 migrate to Khasab and Dibba in date season. Kemp (December 1903) says headman of Kumzar is Wali of Sultan of Maskat. K UN-.—Precipitous island, 600 feet high, about 1 mile long east and west, with depression in centre. West and higher peak is 4 miles west by south from Ras Musandam. KURNA.—Village. (1) On Shameiliya coast in Sharki district of Sharga. (2)-(l0). LEEVAH.—Fort of this place, which is in Abu Dhabi territory, was scene of massacre by Katar forces in 1889. Also described as being a place near Bainnon. LIBINI— Town mentioned in Bombay Records XXIV, 1856, at page 543, as containing 600 inhabitants of Al (Bu ?) Ali tribe, situated apparently on what is at high tide an island, between Umm ul Kawainand Jazirat al Hamra. LIGLUDDI.—See Ruus el Jebel. LIMA.—Village. (1) At bottom of a bay facing north, on east side of Ruus el Jebel promontory. (2) Part of village is built up hill, on steps of (C912FD)10 strata, one hut above another. Date-grove and some cultivation in valley ; precipitous hills in immediate vicinity. Inhabitants can cross hills to Has al Khaimain one day. 3) (4) Population 200. Palgrave put it at 2,000 and said place was most populous in lluus el Jebel. (5) Shihiyyin. (6) (7) Cattle procurable. Good water not in any quantity. Firewood difficult. According to Palgrave, there are oaks, palms, lotos-trees and acacias in the valley behind. ( 8 )-( 11 ). LIYA. —Village. (1) Suburb of Sharga town. (2) Stands on narrow strip of sand between Sharga creek and sea ; dwellings mostly mat-huts. (3) Large tower at south end. (4)—(10). LUBEYDHA.—Cove mentioned by Whitelock as near Ummul Kawein and sheltered from all winds. MAD A.—Hamlet within Elphinstone Inlet, on south side of neck of Jebel Shem peninsula. Wells of good water, said to be best in Inlet. MAHAMI.—Section of Naim tribe (?). MAHDEH.—District or tribe, inland from Shamaliya coast—see map of Parts of Arabia and Persia. MAH SARA H.—Map opposite page 15 in Bombay Government Records XXIV, 1856, shows considerable place of this name on mainland over against Ras al Khaima. Persian Gulf Pilot, 189S, page 87, mentions small fishing village on low islet in back-water opposite Ras ui Khaima. MAILI.—Small village (what name?) on sandy beach in bay on north face of Musandam peninsula opposite Kun Island, at foot of Jebel Maili. MAILI (JEBEL).—Remarkable sharp peak on north face of Musandam promontory, 1,894 feet high. Overhangs slightl /to east. MAKHI.—Large fishing village with wells of fairly good water on west side of entrance of Kada cove, between town of Khasab and Ras Sheikh Masud. MAKLAB.—Bay in west side of an isthmus, which is at one point only about 400 yards wide and separates Malcolm and Elphinstone Inlets. Bay lies between Telegraph Islet and Hana and dimensions are about 1 mile each way. [Is isthmus properly called Maklab, and is there village of this name ?] MAKTAA.—Creek, 10 miles from Abu Dhabi on route to Bereymi. Can be crossed by camels at low water. Fort belonging to chief of Abu Dhabi stands in midst of water to defend crossing against Bedouins. Creek connects Khor Laffan with Khor of Abu Dhabi; only one ford. MANASIR.— Section of Beni Yas (?). Palgrave treats them as a distinct tribe, widely different from the Beni Yas in origin and appearance. He says they are by tradition, physical outline and dialect a branch of the Abs family and therefore Nejdeans. Douglas estimates their number at 2,000 and fighting strength at 400 t in neighbourhood of Hasa) and says their chiefs receive Turkish subsidies. MANSUL,—Village in Malcolm Inlet almost opposite Filam bay. Alter native settlement of Pilam people. MARRAR—Tribe some of whom have transferred their allegiance from Dabai to Sharga. MATARISH.—Tribe represented at Ras ul Khaima and Abu Hail. MAZARI’A.—Tribe who attacked Naim of Bereymi in 1875. MEFRAZ.—Mentioned by Palgrave as a good-sized village 3 or 4 miles north of Sharga with handsome palace and better plantations than Sharga. Can Fasht or Haira be meant ? MEHAMA.—Pirates between Sharga and Katar, mentioned in Povah's Gazetteer of Arabia. METOWWA (BEDA-EL).—Fourth stage on eastern route from Bereymi to Hasa. METOWWA (B1R-EL).—Sixth stage on western route from Bereymi to Hasa. There is acacia jungle and sweet water but wells are deep. MOKABER.—Place marked in Philip’s Map of Arabia, some distance south-south-east of Khor Dhoan.11 MUKAKA.—Hamlet in the western of two large coves ^ at run out of Glmbbat Gbazira (Malcolm Inlet). At north-east corner of Maklab Isth- mus. Houses are of dry stone with plank roofs surmounted by stones. MUSA (ABU).-(l) Highest p°iat 25^53'^ nor^SS 0 About midway botween Sharga ^ndLiuga^ ( 2 ’i miles&gt; breadth If miles. I’aTiow J isolatedrdarCvolcaniodo.Aing hills ; slightly north of centre ts (3) Low n itn isoiatea a , , f f {or natlTe boats m had 3her ( 4 ) Goofwater in wells aTdate palms planted by Sheikh of Sharga. X visits i land in hot weather and sends his horses and camels to graze here ^ Vari, s In winter people from Sharga and Khan visit island to fish and grazl cauk In pearling season only 2 or 3 men remain to tend date-trees. (6) Pirate Coast. (7) Sharga. MTT^ 4ND AM Island at extremity of Oman promontory, 2 miles STSA r-i Wf f^northand 0 loSle' tfS Musa^dtm IskndTs separated from mainland tt rak al Asad sfrait, 3 cables wide, quite clear, with depth of 24 fathoms /orth and east of Musandam are soundings of 100 fathoms, only places nort of Has al Kuh where such depth is obtained. MUZAHMA.—Cove mentioned by Whitelock as famous shelter o peai fishers between Has al Khaima and Umm-ul-Kawain. MUZARIYA.—Tribe alleged to have committed raids on Fujaira recently at instigation of Chief of Sharga. . . NABIYU TAAIB.—Barren and uninhabited island without water, less than 1 mile square. Lies 7 miles west by south from Tamb. l .. NACHSHILA.—Half-ruined village with a few date trees, also wel s, about 18 miles east of Bereymi on route to Abu Dhabi. NAIM —Tribe represented at Hamriya and Ajman. Is this same tribe as at Bereymi etc.? Al Bu Khereyban are mentioned as a section, also Mahami. tvjaT-R fSTR ABU 1 ) —(D 25° 13' north 54° 14'east. Almost due north from Ahu Dhabi and due west from Dabai on north edge of pearl hanks. (2) 2f mites tens by 2 broad. (3) Covered with hills, highest point 240 feet volcanic “ b very low sandy point at south-east corner. 4) Only brushwood and brackish water in wells ou east side. Sulphur said to be found. (5) ho uermanent inhabitants, but fleets visit to open oysters in peail season, and Sharga and Dabai fishermen with families come in winter to catch sharks and sawfish. (6) Territory of Trucial Chiefs. (7) Sharga. NAKBIYY1N.—Section of Sharkiyyin inhabiting Dibba. NARSAILA.— See Iblis (Hisn). NAZIFI —Yillao-e on west side of little land-locked cove in south shore of entrance to Khor ash Shem, convenient place for laying a vessel aground. ODAID Deserted site on winding inlet of that name, 5 miles long, which opens out inside into lagoon 5 miles long and 3 broad. Previous to 1856 there was town with small square fort having 2 towers, also 7 detached towers and blockhouse commanding wells. Vessels of war could not approach witnin 3 miles. Fishermen from Abu Dhabi remain here some months m winter and fine mullet are caught, ODAID /'KHOP-AL).—Inlet where territory of Ahu Dhabi ends and that of Katar begins. See Odaid. PIRATE COAST.—See Trucial Chiefs’ Territory. RAMS. Town. (1) 10J miles south of Has Ash Shuam on West coast of Runs al Jabal promontory in Ras ul Khaima district of Sharp. (2) On creek, entrance to which is nearly dry at low water ; swampy with date groves at some distance from it. (3) (4) 300 or 400 inhabitants. (5) Tannagis. (o) ( 0).I12 RUFFTHBA.—District inland from Shamaliya Coast. BUUS EL JEHEL.-Raage of VComm^ef aflL ^L^anCl aima (or further south ?) and extends north to MaWab Si% r=t . Er ^ ssssr- a—««--? y^ya^iuaijlgt when^nd Sre^Ltoholea exist by small communities of hardy Shihu shepherds with their goats, and aspiring to a little cultivation where ground and water make impossible. Hills are almost entirely bare. There are a It dlte groves in the Talleys ; and scanty vegetation m fissures of the rock on which Croats feed. On east side coast is precipitous throughout and cliffs are VeneraUy undercut at sea level. There are small sandy bays at mouths of valleys, 'and mountains rise abruptly from water s edge. There are nuJeroua deep-water inlets, some of considerable extent, which native boats t nronelled hv oars never enter on account of baffling winds, liincipal ifflets are Dibba Bay, Duhat Haffa, Ghubbat Akahah, Duhat Kahal, Ghubbat Ghazira Ghubbat Shahus, Duhat Shisa, Khor Ghub Ah, Kliasab Bay, and Khor ash Shem. On west side, from Has Sheikh Masood to Tibha, mountains run close to sea. The villages of Kalba, Gherefa, Eujaira and Sakamkam are enclosed on the landward side by a chain of desolate hills which retire to some distance from the sea, forming a semi-circle of which the shore is a chrnd 9 or 10 miles in length. From Sakamkam to Khor Fakan is a mass of low hills, 10 miles in length, coming close to the sea and relieved by many little indentations which contain small hamlets and date gardens. (3) tleva ion is generally 3,000 to 4,000 feet. (4) Chief peaks are~(Fme Peak) behind Fudar 4,470 feet; Jebel el Harim (Shuam Peak) between bhuam and Lima m centre of promontory, 6,730 feet, with small table-top ; and Jebel Kawa short distance north-north-west of Dibha, 5,800 feet. (5) Snow does not (?) fa 1. b) South of Bas al Khaima and Dibha, range retains approximately same breadth as in north, and coast on both sides recedes from it. (Should this _ portion be included in Hajar, in Oman?) More rapid trend of west coast gives broader lowlands on that side. (7) Not basalt as formerly supposed, but jet black and dark black-grey limestone interstratified and veined with white and pinkish brown calc spar. Strata are horizontal. (8) Wolves, leopards, hyaenas, and foxes are found in bills. (9) Inhabitants are Shihiyyin and Zahooriyeen. (10) L aths across mountains are generally only tracks fit for Arabs and goats, but there is well-defined camel track from Dibba to Ras al Khaima which meets Ras al Khaima-Bereymi road on debouching into western maritime plain. Ibis route has not been described. Ross’s Map shows a pass called Ligluddi onioute between Dibba and Ras al Khaima. Gulf Pilot, 1898, mentions a land route, 1 day’s journey, from Lima to Ras al Khaima. Wadi Ham appears, from Ross’s Map, to conduct from Sharga to Fujaira. (11). RUWUL ZA.DNA.—Village. (1) Between Zadna and Dibba on Sliameiliya coast in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) (10) • SABKHEII (WADI).—Or Sabkheh Math. Marshy tract or valley, about 40 miles broad, commencing in vicinity of Wadi Jabrin and entering Gulf between long. 51 °60' and 52° 20' east, in lat. 24° north. In some parts it is a treacherous morass, only to be crossed on beaten tracks ; camels missing path become engulfed in mud. Part consists of sand and part of saline incrustations. There is no grass. The Sabkheh lies between Sil and Dhafreh at one day s rtistannft from each. SAKAMKAM.— Village. (1) Three miles north of Eujaira in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) (3) (4) Population 50. (6)—(10). SALAMA WA BINATAHA.—Or the Quoins. Group of 3 remarkable islets in lat. 26° 30'north and long. 66° 31'east, 5 to 7 miles north of Has Musandam. Largest, Salama or Great Quoin, is 540 feet high and furthest from mainland; nearest is Little Quoin, 168 feet high; and between is Gap Island with peak 250 feet high. Miles says the Arabs call the 2 Quoins Koseyr and Oweyr.13 SAMAIH.—Place with water, from which Sheikh of Katar made attack on Bainnon in 1888. SAMEII.—Place fixed as rendezvous by Chiefs of Abu Dhabi and Dabai, when preparing to march together against Chief of Katar in 1889. SAMEYAH.— Place from which Chief of Abu Dhabi finally started to invade Katar in 1889. Is this same as last ? SEBAD1H.—Third stage on eastern route from Bereymi to Hasa, SEYKHAH.—Place within 5 days of Katar where Chief of Ahu Dhabi was to have been joined for his invasion of Katar in 1889 by Awamir, Deroo and other allies. S HA A11 (AL BU).—A branch of the Manasir (?) ; Dependent on Chief of Abu Dhabi and made a raid on Katar Bedouins at Naijah in 1885. SHABUS.—Village in little bay on south-west side of Ghubbat Shabus, an opening on east side of Musandam peninsula between Malcolm Inlet and I)uhat Shisa. There are 2 hamlets (what names ?) in north part of same opening. SHAHBAGHUL.— Village in Dhafreh taken by Chief of Katar during his great raid in 1888-89. SHAM ALIY A.—Coast of Oman peninsula from Has ul Khaima to Abu Dhabi, so called from its exposure to Shamal or north-wester. SHAM El LIYA.—Littoral tract on east side of Oman promontory, from Mureir to Dibba inclusive, lying between the Batina tract on the south and that of Runs el Jebel on the* north. Tho plain between mountains and sea becomes narrower from south to north and 15 miles north of Khor Kalba hills come down close to sea. Coast line is formed of cliffs with sandy bays in which are villages and date groves. Tributary to Sharga. (3)—(10). SHARJA. At head of indentation of this name in east side of Runs el Jebel promontory, between Dibba and Lima, is small village ( what name ?) with date grove on south side. SHARGA.—Town. (1) Principal place on Pirate Coast, 25° 22' north 55° 21' east capital of Sharga district and principality. (2) Extends for 1J miles along east’bank of small narrow creek parallel to sea and divided from sea by narrow sand-spit. Large proportion of stone houses. At south end of town is rocky rising around, 30 or 10 feet high, forming bluff at south end. Country for some distance inland is complete desert with few scattered date groves. Sliarga creek has only one foot on bar at low water. It joins creek from Kban village. Best landing place for Sharga is Liyah Point. (3) Several detached towers. In 1861 Sharga was open to the sea and walled, but not strongly, on the landward side with walls of reddish-yellow sandstone. (4) Population 1,000 (Kemball), 8 000 to 10,000 (Gulf Pilot), between 20,000 and 30,000 (Palgrave). (5)^ Mostly Joasmis, Al Abu Alis and Shihiyyin ; some Sunnis, others Wahabis; with 70 British subjects, Khojas and Hindus. Zwemer says it is still a Wahabi centre and that tobacco has to he sold secretly. (6) Sends 350 boats to pearl fishery. Several baghalas belong to this port and fine bakaras and batils are built. In Palgrave’s time it was principal port of w r est Oman, resembling Linga as an entrepot, and unrivalled on its own coast between Bidaa and Dibba. In 1863 it was principal mart on Pirate Coast for camels, donkeys and slaves; there were weavers who made light red cloaks, robes, carpets and curtains, also 'old and silver-smiths. Shops were neat and well-built and there w r as general air of solidity and wealth. At south end of town was market place divided into Suks; in centre Kaisariah (long and lofty vaulted building) ; at north end weavers. (7)—(10). SHARGA.— District (1)—(4) (5). There is route from Sharga to Bereymi in interior, distance 36 hours, see Bombay Records, XXIV, 1856; also one from Sharka to Khadhrawain in Batina (Ross’s Map of Oman). Aote.—Uncertain to what distance these lie in Sharga territory. (6)—(8). SHARGA.—Principality. Consists of 3 districts, vie., Sharga Proper, Ras al Khaima, and Sharki. Eor particulars see articles on these districts. 912ED D« 14 SHARKI.—la this proper name to apply to district surrounding Fujaira tributary to Sharga Chief ? South Dibba is apparently its most northern village and Kalba its most southern ? Is it exactly co-extensive with Shameiliya ? (2)— (10). In 1902 Joasmi flag flew at Kalba, Khor Fakan and Gherefa and there was at each of these places a representative of cousin of Chief of Sharga, who held villages in fief and levied what tribute he could in date season. Present revenue said to be $ 2,500 annually of which $ 1,600 from Dibba, SHARKIYYIN.—Tribe in Fujaira and neighbourhood. One of their sections is Nakbiyyin. SHEM.—--Little village on north side of Khor ash Shem, 4 miles within entrance, immediately under Shem Peak ; with wells of brackish water. Alter native settlement of inhabitants of Kana. SHEM (JEBEL).—Mountain, elevation 3,000', overlooking entrance of Khor ash Shem (Elphinstone Inlet) from north; has great precipice on south east side. SHEM (KHOK-ASH).—Or Elphinstone Inlet. Extensive and wind ing inlet on west side of Oman promontory, running south at entrance and north-east within ; 8 miles long and in parts less than half a mile wide; overhung at its east end by Jebel Shem. Largest village in inlet is Sibi and best water is said to be found at Mada. Inlet is divided from Ghubbat Ghazira by Maklab isthmus, only mile wide in places. Near Maklab is Tele graph Islet. Only danger in inlet is one sunken rock near Telegraph Islet. SHETAIR (BENI).—Section of Shihiyyin mentioned by Cox at Lima. SHIHIYYIN —Or Shihus. Tribe. (1) Himyaritic and Hinawi. Miles regards them as distinct from the Arabs whom, he says, they avoid dealings with, as far as possible. (2) Ross divides them into Beni Hidiyah and Kumazireh. Cox regards the latter as not really Shihiyyin though now merged in them and mentions a section called Beni Shetair at Lima. What then are divisions of Shihiyyin proper P Miles mentions a subtribe called Makadeheh. (3) They number 12,000 to 15,000 souls and inhabit practically whole Oman promontory north of line joining Dibba Bay to Rams on Pirate Coast, except the Malcolm and Elphinstone Inlets which are occupied by Zahooriyeen. Lima, Kumzar and Khasab are their chief places; in first and last of the population is fluctuating. They are also found on island of Larek. (4) Inoffensive, ignorant and super stitious. According to Wellsted they have no clothing but small loin-cloth and are not lighter in complexion than other Arabs. (5) Sunnis. According to Palgrave their villages have no mosques, but in some are cupolas fenced in and surrounded with a grove and styled “ mezar ’* or “ saiyid.” (6) Mostly herds men and fishermen. Some subsist largely on shellfish. Their fishing hamlets are many of them moveable- Majority are extremely poor and accept pre sents of rice and dates with gratitude. They keep a few poultry, including ducks not seen in many places in Arabia. During date harvest numbers seek employment at Khasab and Dibba or in Batina. Some have date planta tions of their own at the two former places. Wellsted says the majority live in caves and hollows, the rest in circular huts of loose stones about 4 feet high, or within walls built under overhanging rocks. (7) Fishing, goat- herding and date-harvesting ; Bombay Records XXIV add pearl-fishing. (8) Corrupt dialect of Arabic (?). Zwemer says it resembles Himyaritic dialect of the Mahras. Miles says Shihiyyin of Kumzar and Larek speak a dialect unintelligi ble to the Arabs. (9) (10) (11) Practically unarmed. (12) Political position of bulk of tribe is uncertain. Those of Shuam, Ghaleelah, Khoweir and Rams are at present subject to Ras al Khaima. Remainder are regarded by Government of India as being independent. SHISA.—Village with 200 inhabitants on south-west side of bay of same name in east of Musandam peninsula between Malcolm Inlet and Musandam Island. SHOW A (BENI).—-Mentioned by Whitelockas inhabiting Cosaab (Kha« sab ?) SHUAM.—Town. (1) About 2 miles south of Shuam Point on west coast of Ruus el Jebel promontory in Ras al Khaima district of Sharga. (2) On low16 sandy shore, with plain 1 to mile broad between town and mountains, partly cultivated with date-groves, vegetables, &amp;c., and good water in wells. About 4 miles south of town is creek used by boats at high water. (3) Tower on hillock about 60 feet high. (4) 600. (6) J Tannagi others; Sunnis with a few Wahabis. (6) Fishing and agriculture. (7)—(10). SHUAMS. Or Shuoms?—Inland from Shamaliya Coast. See Ross's Map of Oman and Map of Parts of Arabia and Persia. SHUANIL.—A tribe. See Bombay Selections XXIV, page 456. SIBI.—Largest village of Khor ash Shem, situated at east end of it under Jebel Sibi; sandy beach with deep water off it. Has a deep well of water# said to be brackish after drought. SIBI (JEBEL).—Mountain 3,000' high in centre of Musandam peninsula between head of Kubbat Shabus on east and Khor ash Shem on west. SIBINI.—Whitelock places a town of this name on Jezirat al Hamra. Is there a misprint and some confusion with Libini ? SIL.—Place of Manasir on coast, to which Chief of Abu Dhabi sent pro visions for his force preparatory to his attack on Bidaa in 1888. It is said to be 16 miles from Odaid and one day's march from the Sabkheh. There are springs of sweet water at surface and acacia jungle. By another account it is a day from the sea. Limit of Dhafreh. SIR.—OrJulfar. See pages 14 and 42 of Bombay Government Records, XXIV, 1856. These names do not occur in modern correspondence. Do they mean Ras al Khaima ? According to Kiebuhr (Description de PArabie, p. 266) the whole Oman promontory north of a line joining KhorEakan and Sharga is called Ser or Julfar, the name Ser being Arabic and being derived from a place near Sharga which had a good port, and that of Julfar being Persian and taken from a cope called Ras Julfar. If these designations really exist they would supply a much needed general name for the promontory. SIR (ABU).—Island. Off north face of Oman promontory, 6f miles west of Musandam. Separated from mainland by Bab Mukhalif strait, £ mile broad with 35 fathoms in it and high rock in mid-channel. Abu Sir is 6 cables long with cliffs all round and peaked hill 400 feet high. SIRRI.—(1) Almost due west of Abu Musa Island and due south of Mughu. (2) Triangular, 3| miles long from east to west and 2£ miles broad at east end. (3) Low with many small detached hills, none higher than 60 feet. (4) Some cultivation, flocks and cattle. Some water in wells about centre of south side. (5) Small village at north-east corner with 20 families. (6) Nearer Persian than Arab coast. (7). SOIIBA (WADI).—Formed by the junction at Randha of tbe Wadi Hanifa and other Wadis from Nejd. Supposed to reach the Gulf at Khor Dhoan. SOOR.—Palgrave says the head-quarters of the Beni Yas is so called and consists of aggregation of huts and old forts. The existence of this place is denied by Miles. SUDAN.—Tribe mentioned as visiting Tamb Island. SUIDAN.—Tribe who removed from Sharga and settled atDeira in 1826. TAMB —(1) North-east corner is in 26° 16' 11' north, 65° 19' 40' east. About due south from Basidu and due west from Ras Sheikh Masud on Ruus el Jebel promontory. (2) Circular and about two miles in diameter. (3) Level, with peaked hummock 166 feet high at north-east corner. (4) Indifferent water in well on south side; covered with coarse grass and shrubs. Some wild antelope. Fine oysters. (6) Uninhabited. At times a few cattle are brought for pasture. (6) Nearer Persian than Arab coast. (7) Government of India advised Chief of Sharga to hoist his flag here in 1903. TANNAGIS.—Tribe mentioned as residing at Bakha, Rams, etc. TAWAKKUL—Or Suwaik. Precipitous islet, 460 feet high, 1} miles north-west by west of Ras Musandam. Similar in size and appearance to Salama.16 TELEGRAPH ISLET.—-Small islet in Khor ash Shem, 50 feet high on which are ruins of British telegraph station abandoned in 1869. TIBBA.—Hamlet. (1) Between Ghamtha and Shuam on west coast of Ruus el Jebel promontory in Ras ul Khairaa district of Sharga. (2) On sandy beach with few date trees. (3)—(5) (6) Fishing. (7)—(10). TRUCIAL CHIEFS’TERRITORY.— (1) Extends from Shuam to Odaid along south-east shores of Persian Gulf, distance of over 350 miles, of which only 150 miles (Shuam to Abu Dhabi) can be called inhabited(P). This territory includes former Pirate Coast which began at Rams on north and extended to Dabai, though Dabai itself was hardly considered as a Pirate port. Boun dary is sea on west and north. Inland limits are undetermined. (2) Pol itical divisions are Sharga (including Ras al Khaima and Fujaira districts as well as Sharga proper) ; Umm ul Kawain ; Hamriya ; Ajman; Dabai; Abu Dhabi. Each of these divisions is dealt with under its own name. (8) Coast from Shuam to Ras al Khaima is low and nearly straight, with high land in background ; and soundings off coast decrease from north south wards. There are date palms at Shuam and a dense palmgrove extends from Rams to Ras al Khaima. The hills are miles from coast at Shuam, 6 miles distant at Ras al Khaima, and south of this the maritime plain widens very rapidly. Erom Ras al Khaima to Abu Dhabi coast is low and sandy throughout. The coast towns generally are very similar in appearance and consequently difficult to distinguish. There are many creeks, often com municating with each other inland and forming back-waters. Between Ras al Khaima and Umm ul Kawain shoal w ater and reefs extend about 2 miles from coast. There are date trees at Umm ul Kaw r ain but none at Jezirat al Hamra, and no trees at all at Hamriya. The country from Ras al Khaima to Ajman is not exactly sterile but neither is it well cultivated. The tidal stream sets parallel to shore on this const with a speed of 1 to 2 knots. The great Pearl Bank begins opposite Sharga and covers w hole space south of 20 fathom contour line. Haira, Easht and Sharga have date groves which extend some distance south from last mentioned place. Inland from Sharga the land is a flat sandy plain. From Abu Hail to Dabai there are no groves. From 4 miles south-west of Dabai to Abu Dhabi coast has average direction about south-west: throughout this stretch it is barren and uninhabited, very low and uniform in appearance, consisting of sand hillocks with coarse grass in tufts and cut up by creeks and extensive swamps, without any tree larger than mangrove hush. Jebel Ali, 220 feet high, is only landmark in these parts. As Abu Dhabi is approached a succession of intercommunicating creeks and extensive swamps and backwaters is passed. These extend many miles into interior and are separated from sea by small strip of sand only : they yield fish and fire-w T ood. From Abu Dhabi to Bereymi the country seems to be chiefly sandy desert, shale and shingle cropping out with dip of 30° to north. There are only a few' stunted date trees at Abu Dhabi. Three miles south of Abu Dhabi is large bay, unexplor ed, miles wide at entrance and perhaps 20 miles deep. Beyond this point coast is sandy or stony, with rocky hills and sandhills of moderate height. It soon assumes a west direction which it preserves till near Odaid when it turns north-west. About opposite the island of Dalma is the mouth of the Sabkheh, a wide depression or morass which separates Oman from Nejd. From Abu Dhabi to Odaid the coast is barren and desolate, with water at but few places, and there indifferent. Great reefs extend as much as 30 miles to seaward, one of the principal being Bazim which has a length east and west of 53 miles and running parallel to the coast forms an inlet or blind channel called Khor Bazim about 50 miles long ; entrance of this channel is at its west end, 19 miles east of Sir Beni Yas. The whole of the great bay between Abu Dhabi and Odaid is full of islands, reefs and shoals and is but imperfectly known or surveyed. Only inhabited island is Dalma. Even Arab vessels larger than pearl boats seldom venture here and Arab mariners seldom visit mainland in these parts. Eishermen fre quent the islands to catch fish and turtle. Pilots for this sea are obtained at Abu Dhabi. (4) The heat is intense in summer. Palgrave however considered the atmosphere at Sharga to resemble that of India rather than Arabia. (5) There are routes from Sharga, Abu Dhabi and Ras al Khaima to Bereymi.17 Hamerton (1840) gives the following stages on the route from Sharga to Bereymi: from Sharga 3 hours south by east to Fellah, w r here there is a well with good water hut no habitations nor trace of road; from Fellah 10 hours south-south-east to Bir Mohafiz where there is fine well but no forage wdiat- ever, a gradual ascent over sandhills ; from Bir Mohafiz 3|- hours south by east and south-south-east to Ghureef, an old ruined fort in thick babool jungle with several wells of good water and good forage for camels iu cold season ; from Ghureef hours south by east and south-south-east to Jebel Yiff over hard sandhills with babool jungle, including some considerable trees, on right; from Jebel Yiff 13 hours south to Bereymi, very heavy road, over and round high sandhills, difficult for camels. B/Oute from Abu Dhabi to Bereymi is described as follows : general direction a little south of east; Abu Dhabi to Maktaa, 4 hours; Maktaa to Narsaila or Hisn Iblis, 51 hours ; Hisn Iblis to water-holes 11 hours; waterholes to Howeil wells, 6 hours; Howeil wells to water-holes, 10 hours ; waterholes, to Bereymi oasis, 4^ hours; total 41 hours (Cox). Zwemer makes it 33 hours, but he and Cox agree in making distance about 100 miles. Cox says there is no grazing on way for camels but Zweraer says camel-grass and tamarisk shrubs are plentiful after passing Remlah el Kabira which in his map is about midway between Abu Dhabi and Bereymi. Water is scarce. Zwemer has a half ruined village, Nachshila, about equidis tant from Bereymi and Bamlah el Kabira. Route from Ras al Khaima to Berey mi has not been described. (6) Pearls, fish, dates, wool and cheese are amon«- principal products. Cattle are good but the bullocks seldom exceed 200 lb. in weight. Sheep and goats are found and fowls are good and plentiful but small; eggs, cheese and butter are abundant. Fish teem, particularly mullet which are caught in nets in the back-waters. Red rock-fish, occasional seer- fish, small sharks and dogfish—the latter numerous and much esteemed by natives—are taken at sea. Fish are used to feed domestic animals and even for manure (?). (b) (c) According to the Administration Report, 1902-1903, the chief imports of the “Arab Coast” are dates (101,350 cwts.), rice (114,550 cwts.) wheat (23,953 cwts.), provisions (Rs. 93,240), salt (38,200 ewts.), coffee (9,020 cwts.), building materials, (1,035 tons), coir and coir rope (6,800 cwts.), white, grey, dyed and other shirtings and prints (1,321 packages), colours and paints (502 cwts. and 200 drums), gold lace and gold thread (6,200 tolas), hardware and cutlery (Rs. 22.660), tanned leather (Rs. 21,402), mats and mat bags (54,202 pieces), metals (1,140 cwts. iron, 382 cwts. copper, 247 cwts. brass, 60 cwts. tin and 1,244 cwts. other metals) kerosine (4,254 cases) and other oils (4,080 cwts.), perfumes (421 carboys rosewater and Rs. 37,446 worth of other perfumes), porcelain (16,180 cases), silk piece-goods (3,600 pieces), spices (1,560 cwts. turmeric, 680 cwts. black pepper, 59 cwts. ginger and 1,046 cwts. other spices), sugar (Rs. 3,998 loaf, cwts! 10,120 soft), tallow (1,532 cwts.), timber, Rs. 18,999), rafters (14,992 pieces), broad-cloth and other piece and manufactured woollen goods (498 pieces),* specie (Rs. 8,36,395). In 1902 the Arab ports were entered during the year by 21 steamers (all British) with a tonnage of 21,000 and 872 sailing vessels (about i Persian, J Arab and £ Maskat) with a tonnage of 19,650). °(d) The exports according to the same authority were pearls (Rs. 59,89,998 but this suddenly fell in 1902 to Rs. 8,00,000 only), gunnies (1,500 bundles), sharkfins (Rs. 2,500), shells (cwts. 3,000), woollen goods (2,653 pieces, local manu facture ?) and tobacco (653 cwts , locally grown?). There cleared from the Arab ports in the course of the year 21 steamers (all British) and 772 sailino- vessels (more than i Persian and most of the remainder Maskat) with ton nages respectively of 21,000 and 17,650. (e) Dabai (?) is now chief commercial centre. (/) (h) (5) (a) Whitelock in 1835 estimated (adult male?) population at 11,000 to 12,000. (5) Principal tribes are Joasmis, Beni Yas and Manasir with some Shihiyyin, Tannagis and Naim in more northern parts, (r) Men wear loin cloths, woollen robes (camolines) and silk Wahabi headdress; shave their heads, trim their beards and moustaches. Women wear blue shirts or very loose gowns* with kerchief on head and masks having eyeholes: they are much fairer than the men. In early life men are slender and in old age attenuated; but between 30 and 40 thickset and of very powerful build. They are lazy but capable of 'reat and united exertions and inured to privation, fatigue and danger from their youth18 wm Their character is cruel and vindictive and so suspicious that intermediaries are generally employed in bargains. In spite of this they have few ^ quarrels, and among them old age is respected and filial duty faithfully discharged. Their hospitality is proverbial; hut in manner they are stern; triviality is not understood ; and firmness of mind and body are the only qualities respected. {d) Some are Wahabis, others Sunnis. Bigoted and intolerant but do not carry these traits into small matters, {e) Food consists chiefly of fish, dates, bread and milk. Bicher classes indulge in rice. Much coffee is drunk even by lowest orders and smoking is not uncommon in spite of prevalence of Wahabi tenets. All are dirty in person. Principal amusements are frequent ing coffee-houses and gambling. (/) Their sole peaceful occupations are pearling and fishing : the former can only he prosecuted from June to September; and, during bad weather in winter, sea-fishing is impossible. They have therefore periods of enforced idleness which in former times led to piracy and still perhaps drives them to tribal warfare. There is practically no agriculture, (g) (h) Men marry as early as they can support a family and when one wife passes her prime they take another. Women marry as young as 14. The people treat their slaves with kindness and are formally polite to one another. (?') (/) Arms in 1835 were matchlock, spear about 7 feet long, rich dagger in girdle and long double-edged straight sword with long handle and no guard. (8) (a) — (g) (A) Genealogies of ruling families of all principalities are required. En closure to Kemball’s demi-official of 30th October 1903, does not give colla terals. Tables might include dates of birth, accession and death, so far as possible. Cox’s genealogy of Sharga family (in his letter No. 290 of 2nd July 1902) does not give dates nor, apparently, descendants of collaterals. UNIRAH.—Town mentioned by Whitelock as on Pirate Coast near a cove called Muzahma, resorted to by pearlers, between R-as al Khaima and Emm ul Kawain. YAS (BENI).—Bombay Selection, XXIV, divides them into Beni Yas, Manasir and Awamir. Palgrave calls them an ill-famed clan, half Bedouins, half villagers, and all pirates. He says their chief place is Soor and that they belong to the original inhabitants of Oman and, though devoid of its civili sation, partake in its national and political feelings and hence are haters of all Muslims and Wahabis. Beni Bu Eelasa appears to be name of a section. YAS (SIR BENI).—Island of which south-east point is in lat. 2t° 16J' north, and long. 52° 37' east. Length 6 miles north and south, breadth 4 miles. At north-east end is ruined village and bad w^ater can be got by digging. In centre is mass of volcanic hills, highest point 430 feet. At south-east end is singular land-locked harbour, with 4 to 6 fathoms and muddy bottom ; entrance only 2 cables wide; dimensions \ mile by | mile internally. Was (and is ?) much resorted to by pearlers. YIFE (JEBEL).—High peak in the country of the Beni Kaah, ZAAB (or ZAAL?).—Tribe represented at Bas al Khaima and Jazirat-al- Hamra. ZADNA.—Or Ehadna Village. (1) About 4 miles south of Ras Eibba on Shameiliya coast in Sharki district of Sharga. (2)—10). Z APR AH.—Village of Manasir tribe raided by Katar people about 1888 under personal leadership of their Sheikh. ZAHOORIYEEN —Ghafiri tribe who claim to he a branch of Ehowahir of Bereymi, though latter are Hinawis. Zahooriyeen are in practice uncon nected with Dhowahir and they follow fortunes of Shihiyyin to whom they are practically subject. In cold weather they live by fishing. From May to September they migrate bodily toHibba, Khor Fakan and Khasab, leaving care takers behind, and bivouac in date plantations attaching themselves to one of permanent communities at those places. Their villages are Shabus and Shisa and all the villages in the Malcolm and Elphinstone inlets. Some of the women screen their faces in the Egyptian fashion. ZAI.—Hamlet. (1) Two miles inland from Rams in Ras al Khaima dis trict of Sharga. (2) On hill. (3) Fortified. (4)—(10).ZAOUA.—Place where Abu Dhabi wished to locate Sudan settlors and Sharga at first objected. ZAUJ.—Place of Naim on which Beni Yas made descents in 1875. ZENICH.—Strong fort of the A1 Bu Khereyban, situated in a most pro ductive and flourishing spot. See Bombay Selection XXIV, page 458. ZOHAB.—Tribe at Ras-ul-Khaima. ZOWALIM.—A tribe. See Bombay Selection XXIV, page 456. ZUBARA.—Village. (1) On Shameiliya coast, If mile north of Ras Luliya in Sharki district of Sharga. (2) Surrounded, according to Pal grave, by fruitful gardens. (3)—(10).%•&gt; — '4 ■■I 20 B KATAE. The principal authorities for this sub-section are— (i) Admiralty Chart No. 2837 6. (ii) Map of Parts of Arabia and Persia. (iii) Philip and Son's Map of Arabia, the Red Sea, etc. (1) Bombay Selections XXIV, 1856, pages 17 to 18, 108 and 557 to 563. (2) Palgrave's ,f Observations made in Central, Eastern and Southern Arabia’'in the Journal of the Royal Geographical Society for 1864&lt;, pages 144 and 145, (3) Palgrave’s Central and Eastern Arabia,' 1865 (2nd Volume), pages 230 to 243. (4) Curzon's “Persia,' 1892, Volume II, pages 452—454. (5) Douglas's “ Journey from India to the Mediterranean,' 1897, page 8. (6) Persian Gulf Pilot, 1898, pages 114 to 127. .(7) Government of India s Political Records, Persian Gulf Administration Beports and Persian Gulf Residency Diaries. t21 B. KATAR. ABDULLAH (AL) —A tribe unfriendly to Bahrein who were expected to settle at Zubara in 1883. ALASSAR.—Tribe frequently mentioned in Bombay Selections XXIV. ADHWAN (DUHAT).—Large shallow inlet on west coast of Katar, 9 miles in length, with maximum depth of 2 fathoms. ATTEERAT.—See Bombay Selections XXIV, page 561. Is Euairit meant ? Affeerat had (1856) 150 men of A1 Bu Kuwara and Uttoohee tribes. AINAIN (AL BU).—A tribe raided by the A1 Muhammad about 1884. AINAM (AL BU).—A tribe which formerly lived at Wakrah but settled at Ghareeyat about 1886. AINDAR.—Place marked in Philip’s Map of Arabia at bottom of Gulf of Bahrein* ALT (AL BIN).—Branch of Uttoobee.tribe which deserted Bahrein and settled at Zubara in 1895. AMAMERAH.—A tribe frequently mentioned in Katar. On account of murder of their chief, Sultan bin Salama, they have had feud with A1 Bin Ali since 1896. ASEYLIAH —Place south of Nasaimeer. BAKAKALA—A tribe represented at Bidaa. BAKHUR.—Place between Hasa and Katar where an Abu Dhabi force seized camels and sheep belonging to dependents of Katar Chief in 1888. BEHAIH.—Section of A1 Morrah tribe, by whom relations of Bahrein Chief were murdered in 1900, BI DA A.—Large town in lat. 25° 17' north and long. 51° 31'east, situated in deep bay on east coast of Katar promontory, about 65 miles south by east of its extremity at Ras Rekkin. Reefs off the bay make it a natural harbour, but the entrance is shallow and somewhat difficult, and vessels of more than 15 feet draught cannot pass. Land on west side of bay is stony desert, 40 or 50 feet above sea-level. South-east point of bay is quite low. Harbour basin is 3 miles in extent with regular soundings of 3 to 5 fathoms, bottom white mud or clay. Bidaa is built up the side of the rising ground and there is a fort in the town. There are two towers on high land above town and 1J miles south-east of town another tower near the wells, where there is a little culti vation, the rest of the country being desert. Other accounts place the w^ater- supply 3 miles from the town. Doha-as Saghira immediately adjoins Bidaa on east and beyond it, without interval, comes town of Doha. The three places together cover a mile of sea front and contain population of about 5,000 of mixed tribes, always at feud with Bedouins. No large baghalas but many pearl-boats; and inhabitants are all employed in pearl-fishery. Little can be obtained in way of supplies. Water is dear and indifferent, best being brought in skins from desert. Firewood comes from interior and from Clarence Strait (Gulf Pilot, 1898). Kemball (1845) says that inhabitants are mostly Soodan, and that there are 300 houses and 600 to 700 fightino- men. Palgrave (1863) describes town as consisting of mass of smafl and dingy houses separated by irregular lanes, with a long, narrow and dirty market-place; population 6,000 including Bahrein shop-keepers and arti sans and immigrants from Hasa. Palgrave describes male population as over-engrossed and shattered in health by pearl diving. He mentions two mosques, one in simple Wahabi taste, the other smaller and more handsome in semi-Persian style. According to Ross there were here in 1882 no less than 250 pearl boats wmrking under the Chief: but, from his remark that Bidaa had been formed by recent coalescence of 2 small villages, it would C9I2FD p22 seem that he^meant to include Doha and Doha-as-Saghira (?). He mentioned Sheikh’s residence as at extreme south end and Turkish fort and garrison as in centre of town (of Bidaa proper ?). Most of Indian traders were only visitors coming with borrowed capital to trade at Bidaa and visit the islands for 4 or 5 months in the pearl season. In 1882 there were only 3 settled Banyans who were cloth-sellers : 2 of them were bakers as well. ™ C? ABSAH '- A tribe some of whom took part in Katar raid on Abu Dhabi m 1888-9. C 5 IBI SA..~A tribe originally settled at Bidaa, who left it on account of difficulties with TJrair tribe. In 1873 they owned about 25 fishing boats and removed from Khor Hassan to Zubara, being at that time allies of the Naim. CHITEBH (UMM-AL).—Name of a pearl-bank (?). CHURN.-—Place (near Odeid ? ) where it was suspected a Turkish detach ment might be found in 1892. Name occurs in decyphered telegram and mav be mutilated. J DAAPEEN.—Tract to which emigrants from Katar go as well as to Bahrein. DAKEERAH.—Place mentioned as passed on sea-route from Bidaa to Bahrein. , AW ? A A“7 I&gt;lace mentione &lt;* in Katar treaty of 1868 as future residence of Chief. Is Doha meant ? DHAAYEN.—-See Zaayen. Dakemh'S, I ovf?~ Inhabited (?) ^ ° n ^ COaSt ° f Katar - Same as DHANNA.—A small port near Odeid. DOHA.—Town to east of Bidaa and connected with it by villaee of Doha. as-Saghira. Partly walled round and has several towers. Sheikh’s house is at large round tower on beach about centre of town, and west of tower is small bight where boats are haukd up for repair. According to Palgrave (1863) fiO h +r, ro 1 f/ I t- Z fi°l Bl i daaand ) 18 Sltuated m sma11 deep bay with cliffs behind 60 to 80 feet high ; houses lower and meaner than at Bidaa and market-nlace : narrower and dirtier. Ross (1882) appears to include Doha in his description of • a Tribe at feud with A1 Bin Ali in 1900. Some of then inhabit, or used to inhabit, Bidaa. ° inerr nQi?r JMAN w 5 mportan M Bedouin? ) tribe inland from Katar Kembal ( 18 45) says Wakra was founded by Boo Ejman refugees from Bidaa in 19tl century. Total number about 10,000 ; fighting strength 2,000. Sheikhs an subsidised by Turkish Government. ° oeiKns are EAKHRAH (AYAL).—Tribal section (?) at Bidaa. EAREYBAIL—Place in Katar, where, and at Zubara, A1 Bin Ali tribe used in former times (according to Jasim bin Muhammad bin Thani) to reside EARIIIA.-—Small village, 3 miles south of Khor Hasan on west side of SS KZSu.,2, Sj ‘''''s b “'- •«&gt; “ of Katar AtRlr ' _Sma11 WaUed t0WU With SeveraI towers ’ 0,1 north-east coast GHAREEYAT.-—Village, apparently in neighbourhood of •* i wSfolTowf? Chief WiShed t0 attack in 18§6 - Is -nre^s Ghar^a lished^em^ntTfromWakr! 6 With 4 miks n0rth of ^airrt, estab-23 GHODHA.—Halting place on eastern route from Bereymi to Hasa, inland from Katar Peninsula. HAJIR (BENI).—Important (Bedouin ?) tribe whose territory adjoins Katar. Sections are Makhazzabah, Makbzeeyah, Makkhazab, Matair, Al Muhammad and Sahool. Total number about 4,000 to 5,000 ; fighting strength 800. Sheikhs receive Turkish subsidies. HALUL.—Island in lat. 25° 40' north and long. 52° 25' east, 71 miles south-east by east from Has Rakkin. One mile across ; hilly with peak of 180 feet ; anchorage and landing-place on south east side. Quite barren ; no water ; visited by pearl boats. HAMADAL.—Tribe owning 7 boats which migrated from Jumail to Zubara in 1S73. HASAN (KHOR).—Small town and fort on Katar coast 9 miles south west of has Rakkin. Had (before 1856) a square fort and 100 inhabitants, mostly fishermen, of Al Bu Kuwara and Uttoobee tribes. In 1818 it had 400 houses and was retreat of Rahmat bin Jabir (?). HA WAR.—Island about 10 miles long off west coast of Katar, frequented by fishermen. Before 1856 it had 2 fishing villages. HAvYAYLAH.—Place in Katar, once tenanted, according to Jasim bin Muhammed bin Thani, by the Al Bin Ali tribe. Is this same as Howeila below ? HAZARA.—Place in desert where Jasim, Chief of Katar, camped to be out of reach of Turks in 1894. HOWEILA.—Small town with square fort on north-west coast of Katar. Inhabited before 1853 by 400 Al Bu Kuwara and was then a principal pearl fishing station and had water-supply and some cattle. People were employed in pearl fishery. Place was deserted in 1887. There is water. IBRAHIM (BELAD),—Place on Katar coast between Bidaa and Wakra. Uninhabited and ruinous in 1887. ISMxAIL.—Place (in Katar ?) passed after Ghareeyat and Etuweis on sea journey from Bidaa to Bahrein. JAN.—Place in Katar inland (?) from Zubara. JUMAIL.—Place occupied by Hamadal tribe before their removal to Zubara in 1873. KARFAIJ.—Place south of Nasaimeer. KASR KOONAR.—Place at or in Bidaa. KAT—Part or suburb (?) of Bidaa. KATAR.—Bogins north of Khor al Odaid and in the political sense may be taken as extending to eastern extremity of Turkish province of Hasa recog nised by British Government. Does it properly extend to Katif and include Ojair ? See Bombay Selection XXIV, page 18, Beri Gattar. Erom Odaid for 18 miles shore consists of high white sandhills: this tract is called Najhan and ends at Jezirat Mishiryat. Thence to Bidaa is low, sandy or stony desert. At Bidaa there is some slightly elevated rocky ground and there area few hillocks in different other parts between Wakra and Ras Rakkin ; greater part is stony desert and north part is very low. According to Gulf Pilot (1898) Wakra to Ras Rakkin section sends only 200 boats to pearl fishery. Off west coast of Katar, between it and Bahrein, is large Easht-ad-Dibal shoal, 5 miles long north and south by 21 miles broad. Coast of Katar on this side is low, sandy or stony desert with a few little hills here and there. Only vegetation is coarse grass growing in tufts on sand-hills and small brushwood in places. Palgrave (1883) describes Katar as a miserable province consisting of mi’e upon mile of low barren hills, bleak and sun-scorched, with hardly a tree. Beach generally muddy and ^ mile broad. Pasture scanty in extreme. Occasional mud villages and palm leaf huts, all walled in. There are towers, 25 to 30 feet high with door %24 way up and rope ladder, to protect grazing grounds and a few larger fortifications. Fixed inhabitants generally too busy to be warlike. Climate remarkably dry and loses all humidity a few miles inland. Soil poor, gravel and marl mixed with sand : here and there wells are sunk ; gardens small and unproductive; no fields or date-groves worthy of name. Coast unhealthy. Inland south of Bidaa are pebbly upland tracts without trees; women there fetch water from distant wells and there are flocks of goats resembling sheep. Gaskin. (BK)3) says inhabitants of Katar belong to numerous small tribes; practically all are pearl fishers and have hitherto been financed by Chief of Katar. KHOR (1),—Pearl-fishing place financed in 1887, along with Bidaa and Puairit, by Chief of Katar. Is this same as following ? KHOR (2).—A northern village of Katar evacuated by order of Chief of Katar but again reoccupied by his permission in 1889. KOBAISAT.—Tribe at Wakra, connected with Abu Dhabi. Are these same as Kubaisat in sub-section A ? KOHISA.—Tribe. Same as Chibisa above ? KUFARIYA.—Bay on coast in direction of Odaid to which Chief of Katar despatched, or meant to despatch, by boat in 1889, provisions lor his expedition against Abu Dhabi. KUTVARA (AL BU).—Tribe some of whom, disliking Turkish Govern ment or from some other cause, removed from Bidaa to Puairit. Are these the same who had a fray with Beni Hajir in 1874 ? LUSAIL.—Bay some miles north of Bidaa where Jasim, Chief of Katar, was found to have settled with small following of a few families in 1903. MAADEEK.—Tribe (of Bedouins?) owing allegiance to Jasim, Chief of Katar, in 1887. MAADHEED or MAAZEED.—Section (of Beni Hajir tribe?) subject to Jasim, Chief of Katar. MAHANIDAH.—Tribe, some of whom joined in great Katar raid of 1883-9, on Abu Dhabi. Is this same as Mehanedah below ? MAKHAZZABAH.—Section of Beni Hajir, inimical to A1 Muhammad tribe, but friendly and connected with A1 Morrah. Habitat Katar (including Bidaa), also between Ojair and Hassa. MAKHDHOOBEE.—Tribe from political connection with whom Jasim, Chief of Katar, professed in 1887 to have severed himself. MAKHDHEYYAH.—Tribe who raided Abu Dhabi territory about 1855. MAHZEEYAH.—Section of Beni Hajir. MAKHAZZAH.—Section of Beni Hajir against whom Jasim, Chief of Katar, professed enmity in 1888. MANAMANEH.—Tribe, owning 8 boats, which moved from Aboo Zuroof to Zubara in 1873. MASALLATAH.—Tribe, some of whom joined in great Katar raid of 1888-9 on Abu Dhabi territory. MAT AIR.—Branch of Beni Hajir tribe.. MAURAIR —Fort adjoining Zubara. Is this same as Moreyr below ? MEESHEYREE B.—Water place nearer to Bidaa town than Naaiiah but water is brackish and scanty. MEHANEDA—Tribe occupying Khor Shajij. MERREKH.—Place south of Kasaimeer. MISEMIR orMEESEYMEER.—Place where there is water, 2 hours’ dis tance from Bidaa, between Bidaa and Wakra. MOREYR.—Place with laige fort, situated on slightly risin c, ‘ ^round about li miles inland, between Zubara and Fariha. MORRAH (AL).—The most savage looking of all the Bedouins encoun tered by I algrave , their hair elf-locks, their dress rags, their complexion o'rime Dialect an ancient form of Arabic. Widely spread tribe, of whom only small25 portion in 1863 acknowledged Wahabi influence; greater number were regard ed as infidels. Colour dusky verging on black. Eloquent, savage but not bar barous ; good natured, but impudent and predatory. Their flocks of goats can (Palgrave) pass 4 or 5 days without watering. Many of A1 Morrah actually inhabit the Dahna desert taking advantage of the oases. More numerous and widely distributed than Manasir, but less pugnacious. They visit Katar and Oman, sometimes for trade and sometimes for plunder. Douglas gives their number as 3,000 and fighting strength as 500 : he says their Chiefs receive Turkish allowances. MOWAH (JEBEL).—Hill near coast at bottom of Gulf of Bahrein. MUHAMMAD (AL).—Section of Beni Hajir, connected and friendly with Ejman. Habitat near Katif. MUSALLAM (AL).—Tribe in Katar. MUZARIYA.—Tribe occasionally visiting Chief of Bahrein for sake of presents. Habitat not indicated. Can these be identical with tribe of similar name in Oman and territory of Truoial Chiefs ? NAAIJAH.—Place whehce water-supply of Bidaa is derived, variously stated to be at 15 minutes and 3 miles distance from the town. Must be held by garrison if intending to retain possession of Bidaa. NAHUNE.—One of Arab tribes inhabitiug Bidaa (1856). Are Naim meant ? NATJAH.—Port of Jasim in Katar where there are Bedouins. Can this be same as Naaijah above ? NAIM.—Bedouin tribe in Katar who grazed their cattle on pastures surrounding Zubara in 1873: 60 or 70 of them have a hereditary attach ment to Bahrein Chief. Is this a branch of great Naim tribe in Oman and territory of Trucial Chiefs ? Gulf Pilot says they occupy the country between Ojair and Katar, are not unfriendly to strangers and are reported the most powerful tribe of the Katar peninsula. NAJHAN.—See Katar. NASAIMEER.—Place in Katar or inland from it. OBEYJA.—Place between which and Odaid the Turks, in 1879, forbade any new settlements to be established. BIYAT.—Small village with several towers on coast about 2 miles north of Euairit. RUBEIJA.—Village on west coast of Katar, 2 miles south of Eas Ashiraj. Inhabited before 1856 by about 150 Utoobees. RUWEIS.—Small town on north-west coast of Katar, 2j miles south of Eas Eakkin. Has many boats which anchor inside thereof; also a fort with 4 towers, first object visible when making land from north. Before 1856 it had about 100 A1 Bu Kuwara and Utoohee inhabitants. SAKIK.—Halting place on western route from Bereymi to Hasa with sweet springs and some wood. Lies a little south-west of Katar Peninsula. SALATAH.—Tribe who removed from Katar to Bahrein in 1889 on account of their treatment by Jasim, Chief of Katar. SALWA—Halting place on eastern route from Bereymi to Hasa somewhat west of Katar Peninsula. Is it near bay of same name ? SALWA (DUHAT).—Bay, forming south end of Gulf of Bahrein. SAMAISMA.—Place near Khor Shajij, 8 miles from Biddaa. Jasim wish ed, or pretended he wished, to settle herein 1883. SEHALEEYA.—Place about 1J hours* distance from Bidaa southwards. SHAKAB.—Port (?) between Bidaa and Wajbah. SADEH.—Tribe who in 1873 owned 5 boats and removed from Ruweis to Zubara. SAHOOL —Branch of Beni Hajir tribe. SAMEYTEE (AL BU)—Name of a tribe. No particulars.SHAJIJ (KHOR).—There is a small village with several towers in this inlet. Inhabitants are Mehaneda (?). Inlet had (1856) from to 2J fathoms in it. SHEER (UMM AL).—Pearl-bank (?) off Ras Laffan. SHIKOH —Inland place between Euairit and Bidaa with fresh spring. Jasim was building fort here in 1886. SMAITH (AL BU).—Tribe at Bidaa (?). No particulars. SON DAN.—Tribe mentioned in 1887 as subject to Chief of Katar. Is this misprint for Soudan below ? SOUDAN.—Tribe with headquarters at Sharga on Pirate Coast, but represented in 1885 by about 80 men at Bidaa abo. Kemball (1845) called them the principal inhabitants of Bidaa. SWEISIMA.—Place in Katar where the pirate Ahmad bin Selman was residing in 1902. THAEIN.—Place in Katar Peninsula where piracy was committed by Al.mad bin Selman in 1902. THARUF (ABU).—Village on north-west const of Katar. Also called Zaluf (?;. Before 1856 contained about 50 men of A1 Bu Kuwara tribe. TIIOWEIHA.—Small port near Odaid. URAIR.—Tribe on account of differences with whom Chibisa left Bidaa for Khor Hasan some time before 1873. WAJBAH.—Place where there is water, between Wahra and Bidaa, 4 hours from Wakra. AVAKRA.—Rising town on east coast of Katar, south of Bidaa. In 1845 numbered 250 houses and 500 to 600 fighting men. Inhabitants were Boo Ejman emigrants from Bidaa. Is close to beach; has now 12 towers, many boats and perhaps 1,000 inhabitants. One mile to south is Jebel Wakra 85 feet high. Native bo\ts run close up to town at high water, either over or through reef. Vessel, even of small draft, cannot anchor nearer town than 2 miles. Palgrave (1863) described Wakra as independent of Bidaa and other towns; and as thriving and more cheerful in appearance than Bidaa, to which it was equal in size. Distance was less than 10 miles from Bidaa and coast roid, which passed through bleak and barren country, was safe for travellers. Several small traders and artisans were settled here. TAMIL—Village on north-west coast of Katar, 4 miles north-east of Khor Hasan. YUSUFIYA.—Village on north-west coast of Katar, 3 miles north-east of Khor Hasan. Before 1856 had about 50 inhabitants of mixed tribes, all fishermen. ZAAYEN.—Or Dhaayen. Near Samaisma between Bidaa and Khor Shajij. Jasim went to reside and built fort here in 1887, ZAEDEE (AL).—Tribe. No particulars. ZAKHEERAH.-^-Place visited by Jasim in 1886. He came by boat from Bidaa and then went by land to Khor Shajij. Is this same as Dhakira above ? ^ZAKHNUNIYA,.— Island adjoining mainland south of Bahrein. Length 4 miles ; has fort and village. There is shallow channel between it and mainland. Before 1856 it had 400 inhabitants of Alassar tribe. ZILA.—Inland place, south of Odaid, where Jasim talked of settling in 1888, . ZUBARA—Formerly important town, represented in 1898 by extensive rums. Stood on east side of bay enclosed by Ras Ashiraj. Palgrave speaks o it as largest of island (sic) towns and only one of territorial importance, lior to 1856 it had ceased to exist as a town but fine Neidi horses were still embarked here. Formerly it had considerable trade. ZUROOF (ABOO).—See Manamaneh, Is this same as Tharuf above ?28 ■S9Q9SS9SHH0HBPB ABDULLAH (AL).—The branch of the ruling Khalifah family of Bahrein to which Nasir«bin-Mubarak belonged. ABOOKABA.—A tribe of Bahrein. ADHARL—Principal spring on Bahrein Island. See Bahrein. AGARRIA.-—Place in Bahrein where Turkish Mutasarrif halted on way from Katar to Katif. ALT.—Small tumble-down village, about one hour’s ride from Manama in the centre of Bahrein Island. Apparently connected with Manama by remains of an ancient made road. Immediately outside of it are 25 or 30 large tumuli from 40 to 50 feet high and 40 to 50 yards in diameter at base. These are adjoined by chains and groups of innumerable smaller tumuli extending to the south and west of the village. One large and one small tumu lus was opened by Durand in 1879 and the same by Bent in 1889. Ivory fragments found in the interior of Bent’s larger tumulus where pronounced by an expert to be of Phoenician workmanship. Pottery is made here. ALT (AL BIN).—Tribe called by Douglas one of the largest sections of the Bahreinis. AMAMERAH.—A Bahrein tribe. ARAD—Peninsula forming part of Muharrak Island, from the south of which it projects into the horseshoe bay formed by the island on that side. On it are a date grove and large double fort. From Buckingham it would appear that the whole of Muharrak Island was formerly called Arad. ARAD EAMOHAY.—Mentioned at page 566 of Bombay Records XXIV as an island of the Bahrein group. ARZA.—Islet, situated on reef, f mile north-east of Kalali. Has remains of a building and two fresh-water springs near it. ASKER.—Eishing village on east coast of Bahrein Island about east-north east from Jebel Dukhan. AWAL.—Niebuhr gives this name to Bahrein Island. Palgrove ridicules Niebuhr, declaring that Awwal means “ shark ’* and is not the name of any island in the Gulf. Zwemer says that the name Owal still lingers. BAHREIN.—Group of islands forming a principality. Includes the islands of Bahrein (or Awal?), Muharrak (or Arad ?), Sitra and (?) Umm Nahsan, which are described under their own names, (i) The Government of India have decided that the Sheikh of Bahrein has no territorial possessions on the mainland though he owns rights of pasture, etc., there. The boundary of Bahrein in every direction is therefore the surrounding sea. From Ritter it would appear that a tract extending along a considerable portion of the east side of the Gulf once bore the name of Bahrein and was the abode of the Carmathians. (2) No information as to sub-divisions. (3) The physical char acteristics of the separate islands are described under their names. The principal features of the group are the lowness and levelness of the land and the shallowness of the surrounding sea. The whole Gulf of Bahrein is a mass of reefs and shoals from Ras Rakkin to Ras Tanura,a distance of 70 miles, except for one clear and fairly wide channel running north and south, off the east side of Muharrak Island. The most extensive obstacles to navigation are the Fasht-ad-Dibal, 5 miles long from north to south by 2J broad, between Muharrak Island and Ras Rakkin ;°and the Fasht-al-Yarim or Teignmouth Shoal, 13 miles in length from north to south by 8 miles in breadth towards its north end. The latter protects the Manama anchorage from the north and west. The shallow waters of Bahrein may be considered to extend to the Rennie Shoal, over 50 miles north of the island. There is a passage from Bahrein to Katif south of the Fasht-al-Yarim available for vessels drawing not more than 15 feet: it is called the Kbor-al-Bab. Many of the reefs dry in patches at low water, and the island of Muharrak isI29 tripled in area when the tide has receded. A remarkable feature of the Bahrein islands are the fresh-water springs which exist, both on land and under the sea near the shore. The largest on land is the Adhari which rises about 3 miles south-west of Manama near the head of the Nabbi Sali creek : it forms a perfect river of fast-running water, 10 feet broad and 2 deep, which irrigates many miles of date-groves, being conveyed by an ancient stone aqueduct. The Abu Zeidan spring flows from stone arrh under small mosque at Belad-el-Kadim : it is built round and reserved for Chief of Bahrein and his family. There are also the Gassari spring between Manama and Belad el Kadim, and the IImm Shaoom spring 1 mile east of Manama. Bent mentions one called Garsari (is this same as Gassari above?) and Ritter speaks of an Ain Marilgha and an Ain Ghadar. According to Bent the Arabs think springs are fed by an underground continuation of the river Euphrates. The marine springs lie mostly around Muharrak Idand, there being one on Saya islet, 3 inside Kliaseifa opposite Dir, 2 on Arza islet opposite Kahili, one at Bu Shahin and one called Bu Mahir near Muharrak Port (see the articles on these places). There is also a fine fresh marine spring on the Khor Easht about north-west from the Portuguese Fort on Bahrein island and miles from the nearest land, from which Whish obtained 70G gallons of good drinking water in one day in 1859. Most of these springs are brackish (?) and Zwemer says those on the north part of the island are luke-wnrm. The best water in the islands is found at Hanaini whence it is brought daily to Manama by caravan. (4) Ac cording to Bombay Selection (1818) the climate is bad, and the inhabitants more prone to suffer from contagious diseases than elsewhere in the Gulf, cholera being specially virulent here : Gulf fever is prevalent and strangers sleeping on shore are liable to be attacked by it. Palgrave experienced violent gales at Bah rein in January i86'b accompanied by rain, hail and thunder; trees were blow T n down, huts unroofed and ships swamped or cast away. Durand states that the climate is delightful from October to April. Zwemer says the climate is not so bad as has often been stated by casual visitors. October, November, December, March and April are pleasant months, the temperature indoors rang ing from 60° to 85°. January and February when north winds blow and it is cold enough to light fires are the most rainy and least healthy months. From May to September weather is hot, but till the middle of June the nights are cool and the heat is tempered by sea breeze (barih). Land breezes from west and south continue irregularly all summer; when they fail thermometer remains persistently above 100°. In the summer of 1893 at Manama the mini mum indoors was 85° and the maximum in the shade 107°. The prevailing wind is the Shemal, which in winter is violent and endangers shipping : only other strong w ind is Kaus from south-east which blows irregularly between December and April. (5) No information, except that there are traces of a made road to Ali, that caravans ply betw een Manama and Hanaini, and that some excel lent donkeys are obtainable for transport. (6) (a) Products are pearls, dates, figs, citrons, peaches (?) and loazi almonds, of which husk is eaten as well as kernel; also limes, oranges, pomegranates and grapes and a few vegetables of several kinds including onions. Clover (?) and lucerne are grown fur fodder. Bombay Selections mentions mulberries and melons, and Ritter speaks of corn. Palgrave thought the vegetable produce of Bahrein, except citrons, was below mediocrity: palms were numerous but the dates wretched, and generally speaking vegetable growth was rank but quality poor. Small gazelle are common in the rocky highlands. Camels are kept but do not thrive ; the white donkeys of the place are celebrated for strength and swiftness. Mignan says the horses are renowned for their “ gentility. 1 Sheep are few. Oxen and kine are not rare, but the beef is poor. Fish are abundant and good, (b) No information about internal trade except that the agricultural inhabitants sell their surplus produce at Manama, (c) Imports, mostly from India are rice, cloth, cotton, calico and spices to the value of $ 600,000, of which J is for local consumption and f for re-exportation (Bombay Records, 1818). Imports are dates and ghee from Basra; goats, sheep, bullocks, cow^s, camoleens, dates, donkeys and horses from Arabia; sugar, cloth, gunpowder, swords and matchlocks from Persia; rice, cloth, indigo, thread, needles, etc., from India (Whitelock, 1835). Bice, sugar, indigo, iron, metals, ghi and Malabar timber for ship building are imported (Ritter, 1816), Douglas (1896) mentions%30 a trade worth about one lakh of rupees annually in rifles, mostly Martini rifles and carbines, purchased at Rs. 100 each and nearly all re exported to the mainland. He says rice is imported from India and wheat from India and the Persian ports, large quantities being re-exported to the Arabian coast. Ac cording to the Gulf Pilot (1898) imports are piece-goods, rice, cotton, coffee, timber and other shipbuilding materials ; also, largely for re-exportation, cattle, fuel, grain, drugs, tobacco, sugar, oil, etc- Zvvem'r (1900) calls Bahrein the rice, timber and piece-geols depot for all eastern Arabia. The following were the principal imports in 1903 and their approximate values in lakhs of rupees : pearls 45^, specie 43, rice 20f, cotton piece-goods 9, dates 4^, coffee 3f, tobacco 2f, timber and wood 2, wheat If, ghee and sugar each, silk piece- goods 1^, and cattle If lakhs. An arms import, worth 4 lakhs a year only a short time before, had entirely disappeared The total value of the imports for 1903 was 154 lakhs, of which 87 lakhs fiom India and 52 lakhs from Turkey. About f of the coffee, f of the cotton-goods, f of the dates, f of the grain and pulse and of the specie were re-exported, also the wdiole of the pearls. In 1903 no less than 71 steamers with cargo, all British, aggregate tonnage 102,876, enter ed Bahrein, (d) Exports, according to Bombay seiections (1818) are p arls, dried dates and hullinn, worth $800,000 annually. Bahrein boats were calculated to collect 3a0,000 crowns’ wortli of pearls annually, and more than that quantity to be brought to Bahrein for sale from other places. 'Whitelock (1835) mentions wool camoleens and dried fish; also that dite^, horses, pearls and dried fish are taken to India by Bahrein vessels. The Gulf Pilot (1898) gives pearls and dates as principal exports, adding hides, cotton sail-cloth, grain, datemats of fine tex ture, wool, cattle and a few remarkably fine horses and donkeys. The following are given as the strengths of the Bahrein merchant fleet at different periods :— 1,409 fishing boats, of which 700 large, 300 intermediate and 400 small (Bombay Selection^, 1818). 8ome large baggalas, built for trade and war, which made 2 trips to India in beginning of north-east monsoon (Whitelock, 1835). 25 merchant baggalas, some of large size, 12 bateels and ghoonchas, 800 pearl boats (Bombay Selections, 1839). Six large baggalas trading t &gt; India besides 30 or 40 of size used in Gulf trade and 500 to 600 pearl boats as compared with 21 large merchant vessels, 500 fishing and cargo boats and 1,500 pearl boats at an earlier time (Bombay Selections, date uncertain). Latest passage in same autho rity (probably about 1850) gives 20 large boats of 140 to 350 tons and 100 of from 40 to 120 tons. Gulf Pilot (1898) mentions only 300 to 400 pearl boats and 200 native craft of from 20 to 300 tons, besides many of smaller size. Ac cording to Bombay Selections 30,003 inhabitants out 70,000 live by pearl fishery. The chief exports in 1903 were (in lakhs of rupees) : pearls 102f, grain and pulse 6^, specie 4|, dates 3-|, cotton piece-goods 3f, oyster-shells 2^, and coffee 1|- lakhs. Except pearls and oyster-shells these appear to have been almost entirely exports of imported goods. The total value of the exports in lakhs of rupees was 130, of which 106^ went to India and 13 to Turkey. In 1903 steamers clearing from Bahrein with cargo numbered 38 of which 37 were British, total tonnage of latter was 56,055. [Not understood how number of steamers clearing could be so much smaller than that of those entering See Gulf Administration Report, 1903-04 (e) Trade appears to be concentrated at Manama, the commercial capital, (f) —(A) No information. (7) {a) Population has been variously estimated at different, and even in recent times. Niebuhr puts the villages at 40 to 50 Bom bay Selections give (1815) only 15,000 aboriginal Bahreinis and 15,000 self- styled Arabs. 1 he same authority later (IS^) mentions 50,000 inhabitants and later still 69,000, and again 70,000. Whitelock (1835) gives 15,000 as the total of the ruling Uttoobee tribe and says towns w r ere 36 in number and formerly there were more. Palgrave states the agricultural villages at 50 or 60 and gives the population at 70,000 but decreasing. Bent estimates the villages at 50. Douglas (1896) puts the total population at 120,000 and the Gulf Pilot (189S) at 50,000. (/;) The islands seem to contain at least two races, viz., aboriginal Bahreinis and immigrant Arabs. Few travellers discriminate pro perly between the two. The Arabs are said to be Uttoobees, Al Bu Kuwara, A1 Zayed, Al Salata, Al Mahande, Mootsallema, Kaiser, Genahat and some mixed tribes. Bombay Selections (^818) say aboriginal Bahreinis are cruelly oppressed by their Uttoobee conquerors and that there is much doubt as to their31 or] Vin. Mi 'nan (1S39) says the men (Bahreinis ?) are tall, slender, short-lived, with weak and scanty heard, their heads covered with an immense bush of hair anointed with fetid grease and that they wear only a handkerchief secured round their loins by leather thongs. (Does this refer to pearl divers in general or to aboriginal Bahreinis ?) Bombay Selections (1854) makes the aborigines to be of Persian descent: in another place it speaks of them as a mixed breed be tween Arab and Persian. Palgrave describes the country people (aborigines ?) as living in clusters of thatched cottages and maintaining little intercourse with Manama. He says they have an almost savage look, the result of their isolation; that a few in the centre of the island live by bunting, those on the coasts by fishing and rest by agriculture. He calls the town people a hybrid race fused into a distinctive type, with round features and of medium build Bent referring to inhabitants of vilhges (aborigines ?), says they nave little or nothing to do with pearl fisheries hut are an industrious race of peasants. From the above confusing accounts it is hard to say how inhabitants of Bahrein should he classified. (&lt;?) No information as to character of Arabs. Bahreinis are said to have more of the indolence and cunning of the Persian than of the frank and open boldness of the Arab, and to be despised by the Arabs. Palgrave says that the town people are intelligent, easy, good humoured, better adapted to peace than to war, to trade than to agriculture, not equal to Omanis or Indians in regular business, but making excellent weavers, workers m metal, wood and leather, tailors and dyers, (d) Shiahs apparently predominate.^ (Is this only among Bahreinis or also among Arabs?) Niebuhr says that in his time Persians came here to study the Koran in Arabic, and Bahrein was called the Shiah University. Palgrave remarks that the Sunnis of Manama are, curiously enough, Malikis. (&lt;?) Nothing is said of mode of life of Arabs. Some of the information under (b) above refers to life of Bahreinis. Mignan remarks that pearl divers’ families live in cabins of date-leaf and reeds. Bent notes, apparently with regard to the Bahreinis, that some eat seaweed and that they make sheerah for their own consumption out of slightly dried dates with date juice and an addition of sesame seed, walnuts or ginger-powder. (/) Occupa tions of the Arab population are not distinguished from those of Bahreinis. Bent says villagers feed their cows on green dates, date stones and fish bones boiled together and give green dates {salang) as fodder to their donkeys ; water for irrigation is hoisted by charsas worked by donkeys or bullocks and the water is distributed from the channels to the date trees by balanced buckets. The groves are manured with the fins of the ray-fish {awal). {g) (j) No information. (8) In 18 i 8 (Bombay Records) the yearly revenue of the islands was esti mated at 100,000 tomans of 12 piastres Rumi each, f of which was con sidered to be obtained by extortion. Whitelock (1836) reported the revenue to he 2 lacs of rupees ; there were no fixed duties on imports or exports, but the Sheikh and his sons took as much as they could, the Sheikh also receiving i 0 0 f the produce of all date-trees. Whitelock found no police and much oppression. According to the Bombay Records (1845) there were no customs but a revenue of 100,000 crowns was derived mostly from the date planta tions, nearly the whole of which had been seized by the Uttoohees from the original owners. The Sheikh did not receive the whole of this but he collected a tax of 5 to 10 crowns from each pearl-boat on its return from the fishery. About 13 years before the Chief had tried, during seven years, to establish customs, but had failed. There were no fixed taxes but the Sheikh was in the habit of exacting forced contributions, especially from the aboriginal Bahreinis. The Bahrein Chief could muster more vessels than any other potentate in the Gulf; he had 12 large baghlas never employed for trade and could retain for war 25 merchant baghlas that generally traded to India. He had 300 Sidis and 800 Beni Khalid in his pay as soldiers Further on in the same volume it is stated that the Sheikh bad 6 war baghlas and could fit out 15 or 20. One was of 400 tons and mounted 22 guns. He had a fort on a sandy point at Muharrak with 6 or 8 guns, another at Arad and a third at Samahoy; there was also a ruinous wall round the town. On Bahrein Island was Rufaa and about 50 other villages with a number of towers, but the best defences of the island were the reefs surrounding it, enabling 500 resolute men to prevent the landing of 5,000. Palgrave (1862) found the customs administration arbitrary and learning backward. Wahabiism had exercised a blighting, though latterly32 indirect influence on Bahrein, with the result that Bahrein emigrants were settled in places all round the Gulf; there were said to be 30d on the island of Kais (?). In 1898 Sheikh had some very fast sailing war vessels (batils). Zwemer (IbOO) writing of the present Chief says most of his time is devoted to hawking and the chase ; judicial authority is exercised by a Kadhi and oppres sion, blackmail and bribery are universal. BAHREIN ISLAND.—Island 27 miles long with maximum width of 10 miles. According to Bombay Records (1856) about £ of the island is well-watered, thickly inhabited and partly cultivated, the rest is in equal proportions hilly and desert. The soil of about £ is rich and capable of much improvement as, with the exception of the date plantations and a few barley, wheat and clover fields, it lies entirely waste. Wliish (1859) described the road from Manama to Jebel Dukhan as leading through rich date plan tations and gardens in the direction of some minarets, passing which a back water was reached mire or less fordable according to the state of the tide. Beyond this, | a mile, an open space began, covered at first with tumuli but later subsiding into a level plain, swampy in places. A rocky path between steep cliffs, 40 or 50 feet high, then led to elevated ground, barren and very stony. From this point there was a gradual ascmt to Rufaa followed by a des cent into a vast crater surrounded on all sides by cliffs. Over the bottom of the crater the road ran for 5 miles through uneven ground of rocky formation to Jebel Dukhan, a mass of rock standing almost alone in the centre of the crater. From Rufaa to Jebel Dukhan ground was covered with stones, which were coated with green lichen and contained beautiful crystallised spar. Palgrave (186z&gt; described the west side of the island as consisting of dark tenacious mould steeped in moisture. Many paths crossed the north end of the island leading to little clusters of thatched cottages Durand (1879) found that Jebel Dukhan com manded a perfect view of the encircling sea and mainland. The top was visible fro n both Muharrak and Manama and the hill was surrounded hv a ring of cliffs, facing inwards, at a dhtance of 3 or 4 miles; the land surround ing these sloped down more or less gradually to the sea on all sides. Formation was apparently not volcanic as rocks were limestone ,and sandstone. To the south and east the island was very bare, but almost due west of Jebel Dukhan palms began to line the coast and stretched thence all round the north shore To the north-east, nearer the coast, white dusty ground everywhere intruded and mighty mounds bare of vegetation towered above the palm-groves. The mounds stretched in endless chains all round the slope that falls from the cliffs to the sea, clinging rather to the higher ground but occurring also in separate clusters near the sea. The parent group of mounds wal at Ali but they were found also at Balad al Kadim, on the road to Rufaa and at Sirabe. From Manama west to Balad al Kadim were lines of date gardens Principal trees are date, vine, fig, pomegranate, almond, bair, peach tama rind, citron, apricot, mulberry. Castor oil plant flourishes and lucerne grass is largely cultivated. Camels are mostly from Arabia but a few are brtR in the marshes. Horses are carelessly bred and inferior, cows good but race dvina- out as no poor man or cultivator can keep them. White donkeys famed but few except with Sheikhs and rich men and those not so good as Persians Ordinary donkeys common. Wild animals are gazelle, hare and mongoose* Bent (1889) described the island as an almost dead-level of sandy desert relieved by palm-groves, with a good supply of water and occasional cultiva tion. The hills in the centre are limestones ; the rest of coral formation The Gulf Pilot (1898) describes Jebel Dukhan as a small square lump of dark hills and says the north end of the island has a belt, 2 or 3 miles wide, of very fertile land covered with date-groves. Zwemer (1900) states that the sliohtlv elevatpJ table-land in the centre of tbe island is mostly barren. ° J eu BALAD AL KADIM.—Ancient site dating from before Portuguese occupation. Principal feature is Madrasa Abu Zeidan mosque with 2 slender and elegant minarets, surrounded by ruins of houses and buildincr S j n of ruins is Ahu Zeidan spring with well-built baths. Thursday market is still held here. BARBOORA.—Village near north shore of Bahrein Island west of Portuguese Fort. ’S3 BARR (R A S * A L).—Southern extremity of Bahrein Island. B ASAITIN.—Small fishing village on Muharrak Island 2 miles north of Muharrak Eorfc. BICIIA.—Town mentioned by Ritter as belonging to the Bahrein (Volume 12, page 395). BIDIA.—Small village with tower at north-west corner of Bahrein Island. CHA ABAN.—A tribe accustomed to visit the Chief of Bahrein for presents but residing, perhaps, on the mainland. DAIR.—Ruined site on Muharrak Island believed by Arabs to be that of a church. Is this same as Dir below ? DEYAH.—Marked in Whish’s survey on north side of Muharrak Island. Is this same as Dir below ? DIBAL (FASHT-AD).—Shoal, 5 miles in length north and south by 2£ miles broad, about equidistant from Katar and Muharrak Island. DIR.—Small village with date clump, slightly to west of northernmost point of Muharrak Island. DUKHAN (JEBEL).—See Bahrain Island. DULAB.—Or Tholab. See Admiralty Plan No. 20, about miles south- south'east of Rufaa. GENAHAT.—Arab tribe at Bahrein. GRAHEE.—Village. See Bent’s Map, 1J miles south-south-east of Bidia. HADD.—Town at south-east extremity of Muharrak Island. Douglas states population at 20,000. Most of inhabitants are employed in pearl fishery. South-east from Hadd, about f mile off shore, is an islet on reef with fresh water spring called Bu Shahin. Admiralty Plan No. 20 shows a village and a group of huts (both unnamed) as situated on the reef about f mile and H miles respectively south of Hadd. IIALAT-AN-NAMUS.—Fishing village, on point of same name, 1 mile east of Manama. HANAINI.—Village on plain below fort, between the two Rufaas. Has well 20 fathoms deep containing best and “ lightest ” w^ater in Bahrein, which is brought to Manama on camels. HEMS.—Mentioned by Ritter (Volume 12, page 395) as a town belong ing to Bahrein. JASRA (RAS-AL).—At this point of Bahrein Island, 2 miles south-east of Manama, is village (what name ?) wuth detached date-grove and fresh water spring on beach below high-water level. JAU.—Extensive ruins of town, formerly residence of Sheikhs, on east side of Bahrein Island about 12 miles from south end of island. It was abandoned in 1800 for want of a sheltered port and inhabitants transferred to Muharrak. JEFF YR.—Place marked in Whish’s Survey near Ras al Jasra (see above). JELLAHAT-AL-BAHREIN (or AL-FERINGI.)—Portuguese Fort on Bahrein Island is so marked in Whish’s Survey. JEMI.—Small date clump with a few huts miles south of Kalali and just north of Hadd. KAISER.—Arab tribe at Bahrein. KALALI.—Fishing village, with square tower on sandy hillock, at north east corner of Muharrak Island, f mile north-east of it is islet of Arza. KALIYA (KHOR).—Inlet situated immediately south of Muharrak Island, between it and north-east end of Bahrein Island. The entrance, on the C912FD J34 south-east, is narrow with an average depth in midchannel of about 25 feet, hut ^either it nor the basin have been thoroughly examined. The depth of the basin, which is 4 miles long, 1 to 2 miles broad and perfectly sheltered from all winds, exceeds in many places 20 feet. The Khor communicates on the north-west with the open sea by a long, narrow and shallow channel which passes between the towns of Muharrak and Manama. KARBABAD.— Village close to eastward of Portuguese Port. KASHASH.—Rocky reef off Kalali village on which are 2 fresh water springs. KHALID (BENI).—Arab tribe at Bahrein. KHALIFA (AL).—Tribe to which ruling family at Bahrein belong. KHASEIFA.— Small rocky islet off Muharrak Island about 3| cables north of Dir; between it and shore are 3 fresh water springs, uncovered at low tide, from which village is supplied with water. KHATHA.—Town mentioned by Ritter (vol. 12, page 395) as belonging to Bahrein and being a place where good spears are made. KHOR FASHT.—Reef of coral about 6J miles north-west of Bahrein Island. On it is remarkable spring 3 feet below sea at low water from which Whish obtained 700 gallons of perfectly fresh water in a day in 1859. Pearl fishers use this spring in the season, but in the cold weather it is closed up by the natives. KIBLIYA (AL). —Name given by natives to Portuguese Fort. KOEFIH (UMM).—Place with wells 20 fathoms deep, from which drink ing water is brought to Manama. MAH AM A (AL KABIR).—Village on east coast of Bahrein Island, short distance south of south end of Sitra Island. (Whish spells the name Mahamir, and Admiralty Plan No. 20 gives Mahana). MAHAMA (AS SAGHIR).—Small fishing village at south end of Sitra Island. MAHANDE (AL).—Arab tribe at Bahrein. MAHTR (BIT).—Fresh water spring from which Muharrak town is chiefly supplied. It lies in sea £ mile east-south-east of fort and has always a fathom of salt water over it. Whish says the water is warm and is drawn off by a bamboo with hose attached. MANAMA.—Town. (1) At the north-east corner of Bahrein Island in lat- 26 u 14' N. and long. 50° 35' E. (2) At west end in 1862 was large square mass of white building forming residence of Governor of town. Palgrave found first aspect dingy* quarter next beach being three-fourths occupied by sailors* and fishermen’s cabins. He gives dimensions of town as 1|- miles in length (accord ing to Bent nearly 2 miles and to Gulf Pilot only f mile) along beach and $ mile deep inland; and level as 12 feet and less above sea. Cabins of palm-leaf formed majority of houses; they were of varying size and arranged mostly in streets and rows. There were some houses of brick and stone in Persian (Bent calls it Saracenic borrowed from Hasa) style with latticed windows and balconies, but ^ were falling into decay. At centre of town was market-place, a covered square with labyrinth of shop lanes, some vaulted, surrounding it. There were at least 20 coffee-houses in the town, mostly near the beach ; and several mosques (Bent calls them barnlike with low minarets) mostly Shiah, rest Sunni. Behind town was level plain of saltish soil, barren and often swampy. Gulf Pilot adds that landing is inconvenient except at high water, there being (1898) no piers or wharves; the shore reef being very shelving boats cannot get within mile of the beach at low water and donkeys are used to land passengers and unload goods. (3) The Sheikh’s house at the west end is a semi-fortified building. (4) Douglas gives population as 25,000, Gulf Pilot as 8,000 and Zwemer as 10,000. (5) Many Banyans. (6) Exports consist chiefly of pearls and dates, but also of hides, cotton sail-cloth, grain, mats, wool, cattle and a few fine horses and35 asses. Cotton sail-cloth of good quality for baghlas, fine date-leaf mats and coarse cloth for turbans and cloaks are manufactured. Most of trade of Bahrein is carried on here and post and customs offices are at Manama. Im ports are principally piece-goods, rice, cotton, coffee, timber and other materials for shipbuilding ; also, largely for re-exportation, cattle, fuel, grain, drugs, tobacco, sugar and oil. Most of trade is carried by steamers, but some of that with India by locally built boats. (7) Water is plentiful and of good quality. Bullocks, sheep, poultry, vegetables and fruit, Arab bread, rice, flour, etc., are procurable, also firewood but not sufficient for steaming purposes. (8) — (10) There is a European political officer at Manama. MAOSDLLIM (AL).—An Arab tribe of Bahrein. MAUZEED.—An Arab tribe of Bahrein. MOOTSALLEMA.—An Arab tribe of Bahrein. MUHARRAK.—Island. (1) Lies north-east of Bahrein Island from which it is separated by a strait about 1 mile broad and nearly all shallow. (2) It is 3 miles in breadth east and west and nearly 4 miles Ion' from north coast to extreme south-east point. It averages -J a mile in width and is shaped like horse shoe with the hollow curve towards the south, only entered by water at high tide. (3) It consists of a low strip of sand surrounded by broad coral reefs which more than double its area at low water. The islets of Say a, Khaseifa and Arza adjoin it. Three clumps of dates stand on the north side of the island within the space of 1 mile at Dir, Riya and Simahi. (4) Eor fresh-water springs on the reefs surrounding the island, see under Bahrein. (5) The town of Muharrak is on this island and the villages are Basaitin, Dir, Riya, Simahi Kalali, Jomi, Hadd, Musheir and Arad. (6) Independent of mainland. (7) By Sheikh of Bahrein who himself resides on the island. * ; MUIIARRAK.—Town. (1) Situated on south-west point of Muharrak Island. (2) Closely packed, with small snug houses, Perso-Arabian in appear ance. There are numerous spacious but low palaces belonging to A1 Khalifa family. (3) Square fort with four towers stands on low detached piece of ground off south end of town. (4) Douglas makes population 25,000 Persian Gulf Pilot 8,000. (5) (6) In commerce inferior to Manama and market-place smaller and less frequented. Inhabitants are chiefly employed in pearl fishery. (7) Water comes mostly from the submarine spring Bu Mahir, near the fort (8) (9) (10) Muharrak is residence of Chief and capital and seat of Govern ment of Bahrein group of islands. MUHAVIDEH (AL).—An Arab tribe at Bahrein. MUSHEIR Island, ^ a mile .—Small village at extreme south-east point of Muharrak south of Hadd and sometimes separated from it by the tide. NABBI SALE Small island abouta mile in diameter, covered witt date-trees, situated m a branch of Khor Kaliya which is enclosed between tin islands of Sitra and Bahrein. NAHSAN (UMM).—Large island, low, but with 2 small peaks on it of west coast of Bahrein island about 4 miles south-west of Bidia. ’ I mile west o NAYJM.—Pishing village on coast of Bahrein Island, Manama. OM (JSIIEIIR.—Village sliown in Whish’s Survey. Same as Musbeir ? . i p PORTUGUESE PORT.—Called by the natives A1 Kibliya, also Jellaha al orJellahatalBahrem, la situated about 3 miles west of Man,am: It is 150 yards from the beach and the highest part is 80 feet above sea-leve It covers neariy 2 acres of ground and is a regular bastioned fortification c brackish “It bottom 6 0eUtl ' e “ ^ ^ WeU - built Wel1 witU a ^1 extremi^of^hl^ak 0 !^^ 3 ° f ' ^ hUtS&gt; ^ ClUmp ° f dateS - of tlm rt Name + . 0f ‘a 0 Tl 1 ' 3 ^ 9 about a mi '6 apart, situated on the bro, the cliffs at the north end of the depression in which Jebel Dukhan standi£6 These villages are the sanitarium of Bahrein. The more westerly stands on a c liff about 50 feet above desert arid is called liufaa Jibliya, the other Rufaa Sherga. Between them, in the depression, is the village of Hanaini with the best well of water in the island. The Rufaas are probably older than Muharrak or Manama; they are fortified villages with castellated walls of mud bricks and several towers. Many of the Al Khalifa reside m both (P) in comfortable houses, Manama lies about 7 miles to the north. SALATA.—An Arab tribe at Bahrein. SALMAN (AL).—Branch of the Al Khalifa family to which Sheikh Isa bin Ali belongs. SARABI—Village on coast 2^ miles west of Portuguese Port. SAYA.—Small islet on shore reef of Muharrak Island, ^ of a mile from the beach, west of Basaitin. It lias a basin on top filled by a fresh-water spring but liable to be tainted by the sea getting in. Island is 20 yards across and only just above high-water level. SELBA.—Small village at south end of Bahrein Island. SENNABIS.—Coast village between Manama and Portuguese Port. SIIAHIN (BU).*—Islet on the shore reef, south-east by east from Hadd village and f of a mile off shore. Has a fresh-water spring. SHAKOR.—District in Bahrein where there are date plantations. SHEREIBA —Coast village between Portuguese Port and Bidia, see Admiralty plan No. 20. Is this same as Sarabi above ? SIMABI.—Place on Muharrak Island mentioned by Durand as site of an ancient well. Is this misprint for Simahi below ? SIMAHI.—Village consisting of few huts and clump of date trees near north extremity of Mnharrak Island. SIRABE.—Village mentioned by Durand as on north coast of Bahrein Island. Can Sarabi be meant ? S1TRA.—Island off the east side of Bahrein Island, 4 miles long and H miles broad with narrow, shallow Khor between its south-east side and Bahrein Island. Northern half is covered with high date trees. In the grove are village and fort of Sitra and at south end is village of Mahama. Admiralty Plan No. 20 marks another village at north-east corner of island, bnt gives no name. SITRA.—Village with fort on Sitra Island. No particulars. SDL AIM (AL).—An Arab tribe of Bahrein. SULEISIL.—The present Bahrein anchorage or outer harbour for large vessels, about 4 miles north-west of Manama. SUM AIT (AL).—An Arab tribe at Bahrein. UTTOOBEES.—Arab tribe who conquered Bahrein and now form a large portion of the genuine Arab inhabitants. WILAYAT-EL-KADIM.—Given by Durand as an alternative name of Balad al Kadim. YARIM (PASHT-AL).—Extensive pear-shaped reef which protects Bahrein harbour from Shemal; it is 13 miles long north and south and, at north end, 8 miles broad. ZALAK.—Village with fort on west coast of Bahrein Island about 10 miles south of Bidia. Zwemer says there are ruins in neighbourhood and deep wells cut through solid rock. ZARA.— -Mentioned by Ritter (volume 12, page 395) as a town belonging to Bahrein. ZxAUYED (AL),^—Or Zayed. An Arab tribe at Bahrein. ZUNJ.—A district of Bahrein where dates grow.I I f 138 AAKIR.—Village, mentioned by Ritter with places in Katif as inhabited by the Abd-el-Kais. AATHAL.—Given by Ritter as name of a mountain between Central Arabia and Bahrein. ADAN (BARR AL).—Name of the country between Katif and Koweit. This is the Katif use of the word : according to Belly, Koweit people only apply the term to tract between Koweit and creek of Karain, one day south of Koweit. It is inhabited by several Bedouin tribes, principal being the Ejman. Eorl20 miles south of Mishaab there are no fixed inhabitants or villages. The shore is a low sandy or stony desert with a few isolated hills at intervals ; it is fronted for nearly the whole distance by extensive reefs which in places have passages inside them. Several low islets lie off the coast. The water is not generally so clear as it is further south, owing to the bottom being of white clay in many parts. The great Pearl Bank decreases in breadth off this coast and may be said to end about Abu Ali island, although pearls are fished for on a small scale on some banks north of that island. AKARIYAT.—Place where Turkish governor elect of Hasa embarked for Ojairin 1879. ALAWAMIA.—Village in Katif. ALGHA.—Police or military post, apparently between Hasa and Ojair. ALI (JEZIRAT ABU).—Island, 12 miles long east and west, about 60 miles north-north-west of Katif, separated from the mainland by a narrow shoal passage. Eastern point, which is low and rocky, is called Ras Abu Ali, and in bay south of point is good anchorage in Shamal. Arabs say there are date- trees with springs of fresh water in one or two places on south-west side of bay. AMAYIR.—Arab tribe in Katif district. According to Bombay Selections XXIV they are dependent upon the Beni Khalid, and lead a pastoral life, except from spring to summer when they fish for pearls on the banks of the island of Jarim (?). r lhey consisted at one time of 800 families of Bedouins and 100 families of fishermen, the latter settled at Jannaand allied with the Duwad and Sooedan, ANICH.—Port, town and police-post on Katif coast, half-way between Saihat and Katif town. ANTAH.—Village marked in Belly’s map about 40 miles west-north-west of Katif tovm. It is a stage on route via Taj from Hasa to Koweit. ARABI (JAZIRAT).—Small sand bank with rocky base, about 13 miles south from Jazirat Earsi. It is visited by fishermen to catch turtle ; swarms with cormorants, and is covered in the season with nests and youn 0 * ones. There is a deposit of guano, a few inches thick, all over it. ARAM A.—Place marked in Kiepert’s map, about 20 miles inland between Ras lanajib and Ras Mishaab, on route from Katif to Koweit. ARG.—Place marked in Belly’s map about 110 miles north-west of Katif town and. 10 miles from the coast. It is a stage on land route between Hasa and Koweit. of 2,400, mentioned by AWAM EE AH.‘—Walled town with a population Sadlier as under the government of Katif. •rr AZmAH.-Viflage, half deserted in 1862, about 30 miles south-west ol Katif town on road to Hoflmf. BAB-ASH-SOAMAL.—Village in Katif district. BA II It AN. Sadiier and other travellers give this name to the mainland opposite Bahrein. UI 1 ( DU H A 'lj.—Bay and anchorage on coast about 20 miles north, west of Musalannya. From April to June a kind of fair is held here, at which Bedoums from considerable dxstances barter their ghee for dates, rice and other necessaries brought by boat from Katif. b39 BEDRANEE (MAA-UL).—Wells with abundant supply of water near Yaroodeeah village. BEHAIE.—Section of A1 Morrah tribe who in 19:0 committed a niurder- ous attack on Bahrein subjects at Derya 40 miles south of Katif. Tribe is strong and possesses large number of camels; they are nomads without fixed place of residence. In winter and spring they camp on southern confines of Hasa and for about 3 months in summer they move to wells about b miles inland from Duhat Salwa. BEHARI.—Name of a village on mainland of Katif. BELAALAT.—Place between Hasa and Ojair where there was once a fort. BELEE.—Arab clan 3 according to Palgrave, between Katar and Basrah. BISERTIN.—Place about 11 miles from Ojair on route to Hofhuf. Sweet water can be obtained by digging and there is some grazing about. BORGUD —Town of Hasa according to Blau apud Miles. CHATAR.—Place with 3 small wells, situated on edge of large depression fairly clear of sand and covered with saltpetre. Water brackish; no grazing or fuel. Situated 28 miles from Ojair on route to Hofhuf. CHAWAICHIB.—Village on mainland of Katif. CHES-IL-BARI and CHES-IL-TOBE.—Mentioned by Sadlier as open villages under the government of Katif. DAM (JEBEL-ED).—Hill mentioned by Sadlier between Haffeerah and Hoodia. Can this be same as Palgrave’s Aloghor ? DAMMAM.—Important town on Katif coast, occupied by Turks, about 9 miles south-east of Katif town. Principal fort lies on an island, on the shore reef, nearly joined to the mainland. Rest of the town and a smaller fort stand on mainland near it. Channels through the reef, by which native vessels ap proach the town, are shallow and probably practicable only at high water. Shot for the Turkish artillery is said to be kept here. DARIN.—Town with square fort at south point of island of Tarut. DEBATTAH.—Place marked in Pelly’s map in Hasa north of Hofhuf. It is a stage on route from Hasa to Koweit. DEBA1BIA.—Walled village in Katif district. DEBEBI.—Described by Sadlier as an open village with population of 1,200. Is this same as last ? DERYA.—Place in Turkish territory, 30 or 40 miles south of Katif, where cousin of Sheikh of Bahrein was murdered in 1900. DHARAN.—- Place or district about 20 miles south of Katif. DOMEEZEE.—Place with well of good water about 10^ hours east- south-east of Haffeerah. DUTA.—In 1865 a large and flourishing town, recently sprung up in the neighbourhood of Taj. This township was described as being in the centre of a fertile and well-watered region and its inhabitants as being agricultural and addicted to commerce. DTJWAD.—Arab clan formerly allied with the Amayir of Janna. EIN DAR.—Wells where Bedouins camp a few miles west-north-west of Lomeezee. EJMAN,—Tribe extending north from Ras al Ghar by whom Beni Khalid of that part have been absorbed. They are the principal tribe of the Barr- al-Adan. Are these the same as the Ejman of sub-section B ? EARSf (JAZIRAT).—Islet, in lat. 27° 59^' north and long. 50° 10' east, 56 miles from nearest part of Persian coast, and 53 miles from Arab coast just south of Ras-al-Ghar. It is ^ of a mile across, only a few feet above sea level, overgrown with coarse grass and brushwood and frequented by fishermen, chiefly from Kharag, who catch turtle (which abound on the island) for oil and shell. EELASSUR (BU).—Tribe who inhabit Sennabis.PENIA.—Village in Katif district, apparently on Tarut Island and un called. FEZ ARAH.—Arab clan forming, according to Pal grave, part of the popu lation of Hasa, FOOZOOL —Village in Hasa plain about H ho ^ rs fr0m Jislia 011 roacl to Hofhuf. Houses are of stone and clay and have flat mud roots. HA RAH (JEBEL).—Hill, 4 or 5 miles east of Hofhuf, destitute of ve- eetation of no great height and famous for natural caves to which natives of Hasa resort in hot weather. Pelly calls it Gherra and it appears to be the same as Moghor of Palgrave. (See under Mogharat). GHAPR.—Given by Ritter as name of port in Hasa. GHAR Small village in range between Wadi Faruk and Hasa where one route from Nejd to Hofhuf traverses it, apparently about 10 miles west- south-west of Hofhuf. GHOREYMAH.—Mentioned by Ross as a town or village of Hasa. GHOWEYR— Pass leading down from hills west of Hofhuf, about 15 miles to the south of west from that town. There is apparently village of same name at foot of pass on Llasa side. GOFHICH.—Place between Ojair and Hasa where a Turkish detachment was massacred in 1902. HAFFEERAH.—Place with good supply of water in well, 50 or 60 miles north-west of Hofhuf. HA JAR. —This appears to be an ancient name of Hasa and its chief town. Ritter mentions a town (?) Khatt Hajar. HAJIR (BENI).—Large tribe occupying district for about 20 miles each side of Katif town. They wander as far as Odaid, sometimes commit small piracies and bear a bad reputation. Palgrave regards them as among original Arab settlers of Hasa and says they are a Kahtanic tribe. He calls them one of the most spirited and courteous of the Bedouin tribes, better armed and clad and more civilised than the others owing to intercourse with towns of Hasa. HAMAHH.— Place marked in Pelly’s map, near coast about 80 miles north-west of Katif town. It is a stage on the route from Hasa to Koweit tia Taj. jjABB. Mentioned by Zwemer as one of principal tribes of Hasa. HASA.-— Turkish administrative division of the Basra province, also mis leadingly styled Nejd. (1) Its boundaries are those of its component districts which follow. (2) It consists of the districts (Kaimmakamliks) of Hasa Proper, Katif and Katar. The British Government does not recognise the last named as a Turkish possession, hut the Turks maintain in it, at Bidaa, one battalion of regular infantry, 20 mounted Dhabitias and civil officials. (3) The physical genoraphy of the division will be found in the articles on the districts com- posfng it. (4) The climate is not favourable to health or physical activity. It is warm and house fires are out of the question even in the middle of winter, while cloaks are only worn in the cold season. It would be possible to sleep out of doors all the year round. Intermittent fevers and their sequelae are common, especially in the low marshy ground about Katif. (5) Ports are Katif and Ojair, especially latter which is nearer to populous part of division. The roads outside the oasis of Hasa Proper are mere tracks across the sand from well to well. After high wind they are obliterated, neces sitating the employment of Bedouin guides. The principal tracks are (a) from Ojair to Hofhuf, about 40 miles, from coast across sand to edge of Hasa oasis ; water sufficient hut fuel scarce, (b) from Katif town to Hofhuf, about 100 miles, usually considered 3 days’ journey. Water and fuel are said to be plentiful but road is (Douglas, 1890) insecure. Portion of it lies over country which might be, but is not cultivated. Cassim Izeddin says the distance is 36 marching hours but he took 5 days to it. The route was desert, infested41 by nomnds and water very bad except at one stage, (c) Ilofhuf to Katar, about 1*20 miles, entirely across desert but water is procurable. Journey occupies 3 or days. By this route communication is maintained between Hofhuf and Bidaa garrison, {d) Route (Palgrave says there is only one) from Hasa to Nejd across Jebel Toweik. It is all over desert and water is scarce. Journey for caravans occupies about 10 days. More detailed information will be found in Bombay Records, Selection XXIV, pages 111-115 and in Appendix to Douglas’ “ Journey from India to the Mediterranean.” (6) Trade is dealt with in the articles on component districts. (7) (a) Sadlier, 1319, estimated population of plain at 75,000. According to Ross, population declined from 85,000 in 1820 to only 20,000 in 1865 ; but Cassim Izeddin (1897) estimated it at no loss than 500,000, residing in 2 towns (Mubarraz and Hofhuf) and 36 villages. (This last estimate is the more excessive if it was intended to apply, as seems probable, to the district of Hasa Proper and not to the division of Hasa). According to Turkish official report, quoted by Zwemer, total population of province is 250,000. (5) According to Palgrave (1865) the original settlers in Hasa were the Kahtanic Arab tribes of Beni Khalid and Beni Hajir, followed by the Eezarah, the clans of Kelb, Belee, Tenookh and various branches of the Kodaa. Douglas simply mentions agriculturists and Bedouins, of whom the former are a majority in Hasa proper. Among the Bedouins he mentions the Ejman, Beni Hajir, Manasir, Al Morrah and Mutahir. Niebuhr described the whole district as belonging, in his day, to the Beni Khalid who appear since that time to have declined in power. The Persian Gulf Pilot speaks of the Beni Hajir as occupying the country round Katif and of “ the remnant of the once powerful tribe ” of the Beni Khalid as now being incorporated, between Ras al Gliar and Koweit, with the Al Ejman; also of the Al Morra and Mukhatiba as two other tribes in the neighbourhood of Katif. Isiebuhr mentioned also families of Turkish descent as owning con siderable land but taking no share in the government, which was at that epoch Arab, (c) The inhabitants (of the villages ?) are good sized and well propor tioned ; they are sallow and less muscular than the Nejdeans, but as much superior to them in intelligence as they are inferior in military qualities and physical force. They wear gold and silk without scruple and smoke tobacco, while the turhan, Oman vest and light red cloak of the east coast frequently replace the kefiya and Arab smock. They are fond of literature and poetry and indulge in pleasure parties, song and dissipation. Their features are regular but not so marked as those of Nejdeans. The Bedouins are averse to all forms of settled government and unlikely ever to fight for the Turks but would probably be willing to attack an invader for sake of plunder, {d) Niebuhr says most of the inhabitants of the towns, especially near the coast, are Shiahs ; while the Bedouins and villagers of the interior are Sunnis. According to him there are many Sabaean Christians and a few Jews, (e) (f) (y). The Arabic of Hasa is less copious, pure and flexible than that of Nejd. (£) (i) Douglas estimates the fighting strength of the Bedouin tribes at 4,600 men. (/) Nation al arm of the Bedouins is the lance, but about 15 per cent, have breech-loading rifles, mostly Martinis, and some of the remainder muzzle-loaders of different kinds. (8) The Mutasarrif is appointed from Constantinople but is under Waif of Basra. In the districts of Hasa and Katif, and, perhaps, though to a lesser extent in the southern part of the Katar peninsula, Turkish authority is firmly established. The poor agriculturists are easily kept under control by military force, and fear of the Turk is very real; but both agriculturists and merchants are disaffected and favourable to extension of British influence. Regular garrison in 1896 consisted of troops of 6th Army Corps relieved periodi cally from Baghdad, viz., 2 squadrons cavalry, 1 battery of light guns drawn by mules and four battalions of infantry. One battalion infantry was at Bidaa, all other regulars at Hofhuf. Local Commandant had rank of Lieutenant-Colo nel. There were also a special corps of 50 Bedouins, mounted on camels and armed with Sniders to act as guides, etc., and six buluks or companies of Dhabitias of which four were mounted. The Dhabitias are specially raised for local service and are an armed police, occupying small posts in the populous parts and furnishing escorts for travellers and caravans. Of the four mounted buluks, three were Arabs and Kurds mixed, and the C912ED L■ ■ Km ' v I • j42 other entirely Kurdish, commanded by a Kurd chief who drew all the pay and found 100 men and horses. Pay of Dhabitia infantry was Rs. 15 a month and of cavalry Rs. 30, Government supplying only Snider rifle and uni form. There were 60 mounted and 30 foot Dhabitias at Katif, 20 mounted in Katar and £0 foot at Ojair; rest were at head-quarters (Douglas). Accord ing to Zwemer (1900) there are only 600 troops at Hofhuf and 390 in Katar and Katif. The divisions according to this authority are the “ cazas &gt;f of Nejd, Katar and Katif and the three together compose the “ sandjak ” of Hasa : the Mutasarrif resides at Hofhuf, and Katar and Katif have separate kaimmakams. There are the usual Turkish tribunals and each Arab tribe has its represen tative with the Governor. Turkish report mentions three schools and 3,540 pupils. HASA (PROPER).—Eertile oasis or strip of country about 40 miles inland from the coast, forming one of the 3 districts of the Turkish administrative divi sion of Hasa. (1) Roundary on west is a long white range of craggy hills w hich separates it from sandy wastes of the Dahna. On the east is a similar range of no great height which, w ith sandy desert, divides it from coast and district of Katif. On north hills dwindle away and are succeeded by barren tract of firm soil which forms north extremity of district. Southwards also the hills disap pear, Arabian desert approaches sea and boundary in this direction may be locat ed about 20 miles south of Hofhuf. (2) It is divided into the Mudirliks of Ojair, Jafar, Hofhuf and Mubarraz. (3) District consists of plain, perhaps not much more than 100 feet above sea level ; cultivated portion is about 15 miles long by 12 broad with some 30 fixed villages, all surrounded by high walls in bad repair. Country is level except for some sandhills and limestone ridges which are scattered about it; latter are low and fantastically cavernous. Pelly makes the oasis 20 to 30 miles long and 12 broad. General aspect of land is sandy and soil is light, often intermixed with pow dered limestone and mica. A line from Ojair to Hofhuf runs for first 28 miles over loose undulating sand; then for four miles across a non-sandy nitrous depression; then for about six miles over firm ground w ith shifting sandhills on surface, then for tw o miles over open stony plain to Jisha village: thence for nine miles through well watered and fertile country. Palgrave between Kulabia and Hedeeyah first traversed a plain of light and sandy soil w ith occasional ridges of basalt and sandstone and with indications of water at no great depth; dwarf- palms, shrubs, even reeds and rushes occurred at short intervals and there were occasional pools in hollow's. In a shallow valley were palms, high brushwood and gigantic aloes and near Hedeevah a sandy eminence. The rocks of Hasa are frequently igneous, tufa and basalt, and slight earthquakes are not uncommon. There is a solitary hill north-east of Hofhuf. All springs and wells are more or less hot and some have a sulphurous taste. The villages and townships are hidden in date groves and gardens. Water courses and run- mi ^T tr ? ams abouud and there ar e marshes and stagnant lakes. Between Hofhuf and Muharraz nearly the whole space is filled with gardens, plantations and rus ling streams of tepid water ; the road is a raised causeway with deep irrigation on both sides. Barren salt patches and ponds occur arbitrarily here ?&gt; ii ill* Vt ?° r climate and routes see Hasa, above. (6) Described by as . e nc ^ es ^ and mos t commercial, and, with Katif, the most widelv cultivated portion of the Wahabi dominions. The dates of Hasa are of hi°h value especially the Males variety. Wheat and rice are grown in small quantities and there is abundance of grass and very good lucerne for fodder* ut for gram the district is largely dependent on importation. According to Palgrave the date predominates but nabak and papai grow; indigo is cultivated but not m sufficient quantities to meet the local demlnd ; W?’ rlC . e ’/ Uga /- C t ne A maiZe ’ millet * vetches &gt; radishes, onions, garlic and bee ns are produced; but he never saw or heard of barley. Sadlier says wheat barley and rice are cultivated and that the tamarisk grows very tall and fLTJ G U / y t0 1 0btai11 roofi ^ mat ™al. He condemns^all the fruits and vegetables, describing the apricots and melons as bad, the and not e of nnin ^ ^ • 0ni ° nS aS havin S the sha Pe of carrots donkevs arp 1 C m fair numbers i white Persian and common nkejs aie plentiful ; and sheep, camels and horses are easily obtainable43 from the Bedouins. Horses vary from the pure-bred Arab, at an enormously hi°-h price, to the common kadish or baggage horse. Large numbers of good serviceable animals, showing some breeding and able to carry a rider 100 miles in 8 days, can be bought for 20 to 40 liras. Bedouins own many very good riding camels and a well-bred camel costs 20 liras on average but often much more : they are only inferior to those of Oman. There are a few buffaloes on the marshy lands about Hofhuf. Sheep are fewer and meat dearer than in Nejd. Fine cloaks (abbas) are made of silk and wool mixed, embroidered with gold and silver thread. There are workers in copper and brass and the coffee-pots made here are good, (b) (c) Rice is imported from India through Bahrein, and wheat from Persia, partly direct and partly through Bahrein. Cloth, cutlery, ironwork, swords, spears, crockery, silk, gold thread and silver thread are (or used to be) imported, (d) The principal exports are dates, pearls (?) and abbas. Some thousands of camels were exported to Syria annually in Niebuhr’s day and valuable donkeys were sent abroad, (e) (f) Coins are tawila or long-bit; Indian, Maskat, Zanaibar, German and British East African pice; rial or 3 Maria Theresa dollar, always dated 1780; and the Lira or Turkish pound. Values are: Rs. A. P. 1 tawila = i anna. 1 rial = 60 tawdlas V.7 ... 1 14 0 1 lira = 8 rials ... ... ••• 15 0 0 (g) (M* (7) As to population, see article on Hasa, above. (8) In Niebuhr’s day justice was well administered under an Arab regime. Revenue in 1865 was $270,000. The present Turkish Kaimmakamlik of Hasa Proper is divided into the Mudirliks of Ojair, Jafar, Hofhuf and Mubarraz. HASEN.—Place in Beni Hajir country. HASS AM (BENI).—Mentioned by Zwemer as one of principal Arab tribes in Hasa. HE DEE YAH.—Village placed by Palgrave about 50 miles north of Hofhuf. Sadlier describes it as a walled village with cultivation and flocks of sheep. HERKUZ.—Mere sandbank, about 1 cable in length, hardly above the level of high water. Lies 26 miles w r est from Jazirat Farsi. HEWEVERAT (or HOWERAT ?).—Mentioned by Sadlier as walled village, surrounded by large date plantation and well supplied with water from a hot spring and a large lake. Lies about 5 miles north-north-west of Hofhuf (?). Adjoining desert is barren and dreary. HILLAT MEHAISH.—Walled village on mainland in Katif district south of Jarudia and north of Khewaildia. Appears to be identical with the Hilutumhesh of Sadleir, which in his day was unwalled and had population of 1 , 200 . HOFHIJF.—Chief town and administrative capital of Hasa, situated in Hasa proper. Pelly gives latitude as 25° 20' 56' North and longitude as ^9° 40' 50' East. Douglas says it is about 50 miles south-south-west of Ojair. It is reckoned 6 days distant from Riadh and 5 from Bidaa by caravan. (2) Town is an elongated oval, mile broad and 1 to miles long. It is surrounded by date groves and gardens. Palgrave (1862) shows gardens and fields on every side; Jopp (1841) describes the ground to the south and east as clear and on the north as clear to a distance of £00 or 400 yards, hut says the date groves adjoined the wall on the west side. The houses are of stone and clay with flat roofs. There is a regular Municipality. Streets according to some authorities are narrow and dirty ; others say they are wide and clean for an eastern town. Palgrave divides the town into 3 wards: (i) the Kot or fort in north-west corner; (u) the Rifeeyeeyah or “high ” quarter in w T hich a large proportion of the older and nobler families reside; it forms the eastern of half of the town and Palgrave describes it as containing tolerable and44 even handsome houses, white-plastered and ornamented, with arches ; he says the situation is high and the quarter the healthiest in Hofhuf, getting some sea-breeze ; (Hi) Naathar, the largest quarter, on the south and west forming a good half of town and containing all classes of inhabitants ; in it are the principal mosque a few gardens and occasional trees, chiefly fig and citron. Town has 7 gates; and public square, 300 yards long by 75 broad, is at meeting point of all 3 quarters. (Palgrave , s book contains sketch plan of Hofhuf). (3) Town is surrounded by a high wall in had repair environed by ditch which can oe flooded. Fort has been described by Sadlier (1819), Jopp (1841). Pal grave (1862) and DouHas (1896) and the accounts vary somewhat in details. It appears to be a large square construction of small stones in mud, with sides from J to ^ of a mile long. In 1841, walls were 20 to 25 feet high and 7 to 8 feet thick, with towers 40 to 50 feet high at intervals of 40 to 50 yards ; there was a dry ditch 15 to 20 feet deep and the same wide outside the wall, and on a level space between the two, round the whole circuit of the town, was a breast-work of stone and mud commanding the ditch. There was an entrance on the north and anothei on the east. On the south and east there were houses outside close to the walls, but on the other sides the ground was clear. On the east side of the north entrance was a keep with high walls and towers at intervals. ~W ithin the fort were numerous houses and a mosque of which the dome was the most conspicuous object in the town. In 1862 there were 4 gates and the population of the fort was 2,000 to 3,000. There were then 15 or 16 towers to each side of the fort, most of them round, with winding stairs, loopholes and machicoulis. The keep was small but strong with towers 40 feet high. In 1896 the Turkish barracks and residences of all Turkish officials were inside the fort. Palgrave noted a detached fort called Khoteym at a short distance south of the town ; a fort on a conical hill between it and the town; and another fort on a hill to the north of the town. (4) The population was estimated at less than 15,000 in 1819 ; at 23,000 or 24,000 in 1862 ; and at 15,000 in 1897. (5) No information as to races or occupations. Half population are Sunnis ; remainder Shiahs and Wahabis. (6) In 1841 there was a Thursday market to which villa gers brought their goods for sale. In 1862 the chief seat of trade was at the Keysareeyah, a long barrel-vaulted arcade in the Pifeyeevah quarter. Here weapons, cloth, embroidery, gold and silver ornaments were sold. Around it were alleys devoted to sale of foreign merchandise and local manufactured articles. Dates, vegetables, wood, salted locusts and small ware were sold in booths in the open square. In 1897 there was much intercourse with Nejd and one caravan a week came in from Riadh bringing butter (ghi ?) and taking back rice, sugar and cloth. The average number of pilgrims starting annually from Hofhuf for Mecca was 400. In 1900 Hofhuf was still celebrated for the manufacture of elegant abbas richly embroidered with gold and coloured thread and of brass coffee-pots of curious shape, these being exported as far as Basra and Oman (7)—(10). HOWAEtEIN.—According to Ritter, a town of the Abd-el-Kais, apparent ly in Hasa. HUMEED (AL).—Tribe, apparently in Hasa; see Bombay selection XXIV, page 449. HUSAIN (JILAT-AL).-—Small fort on Katif coast, about 6 miles north of the Zabanat hillocks and 20 miles south-east of Katif town, inhabited by a few fishermen. JAAFE11.-—Mentioned by Zwemer as one of principal tribes in Qasa which have submitted to Turkish domination. JAFAR.—Large walled village, a little over 1 mile from Jisha, on left side of road to Hofhuf and rather under 8 miles from Hofhuf. According to Douglas, it is apparently the head quarters of one of the 4 mudirliks of Hasa. Is this same as Jifr, mentioned by Zwemer as one of villages on skirts of Hasa oasis, apparently on route from Ojair to Hofhuf ? Is it identical with Jufoor mentioned by Jopp as on left of route from Jisha to Hofhuf ? JARUDIA.—Village on Katif mainland, north of Hillat Mehaish and south of Debaibia,45 JANNA.--Island under Sheikh of Katif, i a m, e off shore about 12 miles north-west of Jezirat Abu Ali and 6 miles south-east of Musa aauya Lensth east and west is about If miles ; there is fresh water m wells and a small fort and village on north side inhabited by about 200 fishermen of Amayir (?) tribe. JARIM.—Island off the coast of Barr-al-Adan where Amayir tribe fish for pearls ; see Bombay selection XXIV, page 81. What island is meant ? JENAIB (UMM).—Name of considerable district forming central portion of country between Katif and Koweit. JINN A.—Small sandy islet about 10 feet high, half a mile long and very narrow, ten miles east by north of Has Abu Ali. JIRAIDA.—Small sandy islet about 12 feet high and J of a mile in extent, lies 10 or 11 miles off the coast midway between Katif town and Musalamiya. jISPI. Village on Katif mainland north of Saibat and south of Kbewail- dia. This appears to be the walled town with a population of 560 called by Sadlier, Jisba. JISHA—Village in Hasa oasis mentioned by Jopp and Douglas on their routes from Ojair to Hofhuf. It seems to stand on southern or south eastern edge of oasis on right of Ojair-Hofhuf road, 9 miles short of Hof hut. In 1841 it was encompassed by a wall of about 250 yards square, 7 or 8 feet high, with small towers at intervals. Good water, grass, fuel and supplies are obtainable. In map of parts of Arabia and Persia a place Jesba is shown about 10 miles north of Hoilmf : is this a mistake ? JOWDEH.—Place marked in Pelly’s map, apparently in Hasa oasis. It is a stage on route from Hasa to Koweit. J UNI AH.—Village in Hasa proper. In Palgrave’s map it (? Djoon) is placed 25 miles north-north-west of Hofhuf, and he says highest part of Jebel Moghazi range is opposite it. According to Sadlier it (? Jumeah) is a village with an abundant supply of water and date-gardens, and near it is an ex tensive lake which fertilizes the plain in its vicinity. Some cotton is grown. KAIS (ABD-EL).—Mentioned by Hitter as a predominant tribe of Hasa or neighbourhood. RAEATYIN (JEZIHAT-AL).—Small sandy islet, hardly above high water level, 4 miles south of Jezirat-al-Kran. KATA.—Place in Katif, attacked by Bedouins in 1888. KATIF.—Tract, according to Niebuhr once called Shatt; it is now one of the 3 districts which compose the Turkish administrative division of Hasa, (1) Bounded by sea on east; by district of Hasa on south and west, being separ ated from it by range of low hills called Mogharat; and on north by desert (?). (2) No information as to Mudirliks or other subdivisions. (3) Consists of sandy plain, saturated with spring water, only a few feet above sea level. Inhabited portion lies along sea and is 14 miles long by 3 deep. Atmosphere thick and oppressive, heat intense, vegetation ranker and more luxuriant than in Hasa. Hills dividing Katif from Hasa have steep sandstone cliff on side towards Katif. (I) Climate is damp and unhealthy ; malarial fever is celebrated and its results are rampant ; inhabitants weak in frame and sallow in complexion. (5) Communications, so far as described, will be found in article on Hasa division. (Q) (a) According to Sadlier, mutton, rice, dates, musk and water melons are produced, some of latter being of extraordinary size, 35 to 40 lbs. Wheat and barley are not so abundant as riee ; unbealthiness of Katif is attri buted to cultivation of latter. Eigs are abundant and tolerably good- Some apricots and a few mangoes, pomegranates, grapes, citrons, and limes are culti vated. Brinjols, onions and beans are seen in the gardens. There is much irri gation from wells and springs. Palgrave says the date groves extend in a broad C912FD M46 belt along coast and their prodace exceeds in quantity if it does not equal in quality those of Hasa. The palms grow largely in brackish water but are » ot in P r - iouslv affected. The date groves are interspersed with marshes. (6) {h) No information. (7) (a) Palg. ave calls the district populous. Sadher enumerated 9 separate walled towns with population of 19,360 and 7 unwalled villages with population of 5,840, total 25,200. Cassim Izedin says the Caza of Katif (is this coextensive with Katif district ?) contains 16 villages and 20 000 inhabi tants. Gaskin reckons only 19 towns or villages on mainland, with walls, and 4 unwalled on island of Tarut; he makes total population 40,000. (6) Among tribes are Beni Khalid, Amayir, Ejman, Beni Hapr Al Morrah and Mukhatiba. According to one authority the country between Katit and Oiair is held by Uttoobees. Palgrave describes the village population as predo minantly Arab though with a strong Persian strain ; the town people are a mar- grel breed, largely Persian, (d) According to Cassim Izeddin all the inhabi tants of the “ Caza of Katif ” are Shiahs, (e) Rice and fish are the principal foods, (f) (k) (i) Gaskin estimates the fighting strength at 4,000 men. (/) Most of these are armed with breech-loading rifles (8) Governor is a Kaim- makam subject to Mutasarrif of Hasa. Superior officials are Turks but subor dinate officials and Kazi are Arabs, and the Arabs are left to themselves so long as the revenue is paid. Turks have a force of about 60 foot and 40 mounted men distributed through the district. They have no field artillery, but there are 2 brass and a number of iron muzzle-loading guns for which shot are said to be kept at Katif town and Dammam. Pilgrims to Mecca travel m'^Hasa. There is a broken-down masonry aqueduct about 5 miles long in the district, the work of rulers prior to the Wahabis. Sadlier (1819) estimated the revenue at 20,000 German crowns from the Jahand or war-tax (payable by villagers and townsmen as not being liable to be summoned to arms); 50,000 to 60,000 from tithes of agricultural produce collected in kind ; 5,000 to 6,000 from sea customs and lesser amounts from fishery and anchorage dues besides a small revenue from pearl fisheries. KATIF.—Town. (1) Situated on the coast about 37 miles north-west of Bahrein Island and 70 miles from Ojair. (2) In 1839 dense date groves sur rounded the town on all sides except to seaward. In 1862 it was environed by a network of rivers and buried in an interminable succession of gardens. Town itself was gloomy, crowded, damp and dirty. The west gate had a high stone arch of elegant form, flanked by a wall and towers, but all ruinous and dismant led. In 1896 half the population resided in the fort and the remainder in the straggling town on south side of it. The “ Sarai” or government offices and the public buildings were located in the fort, but the bazaar and residences of most of the richer inhabitants were outside. Only the part of the fort next the sea was occupied ; the walls and houses in the remainder were dilapidated. According to Gulf Pilot, 1898, the town is scattered through the date groves that surround the fort. Most of the houses are of stone and some of them are good. The streets are narrow and dirty, and water, though plentiful, is of bad quality. Gaskin (1902) says the proper name of Katif town is Kelat, and differs from Douglas in placing the fort to the west instead of the north of the town : except for the space adjoining the fort the town is surrounded by date gardens. Harbour is unsatisfactory and landing inconvenient. Boats of more than 6 feet draught cannot reach an inner berth. The largest boats enter by a channel opposite Saihat which takes them as far as Burj Abdul Lif. There is a passage round northern side of Tarut Island, only navigable at high water, which joins the other from Burj Abul Lif opposite Katif town. Native boats even can only enter and leave conveniently at high water. Cas sim Izeddin regards the anchorage between RasTanuraand Tarut Island as the harbour of Katif and says it is the berth for all Turkish Government vessels. (3) Main defence is the old (Wahabi ?) Fort which has a citadel of (Por tuguese ?) construction at its north end. Sadlier (1819) described it as irregular oblong with main face to the sea; it had three gates and citadel was supplied by a good spring of water. Douglas (1896) gives it a high bastioned wall and a frontage of 400 yards, wuth a gateway facing the sea, and a depth of 300 yards. In south part of fort is minaret 80 to 100 feet high. According to Gas kin (1902) fort walls are about 20 feet high. There is also a small fort called47 Buri Abul Lif on a reef in front of the town. (4). In 1839 there were 500 houses and 500 fighting men. Douglas (1896) was unable to ® stimat ®P®P u ^ lo “- but placed it between 5,000 and 12,000. Cassim Izeddm (1897) reckoned 5 000. Gaskin (1902) puts it at 7,000. (5) There were no Hindus or Christians in 1819. Paterave found the people a mongrel race with Persian blood predominating : they were mostly Shiahs or belonged to even more heterodox sections of Islam. Zwemer also describes them as Shiahs of Persian origin, abhorred by both Turks and Wahabis. In Niebuhr’s day, also, the inhabitants ^ were Shiahs and were believed to be mostly natives of or refugees from Bahrein. (6) In 183 9 tracie, owin' to unsettled state of country was trifling, chiefly with Bahrein, in spices *u^ar, etc., of Indian provenance. A weekly market was held on T h ur sd a y out side the south gate of the fort. Accordingly to Cassim Izeddin (1897) about 300 sailing ships arrive annually from Bahrein bringing sugar and rice and taking away dates, while about 20 larger ships come yearly from Bombay (taking 20 days on the passage) to obtain cargoes of dried dates. Steamers seldom enter the port on account of its dangers. Date ; branches, vyood, reeds and dates are exported to Bahrein. (7) Water is^ plentiful but not good. (8) (9) (10) There is a Municipality but it is inefficient. Douglas mentions a few Turkish officials in the customs, etc., and a gendarmerie about 80 strong (50 mounted, 30 foot). According to Cassim Izeddiu there is a Capitame tie Port (harbour master ?) at Katif. The revenue is £12,000 Turkish a year. The post goes vid Hasa, which carriers reach in 24 hours, to Basra which it reaches in 7 days from Hasa. KEDAIH.—Walled village on Katif mainland, south of Alawamia and north of Bebari. KELAB (BENI).—Kahtanio tribe from Nejd early settled in Katif, now inhabiting Kulabiah. KELAT,—Proper name of Katif town, q. v. KELB—Arab tribe hostile to the Koreish, apparently among early settlers in Hasa. KHALID (BENI).—In Niebuhr’s day whole of Hasa belonged to this tribe, then one of the most powerful among the Arabs, and ex tending so far into the desert as often to annoy caravans between Baghdad and Aleppo. The other tribes of Hasa at that time recognised the sovereignty of the Beni Khalid. Pal grave mentions them as a Kahtanic tribe among the first to immigrate into Hasa ; he describes them as among most spirited and courteous of Bedouins, and as partially civilised by contact with towns. According to the Gulf Pilot, 1898, the remnant of this once powerful tribe has become incorporated with the Al Ejman, between Koweit and Ras-al-Ghar. In 1874 this tribe furnished the Turkish Governor of Hasa. KHATT.—This name is said to be applied to a coastal strip of the main land adjoining Bahrein and including Katif. KHEWAILDIA.—Walled village on mainland of Katif, south of Hilla^ Mehaish and north of Jish. Is this identical with Khoeldeah which Sadlier described as an open village with 1,600 inhabitants. KHOLEDJA.— Place shewn in Kiepert’s Map, about 100 miles north west of Katif on route to Koweit. KJASIME.—Mentioned by Ritter as a harbour between Katif and Basra, with the remark, however, that it does not appear in any map. KODAA.—One of the noblest and most high-spirited of the Kahtanic tribes, according to Palgrave, and contributed to form the present population of Hasa. KOOT.—Ross gives this in a list of the towns and villages of Hasa, KORA.—Place marked in Kiepert’s Map about 50 miles north-west of Katif on route to Koweit. KRAN (JEZIRAT AL).—Island in lat. 27° 43' north and long. 49° 49' east, about 1 mile in length north-east and south-west, a few feet above the sea, quite level and covered with brush-wood. It is 23 miles south west of Jazirat Earsi and 30 miles from the coast. Frequented by fishermenwho dry fish, make turtle oil, etc., which they dispose of at Koweit and Basra. Anchorage is on south-east side, in 8 fathoms, 2 a mile oft island. KULABIAH.— According to Jopp (1841) is a village 6 miles from Hofhuf on route to Katif; it was small, enclosed by walls and had houses mostly built of date-sticks and mats. Palgrave (1862) found it a good-sized village, about 7 miles north-east of Hofhuf. There was a copious spring applied to the irrigation of gardens. He considered the village to be a colony of the Beni Kelab. LAILIYA.—District on coast, south of Husain, said to have much fresh water and many date plantations. LA JAM. Walled village on mainland of Katif, south of Saihat. Is this the same as Liam ? LIAM.—Walled town mentioned by Sadlier as under the Katif Government and having a population of 800. LIF (BTJRJ ABUL).—Small fort on a reef, in front of Katif town and If miles west of Darin, where the Darin and Saihat channels, leading into Katif harbour, unite (description of channels at Page 145 of Gulf Pilot is far from clear). LUGOOAH.—‘Mentioned by Sadlier as unwalled village in Katif district with population of 400. MAGHAR.—Place marked in Pelly's map, in Hasa district. It is a stage on route via Taj from Hasa to Koweit. MAHASHIR.—Tribe at Katif, disaffected towards Turks in 1879. MAIZ.—Place marked in Kiepert’s Map, about 20 miles inland from Ras Mishaab on route from Katif to Koweit. MALAHA.—Village in Katif or Hasa. MATHRA.—Conical peak, 416 feet high, of coast range south of Katif town. Its position is 17 miles south by west of Ras Tanura. MATTRA.—Mentioned as a coast village of Hasa. Is this same as Meth- trah marked in Map of Parts of Arabia and Persia, about 20 miles south of Katif town ? MAYAS.—Walled village in Katif district, north of Sheria and south of Medaris. MEDARIS.-—Walled village on mainland of Katif north of Mayas and south of Bab-ash-Shamal. MENAZELEH.—Village in Hasa proper about 3 miles from Jafar on way to Hofhuf. MERAGHEH.—Place shown in Pelly’s map, nearly 150 miles north west of Katif and 100 miles south of Koweit, a stage on land route between Hasa and Koweit. MISHAAB (RAS).—Low sandy point of land with patches of low cliff, on coast about 140 miles north-north-west of Katif town and 90 miles south- south-east of Koweit, provisionally assumed in this precis as boundary bet ween Katif and Kow r eit. MISHAAB (BANDAR).—Anchorage, 2^ miles wide at entrance, with depths of 6 and 7 fathoms, between eastern spit of Mukta Island on north and a detached patch of reef on south. Ras Mishaab lies about 3J miles north west of this anchorage. MOGHARAT (JEBEL) —Apparently this is the name of the broad, low range of hills which bounds the plain of Hasa on the east and divides it from Katif district. Village of Azmiah is situated among these hills. Ground is rocky and blackish ; there are few trees, but large clumps of aloes. Principal peak is Jebel Mushahbar about 10 miles south of Katif town and perhaps49 n „ P ilo-ravo calls this peak Moscharrif. Average 700 feet Ugh. In anothei place Pal 1 clear wUether i ong elevation of range may be 200 to 300 e^ pal ave . is part 0 f this extends for at least 100 _ d 40() aboV0 the desert the general el e y®* 10 “ ®^° b j hest nart being opposite Juniah. According to and whole look is fanciful and desolate. MOGHOR—See Mogharat. ^ ,. c , , , • 1 070 MOH ANN A.—Place where refugee Amayir from Katif landed in MORUA (AL).—This tribe is found in Katif, or Hasa, and environs. See aub-section B. m rvtvir A 7PPR A.H —Tribe who in 1839 assisted the Egyptian governor o, h“° 2'.™S.- -»7 ““ 11 •“ ■ a “ u “ 1 with any of the tribes mentioned in sub section B. MOOLIHEH (MAA-OOL).—Or Maa-el-Maliyab. Halting place with well about midway between Katif town and VVab. MOSAILAHA.—Place marked in Philip’s map of Arabia about 45 miles south of Katif town and 12 miles from coast. _ MOSCHAKKER—Mentioned by Ritter as a fort standing on a ig mountain. See Mogharat. . . ... MOTTER—Mentioned by Zwemor as one of the principal tnoes which have submitted to the Turkish Government. lurmARRAZ-Town. (1) In Hasa proper. 2 or 3 miles north of TT rw m Surrounded by wide fields of rice and wheat, and plantations of Hoflmf. (2) buirounaeu ny w irregular appearance, containing lehalas dates. Palgiave tound i wretched hovels. Near Mubarraz many handsome houses intermixed ^ ™d baten and 100 yards north is a salt lake rendering seme ae e ’ j no ip a i obieet in the of town is a hot spring forming m0 ^ ue 186 j e ‘by tiie Wahabis, town was a large and not ine , j or) . to tbe west 0 f the town (3) There '; as a9 lat ® r 2 drv d i t eh) but it is not mentioned by iZXs ffbhO) The town was^escribed in 1813 and 1862 as unwalled m ?865 S as ruinous, and in 1896 as walled. (4) Sadlier estimated P^ 1 ^ 0 ^ 10 ^ with fighting strength o £ t ^’ P A ^7 6 f Ac ZdLg to Pa\grive the inhabitants that the population is ^ yind ss of tU commLcial interest than those of tVhieh the district is famous are mannfao- tured here. Weekly fair in 1S62 was held on Mondays, (7) (9) (10) 1 quarters of Mudirlik of same name. MUGHRIS.—Place marked in Kiepert’s Map, about 140 miles north west of Katif on route to Koweit. M UKHATIBA.— According to Gulf Pilot, a tribe in neighbourhood o Katif town. ■\nTTCTA (TEZIRAT-ALV—Island, close to southward of Has Mishaab, abom^mi^long north-east ind south-west, with cliffs 20 to 30 feet high at east end, and covered with grass and brushwood. There is no channel beUee it and mainland.50 MULLAH A.H.—Given by Sartlier as an unwalled village of Katif with population of 400. Is this same as Malaha above ? MUSALAMIYA.—Island about | a mile in extent, situated in Musala- miya Bay about 75 miles north-north-west of Katif town. Bay is shallow but a deep channel leads up to the island. On the east side of the island is a large village inhabited by fishermen of the Omair (? Amayir) tribe (about 400 men) whose boats lie at the north side of the island. According to Bombay Selection XXIY, however, the inhabitants are 500 men of the Beni Khalid tribe, under iJ Sheikhs subject to the Sheikh of Katif. MUSHAHHAPw—See Mogbarat. MUTAHIR.—Tribe mentioned by Douglas as having a total strength of 4,000 and fighting strength ot bOO. They are a subsidised tribe and nomi nally under Turkish control. NAJM (AIN-lfL).—“ Fountain of the Star”, a small village on or near the foot of the cliffs at Ghoweyr. There is a hot spring of clear water said to be most beneficial in cutaneous disorders. In 1841 it was covered by a dome which by 1862 the Wahabis had destroyed for religious and political reasons. NEAREAH.—Place marked in Felly’s map near the coast, about mid way between Katif town and Abu Ali island. NEDSCHJRAN.—Place or district referred to by Ritter on the mainland opposite Bahrein. NEGAYR.—Place, apparently inhabited, marked in Felly’s map about 80 miles north-west of Katif and 30 miles from coast, on Taj route between Hasa and Koweit. OJAIR —Or Aker. Chief and most convenient port of the administrative division of Hasa. (1) Situated on the Arabian coast in the Gulf of Bahrein about 24 miles east south-east of the south extremity of Bahrein island and nearly 70 miles south by east of Katif town. Distant 16 hours by caravan from Hofhuf. (2) Stands on the south-west side of a cove which runs about 4 miles inland in a north-north-west direction. East side of inlet is formed by long, low, sandy point, called Ras Seihaat its south extremity ; and entrance, 200 or 300 yards broad, lies between this point and Zakhnuniya island (see sub section B). Channel and great portion of inlet are 3 to 4 fathoms deep but sea outside is shallower and prevents approach of ships. There is no bazaar. Sandhills begin immediately behind the place. (3). Town consists of Mudir’s house, which is a fortified building with bastions at corners but old and dilapi dated, and a large “ Khan ” or Sarai, 150 yards long by 80 broad, with walls 16 feet high and sheds round 3 sides leaving a parapet of 3| feet at top. Entrances of “ Khan ” are in centre of front and rear faces. (4) In Wahabi times there were 40 or 50 dwellings ; now there are no inhabitants except Turkish officials and gendarmerie. (5) Buckingham described the inhabitants as Beni Asareeah. Neighbourhood appears to be frequented by Naim Bedouins. (6) The port serves Hasa and the whole of south Nejd. Rice, piece-goods, coflee, sugar and hardware for the interior from Bahrein mostly pass through this entrepot. Zwemer says caravan of 200 to 300 camels leaves Ojair every week. (7) W ater can be obtained in sand-pits near the fort, but it is not good ; better water is procurable at an hour’s distance. (8) (9) (10) Ojair is headquarters of Mudirlik of same name. There were in 1897 a mudir, a customs contractor and detachments of 22 regulars and 24 gendarmes each under a Lieutenant. [Rough plan of Ojair inlet will be found in Douglas’s “ Journey ” opposite page 5.] OOMOOR.'—Bedouin tribe whom Sadlier found encamped at Wab. OOZOOMEEAH.—Place with salt wells, 12 hours march from Katif town, where Sadlier halted on his route to Hofhuf. Can this be same as Azmiah above ? Country between Katif and Oozoomeeah is a desert of sandhills and flat sandy plains, surface of latter being covered with thick crust of cakes51 salt, destitute of verdure, and heavy going? for animals. Sandhills bore scanty tufts of grass and a plant called ishnan from which potash is manufactured. To north or north-west of this desert are 7 hamlets (what names ?) containing each from 15 to 150 families in huts, who have a few date-trees and a little cultiva tion. To west and south-west whole country is a desert. OOMERUBEAH.—Or Umm Rebao. Plain with water, 3 hours march south-west from Wab. Here Sadlier found very large camp of Beni Khalid Bedouins. SABAA (UMM).—Large hot spring, gushing up from the depths of a natural basin, about 50 feet in diameter and very deep, and sending out 7 streams in different directions which are utilised for irrigation. Site is 8 miles due north of Hofhuf. Water is too hot for bathers to enter suddenly, and fish, frogs, etc., cannot live in it. Ancient stone-work surrounds the pool and there is thick vegetation. Little village of Zekkah lies about ^ of a mile to the east. SAEWA.—Walled village mentioned by Gaskin as northernmost in Katif district. In Sadlier’s time a walled town of 2,400 inhabitants. SAT HAT.—Walled town and large fort on coast about 5 miles south-south- east of Katif. Thick date groves commence here and continue for 2 or 3 miles beyond Katif. Opposite the town is Saihat Khor, northern branch of which channel gives boats access to Katif town, and southern branch to Dammam. There is a high sandhill behind Saihat visible 12 miles. In Sadlier’s time (1819) population was 2,009. In 1839 the place was said to contain 1,000 fighting men, celebrated for their warlike qualities, and the chiefs of Katif and Saihat were constantly at feud. SALAS IL.—Wells in desert north-east of Domeezee. SANABIS.—Large unwalled fishing village on eastern shore of Tarut Island, north-east of the fort. SAP AN (AL).—Tribe concerned in attack in 1902 on caravan near Gof- dich, in which Turkish detachment was cut up. SENALIS.—Place where the pirate Ahmad bin Selman stole a boat in which he proceeded to Umm Nasan island. SENNABIS.—Place inhabited by the Bu Eelassur. SERA.—According to Ritter, a river watering the villages of the country (? Hasa Proper). SEYBAT.—A place in Katif territory. SHAABAH.—Town or village iu Katif district, placed about 15 miles south of Hofhuf in Palgrave’s map. It is about 5 miles from Ghoweyr. SHAKEEK.—Town or village in Hasa proper. SHEREYDAH.^-Place where Amayir refugees from Katif landed in 1879. SHERTA.—Walled village on mainland of Katif, north of Chawaichib and south of Mayas. SHE WAT OH A.—-Walled village on mainland of Katif, north of Debaibia and south of Chawaichib. SHOWAISH (AULAD). — Tribe near Katif which in 1881 belonged to the party of Zaeed bin Muhammad. Apparently a section of the Beni Hajir. SIH (DUHAT-AIN-AS).—Small shallow cove in Katif coast, opposite Umm Nahsan island and about 30 miles south by east from Katif town. SITAE.—Mentioned by Ritter, along with Ojair and other places, as inhabited by the Abd-el-Kais. SOOEDAN.—Arab tribe, with whom the Amayir fishermen of Janna Island associated themselves in consequence of feud with Katif in 1832 or earlier.52 SUBEIL—Tribe at Katif, ill-affected towards tlie Turks in 1879. SUBEYH.—Tribe at Katif, against whom were many claims in 1879 for injuries inflicted. Is this same as last? TAJ.—Ruined fort about 3 days’ march inland from Katif. Built of large white stones and formerly chief tovvn of Hasa ; foundations can be traced for a mile or more in length and ^ a mile in breadth. Ruins and water still found in neighbourhood. Is this not same as Thaaj below ? TANURA (RAS).—Sandy cape in lat. 2h° 38' north and long. 50° 10' east, forming north side of Katif bay. It is but 100 yards wide in places and south point is very low. There is an anchorage inside the cape with the point of the latter bearing south-east and 1 to i cables off shore, here Turkish government vessels visiting Katif generally lie, at a distance of about 7 miles from Katif town. Name means “whirlpool” and refers to the strong tides in the neigh bourhood which are very complicated and appear to have a great meeting off this point. Near the point the tide seems to split, south of it the flood stream sets to southward; and outside from it north-westward, towards Koweit. TARUT.—Island (called Jirhoot in Bombay Selection XXIV, page 571)* It lies on shore reef in Katif bay, opposite town of Katif, and is fertile and about 3| miles in length and breadth. Eastern half is closely grown with high date-trees, near centre of which is Tarut Eort with high towers showing above the trees. Villages from north to south are Eenia, Sanabis, Tarut and Darin; they are unprotected by walls. A channel to Katif town leads round the noith of the island ; it is navigable at high water for vessels of under 5 feet draught. Tarut Island is connected with the mainland by a ford dry at low water about ^ a mile above Katif Eort; distance from mainland about miles. TARUT.—Unwalled village with high towers and fort on Tarut Island. It stands in centre of date grove which covers eastern half of island. TEHAMA.—Desert marked in Felly’s map south of Hasa proper and south-west of Katar. TELAIMAH.—Place marked in Felly’s map in Hasa proper. It is a stage on route from Hasa to Koweit. TENOOKH.—Arab clan mentioned by Falgrave as among later settlers on north-east side of Arabia, including Hasa. THAAJ.—Eort, marked in Felly’s map in northern part of Hasa proper. THAHRAN (JEBEL).—Elat-topped hill, 500 feet high, on Katif coast 18 miles south from Ras Tanura. THALUM (DUHAT).—Large shallow bay about 7 miles in extent and uninhabited. At south side is sand hill called Hamadiya, used as a land mark, 2 or 3 miles inland from which natives say there is a small lake of fresh water. Low north point of bay has a ruined fort on it, called Kureya. En trance is about 38 miles south of Katif town and 26 miles north of Ojair. THAROOTH.—Village in Katif (?) District. Can Tarut be meant ? THENEEYAT GHAR.—Small village in Moghazi range, 15 miles south west of Hofhuf, on route between Nejd and Hasa. TOBL—Walled village on mainland in Katif district, south of Behari and north of Kelat. UMMOOLKMAN.—Mentioned by S idlier as a w r ailed town of Katif with 1,600 inhabitants. WAB.—Stage with bad water wdiere Sadlier found camp of 300 Oomoor Bedouins, 3 hours’ march north of Oomerubeah. Falgrave places it about 70 miles north-north west of Hofhuf, says Moghazi chain ends northwards of it and speiks of its copious waters ; but he was never there. YAROODEAH.— Mentioned by Sadlier as a walled town in Katif district with population of 1,200.53 Z AHRAN.—Or Dharan. Locality where pirate boats used to lie in wait in 1887. Is this same name as Thaliran above ? ZALLUN.—Place, apparently on or near Katif coast, where a Bahrein baggarah was looted in 1888. ZABUT.—Place in Katif district, inhabitants of which took refuse from Bedouins at Darin on Tarut island in 1888. ZEKKAH. Small village ^ of a mile east of the Umm Sabaa spring in Hasa jaroper. ZOR.—A village on Tarut island. ZOWAR.—A place, apparently near Darin. ZURAK.—Tow r n in Hasa mentioned by Blau apud Miles. C912PD nSr¥55 ABDULLA (KHOR).—Great inlet, having Bubiyan island on the south- west and the land forming the hanks of the west side of the Shatt-al-Arab on the north. It is 12 miles wide at entrance and runs north-west to Warba Island connecting there with Khor as Sabiya and Khor Umm Kasr. Soundings are 4 to 5 fathoms. Off easternmost point of Bubiyan, and at entrance of Khor Abdulla, lies detached bank of hard sand, called Easht-al-Aich, about 8 miles in length, and nearly parallel to Bubiyan Island. The shore of the Khor Abdulla from the entrance of the Shatt-al-Arab to Umm Kasr is low alluvial ground, covered in places with reeds and grass, and elsewhere with mud. The water carried in by the tide forms as it were an over-flow of the sea extending inland for some miles. At high tide the depression is covered with a broad sheet of shallow water, and at low tide is transformed into a series of mud flats. AD AN.—According to Belly means, as used by Koweit people, the tract stretching from Koweit to Khor Karain only, about 45 miles south of Koweit. Malah, Legait and War fra are in it. It is bounded on south and west by district of Shug. In another place Belly describes it as a strip of rising ground, a few miles to the southward of Koweit, and says that native sailors also call it Hejaj-al-Bint from its supposed resemblance to the curve of a girl's eye-brow. AGHTHI.—Range of hills about 200 feet high, of a dusky brown colour and level on top, about 2^ to 3 miles inland from the north shore of Koweit Bay. Towards sea this range ends in a steep declivity. It curves round from Duhat Kathama to entrance of Khor as Sabiya. Shore between Aghthi and Koweit Bay is sandy and covered with tussocks of coarse grass. From the top of this range the ground rises gradually to a ridge some 5 miles to northward. Ko cultivation on this higher ground. AJUZA (RAS AL).—Low point with some conspicuous dark trees, about 6 miles north-west by west of Kas al-Arz and 2 miles north-east by east of Koweit town. ARRAKI.—Second stage on route from Koweit to Hail, about 78 miles from Koweit via Jahara. There is a little water. ARZ (RAS AL.)—Low, sandy point on south side of entrance to Koweit Bay. For 30 miles to south, coast is a stony desert of brown colour rising gradually to 200 or 300 feet at a few miles inland. Between Ras-aLArz and Rasal-Ajuza and nearer the former are 3 small forts (what names?). Inland, 5 miles south-west of Ras-al-Arz, is small square fort, 184 feet above sea level. (Is this one included in 3 before mentioned ?). ASHEIRIJ (RAS).—Low point 8^ miles west of Ras-al-Ajuza, enclosing with the latter a cove of Koweit Bay in which lie the Akkaz flat (of mud with patches of rock), the islet of Kurein (q.v.), and the low rocky island of Umm- an-Namil. Inner part of cove is very shallow, and is called at head Duhat Abu Tala. BUBIYAN (KHOR).-See Khor-as-Sabiya. BUBIYAN (JEZIRAT).—Large, low island, about 26 miles long north and south, by 12 miles broad. There are no date-trees, habitations or fresh water and part is overflowed at high water. South point called Ras-al-Abreisha is 7 miles north-north-west from Failaka Island. West side is separated from mainland by Khor Sabiya. North-east point of island is called Ras-al-Geit, near which a small Turkish storehouse is at present located with an officer and small detachment. The Sheikh of Koweit claims the island on the ground that his people have occupied it annually for fishing and paid rents. There is other evidence in favour of his claim. CHAWAICHIB.—Blace inland, about 2 or 2J miles north-east of Kathama Boint. CHEBREET or CHEBRUT (DELAA-EL).—“ The Sulphur Hills,a small range of 5 distinct hills arranged in a curve with concavity towards the east about 80 miles south of Koweit on route to Riadh. Only 2 of the 5 hills yield sulphur. It is believed that a continuation of these hills sweeps round to56 — Serphwan (? Safvvan), a remarkable eminence 50 miles north-north-west of Koweit. DAHMAN.—Place marked in Kiepert’s map about 35 miles north of Jahara, on route to Basra. DEBENEH.—Name of the desert district near north extremity of which lies Koweit. BELA A (DELAA-ED).—Low range of hills, about 60 miles south of Koweit, running east and west and reaching coast of the Gulf. DJAAEE.—Place marked in Kiepert’s Map about 40 miles north-west of Jahara on route from Basrah to Zulfa in Nejd. . E.1MAN—Tribe found at Shiaiba. Are these the Ejman of sub-section D? ERMEK (WADI).—Valley or depression, shown in Dowding’s map as commencino- south of Hafr and running east-north-east towards head of Koweit Bay, but not reaching it. Is this the Wadi Rummah of Section III, sub-section B ? EAILAKA.—Island.—(1) Its south-west point, the nearest to Koweit, is about 10 miles east-north-east of Ras al-Arz; and its north-east end is about 7 miles south-east of mouth of Khor-as-Sabiya. (2) Its length is 7 miles north-west and south-east and breadth •’&gt; miles at west end. Its shape is that of a badly- shaped wedge with base to the north-west and point to the south-east. (3) It stands on an extensive flat of mud and sand with rocky patches, which extends south-east from the mouth of Khor-as-Sabiya. Island is very low, and at high spring tides is broken in upon by the sea and must be a veritable swamp in rainy season. Not visible more than 6 or 8 miles, so that it is not often seen when entering harbour. It has two outliers viz. % Uha, small sandy islet on the reef, about 3 miles from its south-east extremity, and Mashkan, a low sandy islet on the great Tharub mud flat, 2 miles from Eailaka towards north-west. Highest part of island is mound, about 30ifeet above sea, on south-west side, with tomb of Said Sadoo. (4) There were in 1839 a few straggling date-trees, yielding little or no fruit, and a few cultivated patches of loamy sand hearing onions, melons and occasionally small quantities of wheat, irrigated from numerous wells. Water was good during rAns and indifferent at other times. Inhabitants depended entirely on other places for supplies, but pos sessed a few flocks ; and a few fish, sheep and poultry were obtainable. The people owned 15 or 16 baghlas trading to Basra, and 45 or 50 date-branch ■boats used only for fishing. (5) In 1825 (?) the inhabitants numbered 400 or 500 and were mostly fishermen. In 1839 there were 3 villages on island ; Toor on west, Saidee on noith and Grane on east, but last 2 had been depopulated by plague. Toor had V0 to 80 houses and about 1 0 inhabitants. Toor is apparently identical with Zowar, mentioned by Gulf Pilot, 1898, as a village in centre of west side of island with small date- grove and about 250 inhabitants. The present chart shows two “ towns ” and a village (without names) in addition to Zowar. People in 1839 were poor and miserable and said the island was unhealthy, that they were much subject to fevers and that infant mortality was heavy. (6) (7) Eadaka forms part of Koweit territory. It has been examined and found unsuitable for a coal depot, unless for steamers drawing under 7 feet, and these too w ould have to lie 300 yards off shore. In 1825 (?) Governor w T as relation of Sheikh of Koweit. EANAITIS.—Small fort containing about 40 men, on the Arabian coast about 10 miles south of Ras-al Arz. People are herdsmen and cultivators. PANT AS.—Small date-clump with habitations (?) half way between Panaitis and Abu Halaifa. GEIT (RAS AL).—See under Bubiyan Island. GRANE.—S3e under Pailaka. HADEIBA (PASHT AL).—See Koweit Bay. HADUBA.—Place marked in Kiepert’s map, about 40 miles south of Kow r eit and 10 miles from coast. HAPR.—Place mentioned by Dowding as situated in the Wadi-er-Rum- mah and forming the 3rd stage on the journeyj from Koweit to Hail, distance57 110 miles from Koweit. In Ins map lie locales it almost due west of Koweifc hut only about 50 miles distant : he shews the Koweit, Basra, Medina and* Mecca caravan routes as meeting there. In another place he mentions that Sheikh of Koweit claims possession, though he has never received tribute. At llafr is a well 35 fathoms deep. HALAIEA (ABU).—Small fort near shore 3 miles south (?) of Fanaitis, with a few date-trees and wells of good water. It is under Sheikh of Koweit and some horses are shipped from here to India. People are herdsmen and cultivators. HEZAIM.—Halting place 3 marches from Koweit on route to Katif. HIER.—Is this another name of the Delaa-ed-Delaa hills ? HUWAJIR.—Tribe numbering 1,500 men, predominant along coast from Ras Mishaab to Shiaiba. Can these be same as Beni Hajir of sub-section B ? ISPHUAN.—Large hill, forming a capital landmark, 1 hour’s distance west of Salphoon. JAHARA.—Village. (1) Situated at extreme west end of Koweit Bay about 15 miles west of Koweit town and some 1,200 yards inland from high water-mark. (2) Three miles to the north is a low sandstone ridge, extending west and east, through gap in which runs route to Basra ; while to' south-west is undulating country covered in spring with grass and flowers, but desti tute of water. In 1863 Jahara consisted of 3 large enclosures or forts and a dozen small gardens, with about 200 acres of barley outside them. It is now (1902) a well-built village of sun-dried bricks with a circumference of about I 2 miles. There are outlying patches of cultivation round the w^alls and many enclosures containing wheat, date-trees, lucerne, tamarisk, etc., surrounded by mud-walls 2 to 3 feet thick and 8 or 10 feet high. The place is said to he healthy, and the air dry like that of Baghdad. (3) There is an old fort in dis- repair on the western frontage of the village, as w ell as a new one, built by the present Sheikh, clear of the south-eastern end of the village. Jahara would be untenable if attacked by force wdth artillery, unless defence w T ere undertaken on more extended scale than at present ; A1 Aghtbi bills which command place would have to be occupied by defenders. Head of Koweit Bay is shoal and ships could not effectively co operate iu defence ; if attack were from south-west assailants would not come under fire at all. (4) Population w as about 100 in 1803 and is 200 to 300 now. (5) (6) Horses w^ere collected here in 1863 and fed on lucerne for shipment to Bombay. (7) In 1863 there were flocks of sheen and plenty of water. There were a dozen small wells of good drinkinn- water on a patch of white ground south of village. In 1902 most of the cultf- vated enclosures contained their own wells, hut the water was, as a rule fit only for irrigation. Sheikh considers Jahara essential to Koweit as being the ^ only locality with any agricultural capabilities or resources Besides being a valuable source of supply of grain, forage, dates, etc’ it is a farounte grazing ground in the winter months of the Bedouins who own allegiance to Koweit (8) (9) (10) A temporary evacuation of the place would entail great loss of prestige to Koweit and, apart from perrnanem damage which might be done to date-trees, the Bedouins would go over to the owners of Jahara. Sheikh was, in last crisis, unwilling to withdraw garri son from Jahara even for effective defence of Koweit. He pointed oufthat abandonment of Jahara would mean abandonment of Kathama, which it was believed Germans wished to acquire as railway terminus. (Sketch diagram of Jahara village will be found in Dowding’s Report on Koweit 1903 ) S ' f r o m J Witto ( ^s ) r ACCOrdinS t0 PelIy ' the ^ 0ral — of tbe country JEZZA. (ABU) — An extensive mud-flat, 3 miles north-east of TCnhW abontlo m.lesm extent Pearls are fished for, so doubtless it is bard in parts * KAREIN (KHOR).—Depression and creek of some evtpnf nKr. i a- miles south of Koweit and 3 hours south of Le ? ait reaching Per,Ln Gulf s^meTame :^ 6611 ^ ^ EaS Mishaab ' Near it. inlfTis hm of at K ^ R ^1 OEZIPvAT).—Sandy islet, in lat. 28° 49' north and lon&lt;r 48” 47 east, 21 miles south-east of Kubbar. Diameter is about 1 cable’and C912FD58 height above high water is only 3 or 4 feet. It has a few tufts of grass and swarms with birds, being covered in the season with their eggs and young. There is a deposit of guano a few inches deep over surface of island. KASR (UMM) —Place with a Turkishfortified post, but no other houses, on west bank of a creek of same name, which joins Khor-as-Sabiyah opposite Warba Island. Umm Kasr is 10 miles south-east of Safwan and 25 to 30 miles south east half south of Zobeir. There are no wells on the direct road between Zobeir and Umm Kasr and caravans prefer the western road by Jebel Sanam and Safwan, where they are plentiful. Except in case of rain coupled with a strong south wund the tidal flow does not generally affect the marshes much beyond Umm Kasr. The fort is a small rectangular enclosure for 40 men with loop- holed mud wall and banquette inside. It is J of a mile from the creek and 7 miles by the creek from Warba Island. Close by is an old ruined fort. Umm Kasr is a general watering place for Arabs of the desert. Tribal quarrels at the well are frequent and often lead to bloodshed. The family of the Sheikhs of Koweit were originally pirates w ith their head-quarters here, and the present Sheikh of Koweit claims the ownership. There is a good water-supply and grazing for sheep but not for horses. KASR (KHOR UMM).—So styled by Kemp in his recent survey, is an inlet leading from the junction of the Khars (?) Abdullah and As-Sabiyah, at the west end of Warba Island, for about 6 miles in an average north-west direction. Opposite the Umm Kasr fort it divides into two branches—one continuing north-w T est, the other running north towards Zobeir. The sound ings between Warba Island and this point of divergence range from six to nine fathoms and the average breadth of this section of the inlet is about f of a mile. The north-west branch opposite Umm Kasr fort is, at low water, nothing but a mud-flat with a shallow channel not more than 3 or 4 feet deep on the west side ; w hile at high tide there is a wide expanse of water to the east as far as the eye can reach and this extends inland, following a natural depression of the ground, for some miles to the north-west. KATHAMA (DUHAT and HAS).-—The innermost cove of Koweit Bay, between Ras Asheirij and Ras Kathama. The south side of it has a west- south-west direction for 5 miles from the former point; the cove shoals gradually from the entrance, which is 4 miles broad, towards the head at which Jahara village is situated. Ras Kathama is a low swampy point, only just above high water, running out some three furlongs from the northern shore of the bay ; it is protected partially by a naturally formed bank of sand along the high water line. It is believed that the Germans w ished to acquire here a plot of land, about 20 square miles in extent, as a terminus for the Baghdad railway. See also under Koweit Bay. KHITTEI on KHATER —Second stage from Koweit on (? coast) route to Basra. Distance about 15 miles from Jahara. KOWEIT.—Principality. (1) Boundaries are somewhat indeterminate, except on east, where formed by Persian Gulf. Sheikh claims Safwan on north and Hafr on west and Bombay Records (probably on authority of Brucks, 1825) state that his authority extends as far south as Khor Khuffagee (? Khafji). Palgrave in 1863 carried the Koweit boundary in bis map about 20 miles south, 30 miles w r est and 60 miles north of the town. Pelly in 1865 considered the country w ithin a radius of 8 or 10 miles only to belong to Sheikh of Koweit; at another time he placed the south boundary at Malah, about 15 miles south-south-east of Koweit. In the present precis, all places north of Ras Mishaab and south of Koweit have been provisionally included in the Koweit sub-section; also all places on the west and north as far as Hafr and Safwan res pectively. (2) Names of districts are not known, unless, following Pelly, Adan in which Koweit town stands, Shug to the south of it, and Debeneh which possi bly includes both the others. (3) The physical geography of various poriions is described under Eailaka, Bubiyan, etc. To begin from the north, there is a desert south of Salphoon (? Safwan) with pebbles and jungle-grass alternating, and here and there shallow beds of nullahs. Towards the Khor* as-Sabiya the mainland is a sandy waste impregnated with salt, with here and there a few tufts of brushw ood. At 9 hours south by w^est of Salphoon■ 59 sandstone begins to crop out and continues for two Lours. ^ From a point 5 Lours north of Jabara begin undulating plains covered, in spring, with grass and flowers. These continue for 4 hours when the sandstone ridge of Aghthi is reached and passed through, 3 miles from Jahara. To the south and west of Jahara is undulating country covered, in spring, with grass and flowers, but without water. The shepherds of that region have water sent to them on camels. Between Jahara and Koweit is a low, flat, salt plain, here and there slightly raised, with sand and a little grass. General character of country is horizon- bounded prairie, undulating like long, low waves. South and west of Malah are boundless, slightly undulating plains with flowers and grass just sufficient in spring to give a glow of green. The Delaa-el-Chebreet and Delaa-ed-Delaa (q.v.) are features of this part of the district; see also articles on Khor Karein and Shug. For 30 miles south of Koweit coast is a stony, brown- coloured desert, rising gradually to a height of 200 or 300 feet at a few miles inland. For 1 hour east of Koweit on route to Malah is scant grass; and thereafter, for 4 hours to south-south-east, plains sprinkled with low brush wood. Generally the country is arid and barren, but there is some cultivation in neighbourhood of forts. (4) Climate of Koweit town is separately dealt with. Begarding remainder no information except that great cold sometimes prevails in tract north of bay of Koweit. In the winter of 1862-63 in the neighbourhood of Salphoon (? Safwan) nearly all the sheep died of cold and on 2nd March 1863, at the same place. Colonel Felly’s water-skins were frozen. (5) Such information as is available regarding routes will be found in the following authorities quoted at the beginning of this sub-section, viz , No. 7, pages 117—H9; No. 9, pages 16—22, and Appendices IV, VI and VII ; No. 16, pages 25—28 and Appendix A. Cassim Izeddin gives the caravan distances from Koweit as 15 days to Hail, 12 days to Aneyza and 8 days to Hasa. Felly makes it 8 days to Katif, 10 to Hasa, Ojair or Zalfah in Nejd, 12 to Kaseem in Nejd, 18 to Jebel Shammar, 18 to Hazm-er-Baji and 26 to Mecca, rate being 8 hours a day on camel-back. (6) (a) Products are nil (?). (p)—~(d) Trade is most ly of a through character, and is therefore dealt with under Koweit town, (e) The only commercial centre is Koweit town, (f) The currency is cosmopolitan. Tne Maria Theresa dollar or rial (=Rs. 1-8-0) may be considered the standard, but Indian rupees, Persian krans and Turkish copper coins circu late, and even English sovereigns are found. It is said bills can be obtained on Basra, Bushire, Bombay and even the capital of Nejd. (7) G?)—-W- There is no estimate of the population of the principality except Kemball’s (1903) of 20,000 people in Koweit town and 30,000 Bedouins owning allegiance. The inhabitants of Koweit town are believed to be mainly U ttoobees and those of the country to the south mostly A1 Ali (a branch of the Beni Khalid). Forty families of Ejman are found at Shiaiba. There are also wandering parties of other tribes, including the Montitik. Coast population live on dry fish and a few dates ; inland people on dates, corn and camels’ milk. In Bedouin encampments both families and horses sometimes subsist exclusively on camels’ milk. Both Bedouins and townspeople store locusts. People smoke Persian nargeilah with tobacco of Lar from Linga, or Turkish chebook with tobacco brought by the Tigris from Mosul or via Mocha from Yemen. In the desert the Arab sabeel is generally smoked. (8) The Gov ernment is patriarchal. The Sheikh exercises political and the Kazi judicial functions. Pu lishment is rarely inflicted and there is little interference w ith the liberty of the subject. No tribute is exacted from the tribes and except for small “ offerings ” at the gate, or from merchants, there is no system of customs, and trade is entirely free. Stocqueler (1832) differing from other authorities mentions an import duty of 2 per cent. Felly (1863) estimated the Sheikh’s receipts to amount to Bs. 20,000. Koweit flies the Turkish flag but the meaning of this is disputed ; and the Sheikh denies having ever paid tribute to Turkey. The fighting force at the disposal of the Sheikh consists of 6,000 men in Koweit town and doubtful number from among the Bedouins. Dowd- ing describes their organisation, armament and efficiency in his report. The Turks regard Koweit as a Kaimmakamlik of the Basra Mutasarriflik. KOWEIT.—Town. (1) Capital of the Koweit principality, having its north end situated in lat. 29° 22' 56 w north and long. 47° 59' 51' east, about60 80 miles south and slightly east of Basra, almost 180 miles west by north of Bushahr and nearly 2b0 miles north-north-west of Bahrein. (2) Town stands on loose sandstone covered with sand on southern shore of Ivoweit Bay, about ^ of the way from its entrance at Ras-al-Arz to its head at Jahara, and faces north-west. Greatest length is about 1 mile from north-east to south-west and breadth is between J and a mile. Inland a desert of white sand stretches away from the very walls: town and surroundings are almost destitute of verdure and cultivation, but there are a few date-trees. There are some stono bouses, but most are of sundried brick. They are occasionally faced with coarse chunam, but exteriors are bare and uniform ; usual design is a central courtyard surrounded by chambers looking into it, with flat roofs. Streets aro wider than at Maskat or Bushahr and some have a gutter down the middle. Belly described the place as clean and active with a broad and open main bazaar. Cassim Izeddin (1897) considered the streets narrow, but not very dirty ; he com mented, however on, the absence of latrines except in the houses of notables and on the abuse of the sea-beach and plain behind the town and even of roofs and streets. There is a large suburb of mat huts outside town-wall on south side, near main gate ; this is point of arrival and departure of up-country caravans and quarter chiefly frequented by Bedouins who do most of their trade here. Shoal water extends about 8 cables off the town, and the beach dries out to a con siderable distance, but at high water the sea washes up to the houses ; the native boats are hauled up on the beach, inside substantial breakwaters of loose stone which form tidal harbours. Landing at low tide is inconvenient. Town is said to contain about 3,000 houses, 500 shops, 3 caravanserais, 6 coffee-houses, 3 schools and 4 mosques^ as well as numerous warehouses and stores. About 30 new bouses are built and 40 new shops opened every year (1902). Climate distinctly good as compared with many ports in Persian Gnlf. In December and January it is bracing in mornings and evenings and never unpleasantly hot. In hot months north-west wind is tempered by blowing across bay. Pever practically unknown and dysentery and ophthalmia rare. Nights are said to be cool in the hot weather. (3) In 1832 town was defended on side next desert by wall not one foot thick, having 3 gates, each protected by 2 honey combed guns. In 1902 town was surrounded by low wall with towers, which however were not in a good condiiion for defence. About 1 mile outside town is line of sandhills and broken ground which could be made strong enough to- resist any probable attack. (4) Population appears to be regularly and rapidly increasing. In 1839 or earlier it was estimated at 6,000 ; in 1^59 at 8,000 ; in 1863 at 15,000 to 20,000 (Peliy); in 1897 at 30,000 (Cassim Izeddin) - r in 1901 at 30,000 to 40,000 (Dowding). Zwemer however (1900) makes population only 10,000 to 12,000. (5) The town is almost entirely Arab ; most of people (?) belong to Uttoobee tribe. Almost all are Sunnis ; there are no Wahabis and a few Persian merchants are the only Shiahs. Beligious toleration prevails and 50 Bushahr Jews here have a synagogue of their own. Inhabitants are chiefly en gaged in trade or navigation, and Pelly calculated that perhaps 4,000 were sailors; hut their boat-builders then (1863) came from Maskat. They are warlike and united. About 200 pilgrims annually proceed hence to Mecca, sometimes by Hail, sometimes by Aneyza; and about 50 go by sea. (6) Koweit has no pro ducts or manufactures and its prosperity proceeds entirely from trade, shipping, ship-building, fishing, pearl-fishing and, to a small extent, cattle breeding Goods tor shipment to Bombay are collected here from other Gulf ports and similarly it is a centre from which foreign merchandise is distributed. It is favoured by comparatively healthy climate, and by position, a creek (? Khors As- Sabiya and Umm Kasr) leading hence to within 3 2 miles of Basra. There is considerable trade by land with Syria and Central Arabia. An annual caravan of 3,000 camels and 250 men goes to Damascus, and horses brought thence which in turn are shipped to Bombay. About 40 caravans from Central Arabia come in during year, average strength 200 men and 500 camels ; their arrival is irregular, sometimes two a week, sometimes one a month. I iesc mng hoiscs, ghi and wool and take in exchange rice, coffee, su^ar cloth iron, petroleum, etc. Local Bedouins bring in horses, cattle, milk, butte°r, truffles! camel-dung, etc , and purchase dates, cloth, arms and other goods. There is also an active coasting trade; much of Gulf carrying trade centres in Koweit andrr lYinvino* between Ivoweit and Basra wbence there are always many Kowe^lmts^m^^ ^ Bombay and Red Sea; dates are brought. Ko e o Indian Oeean every year All carry one or two of these are said o v „ India rice and cloth from Mask at, &lt;]a, . ee XtYrom Red Sea ’ hi 1G39 there was also' an import of tobaoeo and dried trade*in' Bahrein ; of spiees and sugar l ^ davs uith a favourable continue ? From Bombay \o Kwfi? * at K ovve it. More haghlas wind. There is an extensive ‘ . 'Q. u ]f The trading fleet has been belong to this port than to any oil ei tl f G f els 1&amp;rge and small ; in 1839 variously estimated, t nns and 15 hi' ba^hlas of 150 to 400 tons; at 160 trading boats ofl 5 to 1.0 tons and 15 bi { 2( to;j0 o tons . ift-n f-00 trading: ba^hlas; in IVJb at iou vessels ui ^ 11 iL „ fnvs that there are vessels of as much as 1,00.) tons running to Bombay howdmg a&gt;sthat t 9 g, Kovveit sends 40 boats to pearl-fashery and Mesopotamia. Gulf Btlot 1898 sa -' olvdinw (1903) states the pearl-fishing and these do not go soutli of A'-u A . l ov dm t 1903) : ^ estimated fleet at 600 boats vuth crews of 15 o 40 (chiefly long-cloth, rice, coffee, the imports from India at 2 lakhs of inpees ^ 800 horses, R s. 2,40,000 ; Pla i 9 li Ks P 4 ? 000 C: dates, X Rs 60,000 ; and miscellaneous, Rs. 40,000. At an earlier period the total imports were estimated at 5 lakhs of d ?'' a ™Xl Jr yields AvnnrU at less than 1 lakh. (7) Local resources are small. Ihe harbo Jr jieias nn^nhimdance of excellent fish, including soles. Onions are the only (.) vege- tabhe erown^and^atermelons the only (?) fruit. Only agncultura! resources are aUahura where a small amount of cereals and green folder and dates is raised Dm in' winter there is sparse grazing for goats on plain near Ko ei. , but best pastures, much frequented by Bedouins are those round Jahara TCnthama Bay and thence along north shore between A 3 hthi and at ^ fdt ( Barfey and wheat are (or used to be) brought from Basra and India, rice from Mangalore, dal from Basra and Bushire. Cattle, sheep, poultry, milk, butter, truffles and fuel are obtainable, supplied by the local Bedouins. Stone and chunam are plentiful, the latter cheap and good. 1 lenty of eak p auk obtained from Bombay for boathuildnig, used to he available, also a laid wood (what?) from Maskat for knees and timbers. I here is abundance of dates from the Shatt-al-Arab. Horse forage comes in part down Khor-as-Sabiya from Bander Zobeir. Water is brackish. The best in 1863 came from wells 3 a mile south of the town ; now it apparently comes Bom a place 2 miles distant. (9) (10) Government has already been dealt with under Koweit principality. It may be rioted that Bedouins are not allowed to enter the town armed, [« Koweit ” appears to be an Arabic diminutive of the non-Arabic word Kot . a fortified place. The older name, spelt Grain, Grane or Graine, w^as probably taken from the adjacent islet of “ Kurein ” (little horn). I elly says that this name was applied rather to the shore-line of the whole hay than to the town.J KOWEIT BAY.—Large inlet of remarkable form leading out of the ex treme north west corner of the Persian Gulf, on the southern shore of which stands the town of Koweit. Its extreme length east and west is over 20 miles, and breadth north and south 10 miles. Its shape approaches a crescent with the convex side f o the north and one of the horns pointing south-west. The Bay proper is an indentation in the true Arabian coast line re presented on the north by the western hank of the Khor-as-Sabiya and on the south by the coast south of Bas-al-Arz ; hut its shore line is artificially piolonged on the side towards the Shatt-al-Arab by a mud- flat extending 20 miles south-east from the mouth of Khor-as-Sabiya, oil which stands the island of Pailaka. The entrance to the bay between this mud-flat and llas*al*Arz is about 4 miles wide and open to the south-west and south-south-west. In the southern shore of the bay are 3 minor coves , the easternmost cove between Ras-al-Arz and Ras-al-Ajuza is shallow, and vessels are recommended not to enter it; the middle cove, between Ras-al-Ajuza and Ras Asheirij contains Koweit town on its eastern shore, a large mud-flat known as Al Akkaz in the centre, the islet of Ivurein at the south east corner of Al Akkaz, and the island of L T mm-an-Namil near Ras Asheirij ; the westernmost cove (Duhat Kathama) between Ras Asheirij and RasKathama forms the head of the whole bay and contains the village of Jahara. In most C912FD Q62 parts of the bay is water of suitable depth for anchorage and good holding ground. Soundings are 14 fathoms off Ras-al-Arz and 6 to 10 fathoms off Ras* al-Aiuza, shoaling to 6 and 7 fathoms at entrance of Duhat Kathama. Ihere is a rocky 2-fathom shoal called FashA-al-Hadeiba, If miles north of the east end of the town. The anchorage for large vessels oft the town is called Bandar Toweina; it is If to If (?) miles west-north-west of north end of town in 3f to 4 fathoms. (2V.Z?.—These directions from the Gulf Pilot, 1893, do not agree with the latest Admiralty plan of the harbour, corrected to 1903). In a Shamal a con siderable sea gets up in the south part of the bay, but not enough to distress a large vessel. In a Kaus, vessels anchoring outside the Hadeiba shoal or with the town south by west to south-south-west 'would not be much sheltered. Ihe land surrounding the bay is low except on the north side where the Aghthi lulls, parallel to the shore, attain a height of several hundred feet. A flat of soft mud extends some distance off the shore on the north side of the bay, which makes it difficult to communicate between ship and shore at low water. KUBBAR (JEZIRAT).—Low, white, sandy islet, overgrown with brush wood, situated in lat. 29° 4 / N. and long. 48° 30' E., 26 miles south-east of Ras al- Arz and 15f miles from nearest point on mainland which is Ras-al-Kaliya. Islet is about f of a mile in diameter and 8 feet above sea level. A few birds from the mainland frequent it. There is usually no fresh water except after rain. 80 Persian Gulf Pilot, 18b8 ; but Bombay Selection XXIV says there are partridges and fresh water. KUREIN (JEZIRAT).—Barren islet with small, brown-coloured peak 30 to 40 feet high, in same cove of Koweit Bay as Koweit town. Kurein lies 5-s miles west-south-west of Ras-al-Ajuza and ^ a mile off shore. r Io south-east is a small basin with 2 fathoms of water called Bandar Shuwaik, where native boats lie perfectly sheltered from all winds. Prom this island Koweit took its older name of “ Graine.” LEGAIT.—Uninhabited camping-ground on way to Riadb, situated in a depression, 2 marches (? 18 miles) south of Kovveir. Prom this point a track runs south-west to Zulfah in Nejd. MADERA.—Third stage on (? coast) route from Koweit to Basra, about 48 miles from Koweit. MALAH.—Port 5 hours south-south-east of Koweit, first stage on route to Riadh and point at which track ends. Around fort are some w 7 ells, a little cultivation and a few 7 temporary huts. Pelly considered this the south boun dary of Koweit territory in 1865. MARADIM (UMMAL).—Low, sandy islet, 25 miles south by east of Jezirat Kubbar, under ^ a mile in diameter, covered with brushwcod, but dis- titute of water. MASHKAN.—Low, sandy islet lying on the Tharub mud-flat between Pailaka and the mouth of the Khor-as*Sabiya, 2 miles north-west of Pailaka. MEGATA.—Halting place four marches from Kovveit on one route to Katif. MERAGHAH.—Halting place four marches from Koweit on Taj route to Dasa. OMENAG A.—Pifth stage on (? coast) route from Koweit to Basra, about . 78 miles from Koweit. ORIAFA.—Place marked in Kiepert’s Map, about 40 miles south-south west of Koweit and 30 miles from the coast. REDAIE.—Name of a few remarkable sandhills forming a landmark on the route from Koweit to Riadh, between the Shug and Wuriya districts. BHMMAH (WADI-ER).—Valley in which Hafr is situated. See Section III, Sub-section B. SAB HA.—See Sabria. SABIYA (KASR).—Uninhabited square enclosure belonging to Sheikh of Koweit, situated on w r est bank of Khor-as-Sabiya near its mouth. Oppo site Kasr Sabiya direction of Kbor is due north and south and width about 1 -| miles.■■■■■mi63 SABI YA (RHOR-AS) —Called also Khor BuLiyan. A remarkable salt water inlet running from the north-east corner of Koweit Bay to arba Island, in the neighbourhood of which it meets Khor Abdullah from the east and Khor Umm Kasr from the north-west, and separating Bubiyan Island from the main. Its length is over 30 miles, average direction north-north* west-and south-south east and average breadth about 1 mile (one authority says ^ a mile). Out side the mouth navigation is difficult owing to a number of knolls almost dry, and native boats can enter only at half flood. The banks are swampy ; but there are a good many boulders, especially along east shore. Most con venient landing place is on west bank, about of the distance from the south end. .According to Pellv (1883) the depth in the middle is nowhere less than o fathoms, but the latest chart shows soundings of 4, 3 and even 2. Belly men tions a branch about 40 feet wide, thrown off by the Khor Sabiya at its head in a direction north ^ west; he tracked up this branch for 5 miles and entered a larger Khor, 250 yards wide, which opened into the Khor Abdullah ( ? Khor Umm Kasr). Is this branch the “ boat-channelmarked in Kemp’s recent survey, between west of Warba Island and the main ? SABRIA—Or Sabha. Fourth stage on (? coast) route from Koweit to Basra, about 63 miles from Koweit. SABUKA.—Place marked in Kiepert’s map, 50 miles south of Koweit where routes from Koweit to Katif and Nejd diverge. SAID SADOO.—See under Failaka. SAFWAN.—Pleace about 20 miles north-west of Umm Kasr. Mentioned by Dowding as second stage on direct route from Koweit to Basra, al out 41 miles north (?) of Jabara and 29 south (?) of Zobeir. He says Cl ief of Koweit claims possession. Is this the Salphoon of Colvill and Pelly below? In 190^ Safwan bad a Turkish garrison of about 300 men. SAIDEE—See under Fakaha. SALEIBIKHAT.—White sandhills lying some distance to south and west of Koweit town. SALPHOON—Place about 16 miles south by west of Zobeir and about 17 hours from Jabara on route from Basra to Koweit. In 1S63 it consisted of 3 square enclosures or forts, each containing a large well. Water was bitter, but drinkable. Garlic, lucerne and grass were grown by irrigation from wells, but wheat and barley were not produced. No barley or straw was obtainable for horses, nor bread for men, and but little brushwood for fuel. One hour’s distance to west is hill of Isphuan. This appears to be same as Safwan above ; both are on direct route between Basra and Koweit, but whereas Colvill places S dphoon about 16 miles south of Zobeir and about 50 miles north of Jahara, Dowding puts Safwan 29 miles south of Zobeir and 41 north of Jahara. Dowding notes however that individual riders can cover the distance between Zobeir and Safvvan in 4 hours. SANAM (JEBEL).—Mentioned by Zwemer as lying west of route between Koweit and Basra. Dowding shows it in his map about 45 miles north and slightly east of Jahara. Can this he identical with Colvill’s Isphuan ? SELAIB —Tribe, so called in Syria and apparently on east side of Arabia ; in Central Arabia they are spoken of as Sulaba (singular, SulabU. West of Hail they are generally called Khlua (singular, Khelui), i e., “ Solitaries ” or contemptuously Kilab el-Khala, “dogs of the desert.” (1) No reli able account of their origin seems to be extant. They have a tradition that their patriarch forbade them to keep cattle, and ordered them to subsist by the chase. They are not, apparently, Arabs. (2) No information as to their sub-divisions, except that there is said to be one, called Ghuneymy in East ern Arabia, that will not intermarry with the others. (3) There is no estimate of their numbers. They are found in Nejd, Irak, etc., and in the neighbour hood of Koweit; they extend from Syria to Yemen and, as among the Bedouins, the various sections have their own fixed localities. (4) They are peaceful and markedly hospitable and seem more intelligent than the Arabs. They have a more European than Asiatic cast of countenance, and according to Palgrave those in Central Arabia by “ th&lt; ir fair complexion and open,64 sometimes handsome, features and light eyes show the Syrian rather than r imbian type ; while their careless gaiety ^ COn a ^ g with the cloudy and suspicious physiognomy 0 the wanderers amo g whom they live.” Doughty remarks on the full laced beai iV children Felly says the women have the finest features of any wan eri g She but are dVto a proverb. In character they are oleran andhu n e beiocr themselves despised and oppressed ; Bedouins will not dr nk ont o a vessel after a Selaibi. The term Selaib is hurled as a reproach at othei infet ior tribes of Central Arabia, such as the tieteym, Sherarat and Sunna^ ye ea c- lv Bedouin child is sometimes name feulabi or h.helui, loi iuck, p Lt U may -ww up. Their women beg at Bedouin tents though probab y better ted tha°n the Bedouins. (5) In some eases ‘^ey conform outward^o Muhammadanism, but among themselves they ha^e the - observances They believe in one God and respect Muhammad as a man, hut deny his mision. They believe also in some anonymous heayenly persoua/es styl“l the - confidential friends of God.” They pray 3 times daily once as the sun rises, so as to finish ere the d lsc is, nil on the 'horizon ; secondly, before the sun dips from the mendian ; and t urd^y so as to finish with the setting of the sun. Ihe Selaib of IwJc aie said to have a purer worship and to have preserved certain sacred writings in Assyrian or Chaldaean, including the Tsalms of David and some ot the Jew,si, Prophets. The Selaib fast 3 times a year ; 30 days in Ramzan, 4 to 7 da^s in Sliaban, and from B to 9 days in one of the summer months. Ihe Selaib adore the Pole Star (which they call Jah) and reverence it by facing i an spreading out their arms so as to form a cross. They also adore a star called Jedv in the constellation Aries. They respect Mecca hut consider their own proper place of pilgrimage to be Haran, in Irak or Mesopotamia. 1 le Solaib of the desert seem to have conformed to the ceremonies of the dominant religion, until from generation to generation they have lost their own. 1 ey declare they were originally Sahaeans, but Pelly considers this erroneous. Pal 'rave says they have a strong, unchanging hatred of Muhammadanism. DouMitv however, represents them as Muhammadans, knowing r,o other reu'gion^'perhaps this holds of the Sulaba of Nejd. (6) The Selaib will eat any. thin 0, including sheep and camels that have died a natural death , but their diet is mainly dates and locusts, with the milk and butter afforded by their numer ous herds and flocks. Any surplus they sell on the seaboard, where they pitch for about 4 months of the year, wandering about for the remaining 8 months and tending their sheep and camels. Their tents are of black goats hair, and so handy as to be readily transported. They eat the flesh of the gazelle, which they shoot, and wear a long shirt of its skin coming down to their feet. Doughty savs, they work for the Bedouins while they can get milk from them and in summer go off to the desert and live by hunting. Their hunters drink 2 hours before dawn and not again till noon. (7) They hunt the gazelle, and in Central Arabia the ostrich ; and are reported excellent marksmen and unrivalled m the pursuit of both. In land craft they are as superior to the Bedouins as the Bedouins to the fixed population of the oases. They act as drudges and guides of the Arabs. They are the safest guides and best water-tinders m the desert. Tuey come in at Koweit on white donkeys, riding cross-legged on a peculiar saddle and without a bridle ; they bring for sale at the town much the same things as the Arab Bedouins. Their donkeys are famous, and with them they °'0 hunting, and make desert journeys which are difficult even for Bedouins on dromedaries. According to Palgrave, the Selaib are cre dited by the Arabs with the performance of difficult surgical operations. They are tinkers and tin the brass kettles and pots of the Bedouins, whose arms they also mend. They make hatchets, sickles and flint steels, but their work is ruder than that of the Sunna (Section HI, Sub section A). They work also in wood and construct camel saddles of desert acacia, well pulleys and milk vessels. They are farriers and cattle surgeons to the Bedouins. (A few in the direction of Mesopotamia are said to keep cattle of their own ) ^ Ti e Sulaba also take away the vessels of townspeople at Kheybar, etc , to be tinned or mended and return with'them after a time; what money they make they are said to bury in the desert. (8) Language is Arabic (?). (9) Forty days after the birth of a child it is immersed 7 times in water, and a male child must be cir cumcised before it is 7 years old. At a circumcision some sheep are killed and65 all are welcome to the feast. The marriage ceremony is simple and is performed in the presence of the respective fathers, or nearest of kin, of bride and bride* groom. Voluntary consent of the parties is necessary, also the permission of the father. The girl’s father receives a certain payment. A mulla or greybeard then asks the parties if they consent to the union, receives a fee and sends them off to cohabit. There seem to be no particular burial ceremonies. Like the Muhammadans they wash their dead, cover the corpse with a white shroud and inter it with a prayer. Afterwards they kill a sheep and distribute its flesh among the poor. When a shroud is not procurable the Selaib is buried in a new deerskin frock. The characteristic feature of certain festivals of the Selaib, especially of circumcisions or weddings, is the planting of a wooden cross, draped with red cloth and topped with feathers, at the door of the tent where the ceremony takes place. This serves as general invitation to neigh- hours to collect and dance round the cross. From this apparently is derived their name (Saleeb=cross). They have a peculiar dance in which the man lightly kisses his female partner on the shoulder, but may not touch her waist or hand. (10) (11) (12) The political position of the Selaib appears to be one of semi-subordination to the Arabs. They wander among the Arabs and are friends with all tribes yet remain entirely distinct. The Arabs never intermarry with them. They take no part in Arab feuds, etc., and the tribes disdain to plunder them ;Bedouins, says Doughty, would not even rob a soli tary Sulabi of a valuable ostrich skin. They are too useful as guides and menials to be injured. They pay no tribute (so Felly says but Doughty says they pay a small tribute wherever they go) and the tribes scorn to borrow from them. The Selaib have a patron in every considerable tribe, to whom they appeal in case of necessity and the difficulty is then disposed of by mediation. They themselves never plunder. In camp they pitch apart from the Arabs. SELOO.—Two marches from Koweit on one of the routes to Katif. 8HAAYBAT.—First stage on one route from Koweit to Hasa. SHETNA (KHOR).— A somewhat confused description of this Khor will be found at page 678 of Bombay Records, Selection XXIV ; and the name Khor Shetana also occurs in the Admiralty Chart of the Mouth of the Euphrates, but so placed as not to afford any assistance. It is described as a branch of Khor Abdullah “ formed by Warba Island and the main, which continues navigable for large boats above Bussorah.” In Admiralty Chart No. 2371-28376, Persian Gulf (1903), a semi-conjectural Khor somewhat corresponding to the above description is shown ; but the still later survey of the Khors Abdullah and Emm Kasr by Kemp seems to show that no such Khor exists. What then is Khor Shetna ? Is it merely the northern channel bet ween Warba Island and the main; or is it identical with Khor Emm Kasr or Khor Zobeir? In 1903 the Vice-Consul, Basra, found a Khor some what corresponding with the semi-conjectural one mentioned above. SHIAIBA.—Small square fort on the Koweit coast, 5J miles south of Abu Halaifa. Inhabited by 10 families of Ejman tribe. Beach is sandy, but land ing at low water is difficult. In 1898 there was a young date-plantation and some water in wells; the people were herdsmen and cultivators. SHEG.—District immediately south of that called Adan by people of Koweit. It appears to be enclosed between southern part of the parallel ranges shown in Felly’s map as beginning from the Delaa-ed-Delaa and Delaa-el-Cheb- reet hills and running west and then north. The surface rises gently from the sea. SHEW AIK (BANDAR).—See under Kurein. SULABA.—See Selaib. YHAREB.—-The great mud-flat on which Failaka Island and the islet of Mashkan stand. It runs south-east from mouth of Khor Sabiya and forms protection on north and east to Koweit harbour. It is nearly 20 miles long and about 6 miles broad. TOOK.—See under Failaka Island. TOWEINA (BANDAR).—See under Koweit Bay. C912FD R65 UHA.—Small sandy islet near the tip of the reef which runs south-east from Failaka island. It is nearly 3 miles from the south-east corner of Failaka. U RE PL S’AN.—Name, according to Felly, of a route from Koweit to Riadh. It passes between Legait and the Gulf. WAERA.—Place shown in Kiepert’s Map, nearly 100 miles west by south of Koweit, on route between Basra and Zulfah. In some particulars it corres ponds with Hafr above. WARBA.—Island lying in mid-channel between north end of Bubiyan Island and the main. Around it meet the Khor Abdullah from the south-east, Khor-as-Sabiya from the south, and Khor Umm Kasr from the north-west. The island is 8 miles long east and west and shaped like a crescent with its concavity to the south. Its greatest breadth is over 2 miles. Depth of channel between it and mainland on north is 4 j to 6 fathoms. Channel between it and mainland on west is described as a ** boat*passage. No information as to southern channel separating it from Bubiyan Island, except in Admiralty Chart No. 2374)-2837-6, which indicates soundings of 4 to 10 fathoms. WARERA on WUBREH.—Locality between the Karain Khor and the Delaa-ed-Delaa. Felly calls it indifferently Warfra and Wubreh.l “ Map of Parts of Arabia and Persia M gives Wabrah. Pelly says this halting^ place is quite uninhabited and derives its name from the lands of Wubreh which lie a little to the eastward. WUBREH.—See Warfra above. ZOWAR.—See under Eailaka Island. «, 0. Pm*, 0412 V. . D.I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/366</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/366</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Part II: Geographical and descriptive materials, Section II: Western Side of the Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1904</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-14T01:33:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (138 folios)</extent><extent>A list of contents is given on the front cover and folio 3, with reference to the original pagination. Each sub-section is ordered alphabetically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 140; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume, marked confidential, is
                           Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Part II: Geographical and descriptive materials, Section II: Western Side of the Gulf, compiled by John Gordon Lorimer, and includes the printing statement 'G. C. Press, Simla - No. C-912 F. D. - 17.11.04 - 30 - J. D.'. The volume begins with notes from the author, dated 14 November 1904, and is then divided into five subsections, as follows:A - Trucial Chiefs' TerritoryB - Katar [Qatar]C - Bahrein [Bahrain]D - HasaE - Koweit [Kuwait]Each subsection, organised alphabetically by name, contains a variety of geographical information, including towns and villages, districts, physical geography, tribes and tribal sub-sections, wells, and forts.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Physical geography</topic></subject><subject><topic>Human geography</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>