<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023612307.0x000005_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:05:21.110Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">( Circular.) No. J8SZ of 1852. P olitical D epartment. V4 S ir, I am directed by the Right Hon'ble the Governor in Council to transmit, for your guidance, twelve copies of a Proclamation issued by Government, forbidding the immigration into the interior of Foreign Adventurers in search of Military service, more especially Arabs, Mukranees, Beloochees, Seiks, Rohillas, Puthans, and Affghans. 2. I am at the same time desired to request that you will submit, for the orders of Government in the Political Department, all applications for Pass ports hereafter made to you under this Proclamation. I have the honor to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, A. MALET, Chief Secretary. Bombay Castle ,7* September 1852., fy CH-n ■PROCLAMATION. Whereas the peace of Native States in the interior is endangered by the immigration of Foreign Adventurers seeking Military Service within those Territories, and the peace of the Districts of the British Government which are contiguous thereto is also liable to disturbance from the same cause : the Right Honorable the Governor in Council is pleased to forbid a passage through the Districts subordinate to the Presidency of Bombay to any Foreigner who maybe proceeding to the Territories of Native States in the inteiioi, without a Passport from the Senior Magistrate of Police in Bombay, or the Political or local Police Authority at the Port or Frontier Station by which he may enter the British jurisdiction ; and any such person attempting to violate this prohibition shall be arrested, and required to give satisfactory security to refrain from such attempts before he shall obtain his release fiom custody; failing which, he shall be sent back, to his own country. By order of the Right Hon'ble the Governor in Council, A. MALET, Chief Secretary. Bombay Castle, September l s 5i.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023612307.0x000005_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/129, ff 51-52</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023612307.0x000005</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/129, ff 51-52</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Circular No. 3882 of 1852 from Arthur Malet, Chief Secretary to the Government, Political Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1852/1852</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-02T00:24:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The circular is transmitting a proclamation prohibiting the immigration of 'foreign adventurers in search of military service' — that may be proceeding to 'Native States in the [Indian] interior — without a suitable passport. It further requests that all applications for passports are hereafter reported to the Bombay Government.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023612307.0x000005#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>