<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000236_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T05:49:35.627Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">AIR MINISTRY, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1. 1 st December, 1%9 ai/et C.37985/48/S.6 Dear Glipsham, I am sorry to find from your letter EST.1380/49 of 15th November, addressed to Crosthwait (whose place I have taken) that you have had‘no reply to your letter of May last about the proposal that an aircraft should be provided for the use of the Air Adviser to the U.K. High Commissioner in Karachi* I find on looking up the papers that it was decided some time ago that in existing circumstances apiiroval could not be given for the establishment of an aircraft for the use of the Air Adviser to the U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan and that the Air Adviser was informed officially to that effect on 19 th August ladt. Yours sincerely, (SGD) A. LAWSON P.R. CLIPSHAM ESQ., COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE, DOWNING STREET, S.W.1.C*iL —_ Bst.i3aoA9 u Oy mv, 1 ^ 9 . Soar CSrostiwait, «.“ i H. r ® f * r ! n ° e to 3 of your latter C.37^Aa/36 -i ^4^?* 40 ' a?oofc » ^ SlBgdoi iltgh fl—j— i—r in Paktetea has now aiggssted to us that it would be aoat r * quoat for “ aircraft be b * gir * B for citiii “ y° u slreect know fTon Bo«hamioll 'a report, the civil air 1 ^ ne Jollities available in 'Wkistan at 'resent leave a cL ac ! 1 ? a8tr,d * U ls » tlierefors, inadvisable for the High Ooanisaionar or neabers of hU staff to use the civil au* lines when travelling on duty in Pakistan, but this seriously affects their nobility in a country where other ° trails port are also not of a very high standard. Tho High Co-ieeioner, for cxanplc, ha. beei pr^nSTS* visiti^ either the Seat Punjab or the horth ,;eet irontier rovinoe this year because ofachannel'e veto on the us# of either of the t*o civil air linos. m do riot consider that thsrs is need st ^rssent for the ? r0lri ??‘ On ^ aircr * ft for ^ ««« of the High Oosnissioner f* 1 a * b** airead y done for the High Uwaissiowr iri Irdia, but it would be of the greatest assistance if t ere ^ P * ia * t * a which ° 0 « i d «ad« available upon of the High ot *“ ib8i ° n ^ “V“- , ** •hould therefore be grateful if the possibility of a service aircraft being used in this way night be borne'in mind when the question of providing an aircraft for the Air Adviser is being considered. f*L. CHOSmtAIT, £3Q. # AIR MIKISlttT. Yours sincerely, - Ccj Pfufl w.= EX Tel. No. S219 abbey 3411 , Ext r: C.37985/AB/3.6 Dear Crook, AIR MINISTRY WHITdHA r * Thank you for your letter Pol. Sxt. 6727/49 of 22nd April. 9 t enclose two copies of the Directive that has been issued to the Air Advisor to the High Comissaoner for the U.K. in Pakistan. 3 . 4 ? re A^^sor^siletter 6 Not jt^of^ the^n^Apri^and^a. 6 ^ copy^of^the^reply that is sent will be forwarded to you. 4-v,t a t (attsr and its enclosure k. I am sending a copy of this letter ana to* the recipients of your lette '• K.R. Crook, Esq.,Tel. : Abbey 3411. Extn Correspondent on the subject of this letter shoijkf be addressed to :— The yuDER Secretary of State, Air Ministry, £ and should quote the reference :— AIR MINISTRY, \ /HI S&amp;U7 LQNDON, 4 AV.I. Your ref. C. 37985 A 8 /D # D # Polioy (A.S # ) 2 # / 65 V May, 1949 Sir I an directed to forward the enclosed Directive to you in your capacity as the Air Force Adviser to the United Kingdom High Conmissioner in Pakistan with regard to your responsibilities in connection with R#A,F. personnel in Afghanistan. Wg.Cdr. P»A, McWhannell, R.A.F* , Office of the High Commissioner for the United Kingdom, Chamber of Commerce Building, Wood Street, Karachi, Pakistan* I am. Sir Your obedient Servant, » ■ :I c- A 6987 R.A.F, PERSONNEL IN AFGHANISTAN Res pon s ibi lities of tho_Air Advisert^ t he U, K, Hi gh Conaniss ioner in Pakistan, Introduction 1. The Military Attache, Kabul, will continue to be responsible for the administration, discipline and welfare of R.A.F* personnel in Afghanistan. 2. It is desirable, however, that the R.A.F. personnel in Afghanistan shall be able to discuss with and seek the guidance of a senior R.A.F. officer on technical problems affecting the instruction given by them to the Royal Afghan Air Force* It is also desirable that such a senior officer shall be available to report to the Air Ministry on the technical and personal efficiency of R.A.F, personnel after they have arrived in Afghanistan. 3. It has therefore been decided, with the agreement of the High Commissioner for the United Kingdom, Pakistan, that the Air Adviser to the High Commissioner shall pay visits to Kabul for this purpose. Frequ ency of Visit s 4. Such visits are to be made at intervals of not more than 6 months. The duration of each visit and the intervals between such visits are, however, to be arranged so as to interfere as little as possible with this officer's primary duties as Air Adviser to the High Commissioner. Responsibility of Air Adviser 5, Matters of administration, discipline and welfare will remain the responsibility of the Military Attache, Kabul, Matters in this field v/hich come to the notice of the Air Adviser during his visits are to be referred by him to the Military Attache, Kabul. 6, The Air Adviser will give the R.A.F, personnel in Afghanistan any necessary guidance on technical problems in connection with their duties as instructors to the Royal Afghan Air Force, 7* The Military Attache will, in consultation with the Air Adviser, make any necessary approaches to the Afghan Air Force authorities in connection with the instruction given by the R.A.F. personnel to Royal Afghan Air Force personnel. 8. The Air Adviser will render a report to the Air Ministry (D.D.A.F.L.) after each visit, A copy of this report will be forwarded to the Military Attache, Kabul.(352^1) Wt.46030/47 30,000 3/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 / C.R.O. Parly. U.S. of S. Seer clary of State DRAFT LETTER. D.L. CROSTH//AIT, ESQ., AIR MINISTOY, WHITEHALL, S.W.1. Further action. Copy to: Foreign Office. (Mr. Hibuert) Ministry of Defence. (Lt.Col. Waterfield) War Office, M. 1.2. (Lt.Coli Tarver). (File Mo. ^ 7 27 / 49 ^ 2 2 APR 194 c Dear Crosthwait, Please refer to Walsh Atkins letter No.Pol.Ext.6164/49 of 3rd February, about supervision of R.A.F. personnel in Afghanistan by the Air Adviser to our High Commissioner in Karachi and to your undated reply reference C.37985/48/S.6. The terms of the draft directive to be sent to the Air Adviser have now been agreed by the High Commissioner in Karachi; enclosed is a copy of his Savingram No.62 of 1st April. You will see that the High Commissioner supports the request contained in the Air Adviser's letter No.379 of 2nd April, to Air Ministiy (D.D.0.2) for provisionof a coma unications aircraft. No doubt you will do everything poasibie to assist in this matter and let us know what is decided as we should like to reply to the High Coamissioner in due course. 2. Enclosed also is a draft of the directive, incorporating the agreed amendments. With reference to Blackham's letter to Walsh Atkins No. (F.2762/1223/97) of 1st March, copy of which was sent to you^ UPe have, with the agreement of the Foreign Office, amended the first sentence of paragraph 4 of the directive to read 'such visits are to be made at intervals of not more than six months”, as this seems to express more clearly the views of H.M. Ambassador in Kabul. 3. Copies of tnis letter with enclosures are going to Hibbert, Foreign Office,t; 'jr r* r * ^ i T Despatch No. 198 (379) ■*!***» fetr.i-'ts The High Commissioner for the United Kingdom in Pakistan presents his compliments to Cc«nanwealth Relations Office, Whitehall, London,S.W.1. honour to transmit herewith a copy of the undermentioned paper. Description - Ref Savingram No* 62 dated 2J+/2/k9 Subject Cccmuni cat ions Aircraft for Air Adviser to the U.K#High Coramissioner in Pakistan*SECRET OFFICE OF TFtE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR THE UNITED KINGDOM CHAMBER OR COMMERCE BUILDlMC WOOD STREET Ref No. 579 ras&amp;rs n 2nd April, 19V9. Sir, OamnipioaUonE Aircraft for Air Adviser to to Pakistan ~ I have the honour to request that a Conmunication Aircraft may be provided for the above appointment. 2. In a draft directive received through G.ILO. setting out responsibilities oi the Air Mviser to the U.K. Hig^i Commissioner in Pakistan in respect of R.A.F. personnel in Afghanistan, it is stated that visits are to be to i^)ul at approximately 3 monthly intervals. In previous correspondence on tiiis proposed additional duty, the High Commissioner has stressed the fact that an aircraft should be provided for the Air Adviser in order to minimise periods of absence from Karachi. On 28th December, 1948, in a Savingram to C.R«C. the High Commissioner used the words 'and I foresee much difficulty in finding suitable dates for him (Air Adviser) to make these visits unless aai until air travel becomes possible'. 3* In respect of the recommendations of the High Ccranissioner I would like the following points to be considered, concerning this appointment as a whole, nn support of the provision of a oom.mnications aircraft together with one member of the aircrew to act as assistant to this appointment. (*) Travelling facilities - Pakistan - Air (i) Air Lines* In my opinion neither of the two airlines in Pakistan offers an adequate safety factor at present. Pak Air Ltd whic h ha s arisen from ignorant planning had a fatal accident in November, \%8 P the suspected cause of which is inadequate maintenance. Diia Company, which suspended its services for 2 months after the accident, is operated by an American Charter Company for Pak Air Ltd and its personnel do not inspire confidence. Orient Airways is scraping the bottom of the pot for spares, and I hear from confidential sources that the condition of its aircraft are well below our standards. Hiis Company is at present suffering interruptions to its schedules throu^i unservioeability and i Jfaot cannot state viiat routes it will be operating a few days ahead. (ii) Aircraft qf U.S.A. Air Attache. By courtesy of the U.S.A. Air Attache I can travel with him on tour in his aircraft when space permits. Vfy visit to Kabul in November, 1948 was made possible by receiving a lift from him to Peshawar, and return to Karachi, when he carried out a visit to Kabul. / (iii) R.P.A.F Bie Under Secretary of State (D.D.0.2), Air Ministry, King sway, London, V.C.2.HflHl - 2 - (iii) RjPjAsP. Trips may be made as passenger in R*X«A*F* aircraft but these ad noc flight# are seldom suitable, and in many oases of delivery lights a return flight to Karachi is not available. The Air Ccranander R.P.A.F. in comparing the U.S. Air Attache's mobility with my own has, however, offered his cooperation in this matter, but of course cannot guarantee schedules to fit in with my requirements. (b) Bail Travel - Pakistan. This is slow and dirty and, as one has no choice of travelling companions, in many cases unhygienic as all Pakistanis do not conform to European standards of hygiene. Another murder took place in a 1 st Class compartment on a main line train last week, with robbery the motive, and, although the victim was a female nurse, the safety standards are unassuring. 4* Duties of Air Adviser (a) Although the R.P.A.F. is there have been in the past continual changes in organisation and policy, also many problems affecting the large numbers of R.A.F. volunteers in the H.P.A.F. which causes work out of proportion tomthe sise of the R.P.A.F. The existence of the R.A.F. Staging Post at Mauripur also causes its own peculiar type of problem. (b) Civil aviation in Pakistan appears to be in a mess at present and investigations in progress are threatening to involve several British personnel (mostly ex-R.A*F. )• Ihe High fcranission now has the part time services of a Civil Air Adviser but, as he is available in Karachi about one week in four and as I am acquainted with most of the parties concerned and the peculiar history of civil aviation in Pakistan, 1 find that I have to spend considerable time on this aspect of Civil aviation. I have in the last two months attended various magistrates courts nine times - (Stack and Adam Smith cases) — and since January 1 st 1 have had visitors or have made visits over fifty times in connection with this unhappy state of affairs. This is of course abnormal, but it is recorded as an example of unpredictable commitments. (o) Ass embling data for reports to Air Ministry, drafting and issue, goes on continuously throughout the quarter. It is impossible to assess the exact time which would be involved in compiling a report unhindered by other commitments. My report up to 31st December, 194$ issued from this office on 8th February, 194-9 owing to various interruptions e.g., 'Hospitalisation for R.A.F. volunteers with R.P.A.F.' which necessitated numerous visits and interviews, and the Civil Aviation tangle which arose in this period etc.* Only one typist in this office can carry out the typing of these reports. As she also deals with similarly classified typing for the whole of the High Conmission, excluding Military Adviser's Branch, this necessitates on many occasions my personal typing of drafts and minutes. The Military Adviser allows me the use of his clerks when they are available. (d) Beading C.R.O. and other intelligence reports takes a considerable part of each day and is an essential part of this duty. In this post considerable time is spent on small matters with a service angle which cannot be dealt with by the civil pool clerical staff and so require my personal attention; also, when a matter arises which requires prompt attention, routine matters have to be shelved for indefinite periods with consequent wastage in time in picking up the threads after such interruption. Many of these matters could be dealt or progressed by, a junior officer. By comparison, the Military Adviser to this High Commission has a personal service staff of one captain and two B.O.R's, and the U.S. Air Attache (whose mobility has been compared to mine by the Air Commander R.P.A.F.) has &amp; considerable servi&lt;:sL . ^ / staff plusstaff plus an aircraft and aircrew* These people are therefore able to delegate minor duties to their staff and are able to go on tour leaving behind personnel to progress ordinary routine matters, and thfir have this additional help in clearing up accumulations of work which occur whilst on tour* ^5* This note on duties is included to demonstrate that there is not the leisure in this appointment to permit me to reconmend the assumption of further duties in respect of quarterly (approximately) visits to KABUL unless some form of assistance is forthcoming to enable me to carry out this additional duty effectively* In my opinion the most practical form of assistance would be in the provision of a personal communication aircraft vdiich would not only reduce time spent in travelling but would permit my own required schedules to be observed and also allow ad hoc visits to be carried out when conditions are favourable in this office; one menber of the aircrew could act as assistant to me in this office in minor service matters, the incidence of which in the Pakistan oocrdtment alone tends to submerge the major issues* Without this assistance, the aircraft aide of which has always been stressed by the High Commissioner, I cannot see that the Afghanistan ocmmitznent can be added to this post without the risk of serious interruption to my present duties* Suggestions regarding the most economical use of such an aircraft are at Appendix 'A'* 6* The terms of this letter have been approved by the High Commissioner. I have the honour to be, Sir, lour obedient Servant, (P.A. MclHANNELL).Appendix 'A ' TICKS FOR TW B3TABLISHMERT THB USE OP THE AIR OF A OOMMUNI CATIONS THE HIGH C0?1?!ISoI0iiER IN PAKISTAN Mmm ™67^T For the use of the Air Adviser in connection with his duties in Pakistan and Afghanistan* J Posable additional use* On disestablishment of communications ftigiii at R*A.F. Staging Post, Mauripur, this aircraft could be used for the purpose of providing flying practice for any G-.D* laembers on the strength of the Staging Post and thus serve &amp; dual purpose* UTILISATION Estimated average use of the aircraft by Air Adviser* •• 15 * 18 hours per month* MAINTENANCE Maintained by R*A*F* Staging Post, Mauripur* It has been agreed by the Officer Coonaoding that this could be done without increase to his establiefoient* AIRCREW Wireless operator, and navigator or second pilot* The navigator or second pilot could be employed as assistant to the Air Adviser in the office uf the High Comnisaion* The wireless operator could possibly be employed by the Staging Post when not engaged in flying* RANGE OF ■CiaCR.gT Principal distances are as follows Karachi Karachi Karachi Lauox*e *•* ••• *•• Lahore via Multan ••• *•* Peshawar via Multan ** ••• Multan *«• ••• **• * 660 s*iailes« 665 Sesiles* 750 a*miles« 465 s*miles* N*B* MULTAN is a civil aerodrome on the main routes where refueling facilities are available^ Peshawar - Kabul *•* 150 s*miles* No refuelling at Kabul 0 AJDMINISTR a JXON T ransport * The Air Adviser is provided with a car* As this car would be required for t6nsporting the assistant Air Adviser on various duties about Karachi a driver would be required&lt;, Wages for a locally engaged driver are about Rs 110 per month (g 8 - 5 - 0)* ApooBnodation* This is a major problem in Karadii but suitable aocomnodation (Hotel; could be found for an unaccompanied Junior officer at about £ 1 - 7 - 8 per day* This officer, if acting as assistant to Air Adviser should live in Karachi; the wireless operator could be accommodated at Staging Post, Mauripur e5 £&gt; SAVINGRAM c aoV Vou ^ 6727 Prom;- The High Commissioner for the United Kingdom ir*h Pakistan, Karachi, jq ]Q** ' ! t sJ -} To 2 - ^.No. 62. SECRET Commonwealth Relations Office Saving . fcf- ^ 1st April, 1949. yoy£. Ho»„6 2_ Savi ng date d 24 February; supervision of R.A.P. in Afghanistan by Air Adviser. My only comment on the draft directive from Air Ministry is on para 4. The last sentence of this paragraph makes clear' that my Air Adviser^ duties here take priority, but I feel that the wish of Air Ministry that he should visit Kabul at approximately three monthly intervals cannot be fulfilled even under normal conditions, unless he has the use of his own air transport, not only to reduce travelling time, but also to enable him to take full advantage of any temporary lulls in his work in Pakistan. 2. Present conditions here are, I hope, abnormal. In addition to liaison with R.P.A.P. and R.A.P. Staging Post work (which is considerable) Pakistan Civil aviation is in a critical state and a major police investigation into matters connected there-with is being carried out. This gives my Air Adviser much heavy extra work since Civil Air Advisees visits from Delhi are relatively infrequent. Air Adviser reports that this pressure of work, in the absence of any service assistant, is adversely affecting the progress of his routine work in connection with the R.P.A.P. With so much going on that has arisen since issue of my 252 Saving dated 28th December, I find it most difficult to foresee when my Air Adviser will be able to carry out his next visit to Kabul without undue interruption to his duties here. 3. I am anxious to help in this matter and I see no objection to the terms of the draft Directive. But I am equally anxious that Air Ministry should fully appreciate the difficulties which I foresee in meeting their wishes over frequency of visits even under normal conditions, unless aircraft is provided. I think this essential and recommend that one member of the aircrew should act also as assistant to Air Adviser. 4. Air Adviser has now submitted to Air Ministry his request for an aircraft, copy is being sent to you.(35201) Wt.46030/47 30,000 3/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 (FUe No...'lov C.R.O. Mr* Crook, A A? Patly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State DRAFT rRAM United Kingdom High Comnissioner J in Pakistan. Further action. fiodC^c Air Ministry, I'r.'lV.L. Crosthwaite, Foreign Office, Mri Hibbert. Mi/istry of Defenc( Col.Waterfiel&lt; /ar Office, M, t f .0 Printing. SECFffiT / Addressed UKC0M Karachi No. A telegram No#62 Saving of 44th February. Supervision of H.A.F. in Afghanistan by your Air AdviserI io rwply roociivo^r We h^ve been Considering advisability/of lotting this propoeal into effect at present tim/, and should \e grateful for your views/ We are particularly anxious not to do anything which Government o\ Pakistan might consider to be against their interest, but/on other hand, v/e have commitments\to Afgh^/s in regard to training of air pd^sonpfel* and have been careful to/avoid any sugges\/on that we might contemplate withdrawing from ^he^. On whole, we are inclined to thirfk that\as Air Adviserb activities inr Kabul are \o be limited to supervisioj/ of discipline,Velfare and administ/ation of R.A.F. personnel, we should proceed as originally intended.\ If you agree, will/you please let us have as soo\ as possible, coqpnents on draft instructions to beVsent to Air Aihrrs'er. 2. We note from paragraph 5 of your Savingram No.252 of 28 th December, that you have nttifi od pTr/posal to g/er If vi.ser t.n Kabi)3^^. Government of Pakistan of Ait.n Kchni T 'A/Yas repljr ever reoeived? would he..hatter nnt to do-so. be- L- &gt;A—&lt;- A x'U- 6-/1 U- cl± £&lt;/ &lt; rA.fw&lt;n A (? 2762 / 1223 / 97 ) CONFIDENTIAL L- 6 l 0) FORNIffN ’OFfTtCE, S.W. 1 . 1st M^rch, 1949 . I s .4 &gt; &gt; vV 645 I UJD Dear Walsh /Atkins, 4 j !' &lt;Q j ^ ' v\ » Please refer to CrosthwaiVs letter of the’ 21st January (G.379S5/S.6), addressed to you, of which a copy was sent to Ledwidge, forwarding a draft directive for the Air Adviser, Karachi, in connexion with his responsibility for supervising R.A.F. personnel attached to the Afghan Air Force, 2, We referred this draft, on which v/e have no comments ourselves, to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Kabul for observations. His only comment is that it would be sufficient for the first sentence of paragraph 4 to read: ' made at not less than six monthly intervals”, 3* I am copying this letter to Crosthwait, Waterfield at the Ministry of Defence and Lieutenant- Colonel Tarver, M.I,2.at the War Office, Yours sincerely, (R.C. Blackham) L.B, Walsh Atkins, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office. h /?' jr'* ?(968® 1 ) Wt.4flO30, 1 t7 30.000 3/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Up.685 C.R.O. ivr.R....Walsh-At.ld r .na 3 . 3 / 1 . Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State DRAFT SAVTNGRAM PROM C.R.O. TO U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER, KARACHI. Your telegram No. 252 Saving dated 28th December; supervision of R.A.F. in Afghanistan by your Air Adviser. Please be assuved Ural 'fche difficulty of which you run some risk by agreeing to the proposed arrangement, so long as your Air Adviser ¥«m±&amp;. have to travel by surface route, is fully appreciated here an! will of course be kept in mind. We are most grateful to you for your agreement, despite this dlffioulty, to the arrangement prooosed^which is, we feel, the best that can be devised in the general interest for the time being. Attached is a draft of the instructions proposed to be issued by the Air Ministry to your Air Adviser in this regard. We should be grateful for your concurrence in them or any comments you may wish to put forward.. Printing.This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message an&lt;f unless it is marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if commun icated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex must be in a One Time System. Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ALLOTTED TO FINANCE &amp; ECONOMIC DEPARTMENT D«I CYPHER(TYPEX) FROM : U«K* HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN D # Karachi, 18*15 hours, 17th Fehruary, 1949 15#00 hours, 17th February, 1949 IMPORTANT No# 248 TOP SECRET Your telegram No* 168 January 22nd: Air Service to Kabul* When presenting to Pakistan Prime Minister this morning memorandum enclosed in your despatch No* 1 January 29th I asked him whether Pakistan Government considered opening a scheduled air service to Kabul* I explained to him how unwise this seemed to be, putting arguments provided in your first paragraph against general background of U*K*/U*S* memorandum on civil aviation policy towards Russian satellite States* 2* Mr.Liaqat Ali Khan said he did not know of any intention of opening such a service to Kabul but he remarked that in the present somewhat troubled state of Pakistan/Afghanistan relations it would be difficult and delicate for Pakistan Government to refuse an Afghan request to open an air service if this was made* I pointed out that Afghanistan lias no civil air organisation at present and was unlikely to take the initiative in proposing a scheduled service, 3# Pakistan Prime Minister appeared to accept arguments advanced against establishment of this connection but he gave 9 no formal undertakings on the subject. 4# As your telegram under reference was not repeated to Kabul I am not repeating this either. Copies to : C,R.0*(b) Mr*Walsh Atkins Brig, Barker ' Mr.Tims Foreign Office Mr.James Murray M*C,A, Mr#I.Lawton Reg. Tels (20)C8M«1) Wt.46040/47 30,000 3;43 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 (File No...^ 0 ^ * ( ) 616 4/1 ^9 C.R.O. ^...Wa^h^tkin^ 3.3/J- DRAFT LETTER T.L. GROSTHWAIT, ESQ., AIR MINISTRY, WHITEHAI^, S.W. 1. ^0 GONPIDETJTIAL. Thank you for your letter No. C. 37985 /S .6 of 21st January about the supervision of R.A.P. personnel in Afghanistan by the Air Adviser to our High Commissioner in Pakistan. We agree generally with tha-tepmo of- the draft instructions to the Air Adviser, subject to alteration of paragraph 3, to read:- *It has, therefore, been decided with the agreement of the High Commissioner for the United Pvingdom in Pakistan that the Air Adviser to the High Commissioner shall pay visits to Kabul for this purpose', 2 . But, particularly^ in view of the genuine difficulty which the High Commissioner is risking , . fo by agreeing his arrangement, we should like to Further action. L%h-^ cei’(C.^£t*.U • f'o no. /t. fifty- oh'ft- 4 . 0 . r 2 - 3 ttB ^ refer the instructions to him in draft before they are issued and before doing so should be glad to •know uifhetheag^the Foreigi Office or the War Office have any- further comments^ Subject to any such comments our reference to the High Commissioner would be as in the draft attached. tU. tv.i4.njC 5 I5 e are inelinoa to think that it would be more appropriate for the instructions to the Air Adviser to be issued by the Air Ministry rather than by this Office. Do you agree? ^ I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosure to Ledwidge at the Foreign Office, Wat erf i eld at the Ministry of Defence and Tarver of War Office, M.I.2. who, I believe, may wish similarly to send the instructions in draft to the Military Attache 7 at Kabul.Tel. fCa C. 37985 /S EY 3411, Ext. 55 It* * , 6164 MINISTRY, ■ WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l 5)lst Jamary, 1949 confidential A* Dear Waleh- Atkins Tl^te Hig nmi- 2 f«ioner for Pakistan has. as you are^ aware, agreed that his Adviser should undertake the supervision of the R.A.F* personne- attached to the Afghan Air Force in Kabul. draft that we think covers what is required of its enclosure to Ledwidge at the Foreign Office, Waterfield at the Ministry of Defence, and to Lieutenant-Colonel Tarver, M. 1*2 at the Far Office* I suggest that they should send any amendments that they consider necessary to you direct. You will no doubt wish to issue formal him. 3 . I am sending conies of this letter and Yours sincerely. L.B. Walsh-Atkins, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, S. W. 1.EX l' tr DRAFT ! 6164 R»A.F» Personnel In Afghanistan Responsibilities of the Air Adviser to the U»K» Hl&amp;h Commissioner in Pakistan Introduction 1. -It has- been-decided that an Air Attache—eennot Military Attache, Kabul, -sha-XI continue to be responsible for the administration, discipline and welfare of R*A.F* personnel in Afghanistan,, personnel in Afghanistan shall be able to discuss with and seek the guidance of a senior R*A*F* officer on technical problems affecting the instruction given by them to the Royal Afghan Air Force# It is also desirable that such a senior officer shall be available to report to the Air Ministry on the technical and personal efficiency of R.a.F* personnel after they have arrived in Afghanistan., ■ (UcidUA. t It has therefore been .aggiefr^that the Air Adviser to the High Commissioner in PafeAotftii shall pay visits to Kabul for this purpose. Frequency of Visits 4. Such visits are^to bq, made a£-»appr€&gt;ximatoly Zr ojg Cy~ /U- 'fL.c—- &amp;&gt; *—&amp;&lt;•£*** monthly^jLintervals^ The duration of each visit and the intervals between such visits are, however, to be arranged so as to interfere as little as possible with this officer f s primary duties as Air Adviser to the High welfare will remain the responsibility of the Military Attache, Kabul* Matters in this field which come to the It is desirable, however, that the R.A*F. Responsibility of Air Adviser 5. Matters of administration, discipline and Commissioner* /noticenotice of the Air Adviser during his visits are to be referred by him to the Military Attache, Kabul* 6 # The Air Adviser will give the R.AJ?* personnel in Afghanistan any necessary guidance on technical problems in connection with their duties as instructors to the Royal Afghan Air Force* 7. The Military Attache will, in consultation with the Air Adviser, make any necessary approaches to the Afghan Air Force authorities in connection with the instruction given by the R*A*F* personnel to Royal Afghan Air Force personnel. 8. The Air Adviser will render a report to the Air Ministry (B.D.A.F.L.) after each visit* A copy of this report will be forwarded to the Military Attache, Kabul*I' m ( H/l0/3 2A8) ‘ Extract from Letter from the British Embassy, Kabul to The l-?i4it Honourable Ernest ^evin, dated llith Deceiiiberi 19^8 , * * * * * Last week His Ivigesty inspected the new Avro XIX aeroplanes which have arrived from ISngland and the hangars which are being erected to accommodate them, and at the close of the interview he expressed to me his great satisfaction with the planes themselves and with the team of British instructors who are training the Afghans in their use, as also with the hangars which are being erected under the supervision of a British engineer.— mmmm ■I IHI o i BRITISH EL34SSY K k B U L (C/20/20/48) INe «Xe 0 ^ Becanber, 1948 H , r T -&gt;T3 , i7i /■V loOtO (i x &gt; 078 ' ?f,t &gt;• . -- - ’ ^ i34« I l ^nr C / Ple ^ se rQfer to your secret letter No. N. 149o5/108/a ox November the 18th, on the subject of plans xor the expansion ot' the Afghan ^ir x’orco. I do not think that 7:e need take the situation uoo^ seriously. Pi^ior to august, 1947, the uhole of our assistance to the Afghan Government in mil1tar3 r and air lorce matters v:as tho joint concern of His Najest / 's Government an_ the former Government of India' and’prac- corres P° n ^ n 9^ was addressed to both London ~aia .js-aii. from the oint of view of Afghanistan the cnanged situation does not appear so complete as it lias ^een in fact. Afghan military officers, whom the Afghan Government previously sent abroad for traininc, are still being sent to the United Kingdom, India and Pams ^.an, trxe only difference being that the Afghans have now to correspond on the subject with three Smbassies instead of with one. In air force matters the situation is alien one same. ^e still discuss certain matters regarding training and most matters regarding transport -aciliuies xor the Afghan air force with Pakistan, and I see no particular harm in the Afghans knowing that Pak- ■fv^ a ?u ar ? a I /a r e oP the air Ministry's proposals for the training of the Afghan Air force, more especially splice uhese orig’inated with us and not with the Afghans. . . The Afghans Imow that there is still close our ^ h f ee Embassies in Kabul, and it seems to me that it would be perfectly natural for our military attacne to keep both Dominion Embassies *eneralf r informed^as to our interests in Afghan military and air xorceaflairs. This will be easier if and when t e Pakistan Government appoint a Military Attache to their Kama Embassy. The Indians have of course had one for soir e t_me and Premergast is in close touch with nin. P.f. Grey, Esq., foreign Office, LO. DON.a~T S/j~A - A V • t -« , w r iNDCXED SAVINGRAK '“ j T 0 :349 * . srri— — ^ KARACHI. /V To:- The Commonwealth Relations Office, LONDON. No.: 252 Saving 28th December, 1948. 2/°c_ . S EC RET. y c « 7 w v /rr t - : # U +*&lt;&gt;l&lt;vC^) W^c ~ 9 Ok / VvO ***^4+' \ W* Your Savingram No. 231 of 29th November. Supervision of RAF in Afghanistan by my Air Adviser. ^ 2. My Air Adviser is preparing case for submission to Ministry requesting provision of an aircraft for his use, to be kept and ser viced at RAF Staging Post, Ma-uripur. Such aircraft would be '^tate Aircraft” within the meaning of Article 3(b) of the Chicago Conven tion and would therefore not be governed by Article 9 of the Conven tion. On the basis of purely informal discussions with officials of Ministries of Defence and Foreign Affairs, my Air Adviser considers that there should be no difficulty in obtaining authorisation for individual flights to Kabul under Article 3(c). 3. Aircraft supplied for my own use would of course attract Article 9 of the Convention. Civil Air Adviser nevertheless considers that it would be possible to secure ad hoc pormission for 3—4 flights to Kabul in a year, though permission for a regular courier service would probably not be granted and I should be reluctant to embarrass Pakistan Government by seeking it. 4. For the present, however, the question of permission is academic, since no aircraft, either civil or military, is available; and I am bound to emphasise that a visit to Kabul by surface trans port would involve my Air Adviser in absence from Karachi for a con siderable period, since eight days would normally be required for travelling alone. The Air Adviser plays a pivotal role in our dis cussions of emergency procedure, and I foresee much difficulty in finding suitable dates forhim to make these visits unless and until air travel becomes possible. However, I am anxious to help as far as I can and I agree to the proposed arrangement on the understanding that this difficulty is appreciated, as I am sure it is. 5. I am arranging to inform the Pakistan authorities in accor dance with your last paragraph. RMKS/AHCYi/6.A.M. Form 1700 FRQvl: “ ' M (*19961—17871) Wt. 10717—0442 jom 3/48 T^. 700 *20279—17871) Wt. 23129—O1325 15011 9/48 T.S. 700 CYPHER MESSAGE WARNING.—This cypher message must first be paraphrased if it is necessary to publish its text or to communicate it to persons outside British or United States Government Services and Departments. Messages marked ‘'One-Time Pad ” or “O.T.P.” are excepted from this rule. h * APX.6384 (Dosp. Registry Telegrams. 6th December, 194-8). AIR HENISTKT L(TIT)ON. 1/HLITARY ATTACH KABUL. U.K. HIGH CaMISSKMfJR IN PAKISTAN.. SHCRET. ROUTINE. APX.638A- 6th December, 1948. 1. Subject is contracts and salaries for R.A.P.personnel. 2. Reference your letter D0.409/A/KA dated 3rd November, 1 948 and Air Adviser High Commissioner Pakistan telegram Number 1474 dated 1st December,1948. Contracts being forwarded by next bag. 3. In covering letter we are asking you to approach the Afghan Government to increase pay of R.A.F. personnel to the following:- Squadron Leader Reid £1830 per annum ' Woolley £1850 ' ' Warrant Officer Blyth £1400 ' ' Plight Sergeant Orboll £1300 ' ' Sergeant Hammond £1100 ' ' /l / / / UI 4. You will appreciate that these rates of pay involve fairly substantial increases on the present salaries and that it will need delicate handling to obtain Afghan Agreement•You should therefore when the contract are received consult H.M. Ambassador on tactics before making any approach to Afghan authorities. 5. -Detailed points regarding the contract sare contained in covering letter. Time of origin: 061015 COPIES TO: A.F.L.4#(GRIG). Foreign Office, S.E. Asia. Department (Mr. Ledwitch)(2 copies Commonwealth Relations Offica.) (Mr. Welsh Atkins)(2 copi Monsage Control, War Office for D.K.1. (2 copies). FILE. 35996 refers. K Note.—In the Interests of economy, both sides of this sheet should be used.OUTWARD SAVING TELEGRAM FROM COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE (BY AIR MAIL) POLITICAL ( EXTERNAL 1 DKPAPTWCTJT POL. EXT. 17607/U8. LIST. II. v7 I '2- TO: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN. (SENT 29th November, 1948). No. 2 7 i1 SAVING. SECRET Your telegram No. 474 Gated 6th May and paragraphs 29 to 31 of report by Wing Commander Griffiths on his subsequent visit to Afghanistan: supervision of R.A.P. in Afghanistan by your Air Adviser. We have delayed further action on this, pending the disposal of a matter referred to in Laithwaite*s top secret letter to you No. Pol. Ext. 17406/48 dated 28th October. We should hov/ever now like, if you see no objection, to set on foot arrangement under which your Air Adviser, while not formally accredited (at least at present) as Air Attache at Kabul, would include in his responsibilities supervision of R.A.P. matters in Afghanistan as desired by Air Ministry. This would entail probably not more than three or four brief visits a year to Kabul. 2. We appreciate that such an arrangement might possibly entail some inconvenience for you if Air Adviser could not fly to and fro direct. As regards provision of aircraft, see correspondence resting with Burnett’s letter to Field No. 392 of 31st August. As regards direct flights, U.K. Ambassador, Kabul, reported on 23rd September that Americans had encountered refusal by Pakistan to permit regular courier air service across the frontier. We would not wish to. exclude possibility that Pakistan might be willing to permit occasional flights by representative of Commonwealth Country, especially for the /purposepurpose in mind# But it would doubtless be unwise to try to r work to this too early. 3» We hope, however, that even if, for. either or both these reasons, Air Adviser could not at present fly direct, you will feel able to agree to proposed arrangement having regard to infrequency and shortness of visits contemplated,and to the ' difficulty of making any other arrangement. 4* If you agree, you may wish to take some suitable opportunity of apprising Pakistan authorities informally of the arrangement proposed against back-ground of the subject of Laithwaite f s letter under reference. Copy to:- C.R.O, Foreign Office Air Ministry u it Ministry of Defence Mr. Field. Mr. B.J, Ledwidge. Mr, T.L. Qrosthwait. Reg. Tels. (4)# Lieutenant Colonel Waterfield.¥ 158 ^ r' v «i 'C (35291) Wt. 40030/47 30,00g 3/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 C.R.O. Mr. 7alsh Atkins. j- Parly. US. of S. Secretary of State DRAFT SAVTIIG- TEI^GRA^ United Kingdom High Commissioner Karachi • \ajO Further action. Distribution If i'r. ■Pfi' 1 »■ syr ^ Foreign Offic&lt; Mr. T.L. CrostFv;ai1^, Air Ministry, S*6. Lieutenant Colonel V/aterfieloi, Ministry/of Defence. C.R.O*, l(ing Charles Jtreei Mr. Field .&gt; c. Printing, ^948 ? xe l (File No Iol. fe-XV.r. SECRET Your telegram No* 474 dated 6th Llay said paragraphs 29 to 31 of report by Yfing Commander Griffiths on his subsequent visit to Afghanistan: supervision of R.A.F. in Afghanistan by your Air Adviser. Y/e have delayed further' action on this, pending the disposal of a matter referred to in Laithv/aite* s top secret letter to* you No.Pol.Ext.17406/48 dated 28th October. Y/e should however now like)to set on foot arrangement under v/hich your Air Adviser, /cot* while.^formally accreditedj^at least at present^ as Air Attache at Kabul, would include in his responsibilities^ supervision of R.A.F. toatters in Afghanistan as desired ^ *# by Air Ministry. This would entail - probably not more thap. or t'rvji brief a. visits to Kabul. 2. ,/e appreciate that -such an arrangement might possibly entail some inconvenience for ydu if Air Adviser could not fly to and fro direct. As regards provision of aircraft, see correspondence resting with Burnett's letter to Field No.392 of 31st August. As regards direct flights, U.K. Ambassador, Kabul, reported on 23rd September that Americans had encountered refusal by Pakistan to permit regular courier air service across the frontier.ZxcCcuitL Wel4*- not possibility that Pakistan might be ’.Tilling to permit occasional flights by representative of Conanonwealth Country^ especially for the purpose in mind^f our action with-Gawthogn hn r i h-v 1 ^’ij But it would doubt less be unwise to try to work to this too early. 3. We hope, however, that even if for either or both these reasons, Air Adviser could not at present fly direct, you will .feel, able to agree to proposed arrangement having regard to infrequency and shortnes-s of visits contemplated, fNCvCint- V CN-CO-Af and to the- difficulty of acono^cally servang. v ... v ... . f general interoot oth.^rwiR^ 4. .'If you agree, you .may wish to take sbme suitable opportunity of apprising Pakistani ; i Authorities informally of the arrangement: against jr back—ground of the «e»33± of Laithwaite's letter under reference. You might in particular-pH.'.* ini FORBIGN OFFICE, S.W.!• r 18th November, 1948* | ^* (P 14955/108/0) SBC RET You will remember that the United Kingdom High Commissioner in Karachi reported, in his telegram No. 148 Saving of 14th July, copied to you, that the Pakistan - Government had asked for a copy of the plan prepared by the Air Ministry in 1946 for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force.- 2. The Pakistan High Commission in London repeated this request late in August and we, along with the other departments concerned, had to consider it in the light of the policy laid down by the Cabinet on the disclosure of information to the New Dominions; which is that, in the military category, only such information should be given as is necessary for the immediate military needs of the Dominion concerned, the question of what information conies under this heading being decided in each case as it arises. It was felt that, given this policy, it was hardly possible to refuse the Pakistan request to see the Air Ministry plan, despite the obvious risk, to Which we gave due emphasis, that if the Afghans discovered that we were passing on information of this kind, even though it was obsolete, our whole position as the trusted advisers of their armed forces would be seriously prejudiced. 3. In order however to minimise the chance of a leakage to the Afghans it was agreed not to supply the Pakistan Government direct with a complete copy of the plan but to hand to the Pakistan Deputy Chief of Staff, General Cawthorne, who was then in London, an abridged version made up to resemble a complete copy. The portions of the plan, of which I understand your Military Attachd has copies, which were given to General Cawthome were the following: (1) The present covering Memorandum (marked ’A* in pencil) less the references to Appendix f D f and Appendix , F f ; (2) Appendix f A t ; (3) Appendix ’B* down to and including paragraph 24 only, without its Annexure , A*, and with the deletion and amendment indicated in paragraph 20 ; /( 4 ) Sir Olles Squire, K.B.B., Kabul.ti E X T 17576 (k) Appendix ’c 1 Annexuree ' G', ’H’, 'J* (5) Appendix t E f - ^ — 0 9 less Hissing Chart. General Cawthorne himself saw the whole plan and it _ - hi8 y ice ^ that the abridged veraion was was duldone, and the opportunity Zt'L tK ‘; en to emphasise to General Cawthome that we were passing on information acquired not in the ordinary in' 1 *?* but 111 ver y delicate circumstances h .r were actuall y adviser to the Afghan Air Force. We expressed the hope that the Pakistanis would obvio*siv &amp; to^i?h 0 ?°* eadang * r our position, which was oDviouely to their advantage as well as our own. bv hP«n W fl ? 8 * n3r . hlB J t0 reach the Afghans that we had“ allured 8 us 8 tw * hia matter together. General Cawthorne wrin?? * 1 ?* h fully understood the position and voula take all necessary precautions. thoi *«,vf n a lv aid ^ at this matter may not end here, and that, when the Pakistan Government realise that the plan they have been given is obsolete, they will ask for Afghan^ir'p^® i ^° rmat ^ on a ® w ® possess about the ^ iorce perhaps the Army as well. We have „$ 1Sar ^ the ot her Departments concerned that we do not regard ourselves as in any way corwaitted to the acceptance of a request of this kind but I must confess tWyLbi* 1 ? n0t tllink 111 wil1 1)6 eaa y to give a complete refusal to any such request, while policy on the unchanged* ° f infor! ' ,ation to the n ew Dominions remains , w f should welcome your conments on this problem which is obviously not easy.' A fJTT ^ TOP SECRET. OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR THE UNITED KINGDOM CHAMBER OF COMMERCE BUIIDI NG »ocftrmrerr No. 526. &lt;5Vs . ^EXT L. w f7589 Very many thanks for your letter ^ofjoc to be about the Pakistan Government’s interest iiT lIUT'Hff plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force. I entirely agree with what you say about the desirability of such matters being pursued ty the Pakistan Government through this High Conmission and not through their High Commission in London. In this case, it was, of course, our fault here that the Pakistan Government became aware of the existence of any Afghan’^lan” at all, and it is generous of you not to utter the reproaches such an error deserves. I am happy to know that the discussions which you have had with Cawthom have got over the difficulty.Mr* '&lt;&amp;lsh Atkins Your teisgr&amp;iu No* 474 dated 6 th May and peuagmptui 29 to 31 of report by . ing Oonauider Griffiths on his subsequent visit to Afghanistan! supervision of R*A*P. in Afghanistan by your Air Adviser, we have delayed further action on tais, pending the disposal of a matter referred to in Laithwaite's top secret letter to you No. xol. however now like to set on foot arrangement under accredited (at least at present) as Air Attache at Kabul, *ould include in his responsibilities supf ivisicn of R.A.F. matters In Afghanistan as desired by Air Ministry. This would entail probaity not more than two or three brief visits a year Adviser could not fly to and fro direct, as erclude possibility th*.t 1B nkistsn mljdit be wi 1 ling to permit occasional flights .,y representative of Coniucfiwealth Country, especially for the purpose in mind. But it would doubtless be unwise to try to work to this too early. 3 . we hope, however, tlv»t even if, for either or both these reasons. Air Adviser oo Id not at HAVING- TaL^GRA:.! Mxt. 174^48 dated 2dth October. **e should United Kingdom High ^om dsai ner, Karachi. which your Air Adviser, while not formally / to Kabul 2. e appreciate that such an arrangement might possibly entail some inconvenience for you if Air Distribution 11 Mr* f. L* brosthwait, Air ministry’, d # 6 . r. .. B. J. Ledwidge Foreign Office. regards provision of aircraft, see correspondence resting with Burnett*s letter to Field No. 39k of 31st August, as regards direct flights, U. • Ambassador, Kabul, reported on 2 3rd oeptaober Lieutenant Col. «aterfield, iiinistxy of Def ence. C*ii.O* King Charles Street Ir. Field. tnat i«aaeri.oons had enoouitered refusal by iakisten to permit regular courier air service across the frontier. ..e would not wish to present/eot f you will feel able to agree to proposed arrangement having regard to infrequency and shortness of visits oonteuplated end to the difficulty of making any other arrangement, i* If you agree 9 you may wish to take some suitable opportunity of apprising Pakistan authorities informally of the arrangement proposed against back-ground of the subject of Laithwaite*s letter under reference.4 (16354) Wt. 22753-8 10m 9/47 G.S.St. ^C)W. fe'Cx . l*^»vD'o| U-S C. R. O. Mr. Mr. Mr. Mr. Sycrs Sir Charles Dixon Depy. U.S. of S. Permt. U.S. of S. Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State. DRAFT. Sir L.Grafftey-Smith, KBE.,CMG. Further action. TOP SECRET (For Sir G.Laithwaite's signature ) 2 8 OCT 1948 You will remember that in your telegram No. 148 Saving of 14th 'July, you mentioned the Pakistan Government's interest in the Air Ministry plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force. We subsequently received the request from the Pakistan Government V do therein foreshadowed w*. f letter from the Counsellor to their High Commissioner in London dated 24th August, of which I enclose a copy. 2. As you, we know, realise, this enquiry raised some difficult issues, since considerations of security and consideration of our relation with the Afghan Government were both involved. We were much helped by the visit at about this time of Major General Cawthorn, and after discussion with him the con siderations to which we had to give weight in relation both to security and to telations with Afghanistan, were made entirely clear. He was on a top secret basis allowed to see the whole of the relevant material, and approval was given to his taking back certain selected papers /withwith discretion to make such use, on a top secret basis, of the material contained in them as seemed desirable. He was informed also that the plan under discussion was, so far as we were concerned, dead, since in the view of our experts it was too ambitious in the terms of the small numbers of trained personnel, method of recruiting, the low standard of recruits, and the lack of money and facilities. 3. I will only add that this formal request having been made to us through the Pakistan High Commissioner, we regarded it as essential to be satisfied that the High Commissioner would see no objection to our answer going by safe hand via Cawthorn. Hr assures us that this is entirely understood, ■ 5 nd _ 'wp-tra've for the purposes of record confirmed in writing to the High Commissioner that this chaAi^i has Jbeen used~ . 4. This case presented perhaps somewhat special features but, subject to your view, we would in the ordinary way like to encourage, so far as possible, the Government of Pakistan to pursue matters of this type through the U.K.High Commissioner. We think,that important from the point of view of the High Commissioner himself, and, as you will appreciate, there are certain arguments from the security point of view for such material as it may be /necessarynecessary to provide in answer to requests from them, conveyed through you rather than through any other channel. We feel, finally, that your hrt&gt; excellent relations with the Pakistan Government are likely to be of real assistance in getting round awkward corners which present much sharper angles when the discussion ±s_to take place via London.—- U-?r 'Ti) (36291) Wt.46030/4 7 30,000 3/48 A.&amp; E.W.\td. Gp.685 (File No. C.R.O. Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State DRAFT LETTER To:- TOP SECRET (For Sir G. Laithwaite^ signature) Please refer to your telegram No.148 Saving of 14th July about the Pakistan Govern ment's interest in the Air Ministry plan for the ^expansion of the Afghan Air Force. The request •om the Pakistan Government reached us through Sir Laurence Grafftey-Smith,KBE. ,GMG., thd^r High Commission in London in a letter from High Commissioner for the United the Counsellor, Ahmad, dated 24th August, Kingdom, KARACHI. PAKISTAN, of whiyh I enclose a copy. Leutuu/ 2. As $pu foresaw, this was -not altogether oaay tTr^do. m fully recognised in principle that Pakistan cdfild make out a strong case, as a member of thfe Commonwealth, to be put in possession of information of this nature. We were, however, \jandioapped by diatruSt of Pakiotan^o security arrangements, which indeed is an obataqle affCctlhg the transtnibaiun^ all secret inf orAition.^ Mopocnrerj this \ ( particular information did not fall into any ordinary category of foreign intelligence. It was obtained by United Kingdom authorities who had been called in as advisers by the Afghan Government and were thus iA the position rather of the private consultant e&gt;g4#oi:iiIy deeper. Great importance is attached I^ere to the maintenance of the confidence ^id friendly relations which exist at presentVbetween ourselves and the Afghans; and that position would be /gravtelygravely prejudiced if it came to the knowledge of the Afghans that we were passing on information obtained in\ this way. This would be unfortunate from Pakistan's point of view as well as our own, because it is to their advantage as well as to ours that we rather than others, should continue to advise the Afghans in matters of this sort and that our influence should be maintained in Kabul. 3. We therefore took advantage of Cawthom* s presence in London. We explained the position set out above to him quite frankly. We showed him the Air Ministry plan (which was very voluminous) and \ invited him to say tohat pieces he would like. This had the advantages (a) that he could say that he had seen the whole thing, and (b) that, by • giving him aselection only we reduced to some extent the risk of embarrassment with the Afghans. A copy of the \papers he had selected was handed to him on 19th October with a further explanation that the plan was dead so far as we were concerned, since in the opinion of our \ experts it was too ambitious in the face of the small numbers of trained personnel in Afghanistan, the method of recruiting and the low standard \ of recruits, and the lack of money and facilities. We are confident that he himself has taken out points \ and we have left it to his personal discretion to make what use he thinks fit of the phpers he has been given. 4. Cawthom secured, quite readily we gather, the agreement of the Pakistan High C&amp;mn.ission to their request being answered through him personally. They also recognised, when he pointed it out, that their request, which included the word 'demand”, was . not very happily phrased. 5. Perhaps I might mention in this context that we /wouldParly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State DRAFT (36201) Wt.40080/47 30,000 8/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 Further action. (File No - 3 - would ordinarily prefer delicate and possibly inconvenient matters of this sort to be handled between ourselves and the Pakistan Government through you at Karachi father than the Pakistan \ % High Commissioner*^ Office in London, This ensures that our points are made in the right quarter in the Pakistan Government and in the way we would wish, while we cannot be certain that the Pakistan High Comciissioner's Office would transmit a message accurately, It is also preferable from the security Voint of view for us to send secret material 'to the Pakistan Government through you rather than through their High Commission in London. We should, therefore, be grateful if, as a general rule, you could try to avoid encouraging the Pakistan Government to pursue matters ef - this nature in London instead of through you.^ ^ coj-&gt; ^nk t a/ K @) TOP S jCRfc)T Tkere is attached for use at General Cawthorn's discretion, a set of papers regarding the Air Ministry plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force, information about which was sought in the letter frost the Counsellor of the High Commissioner for Pakistan to Sir A. Carter No*S«24 of 24th August. 2* It is understood that General Cawthom informed Mr. Ahmad that arrang sients were being made for General Cawthom to take back to Pakistan by his own safe hand the information referred to in Mr. Ahmad's letter of 24th August and that Mr. Ahmad was satisfied with this proposal. Mr. Ahmad, however, has now, we hear, left the Pakistan High Commissioner's Office, and the High Commissioner's i rivute Secretary rang up a few days ago to know when an answer to the letter of 24th August might be expected. Perhaps General Cawthom will be good enough to ensure that the arrangements made after discussion vath Mr. Ahmad are .nown by the Pakistan High Commission. 3. It has become clear that the Air Ministry plan which was prepared at the request of the Afghan authorities, for the expansion of the Afghan Air Foz-cs to five operational squadrons, is too ambitious Among the reasons for this conclusion are the very small numbers of trained personnel available, the method of recruiting and the low standard of recruits, and the lack of money and facilities. The United Kingdom authorities have, therefore, taken no further action on the plan. 4. In Appendix A of the present papers reference is made, in the plana for the third and subsequent years, to the use of Fury aircraft. So fair as is known there are no negotiations in progress between the Afghans and aircraft firms in this country for the purchase of this type or any similar type of aircraft. The Fury vaa chosen in the drafting of the plan simply as a representative type of aircraft on which to base the establishment and type of personnel required by the Afghan Air Force in expansion. The naming of this type does not, therefore, necessarily indicate that /thethe Afghans intend to purchase aircraft of this type* 5. For reasons which hare been fully explained to General Cawthom personally, it id of the utnost importance that the material referred to in this Memorandum should he treated as of the first seoreoy, and that all possible precautions should be taken V to protect its strictly secret character and the fact that it is in the possession of the Government of Pakistan* »/ • • C0MMCNWKAL2H RELATIONS (FPIC*, DOWNING STREET. (Q October, 1948.Mr. ¥alsh-Atkins 15/10. I h ■\ x Laa~^ /^*- &gt;1 i tv. curies to I M X./fe u»rt 4. ■&gt; Permt. U.S. of S. Parly. U.S. of S. % Secretary of State. DRAFT. Cbc\CWico^ I 4*t be Cfax. OiC^Vw'-*- bfA^iir du^xs- b£ri*Juv^\ *a Apfcf Further action. ura. Printing. {Vcy&amp;r/ (AZ/e Ao •) fo (fU\4\.CLK*c£&lt;\ QtiAPf PERSONAL *tWS-POR GENERAL CAWTHORN H«*^erWv4r67 a set of papers regarding the Air Ministry plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force, information about which was sought in the letter from Mo the ffakieton Counsello^Pto Sir A, Carter, -roferonoc S.24 of 2Ath Augusty/for use at General Cawthorn* s It is understood, that General Cawthom informed^ Mr. Ahmad that arrangements were being made for h^m to take infor‘•■atio-n^back to Paid s t aiv^t^-Ww^ and that Mi*. Ahmad was quaW satisfied with this proposal. ^ Lea*, *4. &gt; has now \ left - ; L the Pakistan High Commission^hnd the High CoITlIIrLssioner , s Private Secretary rang up a few days ago to know when an answer to the letter of 24th August might be expected. Perhaps General Cawthorn will be good enough are known by to ensure that the arrangements boa-ng made the Pakistan High Commission, 3. 'Bhe Pakvstan anthnritica should be aware that 3t has become clear to -^ho U,K. Rnthoritlos concerned nW\e ujci that the Air Ministry plan^prepared at the request of the Afghan authorities^ for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force to five operational squadrons^is too ambitious^ for the Afghan Air Force ao at nreoent oonoti-tutodL Among the reasons for this conclusion are the very small numbers of trainyi* personnel available, the method of recruiting and the low standard of recruits, and the lack of money and facilities. The U.K. authorities have, therefore, taken no further action on the plan. 4. In Appendix A of the present papers reference is made(F 14131/108/G) Secret FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. 14th October, 1948. * Please refer to your letter No. POL (Ext) 17164/48 of 5th October and Air Ministry letter to you No. AFL4/C.35939/674 of 8th October about the Government of Pakistani request to see the Air Ministry plan for the Afghan Air Force. We see no objection to General Cawthome being given the abridged version of this plan which the Air Ministry have prepared, and being told the facts in paragraph 3 of the Air Ministry letter under reference. We also agree that he should be free to make it clear to such authorities in Pakistan as he finds necessary that this plan is now dead. In fact it seems rather important that he should do so. Cawthorne might also be asked to emphasize that we are passing on information acquired not in the ordinary course of intelligence, but in very delicate circumstances in which we are actually advisers to the Afghan air force. As it must be to the advantage of Pakistan as well as ourselves that we should be in a position to organise and control the Afghan air force, the Pakistan authorities should be very careful not to endanger our position or our source of information by allowing any hint to get to the Afghans that we have been discussing the matter together. We hope that they will bear these considerations in mind if they ask us for further L.B. Walsh Atkins, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office. information/information about current plans for the Afghan air force. You remark that even if Pakistan does not ask for information about any new plan that may be evolved, you would feel under some obligation to pass them some news of it. We are not sure that, as matters now s.tand, we should share this feeling, but perhaps it will be easier to come to a decision on this point when policy on the disclosure of information to the new Dominions has been settled. I am copying this letter to Waterfield at the Ministry of Defence and Griffiths at the Air Ministry.wgm From:- Winp; Commander A«R«L« Griffiths Vow.- iA\ .. . AIR MINISTRY, | ' 3411, Ext rffly/c 36 ?3 9/ Lf. 17 MONGK STREET, ts;^LONDON, S.W.1. •Bth October, 1948. Dear ^ ^ &lt;. « Thank you for your letter Pol.(EXT) 17614/48 dated / }&gt;l l 5th October, 1948, in connection with handing over of the Afghan Plan for Expansion^ to Pakistan. As requested I enclose herewith copies of the Plan^with certain parts deleted and amended as requested in para. 3 your letter. You should note^ that it is considered that appendix 'E” of the Plan would be meaningless without the Phasing Chart, and we have therefore^ included the Phasing Chart, suitably amended so as not to show the numbers of personnel , involved. ^ In appendix 'A” of the amended Plan, forwarded herewith, you will note that in the 3rd year the general purpose squadron is shown as being manned with Fury aircraft. It is requested that you will point out, when handing over this Plan to the negotiations in progress between the Afghan and aircraft firms in this country for the purchase of this type, or any aindlar type of aircraft. The Fury was chosen as a representative type aircraft on which to base the establishment and type of personnel required by the Afghan Air Force in expansion, and therefore^ the name of this aircraft in the Plan does not necessarily indicate that the Afghans intend to purchase thisWe have not seen a reply from Grey of the Foreign Office to your letter to Mm, so we are not yet aware whether the Foreign Office has agreed to the handing over of this Plan to Pakistan* In view, however, of the time factor, we have completed the Plan, as requested, in order that y should it be decided to hand the Plan over, copies will be available* I am copying this letter to Grey (Foreign Office) and Waterfield (Ministry of Defence)* Yours' 4 % &amp;UW&amp;10N FOR niA ■•■jUiliiN ii-LK FOnGl? Appendix 'A 1 ^ Appendix 'B* Appendix , C I Appendix 'D* - Order of Battle* - Signals Plan. - Servicing and Repair Plan. - ■t'lying Training Plan. 1. This Plan has been drawn up from the recommencL tions of the iiir Ministry branches conoernecU 2# The overall cost of training the ground trades shown at Appendix *1)* will be somewhere in the region of which xnclude lid? #000 for rations and acooimnocittion* 3* The cost of training one pilot from Initial Training up to and including advanced Training is in the region of £4,000 to £5,000* ^his does not, include accommodation and rations* 4* It is not anticipated that there will be any difficulty in carrying out the Initial and Basic iraining in the United Kingdom - the letter by civil contract. The Applied and Advanced Trainin^ will have to be the subject of further stucty when the exact requirements in numbers ol the Afghan Air Force are known* 5* It is essential that the Afghans selected for training have a complete grasp of the English language. The Training Schemes depend upon this entirely.* 6* The figures in paragraphs 2 and only represent estimates of cost and are liable to fluctuation particularly in view of the long-term nature of the programme and the possibility of a rise in basic costs*Appendix ‘a* to OX -L .A. XX \J\J t _ • L.iti. 11BE/0.5* dated /l/48„ Order of Battle for the 5 year Expansion of the Afghan Air fforce» 1st Year Plan (19A-8) (i) nir Force H.Q. (ii) 1 Station h.Q. (Kabul) 2 General Purpose Squadrons (Hind and Romeo) 1 Training Flight (Tiger Moth) (iii) 1 aKD/ERD and Unit Equipment Depot (iv) R.S.U. (Kabul) 2nd Year Plan (1949) (i) Air Force H.Q, (ii) 1 Station H.Q. (Kabul) 2 General Purpose Squadrons (Hind and Romeo) 1 Transport Flight (Anson) 1 Training Flight (Tiger Moth) (iii) 1 AKD/ERD and U.E.D. (iv) R.S.U. (Kabul) 3rd Year Plan (1950) (i) ^iir Force H.Q. (ii) 1 Station H.Q. (Kabul) 1 General Purpose Squadron (Fury) 1 Transport Flight (Anson) 1 Training Squadron (Tiger Moth and Hind) (iii) 1 Station H.Q. 1 General Purpose Squadron (Fury) (iv) 1 ARD/ERD. (v) 1 A.S.U./U.E.D. (vi) R.S.U. Note:- In the 3rd Year the U.E.D. breaks away from the jMID/ERD and is re-formed with the A.S.U, on the same Station. The Training Squadron at Item (ii) will' consist of 1 Basic Flight and 1 Intermediate Flight, 4th Year Plan (1951) (i)' Air Force H.Q. (ii) 1 Station H.Q, (Kabul) 1 General Purpose Squadron (Fury) 1 Transport Squadron (Anson) 1 Training Squadron (Tiger Moth and Hind) G. 187823mmmm SiXJRc.T. AiiiiNDUC •B 1 to L. dated ,.M.nayo.5. lated /l/48e Afghan Air Foroe - Signals Plan &gt; Introduotion* 1« The purpose of this paper is to recommend the general principles on which the Afghan Air Foroe signals organisation should be based in the future* 2* The organisation and equipment at present existing in Afghanistan have been ignored for the purpose of this paper as they are believed to be obsolescent and could not be integrated with a modern organisation* In order to conserve the very limited manpower resources which it is understood will be available, the keynote of the plan is simplicity. It is considered that the facilities recommended in this plan represent the maximum which the Afghan Air Foroe will be capable of operating during the next five years. Basis of the Organisation : The organisation upon which the plan is based is as follows: (a) The headquarters is based at Kabul* (b) There are five permanent airfields: Herat, Kandehar, Baghlan, Gardes and Kabul* (o) U) That squadrons will operate from unprepared bases in the field* The main role of the squadrons will be Army support. There will be no night operations and no Fighter Interception role* 4* The signals organisation recommended to provide adequate facilities to meet the general organisation given above is broadly speaking as follows :- V a) That simplicity is essential because of the limited manpower* (b) That communication between the headquarters and the five permanent airfields should be on a static basis consisting of a landlipe system backed up by a standby wireless system* (c&gt; That the squadrons should have mobile equipment to allow then to operate in the field* (A) (e) That adequate radio navigational aids should be provided at both static and temporary airfields* That there should be facilities for corumunioation between aircraft employed on direct support and forward units of the arroy* (fj Meteorological facilities will be required* Communications between Headquarters and Static Airfields* f}* Landlines: Telephones, trunk circuits and exchange* required to oonnedT Air Headquarters and the five main airfields should be provided by the government posts and telegraphs department* Both telephone and teleprinter channels should be provided* be 6. w/T Communications: Low powsred hand operatsd jji/T channels should provided between ,'.abul and the five permanent airfields for standby to line. It is considered that s ingle channel should be adequate but dependent uiMin the reliability of the landline system the need for a common net G.187863 /onnot on which Kabul and tho fivo static stations should operate should be considered in addition to the one channel between each station and Kabul* 7* foint-to»Point Signals Organisation for Squadrons Operating on a Mobile basis * .aaoh Squadron should be provided with adequate mobile iV/T communication facilities to allow it to operate independently from emergency forward airfields* The rt/T point-to-point facilities which it is considered would be required at each squadron operating independently are as follows* (a) One channel back, to controlling formation* (bj One channel back, to administrative base or to other Squadrons operating* (o) One channel for meteorological reception* Air to Ground Communications : 8* It is considered that all fighter aircraft should be equipped with VHF. The normal channel set-up should be:- ,a) local airfield control: ( b} operational channel: common guard operational channel: 'dj homing J,D/¥) channel and approach control* 9* Transport aircraft should be fitted with VHP as above, and in addition should be fitted with HP W/T equipment* 10. bach permanent airfield should be equipped with static low power VHP R/T equipment, for the following facilities* (a) Local airfield control* (b) Two operational channels to aircraft* (c) VHP D/F. 11* x,ach airfield at which transport aircraft are permanently based should be equipped with the following additional equipment for ground to air purposes. (a&gt; One HP w/T channel* (bj One VLP MF radio beacon. 12* There should be VHF mobile equipments provided for use with Am\y units with which aircraft may have to operate in close support. Kadio Navigational Aids : 13* Permanent airfields should have static VHP Dj/F stations to provide VHP homing* Airfields at which transport aircraft are permanently based should have a static MF beacon* 14. Squadrons which may operate from forward bases should be equipped with mobile VHP D/F equipment. Meteorological Information: 15« The conununications plan for meteorological purposes is dependent on the meteorological plan* However, it is considered that in view oi the economy necessary the following plan would give reasonably satisiaotory results* (a) There should be a medium power HP W/T broadcast from Kabul of the meteorological information received from the state meteorological service. This information should be received at all permanent airfields and at any squadrons operating from forward emergency airfields* Gr« 18763*(b) Ther« should be facilities for pa sing actuals at all airfields to Kabul, but this can be done over operational W/T channels. These actuals would be re-broadcast on the Kabul broadcast* ^iiiaintenanoe: 16* It is reoouuuended that at each main airfield a signals ^or .on . &lt;s provided which will carry out work on all signals equipment belonging to the airfield and to the squadrons operating there. Major repair work beyond the capacity of these workshops should be done at Kabul* A three months spares backing for equipment should be held at each of these workshops, the i euiaining spares to be held at some central equipment de, ot* i^aoh workshop should be equipped with all necessary test equipment® 17* iiaoh squadron should have a mobile signals workshop for use when operating away from the base airfield* x.ach of these mobile signals workshops should carry a one month*s spares backing and should have a reduced scale of test equipment* 18. A reserve pool of mobile equipment to meet any extra commitments should be held in the base area. It is thought that the reserve pool of equipment should consist of the following items. 2 LE HP W/T transmitting vehicles. 2 HP W/T receiving vehicles* 2 VHP D/P vehicles. 2 standby power vehicles* Power Supplies : 19. All R.A.F. static equipment which would be provided under this plfcn operates from 230-volt 53 -cycle AC electric supply. Suitable power equipment must be provided at each permanent airfield. R.A.F. mobile equriment which would be provided under this plan either carries its own power generating equipmentor operates from batteries. Battery charging facilities should be provided at permanent airfields and where necessary for mobile equipment. i hassd usveloEment : 20. The plan given here will have to be built up over a period of years. The rate at which it can be developed will be determined principally by the rate of output of trained personnel. The development of the signals organisation must follow the operational and administrative development of who It force and can be phased as follows. 21. Phase I (1st Year) 1948 (i) Select suitable officers for training as signals officers. (ii) iistablish and equip Signals School. (iii) Recruit suitable personnel for trainipg as officers and men in radio (iv) Modernise and equip airfield at Kabul® (v) establish Main equipment Unit. (vi) Establish and equip meteorological organisation at Kabul, i.e. MP transmitter for broadcasting met information* Complete telephone installation (landlines etc.) to sub units in Kabul area, and commence installation of landlines to aiixelus being reconstructed* G.1876} / 22 .22# Phase II (2nd YearJ 194.9 * (ij expand school and general training programme* (ii) Conmenoe installation of signals facilities at main airfields* (Use mobile equipment until static equipment is installed and serviceable*; Sufficient trained personnel should be available to provide skeleton staff at a total of three airfields. (iii; Meteorological radio facilities (one reception point at each main airfield;, to be manned 24-hour watch basis. (iv) Complete telephone installations at main airfields. (v; Increase capacity and facilities of Signals School. 23. Phase III (3rd Yearj 1930 . (i; Complete installation of tf/T communications from Kabul to each main airfield. (ii) Complete installation at main airfields of all static electrical and radio equipment shown in this plan. (lii) Deploy signals vehicles on semi permanent basis. (iv) Complete radio servicing facilities, workshops etc, at each main airfield. (v) Install local telephone system at each main airfield. 24* Phase IV v. (i) Review training requirements and amend schedules to ensure even flow of trained personnel necessary to maintain force. (iij Heriew navigational aids* a. 187863AFGHAN AIR FORCE AKNEXURE ,, G U PROPOSED ORGANISATION FOR ^iIR HEADQUARTERS G•-in-C• S*iv&gt;S« 0 » S. T. S. O# A« 0 «A« S&gt;T»S»0» (a) Responsible to the C.-in-C. for the formulation and implementation of technical policy* (b) Responsible for tho co-ordination of Armament, Engineering and Signals (Technical) Staffs and for the control of the technical servicing organisation* C#_Ann*0* (a) Responsible to the S*T*S.O. for the fomulation and implementation of the armament servicing policy as defined by the Air Ministry* (b) Responsible for the control of the armament servicing organisation* (c) Responsible for liaison with the Weapons Officer on armament operational problems* 0* Eng»0 i (a) Responsible to the S*T.S*0* for the femulation and implementation of the engineering servicing policy (including electrical, instruments and M*T* policy). (b) Responsible for the engineer (including electrical, instruments and M*T*) servicing organisation. G.187876(c) /c» Sigr,0- 2 - C. Sigs» 0&gt; (a) Responsible to the S.A.S*0. (on operational aspects) and S.T.S.O. (on servicing aspects) for the formulation and inip lenent at ion of Signals policy. (b) Responsible for the Signals operating and servicing organisation. 1 41.© SijQRiag ^pendix /CV to L&gt;4&gt; - lia dated - January. 194£ Ri^GCM^NDSD &gt;i^RVXUlNc; Jc'+jAN FOR Tliii. Alii Proposed ^orvioing ^olioy Or&amp;£iaalMn at ^t^ionLev^ lat ano 2nd .bine Servicing: o£ Operational oguadrons (lighter and I'ransportJ 1* Servicing should be based on the following system of inspections as used in the i- (•) For Fighter Aircraft* ire-flightj Between Flight; After Flight* Daily* weekly. Minor and Major Inspections# The frequencies between minor inspections and between major inspections should be determined by calendar time an^ or flying hours. (b) For Transport Squadrons. Route* Terminal and Base Inspections. Route inspections should be done at each stopping plaoe on route* Terminal inspections at the outward end of a route flight and Base inspections at the aerodrome on which the aircraft is based and when the aircraft returns from a route flight. 2* Technical ftings under the command of a technical officer should be established on each station in accordance with the chart attached at Annexure 'A'. The bulk of the personnel for such wings shouia be provided by Servicing aiaheions estabiished as separate units on a scale calculated to enable them to support one squadron. Mach Servicing Ache Ion should be mobile and* thus, separate elements of the Teohnical Wing can be removed, in order to support a squadron which is moved from the station, without disrupting the organisation of the wing. Daily servicing should be the responsibility of each squadron commander and to achieve this the necessary technical personnel should be technically and administratively controlled by each squadron connander. 4. Minor and Major Inspections and minor repairs should be done in the Technical Wing (established on each station) where the arisings of inspections anchor repairs from all squadrons or flights on the station should be centralised. 1st and 2nd x.ino oervi-C-Ln*, of Trainia^ _Flights_U Flights^ 5. Bervicing of training aircraft xhould be based on the following system of inspection as used in the R # A.F # (a) For training aircraft - Pre-Flight, Between Flight* After Flight* Daily* Weekly, Minor and Major Inspections. The frequencies between successive minor inspections and major inspections should be determined by calendar time an^or flying hours. 6. Daily servicing* inspections and minor repairs should be the responsibility of the officer commanding the Technical Wing in the oaae of Training Flights. Thus the Teohnical wing which will be a static unit should be organised with two flights, namely a Repair and Inspection Flight, and a Daily Servicing Flight. All technical personnelwill thus be under the administralrion and technical control of the Officer Connanding the Technical &gt;iing» A chart show ing the organisation is at Annexure 'B*. /planned Inspection.Planned InspeqtAon - 2 - 7* I’he aim in aervicing procedure should be to adopt the teohnique Known as Planned Inspection in the This technique requires, however, a well organised technical and supply service and therefore it should be introduced into the Afghan air force only when these pre-requisites are satisfied* .&gt;ir lieadguarters Organisation of the Technical dtaff d« It is recoomended that the technical staff should be established in an air Headquarters as tb e third prong of the policy staff# The organisation recommended is shown in the attached chart at Annexure N C M # 9# The technical staff should fonnulate the servicing policy to be followed at operational and training stations, the Repair and Salvage Unit, Aircraft bepot and Aircraft Storage Unit# Direct technical control should be exercised between Air Headquarters and these units# jrd Line Servicing and Base Repair. Assunutions 1U» In preparing the recommendations in Paras. 3 and 4 the following assumptions have been made:-* (a) The five Operational Squadrons to be single engined fighter aircraft of the firefly or fuxy type. 1'he Transport Squadron to be Anson AIA# (b) The Training Squadron to be comprised of a Basic flight of Tiger Aoths and an Intermediate Training flight of a type of aircraft similar to that of the Harvard# (o) The Operational assumptions are:- 3 fighter Squadrons 12 U.£ # affort 23 hr^month 1 Medium Transport Squadron 12 li.R. effort 40 hrsp month The Training assumptions are:- 1 Basic Flight 10 D#£ Rffort 40 hrV month 1 intermediate flight 10 U#£? affort 40 hrs/month (e) The Reserve of aircraft to be 4 aircraft per Squadron plus a Command reserve of 4 aircraft per Squadron# it) The Operational Squaorons to be fully mobile and able to operate independent ly# 11# a risings (*) firefly Anson Tiger Moth Harvard (b) Aeroengines Griffon Cheetah G# Major ?• do w* 1340 a risings^ Month Cat AC# Cat B. •099 .099 .240 .124 • 04 .04 .11 .11 Rngine Overhaul^Month S#d 1.15 •44 • Bd(o) Anoillarv i ; riain;:3 per i pnth Propellors Magnetos Compressors Pumps Feathering Hydraulic Components Compasses Clocks Rate of Climb airspeed Gauges Boost 12 2.7 1 . 6 ? 1.67 Ignition Harness Viouum Pumps Garb 3 Parachutes Camera altimeter Turn and Bank 1.67 7.5 4.3 6 27 5 3 6 11 8 5 5 7 3 5 6 5 3.3 11 6 Gauges Brake Pressure 7 ' Fuel Contents 10 Fuel Contents Oil Pressure ' Suction Indio, bng: opeed Voltage Regulators Starters Reflector Sights Oxygen Regulators * Fuel Pressure 5 12 Artificial Horizon Directional Gyro Generators Hydraulic Pump R.P.M. Generators Economisers 10 6 6 5 3 11 4 12 . Cylinder Temp .stations . (a) Aircraft - Stations should be organised to Selvage and Kepeir Cat. aC aircraft within *heir areas. Station Workshops to be eugjnent to enable this to be carried out. (b) MtT.- Stations will carry out Inspections up to tnd including 10,000 miles, 500 hours inspections and minor repairs, end to Selvage vehicles within their own areas. ; noillary Units (e) /.Rb/ERD - One ARD/ERD to be established to carry out (i/ Major Repair and Overhaul of airframes. (ii) Overhaul and Repair of Engines (including K.T. engines;. ^HI.) Overhaul of aircraft accessories, instruments -nd electrics. (iv) Repair and Overhaul of Propellors. (v) Overhaul of Signals, armament end Safety Equipment. (vi) Repair and Overhaul of M.T. beyond Unit capacity. (vii) G.E.3. (b) A small storage to liold reserve aircraft end M.T. It is suggested that this be situated on tlie same station upon which the ARD/KRD is sited. If the whole force is to be housed on Five stations, it is rceoiomended each station be established with a Servicing ^ing H.&lt;*. of .C. ot* tus Esteblishmentastations oporeting only one iiviutuirun at K^BUL end P.L. atetua on the otVier -v each. 15. No Signals personnel ere shewn except in the oase of the Open tioiu-l Squadrons • 16. All Squadrons asauiaed to be operating on 2 ?li £ ht btsia * 17. A email element to cover Bepair and Salvage has been allowed on station , ork shops to be established on ec oh Station.ArTSNDIX D . APGHAM AIR ^HC3 - FLYU^O ^ II , The following plan has hoen drawn up to give the Afghan Air Force an idee/ of the flying training which their pilots should undertake if they are to achieve the five year expansion and re-equipment scheme. 2 m It must he understood that expansion cannot canmence until two years after the first course enters training out that it will he' completed within three years of the first course passing out of training. It has heen assumed that all pilots will he long service and that there will he no problems of replacement for engagement termination during the expansion period. 4 . Normal R.A.F. course lengths which include leave have heen assumed. These arcs Initial training - 86 weeks Basic training - 86 weeks Applies training - 26 weeks Advanced flying and operational conversion - 26 weeks[8059] Wt. 9899/56 10m 5/48 C.N.Ld. 748 C.R.O. /ft Mr*Walsh Atkins. 3/ 10 /48* i^'V^v+Sf 0 ) Permt. U.S. of S. Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State. DRAFT. LSTTSR Wing Commander A.R.L.Griffiths, Air Ministry, 17 Monck Street, S «W . 1 . . mr^Fi it - j** P Further action. Copy to:- P.P.Grey^ Esq., (tu. Foreign Office. Lt. Col .P .R .Wa terfield, Ministry of Defence. / i/ Printing. (File No f'CC^-cX^’ n Dear Griffiths, Many thanks for your letter of 24th September No. C.3629^/4*5/39, with which you sent me a copy of the Air Ministry plan # for the Afghan Air Force. 2 . I enclose a copy of the letter which I am sending to Grey at the Foreign Office which will, I think, bring Sen up to date with what has happened vis-a-vis the Pakistan authorities. I also return your copy of the plan. 3* Cawthorn£ suggests that he should be % given copies of the following parts of the plan, suitably amended to make them appear ■ft? a. uCmCc* (1) the present covering llemorandisn (marked ’A* in pencil) less the ' references to Appendix tP* and Appendix ‘F* ; (2) Appendix •A* ; (3) Appendix ’B* down to*, and including^, paragraph 24 only, without its Annexure ’A* , and with the deletion and amendment indicated in paragraph 20 ; (4) Appendix ‘C* less paragraph 18 and Annexures ‘D* , •£• , ^l)', ‘FUl)* •G* , •H* , ‘J*, »K» , ’LCl)* , , L(2)* (5) Appendix 'E* less Phasing Chart. 4. We should be most grateful if you could cause a set of documents to be preparedIS accordingly. If* it could be conveniently done while you are about it, perhaps we could have a similar set for our own retention, as a record of what has gone to CawthorcJ. (f ^^ 5 . As for the tijas factory Caw thorn# was to return to Pakistan next Thursday, 7th October. We understand, however, that he has lately received instructions to defer his departure at least for another week. We may, therefore, have that much grace, but it would perhaps be well, if you can, to get the thing done with expedition. 6 . I am sending a copy of this letter to Grey at the Foreign Office and * V Waterfield, Ministry of Defence. Yours sincerely, LaUK- 'XtKi ■ » xf-Jrr m . J:\T[80591 Wt. 9899/56 10m 5/48 C.N.Ld. 748 C C.R.O. Mr .Walsh Atkins. 3/^48. ) 5 OCT 1948 Permt. U.S. of S. Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State. DRAFT. IETTEB PJ'.Grey, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.I. Further action. Copy toj- Wing ConaDander A.R.L.Grriffitlks Air Ministry ^ Lt.Col. PJlJi.Waterfield, Ministry of Defence. Printing. * TLa^u U\ €-4 i pci/rn-*- b L J ' »' lephone eowpewafttion Oi* ■ &amp;t 27th September about the Government of Pakistan* s request to see the Air Ministry* s plan for the Afghan Air Force. Laithwaite had already had a private word with General Cawthornff about it, and on the basis of the two conversations^ the following action has now been taken:- (a) Cawthornf has spoken to the Pakistan High Commission, who recognise and regret that their letter of 24th August was not very iMfPttsy phrased. They are, moreover, # perfectly happy that the desired information should be given to General Cawthornf himself instead of to them. (b) We explained to General Caw thorn# here the difficulties which were felt, in regard to our relations with the Afghans, in passing this information to Pakistan^ despite our very full recognition of Pakistan* s legitimate interest in the matter. Cawthorn# entirely feel confident that we may rely on his co-operation and discretion. We^/gave him the full copy of the plan which Griffiths of the Air Ministry had just sent me, partly so that he could say that he had seen the whole thing^ and partly so that he could pick out /the- 2 - the information which he imimi mid Smr Pakistan* s purposes. We asked him to ■take no copies or extracts himself but to send the whole thing ( CriuiL uc UxJla. ^ back to us with a note of requirements J It seemed to us that this went some way towards preserving wMaor position as well as having practical advantages ; because the volume of paper in the whole report is quite formidable. 2. We are, therefore, asking the Air Ministry to be good enough to extract for us the information which Cawthorn^ asks/ and put it in a Ir* suitable form. We hope that you will see no objection to this. I enclose a copy of pur letter^ . 3 . We have already mentioned to Cawthory that this plan is dead. We think it only honest to permit him to make this clear to such authorities as he finds necessary. io that,since its death was caused by over—ambition, the plan will then be known by the Pakistanis to be something more than the most that is likely in fact to develop in Afghanistan. They are, of course, likely to ask that in this case*, we should let them know about whatever new plan may be evolved; jnwfc we dn not nr* hr i 11 ^'Ti ' 1 r M'y n ■norjTinn+ whan Tiu.,a n?&gt;%rt)i.i though we might hope to be able to deal with it through a similar . _ , ^ At* A ^ r ^ cji3.nne±j i / — N r 4. I am sending a copy of this oorpoopondenoo also to Waterfield at the Ministry of Defence. ^ . -P- lUPt'sWz Xi&gt;i CaSX if* e * *8 35598 \ j /fi. WM-fojL' ; w^- With the Compliments of the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (ftl3L*&amp;//0g/&lt;tyj SECRET Foreign Office, 3# Hus'.\ M 7- LT'Us tc.lcr;rc;i is of p^tioular secrecy and s^uld be retained by the”authorised *rc‘ciplent and not passed pn. ] G^cr/OTP. m^m^ivn . Emjm&amp; .TO KK2JZX OEEM* Sir ^.Squire. D. 10.00 a.r:. 23rd Senteaber,1848 Fo. 169. ^‘SiS^’Septe^ber,* 1948. R. 8.14 a.m. 23rd S^te ,ber,1948 SECRET. Your telegram number 146. V ie vs e pressed in my tele .nr am 42 remain unchanged. I see no obiection to air adviser Karachi be inn; appointed to look after Royal Air Force personnel in Kabul and to his pay inn; brief visits as often as may be necessary. .2. If, however, it is desired formally to credit him as Air_Attachd in Kabul I should prefer to consult Afghanistan minister for Foreign Affairs informally first. Americans have recently abandoned similar proposal because of Afghan opposition, lack of airfield facilities and refusal of Pakistan to permit regular courier air serv ice across n orth west fron tier province. 1 doubt ir there is enough work to Lomit, j _ more tnair two or three visits a year and there is no separate accommodation for him in the Embassy at present. 5 5 5STRICT, LONDON, S.W.l. 24th September, 1948. You asked Mr. Thorp for two copies of the air Ministry plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force. I regret that I cannot produce two copies at the moment, but as I understand you only wish to have a look at the plan, I enclose one copy. Perhaps when you have finished with it, you will return it to me, (X/&gt; (JV GuJvcmA /l— J ^wpCttueA. J2. v-Of A/lttZo t-»I C/fUAAlt Yours &lt;xaaJ^ a. L.B. WAL3H-ATKINS, isq., Gorjnonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, London, S.W.l* «p- Jfr*P OUTWARD TELEGRAM IND-XED [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on], Cypher/OTP DEPaR'aMTAL DIST RI BUTION F12150/108/97, Secret. FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO KABUL NO. 11.6. September 13 th, 1918. SECRET Your tel egram in Kabul], D. 7.30.p.m. September 13th, 1918. [Appointment of Air AttachS air Ministry have now raised this question again an suggested that best arrangement, if all concerned agree, would be to accredit Air adviser to United Kingdom High Commissioner, Karachi, to you as well. They say. however, that it is doubtful v/hether he would have aircraft' allotted to him, . we welcome proposal in principle but feel that political and financial difficulties raised in reference must be given due weight. We think Air Ministry plan might reduce financial and accommodation difficulties, but if ^ttach6 has no aircraft and has to spend four days en route on each journey between Karachi and Kabul, his utility will be much diminished. 3# Before examining the question further we should welcome your comments. Do you consider that there is the same political objection to approaching the Afghan Government on-this subject as there was last Spring?tow- fc-*' - W.B. J. Ledvddge, Esq., DRAFT LETTER -— ^ U SEP 1948 Many thanks for your letter No.F.104-55/108/9 of 20th August about Pakistan’s request to see a I copy of the Air Ministry’s plan for the Afghan Air Force. Your hope, which we shared, that we might be able to dodge this problem, has been defeated by the letter from the Pakistan High Commission in Foreign Office, S.W.1 Copy with en* to Mr.T.L. C ^sthwait, p s\ 7*^’ ^ if ^Air Ministry, 1 Whitehall, London of the 24th August, of which I enclose a copy, . ly Sfrj and we have clearly got to to grips with-the 2. We entirely appreciate the force of the arguments in paragraph 3 of your letter about our relations with Afghanistan. But though the use of the word 'Demand' * — in the last paragraph of Ahmad’s letter is not very happy, we see a very great deal of difficulty in ¥ declining to meet the Pakistan request. Their argument is a formidable one, especially during a period such as the present, when the advantages to Pakistan of membership of the Commonwealth are being so actively considered at all levels. If we are anxious to preserve the confidence of the Afghans, we must surely be still more concerned to preserve the confidence of a Commonwealth country. As we understand it, our policy regarding the passing of top secret and military information to Pakistan was laid down, in D.C.O.S. (46) 193(Final) of 2nd October 1946, as being that only such information in these categories as was necessary for Pakistan's immediate military needs should be sent; and that in accordance with D.0.(48), 11th Meeting of 15th July 1948 , the question of what secret information should be communicated to any particular Dominion is to be dealt with ad hoc pending the discussions with Commonwealth Prime Ministers in October. It seems to us that the information asked for can hardly be regarded as other than secret, or top secret, /information- 2 - information essential to Pakistani immediate military needs* 3. We feel therefore that we have little choice hut no strong brief for Pakistani security arrangements, we would place some reliance in the present case on that very suspicion between Pakistan and Afghanistan to give the document to the Pakistan High Commissioner's ycinv agrr^ir.^nt- -bn s raoiil Comnvi sstoner--to givp him the ilocnment. Griffiths on his visit to Kabul, in or clear that the Air Ministry's plan is We would be grateful if you could let • the Foreign Office agree to this proce 5 . If you so, we should then for our part be ready to pursue the question of the United Kingdom High Commissioner's Air Adviser undertaking certain duties in Afghanistan, raised in Crosthwait's letter to Grey No.B.J.S.6/387 of 30th August. 6 . I am sending copies of this letter and its enclosure to Crosthwait at the Air Ministry and Waterfield at the Ministry of Defence. / to meet the Pakistanis' request. We note, moreover. from Crosthwait's letter of the 17th August that the Air Ministry for their part are prepared to agree that it should be met. 4. As regards your paragraph 4, while we hold the Pakistan Deputy Chief of Staff^ who is now in London^ aad-tcll Ahmad that we have do CaVthornc has returned to Koraohi bofo to which you refer. .&lt;e would, however, propose not Office in London, but to Hmid it t,n neral Cawthome, at the same time to let Cawthome have relevant extract from the report of WiFurther action. y ^ r^cocu'F i 1 jY. /U ll^ / Printing. {File No . Dear Ledwidge, \ Many thanks for yoiA* letter No, F. 1^455/108/9 of 20th August about Pakist^in’s request to see a oopy of the Air Ministry’s plan for the Afghan Air Force, Your hope, which we shared\, that we might be able to dodge this problem, has bedn defeated by the letter from the Pakistan High Commission in London of the 24th August, of which I aiclose a; copy, and we have clearly » got to get to grips with the question. 2 We entirely appreciate tihe force of the arguments in paragraph 3 of your letterl about our relations with Afghanistan. But though the \|se of the word 'Demand' in the last paragraph of Ahmad’s letter is not very happy, we see a very great dea(L of difficulty in declin ing to meet the Pakistan request. Their argument is a formidable one, especially during a period such as the present, when the advantages to Pakistan of membership of the Commonwealth are being sto actively considered at all levels. If we are anxious to preserve the confidence of the Afghans, we mist surely be still more concerned to preserve the confidence of* a Commonwealth countryf As we understand it, our policy regarding the passing of top secret and military information to Pakistan was laid down^in D.C.O.S. (46) 193 (Final) of 2nd October 1946, as being that only such infomation in these categories as was necessary for Pakistan's immediate military greeds should be sett I-edj and that in accordance wi-fth D.O. (48), 11th Meeting of 15th July 1948, the question of what secret information should be corrmunicated to any particular Dominion is to be dealt with ad hoc pending the discus- sions Commonwealth Prime Ministers in October. It seems/W-th the Corapliraents of Ivlr. T.L. Crosthwait, A: ir ^ n istry, S* 6 . Whitenaxx* J,' B,j.s.6./387 30th August, 194-6. Dear Since the return of Wing Co-Tnander Griffiths from his visit to Kabul we h ve been considering the question of A.A.P. representation in Afghanistan last referred in /our letter Aop3/10o/ 97 of the 3rd April to Low. You have doubtless seen the report of Griffith's visit. 2. The conclusion reached in April was that the matter should be reviewed when the military Attache, Golonel Lanco.ster, was due to leave. We understand that he is likely to hand over fairly soon, and this seems the right time to go into the iaattcr aga : -n. 3 . As you will see from paras. 29-31 of his rexx&gt;rt, the possibility of accrediting the Air Adviser to the U.K. High Convussioner in Pakistan to the Afghan Goveriuaent as air Attache was discussed by Griffiths, and we are inclined to think that this solution is the most promising one, provided i&amp; is acceptable to H.M. Minister in Kabul and to the i igh Gora Issioner in Karchi as well as to the Governments of Afghanistan and Pakistan. It seems, however, improbable that agreement could be obtained to the provision of an aircraft for the purpose. A. -ie should be grateful for your views on the natter. 3* I ata sending a copy o this letter to Walsh-Atdns at the Commonwealth Relations Office. Yours T. 1 . CROsnrn*xr P.F. Grey, Ssq., Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.Telephone: WELBECK 0791. Ext. Telegrams : PAHIC, WESDO, LONDON. Cables : PANIC. LONDON. In /our reply please quote Department. Reference — - L L dir ibald, Kingdom proposed to send T Kabul to discuss with the His Kaoesty* s Ambassador, of the Afghan Air _; 1 orce. Wing Commander Griffiths, Military and Air Advisers THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR PAKISTAN, 16 FITZHARDINGE STREET, ^ LONDON, I &amp; ^ V-' ~ ' &lt;•4 •#£. 17102 /oi^ ' ™— 2Uth August, 19Uo. 343 The United Kingdom high Cor missioner in Pakistan informed the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, Government of Pakistan, in Karachi on May 15th, 19U8, that the Air Ministry in the United ing Commander A.R.L. Griffiths to Afghan authorities and with problems regarding the organisation It was suggested that who was to be accompanied by be granted transit facilities through Pakistan to Afghanistan. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs replied to the High Commissioner on May 23rd, stating that they had no objection to the proposed flight. At the same time, they requested that copies of the plan prepared by the Air Ministry about the expansion of the Afghan Air Force may be supplied for their information. A few days later, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs was advised by the United Kingdom Commission that the correspondence may be considered as cancelled. The Government of Pakistan, as a member of the British Commonwealth, would appear to be entitled to^demand from the United Kingdom information regarding the Armed Forces of a foreign country who has a common frontier with Pakistan, and particularly in this case when His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom has been rendering assistance in the J expansion/2 expansion of the Afghan Air 'orce. I am, therefore, to request you kindly to obtain the relevant information and a copy of the plan, v/hich I shall arrange to^ forward to the frovemment of Pakistan for their&gt; information. Yours sincerely, (I . Ahmad) Counsellor. Sir Archibald Carter, K.C.B., K.J.I.E., The Commonwealth Relations Office, Dov/ning Street, S.W.1 .please refer to your letter of the 26th .July abou^t 30 - tile- request of the Pakistan Government to be'~'aXlo\ved to see a copy of the plan prepared by the Air Ministry for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force* followed up by their High Commissioner in London, as suggested in paragraph 4, it will not be incumbent upon us to take the matter any further, beyond perhaps explaining, our views to Karachi* We hope that you will agree with this, since the Pakistan request raises two awkward problems. _ , 3* In the first place, it will hardly be possible to decide how much, if anything, to tell the Pakistanis until His Majesty's Government has reached a decision on policy on the supply of security information to the new Dominions, which, I understand, cannot be expected until after the commonwealth Conference in October. Secondly, if we do decide, to pass on information to Pakistan, it will be of the first importance to prevent our action becoming known to the Afghan Government. Their own relations with Pakistan are, unfortunately, none too friendly at present and they would certainly be furious if they learnt that we were providing their neighbours with information of this kind, oar whole position as the most trusted advisers of the Afghan army and air force, which we have built up with considerable difficulty, might thereby be undermined. 2* As we read Savin gram No. 148 from Karachi the Pakistan approach was informal and unless it is L.B. Walsh-Atkins, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office4. It would therefore be necessary to impress very forcibly on tbe Pakistan authorities the need for secrecy in this matter, and to have a reasonable assurance that, they would be able to keep the secret* Do you think, from what you know of security conditions in Pakistan, that we could in fact be sure * that it would not leak out to the Afghans? 5 . This is, in fact, a problem which we should much rather not have to consider at all, and which, in any event, could hardly be decided before October. 6. I am copying this letter to crosthwait at the Air Ministry.COPY ^ a ’ Tel. No. Abbey 3411 . Ext. 521% Tlc/MK AIR MINISTRY, G. 36298/36. 3 E G R B T Dear ^ ^ C- ^ •' A ' I am writing with reference to your letter of the 26th July'tfb SlO* Tull at the Foreign Office on the subject of the Pakistan Government’s request to see a copy of the plan prepared by the Air Ministry for the expansion of the Afghanistan Air Force. We are inclined to think that Pakistan’s claim to be informed of military preparations in neighbouring foreign countries is reasonable, and provided that a precedent is not created, which might prove embarrassing with for instance our relations with India, the information for which they ask might very well be given them. Y/e suggest, however, that a final decision on the point can be deferred until the form and nature of .the approach, which the High Oomnissioner for Pakistan in London [.apparently i*- being instructed to make, is known. I am sending a copy of this letter to Ledwidge at the Foreign Office. Yc (TL. GR03THWAIT) L.B. Walsh-Atkins, Esq., Political Department, Oommonwealth Relations Office Downing Street, S.W.l.C^PY |' j \f ^'’•^ A TION^ INWARD SAVING TELEGRAM id ^ «ck 7ii&lt; DOMINIONS OFFICE /iVos*(BY A ' A 4^0 ALLOTTED TO POLITICAL (SXT.) DSPARTMSNT PROM: U. R. HIGH C 0 MM IS SIOI-TER IN PAKISTilN* 0. KARACHI, -lUth July, -19^8 R. 22nd No.148 SAVING. Jnly ’ s /o; SECRET. ^ Your telegram No ,837 da ted 11th May* Visit of W/Cdr. Griffiths to Kabul, 2. When requesting permission for special Karachi-Kabul flight from Afghan Embassy and. Pakistan Government, we unfortunately quoted verbatim objects of visit as stated in your telegram under reference, Pakistan Government have since asked for a copy of the plan prepared by the Air Ministry for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force, They were told that we had no copy. 3. I now understand from my Air Adviser (who has had unofficial talks with Pakistan Defence Ministry officials)that the Pakistan Government consider Commonwealth membership entitles them to the supply of information direct from us on matters within our knowledge relating to military preparations in a neighbouring country. They have been told that their interest is being conveyed to you and advised to raise matter with you through their High Commissioner in London, 3* I am sorry to have caused you this possible embarrassment. But as it appears from Griffith’s report that the plan as it now stands must be regarded as a dead letter, you may feel that you can give the Pakistan Government some information about it, A copy of this Savingram has been sent to H.M. Ambassador, Kabul, /Cop ies toBrigadier barker. Foreign Office - Mr, Tull, (3) Air Miny, - Mr, M.W, Low, S.6. ' ' W/Cdr, Griffiths, Monk House, War Office - Major Gen, Packard, i/ asfT; i i ft- WT: '( V IVictoria 8 * 4.56 From: Wing Commander A.R.L. Griffiths 10 Tel. No. AIK MINISTRY, ^ ' *r\ &gt; • Vo ^iJ Jt 1 17, MOKGK 3TES2T, A.P.L.4.A-' D^-r /indexed I 1 *? S -V-- i * ’ w S&gt; 6 th Juljr, 1945* IV k. 348 With reference to your letter Pol«B xt» 16 * 4 - 99 /A -8 dated 2nd July 1914.85 concerning ray report on ny'visit to Afghanistan. As n^ted in ny report I was unahle, through lack of time, to discuss with the U*K.» High Commissioner in Pakistan the question you raise4l ahout IvicvVhannell obtaining permission from the Pakistan authorities to fly to Kabul* I did discuss this, however, with KoWhannell himself and with the acting Deputy ^ligh Commissioner, Mr. Cotton, and they consider that there would be no difficulty from Hie U.K. High Commissioner’s point of view, provided that ; as explained in the reportjLcYrtiannell was provided with an aircraft for his use. I also understood from them that there was unlikely to be any difficulties with the x-akistan Government in arranging^terja^for these flights as required. The impression I received from Mr* Cotton and Mc.Yhannell was that as these flights were unlikely to be of greater frequency than three or four months’ intervals they did not anticipate any objections from the Pakistan Government. It will of course only be proved in the event &amp; whether this supposition is correct and the occasion is not likely to arise in the inmediate future, at least until the question of whether an aircraft can be provided for McWhannell has been settled* I hope this makes the position clear as far as I know it. I am sending a copy of this letter to Mr. Tull (i ? oreign Office). Whitehall, S. W. 1 • (Attention Hr. Walsh—Atkins)i A MvE XT r Revolt, on A,:i, L t . Griffith s ,&gt; Air M inist ryi A ,F,L., 2 Ath May - 28th May» 1 9A§ » INTRODUCTION 1 , Prior to the partition of India into the two dominions of India and Pakistan, responsibility for the administration and welfare of R.A.P. personnel seconded’to the Royal Afghan Air Force had been assumed by Air Headquarters, India, After the partition, this responsibility was transferred to the Air Ministry, D.D,A.F,L. with effect from 1?th November, 1947. 2, No details were forwarded by Air Headquarters India of the terms under which the R.A, F, personnel were serving in Afghanistan. It was therefore decided to send an Air Ministry Staff Officer to Afghanistan to enquire into conditions on the spot and to make the necessary arrangements for their proper administration and welfare. , 3, Prior to my departure, the question of the appointment of an Air Attache in Afghanistan was’ raised. The Foreign Office ruled that it would be politically undesirable to raise this matter with the Afghan authorities at the present moment, and it was suggested that the Air Adviser to the United Kingdom High Commissioner for Pakistan should assume responsibility for the local administration and welfare of R.A.F. personnel in Afghanistan. It was agreed that this matter could best be discussed and. settled on the spot. 4. I left Lyncham by R.A.F. Transport Command York aircraft on 19th May, 1948, and arrived at Karachi on 22nd May, 1948, I made contact with Group Captain R, Grice, O.B.E. , D.F.C., Officer Commanding R.A.F, Staging Post, Mauripur, Wing Commander R,D. Baughan, Wing Commander Flying, Wing Commander P.A. McWhannell, Air Adviser to the United Kingdom High Commissioner in Pakistan and Squadron Leader G.F. Reid, D.F,G. , Pilot Instructor to the Royal Afghan Air Force who- was in Karachi, I found that arrangements had been made for me to be flown to Kabul in a Dakota.of the R.A.F. Communication Flight, Mauripur, accompanied by Wing CommanderMcWhannolland Squadron Leader Reid. We left Karachi on the morning of 24th May, 1948 and arrived in Khwaja Rawash airfield, Kabul via Peshawar in the afternoon, where we were met by the Military Attache, Colonel A.S. Lancaster, C.I.E. , O.B.E. On arrival, we found that H.M. Ambassador, Sir Giles Squire, K.B.E. , C.I.E.. had invited Wing Commander McWhannell and myself to stay at the British Embassy during our visit in Kabul. 5 . During the evening of the 24th May, 1948 I was introduced to His Excellency Ali Mohammed Kahn, the Foreign Minister and General Muhd Umar Kahn, Private Secretary to H.M. The King. In the .afternoon of 29 th May, 1948, a meeting was arranged v/ith Lieutenant Colonel Abdur Razaq Khan, the Acting Commandant of the Royal Afghan Air Force, at which the problems facing the Royal Afghan Air Force were discussed generally. Squadron Leader Reid was present at this meeting. In the morning of 26th May, 1948, a discussion was held with Colonel Lancaster. I then mot the R.A.F. N.C.O. Instructors, Warrant Officdr'R.L. Blyth, Fitter IIA Instructor and Sergeant A. Hammond, Wireless Instructor. This was followed by a meeting with His Excellency General Asadullah Khan who holds the posts of Chief of the General Staff, Officiating Commandant of the Royal Afghan Air Force and Acting War Minister. At this meeting, the Air Ministry plan for the expansion of the Royal Afghan Air Force was discussed, together with other problems affecting the R.A.F, personnel seconded to Afghanistan, In the afternoon a visit was paid to the airfield at Sherpur, where I was shown round the hangars, workshops, stores and training school by Colonel Razaq Khan. In the evening, a dinner was given by the Ambassador at which Generals Asadullah, Umar and Colonel Razaq were present. ITINERARY / 6. G. 1 69630/IMM/6A8.G.169630/IMM/6A8. ■n* 2 . 6 . In the morning of the 2?th May, 1948&gt; I had an interview with the Ambassador together with Colonel Lancaster, In the afternoon, a tea party was arranged at Paghman, a hill station some ten miles from Kabul, at which ^ we were entertained by Colonel Razaq and several Afghan Air Force officers. On the return from this trip, final talks were held with the Ambassador, Colonel Lancaster and Squadron Leader Reid, The aircraft left Kabul for Karachi in *the early morning of 28th May, I arrived back in United Kingdom on 3rd June, 1948, A detailed itinerary is at Appendix ’A’, AFGH AN AIR' FORCE Air Ministry Plan for Exp ansion o f Roya l Afghan A ir F orc e. 7. Prior to my departure for A-fghanistari, a five year plan for the expansion oi the Royal Afghan Air Force to five operational squadrons had been prepared by the Air Ministry at the request of Lieutenant Colonel Razaq Khan, who had been in U.K. negotiating for the supply of 12 Avro Ansons. This plan was handed to Colonel Razaq before he returned to Afghanistan, In my talk with General Asadullah and with Colonel Razaq, I enquired whether the plan as prepared by the Air Ministry had met with the approval of the Afghan authori ties or whether it was considered too ambitious to be effected. General Asadullah expressed the Afghan Government's thanks for this plan and said that he was satisfied with it. He wished to know however the cost involved in putting the plan into effect and said that until this cost could be estimated, it would not be possible to say to whq.t extent the plan could be implemented. He also asked, speaking infoimally, whether 1 could say what assistance Air • Ministry could give in reducing the cost to the Afghan Government of putting' the plan into effect, namely, by free training dr by the free provision of instructors. I explained that I was unable to give any assurances on mis matter as it was outside my terms of reference, 8 . In consultation with Colonel Lancaster and Squadron Leader Reid, sub sequent to the above-mentioned meeting, it was obvious that the plan as pro duced was too ambitious for the Afghan Air Force as at present constituted, due to many reasons of which the chief are the very'small numbers of trained personnel at present in the Air Force, the method of recruiting and the low standard of recruits, the very evident lack of money and the lack of facilities at present existing in Afghanistan, It was therefore agreed with f H.M. Ambassador that no useful object would be served by costing the plan for the expansion as at present prepared, since it could not be put into practice// no matter what the cost, *‘ I Recruit ing for the Af ghan A ir Force, ,9» One of the main 1 actors which will .prejudice any rapid advancement of the Afghan air Force is the problem of recruiting. The present educational standard of recruits is very low, and the only source of better educated recruits is from the output ol two schools and a military academy whose pupils come from the more wealthy Afghan families. These pupils on leaving invariably require to be granted commissions before they can be attracted into the military services, and there is therefore no class from which • * recruits can be drawn who would make satisfactory technical N.C.O.'s or tradesmen, ^he only solution to the problem would appear to be to change the basis of recruiting which is largely by short term conscription, and to accept young recruits^on a long-term basis who could be educated while in the Air Force. This is of course a very long-term policy. /ivro Anson X VIII . 10 . It was agreed that the much more pressing need of the Afghan Air Force was the maintenance of the Avro Anson XVIII, the first of which was due / to■ I 3. to arrive in Kabul shortly after I left, (it has since been learnt that this first^iinson crashed in transit at Kiwani, Persia and is written off). It was therefore decided that Squadron Leader Reid should prepare a simple scheme for the training ol pilots and greund personnel to operate and maintain these Avro Anson aircrait. This scheme would be submitted in draft form to the Air Ministry who would complete it, estimate the cost and present-it to the Afghan Government as a proposal for immediate action. This would ensure that a workable scheme could be started on, which when complete would provide the nucleus of trained personnel on which the Afghan Air Force could expand to the proposed five squadrons of Fireflies at a later date if required. This proposal would have the added advantage that the training commitment for the Royal Afghan Air Force would be small. Assist ance by R.A .F. perso nnel 11 . It was apparent during my visit that the Afghan Air Force authorities ^ avc ^ co:riG ^ G P enc '’‘ very much on the guidance and help given to them by the R.a. . , Instructors , and that without this help the Royal Afghan Air Force would hardly be capable of operating its aircraft satisfactorily. This will apply oven more v/hen the Avro Ansons are received and the Afghan Government are therefore most anxious that the R.A.F. Engineer Officer and the N.C.O. fitter Instructor for which they have asked should be sent out as soon as possible. 'his ofiicer and N.C.O. have now been selected and will be leaving as soon as can be arranged. Bonuses for R.; J^ r sonne 1 4 I 12. It was the* practice to give R.A.F. Instructors v/ho satisfactorily com pleted a t 'ur with the Afghan Air Force a present on leaving, such as a watch, carpets, or a money grant. This practice v/as dropped in the case of Warrant Officer Waterhouse, the N.C.O. Fitter Instructor who was recently repatriated and it is understood that the iii'ghan authorities propose to present him with a medal, ihis procedure if adopted is likely to be continued for all R.A.F, personnel who complete two years with the Afghan Air Force. Tiger Noth s 13. The Afghan Air Force have at present eight Tiger Moths which they bought from India before the partition. Those aircraft are in a very dilapidated state and are of little use. Furthermore the five years’ spares which were to have been supplied with, them are incomplete, especially in the supply of air frame-spares, Representations have been made to the Government of India for tnese spares but it is not known what results arc likely to be achieved. If the Afghan Air Force does not eventually receive a full amount of spares, it is likely that they will seek Air Ministry assistance in this matter, Av ro Anson s 14. As stated above, the first Avro Anson was due to arrive at Karachi shortly after l loft. The delay in arrival has been due to difficulty in arranging clearance for these aircraft to fly over Pakistan. It is understood that the Pakistan Government were upset by the fact that the request for clearance came through the British Government and not directly from the Afghan Government, However this difficulty has now been overcome and clearance granted, \ M&amp;jja-tQ ramoe Personnel.sup plied by A,v, R Qe ,. 15. _ The technicians whom Messrs. Avros had agreed to supply at Karachi to assist ^ the Afghan Air Force in maintaining their An sons had arrived at Karachi before I left, where they were first informed that the Afghan Government had decided to carry out training at Kabul .and not at Karachi as originaHy mtonded. This has raised problems concerning their accommodation anc. these technicians had informed Squadron Leader Reid that they w uld not' go to Kabul unless they were provided with free accommodation and a car and / certain G. 1 69639/010/6/48.certain other conditions were net. This is a natter for adjustment between Messrs, Avros and the Afghan Government, R.A,F, PERSONNEL IN AFGHANISTAN Duties of R.A .F. Personnel.. * 16 . One R.A.F. Officer and two R.A.F, N,C,0's are at present serving in Afghanistan, namely Squadron Leader Reid, Pilot Instructor, Warrant Officer. Blyth, Fitter IIA Instructor and Sergeant Hammond, Wireless Instructor, The duties of these personnel exceed their designated functions considerably and, especially in the case of the Pilot Instructor, they are called upon to assist and advise to a very large extent, * • • Living con ditions. 17. Squadron Leader Reid, who is accompanied by his wife and child, is living in a house in the European residential quarter in Kabul, not far from the airfield at Shorpur, The house is rented by hi , but the Afghan authorities pay him the amount oi the rent, .Under Afghan law, a change of ownership of the house permits the new landlord to re-assess the rent, the old rent agreement becoming void. This has caused some trouble and inconvenience to Squadron Leader Reid in the past, due to increases in rent brought about by a change l -1 landlord, but through the influence of the War Minister, the landlord has now been persuaded from charging an excessive rent. Squadron Leader Reid has to buy all his furniture, which is expensive and nay not be imported into Afghanistan, his results in a heavy-initial outlay to R,A,F, personnel arriving for duty in iifghanistan. General Asadullah stated that it was the intention^ to build and furnish houses to accommodate the R.ii.F, Instructors, but this is nqt likely to be put into effect for some oonsiderable time, 18 . Warrant Officer Blyth, who is accompanied by his wife and two children, is living under similar conditions to Squadron Leader Reid, Sergeant Hammond, ..ho is single , is living with Warrant Officer Blyth, which arrangement is considered mutually satisfactory. Cost of L iving 19. The cost of living in Afghanistan is extremely high and prices of food, furniture, and some articles of.clothing are much higher than in United Kingdom. Squadron Leader Reid finds it difficult, though not impossible, to live on his pay of £ 1,750 per year. Warrant Officer Blyth has stated that his pay of £850 per year was definitely insufficient to support himself and his family and he considered that £1 ,200 was necessary. This statement was not confirmed by the Military Attache, however, who thought that £950 per year would be sufficient. It was agreed that the Air Ministry would assess the amount it was considered that Warrant Officer Blyth should receive, in relation to the cost of living in Afghanistan, and when this was' known a ’ decision would be made regarding any approach to the Afghan authorities for an increase in pay for Warrant Officer Blyth. Reereationed facilities . ?V’ ° nC factor 115 high cost of living lies in the fact that there are iittle or no recreational facilities for Europeans residing in Afghanistan and the European community has to rely on itself for its entertainment. XTiis results m a large nuribor of invitations to parties being received by the personnel who feel bound to return this hospitality. The cost of inland drink 'being high, this return for hospitality received involves the personnel in heavier expenditure than would be recognised at home. / Working g, 169 63 o/noy 6 / 4 £.Yforkinfr- condi tions 21. The H.ii.F. personnel work at tho airfield at Shcrpur where the Royal Afghan Air Force is at present hased. Warrant Officer Blyth runs the A,R,S # as well as giving instruction and supervising the .laintenance of aircraft. Sergeant Haixiond is employed largely on instructing a sraall class of wireless mechanics, since the Afghan signals organisation is at present largely non existent, Squadron Leader Reid’s functions are divided between the Headquarters, also at Sherpur, and training Afghan pilots. This latter commitment will become his main task on the arrival of the Ansons, Medic al fac ilities. 22. The Afghan authorities arc willing to provide free medical treatment for the R.A.F, personnel, but this would mean providing the services of an Afghan doctor, v/hich is not considered satisfactory. On the other hand, the Afghan Government will not pay for tho services of a European doctor for attendance on R.A.F, personnel or their families, 23. The British Embassy has at present a surgeon on strength who attends the R.A.F. personnel as required though this is not strictly within his terms of reference and he can, and in fact,has charged for his services. It is under stood however that this surgeon is shortly to be withdrawn and the Embassy will have to roly on*a*German or French doctor at present working in Kabul. This will leave the R.A.F. personnel witliout free medical attention. There are two possible solutions to this problem:- The Foreign Office, it is understood, are willing to pay the sum of BifOO towards the cost of a doctor, and II.M. Ambassador hopes that the American Embassy in Kabul will also contribute £400. It is hoped thereby to obtain a doctor who will, be able £0. supple ment the £800 thus received by private x-ractice. Should this prox)osal be put into effect, then arrangements oould be made for the R.A.F, x^ersonnel to pay to the Embassy funds' a small yearly .sum and they would then be covered for medical attention in the same way as the Embassy staff. Payment by the R.A.F. personnel of contributions under the National Health Scheme may autom atically entitle them to free treatment by.this doctor, and con sideration should be given to this asxoect. The alternative proposal is that the Embassy would contract with a European doctor at present working in Kabul, who would attend the Embassy staff as required. By arrangement with the Embassy, and the payment by the R.A.F. personnel to the Embassy funds of a small yearly sum, the R.A,F. could be included in this scheme, CONDITIONS OF SERVICE ' ' • 24. The loan of the Pilot Instructor, Squadron Leader Reid is covered by the terns of a contract which is generally satisfactory. There arc however two points not covered by the contract which require clarifying. These are: (a) The contract for Squadron-Leader Reid specifies that his tour of service commences on the date of crossing the Afghan frontier and terminates similarly. This was satisfactory when the R.A.F. was in India, since Squadron Leader Reid could be brought back on to R.A.F. strength with effect from the date of arrival in India, Now however the time taken in travelling from Afghanistan to United Kingdom must be covered. It is recoixicnded that Squadron Leader Reid should be officially reabsorbed into R.A.F, strength G.169630/DMM/6/A8. / andG. 16963O/DMH/6/48. his pay from R,A, F. sources reconinenced with effect from the date of leaving Afghanistan. ('b) Payment under the new National health scheme is not covered and it will he necessary for some arrangements to be made concerning this. 25. There is no contract for the loan of Warrant Officer Blyth or Sergeant Hammond. It was agreed that the contract for the services of these two N.C.O's.should be prepared by Air Ministry and submitted for agreement to the Afghan Government. The Afghan authorities agreed that this would be acceptable to them. 26 . A draft contract was prepared for the Squadron Leader Engineer Officer due to leave United Kingdom shortly for Afghanistan and I took a copy of this draft contract to Afghanistan. The basis of this contract was that the officer should be paid from Air Force funds and the Afghan Government would subsequently reimburse the Air Ministry. This proposal was unacceptable to the Afghan Government because of their system of contracts, and it was therefore necessary to re-draft the contract. __ Due to lack of time, this could not be done before I left, but agreement in principle was reached.con cerning the terms of service for this officer, and a new contract is now being prepared by Air Ministry for submission to the Afghan Government. 27. A similar contract must be prepared for the N.C.O. Fitter Instructor also due to.leave United'Kingdom shortly. Social A meneties . 28 . The Afghan Government do not acknowledge that any si^ecial provision should be made for married personnel and the pay offered is the same whether the officer or airman is married or not. It is therefore desirable x’rom this point of view that only unmarried personnel should be sent to Afghanistan but this is offset by the lack of social amenities for the unmarried officer or airman. H.M. Ambassador stated that hitherto he had considered it undesirable for unmarried personnel to be sent to Afghanistan, but that as the European population had, since the end of the war, increased, this was not now the stumbling block it was. AH'IIKESTAATIVE ARRANGEMENTS Responsibility of Air Adviser to the U.K,-High Commissioner in Pakistan. 29. Wing Commander McWhannell, the Air Adviser to the United Kingdom High Commissioner for Pakistan, who accompanied me on my tour was present at all the meetings referred to above. It was agreed that, in order that a senior R.A,F. officer might be available at short notice to assist in advising H.M. Ambassador in Kabul on natters of R.A.F. discipline, welfare and administration, that Wing Commander McWhannell could supervise on behalf of the Air Ministry the R.A.F. personnel in Afghanistan. This would necessi tate infrequent visits, at not more than three to four months intervals, when problems encountered by the R.A.F. personnel could be brought to his notice and arrangements could be made on the spot to overcome any difficulties. 30 . This proix&gt;sal was welcomed by H.M. Ambassador and the Military Attache, Kabul and the Acting Deputy High Commissioner in Karachi, as it was felt thht such a liaison might assist in bringing the Afghan and Pakistan authorities in closer touch. The Military Attache, Kabul.suggested that eventually the Air Adviser might become officially accredited as Air Attache to the Afghan Government. It was apparent, however, that this I arrangement could only work provided that Wing Commander KcWhanndll had an / aircraftaircraft at his disposal. Present method of travel from Karachi to Kabul and return involves a minimum of eight days travelling, in order to spend one day in Kabul, whereas Kabul is only 5i hours flight from Karachi (see Appendix 'B'), Wing Commander ivicWhannell has already submitted*, a ease for provision of an '^aircraft in order to carry out his duties in Pakistan satisfactorily. Provided that this .aircraft is supplied, the arrangement for Wing Commander McWhannell to supervise the R.A.F, personnel in Afghanistan is acceptable. Should it not be possible to provide an aircraft for him, some alternative arrangements must be made. General Asadullah ensidered there would be no difficulty in obtaining permission for Wing Commander McWhannell to fly into Afghanistan whenever required, 31. It was agreed that, should the Air Adviser become responsible for the welfare of R.A.F. personnel in Afghanistan, he should receive copies of all correspondence passing between .the Air Ministry and Afghanistan which affected the discipline, administration and welfare of the R.A.F. personnel. In addition, it was suggested that Squadron Leader Reid should send a monthly report to the Air Adviser on these matters with a copy to the Air Ministry, D.D.A.F.L. for information. C orrespondence with th e A i r Minis try 32. It was agreed with II,M, Ambassador and Military Attache, Kabul that Squadron Leader Reid could correspond direct with the Air Ministry, D.D.A.F.L, on all matters affecting the administration of R.A.F, personnel in Afghanistan and in matters relating to the provision of training assistance, such as the provision of publications, syllabi and training equipment, for the Afghan Air Force. He would not however correspond with the Air Ministry on matters of policy or matters affecting the political situation, or on Air Force intelli gence natters which would continue to be dealt with by the Military Attache as hitherto. \ 33. The following is a summary of the impressions I received during my visit: (a) The Afghan authorities rely&gt;considerably on the assistance given'by the R.A,F.. personnel in Afghanistan and wish this help to be* continued and extended. They are willing to pay for the services of these R.A.F. Instructors. (b) The R.A.F. Instructors at present in Afghanistan are being usefully employed and without their assistance the Afghan Air Force would have difficulty in maintaining any operational value. (c) The conditions under which these Instructors arc living and serving are reasonable, though the pay of the N.C.O. Instructors might justifiably be raised. In order that the interests of the R.A.F. N.C.O.'s should be safeguarded, it is necessary that a contract governing their terms of service should be prepared and agreed with the Afghan authorities as soon as possible. (d) ‘ It cannot bo expected that any great advances will be made by the Afghan Air Force in the near future, since there is a sjtrong clement which is extremely resistant to change. Until this non progressive element is removed andjarrangenents made to improve conditions of service and attract the right kind of recruit, it is considered there is little chance of the Royal Afghan Air Force becoming an efficient up-to-date force. It is understood however that action is to bo taken to achieve this. / (e) G. 169 630/DMJt/6/48.G. 169630 /DIlv / 6 /A 8 . ', 8 . (e) The Afghan Government are extremely anxious for any financial assistance v/hich can he given by the British Government in help ing then to build up their Air Force. It is xx&gt;ssible that by insisting that any help given, either by providing Instructors or in training, must be paid for, the Afghan Government may look elseT/here for this assistance. They realise however that the previous help they have received from the R.A.F. has been invaluable to them and I consider that this possibility while it cannot be ignored, is at present not likely to occur. The R.A.F. enjoys a unique position with the Afghan Air Force at the moment and it can be confidently expected that the Afghan Government will continue to seek RfA.F. assistance and advice, CO it is considered that the Air Adviser to.the U.K, High Commissioner in Pakistan can supervise the administration and welfare of the R.A.F. personnel in Afghanistan, provided that he is supplied with an aircraft. If an aircraft cannot be provided, it is recommended' that reconsideration should be given to the question of appointing an Air Attache in Afghanistan. Diam-BUJXQJN 1 • AixJJipiatry External Foreign Office (Hr. Tull) Commonwealth Relautions Office A. 1.3. Ob). 2. A.c.L,1. A, F, L. A* S.A. O). S. 6 . D.D.A. F.L (Mr. Yi alsh-Atkins) H.M, Ambassador, Kabul. Mi 1 itary At t ache, Kabul. Squadron Leader Reid, Kabul War Office. U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan Air Adviser to U.K. High Commissioner in Karachi. A.D.T.(Plans) D. D.2,1 A. D.D. of Sigs.(p) / ■• / APPENDIX Report..-S lU- vi sit . to Afghanistan . by W ing Coixiander A t R.L . Griffiths, Air Ilini s try, A .F. 1,4., o n 24 -th H ay - 28th H ay, 1948. Norraal Hethod of Trave l - Kar achi to Kabul and Return Monday By Orient Airline to Peshawar, Arrive 13.30 hours. Tuesday Stay at Peshawar. Wednesday By Embassy lorry from Peshawar to Jalalabad Thursday Jalalabad to Kabul, Arrive p.o. Friday At Kabul, Saturday Via Embassy lorry Kabul to Jalalabad Sunday Jalalabad to Peshawar Monday By Orient Airlines to Karachi. Arrive 23,00 hours. ; G, 169630/01.11/6/4.8.fht&amp;cU' — This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate it to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office FINANCE a ECONOMIC DEPT. D.I ^ (B) 121U7/U8 v/PHER(TYPEX) TO:U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN (Sent 1 .UO p.m. 14th May 1948) IMPORTANT No. 856 SECRET For Cotton from Tims. Your letter to Gordon No. 217 dated 6th April. Pakistan Note to Moscow. Although we entirely agree with the object of the Note v/e feel that Pakistan Government gain nothing, and very likely risk embarrassment for themselves and others, by advancing arguments based on Chicago Convention and Air Transit Agreement, since Russia is not a signatory of either and cannot claim privileges under them. Main stand can best be taken on Pakistan Aircraft Rules, which, vis-a-vis Russia are quite sufficient. 2. Furthermore, sentence in paragraph 4 (ii) of the Note beginning 'Accordingly the Government of Pakistan' and ending 'from the West' would seem to invite application from the Russians to fly to Pakistan via the western route and Karachi. The terms of the Note suggest that Pakistan would not wish them to come that way either. 3* If you see no objection, v/e think that you.should put these points to Pakistan Government and suggest for their consideration that best line for us to instruct U.K.Embassy Moscow to take on their behalf might be as follows:- (a) reference to Indian Aircraft Rules, 1937; (b) if Soviet aircraft are permitted to fly over prohibited areas Pakistan Government may be obliged as party to the Chicago Convention to open route to aircraft of o^hcr states. This Pakistan Government is not prepared to do; /(c) Government(c) Government of Pakistan therefore hope that they will not he placed in embarrassing position of having to refuse permission to Soviet aircraft to use Peshawar-Lahore route. ^ou could explain that our motive in making these suggestions is to strengthen their hand so that they may he in better position to secure their objective. You could also say that we would, of course, transmit the Note in its present form if Pakistan Government so desire,‘though in this case we strongly urge that, as a minimum amendment, the words 'of contracting states' should be inserted after 'the first airport of call for aircraft' in sub-paragraph (ii) of paragraph U» ^* -ith reference to paragraph 3 of my telegram No. 837 , you will see from the foregoing that concessions to your Air Adviser would not entitle Russians to claim similar facilities under any international instrument. Pakistan could also (a) refer to the Commonwealth relationship, and/or (b) hold out for similar facilities between Pakistan Embassies in Kabul and Moscow. V/G appreciate that this matter may have been made more delicate by recent Pakistan decision to exchange diplomatic representatives with Russia. But communication suggested above may help to bring home to Pakistan Government potential inconveniences to them of that decision. Cony to : Mr.James Murray, Foreign Office Ivir, ./alsh .M-tkins, Political Dept.‘I*- :» [This telegraa is of particular secrecy and should be_ retained by the authorised recipient &amp;nd not passed on] Cypher/OTP DEPARTMEFfAL DISTRIBUTICF FROM KABUL TO FOREIGN OFFICE 3ir G-. Squire No &gt; 115 D. 5.05 p.m. 20th May, 1948 20th May, 1948 R. 3.51 p.'H. 20th May, 1948 Repeated to Karachi. MPOKTANT SECRET Add re ssed to Foreign Office telegra.ui No. 115 of M ay 20th, repeated for information to Karachi. ^Iy t elegram No. 113, and Karachi tele gram NQ ( 519 to Commonwealth Relations office. Afghan Government agree to visit of Griffiths and McWhannell by air. 2. V/ill Karachi please telegraph firm'&gt;c Sir &amp;. Squire. No. 115. 14th Hay, 1948. SECRET. 1 &amp; f r rhis telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on] Cypher/OTP. DJff^RTMENTi.L PISTRIBUTION , FROM IQ^BUL TO FOREI&amp;N OFFICE. D. 3.30 p.m. 14th May, 1948. R. 2.50 p.m. 14th May, 1948. te;L ^ rajI1 No.99. Visit of Wing Commander Griffiths. Lancaster will delay his tour till early June, 2. .Wing Commander must (repeat must) wear mufti. I presume he will travel on an unarmed military transport aircraft. 3. I am making official request to Afghan Government but do not anticipate difficulty securing their assent to visit. m(fubto/wsfey f ^f 2 umajQ/A. ~ With the compi/m^ts of the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs Reference: — FILE COPY Copies also sent to: — 34910 £\OUTWARD TELEGRAM j* i ['iliia telegram is of particular secrecy and should be' retained by the authorised recipient arid not passed ori] * i .a'.. Cypher/CSP DEPjffiTii 1 iJl«'AL DISTRIBUTION p Secret FROju FOitjilGM ORigCii! TO KkBUL Ii2^_99 D, 5.55 pm. 11th my, 1948. • 11th toy, 1948. SDCRDT My telegram No. 76 [of 1st April: Senior Air Force Officer to Ivahull, Officer selected is Wing Commander A.R.L. Griffiths who expects to leave here 20th May spending a day in Karachi and arriving Kabul by air 24th or 25th. 2, Firm A.T,A 0 will be sent as soon as possible. In the meantime, we suggest that Lancaster's tour referred to in your telegram No. 107 might profitably be deferred until early’June so that the benefit of his service and experience can be available to Griffiths while he is in Kabul, ,This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate it to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office POLITICAL DEPARTMENT (B ) Pol&gt;Ext. 1 G'\ 5 i|-/l+?n CYPHER (TYPEX) TO: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN (SENT: 17.15 hours, 18th May 1948) IMPORTANT No.874 . Your telegram No.519* Visit of Wing Commander Griffiths to Kabul, Your paragraph 3« Both presumptions confirmed. He already has visa. 2, His E.T.A. Karachi remains as p.m. 21st. Copies to : - Foreign Office - Mr. Thll (3). Air Miny. (S,6)~ Mr. 'Low. War Office - Majo leral Packard, C.R.O - Mr.»iara&lt;o ( ' a y 10 . Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ucl Vc AiAOTTED TO POLITICAL DEPARTMENT (B) cypher (o.t.p.) Ai'h, FROM : U«K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN* RPTD.TO i KABUL ( No* 37 ) D. KARACHI* 15th May, 1948* R. 17*00 hours, 15th May, 1948* IMMEDIATE * NO i, £ 12 &gt; Your telegram 857, 11th May not rep eated to Kabul* Visit of Wing Commander Griffiths to Kabul* 2* I have no objections to McWhannell accompanying Griffiths* Provisional arrangements are being made for staging post aircraft to (?omission) the party to Kabul on 24th May, returning Karachi on 28th May* Permission of Pakistan and Afghanistan authorities is being sought, 3 * We presume Griffiths holder of passport* We are arranging visas for the rest of party and could probably obtain one for Griffiths here if he has not already obtained it. Party will presumably travel in civilian clothing* 4* Griffiths should be advised to ensure that his yellow fever and cholera inoculation comply with international regulations* Foreign Office Mr. T,S. Tull (3). Air Ministry - Mr* ftLW, Low, 11 ff - W/C^rJ Griffiths, Monk House, Maj /# Gen* Packard* War Office C, R* 0* - Mr* Tims, 1 / 1 itl 'This is an unparaph-rased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate It to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office ‘ CYPHER (TYPEX) TO: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN. ( SENT 21.45 hours, 11th May, 1948) IMPORTANT No. 837. On proposal of Air Ministry, Wing Commander A.R.L. Griffiths will leave United Kingdom on 19th May for a visit to Kabul to discuss with Squire and with the Afghan authorities (a) problems regarding the employment of R.A,F. personnel by the Afghan Air Force; (b) the assistance which the Air Ministry cun give in training Afghan Air Force personnel, and (c) other problems regarding the plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force which the Air Ministry prepared for the Afghan Air Force Chief of Staff on his recent vixit to London. 2. We think that there would be advantage in Griffiths being accompanied by McWhannel if you agree. We fully appreciate your reluctance to be deprived of your Air Adviser for periods of any length (Burnett*s telegram to V/alsh-Atkins No.474 of 6 th May); but we hope that despite the short notice of this request you will be able to spare McWhannel to accompany Griffith Duration of stay in Kabul is expected to be only about 4 days. 3» We suggest that future arrangements for our Air representat tion at Kabul should be discussed during and in the light of Griffiths’ and McWhannel f s trip. We hope to be able to provide you with good arguments to refute Pakistan Government’s fear that if they allow your Air Adviser to fly to Kabul similar POLITICAL DEPARTMENT (b) /facilities// £ y;ill have to be given to Russians# Visits by your Air Adviser to Kabul v;ould be quite infrequent# ’ * 4» In present case we should greatly prefer the party to fly '• direct from Karachi to Kabul to save tine, as Lancaster is due to leave Kabul on tour shortly. The Air Ministry have no objection to use of staging-post aircraft, about which McWhannel wrote to them on 17th April# Unless you see strong objection please seek permission for this special occasion. Failing this please make most expeditious alternative arrangements, on assumption that Griffiths will reach Karachi on evening of 21st May# • v &lt; '&lt; Copy to ( W/Cdr#/Griffiths, Monk House© g* F.a, 194 Despatched M. SECRET My telegram No. 76 /of* 1st April: Senior Air Force Officer to Kabul/ Officer selected is Wing Commander A.R.L. Griffiths who expects to leave here 20th May spending a day in Karachi and arriving Kabul by air 24th or 25th. 2. Firm E. T.A. will be sent as soon as possible. In the meantime, we suggest that Lancaster's tour referred to in your telegram No. 107 might profitably be deferred until early June so that the benefit of his advice and experience can be available to Griffiths while he is in Kabul. A a. ,// ' As ffa '+si'C i it &gt; c_ RLE COPY f^ix-r^j This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and the text must first be paraphrased If it is essential to If*/Y to persons outside British and United States Government Services.: 1 ' f i. ' ~ Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relatio ALL0TT3D TO POLITICAL DEPT.f Bl iokrOffhre- CYPHER(TYPEX) FROM : II.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN D. Karachi, 18.00 hours, 6th May 1948 R. 16.20 hours, 6th May 1948 IMPORTANT No. 474 SECRET. Walsh-Atkins from Burnett. Your letter Ext. 5710/48 April 6th: Kabul Air Attache. V.-e see no objection in principle to arrangement mentioned in your paragraph 3 but there are practical uiffieulties. Owing to length of (? absence) otherwise involved, High Commissioner could only spare Air Adviser for periodical visits to Kabul if latter had his own aircraft for the purpose. Pakistan Government would not repeat not be likely to welcome regular flights by Air Adviser over North-West frontier for reasons explained in their Ministry of Foreign Affair s note dated 24th Mar ch on subject of non-scheduled flight via Peshawar by Soviet aircraft copy sent with Cotton’s letter C- _to Gordon No. 217 fif g t^ApiaL, Objection is likely to be even «&gt; Iro . stronger, since Pakistan^ Government would apprehend that ^rant of permission for flights by our Air Adviser would lead to 'W u V Ck JiUL lsoWj( request from Soviet Embassy for same facilities. C opies to : \ Foreign Office Air Ministry/s.6) War Office ' V Mr.P.Grey Mr.M.W.Low Maj.Gen.Packardtil'll T'' iCKiJvTIOR S OFPICB, DOW3NG iiTRKKT .ear Fumett, Tkus is anly to ask if you will shortly be able to let me bawe a reply to my letter of 6th April Ko* ifct* 5710/4^ about periodic visits to Kabul by the High Commissioner's &lt;*ir Adviser. Lieutenant Colonel K.K.Pumett, 1«L. ^ 0.f-« i‘i • Yours sincerely. Office of the United Kingdom High Commissioner, Pakistan*mam IVSSS lo? OUTWARD TELEGRAM retained by the authorised recipient and not^assed on]. 1st April, 1948. D. 11.10 a.m. 2nd April, 1948. Air Ministry desire to send a Senior Staff Officer to Kabul to discuss with you and the Afghan authorities can give in training fghan Air Force personnel; and the expansion of the Afghan .dr Force which the Air Ministry prepared for the .dghan .dr Force Chief of Staff on his recent visit to London. 2. Fe have informed the .dr Ministry that we have no objection to this visit, but have suggested that the Air Ministry Staff Officer should be accompanied by a Senior dir Force Officer from the United Kingdom High Commissioner’s staff in Karachi on his visit. 3. F e vail inform you when we know the name of the officer selected and the date of his departure. Cypher/OTP SECRET DEPARTMENT.iL DISTRIBUTION FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO K.JBUL No. 76 SECRET (a) problems regarding the employment of R.a.F. personnel by the Afghan .dr Force; (b) the assistance which the .dr Ministry (c) other problems regarding the plan for 0 0 0 0(16354) Wt. 22753-8 10m 9/47 G.S.St. V- At ? C. R. O. Mr. Walsh-Atkins. V V4^. f Mr. Mr. Mr. Sycrs Sir Charles Dixon Depy. U.S. of S. Permt. U.S. of S. Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State. ^ /lx 6 APR Dear Burnett, The Air Ministry suggested that as Air Headquarters^ India no longer exists, it would be DRAFT. LETTHR. in our interest to appoint an Air Attache to our Embassy at Kabul with a rank of Wing Commander, Lt • Col, R.R .Burnett, Clfi - OBE ♦ &lt;%- £t lef o.«.~ rs. r His duties would be to study the development of the Afghan Air Force and supervise the work of its R.A.F. advisers. 2. The War Office are agreeable. But while both Squire and the Foreign Office welcome the proposal in general, they doubt, for reasons both political and financial, whether the time is quite r~ Jj tx**. • ^ c^. o-uz-* ciilboC*- Lr\ rc { opportune to make such an appointment. U.CLA 3* In consequence it had been suggested that the solution for the time being might be that the Further action. i:P A . ? c e-'t-. % 3 //^/%. / a. C &lt; i . C Air Adviser to the United Kingdom High Ccmmissioner in Pakistan should make periodic visits to Kabul • 7s to/supervise the work of the R.A.F. advisory staff. We=-*houi^=the?»efore j be glftd-to knuw-whflthej^-the High- Comini ssi nner-wev.ld see any Qh jectio» te~this-5219 BJ/3S7/8.6. !&gt;•«• Orey # Thank you for your letter ?.2BG5/l')p/g7 of the 9th ! r arch about the establishment of an Air Attache in Kabul* In view o* whet you say # we agree to defer the question of the establishment of the Air Attache for the time *bein£. *'e e^rde also that the Air Adviser to the TJ*K* High Conanlssloner In Pakistan Snruld make periodic visits to Kabul to supervise the work of the R*A*P. Advisory ftcff attached to ^^^an Air ^orce. Perhaps Unes, to whom T am cor.ylng this letter, would say whether there would be any oblfiiction orLthe^pArt of the High Comralceloner to thla arrange out;. wo had not intended that the ranior Air Force Officer In Kabul should communicate direct with the Air Ministry on any matters having political implications* Our intention was that he shoula bo permitted to correspond direct with the Air Ministry on purely air matters, and we should very much like this arrangement to be node* Wo have beard that the F*A*F. Advlsere in Wrbul have b^ep recently experiencing difficulties in carrying out their wortc* They have f ’ouix3 difficulty In drawing their nay from the Afghan authorities, their advice has been some times ignored, and they have been treated occasionally with considerable discourtesy* We are therefore /proposing P* Gray, Eeq*, Foreign Office, # I&gt;owninc °treet, 8* 1. » . ' &gt;• i ' 1943 i soth Him, irb:—En Glair AIR MINISTRY BI FROM KABUL TO FOREIGN OFFICE Sir G. Squire No. 70. D: 4.OO.p.m. March 26th, 1948, R: 2.55.p. m. March 26th, 1948 March 26th, 1948. For.Air Ministry from Military Attache: My telegram 009 dated 13/3/48. Grateful if you will authorise R.a.F. staging post Kauripur Pakistan to issue air passages for 560469 VI/0 Waterhouse and wife some time in April. Yfa ter house was seconded from.R.^.F. in India for duty in Afghanistan. —oOo—U.o&gt; i&gt;lr. ..alsh i.t.&lt;ins « 1. Yoixr fears have been realised - see page 23 '• O • Our policy as regards passing of clas.iiied information to India and Pakistan is : n generally only such top secret and secret information as was necessary for her immediate military needs should be sent to her'. DCOS(46)193(final) 2nd October 1946. This policy v/as re-stated in D.0.(48) 11th Meeting of 15th July 1948 as : 'pending the discussions with Commonwealth Prime Ministers in October, the question of what secret information in the political or the defence field should be communicated to any particular Dominion should be dealt with on an ad hoc basis.' information essential to Pakistan's military needs. Moreover it would be a concerning the air strengths of a foreign country with whom she has a common frontier and whose attitude she has some reason to regard with apprehension, I feel Pakistan will have very real cause to doubt our good will. 3. I think the information required can clearly be regarded as Top Secret most difficult one to dodge. Pakistan knows of the existence of this plan, she knows we have it and she now asxs us categorically xor it. 4. I think we must pass this to the C.O.S. for their opinion, and I think we should say that w r e and the Air Ministry (page 21) are in iavour of granting this request. If we do not pass to Pakistan, a Commonwealth country, iniormation 5. I think we can rely on Pakistan to see that this information does not leak to Afghanistan. In any case I feel we must taxe the risk. B. G. S. 26th August, 1948mm Please see pages 5-9 a nd following and the related minutes. I entirely agree with Brigadier Barker's observations in his note of the 26th August, and after discussion with him, I suggest that I should write to the Foreign Office on the lines of the draft submitted. General Scoones I agree that we shall have to give the Pakistan Government this report, but I do not much like giving it to their High Commissioner’s Office in London, partly because this means that it would pass through quite a large number of hands before it reaches the right quarters in Pakistan and partly because Mr. Ahmad’s letter is not quite the sort of letter which he should have written. I therefore think that the best course would be for the report to be handed to General Cawthorn, in London, if he is still here when a decision has been taken as to what to do, or alternatively through our High Commission at Karachi, if he has returned to India. We can then tell Mr. Ahmad what we have done. We ought perhaps to have a look at the document in question r hef ore we 'decdde what to do with it and for this purpose it would be useful if two copies could be acquired from the Air Ministry. I am rather\hesitant about putting this issue in a cocked hat manner to the Chiefs of Staff. Would it not suffice for us to copy to the Chiefs of Staff Secretariat our letter to the Foreign Office, together with copies of the other relevant papers, with a brief d.o. letter asking whether the Secretariat had any comments. A further consideration in favour of this course is that the political issues affecting our position seem to me to be at least as important as the military ones, and it would be a little awkward if the Chiefs of Staff recommenced a course of action which is different from that wnich seems to us right on political grounds. We would then have to take the matter to Ministers and a lot of trouble and bother would be created for all concerned. 31.8.48.preferable to handle our business through our own representatives on the spot. go into too much detail about this with Sir L.Grafftey-Smith. because I think the less we have about it on paper the better. Do you think that the very much more condensed draft which I attach would meet the case? Please see the papers relating to an arrangement under which the Air Adviser to the High Commissioner in Karachi would extend his duties to include supervision of the R.A.P. in Afghanistan, at pages 3, 6, 16 (paragraphs 29-31) 24, 27 and 29. far ft.n. ud.. Lu*. r. has been no particular development on this matter, «^» r / I have been stalling until we should dispose of the matter of the Afghan Air Force Plan. Air inis try wish to know if we would support them in an application to the Treasury for an aircraft for the High Commission at Karachi which would facilitate the discharge by the Air Adviser of the proposed additional duties. From S. ¥ &amp; G-. File 44/60 which I have just received it looks as 25.10.48. I am rather inclined not to 27.10.48 ; Mr. Rumbold though this is out for the present. The Chancellor of the Exchequer/ -Exchequer has not been able to agree to more than an experimental one-year charter of* one light aircraft for the use of the high Commission at Delhi. Whether Karachi will have any use for this aircraft, does not yet appear: I should imagine that Delhi will want to see how much they can spare it, first. I have therefore told I'r. Crosthwait^ at the Air Ministry that we should not be able to join them in such an application at present,but that if he liked we would try to get the High Commissioner to agree to the arrangement, even if the Air Adviser cannot fly direct to and rKaJnu UPm j I think we ought to go as far as this because^since . / the High Commissioner expressed the view contained in the ^ telegram at 6, Y/ing Commander Griffiths has been out for jufe**'**^ ^ J our to Kabul and it has become clear that the proposed visits by the Air Adviser would be infrequent and brief. /j, a. Cuf' I submit a draft Saving Telegram which, if approved, I would clear with Foreign Office before despatch and also with Air Ministry, though I am sure that they will agree. I suggest that we defer informing Delhi until the arrangement is agreed with Karachi. co-*c-»cce-*vi Wvve, VTo ■ &lt;4, i/tr L ^ 0. touu#. 1 6 N0V194P h.k l\^ do oUr*'*- ■ ' ^ • : et«x Jf*** . U^Yc^ ^ ' Cj °V M 4 ^ dA &gt;/^»ij KcJfcwutl d- (W {2s* odr*to* There is a difference of status between Advisers and Attaches. The latter are sent to foreign countries only and are under the Intelligence directorate of their Ministry; Advisers go to Dominions and are under Operations, not Intelligence. 3. I, therefore, think the attached directive should be sent direct by the Air Ministry to the UKHC and to the Air Adviser with a copy to C.R.O.^ ArflU JU I have discussed this with Crosthwaite and ho accepts above opinion. 4. Amendments suggestedj- Para. 3. Delete 'agreed” and insert 'decided with the agreement of the U.K. Hi$i Commissioner in Pakistan'. I do not think we need raise the point that a copy of the Air Adviser’s report on his Kabul visits should be given to the UKHC. This will, I am sure, be automatic. He is Air Adviser to the U.K.H.C. B.(r.3 . 28th January,1949. r&gt;V L i • A ' Wr, Rumty^ld fith the receipt of Sir L. G•^afftey-SI^ith , s reply at (43) agreeing, though reluctant ly, ^o^ his Air Adviser taking on certain responsibilities in Ttoraofc, the Air Ministry have prepared and sent over to us for concurrence and issue a draft of the Air Adviser's instructions in this regard. I agree with the amendment to paragraph 3 of the draft instructions proposed by Brigadier Barker. I have no other comments on the draft instructions, I am inclined to agree with the view expressed in the foregoing minuting that it would be more appropriate for any such instructions to be issued by the Air Ministry. As a matter of courtesy I think that we should transmit the instructions to Sir L. G-rafftey-Smith in draft under cover of a suitable reply to his Savingram at (43)* This will, incidentally, give the War* Office a similar opportunity of consulting the Military Attache / at Kabul (which they are:9m r '''ttcrv US- \moKS UKWC* . Vc^fe i^cx^ . V/o SUS. d. n UC^ ^ Le *» C\.; c*. ^ b ,? .a ^ C~J c —.. /• 6/« K 'H r l\CL4. c.c£~ o^. cL^CJ^fc X**^- eCls -~&gt; &amp;~c£oa^~—4_ t* ^ • 51// x . ^0 Xc ■ '” ftfc&lt;-*lfris. Jt^f' S&gt;0*»v^ ^ V €—yG&gt; Ol. C? (i Le»5» f.Q, ^ 1.2). w (L£—&lt; /. “/ J d+*olh*~*~ J^ct • \ Sir Cecil Griffin Please see recent correspondence on the proposal that the Air Adviser to the High Conmissioner should,jpay periodic visits to Kabul to supervise R.A*F* personnel V^corided to Royal Afghan Air Force. The High Comnissioner has agreed to the proposal, although with sorne reluctance* in view of the fact that no aircraft is available to transport the Adviser to and from Kabul. We are now av/aiting Sir L.G. Smiths concurrence in the draft instructions to be sent by Air Ministry to his Air Adviser, and it is time to chase him for a reply to our telegram at paper 5 °* It is for consideration whether we could put the proposal into effect at the present time. The Adviser is to go in the interests of R.A.F. personnel, but the R.A.F. people are of course assisting the Afghan Air Force, and it might be held by the Pakistanis that we were acting against their interests. On the other hand, we have our commitments to the Afghans in respect of Air Force ftainaiifcpersonnel, and there has been no suggestion yet that we should withdraw from them. I suggest that we should seek the High Commissioner's views on this point, and I have drafted a telegram accordingly, I have put forward my own view that we should go ahead with the proposal. 1 tL-ir a k l v hy- ^ A fu /7U _ C '-- Ll - /l - ^ ZT X ^ &lt;s. S's. o c-,y 'L.^^ //* (*• ■ tC. it,. (^— ~ C%-&lt;rck. , 6/ &lt; f/‘t&lt;j 65. _ P£t*-~c. ^ Ue^jLr feCc^/e l^A, ^C^J—*V&lt; &gt; I Cl - - . CV&gt;i % o C^ »k Ok *A Vo K t^G Kt^. ^ ^ cl 6t). ^ okmc . V RR ncu\.^c*. » w.xvcj (/\&lt;s/ ''7'S' 'Y* c»^ 6 ^7 Sir Cecil G-riffin , The Draft Savingram at paper 52 did not issue as we received in the meanwhile Karachi Savingram No.62 of 1st April. We agreed that in the circumstances it will not be necessary to raise again the possibility of difficulties arising as a result of the strained relations between Afghanistan and Pakistan. Sir L. G-rafftey-Smith raises again the question of provision of a communications aircraft. A copy of the Air Adviser’s request to Air Ministry on this subject has been received and is at paper 54* I think he is most unlikely to get one, particularly since he is now to go to Kabul only every six months. On this latter point, I have agreed with Foreign Office that this is what the Ambassador in Kabul really means by his curious phraseology quoted in paragraph 2 of paper 51 and I have amended the draft directive accordingly. I now attach a draft letter which I propose to send to Crosthwait at Air Ministry. Do you agree please? 1574.49.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000236_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2028</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000236</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2028</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/65 ‘ESTABLISHMENT OF AN AIR ATTACHE KABUL &amp; LOAN OF AIR PERSONNEL TO AFGHAN GOVNT’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-20T00:26:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (128 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file. At the beginning of the correspondence is a set of file notes: see folios 118-129. Serial numbers in black, blue, and red ink, which occur throughout the file refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 129; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file is predominantly concerned with plans for the supervision of Royal Air Force (RAF) personnel working for the Afghan Air Force at Kabul. This includes the drafting of a directive for Wing Commander P A McWhannel, the Air Adviser attached to the UK High Commission to Pakistan at Karachi, outlining the responsibilities he is to assume over the aforementioned personnel. The file also contains an application from McWhannel for an aircraft to be made available to facilitate regular visits to Kabul: see folios 12-15.Another significant topic covered by the file is a request from the Government of Pakistan for a copy of a plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force; the Air Ministry had prepared a plan for the expansion of the Afghan Air Force at the request of the Afghan Government. A copy of an abridged version of this plan is included in the file: see folios 52-66.A report by Wing Commander A R L Griffiths on his visit to Afghanistan (24-28 May 1948) has also been filed: see folios 88-93. This reports on the Afghan Air Force and the role of RAF personnel. It also tackles the question of supplying an aircraft for the use of the Air Adviser at Karachi.The main correspondents are: HM Minister/Ambassador at Kabul (Giles Frederick Squire), the UK High Commissioner to Pakistan (Sir Laurence Barton Grafftey-Smith), officials of the Air Ministry, officials of the Commonwealth Relations Office, and officials of the Foreign Office.On the inside front cover can be found a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>UK High Commissioner to Pakistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Afghan Air Force</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Adviser, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kabul</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Personnel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000236#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>