<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000029_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:49:29.729Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INDEXED SECRET ■&amp;0OK i I q \ • I U 'T B. 478 . India Office, 13th March, 1%4«&gt; IIEI.DIIAIijJJi 1 ON TIIE OI L OOIiC^SSIQNS IN THE SIETKIffiOLIS OF TIE G-ULF. In the projected discussions with the U.S. Government on oil in the Middle East, it is iiriportant that H.II.G-. f s special strategic and political interests in this area should 'be 'borne in mind. This memorandum is designed to give some account of those interests, to explain our relations with the Rulers 01 1 the States in the Persian G-ulf and our policy generally, and to describe the various oil concessions that have been granted in these States» 2• The G eographical Situ, tion and Treaty position of Sheikhdoms . Except for the Hasa area 'between Koweit and Bahrein, which forms pai c of the territories of Saudi ^rabia, the Arab Sheikhdoms and Muscat cover the whole of the western and southern coast-line of the Persi an Gulf and th- eastern half of the south coast of Arabia. They consist of:- (a) Koweit, (^population 70-90,000; area including the Neutral Zone about 6,000 square miles) occupying a strategical position at the head of the G-ulf between Iraq and Saudi Ar ibia» (b) Bahrein, (population approximately 130,000; area about 200 square miles) a group of islands some 200 miles to the south of Koweit, off the Hasa coast. (c) Qatar, (population about 25&gt;000; area3000 square miles) a promontory south of Bahrain. (d) The seven petty Sheikhdoms of th- Trucial Coast (so-called from the maritime truce imposed in 1820 by the East India Company on the chieftains of this district). Their names in order eastwards from Qatar are;- Abu Ihabi (population 10&gt;000), Libai (population 20,000), Sharjah population/(populr-tion a.2,000) &gt; jnan (populutiun 2,000), Urn al Qav/ain (population 4.»000), .1 Khaitiah (population 1^,000), and ICalba (population 2,000).- (o.) Huso .t, a coastal fringe of territory extending frou the tip of tho peninsula at the i.:uuth cf the Gulf as far as one nd^n Protectorate• ©k. po^'Ul .tion is estinated, c aoeuu h^ili a rail],ion. 3, With the exception of Ivluscat, all these states are _3ri wish protected states in special treaty relations with -- the conr.on form, of treaty the ruler undertalces to have no negotiations with or receive representatives of any power other than tno British Governnent without whose consent he is precluded fron alienating any part of his territory or iron granting '■iiy concessi-Ti for oil, pearl fishing etc. .7e further exercise jurisdicti' n over British subjects and foreigners in their territories and are under certain Obligations to protect then at least on the seaward side, Muscat is in a special posili^ iij its independence is guaranteed 'by a joint Anglo -French declaration nade in 1862 and Muscat is thus entitled'to have direct relations with foreign powers, hut in accordance with his treaties with us the Ruler undertakes not to alienate any part of his territory except to the British Governnent and not to give any oil concession without our pemission* H.ii.G, exercise Jurisdiction in Muscat over British subjects 'but not over foreigners, Muscat's relations however with us, particularly India, are so close that in practice its position roseribles that of a Protectorate* In all the states we respect the independence of the Rulers in internal affairs and intervene only in the case cx serious nai ad i li ni s t rat ion or of the throat of a 'breach ot the peace likely to endanger oui' own or foreign interests. The Political ^osi ^ent in tho Persian Gulf, together with three Political Agents-at Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat -represent British interests on the spot and 'by their/their advice guide the Rulers on lines of policy iavourable t . ur interests. None of the Rulers, except the Gultan of xiusc t, to whom a wcrtine subsidy has been granted in consideration of the strategical facilities which he has placed at our disposal^ receives any financial assistance fron the British Government, 4, Strate[g.c irportance 01' the Sheikhdoms, British interest the Persian Gulf dates from the 17th and 18th Centuriob anu xj . i t -.e earlier stages was concerned primarily with trade. At the beginning of the 19th Century Great Britain entered upon the task at considerable cost to herself of clearing the Gulf cf piracyj of putting down tho slave trade and, later,, gun-running, and of buoying and beaconing its waters for the peaceiul devel^jJiAeut of the corxierce uf ?.11 nations* iis a result the-states ha^e v j . long ejoyed a period of political tranquillity and relati prosperity, while Great Britain on her side has insured herself against the establishment of .any hostile power in the Gulf to threaten her cormunications with India, 5, In recent years, however, and particulrrly since the last war, the strategic importance of the Persian Gulf has greatly increased, for two reasons, firstly because of the development of air transport an 1, secondly, through the discovery of large and strategically placed oil reserves in the territories oi tne Sheikhdoms, ^s regards the first factor, the Persian Gulf is on the most direct air route between this country, the Mediterranean and India, Bahrein,being an important stopping place. It is considered probable thut the importance ox ohe Persian Gulf from this aspect will be greatly increased after the war and that Bahrein may well be a place of considerable significance as a link ^n the Smpire route to Inaia ana the 1 ar East, The area is also of considerable importance to the R.A.F, and the question is now under consideration of the .cquisition of permanent rights on Masirah Island (off the South-/South-oast cornor . f ij^dblci) as a 'baso for reconnoitring anc patrolling ovor th^ Indian Ocean anJ the entrance to the G-ulf • 6, 'As re;;:r(l£ the sec^ixl iriportant new factor, nancly, oil, it need not 'be enphasiaed hov/ inportant t - a sea power like our selves it is to have oil reserves in this area which we can readily draw upon in tine of need, as an addition or alternative to the Persian and Iraq supplies, ^ccess tv. the oil of the Sheikhdoms is, moreover, not as in the case of the Iraq and Persian oilfields dependent upon the goodwill of countries anxi j&gt;us to assert their own national independence, 7, T he na tur e of our relations with the P t uLers and the importance of maintaining our present exclusive position. As has 'been pointed out above, Kuscat is the only one of the ^jrdb Sheikhdoms which receives any subsidy from ourselves but in spite of this we have so far been able to obtain from the Rulers, with the greatest ease and goodwill, such wartime requirements as we have asked for. Thus,, C ■ they have provided the R,A,F, with all tho facilities in their territories which have been required, When at the time of. the » - ' German threat to the Caucasus and beyond, it was considered necessary to construct an alternative port to Basra on the territory of the Sheikh of Koweit, the latter offered us all tho assistance at his command with the utmost readiness, Again, when it was found necessary to plug a proportion of the oil wells already / drilled and tc cease further exploration, the Rulers accepted this without serious demur in spite of their natural desire for the expeditious exploitation of the concessions, 8, It may well be asked -./hat is the reason that we have hitherto 'been able to secure with so little difficulty and such conspicuous goodwill our requirements in these states. The answer is that . . the Sheikhdoms regard H.Iu.G, as their natural protector both within the limits of our Treaty obligations raid outside them. They consider with some truth, that it io only that stands between them and absorption/absorption by Ibn Savid, Iraq or Persia, all of whom have from time to tixaS cast covetous eyes upon their territories and «ho certainly '.lould not hesitate to take any opportunity offered them of bringing the Rulers under their control. It is because of this regard in yhich ve are held that wo have boon able to guide the Sheikhs in their administration on linos satisfactory to ourselves by means of a cadre of officers consisting of one Resident and three Political Agents vdthout the aid of any subsidies (except to Muscat) and without the need of a single soldier or policeman in peace-time to ensure our requirements 'bein^ fulfilled. 9. The goodwill which/have hitherto enjoyed, however, sn. -aid nt t bo regarded too lightly nor taken for granted. In common with other more advanced countries, there are developments taking place in the Shoikhdona, particul xly through the influx of new wealth derived from oil, which may well in tine bring in their train movements of national self -consciousness, such as have already affected Iraq and Bgypt. The compliancy of the Sheikhs in meeting our requirements can therefore no longer be trken for mted and wo should avoid taking any step which would lessen the confidence that the Shoildidoms have in H.II.G. as their natural protector• 10. It has been cur consistent policy in the Gulf to maintain close and friendly relations with the various Sheikhs and at tV, same time to discourage any attempt by other Powers to conpete with ourselves for their favours. Oho motive for tins polio, of exclnsiveness has not been a selfish one but is.based on tho knowledge gained from long experience that in dealing with Eastern Rulers it is esse&amp;i .O. to avoid placing in their hands iae opportunity to play off one country against another: history hae shown that nothing is more likely to lead to trouble for sides in ti e end. In the Gull' we have avoided this error and it/it can 'be claimed for our policy that it has secured peace and security in the area and has b^cn in the 'best interests of the Sheikhs as well as our ovm. If v;e are to secure a continuance of this satisfactory state of al'f tirs, wo must avoid entering into any arrangements 'with the Americans which are likely to • v.. result in the introduction into the arCa of a foreign pc.Jer to rival our political influence 13., Oil Concussions in the CTu li. The most important oil enterprise in the Gull area (ap-rt from Persia) is the Baiirein petroleum Company w'liich though technically a British (Canadian) Company is \/holly ^.j-icrican owned and conir ^llv- d. This Company' has 'been established since 1930 and 'works in close coopuratioi with the California .jrabian Standard Oil Company engaged in production in the liasa area of'Saudi ^jrahia. Oil production has averaged , million tons a year and a refinery has 'been 'built on Bahrein Island .t which the normal rate 01 processing crude oil is 'barrels a day. This as no'.; to be considci' bly cnl .r jed in order to produce 100 octane avi .tion fuel, the project being 1 .rgely 1'inanced by th^ J.J. Government. The relations of tho Company with the Sheildi md the Political / authorities have been entirely satisfactory. In Koweijb a concession './as secured in 1934 by the Ku/ait Oil Company - a British Oompany owned equally by the ...I.O.C. and the Gulf Kxplor-Ltion Gompr\ny (U«S.^). The Company h-.s not yet reached the stage of producing., but the question of re-starting operations (now that denial mc .sm- je have been relaxed) is under consideration. Between Koweit aid Saudi /.raoia oxiex^e is a Neutral Zone in which Ibn Saud . nd the Jli^ildi of Koweit hold equal rights and where there are good prospects of oil being found. The C....S.0.0. obtained Ibn jaud's rights in this zone in 1939 and there is keen competition between British and American interests to secure a simil -r agreement with the Sheikh oj. Koweit. The/@ 7. The Schikh hoy ever has hitherto refused to discuss his rights in the Zon^ vith any party. Oil concessions in liuscat, the Trucial Coast and Qatar are held 'by subsidiaries of petroled Concessions Ltd., the capital of this Company Doing divided in equal shares 'between British, French, Dutch (Royal Dutch Shell) and American holders. In none of these areas, except Qatar, has oil developncnt passed the exploration stage. In Qatar three test wells had 'been drill 'before the Company received' orders from in June 1942 to plug their wells and suspend operations for the duration of the war. These restrictions have now 'been relaxed and it is under stood that plans are under discussion at Washington for the renewal of operations at Qatar, A separate note dealing in more detail with all these concessions is attached as an Appendix, 12, interests in the oil concessions . In the case of all the various oil concessions in the Persian G-ulf Sheikhdoms the Company concerned has signed a political agreement with H,M,G, whereby in recognition of HJvI.G's sx^ecial position in the Sheikhdoms, undertakings are given designed to safeguard the position of the - political -uthorities, to ensure that British strategic and other interests are respected and to enable the preduction and resources of the Company to be placed at the disposal of H.M.Gr, should this be rendered necessary by national emergency or war. The Companies further undertake to remain British by registration with at least one of their DLrectors a British subject, and to employ as many British subjects or subjects of the Ruler as is consistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking. Thus it is ensured that relations with the Rulers should be through, or at any rate under the supervision of, the British Political authorities. This safeguards our own interests and is, as a matter of fact, also of considerable assistance to the Companies since it would be quite impossible for them without such/such co-operation to secure fron the Rulers the assistance they require in developing oilfields in the hinterland and in securing protection against tribesmen. 13, U.S. interests in the Persian G-ull . bni-e : j- &gt;too have 'been taking an increasing interest in this area 'both iron the point of viev; of oil developnent and with an eye to post-war civil aviation. As stated aTDovo, the important oil concession in Bahrein is ovmed Dy the Americans. V .hile our relations with the Bahrein Petroleum Company have always been most tnendly, the Company co-operating fully in the/spirit of the agreement, there have, nev rtheless, teen indications that the United States Government' ar- lot altogether satisfied with the arrangement wherehy political relation: '. ith the Sheikhs, affecting as they do the interests of ^de.ioan subjects, are left entirely in tne hands of the British Policical authorities. The United States Government recently put forward a proposal iox wj_;(jnin 0 /jierican Consul, -te at Bahrein which was successfully resisted on our part, mainly on the grounds that to allow thei Consular representation there would open the way to other countries, such as Iraq, Persia and Saudi^jrahia, and that the proposal could not 'be justified 'by the number of .jierican subjects j.ivin^ m Bahrein or the magnitude of American interests there. 14. It therefore appears not improhahle that in any discussions with us they may press to 'be allowed greater freedom in conducting .direct relations with the Sheikhs. .iny such request should, from our own interests, 'be most firmly opposed on the ground that to admit such a request in the case of the United Status would 'be to*open the duor tc intrusion by other countries such as Iiaq, Persia and Saudi ijrabia, which would certainly no detrimental in the long -un both to our interests and those of the United States. It may not, however, be easy to resist such proposals by the Americans in the case of Huscat, sincu the latteris an independent state and in fact already has a Treaty with the United States, although it is probable that the Sultan himself will not welcome the opening of direct relations with any other foreign power than ourselves^ 15, As regards the immediate question of the development of oil in the Sheikhdoms, it is, of course, to the Sheikhs' immediate interests that this should proceed as fast as possible in view of the royalties which they will obtain. Hitherto the British Oil Companies have lagged somewhat behind the Bahrein Oil Company (and C.A.S.O.C. in Saudi-Arabia) in the matter of development. Insofar as they have financial interests in the British Companies (viz, the Kuwait Oil Company and Petroleum Concessions Ltd,), it is also to the interest of the American shareholders concerned that development should be speeded up« 16. If in connection with any discussions with the United States the question were to arise of requiring the Sheikhs to make adjustments in their existing agreements with H,M,G. or the oil companies, or to enter into now arrangements in the interests of Anglo -aimer i can policy (for example the U,S. have already put forward a suggestion of piping Kc»veit oil across Arabia to a Mediterranean port) it may be said that, while we could in the last resort no doubt induce the Sheikhs to f^ll into line, this would probably not be without detriment to our general relations with them, and we should be reluctant to put pressure on them unless it could be shown that they themselves would stand to benefit from the measures proposed. External Department, India Office March, 1944.APPENDIX Details of the Oil ConcessionG granted in the iiralD Sheikhdomc of the Persian G-ulf. 1. Bahrain ,. The Bahrein Petroleun Coripany estahlished itself in Bahrein in 1930 'by purchasing from the Eastern and G-eneral Syndicate a concession dating from 1925, which granted exclusive rights of exploration throughout the Sheikh's territories and promised a mining lease for a maximum area of 100,000 a.cres to 'be selected 'by the concessionaires. In 1924 the Company secured a lease covering the greater part of the two main islands comprising the Sheikhdom and in 1940 this lease was confirmed and extended to include the whole of the Sheikh's present and future dominions, including the reefs and territorial waters surrounding the islands. Up to th. present the Company has drilled 7k wells in the area of their 1934 lease hut in the early months of 1942 40 of these wells were plugged with cement in order to facilitate the denial of the whole field in case of emergency. In the additional area obtained 'by their deed of 1940 the company has done some exploratory work which is understood to have shown promising results, 'but they have 'been obliged to suspend their programme owing to war conditions. These denial restrictions have now been relaxed. Oil production from the Bahrein field has averaged about a million tons a year - in 1942 it was 836,000 tons. The Company have built a refinery on Bahrein Island of which the normal rate of processing crude oil is 33,500 barrels a day. The refinery is now being enlarged in order to produce 100 octane aviation fuel,'' the project being largely financed by the United States Government and planned to begin production an July 1944 at the rate of 23^,000 tons a year. The Bahrein Petroleum Company works in very close co-operation with the California -Arabian Standard Oil Company who are engaged in production in the Hasa area of Saudi-Arabia, both Companies being owned by the same American interests. The C.A.S.O.C's. oil is refined in the Bahrein refinery and a project has now been put forward of/- 2 - of connecting the Hasa coast with Bahrein 'by a pipe line io facilitate transport of c;rude oil to the refinery from Hasa, 2« Koweit, The ril concession here was secured by the Kuwait Oil Company in 1934. This is a British Company owned ^ equally 'by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company anB. the Gulf Exploration Ccnpany (iT.S.:.. )• Soon after obtaining their cjncessi3n the Company started exploratory work and their first wells were drilled in 193^. Early in 1939 they embarked on a large development scheme but thij was cancelled on the outbreak of war and they caatinued to drill with one rig only. They have not yet reached the stage of producing oil. In July 1942 :nvin._ to the war situation, denial measures were CDnsidered necessary and the Company were ordered by H.II.C, to suspend drilling operations and plug all their wells with cement. These restrictions have now been relaxed and the question of re-starting operations is under consideration. South of Koweit lies a considerable area known as the Neutral Zone in whic' r.tn Saud anc the Sheildi of Koweit enjoy e^ual rights u. .er the Coweit-IJejc Boundary Convention of 1922, until such time as through the good- offices of H,' i.G-, a further agreement is made between the two Rulers. There is every likelihood that oil will be found in the zone. In 1 939 the California-Arabian Standard Oil Company signed an agreement with the Saudi-Arabian Government under which theii oil concession was extended to cover, int^r alia, Ibn oaud's rights in the zone. There is- keen competition to secure a similar agreement '^rLth the Sheikh between Ilessrs, Petrol Concessions Limited, a -British Company already holding various oil concessions in the ^rabian Peninsula, and the Eastern Gulf Oil Company which althou h registered in the United Kingdom, is controlled by the sajup- American i vterests as J 'he Gulf Exploration Company, The Sheikh, however, has consiston-cly refused to discuss the question of his rights in the neutral -one with any would-be concessionaires, probably because he hopes/- 3 - hopes that on Ihn Saud's death, he will he able to implement his claim to thu v/hole of the Neutral Zone, 3, Duhai , A Political Arrreement on the usual lines between His Majesty's G-overnment and Petroleum Concessions Lt&lt;l,, '.vas signed on t ;.c 3th February, 19j&gt;7&gt; an d an Agreaiient 'betv/een the Sheikh and the Gompcny on 22nd I .ay, 193 7 &gt; with a provision for transfer to Petroleum Development (Truciil Coast) Ltd, The latter Agreement, which is for 75 years grants the Company exclusive rights to develop oil in the Sheikh's territory, islands and territorial waters, and covers his rights in any neutral zone. It specifically excludes Hatta-Al-Jahaliyah and the area at Dubai Khor surveyed 'by Imperial Airv.ays under the Dubia Civil Air Agreement. The Company has the right to import oil 'by pipe line frim adjoining territories. No work appears to have heen done, and in 1939 and 1 3k0 the Sheikh was informed that the Company had 'been forced to abandon their exploration survey progranme owing to the war, 4, Sharjah . An Agreement for 75 years was signed on 17th September,, 1937. 'between the Sheikh and Petroleum Concessions Ltd,, with a provision for a transfer to Petroleum Development (.Crucial Coast) Ltd, This Agreonent grants the Company exclusive rights to develop* oil in the territories, islands and territorial waters of the Sheikh, and covers his rights in any neutral area, but excludes the sites being used by Imperial Airways and the R, A,P, In a schedule attached to the agreement it is stipulated that drilling shall begin within 9 calendar years after its signature. The usual form of Political Agreement between His Majesty's G-ovemment and Petroleum Concessions Ltd, was signed on 12th November, 1 937. Drilling does not yet appear to have conrnenced at Sharjah, but during 193B and 1939/40, various expeditions were made into the hinterland. In 19^0 the Sheikh was infoimed that owing to the/- A- - the War the Cor.ipany unable to undertake further exploratory survey expeditions, 5. K_JLba, On 20th Duoaiber, 1938? an Agreexient for 75 years was sicnod 'between Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., and the Regent of Kalba, Sheikh Khalid Bin Ahmad Bin Sultan, who signed as Ruler of Kalba, The iigreement covered the Sheikh's territory and territorial v/aters, and contained provision for the builcing of a refinery and the construction of a pipo line through the Sheikh's territory. Article k in which the Sheikh 'undertakes to offer to the Company all assistance in its relations with other Rulers and neighbouring tribes with a view to securing the free access and movement of the Company in their territories' is unique in oil Agreements on the Trucial Coast, and emphasizes the value which the Company set on the assistance of the Sheikh in their future efforts to obtain access to the hinterland. That the Sheikh fully understood this is shown 'by his stacanent in his letter to the Political Agent, Bahrein, of the 23rd July, 1939? that part of the concession money would 'be spent 'to ensure facilities for the future and to obtain the necessary security for the geologists and all other work'.. An agreement 'between His Majesty's Governnent and the Ccmpany which took into account the exchange of letters 'between the Ccmpany and the Regent mentioned above, was signed on the 11th April, 1940, In 1 939 the Regent was informed that the Company had had to abandon their exploratory drilling program ie owing to the ar, 6, Ras~al-Khainah , The two years' option from 1st August, 1935, granted 'by the Sheikh to the D'Arcy Exploration Company, a subsidiary of the A.P.G.C, and later transferred to P .C.L, expired 1st August, 1937. On 25th March, 1938, a Political Agreement was signed between His Majesty's G-ovemment and Petroleum Devel opment (Trucial Coast) Ltd., in anticipation of a conoeosion 'being obtained from the Sheikh, On the 7th Decanber, 1 938, an Exploration Agreement between the Sheikh and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., was signed. This Agreement whiciy'v /hich ^ave the Ccopany exclusive exploration rights for years extendable for 1 further year did not cover 'boring and drilling which would need a separate .greanent, and contained the premise of a grant of a concession to the Cxipany should oil 'be discovered, Ivhen, aftur the outlreak of ar, the Company found itself unatle to carry out their exploration prograizie, negotiations were opened for an extension of thu period to 1 2 months after Hie conclusion of hostilities. This extension v .lth an annual payment to the Sheikh of Rs,4-5,000 from 6th June 19^-2, was agreed in an exchange, of letters 'between, the company and the Sheikh in March, 19Vi. 7. &gt;i.'bu Dbal i ^ The two years' option v/hich v.tls granted 'by the Sheik to the D'Arcy Exploration Company on 3rd Jiinuary, 1936, and was later transferred to Petroleum Concessions Ltd,, expiree on .^rd January, 1939, and on 11th January, 1939, a new Agreement for 75 years 'between the Sheikh and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., v.ns signed. This Agreement covers the Sheikh's territory, dependencies, islands, territorio.1 waters and rights in any neutral zone widch may 'be created hereafter An .agreement 'between His Hajesty's G-ovemmcnt and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., was signed on the 11th April, 19A-0 In 1939 and again in 1940 the Ruler was informed that the Co: p ny were, unable to undertake exploration surveys owing to the V/ar, and in January, 194-3? the Company agreed to increase their payment of 100,000 Rs. 'by 23yo under Article 5D of the Agreement rather than plead 'force majeure,' 8, A,jman . The P,C.L. option expired P.Pnn Jorcunry, 1938, and on 23rd March, 1939, an Exploxation Agreement Letween thu Sheikh and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., was signed, lA-ia . groament, which was for 5 years, with provision for 1 year 1 s extension, contains a clause for thu conclusion of a future- concession should the Company strike oil,..31 the Sheikh's territories/territories were covered, 'but the Company were denied the right to explore any area without his written or verbal pcn.iissiin; apparently there was an understanding;; that this ^ restriction referred only to an area known as Manama, In 1939 and again in 1940 the Ruler was informed that the Gorrrpany were unable to carry out their exploration survey pro^rai-nne v.lnj to the ,.ar. Negotiations are now in progress for the; extension of the ■/;ieement for 3 years after the conclusion of hostilities with Gormony, 9* al Quwaim. No option or concession has yet teen obtained in respect 01 this territory, though the Sheikh informed Petroleum Concessions Ltd, in about 1938 that he was willing to negotiate. . 1 0&lt; - Commercial iigreement for 75 years between the Sheikh and the A.T.O.G. was signed on 1 7th May, 1935, grartLng the Company exclusive rights to develop oil in the Qatar Peninsula an. the whole of the Sheik's territory. On the th l ecruury, 19;&gt;7, the concession was tranf erred to Petroleum j cvelopment (oatar) Ltd. An agreement betrreen His Majesty's Government and the A.I.O.C. v/hich v/as signed on the 5th June, 1935, has a ; re-emption clause attached as a schedule. By the . of A-ril, 1942, tliree test wells in the Dukhan area had been drilled and a promising show of oil obtained. A fourth well was i n preparation when in June, 1942, the Company suspended its operations on the orders of His Majesty's Government, and an agreanent vdth the Sheikh covering the suspension was signed, I. : - us 9&gt;' .1* Commercial .greeneiitij Letv/een them covering -.il nis icn i 1 j^ies except Iwadui* were signed by the Sulton ^vith Petroleum Concessions Ltd., on 24th June, 1937:- M) the Muscat-Oman ; -ve-nr nt applying to the territory of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman, its is lands and territorial voters, but enoluding Dhofar and Gwadur; (2) the Dhofar ... aop lying to 'the district called Dhofar including/, * ♦ - 7 - J. *i i p A i i O'l including all islmds and territorial waters appertain I 944 thereto', The ilrrreementa grant the Gompany oxclucive rights to develop oil, and are for 75 years with a 3 years 1 option period (extendable to 7 years) during which the Cxipmy my teminate the Agreement or declare in writing its intention tD take up the concessions. In Article 12 of 'both Agreements, the Gcrjpany 'recognise that certain parts of the Sultan's territory are not at prc.sent safe for its operations. The Sultan undertakes on his part to use his good offices with a view to nakin-j it possible for the Reprusentatives of Hie Company to enter such parts, and will inform the Company as soon as such parts 'becone safe,' Provision is made for import from neighbou ing territories 'by pipe line, the erection of pumping stations, t.mks, etc., and the construction of a refinery, 1 Political Agreement between His Majesty's Government and Petroleum Development (Oman and Dhofar) (a subsidiary of r',G»L. to v.aom the concession was transferred) was signed on 27th September, 1 938, and takes note of 'both Commercial Agreements, A separate pre-emption Agreement between His Majesty's G-overnment and ihe Company was signed on the same date- Exploratory expeditions into the hinterland were taken in 1938-''939# In September, 1939, the Sultan was informed that owing to War conditions the Company were unable to carry out their plans for geological exploration. On 7th jlay, 19A-2, the Sultan agreed to the extension of the option periods to 23rd June, 1944. Negotiations are not in progress for the extension of the option periods for 3 years, with a provision for their further extension to allow 3 clear years frcm the time that materials becjme available after the conclusion of hostilities with Germany, i</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000029_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B478</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000029</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B478</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on the Oil Concessions in the Arab Sheikhdoms'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-01T11:07:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 1 and terminates at folio 9, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: The item also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed secret memorandum by the India Office, dated 13 March 1944, concerns oil concessions in the Arab sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf in the context of the United States of America's discussions on oil in the Middle East. The aim of the memorandum is to give an account of British interests, explain British relations with the rulers of the Persian Gulf states and British policy more generally, and describes various oil concessions that have been granted in these states.The memorandum, which is signed with the initials 'F.A.K.H' of the External Department of the India Office, consists of six sections: 'The Geographical Situation and Treaty position of the Sheikhdoms', including Koweit [Kuwait], Bahrein [Bahrain], Qatar, 'The seven petty Sheikhdoms of the Trucial Coast', and Muscat; 'Strategic importance of the Sheikhdom'; 'The nature of our relations with the Rulers and the importance of maintaining our present exclusive position'; 'Oil Concessions in the Gulf'; 'HMG's interests in the oil concessions'; and 'US interests in the Persian Gulf'.This first section of the memorandum is followed by an appendix entitled 'Details of the Oil Concessions granted in the Arab Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf' (folios 6-9) and is divided into sections covering Bahrain, Kuwait, Dubai, Sharjah, Kalba, Ras-al-Khaimah [Ras al-Khaymah], Abu Dhabi, Ajman, Umm al Quwaim [Umm al-Qaywayn], Qatar, and Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Oil</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000029#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>