<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024052050.0x000045_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:38:22.528Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">we m To C Circular,) 9 « No. 1855. r/L Judicial Department. Sir, I am directed by the Right Honorable the Governor in Council to subjoin, for your information and guidance, copies of despatches from the Honorable the Court of Direc tors, dated as per margin. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, A H. L. ANDERSON, ■O 1 sy ! S, /) TL-r . Secretary to Government. Bombay Castle, J/ 7 November 1855. 5th September 1855. X 28th October 1840. 29th May 1844. 26th November 1845. — Extract Paragraph 15 0/a Despatch from the 5th September 1855, No. 11. 15. It appears that in six districts the fines imposed on the Stipendiary Police were in 28tb October (No. 7) 1840. the proportion of 37^ per cent, to their pay. This hard and fw &amp;mber ( ( N„ 0 ; 25) Is« arbi '' ary f™ 1 ™ enti, ' ely at variance «ith our instruo- tl0 ns noted in the margin. We there pointed out to you that the pay of our Native servants, from a necessary regard to economy, is fixed on the lowest scale on which the services required from them can be obtained; that it cannot be consi derably reduced by their immediate superiors, without great hardship ; and that there must always be a risk that the discrepancy will be made good by a resort to irregular means of I 310 ! rwK extent t0 wIllch fines have been imposed proves that the authority vested in Local Officers has befen abused, and there can be no doubt that these fines must have been teitas an engine of severe oppression. The remarks on the general subject in your Circular ers are very just, but they do not enjoin such a total change of practice as we deem essentia y necessan'-. We have therefore to draw your attention to our Despatches above referred to, and to desire that measures may be immediately taken for giving effect to the sentiments therein expressed. KI* 2 ] Extract Paragraph of a Despatch from the 28//. October 1840. No. 7. 3 V In this letter a proposition is submitted for o«r approval, that all Judicial fines should be appropriated to the improvement of the distriet in which th.y are le ^ f ^ 1'° perceive any propriety in proportioning public imprevements to the amount of fines impos ed by Courts of Justice ; and the'rule might possibly a? ^ m0 '^/^/'ifvied in mode of punishment. To this we are the more averse, from see.ng.that the fines levtet the year 1838 amounted to no less than Rs. 58,000. r No. 6 of 1844. Judicial Department. Our Governor in Council at Bombay. Para. 1. In your letter in the Revenue Departn^ent, dated 31st January (No. 6) 1844, you refer for our decision a question at issue between you and the Government of India, respecting the continuance of the Funds formed in Public Offices under your Presidency from fines and deductions from the pay of establishments, and appropriated as gratuities ior good conduct at the discretion of Heads of Offices. 2. We think the practice liable to the objection suggested by the Government of India, that payments from the Funds are made without means of securing uniformity, or guard- in- aaainst caprice. But we consider the imposition of fines, for the purpose of forming such Funds, much more seriously objectionable than the discretionary authority for awarding gratuities. The salaries of our public establishments, from a necessary regard to economy, are upon the lowest scale on which the requisite services are procurable. The consequence, therefore, of imposing a fine upon any servant, is to subject him to pecuniary embarrass ment, and, in situations of trust, to take away a guarantee for the faithful discharge of his duty,'or at leasts lay him open to the temptation of betraying it. Nor, considering the variety found in the temper of different men's minds, and even in the same man's mood at different times, do we think that every person at the head of an establishment can with propriety be entrusted with the arbitrary power of inflicting a heavy punishment, which must always be attended-with hardship, and, in the case of the higher class of servants, with some degree of disgrace. Absence from duty is generally .visited by a fixed rate, with some loss of allowances, not liable to the same objections ; and want of zeal, diligence, or capacity can be corrected by censure, or by the fear of ultimate removal by competent authority. 3. The considerations thus explained have the more influence on our minds, as we deem it an object of great importance that our Native public servants, through whose intrumen- tality so large a share of the administration of the several branches of civil government is carried on, should be encouraged to entertain a feeling of self-respect, and should be raised in the estimation of their official superiors as well as of the community..rzz [ 3 ] . 4. We are therefore of opinion that Funds raised by means of fines should be discon tinued, unless the foregoing objections should, on grounds to which we have not adverted seem to you inapplicable to the Funds of-tjiat nature existing under your Presidency. « We are, Your loving friends, *• (Signed) John Shepherd. ,, Henry Willock. „ W. H. C. Plowden. „ John Lock. „ Russell Ellice. „ John C. Whiteman. „ R. Jenkins. „ H. Alexander. „ J. Oliphant. „ J. W. Masterman. ,, H. Shank. „ F. Warden. „ A. Robertson. London^ 29&lt;A May 1844. No. 25 of 1845. Judicial Department. Our Governor in Council at Bombay. Para. 1. In your letter in the Revenue Department, dated the 18th of July last, No. 52, you have replied to our letter in this Department, dated the 29th of May 1844 (No, 6), in which we stated our objections to the ' Fine Funds' in public offices under your Presidency. 2. Those Funds consist of fines imposed for official irregularities, and out of thern gratuities are awarded for particular instances of good conduct, in both eases at the discretion of the Head of the Office. Our main objection to the practice was that the salaries of public establishments, from a necessary regard to economy, are upon so low a scale that they do not admit of reduction by fine, without making the party liable to pecuniary embar rassment, and, in situations of trust, taking away a guarantee for the faithful discharge of his duty. In reply, you urge the inexpediency of divesting the Heads of Departments of a powerful aid in securing efficient services from those under their authority ; and in order to guard against abijse, you have required quarterly returns of fines imposed to be furnished, in the Revenue Department to the Commissioners, and in the Judicial Department to the Sudder Adawlut. 3, Our views on the subject are unchanged; and we are apprehensive that the proposed review of the condact of Public Officers in the exercise of the discretion in question might tend to weaken their just authority, and also might lead to an unprofitable correspondence</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100024052050.0x000045_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/149, ff 192-193</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024052050.0x000045</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/149, ff 192-193</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Circular no.5105 of 1855, from Henry Anderson, Secretary to the Government of Bombay, to the Resident in the Persian Gulf</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1855/1855</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T00:19:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The printed circular encloses a number of despatches for the attention of the Resident, as follows:1. An extract of paragraph 15 of despatch no.11 of 1855 from the Court of Directors, dated 5 September 1855, relating to inappropriately heavy fines imposed on the Stipendiary Police, in relation to the salary levels of native government employees;2. An extract of paragraph 31 of a despatch from the Court of Directors, dated 28 October 1840, specifying that judicial fines should be appropriated to the improvement of the district in which they were levied;3. Memorandum no.6 of 1844 from the Judicial Department, dated 29 May 1844, relating to the detrimental effect resulting from funds being raised by fines and deductions made against native government employees, with the request that such practice be discontinued;4. Memorandum no.25 of 1845 from the Judicial Department, dated 26 November 1845; a reiteration of the request for the discontinuation of funds raised by fines and deductions against native government employees.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024052050.0x000045#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>