<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023549653.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T19:48:00.539Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">LONG LOAN This book is on loan to you for 3 weeks. The loan period is automatically extended by 12 weeks UNLESS the book is requested by another customer. If that happens, you will receive a recall notification and the book must then be returned to the British Library Document Supply Centre without delay. THE BRITISH LIBRARY DOCUMENT SUPPLY CENTRE Boston Spa, Wetherby, West Yorkshire United Kingdom, LS23 7BQ llllllllll 22257000 International Loan, Return Ai weeks of date of receipt unless Request Ref. No. 69-300/008 LOAN If no other library indicated please return loan to:- The British Library Document Supply Centre, Boston Spa, Wetherby, West Yorkshire, United Kingdom, LS23 7BQCONTENTS. l?aqe inteoductort Eemaeks, 1 ANNALS OF 'OMA'N. Book First —Account of the immigration of the el-Azd into 'Oman, and the expulsion therefrom of the Persians, 3 Book Second .—Account of the people of 'Oman from the period when they embraced the religion of el-Islam until they became disunited (A. D. 886), 9 Book Third .—From the outbreak of Civil Dissensions to the Imamate of Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah. (A. D. 886 to 934), 20 Book Foijetii .—Account of the Imams Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah and Rashid-bin el-Walid and their successors to the time of 'Omar- bin el-Kasim el-Fadheyli (A. D. 1560), 25 Book Fifth .—Account of the later Princes of the el-Nebahenah and others, up to the accession of the Imam Nagdr-bin Murshid. (A. D. 1560 to 1624), ' 35 Book Sixth .—Appearance of the Imam Nagir-bin Murshid and an Account of the Imams who succeeded him up to the occurrence of dissensions amongst the el-Ya'arabeh. (A. D. 1624 to 1728),.. 44 Book Seventh .—Account of the Civil Wars in 'Oman, and of the state to which the country was reduced. (A. D. 1718 to A. D. 1728), 57&lt;■ errata. Page 7, last line, for Zoheir, 23 read Zoheir, 29 Page 24, line 1, for Kasim, read bin el-Kasim. Page 75, lines 1 2, &amp;e., up to the seventh note, for (p. 5), read (p. 3). Page 75, line 3 from below, for (p. 6), read (p. 4). ?age 76, in notes 9 to 11, for (p. 6), read (p. 4)NTRODUCTORY J^EMARKS. The Arabic work from which the following account of the History of 'Oman is translated, is entitled ' Keshf-ul-Ghummeh,' or ' Dispeller of grief.' That work, which forms a good sized MS. volume, is not devoted exclusively to the subject of 'Oman, but contains likewise accounts of other countries, and descriptions of various sects of Islam. Copies of the ' Keshf-ul-Ghummeh' are extremely rare in 'Oman ; and out of that country I doubt if it is known, I have only heard of two copies existing. That from which I prepared this translation was lent to me by a gentleman residing at Maskat, a member of the A'l-bu-Sa'id family. The name of the author was not inscribed on the pages, and no one at Maskat seemed able to supply the omission. At length, one of the Kadhis wrote to certain learned persons at Nezwa, who replied that the author was Sirhan- bin-Sa'id, a native of Izld or Zikki. It would appear that in 'Oman it has been customary with the learned of the priests and Kadhis at times to write narratives of contemporaneous events in prose or verse, chiefly touching religious matters. Numerous re cords of this class are probably in existence, and from such sources it may be that the author of the ' Keshf-ul-Ghummeh' has composed his annals of 'Oman. The first part, however, shows acquaintance with some of the standard Arabian works. The date of the composition of the work can be approximately stated. The narrative is brought down to the year 1728, A. D., and therefore could not have been concluded at an earlier period. The abrupt manner in which it terminates, tends to show that the work was not written much later than that date. The author of the Arabic work translated by the Rev. G. P. Badger for the Hakluyt Society in 1871, occasionally quotes the ' Author of the Keshf-ul-Ghemmeh' as making such and such a state ment. I have not seen the original Arabic of Mr. Badger's author, but by a comparison of the English version with the ' Keshf ul-Ghummeh,' I have * In the following, pronounce a as in hat; e as in ied; i as in hid ; o as in ohey ; u as in hull; d as hx father ; i as ee in deed ; 6 as in note; u as oo in hoot; ei as i in hite ; ey as in they ; ow as in cow; th as in hoth ( l -:) ; th as th in the (i); hh corresponds to ^; ghto dh to ^ and io ; A to ; g to ^; k to ^ is represented by an inverted comma2 Introductory Remarks. been led to the conclusion that Salil-bin-Eazik* copied the majority of the earlier portion of his book verbatim from the ' Keshf-ul-Ghummeh.' In deed, when, as occasionally happens, he strays from the pages of that work, the order of events is confused, and many puerilities not observable in the older work are introduced. The work now translated may fairly be considered, as far as it goes, the most authentic and coherent account of the history of 'Oman that has emanated from native sources. But almost all native works of this sort have striking deficiencies. Trifling details are dwelt on, whilst comparatively important events are only casually alluded to or dismissed without a word. It is left as a task for European students to sift, prune, and supplement the accounts of native historians, and for this purpose no materials are to be despised. In the original work, the divisions are similar to those adhered to in this translation ; only the numbering is different. The account of the migration of Azdites and their settlement in 'Oman forms the 4th Chapter, or Book, of the ' Keshf-ul-Ghummeh,' and the rest of the history of 'Oman is found in Chapters 34 to 39 of that work. The intervening portion is on other subjects. * The name of this person was Hamed-hin Muhammad-bin Eazlk, the designation 'Salil' signifying 'son.' He died at Maskat in 1873.annals of 'oman. Book I. 1 An account of the immigration of the el-Azd 2 into 'Oman, and the expulsion therefrom of the Persians. It is said by el-Kelbi that the first of the el-Azd who came to 'Omdn was Malik-bin Fahm 3 -bin Ghanim-bin Dows-bin 'Adnan-bin 'Abdullah-, bin Zahran-bin Ka'b 4 -bin el-Harith-bin Ka'b-bin 'Abdullah-bin Malik-bin Nasr 5 -bin el-Azd, the Azdi, the DowsL Now the cause of his emigrating to 'Oman was as follows : His nephews, the sons of his brother 'Amru-bin Fahm, were wont, when taking the flocks to pasture and returning at even ing, to pass by the house of a neighbour. The latter had a bitch which used to bark at them and scatter their flocks, and one of them killed it with his spear. The man, who was under Malik's protection, complained to him, and Malik being angered, said he would no longer remain in a country where a person under his protection suffered such treatment; and went forth and separated from his brother 6 against the wish of the latter. An other story is, that a herdsman was set on by a savage dog belonging to a bondsman of ' Dows,' and slew it with his spear, on which the owner of the dog slew the herdsman. That upland is named ' Nejd-el-Kelbeh.' 7 Malik then went forth from el-Sarat with those of his tribe who bore obe-r ■ 4 Annals of 1 Oman. dience to him. Wlien lie was well on the road, his camels yearned for their pasture grounds, and turned wistfully towards el-Sarat. But he journeyed on towards 'Oman. And he passed not any tribe of the tribes of the Arabs, of Ma'add or of 'Adnan, 8 but they sought his friendship, and formed allian ces with him, on account of his dignity and the number of his fighting men. He marched on until he reached Eahut, 9 a valley in Hadhramowt, where he halted awhile for rest. Then he learned that the Persians were in 'Oman, inhabiting it. So he drew up his forces and reviewed them, and it is said they were upwards of 6000 in number, horse and foot. They then arranged themselves in order before proceeding onwards to 'Oman, Malik placed his son Honat, 10 or as some say Ferahid, in command of an advanced guard consisting of 2,000 horsemen of the bravest of his army. When they arrived at el-Shihr, 11 Mahrah l2 -bin Hidan-bin el-Haf- bin Kadha'ah-bin Malik-bin Himyar separated from Malik, and stayed be hind at el-Shihr. Malik marched onwards until he entered 'Oman with his numerous and well equipped army. He found the Persians holding 'Oman for the king Dara, son of Dara, 13 son of Bahman ; and at that time they were the inhabitants of 'Oman and the dwellers therein. In those days their leader was the Marzaban, 14 who was Lieutenant for their king. Malik drew aside with his followers to Kalhat 15 on the coast of 'Oman, as being a more secure position against the Persians. He there left the families and heavy baggage with a guard to protect them against the ene my's force, and advanced with the remainder of his army ; his son Honat leading the advanced guard of 2,000 horsemen. He proceeded in this man ner until he arrived at the district of el-Jowf, 16 where he pitched his camp on the plain. Thence he sent to the Persians asking them to allot him land in 'Oman to settle on, with water and pasture, so that he might dwell amongst them. When his messengers arrived, the Marzaban and his subordinates held an earnest and prolonged consultation which resulted in their unanimously deciding to refuse the request of Malik, so they replied : ' we do not wish this Arab to settle amongst us, that our land should be- ' come straitened unto us ; we have no need of his neighbourship.' When their answer reached Malik, he sent a message to them, saying ; ' I must positively settle in a district of 'Oman j if you accord me willingly a share of the water, produce, and pasture, I shall settle in the country and praise ' you. If, however, you refuse, I shall remain in spite of you. If you at- ' tack me, I shall resist you, and if I prevail against you, I shall slay you, and cany oil your offspring, and shall not allow one of you to remain in Oman. -They, however, refused him permission, and prepared to make war on him. Malik on his part remained in the district of el-Jowf until his people had rested, and he prepared for the struggle with the Persians.Hook First. in Ha( Meanwliile the Persians had made ready to attack him, and the Mar- zaban ordered the trumpets to be sounded and the drums beaten, and set out with all his host from Sohar, It is said his army numbered more than 40,000 men, and some say 30,000, and he had with him elephants. He proceeded towards el-Jowf to encounter Malik, and halted at the plain of Selut near Nezwa. When Malik received intelligence of this, he set out for the plain of Selut with 6,000 men, and encamped opposite the army of the Marzaban. They remained in their respective positions that day with out fighting. Malik-bin Fahm spent the night drawing up his forces in order of battle, forming them into right and left wings, and centre, and stationing the horsemen of the el-Azd in position. He placed his son Honat in command of the right wing, gave the left to his son Ferahid, and took his station himself in the centre with chosen men. The Marzaban also was similarly employed, and both sides were prepared, Malik mount ed a pie-bald charger, clad in bis armour over which he wore a red robe, and on his head was his iron helmet encircled by a yellow turban. His sons and the warriors of the el-Azd were similarly accoutred in armour and hel met, their eyes only being visible^ When the ranks were formed in order of battle, Malik went around and addressed his followers troop by troop, encouraging them and exhorting them to stand firm and warning them that if they fled, they would be pur sued and destroyed by the Persians. The Marzaban then advanced with all his forces under their comman ders, placing his elephants in front, Malik met them with his followers crying out to his men of the el- Azd to charge with him, and to ply the elephants with their swords and javelins. Thereupon he charged and his men charged with him, and they attacked the elephants with sword and spear, piercing them with darts until the elephants goaded by their weapons turned in flight, trampling under foot many of the Marzaban's men. Malik then fell on the army of the Marzaban with all his men, piercing the ranks of the Persians. The latter rallied together, and the two forces continued to fight with fury, and noth ing could be heard but the clashing of their weapons. The battle was kept up the whole of that day until the fall of night separated the opposing armies, and they retired to their respective positions leaving many dead and wounded. The next day the conflict was renewed and kept up until night, the Persians losing many of their men. On the third day the battle was again renewed and the Persian com mander having been slain by Malik in single combat, the Persian army gave way and fled, losing an immense number in killed and wounded. J?G Annah of 1 Oman. The Persians then sent to Malik suing for a truce and demanding a year's time to evacuate 'Oman and return to their own country. Malik agreed to this and promised not to molest them unless they recommenced the war. The Persians thereupon returned to Sohar, and Malik withdrew to Kalhat. It is said that the Persians during the period of this truce destroyed a great many water channels. Suleiman-bin Daud had constructed 10,000 aqueducts in 'Omiin. 18 The Persians then wrote to Dara-bin Dara informing him of the ad vent of Malik and his followers to 'Oman, and the struggle that had occur red between him and themselves, how his general the Marzaban had been slain with many of their companions. Then telling him of their weak and helpless condition, they asked permission to return to their own country with their families. When their letter reached the king and he read it, he was incensed, and burned with a desire to avenge the slaughter of his sol diers and generals, so he sent for one of the greatest of his Marzabans, and giving him command of 3,000 of his most renowned warriors and comman ders, despatched them to the aid of his subjects in 'Oman. They proceeded first to el-Bahrein and thence to 'Oman. All this while Malik was in igno rance of what was going on. When this reinforcement reached the Persians, they commenced pre parations to renew the war as soon as the period of truce should expire. W hen Malik heard of the arrival of the succours, he wrote to the Pers ians informing them that if they did not quit 'Oman, he would march against them and expel them by force, and seize all their property. But they, confident in their strength and in the comparative smallness of Malik's army, returned a defiant and insolent answer. Malik accordingly marched against them with his whole army and entered their territory. The Pers ians on their side prepared for battle. When the two armies met, Malik drew up his army as before, placing his son Honat in command of the right, and 1 era hid ot the left, he stationing himself with the remainder of his sons in the centre. A fierce and prolonged battle was fought, in which the Persians employed their elephants. One huge animal was killed by Honat and his brother Ma'n-bin Malik. Alter a fierce struggle, the Persians were routed and fled, pursued by the el-Azd horsemen, who slew an immense number and made many prisoners. The remnant of the Persian army em barked in their ships and passed across the sea to Persia. So Malik con quered all 'Oman and took all the property of the Persians. He made many of the latter prisoners and kept them a long time in prison, after which he released them, and caused them to be conveyed to the ships, with their clothing and provisions, and sent back to Persia. Malik then ruled over 'Oman and its adjacent districts, and governed it wisely and well. TheBook First. : amir #• journey of Malik and his sons to 'Oman and their battle with the Persians have been celebrated in many poems and traditions from which I have only given an abridged account. Then came to 'Oman many tribes of the el- Azd. The first of the el-Azd to join Malik was 'Imran-bin 'Amru-bin 'Amir-Ma-el-Sema with his sons el-Hajr and el-Aswad. From the two latter many tribes in 'Oman derive. Afterwards Rabi'ah-bin el-Harith-bin- 'Abdullah-bin ' Amir-el-Ghitrif went forth with his brothers, also Muladis' bin 'Amru-bin 'Adi-bin Harithah came and entered Hudad, also 'Arman- bin 'Amru-bin el-Azd, then came el-Yahmad-bin Homma, also the sons of Ghanm-bin Glialib-bin 'Othman ; and Ziyad or el-Nadab the junior. Then Ma'walah, the sons of Shams, and el-Nadab the senior went forth, also el- Dheyyak, and some of the Benu-Yashkar and of the Benu 'Amid, and men of Khawaleh. All these tribes 19 went forth, each tribe with its banners. As they journeyed on, they consumed the substance of all by whom they passed, until they reached 'Oman. They extended themselves throughout 'Oman, and settled in its rich and spacious lands. The el-Azd named it 'Oman 20 , because their dwellings had been in a watered valley in (Yemen) which was probably called 'Amman, and to which they likened their new home. The Persians called 'Oman by the name of Mazun. 21 As an Arab poet has said— ' The Kesra named 'Oman Mazun, ' And Mazun, O friend ! is a goodly land, ' A land abounding in fields and groves, ' With pastures and unfailing springs.' The tribes of the el-Azd ceased not to migrate to 'Oman, until they became numerous therein, and their power and fame increased. At length, they overran the country and extended as far as el Bahrein and Hajar [el-Hassa]. Then came to 'Oman Samah-bin Loweij-bin- Gbalib 20 , and settled at Towvvam, which is el-Jow, 23 in the vicinity of the el-Azd. There were also in that place some of the Benu-Sa'd, and Benu 'Abd-el-Keis. Samah married his daughter to Asd-bin Tmran bin- ' Am rii 94 Some of the Benu-Tamim also settled in 'Oman, the Al-Kba- zci'ah-bin Hazem settlers, too, arrived from the Benu-el-Nabat, whose abodes were at 'Obri and el-Seleyf, and Ten'am, and el-Sirr. 25 Some of the Benu-el-Harith-bin Ka'b came and settled at Dhank, About one hun dred persons of the Khadha'ah also settled at Dhank. Some of the family of Benu Ru-aheh 26 -bin Kati'ah-bin 'Abs came to 'Oman, amongst them Abu '1-Hishm. The rule of Malik became strong in 'Oman and his wealth increased, and he was feared by all the tribes of the ' \emen' and ' Ni- zar.' 27 He was more daring and adventurous than any other Prince. He chiefly resided on the Kalhat coast and at Yankal. One of the Princes ot the el-Azd, named Malik-bin Zoheir, 23 settled in the vicinity of Malik-bin8 Annals of 1 Oman. Fahm, and being a chief of great renown, well nigh rivalled the latter in power. So Malik-bin Fahm fearing that mutual jealousy and strife mk'ht arise between them, demanded his daughter in marriage, and Malik-bin Zoheir gave his daughter, but stipulated that her offspring should have precedence of all Malik-bin Fahm's sons by other wives. Malik-bin Fahm assented and married her on these conditions. By this marriao-e he had issue Salimah-bin Malik. Malik reigned over 'Oman for seventy years, during which time neither Arab nor Persian opposed his rule. His age was 120 years. It is said that Malik'bin Fahm was slain accidentally by his son Sali- mah, 29 in the following manner: It is said that Malik used to require his sons to keep guard at night, each in turn with a body selected from Malik's most trusty nobles and followers. Now Saltmah was more beloved of his father than any of his brothers, and had higher rank and dignity assigned him. His father had taught him archery until he excelled in the art. His bro thers envied him on account of the preference shown him, and sought to lowei him in his father s estimation, but found no opportunity to find fault with him. At length, one day some of them approached their father, and accused Salimah of leaving his post when on watch and retiring aplrt to sleep. Malik, however, reproved them, and told them he knew that envy prompted them to traduce his son Salimah, and that he judged the latter by his knowledge of him, so they were forced to withdraw without gaining their object. Afterwards, however, misgiving entered Malik's mind, and he resolved to put the charges against his son Salimah to the test' He accordingly went forth in disguise and secretly, on a night when it was Salimah's turn to keep guard. Now it was Salimah's custom to withdraw from his comrades and keep watch close to his father's house. On this night he had taken his usual station ; and sleep had overtaken him just at the hour his father came out. His mare seeing the form of Malik in the distance neighed, on which Salimah started from his sleep in alarm, and saw his mare with her ears erected. Now it was the habit of the mare on seeing anything approaching to point her ears in the direction of the object and the rider would aim his arrow accordingly. So Salimah discharged his arrow between the mare's ears towards Malik not knowing it was his father. heard the sound of the arr ow as it left the bow, and called out, 'Do not shoot, my son, I am your father.' It was too late, however, and the dart pierced the centre of his heart. Salimah, after haying slain his father, fled to the Persian coast in fear of his brothers, and abode at Jashk, where he married a native of the land named el-Asfaluyeh. H 1 s offspring by this marriage were called Benu-el- Asfahiyeh. Sahmah afterwards removed to Kerman which he made himself master of after a series of adventures.' and reigned as king nntil his deathJBoolc Second. 9 lUii 'Is By a marriage with a Persian lady he had ten sons, named 'Abd and Hima- yeh and Sa'd and Ruaheh and Majash and Kelah and Asd and Taher and Aswad and 'Othman. After his death, his sons were disunited, and the Persians expelled them, and some went to 'Oman. The majority of the children of Salimah, however, remained in Kerman, where they were numerous and powerful. The Persians did not return to 'Oman after their expulsion by Malik until his reign terminated, and his children reigned in his place, and the kingdom of'Oman came into the possession of el-Julanda-bin el-Mustatir 31 el-Ma'wall, and Persia fell into the hands of the Benu Sasan. 32 There was peace between them and el-Julanda in 'Oman, and the Persians kept a force of 4000 warriors in 'Oman and a deputy with the kings of the el-Azd. The Persians abode on the sea coast, and the el-Azd ruled in the interior plains and hills and districts of 'Oman, the direction of affairs being entirely with them. The Persian monarchs used to send persons who had incurred their displeasure or whom they feared to their army in 'Oman. So it continued until God caused el-Islam to be manifested. 33 Book II.i Account of the people of 1 Oman from the period when they embraced the religion of el-Islam until they became disunited. There is a tradition that the first man of 'Oman to embrace el-Islam was one Mazin-bin-Grhadhdbah, who visited the Prophet and asked him to pray for him and the people of 'Oman. Afterwards the Apostle of Grod wrote to the people of 'Oman, inviting them to adopt the religion of Islam. He wrote amongst others to 'Abd and Jeifar 2 , the sons of el-Julanda (who had died a short time before), to the effect that if they would accept el-Islam, he would confirm them as Governors; otherwise they would be deposed. He sent this letter by 'Amr- bin el-'As, who alighted at a place near Sohar named Damsetjerd, which had been built by the Persians. Thence he sent a message to the sons of Julanda, who were the foremost and most influential chiefs of 'Oman. The first who met the messenger was 'Abd, who was the most discerning and sensible of the two brothers. He sent on 'Amr to his brother Jeifar with the sealed letter, and Jeifar broke the seal and read it, and then passed it to 'Abd who also read it. The latter then told 'Amr that this was no trifling matter he had come about, and that he would reflect on it, and afterwards give a reply. He then assembled a council of the el-Azd, and sent to Ka'b-bin Barshah el- '17di. They all became converts to el-Islam, and sent to all their kinsmen who vowed obedience to the Prophet, and agreed to offer the proper religious alms. Jeifar sent messengers to Maheyreh, and Shihr in the south, and to Daba, 310 Annals of'Otndn. and the furthest limits of 'Oman to the north; and at liis invitation all the people accepted el-Islam, save the Persians who dwelt in 'Oman, When the Persians rejected el-Islam, the el-Azd assembled round Jeifar, and all agreed to expel the Persian deputy Maskan and his followers from the country. As the Persians refused either to join el-Islam or to leave the country quiet ly, the el-Azd attacked them, killed their leader Maskan and many more, and drove the remainder into their town of Damsetjerd, when they besieged them rigorously, until they sued for terms. The el-Azd granted them quar ter on condition that they left all their gold and silver and other property behind and quitted 'Oman, which they did. 'Amr continued to reside with and direct the el-Azd, until the death of the Prophet. After that, 'Abd-bin- el-Julanda and many of the el-Azd proceeded to visit Abu-Bekr 4 the Just, who praised the conduct of the people of 'Oman in accepting the message of the Prophet willingly and spontaneously. It is said too that 'Ahd served the Khalifeh in an expedition against the A'l-Jifneh. Abu-Bekr then wrote to the people of 'Oman thanking them and confirming Jeifar and 'Abd in the government. The virtues of these two cannot be fully described, but much might be written of them. They continued pre-eminent in 'Oman until they died. They were succeeded by 'Abbad-bin 'Abd-bin el-Julanda, in the time of 'Othman-bin 'Affan and 'AH. Then came the wars and divisions, and Mu'awiyah succeeded to power; but his authority was not established in 'Oman. At the period when 'Abdul-Malik-bin Marwan reigned and el-Hejjaj governed el-'Irak, Sulei man and Sa'id, the sons of 'Abbad-bin 'Abd-bin el-Julanda, ruled in 'Oman. El-Hejjaj sent several large armies against them, but they defeated them on each occasion and put them to flight until at length el-Kasim-bin Shi'wah came with a numerous army to 'Oman in ships, which anchored at one of the villages of'Oman, named Hataf. Suleiman-bin'Abbad led the el-Azd against the invaders, and a battle ensued in which the troops of el-Hejjaj were routed and el-Kasim and many of his followers slain ; and Suleiman captured all their property. When this alarming news reached el-Hejjaj, he sent for Muja'ah-bin Shi wah, hi other of el-Kasim, and ordered him to rouse the people and make a general levy of the Nizar 5 tribes. El-Hejjaj was personally incensed and eager for revenge. He wrote to 'Abd-el-Malik-bin Marwan, and restrained the chiefs of the el-Azd of el-Basrah from aiding Suleiman-bin 'Abbad. I have found it stated that the army which el-Hejjaj collected and sent against 'Oman, numbered 40,000 men. One half was despatched by land and the other half by sea. The former portion of the army having marched to 'Oman was opposed by Suleiman at the head of a force of the el-Azd, con sisting of 3,000 horsemen and 3,500 camel riders. The encounter took place by the water, which is within five, or some say three, days' march ofBool Second. 11 tlie desert country. 6 It is the water near the village of Busher (it is now called el-Balka'ein). The battle which was a severe one, resulted in the defeat of el-Hejjaj's men, who fled and were pursued by Suleiman for along distance, the latter being wholly unaware of the approach of the second army by sea, which meanwhile arrived at Bunaneh, and the commander was informed that Suleiman had gone forth with the main body of his army to oppose the force which had come by the land route, and that those who remained with his brother Sa'id were only a handful. Muja'ah thereupon marched night and day until he reached Birkeh, where Sa'id attacked his force, and a fierce battle occurred, which lasted until night separated the combatants. Sa'id then regarding his army perceived that it was to that of the enemy like as a white spot on the body of a black bull, and many had been killed. So he retired during the night taking with him his own and his brother's children, and proceeded to the great mountain of the Benu- Eiyam, which is called el-Jebel el-Akhdhar, and also Rodhwan (spelt with dhammah). The enemy came up with him, and they remained besieged until Suleiman came up. Muja'ah had anchored his fleet of 300 vessels in Maskat 7 harbour, and Suleiman proceeded there and burned more than fifty vessels, the rest escaping seaward. He then marched against Muja'ah's army, and Muja'ah conceiving himself unable to cope with Suleiman sought to escape to sea, but was encountered by Suleiman at the village of Semail. A severe conflict ensued, in which Muja'ah was worsted and fled. He, how ever, succeeded in reaching his ships, and embarking sailed to Julfar. 3 Thence he wrote to el-Hejjaj who sent to his aid a re-inforcement of 5,000 mounted men, selected from the Bedouins of el-Sham, under 'Abd-ul-Rah- man-bin Suleiman, by land. Amongst them was a man of the tribe of el-Azd who was known by the title ' el-Malaheh,' and they were unaware that he was of that tribe. This person fled by night to Suleiman and Sa'id, and informed them of the approach of the fresh force ; whereupon they perceived they were unable to resist longer, and taking with them their families' property and those of their tribe who chose to follow them, they reached one of the districts of the Zenj 9 , where they abode until their death. Muja'ah and 'Abd-ul-Rahman then entered 'Oman with their forces and exercised great severity, plundering the inhabitants. (We seek refuge with God from such things.) El-Hejjaj after that appointed el-Kheiyai-bin Sirah el-Mujasha'i governor of 'Oman. When 'Abdul-Malek died (A. D. 705), and el-Walid-bin 'Abdul-Malek succeeded him, and el-Hejjaj died, Walid ap- pointed Yezid-bin Abu-Muslim Governor of el-'Irak, and the latter sent Seyf-bin el-Hani-el-Hamadam to govern 'Oman. When Walid-bin 'Abdul-Malek died and his brother Suleiman suc ceeded, the latter removed all the governors who had been appointed in 'Oman, and sent Salih-bin 'Abdul-Rahman el-Leithi. Afterwards he saw fit12 Annals of 1 Oman. to re-instate the governors, but made them subordinate to Silih-bin 'Abdul- Kahman. After that Yazi'd-bin el-Muhallib became Governor of 'Irak and Kho- rasan, and he appointed his brother Ziyad over 'Oman, and he treated its inhabitants kindly, and continued to rule until Suleiman-bin 'Abdul-Malek died, and 'Omar-bin 'Abdul-'Aziz succeeded to the government (of 'Irak). He placed 'Adi-bin ArtSh el-Fezari over el-'Irak, who sent a governor to 'Omfin who behaved so badly to the people that they wrote to 'Oman-bin 'Abdul-'Aziz, The latter placed over them 'Omar-bin 'Abdullah-bin Sabi- hah el-Ansan, who treated them well and remained Governor over 'Oman honored by the inhabitants, and receiving their contributions voluntarily until Omar-bin Abdul-'Aziz died. Then said 'Omar-bin 'Abdullah to Ziyad-bin el-Muhallib, ' this country is the land of your tribe, do as you please with it,' and straightway went forth from 'Oman. Ziyad-bin el- Muhallib then governed 'Oman, until Abul-'Abbas el-Saffah appeared, and the empire of the Benu-Omeyyeh passed to him. He appointed Abu-Ja'far el-Mansur over el-'Irak. The latter appointed Jenah-bin 'Abbadah-bin Keis-bin 'Omar el-Hinai' 10 governor of 'Oman, who was the builder of the mosque known as el-Jenah. Afterwards he was deposed, and his son Mo hammed-bin Jenah appointed in his stead. Thereupon Jenah-bin 'Abbadah sided with the Ibadhiyeh 11 (Ibadhis), until at length the latter acquired the sovereignty in 'Oman. 1 he Ima'm el-Jttlanda'-but Mes'u'd .—Thereupon they elected el-Ju- landa-bin Mes'ud their Imam, 12 and he was the cause of strength to the sect, and was a just and popular ruler. A. D. 750. At the call of el-Saffah, Shiban went forth against el-Julanda, who, on his reaching 'Oman, sent against him Hilal-bin 'Atiyah el-Khorasani and Yahya-bm Xajih with a force of Musalmans. 13 Now Yahya was famed for his virtue ; he uttered a prayer in which he mentioned both sides saying &lt;'O God,ifThouknowest us to be in the faith Thou approvest, and to 'follow the truth Thou wishest us to hold, grant, that I may be the first of my comrades killed, and Shiban the first on his side, after which cause defeat to befall his followers. If on the contrary Thou knowest that Shiban and his followers hold the faith that pleaseth Thee, and the truth Ihou wishest to be established, then cause Shiban to fall the first.' Then the forces encountered one another, and the first who was slain on the side of the Mnsalrnans was Yahya-hinNajih whilst Slilban was the first to lall on his side. After the death of Shiban, there came to 'Oman Khazim-bin Khozey- mah saying they had come in search of that force, namely, Shiban and his followers, but ' xt suffices that God has decreed they should be slain by youi hands. I wish, however, to go forth from you to the Khalifah andN i. L (of'Iiil u inform him you bear liim obedience.' El-Julanda consulted the Musal- mans as to this proposal, but they were against it. It is also said Khazim demanded the sword and seal of Shiban, and that el-Julanda refused ; on which a battle ensued between him and Khazim, in which all el-Julauda's followers were slain, and none remained alive save himself and Hilal-bin 'Atiyah el-Khorasani. Then said Hilal to el-Julanda, ' You are my Imam, precede me, 14 and I engage not to survive you,' El-Julanda then advan ced and fought until he fell. Hilal then rushed on clad in armour, and the . enemy amazed at his valour for some time failed to recognize him, but at length they discovered who he was, and raising the cry ' Hilal-bin 'Atiyah !' fell on him and slew him. The Imamate of el-Julanda had lasted for two years and a month. It is said that it was Khazim-bin Khozeymah who caused el-Julanda to be slain. It has also been told me that at his death Khazim was congratu lated by some one on his conquest of 'Oman, and that he replied, ' Ye ' deceived me in my lifetime and do ye seek to do so at my death ? Alas! ' how will it be for me for slaying the 'Oman Sheykh!' I have also found it stated that a native of 'Oman went on the pilgrim age ; and with him was a man from el-Basrah who rested not by night nor slept. The 'Oman! asked him about this, and he replied not knowing his companion was a native of 'Oman, that he had gone with Khazim-bin Khozeymah to 'Oman and had there fought against a people, the like of whom he had never seen, and since that day sleep did not visit him. The 'Omani said to himself, ' You deserve it, if you are one of those who fought against 'Oman,' After el-Julanda was killed, 'Oman fell into the hands of tyrants who misgoverned the country and oppressed the inhabitants. Amongst those oppressors were the two Julandaites Mohammed-bin Zaidah and Rashid-bin Shathan-bin el-Nadhr, In the time of those two, Ghassan- el-Henai, of the Benu-Maharib, plundered Nezwa, and the Benu Nafa and Benu-Hamim fled therefrom after many had been slain. This occurred in the month of Sha'ban, A, H. 145. [A. D. 762]. Thereupon the Benul-Harith of Ibra espoused their cause, and amongst them there was a slave belonging to Bakarah called Ziyad-bin Sa'id el-Bakari, so they agreed upon proceeding to el-'Atik for the purpose of putting to death Grhassan el-Hinai, and they met him between his house and that of Jenah-bin Sa'd, at a place called el-Khdr, as he was returning from visiting a sick person of the Benu-Hinah. He passed by unaware of their presence, and they slew him, Manazil-bin Khanbash, who resided at Naba and was agent for Mohammed-bin-Zaidah, and Rashid-bin Shathan the Julandaites, were angered at this proceeding; and they attacked the people of Ibra unawares. The latter, however, re pulsed them, and forty of them were slain, God then blessed the people of 'Oman by bestowing on them love of14 Annals of 1 Oman. the Truth, and a portion of the Musalmans rose up in defence of God's Truth, and overthrew the power of those tyrants. Insomuch as the learn ed Sheykhs of the people of 'Oman assembled at Nezwa under the guidance of Musa-bin Abu-Jabir el-Azkam, and desired the Imamate to be conferred on Mohammed-ibn Abu-'Aifan. Now amongst those present were certain chiefs who did not favour the change; and the Sheykh Musa fearing the purpose of the Musalmans might be frustrated and strife ensue, said, 'We have elected the son of 'Abu-'Affau to govern Nezwa and the towns of el-Jowf; and I fancy he ' added until war ceases.' T he I ma'm M ohammed-bin A bu-' A ffa'k .—And the Sheykh Abul- Manthar Bushir-bin el-Manthar remarked, ' We expected to see what would please us, but we have seen what disgusts us.' Musa rejoined, ' We have done what you wish,' but his object was to separate them, lest strife should arise. When the refractory chiefs returned to their respective dis tricts, the Sheykh wrote letters deposing them, and sent governors to the various towns. I imagine they were deposed before the arrival of the new Governors. Mohammed-bin Abu-'Affan then remained in the camp, and behaved in such a manner as to displease the Musalmans. It has reached me that what revolted them was his tyranny towards the Musalmans, and his rejection of good advice. However that be, they devised a stratagem by means of which they effected his expulsion from the camp of Nezwa; after which they held a meeting and deposed Mohammed and elected ano ther Imam. Mohammed had been Imam for two years and one month. T he I mam E l -W a'eith-bin K a'b .—Their choice fell on El -Warith- bin Ka'b el-Kharusi el-Shari 1 ' el-\ahmadi el-Azdi, who became Imam in the year 177 A. H. [A. D. 783.] El -Warith revived the ancient virtues of the Musalmans, and treading the paths of rectitude, honored the Truth and her followers. He repressed infidelity, and thus God vouchsafed the fall of the oppressors. In his time, Harun el-Rashid sent [against 'Oman] 'Isa-bin Ja'far-bin Abul-Mansur with a force of 1,000 cavalry and 5,000 infantry. Daud- bin \azid el-Mahallabi wrote to the Imam Waiith informing him of the arrival of 'Isa with his army, whereupon the Imam sent Faris-bin Moham med against him. The opposing forces encountered one another at Hatta, 16 and 'Isa-bin Ja'fer was defeated and forced to fly to his ships and put to sea. Abu-Hamid-bin Feleh el-Haddani el-Saluni followed him up, accompanied by 'Amru-bin 'Omar with three ships, and succeeded in capturing Tsa, who was taken to Sohar and there imprisoned. The Imam consulted the Sheykh Ah-bin 'Azrah concerning him, and he replied : ' It rests with you whether to put him to death or to spai'e him.' The Imam refrained from putting him to death and kept him imprisoned. I have heard that a party of Mu-Boole Second. 15 ShejH U salmans, amongst whom was Yahya-bin 'Abdul-'Aziz, set out without the knowledge of the Imam, and coming to Sohar scaled the wall of the prison and slew 'I'sa ; the Imam and the Wali being neither of them cognizant of their proceedings. They then returned to their homes the same night. On hearing of the death of Tsa, Harun resolved to send another army to 'Oman, and the people were in great fear of him. But he died ere his design was carried out, and God saved the people from the evil he had in store for them. [A. D. 809.] It is said that Yahya-bin 'Abdul-'Aziz was one of the most excellent of the Musalmans; he seems indeed to have been unsurpassed by any of his contemporaries. His fame equalled that of 'Abdul Aziz-bin Suleiman. It is handed down to us that the Sheykh Bashir-bin el-Mantbar was wont to say that the slayer of 'I'sa should not taste the tire. El-Warith continued to govern as Imam with virtue and justice, until God took him. He was drowned in a flood of the Wadi el-Nejdi (or the Wadi Kalbuh), and seven ty of his followers perished with him. This event happened as follows: He seems to have formed a prison near a scammony tree, and many Mu salmans were confined there. The Wadi became flooded, and the waters flowed down in a raging torrent, when the Imam was informed that the flood would reach the prisoners. He at once ordered them to be released, but no one would venture to their rescue from fear of the torrent. Then the Imam said, ' Since they are in my charge, and I shall be responsible for them at the day of Resurrection, I shall go across to them.' Accord ingly he made towards the prisoners, followed by a number of his attendants, but the torrent overtook them and swept all, including the prisoners, away. When the water of the Wadi dried up, the Imam's body was buried between 'Akr and Sa'al, where his grave is well known. His Imamate had lasted for twelve years and about six months. The Ima'm Ghassa'st-bin 'Abdullah . His successor was Ghassan-bin 'Abdullah el-Fajhi el-Yehmadi el-Azdi, who walked in the paths of the true Musalmans, and honoring the truth and those who followed it put a check on intidelity. In his time the ' Bowarih' 17 used to make descents on and ravage the coasts of 'Oman. Ghassan, however, fitted out small vessels with which he attacked the pirates in reprisal, until they were obliged to discontinue their attacks on 'Oman. He was the first ruler of 'Oman, who constructed vessels and employed them in naval warfare. During his reign el-Sakr-bin Moham med-bin Zaidah was slain. This person was amongst the number of those who declared the allegiance of the Musalmans due to Bashid-bin el-Nadhr el-Julandai, and he aided them with m.oney and arms. He was slain in the following manner: A person belonging to the Eastern districts, 18 raised a revolt against the Musalmans, and was joined by Benu-Hinah10 Annals of'Oman. and others. It was told to the M usalmans that the brother of el-Sakr was with the rebels; but el-Sakr denied it and gave out that his brother was lying sick in his house. When, however, God caused the rebels to be put to flight, it was ascertained that el-Sakr's brother was with them. El- Sakr was, therefore, suspected of treachery in concealing the conduct of his brother. So the Imam sent a party to Semail where he was residing. The Wall of Semail was Abul-Wadhdhah el-Sakr-bin Mohammed, who accompanied the Imam's messengers to el-Sakr, fearing on his ac count lest they should fall on him. The Imam had in the meantime sent a second party after him, and with them Musa-bin 'All. They met at Nejd-el-Sahamat. Whilst they were proceeding on their way, certain persons of their troop attacked el-Sakr, and killed him, Abul-Wadhdhah and Musa-bin 'Ali being unable to prevent them. The latter, it is indeed said, was alarmed for his own safety ; and had he opened his lips, he would have been slain with el-Sakr. It has been recorded that the Imam Grhassan showed displeasure against those who slew el-Sakr. Those were the days when the kingdom was in its prime and in the fulness of its power, and learning at its height. Such was the manner of el-Sakr s death, but God knows the truth. Among the executive measures of the Imam Ghassan, the following may be mentioned. There was at Semed of Nezwa a house belonging to the Benu-Julanda, the site of which was probably in the plantation named el-Akiidiyeh [arches]. One of the arches of this building spanned the high road, and above the arch were windows. Now the archway was dark, and was frequented by licentious and disreputable persons. It was said that a woman who happened to pass through the archway was molested by one of these bad characters, and the affair came to the knowledge of the Imam Ghassan, who ordered the owners of the house either to pull down the arch or to light it up by night, so that the persons passing should see who was there. The owners of the house, thereupon, opened out a new road for the public through their plantation, and it was used by people passing until the house was pulled down, after which the proprietors built a house across the new road, and the former highway was re-opened to the public. The remains of the arch may be seen in the southern wall of the mosque at Semed of Nezwa. Ghassan continued to govern justly and uprightly, until he fell ill on Wednesday, the 22nd of Thul-Ka'deh in the year of the Hijreh 207, and died of his illness [A. D. 822]. His Imamate had lasted fifteen years, seven months, and seven days. 19 He was succeeded by Iiie Imam 'Abdul-Ma'lik-bjn Hami'd , who derived from the stock of Sudah-bin 'All-bin 'Amr-bin 'Amir, surnamed Ma-el-Sema, the Azdite. Ihis Prince governed righteously and justly, and followed in the footstepsBooh Second. 17 % met n ' far, esbL of his virtuous predecessors. In those days 'Oman was blessed with prosperity. He was installed on Monday, the 22nd of the month of Showwal, A. H. 208. [A. D. 823], He continued to govern justly until he became aged and infirm, when dissensions broke out amongst his soldiery. The Musalmaus thereupon consulted Musa-bin 'All concern ing his deposition, and he advised them to assemble the soldiers and arrange for the government. Musa then assembled the troops, and proceeded to administer the Government, forbidding wrong-doing and strengthening the power of the Musalmans. Meanwhile Abdul-Malik remained in his house, and they did not depose him, so he remained Imam until he died. 20 His reign lasted eighteen years. T he I ma'm E l- M uhenna'-bin J eifar . The Musalmans then elected El-Muhenna-bin Jeifar el-Fajhi el-Yahmadi el-Azdi, on Friday in the month of Eejeb in the year 226 A. H. [A. D. 840]. This Prince trod in the footsteps of the Musalmans, and adhered to their principles. He was possessed of much firmness and decision of character. At his assemblies no person could presume to speak nor to interfere in favour of one litigant against another ; nor would any of his attendants venture to rise so long as he was seated ; neither would any person in receipt of military allowances enter unless properly armed. One of his agents for the collection of the sadakat (or poor rates) was a person named 'Abdullah-bin Suleiman of the Benu-Dhabbah of Manh, and he used to be sent to the grazing grounds to receive the contributions of cattle. It is related that he entered the land of Mahrah, 21 and went to a person of that district named Wasim-bin Ja'fer, from whom two payments were due. He, however, refused to pay more than one contribution, saying to the collector, ' Take that, if you like, and if not, behold the graves of your comrades.' 'Abdullah thereon held his peace and returned. He had with him a camel driver, and when he reached Azz, where his home was, he tarried there, and sent the camel driver on to the Imam. The man arrived whilst the Imam was holding his levee. As soon as that was over, he summoned the camel driver, and asked him about 'Abdullah and how he had fared on his journey. So he informed the Imam of the conduct of Wasim. The Imam strictly enjoined the camel man not to disclose what he had reported to any one, but to keep the matter secret. When 'Abdullah- bin Suleiman arrived, the Imam questioned him about Wasim, and 'Abdullah repeated what the camel driver had reported. Thereupon the Imam at once wrote to the Walls of Adam, Senao, and Ja'alan to the effect that if they could succeed in capturing Wasim of Mahrah, they were to keep him securely and send him word. The Wall of Adam wrote to say he had taken Wasim, whereon the Imam sent to him Yahya the Yahmam, known as Abu-Makarish, with a body of horsemen. After them he despatched a18 Annals of 1 Oman. second detachment who came up with the first at el-Menaif; then a third, which joined at the village of 'Azz ; and a fourth troop, which overtook the others at Manh. In this manner he continued despatching troop after troop, so that it might be said the prisoner was borne along on their spears, until they arrived at Nezwa with him. There the Imam ordered him to be imprisoned, and he remained a year in confinement, during which period no one dared to mention his name, nor to enquire concerning him. At length, a deputation of persons arrived from el-Mahrah, who through the el-Yahmad chiefs interceded for him with el-Muhenna, who consented to release him on one of the following conditions, from which he desired them- to choose— First,—that they should emigrate from 'Oman. Second,—that they should agree to fight. Third,—that they should bring the cattle every year to the camp of Nezwa, where impartial witnesses should attest that the due complement was produced and that none were withheld; also the witnesses should arbitrate concerning them at Adam. To these proposals the deputation replied in the following terms : ' As for emigrating, it is impossible for us ' to do so; and as for war, we shall not fight against the Imam; but we ' are ready to bring the camels.' On this the Imam appointed the witnesses, and thenceforth they used to bring their camels, and max-ch them round every year. I have heard say that the pillar which stands at Fark was erected in the time of el-Muhenna as a mark for the Benu-Mahrah, that they should assemble their camels on that spot; but Grod knows if this is true. And in those days el-Mogheyreh- bin Rusin, the Julandaite, and his associates of the Benu-Julanda, and other turbulent people raised a rebellion, and went forth to Towwam where Abul- Wadhdhah was Wall for the Imam el-Muhenna. The insurgents slew the said Wall. Now at that time Abu-Marwan was Wall of Sohar ; and as soon as the intelligence reached the Musalmans, he at once set out with his followers and allies, amongst whom was el-Mattar el-Hindi and his followers of the el-Hind. When they reached Towwam, God caused the Benu-Julan'da to be defeated and dispersed ; some of them were slain, and the rest took to flight. On this el-Mattar and a number of ignorant soldiers made for the houses of the Benu-Julanda and set fire to them. The cattle were tied up within the enclosure, and it is related that one of the soldiers repeatedly threw himself into the water, so as to wet his body and clothes and rushed into the midst of the fire, in order to cut the tethers and to allow the beasts to save themselves from burning. It is said from fifty to seventy buildings were burned down. I have heard it related that the women of the Benu- Julanda fled to the desert, where they remained for some time. They had with them a handmaid, whom, when they fell in want of food and drink, they sent by night to beg a supply from a neighbouring village. The girl'Boole Second. 19 Uta «) MtB lie girl succeeded in obtaining some meal and a skin for holding milk and a fragment of ajar. She then tilled her skin with water from the stream, and was returning to the women, when she was perceived by a soldier, who overtook her and took from her the meal which he poured on the ground, and after taking the water from her also, left her. I have found it stated that Abu-Marwan did not give the order for burning the village ; it is more probable that he had forbidden such a proceeding, but that his words were disregarded. It is said that the Imam sent two messengers to the tribe whose village had been burnt, inviting them to return and promising to make them fitting compensation. The number of Abu-Marwan's forces is stated to have been 12,000. El-Muhenna remained Imam until his death, which occurred on the 16th of Rabi'-ul Akhir, A. H. 237, [A. D. 851] he having reigned as Imam for ten years and some months and days, during which time he enjoyed the approval and support of the Musalmans in general. Nevertheless, I find it mentioned in the biography of the Sheykh Abu-Kahtan Khalid-bin Kahtan that the Sheykh Mohammed-bin Mahbub and Bashir had knowledge of the conduct of el-Muhenna incompatible with the retention of the Imamate, and consequently they secretly renounced him. God knows whether this is true. The Ima'm El-Salt-bin Ma'lik . On the day of el-Muhenna's death, the Musalmans elected el-Salt-bin Malik to be their ruler. At that time, the most excellent of the Musalmans and their leader and guide in science and religious learning was Mohammed-bin Mahbub. They swore allegiance to el-Salt-bin Malik in the same manner that the just Imams who preceded him had been acknowledged. He governed justly and uprightly for a long period, until all the Sheykhs of the Musalmans who had elected him had passed away. Not one of them, as far as we know, seceded from him. He lived as Imam longer than any of his predecessors, until he grew old and feeble. His infirmity, however, was only in his limbs, for we are not aware that any one asserted that his mind, hearing, or sight had become impaired. When the scroll of Destiny announced that his time was come, and God willed to try the people of 'Oman, as He had tried those who had gone before them, Musa-bin Musa rose up against him, and pursued him until he alighted at Fark. 22 Thereupon the people forsook el-Salt, who being too weak to retain his position was deposed from the Imamate. The Ima'm Ra'shid-bin el-Nadhb . Musa then conferred the Imamate on Rashid-bin el-Nadhr on Thursday, three days before the end of the month of el-Hijj, 273 A. H. [A. D. 886]. The Imamate of el-Salt had lasted 35 years, 7 months, and 8 days. His death occurred on Friday night in the middle of Thul-Hijjah, 275 A. H. In his days died the most accomplished and eminent of scholars Mohammed-bin Mahbub.20 Annals of 1 Oman. Book III. 'om the Outbreak of Civil Dissensions to the Imdmate of Sa'id-hin- 1 Abdullah. A. D. 886 to A. D. 934. There then arose dissensions in 'Oman, and much misery ensued. The people became divided in religion and counsels, and civil war and discord fell grievously upon them. Then Musa renounced liashid and his wickedness and error, and rising against him deposed him. The Ima m 'Azza'n-bin Temi'm . 'Azzan-bin Termm el-Kharusi suc ceeded to the Imamate on Tuesday, three nights before the end of the month of Safar, A. H. 277. [A. D. 890.] Amongst those present at the ceremony of vowing obedience were 'Omar-bin Mohammed the Kadhl, and Mohammed-bin Musa-bin 'AH and 'Azzan-bin el-Hizabr, and Azhar-bin Mohammed-bin Suleiman. Musa and 'Azzan continued to be mutual friends for a long time, but at length they quarrelled, and 'Azzan deposed Musa from the office of Kadhi. 'Azzan then feared what might happen to him from Musa, and hastened to send a force against him, which he raised partly from the inmates of the prisons. They proceeded to Izkl, 1 where they entered the walled enclosure of the el-Nizar, 2 and set to work to slaughter, seize, carry off and plunder the inhabitants of Izki. They then set fire to the place, and burned many of the people alive. Musa-bin Musa was killed by the pebbles of Roddah near the mosque of el-Hajar in the quarter of el-Jenur, In short, they treated the people of Izki with unheard-of barbarity. The warfare thenceforward became grievous, and hatred and anger were rife; each side endeavoured by every means in its power to inflict loss on its rival. 'Azzan received those who brought the intelligence of this affair with honour, and rewarded them with largesse, and withheld his favours from such as had held back from the expedition against Izki. This affair took place on Sunday, one day before the end of Sha'ban, A. H. 278. [A. D. 891]. In consequence of this occurrence el-Fadhl-bin el-Hawarl el-Koreishi- el-Nizari took the field, in order to avenge the massacre of the people of Izki. He was joined by the el-Madhariyeh, 3 and the el-Haddan and some of the Benul-Harith of el-Batineh ; and he was met by 'Abdullah el- Haddani in the mountains of the el-Haddan. 4 El-Fadhl proceeded to Towwam which is el-Jow. s Thence he returned to el-Haddan. He was there joined by el-Hawari-bin 'Abdullah el-Salunl, and they proceeded on the 16th of Showwal of the same year to Sohar, which they entered on the 23rd of the same month on a Friday. They attended Friday prayers, 6 and Zeyd-bin Suleiman officiated on the occasion, and preached to the people, after which he blessed el-Hawari-bin 'Abdullah el- Saluni from the pulpit. They remained in Sohar the rest of Friday andBooh Third. 21 mk «*Dl Saturday ; and in the evening of Sunday, they went forth to encounter el- AMf-bin Hamham el-Hinai, and those who accompanied him of the adherents of 'Azzan-hin Temim. For when the latter heard of their move ment, he sent against them el-Ahif-bin Hamham, chief of the Benu-Hinah T with a force of the el-Yahmad, amongst them Fahm-bin Warith. They proceeded until they reached Majiz in el-Batineh, and summoned el-Salt-bin Nadhr, who came forth against them with horse and foot. El-Fadhl-bin el-Hawan and el-Hawari-bin 'Abdullah also came up, and a battle ensued, in which a great number of the Madhrxyeh were slain, and the remainder were forced to fly. This encounter took place on Monday, four days before the end of the month of Showwal of the above mentioned year. There continued to be strife amongst the people of 'Oman, and their mutual animosities increased in bitterness. The Imamate became to them as a thing to sport with, and an object of rebellious contention and incentive to ambitious designs. They followed not God's book nor the footsteps of their virtuous ancestors. Matters reached such a pass that in one year they set up sixteen different Imams, and in each case failed to hold to the allegiance they had vowed. At length, when the fulness of the time was come, Mohammed-bin Abil-Kasim and Bashir-bin el-Manther of the Benu-Samah-bin Lawa-bin- Gh.tlib went forth and proceeded to el-Bahreyn, where at that time Mohammed-bin Nur 8 was governor on the part of el-Mo'tadhid. 9 To him they complained, on arrival, of the sufferings they had endured from the Himyarite 10 faction, and invited him to accompany them to'Oman, tempting him by holding out hopes of great advantages. The governor acquiesced, but advised them to visit the Khalifeh at Baghdad and state the circum stances to him, and that their object in coming was a desire for his success. So Mohammed-bin Abil-Kasim went on to Baghdad, whilst Bushfr remained with Mohammed-bin Niir. When Mohammed was admitted to the Khalifeh's presence, he related to him the whole matter, and obtained a commission for Mohammed-bin Nur to proceed against 'Oman ; after which he returned to el-Bahreyn. On his return there, Mohammed-bin Nur commenced raising a force from the various tribes, but principally from the Nizar. He was joined also by some of the tribe Tei from el-Sham, and inarched against 'Oman at the head of 25,000 men, of whom 3,500 were horsemen equipped in armour and with their baggage. The report of Mohammed-bin Nur's approach caused great commotion in 'Oman, where the people were split up into rival factions, their counsels devoid of concert and their hearts disunited. Some there were who emigrated from 'Oman with their families and property, and others found no resource but to resign themselves to disgrace. Suleiman-bin 'Abd-el-Malik-bin- Bilal-el-Salirm with his retainers proceeded to Hormuz, and the people of22 AnnaU of'Oman. Sohar emigrated with their property and families to Shiriz and el-Basreh. Mohammed-Vjin Nur meanwhile advanced with his forces and took Julfar, whence he proceeded to Towwam, which he reached, after some encounters had taken place in the sandy wastes, on Wednesday, six days before the end of the month el-Moharram, A. H. 280 [A D. 893] ; and conquered el-Sirr and neighbouring districts. He then advanced on Xezwa, from which place 'Azzan-bin Temim, finding himself deserted by the people, fled to Semed-el- Shan. As soon as Mohammed-bin Xur appeared, Xezwa surrendered to him, and he continued his advance on Semed-el-Shan, and encountered 'Azzan- bin Temi'm, and on Wednesday, five days before the end of Safar of the same year, a severe contest occurred, which resulted in the flight of the people of 'Oman and the death of 'Azzan-bin Temim. Thus 'Oman passed out of the hands of its inhabitants. ' It was not ' that God had changed His grace which was in them, but they themselves ' changed the disposition in their souls by sin. '' For they fought amongst themselves for power and supremacy, each one aiming at having the authority in his own hands or in the hands of those he favoured. So God delivered them into the power of one more unjust than themselves. And since they had become corrupt in their religion, therefore God deprived them of their kingdom, and set an enemy over them to rule them. The rule of the Ibadhiyeh from their first accession to power until their overthrow by Mohammed-bin Xur had lasted one hundred and sixty-three years all but a month and twelve days. God knows the truth ! Mohammed-bin Xur sent the head of 'Azzan-bin Temi'm to the Khali'feh at Baghdad, and returned to Xezwa, where he took up his residence. Soon after el-Ahif-bin Hamham el-Hinai wrote to the Sheykhs of 'Oman and the tribes of all the districts, calling on and exhorting them to rise against Mohammed-bin Xur and drive him from 'Oman. They responded to the summons, and he marched against Mohammed-bin Xur with a numerous and well ordered force. When the latter heard of this, terror seized his heart and he took to flight, and was pursued by el-AMf and his army. The prudent course would have been to avoid a battle, and follow leisurely until Mohammed-bin Xur should pass the frontier of 'Oman and then to return. But God so willed it for His purposes that they marched quickly and overtook him at Damma, and a severe encounter took place, in which many were killed and wounded on both sides. The contest was going against Mohammed-bin Xur and his followers who were on the point of taking to flight, and had sought safety on the sea shore. At this juncture a body of troops appeared on the scene mounted by twos on camels. These were the advance guard and others of a force of Madhari- yeh sent by Abu-'Obeydeh-bin Mohammed-el-Sami to the assistance of Mohammed-bin Xur. As soon as they had drawn nigh to the rival armies,JBooh Third. 23 - - ^ ^ -m ^ ^ *S5t 'Its® they alighted from their camels and seizing their weapons charged with Mohammed-bin Nur against el-Ahif and his followers, who were exhausted by fatigue. So it happened that when on the point of gaining the victory, the people of 'Oman were put to flight, and El-Ahif-bin Hamham and many of his relatives and others were slain, few of the people of 'Oman escaping. Mohammed-bin Nur after this returned to Nezwa, and ruled supreme over all 'Oman dividing the people and committing evil throughout the land, which together with the sons of the land he ruined by his tyranny. As soon as Mohammed-bin Nur had re-established his authority in 'Oman, he degraded the most honorable of the inhabitants and reduced them to the most abject condition. He caused people to have their hands, feet, and ears cut off, their eyes put out, and generally treated the inhabitants with the greatest severity and contempt. He also filled up the water channels, burnt the books, and 'Oman passed out of the hands of its people. After wards desiring to return to el-Bahrein, he placed a person named Ahmed- bin Hilal as Governor of all 'Oman, and himself returned to el-Bahrein. The residence of this Ahmed was at Bahla. He also placed a Governor at Nezwa, named Beyharah, surnamed Abu-Ahmed. This person was informed one day that Abul-Hawan and his adherents repudiated Musa-bin Musa, on hearing which he sent a soldier to Abul-Hawari, who came to him as he was seated after morning prayer in the Mihrab 1 ' Sa'id, known by the name of Abul-Kasim (that is the mosque of el-Shejebi), reading the Koran, and informed him that Abu-Ahmed required his presence. Abul-Hawari replied that he had nothing to do with him, and resumed his reading. The soldier remained in astonishment, not knowing what course to tako with him, until a messenger came from el-Beyharah with orders not to interfere with Abul-Hawari, whereupon the soldier returned, and Abul- Hawari remained unmolested by the blessed infiuence of the sacred book. It is said the soldier related afterwards that he had summoned him to arise^ fearing lest his blood should be spilt in the Mihrab. El-Beyharah continued to be governor of Nezwa until the people rose and slew him. His corpse was dragged away and buried in a well known spot a little below the gate called Mo'thir, by the way side of the road leading to Fark, where they cast manure and ashes and other refuse. God knows the truth 1 The people then gave allegiance to The Ima'm Mohammed-bin el-Hasan el-Khaeusi as a Shari Imam. 13 He soon after abdicated, and they elected The Ima'm El-Salt-bin el-Ka'sim . They deposed him and declared for The Ima'm 'Azza'n-bin Hazabe el-Ma'liki ', who derived from Kelb-el- Yahmad. He was also deposed and their choice fell on The Ima'm 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed el-Hadda'ni ', known as Abu- Sa'id cl-Karmati. They deposed him also and re-elected24 Annals of 1 Oman. T he I ma m E l- S alt- K a'sim (eestobed), w L o died in the Imamate. Next they elected T he I ma'm el-hasan-bur el- S ahteynt ', who died in less than a month. T he I ma'm el- H awa'ei'-bii? M atraf . Then they elected el-Hawaii- bin Matraf el-Haddam as a Dafi'i 14 Imam. He set to work to repress the licentious workers of folly with j^reat severity. But on each occasion when the Sultan came to 'Oman to tax the inhabitants, he was wont to withdraw from the house of the Imamate to his private residence, and made no attempt to prevent his committing injustice and tyranny. As soon as the Sultan had quitted 'Oman, he would return to the house of the Imamate, and placing the crown of office on his head, would say to those around him ; ' There is no Gov ernment but belongstoGod, and noobedience is due to those who rebel against God. Lp to the time of his death, some of the Benu-Asameh remained in attendance on him by order of the Sultan. The Sultan here mentioned was the Sultan of Baghdad.' God knows the truth ! On his death, they elected his nephew 'Omar-bin Mohammed-bin Mat'af. Ihe Imam ■Omae-bin Mohammed . This Prince adhered to the same policy as his uncle had adopted, retiring when the Sultan came and returning to office on the latter's departure. At this period the Karamiteh 16 invaded 'Oman, on which 'Omar resigned the Imamate. When the Kararnit -h returned to Bahreyn, he did not resume office. These Karamiteh had overrun many countries including Mekkah and el-Sham and subdued the various tribes. They were styled Bemi-Abi-Sa'id- el-Hasan-ibn Bahram-bin Bohrist-el-Heyyani.' Abu-Sa'id abolished prayer, the fast, pilgrimage, and religious alms, and turned these observances into allegory. He so deluded his weak-minded followers, that they deified him in the place of the Almighty. He was at length overthrown by 'Abdullah- bin- All, who fought against him with only -400 men, notwithstanding that their armies were numerous. He continued to strive with them for seven years, until they were deprived of power. I nteiiuegxum . After this there was an interregnum in 'Oman, during which period no Imam was elected. T he I ma'm M ohammed-but Y ezi'd . At length, they elected to the Imamate Mohammed-bin Yezid el-Kundi [or Kindi], whose residence was at Semed-el-Kundi. He was elected as a Bafi'i Imam, being incapacitated from election as Shan on account of being in debt. 18 At this time the Sultan subdued 'Oman, and placed two forces in occupation of it, one at el-Sin, and the other at el-'Atik. thereupon Mohammedrbin Yezid fled from 'Oman, and el-Hakam-bin el-Mulla el-Bohri, a resident of Sa'al, was elected Imam. I ke I mam el- H akam-bin el- M ulla. We know not of any previous'•ssina^ Sj^ a: aa: aj tlsjcii' ' Wii Jflj iiiEiajj iaa-iiWrii iiotedinTir, ieniiteSEiio rT (Eftji lia K'iodiua- siaiajtiat iSikfcrai &gt; r ari? xtec to tk jq&lt;Hl!¥ fli j: e!t ibs }f it ok ii n Yeniilfei ^Sril,« Book IV. Containing an Account of tJie Imams Sa'id-hin '■Abdullah and ltdsldd-bin- el-M'olid and their successors to the time of ''Omar-bin el-Kdsim el- Fadheyli. A.D. 934 to A.D, 1560. The next of the Imams appointed in 'Oman, after the people had come to be divided into factions, was Abul-Kasim Sa'fd-hin £ Ahdullah-bin Moham med-bin Mahbub-bin el-Eaheyl-bin Seyf-bin Hubeyrah, the horseman of the Prophet (on whom be peace !). I know not the date of his election, nor how long he was Imam 1 ; neither have I learnt by whom he was slain, and for what cause. I have perused many books and questioned many well-informed persons in search of information on these subjects, but in vain. Please God, however, I shall still endeavour to discover. I find that the first person to declare Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah Imam was Abu-Mohammed el-Hawari-bin 'Othman, then Abu-Mohammed 'Abdullah- bin Mohammed-bin Abil-Muathir. Next I reckon Mohammed-bin Zaideh el-Simuli. I find also that this Imam was elected as a Dafi'i, not as a Shari. 2 Abu-Mohammed 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed was wont to extol his learninar and to assert that his attainments surpassed those of any previous Imam. It has also come down to us that Abu-'Abdullah Mohammed-bin Pub said that the Imam Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah was more learned than any of those who elected him and associated with him. It is known to us from the unanimous testimony of the select circle of those who profess the true Faith, 3 that he was recognised as our Ruler and Imam. He passed away. May God have mercy on his soul! We know not that an}' found fault with his election to the Imamate, nor with his character; neither did any secede from him. We learn moreover of Abu-Mohammed 'Abdullah-bin Moham med-bin Abil-Muathir that he said : 'We know of no Imam of the 'Musalmans in 'Oman more excellent than Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah, for he was ' an upright and learned Imam, and he died the death of a martyr. All Imam, whether Musalman or sinner, who equalled el-Hakam-bin el-Mulla in weakness and imbecility. He soon abdicated, and the Sultan placed an army at Nezwa. God knows the truth I My own opinion is, that none of the Imams mentioned after el Salt-bin Malik were universally recognised by the people of 'Oman, and that their rule did not extend over the entire country. They were recognised in certain districts and not in others, by some of the tribes only, and not by all. For after the dissensions which had arisen amongst them, the people of 'Oman had ceased to act in unison, and could not agree in the choice of an Imam. As they had cast away the blessings bestowed on them by God, so their hearts became disunited. Booh Fourth.26 Annals of 1 Oman. ' these things were combined in him. May God have mercy on him f' It may he, however, that el-Julanda-hin Mes'dd was his equal; but we are told that the Sheykh Abu-Ibralnm Mohammed-hin Sa'id-hin Ahu-Bekr said— 'The Imam Sa'id-hin 'Abdullah was superior to Julanda-bin Mes'ud; for ' he was a just and righteous Imam, excelling the people of his time in ' learning, and he died a martyr withal. May God pardon him and ' compensate us and el-Islam for his loss with the highest requital, where- ' with He compensates a people for their Imam!' This is what I have found recorded of his excellence. I find the date of the affair in which he was killed stated to have been the year 323 A. H. [A. D. 934]. 1 have read a book in which it is stated that he met his death in the following manner. A woman of the people of el-Ghashb of el-Rostak was drying grain in the sun, when a sheep came and ate some of it, on seeing which the woman cast a stone and broke the sheep's leg. Another woman who owned the sheep, then came up and began beating the first woman, who cried to her people to aid her. One of her friends came up and also one of the other woman's friends, and each side being augmented by fresh arrivals a severe contest commenced. The Imam Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah repaired to the scene with a single attendant for the purpose of separating the combatants, and was killed in the melee. God knows the truth of this. The Ima'm Ka'shid-bik el-Wali d . The next Imam was Rashid-bin- el-Walfd, who was elected in the following manner . There assembled toge ther the Sheykh Abu-Mohammed 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed-bin Abul- Muathir and Abu-Mes'ud el-Na'man-bin 'Abdul-Hamid, and Abu-Moham med 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed-bin Shikheh. And amongst those present at the ceremony were Abu-'Othman llamshaki-bin Eashid and Abu- Mohammed 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed-bin Salih and Abu-Manthir-hin Abu- Mohammed-bin Rub. These persons who assembled on this occasion were respected and distinguished in the same degree as were those who elected the Imam Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah in their time. No persons of sense denied their excellence nor ignored their uprightness, and of their contemporaries in the same Faith none were comparable to them. Thus ' there are men for every time, as there is a word for every occasion.' People of every age desire the general welfare of their religion. This is proverbial. The authority was with those who were present and not with the absent. Those who bore witness could not alter, and those who did not could not demur. He who gave admittance could not expel, nor could the alfirmer deny his word. Now it was known to this assembly that there was an adversity of sentiment amongst the members, and that mutual recrimination had place with regard to the affair of Musa-bin Musa, and Rashid-bin el-Nadhr. Wherefore, when they had resolved to elect Rashid-bin el-Walid Imam, they deemed it expedient to summon a general council, to come to anBoole Fourth. 27 i llSfj ilfirs ■asKasii agreement as to the course to be adopted in that matter. Accordingly, a great number of the elect of the true Faith assembled in the house at Nezwa, in which Rashid-bin el-Walid used to reside. All of those we have named as having been present at the election of Rashid-bin el-Walid attended except Abu-Mes'ud-el-Na'man, who was absent. The President of the Council was Abu-Mohammed 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed-bin Abul- Muathir. They unanimously resolved to adopt a policy of neutrality as between Musa-bin Musa and Rashid-bin ebNadhr, and to hold aloof from both as regarded the Government, granting at the same time that both were sincere believers in their religion. We know not of any of them that he acted wrongfully in either of these courses. The matter, then, was settled amongst them in this fashion ; although the wording as to details may be more or less incomplete, still, the general result was as stated. 4 Having agreed on this course, they thereupon proceeded to swear allegiance to the Imam Rashid-bin el-Walid, binding him to administer the duties of his office in obedience to God and his Apostle; to govern uprightly and repress crime ; to prosecute wars in defence of the Faith as a Dafi'i Imam ; and further to tread in the footsteps of the just Imams, his predecessors, in imitation of their virtue and uprightness. On such conditions did Abu- Mohammed-bin Abil-Muathir swear fealty in the house at Nezwa, and after him, in the same manner, Abu-Mes'ud and the rest of the assembly. The Imam having accepted their vows, they went forth to the open plain at Nezwa, where a vast concourse of the people of 'Oman had collected. They had come not only from Nezwa, but from the various towns of the East and the West of 'Oman, and the assemblage was composed of persons of unimpeachable integrity, holding positions of rank and authority. They all assented to and obeyed the decision of the Council without the slightest sign of repugnance or disapproval. Then arose Abu-Mohammed 'Abdullah- bin Mohammed-bin Shikheh, and approaching Rashid hailed him as Imam, and announced to the people that the Council had elected him, commanding them to vow their allegiance. This they did openly and willingly without a dissentient voice. Some of the persons referred to made their vows separately, and in other cases in parties ; and for some time people kept arriving for the purpose of making the compact, until the whole kingdom had declared for the new Imam. Some appeared in person to swear allegiance, others saluted him as Imam,® whilst others again proved their minds by exhibiting a ready submission. The Imam had no occasion to use force, as no secret disaffection existed. He sent his governors and agents to all the districts and villages, and no one molested them. He performed the Friday service at Nezwa, and he and his agents collected the sadakat 6 , or poor-rate. He also reviewed the troops, presenting standards and issuing all necessary orders. His receipts on account of the revenues of the kingdom were large,28 Annals of 1 Oman. and every district of 'Oman acknowledged his authority as Sultan, 7 and none rebelled against it in those days. All paid what was his due and openly acknowledged him as Imam, without the exercise on his part of any severity, open or secret, or any form of intimidation. On the other hand, there was no display of weak leniency, nor undue conciliation; nor was it necessary for him to work on the sordid feelings and hopes of profit of those who dissemble their fears, and betray others for gain or ambition. He was gentle to his subjects, and acted in harmony with their opinions, kindly indulgent to their defects and faults and pleased with their virtues. He was impartial in his judgment between all classes, whether noble, religious, poor, or rich. Those at a distance received equal consideration with those present. All were received with hospitality, and assiduous attention given to their affairs. He was accustomed also to consult with those below him in rank and to avail himself of their advice. Thus he continued to take on himself the burden of the cases of his subjects, sacrificing his own enjoyments and the society of those he loved for their good; and he ceased not in the same manner to bear patiently the misfortunes and deprivation of enjoyment and separation from friends, which his subjects caused him to suffer. He had to endure slander and injury, 8 calamity, and indignity, and bore all with patience, trusting to Ood for better times. Many of his subjects were watching for an opportunity to injure him, and in secret entertained most evil designs against him. Iniquity appears in the countenances of the unbelievers, and their breasts hide not hatred and envy.' 9 The Evil one had gained the mastery over their minds, and an evil fate and their own animosities overcame them. Some amongst them, whilst seeking his ruin, pretended friendship outwardly. If God gave him success, they feigned to rejoice and congratulate him. If, however, success attended the enemy, they would abandon him on pretence of inability to assist, asserting that if they only had the power, they would fight against the enemies of the Truth. Many proffered aid in words, whilst in secret abandoning his cause. Others again assisted him from interested motives, but only nominally and without sincerity. If good befel, they took advantage of it, but in time of adversity turned their backs. In short, it is impossible to enumerate the various evil motives by which they were actuated. Exception may be made in the case of a few persons who had not power to assist him, who saw they could not mend a hopeless cause by remaining faithful. At length his affairs reached such a point that his people opposed and abandoned him, and the nobles conspired together to enter into intrigues against his power with the Sultan whom they prepared to support. The Imam made strong attempts to prevent this, and fierce enmity ensued be tween him and his subjects, who separated from him at the town of Bahla,Boole Fourth. 29 and went forth obstinately in open rebellion, resolved on his downfal. The Sultan meanwhile had been advancing to el-Sirr, whilst the Imam, beiug deserted by the main body of his army who were now opposed to him, had only a small and weak body of followers. He had only left Nezwa indeed in hopes of inducing them to abandon their intention of going forth to join the approaching foe. Finding himself deserted and rebelled against, and unable with his small party to oppose the Sultan, he feared to be sur prised in the place, and withdrew with his followers from Bahla to Ka- dam. 10 He hoped that by this step he had ensured his safety and kept on his guard. He remained at Kadam until he ascertained that the enemy had entered el-Jowf, when he became alarmed, and removed with a small party of attendants to Wadi el-Nakhr. 11 He then busied himself actively in endeavouring to raise a force to oppose the Sultan, and at length succeeded in assembling a sufficient num ber of allies and adherents to commence active operations against the enemy. By this time the Sultan was encamped at Nezvva. By the advice of those present of his kinsmen and well-wishers, who thought it best in the interests of Islam, the Imam remained behind the army which he sent against the tyrant Sultan at Nezwa. He took his position close to the pass to Manh, so he was not distant from them. As God had ordained, his army was defeated and put to flight and dispersed, and the Imam went forth vanquished and panic-stricken, seeking safety from his pursuers. The battle occurred in the forenoon, and by evening he found himself aban doned by all his followers, a prey to terror and deprived of all hope of the success of his people. The tyrant Sultan then reduced all 'Oman with its various districts to submission. The people sought to ingratiate themselves with the Sultan, who, on his part, deluded and beguiled them, until all the districts had submitted to his rule. Meanwhile the Imam lay concealed amongst the heights of the mountains and in desert places, in fear alike from the Sultan and from his own subjects, dreading to meet death at every place, and in terror of being surprised in his sleep. Whilst he was thus a fugitive from home and family in terror of his life, the people of his kingdom were dwell ing in their houses in peace and security, having artfully conciliated the Sultan and ingratiated themselves with him. There was nothing to induce the Imam to withhold his submission ; indeed there was no other course open to him but submission, as no further effort was possible. H e deliber ated concerning his position and consulted with persons of sound judgment. He acted in accordance with the decisions and sanctions of people of piety, who pronounced an opinion, which, as far as we know is incontrovertible, that a Dafi'i Imam is justified in practising ' religious dissimulation' 12 when abandoned by his subjects. And we know not of a more signal80 Annals of '■Oman. instance of desertion and rebellion on the part of the subjects against their Sovereign. But God is merciful and beneficent, and He provides for His servants an escape from every difficulty in matters of religion, and grants an excuse for all who are helpless. The Imam and his people alike suffered in accordance with the decrees of Fate. He accordingly returned to his home and made his submission, hoping to remain in unmolested retirement. A messenger came to him from the Sultan with an assurance of safety, but he seems to have given the promise verbally and not on oath. The Imam abstained from frequenting the Sultan's levees until the latter came to him and forcibly insisted on his doing so. By this act of submission his Imam- ate, in our opinion, terminated forthwith ; and this furnished an evident excuse for the establishment of the rule of his rival. We have not heard that, during his administration of the Imamate and the vicissitudes which befel, any reproach or blame attached to Eashid-bin el-Walfd. He lived for a short time after these events, admired by all, and was much regretted when he died. In his time, Rashid-bin el-Walid was humble in spirit, and none of the pious found fault with him on account of any of his actions. May God requite el-Islam and its people for the loss of one who acted just ly and uprightly ! and may He recompense us all and all who knew his excellence, as a people is recompensed for their Imam, a brother for a bro ther ! We have recounted only a portion of the virtues of Rashid-bin el- W alid, which we trust will not be questioned, but much more might have been added on this subject. For he was endowed with every virtue, so much so in fact, that his good qualities are proverbial, and such as to baffle all attempts to recount them. His fall dated from the battle of Nezwa, after which, deserted by his own subjects, he was obliged to dissimulate and seek the favour of the Sultan ; for there was no refuge for him from the confines of Julfar to the borders of Ra'wan; neither in the hills of 'Ataleh, nor in the land of el-Haddan, nor el-Rostak. Everywhere was bitterness and vileness, and every foe treated him with obloquy. 13 The Ima m el-Khali'l-bik Siia'tha'n '. Amongst the Imams elected in 'Oman was el-Khalil-bin Shathan, who probably reigned in the begin ning of the 5th century of the Hijrah. The Imam Rasiiid-bin Sa'i'd . Next was Rashid-bin Sa'id, who died in the month of Moharram, A. H. 445. [A. D. 1053.] Verse. W e mourn not for the loss of goats or sheep or camels j but when one dies whose loss brings death to many, then is real woe.' The Ima'm Mohammed-bin Habi's , On the day of his death, Moham med-bin Habis was invested as Imam by Nijad-bin Musa, the Kadlu of theBoole Fourth. 31 1 ©iiti J iii spirit, and late Imam, and the preceptor Abu-Bekr Ahmed-bin Mohammed pronounced the khotbeh. This was in 510 A. H. [A. D. 111G.] # * # * * The Ima'm Mohammed-best Kilajstbash . Afterwards, Mohammed-bin Khanbash became Imam. He died in 557 A. H. [A. D. 1162], and was buried by the small black hill, called Jebel Thu-Juyud, near Feleij el-Kantak. His death occasioned greater suffering to the people of 'Oman than that of any previous Imam. The Ima'm Haps-bin Ra'shid . His son Hafs-bin liashid was then elected. The Ima'm Ra'shid-bik 'Alt '. Then came Rashid-bin 'All, who died on Sunday, in the middle of Thul-Ka'deh, A. H. 476. In one work, how ever, the date of his death is placed at A. H. 513. God knows which of the dates is most correct. 14 The Ima'm Mu'sa-bin Abu-Ja'bib . Then was elected Musa-bin Jabir- el-Mu'ali-bin Musa-bin Nejad, who died in the year 549 A. H. [A. D. 1153.] I have translated the following passage from the MS. work of the learned 'Othman-bin Musa-bin Mohammed-bin 'Othman, who lived in the quarter named el-Jarmah of 'Akr at Nezwa. The Ima'm Habi's-bin Mohammed. The Ima'm Ma'xik-bin el- Hawa'bi'. On the 17th of Jumadi-el-Awwal,' died the Imam Habfs-bin Moham- med-bin Hisham, whose death was a severe affliction to the people. Malik- bin el-Hawari became Imam in the year 809 [A. D. 1406], and died in 83.2 A. H. [A. D. 1429]. I have not discovered accounts of any Imams during the interval that here elapses of a little more than two hundred years. 16 God knows whether those were years of an interregnum during which no Imam was elected, or whether the names of the Imams have been lost to us. I have, however, found an account of an expedition of the people of Shiraz against 'Oman, under Fakhr el-din Ahmed-bin el-Dayah and Shihab el-din with 4,500 horsemen. The people of 'Oman endured extreme suffering from these invaders. They ejected the principal persons of el- Aki at Nezwa from their houses, and remained in this manner for four months in 'Oman. They also besieged Bahla, but were unable to take it. Ibn-Dayah having died, God caused their fall. The people also suffered from a severe famine. That was in the reign of the Sultan 'Omar-bin ISebhan in the }eai 6/4 A. H 18 [A. D. 1279]. I have also lighted on an account of an expedition of one of the Amirs of Hormuz, named Mahmud-bin Ahmed el-Kashi, who landed at the town of Kalhat. 19 At that time Abul-Ma'ali-Kahlan-bin Nebhan and his brother 'Omar-bin Nebhan ruled over 'Oman. On arrival at Kalhat, Mahmud summoned Abul Ma'ali, who told him that he held possession of82 Annals of '■Oman. only one district of'Oman, whereupon Mahmncl replied, ' Take as many of my soldiers as j^ou please, and proceed against those of 'Oman who oppose you.' Abul-Ma'ali then told him that the people of 'Oman had not the means of paying tribute. All this he said with a view to protect the people of 'Oman. Mahmud dissimulated his hostile feelings, and sought to gain his end by stratagem ; so he invited all the Bedouin chiefs of 'Oman and gave them presents, on which they promised him victory over the people of 'Oman and engaged to join him. He then proceeded by sea to Dhafar. 20 Arrived there, he slaughtered many of the inhabitants, plundered much pro perty, and returned towards 'Oman. He embarked his baggage in vessels, and performed the first part of the journey by sea. When subsequently they landed and proceeded by land route, their provisions failed, and they were beset by hunger. So great was the scarcity, that a maun of meat sold for a dinar. 21 They also suffered greatly from thirst, water beino- scarce on that route. It is said thait 5,000 of his men died, and some say more. This was in the year GGO A. H. [A. D. 1262]. I have also found another narrative of an expedition of the Owlad el-Reis 22 against 'Oman. They set out in the end of Showwal, A. H. 675 [A. D. 1276]. At that time the ruler 23 of 'Oman was the Seyyid 24 Kahlan-bin 'Omar-bin Nebhan, who advanced by the desert to oppose them, accompanied by all the people of el- 'Akr. The Owlad el-Reis surprised el-'Akr, entered it, and burned its market places. They plundered the place of all it contained, carried off the women, and burned the magazines and the principal mosque. The books were likewise burned. All this occurred in the space of half a day. Kah- lan thereupon returned with his force, and united with his detached parties. The Owlad el-Reis and their allies of the el-Haddan attacked Kahlan's army, and in the battle which ensued 300 men were slain. It is probable that during the interval between Mohammed-bin Khan- bash and Malik-bin el-Hawari, the government was in the hands of the el-Nebaheneh, but God knows! It seems probable, also, that they held power for more than 500 years, with this qualification that, after the term of yeais referred to. Imams were elected, the Nebahenoh being rulers in some districts, and the Imams being recognized in the rest. 25 God knows ! Iiie Imam Abll-Hasan-bin Kiiami's . Seven years after the decease of Malik-bin el-Hawan, Abul-Hasan-bin Khamis-bin 'Amir 26 was elected Imam, ihis was on Ihursday in the month of Ramadhan, in the year 839, A. H. [A. D. 1435]. He died on Saturday, the 21st of Thul-Ka'deh A. H. 846. [A. D. 1442.] The Ima'm 'Omae-bin Khattab . In the year 885 A. H. [A. D. 1481], they elected the Imam 'Omar-bin Khattab-bin Mohammed-bin Ahmed-bin Shidan-bin Salt. 27 He it was who seized the property of the Benu-Nebhan, and divided it amongst those about him of his own sect. 28 He took theHook Fourth. 33 administration of this property into liis own hands. This was by the unani mous wish of the Musalmans, who assembled and held inquiry regarding the bloodshed and the property unlawfully seized and appropriated by the Al- Nebhan. It was found that it was more than their possessions. 39 The Kadhi under the Imam 'Omar-bin Khattab was Abu-'Abdullah Mohammed-bin Suleiman-bin Ahmed-bin Mufarrij, and he appointed Mohammed-bin 'Omar- bin Mufarrij agent for those of the Musalmans of 'Oman who had suffered injustice at the hands of the A'l-Nebhan. Ahmed-bin 'Omar acted in like capa city for the Al-Nebhan Princes. Ahmed-bin Salih-bin Mohammed-bin 'Omar adjudged the whole of the property of the Al-Nebhan, their lands, plantations, tenements, arms, utensils, water-runs, dykes, in fact all they possessed of dwellings, wells, furniture, and goods, to those whom they had oppressed. Mohammed-bin 'Omar accepted this decree for those of the people of 'Oman who had suffered injury, whether living or dead, old or young, male or female. By this decisive decree the property in question could be claimed by those injured. Many, however, were unknown, and their claims forgotten, and it was impossible in such cases to distribute the shares. All such unclaimed shares of the property were ordered to be given to the poor, it also being decreed that, whilst there was a just Imam reigning, he was the most fitting person to receive such property awarded to the poor, and to expend it foi the glory and maintenance of the government of the Musalmans. All persons who established their claims, were to receive their shares of the property of the Benu-Nebhan. On the property being awarded, an estimate was to be made of what was due in arrears for the yearly produce of such property, if the claimant had the necessary information, but if he was unable to estimate this, that portion of the claim was to come under the head of unknown claims, and to be assigned to the poor, and taken charge of by the Imam as above. This decree was confirmed and ordered to be carried into execution. ' If any should alter it after hearing it, verily the guilt is on those who shall alter it, for Ood hears and knows. , This order was passed on Wednesday evening, seven days before the end of Jumadi el-Akhir, in the year 887 A. H. [A. D. 1482]. This occurred in the second reign of the Imam 'Omar. For one year after his first election Suleiman- bin Suleiman rose against him, and his army was defeated at Himat in Wadi Semail. Afterwards he was re-elected He was succeeded by The Ima'm Mohammed-bin Stileima'n bin Ahmed-bin Mufaeeij , the Kadhi, in the year of the Hijreh 894 [A. D. 1489.] He was deposed and The Ima'm 'Omae el-Sheei'e was elected in his place and reigned for one year, after which he retired to Bahla. The people of Nezwa then re-installed Mohammed-bin Suleiman. The Ima'm Ahmed-bin 'Omae . Next was Ahmed-bin 'Omar-bin Mohammed el-Zenji,34 Annals of 'Oman. The Ima'm Abul-Hasan-bin 'Abd-el-Sela'm . Tlien Abul Hasan: bin 'Abd-el-Selam reigned as Imam for less than a year, and was overthrown by Suleiman-bin-Suleiman, who made war against him. The Ima'm Moha'mmed-bin- Suleima'n was then set up once more, and remained in power for a few days. The Ima'm Mohammed-bin IsmaVl . The next Imam was Moham- med-bin Isma'il el-Isma'ili, who resided in the quarter of Wadi el-Gharbiyeh on the road which leads to the Mazar gate. 31 The cause of his being chosen was that Suleiman-bin Suleiman assaulted a woman, who was bathing at el-'Antak. The woman rushed out of the stream naked and fled from him. Suleiman chased her as far as the Wadi, when they were perceived by Mohammed-bin Isma'il, who seized Suleiman, threw him down, and held him there until the woman had escaped into el-'Akr, when he let him go his ways. The jNlusalmans were so pleased at this proof of his strength to do right and oppose wickedness, that they elected him Imam in the year 906 A, H. [A. D. 1500.] He died on Thursday, nine days before the end of Showwal, A. H. 942 32 [A. D. 1535.] His son The Ima'm Baeaka't-bin Mohammed-bin Ismail was installed on the same day on which his father died. On Saturday, ten days before the end of the month of Moharram, A. H. 905 [A. D. 1557], Barakat evacuated the fort of Bahla, which was forcibly seized by Mohammed-bin Jafir-bin 'All-bin Hilal. Previous to tliis, however, in the year OGi A. H. [A. D. 1556], the powerful Sul tan, Sultan-bin Mohsin-bin Suleiman-bin Nebhan had taken possession of Aczvwi. Mohammed-bin Jafir continued to hold possession of the Fortress of Bahla until the Al-'Omeyr bought it from him for three hundred laks. The Al- Omeyr entered the i ort of Bahla on Tuesday, nine days before the end of Jumadi el-A'khir, A. H. 967. [A. D. 1559.] It seems probable that 'Omar-bin Kasim el-Fadheyli was Imam in the tune of Barakat-bin Mohammed-bin Isma'il, but this is not certain. The Ima'm 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed . On Friday, fifteen days remaining of the month of Bejeb, A, H. 967 [A. D. 1559], the Imam 'Abdul- lab-bin Mohammed el-Karan was'invested at Manh, and on Monday, two days before the end of the same month, he entered the Fort of Bahla. On Wednesday, three days before the end of the month of Ramadhan, A. H. 969 [A. D. 1561], Barakat-bin Mohammed-bin Isma'il re-entered the Fort of Bahla, which was vacated by 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed el-Karan. The learned theologian Ahmed-bin Maddad denounced both Mohammed-bin Isma il and his son Barakat. He says in his work—' The religion which ^ we profess, and in which we worship God, enjoins renunciation of Moham- ' med-bin Isma'il on account of his having forcibly levied zekat 33 from hisBook Fifth. 35 « subjects, whilst neglecting to protect them and prevent oppression. For ' it has been rightly handed down as an article of the religion of the ' Musalmans that the « Jeziah' 34 or the ' Sadakat' cannot be lawfully ' levied except by rulers who prevent the unjust and oppressive levy of ' exactions. According to the religion of the Musulmans, their means of ' subsistence cannot be taxed in a land where they are not afforded ' protection and security.' 35 Likewise Mohammed-bin Mahbub said that our Imam cannot lawfully levy taxes, nor receive the free offerings from a people whom he fails to protect from oppression. If he does so, he acts unjustly towards them, and there is no difference between him and the oppressors who plunder the people. The Imam must not take aught from such people, and must refrain fiom appointing governors over them without protecting them. Ihe idigion of the Musalmans also forbids the levy of both hhciTaj and zehat fiom one and the same class of the subjects. Serving Almighty G-od, we repudiate Mohammed-bin Isma'il on account of his oppression of his subjects in forcing sales of the zekat due on the produce of the date plantations, in accordance with the arbitrary estimates of his agents, and in foicibly insisting on it being levied at that valuation to the injury of the people. Foi the forced purchase of the zekat on grain and dates, either in advance or after receipt, is not allowed by the religion of el-Islam. Such is prohibited by the book and the law and by accord of the peoples. Forced sales also aie forbidden except in cases of storing up against times of famine or refusal to satisfy just claims. There is no difference of opinion in this matter. So we renounce and hold ourselves free from the guilt of Mohammed-bin Isma il and his son Barakat. Book V. Account of the later Princes of the el-Nebaheneh, and others, up to the accession of the Imam Nasir-bin Murshid. A.D, 1560 to A.D. 1G2I. It is related that when Sultan-bin Mohsin died, (which event occurred on Monday, eleven days before the end of Eabi'ul-Akhir, A. H. 973, [A. D. 1565]) he left three sons, Tahyas-bin Sultan, Sultan-bin Sultan, and Modhaffar-bin Sultan. The last named was foremost of them in the Government until he died, on a Saturday in the month of el-Moharram, m the year 996 A. H. [A. D. 1588.]. He left a young son, named Suleiman, who, on account of his youth, was incapable of assuming the reins ^ of Government. His uncle Fellah-bin Mohsin, who was Malik of Makinat, 1 on hearing of the death of Modhaffar, came to Bahla, and assumed the Government in his brother's place. He continued to govern for seven years when he died. Suleiman-bin Modhaffar succeeded him when only twelve years of age, and ruled supreme in 4 Oman and all its districts, levying 1 ^ H^, e of ^ iJked sdu 'wtaiin, s proof of Us lauij ■UEMf &gt; ntdUi j of Jlokma, la, n Prras to powerful Sal- pOSHl of ie Fortes of dlik Tk retWof jnamin tk tain, fifteen (b lim 'AMi \ ondav, two ila. Bamaiiliaii, entered tie [aran. He ammed-biii rjon wiieli ( Hota- ' from lis '3G Annals of 'Oman. taxes from the people by fair or forcible means, from those at a distance, as well as those close by. The people of Nezwa collected to oppose him[ and amongst the rebellious was a Jabari, named Mohammed-bin Jafir, who had a large force under his command. Suleiman-bin Modhaffar and 'Arrar- bin Fellah accompanied by Nasir-bin Katan and his followers marched against the rebels: and in the battle which ensued, Mohammed-bin Jafir was killed and his army defeated. Nasir-bin Katan, who was watching the result, interfered to prevent further slaughter. Mohammed-bin Jafir left a young son, named Mohammed, whose mother was a daughter of £ Omeyr-bin 'A'mir. Suleiman-bin Modhaffar espoused this lady, when her husband was killed, and spent the cold weather with her in the plains of el-Shemal, leaving his cousin 'Arrar-bin Fellah to act for him at Bah la. Mohenna-bin Mohammed el-Hadeyfi was at that time Malik of Sohar. Having received intelligence that the Persians were preparing to attack him, he sent to ask Suleiman-bin Modhaffar to assist him against them. The latter consented and proceeded with his forces to Sohar, where the army was completely organized. The Persians arrived by sea, and a severe fio-ht occurred, which resulted in the defeat of the Persians and the slaughter of a great number of their army. After this, Suleiman returned'to his residence at Bahla. He had with him his cousins 'Arrar, Nebhan, and Makhzum, sons of Fellah-bin Mohsin, 2 of whom there were ten in all. 'Arrar was the first of them, and his brother Nebhan had no will but his El 'Arrar was Prince (Melik) of el-Dhahireh, and Suleiman bestowed on Makhzum the district of Yankal. Of the cousins of Suleiman there was also Himyer-bin Hafidh, who had four sons, Hafidh-bin Himyer, Sultan-bin Himyer, Kahlan-bin Himyer and Hud-bin Himyer. The first of these died a year after the return to' jBahla. There were in Suleiman's service also his relations Muhenna-bin- lohammed-bm Hafidh and 'AH-bin Thahal-bin Mobammed-hin Hafidh. Suleiman had TVazirs at el-Kareiyeh and amongst the el-Nizar of Azld and at Semed el-Shan. The latter place belonged to the el-Jahadhim tribe whom Suleiman treated with severity. They were forced to fiy from his' violence and power, and remained dispersed in the districts for the space oi thirty years, fearing to return to the town. The Benu-HinSh clan was held in the highest estimation hv Sulaiman-bin Modhaffar, and they were a most numerous, powerful and warhke tnbe The leaders of this tribe were Khalf-bin Abu-Sa'id, an Seif-bin Mohammad-bin Abu-Sa'id, men renowned amongst the peo- ple of their time. There were two tribes of the people of Seikam, the Bcnu-Maan and Benu-Neyyer, both cognate to, and allies of, the Benu- Hmah. A feud broke out between these two tribes, arising from a quarrelBoole Fifth. 37 between two women, and because of tbe mutilation of a camel, and they became divided ; the Benu Ma'an with the Benu-Shakeyl joining Suleiman- bin-Modhaffar, and the Benu-Nayyer joining the Benu-Hinah. On this, Khalf-bin Abu-Sa'id went to his house at Darseyt 3 with his cousins. Suleiman-bin ModhafFar was then in the desert, and when he heard what had occurred, he sent to his Wazir Mohammed-bin Ivhanjar, desiring him to tell Khalf to desist from interference with the tribe (Benu-Ma'an). The Wazir sent to Khalf accordingly, but finding he did not stop his proceedings, he reported to his master that Khalf would not attend to his orders. Suleiman then sent instructions to his Wazir to operate against the property of the Benu-Hinah at Kadam, and the Wazir ordered this to be destroyed. As this property belonged to the Sheykh Khalf, this occasioned a rupture between him and Suleiman, and in reprisal Sheykh Khalf ordered his cousins to make a raid on Bahla. This they did, and they killed many of the inhabitants of that place. The Wazir Mohammed-bin Khanjar then wrote to inform Suleiman of what had occurred at Bahla. On hearing this intelligence, Suleiman returned from el-Shemal to Bahla, and endeavoured to effect a reconciliation with the Benu-Hinah.' In this he was unsuccessful, and both sides prepared for a struggle; and the Sultan Suleiman collected all his available forces to attack the Benu-Hinah. As soon as the Sheykh Khalf heard of this, he sent to ask aid of the Amir 5 'Omeyr-bin Himyer, the Prince of Semail, against Suleiman-bin Modhaffar. &lt;Omeyr consented and came from Semail with his followers. Suleiman, being apprised of this movement, marched with his forces to Ghobrah, near Bahla, and there encountered 'Omeyr-bin Himyer. A battle was fought which lasted for an hour, and which resulted in Suleiman returning to Bahla, and the Amir 'Omeyr to Semail, the latter leaving some of his men in Darseyt. The Amir was a person of noble and prudent disposition. On his arrival at Semail, he sent to the Benu-Jahadhim who were dispersed in various villages. They came at his summons, and a friendly alliance was established. He next sent to the Sultan of el-Eostak, Malik-bin Abul-'Arab, to invite him to Semail, who accepted his invitation, and with him went also Abul- Hasan 'Ali-bin Katan. From Semail they proceeded with the Benu- Jahadhim to Semed el-Shan, where they entrenched themselves. ^ The Amu- left with them some of his own clansmen and whatever provisions, water, and munitions of war they required, and returned himself to Semail. As to Suleiman-bin Modhaffar and the Benu-Hinah, there was incessant warfare between them. w* * The Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer and the Sultan Malik-bin Abul- Arab betook themselves to Nezwa to watch the cause of events. Now Malik- bin Abul-'Arab had a Wazir in 'Eini of el-Rostak, and certain inmates o his house ejected the Wazir. Next, one of the inhabitants of 'Eini repaired38 Annals of 'Oman. to Suleinaan-bin Mudhaffar, and sought his aid against the hostile faction. Suleiman sent some of his men under 'Arrar-bin Fellah to their assistance! When the Sultan Malik-bin Abul-'Arab heard what had occurred in his home, he prepared to set out to return thither. The Amir, however, said to him: ' Stay with us and fear not, for this affair promises happy results.' He asked how that could be with the enemy in his house. The Amir replied, ' That is my affair: and, please God, I shall be victorious. God (whose name be exalted !) has said, £ Difficulty and ease go hand in hand.' ' The poet says— ' When events overwhelm, and the spirit is ready to sink beneath them ; when misfortunes descend and patience is failing,—still in the end comes relief.' The Benu-Hinah then invited the Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer to advance with his men, promising to give them admission to Bahla. He accordingly proceeded a part of the way with his forces, but, deeming them too weak in numbers, he returned to Nezwa. Meanwhile the Benu-Hinah were in expectation of his arrival on the night fixed for his entry. On his failing to join them, the Sheykh Seyf-bin Mohammed went from Darseyt to Nezwa to see him, and a stormy discussion ensued between them, the Sheykh censuring the conduct of the Amir. The latter ended by desiring the Sheykh to take as many of his men as he pleased. The Sheykh accordingly took a great number of men and proceeded to Darseyt, whilst the Amir awaited the result at Nezwa. Suleiman-bin Mudhaffar was informed that the enemy's force had marched from Nezwa to Darseyt, some saying their object was el-Kareyeh, others Seyfam, and others again Bahla. So Suleiman divided his army, placing a division at Kareyeh and another at Seyfam. He also built a fort to cover Felej el-Juzyein, fearing an attack in that quarter, and placed a detachment in it. Of the rest of his forces some were stationed at Bahl.i, and a detachment at el-Khadhra. He also posted men in the el-Ghaf quarter. Himyer-bin Hafidh with some of his retainers held the principal mosque of the town, the rest of his men being placed in el-'Akr. His cousin Arrar-bin Fellah with his followers was at 'Eini of el-Rostak. Seyf-bin Mohammed proceeded with his force from Darseyt with the intention of occupying Bahla. They first entered from the western side, scaling the outer wall. This design they carried out so skilfully, that their entry was not discovered by any one. Seyf then divided his force into three parties, one for the right, one for the left, and the third in the centre ; the latter being opposite the chief mosque of the town. In this manner he occupied positions well chosen for further opera tions. Subsequently, in the fighting which took place, many of Suleiman's chiefs and warriors were slain, and he retained only the Fort and el-Boole Fifth. 39 Khadhra. Seyf-bin Mohammed then proclaimed an amnesty, and was joined by many of the towns-people. When the news reached the Amir 'Omeyr at Nezwa that his men had entered Bahla, he set out accompanied by the Amir Sultan-bin Mohammed, and the Sultan Malik-bin Abul-'Arab, and el-Mansur 'Ali-bin Katan and the people of Nezwa. Khalf-bin Abu-Sa'id el-Hinai also moved with his followers from Darseyt to assist their comrades. They entered Bahla by night, and the Amir 'Omeyr alighted in the el-Ghaf quarter, El-Khadhra was held for the Sultan Suleiman by 'Ali-bin Thahal with a large force; and the Amir sent word to them inviting them to evacuate the place with their flags. 6 'Ali-bin Thahal went amongst his men exhorting them to hold out, but they refused to obey him, and prepared to leave the place. Meanwhile 'Arrar-bin Fellah, who was at 'Eini of el-Kostak, hearing of the enemy's entry of Bahla, immediately marched with his followers to el-Kareyeh. The siege of the Fort of Bahla continued, and it was surrounded by the enemy. The besiegers constructed a wooden tower on a tamarind tree in the market-place during the night. In this one of the el-Jahadhim, named Jum'ah-bin Mohammed, esconced himself and shot one of the garrison. Another such tower was built by the Amir on the mosque, and its occupant also shot one of Suleiman's soldiers in the upper part of the Fort. The besiegers at length demolished the wall of the i ort during the night. Suleiman's men, however, opposed them and prevented their entry. Then the garrison, fearing to be slain, asked permission of Suleiman to evacuate the place. Still they held out for thirteen days more, when, Suleiman, having given permission, they asked the Amir Omeyr to allow them to maich out. He allowed them to pass out with their personal effects, and sent his Wazir to see them safe. Suleiman-bin Mudhaffar with his cousins and followers went forth from Bahla, and proceeded to el-Kareyeh, whence he and 'Arrar went to el-Dhahireh. The Amir 'Omeyr then ordered the Fort of Bahla to be razed to the ground, which was done, and not a wall nor a building was left standing. Thus is manifested the power of God, who bestows kingdoms on whomsoever He willeth. 'Omeyr then left Khalf-bin Abu-Sa'id in charge of Bahla and returned to Semail. Khalf had been only four months in Bahla, when he was attacked by Suleiman-bin Mudhaffar and his cousin 'Arrar-bin Fellah, who entered el-Khadhra whilst he was in el-'Akr. This occurred on the 4.th of Eabi 'ul-Awwal, A. H. 1019 [A. D. 1610] ; and at that time Seyf-bin Mohammed with some of his followers was in el-Sirr. Suleiman-bin Mudhaffar sent to Khalf-bin Abu-Sa'id, and offered him the option of40 Annals of '■Oman. marching out with his personal effects, and Khalf accepted this offer after obtaining an amnesty for the people of the district. Some of the latter remained in their abodes, others went forth from fear of the Sultan. When Seyf-bin Mohammed heard of these occurrences, he returned from el-Sirr, and the Amir 'Omeyr also, aware of his movements, marched from Semail to ISTezwa and thence on to el-Kareyeh, which he took and made over to Seyf-bin Mohammed to hold for him. The Amir then returned to Nezwa, where he remained some days watching events. Soon after, Suleiman-bin Mudhaffar died, leaving a son of tender years, and £ Arrar-bin Fellah assumed the Government of Bahla. Seyf-bin Moham med then proceeded to Nezwa, and, taking a large force from the Amir 'Omeyr, went to el-Kareyeh, where they halted for seven days. Thence they marched on Bahla, and entered the quarter called Abu-Man, and besieged 'Arrar-bin Fellah for some days. Then he sent them on their ways with their arms, &amp;c., and the Fort of el-Kareyeh remained in his hands, and he spent some years in repairing it. This entry (?) took place on 6th of Safar, A. H. 1024. 7 [A. D. 1G15.] After him Mudhaffar-bin Suleiman held power, but he died after two months. Makhzum-bin Fellah then governed for two months, after which Nebhan and Seyf-bin Mohammed rose against him to eject him from the Fort. They allowed him at his request to march out without arms or effects. He proceeded to Yankal in el-Dhahireh. Nebhan-bin Fellah was the next to rule. He placed his cousin 'Ali- bin Thahal as his representative in Bahla and after him Seyf-bin Mohammed. Nebhan-bin Fellah then went to his home at Makaniyat after removing his cousin Sultan-bin Himyer from Bahla, fearing lest he should usurp the government. The latter went to Sohar, and Seyf-bin Mohammed held his place for a year. God knows ! After that the Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer went up with his followers to Bahla, but, being opposed by Seyf-bin Mohammed, he returned with his tioops to Nezwa to watch events. After a while, 'Omeyr again marched to Bahla and entered el-'Akr. Seyf-bin Mohammed, who happened to be at Darseyt at the time, on hearing of 'Omeyr's movement, marched with his followers and entered the Fort unopposed. Thence he wrote to Nebhan- bin i ellah, informing him that the enemy had entered the town, and request ing him to come with the men he had with him. He was some days collecting his force, and meanwhile the Amir 'Omeyr had occupied all the strong positions m the district. Se^f-bin Mohammed continued to hold the Fort with his men, expecting Nebhan to succour him, but the latter did not appear. 'Omeyr-bin Himyer sent to offer him safe -conduct out, but Seyf declined, hoping for the arrival of Nebhan. When, however, he despaired of'Boole Fifth. 41 this, he accepted the terms, and was allowed to march out with his men with all their effects. Seyf then went to el-Kareyeh, and 'Omeyr remained for some time at Bahla, after which he sent to Seyf-bin Mohammed, and a reconciliation took place between them. Seyf thereafter continued ^ to administer the Government, and ruled the people justly. He exercised authority over his cousins, who remained faithful to him. After the affaii of Seyf-bin Mohammed had been settled in this manner, the following events occurred. Sultan-bin Himyer, Mohenna-bin Mohammed-bin Hafidh, and 'All bin Thahal were then residing at Sohar with Mohammed-bin Mohenna el- Hadeyfi, who wished to take them to their cousin Nebhan-bin Fellah at Makaniyat, in order to mediate a reconciliation between them. Makhzum was then in the Fort of Yankal. They were unable to come to terms. Afterwards Sultan-bin Himyer the Nebhani and 'Ali-bin Thahal moved -with their combined forces from el-Dhahireh against Bahla, and entered the quarter of the Benu-Salt of Bahla, on the 9th of Safar, 1024 A. H. [A D. 1615]. The Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer, who was at bemail, hearing of their movement, marched at once to Bahla with a force, and after him, came up Seyf-bin Mohammed, and an engagement was fought. The Nebhani army built a wall of defence all round the quarter they occupied. 'Omeyr sent to his adherents in all the villages. He was joined by the Sheykh Majid-bin Eabi'ah-bin Ahmed-bin Suleiman el-Kundi and 'Omar- bin Suleiman el-'AM and the Sheykh Sa'id-bin Hamd-bin Abu-Sa'id el- Na'abi, with the principal inhabitants of Nezwa and Manh. Sultan-bm Himyer and his force remained for a long time so closely besieged, that not a man could come out, nor could any one enter to them. At length. Sultan offered to evacuate the place, if suffered to pass m safety^ and the Amu- consenting, they were allowed to march off to el-Dhahireh with their arms and effects. . Sultan-bin Himyer, Kahlan-bin Himyer, 'Ali-bin Thahal, and Muhenna -bin Mohammed-bin Hafidh continued to reside at Makaniyat until Nebhan dismissed them from dread of their ejecting him from the place. They then proceeded to Sohar, and dwelt there for a year with the Hadeyfi Mohammed-bin Muhenna. But Ood knows ! . ^ . Sultan -bin Himyer next suggested to Mohammed-bm Muhenna that they should make an attack on the district of 'Omeyr-bin Himyer about el-Sib of the Batineh. 'Omeyr was away, and there were present in his dis tricts Sinan -bin Sultan, the Amir 'Ali-bin Himyer and Sa 'id -bm Himyer. Mohammed-bin Muhenna and Sultan-bin Himyer mounted with their fol lowers and set out from Sohar, and the news of this was carried to Sinan and 'All and Sa'id. In as short a time as would serve a man to put oft his shoes, or wash his feet, the hostile forces met and swords were bared on land and sea, on plain and hill, and a terrible battle was fought, m which42 Annals of 'Oman, 'Ali-bin Himyer was slain. The contest then terminated, and Mohammed- bin Muhenna returned to Sohar. When the Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer, who was at Bahla, heard what had befallen his brothers and his cousin, he solemnly vowed not to turn back from Sohar until he had reaped the enemies with the sword, burnt them with fire, and scattered them in all directions. He commenced col- lecting forces by land and by sea, and there assembled round him a force of whom God alone could tell the number. He then proceeded to Maskat, to obtain re-inforcements by sea. He sent also to the Malik of Hormuz for assistance, and he sent him a number of ships laden with stores and men and munitions of war. A ship also had arrived on the coast from India, carrying a large number of troops and some munitions of war 8 and had been driven back by the wind to Maskat. The Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer took it, and proceeded with the Christians and others who had join ed him from Maskat, and halted for seven nights at Batineh el-Sib. Mo hammed-bin Jafir, hearing of this, marched with his 'tribe to the aid of Mohammed-bm Muhenna, and entered Sohar, to the joy of the latter, who gave him admission to the Fort and encouraged his men. A collision' took place between Mohammed-bin Jafir's men and a party in one of the bas tions of the Fort, and they fought for an hour. Mohammed-bin Jafir and Ins people then quitted Sohar. Wlion the Amir 'Omeyr heard of this oeeurrenee, he moved his forces on Sohar by land and sea, and entered that town on the 19th of Kahi' ul- Aklnr, A. H. 1025, [A. D. 1016.] A battle which ensned between the rival forces, lasted from morninj; to night, but without decisive result. A day or two later, the Christians dis embarked Irom the ships with their implements of war. In advancing they pushed before them gabions of cotton, to shelter them from the musketry hre. 1 hey also employed cannon, which moved by land on wooden carriages, and were fitted with wooden screens. On one side of the Fort, Mohammed- bin Muhenna had a tower m which were a large number of soldiers The besiegers dragged their cotton screens to a position opposite this tower, and battered it with eannon until a breach was effected, when the garrison evacuated it and the Christians entered. When Mohammed-bin Muhenna heard of this he urged on his men, and a fight took place by night at the neTh- m MV Ch .'?; bl ° Thahal ' bin Mohammed-bin Hafidh and Mobam- I H WM [A n D leieT' Were kille&lt;1 ' 0n the 21st of fiaM ' ul ' A lihir ' After this event, Snlffa-bin Himyer-bin Mohammed-bin Hafidh el- Nehham with Ins brother Kahlan-bin Himyer and his cousin Muhenna- Mohammed-bin Hafidh and their forces occupied the fort. As soon as the Amir 'Omeyr became aware of the death of the chief ofISooTc 'Fifth. 43 war* fT-Dlil iki'nl- the enemy's army, he led his men to battle. The encounter took place in the quarter of el-Nakhl, 'Omeyr and his followers issuing without opposition from the vicinity of the chief mosque. In the contest Sultan-bin Himyer was killed, and the enemy's forces were routed and dispersed ; some were slain, some burnt, some captured, some wounded, and the rest fled they knew not whither. In this manner the whole population of the place was disposed of, and the town itself was completely burnt. The Christians remained in occupation of the Fort of Sohar, and the Amir 'Omeyr returned to Semail intoxicated with joy. At this period, Makhzum-bin Fellah was in possession of the fort of Yankal. He seized two of them (?), and ordered one of his slaves to execute one of these two. The slave bared his sword to strike, on which the prisoner prayed him to protect him. He did not heed him and struck one blow. A second time he cried in vain for mei-cy, and when he was about to strike a third blow, the man appealed for protection to God. Makhzum, on this, rushed on him to gag his mouth, at the same instant the slave's sword descending struck the hand of Makhzum, who died from the effects of the wound in seven days. As for the prisoner, the slave dragged him away thinking him dead, but he was found by one of the towns-people who succoured him, and he recovered of his wounds and lived for some time after that. This happened three months after the capture of Sohar. When Nebhan heard of his brother's death, he rode from Makaniyat to Yankal, and placing there a Wazir returned to the former place. Since he had left Bahla for el-Dhahireh, a period of thirty months had elapsed. After that Nebhan-bin Fellah went a second time to Yankal, leaving some of his men in the fort of Makaniyat. But the people of the latter place were weary of his tyranny and oppression, and planned to expel him from the place. So they sent an emissary to the Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer and to Seyf-bin Mohammed, asking their aid. Both of them marched with their followers to Makaniyat, and entered the fort without opposition or bloodshed. After remaining there some days, they rode with a portion of their forces to Yankal. When Nebhin-bin Fellah became aware of this, he feared for his safety, and mounting on horseback fled with only four attendants and without baggage to the town of his maternal uncles of the el-Rivaveseh. This was twelve days before the end of Safar, 1026 A. H. [A. D. 1617.] The Amir 'Omeyr and Seyf-bin Mohammed remained for some time at Yankal. The Amir then made over the lands to the rightful possessors to freely enjoy the produce thereof, and returned to Makaniyat. He enquired of the inhabitants what Nebhan was in the habit of taking from them. They told him that he took one half the produce of the date trees and one quarter of the yield of the sown ground. The Amir 'Omeyr reduced44 Annals of 'Oman. the impost to one-tenth of the yield of the crops. The property of the Sultan was assigned to whomsoever should be in charge of the fort. After placing 'Omar-bin Mohammed-bin Abu-Sa'id in command of the fort, the Amir and Seyf-bin Mohammed returned to Bahla. Meanwhile Nebhan-bin Fellah, having procured a force from his uncles of the Al-Eeis, returned to el-Dhahireh and entered Fida. There he re mained for some days, when an inhabitant of Yankal, who was one of his well-wishers, came to him and offered to procure him admission to the town and support against the garrison, and to open the fort to him. So he went and re-entered Yankal with his followers in the middle of Eabi' ul- Akhir, A. H. 1026 [A. D. 1617.] He occupied all the commanding posi tions of the place except the fort itself, which was held by some of the Benu-'Ali tribe. Nebhdn proceeded to besiege these, and some fighting took place. One of the besieged went forth from the Fort, and proceeded to ask assistance of the Amirs who dwelt in el-Shemal, Katan-bin Katan and Nasir-bin Nasir. They with their followers proceeded to Yankal, and attacked and dispersed the forces of Nebhan-bin Fellah. On hearing of the entry of Yankal by Nebhan-bin Fellah, the Sheykh Seyf-bin Mohammed el-Hinai had marched with his troops to oppose him. When he had traversed a portion of the way, he heard what had happened to Nebhan at the hands of the Amirs, and thereupon returned to Bahla with his army. The Amir 'Omeyr-bin Himyer at that time collected men to aid the Sultan Malik-bin Abul-'Arab el-Ya'rabi against the Benu-Lamak, and having lent the aid of all his forces, the result was disastrous to the Benu- Lamak. Seyf-bin Mohammed el-Hinai remained in Bahla, and the Al-'Omeyr in Semall, and Malik-bin Abul-'Arab in Rostak and the el-Jibur in el-Dha- hireh until the appearance of the wise Imam of the Musalmans, Nasir-bin Murshid, who subdued all 'Oman and reduced to obedience all its districts, purging the land of tyranny and oppression, of infidelity and rebellion, and restoring to it justice and security, and governing the people with equity and kindness until God took him to Paradise. I shall, please God, relate his advent in the following book. Book VI. Appearance of the Imam Nasir-bin Murshid and an Account of the Imams who succeeded him up to the occurrence of dissensions amongst the el- Ya'araheh. A. D. 1624 to 1718. When it was the will of God to be gracious to the people of 'Oman, and to save them from further violence and oppression, after the sufferingsBooh Sixth. 45 Sole they had experienced from civil wars, it came to pass that an nneventful period ensued in their annals, during which the fierce passions and animosi ties which had animated them were obliterated from their minds. Genera tion succeeded generation, but the country long continued impoverished after those truculent chiefs and contending factions had disappeared from the scene. There remained only the record of the virtuous amongst them and what they commemorated in their books and traditions. Learning declined and the learned were few. Friendly intercourse was resumed and the fire of hatred died out of their hearts ; the flames of war were extin guished, and party differences were reconciled. A time came when learning had so declined and its possessors were so scarce, that it was said that one of the Princes of the Ya'arabeh of Wabl of el-Eostak wanted a Kadhi and was unable to find one amongst the followers of the true sect, 1 and therefore selected a Kadhi from the heretics ; of what sect I know not. This person endeavoured to overturn our sect and establish his own instead. The peo ple of 'Oman, on hearing of this, sent to that Prince, who thereupon dis missed the Kadhi and appointed for them one of their own persuasion. From him the people of el-Rostak received instruction and became steadlast in the faith. The majority of the Meliks of 'Oman were wicked and turbulent op pressors, and they were abetted in their tyranny by the chiefs of the tribes. Throughout the land, whether in desert or valley, everywhere oppression was rampant. The people of 'Oman suffered from those evil doers the severest misery, from which neither the young nor the aged escaped. All alike were subject to be plundered, or seized and imprisoned, to be scourged or even slaughtered. And God caused animosity and hatred to grow in their hearts. Now the people of 'Oman are endowed with certain qualities, which it is my hope they may never lose. They are a people of soaring ambition, and oi haughty spirit ; they brook not the control of any Sultan, and are quick to resent affront; thev yield only to irresistible force, and without evci aban doning their purpose. A man of comparatively poor spirit, judged by their standard, is on a par as regards magnanimity with, an Amir of any other people. Each individual aims at having the power in his own hands or in the hands of those he loves. He desires every one to be submissive to him, and his neighbour has the same ambition. 2 Unfortunately none are worthy of such things, but those whom God elects, pious, chaste, and blessed persons, who are not swayed by their desires, nor prone to be led away by blind passions. So it came to pass that fierce animosities broke out amongst them, and they fought amongst themselves, plundering, and carrying off captives. In short, each party neglected no means of injuring their opponents. There were none to be found, whether dwellers in houses or dwellers in tents, whether40 Annals of l Omdn. ' 13edu' or 'Hadhr' 3 , whether on the mountain heights or in the sandy levels, but had quaffed the draught of terror, and suffered from the general destruction which encompassed religion, property, and life, except those for whom God tempered their troubles and whom He saved from the strife by His bounteous protection. In this manner, they ceased not to struggle in the abysses of desolation, walking in evil ways, until God vouchsafed unto them the appearance of his wise servant, the Imam of the Musalmans, Nasir- bin Murshid-bin Malik 4 , which occurred as follows. It happened that when Malik-bin Abul-'Arab, who has been mention ed in the previous book, was their Sultan, dissensions occurred amongst the people of el-Rostak. Those of the Musalmans who were steadfast in the faith, consulted with the learned regarding the election of an Imam, to govern them in accordance with right and justice, and they deliberated as to who was worthy of their choice. At that period, the most respected per son amongst them was Khamis-bin Sa'id el-Shakasi. Their unanimous decision was to elect the illustrious Seyyid [NasirJ. So they went to him and asked this of him, exhorting him to rule uprightly. The Imam Na'sie-bin Muesuid . He consented, and was elected Imam in the year 1034 A. H. [A. D. 1625], and fixed his residence at Kasra, in the district of el-Eostak, and acted justly, and exerted himself to uproot ignorance. The tribe el-Yahmad actively supported him, and agreed to seize by night the fort in which his cousins had resided since the death of his grandfather Malik. After gaining possession of the fort, the Imam proceeded to the town of el-Nakhl, in which his uncle Sultan-bin Abul- Ai ab was residing, and took that place after a siege of some days. A por tion of the inhabitants, however, refused to acknowledge the Imam and besieged him in the fort, until he was relieved by a body of the el-Yahmad, and his enemies were dispersed, after which he returned to el-Eostak. There he received visits from Ahmed-bin Suleiman el-Iiueyhi with a party of the el-Euaheh and envoys from Mani'-bin Sinan el-'Omeyri, who abode some time with him and invited him to Semail and Wadi Beni-Euaheh. To this he assented, and marched accompanied by some of the ebYahmed until he reached Semail, where he left some of his men with Mani'-bin Sinan and proceeded on to the Wadi Beni-Euaheh. As agreed upon with Mani', he went on thence to Nezwa, attended by the Kadhi Khamis-bin Sal'd. On reaching Izki, many of the inhabitants gave him personal and pecuniary assistance, and he took possession of the place, and proceeded towards Nezvva, u iere he was welcomed by the people and entered the town in safety. He took up his residence in el-'Akr, and continued to administer justly for some months. The Benu bu-Sa'id, 5 the chief family of el-'Akr, then formed a conspiracy m view of ejecting the Imam from the place. The execution of us plot was fixed for a Friday, when the Imam went forth to prayers, butBooh Sixth. 47 aij, ■i he received timely warning from a person, to whom he had shown kindness, of what they meditated, and when he had ascertained the truth ot the intelligence, he ordered the family to he banished from the district, but for bade any one to slay or attack them. So they were forced to go forth, and dispersed throughout the districts. A party of them resorted to Mani'-bin Sinan, who had made a compact with the Imam and taken an oath to follow the truth. By receiving these persons he broke his word. Another body of them took refuge with the el-Hinai at Bahla, and assisted that tribe in their war against the Imam, which then broke out. The Imam ordered a new Fort to be constructed in 'Akr of Nezwa in lieu of the old one, which had been built by el-Sult-bin Malik, and the work was completed. The people of Manh also invited him to extend his just rule to them, and he proceeded to that town, which was opened to him, and administered the affairs with the active and substantial support of the inhabitants. So also the people of Semed el-Shan came to him. The governor [Malik] of Semed at that time was 'All-bin ftatan el-Hilali. The Imam despatched an army under the command of the learned Sheykh Mes'ud-bin liamadhan, who took possession of the town. At the invitation ot the people of Ibra, the Malik of which was Mohammed-bin Jafir, the Imam sent a force there also, which took the place. In this way the whole of el-Sharkiyeh submitted to the Imam, except Sur and Keriyat, which were held by the Christians. The Imam next assembled an army and marched against the el-Hinai of Bahla. When he had proceeded as far as the plain of el-Markh, he dis covered treason amongst certain persons of his army, and deemed it most prudent to return to Nezwa, where he commenced raising a fresh force. A large number of men being assembled, he marched with them towards el-Dhahireh, and succeeded in gaining possession of Wadi Fadda, where he ordered a Fort to be built. The inhabitants of the uplands of Dhank, whose leader was the learned Sheykh Khamis-bin Rueyshid, joined the Imam, and also the men of el-GMalin, and his authority was established in spite of his enemies. After this the Imam made a tour of the districts he had conqueied, un til he reached Semed el-Shan, whence he returned to el-Rostak with the Benu lily am. 6 There he remained until the army of Mohammed-bin Jafir advanced to the town of Nakhl, which they entered and took possession of, all but the Fort. The Imam marched against them at the head ot a numerous army, and was aided by the el-Ma'awal clan. The enemy had only occupied the town two or three nights, when they were forced to fly, and the Imam returned to el-Rostak. Soon after, the Sheykh Khamifc-bin Rueyshid came to the Imam seek-48 Annals of 'Oman. ing his assistance against el-Dhahireh. The Imam thereupon prepared an army with which he marched to the assistance of the Sheykh, and halted at el-Sakhbari. The people of el-Sirr and el-Dhahireh assisted the Imam with contributions of men and money. Thence he proceeded to the Fort of el-Grhabbi, in which was posted the main body of the A'1-Hilal with 'Bedu 7 ' and ' Hadhr.' Here there was a severe engagement, in the course of which the Imam's brother Je'ad-bin Murshid was killed. The Imam then marched to 'Ibri 8 , which he took, and remaining there two nights, he returned to el-Sakhbari, after which he besieged the Fort of el- Ghabbi until God gave him victory over it, when he placed in it as Wall Khamis-bin Rueyshid. In the town of Bat he placed as Wall a person belonging to el-Uostak, associating with him Muhammed-bin Seyf el-How- kani. These two the Imam ordered to reduce the remaining towns of el-Dhahireh, and himself returned to Nezwa. The A l-Hilal, who occupied a position by the water courses near Dhank made war on the Walls. The latter encountered them at el-Deir, routed them, and captured the camels of Katan-bin Katan, to make use of them in overcoming the others. They also laid siege to Katan-bin Katan's Fort. Katan-bin Katan then went to the Imam, and offered to surrender his Fort, if his camels were restored to him. These terms were accepted, and the Imam ordered the camels to be given back to Katan, who surrendered his Fort and was confirmed as Wall of it by the Imam. The two Walis then proceeded to Makaniyat, which was held by a Wazir of the el-Jibur. The latter tribe raised the whole of the Benu-Hilal, ' Bedu'' ^ and ' Hadhr,' and the Owlad el-Reis, and marched towards Makanryat; but, considering themselves unequal to the relief of that place, they advanced on Bat. The Walls feared for the safety of that town on account of the scanty supply of water on which the Governor relied, so the Musalmans marched from before Makaniyat, and surprised the el-Jibur at Bat. After an encounter, the el-Jibur retreated towards Makaniyat; but the Musalmans overtook them, and a battle was fought which lasted from morning prayer till noon. The Musalmans had to exert themselves to the utmost, and the slaughter of the rebels was so great, that it is said they were unable to bury the slain separately, and were obliged to put seven and eight corpses in one pit. So God upheld the Musalmans. When intelligence of this affair reached the Imam, he assembled an army and marched with it against the el-Hinal of Bahla, at which place he anived # on the night ol the festival of the Hijj. He besieged the place for two months, all but three days, when the el-Jibur came to the relief of the el-Hinal. They were encountered by the Imam's troops, and a severe en gagement took place, in which Kasim-bin Mathkur el-Dahmashl and a great number of the army of the el-Jibur were slain. The latter thenBooh Sixth. 49 retreated, leaving the Hinai chief and his followers besieged in the Fort. He was at length forced to surrender, and evacuated the place with all his men, arms, and property, leaving the Fort empty. The Imam after placing a Wall there returned to Nezwa. The Imam next marched to Semail against Mani'-bin Sinan el-'Omeyri. The latter, as soon as he heard of the Imam's approach, made his submission, and advised the Imam to suffer him to remain in the Fort, promising to be faithful for the future. This the Imam consented to, and, after completing his design of rebuilding the old Fort of Semail, returned to Nezwa. After that, the Imam proceeded with a force to Makamyat, where he attacked and defeated the enemy. The garrison, however, held out for nearly three months in the Fort, after which time the Imam captured it, and placed Mohammed-bin 'All there as Wall. Sa'id el-Khiyali and his clan ceased not to persevere in their enmity towards the Imam, and to correspond with the el-Jibur, until the latter admitted them to the town of el-Sakhban, where they slew a man of the el-Dhahahakeh and many of the Imam's soldiers and others, the number of whom God alone knows. The Imam's army was completely shut up, and several engagements were fought; one a very severe one at el-'Ajeyfiyeh, another at el-Ghabeh, another at el-Mathareh, another at el-Ziyadeh, and many more hard fights, so that the pillars of el-Islam were well nigh crumbled to ruins. The Wall was deserted by many of the people, and left with only a small number, beset by the enemy banded to oppose him, so that his resolution was almost overcome by his terror. He remained be- sieo-ed in the fort of el-Ghabbi, the governor of which was Mohammed-bm Seyf. When Mohammed-bin 'All, Wall of Makaniyat, became aware of the state of affairs, he assembled a force to relieve Mohammed-bm Seyf at el-Ghabbi, and, coming on the enemy unawares, he entered the place, and defeated and scattered them in all directions. Some gained el-Sakhbaii, some fled to the desert, and the rest set out for Yankal, which place was held by Nasir-bin Katan. So God gave the victory to the Musalmans. After these occurrences, Mani'-bin Sinan secretly entered into corre spondence with Seyf-bin Mohammed el-Hinai, and played the traitor by violatino- the compact he had entered into with the Imam. Having col lected a'force, the two entered Nezwa, the inhabitants of which place were not guiltless of treachery and disaffection, as this was effected with their secret connivance, and with the aid of some of the tribes. On entering Nezwa, they possessed themselves of el-'Akr. n , • , The Imam retained only the fort, which they rigorously beset, but just as they were on the point of breaching the wall, succours arrived from Izki and Bahla, including the Benu-Elyam. These having entered the place to the relief of the Imam, who was overjoyed at their arrival, the enemy s orcesdispersed and many of them were slain. This circumstance served to forti fy the Imam's resolution and strengthen his power. He was then advised to destroy the fort of Mani'-bin Sinan, who hearing of the preparation of an army for service against him fled to Fanja. The Imam's troops pro ceeded to raze the fort, on which Mani'-hin Sinan proceeded to Maskat, and thence to Lawa, where he joined Mohammed-bin Jafir. The Imam then ordered his army to Bilid-Seyt, at which place Seyf the Hinai had built a fort, after he went forth from Bahla. The leader of this army was the Sheykh 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed-bin Ghassan, the author of the work entitled the ' Khazanat ul-Akhyar fi bei' il-Kheiyar.' When the army arrived at Bilad-Seyt, the Hinai fled from the place, and, by order of the commander, the fort was razed to the ground. The Hinai then repaired to the Imam and sought his forgiveness, and all the tribes of 'Oman made their submission. I lie Imam soon aftei assembled a large force with which he proceeded in person, accompanied by the Sheykh Khamis-bin Sa'id of el-Eostak, against ^sash -hip Katan of \ ankal. After a siege of some days, the place surrender ed, and the Imam after placing a Wall there returned to el-Rostak. The Imam raised another strong force, in command of which he placed the Sheykh 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed-bin Ghassan of Nezwa, whom he in structed to march to el-Jow. With him he sent also the Sheykh Khamis- bin Rueyshid of Dhank and Hafidh-bin Jum'ah el-Hinai with Moham med-bin 'All of el-Rostak and Mohammed-bin Seyf el-Howkani. On arrival, they gained possession of the place, and leaving Mohammed-bin Seyf as Wall, the commander proceeded with his forces in the direction of the town of Lawa. For dissensions had broken out amongst the el-Jibur and, in the strife, Mohammed-bin Jafir had been killed. 'Abdullah took up his quarters at the principal mosque, and his army surrounded the fort, which was held by Seyf, the son of the deceased Mohammed-bin Jafir el- Hilali. Self's brothers and Wazirs, however, had recourse to the Christians® at Sohar, where Mani'-bin Sinan el-'Omeyri, also, was then residing. Thence they harassed the Imam's army before Lawa by making night attacks, and they also aided the garrison with provisions and munitions of war. The sons of Mohammed-bin Jafir next wrote to the Wall proposing terms of peace, but he, aware this was merely a ruse, sent a detachment against them under Mohammed-bin 'All, who fell on the enemy before day break at a place called Mankal, where the southern part of the Fort abuts on the seashore. The millstones of war revolved amongst them, and after a severe engagement Mohammed retired with his forces to the fort of Lawa They continued to besiege the Fort until Seyf-bin Mohammed sent to them, begging to be allowed safe egress from the place. The Wall gave him the required guarantee, and he evacuated the fort with his followers, on whichJBoolc Sixth. 51 the Wall entered it. During the siege, the Wall had received assistance from Nasir-bin Katan and the men of the el-'Umur. 'Abdullah having placed a governor there returned himself to the Imam. The Imam afterwards raised another army, in command of which he placed Mes'ud-bin Hamadhan and ordered him to lead them to Maskat. He marched until he arrived at the well called el-Ruleh 10 at el-Matreh. There the millstones of death revolved between the Musalmans and the unbelievers, and God granted victory to the former, who demolished the high towers of Maskat. Many of the unbelievers were slain, after which they sued for peace, which was granted to them by the Wall, on condition of their restoring all the property of the el-'Umur, which was in their pos session, and also that of the Shi'ahs 11 of Sohar. On their submitting to these terms, the Wall assured them of safety, and after obtaining from them pledges of good faith, returned to the Imam. Mani'-bin Sinan meanwhile ceased not to cherish secret enmity against the Imam and. to preach rebellion against his Government. So Maddad- bin Holwan asked permission of the Imam to compass Mani s death by stratagem. The Imam having consented, Maddad wrote to Mani, inviting him to come to the fort of Lawa and expressing himself in such kind lan guage that it disposed the other to accede. Now the Wall of Lawa at that time was Hafidh-bin Seyf. El-Maddad ceased not to ply the 'Omeyri with letters couched in terms of friendly advice, and to adjure him on the true faith not to allow suspicions of evil to enter his heart. Mani' rejoiced at this and placed confidence in Maddad's counsels. He was then residing at the town of Dibba, from which place he rode into Sohar, where he halted some days awaiting further advices from Maddad. The latter renewed the promises he had made, and fixed a certain night on which he engaged he should have admission to the Fort, on which Mani' rode to Lawa and alight ed in the town. On the appointed night, the Wall dispersed his forces and caused them to wander about the streets, as if about to depart; it being however, ^ ar ranged amongst them that they should concentrate on Mam' from the rig it and &amp; left. Before Mani' was aware of their intentions, the troops had sur rounded him from both sides, and he was seized and slam on the spot, and his followers dispersed, those who remained by him being slam. The Imam next prepared a force, the command of which he gave o 'All-bin Ahmed, assisted by his cousins of the Al-Ya'rub, and ordered um to proceed to the town of Julfar, which is el-Sir. 13 In those days, that place was held by the Persian Nasiruddin with a force of Persians. Ahmed-bin 'All proceeded to besiege them in the fort of el-Sir, the Persians actively defending themselves, and some hard fighting occurred. Some of the peo ple of el-Sir sided with the Persians against the Imam's forces. There was52 Annals of '■Oman. a flanking tower connected by a wall with the fort, and in this tower were stationed a body of the garrison who kept up a fire by night and day. On the sea side there were also two ships of the Christians, which by the fire of their guns protected the fort from assault by the Musalmans. The latter determined to attack the tower, which they seized by a night assault, and from thence they gained possession of the fort, one of the leaders of the army was placed there as Wall. More troops came up afterwards, amongst them a body of the el-Dahamish and Khamis-bin Mahzam, There was also another Fort situated on the seashore held by the el-Efrenj. 13 The Imam's army entered this place by day and took possession of it, and besieged those who were in the fort, which they occupied themselves. The power of the unbelievers was humbled, and they sued for peace, which was granted them, and they evacuated the fort, in which the Wall placed a garrison. Leaving with the latter a portion of his army 'All-bin Ahmed, they returned with the remainder to Nezwa. The Imam was rejoiced at his arrival and at the news of the capture of el-Sir. The Imam next ordered Kafidh-bin Seyf, the Wall of Lawa, who had a body of el-'Amur with him, to proceed and build a fort against Sohar, some of the inhabitants of which town had been inviting him to take the place. The Wall accordingly summoned all in the neighbourhood from the towns of the Benu-Khalid, Benu-Lam, and the el-'Amur, and a numer ous force assembled. The Wall then marched on Sohar and passed the night in the village of 'Amak. Next day, in the forenoon, he reached Sohar district without being discovered by any of his enemies. This was on the last day of el-Moharram, A. H. 1043 [A. D. 1633]. He encamped in a quarter of Sohar, called el-Bid'ah, and the Musalmans commenced an at tack on the unbelievers. The combat raged fiercely for a time, the Chris tians keeping up a fire of cannon from the fort. The Wall then changed his position, the fighting and cannonading continuing. A cannon shot pierced through the ranks of the besiegers until it reached the ' Mejlis' of the Wali and struck Eashid-bin 'Abbad, who thus suffered the death of a martyr. A fort was then erected by the Wall's orders, and he took up his position in it. There ceased not to be warfare between them nio-ht and day. 14 After this the Kadhi Khamis-bin Sa'id of el-Bostak proceeded with his followers to the village of Busher, 15 where he received a message from the Christians asking for peace, which request he granted. Afterwards he sent on his messengers to Maskat and, having mounted himself, rode to el-Matreh, where he was met by the leaders of the Chris tians, and terms of peace were agreed upon. Khamis thereupon ordered the abandonment of the strong positions he had occupied against them, and allowed free communication to be re-established with the town. In this manner hostilities were avoided.I : 'h Boole Sixth. 53 The Imam next despatched a force against Sur, which besieged and took that place. A portion of the force went to Keriyat, where the Christ ians possessed a Fort. The Musalmans erected a fort there and took that of the Christians. Thus the Imam acquired possession of the whole kingdom of 'Oman excepting Sohar and Maskat. Meanwhile Nasir-bin Katan continued to make raids into 'Oman .every year from el-Ahsa, 16 carrying off cattle and pillaging the country and re turning to el-Ahsa. The Imam therefore wrote to his Wall, Mohammed- hin Seyf el-Howkani, directing him to obtain information of Nagir's move ments, and as soon as he heard of his approach, to intercept him with an army beyond the frontier of f Oman. The Wall accordingly collected a force of ' Bedu' and ' Hadhr,' and when he heard of Nasir's approach advanced to meet him. Nasir hearing of the Imam's army made for el-Dhafreh and entered its fort, the Benu-Yas assisting him. Thence he sent messengers to the Wall to sue for peace. The Wall being in straits for provisions, and distant from his supplies, agreed to make peace on condition of Nasir re storing all plundered property in his possession and paying compensation for what had been continued, after which the Wall retired with his fol lowers. Nasir, however, collected the Bedouins of el-Dhafreh and proceeded to attack the fort of el-Jow, of which Ahmed-bin Kbalf was Wall. ^ Nasir being joined by all the inhabitants, who aided him against the Wall, laid siege'to the fort; but the Walls of el-Batineh and el-Dhahireh, hearing of this, sent succours to Ahmed-bin Khalf, and the enemy's forces retired from the district. The chief Wall then came with an army from Nezwa, and ordered the demolition of all the Forts of el-Jow, except that of the and the enemies were dispersed. 'Omeyr-bin Mohammed fled to the Christ ians at Sohar, and others made for the hill pass of Julfar, where they took to highway robbery and pillaging the districts. The Walls proceeded against them, and some were killed and others fled. The Wall having seiz ed their camels returned to 'Oman. Nasir-bin Katan then led his followers to el-Batineh, and made raids on the camels of the Benu-Khahd and Benu- Lam. 17 They also plundered the women of their ornaments and clothes, after' which they retired to el-Ahsa. Soon after, he again invaded 'Oman, and advanced towards el-Batineh, in order to pillage that district. The Imam, however, assembled an army to repel him, and placed in command 'Ali-bin Ahmed, supported by Mohammed-bin Salt el-Riyami, 'All-bin Mo- hammed-el-'Ibrl, and Ahmed-bin Belhasan el-Busheri They proceeded to the town of Lawa, where they encountered Nasir-bin Katan and his force. An engagement occurred, in which Nasir was worsted, and fled to Majis, pursued by the Wall and his followers. Nasir then made for el-Shemal, and the Wall rode in pursuit. The first to come up with Nasir were Ahmed-bin Belhasan, and Murad and Eashid-bm Hisam, and a few of the54 Annals of 'Oman. faithful, 18 who overtook him at a place called el-Kharus. This advanced party of the Musalmans having been assailed by Nasir's force before the main body of the Imam's army came up, they were slain to a man. Grod alone is Immortal! When the army arrived at the spot, they saw their comrades lying dead, and not a man of Nasir's force was in sight. About this time Hamid, alias Mohammed-bin 'Othman, attacked the district of el-Sirr, where Mohammed-bin Seyf el-Howkani was Wall. Sa'id- bin Khalfan, who happened to be in el-Sirr at the time, demanded an inter view with Ibn-Hamid, and they met at el-Ghabbi, in the mosque of el- Shan'ah, when Sa'id demanded restitution of the property they had plunder ed ; but the other refused and became still more insolent and audacious, so that Sa'id was obliged to have him imprisoned in irons in the fort of el- Ghabbi. Sa'id then proceeded to el-JRostak and informed the Imam of the seizure of Mohammed-bin 'Othman at el-Ghabbi. The Imam ordered him to be brought to el-Rostak, and he was accordingly conveyed there in fet ters, and remained in confinement for seven months when he died. The Imam soon after raised another army under command of Sa'id-bin Khalfan, supported by 'Omeyr-bin Mohammed-bin Jafir. This force pro ceeded with the design of seizing the camel herds of Nasir-bin Katan el- Hilah. Before they reached the spot where the camels were, they were encountered, at a place named el-Sha'ib near el-Dhafrah, by the Benu-Yas, and a battle ensued, in which the leader of the Benu-Yas, Sakeyr-bin 'I'sa, and his brother Mohammed with a number of the tribe were slain. On this they sued for peace, which the Wall granted, and the army returned. The Imam then directed them to proceed to a place called Daghfis, where Nasir-bin Katan had herds of camels. They succeeded in capturing these camels, which were made over to the charge of 'Omeyr-bin Moaammed-bin Jafir, but the latter's brother, at the instigation of others, restored the camels to^Nasir-bin Katan. The latter and his followers ceased not to pil lage 'Oman until he became the dread of ' Bedu' and ' Hadhr,' and the people of the desert sought refuge in the villages. On the occasion of one of his raiding expeditions, Nasir halted with his army in the south, and sent a body ot his people to close the passes. The Imam sent an army against him under Seyf-bin Malik and Seyf-bin Abul-'Arab. The advanced guard of the Imam s force came suddenly on Nasir's force and, being few in com parison with the latter, they were all slain. Nasir then withdrew to el-Ahsa, and the Imam's army returned. After this God aided the Imam of the Musalmans against all wrong doers, whom he ejected from their habitations and removed with the strong arm. He took pledges from the disaffected and humbled their leaders, crushed the tyrannical, and checked all oppressors. God was on his side and bestowed His grace on him, so that el-Islam was exalted and shone forth,Hooic Sixth. 55 whilst evil and wrong-doing hid their heads. Justice was extended to all the people of'Oman, whether ' Bedu' or 'Hadhr.' There remained only the party of Christians, who held out within the walls of Maskat, and these had suffered from war to such an extent that they had become weak, and their power was falling to decay. Their allies were dispersed, and death and slaughter had well nigh done their work on the majority of them. Then God decreed that the Imam should die, and this event occurred on Friday ten days before the end of EaM 4 ul-Akhir, A. H. 1050 [A. D. 1640], 19 his reign having lasted twenty-six years. All the just were content with, nay devoted to him. He was buried at Nezwa, where his tomb is well known. The Ima'm Sulta'jt-bt^ Setp . On the same day on which the Imam. Nasir-bin Murshid-bin Malik expired, the Musalmans elected his cousin the Imam Sultan-bin Seyf-bin Malik. This Prince ruled justly, and was active and diligent in the service of God, failing in no respect. He waged war on the Christians, who still remained in Maskat, and personally con ducted the operations against them until God gave him the victory over them and he took the place. 20 He continued afterwards to carry on Weir against them by land and sea wherever he found them, and succeeded in taking many of their towns and ships, and enriched himself with much booty taken from them. It is said that he built the fort which is at Nezwa entirely from the spoil of Sirr, and it took him twelve years to complete the work. He also constructed the aqueduct of el-Birkeh, which is between Izki and Nezwa, but nearer to the former place. It is probable that strict ures were passed on him as regards his Imamship on account of his engag ing in commerce, as he had agents who were known to trade on his account. In his time there were many learned men in'Oman. Wealth also increased, and the country was prosperous and brilliant, the people gratefully enjoy ing tranquillity. The harvests were abundant and prices low. He was affable to his subjects and liked by all. He used to walk out without a guard and sit and converse with the people. He would salute all, great or little, slave or free. Thus he continued assiduously to administer the Go vernment until his death, which occurred on Friday morning, the 16th of Thul-Ka'deh, A. H. 1090 [4th October, 1680.] His body was interred where the Imam Nasir-bin Murshid had been buried. The Ima'm Bel'aeab-bin Sulta'jst . They then elected his son Bel'arab- bin Sultan-bin Seyf-bin Malik. This prince was generous and beneficent, and the people ceased not to be grateful to him and to extol his virtue. He removed from Nezwa to Yabrm, which he made a flourishing place and where he built a fort. But strife broke out between the Imam and his brother Seyf, and in the course of their contention many of the people of 'Oman, learned men, elders, and pious persons, suffered great troubles. Many56 Annah of '■(hndn,. soak went to perdition from fbllowirig the opinions and suivice of tKe fbo&gt;I- iA. The Imam, having gone on an expedition to el-Shemah on his retnm was forbidden entry to Nezwi by the inhabitant on which he went to Tabrtn. The I vfA it Setp-bts' SrLTx'y. The majority of the people of 'Oman then assembled, and conferred the Imamate on his brother Seyf-bin. Saltan; bat I conceive that most o£ them entered into the matter from fear of eon- aet^aenees, and that some suffered for refasing to join in the plot. Seyf then went against his brother, and took all the forts of 'Oman, except \ abrin which he besieged, and fighting continued antil Bel'arab died in the castle. His adherents begged to be allowed to qait the place unmo lested, and Seyf consented. I imagine that some of the learned continued to regard Bel'arab as Imam ap to the time of his rk^h., looking on Seyf as a rebel against his brother. After that, Seyf subdued all 'Oman and ruled juatly r protecting the weak from the strong, and inspiring the tribes of 'Oman anH other countries with fear. He made war on the Christians in every eounlry r drove them from their abodes and uprooted them from places where they had establish ed themselves. He wrested from them Bender-Mombasah, .Liziret el-Kha- dhri, 21 Kilwah, Battah, and other places belonging to 'Oman became very prosperous, and the Imam constrncted many aque ducts, and planted date trees and other descriptions of trees. The Imam amassed much wealth, and possessed many male and female slaves, for he was very greedy of wealth. 'Oman was strong and prosperous under his sway, and he went on in this manner until he died at el-E.ostak and was buned there. His death occurred on Friday night, three days before the end of Ramadhan, A. H. 1120 [A. D. 170S.] The Ima'm sclta'^-bnf Setf-blx Ma'lik was then elected Imam and governed firmly and diligently, warring against the foes by land and by sea. He attacked the Persians in several places, and drove them from their pos sessions. He also built the fort of el-Hazam, and removed from el-Rostak to that place. He expended all the wealth he had inherited from his father, and moreover borrowed lacs from the property of the mosques and religious endowments. He attacked and took el-Bahrein; and neither the people of 'Oman, nor of any other country, ventured to stir against him. At length, he died in the fort of el -Hazam, on Wednesday five days before the end of Jumadi el-Akhir, A. H. 1131 [A. D. 1718], and was buried there. Thereupon there occurred a difference between the el-Ya'arabeh and the heads of the tribes, who were clannish and touchy. They wished to elect in the Im;im's place his son Seyf, who was still of unripe vears. But the men of learning, as well as the daughter of the Imam Seyf,Boole Seventh. 57 desired that the Imam ate should be conferred on Mohenna-bin Sultan, con sidering him worthy of the position and powerful enough to maintain it. They were moreover not aware of anything in his character or conduct which should exclude him from reigning. They argued also that the Imamate of a boy was not allowable in any circumstances. It would not be lawful for him to lead the prayers ; how then could he be Imam of the country, to govern it, and have power over the property, lives, and honor of the people ? When it was not lawful for him to take possession of his own property, how could it be right that he should have charge of the property of God, or of orphans, or of absentees, and others incapacitated for the administiation of their affairs ? The Sheykh 'Adi-bin Suleiman el-Thahali perceived that the people favoured the claims of the Imam's son, and though he did not consider him self justified in assisting them in that course, he feared that, as the assembled people were armed, opposition might induce them to use their weapons and lead to bloodshed. Accordingly he wished to silence them and break up the assembly. So he said to them ' Seyf is ' Amam' or ' before you.' ' On this, they proclaimed him Imam, and fired the guns to announce the event. The news spread throughout 'Oman that Seyf-bin Sultan was Imam. When, however, the commotion had subsided, and people had quieted down, they brought the Sheykh Muhenna secretly into the fort and elected him Imam. This was in the same month and year in which Sultan-bin Seyf died. The Im'am Muhenna-bin Sultan . The new Imam applied himself to the Government, and the people enjoyed tranquillity during his time. He abolished the custom duties at Maskat, and appointed no agent to reside there, so that the inhabitants made profit by the trade of the place. ^ Prices fell and the harvests were rich. None of the learned refused allegiance to Muhenna. He continued to reign for one year when he was slain. I shall, if it be the will of God, narrate the circumstances attending his slaughter, and the causes of the disturbances which took place in 'Oman and of the condition to which the affairs of its people tended, in a separate book. Book VII. Account of the Civil Wars in 'Oman and of the state to which the country was reduced. A. D. 1718 to A. D. 1/28. After the election of Muhenna-bin Sultan, the el-Ya'arabeh and people of el-Eostak ceased not to cherish enmity against him and the Kadlu 'Adi- bin Suleiman el-Thahali and to urge Ya'rab-bin Bel'arab to rise against the Imam ; which he at length did, and took possession of Maskat, the Wall ot which was at that time Mes'ud-bin Mohammed-bin Mes'ud el-Sanmi el- RiyamL As Ya'rab did not enter Maskat with a force, it is probable the58 Annals of l Omdn. inhabitants were not guiltless of treason towards the Imam Muhenna. The latter had gone to Felej el-Bazil in the districts of el-Jow, hut as soon as he heard this intelligence, he returned to el-Rostak and spared no effort to meet the emergency. He called on the people of 'Oman to aid him against the enemy, hut they did not respond to his call and abandoned him to his fate. The people of el-Rostak had besieged him in the Fort. Ya'rab, hearing this, came from Maskat to el-Rostak, and summoned Muhenna to come forth from the Fort, offering him safe-conduct for himself and follow ers and property. Muhenna reflected on his position : abandoned as he was and unaided by any of the people of 'Oman, he was evidently helpless, and accordingly accepted the proffered terms and came down from the Fort. By this act, his Imamate came to an end. Notwithstanding the promises of security, he was immediately seized, fettered, and placed in the stocks, with one of his companions. Soon after, some of his enemies' servants came, and slaughtered them both as they lay bound and helpless. Ya'rab then assumed the reins of government, but did not aspire to the Imamate, which office pertained to his cousin Seyf-bin Sultan, contenting himself with acting as regent for the latter, who was too young to assume the Government himself. All the Forts of 'Oman surrendered to them, and all the tribes made their submission. This was in the year 1133 A. H. [A. D. 1720.] Matters went on in this way for a year, after which the Kadhi 'Adi-bin Suleiman el-Thahali proposed to Ya'rab that he should repent of all his mis deeds, his oppression of the Musahnans, and his rebellion against Mohenna- bin Sultan and seizure of the Government of the Musalmans. In case of his doing this, Ya'rab would be absolved of the guilt of rebellion, and it would not be necessary for him to make restitution for what he had de stroyed ; for compensation is not incumbent on one who has repented and received absolution. \ a'rab followed these counsels, on which he was made Imam in the year 1134 A. H. [A. D. 1721.] The Ima'm Ya'eab-bin Bel'aeab . He then received charge of the Government in his own name and the various forts of 'Oman were surren dered to him. After remaining a few days at el-Rostak, he proceeded to Nezwa, which he entered on the 29th of el-Sha'ban of the same year. The people of el-Rostak were not content that Ya'rab should be Imam, and displayed a preference for the Sayyid Seyf-bin Sultan. They constantly wrote to Bel'arab-bin Nagir, the maternal uncle of the Seyyid Seyf-bin Sultan, who was at Nezwa with the Imam Ya'rab. They ceased not to urge Bel'arab until he left Nezwa, on the 7th of Showwal of that year, and proceeded to Bilad-Seyt, where he succeeded in binding the Benu-Hinah to support him by engaging to release them from the restrictions placed on them by the Imam Nasir-bin Murshid in the matters of building, carrying arms, &amp;c. He also gave them rich presents. They accordingly took him to el-BooTc Seventh. 59 Eostak, where fighting went on, until they succeeded in ejecting the Wall from the place. They set fire to the gate of the Fort, and the whole front of the place was burnt, and many leaders of the Benu-Hinah, as also some chiefs of the Benu-'Adi, were burnt to death. From what I have gathered, it seems one hundred and fifty lives were lost by the fire. Many books also were destroyed on this occasion, such as the ' Bayan ul-Shara'' ' el- Musannif' ' Kit ah ul-Istikdmeh' ' Mujlibdt ul-Tilismat,' of about forty volumes. Many other works were burnt, which were unique in 'Oman. Through this fire a vast treasure was discovered. When intelligence of what the people of el-Eostak had done reached the Imam Ya'rab, he detached a body of horsemen 1 under the command of the Sheykh Salih-bin Mohammed-bin Khalf el-Suleymi, and ordered them to proceed to el-Rostak ; but after reaching 'Awabi, they were obliged to retreat, not being strong enough to fight. Bel'arab-bin Nasir then wrote to the Wall of Maskat, Himyer-bin Suleiman-bin Ahmed el-Riyami, to surren der that place to them, which he did. The town of Nakhl also was delivered up without a blow. The insurgents then sent forth a detachment under Malik bin-Seyf el-Ya'rabi, who succeeded in taking Semail without opposition, the 'Wall evacuating the place. This was in the month of ihul-Ka'deh of the same year. The Benu-Euaheh joined Malik, who next marched to Izki, which he took without any fighting. Ya'rab then marched with his adherents of the Nezwa people and the Benu-Eiyam, attended by the Kadhi 'Adi-bin Suleiman el-Thahali, and came to IzkL The Sheykhs of that place declared for him, and came out to meet him with offers of hospitality and supplies. For two days he remained writing to Malik-bin Seyf, summoning him to come forth from the Fort. And as he refused to do so after that time, Ya'rab commenced hostilities and fired twice on him with cannon. The detachment of the Benu-Hinah under hahib el-'Anbur 2 of el-Eostak, however, coming up against Ya'rab, his army was scattered, and he, finding himself deserted, returned to Nezwa. The Kadhi 'Adi-bin Suleiman fled to el- Eostak, where the people seized him and Suleiman-bin Khalfan, and bound them to the pillory, where they were slain by some of Belaiab-bin Na&amp;ii s people, and their bodies were dragged through the streets by the people of el-Eostak. This occurred on the feast of the Hijj in the same year. Sahib el-'Anbur then proceeded to Nezwa, and commenced wiiting to Yaiab, urging him to come forth from the Fort. Some of the Nezwa people, also, went to him and asked him to evacuate the place, in order to save bloodshed. They did not cease importuning him to this end, until at length he consented, on condition of their leaving him in the loit of Yabrin and abstaining from molesting him. They entered into a compact with him to that effect, on which he went forth from Nezwa. By this act his Imamate terminated. He proceeded straight to Yabrin, and Sahib60 Annals of l Oman. el-'Anbur entered the Fort of Nezwa, and firing a salute from all the guns proclaimed Seyf-bin Sultan Imam. The Imam Setf-bin Sulta/it . All the forts of 'Oman were surren dered to him, and all the tribes and towns submitted to his authority. Matters went on in this wise for two months all but three days, when it was the will of God to bring to pass what He had foreseen would befall the people of 'Oman, on account of their fickle and changeable behaviour. For God does not send vicissitudes on a people until they are untrue to themselves. In the trials He sends, he who is steadfast in his religion is distinguished from the backslider and hypocrite. God said those words, ' Do men imagine it shall he sufficient for them to say, 1 we helieve] while they he not proved ? We proved heretofore those who were before them ; for God will surely know those who are sincere, and He will surely know the liars'* God then foresaw what was predestined to occur, that the actions of all men should come to light, and the evildoer suffer for his misdeeds, and the obedient be fortified, each being requited according to his good or evil deeds, like as pure gold is tested by fire. It has been said too, ' By trial is a man honored or despised.' When it was settled that Bel £ arab-bin Nasir should administer the Government as regent, and that Seyf-bin Sultan was Imam, the various tribes and chiefs came to offer their congratulations on this. Bel'arab-bin Nasir on this occasion let fall threats against certain tribes, especially the Benu-Ghafir 4 and the people of Bahla. It is said when Mohammed-bin Nasir- bin 'Amir el-Ghafm came with a party of his tribe, the Seyyid Bel'arab uttered menaces against them, on which Mohammed-bin Nasir retired deeply offended, and entered into correspondence with Ya'rab-bin Bel'arab and the people of Bahla, urging them to rise in revolt. He went also himself to the Bedouins of el-Dhafrah, the Benu-Na'im, Benu-Katab, and the rest. Bel'arab on his part sent to invite the chiefs of Nezwa to join him, and a large number of them did so, and were received with honor, and desired to give their allegiance to Seyf-bin Sultan. He then sent a detachment 5 under his brother Suleiman-bin Nasir with orders to proceed by Wadi- Semail, and bring Ya'rab to el-Rostak. He ordered the Nezwa people to accompany this force, but they ceased not to ask the chiefs of el-Rostak to intercede with him to excuse them from this duty until he consented. The detachment proceeded as far as Fark, where they passed the night, and the people of Nezwa sent them food and refreshments. Suddenly, they heard the firing of cannon from the lort of Nezwa, and enquiring what had happened, were informed that Ya'rab-bin Bel'arab had entered the Fort. Thereupon they returned to Izki, where Suleiman-bin Nasir seized the Fort and remained in the town. Bel'arab-bin Nasir had meanwhile despatched a second, detachment against Tia'rab by way of el-Dhahireh, but on theirJ^oolc Seventh. G1 reaching Balila, the people of that place seized and imprisoned them there. A third party, which was sent to Wadi Beni-Ghafir, was defeated and retired to el-Rostak. Ya'rab, on the other hand, sent a detachment with two gnns against Izki. When they arrived before the place, they opened fire on the Fort, but were worsted and retired to Nezwa after losing several men. He then sent another force against Izki. They halted for a day on the west side of the town, and the following morning saw them in retreat on Nezwa without having struck a blow. A third force, also, was sent which occupied the western side of Izki, and bombarded the Fort with cannon for about ten days, after which Malik-bin Nasir arrived at Izki from el-Rostak, and, having been joined by the garrison, made a sortie on Ya'rab's troops, but was repulsed. The Bedouins of Ya'rab's army attacked and plundered Sudda and the quarter named el-Rahha of Izki, and burned the abode of Himyer- bin Manir outside el-Rahha. The leaders of Ya'rab's force next attacked el-Yemen tribe, but were defeated, and one of the commanders, Mohammed- bin Sa'id-bin Ziyad of Bahla, was killed. Malik-binNasir, having been told that the el-Nizar 6 had joined Ya'rab's men in the attack on the el-Yemen, sent for the Sheykhs of the former clan and placed them in irons in the chief mosque. He then sent to the people of el-Sharkiyeh, and a large army of them came to his aid. The Benu-Hmah also came in large numbers, and the whole having united at Izki attacked Ya'rab's force. The drums and a small body of men were sent out by the side of el-Manzaliyeh, and the main body marched out from the directions of el-'Atab on Friday at sunset. A great battle was fought, in which the musketry rattled like peals of thunder, and swords flashed like lightning. The result was the defeat of Ya'rab's army. The slaughter was great: from what I have heard, three hundred men fell on both sides, but God knows! Nagir-bin Malik then marched with his followers on the town of Manh, and a detachment attacked Faleyj of Wadi el-Hajar, killed many of the inhabitants, and plundered all that they found in the place. They then burned down the houses of Zakit and Mahyul, after which they reached Manh, where they plundered the ' Hujreh' of Ma'mad, burned the houses, and slew numbers of the inhabitants, who were dispersed in all directions. They next marched on Nezwa, and pitched their camp at the mosque of el-Makhass of Fai'k, and laid siege to Nezwa. They destroyed the cultiva tion, and burned many sugar-cane fields of el-Heyli and el-Khadhra. I hey also burned the houses of Fark, and committed depredations everywhere. The people of Nezvva and Ya'rab's followers sallied out against them, and, after an engagement in which several were slain on each side, both ar mi es fell back to their former positions. After this, there was lightingG2 Annals of l Omdn. every day : many were killed and the people of Nezwa experienced much suffering. At length, a great battle was fought, the like of which we have not heard of the forces of. The forces of Malik were well nigh put to flight only ; when half of them had fled, the remainder were unable to escape, as the enemy had surrounded them like a ring. Despairing of escape from slaughter, they made a desperate rally and fought with fury. The Nezwa men, on the other hand, thought victory secured, and many commenced to plunder, each one trusting to his comrades to keep watch. In this situation, a body of Malik's men made a determined attack on them and routed them. In their flight they lost numbers in killed and wounded. The enemy pursued as far as a place called Jannur el-Khoseh, near the bend of el-'Akr, slaying and capturing. A great number of the inhabitants of Nezwa fell on that day. Bel'arab then returned to his camp, and for some time desultory skirmishing daily occurred. At length, Malik marched out with all his force, ex cepting only a few, whom he left to guard his camp, and advanced as far as Hindt of el-'Akr. His plan was to attack that place from the enclosed garden of Showeykh, making loopholes in the wall for musketry. The people of Nezwa, however, sallied out against him, and the millstones of war revolved amongst them for an hour of that day, at the end of which Malik- bin Nasir was slain, and his forces were routed and forced to retreat to their camp. They remained encamped there, but were much weakened by the fall of Nasir. Fighting nevertheless continued between them and the people of Nezwa, until Mohammed-bin Nasir the Ghafiri arrived with his force from el-Gharbiyeh, after having fought several severe battles at Wadi el-Sakal and in el-Jow, and at Dhank and el-Grhabbi. I refrain from describ ing these actions to avoid prolixity, and as moreover they are well known. Mohammed-bin Nasir now ordered an attack to be made on a body of the enemy in el-Makhadh. His forces accordingly attacked and surrounded them, and the fire of matchlocks was sustained from morning till night. When night fell, Mohammed-bin-Nasir ordered an assault to be made on them from the el-Sakal side along the Wadi leading to Fark. The attack succeeded, and morning found the place completely evacuated, not one of the enemy being left in it, all having fled. At this time, the Seyyid Ya'rab was ill. Mohammed-bin Nasir then returned to Nezwa, where he remained a few days, after which he ordered his army to march on el-Hostak. The siege of Nezwa had lasted two months all but six days. On arrival at el-Rostak, Mohammed-bin Nasir encamped with his entire force at Felej el-Sharat. His men desired to assault a tower in which 'All-bin Mohammed Sahib el-'Anbur had ensconced himself; but Mohammed- bin ISasir restrained them until Sahib el-'Anbur and his men commenced hostilities, when the assault was ordered. A severe fight ensued, in whichBoole Seventh. 63 Sal lib el-'Anbur and many of bis people were slain and tbe remainder routed. Mohammed-bin Nasir tben returned to Felej el-Sbarat, and, on tbe following day, entered Felej el-Madra, wbere Bel'arab-bin Nasir met bim as a sup plicant. Mobammed agreed to make peace on condition of bis surrendering tbe Fort of el-Kostak, and all otber Forts in bis possession. Tbey accordingly proceeded together to tbe Fort of el-Rostak. Now Bel'arab meditated treachery towards Mohammed-bin Nasir, but tbe latter, shrewd and cautious, declined to enter except with bis men, and when all had entered, be entered also. As soon as they were in, bis troops commenced to pillage the town, and tbey abducted so many children that tbey were sold into foreign countries. This treatment was the requital of their evil doing and of their treatment of the Kadhi of tho Musalmans 'Adi-bin Suleiman, ' Verily God ivill not chanqe Sis grace loliich is in men, until they change the disposition in their souls hy sin.'''' Tbe death of Ya'rab-bin Eel'arab occurred whilst Mohammed-bin Nasir was at el-Eostak, thirteen days before the expiry of Jumadi el-Ukbra, A. H. 1135. [A. D. 1723]. The people of Nezwa, however, fearing tbe enemy would attack them, concealed the fact for nearly fifty days. Mohammed-bin Nasir ordered Bel'arab to be imprisoned in fetters, after be had commanded him to surrender all tbe Forts in bis possession. There remained only Maskat and Birkeb 8 in the bands of the Benu-Hinab. Mohammed-bin Nasir remained at el-Kostak and proclaimed Seyf-bin Sultan Imam. The people of el-Rostak fled to the hills and valleys. I have beard that in a cavern, in the direction of tbe district of Mabalil, were found tbe bodies of about one hundred women and children, who bad perished ol thirst, afraid to return to el-Rostak lest they should be carried off and sold into slavery. Three days after he took el-Rostak, Mohammed-bin Nasir was joined by a re-inforcement of about fifteen hundred men of tbe Benu-Koleyb and Benu-Ka'b, armed with matchlocks and spears. There also arrived Rahmeh- bin Matr-bin Rabmeb el-Hawali with about 5000 ' Bedu' and ' Hadhr,' amongst whom were some who did not understand Arabic 9 and were unable to distinguish friend from foe. Khalf-bin Mubarik, known as el-K a sir [or the Dwarf], a native of el- Ghashb, who was not at el-Rostak during tbe fighting, took possession of the Forts of Birkeh and Maskat, having with bim tbe Benu-Hinab. Mohammed-bin Nasir sent'All-bin Mohammed el-Kharusi as AV all ot the Fort of Barka, but be was slain and his followers returned to Mohammed- bin Nasir at el-Rostak. The latter thereupon directed the whole oi his forces on Barka. So Rahmeh-bin Matr el-Hawali marched with bis con tingent ; also Hamzah-bin Hammad el-Koleybi with his men, and Ahmed- bin 'All el-Grhaliri with tbe force contributed by Mohammed-bin Nasir.G4 Annals of '■Oman. Likewise Mohammed-bin 'Adi-bin Suleiman el-Thabali, with the men he had brought from el-Sir. Also Mohammed-bin Nasir el-Harrasi with his clan. All these proceeded, each in command of his own division, until they reached Mesna'a. There a letter arrived from the Benu-Hinah, addressed by Kar 'a el-Darmald to Rahmeh-el-Hawali saying; ' Do not come further against us, as we are coming to meet you,' in the sense of a threat. When Rahmeh read the letter, he understood its meaning, and at once ordered an advance on Barka, sending scouts ahead to that place. The latter finding Kar 'a and his followers advancing against Rahmeh, returned with the intelligence. Rahmeh encountered them at a place called el-Kasim. Kodheyb el-Hawali charged the enemy on horseback, followed closely by the remainder of the force. Ten of the enemy were killed, and Kar'a and his followers were routed. Kodheyb received a slight wound. Rahmeh then moved his men eastward, and halted at el-Hifri, 10 which belongs to the el-Jibur, to allow his men rest and refreshment. Thence he sent out his scouts, who reported that Khalf- bin Mubarik el-Kasir had moved by land and sea with an innumerable force. Those on the side of Mohammed-bin Nasir amounted to 5000 men, 'Bedu' and'Hadhr' of various tribes. The rival armies encountered to the west of Barka, and a severe contest ensued. Rahmeh's men had cannon, with which they fired on the vessels which were on the sea, and forced them to stand further out. The battle ended in the defeat of Khalf-bin Mubarik, who mounted a camel and fied. His forces were broken and pursued by those of Mohammed-bin Nasir, who slew and captured many, until finding no refuge from slaughter many plunged into the sea, and endeavoured to gain the ships. These, however, had put to sea, and they failed to reach them. The victors meanwhile kept up a fire on them until all perished. The bodies were then stripped of arms and all else on them. When the dead bodies were thrown up by the sea, they found the number of killed amounted to 1012 men. The remainder of the fugitives were pursued until they entered the Fort of Barka. The adherents of Mohammed-bin Nasir then encamped by the side of the hill at Barka, and laid siege to the Fort. Four days afterwards, the garrison embarked in the ships, and went to Maskat, leaving only a few men in the Fort, the town being empty. The army of Mohammed-bin Nasir then returned to el-Rostak, and Rahmeh returned to his own country. Mohammed-bin Nasir remained a time in el-Rostak, where he had so severe an attack of small-pox, that fears were entertained for his life. When he recovered, he ordered an expedition to proceed to Yankal. He placed in el-Rostak as Wall Mohammed-bin Nasir el-Harrasi, and with him in the Fort he left the Bahla chiefs and Sinan-bin Mohammed-bin Sinan el- Mahthur el-Grhafiri. Mohammed-bin Nasir and Seyf-bin Sultan then marched carryingBoo'k Seventh. 65 d-bin Sn'' 1 «.y tai^ ■with them Bel'arab-bin Nasir and all the Ya'arabeh in fetters, 11 and proceeded until they reached Makaniyat. Mohammed-bin Nasir's stay at el- Eostak had lasted about two months. On arrival at Makaniyat, he sent to the tribes of Dhahireh and 'Oman and to the Benu-Yas, summoning them to his aid. They obeyed his call, and a large army of about 12,000 men assembled under him. His camp was at Felej el-Manadereh, on the Yankal side. On summoning the people of the town to surrender the Fort to him, they failed to do so, and returned him no answer. In the morning, he moved his camp, intending to occupy the high ground, above the source of the el-Mohidith stream of el-Batha. The Benu-'Ali and their allies of Yankal opposed him, and a severe conflict occurred, in which many of the Benu-'Ali were slain, notably the son of their Sheykh Suleiman-bin Salim. On Mohammed-bin Nasir's side, Salim-bin Ziyad el-Ghafiri, Seyf-bin Kasir el-Shakeyli and one other were wounded. Mohammed-bin Nasir then encamped on the heights above the fountain head of the el-Mohidith stream, and besieged the garrison, firing on them from guns and matchlocks. Another engagement was fought, in which many were killed. On the side of Mohammed-bin Nasir there fell the Wall of Dhank, Mohammed-bin Khalf el-Kuyudhi, and one of his cousins. They then cut off' the supply of water by breaking up the aqueduct, on which the garrison accepted terms, and agreed to surrender the Forts. Intelligence next reached Mohammed-bin Nasir that Sa'id-bin Haweyd had entered el-Seleyf with his followers and joined the el-Suawafeh, who sided with the Benu-Hinah. He accordingly directed his army on el-Seleyf, and on arrival there sent a message to Sa'id-bin Haweyd and the people of el-Seleyf, inviting them to make their submission, but they declined. A number of the el-Suawafeh of Ten'am, however, joined Mohammed-bin Nasir, and tendered their allegiance. He then attacked the Fort of the el- Murashid of el-Seleyf, and overturned the walls, burying under the ruins all the men, women, and children, who were within the place. Sa'id-bin Haweyd then requested safe passage for himself and his followers to his own district, Mohammed-bin Nasir acceded to his request, and not only allowed him free egress, but supplied him with provisions for his journey. After this, there only remained at el-Seleyf the Forts of the el-Suawafeh and the el-Manadereh. The latter seeing what had befallen the el- Murashid, made their submission to Mohammed-bin Nasir, who pardoned them and suffered them to remain unmolested in their stronghold. The el-Suawafeh, on the contrary, held out, so Mohammed-bin Nasir continued to besiege them, cutting down their date trees, and slaying them daily. He dismissed his Bedouin auxiliaries, retaining only the Benu-\as and the ' Hadhr' tribes. When the siege had lasted over two months, the garrison agreed to demolish the Fort with their own hands ] on their doing hmimmMP6G Annals of '■Oman. this, peace was concluded. Meanwhile Khalf-hin Mubarik el-Kasir, seeing Mohammed-bin Nasir engaged in the siege of el-Seleyf, laid siege to el- Kostak. Now Saba' el-'Amur! had previously taken the Fort of Sohar. When Sinan-bin Mohammed el-Mahthur el-Ghafiri, the warden of the Fort, was killed, Mohammed-bin Nagir el-Harrasi and his followers came forth from the Fort of el-Iiostak, and, Khalf-bin Mubarik entering, the place was surrendered to him. Saba' el-'Amuri had meanwhile taken the Fort of Sohar, and Moham med-bin Nasir found himself unable to return from el-Seleyf and march to the relief of el-Eostak and Sohar, for fear his enemies in el-Dhahireh should become too strong for him. Khalf el-Kasir then moved against the Fort of el-Hazam, the Wall of which was 'Omer-bin Salih-bin Mes'ud el-Ghafiri. He besieged the place, and diverted the course of the stream which supplied it with water. He then sent a message to the Wali, offering safe passage for him and his men, on condition of their evacuating the Fort. The Wall refused, and wrote to Mohammed-bin Nasir to inform him of what had occurred, and that they had no water except a small quantity in a cistern. Mohammed, accordingly, having made peace with the people of el-Seleyf and razed their Fort, proceeded to el-Hazam with an innumerable army, and when he reached that place, fell upon Khalf's forces. After many had been slain, the latter took to flight, leaving their arms, ammunition, and provisions behind. Mohammed-bin Nasir then returned to el-Dhahireh without visiting el- Eostak, his object being Bilad-Seyt. Having assembled a numerous force of ' Bedii' and ' Hadhr,' he marched from el-Dhahireh to Bilad-Seyt. The inhabitants refusing to comply with his summons to submission, he laid siege to the place, and his men having assaulted, slew many of the people. He next attacked el-'Aridh, which belonged to the Benu-'Adi, and took that place, and also Ghamar. The uplands of the Benu-Hinah fell into his hands, and none of that tribe remained in them. Some were slain, and those who asked quarter were sent away in safety. In the attack on Bilad- Seyt, about ten of Mohammed-bin Nasir's men were slain and sevel'al wounded. He then ordered his army to Nezvva, where he remained about six months, during part of the winter, until harvest time. Having summoned the people of the Manah [or Manh] district to submit to him, they refused, so he sent a force against them which surrounded them, and cut down their date trees at Felej el-iikein and Jarr-'Ali, and, when their property was destroyed, they made their submission. Mohammed-bin Nasir then returned to el-Dhahireh, and, halting at el- Ghabbx of el-Sirr, busied himself raising a fresh army, until he had collected a large number of ' Bedu and ' Hadhr.' He ordered the people of el-DhahirehBoole Seventh. 67 to convey the fresh dates to el-Hazam, and with them he sent the people of Wadi Bem-Ghafir and their belongings. He then set out with all his forces for the settlements of the el-'Awamir in el-Sharkiyeh, He was met by the el-'Awamir and the Al-Wahibeh 12 Bedouins and the Benu-Hinah, and a fierce battle took place, in which Mohammed-bin Nasir's followers were well nigh put to flight; but they rallied and stood firm, and eventually the Benu-Hinah 13 were put to flight, and a great number of them was slain. The pursuit was kept up until they entered the Hujreh of el-'Akil. Mohammed-bin Nasir and his followers returned in triumph to Yabrin, accompanied by the Seyyid Seyf-bin Sultan. Mohammed-bin Nasir then returned to el-Dhahireh, to recruit his forces, and, being joined by a large number, returned to Nezwa. He collected all the people of Nezwa, and Izki and Bahla, also the Benu-Eiyam, and marched with them to Seikam. Thence he sent to summon S a'id-bin Haweyd el-Hinawi, and the followers who had joined him from el-'Akir snd el-Ghafat, and, on their refusal to submit, besieged them. SaMd-bin Haweyd then passed out, and proceeded through el-Dhahireh to Sohar, in order to raise men there and at Yankal, for the people of the latter place had broken the truce. A large force joined him, on which he returned to 'Amla and drew in his forces. He collected many of the Benu-Hinah from Wadi el-'Ula and all their villages. 'When he reached Felej el-'Aislu, he meditated an attack on Mohammed-bin Nasir and his followers. Sa'id-bin Haweyd had been away collecting forces for seven months and seven days, and Mohammed-bin Nasir, fearing he might fall on him unawares, had distributed scouts throughout the districts, and these brought him the intelligence of the advance of Sa'id with a large force. Mohammed ordered his troops to intercept him ere he reached the district, and they accordingly met the advancing foe at the entrance of el- Ghafat. A great battle was fought, in which Sa'id-bin Haweyd el-Hinawi was slain, and amongst those of his adherents who fell was Ghasn-el-'Alawi, chief of Yankal. The total number of Sa'id's followers slain was two hundred, the remainder dispersed. Mohammed-bin Nasir ordered recitations to be pronounced in every district of Bahla and Nezwa, and the towns of el-Dhahireh to celebrate his victory. His followers dragged the corpse of Sa'id-bin Haweyd to the Fort of el-Ghafat, in which were his family, children, and followers, expecting that on beholding the sight, they would surrender; but they refused to do so. The siege was therefore continued for two months longer, when the gani- son, having eaten all their cattle, ran short of provisions. At this time Mubarik-bin Sa'id-bin Bedr commanded the forces of Mohammed-bin Nasir, who after the battle had returned to Yabrin. So, when their provisions were exhausted, and many had been slain, and their property destroyed, the garrison were granted terms on condition of their demolishing the ioit.C8 Annals of 'Oman. This they did with their own hands, on which they were suffered to depart in safety. The Fort of el-'Akir continued, however, to hold out. Mohammed-bin Nasir then dismissed Muharik-hin Sa'id-hin Bedr, and appointed in his place Rashid-bin Sa'id Rashid el-Ghafiri, who continued the siege of el-'Akir. He had under his orders the men of Bahla, Nezwa Izki, and el-Dhahireh, and also the Benu-Ghafir, and Benu-Riyam, They so closely invested the place, that not a soul could enter or leave it. When the provisions were exhausted, the garrison sued for peace, which was grant ed, the terms being the demolition of their Fort. They were accordingly obliged to demolish the walls, after losing all they possessed. There remained to them neither date trees nor water-courses, and they had con sumed the whole of their cattle. So under these conditions they were granted peace and safety of their persons. After which the troops returned, each man to his native place. Mohammed-bin Nasir next prepared another force of ' Bedii' and ' Hadhr,' and marched on the towns of the el-Habus of el-Sharkiyeh, namely, Madheybi, and el-Rowdheh. At the former town, they encountered the army of Khalf-bin Mubarik el-Kasir, consisting of the el-Habus and others of the Benu-Hinah. In the battle which ensued, Khalf-bin Mubarik was defeated and forced to take refuge in the ' Hujreh' of el-Madheybi. Mohammed-bin Nasir besieged them, and began to cut down the date trees, on which they sued for peace and quarter. Mohammed acceded, not know ing that Khalf-bin Mubarik was with them in the ' Hujreh.' Afterwards a certain person came and informed him that Khalf was in the place, but it did not seem good to him to break the terms of peace. Khalf then fled from el-Madheybi, and Mohammed-bin Nasir pursued him with his army until he reached Ibra, which place Khalf entered, not imagining that Mo hammed-bin Nasir would pursue him so far. He abode with the el-Harth, 14 to whom Mohammed sent summoning them to submit themselves to him, and to eject Khalf from amongst them. On their refusing to do so, he made daily attacks on them, cutting down their date and other trees, and destroying their water-courses. Finding themselves powerless to cope with Mohammed-bin Nagir, they secretly sent away Khalf from amongst them. The latter who was head of the whole of the Benu-Hinah, proceeded to Maskat. After his departure, Mohammed-bin Nasir made peace with the el- Harth, granting them an amnesty, and retiring from the place. The whole of el-Sharkiyeh submitted to him. He then returned to Yabrin, and tarried a space at that place, which was his favourite residence. He next went to el-Dhahireh and collected a numerous force there, with which he marched westwards, not one of his followers knowing whither he purposed to proceed. Passing through the districts of el-Na'im, 15 he col-Booh Seventh. 69 iectecl men from that tribe and the Benu-Yas, and led them to Ncjd el- Jezi, traversing the district of the Benu-Koleyb, some of whom joined him. He then passed into the sea-hoard tract of el-Batineh, causing terror to the people of Sohar, without, however, attacking them. He then marched east ward. The inhabitants of Felej el-Howasineh were alarmed lest he should destroy their valley. His troops seized and ate all the camels and cattle they found. Some amongst them had no conception who were their friends and who their enemies. Khalf-bin Mubarik having received intelligence of Mohammed's movements, encountered him at Aflaj-Ar'ar. A severe con test ensued, and Khalf's followers took to flight, and he himself was shut up in a house. Mohammed-bin Nasir and his men went in pursuit of the flying enemy, not knowing of Khalf's being in that house. The latter, on his part, imagined that Mohammed satisfied with his victory had left him. Mohammed-bin Nasir then entered el-Rostak, and commenced destroying the water channels, and writing to the people, summoning them to submit. As they refused, he destined the aqueducts of el-Meyser, Bu-Tha'lab, and el-Hammam, and cut down some date groves. The people of el-Rostak, being unable to sally forth to oppose him, at length thought of making their submission. Mohammed-bin Nasir now received intelligence that Rashid-bin Sa'id el-Ghafiri had seized the Fort of Makaniyat, the Wall of which was Muba- rik-bin Sa'id-bin Bedr. This was caused by Rashid's jealousy of Mubarik on account of the preference shown for him by Mohammed-bin Nasir. The latter on hearing the news ordered his forces to march on el-Rostak, after having destroyed its water-courses. Meanwhile 'Ali-bin Nasir-bin Ahmed el-Kelbani, went to Rashid-bin Sa'id, and by his advice induced him to make over the Fort to himself, guaranteeing that Mohammed-bin Nasir would not punish him. So 'All-bin Nasir took charge of the Fort until the arrival of Mohammed-bin Nasir, who left Mubarik there as Wall, with the tribe el-Hawatim, and himself returned to Yabrin, where he remained for a considerable time. Thence he proceeded with his attendants to Nezwa, and summoned the chiefs of tribes and learned men from the east and from the west of 'Oman. A great number of these having assembled, he demand ed of them that he should be excused from waging wars, and administrating the affairs of the Musalmans, and that they would appoint whomsoever they pleased to govern for the Seyyid Seyf-bin Sultan. However, the Kadhi Nasir-bin Suleiman-bin Mohammed-bin Maddad, and 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed-bin Rushi-bin Maddad, who was Wall of Nezwa fort, and the chiefs of tribes who were present, would not accept his resignation. They closed the gates of the Fort of Nezwa and el-'Akr, allowing none to entei or depart. All that day and night they ceased not to apply themselves to adjust the matter, until near morning they elected Mohammed-bin i^asii Imam as a measure of precaution.70 Annals of 1 Oman, The Imam Mohammed-bin Na'sir-bin 'A'mtr el-Gha'firi '. Tlie guns of the Fort of Nezwa were accordingly fired, and a proclamation was issued announcing the Imamate of Mohammed-bin Nasir and offering honorable treatment and security to every tribe, whether ' Yemen' or ' Nizar,' ' Bedu' or ' Hadhr,' which should enter Nezvva to visit him. This was on Saturday, seven days before the expiry of the month of el-Moharram, A. H. 1137 [A. D. 1724!.]. The Imam remained at Nezwa to lead the prayers on the following Friday, after which he removed with his attendants to Yabrin, and, having dismissed his forces, tarried there a space. Hearing that Mini-bin Khamis el-Azizi had attacked el Grhabbi, taken its Fort, plundered the bazar, and committed other depredations, he pro ceeded to that place, and scaled the Fort wall with only six followers. He gained the upper part of the Fort before the garrison were aware of his presence, and when they discovered him, they fled in terror, one of Mani'- bin Khamis's slaves being slain. In this manner he captured the Fort, and having appointed a Wall, returned to Yabrin. Soon after, Muhenna bin 'Adi el-Ya'rabi with 'Amir-bin Suleiman-bin Bel'arab el-Eiyami and Suleiman-bin Himyer-bin 'All el-Ya'rabi attacked and took the magazine of el-Birkeh. On hearing of this, Mohammed-bin Nasir proceeded against them, and sent to the Kadhi Nagir-bin Suleiman and the Wall 'Abdullah-bin Mohammed, desiring him to join him with a -force from Nezwa at Birkeh. He himself did not go to Nezwa. With the few soldiers and attendants he had with him, he attacked the enemy in the forenoon and put many to the sword. He then advised them to retire, and (restore what they had taken from the magazine, but they refused and fought against him. They held the Mesjid el-Shari'eh above el-Birkeh and the hill to the last, and broke up the water-course. Mohammed-bin Nasir •constructed a tower in the Mesjid below el-Shari'eh el-Birkeh on the lower hill. They kept up a fire of matchlocks on either side and one of the Maghribi 16 horsemen of Mohammed-bin Nasir's force was killed, and one wounded. He then ordered his men to attack the enemy, who fled in dis order, and Nasir-bin Bel'arab el-Riyami and 'All-bin Salih, the chief of Kemeh, were made prisoners. This happened before the reinforcement from Nezwa had come up. Mohammed then ordered the dates to be conveyed to Yabrin, and returned himself to Nezwa, taking up his abode in the mosque of el-Grhantak. He had intended to make war on the people of Tenuf,' but God saved them from this, and they met him and made promises that they would not act treacherously by him, on which he became reconciled to them. He then ordered all who owed allegiance to him in 'Oman to assem ble ; and accordingly, a large number having collected, he marched with them fiom Nezwa purposing to proceed to I)hank to arrange for the return ofBook Seventh. 71 the Washahat to their own district, and to rebuild for the people of Dhauk the Fort which he had destroyed when they were in allegiance to Khalf-- bin-Muharik. The Al-Aziz, however, demurred to their return and to the rebuilding of the Fort. This tribe having collected some of the Bedouins, and their own adherents, resolved to fight him and those of the el-Washa hat with him. The encounter took place at Dhank, and the Al-Aziz, dis covering their inability to cope with him, dispersed. Mani'-bin Khamis having gone to Seneyneh to the el-Na'im, Mohammed went in search of him with a small body of his followers mounted on horses and swift camels, and coming on them unawares, made prisoner Mani'-bin Khamis and return ed to Dhank. On his return towards el-Ghabbi, he passed by the water-courses of the Al-'Aziz Bedouins, who had plundered the bazar of el-Ghabbi, and de stroyed them, after which he went onto el-Ghabbi, and remained there until all those of the tribes of el-Dhahireh who were willing had assembled. then proceeded to Yabrin, and after a short stay there came to Nezwa, and abode in the house of el-Mazra' until he had collected a force. He then went to Izki, and gathered men from that place and also from all el-Shar- kiyeh. The Benu-Ruaheh were alarmed at his proceedings. He next proceeded to Semail and ceased not to admonish the el-Bckri- in and people of el-Hili and the tribe of 'Akkasheh. The people of el-Hili and the 'Akkasheh having made peace with him and submitted, he sent them to the el-Bekriin to bring them to terms. As they were unable to prevail with the latter tribe, Mohammed-bin Nasir ordered an attack to be made on them on a dark and rainy winter's night, amid thunder and light ning. They did not perceive him until he had gained the top of the wall,- where a watchman was posted. He asked the latter, ' For whom are you watching ?' He replied, ' fearing lest Mohammed-bin Nasir should attack us.' ' This,' he rejoined, ' is Mohammed-bin Nasir at your side.' Those in the ' Hujreh' then fled, and most of them were permitted to go forth unmolested. There only remained to be taken a tower and some upper rooms, in which were Bekr and his sons and cousins. A lilt of matchlocks was kept up upon these until they were slain to the last man. Of Moham med's followers four were slain, one of whom was a slave of his, named Bakhit el-Nubi [the Nubian], whom he had placed over all his slaves. He fell from a matchlock bullet. The ' Hujreh' was razed to the ground. Semail now paid up three years arrears of zekat. Before this the A1 'Omeyr had done much harm in the place, and had appropriated the property of absent persons. Mohammed-bin Nasir therefore restored all property to the rightful owners. He imprisoned the Owlad Sa'id-bm 'All and razed their ' Hujreh' to the ground. After 'that, Mohammed-bin Nasir directed his forces on el-Heyl in el-72 Annals of Oman, Batinefa, to intercut Khalf-biu Mubarik el-Kutiir iii las mareli from Maskat to el-lioBtak. He with Iub slaves patrolled the road as far as el-Ghobrah. Khalf-bin aMubarik, however, haviug aseertaiued that Mohammed had closed the road against him, and not being sufficientlj strong to encounter him, remained at Maskat, and placed sentries on the roads and walls. Mo hammed-bin Is asir remained at el-Herl for about half a month, during- which time the el-Ma'awal tribe came to terms with him, but subsequently broke faith. He then returned to Semail, and taking with him men of that place proceeded against the Bedouins of 'Amer E,abrah and A'l-Sa'ali, and those of the dwellers in el Batineh comprised under those names. He was liim- Belf mounted on a mare and armed with spear and scimitar, with which he etruck right and left, hamstringing their camels, to prevent their carrying them away. Coming on a body of his enemies, he slew their men, on which the women, taking him for Khalf, cried out, ' Quarter! O Khalf-biu Muba rik . we are in allegiar? 3e to you. He, however, redoubled his efforts in slaying them, riding in front of his men, so that none kept up with him save those on horseback or on swift camels. The Seyyid Seyf-bin Sultan was with him; indeed he was never separated from him in all his expeditions. Alter this, he returned to el-Hazam, and after remainmg' there a few days went to 8eni in ^ adi Bem-G-hafir, where he remained a short time, and dis missed a±l his followers, except the guard and his personal retainers. He next went to el-Ghabbi and, after spending a few days there, returned to Yabrin, which was his chief residence. At this time, the Bedouins had so infested all the roads of 'Oman, plundering and murdering, that people could onlv travel in large parties. The chief offenders were the Al-W ahibeh, who had a chief whom they called Bu-Khark. Mohammed-bin Xasir assembled them, with all their families, camels, and flocks, and commanded them to encamp round Yabrm. This he did, in order to show his resentment towards them : and he kept them bo uniii their camels and flocks perished, they being powerless to resist him. On the 11th of the month of el-Hijj. he issued forth with his followers in search of the Al-W ahibeh. He destroyed their settlement erf el-Sadeyreh, and slew all of them who were in that place. The rest fled to the low lying sands of •Oman and its desert tracts, where no water is found, imagining he would be unable to reach them there, as the ' Hadhr' Arabs had little knowledge of the routes of those localities, and it would be difficult for them to find the way to their haunts. But Mohammed-bin Xasir followed them even there, anu killed thirty-six of their chief men, and made prisoners of ninetv-five. He also killed their camels and other cattle, and carried the prisoners bound with cords to Yabrin. But Abu-Khark escaped to Maskat and joined tlu- Benu-Hinah. Mohammed-bin Xasir kept the prisoners inBoole Seventh. 7S fetters at Yabrin until they all died. He remained at Yabrin some months after this. Abu-Khark then sent a message to Mohammed-bin Nasir, say ing that in future he would not molest any one, nor commit any depreda tions. And after those occurrences, from that day to this, we have not heard of any one being robbed or ill-treated on any of the roads of 'Oman, from the east of it to the west. Mohammed-bin Nasir then ordered a general levy of all in allegiance to him in 'Oman, from east to west. An immense force accordingly ga thered round him at Yabrin, the number of which God only knows. He sent to the districts of the Benu-Hinah of Wall el-'Ula, and el-Heyl, and Samm, and 'Omla. All the Benu-Hinah submitted and none opposed him. He then proceeded to Yankal, and having encamped on the high ground, sent a summons to the garrison to surrender the Fort to him. They, how ever, refused and prepared to resist. One night, an inhabitant of Yankal named 'Asam came forth, and secretly made terms for himself, saying only, the place was not in his hands. Mohammed-bin Nasir replied, ' Counsel your men to submit, in order to avoid bloodshed.' They, however, would not follow his advice and continued to resist. Now the house of 'Asam was on the wall, in which was a small gateway. 'Asam admitted Mohammed and his followers by this gate into the town, and two of the inhabitants- were slain. They then begged for quarter, which Mohammed granted, but he imprisoned their Sheykhs and carried them off to Yabrin. He left a Wall in Yankal, the inhabitants of which submitted to him. He then marched towards Sohar, and sent forward Rabi'ah-bin Ahmed el-Wahashi. to advise his cousins to descend from the Fort of Sohar. This person, how ever, instead of doing so, when he came to them, advised them to resist firmly. When Mohammed arrived at Sohar, he was encountered by the Benu-Hinah, and a battle was fought in which many of them were slain. Rabi'ah-bin Ahmed was wounded and made prisoner. The Benu-Hinah were defeated and retired into the Fort. Mohammed's army occupied the principal mosque, and he himself took up his quarters in the house of Bin-Mahmud. He then spoke to llabi'ah- bin Ahmed and said to him,' If you wish to remain with us, you are secure, but if you wish to join your companions in the Fort, I will send you in safety.' As he elected to be sent to the Fort, his wish was complied with. Mohammed-bin Nasir had placed twelve men mounted on mares as videttes on the eastern side of Sohar, as he had heard that Khalf-bin Mubarik had collected the Benu-Hinah from el-Rostak and Maskat, and had arrived at the Fort of Saham. Meanwhile Mohammed-bin Nasir had received the submission of all Sohar and its inhabitants, and the lattei, to whatsoever tribe belonging, had received assurances of security and none were molested. With him were Bedouins of the Benu-Yas, and Benu- Na'hn, and their sub-tribes, and also the ' Hadhr.'74 Annals of'Oman. One niglit, a field of millet by the wells of the town was destroyed. The owner complained to Mohammed-bin Nasir, who inquired who had de stroyed his field. He replied, ' the Benu-Yas and the el-Na'im, and the Be douins, and others with you.' He said, ' How much compensation do you require for your field ? take two hundred Mohammedis.' 18 On his refusal he said, ' Take four hundred.' He still refused, and Mohammed-bin Nasir offered five hundred. But the man said, ' I will not be content unless you exact justice of them ?' So he summoned the Sheykhs, and on their presenting themselves, ordered them to be bound to stakes. The man would only accept their being whipped as reparation, so he had them all scourged, and would not heed their appeals to him for mercy until justice had been exacted, when he released them from the cords. Now this was a stratagem of the Benu-Hinah to estrange from him the Bedouins, who then left Mohammed-bin Nasir, and returned to their own lands. As soon as he heard of their departure, Khalf-bin Mubarik attacked Mohammed-bin Nasir with his adherents. The attack was made soon after sunrise, and Mohammed-bin Nasir's followers were taken by sur prise. When the latter was informed of the arrival of Khalf-bin Mubarik, he is said to have remarked, ' This hour is not to us, and not to them, but as God wills.' Thereupon he mounted his mare, and his followers mounted with him, and they encountered Khalf at the gate of the Fort of Sohar. In the engagement Khalf-bin Mubarik was killed, and the Benu-Hinah were defeated and pursued by Mohammed-bin Nasir to the fort wall. There a bullet fired from the Fort above struck him, and his followers car ried him off and he died. 19 Fifteen of his followers also were killed whose names we do not mention. The people of Maskat and el-llostak retired to the latter place. For three days after the burial of Mohammed-bin-Nasir, none but the leaders knew of his death, and the garrison of the Fort of Sohar had well nigh surrendered it. They then returned with the Seyyid Seyf-bin Sultan to Nezwa, and he was appointed Imam of the Musalmans by the Kadhi, on Friday after sunset in the early part of Sha'ban, in the year 1140 of the Hijreh [A. D. 1728.}.Notes to Bool; First. 75 Notes to Book I. 1 (p. 5.) The fourtli Book of the ' Kesh-ul-Ghummeh.' 2 (p. 5.) The el-Azd. The tribe el-Azd (the' Azdites) derives from Darra el-Azd, who according to the Arabian genealogers was in the tenth line of descent from Kahtan. Kahtan begat Ya'rub, who begat Yashjob, who begat 'Abd-el-Shems, or Saba, who begat Kahlan, who begat Zeid, who begat Malik, who begat Xabt, who begat el-Ghauth, who begat Darra el-Azd. 8 (p. 5.) Malik-bin Fahm. The leadership of the Azdites into 'Oman is commonly, as here, ascribed to Malik-bin Fahm, whose pedigree is correctly given to el-Azd. It will thus be seen that he was in the 23rd line of descent from Kahtan. The mention of the younger Darius might lead one to suppose that the immigration of Yemenites to 'Oman under Malik-bin Fahm occurred in the fourth century before Christ. The account also given by the writer of a paper on 'Oman, in the Bombay Government Selections, Vol. XXIV, gives the following account of this event: ' Malik-bin Fahm of the province of Najd, the first native Arabian who entered 'Oman four centuries before the Christian era, came by the route of Yemen, &amp;c.' Now it is generally allowed that the period of Kahtan, the ancestor of Malik, may be fixed somewhere about 700 B. C. Assuming this, it is impossible to believe that Malik- bin Fahm lived at the early period mentioned above. Other and more authentic accounts of Malik also prove that his period was much later. The following biographical notice of that leader is extracted from the Index to Dr. Wiisteufeld's Genealogical Tables. ' Malik-bin Fahm was leader of the Azdites when they emigrated on account of the 'imminent breaking of the dyke of Mareb. He led them first to 'Oman, then to c 1 - ' Bahrain, and finally established himself on the borders of Syria, where he founded the ' kingdom, the government of which through the marriage of his daughter Racash passed rt to the Lakhmidites.' (Reiske, Hist. Arab., p. 8.) The bursting of the dyke Mareb and consequent emigration of Yemen tribes are events which are supposed to have happened in the 1st century of our era or beginning of the 2nd. By some accounts 'Amr-Muzeikia, who was 17th in descent from Kahtan and also an Azdite, was the original leader of the Yemen emigrants, and Malik is said to have arrived in 'Oman later. At all events the probability is that the entry of Malik-bin Fahm to 'Oman occurred in the early part of the 2nd century after Christ. The part he played in the history of 'Oman is probably exaggerated in native popular traditions. 'Oman had in older times formed a province of the Yemenite kingdom under Ya'rub-bin Kahtan. The period ot Persian conquest is, I imagine, unknown. 4 (p 5.) Ka'b was ancestor of a branch of the Azdites called el-Azd el-Shanua, a term signifying the hatred they mutually bore one another. 8 (p. 5.) Nasr-bin el-Azd. This personage has also been named as the leader of the Azdites from Yemen and founder of the el-Azd of 'Oman. {Vide Rev. C. P. Badger's 'Imams and Seyyids of 'Oman,' Intro., pp. VI and VII.) 6 (p. 5.) Malik-bin Fahm appears to have had two brothers Soleym and 'Amr. 7 (p. 5.) Kelbeh meaning ' bitch.' 8 (p. 6 ) Of Ma'add or 'Adnan. All the preserved Arabian genealogies are traced back to one of two ancestois, either to Kahtan or to 'Adnau. Ma'add was the son of 'Adnan, so that the term Ma addite is7G Annals of 1 Oman. included in that of 'Adnanite. 'Adnan being 1 accounted a descendant of Ishmael, this division of Arabian families is commonly called Isma'ilite. The prophet Muhammed be longed to this stock, and was of the 22nd generation from 'Aduan, whose period is placed at about 300 B. C. The great rival division consists of the Arabs of Yemen descended from K ah tan, and these are designated Yemenite or Kahtanite Arabs. Kahtan is often supposed to be iden tical with Joktan of Genesis, but the period of the latter must have been fully 2000 years B. C., whilst the Arabs calculate this Kahtan to have lived 400 years before ' Adnan, or in B. C. 700, leaving a discrepancy of 1300 years. Kahtan is by some Arabic historians asserted to be descended from Ishmael. Arabian historians employ four terms in classify ing the various Arab stocks, and are not in accord in the application of those terms. They are— el-'Arab el-Badiyeh „ „ el-'Aribeli „ „ el-Mota'arribeh (Ajytl+jj) „ „ el-Mosta'ribeh The terms 'Aribeh and Mosta'ribeh frequently are taken to indicate the Kahtanite stock; Mosta'ribeh being applied to the Ishmailites. These divisions also are sometimes designated respectively 'pure' or 'genuine' and 'naturalized' Arabs. Abul-Feda says, historians divide the Arabs into three classes; (1) Badiyeh, (2) 'Aribeh, and (3) Mosta'ribeh. The first were the lost tribes of Ad, Thamud, and Jorham the elder, who were destroyed for impiety in the time of Ad. The second are the Arabs of Yemen descended from Kahtan. The third are descendants of Ishmael, son of Abraham. Another account taken from Ibn-Dihhiyeh divides the surviving Arabs into: 1st, el-'Aribeh, Arabs ' par excellence,' claiming descent from Iram (Aram of Gen. x. 23), son of Shem. 2nd, el-Mota'arribeh, naturalized and not Arabs, descended from Kahtan. 3rd, el-Mosta'ribeh, still less pure Arabs, descendants of Ishmael. I extract yet another account from a note in Chenery's translation of Hariri. ' Shem was the primate of the ' earth after his father, and according to his father's blessing became the ancestor of the ' prophets, all of whom, whether Arabs or foreigners, are of the posterity of Shem. He ' went as far as \ emeu and founded San'a, and settled in the middle region of the earth ' from \ emeu to esh-Sham, possessing the Holy Place. From him were descended Ad 'and Thamud and Tasm and Jedls and el-'Amalik, and the subjects ofYa'rob and Jorhom the elder, who were called el-'Arab el-'Aribeh, because they were 'created speaking Arabic; also the descendants of Ismail, called I^ el- ' 'Arab el-Mota'arribeh, because they acquired the Arabic tongue by settling among the 'former; also el-'Arab el-Mosta'ribeh, who are defined as specially the descendants of 'Adnan.' [Assemblies of Hariri, Chenery, Vol. I, p. 466.] S (P- 6.) Wadi Rekot ? 10 (?• 6.) Ten sons of Malik are mentioned, Honaa being youngest. He appears to have had a grandson named Ferhud. The name Ferahid does not appear in M iistenfeld's collection of pedigrees. (p. 6.) Ll-Shihr. The Esher of Marco Polo, who wrote ' concerning the city of Esher, Esher is a great city * * 400 miles distant from the Port of Aden. It has a king, who is subject to the Soldan of Aden. He has a number of towns and villages under him and administers his territory well and justly. The people are Saracens. The place has a very good haven, wherefore many ships from India come thither with various cargoes; and they export many good chargers thence to India. A great deal of whiteNotes to Boole First. 77 incense grows in this country and brings in a great revenue to the Prince, &amp;c. Ac.' (Chap. XXX\II., Book III., \ ol. 2, Colonel Yule's Edition of Marco Polo), The following information is extracted from- Colonel Yule's notes : Shihr, or Shehr, with the article Es-Shehr, still exists on the Arabian Coast as a town and district about 330 miles east of Aden. * * The hills of the Sheor and Dhafar districts were the great source of produce of the Arabian frankincense. (Vide pp. 378 879, Yule's Marco Polo.) In modern times the port of Makalla appears to have superseded el-Shihr, and the sources of wealth of that port of Arabia have become exhausted. 12 (P- 4-) Mahrah-bin Heidan, from whom the district Mahra was named. The full pedigree is not given, Mahrah being of the 15th. generation from Kahtan. The following notices are translated from Dr. Wustenfeld's Register. ' Some say Mahra-bin Heidan «belongs to the branch Ma'add-bin 'Adnan, others to Codha'a. The family, after 'separation, settled in the coast line of el-Shihr between Yemen and 'Oman, and retained ' the old Himyaric language. The celebrated Mahari camels derive their name from Mahra.' The district of Mahra was at one period in a measure under the power of the Imams of 'Oman. The language is said to be still peculiar to its inhabitants. It is to be remarked that the settlement of Mahra-bin Heidan at el-Shihr was probably earlier than the period of Malik-bin Falun, 13 (P- 4.) The king Dara, son of Dara. An obvious anachronism. The period of younger Darius was about 337 B. C. As from about 300 B. C. to 220 A. D. Persia was under the kings of the Ashkanian dynasty, or the Arsacides, one of that line must have been in power at the time of Malik-bin Fahm. 14 (p. 4.) Marzaban. A Persian word meaning a governor of an outlying province, or ' Margrave.' 15 (p. 4r.) Kalhat. This town was visited by Marco Polo- towards the end of the 13th century, who wrote concerning it—' Calatu is a great city, within a gulf which bears ' the name of the Gulf of Calatu. It is a noble city # * The people are Saracens, and ' are subject to Hormos. And whenever the Melik of Hormos is at war with some prince ' more potent than himself, he betakes himself to this city of Calatu, because it is very ' strong, both from its position and its fortifications. * * * They also export many ' good Arab horses from this to India. For as I have told you before the number of ' horses exported from this and the other cities to India is something astonishing.' * * * * ' The city of Kalhat, says Ibn Batuta, stands on the sea-shore. It has fine 'bazars and one of the most beautiful mosques that you could see any where, the walls of ' which are covered with enamelled tiles of Kashan. * * * Most of them (inhabi- ' tants) are Schismatics, but they canno-t openly practise their tenets, for they are under ' the rule of Sultan Tehemten, Malik of Hormuz, who is orthodox. * * There was ' still a horse tnule at Kalhat in 1517.' * # (Travels of Marco Polo, Col. Yule's edition, pp. 381, 282, Vol. 2.) Ibn Batuta wrote in 1328. In modern times, Kalhat is art insignificant place, but extensive ruins are traced. The Schismatics alluded to by Ibn Batuta were doubtless Ibadhis, then the prevailing sect in 'Oman. The author of the ' Keshf ul-Ghummeh' mentions the rule of Malik of Hormuz as will be seen. In modern times scarcely any horses are produced in 'Oman, except for the Sultan's private stable. 16 (p. 4.) El-Jowf. A term which was applied to the central valley region from 'Oman proper to el-Dhahireh. Mr. Badger identifies el-Jow and el-Jowf, but this is erroneous.78 Annals of 1 Oman, il (p. 5.) The account of the battle has been abridged in translating. is (p. 6.) Aqueducts. In the Arabic ' felej.' They are subterraneous artificial channels, similar in all respects to the ' Kanats' or ' Karizes' of Persia and neighbouring countries. Probably the system was introduced into 'Oman by Persians, 19 (p. 7.) The families here enumerated are all Azdite, and the pedigrees are correctly given. The mention of 'Annan-bin 'Amr-bin el-Azd amongst the contemporaries of Malik-bin Fahm must be an anachronism, the former personage having been in the 10th line of descent only from Kahtan. The Yahmadi family of'Oman derive, I take it, from el-Yahmad-bin Homma. It is more than doubtful whether so many famous Yemenite families settled in 'Oman, as stated by the author. 2° (p. 7.) The el-Azd named it 'Oman, &amp;c. The name is also by some asserted to be derived from a son of Kahtan, named 'Oman. According to this version, when Ya'rub-bin Kahtan established the Yemenite Empire, he conferred the government of two Provinces on his brothers 'Oman and Hadhramowt, and the Provinces were thereafter so named. These two personages are, however, usually thought mythical. The country might have been named by Arabians from the root 'Oman, which has a sense of tarrying or abiding. 21 (p. 7.) The Persians called it ' Mazun.' This statement is borne out by other authorities. 22 (p. 7.) Samah-bin Loweij. This name may be noted as the first mentioned of the Ishmailite branch. Samah be longed to the famous Koreysh family and was of the 14th generation from 'Adnan. The following notice of him is translated from Dr. Wiistenfeld's Index. ' Sama-biu Loweij ' on account of a quarrel with his brother 'Amir abandoned the ' Heimath' and journeyed ' towards 'Oman. In Jowf el-Hamila his camel fell over an 'Arfaja tree (a thorny shrub), ' in which a snake had concealed itself. The snake struck at his leg and bit him sa that « he died. His descendants who were called after his mother ' Beni-Najiya,' dwelt in ' 'Oman in the hamlet of el-Towam.' A portion ultimately settled themselves in Basra, where the Quarter Sama is named after him. 2 3 (p. 7.) El-Jow is the name of the district immediately surrounding Bereymf. 2 4 (p. 7.) As Asd-bin 'Imran was Azdite, this was an intermarriage between the great rival stocks. 2 5 (p. 7 ) El-Sirr. This name has been variously applied. Sometimes it has designated the Western coastline of 'Oman. As here used, its site was apparently some where between Bereymi and the modern Abu-Dhebi. 2 6 (p. 7.) Benu-Iluaheh. There is a strong clan so called now in 'Oman. 2 7 (p. 7.) Nizar. From Nizar-bin Ma'add-bin 'Adnan. '2 8 (p. 7.) Malik-bin Zoheir. This person was not of the Azdite stock, but was of the tribe el-Tanukh whom he led from Nejd to el-Hira in 'Irak. 2 0 (p 8) 'The historian Hamza relates that Malik-bin Fahm wa^ 1 accidentally slain 'by his sou Suleimah, who thereupon fied into 'Oman, where he left a large progeny, « which existed a long time after the rise of Islam.' Imams and Seyyids of 'Oman, Intro., p. VII. Als o ' Salimah-bin Malik shot his father by accident in the darkness, who had himself instructed him in the use of the bow.' Reiske, Hist, Arab., p. 12. [Register zu den genealogischen Tabellen, Dr. Wiistenfeld, p. 408]. The Arabic couplet is a favorite quotation in allusion to ingratitude— ' I taught him archery day by day : when his arm grew strong, he shot me.' 30 (p. 8-) His adventui-es are omitted in translation.Notes to Book Second. 79 3 i (p 9.) El-Mustatir meaning ' the wary.' The descendants of this el-Julanda, who was an Azdite^ appeal- to have assumed the name Benu-Julanda, It is said that each one who became king in 'Oman, took the name of Julanda. [ Vide Imams and Seyyids of 'Oman, p. V]. s 2 (p. 9.) The commencement of the Sassanian dynasty was A. D. 220; it terminated with the Mohammedan conquest. 3 3 (p. 9.) This Book serves as an introduction to the subsequent narrative. The author must have been at considerable pains to collect his materials judging from the paucity of books now in 'Oman. The more ancient Arab historical works are chiefly accounts of famous tribes or families, and the genealogies of important personages are very minutely traced. The science of genealogy was highly elaborate. There were ten recog nized gradations of communities, from the 'people' as a whole down to the 'family' of less than ten persons. The terms used to describe those various classes are analogous to our words, 'race,' ' nation,' ' tribe,' ' clan,' ' kin,' ' family.' But the shades of gradation are more minutely given in Arabic than English can describe. The term ' Kabileh,' answering to our ' tribe' or ' clan' was fourth in the Arab classification. In modern times Arabs have ceased to preserve their pedigrees, and in 'Oman the people know little of their origin. Summarized, the events related in this book are as follows. Yemenite Arabs chiefly Azdite arrive in 'Oman and drive out the Persians, who were previously in posses sion of the whole province. Thenceforward, for a considerable time, the Azdites were sole masters and their chiefs ruled supreme. Later, however, the Persians regained a footing, and at the time of the introduction of Mohammedanism, a Persian deputy was residing in 'Oman, and was subsequently expelled by the Azdite tribes under the descendants of el-Julanda. 'Oman and Bahrain were included in the conquests of the Persian Monarch Khosru Parwiz at the end of the 6th century. Notes to Book II. 1 (p. 9.) Book or Chapter 33 of the ' Keshf ul-Ghummeh.' 2 (p. 9.) The subjugation of 'Oman by the Persians in the time of the Julandaites appears to have been only temporary or partial, as at the commencement of the Mohammedan Era the Julandaites 'Abd and Jeifar were undoubtedly in power. When the remnant of the Persians were expelled, ' Oman did not, however, become an independent kingdom. Its princes embraced the religion of Islam in the time of Mohammed, whose paramount authority they acknowledged. Thenceforward until about 751 A. D., 'Oman was nominally under the KhaUfehs and immediately controlled by the governors of 'Irak. Before the success of Mohammed in 'Oman it is mentioned that one Abu-Basir-bin Asid or 'Otba had retired to the coast of 'Oman [sif el-bahr], and collected round him there those who in Mekka had embraced the new Faith, but they were unable to maintain themselves, and their numbers gradually decreased to 62 or 70. ^ [Nawawi.] 8 (p. 9 ) Daba. There is a small town now named Dibba, north of Sohar. There appears to have been also a place named Daba between Bahrain and 'Oman, where el- Atik-bin el-Asd settled after the emigration from Mareb. Hence the family called Azd- Daba. [Wiistenfeld, Index.] 4 (p. 10.) Abu -Bekr succeeded Mohammed, and was Khali'feh from A. D. 632 to 634. On his accession rebellions occurred in several provinces, 'Oman amongst the number. An expedition was despatched to 'Oman and Yemen under 'Ikrimah-bin Abu-Jahl, who80 Annals of 1, Oman. assisted by the Julandaites 'Abd and .Teifar and other Azdites, succeeded in quelling the rebellion. In a great battle fought at Daba (vide note 3), ten thousand rebels fell, and many were carried into captivity. It is stated that 'Othman-bin Abu 1-A'si was appointed governor of 'Oman and el-Bahrain by Abu-Bekr, and that he defeated and slew a Persian commander named Zohrak at Towwaj. In Mr. Badger's Introduction to the 'Imams and Sayyids of 'Oman/ when these events are summarized, it is stated that 'Othman was appointed by 'Omar (the successor of Abu-Bekr). For incidental notices of the history of 'Oman at this period many Arabian authors may be consulted, amongst them Nawawi, Ibu-Sa'd, Ibn-Koteiba, Beladzon, Abu-Ja'far's Tarikh-el Muluk. 5 (p. 10.) The Nizariyeh as opposed to the Yemenites. For explanation of the term vide Note 57 to Book I. 6 (p. 11.) The Desert Country. It may also be read ' within three days' march' of ' el-Balka'ah.' The latter word, however, means waste, uninhabited land. Probably the country west of Bereymf is meant. 7 (p. 11.) Maskat. In this part of the ' Keshf ul-Ghummeh' the name is spelt whilst in later books it is spelt (maskad). 8 (p. 11.) Julfar. The Persian name for the town on the site of the modem Eas- el-Kheimah. 9 (p. 11.) Zenj. The inhabitants of the East African Coast. Mr. Badger thinks this the most reliable record we possess of the first emigration of Arabs of 'Oman to the east coast of Africa. 1 o (p. 12.) This appointment of a native of 'Oman to the governorship appears to have led to the assertion of independence soon after. (p. 12.) The Ibadhiyeh. This is the first mention of the remarkable Ibadlu sect, which has from this time forward exercised so powerful an influence in 'Oman, and which appears already at this early period to have become predominant there. The sect takes its name from 'Abdullah-bin Ibadh, who flourished according to the author of the ' Keshf- ul-Ghummeh' about A. D. 685-705, but, according to the other works quoted by Badger, A I). 711-719. The sect is undoubtedly an off-shoot of the Kharijite schism. In the year 657 A. D., a large number of the Caliph 'Ah's followers revolted from him, and these received the appellation of ' Khawarij,' i. e. schismatics, or heretics, who went forth from the true faith. In the following year, the Kharijites to the number of 4000 were at tacked and cut to pieces by 'All. Nine only escaped, of whom two reached 'Oman, where they became apparently successful propagandists of the Kharijite doctrines, the most im portant perhaps of which consisted in the positive rejection of the Caliphs or Imams 'Othman and 'AH, and the assertion of the right to elect and depose their Imams. In this and other fundamental points 'Abdullah-bin Ibadh simply followed the Kharijites. It seems probable that the people of 'Oman were imbued with these views before the time of 'Abdullah-bin Ibadh, and were thus prepared beforehand to accept his teaching. In what manner the latter was propagated does not appear. The Ibadhi doctrine as to the Imams may be roughly contrasted with that of the Sunnites and Shl'ahs as follows : 1. Sunnites accept the four successors of the prophet as true Khahfehs, or Imams, and the generally acknowledged representatives known to the present day, when they re cognize the Sultan of Turkey as head of the orthodox. 2. SM'ahs absolutely reject all claims to the Imamate other than those of 'AK and his descendants. At the present time they acknowledge no visible Imam. 3. IbddMs reject 'Othman and 'All and curse them as infidels. They assert the right of true believing Muslims (themselves that is) to elect their Imams, and to depose them for transgressions. The persons successively elected to their Imams by the IbadhisNotes to Booh Third. 81 have also usually been temporal rulers in 'Oman. They were styled u Imam of the Musalmans,' not ' Imam of 'Oman.' It is to be noted that it is not considered indispens able by the Ibadlns to have an Imam at all. An account of the sect is given by Mr. Badger in his work 'Imams and Seyyids of 'Oman.' The ' Keshful-Ghununeh' also supplies some information about it, which has been submitted to Government in a pre vious paper, regarding which vide Proceedings, Asiatic Society of Bengal, for January, 1873, pp. 2 to 10. In the same work may be found some of the correspondence of 'Abdul lah-bin Ibadh. 12 (p. 12.) The first of the Imams probably. 13 (p. 12.) Musalmans, i. e. Ibadhis. 14 (p. 13.) You are my Imam, go before (amam) me. 15 (p. 14.) For meaning of el-Sharf, see Note 13 to Book III. 16 (p. 14.) Wadi Hatta is a valley north-west of Sohar. 11 (p. 15.) Bowarih. According to Mr. Badger, ' Bowarij,' or war-vessels. 18 (p. 15.) Eastern districts, or el-Sharkfyeh. Similarly, the western part of 'Oman is occasionally distinguished as el-Gharbiyeh,' or el-Gharb.' The divisions of the whole Province commonly used by the people of 'Oman are, 1, ' 'Oman proper,' limited to the central region. 2, ' el-SJuirkviieh,'' eastern districts, including Ja'ldn. 3, el-Bdlineh, the plain situated between the mountains and the sea north of Maskat. 4, JEl-Dhdhireh including el-Jow, the tract beyond the hills extending from 'Oman to el-Bereymi. 5, el- Shemdl, the north and west. 6, lastly there are the hill tracts and Wadls not comprised in any of the preceding divisions. The former between el-Batineh and el-Dhahireh are called in plural el-hujur, sing. hejer-el-Batineh, hejer-el-Dhahireh. Each Wadi has its distinctive name, sometimes taken from the tribe inhabiting it. 19 (p. 16.) Accordingly his reign commenced A. D. 808. 20 (p. 17.) He retained the spiritual office whilst deprived of the temporal power. 2 i (p. 17.) Mahrah appears from this to have acknowledged the Imam Muhenna, but the authority of the 'Oman rulers over that district must have been very precarious. 22 (p. 19.) Park is a village a few miles south of Nezwa. Notes to Book III. 1 (p. 20.) Izki, or Azka, now vulgarly named Zikki. 2 (p. 20.) El-Nizar. At Zikki there are two resident families or tribes representing the great rival branches. These families are still called Yemen and Nizar. The attack here described would at the present day be called an attack by the Ghafirfs upon the Hinawfs. 3 (p. 20.) El-Madhariyeh, a term synonymous with Nizariyeh, being derived from Madhar-bin Nizar-bin Ma'ad-bin 'Adnan. 4 (p. 20.) El-Haddan. That is in the mountains between el-Batiueh and el- Dhahireh. 5 (p. 20 ) El-Jow. The district about the modern el-Bereynu. 6 (p. 20.) Sohar was and still is one of the towns where the Imam could perform Friday's divine service. 7 (p. 21.) Benu-Hinah. The name of this clan became celebrated in 'Oman, and gave its name to the whole Yemenite party in later times. Badger refers the origin of this tribe to Hana or Hina-bin 'Amr-bin el-Ghauth-bin Tai-bin 'Odad, a descendant of Kahlan. According to this genealogy, the Benu Hinah, though Kahtanite and Yemenite, were not of the Azdite stock. I am inclined to think the forefather of the Hinai tribe of82 Annals of 1 Oman. •Oman is to be sought amongst the descendants of el-Azd. Amongst the immediate progeny of el-Azd, we find the name el-Hinw, and in the next generation el-Hann. Again, one of the sons of Malik-bin Fahm was named Honaa, or Honat, or perhaps Hinah. There is on other grounds much reason to believe that the Benu-Hinah are an Azdite clan, 8 (p 21.) Mohammed-bin Nur. This name is still a by-word in'Oman. From the detestation in which this person was held, he was dubbed Mohammed-bin ' Biir,' instead of 'Nur,' the former word bearing an evil signification. 9 (p. 21.) The Caliph el-Mo'tadhid-billah reigned from A. D. 892 to 902. 10 fp. 21.) Himyarite, another term for the Yemenites, &amp;c. 11 (p. 22.) Koran, Chap. XIII. 12 (p. 23 ) The Mihrab is the place in a mosque where the priest prays with his face towards Mecca. 13 (p. 23.) As a ' Shari' Imam. This means that the Imam had vowed on assuming office to sacrifice life rather than yield or fly in battle with the enemies of the Faith. Those not so bound were termed Dafl'i Imams. Vide note 28 to Book IV. 14 (p. 24.) As a Dafl'i. See preceding note. 55 fp. 24.) Sultan of Baghdad, i. e the Caliph. The Ibadhis would grudge him the title of Caliph. 16 (p. 24.) The Karamitah, or Karmatians, a sect very inimical to the Moham medans. They turned the precepts of the Koran into allegory. They caused great disturb ance, and under Abu-Dhahir took Mecca {vide Sale's Koran, p. 130). 17 (p. 24.) Abu Sa'id. De Sacy styles him ' Abou-Sa'id Hasan, flls de Behram, surnomm^ Djenabi, parce qu'il dtait de Djenaba.' Abulfeda says, Junnabah (or, as Ibn Kballikan writes it, Jannabah), is a small town of el-Bahrein, from whence sprang Abu-Sa'id el-Junnaby, the libertine, the Karmuty, who attacked the Hijj and killed many of them. Imams and Seyyids of'Oman, p. 28, note 1. 18 (p. 24.) Probably the creditors would object to his devoting himself to death until their claims were satisfied. Notes to Book IV. 1 (p. 25.) Mr. Badger's author, Sah'1-bin Razik, has the following statement here— ' 11)71 Kaisar says : I have not been able to find the date when allegiance was given to him [Sa'id-bin 'Abdullah], nor how long he retained the Imamate.' I have not been able to discover who Ibn Kaisar is, but Salfl-bin llazik's quotations appear to be from the ' Keshf ul-Ghummeh.' I once questioned Salil-bin liazik concerning the authorship of the ' Keshful-Ghummeh,' but he was then very feeble from age, and could not inform me. 2 (p. 25.) Vide note 13, Book III. Mr. Badger has in his work—' This appoint ment also was made in spite of much opposition.' 3 (p. 25.) That is, the Ibadhi faith. 4 (p. 27.) I am sorry I cannot make the preceding account more clear, the original is very obscure. 5 (p. 27.) Saluted him as Imam. That is, recognized the fact of his election without positively swearing fealty. 6 (p. 27.) Sadakat, voluntary poor-rate. 7 (p. 28.) As Sultan. The term means probably as temporal ruler, and was not used as a title. That of Imam would include the other. 8 (p. 28.) What follows is inconsistent with the previous statements, but such incon sistencies abound in most Arabic writings.Notes to Boole Fourth. 83 9 fp. 28.) The quotation is from a religious work. It is one of the verses alleged by the SM'ahs to have been abstracted from the original Koran and suppressed. They take it to point to the oppressors of 'AH and his descendants. i o (p. 29.) Kadam, Between Bahla and el-Homra. » i (p. 29.) Wadi el-Nakhr. About 2 hours west of el-Homra. 12 (p. 29.) Takiyeh. 13 (p. 30.) The history of this period is confused and defective, probably because the standard Arabian works contain no accounts of this portion of 'Oman history. Hence forward the Caliphs seem to have lost their hold on 'Oman. 14 (p. 31.) The dates are confused and unreliable, and several of the Imams are, as will be observed, introduced out of their chronological order. 1 5 (p. 31.) The year is not stated. i 6 (p. 31.) That is, from Mohammed-bin Khanbash to Malik-bin el-Hawari, from A. D. 1162 to A. D. 1406. 1 1 (p. 31.) The government of at least a portion of 'Oman had fallen after the time of Mohammed -bin Khanbash into the hands of the Benu-Nebhan, who were descended from another stock than the Azdites, though also Kahtanito. Their progenitor appears to have been Nebhan-bin Amr-bin el-Ghauth-bin Taa. The Princes of this family were never elected to the religious office of Imam, but were called ' Maliks,' or Lords. They were strongest in el-Dhahireh, and probably none of them reigned supreme over entire 'Oman. Their power lasted more or less to A. D. 1617, or for nearly 500 years. At the present day, no clan of 'Oman is poorer or more despised than the Nebaheneh. J s (p. 31.) At that period Abaka Khan, son of Hulagu Khan, was monarch of Persia, 19 (p. 31.) Kalhat, vide note 5, Book I. 20 (p. 32.) Dhafar. Marco Polo says of Dhafar—' Dufar is a great and noble and ' fine city, * * * The people are Saracens and have a Count for their chief who is 'subject to the Soldan of Aden * * * Much white incense is produced here, and I ' will tell you how it grows. The trees are like small fir trees; these are notched with ' a knife in several places, and from these notches the incense is exuded. Sometimes « a i S o it flows from the tree without any notch ; this is by reason of the great heat of the ' sun there. * * * This Dhafar is supposed to be the Sephar of Genesis, x. 30.' [Colonel Yule's Marco Polo, pp. 379-80, Vol. II.] 2 i (p. 32.) Dinar, A gold coin weighing 7U barley-corns [Lane]. 82 (p. 32.) Owlad el-Reis, or the Riayeseh, a tribe inhabiting a district west of Sohar. 23 (p. 32.) The Malik or Lord. 24 (p. 32.) Seyyid. This term, here occurring for the first time, means,Prince or Lord or Master or Noble. In 'Oman it is prefixed to noble names as a ' handle.' At the present time, the Ruler of 'Oman is styled the Seyyid ' par excellence.' 23 (p. 32.) See note 17. 26 (p. 32.) According to Badger, an Azdite. 27 (p. 32.) According to Badger, also an Azdite of the el-Yahmad. 28 (p. 32.) The term employed is el-Shurat, which was applied to the Khanjite schismatics, because they said, 'We have sold ourselves iu obedience to God for Paradise, when we separated ourselves from the erring Imams.' [Lane's Lex., Art. J- )e singular ' Shan,' we have seen applied in a peculiar sense to the Imams, vide note 13 to Book III. . - . 2 9 (p 33.) The priest el-Khaleyli, the Imam 'Azzan's Samuel in later days, when wishing to perpetrate a similar spoliation, appealed to this period of 'Oman history as precedent and justification.84 Annals of 1 Oman. 30 (p. 33 ) Koran, Chap. II. 3 1 (p. 34.) At Nezwa. 3 2 (p. 34 ) It must have been during the reign of Mohammed-bin I small that the Portuguese under Alfonso di Albuquerque captured the sea-port towns of 'Oman. Maskat was taken in A.D- 1508. There is no mention of the advent of the Portuguese in ' Keshf ul-Ghummeh.' 3 3 (p. 34.) ' Zekat' and ' Sadakat' are both terms denoting religious alms. The former however is obligatory. 34 (p. 35.) Jeziyah, or capitation tax. 35 (p. 35.) The sentiments are in accordance with modern enlightenment. In the East, under native rulers, such principles are seldom acted on. 36 (p. 35.) Kharaj, or land tax. Notes to Book V. (p. 35.) Makinat. So in the original, but generally spelt Makam'yat. (p. 36.) Mohsiu Sultan Fellah Mudhaffar Tahyas Sultan 'Arrar (Prince of Dhahireh) Makhzum (Yankal) Nebhan Suleiman 3 (p. 37 ) Or Bilad-Seyt. 4 (p. 37.) The narrative is very involved. 5 (p. 37.) Amir. The term was employed in 'Oman in some cases to denote the chief of a powerful clan. 6 (p. 39.) The clans of 'Oman, when 'on the war path,' march with drums beating and banners flying. 7 (p. 40.) The original is very obscure. 8 (p. 42.) Doubtless a Portuguese vessel. The author seems to avoid mention of the conquests of the Portuguese in 'Oman as much as possible. It would appear, however, that at this period the Portuguese had not possession of Sohar. Notes to Book VI. 1 (p. 45.) ' The true sect,' i. e. Ibadhi. 2 (p. 45.) Any one Avho has had much to do with 'Oman politics must allow that there are several true points in this description of the native character. 3 (p. 46.) ' Bedu' and ' Hadhr.' The Bedu, or Bedouins, are the pastoral Arab i inhabiting the great plains, and partly nomadic. The Hadhr are the dwellers in towns and villages and cultivated lands, the fixed, working, or agricultural population. The Bedd exercise much influence in 'Oman. 4 (p. 46.) Nasir-bin Murshid appears to have been the first Imam of the Ya'rabi family.Notes to JBooJc Sixth. 85 kattli 3 (p. 46.) Now called Al-bu-Sa'Id. The family of the present Seyylds. 6 (p. 47.) The Benu-Riyam inhabit the Green Mountains, ' Jehel el-Akhdliar.' Mr. Badger considers them of Mahrah origin. At present they belong to the Ghafiri division. 7 (p. 48.) Mr. Badger says—'The Benu Hilal I take to be descendants of Hilal, one of the four sons of Amir-bin Sa'asa'ah (born about A. D. 381), a descendant of Ma'add and Adnan, &amp;c.' (Imams and Seyyids of 'Oman.) 8 (p. 48.) 'Ibri or 'Obri. A town in el-Dhahireh, which was visited by Wellsted, and where he had a bad reception. There is also a tribe or clan, named el-'Ibrim. Whe ther the clan takes its name from the place or vice versa, I cannot say. The root of the name is the same as that of Heber, from which ' Hebrew.' The siguification is ' on the other side.' The Latin form of the same word is Iber (Iberes, Iberian), equivalent to trans-ultra, &amp;c. (Types of Mankind.) 9 (p. 50.) The Portuguese. * o (p. 51.) El-Ruleh. The banyan tree, Ficus Indica. 11 (p. 51.) Shi'ahs. Probably Persians. 1 2 (p. 51.) El-Sir to be distinguished from el-Sirr, was another name for Julfar, now Eas el-Kheimah. 13 (p. 52.) El-Efrenj, or Franks, meaning Portuguese, no doubt. 14 (p. 52.) The narrative here suddenly terminates, but we may assume the attack on Sohar failed. 15 (p. 52.) About 20 miles from Maskat, noted for its hot mineral springs. 16 (p. 53.) El-Ahsa. A district of Xejd, called vulgarly Lahsa. 17 (p. 53.) Benu-Lam. The ' Benu-Lam' are a branch of the great Tai tribe, and therefore of Kahtanic origin through Kahlan; for Lam, born about A. D. 470, was the descendant of Tai, the descendant of'Odad, the descendant of Kahlan (Badger's Seyyids of 'Oman, p. 67 note). Until subjugated by the Wahhabls, the Benu-Khalid were the most prominent tribe on the Arabian shore of the Persian Gulf. (Ibid.) i 8 (p. 54.) The term used is el-Shurat, vide note 28, Book IV. 1 9 (p. 55.) In Badger's work, the date is A. H. 1059, or A. D. 1649. 20 (p. 55.) No details of the capture of Maskat are given, but Mr. Badger's author has a long and detailed account of the matter, derived apparently from the popular legends. One story current is that the Arabs entered Maskat in the guise of peaceful peasants, hiding their arms in bundles of fire wood, and that they took the opportunity of the Portuguese garrison being assembled without arms at chapel to attack and massacre them. The Portuguese residence, or Factory home, is called by the Arabs el- Jereza ( for Igrezia, or church). Mr. Badger has mistaken the word for Jezirah or ' Island,' which it closely resembles in the Arabic. Sultan-bin Seyf commenced to reign A. D, 1640, and died on 4th October, 1680. The date of the Portuguese expulsion is stated by European authorities 1650 or 1658. The present work does not enable us to fix it more accurately. ' In anno 1715, the Arabian fleet [meaning the Imam's] consisted of one ship of ' 74 guns, two of 60, one of 50, and 18 small ships from 32 to 12 guns each, and some ' Trankies, or rowing vessels, from 4 to 8 guns each, with which sea-forces they keep all ' the sea coasts from Cape Comorin to the Red Sea. They have often made ' descents on the Portuguese Colonies on the coast of India, destroying their villages and ' farms, but spare the churches for better reasons than we can give for plundering them. mmm86 Annals of'Oman. ' They kill none in cold blood, but use their captives courteously. In anno 1695, they ' quarrelled with the Carnatick llajah, a potent Princely lord. Yet they came with their ' fleet and plundered and burned the towns of Barsalore and Mangalore, two of the best ' and richest towns on that Coast.' [The above is from Captain Alexander Hamilton's ' New Account of the East Indies.' He travelled from 1688 to 1723, and is therefore a valuable authority for this period.] 2 1 (p. 56.) Jezfret el-Khadhra, or Pemba. Notes to Book VII. 1 (p. 59.) Body of horsemen. The term used is ' sariyeh,' which means a party of from five to three hundred or four hundred. 2 (p. 59.) Sahib el-'Anbur. A title or a nick-name. ' Anbur in 'Oman sometimes means a purse. 3 (p. 60.) Koran XXIX, 1, Sale's translation. 4 (p. 60.) Benu-Ghafir. The origin of the appellation of this tribe seems unknown, but they are undoubtedly Ishmaelite or 'Adnanite, and were therefore naturally opposed to the Yemenites or Kahtanites. As will be seen further on, under their able and brave chief, Mohammed-bin Nasir, this clan became renowned and powerful in 'Oman. This chief headed the faction against their rivals the Yemenites, who also found a skilful and courageous leader in Khalf-bin Mubarik, the Dwarf, chief of the Benu-Hinah. This civil war was one of the fiercest recorded in the annals of 'Oman, a great number of the clans ranging themselves under their respective leaders, declaring either for the ' Hinal' or ' (rhafiri.' Those faction terms have survived to the present day, and almost entirely supersede the older classifications, the rival factions being now termed el-Hinawiyeh and el-Ghafiriyeh. This is the explanation of the undue pre-eminence assigned by European writers on 'Oman to these two tribes, whose importance was accidental and temporary. For a time the Ghafiris gained the day, and their chief became Imam, but the Hiiiawis soon regained the ascendancy. At present, the power of the two sections is tolerably evenly balanced, the Ghafiris preponderating in the West and their rivals in the East. It is to be noticed that at the present day the fact of a clan styling itself of the Hinawf or the Ghafiri faction does not necessarily prove its origin to be Kahtanite, or Ishmaelite; for several Yemen tribes have ranged themselves with the Nejd- ites and vice versa. This fact occasions additional difficulty in tracing tribal genealogies. 5 (p. 60.) See Note 1. 6 (p. 61.) The names Yemen and Mzar here apply to viyh I families so called, not to factions. 7 (p. 63.) Koran, XIII, 12. 8 (p. 63.) Birkeh. This name is sometimes written so and sometimes Barka. In the Kamus it appears as ' Birket el-Rameys.' 9 (p. 63.) ' Did not understand Arabic.' Probably these were some of the people inhabitingthe Ruus el-Jebel from Cape Mussendom. Southward the inhabitants of that loca lity differ in appearance from the other Arabs and speak a different dialect. Some, from their reddish skins and light eyes, have conceived them to have an admixture of European blood. On examination their language will probably be found to be a Himyarite dialect. They may be descendants of a Himyarite people who inhabited 'Oman before the inflow of Yemenites and others. They are named el-Shehuh or el-Shihiyln. C^pe Mussendom has been identified with 'the promontory of the Asabi' of Ptolemy (by Forster), and the Asabi or Sabi with the Seba or Sebaim of Scripture. In accordance with this theory, this part of 'Oman was originally the seat of Cushite colonies,Notes to Boole Seventh. 87 in witness of which are adduced the names ' Cuscan' (Cushan of Hebrew writers), [probably meaning Khasam] and a littoral termed by Pliny ' the shore of Ham,' ' Litus Hammeum,' now Maham, (?), adjacent to which is a ' Wadi Ham,' ' Valley of Ham'' (Types of Mankind). Again ; ' Ramss, an Arab port, just inside the Persian Gulf, perfectly answers to the sites of Raamah, catalogued among Kushite personifications in xth Genesis {ibid.).' 10 (p. 64.) About six miles from Barka. 11 (p. 65.) The prisoners were sometimes placed in exposed situations during a siege or battle to slacken the enemies' fire. 12 (p. 67.) Al-Walubeh. A numerous, powerful, and warlike Bedouin clan of Sharkiyeh. 13 (p. 67.) 'The Benu-IIindh and their allies' would be more accurate, but at this period the term Hinai began to be used in its modern extended sense. 1 ^ (p. 68.) The el-Harth is the richest of the Hinawi tribes of the eastern districts. Many of this family inhabit Zanzibar. 15 (p. 68.) El-Na'im. The dominant tribe of el-Jow and Bereyim. 16 (p. 70.) MaghriM meaning Nejdean. 1 7 (p. 70.) Tenuf. A town of the Green Mountain. 1 8 (p. 74.) A Mohammedi is about three pence. 1 9 (p. 74.) The election of Mohammed-bin Nasir to be Imam was evidently a forced measure and adopted only because of the great power he wielded as a warrior and ruler. His military genius seems to have surpassed that of any previous Imam or governor of 'Oman, and he had well nigh become by sheer talent and energy supreme over all 'Oman. The restless energy of this Prince was imitated, for a time with much success, by the late 'Azzan bin-Kais. r M</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023549653.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>W20/5476</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023549653.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Printed Collections</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>W20/5476</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Annals of 'Omān'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1874/1874</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-11-03T13:58:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (88 pages)</extent><extent>There is a table of contents at the beginning of the volume.</extent><extent>Conditioning: there is a loose unpaginated map at the end of the book.Dimensions: 235 mm x 160 mm.Pagination: 1-87.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Annals of 'Omān.The book is written by Sirhān-bīn Sa'īd-bin Sirhān of the Benū 'Alī tribe of 'Omān; translated and annotated by Edward Charles Ross, Political Agent at Muscat. Reprinted from the Journal, Asiatic Society of Bengal, for 1874, part 1, no 2.There is a loose map at the end of the volume 'A Revised Map of Oman and the Persian Gulf'.Publication Details: Calcutta : pr by G. H. Rouse, Baptist Mission Pr., 1874.Ownership: With stamps of the Bedford College Library and Sir Charles Umpherston Aitchison.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>The Asiatic Society</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sirhān bin Sa‘īd-bin Sirhān</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Edward Charles Ross</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>George Henry Rouse</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023549653.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>