<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00016e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:22:35.623Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00016e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/323</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00016e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/323</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/1 V Claims and complaints'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-13T22:27:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (324 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at inside back cover with 326; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Additional foliation sequences are present in parallel between ff 3-60, ff 129-160 and ff 195-215; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is present between ff 2-326 and is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains letters and correspondence between various merchants and suppliers of goods, primarily building materials and manufactured equipment, relating to claims of unpaid bills, damaged goods, and other trade disputes. Most of the papers are exchanges between Kuwaiti merchants and the Political Agency in Kuwait. A minority of the papers are those relating to merchandise suppliers to Kuwaiti businesses, mainly in the United Kingdom, Iran or Iraq.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Trade disputes</topic></subject><subject><topic>International trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00016e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>