<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000292_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T14:14:50.085Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Q v N©. 45-C of 1930. political Agency Consulate, Muscat, the 5th April 1930. tfrom To Major Gr.P. Murphy, I.A., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M*3 Consul, MUSCAT. The Hon’ble the Political Kesident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire, ' 1 t ^ Sir, I have tne honour to forward, nerewith, for your consideration, a letter from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman requesting that tne contract of Mr. B.S. Thomas O.B.JS., with the State which expired on the 1st of April may he extended for a further period of 3 years. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political At;ent H.B.M* s Consul, ^ MUSCAT.(J -Letter dated 19th Shagal 1348 ( 21st March 1930) Sir from His Highness/Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal, C.8.I., bultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, to Major O.P. Murphy, I.A., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat^ After Compliments, I deem it necessary to inform you that I and *azir Thomas have mutually agreed that he ( Mr. Thomas) should continue his services to my Government for a period of 3 years in accordance with the previous agreement ana on the same terms as laid down in that agreement. And as it is not hidden to you that we have been obliged to emplpy him for my Government in his present post, I request you to represent this matter to ray friend the Government and inform them of our agree ment and I hope that they will accord their sanction as they did before. I intended to maice the new period for 5 years but he did not agree to it and did not concur with me. U.M. —oOo — --------© Letter aated. i'Jth tihawai 104 b (kiret ^arch i9ou) iroia i.II.Sir Sai^id Taiiuur bin j?aieai, K.C.I.L., C.S.T., buxtan Ui muscat i: Oraan, to Major G.P.Murptiy, I»a. » rolitrcal Agent L H.B.H’s Consul, Muscat. A. C • I dcen it necessary to iniorm you that I ana V'azir Thomas have mutually agreed that he (Hr.Thomas) should continue his services to my Government lor a period or 5 years in accordance with the previous agreement ana on the same terras as laid aov/n in that agreement. And as it i$ not hidden to you that we have been obliged to employ him lor ray Government in his present post, I request you to represent this matter to my iriena the Government and iniorm them oi our agreement and r hope that they will accord tneir sanction as they aid del ore* i intended to maice the new period lor b years but he did not'agree to it and aid not conaui' with my. U. I35/136. / % Telegran Code. Frorii Klgd Corimiss ioner, Baghdad. To Political Besident, Bustiire. No. 196. Bated 3rd reed 4th iuay 1930. * Beference note 'which Ruesell left about Financial Adviser Muscat. Please telegraph conditions of leave or recess in hot weather, 'whether pay is subject to income tax, any details regarding allowances or easments ana date on vrhich vacancy occurs. High Commissioner. Telegram Coae. From Political Resident, 'Patrick Stewart” To High Commissioner, Baghdad. No. T-79. Latea 6 tn May 1930. Your telegram No.l9^(of »rd May. Matter is at present under cons iaeration. I arrive Simla 19th and will discuss it with Government .of India and wire you aecision arrived at. Resiaent.35/138. Telegram Code. From Pclitical Resident, Busniie. To High Commissioner, Baghaad. No. 507. Bated 29th May 1930. Tn ur &gt;T ^ fl' r,n * 1 - Mj y I discussed matter v/ith Howell and it was aeciced that as he knew many of the officers in Iraq he would write to you himself. I suggested pay Rs 1000/100/1500 and 3 months recess at Karachi. Oil icer required should have administrative rather than political training. Res ident.BY AIR MAIL. Q) |D Oonfitie ntia1. L.O.No.247-3 of 1930. British Residency, Bushire, the 18th June 1930. My dear Wylie, Please refer to your Confidential D.O.No. 1804-N/30 of 5th June 1930 regarding the pay of the Wazir at Muscat. 2. As the Air Mail leaves tomorrow morning and a reply to the points raised in your letter*would involve the despatch of a somewhat lengthy telegram I am sending this hy Air Mail instead. 3. As you are doubtless aware Belgrave's original agreement has been amended ( vide Foreign and Political Department letter No.142 N dated 5th July 1927 ) and he does not now in practice get any recess. He is allowed one month's recess per annum and can accumulate this up to 2 months and add it on * to h/s furlough and this is what all the Bahrain officials now do, i.e. after 2 or 2i years* service , they get 3 month$\ furlough plus 2 months accumulated recess, and also draw the cost of the return tickets to Karachi of which they have not availed themselves, and put it towards their passage home. I do not like this arrangement as 1 think a short recess is good both for a man's body and mind, but am not in a position to alter it. In any case I do not think 7.Wylie Esq.,C.1.E., Deputy Secretary(Foreign) to the G-overnment of India, SIMLA .© - 2 - think it is desirable that the official at Unseat should not take a recess. Muscat nowadays has fewer amenities and a good deal less society than Bahrain, and I certainly think it would he a good thing if the official there went into Karachi at any rate for a couple of months. If, however, he is going to do this then he should get more furlough than the Bahrain officials do, since he will not he able to add recess and li months 1 furlough per annum seems to me very illiberal especially having regard to Gulf conditions. for the above reasons I do not think it is desirable to give the Officer at Muscat the same terms as at Bahrain. On the other hand it must be borne in mind that when the Bahrain contracts were first drafted it was assumed that the officers concerned would remain in the service of the Bahrain State for a prolonged period and in fact would make their careers there and it is for this reason I imagine that the initial pay was low and the rate of increment small. I think 5 years is long enough for any man to stay in Muscat and therefore the contract should be based on that assumption. I would like to modify my original pro posals as follows: a. 2 months* recess at Karachi instead of .3. The Navy told me that Muscat is one of the coolest places in the Gulf during the Monsoon and thereforelf the official-3- official concerned goes on recess for a couple of months before the monsoon breaks he should he able to get through the summer all right. b. The contract might be terminable at 3 months* notice on either side in stead of 6 months* as in the case of Bahrain. c. I do not think 6 months* leave after 3 years is excessive. Bahrain get f 5 months after 2 or 2v years. d. As mentioned above, Bahrain get some assistance towards the cost of their passages home, owing to the fact that they do not take recess. As it is desirable that the Muscat official should take a recess and that no induce- ment should be given to him to forego it, I think the State should give him a passage home. I admit the conditions which I now propose are somewhat more liberal than the Bahrain conaitions, but personally I regard the latter as distinctly illiberal and if we are to get the right stamp of man for Muscat then we must offer somewhat better terms and Justify them on the grounds that Muscat is a worse place to serve in and that a short term of contract is contemplated. Yours sincerely, sd/- H.V.Biscoe.35/138. Telegram Code. From High Commissioner, Baghdad. To Government of India, Simla. Repeated. Political Resident, Busnire. Ho. 247. • Latea and reed 26th June 1930. Important. I am leaving Bagndad 2nd July anji should be very grateful if I might be given immediately full particular of post of Financial Acviser to the State of Muscat which I understand you have discussed with the Political Resident. I may be able to find a suitable candidate. High Commissioner.1 3t&gt;/136. Telegram P. From Political Kesident, Buehire. To High Commiseicner, Bagndad. Repeated Government of India, Eimla. No.565. Fated 1st July 1930. Government of India telegram No.920-H of 30tn June. Thomas‘ contract expired April last, and nothing is laid down about notice required to terminate employment. I consider that as soon as suitable successor iounc Thomas snould be given 3 months’not ice and successor *' should take over in Kovember. Fes icent. I «35/13b. Telegram Code. From High Corarr-lseioner, Baghdad. To Government of India, Pimla. Repeated Political Resident, Busnire. No. 252. dated 1st reed 2nd July 1930. Your telegram No.917-N. I recoir»mena Hedgecock who is being retrenched from iruch red!iced State domain department, where he has been drawing salary of ks 2200/-. In view of hie experience and qualificatlone, with which you are familiar, you may perhape agree he should be brought in at the top of the grade. Particulars by next air mail. Meanwhile I should be grateful if you could let me know if individual named is acceptable, and if so, approximate date when his services would be required. High Commissioner. P]L/SCtf / Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, m\mm it. By order, for Secretary to th^ Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 2nd July, 1930.&lt;§&gt; Telegram Code. From Political Fesident, Buedire. To Government of India, £ imla. Hepeated High Commiesloner, Baghoad. No. 671. lb Bated 2nd July 1930. Higt^ o ■ w - L t: telegram No.252 of let July. One of tne chief re&amp;feone lor dispensing with Thomae 1 services is urgent necessity 1 or retrenchment in Muscat Expenditure. This has been further emphasised by recent heavy fall in dollar exchange. I therefore deprecate any higher salary than rate proposec unless it is impossible to obtain suitable officer on that pay. ■see ident. Post copy forv.araed to the olitical Agent Muscat. By orcer, for vecreta _ bical Resident in the Persian Gulf. Buenire, 2nd July,1930.;, &gt;y 136 . Telegram Code. From Government ot India, Simla. To Political ^eident, Bushire. Ko. 932-N. Dated 2nd reed 3rd July 1930. Demi-Official. Howell to. Biecoe. Deference High Commissioner Baghdad telegram Ko. 252. of 2nd July. I know Hedgecock well and have hign opinion of hie qualities. II he would come on *&lt;. vs 1200/- I think he will be Y/orth taking. \Whole point of change of officers would be lost if we cannot effect some real economy in salary. Foreign. Telegram Code. From Political Fesident, Buehire. To Government of India, Simla. £0. 674. lateo 3rd July 1930. Demi-Official. Biscoe to Howell. Your telegram No.932-H of 2nd July. I quite agree-wide my 671^ o^t think that in view of your opinion of Hedgecock we migut run to 1200/. I imagine living in iyecat is considerably cheaper than in Baghdad, but you are oetter judge of this than I am. Peeident. Post copy forwarded to Political Agent, Muscat By order, for fecretary to tae Political Hesident, in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, ZrdTelegram: Code* From: Repeated: To: No* Government of India, Simla* High Commissioner, Baghdad. Political Resident, Bushire. 492/N. Dated : 4th (received 5th ) luly 1930* Your telegram No*252 of 1st July* We should like to employ Hedgecoek hut ratification by Council of Muscat State will probably be necessary preliminary* In any case we could not contemplate (offering ?) initial salary of ( more ? ) than Rs*1200/ - and that only in consideration of hedgecock’s known abilities and capacity for dealing with Arabs* He would probably be required in Novembe FOREIGNImportant ♦ Telegram, l T o. 917-N. , dated the 28th June 1930. From- Foreign, Simla. To- High Commissioner, Baghdad. Copy to Bushire by Air Mail with the request that Political Resident will telegraph to Hign Commissioner and to tnis office date on which officer’s services are likely to oe required. Your telegram of 26th instant, No.247. Muscat State are likely to want in near future tactful Britisa officer with financial ana administrative experience ana v/orking knowledge of Arabic for three years in first instance on loll owing terms :- (aj Pay &amp; 1000-100-1500. , , f (b; Two months recess at Karachi each year. . / (cj Contract terminable at 3 months notice on either side. (h) (e) Leave -6 months after 3 years. i&gt; ' A 1st Class P.&amp;. 0. B passage home and out after / every 3 years service. (f) Free quarters plainly furnished. Government of Bid ia will oe grateful if y ,u could recommend a suitoale officer from those likely to be retrenched from ’Iraq. *' Baghdad, 6 th July, 1930. To H. E\ trie Hlgrx Commissioner for Iraq, Bagnaaa. Sir, I have the honour to submit this my application for tne post of rinancial Adviser to H. E. Tne bultan oi Muscat, which post will, l understand, shortly ce vacant. My previous experience is as under War service ; from 4/8/14. Lemooilized wita tae rank of Ma.ior. Service in the Civil Administration of Iraq: 12 |- years, mace up roughly as under : 5 years as district official, including nearly 3 years as Political Officer in charge of the Amarah Division, 4 years in tae Ministry of Finance, foi Ig- years of which I held tae appointment oi Revenue Secretary. 3£ years as Director of the State Domains Department unuer tne Ministry of Irrigation and Agriculture. I possess the necessary knowledge of Arabic. My age is 37. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your humble and obedient servant (Sgd.j S. E. Heagcock. wy#' iwwpi — m —■—'■ ■• 1L —p m —«|| p(Mi ||||| |» im3n/128. t- M.-loU f Telegram S’rom To Bepeatea Code. High Comfr.ifesioner, Baghdad. Goverr^rent ol Inaia, Simla. Political Peeident, Buehlre. Ho. 261. ' ~ Dated 9th reed 10th July 1930. Your telegram No. 492-N. Hedgecock If prepared to accept 1200/-. I ehould be glad to knew as soon as possible when appointment Fy confirmed so as to enable him to settle hit affairs Delore proceeding on leave. High CoiiJEie eioner. |. -53. XU; 2«&lt; &lt;3 i Telegram P. From Political Pesidant, Bushire. To Government of India, Simla. No. 0&lt;?O rated 31th July 1930. - Baghdad telegrams No. 261 of 9th July. Sultan in April lest addressee; i ormal letter to Political Agent asking fcr sanction to rttent ion of Thomas* services for further period of 3 years. I suggest Political Agent should now be instructed to inform Multan in suitable terms that having regard to urgent necessity for retrenenment in iiutoat finances Government oi India consider that it would be preierable that Thomas* services should not be extended but that he should be replaced oy an officer on a considerably lowe&lt;salary, and recommend Hedgecock on salary te 120C/1&amp;00 and trust Hie Highness will agree. They suggest Thomas should be given 3 months notice and Hedgecock should assume charge beginring oi Novemcer, As Sultan i- now in India Political Agent {Pight send similar intimation to Council of Ministers, but as Thomas is c ember of the council the come from Sultan. the actual notice shouldPost copy forwaraeG to tne Political Agent, * * Muscat By oraer, ■\ for Secretary to the Political nesident in the Persian Gulf. Bus hi re , llth. July 19.)0./, r?. 1 a i . C . ^ u, w Telegram P. From, Political Resident. To, P.A. Muscat. No. 703. D. and R. 16th July 1930. YaiutxJfcKlKgxxmxls££BXxNax4t5x&amp;xfi£xA|&gt;x±lx5th. Please be good enough to Inform the Sultan,In whatever terms you think appropriate,that Government of India,in view of of the urgent need of retrenchment in the finances of Muscat, consider that It would be preferable that Thomas’ services should not be extended,and that he should be replaced by an officer on a considerably lower sjfalary. There is available a suitable offleer,as his successor,who has a long administrative experience,and a go^d knowledge of Arabic,and who is prepared a to accept the appointment oa salary of Rs1200- rising to Rsl500-. They suggest that Thomas should be given 3 months notice and that his succstssoi- should assume charge beginning of November. They trust that H.B. will agree to these proposals which are made in best interests of the State having regard to serious financial situation. The copy of the letter which you address to H.H. should be sent to Council of Ministers for information. Letter The above has reference to your £*i*gxaiii No.45-C dated 5th April.Telegram P H Prom, P.A. Muscat* To, Political Resident,Bushire. No. 87C. D. 17th July 1930. Reference letter to Sultan. Thomas is close personal friend of Sultan who specially made him not Wazlr (which was T*s original appointment at all) for the specific purpose of looking after his interests. T*8 departure will be in the nature of a bombshell to the Sultan,and if this is intimated to the latter by letter,no matter how tactfully worded,will in all probability produce in reply a declaration of abdication#! venture to suggest that it would be far better for me^ break the news personally to the Sultan when I see him at Dehra Dun and try and convince him (what is the crux from his point of view) that his interests will be equally safe with me (as representing you) as with Thomas. I have reason to believe that he is prepared to regard me as a persona grata . As I propose leaving here on recess by next down mall (vide my telegram of 84C of 9th July),and can see the Suljsan during the first fortnight of August no delay will occur. Reference Thomas' date of departure. I should prefer him to stay until beginning of January for reasons given in my D.O. of 16th July despatched before I received your telegram. December is also thejrf end of the Muscat financial year so his successor could start clear. The above refers to your telegram No.703 of 16th JulyFrom, P*R. Bushire Telegram P. P &gt; To, P.A. Muscat. NO. 710. D. and R. 18th Juxy 1930. I agree that iu would be preferable that announcement to Sultan should be made verbally,and will endeavour to arrange that Thomas should remain till January but cannot say definitely at present. / The above Is in reply to yourXimgr Telegram No.87-0.^ f ^, dj fj 'yj ^v . ) No. I. Q./99. \ ir Ja il 7 Secretariat of H. E. The Hign Commissioner For ’Iraq, Bagnaaa, 8 July, 1930. i • * S ir, I am directed by His Excellency the Acting High Commissioner to refer to Sir Francis Humphry’s * telegram No.252,dated the 1st oi July, 1930^ recommending Mr. S. E. Kedgecock for the sppointment of Financial Adviser to tae State of Muscat, and to transmit the enclosed copy of a formal application for the appointment submitted by Mr. Heagecock. 2. As yo” v/ill observe from tae particulars given in his application Mr. Hedgecock has held a number of very responsible appointments in this country from which he has derived a wide administrative experience especially in the Revenue and State Domains Departments. He has acquired tne reputation of being a most conscientious ana hard working officer. He has. a thorough knowledge of Arabic and during his 12^ years service in the civil administration of this country he has acquired considerable insight into the Arab character His Excellency confidently recommends him for tne. Muscat appointment ana would be grateful if ne could oe informed by telegraph of the decision of the Government of India as Mr Hedgecock is leaving for England in a fortnight's time and desires to make arrangements for the forwarding ox ais kit, if possiole oefore nis ueparture. Secretary To The Government Of India. Foreign and Political Department, S iml a. Tne2- i 1 His Excellency aesires further to arav/ attention to the suggestion contained in Sir Francis Humphry's telegram, that in view of Mr. Hedgecock's qualifications ana of the salary wnicn he has been receiving from tne Iraq Government, he should be permitted to enter on the appointment at the top of the grace. 4. I am sending a copy of tais letter to the Secretary to tne Hon'ble tae Political Besiaent in the Persian Gulf, Busaire. i nave tne honour to be, Sir, Your most ooedient servant, (Sd.) R. S. M. Sturges. Acting Counsellor to H. E. The High Commissioner for ' Iraq.Ho.K/ r of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M *8 Consulate.Muscat. Recess Office at Karachi. July, 31st, 1930. To His Highness Sir Saiyid Tairaur bin Paisal, K.C.I.E., C.S.I Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, C/O Postmaster Srinagar. A.C. I have just received Your Highness’s telegram^from Srinaga - * I have sent Your Highness a telegram that I shall be very pleased to meet you at lahore as you suggested pn^the 2td]t of August and that I am addressing you an important communication C/0 Postmaster Srinagar. 2» The communication is as follows:- I am directed by the Hon’ble the Political Resident to inform Your Highness that the Government of India, in view of the urgent need of retrenchment of the finances of Muscat, WyrtT consider that it would be preferrable that the services of Wazir Thomas should not be extended, and that he should be replaced by an Officer on a much lower salary. As Wazir Thomas’s successor a suitable Officer is available who has a long administrative experience, a good knowledge of Arabic, and who is prepared to accept the appointment on a salary of Rs.1200/- rising to Rs.1500/- per mensem,, The Government of India suggest that Wazir Thomas should be given 3 months notice, and that his successor should assume charge about the » beginning of Nove^iber. The Government of India trust that Your Highness will agree to this proposal which they make in the interest of the State having regard to its serious financial situation. Major, P#A. and H.M’s Consul, Muscat.Telegram From Political Muscat Karachi To Resident Triad Henjam Radio No .K 8 D. 4th August 1930r My telegram K 6 . I have not yet sent to Council of Ministers copy of my letter to Sultan vide your telegram 703 and personally I think it would be preferrable to post pone doing this until I have seen H.H. Do you approve?Telegram From Resident S.S.Vansa Henjam Radio To Major Fowle C/0 Postmaster, Karachi N0.TS98 D. and R. 5th August 1930. Your telegram K 8 I approve.Telegram From Political Agent Muscat (on leave) Ranikhet. To Political Resident Bushire No. Nil D. 16th August 19o0. My telegram K. 6 . I have received a reply from the Sultan which is not quite conclusive. He states that he agrees to the proposal, but adds that he will inform me verbally when we wkmc± meet what his wishes are with regard to the matter. I meet the Sultan at Dehra Dun on 29th inst. and suggest that further action be postponed till I have seen himoTelegram Prom Ismail, Karachi To Major Powle, West View Hotel, Ranikhet Dated 27th August 1930. Following from Resident begins please telegraph result of interview of Sultan Government of India pressing for decision ends.Telegram Prom Major Fowle, Dehra Dun To Resident, Bushire No. Nil D. 30th August 1930. I have seen Sultan whose reception of me was most cordial. He definitely accepts suggestion of Mr. Thomas *s departure hut equally definitely in spite of persuation of my part states that he has no intention of ever returning to Muscat. I will write from Karachi,,H C. Telegram Prom Resident Bushire To Major Powle repeated from Karachi to Ranikhet and from- there to Cawnpore. No.798. D. 31st August 1930. Your telegram unnumbered August 30th.What reason does Sultan give for abdication? Is it Thomas’s departure or any other specific cause.Telegram From Major Fowle, Karachi To Resident, Bushire No.K 26 D. 4th September 1930. j U ( * t Your telegram No.798. During my sereval long coversar tions with the Sultan only specific cause which latter gave was ill health. As, however, he is fit enough to go tiger shotting this excuse hardly holds water. He did not mention Thomas’s departure as a reason and I did not get the impressi that it was. What I did gather was that he heartily dislike Muscat and its responsibility and much prefers the life of a gentleman at large. He said that he was under the impressio that we understood when he last left Muscat it was never to return. Finally I suggested that probably you would like to see him at some convenient spot to which of course he agreed. Despatch follows.Telegram From Major Fowle, Karachi To Resident, Buehire No.K 28 D. 4th September 1930o Your telegram No 0 798. During my several long conversa* tions with the Sultan only specific course which latter gave was ill-health. As, however, he is fit enough to go tiger shotting this excuse hardly holds water. He did not mention Thomas^ departure as a reason and I did not get the im pression that it was. ^iiat I did gather was that he heartily dislikes Muscat and its responsibility and much prefers the life of a gentleman at large. He said that he was under the impression that we understood when he last left Muscat it was never to return. Finally I suggested that probably you would like to see him at some convenient spot to which of course he agreed. Despatch follows.Telegram (code) from Major Fowle, Karachi To Resident, Bushire No.K/35 D. 9th September 1930. As Sultan has now sanctioned Thomas’s departure shall I write letter to Council of Ministers in terms of your telegram No.703 of 17th July adding that Sultan has sanctioned the change. Thomas has just arrived here for dental treatment and is also taking the opportunity to visit Sultan slaJbbog starting perhaps tomorrow evening. I should like to give the letter as t representative of the Council before he leaves to Dehra Dun. Telegram (code) Prom Resident Bushire To Major Powle f Karachi No.819 D. 9th and R. 10-th September 1930. i Your telegram K 35. Bommunication proposed may be made to Thomas as reprepresentative of Council of Ministers. He may be informed date when his succesj^r will arive is not yet settled. It will nfct be earlier than November and may be deferred till beginning of January.N 0 .K /37 l 930 * Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate # Muscat. Recess Office at Karacni. 10th September 1930. To \ Jl&gt; \j^ / T^^o&gt;' 0-^5 ^3 3 -3^3 rY^ V- ^^cfCLV\^ s s The Council of Iffinisters to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. After Compliments. I am directed by the Hon’ble the Political Resident to inform you that the Government of India, in view of the urgent need of retrenchment of the finances of Muscat, consider that it would be preferyab able that the services of Wazir Thomas should not be extended, and that he should be replaced by an Officer on a much lower salary. As Wazir Thomas's successor a suit able Officer is available who has a long administrative experience, a good knowledge of Arabic, and who is prepared to accept the appointment otf a salary of Rs.1200/- rising to Rs.1500/- per mensem. The Government of India suggest that Wazir Thomas should be given 3 months notice. The date when Y»'zir Bhomas' s successor may be expected is not yet settled. It will not be earlier than November and may be defeefed until the beginning of January. I have to add that His Highness the Sultan has agreed to the above change. This letter is being given to Wazir Thomas as representative of the Council# since he happens to be in Karachi at the present moment.This is what had to he said and cA^- 6 ^ s \j2&gt;J^b&amp; *v I salaams• ' Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.35/135. ^ A?-A/ / 4'} fi] ii-ll[to 35/138. B. Political Eesideot, Soshire. Government of India, Simla. September 1930. Important Telegram From To No. 804. Bated 3rd Your telegram No. 2802-S of Slat August. Sultan has definitely accepted suggestion of Thomas• replacement. He has hj^evei' informed at Political Agent^the same time that he does not intend to return to Muscat. I am awaiting detailed report,from Political Agent and will telegraph further regarding this decision, which is apparently unconnected with question of Thomas, and hope that it will be possible to get His Highness to reconsider it. Pegret dela^, , which Las been due to absence of Sultan from Behra Bun. Kesident. Post copy forwarded to the Political &amp;gent, Muscat at Karachi. By order, for Secretary to the Political Aesident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire 3rd September 1930^ c X.JL. 36/135. 35/133 Telegram From lolitioai Koaiuent, BviaUire Governi ©nt of India, Giiula* it To No. 30d. i^atod 4tti September 1950 Isuortani^ Ky telegram of 3rd September Ho.804* Following from Political 4gent Kusoat^ begins:- 'During my several long conversations......... • .despatch follows^ i^nds. 1 propose to await Fowle*s despatch and then to address personal letter to dultan. I suggest that iiedgeooek should now he appointed definitely to sucoeeci Thomas hut Fowl© has represented that as iusoat financial year ends 31st lecemher it would he preferable that :edgeoook should assume charge early January. In view of delay which has occurred and necessity of giving Thomas at least 3 months 7 notice I agree with this view* Easideiit Post cjpy forwarded to the Political Agent, lusoat at Karachi. By order, , for Secretary to %he Political Besident in the Persian Gulf. i^ushire 4th September 1930.35/138. £ rt/o- /^/ Telegram Prom To Repeat eel R. Government of India, Simla# Secretary of State for India, London. High Coimaissioner, Baghdad. Political Resident, P/ushire. No.3049-S. Dated 9th reed 10th September 1930. Your telegram of 5th September No.2856. Sultaa has accepted suggestion of Thomas* replacement. Hodgcock will be required to assume charge early January. Postponement of his appointment till then has been considered advisable for two reasons. (1) It is necessary to give Thomas at least three months notice. (2) Muscat financial year ends on December 31st. Foreign. Post copy forwarded to the Political '.gent, Muscat at Karachi. ,By order, # lor Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf., 1 ^'1 No.K/ 11*] of 1930. “ &amp;} Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate.Muscat. Recess Office at Karachi. )\t&amp; October 1930. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. X I attach herewith copy of letter from Mr. Thomas. Both the annual leave and furlough ^ould appear to be due to Mr. Thomas, The former is part of his annual leave tbiR veer in* the latter he ^ill have earned by the end of December next, provided it is t^o years and 3 months sinee his last furlough concluded. The fact that he is leaving the service of the State on or about that date does^effect the question. This will mean that from the 1 st of January next the State will have to pay for 4i months t^o Financial Advisers; Mr.Hedgecock, the incumbent of the post at Rs.1200/- per mensem, and Mr. r Thomas, the retiring incumbent, at Rs. 2000/-. 4 Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.E0.494-J of 1930. British Residency &amp; ConeuZate~General, Bushire, the 16th September 1930. *Mfs' L IS30 !) Irom - The Hon'ble It.Colonel H^V.Siscoe,I.A. # Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To • The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Sir, With reference to tne correspondence ending with ny telegram Ho,808, dated 4th September 1930, regarding the appointment of successor to Mr.Thomas, at present £asir of the Muscat State, and the 8ultan f s intention, announced to the Political Agent, of abdicating, I hare the honour to state that 1 have since received from aajor Fowls a detailed account of his interview with the Rultan. 2. Raj or Fowl© writes* * His Highness seemed to take Mr. Thomas* departure philosophically, which was convenient. Unfortunately this philosophy was evidently based on the state of mind of benevolent neutrality described by Colonel Trevsr in his letter Jo.236 of 4th October 1921. His Highness 1 present idea is that he has now divested himself of all responsibility for the administration of the State, and thrown it on us, and that he can live at his ease in India on a comfortable allowance/ his hi .hnees* &lt; ebhts on the change of Financial Advisers were apparently as to thethe qualifications of Mr# Thomas* successor, and once I was ahle to assure him on this point his mind seemed at rest* I enclose copies of letters A and B received from him# H 3. I do not think it necessary to forward oopies of these letters to the Government of India* In the first one the Sultan agrees definitely to the Governaent of Indian proposal that Mr* Thomas should be replaced by an officer on a smaller salary and in the second letter he expressed the view that he eho^ld w employ himsell in the political affairs of the Council of Ministers.” 4 # the exact functions to be exercised hy Mr. Thomas 1 successor an*, I think, a matter needing careful consideration and I am not at all sure that it is desirable that he should be a member of the Council of Ministers. Mr* Thomas was not originally a member but was subsequently appointed one. I will address the Government of India later on OflT the subject* 5 # Then, as already reported telegraphically. His Highness informed Major y©wle that he did not intend i-o return to Muscat. Major iowle expressed considerable surprise at this decision and pointed out that His Highness had not mentioned the subject to me at our last m etingi that efforts were being made to improve the finances of the Gtate and to re-establish His Highness* authority at Sur, the two requests that he had specifically made to me. The Sultan was however unmoved by these arguments and alleged the ground oi ill-health. As however he had made arrangements to go tiger shooting in 10 days* time this reason can hardly be regarded as valid, and Major Fowle sums up the position by stating that he hat a 'complex' against Muscat and its responsibilities which he heartily dislikes, and, in his opinion, nothing will remove this complex. He adds howeverif •3* however that it would be &amp; great advantage if we could post pone baiyid Tai«ur ! e abdication for another year and prii.mriiy on financial grounds 1 entirely agree with thie view* 6 . There is one illusion that the Sultan seems to labour under, namely, that the State will be in a position to pay hiin a comfortable allowance for doing nothing and I think it should be pointed out to him that this is not the case* I have therefore addressed him a letter, of which X [dienclose a copy herewith, and have asked him to meet me in -uscat when I go there in November for a full discussion of the whole matter and, as will be seen, have hinted strongly that, ix ne persists in abdicating, the allowance which the tate will be able to afford to pay him will be a very small one* 1 trust that in these circumstances he will see xit to accept my proposal. I will communicate to the Govern ment of India his rsply as soon as I receive it* 7 * 1 am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd/ H.Y.Biscoe Lt* Colonel, .olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf* Copy forwarded, to the political Agent, muscat, at Karachi, for information. AT'fSSY'KD: IFTfit ^/&gt;V Confidential Assistant,No. |y&lt;L Political /*enoy 4c H.B.lt , o conoulato L!u8oat t the 4th November 1930. TO The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushlre. SUBJECT Status of Flnenolal Mvloey * •lemorrndua. With the appointment of a new Financial Mviser the question of his exact status arises. Mr.Thom&amp;s, ae you are aware, though originally appointed as Financial Mviser only, was later given a seat on the Council of Ministers, ^nd was made responsible •with the rest of the Council* for political affairs as well, i.e. for the general administration of the State. Personally I am of opinion, for a number of reasons, that this extra responsibility should not be put upon the Mviser, and I gather that you are inclined to be of the same opinion, vide para 4 of your letter to the Government of India No. 494 . 3 , dated the 16th September 1930. 2. If he is to do hie work thoroughly the Financial Adviser should be free to devote the whole of his time to financial matters. The Council, for Instance, acta as a sort of High Court In serious oases: murder etc. The proceedings of the Court •in Arab fashion* are protracted and the Financial Adviser *as full member of the Council* has to attend the sittings. This is merely one example, there are many others, of the way in which his time Is spent in matters other than finance. Tn this particular instance, apart from the waste of the Mvieer^ time, I doubt personally -though I happen to be a firm believer in capital punishment* whether it is desirable for a British officer, even though in the enq&gt;loy of the Muscat State, to be a party to the infliction of localdeath eentenooe* 3* Our aim again ie to endeavour to make the state stand on its own feet, but thie is difficult with a British officer -the conduct of affairs naturally drifting into his hands- in political charge of the Council. 4« From our point of view a Financial Mviscr in control of the Council, or at any rate fully sharing in its responsi bilities, creates an awkward eituation. The Political Agent is responsible to the Political resident for affairs in general in the Muscat State and should -in my personal opinion- exercise whatever political control is necessary. Yet side by side with him there is another British Officer -the Adviser- who wields as much, and perhaps in some oese^morej influence than he does, roreover, since the Adviser is a British Officer, though in the service of the State, anything which he does is regarded locally as having the sanction of the British Authorities, in spite of the fact that he is an independent official not under British control. 5, Bo much on general grounds. With regard to IT. HedgeoockH appointment. As he will be new to Muscat he will not in any oaee for some time be able to assume political responsibilities and will require all his energies for tackling his financial problems, ^at I venture to suggest is that he:- (a) be given a seat on the Council -this would seem advisable to give him the necessary prestige# (b) have the title of ffeair -which merely indicates that he is such a member, (c) but have responsibility for financial ailaire onljr -the rest of the Council carrying on the general administration. Thle change of status would he explained to the Council officially* At the same time, if you see fit, a hint might he given to Sayid Said that In political matters no important step ehould he taken without Informing me. T an cure thathe would be ready to do thle # ae we get on very well and T think that he hoe taken &amp; liking for ae« I erhape you would oare to dieouBB the matter on your approaching rieit to miecat* _ ' ^ ~ajor f lolitioal Agent &amp; H.B*M f B coneul. Muscat* ‘C i 6* p* s * Since signing the abo^re Sy^d Seid hae, entirely on his own initiative, asked for an interview with me, and asked my advice on voriou© matters* This bears out my assumption that he would be ready to consult me*Letter Kaz unnumbered dated 1st tlovember 1930 from the Council of Ministers to H.H.the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman to Major T.G.Fo^le, C.E.E., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M*s Consul, Muscat. A. C. have received your letter No. 37 dated the 10th September 1930 through Mr. Thomas, the Finance Minister, and were acquainted with its contents. You h&amp;xz intimated that you have been directed by the Political Resident to inform us that in vie^ of the entrenchment of the finances of Muscat State the Government of India propose that no extension should be given to the services of Mr. Thomas and that another suitable Officer should take his place at at a less pay. That the (ne w ) Oficer has a good knowledge of Arabic and is to accept the appointment at Rs.1200/- per mensem rising to Rs.1500/-, that 3 months notice should be given to Mr. Thomas and that H.H. trie * Sultan has agreed to this change. -e concur with the proposal of the Government of India as it is to the benefit of the Muscat State and appreciate this idea and have no oojection. Mr. Thomas the present Finance Minister has been informed of it.m * Telegram Code Dated 6 th November 1930. From Resident, M Patrick Sewart* E No To Political, Muscat 0-113 Please consult and wire decision of Muscat Government on the following points regarding Hedgecock:- (1) Should he arrive last week of December to take over personally from Thomas. (2) Can he come out overland being paid actual travelling expenses subject to maximum cost of 1st Class B P &amp; 0 fare to Muscat. (3) Will his wife’s passage to Muscat be paid from the date of departure from England or from the date of assuming charge. Colonial Office practice is to give half pay from former date. Hedgecock understands that if he comes earlier overland he will not be entitled to pay for period prior to date on which he would otherwise have sailed by P &amp; 0» I favour answering first thfee points in affirmative and fixing pay from the date of assuming charge but questions are primarily ones for decision of the State.Telegram Code I From Political, Muscat. To Resident ’♦Patrick Stewart' Bushire Radio No. 1076 Bated 8 th November 1930. Muscat Government agree that Hedgecoek ( 1 ) should arrive last week of December (2) That he can come over land ( 3 ) That his wife’s passage to Muscat will be paid from date of his departure from England. I am not clear as to exact meaning of your last para and so have not yet put it up to Council. Is it a question/ as to whether Hedgecock will receive half pay from date of departure from England to date of assuming charge here, but that you are in favour of his receiving no pay until he takes over charge?Telegram Code Your No.1076, 8 th November. do n i) Assumethat) in fourth paragraph correct. But matter may be left to Council for decision.Dated i Code. Political, Muscat. Resident, Patrick Stewart, Bahrain. 1084 11th November 1930 Your telegram No.T*129. Council will pay Hedgecock from date of charge here but not half pay from date of v e from England. In view of fact that State ng Mrs. Hedgecock f s passage as well as Hedgecock my opinion is as much as can be expected. DatedDEMI- OFFICIAL. hA\ Off ice in of the Political Pesident the Persian Oulf, Camp, Kuwait, 6th November 1930. D.0. No. 26-T. lysux^f In continuation of ny telegrac No. T-113 of today 1 s date regarding Heagcock I enclose copy of two demi-official letters from the India Office, No. P.6Q22/30, dated ICth October. Major T.C.W.Fowle, C.B.F., Political Agent, Muscat.BY AIR HAIL. India Office, P.6922/30. Whitehall, S.W.l 10th October, 1930. Appointment of Mr.Hedgcock as Financial Adviser, Muscat. My dear Biscoe, Hedgcock mentioned yesterday that he under stood he was required to arrive in Muscat at the beginning of January, and that Thomas was being given three months* notice from 1st October. He was anxious to know whether any objection would be seen to his arriving in Muscat before Thomas had actually left. If not, he would be willing to reach there in the last week of December, so that he could have an opportunity of comparing notes with Thomas and taking over from him personally. Would you be so kind as to let us know if any objection is seen to Hedgcock acting as he suggests. Yours sincerely, sd/ J.G.Laithwaite The Hon T ble Lieut-Colonel H.V.Biscoe,I*A., Bush ire.P. 6922/30 India 0 fice, Whitehall,S*W # 1. 10th October 1930 My dear Biscoe, With reference to previous correspondence between you and the Government of India as regards the appointment of a successor to Thomas as Financial Adviser, Muscat, I enclose copy of a demi-official letter, dated 5th October from Hedgcock, in which he raises three points. As regards the first point, there seems no objection to his travelling via the Gulf, and possibly definite advantage, in that he might be able to call at BusMre on his way out? Subject to your observations, we think he might be told that there is no objection, and that he will be reimbursed actual travelling expenses, possibly subject to a maximum of the cost of a first-class Tt B w P. &amp; 0. fare to Muscat, Point 2 ,- Our Financial Department advise that while we do not normally give free passages to wives in the case of short-term contracts, we have on occasion done so where it was desirable to get a man who stood, out -or t^is concession. Hedgcock has represented personally that he will draw a substantially smaller salary in Muscat than he has been drawing in ’Iraq, and that, ashe has three cniidien who are now being educated, the terms which he has accepted will leave very little margin. It is possiole, in oiiese circumstances, that Muscat may be willing to pay his wife’s passage, and we are inclined to think ti.au he ccneessioa, •? -p Hon.Lieut-Col. H.V.Biscoe,1.A., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire.- 2 - if they see no objection to granting it, would be not unreasonable• i-'Oint The financial Department here advise us that the normal Indian practice is that pay shall start from the date of assuming duty. The Colonial Office, on the other hand, I understand, normally pay half pay for the period of the voyage from the date of embarkation. Having regard to Hedgcock’s circumstances, there is per haps sane thing to be said, if Muscat sees no objection and the money can be found, for ps ying him at the half rate on the journey out, subject to the condition that he shall not be paid for a longer period than would have been taken had he travelled by P. &amp; 0. to Muscat. As all the points involved are matters for decision by the Muscat authorities, who will have to bear the expenditure involved, and as there is very little time to spare, I have ventured to write direct to you about this. 7/e should be very grateful if you would be so kind as to telegraph a reply, which we can pass on to Hedgeock. 7/e are sending a copy of this letter and its enclosure to Howell. Yours sincerely, sd/- J. G. Laithwaite( P.6922/30 ) 6, Shinfield ^oad Reading. 6th October, 1930. My dear Laithwaite, I should be very grateful if you could obtain for me a ruling on the following three points. (D According to the terms of my engagement, I am entitled to a 1st class B cabin F* &amp; O.fare to Muscat. By travelling via Baghdad and by the slow mail down the Persian Gulf, I could pick up my kit at Baghdad and also, should he wish it, visit the P.R. at Bushire. I presume that there would be no objection to my travelling by this route instead of by P. Sc 0. As to do so would be partly for my own convenience, I should not expect to draw from the Muscat S’ Treasury more than the cost of the P. Sc 0. fare mentioned above. (2) May I assume that my wife’s passage will be paid to Muscat? As Thomas was unmarried, and drew a much higher rate of pay than I shall be drawing, no precedent exists. (3) ’.Vill my pay start from the day I leave England for Muscat? In this connection I may mention that the date originally fixed was postponed for two months owing to difficul ies in obtaining the Sultan’s consent to my appoint ment. It is understood. that, should I travel by the over land route, I shall not be entitled to pay for any period prior to the sailing of the P#&amp; 0. which I should otherwise have taken Yours sincerely, sd/ S.E.HedgcoekTelegram* From* To* Ho* Dated * i ^ /L '0 G*T«C• m EISCOE, Patrick Stewea-t.' r&gt;ecectary of State for Io&lt;iia l London. M&amp;R Tt3i 12 th November 1D30* Lalthwaite*s demi-official letter Ho.I*692r/ 30 of 10th October 1930* Hedgcock. Muscat Government agree 1* that he should arrive last week in December* 2 * that he can coxae out overland being paid actual expenses subject to maximum of cost of first class B. !#&amp; 0# fare* 3 . that his wife's fare should he paid. In view of fact that his and his wife's fiarea are being paid and acute financial stringency State are no£. willing to give half pay during journey. . BlSCOiS - • • • • • V Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 12-11-30.C ONF id: kt iai . U ■ Hi D. 0. No. 46-T. of 1920. Of!ice of the Political Resident in the Perisn Gulf. I.O.^.S. 'PATRICK STEWART', 11th November 1920. I notice from your diary that Thomas has gone on six weeks’ local leave. I have not got his con- -tract here, but Croning tells me he is entitled to a certain amount of local leave every year unaer it. If so, he is, of course, entitled to take it unaer the letter of the lav/. I think, however, that he has very definitely broken the spirit. The v/hole object of this local leave is to let a man get a change in the hot weather. Por a Muscat official to taxe this leave in the cold weather, and at a time v/hen the Muscat finances must require close supervision, is, I think, entirely wrong, ana especially iRxik* so in the case of an official who has been most generously treatea by the State, and should therefore be preparea to give tnem of; his best up to the end. ajor T.C.W.Fowle, C.B.ii., Political Agent, MuscatiV ^ ft ^.^ 1 . -ffw! ' r f^3o ^ fo 7. CV^ 1 u^'U€-oCcU^ «. ^ ae ’u^r tr ^J,c Ho.ai.T.of 1930. - Oific« oi th« Political neoldout i« the 1 ercian Oull, Camp, Muscat, Bated the 27th November 1930. Froa - To The lioo # ble Lt.Colonel H.Y.Bleooe, I.A., PolItleal Healdent in the Persian null The Foreign e crater? tc the Govern merit of India, Sew Pelhi• Functions of the F; ancial Adviser, MHSOeU sir. !&gt; v I have the honour to lnvj4£ a reference to para graph 4 of despatch 110 . 494 -^of 16th epter&amp;ber 1930, regarding the ap pointment of a new Financial Adviser to the Mueeat State. 2. I stated therein that I would aridrtue the Govern ment of India later on the question of the exact functions to be exercised by '-tr. Pedgcocic, who has now been aeleoted for this appointment, and as * br^ve now had an * pertui ity of discussing the matter with the Council and the Political .Agent I submit my views herewith. 3 . Then T.Thomas was first appointed It was decided that he should not be a member of the Council, but within a few months, at the request of Hie Highness, he wse appointed a member with the title of Waxir, and this arrangement has continued ever since. At th^t time the Council oondVbted of four Muscat members and #r. Thomas. ince then one of U£S*tha&amp;« has died while another has resigned* ami of late the Council has co sis ted only of Ssyid aid, the heir apparent, hatich Zufcair and Themes* The result has not been alto gether happy* *ay*d aid was till recently a minor; Shaikh 7 ubair has plenty of other work to do, such as the trial of judicial oasee, etc#, and the tendency has been for the Finance msaiber to take many decisions without rtferenee to the Other Mahers of ths Council and also to atsume charge of the political and internal affairs of the state. 4 # In a memorandum aadreaaed to me on tie subject, '4ajor Fowls writes as follows:- S' «♦ 2 . If he is to do his work thoroug iy the Finan- S oial /adviser should be free to devote the whole of his tiaa to financial matters# The Council# for Instance# acts as a sort of High court in ceriotis oases: murder, etc# The proceedings of ths Court - in Arab fashion - are protracted and the Timmoial Mviser - os full msmbe of the Council- has to attend the sittings# ibis is xaerely one example # tie re ere :aony others, of the way in which his time is spent in mat ten other than finance. Tn tine particular inetance, apart froia the waste of the Afiriaer'e time, i doubt per»onaiJ.y - though I happen to be a firm believer in capital punishment - whether it la desirable for a British off ci,r, even though in the employ of the isueoat Stai«, to be a party to the infliction of locnl ucath sentences# • 3 , cur aim again is to endeavour to miike the ctste stand on its own feat, tut this is difficult..$ •5* * dimcult with a Britiah aif ioer - tnt conduct ol altairo naturailn drifting into hio own hands - in political charge of the Council* • 4.From our point of view a FlnoOclol AdvUer in control of the Council, or at aa^ rote fully sharing In its responsibilities, creates an awkward situation* The Political Agent is responsible to the Political Resident for affairs in general in the xuscat Ftate and should * in say personal opinion • exercise whatever political control ie necessary* Yet side by side with hiis there is another British officer * the Adviser • who we(ilds as * uoh, and perhaps in some oases more, influenoe tiuin he does* moreover, since the Adviser is a British officer, though In the service of the rotate, anything which ue does ie regarded locally ashaving the sanction of the British authorities, in spite of the fact that he is an independent official not under British control** 5 , T agree generally with these views and consider that it is desirable to strengthen the reunoil os muc* s •= Ui - ' and to endeavour, as Major Fowle puta it, to *u»fce the State stand on its own feet aa far as its own internal affairs are concerned; and as long as there is a British officer on the Council it is almost inevitable that more and more power will be concentrated in his hands am the general direction of affairs be left to him* For the above rea* *na I consider it essential • #that the Council eho dd be strengthened and restored to its forsasr numbers and recommend that Hi« High* neos the sultan should be invited to nominate two other member# to the Council* The heir apparent* with whom t disoueeed the matter this morning, informed m that it wae difficult to find suitable persons to serve on the Council; at the same time he fully u^rcea ae to the desirability of adding two additional members, and I heps the difficulty will not prove insuperable* 6 , I further reeam* end that the Financial Adviser should not be a meriber of the Council* &lt;*e will then have ample tim to devote to the reorganisation of the finanees of the state, but will not interfere in local politice or in internal affaire ehlch do not involve expenditure* At the came time it will clearly be necessary to establish a modus vivendi between the Council and the Financial Adviser as regards the control of financial matters* T suggest therefore th t the Financial Mviaer should preeent t e budget to the Council in December each year ( the state financial year coincides with the calendar year } and that it Should then after dieouesion be parsed by the Council; should disagreements arise I have no doubt that they oo Id be composed by the friendly advice of the olitichl Agent* Once the budget bee been passed then the Council should not be esapov/ered to incur any expenditure not provided lor 'n t e budget except with the advice ©nd concurrence of the Financial Mvlser* 0 » tm other hand the Fintncial adviser shoi&amp;d not be entitled to raise salaries or Incur expenditure not pro vided for in the budget except with the concurrence of the x i)mt it had Council. :~*yid *l&lt;l inromed m this Bornlng v, fc notnot feoen oustomary in tho past for a regular budget to be brought before the council each year and readily agreed to the suggest ion that the Council should not incur expenditure not provided for in the budget without the concurrence of the 1 inanoial Adviser provided the latter was Aimilerly bound, and mentioned that in the past salaries had been raised and other expenditure incurred without reference to the Council. 7 . in diocuusing the laatter however with the heir apparent and thaihh Tubair, t made one stipulation, and that was that the Council should not have power to reduce expen* diture on the Levy Corps without prior consultation with the Political Agent. I pointed out to them that in the past the Covrrresent of India had been called on to defend the State against outside aggressions. ~ven so lately as last April they had solicited the support of the jrritieh Govsrniaent against their rebellious subject, the Shaikh of Rhassab* I told thera that oo long as the rtate had to look to the British Government for protection and support the British Government had on their side, in my opinion, the right to demand that the Htote should contribute their s* are tow-M-e their own defence and the maintenance of order in their own territories. Thie they were doing by maintaining the ^evy Corps, which was adequate for the defence of .-tuscst anc. Muttra age lust everything except a generol rising in the Interior and ought to be ebie to deal with asinor dietur~ bonces occurring within areas within which the writ of the Muscat : : tate rune. 8 . T am addressing to the Government of India e separate despatch regarding tne general policy to be pursued In connection with the Levy Corps in the futurs and am recommending that instead of the eomewhet haphazard fashionNo U~&gt; To // ? of i930. / I Political Agency &amp; H.B.N's Consulat: Muscat* 2nd December 1930. &lt;£) . ^ -^Uiii ^ i L I JJQ^uC-A ' lAV L &gt;*A^U.^\ (J) G 1 '-jV&gt;' !^i'OCS« 5 AA-u .^1 rfy' 'CiAAiwj p |'?V- r J ' w^v&gt;, ' ^ y ifc' cJ d ^ . Sv, ( . -■- 5 /~ 4 The Council of Ministers* Muscat State* After Compliments* In continuation of the correspondence *; ending with your unndmbered letter ddted the 9th Jamadi II, 1349 ( l-il-30 ) in which you agreed to the terms of pay of Mr. Hedgecock the new Financial Adviser. 2 . In a conversation which 1 had with you on the 8th November 1930 you agreed to the following further terms with regard to Mr. Hedgecock. (1) He will get the same terms of leave and furlough as Mr. Thomas with the exception that he will get two months recess a year instead of one * and that this recess must be taken during the summer. The reason for the extra months recess is to enable Mr. Hedgecock to recruit his health by leaving Muscat for some month during the trying hot weather, and one month is not sufiieient for this purpose considering the time spent on the journey to and m fro. (2) His passage and that of his wife will be paid from England to Mus cat at 1st class P &amp; 0. B rate. He can travel by any route he likes. (3) His pay will commence fromCONFIDENTIAL No. 104-C of 1930. Political Agency and H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat. The 19th December 1930. To XL- The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Reference my Memorandum No. K/H7 dated 11th Octobei 1930 to the address of the Secretary. The State gunboat AL SAID returned yesterday from DHOFAR where she had taken the Wall of the place returning from leave, and whence she *as to bring Mr. Thomas back to Muscat at the conclusion of his leave which he was spending the re • 2. Mr. Thomas did not return on her, but sent a letter to me to the effect that he had applied to the Council • for one month’s special leave without pay • from 1st - 31st December • As there are no communications with DHOFAR except by dhow , which take a considerable time, or by the AL SAID, each of whose trips costs a certain amount in coal, no reply can be sent to this * application *• 3 . Mr. Thomas’s absence of course at the end of the financial year when he should be preparing his Budget Estima for next year, especially in view of the fact that a new Finaj al Adviser is on the way to take over his duties, is most in convenient. The State of course saves Rs 2,000/. 4 . From reports brought back by the AL SAID it appea; that Mr. Thomas has made for the RUB-AL-KHALI. He left DHOFAR about the 10th. If it is his intention to try and cross the desert it seems unlikely that he will be back by the end of t month. 5 # j have learnt from Mr. Hedgecock that he is arriv here on the 30th instant. He will take over the duties of FinancialFinancial Advi&amp;er immediately from Saiyid Said wh® is at carrying on in the absence of Mr. Thomas. $ ^ Major, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Conoul, Muscat. (pri*No. I 0 $ - C of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat the 29th December 1930. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Mr. Hedgecock the new Financial Adviser to the Muscat State arrived here on the 27th instant. ^ Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.Telegram From, Resident Bushlre ipo t r. A • Mu scat* No. 6 * D and R 2nd January 1930. Your Despatch No.104.§. of December 18th. I consider action of ’fhomas in thus taking leave without prior consent of Council and at a time when it is obvius^fiiE 8 HYKRiBRjs most inconvenient is deplorable and that he has shown little regard for the interests of the State by whom he has been most generously treated. I consider the least amends he can make is to ^ stay on in Muscat until Budget has been prepared and Hedgcock ■ put in touch with current work such period being counted as leave. Under Article 4 (d) of his Contract leave without pay does not ESMRi reckon as active service.No. &amp; of 1931 Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate. To The Council of Ministers to Hie High ness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Tmscat. After Compliments. MT. Thomas I understand was due on the 31st of December 1931. Have Your Honours got any information about him? If not I suggest that a letter might be sent to the Wali of Dhofar asking what news he has about Mr. Thomas, and if he knows what route Mr. Thomas intended to take. The Wali of Dhofar would of course give any assistance possible to Mr. Thomas if the latter were in difficulties, more especially as I understand he and Mr. Thomas are personal friends. % This is what had to be said and salaams. A Maj or, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, MuscatTelegram Code. From Political, Muscat. To Britconsul, No. 60 Dated 11th January 1931. Reference my letter No.l04-C. No news of Thomas. He gave us no information as to what route he was taking. If he has tried to cross the- Rub-al-Khali it is possible he may be in serious difficulties, but I do not see that we can do anything, and I merely report this for your information. I have asked Council to send letter to Wali of Dhofar enquiring what news if any k * 8 °f Thomas.Letter L T o.84 Ministers to His Major T.C.Fo^le, muscat. dated /th January 1931 from the Council of Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, to C.B.E., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, iv. 0 . T Je have received your letter Lo.^8 dated the 2nd December 1930 T*v,^*’ding Mr. Hedgcock, the Financial Adviser to Muscat Stctte, and were acquainted ^ r ith its contents. As regards his pay ^e have already expressed our agree ment that he should get Hs.1200/- per mensem TtT ith an incre ment ox As.lOu/- every year, that he should get t^o months’ leave every year during summer instead of one, that his as ^ell as his life's passage should be given at the rate of first class b. P &amp; 0, and that his pay should commence from the date of his taking charge of his duties. We agree to all the above. xxxx 5 gpcadx Yes -ire have not discussed the question of xx^xxxxixxxix Mr. Hedgcock’s contract and the period of of his services to the Muscat State. U. us h* C W. &gt;j ~zt NO. / 3 '&lt;e= :r 7 Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat, the 16th January 1931« Copy together with copies of letters Fo.K/37, dated 10-9-30, -^and Ho. 118-C, dated 2-12-30, from;.the political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, to the Council of Ministers^ forwarded to S*E» &lt; Hedgecock, Esquire, Financial Adviser to H.H. the Sultan of Musca for information. • ** i Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,—r vinfident iftl. Q no. lb-». of 1931, isritish nesidency and Consulate-u-eneral, isushlre, the 6 th January 1931 . A copy o 1* the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the political Agent at muscat, reference this office letter no. 81-*., dated the 27th november 1930 {attested copy sent him). The Hon * ble the political itesiaent hopes Ujqyft steps will be taken to strengthen the Council as occasion offers, and when suitable persons can be found. ne presumes that this proposal will not involve much increased expenditure, but would be glad to know if this presumption is correct. ±$y order, Captain, Secretary to the political nesident in the rersian tiulf. Sub.j e c t :- functions of the irinancial Adviser, muscat. Letter no.i?*. 182-is/30, dated 24th .uecemDer 1930, the foreign and rolitical department, ne«Confidential if. 162-n/dO. j5‘roin The Addl. Deputy becretsTj'' to the Government of india in the foreign and political Department, To l! f The Hon^le the political nesident in the Persian Dulf. ■ ■ Dated neyf Delhi, the 24th Deceiii'berl930 hTJDGTiODb UF XHJS FlDAWClAL AUViSKK, HUtiCAT. Sir, IOU 1 am directed to acknowledge the receipt of x fj 7/ your letter do. 81 -x., dated the 27th xiovemher 1930, are no doubt satisfied that two additional Members of Council can be appointed without endangering the financial equilibrium of the muscat state. un this understanding i am to convey the approval of the Government of India to your proposals. i have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, m U ill il SD/ P. is. ifiraraer. for Additional Deputy secretary to tne Government of india.' D*0*^o#F.i82-l&gt;/30* 1 Foreign and Political Department, Kew Delhi» January ^3 SI CfC/u+f , please refer to the demi-official letter 'rroci the /^i ndis office *o.P,8062/30i dated the 4th December 1930 t a A COi)y 0 f which was sent to you informally on the 7th instant. You will no doubt take steps for the recovery from the Muscat State of the sum of £ x 6 U, which the secretary of St«*te has advanced to Kedgcook on account of travelling expenses of himself and his wife. Yours sincerely, 3d• C.G.N. Edwards.Telegram- Code, i’rorn roliticai) To Political, Bahrein, Liu s cat, ho. Bated and received 21 st iVby.1931. Thomas arrived from Interior via Dohah; jjr^ceeds Muscat next down mail. Addressed to Bushire and repeated to Muscat. 4. !?. M &amp; A Telegram Code. From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Muscat. No. 121 Bated 23rd February 1931. Political Agent, Bahrain, informs me on 21st February that Thomas arrived jDovh' A; there from interior via BOSKS proceeds to Muscat hy next down mail* Addressed Muscat repeated 3.F.O. H.M«S.'Triad rt and M Hastings •The Politic*! Agency &amp; H.B.M'e Consul* Muscat» 22nd February 1931. To The Council of Ministers to H.H.the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman MUSCAT. A.C . I beg to repeat for the information of Your Honours the following telegram (dated 21st February) received from the Political Agent, Bahrein*- • Thoms arrived from interior via Dohah; proceeds Muscat next down mail. Addressed to Bushire and repeated to Muscat. M This ia what had to be communicated and salams. Treasury Officer In the absence of the Political Agent &amp; H.B.li's Conaul.Muscat.■— British Residency, Bushire, the 27th February 1931. D.O.lTo.83-3 of h- 93 The Political Resident has asked me to invite your attention to his telegram ho. 6 , dated the 2nd .January 1931, wherein he has suggested that the least amends Mr.Thomas can € make is to stay on in Muscat until the budget has been prepared, such period being counted as leave, and to enquire what arrangement you have come to with Mr.Thomas in this respect. The Political Resident further wishes you to ask Mr.Thomas to explain why he took leave without obtaining the prior consent of the Council and^ secondly^ why he overstayed his leave. h- 93 bajor T. C . W . F owl e Political Agent, Muscat.if I in: jou why consent leoTe* Bertraa3th K&amp;roh 193t* ofc 0 K«f ersno* our conversation of yesterday• j lnfora ed you the Political Resident desires ne to ask ■ shy you took leave without obtaining the prior Consent of the Council,and,secondly,why you overstayed your 1 leara* fertr&amp;a Thoiaa* E*C|» 0*B*E«' rVv ^vvr^ . 9th March 1931 I do not understand the first paragraph of your letter of todays date. The Council gave you 6 weeks leave and you proooodod to Dhofap* At the end of this period you should have returned In the A1 Saldl which took the Vail of Dhofar*who had been on leave,baok to his post and was to bring you book to yours* Instead of returning by the A1 Saldl you sent a letter back 1$ her Captain asking the Council for leave without pay from t*t-3tet December# Owing to the distance of Dhofar from Sfuecat no reply could be sent by the Council fiacre especially as the A1 Saldl brought back news that you had gone Into the Ruba~al~Khelle You therefore took Iscvs without obtaining the prior consent of the Council»and also instead of returning to Muscat by the 31st December you did not rsaoh here until 7th March# if Bertram Thomas Esq. O.B.E.Telegram- Code From ^ o. 5 4 Political, Muscat, Resident, Bushire, uated iith March 1931. Your letter dated 27th February. I have discussed question with Hedgcock. matter has budget well in hand and has no desire that Thomas should stay on, in fact would rather he left which he proposes to do Saturday next. I concur. I have asked Thomas in writing for explanation desired by you. Question of how much pay Thomas should receive, in view of the fact that lie proceeded on leave without permission e^c, is being submitted to you by council under article 7 of Thomas’s contract.Muscat,fl|Rtk 13th March I931. Dear Thomas, My letter of the 9 th Instant. Have you any reply to make? Yours sincerely, B.S.Thomas, Esqr. O.B.E. Muscat.16/3/31. To the Political A^ent ana Consul, Lius cat. Memorandum, Settlement of Mr Thomas 1 Accounts. 1 forward herewith copies of correspondence between Mr Thomas and myself concerning the settlement of his accounts, with the request that the joints at issue may be decided by the Political Resident in accordance with Art.VII Z£ 3 of Hr Thomas* contract. Rulings are required on the following. (Reference is to j*.his letter dated 11/3/31.; Is ...r Thomas entitled to claim as 'service days'* earning furlough the 3&lt;s days spent in attendance on H,H. the ^ 1 mm on lis visit to England in 1 ^ 3 tiv Tou v/ill ooserve ^hat in his subsequent memorandum dated 13/3/31 he shoves the period the Su] tan was in England (though a large part ° L ^ ' as s P e nt in hospital) as furlough-earning service. It w &gt;uld appear from this letter that he actual].^ took in 1938 the extra days of furlough to which he was entitled ‘°J ris attendance on the Sultan, but is claiming them again in the memo dated 11/3/31. Did he overstay his furlough in 1828 , and if so should uae ^cess number of days be deducted from the furlough now e to hi 14 ; Mfc Tnomas left Iluscat on 4/lC/?0j and returned on 6/3/31,T 7 I OS $ &lt;g) \ 1 iJi 6 n cli( ; j service ith. tihe otate of Muscsit expire^ Accot r _ i in u-.c refutations of tiie IraQ Gover nm ent if ordinary leave is overstayed, the whole period of leave co unto as f jr loufic* Xn iilr Thomas * case, does his service end taj on the day he left Muscat en route to the Ruba al Khali, i.e # Oct. 4 th, or (b) on the day he claims that his leave began, i.e. October 11th, or (c) on the day his leave ended, in which case is his explanation that the one month referred to is in reality six weeks to be accepted^ 4) Does furlough-earning service begin at Muscat, or At Bombay or Basra as claimed by Mr Thomas* Except for the sura of Rs 2,000 sent to Bahrain telegraphically at his request, nothing has yet been paiu to Mr Tnomas of the Rs 8,000 (approx.) claimed by y hir:l as due on account of furlough. Mr Thomas replied to p./tHhls Ministry 1 s Mo B/l/8? of 18/S/J1 at 1 0 a.m. on 14/3/81 yj7//z^° re Ply was received to ^ D.O. No 3/ 14/3/31 handed to him at noon the same day, though the B.I. steamer did not leave until b p.m. Financial Adviser, Muscat State.From the Late Financial Adviser, Muscat State. To the Financial Adviser, Muscat State. Muscat, Arabia, lithe March 1S31 In accordance with our conversation to-day I am entitled under my contract to the following (a) a first-class sea passage to U.K.vide para V transport, (b) furlough pay on the basis of 1/6 actual service (including annual leave) commencing and ending on arrival Bombay vide para IV Furlough (a) and (b). As regards (a) will you kindly issue me with a single first-class ticket to Karachi by the next down mail and pay to me Es.900/- for the sea passage from there to London, The actual fare Karachi - Liverpool by City line by which I have booked is Rs.853/- vide attached telegram. The difference of &amp;,47/- is for 1st class passage railway fare to London plus pae baggage expense throughout. As regards (b) the following are det and furlougnTon contract basis. Service Left Basrah en route Muscat 20th days. January (arrived Muscat 27th via Bushire whereby official direction had to see the Political Besident. Basrah and Bombay are same distance 679 in time from Muscat and for purposes of assessing furlough eaual) On service till 30th November 1931. ails of service Furlough earned days. 113.16 Time to be spent on passage from Muscat to Bombay (City of Nagpur leaves Bombay 21st) Next down mail leaves Muscat 14th. On deputation at home by direction of India'Office. Journey to Marseilles to' meet H.H.the Sultan. Official interpreter interviews (a) H.M.the King (b) the Secretary of State for India. Accompany H.H.the Sultan to Skegness hospital where K.H. was received 21 st- 28th July 1928. One month's deputation conducting H.H's party while guest of H.B.K. Government 15th September - 14th October 1928. 1.32 5. 120.64 Equal to 3 months and 28 days.Already received one month’s furlough. Balance due 2 months and 28 days. I shall he glad if you will (a) pay me in resnect of nne month’s furlough now (h; one month he remitted in~April (c'] and the balance 28 days in May. B &amp; C hy payment into my private current account with Messrs Lloyds, Bombay. B.S.Thomas Late Financial Adviser, Muscat State,B/l/37. l£th March 1931, B.S. Thomas Esar. Beference your claim for the settlement of your account dated 11/3/31. In order to calculate the sum due to you this Ministry requires the following information. No.of days furlough (with dates) taken hy you prior to your return to Muscat on January 27th 1929. No 0 of days leave (with dates) taken hy you during your period of service,qLuoting authority for any extensions S.E.Hedgcock, Financial Adviser, Muscat State.n t»v ' C&gt;\ OxlT tnucrr. t iah 5Q liJO 13th March 1931. 305 Prom the Late Financial Adviser, Muscat♦ To the Financial Adviser, Muscat. Figures you want as near as I can give them without recourse to personal diaries in England, as follows;-r I. Service . Arrival Muscat 2nd April 1925. . Left Bombay on leave (City of Parisj2nd April 1928. Plus attendance on Sultan’s visit to England. Arrival Marseilles 14 July 1928. Departure Calais 14 Oct. 1928. Leave . ' Left Bombay on leave 2nd April 1928.(City of Paris) Arrived Basrah from leave 2nd Jan.1929. Less duty attendance on Sultan in England. H.H.arrival Marseilles 14 July 1928, departure from Dover 14 Oct.28 That this was not leave see views of India Office vide (authorities private letter of 14 June and sanctioned by H.H.the Sultan on arrival in England). II. Annual leave . . 1925. 1 month in India June-July. 1927° 41^days 6 Jan - 15 Feb. - Journey to Dhufar by order of Sultan to introduce Muscat 1929. 32 P days C li r jan y - 15 Feb. To and from Dhufar 1930. S'days'll^ct-Is ^o™ Bhufar also by arrangement with Sultan. The relevant contract clause was intended as a pi ovi slon for a full month's leave i.e. six weeks ° ellin g||| leaving Muscat to date of returning - time spent m trav g jft III INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL? S.W.l. 14th June 1928, m private pear Thomas, Y T ith reference to our conversation two or three days a g 0f i write to say that the Secretary of State has now telegraphed to the Government of India that His Majesty’s Government approve the entertainment of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat for a period of one month during his visit to this country; and that you would he ready to meet His Higness at Marseilles and to accompany him throughout your leave,on the understanding that you would receive an extension which, it was suggested, would prohahly he of three months or so,on the conclusion of his visit. We have also put to the Govern ment of India the proposals as to the terms which are discussed with you here, and I will let you know at once as soon as we hear from them on this. They have been asked to telegraphed as soon as possible the date of His Highness’ arrival at Marseilles and full particulars of his suite. From your confidential information, I may add that it now seems prohahle that, even if the Sultan should not a State guest until after his operation, an endeavour will he ( made to arrange an audience with the King very shortly his arrival. It would, therefore, oe of great assn^tance i y could, without inconvenience, draft a brief memorandum on the lines suggested hy Sir Arthur Bannerman in your conv with him, which would now he laid before the King. The memo randum,Sir Arthur suggests, might well begin with description of the territories ruled over by tue ^ult-n contain remarks on His Highness’s salient character* yours Sincerely»Muscat 14th March 1931, jty dear Hedgcock, X have just seen Political Agent and wished him good hye. I am leaving with his approval hy to-day’s ship. Kindly send me 1 first-class ticket to Karachi plus Rs.900/-for journey home, plus Rs.2000/- furlough pay plus te. 590/- for furniture(if that is the ameded figure). I enclose a reply to your note which would have been typed earlier hut yesterday was Friday, iou Aixx remember calling my attention to the small matter of £ ^00/ etter j incurred hy me in first instance so State ought to he ,/2 of) ) handsome in its treatment. Will look in and say good hye to you. Yours sihcerely B.S.Thomas.Finance Ministry, NO.B/l/ 2 - i;uscat,the 8tii April 1920 To, The political Agent &amp; H.B.JPs Consul, Muscat, Sea-Passage Allowance - Financial Adviser, I have in my letter No.Bl/1 of to-day/*s date raised the Question of recovery of payment of sea passage from London, on the occasion of taking up the appointment of Financial Adviser to the State of Oman. I shall he glad to have your approval of mj claim for &lt;0 7? sterling which sum I pajd for a 1st class ticket from London to Muscat, enclosed are shipping documents in support of the expenditure. I would venture to point out that I have already v'ithin the past year home the eroense of a journey iron Trans-Jordan to Eushire, Muscat, Bombay and Kashmir and hack for the purpose of being '’vetted' for the Muscat port. This cost me (a) travelling expense of £ 151 plus (t) seven weeks leave of absence without pay representing another £ 155 i.e.£ 505 in all vile ny letter of 12th September 1924 addressee! to political resident Persian Gulf. I have the honour etc. • Bertram Thomas, financial Adviser, Oman ftate.Ministry of Finance,®) Muscat 14-3-1S31, D.O. S 14/3 I am sorry,Dut I find it cmite impossible to settle up your account on the information you have given rue.To take one example only, in your letter dated 13 / 3/31 you showed three months' attendance on the Sultan as furlough- earning service, and you actually took this furlough(plus and additional 14 days) in 1928. in your letter dated 11/3/s you again showed 38 days' attendance on the Sultan as furlough-earning service. There also other points which I find difficult to reconcile with the terms of you contract. As, however/, according to Art. VII of the contract it is not my place hut the Political Resident's to settle any doubtful points, I am referring the matter to him for settlement. I have given you a first-class ticket to Karachi,and I have instructed the Treasury Officer to pay you Rs.353 (1st class fare to Karachi-United Kingdom) and Rs.673 cost of furniture bought from you by the State. Ill Bertram Thomas Esq.* O.B.E 01 ^ U-oWcA. 'V^rV lV 0 S-u|li. ^ Wv^, f.R.Jrf^ &gt;V^3-&gt; / ||4 11 levy Budget j Precia of Events* 1 ) 7-/ The first oudget i-iukuittad rj Captain Walker this year was for Rs 1,54,000* This was the figure which, at the P.R^s request, the Council had a jionth or so before my arrival been asked to accept for the next three years. The Council had postponed giving any decision. The total is Rs SI,080 aore than the actual average expenditure of the last two years, whicli accox^ding to Captain Walker’s figures is: Expenditure 1929 ..Be Rs 1,33,510 ' 1030 1,38,331 Average annual expenditure.... 1,38,920. As the strength sanctioned by the Oovernient of India for 1931 is 150, and tne numbers of the rank and file were in 1.J29 and 1930 respectively lei and 156, it Till be seen that this basis of comparison if advantageous to the Levy. _ This first budget was reduced by Capt. Walker to R 8 1,43,000 on 7/1/31, and to Rs 1,34,650 on 19/1/31. At W363 thia Point (i.e. R e 2 , 51 © above last year’s expenditure), Capt. Walker stated that r ; v n Tnc Levy is down to absolute bedrock in economies* The Levy cannot make any further sacrifices if it ic to regain worthy of the name* It is difficult to reconcile these statements with my sub- Sequent report, which showed (No S 26/l) that (&amp;) The pay of the rank and file was disproportionately high. With rations, clothing, and pay of Rs 30 p.n* the sepoy receives the equivalent of nearly Rs 40 p*m.The oay of a State askari ia Rs 7 to 10 net (rifle not provided by the State), and a road sangaan working in j'uscat receives Rs 8/8 (no pickings)/*a skilled artizan Rs 31 p.ia* (h) Til© proportion of N.C.O.c to men was 1 to 2^ . (c) Non-combatants had increased as the number of military - effectives had decreased: in 19*36 there were °00 rank and file, and 95 non-combatants, in 1930, 150 rank and file and 34 non-combatants* (d) The number and pay of non-combatants was on an absurdly laviah scale. (e) Expensive Indian artisans were engaged, when sufficient^ though less skilled men were available locally. In addition to their high pay (average Rs 74 p.m. with rations** 1 * Iba.Jitta daily) these men received,like the rank and file''two inonths' leave on ffcll pay each year. Leave takeiT in India included free sea and rail passages, and in some cases free passages for wife, children, and ^servants. I asked for a reduction of Rs 31,000 representing l# on • the Levy's astx 'annual spendings'. (My No S 22/1 of January 22nd.K 4) After discussions with the P.A., a compromise budget of Rs 1,20,854, representing Sjf reduction on last year's ex penditure, was agreed to by P.A., F.A.J Council of Ministers and Coiamandant, the lawst-naaed making a reservation that a cut in pay night cause discontent* The Levy budget was the first and most Important step In a general retrenchment scheme which would reduce lonthly expenditure to the leevej) of monthly income* The key-stone of this budget was a 16 reduction in the pay of the rank and file . (If rations, clothing etc. is taken into account, the reduction on a 0 poy'a total emoluments works out at approx. 12£$&lt;.) The iead thus set by the Levy would enable proportionate reflduc- lions to be made in thebther much lower-paid department®* On his visit of February 13th to 15th, the p.R., if ter hearing ay views, handed we a budget of Re 1,37,846. He left l-Usat under the impression that he had sanctioned savingson the previous year's expenditure of Rs 165. Actually, owing to two : iinor and two serious errors subsequently discovered in the budget prepared f-.r him, the savings were Rs 4,365, or 3^. This budget included (a) A reduction of 6 in the number of N.C.O.s., and a - corresponding increase in the seoovs (b) A reduction of 6 in the number of non**combatarts and decreases in pay. ’ (c) A reduction in G.C. pay (d) A reduction in the pa/ of the raiu: and file of 6\% or, including ratione, clothing etc., a reduction of 5% approx. As a ainor ij.lusti’at: 021 . of tlie general lavishness, I may instance one of several such posts still included in this budget: punkahs boys are paid Rs 16 plus rations, for twelve months o”' tie year, and are allowed two months' leave on full pay; at the Agency, punkah boys are paid Rs 7 p.m # for six months in the year* After the P.R.'s departure I found Baiyid Said discouraged ona listless. He said that in his interview he had urgexJl many arguments in favour of economy in the Levy budget in general, and in the pay of the rank and file in particular, ' ^d protested that none of his argumei ts had been fairly ♦aet. He gave me to understand that the Government of India* half-hearted lead towards retrenchment did not put the Council In a strong enough position to effect the economies ©nvisaged in allowances to the Ruling Family and in other departments of the administration. The p.R.'s advising him not take the advlco of his Financial Adviser had taoroughly confi/sed him. While Saiyid 3aid was down with malaria, I wrote myHo S 24/,°, in which I accepted the P.R.’s tox&amp;gefc decision concerning the small cut in the pay of the rank and file, hut pointed out the consequences: increased taxation and a probable deficit. 1 also considered whether it would be sounder policy to advise toe 0 ^.unoil at once to put through an emasculated retrenchment scheme, or to wait until a more favourable opportunity for putting into effect a compre hensive scheme. I felt sure that if the first were done, the Council would not be prepared to name a second shot later on. In any case, the sane anount of time and trouble, and almost the same amount of odium, would be incurred by either scheme. The decision was eventually taken out of my hands, as is shown in the following paragraph. 4&gt; l ^i In his No 34 C of 17/2/31, the P.A. asked for the Council's approval to the budget proposed by the P.R. Vkiie the Council were considering this, the Commandant prematurely announced the budget; he also dismissed Saiyid Said's syce, and stopped the issue of rations to the horses of the Ruling Family - the latter an arbitrary act, as these rations do not appear in the Levy budget. Angry at this flouting of his authority, Saiyid Said came to my office and announced that he had not accepted and would not accept this budeet * The P.A. and the Commandant made to Saiyid Said explanations ? hich were officially accepted, but this did not deter rim from continuing to press for farther reductions* afEZtaOuift figure After six weeks' negotiations, further savings to the ex tent of Rs 6,035 were made, bringing the total savings up 00 11,000 representing an 8 $ reduction on last year's5. I expenditure. These included a reduction in the number and ?a\ r of followers, discontinuance of rations to followers, and a cut of Rs 4,271 in the Rs 7,000 provision for re-armament and equipment, (ity ovn reference would have been to keep the provision for new rifles, and dispense with the dhobi and other surplus menials.) The above savings represent the pruning of most, though not all, of the extravagant expenditure of the past few years. Under this provisionally accepted budget, the Levy will not begin to feel the pinch of real economy* g) At this stage the Council decided, as revenue collections continued to show so marked and steady a decrease, to give up asking for any further piecemeal reductions. Instead they informed the P.A. that they accepted the P.R.*s budget, less the R: 6,635 mentioned above, but propcesed to ask for the P.R/s promised second cut at once, instead of in the autumn as he had suggested, if the financial outlook was still unfavourable. The Council^ first and second (requested) cut represent a saving of 16# on the average expenditure of the last two year*, viz. Rs 21,264* A reference to the last line of para. 3 will show that the Council are not demanding any more than I asked for seven veeks earlier* Up to date, they have succeeded in obtaining 8 # 0 *zX, out of the 16# which they consider neceesary. Dunned by creditors, acutely embarrassed by the lack of ready cash, and faced by falling revenues and a debt £aily increasing, the Council felt that they had no alternative but to ask for a further reduction in the budget of the Muscat Infantry* They considered that forthe full realisation of their scheme of retrenchment a further out of Re 3 p. ra . in the out of each sepoy, and of N.C.O.s pro rata, was a sine cue non , and Zt*.y that the State's heavy debts and the anticipated deficit of Re 90,000 fully justified any risk there m-ht te in cutting down the pey of arned mens; To expea u the State of Muscat to contribute one-sixth of its total income on the maintenance of the small Levy force, seems to me to be a drain oil the country's impoverished exchequer out of all proportion to the ' value to the Indian Army of 150 men in the event of Muscat's being attacked in force. Nevertheless, in an my discussions with the Council I have met with no hint that they wish to abolish the Muscat Infantry, or to evade the responsibility of defending their own country. They are prepared to provide the Levy with funds up to the maximum of the Site's resources, but they do expect that, more particularly nos that Muscat is on the verge of bankruptcy, the Levy should be run with a reasonable economy and v;ith Bom eenee of responsibility for public money*Political Agency Sc H.B.M'a Consulate, Muscat, the ^ Search 1931. prom Major T.C.Powle, C.B.E., Political Agent L H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, f). i ca* I have the honour to enclose letter No.S. 16/3, dated the 16th March 1931, from the Financial Adviser, Muscat State, with enclosures. I also make some comments below on the points raised by Mr. Hedgeock which you may like to consider. They are f/? I6(&gt; f course only my own personal opinions. . Mr. Thomas’ letter of 13th March is explanatory of is letter of 11th March and it is the latter that can be tade, as it seems to me, a basis for deexsion. 3. ( Reference ^ara 1 of Mr. Hedg coct^letter) • Ur.Thomas took 6 months leave, while he was on this leave he was put on duty for 3 months (vide India Oiiice letter dated the 14th June 1928) with His Highness the Sultan. To compensate him for this 3 months duty, 3 months leave was given to him. in his letter of 13th Karch he claims these 3 months duty with His Highness the Sultan as a furlough earning period. This seems to me correct. 4•( Reference para 2 )• I overstayed his furlough, extended to 9 months in am not of the opinion that he He had 6 months furlough the circumstances explained inpara 3 aoove. He went on furlough on 2nd A*ril 1928 and ^ returned on 2nd January 1929 f i«e« a period of 9 months* 5» (jtej^eren Ge par a 3)* Mr* 'fhomas according to para IV(b) of his Contract is permitted one month’s annual leave to he spent out of Muscat* Reasonable time, say, a week, for coming and going, might be added to this (it takes for instance about 4 or 5 days, Muscat-Karachi and back)* He took 6 weeks leave from the Council of Ministers^leaving Muscat 4th October 1930, and thus should have been back on the 23rd November* I understand that it was arranged that the 'Al Saidi * 1 .(State gunboat) should fetch him bacic from Dhofar, when it took back the Wall of ^hofar at the expiration of the latter’s leave. In point of fact the 'Al Saidi' did not leave Muscat till 30th November and did not start bacx from bhofar till about the 14th December, reaching Muscat on the i.Sth December 1930* Mr* Thomas, if he had come back on that date, could I thm*. nave argueu ■f t/Lrt ’ that he came back by the available means* Under these circumstances I am of the opinion that Mr* Thomas sei/xc^ with the State terminated on the date on which he could have embarked for Muscat from Dhoiar* ( Reference para 4 )* There is nothing m the Contract as to where furlough earning service begins, but as in the case of Government officials, I should think that it should begin or end either at Bombay or Basrah, as the case may b 2 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Maj or. Political Agent &amp; H.B.E’s Consul, flftf Muscat.D.O. political Agency &amp; H.B.M'b Consulate Muscat,the 25th March 1931 , / ft ] Please refer to my le tter No. £5~^c» dated the ^,5^ March 1931» regarding Mr. Thomas. I pointed out to Mr. Hedgcock that the most important point in Mr. Thomas* conduct, i.e. the latter’s proceeding on leave without prior consent of the Council had not been put up for arbitration. Mr. Hedgcock said he would add it to his letter No.S. 16/3, dated the 16th March 1931 and so I prepared the note which I attach. Mr. Hedgcock afterwards changed his mind and said that he did not care to put up this point as it might appear 'vindictive'• I don’t see any force in his argumen^ and I think the point should certainly have been put upjbut as Mr. Hedgcock has taken up this attitude I have had to excise my remarks from my official draft and to put them up under cover of this D.O. . ifours sincerely, Hon’ble Lieut.Colonel H.V.Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.7. f rtel'eienee ^ 5 ). The most important iioint on ..hioh arbitration is requested is that which concerns Mr. Thomas proceeding on ieave from Bhofar without prior consent of the Council. That he did so proceed is beyond dispute. Vhen the 'A1 Saidi' left Bhofar to return to Muscat (para 5 above) Mr. Thomas instead of returning, sent by her an 'application- for leave without pay from lst-31st Becember. Owing to the distance of Bhofar from Muscat no reply could be sent by the Council, more especially as the ”Al Saidi- brought bac* news that Mr. Thomas had gone into the Huba-al-KhaU. An even then Mr. Thomas overstayed his applic»ti3. did not return to Muscat until the 6 th March. ,hat maJces Mr. Thomas’ action all the more grave is the fact that the Muscat State, to which Kr. Thomas was Financial Adviser, v/as in a difficult financial position, and that a new Financial Adviser was due to take over from Mr. Thomas at the end of December. 3. That Mr. Thomas has no explanation for his conduct can bo seen from the copies of the correspondence between us attached herewith. All he can say is that he was p- 48 Uy letter to Mr. Thomas dated 3.o.31. } delayed in his mx. Thomas' reply dated 9-3-31. } /CO It start from Dhofar, My reply dated 9-3-31. $ Mr.Thomas' final letter dated 13-3-31.* and en route 'through circumstances outside his control'. hat was well within his control was his leaving Dhofar for the Ruba-al- Khali instead of for his post at Muscat. 9. .hat Mr. Thomas' letter of 9th Larch does reveal is the fact that when he went to Dhofar he intended to make his desert journey. His statejaent ^ when I left Muscat I did so in the belief that I would accomplish my journey and be back about the time of the arrival of my successor' cannot possibly oe accepted. (Though in any ca^e it is something of a side issue). Nobody knows better than Mr. Thomas the delays attendant even on an ordinary camel trip in Arabia, much more on a journey oi exploratj.on nach c~s he contemplated. He did not arrire at Dhofar till about the middle of October, and cou-id not have counted on getting ills Arabs and caaiels together reauj - &gt; “ ^ J ‘ early November. His actual journey from Dhofar across the desert and bac* to Muscat tooK him 3 months, (from about 10th December to 7th March), and this - allowing ior inevitable delays - whs quiCK travelling, -hen he left Muscat therefore he could not have counted on getting bac* to his post before early February, his successor - as he knew well - being due at the enu of December. 10 . That Mr. Thomas performed a courageous and brilliant4 m WKNmi jfcs't of exploration \jy his conduct is of* course quite beside the point* Other travellers have performed (j^) eoually admirable feats of exploration without neglecting the duty which thev frne t-hey ov e their employers •whether the latter were Governrsent or otherwise, and there is no reason why fcr.Thoiaaa should not have followed their example* 11 . With regard to the specific question but for arbitration by iHr*Hedgeocx* It certainly appears to me that some penalty should attach* To take analogous cases* If a Political ar Military Officer had acted as hr*Thomas had done the Civil or Military Authorities would undoubtedly heve shown spme mark of their displeasure, and this mark would most probably have involved pecuniary loss in pay etc to the officer concerned - if indeed it did not take a severer form* If Mr* Thomas had been the employe / of a business firm, he would most likely have been summarily dismissed* There is no case of r* Thomas being dismissed, as he has already left the service of the State* By tne terms of his Contract he is, however, due so majiy months furlough and full pay for service under the State up to the date he left it* But in every contract tnere are certain implied promises, / one of fcbeni being of couroe tiiat an employe will not tase leave without permission, and this Mr. Thomas uun deliberately brosen under circumstances which aggravate the breach. It would seem therefore to be for considerati whether the Muscat State should be kept in full to their side of the agreement, or whether a penalty on Mr. Thomas of total loss of benefits accruing after termination of his service - i.e. his period of furlough and full pay - should not be inflicted* 12 . I have not considered what actual sum is, or may he, due to Mr. Thomas. Once a decision has been on the above point, and on the others put for arbitrationby ItedgcocJCf uiie matter is Tor accounting in the Jf Muscat Treasury* ^he latter find that they have already paid ITr* Thomas more than is granted by the decision, that is their affair* 1 do not imagine that they will # succeed in getting the balance back from Mr* Thomas.mmI uscat 10th A|&gt;rll 1931. tty dear alien 1 came to Muscat, the State fcaa banlcrupt} since then* in apite of a number of aiaali reforroa, the financial jxjaition has become worsen revenue h&amp;a steadily falleri* and the Stated liabilities have increased by over Hb«bO*OOC In order to prevent a complete financial breaicdown, ♦ I drew up a retrenchment ccheme shich in my opinion would quickly enable Monthly expenditure tc be met from monthly income* In putting this into effect I had expected to be :1m ' i ^ able to rely on the help and co-operation of the Government of India} the reverse has been the caae. The crux of this programme was a X2% c / cut in the emoluments of the extremely well-paid* not to say over-paid* Levy force* This reduction was approved by you* by the Council of Ministers* by myself and by the Commandant* who made a reservation* not strongly pressed* that the cut in pay might lead to discontent* The Council of Ministers* Kith their wider knowledge of local conditions* did not uphold this objection} nor did you* As you are a are* the political Resident on his visit here on February 15th sanctioned only a reduction* K&amp;d cogent arguments been advanced in au^^ort o* decision, I should have accepted them even though personally I might not have found myself in agreement; as it was* omy sentimental reasons were given me* ith due respect I venture to submit that a bankrupt state cannot afford to entertain reasons of this nature* Since that date, the Council and myself nave riven to the Political Heaiaent pointing out tost the financial situation is more serious than he thought it was or his visit here* and asking him to sanction at unce, instead of in th e autumn* the second cut ^rosiiscd by him* Jp much as been acinofledged* date these letters have not so It i» ptrhai* difficult for officials jX tht Government of TruUa, acouatotsad as they are ^ think in crores oxrupees* to realize that &amp; mere Batter of two or three lakhs is of Yital itu^orWice to a snatll State such as Muscat* I *ish to assure you that the Council regards with considerable alarm We country 9 s growing indebted- ness* and is at a lost to understand the Government of India 9 s attitude in tne matter of the jjevy budget* Por a bankrupt State to ask for no more than a 16$£ reduction (a reduction of has Just been sanctioned by the Council on the crew of the State 9 s gunboat) on the average expenditure of the last two years seems to me a Boat moderate demand* We more so as toe economies can be effected by pruning extravagances tduch ought not to have been allowed to exist* and *111 neither reduce the numbers of the force nor impair in &amp;ny way its military efficiency* I have now spent three months and ten days in trying to obtain the sanction of We Government of India to what I consider easenUai for the realization of my retrenchment aheine* Anything short of this will not enable the State to *ay its way* At present I see to be as far from success as I w^s et the beginning* In We circumstances it seems to me that I am doing no good to s^yself or to We Government I serve by remaining in charge of ^fuscaWs finances while my financial advice is consistently disregarded We Government of India* I see no oWer course open to me Wuin reluctantly to tender *ry resignation froA today 9 s ?ate* fours sincerely* SdA S*E • Hedgeoek*Telegram- R. Prom Political, Muscat To Commissioner in Sind, Karachi, ho* HO* Bated ilth April 1931* yLp. 2C(,A Important* Please deliver following to Political Resident on hoard 'Varela”i- 'HedgcocJc has handed in his resignation to Council of Ministers and has informed me of same demi-officially giving as reason that his Levy retrenchment scheme has not heen accepted in full, that financial stability of State can only be obtained by his scheme, and that therefore he sees no good in retaining his appointment* I had given him before he tendered his resignation )&lt;&gt; copy of your telegram Uo*52-T and as Levy Budget is now under the Ls. 121,000 he asked for in February his alleged reason is very weak* Council with whom I have discussed matter inform me that Hedgcock is willing to stay on 2 or 3 months. They ask that if Government accept Hedgeock* s resignation another Financial Adviser should be supplied in his place. There seems no point in trying to retain a dissatisfied official and I suggest Hedgcock-s resignation oe accepted and that a new Financial Adviser be procured as soon as possible. y-f) 1 will send Hedgcodc's letter of resignation with my comments to you by next mail as also reply to your letter il i»Copies ih filest* Telegram - H. From Political, Muscat To . Keeident M Varela M Henjamradio f No*113 Dated 13th A±&gt;ril T /^3/ My telegram NoellO# Ky laeaning was that Hedgcocic’s resignation should, he accex^ted hut that he should stay on the 2 or 3 months to enable net? Financial Adviser to he obtained* I do net know if I made this clear. Said Saiyid who has teen suffering from fever is proceeding to Karachi on 17th for one iaonth*5 change on medical certificate* i ^repose leaving on recess on 17th* 1 could interview oultan who is now at Itehra Tun vide your letter »o.86-S of 12th January para 13 and give him coiuminlcation indicated in your letter 17-T of 3 l 8 t fcaroh. D# you approve?/ 34 11 111 K H«. Im -c of 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.B.ITs Consulate, Uuscat,the fU April 1931. To The Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. H, IK ID: Sir, In continuation of my telegrams Bos. 110 and 113 of - . 11th and 13th April respectiTely, I have the honour to forward herewith Mr. Hedgcock* s letter of resignation to me* he has sent in another to the Council of Ministers. 2 . I have already in my above quoted telegrams given my views on Mr. Hedgeock’s resignation, i.e. that it should he accepted and that he should stay on the two or three months he proposes to the Council until the new Financial Adviser - asked for hy the Council - is procured. In any case - though he has not yet signed any contract with the Council, (for the reason ~ as he told me - that he thought it a oad one from his point of view), he oould hardly throw up his billet at a moment's notice. 3* On general # principles it is not advisable to try and retain the services of a dissatisfied and disgruntled iioial and the tone of his letter is sufficient to show - besides various examples 1 have had of it here - that MT. Hedgcock is both. He states for instance that his and the Council's letters^have not so much as been acknowledged'. There is ne object in 'acknowledging* a letter until the recipient is in a position to take action. All his letters nave x coarse been sent on by me, but as I pointed out to mt. Heagcock mor than once ( but without result), his method of supplying information piecemeal in separate communications, each of considerable length, is bound to lead to a 'wood which cannbe seen for the trees’• This is exactly Mihat has occurred* I endeavoured to give a financial picture of the state by gununarising his letters in my No*83«»c of ^ )y\j)u\sC/^ m There were, however, still some points not clear, and on receipt of * 25 ^ y° ur No*T*/ ^ asked Mr* Hedgeocic for the summarised 3 £V ^information required hy you. Instead of being pleased at the n&gt; «aciaiowledgment f of his letters in the very practical form of an enquiry for more light, Mr. HedgcocJc in reply informed me that he was not going to discuss the Levy Budget any further, * and that he intended to resign. I told Mr. Hedgcock that whatever his reasons might be for resigning I did not see why he should refuse to (five the information asked for, and finally after a long conversation I persuaded him to come and talk it over with me next morning. Next morning, however, brought not Mr. Hedgcock, but a note from him to the effect that *on second thought ! 1 he had gone back to his original view that he would discuss the Levy Budget no further. I think I would have been quite justified in leaving the matter there, and reporting to you that Mr. Hedgoock refused to give the information asked for. I do not think, however, that a Political Officer is paid for standing on his dignity if anything is to be gained by stepping off it, and so as Mr. Hedgcock would not come to see me I went round to his house^o see him, and after another j-^ng conversation persuaded him to change his views. I suggested a schedule form with some notes as the most convenient way of presenting the information required. Mr. Hedgcock produced the schedule, and finally - after some further persuasion ( he stated he did not like his figures being ’queried’) - his notes. In order to assist him and endeavour^ to get the letter ready A for the mail I offered to have copies of his schedule, notes and letter of resignation typed in my office, which was accordingly done. I have given the above incident in some detail as it shows clearly the frame of mind in which Mr. Hedgcock now is* Another reason against his continuance here is that - since cennaitting himself to a most pessimistic view of the financial future ofstate after the Political Resident’s visit in February - lie ha» shown a certain indifference to the possibility of increasing the State’s revenues, $ien I visited Gwadur in ection with the murder of Ghulam Ali I suggested to Mr, Hedge ock that he should accompany me, not in connection with rr rder of course but to investigate financial conditions on the s^ot. The sloop which was taking me would doubtless rive him a passage too, and he could accompany me back on the mail* special arrangements for diverting which would be made, thus involving a minimum of absence from Muscat, He said he would rather not cone. Sohar, which previously he regarded as a possible source of extra revenue, he now dismisses as such. He nay be right but he cannot say for certain until he has been there and made investigations on the spot. X have suggested this to him pointing out that the deposition of Sheiith Hamad affords an excellent opportunity for lightening of the revenue administration there. He seems luke-warm, however, about a visit and talks vaguely of taking up the question of the provinces in the Autumn*. 5. Briefly there is all the difference between a Pinancia. Adviser who is 'all out' to increase the revenues of the State, and one who - because he has committed himself to a certain definite prophe.y of bankruptcy - sees his frophecy in danger of being nullified by any unexpected increase of revenue. Mr. Hedgoock seems to me to be in the latter position - admittedly a difficult one. 6 . 1 do not wish it to be thought that my strictures on Hr. Hedgcock are in any way actuated by personal feelings, or that I do not recognise his good qualities, or the go he has done here. If indeed my personal relations most friendly with him I could not successfully have , taken the action mentioned in para 3 above, and thereby saved him from utting himself in a false position. He is a capable ha orking financier and following Mr. Thomas Has a difficult ob to tackle. But he is 'temperamental* - tnough ne does not t . nt his habit of putting up his ook it, impetuous and impatient. Hia na tatiiai'-a. otuiLjajrten tly ^ r&lt;t!arguments occur to him t has not a little complicated the situation# 5 7 . If it is decided to accept Mr# Hedgcock*s resignation it should not he difficult to find a successor# The terms offered by the State are good, though Mr. Hedgcock is dissatis fled with them, (para 2 above), nor should his successor find his task a difficult one after the investigation which Mr. ledgcock has made tfith the various departments of the State# In fact Mr. Hedgcock’s term of duty here might be regarded as the visit of a Financial Expert, (such as is ^he fashion now-a-days for most small countries to receive), who has made certain financial recommendations, which have to be weighed against certain other considerations, (e.g. contentment of the armed forces of the State), and which will gradually be put into force as circumstances permit. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. P. S • Mr.Hedgcock has at the last moment, suo more, handed me another letter, his resignation to the Council, for forwarding you# I have no time to comment on it. I have informed him that I cannot, of course, let him have a copy of my despatch to the Political Resident as it is confidential#TTpHi- Telegram - R. ij’rom liesident, 'Varela” Henjamradio, To ^/^olitical, Muscat, Mo. T-54 Dated 8c deceived i4tii April 1931. t 4 ** &amp; ?C I iy Your telegram Ko.xlO. I agree with you that in the circumstances it would he better to j. e t Hedgcock go, it will take time ( undecipher able grou^) to find suitable successor and it is doubtful whether it will be possible to get anyone } till autumn. ^Iban has commanded Muscat Levies and has acted previously as Political Agent and ...ill act for you, the only suggestion I can make is that he should advise Council on linance matters during summer in addition to his own duties receiving small allowance, p-eaoe ascertain whether this arrangement would be agx&amp;s* agreeable to Council. Ii so I will reco^end it to Government of India, Hedgcock could then leave when Alban arrives. ll ’ 6 ~ Telegram- A. - ’'Varela 11 Henjamradio, prom Resident, To Political Agent, I'uscat, Ho. T-59 dated and deceived 14th April 19ZI. Your telegram Ho.xi3. I ap^xove./ w Telegram -t* political&gt; Muscat. Bri tconsul, Bushire* 18th April 1931* Brom To 1 TO. &gt;»a v*ea /3^ Your telegram 1\0*T*54* Council have now changed their minds and have asked Kedgcock to reconsider his resignation and give them , final re^ly when Saiyid Said returns from Karachi in a month’s time. Hedgcock has agreed to do so. Though I think it would he better for Hedgcock to go it would have tenj been impolitic for me to have pressed Council to accept his resignation forthwith, I suggest we wait and see what Hedgcock* s iinai reply is» X leave ior Karachi today*Copy on File 11^ K II Telegram H* From To Reoident, BuLhire. Fowle, KsraGhi. Ho* 2S1. ^^ted and received 21st April 1931. I have just received your memorandum forwarding Hedgecoclc’s resignation. T consider his attitude deplorable and that his retention would not 'be in interests of ^t;te and detriment to relations between them and Government of India. I am therefore recommending to Government that I should be authorised to advise Council to accept resignation.Telegrnm From P. Fo%le f Cavsrnpore* Resident, Buehire No. ^ pit** 28th /pril 1931 • I le£&gt;ve Cawnpore 29th* The Sultan and 1 have r et are and X having another interview at Lahore on my way to Karachi. Sultan hae wired £alyid Said to meet ue ther^. T anall he at Lahore from morning 30th till morningl let of £ f ay. addreee care of Station Mae ter. I reach Karachi on 2nd Fay, from where T will telegraph. The above ta in continuation of my telegram 2 - .. ? ith referenoa to your telegram No.260. Saiyid Said ia in Karachi until about the middle oi '-y v 1 c '' my telegram So.XMX. ShniKh Zubair merely follows hie lead and eo Paly id Said virtually comprieefc the Council. hie being eo I veriturt to euggeet that 3 oould do neces sary consultation in KarachiTelegram. From To Fowle, Cawnpore. Alsaid, Dehra Dun Dated 28th April 1531. Much regret ro hear of your illness. We discus -ed matters fully here and unless you particularly wish to see me in which case please send me an urgent telegram I propose returning to Karachi 29th leaving here 15 hours Am sending Saiyid Said letter care of you. Fowle.tW 41 •coilt•at in th« C«rp» # J my mention that the original sanctioned strength of the Corps was 240 t end it has now been reduced to 150| no further reduction in the number of personnel was therefore poeaible if the Corps was to retain ouy walue a* a fitting force* Captain filter further agreed to effect many other reductions in the number of followers and non«eombat*nt personnel and a total reduction in the levy budget ef 'He* 12,000 was agreed to* I also stated my willing* ness, not as stated in &amp;r* Hedgoock* s latter, to agreo to a further cut in pay later on, but, if the financial position 3 *ue it absolutely necessary, to consider further economies in the Miry Corps towards the sloes of the current year* X left Muscat in the belief that the matter had been settled and accepted by both parties* Shortly after wy return, howerer, to a* •urprloo 1 rMolrod * l*U«r tram tho olitical gent to the oil act tiu t they^f inaneial position was worse than had been anticipated and informing me that the Council asked for a further cut in the men 1 s pay* This request was supported by no figures, but merely by some isolated net as from Mr* Hedge ock, snowing there had been a decline in the easterns receipts* ?h* iolitieel did not support the re&lt;iesst. I considered however that it weald fee desirable to giro a eoneidsred reply to the Ceuacil ** 1 therefore instructed the i olitieal t ‘° ol9tft ^ n froia ^ r * Hedgcook a revised budget estimate to substantiate the contention that the finances of the state did actually necessitate such drastic measures* COfiuaunications with husoat are very slow sod it tf*kes at the shortest three we 1® get a reply from there, and by this time it the '^areh and I left for &gt;elhi on a riBlt to the OoTernaent of India* X had submitted a report regarding the redsetieoi I* the • • •7 current y«ar f to at least Fi*17 # 0CO* He aake however not aerely that the econoroy should amount to a certain figure but ahould be offected In the particular way that he preeerlbee and totally fail# to recognise that he hae been set, in my opinion, moet liDerally and eympethetlcally, Xq 0 In the penultimate paragraph of hie letter iledgeock ref ere to hie disagreement with the apparent policy of the Government of India on mere fundamental iseuee* hat these fundamental ieeuee are 2 have not the leael knowledge, unleee It be that the Musoat ^tate should be Absolute meter in its own house and should be at liberty to abolish or reduce the levy Corps as it thinks fit* If this is correct, the answer is that the Muscat State looks to the British Government to defend it from external enemies, and as long as this is the case* the British Government have a reasonable right to ask that the state should maintain suoh a lores as will enable it to deal, at any rate, wi th minor troubles. 11. hot having obtained hie deaanae in toto, Mr. Hedgcook has apparently adopted wh&amp;t 1 can only descr^ ue t * an attitude of sulkiness and has made little or no further attempt to improve the resources of tho state* *hen i was is Muscat he laid great etrees on the fast that he hoped to obtain largely increased revenues from the rich date-producing Bat inch ooaet* the control of this oosst had lor may ysars pm been In the imnde of one Seiyid Hamid, e brother ef the Suit an, who had paid leee end lee# revenue* into the centra treeeury till during the leit year he only remitted e.l30C. Seiyid 'Hamid had further adopted a moet eontumaeioue attitude tower da the Council, and had refused t# acicnowled*# their authority, Ur. Hedgcock informed me that he thought *.«e revenue obtainable from this dietrlot should amount to about ae,30,000. ♦ • •P# 5C,00€. teiyid h«lr-upp^rtot, p roe®«icd ^«r»oimUy to Sob&amp;r with an eecort of tha L#fy Corp® roraorod sniyid Ha^idf thereby a*oort;n^ tho authority of th® Cou oil* Thwn t »ur*ly f mt tho tijao for Ur* Kod^oaofc to prooeod to -*ohar to oxasiino and roor^anioo tho finanoo® of that district, but it will b* soon from iajor lo«l® f i Xottor that n® decline® to do so and taU® vaguely of proceed- log there in the aututan. Ui«iUerly it will bo seen that he refused to accompany the 1 olitiool Agent to Owadur fclthou ;h the latter offered to arrange a paeoage for hin in a •loop. 12. 'hen 1 wae in Muscat» Ur* hedge ook infomed sae that he wee urging on alyid uid the desirability of mking eats in the family allowancee* but apparently owin^ to the foot that the pay of the leries has not been reduced to the extent that Ur* H*4«S®ek demanded this idsa has bssn given up* and doubt lees now that i\» has been informed by hi® financial adviser that the woes of the state are due to the uneympathetlc attitude of the Goverixaent of India* aiyid ^eid will not U e any eteps to introduce sueh unpopular aeaeuree* 13. I consider Mr* iiedgcock’e conduct has been deplor able* I hr to done my beet to rtssiet him and have* 1 oeneidert met him more tlian half way, but he has totally failed to re- cognise the fact and has done his best to make relation® bstween the Government of India and the Stats as difficult as possibls. I consider that by his conduct hs h^s shown hlm*#f mentally unfitted for ths appointment. It *» vaseriial tbs appointment should be held by an ofi i ^ - * - e.^t^lt. temperament* with a reasonable spirit of give take and # finally, with considerabls tact* in *1* thsss qwslltiss Hedgeock seems to be looking# - r ■ tC0 ' •hould be authorised to advise the Council to oeccp resignation.in •*• «&amp;» If tni* recoiAmenaatioa 1» r^rav^dt it i» ne««»» iry to co«®i^ r arrang«ia*nai to bo aodo for tho faturo* CU^Ula AXb«n !• procooding ohortly to Muoeat to offioUte oo political Afont# ^ tomli tho du«l appointment of Coi&amp;mndont of the jtoYios and Ilnanoial AdTioor during 1925 for over a year, and later in 192b he officiated as Political Agent* during this period he gained a very elde knowledge of the state* he h-a trarel^ad extensively through the whole are^ within which the writ of Muscat rune# and knows the country and the peoplc f and heo also a thorough knowledge of the system of adiainietro* tion* Further, he le an officer of exceptional seal and energy* 1 % I consider it undesirable in principle that the iolitical Agent should combine the duties of Financial adviser, though, i believe, that in practice, when .ur* innate was i olltical Agent the e, tie did exercise a very large aeaeure of financial control. t propose therefore, subject to the approval of the G©vcrn«e»t of India, to mfora the Council that it will not be possible te find a Financial Mviser at one, but that Captain ^Iban, whom they already Know well, assist them with his advice while actin* a* Felitioal aont. in the autusm when sajor iowl# ree-usee the ppoi»t»ent Political Agent 1 would recommend that Captain /*lban saould be appointed Financial Adviser and should also at r trial at any rate, eonwaand the levies* stated acove h except! mol qualifieatione for thee# peete and has al 3F combined these two functions for more than a &gt;ear, and convinced that he will perform the w^rk effioisntlF *»* * ith st keenness and seal and, if a^ one can re.tore the state t tnAt it is her a eonaition of solvencyCo -9- w , | jI \ In oaoe tht*re •nouid be any difficulty about aafein* the 40 officer of the iolitioal apartment «Tail-* able for an extra cadre appointment, I would nention that I hate already euggeeted that an officer not on the cadre of tit* i olitlcal department ehould be appointed to relieve Captain Bradshaw, my Secretary, when the latter goes on leave in the autumn# It la desirable that a decision should be come to in this matter ae soon ae possible. U Is no use keeping on, Ion* er than can be helped, an officer in the state who is obviously 4ise*ti*fied and ie making but little attempt to improve the finances of the state, and the longer the situation last* the worse will it become. I would therefore solicit orders by telegram# 18 t X am sending a copy ofdespatch by air m 1 1 to Hie Bajeety^ fecretary of State for India# I li r fi: li ' It I habe the honour to be, Sir, Your moot obedient servant, sd/ H.V.Kiscoe, lt#Colo»el, olUicni e.ideBt in the iereiMi .uli. ZsS* In reahing to t-orrect/ I ^r r : f r»r l(11 effect from the l--t t-- )|ot be during the reduction oi Ks. 12, finanolal year ie the same current year: the hui- •• d ction 0 f expenditure ||| &gt; ae the calendar year. ;“ r ainount t0 about during the current -ra* - aanent reduction and ( Re. 15.00°. i-«- fl.^ee of Oomnandant. He. b,000 owing to absenceCopy forwarded to the wiitical Agent at Karachi, for information, reference his lett dated the 14th April 1931* Atte sted:- .British Kesidency ard Consulate -Hentral * Bus hire, 22nd April_1931.Telegram Code From Resident, Buehire# To Fowle, Karachi. Bo. 282 Dated 4th May 1931* *&gt; Your telegram of 28th April. I agree. I here 29th 1/ay. You should arrive by fast mail due Vednesday 27th. Resident.Confide nt jial. • X).0- -W 0, 1931. British nesidency ana Consulate-General, uuBhire, 2lst April 1931, '^hile at uelhi i discussed the muscat questions generally vd th the foreign secretary though in the absence of detailed figures i v;as not in a position to submit any concrete proposals. Mr howell took the view that a cut in men’s pay was a serious matter and was inclined to think tnat nad the proposal to reduce the pay of the men by ns. 2 been referred to the government of india it would probably not have been sanctioned. However, as j. had arranged ohe matter locally, he did not propose to interfere, and generally he saw ejre to eye with me in this matter, namexy, that while we were quite ready to assist nedgcock to the ■best of our ability by effecting every possible economy in the levies, it was not a matter in which we should move too fast; he agreed that the cut already made was adequate for the time-being but that we were of course quite ready to consider the matter further later on, if this economy proved inadequate. While we felt the force of walker's argument that it was undesirable to have men servigg alongside each other on different rates of pay, we felt it might ultimately have to be fiaced as a reduction ox pa^ 11 - the case of new entrant s v , Pom • ^ w C.H.iil. , I.A., C/n .. 1 Ca ^ A Sent, mus cat, Karaev. i ' 0Stn!a8ter -. an ts seemed to be the only feasible solution of the problem. ^ II 0 ' ' W ^ view of* the t'ac 4 ' that a large number of* the men a v e v 0T1 furlough and the Commandant is normally on a two-months’ p Wv* QOC , t recommended that no successor should be appointed to reces^j-’ * * n j^Yer for four months, and this was approved. This will effect a further saving of about Rs. 5,000 and therefore we shall have •reed to a saving amounting to Rs.17,000 against Rs.21,;Q00 esked ] ^ or w Hedgeock. He must admit therefore that we have met him Vf5r y 1 liberally* I consider that in the circumstances his resignation (k splays ouite an unreasonable spirit, and a complete failure to recognise the support that he is receiving. 0 n^ one point he seems to be under an illusion: in his M Levy Budget: precis of events” of which he sent me a copy with his private letter,dated' the 27th March 1931, he states that the sanctioned strength of the Corps is 150: this, as you know, is not the case. The sanctioned strength of the corps is about 240 and it has been reduced free that figure to the present strength without reference| to the Government of India, and we feel that a he.lt should now te called; the State have always objected to the corps; the Sultan tried to get out of having a levy c 0 j.ps ff-.en started, and naturally when they find the 5 'inancio.l Advis determined to cut down the corps as far as possible, they e reet the proposal with enthusiasm. . a +v- rvronosal for a loan, Hedgcock suggests As regards the proposal xux fhpt the Council may or that we should get sanction ^or i pp that it is not may not accept it. You will, I am sure, for He^gcock to apply for a loan but for the Council; it is quite ^ + r, -i-Vip Cove^nment of Indies' and as^ impossible for me to go up to the ^ove.r . + ■Wp told that the Council them to sanction the loan and then . , i v_ r-attpr should have been don't want it, and I do not think the t fh t nk Hedge ock has shown himself submitted to me in this form. I thin temperamentally unfitun fxt for the post of jrinancial Mvieer at muscat. ne is inclined to rush his fences and his action in throwing in his hand because he has not got exactly what he wanted, has impressed me very unfavourably. ± feel we want for the post someone with a more pliant mind and less aggressiwe« X do not think ’Iraq really is a very good training ground. An officer used to rigid administration carried on on regular British lines is naturally somewhat aghast at the less regular methods in vogue in muscat, but those of us who have served in Indian states realise that simpler and more orimative or, if you like, more irregular methods frequently work just as will in practice, Alban has already acted as rolitical Agent at Muscat, and alio filled the combined posts of uinanciai Adviser and Commandant of the nevy Corps, and i am quite convinced that he would be a great success there, ne knows everyone in the place; is lull ol keenness and zeal, and l think would run the place on the right lines* i should very much like him to act in your absence provisionally as financial Adviser ana then possibly wnen you went back to Muscat, he could stay on as financial Adviser and Commandant of the levies. ihis would be ar economic arrangement for the state; he has ail - lu J two jobs in Wingate's time and, i believe, _ou.d comb in them again. Since drafting the above i have just receivea your memorandum forwarding nedgcock's resignation*^ emphasises the impression i had already lormed. obviously lost his temper because ne has not got y what he wants and is now sulking. We really cannot have a financial Adviser v/ho sasipai complains aboutabout tiie attitude of what he calls the Government of India, actually myself, and I think the sooner he goes the better. I have just received your private and personal tele gram of 23rd April. I see your point but I think the issue will have to he faced. 7/e cannot have at Muscat as Financial Adviser an officer who informs the state that all their difficulties are due to the unsympathetic attitude of the British Government. I think you might let Hedgeock know the view taken in Delhi about any further reduction in the men’s pay, which I have given above. This will anyhow show \ him that it is not likely to be approved. If he goes, the matter is settled and all is well. If he reconsiders the * matter, then I think there is nothing to be done but to advise the Council to accept his resignation. As long as he is there relations between the State and the British Government are bound to be bad. He is ooviously sulking, and will make no effort to improve the State’s finances, since this wio.1 prove his case. It would be better to get rid cf him and th^n work gradually to undo the mischief he has done. As regards Alban I agree that while acting as Political Agent he should only advise, as you will see from a copy of my despatch to the Government of India which I am sending you. If out to Saiyid Said the bait of being in executive charge of the finances, it may make him think better of xeepin^ on Bed 0 cTelegram P. X f737 From Resident, Eushire To Fowle, Karachi No. 298. D. and R. 9th Kay 1931. Demi-official. T have received a telegram from Howell to the effect that Hedgcock has written to him and that he has replied not attempting to diauade from resigning. persist Presumably therefore H- will in his intention and matter will settle itself. If so unless you consider it desirable there would seem to be no necessity to discuss the matter with Saiyid Said ixikxhB.r until he receives a definite reply from H-. Government of India approve of Council being informed as proposed in my despatch No.202-S, dated 27th April paragraph 15. They consider however that post of financial Aaviser snould be definitely i held in abeyance until permanent arrangements can be made which are at present under consideration, xhis communica tion could be made when H's resignation has finally receivedTele£ rani Code From Fowle, Karachi To Political, Muscat Ho. &gt;[K rj. 18th May 1931. Pollov/ing for Hedgcock from Saiyid Said 'begins as Major Fov/le is leaving for Bushire on 24th snd as I would like to discuss future arrangements with him 'before he leaves I would 'be grateful if you could let me have a reply by telegram with regard to your resignation.ends. Fowle.$ '(lij) Telegram Code prom Fowle, Karachi To Resident, Bushire. Ho. 50-K paled 21st May 1931. In reply to a communicstion from Saiyid Said asking Hedgcock to give reply regarding his resignation as he wished to discuss with me future arrangements before my departure for Bushire H. has replied as follows begins:- In view of your request for early decision prepared continue serve your Government and withdraw my resignation . Please inform liajor Fowle ends.Telegram Code From Resident, Bushire To Fowle, Karachi. No. 322 D. 22 nd R. 23rd May 1231. Important. Your telegram dated 21st Bay 50-K. I am inclined to recommend to Government that Council should he advised to dispense with the services of Hedgcock. Please wire your views. Resident. Telegram Code Prom Fowle, Karachi To Resident, Bushire No. 56-K Dated 23rd May 1931. Your telegram No.322. I entirely concur.!(? V' Telegram - Cede, from fowle# .^araciiif Te Political, Muscat Dated &amp;, deceived 18th May 1931, Ho. Following for Hedgeoch from Saiyid Said beginsi- 'As Major Fowle is leaving for Bushire on 24th and as I would like to discuss future arrangements with him before he leaves, I would be grateful if you could let me have a reply by telegraph with regard to your resignation, 11 Ends. Fowle. i ii r ,ii! m Forwarded Muscat State. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M 1 s consulate Muscat f 19th Hay 1931. to S.E.Hadgcocic, Esquire, Financial Adviaar, political &amp; H.B.M’s ConsulBritish Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 29th May 1931. !&amp;(&gt; A copy of Government of Inaia telegram No. 142 1-S* dated 26th May 1931, is forwarded to the Polit- -ical Agent, Muscat, for action as indicated in para- -graph 12 of the Hobble the Political Pesiaent’s letter to the Government of India, No. 202-S, dated 22nd April 1931. g' Copies of the telegrams quoted in the Gov- -ernment of India telegram are enclosed, together with a copy of a letter, dated 28th May 1931. from Colonel (j Biscoe to Saiyid Said. 3 . A copy of the Political Resident's despatch No. 202-S. dated 22nd April 1S31, was forwarded on the 22nd April 1931. By order, Capt ■ * Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.35/138 )(&gt;l Tel0S raB1 from To HO. 1421-^ i/ated 26th* Government of India, Foreign d Political .Department. 8imla # Political i^esident,Bushire. received 27th. kay 1931. Your telegrams Bos. 324,326 and 327 of lay 25th. 1. Yon are authorised to take action as suggested in paragraph thirteen of your despatch No.202-s of April 22nd. 2. Government of *nida agree,that if State Council see no objection, that Hedgoock he given ttxree months pay and passages home for himself and wife. 3. In case Syed Said's health fails in Muscat Gove nment of India agree that as emergency measure Aldan may act as Financial Adviser. Foreign.£$ 16 ? o Telegram From To Ho. 324 -at-od 25th. hay 1521. Tour telegram 1291-o of 8th. ^ay. Respite terms of your latter to him, fiedgcock has now telegraphed to Saiyid oaid that he is prepared to continue to serve luscat verrment and withdraw his resignation. l presume 1 may now act on authority conveyed in your telegram referred to above, and advise Council as suggested in paragraph 13 of my des- -patch No.202-3 of 22nd. April 1931. I consider bis retention at Unseat after what has happened , as most undesirable. Resident . R. Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department. Simla.G.T.C. Political iiesiaent, Busture. Goveiinment of India,Foreign &amp; Politick Department. Simla. Copy By airmail Secretary of State for India. London. No. 326 JJated 25th. Lay 1931. Following from Political Agent, Muscat 'begins:- ' x n spite of advice of doctor and Sultan and much pressure from myself, Saiyid Said insists on returning to Muscat leaving here on the 31st.^ay. If he creaks down there, approval of Government of India for Alhan to act as Financial Adviser will still he useful. M ends. BBSIDENT. 1' tf IL Telegram From To G.T.C Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, Foreign Political Department, oimla. Copy by airmail Secretary of State for India, Londor,. No 227 ,ated 25th. fey 1921. has reference to of 17th. fey. l. y iiameulately preeeaing telegram overnmentof India telegram No.1253 Besia ent — oJr British Residency# Bush!re, the 28th Hay 1931. (§&gt; I am so sorry to hear that you have been lilt X hope that you hare not been unwise In returning to :iuscat against the doctor's adrioe, and that if you get ill again there you will at once leave for a cooler cliaate. I am glad that during Major Fowle' a temporary a senee the poet of Political Agent, Muscat, will be held by an officer who has already been Political Agent before, and who has also commanded the Levies ana also acted as Financial Adviser. He is therefore well acquainted with local conditions, and X am sure you will find him most sympathetic and ready to advise and asaist you in any way he can. I understand that Mr. Hedgcock has since withdrawn his resignation, the Government of India however have instructed me to advise the Council to accept Mr.Hsdgcock's resignation and to dispense with hi. services. A. you know the relation, between the State of 'Oman and the Government of India have for , rr close and intimate, and I a* you many years been close a + *&amp;id to you before a as M&amp; 1 or Fowle aaiu WO J will recogniee that as «« — , » y ° U of India in the past. M* that he does not appio ve in hie letter of resignatio see^ 170 at the general policy of the OoTernnent of India, and I am confident that Hia Highness would not desire to retain in g0 i B portant a post in the seryiee of the State an officer who holds euch views, which must obviously render difficult that close collaboration between the State and rirltiB h authorities which is so essential for the prosperity of •Onu-n. In these eiroumstances I am sure that you will agree with me that it would be better that Hr. Hedge 00 k'a services should be dispensed with. #ith kind regards. {(£)) Crt.COKFIDEHTIAL. /?/ Ho.(? li^jot 1931. (^&lt; 3 ^ Political Agency &amp; H.B.M'e Consulate, • * Muscat, ath Jur.e 1S31. To The Council of Ministers to H.H* the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. i\fter Compliments. / Tith reference to the resignation submitted to Your Honours by Mr. S.E. Hedgeook, Financial Adviser to the State, I am directed by the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to inform you that the Government of India, in view of the attitude taken up by Mr. Hedgeock and the terms in which the application is worded, consiuer that it would be preferable that the resignation be accepted and the services of Mr. Hedgcock be terminated from the 30th of June 1931. I am also to add that the Government of India recommend** that If Your Honours see no objection ( Mr. Hedgcock be given three months pay and passages home for himself and his wife. This ia what had to be said and salama. ^V- captain, . « -r t's Consul, Muscat. Political Agent &amp; H.B.i. • ! f J « |ll It^v )&amp;) \ ^fn V&amp;ImT Telegram Cede* yrem Pelitical* Muscat, Te Britconsul, Bushire, &lt;§) is. 131 Dated 10th June 1931* HeTised and balanced budget ceasing inte ferce July first from which, date State ceoDiencee te become A&gt;- f AAA/JL' selvent, I suggest early telegraphic appreyal te IZ±% reduction in Lory e me lumen te, this cut has already been announced and has been accepted eheerfully 0 Pay will new stand at He*25 plus geed cenduct pay plus ratiens, clothing etc still en high side. Council has verbally con sented te meet wishes ef Government and dispense with services ef Hedgceck, am awaiting written reply to siy letter recommending date ef terminatien June 30th, hedgeech geing en recess Friday 12th with intent!en ef visiting Simla and making final appeal te Fereign Secretary* I have experienced no difficulty either witn Council er Hedgcook#Copies i» files S2/12 Vol.Ill &amp; 35/5 Telegram- Code, jj’rom Hesident, Bushire, Xo irolitical, lluscat, KO • 3 b b (§) Dated Sc deceived 13th June 1931. Your telegram No.131. I approve of 12 and (■$■ omitted) per cent reduction in Levy emoluments tut in future please ask for my approval for your demands before they are announced and not after. Telegram - Code. jj‘ r om yisI Resident, Bushire, X 0 Political, Luscat, No.356 Dated and received 13th June 1931. %^ T ' p.i7' v ' Your telegram No. 131. flease tele t raph when you receive written consent of Council to dispense with Hed S oook's services. Telegram - Code. Prom Resident, Bushire, To Political, kuscat, No.358 v Dated &amp; xteceived 13th June 1931 i? Yours telegram 131. udget as soon as possible. rlease send me revisedPolitical A«ent and H.B.I- ^ Consul, Muscat. Political Afency &amp; H.B.M’s Coneulate, Muscat, 15th June 1931. To The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. After Compliments. With reference to my letter iTo.C-129 d 8 ted June 8 th 1931 I have to inform Your Honours that on June 13th I received a telegram from the Hon'tle the Political Resident requesting me to inform him hy telegraph when your reply to my above letter may be expected. ! request that you may Kindly expedite the reply as eoon a8 l 0Bs t&gt;le This is what had to be said and salams. Captain,^fter Compliments. 1^)7/ . ( ^e had the pleasure of receiving your letter i:o.C-i29 Luted June 8 th 1931, we ^eru^ed it with interest and under stand that according to your message from the Hon’tle the Political Resident, the Government of India consider that in vievj of the attitude adopted by hr. Hed^cock and the terms in which his application was worded it would be preferable that hr. Hed^coch’s resignation be accepted and his services dispensed with from 3Cth June 1^31. 7e also note that the Government of India recommend that if we see no objection Hr. Hedge ock be paid three months salary and passages home for himself and his wife. In accordance with the discussions which took place between us, our reply is, that, in consideration of suggestion made by the Government of India and the view they have taken of the wording of I'r. liedgcock’s application, heartily a^ree with the recommendation made o, ' hem ar ‘ a all that may be to the interest and advantage of Muscat State. . + .„ rovernment of India kindly to appoint Tfe boy/ request the Gover eno i m,- &lt; 3 + -te of muscat another man who ss Jinanciai Adviser to one at^ it i enced and who should know Aranc. should be capable ana experienced anu j.. a 4 /ik-i itvn + i T 'hhe We ouraelves will car^j v on the finance duties until the ‘ival of Mr. Hedgcoch’s successor. . +hp Government of Indie to r 7 e also rcc^uest the u v ^psire to strengthen the it we are firm in our desi c onsider friendly relations existing between Usual Ending*ConfldsntUl. Ho. C- or 1931. political Agenoy &amp; H.B.H'a Consulate, # Muscat, 15th June 1931* To The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. After Compliments. I had the pleasure of receiving your letter Mo. 5 dated the 26th Moharram 1350 (14th June 3931) the contents of whi.h I read with muoh interest. It is noted that you agree with V recommendation of the Government of India that hr. Hedge ook's services he terminated from the 30th June 1931 and that he be given three months salary and passages home both for himself and for his wif«« The above together with your r.r . ........ “ .,u b. ° f dia* I take this opportunity of nveying to you th. pleasure with the Government of India and the , n .Ue the Political Resident will learnTg&gt; of friendship and mutual eo-oper&amp;tion expressed by you on behalf of the Muscat State towards the Government of India* This is what had to be said and salams* yiY- Captain, Political Agent A H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat* »c , II 'C onf idcnti'il • / S' From The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Suita oi a .use a t and Oman, Mu scat. To - Cup cain R • Gr• A1 can, H.R.Iu’s Consul, Tluscct. fo . 6 -. Rated 27th Toharram 1350 (loth June 1231). After Compliments j /7^ At an auspicious time v.c received your letter of toady’s date, 15tli June li31, }. r o.C-i36 and noted whet you so&gt;id on the subject of your letter Jo.C-i2S cf 8 th r une 1531 and re. ardins a telegram received by you from the Kon’tle the Resident requesting you to inform him v/hen a reply to the above letter may be expected. 7e have to inform you that v/e v/rote you a letter unde .c *-.0 - of yesterdey T s date, but as yesterday v/as Sunday auu. your office was closed y;c did not send it to you. It v/as sent to you this norniny before the receipt of your above mentioned letter.Confidential y I frl' Ko. C-/3jot 1931. Politioal Afeney &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, # Muscat, 15th June 1931* To The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat* After Compliments. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.6 dated the 27th Moharram 1350 (15th June 1931). Please accept my sincere thanks for your excellent reply and my apologies for having troubled you unnecessarily* This is what had to be said and salams* Captain, Acent &amp; H.B.K'* Consulr (7* Ic l/ M*.C-140 of 1931. The Peltticai Agency h H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, 17th June 1931, Ga^tam political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, The Secretary to the Hen’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. Sir, 1 hr.ve the honour to forward herewith copies of the / il.C-129 D/ 8-6-31 to Council of Uinistors i mr C inaUy not 5 D/14-6-31 from *d0- I , llo.C-136 Ti/15-6-31 to -^o- 5 * 0 . 6 -do- from -do- correspondence exchanged between Ho, 0-1 st; -do- to -do- * Ho.0-139 -do- this office and IS!' | - state, concerning the termination of Council of Ain listers, Muscat th« eerTicea of Mr. S.K.Hedgcoci, /inanciax ..aviaer. j* Tv/ &gt;v*a •• id three months pay 2. lir.Hed^coch will accordingly be P^id tm „ to the United Kingdom for from July 1st and be given passag himself and his wife, to l8 tter ho.O dated 26th Moharram 1350 3, With reference to lei-tr t Council sf Ainist^rs, paragraph 4, it (Hth June 1931), from the Goancii „ ,, ^ requesting the Government of 1b to oe noted that the Coum- „ T Adviser possessing the qualifl- laaia to provide them witli ano cations enumerated* . - i.tter is also worthy of note. last paragraph of the »am ^iaer at for a new adviser au There is no immediate nec a and prices have practically present, as the Budget is balance ceased to decline* The 4, I have the honour to be, mfl . t obedient servant, Your mo bt. k P© litical Agent &amp; H*Bi Captaini U» s Consul*Telegram- (GTC) Jrom Political, Muscat, n’ 0 3ritconsul, Bushire. r IJo.C-142 Dated 24th June 1931, I Hed^cocic wires from Simla successful. Council have dispensed with his services from 30th June. If Government have reversed decision telegraphic instructions should he £ sent to me. u.V , : i &gt; iTelegram (u.T.C) From rolitical, Muscat f £ 0 xiesident, Bushire No.147-C -nated 30th June 1931. Said Saiyid/has called on me to remind that HedgcocK’s service* have 'been terminated today. He appears to he anxious that Hedgcocie should leave as soon as possible. Saiyid Said is managing very well now and seems anxious to he allowed to carry on. Unles^ie is allowed to run his own state he will never develop into an independent ruler, he shows great promise and is about to ^o to Sur to study and if possible settle the Customs question. In any case under no circumstances should Government now alter their decision retarding Hedg^cock. In accordance with orders 1 shall as* him to leave as soon as he returns from India.Telegram (G#T.C.) iTrom Political, Muscat Britconsul, Bushire No*146-C Bated 2nd July 1931* Following telegram has been received from Hedgcock Foreign Secretary vashes me by Council, begins:- proceed July 5th fast mail Bushire discuss official matters with Resident. May I have Council’s permission, Hed^cock, Bristol Hotel, Karachi;’ Ends. Services of Hedgcock terminated June 30th and Council do not feel they can authorise this in present circumstances. Hedgcock must act privately until officially reinstated. Please confirm this for the information of the Council*Telegram (GTG) From riesiident f Buahire To -t'clitical, Muscat, 1^0.385 Bated &amp; Red. 3rd July 1931. b I s ' Your telegram Iso. 148. I agree v.ith Council’s vievijt &amp;-nd have wired to Hedgcocic accordingly adding that if he liked to come here privately I am prepared to discuss matters with him. Demi-official . I wired on gist of your telegram dated £4th June No.i42-C demi-officially to i’oreien, actually I presumed Government had not changed their mind H going but received no reply.Telegram- (GTC) ?rcm Political,Muscat, Britconsul, Bushire Ke. 150-C Bated 4tii July i931« 0 i«7 Your telegram N©.385. Have informed Council. As Government has left matters in your hands I suggest ueation of reinstatement should not he discussed with Pedgcocic. The matter is closed now and he should leave the country without further delay. His attitude up to date of leaving here suggested had feeling on part of State towards Government whereas I find no such feeling exists. it is not in the best interests of the State or its relations with the Government of India to reinstate him. I would ur&amp;e that the Council are doing well now and should not he interfered with again. /7 ' ^7 r f 11 |.|| ■I: ilito fraud and lax collactton on the j&gt;art of the cuetoaa farmers, the exyendl ture alnaye exceeded the rerenue. 4 . It was at this stage, in m», that the Oorernment of India stef#ed in with the offer of financial assistance to fay off the Sultan's debts. In return for this the Sultan wae to reform his administration and to assist him in this a lurofean Adviser was engaged. 5 # Th* prim* reason for engaging and retaining the serrioss of this official was to supervise the wording of the n fonns mentioned above» control expenditure and watch the oollsction of revsnus by the customs* Of ths Sultan, llajor Haworth wrote in 1919, “he is wtalc in mny w*ys, though not in all, while in any case he is totally ignorant M • 6# tfnder these circumstances, with the stats finances in complete chaos, so complete that no accounts oi revenue or expenditure were in existence other than those contained in the Bannia 9 s private account books, with the sultan hopelessly at sea and quite unfitted to clear uj. the situation and set Uf a frofsr Treasury and Customs AcUui.is trail «iu» a re fc jiar system of accounting, there was no otuer course left open than reluctantly to engage a European Adviser until s cn t me as the State could Btand uyon its own feet. This desirable result would obviously come about her (a) by the Sultan himself develoying a Jteenness and .itude for affairs of state, or it.- “ h the., qualities. It would also be necessary to employ fieiently cafable and trustworthy heuas 01 ^ enable the machine to function with only the minimum of mrvielon. a . .«, lye years during which the state After, laye-of twelve , n hv BrlUs&gt; h Adviser., nominally -orbing » been completely rxxn oy , uvrii*t.ctrfie ttie Multan has a the Council oiproduced a coat S&amp;iyid t&gt;aid| isho wiailt posoosainf all the dignity of hi» father has ail the qualities which he lacks. 9 # At the sad of 1930 Hr* ThoiaaSf the last Adviser, completed his term of five years with the State and left. At the same time, the services of new Adviser, Mr. Hedgcock, were engaged,but, after a few months em^loyiuent in the state, his services were, for sound reasons, dispensed with. „ 4 &amp;_.^ •— la the mean time, Saiyid Said, the Heir Apparent, has suddenly come forward* He is now 21, has had a first olass education at the Chiefs College, Ajmer, and has also completed a finishing course at Baghdad* Hi takes a very deep interest in the Stats and is unhappy when out of it, he is careful over money matters, has a complete grasp of the details of the State budget and finance, his Justice and the swiftness with which he metes out retribution te offenders are a byword throughout tne country* His energy and courage are well known, it 1* only a few monXt* since ha tallied forth with a handfull of inen ana Sidpiacec. ax a uncle, the wall of Sahar, who for wu*y years has *e« , notorious for his brutality and tyranny and was ay way of beoomminc a independent ruler, Kow, again, he is Sur to study the situation there xta a view to ma 'ng lasting settlement of what has, in the past been, a rau.er disturbed area, v ._, th . dignified demeanour 11. xheoe quaUties, combined with • , , , rath . r the Sultan, and a fixed deter- a proper respect for his f&amp;wsr the long friencteh** existing mi nation to continue unabated the between the Sultanate of Muscat and Cnan *** Br4 and Indian Governmsnts, have earned for hia; t respect «d lenity of his subset. ^ ' suitable person to be entrusted with the full * the affairs of ths Stats. U* Thu dav. for .vuoh the British Government has4« tweXTe yeare» ha» now arrived and the complete admini ^ticri of the State ie now in the hands of Uie Heir Ajjarentf^y Yeeterdayt after years of deficit budgets under a British adviser during which the State has contracted some three iaos if debtst Saiyid Said entireiy unaided and alone 9 produced his firet budget* i 5 # Kotwithalanding the fact that six months of the year 1931 k**® already passed and that only on the second six months can the revised budget take effect f yet f so efieotive »re Ui* econouJ.ee »*de and eo carefully has each item been cheeked that the expenditure for the whole year 1931 will be aubatantially leee than the rerenue, and, after jaying^aoui ineUlaent of the Government of India dobt, a eurylue will . of tne deots jwintioned remain with which to cowuence repayment oi above* u , Thle, I may mention, ie &lt;iu*te unprecedented, no aember of the rulinc family hae ever been able or had Ull „ „ co,. ..u, «n»«. ^ it 1 . i.lr « “i “»• ‘ ‘ t, ,, ( ,re talked over with and urthir 1 '**** meet of the economiee were taut . , Bek before he left Muscat nearly a month •utiined by Mr. Hed*cook oeiore ♦v,« Treasury Officer tells me. &gt; •Co, yet Saiyid Said hae, v ..nditure ef item ef expenditure himself been carefully throufh ..its and reductions himself. the State and We all out. ^ ^ ^ ^ AS resards the lery C.rps, ^ r , BU lt many ooneultations with the Oifleer C laB , than that draw u# by hr. is a bud«et considerably ie - ♦. 0 t ..tin* all the requirements » Hedcoock and yet ample for ® the force as it at and a. N y . a „ n ta end deeoription ef “• im f '~‘“,»-- «« .Itu.tioo «... io Jtli „ .„. lr . « Government of India, wW* be in !«»«- of these removed from the sesns o ace of the tru itate of affaire* ooJU# t0 an and ie That the period of interred has5. dear and no further reason exists for jOaolnc a GoTermaont 9 fa trainee in control of finance and thus^ of the whole State» fir the finances and the administration of the State art bound U j toother* 1 $. The placing; of a British official in such a position in a soall State lihe MUec&amp;t, experience teaches us* is bound to load a gradual absorftien by him of all the functions of the &lt;uicr and at this particular moment it would» in addition lead to the stultification arid atrophy of those very powers of rule and administration which are beginning to show so clearly in the Heir Afjpa r ® n ^* w hieh the Government of India deoires ab0 ve all things to foster* The tendency to leave more and oero things to be done by the Adviser is bound to appear and unless the prospective Ruler himself centrels the nnances no li Marcely to bo ox#octod to fain that control of the admimo- tratiTO de^artmonto of tho SUto which io »o ooBontial. 17. Tho oubject of the late Adrlcer and tn« reaft^r.s *hy hlo eerrloea woro dla^enood with by tha State, are new. in f •f the length of time which has elajased and the imroaoibility •f the State having any further use icr his aorvieoo* Mated cal* m view, hewever, of the joBeibility o* aem .ncourafejtont having boon given him, on hi. wandoringa, to hof. fer ro«offlployment in tho State, it !• M ** 11 ** ****' that tho reasons for having adviced tho * diagOMt wi hi. sorvico. woro. that ho had taxon u, an attitude which con- reyed that tho Government of India ware not sorting . t v.t he had omdodiod those sontimsnts interesto of tho Stato and that no na in his lottor to tho Council preferring hii jfrtiirt What hoover. \i». tnat up to «... is infinitely worse, however, » , .hi* re ret to tho Govsrn- he aoment of leaving hero to •***•• ^ t e oe t tiade ,te and reftuoot that they bo •nt of India for tnose pact miS“ d &gt;-y , i ortunity of filling ny * iUl lost ». o,o*ttuiaw t •forto or «». &lt;•» •* 1 '“ ““ “State etandin* ^ wo °'' n as an inda^endend Arab jirinci* ^gXity now at la»t r«iali*ad and it 1§ bigbly desirauia tiia t no move be iaade which might tend to discourage in any wa / those who are now responsible for the administration of the State* I have the honour to bs t Slr t Your wont obedient servant# flfjQlMnu. . Obtain, Political Atfant k H.B.M’s Conaul, MuscatTeles r£in Cocie * Resident, Bushire. Political, Muscat. 3SS P.nd received 14th July 1931. yrom To Ho. Deted n4 Your telegrams Nos. 137 and 142-C. Hedgcock states that he has received no intimation from the Council terminating his services. How is it Council did not inform?Teleo-f&amp;H- (CrTC) jj’roin Political, I'uacat 10 j Hesident, Bushire No* 1 j9-'J Nated 15th July 1931 Your telegram No.399. council state they xiac. no ciiaiice to iniorm Kedgcocic. He was allowed to go to Simla privately on distinct understanding that he would return beiore end of June when he would have been informed. He knew very v/ell Council would dispense with his services on June 30th and he should not have stayed away so long without intimating his movements. Council naturally considered he was on way back. Council have now written to Bushire. Saiyid Said replied him telegraphically Karachi July 3rd saying journey Bushire could not be authorised by Council.Political A**noy &amp; H.B.li'e Coneulata J£uaoat,th» 15th July I 931 About Hedcoook. You wirad yesterday to the effect th* M was ntver informed by the Council that his resignation had been accepted by tnenie Hov, although, I have only met Hedfcock for a few days and liked him personally, I begin to think that hie treatment of the Council and me in this matter leaves something to be desired* To be brief; I arrived on th« dik* interviewed the Council on the 7th, when they gave p verbal consent to accepting Hedgcock's resignation, wrote to them on the 8 th and received their reply on the 14th saying they would do as we asked them* 2 . On the 12th, i.e. four days after ay writing to the Council end knowing all about what had occurred and that their answer was only a question of days, he asked if he might go and put up his own case at Simla* 1 naturally did not wish to stop him, so I said he could go provided the Council agreed and provided he returned by the boat of the 23rd or at latest that of June 30th. I also told him that I had put the date of termination of his services at June 30th and that he would be informed when he returned. On Jun* 12th h* l*ft. On Jun* 23rd and June 30th w* all duly turnsd out on board the mail steamers to meet Hedgoook, without any result* Later, on the 30th I cot a letter from Mm dated at Simla saying he was s°in« to Buehire by fast mail on the 5th. On July 2nd Sa 2nd Saiyid Said' received a wire 3rd 'Council cannot authorise going to Bus 3* Now, Hedgcock says he has no means, may I ask, does he suppose the C informed him? In order to reach here on the 23rd he would Bushirt.have lift Simla about the 17th, not arriving by that ahip it was concluded that he was on the way to oatoh that arriv ing the 30th. Why did he not inform the Council (a) of his address and (b) of the probable duration of his ^stay in Simla 4 , The Council have been treated rather shabbily by him and this is not an occasion when the issue can be evaded by these quibbles. The Council have now written to Bushire, as being the first fixed address they have had, informing him that his resignation has been accepted from June 30th. 5 , While on this subject I would like to say that Mr. Howell’s letter to Colonel Bisooe implies that the reason for accepting Hedgcock’s resignation was his method of attacking the Levy Question which was characterised as 'tactless * 1 and H impetuou 8 M • I have read all the correspondence on the subject and this is not at sill my impression. The reason why it was do si red to dispense with his services was hie attitude towards the Government of India end because he did not work in with the Political Officers in Muscat and Bushire. These two points remain unchanged^is further explained In ay d.epstoh No.C-156, dat.d the 8 th July ww* to your eiddresBi the Council he.e -accepted then end els Me resignation and the matter 1 b now closed. He has received three months pay in lieu of notice *nd has therefore no complaint. «. I„ o... th, » V the of the Council .nd no WMJ ln — 3 ““ | which could be filled by Mr.Hedgcock. Yours sincerel}»Confi&lt;ie ntial i* 0 * ' ihe CounoU °f “ i ' i8ters t0 H.H. the Sultan of Husoat and Oman, Musoat. 80at fo - Captain H.G. Alban, Political Agent and H.B.lI'a Consul, liuacat. NO • 25 A.C* Dated 28th Safer 1350 (15th July 1931). With reference to our conversation on the subject of Mr. Hedffcoclc and our consent to the suggestion of the Government resignation to accept his &amp;&amp;K712 lx3lx -.roin the 30th June 1931, we now forward herewith a copy of our letter to Mr. Hedgcock. It will be seen from our letter that we were unable to communicate with him before owing to the fact that we had no knowledge of his address. Te were thinking that he would return to Muscat before the date his services terminated, but he did not return and we have just come to know that he is at present at Bushire. 7/e are therefore addressing this letter to him which will be sent by today’s mail in confirmation of our verbal communication to him regarding the termination of his services from 30th June 1931.To The Council of Ministers to H.H. and Om*n, Muscat. S.S. Hedgeock. the Sultan of Muscat Ho.2. I,ted 28th ssfar 1350 (15th July 1931). A.C. You were already informed that your services with lluicat State would terminate from 30th June last. '.Ye were unable to communicate with you in writing before this because u did not know your actual address after you left Kuscat which m fr ivate and because we presumed that you would return to iuaeat before the termination of your services. Yfe have just learnt that you are at Bushire hence we are writing this letter to you in confirmation of what had been already stated.Telegram Code &gt;o&gt; From Political, Muscat. To Resident, Bushire. Dated 16th July 1931. Following despatched .yesterday’s mail letter irom Council to Hedgcock, Budget and despatch regarding Sur.ffx Telegram-Code (GTG) Jrorn Resident ,Bushire To Political, Unseat, No.406 Dated &amp; Received 17th July 1931. Your telegram No. 159. Please telegraph gist of Gouncii’s letter to HedgcocJs. S-fUfil ii-t 21 Telegram (GTG) Prom Political,Muscat To Resident, Bushire, V No.162-C Dated 18th July 1931. Your telegram No.406. Hedgcocic imew services would be terminated 30th June before which date he was expected back from private visit to Simla and could not be written to for want of proper address. Council now write confirming what he already knew.$ $_Jfi llii, ■ % Telegram- (GTC) Froia Resident, Buahire Xo Political, Muscat, 110.411 Dated &amp; Received 18tli July 1931 . Hedgcock leaves for Muscat by the next slow mail.■f y No.C- / of 1931. TUt political A«®ncy &amp; Contuiat®, Muscatf 20th July 1931. To The Council of Ministers to H'H'the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman MUSCAT. A.C. I have the honour to inform Your Honours that* according to a telegram received from the Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# Bushirc. Mr.Hedgcoclc will leave for Itu.oat bype next mail. This is what had to be said and salaams* Political Agent &amp; H.B.M*s Consul.Telegram (GTC) From To irolitical, kuscat x / resident, Bushire No. 167-C Dated 23rd July i931. Your tele train No. 411. Council is not pleased. I recommend that Hedtcock taken on as Director of Customs as at Bahrein. All revenue collected by Customs. A -&gt;ointment is very suitable as control would remain with President.Telegram- (GTG) 2 t+q To From Hesident,Bushire iroli tic alj Mu scat Ko* 426 Dated &amp; xieceived 23rd July 1931, &lt;5 y Your telegram No.167. Government of India have not yet given orders for Hedgcocic to be reinstated and I suggest that Council give him co^y of their letter of 15th July which arrived here after his departure.Office of the Accountant-General, Central Revenues. / IMPERIAL SECRETARIAT BUILDINGS. , New Delhi, the Vi June i&amp;l . The ACCOUNTANT-GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, To The Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat 1 have the honour to state that a sum of £160/- was taken in ^land by Mr. b.i.Hedgcock in November 1S60 to meet travelling expenses for himself and his wife on his appointment as financial Adviser to the Muscit Government and as this amount does not appear to have so far been recovered, 1 have to request you kindly to take steps towards the recovery of its equivalent in Indian current at the rate of Is. 6d. the rupee from the ®iscat GovernmentPolitical kgtnoy &amp; H.B.M’s C©r»ulatt # Mu»cat # th« 23rd July 1931* The Ceuncil ex' Miniatere to Hit Hichneat the Sultan of Muacat and Oman* After com*limenta# I have been requeated to tec over from the Muscat State a aum of £ 160 at the rate of !• 6d j»er rujee, which wa» taken in England by Ur. S.E.Hedgoook in November 1930 to meet travelling exyenees for himself and hie wife* Ur, Hedgcock was addressed on the subject in February last but no action Hat been tahen* This is what had to be said and salaams* ./7, Ca#tain # political Agent AH.B.H's Consul, Muscat.-C ' -Confidential. Ho.28. Dated ilth Radi al awal 1350 (27th July 1931). From - The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. To - Captain R.G. Alban, Political A*ent and H.33.M's Consul, Muscat. a.c. • m-vol 7 /e invite a reference to our letter Ho.25 dated 28th Safar 1350 (15th July 1931) enclosing a copy of our letter regarding the termination of Mr. Hedgcock’s services from the 30th June 1931, which was sent to him at Bushire. As you are aware Mr. Hedgcock returned to Muscat from Bushire on the 25th instant and we learnt that the letter sent to him did not reach him as he left Bushire before the receipt of the said letter. We however made out a copy of the above letter and delivered it to him on his arrival so as to ovoid any misunderstanding. Moreover we have had a conversation with him on the subject. This is for your information.-Confidential* No. c !&gt;i Z*t 1951. Political Aganoy &amp; H.D.’I’s Consulate, Muscat, the 27th July 1931. To The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan ef Muscat and Oman, Muscat. After Corjiliitents. I have the honour to acl^novled^e receipt of your letter No.28 of today ! s dal. on the BUtj.at of the termination ef Hr. Hedtcook's ecrvlc.e from th. 30th June 1331* This is what had to bo saiu and salaan. Captain, ' -e, i W r Political A*ent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat- iMp Confidential. vrom - The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of l T uscat and Oman, L r uscat. To - Captain R.G. Alban, H.B.F’s Consul, ITuecat. Ho. ITil. Dated 22nd Rabi al awal 1350 (7th August 1931). f.tf. J\/* acii A.C. We forward herewith a copy of our letter addressed to Hr. H.ll. Hcdgcock today- from which you will observe that he does not come to settle his accounts though he waE requested by the President of the Council to do so immediately he arrived from Eushire. As you are aware he has no more connection with the State of Muscat and Oman. Usual Ending.Copy of the letter to Mr. S.E*Hedgcock. Dated 22nd R&amp;bi al awal 1350 (7th August 1931). After Compliments. As you were Informed hy the President of the Council ixmnediately you arrived from Bushire, you ought to have settled your accounts hut you hove not done so yet though your services terminated a month and six days ago. You are already av.are that you are no longer in the service (of the State). We are nov; addressing this letter to you so that you may come and settle your accounts. copy of the above letter is forwarded to H.B.I^s Consul. Muscat.Tele&amp;raia- (GTC) From Political, Hu scat, T© xiesicitnt, Buchire No• C-176 Bated 7th August 1931. Council have today a^ain written Hed^cocic informing him that he has no further connection with the State and requesting him to settle his accounts. Kedgcock 1 * departure cannot he delayed longer, please telegraph instructions urgently.Confidential. Ho. C-l'I'fot 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.B.K’s Consulate Muscat, the ?th August 1931. To The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Om^n, Muscat. After Compliments. I acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your letter of day-e date about Mr. Hedgcook. The contents have been telegraphed to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Bushire, and I h&amp;ve asked him to wire iiie instructions about Mr. Hedgcock. This is what had to be said and salams. / Political Agent ' Captain, and H.B.M’s Consul ^Muscat.Original in file 35/5 Co x .y M ' ’’L' Telegram (GTC ) ^ &amp; ff- ^7^ From Resident, Shiraz, liT. &amp; */ To Political, Muscat, lTo.T/66 Dated Received 14th August 1531* P Your telegram Do.176, 7th August* _ A ' * me to got into touch who hve replied as follows, hegins:- H As you have already 'been told Hedgcock’s resignation must he regarded as in abeyance until charges against Talker are cleared up (para 2 of Tylie*s demi-official letter F19 ^31 dated 2nd July 1931). Government of Indie have not yet received Alban’s report referred to in para 7 of your ‘demi-official letter 429-S dated 17th J uly • &gt;* SndSf Please expedite your report.The .tclitical Agency &amp; H.B.M 1 * Ceneulate, vW Muscat) 15th yvuguet 1^31. Dear llajor Ftwle, vlth reference te my letter ho.C-156 dated Qth July about Hedgcooki I^liJce^te Jcnow how things are at prese»t. ?• begin with, A would liice to malce it clear, that all I hare said about him in my fenaer despatches and D.Os is true, the facte have neither been exaggerated nor belittled* jrfhat I strongly objected to, and would atii£ object to if he did it again, was hie attitude towards Gevernment and his idea that he was championing an eppressed State. Since hie return, however, three weeks age, he has quite changed all that and spares no pains beth to do hie work (at present investigation of the Levy accounts) and to show that his former ideas about the State being oppressed have been given up* Under thefic circunst&amp;rcct ano il he continues like this in future there is no reason why he shouldn't stay on* His expe* rience would be valuable to the state and in case ti Saiyld Said's eiafcneae or anything there should be someene te kaap J things going* la any case no, that ne regrets wnat he nas dene and has learnt his le«s*n, 1 tor «ne have nothing ag^nst M» and, if he carries *n in future as he is *t present theie sill he nc xore complaints against him* It wae mj duty to bring up everything against hi*, ss that Government may Know exactly what they are doing and if in future there should be any more trouble over HedgcocJc then it will »*t be possible for anyon. to contend that his former actions were nst reported* Saiyid Said, this morning, said that the C.uncil are in- different ,il ' Hin'ble fejor T.c.yowle, C.S.E., ^•litical ftesiaent in tne Persian Gulf, Mushiretb*y have no tfficial relations with Hedgcocic and they den’t mind if he remain* here, and if he is te he reinstated or his resignation te be cancelled, then, they want eflcial intimation te this effect before he can work for A the State. As I have brought to notice all that Hedgceck has dene or said which I considered wrong and as some extracts frsm ay lettsrs have been fsrwardsd to the Government of India, I hope that a espy sf this letter may also be forwarded ts them so that all the weight of Judgment may not be against him. Yours sincerely R.G.Alban.T-e 31 dated July 2nd. Tylies letter No. ?• 19 N yrM f Please telegraph if you ever informed the Council that Hedge cocks resignation- must be regarded as in abeyance pending receipt of Biscoes views and clearing up of charges againstFrom Resident Bushire. To Political Muscat. ■ L ' J ‘ oQ Bated 20/8/21. Reed 20/8/31 Extract from telegram from Govt, of India begins- Receipt oj Aloans report completes investigation into alleged irregula f.^rt as far as latter concern Hedgecock and so it is now for Council to decide whether they -'is h to retain Hedgecocks services after June 30th. date on -hiich period of notice expired. Government of India -hile not pled ging taemselves to be bound by Councils vie-ns w ill be glad t&lt; kno w ^hat they are and ^ill of course give them full consider ■ation**ends . Please enquire from Council and telegraph he the r they i s h to retain Hedgecocks services.s. a. sfi- ^&gt;0 From 8 'isident Bush ire. ; To Political Muscat. lty.459. Dated &amp; Reed. 20/8/u? . Vcj immediately preceding telegram and your D.O.No.lBi of August 11 th. . I am forwarding Hedgecocks further charges v. talker to Trovt. but this in my opinion does not prevent Hedgecocks departure as,if further investigation is decide on material is lying in • Muscat. and you can carry it out.ConfIdtntla^. Ho. C-/f^ofl931. Politic*! Ag*n*y &amp; H.B.M's Consulat*. Muscat* the 24th August lt3i. To The Counell of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oaan, Muscat. After CospllMents. The Hon^le the Political Resident has telegraphed that nov that the investigations vhish were being made by Mr. Hedgeoek into the Administration of the Levy Corps, are completed, the Government of India desire to know whether the Council wish to retain the services of Mr. Hcdgooek, after the 30th of June, the date on which the period of notice expired, or not. jhgy further add that although they do not pledge themselves to be bound by the views of the Council they will of course give them full consideration. This is what had to be said and 8 alams. y7r ‘ Cajtain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’a Consul. MuscatNo. 27 Dated lith Hebi el Thanl 1350 (26th August 1931 )• iron - The Counell of Ministers, Muscat State. To ~ Captain R.G. Alban, H.B.M 9 s Consul, Muscat. A. C • At an auspicious time we reoelved your letter No.C~184 dated the 24th August 1931, and noted that the Hobble the Resident has telegraphed that, now that the investigations whleh were being made by Mr. Hedgeoek into the Adainiatratioi of the Levy Corps have been oompleted, the Government of India desire to know whether the Council wish to retain the services of Mr. Hedgeoek after the 30th June. In reply we have to say that the Couneil have no desire and views other than those already expressed in their letter Ho.5 of 26th ttoharm 1360 (14th Jun. 1*31) which w*. * r.»ly to your l.tt.r Ho.C-12* d.t.d the 8th Jun. 1931, agreeing with th. view, of th. Oov.rnaent of India. But if the Government of India h.vo now other vlowa regarding Mr. Hodgeoolc he.Ida. tho.e already ex,ro..ed, we would U* to be informed of them. U.E.IdfPtl&amp;l Na*C«i87 of 1931. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate Muscat,26th August 1931 . Fro* to Captain R.G.ATban, political Agent &amp; n*B.M t s Consul Muscat The ^on’tle the Political Resident in the Persian &lt;hilf # Bushire* ^ir, In reference to your telegra* J51o*458 dated the 20th letter Ho.C-184 D/24-8-31 to Council of Ministers 0 August 1931, Letter Ho. 27 D/26-8-31 fro* -do- v - I have the honour to forward herewith copies oi the marginally corres pondenot hetween this office and the Council of Ministers, mus cat State. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain, Political Agent * H.B.K's Consul.Telegram (R) From Political, Muscat, To Resident, Bushire No. C-186 Dated 26th August 1931. Your telegram No.456 dated 20th August, President w as informed verbally about fortnight ago. Your telegram No. 458, Council have replied offi- cially stating f w e have no vie^s other than those expressed in our letter No«5 dated lith June (forwarded to you under my No.C-140 dated 17th June), ftov'ever if Government have have any fres^l V ie-s about Mr.Hedgcock -e -ill be pleased to hear them._______the*® fur tb ®t • 4 , Xlth r*&amp;uc&amp; to Alban* • oug^totion that Hed^oock* s ^pariwoo would bo raluablo to Urn state in case of aalyid Seid f o illnoae or * anyth ing* # If ;Mgeook goeo* oitbor gnotbor financial drioer can be obtained, or aa a taaporary aawurc to oovsr the next year or ao, while we see bow things fcru going. It slight bo possible tor Alban to act as Financial (jvlcor and Coiaiaaadant of the lowiss as suggested by Colonel y. O, 3 lsooo In bis despatch jSo.202-3 of 22nd April 1931 tparagraph 13), or If neither of these alternatives is considered practiseble, iSalyid :eld eight be left to run the finaneee of the iitete under earn system of auditory control, it any be reuerhed that be * dalyid Sold _ has now got a gdd i Aoeountant 3«.icr/;.l in ,,hi h 4mll cbsnd f 1,081 •b» •bo wao recently R»dc a Rat Oahlb tgp the coverneont of India. 6, 2 aa sending a copy of thio lottor, with a copy of Alban'a letter, to Colonel Blooo# end to iiam. ALJ-eM.flon'f ident x 3.X • J JjjUf. 3lD D.O.No. 553-3 of 1931# British Besidency t Bushire, the 28th August 1931. Very sorry to hear that you have been ill. I hope you are recovered by now. If you should want a ♦refresher* don f t forget that you have 6 weeks recess due to you: the total period is 3 months, and I only took half of it. The only thing that need keep you in Muscat is I suppose 1 1* affaire Hedgcock* which I sincerely trust will be settled one way or the other very soon. 2. I enclose copies of the following correspondence* vj) ^ I (1) My letter fio.448-S of 20th July 1931 to the Government of India; v (2) Government of India telegram Bo.2072-S of 18th August 1931 to me; (3) My telegram Ho.468 of 2 7th-August 1931 to the Government of India, nf 16th June 1931 to the (4) My telegram flo.362 of 1 Hovemment of India. 3. With reference to Government of India tele^r , Mo.2072 -S of 18 th August 1931. 1 p s£SSE ^. i » “ 0 '''” nl India on this point and will let you S.W.Albaa, Political Agent, Muscat * ”1)1, u n ^ve a copy of my letter. Personally I do not see how the question of the date on which -abeyance- was communicated to the Council affects Hedgcoch* s situation one way or the other# y fThis has already been telegraph- v ed you in iqy wire Ho.458 of 20th August, and you have replied in your telegram Ho.186 of 26th August, and I have telegraphed this on to Government in my tele- * gram Ho.468 of 27th August. The situation, as I understand it, is as follows: The Govern ment of India accept the fact that hedgcock, after 30th June, was in their service and not in that of the State. If Hedgcock does not go then he will re-enter State service from the date on which instructions are received to that effect from the Government of India, say, for the sake of illustration, the 15th August. The question toen arises who pays Hedgcock from the 1st July to the 15th August? If Hedgcock does go then instructions to that effect will also l3e received on a certain date, say, again for the sake of illustration, the 15th August. Again the question of pays him from the 1st July ;he 15th August arises, and case-3- Paragraph 6» . ^3. G case the Government of India. I suppo it is arguing on these lines that Govern ment have asked this query. Please enquire from the Council and telegraph me if they wish to put in a claim as indicated in paragraph 5 of Government’s telegram. This particular question seems to lie as between the Government of India and the Muscat State, and does not affect Hedgcock directly, as, whatever the reply of the Council, he gets his pay from some source. Before telegraphing to the Government of India I am awaiting your reply to my te] gram **0.467 of 27th August. I presume that the notice which missed Hedgcock here, or a copy of it, was given him sometime towards the end of July, but I not know that this really affects the question, though I shall mention it to Government of India. If the latter ta the attitude, which apparently they do, that Hedgcock’s services with the State terminated on 30th June, then no 'fresh notice ’ is necessary, Hedgcock's 3 months’ notice running from 1st July. nedgcocK may, however, take up the stand that his services did not terminate with the State until he received an actual notice in writing to that effect. He might further aa y that the notice in writing he received at the end of July was not valid, as he ;! was-4- was then working for the Government of India and could not leave Muscat until he had received instructions from them to do so, ^n this stand he might claim that fresh notice should be issued to him from the date on which final instructions are received from the Government of India that he is to go, say, the 15th August. Against this, however, if, he has already accepted 3 months* advance of pay in lieu of notice - vide ny telegram to you,Ho.469 of 28th August 1931 - he is obviously debarred from taking up this stand, and by accepting the advance he has tacitly accepted the notice*J: A- AP- 1 ^ R. 27. Political Resident, Bushire Gove nment of India, Simla* Telegram: From: To: No • ^ * Dated the 29th August 1931. v* 1 telegram of 27th August No.463. Your paragraph 6. Letter referred tc in my U.C letter Uo.448.3 of 20th July paragraph 6 was given to Hedgoock at Muscat on 25th July, extract from it reads as follows, begins; As it is already known to you your services with the Government of the Sultan of Muscat cane to an end by the 30th June. Ends. Mo other notice is in my opinion necessary, and date on which notice was given would seem immaterial as hedgoock will in any case get 3 months' pay from State and if State make claim mentioned in V'your paragraph 5 salary after 30th June will presumably be paid by Government of India ? Your paragraph 5# As this poin* does not seem urgent X have referred to the Political Agent by letter for telegraphic replyr - KBSIDEBT - . • • Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat. Order. Under Secretary to the Resident in the Persian Gulf.35/138 Telegram H. From Government of India, Foreign &lt; 5 . lolitioal Bapartment* Sujfeia, -*• o lolitioal Besidant, Busblre* Ko 2072-B Bated and received 18tb August 1931 ¥our letter Ko 448-d of 20th July last and oonneoted correspondence* 2* You were informed fcytenoioaure to Wylie’s letter of June 29th that ^edgc ck*s resignation was held to he in abeyance ponding the receipt of hiscoe’s views and investigation into allegations against Walker. n what dated did you coanunicate this to Muscat otate Coun- •cil ? 3, Blsooe'8 views have since been received and receipt of Albania report completes investigation into alleged irregularities on ^8iker # s part as far as latter is concerned. 4 . It is now for Council to decide if they wish to retain ^edgccck^s services after June 30th, date on which period of notice expired* '.rov eminent of ^ndda while not pledging tbeeaelvea t. be bound by Oouncil*® views, will be glad to know what they are and will ol course give them full consideration. Xtiey should understand the tact that j^eog- -ooolc ala not return to Luscat toy June 30th is In no *ay his fault. h 9 was aeualnea hyre ana then went to iiushire to su t, convenience of Gov.rnm.nt of India, fihlchevwr way Council decide they should be M*«« « they desire to ..k. any olal. M.ln.« Oo'®™*”* ° r 4Ml “ ror “ S - 6 ‘ -cock’sEedgcock*s pay during interval between June 30tti and date on which he finally loaves Muscat. 6* 11ease telegraph after hearing from State Counoil whether you consider fresh notice to ^edgcook necessary and if so for what period. Foreign.3b/136. Telegram From To No. 466. P. (27). Political Pesiaent, Bub hi re. Government of India. Simla. Dated 27th Auguet 1931. /joV'? Your telegram No. 2072-S. of 16th August. Lelay in reply has been cautea oy Alban's illness. Your paragraph 2. Alban telegraphs that Council were informed re abeyance about two weeks ago. Letter follows on this point. V .r *: U- Your paragraph 4. Aloan wires that Council have replies officially as follows, begins 'We have no views other than those stated in our 'letter No. 5 dated 14th June, however if Government 'of Inoia have any Iresh views regarding Mr. Heug- •-cock we will be pleasec to hear them.' ends. Letter referred to by Council is the reply given to Alban y f) referreu to in my telegram No. 362 of 16th June. Copy of letter by next mail. Your paragraph b. Council are being approached. Your paragraph 6. Reply will follow later. RE ELDEST.«. Telegram: G.T.C. From: Political Resident, Bushire. To Foreign Secretary, Simla. No. 362 • Dated the 16th June 1931. Muscat Finances. Muscat Council have agreed to dispense with Hedgcock’s services from the 30th June. Demi&gt;official . Fowle to Howell. Hedgcock who has left for India proposes to visit Simla very shortly. -Resident -■ ho. C-X^7 of 1931. Politioax Agency &amp; Consulate, Kusoat, bth deptember 1931. To T*ie Council cf kinietere to H.H# the Sultan of Muscat and Osian, Muscat* After Coispllx ente* The Hon’ole the Political Resideni has v'ritten to say that the Government of India wish the Council to know that the fact that l'r. Hed^oooK did not return to ;£uB?8t by June 30, 1931 is in no way h.'.s fault. He w«© detained in oisala fjnd then cent to Buehire to suit the convenience of the (rovernenent cf India. The Hon’ble the Politicel Refiident now *sks whether the Counoll/wieh to make anv clai» against the Gov^rnicent of India on account cf Mr. Hed^ccjk’s pay during the interval between June 39th ond the date of his departure from Muscat or retumption of servioe m the State as may ultinately be decided. This is what had to be said end palans. A Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul.3,1 The Council of Kinisters to H.H. the Sultan (Si) of l.uscet and Oman, Muscat. CCITTTDDITTIAL. yrom. To - Captain R*G. Allan, TT .B.r f s Consul, Muscat. ho.3.26. Bated 25th Rail al Thani 1350 (9-9-31). A.C. p 1 S' ^ R r e had the pleasure of receiving your letter Ro.C-197, dated the 5th September 1931, wherein you mentioned that the Hon'hie the Political Resident has v/ritten to soy that Hr. Hed cock did not return to Tuscat by 30th June 1931 is not his fault, etc. You further mentioned that the Hon’ble the Political Resident has now asked whether the Council wish to make any claim against the Government of India, etc. In re x .‘ly we have to say that Hr. Hedgcock’s services in the State of This cat and Oman terminated on the 30th June last and he therefore has had no connection with the said State nor has he attended the work of the 't:te emce tne aforesaid date. According to the agreement arrived at Hr. Hedgcock has to be paid three months’s pay e-d passages to England fo. himself and his wife. He have asked him to come and receive the same but he has neither come nor sent in any reply as you have already been informed about it and the money ly i ng v i t h us. We do not fully understand the Hon'hie the Resident's enquiry as Er. HedgcocJc's services were terminated as already explained and he has had no connection with the Husect State. Usual Hnding.*Telegram (R) From Political, LIuscat, To y Resident, Bushire, No.G-1^9 Dated 9th September 1931. 4' p^paii Your confidential D.0.Ko.553-S dated August 28th para 5. Council reply Hedgcock’s services with State terminated on June 30th and they are ready to pay three months 1 pay and passages as already agreed. As he has since had no connection with the State Council do not understand how questior asked hy Resident concerns them. I suggest that Government be informed that had Hedgcock resuraed duties on return from Bushire Council might have backed him mcrui. His conduct has been exemplary since his return.R. v/ £R. Telegram From To Political Resident, Bushiie. Governraent of India, iroreign &amp; Department, Bimla. Political —^ Ro 481 Dated 10th Beptember 1931 # My telegram ho 471 of the 29th August, last paragraph. Political Agent, Muscat, wires as follows begins ' Council of Ministers reply concerns them.' ends. It seems clear from this that Council expect Government of India to pay Hedgcc ck after June 30th Resident. Poet copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, fo r in fo rroa ti on. By urder, for Secretary to ttiePolitical hesiuent in the Persian (iuif. Buahire. 12th Sept. 1931■ ■■ ■ Telegram - P, From Foreign, Simla To xiesident, Bushire Rpted to rolitical Muscat No. 2344/S. Dated &amp; Red. i9th September i931. 'I VitN reference to correspondence ending with your y telegram No.481 dated 10th September. As retention of services of Hedgcock as Financial Adviser is not desired by the Muscat State Council it has been decided by the G.oi India that his resignation tendered on 10th April and accepted by the Council Muscat State on 25th July must be considered to be operative, please inform Council accordingly. As already agreed HedgcocK will receive pay up to 1st July and passage from Muscat State. G. of India will pay him at the same rate from xst July to date of departure. He should be instructed to leave Muscat as soon as possible. * / — yjzyf Telegram- P. From Resident, Bushire To political, Muscat, Oatefi received 19th September 1931. *l eaa e convey immediately decision of Govt, of India to Council and Hedgcoc* and telegraph to me when Hedgcock proposes to leave. of India telegram This has reference to Govt.o. fio. 2344-3 dated 19th September. .v/ COKFI:~'ENTIAL« Ho.C-207 Of 1931. f political Agenoy &amp; H.B.H'a Conaulate, Kuecot, 21st September 1931a f ( y)f\ % b .^ v Te The Council of Ministers te M.H.the Sultan ef Muscat and Oman, Muscats After Compliments a Y* I have been instructed by the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to inform you that the GoTcrnment of India have decided that as the retention of Mra Hedgoock’e uervices as Financial Ad y leer is not desired by the Muscat state, his resigns-* tion tenderad on April 10th and accepted by you on July 25th muat be considered to be operativee As has been already agreed Mr. Hedge ook will recelre pay, up to July lot, and paeaagea from the Kuecat State. From July l'! untU the date oi hie leaving Muscat he will t&gt;e P» id at the eame rate by the Oovernment of India. Thin io what had to be said and sal&amp;mse bd. R.G. Alban. captain, Political Agent * H.B.M’a Coneul. V no.C-208o bated 21st September 1931 Copy forwarded to ^^•^ef^esirrthat’^u'shauld The Government of n eaBrly aB possible. inform arrango^to^leave^MUSca ^ Bo.id.nt to leave 1,1 ” should transmit to him. ^ Captain, &lt; 1 - Vv PoliticalTelegram P. prom Political Agent, Muscat. To Foreign, Simla. y/ 210. Ho. Dated 22rd September x931. He leaves for Sngland CctolDer 2nd. Sc your telegram dated 2 ist instant.Telegram Code. jj’roiii rolltical, L'uscat. To Resident, Bugfcire. / Ro. &lt;^11. Jated 23rd September 1931 Rlease obtain authority to pay Hedgeock from July ' 1st to date of departure. He claims T.A. according to Fundamental Rules from Karachi-Bu shire-Muscat. He leaves for England on October 2nd.T«lC4ra-» P. A From Foreign, Simla To Political, Muscat* No. 2363-S, Dated 21st received 22nd September 1931* Reference telegram dated 19th Septenher regarding Hedgcoeh* Please inform him that decision already com municated is final, and telegraph date of his departure and destination* Telegram P* From Political, Muscat* To Foreign, Simla* No* 2it&gt;. Dated 23rd September 1931* He leaves for England October 2nd* This refers to your telegram dated 21 st i.n&amp; c.ant« 7 No* C-212 of 1931. Political A«*n«y &amp; H.B.M*■ Consulat*, fcuacat.tk* 25rd Septartar 1931. Lf. Captain, political A*ent &amp; H.B.M'b consul. Muscat*Office of the Accountant-General^ Central Revenues. graphic Address kjounts, India. (omrotraications to be jj ^ the Acooantant- : Central Revennea. IMPERIAL SECRETARIAT BUILDINGS. New Delhi, the ' | * JlU Tlst 19$l N°- TjS.L'uscat 4/615 weare. From The ACCOUNTANT-GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, To The Political and iiis Britannic Majesty*s consul, Muscat. Sir, Subject:- itecovery in respect of a sum of £160/- taicen m jnglana by I'jc. S. £l.^i,dgcoclc , in November IpoO on his apoointment es Financial idvisor to the Muscat Goveronent. 1 1 have the nonour to invite a reference to t.is office letcer No.I'A.Muscat 4/305 dated ^3nd June 1931 on the subject indicated above, and to enquire when the sum of Rs.2133-5-0 representing the equivalent of the sterling amount at Is. 6d. the rupee is likely to be recovered. &gt;s&amp; Co,' r Re?^ No r ^ 1 ;ErConfidential c/ ' No.C-20/f of 1931 Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’a Consulate, Muscat, lj£th SepteaBer 1931. To The Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan od Muscat and Oman, Muscat. After Compliments. With reference to my letter No.C-168 dated the 23rd July 1931, please let me know for the information of the Aaaountant General Central Revenues, Mew Delhi, when the sum of Rs.2133-5-0, equivalent of £.160/- at 1 s. 6 d. the Rupee, advanced to Mr. Hedgcook in England in November 1930, is likely to be paid. Usual Ending. Captain, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul.2-7/ f.ft. 33^ 3 'J/” FINANCE MINISTRY, MUSCAT STATE, Dated i™. 29- To The Political Igent &amp; F.TJ^s Consul, Muscat. Memorandum. t- -&gt;70 Preference Your Yo.C-204 Sated 15-9-C1. m he amount in question v/ill he paid as soon as the funds “becomes available. I hope that the payment mill not “be delayed latfer than the end of the year 1931. S' OLA^ dL I President Council of Ministers, Muscat Government.No*C/216 cu' Politics.1 A^enejr &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat the 24th September 1931* Frojn To The Poll tl cel Agent % Ccnsul, Muecat* The Accountant General# Central Revenue8# New Delhi* Sir, ^ with reference to your letter No*TA*l£usc£.t 4/65 dated the 24 th August 1931, I have the honour to inf one you that the Muscat State hopes to pay the amount by the end of December 1931 I nave the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient eervant. ■ / \r 1 Captain, Political Agent &amp; H*B*M f &amp; Coneul*Mu»catmummaa r 9- y]f° 36D ^7-3 i Telegram G.T.C. iTrom Foreign, Simla. Political, L'uscat. 1036 K. X T&gt; I To No Dated and received 25th Se v tenber 1931. Payment oi salary u^&lt; to 2nd October and of Travelling Allowance for journey from Karachi to Bushire thence to ITuscat with halting allowance at Bushire may be made according to rules to Head B cock as proposed by Political Agent: this is in reply to your 4^8. Telegram-(GTC) From Political,kuscat, To Foreign, Simla ho.0-2^7 Dated 26th September 1931. Your telegram b 1 o.iJ36 N dated 25th Dejjtember. Please tele fo raph authority required by article 8, Civil Account Coae.Tele^raii: 5 1 rom xiesiaent, Bushire To Political, Hub cat fto.501. Pated and received 27th September i931. Your telegram Ko,2xl. Following complete Governrent of India NO.1036N, 25th September begins:- Payment of salary up to 2nd October and of Travelling Allowance for journey from Karachi to Bushire thence to Muscat with halting allowance at Bushire may be paid accord ing to rules to Kedgcock as proposed by political A^ent.Telegram G.T.C. From Foreign, bimla* a.o roiltical /tgeni, LiiAscsut* No• 1Q44N. Dated 28th received 29th September 1931. yVii Your telegram ITo.217-C, September 26th. Government of India authorise payiuent to Hedgeock as '*L / (s sanctioned in telegram Ho. 10361J September 25th. As matter is urgent authorization is not being communicated to you through Accountant General, Central Revenues.J W*.C-23&gt;/ «f 1931. Political Agency &amp; M.B.M’* Ceneulate, Muscat,the 5^ Oeteber 1931. Pram Tt Captain K.G.Alban, 1«A«, Political Agent &amp; Coniul, Muscat. The tton’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. n Mcreorandma * y Reference your telegraa xio.501, dated the 27th bepteaber 1931. Ip I forward a copy of meat dated the 30th September 1931 from Mr. S.E.Hed*ecoo]c, claimin* furlou*h pay and haltine .U&lt;»w»nce In India, for favour of necee- sary action. 2 . A. the mail wo. timed to leave in the afternoen of the 2nd Oetober Mr. Hed,ecoelc was paid up to that date but einoe she was delayed and actually left in the after- noen ef the 5rd Mr. Hedgecock claims pay for an extra day. nr Captain, Political A*ent &amp; H.S.M’s Consul.From Political Resident, Bushire. To Government of India, siml^. No 498. Dated the 23rd September 193i. pollov/in^ from political Agent, Muscat, Begins, please obtain authority to pay He£gc ock xj-ixxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxkxxxx 2nd October. Ends. please telegraph sanction for pay ment of salary ana orders regarding travel' lin 0 alxov/ance claimed. -RESIDENT- * ost copy forwarded to the political ^gent, Muscat for information. Atte sted. Confidential i ASBis ^ t c onsul gte-uene ral. British Kesidency and oonsuxa« Bushire« 24/9/31iof ^ letter If©* 30, dated th.e 5th. October 1931, from the Council of AiinisterB t© H.H. the Sultan Muscat and OiLan, muscat, to Captain K.G. Alban, l.A., Coneul, Muscat. After Compliments. At an auspieious hour we receixed your letter h©.C-207 dated the 21st September 1931 and noted that you tiaxe been instructed by the Hen f ble the Political Resident to inform us that the Government of India hare decided that, as the retention of Mr. Hedgcock^ services as Financial Adviser is not desired by the Muscat State, the resignation tendered by him should be considered to be operative. We have acted upon the advice of the Hon'ble Government respecting the termination of Mr. Medgcock’s services with the Htate of Muscat and Oman for the reason given in hie resignation. We concurred in the suggestion of the Hobble Government abd dispensed with his services. There is no doubt that we are ever ready to follow the advice of the Mon , ble Government in the interest and welfare dfi the Government of the yultan of Muscat and Oman. /e are aware that the Men’ble Government desire nothing but the welfare of our otate. As agreed we have paid Mr. Hedgcock three months’ pay and passage* to England far himself and his wife. He has no further account with us and as you are aware he has left Muscat. We trust that the Hon'ble Government have no doubt that we are ever desirous *f strengthening the friendly relations existing between us. Usual Ending.% ao # 6S8-S of 1933U British Kssldeno^ &amp; Consulate* General, Buohire, the 16th October 1951, From • The Hon* ble iajor T,C,tf.Fowle f C,3,$;, l QTfioiatlng Political Keeident in the Fere1an Gulf, To The Foreign Secretary to the Governraent of India, He* Delhi, Claim for furlough pay and halting allowance by Mr,Hedgeocic, late Financial Adviser, Hueeat State, With reference to correepandence ending with Govern* aent of India telegram Ko,1026-3, dated the 25th September 1951, 1 have the honour to submit for the orders of Government jj - i- ( the enclosed copy of a memorandum Ho«C,881, dated the 5th El*'*'* ^ /d.tc/ October 1951, from tlie Political Agent, ;4usoat, and of its enclosure. 2, letter. With reference to paragraph 2 (a) of Mr, Hedgcock'a In addition to the three montAs* pay sanctioned in ... V p / Government of India telegram Ho, 1421-i, dated 26th itay 1931, the Muscat State has apparently paid Hr, Hedgcook furlough pay at the rate of 5 days per month of aervioe ( vide government V ? •'. of India telegram Ho,917—s, dated 28th June 1950, coi.dition * / ( 7 (d) )• ^r, Hedgeock nvw claims a similar concession from the Government of India in respect of the period of 3 months spent in their service calculating a day’s pay at Ks,40/- ( his monthlymonthly salary being Re* 1200/-)* Ae regards paragraph 2(b) of Mr. Hedgcock^ letter, lfr« ;iQd ti cook 10 ft ^raohl for &gt;ushtre on the morning of 5th July. I do not know the extent of his halts after let July at Simla and Karachi but he has doubtless furnished the Political Agent with details. 4 . Ilth reference to paragraph 2 of the Political Agent 9 s memorandum, as Mr. Hedgoook actually left Muscat on the afternoon of 3rd October he is preauiaably entitled to payment for that day* 1 hare the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd/- T. G • ?ov;le, Maj or, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. d^ential Assistant, . Residency &amp; Consulate-General. Copy forwarded to the lolitical Agent, Muscat, with reference to his memorandum No.C-231 of 5th October 1931* K</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000292_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/58</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000292</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/58</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File XXXV/5 VOL. I. APPOINTMENT OF NEW BRITISH FINANCIAL ADVISER. April 1930- Oct: 1931'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-19T22:05:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (306 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 308; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Three additional foliation sequences are also present in parallel between ff 3-308, these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and ff 38-307 and ff 68-308; these numbers are also written in pencil and circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of telegrams, reports and letters regarding the appointment of a new Financial Advisor to Muscat State instead of Bertram Thomas whose contract ended in 1930. Among the names suggested by the High Commissioner in Baghdad was Stuart Edwin Hedgcock who was serving in Iraq at the time and who had a thorough knowledge of Arabic. The correspondence in the file contains discussions regarding the financial status of the Council of Ministers, Muscat, before Hedgcock starting his position as a Minister, and the terms and conditions of his contract, in particular his salary and annual leave allowance in comparison to Thomas’s.The file also contains correspondence between Thomas and Hedgcock to set the former’s account and recovery of payment of his sea trips allowance. Upon taking his position Hedgcock provided a report titled ‘Levy Budget: Précis of Events’ (ff 123-128), in which he raised a few requests to the British Government which eventually were not answered. As a result, Hedgcock decided to resign in April 1931. Hedgcock’s resignation question went back and forth between British officials, the Council of Ministers and Hedgcock. Initially British officials were inclined to accept his resignation and tried to convince the Council to do so. Later in the correspondence Hedgcock decided to withdraw his resignation letter in agreement with the British Government. The Council of Ministers refused Hedgcock’s withdrawal and confirmed that his service to the State of Muscat terminated on 30 June 1931. The Council approved the payment of three months’ salary as leave pay and halting allowance for the time Hedgcock was in Muscat after June 1931. The file also contains revised budget estimates of Muscat State for the year 1931 (ff 227-230) prepared by the Political Agent, Muscat.Folio 120 contains a letter that is incorrectly dated 8 April 1920 from Bertram Thomas to the Political Agent, Muscat, discussing sea passage allowance. Thomas was appointed as a Financial Advisor in 1925. There is a copy of the same letter on folio 56 of file IOR/R/15/6/57.The majority of the correspondence is dated 1930-1931; the earlier start date given to the file is due to a letter (f 118) from the India Office to Bertram Thomas. Thomas provided this letter as an attachment to a letter he sent to the new Financial Advisor, Stuart Edwin Hedgcock, to support his claim for travel allowance.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Stuart Edwin Hedgcock</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Finance</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Council of Ministers</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Resignation (employee)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Annual financial statement</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Financial Advisor to the Sultan of Muscat</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Leave</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000292#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>