<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T08:57:27.319Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ABDULLA HULLA SALEH KUWAIT irPCRTANOT. y- ^ &gt;»Ai A I am enclosing herewith a letter from the Kuwait 7/a ter Supply Co Ltd addressed to His Highness the Shaikh, which speaks for itself. I shall he very grateful if you will submit the same to P. A. for his perusal and kind action. You will find in the enclosed letter the action of the thieves, v/hich may also have #v bad effect* on other d[ows. So, I hope that you make proper investigation with the authorities concerned. With many thanks and best wishes, Yours s: Ly, AIJAZALI KHAN ESQR., Kuwait.Trans la ,ion of letter dated trie Id/l2/l362 (11-12-1943) from the iuana^er of ^u-ait 7ater Sunply ComDany, Kuwait, Go His Highness the Tuler of Kuwait. V; &amp; After Corapliments, ^One of the country crafts belonging to the Kuwait ’7ater ^upol\ company, nokhudha Hhuloom bin 'bdullah, a subject of Your -i^hness, while returning bacK from al-MeKhraq, in Shatt-al-'rab carrying water from there, he -ms atoacked by some robbers, north of a p.ace named T- v/hat \bu Shaneo, and the time was about 7 o'cIock ?o rrl °^ 5 ^ n lece -ber, 1943. The naKhudha reported the matter to the -olice station at Fao on the next morning 6th December, 1943. The naxhudha reoorted the matter to us on his arrival here st- ting Ghat the robbers came on the decx of his boat and asxed him /net his name was and where ron he was coming and when he was replying their Questions , they started beating him with one of his Th' 0 T' T° haD ,ened ?° be near hilr - robbers then ordered the na.chuina to ta.te off his cloths, which they took sway with some cloths t g :e other sailors. They also robbed him Rs.200/- in cash, cookine- oishes etc. .ompass, 1-mps and many other things belonging to the ’ ^ n ' &gt;iOP t» which they found easy to be carried away. The naxhudha^believes that the thieves had come in two small boats from tf e .Iranian shores, but he could not see their feces and xnows not tneir names or descriptions, as it was derx night and they were mding their faces with, their head-cloths. The naxhudha and his sailors were terribly frip-htened because the robbers were fully armed. , , '’his accident has caused a great fear among the naxhudhas an': the sailors as it has happened in their way. 'e hope that you will taxe up the matter with the authorities concerned to stop the reoccurrence of such accidents in the future.mmABDULLA MULLA SALEH j . KUWAIT l A 1 J y Kuw ,vait«30th Decem'ber, 1943 L x - ^ dear Aijazali, f'~$ o' V. r ith reference to my verbal conversation with P.A. regarding the robbery of a dhow belongin to Mbssrs*Kuwait Vater Supply Co, I ani sending herewith an original report from the Nakhudah of the stolen Dhow. -ill you please submit the same to P.A. for his kind action, .Vith my best wishes, ^V\Copy of translation of a report of one of the nakhudhas of the Water Supply Company, Kuwait, dated the 29th December, 1943, submitted to His Highness the Huler of Kuwait. Abdullah bin Ahmed Burmaihan one of the naKhudhas of a boom belonging to the Company, his boat was sticking at the Manyuhi for 13 days north of Nasir Bu-Mutraq behind four rivers and on the fourteenth night from the date of his sticking i.e. Thursday night 23rd of December. He was attached by a large number of robbers who took a ay the large sail, compass, furnitures and the cloths of the nakhudha and sailors. As the nakhudha knows that land and he Knows many of the natives there he could discover the head of the gang without showing himself that he knew him and in the morning of the next day l.e. Thursday 23rd December the nakhudha went to Shaikh Mathkhoor and reported the natter to him in details spying that the thief is one of his followers and his name was Alwan bin , Alkam whose camp is no -th of Mathkhoor’s place by distant of five rivers. Mathkhoor when heard the story frbm the naKhudha he showee that he was very sorry as he always shows that he is very much ^ interested in the Kuwaities and their affairs and he pretends to be a humble servant of the As-Subah family and that, his benefits and that of his people are derived from Kuwait and as a matter of fact he told the nakhudha be comfortable today in the afternoon you will recover the f .rnitures of your boom and Ohuloom bin Abdulla T s boom who was robbed by Alwan bin Alxtam the forementioned on the 5th December, because the nekhudha Abdullah bin A.med told Shaikh Mathkhoor that the man who robbed me is the same robber who robbed C-h loom bin Abdulla and this is the furwah which he is now putting on, it is in fact belongs uo Ghuloom bin Abdullah'' and all the luggage etc. belonging to Ghuloom are Kept in his house and in the houses of the members of his gang. Shaikh Mathkhoor’s interest desappeared in the afternoon when Abdullah bin Ahmed came to receive his articles from him and after some hard conversations he promised him to come to him in the morning of the next day. On the next morning Mathkhoor told the nakhudha that the thief has denied and if the nakhudha wanted the thief was prepared to take an oath at Abbas, Mathkhoor added that he was prepared to send them to Abbas for the same prupose, but the nakhudha refused to accept the oath of the thief and came to report the case,and the matter is left to you, Sir. sssrssssssssssssssssssssszsssNo. S ' From To -9/l-VI. Political Agency, Kuwait, 16th January, 1944 a The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr. Sir, if /&lt;i / ? I liave the honour to enclose herewith a copy of a translation of a report from a naichudha of a sailing craft belonging to the Kuwait Water Supply Company, Limited. I shall be grateful for any action you can take to have restitution made to the complainants and to prevent the recurrence of such robberies. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, Political Agent, Kuwait.Translation of letter No.25/3/35 dated the 3rd February, 1944, from His Excellency t,he M' srah Liwa, Basrah, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. SUBJECT:- Robbery . After Compliments, Reference your letter No.293 dated the 9th January, 1944 regarding the robbery of the clothes and money belonging to Ghulam bin Abdulla of Kuwait. This incident was reported to this Mutassarifia and the results of the investigations of Lhe case had confirmed the case and had it had happened on the Iranian coast, in the neighbourhood of a place near the Iranian O.esba, and the criminals were an Insnian gang, whose members disappeared and hid uhemselves in/ the Iranian territory after committing the theft. In spite of the facts that the robbers are Iranian and i-he robbery happened on the Iranian coast, we have been very much interested in the case 4 —- ' o ing to importance of its result which will have an effect on the river comiaunfcacions and will create disorder. The Iranian frontier Police authorities at Khorramshahr have been approached immediately and have been asKed oo taKe the necessary measures to find out the members of the gang and to put an end to such actions. You may communicate with the Iranian authorities in this connection as Che case is related to the Iranian Government, as we have already mentioned above. reported at the Police Station of Fao, that the amount of money which had been robbed from him was Rs. 180/- only and not 3.200/- as it has been understood from His Highness’ letter, a copy of v/hich was attached to your letter, to which this leCter is the It is worth mencioning that the naxhudah Ghulam bin Abdulla reply. Usual EndingCONFIDENTIAL. No. /3i -g/i _vi. The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to His Hasty’s Consul, Kho.L raFishshr. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). requesting such action as is possible to prevent a repetition or these incidents. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the —bruagy, -1944 Reference to previous correspondence : / Ku- ait letter No.51-^/l-VI dated the 16th January, 1944. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. 1. 2 . 3. Name and Date, v* r'l . Letter dated 11-12-1943 from zhe Manager of Kuwait Supply Company, Kuwa.'t, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. ^ Letter No.293-9/l-VI, lated the 19th December, 1943, from the Political Agent, Kuwait, to His Excellency the Mutassarif, Basrah Liwa, Basrah. ^ #/ Letter No.25/3/35 dated the 3rd ! February, 1944, from His Excellency the Mutassarif, Basrah Liwa, Basrah, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Subject. ROBBERY IN THE 3HATT-AL-ARAB.Frop ... SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF. POLITIGiiL iiGEWT, KOGGH. # Copy to: The Hon'ble Political Resident Persian Gulf. With reference to the attached copi of a letter from the Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi, I should be grateful if you would make enquiries concerning this craft. I ajn afraid that the scent is rather stale bj now, but this is due to postal delays. /hue ... March, 1944 To .. T No. P.G. 404 ^ PlirdiCl IN PRhbl^N GbbF \j 0 ASL COMMODOREJ244 Enclosure to Persian Gulf letter No. P.G.4Q4 of 22 March &amp; SECRET H.M.I. Ni.V/xL OFFICE To: The Senior Navul Officer, Fersian Gulf H- Februtiry Jilst 1944. Froir: The Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi NO KINX 24/24 Subject: PXKaCl IN FEavSIi-Jj GULF The following report uatea February 16th has been received from the Military Port Security Officer, Karachi. The reliability of it is unknown. No.515b, Tindal NCR MOHS; ERaiibaNaK was on its way from SOkBal to KUmaXT ana between DUEal and ChariBaR it anchored due to rough weather. There was also another arab craft anchored with it. Whilst these crafts were anchored another craft approached them from the opposite direction ana was raaaing for the above mentioned craft but the Tindal of the arab craft saw through his binoculars that the men of the approaching craft were pirates, so immediately oponed fire. he fired six shots and the craft made off. it is learnt that these pirates are IRANI—BaLOCH”• 'It is reported that about a month ago the Country Craft MaNSOGKI (Signed) CAPTaXN it.X.N NaVaL OF^ICEn IN ChauGE, KaiuUnl.i) f-' rom SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF. IAN GULF. ^ 21 May 1944. ' Vo -P.G.404. J^IKAUY in ¥RE PERSIAN GULP. be informed of the outcome of your Q**luiries concerning this matter ^..xch I brought to your notice in Persian Gulf letter Number 404 of 22 March 1944. POLITICAL AGENT. KUWAIT.® Copy to the Hobble Political Resident, -- -^Persian Gulf. It is requested that I may COMMODORE.Translation of letter No.R.6.2373,dated 8th t/ June 1944, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political ^ent, Kuwait. A.fter Compli tents, X I wish to acKnowl^&amp;^X the receipt of your two letter* Nos. C/16^ &amp; IX, dated 26th April and 6th June, 1944, snd have noted the translation of the letter dated 21st February,1944, from the Naval Officer in Charge, Karachi, regarding the sailing craft 'MANSURI' No^3138, Nakhoda Nur Mohammad Shah. I wish to inform you that I had issued instruc tions that enquiries be made about the said sailing craft during all this period,and have come to know later that the aforementioned boat arrived here a long time ago i.e. on the 12 th December,1943. You can make out from this ^our letter was received after ; 43*rt the boat had sailed and so it was not possib e for us to make any enquiries from its owners Usual EndingNo.c /467 Kuv/&amp; It, lijfcil t-UlTit:, Xi)‘i 4 . I havo tiie honour i&gt;o refer to ' our letter No.PG.404 dated the 32nd ’lerch, 1944, on the subject of Piracy in the Persian Gulf and to inform you that His Highness the Shaikh, to whom the matter was referred for enquiry has reported that the craft in question last caired here on the 12th of December, 1943, and tnat it nad left for India before your letter was received here. The craft is not registered in Kuwait, 2. I am sending a copy of this to Bushire. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, BASRAH . I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Agent, Kuwait.With refernce to my verbal c nversotion with you on Thursday the hoth July,1944, on the subject of the sailinj craft belon 3 in 3 to the Kuwait oter Supply Co. Ltd., and how it .as attacked by some unknown persons at the entrance of Shat al-Arab, I enclose herewith a letter, in original, which I have received from the abovementioned Co. The letter is self explanatory. I,therefore request you kin lly to communicate with the authorities concerned in this respect with a view to stopping a repetition of such incidence. Usual Ending.m./6/6 -9/l-VI. Political Agency Kuwait, 31st July, 1944 To His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr. Sir I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with my Printed Letter No.133-9/1 dated the 9th February, 1944, and to enclose a translation of a letter No.R/6/2408 dated the 22nd July, 1944, and of its enclosure, received from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. I shall be grateful if you will be good enough to take up the matterjwith the Persian authorities with a view to having the culprits brought to justice and to prevent a repetition of such incidents in future. It will also be appreciated if you can inform me of the results of your representations in due course. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant Political Agent, Kuwait.No -9/1 -VI. Political Agency, Kuwait, S6th September, 1944. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.948-15/23 dated the 26th August, 1944, andvto inform you that.the incident in question took place on the Iranian side of the entrance to the Shatt-Al-Arab river. His Majesty 1 s Consul, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Agent, Kuwait f) 7 ni fKuwait Water Supply Co. Ltd. CaJ\&amp; Translation of letter No.R/6/2607 dated the 30th December, 1944, from His Highness the/?fyler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. await. / / JBtJS JL -(JxJLs After Compliments, i t / v $ We have already informed you of the repeated attacks on the boats taking place in Shatt-Al-Arab and these attacks are made by armed persons who are unknown and who have attacked some of the sailing craft and see sfciii have tried also to attacK some of the sailing craft which are used for carrying water for Kuwait. As you are well aware that these attacks are causing great harm for the public, we found it necessary for us to inform you so that you will explain the situation to the authorities concerned and in the meantime we request you to ask that all Kuwaiti sailing craft will be allowed to carry arms for self-defence. Enclosed please find a letter, in original, received by us from the Manager of the Kuwait Water Supply Company, which is self explanatory. Usual Ending. Translation of letter dated the 30th December, 1944, from the Manager, Kuwait Water Supply Company, Kuwait, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments, I have the honour to inform Your Highness that we hxxE had submitted a letter to Your Highness in which we informed you of the accidents which took place in Lhe sea when our nakhudhas were repeatedly attacxed by theives, both in the day and night. Now that some theives have again repeated their attack on three sailing craft at the entrance to the Khor on the evening of Eriday 29th and the attackers shot fourteen rounds at one of the sailing craft, tearing the sail. This accident has caused a strick among the nakhudhas who refuse to sail. I therefore have the honour to submit the matter to Your Highness as this action will cause a great harm to the welfare of the country. Usual EndingTelegram ^ i-rom political, ait to resident, Husaire TT o. 2 ^ ted the 2nd January 1945 His “Highness complains that on evening of December 2°th three sailing craft /ere attached in mouth of fhatt-U-iralD above 7oa*by armed pirates^ in a ballam. -'Only one of the craft attached was a ivuvaiti and it escaped by out sailing the uirates; but sustained fourteen shot holes in s'ils, ^ 2. There /ere similar attacks in same area on 5th Teceaber, 1943 and on 15th July, 1944, in which Ku./ait dhows ./ere looted and ~ have so far not succeeded in getting any final reply -to my represent ations ato Kutassarif of Hasrah or Consul, Khorranshahi Shaikh asks that .steps be tajten to ensure security in mouth of Shatt,,and that Trap Government be moved to permit Hu:; a it dhows to carry arms beyond ?oa for self-defence. Present insecurity has .nade Hu.ait crev/s very reluctant to sail unarmed, -mid water supply is jeopardized.No. J?'/ iDlitical Agency, Kuwait, 10th January, 1945. To H.BJ.'ajesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr. Sir, / I hav/r the honour to refer to my letter No. 139(5-9/l-VT dated the 26th September, 1944, and to enquire when I may expect a reply. I have the honour to be, S’r, Your obedient servant, &gt;litical Agent, Kuwait.Alfyli GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbpabtuent, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B'—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political aesident, Sushir©* confidential Kuu'aii Receipt , \ N ° y/ htaleri jif// Prodpoia« t hd«d. repeated senior Uaval officer f Pe»sian Gulf, Bpltoousuly Khoppanksluiiip, To Political Agent f Kuwait, -3.S 'S' No. 3 ^-s Date 4&gt;th January m M A 44. Shaikh of Kuwait has ra.orted tiiat on evenjj.g of 29th teceiiber 1944 thru© sailing craft, one of which was a Kuwaiti bo£ t. ^ ssoutli of the ohutt~el'»ar&amp;b above Fao by anaed t-aiate* in a o&amp;iiaja, ar*d that the Kuwaiti boat ©scaped by out sail ini' tne pirates but sustained fourteen bullet holes in its sails. 1943 SlBiiiiir uttiicks occur rati In the same area on 5 th Decenber end on 1 -th Jur,e A ln which Kuwaiti dhows were looted, and in respect rt # 1 wK I +V 0 ^ 244^4 I ^ M ***l\sm* ^ etliU ill resp ox which the Political , 4 ;«it f Kuwait, reports that 1)© has received no ruu .1 re,jly to his representations to the fiiUtascirrif, B^sr*. 3« His Highness has asked ti«at steps iuay be taketi to iisprove security in the sjouth of the ohatt-tl-^trab and it is requested that, if you see no objection, the Iraq Ucvernisent, who normally police these waters, may be asked to take steps accordingly. 4, His Highness has also asked that the Iraq Governaent may be moved to permit Kuwaiti dhows to carry arms beyond Fee for self protect- i^n imi + ccrisider that for the present the Iraq Government should not be approached on this point. 5. lo Khoyramshahr only . The Political Agent, Kuwait, reports that no final reply has been received from you to similar representations made in respect of the earlier incidents mentioned in paragraph 2 . SD. GEOFFREY PRIOR, ATTESTED . POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULP 1 . C'Fl for Secretary to the Political Resid$n£, Persian G^lf. MFP—501 S&lt;teP—(M-S20)—23-7-36—300.000.yANIAD Co TEL . ADRESS ARABI i? KUWAIT % P.GULF COD USED BENTLY S OJR REfLRAHICE P/2 C/4 5 ( a*jl» 0 ^ ) 12th January 194 5« H« B® M f B Political Agent, Kuwait® Dear Sir, CON rfOtiNTlAL Kuwait Receipt, i n *_12 I beg to bring to your notice that lately some of the dhows which load sand for me to be taken to Abadan,toavo been attacked by pirates at various places in Shatt-ul-Arab® I have this day received a report that the following three dhows have been attacked, full particulars are givffi against each dhow:~ £C&gt; ; 1) , Dhow No:KT-21 Nakhooda Mohamed Abbas attacked NirtJi of &lt;Jusba on 14th October 1944* 2) &lt; Dhow No :BS-12 Nakhooda Khalifah Amir attacked near Light Buoy in river* on 19th November 1944. icy* 3) 4 Dhow NosKT-294 Nakhooda Abdul Khazir Salman attacked near Fao at creek Kariam Sahi on 29 th November 1944. I would like to add that at present I have about 30 dhows ready loaded with sand but the Nakhoodas refuse to sail unless I make some arrangements to get them a few arms for their self defence® I shall be grateful if you kindly assist me in the matter. Thanking you. Yours faithfully. c.c. to Messrs Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited,Abadan for information®V^MAD % TEL . A DRESS ARABI ^ KUWAIT \ P.GULF COD USED BENTLYS OUR REFEIfANCE • J P/26/45 { ) 3 j c ' ^ 16th January 194 5 H* B« M r b Political Agent, Kuwait* Dear air, CO HIDDEN HA i Kuwait Receipt $$ Dated J 7^1 . with further reference to my letter wo:P/2t/45 dated the 12 th instant, I have to inform you that I have received a further report that the following two Nakhoodas were also attacked near the bight auoy in the river on 19th November 1944 at about 8 P.M. 1) ttakheeda Mustafa Ibrahim 2) Makheeda Messhal Abdul ^abi« On making through enquiries, I understand that all the pirates concerned live opposite rae at Uusbah which is Iran territory# They occupy the lands of some big landlords in that territory and if those landlords are approached, they could easily stop these attacks with their influence© 1 give below the names of a few landlords with theta name of their place they occupy:- GUbbAH PrtCPKR OPr: *’A C. Majeed Gat a Living Sbrahim if d ah an* Tiryag Abood© w wassar naji sultan© Mohalla ain jabbar ralah dufayiha buleman x^assar M barhan ohahiya Madkheor Mohisin M in biha Creek© M Machri creek© M nassan uailap Creek* M Gasser creek. “ Abu badrain©Creek * Abu Dhanak© creek w Abu Abeed. creek w Abu bahi© ureek ** Machri creek AT MAN UHAi ALC 1 MG bibb GUbbAii Tiryag Al-nukhakh Abood bheikh i^assar bumatark© Dheikh ^assar bin nassir©/ ^MAD G TEL . ADRESS ARABI KUWAIT P.GULF COD USED BENTLYS % % % OUR REFERENCE •J [/&lt;y , y. ¥1 S o CA ' .1 * 1 J- ( ) 3&gt; ^ AT BAHAWbH&amp; i ^R BmWD GUSBAH Do t&gt;a##d uaji Hamad in uhuabda Otanga creek 2) fl Tiryag mkhakh in Tara Creek® 1 am alse informed that the ring leader ef the pirates is one sADCCN* He is the brother of Madkhoer Mehisin living at Machri creek at Gusbah (wo:9 mentioned in the above list)* He could be caught through his brother and then all the names of the others pirates could be had from him® 1 trust the above information would be useful to you in communicating with the authorities concerned# lours faithfully* c*c# to Messrs Anglo-lranian Oil Co;Ltd; Abadan*0/60-3/7 Political Agency, Kuwait. The 19th January 1945. From. The Political Agent., Kuwait. To. Messrs. Yusuf Ahmad A1 Ghanim., Kuwait Dear Sir, / ' I nave the honour to thank you for your letters Nos P/20/45 Hnd P/26/45 dated the 12th and 16th January respectively and to say tnat I have taken up the matter with the appropriate authorities and have passed on the information you supplied. 2 . I shall he glad if you will continue to give me an/ information on this subject tnat you may get from time to time. Yours faithfully, Political Agent ^ Kuwait. &gt;N0.86/V4- 1 ? January 22nd, 194 1 ? Forwarded to the Political Agent, Kov/eit with the compliments of His Tajesty’s Embassy, Bagdad, w Kof Vgrbe-U V11, 'lljl l \J s /%■ ¥■ Hi* Uajcsty's Kohassy pr«s«nta it* eonplinant* to th* *tii»l*try of Foroijpa Affair* and ha* tha hoi.our to inform than that inferssation ha* baan raealvad from tha Kowait (crarnaant that on '.naawhar 29th, 19*4 thra# aalling craft, on* of which wa* a Kowaiti boat, war* attacked in tha month of th* Shatt-«1-Arab above Fao by armad pirates in a bailaa. Th* Kowaiti boat escaped but a medbar of ahet* war* fired at It* 2* It is further statsd that similar attacks occurrad in tha ssuaa area &lt;m !&gt;acamhar 5 th f 19*3t 0X1 ^ un# 15th f 19^ in which Kowaiti dhows wars looted and in res pact of which His Majesty's Hepresantativa at Kowalt reports that no final reply has yet been received fro® tha $ufcasarrlf of Basra to who® representations were jaade* 3 . In view of these incidents the Gwernsaent of Koweit have asked that steps should be taken to Improve the security of the 3hatt-wl-Arab and His Majesty's Mhaasf accordingly has tha honour to raquast that tha Iraqi authoritiaa conceriwd who normally police these waters will taka all necessary mea sures for the prevent!or. of piracy in future* His Majesty's iimbassy avails itself of this opportunity to r^new tha expression of its 'ugloat consideration* m\nmu mmm&amp;Y BACDA0* 22nd January t 19*5No. 86/3/45 January 22nd, Forwarded to the Political Re-sident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with the compliments of H.M.Ambassy, Baghdad. No. 28 Note Verbale. His Majesty's Embassy presents its compli ments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to inform them that information has been received from the Kuwait Government that on December 29th, 1944, three s a iling craft, one of which was a Kuw a iti boat, were attacked in the mouth of the Bhatt- eI tA rab above Fao by armed pirates in a be 11am. The Kuwaiti boat escaped but a number of shots were fired at it. 2. It is further stated that similar attacks occurred in the s^me area on December 5th, 1943, and on June 15th, 1944, in which Kuwaiti dhows were looted a nd in respect of which His Majesty's Representative at Kuwait reports that no final reply has yet been received from the Mutasarrif of Basra to whom representations were made. 3. In view of these incidents the Government of Kuwait have asked that steps should be taken to improve the security of the 3hatt-el-Arab and His Majesty's Embassy accordingly has the honour to request that the Iraqi authorities concerned who normally police these waters will take all necessary measures for the prevention of piracy in future. His Majesty's Embassy avails itself of this opportunity to renew the expression of its highest consideration. BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGHDAD. CONFIDENTIAL British Residency 6 c Consulate-General, No. 134-S Bushire, the 30th January,1945 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, Kuwait h 31 with reference to Kuwait telegram No. 3 dated 2 nd January,1945.\ EXPiJSSo LETTEH • i?‘rom Britconsul, J^horrambhahr To Repeated Bolioical, Kuwait v/ Britconsul, Bushire (deference paragraph 5 of Bushire Residency ■xpreas Letter No. 3S-3 dated 6 th January 1S45) No. 6^ -16/23 dated 16th January, 1S45. Subject:- attacks on Kuwait boats in the Snatt-al-^ral Beference correspondence resting with your* letter No. 1396-9/1-VI, dated 26th September 1944. 2 . The matter has been taken up with the Military Governor, Abadan who it is understood has approached the Iraqi authorities at i?’ao in endeavour to come to some an ange/oent to prevent a repetition of such occurrences in the future. The case is hov/ever complicated since it noo only involves the question of responsibility for patrolling tne waters of the Shatt-al-Apab but also resents the Military Governor with tne opportunity to demand greater freedom of movement for Persian troops in the ^badan Island, a demand which the British military authorities, for security reasons, are not at present prepared to grant. His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr.Translation of letter from the Mutasarrif of Basra Liwa, Basra, to the Political A^ent, Kuwait'. clear that the offenders are Iranians and have come out of the Iranian shore, and that the victims were Kuwaities, even you have not mention their names in your letter under reference. us and we have communicated with the Iranian Commissar at Khorramshahr and have asised them to investigate in the matter with care and interest and find out the criminals. The communications are still carried on between them and ourselves and will let you know of the result of the investigations of the Iranian authorities in connection with this ^ang. his case has been ^iven a great attention by Usual Ending.COiiflOHijTlAL GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [A T , C ,—This is an ORIGINAL MUSSAGN, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Bushire. To. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Repeated Prodrome, Baghdad. Britconsul, Khorranshahr. Political, Kuwait. So, 169-i» 6 th February 44 . Reference Kuwait Express Letter No. C/61-3/7 dated the IBth January, 194b ( Copy with copy of Khorramshahr Express Letter No. 64-16/23 dated 16th January, 1946 enclosed for Baghdad). Attacks on Kuwaiti dhows in Shatt-al-Arab. 2. Since the present situation on Abadan island precludes effective measures being taken by the local Persian authorities, grateful for any action you can take to deal with these pirates. ATTESTED . 3d/- GEOFFREY PRIOR Political Resident, Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. OLG. s. 6 . MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000.SECRET No.39-K. ' 7 /# His Majesty's Consul, Khorrarshahr, presents ais compliments to - 1) The Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BUbKIKE . / f\ 2) The Political Agent, KUWAIT , 3) The Political Adviser to the Brit Consulates, Khuzistan, ABADAN, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document. BRITISH COMUIATE, rvHORR AMSHAJiR. 3J3 XtfC 3rd February, 1945. REFii.Btl.CL TO PRiiVICUO CwPJtESPON^ENCE: Khorramsiiahr Lx;)ress Letter No.64-15/23, dated 16th January 1945 (to Bushire &amp; Kuwait only). Letter No.2S-T, dated 2nd Februaiy' 1945, from H.M. Consul, Khorramshahr, to H.M. lj?.bassador, Tehran, regarding PIRACY IN THE LHATT-AL-ARA3.British Consulate y Kho r ram shah r. flo.28-T. 2nd February, 1945. Sir, * I have the honour to state that daring the past few months I have received a number of complaints regarding piracy at the mouth of the Shatt-al-Arab. Many of these have Affected Koweiti boats and in nearly all cases it is complained that the assailants come from the northern part of Abadan Island, in the vicinity of Gusba. As the incidents have occurred I have brought them to the notice of the Military Governor of Abadan and urged him to take the necessary steps to arrest the culprits and insure that the incidents do not recur. The problem is, however, complicated by the fact that firstly, patrolling of the bhatt- al-Arab is maintained by the Iraqi Government}, secondly, the Military Governor acknowledges that the Sheikhs in the more remote parts of the Island are out of hand and maintains that the only way of regaining control over them is to station a small permanent military garrison in the area. So far as patrolling the Shatt-al-Arab is concerned I understand that the matter has been represented to the Iraqi Government by Hie Majesty*s Ambassador in Baghdad. The question of despatching troops to the northern part of the Island is however one which affects the British Military authorities, who have stated,most definitely, that they are unwilling to permit a Persian garrison on the Island. I am however inclined to agree with the Military - Governor that unless he can have a small garrison of Persian soldiers, at least in the northern part of the Island, it is impossible for him to control adequately the Sheikhs of this area who are becoming increasingly more turbulent. There is admittedly a small gendarmerie detachment in the area, but the total number of gendarmes available for the whole of Abadan is only sixty, and of these, I understand some twenty- five will shortly be allocated for duty with the security authorities of the British, Army. Steps are also being taken to disarm the tribes in the Khorramshahr-Abadan district but for the time being at least this disarmament plan only affects Abadan Island to the extent that the Persian military authorities ere permitted to send individual officers to summon Sheikhs to surrender their arms. If this fails to achieve any reasonable success the Persians may be permitted, at a later date, to despatch flying columns across the Bahamshir into the area. Ahen this happens it may be possible to reduce to some extent these piracies. I do not consider however that they will ever be completely suppressed unless the Persians are permitted a certain freedom to maintain*and operate a small permanent garrison in the area. I strongly recommend for Your Bxcellency’i His Excellency Sir Reader W. Bullard, KCB., KCMG., C1E., His Majesty's Ambassador, TEHRAILiucc«llency 1 s coneideretion that tht British nilit&amp;ry author!tiec may once again he approached to obtain their agreement to the establishment of a small permanent Persian garrison in the area of the northern half of Abadan. Failing this 1 feel that it is unlikely that *e shall ever obtain much redress for these piracies which are recurring with increasing frequency and which are becoming a menace to shipping under British protection. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, C 3 W' Vi A ri ewart His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr.0 tr-i rir&gt; n oi kji-i 0 * Jl mmuxEMTikh. i vr €7 No. Xio ’73-J The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, KUWAIT CON, NTIAL Kuwait Roc&gt;'&lt; 1-1 £iL . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...2^nd..LAr.cJj.&gt;. Reference to previous correspondence : IChorranshahf Printed Letter No* 39-K dated 3rd February, 1945 v '■V &amp;=t % *?im, &amp;ln Description of Enclosure. &gt; Name and Date. 1* Tehran letter No. 114/27/45 dated 16th February, It45. 2 . Khorramshahr letter No. 39- da ted 23rd February, 1245. 3. Khorramshahr letter No.51-f dated 15th February, 1245. Subject. PIRACY IN THE GULFReceived under Khorramshahr Printed Letter No. 66 -K &amp;ated 28th L^j February, 1945. No.114/27/45 British Embassy, Tehran. 16th February, 1945. Dear Consulate, Please refer to your despatch No. 28-T about piracy at the mouth of the Jhatt-al-Arab. ' As you know, the British military Authorities are unwilling to admit a permanent Persian garrison on the Island of Abadan. Perhaps, however, they might \&gt;e persuaded to take some action against the pirates, either by allowing the Persian operation or by a raid of their own, if it could be shov/n to be certain tnat the pirates really do operate from the northern end of the island. 2 . Nould you therefore please press for evidence and details of the existence of pirate bases in the vicinitv of Gusba or elsewhere. Yours ever, Bd/- J.3. Comers Cocks. British Consulate, IBiorranshahr. No. BP-T British Consulate, Khorramshahr, 23rd February, 1945. Dear Chancery, Please refer to your letter No. 114/27/45 dated 16th February, 1945. Ne enclose for your information a copy of our latest letter to the military Governor, Abadan, on the subject of these piracies. The difficulty is that while tnis letter provides information as to suspects it does not provide proof which would be acceptable in a Court of Law. This, the Persian authorities must provide for them= selves, and in the existing circumstances when they have practically no real control over what happens in this part of the Island, it is not too easy for them to do this.* It is for this reason that we are anxious that they should be permitted to reinforce their small garrison. we cannot see that such a garrison would in any way damage our own military security in the northern half of the Island, and it would certainly place us in a stronger position to demand greater activity in suppression of these piracies. At present, we are in an intolerably weak position, since every time we press for action the Military Governor professes his willing ness to do all that is required, if only he is given freedom of action in the area. V/e are doubtful whether rands by our own military authorities would be effective, since any suspects picked up would have to be handed over to the Persian Courts for trial, with evidence, and it is only on the rarest occasions that tnis evidence would be forthcoming. Yours ever, Bd/ A.C. Btewart. The Chancery, British Embassy, Tehran.Ec»17A HI* a*J**ty'* Er.b***y pre*«it* It* coapliawts to tho Mini*try of Forties Affair* and has th* honour to aeteoolodgt with tharJc* rtcalpt of thtlr Kota 7orbalo Ho«4 52/452/^/2302 of M«ir«h 24th ee&amp;eerniAg piracy on tho Shott ftl Ar«b f ac4 to infora thoa that tho irfcmaticc ccrtaiiod therein has boon noted and passed to tho irtorestod British ard othor authorities* 2* While it appears that the persona responsible for tho acts of piracy wore Iranian subjccto 9 tho ftntrstsy •cold again point out that tho ettacka of which tho Koweltl Geworniiont coaplain, wore node in waters policed by tho Iraqi authorities* Tho Sabassy assumes that, in those circumstances, tho Iraqi authorities concerned are arrangira for offoctiwo patrolllrig of tho Shatt al Arab to prevent the recurrence of regrettable Incidents of this nature* . lie Majesty 9 ! Massy avails itself of this oppor tunity to renew tho expression of its highest consideration*A COPY K.9.i 4 ??/*S/7/339? MIMSTHY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS BAGDAD, 26th March, 1945. fyv/ b*4-' The Ministry of Foreign Affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty's Embassy, Bagdad, and with reference to the Embassy^ note No.108 dated 26th February, 1945. have the honour to state that as a result of enquiries it is revealed that the culprits in the Incident In question are Iranian nationals. Accordingly, the ^utasarriftyah of Basra Liwa approached the Iranian (Frontier) Commissioner at Khorrsoshahr on the subject of the incident and requested him to take stringent measures against the aggressors and to prevent the recurrence of similar incidents in future. The J utasarrifiyah of Basra Liwa have also written in the above sense to the ln * ut *' ’ ic inistry avail themselves of the opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. HIS BRITAKNIC MAJESTY f S EMBASSY. BAGDAD, ’R ece 1 ved under 3 aphdad gndorserient Ro, ^-6/ 7' /45 dated March 10th-1. 4 5 Jo. 173 Jote 7erbal e, 73 / His Majesty's embassy presents its compliments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to acknowledge w;th thanks receipt of their Note Verbale No. 452/452/7/2302 of March 26th concerning piracy on the Jhatt al Arab, and to inform them that the information contained therein has been noted and passed to the interested British and other authorities. 2 . ,/hile it appears that the persons responsible for the acts of piracy were Iranian subjects, the Embassy would again point out that the attacks of which the Koweiti Government complain, were made in waters policed by the Iraqi authorities. The Embassy assumes that, in these circumstances, the Iraqi authorities concerned are arranging for effective patrolling of the Jhatt al Arab to prevent the recurrence of regrettable incidents of this nature. His Majesty's Embassy avails itself of this opportunity to renew the expression of its highest consideration. MINIETRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRE BAG. ID AD, 20 th March ,1945 The Ministry of Foreign affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty's Embassy, Baghdad, and with reference to teh the Embassy note No. 108 dated 26th February, 1945, have the honour to state thal as a result of enquiries it is revealed that the culprits in the incident in question are Iranian nationals. Accordingly, the LIutasarrifiyah of Basra Livja approached the Iranian/Frontier) Commissioner at Khorrams ahr on the subject of the incident and requested him to take stringent measures against the aggressors and to prevent the recurrence of similar incidents in future. The Mutasarrifiyah of Basra Liwa have also^ written in the above sense to the Political Agent, Koweit, in a letter No. 55/3/15 dated 27th January, 1345. The Ministry avail themselves of the opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. HIE JR I TAN JIG MAJEETY'E El BAB BY BAGHDAD. CONFIDE: TIAL No . 410- E Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, Dated the 23rd April, 1345. Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, Khorr^mshahr.corr Urgent* Ho. I&amp;/U&amp;/7/2909 Ulniatxy of Fcrolgn Attaira, Biw dad* X9th April, 194^. The HlMlStoy ot Foreign Affaire present their ca^plliaenta to His Britaxmio Majesty's ^ubaaay, Bagdad, and with referenee to the :jabLssssy , » note Ko.173 dated 3Cth fc^roh, I94v&gt;, hsvw the honour to state that the Ministry have taken note of the infarction contained in the iaba&amp;sy’s abowe*-cientinned note end have referred this infona&amp;tiosi to the appropriate Iratji quarters in oruor to take effeotiwe zaaaaur^a for the strengthening and consolidation of security in Shatt-el-Arsb. At the eaiae tine, the Ministry instructed the Hcyal ira&lt;ii Legation Tehran, on 3th April, 1943* to approach the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affaire with a view to punishing the aggressors and to similar jaeasurea being taken by the appropriate Iranian charters to ensure the object sought by the esteemed mbasay in their above-mentioned note* The Ministry avail themselves etc* f&amp;s ^Ifcannio Majesty*» labasay, Bagdad*(Received under Baghdad endorsement No. 86/8/45 dated 23rd. April, 1945) Urgen t No. 452/452/7/2909 Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Baghdad, • 19th April, 1945. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty's Embassy, Baghdad, and with reference to the Embassy's note No. 173 dated 30th March, 1945, have the honour to state that the Ministry have taken note of the information contained in the Embassy's above-mentioned note and have referred this information to the appropriate Iraqi quarters in order to take effective measures for the strengthening and consolidatior of security in Shatt-el-Arab. At the same time, the Ministry instructed the Royal Iraqi Legation Tehran, on 5th April, 1945, to approach the Iranina Ministry 6f Foreign Affairs with a view to punishing the aggressors and to similar measures being taken by the appropriate Iranina quarters to ensure the object sought by the esteemed Embassy in their above-mentioned note. The Ministry avail themselves etc. CONFIDENTIAL No. 517-5 . Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, 17th May, 1945. Copy forwarded with compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait i H.M's Consul, Khorramshahr . witfci reference to Residency Endorsement No. 410-S dated 23rd April, 1945.Translation of letter No.1143, dated the 29th Khordad 1324 (19th June) from the Vilitary Governor of Abadan. In reply to your letter No.208-15/36 dated February 1945 on the subject of theft from the property of Haji Abbas,' son of Hussain, a Kuwaiti subject, who travelled in the sail-boat of Abdul Khudayyar, an Iraqi subject, resident of Shelha M’aamar (Iraq). Haji Abbas was subjected to attack by 15 armed men in the said Shelha who robbed him of his belongings. Though the robbery took place on the Iraqi Frontier, and it is perfectly evident that Hakhuda Abdul Khudayyar had a hand in it, yet instructions have been issued that persons suspected should be subjected to investigation. According to an unofficial source Yaqub Sobbah, brother of Ishaq, a Persian subject, resident of Kehr Abu Shanak was arrested while trying to sell a piece of gold stolen from Haji Abbas. He is under custody in Kuwait at present. Since a number of men are under prosecution on this accustation it is requested that the correctness or otherwise of this information may be ascertained from the authorities concerned and this Governorate inforaed since it has a great deal to do with the discovery of facts and in making investigations from others. Sgd.Colonel Daulatshahi. Military Governor of Abadan.Translation of letter darei 20.^ 45 from the Head of Public Security Pept., Kuwait, to After CoTiplinents, In reply to the letter received by Your Highness fro-n the Political Ajency, Kuwait, re- jerdin.^ the person naaied Yacoob Saba, Iranian subject. I was informed that this person was offering some stones( for rings) for sale in the market. I arrested tV&gt;e '’n 9 ^ade the preli.'ninary inves tigations. I found out thet these stones are a part of tilings seized by force from Haj i Abbas bif\Husein at Shat-ul-Arab. This was confirmed by Haji Abbas himself when he claimed that these stones were his and he supported it by the witness who confirmed it in my presence. I, therefore made further investigations whether this man was one of the people who attacked the sailing craft, but inspite of all the inquiries, no evi ience could be found to prove that this man was one of the oarty vho attacked the craft. The aforemntioned Yacoob has claimed that he purchased those stones from a person, whom he did not knov, and that he purchased them in Iran. Even then, we did nor i release the man, but kept him in prison so that ve may be quite sure of the case. He was taken ill, while in orison, and as we had no evidence against him, and on account of his illness, we released him. His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait UsualTranslation of letter No.1191, dated the 12th Tir 1324 (3rd July 1245), from the Frontier Commissioner, Khorram- shahr, tc His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr. I nave the honour to inform you that, according to a report made oy the Gendarmerie Unit, at Gusba, some time in the middle of winter of 1322 (December-February 1944-45) some of the inhabitants of Sur, situated at the mouth of the Shatt-al-Arab, loaded s certain quantity of sugar, tea, cloth and other commodities on to the boat of Fakhuda Abood Kuhais destined for Kuwait. Three men from Sur also embarked on the boat. Nakhuda Abood forced the passengers to disembark at Jazira Bomian and took tne commodities to Nehr Khamisa, Gusba Fassar, and sold them there. The owner of the commodities then proceeded to Kuwait and brought the matter to the notice of the Snaikh of Kuwait; the proceedings of the case are fully known in Kuwait. It appears that a communication has also been made to the Persian authorities on this subject. At present Fakhuda Abood, the culprit, is under arrest and has admitted the theft of 25 bags of sugar and a quantity of tea. It is rumoured that large quantities of otner material incl iding amber, gold, etc. formed part of the cargo, it is therefore requested that inquiries may kindly be made from the Shaikh of Kuwait regarding the details of the case and the quantities of material involved. One of the consignees or an informed person may be sent to this Frontier Commissionerate or direct to the Gendarmerie Unit at Gusba, to identify Kakhuda Abood. Since Nakhuda Abood will remain under detention until any result is obtained, it is requested that in order to avoid any undue detention, this office may be informed of your measures as soon as possible. ^itfr'kinde; regards, Sgd. Major Khujaste. Imperial Frontier Commissioner, Khorramshahr-Abadan. for favour of necessary action.CONFIDENTIAL E X P R E From To No.C/716. S S L E t T TER Political, Kuwait. Britain, Khorranshahr Dated the 2nd August, 1945. Reference your Pointed Letter NO.2G0-K dated the 25th June, 1945. Piracy in the Shatt-al-Arab. 2. The Kuwait Government have confirmed that Yaqub Saba was arrested here while trying to sell jewels for rings which were identified by Haji Abbas and others as the property of the latter. 3. Proof was not forthcoming that he had been involved in the actual piracy and he was subsequently released owing to illness. LESTr nslation of letter dRted 4.8.45 from the Public Security Deportment, Kivvo i t, to Hie Kighn esu the Huler of Kuue.it. Pt ^c? After Compliments, I have the honour to 'nfo.rm Your Hi_hness that I have ^one through the letter received by Your -tiighness from tie Political Agerytcv, Kuwait, regarding the Mahr^**-!# Sailing . . ■ ' l ' . Craft which was attacked by Ab^nood bin Lluhaisen, Naichoda. of i x &gt;va&gt; Nassa.ry Beilum. i\hi 1 e the abovementioned craft was anchoring inside Khor al-Basrah, on the sea side, the Beilum, belonging to Abiood Mehaisen arrived there and anchored in front of the ' (|jU»€v^4Uvl Ct '&amp; Mahri craft, end thr a ^ got do-rn the Helium and went to the craft with the object of asking the owner of the craft to give them some fish** Th is is a custom followed by the seamen. The people on the ^ahri craft told them that they had no t i } o n d i n the meantime they asked them where they were Toin^ with their Be Hum, and hen they replied that they were ^mce^din to Kuwait to load sand, they asked them if they jJ ~ * W- vould carry 20 bags sugar of 2 cwts each,PO tins Jhtm sugar, 300 lbs tea and one Ambara and a letter addressed to Abdul- Yuhhb Abdula?.! z Qetami regarding the said car^o. The Be Hum people agreed to carry th^ said cargo, and they were asked by the Mahrie' to go back to their Bellum and brinj, the^r Pakhoda, Abbood bin Muhaisen, who met the Mahri Nakhodha, Ahmad bin Yekaiter and a 3 '? , 5 , ¥ ! ’t the two parties agreed on frieght ^ Rs.SGQ/-# Jhe 3 o ods were transferred from, the Mahri craft to the Kassa- rv Be Hum, and two Mahri men with a young boy were also sent with the said Bellum to Kuwait to deleiver the cargo to its owner. The two crafts sailed, one to Basra, and the other lowest, on her way to Kuwait. dHien the latter, the ^ellum^reached Bubyan Island, on the west side of it, they saw a fisherman removing his fish-traps and they asked him to give them some fish, and in the evening th e ' D ^' 11 'hanged direction to the east,i.e. to the direction of Qusba. Vhen the Mahries, who were on board ■*£/■ &amp; fa the Be Hum saw the ch^njinj of the jj rr r t i ot~ of the o^.ft, -- UnTL , 4—&gt; ‘vV^ (7^ '^3 * re w the h T a&lt;hoiho T s attention an^ told him. that his Belloj- was not sailin y in the direct! on Kuwait, and they expressed their doubts, but he, the Naxhodah Abbood told them that the ci at t '.'o s to change her d4-r^ei^iJdr-rm a^ain and would sail d-Uro-e-t* to Kuwait. ’Vhen they reached the Kastren end of Bubyan Island, Ab^ood, the Kakhoda,and his sailors started '^br' threatening the t h o Mahries the child v.ith a gun, which jf Ab^Jood had in his hands, a,nd also with another gun carried bv uSn ^ one of the sailors and by knives, with which the other sailors were armed. They tried to kill the Mahries, who fy* — started begging them, for mercy and telling that such treatment as against \rab principals and character^, especialDgr that they had shared with them bread and salt, to which Abbood replied that they were to make their choice, whether they wanted to save their lives by landing on the Island, or to l^ose them. The Mabries had to quit the Bellum. and land there, being afraid of being murdered. While they were leaving the Bellum, Abbood, the happen! to notice that one of the Mahries was carrying an AM 8 ARA, which he s.eized. Ke then exa mined them carefully, and he found that they were carryin_ a letter to Abdulwahab Abdulaziz ^etami, which he also seized. He then left tj^jr Bubyari Island and returned to Qusba. Ae -^o^lthe two ^hries a; d the child continued their walk to the other end of the Island, vvhere they met again the fisherman ar.d took refuge with him. The fisherman brought them in his boat to Kuwait be en / As to the question of sending a person or persons to identify the Nakhoda, I beg to state that this is impossible at present, as the Nakhodah and the crew of the Mahri craft who ^ his boat saw SHafehoda Abbood when/ks was chartered ^ are not here but in Bur. They may come to Basra during the season as usual. We have informed/Abdulwahab Abdulaziz al-Q^e tami, that he lias sent a telegram, to his agent in Muscat asking him to write to Ahmad bin Mukaiter at Sur to come personally, and if not, he J&amp;)asked to send some one to represent h.im. We hope he will do so./ Usual Ending.CONFIDENTIAL No ,'843 The Political Agency, KUWAIT. / i Dated the 12th September, 1945. His Majesty^ Consul, KHORKAMSHAHR. / Subject:- Robbery at Bubyan . MEMORANDUM / Reference my Endorsement No.C/751 dated the 13th August, 1945. The bearer of this is Said bin Musallim who was in the Mahri boat at the time of the alleged offence committed by Abood Muhaisin. He is prepared to id^tify the latter. •U-’ I'&gt;/■» British Consulate, Khorramshahr. 8th October, 1045. To The Political Agent, k u V. Al T. Iv'lhuHAl.lJU Reference your mernorandum ho . C/843 dated the 12th September 1945. Said bin Musallim identified Abood Muhaisin at the Interrogation Branch of the Abadan Military Court. Further evidence is being collected, and the Chief of the Military Court has said that, from what has transpired so far, it is certain that a bill of indictment will be issued against Abood Muh ai sin. The Kuwaitis were given the option of appointing an Agent and returning hone. They accepted this offer and, after complying with its terms, left Abadan. /i// '/VCr.T.C. Political, Kuwait. Bepgu, Bahrain. Telegram Prom To No.112. Dated the 17th Pehruary, 1 947. In view of B.B.G. report of attack: hy . \ armed Arabs on S.S. Star of Mex while aground near Bahrain grateful for any facts which I may give in reply to local enquiries. Ship.had some cargo for Kuwait. = POLITICAL = A.M.'LE3' - REPGU - To From Political Resident, Bahrain. Political A^ent, Kuwait. No.207. Dated the 18th and received 19th February, 1947 2 . Your telegram No.112 February 17th. Star of Mex ran aground just south of Pas al Had in Muscat territory on or about February 1st. H.M.S. 'Wren' gave .vhat assistance possible but left February 7th as she was unable to get ship off. Grew Egyptians with Egyptian master abandoned ship February 14th. Political Agent Muscat now reports that most of the cargo which can be readily moved and ships fittings have been looted by local tribesmen who have returned to their homes. Wali of Sur and his guards are now on board. Balance of cargo consists of coal and corrugated iron and it is doubtful if it can be salvaged. /That would seem to have been partly fault of master who allowed on board to / • unload cargo.K* Dm* ghlsflU The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - THE POLITICAL AGENT, KUy/AIT , v/ e and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. ;// /y/Yf? PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 18th February 1947. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency telegram No.207 dated 18th Feb. 1947. * 1 DESCRIPT ION OF ENCLOSURES 1) Residency telegram No.201, dated 17th February 1947. '2) Residency telegram No.208, dated 18th February 1947.^ rom Political Resident, Bahrain, To India Office, London. Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. H.M.Ambassador, Cairo. No.201. Dated the 17th February 1947. B.B.C. announced on February 16th that the 'Star of Mex* 1 had been looted off Bahrain. 2. Facts are that ’'Star of Mex' a cargo vessel owned by the Alexandria Steam Navigation Company Alexandria with an Egyptian crew proceeding to Basra ran aground just south of Ras al Hadd in Muscat territory on or about February 1st. Reports having been received that Master required assistance to remove Arab guards who had boarded vessel H.M.S. 'Viren' proceeded to the spot to render assistance. Military Adviser to Sultan also went to spot in launch. H.M.S. 'Viren' was unable to get ship off and ^ left on February 7th after giving Master such assistance as was possible. Sultan's representatives were then on board and promised to prevent pilfering and arrange local supplies. Crew abandoned ship on February 14th apparently from fear of local Arabs and went aboard 'British Destiny' a tanker outward bound from Gulf. On February 15th a report was received from Muscat that armed Arabs were looting ship and Sultan's representatives were unable to control situation. Political Agent Muscat has proceeded to spot in H.M.I.S. 'Dhanush' and further report is awaited from him. - HAY - \ NPG.33/134 Telegram From To Repeated G. T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. India Office, London* Government of India, New Delhi* H. &amp;.Ambassador, Cairo* No.208. Dated the 18th February 1947. In continuation of my telegram iio.201 February 7th. Star of Mex* Political Agent Muscat reports that most of cargo nvhich can be readily moved and ship's fittings have been looted by local tribesmen who have returned to their liomes* Y&lt;ali of Sur and his guards are nov/ on board. Balance of cargo consists of coal and corrugated iron sheets and it is doubtful if it can be salvaged. Looting appears to have been parti} fault of Master who ^ allowed tribesmen on board to unload cargo. Crew were not in any way molested and left with their personal belongings intact. Copy of Political Agent's report follows by post. - HAY - NPG.3/7 1. Letter dated the ilth December, 1943 from AMulla 7, ull.ah Issued letter No.293-9/1-YI to Mutassarif, Basra Li/a. 2. Letter dated 30/12/43 from Addulla Nullah, Kuwait. P.^. - - Nasir Bu-Nutraq is a village near Gusha in Jran and is withir the Consular*district of H.?i*s consul, Khorramshahr. Nay ve 'write to Consul on the suh'ect? -Perhaps he might he able to bring pressure through the Governor of TOhorramshahr which might result in fcrinxtng prevent a repetition of such robberies in future. ~ ' The translation of the letter from the''water company is not clear. Hay Interpreter be asked to translate it again carefully ltd..A.!.K. 9/1/44 Yes- write to Consul, NOhorrarrishahr enclosing a copy of the translation and saying that I should be grateful for any action he 'can take to have restitution made to the complainants and to prevent the recurrence of such robseries. The f^cts are cjiear on the translation- it will do. ■Qraft submitted please Id/- C.J.P. 10/1/44 Id/- A.A.K. 4. 5 6 . 10/1/44 ' . • . &lt; v .. ■ Issued letter No.51 dated 16/1/44 to Consul, Khorramshahr. Letter No.25/3/35 dated 3.2.44 from Mutassarif , ^asra Li./a. P.\ . ’“'Te have already reported the matter to the British Consul, Khorramshahr vide page May file? Id. A.A.K. 3/2 Id/- C.d.p. 8/2 I think a copy of the original letter at page at and of the p.u.c. should be forwards, under P.L.- to H.M’s Consul, Khorramshar with reference to our letter at page requesting such action as .is. possible to prevent, a repetition of these incidents. ' ' Id/- G.J.P. Issued P.I. No.133 dated 9/2/44 to Consul, Khorramshahr. • Memo. No.P.G.404 dated 22/3/44 from S.N.O.^.G. yeen by P.A.and filed. -* - Is:ued letter No.C/162 dated 25/4/44 to H.H. Nemo No.p.0.404 dated 21/5/44 from C.N.O.P.G. Issued letter No.0/197 dated 6/6/44 to H.H. Letter ' T 4).H.6.2372 dated 8/6/4^ from H.H. P. A . Draft to 3.N.O.P.G. submitted pi. Id/- AjK. ^/6 Issue as amended. 3d/- ■ G,N. 'Iaekson. Issued letter No.C/467 dated 12/6/4^ to 3.N.O.P.G.Mnirim to the Mutassarif •j Have we had any reference from Sheikh at out defend themselves from rohoenes m the Shatt? e mcnoiuneu . me the other day. - . v Id/- • 2/7 ?.A . ^ ;,;0 think''t , ipre is some misunderstanding as pas es are issued ty tMs AFenSv to hakhudas of sailing crafts plying hetveen Shatt-al- -Arlh^ India, Yeman and Zanzibar eta? to carry arms and ammunition I? 1 ' There d we?e C two cases of robberies in^cemher last year in the Shatt-al-Arat) - plea. e ses subject S^of^xile 9/1 Vi. 7 23/7/44* Pi pose psk Abdulla Mullah for particulars of the recent roouery committed in the Shatt. The Sheikh mentioned it to me xour days « gd/- J.N. Jackson. 24/7/44 X&gt; * have spoken to Abdulla Mullah and he says that he is writing officially. ,*/-/** ' ^ Id/- k.k.YL. 24/7/44 7 # Letter • No .H.6• 2408 dated 2^/ '/ 4- i.roin H.. . p (\ page ^ '* T i 11 imu nlease see of this file? 7e represented a similar case/in December last year but he could not take any actiT. peainst the robbers on the ground that they #ere Iranians. &lt;e t&gt;.ari cSicated to M/s Consuf , a ? rrm ? s &amp; ^ but received no reply. Thp Tmnian Sovt have no oowers and it is doubtful if tne^ voun \b ameioMoMfyMinffn suSh matters. Besides tfs t^y might say thpt the robbers are Iraois and not Iranians. I think tne best thirw to dta to overcpme this trouble would be to^approach the Iraqi authorities through the P.K. to allow the Kuwaiti booms oelonging to the water company to take their arms and ammunition witn them, as a Leciai case.inside the shatt-al-Arab river when they enter at night time for water instead of depositing them-'with the -Oiice station atYPao. Id/- A.A.K. , , 25/7/44. Please draft taking up the matter with the Uutassarif of the -'csra liwa and H.M’s Consul, TChorramshahr, simaltaneously. we ^et no satisfaction we can take up the question of arms, as suggested, and use the impotence of the authorities concerned as 'm argument. • . . „ Id/- O.N.J. 28/7/44 t P. A. I/o drafts submitted please. id/- A7A.K. 30/7/44 Issued letter No. 1010 dated 3l/ 7 /44 to .idiorramshahr. Please issue reminders to my letters at pages P . fi t. Draft reminder to Hutassar Khorramshahr submitted 'please. Id/- G.N.J. 2'1/8/44 Id/- A.A.K. Iwa, Consul, n &gt; T T Issued reminder Ho. 1185 dated 22/V44 to Khorramshahr Issued letter : T o.279 dated 24/3/44 to ’!utas anf, asea Liwa.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/177</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/177</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 3/7 PIRACY in the Persian Gulf.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-07T14:30:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (86 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 88; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Additional foliation sequences are present in parallel between ff 2-28 and ff 29-87; these numbers are written in pencil and coloured pencil, but are not circled, and some have been crossed out. A previous foliation sequence between ff 1-88, which is written in pencil and circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file relates to several cases of robbery, which have reportedly been committed by Persian subjects (referred to in the file as pirates) in the Shatt-al-Arab, against Kuwaiti sailing boats, including those belonging to the Kuwait Water Supply Company.The file includes copies of correspondence from other British officials, including a letter, dated 22 January 1945, from the British Embassy, Baghdad, to the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs, in which a request is made on behalf of the Government of Kuwait for steps to be taken to improve the security of the Shatt-al-Arab (since the attacks have taken place in waters policed by the Iraqi authorities). Elsewhere in the file, the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al Jabir As-Subah [Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ], asks the Political Agent at Kuwait to request that the Iraqi Government permit all Kuwaiti sailing craft the right to carry arms for self-defence.In a copy of a letter, dated 2 February 1945 and addressed to His Majesty's Ambassador, Tehran, the British Consul at Khorramshahr, Andrew Charles Stewart, suggests that the robberies will never be completely suppressed unless the British military authorities permit the Persians the freedom to maintain and operate a small, permanent garrison in the northern half of Abadan.Other correspondents in the file include the following: the Political Agent, Kuwait; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf; the Mutassarif [Mutasarrif] of Basrah Liwa, Basrah; the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Khorramshahr</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy in Iraq, Baghdad</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Abadan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Shatt-al-Arab</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Sailing vessels</topic></subject><subject><topic>Piracy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000a4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>