<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:54:19.437Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I© Political Agency, Bahrain. The/^^September 1944. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Reaident in the Persian Gulf, Buohire. V, MliVt 'RAIiDUM . I enclobe herewith, in duplicate, the budget t estimates for this Agency for the year 1945-46. No. ^r^-4/4. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram From To No. A/1532 Dated © No Bahrain Receipt Jyjtf Britconsul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. ^7? 18th received 19th September, 1944. Please expedite despatch of your Budget estimate for 1945-1946. Most urgently required. -3RITC0NSUL-BRITISH RESIDENCY AMD CCi'SULAi'E GBMERAL, BUSElKE. o, 2409 -60/53. A copy of the forwarded to Dated the 8th June IS45 undermentioned paper is fne 2* The Z} The 4. His 5. His 6. His 7. His 8. His Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Agent, Muscat, Political Agent. Kuwait^ Consul, Herman. Consul’, Shiraz * Majesty * s Consul-General, Ahwaz Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas© Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshalir. Majesty’s T n r&gt; +• 1 7 t esty Hahra’V, / (^..'.^.1 Ly order, for Secretary to tips^rolitiCo-1 .iesicoii^ in the Persian Gulf© Relevant extract from Budget Estimates for 1945-46. mPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, (gKoJune, 1945. w The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . SUBJECT:- 15 C.W.T. Military type truck for the use of the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. Memorandum :- Reference correspondence resting with your endorsement on memorandum No.94-13/286, dated nil, addressed to Government of India, External Affairs department asking for sanction to incur expenditure of Ks.2400/- per annum for Sharjah truck. 2. May I be informed whether the above grant has been sanctioned? for Political Agent, Bahrain. UuA.^ ^ -No.670.0130 (9 British Agency, oharjah. Jated the 18th June 1915 ii/ To No Bahrain Receipt . The Political Agent, Bahrain. subjectj- oharjah office Ford Truck : .. v^, S u ^ memorandum. ^ L ^ f Reference your memorandum No.1587-4/4 dated the 17th of April 1945. 2. will you Kindly let me knowAthe amount provided for maintaining the Pord Truck for the financial year ending die 31st of inarch 1946? Political Officer, Tru oaal Coast, Jharjah—Ii NO. c2|&gt;§'g- 4/4-Vol.VII. POLITICAIi AGENCY, (9 BAHRAIN, %26&lt;JtjJun e , 1945* To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, SHARJAH* SUBJECTS- 15 C.W.T.Military type truck for the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. dated the 18th June, 1945* Rs.2400/- per annum for Sharjah truck is still awaited from Bushire. It will be communicated to you as soon as it is received. . 2 Sanction to incur expenditure of Yc » ^Political Agent, Bahrain. JNo. 2631-13/286 BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, Bushire, Dated the 30th June 1946. To CD The Political Agent, , Bahrain. ’ Subject : Supply of a 15 cwt. truck to the Political Officer Trucial Coast (Persian Gulf). Memorandum. Y . Reference your memorandum No. 2529-4/4 dateci the 18th June 1945 on the above subject. 2. The question of the sanction of the maintenance grant is still under corres pondence between the Government of India and India Office and their orders are awaited. Secretary to\the Political Resident in the^Persian Gulf. GSLNO. 4/4 POLITICAL AGKNCYj BAHRAIN, |^/C. July, ±945* To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Uulf, mshire * I enclose, in triplicate, the statements of Fixed and Contract Grants for the year 1944- -45* OfC ^ for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. 3522 - 30/6. No- USS.^Dato ^ The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .. 23rd _ Augus t 1945. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency rcenorandura No. 2631 - 13/286 dated the 30th June, &gt;/ 1945. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Letter No. F.35-A/44 dated the 12th July, 1945, from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject. Maintenance grant for the 15 cwt. truck of Canadian Military type supplied to the Political Officer, ✓ Trucial Coast.ex P r 03a letter No. ^•2848/45 dated the 21st June 1945 frpm the Secretary of State or India, London to tne G-overn* ment of India, External Affairs Department. 9 • • * Reference your letter No. ^Larch. Supply &lt;?£ cwt# truck to Political Officer on the Trucial Coast. 2. His Majesty^ Groveniraent iax mf; r 2P 03a ^. ' or annua l grant or Rs.2400 for maintaaance of thia truck to be classified as 'Special far Expenditure* in the Persian GrUlf . The issue of the above has been authorised. oOoBy Air Mail No.F.35-A/44. From The Under Secretary to tne Grovernmant of India in the Sxtarnal Affairs Department* To Ihe Hon'ble tho Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Dated aimla, the /^/'f July 1945. Subject:- Maintenance Kfant for the 15 Cwt. truck: of Canadian Military lype supplied to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. • • • « • • • Sir,, swith reference to the correspondence ending with this Departaient enaorsement Me* F.35-A/44, aated the 7th Larch 1S45. I am directed to forft r ard herewith a copy of express letter from the Secretary of State for India. London No .Sri* 2848/45, dated the 21st June 1945 and to convey the sanction of tho Government of India to the incurring of expenditure not exceeding R&gt;#2,400/- per annum with client from the 1st Septem ber 1944 on tha miaintenance of the 15 Cwt* truck of Canadian Military Type supplied to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. I am to request that efforts 0 iay be made to meet as much of the expenditure involved as possible from your sanctioned budget grant for the current financial year and the oaiance which cannot be 30 met may be included in your state ment of savings and exc&amp;sses to be submitted to this Department in November next* I have the honour to be, Your most obedient servant. ( SD/- P.N. KRISHNASWAMY ) | Under Secretary to the Government of India* ‘ tNO. 4/4 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, November, 1945. To (v The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . kKiitLORANDBii i - I enclose herewith the statement of anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants of this Agency for the year 1945-46. Political Bahrain. Agent,No. 4 rO - 4/4. POLITICAL AGLNCY, jv BAHRAIN. The December 1945. To The Political Officer t Trucial Coast, SHAHJAH. MKijIO^ANDUM Subject: iiaintenance grant of the Sharjah Reference my endorsement No. 3473 - 4/4, dated the 30th August 1945, to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. hundred): only) from the Budget grant for the financial year 1945-46 to meet the expenditure for the pay of the driver, the cost of minor repairs etc. of the Sharjah Truck from the 1st April 1045, to 30th September 1945, is sent herewith. A further amount for the remaining six months up to the end of March 1946, has been asked for from the Government of India, and will be remitted to you when sanctioned. 3. Please acknowledge receipt and send me the relevant receipts. Trucks 2 . An amount of fcs. 1200/- (one thousand two for POLITICAL AGLNT, BAHRAIN. KMS Qs&gt; \BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION Kar. Form So. 251 H. 94528— 20 pads —44 INSTRUCTIONS FOR DESPATCH OF GOODS. CONSIGNEE f,(\ C ADDRESS: S k p TELEPHONE No. Number of Packages Method of Packing Marks or Numbers Quantity and j Volume or Weight Value for Customs Country of Origin nature or Coods Dimensions of Goods (including packing) Gross Net r~VM, St £ A cA cL - \ CaaA ~ { t&gt; W y ,.. r : ; . ' n no i j 0 Z 'Oil CAM iiA d &gt;3 ) 10 290lU rrrjr ^rrrrr i iTiy ; Two copie* of the relative invoice mutt be attached to avoid ■delay in clearance and delivery. ■7 rh Zrff The Consignor hereby expressly declares that the above particulars furnished by him or his agent are correct and that he is aware of and accepts the CONDITION OF CARRIAGE more particularly referred to on the back of this document. The Consignor hereby authorises and requests the Company to complete consignment notes and olher documents in connection with despatch, carriage and delivery of the goods, as agents for and on behalf of the Consignor under the provisions of Article 4 para. 5 and Article 5 (3) of the General Conditions of Carriage. * \ &gt; Date --11: ^ $ IMPORTANT. Consignor’s Telephone No. (To save delay in case of difficulty). SEE BACKv &gt; H/ • i CONDITIONS OF CARRIAGE CARRIAGE BY AIR. The general Conditions of Carriage of Goods are applicable to both internal and ‘‘international” carriage as hereinafter mentioned and can be inspected at the Booking Offices of British Overseas Airways Corporation and its Associated and Subsidiary Companies and the Airports to and from which their regular services operate. COMBINED TRANSPORT. The general Conditions of Air-Rail Transport of goods are applicable to combined transport (air-rail). ADDITIONAL CONDITIONS. International Carriage, as defined by Article I paragraphs 2 and 3 of the Convention of Warsaw of 12th October 1929, is subject to the rules relating to liability established by the said Convention, upon which the aforesaid General Conditions are based. In no case are goods accepted for carriage with a special declaration of value at delivery. The insertion of the value of goods, for any purpose, in any part of this document or of the Consignment Note(s) shall not constitute a special declaration of value at delivery. The right to substitute alternative carriers is reserved. BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION, and its Associated and Subsidiary Companies are not Common Carriers; and do not accept the obligations or liability of Common Carriers; nor is there implied in the contract of carriage any warranty concerning the aircraft engaged in the carriage or concerning its fitness for the carriage of goods to which such contract relates./TV/, / \ A- A. T. 0. 5-A. (Art. 208-B, Audit Code.) \ fa (— ' (Lo- lj Reeei^t Payment Abstract. w oti * / /^ v, ‘'&lt;iiste lists of slips are sent for separate departments and for receipts and payments. of Suspense Slips issued by Departmental Adjusting Account during the month of ■ * * section intimating adjustment under 19 . 1 Suspense Slip. -No. Amount. Date. Date of delivery to the section concerned for adjustment. Month’s account in which adjusted (To be filled in by the adjusting section). Remarks. Rs. a. p. 7^ K, • 2 Z 1 jT“ •M No. - 61/2. ®) 3 / BBITISK RECIDEHCZ AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSH IRE. the 9th Jenutry, 1946. Ps!&gt; (t The Political The political The Political ils Majesty's ills Majesty's His Majesty's /igant, Muscat. Agent, Bahrain. ^ Agent, Kuvalt. Consul, Kerman. Consol, Khorramshahr. Consul, Bandax'* Abbac. A statement showing the modifications made in your budget estimates for 1945 - 46 is enclosed. 2. In submitting your proposals for the final financial review it may be assumed unless intimation is sent‘to the contrary, that the additional funas waich the Government of India have been asked to provide have actually been provided i /1 Secretary to the pojrltlcal Kesident in the J^ersian Gulf.) iJOLllX d The ^/^ebruary, 1946 To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . Memorandum: I enclose herewith the statement of final excesses and savings in the budget grants of this Agency for the year 1945-46. for Political Agent, Bahrain Kncls1MOTPolitical Agency, liahrain Ihe ^^February, li&gt;46, No. To Ihe Political Officer, Shar.lah. Trucial Coust memorandum: aub: .maintenance grant for the bharjah Truck. I In continuation of my uemorandUia No.5173- 4/4 of the 20th December, 1945, a further sum of Rs.1200/- is forwarded herewith to meet the expenditure connected with the truck from the 1st October, 1945 to the 31st ilarch, 1946. 2. Please acknowledge receipt and send me the relevant receipts. The receipts in respect of the sum of .is. 1200/- sent with my letter quoted above are still awaited. /f.V.w.X—~ • for Political A^ent, Bahrain.(g) Telegram GTC From Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. A/315 Dated 26th received 27th February, 194-6. (* 3 Your Memorandum No. 457- , 4-/4 dated February 9th. 2. Please telegraph briefly reasons for anticipated excesses under launch grant and office allowance. AMO =BRITAIN= Bahrain Receint N °—/.(}.$...Date . “52 • 2 - LTelegram GTC From Political Agent, To Secretary to the No. 153 Dated 3rd '“arch, 1946. • • • • Your telegram 2. Reasons are:- Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. A/315 February 36 th # Launch Grant . Increased cost of winter liveries for launch crew and paints and unforeseen expenditure for spare parts for launch. Office Allowance . Proposed to purchase new safe for office, winter liveries for menials and additional expenditure on account of office furniture and electric current charges. AMO . =POLITICAL=h-Q. (g) Telegram GTC From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Secretary to the Political Resident No. 171 Dated 14th March, 1946. S&gt; Reference my telegram 93 February 5th. Anticipate saving of Rs.4200 half 8400 under Posts and telegraphs charges. =P0LITICAL= AMO .a No. (olit -4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 28th March, 1946. SWir- To The Treasury Officer, Quetta . 0 A iieiiiorcindum: Sub: Reward for passing Arabic Language examination- Payment of Rs.600/- to Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E. Reference letter No.GF 61-62-3037 dated the 29th November, 1946, from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, addressed to you and copy endors ed to me. 2. Please intimate to this office the voucher number and date of payment of the sum of Rs.600/- to Major Hickinbotham, C.I.E.Copy of memo No.FC 35-93-2623 dated the 12th February, 1946 from the A.G.C.R., N.Delhi, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to inform you that the expenditure under the heads nested below up to December, 1945 has exceeded the sanctioned appropriation for the current year, and to request that you let me know, on an early date, what steps you have taken to obtain an additional appropriation to ccfer the excess and any further expenditure that may be incurred during the cunrent year(Art.91, S.A.C., Vol.I). If an additional appropriation has been applied for, the number and date of your application should be quoted. External Affairs: Returned to the A.G.C.R., N.Delhi. Additional appropriation was applied for to the Hon’ble the P.R., who has revised the grant under these heads to Rs.19,100/- and 26,500/- respy. K-Gpecial War expenditure: K-2 Pay of Establishment Exp.up to Excess Deer.45 Appropriation for the year 12500 13900 1400 K-3 Allowances, Hon.etc Apprn. for the year 14800 19146 4346 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 31st ASarch, 1946. for Poll Agent, Bahrain.BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. No. &lt;233^-61/2. Dated the 14th June,1946. To The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Bahrain y/ The Political Agent. KuwAit His Majesty^ Consul, Kerman His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas. MMOMMSW. A statement showing the final modifications made in your budget estimates for 1946-1946 is enclosed. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. VCS.No.2461-4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 29th July, 1946. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum : The statements of Fixed and Contract Grants for the year 1945-*46 are sent herewith in triplicate. for Political Agent, . Bahrain.NO. i's‘^.cl3o * i * ;• To (g) British Agency, Sharjah. Dstea l£th ),.ay, 1946. 5° Pahr- -.••• T^e political Agent Bthr&amp;ir u, /tv) Subject*- Maintenance grant fcr the GoverniLeiit TruclLj ^emoranduma Ref er tinee youi* meinoranduiii bo •674-4/4 dated the 26th of February lfc46. 2. I acknowledge with thanka Uie receipt of Rs.1200 (Rupees one thousand and two hundred only) ana enclose the relevant bills and receipts for this and the sum of as*1200/- referred to in your para 2.(§) Enclosures to Vouchers No. 40 or December, 1945 and No. 42 of February, 1946 of the Political Agency, Bahrain. 26 receipts of the payees in respect of the expenditure incurred for the maintenance of the Truck supplied to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, during the financial year 1945-46.No. 1186-62/1 Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain* Dated 20th Kay, 1947. To The Accountant General Central Revenues t flew Delhi. S ubject * Statement of excesses and savings over Contract Grants 1946 - 46. Memorandum . ^ R ?£?£ ence your ®«®orandum No. TA 8.13/222 dated 6th May, 1947. 2. The book adjustments carried out by you under Busnire Office Allowance and Medical Grant have been incorporated in this office statement* The necessary adjust ment on account of Khorramshahr Central Contract Grant for March *46 may kindly be carried out in your books. As regards the discrepancies relating to Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat grants a copy of your Memorandum under reference is being forwarded to the Political Agents, Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat for necessary action. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Political Agent, KuwaitCopy of A.G.C^s Memorandum No. TA 8-13/222 dated 6th May, 1947 to the Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subject. Statement of excesses and savings over Contract Grants 1946-46. Reference your letter No. A.B. 129-62/1 dated 8th February 1947. The following discrepancies have been noticed and are explained as undert- (1) Dushlre ; Office Allowance. as per statement * 157824 as per this office = 162959 difference 51^5 The flifference is due to the following adjustments having been carried out in this office but not included by youi- Rs 4600/- on account of advances recovered from new recruits in 1944-46 adjusted in 1945-46. Rs 85/- Sharjah Office allowance. Rs 460/- book debit received from C.S.A. Medical Grants. as per statement s 10065 this office figure = 10116 difference •••••••• The difference is due to book debit to this extent received from A .G. Bofcbay on account of medical supplied having been adjusted in this office but not Included by you Central Contract Grants . as per statement * 44979 as per this office = 44479 difference •••••••••o 500 Khorrs,mshahr Central Contract grant for 3/46 having not been adjusted in this office. (2) Kuwait . Office Allowance . as per statement ^ 17903 as per this office = 16696 difference ••••••••• 1207 The difference is made up of as followsx- 1073/- Book debits to the extent of Rs 107/2/- only have bee adjusted in this office whereas book debits to the extent of Rs 1180/4-/- h ave k* en ken into account by you. Kindly furnish details. 134/- Office allowance for 4/45 drawn vide voucher No. 12 of 4/45 should be Rs 745/3/- and not Rs 879/6/- as shown by you. Tour GrantC 5 / ^CvA. ^ ' G- *■ ^ * f\/ r^A^K — • . I --1 V x ’ ^ P-0 b +* I - o a -VNCuC^X . ^ f ■x-v r'k-'- o. ’ ^»{ , i. V r . *' \^,Va^a ») m.5 IV/iV ftz*^ A/r / 2 £ -&amp;//Z erf &lt;? 'A 4-6 vT- The excesses and savings in our budget grants anticipated after the final review have to be telegraphed to Bushire on the 5th Feb. The revised grants (as per p.u.c.16), total expenses up to the end of January, 1946 and anticipated expenses for February and March 46 are given in the statement placed below: f It is considered that the following additional amounts will be necessary:- Rs. 1900/- U 31 A C.3. Allowances, Hon. etc. Launch Grant (provision has been made for the cost of Diana's engine, Rs.3110/-) 1000/- Office Allowance 4000/- K.2. Pay of Establishment 2100/- K.3. Alices. Hon. etc. (includes T.A. and D.A. admissible to Capt. Murphy for his trip to Jerusalem) 3150/- The following are anticipated savings:- r .3. Pay of Officers 1800/- B.5. Other Charges 400/- K.l- Pay of Officers (Provision has been made for the Joining time pay of Capt. Murphy from 28-2-to3-4-45 for which authority from AGCK is awaited) 1200/- K.4. Other Charges 3000/- rushire ha\e Sanctioned Rs.2400/- for the bharjah Truck and have 3^ include': the amount under the head K-4 .Other Charges, $sri which the revised grant is Rs.5700/-. We have already spent : s.82/5/- fromLaunch Grant . Diana’s engine costs Rs.3200/- nearly and in February we have spent Rs.500/-. there‘is a debit balance of Rs. 300/- under this head, which and the expenses for March, 45 can be Met only by the additional fund of Rs.1000/- asked for. Office Allowance n'e showed c* sum of^is.ByOO/- as anticipated expenditure under O.a. for February F March, 46, basing on the actual expenditure under this head in January, which was Rs.3900/- As there has not been much of additional expenditure due to repairs ^or furniture etc. the expenses for February have come to Rs. 1700/- only. Alec uric current charges have been on the increase and funds have to be provided for the purchase of the safes. If approved, in view of the low expen- i diture in Feby., we Might surrender As.iOOO/- out of -fee the j^ 1 x\S.4000/- that we hcive asked for. D.f.a. 3 o (F/). fj) _ qltlLeJl. 3/ . r • y Jk JL&gt;tf J2. ^ 3 jl . V 3 c, ('L, &amp; G /— '</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1126</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1126</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/4 VII Budget Estimates for 1945-46.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T12:01:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (60 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, and terminates with a set of notes at folios 56-61. Circled serial numbers in ink, which occur throughout the file (red for incoming, blue/black for outgoing correspondence), refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 62; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-53; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the statement of budget estimates for the Political Agency, Bahrain for the financial year 1945-46, and associated financial statements and correspondence for the same period.The correspondence is mainly between staff of the Political Agency, Bahrain, and the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf. There is also some correspondence with the Political Officer, Trucial Coast (POTC); and the Residency Agent, Sharjah.The budget estimates cover expenditure on pay of officers; pay of establishment; allowances, honoraria etc.; secret expenditure; and other charges. Also included are detailed pay statements for officers and establishment; statements of 'K-Special War Charges'; statements of fixed and contract grants; statements of anticipated excesses and savings; and statements of modifications.The correspondence consists of covering letters, and correspondence concerning particular items of expenditure. The latter particularly concerns the maintenance grant for the truck supplied to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, December 1945 - August 1946.The date range gives the covering dates for the main items of correspondence; the earliest and latest dated additions to the file are entries in the notes dated 25 June 1944 and 15 June 1947.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Motor vehicles</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food prices</topic></subject><subject><topic>Funds</topic></subject><subject><topic>Fees</topic></subject><subject><topic>Cost of living</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air force personnel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Army</topic></subject><subject><topic>Travel allowances</topic></subject><subject><topic>Coffee</topic></subject><subject><topic>Hospitality</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>