<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000255_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:46.075Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SECRET. o (/ No. C. 273. From Brigadier-General William 0. Walton, Acting Political Resident, Aden, to tlie Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay. Aden Residency, Sir, 14th March 191 b. 1 have the honour to forward herewith a Note on the present political situation in our Hinterland and beyond the Border, by Lieutenant Colonel Jacob, Imst Assistant Resident, and to state that I am in general agreement with his views. 2. If I may say so, our past policy in this part of the world appears, for some reason of which 1 am not aware, to have been based on passive principles corresponding to and probably partially accounting for our present military role of “passive defence.” 3. As a result of the world war, the past will remain in history sharply divided from the future, and each will receive judgment on its merits. The present, being the child of the past, must inherit its qualities. The passive defence cannot now be changed until the Imperial Military situation permits. The sooner the better. But, at least, the foundations of a future policy may be laid now. 4.. To me, if 1 may say so without presumption, it seems as necessary in South Arabia as ever it was in India or Lgypt, that we should undertake “ the white man’s burden,” and accomplish our mission by means of gradual, masterful penetration, including the construction of roads, railways, schools, hospitals, Ac., and the maintenance of law and the pujc Britainiica. If we do not, other white men, less conscientious perhaps, but more alert, will, before long, claim the responsibility, and the right to open up this country to free traflic and to civilization. To sum up, l advocate for political as well as military reasons the immediate commencement and further continuation, in accordance with the situation, of roads and railways on a pre-arranged scheme, with a tinal view to the proper government and protection of our Protectorate. 5. It seems improbable that Government can have already determined what is to be their future policy in the Yemen, but 1 feel sure that an early indication of what is to come would be of great value. I have. Ac., William 0. Walton, Bri gad ier-G eneral, Acting Political Resident, Aden. No. 0. 274. 14th March 1916. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. William C. Walton, Brigadier-General, Acting Political Resident, Aden. S. 303 A9 Present Political Situation in our Hinterland and the Border. beyond 1 Since the fall of Lahej on 4th .Inly 1U15 our prestige lias naln all&gt; been on the wane No Aral) loves the Turk, whose rule is strict ami ichn « The Amb does not love us, but it is just a matter o coinparatne reatine.lt. lie receives our doles, and is not going to forgo this concession in return for a very nebulous compensation irom elsewhere. o Since the fate of Uhej we are now to-day confronted with the following facts : — The 1 laushabi Sultan, through whose country the Turks is now Turkish So is the entire tract of Subeln country and the inanj Sheikhs \mir N'asr, of Dala, too, has gone over and draws a luikish stipend. Some of the Shairi villages and Sheikhs have followed surt ; a so the Hill of Jihaf. The Alawi Sheikh had to go to l.ahej owing to 1 iikn pressure The principal Sheikh of the Itedfan coterie-Mtd.annned Saleh he Kotaibi—declares for us, but is apprehensive of a lurkish mcuiston afle seeing the fate of tlie Shairi village of A1 .Malaha and the phg ll o *° se ° 11 the itla plateau. Ills nephew went to Lahej to treat and temporise 1116 TheLadl, Sultan, urged by fear, and seeing what befell the Abdalt at I diei answered the I’asha’s call to Lahej. We protested at his action, md in fact we checked the Turkish advance on Harm- by the reconnaissance ' f l;)ih l inuirv I'lHi when the Turks had the worst of the engagement. We shal( bhune Sultan llusein for this defection if we view tlnngs through his spectacles. He knows of our power in ordinary times, hut sees us engaged all over the globe, and has noted our witlnhawal tom Gallipoli and the present impasse at Lut-al-Amara. . j'' as umn'' 1 \ ) . a h’ s ,S concerned the Turks are in closer touch with him. l ie Arabs intellect,” as their proverb puts it, “ lies in Ins eyes.’ Ho has no future and ‘““The^ate'luUan of the Bani Kashi (Lower Yafa) was anti-British a.ul auti-Fadli alike. The newly elected Sultan is an unknown quantity. 1 e is said to he a Turcophobe. lie has no incentive to join us at this jumtuic. His tribesmen are out of hand. Several of the various clans have addressed us to know our policy. i *1 41 ..,;,. Some of the Upper Yafa nou-stipendianes have long resented ihcii exclusion from our circle of friends, i.e., recipients of doles, for democratic ' Arabia owns no superior, ami cannot understand our choice ol Inends _not always a happy one. Goaded by the non-recognition of their claims, these malcontents have for long been in touch with the Imam of Sana, and the descent of the Turkish forces opened an avenue lor securing loot and some monetary consideration from the Pasha. .... - , ., The Bed a Sultanate is hedged in by a coterie of tribesmen, of whom the Humekani and Azzani are the.most influential. The former have been for some time past in communication with the Imam. Hie new Multan has not collie down to sign the Treaty. It is doubtful whether Ins tribesmen will ^ el The Slier if ^o^Behan to his norih fears Imam’s intrigue, and is always at variance with his tribesmen and the rival faction of the Saiyids. I am not cpiite sure of the attitude of some other of our stipendiaries in Upper Yafa. They write letters teeming with loyalty, but 1 know of an interchange of letters between some of them and the transborder Arabs, and some sort of secret understanding exists. Prior to the affair at Lahej the yiausta NukaM (stipendiaries) wrote to the Abdali Sultan that they would come as mercenaries to his standard if called hy hini, but would not attend the cab of the Resident. These Yafais will go where their interest leads 'Lhe passing over of Arabs to the Turks does not mean that they will assist the Pasha in arms against us, nor indeed does the Pasha desire a horde of Arab mercenaries in his camp. He has his own Arabs of laiz and oi3 I he l urks came down to Lahej rather reluctantly, and the 1'asha’s object was to prove to the Arabs that their interests lay in espousing the call of Islam under his leadership. Another, and military, reason, was to tie up British troops in Aden. Mis own circulars ceaselessly aim at repre senting us as forcing the Moslems to light their brother-Mosleins, the Turks; and he is a glib quoter of the Koran. 1 he presence ol the 1 urkish camps in our close vicinity has politically a bad efleet. This ellect wilt be more serious as time advances. So Jar the Pasha has failed to win over such eminent leaders as the two Aulaki Sultans, the Aulaki Sheikh, the Amlhali Sultan, or indeed any one in the Hadramaut (so far as we know though letters have passed) and as a whole ( pper Vafa have rejected Turkish overtures. The idea of a Jihad is g( n&lt; i'ill\ iidicuhal. I here is a limit, however, to Arab patience and with the march of the days these our friends may get to think our cause is less stiong than the\ believed. I he fadli reluses to accept that his going to hahej was a defection and stoutly alleges he was impelled by “force majeure and that his return to Abyan and the partial resumption of the cnia\nn tiaflio to .\den will coiioborate this allegation. Since, however, he is thought to be in receipt of a Turkish dole and also allows a’ free How’ of supplies to Lahej w r e have been obliged to withhold his stipend and to lay an embargo on his port of Shukra. lie has been invited to Aden to state his case and prove his friendliness, but he is not expected to complv. His position on the sea coast and the fact that Shukra is the chief inlet for trade fiom Aden to the eountiies up north and east has generally inconvenienced our friendlies inland. In this lies the real significance of the Fadli’s defection to Lahej. lo palliate the dilliculty we have allowed certain goods, under guarantee, to go to Shukra for the* use of the tribes above, but the supply i s necessarily very restricted, so as to guard against Arab cupidity and the transfer of some of these goods even to the troops at Lahej. It is not reasonable to trust to the display of the outraged feelings of our Friendlies against the had 1 1 Sultan, and the net result ol our action will be resentment against the authors of a policy which has failed to differentiate between friend and foe. The genius of the Arab is to defend his hearth and home and he has a marked disinclination to unite against a brother Sultan, lie may fall back on the pious reflection that all is (Jod's will, but he will think little of the ( lovernment w hich cannot remedy the situation. The Sultans have little power over their armies and it is these rather that direct the Arab policy. I he tribesmen of Bani Kasid would have resented a curtailment of their supplies ex Aden. Here the Pasha intervened and sagely arranged a three months’ truce betw'een the Ladli and those of Al Kara and between the Fadli and his recalcitrant tribesmen of 1 laidara Am Mansur, a clan who were the first to hasten to the Turkish overtures. That a Tui kish Pasha could succeed in reconciling even temporarily tribes so long at variance is a tribute to Islam’s success where we have always failed. This will be the interpretation by Arabs generally and is detrimental to our prestige. There is only one way of counteracting the ill-effects of this Turkish incursion, and that is by force of arms, and, if successful, the whole trend of Arab feeling will be revolutionised. No diplomacy hereafter will lie of any avail. A peace with Turkey and a diplomatic set-back of Turks will not improve our relations with the Arabs. Our retreat from Bala in lb07 was ascribed to superior Turkish diplomacy and the earlier delimitation of the border did not enhance our military prowess. We have engaged at the conclusion of the war to adjudicate, where feasible, between the conflicting claims of the Imam and the Idrisi. Unless we act by force, and that successfully, none will accept our mediation. Further, when Turks are set back by diplomatic machinery, we shall require a very large force to bring to book Arab tribes who have not so far been impressed wdth our military resources. I am sure that a march on Lahej would draw large hordes of Arabs on the retreating Turks. To proceed to outside spheres : — “ The raising of the standard of Islam behind Aden ' writes Mr. Archer of Somaliland, “ has not passed unnoticed in the Somaliland Protectorate.” His despatch refers also to the bad effect of our inaction in Abyssinia, s. 308. Ati,. hm **» »i **» 'A • fc ssjrit gun iiiiiiniinition. I lieu' i» &gt;i“» u 11 11 '. , n e t() |,i nie a t lljezan the our militiuy movements here, ami 011 ' in ' otller tiehls, but feared that other day that he was assured of w ^ ‘be left m «it«, a so far as he hmise.l ^ \ 8 an extra cheek on his activity perpetual l».ni,rick 10 hm- o won ovel . so l e ly by excess of food to the I he Shent of ;' ec ^. tiouou part and a deiimte programme besides. The Idris, distrusts him, S , ’ l ^ sU ! a Te i, reconcilables and for well-know n causes. ; fs have their game to play. 1 hey against the l urks. ‘. ' t ,.| v if tl.&lt;-v have a given and acceptable programme in8 y oppoee the lurks n oM^ volley tliscloaed. The iahl 'lown. I lue is 7^^;: ',' ;;^ Z TuI . Un though he has supplied food haain of bana has not act. J ) y en are peculiar and of wide range, to tl.eir forces Iha.wpiratiw.sm 1 u jtli 1 y.^.^ ,. e( | aj ISehan, Marib, For years he has been m • I „ an d there is no chief within our Murad, Xawa, .luban, '• ll ' ’|| ] iat i a special fondness for the late sphere to whom he has not written. ' 0 '“u 1 sir Ahmed Sultan Sir Ahmed Fadl, with whom he ~ ^ , V a whole is of the reciprocated the Imam s Iriendship. Om 11^^;^ Zai(Ji llminl . H is ShalV. persuasion ^ 'mt ) ^ mK , er Zai( ]i control and true, however, that all ti n • , t ) )e brought about in eertam it is not impossible that a i* a . over-relinious, thinks he circumstances if the ^ ^ The 1,nan. sees llritish inaction winch ln ' l 'f,,, t0 o ,‘cial dilliculties lies in the way loathes the lurk and &lt;»&gt;'&gt; 1’^ 0 [ 1911 which was concluded to of his tearing up the l/.zat 1 ash. t Anib 01ice believes that oppose the Italian mcnai t. rtunioii along certain lines. Ahmed K •Jgs’-stt triw:.-; ««■'» t!,c 1,1,isi and Imam were once friends. We tried to bring them together early in ITU but the Imam -s pirpied lyy SSK with Italian mterests agmnst d , M ■ ( , 1K , e ' lmlllia l foe without first forgive the In,a n fm « ' lh e Imam was in receipt of a l^'ihi Turkiidtin^ of assistance against his unruly tribesmen Urktsh dole am ,, r :r t widened. d'he Imam rather inclined Of lashul wa r |^ ‘[^^mHng the Turks, and he was much towards uc e' u, • &gt; o lea( . h )lim lhe m anufaeture of gunpow.ler, but nnpressed by out ea jntervention which j s hamlicapping us at tins U 'b ‘Tiunmuie On bombarilme.it of Sheikh Said annoyed the Imam and ^nll aiC at Uhaiya incensed the hlrisi. Both acts spelt aggrattdtse- ment. ; , I(lnsi am l Imam with an influential Saiyid in 1012. Hesidd^ nZwictiirid was impossible. “ Kacb one wtshes .0 get to .. Von of the house.” He added that so long as Maliki, Simla 1 and Ihinih disagreed the Yemen must fall a prey to England 1 discounted all idea o torrhoriai expansion, but he replied : ” a morsel of bread is put into you, f “ m 1 , vou cannot but eat it. You will not conquer the Vemen by fo.ee. .. I s a case for purchase. If al Yemen goes, Islam is gone. There remains another important Sheikh, Ibn Kasir Aukbil of Ma\ia. lie sinned an agreement with us at the beginning of the war, and gave us Ihe choice of three places wherein to meet and come over to us. W e did not I,.ree He is not a traitor to ns and 1 still reckon on Ins support 1 1 occasion oners' He did not join in the tight at Hahej, and long before that date, when constantlv pressed to lead an attack, pleaded sickness and one cause or another. Maria hates both Turk and Imam. Finally, to strike at the Turks before Sheikh Othmaii will imperil their hold both of the Yemen and llejaz, for by it alone will the Idrisi ami Sheril of Mecca enter actively on our side; the former to secure his own territorialL 'll em ]s versus the Imam and the other to assert his spiritual claims in the Jlejaz. The Turkish Caliphate is vulnerable in the vicinity of the Holy Cities of llejaz, and here mainly their prestige lies. I his is the political situation. I he employment of loree is a matter for Military concern. 1 merely state facts I have noted for several years past. H. K Jacob, Lieut.-Colonel, First Assistant Resident, Aden. 10fh March 1910.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000255_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B227</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000255</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B227</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Present political situation in our hinterland and beyond the border'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-31T10:29:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>The file consists of a single document.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 30, and terminates at f 32, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The main document is a note written by Lieutenant-Colonel Harold Fenton Jacob, First Assistant Resident, Aden, and outlines the current situation in Aden with a view to encouraging the British Government to take military action against the 'Turkish incursion' in Yemen. In the attached covering letter which is forwarded to the Secretary of State for India, William Crawford Walton, the Acting Political Resident for Aden, confirms his support of the points put forward by Jacob and urges for decisive action in the region before another Western power takes action and, in turn, takes responsibility for the area. The documents support the institution of a progressive plan by Britain which will involve the construction of public facilities such as roads, railways, schools and hospitals with a view to encouraging support for, and therefore protection of, the Protectorate.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>First Assistant Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Aden</geographic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Protectorates</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sailing vessels</topic></subject><subject><topic>Public services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000255#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>