<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000079_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-03T16:12:56.092Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I IOR:f i —— BRITISH CONSULATE MUSCAT PILE NO: 11/3 NAME OF PILE: CAPTAIN 0* CONNOR* S REPORT ON OMANCHAPTER II. Climate i ■. I *'!' i. v The maxiraum rainfall in 24 hours ^as 3,16 ins. Z6% of the days of the year are calm. On 26% of the days of the year the ^ind is N.T7. and on \6% of the days of the year the wind is S.E. The average annual relative humidity is 2&gt;% greater than that of Basra and 6% less than that of Bahrein. In Basra, however, the maximum humidity occurs in winter, in Muscat in summer. The high relative humidity combined ^ith the high temperature makes the climate of Muscat, in slimmer, exceptionally unpleasant. The unpleasantness is aggravated by the high night temperatures to Wiich the influence of the bare rocky hills almost encircling the to w n contributes. Conditions along the coast are slighly better.Chapter II. Geography. Communications w ith hinterland. The rugged nature of the Hajar of Oman renders communication between the coast towns and the interior difficult, and such routes as exist are confined by the physical conformation of the terrain 'lM and the necessity for water to a few defined tracxs which, in general, follow boulder strewn wadi courses where the going is wearisome to man and beast and frequently dangerous. Commencing from the S.^. corner of Oman at SUR there is the SUR - I3RA - MANAH - NIZWA route following the WADI FULEIJ in a general direction of S.W. by South to KAMIL {Z2 m.) a village of about 200 houses, 'entering the WADI EL HA * IMAH, known also as WADI IBRA in its upper courses, it turns W.N.W. through arid country on the fringe of the desert to BADIYAH, a plain several miles in extent containing small villages in date gardens. The best dates in Oman come from here. Keeping W.N.W. it goes up WADI EL HA’IMAH through an open, sandy plain to IBRA (96 m.) the largest town of SHARillYAH. From IBRA the track, still keeping W.N.W., leads to the oasis of SAMAD,(l32 m.) and then in a gen eral Westerly direction to MANAH (172 m.) an important town and oasis of Oman Proper surrounded by extensive cultivation. Ai t-er leaving MANAH the direction changes N.N.W. through level country to NIZWA the most central town of Oman Proper and the residence of the Imam. There is a branch route from KAMIL, direction South by East through cultivated and well-watered country to BILAD BENI BU HASSAN (5 ra.) the principal settlement of the Beni bu Hassan tribe. Continuing S.E. by E. the large village with date plantations of BIIAD BENI BU ALI (7 m.) is reached. It is inhabited exclu sivelysively by the Beni bu All tribe. From BILAD BENI BU ALI the track goes through broken and sandy ground to LASHKHARAH (16 m.) on the coast. 2. From MUSCAT there is a route MUSCAT - SBMAIL - JJIZWA - IBRI - DHAHK - BIREKI. Passing through MATRAH and the village of RUWI where all tracks to the interior diverge, the route enters the populous and fertile WADI SBMAIL at FANJAH (32 m.) The route contin ues in a southerly direction up WADI SiSMAlL passing through cultivated areas and numerous villages to IZKI or ZIKKI (84 m.), at an elevation of 2,150 ft. ( Prom IZKI a route leads 3 .W, by W. to MANAH). Leaving IZKI in a westerly direction NIZWA in Jebel Akhdar is reached at 104 miles. Prom NIZWA the track winds in a westerly direction under the foothills of Jebel Akhdar, then rises over passes,(highest pass 3,700 ft.) descending into the DHAHIRAH to IBRI (198 m.) the largest to w n of DHAHIRAH.(Elevation 1,180 ft.) At 217 miles the large village of NAZUM in a N.W, direction is reached and following a N.E. direction at 231 miles is DRANK the second largest town of DHAHIRAH. From DHANK the track takes a westerly direction over level stony plain and desert vegetation turning first North then N.E. to BIREMI,(294 m.) the principal village of the oasis of that name. 3 * Tfte route juIISUAT - RUSTAQ - Miskin - DHAHK follows the coast to MASHA'AH (65 m.)• It then turns South inland up the WADI VARA' to HAZAM (80 m.). Prom HAZAJj' it passes through several large villages and extensive date groves to ROSTAq or tJAL'AH KKSRA (yo m. ) the principal village of the PARA' valley. Prom R08TAQ to MISKIN (142 m.), direction W. by N. the route lies along the longer axis of the hill range and turning s.w.r 9 § OUH S.w. descends barren and broken ground to *ARIDH.(157 m. altitude 1250 ft.) From ^RIDH across sterile foothills in a general direction W.N.'W. the track leads through fc* FIDA on the WADI DRANK to DRANK.(l93 m.) 4. The route SOHAR - BIREMI leads N.W. over a plain, then turns S.W. up the bed of the WADI JIZZI which is followed with slight intermissions for 30 miles to HAIL (45 m.) the largest settlement between SOHAR and BIREMI. The track then turns North to NEJD the pass Jttu on the Hajar divide and descends to the .fen plain in which the oasis of BIREMI is situated.(78 m.) From BIREMI the route continues through a desert of sand hills to EL MAQTA* 'the ford' where a tidal creek running in from Lhe sea is crossed. The track then lies across a level saline plain to ABU DHABI —nrgmrw mijmiwi' . ' (99 m.) one of the chief towns on the Trucial Coast. *- Water is in general fairly plentiful in the hilly and mountainous tracts but scarce in the plains. mMCHAPTER IV. Resources - Oman 1 .General • V^e tables •*S 5. Fuel The local resources in Oman are, for prac tical purposes, ne^libible. The country is barren in the extreme and except for dates and fuel, both of ^hich • • • are largely exported, produces nothing. The aridity of the soil except in a fe^ places in the Batinah, and there in mere patches, ^ill not support the growth of cereals, all of ^hich are imported from India, in quan tities sufficient only for the needs of the population. A force landing in Oman ’'ould therefore be dependent for all supplies, except fuel, on an overseas base. Vegetables are gro^n in quantities sufficient for local consumption at Rlfri near Matrah, but the supply of vegetables at other places is negligible. A limited quantity is available at KURAYAT, SUR, SIB, and SAHAR, in which peaces cultivation could be extended RUWI supplies vegetables for the markets of Matrah and Muscat and as it has a large water supply the culti vation of vegetables could be extended. The undermentioned vegetables are obtainable at Matrah and Muscat. Arabic name brinjal badinjan ladies fingers bamia broad beans lubia pumpkin wa'a SUR dibbah cucumber khiad water melon jah melon batikh The main source of supply of fuel is the Batinah4,Grazing / 5.Cattle BaUnah coast. Wood is exported from here to the Trucial Coast and to Persian ports. The acacia bush called 'surar' grows everywhere and is used as fuel. There is no grazing for horses. Small quantities of clover are obtainable at Rir. 7 I, sur, and JCURYAT. Camel grazing is to be found in most parts of the country. There are no supplies of cattle. The few head there are, are used for drawing water from wells, and are chiefly to be seen along the Batinah. Goats are fairly plentiful; the local supply being supple mented by imports from the Mekran coast. Goats in Oman are called 'ghanara'. Sheep are very scarce.4 \ i 1. System of ctrir^ kr^ ^ ^ CHAPTTSH VII. Political. The internal administration of Muscat is civil carried out by an Advisory Council of Ministers. (Pres- odministration ident, Minister of Finance, Minister of Religious Af fairs and the Minister of Justice.) In theory it exer cises all ordinary powers of adrainistration both in the absence and during the presence of the Sultan, subject to the retention by His Highness of the po w er to decide Extent of Sultan 1 s chority. all matters of extraordinary importance affecting the interests of his State or dynasty. It does not, however, appear in the past to have exercised in practise very effective control. At the request of the Sultan an Englishman, Mr.B.S.Thomas O.B.E., was appointed Financial Adviser in 1925. He is a member of the Muscat Council, functioning as Finance Minister and has also a full share in the government of the country. The result lias been a marked improvement in the general level of efficiency of administration. Since 1916 the Sultan’s authority is limited to his capital and the coast line; the populations of ooth the interior and the ^est and North of Oman, and those of Ja&amp;alan in the Southeast, in other words the great proportion oi the inhabitants, do not acknowledge nis sway, and live in practical independence of him under their own chiefs. 5.British Although the Sultan of Muscat is in theory a influence. wholly independent ruler, British influence has been predominant in Muscat since the end of the 18th century; and in practise the relations which exist between the Sultan and H.M.’s Government and the Government of India very closely approximate to those which obtain between the Government of India and an Indian State under the suzerainty of His Majesty. His♦ i His Majesty^ Government and the Government of India have been represented in Muscat by the Political Agtnt since 1861 t ^ho also since 1867 holds a commission as Consul ior Muscat, Political control rests with the Government of India subject to the general control of 1 H.M.’s Government, The Sultan receives an annual subsidy of iw S 6 , 00 u and has since 1912 received a further annual subsidy of 1 Lakh, in compensation for losses arising out of suppression of aras traffic, which will cease with the tenure of power of the present Sultan, Seiyed Taimur bin Faisal bin Turki,K.C.I.B., C.S.I. The Sultan has commercial treaties with the governments of France, 1844; U.S.A. 1833; Holland, 1877, as well as with H.M. f s Government.4. CHAPTER VII. 4.Personalities Suleiman Pasha A1 Baruni . A Berber Ibadhi from Tripolitania. Of the Barun tribe born at Nafasah in Tunis. Has been a prom inent figure in North African politics. An intriguer and agitator, having served Turks, French, and Italians. 'In appearance'(May 1927, Dobson)'short, slightly ^rey w ith beard slightly greyer on right side than on left, trimmed to a blunt point and not allowed to gro^ as a long and ragged fringe as in the fashion of the country; his voice low, his speech easy to understand, his manner dignified and courteous, his clothes all white, of the sort worn by a lettered man of Tunis - such is this exile from Tripoli, He came to Oman three years ago having been refused asylum in French North Africa and- The climate and fever of Oman are said to have aged him very much judging from the precautions he obseived, he must be in some fear of assassination.' Credited with writing anti-European articles for the Egyptian and Hedjaz press. On the occasion of tne R.A«]?. reconnaissance of Peninsula Oioan in 1927 he '-rote a letter saying that if the project -as pro ceeded with,'el barq yi'lam fi taill raakan' lit light ening will flash in every place;i.e. insurrection. He carries very little weight now. Visa bin Saleh el Harithi. Sheikh of Harithi tribe, head of the Hinawi section. An extremely able and intelligent man. Tempers his religion (Ibadhi) with knowledge. Signed a treaty with Wingate 1920. The prop and main support of the Imam of the Interior,me.* . J Interior, the power behind the throne without whose aid his puppet, the Imam, would be powerless. Hereditary enemy of the A1 Bu Said family. Ali bin Abdullah A1 Hamudah. Sheikh of Beni Bu Ali and self styled Amir of Ja f alan. An ambitious and intriguing personality. Has made himself independent of Muscat State and col lects his own customs revenue from the port of Aiqa, adjoining Sur. The Beni Bu Ali are Wahabis but not rigorous in their religious observances. Issued his own passports in 19^9. Professes great regard for British Government to w&gt;hom he looks for recognition as an Independent Ruler. T ‘7as thanked by Wingate(1920) for helping officers and crew of Charles Tellier'. Seiyed Hamed bin Faisul bin Turki. A brother of H.H. the Sultan and Wall of Sahar• Undoubtedly the most able living member of the A1 Bu Said family. The Sultan dislikes and fears him. Suave and courteous he is possessed of boundless energy and enterprise. Issued his own customs stamps. Has a houseful of European furniture and knick knacks and entertains lavishly in European style. Owns a motor car and has roads cleared in his wiiaiyat by means of w^at is practically forced labour. He is in consequence much disliked by the people. Is heavily in debt.CHAPTER VIII. Communications - v)man The only road, properly so oalled, in the country, is- the motor road capable of taking ;50 c^t. lorries from MUSCAT through MATRAH, BXIT-RL-FSLSJ, HT 77 I to BOSHSR. Work is being done on this road which it is intended to continue up the BATINAH coast. All others are mere tracks fit only for camels and donkeys. It is possible to motor from Muscat up the coast as far as MURAIR in Peninsula Oman. No actual road exists beyond the point up to which the motor road referred to above is followed, i.e. 2 miles from HIT I, and light cars need man handling frequently in the many shallow, sandy, wadi beds that are crossed. This route '’Quid be impassable for a 30 cwt. lorry, in its present state. MUSCAT - RTJ^M - SIB - KHABURAH - SAHAR motor road. gpitome . The road traverses the Batinah tract in a general North Westerly direction, through many date gardens and villages along the coast. It is low and sandy ^ith sandhills in places and many sandy water coursesKadis) are crossed. The going is in general heavy. It is just possible for light M.T., e.g. Pord cars, but nothing heavier. Camel ^razing and fuel 1 % axe plentiful throughout the route. .Limited quantities of vegetables, chickens, and eggs are obtainable. Ooate are obtainable in sufficient quantities. «'ater is plentiful, from wells, at 15-20 ft. and less all along the route Limited quantities supplies are obtain able at SIB, 3IRKAH, MUS3H* AH and SAHAJt.No, of stops and total distance. Details. 29 miles SIB 29 miles. General direc tion West. By made motor road through MATRAH, BEIT- EL-JKLKJ. RUWI # (i 500 d and plentiful water) to SARIJC^ ra. village about 30 houses. Road no^ goes along sea shore (lo^ tide) to ADHEIBA 16i ra. # 100 huts; water from ^adi bed slightly brackish but a ~ell ^ith six whitewashed pillars is passed in wadi bed K. of ADHEIBA. Track now along sandy shore of Batinah about 1 m. inland to HaIju &amp;aj L-*m. about 50 huts to SIB capital of Vilayet; abun' dant water from wells 12-15 ft. T)_te palms all places. After rain streams flow along some of the mouths of Wadi Seraail. BIRKAH 18 miles. Route continues through date groves and some cultivation for 2 miles. At 4 ra. MA’ABSLAH LOO huts; water plentiful from -&gt;!Us KHA&amp;rlKBAH 4$ a., 100 huts, ’-ater Xjlentiful. ^a&lt;U KASUHAK 61 m. . 100 huts. SHAKHAKHIT scattered Bedu huts of Kashaiira and Mualiic. rater limited. iiUMBIS m.. 250 huts of Mashafira and Muta'arifa, ' v(tter Um ' ited. HARADI village 200 scattered huts. BXRKAH seat of -Vali on S. bank «adi MA iL population 3000, one third of this Baluchis. Large but ruinous fort. 3 Indian banyans here. Water plentiful from wells 2 m. B. of town.l £6 inilea SAHAM ^4 iu. MANAT IF 4 m. scat tered villages of a total of 600 huts* Track then passes through neighbour ing villages of DIL YAL BRSIK, 100 huts and DIL YAD A3^) 3S SAUM, 70 huts. UAKHAILI? 16m. 100 huts. WOn KL HAMMAK. 150 huts. Wadi Ahin then crossed to SAHAM, seat of a Wall. Coast tov, r n population about 3 # 500; ’^ater everywhere plentiful; 30 bedans. 7 SAHAR 19 m. After leaving SAHAM 145 railss track improves as work has been done on it. 4 xa. KISHDAH. 70 nuts. Track passes through villages of J7AJBZ KL TAHI^IAH and MAJKZ KN NUAFIL &gt;iaving a total of about 100 huts, to AWR IN AT 14 m. , hamlet of 20 huts. SAWKIHARAH village of about 150 huts to SAHAR capital of Wilayat; Prominent very high fort ( 4 storeyr ) and good bazaar. 800 mud houses. Throughout route: Camping grounds - in vicinity of wells which are scattered; numerous choices, but soil is practically everywhere sandy. Water - sufficient everywhere for a Battalion. Transport - about 30 donkeys could be collected at larger villages and towns. Fuel and Camel Grazing - Everywhere plentif il. Supplies - limited. Note: There is a fairly good motor road from SAHAR to MURAIR and it is possible to motor to villages in vi cinitycinity of SAKAR. There is another track over which it ie pos- % sible to motor in a li^ht car. This leaves the main track (which passes through date ^p-oves) at MUSJBJi * AH and skirting the southern irin^e of palm gardens in open country, inland, rejoins the main track at KHABURAH. But it is doubtful whether the diversion has any com pensating advantages as a motor road. .Telegraphs, telephones, wireless. Cables. There are no telegraphs in the country. A private telephone line runs from the Con sulate in Muscat to Beit-el-Feloj, 5 m. where the Muscat Levies are quartered. There are in addition seven tel ephone lines between Muscat and Matrah privately owned by merchants. There are at present no w'/T sets in the coun try. The R.A.F. intend to erect a small W/T set at Muscat with a sending range of miles and a receiving range of miles. It is not certain when this will be in operation. Muscat is connected by the Indo European Telegraph Department’s cable system to the following places: MUSCAT ^ to JASJC 131 miles. JASK to CHARBAR 159 miles. JASK to KARACHI 500 miles JASK via HKSfJAX to BUSHIRJS 481 miles. JASK via HTSSTJAH, BUCK IRK to RAO 6k3 miles. There is also another cable from Jask via BUSHIRK to RAO, 608 miles. KUNJAM is connected by short cable to KISHM island; across the island by land line and then by cable to BUNDER ABBAS. From JASK there is a land telegraph system through CHARBAR, CWAT)UR, ORMARA, to KARACHI. This system connects up with the Baluchistan system through TUR3AT and PANTUR.Authority: ROUTE NO MUSCAT TO SUR R.L.O^QNRQR. January. 1930. ISPITOkK The route ia t in general, unsuitable for wheeled traffio* There ia a good motor road # lately oompieted, from MUSCAT to RUKI miles, passing through the to#n of kATKAH 14 miles, and skirting the barracks of MUSCAT LSVIKS at BEIT-KL-F3LKK 4f miles. BEIT - EL - FELEF is the camping ground for a force landing at MUSCAT. From RUtfl to EURYAT hours, the route lies along aide valleys or follows wid^ wadis where going offers no difficulties. The country tc DHIPAB 23 ^ hours, is mountainous and cut by steep war*la where“lroIng is difficult. From ^IBAB to SUR Ue coastal plain is traversed raid is, in general, level but irterseoted by many wadir with steep *»nd rough approeehee. In places, unshod donkeys have to be assisted, animals if shod, would have great difficulty. Good water is available all along the route. In places sufficient for a Battalion, in places sufficient for a Company only. Supplies are neglliable*, when obtainable, lucerne is the only animal food to be had. There is no grain or grezing for horsea and mule**. Donkeys and cattle are largely fed on dates. Camel grazing is fairly plentiful everywhere. ^ Note:- Garris ions of Sultana Askers referred to are all of BENI AMR tribe from the HADRIPAH. No of stage and time taken in hours. 1 . §i. H aJaR . General direction South, going easy all the way, £ hour R 0 «I, Yi.Tlaro cf about »0 stone houses and huts. Water good and plentiful fror. 5 wells, date palms and extensive market cultivation supplying MUSCAT and MATRAK. Of military importance as all routes to interior diverge here. Leaving RUAI track leads off from motor road and follows kadi ADDAI, until the hamlet of KEIDR, hours, is reached. KHIDR 3 ftone built houses, 1 well 12 ft diameter, 18 ft deeo, height of water gj ft. t dll® to Heat of IHIUR hamlet of MUT*^. ADAM AT, once prosperous, village of Hearn' palms new dying from shortage of water (from msft). There are'about 16 houses and huts. From KHIDR track turns S.E then East along wadi HaTAT to HAJAR. Scattered village of about 20 houses and huts, and extensive date gardens. Part is named MEZRA where the Sheikh Salim bin RAMUD lives. The people are Beni Wahaib. CAfcPINQ GR OUND - South of gardens, level and exbensive. jIATER. Good and very plentiful from large felek. TRANSPORT aND w^UPFLIES . • Nil. FUEL AND CAkKL GRAZING . - Plentiful and near.No of stag© and time takan in hours. DETAILS 2. 11 HAIDAH AND hours. General direction East FAIYADK# along ^ADI HATAT# Easy going. At 5| hours well 4^ ft diameter f 6 ft deep height of water 4 ft. EAIDAH a few huts and date gardens, i mile South of HAIDAH is the date garden called FAIYAER• GiiliPINO GhOUNSc: « Level and extensive. A AT 3:^ - Good, from felek. There &amp;r© also 6 wells,16 ft deep, height of water 2 ft. Sufficient for Battalion. TRaN&amp;PGKT k SPFPLIKfr - K 11 . FlfEL A G^ m L dh AZIKQ, . Seattered. 5^ hours. General diroetion East. Track (on Sea Coast).continues along *adl HATAT and going is jkfefeV. At 1 rtf’ TRITUT i easy. At l£ hours hamlet of rfAHAIBUBIA (BENT NAH.AIB) is pasoed, lying ^ mile to R of track. It has some palms and pro/oinent tower on snail hill. A track to HAIL Gap branches off here; distance to HAIL GAF said to be 7 hours. At If hours hamlet of St)AEIK is reached. It has 4 stone built houses and about IS huts and 1 larg*, prominent double - storyed house on edge of palm gardens. From RTJAF.IM track turns N.E. down A ADI LULAS by easy downward grade th/ough surface is pebbly. At 3 hours well, 4 ft diameter, 20 ft deep, height of water 3 ft. NADI HIJLAE varies from 50 to 300 yards wide with walls rising sheer up to 000 ft. FURYA? la tfca s-aat of a **&amp;ii. There are extensive da to gai^de’^s and sone mangoe trees. Town cons isto of about ISO stone nouses and 400 huts: 2 forts ’’Europe'* built on a rook in the sea and ? ABIA’* at landward ILilt of to^n. Forts have garrisions of a feu Sultans Askefts• Principal occupation of people is fishing. There ere b lar^c bedans, 5 smftli bedane and about 00 , small craft. Thei’e is &amp; track to HAIL OAF (2 hours) and on to HEEARA (l day) the Headquarters of BENI DATASFt - the only considerable tribe in this area, Sultan bin Luhammed (Shaikh). KURYAT has an open Suk and some shops. There are 3 Indian Banyan merchants in KURYAT. C AfcPINQ GROUND - Near sweet wells to Aeat of town and about 1 % mile away from it. WATER.- Good and plentiful from 30-40 shallow wells in bed of WADI MIJLAS. Nells nearer the sea are brackish and used for cultivation only. TRANSPORT - About 30 donkeys could be hired.'5 KURYAT. lo^* oUP^LIj^ . - Piah, lucerne In limited quantltlea• FUE L &amp; CAMEL GRAZING ^- Plentiful and near, fuel can also be bought In the town* 4. 19| KARAIYAT- EB-SA®IKA (On sea coast) (Group of 2 villagea OAGMAH (or RrtJAR and QARIB). n 23*. DHIBAB. /r\ 6. 26., BXMMA. 3 ,Hours. General direction iS&amp;st. Going easy but a short belt of low sand hills is cronsed in 3rd hour. Villages of KURYAT-3b- 8 AGRIRA lio on either side of 4ADI EHAIKA, a large wadi which la impassable for 2 or 3 d*yn after heavy rain(winter). DAGMAR, on east side of tfadi has SO huts. Inhabitants all fishermen. There are a few pains. A Fort (JINAH) on West side Wadi built on »reminent hill has a ^arrision of 7 Sultans Askers, G FOUNp - West of DAtBfiAH. • Good from 1 -frell 10 ft diameter XBft deep, height of water 3 ft. IfrnN^POKT fr St3?PLII^ . - Nil. FUEL &amp; 0A,a! 11, GRAZIN G - Ample. 3f hours. General direction S.K. On leaving DAGMaR track rises steeply over hills and descends on far side, along rooky watercourse. For first f hour going is rough. Thereafter going is easy over tops of hills until DHIBAB is reaoned by long gradual descent; highest hAght recorded by baroicciter 80C ft. At hours from pAGBtiAR track bends t (Eastwards) to DHIBAB. At this noint one track continues South to ASZARA while another branches off H (Westwards) to HAIL GAF (1J hour^ ) on 4ADI DHAIEA, miBAB on east side of wadi, 50 houses,large date groves. The people are GADANA. - East of village,hilly and s ion/' ~ Good from 5 wells in ,Yadl basin TK^rOK? ^UPPLII^S . - Nil. FUEL A OA-^iL (HAZING - Scattered. 2 f hours. General direction 3.E. Track traverse* coastal plain where going is easy. Plain is here, on average 1* miles wide. This part of coastal mountain range is called JEBEL QATAR. BIMKA about 60 nouses. The people are GADANA. CAMPING GROUND. - East of village. extensive^ Good from 4 wells, 12 ft deep height of water g* ft. Tiv ANapQRT Sc SUPPLIES . - Nil. WiKL lc QuaiiL OttitziNO - Scattered.7. TI#I 30S. 9. S4|. hours* Oonoral direction Bast* Track follows coastal plain here about 3 miles wide* At 1 hour large prominent 'Sumr' tree on small headland* Going excellent* At 2 hours x fishing village of FIHS is reached, 6 G houses; no palms, water from spring in mountains S.5~, li hours away* After rain, water is obtained in ample quantitios from shallow holes in wadi bed near village. Sheikh of coastal GADANA Said bin Aleh lives here* After leaving FINS several wadis with very difficult approaches are crossed. At 4 hours track passes along beach. At 4^ hours SHABB, a small village of 15-20 houses built on edge of very precipiloue wadi, is passed. TiftI, large village of many palm trees on tfadi KEKHA - 150 houses. OA&amp;PING ORODH P, - 8 .B. of village. Level a&amp;d extensiveT WATliJR.- From 20 wells, 10 ft deep, height of - water 3| ft - water plentiful. T5\kNS P ORT aUFFLUS* - Nil. FUFiL &amp; GAiviBL CSinZIN G. - Scattered. KALHAT » 3^ hours. General direction Bast, along coastal plain. Going easy between wadis but many of these are crossed and all are difficult. At 2-2 hours the small village of HAI3EA is passed. It lies J mile to R of track at foot of mountains (Seelt RAItfA on Admiralty Chart). KALRAT,*115 houses, one large prominent tower has garrison of 2 Sultans Askers. Two smaller towers unoccupied. There is a ruined building S.E. of and close to village said to be a relic of Persian occupation. Kalhat la in rt&amp;di of sffcm© name also called ftadi Beni Jabir from which tribe mountain range is here also named. OAhPING QR 0U1Q - Last of village. Uneven aM sicnf&gt;r WATH\ - From 4 wells 12 ft deep, height of water 3 ft. Tho water is very slightly brackish. f jftANbPQftI &amp;. SUFPLI:^ . - Nil. FU EL &amp; CAMEL GfinZINQ , - Plentiful but scattered. BBLAD- 3f hour’s. General direction S.E. Going is ESj-SUR. easy. At 2 4 wadi HAFAR, a few poor huts are reached. There is here a well 6 ft deep 1 ft of water. 2f hours. KUHIA is reached. Two wells 6 1 deep, l| ft of water. A Fort (JINAH) containing 35 Sultans Askers is passed before reaching BELAD- ES-SUR. 8 KLAD•BS-SUPw, large village, extensive date gardens. Over 80 wells. CAMPING GROUND .~ On ridge S.5. of village « Level anrTextentive. TRANSPORT - About 30-40 donkeys could be HIFea;— FUEL .- Plentiful. GRAZING.- Plentiful.Lucerne is available -Appendix I. The currency of the country is predominantly the silver Maria Theresa dollar called 'riyal' and the Muscat copper coin called w 'beza ,, (a corruption of the Indian word 'paisa'). The principal silver coin in use in Muscat and Matrah is the Rupee w hich would also be accepted in all places alon^ the Batineh and now-a-days in most places inland. The generic term in common use for money is ♦ 'gawazi', plural of 'gazi', originally a Persian copper coin no longer in general use but which still circulates in Ja’alan. The value of the dollar fluctuates according to fluctuations in the price of silver, and that of the Rupee according to the requirements of local merchants. The table given below shows the fluctuations in the rate of exchange during the years 1927, 28, 29, and the first three months of 1930. Year Rupee exchange per 100 dollars. 7/aximum Minimum per 100 dollars. 1927 Hs 133 1928 &amp; 132 1929 &amp; 126 1930(firsts 103 3 months) (June) (September) (January) (January) 3s 126 (May) 3s 1 25 (December) 3s 104 (December) Ks 90 (March)— -1 . 8 # ater Supply (a) (b) (c) (a) (e) (f) (g) (h) Regarding - bat larding j'eciliti # .'e are there at ani als i\ao he: v. vehicles• for lancing troops. X*otr 1 &lt; 0 • of ?elJs available enr* their er ro&gt; • c: pncity* hovf ere the wells lined e.g. with brick. Iier eter of we! 1 £ # l epth of rurfnce of water belov ground level • i ot j this vary with the tine of the yerr and if so hov; ? -leipht of vjiter in wells. -inimura daily yield from wells, it gpHone, which coul^ be relied on «• Does this vary with the tine of the yenr. how Mi cl* vp ter available for troop r?fter need of inhabit, nts have been meet. • hpt possibilities are there of obtaining water fro'r* othe places within reasonable distance of and if these posoi. ilitles are worth considering vRJt me nr&gt; of transport ? ist. (i) • . t • ies (c, 5 • A c. c oinrr.oda t i oi (ai (b (c ould it bo pos. ible to sink fresh veils after troops have li nded. If so what locolities p-r^ rr cor ended. ^hat local supplies ere obtainable. hat quantity could be available for troops after needs of civil population have been supplied. /re there any possibilities of extending cultivation. hat locrl forms of transport are ther&lt; • Id these be use any pur In whrt aurntities# Are there any restrictions to movement in vicinity of Is there any suitable covered scco. ; odftion available for hous 1 ng troops• If not, would t^nts be suitable or would it he neces ; ary to provide hutting. II the latter is material avail,'b!e locrlly. Is the selectionof camp sites entirely governed by water supply. ♦ ice (a hat are the most suitable positions for defence (i) of the town. (iij of the troops tt.l ing as a basis a minimum of 1 Bn. hat points of locrl tactical importance should he occupied*(b) (c) (d) (e) (f) ( s) (h) (i ) U) (k) (D ■#hat Is the recent history? (to enable one to a opr 0 date present political situation). What are the political boundaries? What are present relations v/i th neighbours? Who is the Imam? Where does he live? What is his faction? To what extent has Wahabi influence infiltrated? Who is the Sultan? When appointed? relation to Imam? What are the treaties with Great Britain? and to what extent do they render Great Britain liable to protect him by land? Do our Treaties extend to Imam? Brief Note on outstanding feuds and their origin. Ghafiri^aii, Hinawiyah - present significance . 0 What control has Sultan outside Muscat? Mention a few personalities. b Cth, . is Suleiman A1 Bar uni worth a mention. Sources of In format! on. K, Political Agent. Handbook of Arabia vol.l. Gazetteer Persian Gulf. Local.geography* (a) (b) (o) (d&gt; (o) (f) U) (M ll . Afti&gt; CLl^A^F.. ( AU, ) (toiidral do&amp;ciiptlon e*^« »»* liberal, barren hills acne, oulilvated aroap, s^iall borne and vlilapps, ohief cases, desert* What are the geo^raphleal boundaries of ? Into ahat dlvlalona Is divided? What strategic points or* places exist In ? What landing fuel 11 ties exist at for landing troo[», airlmals, guns, heavy vehicles e # g. M*^.? What lai.dlng places ai e there other than port(a)? What wa^er supply la there at ifiiat ccmnunlcations are there frexa (i&gt;\xmary of • n: detail)* ? to hinterland! . ketches, where possible, shewing positions ©* wells* tabula* ed list oarping grounds shewing details of water arrangements * OlljRate* (a) Oener^l note* (b) (c) (d) l«) sources of In format 1 on • ^abis shewing average ten per a lure and aumldlty d*^ring 12 months* lain fall average and at what 11 xne of the year may It be expected* Local climatic pecoll aril lea, storms, shemal etc*, and their effect on local conditions fra? a military point of view* Prevalent Illnesses and diseases V a ) T&amp;demi o * (b) Kpiaomic* (c) Insects* (health pieoautlcns NO'’needed )• Handbook of Arabia Vols* 1 &amp; 11 • mset tser Persi an Tulf* Local Politic*!, l*A,^* Purvey* Senior Naval O^Ticer* Personal 1 ecormial rs^nce.1. znAirnt. xix. j &gt; cpui,Anc» ^hno^raphy * hort nor«. General ehaxaoterlatl ea. Stocrt Hole* Population ♦•owns by oate^orl.ee In round nimbore with short description (of Teople )• 4* Bi le* hi stfoy and orl ^ns o'* ,f 4 ms*. . Tabulated Hat of tribes (in form ©hewn below). Details of Wahabi and other tribes Immediately outside area, e. 3 . Ajman, Awaalm, Putolr, etc. m he most important factor in ccnsidertn r the tribes ts the extent to which aha hi Ideas have or are spleading. Principal camping centres of tribes 'Von hinterland when entering area 0 8 . Labour avallab e In dl^eient districts, normal wages, how beet obtained, availability cut el da Its own district. 1 ell ^cos. short not e. Fahabls, Tbatthls, Dunnes, ??hla 8 , Jews, etc.. oui ces of Infcrmat 1 on • Poll tl oal, Handbook of Arabia. Gazetteer Persian dolf• Local.&amp; No. * X /U.U.3 - 'VfT kmj Headquarters, India, General 3tai f Branch, Hew Delhi, the B6th. Novenber 193u # To : Ihe Political Lgent and H.B.LPs Consul, MUSCAT, P3iSIkM tiULF. V«ith reference to your Ho,1124 dated the 16th. November 1930. I send herewith copies of Captain O’Connor’s report on the routes MUBCaT - oOHAR. MUSCAT - BUR. 2. There is no particular point on which 1 require information re^ardin^ these routes, but I would be ^lad if you could find the time to comment on these reports after the conclusion of your journeys and send ne any additions,or possibly,corrections, which you may think necessary. DEPUTY DIRECTOR, MILITARY INTELLIWSMCE.CHATTER Till. Communications - Oman The only road, properly so called, in the country, is the motor road capable of taking 30 cwt. lorries from ITUS CAT done on this road which it is intended to continue up the HATIUAH coast. All others are mere tracks fit only for camels and donkeys. It is possible to motor from Muscat up the coast as far as MURAIR in Teninsula Oman. Uo actual road exists beyond the point up to which the motor road referred to above is followed i.e. 2 miles from RITUI, and light cars need man handling frequently in the many shallow, sandy, wadi beds that are crossed. This route would be impassable for a 30 cwt lorry, it its present state. U Epitome . The road traverses the Batinah tract in a general Uorth Uesterly direction, through many date gardens and villages along the coast. It is low and sandy with sandhills in places and many sandy water courses ( wadis) are crossed. The going is in general heavy. It is just possible for light U.T., e.g. Ford cars, but nothing heavier. Camel grazing and fuel are plentiful throughout the route. Limited quantities of vegetables, chickens, and eggs are obtainable. Coats are obtainable in sufficient quantities. Uater is plentiful, from wells, at 15-20 ft. and less, all along the route Limited quantities supplies are obtainable at 3IB, BIRKAH,MU81IJ f AH and Sahar. No. of stops and total, d istance -R e .tail&amp; 1 29 29 miles. General direction Test. Uy made motor road through MATRAH,BEIT-UL-rELEJ, and nelntiful water) to SARUQ 7* mvillage about 30 houses. Road now goes along sea shore (low tide) tc ADERIBA 16-J-m., 100 huts; water from wadi bed slightly brackish but a well v/ith six whitewashed pillars is passed in wadi bed R. of AIKEPA, Track now along sandy shore of Ratinah about 1 m. inland to HAIL RL IRTRIR 24 m, about 50 huts to SIB capital of Rilayet; abundant water from wells 12-15 ft. Date palms at all places.After rain streams flow along some of the mouths of Radi Semail BIRKAH 18 miles Route continues through date groves and some cultivation for 2 miles. At 4 ip.MA’ABRLAH 200 huts; water plentiful from wells KHASHRBAH 4^- m., 100 huts, v/ater plentiful Wadi MANUMH of m., 100 huts SHAKHAKHIT scattered Bedu huts of ITashafira and Tualik, v/ater limited RULIRIS 9f m., 250 huts of Uashafira and Muta f arifa water limited. HARADI village 200 scattered huts. BIRKAJI seat of Wall on E. bank 7/a.di 'lAM'AL population 3000, one third of this Baluchis. Ig.rge but ruinous fort. 3 Indian banyans here.Water plentiful from wells 2 m. E. of town. MUSEN f AH 18 m. Route oasses through date groves and villages of WADI RAFIRI,0GADA,MUREIGHAT,BILLAH each from 100-200 huts of Mualik,Yal Bedr Arabs and Baluch. 5 m. HADHIB 100 huts Beni bu Ilassan then through the smaller settlements of SL T ADI,BIJ ABALI and SHAIBAII of mixed Beni Bu Hassan, Yal Jar rad and Baluch to ' RISER f AK at mouth of Wadis FARA and R0STAQ; population mixed. Water from Wadi AIF at a few feet.4 7? miles SUITEIQ 14 m. WADI AIF 150 huts; SHADS 300-350 huts in two separate quarters population mixed.Hadhadhiha predom inating. WUDAM large scattered village 500 huts 8 n. SAR!.!AT 800 huts. KHAEBAT MAAWAL and KHABBAT OHOWAHIB of 100 huts each. Date gardens contiguous all the way, and water plentiful. SpWEIQ* capital of V'ilayet; ruinous fort. About 8 Indian banyans here. 5 KHABURAH 23 m. KHADRA fishing village about TO 2 miles 400 huts chiefly Yal SA f AD: date palms. DHIYAM 14 m. about 100 scattered huts. HAeJHIRAH 30 permanaut houses, and huts of Albu Qarein. HADHIB 18 m. small village 50 huts. ABBASAH, 150 scattered huts. KHABURAH large coast town. Capital of 'Vilayet. Water all along route. ISo miles SAHAII 24 m. MANATIF 4 m. scattered villas of a total of 800 huts. Track then passes through neighbouring villages of DIL YAL BRBIK, 100 huts and DIL YAD ABD HS SALAIJ, 70 huts.LIAKHAILIF 18 m. 100 huts. KH0R HI HALH.IAI.!, 150 huts. Wadi Ahin then crossed to SAHA!!, seat of a Wali. Coast town population about 3,500;' water everywhere plentiful; 30 bedans. miles SAHAR 19 m. After leaving SAHAM track improves as work has been done on it. 4m. KISHDAH, 70 huts. Track passes through villages of MAJEX EL 17AHIBAH and MAJE2 EN HUAFIL having a total of about 100 huts, to ^EIUAT 14 m., hamlet of 20 huts. SAWEIBARAH village of about 150 huts of SAHAR capital of Wilayet Trominent very high fort ( 4 storeys) and good bazaar 800 mud houses.Throughout route: Camping grounds - in vicinity of wells which are scattered; numerous choices, hut soil is practically everywhere sandy. Water- sufficient everywhere' for a Battalion. Transport - about 30 donkeys could he collected at larger villages and towns. Fuel and Camel Crazing - Everywhere plentiful. Supplies - limited. llote : There is a fairly good motor road from SAHAR to MURAIR and it is possible to motor to villages in vi cinity of SAHAR. There is another track over which it is possible to motor in a light car. This leaves the main track ( (which passes through date groves) at MUSE? Tt AE‘ and skirting the southern fringe of palm gardens in open country, inland, rejoins the main track at KHABURAH. But it is doubtful whether the diversion has any com pensating advantages as a motor road./Oj dw&amp;U' PCtiudo -U 'Mtti ; £lpf' fl/Mj 2. Telegraphs, There are no telegranhs in the country. telephones A private telephone line runs from the Consulate wireless. in Unseat to Beit-el-Felej, 5 m. where the Muscat Levies are quartered. There are in addition seven telephone lines between Muscat and Matrah privately owned by merchants. There are at present no T/T sets in the country. The R.A.F. intend to erect a small W/T set at Muscat witn a ^ sending range of miles and a receiving range of 1 miles. It is not certain when this will be in operation. Gables Muscat is connected by the Indo European Telegraph Department’s cable system to the following places MUSCAT to .TASK 131 miles ^ JA3K to CHARBAR 159 miles. ^ 'JASK to KARACHI 500 miles. JA3K via HENJAM to BUSHIRE 481 miles JASK via HENJAM,BUSHIRE to FAO 623 miles. There is also another cable from Jask via BUSITIRE to FAO, 608 miles.HENJAM is connected by short cable to KISHIM island; across the island by land line and then by cable to BUIITfbR ABBAS. From JASK there is a land telegraph system through CHARBAR GNADUR ORMARA to KARACHI. This system connects up with the Baluchistan system through TURBAT and PANJUR.Authority R.L.0 f CONNOR. January 1930. General Report. The route is in general, unsuitable for wheeled traffic. There is a good motor road, lately complet- ^ ed from MUSCAT to RTJV/I miles, passing through the town of MATRAH 1£- miles, and skirting tne barracks of Muscat Levies at BSIT-BL-PELKK miles. BEIT-EL- FSLEK is the camping ground for a force landing at MUS CAT. Prom RUNI to KnRYAT (16i miles)the route lies along wide valleys or follows wide wadis where going offers.no difficulties. The country to DHIBAB (23J miles ), is mountainous and cut by steer wadis where where goingis difficult. Prom DHIBAB to SUB the coastal plain is traversed and is, in general, level but intersected by many wadis with steep and rough approaches. In places, unshod donkeys have to be assisted, animalsif shod, would have great difficulty, Goodwater is available all along the route. In places sufficient for a Battalion, in places sufficient for a Company only. Supplies are negligable; when obtain able, lucerne is the only animal food to be had. There is no grain or grazing for horses and mules. Donkeys and cattle are largely fed on dates. Camel grazing is fairly plentiful everywhere. So is fuel. Note Garrisions of Sultans Askers referred to are all of BENI AMR tribe from the HAND- IRAH. Miles. Inter mediate . 5ir Total % HAJAR Detailed Report. General direction South, going easy all the way ,-2 hour RUNI, village of about 50 stone aouses and huts. Rater good and plentiful from 5 wells, date palms and ex tensive market cultivation supplying MUSCAT and MATRAH. Of military importance as all routes to interior diverge here. Leaving RUNI track leads off from motor road and one J T . JB, ■ - , 18ft deep, height of water 2i ft. i mile to .test of KHJDR hamlet of MUTAHADAMAT, once prosperous, village of many palms now dying from shortage of water (from PELEK ). There are about 15 houses and huts. Prom IQIIDR track turns S.E.then East along wadi UATAT to HAJAR. Scattered villages of about 20 houses and huts, and extensive date gard ens. Fart is named MEZRA where the Sheikh Salim bin HAMUD lives. The people are Beni iiiahaib.Miles Inter- Total mediate * CAUING GROUND South of gardens, level and extensive. WATiilH Good and very plentiful from large felek. TRANSPORT AND SUPPLIES , Nil. FUEL AND OAMUL GRAZING . Plentiful and near. 2 11 HAIDAH AND Sir hours. General direction East along FAIYADH. NADI HATAT. Easy going. At 3f hours well 4i ft diameter, 6 ft deep height of water 4 ft. HAIDAH a few huts and date gardens. i mile South of HAIDAH is the date garden called FAIYADH. GAMPING GROUND S Level and extensive. NATER. -Good, from felek. There are also 6 wells, 16 ft. deep, height of water 2 ft. Sufficient for Battalion! 3 PD. THAN3ICRT &amp; SUIT LIES Nil. FUEL &amp; CAMEL GRAZING . Scattered. 16i KURYAT. Hours. General direction East. Track On Sea Goast)continues along wadi HATAT and going is easy. At 1£ hours hamlet of NAHAIBUBIA (BENI WAHAlB) is passed, lying i mile to R of track. It has some palms and prominent tov/er on small hill. A track to HAIL GAP branches off here; distance to HAIL GAF said to be 7 hours. At li hours hamlet of SHAKE' is reached. It has 4 stone built houses and about 15 huts and 1 lar^e, prominent double-storyed house on edge ol palm gardens. From SUAKIM track turns N.E. down A AD I LIIJLAS by easy downward grade though surface is pebbly. At 3 hours well, 4 ft diameter, 20 ft deep height of wat er 3 ft : NADI MIJLAS varies from 50 to 300 yards wide with walls rising sheer up to 600 f’ ft. KURYAT is the seat of a Nali. There are ex tensive date gardens and some mangoe trees. Town consists of about 120 stone houses and 400 huts: 2 forts 'Europe’’ built on a rock in the sea and 'Asia' at landward limit of town. Forts have garrisions of a fev/ Sultans Askers. Principal occupation of people is fishing. There are 5 large bedans,Ismail bedans and about 60 small craft. There is a track to JiAIL GAF (2 Hours) and on to MEZ- ARA (1 day) the Headquarters of BgNI BATA3H - the only considerable tribe in this area, Sultan bin Muhammed (Shaikh). KURYAT has an open Suk and some shops. There are 3 Indian Banyan merchants m KURYAT. GAiVu ING GROUND Near sweet wells to West of town and about li mile away from it. AnTER Good and plentiful from 30-40 shallow wells in bed of AnDI MIJLAS. *&lt;ells nearer th. s.a are brackish ahd ased for cul UlatiMmediate. 3 , I6h KUIiYAT. TRANSPOiyP . About 30 donkeys could be hired, SUFILLig. Pish, lucerne in limited quantities. PUIilL &amp; QA'„lEh GHAZING . Plentiful and near, fuel can also be bought in tTie to : .”n. 4 19^ KARAIYAT-SS-SAGHIIiA (On sea coast. Group of 2 villages DAGMAH or HAJAR &amp; QABIB ) 3 Hours. General direction Hast. Going easy but a short belt of low sand hills is crossed in 3rd hour. .i Villages of KUHYAT-HS-SAGHIRA lie on either side of .7 AD I DHAIKA, a large wadi which is impassable for 2 or 3 days after heavy rain (winter). DAOKAR, on east side of wadi has 50 huts. Inhabitants all fishermen. There are a few palms. A fort (JINAH) on Jest side Wadi built on prominent hill has a garrision of 7 Sultans Askers. CAHTING GROUND West of DAGMAR. WATER Good from 1 well 10 ft diameter 18 ft deep, height of water 3 ft. TRANSPORT &amp; 5UPILIES. Mil. FUEL &amp; GAI.1EL GRAZING . Ample. 5 6 23i DHIBAB. 3£ Hours. General direction S.S. On le ving DAGMAR track rises steeply over hills and descends on'far side, along rocky watercourse. For first £ hour going is rough. Thereafter going is easy over tops of hills until DHIBAB is reached by long gradual descent; highest height record ed by barometer 800 ft. At l-fc hours from DAGMAR track bends L (Eastwards) to DHIBAB. At this point one track continues South to MBZARA while another branches off R (Westwards) to HAIL GAF(li hours) on WADI DHAIKA. LHIBAB on east side of wadi, 5 j houses, large date groves. The people are GrADANA. CAHPING GROUND Bast of village, hilly and stony. WA m PR Good from 5 wells in Wadi basin. TRANS! ORT &amp; SIR PUBS . Nil. FUEL &amp; CAilKL GRAZING . Scattered. 26 BILMA. PD 2# hours. General direction S.E. Track traverses coast al plain wher* scoing is easy. Plain is here where going is easy. Plain is here, on average li miles wide. ' This part of costal mountain range is called JEBEL pATAR. BIMMA about 60 houses. The people are GADANA. 0AM1ING GROUND . Bast of village. Extensive. WATER . Good from 4 wells, 12 ft deep height of water 2£ ft. TRANSPORT &amp; SU1ILIES . Nil. FUEL &amp; CAMEL GRAZING - Scattered.Inter- Total, mediate. 7 3Qf TUI vTHours. General direction Sast. Track follows coast- * al plain here about 3 miles wide. At 1 hour lar^e prorain ent ’ t Sumr ff tree on small headland. Going excellent. At 2 hours fishing village of FINS is reached, 60 houses; no palms, water from spring in mountains S.F.ls- hours av/ay. After rain water is obtained in ample quantities from shallow holes in wadi bed near village. Sheikh of coast al GADANA Said bin Aleh lives here. After leaving FINS ^ several wadis with very difficult approaches are crossed. At 4 hours track passes along beach. At 4i hours 3HABB, a small village of 15-20 houses built on edge of very pre- cipilous wadi, is passed. TUI, large village of many palm trees on Ifadi KEKHA -150 houses. OAiArING GRCUND . S.E. of village. Level and extensive. tLiTIfd . From 20 wells, 10 ft deep, height of v/ater 3^ ft water plentiful. TRANS10RT &amp; 3UULILS . Nil. FUEL &amp; GAilSL GIUZING Scattered. 6 34i KALHAT 3^ hours. General direction Sast, along coastal plain. Going easy between wadis but many of these are crossed and all are difficult. At 2f hours the small village of HAIDHA is passed. It lies i mile to H of track at foot of mountains (Spelt HALVA on Admiralty Chart.) KAIfiAT, 115 houses one large prominent tower has garrison of 2 Sultans Askers. Two smaller towers unoccupied. There is a ruined building S.E. of and close to village said to be a relic of Persian occupatior. Kalhat is in wadi of same name also called Uadi Beni Jabir from which tribe the coastal mountain range is here also named. CAMPING GROUND East of village. Uneven and stony. UATSR From 4 wells 12 ft deep, height of water 3 ft. The water is very slightly brackish. TRANSPORT &amp; SUPPLIES. Nil. FUEL &amp; QAI.IEL GRAZING. Plentiful but scattered. 9 34i B3LAD-ES-SUR 3*- hours. General direction S.E. Going is easy. At 2i wadi HAFAR, a few poor huts are reached. There is here a well 6 ft deep 1 ft of water. 2-£ hours, RUHIA is reached. Two wells 6ft deep, 1£ ft of water. A fort (JINAH) containing 35 Sultans Askers is passed before reaching BSLAD-ES-SUR. BELAD-ES-SUR, large village, ex tensive date gardens. Over 80 wells. CAMPING GROUND On ridge S.E. of village. Level and ex- tensive.’ TRAN SIORT . About 30-40 donkeys could be hired. FUEL Plentiful GRAZING. Plentiful Lucerne is available. PD.fV”; Miles. • r j '■ ■ later-,'■'Total mediate '! 9 34 ? BELAD-BS -SUB *' I * GRAZING (Oontd.) * Lucerne is available in fairly large quantities. * ^ATEH From village. Over BO good v/ells. » i‘ '</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000079_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/346</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000079</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/346</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 11/3 Diaries and reports: Capt O'Connor's report on Oman'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-20T22:37:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (53 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 55; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a Military Report on Oman by Captain R L O'Connor, and a letter from the Deputy Director, Military intelligence in New Delhi to the Political Agent at Muscat, enclosing copies of O'Connor's reports on the routes from Muscat to Sohar and Muscat to Sur.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Sur</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sohar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000079#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>