<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ca_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T15:44:50.302Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Previous POLITICAL (EXTERNAL) DE COLLECTION General Heading &lt; Sub-head This File contains the following papers Papers may be removed from or placed within this File only by the Political Registry Wt.21o70/P251 1,000 7/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 (11192)Notes for Registry Under Secretary... Secretary of State Committee y*-- 'wyy - Department. Ext.6870/47 Supply of arras and amniunit ion to the Tibetan Government. ^t will be recalled (vide the minute at Ext. 238/46) that H.M.G, i^e^agree'd in principle to the supply/or arms on a limited scale to the Tibetan G-overnment, ' ^ provided that the initiative came from the Tibetan side. The Government of India have now been asked by the Tibetan Government to supply Rs.13,19,406 worth of arms and ammunition, apparently in order to lay up a sufficient stock to cover the next few years when the supply from India may be doubtful. The Government of india, howevej have agreed to supply only Rs.3,26,000 worthy C CrC f&gt;o^&amp; tZ-SfeX*****?* The arms to be supplied include Bren LMGs, Stens, Rifles, Verey Pistols and ammunition for these arms. \N r- ; (26620) Wt.38611/P.141 6,000 10/48 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Op.685SECRET BY FAST AIR MAIL D.O. N0.F.7(2)-NEF/46. External Affairs Department, New Delhi, — the June • &gt; / [ ^ 1947 Subjects- Supply of arms and ammunition to Tibetan Government. fo. D.H ^ 19 JUN. 1947 iwf I am desired to refer to the correspondence resting with India Office telegram No.1181 of the 16th January 1946, 1. Express Letter No.6(2)-L/47, dated the 27th March f 47, from Mission,Lhasa,to Political Sikkim, repeated Foreign, } New Delhi. { 5 2. Telegram No.43/17,dated the { 17th May*47,from Foreign, J New Delhi, to Political, Sikkim, repeated Mission, jj Lhasa. I 5 3. Express Letter No.F.7(2)-NEF/46, j dated the 20th May*47,from Foreign, New Delhi, to Political,5 Sikkim. 3 3 4. Telegram from the British Mission, Lhasa,No.Nil,dated 3 the 30th May 1947. I and to enclose for your informa tion copies of the communications noted in the margin. To E.P.Donaldson,Esquire ,C.M.G., External Department, India Office, London . PCB/31-5- (N VE-X-P-R-E-S-S L-E-T-T-E-R. r~\ From - Mission, Lhasa, P.0. Gyantse, Tibet To - Political Sikkim, Gangtok. (Repeated - Foreign, New Delhi). No.6(2)-L/47. Dated Lhasa, Tibet, the 27th March 1947. i &amp; • o Subject ARMS &amp; AMMUNITION FOR TIBETAN GOVT . Reference Foreign Express Letter No.F.7(2)-NEF/46, dated the 2nd January 1947. 2. The Tibetan Government have made definite request for following arms and ammunition. WEAPON. NUMBER. AMMUNITION 2 ,, Mortars. 42 63,000 LGMS Bren with tripods. 144 - 5,000,000 Carbines Machine Sten. 168 _ 3,000,000 Rifles No.1MK III. 1260 _ 2,000,000 Verey Pistols. 42 - 8,400 3. They, have not asked for 3' mortars. 4. In addition to above named weapons which were mentioned in Foreign Express Letter under reference the Tibetan Government have asked for 12 Anti Aircraft Guns of a light type, with 100 rounds for each see my telegram No.20, dated the 3rd February 1947. 5. The cost of the above items required by the Tibetan Government would be Ks. 1,319,406/- and they have asked for permission to pay by instalments. Presenting the request the Foreign Bureau diffidently suggested in yearly instalments of ks.40,000/-which I said at once was quite inadeouate. 6. The demand for ammunition for all types of weapon (except Anti Aircraft Guns) appears most excessive. Tibetan Government probably want to lay in large stock so that they will not require to ask future Government of India for more until the latter have settled down. 7. Perhaps the Government of India would consider supplying double the Quantity of ammunition recommended by them in their Express Letter under reference which would mean a cost of approximately Ps.4,30,000/-; and that 4-£ years should be allowed for payment by 5 instalments 4 of 1 lakh and one for the balance. If, however, the Government of India are in a position, and are willing, to supply the total requirements of ammunition I consider supply should be made conditional on Tibetan willingness to pay off the total cost in annual instalments of 2 lakhs, or possibly l£ lakhs. I think that if put to it, they could manage payments of 2 lakhs a year; but that this would be a strain on their resources. Their willingness to make this effort would therefore be test of importance they attach to their request. Sd/-illegible, British Trade Agent, Gyantse, &amp; Officer in Charge, British Mission, Lhasa. PCB/2-6 -Telegram O.^'.P. No.43/17 dated 17th May 1947. From - Foreign, New Delhi. To - Political Sikkim, Gangtok, No.43. (Repeated - British Mission, Lhasa). No.17. Reference Lhasa Express Letter No.6(2)-L/47 28th April. Arms for Tibet. 2. Government of India agree to supply the arms and double the quantity of ammunition listed in Foreign express letter No.F.7(2)-NEF/46 dated 2 January 1947, with exception of motars. Mottars and anti-aircraft guns (see para 2 Lhasa telegram No.3 dated 4th February 1947) are not readily available and cannot, it is regretted, be supplied. 3. Approximate total cost will be Ks.3,26,000/- which may be repaid in annual instalments of one lakh (first instalment to be paid on receipt of weapons) free of interest. 4. Grateful for consignment instructions. PCB/31-5- ft/GOVERNMENT OF INDIA External Affairs Department, EXPRESS LETTER. From - Foreign, New Delhi 3. To - Political Sikkim, Gangtok. (via Calcutta, Siliguri, Bengal). No.F.7(2)-NEF/46. Dated the 20th May 1947. Reference Foreign telegram No.43/17, May 17th. Arms for Tibet. 2. Tibetan Government may kindly be requested to repeat assurance given in 1922 (see para.6 Gould's tele gram No.308, 26th June 1943) that arms and ammunition supplied from India will be used only for self-defence n nd internal security. Issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/-V.M.M. Nair, Under Secretary to the Government of India.■■n if PJN 30/5/47 TELEGRAM 0„T o P SECRET 6592 From, To.. ..Mission, Lhasa. ..Foreign, New Delhi. Repeated Political Officer Sikkim, Ga No. Nil Dated (&amp; reed. 30th) May 1947 T.0.0. 0900 T.O.R. 1010 Your telegram No. 17 May 19th. Arms for Tibet. 2. Regent has directed Tibetan Foreign Bureau to send a message to Pandit Ne.iru through Mission expressing Tibetan Government’s pleasure and gratitude for suoply of arms and their hopes for continuance of Pandit Nehru ! -s help in strength ening existing friendly relations between Government of India and Tibetan Government. 3. I was particularly asked, to telegraph gist of message translation of which follows by mail. o o o • o PS to HMs NEF Branch:(ad FSs OSD s JS(X): JS(F)b JS(C)s DS(X)s US(CA)s Commonwealth R£laJ;ions Department - Secretary: and Joint Secretary: P§V:(2)^Cabinet Secretary: copies to Defence Department: Finance Department: and Sikkim:EXTERNALLX =—^' -f Please refer to previous minutes on Sxt. 238 / 46 * ^ accordance with the Secretary of State *s telegram the Government of India have consulted the General Staff (India) on the subject of military aid to Tibet. . The conclusions reached are that from a short term point of view there, is no practical means of aiding Tibet against a major eneny, either Russia or China. They point in particular to the poverty of communications in Tibet, the lack of supplies and the non-military nature of the people. Tte Government of India were authorised in the Secretary of Stated telegramrto give a reasonably encouraging reply to a spontaneous Tibetan approach (or even to manoeuvre them into such an approach). If this eventuality should arise, the matter will have to be considered again, in the light of the political factors which would then apply. A draft demi-official letter to the Foreign Office is submitted. &gt; n$i S)FAitf Copy. InlXA t»PICE, Ert, 521346* TOP aSCRST /lilTiilALL, U .1 August, 1%£&gt;, f 1 WG B 46 Please refer to G-ovennuent of India telegram No* 227 of 8th January about military assistance to Tibet, and our telegram No. 1181 of 16th February. We have now received the enclosed reply. Ihe Govemiuent No. I&gt;93^EP/46 of') of India indicate that, in view of the 19th i unfavourable qpinicxi of the General Staff on the practicability of (hiding Tibet from a short-term point of view against a major enaiy and their conclusion that there is no real threat to India from that direction, it is not proposed to pursue the Hotter at present. It will of course have to be considered from a rather different angle if the Tibetans should raise the matter spontaneously, but we can assume that there is now no question of manoeuvring the Tibetan Govemnent into making a request as suggested in paragraph 5 of our telegram under reference. fi&amp;tt alnooitlfe £. D0NA1C-®® G.V. Kitson, Esq. , C.B.E., Forei^i Office, S..1.Ext, 5213 A 6 DRAFT LETTER G.V.Kitson, Esq., , Foreign Office, S.W.l. 1 You will recall our oral conversation regarding Government of India telegram No.227 of 8 th January about military assistance to Tibet, in accordance with which we sent our telegram No. 1181 of l 6 th February. We have now received the enclosed reply, D.D 93 -NEF/I 4.6 of 19 th Ju 3 y^ / The Government of India indicate that^ in view of the unfavourable opinion of the General Staff on the practicability of aiding Tibet from a short term point of view against a major enemy and their conclusion that there is no real threat to India from that direction, the- Govornmont -of- present. It will of course have to be considered from a rather different angle if the Tibetans /shouldv : r should raise the matter spontaneously, but we can assume that there is now no question of manoeuvring the Tibetan Government into making a request as suggested in paragraph 5 of our telegram under reference.PJLE-CQEX EXT Fr in: 4B To f L* 0,93-^/460 THe’aecrotary to the Govemnent of India in the internal Affairs Department, The Under Secretary of State for India, Uxternal Depar cment, India Office, Ldni&amp;IU. It' Dated New Deltii the n~, July 1946* Subject:- Military aid to Tibet. Sir, I am directed to refer to paragraph 5 of S'/f/ V this Depark.ent T s letter No . M. 183-(0/45 . dated the 1 19th September IM S and paragraph 5 of your telegraDi No. i'IBi, aai-od the 16th January 1946 and to forward herewith papers prepared in the Secretariat of iks ^ Excellency the Commander-in-Chief and Air Headquarters / (India) on the subject of military aid to Tibet. It is understood that these have already been forwarded demi-officially by the General Staff (India) to the Car Staff at the India Office. 2. In view of the opinion now expressed by the General Staff, that from a short term point of view there is no practicable means of aiding Tibet against a major enemy and that there is no real threat to* India from that direction, the Goverment of India do not propose further to consider at present the possibility of..offering military assistance to Tibet. They will, however, continue to meet as far as possible reasonable Tibetan requests for the supply of arms • and ammunition. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, &lt;J ( ' 1 { ' Ju, ”‘ y for Secretary to the Government of India. Ravi. ^ u, • *3 2^.)/Tv^ 5 ~ 2 / 3 / 4 6 Ko C in C i9ctt/37/3fi .C_ln c*» secretariat i2Ll8f3 of Jtaff Comm 1 feta Copy Wo has been re-examined by the JpC at their meeting on Thu 23 May 46. ** *.u . ?h0 ^commendations of the JPC are forwarded herewith in the form of an explanatory note. This note should now be attached „o the cover of the copy of 003 (46) 736 in your possession, *n order to ensure that the note is read as a preliminary to any study of the paper itself being made. 3d A Macdonal d Col Secretary 24 May 46 phone 3519 CGS (Chairman CO3 Cta) Copy ?To 1-3 ( Chairman JPC) Copy No 10-11 ' rt 12-13 “ H 14-15 CMC SA30g m c 9 MCKAt™ 1 T ifaiS (.46) 736 - ao TO Tf -Kr - p aP i,n- i-ttoux. cr:K ir/ th.a oot'inatior of TIBET iy a pc ten tj ally hcstl3o *’^?F4 f » wr SL 1 ' 1 ^ ccrsttti-te B fiirect threat to the security cf I; OTA. The Government of IfOT a are, therefore, vitally IntoreswfKl ir, Ralnt«jning frier.cily relations r&gt;3 th TXBLi? «ind in presonln r for TIBET at least that manure cf a toronv wm rsn s&gt; e row or Joys. ?• _ T?1 ° a cf Ti he tar' antoncny rs’st rest in strong (Uplonat^c si y port by irt'G and by IfTOA so that ti.a Tibatuna will not to r? tjoo tod to pressure by any potential hostile power• n v /&gt; V^rtievlsir Tl HliT wist V&gt;e supported a^ainat zne n=e.iods of peaceful psoetratJcn' ard subUrsion #3ch have sccceaa ^f 1 / b y H 8&amp;A in l ortlierr, PKRSIA. and w* . on CFfT. A Is very UVely to employ against her* L*. . neither H ;?;3A nor ant’U rauat be allowod to -/lolate Tibota-: autonomy by si ch methods, since it would tier V possible for them to t»-’ild roads and airfields to their o«! advantage, wiich would vitally affect I: DlA's strateirfc j' o sx oS.on • / * Should it prove impossible to preserve Tibetan ai, torony by diplomatic metlicds alone or should H. SOT A or attack nBBT, it right necessary for the Gr4. cf *v nr * to provide direct mifltary SJT to TIBET which would involve »nar. Tiie purpose of this paper i s to study tlie t Xt vrF?. r ? r,arr(!r c,r direct military aid that could be giver, to HULa In pursuance of the political object. UMil military aid is to prevent a hostile power establishing 3 tself in areas fren which it can threaten J In rractice this means y re venting the enemy from occupyir g those parts of TI HET from which air attack or rccl:e. rdasiles can be launched cn in&gt;3 A. Uilltary aid must depend upon the goo 1 Till o tlie MijLi oary ana must dep Tijwtans, and confidence in us both row and when direct military assistance is sent tc thon. It will therefore ofTtf ^m^ryl 0 ^ C * rlttl ard the prcvinces niLgii ■ v mvx 1* n ,, T a „ D »ilit a ry aid is nost likely to be re wired by TTBaT &amp;„ a ttne when a major war is imminent or in progress. SIna H E? rt ^ f J 31 ® re *hrces of 1*TM A aid tie iji woi^ld lie available to give aid to TIBET. 1. U) M?.,anAHnc a p ■:T'.0L0 iY cf nrmT The main geographical factors affecting th&gt; problem aret- Tie ovorall sparsity of population, crops and animals, and the comparative wealth of 3B HUr, and the tmlaus historical and religious importance of LrhUAi an ln\ T a(11ng army of any size can not therefor® live off the country, except in SB TIBET where each house has ample reserves of grain, and even a small force can do .so only by oppression and by constantly moving about in the more populous areas. LHlJA and 33 TI3BT are lively to be tb® ©objectives of any invasione2 (b) The corraratlve proxinity cf 3£i T3 BKT tc Ic^rr^ant targets 5.n I' D3 a* It will, therefore, be the most Ijkely strategic object of a Rl SSlAr T attack. (c) The ron-exj sterce of any re ads fer wheeled traffic, and the /— renoteres* of the ccurtry from ail possible oreny basest any 3 and approach from T* SfSlA or CHIT A nr at be made over an average of 100 miles of pack track at high altitudes, over bad going and occasional very high passes, though once into the country wheeled traffic can move freexy over the plains. ■Ml snch yet!tea converge at FAOCHl 1 A or Cl i'IX), Tlie main tenance over these rortes of hostile forces in TIBET will present grave difficulties ar&gt;d will lini.t tho size of the forces that can be deployed. FaQC! tKA and C U DO are tijlitarily imjortant. (d) Tho height and breadth of the mountains surrounding TIBET, and the height and character of the country* alrlxme operations will be hazardous and comyiarwtively difficult; the present types of aircraft could only be operated from TlBETAT airfields by the most experi enced pilots, and even then the risks involved would bo extremely highj glider* can not be used, vtfith present equipment it is net possible to use para troops at heights. It is however considered that there is a possibility that the technical difficulties could be overcome If it is decided that preparation must be made to drop paratroops in UBET. The beds of old lakes frequently offer good sites for airfields. (e) The people of ‘H 3ET are naturally brave and tough, though by religion pacifist and unmilitary. They are wbcllv untrained and unequipped to opose even the smallest of modem forces and have never seen modem weapons and e'p^ipmentj though this could be overcome by training and arousing interest injmilitary matters. The country has no manufacturing resources to enable it to e^lp its own forces. In view of the smallness of the forces that can be put into TIBET by possible enemies, and the inefficiency of the CH r E3E, the training and equipping o* a srail Tibetan force on modem lines would have an effect on any campaign out of all proportion to the size of the force. In addition there is considerable scope for the activities of .guerilla bands, preferably led by trained British or Indian officers, in some parts of the country eg the sparsely populated NORTH and WEST. 9. Uqo-biO 111 Consideration of the geographical factors leads to the conclusion that the military object referred to in ganerjl terms in para S above should bes- 'To prevent the enemy establlshiag himself SOUTH of a general line cn 7 X- T T AQC'!UK A-G ARYdRSA-LSd 11 , NOTBl- There are two OABTOKS in TldET. The GARTOK in lestem TIBET is also known as 0ARY\RSA, by which name it will be called in this paper) 10, ^.aasiblc enemies- H 33IA (a) RUSrllA cannot attack TIBET without first entering CHINK S3 territory, and this is likely to be done only iiamediately before, or during, a major war when the b»?lk of K oi&gt;l A 1 s armed forces would be deployed elsewhere. It is not known what forces RUSSIA couldTOP SECRET TOP SECRET 3. make avcliable in TIBET, but It *111 be aacumed that she v.ould employ the maximum force? that could be maintained by land route; mci by air. E TIBET would be the main objective of a MJ Jl N attack. (b) To reach TIBET, HUESOtA must Hr; t build forward bases in the cmHT E provinces of KANSU and CHINCH/1, 1000 miles forward from her ix. iliicad s at 8IMIPA1./TIN &amp;, SPKIGIOPOL, / LMA. j Ti , FRUNZE, ANDIJAN and C&amp;H, over reasonable existing roads. Thence the routes to LHA.sA average 1100 miles of pack track. All practic able routes again converge at N/GQIUKA. (c) orking on British standards the force the RUSSIANS could maintain In the LHASA area would be on© brigade group; even this would require over 50,000 pack animals. Since the RUSSIANS will probably use Mongol ian troops, and rely to a greater extent than the British on local supplies, the maintenance of one brigade group might however, be carried out with many fewer pack animals. (d) After building rear maintenance airfields the RUSSIAN; could maintain one dlv by air in the LHASA are« , in addition to the necessary fighters and some bombers for offensive operations. It is estimated that this would entail the use of ^53 tpt sqns of aircraft and the building of about IS airfields in TIBET, 11 In CKINGHAI and 3 in K/NSU, 26 in all. (e) The likely course of RUSSIAN operations would there fore bes first attack or infiltration into the parts of SINKJANG, CHINCH/I and K/NSU they require; then a build up of bases, airfields and communications in these areas. Simultaneously one brigade group might advance by land towards LHASA and construct airfields there; lastly the air transportation of one div into the LH/SA and 3E TIBET areas. The whole force would be adequately provided with offensive air support. A small force which might consist of mounted infantry might move direct from AEeT SINKIZNG to GAHTARSAt this operation if attempted would probably be In the nature of a diversion. 11 # Possible enemies - CHINA (a) The Chinese can attack TIBisT from SINJKlANG, CH1NGHAI and SIRING provinces. A large number of divisions, with no AFVs and little or no air support, could be made available, but internal political factors would certainly greatly reduce the number. It will be assumed that CHINA would be in a position to employ the maximum forces that could be maintained in TTEjsT # (b) Routes from Chinese railheads in SZECHW/K end TUNKAN to LHASA vary froi 1000 - 1860 miles in length: the smallest distance to be covered by pack track is 850 miles. All routes converge at NAGCHUK/ or CHAMD0, respectively 130, and 450, mile* by peck track from LHASA . (c) working by British maintenance standarde the force which the Chinese could maintain by each of the roads NAGCHUKA LHASA and CHAMDO - LHASA is one bde gp. Owing to their more modest requirements and by making full use of impressed transport and pillaging, there is no doubt that/Tx&lt; S'? /3/u.(«&lt;S TOP SECRET tJhe Chinese coulu in fact mainttiin in the LHASA trca a lar, er total force than two bhe It is unlixely, however, that it could exceed a total of three bde gps. (d) CHINA will already have suitable ready-xuade rear maintenance airfields in the KUNMING and 0HB1KJTU areas developed by United States Air forces in tfc last war Suitable sites ior forward maintenance airiields on trie routes to LHASA probably exist. It is unlikely however that CHINA will either make or receive sufficient transport aircraft from AMkBICA or BkITAIN within the next 15 years to enable her to maintain a large force by air in TltfET. It is possible that she could mount a small airborne operation of a maximum of one brigade group Airborne operations and air maintenance require considerable skill and experience, and it is not considered that such an operation could be so efficiently organised by the Chinese ©s to constitute a serious threat. « (e) The CHUfbUE Air Force could assist their land forces by some offensive action, which might have a serious effect upon the morale of the simple Tibetans. (f) The CHINESE effort therefore is likely to be not more tnan three brigade groups, without AFVs but with slight ail support. It wSuldbi directed at LHASA, end would use the routes converging on LHACA from NAGCtfUKA and .A* small force which might consist of mounted infantry from oINKIANG might seize GAETAHSAj this operation, if attempted, would be in the nature- of a diversion. L£. Joint action by RUSbIA and CHINA Since all the routes that can be used by either t^e HUSSIES or the CHINESE converge et NAGCillXA end CKAMDO, «o® bln ® effort would not to much lerger then thet of Rlh.IA alone T “ e RCEhlANS would probably NOT send en infantry force to LIU.A at all, tut would esfclst the CHINE® Innd force with air action, military edvice, mllitery equipment, and anglneers to contxruct the air fields required by HD:*®A in ® TIBET for the reception of tne KUSSIAN division and the operation of RDaSIAN air loicee It^.s not considered thet Joint action by RUSSIA and CHINA would materi ally Inox-ease the speed of their operations ae sirce RUSSIA must still build forward bases at KAltfU ana C ILGHAI. 13. British Mlltery position BRITISH ability to give direct military aid to TIBjsT depends on the following factors:- (©) Maintenance capacity by air. (b) Maintenance capacity by road. (c) Availability of troops, aircraft and TIBETAN airfields. (d) Time factor. (e) Ability of the TIBETANS to help themselves. These factors will now be studied in turn. 14. Maintenance capacity by air (a) working from airfields in the TEZFUR and DIN JAN area, DAKOTA type aircraft could take a 3000 lb pay load to LRAo .TOP SECRET TOP SECRET The tiistenee la 300 miles. Assuming that the minimum number of transport squadrons demanded by the Army ie 7 # will be arailable, it can be calculated that with squadrons maintaining an average serviceability of 70^, ie 14 aircraft from a U*; of 20, the lift per squadron would be about 20 tons The gross lift is 140 tons per sortie. Two sorties might be flown per flying day giving a total daily lift of 280 tons. (b) It is proposed to retain at-least 5 airfields in NE AS;AM This number is sufficient to provide bases for all the aircraft that would be required. Administrative base facilities either exist or could be rapidly improvised . hail facilities for bases end airfields are sufficient'’ (c) One Infantry Division normally requires 150 tons maintenance per day. In TIBET however, few vehicles would be required and fighting would not be on a heavy scale. Maintenance requirements may be calculated at 125 tons per day for one division Approx 155 tons per day is therefore available for special engineer stores and air force requirements during tti© initial build up. (d) The meteorological conditions in NE ASSAM will probably allow the following percentages of maximum air effort to be achieved in each month. Ian 95 lul 50 Feb 85 Aug 50 Mar 85 Sep 60 Apr 85 Oct 80 May 70 Nov 95 Jun 50 Dec 95 It should be noted therefore that the speed of the build up and degree of safety margin Will vary with the season in which operations have to be carried out. The figures given in para 17(c) below should therefore be reed with caution, though in fact they are unlikely to be greatly exceeded. (e) Vile have not sufficient information on flying conditions in' HE TIBET to say whether they vary greatly from those in NE ASSAM. More meteorological information of SE TIBET must be obtained. A full meteorological appreciation of the whole area Is the first essential if detailed plans ere to be prepared. 15. Maintenance capacity by road (a) Although there are several possible tracks leading into SE TIBET from BHITIfH IKulA, the only one feasible for use by a force larger than a company is the KALIMPONG-GYANTSE-LHASA trade route. This is only a pack track but could possibly be made suitable for jeeps by (i) extensive rebuilding in the sector where it crosses the HIMALAYAS; (ii) provision of lerry facilities over tne TSANG PC (BRAHMAKJTKA), South of LHASA; (ill) minor improvements and grading elsewhere. (b) The railhead and base facilities that Could be quickly got ready in the KAI^IMPGNG-SH.IGUKI areas would suffice for a brigade group. (c) The distance from a railhead at KALIMF0NG ROAD to LHASA. TOP SKCRET TOP S&amp;CKIST e. is IS miles by NTT rood followed by approxiirif tely 250 miles of peck track. About 17 f 000 animnls would be needed to maintain a brigade group at III ABA by this route. It is doubtful If these could be provided, even with the fullest cooperation of the Tibetans. (d) It is not therefore worthwhile to send by lend forces other than those which m? y be needed to prepare for the reception of air forces or airborne troops. 16. /vailability of troops, aircraft and TIBKTaN airfields (a) It may be assumed that one div, which is the largest force that can be maintained, ccula be made available. (b) The availability of transport aircraft for this operation has already been ui©cussed in para 14 above. After the iAltial build up the number of squadrons required for maintenance might be reduced to 3 or 4. (c) It is impossible to estimate what offensive aircraft will be available: but the open nature of the country, the sparseness of population, and the fewness of tracks would probably enable one tactical reconnaissance squadron based in TIPI7T to cover the front of the whole of the div. Fighter cover could be provided from AftfAM when required, and preparations should be made to enable fighters to step forward should the enemy start to build up his air resources. light bombers of the Mosquito type could bomb or reconnoitre enemy rear maintenance areas, (d) Sites for airfields exist at TON A, LHASA and HAGCmUKA. It may also be possible to build an airfield at CHAMDC, Reconnaissances should be made now to clarify this point. All the above places are Important, and would be used ip the initial fly in t . To hasten concentration, therefore, end to avoid uneconomical use of para troops, if their use is feasible in the circumstances at the time, arrangements should be made to improve, and keep in reasonable repair, the sites of any possible airfields at the above places. The Time Fact or (a) From the time of their initial entry into SINKIANG, the RUSSIANS could produce forces in the LHAfA area as follows (1) One brigade group maintained by land months OR (li) Alternatively, if it stopped to build maintenance airfields (iii) Cne div air supplied In addition A small force of mounted infantry from S1NKIANG to aARTAKSA (Western TIBET) 12 months 18 months. 2 months. (b) From the time they crossed the TIRKTAH border, the CHINESE could produce forces in the LHAilA area as follows (1) one brigade group via CHAMDO (ii) One brigade group via NAGCHUKA 1 month months.4 T s' 2 / 2 A 6 TOA' SjsCKET In adaltlon A sioall force of loounted Infantry from Bimiim to aARYAKftA 2 non the. (c) Assuming that preparation hed betn au^de in the base areas in IT’IDIA, and that our troops and aircraft had been concentrated there when RUSSIAN or CIIIN.is;SJs intentions against TIBET became obvious, we could cany out the following moves:- (i) Parachute engineers to TBWA, IHAaA, HAGCHXJKA and poealbly CHAMDO 3-7 days. One brigade ( roup to HAGCKOEA 1-8 weeks. OR One bn group to NAGCHUKA 1-lJ weeks One brigade group to CHAMDO * 1-8 weeks OK One bn group to CHAMDO * 1-1&amp; weeks On© additional brigade group to LHASA 2-4 weeks. One small detachment at GAKTARaA 1 month. (except between Cct - April), If paratroops cannot be dropped on the Tibetan plateau owing to the height, the timings will be delayed by the period required to local arrangements to prepare landing strips for transport aircraft. This mif^ht entail a delay of at least a month, (See para 8(d)), (d) Cur forces can probably therefore forestal either the HD 81 AHS or CHIN ASK at the vital points of LHASA and HAGCHUKA, providing parachute ensineeis con prepare the landing strips, but the CHIHitSB would probably reach CHAMDO first, 16 # Ability of the TIB^T/xBS to help themselves (a) The present position has been discussed in para 6(e) above. It must be stressed that the TIBETAH will to help themselves depends on the strength of the Indian Govt, and the diplomatic support it gives to TIBET, (b) If a small TIBETAN force, about one mounted infantry brigade group, were trained and equipped on modern lines, it wsuld be enable TIBET to impose some delay on the RUSSIANS, and possibly to hold up altogether OBZRB&amp;i forces advancing on the routes from CH/MDO end NAOCHDKA, (c) The necessary training could be provided by giving; selected Tibetan officers and HCos free instruction in.IHDIA, \ (d) Equipment and replacements would have to be provided from outside TIBET either free or at a token cost, (e) A small military mission resident in TIBET would also be required. Its tacks would te to help the Tibetans in matters connected with the modernization of a part of their .Armyj and to mtke preparations for the reception of our lorces should they te required. It would also urge on the Tibetans the Importance of organising and arming guerilla bands in tae NOHTh TCP vSECKJ TTOP SECRET —- ■ (Si TOP SKCHKT ,, 3. and WlvTT. In war it would act as the liaison link between the British Coamaixler in the field and the Tibetan Govt. 19 # aifttfliary of KliS^IAH actions (a) They ai»e unlikely to deploy more then one dlv plus one brigade group against TIBfcT. The former would heve to be i air supplied and could not operate vdthln 18 months of a RUSSIAN entry into SUtaXAHt! - the letter could, with great difficulty, be maintained by land and could reach LHASA within 2b months, (b) They may attempt a coup with a small para force against NAGCHUKA, and possibly with a small cavalry force against GAKYAKsA. (c) Their air forces could not build up to opeiate agi inat INDIA from Si*. TIHTvT in e shorter period than 18 months, (d) If the RUSSIANS acted in cooperation with the CHINESE there would be no materiel increase in the size of the iorces they could deploy nor in speed with which they could threated. SE TIBET. 20 , Suffiaary of 0 Ml ness actions They are unlikely to deploy wore than two or possilly three brigade groups against TIB&amp;T, They could reach Lh/sA witnin 6 weeks, but would probably take longer. Air support is likely to be at most token, though its ©fleet on TIBETAN morale might be serious, si, sumyry, of, IP :rT They could not seriously impede © HUfCTAK land advance, and would be helpless in the face ol a RUb’Ul/N air operation. They could however seriously delay a CHINESE advance, end with air support, modern equipinent and training, would probably deieat It, 22, Sunnaary of our capabilities (a) &amp;e can deploy forces in SE TIBET quickly enough to forestal the RUSSIANS, and with bettor and shorter air supply lines, could probably defeat any RUSTIAH attacks by deploying equal or even smaller lorces, (b) fte would probably not be able to forestall the CHINESE at some key points EAST of LHASA if the TIBETANS Imposed no delay, but we would have little difficulty when assisted by the TIBETANS, in destroying any CHINESE invaders, CCNOTUSIONS 23 The TIBETAN Govemment should be approached with a view to arranging the training in INDIA of a nucleus of officers and NCOs tc modernise v. force sufficient to impose considerable delay on an enemy brigade group operating on one of the two main approaches to LHASA, A mounted infantry brigade group or about 3000 men, would be sufficient. Suitable modern equipment for a force of this nature should be provided free of at a nominal cost by the INDIAN Covt, end re x&gt;l a cements for that equipment should be on the same basis. Two or three supervisory officers should reside in TIFET ©so Resident Military Mission, 24 The maximum aid that can be given to TIBFT fs one air supp lied and air transported div with offensive air support. orae long range bombing of a strategical nature could also be done, probablyTOP SECRET TOP SECRET n with slight effect. 25. SUfrigesteci outllno BRJTiai for a i r to TIP&gt;T (a) Airfields at T^JKA., LHASA, CHAMDO and NAGCHUKA should be made, and by arrangement rith tlie Tir^rATi Govt kept in a. reasonably good condition. Cn their actual condition v.lll depend the possibilities for early use of airlanded troops by the BRITISH. (b) When HDS6XAH intentions against SIN/IAEC, CJllfBH/I or KANSU, or CJINk E intentions against TIPUT become obviously hostile, detailed plans for the operations should be drawn up. (c) A thorough and detailed meteorological appreciation of the wholfj area should be put in hand early. (d) Troops likely to be required will be:- (i) In ease of Q lNisSE aggrenaion One brigade group CHAMDO (possibly para) One bn group HAOCHUKA (possibly pare) (ii) In case of RUSSIAN aggression One brigade group NAGCifUKA (possibly para) One bn group CHAMDO (possibly para) (ill) In both cases One div (possibly airborne) LHASA (less one bde &amp;p and one bn gp) A small detachment. GARYAREA (e) Air forces likely to be required will be Seven transport squadrons initially reducing to three or four squadrons after the first two months; One tactical R aqn; Air OP. Air VCP acts; light aircraft for casualty evacuation if they can operate at the heights required; Fighters, fighter-bombers, light bombers, according to scale of enemy air and land operations. 86. The course of operations within the above framework will be on the following linos, all timings being as from the start of tie operation ' (a) Airfield improvements in TUFT (about 1 week). (b) Rapid occupation of CHAflDG and NAGC.UKA (about 8 weeks). Recce and patrolling from these places, J&amp;AlT and NS along likely routes.I (o) Siting of reserves, HQ. md close support air cm ft in LHASA {2-4 week s) # (d) Miaini stretivo build up in LHASA area including ImproYeaent of airfields. (e) Occupation of Q.’TCt/MSA by a small tietashment of officers erul men, with wireless sets, to raise local guerillas and collect inforxaation. A d^taciuiient of the Indian Long Lange Squadron, reaching Its ot.jbctive by parachute or by iatyrehing, would be suitable, (f) Tice tan forces would set as screens well ahead of tie British, and on flanks covering unlikely but possible cppro&amp;caoa.EXTERNAL . (Political Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. rj if. / REGISTER NO. EXT. 238/46 19...M,. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary %■ Supply of arms and ammunition to Tibetans, Secretary of State l t(&lt; Id) c Committee Government of India propose to make the Tibetan Government an offer. Under Secretary Secretary of State ? SU45 C Cct- Fj? C((*J (a (i(u- ^ (v-'f r FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. Draft telegram to the Government of India disagreeing^ a , itj- turffsc** t+u a~ ^ iQjiejm b2U I b • I ■ (-4- 4&gt;As will be seen from the submission at Ext.296/46 (travelling concurrently) Mr. Hopkinson, the Political Officer in Sikkim, is about to deliver to the Tibetan G-overnment a memorandum explaining and maintaining our attitude in regard to the extension of the Government of Indian control in the areas inruediately to the south of the Indo Tibetan Frontier (the McMahon Line). The Government of India now suggest that this memorandum might be made more palatable if Mr.Hopkinson informs the Tibetans - before he leaves Lhasa on the 2?th January - that the Government of India would be prepared to supply them with modern arms and equipment if they require them. The flagged papers on the file below show that there are precedents for the supply of arms and equipment to Tibet and we also know, as is pointed out in the final paragraph of the Government of India* s telegram that Chiang Kai Shek has not only offered the Tibetan Government a supply of weapons but has also made it clear to them that he wishes the Tibetan Government to apply to no country but China for arms in the future. In' 1 he is reported to have threatened the Tibetans that if they d conform with his wishes he would have to take military action against them (the relevant papers are flagged in collections and 36/30 (2) below). Both these factors provide grounds for offering arms to the Tibetans now that the war is over and the Government of India have a considerable surplus on their hands. Such an offer might also - as the Government of India suggest - assist Mr.Hopkinson in conducting his negotiations in Lhasa. On the other hand, when the question was considered on Ext. ''*’ ***' 5925/45 (flagged 'A H on the attached file) of making the Tibetans a token offer of arms in order to boost up their resistance to Chinese pressure, we came to the conclusion that it would be undesirable to put this proposal into effect until H.M.G. had had sin opportunity of considering the review of the whole question of military support to Tibet which the Government of India have promised us: - see para. 5 of the Government of India's letter of EXT. 515V45 WX.b32.5j Kb the 19th September (flagged 'B') and para. 6 of our letter to the Foreign Office of the 8th January (flagged 'X”). In the light of that letter a draft telegram is submitted disagreeing with the Government of India*s suggestion. It will, of course, need Foreign Office concurrence and n ^a mtm Mr.Kitson is x- / - ^ J .. T . tr « i* 4 Xos* u*y\.(b J- G-.V. Kitson,\ Rsq., Foreign Office, S • &gt; &lt; • 1 • Dear ICitson, 1 I In connection with the telegrams we recently sent you about Hopkinson*s negotiations * with the Tibetan Government on the question of the McMahon Line I enclose a copy of a further telegram from the Government of India (No.227 dated 8 th ’January) in which they suggest that it might help’’ to smooth Hopkins on 1 s negotiations if he were to inform the^/that the Government of India would be prepared to supply them with modem arms if they required them. ■ /■. The telegram referred- to in the first paragraph U+* ^ 4 is No. 21302 of 16 th September, 1943, which was ^ -vd t. u copied to G.P. Young oh. the same date under No. diet. 5187/43 (i'.O. Reference i''.4549/40/l0)i and trie papers referred to in the final paragraph V- were forwarded to the Foreign Office on the \ 15tVmam mmmmmmmmmu Iptu '[9hU, under Ko*Ext*34&gt;7V44, und on the 7th July, 1945? under No. Nxt. 5233/45 respectively. The telegram 191 of 6th January referred to in paragraph 3 is of course one of those recently forwarded to you in connection with Hopkinson* s negotiations. This question of the supply of arms to Tibet Cl Tin ~ ■ in paragraph 6 of our official letter to the Foreign Office of 8th January, Ext. 5925/45? on the subject of H.M.G*s policy towards Tibet. let us have the viev/s of the Foreign Office on the U- umJ fa general questions raised in that letter, in order that we may deal with the enclosed telegram + iP..uLrlLi Uiij if you jdoul&lt;yiet us know straight s4ca4. t* 7tAu+ av/ay whether the Foreign Office ~r ' th tiifa 1 i no^ paragraph^we would propose to telegraph to the Government of India as in the enclosed draft^On which I should be glad of your comments. as liopkinson now proposes/proposes to leave Lhasa on 27th January I am afraid that this is a matter of some urgency.FILE COPY INWARD TELEGRAM \ 696 (If in any case the communication oi the contents of this doemnent to any persen outside British or U.B. O-cvernment Service is authorised, it limst-be p£ rephrased) • rafR be p 1 raphra6ed) A llotted to Ititernal^ .'Departi^ent * ^Toples To MilitarF jDepartment a n d War Staff . Copies circulated^ CYPHER yELEQRAM To Government of India, External Affairs Dept Secretary of State for India* Dated New Delhi, 03*55 hours, 8th January 1946 Received 00*35 hours, 8th January 1946, Your telegram 2130 (sic ? 21302) 16th September 1943* 2* Now that war is over we are considering possibility of supplying Tibetan Government at favourable rates with (?simple) modern weapons of type suited to Tibetan conditions and abilities as a means of strengthening their self-confidence. Military authorities recommend 5 inch mortar, 2 inches mortars, Bren guns, Sten guns, rifles and hand grenades, 5, It is possible that if HopKInson can inform the Tibetan Government before he leaves that Government of India are able to supply Tibetans with modern arms if they require them he v/ill be able to create more favourable atmosphere for reception of his communication re McMahon line, see our telegram No* 191 6th January 1946, We should therefore be grateful for early reply whe t herTT m«G, agree that such a statement may be made to Tibetan Government leaving details to be worked out at leisure if Tibetans accept the offer, 4, Further consideration in favour of offering the Tibetan Government supply of weapons now is that Chinese Government have recently made suggestions to Tibetan Government that they should obtain their requirements of arms from China. In this connection please see Lhasa telegram 673 14th July 1944 copied to you with out letter oG AM dated 25th July 194-4 an d para, 3 of Lhasa n emo 5L/45 27th May 1945 sent with our 28 AM dated 3rd July 1946, - JAN194-P INDIA OFFICE;7 1 SECRET EXT. 4111/44 k Extract from memorandun No.3(4)“L/43» dated the 10th August 1944 from the Additional Assistant to the Political Officer in Sikkim, in charge, British Mission, Lhasa to the Political Officer in Sikkim, Gangtok, Subject: NEWS REPORT + + + + + + + + + I have had further confirmation of the very great Importance which the Tibetan Government attached to the recent supply of ammunition by the Government of India, and its effect in restoring Tibetan confidence in British intentions. It appears that this question of ammunition was treated as a ballon d'essai, and that Tibetan confidence had been shaken as much by quite a small detail as by the larger question of Trans Tibet Transport, This detail was the delay in agreeing to transmit by our wireless a telegram from the Tibetan Government to their representative in Chungking, ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY 1 S LETTER NO. DATE RECEIVED 36 5-9 15-9-19W-EXT.U11A4 ti Extract from memorandum No.3(4)-L/2f3&gt; dated the 10th August 1944 from the Additional Assistant to the Political Officer in Sikkim, in charge, British Mission, Lhasa to the Political Officer in Sikkim, Gangtok. Subject:- HEWS REPORT + + + + + + + + 3. I believe that,as reported in para 6 of my memorandum under reference, Tibetan trust in us is now thoroughly restored; and it will be further strengthened when they learn from you of the Government of India's spontaneous readiness to supply them with a new type of gun to replace the 2.75 mountain guns which have now become obsolete in India (See your telegram No.235 of 3rd July 1944). ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETART*S LETTER NO. DATE RECEIVED 36 5-9 15-9-1944EXT 3344/2.4, COI'grCENTIiiL. Extract fl'om Tatung News Report for the period ending the 30 th June, 1944. 1* The Tibetan Trade Agent, Tatung and the wool tax officer at Hiari, have received further orders from the Tibetan Government to expedite despatch of the ammunition cases from Tatung and Hiari to Lhasa. The Chunbi valley and Phari people are busy in transporting the cases within their respective jurisdiction.' ‘ , 3029/44. • ^ Extract rrom ^ Enclosure in India foreign Secretary* s letter No. 25 dated 20th June, received 8th July 1944, / \ 4. Reference para 2 of my report for period ending 15 th April 1944. About 3000 cases of ammunition have reached Yatung and Phari. The Tibetan Trade Agent, Yatung is expected to remove the remaining cases to Tibet from Sikkim by the end of June 1944. The entire Tibetan mules are employed in conveyance of munitions* The Tibetan Government have again telegraphed to the Tibetan Trade Agent, Yatung, to expedite removal of all cases to Tibet without further delay.■ MM'M ^-V EXT&gt; 2221/Vi CCKE'UDENTIAL ttx tract frcm lir^asa Letter for week ending April &lt;Hh t 19M« 7* ••••••• •From the Comiaiider-in-Chief I gathered that the four 2 •75* guns which have been out of store and in use for training for three months after lying in store for six years, will now return to store probably for another six years or until the next serious scare#..MBS EXT.2C71A4 Extract from Yatunr News Report for the Period ending the 51st L&amp;rch « 1. Khenchung Lobzang Keaang (vide revised ’Who's Who page Ibj the wool tax officer at ihari* arrived Yatung from Ihari on the 29th March 1944* He called on me on the 51st inarch... .He said that his visit to Yatung is purely in connection with the transhipment of munitions from Gangtok to Tibet. He had received orders from the Tibetan Government to assist the Tibetan Trade Agent, Yatung, and to expedite despatch of munitions so kindly supplied by the British Government. The entire Chumbi valley mules are now employed in transporting munitions from Gangtok to Ihari. It seems that he and the Tibetan Trade Agent, Yatung, have received strict orde, s from the Tibetan Government to remove the munitions from Sikkim without further delay. _&amp; OOTFIDMTAL. IJ* Ext. 1863/44-. Extract from Lhasa Letter for week ending March 19th 1944 - Memorandun No.3(6)-l/43, dated the 19th March 1944 from the Additional Assistant Political Officer in Sikkim, In Charge British Mission Lhasa to the Political Officer in Sikkim, Gangtok. 3« News of the arrival of ammunition for the Tibetan Government in Sikkim is now pretty general. When the Kashag heard that there was some delay in supplying transport from the Chimbi valley, they realised at once the urgency of inmediate supply, and sent a special despatch rider to Yatung with firm orders. This man, who must ride the whole way himself, has orders to reach his destination in three days. This would seem an almost impossible feat, but I am assured that he will reach Yatung within five days.Ext.5750/43 Extract from Lhasa letter for week ending September 1 2th 1 943&gt; 7# . ^ On September 10th the Foreign Office ca. id on the Mission* They asked whether I could give any reply regarding the supply of anmunition by the Government of India* (My telegram to Gould repeated Foreign No* 850, dated September 10th refers)*±XtmllLll/kk \ Confidential Extract from Lhasa letter for week ending February 13th,1943* On February 'Yth I went to Norbhu Lingka to continue instruction on the guns, as the Commander-in-Chief is anxious that this should be done. The men are very keen on this and learn quickly. Not so the officers one of whom did not turn up: the other turned up over an hour late. I have told the Commander-in-Chief that if this happens again I will not continue instruction.Ext, lV : &gt;2/h}± Gonfidential . Extract from Lhasa Letter for week ending February 6th, 1944* £• On February 1st Mr«Sendall put the finishing touches to the Tibetan 2.?5 n guns, and I shot them in the afternoon. No officers are yet capable, of putting the guns on a target, or of shooting them. The men, on tne other hand, put up a very creditable show, and each of two targets were well hit. A large crowd, as yrell as many monk and lay officials watched the show from the gun position. Among the crowd I noticed a good many of Dr. Kung's staff. The Kashag, who watched from the roof of the Petala seem to have been veiy impressed with the results. I have agreed to do’ some more training once a week, and will endeavour to instil some kind of keenness into the officers. I would not be surprised if the CJornraander-in-Chief decides shortly to shut the guns up in the Armoury until another scare makes him realize that no one is capable of shooting them. Although the men took the shoot seriously and were intensely keen, the Commander-in-Chief's chief anxiety seemed to be to get Hr. Sendall and myself, v/ith the other officers to tea and dinner. When the shooting was over, all officers and men who had been trained/1 ^ t .* 1 J6 2 /kk Conl'idential Bixtract from Lhasa Letter for v/eek ending February 6th, 1944* 10. On February/ 4'th Mr# Sendai left Lhasa. Since his arrival here on January 17th he never spared himself but showed the greatest keenness on getting the guns in perfect order. This, in spite of considerable difficulties, he succeeded in doing.OOHFIEEKTIAL. Ext. 1343/44. Extract from Yatung News Report for the Period Ending the 15th February 19A4. In the course of conversation, he told me that the recent supply of munitions by the British Govemnent to the Tibetan Govemnent has helped a great deal in restoring the confidence of the Tibetan Government and the people vis-h-vis Ohina. He added that this might also result in the increase of the rate of exchange of the rupee, as the Tibetan Govemnent will now have to secure Indian currency to pay for the ammunition.:xt.382/44 lixtract from Lhasa letter for ’. 702 k ending January 30th, 1944. 3. I.ir» Seniall has continued his work on the guns without a pause during the week. Some small parts had to be made, anu he visited the Government Workshops at Trapchi for this purpose. He was amazed at the amount of once good machinery here. (The Tibetans have at one time maae rifles and shells here). He was also amazed at the dreaoful state of filth the Workshops ware now in. nothing has beencared for: good machinery was just planted down on a ausfcy floor: electric power w ires were bare and the whole place in a pitiful state of disrepair. The guns are now ready to fire, and it is hoped they will be fired on February 1st.axt.831/44 Extract from Lhasa letter for week ending January 23rd 1944. 3. On January 17th Lieut. Sendall arrived in Lhasa and is staying in the British Mission. vith hirn came the gun from Gyantse and the officers and iaen -who have been under training there. They were all met by a guard of honour outside Lhasa. Hr. Sendall has rather horrified the officers by his keenness to work:. He is being given all possible help in insioecting and repairing the guns. The day after Mr. Sendall arrived, Dr. Hung sent his interpreter to qy office to ask for his name, which was given. He also asked that Dr. Kung should be informed ’when the guns would fire as he wanted to be present, but was told that we knew nothing of this.jiXt.881/2^. jSxcract fran Lhcisa letter for week erring January 23rd IJbU. 3. On January 19th Mr. Sendall and I arranged for the guns which have remained so long in store in Lhasa to he taken to Norbhu Lingka, where Mr. Sendall started work at once.Ext &gt;681/44 Extract from Lhasa letter for v/eak ending January 23rd 1944* 7» On January 20th X called on the Foreign Office and handed them a private letter which the American airmen had written to the Tibetan Government thanking the latter for their help and kind treatment. Even now many officials do not believe that the plane came over Lhasa due to navigational errors. The belief is still strong that the Chinese had a hand in the business and that it was just bad luck that the plane crashed and did not get back safely to China.Ext» 1035Aii- Ex tract fran Yatun^ News Report for the period ending the 31st January T 3. The Tibetan Trade Agent, Yatung, has received orders from the Tibetan Government to forward the consignment of ammunition on its arrival at Yatung from India. In this letter, the Tibetan Government stated that they found it inconvenient to depute a special officer for the purpose. He has also been instructed to avoid publicity as far as possible on the subject and to despatch the cases in small quantities of about 300 loads at a time. The Tibetan Government, while informing the Tibetan Trade Agent, Yatung, that the carriage of the boxes of ammunition from Gangtok to Yatung will be arranged by the Political Officer in Sikkim, have ordered him that he should render every assistance if the Political Officer in Sikkim finds difficulty in arranging the required number of transport from Gangtok to Yatung.n&gt; OONFIDErcriAL. Ext. 47^44. Extract from Lhasa Letter for week ending December 26th 1943 &gt; No. 3(6)-l/43» 8. On December 23rd I called on Ragashar Dzasa to ask if arrangements had been madefbr Lieutenant Sendall's visit to Lhasa. He informed me that the Kashag had given instructions to the Tibetan Trade Agent, Yatung to issue the necessary passport and free transport. I understand that the Tibetan G-unners under instruction in G-yantse will accompany Lieutenant Sendall to Lhasa.Extract from Lhasa letter for week ending Lece..l)er 5th 19h-3- 9. On December 5th I ’.vent to the Any stores godovvn below the Ghokpori with the Commander in Chief to get everything ready as far as possible for the visit of Lieut. Sendall (vide ?orei^prl , s telegram No,10517 dated 27th November 1943) • It is a great pity that more care and interest is not taken by all concerned in the weapons of the Tibetan army. Owing to a favourable climate equipment aoes not deteriorate in this godown, but no one is encouraged to go and inspect it or learn anything about. In fact, it takes four or five days notice at least before the godown can be opened. It bears the seal of the Dalai Lama, Regent, kasha and Commander in Chief, and representatives from all of / these must be present when it is opened.Confidential. n (S' Extract from Lhasa Letter Veek ending Novanber 7th 3-943• 1. On ITovember 1st Ragashar Dzasa, the Cormnander-in-Chief called. He told me he had heard that the Tibetan Crimriers under training in Gyantse had been taught all about assembling and disioantling the gun there, but that the Eashag ■were ^fry keen tlmt further trainin should be given. In particular he asked for further training in limbering up and in laying the gun. Ee asked what would be necessary oefore the guns were fired, and _ to3_d him that I considered it necessarv that a competent officer should inspect the buffers. 2 . The following day Ragashar Dsasa called again, after having seen the Kashag. lie again asked for further oraining in lj r antse, and told me that. should an officer competent to inspect and adjust the gun buffers be available the Kashag would be very pleased to •provide free transport for him to Lhasa and give all facilities.Please see 'the reply from ■fch.e Tibetan Government regarding the airnnunition which, the Government oi India have undertaken to supply to Tibet. (The previous papers will be found below on Ext* and nxt* ol+tyo/k-3, • The suggestion of secrecy over the transaction is no doubt a wise course to talce. The vninese could mane mischievous propaganda out of it if they j-elt so disposed - although of course vre have got material v/ith wliich toEXT 42ji;6A3 &amp; Extract froLa liiasa lexter for weel. ending June 2yth, 1945. 1. I called on Surkhan^ Dzasa on June 20tli and asked if he could give rae the f i ( . 'ures of arms and ami;.unition supplied in the past to the Tibetan Government. He produced these totals two days later (my telegram to Foreign repeated to Political he^Vl June 23rd refers).EXT. r )568A3 /“ • Extract from Ihasa letter for week ending Augi^t l^th, 1943. 9 • Dn the afternoon of August 15th 1 called on the Conanander-in- Chief, Regashar Dzasa, to enquire about the condition of the gun in Gyantse• It is unfortunate that he takes so little interest in the equipment of his Army. He has asked me to look at the ether three B.L.2.75' guns which are in Lhasa.Ext.5597/43 Extract from Lhasa Letter for week ending August 29th 1943* !• On August 22nd I saw the three 2.75' B.L. grins in the store below the Chokpo-ri. The Conimander-in-Chief had asked me to do this, as various items of equipment were missing from the gun used for training in Gyantse. These three guns have never been out since they were brought from India by Lachag Tering. They were in good condition, still covered with the original grease, and optical equipment showed no signs of deterioration. There is however, no one in Lhasa capable even of putting these guns together correctly.iffCT. 3187/43. LEAPT TSLSC21AM. From: Secretary of State, To: Government of India, External Affairs Department, &amp;/yu Your Express Letter 27 th July 6773-X/43* H.M.G-. agree that request is unfortunate at this juncture and that v?e should not supply new aims (on that they cannot be spared during ■war)* ut they consider that ammunition for existing eapons could reasonably be supplied since Tibetan tocks may well be low and any objection byjcJhinese Government could effectively be met by reference to Government of India*s established practice of supplying munitions at adequate intervals for police purposes and self-defence. I suggest therefore $*cL aMk+v+K 7 that you might agree to supply Itamn. requires (A4* - X . y Qaaa* A*fe*fe* M *£*i aA S. A A- ** Cam IrthA+bl- aval Able without detriment jto war effort^ but see that certain amount of delay takes place in actual delivery (which might be in instalments) in hope of present tension being eased meanwhile.—imm QUTTiiKD TBIEGRAI/I. (if in any case the comramication of the contents of this docuiient to an^^ person outside Government Servioo is authorised, it must ho paraphrased.) External Department, Ext.'5167/^5 . SECRET . CYPHER TELEGEAi.h Prom Secretary of State for India To Government of India, External Affairs Department. Despatched 16th September, 19A3 at 12.00 hours. 21302. Your Express Letter 27th July 6773- ^A3, H.M.G-. agree that request is unfortunate at this juncture and that v/e should not supply nev/ arms (on ground that they cannot ho spared during war) • But they consider that ammunition for existing weapons could reasonelhy he supplied since Tibetan stock .nay •.veil he low and any objection hy Chines Government could effectively he met hy rei .renco to Government of India*s established practice of supplying munitions at adequate inter/als for police purposes and self-defence. I suggest therefore that you might agree to supply such amounts of 2.73 gun ammunition and of S.a.A. as can he made available without detriment to \7ar effort hut see that cert:.in amount of delay takes place in actual delivery (which might ho in instalments) in hope of present tension being eased meanwhile.% r - \ V* \ .L.C- -' - ;:-• POREIG-N OFFICE, S. W. 1. (F 4549/40/10) »*• i • _ ^ - —^ -1 7th ^ep^embef? a&gt;j 9^31 jlj Q ~ 7 u 5187 Dear Peel, A s Ashley C la ike i d gp leave, I am answering your letter Ext. 4560/43 of the 30th August, about the Tibetan Government 1 s request for certain arms and ammunition. We share your view that the advantages of keeping the Tibetan Government sweet outweigh the possible risks of the propaganda which the Chinese might make of any such action. It seems as certain as anything is that the Tibetans are not going to invade Gftina, so no harm can come of supplying the ammunition - icularly as most of it seems to bsolete - unless the Chinese de Tibet, which they say (and we eve) they have no intention of V/e agree with you that there Id be a certain amount of delay applying the ammunition and that hould be supplied in instalments. When Peel, Esq., C.B.E. , M.C. , India Office.rr //hen the final decision is taken we had 'better inform the Embassy at Chungking. (G-. P. Young)- « 4 UK'T IHNUTS Please see the attached riinutes and a note by General Molesworth on the subject of a recent request by the Tibetan Government for aims and ammunition. General Molesworth is agreeable to Mr. Peel^ suggestion that we should ask the Government of India to supply ammunition in the quantities which they^ had indicated in their letter as being available ^ for the arms which the Tibetans already possess, but that it would be as well not to be in a huny to supply them in the hope that the existing tension over Chinese troop movements on the Tibetan Border may have died down. Mr. Peel has also discussed the matter with Mr. Caroe who has said that the Government of India deliberately took up the attitude that it would be a mistake to supply munitions of war at this Juncture, because they thought it would please H.M.G* He agreed that the Government of India would not mind supplying the ammunition which they have available and in fact would be quite pleased to do so. A draft B*0. letter to the Foreign Office asking their agreement to this proposal is accordingly submitted. io h !»vw dtcS. (c, ‘TC &lt;fc, i ''U—3” 3 Ah 1Minute Paper. Department. Tibetaji request for Anns and Ammunition, In we gave the Tibetans 5&gt;000 rifles *303, and a certain quantity of Mark VI am mini t ion. In 1919 they renewed the request they had made during the v/ar ; for machine guns, artillery and ammunition, and Major Campbell ; the Political Officer in Sikkim , considered that if we could supply the Tibetans^with a reasonable quantity of Military Stores, sufficient for defence but not for an active forward policy ^’d/e should probably avoid the possibility of having to face the reappearance of the Chinese on the North Eastern Frontier of Inaia ? Tz.jqrr The agreement which followed in 1921, and the details of the arms supplied to Tibet by the Government of India between 1921 and 1933 are set out in a note by Lord Hood, dated 23rd September, 1936, flagged at P.Z. 5977/36. fit. thj, 'Ms. In 1937 in response to a further Tibetan request the Government of India appear, after some discussion with H.M.G., to have supplied on the same conditions the following anns:- 4 Mountain guns (2.75) with 800 rounds of ammunition. 5 Vickers machine guns. 3 old machine guns for training. 10 Lewis guns. 16,000 rounds of .303 ammunition. In 1940 H.M.G. sanctioned the supply to the Tibetans by the Government of India of 233 rifles .303 and 43,000 rounds of .303 ammunition to replace those which a rebel Tibetan had handed over to the Chinese in 1934* It is not clear from the correspondence whether these arms were in fact supplied. PI 'v.. The letter from the Government of India now attached gives details of a further Tibetan request for arms and ammunition. Sir Basil Gould, in his telegram also attached, considers that we must certainly supply a reasonable amount on payment. The Government of India, however, although admitting that a certaun amount of ammunition is available and could be supplied, incline^ to the view that it would be a mistake to provide munitions of war to Tibet at this time for various reasons set out in their paragraph 5&gt; ana would prefer to supply a considerable quantity after the war. 7e can appreciate the Government of India 1 s argument that compliance with the Tibetan's request might lay H.-^.G. anu the Government of India open to propaganda that our war effort was being diverted to enable Tibet to resist China. 7e used a similar argument recently, at the request of the Foreign Office ,over the Government of India's proposal to establish control on iie North Eastern Frontier up to tbs iiicmahon L-ne. Propaganda in China ana America of this nature would be most undesirable, but we have a veiy good reply and one that we have used before on previous occasions 'when the Chinese have made representations in the matter (4aP.Z 02 * 44 / 36 ). ‘e stated then that we held ourselves free to meet such requests from Tibet for munitions on condition that they were used only for police purposes and for self defence. It would possibly be desirable to avoid using the actual wording which will be found at P.Z. 9226/36 and which refers to Tibet's status. It would be possible to say, however, that the supply of munitions to Tibet in instalments at adequate intervals is a practice which/ (6010) Wt.25950/235 10,000 9/38 A.&amp;E.W.Ltd. Gp.685v/hich has been established by the G-overniiient of India since the last war. Other reasons for i.ieeting the Tibetaiis' request so far as is possible are:- (a) It seems unreasonable to have sold them guns in the past and yet to refuse to provide sufficient ammunition for their upkeep. (b) The undesirability of the Tibetans going elsevrtiere for help e.g. the Americans. (The Tibetans have recently established rather friendly relations through the President* s £ru)dssaries , and it seems not unlikely that they might follow this up -with a request to America for arms if we refuse them.) (c) There are still persistent rumours of Chinese aggressive intentions and troop movements in the neighbourhood of Eastern Tibet. We can only promise Tibet diplomatic support, but a supply of ammunition in reftsenable quantities would be an earnest of our good faith and support, and might go some way to restore the nerves from which the Tibetan Government have suffered over Chinese intentions recently. It is unlikely that die supply of such a small quantity would act as a deterrent to the Chinese but rather as a moral prop to the Tibetans. It is suggested that we might tell the Government of India that we see some advantage in the supply,on payment,of the ammunition which they state in paragraph 5 is available viz:- jooo 5 million rounds of St.A.a. Maik VII and'2.75 gun ammunition. There would of course be no question of supplying item D. War Staff. May v/e have your views? Cl l • hA A—r tx*. llZsu^ ^ L+. erdc^ej- (T fW t O^r pv &lt; of • a~J- it &lt;s IzU: C^y X C&gt; 4^ (K~l trv-*. p'- , As. fc. h Lw-c La~ ^ U, ^ ) fa tzU &gt; ,'s fr u, t ^ ^ ^ ( ^ k^X l^uM jl tz c&lt;^'dU-UZ~; -X ft*— (o ^ L Vs UjL . /iK. ^ k-2*, t a 46^ ^cc^* fc it ii_^ ^ ^ JUx cJU^ ■&gt;; &gt; O’ A, oZb h (x. .— t wf /L Lfy*. IcJt 1 t^w&gt; 4- , J*»v.■ '^V s DRAFT D. 0. LETTER Ext. A36QA5 H. Ashley Clarke, Esq., Foreign Office, S. W. 1. I enclose a copy of an express letter from the G-overnment of India, regarding / H 0 . 6773 -X /43 At/- 2Y T 1+15 • a request from the Tibetan Governnent for the supply of certain arms and ammunition. 2. The Tibetans have long been dependent on India for the supply of their munitions and since the end of the last war the Government of India have from time to time met their requests for the sale of a limited quantity of mountain guns, machine guns, Lewis guns, rifles and ammunition. The munitions have been supplied on condition that they were used solely for self-defence and for internal Police work. The Government of India have supplied little in recent years and no doubt Tibetan stocks are running low. Their request is therefore not unreasonable* n^i then- a.n- at Lt L (fC. °Lv~CC fyuJt tCi cJt fcc uauimil-and we snould feel no teJ.lab.kan ia-ths matt or meinj 1 L not •cnal LllUir &lt;5 roquoot/is rre- doubt prompted by their apprehensions of Chinese aggression ; due to the movements of Chinese troops near the Tibetan Frontier. You will recall that when they reported these movements to us last April they said that if the Chinese did encroach on their territory, they would be obliged to use force and 'also apply to our Ally, the British Government, for the supply of arms and airmunition; and it is sincerely hoped that this will be granted as it is required for defence of our own territory and not for aggressive purposes'. (See Government of India telegram No. 3426 dated 1st May sent to Foreign Office on same date under No. Ext*2283/43) • 3. As the Government of India have stated in paragraph 6 of their letter^the provision of munitions of war to Tibet at this juncture 'ttould lay H.M.G. and the Government of India open to propaganda that their war effort is/-A is being diverted to enable Tibet to resist China. We agree that propaganda of this nature would be most undesirable, but it could be met with the answer that in supplying ammunition to Tibet the Government of India are only following their riractice established since the last war of supplying munitions to Tibet in instalments at adequate intervals for self-defence and « « «• • internal Police purposes. The Chinese Government have on past occasions made representations through their Embassy with regard to the sale of arms to Tibet by the — « Government of India (please see Foreign Office letters of g0th November 1936 No.F. 719^/4/10 to the India Office and No.777Wl0 of 23rd December 1936 to the Chinese Ambassador). If similar approaches were to be made in the present instance we consider that the reply which was then used would still be adequate. hr* T hnve. lur.rl nn opportunity uf ttlSjuus^Lng this ma^^-wa^hJCaroe- ( who on '—IcpuL'tiuiv^deputation) and I gathered from him that the altitude which the Government of India ha^ft adopted in paragraph 6 of their letter was\largely determined 'by what they considered H.ihG’s ts 'be* They themselves would see no objection to supplying the Tibetan Government with the ammunition which is available, that is with 5 million rounds of S*A*A. Mark VII and 1,000 rounds of 2*75 gunNanmunition, and in fact they would be pleased to do so. 'LCL^v^c- 4 -, ^ On consideration,-v/e A imfe'] i np io the view that it would be unreasonable to refuse to provideya certain quantity of ammunition for the upkeep of weapons which we have supplied in the past, although we should refuse to supply any new aims on the grounds that they cannot be spared during the wsjt* From the political angle, our readiness in the past to supply the Tibetan Government with such necessities las no doubt strengthened / considerably(21 (JUJbtA * ^j^L+aAJ. k 1/ [iry^cL/ fcJt \ — Lc ^ «■&gt;/». - Cw+JL(.*M*. i*s*£~r&gt;£ c(a&amp; \Z&gt;«-*vyjt k ct**? (***■ l*ft*&lt;. con side ralDly our influence with Tibetj&lt;w(.22e ls^ xcLasl+A. C should not like to see he return to the U. S*A* for help^ if u/nr iuPiue. we consider such a move ’to he not unlikely^/ since the friendly exchange of messages between the Dalai Lama and President Soosevelt the medium of the i^merican Officers, Captain Tolstoy and Lieutenant Brooke Dolan* U/uw/U «. C t* 'ho. S-Cc 1^-0 §&gt;• - that tlie Goverment of India ifftght he advised to offer to supply the ammunition referred to in paragraph 5 of their letter^? hut that they should see that a certain y U~ fc* ft, *S C^, ta, ^4^*AW—^'C^. amount of delay takes placej^in the hope that Us*L Ks, the present tension ever Chinese a-ggrr-ni rf may die down hofore tho .•rgmmition ch-'niges l'u rkfe« fc. T, GoCc*^, 6*-*w&lt;. ^ A. ^ t We shell he g1^n to-have the P t 0. views a PEAL,--=ap—-k r I4g-, ^ 'l/l \*u cufa-al ^ti o&amp;»&lt;Jc &amp;U u 'Jbbsbs ^sas sc reference in a Lhasa letter of October to the payment to Government of India in respect of munitions which vtmm fi&amp;tii bgfcn.% completed. Prom P.Z. 360 of 1937 and P.Z.5977 of 1936 flagged on the attached file, I think we can deduce that this refers to munitions supplied to Tibet as the result of the agreement in 1921 by an exchange of letters between Sir Charles Bell and the Dalai Lama. The munitions were supplied over a period of years finishing in 1933. In 1937 it appears that Tibet still owed Rupees 6 lakhs to the Government of India. Since that date, such small quantities of munitions which have been supplied have been paid for with cash down.D* 0. W o. 3 (3) - P/41. Dear Weightman, Tne presents which are rntisti apprelbiated in Tioet and Bhutan are ^i^les with ammunition, and revolers (or pistols of any kind) and ammunition. T#iat the Maharaja of Bhutan likes oest are new British .303 rifles. These used to be popular in Tibet also, but the late Dalai Lama passed a rule that all .303’s in Tibet wbul^ bet considered to be the property of the Tibetan Gfovernment. 3b in Tibet we nave mostly given Mausers, .275 bore, usually German made. Such weapons will I suppose be difficult to ootam, or unprocurable, of some time to come. And it may oe difficult to get Winchesters etc from lAmerica. But i,s there a prospect that captured Italian arms may oe procurable? If so, and if the price is reasonable, I should like to get an option on 100 to 200 rifles in oest possible condition, with bayonets if available. Also slings if available, and cleaning rods or pull throughs. 30 to 100 pistols or rifles. Ammunition. At 300 to 400 rounds per weapon. When you are able to reply on general- lines, 1 will go into more detail. Supplies of different kinds of arms to Tibetans do ifrttle if anything to strengthen the country against us (if it were conceivable that tne country shoula be opposed to us). But they do tend to increase good will and confidence, and to suppress brigandage. Yours sincerly Sd/- 3. J. Groul d. H. Weightman, Esquire, C.I.E., Deputy Secretary to the Crovernment of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Un i i_ &lt; \r 1 b-5-1941 £R EDPILE copy ^ ri (?2 ) No.—Gerrard 6933. .—Gerrard 6933. and the following number quoted. subject should be addressed to :— The Secretary. Any further communication on this Ministry of Supply, London. W.C.2. MINISTRY OF SUPPLY, THE ADELPH1, (code VA) LONDON, W.C.2. 2164/6 (M.P.o) |I7- I Uoj , 1940 j 15th February, 1940. H Sir, In reply to your letter of the 51st ultimo. No. PZ/112/40 regarding the supply for the use of the Tibetan G-ovemment of 238 .SOS'* Rifles (complete with bayonets and slings) and 48,000 rounds of ammunition, I am directed by the Minister of Supply to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that the matter has been discussed at a meeting of the War Office Branch Priority Committee, and it was agreed that, as far as the War Office and this Ministry are concerned, there would be no objection to the stores in question being supplied by the G-ovemment of India as proposed. I am. Sir * Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State for India India Office, REC». P®L. MPr. 19 FEB 1940 INDIA OFFICEft \ y | ' ? Political Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. REGISTER NO. P. Z. 112/40. 51 JAN WO Telegram {roni Letter 194«? . Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State ... / ... Committee ... Under Secretary /.. Secretary of State aLM Id. TI35T . proposal to supply to P&amp;ngdatsang 238 .303 rifles and 48,000 rounds of .303 ammunition for use of Tibetan Government. A ^ ^ . r- FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. Draft letter to Ministry of Supply, requesting their concurrence in proposal*m •'*' 23 &amp; Minute Paper. p.z.112/40. Department. In 19^4 Tobgye, the younger brother of Pangdatsang, a Tibetan Government trader, revolted and handed over a number of rifles to the Chinese. The Tibetan Government have aslred (p.Z. 3782/39) that 238 rifles (complete with bayonets and slings) and 200 rounds of ammunition per rifle should be supplied to Pangdatsang by the Government of India for cash, in order that he may make good the Tibetan Government's loss. The Government of India have offered to supply these stores on the terms described in Major Fletcher’s demi-official letter of the 14th December at P.Z.7952/39, and the Tibetan Government and Pangdatsang have agreed. The Government desire the sanction of His Majesty's Government to the transaction by telegraph. It is understood that all supplies of .303 ammunition in India he.ve been earmarked by His Majesty's Government, and that it will be necessary to secure the sanction of the Ministry of Supply if the ammunition in question (48,000 rounds) is to be sjo4rd to the Tibetan Government. Apart from this, there would seem to be no objection to the proposal. A draft letter to the Ministry of Supply isV Draft Paper. P.Z.112/40. $9 Department. The Under Secretary of State, Ministry of Supply. Dated Sth January P.Z.795S,p.Z.7C7j,\ P. Z, Cl'S^ ,P.Z.3782. (p^ ^ (Sgd.) R. PEEL- Sir, 31 JAN 1940 I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose herewith a copy of a telegram from the Government of India together with a copy of previous correspondence, on the subject of the supply for the use of the Tibetan Government of 238 .3C3 H rifles (complete with bayonets and slings) and 48,COO rounds of .303“ ammunition. Lord Zetland considers that on political grounds it would be undesirable to withhold the supply lu t +‘+u(&lt;{ (k* of any part of these stores, and I aw (jlcU it ** ** er»ocrd ingl-y t-o on quire whether Mr. Burgin would see any objection to sanction being accorded to the proposal in question. A copy of this letter is being sent tojthe Foreign Office and theINDEXED F!L Allotted to Political Dept^ Copies circulated* i ! O 1 I £~ (40 groups.) 1940 j -/ •' »*♦ rPMjL Qz- roM *w 157. DSCYPHSR OP TELaQRAM.- Prom Government of India, External Affaire Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 14.40 hours, 8th January, 1940. Received 11*15 hours, 8th January, 1940. X 52. Reference correspondence forwarded v/ith weekly air mail letter from Secretary, Department of External Affairs, No.235(a)M, December 14th. Arms and ammunition for Tibetan Government. Tibetan Government and Pangdatsang have agreed to purchase on t erms proposed and will pay on delivery. Kindly telegraph sanction. RCC.lPOL.DEPt - 8 JAN 1940 INDIA OFFICEKk. • 2 - Oovernment of India will be glad to be informed by telegram if the Tibetan Gefernment and h*agdatean£ with to purohaae on the above terms*Copy of confidential memorandum No.6(4j-L/39, dated the 1st October 1939, H.E. Richardson, Esq., ICS., British Trade -agent, Gyantse, and Asstt. to the Political Officer in Sikkim, British Mission, Lhasa, to the Political officer in olkkim. I &amp; . *— ■ 7 o y * supply of arms and ammunltloja / d/ * to Tibetan Government*. Reference your memorandum No.3(3)-P/39, dated the 18th September 1939. I saw Pangdatsang and explained to him the terms ofifered by the military authorities. As there appeared to be some doubt about the exact nature of the ’long ’ rifles wanted by him I asked him whether he could show me a specimen. It turns out that what he wants are Lee Enfields bearing the mark V.R. 1889.1. and also E.Y. on the breach. If these are available they must be obsolete now and presumably very cheap. Pangdatsang would like 173 of these and 65 short L.E.303 rifles. If the Mark I rifles are not available he will be glad to accept the supply of the rifles detailed by the Government of India in their demi- official letter R0.F.356-X/39 dated the 16th .august 193£ It appears to me that the charges are unusually high coming as they do to more than 21% of the total amount and to more than 27% of the cost of the stores. This is my own opinion and not a comment of Pangdatsang’s. Payment will be made by Pangdatsang, Kalimpong, to the Kalimpong treasury on delivery.HUE COPY % I J ' &gt; / f\) ^ QOMKI J.JfriAL.[ IQ’d?' • eternal Affairs iiepartment t Simla, The ' August 1939. With reference to your demi-official letter Ho. 3(3)-P/39, dated the 26th !iay 1939, I am ueaired to inform you tnat trie asitter me referred to the Mlitiry authorities concerned from ehoa it is understood that the following stores are available for issue on payraent from the Allahabad Araenali- Ho Rifles No. 1 Hk. Ill (a) 173 65 236 236 Long Butt Short Butt Bayonets No. 1, Mk.I Scabbards Bayonet Ho.l, Mk.II Slings rifle Cartricyss 3.A. Ball .SOS* 1/k.VII .. Hda.48,000 (b) (a) P.W.S* (Arsenal repaired) rifles can be issued. It is presumed that by hon.^ rifle Short is meant ’Rifles eith Lort^: Butts 9 * Short The Arsenals have no stocks of long rifles. (b) ENCLOSURE in INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S LETTER No. DATE -J 50 18-8(b) 48*000 rounas nave bden proposed insUad of 47*600 dei»mded in order to make into oomplete factory sealeii boxes of 1*000 round* each* 2* The following special packing will ammunition demanded:-* be issued with the Saction Q. 2. as o • Boxes A*S*A** H-17 Mk.I 46 Bandoliers cotton 50 rds* Mk.II 960 Chargers *303' cartridges Ilk*IV 9600 It is understood that in 1762 the rifles supplied to ttie Government of Tibet ware paaked as uuiari - (a) Bolts ware romovod and packed separately in strong cases wei^hin^ not more than one inauna each when packed* (b) Rifles were packed (heads am tails) in gunny bundles with tow round each rifle to prevent damage* i (c) &amp;*.oh bundle of rifles was secured by strong coir before giunny was sewn round tne bundle. (d) Complete gunny bundles were wired outside; each bundle not exceeding one xaaund in weight* which m&gt;ml 8 rifles per bundle* If the above meUiod is not to be &lt;sudopted on the present occasion* it is understood the followi/^ will be required*- Chests* **•CONFIDBWTIAT,. FILE C A L? 7 * 7 7 p ^ j V/ / O ( 21 JUN 1939 ) v£&gt; 'W. Copy of 'demi-official letter No. 3(3)-P/39, dated the 26th May 1939, from the Residency, G&lt;ingtok, Sikkim, to the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. I enclose copy of demi-official letter No 6(4)-L/39 dated the 6th April 1939 from Richardson with enclosure. 2. For the story of the revolt of Pan^datsang*s brother please refer to late Mr. T 7illiamson f s letter No. 7(9)-P/34 dated the 14th July 1934. * 1 2 3 4 3. The questions for consideration are:- (1) -/hether it is feasible to supply, for cash, to Psngdatsang, for delivery to the Tibetan Government 238. 303 rifles complete^with bayonets and slings. 200 rounds of ammunition per rifle. (2) Whether these can be supplied in the proportion of 173 long rifles 65 short rifles. (3) Whether used but service-able rifles can be supplied, and at what price. (4) What would be the price if new rifles were supplied. 4. It is encouraging to notice that the Tibetan Government obviously attach importance to the maintenance intact of the full quota of arms which we have from time to time supplied to them, and it is to be hoped that it may be found convenient to supply the comparatively small quantity of arms and ammunition now asked for.sa— PST-M' ^ - mmmmmasmms=am Copy of a demi-official letter No. 6(4)-L/39, dated the 6th April 1939, from the British Mission Lhasa, to the Political Officer in Sikkim. I enclose a copy of a letter from the ilbetan Government asking for certain arms and ammunition taken by Pangdatsang's brother to be replaced at Pangdatsang 1 s expense, pangdatsang, who ms given the letter to bring to me, seems to have kept it for about a fortnight. He said that the arms taken by his brother were all old and asked that, if possible, used anAnot new rifles might be supplied as cheaply as possible, 1 am not sure what is meant by long service rifles but perojBps your files will show what type of service rifles were supplied to the Tibetan Government before 3.L.E. 303 So As the Tibetan Government do not specify that new rifles should be provided I see no harm in helping Pangdatsang so far as is possible. But if old| ,303 s are supplied they should be serviceable and not D.P. (drill purposes). Pangdatsang would, of course pay for the arms; and they should be consigned care of him at Kalimpong. Railway vouchers and bills snould a.lso be sent to him.COPY. Translation. '7 ~ v C &lt;«■/ $ u -&lt;.a Tibetan month of the Earth Hare Year(Corresponding to the 20th March 1939) from the Ministers of Tibet, Lhasa, to H.E.Richardson, Esquire, I.C.S., British Trade Agent, Cyaatse. The reason for sending this letter is to inform you that in the judgement passed by the Tibetan Government in respect of the case concerning the loss of long and short rifles of the Tibetan Government’s soldiers complete with bayonets and ammu nition at the time when Tobgay, youngest brother of Pan^datsang, committed! the evil deed of revolting against the Tibetan Government in Markham in the Wood- dog year (corresponding to the year 1934), Panadatsang is ordered to make good the loss of 173 long and 65 short British service rifles complete with bayonets, slings and 200 rounds of ammunition for each rifle. It is, therefore, requested that you will kindly approach the Government of India through the political Officer in Sikkim for favour of the sale of these weapons to Pangdatsang to whom the munitions may kindly be given delivery after recovering the cost due. We may please be informed when you receive a reply to the action taken by you 0 Sent with a silk scarf.♦Ay Ati. M*oC k /’■exicy Telegram II. ^ Fr cm . . . . T o j- ^ • • • • • No. 24, dated (&amp;. rood.) . . . Crould 9 Lhasa. . . . Foreign, New Lelhi 21st January 1937*, r) * :• r: ? iL~ \J \ lour telegram No. 2C), January 18th. Tibetan Government are likely to request prompt delivery of such munitions as are immediately available. As Government of India desire payment (; on delivery (your telegram No, 158) it will be necessary tc intimate to Tibetan Government'cost of items (a) to (d) mention ed in your telegram No. 297 0,, They also re^uira to know cost for the purpose of stock keeping. 2. N earn a had estimated cost of new material plus three I).?* Vickers gums at fc* £3,CC( exclusive of carriage, in view of this, Ln i,2C,00C mentioned in your telegram No. 297C tc w serviceabj e^guns seems high particularly in view of policy of Government of India to supply Tibet at a price which will not tempt her to turn elsewhere for munitions. I., F.3., D.3.(F)., J.3., J.3.(Fed.), A.D.S.(F)., U.S.(G) and T J.r. M.S.H. enclosure in [&gt;IA FOREIGN SECRETARY 8 . 3 3N. iata.i5 ]2 ‘ EB. 22 FEE. 1937Telegram XX., ''From , . , . No. 260, dated 24th January 1937 Foreign, N ev Delhi. • Gould, Lhasa. To Your telegram No. 24 dated 21st January. Cost of items (a) to (d) including packing and freightso Kalimpong is Full rates have been charged for items (b) and (d). Cost- quoted for item (a&gt; is 90/3 cf full rates for all items except chests for v/hich ?5&gt;c of full rates are charged and for (c) 7£j/c of full rates. Cost of items (e) and (f) comes to fe.23,565 andp£.56,35C respectively. (e) has been charged at 60% for cartridges, and 7 6% of full rates for shell bodies, and fillings, and full rates for other components as these for tne most part will have to be manufactured; and (f) at 75&gt;c of full rates for guns except for certain items for which full rates are charged. hlovd figures are considered reasonable and cannot be reduced. If by cost for purpose of stock keeping you mean detailed figures for every item of equipment, they can be supplied. U.Dto&lt;t I &amp; L 428. Telegram No.38 Dated (and reed; 7th February 1937. From.Gould, Lhasa. To..t.. Foreign, New Delfei. Your telegram No.260 of 24th January. Kashag request that expression of their warm gratitude for supply of arms may be conveyed to H.E. the Viceroy and Government of India. 2. Cash will be paid on delivery Kalimpong. Bequest that items a, b, c and d may be delivered at talimpong first week of March and e and f later on. They trust that time Wj.il in no case exceed six months. 3. Everything should be packed for mule transport in loads not exceeding one maund gross. If anyjloads exceed this weight Mission may please be informed by telegram. 4. Contents to be plainly marked outside boxes. 5. In order to ensure safe transit it is not proposed to open boxes prior to arrival at Lhasa. 6. With reference to last sentence of your telegram detailed figures for every item may please be supplied. 7. Tibetan Government would be grateful for advice whether any extra items are desirable. In any case they request supply on payment of moderate amount of oil and cleaning materials. These may be preferably charged on separate hill. (X. E.S. D.S.E. J.S. J.3.ELD. A.D.S.F. U.S.G. &amp;U.D.) M.B.\ Their express letter of 13th April last, however, contemplated farther proposals as if something on a more generous scale than these small concessions was being considered. The G. of I. will, as we suggested, examine the question farther in consultation with Mr. Gould on his return to India, though they indicate that the present financial difficulties militate against farther expenditure. SEEN POUTICAL COMMITTE 1 8 FEB 1937(^c£ SECRET JHJ./C'.i/VH 62 4 (COf-Iii. CXHCDI/ATliiD) D A C T x H ^ i&lt; Oj' l 1 i, ii jj S B A i-,. E’roiii OoTernment of India, Foreign and iolitical department, to Secretary of State for India 0 dated New Delhi, 1st February,19o7 3 Receired 10 o 46 p,m 0 1st February ,1ja7„ XXX 335 Addressed to Secretary of State for India, ^^repeated to Pekingo Your telegram No„3676, S3rd December 1936 0 Tibeto V.e have not abanaouec proposals for offer of practical u-aia unce onvis^^sd in our « Aprsus letter &gt;i 13 rh April last 0 Training of military officers free of charge has been agreed to;free transit of Chinese brick tea has been conceded; and increasingly frequent requests for free transit of goods consigned through India to Regent or monasteries have invariably seen complied witho Question will be farther examined in consultation with Gould when he returns to India, but we must point out that,in the present financial circumstances, we cannot justify farther expenditure from Inuian Revenues on neighbouring countries unless we are confident that results of real importance to India will be secured,, Paragraph No 0 £o ifch reference to paragraph No 0 3 of your telegram, we do not wish to plc.ee Tibetan Government further in our debt but wil1 consider your suggestion if Tibetan Government plead inability to pay cash*JGS/DiAi (121 group^ SECRET T 6 - (/ 292 decyphbr of From TEL E GRAM . (COPIES CIRCULATED) Goverlament of India* Foreign Political Department* to Secretary of state for India, repeating telegram addressed to Political Officer* Sikkim* XXX Dated Ksw Delhi, 15th t T a nuai'y ? 193Vo Received 15th January, 193V, 3 P-m. 155. Addressed to Ckmld, Lhasa, repeated to Secretary of State and Peking« Our telegram No. 2970, Deoemher 12th, 1956, to Secretary of State, repeated to you. 2„ You may now inform Tibetan Government that Government of India are prepared to supply munitions required by them, ride paragraph No.l of telegram referred to above. Government of India note, from your telegram_168, (v October 7th), that the Tibetan Government will probably manage cash Government of Indict would prefer this payment on delivenyo uol ' Ci - iUU * course as Tibetan ('? Gcvernment) already owe them about 6 lakhs of rupees on account of previous supply of munitions. 5. Government of India are prepared to carry out, free „ nffieers and 12 non-commissioned of charge, training ox 12 oiiic-rs • fr-p n -o^riod of 3 months, Gos-c of officers at Shillong xor a p^x-uu. .in «„». W psqo ~p,«. includes accommodation in tents, messing at Ind^i.n Anny standard and transportation to Shillong xroi,. Six-guri a ^ for the whole party. It does not include pay or allowances. RECD. PCI. BEPr. 1SdANl937—7774/4/10) V You will romenber that you mentioned to me recently a report you had received regarding the sup &gt;ly of arms to Tibet from India. I have looked into the matter, and find that t2ie position is that a proposal for certain supplies (on a considerably more modest scale, however, than you indicated) has been put forward by the Tibetan Government, and is at present under consideration. As you are aw^re from statements made in the past, we hold ourselves free to wieet such requests for munitions from Tibet, ae an autonomous dtute under Chinese suzerainty. For example, \fhen Dr Gh f en called hertj on the 4th October, 1932, we informed him of the assurance given to the Tibetan Government that they would be permitted to purchase ams tram India in instalments at adequate intervals, on condition Us Excellency Mr *uo Tai-chi. that . # # •In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. P 7918/4/10- 9228 and address, not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. Foreign Office. S.'V.l 29th December, 1936 Sir I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to refer to India Office letter No. P.Z.8902/36 of 21st December regarding the supply of certain munitions to the Tibetan Government and the training of Tibetan officers in India, and to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that Mr. Eden concurs in the terms of the draft telegram to the Government of India enclosed therein. 2 . I am to request that this telegram may be repeated to Peking for the information of His Majesty’s Ambassador. I am Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State India Office.Minute Paper. Department. The Tibetan Govt.’s requirements of munitions mentioned in this telegram are very nearly the same as those recommended by Brigadier Neame on page 5 of his note at flag A. He also recommended much more extensive training in India (e.g., the training of Commanders) than the General Staff are at present able to undertake. Generally speaking, the non possumus attitude displayed in the present telegram is in striking contrast to the very forthcoming statements contained in the G. of I.’s communications when the Mission to Lhasa was in preparation. For example, in their express letter of 13th April the G. of I. stated “It should be our aim now, as in the past, to preserve an autonomous and friendly Tibetan Govt., determined and able to resist Chinese aggression, political or military, and also to retain full independence against Russian or Japanese influence', and they proposed that Mr. Gould should make proposals to the Tibetan Govt, which would tend to implement this policy; they promised to address the S. of S. separately in regard to these proposals, which they said would include 'offers of practical assistance in various forms calculated to improve the financial strength of the Lhasa Govt., and to convince them of the practical interest which we take in their stability and welfare'. The case for such practical assistance has certainly not been weakened, but quite the contrary, by the results of hr. Gould’s mission, which confirm that, as was to be expected, the main danger at present is the weakness and instability of the Govt, at Lhasa. Indeed, this fact is stressed by the G. of I. in their present telegram; no doubt the Tibetan Govt, are not only weak but incapable, but this fact does not demolish 4424 5000 1.36 the/c the case for practical assistance accompanied by advice. It is suggested that if the F.O. concur we might address the G. of I. on the lines of the attached draft telegram. t • l^j-LCvy* /l. &lt;i. 3lDraft Paper. Department. Sir, 21 0E[I,9SS I am directed by the S. of 3. for 1. to enclose copy of a telegram from the G. of 1. on the subject of the supply of certain munitions to the Tibetan Govt, and the training of Tibetan officers in India. 2. It will be observed that the G. of I.’s recommendations under each head are very modest, .and, subject to Mr. Secy. Eden’s concurrence, the Marquess of Zetland would propose to inform the G. of I. that there is no objection to these recommendations. 3. At the same time Lord Zetland would propose, in telegraphing to the G. of I., to make a reference to the general question^which they had previously raised,of offering practical assistance in various forms calculated to improve the financial strength of the Lhasa Govt.; and also to ask whether it is necessary to insist on the condition/ which they now propose^of cash payment for the munitions. Copy is enclosed of a draft telegram which Lord Zetland would propose to address to the G. of I. (Sd.'i .t. n. wat/to^&amp; Draft Paper* Department. 2 . '' s' ' outstanding debt being liquidated as a ^ S' loan carrying interest, in accordance with proposal in your telegram to Sikkim No.2217, dated 9th September, ^ S' ^ s~ s 1933, and could not similar procedure ^ ^ ^ - be adopted for present supply?DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE p 2L. fycxfiG TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) Send. Copy to Ify.. J tloJJ- 4862 500 6.36 Yoar telegrair. 12th December, 2970. Tibet. There is no objection to supply of the munitions recommended^br ery jhrU-i-t- J /TV to training of instructors in India. I had assumed, however, from your express letter of 13th April last and other communications that you were prepared for a more generous measure of assistance to Tibetan Govt, than that which you now appear to contemplate^ It is clear from Gould’s reports that mam danger at present is weakness and instability of Lhasa Govt, rather than any risk of their undertaking adventures such as is envisaged in para. 5 of your telegram^ In view of our interest in stability of a friendly and autonomous Tibet ^ L-t rust t hat you^tiave^TOt- abandon&amp;4 proposals^riaich 1- was hoping^ te--i?ectrnn8y for offers of practical assistance calculated to improve financial strength of Lhasa Govt.^ You will perhaps consider the whole position in the light of Gould’s final report after his return. I trust that as regards munitions you may be able to waive condition of cash payment, which Tibetan Govt, might not be able to accept. Is not outstanding debt being liquidated as a loan carrying interest, in accordance with oroposal in your telegram to Sikkim - No./flSCM. a WALTON. Draft Paper. { 19 56 Department. I am sorry not to have replied before to your letter of 26th November, J.6 D 1356 C.W. Orde, Esn., G.M.G., F.O. F 7198/4/10. It seemed desirable to wait for the reply to enquiries which we had made of the G. of I. as to the position regarding munitions and wireless Their reply regarding munitions is contained in their telegram of 12th December, No. 2970, and that regarding the wireless question in their telegram No. 2971 and para. 6 of their telegram No. 2972. Copy of these telegrams is enclosed for ease of reference. \/e concur in the draft reply to the Chinese Ambassador enclosed with your letter, subject to the suggestion that the second sentence and following of the last paragraph might read somewhat as follows:- 'I understand that the Tibetan Govt . desire to obtain a wireless set from India, and that the matter is now under consideration; we feel that it is quite natural . . . etc.'4 GCH/MJL UJ- 7 groups.) SECRET &amp; 5698.(Part 2) D E 0 Y P H E R 0,1 . TJLkJ-SJLJJk. (COPIES CIRCULATED) From Government of India ; Foreign ard Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhij. 12th December, 1936 Received 4.45 p.m., 12th December, 1936 XXX 1 )( 29?0 J . (a) Regent and Kashag ar-e incapable of taking stror^ line about anything or of following any consistent policy except chat of waiting on eventso (b) Tibetan army requires complete reorganisation and elaborate training before it could be regarded as of any military value even if additional armament now asked for is supplied. Paragraph No&lt;, 3.«. General Staff in India regret that in present circumstances they are unable to undertake the training suggested by Neaxti© and anything on these elaborate lines must be ruled out* The most that they could undertake at present ia the training of a small cadre of officers and or non~commissioned officer instructors at &amp; selected station in Indi&amp;« This would hardly touch the fringe of the problems Para gr aph No .4. Further difficulty ia finance. Tibetan Government already owe us about 6 lakhe for arms and ammunition previously supplied and we should have to insist on them paying cash on delivery for this consignment.- -j:— &lt;iS? SECRET Izi rs JGS/VH, (131 groups 5700 (Part 3 and laetc) (COPIES CIHCU1A1ED) P E C Y P H E H OF TELEGRAM. Prom GoTernment of India, Foreign and Political department, to Secretary of State for India, dated Delhi, ISIh December,1936 0 Reoeired 9 0 16 p 0 m 0 ,12th December,1936 XXX 2970’ o Even if these practical difficulties could be overcome, we ere by no means satisfied that it is in Indians interest to have a well trained, well armed and highly organised army in Tibet, Such an army might encourage the Lhasa Government uo undertake adventures on the Tibetan-Chinese frontier, which would cause further complications, and, if we bring such an army xnto existence, se shall be committed not only to continual inspections on the military side but also to some responsibility for control of Tibet’s foreign policy. Although, therefore, we appreciate that Gould attaches much importance to this supply as a means of stiffening Tibetan Government's resistance to Chinese influence and A /&gt; */V^ /U\ Jktf \ r {tamk. •«_. (A penetration, we cannot agree to do more than !lj offer supply on usual conditions V of arms and h/ —^ ammunition for cash pa^ilti and !c, undertake to train a few instructors in India. ’ Te W0Uld b9 grateful His Majesty’s Government's approval to this course, ?0 Position regarding wireless is dealt with in our immediately following telegram.(P 7198/4/10) Ip/'-'' ' tn44 ! POSEIGN OPPICE, S.W.l. 26th November, 1936. In your letter (P.Z.7012/36) of 22nd October you suggested the lines upon which v/e might reply / should the Chinese Embassy return to the charge about ^ the supply of arms to Tibet, The matter was raised by the Ambassador when he saw Cadogan recently: he referred to Dr. Oh’en’s previous conversations with me regarding the supply of X arms and the alleged erection of a wireless installation Lhasa, and said that they had now received a further report to the effect that eight small field guns, eight small machine guns and thirty light machine guns, together with ammunition, had already been sold to the Tibetan Government. I enclose the draft of a letter which we propose to send in reply to the Ambassador, and should be glad to AIR MAH. I * 1 know/ J.C.Walton, Esq., C.B., M.C. ,..4 9 £ 8 N ,! V 1956V 7198/4/10 3 . ¥.1 J November Chinese Anibassador# You will renember that you mentioned to me the other day a report you had received regarding the supply of arms to Tibet from India. I have looked into the matter, and find that the position is that a proposal for certain supplies (on a considerably more modest scale, however, than you indicated) has been put forward by the Tibetan Government, and is at present under consideration. As you are aware from statements made in the past, we hold ourselves free to neat such requests for muni tl cue from Tibet, as an autonomous 3tate under Chinese suzerainty. For example, when Dr. Ch’ called here on 4th October, 193:3, we informed him of the assurance given to the Tibetan Govern :ent that they would be permitted to purchase arms from India in instal :ents at adequate/( adequ te intervals, on condition that they were ohl;/ for police purposes and for self- defence. It was also pointed out to Dr. Ch f en that the Tibetans naturally sought these ams in India rather than in Europe, and that purchases had to be nade from the Government of India, as there were no other sources of supply in India* In our view these considerations apply equally to the present Tibetan request. You also mentioned a recent enquiry made by Dr. Ch'en regarding a report he had received that we were erecting a wireless installation at Lhasa. I assume that this rumour must have originated in the fact that the Tibetan Government recently indicated their desire to purchase a certain amount of wireless apparatus in India* The matter is now under ciscusaion: we feel that it is quite natural that in their remote geographical situation means of communication, and that it is only reasonable that we should give them what the Tibetans should want to possess up-to-date assistance we can in the matter*•\) Whitehall Tel. No.- VwC 9400. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to :— The Under-Secretary of State, The War Office, London, S.W. 1, and the following number quoted. 57/M.I./4142 (M.1.2) —, , f . r&gt; ( . , — v io'jd THE WAR OFFICE, &lt;jJJ LONDON, S.W.l. ^ ^ R 27th November, 1936. Sir, I am commanded by the Army Council to refer to your letter P.Z. 5977/36, dated 21st September, 1936, on the subject of the sw^ply of secondhand 1914 pattern .303-inch rifles to Tibet. 2. In reply, I have to say that, owing to the fact that there are no surplus stocks of these rifles available for issue, the Council regret that supply cannot be made to Tibet. y« I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, S. W. 1. E'iCLOSURC IH WEEKLY LETTER NO. 49 -3DE:C 19.36 j ( TOM SECRETARY, POLi.TCAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE ft *v ’ • &gt; 2 8 NOV 1936 L ,,-F.C£ 7&lt; s.FOREIGN OFFICE, E.W.l 17th November, 1936 (F 6844/4/10) Dear Walton, | The recent telegrams between Gould and Gimla about the supply of certain arms to Tibet (your last reference P.Z. 7606/36) make us wonder whether the Government of India are prepared to go ahead without sanction from London. It seems to us desirable that we should be consulted before anything is definitely settled. I suppose in any case any supply of arms would be subject to the conditions as to use for defence and internal order only which applied to earlier consignments. As the Chinese Government are liable to attack us on the subject at any time it is important that we should always be fully informed. t , , t ts NOV]$, J.C. Walton, Esq.,, C.B., M.OSECRET acp/fhb/yh (J¥t ) i COPIES CIHCULaTED ) (317 groups77 5143 DECYPH’ER Off TE^EG-RA S. From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department^ to Secretary of State for India repeating telegram from Gould. Dated New Delhi, 14th November,1936 Received 5 0 45 pom 0 14th November,1936 0 XXX 8672 Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Peking and Gould 0 My telegram No&lt;&gt;2546, 2nd November 0 Following telegram from Gould 18.1, 11th November, is repeated* B egins :- Z&amp;VS q Request instructions whether I should now inform Tibetan Government of result of protest* 2* To our diplomatic influence, Tibetans set no limit* Since the death oi the Dalai Lama, it is on our diplomatic support that they have chiefly- relied, and it was at our suggestion that their reiterated protest was forwarded through us. They will be apt to regard refusal of protest either as involving question of our good faith, or ae derogatory to our prestige* They will now want to know whether we can afford them any further diplomatic help ' n w * le m&amp; -tter of escort, Tashi Lama, and adjustment of Sino- Tibetan relations,(? or whether) they must fend for themselves. See paragraph No*8 of my express letter 7 (!) p 36, March 7th* 3* Question then for consideration is whether, in communicating result of protest, I can safely add that, notwithstanding Chinese reiusal to (? accept) it, His Majesty ? s Government will continue to extend diplomatic support lit the matter mentioned above* It would,of course, not be advisable to mention support unless there is prospect of it being effective* 4*/ #rr.I4-r, Gan I also, for encouragement of the patriotic party, be given materials for, at least, an interim reply on the subject of supply of guns, etc?* 5 0 Unless we can continue to extend support, outlook is not favourable 0 As time passed without news of delivery of protest confidence has tended to evaporate 0 With Regent, who has with him 2 out of the 4 of the Cabinet, temporarily withdrawn from affairs * owing to the death of his wife, it can hardly be said that there is effective government in being 0 It has recently been ascertained that last spring Regent, by threat of resignation, obtained from Rational Assembly and all officials an undertaking that they would unquestionably abide by his decision in all matters 0 In this connection aee my telegram 177 0 It is not inconceivable that, once they realise that Tibet must fend for itself, Tsarong and the Rational (? Assembly) might assert themselves and insist on active opposition to escort* But it is at least equally probable escort moy oe allowed to enter Tibet unopposed* '* Your telegram 2621, both Tsarong and Ngagcjfen have privately expressed hope that mediation in some form may yet prove feasible., ouspect that its rejection by Tibetan Government in July v/as due to Chinese influence, Bads.. Subject to comments of Ambassador at Peking,to whom '* 0ula ‘ s telegram Ho. 181 is being repeated, we suggest that Gould, ■while communicating result of protest to Tibetan Government, should oe authorised to assure them that our diplomatic support would contin to be oxertad. on this behalf with Chinese Government, Communication regarding supply of guns,etc.,will followMILITARY R300MMJ DAT I01T S TO BE ADS TO TES GOVERlT r ®T 05* TIEST. 1* The j^rifnery tesk. of the Tibetan arrry at the^present time is the protection of the Eastern Frontier of Tibet. The **de facto' frontier at the ;ao sent is|the line of the Yangtze River along the line (exclusive) Batang-( inclusive) Chiamdo- ( exclusive) jyekundo. 2 . it is understood that the Tibetan forces in Kham now comprise 9 regular and 11 militia or local regiments* and that these are located in many different detachments, possibly 20 detachments along the frontier. They have XL 1 mountain gun in good order and 3 doubtful ones* and six good lewis guns. It is further understood that a considerable portion of the above troops are not now with their regiments on the frontier but are at their homes on leave* a result of the peaceful conditions now prevailing. 3, From considerations of sound strategy it is unwise to have all the available troops extended along a wide stretch of frontier with no reserves behind to reinforce any threatened point. lUrther it is difficult to ensure that troops receive any training if they are scattered on frontier duties. Opportunity has been taken to make all possible enquiries regarding the condition of the Tibetan army* and an inspection has been carried out of those troops left in Lhasa* and of range practice with mountain guns and machine gunks. Although the shooting of the mountain guns and machine guns at stationery and non tactical targets was satisfactory; the Yifle shooting on which cnief reliance must be placed* deplorably weak, rws a result the conclusion is that at the present moment the Tibetan army is not sufficiently well trained either in the use of their weapons or in tactics of attack, and defence to enable them to resist a determined advance by an even moderately efficient enemy. The Tibetan Government has asked for advice and assistance in improving the condition and efficiency of its army.It is considered that the Govern jent should $ now that conditions are qu&lt;$/e| in Eastern Tibet, collect a body of troops at soue central place where they will be available to reinforce quickly any threatened portion of the frontier. e It is understood that jykundo was lost to the Chinese because Tibetan troops at jyekundo had to be withdrawn to reinforce a threatened sector further south. If a central reserve had been available this could have been used, and after successfully repelling the Chinese it could again have co.ne into reserve. It is too late to try to fom a reserve when the eiaergency has come, and it is too late to try and train troops T/tfien war has started. These things must be done beforehand in times of tranquility. The aim of the Government should therefore be to collect a reserve, and then give it thorough trainingpn the use of ail weapons, and in the tactics of attack and defence, etc., © fhen this body of troops has been ti^-oughly trained as a ’♦Chips de i 2 ilite M or *2jaimina paltan'S it should be possible gradually to improve the standard of the rest of the Tibetan regular army, by arranging periodical relief between units of this force and units in Kham. s^ch reliefs should also prevent any feelings of jealousy developing between the army in Kham and the in Lha ^. The first relief of one regiment should be after 2 years, and thereafter one regiment relieved every year. Considerations governing the size of this reserve, its armament, and the units comprising it are firstly the military tasks facing it and secondly questions of finance. It must be strong enough to deal with any enemy force likely to be met with on any particular line of advance. A nostile advance into Tibet is, by natural oostacles such as mountains or deserts, tied to some known route. It is considered that a force of about a mixed x-rlggste brigade of all arms should siffice to harass and delay any probable hostile advance, and finally aided by natural obstacles and-3- difficulties of supply and transport, bring it to a halt and perhaps defeat it decisively before it has penetrated far into .c^a st e ra t i oet • Financial considerations would preclude organising and training efficiently any larger force at present. It is therefore reco mended that a Brigade should be formed of the following units by withdrawing some regiments froi the frontier, *faile the strength of the frontier can be main tained if too many men are not allowed on leave at a time. Brigade Headquarters under a Depon with two or three Staff officers, or assistants, and a number of mounted orderlies and foot runners for carrying orders. Mounted infantry Company 210 men. Three regiments of riflemen (800 men each). One battery of mountain artillery (4 guns) 150 to 200 men. One ’'8 chine Gun Company of six machine guns and six Lewis gins, about 150 men. The machine and Lewis guns are separated from the Yif*le regiments, because it is considered very desoracle to mainta in the natural mobility of the fibetan tfifle regiment;. They are practically independent of transport, for tney can carry all their kit and rations for a number of days on the person. Their tactics should be to use their mobility by surprise movements on the flanks of the ®in route, j^acnine or Lewis guns can be attached when necessary. It is also essential to simplify the organization of training as much as possible, and to start with to aim at each commander learning a liiiiited task throughly. A mounted infantry unit would be invaluable in the norael Tibetan type of country, even on the Chang Tang. .phe location of this brigade is an importan t que stion, and the following points should be given full consideration before deciding the matter. Strategically it should be placed at some central place in Kham such as Chiamdo whence it is equally distant from any point on the frontier wiere an inva siorjfmay come.Ajzmuciticn at 6QQ0 rounds per machine gun and 4000 round® per Lewis gun should be provided, and aorzie old M drill purpose machine and Lewie guns for training. jaw armament and ammumition required after allowing for existing stocks is thereforei- Four mountain guns and 800 rounds of ammunition all common shell • Five new Vickers .SOS '©chine guns, and three (old) machine guns. Ten #30 3 Lewis guns, and three #D.P# l, (old) Lewis guns, rounds of •303 M.K# VII amnunition. The Tibetan Government have recently asked to be supplied with 4 mountain guns, 4 machine guns and lQ Lewis guns, but the numbers given above are recommended. (ii) Signal ^qu ipyient . The sending of messages and orders within the brigade must at present be done by mounted and foot orderlies at Brigade headquarters* But it is recommended that one set of wireless equipment should be provided to go with Brigade Headquarters in the fi«ld and another set at Lhasa so that rapid conmunication may be maintained. Additional 7//T sets would be desirable for communication along the frontier. 8 * T ra in ing . The aim of any assistance which the Government of India ir&amp;y offer in training the Tibetan army should be to produce suffieient linst motors within a year or two for the Brigade wnich it is proposed to forin* it must be recognized that it will be a matter of some time, perhaps 2 or 3 years, before this Brigade can be adequately trained. Therefore the sooner a start is made the better. The most important matter id|fo train good Commander®. The following are of first importance. One Depon in command of the Brigade. Two Assistants to him. One Depon for the J^ounted infantry Company.-—~ — &lt;5 rx Three Depons for tne rifle regi/nents. One Depon for the artillery battery. One Depon for the chine gun Company. A total of nine Depons* all of -ahoia, it is recommended, snould be Cra ined in India, preferably in fasiristan on the North west Frontier, where th^y could learn tactics eminently suited to their tash in Tioet, and inhere also the climate would bot be unsuitable for them. A Period of attachment to units of Ra zmak Brigade and to one of the faziristan Scout Corps is recommended; because the Counted infantry and to some extent the rifle Regiments would often be required to operate in similar manner to these scout Corps. It would be eminenly desirable for two Depons or one Depon and one junior grade officer to be trained for each unit, viz Counted infantry, Rifle Regiment, Battery, and M.G. Coy. If these were agreed to the total would be 15 officers and they might preferably be sent in two batches, of S and 7. ijiach batch woold require a minimum of 6 months and preferably a year's training. This higher training should aim at instilling the tactics and organization of a unit, and organization of its training, rather than detailed drill or weapon training; although some of this more elementary work will of course be necessary. In addition junior officers a nd N. C*0» * a should receive training in the details of drill, minor tactics, and weapon training. This might well be given in H cadre M classes held at Gyantse, if the necessary instructors can be provided there from the battalion finding the escort. Classes of 20 to 30 Tibetan lasting for 3 to 4 months should sdtffice. If possible three successive classes should be trained, i.e. to train 6 0 to 30 Tibetan junior ranks in the course of a year or so, who should be selected from-7- Mounted infantry. Rifle Regiiaente, and M.S. coy* This would provicte adequate Tibetan instructors for weapon training etc., in the units of the Tibetan Birgade. It night be found desirable to hold longer courses at Gyantse, i.e. 6 months# This could best be judged after they have started, or perhaps from knowledge of previous instruction given there 4 years ago. 9 • Important matters of military organization to which the attention of the Tibetan Govemruent should be drawn. If any good lasting results are to be obtained from the recoiiMenda tions set out above » certain principles of military organization and training must be adhered to, and the Tibetan Government is moist strongly urgfed to enforce them in the future. (i) Officers and other ranks selcted for training in India or at Gyantse snould be young, energetic and keen so that the Tibetan army may benefit fromtheir knowledge for sometime to come. Officers who have previously been trained in India ^ibuld if suitable go again. When they have been trained they nust be used at once with units of the army* and kept with the army for the rest of their official career, and not transferred to civil appointments. Spme of these officers snould algo if possible have had experience of the fighting in Khaia. They will lea m and appreciate tactics etc, far quicker. (ii) it is essential to pick a first class commander of the Brigade and first class assistants all with experience of fighting if passible* and to keep them with the Brigade for gay 4 years until it is throughly trained. (iii) i raining must be continuous throughout the year. Units must be kept up to strength, soldiers being allowed a fixed amount of leave, say 2 or 3 months in the year, soldiers must not be taken for coolies work, or a lot of guard duties. ( iv) Weapon training must be carried out anrery year,- 8 - 50 rounds per rifleuBn, 5Op rounds per laachine or Lewis gun # and 20 rounds per gun should be fired in practice every year* This will in the end save arununition on the battlefield. (v) Sfcdeavour should be tfiade to make the selected units the best in the army, with soldiers and civilians proud of them. The soldiers must be isell and regularly paid and well rationed. (vi) soldiers must be made to clean their weapons and keep them in good order. Daily inspection by N.0.0*8 and frequent inspections by officers are necessary. (vii) it is considered that the uniform adopted for the Tibetan army, as seen on the body Guard troops at Lha ga, is most unsuited for Tibetan soldiers and Tibetan conditions. The Wolseley helmet or •topi*. Khaki drill of inferior in quality, and British service ooots (not kept/good condition), is an unpractical dress for Tibet, and moreover difficult to supply in adequate quantities in emergency. he helmet especially is condemned. It is recommended that some Tibetan form of head dress should be introduced, home spun Tibetan cloth used for uniform, and Tibetan boots, easily obtained, be substituted for British boots. Lhasa, Tibet. The 8th September 19 36. Sd/- P. He a me. Brigadier General staffThe War Office, r Whitehall, s.w.i. ^ vS^' . '■'V7/M. I./4184 (M. 1.2) November, 1936. C\ i 4.1 Dear Reference your D*0« letter No. P*Z. 5977/36 dated 21st September. The delay in letting you have a reply is due to the fact that the question of policy as to the stocks of rifles to be maintained for our own War Reserve is under review. An official answer will be sent in due 3 course in reply to the official letter from the India Office, I am afraid it will be to the effect that no rifles are available. We quite realise the political importance 4 of meeting the requirements of the Government of Tibet and, as you suggest, they may claim that they should be accorded similar treatment to Afghanistan, but, as a matter of fact, the Afghans are getting all the second-hand rifles that can be spared and there are no more which can be regarded as surplus. H.A.F. Rumbold, Esq., India office, London, S.W.I.V 10/ Minute Paper. P.Z. 7828/36. POLITICAL Department. 9.1 ?a ^3oi+ ■i.i-, Mr. Walton, l Brigadier Neame made certain suggestions to the Tihetan Government for the re-organisation of their army, which have heen accepted hy them and, although the correspondence is incomplete, seem to be now under the consideration of the Government of India. There is, however, no indication that the Government of India contemplate consulting the Secretary of State in the matter. These proposals consist of: (a) The training of senior Tibetan officers on the North-West Frontier and of junior officers and N.C.O^’s at Gyantse, and the inspection of the Tibetan army at regular intervals by a British officer. This seems to go beyond the proposal to train Tibetan military officers in India, approved in the Secretary of Stated telegram of 21st May. In their telegram of 21st July the Government of India suggested that Mr. Gould should advise the Tibetan Government to re-organise their army and to indicate the readiness of the Government of India to ’’assist them with instruction etc., if they desire this for their fighting forces”. In our reply of the 30th July we said ”If proposed offer of military instruction exceeds proposal sanctioned in my telegram of 21st May, please refer matter to me before precise offer is made to Tibetan Government”. It is, however, suggested that we need not intervene. Ovv. (b) The supply'’of: 4, 2.75 mountain guns; with 800 rounds of ammunition. 4795 5000 5/86 5 Vickers machine guns. 3 old machine guns for trainingT * 10 Lewis guns. \oO i6,000 rounds of #303 aminunition. No rifles are required. We have completpd 'the supply of the arms promised to the Tibetans in 1921 (vide Lord Hood*s note at P. Z.5977/36). In view* however, of our statement to the Chinese in 1932 that no further arms will be supplied to thi Tibetans, unless the Government of India are satisfied that they will use them exclusively for self-defence or internal police work (P. Z. 24-999/32) and, your letter of 22nd October to Mr. Orde, ^P. Z. 7012/36) it seems desirable to make quite certain that the same conditions are * ^ ’• attached to the present supply to the Tibetan Government. A draft telegram is suggested in which the Foreign . . . Office concurrence seems desirable.I | lib &amp;■ 2323. Telegram XX No-2328 Dated 12th October 1936 From Fore ign, Simla. To Gould, Lhasa. Your telegram No.143 September 22nd. 7;e agree that private purchase should preferably be of British *303 rifles. 1914 pattern rifles not available here but inquiry has been made from His Majesty 1 s Government whether they oar* ' ^ ^ supply six rifles as desired by you. (X. I’.S. 7 . 3 . J.SJfiD. A.B.S.F. &amp; U.D.) X.B.2758. &amp; Telegram XI Nu.160 Df.ted (and reed) 9th October 1936. Trom Gould, Lhasa. To Foreign, Simla. My telegram No.158 of 7th October, paragraph (1). Iffould it be possible to consult Neame personally on subject of Lrospeotive military training ? Also see my telegram No.126 of 9th September, paragraph 4. Feature of policy is that Chinese Government is always extremely hospitable to Tibetans who proceed to China or who come into touch with them in any way. I think v;e should be prepared to meet all expenses uf Depons while they arc in India and also not only tc make no charge for training at Gyantse but also to contribute towards expenses of officers and men while being trained at Gyantse. Otherwise they are apt tc be a burden to local people. Neame would be able to roughly estimate jest. (X. F.S. D.S.F. J.S. J.S.FED. A.D.S.F. &amp; F.D.) M.E.% | sc? 2215. ielegnm XX No. 2215 dated 30th September 1936, From... .Foreign, Simla. Qould, Lhasa. XXK-S3S Your telegram No. 137 September 20th. Cost oi munitions required will be intimated to you as soon as possible together with earliest date of delivery. Meanwhile please clear following points (a) Only snrapnel and H,L, shell are now used with mountain t^urio but as fuze No. 106 supplied with H.E, is not considered safe for nandling by Tibetans Military Authorities suggest supply of shrapnel. Tnis can be supplied with fuzes of ’Time and percussion- type which are safe to handle. (b) Presume pack saddlery required with mountain gun, Vickers gun and Lewis gun equipments. (c) It will be necessary to consider carefully financial terms on which supply could be arranged - see Foreign telegram No. 1912. './hat are your provisional views on this uoint ? (X. F.3. D.3.F. J.S. J. FLj. A.D.S.F. &amp; U.D.) GrK.o FILE COPY Z. ! &amp; ^ IS! iv' 0.(JS3 | 7828 |. I !956 j 2612. 2 el eg ram XX* ? No. 143, dated 22nd (rood. 23rd) September 1936. From . * Gould, Lhasa. ( 2o Foreign, Simla. Y I have considered it advisable to recommend by post issue of export licenses for certain high officials in respect of Mauser rifles which they habitually prefer. 2. Reason for this preference is that Tibetan Government according to precedent set up by late Dalai Lama habitually confiscate service .303 arms and ammunition purchased privately even if pemit to purchase may have been supported by Tibetan G overnment. 3. For many reasons it would be preferable that as a general rule private purchases should not be of Mauser but of British .303 rifles. 4. Nov/ that Kashag have agreed with N earn a that Tibetan Government hold sufficient rifles for war purposes it is possible that I may be able to induce them to favour private purchase and retention of .303s. 5. Then I was at Simla I was informed that Government of India might be able to supply special pattern .303 rifle manu factured in 1914 and to do so as (?at) a very low price. 6. I request to be informed (a) whether such rifles can bo made available; (b) price; (c) whether they distinctly differ in appearance from rifles hitherto supplied to Tibetan Government; ig cartridges, as rifles held by Tibetan Government/ DGove rnment; (e) whether you could send me about six of these rifles at an early date for demonstration. These should he sent me care of Pangdatsang Kalbnpong for express delivery care of Trade, Gyantse, together with slings and 200 rounds of ammunition per rifle.aa— (COPY TO 1.0. &amp; PEKING). v AIR MAIL. *»««&lt;** ^ 2524. 1 a( C N , ][ , el e 6^^ XX No. 135 dated (and reed.) 14th September 1936. C£3- Fron....Gould, Lhasa. To Foreign, Simla. r I I 7 A'A ir-’v 5 / 'jMh V ^ It My telegram No. 126 of 9th September para. 3. After consult ing Kashag and Nearne have agreed to following as requirements of Tibet in arms etc: Four 12-pounder mountain guns complete Tilth connected, ecu ip-* ment. 800 complete rounds of aninunition all common shell. Five Vickers machine guns v/ith connected equipment. Three D P (old) Vickers machine guns for stripping and training. Ten Lends guns v/ith connected equipment. 160,000 rounds of ammunition mark VII .303 ammunition with chargers and bandoliers. Plea.se intimate cost of items and how soon delivery could be made at rail~nead after definite order is given. Two wireless sets also will be necessary but uhis question will be subject of s e parate c ommunic ation * (X. F.S. D.S.F, J.S. J.Sc FFD. A.D.S.F. &amp; U.Lh) GR. -NCLOSUW INDIA p W Letter Dal., n . .-J ill r .~l ^ ’• I O I '»• I Ov) 1 .2517. TZ. Telegram XX No, 132 Dated (olid reed ) 14th Septanber 1336. From Gould, Lhasa. Foreign, Simla. To PRIORITY. First business meeting with Kashag took place today. They said at this first discussion they wished to raise three questions, two of which being military they had given special precedence in view of Neame f s impending departure. They would raise further questions at subsequent discussions. 2. Questions were first Neame T s view and criticism re garding army, second supply of arms and ammunition, third Chinese escort and result of protest submitted through Govern ment of India. 3c Whole day was actually taken up with detailed discuss ion and explanation regarding first two points. Neane explained closely attentive and quick to appreciate suggestions, all of which they appeared to be prepared to recommend for adoption. 4. There is, however, reason to believe that it is in connection with third question that their minds are chiefly exerois ed. They propose to call me again very shortly for further discussions. I hope, meanwhile, it may be possible to reply to my telegram No.123. M.R.INDIA OFFICE, P.Z. 7012/ 36. WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 22nd October 1936. Lir My dear Metcalfe, Will you kindly refer to Orde’s d.o. letter of 28th September, No.F.5715/4/10, regarding two interviews with the Chinese Charge d'Affaires on 14 and 18 Sept., copy of which was enclosed with my air mail letter of 30 Sept, under No.P.Z.7012/36. A copy is enclosed of a letter to Orde dated 22.10.36. We should be grateful if the G. of I.could let us know their views on the question referred to in the last para., namely, whether it would be worth while trying, in due course, for a satisfactory treaty settlement with China regarding the status of Tibet, if the auguries were favourable. It may be thought that if Chinese suzerainty, which we recognise, over Tibet should ever become effective, an Anglo-Chinese treaty settlement might become desirable, not only to cover the question of our other interests in Tibet, but also the question of the Indo-Tibetan frontier which at present rests only on the basis of Anglo-Tibetan agreements. If this were considered desirable, we should perhaps wait for a really good opportunity such as might be presented by the Chinese Govt, raising the matter or giving some substantial indication that they are prepared to consider it. Given such an opportunity, we might perhaps, if the Tibetan Govt, agreed, refer the Chinese Govt, to the history of the previous attempts at a settlement and say that H.M.G. are still prepared to negotiate on that basis. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) J.C.Walton. A. Metcalfe, KCIE. # CSI.,MV0., Foreign Secretary to the Govt, of India, F. &amp; P.Department.f » a iS^ « INDIA OFFICE Y/HITEHALL, S.YY. 1. 22nd October, 1936. Dear Orde Will you please refer to your letter No.F.5715/4/10 of 28th September regarding Tibet? We entirely agree with the line which you took with the Chinese Charge d’Affaires. 2. We suggest that, if Dr. Chen returns to the charge as regards arms, he might be told thatwe hold ourselves free to meet requests from the Tibetan Government for munitions in accordance with the statements made to the Chinese Minister on 26th August, 1921, by Lord Curzon (Foreign Office despatch to Peking No.824 of 26th August 1921) and to Dr. Chen himself on 4th October, 1932 (Foreign Office despatch to Peking No.822 of 10th October, 1932j. We have, of course, completed the supply to the Tibetan Government of the quantities of munitions promised to them in 1921; but these statements to the Chinese cover any further supply to which we might agree with the same conditions as in 1921 attached. It appears that the Tibetan Government have discussed the question of the supply of arms and ammunition with Gould (his telegram of 14th September to the Government of India which was among the papers sent to the Foreign Office with India Office letter, P.Z.7095 of 8th October). 3. I enclose copies of telegrams from the Government Government of India telegrams ) of India regarding our relations Nos.2208, 2209, 2210 of 30th ) September. ) with Tibet. Our information does not lead us to question the Government of India's view that Foreign Office, S. W. 1.2 . lb 0/ (iS it would be extremely difficult to secure a resumption of tripartite negotiations, and a fortiori to obtain a satisfactory settlement, but we should be glad to know the opinion of the Foreign Office on the point. Dr. Chen’s expression of regret that there is no regular arrangement regarding Tibetan matters and involving China as a party is perhaps interesting in this connection. But I suppose that it would be a mistake to take Dr. Chen's remark too seriously or possibly as applying to anything more than such matters as the supply of munitions. As regards the view of the Government of India expressed in paragraph 3 of their telegram 2210 it may be best to leave the question of the Sino-Tibetan frontier to be settled by usage. But apart from that particular question it might perhaps be a matter for consideration whether a satisfactory treaty settlement of Tibet’s status might not be worth trying for (in due time and not of course in connection with Gould’s present negotiations at Lhasa) if the omens were favourable, i.e. if there were some real indication that the Chinese Government were ready to resile from their negative attitude of 1932-3 (as regards the status of Tibet as distinct from the question of the Sino-Tibetan frontier), and if the Tibetan Government were willing. I enclose a copy of a letter which we are sending to the Government of India requesting their views. Yours sincerely, (Sd.)J. C. WALTONJGS/DIA. li j 4S4X a DECYFHER OF T E L E Prom Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegrams addressed to Foreign and (COPIES Sikhim* CIRCULATED) Dated Simla, 30th September, 1936 a Received 30th September, 1936, 5-20 pemo X IMMEDIATE. 2308 c Following from Gould, 126, September lithe Here insert text of my telegram No u 22G9o Ends Following from Foreign to Gould, 2158, September 23rdo Beginso Here insert text of my telegram No*22i0o Ends( It* 2 ' - SECRET JGS/XJC/IT/EB/AW. (334 grouts) — J 4348. DSCYPHBR OF TBLSGRAM. From Government of India* Foreign and Political Department* to Secretary of State for India* repeating telegram from Political Officer* (COP IBS S licit inu CIRCULATBD) Dated Simlaj 30th September, 1936, Received 30th September, 1536, 7 o 30 p s m, XXX IimSDIATJS. 2209, While I have not yet been able fully to at explore the general position/Lhasa, I am of opinion that time has arrived when we should re-examine general line of our policy, particularly as regards our apparent attitude towards China. 2, Since 1914„ this has been largely in form of supply of arms afforded sic (? affording) Tibetan Government facilities for maintaining some sort of (? equilibrium) on its eastern frontier. While the autocratic Dalai Lams, was alive and was the main executor of (? a) policy and so long as the Chinese were entirely preoccupied with their own affairs, a sort of quo was achieved. On the Dalai Lama 9 s death, military affairs were entirely neglected. Heame 5 s two telegrams make it c'ear that at present the Tibetan Government have no troops which would be likely to give a good account of themselves in face of even a moderately efficient enemy. 3. Dalai Lama s autocracy being dead, many more influential minds, both monk and lay* now give active ooxisi derat ion to the study of policy. Soundest statesmen of Tibet fully realise the value of British connection* but they realise also that the ultimate aim of Tibetan policy must embrace good relations with China. 4. m regard to the Tashi Lama, our known willingness to- w' \ . to face hia return has produced good political impression* Manner of his return continues* however,, produce many difficulties, 5* A few months ago Tibetans were inclined to be soared of communists and contemptuous of Chinese, Today, Tsiang who was left by Huang Masung, appears to enjoy considerable prestige, it is probably through his intermediation that Regent nas agreed to accept from the Chinese Government &amp; great gold seal of office which would probably be brought by Tashi Lama, 6, In such general circumstances^ question which emerges is whether His Majesty’s Government could find it convenient to open with the Chinese Government question of the settlement of the points in dispute between the Chinese Government and Tibet, 7, Principal matter on which 1914 negctiations broke down was rivalry of boundary claims. In recent years, position of stalemate has become established approximately along the line the °f/Yangtze, Recent communist events indicate that this is the line up to which ooth China and Tibet are able to make felt such power as they have, whether against communism or each other, b. Ox Chinese attitude in regard to any negotiations I have no information* As regards Tibet, they have experience of many miseries and anxieties which resulted from failure to agree in 1914, We are now, I thiiik, in a position to exercise considerable pressure to induce them to accept reasonable frontier line, 9, The most urgent single matter of present time is return of Tashi Lama and avoidance of major complications in connection with hia return, I can think of nothing more likely to be conducive to hia return under reasonable conditions than •-hat his happy return should be associated with a fresh attempt to reach settlement on all matters of large importance.“ i 7066 : j o o I bM: SECRET JRIi/VH (1^8 groupso) 4549 (COPIES CIRCULATE j ■DEC T ? H iC R OP T Jii L B a R A M. From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India re-^a' i a;- telegram addressed to Gould Dated Simla, 30th September,1936 0 Received ? 0 45 pom, 30th September,1936„ IMMEDIATE, XXX 3SIQ 0 Tour telegram Ho 1SS, 11th September 0 However desirable it may be to resume tripartite negotiations with China and Tibet with Government of India representing His Majesty { s Government as mediator, Government of India must point out that there are likely to be extreme difficulties in any such course 0 You are aware in 1932 Marshal Chiang categorically refused even to consider any such suggestion, see correspondence ending with Foreign telegram to Sikkim Ho 0 736 of I&lt;th arch, lv33, Hanking Government have recently had considerable success against Canton leading to accretion of prestige, and Government of India have no reason to believe that strong views expressed by Chiang in 1932 will have been modified 0 (?2) (? On these grounds) an approach could not in any case be undertaken without obtaining consent of Tibetan Government who do not appear to have raised the subject 0 In this connection please see paragraph 2 of Secretary of State ? s telegram 2244 of 30th July 0 3 0 Government of India consider that question of Sino- Tibetan frontier can best be settled by stabilisation on the basis of status quo rather than by almost certainly unfruitful attempt, to fix boundary by means of negotiations,,I&amp; 5 P.Z. 7013/36 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1 (F. 5716/4/10) 28th September 1936 Dear Walton, With reference to India Office letter No.P.Z.5977/36, of the 2nd September, the Chinese Charge d'Affaires called on me on the 14th September and said that his Government had heard that we were agreeing to supply arms to Tibet. He asked if this was true, and if so would we desist? I said I would see whether the report was true, but reminded Dr.Chen that after the Simla Convention we had promised to supply arms to Tibet in reasonable quantities and on certain conditions as to their use. I could certainly give no assurance that we would not act in accordance with any undertakings we had given. Dr.Chen then referred to a request he had maae in 1932 for a copy of the agreement of 1921 with Tibet. I made no promise, but I have, of course, no intention of giving him a copy and will if he returns to the charge repeat the language used to him in 1932 (Foreign Office despatch to Peking sent to the India Office in copy on the 11th October 1932). 2. Dr.Chen called again on the 18th September and asked whether I could reply to his representations of the 14th September. I said no, and that I was not yet aware of the facts. I reminded him, however, of our statement to the Chinese Government in 1921 that His Majesty^ Government would hold themselves free to deal with Tibet as an autonomous State under Chinese suzerainty, and observed that we had in the past agreed to supply Tibet with arms in reasonable quantities and on certain conditions - a fact of which I thought the Chinese Government were already aware (they were in fact informed/ J.C. Walton Esq., C.B., M.C., India Office S. W. 1.informed in 1932 if not earlier). I pointed out also that Tibet had to get arms - possession of which could not reasonably be denied to her - from or through India, which necessarily involved connexion of the Government of India with any transaction owing to the strict control exercised by them over the arms traffic. I also observed that Tibet and India were neighbours who had to deal with each other whatever the Chinese Government felt, and that it was impossible to expect India to subordinate all her dealings with Tibet to the wishes of the Chinese Government. Dr.Chen expressed regret that there was not a regular arrangement affecting these matters and involving China as a party, to which I retorted that China had had ample opportunity and that it was her own fault that further negotiations had not taken place when she had failed to ratify the Simla Convention. 3. As Dr.Chen is likely to return to the charge I should be glad of your views as to anything further wnich should be said to him. Yours, &amp;c.. (Sgd.) C.W. ORDEAir an copy to CONFIDENTIAL 2494. • 0 ; ^ c '°^ v Telegram XX. No. 126. Dattd—Ciofe' XfiCiL.)' 10th September 1936. - from Gould, Lhasa. ^ To Foreign, Simla. Reference my telegram No.122 of September 3rd. Following are Nearness considered views which will be communicated to Tibetan Government by him or by me if and when they ask for them. 2. Recent inspection of Tibetan troops has confirmed views given in telegram of September 3rd. 3. At present practically whole of Tibetan army is strung out in a series of small very loosely controlled units along eastern _(? dispositions) frontier. In view of weakness of such depositions^iibetan Government would be well advised to create central reserve consisting of mixed brigade of all arms to be located at Chamdo or Lhasa. This can be done by concentrating some of regiments- now in Kham while frontier defence can be maintained under existing political conditions by keeping units up to strength. Brigade should comprise mounted Infantry, Infantry, Artillery and Machine Guns. New armament requirements correspond closely with that already asked for by Tibet but two or more wireless sets in addition nay be wanted. 4. If Tibetan Government accept above proposals training of officers and non-commissioned officers will be necessary in order that this reserve may be formed into an efficient fighting force. Senior officers should be trained on North-West Frontier where cl climatic military conditions suitable to Tibetan requirements. Waziristan is suggested. Junior officers, N.C.Os. should be p— - trained/- HNCL08URE JN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S2494 . trained at Gyantse if battalion regular escort can provide instructors. Example of this central Brigade should in time pernete rest of army and increase its efficiency. 5. It is essential that Tibetan Government should raise standard of morale, discipline and contentment of these selected troops by means of good regular pay and rations, moreover certain principles of organisation and training must ae adhered to which are at present neglected such as annual allotment of ammunition for weapon training etc. 6. Finally Heane is strongly of opinion that Tibetan Governments higher military authorities are not capable at present of carrying out these or any proposals tor improving their army without outside help in form of inspection and advice at regular intervals by a suitably qualified military officer. LDlH3f fhj Lll/i JitAi-l Copy se'nt to Pekir ' A g. fa. '/ ; ^ 0 0-1 Ou 1 ' J 93 c &lt; 1^ f + U 1 fa 2427. Telegram XX No. 122 dated (and reed.) 4th September 1936. From Gould, Lhasa. To Foreign, Simla, iji/ is/, x {&gt; v\ 3 J s' »L I* iMGriiGb pr el in inary appreciation ol condit/ion oi Tibcitan army is as follows, iioetars as a nation are absolutely non-military and tlie chough gs and energies oi ruling classes are largely absorbed in ieligious matters. Lama officials share all authority with civil ai'ia military Oxiicials. Tibetan Crovernment and officials concerned with army have absolutely no idea of sound military organisation« administration or training. The two Commanders-ibi— Chief one Lama, one military, have no military experience* They correspond perhaps to War Secretaries, Depons or Generals are appointee from nobility with no military training f ?and) no regular soldier of experience can rise beyond rank of Hupon lower grade commissioned officer. i i be tan official hierarchy are ind.iscrimina£;~ elv moveo mom civil to military appointments regardless of their qualifications in fact those Tibetan officers who were trained previously in India were in nearly all cases put into civil appoint ments nctning to do with army on return. They have now forgotten neaily all they learned in India. Instructors trained in machine guns at Gy antso 4 years ago wore never employed again on machine guns until this year and in consequence are now incapable of instructing. e. T deld training is practically never carried out troops Doin^ employed in time oi pea.ec' on coolie work for Government• ENCLOSURE iN INDIA FOREIGN SEORETARY^ J Lettor 1 C CKm. | Dalat J n c p d Range/-2 . 2427, Han^o practice with guns, machine guns or Lewis guns is never carried out and with rifles very seldom in consequence troops cm- on plcyed/active service in East Tibet are incapable of firing with effect and waste much ammunition when in action. Care and cleaning of weapons believed to be very poor. Opportunity going to be given to No (me) to inspect mid watch some firing. 3, State of armament as follows 1 Mountain gun in good order and 3 bad in East Tibet 2 good 2 poor and 2 condemned in Lhasa 4 machine guns in good condition and 2 poor in Lhasa are being used to train 300 machine gunners who on completion of training will be sent to Gyantsu or to regiments in East Tibet, There are 6 good Lewis Guns in East Tibet one with each of 6 regiments and 2 Lewis Guns in Lhasa, 5,000 ,303 rifles for mark 7 ammunition Core with regular troops in East Tibet, 500 with bodyguard in Lhasa and 4 ; 000 in store at Lhasa. 4. Location of troops. Nine regular regiments in East Tibet, 2 strength about 1,000, 2 about 600, 5 about 500, but it is believed that largo proportion, about 75 per cent are on leave at their homes. This is apparently normal custom in peace to save rations. Only about 5 regular regiments believed to bo trustworthy and. ,of staunchs there are also 11 regiments /militia embodied in East Tibet each about 500 and armed with old .303 rifles for mark 6 ammunition and foreign and old Tibutan guns: these 20 regular and militia regiments are believed to be strung out in some 20 detachments along do facto frontier, the Yangtze river from approximately west of Batang to west of Jyekundo. Th only other regular troops are bodyguard 500, Machine gunners 300 under training in Lhasa and a very/-3 \n\ 2427. very few regulars on No peal border. All other districts of Tibet depend for internal security on local levies with ancient guns embodied by local Governor as and when situation demands. o. Under the late Dalai Lama some attempts were being made to improve training and organisation and armament was definitely improved by his obtaining arms from India. On his dea,th all military activities ceased and army deteriorated. Some attempts are now being made to improve matters but under present guidance with little success. 6. In Nome’s opinion it is justifiable to say that except for fear (?fact) that Tibetans possess certain number of modern weapons which few know how to use efficiently 5 condition of their army has advanced little since 1904 when Tibetcan force of 15,000 (or ?) more were unable to resist advance of some 2000 infantry of Indian Army supported seldom by more than one or two guns r 7. The value to be obtained from training Tibetcan Officers at Gyantso or in India will depend on whether KasjJLig can in future bring some method and continuity into the training of troops after return of such officers. Unless this is done progress will bo small and very slow. Hocommendations -as to training and organisa tion are now under consideration. (X. F.Sc D.S.F, T Q J • u . FED. A.D.L.I’. &amp; U.D.) G-R.6./ P.Z. 5304/36. CYPHER TELEGRAM PROM SECRETARY OP STATE, ADDRESSED TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, FOREIGN &amp; POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, REPEATED TO HIS MAJESTY’S AMBASSADOR, PEKING, DATED 30th JULY 1936. XXX (No.of words: 198 &amp; 200) IMPORTANT. 2244. Addressed to India repeated to Peking. Your telegram of 21st July, No. 1640. Tibet. His Majesty’s Government approve generally proposed instructions to Gould subject to the following remarks. 2. As the Tibetan Government have contrary to expectation refused offer of mediation, original and primary object of visit has disappeared. Whilst therefore Gould should give the best possible advice on subjects which Tibetan Government wish to discuss (see paragraph 2(a) of your telegram) he should not press advice on Tibetan Government on matters which are not in the first place raised by them. 3. if proposed offer of military instruction exceeds proposal sanctioned in paragraph 6 of my telegram of 21st May, No.1599, please refer matter to me before precise offer is made to Tibetan Government. 4. As regards British representation at Lhasa., please see paragraph 3 of my telegram of 17th August 1935, No.2623. Gould should be cautious in sounding Tibetan Governmen; regarding permanent representation. 5. in general, main object of Gould’s visit appears to me to be that it offers favourable opportunity for exploring general situation in Tibet. In the light of his report you will no doubt consider question of further offers of material assistance on the lines suggested in the last paragraph of your express letter of 13th April, No.F.l-x/36.4 2. 6. Peking Smbassy are being requested to inform Tashi Lama’s representative of latest developments as suggested by you.FCK/DIA. '' o CT 7 . z ' | 5266 (1ST groups ) IQ” 13 17^ SECRET &lt;s&gt;' 3313, DECYPHER OP T E L E G R A M&lt; /N Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Government of India,, Foreign and Political Department,, to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla, 21st July, 1936&lt;, Received 21st July, 1936, 9~’30 poin^ V V V 1640, ( ? Pirst of Three Parts ) ✓x/aav Addressed to Secretary of State for India, and repeated to Pekingo Our telegram of the 15th Instant, 1581* Tibetan situation, t 2* Tibetan Government have now given Norbhu (a) Cordial oral invitation for Gould to visit Lhasa immediately for short time to give advice on various subjects not (? specified). (b) Sealed letter addressed to Huang IJusung for transmission to Peking. Copy has bean furnished to Horbhu and summary of translation will be telegraphed separately. It contains strong protest against Chinese officials, or single Chinese officer or soldiers entering Tibet with Tashi Lama, (c) Categorical oral statement that they do not desire His Majesty's Government ? s intervention in settlement of dispute with Tashi Lama, which is matter of Tibetan internal affairs. They refer to promise made in 1929 by the Viceroy that no such interference would be made, and claim to have sent deputation to Tashi Lama to bring him back to Tibet,FWJRI/M. (132 groups.) 3314. SECRE1' D,E CYPHER OF TELEGR A H„ (COPIES CIRCULATED) and Politioal Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 21st July, 1936. Received 10.43 p.m., 21st July, 1936, XXX 1640. Part two c Noibhu aiso reports that the Tibetan Government are now reassured as regards communists who have gone off northwards 0 Kefusal of our intervention may s we think, be attributed to optimism induced by considerations noted above, and by the knowledge that the Chinese Government are heavily engaged with domestic diftioultiesc Fresh incident, which may also have inspired decision, is that large consignment of rifles, ammunition and bombs, has just been discovered in advance baggage ot Jashi Lama, which has reached Nagchuka* This event has revived Tibetan suspicions of Tashi Lamars true intentions and may make chances of settlement more remote c 4c After discussion with Gould, we are satisfied that invitation to visit Lhasa must he accepted in spite of this eleventh hour reiusai to accept our intervention in T&amp;shi Lama negotiations,, We are therefore instructing Gould to telegraph acceptance and to start as soon as possibleo He will leave Gangtok about 31st July./- ee/it/dia. SECRET (180 groups) 33l5o (COPIES CIRCULATED) »-E^JLP H E R OP TELEGRAM. Et’oni Government of India^ Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India* Dated Received Simla, 21st July, 1936, 21st July, 1936, 10-30 p,m. — XXX 1640, Third and Last Part . To meet the somewhat altered circumstances, revised instructions are necessary and we recommend, &lt;a&gt; that he sh ould explore situation generally, advise the Tibetan Government against over optimism, and impress upon them the need for strengthening their own position by making peace with Taehi Lama and l ^organising their arity and finances. He should also I indicate our readiness to assist them with instruction, / Ptc ”' , it ‘ they des ire this for their fighting forces. I He wil1 also discuss the possibility of arranging free transit through India for Tibetan Imports . (b) No formal message should be sent to Tashi Lama by uould at present, but Peking Embassy should inform Tashi Lama : s representative there of present situation, particularly of our efforts to facilitate his return and of formal Tibetan protest against Chinese escort. Explanation of bombs and rifles might also be asked for from that representative and suggestion might be renewed -hat if Tashi Lama wishes to return through India, all suitable arrangements will be made by Government of India. Had Norbu not been in Lhasa* (? we should have) remained in complete ignoranaa (? of these) important developments. which— 1-77 which (? emphasis?;) necessity of some permanent contact with hhasao We think* therefore* that Gould should he instructed to examine this question also* without committing use (sic* v us) to any final decision*P.Z. 3075/36, SECRET. CYPHER TELEGRAM PROM SECRETARY OP STATE ADDRESSED TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, FOREIGN &amp; POLITICAL DEPARTMENT REPEATED TO HIS MAJESTY’S CHARGE D’AFFAIRES, PEKING, DATED 21st MAY 1936. XXX (No.of words: 813) IMPORTANT. 1599. Your Express Letter of the 13th April, F.l-X/36. Tibet. His Majesty’s Government approve proposals generally subject to following observations. 2* In order to refute Chinese Government's assertion that they have received no objection from Lhasa about Chinese escort (Cadogan’s telegram of 2nd April, 36-Tour), Norbhu might urge Tibetan Government to repeat their objections to escort and official in a letter to the Chinese Government which Government of India could forward to Peking Embassy for delivery at Nanking. 3. His Majesty's Government agree with suggestions in paragraph 3 of Howe’s telegram No.40 Tour of 2nd May (which was in answer to Foreign Office telegram summarising your proposals and asking Howe’s comments). It is desirable both vis-a-vis the Chinese and also the Tibetan Government to safeguard ourselves so far as possible from any imputation that we are undertaking an undue initiative in intervening. Ii you concur in this view, it will be necessary for Norbhu to obtain letter from Tibetan Government as suggested by Howe, inviting our mediation, and also that in such letter they should themselves express their present attitude, viz: (as indicated in Gould’s draft) that, if the Tashi Lama dispenses with Chinese escort and official, they agree to restore fully to him the position and possessions which he enjoyed before he left Tibet and are anxiously awaiting his return./2. (Ifl return. Their letter might also suggest that any differences as to outstanding questions can he settled after his return. Eventual letter to Tashi Lama would embody the letter of Tibetan Government. 4. His Majesty’s Government agree that Gould should endeavour to mediate settlement of present dispute and are ready to give him discretion regarding tactics. They consider, however, that we should avoid undertaking to guarantee any settlement reached, and that responsibility for its maintenance should be limited to provision in it that both parties will accept our mediation in any future dispute arising out of settlement (between Lhasa Government and present Tashi Lama, i.e. undertaking would terminate on death of Tashi Lama). Letter to Tashi Lama should therefore be amended to convey (a) offer to endeavour to mediate a settlement and (b) willingness, if the Tibetan Government agree, to assist disposal of any disputes arising out of it by means of mediation. 5. I am not clear whether you contemplate that such offer to Tashi Lama should be made dependent on his first returning to Tibet, but this point is left to your discretion in consultation with Gould. 6. His Majesty’s Government agree that we should be prepared to offer Tibetan Government free transit for goods and training of Tibetan military officers in India, and will consider sympathetically further proposals foreshadowed in paragraph 7 of your letter.V* vV^O ^G^fc&gt;tXA^ 5 ( L ^^erv^y lz£jls '^ tr ^ ^' &lt;&gt;L&amp;^0£^cA^ / 3^fc^. ( F~ I — . C j&lt;fi^) Minute Paper. TZ. Ill'S/Si*. Department. G. You will observe that this oaani&amp;icatlou involves our S ^V tafcin^ considerably iuore active part in the negotiations th^ta has hitherto eeen suggested, should the i‘ibetf.vn Government agree to its is -ue *md the Tushi Lama accept the oiler it would be necessary lor Geulcl to go to Lhasa and probably beyond. He would, have to intervene actively in bringing the parties to terms and would also undertake on behalf of His Majesty^ Government some responsibility lor seeing that t^ie agreement was not subsequently broken by either party. As regards the negotiations he could probably induce the Lhasa Government to make further concessions by offering them favours such as free transit of goods through India to Tibet and training of Tibetan military officers in India, both of which we ore prepared to consider favourably, as regarde guaranteeing any settlement arrived at we ore not unmindful of attitude of His majesty*e Government as stated in paragraph 2 of your telegram Hc.hGHS, da.ed 17th August, 1935. But we think that securing of settlement on these lines would justify assumption of reasonable responsibilities by His Majesty^ Government and Government of India as guarantors of settlement and that it should be possible to bring great i-ressure on both sides to observe agreemBnt. Tseng i.revince of which Tashi Lama would obtain control adjoins our frontier, and statement by us that Government of India would refuse him asylum in India in the event of disagreements ^ith Lhasa Government due to non-obsorvance of agreement, should go far to prevent broach oi agreement by Luma, rer contra Tibetan Government are so anxious to retain goodwill of Government of India that threat to withdraw diplomatic support should in itself suffice to secure observance by Lhasa of terms of agreement. There are also other method* of bringing pressure on Tibetan Government e.g. suggestion that arms or precious metals will not in future be supplied on favourable terms, or that trade concessions e.g. free transit for goods consigned through India to Regent would be withdrawn.^ Minute Paper I political Department. n, h»\ c (q ( tCtfo'i (^J* r ' I. In an agreement embodied in an exchange of letters between Sir Charles Bell and the Dalai Lama in 1921-22, the Government of India undertook to grant the Tibetan Government facilities for importin^rinunitions in instalments, for use solely for self-defence and for internal police work. The amount of munitions was specified as follows 10 mountain guns (v/ith a reasonable amount of ammunition) 20 machine guns 10,000 rifles 1 million rounds of small arms ammunition annually. It was originally contemplated that this quantity should be imported as follows First Year . Each s ubsequent year for 7 years. 3 mountain guns 1 mountain gun 6 machine guns 2 machine guns 3,000 rifles 1,000 rifles 1 million rounds of small 1 million rounds of small arms ammunition. arms ammunition. whilst ^the ammunition for mountain guns was to be supplied on the basis /X of 100 rounds for each gun in the first year and 50 rounds for each gun each following year. ‘/N.B. This arrangement gave rise to some confusion, which, so far as our papers show, was never really straightened out.J X Things did not, however, work out entirely according to plan; probably, chiefly because the financial position of the Tibetan Government did not permit them to import arms in such quantities. At the beginning of 1932 the Tibetan Government had received four instalments (the last having been handed over in September 1931) totalling 6 mountain guns 12 machine guns 4,500 rifles 3,200,000 rounds of s.a.a. 2,550 rounds of mountain gun ammunition. *N.B./ 4424 5000 1/36( ^N.B. This amount was considered at the time to be the total quantity available to the Tibetan Government under the 1921 Agreement; ^ the term 'reasonable quantity' was subsequently interpreted more liberally - see below. 3. In the Summer of 1932 hostilities broke out on the Chinese Tibetan frontier, and the Tibetan Government accordingly addressed a request to the Government of India for a considerable supply both of arms and ammunition. In partial satisfaction of this request, the Government of India supplied:- 4 mounta i n guns 8 machine guns (4 Lewis and 4 Maxim) 1.500 rifles l4- million rounds of s.a.a. Mountain gun ammunition: 1500 rounds of common shell 500 rounds of shrapnel 1,000 bombs The Tibetan Government's request was probably entirely independent of the 1921 Agreement; but it will be noted that the amount actually supplied by the Government of India did not exceed the balance of arms and ammunition to which the Tibetan Government were entitled under the 1921 Agreement). It was therefore possible to inform the Chinese Government that the arms supplied to the Tibetan Government represented a part of the arms which the Government of India had agreed in 1921 to supply. 7. In 1933 the Tibetan Government put forward a further request for arms and ammunition, but the Government of India only supplied the quantity of rifles and small arms ammunition still outstanding under the 1921 Agreement, though they added a further supply of mountain gun ammunition. ; , It will be seen, therefore, that the promises made in 1921 have been completely, and, in fact, liberally, substantiated; and there is no room for including any further supply which the Tibetan Government may request within the terms of the 1921 Agreement. When the explanation/ £xce^(‘ J or ) 4fff/ Sz4424 5000 1/36 Minute Paper Department. explanation referred to above was given to the Chinese Government in 1932, they were assured that no further arms would be supplied unless the Government of India were satisfied that the Tibetan Government would use them exclusively for self-defence or internal police work. Provided, however, that these conditions are satisfied, H.M.G. have a free hand to supply arms to the Tibetan Government. It is new part of our general policy towards Tibet to grant the Tibetan Government reasonable assistance in the protection and development of their country. The Chinese Government were so informed in 1921 / when H.M.G. made their declaration to the Chinese Government that they intended to deal with Tibet as an Autonomous State, if necessary, without further reference to China. It is not, therefore, open to the Chinese Government to challenge our right to enter into any arrangement with the Tibetan Government in such matters as the grant of facilities for the import of arms and ammunition.\ 4599 5000 2.36 Draft Paper. Department. DRAFT r\ u.s.s., 0 . / 21 SEP 1956 x 0 ^ Alfl MAIL *-&gt;- • • - 22 SEP 1936 ENCLOSURE ! NO. 3 9 FROM SECRET A Y, PCLITIOM AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA CFFltE 21 SEP 1936 LETTER. CONFIDiiNTIAX. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India dated 7th August regarding a question of the supply of second-hand rifles to Tibet. The Secretary of State would be glad to be informed f^LZ&amp;h^ whether a supply of 1914 .303 rifles L such as has been offered recently to the Afghan Government could be made available, if the Tibetan Government should request a supply of munitions and if H.M.G. and the Government of India should decide that it would be politically desirable.to undertake the supply. 2. With regard to the second paragraph of the Government of India's letter the Secretary of State would be glad to learn whether, in view of the special interest of H.M.G. in the maintenance of stability in Tibet, the rifles could, if available, be supplied as a special case on reimbursement of out-of-pocket expenses only. (Sd.) H. A. F. RUMBOJnD4794 5000 5.36 , Hn$ &lt; *W ‘' L ^ 3f6-A. j- h. informed at an-early ante whether a supply of 1914 .303 rifles such as has been offered recently to the Afghan Government could be made available should imj G. of -l.- deciiie to undertake the supply. In this connection'T^&amp;m to invite a reference to the correspondence under War Office Kro.fVH^4/fiP.ia M.T.P.- 2 . of the epcnl.osedr letter the s/S would be glad to learn whether, in view of the special interest of H.M.G.in the maintenance of stability in Tibet, the rifles could, if available, be supplied as a special case on reimbursement of out-of-pocket expenses only. With regard to the second para. V * enclosed:f By Air Mail. CONFIDENTIAL V NO.F.340-X/36. ^ / / From The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and political Department, To The Secretary VO.JL J 9 Political Department, India Office, LONDON, S.W.l. k Dated Simla, the y August 1936. SUPPLY OF ARMS AND AIVlvUNITICN TO TIBET. Sir According to the information received from the Political Officer in Sildcim the Tibetan Government may wish to be supplied with more arms and might be content to purchase out of date models, or second-hand arms. The Government of India are not yet in a position to estimate their requirements, and the question of policy will require consideration before any offer can be made. Meanwhile, they will be glad to know 1914 .303 whether ^rifles could he made available as offered to the Afghan Government. 2 . If available, it would greatly facilitate any transaction if such rifles could as a special case be provided at out-of-pocket prices rather than at the price quoted to the Afghan Government. I have the honour to be, $y% Co******' Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.r BY AIR XUL 225 ( Tole gram R. No. 31 Dated (and reed.) 26 th August From, . • • .Political, Sikkim, Lhasa. To .......Foreign, Simian At a private interview yesterday Dalai Lama asked me to move Government of India to permit Tibetan Government to pay cost of munitions now under issue ( vide your Express letter dated June 8th No. Fol-X/33) by annual instalments of Rs. 1,00,000. His Holiness stated that although he had no intention of taking any aggressive measures in Khaim, he was compelled to maintain large force there in case of possible Chinese aggression. If litet were in possession of Derge supplies for the troops could be arranged locally, but that Province is now almost entierely in Chinese hands and supplies for the troops have to be sent from Lhasa etc. at great expense. Dalai Lama is anxious to pay earlier if position improves. I enquired whether under the circumstances he wanted all small arms anmunition promised. He replied that he did as, in view of Chinese protest last ENCLOSURE IN &lt; |tirx.. year at supply of munitions, he thought it best-2 to obtain them in peace time and to be prepared against possible eventualities* Only possible means of raising the money earlier was curtailment of religious expenditure which would be most impolitic® I strongly reconmend request be granted expecially as it is a personal one from Dalai Lamac Payment of balance due for all previous consignments is being arranged at once. Government of India o.re aware that there has been delay amounting to years in payment for previous issues and same will probably occur in present circumstances even if we ask for payment at once. Approximate cost calculated on previous figures amounts to about Es. 7 lakhs. I would request a reply by telegram as His Holiness is anxious for me to give him answer personally. Favourable answer will ho-ve great effect in increasing good feeling towards us. ( X. J.S. )MPft 2217 • / Telegram XX., No.2217, Dated 9th September 1933. From......Foreign, Simla. To Political Officer, Sikkim, Your telegram No.31 of the 26th August. Munitions for Tibet. Since Government of India have to make payment for supplies at time of delivery they propose to finance purchases by means of loan. Consequently whole amount due from Tibetan Government for present consignment will be treated as loan on which &lt;v interest at 5 per cent per annum will be changed® Precise amount recoverable will be communicated as soon as possible. Please obtain concurrence of Tibetan Government to this proposal. To enable Government of India to calculate total amount of principal plus interest and number of instalments please telegraph whether one lakh annually is maximum Tibet can pay. (X. J.S.) BLBY AIR MAIL. From To FILE COPY Govern^nt of India. Foreign^ and jp^rtical Department 3753 ' Express Foreign, Simla, Political, Sikkim. No.F.l-X/33. Dated the 8th May June 1933. Tibetan munitions. Reference correspondence ending your letters Nos. 3(3)-P/33 dated 31st March and 6th April 1933 respectively. In view of correspondence in 1932 in regard to the supply of arms and ammunition to the Tibetan Government (vide papers forwarded with endorsement No .F. 123-X/30 dated 2nd August 1932) the Government of India consider that it would be inadvisable to supply to the Tibetan Government at present munitions in excess of those promised in 1921. Arrangements are therefore being made to supply the following as soon as possible ^ 4,000 rifles, 2,950 rounds SJcauA mountain «un ammunition and ^ 37357• 57 1 rounds s.a.a* Supply of s.a.a. ammunition will commence in July at 1 million rounds per mensem to be completed in October 1933. » r . t ij•.- if : -CO The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd. f.K.Fraser-Tytler, q\ | , m . K.'TlLiW.IDSS Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, 2 j i!)N.1933 jCopy to India Office &amp; Peking. v 7 Letter from the olitical Officer in iiikkim No*3(3)-P/33 f dated Gangtok, the 31st March 1933* No.22, I have the honour to invite a reference to my telegram dated the 10th March 1933. 2. The question as to whether the Dalai Lama had issued orders for the recapture of Derge and of Targye Gompa seemed of such importance that I caused further enquiries to be .ade on the subject from the Dalai Lama privately. The latter states that, although Derge is a very productive district and rations for his troops in Eastern Tibet could be more easily obtained there than elsewhere, he has carefully refrained from issuing such orders and that the allegation that he has done so is entirely baseless. He adds that negotiations with the Koko Nor Chinese are in progress and that he has no intention of taking tne offensive. He is issuing further strict orders to the same effect, in view of the advice of the British Government contained in your telegram No.736, dated the 18th March 1933, the contents of which I duly forwai*ded to him. 3. Under the circumstances I do not see any reason id' refusing to supply to Tibet the further munitions which they have asked for.for seven years, of tills total, the Tibetan Government have already received 6 mountain guns. 12 machine guns. 4.500 rifles. 2,550 rounds of mountain gun aiimunitlon. 3,152,429 rounds small arms umnunition. They are therefore still entitled to receive 4 mountain guns, 8 machine guns. 5.500 rifles. 3,847,571 rounds small arras aimnunltlon. (bj In 1932, owing to trouble with the Chinese In Eastern Tibet, the Tibetan Government asked for 8 mountain guns. 8 Lewis guns. 4 iuuxim guns. 1.500 rifles. 3.500 bombs* 1,000,00o small arms arnuunitlon. 2,000 rounds shrapnel, 3,000 rounds common shell, a demand which they required as quite separate from and additional to the quantity promised in 1921. in partial compliance with this request, they were supplied with 4 Lewis {pans. 4 machine guns. 4 Mountain guns. 1.500 rounds coirmon shell. 500 rounds shrapnel, 1000 bombs, l^j^ UQU ro unds anall arms suonunltlon. 1,500 rifles. The Tibetan Government now ask that the balance of31 of these munitions should he supplied to them in addition to the bounce of those promised in 1921. The balance of their 1932 request is 4 Mountain guns. 4 Levels quits. 2.500 bombs. 1.500 rounds cannon shell. 1.500 rounds shrapnel. 4. If their demands are compiled with in full the following nunltluns will h»ve to ba suppliod:- 8 Mountain guns. 8 Machine guns. 4 Lewis guns. v... &gt; 3,ott?,b7i rounds aoull arms rinmunitlon. 2.500 bombs. •'* / ' 1.500 rounds comnon shell, 1,500 rounds shrapnel. a-' 5. In requesting that I my be favoured with the &gt; orders of the Government of India in the matter, I would point out that if the Tibetan Government’s demands are not complied with in full, they are certain to renew than constantly, and will not be satisfied that we are giving them proper support. I would therefore suggest that, if tdnqt are no strong reasons to , \ the contrary, their renuest may be granted in full, especially as it seems quite clear that the ^resent aggressor in the Sino-fibetan trouble is China. 2 have the honour to be, air. Your most obedient servant. Sd/- F. Williamson, Political Officer in siick-imdU t Translation of a letter from the Directors of the New Peerless Tapchi lectricFactory,Lhasa, to Lieut-Col nel « T *L. v.?/eii* f Political Officer in ikklm, dated t e 4th day ul \,!i6 loth raon'Ui of the *titer-^fonkey Year (corresponding t( the 1st scomber 193^.) Ve have received a report from Ka-dron Yutok Oe, who if receiving training in the use of machine £un at Oyantse, to the effect that among the arms and ammunition,which were purcriased from the Covermr^nt/ahd taken over and brought up by Upon DingJa,there were four old njachine guns,which were' replaced by four new ones. Three soldiers v/ere sent to Ph* to take tiiem over and to bring them up to Gyantse. These along with 10 boxes containing accessories and two tins of oil, have reached Gyantse. On the 25th day of the ^th month (23rd November 1932 &gt; arltl8h Tm,e at Yatun « 8nd i r y;mtse and the Officer Coraandlng opened them and handed them over to ta-dron Yutok 3e. r rhou f h Hie ^uns were provider! with all necessary accessories, yet the following, vhich era indispensable accessories for .1503 Vickers machine guns, trn lacking Clinometers. Rang* Finders, eflector Mirrors, lielt Plugs. Director. Telescope. Spare liarrel liases. A quantly of saddla soap and number of sponges. 4 2 4 4 1 1 4 I ve would request that ycm,excellent Lonehen, will kindly as the Government of India to arrange for the supply of these J rSarly dsite. Unless the cost of the above Is included in the munitions brought up by Mpon Dingja, we will arrange to pay irmediately on hearing from you. Usual ending. Deal of tie Directors.Translation of a letter f^om the Ministers of Tibet to Lleut-Colonel J.L.1. .eir. Political Officer in iikkira, dated the 22nd day of the 10th month of the tvater-f onkey Year (corresponding to the 20th December 1932.) During the Incumbency of Sir Charles Bell as the Political Officer in dikklm, the groat British Government undertook to permit the Tibetan Government to export, on payment, a certain number of mountain guns, machine guns, rifles, with aranunltion, for the defence of their country. Again, recently, His Holiness specially requisitioned, by telegraph, for some amunltion, machine guns and bombs. ,Ve would now request that you will kindly arrange for the immediate issue of the balance of these munitions, be have made the Directors of the New Electrical Factory at Tapchi responsible for the payment of the cost of these munitions j and they ere making arrangement accordingly. Accepting the great British Government, in whom our hope is centred, we have no one else to look to for help and assistance. There fore, if, in future,also we need more mountain guns, machine guns, bombs, rifles aid ammunition, we will communicate with you. lie hope that you will, on receipt of our requisition, arrange for the immediate supply of our requirements, be would request you, excellent Lonchen, to submit through the Government of India, to the great British Governraent a renori in our favour so that we can achieve our ends. 1 lease let us have a reply to this letter as early as possible. Usual ending. Beal of the inistar ; of ibet.IT/KM • (51 Sro'^t n h 1 . r: y P H £ R 0 P From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India (COPLiB repeating telegram to Political wiiicei, CIRCULATED) Slfeicim. Dated New Delhi, Hth March, 1933. Received 11 th March, 1933, 3.30 p.m« 670. Addressed Political Officer, Sikkim, repeated to Secretary of State for India and Minister at Peking. Following from British Trade Agent, Gyantse. Begins. Following for Political Officer, Sikkim. Begin s. Boring Teji has received a letter from Lhasa to the effect that Dalai nama has sent orders to Tengong Shape in Kham to try to re-capture Darjye Gompa and Derge. No additional troops appear to have Been sent. There had been rumours of this before. I have no grounds to suppose it has been put about deliberately but am making further investigations. Kn&amp;s. In view of above, please furnish further comments with reference to your letter No. 3 (3) P 33, January 11th, regarding arms for Tibet.HOo89?, (P 7lnl/7/10) POKE I UN OPPIOE. li.V.l. 10th Ootobar f lH5^o Bith roferenoe to the first paregx*eph of your telograsi No* 618 of the £n&amp; September, regarding the supply of ©me by the Government of India to the Tibetan Govoriuaont, I have to inform you that the Chinese aounscllor called on the 4th October end repeated a reciueat i?hich he had mad© some time previously that ho might b© given a copy of tphat he called the treaty* of 1981 between the Government of India ami the Tibetan Government* T)r* Chen vacs informed, in reply* that there tree no treaty* only a little correspondence which was not considered suitable for communication to third parties* He wee reminded of 2‘Ord Cnpj?on e Q intimation to the Chinese Minister in 1NP1 to the effect th?t f unices tho Chinos© Government were prepared to resume negotiations with Tibet within one month. His Majesty*e Government would regard themaolveB ©t liberty to give the Tibetans any reaeonabl© assiatance they xiight require in the development end protection of their country* (SJee Lord Gorgon 1 * despatch &amp;o*8&amp;4 of the £Cth August 1981)* The Tibetans, it vaa continued, had been informed subsequently that they vould bo permitted to import ariTffj in instalments ©t adequate intervals on p^ymenta on condition that they were used only for police purposes and for eelf-defence* The Tibetsne naturally sought these firms in India rather then in Knrope and tmti to buy them from the Government of India as there was no other source of supply in India* The matter was really e^in to the perniseion which Ingram „ fSsq* , 0.B, H ., etc*, etc*, ©to*. Peiclngowhich had bean given to Chinn herself on oocaolon to Import ama through India or Borina» I am# with gre*t truth» Sir t Tour obedient Servant, (For the Bearetorjr of state)SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, Tjetter Telegram from Register No. fz Dated Rec. 19 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. — — SUBJECT. To n h a i T’m a n The Tibeto-Chinese Dispute. * Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... Enquiry by Chinese Legation as to our Agreement of 1921 with Tibet regarding munitions. V ‘ lyj a ^ Copy orl to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft d.o. letter to Foreign Office suggesting reply to Chinese Legation. Af/rM fy.0. UXr tiv Previous Papers :■ 4475a 1000 5.30Minute Paper. Department, ’‘h* Please see Chungking telegram of 24th August (P.Z.5150/52). The boundaries of outer and inner ! Tibet are marked in red on the map flagged in the volume and the approximate course of the Teichman line has been marked in blue ink on that map. It , will be seen that the Chinese capture of Derge ; robs the Tibetans of territory to which they are entitled under the Teichnan Agreement and that they are now thrown back almost to the boundary of outer Tibet, while Chamdo, on which the Chinese are reported to be advancing, is an important point far to the west of the boundary of outer Tibet, i.e. Tibet proper. i, On the other hand it will be noted that the j* Chinese General has stated that he does not intend to advance bevond Chamdo and we may hope that China J is not in a position to undertake large conquests on anything like the scale of her successful occupation of Tibet, including Lhassa, in 1910. Please see also Mr. Orde f s letter of 24th August below. The Agreement of 1921 was, in fact, the first fruits of the policy of granting Tibet reasonable assistance in her protection and development which we had announced to the Chinese Goverrment as a consequence of their failure to resume tripartite negotiations regarding the Tibetan question (see the !' X telegram to Pekir^ of 27th August and Lord Curzon’s y despatch of 26th August). | It does not seem either necessary or desirable to give the Chinese a copy of the embodying i the 1921 Agreement, but Dr. Chen could be informed 401)0 3 32of the purport of the arrangement about the arms^which does not go further than what he has been told already^ It is submitted, however, that if-the Chinese appear to question the autonomous status of Tibet or our right to deal with it as !; an autonomous State^ thev should be reminded of the communications made to them in 1921 and that we should not be'deterred by the fear of raising controvers-ial questions. Our immediate object is to bring about the cessation of hostilitieSjbv presenting ourselves in the role of o* disinterested mediator in order to prevent Vito Chinese suspicion^(Incidentally the prospect of success in this role does not appear to be very bright), ‘But our efforts to avoid alarming Chinese suspioions should not go so far as to pass over any suggestion which they may make that Tibet is not an autonomous State with which we are entitled to enter into agreements regarding such matters as the supply of munitions. JvDraft Paper. !0 DRAFT LiETTSR. isi: St$0 ^ Department. 51952 C.W.Orde, Esq.. C.M.Cx., Foreign Office, S.W.l ENCLOSUR IM W r,/ 'Y ! FTTER No. 235. 1 SER11932 FROM i C!. ITA’Y, TOLITIUaL and 8 EGKE 7 DEPT. INDIA OFFICE 904 4000 5.32 Many thanks for your letter of the 24th August No.F.6311/7/10. *•. The 1921 Agreement regarding the supply of munitions to Tibet is comprised in the documents which you quote. We do not think * i * that copies of them should be supplied to the Chinese Minister. 2 We suggest that Dr. Chen might be informed that the purport of the Agreement in regard to the arms was merely that the G-.of I. permitted the Tibetan Govt, to import munitions in instalments on payment for use solely for self-defence and for internal police work. Some stress might be laid on the words K a CL 'on payment'. Thoro io-r of naurse^ no reason why one State i* should notr-bc granted facilities^ as a matter of business arrange ment for the importation of munitions-^n the territories of another State. Tibet might purchase the arms in India from o 9 • private sources, if there were ary, but it happens that in India •m /no one except the Governnent is in a position to sell arms. Or Tibet might purchase the arms in this country or elsewhere and have them imported through India. You will 1$&lt;JL o notice that as a matter of fact tte V} (l . if) t Agroemoiftt says nothing about the arms being supplied bv the G.of I. In this connection please refer also to para. 4 of G.of 1 1 s telegram of 30th July last which shows that facilities are forth coming on occasion for the importation of arms by China through India 4jbhe case a£/the importation through Burma w-i4-l probably come to ne thing, but this-“is becauoo the-^ firm oone o mod., Messrs. Arnhold^^ ctro not- likely -tro tro prcparod^go' if '/'ll t ^ j &gt; C througl&gt; DumaK ^ The Sinkiang case referred to is that ©f importation of certain munitions from Europe dealt with in the correspondence ending with o^r*^ dated /? M ^ ^ suj- i ^ rJi Cert* ^ Pi *) ^ You will remember that the Agreement of 1921 was made in pursuance of H.M.G.’s policy of granting the Tibetan Govt, reason able assistance in the protection and/Draft Paper. IxH &gt;y &lt;.AVWJ * Lc*J&gt; t 7'^ ^ ~~ IV C**H n t CLj,a. -VwO lt*t Department. and developmeiTb of Tibet. This policy was adopted largely because ■iL KlcJ’n^i t+ rf'* 1 *2^ CU-+++ of the disappointment of the hopes of a pe-newel of the tripartite negotiations regarding Tibet. You will no doubt have referred to the lengthy correspondence of 1921 which eventually led to the action y-o, authorised in yotrr telegrams to Peking Nos. 284 and 285 of 27th August 1921, and Lord Curzon*s action described in his Despatch No.824 to Peking dated 26th August 1921.-) ^ We informed the Chinese Government in writing that in view of the circumstances (including the fact that they had accepted, with C the exception of the boundary Clause, the Draft Convention of 1914 providing for Tibetan autonomy under Chinese suzerainty) we intended to recognise the status of Tibet as an autonomous State yCU** and to deal with her on that basis in future; we further informed them orally that.our future dealings 1)04 4000 5.32 with Tibet might include, £Fe giving £ £ '7&amp;4U/a»vi ^ /of 'anv reasonable assistance they may require in the development protection of their country ,, . If, therefore, the Chinese should/should now return to the charge regarding the arms in a manner which in ar*r way implies that we are not entitled to deal with Tibet as an autonomous State, we suggest that their attention might well be drawn to the communications made to them in 1921 # Though v/e may not /1 JO f-y SUs* want at the present juncture^^fboe drawn into controversy regarding the status of Tibet, it would seem very undesirable to pass without challenge any suggestions by the Chinese that Tibet is not ^ autonomous ^ 4u (AfT t* UvA* .-vA uU ^ ^ av/wA *&gt;. . Yours sincerely* (Sd.) J. C. WALTON.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] 0 Decypher From CHINA Mr. Ingram, (Peking), 24 th Augus t P 1952 O -s' o Da R j 10ol5 aoiiio 9.50 a^mo 24th August, 1952 24th August, 1952, No,588 — 0~0~Q'~Q — Following sent to Foreign Office, India and Mission, Begins:- Following received from Chungking No*8. August 22ndo Begins Your telegram N0o7*. Chinese have captured Derge and Tibetans have evacuated all territory east of Yangtse* Chinese reported to be advanev/ ing on Chamdo* Unconfirmed rumour states that Tibetans have captured Batung, General Yu Sung^li has stated he does not intend to advance beyond Chamdo for fear of complications with Great Britain considering probably the possibility that fall of Chamdo may lead to complications between Szechuen and Kokonor forces- In advancing beyond Tej^line Tibetans appear to have been the original aggressors (see His Majesty’s Ministers 1 despatch 1449 of 1950 to Foreign Office and my despatches . — 'if ^ 5 and 15 of 1951) 0 Chinese appear to have been responsible for reopening hostilities this year but they appear to have been forced to anticipate Tibetan attack (my despatch No*30)« I have at present no evidence that Chinese forces are acting under the authority of the Central Government. Ends* Z'-'X* &gt; FOREIGH OFFICE, S. W. 1 24th August, 1932 (F 6311/7/10) With reference to my letter Ho, F 6141/7/10 of the 16th August I write to say that Dr. Chen oalled again on the 17th August and was told, in compliance with his request, of the instructions which had teen sent to Ingram regarding the reply to te made to the Chinese Government*a representations about the supply of arms to Tibet, He was also told that His Majesty*s Government were anxious to do what they properly could to help to compose the dispute and that Ingram had been instructed to offer the general good offices of His Majesty's Government with this end in view. Before leaving, Dr. Chen asked if his Minister could have, for his information, a copy of the 19B1 agreement between the Government of India and Tibet. I imagine that the 1921 agreement was comprised WEEKLY LETT r 2SAU5. ml /in Nc J.C. V/alton, Esq., C.B., M.C. TARY, POLITICAt A t DEPT. INDIA OFFICEin Bell's letter to the Dalai lama of the 11th October 1921 (sent to us in India Office letter No. P 5241 of the 5th December 1921) and the two declarations of the Tibetan Government of the 9th and 14th May 1922 respectively, regarding the use to which the arms would be put, enclosed in Bailey's despatch to the Government of India of 27th May 1922 (sent to us under cover of India Office printed letter No. P 2794 of the 7th July 1922,) As these documents have presumably never been published there are very probably objections to our giving copies to the Chinese Minister. I should be very grateful if you would let me laiow what reply we should return if the request is repeated. I should add that Dr. Chen told me later that in the Chinese Minister's opinion the offer to mediate would be politely declined.OOF „ _ _ \\ / f A 1 &gt;v Ur a- [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] To CHINA* \ *a \J ZJ Cypher telegram to Mr. Ingram (Peking), Foreign Office. 17th August, 1932 No, 173 «&gt; v Q &lt; ^ 2 0 5 p.m Addressed to Peking No. 173 Repeated to Government of JndJ.a No, 12 0 Your telegram No. *552 (of 13th August). Please inform the Chinese Government in the first instance, in response to their representations, that the arms at present being supplied to the Tibetan Government mere'ly represent part of the arms which the Government cf India agreed to supply in 1921 for use only for self-defence cr Paternal police work, and add an assurance that no further arms will be supplied unless Government of India are satisfied that Tibetan Government will use them exclusively for these purposes. You should then take occasion to make representa tions in the sense desired by the Government of India (see Government of India telegram of 10th August, 1775), In doing so you should bear in mind the danger that the Chinese Government may make the present situation and your representations an opening for raising contro versial matters regarding the status of Tibet. It is important that you should if possible avoid discussions cf this question and therefore your representations should be as general as possible. You should lay stress on the friendly desire cf His Majesty’s Govern ment m the uii.ooo u* ngtorn unci me Go v e ri'iiiient oi in mu to offer their good offices with the object of arranging an armistice and preventing further fighting, avoiding any2 might call in Question the claims of the Chinese Govern ment to suzerainty over Tibet and deprecating any ■ ... i ! n 4- anxious to see achieved. There v/culd on the other hand be distinct advantage in referring to the 1918 precedent as you suggest. You should inform Chinese^ Government that Colonel Weir, Political Officer in Sikkim, is proceeding to Lhassa at the invitation of the Tibetan Government and that he will use his influence solely in the direction of a restoration of peaeec Plea.se instruct His Majesty’s Consul-General at Chungking to report by telegram, repeating to Government of India, any available information regarding future v developments and the present situation with particular reference to the possibility of ascertaining which side was the aggressor and whether the Chinese forces are acting under the authority of the Chinese Central Government cBy Air Mall. a Oi i- s t it rj q o 1706 o Telegram From . . To . . . R. No. 6.,dated (and recd.)27th July 1932. . . .Ingram, Peiping. . . .Foreign,Simla. y t/ Following received from Mission at Nanking, telegram No. 280 dated July 25th. Your despatch No.358. Head of European Department of Wai-Chiao~Pu called on me yesterday to say that Chinese Government had information to the effect that Government of India had recently received a request from Tihetan Government for purchase of supply of arms. He understood that arms had not yet been supplied and ((gr.corrupt? expressed?) strong hope that Government of India would refuse to consider request. I refrained from any comment and simply replied that I would communicate message to you. (X. &amp; U.D.) F.A. U'UUjyUHf: IN ! INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S Lotter No it ti Q M. j Dated 6 AUd 1932 | Beceivea \ / AUG, iB32 IRegister No. Pz °/k i l SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT letter Telegram from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To ( Uiai nnan If. J % T I E LI: Representations by Chinese Govt, regarding supply of arms by the Under Secretary Secretary of State... (Jommittee Under Secretary Secretary of State... Copy of ,/ to / / //.%. £ Cj. // s FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft letter to F.O. suggesting reply 6 aug Previous Papers :■ 4475a 1000 5.30Minute Paper.. Political Department 777 4000 3 32 The total quantities of munitions, now being sent to Tibet appear to be - P.Z.4277 4 ten pounder guns ii 500 rounds ten pounder shrapnel common P.Z.3661 and 4277 shell it 1,500 •' u P.Z.4277 4 maxim guns 4 Lewis guns P.Z.3661 P.Z.4277 1,500 rifles 1,500,000 rounds S.A.A. P.Z.3661 and 4031 It has apparently now been decided not to send any bombs. Colonel Weir's letter of 6th June (P.Z.4277) states what the Tibetan Government are still entitled to under the 1921 arrangement. The arms now in course of supply are covered by the quantities outstanding under that arrangement and leave apparently 4,000 rifles and a large amount of S.A.A. still outstanding. Though in principle there is no reason why munitions supplied for self defence or internal police work should be limited to quantities promised in 1921, the fact that the present supply is within those limits may make matters easier for H.M.R.Peking. Another line which he might take would be to make a counter enquiry as to the position on the Tibeto-China border. Peking telegram of 2nd June referred to the Chinese having captured Kantzu (Kanze) and Chawa whereas the armistice reported in Chungking Despatch No.7 of 25 January, 1932 provided that the Kanze and Chantui Districts should be temporarily occupied by Tibetan troops; we should not therefore accept the suggestion that the Tibetans are the aggressors. Since/Since the alsove was written we h?ve received it Col.Weir’s new r s report of 27 June and the G. of I's telegram of 30 July. From the former it appears that (while in one area aggressive action was taken by the Tibetans contrary to the wishes of the Dalai Lama who has called the commander responsible to account for it) it is the Chinese who have attacked in the Kanze area where at the close of-hostilities last autumn Tibetan troops were in possession of Kanze, Chawa and Chantui. TU ^ A/)h 'iA W' ♦ • • • • £ Ht / ^ CHo\. Csvu, , v ^ ^ , (^r OZ /V4vw ^ ^Cyyx^, *0 J ' T-,t, 7-\Draft Paper. I. L ' ri J &gt;4x Department. ENCLObU ic IN W v/ - rrtu No. 232 11.Alfli 193? FROM SfcCRETARY, POLIilU^L ANO SECRET DEPT, INDIA OFFICE ^ 6 AUG 1932 Sir, With reference to your letter of 30th July, No. F 5854/7/10, regarding, the supply of arms to the Tibetan Govt., I am directed by the S. of S. for I. to forward copy of a telegram which has been received from the G. of I. on this subject. It will be remembered that the G. of I. were informed that H.M.G. have no objection in principle to the supply of munitions to the Tibetan Govt., provided that the G. of I. are satisfied that they are to be used solely for self-defence or internal police work. It will also be seen that all the arms and ammunition now in course of supply to the Tibetan Govt, are included in the quantities which the G. of I. are committed to supplying under the arrangement entered into in 1921. 3 It is observed that H.M.R., Peking, in his telegram of 27th July, No. 508, refers to the present (^Tibetan/ campaign against the Chinese authorities. There appears, however, so far as information is available, to be no justification for any suggestion that may be made by the Chinese that th Tibetans have been the aggressors in the/ 904 4000 5.32the recent fighting. Mr. Ingrain* s telegram of 2nd June, No. 309, referred to reports to the effect that the Chinese had captured Kantzu and Chawa, whereas the armistice reported in Chungking despatch No. 7* of 25th Jany. last, provided that the Kanze and Chantui districts should be temporarily occupied by Tibetan troops. Prima facie . it would appear that the initiative in the recent fighting was taken by the Chinese, and it will be seen that the reports received by the G. of I. are to the effect that the hostilities are entirely due to Chinese aggression (compare para. of Col. Weir’s news report dated 27 copy, of which was forwarded to the F.O. with 1.0. letter of 2 nd August, No. f* ^ ). 4, Secy. Sir Samuel Hoare would suggest that Mr. Ingram might be instructed that if the Chinese Govt, press the matter, they can be informed that the munitions now under supply to the Tibetan Govt, are part of a supply which the G. of I. undertook to make m 1921, and also that he might question any suggestion that the Chinese may make that the Tibetans have been the v fi j 1 a ' pi 5 '7?/^ ^ ' aggressors in the recent fighting. It/i)04 4000 5.32 Draft Paper. -T.It might also be desirable to instruct H.M. Consul-General, Chungking, to report any information , /available regarding the hostilities, and which may tend to show whether the Chinese or the Tibetans are the aggressors, and whether the Chinese forces are acting under orders from Nanking or under those of some semi independent authority in Szechuan. (Sd.) J. C. WALTON. Department.FHB/LJS/MM [ 23 5 Ci -&lt; o l (IB^'groups) O.JS-X.P H.J,,P ■0_F TELEGRAM. 7. SECRET 4028 (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, to Secretary of State for India, Dated Simla, 30th July, 1932. j$7] Received 10.0 p.m. 30th July, 1932./^ XXX \ di: ISMa Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Peking. Peking telegram 508, July 27th. Simply of arms by the Government of India to Tibet. 2. All arms and ammunition are being supplied to Tibet on payment, end are included in quantities promised i/hs a in 1921. .After the supplies now ordered have been completed ohere will still be balance due of 4 f 000 rifles and about 3,000,000 rounds S.A.A. 3. Care has been taken to obtain express undertaking irom the Tibetan Government that such arms and munitions will be employed solely for defence end not for aggression. Reports received here are to effect that hostilities on Tlbete-Chinese border are entirely (? due to) Chinese aggression, and we consider in these circumstances that we are bound to fulfil our promises made in 1921 to Tibet. Failure '•o do so would not only alienate Tibet, but would drive them to obtain munitions from Russia, 4. Lastly, if the Chinese Government suggest that we axe showing special favour to Tibet, in order to enable them to attack Chinese territory, it might be pointed out that 'She Government of India has recently agreed to grant facilities for import of arms both by the Chinese Go vernmen t through Burm a and by the Sinkiang Government through India, so that there is no discrimination ± n favour of Tibet/ ~415—21102 • y ;■ FT any further communication on this subject, please quote ■ No. FftsU 'll ft A - &gt; ? -7 ^ / s —not to any persop by napte, but to—' L } l* and address —not to any persof by liafae, but to—' i'he Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, 8.W. 1. q THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents bis compliments to &lt;rl^ / t^ r ft ^oUa. and, by direction of tne Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop»^&amp; of the under - mentioned papers for such observations as sS t/. &lt;£&lt; &lt;AfCTfiA*-' may desire to offer. Foreign Office, U 3 -' rji Reference to previous correspondence : J c.e^ r.?..M7h°t J ^ 3 ’* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. (ff. fW (ajc^mo otyy^ Subject. / to CJ &lt;AxA' as* oi JoAj Ipk »/ 1 v • t- T i Similar letter sent to enclosure IN No. 5 32 IF AUG. W'’ FROM StCRETARY, POUn^-t AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required f&lt;&amp; official use.] From CHINA c Decode. Mr. Ingram (Peking), 27th July, 1932. D. 27th July, 1932. R. 8.00 p.m. 28th July, 1932. No. 507. (E). Following received from Mission. Nanking telegram No. 280 July 25th. Your despatch No. 358. Head of European department of Waichaopu called on me yesterday to say that Chinese government had informa’oion to the effect that Government of India had recently received a request from Tibetan government for purchase of supply of arms. He understood the arms had not yet been supplied and urged strong hopes that Government of India would refuse to consider request. I refrained from any comment and simply replied I would communicate message to you. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY ' Mo. 5 32 11 AUG. 193P FROM l ORtTARY, POLITICAL AND SEC ! r DEPT. INDIA OFFICE[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for offici Decypher No. 508 From CFIHA . Mr. Ingram (Peking). 27th July, 1932. Do (ViaW/T, ) 27th July, 1932. R. 8.00 p.nio, 28th July, 1932. Mr. Holman’s tologrum No. 280, I understand certain quantity oi arms have already oeen supplied. As regards these we should I presume main main that they represented hajance of consignment promised in 1921. If, however, any further munitions of war are supplied from Government stocks we could hardly defend ourselves against the charge of arming Thibet in the present campaign against the Chinese authorities. According to latest reports through Ciiungking active hostilities are still in progress and Chinese press openly states that Thibetans are receiving arms from the British Government. I should he glad of instructions as to what reply to mane if tne Chinese Government press the matter 0 Ao.dressed to Foreign Office No. 308, repeated to India and Mission,From \ /j ‘ &gt; 7 7 Lieut-Colone^ /L. Political Officer in Sikkim, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* Dated Camp Yatung, the 6 th June 1932. Supply of munitions to the Tibetan Government. aie 4: s|e + 4c ^ 5|e ^ ^ 3it jj: ^ jjc Sir, In continuation of my telegram of 28th May 1932, I have the honour to forward translations of two letters dated the 16th May and 27th May respectively sent to my address by the Tibetan Government. 2. The arms to which the Tibetan Government are entitled on payment are:- 10 mountain guns n with a reasonable amount of ammunition”. 20 machine guns. 10,000 rifles. 1 , 000,000 rounds of small aims ammunition every year. They have already received 6 mountain guns. 12 Lewis guns (including a gift of 3 /ewis guns from Government of India). 4.500 rifles. 2,550 rounds mountain gun ammunition. 3,152,429 rounds small arms ammunition. 3. They seem therefore still entitled to ask for and receive from us 4 Mountain guns. 8 Machine guns. 5.500 rifles. 4. The present request of the Tibetan Government is£• for 2 Mountain guns with 500 Shrapnel and 1500 common shell. 4 Lewis guns. 1500 rifles (with bayonets). 1 , 000,000 rounds small arms ammunition. In addition the Lalai Lama requests (vide my telegram No.3(10)-P/32., dated the 23rd May 1932) the following:- 6 Mountain guns and ammunition. 4 Lewis guns and ammunition. 4 Maxim guns and ammunition. 3.500 Bombs. The combined total of these comes to 8 Mountain guns. 8 Lewis guns. ( 4 Maxim guns. 1.500 rifles. 3.500 bombs in addition to Mountain gun and small arms ammunition. This exceeds the original amount to which the Tibetan Grovernment are entitled by 4 Mountain guns f 4 Machine guns, and 3,500 bombs. 5. From the information available, it is clear that the quantity of Mountain gun ammunition wliich was originall; decided as sufficient for the Tibetan Government is not adequate for their self defence against the Chinese on their Eastern border. One hundred rounds per gun the first year and 50 rounds for each gun for each following year provides a meagre supply of ammunition for actual fighting sifter any rounds have been expended in gun3. practice, I would suggest that the original decision he now waived, 6 * I recommend that the Tibetan Government be allowed to receive at a very early date:- Mountain guns. 500 Shrapnel shelllfor mountain gun. 1500 Common shell. / 4 Lewis guns. 4 Maxim guns. 1500 rifles. 3500 bombs. 1 , 000,000 rounds small anas ammunition. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- J. L. R. Weir, Lieut-Colonel, Political Officer in Sikkim. L.D.Sraosl&amp;tlon or a lotto? from the Mlnioters of Xlhot to Lieut-Coloael J 0 L 0 E* w®ir $ rolltloal Offloor in Sikkim, dattfxi the 11th dear of the 4th month of the !tat 0 ?&lt; 4 iO£Uc 0 y Year (eorresp Gliding to the 16th Hogr 1933}* ¥rm the total inaatlty of amo and tmaxmttlm promised har the British OoTorment, wo aakod for the following (to he soppllod la the 4th lnot;JLisoat){* Balanoo of the 3rd laotalttont* Hr* mouatala guno, with fire thouoimd ahrapaol with aoooooorloo# J^Ito hundred rlfle* # with 1 # 000,000 rounds of ammunition. But Ihedlnt^ 3o teought up only the following this time:* One mountain gun f with 1360 rounds of ammunition. Tm Lewis guns* Five hundred rifles* 1,000,000 rounds of rifle and Lewis gun amualtieii* 500 bayonets. ilth regard to tho oost of tdio ohovo, Ihodlng Be hae paid to you a mm of Es.30,000/*. Please lot us knew the halanse wo have to pay. ^e will arrange to pay. Vi would also ro most for tho fhrthor supply of tl following along with the balanoe of eras and anaunltion duo from tho 3rd and 4th lns*al»entsj* fwo mountain guns, with 500 rounds of shrapnel. 1500 rounds of oomm. shell. Four eo&amp;tplete sot® of Imwtn guns# 1500 short rifles. 1,000,000 rounds of ammunition for Lowls guns rifle®. Please let us Ja^ow imaodlatoli^ o- -i ^h wo idumld send off!ears to take the above over. Usual ending.^ m m .ob Translation of a letter from the Ministers of Tibet to Lieut-Colonel J. L. R, Weir, Political Officer in Sikkim, dated the 19th day of the 4th month of the Water-Monkey Year (corresponding to the 27th May 1932)• *******:»:**************** The reason of sending this letter by the Ministers of Tibet. For the mountain guns already received by us, we badly need the following accessories:- Two complete sets of Range Finders. Forty bags to pack gun powders. 213 fuzes. 78 tubes. Kindly arrange the above by reporting matter to the great British Government. Kindly let us know by telegram as to when our men should be sent to take the above over and also the cost which we have to pay for them. Usual ending. L.D. S' /Telegram X n Prom ••••••••• Pale 1 Lama, Lhasa* To.. Political Officer Sikkim, Yatung. Dated 9th June I93ii. Costs of fourth instalment arms and amnunition bought from British Government will he paid by L&amp;ahag and the responsibility for payment of required amount of costs for arms and ammunitions as requested in m&amp; my telegram and those bought by Tibet Government is for future put upon the debchi electric factory aaa Out of the ammunitions requested before the ammunition for gun named comension being urgent necessity here most kindly have one thousand and five hundred comensions gun ammunition obtained and granted immediately &amp;&amp;&amp; If Government orders not issued still kindly fcnow that application to India Government too may be submitted here from also•1416 . Telegram R. 'No 0 1416.,dated 17th June 1QT2. Prom Foreign,Simla. Political Officer, Sikkim. To My telegram No. 1406 June 16th. Military authorities are arranging despatcfrisg- of following further munitions. Pour ten-pounder guns, 500 rounds each of 10 -pounder shrapnel and common shell, 4 Maxim guns and 1500 rifles. This will complete the total demand recommended hy you excepting 2500 hombs which Government of India are not disposed to supply. (X. &amp; U.D.) F.A„/ BY AIR MAIL. _ ± Prom (Cop/ to India Office and Peking). ofi / To No # 3( 10)-P/3, Lleut-Colonel J.L.R* Weir # Political Officer in Si)ckim # ! /(Pi P -l. W-i. n iT'' v * 4 - The Foreign Secretary to the OoTernment bf India, Simla♦ Dated Cp.mp Yatung, the 12th June 1932, Supply of munitions to the Tibetan Government, k^f - -*\l Sir, I have the honour to submit, for the information of the Government of India, the translation of a letter received from the Dalai Lama which confirms and amplifies his telegram (vide my telegram Ho,3(10)-?/32., dated the 23rd May 1932), 2* In order to meet the wishes of His Holiness the arms and ammunition referred to in paragraph 6 of my letter Ko,3(10)-?/32., dated the 6 th June 1932 should be increased by 1000 rounds 10 pr shrapnel 500000 rounds S.A# ammunition, 3, I would suggest that the 4 Maxim {tuns may be sent as early as possible in order that the training of Tibetan officers and men at Gyantse may not be delayed, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. enclosure m™ ^ E0R EleN SECRETARY | L6t,e ' &gt; No 89 „ &lt; D5tad 2 ^UN.193S Raceiveo ~ JUL. ii/J? 1 Sd, J.L,R, vVeir Licut-Colonel, Political Officer in Sikkim,•Iranslatioii of a letter from His Holiness the Dalai Lama to Lieut•-Cclonal Weip, Political Officer in Si&amp; im f dated the Zlat d^ f of the 4th month of the Water- feonicey ^ear (cori^espending to the £5th Ma^r # 1 52). **%**#*# A special letter. Aa a result of failure of the recent was imperative to adopt retaliatory measures at once and the and ammunition, which we received from i ie British Goverioment previously, and also the munitions, w.iieh //ere Brought up By Lheding Be last year (1931), have almost all Been exhausted. In view of this and for the defence of the country, it is requested that, over and above mhe further supply of arms and ammunition asKed for By the Kash&amp;s in their recent letter, permission may ^ -ranted for the purchase at the same time of the following!- 6 mountain guns# 4 Lewis guns. 1,500 rounds of shrapnel. 1.500 rounds of common shell# 6,00000 rounds o£ Lewis gun urnffiimition. 4 machine guns. If t;eae guns take the Lewis gun ammunition, the ammunition previously ashed for will do, but if they require separate ammunition, permission is solicited to purchase 1.00000 rounds of ammun tion for them. 3.500 Bombs# A. tt..= ^ »•««. I k * 1S to ‘ to purciu.oe tbem. AJro.o;acooto will to k pfty £or these immediately* Also, as reauested in my previous telegram kindly arrange for the training of Tibetan Government o flow, and soldiers under the British military officers at Gyantse in the use of machine guns and b.-nbs as so,r a.as possible. Kindly subr.it a report to the great British Goveroaent through the Ofvmrent of India with regard to the Bho'e e nitlone, ft !1 of which we mast hare before we lose mtch Tibetan territory. In order to perpetrate ih* friendly relations between Britain and Tibet and in order to aohlere the object which I have In view, hladly submit ^ exhaustive report to the ^reat British Qorertmmnt through the viceroy. Gladly lot rae have an fcarljr reply to this letter. 3ent with sllfc se-f-rf. i.ed round seal, of His Holiness the B^lai Umn* ( )h ; t i H • *:&lt; :&gt; 1448. Telegram R 0 Mo. 1448. ? dated 24th June 1932. From . . , . .Foreign,Simla. To .... . .Political Officer, Sikkim. Your 3(10)-P/32,June 12th. Munitions for Tibet. Military authorities are arranging despatch further 500,000 rounds small arms ammunition as soon as possible. Apart from inadvisability of supplying additional 1,000 rounds 10-pcunder shrapnel there would be difficulty in finding sufficient serviceable ammunition for issue. (So &amp; U.D.) F,ANotes. Minute Paper. Register No. p. z. 3360/32. «- ' SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated Rec. 19 SEEN POUTIOAL COMMITTEE. 8 JUL 1952 Previous Papers :— in principle, in the proposal of the G-overnment of India to comply with the Dalai Lama's request for munitions, provided that the Government of India were satisfied that the arms are to be used solely for self-defence or internal police work. The Foreign Office have concurred in the proposal, and the Government of India were informed on the 7th June that H.T.G. had no objection, subject to the reservation stated. (*^S 3U/ &gt;1 /cooooo Sda , 000 rr-vU-, f /*°0 Cf »-uvv 29a 2000 5.31&gt; OOPY TO IiroiA Qggltes MD PEKIHG. BY A-L-R M_A I. L. P. Z. 3661 1932 24-7 /G, 'i* 1337, ' Telerrnn R. No .2(10)-E&gt;/32 dtted (end reed) 5th June 1932. Prom. . . To . .Political Sikkim, Yatung. . .Foreign, Simla. Your telegram of the 3rd instant No.1300. Peking telegram No.309 rerid withDflai Lama's telegram indicates that both Chinese end Tibetan forces have fought to a stand still.owing to lack of ammunition on each side. Wtuchtvei party first receives adequate supplies must gain upper haw. Sympathy of Chinese Central Government will be with their nationals end military supplies for Chinese forces v.ali presumably be forthcoming in near future. Tibet is still entitled to receive from us certain quantity of military stores. Failure or even delay on cui part in providing these will involve her defeat. Situation of affairs in 1909-10 would again arise with important difference that we would have to deal with an embittered and unfriendly Tibet. A strong end friendly Tibet is best and most economical safeguard for India's North-Test Frontier. Policy of the Government of India for last twenty ye&lt;..rs h^.s been to this end. Should we now fall Tibet in her emergency this policy will he stultified, , .V I would urge therefore again: inmediate offer suggested in my telegram March 23rd as preliminary to fuller supply of munitions regarding which lettci fcxlov.'o. •, (,}/ yi £2 W. 193? c. . (Mf\i (x. &amp; u.m)IW' '&lt;■ ' mr .1364 - ‘Telegram No. 1364 dated 9th June 1932, From. . . o ^Foreign, Simla. i Tc Politics 1 Officer, Sikkim,. My endorsement F,123-X/30 June 7th, Follcvang from Jefcrettry of State. Begins . Your telegrams * * 1350 , * * -k work. Ends . Military authorities are arranging despftch munitions withes* least possible delay and also issuing instructions for training of men at feyantse i Please inform Tibetan Government accordingly. You sholild ■ age in impress on them that munitions should he used solely for self-defence. [ p. z. ' 3661 1932 u (X. &amp; U.D.) P.B.I P. z. 1 3661 1952 I 1374. Telegram R. No, 3(10)f/32 dated (raid reed. )9th June 1932 Pron, .political Sikkim. Yatung. telegram of the 5th instant. Dalai Lama has telegraphed urgently today requesting 1500 rounds cotirnon shell white he states are urgent necessity. (X, &amp; U.D,) FeA«/-V P. Z. 3661 — I Q^ 2 , . Telegrarr: R, No, 136^.,dated lOtd June 1932. Prom .... Foreign,Simla. To Political Officer,Sikkim, Yatung. My telegram No. 1364 dated the 9td June. Munitions referred to therein are one thousand rounds common shell one million rounds small arms ammunition one thousand homhs and 4 Lewis guns. Do you recommend despatch of another five hundred common shell vide your telegram 3(10)'P/32 dated the 9th June which crossed my telegram referred to above? (X. &amp; U.D.) F.A.= . In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. p 4636/7/10 and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. O) IMMEDIATE Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Jonn Simon to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.P.Z.3228/32 of tne 3rd June regarding the request received by the Government of India from the Tibetan Government for the supply of munitions. 2. Sir John Simon concurs in the proposal of the Secretary of State for India that the Government of India should be informed that His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom have no objection in principle to the supply of munitions to the Tibetan Government, provided that the Government of India are satisfied tnat the munitions are to be used solely for self-defence or internal police work. I am, ,/FILE CWP/DH, ( 62 groups) DECIPHER OF TELEGRAM, 2940. From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Datad Recsived 1348, G-overnmont of India, Foreign and Political Department* r,o Secretary of Stale for India, Simla, 6 th June, 1932« 8 P 30 p«m*, 6 th June, 1932o Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Peking. Reference to our telegram of the 29th ultimo and connected correspondence, Supply of munitions to Tibet, 2, We have considered .points raised in Peking telegrams .1 and 309 of 30th May and 2nd June but are still inclined to favour immediate supply of munitions* at any rate,, to the extent suggested by the Political Officer, Sikkim* in his telegram of 23rd May repeated to you with our No, 1233, If we now decline to assist Tibet, even by fulfilling promise already made* we might not only be contributing to her defeat by the Chinese but should also certainly antagonise Tibet and endanger position established by our policy of the last 20 years, A strong and friendly Tibet is the best and most economical safeguard for our north-east frontier and we are most anxious to retain it. We should make it clear again to the Tibetan Government that the munitions must be used only for self-defence against external aggression.^ 0 ' In any further communication on this subject, please quote J0***S°- f and address —not to any “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. 'ation on this subject, please q tf-OVi A Ao any person by name, but to— THE Under-Secretary of State f&lt;W presents his compliments to v | ° ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvj of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 3. , 19 a x. / Reference to previous correspondence : L t Description of Enclosure, ^ ^ ^ ^ Name and Date. Subject. N- ^ T -n V Similar letter sent to 14—6757 (2):}5a 3000 5 31 Minute Paper P.Z.3204/32. Department. p. 2794 / 22 . P.4042 &amp; 4799/30. (gg7 In 1921 Mr. (now Sir Charles) Bell, during his visit to Uiasa, promised the Tibetans that facilities woulu be given for the importation of the following munitions from India in instalments at adequate intervals:- 10 mountain guns (with a reasonable quantity of ammunition) 20 machine guns. 10,000 rifles. 1,000,000 rounds S.A.A. annually. (JrNsiju The Tibetan Government gave an assurance that they wi£± be used solely for self-defence and for internal police work. We received no information about the supply of the first two instalments but in 1930 His Majesty’s Government authorized Colonel Weir to inform the Lhasa Government, after his arrival at Lhasa, that the balance of the munitions promised would be supplied on payment in instalments of reasonable size. Since then two instalments have been supplied. It will be seen from the Minutes on P.Z4278 and 6341/31 that there is considerable obscurity as to exactly how much is now owing to the Tibetans, but it seems clear that we still owe mountain and machine guns, rifles and S.A.A. The Tibetans have, however, already received that total quantity of mountain gun ammunition, v/hich the Government of India originally seem to have decided was a '’reasonable quantity'’. In view of the Government of India’s categorical statement that the supply of arms has not yet been completed, we may perhaps assume that they are prepared to interpret afresh the phrase 'a reasonable quantity of ammunition' and that bombs, previouslypreviously unmentioned, are included under that heading In any case Cabinet sanction is no longer required for the supply of arms from Government stocks and -£4- d^s not really affect^ the question whether or not the 1921 promise has yet been fulfilled. The Governmenjb of India may have merely mentioned it by way of an extra inducement to His Majesty 1 s Government. There need not be any difficulty about the permission to have the men trained at Gyantse, as desired by the Dalai ^ Lama^this has been done before. The Government of India do not explicitly mention this point, however, Neither do they make it clear whether they propose to supply the quantity of arms asked for by the Dalai Lama (which is in addition to that requested in the Kash^ T s letter) or the smaller quantity recommended by Colonel Weir. It will be as well to send a telegram , , /, ^ ^UU&gt; U ^ to the Government of India asking them to clear up thes£ ^ a \ doubtful points. 2. So far as the principle is concerned the main difficulty of the supply of these arms turns on the purpose for which they are required. In 1921 the promise of arms was given on the strict understanding t they were to be used only for policing the interior of the country and protection of its frontiers. In 1930 before Colonel Weir f s visit to Lhasa, the Government of India recommended that, should the Dalai Lama press the point, Colonel Weir might be authorised to say that His Majesty’s Government would be prepared favourably to consider the supply of further small quantitites of ammunition. Paras. 5-6 of the Minute on A fry* pi fin * ■iLt/r a-*. 7224]il&amp; 434/22 jhn ^^,1 r ^ / ut cw+Uc^t. t ^***1 In hat ' *0 X ‘/&gt;p jLt. ) . V Uuru T9 xpc* ‘crprvv It^S? S/) A V -y '* &gt; *1t if !» fj// ‘ lufi P Minute Paper. Department. :i5A 3000 5 31 on P. 4422/30 suggested that though we could not Justify the arming of Tibet for the express purpose of defying her suzerain, we were in honour bound to endeavour to safeguard Tibetan interests to the extent of the maintenance of the territorial 1 status quo 1 pending the settlement of her bounaary question. (In the end though Mr. Benn and Mr. Henderson supported the Government of India 1 s recommendation, subject to a written undertaking by the Tibetan Government that the munitions would be used solely for self-defence and for internal police work, the Cabinet, to whom reference was at that time required regarding the supply of arms, preferred that no authority beforehand should be given to Colonel Weir ana that any application for arms £iould be considered if and when it arose.. This is the first time that .such application has arisen). 3. It must therefore be considered whether these arms are required for self-defence. If the Chinese attack has been made by the semi-independent government of Szechf^in, i.e. by organised bandits, as Colonel Weir considers more probable, then clearly they x are required for self-defence and not against the Hanking Government, and the difficulty disappears. In any case the Chinese are the aggressors in the present phase of the struggle and Colonel Weir explicitly states that the arms are needed for self-defence. Hone the less there is a complication. 4. Under the Tripatite Agreement of 1914 a distinction was made between 'Outer 7r or autonomous and ' r Inner Tt or non-autonomous Tibet. For practical purposes the limits of Tibet became the boundary of Outer or Western Tibet. But this Convention was nevernever ratified: fighting was renewed until in 1918, thiough the good offices of Mr. Teichman, a temporary truce heljween the local Tibetan and Chinese military officers laid down a provisional boundary. (The Central Chinese Government has never confirmed this). The Teichman Lin^ must apparently be considered the line of the 1 status quo 1 subsequent to 1918. ‘By this line the boundary is, far as concerns the central section, rather more v* favourable to Lhasa than that of the Tripatite \ Agreement, and stretches as far as the Yangtse. The area between the Yan^bae and the Yal«jHHivers, in this ,v i sector, seems to be neutral. (See Map 2 at bottom of black bound volume). In the summer of 19o0 a dispute broke out between two border monasteries, in which troops of the Lhasa and IMking Governments became involved and which seems from our extremely meagre information to have attained considerable proportions. A T modus vivencfi 1 was at length concluded last autumn between Emissaries of the Governments, under which Tibet, who had had the better of the fighting, seems to have advanced territorially; for it provided for a garrison of both parties at Kanze and ChantiB, which under the Teichman Settlement had both been wholly Chinese (P.Z.2179/32). Our latest report (P.Z.2334) suggested the probable recrudescence of hostilities. It is tempting therefore to connect the present request of the Dalai Lama with this recrudescence, in which case (1) the Nanking Government must to some extent be involved, even if the P. so Chinese attacking force was not acting directly under its ordeiS; (2) even if the Chinese attacked in this phaseMinute Paper. Department. 3 phase of thelfighting, it might he regarded as merely another stage in the dispute of 1930-1, in which case it would be hard to say that one side or the other was definitely the aggressor. Further, even though the f modus vivendi* be regarded as supplanting the feichman Line in regulating the frontier, Tibetan influence does not extend beyond Kanze, and it will be observed that the Chinese attack was rT towards Domed Te«o side', which Colonel Weir places 20 miles East of Kanze. (There is also a Tao-Ws about 80 miles S.E. of Kanze with which Tewo could possibly be identified). It seems possible therefore that the attack was delivered in definitely Chinese territory (unless the T modus vivendi T referred to Kanze district and the latter extends so far) and this puts a different complexion on the matter. 5. Nevertheless, in view of the lack of adequate material, we shall probably have to accept Colonel tfeir f s statement that the arms are required for self- defence, probably against the Szechuan Government, and agree to the Government of India 1 s recommendation. As he says it would be an excellent way of sustaining the good relations established by his Mission and there is always the danger of Tibet turning elsewhere, e.g. to Russia,to get the arms, £f the Mission of four Buriet Mangols, carrying letters frcm the Soviet Government, to which Colonel Weir refers (P.Z.1969/32) we know practically nothing. In normal circumstances it would probably achieve no more than its predecessors but there is always the danger that itsits presence in Lhasa just at this moment might result in the Tibetan Government turning to the Soviet for help. 6. It is submitted that, while the Government of 1 ndia are being ashed for the further details discusse|d in para. 1 above, the Foreign Office might be ashed whether they concur in principle in the Government of India 1 s recommendation. Unless they do not feel satisfied about the 'self-defence', it will then be possible to sanction the propoal - preferably on the understanding the munitions are to be used only for self-defence and internal police worh. I understand that the / Foreign Office wish to consult the Charge d*Affaires at Pehing to whom the Government of India 1 s telegrams were repeated; they have been ashed orally to do so without waiting for our letter, in order to save tim^. ' T ft jnr- hu ^ Aw WvO, 3/* ) '^Minute Paper. Department. fa®'' ^ J ■ It is not possible to make much of the geography from the maps in our possession, especially as they do not mark the boundaries of districts,and the Teichman agreement^ was drawn up on a basis of districts. Evidently Col. Weir himself is rather in the dark as to what has occurred. It appears, however, that the Chinese aggression is in the neighbourhood of Kanze, towards a place which Col. Weir puts 20 miles east of Kanze. The Kanze district was placed by the Teichman agreement under the control of China. 1 But this agreement appears to have been modified^by the Sino-Tibetan agreement for an armistice enclosed with Chungking despatch of 25th January, 1932 - P.Z. 2179/32, flagged.^. This provided that parties should maintain a garrison at Kanze (this seems to mean at the town, but may possibly mean in the Kanze district); it also provided that both parties should maintain a garrison at Dawu and Drangu. A R.G-.S. map which we have marks a place Dawo about 80 miles east south east of Kanze. It seems possible, that under the armistice agreement the /*■ Tibetans have the right of stationing troops some distance to the east of Kanze, and that the present 214b 3000 8.31 Chinese aggression is in violation of the terms of the armistice. In any case, it is submitted that we may be guided by Col. Weir ! s statement that the arms and ammunition are required by the Tibetan Govt, for self- defence. // ‘h-y (.17 5000 1.32 provided/ /£/ Draft Paper. Political P.^,3m/32 Department IMMEDIiTE. DEaFT LETTSR ££ M 1932 The Under Secretary of State, Sir, Foreign Office, S .TT. 1. Copg^Xo India. 'closure in r ^23 ^''kly letter 9 JUIl 1932 Luuul AND sta-y, P - ten. WplA Office With reference to your letter No.F.3963/50/10, of the 25th July, 1930, regarding the supply of munitions to the Tibetan Government, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, copies of three telegrams from the Government of India,c/-25,27 and 29 May. 2. Sir Samuel Hoare has carefully considered the proposals of the Government of India, and also Mr.Thgram f s telegram No.305 of 30th May. He realises that the situation on the Sino-Tibetan frontier is most obscure, but the present Chinese aggression is apparently taking place in the area of Kanzi where the situation between the Tibetan and Chinese forces was thought to have been regulated by the recent modus vivendi or armistice reported in Chungkfng Despatch No.7 of 25th January, 1932, which seems to haveprovided that that ’yistriot should be temporarily occupied by Tibetan troops pending a further arrangement. It would appear improbable that the attack has been launched under orders from /£ c/ Nanking, and more likely it is the act of bandits or of irresponsible elements in the local military forces. In the circumstances he considers that the view of the Political Officer in Sikkim that the munitions are required by Tibet for self-defence may be accepted^ he is impressed by Colonel Weir’s view that ^whereas compliance with the Dalai Lama’s request would sustain the relations established by him at Lhasa in 1930, refusal might well cause the Tibetan G-overnment to turn to the Soviet • In this connection, I am to invite attention to paragraph .4 of the News Report from Sikkim No.4(4) - P.32, of the 25th February, of which a copy was sent to the Foreign Office with India Office letter No.P.F.1969/32, of the 1st April. 3. Sir Samuel Hoare would therefore propose, subject to the concurrence of Sir John Simon, that/Draft Paper. Department that the G-ovemment of India should be informed at once by telegram that His Majesty T s Government have no objection in principle to the supply of munitions to the Tibetan i Government, provided that the Government of India are satisfied that the arms are to be used solely for self-defence or internal police work. Q-npy tq a.. telegram addressed! to the Government of India in order to clear up certain ^jdetalTs uf Lliuii’ proposals «■— (Sd.) J. C. WALTOS,COPY (F 4520/7/10) L 110 DISTRIBUHQF Code telegram to Mr. Ingram (Peking) Foreign Office, 30th May 193S, 5.40 p.m. No. 103. (R), Grovein-ment of India telegrams to Secretary of State for India Ho. 1233 (of 2.5th May) and Mo. 1266 (of 27th May; supply of munitions to fitetan Government) repeated to you. Please telegraph your observations.■If/DH. ( 84 groups) D.E CYPHER OF T E L E G R A M. 2751. 3 lo'v From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Received Government of India, Foreign and Politioal Department, to Secretary of State for India. Simla, 27th May, 1932* 5*30 pom*, 27th May, 1932. I 1266 * My telegram of 25th instant, 1233* Munitions for Tibet* Provided stores are available, we propose to comply with Tibetan Government’s request. Supply of arms in instalments promised in 1921 has not yet been completed, and these munitions can be regarded as instalment covered by that promisee Presume that His Majesty’s Government have no objection* We shall be grateful for early reply by telegram. Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Peking./ ( C*&amp; IT/FUR/DH. ( 99 groups) D JLC.? P HER OF TELESRA From 2710, ll (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Receiyed 1233. m 2 L 0 P m. PARTS. Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India,repeating telegrams from Political Agent,Sikkim. Simla, 25th May, 1932. 4.45 p.m., 25th May, 1932. X 6 / Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Peking, Following £ telegramsy 3 (10) P fc4 32, May 23rd 5 received from Political, Sikkim* (1) Begins * Following telegram has been received from Dalai Lama by me this morning* Begins * Recently, from first day of Tibetan 4th month, Chinese have attacked this side in Khem towards Domed Tewo side and are fighting very strongly* The big (sic) small arms ammunition that were in hand before, and arms and * , • ammunition that were brought along with Lhadingse have also been almost spent and exhausted* Although Kashag has submitted letter for repurchase of arms and amr/unition eto«j in addition to those ? kindly also send along above further 6 guns and 4 Lewis guns with full quantity of ammunition for them and 4 maxim guns and 3,500 bombs more, above being urgently required hers* I am requesting f4hatrj ( 2 corrupt groups) immediate sale* With regard to prices and cost I am arranging and shall pay immediately* Further to learning using maxim guns and bombing, I ask to be allowed to send men soon to British Commanding Officer, Gyantse, for being taught and trained* Most kindly apply all above to British Grovemment the best way possible and reply at earliest convenienceconvenience. Ends. Ends. My comments follow by telegram*RTJ/DIL ( 120 groups) 2711 p DEOYPHER OF TEL E ,.0 R A.. M, From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegrams from Political Agent, Sikkim, Simla, 25th May, 1932. Received 4,45 poim, 25th May, 1932, X 1233. SECOND Ai\&gt;D LAST PART,., (2) Begins o My immediately preceding telegram, i. Tibetan 4th month commenced May 7th. ii. Domed Tev?o probably identical with the Chinese name of (? Chawa), about 20 miles east of Kanze. iiio Lhadingse is Tibetan officer who took up the instalment of munitions last year, iv, Kashag J s letter has not yet been (? received)« Urgent nature of the Dalai Lama f a request wodld seem to indicate that he has received news from Kham of serious setback to Tibetan forces there, Ngabo comes from Tibet, (? Conmssi of ) Kham, whom I met in Lhasa, did not strike me as an alarmist and his news is probably true. It is not clear* if the Chinese mentioned are acting under orders from Nanking and of the semi-independent Government of Szechuan, (? but) latter is more probable. In this case they are organised bandits. Arms and ammunition asked for are required by the , Tibetan Government for self«*defenceo If they are not supplied by us Tibetan Government must turn to Russia. Reception of the recent Russian mission to Lhasa points to the possibility of this. Ammunition rather than arms is probably more urgently requiredir&gt;° t - 2 ^ by the Tibetans in the immediate future* Offer to (? supply) at onoe 1 ? 000 rounds mountain gun ammunition, 1,000 ? 000 rounds small arms ammunition, 1,000 bombs, 4 Lewis guns, coupled with permission to have the men trained as requested at Gyantse, would sustain the relations which were with difficulty established by me in Lhasa, of which the Dalai Lam’s telegram itself is testimony* Ends » Our comments follow.&lt;V.Z. 2808/33) Extract from Annual Report on Gyantse Trade Agency for the year I/arch 31st, 1933. . l \ X X X Early in August 1932, the Tibetan Government MILITARY. sent Yuthok Se Tashi Dhondup now Depon, and 25 soldiers of the 'Royal Guards Regiment' to Gyantse for instruction by Captain 7/.D. Marshall in Machine Gunning and Bombing. Yuthok Se underwent 5 months training in gunnery at Quetta in 1928. Kumar Jigned Tering was deputed as interpreter and was also ordered to undergo the training at the same time. The Officers and men remained until the 1st week of December, when they were called to Lhasa. His Holiness the Dalai Lama, was very pleased with the progress made. Consignments of Arms and Ammunition purchased by Tibetan Government from the Government of India, passed through Gyantse in September and November. Mipon Dingia was at Kalimpong seeing to the forwarding arrangement s.From 7 043 lu 't J \ To , C* S«, ^ 1 ^3f^Wer in Sikkim, /C rT ^ . Xyr ?• Williamson political ( ■? f (*M ^ st The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department SIMLA* Dated Gangtok,the 5th October 1931* Subject-Supply of 4th instalment of munitions to the Tibetan Government. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with your memorandum No123-2/30,dated the 17th September 1931. m— hhwummiA 2* The Tibetan Government have asked me to arrange to supply them with 500 bayonets for the 500 rifles which they have received this year* I would request that arrangements mayjtO-ndly be made to supply these at an early date* 3* The Tibetan Government made no specific request for the supply of these, apparently thinking that, when 1 they asked for rifles, bayonets would be included. Received 23 MAY. ^ I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- F. Williamson, Political Officer in Sikkim*Prom P* Williamson, Eeq*, Political Off ice^ 4x1 Sikkim, **+ : ' £.»&gt;* i. r ' ' V- The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, / &lt; Few De lhi . Dated Gangtok, the 31st October 1931. Subject- Recovery of the cost of the 4th instalment of munitions from the Tibetan Government* Sir, I have the honour to invite a reference to the ~ o reopondence ending with your Memorandum Ho.P. 123 - 3 ^/ 30 , dated the 17th September 1931* 2 . With the exception of the 500 bayonets asked for in my letter Bo. 3(l)-P/3i f dated the 5th October 1931, the 4th instalment of munitions was handed over to the representative of the Tibetan Government at Gangtok in September 1931 . Opto the present Bs.31,000/- has been received from the Tibetan Government ana Paid into the Kalimpong Sub-Treasury for credit to the Controller of Military Accounts, Presidency and Assam Di strict, Calcutta* 3. It is very desirable to send one complete and final demand to the Tibetan Government for the whole cost of the munitions as, if amendments are subsequently made, they will misunderstand the position and great delay and much unnecessary correspondence will result. It would therefore be better to send one demand for everything, including freight and packing charges* As I am still receiving amendments to the priced vouchers f rom.►* V f - ■) , ■ * from the military authorities, I would request you kindly to let me know,as early as convenient, the final total cost of the consignment including packing and railway freight. 5* A demand for the cost of the bayonets, if the Government of India agree to supply them, together with packing and freight charges, can be made later, after their receipt# I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- Williamson Political Officer in Sikkim#From To i • i 7 Q43 Lieut-Colonel J* L* B.« Veir* , Political Officer in ^Si^kim, The Deputy Secretary to the mnent of India in the Foreign and Political Department Hew Delhi. Dated Gangtok, the 24th February* 1932. Subi ect-Recovery of the cost of the 4th instalment of munition from the Tibetan Government. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence end ing wi th Mr#1^illiemson , b letter Ho .3(l)-P/31,dated the 31st October 1931. 2 ^ X enclose, for the infornation of the Government of India, a copy of a letter from the Controller o. Military Accounts, Sastem Command, Meerut, to me, HO.P2231.,dated the 18th February 1932, in which he asks me to recover from the Tibetan Government the sum of Es. 1,58,524/ In tk* 8 c^nuectLOtt connection I would request the definite orders of the Government whether I can ask the Tibetan Government to r ay this amount as our complete and final demand on account of the cost of the 4th instalment of the munitions. I. X would also enquire whether this sum includes the cost of the 500 bayonets and 500 scabbards subsequently issued (vide Amy Headquarters letter Ho.lSV^A* 1 * dated the 5th November 1931. For the reasons given in paragraph 3 of Mr. Williamson 1 s letter quoted in paragraph 1 above, I should kike to sand one complete and final demand to the Tibetan Government. 3 # To enable me to effect early recovery of the cost of the munitions from the Tibetan Government, which would facilitate'Ll' 1 facilitate early adjustment of accounts in the books of the Military Accounts Officers, I may kindly be favoured with early orders in the matter# I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- J# L. R. Weir, Lieut-CoIon el, lolitical Officer in Sikkim.HoJP.2231, MILITARY AGCCUITTS DBPARTMS1TT, EASTERN COMMAND, Belvedere, Meerut, 18th February 1832* From The Controller of Military Accounts, Eastern Command, To ^ The Political Officer in Sikkim, Gangtok* Subject«*Recevery on account of cost of 4th instalment of munitions from the Tibetan Government, Sir, . 1 th e honour to state that out of a sum of Ks.l,8S,524/6/- on account of the cost of 4th instalment of amunition issued to the Tibetan Sovemment, credit for a sum of is.31,CC0/- only has since been received upto date from the Accountant General, Bengal, I would therefore request you to kindljr take such steps as will expedite settlement ol the outstanding balance cf Ss» 1,58,52^6/- , I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- Illegible, D.A.Controller of Military Accounts, Eastern Command,From To ■ j* y ■ Jro.3(5)-F/32.- j 30 ij T Lieut-Colonel ^T* X» f R. Weir, 4 ' 4 ' Political QfiTgft in Sikkim, The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, Dated Gangtok, the Liarch 1932. Recovery of the cost of the 4th instalment of munitions from the Tibetan Government. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with my letter No#3(5)-P/32., dated the 24th February 1932. 2. I enclose, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of a further letter from the Controller of Military Accounts, Eastern Command, Meerut, to me, No.P-2337., dated the 8th March 1932. I would solicit the early orders of the Government of India if this sum Rs.1,65,407/9/- may be accepted as our complete and final demand on the Tibetan Government- on account of the cost of the 4th instalment of munitions. 3. A sum of Rs.8010/9/- is still outCstanding against the Tibetan Government on account of the balance still due on the 3rd instalment of munitions. 4. The total sum due from the Tibetan Government would therefore seem to be Rs.1,73,418/2/-. I would suggest that I may be allowed to present this figure to them as our complete demand on account of munitions supplied to them. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- J. L* Weir &gt; Lieut-Colonel, Political Officer in Sikkim.2J&amp; Copy of ^letter from the Controller of Military Accounts, Eastern-''Mygi-ut, to the Political Officer in Sikkifc March 1932. * --WTTTnXOTXXTXj roarer U 0 , GaSg'toi,' Hoip- 3043 2337., dated the 8th • . f • •* \ * Sahject:- Recovery on account of cost of the 4th instalment of munitions from the Tibetan Government. In inviting a reference to this office letter Ko. P-2231. , dated the 18th February 1932, on the above subject I have the honour to state that the total value of the supplies amounts to Rs.1,96,407/9/- (Rupees one lac, ninety six thousand, four hundred and seven and annas nine only) and not Rs.l,89,524/6/- as previously intimated and that after deducting a credit for Rs.31,000/- which has been received up to date from the Accountant General, Bengal, there is an outstanding balance of Rs.l,65,407/9/- still to be recovered from the Tibetan Government. As all the stores comprising the 4th instalment of munitions have been fully supplied and received by the Tibetan Government I would request you to kindly take such steps as will expedite settlement of ik the outstanding balance mentioned above. L.DHo.3(5j~x'/32. From To '1/tt frypnrr'woir, O/S^oeJ in Sikkim 9 tepuisy M the Groverhmeflfffc of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla* Dated Oangtok, the 18th April 1932, 4th instalment of munitions for the Tibetan Government. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with my letter Uo#3(5)~P/32», dated the 26uh March 1932. 2. I enclose the translation (prepared in Ihasa) of a letter from the Tibetan Government to me, dated the 1st April 1932. I would request that arrangements may kindly T&gt;e made to supply the accessories enumerated in it on payment. In this connection, I would mention that the stores, forming 4th instalment of munitions for the Tibetan GoTernment, were handed over to Lheding Se, the representative of the Tibetan Government, in the latter part of 1931 under receipts signed by him. It is hardly possible that anything has been lost or mis laid before Gangtok, where unpacking and repacking to suit oooly and mule transport was done under the dfirCpt supervision of the Tibetan Government representative. •r au nn/iftr the imoression that any loss/ .1» 2. i 9 \ \ V must have taken place between Gangtok an£&gt; Lhasa# i?hc * y loss is probably due to. perfunctory pricking and lack •. * of supervision of the transport on the road# I have the honour to be g Sir, Your Eiost obedient servant, Sd/- J# L. H. Weir, Lieut-Colonel, Political Officer in Sikkim.Lhasa, 1st April 1932. To Political Officer in Sikkim, Gangtok. From The Chief Ministers of Tibet, Kashak, Lhasa. Sir, Very many thanks for the 1-10 Pdr. mountain gun, 2 Lewis guns and 500 Ho.l P.W.CL rifles with bayonets and amciunition for the guns and rifles, purchased from the British Government, received through Lheding 3e, superintendent of transport of the 4th instalment of arms and ammunition. We are glad to find that the above are quite new and of good workmanship and in complete accordance with the list enclosed. From the above the following accessories are missing:- (1) Two pairs of Breach Straps parts of B.L. 10 Pr. Gun saddles. (2) Two pairs of Chase Straps do. do. do. (3) One .Jheel Strap &amp;o. f * 0# V (4) One pair of Carriage Strap do. do. do. (5) Three Tangent Sight retaining worm spring and screw for the above B.L. 10 Pr. Jointed Mountain Gun. (6) Eighteen special bits ready for fitting to t e gun mule bolters, in case of necessity, being parts of the above saddles and Lewis Gun saddles. We also find that parts of the same pattern mountain gun, which we previously received, namely one Tangent Sight retaining worm spring and screw and two dial Sight pillars have been lost; so please order all the above mentioned parts from the works and dispatch them through Chumbi Tibetan Trade Agent as soon as possible. If the pricepresent Instalment brought of the missiAg pbrta^kf present instalment brought by Iheding Se were npfr lajeluded in the inroioe, we will send you the money together^with the amount for the ab^ve lost parts on receipt of your advise note* With Scarf of Greeting dated 26th of the 2nd Tibetan Month of the Water Monkey Year* Seal ( of the Kaahak ). I* • &lt;s« ^-- m i'rom To in the foreign and - the X-vYeroant or India oi it leal De,-art.aitnt The xolitisal Officer in viii:;!©. aUC B&amp; t r d the ^ w 'MaJT Subject- Recovery of the co»t of the 4th inetalaent of munitions fro a the Tibetan ioremaenU Si r t %ith reference to the correapondence ending with your letter So*3(5j-i/32 dated the 13th April 1932 # 1 «a directed to co firm that the total cost of the 4th inet^i- ment of munitione au^plied to the Tibetan Oovem lent in 1931 Kaounto to £«il # ?3 # 418/^- &amp;e stated in para 4 ef your letter da ed the 26th March 1932* A etatea^nt snowing the details of this amount is enclosed for your inforaatia &lt; 1 am to request that the amount when recovers i Jiay be paid into the nearest civil treasury for credit to the Controller of Military Accounts eastern Ceamand, Meerut 9 with which the office of the late Controller of Military Account* Presidency and Assam District has since been aa^ial gama ted* \ 2 . A further coi uni cation will be made to y u with regard to the su; ply on payment of the mi*sing stores referred te in y ur lett r under reply • Presumably they are to be consigned to you at 'Qielle Ahola (Railway station) Darj ell in g hi mlayan Rai-way - # The cost of these stores will of course* if supplied* be in addition to the totalP.z. 7301/31 Extract from Confidential letter No. 4 (1)-P/31 dated Gangtok, the 21st October 1931, from the Political Officer in Sikkim, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. NS\7S REPORT I have the honour to submit the following news report 2. Tibetan mu nitions. Lheding Se, who was deputed by the Tibetian Government to take over the fourth instalment of munitions, arrived at Gangtok on the 7th September 1931, and stayed at the Residency. He left Gangtok for the Chumbi Valley on the 6th October, after the despatch of all the munitions. Everything has arrived safely in the Chumbi Valley. Lheding Se was accompanied by a young Tibetian known as Derge Theji. The latter is a son of the ex-Raj a of Derge in Eastern Tibet. He was at Mr. Ludlow 1 s school at Gyantse and speaks English well. Lheding Se is the head of the police force at Lhasa.V ,0 &amp; a^ FILE COPY foreign and Political Department, Simla; The 18th- June 1931* D*0.^o.JJ , .123/X./30* ' / fourth instalment of munitione r* ^ for the Tibetan Government* w O H i Dear Williams on, Please refer to your official letter l!to.3(l)-P./31, dated the 7th May 1931, We are unable from our records to calculate how the figure of 5000 rounds of shrapnel is arrived at* 2. as you will observe from Bel^s letter to the Tibet Council dated the 12th December 19^21, the Tibetan Government were promised up to 100 rounds for each gun the first year and up to 50 rounds for each gun for each following year* In 1927 no doubt this practice was departed from and the Tibetan Government were allowed to have 500 rounds per gun vide paragraph 2 of foreign and Political Department memorandum Uo.633-X dated the 8th April 1924. 3. Accordingi^* to our records of^tS gun ammunition promised in 1921 the Tibetan Government have already received 1300 rounds, ^— &lt; viz- 1923 1927 1928 200 rounds. 1000 100 q**. .jo t*i-&lt;ro -'4nV lieJU-J Total 1300. Would you kindly confirm these figures, if they are correct for the guns now in their possession the Tibetan Government are entitled at the rate of supply quoted to receive another 750 rounds. If they got another new gun this year 100 rounds will accompany it. This makes the balance due 850 rounds* 4. .Before deciding the amount of shrapnel ammunition to be supplied, the Government of India will be glad to have your comments* fciince - vide Political Officer’s letter No. 326/P dated theuS'' A the 7th July 1924 - there is no record here of what Bailey may have promi&amp;ed the Tibetans when he went to Bhasa. Yours sincerely, &amp;d. Ifylie. To Williamson, iSsquire, Political Officer in bikkimDo OoA#o vn ( 2 ? The Residency, Gangtok, Sikkim* Camp iatung, Tibet. The 29th June 1931* fourth instalment of munitions for the Tibetan Gorernment. My dear Wylie, Please refer to your Demi-official letter iio.P. 123-X/30 dated the 18th June 1931* 2. as far as can be discovered from my records, the Tibetan Government have received the following mountain guns and ammunitiont- 1923-- 2 guns*.**.** 200 rda. common shell* N 1924-- 2 guns***•*•*(300 rds. shrapnel (100 rds* Star shell* (500 rds. blank arnmn. 1927-—— 1 gun 100 rds. shrapnel* Total 5 guns...... 1200 rda. ammunition* 3. X can find no record of any communication having been made to the Tibetan Government about their being allowed to have 500 rounds per gun. My Personal Assistant does not think that bailey mentioned this at Lhasa, if, however, he did so, it is possible that the Tibetan Government, in asking for 5 more guns and 5000 rounds, may have calculated that they can now have 500 rounds per gun for 10 guns, in addition to what they have already received. If this is the case, they have misunderstood the position. 4* According to bel^s letter to the Tibet Council, dated the 12th December 19 21, the Tibetan Government could have up to 100 rounds for each gun for the first year and up to 50 rounds for each gun for each following year. For the two guns supplied in 1923, they may therefore be considered to be entitled to 200 rounds in 1923 and, for the eight years 1924 to 1931, to 800 rounds - total 1000 rounds* jror the two guns supplied in 1924, they would, by a similar calculation, be entitled to 200 rounds in 1924 and, for the 77 years 1925 to 1931, to 700 rounds - total 900 rounds. j»*or the one gun supplied in 1927, they would be entitled to 100 rounds in 1927 and, for the four years 1928 to 1931, to 200 rounds - Total 300 rounds. The grand total of ammunition thus comes to 2200 rounds. Out of this they have received 1200 rounds, leaving a balance of 1000 rounds due to them, if we disregard the 500 rounds a£ blank ammunition taken in 1924, they might be considered to be entitled to receive 1500 rounds, in addition to ammunition for any more guns which may be provided this year. 5 # The Tibetan Government have asked that they may have this year the remaining five guns out of the ten promised them. They undoubtedly consider that they are entitled to receive them. There may be objections to this, of which I am unaware. But 1 would request that, if possible, they may be allowed the number of guns they ask for. 6. The Tibetan Government recently informed me that an official named Kusho Lheding be would leave Lhasa for Gangtok not later than the 25th June to take over the munitions. It is most unlikely that he will actually leave till much later, and i will inform the Government of India as soon as anything really definite is known about this. Yours sincerely, Sd/- i}’. Williamson. To JS*.V. Wylie, J&amp;sq., C.ljs., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, foreign and Political Department,Te legram 7/15- /&gt;17 J)Tom - The Political Officer in Sikkim, To - The foreign Secretary to the Govt, of India in the foreign and Political Department, iio,428 &gt; dated Gyantee the 17th July 1931. My demi-official letter iuo.3(l)-P./31 last paragraph. LHi£DJJi(GS&amp; ie at uyantse niehes to take over munitions in September at Gangtok. Please wire approximate dates of arrival of munitions at Gielle-Khola railway station. Letter follows.GrOViSHl'IMSlIT OP IlfDlA* E X P H Ji b S LETTER. ^ From p. Williamson, Esq., Politic 1 Officer in SiKkim, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government off India Simla Ro.3(l)-P./31 Dated Can^) Gysntse, the 13th July 1931. Supply of 4th instalment of munitions to the Tibetan Government. Reference my telegram lTo.428 of the 17th July. Kusho Iheding Se, a Tibetan official, has been deputed by the Tibetan Government to receive the 4th instalment of munitions. He saw me on the 15th July and wishes to deposit Rs. 20,000/- in advance towards toe cost of the munitions. 2. Lheding Se desires to take over the munitions at Gangtok about the beginning of September. I should be grateful if you could kindly let Die know at an e&amp;rly date, the approximate date of their arrival et Gielle-Khola Railway Sts tion. 3. I would request that I may Idndly be informed of the total cost of the munitions, including railway freight and other incidental charges. This will enable me to let the Tibetan Government know the total amount which they will 1 b ve to pay, and will obviate the necessity of sending supplementary demands to them which they may not properly understand. 4. I would also request instructions regarding the various accounts officers to whom the amount, when received should be credited. In the meantime I should be grateful for orders as to the crediting of the Rs.20,00c/- which is now being deposited in advance. Sd/- P• Williamson, Political Officer in Sikkim7 Confidential. rv D.O.Uo.J.123-a/31 GOVHRI^BBMT OP I1D L-. PORSIG1T AKD POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Simla; The 5th xaigust 1931. fourth instalment of munitions for Tibet. Dear Williemson, Please refer to your demi-official letter No. 3( 1 )-P./31 dated the 29tli June 1931. The Government of India have decided to supply the following munitions to the Tibetan Government this year:- 1 Mounts in Gun 1350 rounds fountain Gun arnmunition. 2 chine guns. 1&amp;. &lt;J»»H«^j 1 f W SL ov tyLkJr&lt; iJxou will n 50£ Rifles 1 Million rounds^arfrcH- arms ammunition. otice that except for the IToun.ain Gun ammunition, the present consignment represents one yesr f s supply. In arriving at the decision to restrict the consignment to this the cni^f e^nsideretion has been Tibet* s capacity to pay which has always been poor and .at present seems worse than ever. It seems better to disappoint them to some extent now rather than to let them run heavily into debt and then nt ve to keep dunning them for years after. ^is regards the Mountain Gun ajmuunition the statement below explains how the figure of 1,350 rounds has been arrived ati- 5 guns (3! 100 rounds for each gAn......500 2 M * 50 rounds each for 7 y ears 700 2 ^ ** 50 rounds each for years 600 150 1,950The -ttXiny Dep^-rtnent have been asKed to provide a stc Lenient of the exact cost of the above munitions, xhis will include carriage as far as railhead. It will be necessary for you in communication with the Tibetan Government to work out the cost of carriage from rail-head onwards. A further communi ca tion on this subj ect wi 11 be addressed to you as soon as possible Yours sincerely Sd. F.V. Wylie To F# Williamson, Esquire, Political Officer in Sikkimtfram - The Deputy Secretary to the SoTernment of Inaia in the foreign and Jeolitical Department, To - The i'oXlticaX Officer, Memoranaum jso.J. 1^3-X*/3J* Dated &amp;imX&amp;, the beptamber 1931, bupply of munitions to the Tibetan Goremmerit* Reference c oi’res pond ence aiding eith your u&amp;preaft Letter Jso.3(l)-ir,/3l t dated the 18th July 1931. The munitlone now under supply to the Tibetan Government are ee time ted to cost Re. 1,68,292/- vide liet attached. Details of the cost of special packing and actual railway freight will be communicated to you later when known. 2. The sum of Re.20,000 deposited by the Tibetan representative should be paid into the nearest civil treasury for credit to the Oontroller ailitary Accounts, ihresidency and Assam District, Calcutta. ad/- If. 7. Uyiie, Deputy i ecretary to the Co Ter merit of India. Copy forwarded to the a r m y, Accountant -General, Central Revenues for Information, with reftrence to the con-^onaetwo ending with their tadoruement no.lM/lQ/i'-l, dated fcSth AugustNotes. Register No. ( Minute Paper. P. Z. SECRET. 4278/31. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, Dated 19 Dec. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary ‘7-7- fuj TIBET. Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... do Mtj Fourth instalment of munitions for the Tibetan Government. Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. Please see the minute on P.Z.3494. The Tibetan Government have &lt;4&amp;3 bl paid tbs 'final Rs.5,000 owing for the third instalment and there is now nothing to prevent the supply of the fourth. The actual figures are rather obscure. The Tibetan request of last December is a repetition of their requests of 1929 and May 1930 (P.5272/39 and 3354/30) plus 2 machine guns and 200,000 extra rounds of S.A.A. for these. It was assumed at the time . % t}(L (F* of the 'decision of last year (cf. the Previous Papers:-- minute on P.4042/30) that the Tibetan request for the munitions 'to which they are still entitled' did represent the outstanding balance due to Tibet. But the Memorandum since Pk,'** , Ti CAU COMNI‘ tTE T -4 4475b 1000 5.30' - received (P.Z.E643) which is the only detailed piece of 1 UJL information we have Cs.ce since 1921^ shows that the iihetans are in fact still entitled to considerably more weapons than they seem to be aware, viz:- 5 mountain guns. 10 m achine guns. 6,o6C”~rifles. «^ _ — 1 6ocu. I tm - &amp;+{- complicated. It was agreed in 1921 to supply 1,000,000 •prut &amp; to-na^, ^ H /**} to* The question of the ammunition is more rounds S.A.A. annually: ‘titte is all (apart from the extra 200,000) which the Tibetan Government are ashing for. But since in fact payments- seem to have been intended Wr to extend over 8 years, it can be argued that we really agreed to pay* 8,000,000 rounds and therefore still owe 5,847,571 rounds. ignore the inconsistency at line 7 of the Memo:). As for the shrapnel, the position is still worse. In 1921 it was decided to supply 'a reasonable quantity of ammunition rl . The Memo: however, talhs of '100 rounds for each gun the first year and up to 50 rounds for each gun each following year', 3 guns being si^plied the first year and 1 gun for each of the next 7 years. This would entitle Tibet to 500 rounds this year or 2,750 in all. As they have now received 1,200 rounds, they are entitled to 1,550 more: but they are asking for 5,000 rounds. (Presumably the Memo: is based on the interpretation which the Government of India decided to give to the phrase 'a reasonable quantity'). In view of the fact that the Government of India will be acting somewhat disingenuously if they leave the Tibetans under the impression that they are receiving all the machine guns and rifles which we agreed to give them, and because it appears from the Dalai Lama T s letter of 17.10.21. that he understood he was to receive 'a reasonable quantity/ P.524l/21.ji ay 1951* from the Politic*! Officer in Sikkim* to the Foreign 3ecret*ry to the Govern enfc of Indi©* ;iiml»* leeue of 4th instalment of munitions to the fidetan Govern sent* 1 have the honour to invite e reference to telegram Ko* 196* dated the 9th April 1931, in #iioh I informed the Government of India that the Tibet&amp;n Government had paid the coat of the third instalment of munitions* less Ha*5000/-* 2* the balsnce of He. 5000/-* has been paid to the British ?r&lt;de Agent* Gynntse* and nothing ?aore ia therefore due from the Tibetan Govern ent on thia ft account* 3* I would therefore request that I may be favoured with esrly orders regarding the supply of the fourth instalment which the Tibetan Govern! ent are moot anxioue to reeei e at once*dir CJopy of a letter No* 5(1)»P/31» doted 3»ngtokt the 7th fcay 1931 § from the Political Officer in aikkim, to the Foreign Secretory to the Government of ir.diat Simla* mm ***• m I ague of 4th instalment of Biur.itions to the Tibetan Government* I have the honour to invi te a reference to your unnumbered telegram dated the 4th 4ay 1931* The Tibetan Government hove been saked by telegram the df&gt;te on wnich a Tibetan officer c?n take over the munitions at Gangtok* 2* X much regret that in my letter No* 3( 1 )»P/31* t dated the 4th May 1931 1 the quantities of miAitioa* which the ’icetan Govern ent desire were not correctly stated* In a letter from the i-ini store of Tibet to Lieut^Golonel ^elr# dated Uie 21st December 1930# they asked for 5 mountain guns# 5000 rounds of shrapnel# ususl accessories# 500 rifles# 2 meohine guns ?nd 1 #200#000 rounds of small ©ms amiauntion* fhey state that the machine guns ere very necessary and that 200#000 rouns al so of the smell arms anajunition is for them,* They/desire the additional accessories referred to in para reph 3 of Colonel Weir 1 s letter No* 4(7)-P/29«# dated the 8th July l929#namely# 5 clinometers# 3 foresights# 3 tangent alights and 8 wheels for the mountain guns* 3* In paragraph 2 of Colonel Weirs letter referred to above ••100000 rounds of small anas ammunition' ia a mistake for '1 #000#000 rounds of moll arms ammunition'* 4# as regards ammunition for the mountain guns# it ap yearsappears doutotf 1 whether the Tibetan Government »re entitled to receive a 9 much oe tliey aak for* 5* WiUi reference to your telegram ^ 0 * 30Q5-3» dated the 11 th September 193 C, 1 have the honour to invite n reference v. to Colonel Weir* 0 telegram lio* dated the 16th September 1930» in wtiich he aaggested that the munitions might be separately stored at For William Arsenal# in the first inatsnce# to facilitate final despatch* As soon as It is known when the Tibetan officer is likely to arrive at Gangtok# I would request that they may be sent by train to Gielle Kliols station (the new na::e of Kalimpong Hoad Station)# Darjeeling Himalayan Hallway# consigned to the Political Officer in Sikkim* Arrangements will then be made to send a represent stive to teke delivery and bring them to Gangtok* It would simplify the onward journey if es many packages 8» possible were suitable for mule transport* 6* With reference to Colonel Weir’s telegram Ho* 3(8)«*P/3G# dated the 10th September 1930# in which he suggested that certain amnunition in the possession of the Officer Coriananding the British Trade Agent's escort should be earmarked for supply to the Tibetan Govemnent# I am now informed that this uni tion will not be available# as it is required by our detachments in Tibet*Notes. Register No. Minute Paper. P. z. SECRET. 3494/31. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. -f'N Dated 14.5. i * 19 31 * Pec. 1.6. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... * Date. Initials. SUBJECT. /%. c, iL 0 ^ % Us T I B E T: Fourth instalment of munitions for the Tibetan Government. it 4 //.'). A •A J»4. , Lx.k. SEEN POLITICAL COMMITTEE. 24 JON 1951 ;VA i Previous Papers : Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. The Tibetan Government have now paid for the third instalment of munitions supplied to them in 1927, less Rs.5,000, payment of which was expected by the middle of May. The Government of India have expressed their readiness to supply the fourth instalment as soon as payment has been completed. This will comprise the following:- 5 mountain guns; 10 Lewis guns; n 6,000 rifles; 4.V’ • l ,aOO _ rounds mountain gun ammunition; 1 tf.,8oo ,000 rounds small arms ammunition. Secv.. Military Dept., /■ - /ij 5 r g . Vi' ‘ 3 l *&gt;/.3 4 c - Copy of on flocpresa letter Ho# 3(l)-P/3|t I ] Harcjh 1931 f from Poll tical # Sikki^,Gang^k^ 4o Poreign, Hew Delhi# 7 4th instalment of munitions for the Tibetan Government# Reference Government of India, foreign and Political Depertaent, letter Ho#D.610-X/31, dated tiie 19th Pehruary 1931, 2# The Tibetan Government are prepared to take over the 4th instalment of munitions at any moment they are naked to do so# 3# 1 would however bring to the notice of t e Government of India that a gum of Rs# 24,801/- was due from the Tibetan Govern ent on account of the cost of 3rd instalment of munitions supplied to them in 1927. Towards this they have, / in January 1930, paid a sura of Rs# 3260/-, also another aim of Rs# 4000/- recently# They are constantly being reminded for the balance, but they have not yet found their way to remit it# I also took the opportunity of rerai -ding them about this verbally while 1 was in Ihasa last# The position is very unsatisfactory# I am being overwhelmed by reminders from the various i^ilitary Accounts Officers and from the Accountant-General, Central Revenues# Pending full payment of the cost of the 3rd instalment and in order to obviate possible accounts complications, I have not yet asked the Tibetan Government to depute their officers to receive the 4th instalment# Unless the Govern ent of India urgently desire immediate delivery of the 4th instalment of munitions, I venture to suggest that it may be deferred until the cost of ttie 3rd instalment has been recoyere_d. in ful trGtO^Uiic IN I would request early 4 yder^ ; 9 n G ^better N j 64) Dai; . .1^.1931 Reot a v UUN.1931Code* ip' Telegrcm Ko« From•••••••• To # • • •• ••••• 196» dated (and reed.) 9th April 1931* Political Sikkim* Gangtok. Foreign, Hew Delhi. Weir* s express letter Ho. 3(1)~P/31, 26th March. Munitions. Tibetan Government have paid coat of third instalment less He# 5,000/- payment of which is expected within three weeks. May I now inform them that Government of India are ready to send fourth instalment immediately.Telegram R. Ho. 12&amp;2~3 f dated 4th May 1931. From. Foreign, Simln, ToPolitical, 3ikkim. m **** m Your telegram of 9th April 196. Munitions. Government of India are ready to supply fourth instalment on completion of payment for third* Please report date when Tibetan Officer . can take over munitions.- see also my telegram 3085-S September 11th 1930. 1• COPY OF l&amp;itf -nu. ?okl n,;. 1 ^ r ‘ r JyCM.uenUa l. D.0.Ro.lU)-P/ai. O r j. |[4! . L w fc S f 2 6 4 3.1 &lt; 1 ? 1 O Qjke e lae n cy, Hmogtck, Sikkim, the a6th larch 1951. l4«pal*Tibet relations. l*y dear Miards, PXeaie refer tu /cur deffil-official letter l?o*F*279-X/ i50, d.itea the k4th February 19&amp;1. £• I agree that the prospect© of really irienuly relations ever existing between Nepal ana Tibet are very slight* I think the basic cause iu the resentaent xhich the Tibetan Government entertain towards the Tfepaleee ''overnKient* Rightly cr wrongly, they consider that the latter adopt an unnecessarily high handed ana arrogant manner in c,ny mutual negotiations, l am afraid this feeling wiii dbv-ji' disappe^x' until the two countries test each other’s strength in actual *ar. 3. The su gesticr, that t e Government of India should complete as scon as possible the supply of munitione already promised to Nepal and Tibet is a good one. It should not however be ov^rlcoaed that this course might induce the vary crisis which was averted with ex reme difiiculty not uuite a year ago. 1 do not anticipate such a crisis in the near future. If, ana v.hen, it arises he shall have to rely on cur local officers to av‘?rt it. 4. Bo far as Tibet is concerned, the '''overrent of India mUst be prepared to wait an indefinite period for payment of any further munitions supplied to the Tibetan Government The latter have already received 3 instalments of munitions totalling 5 mountain guns 10 machine guns vLOSURc IN UQN SECRSTARY'8 ^ ! ‘ No 4 I M. ^ ^ a:\i mi V 2? AFR1951 !TIBSTAK HUNITIOMS* Tho lolloping is the total amount ol munitions, which the Tibetan Oovornment have been permitted to in port in inaraiments at reasonable intervals:- 10 me un tain guns ¥*ith a reasonable amount of am uni t ion* 20 machine guns. r0 f 0.;J rifles* 1,000,000 rounds of sr«a 11 arms a^mnsun 11lor,. The scale of yearly instalment, on which the Tibetan Government have been permitted to import the above attritions, was iixed as under:- &amp; a u a\ aL—iiaS^ -kaSlU Lt-i-iiB ^-4t;u. 3 at-ntain t uns, 6 machine guns, 3000 rifles the first year and 1 mountain gun, 2 machine guns and 1000 rifles each following year for 7 years. : ^M:UniUuL _^oi. _ ;:.oU3,ain , u;^. . Up U 1JU roueda c! this aiuiiuniiion for each gun the xirst year and up to 50 rounds for each gun each following year. dm aila rm s . aiiaa u n I t ivu . 1,000,000 rounds of this ammunition Qm.ch year. Of the 6 Lewis guns to be supplied the first year, three were given free of cost in order to re deer the promise made by the Government of India son. time ago to give the ’Tibetan Government one or two machine guns* Of the total amount of munitions, which the Tibetan Oov irnment have been permitted to i. i&gt;ox’t, they have already taken over the followings- 5 mo ^jd ta in g unu. 10 machine guns. 4,300 rifles. i,200 rounus ol mountal gun ammunition.2,152,429 roums of sniall arms anis* unit ion# Deducting the quantity already received hy them, the Tibetan Covemment are still entitled t^ in.port the folio v» in g arm o and a mm un i 11 on : - 5 mountain guns, 10 Lewis guns* 6,000 rifl^.«, ¥yith the balance of mountain gun aumunition and small arms ammunition in accordance %lth the scale indicated above*COPY OF Copy to Incia COiice QOVSRKMSKT Oj- GtJIFl^TlAL • Dated, the, Febwaiy,/■?•&gt; 1 X 4 ep£q ^ r i b e t re Xa ti on»* /o /4/ 1 wiU you please refer to paragrapb 14 of the letter from the iPeiitical Cfficer In 3Hekla Ho. 7(14,•l/3 &gt; dated the 18th liioYe^aher 1930, a copy of ehieh was forwarded with trie endoreaaent from the Government of India in the foreign and loiitical department #9*l ? *4-Jv29 dated 6 th deceir.foer 193 • 2 * It la to he feared that the prospects of the eetahiieh- »e«t of good relations between JSepal and Tibet are ©light. That- beiiig so, it is necessary to consider whatsis possible and expedient to minimise the embarrassment to the Government of India should the differences between the two countries become extreme. so long as the practice of torture and flogging for the purpose of extorting oonfession continues to find favour in Tibet, there is always the danger of a Fepale&amp;e subject being t';u treated, and raising another Gyalpo inciderit; and if Chinese influence advances at Lhasa, it seem® not unlikely that the Nepalese capitulatory regime ©ay be threatened. In the circumstances it has been suggested that the Government of India m&gt;uid be well-advised to complete as s on as possible the supply to both iiepal and Tibet of the miinltions already promised, oven though there Pay be delay in payment, and thereafter to avoid as far as possible any further commitments in both this respect. This would ebViatc/the risk of our being obliged to supply warlike material to either vountry rt_s time when DIARY'S ? relati0n »</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ca_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2175</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ca</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2175</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/6 'Tibet: supply of arms from British sources'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:51:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (320 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 320; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An external leather cover wraps around the documents; the front inside of the cover has been foliated as f 1; the back of the external cover has therefore not been foliated. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-319; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the supply of arms, ammunition and training by the British to the Tibetan Government. The details of the 1921 agreement between Britain and Tibet, the quantity of munitions to be supplied, and the intended use of the arms (for internal policing or external policy) are debated throughout the correspondence.The principal correspondents are: the Political Officer at Sikkim (Frederick Williamson, later Basil Gould); the Resident at Sikkim (James Leslie Rose Weir); the British Mission to Peking [Beijing]; and the Government of India Foreign and Political Department. The file also contains notes and memoranda on the above, made by the Foreign Office and the India Office Political Department. A number of translated telegrams from the Chief Ministers of the Tibetan Government, and Thub-bstan-rgya-mtsho, Dalai Lama XIII (1876-1933), are also found within the file.Correspondence dated 1932-1933 concerns the following: clashes between Tibet and China at Kanze [Ganzi] in eastern Tibet; a request for the final supply of arms under the 1921 agreement; the financial situation of the Tibetan Government; and Chinese requests for details of the 1921 agreement.Correspondence dated 1936-1939 concerns the following: Sir Basil Gould's mission to Lhasa; rejection by the Tibetan Government of Britain's intervention in the settlement of the dispute with the Tashi Lama; the supply of munitions and training of Tibetan officers in India; and an incident in which the brother of a Tibetan trade agent passed arms to China.Correspondence dated 1943-1947 concerns the following: the provision of arms and ammunition beyond the amount specified in the 1921 agreement; the extension of Government of India control in areas immediately south of the Indo-Tibet frontier (McMahon line); and the assessment of the importance of Tibet to the security of India's north-eastern frontier. A memorandum found at folio 70 provides a summary of all of the arms supplied following the 1921 agreement; folios 33-68 consist of extracts from intelligence reports, documenting arms traffic within Tibet; and a Chiefs of Staff Committee Report at folios 16-26 provides an assessment of Russian and Chinese military threats to Tibet, and possible Tibetan and British responses.The file includes dividers which give lists of correspondence references contained in the file by year. These are placed at the end of the correspondence (folios 2-3).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Thub-bstan-rgya-mtsho, Dalai Lama XIII</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Tibet</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Peking</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Tibet</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><subject><topic>Weapons</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002ca#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>