<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000301_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:55:26.382Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ADMINISTRATION REPORT ON THE PERSIAN GDLF POLITICAL RESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY roil 1901-1902.Agents for the sale of Books published by the Superintendent of Govern- ment Printing, India, Calcutta. In London. E. A. Arnold, Esq., 37, Bedford Street, Strand, VV. C. Messrs, Constable &amp; Co., 2, hitehall Gardens, S. 'W. „ Sampson Low, Marston &amp; Co., St. Dunstau's House, better Lane, E. C. B. A. Quaritch, Esq., 15, Piccadilly, W. Messrs. P. S. King &amp; Son, 2 &amp; 4, Great Smith Street, Westminster, S. W. „ Luzac &amp; Co., 46, Great llussel Street, W, C. ,, Kegan Paul, Trench, Trubner &amp; Co., Charing 1 Cross Road, W. C, „ Williams and Norgate, Oxford, „ Deighton Bell &amp; Co., Cambridge. On the Continent. Messrs. R. Friedlander &amp; Sohn, Berlin, N, W. Carlstrasse 11. Otto Harrassowitz, Esq., Leipzig. Maitinus Nijhoff, Esq., The Hague Karl W. Hiersemann, Esq., Leipzig. Ernest Leroux, Esq., 28, Rue Bonaparte, Paris. In India. Messrs, Thacker, Spink &amp; Co., Calcutta and Simla. „ Newman &amp; Co., Calcutta. „ Thacker &amp; Co., Ld., Bombay. ,, Higginbotham &amp; Co., Madras. E. Seymour Hale, Esq., Fort Bombay. Superintendent, American Baptist Mission Press, Rangoon. Rai Sahib M. Gulab Singh and Song; Mufid- 1-Am Press, Lahore. Messrs. A, J. Combridge &amp; Co., Bombay.SELECTIONS FEOM THE RECORDS OF THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. No. OCCXCII. Eoreign Department Serial N o . 128. -—■—♦ '• ADMINISTRATION REPORT ON THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1901-1902. «- Publishcb bg ^uthoritg^ CALCUTTA; OFFICE OF THE SUPEEINTENDENT OF GOVERNMENT PRINTING, INDIA. 1902.CONTENTS. PART I.—General Summary .... Appendix A. —Meteorological Tables PART II.—Report on Maskat Affairs PART III.—Trade Report o£ the Persian Gulf for 1901 Appendix A.—Tabular Statistics- . . PART IV.—Trade Report for Maskat Appendix A. —Tabular Statistics . PART V.—Trade Report of Mohammerah , * Appendix A. —Tabular Statistics . PART VI.—Trade Report of Bunder Abbas Appendix A.— Tabular Statistics , . . PART VII.—Trade Report of Bahrein Appendix A.—Tabular Statistics .ADMINISTRATION REPORT on the PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY and MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY TOR 190M902. ♦ P ART I.—GENERAL SUMMAEY. 'Rainfall and Harvest—The season in Bnshire was very unsatisfactory. The i- General rains set in late and have been very deficient, only 2 inches 83 cents having been recorded. The , prices of foodstuffs, at the close of the year, were very^high, wheat selling at krans 25 and barley at krans 18 joer Hashrni man of i24 lbs! In Bushire and its immediate vicinity, the crops have failed almost entirely, but in some of the surrounding districts, the rainfall has been more favourable and a fairly good harvest is expected. At Lingah there has been practically no rain for fourteen months, and a good deal of anxiety is felt as to the wate^-supply. At Shiraz the late rains have been good, and it is understood that the crop pros pects are at present satisfactory. On the Karun the rains came very late, but the late rains have been good, and towards the close of the year the price of grain declined considerably. The Governorship of Bushire and Gulf Forts—Iha Darya Eegi resigned his appointment and left Bushire for Tehran on the 7th April, in obedience to the orders of the Persian Government. His successor, the Salar-i-Mo'azzem, nephew of the Nizam-es-Sultaneh, was appointed on the 18th August 1902, but did not arrive in Bushire until the 28rd December. His deputy, the Moiz-el- Mumalik, arrived in Bushire on the 21st September. Fublic Feace and Tranquillity. —The year under review has been unevent ful. Subsequent to the departure of the Darya Begi affairs in Bushire were more or less disturbed, but no incident of any importance occurred. Tangistan appears to have been in its usual lawless state. Fuhlic Health. —The past year has been a healthy one. A good deal of small-pox prevailed at Mohammerah, but appears to have died out now; and there have been cases in Bushire. The measures for the prevention of plague have been efficiently carried out under the superintendence of the Residency Surgeon. Currency. —The old krans and copper coins have been withdrawn from circulation, and new krans and nickel coins are now in general use. jLdmiuistration of the Customs in the Fersian Gulf. —Ihe management of the Customs in the Gulf has remained in the hands of the Belgians, who have succeeded in extending their control generally throughout the Gulf. The Customs at Charbar and Gwettur, which were hitherto farmed bv British Indian subjects, have now been taken over by the Belgian Administration. The port of Dilam also has been taken over, but Hyder Khan of Bandar Big has, it is understood, hitherto refused to hand over the control of the Customs at that port. The Shaikh of jVIohammeiah, and the Arabs who acknowledge him as Chief, are very averse to the abandonment of their ancient rights connected with the customs at ^lohammerah and on the Karun river, and the Belgian Administration has not B2 Oman- Ma skat. 3. Oman Coast- Bahrein. ADMINISTEATION REPORT ON THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL 5 Koweit and TSojd. vet succeeded in extending its control in this direction. Negotiations on the snt.iect are, it is nnderstood. now proceeding at Tehran where the Shaikh has pent a representative to lay before the Persian Government his views on the subject. At Bushire and the other Gulf Ports a transhipment lee of 8 bran per package has been introduced tor goods transferred within the harbour, and r kran per package on goods landed and kept in bond and subsequently re-exported. A limit of twenty days bas been fixed within which such goods may be re-exported, but this limit may be extended at the discretion of the Customs Administration. Availin 0, itself of the prohibition which exists against the export of provi sions from Persia, the Customs Administration has lately seen fit to impose a 10 per cent, duty on barley, wheat, and rice and other articles ol provisions, notwith standing the fact that these may have paid the 5 per cent, import duty. ^ Ibis duty has been enforced in the case of provisions sent off to British ships within Persian waters. At Lingah, which is an important port of transhipment for the opposite coast of the Gulf, this recent regulation is very unpopular, and it is probable that the prosperity of the place will suffer in consequence. I have not been able to ascertain the income derived from the Customs in the Gulf, as the Director-General is not allowed to communicate the figures. It is probable that a large increase of revenue over last year's figures has resulted, as various new charges have been introduced and the control of the Administra tion generally extended. Settlement of Claims for Compensation. —The Special Commissioner? Hissam-el-Vizareh, alluded to in last year's report, arrived in Bushire on the 29tli April. His mission proved to be a total failure, as he had no sufficient authority from his Government to enable him to enforce his decisions, and consequently the local authorities gave him no assistance whatever. Major P. Z. Cox, I.S.C., was Political Agent throughout the year. Tran quillity has generally prevailed in the Sultan's dominions. His Highness suffered a great loss in the death of his faithful Vazir and adviser, Sayyid Saeed bin Muhammad. The Political Agent's report of the principal events in Maskat during the year forms Tart II of this compilation. The past year has been unusually tranquil and nothing of any importance has occurred. The pearling season was satisfactory, and no cases of piracy or disturbances at sea took place. I visited the Coast in lebruary, and saw most of the Trucial Chiefs. Debay appears to be increasing in size and import ance. Owing to the policy of the Customs Administration at Lingah, more steamers have recently visited the Coast, and landed goods direct, which would otherwise have been transhipped from Lingah. Mr. Gaskin was Assistant Political Agent at Bahrein throughout the vear. The pearling season was satisfactory, and altogether the year has been a pros perous one. The Bedouins on the mainland have been giving a good deal of trouble, and the caravan route between Ojair and El-Hasa has been verv unsafe. No piracies have occurred near Bahrein this year. The Turkish authorities have, as yet, taken no steps to punish the Behaih tribe who were responsible for the murder of the Chief's cousin. Shaikh Salman- bin-Diaij, alluded to in last year's report. The new r Mutasserrif for El-Hasa arrived at Bahrein, on 3rd September, en route to Ojair. The Turkish authori ties, fearing trouble from the Bedouins, have taken steps to strengthen their position at Katif. There appears to be no doubt that the defeat sustained by Shaikh Mubarak at the hands of the Amir of Nejd, on the 17th March, near Aneyza, w r as decisive As is not unusual in Arab warfare, he was deserted in the hour of need bv certain Bedouins of Nejd who had espoused his cause and who went over to the Amir's side, thus changing the fortune of the day. Mubarak's loss was verv heavy and included his brother Hamud and other notables. The Amir's losses appear to have been considerable and to have included some leading- men After this defeat. Shaikh Mubarak returned to Koweit, and the Amir of Neid after inflicting punishment on certain tribes who had espoused Mubarak 's cause' also returned to his capital. Towards the end of September, however, the Amir moved out and encamped for some time on the confines of Koweit, whence he kept up communications with the Turkish authorities at Basrah, demanding their assistance for the purpose of exacting redress from the Shaikh of Koweitresidency and maskat political agency foe the year 1901-1902. for his aggression on Nejcl territory. Tor three months he remained in the vicinity of Koweit, which was kept in a state of constant excitement. Early in January, apparently finding that he could expect no active support from the Turks, he returned to his own country. About the middle oi January, an event of great importance occurred in the capture hy Abdul Aziz, the son of Abdul Eahman-bin-Fey sal, of Kiadh, the old Wahabi capital. Abdul Eahman is the brother of Abdullah-bin-Peysal, the last of the Wahabi Amirs, and it was he who headed the revolt of the partisans of the A1 Saud dynasty against Muhammad Ibn Rashid, the Amir of Nejd, in 1891, which met with no success. Up to the present, the Amir of Nejd has taken no active measures against Abdul Aziz, who has streno'thened his authority at Eiadh and gained many supporters. His Royal Highness the Salar-ed-Howleh was Governor-General of Arabistan 6 - Persian Luristan, etc., throughout the year. The Azam-es-Sultaneh was Lieute- Arabistan, nant-Governor of Arabistan from the middle of July to the end of the year. With the exception of the districts controlled by the Shaikh of Mohammerah, the country has been in a state of marked disorder. His Royal Highness the Shoa-es-Sultaneh, second son of the Shah, was^-Farsand appointed Governor-General of Pars, and arrived at Shiraz towards the end of Persia11 CoaEt - April. Disputes ensued with the Kawam-ul-Mulk, who was summoned to Tehran with his son, the Begler Begi. The Shoaes-Sultaneh ruled Pars with a strong hand and kept good order in the country. He does not, however, appear to have been popular. In January the Kawam returned to Shiraz and intrigues recommenced. Early in March, the state of affairs was very disturbed : the Prince was sum moned to Tehran and left about the middle of March, the Kawam, who had also been summoned, following him a few days later. A new Governor-General, Asaf-ed-Howleh, has since been appointed and is now on his way from Tehran to Shiraz. No political event of particular interest occurred at Lingah during the year. Lieutenant Hunt, the British Vice-Consul and Assistant Resident at Bunder Abbas, was invalided and took leave to England early in the year. Major Phillott, who was appointed to act as Consul at Kerman, in June, was placed in charge of the Bunder Abbas Vice-Consulate. Captain E. H. S. Boxer was appointed to the post in January. Mr. Whitby Smith proceeded on leave on 16th April, returning to India on 8. Persian Baiu- the 23rd December. During his absence, Mr. R. H. New officiated as Director, cllista11 - Persian Gulf Telegraphs, and was in Political Charge of the Makran Coast! Affairs in Persian Baluchistan have been at times very unsettled during the year,—Mir Mahmud Khan, brother of Abdi Khan, Chief of Dashtyari, having given a great deal of trouble, threatening to attack Charbar and looting in its vicinity. Hashem^ Khan remained as Governor at Bampur and appeared to be quite unable to maintain order in the district. Twelve slaves were given manumission certificates during the year. Pour 9t Slave Trade. Africans, who had taken refuge at Bassidore and were living there, were, at their own request, sent back to Zanzibar. During the year under review, four cases of piracy on British Indian sail- io. Piracies, ing craft occurred in the neighbourhood of the Shatt-el-Arab bar. The Shatt-el- Arab itself is well patrolled by the Moez-es-Sultaneh, and the pirates, who come from places on the river, watch the opportunity of vessels being becalmed on the bar or waiting for the tide, to carry on their piratical operations. The difficulty of dealing with these piracies is that the authority within the river is divided, one bank being Turkish territory and the other Persian, and each side throwing the responsibility on the other. The following ships of His Majesty's Navy have been in the Gulf at various n. Navy, times during the year:—H. M. S. Marathon, Fomone, Fox, Perseus, Cossack, Figeon, Lapwing, Redbreast, Assaye, and Sphinx. Of Foreign Navies, the Bussian cruiser Varyag arrived at Bushire on 15th December. She left for Koweit on the 21 st and, on her way down the Gulf, visited Lingah and Bunder Abbas. The French cruiser Catinat arrived at Bushire on 15th February, having visited Bunder Abbas and Lingah on her B 2ADMINISTRATION REPORT ON THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 12. Official changes. 13. Changes among Foreign Representa tives. 14. Observa tory. way up the Gulf. She proeeeded to Keweit en the 19th, returning to Bushire on the 23rd Pehruary and left for Maskat on the 27th. Lieutenant-Colonel 0. A. Kemball Resident throughout the year. Mr. W. S. Davis was First Assistant. He left for India on transfer on the 24th MarC Captain B. Wickham Hore, I.M.S. Residency Surgeon was relieved by Captain Grant on the 1st April 1901, and proceeded on furlough to England. He returned and resumed charge of his appointment as Residency huigeon on the 1st February 1902. Assistant Surgeon J. A. Lobo officiated as Residency Surgeon from 5th July to 9th October, during Captain Grant s absence on privilege leave. A Russian Consulate-General was established at Bushire, M. Ovseenko, who was appointed to act as Consul-General, arriving to take up the appointment on the 17th September. He held charge during the remainder of the year. M. Chaloin took up the appointment of French Vice-Consul on 6th August. Dr. E-einhardt, Imperial German-Consul, was in charge of the German Vice-Consulate during the year. He proceeded to Shiraz for the summer and returned to Bushire via Ispahan, Ahwaz and Mohammerah towards the end of September. Mr. Moesmann of Messrs. Hotz &amp; Sons was acting Consul for the Nether lands throughout the year. The results of the daily observations are recorded in a tabular statement marked Appendix A. C. A. KEMBALL, Lieutenant-Colonel, Officiating ^Political Resident in the JPersian Gulf. B ushike ; The 2ht April 1902.RESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR THE YEAR 1901-1902. 7 P ART II.—ANNUAL ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY POR THE YEAR 1901-1902. 1. During the past year, there have been no serious upheavals in the Political, interior of any political consequence, or calculated to cause the Sultan personal anxiety; and with the exception of one locality, Oman generally has enjoyed a satisfactory measure of immunity from the petty intertribal wars which tend so much and so frequently to hinder the agriculture and prejudice the trade of the country, and Maskat itself has been free from the usual scares of attack by Bedouins. 2. Wadi Maawal. —The exception above mentioned is afforded by the tract comprising the Wadi Maawal and Nakl, i.e., the hinterland of the small port of Bark a, 40 miles west of Maskat, which has been much disturbed for the last seven or eight months from the results of an internecine feud, which, though not extending to a wide stretch of country, has nevertheless from time to time made travelling so unsafe in the area affected, as to bring caravan traffic to and from that neighbourhood to a complete standstill. Such feuds are generally prosecuted in the slack season, after the date crops have been safely gathered, when the fire-eating elements of rival clans, freed from the cares of husbandry, and in want of useful employment, seek diversion in preying upon their neighbours or reviving old quarrels. The present case was no exception to the rule, and the spark necessary to light the fuse of tribal discord seems to have been generated at the end of August, when news reached the Sultan that a party of Beni Ruwaheh inhabiting Nakl, had killed two men of the Beni Riyam, and that intertribal hostilities had been declared in conse quence. Shaikh Rashid-bin-Uzaiz, Governor of Semail, was forthwith deputed to proceed to the locality and endeavour to bring about a reconciliation between the parties before matters had assumed serious proportions, and this official returned to Maskat in due course, reporting that his mission had been successful. With in a few days of his arrival, however, hostilities broke out afresh, and he had to return and repeat his efforts, but with no better success than before. During the months following, the Shaikhs of one party or the other repeatedly addressed communications to the Sultan, stating that they were anxious for the cessation of hostilities, and requesting him to send a repre sentative of his own to arbitrate between them ; and His Highness as often com plied with their representations, deputing at one time Shaikh Rashid before men tioned, and at another, Sayyid Badr-bin-Saif, the military member of his council —but all to no purpose. Truces were no sooner arranged and signed by the elders than they were violated by some headstrong tribesmen and a revival of general hostilities inevitably resulted, and during the despatch of the Saltan's last peace mission to the tribes concerned, an unfortunate incident occurred, which merits passing notice. The deputation in question left Maskat in a large party for Barka by land, intending at that place to pick up ' Khafeers,' or protective guides,' to conduct them in safety to the rendezvous. They persuaded the aged Kazi of Barka, a venerable and much respected greybeard and himself a Maawali, to accompany them in this capacity, hoping no doubt that his religious influence would assist their negotiations. The cavalcade had lost touch with Barka on their outward journey, and was just entering the Wadi Maawal, when it was ambuscaded by a body of Maawalis and Beni Ruwaheh, who (whether by design or mistaking them for enemies has not been satisfactorily ascertained) opened fire upon the party and emptied the saddle of the unfortunate Kazi at the first discharge, killing him on the spot. Apparently they soon realised that they had killed an elder of their own community, for they ceased firing and did not molest the deputation further. The latter, however, did not proceed on their way, but returned to Barka with the Kazi's body for burial, and in order to communicate the news to the Sultan.mm G«rer*i. s ADMINISTRATION BErOET ON THE PERSIAN GTLF POLITICAL Tlik incident regrettable as it was, seems to hare had the effect of bringing +1 . ™rfics to their senses, for hostilities practically ceased from that time, and vn Uh March the welcome news was received of the conclusion of peace. As the ho weTtbcr and the date season are fast approaching, there are some grounds fir hmnn&gt;Ml it this present settlement will be more lasting than its predece^ors. What seems to be wanted under such a set of circumstances is that the Eulcr should make the quarrel his own when once a truce, negotiated by his Stervmien. has been violated, and that he should come down with a heavy hand on the offending party. This, however, in practice entails a costly expedition, and hence it is. no doubt, that the Sultan prefers within limitations to leave the 'Sbc to tilt at one another until they tire of the game, and to hold aloof him- so f until circumstances force him to interfere. On the score of temporary con venience and economy, such a policy may have its advantages but it cannot ultimatelv be for the best interests of the country, the commercial prospentv ol which must naturally bear a direct ratio to the degree of tranquillity prevalent in the interior. 3 Sohar. Towards the end of the hot weather, Suleiman-bm^uweilim, the Sultans Wall at Sohar. created a little diversion bv a small expedition on lm own account, his objective being the Fort of Beit-el-Ainein in the Dhahireh countrv. about SO miles southwest of the port of Sohar. Owing to its being ndvantWxmslv situated from a strategic standpoint, this stronghold has always been a coveted possession amonsr the tribes, and during the last century has manv times chanced hands: but for some years past it has been held against all comers bv the Miyaiheh section of the Beui Ghanr, and on the present occasion Suleiman-bin-Suweilim seems to have come to some personal arrangement with the Beni Kalban tribe, by which they agreed to assist him to wrest the fort from the Miyaiheh and hold it for the Sultan. It is believed that responsibility for the inception of these operations rested originally with Suleiman-bin-Suweilim personally, but once they were started His Hurlmess had to give the expedition his countenance, and to respond to Suleiman's appeal for assistance in the direction of money and commissaiiat. The venture proved abortive, however, the Wall and his adherents being obliged to desist after losing heavily ; and the Sultan, then realising that the fort could not be reduced except at a heavy cost in men and money, sent orders to his W'ali to return to Sohar. Before quitting the subject of the politics of Oman, it must be noted that during the year under review, the Sultan's eldest son. Sayyid T aim cor, has begun to enter into public life and to help Ms father in small matters of internal government. 4. Jtritish Indian svhjetts in Jloskaf and Omon. —During the year, the Political Agent made two soa trips to different ports of the Oman littoral, visit ing the small communities of British Indian traders residing at Sib. Barka, Khabura, Luwa. Kurriyat and Sur. Purine the year robberies have been committed on the premises of British subjects at Luwa, Sur and Barka : also one trader was waylaid and looted on r is way back from the interior, where he had been to recover debts; and one bania of Mesnaa complained of wrongful confinement and ill-treatment by the Wa i of that port.. In all these cases the Local Government has shown a commendable disposition to see justice done. In the more important case, that of wrongful confinement at Mesnaa, the Wali was removed for that and other misdemeanours, and his deputy, who was immediately responsible for the incident, imprisoned. In the theft cases, the value of the stolen property having been investigated and assessed by 3 commit tee appointed jointly by the Sultan and the Political Agent, compensation to the amount arrived at has been recovered from the culprits, or disbursed by ihe Local Government. A second case of theft at Barka is still under investigation, and a committee has not yet been formed, but it will shortly be disposed of. o. Cvstow**.—It will be remembered that last year the Sultan for the first time took the Customs Administration under his own control, instead of fanmns: it out to a contractor, the result being a satisfactory increase of revenue to His Highness.RESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR THE YEAR 1901.1902 9 This year the revenue assessed on the value of trade, according to flffures turnished by the Customs Superintendent, amounts to some its. 4,000 less than last year, but this difference is more than accounted for, by the untoward fact that during the year 2 vessels wiih valuable cargoes bound for Maskat have never , e - 0n j^ ear( ^ of, and presumably foundered at sea; one being the clipper sailing- ship County of Forfa owned by residents in Maskat, and bound from Calcutta with cereals, and the second the S.S. JBasuto from London, with arms and ammunition. There have been occasional complaints from merchants, of incon- sideiate tieatment at the Customs House by the Sultan's officials, sometimes well rounded, sometimes not; but I have always found His Highness anxious to remove causes of complaints when brought to his personal notice, and to meet merchants half-way as far as lies in his power. The great desideratum at present is, undoubtedly, the improvement of the Cus tom house, wharf and premises, which are not a credit to the State, but I am glad to report that the Local Government has lately started work in this direction, which, it is hoped, will be carried to completion. It is interesting to record here that the satisfactory pecuniary results of his Customs Administration at Maskat, have prompted the Sultan to assume the direct control at other ports in Oman, of which hitherto the Customs have been « farmed'. Barka, Mesnaa and Suweik on the Batineh coast have already been taken in hand, and also Sur to the south of Maskat, and it is expected that other ports will follow as time goes on. In order to facilitate the collection of dues at Sur, where the inhabitants have always been very difficult to deal with in this connection, it was His Highness's lirst idea to build a wall on the land side, so as to restrict all import and export caravan traffic to the use of certain gates where Customs guards would be sta tioned. On going into the matter on the spot, however, he realised that owing to the difficulty of obtaining materials and labour at Sur itself, the building of a wall of effective length would take a year or more to complete, and he therefore chose the more economical and speedy alternative of creating a line of block houses on the hills between Sur-el-Bilad and the port of Sur, commanding the caravan routes to and from the interior. These were completed during his recent sojourn at Sur in November. This is decidedly a step in the right direction and will suffice for present purposes, but now that His Highness has taken the Customs collection of the port into his own hands, it is to be hoped that as the administration improves and increased revenue comes in, he will see his way to build a suitable Customs wharf at the entrance to the creek. In connection with the above block-houses, 100 extra sepoys have been engaged for garrison purposes at Sur. 6. The Arms Traffic. —It will be seen from the trade returns appended, that there has-been a considerable decline in the quantity of arms and ammuni tion imported into Maskat during the year, the decrease being roughly 8,000 rifles and 1,400,000 cartridges. The difference is in some measure accountable for by the loss of S.S. JBasuto before mentioned, and also by the fact that at the time the Customs House Returns were furnished by the Superintendent, delivery on all the cases received by the last two steamers had not been taken by the consignees, and duty had not therefore been collected on them. It is worthy of note that the Bedouins are gradually learning to recap and reload their own cartridges; in fact, a demand is beginning to spring up for new empty cases ; riflemen evidently realising that it is more economical to load their own cartridges, often no doubt with home-made powder, and that the light empty cases are less trouble to transport from the coast. 7. Pearl Dispute. —The longstanding dispute mentioned in last year's report, which has been dragging on for more than two years, has at last been brought to a close. It will be remembered that the representative committee which was appointed to assess the shares of the several parties interested, awarded His High ness the Sultan 30,000 dollars, representing a one-third share of the value of the pearl in question, and a document was passed and signed by the Chief of Shargati and others in ratification of the award. This sum was not forthcoming, however, owing to loss meanwhile sustained by the holders, who had evidently been spe culating with money borrowed on the security of the pearl, and the Besident after visiting Shargah, having informed His Highness that in his opinionI ill jjil /-vxt 01x7^ pfrsian gulf political ADMINISTRATION EEPOKT ONTHEm^ —— ~ Savvid Peisal wisely deferred the most he «? uld .K ne ° 9 to content himself with that amount, to hUopinion and expressed typical test case, he had effectively I into account the fact Ta lue of such prizes, ed his title to a definite loya y „ d ^ in .j^ a komed.—Sayyid Saeed-hin- 8. Death of the ^^^Wyazir, who had for many years been promi- n i.*_- ihft fcUitan S vcifAij ,.1 cmlfiPin V on fhp Bs. 12,000 was to his opinion p j. f| ia t m luj» vi'—~ , taking into account on the value of such prizes proved his title to a definite xoy y Saeed .iin-Mahomed.—S 8. Death of _ the SVazir, who had for many , - ■ , Mahomed-hin-Salimm, the ^Itans vaz ' d . ed v sud d e nly on the m-K « 5-°&lt; •»- B » HlKtae ' '• s °'' '■ in Company with the 1 ' oUtl . cal , A ®?° t however, he sent for the Agency Surgeon, Soon after the Darhar ^he up, after riging to gl , eet him . who only arrived to see Sayyid Saeed taU ao^ apparently from an aneurism of the h 01ltline of the late Vazir s career, It will be useful to record heie a vicissitudes of fortune, which are which, needless to say ^ a ^ ohe Sf^ y oriental Government. Of Al-Bu-Saidi ever characteristic of service | several generations, and the deceased Stock, his forbears had hvedmMaskat^seveiai^gn^ ^ p] . csent Sultan . 8 g rand . himself, born in the reign of Say} c i i l , t the ca pital, which, except for a father, received all bis teacbmg and traimn, ^ o{ hig life few brief absences, he nevei qm tte ^ ,, 7 th 011S 0 f Mahomed-bin-Salimm, Sayyid Saeed was one o^hree brothers the som ^ ^ ^ namesake one of whom died, young, and the cldes , . g' Saeed also first entered Sayyid Thuwaini-bm -Saeed, ^ J o{ g u itan's commissariat and trans- public life, being appointed to the 'two Thuwainis, Sultan and Vazir, became port arrangements. Subsequently, che two IMwa de p OS i tioll 0 f the latter, estranged to an extent which J , A te^ to Zanzibar, and was sue- who was deported, or ^ 0 ^ge/^other; and although Thuwaini 'tltdto MaZtt^ or three years faterjie wasncv^againemployed by his namesake, up to the time of the latter's assassination at So har ln following upon this event came four stwm} yeais, pacify turn held the bin-Thuwaini and the Rost ah pretender, Azzan- nii- , seems to have reins of Government for a brief period, and Saeed- , m j 1(r fjoja served both one and the other. At last, m 1871 , Sayyid Tul ^ le , tu fi r '' t § , exile in India, possessed himself of the Sultanate, and appears at fet to have taken both brothers into his employ ; but a few month® after his aocessio elder Thuwaini was shot dead in the streets of Maska , m f nnmnlimtv believed, for a previous murder in which the ex-Vazir was suspected of C0 ™P^, J' For the next fourteen or fifteen years, Sayyid Saeed s life seems to ha^ebeen uneventful, and he continued to pass his days peacefully m the service o Turki. Towards the end of the latter's reign, however, relations between the Vazir and the Sultan, who was at this time a chronic im alid, seem to have un er gone a marked change, and matters gradually went from bad to woise, nn i in May 1888 Sayyid Saeed was deposed, and compelled, much against his will, to leave Maskat; whereupon he took up his temporary abode, first at Kishm anc IciijGX 1 Sit JSxindGI? Meanwhile Sayyid Turki's state of health became suddenly critical, and in July, information reached the exile of his late liege's death at Barka, on receip of which news he was emboldened to return to M askat in the confident hope that Sayyid Feisal, who had now succeeded his father and whose interests he has always supported, would welcome him back. In this however he was disap pointed, for in pursuance of some undertaking given by Sayyid Turki s three sons to their father on his death-bed, the new Sultan refused to sanction his remaining in Maskat, and obliged him to return to Kishm or Bunder Abbas. Later on he was allowed to return to his home and property in Maskat^ ^ Meanwhile his distant kinsman, Mahomed-bin Azzan, had become Vazir. This functionary, having got into disfavour in 1896 for corresponding with the Sultan's enemies in the interior, was in turn deposed and heavily fined. Then Sayyid Saeed s chance came again and he was re-appointed. Sinister influences were at work, however, which brought about his second downfall in October 1898 ; but in May 1900 he w r as once more taken into favour and appointed Co- Vazir, and from that date up to the time of his death he remained in harness.EESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR THE YEAE 1901-1902. 11 A man of masterful disposition and pronounced views wliich he did not hesitate to give expression to, it was not within the nature of things that he should have been a generally popular personality; but while on the one hand it is doubtful if the present Sultan ever had any personal regard for him, it is none the less certain that His Highness fully recognised the fact that in all matters lying beyond the scope of parochial politics the statesmanlike perspicacity of his kinsman was a valuable asset to himself. On the day of the Vazir's demise, the Sultan's Flag was half-masted and the several Consular representatives followed suit as a mark of respect to deceased's memory. They also paid visits of condolence at tiie palace, the Political Agent being directed to convey to His Highness expressions of regret on behalf of His Excellency the Viceroy and of the Resident in the Persian Gulf on hearing of the loss which he had sustained. 9. On 26th November 1901, the telegraph cable, which had been extended Ma ^ t 1 ^ ask from Jask across the Gulf of Oman to Maskat, was opened for traffic—an important event in the annals of Maskat. When the question of the extension was under consideration it was not estimated that the takings would amount to more than Rs. 1,000 per mensem, but the average of the first four months of its working is found to be about l^s. 1,500. 10. Maskat has enjoyed complete immunity from epidemic disease. The duties E ^®^f v | nd of Health Officer of the port were last year entrusted by the Sultan to the Agency Measures, Surseon ; and this year also, the preventive arrangements under his supervision have been carried out most satisfactorily and with an entire absence of friction. On the transfer of Captain F. A. Smith, I.M.S., to India just before the end of the year. His Highness wisely continued the same arrangement m the case of his successor. Captain J. W. Grant, I.M.S. 11. No slave dhows were brought in for adjudication during the year by siave-Trade, anv of His Majesty's men-of-war, and it is to be noted that for the last three i seasons there has been no slave cruising under Admiralty orders. Fifty-four fugitive slaves applied to this Consulate during the year for protection and freedom. Of these one absconded while his case was under investigation ; three were dismissed as not being slaves, and fifty were given freedom with the con currence of the Local Government. The Africans were sent direct to Zanzibar, m accordance with the orders of Government providing for repatriation of Negroes. 12. Maskat was visited during the year by His Majesty's ships Cosset, Navy. Fioeon Assaye, Sphinx, Ferseus, 3Iarathon i Fomone, Lapwing, Fox and Eedbreast—Sind. by the Royal Indian Marine Steamers Minto and Investigator. Foreign navies were represented as under :— French.— Fean F olt I , lufeTnGt, Catinat, Chasseloup Louhat, Russian.— Varyag. 13 Captain F. A. Smith, I.M.S., was transferred to India and handed over his duties to Captain J. W. Grant, I.M.S., on 14th February 1902. Monsieur P. Ottavi, Consul for the French Republic, left for Europe on 5th July 1901, and was relieved by Monsieur R. Laronce. P. Z. COX, Major, Folitical Agent, Masqat. M askat; The 2nd April 1902.General. Imports. Exports. Harvest. Exchange. Currency. 12 ADMINISTRATION EEPOUT ON THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL^ P ART III. TRADE EEPOET OF THE PERSIAN GULF FOR 1901. The improvement in trade, both in import and export noticed in last vear^s report, soon declined owing to the partial failure of f cient rainfall, and the year under review has not been a favourable one tor trade operations, h ^ show a considerab i e advance in the extent of imports over the previous year, the result cannot be said to have been ue to the transactions in any particular class of goods having proved remunerative bu rather to overspeculation encouraged by some farms who allow lon 0 indiscriminatelv to traders of little or no means. . The total imports into Bushire during the year, excluding specie, amount to Es. 2,01,70,511 or an increase of Rs. 16,22,229 on the previous year. Ihe imports into Lingab also show an increase of Bs. 16,80,614. The increase is noticeable m almost everv article imported into Bushire, specially m cotton piece-goods, glass and glassware, hardware and cutlery, kerosine oil, provisions anc tea, all of which show an advance of over 50 per cent. Indigo shows a heavy decline of nearly two lakhs of rupees. Other articles showing more or less decrease are gold-lace and thread, metals, porcelain and china ware, loaf and soit sugar and woollen goods. The class of goods which show an increase in impoits into Lingah are yarn and twist, drugs and medicines, kerosine oil, provisions, loaf and soft sugar, tea and woollen goods. # The exports from Bushire declined by Us. 14,27,404 which is made up by a decrease under all the principal articles exported from this port. Ihe only articles which show an increase are horses, hides and skins, rose*water^ tobacco and wool. The exports from Lingah improved by Rs. 13,15,735, the chief items being pearls and shells, the former of which alone records an increase of Rs. 12,63,000 and the latter of Rs. 41,000. Owing to a scanty rainfall, the grain and other crops failed to the extent of about 50 per cent, and famine prices had actually to be paid for bread stuffs. Had it not been for the partial relief which was afforded by the abundance of fisheries in the Gulf and the plentifulness of the date crop in Turkish Arabia, the effect on the poorer classes would have been most disastrous. No shipments of wheat were made to the United Kingdom during the year, prices on this side being far too high. Towards the close of the year the embargo was reimposed and prices rose still higher and large quantities of grain were imported from India. Sterling exchange rates varied between krans 53 per pound sterling in January and March and krans 55 in September and December. Rupee exchange was lowest in May at krans 356^ per Rs. 100 and highest in December, when it reached krans 367^ per Rs. 100. Bar silver to the value of over Rs. 30,00,000 was imported into Bushire during the year for transmission to Tehran and specie to the extent of four millions krans (Rs. 11,42,867) was sent up-country by caravan. The introduction of the nickel tokens mentioned in last year's report has had a very beneficial effect on the currency of the country and the complica tions arising from the debased copper currency in the ordinary market transac tions, have been finally removed. The only copper coin now seen in the market is the 2-shahi piece which is now accepted for ^-shahi. The old -J- shahi and 1-shahi pieces have entirely disappeared. The old silver coinage has also been withdrawn with the exception of ^-kran pieces which are still in circulation. The silver coins now current in the market are the 2-kran and 1- kran pieces minted by the Imperial Bank of Persia. The total amount of treasure imported into Bushire was Rs. 43,01,661 or an increase of Rs. 14,24,007. The principal countries which contributed to the increase are United Kingdom Rs. 30,00,000, Turkey Rs. 9,60,926 and Persian ports Rs. 3,17,587. The specie imported into Lingah was Rs. 25,12,000 or an increase of Rs. 7 ,06,000. In the export of specie from Bushire there was a decrease of Rs. 6,22,930, while from Lingah there was an increase of Rs. 6,76,000.RESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOE THE YEAH 1901-1902. 13 1 nn 1 ' illg tl 5 e 0 T. tlle ^.T' mule hire for . Slliraz st00(J at krans 95 Mule hire, per 100 m a unds of 7 1 511)8. It went down to 80 krans in April, but in the latter part ot May and during June and July the rate rose to krans 100. Since then it has steadily risen till the quotation at the end of December stood at krans 110. Une unsatisfactory feature in the transport of goods to the interior and which calls tor serious attention on the part of the Persian Government, is the obnoxious practice resorted to by its officials of impressment of pack animals on various pretexts of public emergency. This practice not unfrequently causes serious dislocation in the transport of goods entailing loss and annoyance to the merchants. To secure this impressment, the petty officials start in all directions to catch and blackmail all caravans which may come within their leach. The muleteers who are thus caught, are forced to unload their goods'and to work for the officials without any remuneration. Some muleteers, in order to escape the impressment, pay heavy fines, while others, in order to avoid the harsh treatment, abandon the laden merchandise in any part of the road and fly to the hills. Meanwhile the abandoned goods lie for an indefinite period exposed to all sorts of risks. When the news of the impressment spreads, all caravan traffic ceases for weeks until 'the oppression subsides. Freight.— Preight to London for the first six months of the year graduallv dropped from 25s. to 23^. While in July it further fell to 19s., at which rate it remained standing until December, when owing to competition with a Hussian steamer it declined to ISs. Shipping. One hundred and twelve vessels with a tonnage of 130,273 entered the port of Bushire during the year. Of these, 109 were British and 3 Russian. This, as compared with last year, shows a decline of 2 British, 1 Austrian and 1 Turkish vessels of the tonnage of 9,804, and an increase of 3 Russian of the tonnage of 4,513. The number of vessels which cleared from Bushire is 111 with a tonnage of 132,354. This shows a decrease of 8 British vessels of the tonnage of 3,938 and 2 Austrian of the tonnage of 3,327 and an increase^ of 3 Russian vessels of the tonnage of 4,513, or a net decrease, as com pared with the past year, of 7 ships and 2,687 tons. The number of vessels which entered the port of Lingah is 83 with a tonnage of 91,300 which shows an increase of 3 vessels and 3,300 tons. Of these, 81 were British and 2 Russian. Of those which cleared from Lingah, 45 were British with a tonnage of 49,500 and 3 Russian with a tonnage of 3 ,300. This shows an increase of 9 vessels and 9,900 tons over the figure of the previous year. It appears likely that British shippino 1 will suffer from more serious competition in the future than has been the case in the past, and although the result of the Russian steamer which took cargo from the Gulf to London could not have been very advantageous to those con cerned, it is likely that when trade improves further attempts will be made in this direction. The heavy subsidies which it is said are paid to the Russian steamers will enable them to persevere in their attempts to obtain a share of the trade. Russian Commerce, —A new feature in this year's trade is the establishment of a direct line of steamers between H ussia and the Persian Gulf, inaugurated by the two voyages of the S.S. which brought loaf sugar, kerosine oil, gold-lace and piece-goods, etc., of which the statistics are not available. Customs Administration. —The imposition of 5 per cent, customs duty on both imports and exports for European and native merchants was introduced in the beginning of the Persian official year commencing from the 21st March 1901. This of course met with a good deal of opposition at first on the part of the native merchants. The measure was, however, carried out and has worked smoothly, without having had any appreciable effect on trade. The landing and shipping companies which the late Director of Customs was endeavouring to introduce came to an untimely end by his premature death, and it is unlikely that the project will be renewed again. The facilities for landing and shipping cargo are still inadequate when more than one steamer is in port, and it is very desirable that the customs authorities should take early steps to put the matter on a satisfactory footing. In this connection it may be desirable to mention that until the control of the Gulf port customs was assumed by the present administration, the levy of the customs duties at Lingah was regulated according to a special tariff which wasImports. Exports. Inif nuPOT^T ON THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL ADMIN ISTEAT10N K1POET ON ^ — T ' Tvnrlcr Arab Governors. The com- in vogue from the time ^Hingah is entirely dependent on the fact that mercial importance of the P 0 t ot L ° A b coa8 t, and merchandise imported ' is used ^ a distributmg cei ^-e to the Ara^ ^ ^ or not. paid a into Lingah for re-exportahon abi , ck At the hegmning o thcir nominal transhipment duty ^ so uu P^ fe, th e former practice, hut of late control, the Belgian ^ ular 5 per cent, duty has been levied on aU thev have been more strict and a i c o u . . 1 ^ at tlie time 0 f re-exportation godds imported into Lrngah, and a persisted in, it is possible that Ihen the goods have broken bulk ' t 1 he Al . ab C oast will send their the British and ® ^ transhipment at Lingah, which will no doubt merchandise direct, instead 01 uj tel! upon the prosper! y 0 _ riti h me rchants still suffer from the inatten- Admimstrationof Justice. 1 against Persian subjects. With tion of the Persian Gojernmen to thmcto^ g^ of lead . ng reference to the remarks uudcr th in p eTsia writes that, taking into merchants and a gentlomanof^ J cond itip n s of the country, he consideration tlie sfxaal reh^o ^^ ^ ^ ^ of tho admmls tration of S^rr^advS British merchants to exercise more caution m their dealings, and to avoid giving 3^5x5 wll i ch has been due Cotton Goods.-—The inereas cr edit system, than to actual lb .. Drugs - 0f ^Jfo^s-Theincrease of Ps. 36,289 shown under this head is due to over- speculation, and prices realized were greatly under cost. xr . /-)■ 7 Owino &gt; to keen competition between rival firms m Lushiie, nricefhave gone down considerably. Formerly there was only one firm which useT to import, on a large s^ale K-s/whaTduring the present year it went down to Rs. 3, owing to large shipments which were brought by the S.S. Konnloff. Procisions. —The increase of Rs. 1,66,934 is chiefly due to a large quantity of flour and grain having been imported from Indm owing to high prices ruling in the the local market for wheat, etc. Loaf and Soft Sugar.—the decrease under this head is Rs. 3,42,600 owing to the market being overstocked in the previous year and heavy shipmens having arrived in the early part of the year under review, the prices fell very smartly and business was very much reduced. A steady decline m Marseille , however, led dealers to operate again, but the arrival at the latter part ot year of 4,000 cases again sent prices down. Tea.—The increase of Rs. 3,16,705 is simply due to speculation, and in the maioritv of cases, native merchants who had given laige oideis, ec me o accept the consignments under some pretext or other, owing to the marke being dull. Horses. —The increase under this head is Rs. 22,520. The number of horses exported, though yet small compared with previous years, was an improvement on 1900. Cotton. —This article shows a decline of Rs. 1,79,284 due to a scanty crop and also to a dull market abroad. Almond Kernels. —There has been a large decrease of Rs. 4,01,870. The price of almond kernels which went up very high in the previous year, fell to 60s. in the present year, and there has been no improvement since. Persian sellers on this side having been misled by an unprecedented price of the previous year, invested this year at enhanced prices and did not care to sell unless they could cover cost. Thus a large stock has been left in the country unexported for want of inducement in the consuming markets abroad.residency and maskat political agency for the year 1901-1902. 15 Wheat. —The decline of Rs. 1,59,472 is due to no shipments having been made abroad owing to a partial failure of the crop and heavy prices ruling in the local market. Gwm.—The decline of Es. 1,14,234 is owing to a dull market abroad and large quantities lying uncleared in London did not afford sufficient inducement to shipments being made to any considerable extent. Hides and Skins. —Trade in this article which had dwindled to a consider able extent due to plague and quarantine measures in India, is again regaining its old proportion, and this year the increase recorded is Us. 2,64,970. A large quantity was exported to India and to the United Kingdom. The shipments to India are, as a rule, intended for transhipment abroad. Opium. —The decrease under this head is Es. 5,30,575. Prices in China having fallen heavily, merchants have been unwilling to part with their stock and a large quantity is accumulated in the country. It is said that this fall in price is principally due to adulteration of the drug being carried on to a consi derable extent; and unless some supervision is exercised in the preparation of the drug, Persian opium may eventually be discredited in China. The attention shewn by Japan to Persian opium, is likely to promote exportation to that country. Two Japanese gentlemen, experts in opium, visited the principal opium centres in Persia to study the conditions of the trade and methods of the preparation of the drug. Shells.— decrease under this head is Es. 37,490 due to high prices ruling in the local market, and the markets abroad being overstocked. The export has been in the hands of regular shippers. Tobacco. —The increase of Es. 67,890 is merely nominal. In reality the tobacco crop has been a failure, specially in the Ispahan district, where it is largely cultivated. It is said that the Societe-du-Tombac has sublet its conces sions to a syndicate of Turkish subjects in Beyrout, who have sent a representa tive to Ispahan. This monopoly continues to be distasteful to Persian merchants, but as the Societe pays a certain subsidy to the Persian Government, the priests and the merchants are unable to free themselves from the yoke of the foreign monopolists. Wool. —Though the statistics show an increase of Es. 55,640', yet operations have been disappointing. The expected prices which led to the shipments were not realized. Carpets. —The decrease of Es. 2,53,384 is due to the overstocked state of the markets abroad, in consequence of which, shipments fell considerably. C. A. KEMBALL, His Britannic Majesty's Acting Consul-General for Fars, Khuzistan, etc. Busutre ; The 31st March 1902.f t r ll:- i ^ 16 administration report on the appendix a TO PART III. tabular statistics. Consisting of the following statistics ^ ^ the years 1899j 1900) 190l I. Return of principal articles of exp 1899 ;1900 1901 _ 2 Return of principal articles of import into Huslure auni ^ ^ Return of total number and tonnage of vessels of each nation that entered at the port 0f TRcS » of vessels of each nation that cleared from the port 0£ B f Rettfof iSlartlts^fei' from Lingah during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. 6 Return of principal articles of import into Lingah during the years 1899, W 01 ' J! Return of total number and tonnage of vessels of each nation that entered at the port of Lino-ah during the years 1899, 1900, 19U1. ,, , i a f 8 &amp; Return of total number and tonnage of vessels of each nation that cleared from le port of Lingah during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. p -p • 9. Return of principal articles of export from the ports on the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. i , ^ p x&gt; • 10. Return of principal articles of import into the ports on the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the years 1899, 1900, 19U1. . , . j j . u, f II, Return of total number and tonnage of vessels f entered at 4 p0r ' 3 on the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. 12. Return of total number and tonnage of vessels of «ch nation that cleared from the ports on the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the years 1899, 1900, 1001. 13. Abstract table of exports to principal countries from all the ports specified in the Persian Gulf during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. • • 14. Abstract table of imports from principal countries into all the ports specified m t le Persian Gulf during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. 15. Abstract table showing the total number and tonnage of vessels of each nation that entered at all the ports specified in the Persian Gulf during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. 16. Abstract table showing the total number and tonnage of vessels of each nation that cleared from all the ports specified in the Persian Gulf during* the years 1899, 1900, 1901. 17. Return of principal articles of export from Shiraz during the years 1899, 1900, 1901. 18. Return of principal articles of import into Shiraz during the years Ls99, 1900, 1901.18 ADMINISTRATION EEPOET 01. THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL Micks exported fro* the Port of stateuent ^in 9 Ue Jota^ Value^^ Principal articles and principal countries to which exported. Dyeing and Coloueing Mate eials — United Kingdom India Turkey • Egypt . Bahrein • Arab Coast Persian Ports Feuits and Vegetables— Almonds— United Kingdom India Germany America Turkey . Mas Bat • Persian Ports Almond Kernals~~ United Kingdom India t France . Germany Russia . America Turkey . Persian Ports Baisins and Currants United Kingdom India Turkey . Cbina Maskat t Bahrein . Persian Ports Other sorts of fruits, etc United Kingdom India Turkey . • Egypt . Tklaskat . Zanzibar w Bahrein Persian Ports . Geain and Pulse— Wheat— United Kingdom India . • • Maskat Persian Ports * Barley— United Kingdom India Persian Ports * Bice— United Kingdom India Turkey . Zanzibar Bahrein Arab Coast Persian PortsEESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR THE YEAR 1901-1902. 73 Si P art IV.—TRADE REPORT FOR MASQAT, 1901-1902. The total value of trade for the year as furnished by His Highness's Customs Department is returned at 4,637,764 dollars as against 4,725,776 of last year, showing a decrease of 88,013 dollars. Last year there was an increase on the import side ; this year the imports are responsible for the decrease, the figures falling from 3,365,883 to 2,996,688. The chief items which have contributed to this result are : — 1. Arms. —Due partly to the loss of the Basuto and the fact that a number of cases from the last two ships have not as yet been taken delivery of. Also it is hoped that the culminating point of this traffic was touched last year and that the demand will now decline. 2. Cereals. —One ship laden with cereals foundered en route from Calcutta; and a large quantity arrived too late for the duty to be enclosed in the year's account. 3. Coffiee. —Last year's import was abnormal. This year's calls for no special remark. 4. 6^.—Imports evidently affected by events in China. The market is still uncertain. E xports . There has been an increase in the value of exports this year, the figures standing at 1,641,076 as against 1,359,893 dollars last year. The items mainly accounting for the increase are ;— 1. Dates.—The season was a prosperous one for the Mascat date-trade, the quality being good and in demand. 2. Dried fish. —Here again the increase is due to a prosperous season. There seems nothing further in the returns calling for special notice. P. Z. COX, Major, His Britannic Majesty's Consul and Bolitical Agent, Mascat. 8,450 cases 455 cwts. 38,750 bak 6 3,780 „ l' 3,500 caw I 1,250 „ ! Ho „ i 28 „ ; 1,975 „ „ 1,175 „ | 2,280 „ 1,800 cwtj. •; 3,960 „ 1,250 slabi. 1,250 wts, 235 cases 675 „ 2,250 'RESIDENCY AND MASK AT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR THE YEAR 1901-1902. 77 P ART V.—EEPOET ON THE TEADE OE MOHAMMEEAH EOR THE YEAR 1901. ABSTRACT OF CONTENTS. General. Caravan routes. Exchaoge. Agriculture. Exports. Health. Imports. River trade. Shipping. Statistics. General. —Owing to the failure of crops, trade was generally depressed. Exchange. —Exchange ranged from 51 to 55 kraiis to the £ sterling, the accompanying statistics are calculated at 53 krans to £1. Exports. —The returns only show export of dates by steamers and coasting Dates, craft under British (Indian) flag. . The increase shown in gum and oil-seeds is chiefly from the 1900 crop. Imports. —There was generally a decrease in imports chiefly due to the . famine, hut partly owing to Bombay steamers calling at Koweit during the last six months of the year. In addition to the figures given in the annexed tables there was a large Food stuffs, import of wheat and rice by river boats and coasting craft. There was a certain demand for rice for the Hawizeh district owing to the shortness of the crop there, due to lowness of the rivers. Hawizeh usually exports rice. The town markets were well supplied with imported food stuffs. There was a large increase in the import of coffee, but this article is chiefly for re-shipment to Koweit. The increase in Eussian kerosine oil is due to Indian sailing boats bringing Kerosine. this article up for sale when coming to buy dates. Prices in consequence dropped from ten shillings to four shillings per case. The trade in Manchester ^oods shared the general depression, but at end of cotton goods. December there was a slight revival and increase in demand for Shuster. The principal cotton goods in demand and prices are as given last year. Shippirig. —Twenty steamers called with cargo from and eight took cargo for Europe. The vessels of the two Bombay Companies called regularly. Eeturns of sailing craft under foreign flag are not obtainable. Ereight to London ranged from £1-2-6 to £l»12-6. To Marseilles £1-7-6 Freight, to £1-17-6, and to Bombay from 8s. to 18s. 8d. The Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company's steamer ran fort- River, nightly to Bunder Nasri. The steamer running on the upper river was brought down to dock at the end of 1900, ^nd owing to the lowness of the river was unable to re-cross the rapids after repairs. Cargo was conveyed from Ahwaz to Shuster by lighter. The water was never more than 8 feet above and sank to 2 feet below previous lowest level at Nasri. Ereight from Mohammerah to Nasri is about 8s., 12s. and 15s. according to description of goods. Caravan routes. —There was a small increase in trade by this route, Ahwaz-ispahea. especially in opium. Owing to the great scarcity of fodder many of the local mules were taken to other districts to feed, and the Ispahan muleteers cannot be induced to take cargo by a route on which their villages are not situated. Caravans with opium have done the distance in 15 days, but usuallv caravans take 20 days from Ispahan to Ahwaz. The caravan route from Dizful to Khoremabad was practically closed jizMi-Khorem- through the year owing to lawlessness of the tribes. Agriculture. —The wheat crop was a total failure owing to the absence of spring rains. Prices at Nasri rose to 32s. per maund of 3J cwts. Krans 100.^: 1 Krans 10, Krans 17. Grhee. Xrans 7.- Krans 12. 78 ADMINISTRATION BEPOET ON THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL ■^1. Prospects for next harvest are not good, but depend on the March rains; a much smaller quantity than usual has been sown. ^ ^ , , , The date crop promised well, but owing to continued hot winds and dust a portion of it was spoilt. Prices were about 3 S . KU per maund of li cwt. til after packing for Europe was completed, then owing to the unusual number of coasting craft arriving to purchase dates prices gradually rose to 6s. 3d. Clarified butter which in March was 2s. Id. per 6 lbs. rapidly rose to 4s. 6d. per 6 lbs. owing to want of fodder. Health. During July small-pox appeared in Mohammerah and neighbour ing villages and was epidemic during the rest of the year, being very severe in September and October. Biver trade—A large part of the river cargo now consists of through shipments to or from .Ahwaz where the customs dues on such cargo are collected, transhipped at Mohammerah. For the purpose of comparison with previous years all such cargo in the attached tables is included in the Mohammerah exports and imports. Messrs. Lynch Brothers have supplied statistics of the imports and exports of the Port of Nasri (Ahwaz) which are attached to show the amount of cargo conveyed by river. i ii i . i iiii 'U 'M !■86 AWIISISTB a TION REPORT ON THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL P ART VI.— TRADE REPORT OE BANDAR ABBAS FOR THE YEAR 1901 • Bs. 72 at 114. Ils.26 at 57- ~bSl» Su'i ''1 favourably ojramra will. tb»e ot praadlug ,«» fn recovering from tlie effects of heavy decline last yeai. The rise 0 in exports amovmted to Rs. 7,79,064 compared with the year 1900 -swat .&lt;v - •iswssctas ss tsyrirS'iSwi'''&gt;» 01 'i&gt;« f'' T' 01 ' !»?«■ buted Sfpally to piece-goods, yam and twist, drags and medicines indigo, glaffi and glassware, g P rain fnd pulse, hardware, wmes, matches, oils, spices, silk piece -goods, loaf sugar and woollen piece-goods. ^ Harvest.—The grain crop during the year has not been as productive as was anticipated owin| to the failure of late rains. In consequence of wjjich the ^eM has been below the average. A good deal of gram and pulse was brought from Karachi at the latter part of the year, as there has been a brisk demand for the same from up-country, brought about by the scanty rainfall. Ep o the date of this report, viz., 12th March 1902, there has been practically no rainfa whatever for the last 12 months, and there is no douit that the country will have to face a famine during the ensuing year. ^ Exchange.—The exchange opened with 3^ krans per rupee and varied m the course of the year from 3f krans at the close of the cold season to 3 8 krans per rupee with the advent of the hot weather when rupees were much easier. Consequently the rate per pound sterling fluctuated between 51 and ol krans. Transport. —The rates of hire for carriage up-country have undergone considerable change for the better, varying from 25 to 40 tomans per load ot 1,400 lbs. to Yezd, while the rate for Kerman per load of /00 lbs. varied trom 9 to 18 tomans. It is greatly feared in some quarters that fewer animals will visit bandar Abbas in course of the current year on account of fodder being scarce in these parts, and that the rate will consequently go up much higher as was the case last year. Shipping, —There have been a large number of steam vessels calling at this port during the year with large quantities of cargoes both from England and India which is shown to be one-third greater than the preceding year. The reason for this extraordinary increase in the number of arrivals has been due to large shipments of food stuffs to meet the failure of the crops. The total tonnage of vessels that entered at and cleared from the port ot Bandar Abbas during the period under review has been put down respectively at tons 156,260 and 156 J 20J, showing a respective increase of tons 9,35G and * 8,982. Telegraph. —I may add in conclusion that the mercantile community ot this port consider that if the telegraph system of the Persian Gulf cable be extended to Bandar Abbas, British trade of this port would be greatly benefited thereby. C. H. BOXER, Captain, Sis Britannic Majesty's Vice-Consul, Bandar Jbbas. Bandar Abbas; The 12th March 1902.% 3 L 152 Tom, IP RESIDENCY AND MASKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOE THE YEAR 1901 -1902. 99 P art VII.—REPOET ON THE TRADE AND COMMEECE OE THE BAHREIN ISLANDS EOR 1901. The total trade of Bahrein during 1901 approached to within a lakh and-a- General half of that for 1899, which was the most prosperous year in the annals of the Remark s» Islands. The increase is Bs. 52,34,960 on the figures for 1900, and is principally due to the large importations of Indian rice and a successful pearling season. The exports are in excess of the imports by Bs. 2,23,220. The Pearl Eishery opened on the 8th May and continued to the 9th Septem ber. The operations were very satisfactory, and the export proved to be the largest on record, and of a better average in quality. The demand for small pearls appearing at the end of 1900 continued into the year under review, and in the latter part of the season the larger sizes of pearls advanced in price. The transactions are said to have proved profitable, and only in one case a loss w r as reported. The pearl merchants state that the improvement in the price is due to an anticipation of large sales of the gem being effected in Europe owing to the approaching Coronation of His Majesty King Edward VII. Business in all branches of the trade has been profitable throughout the year. Bice, however, owing to excessive importations, fell slightly in the last quarter, but not below r the imported price. Bice is generally sold on the credit system, realizing profits from 20 to 40 per cent, according to the period arranged which seldom exceeds nine months. Settlements of accounts are effected in April, when cash advances can be obtained by the pearl-divers from the masters of the pearling craft, and at the termination of the date and pearling seasons in August and September. Cotton piece-goods and other merchandise are sold also on credit and payable in weekly instalments. The past year is remarkable for the largest importations of cotton piece- goods on record. Bahrein supplies the adjacent coast and its hinterland where trade routes run to Nejd and beyond, and it may be assumed that when those parts are more settled the trade is likely to increase, the fact, therefore, ought to be borne in mind by British firms desirous of extending their business. The use of tea is slowly becoming more general, and though the quantity imported is insignificant, it shows a steady rise and likely to improve in the future. The importation of coffee has developed considerably and Brazilian brands are now competing successfully against the productions of India and Ceylon. A new r feature in the classification of shells has been introduced in the statistical tables in the hope that it will be more comprehensible to the merchants trading in the commodity. The mother-of-pearl and mussel, as also a certain quantity of oyster shells—known to the trade as Linga shells—are imported from the coast of Katr and the island of Dalma off Abu Thabi. Ihe oyster shells exported from Bahrein are regarded as the best obtainable in the Persian Gulf, being of a better average and heavier than those shipped from other ports. The first description of shells are sold by weight and the oyster by measure ; the ordinary rice-bag being used for the purpose, and the price of the latter in the uncleaned state ranged from Bs. 1J to Bs. 3 the bag. The German firm of Messrs. Prins and Stiirken of Hamburg opened a branch business in Bahrein in the second quarter of the year. The conditions of trade obtaining in Bahrein have also attracted a number of Persian traders and Jews who are said to be doing well. A schedule of the rate of lighterage on cargo brought to Bahrein by steamers is annexed for the information of merchants. The imports exceeded those of 1900 by nearly twenty-seven and three imports, quarter lakhs of rupees. The imports from India represented more than two-thirds of the w r hole and show an advance of nearly seventeen lakhs exclusive of specie which was greater by Bs. 8.17,770. Building materials improved to the extent of Bs. 4,170; coffee Bs. 1,85,945 ; coir and rope, Rs. 1,320 ; cotton piece-goods, Bs. 5,00,0C0 ; JlMASKVT POLITICAL AGENOY FOR THE YEAR 1901.1903. 101 ShippingThe rrumber and tonnage of steamers that put in at Bahrein exceeded those of 1900 by 17 vessels and 21,342 tons. Austria again sent one vessel of 1,750 tons to this port and the remainder were British. The British Companies' running steamers from India are the British India Steam Navigation Company which sent 65 vessels, and the Bombay and Persian Steam Navigation Company which despatched 5 vessels. The British and Colo- nial, and the Anglo-Arabian and Persian Steam Navigation Companies running to London sent one vessel each. J. CALCOTT GASKIN, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein ; The 7th February 1902. Schedule of the rate of Lighterage for the Port of Bahrein. Rs. a. p. Rice, Wheat; Barley, Flour, Moong, Pulse, Potatoes, Onions, and the like . . . . . @ 5 8 0 per 100 packages. Coffee, Sugar, Pepper, Cardamoms, Turmeric, *5 Hamez, Ginger, Wire, Towas, Nails, Anchors, Ground-nuts, Mortars, Lead, and Sal ammoniac @ 7 0 0 Piece-goods, Sowaheli or small bales, and English packed bales, whether large or small and in cases and Yam in bundles . . . . . @ 0 5 0 „ package. Tallow in packages containing 4 tins. Fruits in boxes or in crates and Loaf Sugar in cases . , @ 0 2 0 }&gt; )} Kerosine Oil ....... @ 4 0 0 „ 100 cases. Zeera rice 3 0 0 „ ,, Robbins. Coir and Coir Rope @ 1 0 0 „ Candy (560 lbs.) Crockery in cases ...... 1 0 0 „ package. Lemon ....... @ 0 12 0 )) )) Cotton, Walnuts, Henna, Pomegranate Rind, Halwa, and Senna leaves .... @ 0 10 0 Wire Kegs, Alum, and Tar .... @ 0 5 0 &gt;y v Grain, Raisins, Sandalwood and Lozenges, etc. @ 0 1 6 &gt;&gt; 99 Iron ..... ... @ 0 VI 0 „ Candy (560 lbs.). Tobacco from Turkish Arabia and Oman . f @ 0 4 0 ,, package. Charcoal ....... @ 10 0 0 „ 100 mat bags. Pulleys, Cane Sticks, and Dried Fish , , . @ 0 3 0 „ package. Split Bamboos ...... @ 10 0 0 ,, 100 packages. Cinnamon, Candles, and Tea .... @ 0 2 0 „ package.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000301_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/V/23/80, No 392</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000301</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/V/23/80, No 392</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Administration report on the Persian Gulf Political Residency and Maskat Political Agency for 1901-1902’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1902/1902</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T02:23:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (60 folios)</extent><extent>The report is arranged into a number of parts and sections, with tabulated statistical data directly following written sections. There is a contents page at the front of the report (folio 3), which refers to the report’s internal pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Administration Report on the Persian Gulf Residency and Maskat [Muscat] Political Agency for 1901-02, published by the Office of the Superintendent of Government Printing, India, Calcutta [Kolkata], forming part of the Selections from the Records of the Government of India, Foreign Department, and based on reports sent to Government by the Political Resident and other Agents in the Persian Gulf.The Administration Report is organised as follows:1.
                           General Summary, submitted by Lieutenant-Colonel Charles Arnold Kemball, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated 21 April 1902 (folios 4-6), with overviews of: the year’s rainfall and harvest, and the impact of drought; the governorship of Bushire and Gulf ports; public peace; public health; currency; customs administration in the Gulf, under Belgian control; settlement of claims for compensation. The General Summary also includes summaries for key towns and regions, chiefly comprising accounts of local politics: Oman and Muscat; the Oman Coast; Bahrain; Koweit [Kuwait] and Nejd, including details of the loss of a decisive battle by Shaikh Mubarak al-Sabah at the hands of the Amir of Nejd, and the capture of Riadh [Riyadh] by Abdul Aziz [Ibn Sa‘ūd]; Persian Arabistan; Fars and the Persian Coast; Persian Baluchistan. Further reports are included on: the slave trade, including numbers of slaves manumitted by British officials in the region; incidents of piracy; naval movements, chiefly British but also Russian and French vessels; changes in British official personnel; and movements and changes in foreign representatives. An appendix to part 1 comprises statistical tables with meteorological data for the region.2.
                           Administration Report of the Muscat Political Agency, 1901-02, submitted by Major Percy Zachariah Cox, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul and Political Agent at Muscat, dated 2 April 1902 (folios 7-9) including: an account of recent tribal politics of Oman, most notably disturbances at Wadi Maawal; events in Sohar; ill-treatment of British Indian subjects in Muscat and Oman; customs; arms trafficking; pearl disputes; the death of the Sultan’s Vazir [Wazir], Sayyid Saeed bin Mahomed bin Salimin, and a brief account of his life; opening of the Muscat to Jask telegraph cable; epidemics and preventative measures; the slave trade; and naval movements.3.
                           Trade Report of the Persian Gulf for the Year 1901, submitted by Kemball, in his capacity at His Britannic Majesty’s Acting Consul-General for Fars, Khuzistan, etc., dated 31 March 1902 (folios 9-39), with summaries on: imports and exports; the harvest; exchange; currency and specie; mule hire; freight and shipping activity; Russian commerce; customs administration; administration of justice; further details of imports and exports, with reference to particular commodities including cotton, medicines, kerosene, opium and shells. An appendix follows with tabulated trade data of the principal imports and exports, and number, tonnage and nationality of vessels.4.
                           Trade Report for Maskat[Muscat],
                           1901-02, submitted by Cox (folios 40-41), with brief summaries on the import of arms, cereals, coffee and silk, and the export of dates and dried fish. An appendix follows the report, containing tabulated trade statistics.5.
                           Report on the Trade and Commerce of Mohammerah[Khorramshahr]
                           for 1900(folios 42-46), with remarks on: exchange; exports; imports; shipping; caravan routes; agriculture; health; and the river trade. An appendix follows the report, containing tabulated trade data.6.
                           Trade Report of Bundar Abbas[Bandar-e ʻAbbās]
                           for the Year 1901, submitted by Captain C H Boxer, His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul at Bandar-e ʻAbbās, dated 12 March 1902 (folios 46-52), with remarks on: the value of imports and exports; harvest; exchange; transport; shipping; and the benefits to British trade that an extension of the telegraph cable to Bandar-e ʻAbbās would bring. An appendix follows the report, containing tabulated trade data.7.
                           Report on the Trade and Commerce of the Bahrein Islands for the Year 1901, submitted by John Calcott Gaskin, Assistant Political Agent, dated 7 February 1902 (folios 53-60), containing remarks on: total trade in Bahrain; the year’s pearl fishing season; importation of cotton and coffee; exports, including oyster shells; imports from India, Turkey and Persia; weights and measures in Bahrain; shipping; and a schedule of the lighterage rates at the Port of Bahrain. An appendix follows the report, containing tabulated trade data.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Bandar Abbas</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bandar-e ʻAbbās</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Agriculture</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Meteorological data</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000301#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>