<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000197_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-30T19:43:18.348Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">11 ■ ' ™ ■ ■■ ■ - Received under B; the 5th March 1£ 46, S&amp;’ EXT hra 1 I 9&lt;i c Y . M r - T/O^icuidloOvv 2. tD i g Vr 5 *^! % ^ j feem^nt No. C/256, dated ^ '&gt;/ '&lt;1 Transfixion of letter dated 28th Jafar 1365 (Sl.l.'dS) from Bhaikh Ahmed bin Rashid, Ruler of Uram-ul-Qaiwain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Your honourable }.etber dated 23rd January lb46 corresponding to 20th Bafar 1365 has reached me, the contents of which I have noted. In reply I inform Your Excellency that should I wish to grant permission to a Bank to open a branch or Agency for the Bank in my country as mentioned in Article 25 of the concession I shall obtain the approval of His Majesty's Government before entering into any negotiations with the Bank. CONFIDENTIAL. No.328-B. cP Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. Dated the 27th March 1L46. r Forwarded with compliments to: * •S 1. H.f ' s oecretary of State for India, •India Office, LONDON. 2. Secretary to the Government of India . in the External Affairs Department NEW DELHI. • with reference to Residency .telegram No.46 dated 8th January 1946 (copy forwarded to Government of India under Residency Endorsement No.4b-S dated the 8thoacrJO J TELEGRAMS : INLAND t PETCONCE8S. FlNSQUARE, LONDON. FOREIGN i PETCONCESS, LONDON. errv»«ATE-HtDusc. (^) 3 Ling House, Ftf^oecmv -sooahf^e. Dominion Street, London, e.c.z/j. The Under-Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. 18th February, 1946. Sir, We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter (Ext.629/46) of the 16th February enclosing the Agreement between His Majesty's Government and this Company, regarding the Umm-al-Qaiwain Concession, and fifty additional copies of that Agreement. We have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servants, For PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED,0? GOD IK »fT- r iv LiCIPUL Thia is an ^greencnt iaclo at Urn-al-Qaiwain on the tv?ontieth day of i arch, 1945&gt; corresponding to the sixth day of llnbia II 1364 he J a?cen Hid E CELLHRCY SHJlIIQ: iJE^D 3M Iu.jIIID -n the exercise -f his powers as KUIJE of \I2i-^Lr&lt;yiIWAIN iE4J3Lv, on his own behalf and ai behalf of and in the none jf his heirs and success ra in when is or shall be vested f :r the tine bein^ the responsibility for ttie control and Govornnent of the IoTaTH 0 ? E: *'.lL- 0 ^IbhE? (hereinafter called 'THE SEVIIIi') of the one part and PEEiOIEUli CONCEodlOHS LIhITEE, a Company resisted in Great Britain under the Cor^)anics ..ct, 19254 (hereinafter called 'THE COiiEdlY') its successors and assigns of the second part, ittfIC jIE 1, (a) The area to- which this .p'rocnent applies is the Etato of Er'i-al-Qaiwaiii, ^jrabia, including all Islaius and Territorial ;;aters appertaining thereto, (hereinafter referred to as 'THE o'EEE') 'being all that Territory included in the Shaikhdon of Um-a 1-Qaiwain. The Shaikh agrees that when the Territorial limits of the State of Un: -nl-Qaiwain have been deter lined, the area covered by the Conccssi 'n will be coterninous with the lirdts so ueternined, (b) Nothing in this agreement shall be read as restricting - in any way - the right of the Shaikh to grant to others a lease or permit over an area or areas to be used f r the purpose of constructing an aerodrome and appurtenances thereto for either aeroplanes or seaplanes; and such area, or areas if and so granted shall be entirely excluded far the purpose of this agreement, EtTICLE 2, The porxod of this ^igreenont shall be 75 Calendar years from the date of signature. The expression year, month and Cay -used in this ixgreooent shall mean what is consistent V/ith the English Solar Calendar and not any other, further, the weights mentioned Ln tills agreement shall be reckoned on the English T .&gt;n of 2,240 lbs. AiiTICLE 3* The Shaildi hereby grants to the Corxpany the exclusive right, to explore search for drill for produce and wan natural gas asphalt ozokerite crude petroleum and thmir products and cognate substances (hereinafter referred to as 'THE JlBEEJ'iCEE') within the State, the exclusive ownership of all the Substances so produced and won, the right to refine transport sell for use within and without the State or for expert and t j export or otherwise deal with or dispose of the Substances, and the right to import export pump ship or otherwise transport the Substances acres, or to any country or place at the Company ’ a discretion and the right t . do all tilings necessary for the purpose of these operations, jETICIE 4. If hereafter any neutral E-.no is created adjacent to the territory of the dtato, wherein the Shaikh shall have a co equal and joint interest, the Shaikh hereby agrees to grant to the O' 1 .pony an oil concession ver such neutral zone on terms to be agreed between the Shaikh, the Company and the joint ruler of such Neutral Zone. EdTICiE 5. In con s r. l. erat i &gt; n of the rights granted by the Shaikh by this hgreosmnt the Company shall pay t the Shaikh,(a) on si-jRaturo of the as'roencnt hupooe .jirby th usrjiC (Td) Ru.xics I'.-z hunclrccl thouac-ix' within a periwc ^ ninty (60) claya fron the date up..n '.;hich the Conpany docla.ro 3 in vn. j-ting to tlic Lihaildi that substances have boon discovered in Conner oral quantities. If the Conpany should fail t . ducloj so socnor &gt; then the date of discovery of substances in cn.nercial quontities sha^l be that date upon ’which the Corpany has conoloted and tested a 'well or uells capable of pr.xlucin^ in accordance with first class oil practice not loss than two thousand (2000) dnplish Tons of clean substances per day for a period wf tiiLrty ( 30 ) consecutive days. (c&lt;) Hupees Twenty f ^ur thousand at the end of each year fron the date of s:-.; natuiv hereof until the Conpany declares in writing t- the Shaikh that Substances have been disc&gt;verod m cor' nrcial quantities m accordance with the Sub-Clause (b) of this bioticlo 3* or until the Company can \encos i'rouucti.ni from quantities less than connorcial quantities. In the event -f such Production by the Conpapy quantities less than cornnrcial quantities either Kupecs Pifty thousand per year of rupees 3 (throe ) per English T n of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances s, w-. n and savctl shall be payable, whichever is the greater, (cO At the end of every year from, the date upon which the Cor.par^ makes in writing t the Sliaihh the do cl;.x at i :&gt;n tint the Substances liave been discovered in conn reial quantities Aupees ninety thousand or Aupees 3 (Three.-) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances ther tiu.m natural gas, won and saved durin c j the preceding Calendar yore, w3 sichcvor is the greater* (e) Annas 2 (two) per 1,0X30 cubic feet of natural gas produced and sold. In calculating royalty for the purpose of this .rticlo account shall not be taken of any of the substances used by the Coiapany in its operatians -r used by the Corpary’s e-ployees within the State, necessary for their use, nor f any water or foreign m.tter wliich may be produced with tVx bub stances. ifiTfCTAl 6 , The Co piiy shall net carry on aiy operations within areas occupied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. ifiTICLE 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific methods am shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the Ingres of water to '.ny petroleum-bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive mles drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Co .pany ,hall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be trdated as confidential. .AiTICIE 3* V/itliin three m.onths after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement ,f the amount of the Substances won and saved and in the case of natural gas produced and sold during the said calendar year, and . f the royalty which is or might have been payable ui;dcm article 'j&gt;, together with a ■ jport of its operati ms during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to chock such returns and statements, end all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company's operations sliall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh.iJlTICLE 9. (^) The Co: ipr.r.y shall have the ri;jht to inpert water, the Jubstances, fuel, nacliinc.ry, notor-cars an.:: lorries, aircraft, equipnent, plr.nt, tinb^r, utensils, iron i/ork, bu^lCiiio mtc .rials, food supplies, nedicines, ncdical sullies, office equipnent and h usehold furniture, raid other natcrials, cquipnent and goods of what sever natu. e required by the C 'Upany and its employees for the purpose of its jperations hereunder and to export the dubstances and articles previ ;usiy inported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on a.ll personal g. ods, clothing and general merchandise imported by the Company f ar the personal use of its Oi ipleyces or l\r resale to them the erdin'ry duty in force f r the time being in the otate. Savin , as in ijrticle S and in this .article provided, the Company, ios personnel, its operations, income, profits and property including the Substances shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future harbour duties, imp. rt duties, expert oucios, taxes, imposts and charges of any hme t'vhcttmr State or local, tolls and land, surface rent of whatever nature. In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay in addition to the li yalty of Rupees (3) tiiroc per ton as provided in ^article f - to the Shaildi wit.iin (3) tlirce months after the close of oach calendar year the sum of (L) four annas per English ton of d,240 lbs, in respect of the Substances won and saved durin the said calendar year. (e) The importation by the Company of firearms and other vonp .-im is prohibiten, except with the written permission .. f the Shaiich, (c) TJie Company nay import such alcoholic drinks a.nd liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only witii the ••ritten permission or t)ie ghr-.ikh, a.nd the Political Ag^nt, Bahrain, or ary authority deputed by them, but the C mp-iny shall not sell or give .alcoholic drinks or liquors to the Slibjocts of the Shaikh or to cho Suojects ex adj -ining jiulers wh m.ay be e .oloycd within the St at eg ARTICLE 10. The employees of the Company sh .11 be allowed to enter into and t d leave ohu State ; .i all times without let or hindrance a.nd free of all charge, amid the Slmikh shall grant to the Coi ipany *s employees every facility required for the purpose of the Company * s operations hereunder, Buc the Coi.pany 1 s employees shall net iiiterfer’o or b v their actions canoe any disturbance or cause opposition to the :dhailch t s authority with .n the State of Umi.i-al-Qaiwain and the empl-yces siiall n t ;.p oeyond the liLii t of tnuar duties when employe^: within v.r when leaving the confines of the State of Unn-al-Qaiwain for the purpose f this Agreer.ient • further in the eve no oi any of the Company* s empl yoos - whether hu be a senior of a junior erTployee-corfitting exx offence which ixy cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or interfere with the politics or Subjects of the .jt .te of Um&gt;*al-Qaiwain or excite then to sedition, then the Shaikh nay apply to the Political Agent, Bafirain, ts send, the person concerned - if a foreigner - out of the State of Unn-al-Qaiwain but if a Subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh may arrest the culprit and deal with him according to the laws of the State of Um-a^-Qaiwain. /article 11 *i&amp;Tieiii n. (a) For the yurpoiio of its .vper'-tions hcrcunCoi* the Coipr.ny sh^.ll hr.vo the ri;jht *./ith.&gt;ut hineranco to construct, naintain and operate power stations, refineries, pipelines ana stora.je tanice, fexilities for water supply including boring for water, telegraph mC telephone lines ani' 1 . installations ana wireless installations, r. :.Ps, railways, trar.xways, bu-..Icings, ports, harbours, haro.ur works, aircraft, buildings and lahaing places for aircraft, whexves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, with such ligirtin'-: as nay bo requisite and arq' ether facilities or works which tho Ccnpany ney consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payuents any st .nc, son*., gre.vel, gypsun, line, clay or sinilar materials or water which oiy be available provided alv/ays that the inhabitants of the ntato — e not prevented fro:. taking their usual require!units of those : .atonals and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nonad pcpulation who nay bo dependent -..n the sane is nob endangered, i'ho Ce:pany at its discretion nay select the position of any suc.^i works, fhc Conpany nay likewise install and operate without hindrance all such oeans of transportation by l;ind, air and \iater as nay bo necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder provided it as for the purposes of this .qqrooiaont, (b) The Conpany shall under norar.l conditions accept and transmit free of chorge -’ii its wireless and telegraph installatl-ns such of the fjhaikh r s nossages as will not intorforc with the Corpoany's business, *.nd in ti cs of national or.crgoncy the Shailch. shall have the necessary use froe of charge of the Co;:paxy*s wire.less and telegraph installations 'and railways for governmental purposes, (c) The Shaikh’s ships- shall have the right to use harbours utilised or c &gt;nstructcd by the C : .&gt;nrpany provided that such use in no way hampers the Cemp .ny &gt;r interf eres in any way with the sax ety or its .-peratiuns of diieh the Conpaiiy sh.11 'bo the solo judge. Any wharves or appurtenar.ceo c i tructod by the; C-wipary shall be for its exclusive use. The Company way use f r the purpose f its operations the harbovu-’s along the c w-.ts of tho dtato, but tho Conpany shall not impede or interfere itli tlio subjects of the Shaikli or their right to continue the use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by then for their sailing craft and fishing brats. *duTICLb 12, The Company shall have the nglit and be ;;iven the necessary facilities: (a) for the import of the Substances into the State from and adjoining territory by pipe linos or otherwise for the purpose of operatui : any refinery which the Company may decide to erect within the State, and (b) for the transport of tho Substances by pipe-linos or otherwise over and across tho State fro.. and to any adjoining territory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the Substances, And no duties, taxes, oh rges or duos of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in rvspect of such import or transport, ARTICLE 13. (a) The Company shall have free of cost tho unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all /uncultivated© 8&gt; - 5 - uncultivated lands of the State yhich the Conpany nay need f.r the purpose of its operations and in particular the Conpany shall have the ri^ht to select an area or are &amp;£&gt; of land chosen by the Conpany with exclusive surface rights upon which t^ erect drilling rigs, punp-s tat ions, oil-refineries, storage, teminal, shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Conpary’s operations; and the Conpany nay buy or lease for such purposes any lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terns of such purchase or lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities, (b) The Conpany shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its jperations .under this Agreenent. The Conpany shall inforn the Shaikh fTon tine to tine of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Conpany fron the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Conpany to the Shaikh free of cost, ARTICLE 14. (a) The Conpany shall have the right to purchase at current uarket rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its operations hereunder; further the Shaikh grants to the Conpany the right to construct new roads for motor and general traffic, and to make use of all present and future roads or tracks free of charge, or taxes of any kind whatever. . 00 The Conpany shall employ Subjects of the Shaikh as fox as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the uonpany ! s skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour shoulo in tiie judgment ol the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Conpc»ny shall nave the rignt to import labour, preference being given to labourers fro: neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. . The Company shall also have the right to imp ort skilled and technical employees. The Conpany shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such vjage to be decioeu and ^stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing Subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever, alter the Status of such employees in respect of their rights, privileges and duties as Subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain in all ways, subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Kuler of the State of Umm-*al.'Qaiw a in, ;ARTICLE 1^, The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway- robbery,^assault, wilful damage and destruction, and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the ohaikh permits othexvi/ise to assist in protecting the jaroperty of the Company ana its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accomodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. ARTICLE 16, In measuring the Substances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be siidi f igm o as may be oeterminec and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Conpany after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. /The Company- 6 - The Conpany shall neasure the Substances 'by a nethjd customarily usee m pood technical practice anl the Shaikh by his representative ouly authorised by him shall have the ri^ht to observe such measurir^ ana to examine and test whatever appliances nay be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply uith all necessary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident: and shall make all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the Company's oporaoions. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to ee put m order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be discovered an any such appliance, such error shall - of the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company's explanation - be considered to hav 3 existed for Three (3) Calendar Months previous to the discovery thereof or from the last occasion of examining the sane in case such occasion shall uu within such period of Three Calendar Months and the Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly, if the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any noasur ng appliances it liall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or has reoresentative to enable a representative of the Shaikh to be present durim such alteration, repair or replacement# ° ihe Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh 3 ha ^ c access at a11 reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts' from then. Such records shall be treated eonfidencial oy the shaikh and his representative. , J ‘f?’ ICLE 17 ‘ rj?he Company shall have the right at any time alter the expiry or three years from the date of signature of this agreement to give the Shaikh six months' notice in writing of its intention to terminate this -grcement and this agreement shall notice 617 e ‘ Cerrane on the datd fixed f ^ such termination in such If 1 such natlce 1x3 hiven not later than 30 ye.ars after the cate of such signature the Company shall be entitled on such aetermination to remove free of all taxes and duties all olant builaing scores material and property of every sort provided that for a pence of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase - should be so desire - the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less depreciation which price shall e agreee or failing agreement settled under article 24 hereof. nf* c, If S ? Ch n °? ice u be « iven later thr * n 30 years after the date of the S ^o° e a of an nr ty af0rCSaid 3ha11 ’ De0 ° ne thC pr °^‘ rty l8 * ? n the GX 2 ±r y of this agreement at the end of the period of oeventy-five Years provided in Article 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and inmcvable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to tho Shaikh free of oobt. Producing welis or borings at the tine of such expiry shall be hanaed over m reasonably good order and repair, cu p ub j ect to provisions of , article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take wi wheat payment all the property of the Company in the State if, /( a )^»i ipiMl 'M' i fr* 1 * * f. - 7 - (a) xho Oo.tpany ohali fail t r.r.i:c r.ny the paynents prescribe a ii» this ^^ocnont itixln 6 nonths of the date on which they fall duo, or (*b) The Conpary sir. 11 ho :.n default in respect of an arbitration award under ^jrticle 24 hereof. * ’ 20. Nothin': in thi. : ..o rcerent shall be read .as restricting in ary way the ripht of the Shailrh to prnnt t..&gt; other parties concessions or uomits for naterials other than the Substances as defined in i*rticle 3 provided th t the .peratior^s and riphts of the Conpany hereunder arc .net thereby injuri usly affected* If the Shaikh sh uld av. ary date subsequent to the date of signature of this ^Teeriont prant to any other parties c .ncessiona or pernits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such cmcecsions shall contain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain fron danapinp, inpedin or intorforinp with the orty, ppernti.ns and interests of the Corroany, Deposits of ninerals such as pold, silver, cop * or, lead, irotash, sulphur and salt or the like 1 '..'hich ..iay be discovered by the Conpany shall bo reported to the Shaikh arid shall n &gt;t be vorked by the Company except under specie.], ooncossie.n or pemit fro:., tlie Shaikh. Purther the Company shall instruct Geologists to mai'k carefully and .report to the Company any area and its location whicli appears to them to ^ive promise' of yielding ninerals- or fresh water from a bore-hole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of ail such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas. kdxiCLD 21. The Shaikh hereby a.qpoes that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreoucnt to a British Coopary to be called ’’Xitroleun Devolopncjit (Trucial Coast) Lira tod” or to any other Cor .pany registered witjih the British Evpiro if 'TIC ID 22. Failure on the part a the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of t is agreement shall net give the Ghaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force najeure, and if tin ugh force majeure the fulfilment by the Cortprny a aiy of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the period of ouch delay sha.ll be added to the periods fixed by this agreement. Force rmjeure as used iri this ayreenont includes tim ^ct of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthqu kes and any oth^r happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. klTIClk 23. The Shaikh shall not-by general or sped al legislation or by administrative mea.sures or hy ary other • ot whatever annul this .^gTcomcnt excej)t as provided in article ly, ... No alteration shall be made in the terns of th,.s Agreement bp either the Shallk or the Company except in the event of the Shail-ch and the Company jointly agreeing fchat it is desirable in. the interests of both parties to make certain alterations deletions or additions to this Agreement. /.ITICLD 24.- 8 . - v- jcIaICIjJ -4. (*'.) If ''.t ..ny ti.vio u-ar .n; cho ciirruncy of this ^i.-jrceriont any .cliffs-ronco or ( 2 io utc shall arise ja tween the parties hereto concoiva.i\j the inter :.etat_ori or execution- hereof, or anything herein contained, or in c meet ion herewith, or chc rights or liabilities of cither pnoty he^ouiio-^r, th, sane shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other 'v/ay, be referred to two liTbitrators, one cf when shall bo chosen by each p rty, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbitrators before proceeding to arbitration* (b) Each party nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty clays after delivery of a request s to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator nay at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Besident in the Persian Gulf*. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or design-'tod the British Politic J. He side nt in the . Persian Gulf May appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of then, (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between then the decision of the referee, shall be final and -binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whoia the decision is given shall coni’oru t . the decision and that party shall be in default onlv if that party has failed to confer: to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise, (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as v.iay be agreed by the parties and in default of agrooiaent shall be Lcnd-n* juiTICLE 2b* Should the Shaikh decide to grant goriissi ji for a Banh: to open a Branch or agency in Ui .-al-gaiwain the Shaikh shall c nsult with the Corpany as to which Bah 1 : shall be given the permission The Shaikh ncy iron tine to tine desi ;nate in writing another Baric or Banks for the purpose of tMs igrticle, idiTICLE 26. The Shailch nay select in consultation with the Local Representative of the Conpany a loca.l i.ian - conversant with the English Language - to act as a confidential person as b,tween the Shaikh and the C vipany’s j.iep'.'c sent at i ve and to assist in procuring the labour that the Corr;any nay require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company, through the Shaikh in Unm-al-Qaiwain and shall be at the rate of Rupees Pour hundred* (400) per month. rilTICLE 27. This ...groenent is written in English and translated jntu iraoic. if there should at any time bo disagreement as to the meaning or interpret.-.ti n of an^.- r clause in th.-.s Jt .grcement the English text shall prevail. In witness whereof the parties to this agreement have set their hands the Day and Year first above written.- id ID GOD IS GRACIOUS &gt;d.) B. II. Lermitte.* y ' c f \ LlC ce 1.0) i, 10 .1 1 Stamp 10 s/- 5* 6 • © to* T E I S AGREE II ENT dated the 29th day of January One thousand nine hundred and forty six is made BET E E IT HIS MA.JESTi T S GOVERIE'-EENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOII (hereinafter called 'His Majesty’s GovenLment u ) of the one part and PETROLETJM CONCESSIONS L DTI TED (herein after called ’’the Company’’ which expression shall where the context so admits he deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also he deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part W H E R E A S Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd* is a Subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Limited. A N D WHEREAS the Comparer has obtained a concession dated the Twentieth day of March One thousand nine hundred and forty five from the Sheikh of TJmm-a 1 -Qaiwain (hereinafter called ’’the Sheikh” ) and certain responsibilities devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows;- THE Company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Groat Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE Concession from the Sheikh shall not bo transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Government, and any other company to which that concession may be transferred shall bo and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE employees of the Company in TJmm-a 1-^.a iwa in shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty’s Government, such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking my be employed. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Concession from the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Uram-a 1-Qa iwa in Authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, who shall bo a British subject* The approval of His Majesty’s Government shall be required for the person so designated. Ho will be ordinarily resident in Umm-al- Qaiwain or Bahrein or elsewhere in South-Eastern Arabia and will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the Nmm—a1-Qa iwa in authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty’s Govornment in Bahre in or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. SUBJECT to the terms of the Concession from the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. ANY right given to the Company under its Concession from the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty’s Government, and to any instructions which may be issued by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (1)(2) 7 . 8 . 5. on scs, right to uso for the purposes of its operations such haroours as inay bo developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty's Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available •wlse./nere. Subi^c to the terns of the Concession from the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall bo under its complete and exclusive control. TELEGRAPH, wireless and telephone installations, if any, main tained by the Company shall be for uso only in its business a^d cn provided in the concession, and shall be so.constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the eperations of ouch wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be establisned by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government, or their agent. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Concession -rom the Shoikh the Company shall not have tho risht to use or .coupy, and shall not include in the areas to bo acquired or utilised lor tho purposes of its operations, any sitos which may bo selected by oi behalf of the Sheikh or His Hajesty's Government for defence purpo for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane hasos or for wire CoS an ^ telegraph installations or in connection with the developmcn harbours, provided that with the consent of His i- a j-s y ° ,o.o wn-t-.hhfild the ComnanV shall have th HT the event of a state of national emergency or war (of tho existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall oe the sole judge) His Majesty’s Government shall have tho right of pre emption &lt;*f all the oil produced in Umm-al-Qaiwain in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto. 10* THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of tho Sheikh before working in any particular area, in erder that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the Company. In any case in which the Company feels that tho free move^ont of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily restricted the matter shall be referred to the Political Port Hont IH WITHESS whereof Sir William Daws on Croft, C.I.E., C.V.O. on behalf of His Majesty’s Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written THE SCHEDULE above referred to Pre-emption Clause. In tho event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty’s Government shall bo the sole judge) - (1) His Majesty’s Government shall have tho right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by tho Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in Umn-al-Qaiwain to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that Umm-a 1 -Qaiwain oil ho of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. The Company if required shall also consult with His Majesty’s Government regarding the production of other tils. (2) The Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by tho Government •css ion from the or occupy, and ilisod for the selected by or on ,r defence purposes, wireless and eve 1 opine nt iosty's GovorBbnt iy shall have the h harbours as may icrt if there is where. Subject iours developed .us ive c ont r o 1 . is, if any, main- business and as icted and operated cperations of such ny be established ' agent. or war ( ^f the lent shall be the &gt; right of pre- Ln accordance with of the Sheikh it the Sheikh may r the protection feels that the m area is being 'ed to the Political i.• B• jii#, C.i.E• , •eunto set his ;s Comiri.on Seal to or war (of the bo the sole judge) - ht of pre-emption of by the Sheikh to the have the right to capacity it may have omply with the Umn-al-Qaiwain oil . The Company if ernnent regarding to increo.se so far e supply of oil and/or required by the (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convoy the some, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Umn-al-Qaiwain to be determined by His Majesty's Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company. Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is duo to causes beyond the control of the Company shall bo settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with paver to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to bo held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Yict. c.4r&gt;j 24 and 25 Goo.V. c.14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force. (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall bo settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Umn-al-Qaiwain oil or products sold to- other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of suoh oil or products. (5) His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Umm-al-Qaiwair and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Gove raiment. Compensation shall bo paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the pavers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall bo settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub- clause (3). SIGHED SEA.ED AND DELIVERED by ) the said Sir William Dawson Croft) on behalf of His Majesty’s ) W• E. CROFT Government in the presence of;- ) F.A.K. HARRIS (XT India Office. THE COMM (XT SEAL of Petroleum ) ^ Concessions Limited was hereunto) (SEAL, affixed in the presence of;- ) J. SKLIROS Director Secretary E.J. BROW (3)DATED 29th. January 1946 HIS MAJESTY'S GCVERF.ENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM ^ - and - PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED AGREE M ENT relating to the Umn-al-^al*.vain Oil ConcessLon.1 111 u SZ tin N T dated the 29th. day 1 — of j anuary 9^ thousand BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called n His Majesty's Government' ) of the one part and PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED (herein after called 'the Company' which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part W H E R E A S Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. is a Subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Limited. AND WHEREAS the Company has obtained a concession dated the Twentieth day of March One thousand nine hundred and forty five from the Sheikh of Uinm-al-Qaiwain (hereinafter called 'the Sheikh') and certain responsibilities devolve on His Majesty's Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty's Government as follows 1. THE Company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. 2. THE Concession from the Sheikh shall not bo transforred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty's Government, and any other company to which that concession may bo transforred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times bo a British subject. 3. THE employees of the Company in Num-al-Qatwain shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty's Government, such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Concession from tho Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4# THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with tho Umm-al-Qaiwain Authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, \vho shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty's Government shall bo required for the person so designated. Ho will be ordinarily resideht in Umm-al- Qaiwain or Bahrein or elsewhere in Soubh-Eastem Arabia and will bo responsible for the Company's local relations with the Umm-al-Qaiwain authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty's Government in Bahrein or through any ether person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. 5. SUBJECT to the terms of the Concession from tho Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of tho Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of tho Political Officers subordinate to him. 6 . ANY right given to the Company under its Concession from the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty’s Government, and to any instructions which may be issued by the Political Resident in tho Persian Gulf. a)n tho Concession from tho ht to uso or occupy, and ired or utilised for the ch may ho selected by or on ernment for defence purposes, os or for wireless and with tho development cW of His Majesty’s Government the Company shall have tho ■ations such harbours as may s Government if there is .lable elsewhere. Subject heikh harbours devoloped ,e and exclusive control. ista Hat ions, if any, main- ily in its business and as so constructed and operated i with the operations of such it ions as may be established or their agent. emergency or war (of tho r’s Government shall be the .1 have the right of pre- L-Qaiwain in accordance 'with Dermission of tho Sheikh i order that the Sheikh may Llities for the protection xe Company feels that the } concession area is being L bo referred to the Political &gt;n Croft, K.B.E., C.I.E., mt has hereunto set his ) caused its Common Seal to •itten rred to emergency or war (of the 3 nt shall be the sole judge) - ve the right of pre-emption of n granted by tho Sheikh to the and shall have the right to refining capacity it may have at shall comply with the vided that Umm-al-Qaiwain oil is purpose. Tho Company if lesty’s Government regarding endeavours to increase so far &gt;ilities the supply of oil and/or he extent required by the (3) Tho Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on tho vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in tho quantities at tho time and in the manner required by tho Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Umm-al-Qaiwain to be determined by His Majesty’s Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at tho port of loading tho Company shall pay the amount duo for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is duo to causes beyond tho control of the Company. Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is duo to causes beyond the control of the Company shall bo settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by tho Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to bo held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under tho provisions of tho Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet, c.49; 24 and 25 Goo.V. c.14) of tho Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for tho time being in force. (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as tho same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery tho Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Umm-&lt;il-Qaiwain oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of tho works, plant and premises of tho Company in Hmm-al-Qaiwain, and in such event tho Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Govornment. Compensation shall be paid to tho Company for any loss or damage that may bo proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this sub—clause. Any such componsation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and tho Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub- clausa (3). SIGHED SEALED AMD DELIVERED by ) the said Sir William Dawson Croft) on behalf of His Majesty’s ) Government in the presence of:- ) THE COMMON SEAL of petroleum ) Concessions Limited was hereunto) affixed in the presence oft- ) Director Secretary (3)T H I S AGREEMENT dated the 29th. day of January One thousand nine hundred and forty six is made BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY T S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called 'His Majesty's Government') of the one part and PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED (herein after called 'the Company' which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part WHEREAS Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. is a Subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Limited. AND WHEREA.S the Company has obtained a concession dated the Twentieth day of March One thousand nine hundred and forty five from the Sheikh of Uinm-al-Qaiwain (hereinafter called 'the Sheikh') and certain responsibilities devolve on His Majesty’s Government, tho Company has agreed with His Majesty's Government as follows:- THE Company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE Concession from the Sheikh shall not be transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty's Government, and any other company to which that concession may bo transferred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE employees of the Company in Uinm-al-^aiwain shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty's Government, such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Concession from tho Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Uram-al-Qaiwain Authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, who shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty's Government shall bo required for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident in Umm-al- Qaiwain or Bahrein or elsewhere in South-Eastern Arabia and will be responsible for the Company's local relations with the Hmn-al-Qaiwain authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty's Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. SUBJECT to the terms of the Concession from tho Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay duo deference to the wishes of tho Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. ANY right given to tho Company under its Concession from the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on tho advice of His Majesty's Government, and to any instructions which may be issued by the Political Resident in tho Persian Gulf.NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Concession rom tho Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may be selected by or on tohLf 0 f the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government for defence purposes for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplano bases or for wireless and^ telegraph installations or in connection with the development o harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty's Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have no right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as inay be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government if there is nob reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the Concession from the Sheikh harbours developed ■K-r +-v.« oVmn ho under its ccmolete and exclusive control. TELEGRAPH, wireless and telephone installations, if any, main tained by the Company shall be for uso only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall bo so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such v/ire less, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government, or their agent. IN the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre emption of all the oil produced in Umm-al-Qaiwain in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto. THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of the Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the Company. In any case in which the Company feels that the free movei&amp;ent of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily restricted the matter shall be referred to the Political Resident . IN WITNESS whereof Sir William Dawson Croft, K.B.E.,, G.I.E., C.V.O. on behalf of His Majesty’s Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written THE SCHEDULE above referred to Pre -empt ion C lause. In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the solo judge)-- (1) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in umm-al-Qaiwain to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at tho time provided that Umm-al-Qaiwain oil bo of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. The Company if required shall also consult with His Majesty’s Government regarding the production of other oils. (2) The Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil. and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government,tho Concession 'from the ; to use oi' occupy, and •ed or utilised for the i may bo selected by or on nment for defence purposes, ; or for wireless and^^ Lth the development o^^ &gt; His Majesty’s Government le Company shall have tho :ions such harbours as may 3 Government if there is ible elsewhere. Subject jikh harbours developed and exclusive control. ta Hat ions, if any, main- y in its business and as o constructed and operated vith the operations of such ions as may be established or their agent. mergency or war (of tho s Government shall be the have tho right of pre- Qaiwain in accordance with rmission of tho Sheikh order that the Sheikh may ities for the protection Company feels that tho concession area is being be referred to the Political Croft, G.I.E., t has hereunto set his caused its Cammon Seal to tten ed to imergency or war (of the it shall be the solo judge) — 3 the right of pre-emption of granted by tho Sheikh to the id shall have the right to refining capacity it may have fc shall comply with the ided that Umm-al-Qaiwain oil s purpose• The Company' if sty’s Government regarding ndeavours to increase so for lities the supply of oil.and/or e extort required by the (3) The Company shall with oveiy reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convoy the some, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at tho time and in tho manner required by tho Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Uteim-al-Qaiwain to bo dote mined by His Majesty’s Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at tho po 2 ~t of loading tho Company shall pay the amount duo for demurrage according to tho terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond tho control of tho Ccmpany® Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is duo to causes beyond the control of the Company shall bo settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Gover nme nt (or tho Political Resident) and tho other by tho Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be hold in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under tho provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet. c#49$ 24 and 25 Goo.V. c*14) of tho Imperial Parliament, or any statutory- modification or re-enactment thereof for tho time being in force. (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall bo either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as tho same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential inforaation of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of tho quantities, descriptions and prices of Urnm-&lt;il-Qaiwain oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. r (5) His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of tho works, plarrfc and premises of tho Company in Ifcim-al-Qaiwain, and in such event tho Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this sub—clause. Any such compensation shall bo settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub clause (3). SIGNED SEALED AND DELIVERED by ) the said Sir William Dawson Croffc) on behalf of His Majesty’s ) Government in the presence ofs- ) THE COMMON SEAL of Petroleum ) Concessions Limited was hereunto) affixed in the presendo oft- )* ,10' Ling House Dominion Street London, E.C.2. '7. 9th January, 1945. Dear Sir, In Brigadier Longrigg’s absence overseas, I acknowledge with thanks receipt of your letter of 7th instant enclosing copies of the Abu uhabi and Xalba Political Agreements. Yours faithfully. Private Secretary T.A.K. Harrison India Office, Whitehall, S.V;. 1. Esq.,y d!) jibct. 6733A5. ^January, 1945. I enclose herewith six copies each of the Abu Dhabi and Kalba political agreeifients for which you asked in your letter to Donaldson of the 11th Deceiii&gt;er. lours sincerely. F. A. K. HARRISON Brigadier S.H. Longrig, Petr ole tan Concessions, Ltd., Ling House, Dominion Street, S.C.2*21. Minute Paper. Department. X H, 4 * 0 s~ f ^nsr ** 3 &lt;'•*' Jl ‘‘ r . ■ Prtficil lW~- ^ 4 A*»vtv^ * - r ‘ r + L~&gt; &lt;A 4 - yc u~&gt;~- a thuUZ H*; ; ^ 7 77^ ^ fa- e: {T cSl^ • ■/ 7 ^ /in&gt; ^ /?/*“ ^ / * / o^JlC- ,. WsM' (t «474B Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 101 Aju^ t Z -- -^uZc^v ' jfej. c^J' (i^jtfdty■Mr(X) . /2 • 7 22 THIS AGRBEUBHT dated the —— «f nine hundred end forty *lx !• eede S B T W E £ I HIS 5 IMBSTT t 8 GOTOH^^ST HI THE WITED KXSODOSI (herelmfter celled 'Hie BeJ©^ Geferaacat' ) of the cue pert end PETHOUEGII C0BCKSSICB8 LIFTED (herein^ after celled 'the Cmepiry' which expression shell where the csertext so ednlts be deencd te include its sucoessers end/or asst; 3 '^11 kImo be deeaed te include any subeidiery Cewpeny) ef the ether pert WHEREAS Pstreleus Deselepraertt (Truelei Ceest) ltd. is a Subsidiary Cwapeny ef Petroleum Concessions Limited. A H D WHEREAS the Ce^peny bee obtained a concession dated the Teeaatieth day of March One thousand nine hundred and forty flee from the Sheikh ef TRn-ed'-Qahraln (hereinafter ealied 'the Sheikh') and certain reepenslbllitlee deceive on Hie lla^e sty* e Gewenmenfc, the Cenpeny has agreed with Hie Majesty’s Cevsrvment ee fellcwrot- THE Caapany shall be and revaia a British eaapany registered in Great Britain and having its principal place ef buelneee in Great Britain, and ite Chairman ehall at all ttaes be a Britieh aubjeot. Tim OaEjoeeeian from the shoikh shall net be transferred te say other eo^mny without the prior consent in writing ef Hie iaa&gt;ety«e Goeemnert, and ary sther eompoTy te vfeiah that esceeaslom nay be transferred ehall be anft rmsain a Britieh eonfmay registered in Great Britain and haring its principal place ef business In Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE employees ef the Company in Gto-al-^atwain ehall at all tines be British subjects or sub jests ef the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent ef Hie Majesty’s Gorsraasat, such persons ef ether nationality as are required for the effieienb carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. EOSWrniSTARDXHG anyth! g eontaiaod in the Concession from the Sheikh, the inpertatlea ef fsrel^ active labour shall be subject te the approval ef the Pol it leal Roeidest in the Persian Gulf. THE Company in all oaoeept unimportant or rent ins natters shall deal with the Uma-al-Qabrain Authorities through a Chief Local Repceseatatlve in the Faro lam Gulf, whs ehall be a Britieh wfcject* The approval of Hie Majesty’s Government ehall be required for the person ee dtslgmatcd. He will be ordinarily resident in UtaMl- Qafcmia or Bahrein cr elsewhere in South-Eastern Arabia and will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the tRes-el-^aiwalm authorities, which shall, exsept in routine or unimportant natters, be conducted through the pel it leal representative of Hie Majesty’s Government in Bahrein or through say other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf nay from tine te time designate. SUBJECT te the teres of the Cemoeeslom from the Sheikh the Cempeay undertakes at all times te pay due deference te the wishes ef the Sheikh asd te the advice «f the Pel it leal Resident in the Fere lam Gulf end ef the Pelitieal Officers subordinate te him. AIT right given te the Ceapaay under ite Concession from the Sheikh te utilise means ef traaspertetian by air shall be sdbjeet te any general regulations for civil aircraft wads by the cifceikh on the edvlso ef Hie Majesty’s Government, sad te any Instructions *hich way be issued by the Pelitieal Resident in the Persian Gulf.7. HOnfflTESTiUfDING •Bythlus oaBUiJ»d la th» CosmMion ftrora ttm Shaikh tl* C napojsy shall aot hart tha right to uaa or occupy, aad •hall not inoludo la tha areas to ba acquired or util lead for tha purposes of its operation*, any sites which nay ba selected by or o behalf of tha Sheikh or His l*&gt;sty*s Ooreramast for da fence purposes, for aerodrones, eeroplans or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or la oonnsotlon with the darelopasnt of _ harbours, provided that with the consent of His ISa^ssty's Gorsransat which shall not bo unreasonably withheld the Cosnpauy shall haws tha right to use for the purposes of its operations sueh harbours as 'ny be developed by tha Shaikh or HU Majesty's Gars raws nt if tJiere U not reasonable harbour aeoanaodatioa available eleewhere • Subject to the term of the Canoeeelor fran the Sheikh harbours developed by tha Cospany shall be under its eoaplete and exclusive soontrol. 8. TELEGRAPH, wireless and telephone installations, if a*y, naU- talnsd by the Conpany shall be for use only in its business sad as provided la tha ocnoessioa, sad • all ba so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, tsla^raph or telephone Installations as aay bo established by the Sheikh or His Majesty's Govermasnt, or their agent. 9. HI the event of a state of national ansrgenoy or war (of tha existence of either of which His Majesty's Ooranwast shell be tha sola judge) His Majesty*• Govfcransnfc shall have tha right of pre- eaptioa of all tha oil produced la nbrain in aeeordanoe with the tanas of the Schedule hereto. 10. THB Coopany shall obtain the prior peraise ion of the Shaikh before working in any particular area, la order that the Sheikh nay ba la a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protectioa of the Conpany. la aay ease la which tha Cerapasy fuel* that tha free noveaeat of its personnel within the eonoossioa area Is being unnecessarily restricted the natter shall bo referred to tha Pol it leal Resident. IK WITHESS whereof on behalf of His Majesty's Oorrsmaent has hereunto sat his hand and seal aad the Coapaay has hereunto caused its Conacm Seal to ba affixed tha day and year first aboea written THS SCHEDULE above referred to Pre«aaptioc Clause. Xm the avast of a steto of national omrgeaoy ar war (of the •xisUnoo of whioh His Majesty's Gowamasat shall be the sola judge) - (1) His Majesty's oreraaent shall have the ri?ht of pone-aaption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Shaikh ta tha Company aad of all tha products thereof aad shall have tha right to require tha Company ta tha extant of axy refining capacity it my have la Qm-al-Qai*aln to produce ail foal that shall seaply with the Adairalty speaifieatloas at tha tbaa provided that HaMl-raisala ail be of a suitable kind and quality far this purpose. The Cenpany if required shall also consult with His Majesty's Gave mass* regarding tha produotisa of other ails. (S) The Coapany shall use ito utaoot endeavours ta Isaraaaa oo for as rsassaably possible with existing facilities tha supply of oil and/or product* thereof for the Govaramst to tha extant required by tha Government* &lt;*)■ ——V f &lt;k Al WA/N. UHH- Au% CV- fytntUu*- oU*.® b » THIS AGREEMENT Stamp 10 /- smm l^ys- -so ^cti is made dated the qwolf^h day of TkiMember One thousand BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY’S nine hundred and ^ GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called 'His Majesty s Government') of the one part and PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED (herein after called 'the Company' which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part. W H E R E A Subsidiary Company S Petroleum Development (Truoial Coast) \AA^ L y of Petroleum Concessions Limited. EAS in the ^ the Company obtaining, a^ncession/ f^-Sharjah (hereinafter called ’the Sheikh')/certain AND WHEREAS from the Sheikh of?^ 1 —o— responsibilities devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows 1. Potroloum Conrns-ji nnn- nr,H nni r rnhyidinrv company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. 2. THE Agi 1 element between the Company and the Sheikh shall not pe transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Government, and any other company to which that/ agr^m-nt /x may be transferred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. Amfu - Qo&gt;»WC.I^ 3 THE employees of the Company in Sharjah^shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty's Government, such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement bo twoaa the c the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian unlf. 4 THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal / // j dw^with the/sharjah Authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the 4 ^ pe rs i an Gulf, who shall be a British subject. The approval of His f.j. a Majesty’s Government shall be required for the pe^o^sodo|i|?iatf /y will be ordinarily resident in/shayjoh or Bahrein\anr^rTe^sponsiW 1 ' the Company’s local relations with the/Sharjnh authorities, which shall, lU***-^ **?*** except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty’s Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. ^ Lru-dyryf /W- ^ 5 SUBJECT to the terms of the Agreement botwoon -teho Company and the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. 6&gt; ANY right given to the Company under its agreement with the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty’s Government, and to any instructions which may be issued by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. CJSsT) t 7 NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may **** beff selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty's Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and ( d) •(3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Gkrverzuuexxt under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in^Ghai'jah to be determined by His Majesty’s Government, In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company, Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitra tion Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet, c.49; 24 and 25 Geo.V. c.14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force„ (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty's Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Sharjah oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty's Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty's Government shall be at libertv to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in/Sharjah, and in such event the' Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty's Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause ( 3 ). SIGNED SEALED AND DELIVERED by ) the said tehn Chari 00 Walton O.B J on behalf of His Majesty's ) Government in the presence of:-) J, C.-WALTON (L.S.) At6.D » -SYMON THE COMMON SEAL of Petroleum ) Concessions Limited was here- ) unto affixed in the presence ) of:- ) (SEAL) -W. FRASER Director ■E. BRfWN $eeretaryB $9 C.9.39 Cle. TELEPHONE : KTATTON**- *5W CODES: TELEGRAMS : INLAND ; PETCONCESS, FINSQUAR] pnncircM • PCTmwr«&lt;; v prtRCirzM BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT * LOMBARD BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH * I Q A D Pk BENTLEY'S SECOND COt^fSSlpNS LIMITED 22, G. Legh-f - R:e*?rt&gt;tv .©.r&amp;.»:e-.“&lt;Fr«ndl) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch)^ fcr Mr-befnoy N # A , JrA.+Vtry (French) W. Gr9eWcl (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers Ling House, OITY'-GATE'IHOUSE- Ling House, Dominion Street, FINSBURY-SQUARE Dominion Street LONDON E.C.2 PC.34A 11th December, 1945 y I refer to your letter dated 6th December and the attached draft Political Agreement for Umm al Quwain. The Company will accept, sign and seal the Political Agreement. There is here a confession to be made. It is that, owing to moves of the Company's offices during the war, into the country and back again, some of our records are defective. Among other lacunae is one affecting the Abu Dhabi and : L a-u^&amp; Political Agreements, of which you sent us at the time no less than fifty copies on 15th April, 1940. If you can do so without trouble, could you very kindly cause half a dozen more prints of each to be sent? If this is a nuisance, then please take no action about it. E.P. Donaldson, bsq., India Office, ’Whitehall, S.W. 1.of the word 'unreasonably' may give rise, the inclusion in Article 10 of the phrase 'the Shaikh shall not unreasonably -withhold such permission' is not considered appropriate because^as you are aware » it is not proposed in the case of Abujlhabi and Kalba to require the Ruler to take cognisance of the Political Agreement which 'cannot AthereforeL'Impose obligations tP / —'— r - Lf 7ks on him, / Similar, provisions found in Article of the Dibai and Sharjah Agreements are not relevant here since the Rulers are not to be asked to agree to apply sanctions in the event (which we hope will not occur/) of a, breach of the political Agreement by the Ccmpany'. V The/M Please see Brigadier Longrigg* s letter of 19th November below. I think his suggestion as regards Article Zf is all right. As regards his points regarding Jirticle 10 and the emission of Article 11 of the Dibai and Shar jahyAgreement this was all gone into in the case or Abu$mbi and Kalba Agreeaen*W where we decided' 1 ’with the agreement of the Company to emit;, the passages in question. Since we are not requiring the Shaikh of Uran-al-Qawain to take cognizance of the Political Agreement the case is strictly parallel with that of Ab«$habi and Kalba (where the words in question were Quitted) and not with Aibai and Sharjah. It is suggested that we should point this out to Brigadier Longrigg. A draft is submitted accordingly. (jlfal /4W£ 25M / ^(u IT Ar*f t* t\y K 'toafi^ t h (pyli ^ mU^ rt^ U ^ ^ ^ — ^ %&lt;-6 M C.9.39 OLE.3301 TELEPHONE : NATfONAL 3581 ^ 1 ov. TELEGRAMS: INLAND : PETCONCESS, FINSQUARE, LONDON FOREIGN : PETCONCESS. LONDON V TRXT 60S5 1 F 1 LE COP^f (B?) \ CODES s BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD »f4D c ' A ] , PETROLEDMljQCMSJCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : dnr^n. i G. Legh-J R. Cayrol,j.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. G'-’VTklan (formerly Armenian) i. B. A. ;.ler (Dutch) L. M. Letroy pard(U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros CITY-GATE HOUSE Un 0 House, FINSBURY'SQUARE LONDON 19th November, • E.C.2 1945. v ( t&gt;Solo ' I refer to vour D.O, letter dated 30th October regarding the Political Agreement between H.M.G. and Petroleum Concessions Ltd., arising out of our Umm al QpLwain Concession, an ■ cr - Agreement which accompanied your letter. Certain possible, though minor - and,* tiiirue, des^raou.e amendments or additions occur to me, and I should be grateful if these could be incorporated in the final draft which you will be able, I hope, to send to us for submission to the Board; it is, of course, only after Board a b reement to the final draft that papers can be put before them to receive the Company * s seal. In Article 4 where it is stated that the Company’s chief local representative ’’will be ordinarily resident in ^mm al Quwain or Bahrain', it seems desirable to add: 'or elsewhere in South Eastern Arabia', since our local headquarters might easily turn out to be at Sharjah, Muscat or elsewhere, according to the location of the oilfields discovered. In Article 10, the previous Political Agreements provide, that 'the Shaikh shall not unreasonably withhold such permission'. I suggest that this might be inserted. I I note that Article 11 of the Dibai and the Sharjah Political Agreements has been omitted. It is to the effect tnat tne Shaxxh cannot terminate the Agreement (on the ground that the Company has failed to observe its terms) except after arbitration proceedings and after the Company has failed to comply with the.award of the arbitrators. There seems no special reason why this safeguard in our favour should be omitted?V 3 ' 2 — Somewhat more importance attaches to the suggested addition to Clause 1 in the Schedule, to the effect that 'the Company, ^ if required, shall also consult with H.M.G. regarding the ^ production of other oils'. The Company will not oppose the insertion of this new sentence, since the obli 0 ation which it ^ thus assumes is one only of 'consultation': it is, of course, to be understood that the production of, for instance, a high octane aviation spirit might be a very serious undertaking and one for which provision would need to be agreed between H.M.G. and the Company at the time. If you feel able to send us a revised text of the Political Agreement incorporating the suggestions made above, I shall hope to convey to you the Company’s final agreement and its willingness to seal. E.P. Donaldson, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. MpIBB(25611) Wt.33533/P.lS8 1,000 10/43 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 far' EXTERHi^ Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. ». »'V, &gt;7 REGISTER NO. Ext. 5506/45- 33 19 Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary w fell birr far. Trucial CoastjU.ii:&gt;-al-Qaiwain Oil Concession Agreement. Secretary of St^te I Committee... Under Secretary Secretary &lt;J»f State Box/Tabte FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. Draft letter to Petroleum Development (Trucial Ccfjfet) Limited enclosing draft Political Agreement. 3 0 OCT 1945Please refer to the submission at Ext. 3139/45• The Foreign Office, Admiralty and. K.F.P. have y (ifti*. jf now replied, concurring our proposals. The only point raised, is a suggestion by h*P»P/ r that v. r e should incluae a sentence in the Pre-emption Clause of the Political Agreement specifying that the Company if required wili* . ^ consult with H.M.G. regarding the production of other oils^4 oJirtr* £ -full, A draft letter to the Company is submitted accordingly, ** tU^ ^ 'b~ UL A Ct £ZJT^ JT^ *) ‘f* ^ ^ fy ^ r /j IU (***”'**of the other Trucial Cc/st Oil Concessions^ case DRAFT LETTER ,£A, frvb te Brigadier S.H. Longrigg, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., Ling House, a ___ ^ Dominion Street, '^48 E.C.2. /Qs* Will you please refer to the correspondence resting with ^ letter No. Ext. 1983/45 of the 4 th Hay, 1945, about the Umm—al—Qaiwain Concession. 2. As you will be aware^it is necessary for H.I.l.G.’s formal approval of the Concession Agreement to be conveyed to the Sheikh. This it is now proposed to do, the Sheikh being required at the same time to give an undertaking^ by£exchange of letters^ that he will obtain H.L.C-. 's approval before granting permission for any bank to open a branch in his territory. 3. It will nov/ be desirable ^as in theaiS mmmmm r for a Political iigreement to be concluded between your Company and , though the Sheikh wdll not in this case be required to take cognizance of the Political Agreement before receiving T s approval of the Concession Agreement. I aca^ enclose lUkl draft of such a Political Agreement for your Company’h consideration. This follows the lines generally of the Abu Djoa^i and Kalba Political Agreements, though we have substituted Hm Tiriji il l, 'the Concession from the Sheikh' for 'the agreement by the Company and the Sheikh' in Clausa’S, 3, 5, o smd 7« We ** 3222 , also [y\AholC ^ (0 insert^ at the end of Section ^°f the Pre emption Clause the v/ords ''ihe Company if required shall also consult with H.K.G. regarding the production of other oils.' The reason for doing this is that^while in /modem [l 2 ^*modern warfare 'the inro 02 rb 3 n.ce of Adjiiiralty fuel is as great as ever, this product has 'been joined by a number of other ^ilitaxy oil fuels which have to comply with stringent specifications, sss. HeL.G-. feel that v rJi 1 'i hff nf^riir'- Q covert^ (U~j uW -iaaxs in ^/political Agreement. 2^ If the terns of the draft agreement are acceptable to your Company, we will, on hearing from you further, take the necessary steps to have the Agreement prepared for signature. If^ however ^there are any points £which you would fivst like to d^oauem %, shalll/be glad to doto your letters of 26th July, reference Ext. 3139/45 and 30th August, reference Ext. 3970/45 about the Oil Concession Agreements with the Ruler of Utnnt-al-Qawain and the Sheikh of Ras-Al-Khaimah. We have no observations to offer on the terms of the Concession Agreements and agree with you that there is no need to insist on the Ruler or Sheikh taking cognizance of the political agreement but that he should undertake to obtain the approval of H.M.G. before granting permission for any Bank to open a branch in his territory. 2. We agree with Stocks amendment as suggested in his letter of 8th September. 3* I am sending copies of this letter to Freese-Pennefather and Stock. D. M. Cleary Esq., India office, Whitehall, S.W.1.Reference : Your Reference: IT* Any reply to be addressed :— The Secretary. Telephone: Abbey 7000 Telegrams: Minfupo, Sowes DY .«/(. #.‘(43 INISTRY OF FUEL AND POWER, Petroleum Division, 7, Millbank, London, S.W.l 9th September, 1 J36ar Cleary, ^ o / D of the 26th July and en the Sheikh of Bridgeman re) enclosures about -• Umm-al-Qav/ain and Petroleum Concessions Limited to me, and I must apologise for not having v/ritten to you earlier* We agree with Preese-Pennefather's comments in his letter of the 1 ^th August and have no comments on the text of the draft Agreements, except to raise this point, hitherto tiie pre-emption clauses in these Persian Gulf Agreements have referred to oil fuel complying with Admiralty specifications. In modern warfare the importance of Admiralty fuel is as great as ever, but thisuroduct has been joined by aw-ingreasing number of other^oil *fue 1 s which have to comply with stringent specifications. It would not be reasonable to add a list of these to Admiralty fuel in these Agreements, but I suggest that section ( 1 ) of the of the pre-emption clause might be expanded by the addition of some such phrase as 'the Company, if required, shall consult with H.M.G. regarding the production of other oils”. I am sending a copy of this to Freese-Pennefather and to Mossop* Yours sincerely. D,M. Cleary, Bsq.*, India Office, Whitehall, S.W* 1 . pul deft. T? SEPm? INDIA OFFICE frm file copy (W 10225/12/76) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 15th August, 1945. S-f'''' 2. We agree with the view of the Political Resident that there is no need to insist on the Sheikh taking cognisance of the political agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company, but that he should undertake to obtain the approval of His Majesty's Government before granting permission for any Bank to open a branch in his territory. 3. We have no comments on the draft political agreement. 4. I am sending copies of this letter to Bridgeman and Mossop. Yours sincerely, (H. w. A. Freese-Pennefather). D. M. Cleary, Esq., India Office. RECo. PjL fr AUG 1945 INDIA OFFICE&gt; An oil concession agreement has recently been made between Petroleum Concessions Ltd. (a subsidiary of the Iraq Petroleum Company) and the Ruler of Uram-Al-Qfiaiwain, the text of v/hich will be found at Ext.2691/45. This follows very closely the wording of the Shargah^ oil concession, except for theminor changes pointed out in the Political Resident’s telegram No.997 of the 2-th May. Two points now remain for consideration^ (a) the conveyance to the Ruler of K.M.G. *s approval of the concession agreement (he is precluded from concluding any such agreement without H.11.G-. *s consent}, and (b) the drawing up of a political agreement between H.M.G-. and the Company. In the case Political Agent w r of the Shargah Agreement, which was concluded in 1937* ^he / as instructed, when communicating H.M.G-. f s approval to the pi )cS'i/i/_ Sheikh, to forward at the same time a copy of Uje Political Agreement .^ between H.M.G. and the Company, mentioning a 4 ^*v ——that, if any Ukt****'***} *** the terns of-the two agreements were in oonfl4tjt , those of the Poli tica l *pnefifrtlftb/kD * the Abu Dhabi^and Kalba^ , /- •, Agreement would prevail. In the case, however, of Agreements, which were concluded in 1940, the Rulers were simply informed /CJ' this relaxation was agreed to as a means of facilitating Petroleum . ^ j Ltd.'s negotiations with the Rulers./ 10. tdt • /f’^&gt;J7‘ In the case o f ^ ftlmm-Al -Qijiaiwain, the Political Resident, in his telegram No.997,*f surgested that the procedure regarding political agree ments and the conveyance of H.M.G. *s approval to the Sheikh should follow the Shargah precedent, but in his subsequent telegram No.1145 he says that, on reconsideration, he would now see no objection to the procedure as in the cases of Abu Dhabi and Kalba being followed. I should think that we might be satisfied with the second alternative. There should be no difficulty In securinj fro:;, the ShtMl., by a separate letter, an undertaking that he will obtain H.M.G. *s approval before granting ^ermiscion to a y bank to open a in. his territory. As regards the actual text of the proposed Political Agreement, the Political Resident has suggested that this should follow the lines of the Shargah Political Agreement^, subject to the small point referred to in paragraph 2 of his telegram No.997* The form of the Shargah Political Agreement .is all right , I think, although A ,/ ^ ^ ■ — it did not contain certain amendments of a rather minor nature which had been suggested by the Foreign Office^ rn ho Abu Bhftfci .gmd-KaAbft ^r.ilitiioal-Ar rh Ci. fiirl □ jh^lowod .,hmA. i, t } o ■f 1 Before putting our proposals for a Pol it 2 cal : ^reement to Petroleum\ Concessions Ltd. , we should obtain the concurrence of the interested v ^— Departments, viz: the Foreign Office, the Ministry of Fuel and Power and the Admiralty. Draft letters are submitted accordingly. Iaa+juF (j^ ic ? y * * / J/ 1 ^ 4v / £ ' y r .\ 3) Should we not say 'H.I 4 Go'wU ” instead of 'the Government' in sub clause (2) &amp; ( 3 ) of the schedule. 4) Does the vessel in suo—clause ( 3 ) operate on behalf of His Majesty or IMliG? Or does'nt the point matter? (intlld) D.M.C* 17/7 llr* Gleaiy 1) A CJonpary registered in Great Britain or elsewhere in the British Entire as a British jompany. 2) The spelling varies and is optional (it is only a transliteration of an Arabic word). I suggest Umiu-al-(juwain throughout - which is the spelling in the Concession Agreement. The Sheikh is called the S of U.A.Q because he lives in the town of that name and has dominion of the neighbourhood. Ttere is no separate state of U.A.Q. 3) This is the common fona of preemptive agreement and I should be inclined to leave it as it is, otherwise P.C.L. will ask what we mean. I think * Government • can in the context only be inteipreted as H.M.G. though it might perhaps in certain circumstances be taken to include Government of India which would be all to the good from our point of view. I don't think it matters. (Intlld )P. A.X.H. 1 a / 7 Dear Dibdin, We are preparing a political agreement (between H.M.G* and the Company) with Petroleum Concessions Ltd. to regulate their operations in Umm-al^aiwy^n, an Araoian i-&gt; tate 'under a concession granted by the Sheikh. The/(S&gt; The draft follows established precedent by- providing that 'the company shall be and remain a British coup any registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all tiross be a British subject'* Gan you explain the significance of the -words M a British Conpany' in this context* On the face of it they appear to be tautological but I remember that during the discussion about the proposed U*K* High Commissioner you said something which I understood to mean that a conpany registered in G*3* is not necessarily a British Conpany* Has the terra something to do with the conposition of the Board of Directors? (3gd.) D. 14 CUiAKT. 18/7 No the point was the other way round* Companies registered in India - Rupee Coy*s-are not now accepted by Indians as necessarily or effectively Indian* As far as I know in ordinary usage a ’British Cotpany* is a Conpany registered under the Companies Act in tire U*K* but the term is not apparently defined in the Statute and I suppose it may be used here as a conmon term of general meaning of which the special factors e*g* British Chairmen and the like are set out afterwards. But by itself it vould not imply any of the specially British Features you cite except registration in the U*K* i*e* it probably is tautologous to some degree but harmlessly so. (Intlld) A.D. P.3* I know nothing about this really but have checked ny queries with the VT* (Intlld) A.D.4 - 7 - Il'T 1 ':^- go:o i AiXJjj 'UI, This ia an .^ocnont inJo at U: •rv*&lt;‘:.l**Qr.i'«vain :&gt;n the twontietn day of l arch, 1945* corresponding tc the sixth day of llc.bia II 1364 heta^cen Hid KCSI,IJ3TCY dfLoilCf: HUi Id.ulilD .n the exercise I his powers as KQIuI.l of II 2 K&gt;.3&gt;']ii.IV4xxN on his own behalf and jn behalf of and in the none i his heirs and success rs an wh-Ti is or shall be vested for the tine beinp the responsibility for the control and Govornnent of the oTiffE OP U: C (hereinafter called “THU OIL’.HII') of the uiio part and P^xPOLPUI l COHCEoblONS LlhlTPI), a Coiipany resisted in Great Britain under the Coiipanics ^ct, 1929, (hereinafter called 'THP COiiitliY') its successors and assigns of the second part, hlflCIJI 1. (a) The area to which this ..^roen.cnt applies is the btato of Uin-al-Oaiv/ain, hrabia, including all is Ian hi ond Territorial haters ai&gt;pcrtaining thereto, (licreinaftor ref or rod to as ■nil ) beino all that Territory incivtdcd in the fjhailchdai of Um-al-Qaiwain, Tho Shaikh agrees that when the Territorial Units «. f the State of Uvx .~ai-Qaiwain have been deter’inod tho area covered 'by the Concessi -n will be cotcrninous -with tho limits so deternined. (b) Kothiny in this ayrecn.nit shall be read as restricting - in aii^r way - the riyht of the shaikh to [Taut to others a lease cr pernit over aix ;.rea or areas to be used f r the purpose of constructing .an aorodr one anc appurt 01 lances thereto for either aeroplanes or seaplanes; and such arcs or areas if and so granted shall be entirely excluded - for the purpose of this aproenent, ^.TICLU 2, The ; years fron the date of, ri-d of this ^rcenoiib shall oc 7? Calond signature. The expression year, nonih ano day used in tads is.yreui.ient shall oean what is consistent with the linpli; h Solar Calendar nd not any other. Purther, the weights nentionei in this i.yreenunfc .hall be reckoned ;n the English T .-n of 2,21+0 lbs. ilKTICIil 3. The Shaildi hereby grants to the Conpany the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce and wm n : \tural gas asphalt ozokerite crude peiroleuu end thuir products and cognate substances (hereinafter roferre’d to as n TIII&lt;j JlD.jiil-iCEri') within the State, tho exclusive ownership of all the Substances so produced and won, the. right t &gt; refine transport sell for use within and without the dtate or for export and to ox rt or otherwise deal with or dispose of the Substances, and the right to import export punp ship or otherwise transport the Substances acres, or to any country or place at the Company’s discretion and the righc t do all tilings necussary for the purpose of these operations, jdiTICLiS 4. If hereafter any neutral 2nve is created adjacent to the territory of the jtr.to, 'wherein the Siiaikh shall have a co equal and joint interest, the Chaikh hereby agrees tu grant to the C&gt;. 1 party an oil concession vor such neutral 3 •one on terms to be agreed between the Shaikl*, the Cuirpany and the juint ruler of such Neutral li ne. iiNTICiE 5. In cons:.derati. f n of the rights granted by tho Shaikh by this Agreement the Co ipany shall pay t the Shaikh.- ? - (a) on sijnaturu f the r^reonent Rupees {3ixty th -usanC (h) Hupoco l h .. : hundred the us ail - , within a perioc A einty ( 60 ) days fron the date up. n -which the Company declares in writing to the Llhaildi that Substances iiave been discovered in conncrcial quantities. If the Coupany should fail t. declare so sooner, then the date of discovery of substances in c a.nercial quantities shall be that date upon ’which the Coi .pany has conoleted and tested a well or wells capable of producing ii' : - accordance with first class oil practice not less than two thousand (2000) English Tons of clean substances per day for a period ..f thLi’ty (30) consecutive days. (c) Rupees Twenty f vur thousand at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that Substances have been discovered in comercial quantities in accordance with the Sub-Clause (b) oi' thj.s ^p-ticle 3* or until the Couipany c iv-ences Iroduction from quantities less than conworcial quantities. In the event -f such Eroi.uc'.ijn by the Company from quantities less than corrnrcial quantities either Rupees Rifty thousand per year of Rupees 3 (three) per English I u of 2,240 lbs, in respect of the Substances so w.,n and saved shall be payable, whichever is the greater. (d^ At the end of every year from the date upon which the Company cakes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the Substances have been discovered in coij-orcial quantities Rupees ninety thousand or Rupees 3 (Three) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances other than natural gas, won and saved, hrin^ the preceding Calendar year, wliichcver is the. greater, (e) Annas 2 (two) per 1,000 cubic feet of natural gas produced aiiO sole. In calculating royalty for the purpose of this articlu account shall not be taken of any of the substances used by the Company in it;, operations re used by the Company's employees w.ithm the St..te, necessary for their use, nor .,f any water or foreign natter which nay be produced with the Substances, .AiTICIE 6 , The Company- shall not carry on any operations within areas occupied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, buildings or graveyards. .crcd i'iRTICLE 7. The Company shall conduct its operations an a workmanlike manner and by apx&gt;ropriate scientific methods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum-bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. ARTICLE 8 . v/ithin three months after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement the amount of the Substances won and saved •and in tho case of natural gas produced and sold during the said cal end:.r year, and sf the royalty which is or might have been payable under Reticle 5&gt; together with a report of its operations during the sax., year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and .statement and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Co. pony 1 s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh. /ARTICLE 9,- 3 - &lt;s&gt; ttf- /■V iJlTIGLE 9* (-) Tho Co: ipr.iiy ohrdl have the ri-jht to inp rt viator, the 3 ubata.nces, fuel, r^.ciiincry, n&lt;:tor-curs c.nC lorries, aircraft, oquijnont, plant, tinh^r, utensils, iron uork, buj-lCin^ natcrials, feud supplies, r.oGicinos, ueclical supplies,office equipment aiic! he useholc 1 . furniture, cixC. .other natcrials, equipnent and ^oods of uhatsover natu e required 'by the C i.iouoy .nd its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the substances and articles roreviously inported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other ch .rpcs, but it shall pay on all personal d ods, clothing and general merchandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to then the ordinary duty in force f .r the time being in tho otate, Savin, as in ^drticle 3 and in this .jrticlc provided, the Co* ii '.ny, its personnel, its operations, income, profits and property including the Substances shall be exempt and free during the period of tnis agreement from all present or future harbour duties, itq&gt; rt duties, export duties, taxes, iiposts and charges of any bind 'vheth^r St.-.te or local, tolls and land surface rent of a’h-.tcver nr.ture. In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay in addition to the bayalty of Rupees (3) tiiree per ton as provided in Jerticle 3 - to the Shaikh uit.'iin (3) throe months after the close of eac'i calendar year the sun of (L) four annas per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances vjon and saved durin; the said calendar year. (b) The importation by tho Company of firearms and other vonp.*i.q is prohibited, except vith the written permission &gt;-f the Shaikh. (c) TJie Company may import such alcoholic drinlcs o.nd liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only uith tho mritton per. .issi n f tlic Shaikh, and the Political Agent, Bahrain, or any authority deputed by thou, but tine Company shall not sell or give alcoholic drinks or liquors t . the Siibjects of the * Shaikh or to the Subjects of adj dning Rulers v/h. viithin the State. ay be e ,pl.:yed ikTICLE 10. The employees of the Company sh .11 be allowed to enter into and to leave the State at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charge, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company‘s employees every facility required for the purge so ef the C^pany 1 s operations hereunder. Buc the Company’s employees shall lut interfoi’e or b t , their action: cause any disturbance or cause opposition to tho bhailch’s authority Tilth lH the State of Unm-al-Qaiwain and the onpleyces* shall n t go beyond the limit of their duties vvhen Oi.ployed mithin when leaving the confines of the State of Unm-al-Qaiwain far the purpose of this Agreement. Purther in the event of any of the Company’s empl. yees - whether he bo a senior of a junior ei ploy ec-commit ting an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or interfere with the politics or Subjects of the jt .to of Uimt-al-Qaiwain or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may apply to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to sen' 1 , the person concerned - if a foreigner - ut of the State of Unm-al-Qaiwain but if a Subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh my arrest the culprit and deal with him according t; the laws of the State of Um-ai-Qaiwain. /ARTICLE 11*- 4 - iu^TICL^. II. (a) For the purpose of its operations hcrovmCor the Coi ip any shall have the rip lit v;ith^ut hinorancc to ccinstruct, i mint am one operate power stations, refineries, pipelines ana storage tanlcs, facilities for 'water supply including borinp for water, telegraph one! telephone lines anf installations are wireless installations, r. ..is, railways, tramways, bu. Icings, pC'rts, harbours, harb .ur works, aircraft, buildings and landing places for aircraft, wharves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, 'with such lighting as nay bo requisite and anj r ether facilities or works which the Company nry consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payments any st nc, sand, gravel, gypsun, line, clay or similar materials or water which nay be available provided always that the inhabitants of the otate ere net prevented from taking their usual requirements of these materials and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nomad population who may bo dependent ..n the same is net endangered, ihc Company at its discretion may select the position of any such -works. The Company may likewise install and operate without hindrance ail such moans of transportation by land, air and water as nay be necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder provided it is for the purposes of this ..grcement. (b) The Company shall uiidor normal conditions accept and transmit free of cher go ^n its wireless and telegraph installations such of the vShaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company's business, and in ti .os of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph inetollctiona. and railways for governmental purposes, (c) The Sliaikh*s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or c instructed by the Company provided that such*use in no way hampers the Company &gt;r interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall bo the sole judge, any wharves or appurtenances c n vtructed by the C crip ary shall be for its exclusive use. The Company may use f r the purpose f its operations the harbours along the c :&gt;ats of the gtate, but the Company shall n^t impede or interfere ith the subjects of the Shaikh or their right to continue the use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by them for their sailing craft and fishing boats, .JdTICLo 12. The Company shall have the right and bo given the necessary facilities: (a) for the import of the Substances into the State from any adjoining territory by pipe lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery which the Conpary may decide to eruct within the State, and (b) for the -“transport of the Substances by pipe-lines, or otherwise over and across the State from and to any adjoining territory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the Substances, And no duties, taxes, ch rges or dues of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in rvspect of such import or transport, ARTICLE 13. (a) The Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all /uncultivated■uncultivated lands of the State which the Company nay need for the purpose of its operations and in particular the Company shall have the ri^ht to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect drilling rigs, punp-stations, oil-refineries, storage, terminal, shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Company f s operations; and the Company nay buy or lease for such purposes any lands, houses or buildings with the consent cf and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of such purchase or lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities, (b) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations .under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to tine of the land, houses and buildings which it« requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Cdhpany from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. ARTICLE 14. (a) The Company shall have* the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its operations hereunder; further the Shaikh grants to the Company the right to construct new roads for motor and general traffic, and to make use of all present and future roads or tracks free of charge, or taxes of any kind whatever. (b) The Company slia.ll er.ploy Subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Company’s skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers fro. neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing Subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever, alter the Status of such employees in respect of their rights, privileges and duties as Subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain in all ways, subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority cf the Shaikh in his capacity as the Kuler of the State of Uhn-al-Qaiw a in. ARTICLE 15# The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway, robbery, assault, viliul damage and destruction, * and the Compary may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times bo subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise, to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide, ARTICLE 16. In measuring the Substances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. /The Company- 6 - The Conpany shall noasure the Substances by a nethxl custonarily used in ^ood technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by hin shall have the ri^ht to observe such neasurnig and to examine and test '.-'ha-tever appliances nay be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply uith all necessary and usual safeguards for the piv. vent ion of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such tiroes and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the Company's operations'. If upon such examination «or testing any such appliance shall bo found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be^put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance, such error shall - of the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company's explanation - be considered to ha^i existed for Three (3) Calendar Months previous to the discovery thereof or from the last occasion of examining the sane in case such occasion shall be within such period of Three Calendar Months and the Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or has representative to enable a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable tines to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from then. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. iRETICLE 17. (a) The Company shall have the right at any tine after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months' notice in writing of its intention to terminate this agreement and this agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in such notice. (b) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signature the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and* duties all plant building stores material and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh nay purchase - should be so desire - the same at a price equal to tho replacement value at that date less depreciation which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under article 24 hereof. (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost. MkTICLE 18. On the expiry of this agreement at the end of the period of Seventy-five Years provided in Article, 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair, ARTICLE 19* Subject to the provisions of .article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all.the property of the Company in the State if, /(a)(r.) The Coapany 3 l 1 r.ll full t 1 rx.l:o c.ny cf the paynents pros or ibec ia this ^^preenent T jithin 6 ninths of the date on which they fall due, or (b) The Gonpany shall be m default in respect of an arbitration award under article 24 hereof. • . t idJTlCIE 20. Nothing in this ^(^rconent shall be read as . restricting in any way the ripht of ^the Shaildi to prant to other parties concessions or pemits for naterials other than the .Substances as' defined in -article 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder arc not thereby injuriously affected. If the Shaikh should at any date subsequent to the date of signature of this cement prant to any other x^ties c .neessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such ccncessiohs shall contain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from danapin^, impedinp or interfering; with the prcnierty, operati .ms and interests of the Company, Deposits of minerals such as x 5 °ld, silver, copy or, lead, x )0 ^ as ^ 1 ^ sulphur and salt or the like which nay be discovered by the Company shall bo reported to the Shaikh and shall n &gt;t be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. • Purtbcr the Company shall instruct Geologists to nai : k carefully and report to the Company any area and its location 'which app&gt;ears to them to pive promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a bore-hole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas, bj.T'ICID 21, The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company nay transfer the obligations and benefits of this bpreenent to a British Company to be called 'Petroleum Bevelopnont (Trucial Coast) Limited' or to any other Company registered within the British Empire AkTICLE 22, Failure on tlie part .:d the Coopanj 7 ’ to fulfil any of the conditions of t is ^reenent shall not pive the Ghaildh any claim against the Coi.pany or be deev.'.ed a breach of this Ayr cement in so far as such failure arises from force najeure, and if thr uph force majeure the fulfilment by the Compary of any of the conditions of .this Agreement be delayed the -period of such delay shr.ll be added to the periods fixed .by this ^preenent. Force majeure as used in this ni^reeoent includes the ^ct of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthqu kes and any other happening wh.,eh the Company could net reasonably prevent or control, idlTICIE 2o. The Shaikh sliall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by ary other ct whatever annul this .agreement exeex^t as provided in ijrticlc 19. No alteration shall be made in the terns of this Agreement bp either the Shaildi or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations deletions or additions to this agreement.iJlTICLS 24. (^) if r.t T.ny ting duf -ng curroncy of. this ..■Tcenont aiiy diff^roncc or dispute shall arise jetween the parties hereto concerning the inter retat_on or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunchr, the sane shall, failing any agree non t to settle it in any other way, be referred to two iirbitrators, one of whon shall bo chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbitrators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator cay at the request of the other party be desi nated by the British Political lie si dent in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf cay appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of-either of: thee, (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between then the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against when the decision is given shall confurc to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. •? (e) The place of arbitration shall bo such as- cay be agreed by the parties and in default of agreec-nt shall be London. ib.TICLE 23. Should Bank to open a Branch or consult with the Company the Shaikh decide to grant permission for a agency in U.r ,-aI-gaiwain the Shaikh shall • as to '..hick Bank shall be given the permission The Shaikh may from tine to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this ^erticle. ibiTICLE 26, The Shaikh cay select in consultation with the Local Representative of the -Company a local can - conversant with the English Language - to act as a confidential person as botween the Shaikh and the Company’s Representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company nay require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company, through the Shaikh in Unm-al-Oaiwain and shall be at the rate of Rupees Pour hundred (400) per nonth. ■idtTICLE 27. This ..greonent is written in English and translated into ijrabic. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning-or interpretation of any clause in th .s agreement the English text shall prevail. In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the my and Year first above written 21 ID GOD IS GRACIOUS (od.) B. H. LermitteCYPHER TELEGRAM (O.T.P.) . D mu— iiiiwtw ■ihi-i- n r-T'i —■ — n^»i lll^^l^l ^ v ^ Political Resident in Persian Gulf To Repeated Dated Received Secretary cf State for India* to Government of India and Bahrain (by bag) &lt;r Bushire 17.30 houre 7 S6th June 1945. ♦ 22*86 hours, 26th June 194-5* 1145 Para. No*5 of my telegram 997 May 26th. To facilitate P.C.L, negotiations at the time, requirement that Trucial Sheikhs other than Shargah and Dibai should take cognisance of political: agreement was waived in ’para. ho.. 3 of your telegram 1£ Jqnp &amp;gy 3rd 1939, and Abu Dhabi (your l,ettef_P.Z. 2505/40. •Bth' *9^0} and ICalba (your l etter P.Z.2506 /40 May 1940) concessions were concluded accordingly. 2» Conditions are now more favourable for Company than in 1940 and in our telegram under reference J recommended that procedure in the case of Umm^al- Qaiwain should follow that of Shargah« 'On reconsideration, if this is Iike3.y toj WjQAfPiiL^ I see no objection to Abu Dhabi and Ifaxwa poure being followed in the case of Umr^-al-jOa 1 INDIA OFFICEaa regards undertaking from Sheikh relating to opening cf bank. 3. An attempt is now being made to open a bank on Arab coast (with a branch on the Tmcial Coast«l ^ registered in India (?but with) Iraqi capital anc direction* I think it desirable therefore that \y&amp; should try to secure if possible undertaking from Sheikh of Uram-al-Qaiwain, similar to that obtained from Sheikhs cf Shargah and Dibai, before conveying approval of concession. 4, I suggest similar procedure be followed in the case of Ral~al~Khaimah ? with whom P.C,L. propose to negotiate in the immediate future.5 C.5.40. — i. 9 i ^ AY* 9 i *' - ' ■:. j PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED. V TCL.EPHONE I National. 3582. tbleorams Llllg HOUSS , -F+N9BWRY^SOOARE. INLAND l PETCONCES8, FlNSQUARE, LONDON. FOREION i PETCONCES8. LONDON. CWYyOATE-*MO!tf9e*. Dominion Street, London, e.c.z PC.34V PC.32 21st June, 1945, My dear Harrison, Your letter of 19th June asking for three further copies of the Umm-al-Quwain Concession, three copies are sent you herewith. We have not yet heard particulars, nor received the text, of the Ras-al-Khaimah Agreement, of which however you are aware from the terms of the telegram from Packer which you kindly sent to us. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. EndsFILE CORY CONFIDENTIAL. fJIo. 525-3 n^. ' 09^' EXT 2692 : ^ FNDTA DIRECT ^&gt;5 ^ . * cs The Hon’ble the Politiea^ jle^ident n the Persian Gulf presents his * compliments to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, The India Office, LONDON The Secretary to the Government of India, in the External Affairs Department, NEW DELHI , and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Persian Gulf Residency, Kiotkk]Ocixixadxl)exSKDBC3dt, BUS HIRE. Dated .the. J.7th .May.,. .1945^ Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Express Letter No*524-S dated the 17th May, 1945, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum No. T/SA.20/3952 dated the 15th April, 1945, from the Manager, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, Bahrain, with en closures. LB. UMM-AL-QUWAIN CONCESSION. REGik PUL -t JUN 1945 INDIA OFFJCLf I COPY Translation (Oglgla^l in A^a-^ic) CoZ EX! 2692 After complimejitit'y., To our dear friend Ahmpd bin Rashid ^M*Mcir9HKZjK^.'r &lt;0. Umm al Quwain, 21st March 1945. 7th Rabia Thani 1364. al Mu 1 alia, Ruler of Umm al Quwain. In reply to your verbal proposal for the payment by instalments of the annual amount provided in paragraph (c) of Article 5, I have pleasure in informing Your Excellency that I am agreeable to the payment of the amount in four instalments on condition that you will come to one of the Company's offices to take delivery of each instalment, or send your representative for this purpose. I beg you to favour me with your reply. Compliments. For Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. B. H. LermitteCOPY Translation (Original in Arabic) Uap al Quwain. 22hd March 1945. 8t i Habia Thani 1364. After complimejits. To Mr. B.H.LeriJiitte PetroleunuDev esen JLXX i ative of ucial Coast) Limited. After further compliments. I have received your letter dated 7th Rabia Thani 1364 and T thank vou for your agreement to my verbal proposal'?or f ^'payme^t of the annual amount in four instalments provided that delivery taken at one of the Company’s offices. Seal of Shaikh Ahmed bin Rashid al Mu*alia. witness: Signature of Hamid bin Sultan. cpd/ACMn' FJLe copy- / EXT 2691 GOVERNMENT OF IF j ! 945 DIA, ;XMENT* iNTiA y INDIA DIRECT 'T?^ EXPRESS LETTER [tf. B—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense a?id undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, lo sare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] From Political Resident, Bushire. AO Retaxandum London.v- Repeated Foreign New Delhi Political Bahrain. No. 524-3. Doled 17th May,1945. 293 . TTmm-al-Quwaln Oil Concession Agreement r XI Reference my telegram No.583, dated 29th Mar chJ.945. 2. Copy is enclosed of letter No.T/SA.20/3938, dated 10th * to April 1945, from the Manager, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Office Limited, Bahrain, with one unsigned copy of the Agreement. ° nl y* 3&lt; j shou id be grateful if three copies of the agreement could be obtained from the Company's Head Office and forwarded to the ' Government of India, the Political Agent, Bahrain, and to me. Sd. A.C. GALLOWAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. . POL. ti* n ' •7 JUN ilA OFFICE i S. U. MFP 120G S&amp;P—(M-l723)—4-2 36—200,000.PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (T.C.) LIMITED 2691 T/SA.20/3938 Bahrain, Persian Gulf 10th April, 1945. COIf^TIAL To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Through H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, UMM-AL-QUWAIN OIL CONCESSION AGREEMENT - SITUATION 3RD APRIL 1945 AFTER RETURN OF MR. B.H. LERMITTE TO BAHRAIN We have the honour to refer to our letter No. T/SA. 20/3904 dated the 12th February 1945 in which we brought it to the notice of the Political Agent, Bahrain, that it was the Company^ intention that Mr. Lermitte should proceed to Umm-al-Quwain to negotiate an oil concession with the Ruler. 2. In our DO/SA.20/3934 dated the 25th March 1945, we informed Major Hickinbotham that the Ruler had signed TheConcession on the 20th March 1945 and that a complete report for the information of the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Political Agent, Bahrain, would follow. 3. We now enclose one signed copy of the Agreement and one unsigned copy, and we shall be pleased if you will acknowledge receipt in due course. 4 You will note that the first part of Article 25 has been erased as the Ruler requested quarterly payments . which were arranged by an exchange of letters between Mr. Lermitte and the Ruler. 5 We have sent similar copies to our Iianaging Director, London, and, as far as we are concerned, this brings the matter to a satisfactory conclusion. We have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servants, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM BEVELOP^MENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LTD. Sd/- E.V. PACKER MANAGERJ« ®lfi? Marai? of doBi ®fff Uprclfol 4 9&gt;AVt This is an Agreement made at tl/m/v** Qujurtvcnrv on the Kw+mXjuiX$\, _ day of V^-oAxiv * 19®, corresponding to the $i~A day of TUS^a. JL im 'S.H.L. between His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad Bin Rashid in the exercise of his powers as Ruler of Umm-al-Qaiwain Arabia, on his own behalf and on behalf of and in the name of his heirs and successors in whom is or shall be vested for the time being the responsiblity for the control and Government of the Stale of Umm-a!-Qaiwain(hereinafter called ' The Shaikh 11 ) of the one part and Petroleum Concessions Limited, a Com pany registered in Great Britain under the Companies Act, 1929, (hereinafter called 'The Company,,) its successors and assigns of the second part. ARTICLE 1. (a) The area to which this Agreement applies is the State of Umm-al Qaiwain, Arabia, including all Islands ami Territorial Waters appertaining thereto. ( hereinafter referred to as “ The State ” ) being all that Territory included in tha Shaikhdom of Umm-al-Qaiwain. The Shaikh agrees that whan the Territorial limits of the State of Umm-al- Qaiwain have been determined the area covered by the Concession will be cotermi nous with the limits so determined. ( b ) Nothing in this agreement shall be read as restricting - in any way - the right of the Shaikh to grant to others a lease or permit over an area or areas to be used for the purpose of constructing an aerodrome and appurtenances thereto for either aeroplanes or seaplanes; and such area or areas if and so granted shall be entirely excluded for the purpose of this agreement. ARTICLE 2. The period of this Agreement shall be 75 Calendar years from the date of signature. The expression year, month and day used in this Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English Solar Calendar and not any other. Further, the weights mentioned in this Agreement shall be reckoned on the English Ton of 2,240 lbs. ,j IaU- j AI) yc- LlJl»j 0 ^ p-fJI 1^9 OljLlll ) ©jUI JjjfU * * ■ Vji ji-ti) v * vj^* \c 9 #JLa(M—olll LA li)l 0UIJ ^ ^ • y 0jLl y+i* Oj/a,* J* Jp 0-X&gt; { t L-) JjU y ^ . il'S SI ^’1 Je j : L:r \\ _ l. iJUrVl ajjt J (&lt;S) Ij-^l Cj ^^5 ^1 c? ^---^1 (j-« — *L-jV J yl&gt;[L* j\ yC* * ^J^IOljLlal] LI—A) *UjI' LrlijjJi -jj V iA ^.-kXa ISI»Jjb • oL;VI a J\z y+-+ ’&lt;—sr Ac- Y o *Juk Sju - AJlill ol_ll • ^ Cr* ^ 11 ^ j j a ^jl I .^1 ^ U (ji* d.11^ y? . *1^^. j\l%) A.sU* Nl ^jl^H . Ttt • jy— 2 — ARTICLE 3. The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce and win natural gas asphalt ozokerite crude petroleum and their products and cognate substances (hereinafter referred to as “The Substances”) within the State, the exclusive ownership of all the Substances so produced and won, the right to refine transport sell for use within and without the State or for export and to export or otherwise deal with or dispose of the Substances, and the right to import export pump ship or otherwise transport the Substances across or to any country or place at the Company’s dis cretion and the right to do all things necessary for the purpose of these oper ations. ARTICLE 4. If hereafter any neutral Zone is created adjacent to the territory of the State, wherein the Shaikh shall have a co-equal and joint interest, the Shaikh hereby agrees to grant to the Company an oil concession over such neutral zone on terms to be agreed between the Shaikh, the Company and the joint ruler of such Nautral Zone. ARTICLE 5. In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh by this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikh. (a) on signature of the agreement Rupees (b) Rupees Two- Wu/vcAncd- within a period of sixty (60) days from the date upon which the Com pany declares in writing to the Shaikh that substances have been discovered in com mercial quantities. If the Company should fail to declare so sooner, then the date of discovery of substances in commercial quantities shall be that date upon which the Company has completed and tested a well or wells capable of producing in accordance with first class oil practice not less than two thousand (2000) English Tons of clean substances per day for a period of thirty (30) consecutive days. ( c ) Rupees at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the &lt;»9la'N^*JlA yi ll)l ft . .ft uji jDi jy lil (ju&gt; jiin) fj* 4^1*^ Ail y j J -V^a*\5 ft . y j\e&gt; j* oiyuij . A) Aik^ A; I Jjl-l! J slJLiii ISI — AaiI Jl oil! HI Aa^»^L« • A^Uj'VI *-XA ^ Vlj Ai^&gt;Lil aJul^-l Aakdl ^ IjLlJ &lt;5^111 ^ iljLill ^ILlj ^illj ill jij -Ljj-ij • oJul^-1 AaLLl *Jjk&gt; ci A&gt;-^lL» 1 j^Ll JjU. A»1 — A»~^IL-I ailil . ^^ill A-^UrVI i A-slirVl ^ ) ^ (v) ^ill ^ jbl L»j» (jO- ^cLaT J-iUi: OLil5^'l ^iy.1 o' AjLi^-JJl ^ jl&gt;* o 9 Aft&gt;yi ol** o' o^ '^'j ^iii ^ jb\ ^ -^'y' £*Ljl jLl jl jL Aj j£j ji&gt;- ^ill A-9 A?-jjll ^LaVl l — 9 jl*-« L—&gt;- ■^'y' Lr* y* ( r *** ) J' o^ ‘A ^ . aJ\ y~* U J) (r * ) a ji C«j&gt; A-aJl ( £ ) o' Aj A^iUtN'Com that com the the quar In Cora cial i &amp; per of tl be i the in that in c t$vr Eng] Subs save whii feet of t of a pan; pan; for mat Sub; can pied mos com mar thoc mea to a dulj it ar shal as t opei trea3 — — r— Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities in accordance with the Sub-Clause (b) of this Article 5. or until the Company commences Production from quantities less than commercial quantities. In the event of such Production by the Company from quantities less than commer cial quantities either Rupees tn^u^ VO/n^L per year or Rupees 3 (three) per English Ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances so won and saved shall be payable, whichever is the greater. % (d) At the end of every year from the date upon which the Company makes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities Rupees \tsnjtCy, or Rupees 3 (Three) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances other than natural gas, won and saved during the preceding Calendar year, whichever is the greater. ( e ) Annas 2 (two) per 1,000 cubic feet of natural gas produced and sold. In calculating royalty for the purpose of this article account shall not be taken of any of the substances used by the Com pany in its operations or used by the Com pany’s employees within the State, necessary for their use, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the Substances. ARTICLE 6. The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occu pied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. ARTICLE 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific me thods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum - bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. jr5 LflJl ^». y oLii £*(«-&gt;)• jo'ill ja Jjl jolL. 4 &gt;- u i r ii ry J Ttt • jj Je&gt; J j*- . jlil ^‘oir j (,) I ^11 (jl A&gt; c)* y if ( r ) ^ j* 3UHI Jit U _ yi ^c- a y 11 • jj \ . yf si jLii jir Ci ;iui \• • • ^i r (*) sJjb A&gt; ya-lil y uui (j aj i ^ |»ap ..iLl! ^ O y«J\ aLii AjIj — A^oU^ ailil A«ijV!j j\ ix*'* i aT_ A*; a) I** yi j a*«&lt; y a*l^' oUJ* ^jA a]LL A)' oLi' ^ ^11 0^ j (S jc- AjfyJl j -Lw ^ . » A^Ju J J&amp;L\ Aa«^. A* j A^^-CT^Ui ,j!ARTICLE 8. Within three months after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the Substances won and saved and in the case of natural gas produced and sold during the said calen. dar year,and of the royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 5, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh ARTICLE 9. (a) The Company shall have the right to import water, the Sub stances, fuel, machinery, motor-cars and lorries,aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the Substances and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and general mer chandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the State. Saving as in Article 5 and in this Article provided, the Company, its personnel, its operations, income, profits and property including the Substances shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future harbour duties, import duties, export duties, taxes, imposts and charges of any kind whether State or local, tolls and land surface rent of whatever nature. In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay in addition to the Royalty of Rupees ( 3 ) three per ton _ oltll l»L) ^ ( A—Al^JI rcllll UUI jtH A) ^ . a» a5^JL)I j' jUi' j jf aS^I!! (I) _ a»-U! oUl ill y ^11 j*Ub j y—j ONjA) Olij jil'ISsIlO^^jA^DlO^ll J A) j U j aS^JDI a*'I \jt j aJ ln'MI *JUk Jp j a^JDI aL^'j&gt; A*&gt;-^) L»j Aw»^l A;' j j [fjk&gt; y y aS^JL.' jU aJu&gt; 1)$^-' j j (jl y^ l jr^ l j* aJIaN' (J AaILa j jb 1 y &gt;'yiJ! ) ob ~a*» yC^- I j* aJWI y a) l tjp yjjb jjC- J a5 ^L!l ^ oL y j aj^I) (r )5 —- — o — as provided in Article 5 - to the Shaikh within (3) three months after the close of each calendar year the sum of (4) four annas per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances won and saved during the said calendar year. (b) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. ( c ) The Company may import such alcoholic drinks and liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only with the written permission of the Shaikh, and the Political Agent, Bahrain, or any authority deputed by them, but the Company shall not sell or give alcoholic drinks or liquors to the Subjects of the Shaikh or to the Subjects of adjoining Rulers who may be employed within the State. ARTICLE 10. The employees of the Company shall be allowed to enter into and to leave the State at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charge, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company’s employees every facility required for the purpose of the Company’s operations hereunder. But the Company’s employees shall not interfere or by their actions cause any disturbance or cause opposition to the Shaikh’s authority within the State of Umm- al-Qaiwain and the employees shall not go beyond the limit of their duties when em. ployed within or when leaving the confines of the State of Qmm-al-Qaiwain for the purpose of this Agreement. Further in the event of any of the Company’s employees - whether he be a senior or a junior employee-committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or interfere with the politics or Subjects of the State of Umm-al-Qaiwain or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may apply to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to send the person concerned-if a foreigner-out of the State of Umm-al-Qaiwain but if a Subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh may arrest the culprit and deal with him according to the laws of the State of Umm-al-Qaiwain •La.a&gt;! j&gt; AijlJ) (^-&gt;) 'ill _ A)aLi]L» &lt;j 1 Olj^lil j! IX LWj l»WJ Ai-ii-l £j?J\ ijj&gt; ftjUNI y j' (J! Ijlji—L j! j ^ c^‘ AjkA j y ^ . Ajl’a.’^ *-U yii aS^JJI Jl Aiai-J K^pj\a.a _jl v I (_£ I &lt;£==»j Vj (jf y *jUi -Xip j\ y pi «jl*! y*-0 j &lt;-5UrVI »jjb ^ j\j» t yA^ ojUVI py^ A&gt;-l w^jjI lil l* a!U- j aJIs cUli y _ iy i jjZ' y _ y&amp;y jl plliJL ^1 btiicj j_j-Xy y pLjL»i&lt;-»L—A-ii jJi y a! ^iSi ^sc-iu y &lt;jr y j pr11 Lie_j y~A . ^-LiI y&amp;^ 1^1 jjr^-ali pi •jLI &lt; yry\Of it; * shall cons statii tank born lines ation port build whai with any Com such any or s: be habil iron of t supp popu sann its d such insti such and effec prov Agre cond char stall. as bush the free and gove— 6 — — A — (^3 4^* ARTICLE 11. (a ) For the purpose of its operations hereunder the Company shall have the right without hindrance to construct, maintain and operate power stations, refineries, pipelines and storage tanks, facilities for water supply including boring for water, telegraph and telephone lines and installations and wireless install ations, roads, railways, tramways, buildings, ports, harbours, harbour works, aircraft, buildings and landing places for aircraft, wharves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, with such lighting as may be requisite and any other facilities or works which the Company may consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payments any stone, sand, gravel, gypsum, lime, clay or similar materials or water which may be available provided always that the in habitants of the State are not prevented from taking their usual requirements of these materials and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nomad population who may be dependent on the same is not endangered. The Company at its discretion may select the position of any such works. The Company may likewise install and operate without hindrance all such means of transportation by land, air and water as may be necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder provided it is for the purposes of this Agreement. (b) The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph in stallations such of the Shaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company’s business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. &lt;&gt;)(!) _ t aoII-I oM j Jf j! J&gt;U j;* j)* ji iSjf’ u’j ’ LliHj yJb]1 OlJ j\)Ij Jb Jli-I (i&amp;ClJ! O^jLLlI Jf'} • ~a&gt; jj j*# U y ill • lji jl j v' 1 ^ (jljJjJlj 1J JL^/uL) j J j&gt;-l 5y* {j* *JL_a AoU'i y^\y ^11 *lll *^1* y^^- (j! .i* jd * % ■ \j. J 41 ' J’ ^3 ^ jj 5 J-Xy o' Ul^- \» JUi!l ^LiJI li-ijS ^\ j£'y . 4*.9 IjIi ' • JL&gt; j! v'JI JI^NI j Z^JLii J* ^ ( v ) &lt;jlyjbdl j I If. ULi&gt;* ^ U {*z ^JiLr j ^JJir (jy ‘6^1!! 3' HI «■ Oldjl o' [Ha £jA yy . \+a] e&gt; j— 7 — y /«$ (c) The Shaikh’s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances con structed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. The Company may use for the purpose of its operations the harbours along the coast of the State, but the Company shall not impede or interfere with the subjects of the Shaikh or their right to continue the use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by them for their sailing craft and fishing boats. ARTICLE 12. The Company shall have the right and be given the necessary facilities: (a) for the import of the Substances into the State from any adjoining territory by pipe lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery which the Com pany may decide to erect within the State, and (b) for the transport of the Substances by pipe lines or otherwise over and across the State from and to any adjoining terri tory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the Substances. And no duties, taxes, charges or dues of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in respect of such import or transport. ARTICLE 13. (a) The Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the State which the Company may need for the purpose of its operations and in particular the Company shall have the right to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect drilling rigs, pump-stations, oil - refineries, storage, terminal, shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Company’s operations; and the Company may buy or lease for such purposes (j J If 11/&gt; l A I/' I J i v J • illi J -W 1 J’ UlPl ^ jf jO j jjUNi ^ ^ * p.f4&gt;- j! Qp—y d*J** y ui^i) ^{_i\ j - 5 jXLc ll'l iiLjtl J*\} A)J ^ ijUN! Jl ^1 ^ (I ) • *jUNI ^ yJLH j ji y jCl_r V J'j J* ^ 3&gt;* jl j aIialI j »aj ’J152 dl oil! -Lil ^yy yi J) ijUNl J Uj&gt; 11 ^)1 ^IjNI y^s&gt;-y mS^UI j U \c li y ^mA) iU'l -*j \jijiuii jJ-i a y OLJlLdJ la^j a&gt;1 y^ y* 3 \y ^y o j jl a^^UJj .aS^IJI Jl^l— 8 — —- A any lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of such purchase or lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities. (b) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Skaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. ARTICLE 14. (a) The Company shall have the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its oper ations hereunder; further the Shaikh grants to the Company the right to construct new roads for motor and general traffic, and to make use of all present and future roads or tracks free of charge, or taxes of any kind whatever. ( b ) The Company shall employ Subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Com pany’s skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing Subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever, alter the Status of such employees in respect of their rights, privil eges and duties as Subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain - in all ‘&lt;^9 Jjy j! . y OjJIj J*)i\ Nl 'aT diUNJ (v) ^ L y.£cJJI ;Lr j;) cf' ) jlJI j OjJIj j LAL^f 1 Iff ^ jJJ a^‘ 4 (!) _ ^!Jl iM *ll! j! ^ .'aJU-MI yj\ j ^ji-! ^-^!! j!* d.0^ ft-y ! jl Jjia.H JU : -^ A-*U!\ !j* • J ^ W* s *- J ' d?- 5 ^?i^-!&gt;! j' aJU! ft ^ ^ V ) (jt Aj II (jl^tN! jj.9 ^oJL)l l\cj A^dll ^yJ^A ^i! r t! ^ LA oW- 2 ! Id^ ^ jl 'y J- p-ir.Jy. . LUI j! JJI ja j (3^' of^.j jJL' y . J'+ ty J[ »JLa j a! y.iA ! Jy^~ +■(• L^*1 .J3La^:-'U MzifiU'yif'y&gt; j 1 tlcj a5^i!\ I jli •Vjft Ai-* jy Jjl Ji^V! y aIL A.l 3 — w-4 ^ tie. j 'V— 9 — ways-subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Umm-al-Qaiwain. U- ^A Or (*1 ijl-V ARTICLE 15. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction^nd theCompany may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. ARTICLE 16. In measuring the Sub stances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the Sub stances by a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test whatever applian ces may be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply with all neces sary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the company’s operations* If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be Sjjllx jji 4^'j fr I * • • If-iL *^1 ^--.^11 l»\c j ^ y A? L?- Ij.apL.jJ j*'** ^ &gt;, ***1 . 45^111 \&gt;jJ* j J 4» I — 4.oLJI »ili! j 4 JI J&amp;j Jjk jjjJ' j* 4 b. ^ J 1 I ju&gt; 45^DIj Oy. 4 ^ 1)1 0 * QjZL) j 4^uS\ J LaJ l^L 4i (ji-l LsTj 4L. ^&gt;^11 4j J.AU 4ix~1_y ^--UJ oH j^-\ Ll ^ U_* o' J * 'L—k J-u. ij ) pJLj 4TiU 4;J j\ jU\ OVU-I jj j *1^1 J . JLpI j &gt;a- O 5 ? L ^ JJJbfc 4 j *1j^1 j\ fjai- ^ \*\ ^J\ 4lT V— 10 — —\ — discovered in any such appliance, such error shall - if the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company’s explanation - be considered to have existed for Three(3)Calen- dar Months previous to the discovery there of or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of Three Calendar Months and the Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to en able a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from them. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. ARTICLE 17. (a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months' notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in •uch notice. (b) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signa ture the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and duties all plant building stores mate rial and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase - should he so desire-the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less depreciation which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 24 hereof. lit jup 4&gt; 3 ^' j y 4 J vi •u y jt. y eJ^y 4 ! 1 j JL- «A&gt;-J oa&gt;- 45 y JfCmJ fTy'* r—^ 1 &gt; l o -j i ■uUSf'1 y\ i- 5 t (r) x. ( r ) *UI J J-HJi J-i&gt;- |j&gt;l \jjt 4 J VI 4 -* &gt; 1 *^- jji y\ j jUi-i y £ '.y 0 * j' ^4 lit • li-Ui a“l Z.'I T ^ 31 T l) • - ► JaJ-Jjl j' -C' jl A 4-* is*' &lt;4l&gt;' Ol»L; * - wijjul j oJl! oL~iU!l vj &lt;3^1 (j 4j J~\ Alj *-VJb ^ J ^111 *•&gt; 1*11' li* j jjl[\ 'J UU jJLiir j^UNI '-U Jl. jl ^ (&lt;-&gt;) ^.§ 31)1 U\c j' jy£\ j A-bM 'j oM Ni y* jp v-i \&gt;y~!&gt; o 5 &lt;3&gt;^r ij* jl - j iji l«Uj j* jUMl tali Nlj ji— il — \ s (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become the p~op:rty of the Shaikh free of all cost. ARTICLE 18. On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of Seventy-five Years provided in Article 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. ARTICLE 19. Subject to the provisions of Article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the State if. (a) The Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agree ment within 6 months of the date on which they fall due, or (b) The Company shall be in default in respect of an arbitration award under Article 24 hereof. ARTICLE 20. Nothing in this Agree ment shall be read as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to grant to other parties concessions or permiis for materials other than the Substances as defined in Ar ticle 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. If the Shaikh should at any date sub sequent to the date of signature of this Agreement grant to any other parties con cessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such concessions shall con tain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Company shall be reported to the Shaikh and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. . ^ u* C»&gt; L* u-Mi •JU* •Laa* ! JUf-4) 1 ai ;iUi J® r * • •ii j! ^1 ju AJliil oUl j a) yull j yjd! jli •Jill jj\» U U* ^.^41 Lo *jL»NI j JUc- Jafllll J 11 • oJL»- 4U ^*4^ *-XA j &lt;iJli!l » *-..11. I * jl j eJ&gt; ( I ) •jLMI j ^O&amp;lJhr jldil 01 * 341 ^ ^y\eu» 4-&gt;-y l* . UiVI •JkA (j ylj!J ■ &lt;&gt; l» JLfl) U (jl ijf' jLl«I j»~\ /y y&amp; jl (j &lt; y&gt;- &lt;4 j JL&gt; *1 jl a5^j 4JI (Jl^^ J ^ #jf^jur ^^ ol jLlJ y *)l LL’js* 44^jLiaNI aj&gt; (jli ijf 0 juII ^11 ^*1)1 J! U j»\ ilJ 4^111 4*-* Jr* f z r^ j' 3 l r^. V— 12 — — \Y — Further the Company shall instruct Geologists to mark carefully and report to the Company any area and its location which appears to them to give promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a bore-hole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas. ARTICLE 21. The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called “Petroleum Development ( Trucial Coast) Limited ” or to any other Company registered within the British Empire. ARTICLE 22. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment by the Company of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. Force majeure as used in this Ag reement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. ARTICLE 23. The Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations deletions or additions to this Agreement. Olc-LlH J***' jli cLBS ^ &lt;5^ ^ L*3S^.j ^ 1 (j*- j jlii ^ ^ ^ I ^ J 1 ^ ^ ^ ' # jA&gt;~ ^&gt;^11 y ^ &lt;«&gt; ^ jU' 4 j ^ . £UJI 4*iJI (ill,' Jp li* 4 ^ILj j ^&lt;&gt;^kil j ^ j&gt;-! *£ yt 4)^jt . 4^j IL 4S^y*-'l 4J lit 4^f Ia t Ju,^ ^j£- 4^yitl 4J ike IB t^t J aykli • y* j\^zAl\\ t J&gt; aU- t^l 4-jlibNt ^1*4 1.' (jl • 3»yilt a*1 ^&gt;- y^lllt t^^ 4»iljJ) S yt J?JL&gt;-1» 4^^JJt . 4. 9 UNI 4L.»lt i-ilt ^I '^&gt; -=&gt;JL,' »ykUJl JLa* j oiJIj J.JI UUr^l j oil 4 J-XII aJytl J . j} 45^1!) JJ-U« (J ^yJ ^j*-t 4ili'i olll 4a» 4* I j! t JLI) ^\c Nl 4JUrSt ^*1) jl j&gt;-\ Jy^' ^y oL-i! 4 .Ip 4^jl*)'Nt 3 4)1 (Jp Lu&gt; 45^yittj 34&gt;Nt 4S^yl)l ^ ^ 4&gt;Jlk 4*i ^yyl! . iJU'yi »jla Jl j* jF13 — — \r — ARTICLE 24. (a)If at any time during ^ the currency of this Agreement any dif ference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the interpretation or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbit rators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and 'i in default of agreement shall be London. ARTICLE25. Tho-Gompany ohall all the payment of the sum stated in the Bunk’s ^ lli !S1 •L*I . * ► ► _ » Jli IS! ^ ^ u^- &gt; ~ v—U Ai Jiai ^»***1! l-i^-lj (j-j a jilI . J J-i aS^- ^ f $ bl j j&gt;- ^/l 'j* &lt;L \l-l) J.aj U y aS^»- jlj (iltlJb ^LJIjIL J : A j&gt;. Ml ^ja\\ s * y jL:&gt;-l \*y Ml 3 ^..ii-l j ^L_JI jlL jOI ^jill jli * 1 S \ ' ^ •X+C’ . -X^-I j aH»- j j 1 ^) m ^ U JLii aJ I ( ^ ) # u s J y&gt;-Hl A»^» La \ ^1 I o* y*'i •-L&lt;» j-l^^i|l 3’^^ aII^I 1^1 M| I yl)l!«XA 0^&gt; jl ylll jjy J r &gt; J*U j! a* it- 3^** 0 ^ ( * ) • 0$^? 3^ ! ^ 1 l^lj jU j*}] _ 3j jLOy A^a -LI •ii9va»-Vi 3.«»» MiaUiull -■■ je/Hfi- Ur-iw4l UyA»i^s per mis Agency consull shall 1 1 designs Banks 1 in cor ative versan as a Shaikh and to the Go the Sh; shall 1 Shaikh rate of / ten in If ther as to clause shall i I this P Day ai CO-J l\ Should the Shaikh decide to grant permission for a Bank to open a Branch or Agency in Umm-al-Qaiwain the Shaikh shall consult with the Company as to which Bank shall be given the perm ssion. j' j‘ ^Dl j ) W ^ (jr j-iH £*•*!. cLLJI jLij The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article. ARICLE 26. The Shaikh may select in consultation with the Local Represent ative of the Company a local man - con versant with the English Language - to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company’s Representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company, through the Shaikh in Umm-al-Qaiwain and shall be at the rate of Rupees Four hundred (400) per month. fk.Aa.i~j __ (jjj o^LH ^ l y^- &lt;'Jb&gt;. (j* rt.—ill (jy U Aa&gt; b .Ai jJA\ -X&gt; (j iy ^1 ^ y ^jAA\ 1^*9-XT \ Jt-* V. J (t • • ) ^0^3 ARTICLE 27. This Agreement is writ ten in English and translated into Arabic. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in this Agreement the English text shall prevail. 03 y~*!l J ill ll! l^lj. &lt;L) j*)\ ^ • 1 . »A&gt; y A y *^l-» 3 ^ ^ 5 ^* j Ijl y! &lt;il j 3 * ,,u ^ ^ Aylir^l In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the Day and Year first above written :- Attii dSoii ta (HraoiaiMja A^libV! *J&gt; ^ jljilulil jliyll ^9j U ( A^jikll a: J 1 j ^^*11 S AoiL ^ S kcu&amp;Sv CXSi^nXtdL Ut^v THE COMPANY THE SHAIKH H bvw &amp;'&gt;ruuL «HJJu IN THE PRESENCE OF CXxo^kc t^oJIcajc. H ^r*vufiL lrv&gt;v S uJ 2 X&lt;x-w IN THE PRESENCE OF dUjuB.39 C.9.39 T ELEGRAMS : Inland: PETRIRAQ, AVE. LONDON. Forejgn : PETRIRAQ, LONDON. DIRECTORS : tw, o.c .M .Or ) G. Legh-J. R. Cayrol, .O., D.S.C. (Frenc/i) W. Fraser. C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) ). B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy Jr A.-Merry-(r re web) _ . . \ D.A. Shepard (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers i. Skliros 'V ^ PlLEjcaja^ 4 V EXT jp* 1983 PETROSUM CON CESS IO 945 CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE 'BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD NS LIMITED CRY-GATE-HOUSE Ling House, Dominion Street, FtNSftURY-SQUARE LONDON E.C.2 &gt;7* rS 27th April, 1945. My dear Harrison, PC.34A I refer to the first paragraph of my D.Q, PC.34 dated 12th April addressed to Mr. Peel. We have now received the text of the Umm-al-Quwain Concession which follows identical lines with that of Sharjah and, indeed, is practically an identical copy thereof with a slightly smaller annual payment - Rs. 24,000 p.a. instead of 40,000. An exchange of letters with the Shaikh has provided that the annual payment is to be paid in four instalments. I do not think that you will require us to give you copies of all this, which is somewhat voluminous and of which you already have many examples with the other Trucial Coast Concessions. Would you kindly confirm this? I should be grateful also if you will indicate whether the machinery for a 'Political Agreement between ourselves and you still exists and whether in that case you would wish us to conclude one in respect of Umm-al-Quwain. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. rat kpt. i SSAPRIW / WDJA OFFfCE|m pile c vvVtVa’S * SECRET' 10609 Allotted to External Department . Oooles^Oirculated. CYPHER TELEGRAM (O.T.P.) Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* To Secretary of State for India* Repeated to Government of India* Dated Bushire, 16*15 hours, 29th March 1945* r Received 17*00 hours, 29th March 1945 583 Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Government of India Hew Delhi. My printed lette r C/32 (?1). Umrn~al Xu wain oil nn Ls—i- Politioal Agent repl^ was signed on March March 20th* repeat 30 MAR 1 945 ' INDIA OFFICE203. - • Telegram No. 19. Following £jor Skliros from Packer* } Lermitte reports that Umm-al-Qaiwain concession signed March 20th and terns most satisfactory* Propose return Bahrain after completing payments* Letter follows, • I RECd. POL. EOPt- MAR 10 ^ • INDIA ,^nCE :y OUTWilRD TELEfflAH External Department EXT 630 SECRET CYEHER TELEGRAii (O.T.P. ) Prom: Secretary of State To: Political Agent, Bahrein, Dated; 9th February, 1945- ''^'3550 hours, 3108 . 4 Fuel . Following for PACKER, from SKLIROS. Reference your letter No,3875 of 7th January. Authorities here advise no objection to resumption of negotiations for Urnm El Quwain territory. 2. I prefer outright Concession for 75 years in preference to option or short tern exploration permit and believe the Ruler is of the same mind. 3. Lemitte should undertake negotiations and should endeavour to obtain terms similar to those of Sharjah Agreement but excluding drilling obligations. Financial conditions should not exceed those of Sharjah and I leave it to Lermitte to obtain better terms if possible.INUARP T^LKOHAM! iJfOfiBT &gt;548 Xxx a uy case the communiaatiori o# the c^n tents of this document to any person outside British or tj, b. Government Bervice ia authorised, it must he paraphrased). Allotte d to Extern al Dep artment . GYPH&amp;B gISIxSGRAM From Political A^ent 3ah2*ain, Secretary of State for India Dated Bahrain, 15*00 hours, 15th February, 1945. Reed. 18.30 hours, 15th February, 1945. 102 . Number 9. Following for Okliros from Packer. Your telegram February 8th rupees 60,000 on signature rupees 30,QfX) annually are Shargoh financial terms recorded in text of concessions. Addendum records farther 10,000 confidential annual payment. Bequest for tJral(sic)15,000 for aircraft, relatives find presents of car and lorry were unrecorded payments. Grateful to know which payments are sanctioned for UcMis-al^Qaiwain without further reference to you.Any reply to be addressed :— The Secretary. ViLE O Telegrams: Telephone : Abbey 7000 MINISTRY OF FUEL AND POWER, r -PETROLEUM DIY^SION, Minfupo, Sowest, London.” j'jl Jt^ UlILLB^NK, ^.85 9 / 9 ;e: Lear Harrison, I have recently taken over Bridgeman's work con cerning oil concessions and am now sending you a copy of a letter dated 18th December which we received from Wheatley of the Iraq Petroleum Company organisation, in which he proposes that his group might resume negotiations with the Ruler of Umm El Quwain for exploration rights in his territory, I should be grateful for your views on this point and as I understand that you will wish to await a report from the Political Resident, Bahrein before expressing them, I have warned the Company that it may take a little while before we can given them the answer. Yours sincerely, F.A.K. Harrison, Esq,, India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1.COPY . D omin ion Street, PC. 34. ^P* 2 *... ' }fy dear Bridgeman, In 1938/1939 we were engaged iii negotiations with the Mfciler of Unm El Quwain, one of the Truclal Coast Shaikhdoms a concession or exploration agreement covering his territory. For various reasons, chiefly connected with the Ruler 1 relations with neighbouring Rulers on boundary questions, the Ruler was not prepared, at that time, to conclude an agreement with us. I understand that conditions have now changed and there are no reasons why negotiations should not be resumed and I believe that the Political Agent, Bahrein is also of this opinion. Before issuing instructions to our Bahrein management to resume negotiations, I shall be glad to know that there is no objection, on the part of the India Office and your Ministry, to such action. Yours sincerely, (sgd) H.H. WHEATLEY. The Hon. M.R. Bridgeman, Ministry of Fuel &amp; Power, Petroleum Division, 7, Millbank, S.W.1.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000197_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3839</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000197</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3839</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/110(5) 'Trucial Coast Oil Concessions: Umm-Al-Quwain Concession.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-08T15:32:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (96 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 97; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-97; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the signing of an oil concession agreement between Shaikh Ahmad Bin Rashid [Aḥmad bin Rāshid Āl Mu‘allā], Ruler of Umm-al-Qaiwain (also referred to as Umm-Al-Quwain) and Petroleum Concessions Limited.The papers include copies of the agreement (signed on 20 March 1945); copies (and draft) of the political agreement (signed on 29 January 1946) between HM Government and Petroleum Concessions Limited, relating to the Umm-al-Qaiwain oil concession; correspondence between the India Office, other British Government officials, Petroleum Concessions Limited, and its subsidiary Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited concerning the agreements; and the Ruler's agreement not to enter into negotiations with a bank for permission to open a branch or agency in his country unless he had first obtained the approval of the British Government.The copy of the oil concession agreement between the Ruler of Umm-al-Qaiwain and Petroleum Concessions Limited on folios 66-83 is in both English and Arabic.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Umm-al-Qaiwain</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Umm al Qaywayn</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000197#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>