<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000034_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-26T12:14:03.681Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ Mr, Rum 7 Our Embassy at Tehran have been asked by the Pakistan Embassy there for the loan of files concerning Pakistary' Persian relations, which include a secret pre-partition Government of India memorandum on the Quetta-Sahidan railway. The ;\mbassador asks us (a) whether he may hand over this particular document and (b) whether, as a general rule, there is any objection to his allowing his Pakistan Colleague to have access, to such papers in the British Embassy archives as concern Pakistani immediate interests. It will be seen from the above minuting that some of the pre-partition Government of India, External Affairs Department records have been passed to the Government of Pakistan but that we do not know which or how many, I have spoken to Mr, Rogers, now in the Foreign Office Eastern Department, and until recently a Joint Secretary in the Pakistan Cabinet Office, He has no definite information on this point but thinks that the Government of Pakistan »©£ unlikely to have received anything like the full set of records from the External Affairs Department because the copying of pre-partition documents generally by the Government of India for the use of the Government of Pakistan has been very slow. He thinks there is no doubt but that Pakistan is recognised as having a right to copies of pre-partition files, at any rate those v/hich concern her territory, when the mechanical difficulties of reproducing them can be overcame. With respect to the minuting above, my own view would have been that Pakistan fefcl heir to the pre-partition External Affairs Department records to exactly the same extent as the present Government of India,and that she therefore has as good a title to see copies of any of them in our possession as the present Government of India. I suggest, however, that before we advise the Foreign Office on the reply to be sent to the Ambassador on the general question at (b) we ought to consult our High Commissioners at New Delhi and Karachi, The Memorandum on the gahidan railway is almost exclusively Pakistani concern and I suggest, therefore, that we might advise the Foreign Office to authorise the Ambassador straight away to make this Memorandum available to his Pakistan Colleague, The Memorandum is flagged in the file below. It deals with the history of the negotiations between the Government of India^and the United Kingdom Goverrment and the Persian Government on the extension of the railway line from Quetta to Zahidan and particularly with the question of whether the railway should be continued in operation and whether the section from Mirjawa to Zahidan lying inside Persia should be handed over to the Persian Government or dismantled by the Indian Government. There are references to the views of our Chiefs of Staff on the strategic implications of this railway link with South East Persia but there is nothing in them which we should not want the Pakistan Government to see and, in any case, as the Indian Government have a copy there can be no objection to the Pakistan Government having access to * If you agree I will advise the Foreign Office accordingly and tell them that we will let them know our views on the general question after consulting our High Canmissioners, 0*. o^VbX g.' v&amp;t.'c c*s ^ #Kith the receipt of New Delhi 1 s reply on this question on access to old External Affairs Department records, we are now in a position to advise the foreign Office on their reply to Tehran. May I write as in the draft opposite? I have included in the draft a summary of part of a conversation which I had with Mr. Jackson, formerly attached to the U.K. High Commissioner’s Office, Karachi, and for the last year Second Secretary at our Embassy at Kabul, since this may be useful for the record. It was evident from what Mr. Jackson said that (this is no doubt due to a great deal of hard and tactful work by him and his colleagues) things in Kabul were working very smoothly.r ^a%x Q % i &lt; OUTWARD SAVING TELEGRAM FROM COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFF ^ (BY AIR MAN POLITICAL DEPARTMENT TO: (1) U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN INDIA. (2) ” H n ” PAKISTAN, (Dated 7th February, 1949)» AlP.*—^2 O^VI^G* P ONE T DENT T ^ T 2) No. U3 SAVING. Following is text of cypher O.T.P. telegram No. 107 from Foreign Office to Teheran repeated to the U.K. High Commissioner in India and U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan. Begins . My telegram number 40. Copies of pre-partition Government of India External Affairs Department Records held by you can be made available on request to Pakistan Embassy. Ends* No distribution.lit JtV 4 &gt;8 V* CONFIDENTIAL ^ ' . * .u .£« ’MY TELEGRAM NUMBER 40. COPIES OF PRE-PARTITION GOVERNMENT OF INDIA EXTERNAL AFFAIRS -EPARTMENT RECORDS HELD BY YOU CAN BE MADE AVAILABLE ON REQUEST TO PAKISTAN EMBASSY. a Similar telegram is being sent to the united kingdom high s CO '1MISSI ONER DELHI AND THE UNITED KINGDOM HIGH COMMISSIONER KARACHI. nlv DESPATCHED PAT 7 FEt 10W (9 y ^/ / / Talep^aph Section, Colonial Office, , .Cfeurch House. Telegram Section, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street. Message Control, German Section Foreign Office ^- Norfolk House. Herewith copy of telegram No, War Registry, Admiralty. Duty Signal Office War Office Signal Office / Montague House Annex. 10 i) from; for repetition *in cypher^'- to.. A* v . .A FOREIGN OFFICE. (Date)., 'FICE^ in. ’►Delete when inapplicable. Telegram Section(35291) Wt.46030/47 30,000 3;43 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 R.C. BIACKHAl*!, ESQ., FOREIGN OFFICE. z s\v Printing. (File No.TFov v ran© W • R ' •&gt; ;-eb LL g/2 SECHBT. INDEXED 5? FES 1549, My dear Black ham. You will have seen the telegrams from Pakistan (No. 76) and India (No, X177)/to our telegram of 11th January about access to External Affairs Department records arising out of Tehran's telegram No. 1012 of 29th December. Z This is to invite you to tell Tehran^that they may act /so far as we are concerned^ on the basis of paragraph 2 of our telegram of 11th January. £. It so happens that in the course of a long conversation the other day, I discussed with Donald Jackson, just back from being Second Secretary at our Embassy at Kabul, the question of the machinery used there in disposing of files formerly housed in the sole Embassy but now of interest to all three Commonwealth Embassies, or te any^t-vro of them. He told me that the British Embassy had gone through all the files which might be of interest to the Indians or the Pakistanis or both, removed occasional pages where any were found which were clearly unsuitable to be handed on, and made them quite freely available to the Indian or Pakistani Embassy. One whole batch of files had in fact been sent over to the Pakistan Embassy in the early days. When our people wanted one, or when they were asked for one by the Indians, they had no difficulty in recovering it from the Pakistanis. The whole thing had worked extremely well with no/ill-feeling in any quarter^ and a point had even been reached at which the Pakistanis would let their next-door neighbours,the Indians, have a file without going through the motions of sending it out to the Embassy. 4. In a word, at Kabul they have been going on the basis that except in special cases, files on Indian matters which grew up in the days of British -riule in India are common property and that it is simply a matter of making the most convenient arrangements for lllCLO V Ox wx UKXXVX V I.*v* ^ w &gt; / H ,, / or c their future use and custody. ^ Ju ^ &gt; ^ , ^ ;&gt; A, &lt;4 ^ repetition to New Delhi and Karachi. ^ • L, H, vVAL^^ r.lo* a &amp; This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message and unless it is marked O.LP. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if commun icated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex must be in a One Time System. ALLOTTED TO POLITia'iL (EXTERNAL) DEPAKI MEK'j h^ X i PROM ; U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN INDIA ' TO: COMMONWEALTH RELAT IONS O ^ISE . ; REPTD TO: TEHRAN U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN (BY SAVTNGRAM) New Delhi, 19*45 hours, 27 th January, 1949 16.40 hours, 27 th January, 1949 D R Addressed to Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, No. X177&gt; repeated to Tehran No. X3 (C.R.O. please pass loth addressees) repeated to U.K.High Commissioner in Pakistan (hy Savingram). Without making enquiries v/hich in the light of your paragraph 3 we presume you do not wish us to do we arc unable to confirm whether or not the Indian Government are having copies made for the Pakistan Government of pre-partition Government of India External Department records. In view, however, of Grafftey Smiths understanding as expressed in his telep;ram _ 6 * No#76 to you that this is in fact being done we see no reason why copies of the records available to us should not be made available on request to Pakistan Government representatives. Copy to: Foreign Office (S*E.£ .ckham Copy to Foreign Office Cypher Ro l ission to Tehran6 This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message and unless it is marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if commur ^ icated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex must be in a On i Time System. I* 4 '■t D I ! U INDEXED Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office jJ r - . 19 4 J ALLOTTED TO POLITICAL (EXT. ) DEPARTMENT. CYPHER (TYPEX) FROM : TO: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN SECRETARY OF STATE FOR COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS REPTD,TO : U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN INDIA H.M. EMBASSY, TEHRAN D. KARACHI, 12.35 Lours, 15th January, 1949 R. 11,00 hours, 15th January, 1949 IMPORTANT No.76 . CONFIDENTIAL . Addressed to Secretary of State for Commonv/ealth Relations No.76, repeated to U.K. High Commissioner in India No. 66 , and H.M. Embassy, Tehran No. 2 (Commonwealth Relations Office'-.please pass). Your telegram No. 89 , January 11t h. Access of Pakistan Embassy, Teheran, to pre-partition records. I understand the position to be as stated in your paragraph 1 and agree with your paragraph 2 . Copy to :- EXT. C.R.O. Mr. Belch) Foreign Office (S.E.A.Dept.) Mr. Bl^ckham. Foreign Office Cyphej/ Room for retransmission to Teheran. l/ 17 JAN 1949SECRET. (T) . YOUR TELEGRAM NUMBER 1312. THERE IS NO OBJECTION TO YOU LENDING THE PAKISTAN EMBASSY THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA'S MEMORANDUM ON THE 2AHIDAN RAILWAY. 2 . c.R.O. ARE CONSULTING THE U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONERS AT NEW DELHI AND KARACHI ON THE GENERAL QUESTION OF WHETHER PRE PARTITION GOVERNMENT OF INDIA EXTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT RECORDS SHOULD PE MADE AVAILABLE TO THE PAKISTAN AUTHORITIES ^AND WE HOPE TO BE ABLE TO GIVE YOU INSTRUCTIONS ON THIS POINT SHORTLY. 1^. A SIMILIAR TELEGRAM IS BEING SENT TO THE U.K. H.C. KARACHI.3/C ■ - A-/ _ &gt;:s ^ too*/' Dear Eiackkarfl, Co-^iionweulth Relatione Office, Donning Street, A 4 * January, 1949 Sill you please refer to Tehran telegram Ko# I0i£ of the 29th Deceodjer about the internal Affaire Departraflnt records of the pre—partition Goe^ nuacnt of India* Tr-ie is to confirm that we e ee uo objection to the Go'V* mment of India iiieBJoranduusa on the Aa.tii 'Siin -aii-^ay* referred to in paragraph 1 of the Ambassador’s telegram, being male araliable to his Pakistan oolleague in Tehran. t?e suggest that a reply to the Ambassador*• reference on the general question of whether pr^'partition Goeenuocnt of India external Affairs I^rtment xewj^sshouid be made arailabie to the Pakistan tigh Co.,^iasaeh&gt;r xn Tehran should be deferred until we have had an opportunity of obtainin the viewa of the two High Commissioners at Karachi Tours sincerely. e* Delhi* K. vV. D. K ( VVLER R* C. Blactfasm, Esq., South East Asia Department, Foreign Office. — —* This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher message and unless it is marked O.T.P. (One Time Pad) or Publex must first be paraphrased if com municated to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Any telegraphic retransmission of a telegram marked Publex must be in a One Time System. Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office POLITICAL (EXTERNAL) DEPARTMENT D, II. POL. (EXT.) 6004A 8 . CYPHER (TYPEX) TO: (I) U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN INDIA. (2) » ' » ' PAKISTAN. RPTS. TO : U.K. EMBASSY, TEHRAN. (SENT 22.30 hours, 11th January, 1949). CONFIDENTIAL Addressed to U.K. High Commissioner in India No. 133 and U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan No. 89« Repeated to U.K. Embassy, Tehran for information. Tehran telegram No. 1012 dated 29th December, repeated to U.K. High Commissioners in New Delhi and Kara'chi as our telegrams Nos. 14 and 12 of 1st January. External Affairs Department records. Our understanding is that Indian and •• Pakistan Governments have equal title to pre-partition Government of India External Affairs Department records and that Indian Government are having copies made for Pakistan Government. No doubt this is a slow process still far from complete. 2. If this is correct, we see no reason why copies of pre—partition External Affairs Department records held here or by our Diplomatic posts should not be made available on request to Pakistan Government representatives. 3 . We should be grateful for your views. We think that you should not, repeat not, say anything to the Governments of India and Pakistan at this stage. Copy to:- Poreign Office (S.E. Asia Dept.) Mr. Blackham. (Foreign Office Cypher Section for retransmission to Tehran.)(86291) Wt.40030,47 30,000 3/43 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Op.685 (File No bOOl^ j C.R.O. Mr. Fowler. 13/1/4-9 * C* m ^&amp;QA'\cA ^ for UKC0M NM DELHI; NO. UKCOM KARACHI; NO. Repeated for information to TEHRAN: !9 Parly. U.S. of S. Secretary of State 2 DRAFT TELEGRAM , fs&lt;o\^ ^oc C-ReVpvx'o-vs Vo 1. U.K. Hi^i Commissioner, New Delhi. 2. U.K. High Coranissioner, Karachi. rs.ye.cV’Cfc' to 0 ^C- '^iVCft.vv /* DISTRIBUTICN II. Further action. R^usated for infOxiua. lion T^irair.' O' \ Copy to: .Mr. Blaclijan, ^South-East Asia Dept. Foreign Office^ SENT % AT ^L ON-nji 3Y _ Printing. Rcfereneo Tehran telegram No. 1012 dated 29th December, repeated UKCOMs New Delhi and Karachi as our telegrams No. 14 and 12 of 1st January. External Affairs Department records. Our understanding is that Indian and Pakistan Governments have equal title to pre-partition Government of India External Affairs Department records and that Indian Government are having copies made for Pakistan Government. No doubt this is a slow process still far from complete. J. If this is correct, we see no reason why f copies of pre-partition External Affairs Departmen£\records held here or by our Diplomatic ^osts should not be made available on request^ to Pakistan Government representatives. 4. We should be grateful for 1S&amp; views. IT ■ IT 1 Hti gh Cnimni 1 ?i nnam TTrnr TVltri nnri Kormhi Y*w We think kt-Wtter that they should not, repeat not, say anything to the Governments of India and Pakistan at this stage.(jKO&gt;k[ L)6t.f/{ &gt; s^fr' s ■ y r; w V ? t [This toleg^an i sof particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed onj oypu r/arp. r. ..a?Lai tic ^.gHiBurioK .. ^ v^ •' u -- ^ h _ I rdr J, ■ r ^ 1 ougrt^l.—). l*gTp.-m. I o # 1012, I&gt;ecaftb€r r 1948, . 2.40 29th December, Repeatedio 29th December, 1940. h ommis si oner jelhi, # oniKilssionsr /Ja'acni. . December. repeated for infomaticn to United Kingdaa nigh Tolnis r&gt;i one r elnijand United Kin 4om High C and s si oner Karachi. twlo «jO - i mediate interests: and c^u^^ly pointless to refuse Indian mbassy documents held by their parent department. I have, in fact, already handed over to Indian .mb&amp;ssy a £ppy or Lorrimer* s Gazetteer of Persian Gulf published by uovernment of India and classified as secret. Addres s ed to F oreign Office telegram O.1012 of ,29th The Pakistan mbassy have asked me to la^d them files on certain subjects affecting 1 rkistsn—Persian relations including a secret (roveriment of India iahidan Railway -M12/45 m«aarandum on Zahidan Railway (sent to me under New Delhi's express letter F.10(65)-i /45 of July 1st 1947). 2. My instinct would be to \¥ithhold this raeiaorandua but if I am right in thinking that archives of pre partition Axtemal Affairs Department are in present Indian Government's possession, it would seem unfair to deny Pakistan access to such papers as concern their cwrn 5 # I should be grateful if early guidance by telegram on general question and particular case of memorandum referred to. f Foreign Office please pass-to Unit^d King^^ i High Commissioners Delhi and Karachi as jay telegrams Nos.25 and 50 respectively. ^to Tele ition to U.K. Section C.R^O^for , gn &lt; ^Issioncr^'lfT.hi &amp; Karachi] cy!^yi^ crv\ o^f +A o — ■■■■■</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000034_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3493B</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000034</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3493B</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/87 ‘Persia. Railways. Mirjawa-Duzdap Section of Duzdap Railway; Zahidan Railway; Road communications between Persia &amp; Indian Persia.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-30T10:08:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file. File notes at the rear of the correspondence (ff 2-5) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to an enquiry dated 29 December 1948 from the British Ambassador at Tehran, John Haller Le Rougetel, to the Foreign Office, asking if the archives of the Government of India’s External Affairs Department dating prior to Indian partition (1947) can be freely shared with the Government of Pakistan. The specific document to which Le Rougetel’s enquiry relates is a secret memorandum on the Zahidan railway, situated on the frontier between Iran and Pakistan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Access to information</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Pakistan</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Government archives</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000034#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>