<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000342_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T13:31:21.843Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No . Ilfl ot 1926. British Rpeidenoy and Consulate-oeneral, Bushire , x:i '^'uey 1926 The political .agent, Bahrein I - With his letter No.120, dated the 29^ July 1901 , the assistant political ngeni, , Bahrein, forwarded ** a oow of a letter dated the 12th Rabi - us - Sani 1319 ( 29th July 1901) addressed to him by sheikh Esa bin ^li ^1 Khalifah , in whi#h the latter made a free gift to tne British Government of the land on whioh the Bahrein ^ genoy buildings stand - as you contemplate exchanging some of this land for another piece outside, the Hon'ble the political Resident wishes you to draft a letter which the shaikh may oe asked to issue^ amend ing by mutual consent the original grant. The political Resident would like the proposed draft sent over for his approval before any mention of it is made to Sheikh Hamad - Captain, Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Qulf./ I The Political Agency Baiirain. Persian Gulf. 6/6/&amp;Z6 The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political n esident in the Persian Gulf .Bushire, Memo r and un. With reference to your Memo. No 1359 of 23rd -^ay I&amp;26. The plot of land which has 'been exchanged with the Bahrain Governmmnt is no part of the original site on which the Agency was 'built k which was the land referred to in the Assistant 'olitical Agent's letter No 120 of 29th July 1901. The plot exchanged ws a piece of waste land outside the Agency but adjacent to it on the V /tst side. This plot was gifted to the Agency either in the time Colonel Trevor (the Major Trevor) was in Bahrain or sometime later during the war,I regret I am unable to. trace exactly when. Colonel Trevor himself drew my attention to it olt was originally acquired as there was at the time a proposal to build quarters for clerics a proposal v/hich jz was subsequently ab-mdoncfld on ancount of the expense involved, .1 .V X« * • . The plot has consequently never been used.It has been exchanged for a plot precisely similar adjoining the Agency on the -^ast side. Colonel Trevor originally approved of the paxKhx purckkse of the plot on the -^ast side if funds could be found for the purpose,!: subsequently Colonel ^rideaux when in Bahrain confirmed his approval^ The matter remained in abeyance as I ta had no suggestions as to how payment could be effected lc at the time there seemed no grounds for an excahnge, later the Govt, of Batrain State were anxious to acquire a site to build State offices upon &amp; also the Municipality of Manameh wished to complete the sea-front scheme,!: the only possible place where i. the sea front road could enter the Town was on the plot belonging to the Agency to the Vvest.Shaik Hamad requested KXtkK either that the State be permitted to purchase the plot or toNo» (7 SI of 1926 • British Residency &amp; Consulate General t Bus hire # the Uik July 1926, To The political &lt;t igent t Bahrein, ^emorandugi^ Reference your memorandum No# 65/2 /4 dated the 6th June 1926 » In the circumstances explained , the Hon'ble the political Resident approves the transaction effected regarding the exchange of land and agrees that a further .letter from the sheikh is unnecessary* By order, Captain, Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian (Julf ♦</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000342_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/99</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000342</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/99</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Correspondence re Title-Deeds of Agency Land'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1926</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-02-11T00:05:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged in approximately chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: Circled in pencil, in the top right corner of each folio. It begins on the front cover, on number 1, and runs through to 5, ending on the inside of the back cover.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between Major Clive Kirkpatrick Daly, British Political Agent at Bahrain, and Captain B Stuart Horner, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire. The correspondence concerns the exchange of land between the British Agency and the Bahrain Government, and the possible necessity to amend title-deeds.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000342#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>