<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000298_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:53:09.965Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■■■ A i'ranslation of 'Han No. 21/1359 dated 8th uamad 1 1359 Cl3«6 # 4C) issued by the Manama i-unicipality* Bahrain# In amendment of ‘Ilan ho. 4/1357 dated 8th ^Aiharram 1357(l0th *oarch 1S38) the public are hereby informed that it is strictly forbidden to carry out repairs of cars, buses and other vehicles on public roads and streets. Such repairs should be carried out in garages set for the purpose* Whoever contravenes this order will be prosecuted in the Court by the b a ladiyah. j-P-JiGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN ^ - N U T I G S. ILj~.c /r — No. El/1359. jL Incinerator. y -Owifig to 'cou^laitiirs -ffiade ; by'the Bahrain &gt;—* 4 {4 1-Petroleum Gomjiany Linite^d^agaiust^ certain ;; persons going to the Incinerator and taking away some materials lying there - the Baiirain G-ovemment proclaim to the public that it ^ he is hereby forbidden to go to the INGIKERiiTOR. So, whoever disobeys this order - whether man, woman or child - will be liable to a fine !Lji^ r JSOp exceeding Bs. 50/-. Sd/ G. Dalrymple Belgrave Adviser to the Government Dated, 30th Rajab, 1359. September E, 1940.GOVERNMENT OP BAHRAIN NOTICE \re^ , XI No, 2 4 -i 359 . j RAMADHAN, ^j(Ja.Aj jf-** I — : J*Lu^:c JjUl • jlLiVlj _Vl ^ ^v. Lip &gt;il| ^ -&gt; r • cij 5, apI^JI ¥* • 41 ji* m ^L r - LlWUt a&gt;-j - I At aJI l Up The public are informed that during the month of Ramadhan it is forbidden:- r. To smoke, eat or drink in the streets or the bazzars between the morn ing and evening guns. 2. To open restaurants during the day-time. 3. To bake bread publicly during the day-time except from eight o'clock Arabic. 4 * To play any music which may be audible. W hosoever is found breaking this rule will be severely dealt with. Adviser to the Government &gt;^0^ jLw tV [) ate ^th Shaban, 1359. September 29, 1940.GOVERNMENT OP BAHRAIN c;lU&gt;! NOTICE \ro\ rt No. 24—1359. jLU A* I jy£ — : . jlkjVlj iJL.^^1 ^ * jLjJ — Y jUp &gt;il!&gt;. - -r • L^'J* Apl-Jl 3 L.-*. j O' 4 -^ * U. aJI llitp RAM AD HAN. The public are informed that during the month of Ramadhan it is forbidden:- 1. To smoke, eat or drink in the streets or the bazzars between the morn ing and evening guns. 2. To open restaurants during the day-time. 3. To bake bread publicly during the day-time except from e&gt;ight o’clock Arabic. 4. To play any music which may be audible. Whosoever is found breaking this rule will be severely dealt with. Adviser to the Government &gt;f©A jU- tV jj 5 - N At * XA ^&gt;1 Date 771,1 Shaban &gt; 1 359 - ' September 29, 1940.wmmm-' Srov^ — y \ jh sreV —\« io.^' -Xi^f — : ^rliU \*\:l\ &lt;:i±* J jvUUi j\U^I ^i.dU^l;!.', •\;. xa^j jjT*^ -N . y 4 )^ 5 e.«.« ^ jt {j^ l ^ 4 ^ A.«IaH ol&gt;! £&gt; J\ djAs Ui^l j! J*^ °* J jr Jy. J ftyi' «j *jj^&gt; d^) jl.ly,- j jA. j «d! j i ^ * j » ^Jl _*l ©a* J .a-i;!y b!-r A # ^ *V‘ c? }~ \) oJ\ «c| &lt; 1 * ^,C j j'K*** cJslii^ ^ * J * Aiil^a^-iil aj^ &gt;r\* t\ j jj&gt;- a-*IaI ai^^x* j ^GOVERMENT OF BMRAIN NOTICE. No. 8/1360. The following notice has been published by the Government of Zanzibar, and it is published for information of those who may have business with Zanzibar;- w Qwing to the increasing cost of repatria tion, the Government of Zanzibar has found it necessary to increase the immigration denosit in respect of immigrants lancing in the Protectorate by dhow' from a maximum of Shs. 20/- to a maximum of Shs. 40/-. ,I Sd/ C. Dalrymple Belgrave Adviser to the Government. Dated, 14th Rabi-awwal, 1360. April 10, 1941.Translation of letter No.86/3/1366 dated 29th Dec 46 from the Manama Municipality, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. vVe forward herewith a copy of the agenda for the 1st meeting of the Municipal Committee which will be held on Thursday next, 9th Safar 1366 (2.1.47) at 4.30 Arabic time. income zu'zavi/ d/a as compared with Rs. 168844/ 8/4 for 1364. Sxpenditur 206379/ 9/6 - do - 168567/ 3/6 - do - (The expendit6re exceeded the income by Rs.1988/5/10 in the year 1365). 4. MoTIMnTnp . Or'. MUNICIPAL BUDGET Pl)K TH3 1366 The Account &amp; Budget Board fixed the following budget for the year 1366 Income Rs.204000/0/0 Expenditures- Rs.266000/0/0 (the expenditure will thus exceed the income by Rs.62000/0/0 which will be met from the reserved money. 5• ^gadi ng of the municipal annual report for 1365. ‘ Expiration oi the period, of the survey committee. 7. Heading of letters. Heading of the municipal committee report r A.C. Agenda of th e 1st meeting to be held on Thursday 9th 5afar. Income 54073/15/10 Expenditure 51133/13/00 as compared with Re. 30971/4/3 for 1364. - do - 30190/14/0 - do - Safe _li/ r ” ” •• aovb/ y/ ^ 1364 Rs.95218/ 9/ 5 Rs. 115920/ 6/4 W •GOVKRMENT OF B/iffiAIN. NOTICJS. Ho. J5/1064. VHtMlH The public are)hereby informed, ihut tne present pjtioie I\'o.O of tiie/GoYeriiment proclsmatxon i.o.o/iobJ shell be cancelled ana following substituted Article 5 . PlfiGEGOODS. 9 pieoe^ooda iidported into Bahrain from India shall be pooled. Direct importers shall retain goods imported with them until the Food Control Department a^iot* then to shop keepers to whom direct importers shall then sell at a profit of ia&amp;. , i • . B (o)Retailers S/.all sell to the puolic at a profit of on the wh ole s ale pr i oe. Theyshall not sell such piecegoods to otner retail merchfints*. (d)ETeryd direct importer of piecegoods shall maintain a register grring details of all such piecegood held or imported by him and of every sale to retailers. (e)Freryretailer snail mairtain a register in tne form attached details of all east* and credit purcnasos and sales made by him of tne piecegoods. (fJA notice shall be displayed by the retailers in their shops notifying the public of the retail price fixed by tne price Controller. Let this be known. bdj Smitn, (l Adviser to tne Government, Bai train. Dated, 14th Dhul^aada, 1364, 20th October, 1945. JM.GOVERMEi^T OF 3 AHRAIJM. NOTICE. No.36/1364. The public are hereby informed that the article No.3 (b) of the Bahrain Government proclamation No.3/63 shall be amended‘.to read as follows Article 3 fo). \ihen asses sine the retail prices of rationed foodstuffs referred to in Article 3 (a; of Order No.2 of 1944, a profit of 3$.. and 3J 7 * shall ue allowed to the retailers of Munamah and moharraq res pectively. Order No. 5 of 1944 is hereby cancelled. 3 d G.W.R. Smith, Ag. Adviser to the Government Bahrain. Dated, 16th Dhulq_aada, 1364, 22nd October, 1345. JM.Translation of Notice No.3/1366, dated the 18th Jamada el-Thani issued ty the Manamah Municipality It is hereby notified for the information of the public that the Manamah Municipality, pursuant to the decision of its council, invites tenders for^ farming of taxes leviable on stones and gach piled on the jetty, the taxes being Re.l/“ on a pile of Gatch, Re -/8/- on a pile of flat coral stones and Re. /4/- on a pile of stones, pebbles or sand. apply in writing to this office, giving the amount he is prepared to pay for the contract. It must be borne in mind that every contractor should deposit with the Municipality a sum not less than Rs.300/-. Any one interested in the offer should ■Hi * * Translation of Municipality Notification No.4 of 1366 dated the 23rd of April, 1947. Pursuant to a decision passed by the Municipal Council in its fourth and seventh sessions of the 30th Habi Awwal, 1366 and 27th Janadah Awwal, 1366 i.e. the 20th February, 1947 and 17th April, 1947, respectively, all the residents of Manamah town are hereby notified that Municipal Taxes on residential houses and Commercial buildings used by their owners have been re-adjusted so that the lowest rate does not become less thah Annas 8/- and the highest rate does not exceed Rs.5/-. This regulation will take effect from the 1st day of Rajab 1366 (i.e. the 21st of May, 1947). The Municipality will send all those affected intimations as to the amount levied on each of them. Taxes on rent houses and shops will, however, remain as they are now. Let it be known. Bahrain Receipt »**• r</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000298_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1929</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000298</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1929</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File F/4 II 'Proclamations &amp; Notifications Received from the Manama and Muharraq Municipality'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-10T22:35:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (38 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 38; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This files contains public notices and proclamations from the Manama Municipality and the Government of Bahrain. Their subject matters range from the regulation of building material, particular trades, public sanitation and hygiene, to the regulation of public behaviour during Ramadan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Manamah Municipality</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bahrain, Āl Khalīfa dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Municipal ordinances</topic></subject><subject><topic>Proclamations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000298#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>