<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000089_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T04:43:59.180Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">“n 1 Vuh.- ' Y'-&gt;' l 111 Copy of Secret letter No.84-22/l0-C dated the 4th May 1946, from His Majesty*s Consul-General for Khorasan, Meshed to the Secretary to the Govt#-of India. External EXT Affairs Department, New Delhi. / p. vist of H.M's Embassy, Tehran, who recently visited Zahidan has pointed out that the safe accommodation of the Zahidan i % ^ V Consulate is not sufficient. The reason for this is that '^jp, when there is no officer holding the post of Vice-Consul Zahidan/Zabul thej^ cyphers and codes of that post have to be kept at Zahidan. I therefore request that arrange ments may kindly be made to supply another safe for the Zahidan Consulate, which should be equipped with both a combination and a lock. ■ \iT\(o I have the honour to state % /y_ Copy of Secret X-Letter No.F.84-A/46 dated the 12th December 1946 from Foreign, New Delhi to H.M's Consul, Zahidan. Subject:- Combination lo ck safe fo r Zahidan Consulate. Reference correspondence ending with your letter No.427-A/7, dated the 20th November 1946. 2. M/S Godrej &amp; Boyce Mfg. Co. Ltd., Bombay are unable to supply a combination lock safe of the same dimensions as that supplied to Kerman Consulate. They can however supply a safe of the following specifications:- Godrej new patent superior quality fire and burglar resisting safe measuring, 61' high x 31' wide x 27i' deep outside, 53' high x 23' wide x 17' deep inside, fitted with two drawers at bottom, three adjustable shelves and secured with two double control gordian key locks and one numerical combination lock - colour special grey at E?.2175/- each net, packed and delivered f.o.r. or free on Docks Bombay, delivery in February 1947. If this safe will meet the requirements, the indent in triplicate of which forms are enclosed may be returned j \ urgently • • «2 urgently to this Department duly filled in so that steps may be taken to place an order with the supplying firm. 3* The Government of India would like to know whether it would be oossible to meet the expenditure involved from within the sanctioned budget grant at your disposal for the current financial year. 4. It is presumed that in the event of the supply of Godrej combination lock safe, the Chubb safe at present with the Zahidan Consulate would not be required and would be sold to the best advantage of Government. THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. Copy of Secret X-Letter No.l9-C dared 9th January 1947 from Britain, Zahidan to Foreign, New Delhi. Subject:- Combination lock safe for Zahidan Consulate. —————————— Your Express Letter No. F.84-A/46, dated 12th December, 1946(copy being sent to Prodrome, Tehran). The Godrej safe under reference will meet the require ments of this Consulate and the indent (in triplicate) is returned herewith duly filled in. 2* It will not be possible to meet the expenditure invol ved from within the sanctioned budget grant at my disposal for the current financial year. 3 * The Chubb safe at present with me will be required for X - the use of the Vice Consul, Zabul/ ahidan, when he in residence at Zahidan. The Petambar safe in this Consulate can, however, be disposed of to the best advantage of Government, provided it is not required elsewhere. The origin of this safe is not Known but it is an ordinary lock sat6, the inside measurements being 2 feet high, 1 foot wide and li feet deep. ✓ PTO.Qe) - 3 - Copy of letter No. SR-3/76278/I dated 16-4-1947, from Director General of Supplies, New Delhi to the Under Govt.of India, Secretary(G), External Affairs Department. /New Delhi . Sub:- Supply of combination lock safe for H.M f s consulate at Zahidan against his indent No. Nil dated 9.1.47. Ref:- Your U.O. No.D.3132-A/46 dated 14.11.46 to D.S.,Bombay. BoYce Mfg. Co. Ltd., Bombay have expressed their inability to supply the safe of the size mentioned in the above indent but for earlier delivery they can supply the following safe which is the nearest approach to the 6r f Superior safe. One Godrej 16 Corner Bend Fire &amp; Burglar Resisting Single Door Safe of C quality measuring: fitted with 2 drawers at bottom, 3 adjustable shelves and secured with two double control gordian key locks and one numerical combination lock. Colour: Special Grey. Copy of Secret letter No.F.84-A/46 dated 25.4.47 from Govt, of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi to the Director General, Industries &amp; Supplies, New Delhi. Subject:- Supply of a combination lock safe for H.B.M f s Consulate at Zahidan. With reference to your letter No.SR-3/76278/1 dated the 16th April 1947 on the above noted subject, I am directed to say that there is no objection to the purchase of the combina tion lock safe now offered for H.M*s Consulate at Zahidan. I am to request that the supply of the safe to Zahidan Consulate be arranged at a very early date. I have the honour to inform you that M/s. Godrej &amp; CO’* high x 30' wide x 26' deep (outside) 53' high x 23' wide x 17' deep (inside) Please intimate at an early date whether the above store will suit the Indentor^ requirements. An early reply will be appreciated. — oOoFro® • The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department, To • Kis Britannic Majesty's Consul General for Khorasan* Meshed, Memorandum Ko, F.84-A/46, Dated Mew Delhi 3, the 3 V ^ May, 1947. Subject*- Supply of a combination lock safe for His Britannic Majesty's Consulate at Reference correspondence ending with the endorsement from the Government of India, External Affairs Department No. F.84-A/46, dated the 25th April 1947. combination lock safe for His Britannic Majesty's Consulate at Zahldan at a cost not exceeding: Es.2,175/- plus incidental charges. Efforts should be made to meet as much of this expenditure as possible from within the sanctioned budget at your disposal for\ the current financial, year and the balance which cannot be so met may be included in your statement of savings and excesses to be forwarded to this Department in due course., 3. fhe Government of India agree to the retention of the existing Chubb safe for the use of the Vice-Consul, abul/?ahidan when he is in residence at Zahidan. The Petarabar safe in the Zahidan Consulate should be disposed of to the best advantage of Government and sale proceeds credited to Central Revenues provided it is not required elsewhere* Sanction is accorded to the purchase of a ( Sd/- P.N. Krishnaswamy ) Under Secretary to the Government of India*I have the honour to inform you that M/s Godrej &amp; Boyce Mfg. Co. Ltd., Bombay have expressed their inability to supply the sa4e of the size mentioned in the above^inddnt but for^ earlier delivery they can supply the following saie which is the nearest approach to the 61 n Superior safe. One Godrej 16 Corner Bend Fire &amp; Burglar Resisting single Door Safe of C Quality measuring 60 ,, high x 30' wide x 26' deep (outside) 53' ' x 23' ' x 17' ' (inside), fitted with 2 drawers at bottom, 3 adjustable shelves &amp; secured with two double control gordian keyllocks and on«.numerical combination lock. Colour: Special Grey. Please intimate at an early date whether the above store will suit the Indentor’s requirements. An early reply will be appreciated. Sd/- C.L.Katial. Deputy Director of Supplies, for D.G. I&amp;S. RLK.6.6.47 ENCU&gt;&amp;U&amp;£ WU INDIA. FOREIGN SECBETAIN 1 * LETTFR NO. DATE RECEIVED 4 5 7 - 11-6-1947INWARD TELEGRAM r XT I II n ; ' ^ '-fj '-T^ 7 / B-epartment Allotted to External CONFIDENTIAL CODE ^ ^.a -../I y, i^rom Government of India, ''Internal Affairs, Dept. To Tehran No. l? fSslwV Reptd-to Consul General Meshed and Secretary of | State for India, No. 936 Dated New Delhi 23.00 hours, 3rd February, 1947 Reed. 13.00 hours, 4th February, 194 7. 936 It is proposed to post Major H.D.Rushton Indian Political Service on return from leave in April as Consul Zahidan vice Metcalfe applied for leave. Ruehton served as Secretary and Consul Bushire. in 1939. Trust you will agree*INWARD TELEGR A 'ext COPY 4710 18217 (xmZDmsikrtsiJZsf •mjstmu ■ From Government of India, External ;if fairs Department* To Tehran, Ho- 109 B Repeated, to Consul General Meshed and .Secretary of State for India. Bat cd Hew Delhi, 06*30 hours, 9th July 1946* Received 05.40 hours, 9th July, 1946„ XlitPORgAKT. 6962. foreign telegram Bo« 106 f June 50th* V5.ce-&lt;;onsuX ^ahidan/^ebul* Ma^or P.HvB* Woods 6 th D^GvO* Lancers, an 15*0*0*, who has to sen appointed toiapor-arily to officiate in Indian Political Service f is available imediately* Age 30 y educated Shrewsbury and London School of Engineerings Goo cl war record* Please telegraph whether you agree*A ll a t ted to External D-ept ^ Copies circulated * J CONFIDENTIAL COPE TELEGRAM From To Repeated Dated Received •Government of India, External Affairs Dept, Ambassador Tehran (1ST) to Secretary of State for India and Meshed New Delhi, 23,55 hours, 12th May 194&amp;, 01,20 hours, 13th May 194$, 4566 Meshed telegram 11 February 32nd. Skrlne'a leave and proposal for Smith to officiate as Consul General Meshed. No objection provided you have none* It is proposed to post Captain R.M. Saker of Indian Political Service to Meshed as Vice-Consul in the first instance and then Zahidan as Consul vice Smith. Saker is in hie twelfth year of service in““lndian Political Service and has been officiating as a Political Agent in Baluchistan, Trust you will agree-.India Office, Whitehall, PGL. 182 S/i *4 Iloveidjer, 1944* Subject:- Classification as «S\^erio[r« In reply to your Sxpress Air Mail letter No. D. dated 6t ^ _ September, 1944, on the above subject, I am directed by the Secretory of State to inform you that he sanctions the proposal that the post of Consul, ^ahxdan, shoulu be re-classified as a Superior Post on the cadre of the Indian Political ervxoe. The Secretary to the G-overrment of India, External Affairs Department. of the post of Consul Zahid&amp;n. Sir I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant ^d.) J. p : QIBSGftfirualj? Cf+vt. ? ■£. fi&gt; Co VkM ««0 cl *m\J W«* W&lt;A* WM db * iti Mm A* Meshed to Forei^i t New Delhi. opy of an express letter No. 301/^/35, dated the 10th March 1944. from Consul General, r. n Affairs Department telegram No ^ dated March 1st, • '?. A. xtarnal 0,0 9M Reference Government of India. __ 29/1/Cam 1944. w &gt; ' 2. The sanction to the expenditure' of Rupees 450/« in connection with the provision of j e barters for the Medical Officer sod.Vlce onsul Sahidan conveyed in Government of India External Affairs Department m«norandim wo. 5- A/43 dated title 25th February 1943 was received at Meshed on tbe 15th March 1943. It was then / too late to meet the charts either by re-appro priation or by request for additional grants y 4*bich had already been submitted to the JftxJGovernment of India in this Consulate General ^ ^letter No. 295/A/62 dated the 10th March 1943. i^-vvln the circumstances there was no alternative &lt;j3ut to meet the charge from the grants of the u rf^ahidac Consulate for 1943-44. as a result of is included in r) Rupees 5,250/- under 'Office Allowance in this Consulate General letter No. amount total anticipated excess of llowance' reported 1391/V62. Government of India It is requested that the will kindly approve and sanction the expenditure in 1943-44. It is regretted that the fact was not unicated immediately on the receipt of the randum No. 5-A/43 dated the 25th February ^Cl-OSU E IN INDIA m Sj CF TAI LETTER Is!/i 5atl RECEIVED s Isi 1 4 19-7-1944BM&amp;IiB/Am e&gt; From - The Under Seoretazy to the CrOTernaent of India in the External Affaire Department, To • Hie Britannic Majesty^ Memorandum Ho* 763-A/44. T;/ Dated New Delhi, the April 1944. Reference your express letter No. 301/S/ 35, dated the lOtn March 1944. 2. In the circumstanoes explained, the GoTemmBnt of India are pleased to approve of your action to meet the expenditure of Rs. 450/- sanctioned in paragraph 2 of this Department memorandum No. 5-A/43, dated the 25tn February 1943, from the grants of the Zahidan Consulate for the year 1943*44. Consul Gen for Khorassan, ILE 8 .H S Ot Subject:* Provision of Quarters for the Medical Officer and Vice Consul- Zahid&amp;iu Sd/* V. B. Arte Under Secretary to the Government of India.av/. British Embassy t Tehran, No.99. (230/9/44) Sir, n.o. I have the honour to transmit herewith three specimens oi the oi'X'icial seal and siiiiiature of Lieutenant-Colonel Daniel kichard Siaith, His Majesty’s Consul at Eahidan. 2. Lieutenant-Colonel ^aith assumed his duties at iahidan on the afternoon of the 23rd December 1943. The Right Honourable Anthony den ! .0., , His Majesty’s principal ecretary of itate for Foreign Aifairs, Foreign Office, Youx‘ most obedient, humble Servant, (BOD) A. HOLMAN. For His Majesty’s Minister ONDOM 1.zo Specimen Signature and Seal of Lieut-Colonei D.B. tuith,. His Britannic Majesty* s Consul&gt; Zahid&amp;n. ? jo His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Zahidan. British Consulate, Zahidan. Dated, the 23rd December, 1943 Certified tnat the above are the true signature and seal of His Britannic Majesty*s Consul, i,ahidaiu His Britans i «s Consul-Gene a san* British Consu3.ate-General, Meshed* Da lied* tlie i •No. 711. BRXTI3E XBIUTKIt, ' was 4F- 20th AUi;Uf?t, 194 i. . £-. 7, V © Hi3Maj08ty T B Legation presents its compliaEnts O A to the Imperial Ministry of Foreign A f ir s J 'a nd w'it'h reference to the Ministry’s memorandum Ko.16022/1837 of the 24th August* 1942, has the honour to stite that Csptain Derek Ha dare 11 Harrison has assumed the duties of British Tice-Consul at Zahidan, as from the 17 th t/uly, 1943* in the place of Mr. 7).J. TT-shon* who has been transferred to another post outside Iran. 2. His Majesty’s Legation has the honour to enclose Letter 0 * Appointment in the usual form with the request that a Letter of Recognition may be issued by the Imperial authorities. / 1 Go pies to: F.O. Ko.. r7 &gt;44 Govt, of India Ho.147 Meshed Ho. 12 Zahidan Ho .3.BRITISH LESAtriC%- (757/8/43) Yt&gt; Sir, With reference to your deapatoh Ko.199 (&amp; 9273/909/234) of the 4th Sentember, 1942, I have the honour to return herewith Vr. Upehon’s certificate of apnointraent. He relinquished his oost as Vice-Consul at 2ahi dan on the 17th June,1943 I have the honour to be, With the highest respect. Sir, Your most obeuieat, humble Servant, (sga. ) H.’*/. BULLAKT? • The Hight Honourable Anthony Eden, Foreign Office.01 hi y i: JlL ^•'.0 INYJARD TEUiGRAM 33600 943 i &amp; f a - (' 10 . OOMPIOKOTIAIi OODB TELEGRAM 3o Al lotted to External Dep artment, Fr ora Government of Indiat Kxternal Affairs Department. To Tehran- Repeated to Meshed and Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 22.25 hours, 28th August, 1945, Received 06.45 hours, 29th August, 1943. '305. Addressed to Tehran repeated to His Majesty’s Consul Meshed telegram No. 259, Secretary of State for India. Government of India propose to post Lieutenant Colonel D.R.Smith at present Political Agent Sibi as Consul Zahidan about the end of November vice Watts required for employment as Political Agent Ghagai. Smith was Vice-Consul Duzdap in 1924-26* If no objection necessary agreement may kindly be obtained.vU A'* / m o r* ; 1 ^ ; - . .i.c '1, &lt;• { V: ... -- /'&lt; ^ Co t ,y of letter No. 7 dated the 4th January 1943 from His Majesty*s Consul General for Xnorasnn, leaned 'the wSecretary to the \ • / _„_ied tojthe w v i | ) Gowrfjjent of, todflaUn ti u - Departmenw 1Xuh the ifixternal Iffairs/ur 1/ I/yC- xon of .^p^of fleer suid V 6CT 1 have uarCerB for the medical &amp;pL, Zahldan. nour t*o invite a referejice to Y- 'T.A. 0 . 0 . ^ I V the correspondence r^en*ing with Government of India, External /^fhiEai^p-rt^ent Memoranda?! 'No.8r'4)-3/42 feWr-GeWher 1942 regarding the creation of a new post of ISsdical Officer and Vice Consul, Zanidii. 2. bfforts vers made before their arrival to accommodaoa Dr. Upsnon and hia family in the Consulate compoutid, ao trie ymsll nou^e in the to?;n occupied by the Assistant burgeon was considered unsuitable. His Majesty’s Consul accordingly arranged shat ine new 1/edical officer ana vice Consul Should occupy the Trade Assist ant* s house and tnat tno Trade As sis tan u siiouid move into kie read Clerk’s querters. dome alterations were nsedeu to make une latter house suitable for trie Trade Assistant end his family and am the maLtei was urgent uio necessary expenditure amountiiK to iiials 4,300 was incurred in antici pation of sanction. 3. Dr. Upshon duly arrived with his wife and Ci^iidran on the 16th September 1942 and took up their residence in the Trade Assistant’s nouse. ITe soon found, uowever, (^) tiiat tne house was in eon venient for a family living in tne European stylo (b) that living in the Consulate area, half a mile from the nearest outskirts of tne tov?n f ho had no chance of building up any._sort of private practice. During ray last viaftlto 3~ft- /943 • ••••••- 2 - / fUa' Zaiudan he discuased the question with hie Majestv^s Conaul ahd iirybeif end a&amp;ia that he preferred uAie A.a oiatant Sur^o.; 1 ?. nouse in the tonn. This house ' is no big^or tii&amp;n tat Trade Absikitant’s , but it is of a more modern type end csn be improved and aaapted for liuropsaii occupalion more cheaply, his I^^ai 33 ^y , s Coneu) now r^'ortfl th^t tihe alterations and additions will cost not more tnaado.OOG or say. a* 4 ’* 9 4. Neither of ~he tso homes available is really suitable for an officer of the rank of 52ediceJ and Vice ConBul f but the only alternative is to build* vuuck at uie piosenc» levil of wages and prices woitld be preij.Ulively e^enaivo,apart frorn the extraxe difficulty whicn would be experienced in obtaining tne xicco--*ary matcirials (other than oricics) and fitting. &amp;i6n, after the &lt;^ar, the question of reouilaiiig the eotire Consulate is taken up afresh, tusjy oi providing &amp; proper n^asc for i*ie Ucdicai Officer aoa vice Consul can br* considered at tne asaae c bime. 'InOie should then be no difficulty in selling ihi house in tne tovaa wicich ia me property of Governaent. 5. in tnese circumstances i reconteiia that as a temporary uieasuie the A&amp; si slant burgeon’s nouse in the town be allotted to the Medical uffleer and Vice Concul ana provision maoe in the Zanidan Consulate Uxdg^t for 1943-44 of Ife. 1500 for its adaptation and repair. Coaimencement of the work will be postponed till 1st m hV \pril 1942 ? as the amount cannot be found by re- aLpropriatiori in the current year. The coat of the alterations to bne Head Clerk’s house mentioned in per a 2, Which ti-ough connected with the housing of the M.O. and ?«C- cannot strictly be debited to it, will be found by re^propriatio/. GR/23/2. FTelegram No.1082. Dated 30th July 1942. From - Britconsul, Meshed. To - Foreign, New Delhi. . ^ , Yourtel egr arn-N-n. 5,512 July 15th. With transfer of headquarters of Medical Officer to Zahidan retention of Assistant Surgeon there not essential. Suggest he would be more^suitably employed in charge Consulate dispensary Meshed in which x case increase of allowance to American Hospital (lids my telegram No.121 March 1942) will not be necessary. 2. For this purpose propose that the post of Assistant Surgeon o&amp;hidan be abolished and new post created at Meshed carrying grade pay plus customs compensation allowance Rs.25 plus skx clothing allowance Rs.2. j 3. For many years Medical Officer here has not Jield Persian license and his practice therefore has been limited to Consul ate-G-eneral staff. Assistant Surgeon whom I propose to transfer here, if present proposal sanctioned, has got license and will be able to treat gratis limited number of destitute patients from outside. Dispensary will thus beccme once more useful political asset. Telegram No.1363, dated 15th September 1942. From - Britconsul, Meshed. To - Foreign, New Delhi. My telegram 1082 July 30th. Meshed Dispensary. Grateful if orders could be issued at an early date as Upshon is expected at Zahidan shortly and Major Rao left this morning. Telegram No.775-E, dated 28th September 1942. From - Foreign, New Delhi, To - Britconsul, Meshed. Your telegram No.1363 September 15th. Proposal to transfer AssistaniTourgeon Zahidan to Meshed approved, on terms suggested.In any further communication 3/ / o on this subject, please quote ■ No. K 11280/909/234. COPY and^^lress— Ca%i no. .0 any person by na^e but to- 'The UndetSI&amp;yieJtary of State,’ reiA Office, 'London, S.W.l. Sir, EX rn Fore Foreign Office. 10th October, 1942. I w r ^ n Tith reference to India Office le t er Ext« 5252/42 of the 2nd Octobers 1 am directed by Mr- Secretary iiden to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India that a letter of appointment was issued to Mr. Donald James Upshon by His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran under date of the 26th July, 1942 and that this has since been confirmed by a certificate of appointment issued by this department. 2. A copy of a despatch from Tehran on the subject is enclosed. REC*. POL. DEPt. IJ OCT i942 INBIA OFFICE I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER L,h '° u m s mw^ 3tate ’ FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT., INDIA OFFICE JC o p y TELEGRAM No.275 of 16/7/42. ■From: NEW DELHI To:' PRODROME TEHRAN. 1 .) 2 .) „/&gt; !&lt;? Addressed to Minister Tehran, repeated to Meshed Ho ,5512 reference his Tel. 'x/ - ^ 2 55 of 88th Ma y. vonr tel.256 of 27th May. 3. of 3. has sanctioned:- Raising of Vice-Consulate Zahidan to Consulate and Removal of Headquarters of medical officer KH0RRA8SAN from uSSHBD to Z A HI PAH, medical officer functioning as ex-officio Vice-Consul ZAHTDAH. 2. Assistant burgeon COKALD iFAM^S UTSHOH I.M.D. will succeed RAO and has been instructed to proceed to ZAHIPAH. Orateful if you will apidy for exequatur. (^. Please telegraph d te on which UPSHOH assumes charge. RAC’s leave will then he sanctioned, after which he will he surrendered -or tenrrorary military duty.) PORBIQH*m HB, Roader trm&amp;ius Bullard, Knight ConaKsndaP of tha Boat Biatlmrolahad Opdap of ^atnt Hlehaal and snint GN*or«a, Cotnpmii«m of tha Haat Sainaat Crdar of vha Indian Hla Britannia Majesty's minister and 53nvoy ixtraopdinary at fahrans BE IT KUTSOf to all By whom thase preaenta shall that, by virtue of tha powers veatad in me by Hla iiajeaty'a CosnlsslOR, I VO HSBBBT ocmatituta and appoint Mr. Ji\K.S8 BP8H0B to be Hla Britannic Majesty's Vloa-Conawl at ’.ahldan with . full power and nnthority, by all lawful means, to aid and protest His Majesty's subjects trading la, visiting, or residing in his rfimas m hsad sad asal of Office at Vohran this Twsntysixth day of July in the Tear Ona thousand Mine Hundred and Fortytwo.rnmmmm Ext.525?A2 ERAST LETTER. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. &lt;2(H x l lG /Az. r 'l&lt;» ^ifAraJp^ of- Sc Ofr m Sir, A 0^ With reference to^Foreign Office letter of the / 3rd July t No.K.75^3/909/234 ( regarding the change in the status of the Consular ^ost at Zahidan, I am directed ty the Secretary of State for India to forward^ for the infomation of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, a co-py of a telegram fr om the Government of India ■form 9 No.7^00 dated 25th September.) ■whj oh it wall ho ooob: that Assistant Surgeon Donald James Upshon, has been appointed Medical Officer for Khorasan and ex officio Vice-Consul, Zahidan, and that he assumed charge on September 18th* A^'fU'YvvLo U/iU 2. Mr. Ameiy m&gt;uld be-glad if, provided Mr. Eden gees Ko'Vo- the requisite steps could be taken- to issue &amp;■- a Comnission to Mr. Upshon as Vice-Consul, Zahidan* (Sgd.) E. W. R. LUMBVWlf h vv i l n v**' COPY 'V* fr For'. K)HKIGN OFFICK, ft •;• 1 P 6i»t Sir, i/UV tE')^ The Kina has boorj graciouaii' pleased to app*&gt;i&lt;rt y ;if -to *t his kajesti* a Consul at zahiden unuer date of the lat July, 1^4‘ke _ rfM Guo ^ ^3^) 7) £• The King’s GOuhuisoion will he sent to His Majesty’s Dlolocaatic Representative at Tehran in order that the Exequatur faay he obtained* The Co^i&amp;ission and Exequatur will be forwarded to you in due course* 3. No salary is attached to this appointment and it will give you no claim on Kis Majesty's Government when your services cease. POL, INDIA J am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, &lt;For the Secretary of otate) Rc e j Lieutenant-Colonel lU?m Vatts. 1file copy on this please quote and address— not to any person by name but to— ‘‘ The Under-Secretary of State,” No. K 7563/909/234. Foreign Office. S.W.l. Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 3rd July,1942 Sir With reference to India Office letter _ EXT-3110/42 of the 23rd June, I am direct ecTJiy f Mr.—5ecT , gTary~¥den to stateT fdF^the information of the Secretary of State for India, that he approves the raising of the status of the consular post at Zahidan to that of Consulate and the transfer of the headquarters of the Medical Officer for the Khorasan Agency from Meshed to Zahidan. 2. A new commission will therefore be issued forthwith to Lieutenant-Colonel Watts, appointing him Kis Majesty's Consul at Zahidan, and a commission as Vice-Consul will also be issued to the Medical Officer concerned as soon as his full title and the date on which he assumes duty at Zahidan are known- 3. The extra expenditure involved will be covered by the decision referred to in India Office letter No. P- 10246/42 of the 21st February last I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant rvant, ^ 1 ' 0 - M’(k The Under-Secretary of State, •' India Office. Jwk/ 2. 2l . • ElTCLOSUKt IN AW MAIL LETTER No. 2 8 11 JUL 1942 FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT,. RECd. POL. DEPt. -4JUL1942 INDIA OFFICE INDIA OFFICE JL-—The Government of I n dia have telegraphed recommending that the Vice Consulate at Zahidan should he raised to a Consulate and that the headquarters of the Liedical Officer for the Khorasan Agency should he moved from Meshed to Zahidan, where he should act as ex officio Vice Consul. The Vice Consulate at Zahidan (Duzdap) was established in 1923 and its continuance was sanctioned annually until 1936, when it was established + on a permanent basis, the cost being shared equally 7Ki fdcJt between Imperial and I n dian revenues. (P.Z. 4799/36 tkcJ-tWe * u h ^ flagged). The present incumbent is Lieutenant-Colonel ” ^ R.P. Watts, an officer on the time scale of the I.P.S. u l * - receiving Rs.1900 per mensem, £30 S.O.P. and allowances amounting to Rs.350 per mensem. Presumably the change in the status of the Zahidan Vice Consulate would not affect his salary or allowances? As regards the Government of India*s second proposal, the Persian Government have in the past objected to a Vice Consul practising as a doctor. In 1939 Mr. G.P. Squire, then Consul General at Meshed, proposed that Major B.M. Rao, I.M.S. , the Mediqai ....... .. Officer at Meshed, shoul d be granted consular status. ^ as Vice Consul, Meshed. /^Sir Horace Seymour, 'then H.M. Minister, Tehran, gave it as his opinion that if t\M. ftorit 1$ S&lt;&gt; SOrucrv CUt\ J UAy\c^(Z fhxJt 'fcL uritl kt the. oJftcAAanu. to fhx »1.0. .* ;• -y- ■ } ■ dicf Kof the doctor did not practise outside the Consulate there could be no grounds for objection on the part , of«the Persian Government, but the question was not pursueajtlP.Z.2S75/39 and P.Z. 3511/ 39 flagged on the file attached). As the present Consul General, Khorasan, and the Minister at Tehran have concurred in the Government of India*s proposal, it may be assumed that they anticipate no difficulty with the Persian Government on this point/ The allowance to the Medical Officer for performing Vice Consular duties would be covered by the decision that H.M.G. and the Government of India may each sanction expenditure on items up to £1,000, and the concurrence of the Treasury is not therefore necessary. The papers referred to in paragraph 1 of the Government of India’s telegram (flagged in attached file at P.Z .4658/ 53) are concerned with the amalgamation of the Meshed Consulate General and the Seistan Consulate as a measure of economy, and are not entirely relevant. tkj 1 s/Xupc,: (vvo|&gt;aVrt| / 'IcuSe^l fke g&amp;vuLxicuf UAh\ l&amp;kA&amp;yi . * Qua ' vt/jjkc p***~st kp CO In view of the increasing importance of Zahidan as the terminus of the railway line from Nok Kundi and its position on the roads to the Indian frontier, particularly that from Meshed, it is proposed that the Government of India’s recommendation should be sanctioned and a draft letter to the Foreign Office is submitted accordingly. M, fhz. Ir\ tu H- aJscAre j ^ tKoJ~ thJL ^ fa. fa 'M&amp;CurJL by V&lt;(jl - QfivxvJk ^ , \jc L ^ ^nofy&lt;r^ol ?KaJ~ ^ LiMiruJ aJ 'Lx^dayry fruAjJiJ Vv\ jjnXuaJZ ftvxJZi .UL. .DRAFT LETTER, The Under Secretary of State, The Foreign Office, S.W. 1. “B3 JUN 1M* No. 4533 dated 10th June. Sir, « I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to forward for the consideration of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs a copy of a telegram from the Government of India recommending that lice. Vice Consulate at Zahidan should EMCLOwUHE IN AIN MAIL LETPPEItaLsed to a Consulate and that the ^ ^ JUL 1942 headq larters of the Medical Officer for the FROM btCRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT ,,1 INDIA OFFICE Khorafean Agency should he moved from Meshed . — p- ~ ^ j a($o It uaU ie crise^LreJ( ikcifS. tS'^^Zahidan where he should act^as ex officio H rfCniylZi &lt;d~ TUaok ) vice Consul. Kaa Cc/Acu/vud u\ uAlk Tr\4A£K 1W I In view off the increasing importance pf Zahidan as a road and railhead^ ivi-r, / Arne ry^- appro veer the Cove rnme n t' YFC£ - CmJtvJoJCL ■of- r:iiggoc tion and, subject to the agreement of Mr. Eden&gt;ould he glad tMt the /requisiteY&lt;a focS . requisite steps sHould tie taken to otto in the ■oonouprehoo-of the Pere-ieen Govornment to thc-^ raising of the sta-tus of the Zahid-an Vioc Consulate. Him ^ 3. It io 'aoouinoci' that the^extra expenditure htuGlIs p^oials ivill -fa. J involvethe allov/ance to the Medical Officer •fcO. CLSSi***i\Q6 y^v-O^ when performing Vice-Consular duties, may he treated 'fe. -^e-/covered hy the decision referred to in 1.0. letter No. P.10248/42 of the 21st February, and that^it will not he considered necessary to obtain the fierimM- sanction of H.M. Treasury. fair*.) r. ps tluA (inTUfidr r* 's v FILE ropy 9 ^ •- Allotted to External D £ G Y P EXT 1 10 , ^ 0/ K . tment* to ‘*1 ^3 n 15255 L £ G R A M From Dated Received Governnient of India, External Affairs Department g to Secretary of Sta^e ion India* New Delhi, 05,05 hours, 10th June, 1942* 12,30 hours, 10th June, 1942. X ,4533* v 1 Addressed to Secretary of State for India No. x 4535 repeated to (1) Tehran No. SIS. . 1QA , Correspondence ending with your telegram Ido* Vw &lt;T dated August 6th 1335 regarding East Persian Consulates, 33 o on the recommendation of Consul General Khofasan and with concurrence of Minister at Tehran v/e propose that * - (1) Vice-Consul ate Zahidan he raisea c,o Consulate and (2) Headquarters of Medical Officer in . Khorasan Agency Tie moved from (omission) to Zanidan {-&gt; Medical Officer) (omission)ing also as ez-o-,-fic..o Vice-Consul. Only extra expense will He allowance to Medical. Officer for performing Vice-~Consuiar duuK.s. 3, Zahidan 1 s increasing importance as rai- : and road-head on important lines of communication leading Doth north and west, in our view tn. „y (? warrant) these proposals ' to which we sho^d he grateful for your sanction hy telegram. RECd, POL. L £J»j ) 2JUM 942 INDIA OFFICEgOPY Qf i 6785 D„E C..Y P HER OF T B L E G R A M. Government of India, Ext. Affrs. Department to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 23.35 hours, 24-th October, 1941. Received 14.46 hours, 25th October, 1941. X I MPORTANT . 5621 . Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 5821 and Minister at Tehran 442. Your telegram 13193* October 20th. Vice~Consulates in Persia. (a) Barlow joined Meshed October 19th but is being temporarily transferred to hold Zahidan while-Watts balds temporary charge of the Consulate-General Meshed pending Skrine^s arrival to replace Squire. (b) Wooller, McConaghey have both left India and should join respective posts within a week. (c) Hodsun has been diverted from Kerman to meet urgent military requirements in India and it is proposed to send another officer to Kerman. Minister at Tehran will be addressed shortly regarding substitute. This telegram went out in XXX cypher.f !% EXTRACT FRCS! 'HE GAZETTE OF CTrERI-IAL AFFAIRS DEPT K0TIFIC1TIQMI No. 179-E. - Tr. II.A.N. Barlow t of the Indian Political Service, is posted as His ^jesty’s Vice-Consul, Zahidan. with effect from tie forenoon of the 25th October 1941.(Jt 14-49/891/234) FILE C—~ \ Sir ■fr ap joint you to bi Hie ilejeety’s Vice-Consul at ^&lt;6 ov Zahidan. Th© lag has been graciously «» mm ♦ /v. Vv 4 '14 ♦ «r J •» \f4 r*t**mi ft t a 1 ii , Vhe I ing’s Commission will be sent to Eib Vs^esty’s Diplomatic. Repre sente tire at Tehran In order that the ixequatur may be obtained* he Comnlsoion and • xecuatur ©111 be forwarded to you in due course. 5* go salary ie attached to this appointment and it will give you no claim on Hi a sty’s Ooremaent In the -ml ted ' ing&amp;m ^our Bervices 4. four attention la called to Chapter V, Section 1, cl the General Coni, i r tSMItructtonOf ••' ycu arc reminded that the obligation of secrecy in regard to your official experiences, and information obtained while a consular officer* continues equa lly after your retirement from active service or your transfer from consular employment to any other service under his Majesty’e Gcvernment. cease I am* Sir* four obedient servant* (For the Secretary of State) hieu te nan t-Co lone 1 R • • © f te » rccd. pol. rr.?T. 1 / JUL 941 INDIA CFFICEINDEXED &gt;&lt; fst. COf,T JL m aLJt * ( * (J 'J ^ ob i / Allotted to PoXiti lttLLJ^ajBLg Cop .lee Oirjcuj^etedl ^ f(7 ^'y,. SECRET 2066 6 4 jl.I.C ,Y p H S R OP T S L B Q R A M. '7 X From Government of India, External Affairs Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, SI.50 hours, 12th February, 1941. Received 10.00 hours, ISth February, 1941. _____ XXX r4, iff. P.l.lVfH' it], nstios (vj. 701. Addressed to Tehran, telegram No.36, repeated ro Secretary of State for India. Your telegram jil, February 10th*Watts ! proposed posting. Grateful n you would apply for agreement. S. As regards proposal to omit Watts 5 rank, am constrained to modify suggestion in para, ho.2 of our tele gram 31, February 4th, as just seen Seymour’s letter 33/2/37 dated January 9th, 1937, to Metcalfe and latter’s reply thereto dated May 17th, 193?, and Seymour’s final reply dated July 29th,. 1937. Objections to'omission of rank remain equally substantial so would suggest that Watts be described as '^t.Col.R.P.Watts, a member of Indian Political Service*'. There is also point that watts has previously served in Iran with military rank. RECo. POL. DEPt. lofEB 941 INDIA OFFICEDEC Y PTnn?—DP E LEG R A M. From Government of India? External Affairs Department? to Secretary to State for India Dated New Delhi? 21.25 hours? 4th Fet.? 1941 « Received 19.00 hours? 5th February? 1941. XXX 566. Addressed to Tehran No.31 repeated to Secretary of State for India. It is proposed to post Lt. Col.R. P. Watts? Indian Political Service? as Vice-Consul at Zalxidan in the beginning of April next Vice Bowen wuose services are required elsewhere. Watts served as Vice-Consul at Ahwaz in 1928 and as Consul (? Bus hire) in 1927^26 and 1934. Trust you have no objection. If you think it desirable? military rank could be omitted in approach to Iranian Govt.? but it is to be remembered that they may have the (? dossier) of officer who has f? previously) served in Iran.any further communication on this subject, please quote No. K b'S^y^^VU-• - y6 m 7 m y-7’ and address —not to any person by name, but to— ^ “The Under-Secretary of State , 5 Foreign Office, London, S.W. i, *&gt;* * &gt;6o0 THE Under-Secretary of State foi \For eitfn^Mfairsj presents his compliments to &gt;CVvt ^ ^AojU ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop/dL/&gt; of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 10-vq, 2 I'M Reference to previous correspondence : o . AjuUDtA. ajo . v\ K'&amp;y'^j u.'s i ^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.V%| - 735 j i3o9 THE communicatlofi here^nth en closed, which has been received at the Foreign Office, but which appears to concern the is transmitted with the compliments of the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Foreign Office,\\W In any further counnunicution on this subject, please quote No. &lt; leijw / sau/ ajw and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for compliments uto JLl** 7/\ o ^ |/VW$ present's^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copi&amp;b of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, XV*»&gt;S *•, 193£ . Reference to previous correspondence : 3.0. Na P.'2, l.03«/' 18 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.f (K 10236/826/234) o/o Folkestone, 30th August, 1938• Mrs. E.K. Martin thanks the Under-Secretary of State for his letter, and wishes to inform him that she has now heard from Mrs. A.L.A. Dredge, that all is well.14 6130 17148(4) \ INDEXED In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. k loaau / sau / aiu., and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. r. / . 6038 V •“v rys com THE Under-Secretary of State for Fore ign ^Qii^Spresey its his pliments to *J*~*&amp;+~* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, v c* transmits herewith copi&amp;S of the under-mentioned paper. A. ^ —At- Foreign Office, ♦O ^ 2s 4 ^3^' • fit Reference to previous correspondence : y Description of Enclosure. ji H. At Name and Date. Subject. ^ ^ . Z. fa- Similar letter sent toCOPY (K 10236/826/234) '^o.K 8891/8891/234. c/o NATIONAL PROVINCIAL BANK LIMITED, FOLKESTONE, 22nd August, 1938. Sir, Will you kindly inform me whether there is any interruption with the mail from Iran. I have not had any mail from my daughter Mrs. A.L.A. Dredge, from Zahidan for 4 weeks, and it is so very unusual for her to miss the mail. I cannot understand it. I am most v/orried, and should be grateful if you can inform me if all is well at the Consulate at Zahidan. Thanking, etc., (SIGNED) EMMA KATE MARTIN. The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.uf imu OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.1* 1* / 26th March, 193B. any thanks for your letter of the 28th February about Captain Hr edge, Vice-Consul at Caliidan. If Mrs* arlin makes any farther representations here we she ll be £ lad to reply to her on the lines you suggest, liothir^;, however, has been heard from her since she wrote to the Foreign Office on the 14th January, and we propose to let the nattd rest until she chooses to raise it again. hen I wrote to you before we haul reason to believe that might expect a call from Mrs. Martin some time, which ms an additional reason for consulting you as to wh&amp;t we should say to her. he 1ms not, however, made any move, and this being the case, it v.ill no doubt be best for us not to take the initiative, though, if we have to see or write to her, we will take the line you surest. (Sgd.) J.G. Walton. 1 / i Sir Fubrsy Metcalfe, , J.3.I., M.V.C., External Affairs Department, Government of India.Conf idential. Personal Letter . The 2%^ February 1938 Hew Delhi. Please refer to your personal and confidential letter of February 16th, 1938 about correspondence with Mrs.E.K* Martin, the mother-in-law of Captain A.L.A. Dredge, Vice- Consul at Zahidan. 2. I would suggest that a reply on the following lines might be sent to Mrs. Martin. Dredge’s appointment in Zahidan is for a limited period only and in any case for not more than two years; other junior married officers of the Political have served in Zahidan with their wives; and it is regretted that the exigencies of the service preclude Dredge’s transfer merely on the ground that he is married. ¥e already have, as you know, sufficient posting complica tions and we cannot afford to give the impression that outside interference of this kind will influence our arrangements. I 3. We should have been glad to give Campbell a short further extension in Zahidan. The military authorities, however, were not prepared to spare him on these terms arid would only agree to an extension which would carry him /2 him to the date of his retirement. V/e did not feel justified in taking him on these terms since he was of use to us only as Vice Consul, Zahidan and we did not wish to place ourselves in a position which might entail having to give him employment elsewhere. To J.C. Walton, Esquire, C-B. [alton, Esquire, C.B., M.C., Under Secretary, Political Department, India Office.\ ^•y* :'&lt;y f ( ' l?X '/48/S34) vbnziQ’’ 'ivfio:., . 1 . 15tii February, 193?! The King hm been grnelo isly pleaded to appoint you to be His Majesty's Vice-Consul at gahidan with effect from the 17th November, 1937. 8 . The King 9 s Commission will be sent to Hie Majesty’s Diplomatic Representative at Tehran in order that the Exequatur may be obtained. The Commission and Exequatur will be forwarded to you In due course. 3. No salary ie attached to this appointment and it will give you no claim on Hie Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom when your services cease. 4. Your attention is called to Chapter V # Section 1, of the General Consular Instructions, and you are r&lt;minded , that the obligation of secrecy in regard to your official experiences, nnd information obtained while a consular officer, continues equally after your retirement from active service or your transfer from consular employment to any other service under His Majesty’s Government. Captain ’ • T„ T )redge.IN-31A CFFICi., person: ! ; na ■Jonfideiitial 16th February, 1953 U Under cover of India Office weekly letter • o* 5 of the 3rd February we sent you, as an enclosure to i orei.qn Office letter No, K 826/826/234 of the 29th January, a copy of a letter from Mrr. U,K. srtin, the mother-in-law of Captain u.L.ii. dredge, tiie ice-Consul at ^ahidan. Lxs. * artin’s letter has not yet had a reply beyond the acknowledgment from the Lorei^xi Office, but perhaps it calls for a reply, as it asks a specific question about the probable duration of the appointment, it is rather a puzie, however, to know how to rcoly to a letter of this kind from an officer's mother-in-law, Chat do you advise? ;e have recently had a visit from Major Campbell, who preceded Dredge at Zahiden, and as his name is mentioned by ixs. Martin e took the opportunity of mentioning the matter to him, particularly as he saw something of Dredge and his wife before leaving the &gt;ost. For/ oir Mibrey . etcalfe, ,0,1.h., .1. Government of India, External affairs Department.For what they are worth I a end you his vie ,,T s. 1 e is inclined to agree with the statement in i rs. Martin’s letter that her daughter is living under great nervous strain, and he thinks that this has not been lessened by her knowledge of the incident which took place at the Vice-Consulate on the night of the 30th/31st .august (see the papers enclosed with Uie memorandum No. 221 ( /5) dated 6th September, 1937, from the ^onsul- General at ii eshed to the Government of India). Campbell also thought that dredge himself was suffering from nerves and appeared to be in a highly-strung condition. Incidentally, Cimobell said he would himself like to go back to Zahidan provided he was given the post for four years, which would take him up to the age for retirement. Vf ^ / (Sgd.) J.C. Walton.r v •• »w 4 « -i. COPY. (K 826/886/234) (K^89X/8891/234 ) (18th Aug./S?) Priv&amp;te and Confidential. C: P O L’ w d. ' Q-'O * W •wr' V,.&gt; BERKELEY COURT HOTEL, 29-31, LEINSTER GARDENS, LANCASTER GATE, HYDE PARK, W.2. 14th January, 1938. Sir, Is it possible for you to inform me for about how long duration Captain Dredge's appointment as His Majesty's Vice-Consul at Zahidan is likely to be, as I have now met Major Campbell, and it seems to me that Zahidan is a most impossible place for my daughter to live, and I feel very anxious about her remaining in good health. I understand she can never go outside the building, as it is so isolated in the desert, therefore she will never have any healthy exercise. Apart from that she must be living under a great nervous strain, as she does not speak the native languages and there are no Europeans to whom she could speak French or English. I fully realise she has married a man who has no alternative but to obey orders, and serve where he is sent to do so, and who very naturally wants his wife beside him, but the fact remains that she is still ray daughter, and I am not prepared to see her life sacrificed unnecessarily. I feel Zahidan is absolutely and without doubt unsuitable for a young married woman. There must be older married people, or bachelors in the service that were more suitable for such a lonely station. I consider either your officers should not be allowed to marry, or their wife should have the consideration that is due to a British white woman. The present arrangement is disgraceful, and appalling and anything which happens to my daughter I shall hold you responsible for entirely. The Under-Secretary of State, (Signed) EMMA KATE MARTIN. Foreign Q^f^ice, \ o* /FILE QOPY f I — . M x L jgs/aw. (44 words) 4954. *5 DECODE OF TiDLiiiGRAM . Prom Government of India, External Affaire Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Hew Delhi, 9th November, 1937, Received 9th November, 1937, 12.15 p*m.. 395--E v Express letter from Exter: Affairs Department, D-879-E(P)-37. August 19th. Campbell v s tenure of appointment as vice t Consul, Zahidan. Would be grateful for very early reply as Campbell is being relieved on 15th November and must maice his arrangements at once. 9 NOVl 93 ?i INDIA OFFICE5973 5000 3.37 'V ^ Draft Paper. political Department. 7 DRAFT • ^ Capt. A. L. A. Dr edge , Dryad’s Garth, Teignmouth, Devon. LETTER. Personal. 2Z.^. I'J Dear Dredge, Many thanks for your letter of the 15th September. Yes, do look in on the 18th October, or any day that week. I should not, of course, trouble you to come up specially, and I shall be back from leave by then. There is one matter I wanted to mention, which would hardly wait till then heard.. e^iooiy the other day that you had been ill in India before you came home on leavej^^ there is any question w&gt; r's to your fitness we could of course fix yo u up a M e dical Board here.^ /Rsturally^ o be in good health before going to East Persia^/But perhaps you have had a good long leave and are perfectly fit now. A A ; ArcIMDIA OFFICE, f 10th Septembers 1937 Dear Drecige» I see that you have been i&gt;oated to Xahidan and will be going out there this Autumn. As we have to deal with that part of the world in this Department and like to keep in personal touch, so far as possible, with people who are there, I shall be very glad if you could find it convenient at any time that you are in London to look in and see ua. It would be an advantage if you would be so kind as to let me know beforehand if and when you are able to do so* Captain A*L.A. Dredge, Indian Political Service, C/o The High Commissioner for India, India House, Aldwych, T '.C*3.1 In any further communi''ation on this subject, please quote v no. K *?//* 3 ¥ and address— not to any person by name, but to— s “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign OTice, London, S.W.t r I&gt; /; p 4 o 7 vj H- U / i a '/ THE Under-Secrefcary of State forEoYSt^n’Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop/fis of the under-mentioned papers - . Foreign Office, pf p. -^v Reference to previous correspondence : 3 | Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. —Copy 87 (K 8891/8891/234) .Private and Confidential I.f.4766/37. ESRKCI^Y C-'UP7 HOTEL 29-31, LEINSTER CAP DENS, LANCASTER GATE. HYD 17 PARK, V/.2. 22nd July, 1937 Dear Sir, I understand that Captain A*L*A. Dredge, has recently 'been selected for the post of Vice-Consul at Zahidan in East Iran. I should be most grateful if you will give me the following information about the conditions in Iran* I am into rested as Captain Dredge married my daughter on the 3rd June, and I understand the marriage is recognised by the Political Service. with my daughter I understood his appointment would be in India. plague, cholera and typhoid, as stated in the Pa oport regulations? She was inoculated against smallpox before her marriage, as I thought it wise even xor India. health, through inoculation so soon after marriage and to have to resign from married life. When I consented to the marriage of Captain Dredge Is it necessary for her to be inoculated against I naturally do not want my daughter to lose her Is there likely to be a white medical officer on this station? or any other white women? Is it correct that the only means of transport is Secretary, Indian Political Service, Foreign Office, London*,by caravan? also what leave is Captain Dredge likely to have from his duties? so that he could see his wife occasionally if its thought not wise for her to accompany him to Zahidan. Thanking you in advance. Yours faithfully, (Signed) Emma Kate Martin*COPY. (K 9482/8891/254) K 8891/8891/254 Private and Uonf'id.eriti&amp;l • Berkeley Court Hotel, Leinster Gardens, Hyde Park, London, W.2. 7th August, 1957. Sir, Captain A.L.A. Dredge’s demeanour is so peculiar that I am writing to ask if his health can he investigated He tells me he had a severe attack of malaria, and &lt;-l_^ o- sunstroke before leaving India last year, possibly it is that which is affecting him* I should he most grateful if the matter could have attention very soon. Yours faithfully, (Sd) Emma Kate Martin. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.K 0B91/3B91/334 &lt;■ n? io , IBth Au^rust, 1937 Mad#a» 1th r^f^r^ne^ to 3 fow lotto e of the July mnd 7th *ugu8t regarding Captain Itrodge^a appointment as t&gt;l 8 Majesty 9 a Mloo-conaul at Zahidfm* •' om directed by Viscount Halifax to inform you that th«re arc undaretood to be few if any European women at ahidan and that there ie no our ope on medical officer there. -t wo&gt;ao be sb veil for your daughter to be inooulated before going to Iran. The Journey to ahidaa maet V- maf f -y • ’nd» s. X am to suggest that you ehould consult the ’.ndia Office regarding Oeptoin bredge’e state of health and the amount of leave to whieh he will be entitled. X am. Your obedient ^rvent. Mrct* *K# Martin* Berkeley Court ■ Leinster Cmr Hyde lark. (So.) G 0 ALi CHIN,1 1 &amp; &amp; GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department. h p 4- b EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.—r*M wan ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of tommunieation more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended *° b* * on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to oovia formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.) No. D.879-S(P)/37. Dated Simla the / *7 A - August 293 7. To ‘in-yj i The Secretary of State for India, London. (Repeated .British Minister, Tehran and Consul General, Khorasan*) ff' ■yto. Correspondence resting with your telegram 3698 , December 26th 1936. Campbell's appointment as Vice-Consul, Zahidan. As Captain A. L. A. Dredge, whom it has been decided to send to Zahidan, will not be available till middle of November and as Campbell has applied for four months leave on average pay earned in civil employ, it is proposed to extend the tenure of his appointment as Vice-Consul, Zahidan, till middle Oi Ms.r..■ 1938 when he will have completed his leave. / Would be grateful for sanction by telegram. ••••••••••• Th© issu© of th© above has been authorised* Under Secretary to the Government of India. «£Co. Wm DEPtH STfaQBJSSTi ^.A OFFICE (Signature) S. 44, MFP—287 Si (Designation)DS/XiiP words) TELEGRAM 09408. FROM Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and political Depto TO High Commissioner for India, London* DATED Simla 19th July 1937o RECEIVED 20th JUly 1937 G 10 aofflo Via Imperial Cable f CoDoB^ 195B. PLEASE INFORM FALCONER AND DREDGE INDIAN POLITICAL SERVICE THAT ON EXPIRATION OF THEIR PRESENT LEAVE THEY WILL BE POSTED AS CONSOL AT KERMAN AND VICE-CONSUL AT ZAHIDAN RESPECTIVELY. FALCONER SHOULD CORRESPOND DIRECT WITH LINCOLN PRESENT CONSOL AT KERMAN AND DREDGE WITH CAMPBELL PRESENT VICE CONSUL AT ZAHIDAN FOR FURTHER DETAILS*10 IT/AW, (30 groups) 3479* D E C Y P K EH OF TELEGRAM Prom Government of India, External Affairs Department, to Khorasan and repeated by the former to (COPIES Secretary of State for India* CIRCULATED) Dated Simla, 20th Ju3y p 1937* Received 19th July* 1937 s 10,40 p G m* 1614 Addressed to Khorasan repeated to Secretary of State for India, My telegram 1500 s June 29tho Minister at Tehran has agreed to Dredge-e posting as Vice-Consul., Zahidan, vice Campbell* Dredge is being informed of hie posting and instructed to correspond direct with Campbell for further details* 2 0JUL1937. INSJ,. vrFICE(j) CLo^^ JHI/AWo (36 groups) 3193 ft Ar/ DECYPHEK OE TELEGRAM , From Government of India, External Affairs Department, to His Majesty's Representative, Tehran, and repeated hy former to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla, 29th June, 193? c Received 29th June, 1937, 2 p 0 m ft Addressed to His Majesty's Representative, Tehran, 26, repeated to Secretary of State and Meshed* It is proposed to send Captain AoL*A*Dredge, a fully trained officer of the Indian Political Service, as Vice Consul at Zahidan in the beginning of November next, vice Campbell, whose services are required by the military authorities* Presume you have no objection*any further communication on this subject, please quote No - K 139S9/650/234. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. n-h i Fokeign Office. S.W.l. 23rd December, 1936. Sir, With reference to India Office letter P.Z.8810/36 of the 16th December, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to state, for the information of Lord Zetland, that he has no objection to the retention of Captain J. Campbell, R.I.A.S.C., as His Majesty’s Vice-Consul at Zahidan until the 30th June, 1937. I am, Sir, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.THK/DIA. (48 groups) 5636* D BCYPHER OP TELEGRA M« From Government of India, Foreign and From Political Department, to Secretary of State for Dated New Delhi, 10th Decemb 294-1« Addressed to Secretary of State for India 2941, repeated to Consul-General, Khorasan, Minister at Tehran, 78. Our telegram 11 0-1317 , May 20th, i- 1935o Camphell ? s appointment as Vice-Consul at Zahidan* As Squire has ^ust taken over charge in Khorasan, and as no suitable Political Officer is immediately available, it is proposed to retain Campbell in Zahidan till June 30th P 1937o Would be grateful for sanction by telegram. --LJS/DlA, 1/ 2 r m (COPfES CIf€ULAmO D £ C .Y P H E H 0 P O..^ Prom Government of India. Foreign ^ Pclitical Bepartmant . to Hl« MajestyL.i;: 4 st#r at Tab ran and repeated t-y fo me ■ to Secretary of State for India, wd Sisal a. 20th Uses He&lt;&gt;4,*lved 20tb iviay ; ;.! *tzi 10*20 o m&lt;. 4Xt x 131,T* Addressed to Tehran* (? h9) s sent to Secretary of State for India arid Consul-General* Meshedo Owing to shortage of political officers it is proposed to send Captain J* Campbell* IoAoS«C* s to Zahidan as Vice-Consul* in June* vice Rivett^Carnac proceeding on leave c Campbell served with South Persian Rifles for a year in 1921 and was on language duty for a year* during which period he worked in Ispahan Consulate UfeXisralo He has passed first class interpretership in Persiano Trust you will agree to his posting as ViceKJonsul at Zahidam4' In any furtljer communication on thi* subject, please quote h'2/74//i/234 and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,' Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign 1 j compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop/C^ of the under-mentioned paper. Vlo^cX, 1933 . Reference to previous correspondence Alo. P Z. fee2fo/32 , sf lUrV.ll* i(j32 . Description of Enclosure Subject. ft .IK. lA/CeFILE COPY IJS/DHo ( 36 groups) D SC Y..P 1 JLi J JJLUL 6207, From (OOPISS CIRCULATED) Government of India j Foreign and Political Department 5 Xo Secretary of State for India,, repeating telegram to Teheran. u Dated Heceived 2515. New Delhi ? 11th November v 1952. 1,45 11th November, 1932. Addressed to Tehran 56-1% repeated Seistan and Secretary of State. On the grounds of health Pinhey requires a transfer from Buzdap® He will be required ior appointment aa Assistant Coianissioner, Ajmerj probably in February. It is proposed to replace him by Galloway who will be asked to curtail hie lee.vo if necessaiy. In view of Galloway's services as Vice-Consul at Ahwas f trust you will agree to his posting as Vice-Consul at Zahidan. Please telegraph reply.' ) ETP/MM (22 worde) 5959 DECODE -Q.J’ 3L-E...L,g-S-B-jUU- (COPJES From CIRCULATED) Government of India, Foreign a Political Department, to Secretary of Gtate for indiat Dated New Delhi, 29th October, 1932 Received 1.45 p.m. 29th October, 1932. ^ his child, 27th October, and desirea leave for one month to take wife India. Subject to concurrence of Minister, Teheran, leave being sanctioned. Beausang carrying on at Zahidan during the absence of Pinhey, Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Minister, Teheran. 10 &amp;8.-E. Pinhey, Vice Consul at Zahidan, lost 2 l ^ / A 7^^ ^^^ 7 )t&gt;'D-XED In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. ^ //'frfr Ilia and address —not to any person by name, but to— The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W i. \ V z o -&lt; 1 d) J I THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his for foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ( and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copix^ of the undermentioned paper. (jx Foreign Office, 0-1^^ C ItfCU t 1932 3' Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ^Z/2- Subject. \ v Z//6 OxA' C J 'enclosure in 'weekly letter no. 216 . 21 APR. 1932 from secretary, politic^ a no SECRET SEPT. INDIA OFFICE Similar-tetier-sent ta•v l March 16th. 1932 Sir I have the honour to inform you that Captain L.A.G. Pinhey took up his duties at Zaheaan on November 15th. last, and not on November 18th as reported in my telegram No. 253 of November 22nd last. I beg to express my regrets for this error which was due to the telegram from His Majesty's Consul at Zabul being mutilated in transmission. I have the honour to be with the highest respect 9 Sir Your most obedient Humble Servant 9 (In the absence of His Majesty’s Minister) (Signed) Charles Dodd The Hight Honourable Sir John Simon G.C.S.Io, etc., etc., etc. The Foreign OfficeNo 528 British Legation, Tehran, 23rd September, 19 31* Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of appointment of Captain Pinhey as Hie Majesty's Vice-Consul at Zahedan (Du*dap)• His His Majesty’s Reference:— Tehran despatch Ho. 527 of 23rd September, 1931 • Prom the Director-General of the Persian Ministry for Foreign Affairs, ■o. 16244/710X2330 dated 21et September, 1931.Copy in translation of a note from the Director-General of the Ministry for Fpreign jiffair» addressed to His Majesty^ Charge a*Affaires, Tehran. Ho. 16244/71012310 dated Shahrivar 29, 1310 (Sept 21, 1931). Monsieur le Charge d*Affaires, In reply to your note of Murdad 9th last (August 1st 1931) Ho. 361, regarding the termination of service of Mr. (Captain l.H. ) Castrell, the British Vice-Consul at Zahedan and introduction of Mr. (Captain L.A.G.) Binhey in succession to the former in the same capacity, I hare the honour to state that the appointment of the latter person is agreed to and he has been introduced to the local officials pending the receipt of the Commission of appointment which is necessary for the issue of the usual exequatur. I avail etc., (Signed) Hassan All Ghaffari.FOREIGN OFFICE. Telephone: ^ Victoria 8540. Telegr^iphic Address ; “ Trlpasof. Parr., London.” Please quote Reference....(^..??^./..Q^* Passport Office, l r ’ Queen Ante’s Gate Buildings, ^ | Dartmouth Street, Westminster, .,_.v J London, S.W. 1. 9th Octoher, 1931. 1 9 URGBI'^T. Sir, With reference to your letter P.Z.6419/31 of today T s date addressed to the Foreign Office, I heg to inform you that if the passports of Captain Pinhey and his wife are forwarded to this Office, application will he made to the Persian Legation for the grant of diplomatic visas. The Under Secretary of Political Department, India Off ice.S.W.1.P e Z. 6382/31. CYPHER TELEGRAM PROM SECRETARY OP STATE TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, DATED 7th OCTOBER, 1931. X (NOoOf words: 12). IMPORTANT. 2943 0 Foreign &amp; Political Departmento Please telegraph urgently whether Pinhey’s posting to Duzdap is confirmed. He leaves England 14th October©Persorial. foreign and Political Department, Simla, The July 1931. Subject to any changes v»hich may have to he made between now and October, it has been decided to post you as Vice-Consul,Duzdap, on your return Prom leave in the autumn. £ou will receive official intimation through the High Commissioner in due course Captain L.A.G.Pinhey, 7 T/ilborne Orove, the Boltons London, S.T.10.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000089_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3575</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000089</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3575</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/18 'Duzdap and Zahidan: vice consul and consul; appointments'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-20T22:02:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (133 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 134; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns appointments at the British Vice-Consulate at Duzdap (Zahedan), which became a Consulate in 1942. The file contains internal correspondence about and with subjects appointed. The correspondence regards suitability of the candidates, terms of employment, discussions on pay and starting dates.The file covers:appointment of L A G Pinhey as Vice-Consul, in 1931appointment of Arnold Crawshaw Galloway as Vice-Consul, in 1932temporary appointment of J Campbell as Vice-Consul, in 1935enquiries on the prospective Vice-Consul, A L A Dredge's health, in 1937, and his appointment in 1938appointment of H A N Barlow, followed by R P Watts as Vice-Consul, in 1941appointment of Donald James Upshon as Consul, in 1942appointment of D H Harrison as Vice-Consul, in 1943appointment of Daniel Richard Smith as Consul, in 1944superior post state and special pay granted to the post of Consul, in 1945appointments of Consuls, between 1945 and 1946.The file is composed of correspondence between the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, the British Legation at Tehran, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and Ernest Hyatt Ltd.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><subject><topic>British</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Conditions of employment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Recruitment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000089#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>