<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023876399.0x00000c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:32:13.884Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SHEET NO. 5. TABXjE OF THE , mashari branch OF THE AL SA'UD ruling family OF SOUTHERN NAJD. , # (For the connection of this branch with the other branches of the family, for a chronological list of Amirs, and for notes, see Sheet No. 1.) Mashari. (Dead.) Muhammad (Boris, 1887.) (Dead.) Ibrahim. (Dead.) Mashari. (Dead.) ATbdul Muhsin. (Dead.) 'Ahdnr Rahman. (Dead.) Ibrahim. (Dead.) J Muhammad. (Dead.) Mashari. (Dead.) Hasan. (Dead.) Muhammad. (Died, 1875; no issue.) J] 'Abdul Muhsin. (Born, 1876.) Fahad- (Killed in tkft battle of 'Anaizah, 1904; no issue.) UJ** Maqran (Dead.) Muhammad. (Dead without issue.) Mashari. 'Dead without issue.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023876399.0x00000c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/C91/3, f 18</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023876399.0x00000c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/C91/3, f 18</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Pocket No. 13: Enclosure to Part III of Volume I of the Persian Gulf Gazetteer: Genealogical Table of the (Wahhābi) Āl Sa’ūd (’Anizah) Family of Southern Najd (Sheets Nos. 4 and 5.)' [Sheet No. 5]</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-11-04T02:02:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 folio</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This item is a genealogical table, 'Sheet No. 5. Table of the Mashāri Branch of the Āl Sa’ūd Ruling Family of Southern Najd'. It contains 17 named individuals (in Arabic and English) of the Āl Sa‘ūd family of the ‘Anizah tribe descended from Sa‘ūd bin Muḥammad through his son Mashārī, some appearing with birth and death dates, as well as biographical information. For the connection of this branch with the other branches of the family, as well as chronology of the Wahhabi Amirs of Southern Najd and notes on the arrangements and compilation of this table, see 'Sheet No. 1' (folio 14).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023876399.0x00000c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>