<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001de_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-05T12:59:16.576Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">P.Z.3013/39 Confidential. The Residency, Bushire, the 3rd May, 1939. D.O. No.436-5. My dear Peel, Could you please refer to your letter No.P.Z.1978/ 39, dated the 5th April 1939, with enclosure, on the subject of Persians in Kuwait. 2. (a) With regard to strength of alleged pro-Iraqi feeling in Kuwait please see paragraph 4 of my letter No.244-S, dated the 24th March 1939. (b) Alleged employment by Shaikh of Persian police. This is entirely untrue. There are no Persians, so de Gaury informs me, in the Kuwait police, nor does the Shaikh encourage the immigration of Persians in orde^ to enable him to control his own people. In regard to the general oosition of Persians in Kuwait please see correspondence ending with my letter No.50-S, dated the 12th January 1939, to Peterson (copy to the India Office and the Government of India under Printed Letter No.51-S of same date). (c) How can we carry out our obligations to protect Kuwait if force is used by Iraq? Please see correspondence ending with my telegram No.268, dated the 27th April 1939. * I am sending a copy of your letter under reference, with enclosure, and of this letter to Metcalfe and de Gaury. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) T.C. jj’owle. * R.T. Peel, Esq., M.C., India Office, London. * sent under printed Letter No.437-S of the 3rd May, 19.EXTRACT from Kuwait Intelligence Surnrpary No. 7, dated 15th April, 19o9. 53. LOCAL INTERESTS. Kuwait Oil Company. Following is synopsis of staff and labour employed by the Kuwait Oil Company: British 11 American 2 British Indian 38 Portuguese Indian 5 Kuwaitis 157 British Protected Person. 1 (Kalat State) Enquiry into the origin of these people reveals the fact that nineteen of them had 'Persian' great grand-fathers and that this number stands just about the same ratio as does the ratio of persons of Persian origin in the populations of Kuwait and perhaps below that of Southern Iraq and the head of the Gulf generally. In Iraq the populations of Nejif, Kerbala and Kadhimian and Basra are popularly, and probably rightly, supposed to have a large percentage, over 50%, of persons of Persian origin. The population of al Qatif, and some of the settlements nearby, in Saudi Arabia are said to be largely Persian in origin. On the other hand there are large numbers of 'Arabs' in Iran, both on the Gulf Coast and in Arabistan and inland, there are whole 'Arab' tribal confiderations between Shiraz and Bandar Abbas. In point of fact, Kuwait is well known in the Middle East as an ' Arab (Nejdi)' town with a strikingly 'pure Arab' and 'unspoilt' appearance and population. In this, it is almost, if not quite, unique, as there are no bigger towns than Kuwait in Arabia, and the Hejaz towns population is much more mixed than that of Kuwait. The only town in Iraq which in any way resembles Kuwait is Zobeir, opposite the Kuwait frontier, where many of the population are Nejdi Arabs by origin. KUWAIT POLICE . It has been reiterated in the Iraqi Press that the Shaikh of Kuwait employs Persian Police, with the alleged intention of cowing the Arabs of Kuwait. Enquiry reveals that/r~\ @ CD 2 . that not a single man or even remote Persian origin is employed in the Police, or, for that matter, among the ^ody Guards and 'Fidawiya'. Until the late ^utassarif of Basra, Tahsin Ali, mentioned it in July 1938 to the Political Agent, a 'Persian prohlem' in Kuwait had not 'been heard of hy the Agency. In any case emigration and settlement of Iranians in Kuwait has long been forbidden by the local authorities, and the present Kuwaitis of distant Persian origin, if they were to leave Kuwait would disturb the life of the ’'Arab” community to which they now belong, and of which they are a part. ■i:&gt;j ♦ 0, i.^0 ♦ 370-3« Bushire, the 20th April, 1939. My dear leel, Could you please refer to correspondence ending with my Printed Letter Ko.358-S, dated the 18th April 1939, on the subject of the seizure of the Shaikh of Kuwait’s Fao estate by the Mudir of Fao. 2. In two recent communications de Gaury has given the following information: (a) The fellaheen put in by the Mudir, in place of the K Shaikh's evicted tenents, are partly bad characters previously turned out by the Shaikh and partly Persians from across the frontier whom the Shaikh in the past was careful to release gradually in order to avoid criticism. (b) The Mutassarif of Basrah, in a conversation which he had with the Shaikh's son, stated that the attachment of the estate was so far an attachment more 'in name' than in fact, and that if the Shaikh would deal with him instead of with the British he could arrange for a Bill to be passed in the new Iraqi Parliament with the object of remitting payment of the taxes due from the Shaikh. The Mutassarif went on to warn the Shaikh through his son of the unwisdom of trying to settle his affairs through the British. 3. (l) MLth regard to (a). In view of the fuss made by the Iraqi Government of the employment of Persians by the Shaikh, / the R. T. Peel ^squire, -^.C., The India Office, London.6 ) ! 2 - the choice of Persians by the local Iraqi authorities is of some interest. (2).(b) is interesting as another indication, of which of course we have had several lately, of the definite policy of the Iraqi Government to undermine our position at Kuwait. It may indeed have been mainly with this object and not with that of recovering revenue that the seizure of the estate was made. I am sending copies* of this letter to Metcalfe, Rouston-Boswall and de Gaury. Yours Sincerely (Sd.) I. C. Fowle sent under Printed letter Mo.371-S of 20th April, 1939.P.Z. 1536/39. Enclosure in covering note from Foreign Office No. E.1794/66/91, dated 10th March, 1939- From IRAQ. Decypher. Sir M. Peterson (Bagdad), 8 th March, 1939- D. 12.15 p.m. 9th March, 1939* R. 12.30 p.m. 9th March, 1939* No. 62. My telegram No. 58 . As I anticipated King Ghazi this morning entirely collapsed as soon as I mentioned Koweit. His Majesty’s rather incoherent explanations were to the effect that he had no intention of attacking Koweit but wished only to egg on its ruler to concede liberal institutions. I asked whether His Majesty really imagined that Iraq, could offer herself as an example at present time: I had repeatedly warned him of impropriety of using his private transmitter set for propaganda of any kind and abuse was aggravated when as in this question propaganda was of nature to cause us annoyance if not embarrassment. I went on to insist that His Majesty should disclose his real reason for sponsoring these attacks. King Ghazi said that foreign influence(?s) to which his broadcast had referred were Persia and that he and his government were seriously concerned over influx of Persians into Koweit which they regarded as endangering Iraq’s communications with us in the event of war. I replied that we could be trusted to look after that ourselves: I added that while his last government had shown/shown some interest in this question and while I had obtained some information on the subject to communicate to them (your telegram No. 3 Saving) present government had shown no interest in subject whatever and I had not tnerefore communicated the information. His Majesty must surely realise that matters of tnis kind were better handled through diplomatic channels than in unfortunate manner which he had chosen. King professed great regret and made fullest promises of amendment. Needless to say none of these is of any value whatsoever. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 62, repeated to Jedda No. 12 and Bushire No. 14«CONFIDENTIAL. No. a/75 vv*VV FI ilk c 6 py I'lB The Hon’ble the Poli compliments to ical jl^s^^t in ; the Persian Gulf presents his Till'll I I ■ i ** \ 1. R.T# Peel, Require, M.C. The India office, London. 2. sir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.C.I.E., G.3.I.,M.V.O., Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department, .New Delhi • and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. lamp Bahrain. Dated... 17.th..Pe.b.3CM^. .19.59 Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter ^o.5l-S of 12/1/39. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Bagdad letter Bo. 111/5/39 of the 24th January 1939. Subject. Iraqi interest in Persians in Kuwait.(JO) J (111/5/39) British £anbasey 1186 j 24 th January 1939 .Bagdad* J My dear tfowle, Thank you for your letter -flo.D.0.50-8 of 12th January concerning the enquiries made by the Government on the subject of the lerslana in Kuwait. The new government, formed by Miri Pasha on December 25th last, have not so far raised this question and as they have a great deal to occupy them they may not do so. in any case the foreign Office have told me to defer replying to these enquiries until l receive further instructions. I shall inform you in due course of future developments. lours sincerely, 3d.Maurice Peterson The Hobble Sir Trenchard *owle, K.G.I.E.,C.B.E., Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire •&gt; . FILE COPY NO DISTRIBUTION. Telegram (en clair) from Sir k. Peterson (Bagdad). D. 9th February, 1939. R. 20th February, 1959. No. 15. (Saving). BY BAG. 4 , Your telegram No^ 5 Saving. / New gove rnment have so far shown no interest in matter and I do not propose to communicate information unless and until they do. Paragraph 5. There is a slight misunderstanding. Reference to my despatch of October 20th to Bushire (see my despatch No. 561 of 1938) will show that questions were drawn up by me and not specifically framed by the Iraqis. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 15 Saving, repeated to Resident, Bushire No. 1 Saving by bag.CONFIDENTIAL. No&gt; 51-s of 1939. V 851 ' j I939 ty- (U 6 Xu. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to J 1. Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, KCIE. ,CSI. ,MVO., Secretary to the Government of India, H V 2. R.T.Peel Saquire, MC., The liidia Office, London, 4 Internal Affairs Department, New Delhi. and has the honour to trans ment im a copy of the undermentioned docu- British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.... A?t hi # January . 1939 Reference to previous correspondence : o 1. Residency Printed letter No.621-S of.23rd November 1938. =^To 2. Political Residents letter No.620-S of 23rd Description of Enclosure, November 1938. Name and Date. Letter No.50-3 of the 12th January 1939 to His Majesty’s Ambassador, Bagdad. Subject. Iraqi enquiry with regard to the Iranian population of Kuwait • h* 1;onf ld€ntl*l In oont Inuftt i on of ray letter )fo«&amp;20*3 of tde 23rd laaniret the 12th Jen The 4e*i4en «ovemder to the India iffice* copy sent to you under Printed Letter Ho.621-; of emae date, on the eubject of an Ira^i enquiry with regard to the Iranian population of Kuwait, I haTe received a telecast from the India 'tffice saying they would be glad if I would furnish you with the information asked for In your letter Ite.lsVlV&amp;d of the 20th &gt;ctobar. jl ao no* tmmc x can ao eev er *ruui xorwara you « copy ef sgr letter 40 . 1 /&amp;O 6 of 19th October to the India Off lee* This ie the letter referred to in paragraph 3 of my letter to yeu t go«d47-ft of 3r d 5J or ember (and in paregra^h i&gt; of my letter No 620- i of the 23rd Now^aber to the India office) of which I said X would bo glad to send you a copy should you want one. » you mede no further reference to this letter I did not of course send it. This letter contains all the information in mj possess ion on the subject of Iranians and 'Ohi’aha generally in Kuwait, and answers two of your queries as followst- (1) Your query (n) ie answered in paragraph 3 and the analysis of figures in paragraph 4. Beyond this it is quits impossible to go, and eren this analysis must be taken with caution as the Council in a conversation which de 3*ary and I had with them contested tnat it was the other w»*y abeut,i.e. that the number of '•new* 1 Iranians in Kuwait (who had come in within tne last ■lie 'xoellency Sir Maurice Peterson, 'C.C.H.C., Hie mjsoty’e Ambassador, lagdad xo /(E 542/36/91) NO DI3TRIBUTION. Cypher telegram to Sir M. Peterson, (Bagdad). / Foreign Office, 24th January, 1939, 5 p.m. No. 3 Saving. 0:0:0:0:0:0 My telegram No. IT^lof January 19th: Iraqi enquiry regarding Persian population of Koweit], His Majesty’s (jovernment consider reply on lines given in paragraph 2 of this telegram would he reasonable, taking into account: (a) views which Government of India and Political Resident have expressed as to undesirability of supplying information unless Iraqi Government first explain why they want it (b) undesirability of irritating Iraqi Government by show of suspicion over questions which may have been put in all good faith (c) fact that first three, or at any rate first tv/o, questions relate to matters about which there can be no secrecy and are therefore different from fourth, in regard to which Iraqi Government have admittedly no locus standi . 2. Iraqi Government could be told that Persian population of Koweit is so and so; it had been there for varying periods and in some cases for several generations; according to Koweit Nationality Law (or practice of Koweit Government) all foreigners, including Persians, become Koweiti nationals in such and such circumstances; number of Persians employed by Koweit Oil Company is so and so; and entry of all foreigners, including Persians, into ivoweit, is continually under consideration by Government of Koweit. 3. On this last point enquiry regarding Iraqi motives could be based. On assumption that no such measures are under consideration, you might, for instance, say, at least orally, that althowh this was so, Gulf authorities were curious to know what has rrompteS this particular question. Did Iraqi Government think such restrictions desirable in interests of Koweit? If so, Gulf authorities would be interested to learn their reasons. 4. If, on the other hand, such measures are in fact under con sideration, you could simply add orally that States are seldom willing to give information about their policy in such matters to other States, but that if Iraqi Government could p;ive some idea of what has prompted enquiry, Gulf authorities might be willing to give more definite indication of their policy. 5. Unless you or Political Resident see strong objection please act accordingly when information reaches you. Addressed to Bagdad No. 3 Saving; repeated to Bushire No. 1 Saving. qf]i 1 'ECRFT, In any further oommunioution on this subject, itlease quote ^ and addreg^W)^ to any person by name, b«t to— “TheJIne^Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.VV. 1 ,V' i«V 1 THE Under-Secretary of Stat| foij j^n ^ffairs presents his 487 compliments to r-Secretary of Stat 5 foi and, by direction of the Secretary of State, ^cr transmits herewith cop«Cj of the under-mentioned paper.wmmmmmmmmmmmmrnBiy ,i m r\ i NO DISTRIBUTION. Cypher telegram to Sir M. Peterson (Bagdad). Foreign Office, 19th January, 1939. 1.40 p.m. No. 17. . ^ W- Your despatch No. 561 [of November 15: Iraqi Government enquiry regarding Persian population of Koweit]. Political Resident has been asked to send you answers to four questions put by Iraqi Government on understanding that information will not be given to Iraqi Government, except in accordance with instructions from here. These will follow as soon as possible.$A. .382 ! FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 16th January, 1939 (E 36/36/91). (939 r Immediate. My dear Peel, With reference to our conversation on the 12th January regarding the enquiry from the Iraqi Government about the Persian minority in Koweit, I now send a draft of the telegram which we propose to send to Peterson. 2. Would you let us know as soon as you can whether you concur in it? R#T# Peel, Esq., M.CK 36/36/91 j i939 jinuar y 9 fir ii. Peterson, Bagdad. (K 6939) '’elegrara. No. faving. (Air Mail). ^££her. M trioutlqsi. Your despatch No. 661 (of Noyember 15th. Iraqi enquiry regarding Persian population of Koweit). Political Resident has been asked by telegram to send you answers to four questions put by Iraqi Government on understanding that information will not be given to Iraqi Government except in accordance with instructions from here. 2. Taking into account (1) views which Government of India and Political Resident have expressed as to undesirability of supplying information unless Iraqi Government first explain why they want it (2) undesirability of irritating Iraqi Government by show of suspicion over questions probably put in all good faith. ( 3 )■■■■ ••• - ■JL - jail \ («3) lact that Tiret thr^e # or at any rate first two questions, relate to m&amp;ttera about which there can he no 8r\recy and are therefore different from fourth, in regard to ^hich Iraqi Government have admittedly no locus standi * ills ftjesty'a Government consider reply on following lines would he reasonablej- 3. Persian population of Koweit is so and soj they have been there for varying periods and in some cases for several genera tions; according to Koveiti Nationality Law (or practice of Koweit loverniaent) all foreigners, including Persians, become Koweiti nationals in such and euch circumstances; number of Persians employed by Koweit Oil i S Company is so and so; and entry of all foreigners, including Persians, into Xo^eit, is continually under consideration by Government of Koweit. On this last point enquiry regarding Iraqi motives could be based. On assumption that no such measures are under consideration, you might, for instance, say, at least orally. JL thatthat although this was bo, Gulf author!tlec were curious to know what has prompted this particular question. Did Iraqi Government think such restrictions desirable in interests of Eoweit? If bo, Gulf authorities would be interested to learn their reasons. 5. If, on the other hand, such measures are in fact under consideration, you could simply add orally that f.tatea are seldom willing to give information about their policy in such matters to other States, but that if Iraqi Government could give some idea of what has prompted enquiry, Gulf authorities might be willing to give more definite indication of their policy. 6. Unless you or Political -esident see strong objection please act accordingly when information reaches you. Addressed Bagdad No. Repeated BushireNOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN_ NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN. Minutes, Note on Iraqi enquiry regarding the Persian population of Kov/eit, The Iraqi Government ask the following questions* (a) (i) How many Persians are permanently domiciled in Koweit and (ii) How long have they been there? (b) Will these Persians or their descendants acquire in due course Koweiti + nationality? (c) How many Persians are temporarily living in Koweit as employees of the Koweit Oil Company? (d) Are any measures under consideration for preventing further Persian immigration into Koweit? * 2. The answers to these questions depend upon the following considerations: (a) (i) This is a question of fact. Presumably there has never been a definite census, but there seems reason to suppose that thele are about 20,000 Persians, out of a 50,000 population. ^ fc is,*** (i 1 1' 1 ; (t 1 ■}*&lt;? ' (ii) It is probably impossible, and certainly not necessary, to answer this more than very vaguely, especially as the periods must vary enormously* Several generations is probably near enough. * (b) This depends upon the Koweiti Nationality Law. Presumably most of them will eventually become Koweiti subjects. (c)/Minutes. (c) This again is a question of fact. (d) There seem to be only two alternative$ Either measures are or have been under con sideration or they have not. So far as (a) (i) and (ii), (b) and (c) are concerned, the answers seem, therefore^ to be mainly questions of fact about which there can be no particular secrecy, and little objection to conveying the required information to the Iraqi Government. With regard to (d), however, the position is a little different, as the Iraqis can admittedly have no locus standi for asking what we think on such a point as this. S’. In the circumstances, could not a lead be given to both H.M.Ambassador and the Political Resident somewhat on the following lines? The Iraqis should be informed by H.M. Ambassador that the number of Persians in Koweit is 20,000 (or vhatever it may be); that they have been in Koweit for varying periods and in some cases for several generations; that, according to the Koweiti Nationality Law, all foreigners have become Koweiti nationals •« in the following circumstances .; that about are living in Koweit as eniioyees of the Koweit Oil Company; and that the entry of all foreigners, including Iranians, into Koweit is continually under consideration by the Government of Koweit. On this last point. v u ■~ A ' fc, * -1 Z 0 £ &lt; 2 tn x H Z Ul I- I- E 5 hi m o H 0 Z X H O z NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN. i Z o DC &lt; 2 CO X h Z UJ H H a: 5 LJ CD •-] Minutes. an enquiry could be based as to the motive of the Iraqi Government in putting these questions on one of the two following lines , according to what the position actually is* 6. Assuming that no measures are under consideration, H.M. Ambassador might say that, although no measures are in fact under consideration for preventing further Persian immigration into Koweit, the Koweit authorities •&gt; are somewhat curious to know what has prompted this question* Do the Iraqi Government think that Koweit ought to impose restrictions? If so, the authorities would be interested to know what the! r reasons are for thinking this* If, on the other hand, measures are in fact under consideration, H*M,Ambassador might add that the authorities are naturally reluctant to give information about their policy in these matters to any other Power, without some idea of why the information is required* If therefore the Iraqi Government could give some idea of what has prompted their question, the Kuvrelt might be willing to give some more definite indication of their policy. , Both H.M.Ambassador and the Political Resident may see objections to this, but it will at least be some move made towards ——NOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN. .. &gt; 2CD 1 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 9th January, 1939. 193.9 J My dear Gibson, With reference to your letter PZ 8404/58 o f the 29th December about Iraqi enquiries regarding the number of Persians in Koweit, I write to say that we have some misgivings about the redraft of the despatch to Bagdad enclosed in your letter. 2. We feel that it would be almost impossible for Peterson to approach the Iraqis with an enquiry as to why they wanted the information before he was in a position to give it. But before we can reach a decision on this, more time may have passed. Would it be possible for a telegram to be sent off to Fowle asking him to send the information straight away to Peterson, on the understanding that instructions /to J.P.Gibson, Esq.,,kde.xed A — O' (K 75^6/13/91) 8404 OFFICE, S.W.l. 22nd DecemlDer, 1938. My dear aitson. Many thanks for your letter of the 13th December (p.b.8042/38) regarding the enquiry from the Iraqi Government about the Iranian minority in Koweit. ^* W© should be grateful if you would, as you suggest, ask Powle to supply Peterson with the required particulars for his own information; and we will ask Peterson to use his discretion as to the information which he actually gives to the Iraqi Government, and to ascertain, if he can, what is the basis of the interest which-they have evinced in the Iranian minority. 8. i enclose a draft despatch to Peterson and would be glad to know if you concur. 4. I would suggest that the message to Powle might \ be sent by telegram. I bl. Li-1 T. 2 3 DEC 1938 INDIA OFFICE Yours sincerely, C- f J.p. Gibson, psq.—g Registry No. E 75ii6/13/91 Draft. Sir M. Peterson, Bagdad. No • • • • • I ^ t I s/'^VvtV -J j U a . ^ '' } ^ '^jJ s Y £ r^y/^JL ■ r ^M,j :Km ., // / ;' 4.v ) r ^.0., S.W.l. Deceniber , 193 8. Sir, With reference to your despatch No. 561 of the 15th November (128/15/38) regarding certain enquiries made by the Iraqi Government respecting the Persian population of Koweit, I have to inform Your Excellency that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has been asked, without prejudice to his views as to the prudence of acceding to the Iraqi request, to supply you, for your own information, with the answers to the questions set out in your despatch of the 20th October (128/13/38). 2. , /ls soon as this information is available, I should be glad if you will use „ Ml , Lv . . r ''Bg— bba . , W A, your discretion in deciding how much of .it to £TM_A&gt; t»A i pass on to the Iraqi Government, f and when doing / u— so will endeavour to ascertain, if you can,1 what has prompted the interest which the Iraqi Government have shown in the Persian minorityb 7b'*6/lo/91 bir ,1. Peterson, BB^aea* No* •••• V, a.w.i. BeGcmber 9 bir, \slth rererence t,o your dcapfatoh Wo. 561 oi’ the 15th November (1^6/15/56) regai*ding certain enquiries aade by the Iruqi Goveniment respecting the Persian population of Koweit, I have to infora Your Ixcelleney that the political Kebident in the Persian Gulf hes been asiceci, without prejudice to his views as to the prudence of acceding to the Ira^i request, to supply you, for your own information, with the answers to the questions set out in your despatch of the kiOth October sLlooU, be if y&gt;v ^icnfUi aeccsfau+i by Sod* f&gt;otih (1*8/13/38)* *• hb soon as this information is available, I ehoulu be glad if you will use fit. as H&lt;c&lt;*say, yyyour discretion in decidinfc how much of -tt- to H 7u UjU- of. reply a+A f ^ tModutro* A/^C S “ 7 y 0 « Huy, iUu i Xs d. yjv sU+vt* ysc t*e tdvttHtAn+icr, / pass on to the Iraqi Government^when doing so will endeavour to ascertain, if you ceny 7 whet has prompted the interest which the Iraqi Government have shown in the Persian minority,CONFIDENTIAL. *y v&gt;* Osj to ^ ^ A /Vji^ y T4.#/«t44» Lyd^ficl 1938 ) Would you please refer to the correspondence ending with ( Fowle's demi-official letter No.620-8. of the 23rd Novr. 1938 on the subject of the Iranian Govt.’s enquiry about the Iranian population of Kuwait? We fully appreciate Peterson's reluctance to administer a snub to a friendly Government over a comparatively unimportant matter of this kind. On the other hand, I am inclined to agree with Fowle that the Iraqian questionnaire has been framed at the instance of the Iranian Government in order to save the Iranian Govt, from making a direct approach to us with regard to a matter affecting Kuwait. L».any case, we do not feel that much harm could be done by a polite enquiry from the Iraqian Govt, as to their reasons for asking for information,which prima facie. would not appear to be of direct interest to themselves. Yours sincerely. E. T. Peel, Esqr., M.C., The India Office, London E. T. Peel, Esqr 19 DEC1938 I No; A OFFICEt D. O.tfO. 620-3. r- • •» ^ .. 8042 19*36“' dency Busnire f tne 23rd jsiovember, iy36» 7/fi cU.CvT. ^-ccL Could you pi8as6 refer to Petersoxi's letter ^io*061 oi tne Idtn November 1938 to tne Foreign Of! ice on tue suoject of an Iraqi enquiry witn regard to tne Iranian population of Kuwait ? 2. In making tne suggested reply to tne Iraqi urovermnent contained in paragrapn 4 of my letter imo.o47-^ oi tne 3rd .November 1938 to Peterson, I am afraid it did not occur to me tnat tne Iraqi Government would regard it - suitably wrapped up - as a ^gratuitous snub** 3, #itn regard to tne estaDlisnment oi tne port at, or near, Kuwait regarding wnicn Peterson is or opinion tnat the Iraqi request for information may nave been based. Peterson’s letter of tne 20tn October 1938 made no mention of tne proposed port, and it did not occur to me tnat tne Iraqi request nad been made in tnis connection. If tne project for a port goes forward doubtless at some stage or otner tne Iraqi Government will require statistical information rei trade etc. wnicn of course can be given tnem, out personally I cannot see now replies to tne questionnaire contained in Peterson’s letter of 20tn October would oe of use to tnem in tnis connection. queries (b) and (d) for instance seem to me purely matters of policy for tne Kuwait Government ana also for ourselves to tne extent tuat on us lies tne responsibility / R.T.Peel Esquire, M.C*, Tne India Office, London.mmmmmmmmammmmmmmmKmmmm - 2 - reaponaibility for tne foreign affairs of tne Kuwait State. In any case would it not oe as well to postpone giving tne Iraqis information in connection witn tne port until tney for it ? 4 # you are aware* in regard to tne project oi tne port I was, wnen it was first put forward oy txie Iraqi Government, more or less in favour 01 it - vide my letter No.278-3, dated tne 24tn May 1^38 - and in txiat position 1 remained for some time M in tne glorious minority of one”, since tne first reactions to tne project of tne otner autnorities concerned were distinctly unfavouraDle. 1 merely mention tnis to snow tnat I am not influenced oy an anti- Iraqi bias, and would not oe lively to suggest refusing tne Iraqi Government any information in regard to tne .Port wnicn tney could legitimately asK for. witn regard to wnat Peter son says as to an Iranian claim over Auwait itself, surely tne Iraqi Government are well aware tnat tnis is a pretention wnicn we would never anow. b. Peterson doss not agree witn my opinion tnat tne enquiry in question nas really oeen made at tne instance of tne Iranian tiovernment. Tne reasons for my opinion are as follows. In paragrapn 3 oi my letter of ora aovemoer I referred to tne recent Iranian agitation in Kuwait, and I dealt witn tnis at lengtn in my letter jso. c/606, dated tne I9tn October 1938, to Gibson. (Tnis was tne letter i torn Peterson I would be glad to let nim nave a copy of snoula ne require it.) Tne Persian Government are presumably, and legitimately, interested in^tnis agitation as it concerns tneir /KHSIPfPRM t!'** . « . 8042 to apply to us for information, but as you are aware tney do not recognise our special position at Kuwait, or ror tne matter of tnat at any of tne otner Arab states of tne Uulf, and so nave used tne Iraqi G-overnment instead# If I am rignt in tnis opinion, personally I do not see wny we snould go out of our way to assist tne Persian Government in evading recognition of our special position at Kuwait by allowing tnem to use tne Iraqi Government as species of stalKing norse. 6# I sun certainly in favour of giving tne Iraqi Government any information about tneir cwn suojects, or about any special nappening in Kuwait wnicn may afiect tnem as a neignbouring State e.g# tne formation of tne new Council - vide my telegram IJo#297, dated tne 27tn *&gt;uly 193b, out as indicated in paragrapn 4 of my letter of 3rd November I am not in favour of allowing tnem to imagine tnat tney are in a special position to interest tnemselves at large in Kuwait# tfould it not oe feasible to ask tne Iraqi Government wnat is tne basis for tneir enquiries *r * I am sending a copy of tnis letter to Peterson, as well as a copy to Metcalfe witn a copy oi Peterson’s letter under reference# ♦sent under Printed letter ±io.621-S of tne 23rd Novemoer 193b#77^. under cover of the Political Resident’s Printed Letter No. 548-S of the 3rd November, copies of correspondence between Fowle and Peterson regarding an enquiry from the Iraqi Government about the Iranian minority in Koweit, I now enclose a copy of a despatch from Peterson in which he explains why he considers that the Iraqi Government have a genuine interest in the Iranian colony in Koweit. Powle evidently does not agree with him on this point; but we feel that in the circumstances there can be no harm in letting the Iraqi Government have, as a matter of courtesy, the information they require. If you agree with us, perhaps you would consider suggesting to Fowle that there can be no grave objection to/ c;:glosure in air mail letter | N0 * Jft? d ; FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE R.T• Peel, Esq., M.C.to supplying Peterson with the particulars for which he has asked. We must obviously return an early reply to the Iraqi Government 1 s enquiry, so perhaps the matter could he dealt with by telegram.r 1 Ko, 561, (188/15/38) • / (Copiee by Bag). ~ _ l f 7994 1938 British Kmbassy, Bagdad. l5th NoTeraber, 1938. My Lord, I have the honour to transmit herewith, for Your Lordship’s information, copies of correspondence which has passed between the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and myself on the subject of a recent Ira^i enquiry with regard to the Iranian population of Koweit. 2. I see no reason to endorse Sir Trenchard Powle’s suggestion that this enquiry has really been made at the instance of the Iranian Government. On the contrary, my own feeling is that the enquiry is a perfectly natural and proper one for the Iraqi Government to have made at a time when they are actually in communication with His Majesty’s Government as to the possibility of creating a port in or near Koweit, with a view to relieving the dependence of Iraq’s sea-borne traffic on the Shatt-al- Arab route liable, as it is, to be interrupted by the Iranians. At such a moment it my well be a matter of legitimate concern to the Iraqis to discover that there is an Iranian colony of 20,000 or so in Koweit, a minority which, judging by Persian political tactics in the past, might well give rise at some future date to an Iranian claim The Right Honourable The Viscount Halifax, K.G., G.C.J.I., G.C.I.K., etc., etc., etc*- * claim over Koweit Itself. 3* I have therefore no Intention of passing on to the Iraqi Government - who are allies of Great Britain and as such perfectly entitled to raise this and kindred questions with them - the gratuitous snub suggested by Sir Trenchard Fowle. 4. On the contrary, I should be most grateful if I could be enabled to reply in some way to the Iraqi Governments enquiry. 5* I am sending a copy of this despatch to the honourable the Folltical Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to be with the Highest respect, My I^ord, Your Lordship’s most obedient, humble Servant, (Sgd,) Maurice Peterson. The Minister for Foreign Affairs raised the question again today and pressed me for some information. (Id) M.P.'MB 1 n FILE_COPY CONFIDENTIAL. Ts T o. 548-3 of 1938. A 774j The Hon’ble the Political Redd^ht'hj. th^ Persian Gulf presents his** compliments to 1. Sir Aubrey Metoalfe, KGIE. »G3I. #MVO., Secretary to the Government of India, TSxternal Affairs Department, New Delhi. , 2. R.T.Peel Esquire, MC. , The India Office, London. 3. Qaptain G.S.de Gauxy, MG. » political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). \0 iJ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. 3rd. N.QT. «pb . 1938 . Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure, tr Name and Date. Subject. 1, Letter No. 128/13/38 of the 20th October 1938 from His Majesty’s Interest of the Iraqi Ambassador, Bagdad. Government in the Iranian 2. Letter No.547-Sof the 3rd minority in Kuwait. Hovember 1938 to His Majesty’s Ambassador, Bagdad.copy (128/13/38). Sir, British Utab&amp;ssy, Bagdad. 1 20th October, 193 8. ! I have the honour to inform you that the Iraqi Oorernment have recently evinced interest in the Iranian ’pz. o/s/3*] minority in Kuwait, which I understand from a recent Kuwait Intelligence Summary to amount to some 20,000 out of a total population of about 50,000 persons. 2. It would assist me in dealing with the Iraqi Govern ment’s enquiries if I could be furnished with some further inforraation with regard to these Iranians, and in particular if I could be informed (a) how many of them are permanently domiciled in Kuwait and how long have they been there, (b) whether they or their descendants will, in course of time, acquire Kuwait nationality, (c) how many are temporarily living in Kuwait as employees of the JOiwait Oil Company, and (d) whether any measures are under consideration for preventing further Iranian immigration into Kuwait. 3. I shall accordingly be grateful if I may be furnished with your comments on this subject. I have tne honour to be, 3ir, Your obedient servant, sd. Maurice Peterson. The Honouraole The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.V f L. 5 -W« | Vi.kj (U'l ' Could you pi ease ref or to yeur letter Ho. 128/13/38, dated the 20th October 1938, on the subject of the Interest of the Iraqi OoTemment in the Iranian minority in Kuwait. 2* I do not wish to appear unhelpful or obet rue tire in any way but I really do not see shy the Iraqi Government should interest themselves in Iranians in Khwaits if it were Iraqis they *ere interested in it would of course be another matter. 3. I may be unduly suspicious but I cannot help feeling that in all probability it is the Iranian Government who 9 for •oae reason or other, have put up the Iraqis to ask these questions, Instead of doing it themselves. If the Iranian Government approach ue on the subject this would of course be quite in order. There has been recently some Iranian A agitation is ruwait on which I have written a long letter to the India office. I will not trouble you with this but if you would like a copy I shall of course be glad to send you one. 4 4, as you know it is Hie Hajeety*e aoverament's policy to prevent any increase of Iraqi influence in Kuwait, ana personally I think it would be a mistake to let the Iraqi Government / Hie excellency Sir Maurice Peterson, K.C.M.G., His Majesty's ambassador, Bagdad. '•s,- lx T' '*r- • 2« GOT«rm«nt Imagine that - Ju»t baoauat tiieir frontitr aaroha® with - they are in a special position to interest thetas elves at large in that 3tate« I venture to eu^eet therefore that the irm\i Oovernment might be informed that should thqy aiaxo any enquiries as to Iraqis in *hwait we will be glad to give then any information that we have, but that in regard to Iranians it is the buBlnees of the Iranian hov^rhaent to approach ue» * 2 am sending a copy of your letter and of this to Uetoalfs» Petl and ds Qauxy. Yours sincerely, sd. T.C.I’owle. ♦ sent under Printed letter Ho.548-U of the 5rd November # 1*36 # IZ.7817/58. Confidential. D.O.No.C/806. if - i Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Kuv/ait. Dated the 19th October 1958. My dear Gibson, Could you please refer to my demi-official letter No C/804, dated the 19th October 1938, on the subject of the Kuwait Council. 2. Anot^r matter connected with the Council is as follows. There are here a large number of individuals of the Sh’i’ah persuasion, probably as many as 18,000, the total population of Kuwait Town being, say, 65,000: these figures are extremely rough as there has never been anything like a real census of Kuwait. In 1910, however, Shaikh Mubarak had an j enumeration made of the population of the tov/n which showed a total of 38,000, of v/hich lOOOwere ’’Persians”. (The Bedu tribes and the villages in Kuwait territory outside the town are Sunni). 3. The above Shi'ahs can be divided into the following classes: Persians, numbers about 10,000. Numbers about 3000. Shi*ahs from the Hasa Province of Saudi Arabia. These are the remnants of the old Persian (a) AJAEM i.e. (b) HASAWIS.I -Tv - (d) FUWADRA. (c) BAHARNAS. Niimbers about 3000. Shi’ahs from Bahrain and the coasts of the lov/er middle section of the Persian Gulf. Numbers about 1000. These are Shi'ahs of those Arabs who emigrated from Arabia into Persia, and thence back to Kuwait. (e) Shi'ahs of Iraqi origin. Numbers about 700. 4* All these Shi'ahs have lived contentedly m Kuwait up to within a few months ago, i.e. up to the formation of the Council. Since then, however, they have shown signs of discontent. The reason for this is presumably as follows. Under the one-man rule of the Shaikh the Shi'ahs were at any rate no worse off than the Sunnis. Moreover the Shaikh's State Secretary, himself a Persian Shi'ah by origin, gave them a way of access to the head of the State in case of grievances. With the coming of the Council however - an entirely Sunni body, on which the Shi'ehs are not represented - they ferl that they are unlikely to get a square deal, though up to date they have indeed suffered no actual tyranny from the Council. This discortent culminated lately in applications being received by de Gaury, as Political Agent Kuwait, to the number of more than 4500 to become British subjects. The analysis of these figures is as follows: Bahamas ... ... .... Hasawis ... ... ... Iranians (in Kuwait less than 10 years) 983 37 170 Iranians (in Kuwait up to 120 years and all more than 10 years) 3457This figure includes wives and children of the applicants but not their servants, male and female, which would bring the number up to perhaps 8000. When this move became known to the Council, they allowed themselves to become rattled and, in spite of some good advice from de Gaury, issued a public notice to the effect that anyone applying for foreign nation ality would render himself liable to deportation. This increas ed the apprehensions of the Shi T ahs. 5. Even if we wanted to accede to these applications for British nationality we cannot do so under the rules governing the grant of British nationality to foreigners, v/hich, amongst other stipulations, lay down that the applicant must have long residence in a British possession. de Gaury under my instructions has informed the applicants accordingly, through Said Yusuf Musawi, the Judge of the Shi*ah Religious Court, and the accepted head of the Shi T ah community. 6. Though the Shi T ah question is an internal matter, nevertheless it may have external repercussions since so many of the Shi’ahs in question are Persians, or of recent Persian descent, and if they are hardly treated the Iranian Government may make representations to us on their behalf. Further, we are of course interested in trying to ensure that Kuwait, especially at the present time, continues without internal disturbances. This being so I thought it as well to have a talk with the Shaikh and the Council on the subject and on ohe 15th a meeting took place: the Mejlis was represented by their President and six members. I was accompanied by7. I began by saying that the position with regard to external affairs had already been explained to them at our last meeting, but there were certain border line cases which might arise from time to time, and which though internal might have external reprecussions. On these it would be useful to have mutual discussions, during which I would like to give my personal and unofficial advice. Such a case in point was the Shi^h agitation, on which for instance His Majesty 1 s Government might receive representations from the Iranian Government, and I asked what v/as the view of the Council on this matter. 8. The Deputation had no clear views except beyond insisting that Kuwait was Arab territory, and that they wanted it kept as such, free from Persian intrigue and influence. They said that they could not possibly agree to the demands of the Shi ! ahs, which had been for (a) special Shi ! ah schools (b) representation on the Council (c) representation on the Municipality Council. I agreed that (a) v/as a request which the Kuwait Government need not grant if they were not disposed to do so, but I suggested that (b) ana (c) might be v/orth consider ing. A single Shi*ah representative on the Council could not affect the Council 1 s decisions, but would give the Shi’ahs an opportunity of ”letting off steam ,, , and I explained to them the inadvisability of 'sitting on the safety valve.' 10. The Deputation then repeated their views as given above/</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001de_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3908</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001de</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3908</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/171 'Koweit: Iranian population of Koweit. Iraqi interest.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-07T22:47:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (56 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 57; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns a request by the Government of Iraq to establish the precise numbers of the Shiah population in Kuwait (also referred to as Koweit). This information is given in a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Trenchard Craven William Fowle) to the India Office on folios 52-56.The papers show that there was a difference of opinion between Fowle and the British Ambassador at Bagdad [Baghdad] (Sir Maurice Drummond Peterson) over whether the Government of Iran was behind the request: Fowle thought they were, Peterson disagreed. The Political Resident was also not in favour of allowing the Iraqi Government to imagine that they were in a special position to interest themselves in the affairs of Kuwait (folio 43). The file also contains correspondence from the Foreign Office.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Shīʻah</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001de#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>