<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001fc_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-17T14:35:04.067Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INWARD TELEGRAM »7i&lt; ■ V, A @cjui Allotted to External Departmento , ! &lt; H.D Fr i To Dated Received WORD CODE political Resident In Persian Oulf Secretary of state for Commonwealth Relations Bahrain, 18 e 30 hours, 29th October, 1947 08 o 55 hours, 29th October, 1947* No o A/ / '844c My telegram a 806 of October 13th paragraph NOc3o Prohibition of import of dates from Muscato 2, Government of India have now replied report is Incorrect and that for period July-December 1947 licences for Import of dates are issued on quota basis the quota being 50 per cent of imports made during 1945-1946 0 Further unrestricted imports of dates is permitted from Muscat if carried in country craft e ' — 5* I am passing on the above to Political Agent Muscat and do not press for any representation to be made to Government of India on the subject for the present®I 4 r'~*N ^0 ^ Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relatione Dated Bahrain, 18*40 hour^, 14th October 1947 Received 20*y0 hoursi, 14th October 1947 I Galloway* 3 telegram a.656 27th ^ugust* Prohibition of import of pearls from Gulf to India* 2* Sheik of Bahrein has appealed to me in strongest terms to get embargo removed* It seriously disrupts economy in Bahrein and Trucial Coast* according to Sheikh Bombay is at present sole market where pearls can be properly processed graded etc* and for many classes of pearls there is no market outside India* Has it been possible to take any action vi, s_a vis the Government of India? 3* V/hat is more serious is that Government of India are reported to have prohibited import of dates* 90% of Batinah crops are dry dates of a variety used almost exclusively for weddings and festivals in India* Bahrein has oi3. to support its finance but Muscat depends practically entirely on export of dry dates to finance imports of general merchandise from India* Closing of Indian dry date market will bring ruin to Batinah* Government of India were asked in August for particulars of restrictions imposed but have not reniied. I am sending/sending reminder but should 'be grateful if fUM* Government would also make enquiries and representations.**.?.644-4i/o7. The Deputy Secretary to the ftovemieat of Ir«iia in the external Affaire Uepartnentf To ir. The Hon’bXe tew 1 olitical evident in tiie ror^ian i?ulf # yue*ttioa of the reuuction of euoioKti duty on da tea im|orted froci hacat. hated -irala» the April 195(3. I am uirecteu to state th&amp;t lliu Ki^ineas Uie -ult«c of Muecat uurin^ hia viait to Mew Delhi in Horomber last raised the question of a reduction of eustessi duty on dates imported from Huscat. The question has been exarainea and the position is as fellows. Datee from forei n cotintriea are asaeusec to duty at the s*tan€u«rcl revenue rate of 30 per cent valorem , while there is a preferential rate of 20 per oont. &amp;&amp; yr^onm for colonial products vide item $c.6 of the Indian Custom* 'tariff. The Matory of Uie fixation of tariff valuta of uattsu is as follows. Dates comii\ frotii all sou roes v/ere subject to n uniform tui'iff valuation up to the end of 1932, but as the result of a representation rcceiveu in October 1932 from the .ultan of Muscat separate tariff Wilma were a«v i, n«d for dates taper ted from Iraq ana dates imported from Msse&amp;t and othar countricij with effect fromi the 1st J^iiu^iry 1933. Ihe fallowing were tiic tariff Vfiiues for the year 1933 t He At 1. 10-0-0 per ewi* 5-6-0 per cwh* Basra (Iraq) dates I ’CIA FOREiaN SECRE'ARY’a i otter ^abpve rates were subaequontly r^uced from the let Dated 3L*Pd FiecetVBd c MAY L January /January 1954 to iuud for Iraq ami }i&amp; 0 4/lZ/- for oUwr dated anu lat^r *ua rebult of a fall in market values Uie tariff value of Iraqi dateB was further roamm to Jb,6/1'/- p«r c^t. fror;i th@ 1st January 1955. As su^rior and inferior qualities of dates are imported into India not only from Basra but from otiier places like Mohaaraerah, the basis of olasaifioation, i»hich was on the origin of ary dates, ms eJriar\ed to that of ou^ditv with effect from the 1st January 1956. The present classification roads as follows t Datos f dry, in ba^s Kapkajm, 5hekra Chharra, CliUjiCiiap, and Brumi • Tariff Talus &amp;•£/- p«r cwt. All other qualities - ariff Value b .5/12/- per evrt. 2. It has been ascertained from the Uollectora of Custo^a at Boutbay and i^-racM that about 25 per cent of the ary dates uurivir^ fron Huscat at Bombay are of superior quality known m , B^i^.koria , Him assessed at tariff valuation of ^*8 per cr/t, ana that practically all the re. t of tiio huscrat dates arriving at both ports ai'e of inferior quality and aase&amp;sed at the lower valuation of H«.S/12/* per cwt. These valuations are babea Kjfeinly on tlie all^Zndia ex-ciuty weighted averse of twelve months 1 mrket prices, ana it is only possible to reduce thcr^ when the market prices warrant such a reduction, which is not the caae at present. 5. 1 am to request thftt if you see no objection the position my kinuly be explaineu to the tultfin of S4u«cat in due course. I liave Uie honour to be, dir. Your most obedient servant, :&gt;d/-. W.H. Hay, De uty Secretary to tiiu Government of India.p (11) Seduction of customs duty on ?,iuocat datea . Aa a reeult of representatlona made by the local political authorities towards the end of 1932, some concession v/as made in the Tariff value for dates imported from Muscat, (see P, Z, 1610/33). But the actual rate of duty was governed by the Ottawa Agreement and could not apparently be altered, in favour of Muscat. Although the Ottawa Agreements ore still in force negotiations for a new Agreement are now taking place and it is possible that in the new Agreement something might be done to help f/?uscat. But this is mainly a matter for the Government of India to decide*MPPQPQPl f' S||_E OOP^ ! ,© . ''415 1 Extract between Affairs Muscat, from Note of a disau&amp;iidn^i^ld-Jbn 17.11.37. Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, Secretary, External Department, and His Highness the Sultan of at which the Political Agent, Muscat, was o \ ^ also present. (11) Reduction of Customs Duty on Muscat Dates , The Sultan referred to his request first made at his interview with His Excellency for a reduction on the Duty charged on dates imported into India from Muscat. Secretary said he would go into the question but explained that there were difficulties in the way ov/ing to a number of agreements entered into by the Government of India with various Foreign Powers by which they enjoyed most favoured nation treatment.#S&amp; ' ' C\o) Extract from Note of an interview b&lt; twe^iyl^S iliXX»raui/ .Lium rjuut; ux aii xxiocxvxcw lm Excellency the Viceroy, and His HigmlFS'S' fHC^StlTtan of Muscat, at which Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, Secretary, External Affairs Department, was also present. an interview 3. His Highness then referred to the import duty at present charged upon Muscat dates. This question has not been raised officially within my memory and I am not at all sure that we have any papers on the subject in the office. I will however make enquiries and find out. There was recently a similar request made by the Iraq Government for preferential treatment for their dates in return for some preference which they were prepared to give to Indian and British goods over Japanese imports. So far as I remember, the proposal had to be turned down owing to the restrictions placed upon the Government of India's freedom of action in this matter by the Treaty rights enjoyed under various Commercial Treaties by various other Nations. Many Nations have at present most-favoured nation rights with regard to import duties on goods brought into India which makes it extremely difficult to negotiate special concessions to individual countries. It has been held that schemes of Imperial Preference within the Empire do not violate such most-favoured-nation rights, but since Muscat is not a part of the British Empire, the difficulty does arise in their case. I will however have the matter examined and will ask the Political Resident to let us have a clearer exposition of what His Highness wants.^fowoi. ] Myx, pita (£3 ft^ lj &lt; ^- t .'^ &lt;1^ C } &lt;1 ° ^ 4 ^^4- ^ ^ cc ^, -H yM^ k ^ ^ ^ K W-^ ^4v&lt;r. S ;: ’tv v 4 Ww^j. jv/v» TC 'L. ^ '^c-Uar Uw^ K « ^ ot,^ ^-p- . ^ ^ t(^ 4 n, , Krt- ^ Tt^ f / • ^ U f^M- irvf/a&amp;AAJ*t Register No. P. Z. Minute Paper. 1610/33. Political Department. Letter from O Dated Dec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee /o. . 1~j Muscat. The Indian tariff on Muscat dates Under Secretary Secretary of State... Council Copy to SEEN POUTi^.u COMMITTEE Previous Papers 3453 1000 2.29 The Muscat export trade,which consists in the export of d^tes to India, has been very hardly hit by the Indian date tariff. The Indian duty i^t^j charged on a pre-determined tariff value, fixed for a particular period and computed on the average market price (less customs duty) of all qualities of date* imported from all sources^ 34ai-s—n-yete-r has worked very much to the disadvantage of Muscat, since Muscat dates are of the inferior (BISR) type, and the result has been that the duty actually paid on Muscat date imported into India has been 82^ instead of the /»&lt;**« fiL-' AJ+u&lt;\ nominal fixed rate of 25^.^ / z ( n y Muscat trade was thus in danger of being j completely strangled, a result which would have been/'been most undesirable from the point of view of both parties, since Muscat depends almost entirely for its imports on India, and these imports have decreased to.a more than proportionate extent with the decline in the export trade. As the result of representations fran the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Government of India have now reduced thefe tariff,-ftl dates other than Basra (Irak) dates frcm Rs.9.8 per hundredweight to Rs.5.8. This should lead to a revival of trade in both directions. £e C . e.'r-o •**“*.' 74CV1 U.T5 V (&gt; ~ Vi d O J Secretary Political Department The Tar^iff value for Dates Dry in bags, other sorts is nov Rs5-8, but t le rate of duty, which used to be 25 /° ad valorem has in consequence of the Ottawa agreement been changed to 2C&amp; for British Colonies and for dates from elsewhere. I io not know for certain but I rather doubt if Muscat gets the preference and,if not,tne actual duty to be paid will apparently be Rs1-10-6. per cwt. The preferential rate seems to work out at about Rs^-1-6. while the old bate was Rs 2-6-0. per cwt. I suppose the'tariff value’ is still well above the real value of Muscat dates, but still txhey are better off than they were * /h-tA. &gt; A*”* - « CKX- (*. ivATVA * ^ '1^3-iMi(u . /F s, Vj A . ' \v' \ ll \ Ai 1 ' ( POLITICAL C\a? £ U 1 i a Letter (1) l C J FROM THE HON’BLE THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF, No. 2191 of 1232, dated the 22nd October 1932. I have the honour to forward for favour of your examination and considera tion copies of Political Agent, Muscat’s despatch No. 967 of the 13th September 1932, which speaks for itself. % 2. The present state of affairs benefits neither India nor Muscat. 'While the loss to the former may perhaps appear small the loss to Muscat is disastrous. 3. It is unnecessary for me to emphasise the necessity of helping Muscat in any way possible, and I would invite a reference to the despatches on this subject especially my No. 541-S., dated the 5th August 1932. 4. Finally, the Political Agent, though he has not mentioned it in his despatch, intimates that during his recess he consulted the Collector of Customs at Karachi and that the latter is representing the matter to Government. 5. To save time I am asking the Political Agent, Muscat, to submit a report of his conversation with the Collector of Customs and to send a copy of it to the Government of India direct. Letter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, No. 967 of 1932, dated the 13th September 1932. I have the honour to address you on the subject of the Indian Customs duty levied on the “ Bisr ” or dry date of Oman. 2. As will be seen from the accompanying memorandum No. A.-13/731, dated lst‘September 1932, from the office of the Financial Adviser, the incidence of the duty bears most unfavourably on the Oman dry date exported to India. 3. It is a fact that owing to the Oman date being classified together with Iraq dates, the official 25 per cent, duty has grown to an imposition of more than 80 per cent., and, unless the Tariff Board take very early steps to adjust the incidence to 25 per cent, ad valorem both the merchants and the growers of Oman will practically disappear. 4. It is interesting to note that while trade in India is said to be practically at a standstill the warehouses at Matrah are stacked full of dried dates which would immediately be shipped off to India and sold were the present prohibitive duties reduced to more reasonable proportions. In return for these shipments to India large quantities of rice, coffee, sugar, piece-goods, etc., would be imported into Muscat from India to the mutual benefit of both countries. 5. It is to be hoped that the indicated relief will be granted as early as possi ble so as to commence the trade revival this season. If relief is delayed then the complete cessation of trade between the two countries will only be a matter of time. £ 6. Export of dates to India in 1929-30 totalled .. .. 94,586 Export of dates to India in 1930-31 totalled .. .. 78,054Memorandum from the Financial Adviser, Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s DATED THE 1ST SEPTEMBER 1932. Muscat State, to the Political Consul, Muscat, No. A.-13/731, For some years past, throughout the whole country of Oman, there has been a growing discontent amongst the trading community in general and par icu ar } amongst the British Indian traders, who aie the largest dealers in dry dates, at tlie great disparity between the official rate of Customs duty supposed to be levied on dry dates and the rate which is actually levied. 2. During the last year, however, owing to— (а) the acute trade depression, and (б) the raising of the Indian Customs duty on dates, this general dissatisfaction is beginning to manifest itself by a repeated and increasing number of complaints and representations to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. 3. Bankruptcies also especially amongst British Indian subjects have in creased beyond all bounds. The sole export trade of this country, which consists of dates, is being ruined, date gardens, either owing to the poverty of the owners or to their disgust at the almost insurmountable tariff barrier which has been raised against them, are falling out of cultivation, oceangoing native sailing craft are dis appearing and the British India Steam Navigation Company carrying trade has dwindled almost to nothing. 4. The general ruin and desolation of what was once and could still be, a fairly prosperous country will take more than a decade to repair, no body has been bene- fitted, all parties have lost through this short-sighted and uneconomical policy and the heaviest loser of all, both in import and export revenue, has been India itself. 5. As the natural result of this cessation of the export trade from this country to India there has been a practical stoppage of the once thriving import trade from India to this country, thus bringing about a heavy fall in the Customs revenues of both the countries. 6. Indian Customs duty. —Indian Customs duty on imports is assessed in three different ways— (а) On the C. I. F. value of goods. This includes the invoivee value in cluding all expenses up to port of destination j)lus local charges, such as landing fees, handling, etc. (б) Ad valorem, i. e., on the wholesale value of goods in the port of landing, less duty. (c) Tariff valuation. Duty is charged on a pre-determined tariff value fixed for a particular period. This tariff is the computed average market price (less Customs duty) of all qualities of a particular article, imported from all sources. 7. All dry dates, from whatever country, are assessed on the tariff valuation according to (c) above. This year the Indian Customs duty on dates, is 25 per cent., on the tariff valuation, last year it was 20 per cent, and the year before 15 per cent. 8. Unfair incidence of tariff valuation on Oman dates. —The value of dry dates imported into India is, for tariff purposes, reckoned to be the average market price (less Customs duty) in the port of landing of all qualities, from the very highest to the very lowest price of dry dates imported from all sources. 9. The principal exporter of dry dates is Iraq, where the very finest and most expensive dates abound. The best known of the dry dates variety is Chapchak which commands twice the market price of the ‘ Bisr ’ or Oman dry dates which is practically speaking the only form of dates exported from Oman. While, therefore, Iraq exports a large quantity of the most valuable and expensive dates Oman’s export consists practically of nothing else but the ‘ Bisr ’ of inferior quality leaving still greater quantity unexported due to the tariff barrier.10. From the above it must be clear that the Iraqi exporter with his more valuable dates can, after paying Indian Customs duty on the present tariff valua tion, still sells his goods in India at a handsome profit. On the other hand, the Omani exporter, with his low priced ‘ Bisr ’ date has to pay in India a Customs duty which is reckoned on a tariff valuation or average market rate value of more than three times the market value of his dates, less Customs duty. • 11. Taking for example about one lakh bags of dates are exported from Oman yearly to India which contain l/3rd good and 2/3rd inferior quality dates. Based on average prices current during the last year the C. 1. F. Bombay prices of Oman dates came to :— Rs. 33,000 bags at Rs. 10 per bag (good quality) .. .. .. 3,30,000 67,000 bags at Rs. ^4 per bag (inferior quality) .. .. . • 2,68,000 Total .. 6,98,000 say about Rs. 6,00,000. The C. I. F. Bombay prices came to about Rs. 6 per bag while the fixed tariff valuation in India had been Rs. 9/8 p er cwt. or Rs. 14/4 per bag. Thus an Omani exporter has paid Rs. 3/9 as Indian Customs duty instead of Rs. 1/8 or Rs. 2/1 per bag has been paid in excess of what would have been payable at 25 per cent. ad valorem. The duty thus paid came to 82 per cent, instead of the nominal fixed rate of 25 per cent. A true copy of one of the Forma Invoice for a consignment of 100 bags of dates forwarded to India submitted by the merchants with their representation is enclosed for ready reference. It will show that the merchant received Rs. 67 net for the cultivator on whose behalf the consignment was sent. The cultivator got ^ about 9 as. per bag for his year’s toil while fortunately the merchant escaped the loss he would have incurred if the consignment was sent on his own account, as his purchase price per bag would have been Rs. 4/8 each. 12. A trader desiring to export a consignment of 100 bags of dry dates from Oman to India in addition to paying the transport and Customs charges amounting to Rs. 669 mentioned above, would have to buy his consignment first from the cultivator at a cost of Rs. 290/14 which after selling in India at the market rate quoted above would leave him a balance debit of Rs. 223/14, a manifestly im possible situation. The accuracy of the two incidence given above can be verified by reference to the Kharak Merchants at Bombay. 13. Conclusion .—It is not contended that the system of fixed tariff valuation, whereby an average market value, over a particular period, is assigned to a whole range of commodities, such as dates, which come under one heading, is unfair as a general principle. It is, however, contended that in the particular case of Oman dry dates the incidence of duty is o ppressive beyond all measures and should be modified to a reasonable figure more in keeping with the actual market value of the commodities in question. It cannot be argued that a duty of 82 per cent, ad valorem on such a simple article of daily food as the date is justifiable or even desirable nor, I think, it is a wise policy to crush out the commercial life of a country like Oman which depends almost entirely for its imports on India. 14. It is strongly urged that the Indian Tariff Board may be approached with a view to fixing, as an immediate measure, a special tariff rate for the ‘ Bisr ’ or dry dates which is almost the only export from this country and upon which its very existence depends. In case this may not be possible, I would request that duty may be assessed on Oman dates on ad valorem basis which will be most equit able to both the exports from this country and the Government of India.4 A pro-Forma invoice for 100 bags of dry dates shipped from Muscat to Bombay. Rs. a. p. Rs. a. p- 100 bags dry dates sold at Rs. 40 per candy less Indian expenses • 736 0 0 Indian Government duty .. 342 0 0 • Other expenses .. .. 172 0 0 514 0 0 Total .. • • • 222 0 0 Less local expenses— Empty bags .. 40 0 0 Shipping charges .. 13 0 0 Agents commission ... .. 6 0 0 Duty and weighing .. .. 25 0 0 4 Boat hire .. .. 8 0 0 Expenses at Bhatna .. 18 0 0 Carriage from interior .. 45 0 0 155 0 0 Net proceed for the cultivator : • 67 0 0 ( 2 ) Letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. C/26 of 1932, dated the 10th November 1932. I have the honour to refer to my letter No. 2191 of 22nd October 1932 [Serial No. (1)]. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat, with whom I have discussed the matter, ex plained that there was apparently some mutilation in a telegram that he sent me. The Collector of Customs, Karachi (vide paragraph 4 of my letter quoted above) has not represented the matter to Government, but recommended that this should be done. I venture to suggest therefore that Government, on the case as already detailed to them, should take up the matter with the appropriate authorities. (3) Letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 2502 of 1932, dated the 3rd December 1932. With reference to the Muscat Trade report a copy of which was forwarded to this office by the Political Agent, Muscat, it is hardly necessary for me to draw the attention of the Government of India to the heavy decline in the State’s trade as evidenced by the report under reference. 2. The total volume of trade for the year 1931-32 amounted to Rs. 54,44,445 (£395,958) as against £415,275 of the previous year, (in itself a bad one from the trade point of view), showing a decrease of £19,317 (imports decreasing by £10,689 and exports by £8,628. 3. This serious decrease in its trade renders all the more urgent any measures which we can take to assist the State, and in this connection I shall be most interest ed to learn whether Government have been able to take any steps in connection with the suggestion made in mv letter No. C/36 of 10th November 1932 [Serial No. (3)]. Me22FD—16—27-2-33—GIP8j8&gt; Ho. S.4527-H/32 Fro* tht Ifcputy Secretary to the Oorerinvent of India In the Foreign end Politic*! Depart^entt The Hcn’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Dated Few i&gt;elhif the Zt*' February 1933. MITQ^S DUTY OTT 11HY Sir» With reference to corxespond^ooe ending with your letter No. 2502 of 1932 1 dated the 23rd J&gt;eeember 1932, 1 am directed to inform you that the GoYernnent of India hare sanctioned the following tariff Yaluee for dates, dry,imported in bsge i- Baera (Iraq) dates Hs. 10/-/- per Owt. Al 1 other sorts ••••••«•. Re. 5 /r/— per CJwt. these rates were brought into force on the 16th January 19 33 and will ra aln in operation till the 31st Deeerber 1933 - vide Government of India, Co!??nerce Deoartrent. Notification No. 73-?( 106}, dated the 31et llecsr ber 1932. I have the honour to be, lr, Your most obedient servant Sd/- U.&lt;-&lt;. Deputy Seeret&amp;ry to the Ctovemnent of IndiaILL £ity Ofi5ce: 73, Basinghall St., E.CTB; Telephone: Metropolitan, 4713. OREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. II . jr~d' j) s Head Office: ~ - - Jelephine: Victoria 9040. /v /^elegrins: Advantage, Pari, London s- „y wCodes:! Lieberg* A.B.C. 6 ed. &amp;c / m # v,V ■ &gt; DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 27612/1931. Sir, 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.L 12th October, 1931. With reference to India Office letter No. Z/5522/31 of September 17th, I am directed by Sir Eilton Young to request that you will be so good as to transmit to His Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf the accompanying copy of a letter from Mr. Wills of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation relative to the Muscat date trade, which formed the subject of Bushire despatch No.2 Overseas Trade (B) of July 25th last. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, \ UO * I J-a OCT 1931 i\G v The Under Secretary of State INDIA OFFICE. ± DrEft®Id) i; i(lD6mptif i ol v ife5^-teifeneral. Nc f 43 22OCT.'.931 FROM fatCRtTARY, PCLi.ivL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE COPY SENT TO.122, Leadenhall Street, • *v ' i LONDON, E.C.3. - ■ | 2nd October, 1931. V*- 1 ' W&gt; J w' j v** ■! Vv, ^ C V The C ompt roller-General, • — Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, S.W.l. Dear Sir, I have to thank you for sending me for my confidential information copy of Mr. Dowson's report on the subject of date cultivation in Muscat, which I have read with great interest. The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, Ltd., in whom I am interested, have only an Indian in charge at their Muscat office and have, therefore Restricted their activities to steamers agency work at that port. I understand that The Hills Bros. Co., the firm of which Mr. Dowson is a member, have in the past shipped large quantities of dates from Muscat to America, but in recent years, owing to the quality of the dates having deteriorated, they have reduced the quantity. I am paying my annual visit to Iraq this year and will take up the matter with the head office of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd., in Busreh. Possibly they will arrange, when one of their European staff pays an annual visit to Gulf ports, for him to go into the possibilities of their taJcing an interest in the Muscat date trade. Yours faithfully, (Signed) CHAS. WILLS.1 £ INDIA DIRECT °l FOREIGN OFFICE AND BOARD OF TRADE. ^ ^ 2-1 j /f . Office 73, BaUft ghall St. Dne: Metropolit 4713. Head Office: Telephone: Victoria 9040. Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London. CodeST- ^'L1eCn?^/:.'«re:-^ ed. &amp;c. /, » DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS 'tRADB.. j 1 should be addressed to the Comptroller-General quoting 27612/1931 enclosure in w, . No. *43 FROM StORETARY, FUIlT CAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA 0 FFICF c*-*-^**-* LETTER 35 , Old Queen Street, London, S.W.1. nd 28th August,1931. COPY SENT Ti I am directed to transmit herewith for your information a copy of a despatch (Confidential No.D.O.T. (B) 2 ) of July 25th from the Officiating Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf and His Majesty’s Consul- General for Fare, together with copies of correspondence as indicated in the margin of the first paragraph thereof, regarding the possibilities of extending the Muscat Date Trade. 2. I am to enquire whether the Secretary of State for India concurs in a copy of the section of Mr. Dawson’s report on date cultivation (the last enclosure) being confidentiallyconfidentially communicated to Mr. Wills (the individual referred to at the end of paragraph 4 of Major Powle’s despatch). I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, for the Comptroller-General.diiH'14 *, '49MBi^li|t4MNlS j pj • 4^W4 itif i ,. wn • m tl : W , • »■ «f. V • 1 ?• « * -bt' 'i 'J ‘ « ax i i H1 JN4 M# 1 ' .i ' V aM itt fir *f. « ^Trnr^-: -A^vi; .. ► « ■ ♦ « 1 Mr«*' *rs$, # } -...*- i^.v a v : ; ftU t; &gt;i tirtiWMi Mt* /i rr^tM {% ••&lt; ffei 3 &gt;f it# *# #i^bf ai is#«luin#'. -iv&gt; 4«Jt •‘ •• V &gt;■ fl«j&amp;ufteat, 8 th uuvmtwx ivaa. Dear Dawson 9 • • •#•••• I agree with you about the DeaeibiU ties of ext analog of the muscat trade in dates and certainly ir your flm don't do so someone else will do so eventu&amp;Uy, is you hnew, the date tree is found in all parts of the Qaan i-mltanate ana flaurlshes #T#n at an altitude of over 2000 feet. -he chief areas are hatinah, taai hamail acd shardiyan. he yard is grown chiefly in Henail. j.he Mlbsall ie the principal one in isadlyah me. Mhariilyah uticnce it ia exported through 3ur by dhow to iamboy. in the hatinah, the iilantations font an almost continuous belt* soieetimes 7 niles deep* along the coast, t he belt is at least 120 miles long. I here is no tjaestlon about the length but 1 have been unable to trace my reliable authority regarding lie average depth. ^he great valleys on the aewara slope of western Hajar all traver* tiie Batinsdi on their way to the sea, but their courses within the limits of the jaatinah ore often ill- defined and in sene cases their channels are so broten up and dispersed as to render uncertain the point at which they reach the sea. it is probably m the lower reaches of these wadis that the belt reaches its greatest depth. In the valleys themselves, the date palms are grown on terraces. At Masnaah, the groves belonging to the place are 2 to 5 miles deep, uuladah is 7 milesinland south west of ^»aah» !ihe place depends on its extensive date groves which . •.which arc olTidwC only by a narrow watJk fron tiioco ot M&amp;anaah, thlc gives a depth mi to tia: belt of at least 7 ail os as quoted above from another authority. behind tfactan ».pali» there are 4 villages from b to a niles inland all with extensive groves. fvuqaiq ie the tort for the Wadi i^ani uhaflr, Xhe upper portion of the m&lt;i% contain b at least 2b # UUO pal tea aenongst other crops. \ha lower portifm is said to contain the saMe crops so 1 preeune It also containa date paints though know Z do not^/the mnaber. Khaburah is the port for the wadi nawasinah ,^usaf • one hour Inland, CiXit&amp;ins ex enerve groves, xhmt&amp;i l cannot say whether these are contlgous with those of JUiaburah. At least 9 places in the vradl hawasimth have extensive groves. At ^ahaa, th* dates of the place are estlsuued at about 30,000 hut dates are grown in terraces in the wadi Ahum and «ftdl Dhfink behind it. At .soiiar, the Jiatxnah date belt is about 3 Miles deep# on the other side of the hegar range, at ibrl, there le an extensive date grove • stated by one authority to be the Most extensive in a»aA with he exception of aeMail ipresuiiiably also excluding the natmah, which is not in b»an proper). At BariMl, aoue of the be at varletiee of dates are grown, including &lt;uro, iihalas and albsali but they are n A held la equal eetiraatiun with tliose of ^eMail aim nadiyah. Vhe palms are said to mveber about 00,000. ! -k* breadth of the date belt along the natiaaii is governed by the distance inland at which it is economic to work wells by the primitive methods at present in use. Um wells are lb to 20 feet deep. 1 dara say that with more modern methods of pumping water could be obtni ned ecu mini cally at a greater distance free the coast thereby enlarging the area.0 ®0 Miboya dAta wlach are rroa roiiabx# auureeo in my racorda ar« aa ncur as aiiawar aa I can (Jive yon *o t|ueaticna i and 2. i think per*anally ^hat you imve undnreati*** the number of palate. thirdly, a« regaroa prxceo, i encloee a iiet i have received from the cuatorao ehiah you can c&amp;mpare for youraeif# itourthly, you coviJU:. need expert technical advice to answer thie vacation. :piumal atonne in the la.ter part of the cold weather emeep thia coast and l think would wa*»h away anything but the atrongeet cuna ruction, iiowaver a track ha a been made by the Uuacat Infantry from oat rah through Boeher to alb ( avoiding the pace and th© aoft earn on the beach) and I have been ao far aa alb in my car# 2 liave not tried going further as yet but a yord car ha a been as far as lohar am X understand there are no obstacles. fifthly, there could not be political difficulties if the matter were approached properly by the right kind of man bat the Arab is naturally suapt clous and It you started by building a pier he may think you have other motives end resent it. ihe track to the east of hhaourah including masnaah am ruwaik is inhabited by a troublesome tribe the «kal :mad 11 but otherwise the inhabltents are hamless enough. Sixthly, tia dates are there but i do not suppose that you could bulls up am enormous connection such as you contcmpla e all at once, ihe hen las trade throu^ Arab brokers to idioii X believe hey advance money before the productiem of the dates# X do not know etoat you could do by direct methods. As you see# your mutations have not been ae easy to answer as they seemed at first sight. signed u • * .itur phyi*a»ra, 29th i «c«»ber I92ii. Major 0 *j?.Murpli 3 r»I.A. t v^onsul and rOlXXXQal Agont, Muscat* My u«ar »iajor f X laaT« b&lt;sen T«.y huay and delayed to aneeer; but a copy X eent iantAiateXy I got it to our i^o^le in »•* /ork* X here not yet their anewer; but X have m aneeer to a previous letter on the aubjeetj am X unueretenA that the siatter iatereata LhaM» and that they are yrepa- ed to try the ciatee fj^ia the Batina* thia ne^t aeaaon in a aaalx way. :*rofcably ebaXX get our .• to ao ihie for ues hut ♦ in any caae # I ahouXa be glad, if you aouXci keep thie eonfldentiaX, at any rate, untiX we can ooupXete mv arranf. t wo m ». your letter is exactly what X wan wanting* Sbfoia She tiny scrap X saw# arid from \Muit x hav* bean able to read up about Uie Batinah, X was convinced that it was the second Mn biggest date garden in the tvorld. tour letter oonfireis ay belief. But there x« stl^l a tneaenaous lot to find out* befbre we can do arything: very definite. X do not know; but X should imagine our people in new fork would want to know very aueh wore than they do at present* before they sank any aoney in Musca; or its vicinity. 1 have got sqxae leav&lt;* in April; but i have to be back again in Basrah by the end of August. X should muon like to have anu tiier look at the tkaan and the do&amp;at, and think that fron wy point of view* the west useful Uite mouM be the end of duly* when the date harvest should be begun, asI thinJc l will viait Muscat tiwn, tsar taking a trip the axxa, U&gt; a gAJLMpae ui’ ao. tht tsuoan. X ahoult* lik« to do very MuaU is to taJtt a itord alon^ ^ne aiioXc length of the hatlnah; hut X fe*r that rai^ht toe rather expeneive. it the company thoMtfht Xt worth aiiXXe to pay lay «xi&gt;enoee t then X ahtaiih try anci do that; out» ii the Coapany would not pay ay ex*«nsQe t then X should toe able to afford only a tionkoy, and 2 would got as far aa 1 could with ttut. 2 do not ihlnk 1 would attempt the interior; because the dates there arc acre scattered* and because of the political difficulties, xou* X expect* will not be in iluacat la July, tout if you could leave a word with the nice old *ali ©i Matrah that you would toe obliged, if he would give sac one of thia sualliwa^B as a guide and give ne his toleaslttg* then, i think, a^l would toe well* X heard yesterday that U»ic is now a ♦ora agent in Muscat, la that so? and, if so, what is ills rauae, that I my get into touch with hln ? iiuw ot-es one manage for petrol along the isatinah ? carry it with one ? ihat should not be difficult. Xt would stean lugging along about five tins, X suppose. fou are no doubt familiar with hajor dill’s note on Malaria in Muscat. X reau it wiicn it was first publiahea; tout,then 2 wanted to rertab it a little while ago, X found it was out of print in ^nglarui. mx i got a copy from India, and it has Just arrived, uls adscript lor of the cl lisa te is so documented, so calm, so free from exaggeration that 2 feel tempted to say to myself * bet the dates of Muscat steam in their own juice !*c on of Mr u'oaBoii * b report on Ua« m ************ m*** mm*m*mm* *m*m^*m*****m *m ******** m*mm* ^ *m ******** ** j'auna i;lorft 9 Goo logy ftc*t of tlio parte of tiu; Batlnah vial ted dj/ hlia in 1927 • Ag:ri culture # 7he principal industry of the literal and of the Interior is date growing* feherever there be water*the datepalm is grown* Xtis thcfirstax crop to be oiatiyatedfthe others with the possible exception of wheat and barley,follow and profit by the palr^e shade* icbour * Colonel lilies gives the following tribes as cult* ivators of dates-*Bani All,Ban! Bu Ali,Beni Battash^AJL Kabus,Al KaJ- riyin and Al Ibriyin*More often thannot the date gardens are the pro perty of absentee lords* In the caseo,they are genex’ally not far ab sent,since most of them live in the villages whichfonu the oases - centres, in winter hero also the cultivatoto live,though in summer they remain In the gardens* Many of the owners of Batanah date* gardens livo i&lt;v Muscat or Matrah or in other of the larger coast towns A big landlord is called hankari* 2&amp;lak is not understood,but KAI’AL ^Aol is irequently cpohen cf• fhe actual, cultivation when not carried out by the peasant propri«tor,Bardhul,pi. BeiMdhil,« word also Waning a lazy fellow* ia in the hands of a paid labourer,the Bidar,corre«» ponding with the #alah of the Iraq,enjoying less security of tenure tiian that provided ty the faabah tenancy of that oountxyfor t-ha Mauri si of the Punjab*In the Wadix ^axoayil every Bidar reoeives,at date harvest one bunch of dates from each palm irrespective of the number of bunches borne* In the Da t an ah on the other hand he never receives dates but nearly always money, some times money with food or with food and clothes* In both districts,fruit other than dates i*? the exclusive property of the garden owner. There must be an limmnse amount of pilfering however* Fallen fruit is the tenants right*The provision ofoff shoots,fruit tree* and irrigating cattle and the food of the latter is on the owner*Lucerm seedand thnt of wheatand barley are also provided by the owner who take* fouraflfths of the crop from tht former and nine-tenths of the crop of ine tefo latter* ill lie t is usually grown on the same terms as lucerne but not invariably so*Truck and minotcrops are sown with the tenant’s seed and are his own property* The amount in cash which a *%tanah ^&gt;idar receives,in the cases where no food and clothes are received is about . ive ialot a month* This was the oom ionest figure given in reolv to questions*but an old man at Al Hi said he got fifty Rial a year and two younger fellows with him said they each got forty Mini* A garden nenr ^umais was looked after by a small boy and a Joung man, the former gov v Rial a month plus food and the latter % Rialat plus food.Aadnim a merry and well spoken half negro half arab lad working in the warden of oaiyid Muha»ned got 4 Hi ala t a month in addition, to food and clothing but he seemed to be a favourite with the old iaan*Pood is Mererallv ^ reckoned being wotth i Rial a week* if then the average wage for a tatanah Bidar be only 60 Rial a year as the other emoliments are the Saras ss those oi the wadi Gamoyil*,it might be supposed that 60 Rial is the value of one bunch of dates froia every palm in the averare holding of a ^smayil Bidat* If one bunch per palm be equivalent with one-eigth of the crop,the total crop would be worth on this basis 480 •*£*** dat ~ at 50 Rial a hahar,the total production would be a little less than 10 Bahax # or 16,520 lb*This amount of dates Lhaht be produced on 16b palms or about 3 acres of garden* Actually all the mt- anah tenants appear to prefer to be paid as in the basyil,so it may be pr« B uwd that the rata of pay !• highar ttaara and that tUe area of ..amayll holtiing ia graatar than auggeatad above. Iliatbthie presumption ia oorract la borne out by the other,rough oboervstions,v.hioh indloate that the Jnayll holding la nearer 4 or 6 aorta than 3. in tna however the area la nearer 2.In the latter district, thi ten^t W raise all the Irrigation water from wellailn the former,theater 1 *«Iiao»t entirely i-rorlded Uy flowing springe jconbo^uenUyth* cultlTetoi- can manage a greater area. a bad year, tne -awy cultivator stands to loee. rrobebly liere ; in the high wage rate computed with the lower, but f 1 *?* *'* wag-, rate In the Satanah..further the wage rote in ^h dlati icte le fixed by long cue tom; the drought muat have oaueed tlie tfrloee of agricultural produce,Including dates to rise. Mono* a oultlva paid In kind would be likely to be temporarily at least better off than one rccetaving a money wage* Cultivation y.d implomaiita. ^ ^ 1b Ugbt 8and vyia vm i# no clay though i^algra^e menttonB the exiat^^cv . single fc«d of pottery clay near the coast not far from latrah** Drainage is excellent and there is no alkc11 land if the align! amount nowhere a rank growth of weeds and cultivation is otfe the scantiest and ahalloweat* one who is used to an Dnglieh spade smiles at the ilishah of the Iraq* H» would lawgh aloud anl long at the similarly n med implecient of Oman* Iti indeed maaiablea ocr a weed stubher than a spade* Plate xxv* Ihe Ml shah held hy a hatatoah Cultivator* There ks no hard clay to be turned over no aoddentbwkdd, iron bound land to be broken up nor are any deep channels to be dug out* The chief use of the spade is to dam up the tiny water course#,in turn as each bed by irrigated* The plough Hlttsa, Jtadd&amp;n not understoe is also absurdly small and light and made of wood ironntipped.lt is drav?n by one cow or bull*if plo ughing be by contract and Urn be but a small piece of land to be ploughed containing only a fe .palms the usual rate is 5 r&amp;i a palm,the plough,plough animal# and labour being all provided by the Contractor. This rate is equivalent to about a dial for an aore*generally however if muck land is to be ploughed,a bargain is struck fox' the whole piece* The third implement is the %l^Si&gt;,whic is similar to the long kind ofMIH/U&amp;HEH orMIHJAL of the Iraqithal is it is long only slightly curved,toothed siokle uaedin the Ire only for pruning palms,but in uman also for Cutting fodder,ajdUkl labourax reserved in the Iraq for the smaller more curved Minjal Miqass is scissors in tne Iraq- A H13 a long chisel for separating of 1 shoots from their parents,completes the list of agricultural implements# In the adi i&amp;mauil the si 21 of a man 1 holding is computed from the number of palms it contains* The uij units of area, PIDDAH,&gt;IAI&gt;liUiAH,;&gt;U»ALAii,JAKIh,or DAUhAh,appear unknown* In the Batanah however the garden fruit is the j**i pi* Tawaian,so called presumably in reference to the stone built we] This is the amont of date garden watered by on« tingle or double water hoist*Three of these,at ^ib,belonging to Ldiaikh Kaehid,we3 surveyed,with the following resuit-Pi aring off sixoois 'VruiT bairns trees '‘jfotal ' fdtaT vpprox* Palms Palme &amp; Area* off shoots off shoots In &amp; pruit Acres. Trees JUDoubl* 44 137 69 181 250 3* 3* Single* 13 81 33 94 116 1 »/3 C•Single* 94 0 38 94 132 H. Average 38 Reckoning A ae 2- 1 ■' Sa “ 92 Izi 12/%.I '-J—■ - tlil* yart of ttlb it* said to oonteixi more fruit# troee «sp«olaI3^ u&amp;n&amp;ovu than any other i^art of the feitaxmiu iianoo the incidence of date palme micht be xojocted to be low#.ei a talk from ’lib towards idimietthe nwtiomra of bearing palme in vorboue ihviun nlona the oad oare counted rou^ily* Xhejr* we*e a» foliaw*i 2)# Double Hoibt 300 bearing pc^liae# D* single 800 do Y* do 150 do 0* Double 300 dO H* ringle 175* do 1* do 100 do* J. do 4 do* iC* do 60 dC* h* do 60 do* k* Double 400 do* Average 13b* iieokoning 2)»Ot and U a* two ea oh* aiyid baifiiu the all of Dibyoonaidared the average number of paImw in a wingle fawi aa «i00« iJut thle ****** an over eatl»nite#A fi^uren nearer 100 uould seem mx* likely wltn the averidpi number of aoree In the lt*wl aa two and tije average epaoing of palaa 30 feet jswijt*eaoh way* ^he earn* Inforsaaxit considered that the irrigation of the fawi ooat the owner 100 ^iftl a yeaTydO for the didar and 40 far the bull! but uoet people considered tlm -all ao expensive aa the imiuhatiiclntng that it ooata 120 lilal a year to water and Iqj after 100 bearing ahna#and re kouing the yield per hatanak palm ae 75 lb then the ooat of producing dates without any eliarge for aup^rviaion interest on capital or for taxes vorka out aa 0*95 cent* per pound* One tenth ofvthe groae crop la aOppoeed to be rendered aa goverarsent tax*fhe net return of each pain to the grower thus become 67-5 lb*# so the ooat of producing dates without reckoning anything for In terse on capital or for supervision become 1*60 cents a the aver age priee of dates in the iatanah gardens caring the season be 40 dial a jonx h bar# the price per pound is l*4oent» allowing 0*34 cents between the coot and the selling price ef a pound* Young mature patoae of good varieties well bearing cost nothing up to 100 iiial each|so perhaps a fair average price for a *awi might be 5000 i\ial*3o count In nothing for superviaion# the Interest on invested capital in a ^tanah date garden nay be t bout 9*86 &gt; or 26 30ft per iawl per annum*from date Auxiliary crops add to this re turn* as noted later lucerne con be p prof i table •Fruit brings In sone thing# though prices are low*i4cngoas at 5ib were selling at 850 for a dal last •rune*24LMaa were selling at about the same price in the t.adi amnyil at the time* Ihs water hoist used to irrigate the lawl is of the ordinary Arabian typs*fhs water la about 80 feet below the ground level from AU Hil to kub&amp;1*| so probably acy be at this depth all along the uatanah* ihs vsrMaal supporting hoi etc are usual lly made of palm logs sawn longitudinally In two* ihey are strong and smooth*In other date producing centres the palm logs are the wor^t of building wood#fer the reason that the internal fibres are loose an and tear out*Xo plane suoh a log is like trying to plane a bath lufah the water is dropped from the bucket on to a masonry collsoUrn troiui t ta ? no&lt;l J** 1 though • Iiubaidiaxy teithlnc tank into th* min otorng. tank. '«»• It resaino until Um m.&lt;kur be.a finiufcod Jwlntimul* Uion unjlu^n vont In th* tank aad oocupiae hiiaaalf In dlatrtbutlnr tli» nater.n# lit arawlng wator from be for* the paleut at rank of dn«n to Lunrx^e#.and from early afternoon to suneet*rerhaps he and his bull work about eeven hours a day at tills labour* in all the i^tanaii there ytar tSt#^^ 0 /tt0#r mn miA xmmM an ^ 8 ® 1 * ®« ehployed year in and gl*ta^garl. A a*tor -itoi» t_»t -ifuiah . To uoatoni iOoaa the fcaatagu #f *«» ^ aniJatt:animal power is appaling*V»hat of course is wanted is a crude dielectric power station at Khaburah to supply a high voltage line the whole strength of the Bata ah.There might be five main reduction station and each group of fifty Tawian coul£ have secondary reduction station each Tawi would have a meter, a I.H P. motor a rheostat and a i inch centrifigul pump all buil£ as one unit under one cover. The Bidar would switch onnthe current the water would flow to him all he would have to do would be to direct the flow .Being received of the labour of having to r a is the water,he could spend time improving the cultivation of the land and in growing cotton ground nuts sesamum and other prof itable ground crops instead of leaving the land nearlt bare as now. But of course such a scheme will not materialise un under the present regime. Bven in the capital Maskat a twon possessin 9 climate considered by most visitors £o be more unpleasant in summer than that of any other town in the Bear ^aaVor Par A aS t. £*e are no electric lights fans or ice mac&amp;ines. . However what is feasible in the Batanah is the inbtalj-ation oi either small oil engines and pumps or else mil]l iaere is a sea b»eeze by day and a land breeze by night.The we] and tan^s are already installed.The size of the Tawi is not toe big fox a wina mill to irrigate. Whatever mechanical means were employed to raise the water the stumbling block would by the capital expenditure required. However if some windmill firm wei ,0 estabUsh itselin the Batabah and would be aptient in oollec - to buy 6 V” ^ ? laI1 4 8 Pr0babl y peop l e =°uld be indl to ouy. Windmills are used for irrigating small area date aardf been^ ^nr a V ear A +? n &lt; a Tarious Places in Algeria and have been introduced recently into Bahrein and Amarah in the Iraa.H( P« r si“rind not n °^ the » r WayB Unle8B com Pelled by econ&lt; pressure.Andnet always tnen. Nevertheless if the bigger land- +? brought to see that their irrigation if now cos' ing them tentimes what it could cost them they might make the annufliy * 116 Argentine is bu y in S windmills at the rate^jf 16000 „ 4 . « a ^ 0ne double water hoist r a isednthe level of +• a ter in a tank,200 feet by 24 feet one and a half inches in hand „d hour.On. single water hoist may be exacted therefore raise 375 gallons of water an hour.A half inoh.centrifua-ul mi» F.sF . the palms would probahlv receive mnr* Wat * r •a&amp;ier to come comparable with that of palms i„ the Wadi ^iTmi’ght^lult big euphorbia(?) bushestsL^kar“bornetimes“a*r a i 1 Palms at 20 feet intervals a - d r alling is made of chestnut fencing.To alio °a - s nr “ Ilnis ° ent 01 English eplit out cattle a rS gate In thfrafL &lt; . Pe ft Stria ? s but to * kee pftles and two uprights and once i- a hi° f tbr3e 01 aoaoias(they migh^haYe been Mtfk“busi e t'hif 1 ?^ W ^ re th * was encountered. Da aa &gt; hid bbe palms,a sti] Irrigation. ing the life bloodfof th» e T a wi i ha* ;i bfI all i aS i &lt; t vi S the heart PJ out the Batanah i. Lard t^lSntire a suggestion that th# axles mig, t o c oil^^.b 1 ' 6 °f th * pu;Lli, ‘ noisty wheel was better .Allan in n^ le&lt;i the repl y s a l ne tha in Huf Huf. ° e t 9 p »Ahzain.Major Chessman had the same re. Jr, .,J, „ t!. in ■ these are flooded masonry dam- are oocassions w] «.«.«.». , Ih . r z.xand the water instead of ru&amp;Mxig to the sea Is held up and sinks into the ground irrigating the land and augmenting the subsoil water. In the Wadi Haxnayil and in other wide an seen in the interior with the exception of a little water provided by water hoists to the drier parts of the oases all the itrig- ation water is from springs. The water from thses springs would flow under ground and never be seen were it not that under • ground channels have been constructed with gredients less than those of the wadii. beds above them.At a distance from the spring! varying its depths and with the relative slopes of the channel and the wadi the water is brought to the surface .At this point the oasis begins,and continues until there is left no more wate: to irrigate the palms-.buch an artificial underground water course is called ^'alag.ln Morocco such a one is called JTugarah in Persia anat. Wells are first sunk in KHDouadtibuoi line at intervals varying from ten to thirty feet and then the connectic are established between them#The labour of constructing these channels with a cro.. bar as the only implement is considerable. The interior of the channel is cemented with a mixture of lime and plaster of Paris.Some the channels date from remote times probably, but new ones continue to be made..lt may be that chans channels are more numerous now thi.n formerly but it is more probable that the new ones do no more than take the place of old ones dried up or filled in. In a Palag under construction at Mlsfah al Aliy ah# a well about 20feet deep had been sunk by four men in six days. The main channel of a big spring where it issue from the ground may be two feet wide and two feet deep.i^uch channels were half full in June.aaall effluents are constructed and the ultimate braitchea in the gardens are no more than six inches wide and four inches deep.The elope of these smallest distributaries is reckoned as three fingers aohundred cubidsfawt or rathei’ more than 1 in 1000.The surface channels are construct* of the same sort of cement* as those beneath the ground that is of a mixture of lime and plaster of Paris.A rough foundation is first madeof cemented pebbles.The lime is prepared by burning the rounded limestone pebbles which abound onnthe surface and jui under the surface of the wadi bed acid in the conglomerate of the hi 11s.The piaster of Paris is prepared by burning a reddish eart3 which is widespread after this has bten puddled with vqUr and dried in the sun in cakes. Juch a profusion of calcium sulphate in the soil must be particularly benefioient to agriculture.in that it neutralises toxicity of much of the harmful chloride of cne alkali me tala* It it: certainly a fact that date palms never si seem to do so well as inwell drained districts where the water i^ ^lentilul find where the' soil is rich in gypsum given of course the climatic oonditionds are suitable.In Algeria,in the Wadi buf ar# as the -lench to call it#the Cued ^oud#calcium sulnhal and water are as plentiful as in wadi hamayil and drainage is as goodiand the date palms are perhaps the only ones in the world which approach in vigot those of the bam* il.Gypsum is known as baruq.Jus of the Italian Gesso is not understood#nor is the Persian Gach. Water rights are inherent in the property rijhtQ.Tj.e price of a garden is always inclusive of that amount c •ft, wa ^ er ;° which it is entitled by ousto m.The customary rotatic of water to the gardens is exactly adhered to and disputes which are rare are referred to the shaikh for deoi si on. bom* gardens are watered as often as every four days but the interval varL ^ to a maximum of eighteen days. In the gardens# which /ret suah infrequent waterings pits are dommonly dug round the pelm* «=io th the greatest amount of water may be obtains^ i. don* 1„ the drier garden* of\he Ilg^rian WBt8rlns 88 J atej B and Pate ;■jlBtrUmtlon W* Incljt&lt;iaa£» the oaeee of u»«n »r« *catt*r«d al&lt;wig tlM b«du of thf vator cour«o««Vftter f ao noiod above i» B^ppliod ground channale leading from »ouroe* taigtaar of « ttadi-Mov mny oaooo aro tharo in oU mboh i» diffiou.it to oonjootui Prom the «c»uth of tha ^odi {-aiaiaril at *4b ••^ 8 ® Hub a diatanco of about 40 nil**$%)*** *** about o ^ group of Palme at LiuwU bo ooaoidorod an ono# fho braalloot onoo • *g. alHoduriyah probaoly oontaln no ?*»r« than iQiaudhtPln Jah# Bidbid, and -orur probably contain about &amp;&gt;0Qk) ±ulmx ealb* Tho ro*a&amp;ing two Ira oaaoa any bo put down at m suo«» at an avo ago of $000 pa la* oaoh* 2ho total palae in the valla} ^ and including Hub thoroforo aay bo oatimatod roughly a® &lt;sbout #i40t 000* ?or purpoao of cowpariaa it ay b* aoniionad timt th* number of date palms on ins lx ail port ion of the basuco of Wie uu.. Aradi is about 70UOOUO# hira faapy date palas there art oc j tween i*ub an dabal Akhahar is not known* It i* probalt tmiothey art lt»fc than below ,ittb* But the la&amp;i ^asioyil though it is certainly the richest in p^laa of soy of the (bam widyan yet it is only one of the forty such lying between lias A&amp;sendaa and has al Hadd *and most of those probably contain soiae. palms* it is hasardous to conjecture what is the total papulation of hion*excluding the coaat but 1000000 is a itorc or lessintelli^nt ^piess* If the coastal region be included the number of palms Mght amount to U # bOOOOOO for date palms grew a 1 &lt;juc the in a oontinous belt from ■**‘1 Ittl to w»uhar*^nly first twelve miles of this belt os ginning at A 1 ^1 ere been* but sveral and reliable infotnunts state that this portion ia typical of the whole* £lm average width of the palm belt was generally put do*n at a mile* *o allow for pardoiable lowsl pride half a mile has been considered the width dor the purpose oalsulution* fhs leng of tom belt of 100 miles is verifiable fro^ the mep*$ljus the con clusion sppests that the Bstanah date gar,tone cover bO square ml lew They contain orobably tbs third biggest palwery in the world f Basrah ana 'iafililt being bigger* In these rtly ro\«gh ecloulations» the number of palms per acre is xeokoned st yO*ln the Wadi &gt;ai^yil»the palm are so big ttmt if they were closer that 30 feet to each other the fronds of neighbouring palms would greatly intermingle*ln the £$tsnah the palms arc less vigorous and in the gardens whs re there are nc fruit they are frequently at closer intervals* However in consideration of the large number of fruit trees at the southern en of the belt of the bare clearings amongst the palms and of the un cultivated condition of mpy oi the fawian»aO bearing palms per aor&lt; for the Uncle arcs is probably not too low* Xhs date gardens of the todl vifuaayil are remini ©cent of south More cos the rocky pictureaqu* scenery tlw white cloths© and Imuat the plastered irrigating chaniie: the underground streams and the Uish l^alsk* for *now do you do 9 art oommon to both* And if the uamsyilh be like Morocco, then the 3atana) has points of res* bianco with tns : hattal -xrab district the long oontlnous strip of palms between water and a salty plain and the potponderating Influence of the date palm on the life of the people&lt; But then the eleaking of the water hoists quio ly rewinds one he i^ far from Jla&amp;rah 9 * tidal irri^ation.ri^re are picturesque thickets of burner*Ohaf and other trees where palms art lost to vl*w*one al* meet expects fairies to a^ esr*But the weather is probably too hot for them* She ever iwmrd of a sweaty fairy .Per nape though there aro_ jlau* urn a previous page the cultivation of a date garden has been noticed and the implemtmte, there for* it w- s stated that cne of the reasons cultivation was slight was the lightness of the 0 Cll*Amother is that weeds are few there being no water to spare for theawOne labour the Umani has,which the Iraqi has not is the reweal of surface stones* As in all places where date palms are grown cok ereicUy In Oman they are grewn from off ehoots* fhe$ are plant* out when still quite small half the sise usual in Iraq^i^rhaps in@r ( 3 °\ Xraq»n big about i* wiotooafytb® /tbati foot injggr bit u^nuatli tbc curfaco saXt« 50 to 7 b 2* ^id to Burviva# rtaf aocrli# Ypuilg_lb^ &gt; illob Those owl! shoots mre box* tin** planted in nursery beds^ ;albah # ialbat. They nre Much !••« WfoJ?i»«d up I those of the Iraq probably beeedoe ivinter in the ha tana ii mut near the ooadt brlngu no frost and because in suK&amp;aer then is no or less tearing raging scorching blasting dust l&amp;dent Iraqi Zhvml the wiSd from the burnt up desert* 2he off « shot* are planted nearly always in pi to .Perhaps this is beeai the pits provide ehelterfperhaps beoause the roots get nearer the sub-soil water but more XiireSy It is »t that the roots an buried firstly inuthe light soil and are anchored against high winds.Kony are the pains seen supported by palm buttroase ; oruetimes a palm likely to fal is held in place by a stone w« wall four feet high and six feet in dia&amp;feter.The space between the boll end the val is filled in with raid ed earth* •&gt;n the whole planting is leas regular than 1 in the thatt &amp;1 ^rab district though in some gardens tthe ^clma art se t rightly et the corners of equ^ res«The unevenebs of the land luay be conti ibutaxy cause of Irregular planting though it sa&amp;e exoute does not held for the jfet&amp;nah* The price of off shoots of most of the ooim men varieties is twenty or thirty r&amp;l or about 5c each*but ifaradh off shoots coarmnd twice th#t* zz-VUi: on- »*&gt;.;%* wlnntfd in yltB In a 3* A aoeding la known as j^uhmln the Iraq a ceedlxH» io known as Xftqalahfwhile in Jbroooo»AIger 1 a axiu Tunisia in addition to this woedfithalt is also used* Honoring is practiced, ^aioel dung is the favourite application* xer* Popence states that manuriiig is &amp;nnu*l*iil*touh? states that fish effd is used for manure* Proi what the preaent writer observed after , the goats foewatdonkeys and act the Urteks vcuiu say ; other birds had finished with the fish#there remained very little offal*in horta Africa and thru the date palm sons to morale* the dead fronds are out off olose and distally to the swollen base* in a tears time the swollen base now hard and dry is out of olose to the tnuik sad used for firewood* In Oman the swdllen base is not out off per perhaps be cause the humr nd other tress provide anywhere abundant fuel»uliallarly in the Punjab the bases are left on th palm*In California also the frorid bases were not out until re eentlyu^ome apprenoion was felt when It was observed that roo' were growing out of the trunks undernttetii the frond bases»and were pushing the latter off»*rora what appeared in the 1 adl^ami where roots oeuld be found cossuouly fou&amp;id pushing off the from bases to a height of six feet from the ground»this root produc is not harmful to the palm.The frond abses once pushed off t tl* aerial roots dzy up end drop off* The trunk is called Oaridah when alive but when dead and cut up for the carpenter it is mm chilled warduah* In the Iraq dadhuah lo the trunk alive or dead while Jarldah is the frond midrib*(;f*the district of the Jorid in Tunisla*The frond in the *aUi ‘'mosyil is vurah pl« iuj The vigour of the -anayil palms is a*tcun&lt; trig* The average height is half as high again as that of the Iraqi palms fronds twenty long are com* on and trunks were seen which looked three feet in diameter, though they were not meast And there are the palms which have been subjected to a uime years* draught*u&amp;ny palms in the drier parts cf the oases him died but not a large portion cf the whole*Plate xxix* Dt&amp;d palr-i^ in the QaBia of Mlltgali al Aliyaiif fit wIW terraced ‘Wheat land in foreground# Almost all the palms in the oasis of Miltqah al Aliyah have died|a great many are dead in Al Amqat and some are dead in Sifalsh*Ghubrahti£hunar*AwainBt#Hasa8fSarur f and Miltqah al Hadariyah* yfria ygyictT^i Plate xxx. The oasis of Miltqah al Hadaryiah at the juncti of 1 the hadi Samayil and the Wadi al Gailah where a quarter of the palms have died of drought. Por this cause and exodus of the people to hanaibar is said to have occurred*their levelihood in the Omai being gone. An informant said that one male was planted to every ten feme lee .From observation melee would seem much less frequent than this.One to fifty females appeared znearer the truth. A female palm which in any one year may not b&lt; bearing is called Hai. In the Iraq it is either so called or else Hail. ;DateA of ripening. In Matrah and Masqat on the 3rd of June then was* available and had been for some days Naghal Hates half way between Khalal and hatab.These had come from Batahah. Unripe dates are green*when they reach full size the green colour of the skin changes to yellow or red or red and yellow The flesh is still fimuMany varieties of dates in this stage are edibdd though there is still so muoh precipitated tanin in others that they cannot be eaten t until a later stage of ripening be reached- Hates at this stage of ripening are known as Khalal innthe Iraq but as Bistr in Oman and in Jforth Afrixa. Katab dates are those which have developed beyond the Khalal stage and the flesh has softened.The dates are now syrupy and sticky.On further drying the dates become Tamaa firmer and darker thanthe Hatab.In Ctoan Tamarare called aar Dates picjed up in the Katab stage go bad in a few days in the Tamar stage they keep for ever, if protected from insects, because of the high sugar concentration.In the samayil on the | 7th June Khalal were common and had been so far for over a week, but they had not become to soften into ^atab.It was not until the first week in July that any i^halal were seen in in the Basrah market.Thesewtre Hailawi selling at eight annas a huqqah 1. e. 6.4 o a lb. The earliest dates in the w a di ^amayi are thus six weeka earlier than the earliest in Bascfeh. In the Butanah they are probably two months earlier.lt is stated that Oman has Khalal and Katab dates for five months in the year beginning with Nagal and Qx-sh Batash and ending with the I winter varieties of Khisab and Hilali.In Basrah the season is between four and five months long beginning with Braim and ending with Khasab. J &amp;Qked Dates . There is a great trade in cooked Bisir in the Iraq called Khalal Marbukh in Persia Jiharak the Mabasli b&amp;rietyis that which is most commonly cooked but there are man many other varieties amongst which are the Batni and the Uxani The export of these cooked dates is almost all to India and they and other (Braim and Ghichhab) from Basrah can be found in most North Indian bazaar*. fltti xxxi. Furnace for cooking Bates at SifalaiuThe four Pillars are designed to support a roof over the cooking pots to the left is the chimney. Diseases. In the Batanah the majority boils are 9 iore or less scored with borer holes and in some cases are half eaten away. 5hr i tranyohus . the wei ling red spider waswitlxorarely mostn ooMnionly in tiie dry noitue^n enu oi Khubar. &amp; d«aaea39 oalled Maraq was v/ell linoA?n bu«- no alflicated palms i?ere seen* I was said that a *ioney 1-t. ^ substance covers the date bunches and spoils them. rigid. The yield of palms this year in the v,adi saiaayil is - probably twice that of those in the biatt al ^ab di^trioj If 501b a palm be tha average yield par pain in the latte, location in the fonaer.it might be put at 100 lb end in the Bstenah at 75 lb. The commonest number of spadices or if 1111 bunohhs Asqah.pl.Asaq in the Iraq Athqah and Athaq.in the Semayil was 9. The average per palm was perhaps 6. In the Batanah there were gardens where the yield eppeared truly extraordinary .In some of these particular gardens no pal* 1 had less thah 12 to 15 buncehs and each wopld have weighed about 151b* In the very best gardeJas of Basrah also there are palms. Hallawi which are stated to produce 1501b of fruit annually* A hundred palms such as these would produce more sugar in an acre than is produced by the same area of the finest sugar cane grown under optimum conditions*.&amp;hat is the total yield of dates as cooked Bisir andas bah is a question for the solution of which data are of the scantiest* If the previously suggested figures for yield and numbers provisionally accepted than the 2*500000 palms oearing each i 85 lb of datee would give a total production of about 950000 tons. But to be on the cautious side it would be as well to assume that the other vallies not xeen are drier and less productive than the Samnyil. that the northern end of the Batanah is less flourishing than the southern and the average yield per palm over the whole country is nearer say 60 lb per palm than 85. On this basis the total produoyion would anount to 670000 tons but a remark is appended to show that these customs house figures represent about half the actual total report.That was before the reorganization of the Maskst customs.There is a large export to the interior, if one may I it.but probably greater than either the land or sea export, is the local demand. Bates enter more into the diet of the populace than they do in the Iraq since wheat and barley are not grown on a large scale and rice not at all* Price. The price dates were selling at last year when the crop was considered short*varied in the gardens from 39Kial a Bahar for Umm Billam to 50 or 60 Kial for Barash and Jtfabab i.e.from 1c a lb to 2 last year the high Basrah prices ^erha affooted the Oman market. Pecking. Khalal and Hatab q«re transported in circular protection made of palm fron midribs tied together with pqlm fibre t^ine.These protectors ^re a foot long and six inches i diameter and are open at both ends.The dates are inserted and &amp;he ends plugged with palm fibre.Lif. Such a protective con tainer is called Mishan-About 20 such containers are packed in anopen long squat basket of woven palm leaflets J&amp;husB know asMarhakjah.The mouth is closed with palm fibre twine.The whole weighs snout 14 or 15 Mask at Man or about 125 lb. Two • such baskets is a donkey load as 1001b.Four such baskets are camel load. Plate xxxii. Ahishab dates are usually packed Khasaf*baskets of woven palm leaflets open at the end only for the insertion of the dates.Once the dates are inside the end is closed permanently.lt is in the containers such as these that dates*: stored.These IChasar are longer and flatter than those of the Iraq and hold rather more. The coBKion sizes are made to hold 10 liaskat Mqn and 20 Maskat Man*It might be thought that the Batanah where palms are so abundant would have provided all t containers for its own dates and more*but actually there is a large import of Khasaf from the Bamayil at about 8 Rialat a 1®0 or 5c eafcbxx because the leaflets of the bamayil palms ar are so much long wide and strong than those of the Batanah palms. Varieties. The Barehi palm was seen at bamayil.The fronds sue fine and graceful the leaflets fine long and feathery.The42. The General appearance of the palm is reminiscent of the Dairi and Khadhrawi of the Iraq, The fruit is somewhat sperical and juicy*The palm v&amp;s not found at A1 Hil» A small date called Katni was seen as hardly ripe Khalal in iiatrah market*4»6,k:7 It is said to be exported to India as hhalal JMaybukh* It is considered inferior* Bilaq is found in Lamnyil and in the Batanah* The fruit stalks are orange in colour* Birni palms are very common in Al Aliy ah and less si) in the Batanah*The fruit stalks are bright yellow*The date is long and thin and was still green the first week in June*It is considered a good quality date* 3u H&amp;ringe is found at bam&amp;yil and in the Batanah* The karadh palm is the corraonest in the sever miles of the oasis of Al Aliy ah Saifalah Hhubrab Khubas where it may perhaps constitue one third of the palms*It is said to be one of the three commonest at kinjah and Khaudh*but in the Batanah it is hardly to be met v/ith.The fronds stand well up nor bend but they are not numerous* The date ie small and dark redeish brown* The stone is small the flesh firm, and the skin not easily broken* The flavour is strong.The harvest is not very early for Oman being in the early part of August near the coast but at the end of that month further inland* The date is the only one shipped to America in large quantities* This trad is old established as there are records of as many as four shi calling for these dates to take tnem to America in the year 18 1876*In 1884 the exports of America are first shown seperately by the Custom authorities.The export however appears never to have reached £000 tons* and the average appears to be half tha amount.The total crop within a radtus of two days donkey joum of Matrah probably does not exceed 3,500 tons, kor 1900 the price of Faradh dates was only slightly higher than that of th other dates exyorted.liecently however the average export price of Faradh dates has been double the average price of the total dates exported* The American export is nowadays contained in 1 121b boxes nine of which are packed up in case*The rejects fro: the packing are shipped to India* Plate xxxiii» k a radh palms near Al Aliyah Market* Athtrab tree on right. Hatihmi is a large palm at fcamayil Hamhl dates are small* Handbal or ^ash Handbal palms grown at ^amayil a: in the Batanah* Plate xxxir* A Handbal palm at Miefah Al AliyaluThe untrimme* frond bases orm be seen*On the right is a terrace wall of this excellently terraced oasis* Basas Palms ware common to the badi and Batabah Hilali palms common to both countries. It is an &lt; even later ripening date than Khabad.The quality ib good. Jabri was found at **ib. The Khalas is an important date variety* It is common in the Wadi barneyil*but noe were seen innthe Batanah* The p&amp;lm has a bushy head* The excellent quality of the dates is everywhere recognised# The colour is fine reddish brown. iJiamari palms are the third commonest at Al Hil, The dates are early and the Khalal yellow* The iOiesab palm which is found as far north as iBaghdad innthe Iraii,i8 one of the four couirdonebt Yarieties in A1 Aliyah is corcnon et Ghallah and is present in the Batanah. It is said to be £hjduI the corainonest variety at hakhal# The fronds are upstanding.The leaflets are more at right angles in the midrib than are these of the Khineili.The whole appearance of tne palm is more feathery than that of lithe Faradiu'ihe pelm does not bear *o heavily a® the Fareclh. nlthough the latter dates are more expensivi It isbtht latest date to ripen with the exceptidn of Milali. Tho kahlal are a fine dull carmine and appearing in the groves when th* other dates jpve long been out are striking. Last year’s Tarnar wen to be obtained in Matrah market this June. {China!zi palms were found at Gallah end at A1 Hil.The red Jhalelwere in the Hatrah market on the 4th Of June.The fronds are outetsnding.The leaflets are somewhat closely appressed to the mid rib. The dates are said to be excellent. There are Lazad palms in the wadi iiamayil but none were seen in the Betanah#The dates were green early in June. The Katab t are siad to be good# The ?Jlabasli variety is one of the four coim.'ionest in A1 Aliyah. there are a few palms at A1 Mil# and it ib said to be one of the three commonest varieties at Khaudh.lt is said that it is the oc-mruonest variety at Wadi M&amp;awil*It can claim to be one of the leading varieties of Uman and for export.Almost the entire crop if not all is 2 aade into cooked Li&amp;ir and it is in that form that it is exported.lt is a dearer date than iChasab. The Madulki variety is found in the Wadi and at Al Hil# The Minzif was seen in the Wadi and at bib though not a J Al Hil.The palm is Hallawi like with long thin fronds.The dates w&lt; were still groen the first week in June rather nerrow and rather long. Mizmag palms were seen at Al Hil uhallah and many in t3 Wadi Samayil.There are palms called Mi&amp;mag Al Bahar and others called mizmag Al Uman but these are thought to refer to the same variety.The Khalal are red were on sale in Aatran market on the 4th June. Yellow Khalal called Masri were on sale at .the same pi place on the same day. 'the s&amp;gr&amp;l variety is one of the com?.onest# There are some atvAl Hil. and they are feaid to oe cornuon all along the Batab# They are said to be one of the commonest sorts at kinjah and Kliaudl They are one of the four coinuonest at t&gt;amayil. Ar Ghallah they were common# The date presents points of resemblance with the Uyir of tl Iraq. In that it is common the Khalal are edible, and yellow and ti the half Ratab dates show a very definite and distinctive line of demarkation between the apical ±i*atab naif and tne basel Khalal hal3 On the othot iiand the Iktrbal dates resemble the nallawi An sixe in earlineas and by a charcteristic white babdA part of the iamar. ‘This white base is not noticeable in Jiallawi dates when the palms &lt; on whioh they are borne have suffered from drought and earns from them the title leathers of Little pores Abu tfhashain* upstanding. The leaflets are more at right angles to the midrib than are those of KKIHAILI# The whole appearance of the palm is more as the moot FARALH? » The palm does not bear so heavily as the FARALHff althou^l the latter dates are the more expensive. It is the latest date tc ripen with the exception MILALI. The KHALAl are a fine, dull caz* mineand appearing in the groves wnen the utner dates nave long oeu cut are strixing# Last yearAs TAMAH were to be obtained in Matral nuirket tnis June# A few Marghili palms in AL HIL#Plate xxxv, A Naghal PAlm at Mlellafl at ^lylah.i'he bases of tbe f rtnds ere not cut out* In the foreground a small water fall of irrigation water descending from one terrace toi another* ^ashu Al Kharmak are in A1 hil and in “amayil* Cash Ahmar is the same of a ^amayil variety*Hie red colour of the Kh&amp;la3. was just beginning to show on the 7th June* ^ash durash was seen at ^amayil but not in the Batanah*In the bamayil it is thex earliest date to ripen but it dc does not find its way into the Ifotrah market earliest because the tfaghal of the coast are before It*The Khalal are red* Q^ash Gahaili wascseen at bib*The dates were in the Khalal stage iyellow) • ^ash iianumah is the second comrionest date at Al Hil and is said to be very common along the Hatanah*It was seen only occaoaiormlly in tne Wndi Uamayll*The dates were in the Khalt stage*They are almost as early as Haghal* Wadi* qash haiyims palms are in the Hatanah and in the The big Handsome ^ash duiaaih palms were encounters at iiamayil at Al,H11 and at uib. The dates turn red straight from green without any yellowing and this gives them a curious appear- ance* aarki dates are cooked and exported to India* *iarnak palms have red fruits stalks*They were see; in the Wtiai and in the batanah* Like the ^ash Lawaih the dates of tlie Lhabrut ^ variety melt from dark green to dark red making them look ddkl and unusual* These iChalal are bitter out the Ha tab Tamar are said to be good* Shaham dates are reddish brown yellow Mhalal at Sib early in June* Silani dates were yellow jQiulal at Sib* Suri are said to be sent as Khalal Matbukh to India* Omani are said to be exported in a similar manne: Is this a trade synonym for lihbasil? Plate xxxvi* found umm billah Idims at bib.hound eeah is a circle of Millet Gnasiiinar* uxom Sillah is the coriimonesx Hatab&amp;h date* If 1 be reckoned that one third of all the Batanah palms be of this variety to total .varieties at ^ib h old good for the whole tract tS there*must be about half a million palms Umm Sillah -^arly in June* the dates were still green.i^st years* prices were from 30 tp 40 Kj Rial a -dabar i*e* 1 to l/3 c a pound.lt is the conKiionest date met with in baskets in the markets* The red Khalal of Ib&amp;m Zanag were seen in Matrah*The Zibid palm is common in the Wadi bam&amp;yil and ea^ to find at ‘-'ib* The general is suggestive of the Hallawi of the Iraq*The dates are said to be of good quality.They are small and ver late* * #*•* *#'#*■*#*# **** »»»■»»*» * * ♦*** |</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001fc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2965</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001fc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2965</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/13 'Muscat: Date trade: Indian tariff on Muscat dates'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-06T22:04:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (44 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 46; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of correspondence concerning the cultivation of and trade in dates in Oman. The principal correspondents are the Government of India (Foreign and Political Department), India Office, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the Political Agency in Muscat. The following is contained within the file:Correspondence between Valentine Hugh Wilfred Dowson, date expert and representative of the Hills Brothers Company in Basra, Iraq, Charles Wills, representative of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, the Political Resident, Muscat Political Agent, and the Department of Overseas Trade regarding the possibilities of expanding the cultivation of and trade in dates in Oman. Included is an extract of a report by Dowson on date cultivation in Oman (folios 33-44).Correspondence regarding the high customs tariff on Omani date exports imposed by India and the agreement to lower it during 1933 and their unwillingness to do so again in 1938Correspondence between the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations and the Government of India regarding the embargo on date and pearl imports into India from the Persian Gulf in 1947.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Dates (fruit)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001fc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>