<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-20T11:15:04.681Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">81 . £ 1 . AVIATION. A. CIVIL aVIATION (l) Sanitary Administration on the Arab side of the Gulf. From To Previous number.Political Department. INDIA OFFICE, /© 9 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as ii: it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State To Resident, Persian Gulf, repeated to India, Bahrein, Muscat and Kov/eit Dated 13th March, 1936. No. P.Z. 1454/36 Sanitary administration at Aerodromes on the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf. Please see Foreign Office letter of the 28th February of y/hich a copy is enclosed. I presume you will agree that it is undesirable to give any notice under the Sanitary Convention for Aerial Navigation of 12th April, 1933, in respect of the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. I should, however, be glad of your observations on the other suggestions made in paragraph 4 of the Foreign Office letter. In this connection please refer to Air Ministry demi official letter of the 15th February (and enclosures) of which a copy is also enclosed. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. V - LLj i Ul7,.X4d4/l936 flo. Vi. 945/87/94. 2 ^ Foaibian QFWIQ&amp;, &amp;, X. ^8th February, 1936. Sir, X am directa4 by i&amp;r. secretary £dcn to otate, lor the inforiaation of the lourquass of wetland, that certain correapondenoe regarding an outbreak of emaXXpoac at Sharjah, in the i'er&amp;ian Gull, which hue been comimaticated semi-officialiy to this department by hr. Morgen of the Ministry of Health, raiees the question of the sanitary administration at aerodromee on the Arabian ohoro of the Per elan Guff. It is understood that xjsr. Morgan toe oocamiuioated unoifioialxy to Major-General ; ir Johii . egaw copy of the correepondenoe in question. £» The international saiiitary convention for serial navigation, ei^ned at the Hague, Ihth April, 1933, come into iorce on the let August, 1935 (Treaty Seriee Ho. 19 (1935; Cmd*4938). According to the terms of the emoluAlllg declaration idad© at the time of signature by the United kingdom pleni potentiary under paragraph 1 of Article 65, the convention is not applicable to British colonies and protectorate* unless notice ha* been given by liia Majesty** Government in the United Kingdom that it is desired to apply the convention to any of these territories. Although, therefore, the convention is not applicable to the Arab States of the perslm Qulf which a re under British protection (and in Mr. Aden*© view ala these territories are from he internatfonoi point of view under British protection, except Muscat;, Mr. !&amp;*n i® of opinion that it is open to Hi© ajeety , 8 Government to give the required notice in respect of these State®, including Bahrain and The Under-secretary of state, XiMiA OFFICEi z kowaitf but excluding X am to ^oiut »&gt;ut f Jbowovar, that tha convention prcaoriboa oartain iaeaauros viiioh are to be tafcfta by the oontraoting partie« f ani to rel'^r in thi» connexian to Articles 3 and 7. 5?ha»o jiioaauree shaui.d orxiiA;^iidr be taken before the Convention ie applied to the territories concerned* 3* Mr* iiden w-uid bo glad to receive th &gt; viewc of the* Marq&lt;*e*« of zeVl^ui ua to the advisability of auoh notice beijf given on behalf of the ,yrab iTtatee of the itirelan Calf uiider Briiiah protection* 4* If it is thought in.tovicable to do this either because Hi a H&amp;jacrtjr** Govorit^nt in the United liin. ..uom have not pravioaaiy extenduu. couTenticne to the Ct ,.f states under the colonial article© of convent lone and this lead to &lt; ugg nations for other oxtaiiisione (such se tno bfiu.it ary convent .on itself } akxoh iaay be unu-eoir ie, or because, owing to the fact that the native ruler a enjoy internal independence and huve in moat caaee onl^ sdiewhat pr lultive tteehinory of govexmieht. His Majesty 9 e aovernaent could not be sure that conventional obligations undertaken «ould be fulfilled, it may nevertheleec be desirable that it should be possible for the olaietry of health to give to the international lublic Hoalth Office u ©ur uioes to the following effect i (1) that in the aerodromes used by £r*usrl&amp;i Airways on ^ ^ ..U,. b. taken; and {&amp;) that the lolitioal Hosidonts end loiiticul Agents in the Gull sill ufcMs their best efforts to see that the ordinary sanitary porecaution© arc taken in the territories of the Arab states there and that information relating to these State©, of the kind which i© usually ou plied to the international office relating to territories where the sanitary conventionsuiHima &lt;uf Hijium, L. ; .l. ic9%h Jimuury, l‘i36* D#4MP Barnett, *« r«oeia$ly ruoc^iveu irom the Ofiie-e ioual Hygiene publique a notifioatlua of an oufctir^ak of aiaa-uLpox at Filarj«H in the Feraien Ouif* X had occa&amp;ion laat weeic while in r urie to eee hr. Abt f tm: Bdoctor of the uffice Int'.rnational d«Hy^ion# pubiique, anc dieouated the utter with hi*.* The origin of the information reo^iired at the Peri« Office waa a letter dated the 6th January, oigned by hr* Bmrratt H«g&amp;a on beh«ilf of the OJr eator-acneral oi Healthf Iraq. A oopy of thin letter is annexed* iroa it you will eeo that e&amp;ae 750 caeea of aniJLlpoa: are alleged to hare occurred in eix mwOJI town® in the area during tlm p&amp;at few weeks. The information wan first obtained fr®&amp; the priaoipal Radical officer, Iraq CC^aand, B.A.F., Baghdad, who tdeponed to xr. Hcg^C the 3C*th Septcaiter report in,.; the outbreak of the dieeuee. hr. ao,^« ccjasnuiloatcd at once v,ith the Imperial Air waye Oosapany at Baghdad, ana by urrtix^e^cnt with them the Principal Medical Officer, H.a*F., kindly e,at a Medical officer by airplane from Baghdad to Sharjah. Certain preventive lue&amp;suree ^ere nthcc uentiy taken aith the rcjsult that the civil Health pa* dni at ration, Baghdad, were able to wire to .Karachi, ralectinc -&gt;.nu Alcacsatiria to the effect that vaccination had lean con led out and that it was considered that the only measures necessary were aurveillonce of air passengers and orowe who had stopped at Sharjah. In another iett r from ar. H*gg« to Dr* Abt, also dated the 6tn January, a copy of which is annexed, you will note the remark that an epidemiological infer nation service within the daxi is badly needed and that this can only be arranged intornat ionally •z. The outbre it of mmXXpox at S&amp;arjtift rai^ee a tiu^ber oi quoutiorie in ra^ari to the application oi the International ^anitar^ Cony ntion anl o£ quaruntin«} ol air trailic generally in the lereian Gull* I tear X was unable to &amp;ivo or. Abt any inioriaation on the ioattor # since 1 Hiow nothin;, of the circuit once * 3 * what Oovarrm nt or aovernaients hre reeponeible for sanitary uihaini strut ion aioi^ the southern ahore ©i the ertiian ciulf} are ther . any local aaiainistrntiye authorities, and what are the actual measures for medical supervision quarafitme of air cult., their srsws and paeseit ora, in tiis uerodromoe in the rag 1 Oh? J3T* Abt has prep .rad a note on tiie territorial status of areas in the Persian Gulf in which there or© aerodromes of the Imperial Airways company, but he is not sure whether the infernstien he gives is accurate* The subject will in all probability be referred to at the next session of the Pari© Office in &amp;ay, particularly in regard to the authorities responsible for sanitary control in the aerodromes, the danger ©i infection of the- a^rodroisss from without, especially by local inhabitants, ani finally the poosibliity of establish .nt. © ecrvioe of spidesuiolhgihai iraarmation lor the ar«a* Although X do nor Uib- the o iroumstanoss, some doubt in rained in my mind as to whether the Iraq health services ana the XU A* 3? • in Iraq have any ijandat© to oooupy theiasslvcs with health conditions in the Persian duuf * But perheps this is a local arraagsmsiit concluded between Iraq and imperial Airways. f urs sincerely. ( $d. )«•«. hOBaAiin MIHTSTHY 0? UmSRIOa Public Health I&gt;lwotorate 6 th 1936 . Baghdad Iraq. The Office iatcruational d*Hygiene puhli^ue^ 195 Boulevar . EMM* Six 1 # In ref ere. ice to the report sent to you to-day as to the ©oallpox outbreak at Sharjah area of the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf. I wish to draw your attention to the fact that epidemiological information fro a the Gulf is bad. On a previ &gt;us oecasi m also in 1932 the only information of a ssover© outbreak of waalXpox near Bahrein was a com uni cation fvm the loyal Air Fox*oe of Iraq who had seen a large encsapne t wliile flying dmm the Gulf and had landed to discover a large collection of cases entirely unattended to and unknown. 3. tallpox is endemic in these areas but aox^e hiportant here is the iuesUon of cholera wsxieh rmy cuter the CB If from idia and be equally unknown for a long tiiae* Ait EpideJidological information service witJiin the Gulf is badly needed# This can only be arrmged. internati o*ially# In 1932 we appx*oached all known isedleal officers and iiiasloxuury 1 Victors throughout the Gulf to endeavour to establish a mutual arx^angersent but nothing ca ie of it. In view of the Air Service la addition to the See traffic the matter is worthy of serious 00 ns id era ti on. A vr to express my indebtedness to 'he Irlndtiees of tiie H*A#P. wh&gt; have assisted us in these matters la the past ao readily. X flLMf *' t O • f Sga, BAHKE T HKOOS for dihsctoh ammo, of health.SQEX- Klaiatry of Interior i’utHc Health Directorate . a£ii&lt;ia&lt;i ' T rek ’. BY. m .-AALL- Ho. H 366 6tlx JeLiuary f 1936. To* Thu Office Into rational d f Hygiene puHli^ae Boulevard Saint oeraelaf £HAi» Sir» A j^ALIHPOX OU TBID ; AT i iiarjah Is an Alrermft Statical situated Xjm8»55° Lttt*25° on the Pirate Coast of Ormn cm the Southern or Arslilan coast of the Persian Culf approxi ately S00 dies direct from Basrah and mi away between Bahrein and duseat* It is also a; inteneviiate station between Basrah md . arachi* The Mrcrai t station has a rest house mid 1© a refuelling station* dome 7dv oases of Seallpox hare occurred in the following six small towns in the area during the past few weeks*namely Bus al Kaiaah do cases* 40 deaths* Ob al .avain 80 oases* 4 uc-s.ths* Hears i cases and 2 deaths* Ajman lo ouses anc 7 deaths* Sharjah 1 0 oases ana 18 deaths* Bubal 600 cases ana 60 deaths* ^ our information was first obtained from the principal Medical Officer* Iraq Command* B*A.?«* Baghdad who telephones me or both December chat an outbreak of this disease was reported at dharjah* I communicated at once with the Imperial Airways Company at Baghdad and by arrangement with them the Principal Medical Officer* H*A*P. kindly sent a medical officer by aeroplane from Baghdad to Sharjah. I notified the aerodromes at Basrah and Baghdad. The Imperial Airways Company on 3rd January report that all the Staff of the Aircraft Station and rest house at fiharjah Including the native labour and the guards have been vaccinated. Ho gases have occurred in the Stathm itself. Vaccine was obtained from Karachi and 660 persons in Sharjah were vaccinated by/ms ms by the Aeroaroae atatT and nore vaceine h»e been sent to continue the vaccination* The British political officer at Bahrein has sent a vaccinator from Bahrein to vaccinate the other villagea* Sharjah is informed that log bonice of Aircraft muet be endoreed that Sharjah Area ia iniected with smallpox and that paaeengere and cre^a vho stopped at Sharjah will be under Surveillance only. Karachi» Paleatino and Alexandria informed as follows by wirei- Saallpox tutbreafc at local area of Sharjah Aircraft Station Persian Gulf stop Station free stop Vaccination done stop Consider Surveillance of ilr passengers and crews i who stop there necessary only* Civhealth, Baghdad* I am. Sec• 9 (aigne) BAHBETT HKGGS* for Birector General of Health* Copy to:- The Principal Medical Officer, Iraf Commanu, Baghdad* The fuurantin© Board, Alexanaria* The Director of Health, Jerusalem* The Inspector General of Health Services, High Commissioner, Beyrouth* The Director pastern Bureau League of nations, ingapore* The Medical Officer, Civil Airport, Karachi*m ■f* ^ ■ : t*0*No.^7 of 19B6. The Lo£ldanc}, Buahlre, the April; Pl^ss© refttT/ to XucIIa on lee Printed Letter lo. P.2:. .14M/S6, dated the l»th rch 1^% oa the subject of Simitar? AhudaUtration at Aero- crom&amp; m the Arabian Coast of the Percitn Cuif, 'vhich I am answering in detail later * £• 1 quite agree that we ahou.lt n^t give any notice under the Convention in reai ect of the Arab State#* In the Beanti&amp;e, I would be grateful If, far our guldanee f you coulc kindly aewi ase and each of the three Political Agent$ tw&gt; additional copie* of the Convention* I am sending copies of tills letter to Mete&amp;lfe* he Gaury* Loch and ?* r *tts. Yours sincerely, sc. T.C.Fo^le. k* J. CU-uson Esquire, The India Office, London* -I .P i- ^ n ' V ^ v- y GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N* B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From To Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, nahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. ^ To 2K N(k 839 Dated 15 th April 1936 &amp; Sanitary Administration - Arab Coast. In continuation of my Printed letter No. 8 38 dated 15th April 1936* I enclose herewith draft letter which I propose despatching to the addressees noted. Before doing this, however, please let me have your com- -ments on the letter as soon as possible. 2. X also enclose copy of an office note dated 13th April 1936. 3. To Bahrain and Kuwait only . As I under- -stand it Dr. GSreenway,at Kuwait, visits each aeroplane, while Dr .Holmes, at Joahrain, does not do this - in fact as s. 6. MFP —1515 S&amp;P—(M- 2089 )— 2 - 4 - 35 — 200 , 000 .f) ^90 &amp;s the a«?rodrorof is on teamsifc Inland it irovild 'bs inpoceible for the S&amp;tter to do 50 e haring regard It vould not appear to his other duties* nece sa&amp;ry for the ^uarantl nc nediemX floor to vlsit each acropl^^i vide yarc^raph 1 of nny office no te&gt; hut fii&amp;gor Tlocuey will die cuss this and juar€tf&gt;* • tine nalters get erkllyt e*t&gt; whether the quarantine jetaic«il tiffleer actually ^sivee any aocieaent to the lilot of the aeroplane either direct or throu^i the Imperial Airways Agents* with political Agent* hahrain* on hie approaching rlelt* 4* To iiahi^ain and jOK/alt only* It aoesse to me that the local quarantine judical Ufficeniat Bahrain and tawait might well receive an extra allow- -ance (in addition to the allowance which* I wider- -stand* they already receive frthe Hull re for attending the sea service a) for their duties in con- -neotion with the Air Service* rreswaably this would come from Hi a Majeety'a (bvernment since it is they who have taken over from the Ruler the satire administration of the aerodromes* ad^/ — T.C.?owle* Lieut-Colone 1* Poll tieal Head dent in the Persian oulf. ATn^TSD* ve sident in the Persian Ob If*L h AFT. ETPfiESii LETTEh. /'&gt; From - To Repeated No, Political Resident, Busiiire, Secretary of State for India, London, Government of India, New Delhi, Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Kuwait# Dated Subject * Sanitary administration on the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf. With reference to your Express Letter No, P.Z, 1454/se of the 35th March 1956, with enclosures. In the first place it may be as well to indicate what is the present machinery for dealing with the sanitary adsinistration of the Arab ©oast of the Persian Gulf. (On the Iranian coast this Residency has of course no responsibility! the quarantine administration being en tirely in the hands of the Iranian medical authorities). At Bushire there is a Residency Burgeon of the who is the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer for the Coast in question, and who has immediately under him at Bushire fin Assistant Burgeon. At Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat, besides the Political Agents, there are Assistant Surgeons of the I.II.D. , who are Quarantine Medical Officers for the local Rulers, (from whom they receive an allowance for these duties), and who work under the Residency Burgeon by whom their activities are co-ordina ted. /O *13. A T * - • - ~ ■-i ..: j ■ ♦ni4i*i^« laollrjn^q ^i-aa§A Xea^iXof - aoi *&gt; ~ .oK H* * *•£ lA 4^f lffc» n&amp;t$ . i*Ufv 2'iSS'i ■JeuJ’ xc V ' v ’ ' *''’'• - ftttfihfti jju^r xo * ?A ' U -' :; ' J ' ; ' r : - ■• &lt;*•'• at*.-:* 3*Ti-1 aft# ::X ' :i -' ;: ^ 8 “ ft Tcl vxs^ftasa X:,-.«.&gt;« fe ,v si #** a&lt;; * 1? ' ' -° “' : ' Cc; i5 ^ * 1 ic aoi-t ^tU.uaf W«#teM ~ w&gt;3 lo ,1ft# #,^o ,..# ; ;0) ,11^ '. -S- ri«••..« ««i#aa 5jWi , ^ 5 # I’jfilMiaftei.s,,,, . w-'.-ii. i .:. lWi ,„ iaalftw artiartl wt# io ,asi«l m# al 9rtw t ,a.K.I *rf# 1» soegrurs a *1 »tau# j, 01 '* 3 ° 3 fii ' T W &gt;, ***** ,1 ..i?.;r - ;; , .-s;ft t*UB. ■U-&gt;J3lb«ml taft aft, aao t acifsat.- f . baa nlaarfaS ,ila«ea *ft .£foe S if2 Jasm*,* *« j«3#«xs*a »-ra wcad# &lt;Mrt»%A ; • x©x aft# a* ••■'•'•' ‘ ' ! • &lt;» «.a,X,X aft# lo «aa9«toa - &lt; - • - '■ ■ ■ - =* - • &gt;:•- ‘' t * : “-'’ iv *''' •■* -' »'.«» x«f «e»stui3 icaoabiaal .bsi* -2- 1 ^. 0 S. The two weak linKS in the chain are the Trucial _ _ ' hiumium &gt;i.mhb»^h i** 9 *'•***** ©oast, where we have a kesicency Agent but no Medical Officer* and Gwaaur, whicn though belonging to Muscat is situated jon . •••''■-and _ the Baluchistan co&amp;st^/^here though there is » iresidency Agent there is also no Medical Officer. Moreover the Gwadur fcerodrocie is situated some twelve adles inlam xrom z^a town. I have suggested that an Assistant Surgeon should be posted at Sharjah for work on the Truciai Coast, but there are financial difficulties in the way of this proposition and the question is under the considerstion of the Government of Ixi&gt; ia and His Majesty*s Government - vide correspondence ending with Government of India letter Ko«F«3i (5)-E/£5 of the 5th February 19S6. 3. The Assistant Surgeons at Kuwait and Bahrain have in the past attended to the Sea Services and n&amp;ve now extended their duties to the Air Services under the oivil Air Agicements between His Majesty 1 s Government snc the two Bui era concerned. The Assistant Surgeon at Muscat, owing to the Gw&amp;dur aerodroae being on the opposite coast, is unable to do any work in connection with the Air Services. 4. $ith regard to the smallpox epidemic out of which the present correspondence has arisen, the course oi events was as follows. On the 30th December 1935 in a telegram to use in connection witha proposed flight of aircraft along the Trucial Coast, the Air Officer Commanding, Bagdad, mentioned that the flight might have to avoid Sharjah owing to smallpox. On the same day I received a telegram from tne Political Agent, Bahrain, that smallpox had broken out on the Trucial Coast / mm w* £ &lt;s&gt; Coast ano telegraphed to the Political Agent, Bahrain, that the Residency Agent, Bh&amp;rJah, with whom he is in wireless touch, should arrange with the Shaiiih of Sharjah and Imperial Airways Station Superintendent to isolate the Imperial Airways Best House from the town. On the Slst December the Air Officer Commanding telegraphed to me that he was sending a Medical Officer by Imperial Airways* plane of that date to vaccinate 8i.l personnel of the Best House. This telegram was repeated to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and the Senior N&amp;val Officer, Persian Gulf, so all who were locally concerned knew what was happening. On the 4th January,having obtained from the Residency Agent through the Political Agent, Bahrain, trie number of cases and deaths, I sent the following telegram addressed: Government of India, repeated minister Tehran, Consul Basra for information of Port Health Officer, Vice Consul Khorramshahr for information of Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, Port Health Officers, Karachi, Bombay and Aden, Imperial Airways Karachi and Cairo. For information. Trucial Coast including Charjah and Dibai infected with smallpox 755 cases 89 deaths. In addition I gave the same information to the local Iranian Itedicsl Authorities here, and local Shipping Agents. Since the 4th January the Air Officer Command I ng,B&amp;g dad, and the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf,(since their aero planes and ships have to visit the Trucial Coast frequently), the two local authorities most concerned, have been sent a weekly telegram giving cases and deaths* The epidemic is on the decrease, and when the Residency Burgeon considers that the Trucial Coast can be declared free of smallpox all concerned will be duly informod. 5. It will be seen that the third addressee of my telegram quoted /•—mm £ /■N © q\ioted above was Consul Basra for inforisation of the Port Health Officer, who presua^bly passed the inlor&amp;: tion cn to the PublicK Herlth Directorate of Iraq. Dr. Barrett Heggs’ statecent therefore at the beginning of paragraph f of nis letter of 6th January to the Ministry of Interior, Public Health Directorate at Bagcad, Iraq, that •epidemiological information from the Gulf it bad*, is entirely incorrect. On the 4th January when there were adequate details in my possession as to the extent of the outbreak (merely to telegraph that an outbreak had occurred without giving some indication of deaths and cases would be of little use, - especially as smallpox la endemic along the Arab Coast) x telegraphed the Information to all concerned. Dr. Barrett Heggs makes no mention of this letter telegram though presumably he was informed of it by the Port Health Officer, Basra. There is no need for an Epidemiologies! information service within the Gulf to he arranged internationally, as suggested by Dr. Barrett Heggs. The machinery detailed in paragraph 1 above is quite adequate, and in the present instance has worked well. 6* The vaccination et Sharjah referred to in Dr.Barrett Heggs * letter of 6th January 3936, Iio.H.366, to the Ministry of Interior, Public Health Directorate, Bagdad, was carried out partly by the Koy&amp;l Air Force Medical Officer referred to in the Air Officer Commanding 1 s telegram of 3ist December, partly by the Station Superintendent, Imperial Airways, and partly by &amp; vaccinator and the Assistant Surgeon, Bahrain, sent by the Political Agent of that place. 7. With regard to the possibility of cholera reaching Iraq via the Persian Gulf referred to by Dr. Barrett Reggs in /mm -5- I in hia first letter of 6th J&amp;nuary. In the opinion of the Residency Surgeon cholera Is more likely to reach Iraq vis the Persian than the Arab side of the Gull, and on the latter side we should get warning from the Political Agents at Muscat, Bahrain and Kuwait* 6. With regard to tie last paragraph of Ministry of Health 1 s letter of fSth January 19£6. The Iraq Health Services end tiie Royal Air Force in Iraq have of course no mandate to occupy themselves with health conditions on the Arab side of the Persian Gulf which can normally be- looked after by the residency Surgeon in his capacity of Chief Quarantine Medical Officer and the staff under nia. At the sar.e time in cases of emergency, especially in regard to Sharjah, whore there is no Medical Officer, I am always willing to receive assistance from outside, and I am grate ful to the Royal Air Force for sending their doctor down so promptly. The Superintendent Imperial Air*&amp;ys also did useful work in assisting with the vaccination. 9. With regard to the points raised in paragraph 4 of the Foreign Office letter of 88th February, No.W.945/87/94, to the India Office, on which my observations are asked. I entirely agree that it is undesirable to give any notice under the Sanitary Convention of April 18th 1932 in respect of the Ar?b side of the Persian Gulf. 10. With wegard to the two assurances which might be given to the International Public Health Office, suggested in the same paragraph of the Foreign Office letter in question. The Residency Burgeon sees no objection to giving them, and I concur. hieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ■mm / Subject : Sanitary Administration At Aerodromes on the Arabian Coast of the Persian Oulf* Eesiciency Curgeo^ hei i«y eoisvArA&amp;tlon with you and Under Secretary on this point* Under Article 9 of the Convention the pilot need not carry a Bill of Health ar4 therefore apparent ly need not be given pratique as in the case of &amp; ship* The pilot has however to enter certain observations in his log and these observations must necessarily be based on information sent to him by the local Quarantine Medical Officer through the competent Aerodrome Officer, who, in the case of the Arab side of the Gulf, is tne Imperial Airways Agent* Prlma f cie it t.ouIc not appear necessary for tiie Quarantine Medical Officer to visit each ’plane, but only when necessary from some special circuEstrnews, see Article 5 and Articles £7 - £5* ^ ' In Article f6 the au&amp;rnntine pr cedure with regard to passengers disembarking is laid do*n, and it would appear th&gt; t ,l observatlon ,, i*e. isola tion, placing in quarantine, is only neceas ry in exceptional cases, and is left to the discretion of the local Quarantine Medical Officer* 3 All that t vil Air Agreements with the hulers of Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat enjoin in the way of s^nitfcry precautions are (a) Under Article XX of the 'Heads of Agreement' between the Euler and His Majesty’s Government, air sanitary // wmmmm -E~ [l*\ sanitary formalities will bi? exercised by the Quarantine Medical Officer, and (b) Under Article 10 of the Air Kavigatlon Kegulationa, the aircraft anc persona on board shall laaediately on arrival fro® abroad and prior t departure for abroad submit to the sanitary formalities prescribed by the Public Health Administration* PzrusAu^? u/4/se. t.c.f.goaf iflential. * GOVERXMEXT OF INDIA, Dspartmbsi, [N. n.-This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, by past to swe teler/raphic expet.se and undue use of the in res, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expeddion as \f it had been telegraphed. To sa e time a&gt;td formalities it is tvoraed a d sijred as if it had been so despatched*] From Political, Muscat* * Hrltconsul, Bushirt* So* e-64 fV i'/th May 1 U^ 6 . oanltaxy ^Cmlnlatration • ^rab Coast* , y\°\ Meiarence your talagra* J»o. afiJ' or 14th May 1&amp;*6. AS ragarda your MraTt letter enclosed with your express uatter Mo. 836 or 16th AprU 1336, so rar as the portions therein refer to arrangements In Muscat territory 1 do not consider tnat anythin^ further ohouid, or in f&lt;|Ct could, he said* 3# /*o stated hy you In paragraph M of your iiraft letter referred to above one of the two weak links In the chain of the machinery for dealing with the sanitary administration of % the ^rab side of the (iulf la at Gwadur* this spiles of course not only to ^Ir services using the aerodrome near the tom but to the whole district and port, where there Is no Medical author rlty whatsoever and where In consequence no quarantine arrangmrts S 6 MFP— 400S&amp;P—(M-480 - 26 7-34—2,00,'X^.\ m Mr 4^ ¥‘ s GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, ' Department. EXPRESS LETTER [xY, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hy post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From RESIDENT, BUSHIBE, To POLITICAL, MUSCAT. Y&lt;v Dated ItsCZ the May m 3 + - Arab Coast . Please expedite reply to my Express Letter No. 839 dated the 15th April 1936. RESIDENT. The issue of the above has beeu authorised. Secretary to the Polit in the Persian Gulf. ical Resident! S. 6. MFP—1515 S&amp;P—(M-2089)—2-4-35—200,000.Mi INDIA OFFICE, wHITaHALL j S . u . 1 . P„z.2713/36 27th April, 1956. /-s * Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to Mr. Seymour's letter of the 28th February, No. W. 945/87/94, on the subject of the sanitary administration on the Arab coast of the Persian Gulf, in connection with the recent outbreak of smallpox at Sharjah. The Marquess of Zetland, after consultation with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, considers that it would be inadvisable to give notice under the International Sanitary Convention for Aerial Navigation on behalf of the Arab States of the Persian Gulf. The further considerations raised in paragraph 4 of Foreign Office letter under reference are receiving the attention of the political Resident, and on receipt of his views a further communication will be addressed to you. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Air Ministry. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. W. 1.■■■■■ r'~\. P.Z. 2713/36 INDIA OFFICE, Y/HITEHALL, S.. . 1. 30th April, 1936. cLulQ' -f' Will you please refer to your demi-official letter of the 15th April, No.837/36, on the subject of sanitary administration in the Persian Gulf? I enclose as requested two copies of the International Sanitary Convention for Aerial Navigation. I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe, and, y/ith two copies of the Convention, to de G-aury, Y/atts and Loch. (Sgd.) M. J. GLAUSON Lieutenant-Colonel T.C. Fowle, C.B.E., His Majesty's Consul-General, Bushire.ft ftf MJLUUUlA kjUL!LJx-&amp;' 3 h \ To ifYOffi Political Besldonty Bushlre. Soorotary of Stats for Xn&amp;la v iotidon* KoreigOt sisla i! ^ ' Political Agent, Muscat,V lolitleal Agent, Bahrain, iwe. o. | l Political Agent, Kuwait* Dated the 2nd June 1934* Subject:- Sanitary adainistration on the Arab Oeast of the Persian Gulf* With reference to your Express Letter ho* ?•£• 1454/36 of the 13th ^aroh 1936, with oncloauraa. . in the first place it may he as well to indicate what is the present machinery for dealing with the sani tary administration of the Arah Coast of the Persian Oulf* (On the Iranian coast this Residency has of course no responsibility: the Quarantine administration being entirely in the hands of the Iranian medical autho rities)* At Bus hire there is a Lea Id cm ay Gurgeon of the Indian Medical Service, who is the Thief quarantine tedioal officer for the Coast in Question, and who has immediately under him at Bus hire an Assistant Burgeon. At Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat, besides the Political Agents, there are Assistant Burgeons of the Indian kedi- oal department, who are quarantine kedioal officers for the local Bulers, and who work under the iieaidency sur geon by whom their activities are co-ordinated* 2 ./-■ 2* The three weak llmkss la the quarantine chain are la) the Trucial 'oast, where we have a Kesiciency Agemt l)nt no Med leal Officer* lb) Gwaciur, which though belonging to Muscat is situated on the Baluchistan coast* where though there is a Bealdericy Agent there la no Medical of fleer* and whtre moreover the aerodrome la situated some twelve milea Inland from the town, and (o) the Batlneh coast stretching from Muscat up to the iiaa Musandam peninsula* ith regard to la)* 1 have suggested that an Assistant Burgeon should he posted at :h&amp;rjah for work on the ‘fruoial Boast* but there are financial diffi culties in the way of this proposition and the question is under the consideration of the Government of India and His Majesty’s Government - vide oorrespondence ending with Government of tndia letter *io. /*31U)-V 35 of the 5fch February 1936* Vith regard to lb)* The loiltical Agent* Muscat* has suggested that the post of / esidency Agent there should be held by a retired Sub-Assistant Surgeon who oould perform the duties of local Medical Officer* and 1 will address the Government of India separately on this subject* ^ith regard to lo)* 1 have no proposals to make for this area since it is comparatively unimportant; unlike la) and lb) neither steamships nor air services touch there though it is visited occasionally by His Majesty’s Ships and Hoyal Air Force aircraft* 3* The Assistant Burgeons at Kuwait and Bahrain have in the past attended to the ea Services end have novd extended their duties to the Air Services under the CivilOtTil Air h&amp;rmmmtB Hie Majesty's tiovGrewmt and the two x ulars concern m . 'Dio Asaiatant burgeon at Muacatf owing to the Gwacur aerodrome being on the opposite coast, is unable to do any work in connection with the Air Gerrices* 4* With regf^rd to the smallpox epidemic out of which the present correspondence has arisen, the course of events was as follows* on the 30th December 1935 in a telegram to me in connection with a proposed flight of aircraft along the TrneiaJL Coast, the Air officer Commanding, Bagdad, mentioned that the flight might hawe to avoid Sharjah owing to smallpox* on the same day 1 received a tele* gram from the Political Agent, Bahrain, that smallpox had broken out on the rucial Coast and telegraphed to the Political Agent, Bahrain, that the Kesidency Agent, Bh&amp;rjah, with whom he is in wireless touch, should arrange with the Shaikh of Sharjah and Imperial Airways Station Superintendent to isolate the Imperial Airways Hast House from the town* *n the 31st December the Air Officer Commanding telegraphed to me that he was sending a Medical officer by imperial Airways* plane of that date to vaccinate all personnel of the Hast house* this telegram was repeated to the iolitloal Agent, Bahrain, and the senior Naval Officer, iersiaja Gulf, so all who were locally concerned knew what was happen ing* on the 4th January, having obtained from the heoidency Agent through the Political Agent, Bahrain, the number of cases and deaths, 2 sent the following tolegram addressed t Government of India, repeated Minister, Tehran, Consul Basra for information of iort Health* ••4 il Health officer, Vice-Gonsul ^horraiashAhr for inforamtlot) of Aoglo-lreoiatJ oil Company, *ort Health officere, Karachi, Bombay a net Men, Imperial Alnrays Karachi and Cairo. Kor information* iruciai Coast including Sharjah and Dibai infected with smallpox 7&amp;o oases 89 d oaths* In addition 1 gave the same information to the local Iranian Medical Authorities here, and local Chip ping Agents* Since the 4th January the Air officer Commanding Bagdad, and the Senior Maval Officer, rereien Gulf, who as their aeroplanes and ships visit the Truelal Coast frequently are the two local authorities most concerned, have been sent a weekly telegram giving cases and deaths* The epidemic has now ceased, the Kesidenoy Burgeon has declared that the Trucial Coast can be considered as free of smallpox, and the various authorities concerned have been Informed by telegram* 5* It will be seen that the third addressee of my telegram quoted above was Consul Basra for information of the Jfcbrt wealth Officer, who preaimiably passed the information on to the Public Health directorate of Iraq* Dr*Barrett Heggs* statement therefore at the beginning of paragraph 2 of his letter of 8th January to the Ministry of interior, rublio Health Directorate at Bag dad, Iraq, that •epldemiological information from the Gulf is bad 4 , is - at any rate so far as the rab Ooast is concerned - incorrect. Ma the 4th January when there were adequate details In my possession as to the extent of the outbreak l telegraphed the Information to all concerned*****5 ooncernea* i)r*B&amp;rrett Hoggs makes no mention of this latter telegram though 1 assume he was informed of it hy the i^ort Health officer, Basra# There is no need for an Spidemiologieal information service within the Oulf to he arranged internationally, as suggested hy Dr* Barrett Heggs. The machinery detailed in paragraph 1 above is Quite adequate, and in the present instance has worked well* 6* The vaccination at Sharjah referred to in i&gt;r. Barrett 1 eggs * letter of oth January l9J5rS, o* H*3S6 to the Ministry of Interior, iphlic Health Directorate, Bagdad, was carried out partly hy the Doyal Air Force Medical Officer referred uo in the Air Officer Command ing Bagdad's telegram of 31st December, partly hy the station Superintendent, Imperial airways, and partly hy a vaccinator and the Assistant Surgeon, Bahrain, sent hy the rolltical Agent of that place* Vaccination is, moreover, carried out on the Trueial Coast as opportunity offers and in December 1934 the fedical Officer from Bahrain carried out over 300 vaccinations, mostly at Jiihai, and vaccinated the 37 guards and 4 other employees of the Airways • station* 7* With regard to the possibility of cholera reach ing Iraq via the Persian Gulf referred to hy Dr .Barrett iieggs In his first letter of 6th January. In the opinion of the Hesidanoy Surgeon cholera Is more likely to ranch Iraq via the Persian than the Arab side of the Oulf, and on the latter side we should get warning from the Political Agents at Muscat, Bahrain and Kuwait* 8* vith regard to the last paragraph of 1 inistry of Health's*•&lt;5' Health’s letter of 29th January 1930* The Ira&lt;i health Services and the Hoyal Air force in Iraq have of course no mandate to occupy themi elves vlth health conditions on the Arab side of the feral an Sulf which can adequately he looked after by the Kesldenoy Surgeon In his capacity of vJhief quarantine Medical Offic er and the staff under him. At the same time in oases of emergency, especially In regard to Sharjah, where there Is no medical officer, X am always willing to receive assistance from outside, and 1 am grateful to the l oyal Air Jhrce for sending their doctor down so promptly. The Superintendent Imperial Airways also did vs^ful work in assisting with the vaccination* 9. With regard to the points raised in paragraph 4 of the foreign office letter of 2ith leoruaxy Ho*w.946/ 87/94 to the India office, on which my observatione are asked. 1 entirely agree that it is undesirable to give any notice under the banit&amp;ry Convention of April 12th 1933 in respect of the Arab side of the Persian (3ulf. 10. lith regard to the two assurances which might be given to the international Public iie&amp;lth office, suggested in the same paragraph of the foreign Office letter in question. The Residency Ourgeon sees no objection to giving them, and X concur. ^ith regard to the channel of com^unication in the case of the second assurance, 1 suggest that this infor mation should be given by me to the Government of India to whom, amongst others, 1 already communicate the out break of epidemics. -HSSXDSNT- Tfce issue of the above has been authorised. (SM C. C. L Ryan, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Uulf.5 0 J'JI 1956 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to -f by Mail. - J Sea The Fore iff nS^ecretary, G bVerD The Political Resident in th^ ernment of India. Persian Gulf. 3681 ■■if 1 ,rS ± : .Z. 4-438/36 I1TDIA GI'i'ICAj G HI I-uHALL ? S1. S5th Jul3 r , 1936. A, Will you please refer to your letter of the 15th February, Ho.49344-9/36/A.D. C. A. I, about sanitary :J L administ ration c o r r e s p o nd e no e loritical Resident's iu^zpress 11er of 2nd June . in the hersian Gulf, and connected on this subject. ) I enclose a copy of a letter ) -) which we have received from Colonel Fowle and of the official letter v/hich we have sent to the Foreign Office in reply to their letter of 28th February, No.W.945/87/94. If you concur, perhaps you might inform Dr. Morgan at the Ministry of Health, that the answers to the questions which he raises in paragraph 4 of his letter of 29th January are as follows. Fhe sanitary administration along the Southern shore of the Persian Gulf is supervised by ^ officers appointed by the Government of India. The chief quarantine medical officer is the Residency Surgeon at Bushire, who has under his control an Assistant Surgeon at Bushire and Assistant Surgeons at W.W. Burkett, Esq., II. C. , Air Ministry, W. C. 2.*« 2 . Koweitj Bahrein and Muscat. The necessary medical and quarantine supervision at the Bahrein and Koweit aerodromes is carried out by their respective Assistant Surgeons. At Sharjah it is carried out at present either by the Imperial Airways Station Superintendent or by the Assistant Surgeon at Bahrein. The aerodrome at Gwadur is at present under the control ol the Assistant Surgeon at Muscat. The aerodromes at Sharjah and Gwadur are situated some distance from the town and they can there fore be easily isolated sd that there is little danger of infection from without. As regards the establishment of an Epidemilogical Service, it seems to us from evidence advanced by Colonel Fowle that the present arrangements are working- sat isf act or ily and that there is no necessity for international action in this respect. I am sending copy of rhis letter to Leigh-Smith at the Foreign Office. Blfi'JOGiFQfcA Sgd.) HOOD■■■■■■I 1,3 P.Z. 4438/36 XinDj-A CiAjICa VuIIXZlIlALL, S.v/.l. 14th July, 1936 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary or State for India to refer to India Office letter of 27 th April JTo.P. Z. 2713/56, and connected correspondence regarding the sanitary administration of aerodromes on the Arabian shore of the Political Resident’s Impress Letter) Persian Gulf, and to forward a '' of 2nd June, ITo. 1142/4/142 ) — copy of the communication noted in the margin. 2. The Marquess of Zetland agrees with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that there is no objection to the Ministry of Health giving to the International Public Health Office the two assurances suggested in paragraph 4 of Mr. Seymour’s letter of 28th February Ho.J.945/87/94; and he would suggest that the Office should be informed that the channel for communication to them of any information relating to medical conditions in the Arab States .'ill be through the Government of India. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Air Ministry. I am etc. (Sd.) J.C. YfALTCH. I-. 9 Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. W. 1.ft Hn \ \ J By iUi; Mail. p.z. 5'SS'?/' iyg^ I x. 1 ^ \ Ik \AN^ LONDON, 30 JUL1936 i Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by'^Mail. bea Qyty ■/ ^ The Foreign Secretary, Govermnent of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3681imM ■ VS 1.Z.5358/36 Enclosure in Foreign Office covering note of 24th July, Ho.W.6438/87/94. FOHiSiaH CFFICii, S.'A. 1 2^&gt;rd July, 19 06 . Sir, with reference to Foreign Office letter W*945/07/94 of the 29th February regarding the sanitary administration of aerodromec on the Arabian eiacre of the iersian Gulf, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to inform you that the Secretary of State for India and the political Kesident in t te her si an Gulf a t ree that there is no objection to giving the International iublic Health Office the tv/o assurances suggested in paragrai h 4 of Foreign Office letter to the India Office of the 28th February. 2 . I am accordingly to suggest tn&amp;t the assurances in question should be communicated by the Ministry of Health to the International Health Office and that the latter should be informed that the channel for comniuni cacti on to them of any information relating to medical conditions in the Arab Stages will be through the Government of India. I am etc. (Sd.) H.J. SrimOUH The Secretary, Ministry of Health =!■V 4 } a » . Z.7C XB/?g. IHI3IA CmCS, «H1T4IAU.. .!• 6th October X93&amp;* if ouia you indly reft? uehire express letter of the ?na June, So», sjadi connectea correspondence rei*eraiRg senitery eimir let reties on the hreb Ce^et of the Pereier Oulf ^ You will see from the Foreign Cffioe letter of the f3rc ^uly, of which a copy rent to the Oorernr ent of Inaie, Bo, x. 63f&gt;d ^6/by the aea n^iX of the SOth July, thnt it is proposed to inform the Interostionsl Health ffiee in Ferie thnt the charnel for communication of any information relating to rsedieel eonaitien* in the Arab ftetee will fee through the Goromment of India. 2. In Tiew of the f ct that ipidefniologiefisl Reports are sent as and ^her necessary fey the Cor^mment of India te- the Resident we **e**e that the Gorem^ent of Indie will be able ^nd willing to pe »« on these Reports in the ordinary way to the if nr is Office. 3./ K.r.S. Menon t Foreign and political Department, Ocrernment of India.m wm S 4 ? « 4 NOTS BY MR. M.J. CLAUSON, DaTED 29th SEPTEMBER 1936. /&gt; ► — i Colonel Powle and I discussed with the Medical Adviser this morning the question of quarantine in the Persian Gulf with particular reference to Sharjah. The position was explained to the Medical Adviser who agreed that provided the Government of India pass on to the Paris Office the Epidemiological Reports received by them from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and if a Resident Medical Officer is provided for Sharjah the position should be quite satisfactory. I promised that the Political Department would communicate with the Foreign Department of the Government of India in regard to the first point; in regard to the second point a proposal for a Resident Medical Officer at Sharjah was already under the active consideration of His Majesty’s Government. It was agreed that it would probably be a good thing to get hold of Dr.Morgan on his return from Geneva and explain the whole position informally to him in order that he might be able to pass on any necessary information informally to the Director of the Paris Office or any other member that might raise the subject. It was felt that there was no necessity for any official pronouncement on the matter. *NOTE BY MEDICAL ADVISER, INDIA OPPICE, DATED 18th SEPTEMBER 1936. Please see attached letter from Dr.Morgan. The matter is one of considerable importance and I find myself unable to give a satisfactory reply to the letter. These tov/ns on the Persian Gulf which till recently were remote from civilization have suddenly found themselves on a main line of air-travel. A quarantine organization suited to the new conditions is needed and I think there need be no difficulty in making a proper arrangement•. The weak point in the present scheme is Sharjah which seems to have no medical officer at all. The best means of dealing with the problem would be to ask Government of India to consult their P.H.C. as to the organization of proper quarantine supervision over the whole of the Arabian side of the Persian Gulf where the working of the scheme should be placed under the supervision of the P.H.C. I do not know who is to pay for the quarantine, but the cost should be very small. India is keenly interested in these aerodromes from the point of view of the possible introduction of yellow fever by air traffic, and as the medical officers at present employed are recruited from India, there are obvious advantages in giving control to the Indian Government. I do not think we are justified in pressing Dr.Morgan to give an assurance to the Office International on the lines of the Foreign Office letter of 23rd July, 1936. Perhaps an informal conference would clear the air.COPY OP LETTER PROM DR. MORGAN TO SIR JOHN MEGAW, DATED 14th SEPTEMBER 1936* A short time ago I got a letter (copy enclosed) from Burkett, of the Air Ministry, in reply to one I wrote to him as long ago as January 29th, in which I referred to the sanitary administration of the aerodromes situated along the southern shore of the Persian Gulf and further east, along the northern shore of Baluchistan. You will note in his letter that he took the matter up with the India Office and received from Hood, of that office, certain information regarding the posting of medical officers at the various aerodromes concerned* You will also note that as regards the establishment of an epidemiological service, the view of the India Office is that the present arrangements are v/orking satisfactorily and that there is no necessity for international action in this respect. In this connection I would like to refer you to a letter from the Foreign Office (annexed) dated the 23rd July, 1936, addressed to this Department, in which you / / will see that it is suggested, as an outcome of correspondence between the Foreign Office and the Secretary of State for India, that the Ministry of Health should % give to the International Health Office the assurances referred to in paragraph 4 of the Foreign Office letter of the 29th February, and inform the Office that the channel for communication to them of any information relating to medical conditions in the Arab States will be through the Government of India i/-■■■■■ 2, I confess quite frankly that I am rather uneasy about the whole matter and feel personally disinclined to take the responsibility of giving the assurances referred to above on the strength of the information that is at present in my hands. In the circumstances I should be grateful for your opinion on the matter in general and, in particular* whether on these assurances it would be possible to establish some machinery in the near future by which ^ regular periodic communications could be made to the Paris Office concerning the epidemiological conditions in and around the aerodromes concerned, and urgent communications whenever circumstances called for them. As you know* the Paris Office meets on October 19th and this would ordinarily be the first available opportunity for imparting to the Office the information referred to in the Foreign Office letter of the 23rd July.—Letter from W. Birkett, Esq., Air Ministry, to Dr. M.T. Morgan dated 30th July, 1936. Dear Morgan, As long ago as 29th January you wrote to me about the responsibility for Sanitary Administration along the Arab side of the Persian Gulf, your enquiry being prompted by your conversation with Dr. Abt of the Office International d’Hygiene publique concerning an outbreak of smallpox at Sharjah. I took the matter up with the India Office who pursued it with the Political Resident at Bushire and I have now received from Hood of the India Office the following information. ’’The sanitary administration along the Southern shore of the Persian Gulf is supervised by officers appointed by the Government of India. The chief quarantine medical officer is the Residency Surgeon at Bushire, who has under his control an Assistant Surgeon at Bushire and Assistant Surgeons at Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat. The necessary medical and quarantine supervision at the Bahrein and Koweit aerodromes is carried out by their respective Assistant Surgeons. At Sharjah it is carried out at present either by the Imperial Airways Station Superintendent or by the Assistant Surgeon at Bahrein. The aerodrome at Gwadur is at present under the control of the Assistant Surgeon at Muscat. The aerodromes at Sharjah and Gwadur are situated some distance from the town and they can therefore be easily isolated so that there is little danger of infection from without”. As regards the establishment of an Epidemiological Service/2 . Service ? the view ox the India Office is that the present arrangements are working satisfactorily and that there is no necessity for international action in this respect.'\ 0 S ^ FORE I GIT OF B'ICE, S.F.l. 23rd July, 1936. (g) /'N Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter W.945/87/94 of the 29th February regarding the sanitary administration of aerodromes on the Arabian shore of the Persian Gulf, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to inform you that the Secretary of State for India and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf agree that there is no objection to giving the International Public Health Office the two assurances suggested in paragraph 4 of Foreign Office letter to the India Office of the 28th February. 2. I am accordingly to suggest that the assurances in question should be communicated by the Ministry of Health to the International Health Office and that the latter should be informed that the channel for communication to them of any information relating to medical conditions in the Arab States will be through the Government of India. I am etc. (Sd.) II.M. SEYMOUR. The Secretary Ministry of Health.m ■HMMMHi ■■■■■■■■ f i'7 (g) Copy for information, to (1) The Honourable the Political Resident in /the Persian Gulf, (2) the Political Agent, Behrain, (3) the Political Agent, Muscat. By order, etc., Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. i</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/79</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/79</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 2/4 II. AVIATION. A. CIVIL AVIATION (1) Sanitary Administration on the Arab side of the Gulf’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:03:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (59 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 61; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-60; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of letters and notifications related to the outbreak of smallpox at Sharjah. Correspondents in the file discuss the necessity of the application of the International Sanitary Convention and of quarantine restrictions in the Persian Gulf on the Arabian Coast.The correspondence also discusses the issue of sending a medical officer by airplane from Baghdad to Sharjah; the sanitary administration at aerodromes on the Arabian Coast of the Persian Gulf; and measurements that are taken at Bahrain; Kuwait and Muscat.The main correspondents in the file are the Political Residency, Bushire; the Office International d'Hygiène Publique (International Office of Public Hygiene); India Office; the Ministry of Health, and the Air Ministry.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Office International d'Hygiène Publique</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Smallpox</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>