<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00023a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T05:49:48.870Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">f F,Z.7039/39 , 44 Words , 1 Cypher telegram from Secretary of btate v for Foreign Affairs to His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul, repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department, dated 9th November, 1939. XXX SECRET. 156. Government of India’s telegram No. 2021/365 of 7th November. Following is repetition of Foreign Office telegram No. 124 of 6th November to Tehran. Begins, Your telegram No. 175 (of the 3rd November; Italian air service to Tehran). You should express to the Italian Minister in suitable temns your regret that you are unable to intervene in this question. Ends.■■■■■■■■ CD -7 o / U ;39 o o LIMIT ED DISTRIBUTION . Decypher. No. 175. Sir H. Seyiiiour (Tehran). 5ra Novenber, 1959, D. 6.40 p.,xi., 5rd November, 1959. R. 9.20 p.n. , 5rd November, 1959. The Italian, minister states that he has been endeavouring to secure permission ior Italian air Service Rome-Tehran which would possibly be extended later to Kabul. The Iranian Government have raised the usual objection that the Soviet Government would press ior service on their side if the Italian request were Granted. The Italian Minister thinks the matter could be facilitated if His Majesty's Government expressed approval of the proposal, a view which I think is probably mistaken. I have told him that I cannot, say anything on the subject to the Iranian Government without instructions, 2. Do you wish me to do anything? There seems no reason ior His Majesty s Government to desire the establishment of such a service. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 175, repeated to India No. 75 and Kabul No, 15.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00023a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2032</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00023a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2032</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/70 ‘Proposed air service from Rome to Tehran extending later to Kabul’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-16T12:15:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a small amount of correspondence regarding a – rebuffed – request made by the Italian Government for assistance from HM Minister at Tehran (Horace James Seymour) in securing the consent of the Iranian authorities for an air service between Rome and Tehran.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00023a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>