<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000202_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T04:52:13.467Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">EXT. MlZ/kZ ' Extract from report on the Afghan Alt- Force for the period 1st February to 30th April*1943• 9* U.S.A.Stearman Trainer Aircraft . The Stearman trainer aircraft presented to the Afghan Government by the Government of the U.S*A. was flown to Kabul from Peshawar on 2bth April. The British instructors are not impressed by the construction or performance of this aircraft, and consider that the aircraft may not prove very suitable for use in Afghanistan. It is believed that an N.C.O. mechanic employed by the U.S.A. legation in Kabul has carried out an attachment to an African Air Force unit in India with a view to his being able to assist the Afghan Air Force to service and maintain this aircraft*cgpy EXT. 4312/if3. c^\qJ, SBCRET Extract from Intelligence Smmary No* 21, British Legation, Kabul, dated 29th May &gt; 1943♦ The Air Force «, 29* Presentation of an American Trainer Aircraft. Reference Sunmary No. 17 paragraph 22 . Hie Steerman trainer aircraft was formally presented to the Minister of Defence by Mr. Engert the American Minist er, at the Sherpur airfield on 25th May. Mr. Engert and Major G-.B. Enders, Military Attach^, were later entertained to tea in the Military Club by the Commandant of the Air Force.Ext. 3936/43. SECRET 6 jo {5 Extract from Weekly Suamarv No* 24. dated Feshav/ar. the 12th June. 194-3* 27* It is reported that on 26th May, the trainer aircraft which was recently presented to the .Afghan Government by the Government of the United States was flown for the first time in Kabul in the presence of the King.EXT.3641/43. SECRET. Extract from British Legation Kabul Intelligence Summary for the week ending 30th April 1943. 2£. Presentation of an Aircraft . Reference Summary No.16 paragraph 19. The Stearman trainer v/hich has been presented to the Afghan Government by the Government of the U.S.A. arrived in Kabul on 28th April from Peshawar. The aircraft was flown to Kabul by T.M.Abdur Rafcaq Khan.EXT. 3642/43. * SECRET. Extract from British Legation Kabul Intelligence Summary No.16 for the week ending 23rd April, 1943. 19. Presentation of an Aircraft. Reference Summary No.11 paragraph 30. T.M.Abdur Razak Khan, pilot, and Ghulam Mustafa Khan, mechanic, left Kabul for Peshawar on the 16th April. They are to take over the aircraft being presented to the Afghan Government by the Government of the United States of America.4s&lt;j &lt;({!(, SECRET. © E::t. 2504/43 . Ei:tract from Kabul Intelligence Suinnary, No. 11 for the v;eek ending 19th March 19A-3* 30. Presentation o f an Ai.ierican Aircraft to the Afghan Air Fo rce. Reference Summary No.4 paragraph 31* (a) Major G-.B. Enders, American Military Attach^, has proceeded to Karachi to make arrangements for the delivery of the aircraft which is being presented to the Afghan G-overnment by the U.S.A. Government. (b) The Afghan C.G.S. stated (a) on 18th :arch that this aircraft will probably be flown from Peshawar to Kabul by T.M. Abdur Razaq Khan who is proceeding to Peshawar for this purpose. It is understood that a spare engine and various other spare parts are being supplied with this aircraft.Secret. « 1 Ext.1843/1943. Extract from Kabul Intelligence Summary No. 4 for the week ending 29th January 1943. ,J, q 31. Presentation of a trainer aircraft bv the U.S.A.Government. Reference Summary No.2 paragraph 26. It is understood that this trainer aircraft will be flown from India to Kabul as soon as the Sherpur aerodrome is fit for use. The airfield at Sherpur is under snow at present and unfit for landing or taking off.scr.iyjyw. -Jv/a o .c^xtract from Report on the Afghan Air Force for the period 1st November&gt; 1942 ~ 31st Januaiyj 1943. 9* Presentation of a Trainer xJ-rcraft by the 11,3.A. Government, The Government of the United States of America are presenting one Stearman Trainer aircraft to the Afghan Government, and it is to be flown to Kabul from India as soon as the airfield at Sherpur is fit for use. This trainer aircraft is stated to be one of a batch originally intended for supply to China, but when Burma was captur ed by the Japanese, it was found that they had insufficient ceiling to be able to fly from India to China, and they were kept in store at Karachi. The Stearman trainer is a biplane with dual controls, a 225-250 H*P. radial aircooled engine, a maximum speed of 110 m.p.h. and a cruising speed of 85 m.p.he With normal tankage it can fly for &gt;§- hoursj and if a 50 gallon reserve tank is fitted 6 hour flights will be possible. The aircrafts' ceiling is about 14,000 feet, and it is estimated that it can take off from Kabul with a full petrol load, pilot, one passenger and 140 lbs. of luggage.The British instructors consider that the estimate giyep. regarding the load with which the Stearman trainer ^ can take off in Kabul is optimistic, as the high altitude of the airfields at Sharpur and lOhwaja Raw ash may reduce the carrying capacity of the aircraft.Ext« 717U/42 ‘ \ v '-- v Cjo/ Extract frorn^Intelligence BuBmary No.48 For the V;eelc Ending the 27th November 1942 , SECRET . 19. Proposal to present an American Trainer Aircraft It is believed that the U.S.A.authorities propose to ^ present a trainer aircraft to the Afghan Government as a gesture of their good will. This aircraft, if accepted, will probably be utilized for intercommunication purposes between Kabul and the provinces. A number of these aircraft are said to have arrived in Karachi but to have been found unsuitable owing to their low ceiling, for the flight between India and China.L'ost Secret. Government of India \-IV/ V WJL yj U JL XL1 U JmCX 9 External Affairs Department. Subject:- Offer of an aeroplane by the American *^**TL? Minister at Kabul to the Afghan GrOV8rn- 0 Jb©^''^ / ’ 2. The aircraft is one of a batch o-f light, low powered trainers, held at Karachi. These aircraft, known as PT17, were allotted to the Chinese and, originally, they were to |have been flown to China. The collapse of Burma prevented ithis owing to the aircraft*s restricted ceiling and range. The U.S. Air Force have endeavoured to obtain some of these aircraft for their own use as communication aircraft ! but have been unsuccessful. They have been told that the aircraft still belong to China and are earmarked for the Chinese Elementary Flying Training School which is now being formed in India. 4. It is understood that the Afghan Government are making arrangements for getting the aircraft to Kabul. This | aircraft will have no spares of any kind and will be of {little use to Afghanistan. Issue of the above has been authorised. OEPr. to the Government of India. ^.5.-7/1,,I I616b EX H'\) • 'O'O-V Ci^CMC^cA I- f? H 3V &gt;' ' . jetted to External De pt. Aes circulated ^, INW and to F» 0 » ' • _ . in any case the communication of the dontente of this document to any pensqn^Q^tGovernxnent Senvicq is authorised, it must, ^ 0 - 1 . „( } R E T U 1&lt; 157. From To CYPHER T S L S G R A M . H.M’s Minister^ Kabul Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. 2- (=&gt; Repeated to Dated # Received Government of India, External Affairs Department. Kabul, 18* 30 hours? 18th Jan&gt;1943. 01.00 hours, 19th Jan* 1943 0 16. , n For mink a 6 . Gift of* American aircraft to b Afghan Government. 2, American Legation here is not (?I think) (^■particularly) happy'; bpidy. Ebdes^whom I xr\ct personally (Vregard) as merest flat catcher is , apparently, in accordance with U. S.A. practice, directly under orders of War Department and owes no obedience (?of any) sort {? to) Minister. -He taites fullest advantage .(?of this) situation, is hardly ever here and seems to spend most of his (?fcime) in India or coming and going between India and'Kabul. &lt;; Ask to/ -/INDIA OFF/eE3* (?As to)(?air.ei*aft). (?Encies) told Military Attach© in Novemher that he had suggested to War Dept, that of twelve trainer aircraft lying at^Karachi one he presented to Afghan O-over nment and ('.the/second - placed at his disposal. My telegram_jio J J326 Kavemher feiTJ-l'BOth was hased on conversation with Engert (?who) / —^ lee eras to have '• descrihed (vtype ox ) alrcraxt ^ wrongly. . . j ' 4* War Department sanctioned 'gift Afghan Govt, but refused- to place second aircraft at Endes ? ^ disposal. Latter then suggested to War Department (without .telling Engert) that proposal (Vto) present N aircraft to Afghan Government he cancelled. 'Phis suggestion was then we think: referred t o Erg er t f o r opinion. Latter advised that gilt he made. Oixer was made to Afghan Government (Vaccordingly) and accepted. 5» Machine is of type you describe* viz., Stearman trainer biplane with dual con-’rols. Engine of 225-250 horsepower. Gelling said to he 14,000 ft. Top speed (^llO) w miles per hour. ■ Cruising speed (985) (?miles) per hour. Aircraft can stay in the -air 3 ^ hours but if 50 (?gallon). extra petrol tank is fitted it can fly for 6 hours* Aircraft can take off at Kabul altitude with full petrol load pilot passenger and 140 pounds of kit. . m i_ev 16y Jam ary ISth.^/ 2KDIA. OlTICii, TOi'ilLJX, m^DCN, S # W.l. 28th December, 1942. VwUna IN Thank you for your letter of 2.3rd December, No. D. b. p # 0.1347 regarding the American gift of an aircraft to the Afghan Government. I enclose a draft of a telegram to Kabul on this subject and I would be grateful if you could let me know as soon as you can on the telephone whether you agree tfc its terms, particularly to the statement that we need not object on military grounds to the gift. I should explain that iSnders is the United abates Military Attache at Kabul, who I know some years ago as a civilian, had a plan to run a civil air service to Tibet. He is therefore capable of any hare-brained scheme. I am sending a copy of this letter Wing Commander Gordon Finlay son, D. S.O., D.F.C., Air Ministry, King Charles Street, S.W.l*Tel. No. Abbey 3411. Ext Tpf(o) -lib* AIR MINISTRY, KING CHARLES STREET, WHITEHALL, S.W. I. 24th December, 1942. With the compliments of Wing Commander J. R. Qordon-i ’ 1 inlays on, D.S.O., D.?.C. H.A. Rumbold -Esq. , India Office, S.1.MB. SECRET. CYPHER TELEGRAM. AIRSICK 253 Desp. AIvlCS 1407A hrs. 5 Dec. 42. To. RAPDEL Washington Prom. Air Ministry Whitehall. SECRET. Airsign 253 5 Dec H.M. Minister at Kabul reports that U.S.A. Minister has received instructions from U.S.A. War Department to offer gift of aircraft to Afghan Government. He states aircraft is apparently one of number lying at Karachi which have too low ceiling for service between India and China. He adds that he informed U.S.A. Minister that he saw no objection to offer being made. 2. Request you ascertain inner history of offer and type of aircraft, and why agreed assignment procedure was not followed. 3. If type is suitable for use by R.A.P. request you seek assignment to us of any others which may be available for use in India, where only meagre transport resources available at present. Time of Origin 0945Z/5From W/Cdr. Gordon-Finlayson. Td. No. Abbey 3411. AIR MINISTRY, King Charles Street, Whitehall, S.W.1. Ext..jJ 3SCRET 23rd December, 1942 Dear I am attaching a copy of the signal from our .Delegation in Washington, replying to our query about the American gift of an aircraft to the Afghan Government. v The P.T.17 (Stearman) is a light military I two-seater aircraft with a ceiling of 17,600-ft. and r a maximum speed of 151 miles per hour. particular type of aircraft is, at any rate, of very limited value as a transport aircraft. I think that we can be satisfied that this Yo H.A. Rumbold, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, 3.W.1COPY EGOD. SECRET CYPHER TELEGRAM WX.3450 Reed. AMCS. 0145A Hrs. 12 Dec.42. To:- A.M. Y/hitehall. Prom:- RAPDEL Washington. SIGNAIR 209 Dec. 11. Your Airsign 253 Dec. 5. Inner History of report by H.M. Minister at Kabul concerning gift of aircraft to Afghan Gvt. is (I) U.3.A. Minister is able to fly and requested aircraft for himself. (II) There were at Karachi limited number PT.l^s (Stearmans) on their way to China. (III) War Dept, gave authority for one of these Stearman aircraft to be diverted to U.S.A. Minister. 2i Therefore no other types of aircraft available for assignment to U.K. at Karachi. Time of Origin: 2204Z/11 Hrsyjifo - / 3 i 3 . From Wing Commander J.R. G-ordon-F inlays on . Tel. No. Abbey 3411. AIR MINISTRY, King Charles Street, Whitehall, S.W.l. 21st December, 1942 With reference to your letter dated 28th November, attaching telegram No,226, dated 21/11/42, from Kabul reporting”the intended gift of an aircraft by the U.S.A. to the Afghan Government, the following information is provided. 2, We have telegraphed to Washington to find out the inner history of this report. Our Delegation in Washington have replied that the U.S. Minister at Kabul is able to fly and requested this aircraft for his own use; that there were a limited number of P.T.IT^s (Stearmans) on their way to China, and that the War Department in Washington gave authority for one of these aircraft to be diverted to 3. It is therefore a little difficult to see how our Minister at Kabul managed to get the idea that the aircraft was to be a gift to the Afghan Government, 4 . I would be interested to hear of any developments. Afghanistan for the Minister’s use C^Loael H.A. Rumbold India Office, S.W.1.Bring up on To Mi*. Bring up again on( 4, Jpft -' aS 7 Td. No. Abbsy 3411. tty'' 24- V AIR MINISTRY, V o, ' .SttCCki, p-f- ; °/n King Charles Street, Whitehall, S.W.l.^l tl, ‘ Xb 9th December, 1942. r\ SECRET ^T)-l Dear Vvith reference to your letter dated 28th November enclosing the copy of a telegram from Kabul number 226 dated 21st November, I have arranged to find out the history of this affair. A telegram has been sent to Washington requesting that we may be informed of the type of aircraft and the history of toe o^-^-adr- ‘ir^ 2. As soon as a reply is received I will let you know. 3. I am sending a cop.y of this letter to I.T.M. Pink at the Foreign Office.i 1 «a»3 \\' Allotted to S&gt;;terxial Copies to Forel.^ri Office . E -C- Y. E-.H..B S ._ 0. F SECRET XT i 12 ^ f -&gt;: a * .(NC\ E-EJi-SLOJ^AJI. Ce\f^ fe^r a4 Us Majesty's Minister at Kabul to Secy. o| , O^Y* &gt;tate for Foreign Affairs, India Off ioe-v^w 0 v ^C&lt;- Xiftcjcid a. &amp;&gt;'* %TuMa. e^-.a0xUA pifU-. .Dated Kabul P 16*00 hours p 22nd November, 1942* ^ ^'^&gt; v Reed. 12,60 hours, 83rd November* 1942, 4 From H 8 226&gt; War Department of U.S.A. have instructed Minister here to offer Afghan Q-overr.ment aircraft as gift* Machine is apparently of type 'brought India for service ■between India and China but ceiling bo too low for purpose intended. Minister says number of these aircraft are lying at Karachi. 2* He asked me if I saw any objection to offer being i made* I said none. I added as he (? .already) knew my personal view was that Afghans should-never be offered anything* 1 thought he would presently hirpself come”“ round to this view but this did not mean that 1 had any faintest, objection to IKS,A. Government making offer he describe'I* Wylie 22 6 November ^glst. e v ,FILE COP\ \\ JGS/FCN/EM 2276 j ( 8 ?gsg&gt;3ps) J Vp- T e l.e SECRET (S} 2334 r c )./ 1 ^ w Prom His Britamlc Majesty^s Minister at Kabul to' (COPISS Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India n v -^- CIRCULATED) Office. Dated Kabul through Peshawar, 20th April, 1933« Received 20th April, 1933, 7.15 p.m. vV S XXX Kat.odon 6 q. 2, I have now received information from unofficial, but usually reliable, source, that Afghan Government have Instructed k. ^ Fetters and Ahmed Shar (Who 5 s Who, Afghanistan, 148) to arrange purchase of some American aeroplanes. Intention is said to be to purchase 2 or 3 a year up to maximum of 25. 3. For Fetters, please see annual report of 1932, &gt;4 , paragraph 56, and Military Attache’s Diary 9, J 5rd March, V paragraph No* 1(b). He is persona grata with the War Minister and was formerly in the American air force. Macona chle 61 . iJ^cn* / ^* 5*2 t3L^*rvt P.Z. //f^l ^33 56. In Uay ?r • Fetters, agent in India for the American Caterpillar i rr actor Company, aold eight tree tore, two enow ploughs, and one road~xn&amp;king grader, to the Af^an Government for He*140,000 (Indian)* It wae characteristic of the country that this order was placed as the result of a test, by which one of these tractors drew to the top of a lew hill a gun which two elephants had failed to move, the deal being closed with a fervent embrace of Kr* Fetters by the War Minister; and that five months later, at the Accession Celebrations, W* Fetters sat in an agony of apprehension watching his tractor, as it fired uncertainly on two cylinders in its struggles to drag a gun past the I ing along the level parade ground* 67. British and Indian oil products appear to be holding their own with the Russian in this country*SECRET. Extract from Diary No .9 for the week ending 3rd March 1933* Kabul. General. (h) Mr. J.M. Fetters of the Caterpillar Tractor Company arrived at Kabul on the 25 th February to overhaul the tractors he had sold to the Afghan Government last summer. According to his own statement these tractors have proved a great success and have all been appropriated for military purposes by the War Minister. Six more tractors to be reserved for road work (grading and clearing snow) are now to be purchased.fEZ. : 2145 i r&gt;-T \ FILE COPY (53 groups) D £ 0 Y P H ,S K Q F— From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Redeived &gt;x 4 His Britannic Majesty''a Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office^ Kabul through Peshawar, 13th April, 1^33* XXX 4o3Q pom, 13th April, 1933, f yj&gt; 6 $ Frrminka 21^ 2* Afghan Government are habitually secretive regarding such matters and I have no definite information Rumours of their intention to purchase military aircraft have been current recently, see Military Attache’s diary 12, March 24th,Paragraph No«3 (b), 3 0 If 1 had discretion to use, without mentioning names, information contained in paragraph Nod of your telegram, I might be able to ascertain. jiU Maconachie 60,1550 500 1.33 DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE for FOREIGN AFFAIRS TO A-N-D -RO-BTPI-CfV-1 r TM4PA RTAffiNTr 0 ^©t-amRrhit H.M. Minister Kabul Forminka Peshawar Cypher XXX ^ - O &lt; Qj^u^r- w-&gt; /&gt;, w, J 3 P 2^2005/^ y H.M. Ambassador Washington telegraphs 4th April Begins Military attache has learned from Captain Stewart Morgan, a British friend of his in New York, that Barr Shipping Corporation have undertaken to ship six bombing aeroplanes to Kabul. 6)C. / Barr asked Captain Morgan whether he could advise as to best / / / / means of getting the aeroplanes to /. f y Kabul if permission to transport them through India should be refused Ends. / 2. Have you any information as to / intention of Afgnan Government to ^ / ' y purchase military aircraft in United States of'America? 7T7J$t TIME HECO. IN TEL CODE, X or XX DESPATCH HC T N o. or WORDS SENDER'S wmAV t L_/5 HLi fed ^ A'—COPY. (S 2402/185/97) r p.zt''' 2005 WO I DISTHIBUTION a 1 O J wJ Decypher. Sir R. Lindsay (Washington). 4th April, 1933. D. 5.5 p.m, 4th April, 1933. R. 9.30 a.m. 5th April, 1933, No. 195. Military Attach^ has learned from Captain Stewart Morgan, a British friend of his in New York, that Barr Shipping Corporation have undertaken to ship six 'bombing aeroplanes to Kabul, Mr. Barr asked Captain Morgan whether he could advise as to best means of getting the aeroplanes to Kabul if permission to transport them through India should be refused.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000202_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1976</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000202</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1976</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 5/26 ‘Afghanistan: Purchase of bombing aeroplanes from United States of America’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-16T22:49:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (39 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 41; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file is concerned with two topics. The first is a report from G Stuart Morgan regarding the intention of Barr Shipping Corporation to deliver six American bombers to Afghanistan in 1933: see folios 28-40. The second is the gift of a PT 17 (Stearman) from the United States to the Government of Afghanistan in 1943: see folios 2-27. A couple of notes regarding sales by the American Caterpillar Tractor Company to the Afghan Government can also be found in the file. The main correspondents are as follows: HM Minister at Kabul, HM Embassy in Washington, officials of the Air Ministry, officials of the Foreign Office, and officials of the India Office.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Military aircraft</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms sales</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000202#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>