<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000010_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:34:37.189Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">A*.. I Original is in Pile 16/27. Extract from a Private Demi-Official letter dated the 28th December 1933 from Major C.E. Bremner, Political Agent, Muscat. Tn Muscat - which the Sultan himself describes as shell shattered town -are a number of ruined mosques in all stages of disrepair, from a pile of stones to a roofless hut calling itself 'Masjid'. I believe you had the same sort of thing once in Bahrain before things were cleaned up. Can you tell me how, you proposes of the clean up, the religious principles (sic) of the populace were pre vailed upon. According to 8hara a Mosque once made cannot be moved which of course is interpreted by the fanaticals to mean no ruin or rubbish that has once been a Mosque can l bet ouched. A strong Ruler would of course just order it to be dofm and placate the mob by building a new Mosque elsewhere from material available from the debris. Here that is not possible. If therefore you can throw any light on how you accomplished your good work in the past I should be most grateful.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000010_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1281</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000010</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1281</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/62 Ruined mosques in Bahrain, correspondence regarding'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-30T18:12:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 5; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-4; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the following:a letter from Major Claude Edward Bremner, Political Agent, Muscat, to Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Gordon Loch, Political Agent, Bahrain, in which he reports the poor state of many of the town's mosques and enquires about any procedure of repair or removal that may have taken place in Bahrain;a reply from Loch in which he reports that he does not know of any ruined mosques that have been removed in Bahrain, commenting that to do such a thing would provoke strong feeling from the people.Folio 4 is internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Mosques</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000010#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>