<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T21:46:50.293Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">In Any farther communica- tkfti on this subject, please quote No W. /1916 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, lyondon. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop UL9 of the under-mentioned paper. Reference to previous correspondence : Letter to Foreign Office: 53 r. I Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. f\b .S . j 'Vv»_ (Simtktr loiter sent t&amp; )V**' s The Amario&amp;n Ambassador &lt; ^ 1 V ^ ’ ■ V/ ^ V-&gt; / i ...*• 't 123.MAY I9!6j oorcpliments to H1 b Majesty*® Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and, with reference to Mr. Page 1 ® note of February Bad last, transmitting the text of a telegram received from the Secretary of State in Washington relative to the refusal of the Sublime Porte to authorise American Consular officers from Aden to visit Jeddah in connection with British interests, has the honour to transmit herewith copy of a despatch, dated January 34th last, addressed to the Secretary of State by Mr.Mergenthau, together with a copy of the Ottoman note verbals,dated J nuary 33nd last, on which the telegram above referred to was based. LONDON, May SBnd 1916COPY# i January 34, 1916. The Honorable, The Secretary of State, Washington# Sir:- With reference to the Department’s telegraphies in struction HO.1578 of December 17, 1915, concerning the proposal of the British Government to have the American Consul or Vice Consul at Aden visit Djeddah from time to time in connection with the care of British interests at that place, I have the honor to transmit herewith copy and translation of a note verbale from the Sublime Porte dated January 32, 1916, No.76961/33, stating its attitude in this matter# jgs reported to the Department in my telegram of even date, the Porte states that It cannot authorize the Consul or Vice Consul at Aden to visit Djeddah for the purpose stated. I have the honor to be,Sir, Your obedient servant, (Signed) H.Morgenthau. gnr,i Q ^.£&amp; 2 . : Copy and translation as stated, in duplicate.uopy ..,29326/16., a February 16th, 1916 ^ir:- .ilh reference to the telegram, ho. ...18E A.P., from the iolitical pHiaent at ecu which was cormiuni- cated to your department by the India Office on the 9th instant, I am dir* by .ecretary award orey to state that the Ottoman Government have recently refused permission to the United /bates -onaular .^;ent at . den to visit Oeddali tc enquire into british interests at that port. ♦ This unusual actlpn on the part of the Ottoman Government would appear to confirm the report comauni c&amp;teci by the Heal dent at Aden as to the possible construction of submarines or other hostile vessels in oedciah harbour, and 1 am therefore to bring this point to the attention of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty for such investigation as they may consider desirable. 1 am, CLr, Your most obedient, humble servant. The secretary of the Admiralty.From Political Resident, Actei1 13 In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. W. 23023/16. Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. February 9th, 1916 i , With reference to your letter, P.4513, of the 10th of December last, relative to the representation of British interests at Jeddah, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edv/ard Grey to transmit to you, herewith, to be laid before Mr, Secretary Chamberlain, a copy of a Note from the United States Ambassador in London, reporting that the Ottoman Authorities have refused permission to the United States Consular Agent at Aden to visit Jeddah in connexion with British interests at that place,* Mr. Chamberlain will doubtless consider whether the inference to be drawn from this refusal, namely that British Indian pilgrims in Jeddah are not receiving good treatment from the Ottoman Authorities, and that the foodstuffs supplied to them are being commandeered, is sufficient to justify some public notice being taken of the matter in India. I am Sir Your most obedient humble Servant 10fEB1918 -) The Under Secretary of State, India Office.LONDON. February B, 1916* Sir, With reference to the Note you were good enough to address tc ice on the 14th cf December last, and tc »y reply of the 13th of that month, I have the honour to inform you that I sap in receipt of a telegram fro® the Secretary cf State in Washington to the effect that the Ambassador at Constantinople has been notified by the Sublime Ports the Ottoman Government cannot grant permission to American Consular Officials at Aden to visit Jeddah in connection with British interests at that place, I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration, Sir, Tour most obedient, humble servant, WALTER HIRES P V 'U ble The fight Hon . SIP EWAPD GPEY, Bt., K.O., A’C • ArC« Ac*Telegram from Resident at Aden. Dated 21st December 1915. nr^ /b . 1 17 0 ' ! 91 b 163 A.P. My telegram of the 8th December Mo 156 A.P. Watson has received following telegram from Lansing ' 17th. At the request of farsaa and with approval of Local Authorities Consulate may take charge of British .^9) interests at Jeddah and after Consulsijou or he may visit Jeddah from time to time to pay rent of Consular Staff and to supervise interests of British subjects in neighbourhood. 1 ' Watson will inform Turkish authorities at Jeddah of this by next mail(which is) leaving aoout Both instant. Addressed to 3.of 3.for I..repeated to Foreigi Dept. Government of India; Bombay Government. 'S5A- f*:-- \ U ,22 LECltlt v- '4v ' * * 1-M- The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ; ' and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-men Honed paper. Foreign Office, \f , 1 Q 15 . Reference to previous correspondence: Letter Foreign Office: 10 to fi VIIl’ Description of Inclosure. (Simila r tetter^en t do O-HoN 189173/15) FOREIGH OFFICE, December 14th, 1915. Your Excellency:- I have the honour to state, for Your Excellency’s information, that the Government of India have recently telegraphed to the effect that the Netherlands Government having recalled their Consular Officer at tieddah, British interests at that port now remain without protection. As Your Excellency is no doubt aware, the presence of many British Moslem subjects at deddah render that consular post of considerable importance to Ills Majesty’s Government, and I would be greatly obliged if Your Excellency would be so good as to suggest to your Government that hr. A.G. ,/atson, Acting Vice consul for the inited states at Aden, might ue authorised to visit deddah from time to time for the purpose of paying the rent of the British Vice Consular building and the wages of the Consular Staff, and generally of supervising the interests of British subjects resident in the neighbourhood. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration. Your Excellency’s most obecient, - humble servant. Excellency The Honourable W. B. Page, &amp;G • , &lt; oC. , ocC ..1 Telegram from Resident at Aden, Dated 8th December 1915. 156 A.P. Your telegram of the 7th instant. Grace Act(ing) has left Aden, Watson is far tka jarasaxi Vice Consul United States Government. Watson is a suitable person to look after British interests at Jeddah. Addressed to the S.of S.for I.,repeated to Bombay.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/521/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/521/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'P. 5085/1914 Pt 2 German War: Turkey: Jedda; British interests'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-16T22:08:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (50 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, printed reports and notes, relating to the Consulate Affairs in Jeddah. The discussion in the volume relates to the withdrawal of the British consul from Jeddah with the declaration of war with the Ottoman Empire and arrangements for the maintenance of the building and payment of staff.Further discussion surrounds correspondence with Italy and the Netherlands over such arrangments and the refusal of the Turkish Government to allow the American Consular Agent in Aden to visit Jeddah. The correspondence also discusses arrangements for the safety of British subjects conducting pilgrimage to Mecca.The principal correspondents in the volume include the Viceroy; the Political Resident, Aden, the Paymaster General's Office; the Under-Secretary of State for India and the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed in the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100038750373.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>