<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:52:16.664Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■■ iSM a ■A \ \ ORDER . In exercise of the powers conferred on me by Article 2 read with Article 4 of Regulation No.l of 1940 made by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, I hereby direct that all bullion brokers to whom notice in fnatf this behalf steiSL be sent shall produce every week before the Political Agent an account showing (a) in respect of purchases of gold, the quantity purchased, the date on which it was purchased, and the name and address of the person from whom it was purchased (b) in respect of sales of gold, the quantity sold, the date on which it was sold, and the name and address of the person to whom it was sold. Bahrain, 20th July 1942, Ed. E.B.Wakefield. H.B.M.'s Political Agent, Bahrain,(1) K.M.Sayegh &amp; Ebrahim Noono, Iraq subjects. They deal in soverigns, other gold coins and ornaments and other currencies. ( 2 ) Meneshi Ebrahim Cohen* Iraq subject. He deals in soverigns, other gold coins and ornaments and other currencies. (3) Naji Murad, Iraq subject. He is not a regular dealer in gold. He exported some gold to Iraq through the Bank when we were issuing permits, but he has stopped the gold business since the issue of permits were discontinued. (4) Haji Abdul Aziz Ali al Bassam, Saudi subject. He deals in soverigns only. (5) Khalid al Oujan, Iraq subject. He deals in soverigns only. It is said that he purchased a great quantity of soverigns during the last two months but he stopped purchasing any more since the Kuwaiti launches were searched. He is the chief importer of cigarettes in Bahrain. (6) Muhamad al Advani,£Kuwait subject, and Muhamad al Baker, Qatar They deal in soverigns and other currencies. They also act as brokers for sale and purchase of soverigns. (7) Beder al Sayer and Khalid al Sa'dun, Kuwait subjects. They deal in soverigns only. Beder al Sayer is the agent of Hilal building. (8) Hasan bin Kadhem, Qatar subject. He is the goldsmith appointed by the Municipality for testing gold ornaments. He deals in soverigns and gold ornaments. (9) Khalaf bin Musa Bahrani, Bahrain subject. He deals in gold ornaments only. He melts the ornaments and makes them in blocks which he sells to his customers. (10) Seth Jethanand, 'ritish Indian subject. He is a broker for sale and purchase of soverigns only. subject.Political Agency, Bahrain, the 27th July 1942* To K.M. Sayegh &amp; Ebrahim Noonoo, Bahrain. Meneshi ilbrahiin Cohen, Bahrain \^You are hereby given notice that, in accordance with the order of which a copy is enclosed, you should send to me before noon on 3rd August 1942 and on every subsequent Monday a statement.; of all your transactions in gold during the previous ©even days* The statement should show (a) in respect of purchases of gold, the quantity purchased, the date on which it was purchased, and the name and address of the person from whom it was purchased (b) in respect of sales of gold, the quantity sold, the date on which it was sold, and the name and address of the person to whom it was sold. Political Agent, Bahrain.Political Agency 9 Bahrain, tho 30 th July IMS* Ho.C 40* 41. To Muhamad al Advani and Muhamad al Baker. Bahrain , Beder al Sayer and Khalid al Sa'dun, Bahrain. Ttaa or# horohy given notice that, in aceerdaneo with tho order of which a copy ia enclosed, ym should send to no before noon m 3rd August IMS and on every subsequent Monday a statement of all your transaetlona in gold during the previous sev«ai days* The statement should shew (a) in respect of purchases of gold, the quantity purchased, the date on which It was purchased, and the name and address of the person from whoa it was purchased &lt;b) in respect of sales of gold, the quantity sold, the date on which it waa sold, md the name and address of the person to whom it was sold* Sd. E.B. Wakefield. Political Agent, Bahrain* mmfk) V ^*j'jr. - LJ.j*^ lira in, 3rd August, 1942. To “~ H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. . .aV — Si?, W« bog to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.C/1141, dated 30th July 1942 and have the honour to soy that, at present, we have no gold coins in our possession. Should wc huy gold coins in future, we will submit the required □tr.tomentl' We beg to remain, Your most obedient servants.«r . i K I i-ranslation of a letter dated 3rd August 1942 from Ebrahim Noono, Bahrain, to the Political Agent,Bahrain. A.C. (jb I submit below the quantity of gold which was in my ’possession and which was purchased by me after the issue of your order. The quantity of gold purchased by me up to 7th July on which date I dissolved my partner' Tolas As. ship ?/ith Khedouri Sayegh is:- 127 4 Purchased by me from 7th July up to date of your order purchased from Rashid bin Abdul Aziz of 84 11 Manama on 22-7-42- 13 7 Purchased from Taiba of Manama on 24-7-42 — 2 ' ' Fatma bint Muhd.of Manama on 24-7-42 4 4 ' ,,M Khedhuri Salih Murad of Manama on 24-7-42 10 - ' ' -do T on 24-7-42 ' ' Abdur Rahman bin Muhd. of 1 11 Muharraq on 27-7-42 2 2 243 9 Sold to Salih Sassoon Elias of Manama on 28th July 1942 1 4 242 5 Purchased from Yusuf bin Ahmad of Muharraq on 30th July 1942 Purchased from Salih Abdur Rahman of ' 2 11 on 30th July 1942 Purchased from Ghulum Husain bin Hasan of 1 5 Manamah on 31st July 1942 Purchased from Yusuf bin Yusuf Fakhro of 2 Muharraq on 31s£ July 1942 2 — Purchased from Ahmad bin Saif of Muharraq on 2nd August 1942 .... 1 4 Total 251 V YTranslation of a letter dated 3rd August 1942 from Meneshi Ibrahim Cohen, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. statement of the quantity of gold in my possession up to 20th July 1942. 222 Soverigns 1 Turkish Lira Gold weighing 18 Turkish Liras 17 soverigns purchased from Ali bin Mohsin Bahrani of Manama on 21st July. The above is the detail of the gold which up to date is in my possession. Usual Ending. A. C. In accordance with your below amm wmM Translation of a letter dated 3rd August 1942 from Ebrahim Noono to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Liras, etc. purchased by me. Soverigns . 32 I had in my possession up to date of your notice 55 purchased from Hamad al Rog &amp; Sons on 22nd July 1942 Turkish Liras 23 I had in possession up to date of your notice 1 purchased from Ahmad bin Ahmad Alaiwat on 28th July 1942 24 Russian gold coin s 29 - 2 - I had in my possession up to the date of your notice. American gold dollars . 3 American gold dollars (one worth 20 dollars and two JJ* dollars A. C. I submit below a statement showing the account of soverigns, Turkish 20 50 n ' Khedhouri Salih Murad on 22nd July 1942 ' Chaturbuj broker on 22nd July 1942 157 each).Translation of a letter dated 3rd August 1942 from Muhamad al Advani and Muhamad al Baker, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain, With reference to your notice dated 23rd July 1942 regardin e transaction in gold and in reply to your honour to inform you that we have ceased dealing in gold some time before the issue of your notice, that is, we have neither sold or purchased any. If we deal in gold in future we will submit s statement of the sales and purchases in accordance with your order. Usual Ending. A. C. letter N 40, dated 30th July 1942, we have theAshar - Basrah s _ { aj *+hj) ' L»l .jJt — -— y ♦r-6v\ Bahrain, 5th .August, 1942. H. B, M f s. Political Agent, Bahrain Dear Sir, In reply to your letter No.c/1168 dated 4th. instant, in connection with my letter dated 3rd. August 1942 regarding the gold, I beg to inform you that the particulars given to you therein were held by me before your notice No.c/U21 dated 27th. July 1942 has been issued, ^ I also beg to state that, that outstanding were handed to me by my junior partner Mr• Ebrahim Noono as a partial payment of my account on liquidating our partneship,and since then, I have done no further new transaction. Telegrams : SAGNON Telephone No. 02 - 571 P. O. B. No. 2 JtMouri ll?- Ill 4*0 M sjuj. To1 jit) -ft Translation of a letter dated 10th August 1942 from Ebrahim Nonoo to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A. C. I beg to state below the details of the gold which I bought from 3rd to 10th August 1942. Tolas As. I*' 251 13 balance of gold as stated in my letter of 3rd August 1942. 10 Bought from Salam bin Muhd of Manama on 4/8 7__ ' n Ali bin Ahmad Irani ' ' 252 14 14-4 sold to Hashim bin Sayed Hasan Bahrani of Manama on 4th August. 251 l5l 3 4 Bought from Hasan bin Yusuf Bahrani of Manamah on 5th August. 1 ±2&gt; Bought from Abdur Rahman bin Muhamad of Manamah on 5th August 256 ■' 5i~ 10 sold to Ali bin Muhamad Kanu of Manama on 7th August 1942. 255 1 1 3 11F 13 bought from Jafar bin Abdul Hasan Bahrani of Manamah on 7th August 1942 Bought from Abdul Qadir bin Ali Akbar Irani of Manamah on 9th August 1942 6 Bought from Taibeh bint Mubarak al Yakub of Manama on 9th August 1942 ^c\A HV/ 262l lii Prom;- f/ ul ' K. M* Saye^a, Bahrain, H. B, M*s Political Agent, Bahrain Bahrain, 10th.August, 1 942. . 5 - Dear Sir, y. With reference to your notice Ho.c/1121 dated 27th*July 42, I beg to statefckacfc that I have made no further transactions in gold for the week ending icth.August 1942. I shall be very grateful if you will kindly let me know if it is necessary for me to submit informations weekly in the event of not having made any transactions the previous week, as in this case* Thanking you in anticipation. Obediently,L-, Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th August 1942 To K#M, Sayegh, Bahrain, Memorandum . Reference your letter dated 10th August 1942. 2. You should In any case submit a return showing the balance of gold in your possession, whether any fresh transactions have taken place during the week or not. for Agent 7 Bahrain.Confidential. Reference the list of dealers in gold which was previously submitted, the following two names should be added to it: 1. Chaturbuj Moolchand, British Indian subject residing at Manamah. He is a broker for sale and purchase of soverigns only. 2. Ratumal Kanyanumal, British Indian subject residing at Manamah. He is a merchant and deals in soverigns and gold bars. Abdul Aziz al Bassam whose name was included in the list is still dealing in sovereigns which he purchases from the Nejdi smugglers who come from the mainland. iTranslation of letter dated 17th August 1942 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Ageht, Bahrain. A.C I submit below the gold transactions upto 17th August 1942: Tolas . 262 As per previous statement Purchased from Hamad bin Sh:Abdulla bin Isa of Manama on 11-8-42 ' M Rahmat bin Haider servant of Mohd.Tahir Sherif of manaraa on 11/8 2 H M Sultan bin Muhd.Sami’ of Manama on 13-8-42 ” ” Abdul Qadir Khunji of Manama on 13-8-42 In stock as per previous statement No purchases Annas . ~ 4 ? In stock as per previous statement Purchased from Abdulla bin Husain of Muharraq on 16-8-42 In stock as per previous statement No purchases 24 25 Russian pounds 29-! In stock as per previous statement No purchases. American Dollars (gold&amp; 3M0#C/ 1290 * Political %gmty 9 Bahrain, th« 26th August 1942• f© Ratumal Kanyanumal 9 Bahrain. Tan nr« harahy giiran not lea that, in neoordanoa with th® ardor of which a copy in encloaod, yon ahould aai!id to m hoforc noon on 3Xat &gt;inguat 1942 and on ©very mih#«€|u©tit Monday © atatacaorit of ©XX your tron©action© in gold daring th© pr©viou© ©©van days* Th© 8%®%mm% should ©how (a) in raspaet of ptrehaa©© of goM, the o uantity pm*ch©sM f the data on which it wa© purchased, m&amp; the mm© and ©ddraac of the person fro® wheel it mm purchased &lt;b) in respect of mXm of gold, the quantity ©old, the dot© m which it wa© sold, and the mm* and add?*©© of the person to whom it was ©old* Purchases of gold ornaments should be shown saparately.MO*C/ 1291, Te Politict&amp;X Bahrain, the 26th August Haji Abdul Aziz All Al Bassam, Bahrain. Ttm ere hereby given notice thet f in eccoraence with the order of vhieh e copy ie encloeed, yeti should said to ise before noon on Slot August 1942 end m every subeecfuent Monday « statement of ell your transactions in gold during the previous seven days* the statement should shoe (e) in respect of purchases of gold, the q uentity purchased, the date on shieh it ves purchased, end the name end adless of the person from whom it was purchased (h) in respect of sales of gold, the quantity sold, the date on which it was sold, and the name end address of the person to idiom it was sold* Purchases of gold ornaments should be shown separately# ev- r' forJPolitical Agent, Bahrain* zTo H. B. M’s Politioal Agent, Bahrain Sir, K* M. Sayegh, Bahrain, 24th. August I beg to inform your honour that I have done no transactions in gold during the week ending today.ntsr ^\to- A. To H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain K. M. Sayegh, B ahrain,31st.August 1942. Sir, I beg to inform you that the outstanding of gold on hand shown in my letter dated 3rd. instant not changed and further fresh transactions not done for the week ending 30/8/42. Yours Obe&lt;y.ently,p . , . . . : — ■ ■ ■ - - ^■\ ji 2ft. nib Translation of letter dated 31st August 1942 from Ibrahim Nonoo Bahrain to the Eolitical Agent, Bahrain. A. C. ; my I submit below the quantity of gold in/possession upto date. As. Gold bullion as per my letter of 24/3/42 Gold ornaments M M ' ' »» ' bought from Haider bin Akber Irani of Manama on 25/8 M bought from Ali bin Hasan Bahrani of Sitra on 27/8 ' bought from Ali bin Riqraq Bahrani of Manama on 27/8 ' ' bought from^Sulaiman bin Shaikh Dawood Iraqi of Manama on 27/8 Gold soveriegns as per my letter of 24/8/42 No purchases or sales Turkish.gold pounds as per my letter of 24/8/42 No purchases of sales Russian ;g61d pounds as per my latter of 24/8/42 No purchases or sales American gold dollars as per my letter of 24/8/42 No purchases or sales. 4 &gt; tt in Tolas 140 132 6 279 157 25 29 * 3 7 3 10A ' , ( iTranslation of letter dated 31st August 1942 from 3adr Sayir Khalid as Sadoon, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. | A.C. We have the honour to submit herewith our statement of gold upto date. IT. E.HMiflHHHHHi ih|«v Bahrain, 7th. September 1942. To H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain Sir, I beg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions in gold took place for the week ending 6th. September 1942. Yours Obediently, ours Ob^l.. o ^? e f e ff 1 ? ee 70XLr regarding Jethanand + Xt ?? pe ? r f ' tlia ' fc . 1:1118 is a local money broker, who previously £ in f oP(i ’ tu1: now . in n °tes. I enclose herewith a number oi Bills or Entry covering some of his activities, but pleased return these as they are not supposed to leave this office. Believe me, Yours sincerely, To: - M.G.Dixon Esquire, I.C.S., The Agency, PANAMAS.Ijk?- /.FXj- To K. M. Sayegh, Bahrain,I4th«September 1942. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain Sir, I beg to inform have been made by me your honour that no for the week ending fresh transactions in gold I3th.September 1942. You£s Obediently, £(?• /SUo Translation of letter dated 14th September 1042 from Ebrahi Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A. o. -•* I submit herewith the amount of gold in my possession. Tolas Gold bullion as per my letter dated 7-0-42 140 ' ornaments ' ' n ' ' Sale of gold to Bahiyyeh Ibrahim of Manama on 9/! ' ' ' M Joliet Ibrahim ' ' M M Purchased gold ornaments from Isa Ahmed Mallal of Manama on 9/9 ' M ornaments from Syed Hasan Syed Yusuf of Muharraq on 9/9 Sold gold to Ali bin Husain Hasawi of Manama Sold gold to Yusuf Yaqob Shami’ of Manama, Clerk in the Eastern Bank on 10/9 238 5 11 5 8 271 13 1 4 15 274 &gt; 27 13 246 3 -X- Gold sovereigns as per my letter dated 7/0/42 157 No purchases Turkish gold pounds as per my letter dated 7/9/42 25 No purchases Russian gold pounds as per my letter dated 7/9/42 29j No purchases American gold dollars as per my letter dated 7/9/42 3 b. iii • i ■M—ga1 '?//'&gt; ■ A . Confidential. . / 7- 9_ o-v No. iUk of 1361 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Ramadhan 1, 1361 September 12, 1942. H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- On Thursday 10th September^acting on certain informa tion obtained by me, a watch was kept on the office of Hassan Kadhim, a local goldsmith who is authorised by the Bahrain Government to weigh gold. Two men, Khalaf bin Musa and Amin bin Hassan, Bahrain subjects, came to the office of Hassan Kadhim in the morning and took from him a piece of gold weighing 17 tola and 6 annas, worth Rs. 1,216/4/-. They took this gold to one Hussain bin Mohamed Kowaiti at the shop of Haj Ali Hasawi. Hussain bin Mohamed arrived here about 10 days ago. The Police had reason to believe that he came to Bahrain to buy and export gold. Hussain bought the gold and paid the price to the two brothers who returned to the shop of Hassah Kadhim to whom they paid the money. Plain clothes police were watching the shop of Haj Ali Hasawi and reported these movements to Sub-Inspector Abdul Karim of the State Police who came to the shop and asked Haj Ali for a list of the gold in his possession. On being told by Haj Ali that he could not account for the gold in his possession because it belonged to Hussain bin Mohamed Kowaiti^Sub-Inspector Abdul Karim asked that his safe should be ppened and counted the gold in it. The safe contained 85'tolas of gold ornaments worth approximately between Rs. 4,000 and Rs. 5,000. Hussain bin Mohamed Kowaiti, was present during the inspection and stated that he had bought the gold but on'being asked to produce his register he said he did not keep an account. During this investigation it was found that Mohamed bin Hussain had purchased gold from one Ali bin Hussain, Hasawi. Ali bin Hussain when questioned stated that he too did not keep any register. It is proposed that the Police should prosecute the Kowaiti, Hussain bin Mohamed for trading in gold and failing to keep an account and failing to report his transactions to the proper authorities in contravention t) * 3 of Bahrain Government proclamation No. 22&gt; f bf 1361 which was issued on 9th July 1942. This proclamation was a general one not a notice sent to certain individuals only. Adviser to the Government■Jl ^QQ^^dential♦ Political Agency, 12^^/1104• Bahrain, the 17th Bepta'nber 1942. To The Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Memorandum. In his statement of dealings in gold during the week ending 14th September 1942, Ibrahim Nonoo reports that he made the following sales j- (a) 11 tolas to Bahiyyeh Ibrahim of Manama on September 9th. Cb) 5 '8 annas to Joliet Ibrahim of Manama on M (c) 27 n 13 w to Ali bin Husain Hasawi of Manama through broker Jafar Abdul Hasan of Manama on September 10th. 2. As regards (c) above, reference is invited to your memorandum No.1664, dated v 12th September 1942, to which a reply will be sent shortly. In regard to (a) and (b), enquiries as to the ultimate destination of the gold sold may kindly be made by the police, if you consider that there Is any likelihood of its being intended for eventual export. for Political Agent, Bahrain.w No ,cw T Political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th September 1942# To Hatumal Kanayamal, Bahrain# Memprandua# Reference my Notice No.C/1290, dated 26th August 1942. 2# The statement of your transactions for the week ending 7th September 1942 has not been received and should be forwarded without any further delay# for“Political Agent, Bahrain.xfk- liusain bin Mohammed, a Kuwait subject, states that he came to Bahrain about 10 days ago to buy gold. If permitted he will ship it, if not he will dispose of it in Bahrain. He bought some gold from Husain Kazim through Khalaf, a shop keeper and broker, and also from others. While he was in the bazaar buying gold, he was seized by the Police with the gold and taken to the Police Station. The sellers were called and their statements were taken. He states that 8 days have passed, and no action has been taken. He requests an interview if convenient. The above has been reported to A.P.A. and the Adviser by the Police Department. 4 ? P.S. j- /iS ^ ^ A&amp;r-Msy-ozim- Political Agency^ Bahrain, the 19th 3eptemberl942• To The Political Agent, Kuwait* Memorandum * On September 10th the Bahrain police raided the shop of one Haj Ali Hasawi and found there a safe contain ing 85 tolas of gold ornaments, worth between Rs*4000/- and Ra*5000/-, belonging to Hussain bin Mohamed Kuwaiti* The latter admitted having bought this gold but on being asked to produce a register failed to do so* He subsequently admitted that he intended to export it to Kuwait* 2* Hussain bin Mohamed intended to smuggle gold from Bahrain into Kuwait and thereby break the law of both Govern ments, I shall be glad if you will kindly ensure that he is not again, for the duration of the war, given a visa for Bahrain* Political Agent, BahrainI&amp;&gt;,.*PA412« Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th September 1942 To The Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Memorandum . Reference your memo No.1664, dated 12th September 1942, on the subject of gold purchased in Bahrain by Hussain bin Mohamed Kuwaiti. 2. It is impossible to prosecute Hussain bin Mohamed under the law as it stands, for whereas the Bahrain Gov- Jib* 1IL emment Notice No.22/1361 , dated July 23rd 1942, applies hi to all Bahrainis dealing in gold, the Order which I passed on the 20th July 1942 to cover foreigners applies onlyto those persons dealing in gold to whom a Notice is sent. As no notice was sent either to Hussain bin Mohamed or to Haj All Hasawi, these two persons cannot be prosecuted for infringing the Order. Nor will it be possible to prosecute Hussain bin Mohamed for a breach of the Agency Order dated 30th July 1941 (No.l of 1941), which prohibi ted the export of gold from Bahrain except under an Kxport Licence issued from the Agency, because there is no evi dence, for legal purposes, that Hussain bin Mcharaed in tended to export the gold if he did not obtain a licence; he states of course that he did intend to apply for an export licence unless he could obtain an adequate profit by selling the gold locally. 3. However, although no prosecution can be under taken, there is every reason to suppose that Hussain bin Mohamed did intend to smuggle the gold out of Bahrain into Kuwait and thereby break the law in both places. I am therefore asking the Political Agent, Kuwait to ensure that no visa is again granted to him to visit Bahrain. This should, I think, act at present as a sufficient deterrent to others with similar designs; if ever gold again began to leave Bahrain in considerable quantities,2 we could consider tightening up the present legislation. 4. The police, for whose efforts in this case I am v grateful, will no doubt ensure that Hussain bin Mohamed leaves Bahrain without any gold Political Agent, Bahrain.K. M* Saye^i, Bahrain,21st.September 1942 * To His Britanio Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain Sir, I beg to state to your honour that I have done no fresh transactions in gold for the week ending 20/9/1942.place in this week.&lt;? It- Translation of letter dated 21 st September 1942 from jbrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain, A. C. I submit herewith the statement of gold in my possessior Tolas Annas Gold bullion as per my letter dated 14/9/42 140 ^ M ornaments »t n Purchased from Saad al Hamud of Mptharraq on 14/9 Mulla Abbood Abdur Reza Iraqi of Manama on 16/9 ' Abdulla bin Ghuloom Irani of Manama on 17/9 Abdul Malik bin Mohammed of Muharraq on 18/9 Jafar bin Ahmed of Dar Chulaib on 20/9 M Salih bin Ahmed of Halayil on 20/9 105 niV 10i, ' Hajee bin Ali bin Motar of uharraq through Jafar Abdul Hasan-on 20/9 5 9 7 si 1 257 157 Sovereigns as per my letter of 14/9/42 Ho purchases Turkish gold pounds as per my letter of 14/9/42 25 No purchases Russian gold pounds as per my letter of ' 29-/ No purchases American gold dollars M n ” ' ' 3 No purchasesf' C 5 /?. M t x b No. /7A^ of 1361 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Ramadhan 10, 1361 September 21, 1942 H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memor and uni: - With reference to your memorandum No. C/1412 dated the 19th September, 1942. I appreciate the reason why a prosecution cannot be made against the persons referred to in your letter. I will make every endeavour to ensure that the gold purchased by Hussain bin Mohamed is not smuggled out of Bahrain. j In connection with the Political Agent’s Order dated 20th July 1942 I have the following comments to make. According to this Order no foreign dealer in gold is compelled to submit a return of his transactions unless a copy of the notice has been served on him. Most of the persons dealing legally and illicitly in gold are foreigners, a large proportion of them are Kuwaitis and Iraqis. People who come down here to buy gold intending to smuggle it out of Bahrain do not advertise their activities and it is not generally known that they are dealing in gold therefore it is likely that they have not been or will not be served with a notice drawing their attention to the need for registering their purchases and sales of gold. This state of things seems to defeat the objent of the new regulation. Would it not be possible to alter the wording of your notice in such a way that it becomes a general Order applicable to all persons trading in gold instead of an Order which only affects persons who receive a copjr of2 the notice? If this alteration is impossible could you issue an Order compelling all foreigners who trade in gold to submit their names to you with some punish ment for failing to do so? The Bahrain Government will be glad to co-operate in any such regulation by taking similar action or, if this would assist, to issue a further Order in these lines in which case perhaps you could obtain authority for similar measures being enforced against foreigners. Adviser to the Governmentfit A No.C/1440 , To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd September 1942. / Menashi Ebrahim Cohen, Bahrain. Memorandum . Reference your letter dated 21st September 1942. 2. Information is required not merely of the gold in your possession, but of all your dealings in gold during the week. If you have had no such dealings in any week, the fact should be stated. r ' v &lt; for Political Agent, Bahrain. *1 M&amp; jmb To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd September 1942. Hatumal Kanayamal, Bahrain. Memorandum &lt; 0 Reference your letter dated 21st September 1942. 2. Information is required, not merely of your purchases, but of all your dealings in gold during the week, including sales* If no sales have been effected during the week, the fact should be stated. V for Political Agent, Bahrain. r r,No,C/1499 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 5th October 1942 D The Adviser to the Government Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference your Memorandum No*1729 dated 21st September 1942 2. Before framing my order of 20th July 1942 I considered carefully the advisability of making it a general one applicable to all persons trading in gold. The reason why I did not issue such a general order was that it would have involved too much work for myself and my office scrutinising weekly returns, seeing that they had been submitted by everyone concerned, and checking them against information received from other sources. I decided that it would be better to demand returns only from a few of the lead ing bullion brokers - men who have the capital to deal in large sums at a time. I thought that if the main channels through which gold flows through Bahrain could be dammed, subsidiary channels could, in practice, be ignored. 3. I am entirely satisfied with the results so far achieved. Partly owing to the orders issued in Bahrain, partly owing to the Shaikh of Kuwait’s prohibition of imports of gold by sea, and partly owing to your own efforts to check smuggling, the export of gold from Bahrain has practically ceased. That this is so is evident from the fact that for some weeks now the price of sovereigns has remained steady at a rate which is still considerably lower than the rates in Kuwait or Basrah. In other words, though the incentive to smuggling remains, smuggling has not been taking place, since, if it were taking place, the price of gold in Bahrain would have shown a tendency to rise. 4. No doubt smuggling will begin again, but when it does the fact will at once become obvious from the sudden rise in the / locallocal price of gold - a rise which is inevitable when heavy purchases are made. ’When this happens I shall probably issue an order forbidding the sale of gold, except under a permit, to any foreigner not resident in Bahrain. If the Bahrain Government would agree, in such circumstances, to issue a parallel notification, I think we should be able to register a further score against the brotherhood of smugglers. The advantage of such an order is that it would not involve me or my office in additional work. However, I would prefer to keep such an order in reserve, to be issued if there is a recrudescence of smuggling, rather than issue it now when all is quiet on that particular front. Political Agent, Bahrain.A A ■ K. M. Sayegh, Bahrain,28th.S ept ember 1942. To H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to inform you that no transactions in gold took place by me for the week ending 27th.September 1942. L Yours Obediently,Translation of letter dated 2Rth September 19-^ from Sbrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Banram. I beg to submit my stateme gold:- Gold bullion as per my letter of 21/9 ' ornaments M ' ' M Tola s Annas 140 117 4 ' ' purchased from Abdul vVahab bin Juma of Manama on 25/9 Sovereigns as per my No purchases Turkish gold pounds No,,purchases Russian M letter dated 21/9 M It II M M II II II No purchases American gold .dollars'' No purchases 157 29- 3 U.E IBahrain,5th.October 1942. % 4?. To His Britanio Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain Sir, This is to inform your honour that I have done no transactions in gold during the last week ending 4th.October 1942. Your s ,pb edi i^nt ly, Froms- K. M. Sayegh, Bahrainto-l* /&gt;2&gt;) Translation of letter dated 4th October ;942 from Ratumal Kanayamal, Bahrain to the Bolitical Agent, Bahrain. -l beg to state that during this week I bought an ornament weighing 2% liras for Rs.71/- f-om Abdul All bin Lhalifa of Romman on 29-9-42, which I sold it on the same day to Mosa as-Sayig of Manama for Rs.72/8/-. A. C. U.E.jTranslation of letter dated ? Ramadhan 1361 from Dalmodardas, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.C. I beg to state that I bought ornaments from Has an bin Mohammed of Askar for Rs.52/- on 20th Ramadhan. I also beg to say that I melted the gold in possession weighing 3 tolas and 5 annas, which &gt;old to Ibrahim Nonoo. U.E.S-15. 2nVi-_ \!^&gt; B ahrain, 12tii. October 1942. His Britanio Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, Ibeg to inform your honour that I have done no transactions in gold during the week ending Ilth.October 1942. Khedouri Menashi Sayegh.• Translation of letter date^l 12 th October 1942 from Badr as-3ayir and ;2ialid as Sa loon, Bahrain to P.A. ,• Bahrain. A.C. Te' beg to submit our statement of golds- In stock Nil Purchases Nil Bales Nil r.r.K, M. Sayegli, Hilal Building, Manama, Bahrain,I9th•October 1942. To, His Britanic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrain 7 ! 1 /“ I I # O Sir, I beg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions in gold dealt by me during the week ending I8th. of October 1942. Yours Obediently,/&lt;/{ f-zy K. M. Sayegii, Hilai building,Manamah, Bahrain,26th.October 1942. To, His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain &amp; Dear Sir, I beg to inform you that I have done no business in gold during the week ending 25th.October 1942.C! /./{. /Tf &lt;/?/ I? ~ Translation of letter dated 26th October 1932 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.C. I submit my statement of gold for this week:- Tolas Annas Gold bars as per my letter of 19/10 260 lit ' ornaments u ” ” ' M 28 11 , 289 ej/ Purchased gold from Mohammed bin Ahmed Afghani of Manama on 19/10 10 Gold purchased from Rattomal Kayanamal of Manama on 21/10 8 14 Gold purchased from Sarah bint Ahmed of Manama on 21/10 12 j Gold purchased from Abdulla bin Abdur Rahim of Manama on 21/10 20 9 Gold purchased from HaiderAlibhai of Manama on 21/10 1 4 Gold purchased from Damoderdas B. of Manama through Hasham Abdun n a bi of Manama on 21/10 1 3 Gold purchased from Abdulla bin Mosa of Manama on 23/10 2 ll| - 325 Gold sold to Mohammed bin Rashid of Manama on 23/10 5 320 1 Gold purchased from Mohd.Iqbal of Bapco on 23^10 14 Gold purchased from Dhamanmal Isardas of Manama on 23/10 22 6 Gold purhcased from Mary Ibrahim Cohin of Manama on 23/10 6 8 Total 362 15 / Sovereigns as per my letter of 19/10 157 / 4 No purchases Turkish gold Liras as per my letter of 19/10 25 \/ No purchases Russian gold pounds as per my letter of 19/10 29£\/ No purchases American gold dollars as per my letter of 19/10 3 / No purchasesf, 'f K. M. Sayegii, Hilal Bullding,Manama, Bahrain ,3*fd. November 1942. To, His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, This is to inform your honour that no fresh transactions in gold took place by me for the week ending 2»&amp;.November 1942. JdC- tli I I 1 ! 4 *1 P&gt; K. M. Sayegh, Hilal Building,Manama, Bahrain,9th.Novernier 1942. To, His Britanic Majesty f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to state to your honour and confirm that the outstanding of bullion shown in my letter of 3 rd.August 1942 , has been sent to my Basra Office through the Bank in accordance with your kind order. I further beg to state to your honour that no fresh transactions in gold took place by me for the week ending 8 th.November 1942 .K. M. Sayegh, Hilal Bullding,Manama, Bahrain,I6th.November 1942. To, His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to state that no fresh transactions in gold bullion took place by me for the week ending I5th.November 1942. Yours Obediently, v' !\Translation of letter dated 16-11-42 from Ratoomal Kanayamal, Bahrain to the P.A., Bahraift. I beg to show you my purchases of gold during this week:- Gold purchased on 27th Shauwal 1361 weighing 9^ Liras. Gold purchased on 1st Dil Qada 1361 from Ali Mansoor Rigrag of Manama weighing 2 Liras. A.C (l^ v c o Translation of letter dated 16-11-42 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to.the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.C. I beg to submit the account of gold for this week. Gold bullion as per my letter of 9/11 Gold ornaments' ' ' ' ' Gold sold to Ibrahim Yusuf Salih of Manama on 10/11 Gold sold to G.M. Khan of Manama on ll/ll ' ' ' Selim Ibrahim Nonoo Gold bar of 70 tolas delivered to the Eastern Bahk for shipment to Basra as per your order Sovereigns as per my letter of 9/11 One sovereign purchased from Ahmed bin Jasim of Muharraq on 9/11 Turkish gold Liras as per my letter of 9/11 No purchases Tolas 362 Russian gold pounds ' ' No purchases American gold dollars ' No purchases »i »i u it M It 158 1 159 25 29j 3 U.E. Annas 15 10 11* 373 10* 8i . 373 2 10 372 8 2 4 370 4 70 300 4Bahrein, November 19, 1942 aGOOUNT op gold purchased and sold 11-13/16 Tolas of Gold mentioned in my statement dated November 11, 1942 on ? Hanna Christian, Goldsmith on the evening of November 10th, xor /mieh he advanced me Rs.10/-. Afterwards he refused to accept my gold and the matter is still in dispute. Gold being in my possession. Dil-^ad _ 3 3 Nose ornament - weight 3/16 Tola ) bought from Mohd bin Salim. ) ) Pair, Bar Rings,weight 3/4 Tola ) bought from Rashed bin Mohd. ) Broken piece out of a neclance ) weight 1/2 Tola. ) bought from Yousuf bin Abdullah. ) ) Nose ornament - weight 5/16 Tola ) bought from Abdullah bin Kambar. ) 1 Pinger Ring - weight 1/4 Tola ) bought from Sabz Goldsmith. Pinger Rings - weight 7/16 Tola ) bought from Khalil bin Bbrahim. ) Gold Coins - weight 1-3/8 Tolas ) bought from Meryam bint Hassan Total weight of this gold was 1-3/4 Tolas. I cleaned it and melted it and only 1-3/8 Tolas of pure gold came out. This was sold to Mohd Khan Driver on 6th Dil-Qad. Sold to Hussain, Gold and Silver ) Dealer, weight 1/4 Tola on ) 6th. Dil-Qad. Total weight of this gold was 1-13/16 Tolas, I cleaned it and melted to get pure gold and it came out 1-1/8 Tolas only. THIS IS IN MY POSSESSION YET UNSOLD, y BAMb'bAft dASs B'. KANAKA, BAHREIN. cC ■ I til, ini m ..M W.Mtfill m h ir 1*1 Bahrein, November 22nd, 1942. AOOOUNT OP GOLD PURGHASEB AND SOLD 11-13/16 Tolas of Gold mentioned in my statement dated November 4 :^ , an ? 1942, was sold to Hanna Christian, Goldsmith, and the matter is still in dispute. Gold being in my possession. The last item in my Statement dated November 19, 1942, stating that I had 1-1/8 Tolas of cleaned gold. I have sold this gold today 13th Dil-Qad (November 22nd. 1942) to Jassim bin Mohd - servant of Shaikh Khalifa. “damodar mss b. ~ MANAMA, BAHREIN. atHsauus&amp; . wv in K. M. Sayegh, Hilal Bullding,Manama, Bahrain, 2 3^. November 1942. To, His Brit4nic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to inform you that I have done no fresh transactions in gold for the week ending 22nd.November 1942.'■4 1 'I His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, ^eg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions in gold bullion took place by me during the week ending 29 /'n/' , 942 . Yours Obediently,K. M. Sayegii, Hilal Bullding,Manama, Bahrain,7th.December 1942. I beg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions in gold has been tsken by me during the week ending bth.December 1942. v v~U V 1m Translation of letter dated 7/12/42 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.G. I beg to submit my statement of gold for this week:- Tolas Annas ornament s M M ” ” ft »» purchased from Ali bin Isa Sabbagh of Manama on 2/12 sold to Jasim Kadhmawi of Manama on 2/12 purchased from Syed Sharaf Alawi of Bugaddeh on 2/12 purchased from Syed Hilal bin Syed Ali of Bugaddeh on 2/12 Purchased from Mohammed Buchlaibi of Muharraq on 3/12 sold to Jasim Kadhmawi of Manama on 4/12 purchased from Isa bin Ahmed Khajeh of Manama on 6/12 Sovereigns as per my letter of 30/11 Purchased from Salman Abdulla Zayani of Manama on 4/12 Turkish gold Liras as per my letter of 30/11/42 No purchases Russian gold pounds as oer my letter of 30/11/42 No purchases American gold dollars as per my letter of 30/11/42 No purchases D - E - 292 15 15 308 - 8# 15 309 7i 5 309 5 10 15 316 ei 315 12 316 5^ 160 !_ 161 25 29*!fK. M. Sayegh, Hilal Building,Manama, Bahrain, 1 4tii. December 1942. To, His Britanic Majesty’s Political iigent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to inform you that no fresh transactions in gold took place by me during the week ending I3th.December 1942. Yours Obediently,t (w) Translation of letter dated 14-12-42 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A. C. I beg to submit my statement of gold:- . Tolas Annas Gold bullion as per my letter of 7/12 292 15 m ornaments ” ti it II 23 6^ 316 $2 Gold sold to Mohd. bin Rashid bf Manama on 10/12 1 ..1=2. 315 4 Gold purchased from Abdur Rasool bin Ali of Manama on 13/12 2 8 317 12 Sovereigns as per my letter of 7/12 161 No purchases Turkish gold Liras as per myletter of of 7/12 No purchases 25 Russian gold pounds as my letter of 7/12 29^- No purchases American gold dollars M ' M 3 No purchases U.E.N o «C/191g« political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th December To Mi’. B. Damodar Dass, Manama, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your statement of gold purchases dated 13th December 194«. 2. The total oi the various items bought by you does not tally with the amount of gold declared to be in your possession. *3. please let me know as early as possible what the correct position is. for political Agent, Bahrainju&gt;-'A To, CD Bahrein, December 20, 1942. His Britannic Majesty f s Political BAHREIN. Agent, /« Sir, I am in receipt of your Memorandum No.0/1912 dated 17th December 1942. I very much regret for the error in my statement dated December 13th. 1942. The total weight of the various items bought by me = 9 Tolas + 1^/16 Tola of gold which I declared to be in my possession on that date, i peg to submit a Revised Statement dated December 13th. 1942 and assure you that such mistakes will not reoccur. Hope you will kindly excuse. Thanking you in anticipation. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant DAMODAR DAS'S bT ’ MANAMA, BAHREIN. -P*° * I also enclose herewith another Statement showing all details from Dec.13th. till today.STATEMENT OP G-OLE PURCHASED AND SOLD Bahrein, December 20, 1942. 9 Tolas and 1-g/16 Tola of Cold referred to my Revised Statement dated December 13th. 1942, also submitted today, was sold to one Jamna Pass, Goldsmith, on Dil-Haj 3th. Di' Ha;j 1 7 1 7 1 8 1 Tola Anna Small piece of gold, broken in shape, bought from Mozo bint Ibrahim. Neck Tawiz, bought from Ibrahim bin Hamad Hadi. Piece from broken neclace, bought from Ali bin Abdulla. Neclace - bought from Hassan bin Sazim. Weight ) Sold to Jamna Pass, ) Goldsmith, on Dil-Haj 0 - 3 - ) 5th. ) 0 - 5 - ) ) ) ) 0 - 8 - ) Sold to Jamna Pass, ) Goldsmith, on Dil-Haj ) 9 th. 2 - 4 - ) ) N.B . Please note that there is no balance outstanding with me till today (December 20th. 1942). — DAM0DA&amp;' DAHS’”'B' MANAMA, BAHREIN,&lt;*» MBslmim Am* qht'A- © To, His Britanio Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. K. M. Sayegh, Hilal Building,Manama, Bahrain,21st.Dec.1942. Dear Sir, I beg to inform you that I have done no transactions in gold during the week ending 20th.December 1942.Translation of letter dated 21-12-42 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A. C. I beg to submit my statement of gold for this week:- Gold bullion as per my letter of 14/12 M ornaments n n M ” Gold ornaments sold to Abdulla bin Rashid of Manama on 15/12 Gold purchased from Suleman Sh: Daoud goldsmith of Manama on 16/12 ' ' from Mohad.bin Hasan and Abdulla bin Ahmed of Muharraq on 16/12 10 12/ 330 1 Gold sold to Tuffahah Yaqob Nisan of Manama on 17/12 1 329 1 Tolas Annas . 292 ’ 15 24. 13 317 12 2 Sovereigns as per my letter of 14/12 No purchases Turkish gold Liras M M M ' No purchases Russian gold pounds'! H ' ' No purchases American gold dollars ' ' ' No purchases 161 25 29i 3FN - ^ages 1 to 20 transferred from file 9/10. X idj?|uv Siy^Lwu* Kl avu-o S&amp; Ct.msi*% , 2 statements of balances placed below. The return from Mhd. Al Ad/ani and Mhd. Al Baker has not yet been received, but please seepage 16. H*M* is reminding thefii, Bef 1 _3 and 5. File ? Ref 4. D.F.A* There is no need to remind Advani &amp; Baker in view of p. 16. It has been suggested to me that there are other gold dealers to whom we might well send notices. I have spoken to H.M. , who is going to make enquiries and inform me ox the resalt. Please remind me in a day or two. M r. Belgrave tells me that since the issue of otir notices, people wanting to have gold melted down no longer bring it to the gold weigher as they used to, but now tales it straight to the merchants. ltd. R.H.L. 12/8/42 Issue draft and file P.U.C. M LJ—y j cM E. CoHEM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/357</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/357</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/10 A export of gold and silver from Bahrain; weekly statements submitted by bullion brokers'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-03T09:44:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (267 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 259-265. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 269; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-4 and ff 138-257; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. Pagination: The index section (ff 259-265) has been paginated using pencil; these numbers are located in the top outermost corners of each page.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains an order from the Political Agent in Bahrain for all the bullion brokers to produce a weekly report showing purchases and sales of gold and silver and the subsequent statements received by the brokers, often in Arabic with English translation.There is a list of brokers on folio 3, and some tables with data on their trades, on folios 266-268.The file includes some correspondence with Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Silver</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exchange rates</topic></subject><subject><topic>Gold</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>