<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:04:12.021Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">*r INDIA OFFICE C-cf. B. 396 P. 4231/28' BAHREIN, 1908-1928. A.—Administration. L ® h , ei ^ Is a Bin Ali K.C.LE. (1919), C.S.I. (1915), (born 1848, succeeded 1869), was relieved of control of the administration in 1923 by the Government of India with the approval of His Majestv’s Government 'but remains titular Sheikh of the Islands, his eldest surviving son Sheikh Hamad, O.S.L (1921) (born 1874, right of succession publidy reused by Government of India in 1901, entitled to a salute of seven guns) who has three sons, born in 1895 (Sheikh Salman), 1898 and 1902, and two brothers Sheikh Mohammed (born 1877) and Sheikh Abdulla, C.LE. (1915) (born 1880)’ having taken over responsibility for the administration as the fully empowered agent of his father. Sheikh Isa, although no longer in fact the ruler of Bahrein, is understood to continue to carry weight locally, and his wife, a vigorous and unscrupulous lady in the sixties, who prior to his deposition was stated completely to dominate her husband, remains an important influence in the State. “V principality is an independent Arab State, under the protection oi His Majesty s Government, but not a British Protectorate. Its ruler is precluded by his engagements, of which an abstract is printed in the Precis of treaties appended to this Memorandum, from receiving the representatives of, or entering into relations with, foreign Powers, and from ceding sellino- mortgaging, or giving for occupation, save to His Majesty’s Government, aify part of his territory. He is bound to suppress the slave trade, and to prohibit traffic inarms, within his territory, and he is precluded from granting a concession for oil, or for pearl fishing, save with the approval of His Majesty’s Government. 3. The internal administration is conducted by the Sheikh (Hamad), assisted since 1926 by a European Financial Adviser* (Mr. 0. Dalrymple Belgrave) and since 1924 by a European Director of Customs (Mr. de Gremei),t who has, it is understood, been given a year’s notice, expiring in June 1929, on the initiative of the Government of India, and a European Chief of Police who is also Assistant to the Financial Adviser (Captain L. 8. Bark*).} All these officers are servants of the Sheikh and are paid : Tei. fro,,, p„i. b... s.»f trom Jlanrein tunds. Iheir contracts and their conditions of service like S. for L, T. 10 , Sept, n ‘heir original selection for employment, were, however, approved by the rwo' 24 ’ 1 ' 26 '*'' 1 Government of India. 4. His Majesty s Government and the Government of India are repre sented in Bahrein by the Political Agent, Bahrein (at present Lt.-Col. C. C. J. Lor &gt;. 93i. Barrett, C.S.L, C.I.E., formerly First Assistant Resident at Aden), an appointment created in 1904, and borne on the cadre of the Political Department of the Government of India. The Political Agent is directly subordinate to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. He does not hold His Majesty’s Commission as a Consul, and exercises no consular functions. Under the Bahrein Order in Council, 1913, as amended by the Bahrein (Amendment) Order in Council of 1922, he is the District Magistrate and Sessions Judge, and exercises jurisdiction (subject to appeal to the Court of the Political Resident) in respect of British and foreign subjects in Bahrein. His jurisdiction in the case of foreigners, exercised In the case of foreigners other than Nejdis since 1904-5, was regularised by the Order in Council of 1913 (which, owing first to the undesirability of complicating the 1913-4 negotiations with Turkey and then to the war was not actually brought into operation until February 1919) and was extended to cover all foreigners in 1920. t * . A oT' lte p f ? r n£' r J[“?o&amp; ‘i 1 ® .''“‘“'X*- “bjeot to three months' notice, from June 1926, on Rs. 1,000—oO—2,200, &amp;c. (Tel. from G. of I. to Pol Res 142\ 2S Dm 19 -&gt;t • P.3915/25.) *’ ^ t Appointed for three years from 14 Jan. 1924, P. 2146, letter from G of I to Pol Res No. 480x, 10 April 1924 ; Pol. Res.’s. Ir. to G. of L, 22 Dec. 1923, 7168 ; P. 487/24. ’ 2979d 75 10.28M.S. Report, para. 12. See dison. on P. 1787/23 and P.1878/23. * Sir 1). Bray to Mr. Wakely, D.O. 195(5 E.A., July 21 1921, P. 3588/21. ♦ Tel. from Viceroy, July G 1912, P. 2632/12. t Letter from Pol. Res. to G. of I.. P. 8014. Nov. 25 1911, P. 2062/11; letter from Pol. Res. to G. of I., 3011, Nov. 25 1911, P. 50/12. X F.O. to I.O., Oct. 18 1909, P.4I18/0:»; G. of I. Desp.to S. of S., 116. Nov. 14 1912, P.4582/12; letter from Pol. Res. to G. of I. 1348. May 10 1914. K 2408/14. § Letter from Pol. Res. to G. of L, 1518. May 23 1914, P. 2509/14. Letter from Pol. Res. to G. of I., 1518, Mav23 1314, P. 2509/14. l| Cp- letter from Pol. Res. to G. of I., 779, Mar. 18 1908, P. 1840/08. ** Major Daly’s Report, Nov. 1921, P. 900/22. P. 4624/19. 5. The effect of the recommendations of the Masterton-Smith Committee of 1921 was to leave control of Bahrein affairs, other than matters of policy affecting relations with Ibn Sand, which were reserved to the Colonial Office, to the Government of India, subject to the general control of His Majesty’s Government, and to the .prior concurrence of the Colonial Office in matters of “political significance.” The question of the channels through which the instructions of His Majesty's Government on matters affecting the Islands issue is dealt with in paras. 4 and 5 of the iS'ote on Political Control in the Persian Gulf, p. £5- 6. Expenditure on Bahrein in respect of the suppression of the slave trade (Rs. 52 in 1919-20) and of sanitary arrangements (Rs. 1,200 in 1919-20) is divided equally between the Government of India and the Foreign Office. All other expenditure, on thq Agency, Darbar presents, &amp;c. (amounting in 1919-20 to Rs. 79,304) is borne wholly by the Government of India.* B.*—Internal History of Bahrein (including relations with His Majesty’s „ Government), 1908-1928. 7. The internal history of Bahrein falls into two periods : the first from 1908 to the deposition of Sheikh Isa in 1923, the second from 1923 to the present day. (1) 1908-1923 : Sheikh Isa. 8. Little of importance occurred between 1908 and 1919. In 1909 a formal request in writing that he should be relieved by His Majesty’s Government of the responsibility of exercising jurisdiction over foreigners in his country was obtained by the Political Agent from the Sheikh (P.1314/09). His Excellency explained in 1912 that by “ foreigners ” he had not intended the dependants of petty Arab potentates in the Gulf, a contention which was accepted by His Majesty’s Government in 1919, but which, in view of the attitude of the Arab chiefs affected, it proved impossible, as explained below, to continue to entertain. The Order in Council approved by the King in 1913, the introduction of which was postponed till 1919, limited the jurisdiction of the Political Agent to “foreigners with respect to whom the Sheikh has agreed with His Majesty ior, or consented to, the exercise of jurisdiction by His Majesty.” Certain minor administrative improvements were effected by the Sheikh from time to time under strong pressure from the Political Agent; in 1911 His Excellency agreed not to allow any foreign Power to open a Post Office in Bahrein and not to grant a pearl fishing concession to foreignerst; a wi reless station was erected in 1912; with great difficulty the Sheikh was persuaded between 1912 and 1914 to remedy the grievances of traders in regard to landing arrange- nients and the handling and storage of cargo at Bahrein^ ; after some discussion he agreed in 1914§ not to search for oil himself or give others permission to do so without consulting the Political Agent and receiving the approval of the Government of India (subsequent developments as regards oil concessions in Bahrein are dealt with in para. 19 below); responsibility for the quarantine duties, which had caused some difficulty in the past,,, was taken over in 1916 by the Government of India ; the attitude of the Sheikh and his sons during the war was correct. But the position as between the ruling family and their subjects steadily deteriorated ; administration lapsed until it could be reported in 1922 as far behind the times in comparison with other Arab States” the bigoted incapacity” of the Sheikh (to quote the Political Resident in 1911), the corruption or weakness of members of his family, and the succession of tyrannical acts perpetrated by the Sheikh, his wife and his sons, not only gave rise^ to increasing popular discontent, but, since the Political Agent uas not in a position to intervene effectively (the energies of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India being elsewhere engaged), reacted unfavourably on our position in the Islands. 9. In 1919 Sheikh Abdulla, the Sheikh’s youngest son, visited England 1 r o] 1 -?? • N. E. Bray, to convey to His Majesty the congratulations of Hieikh Isa on the successful outcome of the war, and was received by theKing. In an interview with Sir Arthur Hirtzel on 1st September 1919 he Letter from i.o. t&lt;. g. of i., demanded on behalf of Sheikh Isa that the latter shotild be— ‘ ept ‘ 16 1919, r ,,649/19 ' (а) put on an equality with neighbouring Arab rulers in the exercise of authority over all persons other than subjects of Great Britain and the Great European Powers, and so over Arabs other than subjects of Bahrein ; (б) empowered to select the bench of magistrates [under the Bahrein Order in Council the Majlis-el-Urf, or Civil Court, is composed of not less than four members selected by the Political Agent in concert with the Sheikh]; (c) permitted and assisted to develop the port of Zubarah in El Katr, which he claimed had once belonged to Bahrein (Cp. Lorimer : Persian Gulf Gazetteer I. i. 814); (d) given permission to correspond direct with London, should necessity arise. 10. After consideration of the views of Capt. Bray, Major Dickson, then Political Agent, the Political Pesident and the Civil Commissioner, Mesopotamia, the Government of India on 5th May 1920* informed Sheikh Vf a 6 , 1 k M*^ 5 U ' Ia ’ Abdulla that the procedure for the selection of the members of the Majlis 1920 , p. soro. was laid down in the Bahrein Order in Council and that it was not within their competence to alter it, but that in practice the Arab representatives were understood to be appointed by Sheikh Isa, and that although this appointment was subject to the approval of the Political Agent as representing the Protecting Power, the Political Agent would never interfere or refuse his approval without just cause ; that as regards his third point, the request was an old one which had received much consideration, and that the Government of India remained unable to accede to it in view of the difficulties involved ; while as regards direct correspondence, the political relations of Bahrein were conducted with the Government of India and that it was proper therefore that His Excellency should address them and not His Majesty’s Government. They would if necessar} r forward his correspondence to His Majesty’s Government. As regards the first and most important request, the Government of India agreed that he should exercise jurisdiction over the subjects of other Arab rulers, subject to the formal concurrence of those rulers. Ibn Saudt, however, and the Sheikh of Katr, the one previously, the I If f r other subsequently, took exception to the exercise of control over their c.c., Baghdad, to g. of i., subjects by the Sheikh of Bahrein, and requested the Political Agent to 4801 ’ Apnl 15 l92 °- exercise the jurisdiction in question. The Political Agent in consequence issued on 20th November 1920,f a notice that all foreign subjects, including t Desp. from^Po 1 . Res. to Persians and subjects of Arab rulers and Chiefs other than those of Bahrein, sept. 11927 , r. siitS/ 27 . ’ were, while in Bahrein, entitled to British protection. The transfer to the Political Agent of jurisdiction over all foreigners did not improve relations between the Political Agent and Sheikh Isa, already none too good as a result of the interference by Government in a dispute between the Sheikh and ibn Sand as to the duty to be levied on goods proceeding to Hasa, consequent on which Sheikh Isa had been compelled to accept 2 per cent. duty instead of the 5 per cent, which he desired, and in which he regarded of^'hb^sept Government as having favoured Ibn Sand at his expense.§ p. 1931/26. 11. This (condition of affairs coincided with an internal crisis of a different character, which was destined to lead up to drastic intervention by His Majesty’s Government and the deposition of Sheikh Isa. The difficult situation produced by the Sheikh’s misgovernment, and its reactions on the position of Great Britain in the Islands, have already been mentioned. Captain Bray, in May 1919, expressed the opinion that there was in Bahrein a considerable feeling of hostility to His Majesty’s Government “due to Capt fi»v t° cji, religious, economical, personal and war reasons, and no British party, and p.5040/20. that the activities of the American missionaries were anti-British. Major H. R. P. Dickson, C.I.E., a highly qualified officer with a distinguished record of service in Mesopotamia, who succeeded him as Political Agent, reported in Januarv 1920; that the political situation in Bahrein, while in II Letter from Major -e . *■ n . A . xi x xi . 1 Dickson to Pol. Res., 6 C.. no way dangerous, was wholly unsatisfactory ; that there was a strong and jan. 1920, i\ 504c deep-seated anti-British sentiment of long standing, and that British prestige rested on fear and not on respect. The gross oppression “ amounting toLetter from I’ol. Res. to G. of I., L45 S., Dec. 30 1921, P. 522'22. * Letter from Pol. Res. to G. of I., 495 S . Dec. 30 1921, P. 522/22. Major Daly’s Report, Nov. 1921. Tel. from Viceroy to Pol. Res., 119 S., Jan. 30 1922 P. 900/22. G. of I. to Pol. Res., 549 S., May 2 1922. + F.O. to I.O., Mar. 18 1922. x P. 2228 . Pol. Res. to G. of I., Jan. 27 1923, 1’. 750/23. § Tel. from Viceroy to S. of S. for I., 475 8., April 17, P. 1443. Tel. from Viceroy to S of 8., May 23 192B. Cp. Pol. Res. Desp to G. of I. and C.O., 631 S., Nov. 11 1923, P 4853/23. had ousted Sheikh Hamad from the position he should properlv have occupied as heir apparent, formed the subject of various reports by he fohtical Agen (then Major H. Daly, C.I.E.) in 1921, and led by the end of that jeai to .1 deputation to ask lor intervention to the Political Resident in the 1 ersiau Onlf 12. The Resident accepted the position, and suggested to the Government of India that a possible solution might be that the Political Agent should be empowered to intervene in cases of gross oppression and give individual protection where necessary.*’’ Earlier in 19-1 bheikh. Abdulla had taken alarm at the rising discontent, and Sheikh Isa had appointed his heir, Sheikh. Hamad, to take over control under his orders, but the masterful wife of Sheikh Isa had prevented any advance. The attitude of the people became, however, sufficiently alarming to lead Sheikh Hamad and Sheikh Abdulla early in 1922 to take certain minor steps in the direction of reform, and the Government of India, who in January 1922 had stated that they were not prepared to consider drastic intervention until all local resources had been exhausted and intervention was imperative to secure the protection of foreigners and the position of His Majesty’s Government in the Islands, and who remained anxious to avoid interference if it could be avoided, informed the Resident in the light of this that while it was most undesirable that they should be drawn into interference between the Sheikh and his subjects, they were prepared to lend their moral support to an honest attempt by the Sheikh to put his scheme into force. They emphasised that nothing should he done to encourage the idea that reforms were being introduced by the Sheikh at the dictation of Government. PI The reforms, however, proved illusory ; the internal situation continued threatening ; the Foreign Office, who in March 1922 had urged the taking of immediate steps of reform, in view of the prejudicial effect on the ixisition of His Majesty’s Government in Persia of “ the present highly unsatisfactory state of affairs in Bahrein,”t again represented the necessity for action, in the interests of the Shiah subjects of the Sheikhs, on 29th May 19224 The Secretary of State for India referred the matter to the Government of India, and they to the Resident in the Gulf. The Political Agent thereupon recommended a postponement of action, partly to enable developments to be watched, partly to appraise the importance of the interest in Bahrein affairs of Ibn Saud, and this recommendation was accepted; but by the end of 1922 the Political Resident was obliged to report that the state of affairs in Bahrein called for reform more urgently than ever, and that Government must be prepared to back up moral pressure by material force if the required reforms were to be carried through. 14. Finally, in April 1923,§ the Government of India, who recognised that if the status of Bahrein and our position in the Islands was brought before the League by Persia, “misrule would be the only serious flaw^in our case,” recommended that if Sheikh Isa could not be persuaded to take the necessary steps himself, he should be deposed, his son Abdulla deported, and the required reforms carried out by the Government of India. His Majesty’s Government approved action on these lines, and Sheikh Isa proving obdurate, he was deprived of his control on 26th May 1923, and granted an allowance,|| and his son. Sheikh Hamad, appointed to act for him “as his father’s fully empowered Agent.” It was found unnecessary to deport Sheikh Abdulla. Appeals by Sheikh Isa to the High Commissioner for Iraq and the Viceroy, culminating in an appeal in 1925 to the SecrPto™ nt state tor India, were rejected. (2) 1923—1928 : Sheikh Hamad. 15. After a disturbed beginning, the result of the activities of the partisans of the old regime, in the course of which a firm line h „1 k taken With the (Sunnij Dowasir tribe resident in the north-east of the Island of Bahrein, as a result ol which they migrated to Ibn Sand’s territory |j Rs. 4,000 per mensem from customs, which for some years he reWH ^ a /i&gt; , P. 1193/25 ; P. 2221/27), and Its. 2.000 per i/tddition 1“ 1 (P ' 107 / 25 ' Rs. 2,500 per mensem (letter from Political Resident to Government of of 15th June 1923, P. 2729 A/23). ‘&gt;\einment of India, 283 S, datedten oi ism practised by the Sheikhs, and particularly by Sheikh Abdulla, who m llasa, fiom which they now (1928) show si^ns of returning, conditions in Bahrein have stabilised themselves under the rule of Sheikh Hamad But that rule has been substantially rule by the Political Agent. On the recommendation of the Political Resident in the Gulf, the Government of India with much reluctance, agreed in 1923 to the permanent appointment of a British Director of Customs (this on the request of the Sheikhs-post fi led January 1921), and the raising of a small force to maintain order (raised PL4, changed to an armed police force, in 1926, under a British officer)* wfnle m 1926 a European Adviser was appointed to deal with judicial financial and general administration. All these officials were, in fact appointed on the recommendation and with the approval of Government’ though they are the servants of the Sheikhs and formally appointed by them. 16. The correspondence which has passed since 1923 between the Government of India and the Political Resident in the Gulf shows increasing reluctance on the part of tlie former to assume full responsibility for the •conti ol of Bahrein, or to do more than carry the Sheikh wholeheartedly with them m the path of reform while avoiding the “ Westernisation ” of his State it is understood that m pursuance of this policy they have had under consideration the diminution of the overt signs of British influence in Bahiein ; that the European Director of Customs has now been given a vear’s notice and will not be replaced ; that the European police officer may also be dispensed with, and that an ultimate concentration under a single competent European, such as the present Financial Adviser, of direct lesponsibility lor their Departments is in contemplation. 17 In the discussions between the Sheikhs and the Political Agent which took place consequent on the reassertion in December 1927 of the Persian claim to Bahiein, it is satisfactory to be able to record that while Sheikh Isa remained sensitive regarding the maintenance of his internal inde- pendence Shmkh Hamad, the de facto ruler, Sheikh Abdulla, and also Sheikh Salman, the eldest son of Sheikh Hamad, are stated bv the Political Resident to have displayed anxiety, in their own interests, to admit to the lull the protection of Great Britain. P. 71/27, and Pol. Rea. letter to G. of I., Mar. 27 1927, P. 2222. P. 3393/24, 2432/25. 1. Tel. from G.of I. to Pol. Res., 634 S., May 14 1923, P. 1830/23. 2. Ditto, 1688 S.. Dec. 8 1923, P. 43/24. 3. Letter from Pol. Res. G. of I„ 712 S., Dec. 21 1923, P. 487/24. Pol. Res. to G. of I., March 30 1928, P. 2442. 18. Ihe policy of His Majesty’s Government in Bahrein is one of the points for consideration by the present Sub-Committee, and on the decision on it must turn the decision on the degree of interference and control to be exercised over the internal administration of the Islands. But it is pertinent to quote the remarks of the Political Resident in the Gulf, made though thev weie before the situation was modified by the reassertion of the Persian claim to suzerainty, in his Despatch' 1 *' of 1st September 1927 : — “ We cannot lose Bahrein. But, notwithstanding our outwardly strong position m the Islands, a single serious quarrel with Sheikhs Isa and Hamad, a quarrel engineered by Ibn Saud on religious grounds, or through Persia on political grounds, and we should have to vacate our privileged position or force ourselves on the principality in the face of the world against the wishes of its rulers. * To G. of I., No. 295 S., para. 57, P. 5668/27. b.—Oil in Bahrein. 19. The Sheikh agreed in 1914 not to grant an oil concession without the appioval of His Majesty s Government. The question of obtainino- a concession was revived by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, who appear originally to have raised it in 1918, in 1921. Negotiations on their behalf were undertaken with the Sheikh of Bahrein through the Political Resident, but agreement pioved impracticable, and in the event a concession, granting an exclusive exploration licence for a period not exceeding two vears, subject to renewal by the Sheikh, acting on the advice of the Politicaf Resident for certain further periods, was signed by the Sheikh of Bahrein (also with the approval of His Majesty’s Government) in favour ol the Eastern and General Syndicate on 2nd December 1925. It was decided in 1928 to advise the eoi. W a, c.o. a,» 4 oneikn that all future agreements with oil companies should contain a clause 1928 &gt; p - 4927 - to the effect that no alienation of rights whatever could be made, except with the sanction of the Sheikh and the approval of His Majestv’s Government (The general question of oil in the Gulf is dealt with in the Board of Irade Memorandum on page QjG * Tel. 190S. tel. 95, April 11 D.—External Relations of Bahrein (other than with His Majesty’s Government) 1908-1928. 20. During this period the dominating and almost the only question affecting the external relations of Bahrein remains that of its status vis-d-vis Turkev and Persia. t Teh. Deep. 10 of Jan. 22 1909. I.—Turkey and Bahrein. 21. An agreement between Great Britain and Turkey, signed on 29th July 1913, as part of the general negotiations between His Majesty’s Government and the Ottoman Government, but, like the other agreements concluded in the course of these negotiations, awaiting ratification on the outbreak of war, finally disposed of the Turkish claim to suzerainty, which must in any event have been practically effected by Ibn Baud’s capture of Hasa in 1913. By Article 13 of the Anglo-Turkish Convention the Ottoman Government, renounced all their claims to the Islands of Bahrein, the independence of which they recognised ; His Majesty’s Government declaring on their part that they had no intention of annexing the island. His Majesty’s Government undertook in Article 11 of the same Convention not to allow the Sheikh of Bahrein to disturb the autonomy of the peninsula of El Katr, or to annex it, and in Article 14 that the Sheikh should not discriminate against Ottoman subjects in the matter of dues levied upon pearl fisheries, while the Turkish Government accepted a reservation of the right of the population of Bahrein to visit Zakhnuniyeh Island for fishing, and recognised the right of subjects of the Sheikh to British consular protection in Turkey. Owing to the outbreak of war, the agreement in question was never ratified ; but the Turkish claim to Bahrein would seem to have disappeared with the disappearance of the Turkish Empire and the elimination of Turkey from the Persian Gulf, and no endeavour has been made to revive it since the end of the war. II.—Persia and Bahrein. (a) 1908-1922. 22. Despite the nine repudiations enumerated in the Foreign Olfice Memorandum of 190^, the Persian claim was kept alive in the years 1908-14. Representations made by His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran to the Persian Government in 1908 in regard to the punishment of a Bahrein subject at Lingah, i;: ' produced the reply that instructions had been sent to Lingah “to make reparation and do the man justice,” but that, as to the question of Bahrein, the Minister “ will admit that the proprietary right of the Persian Government over the Island is not a matter to be disputed.” Considerable subsequent discussion took place with the Persian Government, with a view to the withdrawal of this Note or the modification of its terms. In view of the fact that His Majesty’s Government considered it inopportune to raise the question of Bahrein in its general aspect, a somewhat gentler line was taken with the Persian Government than was perhaps altogether consistent with the attitude adopted before and since by His Majesty’s Government; and it was only after unsuccessful efforts to secure the substitution of a modified version that the Persian Note was returned as inadmissible to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.t The Persian Foreign Office thereupon declared that, if the Note returning the objectionable- communication could be withdrawn, the Persian Government would send in substitution for the latter an amended Note in the sense desired, adding that, if this arrangement was not accepted, they would be obliged to send a strong reply to the British Note. The Minister remarked that this would have raised the general question of Bahrein, for which the moment was clearly inopportune, and that he had therefore accepted the proposed arrangement. The amended Note was accepted, and the matter closed with a Note from His Majesty’s Minister dated the 13th May 1909, acknowledging receipt and reaffirming that His Majesty’s Government maintained, as regards the status of Bahreinis in Persia, the position that the Island of Bahrein and its inhabitants were under British protection, and that they would be guided entirely by their own views of the position should any action of the Persian Government make representations necessary.23. Early in 1910 the Persian Government assimilated the formalities to be fulfilled in the case of persons visiting Bahrein to those prescribed in the case of travellers to Persian ports, a measure which, as pointed out by the Foreign Office at the time, constituted a fresh attempt to assert Persian sovereignty over the Island.J It was agreed that, in view of the desirability of avoiding raising of the general question, no protest should be made. 24. In July 1910 the Political Resident reportedfl* that internal Persian coastal passes issued to Persians proceeding to Bahrein from Persian ports were visaed by a Persian merchant residing in Bahrein, who was also in the habit of issuing similar passes (“ llm-o-khabar ”) to Persians proceeding from Bahrein to Persian ports, and His Majesty’s Government approved a proposal that the merchant in question, Abdul Nabi, should be expelled from the Island.§ For various reasons it proved necessary to suspend action on this authority, but in 1912 Abdul Nabi was forbidden to take any action in regard to the endorsement of passes held by Persian subjects for travel in Bahrein. The endorsements in question were, however, thenceforth granted by the Political Agent, a practice, as pointed out by the Political Resident nine years later,;| “ of itself open to objection, as it might be construed into a tacit admission that the Persian passport authorities are justified in giving passes for another Persian port to persons going to Bahrein.” 25. Efforts made by His Majesty’s Government in 1913 to secure Persian recognition of our right to protect Bahreinis and subjects of the Trucial Chiefs as a condition precedent to the granting to Persia of the loan then under negotiation proved unavailing. 0 ** (b) 1922-1927. 26. There were no fresh developments of importance until after the war. In the year .1922 His Britannic Majesty’s Consul at Bandar Abbas reported that the Persian passport officials at Lingah,* at which port British India Steam Navigation Company’s vessels put in from Bahrein, had ruled that Bahreinis were Persian subjects and should be given Persian passports. They seized two British certificates of identity granted to Bahrein subjects, but on representations being made by the Minister at Tehran, instructions were given by the Central Government that there was to be no repetition of this incident. In the same year, His Majesty’s Minister suggested that Persians going to Bahrein should be required to obtain British visas or passes, and should be turned back if they had not got them, a procedure the adoption of which was recommended by the Political Agent, who regarded it as feasible. It was subjected accordingly to examination by the Government of India and the Foreign Office, with the results shown below. In 1922 also the Persian delegate at a Postal Conference held at Bushire, while not for the moment pressing for the transfer to Persia of the Bahrein post office, stated that his action was without prejudice to Persian claims to Bahrein.')' 27. At about the same time a Press campaign for the return of Bahrein to Persia and for its direct representation in the Majlis was started in the Persian papers. This discussion culminated in a motion in the Majlis to give Bahrein the right to return a Member, a demand for the immediate discussion of which was rejected, but which was referred to a Commission for report.J His Majesty’s Government, in the light of this development, decided that it was desirable to instruct the Minister at Tehran to address a formal Note to the Persian Government, in terms similar to those employed in 1906, and considered the question of asking the Admiralty to despatch a vessel to show the Flag in the neighbourhood of Bahrein. The Government of India concurred in the action proposed, and expressed the view that, if a Note was presented, the withdrawal of passport measures should be included, remarking (doubtless with the proposals on the subject of the Minister at Tehran in mind) that, whether a Note was presented or not, they saw no objection to retaliatory measures requiring visitors to Bahrein to take out a British visa.§ They added, however, that the critical internal situation in Persia made it doubtful whether the present moment was opportune for action. At about the same time the Persian Government instructed its X Teh. Deep. 65, April 26 1910, P. 35:19/10. ft P 3655/10. § F.O. tel. to Tehran, 219, July 16 1910. Letter from Pol. Res. to Minister, Tehran, 14/220, Jan. 22 1913, P. 801/13. || Letter to G. of I , 894 8., Dec. 3 1922. ** Teh. Deep, to F.O., 110 May 13 1913, P. 2531/13. * Pol. Res. to G. of I., 1090 June 10 1922, P. 2787/22. P. 2967/22. Para. 62 of Pol. Res. Deep, to G. of 1. Xo. 294 8., Sept. 1 1927. + Tel. from Pol. Res. to G. of I., 11, Dec. 13 1922; F.O. letter E 14044/471/34, P. 90/23. J Teh. tel. 112, April 17 1923. § Tel. from Viceroy, Mav 29 1923, P. 2039/23. ‘8 II Tel. from Viceroy to 8. of 8., 833. S., June 20 1923,P. 2357/23 . Teh. tel. to F.O., 135, July 14 1923. P. 3524 a i 28. register at his Consulate and obtain passpoits.'J 9S The serious internal situation in Persia made it necessary to postpone _8. Ine . Maiestv’s Government, and ternpoiaiily * rsrtf in the Gulf. 9 9 No further steps were taken until September 1923, when the Persian Government were informed that, the Island was now a British 1 rotectorate, and that His Majesty’s Government did not contemplate any aUem ton of its status—a declaration met by a statement b&gt; the Persian .Umistei Jo Foreign Affairs that the Government of which he was a member had no. intention of laying claim to Bahrein on behalf of Persia. 1 his did not prevent the Minister for Foreign Affairs from again raising the qoestton in the following month in a conversation m the course of which b Percy Loraine tentatively suggested, in his personal capacity, the possi i i v of putting the matter to arbitration, a suggestion for making which he was sharplv rebuked by the Foreign Office, and from wdnch nothing resulted. ** Teh. Deep, to F.O. 574, Oct. 31 1925. P. 73/26. * G. of 1. to 1.0 , Sept. 5 1927, P. 4573/27 t F.O. to I.O., Nov. 2 1927, P. 5120/27. tt C.O. to I.O., July 24 192S. T.O. to F.O., Aug. 17 1928. P. 3913 : 4065/28. 30. Between 1923 and 1927 there was a lull, and no point of real importance arose. His Majesty’s Government were reluctant to face the question of the status of Bahrein, and in consequence adopted in general an accommodating attitude so far as possible on minor questions. Ihus, on the vexed question of the use by Bahreinis of Persian passports and travelling passes (Ilm-o-Khabar), agreement was reached in IJ-O that Bahrein subjects should not be subjected to the new Persian passport regulations, the production of an llm-o-Khabar sufficing, and His Majesty s Government, despite the apparent concession of principle involved in the recognition of the Ilm-o-Khabar, decided in 1927 tacitly to acquiesce in this — partly on the ground that the recognition of these documents could be ignored, since they were also being issued by Persia in the case of Koweit, the status of which was not in dispute ;* to let the question of independent Bahreini passports lie; and to allow the matter generally to rest unless it was revived by Persian action.! There were no developments until June 1928, when the refusal of the Persian Consul at Basra to visa the pass of a Bahreini—an incident now under examination again raised the question.Tl Tel. from Pol. Res. to S. of S. for I., Sept. 18 1928, P. 5100. Pol. Res. to S. of S. for I., Sept. 17, P. 5093 28. 31. In September 1928, the Political Resident, on learning that a Persian residing at Bahrein was endorsing Persian Ilm-o-Khabar for Persians for the return journey to Persia, instructed the Political Agent to tell the Sheikh to issue orders that no one bearing such documents would be allowed to land, and to inform the offender who was issuing endorsements that he was usurping the powers of a Government official, which could be performed only with the consent of the Sheikh, and that he would be requested to leave the island unless he desisted. The vigorous reassertion of the Persian claim to Bahrein dealt with below renders it desirable to keep a vigilant watch for any action which might be construed or represented by Persia as an admission of their claim to suzerainty over Bahrein, and while it is not clear how persons carrying llm-o-Khabar are to be identified on landing, Sir Lionel Haworth’s action is not inopportune at a time when there are indications of an inclination on the part of Persia to assert a shadowy claim to suzerainty over the States of the Arab littoral by requiring that their nationals shall take out Persian passports or travelling passes. 32. It may be mentioned at this point that the Belgian Administrator- General of the Persian Customs stated early in 1928 that ‘‘about four years ago ” he had been taken’to task by the Government of the day for imposing customs duties on goods imported from Bahrein to Persia ; and that he had replied that “ customs dues had always been so levied . . . and that before j Teh. Deep. 53 , Jan. 27 they could he abandoned . . . the Persian Government would have io 1928 , p. 879 / 28 . institute a customs control at Bahrein itself.”!Reassertion of Persian Claim and x\ppeal to League, 1027. 33. The deposition of Sheikh Isa by His Majesty’s Government in 1923, and the subsequent increase in the degree of active British influence, emphasised the position publicly taken in Bahrein by His Majesty’s Government, but the Persian claim was not again actively reasserted until the text of the Treaty of Jeddah, concluded with Ibn Saud on 20th May 1927, in which Bahrein was referred to as having “special Treaty relations ” with His Majesty’s Government, provoked a strong protest by Persia, copies of which were despatched to the League of Nations with a request for circulation.|t The Persian protest was based largely on an alleged recognition of Persian sovereignty over Bahrein in a Note dated 29th April 1869, from the Earl of Clarendon, then Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. A reasoned reply to the Persian Note, which (after a brief delay in the hope that an arrangement might be reached with Persia) was equally communicated to, and circulated by, the League, was despatched by His Majesty’s Government on 18th January 1928. Suffice it to say that His Majesty’s Government, while avoiding any deKuite statement as to their own position in Bahrein or its basis, again repudiated the Persian claim in the strongest terms. 34. The Government of India, who but for the Persian protest would have inclined to favour ‘ a proposal of the Political Resident, under consideration at the time of its receipt, that His Majesty’s Government should set the seal on their position in Bahrein by a formal treaty of protection, provided that this was not precluded by wider considerations of foreign policy, recognised the tactical objections to such action in face of Persia’s appeal to the League.§ They commended, in the circumstances, a proposal by Sir L. Haworth that the Sheikhs should be apprised of Persia’s claim and encouraged to give a power of attorney to His Majesty 's Government to defend their independence at Geneva, and if possible state their dependence on our protection. This latter proposal was approved by His Majesty’s Government!) on the understanding that no pressure of any kind should be brought to bear on the Sheikh to secure the documents. His Majesty’s Government added that, in their view, the desirability of stressing the “ dependence on our protection ” of the Sheikhs was doubtful, and suggested that the point could better be disposed of by reference to the special treaty relations of the Sheikhs with His Majesty’s Government. 35. The Political Resident reported on 19th March 1928^[ that he had obtained a letter from Sheikhs Isa and Hamad appointing His Majesty’s Government, in accordance with their treaties, “ to defend Bahrein from outside interference,” and to act as their agents in rebutting the Persian claims, and that the Sheikhs proposed to send Sheikh Mohammed, brother of Sheikh Hamad and son of Isa, as their representative in answering the claim should the case be taken to Geneva. The Resident added that no pressure had been brought to bear to obtain this document, but that now that matters had gone so far with the Sheikhs any compromise with Persia on the basis of the status quo would have a very undesirable and unsettling effect on them, and that a definite disposal of the matter, by Persian withdrawal of the case or its reference to the League, was necessary. 36. There seemed at an earlier stage some reason to believe that the Persian Note to His Majesty’s Government was designed rather to prevent their claim from lapsing sub silentio than in the hope of any positive result, and that the Persian Government regretted the reference to the League.’' ■' 1 he question has come up several times in the course of the recent negotiations with Persia, when Sir R. Clive has uniformly made it clear that there is no prospect of His Majesty’s Government resiling from the position taken in the Note of reply. A formal answer to that Note has, however, now been made by Persia,tt and communicated to the League of Nations, and it seems clear that the claim is to be pressed. The Persian answer is, broadly speaking, based on the claims that Persian suzerainty over Bahrein was recognised by His Majesty’s Government in 1869—a contention disposed of in the Note sent to Persia in January 1928—and that a sine qua non of 2979d B ft Teh. Deep, to F.O. 577, Nov. 25 1927. § Viceroy’s tel., Dec. 29 1.927, P. 59&lt;)7. || Tel. from S. of S. for I. to Viceroy, 181, Jan. 20 1928. Viceroy’s tel. &lt;&gt;31 S., P. 1400/28. # * Cp.Teh. tel. 250, Dec. 28 1927, para. 3, P. 263/28. ft Teh. tel. to F.O. 235, Aug. 6 1928, P. 4184/28.C++ * Cp. Teh. Desp. 79, Feb. 1928, P. 78/28 t Cp. Teh. Desp. 207, May 4 1928. the independence of Bahrein is the recognition of such independence by the former Sovereign State—Persia, an act which has never taken place. No reply to the Note has yet been sent hy His Majesty’s Government. 37. Till this latest development, despite much activity in the Persian 8 Press. 0 and the encouragements of the Soviet Ambassador in Tehran,t there seemed little real probability that the matter would be pursued at Geneva. If however, the latest communication should make this inevitable, not only can the paper arguments be strengthened by the addition of miscellaneous evidence which has come to light since the British Note of .January 1928 was drafted, but the presence of a representative of the Sheikhs will carry some weight. The difficulty in present circumstances of the establishment by Persia of effective control in Bahrein, even should her suzerainty per improbabile be admitted in the island, makes it perhaps more probable that she will endeavour merely to use the question as a pawn in the forthcoming negotiations. In that event consideration will have to be given to the remarks of the Political Resident quoted above as to the necessity for a definite decision and the undesirability of a compromise on the basis of the status quo, remarks recently reinforced by unofficial statements by the Financial Adviser in Bahrein (Mr. Belgravc) as to the apprehensions of the Sheikhs lest His Majesty’s Government should sacrifice their interests to Persia as the price of an accommodation on matters of purely British concern. From the point of view of His Majesty’s Government, a settlement which would enable us to avoid public examination and discussion of our position in the Islands is to be desired. ]}. 349, ])iira 10. Letter from Pol. Res. to . of I., 460 S., June 25 1922, P. 3167; letter from Pol. Res. to O. of I., 529 S July 10 1922, P. 3401. Tel. from C.O. to Pol. Res., 1844, May 18 1923. P. 1868/23; Pol. Res. to S. of S. for I., R./2, Miiv 19 1923, P. 1913. Desj). from Pol. Res. to C.O., 314 S., June 23 1923. P. 3020/23. III. —Ibn Saud and Bahrein. (a) 1913-1923. 38. Ibn Sand’s contact with Bahrein commenced with his capture of Hasa from the Turks in 1913. Under the Treaty concluded with His Majesty’s Government on 26th December 1915, Ibn Saud undertook, “as his Fathers did before him, to refrain from all aggression on or interference with the territories of . . . Bahrein . . /’ During the war he established a commercial forwarding agency in Bahrein (the Qusaibi) and began to take some interest at Bahrein ; in 1919 the Political Agent found it necessary to bung pressure to bear on Sheikh Isa to secure an equitable settlement of a dispute which had arisen owing to the imposition by the Sheikh of customs duties on goods passing through Bahrein in transit to Hasa and Nejd ; at the end °f July 1920 the Political Adviser, Bahrein, reported that Sheikh Salim or Jvoweit had recently been in touch with Sheikh Isa, it was suggested with a view to securing his adherence to the movement against Ibn Saud which . le --then fomenting though nothing appears to have come of this ; while m Saud encouraged the recalcitrant Dowasir Bahrein tribe by o eiing them sanctuary in Hasa, an offer accepted on the abandonment of nan rein by the tribe after the deposition of Sheikh Isa in 1923 } At the moment of the deposition of the Sheikh (April 1923) Ibn Sand’s agent had ac levee an objectionable prominence in the Nejdi-Persian rioting which oov pace at Bahrein; and llis Majesty’s Government finally approved a proposa the Political Resident that he should be removed from Bahrein v h mg sent to Ibn Saud with a letter complaining of his conduct, reques ing the ^ultan to deal with the case, and asking that His Highness, )e oie sending another Agent to Bahrein, should arrange to secure the concunence or His Majesty s Government in his choice. A formal protest ;T n f aiu a .g a mst this action was disposed of by the Political Resident, n..° use( t() compromise, and the Qusaibi was finally allowed to return to a nein on a cleaier understanding as to his position and functions. (b) 1923-1923. un J ueie ^ eve ^ 0 P m ents of importance between 1923 and 1927. AJoi'oof .&gt; G pi 1( a '’eddah was in negotiation with Ibn Saud in 1927, His fmrn fL 8 ovei mucut and the Government of India were anxious to secure in ti t X11 +^ °£ in-, 2 e -j az an d ^ e jd an undertaking similar to that embodied m the treaty of 1915 and quoted in para. 38 above. His Majesty would &gt; , rowever, go &gt;e\ond an undertaking “to maintain friendly and peacefulTeJations with the territories of . . . Bahrein . . There is no evidence at the moment of a more positive interest in Bahrein on the part of Ibn Sand • but there is little question that he and the Wahabi movement, and not Persia! is the real danger; that as matters stand he is our natural successor if we abandon our present position in Bahrein, that his power is appreciated and feared by the Sheikhs, and that an active development of Wahabism on the North Arabian coast, coupled with bad relations with the King of the Hejaz and Nejd, might react embarrassingly on our position in Bahrein, the remarks of Sheikh Hamad in April 1927, that “Ibn Saud was the one big Arab Ruler, and it was natural for all the smaller Sheikhs such as himself to look up to him and try to please him,”* are symptomatic. * Letter from P. A., Bahrein, to Pol. Res., C/53 April 14 11*27, P. 3334/27. E.—Summary. 40. Internally, the last 20 years have seen the consolidation of British influence in Bahrein. The Sheikh has agreed to grant neither oil nor pearling concessions without the sanction of His Majesty’s Government; jurisdiction over foreigners in the islands has passed from’ the Ruler to the Political Agent; internal misrule has been checked by the deposition of Sheikh Isa, the substitution of Sheikh Hamad, and the provision for the new Sheikh of competent and disinterested European advisers under his orders. 41. Externally, the claim to suzerainty of Turkey has lapsed. The claims of Persia have constantly been reasserted, and as constantly repudiated by His Majesty s Government, over the period now in question. They are at the moment under argument, and have acquired a new importance by their reference to the League of Nations. Present indications are that Persia is likely to press them, and the desirability, in the interests of the Sheikhs, who have appointed His Majesty’s Government their agents in the matter, and on whom a compromise with Persia on the basis of the status quo would, according to the Political Resident, have a very unsettling ■effect of securing a decision which will finally dispose of them inter nationally, is for the consideration of His Majesty’s Government. I he rise of Ibn Saud is, however, the development most pregnant with possibility in the external relations of Bahrein. The King of the Hejaz and Nejd has not so far actively interested himself in the islands ; and the fact that the power which he has built up may not survive his death cannot be ignored. But, on the assumption of the survival of the existing state of things in Nejd, the present Memorandum (para. 39) makes the suggestion that it is Ibn baud and the Wahabi movement, rather than Persia, that represent the real danger from a practical standpoint, and that were His Majesty’s Government for any reason to abandon their present position in Bahrein, Ibn Saud would, as matters stand, be their natural successor. Position in Bahrein of His Majesty’s Government. 42. \\ hile, however, His Majesty s Government, as stated above, have over the past 20 years established ade facto control of the Islands of Bahrein, de jure their position is no stronger than before. At the same time, the importance of establishing that position on a stable basis has very greatly increased since 1908. From the naval standpoint. Bahrein, although it has been suggested, as a pis oiler, as a naval base or a coaling depot, has the disadvantage of unhealthy climate and relative remoteness from the exit of the Gulf and so from the probable scene of naval operations in the event of war.* The Air Ministry! regard it, however, as of great potential importance from the standpoint of British air interests—not only because of +AM toC)) Pec 2S its geographical position on the route to India, but because the isolation 1927 ,p. 5 / 28 . ’ 8C of the islands from the mainland, and the long-established influence in them of His Majesty’s Government render them less likely to be disturbed by anti-British rumours than other places on the Arabian coast. The Government of India (substantial Indian commercial interests in Bahrein apart) take the view that Bahrein as a central air base and political centre for the control of the increasingly important Arab littoral may be regarded as a key position inside the Gulf of an importance at least equal to that of Muscat at its mouth. The probability that Persia will press her efforts to terminate British influence on the south Persian coast, the necessity, should * Admiralty to C.O., Jan. 19 1928, P. 345.those efforts succeed, of consolidating that influence on the Arab littoral, and 1 the possibility that the removal of the headquarters of the Political Resident from Bushire may have to be considered, all combine to invest Bahrein with an importance very substantially greater than in 1908 from the standpoint: of His Majesty’s Government. 43. On the assumption, then, that Imperial considerations, our obligations to the Sheikh apart, make it desirable for His Majesty’s Government to maintain and consolidate their position in Bahrein, the question arises of how this is to be achieved. The matter is one which calls for careful handling. On the one hand, Persia has appealed to the League, on the Council of which she is now represented, and there is a possibility that she- may endeavour to make a compromise on Bahrein a condition precedent to agreement with His Majesty’s Government on other Gulf questions. On the other hand, it appears that a compromise, even on the basis of the maintenance of the status quo, would have a definitely unsettling effect on the: Sheikhs, who are suspicious that His Majesty’s Government may use them as pawns to secure concessions from Persia of value to Great Britain only ; that a decision which will definitely dispose internationally of the Persian claim is therefore desirable: and that, while the deposed Sheikh Isa remains sensitive regarding the maintenance of internal independence, the de facto ruler, his heir, and his brother, are anxious, in the face of Persian claims, to- admit to the full the protection of Great Britain. It may perhaps be assumed, that if the Persian claim could be disposed of before His Majesty’s Government had finally consolidated their position, much stronger opposition to such consolidation might be expected from the ruling family, and this appears to make it desirable to seize the present opportunity to establish the British position once for all. 44. The simplest method of at once asserting internationally the British view of the status of Bahrein and establishing the position in the islands of His Majesty’s Government vis-a-vis the Sheikh, would probably on the whole be the conclusion of a formal treaty of protection, a course under consideration in India (see para. 34 above) at the time of the reassertion of the Persian claim last year. Had Persia been prepared to abandon her claim in deference to His Majesty’s Government, the Treaty with Bahrein could have been concluded simultaneously with its abandonment. But as she is undoubtedly not prepared to compromise, such a treaty could only be concluded in the face of Persian protests to the League and elsewhere and the wider considerations of international policy involved in its conclusion would call for close examination before a decision is taken regarding it. An alternative method of solution might be arbitration, objections are obvious. to which various r \ romra . reterr ed to m connection with Persian Gulf Sub-Committee. O. the points in connection with Bahrein which have been specifically ComiSttee are C - neCtl ° n ' the deliberations of the Persian Gulf Sub- (a) Persian claims to suzerainty—degree of control to be exercised b\ His Majesty s Government (P.G. (i, 2 (a) (12)). ^ dteps necessary on the Horth Arabian coast in connection with the protection of the pearl-fisheries at Bahrein (P.G. 6, 2 (c) (3) N in~ ° f f tent t0 Which llis Misty’s Government 'should in Bahrein (KG.'ft'2 ’(“J. an&lt;l C0Iltrol exercified b &gt;- thei » Whether the existing 'coaling stations at Kishmand Heniam can Condusions) Va ‘‘ taSe ^ m0Ved 10 Bahrein ( F - G - Ut Minutes: (0 ( C ) (d) jr; Tiio t - oy Government of India maintenance rTfhe“en°dencS bT ' the view that 1 Trncial Chiefs, is ne^sL,T » o! , ' T’ 08 °* Muscat . Koweit, and t against European encroachments So V' 1)lotectora ‘ e over them suffic opinion by undue Westernisation d m 88 ,' ,e do . not ahenate An by the Wahabi State. At need : t caVb b ' hces al ?°. “gamst encroachmen India Office, ^ eXpllCltl &gt;’ asserted ” 8th October 1928. J. G. L.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B396</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B396</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Bahrein, 1908-1928'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1928</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-02-23T09:31:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The file consists of a single document.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 17, and terminates at f 22, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Document outlining the administration and history of Bahrein [Bahrain] from 1908-28. Covering:administration – control by the Government of India and titular Shaikh of the Islands, Bahrein's status as an independent Arab State, internal administration conducted by the Shaikh and a European Financial Advisor and European Director of Customs, the roles of the Bahrein Political Agent, and the responsibility for expenditure;internal History of Bahrein (including relations with His Majesty's Government), 1908-23 – concerning Sheikh Isa [Shaikh Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah] and the events leading up to his deposition;internal History of Bahrein (including relations with His Majesty's Government), 1923-28 – concerning Sheikh Hamad [Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah] and the role of the Political Agent;oil in Bahrein;external Relations of Bahrein (other than with His Majesty's Government) 1908-28 – concerning Turkey, Persia and the reassertion of Persian claim to Bahrein and appeal to the League of Nations in 1927, and Ibn Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd].It also includes a summary, notes the position in Bahrein of His Majesty's Government, lists points referred to in connection with the Persian Gulf Sub-Committee, and states the view expressed by the Government of India.Written by John Gilbert Laithwaite of the India Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia 'Abd al-'Azīz bin 'Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight John Gilbert Laithwaite</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Bahrain 'Īsá bin 'Alī Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Ḥamad bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah, Hakim of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0003c6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>