<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T07:18:42.881Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">fR9r20) WtlSlir/2750 10,000(2) 12/31 H &amp; Sr Gp 112 B 12b ^— Commumca&amp;Jns on this subject should be addressed to— The Unde,r Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l,’ and the following number quoted :— l *■'''•• 1 vi 1054 i^cn— 4^7-^/u io 5 - lieference to previous correspondence: Letter the Colonial Office of the Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the ^ £&gt; IQ^P■ SESIBeseHMHMMnBHI mm z Confidential &gt; X+n. 0.0. 715, Secretariat of K*^«. the High Commieeioner for •Iraq, Baghdad, dated 13th orember,1931. To Air Headquartera, hkLMk Wiiiitrintti / A copy of the undermentioned despatch is forwarded for favour of comment* &gt;d* ;•&lt;*.&gt;, * iturgee. Acting Counsellor to H. • the High Commissioner for ’Iraq* Beapatch Confidential B dated the 16th of October, 1931, from the Secretary of Jtote for the Colonies, London, with enclosure.i£££SJL« Toi- Hefl- lir quarter a t # Iraq Commmd, Hioaldi* * The Secretariat of Hi » ^xeeUenoy the High Corami asioaer. The Heaideacy, Baghdad. 27th BoT«mber t 1931. S. 10323. 3 “ kJ * et, *‘ Mi^,R o,' iti .a P;:iuiam In reply to your letter Bo.G.o.715 of the 13th Instant f it is considered that ny reduction of the number of &lt; . . Bhifw In the PKB3IAN GULF should be resisted* Owing to the advent of the Persian Havy *iiid the development of the air route along the ARABIA# Coast, the eowmitxaente of h. . ihips are likely to increase in the future* I’he present, therefore, is an inopportune moment for any reduction of naval strength in the Gulf. &gt;d. A.a.a. Garrod, Wing Comnu^nder, for Air Vice-Marshal t Comrr^vnding, 1 Iraq Coi-tat^nd,i2&amp;£X* / BO. G.O. 788. a«opetariat of 1; »i$« the High Coimalseloner for 9 Xraq l Baghdad, dated Srd Beeember f 1951. Te Air Headquartera f (« oopiea) . Ikomoraaduw. Referenoe Air Headquarters Secret memoraudum ^••3#10818 dated the 27th of HoTember, 1931# Hia itoellency appreciates the considerations advanced in your memorandum but doee not consider that they are gsuch aa he could properly transmit to the Secretary of Htate since the latter has addressed the Political He si dent In the Persian &lt; ulf direct on the subject. liis Bxcelloncy would be si ad to know however Aether the Air Officer Commanding is satisfied that the reduction of the number of His Majesty 9 • ships in the .vuli la not open to objection on grounds primarily affecting •Iraq^ e.g* the protection of British interests at Basrah. His Excellency further observes that the scheme for the defence of the Bouth Persian Oil Plelde enclosed with Air Headquarters memorandum Ho.3.10154 dated the 23rd of October, 1939, is in part based upon the assumption that under average conditions there are two sloops and M. .3. Triad available in the Persian Gulf. This is not a matter for which this High € masts si on' d) ■■ Commission is directly responsible but Hi* Hxeellency would be ready to transmit any observation is that the Air Officer Commanding might wish te offer on the effect of the reduction of His Majesty* s naval forces in the Julf on the protection of the oil fields, (*&gt;gd,) aturges 9 Political Secretary to H,:w, the High Coimissioner for f Iraq,-£££&amp;£« tfraia: Air Headqunrtera, ’Iraq Command, ^ Rinaldi, Toi The Secretariat to R •S • the High Coimaiaaionor, The Residency, Baghdad• Bef: 3* 10322. Bate: 15th January, 1932♦ &gt;ubject: &gt;. ItiUMM#, U£ i^ATt-,« i^dL, .t:, ; --Vi aM ,, ^ vr\jhj'' • 1. Reference your secret raemoranuwja J o. U.O. 756 dated 3rd December, 1931. 2. In considering the proposal to reduoe the number of sloop® in the Persian Gulf, it is difficult to divorce the protection of British interest* in ’Iraq from the protection of British interests as a whole, as they are all indirectly bound together by the history of our position in the Gulf* Perhaps it would not be out of place to refer shortly to the re teens which brought British ships to the Gulf and which have progressively led us to consolidate our ini'luence in the Gulf. 3. Great Britain was originally compelled te Interest herself in the Persian Gulf owing to its position relative to the line of sea communications with India, Situated on the flank of those sea coimouni cat ions and at ? ♦ one time the refuge of hordes of pirates it must necessarily have attracted the attention of any maritime power interested in their sea communications with India. i? 1 or these reasons it has been the declared policy ofHis Majesty *9 Corermtent to allow no other nation to establish o naral base in the Persian Gulf or in the Gttlf of Oman # I*ater # trade interests developed and led to tho general pacification of the Gulf* Later again in laeo the arms traffic in the Gulf attracted the attention of the Indian Goveramnt at the time of the Third Afghan ttfar* finally the Gulf became a Tital factor in our system of Imperial defence when the Persian Oil fields were developed and supplied the main source of fuel oil supply under British control* are 4. To these interests now added two other A important ones. In the first place the Persian uulf Is at present the only practicable military line of communication between Great Britain and *Iraq and { between f Ira&lt;| and India f and it is upon this line of communication that we depend for the maintenance of our military forces in this country. Secondly the Persian Gulf now lies directly on our air line of c orseiun i c ^ t i on a with India nnd Auotr 4.1&amp;, the maintenance of vsrhich is one of the principal causes of our preoccupation with •Iraq and its future* 5* It is now therefore more than ever important to maintain naval predominance in tho Persian Gulf and the Gulf of Oman In order that British communications with Basrah and Abadan may be safeguarded* Otherwise, apart from the vital question of oil supplies it would be not only impossible to give effect to pl^ns for the reinforcement of our forces in this country by troops from India, but it would even become impossible to maintain the British force already in this country* That there is some danger of the development of hostile influence in the Gulf is signified by the renewed claims(11 cl Xbm which the Peraiana are nc&amp;lng to territory which is at preaent under British influence and by the purchase by the Persian Government of war vessels for use in the Gulf# 6, Furthermore, it happens Just now that we are trying to establish a civil air route from Basrah via the Arabian littoral of the Gulf to India, the practicability of the safe establishment of this route depends upon the predominance of our influence with the shaikhs of the 1 racial Coast over that of tine Persians or of Ibn la’ud. Our prestige with the T racial shaikhs has already been shaken by our obvious weakness in handling our own and their interests in Persia, Any reduction of force in the Gulf would tend to confirm them in the improsaion that we no longer intend to dispute with Persia our interests in the Gulf. 7, Upon the above general grounds, therefore, it is obvious that any reduction of our number of ships in the Gulf would be most Inopportune at the present time, 8, How as regards the specific role of these |®hips in connection with the local security of th© Persian oil fields and of the town of Basrah, As was exemplified last Summer, serious internal disturbances may develop very quickly in Southern Ur&amp;q and the presence of a sloop at Basrah may be urgently required at very short notice. The present number of four vessels enables the Senior ilsval Officer always to have two ships within the Gulf itself, A reduction of the number of aloops by one wouldxasan that only one ship would be norm lly available within the whole of the Gulf, This would considerably reduce the probability of a ship being at hand in the event of sudden disturbancesiiaturbances in B«»rah # and the r«ductlon ,vould tt arefore Uad to eadangor til© safety of the Juropean population of that town* 9, Tho aehomo for the defence of the An^lo^^ereian Oil Co*»p JW *» oilfielOa in aouth Feroia t referred to in your a^iaoranduni^ is bfeeed on the supposition that there ei.ll ho arailBhle to assist in the defense two sloops as w * lx aa **Triad*, miking three nar«l vessels in all, fho tasks allotted to those vessels are as x'ollow:** (a) The landing of naval parties to protect (b) i’he landing of naval parties to oroteot Mokmmmroh^ (9) fho provision of gunners for four &amp;rmod oars of the A*^,0,0, until the COMp^a'ur can train its own men* (d) Dmenstrations. {©J the covering of the move of European and Indian onployeea from Abadan to Basrah* 10* this number of vessels would not be available if the present force were reduced by one, since one of the four ©loops is generally refitting at Jbombay, the scheme also pre*s?uppoeea that at least oxt^ ^leep will normally be within twentyfour h&gt;urs f distaiice of Abadan, (nd that the rmanlning. two vessels will be available at 3hort notice* If the proposed reductions are carried out this defence scheme will have to be drastically modified and 1 consider that two ships would not bo sufficient for the purposes for which these ships are required, ( ^d *) M #K, XiUdlow^Hewitt, &gt;Ur Viee-*Uar»hal t C nd # •Iraq C osttsand •S^&gt; Conf idential, FIL _ ( - ^ ^ o P V .F.284-N./31. Stftrfst Fo 3 0 DEC 1931 From To The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India In the Foreign and Political Department, Lieutenant Colonel H.V. Blscoe, Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Dated New Delhi, the^ Decentoer 1931. Proposal to reduce the number of subsidised vessels in the Persian Gulf. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your letter NO.703-S, of 1931, dated the 28th October 1931, I am directed to Inform you that In the circumstances explained the Government of India have decided not to pursue further the suggestion for a reduction In the number of His Majesty’s ships maintained In the Persian Gulf. The question of replacing His Majesty’s ship ’’Triad' by a sloop is receiving the consideration of the Government of India. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRt'^Y’s Letter No l178 Dated 1C DEC 1031 n Sd/- F.Ve Wylie, Deputy Secretary to tie Govermert of India*v r v-y /V A Ka. /'A A * / A» ^&lt;V««a jjj, ^ ,* ^ ^ Copy of a Confidential * ■• &gt; • j 6*^ ^4® &gt;75 73 | ' - • letter No. 703-S of 1931, dated B m f r. Buahire, the 28th October 1931, from th-e H on * bl e tlie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* New Delhi. 0^, La 5 . I have the honour to invite a reference to your letter No. F.284-N/31, dated the 8th September 1931, enquiring whether it would be possible in modern conditions to reduce the number of His Majesty's ships in the Persian Gulf without undue dis advantage, to two, which would mean that during 8 or 9 months of the year there would only be 1 ship present in the Gulf. 2. I append herewith a statement showing the multifarious duties performed by His Majesty's ships in the Persian Gulf, fhe Senior Naval Officer informs me that these duties could not be discharged if the number of ships was reduced. The Persian Gulf Division do, I believe, more sea-time than almost any other- ships in His Majesty's Navy, and this despite the exceedingly arduous climatic conditions under which they serve. The climate of the Persian Gulf is trying on shore; it is infinitely worse on small ships at sea, and the strain imposed on the engine room ratings in particular is very severe* It would therefore certainly not be possible for the ships to do more sea-time than at present. 3. It will be seen that the duties performed by His Majesty's ships are both numerous and important. It is perhaps hardly necessary to discuss these in detail, as specific examples taMen chiefly from events of the past 2 or 3 years are given under each heading and details of these events are in possession of the Government of India. I will therefore examine the proposal on somewhat broader lines. British predominance in the Persian Gulf has been to a very large extent built up by means of ships, first by those of the Indian Navy and B'OixsUHt subsequently of the Royal Navy. The constant presence of the INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S | a^gte jensign in these waters is a visible sign of our special Daied 19 MOV. 1931 ! position, V {leeches 7 DhC.19316. J.&amp;) position, and of our determination to maintain law and order, suppress slavery, and enforce the fulfilment of treaties* 4* Moreover the present would seem to he a very inopportune moment to effect any reduction in the number of His Majesty’s ships in the Gulf for two reasons. Firstly, as the Government of India are aware, the PersiansSca; in the course of the next few months propose to create a Persian avy under the command of Italian officers and to exhibit their flag in the Persian Gulf, If simultaneously with the appearance of the Persian flag the Resident was to a very great extent immobilised and the white ensign practically disappeared, then indeed would credence be given all along the Arab coast to the belief so Sedulously fostered by certain interested parties, that the British Umpire was decadent and the British nation no longer capable of ful filling its former responsibilities. 5. As the Government of India point out, the proposal would mean that for about 9 months of the year there would only be one ship in the Gulf. This ship single-handed could obviously perform only a very small portion of the duties at present devolving upon the Persian Gulf Division. It could not be constantly at sea, and when at sea would probably have some specific duty to perform, e.g. the conveyance of a political ofi’iae*’ from one port to another, or possibly the protection of life and property at places as far apart as Gwadur and Ab a dan, or assistance and co-operation with the Royal Air Force. H Showing the flag”, to which I attach great importance, since not only is it a visible sign of our presence but it also keeps the Resident in constant touch through the ships with the many Shaikhs of the Persian Gylf littoral, would be a thing of the past, and th a t contact and those friendly relations that the visits of ships maintain would disappear.6. Meanwhile the Persian sloops would doubtless visit the Arab coast, and the Trucial and other Shaikhs would naturally consider it advisable to come to terms with what they would obviously regard as the rising power. I do not think this picture unduly gloomy and I am confident that the Government of India would not view such a state of affairs with equanimity* It may perhaps be argued that the Persians too would have only two ships, but the duties of their ships would be very limited, and it would suffice for them to cruise between Bahrain and the Trucial Coast, and it is difficult to imagine ^diat other duties they will have to perform than M showing the flag* and what may be termed 'propaganda'* 7. Secondly, there is a probability that the Air Route may have to be transferred within the next six months from the Persian slide to the Arabian side, and this will impose additional responsibilities upon His Majesty’s ships, not merely in assisting aircraft when they may be in difficulty, but in protecting the halting places on the Trucial coast and elsewhere. For whatever arrangement may be arrived at with the Shaikhs of Ras- al-Fhaimsh or Umm-ral~Q,swain , the ultimate guarantee of safety will be the knowledge that any molestation or aggression on their part towards either the representatives of the Imperial Airways or passengers, etc. will receive drastic punishment. 8* The only reduction of expenditure in this respect that I c a n suggest/that H *k. S* 'Triad*, an old ship whose upkeep and refit is, I understand, exceedingly costly, should be replaced by a sloop* I understand that this has been mooted several times and that it would effect an appreciable reduction of expenditure. And further I think it might be possible (though on this point I have not consulted the Senior Naval Officer) to reduce one sloop if the Resident was provided with a suitable despatch vessel. This would relieve the Royal Navy of a certain amount of their present functions* At present if an incident o c cu r s&lt; (a)^ occurs anywhere a wardship is despatched there snd the matter is usually discussed with the local Shaikh by the Resident through the intermediary of the Commander of the ship, which is not very satisfactory and involves much telegraphing. Secondly, the flag can be shown as effectively by the Resident in a despatch vessel as by a man-of-war. Both represent to the Arab mind ’’the eye of the Kukumah H * And thirdly while the Royal Navy cannot carry the Resident or Political officers on tour they do and can carry them for a night or so (though at a great deal of discomfort to them selves) in emergencies or if the matter is really urgent. If the Resident had his own ship they would to a large extent be relieved of this duty, fhe upkeep of a small yacht would certainly be very much less than the upkeep of a war-ship. 9. To sum up (i) the duties performed by His Majesty’s ships in the Persian Gulf are exceedingly onerous and responsible. 'They involve almost constant cruising, and could not be performed by a lesser txumber of ships. (ii) The present moment is a very inopportune one to reduce ships, as the virtual disappearance of the white ensign from these waters would synchronise with the arrival of Persian ships, and the effect on the Arab mind would be lament abl e. (iii) Further if the Air Route is to be transferred to the Arab coast it will certainly impose additional respon sibilities upon the ships of the Royal Uavy. (iv) The only economies th a t I can suggest are (a) that the ’•Triad” should be replaced by a sloop specially adapted to carry the Senior Naval, and (b) that one sloop might be replaced by a despatch vessel for the Resident, thereby relieving the Navy of some of the functions they have to perform at present* The upkeep of a small yacht wouldwould te considerably less then that of a sloop* tut there would still always he three ships in the Gulf which is the minimum number that can perform the duties shown in the attached statement. His Majesty's Minister informs me that a copy of Government of India despatch Ho* ]?• 28 4-I\;/31 * dated the 8th ^ September 1931 has been sent to him and has asked for a copy of my reply. A copy of this despatch is therefore being sent to him*© aUTIBS WHICH THE SHIPS 0? HI3 MAJESTY'S W ^VY ARE REQUIRED TO DISCHARGE. 1 # Policing the Gulf &gt;_ (a) Enforcing the Maritime True e. (b) Suppressing piracy. (c) Suppressing the Arms Traffic* (d) Suppressing the Slave Traffic. (e) Preventing armed conflict at Sea. (f) Periodically visiting the Pe*rl Banks. With only one sloop in the Gulf for 8 or 9 months of the year none of these duties could he effectively performed* II. Showing the Flag. This is of importance on the Arab Coast as emphasising British prestige, a matter of particular importance at present on account of the Arab Air Route. It further serves to maintain contact with the Arat Shaikhs who transmit messages and requests through Comanders of w a r.ships, etc. and reports of the situation prevailing at the various ports are transmitted to the Political Resident* HI. ifriforcing fulfilment ox —Tresjyjss fl , n dTlsunp res sing di so r d e r s_*_ By threat of, or actual punitive demolition or other measures as at Khasah, April 1930, Has,al-Khaimah, June 1930, aiargah, April 1931. The inadequacy of one ship in the Gulf for this purpose is obvious.IV. Preven ting a^&amp;ressio_n_ ^^.nst British or rifjits,!, B^sidu r&gt; etc. Of increasing importance with a Persian havy fast materialising. V. Protection of life and -pro perty of British subjects. a 3 a t Bahrain during Perso-Nejdi riots 1923 and at Abadan during 1929. VI. Assisting in the est ablishment of the _A r^b Air Route. e.g. Installation of tanks on Yas Island, flights to Masirah, etc. VII. Complying with requisit ions of Political Resident and of Poli_tio_a l ^ents for conveyance. The aloops are admittedly not suited for this duty tut with 3 present in the Gulf the Political Resident and Political Agents have teen atle to utilise them and, at any rate, have the assurance that they can get about quickly in an emergency.(R7682) Wt 15933/2537 10,000 2) 11/30 H &amp; SP Gp 112 B 12 b . + Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted V^kt f 0^ (/?' Reference to previous correspondence: V' Letter J' 0 the Colonial Office of the 6--L fc&amp;m fZ. Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the Colonial Office, Downing Street, 1 9 . ENCLOeUftE K1Y LETTER No. - - 22.OCT.1931 FROM SECRETARY; 1 POLITIOAL AMD SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICEPrevious File. P. POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPARTMENT. SUBJECT : YEAR. 19 P. This file contains the following papers :— 19 P. 19 P. 19 P. 19 P. 19 P. If any papers are removed from this File, please inform the Political Registry. 6696b 1000 10.23</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3721</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3721</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/10 'Persian Gulf - Reduction in Number of Subsidised Vessels in as a Measure of Economy'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-13T22:00:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 26; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are also present in parallel between ff 4-12, and ff 17-22; these numbers are also written in pencil or crayon, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding a proposal to reduce the number of British naval vessels stationed permanently in the Persian Gulf.The correspondence is between officials in Iraq, India and the Political Residency in Bushire. It discusses the political impact of the suggested reduction taking place, the economic rationale and how such a decision would be perceived locally.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Naval affairs</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00011d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>