<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000206_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-05T10:13:17.017Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">© / A IvIEMORi'iNDUM DISTRIBUTION BY UNITED KINGDOIvI HIGH COMIISSIQNERS IN INDIA iiND PAKISTivN OF WEEKLY OPDOMS iiND MONTHLY REPRECIAT IONS TO POSTS OVERSEiiS. The following statement shows the posts to which OPDOMS and Monthly Appreciations respectively should be sent direct by the United Kingdom High Commissioners in India and Pakistan and the appropriate method of transmission. 2. It will be seen that in most cases the reports will be sent Saving (by Bag). Where no quicker Bag route is available, the papers should be enclosed in an envelope addressed to the recipient c/o the Commonwealth Relations Office, Foreign Office, or Colonial Office, as the case may be: the envelopes thus addressed should be sent by Bag to the Commonwealth Relations Office who will attend to their onward transmission. 3. It is suggested that papers intended for the United Kingdom High Commissioners in Canada and Australia might be forwarded by courtesy of the Canadian or Australian High Commissioner at New Delhi, in his Bag. Similar expeditious arrangements will no doubt suggest themselves locally at New Delhi and Karachi,POSTS UNDER CGLMONY/E^LTII REL^TIuNS OFFICE WEEKLY PART I OPDOMS PART II MONTHLY APIRECIATIGNS United Kingdom High Commissioner, Karachi New Delhi By Telm. By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) United Kingdom High Commissioners at Ottawa, Canberra, Wellington, Pretoria. Colombo. By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) (N.B. A United Kin-gdom High Coramissioner will be in Ceylon from February 4th, 1948 , and should receive back copies from January 1st). Political Resident in the Persian Gulf By Bag By Bag (Saving) (Saving) (N.B. This post will be transferred to the Foreign Office from April 1st 1948) By Bag (Saving) (4 copies) United Kingdom Representative Dublin. By Bag (Saving) By Bag ( Saving) By Bag (Saving) POSTS UNDER THE FOREIGN OFFICE His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul By Telm. By Bag (Saving) By Bag ( Saving) His Majesty’s ajnbassador, Katmandu By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) His Majesty’s Ambassador, Moscow ' By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) His Majesty's Ambassador, Nanking By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) His Majesty’s ijnbassador, Rangoon By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) His Majesty's Ambassador, Teheran By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) His Majesty’s Ambassador, Washington By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) The Permanent United Kingdom Representative to United Nations, New York By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) The Special Commissioner S.E. Asia, Singapore By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) By Bag (Saving) POSTS UNDER THE COLONLxL OFFICE The Officer Administering the Government Nairobi Kenya Nil Nil By Bag (Saving) (one copy)$ - V *- 2 - X-OSTS UNDER THE COLONli^L CFFICE (contd). 7/EEKLY Ox-DCIvIS PAXtT I I-AIiT II The Officer Administering the Government Government Entebbe, Nil Uganda The Officer Administering the Government Dar-Es-Salam, Tanganyika Territory Nil The Officer Administering the Government Zomba, Nyasaland Nil The Officer Administering the Government Kurd a Lumpur, Malaya Nil The Officer Administering the Government Singapore Nil The Governor General, Cathay Building, The Officer Administering Tne Officer Administering The officer administering The Officer Administering The Officer Administering Singapore Nil the Government Hong Kong Nil the Government Kingston, Jamaica Nil- the Government Port of Spain, Trinidad Nil the Government Suva, Fiji Nil the Government Port Louis, Mauritius Nil The British Resident, Zanzibar Nil MONTHLY AH7RECIATIQNS By Bag (Saving) (one copy) —do— -do ry Bag (Saving) (3 copies) By Bag (Saving) (one copy) -do- -do- -do- -dc~ -do- The Secretary, East African Governors Conference, Nairobi, Kenya Nil -do-€&gt; SECRET f vi. IRS IAN GULF RESIDENCE BAHRAIN. D.O. NP.1791-S EXT &lt;§&gt; the 14th October, 1947 INDEXED t4 We receive here from various sources Intelligence Reports on all the Middle East countries but we learn little or nothing of what is happening in India and Pakistan beyond what we see in the papers and in the fortnightly political appreciation issued by the Ministry of Information and Broad casting, New Delhi. Presumably some kind of Intelligence Reports are compiled about events in the two Dominions. Would it be possible for you to arrange for this Residency and the Political Agencies to be supplied with copies ? We still have many connections with India here and are responsible for the welfare of many Indian subjects. It is, I think, important that we should receive accurate information regarding the Indian political situation. We ourselves send copies of the Residency Monthly Letter and the Agency Fortnightly Summaries to the United Kingdom High Commissioners in India and Pakistani ^ ^ j l0/ ^ Whitehall LONDON, S.W.l■I HH1 f^KfaSnaJl tZXT &amp; OI^/ifi &gt;OLITIC;lL DaP^TI.j^:^ &gt; QQmm:rEnjni podlations 03^iqe. EXH^SS LJTTIIH (All: KIJL) Front The Secretary of State for 0a : .onwealth delations. To: United Kingdon High Conniesloner, New Delhi, Dated: 9th Docenhcr, ^'9h-7 * No. Pol.11643/47 Pollov/ing from Carter 1. . We have been giving some consideration to the arrangenents which have now been evolved for periodical reporting by^you and Grafftey-Smith on political and other developments in India and Pakistan, go have found the reports which you have been sending us of much interest and value. The following suggestions arc based on our experience of handling at this end these reports anu those we get from G-raff toy-Smith. Y/e have had in mind two considerations, namely that wo should be enabled adequately to fulfil the requirements of H.M.G. for infomation without placing an undue load on your staffs, especially at a time when pressure of work is so heavy, and, secondly, that as far as is reasonably racticablc the reports from both High -Commissioners should be prepared and supplied on a uniform basis. We feel that these objects can best be served if in future reporting by both High Commissioners were brought into accordance with the scheme described in paragraph / 2 of the enclosed memorandum. 2. The effect of these suggestions would bo to introduce modifications in your practice mainly in the following respects: - • ( a ) We feel it important that wo should have a summarised monthly appreciation (vide paragraph 2(a) of the memorandum). It was this requirement which we had in mind in paragraphs 6 and 7 of the draft telegram enclosed with my letter of 15th August; but whereas it was there envisaged that this appreciation should be submitted every fortnight, we now consider that, having regard to the other material which you will be sending us, it will be sufficient if it is submitted monthly. This would be a sc If-contained document which would have a much wider circulation than the weekly reports. J M Wo arc asking you to send us your Opdom weekly instead of fortnightly, and in two ports. Part (i) corresponds to the scries of telegrams on the general situation which you already send us and would cover precisely the same scope as these, which we find quite excellent for their purpose. This/1 - 2 - This vnuld enable you to nr.kc Part (ii) s.oev/hat shorter than your present Opdoins, both beoauso of shorter period to be covered ana because there v/ill be no need to reproduce any infornati^n alreaay given in the weekly telegram. N r \'.o-il it be necessary to recapitulate in detail in the weekly Ogdon (Part (ii)) material which is already contained either in the weekly reports from your outposts or in special ad h e rc t . rts n particular subjects which you nay have sent us by despatch, savin, ran or telegram* 3 . -Je should be grateful for your views on those suggestions. If you agree wo hope you will be able to introduce the new procedure with effect from 1st January, 1o4o* 4. I am writing similarly to G-rafftey-Saith, The issue of the above has been duly authorised* ISCt ) H A, f, RUWIBOtPPOLITICAL ESPACTMENT. COM-m7E/J^TH lALa’IT IONS OFF ICE. EAIJ^ES LETTER (AIL K;IL) . Prom: The Secretary of State for Cc j.iorrv/ealth Relations. To: United Kingdon Hi 'h Conniscionor, Karachi• Dated: 9th December, 19A-7* No.Pol.11643/47 Following from Carter 1 • Ae hr.ve been giving some consideration to the arrangements which have now been evolved for peri &gt;dical reporting ty you and Shone on political and other developments in India a.nd Pakistan, do find y .' ) ur weekly review of events most interesting and valuable, and greatly admire the way in which you were able to get arrangements for periodical reporting into working order so quickly notwithstanding smallness of your staff. The following suggestions arc based on our experience of handling these reports .and those we get from Shone at this end. V, r o have had in mind two' considerations, namely that we should be enabled adequately to fulfil the requirements of H.M.G. for information without placing an undue load on your staffs, especially at a time when pressure of work is so heavy and secondly, so far as is reasonably practicable, that reports from both High Commissioners should be prepared and supplied on same basis, lie feel that these objects can be best served if in 1 uturc reporting by both High Commisieners were brought into accordance with the scheme described in paragraph 2 of the enclosed memorandum. 2 * _ The effect of these suggestions w add be to introduce modifications in your present practic mainly in th^ foil .wing respects:- (^•) do feel it important that we should have a summarised monthly appreciation (vide paragraph 2(a) of the memorandum). It was this requirement which we had in mind in paragraphs 6 and 7 of draft telegram enclosed with my letter of 15th^AugUst; but whereas it was there envisaged that this appreciation should be submitted every fortnight, we now consider that, having regard to the other material which you will be sending us, it will be sufficient^if it is .submitted monthly. This would be a self-contained document with a much wider circulation than the weekly reports. This answers the question asked in your Savingram No.23 of 15 th September' I apologise for the delay in replying to this. Fart (i) of the proposed.Opdom will take the place of the weekly telegram on the communal situation which y,u send us at present: L-ut it will, of course, have to cover a wider field md acc rdin'lv will be somewhat longer. (c) Part (ii) of the proposed Opdom sh aid be on the same lines- 2 - as your weekly review of events, 7 e suggest, however, that y u nay he able to reduce its length considerably. In the first place, there will be no heed to introduce any inf emotion already given in the weekly telegram. In the nee n . lace, we are inclined to think that some developments which y u .t resent '.escribe in some detail in your weekly reviews coul be more a.' :&gt;ropri; .tely dealt with in separate ad hoc reports, e,g, the Cabinet crisis in the T v7est Punjab and the Jute export duty., If thin /ere done, it would only be nec- cessary for a very brief mention f such developments to bo made in the weekly Opdom. Kor vd.ll it Le necessary for you to recapitulate in detail in the weekly Opdom (mart (ii)) matters which are covered by the weekly reports from your out a-sts, 3. We would be grateful for your views on these suggestions. If you .agree, we hope you will be able to introduce the new procedure with effect from 1st January, 1948, 4. I am writing similarly to Shone, The issue of the above has been duly authorised. | 5 d&lt;) H. A, P, RUM 8 CLCPol. 11643/1947 MEMOIoiJDUM. Tho Commonwealth iLelationo Office at present recei'/e the followimg political and general situation reports from the U.K. digh Commissioners in India and Pakistan:- U.K.Hi.^h Commissioner in India (a) A weekly telegraphic appreciation of the political situation. (b) A fortnightly Opdom by air mail. UyK.High Cor.Tmissioner in Pakistan. (°) ^ weekly telegraphic report on the communal situation. (d) A weekly review of events by air mail. ^• ^- n substitution for these reports, the Commonwealth Relations Office would like to receive in future from each High Commissioner:- (a) A summarised monthly appreciation of the general situation about 1,500 words in length. This should deal primarily with political developments but it shoulc, also include s me acc ount of important events in other liclds, of economic conditions and of the state of XOwl.ic o; ini' n. In th , main it should be factual, and comment shoulu be cc-iixined to the minimum required for the assessment of the significance of the facts described. It will be given a wide distribution, not &gt;nly to Ministers and Government Depar tments in L ndon, but also to H.M. Representatives abroad. If security conditions permit, the High Commissioners are asked to send copies by air mail direct t ■&gt; the addressees sh wn on the enclosed list. Only two copies need be sent (also by air mail) to the Commonwealth Relations Office, which will arrange for the necessary copying and distribution to other posts abroad and G vernment Departments, etc. in London. ft) A weekly Opdom in two parts:- (i) A telegraphic appreciation of the general situation on the same lines as that already supplied by the U.K.High Commissioner in India (vide paragraph 1 (a)), but covering a wider field then that supplied by the U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan (vide paragraph 1 (c)).' (ii) a ; upplemcntaiy air mail savingram covering much the • same ground as the Opdoms at present supplied by the U.K. HirR Commissioner in India, but omitting any information already given in the weekly telegram. Two copies of this letter should be sent to the Commonwealth Relations Office by fast air mail. It is considered preferable that mattersof sufficient importance/*1 - 2 - importance to merit special ad hoc reports should be so reported separately, either by telegram, savingran or despatch, and that refer nces to‘such matters in the weekly reports (i) or (ii) should be confined t &gt; a brief mention that they are being separately repo rt Gd • For the present the High Cornissi ners should send copies of (i) and (ii) to each other, to the special Commissioner for South East Asia and to the U.K.High Commissioners in Australia and New Zealand* Further consideration will be :,iven to the question whether other posts and, if so, which, should bo supplied with these reports direct from New Nclhi ard Karachi* (c) Neekly reports should be submitted by the outposts to the High Commissioners and cop)ies should be sent to the Commonwealth Relations Office by fast air mail. The High Oommissioners would no doubt wish to incorporate in their weekly telegrams (vide (b)(i) above) any material from those weekly re. orts which they considered specially suitable for the purpose, but it will be unnecessary for their contents to be recapitulated in the weekly air mail report ((b)(ii)). If, however, the High Commissioners are submitting an ad hoc report, in the form of a despatch or otherwise, on any subject, this report might suitably include what is said on the subject in any of the weekly reports from the outposts in order to make it self-contained*I (3 1 . The High Commissioner for the U.K. IrF - ia Pakistan. 2 . do do Australia, 3. do do New Zealand. 4. The Special Coiamissioner for South-East Asia, Singapore* 5* Governor-General, Cathay Building, Singapore. Offioer Administering the Government, Singapore. 7. do do Kuala Lumpur,Malaya (three copies). 8 . do do Hong Kong. 9. H.M.Ambassador, Tehran. 10 . II .M . Ambassador, Katmandu. 11 . H.M.Minister, Kabul. 12 . The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (four copies').Ext. 2297/47 Secretary. Political Department. Please see Sir Rupert Hay* s letter asking to be supplied with copies of reports on events in India and Pakistan. I see that the J.k. High Uomtaissioners send vcj —\ a weekly review of events of which copies are sent to the U#K. krade Oointaissioner and to Singapore; I presume that there will be no difficulty in arranging for copies to be sent to the Political Resident. He should have four copies if possible, three of which he would pass on to the Political Agents under him. Incidentally, I think it would be most desirable that the paragrapns in the Pakistan report relating to events in the North ./est Frontier Province and on foreign affairs should be given both to the Foreign Office and to the British negation in Kabul; I hope that sufficient copies can be produced to enable this to be done. M 'OUTWARD TELEGRAM ||iS£a|^^£artment CYPHER (O.T.P,) Secretary of State for India Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 23*30 hours, 25 th August, 1947 _ rora To Despatched nq&gt; ■HQia . mm. Your telegram 869 of 6th August• 2* I agree in respect of Agency Intelligence summaries. In order however to maintain confidential level of your raonthly letter it would be better that this should not repeat not be sent to India for the present, 3, Copies of both intelligence sunmaries and monthly letter should be sent to U.K. High Commissioners in India and Pakistan, Copy to FOREIGN OFFICE (Mr, Pyraan) =n r? GOMID^TIaL, D*0 *15 o • 135-3 • U- THifi RESIDE CY, BAHRAIN, 15th January 1948. *’&gt;DGXEO Please refer to your demi-official let ter No.Ext 2297 /47 dated the 7th Janu ary abo_ut reports from the U.K. High commissioners in Indi a and Pakistan. 2. I am grateful to you for arranging for the summarised monthly appreciations to be sent to me. 3. With reference to paragraph 3 of your letter I should be grateful if one copy of the first part of the weekly Opdom could be sent to me by each High Commissioner by ai r mail. When I have seen a few specimens I can decide whether it is necessary to ask for additional copies for the Political Agents. E.P. Donaldson nJsquire, C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office, LONDON. RHL.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000206_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1217</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000206</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1217</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 2297/47 'Supply of intelligence summaries from India and Pakistan to Political Resident, Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-18T11:25:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21, these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of letters, notes, memoranda and telegrams between officials of the Foreign Office, the Commonwealth Relations Office, the Secretary to the India Office’s Political Department, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, regarding the distribution of intelligence summaries from India and Pakistan written by Laurence Grafftey-Smith, UK High Commissioner in Pakistan, to the Political Resident. The purpose of the reports is to describe the political situation in India and Pakistan.The file also contains memoranda regarding political and general situation reports from the UK High Commissioners in India and Pakistan.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>India</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Pakistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Memorandums</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000206#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>