<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000fa_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:48:06.469Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">D.O.No. y/A- ft / CD r Adviserate, March 3, 1946 Referring to our recent conversation, herewith a copy of the book on Bahaism and the attack on Shiaam which may interest you. Lt. Colonel A.C. Gallo\»ay, O.B. 3., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. A; . * ConfidentiaL BA.HR A.TN RECEIPT. Confidential. D.O. No. C/496-2E Adviser’s Office, Bahrain, March 6, 1946. The following facts nay he of interest to you. In October 1944 we sent 3 hoys from the Secondary school to Cairo ^or higher education under the aus pices o^ the British Council. After about 13 months two of them returned, one was Khalid bin Mohomed Alkhalifah, grandson of Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa and the other was Fahad Dha’n son of an A^ab pearl mer chant o'f Muharraq. These two boys had become mem bers of a new political organisation which has made considerable progress in Egypt under the name o^f A1-Ansar. The Ansar has apparently a certain likeness to Naziism as one of its most important conditions is that all members must be of pure Arab stock It advocates a simple life back-to-the-land policy and is opposed to all modern inventions, including edu cation. The members are supposed to live in tents, like their forefathers, to till the ground and breed animals and to eschew all modern things. It is surprising that any young men from Bahrain, especially members o^ the Ruling Family, should be in sympathy with these ideas but both these boys and 1 believe some of the othe^ bo' T s are strongly affected by the movement which has now gained a certain number of supporters in Bahrain, some o^ them ^rom Hedd. It does not seem to be a very dangerous movement but 1 ,oI thinic it would be interesting to know more about it, could you obtain more information on the subject from ISgypt? Two other matters have caused Eis Highness some concern lately./^ A number of books published in Teheran, have found their way into Bahrain. There are copies C- in Persian and in Arabic, I sent you a copy o~ This boo;c is said to have been published with the inten tion of stirring up religious trouble in Persia and it is thought to be financed by Russians, this is of course mere heresay. The book is a violent attack on the ohia religion of today and caused a slight disturbance in Bahrain some time ago when some young men began quoting extracts from it. It is now known that the Government is taking an interest in the matter, so copies of the book are not appearing in public. jj The third matter which has ocurred recently is the missionary work of Mr. Faizi, an ex-school teacher, who is a Bahai and has apparently succeeded in convert ing some people in Bahrain to his way of thinking. Arabic edition with my D.O. No. 47Q-9A dated Lieut. Colonel A. C. Galloway, O.B.i!., H.B.MTs Political Agent, Bahrain.No.C/322 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 27th of March, 1946 To The Hon f ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, bus h ire Memorandum Mr. Belgrave informs me that two of the students sent to Egypt, Khalid bin Mohammed A1 Khalifa, a grandson of Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa, and Fahad Dha'n, a son of a local Arab pearl merchant, have recently returned to Bahrain having enlisted as members of a new political organisation which has made considerable progress in Egypt under the name of ,f Al Ansar”. Mr. Belgrave says that they have made a number of proselytes among the young men of Bahrain. He describes ”A1 Ansar” as having ”apparently a certain likeness to Nazism as one of its most important conditions is that all members must be of pure Arab stock. It advocates a simple life, back-to-the-land policy, and is opposed to all modern inventions, including education. The members are supposed to live in tents like their forefathers, to till the ground and breed animals, and to eschew all modern things.” 2. Mr. Belgrave does not consider ”A1 Ansar” a very dangerous movement but wishes to know more about it and has asked me to make enquiries. I suggest therefore, if you see no objection, that His Majesty's Embassy, Cairo, may be asked to supply this information. 3. You may also wish to take up the matter with the British Council since the joining of ”Al Ansar” has of necessity cut short the studies of both these students. They returned to Bahrain after only thirteen months in Cairo, and according to our reports have refused to study further. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED for Assistant Political Agent Bahrain.Extract from Demi-Official letter NO.C/496-2E dated the 6th March, 1946, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the political Agent, Bahrain. © xx xst XX A number of books published in Teheran, have found their way into Bahrain. There are copies in Persian and in Arabic, I sent you a copy of the Arabic edition with my D.0. N0.478-9A dated 3rd March. This book is said to have been published with the intention of stirring up religious trouble in Persia and it is thought to be financed by Russians, this is of course mere heresay. The book is a violent attack on the Shia religion of today and caused a slight disturbance in Bahrain some time ago when some young men began quoting extracts from it. It is now known that the Government is taking an interest in the matter, so copies of the book are not appearing in public. XX XX XX No.C/323. political Agency, Bahrain, The 27th of March, 1946. Forwarded with compliments to: The Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushi for information. f k NS.CONFIDENTIAL. 'Vi- ■'? £ 0 GOVERNMENT OP INDIA; DlPABTHlNT, EXPRESS LETTER [N.B %—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Reference your endorsement No. C/323 dated the 27th and, if possible, the names of the authors and publishers, forward ing copies if obtainable. for Secreta v __ _ .litical Resident,Persian Gulf. HDN. s. 6. MFP—601 S&amp;P-(M-820)—23-7-30—300,000. From Political Resident Bushire • tfo...*- Political Agent Bahrain. No. Dated 4th April IL46 . Larch 1946 2 Please ascertain and report the titles of the books 3d. GEOFFREY PRIOR. Political Resident, Persian Gulf ATTE3TED.No.C/398 political Agency, Bahrain, The 15th of April, 1946. To The Hon»ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. © Memorandum . Reference your Express Letter No.385-S dated the 4th April, 1946. 2. I enclose copies of two of these publications. The particulars required by you are as follows:- (1) (a) Title. At Tashyii (and) Ash Shiah (The Shia f h Faith and the Shia (b) Author. Ahmed al Kisrawi. (c) publisher. Diman Press, Tehran. 1364. (2) (a) Title. Louh Mubarak (The Blessed plank) (b) Author. Shaikh Mohammed Taqi Mojtahid Isfahan! ('Nafafi”) (&lt;=) Publisher. Not given. 3. The return of the books is requested when finished with. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. nfr 1 &gt; 2 - // ^ No. 414-S Persian Gulf Residency Bushire. 6th April li/46. © Dear Embassy, Two Bahraini students who had recently been sent to college in Egypt have now returned to Bahrain after having enlisted as members of a new political organisation called 'al Ansar'• This organisation (which apparently has a certain resemblance to Nazism in that one of its most important conditions is that all members must be of pure Arab stock) is reported to have made considerable progress in Cairo and to advocate, inter alia * a simple life, back-to-the- land policy and opposition to all modern inventions, including education. 2. We would be glad to know more about it and shall be most grateful for any information you can let us have regarding its history and activities. Yours ever RESIDENCY The British Embassy, HDN CAIRO 415-J. Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. 6th April 1^46. Forwarded, with corpliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrain .GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. gOipiP&amp;BTlAl- EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAlTT [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] No. 462 - 3 &gt; To Dated Simla xxxxxxx Persian Gulf Hesideney, t the Bush Ire, 18th April 19 * 46 Repeated Reference His Majesty's Secretary of State for mdia, U)mDOu &gt; The Secretary to the uovernment of India in the ifixtemal Affairs Department, Mi yShe Politioal Agent, DAliaAla . my XXXXXXXXXX POJLiTiCAL ACTIVITIES GJ? BAHRAIN 3TUDEH7C' IKt ; UTBD TO 17.IRQ, r ^ Copy is enclosed of Bahrain memorandum No. C/322 dated the 27th March 1946 with the request that the undesirable ^ contacte formed by these students be brought to the notice of the British Council and that they be pressed to provide a British Director of Education as requested in my telegram No. 537 dated the 5th April 1946 icopy enclosed for the Government of India)* This appointment would not, of course, remove the risk of Persian Gulf students in Cairo making undesirable contacts, but would enable closer liaison with British Co unoil representatives in Cairo, resulting in closer supervision, and thereby reduce this risk. 2. His Majesty's Embassy in Cairo have been asked in the meantime for &amp; note on *Al Ansar** 3d* QWDMR8X PRIOR. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested* &gt;r Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. (Signature) (Designation S. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;P—(M-18705—9-2-39—20,000.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/206 » , 1 .' /6 i © The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s)^ with the request that the Police Report should be treated as confidential. Persian Gulf Residency, mmami Camp Bahrain. the 2nd June, 1946* Reference to previous correspondence : £ / Residency endorsement No. 415-S dated the 6th April, 1946. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. pur - Cairo Chancery letter No, 261/8/46 dated the 25th M A1 Ansar M April, 1946, with enclosure. Coifdantial. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. v. n,t e . i/'r.ht—COPY TCft/JR 261/8/46 British Embassy Cairo, 26th April, 1946 Dear Residency, ' With reference to your letter No, 414-S of the 6th April, regarding the organisation in Egypt known as t»Al Ansar, M the only information which we have at present about that organisation is contained in the enclosed police report of a meeting which it held on December 6th, 1945, at the premises of the Young fcen*s Moslem Association in Cairo, It is requested that this police report should be treated as confidential, The Defence Security Officer, Egypt, is endeavour ing to find out more about this Society, and we will pass on to you any further information that may come to light in due course. Yours ever, Sd, G.L. McDermott. Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire,COPY 1 ^ © Reference the ANSAR ARAB UNION meeting of 5*12*45 at the Y.M.M.A. Abdel Daiem Abul Ata El Bakari, official at the Ministry of Education, and president of Ansar Arab Social Union, applied for permission to the said Union, to celebrate the Hegira Day, on 5*2.45, at the Y*M.M*A*, and the Ministry gave the permission. The meeting was held on time and attended by about 500 persons, headed by the Afghan Minister, Abdel Kader Bey Mokhtar and some of the Pan Arab Group. Some verses of the Qoran were recited at 5.30 p.m. and Abdul Daiem Abul Ata el Bakari delivered a speech on the Prophet*s Hegira and the Ansars* help, and their agreeing together, after having been in discord, and how the Ansar increase and spread in all countries including Egypt. He then spoke on the Arab Ansar Union and how it is co-operative and social to gather all Ansars and make them support their country and religion. He was followed by the u/m speakers. The Afghan Minister, about the Hegira and the Ansar*s attitude, and recommended unity and solidarity in Islam. Moh. Bey El Sheriki, Minister of Finance and Foreign Affairs at Transjordania. On the Islamic history, their wars and attitude. Haj Yacoub Bey El Ghosein, the Palestinian. On how the Hegira teaches patience. How the Arabs, in general, are interested in the Palestinian Question, and how Egypt is to be thanked for her help, and support the Islam. Moh. Doam the Indonesian. Of Indonesia*s struggle for independence, thanking the Arab and Moslem World, for their support. Abbas El Assuani. Poem on the non unity of Islam that made foreigners subjugate them, and how they should unite. Moh. Mazhar Said. On the Ansars* clinging to religion and their pious faith. On faith and putting despair away, and sticking to Islam teaching. / A person readA person read Abdul Rahman Bey el Rafei*s speech, apologizing for non attendance and about the Hegira* Abdul Daiem Abul Ata read Dr. Abdul Wahab Azam*s speech, similar to the formers, and ended by recommending the Ansars' Union to be adopted by all Moslem people, and said that the Union is going on 6.12.45 to Abdin Palce, to submit the congratulations, with regard to the Hegira Day. The meeting ended at 8 p.m. Sd. M. Imam BimbashiCONF INITIAL D*0« No. C/636. Dated the 27th June* 1D46. Dear Colonel Hay, With reference to ray raeraorandura No. C/398 dated the 15th April, 1946 and your roquest for further details, I enclose a brief summary of the Arabic work 'The Shia* Faith and the Shia^* 1 by Ahmed al Kisrawi. As regards the “Blessed Plank 1 *, this is in Persian interpolated with rather technical religious Arabic. I have no one on my staff capable of reading the Persian, and I wonder if you would consider enlisting the aid of the Residency Persian raunshi. Yours sincerely, The Hon * ble Lieut. Colonel W.H. Hay, C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain .Digest from the book 'The Shia’ Faith and the Shia's” by Ahmed al Kisrawi. The division of the Muslims into two major and irreconcilable divisions, which exist today, began after the death of the Prophet Muharnmed when the Caliphate was given to the house of Mua'wiya (OMMAYAD) in place of the house of Ali, the supporters of the former being known as SUNNIS, and the supporters of Ali as SHIA’S. . The divergenc has been strengthened by bitter hatred and civil wars, each sect being convinced that their cause is the only rightful one. The author has made a strong indictment against the Shia’s giving his reasons for maintaining that the Sunnis are much nearer to true Islam. The first and second chapters of the book relate to the events after Muhammed's death, the bitter enmity of the Shia’3 for the Sunnis after the Caliphate was seized from Ali by Mua’wiya, and the continual but fruitless efforts of the Shia's to regain power. The influence of a Shia* named Muhammed bin Haufiya, the originator of Mahdiism, is stressed. Elected as their Mahdi, the Shia's believed and still believe today that he will return and reestablish their power. The author maintains that respons ibility for many of the outrages committed by the Shia’s against the Sunnis is directly due to this Mahdi influence, and mentions the system of ’Taqiya’ whereby the Shia' mullahs claimed divine right as being representatives of the Mahdi's sons, who were mythical deities never to be seen: these Mullahs exercised considerable influence socially, economically and intellectually amongst their followers to the detriment of the Sunnis, especially when the Shia’s were in power in Baghdad. The author denounces these Mahdis as being evil-doers who in the name of religion tried to destroy true Islam. The remaining chapters of the book are a repetition of the indictments against the Shia’s and their beliefs, and a final review a is made of the reasons for the successful growth of Shia’ism. These may be condensed into the following the divine right of Ali, and the intense belief in the rightness of their cause by his followers? the considerable influence of Mahdiisra; the sympathy for the murder of Hussein and his relatives, which has been cultivated into fanaticism; and lastly the strong following that Shia’ism had from the Persians. 15. 6. 46. J.S.H. Hudson, Captain.CONFIDENTIAL. '*? /' ? • . ■ - II —, - No. C/404 The Hmi’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents Ins compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and Imp the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). - Office of the Political Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. ^IkxtjisiK fJoM3Q3da:bex6r0«K3CK^ Resident, ►a ted ath..J.uly. .19.46 ... Reference to previous correspondence: Bahrain memorandum No. C/398 dated the 15th April 1946 Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Two books 1. At Tashyii (and) Ash (The Shia 1 *! Faith 2. Louh Mubarak (The Blessed Plank) Shiah and the Shia*h) Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Sf.fJLkl Date » / 7 / M Cn D.O.No.C/730. The Political Agency, ^ m Bahrain. Dated the 10th July 1946. 12 Dear Belgrave, Please refer to your demi-official letter No. 478 - 9A dated the 3rd March 1946. I thank you for the loan of the two books, ' s which I return herewith. Yours sincerely, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. A • J«S • jCONFIDENTIAL © No. 90 - S. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ The. Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCE, BAHRAIN. Dated the 14th January, 1S47. Reference to previous correspondence : This Residency indorsement No. C/206, (!^ted the 2nd June, 1946. Description of enclosure : 1 Number and Date ’ Subject % » t Letter No. 1314 (32/170/46), 1 dated the 16th December, \1946, 1 from the British Embassy,\ ’ Cairo. \ 1 • r v: Arab Youth movement 'Al-Ansar”. © '' - T ' . , , u) ^ H ’ V' ' . ' &gt; O i Y &gt; G • A • u . Confi^eniiai. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.TCR/HME. N o. 1314 32/170/46 Sir, BRITISH ElffiASSY, CAIRO, 16th December, 1946. In its issue of October 26th last the weekly review 'Akhbar hl-Yom' published an article regarding an Arab Youth movement called 'Al-Ansar' which it stated existed clandestinely in all Arab countries and was directed by a secret organization called ’’Council of Companions” in which all Arab countries were represented. The report mentioned that 'Al-^nsar” was keeping a close watch on the Arab League which it regarded as a British instrument and would eliminate every Arab leader whom it regarded as a danger to the cause of arab unity. It would be prepared to supplant the j- rab League itself if it considered that the latter was failing in its mission of unifying the Arab world. 2. The writer of the article stated that he had obtained his information about this organization from Istaubul, Aleppo and the Lebanon. ”Al-Ansar” is stated to be desirous of organizing Arab youth clubs or hostels to facilitate the exchange of visits between the nationals of one Arab country and another and to grant special facilities for students in this connection. . 3. I enclose a copy of a letter dated 4th December from Defence Security Officer, Egypt, in paragraph 3 of which the programme of ”Al-Ansar” is summarized under eight headings. The Defence Security Officer reports that according to one source the leader of this movement is the ex-Mufti and that in Egypt the -chief is either Mohammed Salah-el-Din Bey, who, as Tanas Pasha's right-hand man in 1942, took a prominent part in the initial discussions which eventually led to the formation of the Arab League. Colonel Jenkins also mentions that Saleh Harb Pasha, the anti-British President of the Young Men's Moslem Association in Egypt, is stated by another source to be the chief of the Egyptian Branch of ”Al-Ansar”. 4. I would invite attention to paragraph 7 of Colonel Jenkins' letter in which it is stated that this movement is specifically anti-British and is said to have the backing of both Russia and France. Azzam Pasha has told Brigadier Clayton that the Arab League are watching this movement. 6. I also enclose an extract from the 'Egyptian Gazette” of 1st December containing a Reuter report on an Arab organization which is stated to be developing a para-military formation among its adherents and which may conceivably be identical with 'Al-Ansar'. 6. I am sending copies of this despatch with enclosures to .As Majesty's Representatives in Bagdad, Beirut, Jerusalem., Jedda, Amman and the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. 1 have the honour to be, With the highest respect, Dir, Your most obedient, hu: ble servant, Sd. Ronald Campbell. Tne Right Honourable Ernest Bevin, r.P., Foreign Office, London, j.W.1. G. A. A .CCPY/HME. No. DS(i^) 200/117 DEFENCE SECURITY OFFICE Cairo. 4th December, 1946. TOP SECRET. Dear Kavensdr. le, I would like to draw your attention to an organisation calied 'A1 /.nsar' - the Disciple or Supporter, which has been set up in the Arab world recently. Information on this movement has emanated from various sources including an article in the ^kbar el Yom. 2. Tnis movement comprises youth elements throughout the Arab world including Irak, Syryil, the Lebanon, Transjordan and Egypt. Its aim would appear to be to keep a watchful eye on the activities of the Arab League. Whenever A1 ..nsar considers that the League leaders have deviated from the path of true pan Arabism, they will arrange for their retribution. Sentence will be passed by the council and one of the 'supporters' will carry it out. The League, A1 Ansar, maintains, needs watching as it is the tool of the British. Apar^ from its primary role of assassination, the movement is based on a programme of eight points. a. The formation of a united Arab/ States which will recognise all Arabs as equal citizens. This will enable them to be as powerful as their European counter parts. c. To build a strong Arab army, 'equipped with modern weapons, as recent history has shown that that is the most effective method of winning respect of the Imperialist powers. c. To introduce an Arab currency similar to sterling which will ensure the economic independence of the Arab States. d. To win back Palestine as an Arab state. e. To regard the Arab League as guilty of not having found a solution to the Palestinian problem. f. To organise Louth clubs in every Arab country and combine them under one central control. g. To issue special documents enabling Arabs to travel freely within the Arab States. 4. The movement is organised on a secret cell basis, the members of one group being unknown to members of another group ..iorcover, tne members of each cell will be aware of the identity of one other member only, the cell leader. According to one source, the leader of the movement is tne Mufti. Another indicates Emir Shakib AHSLAN, a member of the Druze family recently returned from Switzerland.2 6. In cgypt the chief is, according to one source, Mohamed iiey Saleh el Din, under Secretary of State for foreign Aliairs 1942 - 44 in the Nahas government. Yet another source mentions Saleh Harb Pasha, president of tne Shabaan el ^uslimeen. Other people who are quoted as being associated with the movement are Jamil Cardan hey, recent Syrian Minister in Egypt and ’ ahmoud Azmi hey. 7. The movement which is specifically anti-British, is said to have the backing of both Russia and France. Yours sincerely, Sd. G. J. JENKINS. C. Ravensdale, Esquire, British Embassy, Cairo. Copied.—— y COPY/1-aiE. l:-t December, 1946. VY 3TERY LDA DE i TALKS OF M SECR£T ARAB AFu.Y AGAINST IMPERIALISTS ” Baghdad, November 30th. 'We believe that the Drab world, and especially the Arab League, is facing extreme dangers from the jealousies of the Big Powers - dangers we must avoid and neutralise.' This, in a nutshell, is the aim of the newly-formed Pan- ^rab 'Organisation for the defence of the Arab league and Arab world' as described in an interview with Reuter's correspondent by the leader of the Iraqi-branch of the organisation who has asked that his name be not divulged. The organisation's headquarters, he said, are in Cairo, with branches in Baghdad, Beirut, Damascus and Jerusalem. The Iraqi leader, a 36-year-old Oxford graduate, who speaks, apart from English and Arabic, his '-other tongue, Turkish, French, and Persian, has already written three books on ..estern Imperialism, the Road to the Far East, and on British Colonies, using different pen-names on each book. He refused to disclose the name or anything connected with the 'Bupreme Chief' of the organisation, but volunteered information on its aims. The anonymous leader said, 'Every member of our organisa tion will be fully trained to use every kind of wea on - as any ordinary soldier. I am sure that within two years ouk organisation will be able to put on a war footing no less than 1,COG,000 fully-trained 'soldiers and officers'. 'Theirs will be the task to defend our homeland from any foreign aggression.' 'Our organisation is similar in many respects to the old Arab organisation that helped our prophet Mohamed control the entire Arab W' rid within a very short time. Our army will consist of storm-troopers, as well as defence an auxiliary forces.' Interference Saying that the Arab world was fading a crisis, the leader went on to say, 'British imperialism and American economic interference in our world, together with their interests in our oil and Middle East markets generally constitute the main dangers besetting us today. We must, therefore, stand firm and face this danger. Referring specifically to the Arab League, the Iraqi leader states : 'Although everyone knows that the League was established for the benefit of the Arabs and the Arab world, it is unfortunate that the League today is indirectly working under semi-uritish influence. There is no doubt about it. 'It will be our task to defend the League against Foreign influence - from whatever quarter it may be.' i.lhu.ui FROiw THE 'EGYPTIAN GAZETTE'. Watch out • • • •Z-3. Watch out He continued : 'One of our main duties Will be to watch out carefully that every Arab statesman, journalist and everyone who works for the Arab League, does his job properly and with one aim, namely, to strengthen the league for the benefit of the ^rab cause and not for the interests of any foreign power. If any of them fails to work for the realisation of this aim he will be sent to a People's Court for trial and punishment according to the organisation's laws'. deferring to Soviet influence 'spreading like fire in the Near and kiddle East,' the Iraqi leader said : 'The Russians talk too much about democracy, but they believe in imperialism just as any other imperialistic power. Vague 'They are trying to gain a footing in our countries, using vague wor^s. The masses probably believe them, but the intelligentsia understands the truth behind this mask.. Persia is a good example of Soviet influence. No Arab wishes to see his homeland become a second Persia. 'Our religious beliefs, traditions and customs all run counter to Soviet ideology. Besides, we believe that the Russians are like other big nations, after our oil and resources.' (R). Copied.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000fa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/823</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000fa</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/823</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 32/18 Influence of 'Al Ansar' Movement in Bahrain and Entry of Iranian Publications Attacking Shi'ah Faith'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-07-22T21:06:53</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (27 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 27; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-24; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials that is related to two distinct topics as follows:an underground, Pan-Arab and Islamic organisation called Al Ansar. This organisation is said to have been active throughout the Arab world, especially in Egypt. Two Bahrainis that were sent to Cairo for their studies are mentioned in the correspondence as having been influenced by the movement while in the country. The file contains an account of a meeting held by Al Ansar in Cairo on 5 December 1945 that was written by Britain's Defence Security Officer in Egypt (ff 13-14). Also enclosed is an extract from the
                              Egyptian Gazette,1 December 1946, that discusses Al Ansar and contains an interview with a man said to be the movement's leader in Iraq (ff 23-24);the entry into Bahrain of two books published in Iran that were said to be critical of the Shia branch of Islam. The two books are named as The Shia' Faith and the Shia's by Ahmed Al Kisrawi and The Blessed Plank by Shaikh Mohammad Taqi Mojtahid Isfahani ("Nafafi"). A digest of Al Kisrawi's book, written by J E H Hudson (Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain), is contained on folio 16.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000fa#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>