<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00025b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:55.221Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">t 4 i This DQcument is the property of His Britannic Majesty s Government. SECRET. THE WAR WITH TURKEY. Meinorandiini by Political Department, India Office. ' // the alliance bet iceen Central Europe and the East can be broken up Encjlish urorld-power is saved. If not, even tolerablij favourable term* of peace elseirhcre will hardly compensate. ' —Dr. Rohrbach in tl Deutsche rolitik.r Hth February 1916, page 292. The surrender of Kut, following on the evacuation of Gallipoli and the failure of British arms to achieve success against the Turks, suggests the desirability that His Majesty's Government should examine more closely the question of what the war with Turkey means to Great Britain. Dr. Rohrbach s summary statement represents the view that has been urged by the Political Department of the India Office for the last year, and it is proposed to set forth in this memorandum the considerations which make the Turco-German alliance, and consequently the integrity of the Ottoman Empire, so important to Germany, and their dissolution correspondingly important to Great Britain. 1. After the war Germany will require a great addition to her supply of raw materials, and this she hopes to find—whatever the fate of her overseas trade may be - -in Asiatic Turkey. In the first rosy optimism that followed the opening of the way to Constantinople it was thought that raw material would flow in at once from that source ; it is realised now that it must be some years before the great natural resources of Asiatic Turkey can be exploited, and that there are great difficulties to be overcome first. But the Germans have already set themselves with characteristic thoroughness to study the problem. The way is 'being paved not only by the Germanisation of Turkey—18 German professors are revivifying the University of Constantinople and eight more the High School at Stamboul—but by the spread throughout the principal commercial centres of Germany of accurate knowledge of the Middle East; and the scale on which the process is being carried on indicates that it is not inconsistent with the policy of Government. 2. Whether or not Asiatic Turkey will suffice to take the place of overseas sources of supply, Germany has learnt by bitter experience that she must to some extent at least place her supplies beyond the reach of the British Fleet. For the Rohrbach school not only the Berlin-Bagdad scheme (involving the disappearance of Serbia and the retention of Bulgaria in the German alliance) but also a lirst-class fleet are essential to their conception of German world-power. The blue-water school, realising that this is fantastic, and fearing lest, if a choice has to be made, the sea will be sacrificed to the land, are more modest. It must remain a matter of speculation which will carry the day; but in view of the facts (a) that too many other Powers are interested in the freedom of the seas, (b) that the German Fleet will have failed to justify the hopes formed of it, and (c) that, being especially a Hohenzollern toy, it will probably share the discredit into which an un- successful war may be expected to bring the dynasty—it is a reasonable conjecture that it will be the land scheme for which the German Government will fight longest aird most desperately. 3. However that may be, it being recognised that British sea power and Russian land power cannot be destroyed, Germany requires the means of insuring that neither will be used to her disadvantage, and she hopes to find these in the constant threat which her predominant position in the Middle East would be to the Suez Canal and the Dardanelles. With the Syrian railway extended to the Egyptian frontier and under her influence, she would S 307 50 &lt;&gt; 16 Abe able, ii is argued, whenever the diplomatic sitnatioji required to • 1 the necessary pressure to the ' vital nerve ' of the British Empire •' vd • war her interior position would enable her to force her tn n errant ' e • ln apart ^ er| tniies u England's rule in the remoter parts of the world,' writes Professor K Delbriick, the eminent historian, ' is mainly based ou victories won in generations and the prestige which has grown out, of them. Through failure in this war—in particular through the i-evcrses at the Dardaiif'/b' and in Mesopotamia—and scarcely less through the advance of the all'^ Russian forces in Persia, England's prestige is shaken everywhere in A and Africa. The ganglion of the Empire is Egypt with the Suez CanaT If, as we may hope, rurkey emerges from this world-crisis a consolidated State with a future before it; if this State provides itself .-with railways connecting the remote provinces and making possible the rapid concentration of all its military resources in Palestine and the Sinai peninsula; Encrl-n,,!^ 1 rule over Egypt, which she has hitherto been able to maintain with 6,000 European troops, will no longer be an impregnable fortress in the eyes of iho fellaheen and of the whole Moslem world. If the Suez Car d is once lost, all the bonds that bind together the constituent parts of the Empire will be loosed.' (Preussische Jahrhiichcr, May ID 10, page .'583 ) 4. Xot less serious would be the threat to India from Mesopotamia The much criticised operations in that region, however defective they mav have been in execution in their later stages, were sound in design. The event has proved—and may prove yet more forcibly, if the importance of that theatre is under-rated-that the occupation of the whole vilavet of Basra was essential to prevent the spread of hostilities through Persia to Afghaniatan and the Indian frontier; and it has yet to be shown that the vilayet of Hasra is tena de, and that the purpose of its occupation can be secured without the occupation of Bagdad also At the beginning of the present war Mesopo- tamia was at our mercy. ) et even so we have had to 'lock up' live or - six divisions there, and still rely on Kussian help to save the situation in rnn^nflv ff 6 f tS % m ? asi,r ? of lhe danger by which we should he (onstanth threatened n lurkey, in alliance with Germany or accessible L iT^rh r 6 ' We ii eft - ^ t0 C011S0 ^ ate her militarv position at nagdad. 1 he next war will begin at the door of India. ' ^l^ 1 ^ two considerations lead naturally to a fifth. Behind the comn'ion Inna v I ) ( ' 1 8' 1 | )()lll 'ioo(l ol Egypt and in Mesopotamia is the dcrlarpd h 1 0 ! ;V llsI T 1S o ni - 11 Wa * not for 'othing that Wilhelm 11. / of 'Purkevfor 1, i lt { ie i'T'\ m ^^ on Moslems who own the Sultan Of tho Mn«?lpn ( n i&lt; 1 ^ ) ' 1 ^\ 011 1 va . vs a friend in the German Emperor, and this fa-f 1 1,&lt; ^' i &lt;ltln ' 1 0 | ^'orldsome 100 millions are British subjects, siLnihcanor.n!l eCeS v anl J inVe ^ the Turco-German alliance with a new which it (••u'l ocrn' 110 Slir i viva ^ ^e Ottoman Empire, in any shape in well known tliit tho a Ter . man t00 ^ a peculiar menace to us. It is Greek war eontnhnt !']' ai ' N 1 )1P8! Islam, as demonstrated in the Turco- in 1897 • Imi it w!' e( f 110 ri ! &lt;0 t ! le rising on the Indian frontier on the discovery tlv t' - i 0 ''^orientation of British policy consequent that it becr'in 7n 1? i' 1 ' , Jeen our money on the wrong horse ' had captured Md b ( naise ^ ^hat extent the pan-Islamic propaganda Balkan wars m TlU,ia - Duri ^ th « ^urco-Italian and last influence the policv of iVi^*\h!eTt\ S ' by the Iri(lian Moslen ! s to little has been publidv heard rf , . 0Vern ] nient m favour of Turke 3'. condition of Tndii - h f+i during the present war of the internal has been ^reat and I mq ' K Strail 1 1 the lo^-alty of the Moslem population the faikrf of Grea! IWta'^ length of war and The cry of lehad fiilcl !• • i V Ule an ^ In, hfary success against the lurk. been insufficiently prepafed' BuT'e ^ ^ f emat, ' re - The ^ l0U,ld ha( J hostilities by Turkey D hL u . m . i - ^ before the commencement of in Persia and Afghanistan ''V'f ''tiated for inobiiising Islamic feeling would find a mini rV , • 'eimauy had been led to believe that she among the Hindu anarchists ' ^ :u ' 0;1 g Indian Moslems, but also uu anaunists. I his belief was to u certain extent justified.and Hindu mid Moslem Hritidi subjects entered Afghanistan with the merman parties and are now working against us at Kabul. While so near has the cry o jehad been to success on the fanatical frontier that the &lt; .o\ cr nineiit ol India have been unwilling to publish the apparently anti-Islamic Oeiinan circular recently found in East Africa for fear of involving Croat 1 in tain with Germany in a common anti-Christian condemnation. So delicjate is the situation now. Hut it must be remembered that, thou -h the i\ orley-Minto rolorms made Moslem opinion a political force and gave'a great stimulus to the corporate sense, that opinion is still neither organised nor homogeneous. In the plains the Young Moslem is a pan-Islamist and the activity of men like Zafar Ali Khan, and of the Young Moslem press genciallv, smc^ilip war began, leaves little doubt where their true allegiance lies. Hut the North-West Frontier looks at matters from a different 'point of view. There, great as is the prestige of Houm, and profound as is the belief (confirmed, so far as Great Britain is concerned, by the experience of the present war) in Turkish invincibility—when it comes to a question of jcIkkI, it is to i ue local King ol Islam, the Amir of Afghanistan, and' not to distant Constantinople that men look. J he \ oung Moslem has no footing in this most important region yet; but even now the rising generation in the Frontier Province read the newspapers, and the greybeards who control the young bloods are passing away. In twenty years' time there will be a factor here which may be altogether beyond our control, if there is among the Governments of the world either a powerful Moslem State towards which an organised, homogeneous Young Moslem party throughout India can gravitate, or a weak Moslem State under a hostile influence which can mobilise Islam for its own purposes. Next time the mobilisation will not be premaiure. The pan-Islamic danger is a real and permanent one. All the parties to the present war have to face it, except Germany. We cannot get rid of it altogether. Hut we have the opportunity now (if, in conjunction with Russia, we press the war to its natural conclusion) of immensely diminishing it by reducing to impotence the only existing organised Government that can further the pan-Islamic idea; and when we see the progress which that idea has made in India, under Turkish influence, in the last 10 years, does not common prudence require that w T e should do so ? To leave a Moslem State that will count among the Governments of the world is simply to create a focus of which Germany (who will have nothing to lose) will fan the flame when it suits her—and we, in India and Africa, shall be the principal sufferers. 1 These considerations seem to point to this conclusion:—For Great Biitain the war with Turkey can never be a side issue. It is, of course, obvious that by defeating Turkey we have not defeated Germany, whereas if we succeed in defeating Germany, the collapse of Turkey's military power follows automatically. What is less obvious is why this will not suffice for our purpose. Great Britain is an Asiatic and a Moslem power, and what makes the war with Turkey rather a separate war than a mere episode in a world war, is the fact that we are waging it against another Moslem Power with the rest of the Moslem world for spectators. It is on Mesopotamia and not on Europe that attention is fixed in the Persian Gulf, as we heard the other day from Mekran. 44 The intellect of the Arab is in his eyes,' and the Political Assistant at Aden recently expressed the opinion that a merely diplomatic defeat of Turkey will not count in Arabia. In Afghanistan (where Nasrullah Khan has been diligently retailing British defeats in Mesopotamia) it is to Enver Pasha, who is expected to arrive at the head of 200,000 Turks, that people are looking. In India itself the vernacular Press is loth to believe Russian victories, and loses no opportunity of admiring the feats of Turkish arms. With all these people we shall have to deal after the war, and to live with them on terms of moral supremacy. We shall have to govern India itself —where, besides the Moslem problem, the fact has 1 ' I doubt,' wrote Sir V. Chix*ol last year, ' whether the menacing character of [the Pan -Islamic] propaganda has yet been sutficiently appreciated. Had it had another 10 or 20 years to extend and consolidate itself, I believe it would have constituted an extremely serious danger to British power; and every scheme for dealing with the remnants of the Ottoman Empire after tlie war should, in my opinion, be very carefully studied from that particular point of view.4 to l)e reckoned with that the educated Hindus, though tliey have thrown in their lot with us, are not averse to seeing British pride humbled, and humbled by an Asiatic Tower—and to convince the peoples of India' that a handful of white men can still control them, a task which will not have been rendered easier by indiscriminate eulogy of the exploits of the Indian troops in France. In the regions adjoining India, where for a variety of reasons the military prestige of Great Britain had sullered serious eclipse in the 10 years preceding the war, we shall have to rehabilitate it. To restore order on the frontier and maintain tolerable relations with Afghanistan • to conduct the business of everyday life in Persia; to keep order in the Gulf and control those Aral) chiefs with whom we already have relations and to whose number the very important Amir of Xejd lias recently been added ; and finally, if it should so turn out, to develop the resources of Mesopotamia: in all of which regions the Islamic self-consciousness will have been intensitied. The Arabian policy of His Majesty's Government, so far from diminishing the didiculty of these tasks, will add to it, unless Turkey has been decisively defeated—and defeated by us, not merelv by Russians or French. For while the Arabs are content to use us now for their own ends, it is certain that if and when those ends are attained their attitude will always be less antagonistic towards the Moslem Turk, whatever their grievances against him in the past, than towards the Christian; and if the former is believed to be the better soldier they will play him off against us to their heart's content. Indeed, the policv of fanning the Arab nationalist spirit to a flame is, as far as eastern Arabia and Xejd are concerned, a two-edged weapon of a verv dangerous description—innocuous only if the Turk is beaten in the field, but otherwise likely e\entuall\ to lesult in acute antagonism between the Arabs and ourselves. Nor will our difficulties end there. For we shall have to face in the Far East the ambitions and claims ot a highly aggressive Japan, who will reckon thus|he Japanese have beaten the liussians, the Russians have beaten the lurks, the 1 urks have beaten the British ; erno. \ line of argument which will not be the less convincing to them if— as is presumably quite possible-the war ends without the British fleet having battle 11 0pp iinity demonstrating its superiority to the German fleet in If this prognosis is sound, then—unless we are content prop/&lt;??• vilam viveudi pc.rdcie eausas, or until we are m the last ditch—there can be no short cut to peace with lurkey. The war with Turkev was thrust udoii us precisely because the Germans realised its vital iinportance to us and we grief if vve attach ,eso in wi,ce resumfoperaTions on'u ^argu-lc'l'le''it,''\| ''7°™* l08t gr0l,,ld . aud U ] weather uermits -mrl fn i • ' Mtsopotanua, as soon as the cool Purely militarv considpr-1' X ^ I1 r I' 1 e l )aratl0Ils to that end without delay. ment, but it mav be pointed out 'hat'it^'- r'' 0 C0 ' 1 '.P etel l ce of this Depart- that His Majesty's Goverunient n 1 I l&gt;'rely military considerations against the Turk, and that the success oftln!; 0 ?' r U ) r - ,SU ^ i''® ^ by our failure in Egypt at Aden f vl poll . cy 13 being endangered military strength necessary in order to L 10 the &lt;l,8 P la ' V of them when in motion ; with the r,.s„lt il 11 ® Aral) ® 111 motion, or to support that the Turks, who appear to llv 'T 18 ' 0W cou «derab]e risk buy the Arabs bv oftenu -- then. • t clushed J the movement in Syria, will that Turco-Arab bloc which the miilHi 0 ' 0 '^ • hat i We sllaI1 ^ fi ' Ce(i '' itl1 so greatly add to their difficulties' in t utl ' 0 ' tles last year declared would therefore that they were right in dipt, ' I elsewhere. Supposing cogent nature for early action ' . there are military reasons of a In the meantime all tenrntqtmn firmly resisted. That temnt'itiV * &lt;l I )roniature peace with Turkey must be wTk ,rp7rLb.Y b :r' , ' te ' l :°■ opposition party, may ofter terms 1/ ( - 1 Jn ^ nrkey, or some other any Turkish party could + ]S ' vevei '» a^nost inconceivable that consent to part with Constantinople or Syria onconditions that would be ucceptuble to either Iviissiu or inuice, to wliom we are now too deeply committed to accept them ourselves. ' Fortunately, therefore, such proposals, il they come, are not now likely to bs dangerous. (6) A more serious contingency is that Germany may sooner or later put forward proposals for peace which, while giving the Allies all they want in Europe, and even abandoning the ' freedom of the seas,' will involve only the maintenance of the integrity oi the Ottoman Empire subject to guarantees as regards internal reforms, and even some measure of devolution, such as that proposed by the Inter-departmental Committee on the future of Asiatic Turkey. To Russia alone of the Allies such terms would be 'prima facie unacceptable; but some modus vivendi might be found between Germany and her, while for the rest of us they would contain much .that is on the suriace attractive. Ihey would be popular in India, where Moslem feeling desires to see Turkey spared. They would accord with that deep-rooted belief in the inherent excellence of the Turk which still survives in this country and is already reappearing in the Press, in spite of centuries of experience to the contrary. They would be the line of least resistance for the war-weary. It would even he pointed out that the Inter-departmental Committee had recommended something of the kind on its merits. Ought we not to accept them? Would it not be very dilhcult for Great Britain alone of the Towers to refuse them, if she alone had failed to defeat Turks in the lield ? The temptation would be a subtle one. It would be foreign to the purpose of this Memorandum to examine the recommendations of the Committee and show in detail that they provide no safeguard whatever against the recovery by Germany of the supreme position in Turkey which she was found to possess in 1914. That has been done in a separate memo randum. It must sullice hereto point out that the Committee, writing a year ago in entirely different circumstances, were avowedly seeking for ' a solution which, while securing the vital interests of Great Britain, will give to Turkey ' in Asia some prospect ol' a permanent existence ' (paragraph 98). They were not, however, called upon to examine the prior question whether the permanent existence of the Ottoman Empire is compatible with the vital interests of Great Britain ; and the wider considerations affecting Turkey as a world-power, and the relations of Great Britain and Germany with Islam— which the progress of events since the Committee's report has brought clearly to light, and which it is the purpose of this Memorandum to emphasise did not engage their attention. In the light of subsequent events, one con clusion only seems to follow from the premisses stated in the earlier part of their report, viz., that the only completely and finally satisfactory settlement of Asiatic Turkey is one that involves either partition, or division into spheres of influence on lines such as those which have actually been adopted in the recent Uusso-Franco-British agreements ; and it is perhaps only necessary to add now that if the integrity of the Ottoman Empire were consistent with British interests, it could hardly be proposed by Germany compatibly with her own, for it is the foundation on which (if she loses her colonies) she must seek to reconstruct her Welt Politik. Whatever safeguards we may devise on paper, her whole energy will'be ^devoted to evading them, and to adapting her methods of politico-commercial penetration to the new conditions. Emphasis has been laid above on the Mittel-Europa scheme. But it will not have escaped notice that the failure of Germany to bring about that bloc will not materially lessen the danger to British interests of leaving the Ottoman Empire intact, or sufficiently extensive and strong to be an object of German cupidity or to be capable of playing an effective part in world politics. It did not require the existence of a Central European hloc to make German influence supreme over the Turkish Government in 1914, or to enable Germany to undermine in a few years the results attained by a century of British policy, and her policy in Turkey in the last 15 years has not been the least of the contributory causes of the present war. We can only conjecture the future from the past; and if the bloc fails—as it will if the Allies are decisively victorious—it must be assumed that German policy will be more than ever directed to the acquisition of a supreme commercial, and therefore political, position in Turkey, and that that position will be utilised to the detriment of British s 307 binterests. * From whatever point of view, therefore, tlir problem is regarded, the only satisfactory solution is the reduction of the Ottoman Empire to such political non -entity that it shall be worth nobody's while to tamper with it. ... This, however, still belongs to the future. Our immediate concern, if the views stated above are sound, must be to achieve a decisive defeat of Turkey in the field. The actual conduct of military operations must, of course be governed by military considerations ; but the object of this Memo randum is to suggest die political frame in which, so far as the Middle East is concerned, they must be envisaged if they are not to defeat the purpose for which such great sacrifices have already been made—the attainment of a secure and lasting peace. 'That side will win.' writes Dr. Rohrbach, ' which possesses the greater moral strength to make sacrifices for the sake ' of a great future.' Our idea of a great future is more modest than his; and we need aim at nothing more than a peace which does not contain the germs of war. But we can hardly be content with less. 25th May 1910.problem is regarded, Ottoman Empire to ly's while to tamper immediate concern, if ' a decisive defeat of j operations must, of object of this Memc- as the Middle East is lefeat the purpose for -the attainment of a rites Dr. Rohrbach, sacrifices for the sake 3re modest than his ; does not contain the y l APPENDIX I. lie following extract from an article by Dr. Hans Delbruck in the bchnab.sche i erkur oi lali May (quoted from Daili, Retiew of the Forc'uni /''.'f,-'. th . g ,ves a Convenient summary of the German ideal of W eltpoiitik :— lo most people a Colonial policy meant nothing more than an economic qiKvMion, nut it had a political and national aspect also. For colonies served not only economic purposes, but they also developed and enriched the &lt;iiltiiial lite ot a nation, tlie aggregation of many different peoples in one 8tate influencing each other's culture and the State as a whole. Mankind would be poor if only a few great nations remained, after having swallowed all the others together with their languages and individual civilisations. For instaiu e, il Sn C liailes T)ilkes idea that the world was on the wav to become English became true, or if the world was to be divided between England and Russia, what a miserable prospect it would be for mankind. 1 o pie\ent all other races on the surface of the earth from becoming &lt;•111 losities survivals of a previous tune—between the immense empire of of an English-speaking world, and the solid dead-weight of Slavdom, is the special task ol German world policy. Germany cannot and must not allow the world to be divided between the Russians and the Anglo-Saxons. It is the special mission of Germany to step in and save and protect the future not only of its own race, but also of the individualities of all other small nationalities. And for this purpose Germany must provide herself with a considerable Colonial policy of her own, chiefly, one must assume, in Central Airica. 1' urther, it is the task of Germany to defend Turkey from a partition between England and iiussia. Russia in possession of Constantinople and Asia Minor, and England in possession of an empire from Cairo to Calcutta, would have won such an increase of power that there would be no possibility for other States to pursue an independent policy. The only possible way to draw Mesopotamia, Arabia, Svria, Asia Minor, and the Narrows into the circle of European civilisation is by maintaining Turkey, and by providing possibilities for a Turkish renaissance; and this in turn can only be fully accomplished by the reliance of an independent Muhammadan State upon Germany. So this co-operation of Germanism with Young Turkism may be described as only a special form of German Colonial policy. There are then immense tasks which face German policy and German strength before there can be a question of anything which might embarrass or threaten other peoples. Indeed, the more completely we succeed in exorcising the other terrifying spectre of world domination, the easier and better shall we achieve our task of erecting a great Central African Colonial Empire and of supporting the internal development of the Turkish Fmpire. The German world policy, then, is nothing else than an extensive Colonial policy, which, in order to reach this positive goal, must set bounds to the unbounded pretensions of other world Powers. But in order to achieve our goal Germany must enter the arena of world politics and must build her own fleet. Here German interests run side by side with the general interests of humanity. It is not for the purpose of giving civilisation to the niggers, nor out of any particular love for the Turks, that we feel ourselves called to this policy, but because we owe it to our own race to set before it problems,. in the solution of which it can develop itself and win the self-conscientiousness, which is necessary if it is to become one of the leading nations of the world. The solution of our problems is the winning of equal rights, not of world domination. And equal rights means, above all, the freedom of the seas, for which we must fight as one of the most essential, if not the most essential, of our war aims. Not before we have won the freedom of the seas shall we win the secure possession of our Colonies. The freedom of the seas is a problem of world policy, and without a world policy there can be no Colonial policy.APPENDIX II. Extract Memoranduni by Sir Mark Sykes on ' The problem of the Xoar East,' dated 20tli June 19l() : — It is necessary to review the position of Turkey as a factor in the war. As regards the Central Powers, Asiatic Turkey is the last ( iennan colony. If exhaustion proceeds as at present, at the close of the war Turkey will be the most exhausted combatant ; consequently, if the Germans are iu Turkey on peace they will remain there. Jl (iermany can retain her position in Turkey on peace she keeps the Baghdad railway, the Turkish army, her hold on the Caliphate, and has a white man's country in the uplands of Anatolia to colonise. A post-war Germanised Turkey gives Germany her military bases of nal m iincl xaiconuc Wiu^ii 11C1 a Jiuiu &lt;it unuc; u\rj me /jiUUlbLS, I,lie i apacy ami the Orthodox, a strangle hold on Russia in the Bosphorus, and a monopoly of certain oiltields essential to maritime, aerial, and industrial power. As regards the Allies. Control of the Straits is the great prize which keeps Russia determined, solid and united in the war; if ever it appears unattainable Russia will begin to think ol peace. As regards Trance, the 1914 Ix)an gave her financiers such excellent prospects in Turkey, that hope of the maintenance of Turkey as it stands has been a constant drag on negotiations and on French policy in Turkey, nor must it be forgotten that German financiers have in M. Hugenin, a S^viss, a link with the \ itali interests in Paris ; consequently, unless the I 1 rench have good grounds for hope of a solid compensation, the Germans have an opportunity which they will not miss. A&amp; legards Gieat Britain her vital interests have already been stated in the German position, but they may be re-stated. If the Germans end the war in control of Turkey, Great Britain is faced with a situation the dangers of which are difficult to contemplate with calm. le Kussians, baulked ol Constantinople, will be driven by pressure towards the Persian (.ulf, m which the Germans will encourage 'iliem as they have done m the past. France, interested m her Turkish concessions bv the tJI I Loan, will become a pawn of international financiers of Teutonic bias and once again be forced to participate in the Baghdad railwav. The .?.on ?nH T r n • 0f the ^'^tiou which can equally plav linance md iT t se ! ,ltl011 ' ,he resources of Turkev to aimv Mor nvpl ' ' \ 0 ma,1 • a formidable and natural the control ^f tb ! ''ifr' 16 VeSSel ? haV ' n - revolutionised naval warfare, will become ^ la .wast for the future by a hostile naval power Eastern strit^iT' ' eu 0 1 ' s 'imiense oil areas, a greater menace to our strategists Om' rir 1 ,an ever contemplated by former b t Lter untenabU . 'i i | ® S °I' ota ' lla 'i' ^e one at first of sufferance, c^f.wkS IVnrT ? ' 1 haVe . ^ • 811 h0ld 0,1 the Arabs - aild ^ men and a vast Docke f I .k f mblna twn equipped with resources and strategic lines of am!rmrh^ T r 'f the Navy, holding the world'? c the Kh dih t' .t' r and tlle strill gs of the iloslem be 11uatile'to call allies to our aii 1 f r V^ hands, and we shall I i ivp n I '■i'' lances interests will be in '1 eutonic failed to secure her her rights m the r C,ain ' 0 ' . Russia ' havin « arise if the Germans have 'the enft ' c a s ' tuatl0 ' ma y ea ^ly to an exhausted France and a Ru -i , ','l !&gt;( ' aC ® tel ' ms whlcl1 llre acceptable great and longed for prize. ' Our Vctciii';' « pr08l&gt;ec ? of obtainiu S lier of the Sinai Peniasula tlto r fir , 0 ^^ eso P 0 tamia, the evacuation Belgium; .he of t ? f dl ® rebui,di ^ I'oland, and the cession of Krzonm, i ' ■ evacuation of Prussian Germany to pay to make sure of Hvin^ p'' l^i i® il 1 ap pr ' C ® for decade. Hen- Rohrbaeh s iv T i ' • 0 ^ anc ' at ''ei' mercy within a a German l-oiutT Wow Ao^l 'r'l ^ ' t,,eatr ® of war ' an(l l| -' m J'landers, it is Asia Minor that they are now ficti^'for' 1 ^ ^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00025b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B233</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00025b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B233</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'THE WAR WITH TURKEY. Memorandum by Political Department, India Office.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-10T12:23:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>4 folios</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 51 and terminates at folio 54, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in the volume; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Memorandum, written by Sir Frederic Arthur Hirtzel, dated 25 May 1916, examining the implications of war with Turkey on Great Britain particularly the importance to Germany of a Turco-Ottoman alliance and the integrity of the Ottoman Empire, and the corresponding importance of its dissolution to Great Britain.The memorandum discusses Germany's need for raw materials and its realisation that supplies from Asiatic Turkey may take years to establish; the German threat to the Suez Canal and the Dardanelles; the threat to India from Mesopotamia; the dangers of Pan-islamism; the potential risks of waging war on a Moslem [Muslim] power, particularly given British relations in the Persian Gulf; and the possible outcomes of the war with Germany and the likely position of Turkey in relation to them.Enclosed with the memorandum are two appendices:Appendix I: Extract from an article by Dr Hans Delbrück in the
                              Schwäbische Merkur17 May 1916, summarising the German ideal of 'weltpolitik' (world policy);Appendix II: Extract memorandum by Sir Mark Sykes on "The problem of the Near East", dated 20 June 1916.Sir Frederic Arthur Hirtzel is not named on the memorandum as its author, however IOR/L/PS/18/B234 refers to him as its author.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Secretary to the Political and Secret Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Germany</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Suez Canal</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Turkey</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Ottoman Empire</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Panislamism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00025b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>