<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100031201044.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T21:51:28.606Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Jofcf C GOO OOKFIIJ^KTI AL . In accoraance with the Consul General’s note of &amp;0th February X sukait herewith a note on the British connection with Geistan* It is divided into three parts as follows: Part I . A brief review of British Consular activity in Geistan^ Part IX . The present position in seistan. Part III * Possible future changes in Geistan and recommendations as to the policy which we should follow there. Bated the 18th September 19 39 .mimnmt' A UOTB ON THE XKPOITAJ'CK OK Jf.IUTAH TO INDIA. j.. : oner r.- view,_a_r .jrA.Uati v.pi.guXar activity In. ielstun . Thg Hussian i^enace to loctle « It ia unneoesaary to go Isaok further than the beginning of the present century when the eyes of ail India were turned towards Russia* The Russian advance had absorbed the central Asian Khanatos and had reached the borders of Afghanistan and Persia* iihe found .Kngland ready to defend Afghan frontiers by force of arias* but lost no ti&amp;e in xaaid.ng her influence supreme in Tehran and ^ahed. Jeistan was the only large grain*producing area between Kandahar and Kiraan, and Meshed and the sea* and* as such* it was of importance as a base for the armies of those days* It was the last stage for an army on the way to the Persian Onif from the north* on the way to Persia from the i.ast or to India from the west* Russian opinion of the importance of ueistan can be judged from the following extract from the •Novoe Urem/a* of the Una January l9U3s 'Seistan* by its geographical position and intrinsic nature, deserves* rather than Herat* the name of the 'Key to India'# istan* that flank position on the road to India which it is impossible to turn. Were it in our hands the advance to India would be made far easier* in isngliah hands all our operations are rendered considerably more difficult. Lord Curzon has a keen appreciation of the extreme importance of ■ I I ■ I...!3 ae is tan f and he is, therefore, striving to place it as quicKl^ as possiole under British influence M * Persia at the time appeared on the verge of disintegration and the Coverniaent of India too doufct felt that when that occurred aeistan must fall to her snare and not to Russia's* In the last years of the iVth century Captain hirst British % f ©bto-¥are laid out the trade route from Kushfci to connection * ^eistan* Ihe great advantage of this route was its avoidance of the hasards and impositions entailed in passing through Afghan territory. i^jor Chenevix- Trench, officer on deputation, arrived in ceistan in January 1900 with orders to promote friendly Perso- British relations, to counteract Russian influence, and to promote trade. A liussian Vice-Consul was in residence before him. m found the deistanis already afraid of further Russian advance ana heara rumours that the Russian railway was being pushed on from Kushk via Herat to ceist&amp;n and Ghahbar on the Persian Gulf. The oeistanls had already connections with Quetta where they used to send their wool and ghi, and the British officer was everywhere welcomed warmly. loigland wafc looked to as the likeliest saviour from the Russian menace, ana the Beistanis expected soon to be brought unaer British rule, a prospect which they viewed with approval. The trade route was widely advertised in India, loans were advanced by Government to Induce Indian traders to come to Bast Persia and Persian merchants were given free railway passes in India to encourage them to open . up the trade. Under these stimuli the tirade rapidly bxpaubbd\ ^elstan f iQD • I'en; aorwry azllkah ascendency. «»2** expanded. The Hussianat however, were not long In showing their disapproval of this idyllic state of affairs. The Anglo-phlle governor of jeistan was hotherea with ii^^urs and Kargusars ana demands for money from Tehran where his superiors were under the Russian thumb. Doctors arrived to harry caravans with unnecessary quarantine, end Jjelgiaa customs officers of Russian sympathies to enforce the full collection of customs dues. The Russians pushed through a telegraph line from Reshed and worKed up so much anti-British feeling that there was even talk of resisting the arrival of the hacRahon boundary commission by force. tinder the Anglo-Persian treaty of 1867 Persia was bound to accept British arbitration in disputes with Afghanistan, and a British commission was sent in 1903 to settle the Perso-Afghan frontier in Deistan and decide on each country’s share of the lielmand water. Persian officialdom looked on the mission as the fore-runner of the long expected invasion, and no form of obstruction which ingenuity could contrive was left untried. When they saw that the mission had not come to stay and realised the impartiality of its award, this attitude changed to one of gratitude and friendliness. The Afghans were consistently friendly and helpful throughout. It is noteworthy that after the departure of the mission the British population in aeistan was only seven while the Russian population was fifty-three, although there was not n single non-official Russian subject therei 1^04, however, saw an increase of British influence end a decrease of Russian, due partly-4- i?artly to the advance of our railway to r r uohlci and partly to the issue of the Husao-Japanese war. The advance of the railway combined with a Government contract system for caiaels for transport of goods from Huahki to Meshed materially increased our trade. our popularity with the Persians, however, varied inversely with our ascendency over the Russians* The stronger country was feared, and the weaker encouraged. In 1906 aeistan wr s swept by a severe epidemic of plague In combating which the British Consulate took a leading part. Amongst other normal anti-plague measures a plague hospital was built near the consulate hospital for the isolation and proper treatment of cases. These measures however did not commend themselves to the mullaa who incited the Zabul mob to riot. During this riot the plague hospital was burnt and the consulate hospital damaged. There were grounds for believing that the Russians were not entirely innocent of complicity in this affair as some of the ringleaders were Russian adherents. The neglect of the Persians to punish the ringleaders and their inability to protect the consulate (aggravated by the desertion of many troops during the epidemic) led the Government of India to send anas into Persia for the protection of their consulates. This had to be done without the sanction of the Persian Government (which would heve taken months to procure) and the blow to their teour propre finally extinguished any desire they may have had to bring the rioters to justice. The immunity of the ringleaders was locally attributed to1'he Anglo- Husbihn convention* • 5«» to Russian protection ana construed as a sign of the ascendency of Russia over Knglanti at Tehran. On the other hand the efficacy of the inoculation at the British hospital was in marked contrast to the inefficiency of the Russian arrangements and was much appreciated by the .ieiat&amp;nis who freely availed themselves of it. Finally even the ringleaders of the riot came to he inoculated and peace was restored. The effect of the /inglo-Russian Convention of 1907 was to ease t .e strained relations between the representatives of the two countries in ueistan; though it became apparent that Russia* having secured Tehran in the division of Persia* had the last say. It is noteworthy that at this time there was &amp; Russian Lieutenant-Colonel as military Attache to the Vice-Consulate in Reis tan* The succeeding years were marked by the severe growing-pains of const!tutionallsia in Persia. Crisis followed crisis in Tehran and lawlessness and highway robbery was rife in jeistan. ./xias- smug^ling caravans of truculent Afghans* against whom the Persian authorities were powerless* passed through deistan and the Kein&amp;t every few days. In 1909 the Russians dealt a fatal blow to any slight popularity they may have had with the Persians by bombarding tne shrine of Imam Ressa at meshed. In 1910 the Russian Consul for dels ten and Kaln practically made his headquarters in Birjana and the British telegraphist there was made Vice-Consul as an antidote. In 1911 the Russian bank at ilabul was closed as It had never paid its way*f mm • 6 - fhe iiritlah hospital at bul became very popular and undoubtedly made the UeIstanla think kindly of us. finally in 191^ the iRnaing of British troops in south Persia to counteract Bussian action in north Persia was rather welcomed than resented in 3e is tan* Although in 1914 Persian public opinion The ffar . seemed to prefer }&amp;i gland to Ui a si at when oon fronted with an alliance of these two enemies it became strongly pro-Clerman • The inability or unwillingness of Persia to stop German •military missions'* passing through to Afghanistan or to control illegal arms traffic, compelled us to Institute the Aast Persian Cordon* Uo attempt was made to resist the entry of iiriUsh troops and the prosperity and security they brought in their wake was much appreciated* The old struggle between ng^/tnd and lus ia for influence in .eistan and Baluchistan was ended in England’s favour when in March 1918 charge of the lusai&amp;n ?ice-Consuiate in Babul was handed over to the British Consul* At the end of the war our railway reached i&amp;llpse of Sahidan and the Palang Kuh I'oute to Aeahsd to the rp: i?tan ; west of Jeistan was adopted. Babul was therefore short-circuited and ceased to be an entreaot for laatax^uasias Indo-Persian trade. in X9kk when the Persian customs authorities moved from Babul to Za hi dan the British Consul reported in his m diary ? •husdap (Bnhidan 5 has now entirely superseded beistan as the chief trade centre in Sou th-Ea s t Pers i&amp; • The * Jelst&amp;n Olary Po. 31 of 4th April I9aa, para 37a.■ovlut aot mtjf in .jelavati* -7- Th« ten /ears 19 kO to 1930 saw oonsiaerable anti*jBrtttch activity on the part of the soviet Vice-Consul in ^atoul* who did hie heat to capture the Jielst&amp;n naricet for moaian goods# Kven the ;i«lstanl 3 » hoeevor 9 soon saw Uifough his rude propaganda methods which were effectively put a stop to fcy Carhnng mirtaea Khan Kukri (present Uatandar for Jgukranj; ana when the lusaiana realised that there was no :;eistan market to oapture they closed their Consulate (1930)# This coincided with the visit of the present uhah to jelstan and was attributed entirely to his action# At the same time Iran was striving every nerve to become up-to-date and western, to eliminate foreign influence from the country and to develop her natural resources# In his diary for January 1932 para £, the Consul for ielstan states 'The new Governor tola H#M*Consul that the Persians had, since the iihah'a visit, definitely decided to develop Jeietan# The first step was to he the construction of t&gt; galled road to link Zahidan with he shed v£a Zefcul, and it is hoped also to link the latter place with Kandahar hy road#•••••••• •**• heedless to say this ambitious plan was never translated into action, and Goiatan, after a brief period in the limelight, has gratefully relapsed into the slumber of ce turies from which it was so ruaely awakened forty years ago# » m r-ii- i&amp;E.t, Hi A fl |l a©istan is one of the remoteat of the provinces of Iran an! gets correapomUngly little attention froM the got©‘ iment* Its only importance in the eyes of i'eraian officialdom is aa an outpost threatened fcy British and/or Afghan aggression* Bosslhly for this reason, and possibly out of sheer inertia and financial inability nothing is being done for the improvement of the country. It is clear that at one time Seiatan was a populous ana prosperous tract, when it was the birth place of the celebrated Bustum and the cradle of the dynasty which cam© to rule over Persia* It is &amp; land with abundant water lying between the dessicated wastes of Afghanistan and Iran, and could again be rendered fertile by modern irrigation and drainage* Although there are frequently disastrous floods in the spring, there is nearly always a water shortage in the autumn. The land is waterlogged and treeless, and the present methods of irrigation are aboriginal. The uelatan peasant is deterred from making improvements by insecurity of tenure and by the fact that any pr .fit which he may wring from the soil goes forthwith into the pockets of Government* His standard of living is as low as, or even lower than, that of the Indian peasant* ihere is no prospect of improvement for many years to come as her ambitious programme of railway construction_U£aU and .■e l a ton » ADKlo-Irttnian ESl&amp;ilSRS. tan • -9- constraction leaves Iran with no ^oney to spend on irrigating ana draining fnr-off ieistan. •furthert remoteness end paucity of com lunica tiona would prohibit the profitable exportation of an agricultural surplus. Finally, any large irrigation scheme would have to be carried out jointly by Iran and Afghanistan and would involve negotiations far more intricate and prolonged than any we have yet seen in ^urope. The first British officer was sgj&amp;t to Selstan to counteract Russian ititrigues, promote Anglo-Iranian friendship, ana to encourage Ihdo-Iranian trace, ana it will be simplest now to consider the present work for a Vice-Consul under these three heads, anu finally to review the various offices performed by the consulate in the past in the light of trie necessities of today* There is now no tussian Consulate, hospital or bank in Jeistan; nor is there any Hussian trad© or intrigue. All that Zabul sees of the outside world is the British Consulate. The Huasian bogey has oeen laid, and, as there appears no immediate prospect of its resurrection, that part of our worie is finished. In pre-war Persia there was some point in winning the good opinions of the hereditary Governors of Be is tan and the iCainat, who were under very light control from Tehran. Nowadays, under a rigid autocracy, the local Governor retains not a vestige of initiative or independence. In even the most trivial matters he must refer to Tehran, and his personal friendship for oritain.- 10 - if he dared to bestow it, would be valueless* British influence can only be effectively asserted at Tehran* Modern Iran in the days of her childhood was beset by the wicked uncles of Jin gland and Hussia# and the treatment she received at their hands has Made her violently anti-foreign in these# the days of her adolescence* Part I of this minute should have made it clear that the love of Iran for her neighbours has always varied inversely with their power* How that the nusainns are no longer on the scene In ueiat&amp;n the animosity of the Iranians is concentrated on the British* ^hat amounts to a boycott of the cons late is enforced* ir.luch Uara&amp;rs and local notables are now no longer allowed to visit the Vice-Consul# whose influence with them is nil* In any case the course of the operations which Iran has conducted against the Baluchis of the uarhad in the last few years must have convinced them that there is no help to be looked for fro© Britain* Members of the consulate are watched and their movements reported* The consulate hospital, it is true, still cerates; but it will only do so as long as the present aub-Mssist&amp;nt surgeon, who obtained a licence to practice before the days of the boycott, remains. When he goes (and he has been many years there now) the consulate hospital in fabul, as elsewhere, will have to close its doors to the local people* The Iranians do not know what our object is in maintaining an expensive consulate where there is no visible justification for one, but they are sure it is nefarious. * The Vice-Consul, almost incarceratedfefter duties the pagt» igla.Wn ,ag a~Ms£_ia **&amp;£ • &lt;11111 Hr imi » XI* iDcaroerated in his house and cut off from all contact with the people, can do nothing to promote Anglo- Iranian friendship* In fact his very presence imperils It* In days past even Afghan trade from Herat to Quetta used to pass through 36istan to avoid the duties levied in Kandahar, and the Consul used to do his best to facilitate it* Large numbers of Habers from the ^hoh used to visit dels tan in the winter to collect a; safoetida* Xhey now no longer come into Iran* Lastly, the Consul used to endeavour to stir the Persians into resisting the passage of arma-smugglers from ^rsia to Afghanistan* Hone of these duties at present exist to occupy the Vice-Consul* In the past the Consul used to collect information from as far afield as Herat, Kandahar and the uarhad, for which Lebul was the metropolis* This is now impossible as the Afghan frontier is to all Intents and purposes closed and the darhad centres round gahidan. In fact the Vice-Consul has to rely on his clerk and the British Indian traders for information about jelstan, ana from his own Knowledge can add nothing to, nor subtract anything from, what they say* Intelligence from the Sarhad is collected in ^ahidan. The Vice-Consul no longer, therefore, performs useful service in any of the ways mentioned above* finally, I venture to think that the mechanisation of modern armies has materially lessened the importance of ueiat&amp;n as a base for war* Large grain supplies are no longer so essentialessential for an army as supplies of petrol* Commercially Bel atan is a complete backwater* there is no legitimate trade across the Afghan frontier* mere is not a single aeronaut, Indian or Iranian, in Znbul who imports merchandise from abroad* Tea, apices and paper, the chief articles of Indian origin, are all ordered from Zehldan, to &amp; total value of some Uals 55,000 per annum only* The estimated annual value ?f the articles smuggled fron Afghanistan and Baluchistan is Hials 100,000, but I am informed that British subjects uo not engage in this trade* \part from a little cloth and haberdashery there is no market for British goods in Selstan, the few needs of the Beistani peasant being all supplied from Iranian sources* Exports from selotan go only to other parts of Iran and are of the estimated value of three to four million Hials per annum* only one British Indian trader exports wool, ghl and hides from uelstan (to Bashed), and that to an annual value of only Kials 60,000. Appendix I gives statistics for mdo~Tr&amp;nlan trade since 1904, but it should be rsmefebered that since 1918 this trade has not gone through Beistan at all but through z&amp;hidan* There are now only some eighty British Indian Ejects subjects in ieiatan including women and children, and of these a certain number are l&amp;rberis who are not traders, and keep their British nationality only to avoid conscription. (Bee Appendix II) The traders who remain are maicing no profits and Trade in The trade from Inula to Persia passes it by and onlyonly gfciy because they cannot at present get what rsoney they have aavea out of the country# It is clear that there is no justification for the retention of e whole time Vice-Uonsul in £&amp;bul for the protection of trade , for the promotion of Anglo-Iranian good relauionsi f or to counter lussian intrigue# agJLiLL— ^amtULlangi. aP-4. t,iK kites'reeomeiia&amp;a to Goyfe^DiufeDt, . v/ithout adventuring too fnr into the realm of prophesy I wish to suggest some possible future developments which would affect the position of the British Vice-Consulate in Sabul. In spite of widespread discontent among the trading classes f the robust health of the present iihah and the faith of the younger generation in the new regime seems to indicate that there is no sudden change of economic policy to be expected# Avan if such a change were to tmee place, the position of British Indian traders in ^bul would not b© much affected unless steps were taken to improve the material position of deist&amp;n and increase the purchasing power of the deistanis. It is likely that a way may soon be found to enable the Indians to export their capital from Iran at a not too ruinous rate. The most likely development appears, therefore, to be a decrease to-14- %o vanishing point of the British Indian population and trade in aeistan* Although it is a tract capable of great Agriculture* development, any comprehensive improvement in the irrigation of Seistan presents great ditVicuities* 'Xhe Bel mam is an Afghan river and bears the water from the snow and rain which rails on Afghan soil, but the H&amp;oMaboft award divided the water and the land of aeist&amp;n between Afghanistan and Persia* Sir Henry MaoHahoa aid not expect this award to be permanent, m&lt;i it presents great obstacles to the utilisation of the lieimauu water on modern lines* a scheme is necessary to hold up the spring floods of the HelgSnd, store them, and release the water in the summer and autumn for irrigation* Xhe B&amp;mina should also be drained* The first part of thia scheme would entail the construction of a dam which must lie either wholly or partly in Afghan territory* Xhe second part would involve drainage into the Oaud-l-Zirreh which lies within Afghanistan* With the present Perso-Afghan frontier it is extremely unlikely that any such scheme could be agreed upon or financed for many years to come. The agricultural condition of tieis&amp;an will, therefore, probably remain unchanged and no development of the country is to be expected to turn it into a valuable market for British trade. The distance to the sea ana lack of Minerals * communications renders it unlikely that oil or other minerals (if present) will be exploited in Beistan in the near future* AlthoughAlfcjiough the \uasiana at present appear unin teres ted in Iran, it is always possible that Soviet policy iaay turn bacK into its pre-war channel of expansion towards the south* It is possible that Iran my com© undex* Hussian influence or control and seist&amp;n again be made a centre for intrigue against India* In such a case the Vice-Consul could at least provide the Government of India with authoritative information and, if the worst caae to the worst, might organise local resistance* as, at present, the Vice-Consul at bul is without any woric whatsoever, and as there appears no prospect of his being called upon to perf rm any useful service in the next few years, X recommend that the post be held in abeyance* It is , however, possible that, in certain circumstances, the post may again become necessary, and in view of the Known hostile attitude of the Iranians to Foreign consulates, it seems pruaent that we should be in a position to re-establish the Vice-Consulate without having to obtain their sanction. How this can best be &amp;*&amp;£ ensured ie beyond the scope of this note*. ,V hJJ^l'uZX III * A Do^e on Birjand. As the Birjand Vice-Consulate is in the charge of the Vice-Consul, v* bul, I append a very Brief note on conditions there* In general the sanie arguments and considerations which apply to Zahul apply to Birjand also. The Vice-Consulate was established in 1911 solely because the Uasaian Vice-Consul in aeistan chose to spend the summer months at .sirjand and practically made it his headquarters* .Cater the iiirjand Vice-Consulate was a useful summer station for our Consul in ;^istan* It was also, as the capital of the Kainat and the seat of the local Gove nor, the most important halting place on the trade route between Sahid&amp;n and - eshed• Nowadays the trade is carried in lorries which merely pull in for the night at Birjand* It is merely a large and squalid village which is the headquarters of a poor agricultural district where the only Industry is carpet weaving* As to the present Importance of British Indian trade in Birjand, the figures given in Appendix II (b) apeak for themselves* K</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100031201044.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur C600/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031201044.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur C600/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'A NOTE ON THE IMPORTANCE OF SEISTAN TO INDIA.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-06T22:04:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the first folio with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 19; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A paper by Captain Maurice Patrick O'Connor Tandy detailing the British connection with Seistan.The paper is divided into three sections:Part I: 'A brief review of British Consular activity in Seistan.';Part II: 'The present position in Seistan.';Part III: 'Possible future changes in Seistan and the policy recommended to Government.'Three appendices (folios 17-19) give the value of overland trade between India and Iran, 1900-1938; the numbers of British subjects in (a) Seistan, and (b) Birjand, 1934-39; and 'A brief note on Birjand'.The paper is accompanied by a covering letter (folio 1) from Tandy in his capacity as HM Vice-Consul, Birjand, dated 18 September 1939.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Seistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031201044.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>