<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001bc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:52:38.161Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">' 4f- m U'JU Jf il Kt, Vn -v (T \ Visit by Rahran General Ferchants Association The Committee was composed of Messrs. Ashraf, Hussein Yateem, Rashid bin Abdur Rahman bin Abdul Wahab Zayani and Affimiwallah. Mr. Ashraf began by saying that a General Mer chants’ Association had been formed with the intention of taking care of the interests of all merchants in Bahrain who cared to join and that it had been recog nised by the Bahrain Government. They went on to dis cuss certain matters Electricity They said they had very grave discontentment amongst all classes with regard to the heavy charges made by the Bahrain Electric Department. They said the charge per unit ought not to exceed 4 as instead of 7 as as it is now and they quoted the case of Mr. Hussein Yateem who used to take electricity from the State and was charged from 1 anna to 6 as. per unit. He thereupon installed his own electric plant and is able to produce electricity at one-fourth of an anna per unit. Customs They also brought up the question of the Customs Several merchants, they said, had imported articles of Italian and other alien manufacture from merchants in India. These goods were being held up in the Customs at Bahrain forwent of authority to import. They said that as these goods had been admitted into India by the Indian Government there could surely be no question as to their ownership still lying with the Italians, etc. Had it been so the Controller of Enemy Property would undoubtedly have seized them long ago. The fact of the goods having been allowed*to enter India and then be exported again shows that there c an be no question of their being enemy property. They also requested toknow as to who would have to pay Khanchieh and other charges. They fa ther requested that if any regulations on this subject hadb een issued they might be informed of them to enable merchants to decidevhether to import goods of enemy origin from Tndia or not. 10/12/40 y</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001bc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/365</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001bc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/365</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/17 Bahrain General Merchants' Association'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-03T09:44:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 3; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The document is a report on the visit by representatives of the Bahrain General Merchants Association to the Political Agency at Bahrain. The newly formed association voiced its discontent for the electricity costs imposed by the Bahrain Electric Department and requested clarity on the import of Italian goods to India when the two countries were at war.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain General Merchants Association</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Electric Department</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001bc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>