<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000b4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:01:56.716Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Tel. No.: Whitehall 1234 ua Your Reference ivXT • 2907/W Treasury Reference Dear Harrison, In reply to your letter of 2nd Ja nuary f 192i5 r I confirm our oral ^ t eement that the Government of India rulej relating to travelling allowances and use of Government vehicles may continue to be applied to officers serving in the Persian Gulf administration during the current financial year. Yours sincerely.FSL XB'04( 108/47) fry-**- A 1 UNDEXED 16th December, 1947- Hoar Hallows, fhanfc you for your fette r 2295/47 of the 5th } j K j / Deceiaber about travelling rules^ in the Persian Gulf. We agree that it would be much simpler to sticlf to the old. rules until 1st April next and make the general change-over then. There will, of course, be a large number of problems connected with the change-over, and it is for that reason that we have asked for and just obtained sanction for a Branch B Foreign Service Officer to proceed to Bahrain to act as Chief Clerk, and you will have seen a copy of Gardener f s letter to Pitblado. I am sending a copy of this letter toBeighton at the Treasury, whose sanction you will presumably need to carry on on the Indian rules until 1st ^pril. Yours sincerely. // if) n R. I. Hallows, Esq., n.B.E., Commonwealth Relations Office.DRAFT LETTER, J.D.K. Beighton, Treasury. L- • (rf' 29th December, 1947« -f JAN Would you please refer to letter No. XFO.4(108/47) of the 16th December from Fisher of the Foreign Office about the rules to be applied during-the current finanoial year ^orthe drawal of travelling allowance^ and the use of Government cars by officers serving in 7 the Persian Gulf Administration. Bier the- reasono sot out- in ray letter No.Ext.-2293/4-7-to Fisher, wm consider, and.the Foreign Office agree, -that it-is r3aa t t-q'KI a +&gt;ip+ ^1^ n ■ in n r n 1 ^ | finanpiful yoar-^ both travelling allowance and the use of Government oaro ohould be ccvered b,y GuveiimiBlil of India i ul^s.2. We should be glad if you tiould let us have your early approval to-^thc- suggestiorr to /enablea— r EXT O \ £r t} D.O. No. 2183-30/20 b 0 */ S Y o PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 17th October, 1947. v -.jk- ( 3 ) I find that up to date no instructions have yet been issued regarding the drawal of travelling allowances by Grade A officers in the Gulf and that such officers have been continuing to draw their Travelling allowance under the old Indian rules. I have studied Foreign Service Regulation No. 7 on the subject and think there will be little difficulty in enforcing the rules in the Gulf though there are a few minor points which will require clearing up. In some respects they appear to be more liberal and in others less liberal than the Indian rules. 2. A good deal of trouble and difficulty will however be involved if officers have to refund what they have already drawn on account of travelling allowance under the Indian rules and submit fresh bills in accordance with the Foreign Office rules, and it is only reasonable that they should be given the prior notice of the change in procedure. I would suggest therefore that officers might be allowed to draw travelling allowance under the Indian rules until the 1st April which will give them ample time to make themselves acquainted v/ith the Foreign Office procedure and to raise any points about which they may be doubtful or which may require special consideration in view of the peculiar j circumstances prevailing in the Gulf. I make this suggestion in I respect of journeys on tour only. Journeys on transfer or leave if any during the period indicated should be governed by the Foreign Office rules, or by any special terms granted to the officers concerned. I doubt if the adoption of the Foreign Office rules for journeys on tour would result in any appreciable saving in expedditure over the period concerned especially as there are at present only four Grade A officers serving in the Gulf and it is not known when more are likely to arrive. 3. Personnel other than Grade A officers serving under this I Residency have been promised their previous conditions of service and will therefore continue to draw travelling allowance in accordance with the Indian rules. 4. There is one small point arising from Foreign Service Regulation No. 7 which I should like clarified. It would appear I from paragraph 3(a) that I have to obtain the sanction of His Majesty 1 s Government before,going on tour even within my own jurisdiction. Do the Commonwealth Relations Office wish me to do this while they remain in charge ? In the past the Political R.I. Hallows, Esquire, M.3.E., / Resident has always kept ... Commonwealth Relations Office, LONDON.2 Resident has always kept His Majesty’s Government informed of his absences from headquarters but it has not been the practice for him to obtain any sanction before proceeding on tour except outside his jurisdiction. k/*&lt;DRAFT J. M. F i sher, S sq,, Foreign Office, 8, Carlton House Terrace, London, S, W. 1&lt;, ^mrn: 0 U' (ss&gt;L- e~U l 0 - &gt;; Dear Fisher, Would you please refer to your letter No.XA* 0512(5/47) of the 27th September, about the rules to be applied for the use of cars at the Persian Culf Residency and subordinate posts? It seems to us to be desirable that this question should be considered along with the question of the rules to be followed for the drawal of travelling allowance by Branch , A , officers appointed to the - - — _ Persian Gulf and to Muscat. 2. In regard to travelling allowance, I enclos^eSfov your information a copy of a letter ^4 I t c^^ 183-3Q/20 of the 17th October from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in which he suggests that^ for the current financial year, officers, both Foreign Service and on contract, should continue to draw travelling allowance in /accordance_ - accordance with Govemnien'b of India nixes for journeys &lt; * i - ' performed on tour* You will see that the Political Resident reports that some officers have already drawn travelling allowance under these rules and that he points out that if the Government of India rules remain in force for the current financial year, the trouble of officers having to refund amounts drawn and of having to submit fresh bills in accordance with Foreign Office Regulations, would be avoided, /I- l/tf Uj % . . - 3* We hav^ e to the conclusion, that tDe political Resident* s suggestion should be approved on practical grounds. The Auditor General of India is to be responsible for the audit of the 1947-^ accounts of the Persian Gulf Administration and we think it clearly desirable that substantial disbursements should, as far as possible, be 4 »■ _ made in accordance with rules with which he and his subordinates are familiar. The cost of tne Persian Gulf administration is to be borne entirely by H.M.G. from 1st April this year, but from that date up to the 14th August, when the Government of India continued to administer the Gulf on behalf of H*M*G. all disbursements /of3. of Government money have been made under Government of India rules. The complications of introducing now an entirely fresh set of rules would be to all also concerned on the spot and probably jcw eeial^ to the Auditor General. It would seem to involve a risk of confusion and much extra work with little or no attendant advantage. ^ In addition to this the following points deserve mention ; — (a;) As pointed out by the Political Resident, personnel of the Persian Gulf Administration, other than Grade ’A* officers, will continue to draw U travelling allowance under the old rules, andrwould VGU| U appear^ desirable to avoid the complication of having two sets of travelling allowance rules in force in the Gulf ^ ^ SOAsmt IZlw A (b) It is perhaps not altogether certain that the Foreign Office rules are in all respects suitable for application to the Gulf where special circumstances prevail. This question in our view /requiresh requires examination in detail together with the question of subsistence allowance provided for in Section 10 of the rules. This and similar work would normally be done by the Resident* s Secretary, but as you know we have not so far been able to £U*- provide^ officerjfc for this post,though we hope to do so very shortly. ST* We are not in a position to say which of the rules would involve the greater expenditure^as our copies of the Indian Rules do not contain up-to-date amendments, but we are inclined to think that, if anything, the officers concerned would derive more benefit from the Indian Rules* I should mention that the budget estimate^an tte travelling allowance head (which has been approved by the Treasury) was based on anticipated expenditure under Indian rules. So far as rules for the use of cars are concerned, 1 these our view is that ^ntil the 1st April next yeai too should be the G-ovemment of India rules] for the reasons given in paragraph 3 above. Ye should like to reach a decision on these questions „ith the minimum of delay and should therefore he grateful /if, ft .1. HtZiKf'v 3 &lt;g&gt; 5. if you would inform us as early as possible whether you concur with our views. It is of course understood that from April 1st next year when the Foreign Office take over the control of Gulf affairs and the Government of India are no longer concerned with Gulf accounts, the old rules will cease to apply. I am sending of this letter together with its enclosure, and a % of your^r^ter of the 2?th September, to Beighton at # £he Treasury.DR A F T Sir Rupert Hay, K«G.I # S,, C.S.I Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bahrein. • f ^61 030 5 k 5 DEC 1947 J&amp;utf T A I must apologise for the delay in replying to your letter No.2183-30/20 of the 17th October about travelling allowance. The matter has been under consideration by the various departments concerned and I hope to let you have a decision shortly. As regards paragraph A of your letter, it will be sufficient for you to keep us informed of your absence from Bahrein and to apply for sanction c»Jr only in the case of joume^Sfe 4jfeide your jurisdiction. This question should however be raised again with the Foreign Office when they take over next year. J. ft'i* h#M CTA) S&lt;© (5lv.'c i^oJl AaaLLaaliaa at ersian RecentV twn inatancca riaRre occurred wtiich uave matlc it neoesiiary tu cjnsidor ivhetiier certain Foreign Office tiegulatiuns ^^hottid be applied to the eraian Oulf as soon as jjosaible said not t the time of the ) oreign Office asamaption of responsibility ^rt prii. The Regulations in ijestion are t .ose governing the iuaintennnoe of notor-cara and tlue dr: wing of travelling allovmncei Aa ministerial st ft in tne leraian Gulf poata ia on deputa tion fro. tl» Goverrsaont of India nnl the Gwerrsaont of I akin tan, it ia dear that tiiey will tave to be paid their alla^?anoes ia accorhaace witii too old Government &gt;f India Hales, or according to any nev; ones node V ti»e Govemaent of India or lakistan* 1th the superior officera tao case is complicated by soioe of the officers being on contract to the C*R*0. (jabso }ue::tV to ttie Foreign off ice j vK lie others are or will be career Foreign Servants* Colonel 1 £y, in uis letter at flog has suggested that officers might be allowsd to draw travelling allcwmaoes im&lt;ier the Indian Rules until 1st April ne t, tiiua giving ticae botn for aiy anamalies in the Foreign service egifLations to be noticed and tiL tiie officers thttoselves to stuciy the new Keg il at ions, T e KR, stresses that tias proceckire armould ondy e$v3y to journeys on tou anil taat for U*h* leave, first appointjoent and term nation of service, the loroign Office ’ ilea aliould a^vply. T e arguments ic support of this contention way be suomariaed as I'oll jwa: (aj ,uiditi^» The ccountant-Ce: 1 ci*al, Central Revenues, is res^jonsible for auditing the ] eraian Gulf accounts and if moreign Service iiegulctlons are introduced now, he will iimre to be fumisiied wita copies of tiie^a aid given a: agreed date from which the accounts of certain officers suould bo dealt i with according to the !•:&gt;« ;ulea. ,*.3 it is doubtful wiietiier this could be arranged by tioe end of trie year, the advantages of introducing a new systeu for a few montiis only see ratuer uncertain* (b) Tiie clerical staff In tiw diiferent Agencies and in tlie Indian Treasuries in the Gulf would also lusve to accustom /tiianselveaythesaaelvea to now regulations, and at tho saiae tiioa maintain a d ial aooainting t$y ateia* (g) Tiio J 3 reign office will preaumably betv/eon now and 1st .*j&gt;ril # itave to review tno entire 3y ;teia of allcfcvanoes posable t&gt; s iperior officers in the 0 tlf # e.g* t*ie Golf posts will liave to be included in the loreign office hist of uniiealti^ stations and peraission granted for paid rtsoesain**; for e t proveu i^rloda and at approved stations, etc, ti* i oreign iervioc w©g action ho.7 - 'travelling Uovruncea is siiaple in application and need only be onsldered in the present connection in relation to purneys on tour* Jnder Secticm 3 the pnyje-nt of tue fare of tae officer, and, in curtain casoo, his aunmnt, is envisaged and under ection 10 a subsistence allowance is granted to ucet toe oxpenzoa of f &gt;od and aleex)lng acoora-iodation when not included in the fare* this subsistence allowance is 'at .he rate in force'* at tne time for trio country )V countries in rjuostion* The GovsraesBt of India Jiules ice ratiier more complicated, making as they do provision for railway journeys wnicn will not be normally obtain in the Gulf. he Regulations applicable arei- &amp; convey arvoe or itorse allowaaco (when specially a auctioned ty tire Government of indi&amp;&gt;, a milee^ie aJLl&lt;&gt;.yance, a daily allowance or tlss actual cost of travelling, ifithout going into details the principle benind than, la tnat an officer receiver either double tiie cost of tiie fare for kuoaelf attd party* ^&gt;r else tin allowance %j cover incidentals '■.■hen transport is provided by tue .State. As far rs tl&amp; , hintcnauco of -aotor^cara la concerned, the Governnent of India principle is that an individual officer rec ives a motor-car on cliarge, peys its running expenses and is reimbursed for tiie Journeys for which he uses it on the public service. The foreign office systeiii is to ma*e m allocation of motor vehicles to the lead of &amp; Mission, who then assigns tiiam to his subordinates mu pey at a fixed milsegs mte for using the vehicle for pleasure, but its .jetrol, mainien^iic®, etc. is provi.ied free. (The oreign off ice Oar Gods is rt flag G and tlio Government of India Rules at flag i»). A possible&amp; A possible solution ould be in the case of:- (aj ravellini. to wiy the l oroign Serrlce Regulations tor journeys outside tne dulf in the case of officers serving on contract and to ^aaint&amp;in t jq Government of India Hales for officers touring witiiin the Gulf area* iid&amp;itt&amp;dly an anaaaly **^rill &gt;ccur in the eases of career Foreign Gervanta, but if they t&gt; draw ttislr ioeal a v nces of pey s’roia tim Indian reaauriei will be better for tiieir clairas for travelling allowances to ue suhaitted in accordance with Government of India Rules, and thf different en^itleraents (l«e» Gjvemaont of India as against - oreign Gervioe Rules; to be adju sted at the prerjentation of the last ndia office ouiget* as tar as I o n discover, the Foreign Office fix aubaiitenoe rates in accordance with local conditions, an tiwy will ivwe t* decide t e:^ rates eit cr on the evidence supplied I$r t is office (^.e, on tiie basis of all Avancoa already s actioned by tue Govermsent of India;, or by desp^ttching an officer ti tho Gulf to inspect and to report. A solution of this point is of sjroe lioediftte baportanoG, as all officers, career or contract, will presumably be required t&gt; do same tours between now ami April 1st, 1^4G. (b; iioto^-cars. Tbs ondian Gar wexie lai^^t be maintained until - pril 1st, I^AG, wkien .. rcsumbly all vehicles in the Gulf will canoe under the F oreign ffice Gar l ool in matters of maintenance anl supply. Tii© A Oliticul Resident refers to tiie } oreign Gcrvioe emulation ho.7, paragra^ja iCaj, laying down that iie just obtain tlie aut/ioriV of t'oe Secretary of dtate bel'oro going on tour. I thin.&lt; tills alter need only be taken up wit i tae ioi'eign Office U it Is decided to apply Foreign Service Regulations ea bloc during the current year. * (Sgd.}A.;i. Rood, ’flu? question is to scroc extent connected with tho general question of payment of off lexers and auditing arrangc^osnts, ^^ers regarding miioh are nov? with A.G. /FromFrau tike adainiatrative point of view x tlila^ the sL iplest solution would be (1) In regard to cars, t^ laaintain the (iovermaent of India Code until next April, when it should be replaced by the Forei^i office dor Code* (2) In rsgarl tj travellinti allowances generally to ecc^gL the proposals in iir .. u letter ox* 17 tii Cctobei* Tikis arrr^ngenont would be tlia most convenient ttam tiie -practical point of view though on the otiier iiand the Foreign office miglit see soiae dlifioulty in agreeing that Indian rules should be applied to Foreign hervr^its* On tiie financial si-.ie it seams liJsely to jaork out to tiio advraitage of tiae politicfil officers concerned and tise reaaury might qpmrry this, but it would be pointed out to them that it is only the continuance of previous practice and in aq/ case tue only practical arrangeroent. It will « necessary to obtain the agreement of tike Treasury and Foreign Uffice to iir -iiy*s proposals in his letter of 17th October. If you agree, s/e could write enclosing a oojjy and malting tiie beat Ciise on t.je lines above, .ilternativaly it lalght be quic r jest t call a m ©ting, I unring previously clroulated copies of 3ir R* letter. 1 or ary conic nets, please. F..*..K. ilarrison, Vll. I ai inclined to agree with .ir. .iarrison on both ^xiinta, but t ie Trcosuiy r;iay be sticky about Travelling Allowanoes. 1 had a similar question in regard to .ord Mountbatten's a^ecial staff in India f nd after some fruitioss iiscuasion, tne reasury deci. ed tfiat their won rules should apply* The argisoento put for^vard ty .Jr. nllov/s (wuioti did not exist in tiie case of t &amp; s &lt; 5 CiaI staff) it fly, iOwever, imluce t.ten to ^gree. xnciiientally the gravelling Ail /vrnnee ales in tim b. d*il. uave long been out of date exoeet /fir</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000b4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3618</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000b4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3618</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/45(6) 'Travelling allowances for officers in Gulf posts'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-22T14:29:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (16 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 18; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the application of Foreign Service Regulation to the Persian Gulf, regarding travelling allowances and use of Government vehicles.The file is composed of correspondence between the India Office, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, and the Treasury.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000b4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>