<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:03:45.567Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">j \H0^ EC (313/2/40) A JOO 3 HJ P.Z. 2132 i94g j •C ; miTISH LEGATIOli^ TEHRAN. 16th February 1940. c - Dear Department, Please refer to Hay 1 s secret letter No. D. 4863-N/39 of the 29th December to Alban at Kabul. 2. We have confirmed from the American Consul in Tehran that there is no truth whatever in the report that American citizens in Iran had been warned that the American Consulate would not be responsible for their safety in Iran after the end of November 1939. 3. We are sending a copy of this letter to His Majesty's Minister at Kabul. Yours ever, CHANCERY. External Affairs Department, Government of India, New Delhi.r Copy to Inuic. i i i ce. Tehran Persia*- u-ulf is • ,1) « X • C • ! l\ja t Avvi ttAwk bii/vl fl 1 , ,1 % To r ara&lt; p.z. . iuthii-P 6th Deceesbor 1940 j ,1 •' ' ■ ^ rxce ( 3 1 xcar, I have Hiaie contact with the United Hates Consul in ara 0 hi f Mr.? acy f #io informs me that there is no truth in the rumour that American subjects have been advised by their jrespective Consuls to leave Iran. It is a fact t however, that certain Americans in the employ of the Bahrain Petroleum Go. Ltd. voluntarily left for »merica after the outbreak of war; this I understand may have been due to their realisation of&gt;6ha vulnerability of a British controlled Company to attack by ^stile naval and air forces. It will be recalled that the attitude of the Italian Government was at that time uncertain. Mr* lacy further informed me that a )r. Lolaer, an American Ornithologist now in India, is shortly leaving for Iran. He was in Afghanistan until lately, on his w birds nesting expeditions, and from what he saw of Trans Oxus territory was of the opinion that the unpopular administration and control by the Afghan Government over the Turcoman needed but little extraneous impetus to cause revolt. The Consul observed that the number of Genian nationals in Iran and Afghanistan was remarkable and that business, in the usual sense, could not account for their presence or even cover their expense accounts. He was somewhat perturbed by the existing unsatisfactory trade situation in Afghanistan especially the way in which busi ness was now being conducted by officials in the Goveramer each in his own department and to his own financial advan tage, in the Qonsul T s words,developing into a regular scrable with Mevii ta^e the hindermosV and did not augur well for the future* i. F. Deputy Home T )ep tor io nge Bureau, . dia, ’ ew Delhi. * C.I.S. *•</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/334</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/334</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 831/40 'Rumour (unfounded) that Americans had been warned to leave Persia before the end of November 1939'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-29T22:06:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 5; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials relating to a rumour that American citizens had been advised by their Consuls to leave Iran, as the American Consulate would not be responsible for their safety after November 1939.The main correspondents are the Central Intelligence Officer, Karachi, the Government of India External Affairs Department, and the British Legation, Tehran.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Consulate</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Central Intelligence Officer, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Americans</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Embassies and consulates</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002d1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>