<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00034e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T17:32:51.004Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&lt;] COXFIDEXTIAL. Xo. C/138-7/2, The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Residency Agent, r t and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). 1 &lt; vr The Agency, BAHRAIX, Persian Gulf. 7 Dated ..the . 13th. February 1 3 r i JL Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain letter No.C/5-7/2 dated the 8 th January 1937. Description of Enclosure. Xame and Date. Subject. Agreement between His Majesty 1 s Government and the Ruler of Kalba Shaikh Satid bin Hamad bin Majid al ^asimi conclude^ on the 28th August 1936 (9th J/Thani 1355). AIR FACILITIES AT KALBA,4-Sj£U J-** ^ {J_y jh *t ^ 4iA&gt;«%J 1 4 -La ^ * c*J o^=&gt;* i&gt;* J*&gt;?“l ^ — ° -Up a-Jlp L Cui ^^Jl pJ-Li m v5 ^L) ^ ~~&gt;j l*J l I ; -«*^ j ^ ui^ Aji^rr^'ii j^j^i j * JL^L* t jj(? ^ L ^ ' i ^ ;&gt; “ 1 ^y* ^ ^ ^ ^ C^I J LJsJ I iirv.-**^ JjJL*£J U ( J^ V U U ^ J J it ^ i«* ^ • &gt; ‘i-*'’ (J l * i -•• aJ j jJ l j y*^ U y ^-iJJ 4 * r* )i—J J-LjJ I (Jy^-J iia^^JI V J L&gt;^ ^4 % -^Ju&gt;-i J&gt;-J J ^.A Ju»-l l JLA • JJ L&gt;- (j I J vJ ^ jf° iS ^ ^ £*** ^ • ^JJi ^&gt;p i^UJI — A ‘c^l* — (T) _ n • A^ l y V i — «--wl l A.m * &gt; »»J I ^jjJ I t ^J \ I J ^t V — C w ) A. —-J --1 jJ I jy 1 *(jj^ w^f-v cr 1 ^ “ 1 * *J U-* 5 ’ (J^ ^!*o} J {j +Y iji — I I L^JlaIjI \j 1 2^04 work is to be borne by the Company and the Shaikh will in no way be held liable for the payment of any compensation to the Com pany. 4. Labourers required for work on the landing base should be natives of Dubai. 5. Should any employee of the Company commit any crime, the Shaikh should lodge a complaint against him with the Political Resident who will investigate the case and take what action may be desirable. 6. Should any Dubai subject be accused of any offence in respect of the Commercial Landing Base at Dubai he shall not be pu nished until the offence has been proved to the joint satisfaction of the Shaikh of Dubai and the Political Agent. 7. No employee (foreign) of the Company shall enter the town at night. Should any person infringe this rule by entering the town at night and, God forbid, suffer in jury or loss, then the Shaikh will not be held responsible. 8. Guards and watchmen of the landing base will be appointed by the Shaikh. 9. (a) No women or sailors should be per mitted to seek refuge in the landing base. (b) The Shaikh* s internal affairs shall not be interfered with in any manner what soever. 10. A charge of Rs. 5/- will be paid to the Shaikh for every landing by an aircraft, 11. If any injury is done to the craft oi its people by any outside enemy then the Government/-r ‘ — r— -3- &gt; I &lt; '** ^ ^ -ifrL-J I J ^a I J. J»- ^ I j t M. 1 T jl iiliOl 4 ^^ * 4^ r‘«J 1 &lt;ULi&lt;C JU.^u.*. 1 4-^uh*JI t.^?* lil — IT Jutx&gt;-^ ^ r^ juvi &gt;^L^iji£, • C« J U-^J 1 J^. J ^r**- JJUll t juft JwU jj Si 1 i • 1 ITA _;;V&gt;?- VT i&gt; I^Uel Jjly- Government, when necessity arises, should assist the Shaikh by all means. 12. Natives of Dubai should be employ ed by the Company in the landing base for all such work as they are capable of doing 13# Should liquor be necessary for the special use of the landing base the Com pany shall on no account permit the sale of such liquor to the natives of and per • sons residing in the Country and Town of Dubai. 14. This Agreement will be for a period of five years with effect fi*om the 22nd July 1938•I, Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Has al Khaimah, have accepted and agreed to the conditions mentioned below for the British 'Government Firstly I have accepted that the iron boat in which petrol is stored for aeroplanes to remain in the creek in place of the jolly boat for a period of one year and should the Go vernment wish to place more petrol in the said boat I shall have no objection, and I have posted guards for the said boat. And during the period of the year we shall exchange opinions with the Hon’ble the Political Resident on the above mentioned matters. Secondly. I have undertaken safety for the aeroplane when it arrives at Has al Khaimah to take in petrol from the said boat as was done in the past. Thirdly. I have accepted responsibility for the safety of the Residency Agent, Khan Bahadur Isa, and his dependents: they will enjoy complete safety and security at Has al Khaimah and its dependencies in the desert; and I shall not make any intrigue against him when he is in Has al Khaimah or at Sharjah or elsewhere. Should anything (of this nature) emanate from me or from any of my dependents to the said Residency Agent at Has al Khaimah and its suburbs, may God forbid, I shall be responsible to the British Government. Signed and sealed. Dated 17th Muharram 1349 - 15th June 1930. Sultan bin Salim, Ruler of Ras al Khaimah. Witnesses: A witness hereunto, signed and sealed, Sultan bin Saqar, in his own handwriting. A witness hereunto, signed and sealed, Muhammad bin Salim. V/itnesses hereunto, signed and sealed. Abdullah bin Muhammad bin Khadim and Salim bin Khamis al-Holi.Agreement made on between the nnglo- Iraniaix oil Company iiimited, hereinafter referred to as the Company and his excellency ^heixvh bultan bin ^aqar, Kuier of oharjah 9 referrea to nereinaiter as tne eessor* Ihe Lessor agrees to lease to tne company a plot 01 land situated on the ^harjah Lagoon, nearby •duoail', measuring 25Q'x‘]5Q' 9 including the pxesent storage. Tne site in question is on tne Louth of tne present store. ihis Agreement will be for a period of Teh Years only. The Lessor agrees to allow the company to erect on tne aforesaid plot of land such buildings as they require to perform their services as suppliers of Oil rrouucts in charjah ana for delivery to aircraft. % Tne company agrees to pay to tne nessor for tne plot of land above mentioned a montnly rent of ns.122/b/4. The rent of tne present oil storage f iwneiy ns.200/- per montn, shalr remain tae same during tne currency ox tnis agreement auU will oe paiu to the sheikh as usual. Total rents payaole being tnerefore hs. 533/5/4 per month. The nessor unaertanes to guax d tne x/epot buildings during tne term of this -agreement. The Company undertakes to bear all cost of construction of tne buildings. The Lheikh does not bear any expenses wnatever. ^fter the expiry of this Agreement, the company undertakes to hand over to tne Lessor all tne buildings, including tneir doors, roofs, aiiu wixidows. The rent, i.e.ns. 133/5/4 of tne hew xlot ox jjaxid snail commence from tne date ox completion of construction. The Company will endeavour to complete construction work at early as possibleConfidential* No.C/33-6/4. The Political Officer,Trueial Coast, presents Cora- li ents, to the political Agent,Bahraini and has tlie honour to s him a copy of the undermentioned documents,for informat \ H Dated Sharjah, 23rd January 1940. Agreement concluded on 18th January 1940 between the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited and the Shaikh of Oil Store at Sharjah. \ Sharjah.S'-l—L’' .. J c /: it • j . A &lt;*,£&gt;; AGRESJ'IEMT BETWEEN SHAIKH SULTAN BIN 3AQAR, RULEH OF SHARJAH, Shaikh of Sharjah and its villages, by Lieutenant Colonel Sir Hugh Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, that the High British Government desire to establish an air route along the Arab Coast for t he aeroplanes of the Imperial Airv/ays Company (hereinafter referred to as the Company), and that they wish to have an air station at Sharjah at which British aeroplanes can land, I hereby agree to grant to the said Company the following facilities 1 . The Company may select a landing ground at Sharjah, and may put on it such marks as are necessary, and their aeroplanes may land on t'^at ground. 2 . I will construct a rest house for the passengers and staff of the Company on a site to be selected by the Company and in accordance with olans drawn up by them, and under the supervision of an Engineer of the British Government. The house and fixed fittings to be con sidered as my property. 3. The Company shall have the right to import, free of duty, petrol and spare parts for aircraft, provisions for the passengers and staff, and whatever may be required for their service. 4 . The Company may send their employees to reside in the rest house', but neither they nor the passengers shall enter the town of Sharjah without my permission. protection of the staff and passengers of the Company and their aircraft, so far as my dependents, relatives and subjects are concerned, and further for their protection as far as possible against marauders from outside my juris diction. STATION AT SHARJAH. It having been intimated to me, Sultan bin Saqar, I further accept full responsibility for the I will supply 35 guards qnd 2 head guards. In return for the above, it is agreed that the British/-r^S British Government shall make me the following payments Cl) Pay for 35 guards and two chiefs at the rate of Rs .20 p.m. for each guard and 3s.40 p.m. for each of the two head guards, payment to commence from the date the guards are appointed. (ii) Rent for the Air Station is Rs.800 p.m., payment to commence from the date the first commercial aeroplane lands. (iii) Rent for the Rest Piouse Rs.300 p.m. The Government shall advance me by instalments such sums as may be considered reasonable by the Engineer supervising the v.’ork for the construction of the building, and no rent shall be payable to me until all sums advanced have been repaid. The Government shall supply gratis doors, windows and steel joints and corrugated iron. (iv) For the responsibility that I have accepted, a personal subsidy of Rs.500 p.m. to commence from 1 st July 1932. (v) A landing fee of Rs.5. for every commercial aero plane that lands on the aerodrome. No charge shall be made for aeroplanes belonging to the Royal Air Force. The Comoany and their emoloyees shall not deal direct with the ihaikh but through the Residency Agent or Political Resident. This agreement shall be for Eleven v ears but payments will only be made for so long as the facilities are utilised. Should the British Government require to renew this agreement at the end of the above period they may do so provided three months' notice is given me. Should there be any dispute as to the text of this Agreement the English wording shall prevail. sd/. H.R.P.Dickson, Lt.-Col., for the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 22nd July 1932. fSigned) Sultan bin Saqar, (&amp; sealed) Ruler of Sharjah. V/itnesses sd/-«f ' V3 relegram - G.T.^.(S) From - politicalj-bahtfain TO - political,^harjaJi No. - 278 Dated and received 12th April Keference x^enultimat 6 paragi'ajjh oliarjali Air arrange -ments July 22nd 1932• . please give Shaikh of Sharjah written notice that British Government f s desire renew agreement for 5 years from July 1943. Notice must be given before April 22nd. -Politicali i r INLAND' Immediate Class for telegrams important Express Ordinary To be issued on l?t Eeminder 2ud Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary Xo. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. Draft, Memorandum FOREIGN : Immediate Velesrata No. Important Ordinary Without priority Issued on To (Code word for telegrams.' 1 File No serial No. Dated 19 - *+No. C/513 ~ ' 7 - ^ - «f 3 Polltlosl Agency, Bahrain, 12th April 1243. * 4 ,'~ p r 1 he Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to \ The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah an! has tue honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document. Reference to previous correspondence Bahrain telegram Fo. 278 dated 12th Anril 1943 _L_ 4*^ Wl.- i' Description of enclosure Agreement between Shaikh Sultan bin and the British Cover ment for the station at Sharjah. Saqar, Buler of Sharjah, establishment of an airA r r r vT , r ^ TT T wzvtrznv D^AJYV Sl'TSTAY ^T rT bAOA 7 ?, ^7 r;r? ( &gt;v SHAHJAH, AHH T 1 - 17 ! HHTTTSH S^ r 'H T ' T - T’HHT FCR T t TH F 3 TARTH^ T TF f T T T OF AI T AI^ STAT^' 1 '' vr ''vwa”. It having been intimated to me, Saltan bin Saner, Shaikh of Sharjah and its villages, by lieutenant Solonel Sir Hugh Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Suit, that the High British Government desire to establish an air route along the Arab Coast for the aeroplanes of the Imperial Airways Company ( herein after referred to as the Company ), and that they wish to have an air station at Sharjah at which British aeroplanes can land, 1 hereby erree to rrant to the said Company the following facilities;- 1. The Company may select a landing ground at Sharjah, and may put on it such marks as are necessary, and their aeroplanes may land on that ground. 2 . 1 will construct a rest house for the oassengers and staff of the Company on a site to be selected by the Company cand in accordance with olans drawn up by them, and under the supervision of an Engineer of the British Government. The house and fixed fitt ings to b e considered as my property, 3. The Company shall have the right to inoort, free of duty, petrol and spare parts for aircraft, provisions for the passengers and staff, and whatever my be reouired for their service. 4. The Company may send their employees to reside in the rest house, but neither they nor the passengers shall enter the town of bharjah without my permission. 1 further accept full responsibility for the prote ction of the staff and oassengers of the Company and their air-craft, so far as my dependents, relatives and subjects Are concerned, end further for their nrotection. as far as possible against marauders from outside my jurisdiction. i will supply 35 guards and 2 head guards, in return for the above, it is agreed that the ■'O’'. British/-3d. Isa tin Abdul Latif ? Residency A gent, Sharjah. British Government shall make me the following oayments.;- (1) Pay for 35 guards and two chiefs at the rate of ks.20 p.m. for each guard and Ks.40 p.m. for each of the two head guards, payment to commence from the date the guards are appointed. - (.ii)Hent for air station Ks.800 p.m. pa 2 r ment to com mence from the date the first commercial aeroplane lands. (iii)Pent for the Pest House Ps.300 p.m. . The Government shall advance me by instalments such sums as may be considered reasonable by the Engineer suoer- . vising the work for the construction of the building and no rent shall be payable to me until all the sums advanced have ^ been repaid. The Government will supoly gratis doors, win- dov/s and steel joists and corrugated iron. x (iv) For the responsibillty that i have accepted, a * personal subsidy of Ks. 500.p.m. to commence from 1st July, 1032. —(v) — A—landing fee of ks.5. for'every Commercial aero- olane that lands on the aerodrome. Ho charges shall be made for aeroplanes belonging to the Koval Air Force. The Company and their employees shall not deal'dire-yy, ct with the Shaikh but through the Kesidency Agent or Poli tical Resident. This Agreement shall be for Eleven Years but pay ments will only be made for so long as the facilities are utilised. Should the British Government reouire to renew this Agreement at the end of the above period they may do so pro vided three months’ notice is given me. Should there be any dispute as to the text of this Agreement the English wording shall prevail. Sd. TT .P.P.Pickson, Lt-Col., for the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sd. Sultan bin Saqar, (&amp; sealed ) Ruler of Sharjah. 22nd July 1932. Witnesses Sd. Edward C.Denison,Capt.P.N. .Commanding T - T .! T .S.'Bidefov 3 d. Humaid bin All bin Puma id.. Translation of letter dated 16th Rabi ul Than! 1362(21st April 1943) % ¥ l from Shaikh sultad bin Saqr,Ruel:lr of Sharjah to the Political Officer, — Trucial Coast* After compliments, Reference your latter No.346 dated 14th April 1943(9 Rabi ul -Thani 1362). it is undersittod that H.B.M's Government wish the renewal of the Agreement reached between me and the B.O.A.C. on 22nfl July 1932 and its extention for 5 years from 1st July 1943 and I accordingly agree to that while directing the attention of the Government to my right to the calling of commercial steamships at my town of Sharjah as was promis -ed to me by the Government in its letter dated 17th Rabi ul awwal 1361 attached to the above mentioned agreement. Steamships continued calling regularly at Sharjah until the last steamship Virginia(lab January)arriv -ed from Karachi on 25th August 1942(13th sha’ban 1361). They then stopp -ed coming with no small harm to the trade of Sharjah oo tlie extent that many merchants left the town. As the rent paid by the company to me is small in view of present conditions I expect gracious kindness from the Government, and I am sure that the Government will estimatq(and we will not cease to th«t| thank it for its good intentions towards us and we supplicate ^od and praise him for giving to the Government victory over its enemies the dictators. Seal and signature, Sultan bin saqr. Usual endingsINLAND: Immediate Class for telegrams important Express To be issued on 1st Reminder 2nd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading : Diary No. V' ^ Ordinary DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. | J rait Memorancu m Telegram FOREIGN« Immediate j ^O. Important Ordinary Without priority To Issued on Dated File No. Seiial No, 10 . £Confidential No. C/o43 J ■ 4- QZ 2 VtA '■olitical Agency, ahrain, 20th April 1943 To xhe r'oiiuical officer, Trucial Coast, Charjah. memorandum reference .esidency Agent, Charjah’s confidential memorandum No. 0/440-6/1 dated the 4th July 1938. 2 . I have received instructions from the molitical Resident to arrange a renewal of the Dubai Civil Air Agreement for a further period of five years from the date of its expiry, i.e. 22nd July 1943. 3. If you can ascertain informally that the ohaikh is willing to renew the agreement I suggest that his written assent be secured' in a'' formal exchange of letters. If, however, it seems that renewal of the agreement is likely to be a matter for negotiation you may prefer to postpone a formal approach to the ohaikh until the return of the residency Agent. 4. Please let me know in due course what action you have taken. Political Agent, Bahrain.—A, N iDSKTXyiL * NO • C/4X6-6/4 ro, British Agency, Sharjah. 3rd May 1943. The political Agent, BAHRAIN . Subjects- Renewal of Dubai Cxvjl Air Agreement. MBMQI^-UTDblA . I '' ^ Reference your confidential merjorancium No. C/543 dated 20th April 1943. 2. The Shaikh of Dubai has informed me in wri -ling that he agrees to extend the Civil Air Agreeuient with the B.O.A.C. for a further period of 6 year s from 22nd July 1943. Political Officer7*rmcial\oast. mFile No. INLAND : Immediate Class for telegrams Express Ordinalv DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. Draft' Memorandum Telegram FOREIGN : Immediate No. 1 mjiortant Ordinary To Iv issued on • . 1st Reminder Ihul Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above Without priority Issued on Dated To Serial No 19*■ Confidential No. C/693 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharj ah. Renewal of Shariah Civil Air Memorandum Agreement C* r J Reference your demi-official letter No. C/407-6/4 dated the 2nd May 1943. 2. Will you kindly send me a copy of your letter No. 348 dated the 14th April 1943, referred to by the Shaikh of Shariah in his letter to you dated the 16th Rabi ul Thani 1362 (21st April 1943) ? Political Agent, Bahrain. ^3) Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd May 1943(gl) Confidential No. C/694 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd May 1943. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Renewal of Dubai Civil Air Memorandum Agreement 3 f * Reference your memorandum No. C/416-6/4 dated the 3rd May 1943. 2. Please send j the Shaikh of Dubai \\\ \ i'X . of the letters exchanged with Political Agent, Bahrain,4 Confidential* No.C/492-6/4 To, British Agency, Sharjah* Dated the 25th May 1943* The political Agent, Bahrain* MEMORANDUM■ Reference your confidential memorandum No*C/ 693 dated the 22nd May 1943. 2* Appended is the copy of our letter No*348 dated the 14th April 1943 to the Shaikh of »harjah* political OfficerjTrueial Coast* Confidential* No.c/493-6/4 To MEMORANDUM, British Agency, Sharjah* Dated the 25th May 1943* The political Agent, Bahrain* Reference your confidential memorandum No*C/ 694 dated the 22nd May 1943* ^ o d 3 / ■, 2* Appended are the copies of the letters exchanged with the shaikh of Dubai* political Officer^CTrucial Coast*~S£&gt; hl2A~^ ^ ^ - H 7, Political Agency, No* C/785» Bahrain, the 9th June, 1943. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah* Memorandum. Reference the enclosure to your Confidential Memorandum No. C/492-6/4 dated the 25th May, 1943. - ^ 3 The intention was that the Sharjah Air Agreement should be renewed for five years from the 22nd July, 1943 rather than from the 1st July, 1943. Could the Shaikh*s agreement be obtained to the small change necessary ? /) y^ii % Political Agent, Bahrain. NCJConfidential* No7375g7^T To | British Agency, Sharjah. Dated the 16th June 1943* The political Agent, Bahrein. Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.C/785 dated 9th June 1943. 2. i beg to enclose herewith, in original and translation, letter tjo. 691 dated 13th jaraad ath-^hani 1362(i.e. 16th June 1943) from the Shaikh of Sharjah giving his agftiment for the renewal and extension of the Air Agreement for a period of five ye^rs with effect from 22nd July 1943. Residency Agent,dharj ah Translation of letter no.591 date! 13th jamad ath- Than! 1362(i.e* 16-th Juno 1943)from Shaikh sultan hi bin Saqr,Ruler of jharjah to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. After Compliments, Reference our conversation, I have the honour to infirm you that i agree to the renewal and extension for a period of five years -tith effect from 22n£ July 1943 of tlxe agreement reached between me and His Majesty’s Government on 22nd July 1932 for the establishnent of an Air station for rthe imperial Aiztways* Usual landings.Agreement between Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar, Ruler of Shargah, and the British Government for the Estab lishment of an Air Station at Shargah. It having been intimated to me, Sultan bin Saqar, Shaikh of Shargah and its villages, by Lieutenant Colonel Sir Hugh Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, that the High British Government desire to establish an air route along the Arab Coast for the aeroplanes of the Imperial Airways Company (hereinafter referred to as the Company), and that they wish to have an air station at Shargah at which British aeroplanes can land, I hereby agree to grant to the said Company the following facilitiess- 1. The Company may select a landing ground at Shargah, and may put on it such marks as are necessary, and their aeroplanes may land on that ground. 2. I will construct a rest house for the passengers and staff of the company on a site to be selected by the Company and in accordance with plans drawn up by them, and under the super vision of an Engineer of the British Government. The house and fixed fittings to be considered as my property. 3. The Company shall have the right to import, free of duty, petrol and spare parts for aircraft, provisions for the passengers and staff, and whatever may be required for their service. 4. The Company may send their employes to reside in the rest house, but neither they nor the passengers shall enter the town of Shargah without my per mission. I further accept full responsibility for the protection of the staff and passengers of the Company and their aircraft, so far as my dependents, relatives and subjects are concerned, and further for their protection as far as possible against marauders from outside my jurisdiction. I will supply 35 guards and 2 head guards.- 2 - P In return for the above, it is agreed that the British Government.shall make me the following payments:- (i) Pay for 35 guards and two chiefs at the rate of Rs.20/-p*m. for each guard and Rs.40/-p.m. for each of the two head guards, payment to commence from the date the guards are appointed, (ii) Rent for the Air Station Rs.800 p.m., payment to commence from the date the first commercial aeroplane lands. (iii) Rent for the Rest House Rs.300 p.m. The Government shall advance me by instalments such sums as may be considered reasonable by the Engineer supervising the work for the construction of the building and no xss&amp;a rent shall be payable to me until all the sums advanced have been repaid. The Government will supply gratis doors, windows and steel joists and corrugated iron. (iv) For the responsibility that I have accepted, a personal subsidy of Rs.500 p.m. to commence from 1st Jlily, 1932. (v) A landing fee of Rs.5. for every commercial aeroplane that lands on the aerodrome. No charge shall be made for aeroplanes belonging to the Royal Air Force. The company and their employes shall not deal direct with the Shaikh but through the Residency Agent or Political Resident. This Agreement shall be for Eleven Years but payments will only be made for so long as the facilities are utilised. Should the British Government require to renew this Agreement at the end of the above period they may do so provided three months 1 notice is given me. Should there be any dispute as to the text of /thisthis Agreement the English woidting shall prevail ' sd/- DICKSON, Lt-Col., for the Hon* ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 22nd July 1932. sd/- SULTAN bin SAQAR, (&amp; sealed) Ruler of Shargah. Witnesses . sd/- Edward C. Denison, Capt., R.N., Commanding H.Sfl.S. 'Bideford'. sd/- Humaid bin Ali bin Humaid. sd/- Isa bin Abdul Latif, Residency Agent, Shargah. Translation of letter No. 591 dated 13th Jaraad al Thani 1362 (i.e. 16th June 1943) from Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah, to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. After Compliments, Reference our conversation, I have the honour to inform you that I agree to the renewal and extension for a period of five years with effect from 22nd July i 1943 of the Agreement reached between me and His Majesty Government on 22nd July 1932 for the establishment of an / Air Station for the Imperial Airways. Usual Ending./ DUBAI COMMERCIAL AIR AGR This Agreement is made between His Majesty’s Government and Shaikh sa’id bin Maktum, Ruler of Dubai. Base for aircraft of Imperial Airways Limited. (a) The area to be defined as before by Imperial Airways Limited and properly buoyed and marked. (b) The rent to be charged is to include the pay of guards, the use of the alighting area and the space required for the per manent jetty, sheds for the motor launches, passenger shelter and store. It will be Rs.940/- a month. This sum is exclusive of landing charges. (a) The buildings and other constructions mention in clause 1(b) above will be carried out by the Company. All such buildings and constructions, if of an immovable nature, will become the Shaikh f s property on ter mination of the lease. (b) Buildings and constructions must be on land or water owned by the Shaikh. (c) All materials such as stones and lime required for building and construction work to be obtained from the Dubai mines. or other work carried out in connection with it, then thabost of such work is to be borne by the Company and the Shaikh will in no way be held liable for the payment of any compensation to the Company. crime, the Shaikh should lodge a complaint against him with the Political Resident who will investigate the case and take what action may be desirable. 1 This Agreement to be for a Commercial Landing 3 Should this sea landing base require dredging 4. Labourers required for work on the landing base should be natives of Dubai. 5. should any employee of the Company commit any /6. Should any- 2 - 6* Should any Dubai subject be accused of any offence in respect of the Commercial Landing Base at Dubai he shall not be punished until the offence has been proved to the joint satisfaction of the Shaikh of Dubai and the Political Agent. 7. No employee (foreign) of the Company shall enter the town at night. Should any person infringe this rule by entering the town at night and, God forbid, suffer injury or loss, then the Shaikh will not be held responsible. 8. Guards and watchmen of the landing base will be appointed by the shaikh. 9. (a) No women or sailors should be permitted to seek refuge in the landing base. (b) The shaikhs internal affairs shall not be interfered with in any manner whatsoever. 10. A charge of Rs.5/- will be paid to the Shaikh for every landing by an aircraft. 11. If any injury is done to the craft or its people by any outside enemy then the Government, v/hen necessity arises, should assist the Shaikh by all means. 12. Natives of Dubai should be employed by the Company in the landing base for all such work as they are capable of doing. 13. Should liquor be necessary for the special use of the landing base the Company shall on no account permit the sale of such liquor to the natives of and persons residing in the Country and Towns of Dubai.. 14. This Agreement will be for a period of five years with effect from the 22nd July, 1938. sd/- Sa’id bin Maktum sd/- H. WEIGHTMAN Ruler of 0ubai. Political Agent, Bahrain.Translation of letter dated 27th Rabi al Thani 1362 (3rd May 1943) from the Shaikh of Dubai to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, After Compliments. Your esteemed letter has been received and I have noted what you say about the (sc, renewal of the) five year agreement with the British Overseas Airways Corporation concerning the civil seaplane base at Dubai. There is no harm in this, and I agree to that agreement in accordance with your suggestion, and wish you to be informed accordingly. Usual Ending. NS/ SI S' 0~i sj)+&gt; 0*-~ &amp; jU || ^—► ^ vA^o ,4lUjuJI oKMj*' M llXliy 1 jjp&amp;jl ♦ aa ^ 2^Jt j!?*^ *1* ^ ^jiUJtjt^^l^^ ^ S-r^C^- 9 ^jt ^ oW^^ CrtHi • L~*j^Uj p*A» ^ #1; j( Lfy oJt 4^fM tfrL.gj*wJ \ jfo i&gt;-l t yi* ( t ) • LAu»%J Lua* t ST^JlJI I^wo 1 # ^ 1 (T) ^M 1 lm*j^ Uu^&amp;s *U:I Ui;l r -Jc.U»lr^^ J * t,.^^ ^^a-J 32 [|mI-U tyu J^*^M vl^ 1^ *;i^^ ^} Jliyjif ijt^j**** iH^O J1^*&lt; &amp;Ja#0'C*^“' ^Ji ^ 9 %ki p**J\ • v Jkjl^Al3^4il ^V*^0» J A»&gt;c *^^ 0 ^ ^IS l***j£L»j»Jt^^ &amp;j*2J\ JH^t ^ J—£***-*k«*-^ *!&gt;- ^fr y »w*&gt;t 9 &lt;J^ t .I ,ljtjil^aaa^} £ Jtl^. J^UJl^SSjjJ\ y U-M^ UjiiCJ^ 2Sj*Jjl {*) *j JUaS Ui Uij 5^^-tJl i^ikM u^y j v^ij &amp;&gt;-i-u i 4su io^y^i 0 yfyXijfi*% ^ •&gt; J ^11 I,—W O 1 *&gt;^ 1 &gt; (» ) 4J&gt; J1 NT Kad« cn tht FIRST ±^? 19^6 between the SEMI ^,;v^i Ql ^jw&gt;~ •*’ /''^ *''•■’ AHGLO^XPAltUK 6 lL CO^FAKYj IH ITED, (Incorporated in Great Britain) on the one part hereinafter called the CG&amp;FAHT and Mesara* RUSSAIK BIB BAS GAB f 1 AD 9 ABDUL BAIT# AN BIB BUSSAIH and All ABDULLAL AAAZI % on the other part hereinafter called the AGENTS• u^ 1 VJ^M J~Mi&lt; mm t-AJtlj A—^—J#-- A^U*&gt; If Cf ■■&gt;!&gt;*■*■* !r^ O* Cd^^H A4, ..-UJ J -O J» ^.. . ■■■IflH i «&lt; ^2^ AJ-XICLE (1) - Th« two parties agree that the Agenta ahall act jointly and severally at Dubai as Agents for the sale of the Co&amp;pany^ goods* All reference to Cor panjr’s goods in this Agreement shall be understood to refer to all goods belonging to the Corpany other than bulk Aviation Spirit* It is incumbent on the Agents that they confer* with the conditions set out below and do not exceed then* mj&amp;MkJJil. The Agents shall in all cases connected with the Coapany’s goods or interests act according to Instructions given by the Company* M.,mM^Lll - The Agents shall take delivery or all goods sent by the Company for sale and shall take all due precautions in the safe handling, storage and custody of such goods, which shall remain the property of the Company until sold* The Agents shall take all reasonable precautions for the safe custody of the Company 1 ! goods and shall be responsible Jointly and severally for the full payment to the Company on demand of the sale proceeds of such goods* It is further understood that the Agents shall be jointly and severally responsible for indemnifying the Company for any less it ©ay sustain of whatever nature whether occasioned by robbery, or bankruptcy or insol* vency of any third party or otherwise* ,4), * The Agents shall maintain and hold for the Company's inspection separate records of all transactions on their behalf, in accordance with such of the Company's Instructions as may be issued in this respect and shall hold all sale proceeds es the Company's property payable on demand to the Company, moreover these proceeds shall not be used by the Agents for any other purposes. the goods for The Agents shall sell goodsfor cash only except in cases where they have received special instructions fro* the Company, but the Agents agree that\ 3 i A _ r _ ^Sji 0 i r ^^iyAJ'a' t}S J •^ Jt J-h • 4jU&gt;l Llfc^ j ^ «pl*JI *^&gt;iJ V SJBjJI z-i JL1» ^jt J^JI li llaU')l^^s&gt;-'•i' Jj-^UJUjUI ..k jiiJI, ^ 4 jUI »J cr (M ) «j ^L—: ^Iwr-s * j-* j~* l,- U t fJlc.)UUJ! ij_JU)lvi&gt; J r-J‘«^ • ^kUU, (&gt; r ) #jI -J' CilV • 4U i ) 4^1 -Ji ^ I £\ji y \ cLt * 4 )^ jj ^ ^ J 1 ^r- - * v 0- ’ (J ^ ^ J ^ 4P ' x ** J-^^t - 5 •^ ji ’ ^ jUj'jIlt *JU ^U^UJi sjjty^ ^ ii* 1 r 15,31 li&gt; &lt;; bj^-^ Ua^. I j ^ jU:l J-«»h 4ijUJ» Jt 5 ^ 1 ! CrT^*^ 1 Jl J cA-^ Crfff Jw&lt; ^ jU &lt; ^*4 p&gt;Pr U^x* j UJ ^ j 1/SJ ^ • 4 —JuU-JI UJl^ ^jJUjuJI ( ^« ) 4J^ Jy**' id *** j(^ ^ f 5 * 1 ^ ^a#U.'uit 4^L*J JP a* L--^v&gt;J«aJli if J^P 1 • l | - y ( ^ 'V ) 4 *&gt; i l l ■ ■ n jJpUJi 4J*M y 4.*%.»X ^ jlUCfcli (^ Y ) 4jl 4.J ! [ tfpt aXU. ,&gt;» 4j^ 4J '* o' 4 j lj^ JP ^uJaP^-j^ &lt; Ot O^p* J jU# —»- ^ undeptake to advise the Company promptly of any saving or reduction In these charges or expenses which can be or have been effected* AflnCi*4 mj» Hiis agreement is terminable by three months notice at the option of either party, but the Company retains the right to dismiss the Agents at any time if the abovementioned conditions are not complied with* At the termination of their Agency, the Agents will have no right to salary or compensation over and above the payment of any balance which may be outstanding for their services agreed upon in Clause (10) of this Contract* AK-XICLt; (12). All the record* of the transactions carried out by the Agents on behalf of the Company shall be handed over to the Company on termination of this Agreement* AfillCha (l^j. Should any questions arise regarding the interpretation of this Agreement, the English version shall prevail. .Vinfifc ,U4i.« In the event of any doubt, differences or dispute arising between the Company and the Agents as to the meaning or effect of any of the provisions of this Agreement which cannot be settled by mutual agreement, the same shall be referred to two arDitrators to be nominated by each party and a referee who shall be chosen by the arbitrators or failing agreement, the Company shall request iioB*^ 1 * the Residency Agent at Sharjah, to appoint a referee* The decision of the arbitrators or in the case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon the contracting parties to this agreement* mKM, cm. In case of litigation it is agreed that all legal actions brought by one party against the other shall be dealt with by H*l*lt , s the Residency Agent at Sharjah* AKTIC^ (16). Copy of this Agrea ent shall be retained by each of the Contracting Parties* (17) . this Agency Agreement _s superseded the Agendy Agreement signed on 29th September 1936 con cluded between the Company and Messrs* Hussain Bin Hassan Emad and Abdul Rahman Bin Hussain* T i Ci&gt; C«wConfidential ^o. 221.0425 -British ^:ency, Sharjah. Dated the 1,3th Karch,1948/ To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject * Dubai Commercial Air Agreement« :emorandum. The period of validity of the Commercial Air Agreement with the Ruler of Dubai is due to expire on the 22nd July,1948. ' • would be appreciated if I could be informed whether it is intended this agreement should be renewed or not. Ay\, A Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah*11 i *&gt; v / ? . ; ' ■ -/-V. KKPHESS- LETTKK From. To. Political .Resident, Persian dulf, Bahrain. H.M's Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London. Repeated A.O.C., R.A.F., 'Iraq, liabbaniyah. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 609-S Dated Bahrain the 20th March, 1948. Subject: ftaiba PgQ.Uhd Copy is enclosed of Bahrain memorandum No. C/258 dated the 14th March, 1948 and of its enclosures. 2 . The present Agreement covering this landing ground is due to expire on the 27th August 1248 and if neither the R.A.F. nor the B.O.A.C. are likely to require air facilities in Kalba in future, I suggest that the Ruler be given adequate warning that the Agreement will be allowed to lapse and that no further payments will be made to him after 27th August 1948. 'Sgd. VV.R. HAY Political Resident, Persian Culf. ATTRSTKD. Sgd. THOMAS for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian 8ulf.C THii POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHiL* :N, Dated the 23'rd May ? 3 48. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his complimento tp s- Th« Political Officer, Irucial Coast, Charjah, , I \ ■ CONFID^NTUL No. C/S. 15 and has the honour tQ send him a copy of the undermentioned document^) for favour of action. liEFLALNCi-» TO PH^VIOUS COxtrUSPONDLHCL Agency Printed Lector No. C/336 dated the 1st April, 1948. D^BCHIPTION' OF LNCLOSUiiL Express letter No. B/126 (81/43) dated 13th May, 1948 from the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. SUBJECT. Kalba Landing Ground. A k \ if Iconfidential EXPRESS LETTEK From, Political Resident, Bahrain, To. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. B/125 (81/42) Dated the 19th May, 1948. Reference your memorandum No. C/258 dated the 14th March, 1948. Kalba Landing Ground. 2. His Majesty*s Government have stated that the landing ground is no longer required either for the R.A.F or civil aviation purposes. 3. The Ruler may be informed therefore that the Agreement will be allowed to lapse and that no further payments will be made to him after 27th August, 1948. Sd/- W • R• IlitY Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. ATTESTED. Sd/- A.L.A. DREDGE Secretary to the Political Resident Persian Gulf. L2 - JpU IJ —A 4. H.M. Government also require your permission for the R»A«F« to ise in the landing basememergencies and I should be grateful if you could agree to this also. Usual Ending. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah.i,*l J=*3 Lj- o*/ 14' G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah 47 7th June 1948. IMPORTANT. H.M. Government have telegraphed that B.O.A.C. may wish to use Dubai as long as their Hythe flying boat service continues and R..A.F* still requiring a mooring for emergency flying boat landing. You are directed to negotiate on extension of commercial air agreement on its present terms for a further period of 3 years. 2. it would seem that both B.O.A.C. and r.A.F. only requiring Dubai for emergency use. There is therefore of course no objection to^ your obtaining renewal on cheaper terms but in view of H.K.^^oyernment's order this considera tion shouldyjprejudice the negotiation. =POLITICAL=I £ INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record Ref. No. IOL: ICR Date Name Proce s s No. of exposures 1 'WS v 2 3 4 5 6 REFER TO THE SPECIALIST CONCERNED</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00034e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/4/4</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00034e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/4/4</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 0425 Copies of Agreements, Concessions etc'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-03T10:47:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (63 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in rough chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 65; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional mixed foliation/pagination sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-31; these numbers are written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains copies of the following agreements:Agreement between the British government and Shaikh Said bin Hamad [Sa‘īd bin Ḥamad Āl Qāsimī], ruler of Kalba, for facilitation of an airfield, 28 August 1936;Agreement between the British government and Shaikh Sa’id bin Maktum [Sa‘īd bin Maktūm Āl Maktūm], ruler of Dubai, for the provision of a jolly-boat for storage of petrol in Dubai creek, 15 December 1933;Agreement between the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and Shaikh Sa’id bin Maktum, 10 May 1939;Dubai Commercial Air Agreement between the British Government and Shaikh Sa’id bin Maktum, 22 July 1938 (with renewals on 3 May 1943 and 8 June 1948);Agreement of Sultan bin Salim [Sulṭān bin Sālim Āl Qasimī], ruler of Ras al Khaimah, to provide for petrol storage and protection of aeroplanes, and a guarantee for the security of Khan Bahadur Isa, the Residency Agent, 15 June 1930;Agreement between the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar [Sulṭān II bin Saqr Āl Qasimī], ruler of Sharjah, 18 January 1940;Agreement between the British government and Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar for the establishment of an air station in Sharjah, 22 July 1932 (with renewal on 22 July 1943);Agreement of Shaikh Sa’id bin Maktum to charter his motor launch to the British Overseas Airways Corporation and the Government of India, 16 November 1941;Agreement between the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and Said bin Maktum for the lease of a plot of land near the creek, map included (folio 42), 1 May 1944;Agreement between the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and Messrs. Hussain bin Hassan Emad, Abdul Rahman bin Hussain, and Ali Abdullah Awazi to act as company agents in Dubai, 1 September 1946.Included is correspondence between the Residency Agent and Political Officer at Sharjah, the Political Agency at Bahrain, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf at Bushire (Bahrain from 1946), and a number of Trucial Coast rulers. The correspondence is related to renewals of air agreements.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00034e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>