<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002a4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:01:02.767Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">B. 273. MIDDLE EAST COMMITTEF. .Mesopotamia : Britisli Engagements as to future Status. I. —Pledges to local Arabs, &amp;c. . Si*' {&gt; - ^ ox wrote as follows to various Arab Chiefs in the Persian Culf reo-ion (including Bin Saud and the Sheikh of Mohammerah) in November ]914 ;— ' J an) authorised by my GoA r ernment to assure Your Excellency that in the e\ ent ot oui success and succeed we shall, Inshallah—Basra will never again be allowed to be subject to Turkish authority.' In acknowledging Sir P. Cox's letter, the Chiefs of Maskat, Koweit, and El Katr said that they had circulated the information which it contained. 2. A proclamation addressed to the people of Basra and issued on the ^nd November 1914, contained the following passage :— ' We have no enmity or ill-will against the populace, to whom we hope to prove good friends and protectors. No remnant of Turkish administration now remains in this region. In place thereof the British flag has been established, under which you will enjoy the benefits of liberty and justice both in regard to your religious and, your secular affairs.' 3. Tn December 1914 Sir P. Cox asked for authority to make a definite public announcement to the effect that ' our occupation of Basra is permanent.' His Majesty's Government demurred, on the ground that such an announcement ' would be regarded as a definite breach of the under- ' taking between the Allies that a final settlement must await the end of the ' war ' ; but they raised no objection to a proposal made by the Government of India that Sir P. Cox ' should allow it to be understood in conversation ' that places where we assume control with the co-operation of the ' inhabitants may in all circumstances count on our future protection ' against the Turks.' 4. On the 3rd February 1915 the Viceroy (Lord Hardinge), replying to a deputation at Basra, said : — ' You are, of course, aware that, in the great struggle in which we are involved, we are not fighting single-handed, and we cannot therefore lay down plans for the future without a full exchange of views with the other great Powers who are our Allies ; but in any case we may be permitted to indulge a very confident assurance that henceforth a more benign administration will bring back to Iraq that prosperity to which her rich potentialities give her so clear a title.' 5. The famous proclamation issued by General Maude ' to the people of Baghdad ' (19th March 1917) on the occupation of the city, contained nothing amounting to an absolute pledge that Baghdad would never be allowed to revert to Ottoman rule ; but the general sense of the document (the language of which, it will be remembered, was adopted after very careful consideration by His Majesty's Government) pointed strongly in that direction. Its character can only be conveyed by copious quotation. After opening with an assurance that 'our armies do not come into your cities and lands as conquerors or enemies, but as liberators, and dwelling upon the evils wrought by Turkish rule in the past, the proclamation proceeded :— (4) Since the days of Midhat, the Turks have talked of reforms, yet do not the ruins and wastes of to-day testify the vanity of those promises ? 10 S o 175 11/18 A ~n .iii.m. .(5) It is the wish not only of my King and his peoples, but it is also the wish of the great nations with whom lie is in alliance, that you should prosper even as in the past, when your lands were fertile when your ancestors gave to the world literature, science, and art' and when Baghdad city was one of the wonders of the world. (6) Between your people and the dominions of my King there has been a close bond of interest. For 200 years have the merchants of Baghdad and Great Britain traded together in mutual profit and friendship. On the other hand, the Germans and Turks who have despoiled you and yours, have for 20 years made Baghdad a centre of power from which to assail the power of the British and the Allies of the British in Persia and Arabia. Therefore the British Government cannot remain indifferent as to what takes place in your country now or in the future, for in duty to the interests of the British people and their Allies, the British Government cannot risk that being done in Baghdad again which has been done by the Turks and Germans during the war. (7) But you people of Baghdad, whose commercial prosperity and whose safety from oppression and invasion must ever be a matter of the closest concern to the British Government, are not to understand that it is the wish of the British Government to impose upon you alien 'institutions. It is the hope of the British Government that the aspirations of your philosophers and writers shall be realised and that once again the people of Baghdad shall flourish, enjoying their wealth and substance under institutions which are in con sonance with their sacred laws and their racial ideals. In Hejaz the Arabs have expelled the Turks and Germans who oppressed them and proclaimed the Sherif Hussein as their King, and his Lordship rules in independence and freedom, and is the ally of the nations who are fighting against the power of Turkey and tiermany ; so, indeed, are the noble Arabs, the Lords of Koweyt, Nejd, and A sir. (8) Many noble Arabs have perished in the cause of Arab freedom, at the hands of those alien rulers, the Turks, who oppressed them. It is the determination of the Government of Great Britain and the great Powers allied to Great Britain, that these noble Arabs shall not have sullered in vain. It is the hope and desire of the Biitisli people and the nations in alliance with them, that the Aiab race may rise once more to greatness and renown among the peoples of the earth, and that it shall bind itself together to this end in unity and concord. «&lt; 11 conclusion, the inhabitants were called upon ' to participate in tl 16 mana &amp; e i m e n t ol your civil affairs in collaboration with the political u 1( P reson tatives of Great Britain who accompany the British Army, so that u yoi i. may 7 uluted with your kinsmen in North, East, South and West in realising the aspirations of your race.' to t v! 3 -r Atthe eil( ' Majesty's Government, in a telegram Vil-ivpt 0 . dia » ^ down as their policy (1) that the Basra (2^'tint iVu^'p. I 0 ! 11 '! 11 ^ .P ei ' mailen tly under British administration; and loc il rnlpr - . lC tU '^yct should be made into an Arab State with a but mure- H10'°^f 1 . nln ^ nt ' ^^^ er a British Protectorate in everything Arab nrovi'nro 1 • ,1 r 1 ^ ra h facade, to be administered as an »««-• Minister 011 ll ' C ,var aims of Britain, the Prime ' Syria and Palestine 'ire'', 1 ' 0 ' ,lmt ' Aral,ia ' Armenia, Mesopotamia. ' separate national conditions 0 ' 1 J J'| c ' itul ? d 10 a recognition of their restore ' the territovioc • ' • ^^ed that it would be ' impossible to lioth I^hdad and Hn 5 ' 1681 , 10 ' '• , . 0 . their former sovereignty.' Anglo-Russo -French \or &lt;lSia e tbe 'red area ' as defined by the ^ British Govennn^ r't». 19 l^zone within which ' tion or control as thpv A e:sta blibh suoh direct or indirect administra- '■ Arab State or Confederatiin^?/'vAVsIat^' think &lt;il to arl ' allge witl1 tlieII. Pledges to King Husain. i. I lie Shenf of Mecca's territorial demands, as formulated bv him ^ h.s m-gotiatmas w.th the High Conuoissiouer for lOgvpt (Sir Henry Jlacjlahon) in the latter part of I'J 15 were aa follows ; ' England to acknowledge the independence of the Arab countries oomide.l oil 'hi' north by Jlersma-Adana up to the 37° of latitude, on i, tl'i ( ! e ^ree falls Ihnjik, Lrfa, Mardin, Midiat, Amadia Island, up ili ('■ ir' VT, ersui; on the east by the borders of Persia up to the i.ull of Basra; on the south by the Indian Ocean, with the 0 ' ,e P™ 1 ' 0 ' 1 of A, ''- n t0 remain as it is; on the west by the lied bea, the Mediterranean Sea up to Mersina.' ihe area so defined includes the whole of Mesopotamia and Irak. Keplyiug on the 24th October 1915, Sir H. MacMahon informed the Sherif hat, subject to certain modifications (not. affecting Mesopotamia), Great luitaiu was prepared to recognise and support the Independence of the Arabs within the territories included in the limits and boundaries proposed.' tin legaid to Mesoputomia lie put in the following caveat:— •' With regard to the vilayets of Baghdad and Basra., the Arabs will recognise that the established position and interests of Great Britain necessitate special measures of administrative control in order to secure those territories from foreign aggression, to promote the nelfaie oi the local populations and to safeguard our mutual economic interests.' 9. The Sherif replied (5th November 1915);— As the J rovmces oi Irak are parts of the pure Arab Kingdom and were in lact the seat of its Governments in the time of Ali Ibn Abu Talib, and in the time of all Caliphs who succeeded him ; and as in them began the civilisation of the Arabs, and as their towns in those piovmces \\eie the iirst towns built in Islam whero the Arab power became so groat ; therefore these provinces are greatly valued by all Arabs far and near, and their traditions cannot be forgotten by them. Consoqnciuly we cannot satisly the Arab nations or make them submit to give up such a title to nobility. But in order to render an accord easy, and taking into consideration the assurances mentioned in the liith article of your letter, to keep and guard our mutual interests in that country as they are one and the same, for all these reasons we might agree to leave under the British Administration for a short time those districts now occupied by the British troops, without the rights of either party being prejudiced thereby (especially those of the Arab nation, which interests are to it economic and vital) and against a suitable sum paid as compensation to the Arab Kingdom for the period of occupation, in order to meet the expenses which every new kingdom is bound to support, at the same time respecting your agreements with the Sheikhs of those districts, and especially those which are essential.' 10. The Sherif s proposal was never formally accepted. Sir H. MacMahon merely replied (17th December 1915):— 44 The Government of Great Britain, as I have already informed you, are ready to give all guarantees of assistance and support within their power to the Arab Kingdom, but their interests demand, as you yourself have recognised, a friendly and stable administration in the vilayet of Baghdad, and the adequate safeguarding of these interests calls for a much fuller and more detailed consideration than the present situation and the urgency of these negotiations permits.' 11. The Sherif's reply (1st January 1916) purported to be an acceptance of Sir H. MacMahon's view, but he was careful not to let the question ofnHHOiM compensation (vvhicli Sir H. MacMahon had ignored) go by defaidt. It ran as follows:— . ' With regard to what had been stated in your honoured com mu meat ion. concerning El Irak, as to the matter of compensation for the period of occupation, we, in order to strengthen the confidence of Great Britain in our attitude and in our words and actions, leall} and veritably, and in order to give her evidence of our certainty and assurance in trusting her glorious Government, leave the determi nation of the amount to the perception of her wisdom and justice. 12. The correspondence, so far as Mesopotamia is concerned, closed with Sir H. MacMahon's reply, in which he merely ' took note ' of the bhent s ' remarks concerning the \ ilayet of Baghdad, and promised that he would ' take the question into careful consideration when the enemy has been ' defeated and the time for peaceful settlement arrives.' 13 On the 25th August 191G the Sherif, in acknowledging the grant to him of a monthly subsidy of 125,0001. by His Majesty's Government, wrote as follows to Sir H. MacMahon :— u Your Excellency knows that the above-mentioned monthly pay of 125,0007. is for the organisation of government and its necessary administrations, and will be deducted from the amount which we left to the justice of Great Britain to decide for our deficient Government, which is under Great Britain's guardianship and protection, during her occupation of Basrah and Irak.' No reply appears to have been returned to this letter. 14. In a recent telegram (22nd January 1918) Sir Li. Wingate has recommended that, in view of what he describes as the 'growing uneasiness among Arabs about the Entente's intentions for Arab countries,' he should be authorised at once to give King Hueain the following definite assurances ;— (1) that His Majesty's Government is still determined to secure Arab independence and to fulfil the promises made at the beginning of the Hejaz revolt; (2) that His Majesty's Government will countenance no permanent foreign or European occupation of Palestine, Irak (except the province ot Basrah) or Syria after the war; and (3) That these districts will be in the possession of their natives, and that foreign interference with Arab countries will be restricted to assistance and protection. 15. Commenting on these recommendations, Sir P. Cox (telegram of 25th January 11)18) has protested strongly against Mesopotamia being ' treated as a pawn in our negotiations or relations with young Arabs of ' Egypt and the Sherif ' ; and has urged that, if any new declarations are considered necessary, no reference should be made to the promises of 1915, at all events so far as Mesopotamia is concerned. The Government of India (telegram of 29th January) support Sir P. Cox s view, and recommend that, if further discussion with King Husain at the present stage is really unavoidable, an endeavour should be made to obtain the King's assent to a ^ definite modification ol MacMahon's unfortunate pledge in the light of ' actual iacts and his acceptance of principle that we should have rio-ht to ^ f 0 ^ ue m jji s tration of both Vilayets with the object of gradually building up self-government m both.' Political Department, India Office, 30th January 1918.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002a4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B273</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002a4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B273</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Middle East Committee. Mesopotamia: British Engagements as to future Status'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1918</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T10:49:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 31 and terminates at folio 32, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 11-158; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum is a report by the Political Department, India Office, dated 30 January 1918, concerning British engagements as to the future status of Mesopotamia. It is divided into two sections containing extracts from various correspondence and sources. The first section concerns pledges made to local Arabs, for example, the Arab chiefs in the Persian Gulf and the peoples of Basra and Baghdad between 1914 and 1918. The second section concerns pledges made to King Husain [Ḥusayn bin ‘Alī al-Hāshimī], King of Hijaz, between 1915 and 1918.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Hejaz</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002a4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>