<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00017a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:10:46.523Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. No- 684-S of 1936. ^Pp.9 dfo, ' © I The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, C/0 The Postalster, KARACHI. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document with the request that he will ma|fe discreet enquiries for a suitable house. A spare copy of this Printed Letter and of its enclosure# has been sent to the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. r- Description of Enclosure.Copy. No. I* • 133 -a/S 6. ?rom - the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, ro - The Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf*- Dated Simla, the 7th August,1936. Subject:- Provision of accommodation for the staff of the Political Resident when on tour at Bahrain. f ^ ' Sir, tfith reference to your letter !To.c/69, dated the 19th June 1936, I am directed to c 0 nvey the sanction of the Government of India to private quarters being leased at Bahrain, for a period of one year in the first insta.nce, for the accommodation of the staff that accompanies you on tour, at a rent of Rs.70/- per mensem, and to their being furnished at a coot of R 3 . 60 O/-. The expenditure should be debited to the office allowance grant of the Bushire Reaisency and met from within the sanctioned budget ^rant for the current year. I have the honour t 0 be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd. G.K.S.Sarma. Under Secretary to the Government of India.GoaTidfcnti&amp;l* KQ«llo»635-3 , The aeaideucy, Euahire, the 18th September 19M* Will yy&gt;4 fciacly refer to my oliioiej. Printed Letter lslo.684-S of todity 1 s date, about a house for the Political hesident*a staff* It seeas to ae just possible that this affords an opportunity for getting for the Assistant Political Agent the house which was built for Kr«H*enggi by Husain Yati»* i ac not however ^now what the present po si tiori is, but you ©igiit consiaer whetner any tiling can be done* Yours sincerely. £d. G. LOCH Captain T.dicAinbothas, I*A*, Political Agent, Bahrain, C/0 The Postawister, &amp;ABACHI. / A spare copy of this letter has been sent to lir*J*B«Howe&amp;, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain*}HHWH H ih) \AJ^^ &gt; TELEGRAM From To No. G.T. CODE. Political Agent, Bahrain at Karachi. Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. 107. Dated and received 23rd September 1936 (at 13.20 hours). * /d^'- Resident’s 684 of 18th September. * m I am informed by Resident that there will be an unexpected demand for houses shortly so take action at once but do not confirm anything until I arrive. - POLITICAL - kf- U=zUc . H-t '» l-A.^ wJU. -«— y**-*- / r- ''Sri &amp; A -\i rfl.Please refer to your demi-official letter of the 18th September 1936 to Hickinbotham on the subject of accommodation at Bahrain for the Political Resident s s taff• I do not think that your suggestion is feasible and I am afraid that it will only lead to complications in the end. The sum of Rs.70/- should be spent on acquiring quarters for my staff* and if a higher rent is required for another house for the Assistant Political Agent this should be put up as a separate quest ion. /\ Could you please let Barduli make the necessary enquiries for quarters for ray staff. Croning is writing to him privately what the requirements are. Lieut.-Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. — .C. ,What is the position regarding the proposed quarters for P.R. f s staff while on tour in Bahrain ? 2. We shd maKe enquiries before P.R. arrives with a view to finding what places are possible and then they xan make the final choice v/hen they are here. 9.11.36 rafn. A.P.A, C The houses available are 1. K.3. ^asaibi^ house 2. Shaikh liustafa’ s house 3. Certain rooms in Kanoo’s building 4. A small house of Ahalil Inayyad. I have arranged with the landlords and agents to keep them vacant until the arrival of the P.R's party v/hen they can see and make their choice please. 9. A. v 7 /-fv, ^ ' l U‘(( I had No* 3 in view: I mentioned it to Mr. Croning when here recently: he did not liice the pic».ce and would prefer not to rent these rooms. Haji Aodul Aziz A1 Bassam or Shaijch Musto».ia oiu Abdullhtif’s agent would be willing to ouild a house to plan; but I have not ap^roacnea them on the suDject. I wrote and told Mr. Croniu fe «.ua sug^esteu the letter 1 s name in a private letter to him.The houses li constructed would oe in the vicinity of my house. ?.A. I thought that there was a small house in the vici dty of A.P.A.’s house , but Mr Stephens things that it is now occupied. I have told him to maAe enquiries. I do not thinK that getting people to build would do , unless they are going to build in any case, as we can give no guarantee beyond at most two or three years. H.M- is making all arrangements, reference tne latest corresporidence from Budiire. The house in the vicinity of A*P#A* f s house is not availaole.Till you T)le*se refer to the corresponaence erair^ with Colonel '^owle’s deini-official letter ’O# 779-3 dated the 28th Octohpr 19,36 on the subject of accoTnmodation at Bahrain for the Political Resident s staff? 2. Croning looked at some houses the otter day and considers as suitable one near the American Mission of which Tassam is the agent and which *-irza J asim Barduli can point out. 'he landlord, however, wants a rental of ^s. l n n/- per mensem and Government have only sanc tioned ^s. 70/- per mensem. It has been suggested that it might be possible to make up the deficit of Rs. 30/- per mensem by some arrangement whereby one of the 'Bah rain Agency clerks should rent a portion of the house, and T am to enouire whether you think such an arrange ment nracticable. Tieut-Colonel Gordon foch, O.T.G., Political Agent, ■8 A F P A I IT. / j k ■lv U.O. No. 23~18/1% The mth January 1037. • » fill you ilonso ^o£t?r to your demi-official letter No. 2632-33/113 dated ’.he 24th Doconber 1936. 3. Colonel Loch dorIren ^e to any that none of the Agency clerical otnff are v/lllin * to rent a portion of the house. An an altemotive hov/ever il hrs been suvgented that the 3-hr a in Snorts Club, rfilch for some time has been const derinr the r-ntlu* of suitable olace for a ’Onu ioiso , mny be or . c J to trbe over a portion of the house* The Club is not in a position to pay more than a monthly mnt of b.10/- mid should you consider it prac .ica )le to rent a portito* of the house to tho Club it will be ncces.-ry for us to try me persuade the landlord to acc pt a rent o:° :.ot one thah b.bf/- par onth* ^ • ol1 &lt;W lot oe km* whether you would li*e un^ondeavour to ' ’ -&gt;• nt with the landlord on the above lines. 0 * ^ Just por.oiblo 'o at, when final sanction has been accorded .o the A *ency Office Haor anient ion .ichame, the extrn clorh will bo ;lai to solve the accbmnodation problem by tnklnv over a portion of the house. E?Jor C.C.L. %an, secretary to th • • j Honourable the Political ^nxaent .ul: BklchilHrr 0 . 3o3 ^iCc - Dated / 3 ‘Fe'bruary 1937 Please refer to Stewart # s demi-official letter No.£23-18/12, dated the 2Sth January 1937 of a portion of the house to the Bahrain Sports Club for a monthly rental of Rs.15/-. The 'balance of Jh#85/- will he paid 'by this office* 3. ^ould you kindly close with the landlord and lease the house and inform us when this has 'been done. 2. Colonel Towle authorises the suh-letting Tieut-Colonel C.Loch, C.I.B., Political Agent, Bahrain•H ou s eforP. R. * a Staff I aa^ Baasam soon after our arrival here and had arranged to ive him a list of the repairs required. Before P.R. left for Delhi, however, he left for the mainland to bring hi a family. He ia expected back ahortly, and matters will have to await his return. which is being built only a couple of hundred yards from the Agency and will be ready for occupation in May, that of Shaikh Mustapha. It is to have water laid on and flush closets and is generally more auitacle than Bassam's house. I saw the Agent, Shaikh Ishak, a Persian. He wanted a rental of Rs.100/- per mensem with fans and fly-proofing, but later agreed to let us have it without fans but with fly-proofing at Rs.75/- per mensem. 1 was on the point of closing with him and had prepared the draft lease attached (leaving the rental blank as 7 hoped to bring him down to Rs.70/- per mensem, the limit sanctioned by Government) when he stuck out for Rs.75/- with neither fans nor f ly-pro of ing. 3. when refinery construction is completed in July or so the services of a large proportion of the present Bahrain Petroleum Company staff will be dispensed with, rentals are expected to fall, and we snail b e in a better position to bargain. Further, there is not likely to be ar\y difficulty in arranging accommodation for ourselves privately during this summer. I have therefore let matters lie. i 4. I «un leaving a copy of this note at Bahrain, and we can close with Shaikh Ishak any t ime that he shows 2 In the meantime I have also seen another house himself more accommodating. Time is in our favour as it is /is not likely that the house without fans and fly-proofin&lt; will be taken for Rs.757- pay Rs.lo/- per mensem for the use or a room on me ground flior of Shaikh Mustapha*s house, so that at the worst we can go up to Rs.85/- per mensem without exceeding the sanctioned rental. I do not think, however, that it is advisable to make any advance at present in our offer to the landlord. 5. The Bahrain sports Club are still prepared to pay Rs.lS/- per mensem for the use of a room on the Bahrain. 19/3/3®.iiwh 11 DRAFT LEASE. ' !• . • ••••••• on c 6 n 3 .lt oi ( nereinafter called the Lessor ), agree to rent Lessor’s house situated at •••••••••••••••• Manama, Bahrain, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gull' [ herein- -after called the Lessee ), for a period of one year on the following terms. The rental shall be Rupees . • per month, to be paid after the close of each English calendar month. 2. The lease shall run from the date on which the house shall be completed and fully ready for occupation to the satisfaction of the Lessee.Telegram From To No. 205. Dated 29th May 1937. G.T.C. Political Agent, Political Resident Bahrain. , Bushire. Following for Croning from Stephens My landlord after much persuasion accepts rental of seventy a month. He will put in two extra ceiling fans and trap with gas escape in water closet but refuses to fly proof place on grounds of cost and necessity for annual renewal. He agrees to terms of draft lease. Barduli was present. Political4 . A care-taker will be required. Mohammad, at British Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, the &amp;bth May 1957. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memoranaum . 1 Subject : Accomodation for P.R’s staff when on tour in Bahrain. In view of Mr Stephe ’F probable transfer ne was asked by Mr Croning to try and arrange witn his landlord (Bassam) for a lease of the iiouse occupied by him(Stephens) 2. The following were the requirements:- (a) Complete fine mesh fly proofing. (b) Two additional ceiling fans, and ^c) Water trap U bends in both bath rooms in the horizontal drain pipes leading to the vertical drain pipes flowing into the simc: separate air vent for simc. 5. It is understood that Bassam wants Rs 80/- per mensem, which may be paid in the last resort, but please make every effort to secure the house witnin the sanctioned rental of Rs 70/-. A lease on the lines of the draft left at Bahrain on 19th March 1957 by Mr Croning could be entered into.who is a suitable at present in Mr StepherjA ^ employ^ individual and is prepared to work on Rs 15/- per mensem, may be engaged. It would be convenient if one key of the i house could be kept by Mr hajagopal, who lives next door ! and could occasionally inspect it. Sd. T.C, Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. AUi ^I hD. for ^Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.i4 Ho. I 0-^^ of 1937. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire, 29thMay 1937 • '1 ✓ To The Political Agent, Bahrain. ?«vTORANDIM. Accomodation for Political Resident's staff when on tour in Bahrain. Your telegram No 1 . 206 dated 29th May 1937. Please close with landlord on terms mentioned* my memorandum No. 990, dated 26th May 1937, may be treated as modified accordingly. 3# ? he h ° u se is already partly fly-proofed. Please instruct P.W.D. Overseer to complete the flyproofing with fine mesh copper gnaze. Sd/- T.C.Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for ecretary to the Politica Resident in the Persian Gulf.\ w 1 If i k.Y.k Reference corner wire gat**® to doors and windows of P.Rs staff quarter Locally 52 Running feet of wire gau*e is available t and it costs Es52/-at 1/ per running foot(Very dear) The quantity available will only be sufficient for 8 doors or windows*I propose if rates approved*that 5 dpprs anafl 2 rotary windows in upstairs and 1 door in downstairs»may be provided with wire gauze. Estimate is submitted for orders please. ^efficient quantity of wire gauze of 16 mesh 2 Rolls of 100 fept, 1 on^, and 3 vide will he required to complete the work*and there will he an excess of quantity of about 5C feet as half a fl ©11 cannot oe purchasd. I think I .A* - has oraered for some Conner wire gauze from London,if he spares some, there will be savings in the estimate If he cannot spare,necessary quantity may please be ordered from India• . AS' •N.■» . -mm*. 1% S^/sVlS. a?tea the S 4 -^ ray, 1937 (received tiere or 8th Jure). 2« T he fittirg of wire gauze screers to 13 doors ard 11 wirdows Is approved hut the estimate of the supervisor is corsidered high. 3* Actual rates are rot available hut sirce copper gauze car he purchased ir fuscat at arras 8 per rurrirg foot it is thought that a reasorahle figure would he, say, arras 10 for B a hrair. It is requested that the supervisor may he irstructed to malce every effort to keep costs as low as possible. 4* 'The work or items marked 0 ard D ir the / estimates, (fittirg copper gauze to rotatirg wirdows ard the mair ertrarce) should rot he carried out.No. r^/2..- 18/12 Political Agency, Bahrain,the 12th April 1938 To Mr. D. J. Stephens C/o Mrs. A. Chatterton, ' Silver Lea rt Ootacamund, Niligiris, South India. Memoranchirfl Reference your letter dated the 5th April 1938. There is no objection to your staying in the Political Resident’s Staff House for a short time. [ui n for Political Agent, Bahrain.— 3 Copy of letteiA^dated %he Vth August 1939 from Abdulaziz Alibassam, Bahraip to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 'I most humbly beg to state that fis. 840/-, the rent of my house (occupied by you for the Hon’ble Resident) is due for 12 months from 16th June 1938 to 15th June 1939 @ Rs. 70/- per month. I shall be gald to receive the payment at your convenience'* • Original sent to the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, under P.L.No. 1404-18/12 dated the 9th August 1939 for favour of necesiarv action. / » A % t * * .Ho. /£2y_27/l2 British Consulate-General, Bush ire September 9 th, 1939. ^2# ■Po, The Political Agent, Bahrain. 1 / Memorandum . Reference your printed letter No.l408/lfi/l2 dated ir ^ 1 11 '*— . .n r the 16th August, 1939. A supply Bill for Rs.840/- corering the rent for the period from 16th June i938 to 15th June 1939, is enclosed. Receipt of the amount may please Be acknowledged. By Order, . s for Secr**ary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.No. if 1^-18/12 Political Agency, Bahrain, September 13, 1939. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum . The Supply Bill for ^840/-forwarded with your memorandum No.1224-27/12 dated the 9th September 1939 has been received. for Political Agent, BahrainCopy Bahrain• Batscl 4*6*40« Political Agent, Bahrain. Respected Sir, The under mentioned is the bill for the house rented to you and we shall be gldd to receive the payment at your earliest convenience. Rupees Eight hundred and forty only. Thanking you in anticipation. He beg to remain. Sir, Your most obedient servant Sd/- Abdul Aziz Ali A1 Bassam. Copy sent to the Secy: to P.R. under P.L. No.1111-18/12 dated 9-6-40, for favour of necessary action. To rent of the house from 16th June 1939 to 16th June 1940 @ Rs.70/- per month fa.840- 0-0No. ^^7 - 27 /l 2 - Dated the 1st July 1940. MEMORANDUM Reference your printed letter No.1111-18/12 II (S' dated the 9 th June 1940. 2. A supply bill for Rs. 840/- covering the rent for the period from 16th June 1959 to 15th June 1940, is enclosed. Receipt of the amount may please be acknowledged. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfNo.1307-18/12 Politico! Agency| Bahrain. 9th Julyf 1940. To The Secretary to the IIon , blc the Political Heaident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . Memorand um. - ■ i The Sup ly Bill for fc.84u/- for^arTed vsith \ our iv'emoranduiD iio • 367-27/12 date! the 1st July 10-10 has been received. /^Aliv for Political Agent, L 'laptain, Bahrain. sNo. G /147 of 1941 . The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents compliments to The Political ^ent, Bahrain, his and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document with a request that rental after July 1941 may be paid to lessor monthly and debited to the Residency account. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, Bahrain. Dated 2Ctil March &gt; 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Agreement dated the 20th j^ar al Moayed, Bahrain, and General, Bushi dh 1941 between Yusuf Khalil r.J.Croning,British Consulate re.No.78/60 The undermentioned is the bill for the rent of the house and we shall be glad to receive the payment at your earliest convenience. To rent of the house for 12 months from 16th June 1940 to 15th June 1941, @ Rs.70/- per month ••• Rs. 840-0-0 Rupees eight hundred and forty only. Thanking you in anticipation. We remain Yours faithfully, Sd/- Abdulaziz al Bassami / l J 0 653-18/12 No. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Secretary to the Hon ble the Political Heailert in the Persian ^ulf* f Pns hire &gt; in original and has the honour to send him a copy* of the undermentioned document ( s ’) favour of necessary action* The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. \ &gt; ^ , hth.Anrii, 1941. Dated 1 - Reference to previous correspondence: This Agency P.L. No.1111-18/12 datea the 9th June, 1940. Description dj Enclosure. Name and Date. Latter No.78/60 dated the 2nd Ba s nam, Bahrain, to the Poli Subject. April, 1941 j from Ahdulaziz al ical Ag^nt, %hrain*I ,Ar * TT • ■ *' • - f I ABDULAZIZ ALI BASSAM. TELEGRAMS: '’ABDULAZIZ' BAHREIN. 100/60 H.B.M’S Political Agent Bahrain«, Respected sir. j jJ' * C* I Bahrain, Bated 19o5,41 4J) &gt; J 0 W- We beg to remind you of our bill sent to you on 2nd jqslxiX april 1941 regarding the rent of the house for 12 months from 16th June 1940 to Ibth June 1941, and shall be glad to receive the payment at your earliest convinience. Thanking you in anticipation. We remein Yours faithfully. * /0 , REMINDER. Frcrr THE POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrain. No 958-18/12 To The Secretary to tlie Hon * ble the Pplliic&amp;l. Resident # in the Pers ia n Gulf, Buehire. Bahrain, dated 21at Hay, 194 1. / /// # MEMORANDUM. f) if C ' Printed I have to draw your early attention to this oliiceXetter No. 653 — 18/12 dated 8th A P rll » 194 i regarding rent of ^at Houee to request that its reply may be expedited. an i for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. 13 0^-27/12 The Secretary to the Hon’blfe the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tne Political Agent, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him Hriwpy of the undermentioned document^. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated tne “ a y»... ^.41. Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain Printed Letter No.6t&gt;3-la/12, dated the Utn April, 1941. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Kent of P.R* a staff quarters at Bahrain. Draft for lfc.tt40/-No. -27/12 ISH CONSULATE GENERAL ^ BUSHIRE. ^ Vi E'-Wie jf May, 1942. &lt;&lt;•/ From ' r'l :—^ The Secretary to the Horrble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Political Agent, Bahrain xbbncxik, MEMORANDUM. Moharaed Caretaker of the Residency staff resthouse at Bahrain may please be paid at the living allowance with effect from the 1st May, 1942 for the duration of the War. Bushire To rate of Rs. 20 /- p.ra. pay and Rs. 2 /-p.m. cost of By order Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No. 570-27/12 The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him 0 copy of the undermentioned documentor British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. A ^ Dated ..th^ JVfey.j.. 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain endorsement No.773-18/12, dated the 27th April,1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Draft for Rs.840. • v Subject. Rent of. P.R f s staff quarters at Bahrain.No.(,tJ -27/12. 4 \ BRITISH COHSOLATE GENERAL BUSHIRE. i ^4 - The ^ ^ June 1942. The Political Agent, Bahrain. / ^ J Zr** ... \ \ MEMORANDUM. o 2 J j r &lt;rb v&gt; .?*, PERS\^V A Please pay a sum of Rs.60/- to Yousuf Bin Khalil Almoayyed being the rent of our servants* quarters for the 6 months ending 30th April 1942, by debit to our unofficial account. By order, Secretary to the Political Resident in'the Persian Gulf.DUPLICATE 3FCETPT . Received from the Political Jigent, Bahrein, Re.60/- (Rupees eixty only) being the rent of the Hon’ble the Political Resident f e eervante quartered for the six months ended 50th April,1942. Sd.Youeuf bin Ahalil Almoayyed Bahrain. lh e/3 &amp; ' jTune, 19&lt;±2 &gt;&lt;I 1 — /No.882-27/12. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire. 26th May 1943. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your endorsement No.956-18/12 dated the 8 th May 1943. 2. I enclose herewith Reserve Bank ftwYgnrwmBrwir draft for Rs.840/- in your favour, receipt of which kindly acknowledge. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.COPY YOUSUF BIN KHALIL ALMOAYYED BAHRAIN i2x No. ' 1224 Dated 3.3.44 Political Resident Bushire. Through Political Agent, Bahrain. House rent: Being the rent of our House which are the resident of the P.R. Servants here, from the first of July 1S43 to the aid of January 1544 is seven month at Rs. 10/- a Month. Rs.70-0-0 Seventy rupees only. Sd. Y.k. Almoayyed.(T 1 Copy of bill elated the 16th*May 1944, from nr. Abdul Aziz All Basaam, *i 3 ahrain, to His Britannic Majesty's political Agent, Dahra in. His Britannic Majesty's Political agent rent of the house from 16th June 1943 to 15th June 1944 @ itf. 70/- per months. 840/- Kupees eight hundred and forty only. Forwarded in original to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Politcal resident in the Persaan Gulf, Bushire, for necessary action. To the undersigned. To Bahrain Dated the 16th May 1944 (3d) Abdul Aziz Ali Bassam NO.'-O'? -18/1^ POLITICAL ACiT’CV' BAHRAIN. The £ ^tZllay 194^1 i ■ for Political ^gent^ Bahi-*ain « /7c/? ^ $h. British Consulate-General, Bushire, June, 1944. The Political Agent, Bahrain. M emorandum It is requested that the attached hill for . Es.50/- representing the rent of servants quarters for the period 1st february to 30th June, 1944, may kindly be paid by debit to the Bushire account. SecrcVCary to the -olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf.The Caretaker of the Residency Resthouse, Mohammed, has represented that he cannot live on his pay which is only Rs.20/- plus Rs.8/- deaaness allowance. 2. He also begs that he may be allowed the privilege of purchasing rations issued by the Agency to its menials• 3. Mohammed has served us well, knows the routine, and would be impossible to replace even at twice his present wage. He is forced to supplement his pay by odd jobs, which is undesirable. 4. I recommend that with effect from 1st November he should be given at least Rs.40/-, which is Rs.5/- less than it is proposed to give the most junior Agency farrash, and, if P.A. sees no objection, that he may be brought on the Agency ration list. pay and dearness allowance, so as to permit oi reduction, if necessary, later, the Rs.40/- should be split up into P a Y Rs.25/- and dearness allowance Rs.15/-. 8-11-44 Have you any objection 'Co 'A n ? 9/11. P.A.(Bahrain) Itd.T.H 9/11 Ita. G.P 9/11 In order to split up the increase between 12-11-44!** GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. ELECTRIC SUPPLY DEPARTMENT. STATE ENGINEER * S DEPARTMENT No. PA/ 9$/ 64 \J f-CC (2.NT &amp; ’ 7/ % ox H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: BAHRAIN. 7th January, 1945 Dated: 22nd Moharram,1364 In accordance with a telephone message received from the Agency, we inspected the wiring at the Agency Rest House and found it to he defective, causing leakage. It is observed that this leakage is causing loss of power, and as this loss is being registered on the meter, we would advise you to repair it at once. The Bahrain Government is not responsible for loss of power due to leakage in circuits. We should be pleased to do the necessary repairs if you wish us to do so. Vv State E&amp;gDiear, Government of Bahrain. H. P. Cj. LfclCiH. s .£ Cony of bill dated the 6th March, 1945 from Mr.Y.K. Almoayyad, Manama, Bahrain. ' © Rent of my house which the servants are living in from Jul%y 1944 to the errl of February, 1945 (eight months) Rs.10/- Rs ^ ao/ permonth (Ruoees eighty only) No .^13/12 Political Agency, Bahrain^ The 7th March, 1945. Forwarded in original to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for necessary action. % % for Political Agent, Bahrain,-— , No.1300-27/12. British Residency and (Jonsula te-General, Bus hire. Bated the 17th March 1945, To The Political Agent, Bahrain. ft Meraorandum, pePererice your endorsement No. 892-18/12 dated the 7th March 1945, 2. It is requested that a, sum of E . 80/- (eighty) may he paid, hy dehit to the .Residency account, to Yusuf* Khalil al. Moayyed, Bahrain, on account oP rent Prom July 1944 to Aehruary 1945 inclusive. / MA.7 ? Wo.2717-18/12 Poiiticul Agancy, Bahrain, The 1st July, 1945. To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandu m Reference correspondence ending vr.ith your memorcindum No.AB.638-3/6 dated the 22nd June, 1944 on the subject of the rent of the Resthouse. rent of the house for the period from 16th June 1944 to 15th June, 1945 is enclosed. I shall,be glad to know if the amount Con be paid by debit to the Bushire account. 3. The landlord has increased the rent by 10$ rtith effect from the termination of the last annual lease and this increase is permitted under the local rent la.v. 4 4 . I enclose a form of lease in duplicate for signature and return of one copy to me. 2. A bill In original for !?$.840/- representing for Political Agent, Bahrain. C.No. 3P92 - 58/17. BIiITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. the 14th August, 1S45. To The Political Agent Bahrain .• MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No. 2717 - 18/12 dated the 1st July, 1945. 2. The sum of P 840/- representing the rent of the- RestHouse for the period ended 14th June, 1945, may please be paid by debit to •Bushire account. The bill is returned herewith. 3. One copy of the lease duly signed by me is also returned herewith. for Secretary to :ical Resident in the Persian Gulf.L E A S K. Haji Abdulaziz Ali A1 Bassara (hereinafter called the Lessor) 9 agree to rent my house situated in Av/azi quarter in Manama Bahrain to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (hereinafter called the Lessee on the following terms). 1. The period for lease shall be for one year only. 2*. The rent shall be Rs*77/- per month to be paid after the close of each English Calendar month* 3* Lessor undertakes to' maintain the building in a state of good repair and to cany out at his own expences such necessary repairs. 4* The lease shall commence from 16th June 1945 equivalent to 6 th Raj ab 1364. Sd. Abdulaziz Ali al Bassam. Lessor. Sd. T.E. Rogers, for and on behalf of Lessee.mmgE ' $ m^l Manama Municipality, Bahrain. No.125/23/1364. 3rd Dil Hijjah 1364 (8-11-45) To ^ The ,Political Agent, Bahrain. ■ . . '■ ' • ' ' i Municipal tax on house No.780, occupied by the clerks of the Political Resident (house belonging to Abdul-Aziz al-Ali al-Bassam) for 12 months - from Muharram to the end of- Dil Hiijah 1364 with a rent of Rs.70/- per month. Rs.-52-8-0 — — — — — — . — — ** • - ——— N °• 67) /0“iV 12 ^ Political Agency, Bahrain, 1 ^ The 6th December, 1945. Forwarded to the Secretary to the iion’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for favour of necessary action.Bill dated 2nd January, 194-6 from Mr.Y.K. Almoayyed, Bahrain. (^) Political Agent, Bahrain. Being the rent of our house which the P.R*s servants are. living from 1st March 194-5 to the end of Decernber '5 (ten months) at the rate of Rs.lO/.per Rupees one hundred only Sd.Y.K. Almoayyad. No. |27- 18/12 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 9th January, 194-6. Forwarded in original to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire for favour of necessary action. J for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. 279 - 18/12 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 24th January 1946 To The Manana Municipality, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your municipal tax 23/1364, dated the 3rd Dil Hijjah 1364 house No. 78G for Rs. 52/8/-. 2. I enclose herewith Rs. 52/8/ two and annas eight only) Kindly acknowledge receipt. bill No. 125/ (8-11-1945) for (Rupees fifty for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN■ C“-w . , Translation of letter lio.201/3/1364, dated 29th January 1946 from Manama Municipality, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. t\ • O • I have received your letter Po.12/18-279, t dated 24th January 1946 enclosing the sun of Rs.52/8/- being the Municipal tax for House Ho.780 until the end of Dil Hijjah 1364. I have the honour to attach herewith a receipt for the amount. U.E. aEC^IPT . 1,0.729. Received from the^Pplatical Agent, Bahrain the sum of Rs.52/8/- being tax on house Mo.780 for 12 months ending .oil Hijjah 64 as per Bill il0.125/23/64. Jated 25th Safar 1365. ifi&gt;No. 509 - 58/17 BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. the 30th January, 1946 Reference your endorsement No. 127 - 18/12 dated the 9th January, 1946. 2. It is requested that a sum of Ks 100/- may be paid, by debit to Residency account, to Yousuf bin Khalil Al Moayyed on account of rent from 1st March, 1945, to the end of December,: No. 1177 - 18/12. To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 16th April 194&lt;? 1 7 V J The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. iv'IEMORANDUM Reference correspondence ending with your memorandum No. 3392 - 58/17, dated the 14th August 1945. 2. A bill in original for Rs.924/- representing rent of the Resthouse for the period from 16th June 1945 to l6th June 1946 is enclosed. I shall be grateful for authorisation of payment from the Bushire Residency Account. for POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KMS/ Ho. 4/1- / f J”'- Bushire, 8th May, 19£6* From - The Executive Engineer, Ind. Persian Gulf Sub-Divn., Bushire. v^TvAcxiJi' j I have the honour to forward herewith a Bank Draft No• 28/578810 dated the 7th May 1946 for R&gt;. 900/- in lieu of payment made by you to the Supervisor, Bahrain, for repairs to Rest House. If the payment has not since been made by you, this amount may now please be given to him to enable him to carry out the repairs as early as possible. To The Political ngei Bahrai n. Bahrai n IS ipt n -S' &lt;&lt;£ Sir In continuation of telegram No. E/77 I have the honour to be, Sir, . Your most obedient servant Enclosure: Draft. Executive Engineer, Tnd. Persian Gulf Sub-DivisionDa^ 7 Hh ^\s No. 1904-58/17. fP BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. Dated the 13th May, 1946 To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. ( &amp; Memorandum . Reference your memorandum No. 1177-18/12, dated the 16th April, 1946. 2. The sum of Rs. 924/- representing the rent of the Rest House for the period ended 15th June, 1946 may please be paid by debit to Bushire Account. ===== The bill is returned herewith. 7&lt;~ for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. /«• &gt; ' i «- S DtV. ' SARRiA *No. 2-1 IT) -18/12 POLITICAL AGfiNOr, BAHRAIN. The 29th June, 1947 3&gt;o^ To The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain* MEMORANDUM* . Reference your printed letter No* 1386- 68/17 dated the 14th June, 1947. 2, Strictly speaking there is no lease for this house at present, a^&gt; the original agree* ment executed in March 1941, tenable for a period of one year from 1st February 1941 to 31st March 1942, was never formally renewed, though the land - lord accepted rent for the house all these years. The landlord is within his rights in asking for an assessment of the rent by the Assessment Commit tee, who in the present conditions prevailing in Bahrain are sure to evaluate the rent at a figure Konsi- derably higher than Rs. 10/- par month* Sd. C. J. PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain Attested,' Superintendent, Political Agency, BahrainNo. 18/12 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The y July, 1947. To :a 3 The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM . S'- &gt;&lt; ^ S' Reference your memorandum No. 1904-58/17 dated the 13th May 1946. 2. A bill in original for Rs. 1016-4-0, rep resenting the rent of the Rest House, for the period from 16th June 1946 to 16th June 1947 is enclosed, for settlement. The increase of 10# in the rent is allowed by the 'Law of Rents and Leases” promulgated by the Bahrain Government. , Attested SD. C.J. PHLLY.. Political Agent, Bahrain. indent. - . .cajBBS ‘ - Translation of letter No.225/3/1367, dated the 10th February, 1948, from Mananah Municipality to the Political Agent, Bahrain. on the 24th Ramadhan, 1366 (10th August, 1948) this office submitted bill No.35/23/1366 for Rs.337/ 5/- on account of Municipal taxes on some of the buildings rented by you, but so far the amount of the bill has not been paid or any reply from Your Excellency been received. Hence this reminder to you. After Compliments, I beg to inform Your Kxcellency that Usual Endingwmm*m \' Translation of letter No.254/3/1367, dated the 22nd February, 1948, from Manmah Municipality to the F.&gt;itfT7B#hrain. After Compliments, 9 With reference to Your Excellency’s letter .57-18/12, dated the 15th February* 1948, I have the honour to enclose herewith a copy of our bill No.35/23/1366, dated the 24th Ramadhan, 1366. Usual Ending.No.809-18/12 political agency, BAHRAIN• The 13th U^rch, 1948. To Public Relations Office, Bahrain. Mcmorindum v Municipal tax amounting to Rs. 19 /“ is payabl.e to the Manama Municipality for the g-ira^e occupied by the Public ^ Relations Office truck from Muharrau 136- (16.12.44) to end of 1946. It is requested that this amount be sent to me as e«rly as possible for payment to the Municipality. 2. Tax from 1st January, 1947, is paid by this office. % for Political Agent,Bahrain. IMk(S) POLITICAL AGLNCX, B Aiffi AIN. No.810-18/12 The 13th iiarch, 1948. — &gt; v , ** rT '*s u *- &lt;w To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, Me mo rand urn Municipal ’taxes amounting to Rs.217-8-0 are payable to the Manama Municipality, as detailno below, on account of the two houses rented by the Residency: a) Tax for house No,730 (owner Abdul Aziz Al-B*ssani-Residency Rest House) for 24 months from Muharram .366 (6.12,45) to the end of Dhul Haj 1366 (13.11.47) computed on rent at Rs.70/-p.m. Rs#157-8-0 b) Balance of tax for same house for year 1364 according to their bill No.125/23/64 c) Tax for house No.377 (owner Khalil bin Ibrahim Mu'ayyad -Residency serv«*itt f s quarter* for 33 months from Muharram 1364 (16.11.44) to end of Dhul Haj ja 1366 (13.11.47) computed on rent Rs.120/- a year. Total Rs. 2. It is requested that this amount may either be sent to this office or paid direct to the Municipality. 26-4-0 33-12-0 217- 8-0Translation of letter No.474/3/1367, dated the 5th April, 1948, from the Manmah Municipality^ to the Political A^ent, Bahrain. 0* ^ V* * After Compliments, .1 have received with thanks your letter No.107-18/12, dated the 1st April, enclosing No.526252, for R?.241/8/- (two hundred and forty- one and annas eight) only in settlement of the Municipality’s bill No.35/23/1366. I enclose herewit four receipts to cover this amount. Usual Ending.No.R.24-18/12 political agcncy; BAHRAIN, The 6 th iday, 1948 The undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident 3n the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, for necessary action. Bill No.43/23/1367 dated the 13th April 1948 from the Secretary to the Manamah Municipality, Bahrain For Political Agent, Bahrain SM°No. R. 49.13/12 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN 9 The 12th May 1948 Th&lt;a undermentioned paper Is forwarded to The Secretary to His Kxcelleney the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, for direct payment. 4 . For Political Agent, Bahrain. Bill dated the 3th May 1948 from Abdulaziz Ali Bassam, BahrainDear Agency, The Foreign Office have approved the payment from public funds of the rent and municipal tax of the'Rest House” during its occupation by a member of the .Agency or Pesidency staff. Occupational charges such as electric light, cleaning, etc. are, however, the concern of the occupant and are not payable by the Foreign Office. We understand that the house was first occupied under the Foreign Office by Alyer on July 4th, 1948, and subsequently by Rahman who is still in occupation. The rent and tax would, therefore, be payable by the Foreign Office as from that date. The present rent of the house is fis 1,117 p.a. and the municipal tax Rs 78-12 p.a. making a total of Hs 1,195-12 p.a. or £ 90-3-7. As it has been in continuous occupation by a member of your staff, we should be glad if you would pay these charges • from your Foreign Office account when they fall ] due. Yours ever. Pesidency Bahrain cMl ■hi / if ^ - (6VHV49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 28th July, 1949. .v \A Dear Agency, Please refer to your letter R 211/18/12 of May 2nd about the 10$ increase in rent. We enclose a copy of F.O. letter XA01/ 34K2(34/49) on the subject. Presumably you will take action direct on the second para graph. Yours ever,XA01/34K2(34/49) COPY FOREIGN OFFICE, LONDON, S.W.1. 22nd June, 1949. Dear Residency, Please refer to your letter 61/77/49 of the 30th May about the rent of the rest house. We give you covering approval for the increase of 10% in the rent admissible under Bahrain law. We should be glad to know in due course the effective date and whether the amount of municipal tax is affected. Yours 'ever, ESTABLISHMENT i&gt;ND ORGANISATION DEPT. Residency, BAHaR&amp;IN.•» r j h % Translation of bill No.57/23/68 dated thel4th September, 1949, from the Manamah Munidicpality Bahrain to H.b.M's Political 4gent, Bahrain. Municipal tax on house No.414 (occupied by Mr.Hafiz) 168-12-C ' for 18 months from Rajah 1367 till the end^of Thilhaj,1368 according to the monthly rent of Rs . 100/- g - „ y g 2 Ji. - ' * ' ^9 Municipal tax on house No.746 (property of Abdul- 39- 6-0• / Aziz ali Albassam) and occupied by Mr. Abdulrahman, for six months from Rajab till the end of Thilhaj, 1367 , according to the monthly rent of Rs.70/-. , Municipal tax on the'same house for 12 months 86-10 -0 from Moharram till the end of Xhelhaj,1368, 294 -12- 0 according to the monthly rent of Rs.77/-. £ - //- vy js 3l- y ^ (Total - Rupees two hundred and ninety four and annas twelve only)Ko.s Sfy- S' of 1369 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 1st Dulhaj, 1369 September 14, 1950. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum I forward herewith a hill from the Manama Municipality for Rs. 493/14/- for municipal tax on two houses occupied by your staff, as follows House occupied by the Judicial Assistant - from Rajab 1367 to end of Bilbao 1369 - 30 months. (Tax assessed at rental of Rs. 100/- per month) Rs. 281. 4.- House occupied by your Office Superintendent from Rajah 1367 to Dilhaj 1367 - 6 months. (Tax assessed at a rental of Rs. 70/- per month) 39. 6.- Tax - on above from 1st Muharram 1368 till end of year 1369 - 24 months. - (Tax assessed at a rental of Rs. 77/- per month) 173. 4, - Rs.493.14.- As the financial year of the Municipality closes at the end of this (Arabic) year (one month from today) and as the Municipality is anxious to collect all arrears before end of the year, i request you to kindly arrange this account to be settled. Adviser to the Government.* % • ' ' v &gt; ,v ; . ‘'v 1 DEPT. BRANCH. I £^j l “L . Section. File No. Heading. NOTES. Prog. 19 ; Nos. Serial No. Subject. Accommodation i'o~ the staff of the Honourable the Political Itesident when on tour at Bahrain• Notes and Orders.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00017a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1643</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00017a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1643</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 18/12 'Accommodation for the Staff of the Hon'ble the Political Resident when on Tour at Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-24T22:30:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (141 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 143; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-94; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding the rental of residential properties in Bahrain for the use of the staff of the Political Resident while on tour in the country. The correspondence is between officials at the Political Residency in Bushire, the Political Agency in Bahrain, the Manama Municipality, the Bahrain Public Works Department and two Bahraini property owners (Abdul Aziz al Ali al Bassam and Yusuf Khalil al Moayed). Some of this correspondence is in Arabic with English translations. In addition to details concerning the payment of rent and taxes, the correspondence also discusses the refurbishment of a number of properties that were rented. The file also contains copies of lease agreements for these properties. Detailed file notes are found on folios 124-142.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Building leases</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Manamah Municipality</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Rented accommodation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00017a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>