<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000261_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:59.922Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">This Document is the property of the Secirtarj/ of Slate for India. S 13 40 o is A SECRET. B. 239. TERRITORIAL CHANGES. Memorandum by the India Office. —* ;— 7 — (The views of the (Jovernme^ of India will he found in Appendix .4.) 1 . The question of Turkey in Asia having been otherwise disposed of, India has little direct interest in the conquered* territories. German East Africa is, however, of some indirect concern to her, owing to the trade which exists between that country and Muscat. Before the war there had been a certain tendency among Muscat subjects to acquire the German flag, and there was also evidence of anti-British propaganda emanating from German East Africa. It would seem desirable that this territory should not pass into the hands of any Power (such as Italy) which has ambitions in Arabia. 2. India has, however, some desiderata which it maybe possible to secure by exchanges or compensations among the Allies. 3 . Mr. Thesiger, in despatches Nos. 33 and 34, dated 13th and IGth March 191(j, and Sir IT. McMahon in Despatch No. 112, of 24th May 1916, have called attention to the standing danger caused to the Middle East and the North-West Frontier of India by the French arms trade at Jibuti. In these views Mr. Chamberlain has expressed his concurrence.- lie has pointed out to the Foreign Office (letter No. P. 2416 of 4th July) that “ The Arab policy of “ His Majesty’s Government, if successful, will have greatly stimulated Arab “ race-consciousness, while the rivalries ol various chiefs may lead 40 pro- “ longed internal disturbances, Neither Great Britain nor France will be “ in a position to interfere effectively in the interior of Arabia, though their “ interests on the coast will be adversely affected by unrest there. It should “ therefore be the policy of both Powers to reduce the import of arms to a “ minimum. But though the recently concluded agreement with France “ regarding the future of the Arab State provides for an eventual arrange- “ ment as to the traffic in arms, the geographical conditions of Arabia are “ such as to render any such arrangement ineffective so long as there is an “ entrepot in close proximity, by means of which powerful pm ate interests “ are concerned in exploiting a highly profitable trade to the utmost. Both Sir 11. McMahon and Mr. Thesiger suggested the possibility that by some exchange of territories French Somaliland might pass into British hands, and from the Indian point of view this would be very desiiable. 4 If it were similarlv possible to induce the French to withdraw from the joint declaration of 10th March 1862 respecting the independence of Muscat (Appendix B) it would be advantageous. It is true that alter the extinction of the French arms trade there, the fact that France has the special footing which the declaration affords, has lost some of its importance. But it enables her at any moment to thwart us, &lt;y/., supposing 4 hat it were necessary for us to acquire land for a naval base on Musandim peninsula. It was formerly hoped to buy France entirely out of Muscat in connection with the arms traffic, but the price asked (Gambia) was too high. C ircum- stances may be more favourable now. The territorv of Oman, lying as it does along the Arabian side or the narrow entrance to the Persian Gulf, is of considerable strategic importance- a fact which has recently been emphasised by a German writer, who has laid down the freedom of the Straits of Hormuz as an essential point in the polic\ of the Central Powers if the Bagdad Railway is to attain its full eommeieiaand strategical objects. It is, of course, uncertain what the fate of the Bagdad Railway will be; but it is at least conceivable that if, under the pressure of French capitalists, it is completed, the same French capitalists may make it their business to prevent or nullify any measure on our part that would enable us to block the entrance to the Gulf; and if France still had an equal footing with us in Muscat much friction might thus arise. It may be suggested that by the Anglo-French agreement regarding the Arab State, whereby a French sphere is definitely fixed and recognised France has implicitly disinterested herself in the rest of Arabia. And this consideration would app'y also to Sheikh Said, to which the Government of India refer. See Section 8 below and Appendix C. 5. The question of the French settlements in India forms the subject of a separate memorandum (Appendix D). It is desirable, if possible, to eliminate them altogether. Short of that, to eliminate Chandernagore and the minor loges and settlements in return for a consolidated^ bloc of territory round Pondicherry. The real interest of French politicians in these settlements lies in the fact that they are “rotten boroughs.” &lt;h It is for consideration, whether, if opportunity offers, an attempt should not be made to get lid ol the Portuguese settlements also by offering compensation in Africa. These consist of the territories of Goa (1 ,d 01 square miles; population in 1900, 475,513), Daman (149 square miles; population, 41,071), and Diu (20 square miles ; population, 14,614). They were acquired in the sixteenth century, and undoubtedly have a great sentimental value to Portugal, out ol whose possession they have never passed. Their economic value is less. The estimated revenue of Goa in 1913-14 was a little over 300,000/., and theie vas an estimated surplus of G0,000Z. Imports and exports amounted respectively to 560,855/. and 178,340/., the overwhelming pionoition of the tiade being with British India (imports from Portugal 42,178/.; exports to Portugal, 268/.). The number of ships visiting Marmugao during 1914 was 04, of which 29 were British (78,530 tons) and 27 German ^79,385 tons). y . insecuiit) which is apt to prevail has occasionally been a source of inconvenience to neighbouring British territory (e.g., in 1912); from time to time there aie small frontier difficulties, while excise questions give constant tiou ne. Questions, too, have arisen between the two Governments reoardino telegraphs Thus, in 1012 , the Portuguese Government were negotiating w.tl; the German lelefunken Company for the establishment of wireless stations, to which the Government of India expressed themselves as “unable to agree m.der any circumstances whatever” (telegram of 20th September l.H.j, and it was only after long protracted negotiations (and even so, with a comlmon attached which would make British censorship in war time m 4 e°e SS lhI e t the 4 16 '^^nunent last month were induced to ag.ee that, they would not grant cable landing rights nor authorise the establishment of any wireless telegraph stations without having arrived at a of^TAnglfsuSr W ' th the i! '' itiSh tiovernmPnt (^. Carnegie, No. 199, asvlnmns for ^hT. 7 ! e T ntS , haVe hithe »o g.ven serious trouble t correspondence h tb 10, ! ! = 1 lece ntly there have been cases in whic ,uT' s nbtinp U i SU1 pers0ns seeilis t0 have transmitte • V* r ® 8 ' c| ents in 1 ortuguese territory. If, however we are suoeessfi wi]fZT he?r t hs 'rX h ^ ttle p ne,lt8,it U1 ' St be ex l'ected that anarchist o L .1 it a no , t f f , ;V 0 !‘‘ Ug ' eSe S0I, &gt; Germany may a,tern, jurisiliction^woidd presumablv'disn 1 ] 641114 011 1 ' V ' tb l^rtuguese ierntori! siastical jurisdiction which would in^sllf 3 80 the ' r P!' e P( )stero,,s ecdt Formerly the Crown of Portuoal , 1 .,; f Je no . sm aH advantage to us diction over Roman P-itlmr i c &lt;ll, ^ e d t0 exercise patronage and juris concordat with the Vatican iiMSStT '' 1 ' 1 all&lt; l though by Archl.ishopric and seven Iff.. &amp;8 theSe T ere hlllited to the .Metropolis Homan Catholic bishops in ' auolna (&gt;’ still remains that si b,shops in British India and Native States are nominated b;a foreign Goverument, ami British Indian Roman Catholics are constantly memorialising and asking that they may be removed from foreign jurisdiction (the last memorial is as recent as 18th May hist: Sir II. Howard, No. 41 of T,' ' ', ne •. l | l ' ) - , 1I|IS . 18 ! he m01 'e anomalous in that the Republic of I ortugal is violently anti clerical. • 1 1 . lo return to Arabia Italy was not a party to the Anglo-Russo-Krench agreements regarding the Arab State, and while it is almost certain that she wil object to the allotment of Mersina and Adana to France, it is possible that she u ill also object to Article 10 (of M. Cambon’s note of 9 th May 1916) u iicli is in iact directed against her, and which provides that “ Res „ Houvernenients anglais et fran ? ais . . . se meltront d’accord pour no pas acquem, et ne consentiront pas qu’une tierce Puissance acquiere, do ‘‘ possessions territoriales dans la peninsule arabique on construise une base n a vale dans les lies snr la cote est de la mer Rouge.” And though she may acquiesce in this, she may yet claim a sphere of influence, short of territorial possession, *in the ^ emeu. Italian interests in that district have hc( n t mphasised lately in llie imperialist press, c.g., TSidea ^azioucile, which wrote on 23rd July that the really important matter is to secure the political .oid i conomic influence of Italy m the ^emen, which is an indispensable complement to Piitlnea. and asked il any other Rower could put in counter claims (Sir R. Rodd, No. 231 of 24th July). Our policy, of course, is “Arabia for the Arabs.” We have no counter claims; but we do not recognise anyone else’s claims. The Arabs detest the Italians; and since in the Turco-Italian war, the Italians supported the Idrisi Saiyid of Asir and blockaded the coast of the 'i emen, it is hardly to be supposed that the Imam of Sanaa—the Idrisi's mortal enemy and the dc facto Master of the Yemen — would welcome them. 1 heir intrusion could only be a constant source of dis turbance, and of inconvenience to us at Aden. For this reason, it is desirable if possible to induce them to accept the Anglo-French agreement and to abandon all claims in Arabia and the Red Sea by compensation elsewhere. Possibly French Somaliland—if, as suggested in Section 3 above, the French can be induced to quit it—might be allotted to them. But it would have to be in return for a very binding agreement regarding the arms trallic ; for no purpose will have been served if a French trade is merely to be replaced by an Italian one. 8 . The Government of India discuss the question of Aden at some length, but it is unnecessary to go into it in detail for the present purpose. The only points to which reference need be made are ( 1 ), ( 2 ) and ( 6 ) in their telegram. We have given assurances to the Arabs that we do not intend to make annexations, and we have agreed jointly with the French not to do so—- with the proviso, however, that “ Ceei n’empechera pas telle rectification de “ la frontiere d’Aden qui pourra etre jugee necessaire, par suite de la recente “ agression des Turcs ” (Article 10 of M. Cambon’s note referred to above). This proviso was inserted for two reasons : (a) because it is not certain that the existing frontier divides the tribes in the best possible way ; (b) because we might find it necessary to take over Sheikh Said. This fortified pro montory is within gunshot of our station on Periin Island, which has, in fact, been bombarded from it during the war. We ejected the Turks in December 1911, but allowed them to return, and they have been entrenched there ever since. It may seem desirable, in order to make a repetition impossible, and at the same time to secure Sheikh Said against French claim, to annex the peninsula. The Government of India are content to leave it to the neighbouring Arabs. In that case, we must induce the French formally to withdraw their claim, whether in virtue of the terms of our agreement or by offering them compensation elsewhere. Their claim dates from 1869, when two Frenchmen purchased the place from the local Sheikh for $80,000. The Porte denied the right of the Sheikh to sell, but the French, though they occupied the place for a very short time, have never abandoned their interest in it, and have always evaded recognising it as Turkish territory. In 1893 M. Delonele urged in the Chamber the importance of occupying it; and as recently as November 1914 a company styling itself the “Guest-Asiatiquc Compagnie h.tenmtionale &lt;le 1'Arabie ” claimed to ha '' e ll the rights of the original proprietors. It appeared on enquii\ 1 hat the eomt.anv was not registered, and that its spokesman was ‘of the shadiest character” (Sir F. Bertie, No. 0, 10 th January 19l;&gt;). Nothing moie has been heard of it; but it would seem desirable to set the question at rest once 01 It should he noticed that Shiekh Said is situated in a triangular area, measuring some 550 square miles, having the sea as its base, anil itnme- diatelv adjoining the frontier of the Aden Protectorate, which the 1 urkish Government agreed, after the Aden Delimitation Commission in P.tOo, not to alienate “ de quelque maniere que ce soit.” An instrument conhrimng this ■ oreement was signed on 9th March 1914, and was awaiting ratification when he war broke out (Appendix &lt;J). The ejection of the I urks from Arabia .... i • • a.. wrliir.h mnUpg: it. (psirn.hm th t, a will thus expose'tids'piece of territory—a 'fact which makes it desirable that w© should not tie our hands more tightly than is necessary in this region. 9 Sections 13 and D in the Government of India’s telegram do not directly raise territorial questions, and it is therefore not proposed to deal with them here. But there are two political desiderata as regards Japan which may be mentioned. - , 1 .... .. n , (i) The India Oifice has already urged upon the boreign &lt; dlice the importance of not allowing Japan to establish heisell po itna \ oi commercially in the two Chinese provinces of Szechuan and Tuiman which border on Tibet and India (India Office letter to foreign Office dated 23rd March 1910). If, in return for territorial compensation elsewhere, she could be induced formally to recognise that these two provinces and Tibet itself lie outside her sphere of influence, it would be a great advantage. (ii) It has been suggested that after the war h ranee, having made gicat acquisitions elsewhere, will no longer he able to maintain bei position— already none too strong—in Indo-China, and may be compelled to lelinquish it. Should that at any time happen, it is most important that the province should not pass to Japan. Whether it is possible to pi oa ide againM tlu^ eventuality now, the India Oflice is not in a position to sa\.2E9BES1 APPENDICES. APPENDIX A. Telegram from Government of India to Secretary of State, dated Sth September 1916. Secret. Your telegram of the 21st ultimo. Disposal of captured territory. \Ye are replying fully by despatch as it is difficult to compress our views into a telegram, but following is summary subject to fuller consideration or revision in our despatch. Only captured territories in which India is interested are Iraq and German East Africa. We assume both will be retained. As regards future administration of Iraq there will obviously be important Military, Political and Administrative considerations on which we trust we may be consulted. As regards German East Africa, whatever may be its eventual administration, we trust arrangements to admit of Indian emigration on equitable lines may be made. As regards obsolete treaty rights and territorial readjustments vis-d-vis our allies following are our views :— (A) . France. We strongly recommend negotiations for extinction of territorial rights in India on lines proposed in paragraph 7 of the India Office memorandum dated 20th April 1915 to secure concession indicated. To this end we are prepared further to agree to modification of our extra dition rights as regards political offenders under treaty of 1815. x\s regards Maskat we recommend, if possible, the abrogation of treaty of 1862 on the ground that, as subsequently interpreted, it gives France a position at Maskat and in the Gulf generally which interferes with our prescriptive rights in that region, and that it precludes our acquiring or even leasing territory belonging to Maskat, exempli gratia Gwadur. There seems no need now to ask for amendment of Article II of French commercial treaty with Maskat of 1814, since arms question has been disposed of by French Government’s note of 1911. Opportunity should be taken to infoim 1 icnch Government that His Majesty’s Government have never recognised 1 rench claims in any shape or form in regard to feheikh Said or \\ estern Arabia put forward by the Societe Ouest Asiatique (vide India Office letter 4769/11 of 11th December 1914 to Foreign Office.) Further, we would impress the necessity of some efficient arrangement to pi event Jibuti from becoming centre of arms traffic in lied Sea. (B) . Russia. Our'views have already been put forward in our telegrams of the 19th April, 13th May and 12th June 1915, but we would emphasise following points : — (1) Practical partition of Persia should be avoided as calculated to increase our obligations and responsibilities most seriously. ( 2 ) If spheres of influence are to be re-arranged we need not press too strongly for the line proposed in our telegrams referred to. ( 3 ) We must, however, press most strongly for generous treatment so far as Afghanistan is concerned. ,1) As regards Tibet we adhere to the views contained in the corre spondence ending with our telegram dated 21st May 1915, though here again we should prefer that Russia should be urged to adopt a generous policy. i i i (5) For reasons given in our telegram of^ 11th October 191o, we should avoid raising question of Chinese Turkestan. ( 6 N If Anglo-Russian Agreement of 1907 is to be revised, we trust we shall be allowed to consult Amir regarding any positions affecting Afghanistan before Agreement is concluded. (0). Italv. We should be glad of arrangement which would prevent Italian territory on Bed Sea littoral from affording facilities to arms traffic. It would further be desirable, if possible, to obtain from Italy some assurance that she admits Red Sea Islands and Western and Southern Arabia to be outside her sphere of influence. s 13 B(D). Japan. Though Indian trade and question of internal unrest in India are intimately concerned, we are not, in view of the delicacy o i&lt; situation in a position to formulate any definite suggestions. /* n Turning to Aden, on assumption that Turks will eventually lie hna y ousted from southern Arabia, our views are as follows (l) We should adhere faithfully to our guarantee to Arabs not to extend (21 y s there will presumably be no single power with whom to define W spheres of influence, it will be useless to attempt to define any iresh boundary or protectorate. . (.‘V) Assuming Imam remains neutral we should come to terms \wtfi inm. ( 4 ) We should make such arrangements with other chiefs as aie compatible with (3). ( 5 ) We should freely pardon all chiefs of protectorate, and reaffirm treaties with them. . • ( 6 ) We should leave Sheikh Said in hands of appropriate duels. ( 7 ) Our agreements with Imam, &amp;c., should include a clause precluding them from granting concessions of any kind to foreign powers, or subjects of foreign powers, without our consent. ( 8 ) We should not advocate hereafter placing garrisons in protectorate outside of the Aden settlement. ( 9 ) Hodeida should be left to Imam or other suitable chief. (10) Our policy in hinterland should be one of peaceful penetration. ' All that we really require is to maintain reasonably' friendly relations with our neighbours ol hinterland. 1 resent uai has shown that Aden itself is easily defensible without regard to •hinterland. If, however, there is any idea, which we strongly deprecate, of leaving Turkish enclave in Yemen, our views would require full reconsideration. APPENDIX B. Declaration respecting the Independence of Muscat and Zanzibar, 1^02. 8 a Majeste la Heine du Hoyaume Uni de la Grande Bretagne et de ITrland et Sa Majeste PEmpereur des Fran^ais, prenant en consideration Pimportance qui s’attaclie an maintien de 1 independance du Sultan de Muscat dune part et du Sultan de Zanzibar de Pautre, out juge convenable de s’engager reciproquement a respecter 1 independance de ces deux Princes. Les Soussignes, Ambassadeur extraordinaire et pienipotentiaire de Sa Majeste Britannique, pres la cour de France, et Ministre (les Affaires Etrangeres de Sa Majeste I’Empereur des Eran^ais, etant emmis de pouyoir a cet effet, declarent en consequence par le present Acte, que leurs dites Majestes prennent reciproquement 1 engagement indique ci-dessus. En foi de quoi,les Soussignes out signe en double la presente declaration et y out oppose le cachet de leurs annes. Fait a Paris, le 10 Mars 1862. APPENDIX C. Extract from Anglo-Turkish Convention of 0th March 1914. Article 11. Pour confirmer Pengagement pris a Palinea 1' du protocole en date du 20 Avril 1905, Sa Majeste PEmpereur des Ottomans declare qu’il n’alienera pas de quelque maniere que ce soit le lerritoire, (Pune etendue d’environ 550 milles Anglais carres, contigu a la ligne Djebel Nouman-llusn Mourad et situe dans les limites de Pancien canton des Soubeha.wmm \ French Possessions in India. 1 . The French possessions in India fall under two heads, viz. - ( 1 ) Settlements held in full sovereignty and administered by French resident officials ; and (2) certain scattered patches of land, known as the Logos, the sites of former French factories, over which the French (jovernment claim to exercise certain rights of jurisdiction. The Settlements are five in number, viz. :— Area in square miles. Population in 1901. ( 1 ) Pondicherry and its dependencies - 115 1 74,450 ( 2 ) Karikal 53 50,600 (3) Mahe • - - 26 10,300 (4) Yanaon 5 5,000 (5) Chandernagore 4 2(5,800 Of these, Nos. 1-4 are all situated on the coast and within the limits of the Madras Presidency. Chandernagore is on the River Hooghly, some 20 miles north of Calcutta. The Pondicherry Settlement, it may be observed, is not a compact block of territory, but comprises, besides the main settle ment on the coast, in which the town of Pondicherry is situated, some ten isolated strips of French territory in the adjoining British district. The main settlement itself is very irregular in shape, dovetailing in and out with British territory; it also contains a British enclave approximately in its centre. The French Settlements. The French Loges are situated at the following places Province. Area of Loge. The “ Loges. (1) Masulipatam (2) Calicut (3) Dacca (2) (4) Bala sore - (o) Ghoorpuda ( 6 ) Surat (2) Madras Bengal Bihar and Orissa 07 acres. 0 acres. 5 and 36 acres. 38 acres. 2 roods. 2\ and 19.\ acres. - Bombay The French also claim rights, or did when the question was under discussion in 1885, over further small areas at (7) Patna, in Bihar and Orissa, and at ( 8 ) Cazimbazar and (9) Jugdea or Jongdia, in Bengal. The Government of India reported, however, on the 11th September 1885, that “ there is no evidence forthcoming that since 1815 the French have exercised any rights in the ancient loges ” at these three places. Another place at which there was formerly a French factory is (10) Berhampore, in Bengal. As to this place the Bengal Government reported in 1882 :—“There was formerly “ a loge . . . . in Berhampore, but it is no longer in existence ; the “ i am i 01l which the factory building stood was held on lease by the French, “ but it always has been, and is now, under the jurisdiction of the British “ Courts.” The French do not appear to have claimed this loge in 1885, and coidd presumably assert no claim to it now . 1 1 In August 1884 the draft of a Convention was handed to the French Government, of which the preamble ran as followsWhereas certain rights and privileges are possessed “ and exercised bv France in the parcels of land designated Factories or Loges situated at the following places, namely:—(1) at Masulipatam, in the Madras Presidency; (2) at ^Francc qui seraient I'objet de la transaction, ne fait pas mention des autres loges francaises “ uni existent egalement, a 1’ctat d’enclaves, dans les Indes anglaises, telles que cedes de “Dacca Patna,^Cazimbazar et Yangdia”; and M. Waddington went on to ask for an assurance that there was no intention to call in question the rights of the French Government l t these places. He did not mention Berhampore. . , , . It is to be noted, however, that Berhampore is among the places mentioned by the “ Imperial Gazetteer” (Vol. IV., p. 12d) in the passage dealing with the French Loges in 1iwl1Ux 8 French rights in the Loges.” 'N J Past Negotiations. €handeniagore. 4 Even in the areas where the rights of the hrench Go\ eminent aie- more substantial, the extent to which French authority is either admitted or exercised varies in the different cases. Thus, as regards the Dacca Loye*. the Government of India reported in 1885 that thougli the i tench Govern ment still retained “ proprietary rights ' in the two plots, they had exercised no “jurisdictional authority within them for bO years ; and when the limits of these areas were fixed by local British and brencli officials m 1908 the Government of India were careful to remind the I rench authorities that sovereign rights over the Dacca L/oge# lie exclusively with the Butish Government.” On the other hand the French Government apparently regard the two plots at Surat as territory under full French sovereignty, and claim (though we have never admitted the claim) to exercise full and complete jurisdiction over them. As to the two Loges in the Madras Presidency (Masulipatam and Calicut), the Madras Government reported in 1909 that “all essential rights” are exercised by the British Government, although (i) do municipal taxation is levied, and (ii) the French authorities exercise civil jurisdiction in suits which litigants institute before them. At Balasore, as the Bengal Government reported in 1868, the French T.oge “has . . “ been regarded as the territory of a foreign power exempt from “ the jurisdiction of the British Courts,” a doctrine which has resulted in serious administrative inconveniences and abuses . 1 The question of this Loge was brought to the notice of the Government of India by the Local (invermnent (Bihar and Orissa) in July 1911. 5 . Negotiations on the subject of the French settlements in India passed between the French and British Governments in 1857 and again in 1883- 85. On the former occasion the object aimed at was the cession of all French territory except Pondicherry and Ivarikal; on the latter, the extinction of French rights in the Loge8 in return for territorial concessions in the Pondi cherry region. On neither occasion was any agreement reached. The question was tentatively raised in 1901 aifd 1904; but it did not again engage the serious attention of the Government of India and IIis Majesty’s Government until 1909-10, when it was revived in connection with the negotiations then in progress with the French Government regarding the Maskat arms traffic. In a despatch dated the 30th dune 1910 the Government of India submitted proposals for the cession to France of a considerable area of land in the neighbourhood of Pondicherry in exchange for the surrender to Great Britain of all the French settlements in India, other than Pondicherry and the surrounding district, as well as of the scattered Logos. The area to be ceded to France covered about 138 square miles; its population was estimated at 98,300, and its annual revenue at about Rs.-,75,000 (IS,333£.). The territory to be ceded to Great Britain (i.c., the four settlements of Karikal, Mahe, Yanaon and Chandernagore), amounted in all to about 88 square miles, with a population of some 98,700 persons. Hie revenue of the French settlements was not known. The Government of India supported their proposals on the ground that “ we should derive very considerable advantages from the concentration of French terntorg m one compact area and from the control which we should obtain over that dangerous ce-ntre of sedition, Chandernagore.' 6 . In the event, the Government of India’s proposals were never placed before the 4 rench Government. But the question of Chandernagore, which had become more and more prominent in connection with Indian sedition, was revived by the A iceroy in October 1913. Lord Hardinge pointed out. that this town, wdiich was to all intents and purposes a suburb of Lalcutta, had become the centre of the chief and most dangerous anarchical conspiracy in India, to which could be traced a number of recent outrages, including in ail probability the attack made upon the Viceroy himself in December 1912. I he position of the Government of India had been icndeied intolerable by the existence, within a few miles of Calcutta, oi an anaichist centre where plans could be hatched, bombs manufactured, arms ' Similar inconvenience* at Surat led to a proposal by the Bombay Government in 1912 t ia an ( in laMnu s muld &gt;e made to obtain a least* of the French lands by local negotiation.. J lie proposal was negatived. J °imported, emissaries instructed and youths depraved with absolute imwmitu Other places might have their seditious organisations ; but they were at least amenable to British law, whereas at Chandernagore our police and magistracy were quite impotent, and even if the French Government were to send out instructions for more rigorous action, the local authorities were too weak to carry them out . 1 In view of the growing danger of the situation Fold I laidmge stiongly piessed upon His Alajestv's Government the necessity of coming to some arrangement with France for the transfer of Chandernagore, whether by cession or lease, to British jurisdiction. He threw out the suggestion ol a 2 (&gt; years lease, failing a more satisfactory arrange ment. As a result of the Viceroy’s representations, the matter was brought informally m the notne of the French Government j and Sir H. Grey, during his visit to Paris in April 1914, spoke very plainly on the subject to M. Doumergue in the course of a conversation at the Quai d’Orsay. But so lai as is know n at the India Office, no progress has been made towards an agreement. i . It is now understood that an opportunity may arise of dealing with the Prospects of question of the French settlements as part of a wider arrangement with the Settlement. French Government. From the Indian point, of view, the most satisfactory solution would undoubtedly be the complete extinction of French territorial rights of every description throughout India. Liter alia, this would get rid of the difficulties which have arisen in regard to cable and wireless rights in French India—a matter to which the Indian military authorities attach considerable importance from the point of view of censorship requirements in war time. Such a solution—involving as it would the final disappearance of the French Empire in India—would doubtless be distasteful to French national sentiment. But it might possibly be accepted as part of a general settlement at the conclusion of a victorious war, particularly if France, largely owing to British assistance, had made important acquisitions of territory nearer home. At all events,, we might aim at this in the first instance. If the French decline to entertain the proposal, our main energies must be directed towards securing the cession of Chandernagore. This is a matter of really vital importance, in comparison with which nothing else counts for very much. But it is also very desirable that French rights in the Luges should be extinguished, both on account of the practical inconveniences mentioned above, and because the continued existence of these small enclaves is an anomaly which contains a certain element of danger—however slight it may be—to the good relations between ourselves and our allies. It ought to be possible to secure these two desiderata without territorial compensation in India, which is undesirable both in principle and in practice. But if this proves impossible, an arrangement might be concluded on the lines recommended by the Government of India in 1910 (see paragraph o), viz.:—cession to France of territory round Pondicherry in return for the surrender of all the other settlements and of all French rights in the Luges. In negotiating regarding the Jjoges it will be desirable to avoid the use of language which may be construed hereafter—in the event of the negotiations failing—as an admission of French jurisdictional rights (e.g.,at Patna. Cazimbazar, Jugdea and Dacca), the existence of which we have always denied. Political Department, India Office, 20 th April 1915. i Besides its connection with sedition, Cliandernagoie is the home of a consider!*hie contraband trade. [P.T.O.10 p S.—The Government of India are anxious to secure an arrangement on the lines advocated in paragraph / i eleg A l T ot 8th St ‘ p ' above, and (if the complete elimination tember 191b (Appendix A.). of th ; Freilch proves impracticable, and a further concession is necessary to secure even the lesser alternative) thev are prepared 1 to agree to the modification—so far as political offenders are concerned—of British extradition rights under Article IX. of the 1 reaty of 1815. This article requires that all persons against whom judicial proceedings have been instituted for offences committed in British territory shall be surrendered by the French authorities to the British Government, and vice versa. The provision has not been enforced in regard to political offenders for many years past ; but it is believed that the French Government would attach some value to its formal abrogation. 12th September 191(5.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000261_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B239</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000261</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B239</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Territorial changes. Memorandum by the India Office'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-24T15:23:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single memorandum.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 74, and terminates at f 78, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The document outlines territorial changes across Arabia and Africa, and details the main countries who hold influence in the regions, namely Britain, France, Italy, Russia and Portugal. Four appendices are attached to the main memorandum as follows:Appendix A: Telegram from Government of India to Secretary of State [for India], dated 8 September 1916;Appendix B: Declaration respecting the Independence of Muscat and Zanzibar, 1862;Appendix C: Extract from the Anglo-Turkish Convention of 9 March 1914;Appendix D: French Possessions in India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000261#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>