<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:37:48.172Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">J* /to the bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, December 1, 1933. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: In connection with the installation of a Submarine Oil Loading Line and Shipping Terminal, we are planning to use radio telephone transmitters operating on 10 matters or less wave length and equipped to radiate three watts or less power. There is a possibility of these same sets being used for communication between ship and shore during loading of the tankers after completion of the submarine line. We assume there is no objection to the use of thtfselow powered short distance sets, and also that no special permit is necessary. Yours very truly. . A. SKINNER • B isT n*i ^ No:C/bbO. Political Agency, Bahrain, tJie Xnd December 1933. To, The Oflicer-in-Charge, imperial &amp; International Communications Company Limited, Bahrain. Lear Sir, In connection 7 /1 th the work ol The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,the Company are planning to use radio telephone transmitters operating on ten meters or less wave length and equipped to radiate three watts or less power. There is also a possibility ot the same sets oemg used lor communication between ships and shore in connection with their loading operations. kU I should be glad if you would inform me whether the use of these low powered short distance sets will interfere with the work of your Company. 3. It would be convenient if you would let me have an answer as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, 0 Lieut-Colonel. Political Agent.,Bahrain.. A k. the bahrein petroleum company limited S, /lo: A ' y &gt; ft &lt; URGENT Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, December 5, 1933, His Britannic Majesty»s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: J j Reference my letter of December 1, 1933, regarding radio telephones« I have a telegraphic communication requesting the information asked for by cable. I would appreciate your giving me any information you can on this subject, or if this must go through the India Office, please advise them to communicate the information to our London Representative. Yours very truly. E. A. SKINNER. B ——fa; i' Note. The Of!icer-m-Charge,Imperial and International Communications Company Limited statea on the telephone on the bth December iy33 that no reply had been received. The matter nad been relerred to London.Telegram: From:- To:- Rptd:- No:- Dated:- In connection with installation of submarine oil loading and shipping terminal Bahrain Petroleum Company wish to use radio telephone transmitters on ten metres or less using up to three watts# Conditions of Mining Lease are not yet in force and Article 1 of Mining Lease covers telegraph apparatus only but Shaikh has no objection to wireless telephones provided they do not interfere with Imperial and International Communications Company and Imperial Airways and that they are not used for transmission to stations outside Bahrain. As these instruments are covered by spirit of Agreement and Company are anxious to arrange equipment I have informed Chief Local Representative accordingly and have suggested that Bahrain Petroleum Company's Representative in London should consult with those Companies with a view to making technical arrangements to avoid interference with working. I suggest that they be asked to assist Bahrain Petroleum Company in this matter. Copy of correspondence by post. - G.T.C. Political Bahrain. Resident,Bushire. Secretary of State for India,London. 566. 6th December 1933.1^ r IT) . C's. P. P.—L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. ./ O ' 'J No. C/56'/-10/l(b&gt;. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to til© Hoil^ble tile Persian Gulf ^Busiiire, oliticai Hesident in tlie / and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. The Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 6tii December 9? # • Reference to previous correspondence^ Folxtioal Agent f s telegram No:56b dated btli December 193J. Description of Enclosure. Name and date. ?■ P3 1.Letter dated 1st December 1933 from the Chief Local Representatiye^he Bahrain Petroleum Coapan/ Limited. ^.Letter No:C/bt)0 of ^1^-1933 to the Ot'licer-in-Charge, Imperial dblntemational Communications Company Ltd 3.Letter ho:6/2 ot ii-lid-1933 from the Oflicer-in-Charge, Imperial &amp; International Communications Company Ltd* 4.Letter Hated b-lH-1933 from the Chief Local RepresentatftTe b.Note datec b-13-1^3. 6.Letter No:C/564 of 6-1^-1933 P. L to AdTiser to the Bahrain Government. 7.Letter No:C/b65 of 6-lii-1933j ^ ' to the Chief Local Bepresentatire. Subject. Bahrain Petroleum oompany Limitec T s ivadio Telephones. -do- -do- -do- -do- -do- -do- Copy to:- His Majesty's Secretary of State for IndiajLondon. ?\ • AII The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, December 7, 1933. J. /U:/o His Britannic Majesty^s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: I beg to acknowledge with thanks your letter No. C/565-10/1.(b) of December 6, 1933, which referred to my letters dated 1st of December and 5th of December, 1933, and to our conversation on the 6th of December, regarding radio telephones. This information was sent to our London Office yesterday both by telegram and by air mail. Yours very truly, A. SKINNER) Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY,LB!ITED B % 7 Lf'V v&gt; /tn :// Telegram:- 1/27. Prom:- Resident Bushire. To:- Political Bahrain. Repeated:- Secretary or State lor India. No:- 1101. Datea:- 7th (received dtia) December 193o. Addressea Political Agent,BaJarain,repeatea to Secretary ol State for India. Your telegram of otii Instant,boo. Prima lacie question aoes not seem so urgent as to have necessitated telegrapmc reference ana it looics as it Company were trying to employ their customary hustling tactics. Every request of Company for something to which they are not strictly entitled (as in present instance) before being granted must be carefully considered in the light of a possible bargain counter having regard to the many amend(ment)s which His Majesty's G-overnment wish to try and insert in Mining Lease (vide Enclosure 4 ot my Pnntea ^ S k Svtc: Lf. {YJ Letter No!l3bd-S). In this connection our recent bargaining experience with Company in Banram must also be borne in mind. 3. In luture please do not grant any request of Company or advise Shaikh to do so without reference to me.S /Zo /v Uo, G. 108. Office of the Adviser to the Govern ;ent of Bahrain. 6th Deceinber 1933. Prom;- C. Dalrymple Bel^rave, Adviser to the Bahrain Government, • Bahrain. To:- Lieut-Colonel Gordon i»och,I.A, Political Agency, Bahrain. Sir. fx I have tj&lt;e honour to j cknowledge the receipt of your letter Mo G/564-lO/l.VI. dated today. 2. The Goverrmient of Bahrain has no objection to the Bahrain Petroleum Company installing a radio telephone proviaed that it does not in any way interfere with ti.e working of the Imperial and International Communications Coy; Ltd: and the Imperial Air..ays and provided that it is not used for communications to aaa from any station outside of Bahrain. I have the honour to be Sir, your most obecient servant, Adviser to t^e Government of Ba.jrC's. P. p.— L (in) 980—300-12-29—c. .9&gt;' L&gt; No.Q/bya-10/l(b; nts his comp ( Busliire .P , , and has the honour to transmit to mm the O :&lt;&gt; The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to tile Hoil'ble tlie - N e v Persian Gulf ,BusJiire. Political Resident in the / under-mentioned documents. The Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 9 th Lecember P/0 Reference to previous correspondence. Bahrain : rinted Letter No:C/&amp;6V-10/l(b) or 6th December 193b. Description of Enclosure. Name and date. THir Subject. Letter No:C/lOti of 6-1^-3^ from the Adviser to the GoYernment of Bahrain. Bahrain Petroleum Company*3 Radio Telephones. A' Copy to:- His Majesty's Secretary or State tor India,London, by air mail. 1,v Ci o .-o 5? GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. D epartments EXPRESS LETTER IN.B .-Thisis anORIGlNAL MESSAGE sent by post to save telegraph ic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities U is vwrded and signed as if it had been so despatehed*] From Political Bahrain. To Repeated Resident Bushire. Secretary of State for India,London. A T at//580-l j /1 • b. Dated 10th December .* Addressed Political Resident in the Persian GulfRepeated to Secretary of State for India,London,by Air idail. My telegram 566 Lecember 6th. 2. His Majesty*3 Ships use short ware long distance wireless communication,but i do not know whether the proposed radio telephones would interfere with this type of transmission^ S Admiralty will no doubt be consulted.^ Liwut-Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain. PC F P—\ 666S&amp;P—(M-1881)—27 9-32—2,40.000CONFIDENTIAL. No. -'v S 1912-3 of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 'Tie I'orelftn ''eeretary to (roveinnert of iR # ITe^i Delhi • and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dooa- ment (s). 8. CoBles of the enclotnires have beer Betrt by the '■olltloal Afrent. Bahrain, to the Inciia Office under Mb Printed letter TIo.C/567-10/l(b) dated the 6th December 1933. ^ British Consulate-General, * ftJX BUSHIRE. Dated. XAt.U RP.OTSt.T.. ASS?' -fc- Reference to previous correspondence : ^T/ ^ V ^flBldencv Printed Letter Ho.l8Pl-t? of 7th T)eoe'nber 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Ar. tier echedule attached Copy, with corr-oliTnent s, ^oli^iical Afrent p Bahrain, Subject. 3ainum oil. forwarded to the ^ for infoinatior.X( INDIA OFFICE, X/U • 1-7 tLfatjl* , iiVHITi£ i iAliL s,v/, 1. TSj S.L 115*. V A* P.Z.7941/33. 14th December 1933. Dear Duncan, With reference to our telephone conversation tnis morning I enclose copy of a letter sent to Imperial and International Goriiriunications Ltd. and of the relevant ■¥r papers. We shoula he grateful for Air Ministry advice - on this question in so far as I'Text of Bahrein Petroleum ^ q ^ Concession. 1 { it affects Imperial Airways. Telegram from political-'Agent, ^ k Bahrein, dateo^bth &lt; Perhaps you would also advise ^ December, No. 066. { ' ^ Telegram from political ^0sident&lt; whether copies of the aatea 7th December, &lt; No. 1101. P. |v^ &lt; correspondence should be sent to the Communications Sub- Coninittee of the Committee of Imperial Defence? As you will see, the Bahrein petroleum Company are not strictly entitled to what tney ask. until they have taken out a mining lease, though unuer Article I of Schedule III to their concession tney will then have the right to erect telegraph apparatus of all kinas for the purposes of their operations. But as the Sheikh's concurrence has already been/ Flight Lieutenant W#A* Duncan, Air Ministry, Aaastral House, Kingsway, W.C- 2.1-^ - 2 - been intimated to them locally, it would be difficult now to refuse, more particularly as the mining lease is due to be taken out in so relatively short a time. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHV/AITE.M '&gt; P: ■Tio INDIA OFFICE, WHmHALL, 3.'//. 1. P.Z.7^41/33. i4th December 1933. Dear Captain Lawson, As you may be aware, the Bahrein petroleum Company are engaged in developing an oil concession which nas been grantea to them by the Sheikh of Bahrein. Under the terms (which aate from 1925) of their concession they are entitled in certain circumstances on taking out a mining lease to erect 'telegraph apparatus of all kinds' so far as may be necessary for the purpose of their business. They have not yet taken out a mining lease, though they have to reach a decision as to whether or not to do so by not later than January 1935. But they have now askea permission, in connection with the installation of a submarine oil loading ana shipping terminal, to use a raaio telephone transmitter on 10 metres or less, using up to 3 watts. Tne Sheikh has intimated that he has no objection to action on these lines, so long as the wireless telephone in question do not/ G^ptairi Lawson, Imperial ana International Conrnun i cat ions, i-ta., Electrcx House, Victoria Embankment, W.C-. 2. Xifcnot interfere with the installations 01 Imperial and. International Gonmunications or Imperial Airways una so long as they are not used for transmission to stations outsiae Bahrein. 2, The Company are represented in this country hy Mr. H.R. Ballantyne, whose offices are at 19 Loorgate, I unaerstana that the Company will gladly comply with the Sheikh*^ stipulations, out are anxious to know how best to secure that there shall he no interference with your installations or with those of Imperial Airways Ltd. If there is likely to he any difficulty in securing this, perhaps the simplest course would he that . . Mr. Ballantyne should 'be placed in direct touch with you with a view to discussing the matter. But if apparatus of the nature they mention would he insufficiently powerful to interfere, perhaps discussion would he unnecessary and on receipt of a reply from you ana from the Air Ministry we could inform the Company, if this was agreed, that so long as their apparatus was on 10 metres or less, and using not more than 3 watts there would he no danger of interference, hut that with a view to keeping within the terms of the Sheikh's permission, they should consult us further/- 3 - further if 8.nci wtion 8iiy til't6r^t/ion. w&amp;s con06mplc41/6q• 3, We shouia toe glad of your observations in the matter to enable a decision to he reached. I ought to add that we have impressed on Mr. Ballantyne (with reference to the oheiKh's se-conu stipulation referred to ahove) that for the purposes of conmunication outsiae the islands we consider that the facilities aiiorcied hy Imperial and International Communications Luiidted should he employed. Yours sincerely, J' • Gr • LAliH iVAl il*.u \ INDIA OFFICE. POLITICAL D3PAHTISNT. £ylt-?ui33 L^TTJH (AI^ MIL). &gt;7 &amp;uo ♦&lt;2X» \\\\ Secretary of otate. Political Resident, Bushirs. 12th January 1954. p.Z.305/34. Repeated political Agent, Bahrein Go ve rniuS n t of In a i a. A IV Your tele^rarn Qateu /tn DeceiiiDei, llol, and connected correspondence. Installation of rauio-tele phones by Bahrein Petroleum Company. ^ ft please see correspo^ence ending with reference to Communications 3uh-Committee of 0.1.D.,{copy sent to you, Government of Inaia, and Banrein hy air mail ox ^Oth Becember.) In light of their views we see no objection to proposed installation, subject to following conditions, and suggest that Sheikh be aavised accordingly. We should be glaa to receive copy of any communication sent to Sheikh. (a) That the raaio-electric installation shall be maintained and operated in such a manner as not to interfere with the commercial operation of the wireless stat/ion operated by The Imperial and International Communications Company, Limited, or with such wireless stations as may be ; i x a . &gt; &lt; WUSl h Vl Uc. ^ ^ , maintained by Imperial Airways or by nis iwaj^sty s Government. (b) That no communication shall be carried out with any station outsxae the Islana of Banrein, except with ships owned or chartered by the Bahrein Petroleum company, and/ theand that communication with such ships snail in no case oe attemptea when trie vessel is more than three miles from the coastline of the Island of Bahrein. (c) That comunications shall concern solely the legitimate business of the Bahrein petroleum Company. 2. As regards condition (a) we have thought it aesirahle to add safeguard in respect of H.M.G., since H.A.F. (and perhaps Admiralty also) may well wish in future to maintain separate wireless installations. If you think this aesirahle it woula, of course, he possible in any communication made to sneikh to add words 'with consent of sheikh' before words 'by Imperial Airways or by H.L.G.' 3. Copy of letter sent to-day to Ballantyne is enclosed. The issue of the above has been authorised. (Sd.) J. a WATJTflgf1 P.Z. 305/34 India. Office, [Whi tehall, S.W.I. 2th January 1934. Dear Mr. Ballantyne, With reference to our discussion on 7th December and to subsequent conversations on the subject of your Company's request to be permitted to establish radio telephone transmitters operating on 10 metres or less wave-length, and equipped to radiate 3 watts or less power, I write to say that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is now being instructed to inform the Sheikh of Bahrein that His Majesty's Government see no reason to advise him to object to the proposed installation subject to the following conditions; (a) that the radio-electric installation shall be maintained and operated in such a manner as not to interfere with the conuaercial operation of the wireless station operated by the Imperial and International Communications Company Limited, or with such wiroiiss stations as may be maintained by Imperial Airways or by His Majesty's Government (*)/ R•Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Co., 19, Moorgate, E.C.2. i, rili3^ 2. (b) that no coomunioation shall be carried out with any station outside the Island of Bahrein, exoept with ships owned or chartered hy the Bahrein Petroleum Company, and that communication with such ships shall in no case be attempted when the vessel is more than three miles from the coastline of the Island of Bahrein. (o) that communications shall concern solely the legitimate business of the Bahrein Petroleum Compwiy. y, G. LAi I riWAl * £'•Ctmfldantlal . GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department* EXPRESS LETTE [N. I&gt;,— Tim is an OPiJGINAL MESSAGE, sent hy post to save telegraphic expense and ttotdue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt,, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sam time and formalities it is vxyrded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] FiMMi - Political Resident, Bushlre# To - Political Agent, Bahrain. &gt;/ Repeated to Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, New Delhi. xxsx No* 124 ~ s of i) ate £ 6th Fehruaiy 23$ Installation of radio-telephones 'by Bahrain Petroleum Company t Reference Express Letter No305/34• t'f liith Jtnuar^ fx India Office. ?rlma facie it would appear desirable that reference para graph 1 (a) the words ••with the consent of the ShaiKh 11 should 'be included. sd. T.C.!Powle, Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTES^SD . Major, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 8 €i DCFP—\S66S&lt;&amp;F—(M-18S1)—27-9-32—2,40,000, i- c-lNo. 'H of 1352 Office of the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain. Dated, Dil Qaad 11. 1352 February 25,1934. From The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrain. Ju Sir, I have the honour to refer to letters . nave l^t a: x dated l^t and 5th December 1933, forwarded by you, from the Bahrain Petroleum Company regarding radio telephones. His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al-Ehalifah has instructed me to ask you to inform the Company that he does not object to the proposed installation provided that the following conditions are complied with.- (a) That the radio-electric instal lation shall be maintained and operated in such a manner as not to interfere with the commercial opera tion of the wireless station operated by — i-2- ^7 by the Imperial and Inter national Communications Company, Limited or with such wireless stations as may be maintained, with the consent of His Excel lency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al- Khalifah, by Imperial Airways Limited or by His Majesty's Government. (b) That no communication shall be carried out with any station outside the Island of Bahrain, except with ships owned or chartered by the Bahrein Petro leum Company Limited, and that communication with such ships shall in no case be attempted when the vessel is more than three miles from the coast line of the Island of Bahrain. (c) That communications shall con cern solely the legitimate business of the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Limited. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. 3 Adviser to the Government.Ko: w/H6-10/l (b j. rolitical Afjencj, jatirain,^ cutii f «bruar/ 1934. The Ohi*t uoohl .eprestntativ^ , Tiie Bahrain ?etroieum Co/npany iamiteo, I«ar Sir I beg to refer to tixe correaponaence eu-in^ with a\/ letter ao:u/565-10/1 (b; d&amp;tec tne 6tii December 1^33 re^araing radio-telephones,and to say that the aatter has been further considered by his w &gt;ceilcncy » haiich Hamaa Dm Usa Ai Kh&amp;lilah, who uesires me to inlora you that he nas no objection to tne proposed r&amp;aio-eiectnc telephone installation,proviaec tuat the toilowi%' conaitions are coaplied with:- (i) Ihat the raaxo-electrxc telephone installation shall be uUtintauaec end operated in such a amnner as not to interlere with the ooaojercial operations ox tae wireless station operated by the imperial and international Communications Limited or «itn such wireless stations as may be maintained,with the consent ol His excellency Lhaikh Hamad bin f isa a 1 :h&amp;lifah,by Imperial Airwa/s Limited or by llis majesty f a Government. (ii) ihat no conununication shall be carne- out with any station outside the Island of Bahrain,except with ships owned or chartered by ±he Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,ana that communication with tmch ships shall m no case be attempted when the vessel is more than three miles from the coastline of the island of Bahrain, (iii) lhat communications shall concern solely tne legitimate business of the Company. Tours faithfully, Lieut-Colonel, Political A^ent^tnrain.Goni idcntigl . No:C/lbl-10/l (b)• ihe Political Agent,Bahrain,presents ins compliments to:- (1). The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (2). His Majesty r s Secretary oi* State for India, India Oflice, London. By air mail. (3). The roreign Secietarv to the Government of India, New Lelhi. By air mail. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document/s. The Ag ram, Lated the &lt;i6th February 1^34. Persian Gulf. Reference to previous correspoo^nce. (2). Tolitical Agent's Printed Letter No:C/l53-10/l(b) datea the ^&amp;id February 1934. Lescription of ^closures ■ ■ i ■ ■■ ■■ ■ ■ i ■■ i ■■ ii liame and Late. &gt;3/; Subject. Letter No:G/llb '0: ^5-^-1^34 Bahrain Oil. installation of irom the Adviser to the radio-electric telephones. Bahrain Government. pj g Letter i:o:G/l48-10/i(bj dated &lt;:6th February 1934 to the Ghief Local nepresentative.The -cio- -ao- Bahrain Petroleum Company ^td.itfUlr)- The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited S/lo&gt;2&lt;f Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, February 28, 1934. No. rA-25. His Britannic !.!ajesty f s Political A^nt, Bahrein. Dear Sir; . P,3? Please accept my thanks for your letter No ,0/148-10/1(b) dated February 26, 1934, on the subject of the use c: radio telephones, contents of which are duly noted and have been passed on to the operators both on ship and shore. Yours very truly, ft CJ'/ . 2x» — ■—-Xi j Chief Local Representative, TFIS BAHREIN PETROLEU!^ GCr.TAI ^Y LE^ITED. BP /U:&amp;0 ConliQential * No:C/176-10/1(bj. The Political ^ent,3aiirain,presents nis coraplnnenta to:- (l;. The Honoarable the Political Resident m the r ersian Guli, Bushire. (Idj. His i\'6jesty f s Secretary of State for India, London. (3). The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New lelhi. and has the honour to transiait to him a copy of the under mentioned document. r ihe xigency, Bahrain, Dated the bth arch 1934. ^ersian Gulf. A* Heference to previous correspondtnoe. Political Agent's Pnnteu Letter No:G/lbl-10/l(b) of ^6-ki-iy^. Description of enclosures. Name arid Lete. a Subject li Jly. 0 .. Letter 80:PA-2b of i&amp;-ii-1934 from Bahrain Oil. Installation Ghiel Local Representative,ihe of radio-electric telephones. Bahrain Petroleum Company ^imiteu.UtV The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited KO .PA-39. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf March 18, 19 His Britannic Majesty^s Political Agent, Bahrein. Use of Radio Telephones. ,y- Dear Sir: p,^ |?MO Further to my letter No.PA-25 which in turn referred to your letter No.C/l48-10/l(b), paragraph (ii), which stated : 'That no ccraniunication shall be carried out with any station outside the Island of Bahrein, except with ships owned or chartered by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited and that communication with such ships shall in no case be attempted when the vessel is more than three miles from the coastline off the Island of Bahrein. My Company requests that the limitation of the three mile limit be deleted and that the permission granted shall not be limited to Company ships or ships chartered by the Company but should be extended to any ships coming to Bahrein to take away Company products. You doubtless understand that we will maintain a Mooring Master at Sitra who will also act as Pilot to inccming ships. When informed of the approach of any ship he will proceed to the Outer buoy off the north east coast of Muharraq, from which point he will guide the ship to the sitra Anchorage. One Radio Telephone Set will be maintained at sitra, the second set will be carried by the Mooring Master to the incoming ship. For reasons of safety it will be desirable for him to be in communication with sitra during his trip to ship in small boat. After boarding ship it will be important for shipping teminal personnel to be in constant touch with the ship while she is approaching so that every thing may be ready for the loading immediately after mooring. ft I * *1 ii Yours very truly, E.A. SKINNER. CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Hi* By Air Mail, P.Z. . Forwarded v/ith the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. / i v India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.I. Copy sent to. ^P.Z. 1779 /34. .'HE BAHREIN PETROLEUM CO^iPMY LIMITED. -ft: 3 . 19, MOORGATE, LONDON, E.G. 2« 15th March 1934, Dear Mr.Laithwaite, p I v/ould refer to your letter P .Z.305/34 addressed to me under date the 12th January 1934. Condition (h) of that letter provides that no communication shall he carried out with any station outside the Island of Bahrain, except v/ith ships owned or chartered by the Bahrein Petroleum Company, and that communicati on with such ships shall in no case be attempted when the vessel is more than three miles from the coastline of the Island of Bahrein. This Company now asks that it should b e able to communicate with all the ships coming in to take away from Bahrain the products of the Company's oil operations there, and that the three mile limit should be deleted. In explanation, I would add that the ships calling to take away the Company's produce may well be ships owned or chartered by the buyers. I think this would be so in the cases where the Company sells its produce ex Bahrain. As to the three mile limit, it is, as I have explained to you, very desirable that preparations to load incoming vessels should be made well in advance of their arrival. It will, I think, be appreciated from what I have said, that the foregoing modifications are of great practical importance to the Company in its trading operations and it is hoped that the request of the Company can be acceded to with, J .G. Laithwaite Esq^., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I. (Of/ —qcj 2. of course, all safeguards which His Britannic Majesty^ Government think should 'be imposed. Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) H.H. BALLANTYHE.Vi' PfU-33 Conrid^ntiRl. Political As«ncjr, Ssnrsin, tee Mtn ...eroli 1334. Froa:- Liaut-Colonel Gordon Locb.i.A., Political Agant, Bail rain. to:- The Honourable tLe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buttiiire* Sir, I a\ v I julve tue lionour to refer to mj Printea Letter 8o :C /iy6 -lv //l (b) u &amp;teu tlie btii toh. 1934 and to enclose a copy of a letter ftoifA-Sy dhiec tut lau ^arcn 1934 # rro» the Jhiel Local Representative,liie -^anrain Jetroleum Oonpany Limited,regarding tue installation of radio-eleotric tele phones at Bahrain. Jd» Ihe request of the Goapan/ seems reasonable provided that the use ot the instriuaent is limiteu to the area recently surveyed on behalf of the uoapany by H.a.S Oraonde,which includes th« track which will be usea by mcoain^ steaiaers. f ihe concession,if granted should not,! venture to thinic,bs held to cover tne use of the radio telephone in the Mooring M&amp;stertg boat anywhere except in that area,*ith peraaps the adcitlon of the ordinary harbour,which the oail steamers use* 3« 1 aia not much impre&amp;seu. oy tne reasons of safety adduced in the last paragraph ox the Chief Local hepresentative T 8 letter,as tue boats of the alcsopotamia ersia Corporation Limited regularly go out to the outer buoy without any means of coamunication. Nevertheless,it cannot be denied tnat in ti^es /of stressCONFIDENTIAL. No. C/lfi9 of 1934. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The ▼orelfcn Secretary to the Oovrrwent of InfUft, Mew l&gt;elhl • and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermeniioned docu- ment R riHs h Rpsitlp.nr»v Office of the Political ^sldent In the !, emiae Gulf, T r hml . Dated.. Iwt ATTH logrf,. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter ^o.O/lfSB of Int ^rrrll 1934 to Hie Mnjesty's Secretary of rotate for India. Subject. iVthraln ^et mletm Cowaany Installation of radlo- electrlc teleohonee at Bahrain* Copy, Yr'ith cop:/- o^ er closure, forwarded, ^Ith compliments, to the Pclitical Agent, Bahrain, for in to mat Ion .fo r\ Confidential . No:C/354-10/l(b). Political Agency, Bahrain,the 1st April iy34 1 Fppm:- Lieut-Colonel Gordon Locn,I.A, Political Agent, Bahrain. To:- The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Sir, I nave the honour to refer to your letter No:G/115 dated the 11th Dhil ^'ad 1352,equivalent to the ^bth February 19iJ4,and to enclose a copy of a letter No:PA-39 dated the 18th March 1934 from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,regarding the use of radio telephones by his Company. 2. I aim obtaining advice on the subject for His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin 'Isa Al Khalifah. 3. Mention is made of an appointment of Mooring Master and Pilot,and it appears that,though there is no objection to the appointment in practice,the consent of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad,who already has a Port Officer,should be obtained by the Company as a matter of principle. It seems desirable that the Mooring Master and Pilot saould be subject to the authority of the Port Officer. I should be glad if you would inform me of the views of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin f isa Al Khalifah. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.OONKIDENTIAL. No - C/3b5-10/l(b). /! V^f. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—■ Tile Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gull', at Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulf. Dated. .tttfc. .Wft. Apr U.. 1 ^34 Reference to previous correspondence : Residents Printed Letter No:C/lby dated 1st April 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, I D Subject. Letter No:C/364 dated the 1st April 1934 from the Political Agent,Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Bahrain G-overnment. Use ol radio telephones and appointment of a Mooring Master ana Pilot by The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited.P. Z. 2457/34. INDIA OFFICE, WHITSHALL, 3.W. 1. 13th April 1934. IVIy dear seal, I enclose a copy of a further letter from the Political .-(esiaent gthout the installation of radio electric telephones at Bahrein by the Bahrein Petroleum Company. As I mentioned on the telephone, the Communications Sub-comriittee of the C.I.D, this morning approved the suggestions in ray letter of ^gth ivarch to Clarke, No.P.z.2151/34, of which copies were sent to you ana the other interested Departments. Reference was made at the meeting to Colonel Powle's letter now enclosed and to the fact tnat neltner he nor the / Political ~gent saw any objection to the concession asked xor oy the Chief Local Representative. I saifl,- however that I ha.0 not haa olme to consult the i.aiuiralty as to the precise position of the outer buoy off the north-east coast of Muharraq, but that I was unoer tne impression that it was well outsiae territorial waters. The committee agreed that if this impression was confirmed by the Admiralty then that the refusal to agree to the operation of wireless telephones outside the three-mile limit might be relaxed to the extent suggested/ E. A# Seal, E sq., Admiralty, 3•W• 1.- 2 - V suggested in paragraphs 4 ana 5 of Mr. skinner's letter No. p,a*39 of 18th karch to the politictil A^ent, Bahrein. 2, will you he so kina as to confirm my impression thct the outer huoy is well outsiae territorial waters? We will tnen telegraph to tne Political i^esiaent approving his reconiiiendb-tion (una inciaentally expressing our entire agreement with the remarks in paragraph 3 of his letter of 1st April, 0.158). 3. I am sending copies of tnis letter and its enclosure to the foreign Office, --i/imiraUy ? petroleum Department, General post Office, and Commander Clarke at the C.I.D. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAlTHWAlTi],Telegram:- X/27. From:- Secretary of State for Inaia, Lonaon. To:- Resident, Bushire. No:970. Repeated:- Political, Bahrain. Copy by Air Mail to the Government of India. No:- 971. Dated:- 18th (received 19th) April 1934. A* P iff Your telegram of February 27th,236, and connected correspondence. Bahrain radio telephones etcetera. Shaikh should be advised to reply as follows to requests put forward on behalf of Company. (a) as adequate service is operated by I &amp; I C is already available direct communication with San Francisco cannot be permitted, (b) Shaikh is not prepared to relax three mile limit save to extent that Mooring Master at Sitrah may use radio telephones between it ana outer buoy within area defined by first sentence of paragraph 2 of Loch's letter of March 24th, C/232-10/l(b) to extent specified in paragraph 4 and # paragraph 5 of Skinner f s letter PA-39 of March 18th. (c) within three lim mile limit Company may communicate with all Tankers coming in to remove Company's oil products whether or not belonging to or chartered by them. (d).concessions under (b) and (c) represent special concessions to Company to which they are not entitled and which Shaikh expects taken account of in considering his various desiderata. 2. Ballantyne has been informed as above. 3. Paragraph 3 of your letter of 1st April C/158. We agree entirely and have so informed Ballantyne. I' • ma * iTelegram:- EX. From:- Resident, Bushire. To:- Political, Bahrain. Copy sent by post (mail) to Secretary of State for Inaia. -go - -do- Government of India. No:- 410. Dated:- 25th April 1934. Telegram from Secretary of State for India 970, April 18th. r lease take action accordingly. Resident. f ■SICRIT . E.0 # No:C/574-10/l(b). 1st December ljS6« A There has for some time been a suspicion that Ihe Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited end the California Arabian Btrmdsrd Oil Compeny commnicete with each other by v -lreless telephones- ^he use of wireless telephones was permitted In Bchraln on the following express understanding!- ^Thst no communication shall be carried out with eny stftlon outside the Island of Brhrain, except with ships owned or chartered by The Bahrain Petroleum Com' any Limited, and that commonlcatlon with such ships shell In no case be attempted when the vessel is more than three miles from the coast line of the Island of Behrain.' 2, I hear that they now comnainicate on a wave length of approximately 42 metres with call signs of BBB and KKK respectively, and come up between about 19»00 or 20.00 nours, usually 19 # ^ 0 hours Zone time. 2. I should be so grateful if you could errange to check whether this Information is correct and If possible to record enough of their communications to enable us to determine whether they are infringing the above proviso. Captain V # S # Butler, D.£»0», Senior Neval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.r Chorehem. Ctfa ijp/vd C\.i (9 fL dtjs.tn CRI T . Ho:C/580-10/1(b). 2pd l&gt;eceiiibor 1^- 6. 1$ I enclose a copy of a demi-official letter -ioiC/574-10/lb dated the 1st Deceaber 1925, which i have vritten to the senior N^val Officer asking him kindly to try to fine out whether Tin Bahrain Petroleurc Com any are using their vireless telephones to coxnmmicate with the California Arabian standard ^il ^om any in iiasa. •?. RumDurs have reached mt from time to tiaifc that taey were doing so and, though I was loath to believe that a Company of such standing wou-d so dishonour their undertakings, latterly the reports have become so circumstantial that I am inclined to think that the Companies are in fact comnianicating with aach other in this way* One report is to the effect that the California Arabian Standard Oil Company telephone their oraers for nt tcrial and so on to The Bahrain Petroleum Com: any, T.ho code them and despctch them from Bahrain. Should it prove to be the case the Bahrain Petroleum Company limited will have infringed the conditions on which they were allowed to use wireless telephones in Bahrain# ^his is a serious matter. 4« Apart from any cuestion of the Company 's possible infringement of their conditions of working the wireless tele phones in Bahrain or of international wireless arrangem nts, it is politically undesirable that there should be in private hant^s means by which wireless cocynun'.cation is possible between /Bahrain Honourable tjl&lt; utcnant-Coloncl T.C«?ovle, C.B.I'#, Political Resident In the Persian Silf Buahire•s. Bchraln and the aif Inland, unless the users can be trusted to observe their undertakings, and I gather in informal conver sation that the ^tnior Nc val Officer regj rds it as undesirab-ue from the Nt val ooint of viev;» S. Since writing the above I tm informed that the California Arabian Standard Hi ^omuany were distinctly heard giving a letter code message to The Bahrain Petroleum Com any at about hours local time on the night of the ^nd/2rd l^ecember#Telephone Message. From:- Senior Naval Officer In the Persian Gulf To;- Political Agent, Bahrain. Unrrambered • Dated:- 8th December 1935. Your C/574 of December l«t. Have had no result. Must now defer till our return in January. S.N.O.P.G.V SECRET. D.0.NO.1015-S. t &gt;3&gt; The Residency, Bushire, the 19th December,1935. o^osl tCo Please refer to ^our demi-official letter No.C/580-li&gt;/i ( b), dated the 3rd December 1935. //hen you have received Butler^ reply please hold the matter in abeyance until my arrival in Bahrain when we can discuss what action should be taken. A 7 \c . Lieut.^Colonel Gordon Loch,G.I.S.» Political Agent, Bahrain. mKm.SFCRIT . NO!C/9. Cth January In continuation of my letter ibJC/57j-10/lb ( 8ted the ?rd ^oveinber 1l '5, I understand that are likely to call up KKK at 09.00 G.M.T this morning (January fth). This Is likely to be on 48 metres. Captain V.S.Butler, C.S.O., Eenior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, H.M.E Ehoreham.BHHB HIiHHBHBHHHHI r.o.NoiCA4-PA. jth February 1 to'your t^K yo rill you kindly refer to your demi-official letter NorlOlS-f dated the 10th lecember 1925 and to our conversation durin? your recent visit to Bahrain. I have not been able to get definite ^roof of the commnicatlon between the Bahrain Petroleuic Company and the California i^rabirn v-tanci rd Oil Comj^any on the mainlend by means of v ire less and certain inforiration y-hich I nov aave t&lt; ncs to .suggest t :at, thought they iray have used their v. ire- Less in this vay, aesse ;es usually come taroagh tac commercial ireless between Hasa and Bahrain. 3. I will m-ke ^urther enruiries Itself, but vrite to say t if t I do not take any action unless and until we roof of misuse of tieir vireless by Compf-ny.H .M.S. 'SHORMAM' at Bahrain. No. &gt;&gt;.o iCj&lt;g-, 22ii(i January, 1936. Dear ^ o .With reference to jour deail-offlclal letters No .c /574-10/l(l)), No.C/579-10/lb and No,C.9, 'SHOREHAM' has heen listening for any communications between the parties concerned and nothing more has been heard since my last report. As we are leaving for Boibay on the 24th January we shall not be able to listen any more. The reiaalnlng sloops In the Division are fitted with one receiving set only, so I am afraid they will not be able to help you during 'SHOREHAli'S' absence. Tours sincerely. Lieut-Colonel G. Loch, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.the bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, September 11, iy3y Awali, No. PA-44b RADIO TRANSMITTSR HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN, Dear Sir, May we liave your decision on the use or a transmitter on the GeophysicalHouse-boat to communicate with the Awali Main Ofrice. costly delays, and to report possible accidents. Also it is likely that reflection shooting will not be success ful in which case retraction shooting will be used. It is absolutely necessary to use two-way radio transmission in refraction shooting to time the explosion and maintain contact over wide areas. would not communicate with Arabia or elsewhere. Tne only man who would use the transmitter would be Mr. Beverley who would be responsible for all messages sent, and on land no one would transmit but Mr. Reith and he would be responsible ror the entire layout. This communication is badly needed to prevent We would use only one assigned frequency, and Acting Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. MHL;LAConfidential Political Agency, No. C/660-10/l,b, Bahrain, the 17th September 1939. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A H H A IN 1 Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PA-445 dated the 11th September 1939 regarding the use of a radio transmitter on the Geophysical House-Boat to communicate with the Awali Main Office. 2. There is no objection to the use of this transmitter as proposed in your letter provided that the following con^ ditions are strictly observed :• (i) the radio transmitter shall be maintained and operated in such a manner as not to interfere with the commercial operations of Cable and Wireless Limited, or with such wireless stations as may be maintained, with the consent of His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin 'Isa al Khalifah, by Imperial Airways Limited or by His Majesty^ Government; (ii) tfca* communications shall only be allowed between the units employed by the Survey party and the House-Boat within the area under survey and the Company's Main Office at Awali; (iii) tftwrt communications shall concern solely the legitimate business of the Company. Yours faithfully, L for Political Agent, Bahrain.m Confidential No. C/39-10/l-b. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th January 1941. To The Officer-in-Charge, Cable and ivireleaa Limited, BAHRAIN Dear Sir, f n Reference your letter No. CON/6 'aated the 7th January 1941 regarding the use of radio transmitting sets by the Bahrain Petroleum Company. 2. According to my file, Imperial and International Communications Limited were consulted on the subject of the installation of this transmitter. They replied in X h a letter dated the 21at December 1933 that they saw no objection as far as the Company were concerned to the proposed installation. As far as X know the system is still in use at the present time. Political Agent, Bahrain. 1' ■—D.O, No. C/91 - lO/l-b. Political Agency, Bahrain, 26th January 1941. Will you please refer to your letter No« Con/6 dated the 25th January 1941 ? 2# I am very much afraid that I am unable to give you a copy of this letter as It is not mine and was only sent here for information, I suggest your Divisional Manager might try and get it from your Head Office. v ours sincerely, C. Gahan, Esq., Officer in Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Bahrein. £1 S^ \o 0 the bahrein petroleum company limited lr ah i*ir Awali ' . ^ ^ Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. No. PA-431. March 24, 1941. of 'V RADIO COMMUNICATION H. B. M* s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We are today advising the Officer-in-Charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, that the oil barge 'GALTEX II tf is due to arrive in Bahrein (theoretically) on or about March 28, 1941, and for your information it is stated that this vessel is not equipped with a regular C-W set, but has a voice tremsmitter that operates on the following schedule: Call letters Transmitting Receiving C Q, 6100 K.C. or 78 meters 2738 K.C. or 110 meters The vessel has no regular radio operator, but instead one of the deck officers operates the phone twice eacn day, and is able to receive codes. The scheduled times of operation are not known. Yours very truly. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTD.V V ^0° The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited n&lt; V . c ^Awali u March 85, 1941 \ y / ^ B ahrein I sland , P ersian G ulf. A V His Britannic Majesty♦s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, W Te will shortly be re-starting our submarine geophysical explorations in the 'Additional Area' around Bahrein. As has been our custom in the past, vie are install ing a wireless transmitter and receiver in the launch attached to this expedition, and a corresponding set in Awali. The launch is the 'Zellak' and the set on board will be a 25 watt ! voice transmitter working on^^^ kilocycles. The Awali wire- i I less telephony set is of 50 watts and transmits on 5050 kilo cycles. The sets will be used only when necessary. The times of operation are likely to be quite irregular. Our usual precautions will be taken to prevent un authorized use of the sets. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative T1U 3AIIR2IN PSTRCLjIUI.: CGIIFAKY LTD, .::/wg nfi.Copy of Note from the General StafBranch, Censer section, kvxj ^Headquarters, India, No.359/Censors, 4 &lt;Jated the 21st February 1941. ^adio communication between BaJirein and U .o.A. Karachi Infor.aation ouimaary ITo. 31 Part A reports the following extract from a letter written by H.H. Head, Cable and Wireless Ltd., Kuwait, to F.L. Thornton i^sq. , Divisional ;:ana^er. Cable and .Vireless Ltd. , Post Box lJo.57, KARACHI, dated January 26th, 1941. ^Auout half a dozen Americans got on board at Bahrein going for a month's leave to Persia. Funnily enough one of them br^u^nt up the question of communication with New York. I kept q ite dumb for a oit, t'.en by Judicious questioning ascer tained the fact that they do definite ly work an American Station, Jan Francisco 1 think by 3. 7. .Vireless. To overcome local restrictions the gear is fixed up ^_ a^_]^uncji* They have i think a ItfKT '/. xmtrT? ^ of Bahrein (oil traffic) work br.ught over in a launch and/..•P.T.O. bMT. J lot ^ alsoand aent off in the same manner. 5o that's that. I did not appear particularly interested, out thought it was a bit of luck getting the whole story from the Korsa's mouth.' 1 - -• . ■ ' —~ V v ,v ' 1^^ ,p THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. April 23, 1941 CON-788 His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, / Bahrein. \ Dear Sir, /r ' In our letter Con-774 we advised you of our plans to set up and operate two small wireless transmitters for intra-Shaikhdom business communications in accordance with our concession agreement. We wish to correct the statement made in that letter that the transmitter on the launch 'Zellak' would operate on 3287 kilocycles. The crystal is ground to 3287 but the set is tuned to operate at double frequency or 6575 kilocycles. Also we wish to inform you that these two trans mitters are being installed and tested today. s very truly. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM CCMPAKY LTD.Confidential C/388-10/l(b) The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for information Thk agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the 29th Api*44.- i941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Letter No.PA431 dated 24th March 1941 from the Chief ✓ M Local Representative, the Bahrain Petroleum Company. 2. Letter No.CON-774 dated 25th March 1941 from the Chief Local Kepresentative, the Bahrain Petroleum Com pany Limited, ^ 3. Letter No.CON-788 dated 23rd March 1941 from the Chief Local Representative, the Bahrain Petroleum Com pany Limited. 1 Subject. n ^ • -if / • . Use of Radio Transmitters by Bahrain Petroleum CompanyTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED .r .O Awall, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. No,PA»823 November 30, 1941 His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir: In accordance with our usual practice of informing you before using the Radio installed on the Launch 'Zellaq' we wish to confirm having telephoned to your office this morning the following times of contact between Awali and the Launch; Sunday Nov. 30, 1941 3.00 P.M. ' n n 6#00 ft Monday Dec. 1, 1941 8.00 A.M. The above times of contact will be strictly adhered to except in case of emergency and the frequencies used will be 6575 Kcs and 5050 Kcs for the n Zellaq w and Awali respectively. Yours very truly, M. H. LIPP ' Chief Local Representative THE BAHRSIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED IfcV W- '///Wv''I • i\ S ; i ■ / I . | ' / v J • ^ / -4. fo^iir] S»No:l. S.No:^. S.No:3. ■r\ S.No:4. / s , S.Norb. S.No:6. S.No:7. S.No:8. Letter dated 1/12/1933 from the Ciiief Local Representative. Letter No:0/5b0 aatea 11/33 to Ol'licer in charge,BaJiram Radio. Letter No:6/3 of 2/12/1933 from Officer-in-Ciiarge,Bahrain Radio. P.A . Submitted. Please see undertaking by the ShaiiOi of Bahrain in regard to the establishment of a Wireless Telegraph Installation at Bahrain datea the 19th June 1912. According to this the sole rights were presumably vestea in the I.S.T.D,ana nave jar been transferred to the Imperial and International Communications Company Limiteu (there is nothing on record in office to show the conditions under which the transfer was madej. i ' Jfi P.A. Please also see Article I of the Third Schedule to the Concession Agreement dated the 2nd December 1925. % iV Urgent letter dated 5-12-1933 ( from Chief Local Represent ative. ^ . P.A . Submitted. Please see notes above. Under Article 1 ot the Third Schedule to the Concession Agreement dated the 2nd December 1933,the Shaikh 'also grants the Company the exclusive right to consttuct and telegraph apparatus of all kinds in any part of the territory under' Ms control. % P-r Note on telephone message irom O.C.,I &amp; I C.C Ltd,Bahrain. Letter No:C/564 of 6-12-1933 to Adviser,Bahrain Government Letter No:C/565 of 6-12-33 to Chief Local Representative. Telegram No:566''ol o-12-33 to Resident &amp; S of S for India.-—— ■ '&lt;!' ' .i The Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. is Advice No. !• February 2, 1942, His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 9.45 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: JagTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED v \ &amp; %G 0 Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 2. February 3, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving probably at 10.45 a.m. equipment at 9.45 a.m. and / today for 'Che purpose ot contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jag3 ^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No, 3. February 5, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 9.45 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: leg't Ife ^ r&amp;'' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED v \* \cP Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, February 14, 1942, PA-963. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Attached hereto will you please find a copy of our Advice No. 4 dated February 10, 1942 on the subject of radio transmission. We very much regret delay in sending this Advice to you but it was inadvertently transmitted to Arabia with our mail for the Company there. Yours very truly. ^7%// M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Attach:The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Advice No. 4. February 10, 1942 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent. Bahrein. Dear Sir, Foi 4 your information , vie have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 5«50 p.m. today for the purpose of Contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jeg^ tJ? ^ - THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED V 0 ^ Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Advice No. 5. February 15, 1942. i ii His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Baiirein. Dear Sir, For yout* information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 9.30 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly. Chief Local Representative^ THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED SW: Jag idyh W ■K ^r The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited vv V 0 &amp; Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 6, February 18, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our ihtention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 9.30 a.m« today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW; Jag ■ ^THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED vjw® 0C 0 c&gt; Awali , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Advice No. 7. February 21, 1942. His Britannic Majesty 1 fi Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 9.45 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq ft . Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. S7/: Jeg &gt;y/■&gt; v \e .0° THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awal i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 8. February 24, 1942 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10. l-Q a »m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch ^Zellaq'. Youns very truly. ^ A \o&gt; Y\- The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited V 0 &amp; Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Advice No. 9, February 2G, 194c. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Baiirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of Using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10,30 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq/'. Yours very truly. Chief Local Representativej THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED SW: Jaglo THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No.10. March 7, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 11.00 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jag d 'v\VThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awall, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 11 March 11, 1942 His Britannic Majesty 's Political Agent, Balirein, Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10.50 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours _yery truly. -70 Chief Local Representative', THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Chief Local Representati SW; JagThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Advice No. 12 March 15th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Baiirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 11.00 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq if . Yours very truly. SW: JagTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, Advice No. 13. March 18th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10-30 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jag \vXTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Advice No. 14. March 19, 1942. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, ?or your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10.00 a.m. . today for the purpose of contacting our launch n Zellaq_ . Yours^yery truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW; JagTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 15. March 24, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Baiirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using cur radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 9.50 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: JsgTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Advice No. 16 March 29, 1942 His Britannic Majesty's political Agent, Baiirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10.00 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: JagTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Advice No. 17. April 2nd, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10.50 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jag l/A0^°' J/- Jp.. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Advice No&gt; 18 . April 4, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Ealii^ein. Dear Sir, For your information, We have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 9.00 8c 10.00 am today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Ycurs very truly. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jag- , • 11 o THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED c^ e Awall, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 19. April 5th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir , For your information., we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 10.00 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: JagTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 20. April 6th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 11«00 a.m. today for che purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW; JagwM &gt;• Jp* THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ^ % &amp;0 ^ Awal i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Advice No. 21. April 7th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent Baiirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using cur radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 11 a.m. &amp; 1 p .m.today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jag\V^ e &gt;»'- V C 0 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 21 Advice No. 22. April 8th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Balirein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 11.00 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, SW: Jsg |THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awall, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Advice No. 23. April 9th, 1942. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, For your information, we have to advise our intention of using our radio transmitting and receiving equipment at 11.00 a.m. today for the purpose of contacting our launch 'Zellaq'. Yours very truly. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHR3IN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jagvt\ CONFIRMATION OF COMMUNICATION BETWEEN* 'BBB' and 'KKK' Tf KXK tT using morse. Operator apparently inexperienced in telegraphy. Signals good and easily read. rT BB3' using Radio-Telephony. Speech very indistinct and hard to copy. ?ro'ba'bly uses a directional aerial. vVavelength used a'bout 44 metres 'by 'both stations. Following si pials were intercepted 'between 0900 G ,M ,T, and 0940 Cr,1. .7. on 6th January 1936. By TT Kf&lt; TT in morse. HAVE SACOME TO DAY ARE YOU SENDING A COOK ARE YOU SENDING A COOK GA By 'BBB' using R/T. Hallo Kallo KKK BBB calling KKK OK your message as this information has 'been requested present time T.'' this is 3BB standing 'by for KKK go ahead (Above is very disjointed, only scraps o. coi^vor: ■ tion could 'be intercepted) By 'K K' in morse. de KKK TOl.IORROW BEING liklL DAY IF DELAY NOT IL1P0LITE CAl^CEL ABOVE FORlvIER INSTRUCTIONS OKT F0RI\/IER INSTRUCTIONS OKT RUNNING TESTER TO DETERMINE IF n /ATER SHUT OFF- RUNNING TESTER TO DETERMINE IF r ' T ATER SHUT OFF- GA (Ahove message is complete) By 'BBB' using R/T. This is BBB calling KKK. ? ? Stand 'by for call up ? (Speech too indistinct) By 'K- k ' in morse, de KKK YOUR MESSAGE CUT OFF ALL OK ALL OK) IF YOU HAVE MORE IF YOU HAVE MORE - GA By 'BBB' using R/T. Hallo KKK Hallo KKK ( Speech to indistinct to copy) Both Stations apparently then closed down as nothing further was heard. iajm. 6/i/u ■SECRET. p.a. I vas given the following tv.o items of news (I cannot vouch for the authenticity) yesterday:- 1. Iijjf ' I 1- A (U'K ^ X«A ^ ^ The ^ahrain Petroleum Company wish to employ a Wireless Operator. S. .(( ^r 5'&gt; KKK has been overheard talking to San Francisco Re: 1. I reported to you a few days ago that BBB had asked KKK to send across a transmitter. This may have some connection with the employment of a Wireless Operator. Re:2. If the report regarding the employment pf a Wireless Operator is correct, the rtitentions d the Company are obvious. I may mention that my informants were two differentV 4 On the 30.1.19?6 I heard , KKK t calling 1 kkA } at about 'p 1 „ 19.00 hours. The following wasmrt of a conversation:- C-oUX •*/». dec • %' tT Fe received your message tonight but the reception was very very poor. Your voice was not only rough but at times the atmospherics were very strong'. , TT F.A.D wants to know and for you to tell us tomorrow night the mileage from Hafar si Bat in to A1 Bashuq. F.A.D is trying to figure why it should take camels five days from Hafar al Batin to A1 Bashuq.' 2. On the evening of the 31.1.1936, 'AAA* informed 'KilK* that the mileage was 85 kilometers. There was further conver sation but I couldn't listen to it for various reasons. 3. On the 5.P.1936 at 18.45 hours l KKK , called up 'DDD 1 . 'DDD 1 calling ^KK 1 (this was repeated several times.' T.F.H calling F.V.D at KKK. I have received following message by telegram:- Hasa, Saudi Arabia Safar 1354. To:- Company Jubail. The camels and camelmen are ready if you need them let me know by tomorrow. Saleh al Hav/as. ' (tht^ above message was repeated 3 times). Later the following was sent by DDD to KKK; ' f The boat will be ready for you on Friday and the captain wants $5.60/- for the trip. Please let me know if that price is O .K. I will stay in the office on Friday and will gladly help in loading the aeroplane'. (From the above two messages it is clear that 'DDD' is Jubail and 'KKK' Al Akhbar). Later KKK called up DDD. 3 Ks calling 3 Ds. O.K. DDD. Received your message very well tonight. The telegram which ^ou received this afternoon. Please disregard the telegram and we will inform F.A.D when he returns to KKK. There is no answer</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/448</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/448</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/21 (10/1 B) Bahrain Oil Concession: Proposal by the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited to install radio telephones'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-09-17T00:01:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (128 folios)</extent><extent>The file is formed by two files put together. The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order. There are notes at the end of the first part of the file (folios 82-90). The index is arranged chronologically and refers to documents within the file.</extent><extent>The foliation starts on first page of writing, in pencil in centre top of recto, then from folio 18 in top right corner of recto. The numbering starts with 1-41; 42,42A; 51,51A and carries on until 126, which is the last number given on the last folio of the file. The file is formed by two files together, so an additional foliation sequence starts on folio 93 (numbered 1).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file is formed by two files put together.The first part of the file contains minutes of meetings at Office of the Secretary of State for India in London, and correspondence and telegrams between the Political Agent in Bahrain, the Political Resident in Bushire, the Financial Adviser to the Government in Bahrain, Charles Darlymple Belgrave, and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) on the installation of radio telephone systems, to be used solely for telecommunications inside Bahrain and about BAPCO business.The second part of the file contains later documents, mainly BAPCO advising of their intention of using the radio equipment, from February to March 1942.There are notes at the end of the first part of the file (folios 82-90)</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Ḥamad bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah, Hakim of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Bahrain Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia Sa'ūd bin 'Abd al-'Azīz Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Communication methods</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>