<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003ba_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:56:17.190Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ O . P.Z.565a/l9^6. ^ &lt;rv |* ■ArtJ^iAsinr^tt ■•^j 4^Li. ^ tfcu . C. o THE GOLDSMITHS &amp; SILVERSMITHS COMPANY LTD. / 112, Regent Street, /o • $ * 24 London, W.1. *Z» MILITARY DEPT. 5th August,1956. The Secretary of State, India Office, Whitehall, SJ{. Sir, At the request of Lieut.Colonel B.H.Bonham Carter, we are writing to ask if you would favour us with the correct title of His Highness The Multan of Lahej of the Aden Protectorate. This is required to he incorporated in an inscription to he engraved on a piece of silver which we have heen commissioned to make for presentation to this gentleman, hy the Officers of the 5th/l4th Punjab Regiment. Thanking you in anticipation, We are, Yours faithfully. THE GOLDSMITHS &amp; SILVERSMITHS COMPANY,LIMITED^ a Sir, I have the honour to refer to the Resident's confidential despatch Ho. 65 of the 22nd of March regarding the succession to the Sultanate of L&amp;hej, and to inform you that I agree generally with the viewa expressed therein and the course of action proposed in paragraph 13. 2. The proposed reply to the Multan of Lahej should, however, be modified in the following manner:- («.) he should be informed that 'the contents of his letter are noted', instead of that 'the election has been noted', and (b) the word 'formal' should be omitted before 'recognition' in informing him that the recognition of his successor must be deferred until the latter's actual succession to the Sultanate* Colonel ^eilly, who has been consulted, agrees with these modifications* I have the honour to be, * Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, —* ) O •-’V J T„ THE ACTIHG HESIDEHT C .* &gt; - - - ? Downing Street, | *5 July, 1933. AT KDm.Register No. P. z. 2871/33. &amp; © SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. L &gt;ter telegram- from C. 0. Dat,r,d 17 th May Rec. Formally acknowledged 1933 Date. | Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairm^i Under Secretary ... / Secretary of State. Committee Under Secretary... Secretary of S^ite.. / xy. r. u*-» Aden Protectorate. Question of recognition of eldest son of the Sultan of Lahej as his successor. FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft Letter to C.O. concurring in proposal to approve course of action suggested by t he^Resident^ ^ /c» D • (I 95 J x -/ato® opportunity of Col. Reilly’s presence in London to clear the point up. As this is primarily a C.O. matter, it seemed best to obtain their concurrence before making an enquiry of Col. Reilly. I accordingly arranged with Sir D. Bray that I should write d.o. to the C.O. in the sense of the letter of 6th June below and, if they saw no objection, put the point to CoL ReiHy. / A A c ^ ^ ^ ^ A Col. Reilly came up to London yesterday, and he and Hr. Cowell discussed this question with Hr. Laithwaite and myself this morning. Col. Reilly informed us that he had the point regarding the importance of local custom prominently in mind, as well as the other considerations, in thinking over what action he should recommend in the peculiar circumstances. He is satisfied that the election was duly and properly made in a public manner by the electors, and that the majority of them (the custom is to elect by a majority) are genuinely in favour of the election and of the change of custom entailed thereby; he takes^a gram of salt CTfch the Sultan’s statement that it was the electors themselves who initiated the proposal of an election during the lifetime, but he has no evidence to the contrary. The election by the duly constituted electors is properly on record. The attempted assassination, of course, indicated the existence of some opposition; but this incident has had the effect of weakening the opposition and rallying further support to the party. It will thus be seen that Col. Reilly is satisxied on the main issue; he would see no objection, however, to slightly/&amp; ^ t /i V, ^ slightly modifying the proposed terms of his reply to the Saltan by substituting a statement that the contents of the Sultan’s letter are noted instead of the words H that the election has been noted”; this change, small thou^i it appears, gives an even more noncommittal ring to the proposed reply, and goes further in the direction of avoiding any implication that the Sultan’s account of the manner in which the election was brought about is necessarily taken as correct. From what Sir D. Bray told me, I think that there is no doubt that he would be satisfied by Col. Reilly’s account of the matter, and by the small change of wording suggested above. The Air Ministry and F.O. have now concurred in the proposal in the C.O.letter of 17th May. Perhaps the draft letter might be approved with the addition suggested in the margin. ]UJ '*■ (&gt;■ k1 Politic-g ^omwittee . Perhaps the attached revised draft might be approved. After speaking to Sir R. Glancy, I saw Col. Reilly yesterday. He did not intend any emphasis on the word 'formal' in para. 13 of his despatch, and sees no objection to its being omitted in the instructions to be given to him. &gt;*(J3P.z.2871/33. 1 Minute Paper. POLITICAL Department. Please see the passages marked in the A Intelligence summaries regarding the election as heir apparent and attempted assassination of the eldest son of the Sultan of Lahej. As explained in the Resident’s despatch of 22nd March enclosed with the C.O. letter the custom for many years pa.st in regard to the succession to the Sultanate has been that after the death of the reigning Sultan his successor is elected by certain tribal Aqils and Q,adhis and later recognised officially by the Resident (unless there are cogent reasons for non-recognition). As the result of an unsuccessful conspiracy in 1930 to remove the Sultan and arrange the succession of a member of a rival branch of the ruling family. His * Highness made tentative proposals to the Residency that he should ensure continuity in the succession by 9 proclaiming his eldest son as heir apparent, but was advised by Sir Stewart Symes not to do so. In February of this year, however. His Highness informed Colonel Reilly that an election had been held and that Sultan Fadl has been unanimously elected as his successor. The Resident was about to express objection to this action which was taken without consulting him when he heard ol the attempt on Suloan Fadl’s life which made it impolitic for him to do so. He therefore confined himself to asking the Sultan ot Lahej for an explanation of his reasons for departing from customary practice in regard to the succession. His Highness replied that the intention was to guard against strife and dissension in the event of his death. Colonel Reilly sympathises with the Sultan and sees considerable advantage in a settlement of the succession during/during his lifetime if it is loyally observed on his death. His Highness is a capable ruler and perhaps the most important of the Protectorate Chiefs and his territories adjoin the settlement of Aden. On the other hand Colonel Reilly does not recommend any departure on our part from the existing procedure, since he considers that recognition of a pre-elected successor would seldom be effective. He therefore proposes to inform the Sultan that the election has been noted but that formal recognition of his successor must be deferred until the latter’s actual succession. This is primarily a matter for the Colonial Offic e who propose to approve the Resident’s proposal subject to the concurrence of the other interested departments. We may I think concur, and a draft letter to the Colonial Office is submitted accordingly. /7-I think we ought to proceed with extreme caution over this case. Happily Colonel Reilly is still in the (r\ country and it will he very helpful if^j^ can discus? A /* with him personally. It is at all times a tricky business to introduce changes into ancient tribal custom. Left to themselves tribes are very chary of doing so, but if things go wrong they have their own ways of rectifying matters. The introduction of ourselves as the Paramount power is a doubly . -A disturbing ^actor: on the one hand, reformers use us for their own ends; on the other, we act as a brake on the ordinary forceful rectification of a reform which has gone wrong. It is clear that succession in Lahej depends on hereditfe^^tempered, and indeed sanctioned, by election, fnis double principle is well-known: it obtains e.g. in Kalat, where the chiefs have a strong feeling that the son of the Khan should sit in the seat of his fathers and an equally strong feeling that thev have themselves an over- ncing right to decide whether to put him there, ft* is the free play of these two principles which is chiefly responsible for the control the hereditary and yet elected leader exercises by semi-divine right over the tribesmen. '' It is of course the natural desire of every ruler to make his dynasty secure during his lifetime. His obvious tactics in a case like this would be to win over a certain number of the electors to declare for a change in the old custom . Before we ourselves should recognise, even in the cautious form proposed, so radical a change, we should - have/2 . have to he satisfied that the declaration of custom was made by the whole body of electors and was made in grim earnest. I confess I am very sceptical in the present case. For one thing, in adopting election during the chief’s lifetime, the electors are real ear to surrendering their free powers of elect!-... ffould require the electors to declare their custom in the most formal and authoritative manner in open Jirga or Durbar or the like. It is not clear whether the Resident has had any such evidence: certainly the word of the ruler himself would be unsatisfying. Even without the attempted assassination of the newly-elected heir as the Ajamatic sequel to the new-fangled election, caution would have been desirable, for in a tribal state of society law and order and the whole well-being of tribe^ depend on the observance of accepted custom. As it is, it is imperative. 41401 5000 11.32 P.Z. 2871/33. ■ i Department. '■v W12E2. U.S.S., c.o. Copy to India 2 r JUN 1933 Sir, With reference to C.O. letter, No. 17963/33, of 17th May, 1933, regarding the succession to the Sultanate of Lahej, I arr. directed by the S. of S. for I. to say that he suggests that it might be preferable to inform the Sultan M that the contents of his letter are noted** rather than M that the election has been noted', and to omit the word 'formal' before 'recognition' in informing him that the recognition of his successor must be deferred until the latter*s actual accession to the Sultanate. Otherwise Secy. Sir Samuel Hoare agrees with the proposal of the S. of S. for the Colonies to approve the course of action suggested in para. 13 of the despatch from the Resident at Aden enclosed with your letter. 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the F.O. and A.M. f^L) J. a WALTON. /Draft Paper. P.Z. 2871/33. political Department* DRAFT LETTER. The Under-Secretary of* State, Colonial Office, With reference to Colonial Office letter No.17963/33, of 17th May 1933, regarding the succession to the Sultanate of Lahej, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that^ subject to the concurrence of the other interested departments-^- he/ agrees with the proposal of the Secretary of State for the Colonies to approve the course of action suggested in paragraph 13 of the despatch from the Resident at Aden enclosed with your letter. * 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office and Air Ministry.IHDIji OFFICE 9 WHITEHALL» S.tf. 1 . 16th Jane, 1933. with farther reference to the question of the Lahej succession, about which we talked on 9th June, I write to say that the Political Committee here haye raised another small point, yi? . t the ap Topriateness of the word '‘formal' before '’recognition* in the third line of oaragraoh 13 of ^den despatch. Ho* 65, of 22nd 1 arch* I mentioned this to Reilly when he happened to be here on 14th June, and he said that he attached no a &gt;ecial emphasis to the word ‘’formal*, and would be content if it were omitted from his instructions. Vie are therefore making this small suggestion also in our official reply to your letter, no. 17963/33 of 17th ! ay. (Sgd.) J.C. Walton. H.R. Cowell, Esn. # C.‘ *G*iNtffcXEB 'O &lt; 7 . In any further communication on this subject, please quote ■v No. V and address —not to any person by name, out to— The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. 205 %&gt; ... : rl£,£-J THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Adairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop'uLo of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193J ;si' Refere?ice to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. \d O' XU 26 SECRET DEPT. INDIA •*4 Similar letter sent to I 4—6130 8 i 8 &gt; ( 2 ) 'Q. .6\U £561/299/91. FORtflGH OFFICE, S.W.l. 26til Jay, 1933. 2tl( a? 7/ Sir, With reference to your letter No. 17963/33 of the 17th Jay regarding the succession to the Sultanate of Lahe,;, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to request * yon to inform Secretary Sir Philip Cunliff©-Lister that he concurs in the proposal to aoprove the course of action suggested by the Resident at Aden in paragraoh 13 of his confidential despatch No. 65 of the 22nd Jarch. £• Copies of this letter are being sent to the India Office and the air Ministry. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Undersecretary of State, Colonial Office.Sir* T conrcanded by th*&gt; air CouoclX to re for to Colonial Office letter Ho. 17963/35 amtml the 17th Mar* for »ardin^ a espy of &amp; despatch from the Hoeident at Aden regardin.tr the sacoeseion to the iclt^nate of ^ahej and to eocaaint you* for the iafomation of th ^eoretar? of tale for ‘he Jolonies, that they are in a^reemeat srith the proeel are proposed # Copies of this letter are beln« sent to the foreign Offioe and India, Offlee. I uie. Sir* Tour obedient errant. The Jnder Secretary of tate. Colonial Office, Downing :treet, s. SI # 1. (Sgd.) CHARLES EVAKS, far Seoreta*^. ■ 9should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, Communications on this subject Downing Si | j May , 1933 . Downing umber quoted: 17963/33. London, S.W. the following London, S.W.l. r i ^ i Sir I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe-Liater to transmit to you, to be laid before the Resident at Aden regarding the succession to the Sultanate of Lahej. 2. Sir Philip Cunliffe-lister agrees with the Residents views as to the attitude which he should adopt in the matter, and, subject to Sir Samuel Hoare’s concurrence, he proposes to approve the course of action suggested in paragraph 13pf the Resident's despatch. 3. A similar 3igi Samuel Hoare, a copy of a despatch from Office and Air Minis I am, Your most obedient servant. THE UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE, INDIA OFFICE.;r . Copy, coiyyii}EMTiAi&gt; i Wo 4 ^ 66* THE RESIDENCY, Aden, 2and l» arch, 1933. Sir, I hare the honour to refer to the recent political events in Lahej in connection with the euooeseion to the Sultanate, that have been reported briefly in iolitioal Intelligence Sumaiary, paragrapha £t aeq . Z* For very many years the custom in regard to the succession to the Sultanate of lahej has been that after the death of the reigning Sultan hia successor la elected by certain tribal Aqila and .adhie, who are entitled to do so. The election is then reported to the Resident, and the new Sultan is accorded official re ognition unless there are very cogent reaaona to withhold it. The customary rooeciure thus briefly outlined is oommon to the whole 1 roteotorate. 3. There are five branches of the family of the Sultan of lahej, in two of which (the All Kuhsin and the Fadhl lluhain) the sucoesaion has been confined, with fairly regular alternation, since the death of the oonnion ancestor, Sultan Kuhsin ’’adhl, in 1847. 4. On the ?iOOei&gt;eion of the present Sultan, Hia Highness Sir abdui Karim bin Fadhl Ali Kuhain, in 1918, the heads of the 4 ad hi uh&amp;ln branch re fused to rcco j - nise him. In 1919 a rapproaohment was brou :ht nbout betwesa His Kajeaty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, London.this dissident element and His Highness, but the animosity still smouldered, and in 1930 it brojte out in the form of a conspiracy, instigated by these persons during the absence of His Highness in India, to remoYe him and to arrange the succession of a member of the Fadhl Muhsln branch* The conspiracy was discoYered; and, on his return from India, the Sultan took such action against the ringleaders as he hoped would put on end to overt opposition to his authority. 5. In consequence of this incident His Highness made tentative proposals to the Residency that he should ensure Continuity in the succession by proclaiming his eldest son, Sultan &gt;*acihl bin Abdul Karim as heir apparent, -y predecessor advised him not to do so and the matter 1 appeared to have dros&gt;ped. 6 . On the lath February of this year, however, His Highness informed me that at the instance of the electors, and v.ith his permission, an election had been held, that his eldest son Sultan Fadhl bin /ibdul Karim had been unanimously elected as his euoeescor, and that he had ancordingly nominated him as such. 7* His Hi hness had caused or allowed these steps to be taken without prior reference to the Residency, find I was about to express my objections to this procedure when the report was received of the attempted assassination of Sultan Fadhl at the hands or at the instigation of the leaders of the Fadhl luhsin brunch (vide Political Intelligence Summary paragraphs 22 o 0 , et seq). This new circumstance made it impolitic for me to sdyi. e His Ri chness to retract his reoogniti n of Sultan 'adhl as hishla successor, for the reason that His Highness's acquiescence in my request might seem to he a concession to violence; and 1 therefore considered it advisable to confine myself at the moment to asking His Highness for an explanation of the reasons that had prompted him in departing from the customary practice in regard to the succession* 8* In reply His Highness explained that his action was designed to guard against the strife and dissension that are the usual consequences of disputes regarding the succession on the death of a tribal Chief. He argued that the hultanate of lahej has come to bo recognised as the centre of arbitration between tribal Chiefs over a wide area, and that it is therefore particularly necessary that continuous security and order should be ensured in it; and he pointed out that continuance of the custom hitherto existing in regard to the succession tended towards multiplicity of claimants and complexity of issue. of on election during his life-time, and that he had. to His Majesty's Corernment. 10. A settlement of the succession during the life-time of the present Sultan will have considerable advantages if it is loyally observed hen his death occurs. Since 1918 and especially during the past five years, the He further contended that the electors, who are the custodians of custom, hf^d themselves initiated the proposal acceded to their wishes in the best interests of his State 9. I have told His Highness that I am reporting what has occurred and the explanation that he has given ms Sultanat#b Sultanate of Lahej has assumed an importance unknown before \ Oreat 1 ar, prinoipally due to the personality of the teent Sultan and to his advisers -ind aealstants from his i branch of the family. ^nd the very close contact that \ been established between His Highness and the Residency in the consideration of all major matters of general importance in the irotectorate reader continuity of succession {and consequently of policy), at Inhej, very desirable. 11. In view, however, of the uncertainty that must, in the nature of rab tribal polity, still exist as to the actual accession of an heir-apparent on the death of a ruling Chief, 1 consider that official recognition of a pre-eleoted successor would seldom be effective, and ought not to be accorded. la. ~M2e, therefore, I tut sympathetic towards the efforts of the :ultan of Lahej to protect the admirable results of his organisation and industry in Lahej from disintegration at the hands of a less able, and possibly iiOstile, successor who might be elected from another brruich of the family, after his death, 1 do not recommend any departure, on our part, from the existing procedure in regard to succession. 13. 1 propose, therefore, subject to your approval, to limit myself to informing His Highness that the election has been noted, but that formal recognition of his successor must be deferred until the latt r f e actual accession to the .&gt;ult mate; and I intend to avoid the use of iny expression th t would im ly a ,;iu rantee by His Majesty’s Government of the arr&amp;ngsm*mt that has been made. I have, Akj ., (signed) 3.R.Reilly Resident, etc.12b ^ Communications on this subject si ild be addressed to— Ihe Undek Secretary of State, Colonial Office, &lt; Sub ject London, S.JVY.l, ! P. zTi 4 ^ and the following number quoted • n-»vy» - ' 2324 ' x i -v 1933 Reference to previous correspondence: I j€,tter from tJie Colonial Office of the ^ ^ transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Coloniesi PARAPHRASE TELEGRAM from th« Roaidant Secretary of State for the Soloniaa, xier t j the Dated 6 th April 1 (Received, Colonial Ibffi 1&gt; Zs p. No. 20. %W«4 /V )U^ LJ4* r r i., 6th Ar&gt;r: 1 1633.' 1933 y m-h referwm to p&amp;IIfical inteii i ( ;ert 08 surrmarie 3 112U a?id 2260 I have to inform you that as a result of the conspiracy against Sultan of Labe ’ in 7 ’ arch, I9'6u and of the attempt on the life of his eldest son in February 1933, His Highness has asked that four of principal conspirators whc are his relatives may be deported from his territories,. Having regard to the special position of His Highness in Protects,rute and in relation to Men of need for political stability in l,ahej i consider that removal of these persons to a distance is necessary. It is not considered desirable to place them elsewhere in Protectorate or in Ade(? n omitted) for fear of subversive intrigue with tribes«. I recommend their deportation to Zanzibar or Palestine where they would be hamless. I should be glad to be informed whether either Government would consent to receive them md to withhold facilities for return for at least four years. 3ultan of Lahej will arrange for their travelling and maintenance charges to be met by payments throu^i me. Similar case occurred in 1926 and 1931 when Government of India with the Approval of Secretary* of State authorised deportation of a Chief from Sharga in Persian Gulf to Aden, May I have an urgent reply by telegraph. ft©) VPARAPIil^SE TELEGRAM from the Secretary of State for the ^ Colonies to the Acting Resident at Adem (Sent 4,45 p.su, 20th April* 1933,) rmt t=0 «-a W &lt;9 *9 w&gt; «« c^» cJt No.15, Reference my telegram of 6th April No.12. The suggestion that conspirators should be sent to Zanzibar is deprecated by the Resident owing to risk of intri^iea and I am not in favour of Palestine for similar reasons, Seychelles appears to me suitable place and I have consulted Governor, He has replied that he has no objection and states that the estimated yearly cost for the four individuals to cover food rent and guards will be five thousand rupees. If you and Sultan agree to deportation to Seychelles will you please make arrangements direct with the Governor.(P. 2244/30) SECRET . Extract from Aden Political Intelligence Summary No. 165 for week ending 8th March, 1930. I. ADEN PROTECTORATE. 1120. It is reported that a conspiracy directed against the person of the SULTAN of LAHEJ, and alleged to have been inspired by SULTANS ALI and FADHL, sons of the late SULTAN SIR AHMED FADHL, K.C.S.I., was discovered daring the recent absence of His Hi^iness in India (vide paragraph 1112). The movement was abortive, and His Highness has the situation in hand.(P.Z. 1469/33) SECRET . Extract from Aden Political Intelligence Summary No. 319 for week ending 21st February, 1933. I, ADEN PROTECTOR AT hi . 2260. An attempt was made on the life of SULTAN FADH1, the elder son of His Highness the SULTAN of LAHEJ on the night of 19th February. Two pistol shots were fired at him at close quarters, one penetrating an eye, and the other the groin. SULTAN FADHL is progressing satisfactorily. The perpetrator of the deed who was the nephew of the AtJR of DIP AL AMIR was killed on the spot by SULTAN AHMED BIN MEHDI, FADHL'S cousin. The deed is supposed to have been instigated by members of other branches of His Highness's family who were opposed to the election of His Highness's son as Heir Apparent. Several arrests have been made, chief among whom are SULTANS 'ALI and FADHL, sons of the late SIR AHMED FADHL, K.C.S.I., and SULTAN AHMED MUNASSAR who are accused of being responsible for the conspiracy (vide paragraph 1120 ).sbcbst 4 The Res4d&lt; Aden, 1st March 1931 X: \ is) V '‘v Political Intelligence Summary No*320 for the week ending k 8 th X February 1933* I 4 ADSW PROTECTOR ATE* 2262,' Lieutenant-Colonel B*R.REILLY, CIE*, 0 BE 4 , accompanied by Captain HiV^ROSE, Personal Assistant, and Flying-Officer J*R.WEMYSS, • left ADM in 'PENZANCE' (Ccanmander FARQUHAR, D*S.CO on 28th February, for a tour of SOCOTRA, $ISHN, MUKALLA, AL HADHRAMAUT, BXR *^1 and BALIHAF. 2263* (Reference paragraph 1906), Lieutenant-Colonel BOSCAWM arrived in ADM on 19th February aid left for AL HADHRAMALT on 25th February* 2264* (Reference paragraph 2255). LORD LAMINGTON left ADEN for PORT SUDAN on 18th February, en route to KHARTOUM aid the UNITED KINGDOM. 2265. Sultan •AIDRUS BIN MUHSIN AL *AFIFI, Chief of the LONER YAF»A (BENI QASID) tribe, paid his annual official visit to ADEN from 14th to 21st February* During his visit, he v/as given a flight over his own Capital* 2266* (Reference paragraph 2260)* (1) Sultan FADHL continues to make progress, but vail lose the sight of one eye* (2) The Resident, in forwarding to His Highness the Sultan of LAHEJ, a copy of a protest against the election by the opposition and in addressing His Highness on the unconstitutional action taken by him in having his son elected Heir Apparent, asked His Highness for his considered comments* The main points in Hts Highness's reply to the Resident's letter may be summarised as follows (a) Danger of tribal fighting end family disputes tn the death of a Sultan, if no Heir Apparent is elected. (b) Necessity for the Sultan of LAHEJ, as Protectorate 'arbitrator', to have an orderly realm* (c) Increasing multiplicity of members of the different family branches, thereby making disputes mere likely and the security of the succession to one particular branch more advisable* (d) Request for the Resident's favourable consideration of the election. ( 8 ) Under instructions from the Resident, the Acting Political Secretary visited His Highnesw to ensure that the arrested persons would be given a fair trial and that no extreme penalty would be imposed on them v/ithout first consulting the R e sident* His Highness readily gave this assurance but pointed out the necessity ©f taking adequate steps to put an end to the opposition's disloyalty to him once and for all* The Acting Political Secretary made known to His Highness the Resident's recognition of this necessity ahd of the fact that it might mean deportation of a lengthy term of imprisonment for the chief conspirators* (4) Sultan AHMED MUNASSAR has been acquitted of any complicity in the recent outrage against Sultan FADHL, and his branch of the family, with the exception of of FADHL BIN 'ABDULQAWI, has expressed its loyalty to the Sultan* (5) The er± crime is universally condemned and it appears that His Highness has the tribes and notables almost unanimously on his side, the opposition party now being confined to the descendants ef the late SIR AHMED FADHL, and some mambers of the ’ABDULLA HUHSIN FADHL branch* m JTHE _YEMEN. 22o7* JEAN KOUDRACHOFF, a Russian, and his wife, arrived at HODBIDA on 9th February, to act as Manager of the HODEIDA branch of the Russian Trad mg ^Company vice N«SI!pG:N proceeding on leave. MRS* KOUDRACHOFF isSSCRBT. Political Intelligence ^Ict February 1933* The Residency, I ' , C2nd February 1933* 19 for the week ending I. AjDEIT PROT BCT 0P^,TE. 2260* An attempt was made on the life of SULTAK FADKL, the elder son of His Highness the SULTAH of LAHEJ on the night of 19th February, Two pistol shots were fired at him at close ^sn quarters, one penetrating an eye, and the other the groin* SULTAN FADHL is progressing satisfac torily* The perpetrator of the deed who was the nephew of the AMIR ef DAR AL AMIR was killed on the spot by SULTAN AHMED BIN MEKDI, FADHL 1 S cousin* The deed is supposed to have been instigated by members of other branches of His Highness’s family vJho were opposed to the election of His Highness’s son as Heir Apparent. Several arrests have been made, chief among whom are SULTANS 'ALI and FADHL, sons of the late SIR AHMED FADHL, IC*C*S*I&lt;, and SULTAN AHMED MUNASSAR who are accused of being responsible for the conspiracy, (vide paragraph 1120). 2261* The BEIDKANI (RASASI) SUET AN, KUSEIN BIN AHMED, vfoo lives at MISHV/ARA, is reported to have risen against the ’AMIL of BEIDHA, and t© be supported by deveral sections of the RASASI tribe* Details are at present lacking* II* THE YEMEN. Nothing ef interest to report* Sd/ M«C*Lake, AgiPolitical Secretary* His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, London* NOTES- DISTRIBUTION AS USUAL*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003ba_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1464</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003ba</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1464</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 1/28 'Aden Protectorate, Lahej; conspiracy against the Sultan of Lahej and question of recognition of his eldest son as his successor'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-25T22:09:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (37 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 37; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers relating to the attempted assassination of Sultan Fadhl bin Abdul Karim, in response to his being named heir apparent to the Sultanate of Lahej by his father, Sultan 'Abd al Karim II ibn Al Fadhl Al 'Abdali.The file consists of copies of Political Intelligence Summaries submitted to the Colonial Office by the Protectorate Secretary, and correspondence between the Aden Chief Commissioner, the Secretary of State for the Colonies, and the Secretary of the India Office Political Department (John Charles Walton).The correspondence concerns: the assassination attempt; the petition against the election of Sultan Fadhl bin Abdul Karim; the break from the standard procedure of electing a successor following the death of the incumbent Sultan; discussion of the appropriate response to be issued from the Resident; the punishment of the conspirators, and their eventual deportation to the Seychelles. The Aden Chief Commissioner had initially proposed deportation to Zanzibar or Palestine, but this was overruled by the Secretary of State for the Colonies, 'owing to risk of intrigues'.At folios 24-27 is a communication from the Resident regarding the custom of tribal succession in the Aden Protectorate, providing a brief summary of successions in the early twentieth century.The file includes a divider which gives a list of the correspondence contained within the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for the Colonies, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief Commissioner, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Secretary, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Fadhl bin Abdul Karim Al 'Abdali</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>'Abd Al Karim II ibn Al Fadhl Al 'Abdali Sultan</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Lahej</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Kings and rulers--Succession</topic></subject><subject><topic>Attempted assassination</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003ba#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>