<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000009_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-15T10:17:54.810Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Tele pram Q From To Repeated. V-- 06 H.IR Ambassador, Ba^hdad.^ / Political Resident, Bushile IIo^ CliJ .4 Political Apent, Kuwait Mo.8 Political Agent, Bahrain No. 10 Political Agent, Muscat. No.4 H.M. Consul-General, Basra. Bavinr. Dated 21th February received 3rd March 1944. U.J.A. Minister here has been instructed to visit Persian Gulf and plans to leave March 5th or March 6th for Basra thence to Kuwait, Bahrain and possibly Muscat. Full particulars follow. Grateful if all concerned would extend usual courtesies and facilities. II.M. Representative Baghdad.Teaepram I^ron To Repeated. No. C/461 Dated 22nd Political Arent, I/luscat H.I . Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Resident, Bushire. and received 23r Narch 11/44. i I Political Your telepran No. Resident.) Visit of 4 February No. 4A^o U.S.A. Minister. 2. If this is unofficial I am happy to entertain him provided party is not too larpe and it is realised that rood fresh food will shortly be unobtainable. 3. If vis-it is official Sultan has ashed me to say he is not in Muscat and will not return until the autumn. POLITICAL. rt ONFIDENTIAL D.O. No. C/4S4 Political Agency, Muscat. 28th March 1044. V isit of U.3. Min ister to. ] lusca t. My dear Sir Geoffrey 5 './ill you please refer to ny telepram No. C/461 dated the 22nd March 1044 on the above subject. 2. The Sultan was obviously not happy fcbout the proposed visit. He drew very pointed attention to the fact that Mr. Knabenshuhe, when he came to Muscat in 1934, had been appointed a Special Mnvoy and it was clear that His Highness had no desire to welcome either at Muscat or Salalah a peripatetic U.S. Minister from Iraq. 3. He was also annoyed because the approach had been made through us and not direct. But Mr. Knabenshuhe's visit was similarly arranged, and in any case, his annoyance was not directed at us but at the U.S.A. 4. Paragraph 9 (b) of Part I of the Muscat Administration Report for 1936 says that American interests remained in the hands of the Political Agent throughout the year. It appears that this is still the arrangement and that if the ; U.S. Minister had come, his visit could only have been unofficial unless he had received a special appointment under the American Treaty, as in trie case of Mr. Knabenshuhe. The point is academic at the moment but may arise again. 5. So far, the only American interests which have cone my way are an enquiry from Baghdad regarding burial facilities, to which I replied that a Christian cemetery and an American Mission parson were available, and the renewal of Mrs. Thoms' registration as an American citizen, which I attested as district Judge Muscat and forwarded to her Consul in Karachi. Yours sincerely, Sd. R.D. Metcalf. The Hon'ble ~&gt;ir Geoffrey Prior ,K.C. I.B. , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. B ushire ..© ,i:iviA LiiiCCT coryiD^Tila. RQpeu' D^ted 8th 3ha.rge d^-Lff^ires., Baghdad. For ei gri office, I 23 Buahiie Ho.3. ) Kuwait No. l . j Sfevin&amp;tf ^ Bahrain Ho. 3.)^ J r -r ..pril 1944. a; . ^.6 Baghdad telekrat. , , tjr , „ ^ i I H * 4 a j Since his return on March 2lst United States Minister has talked » 4 uite a lot about his visits to Kuwait a .id Bani ai n but without indicating that they had any particular objective other than those outlined by His Majesty’s ambassador in his telegram under reference. i t 9,m424 i . it is satisfactory that Mr. Henderson was much pleased with his reception by the Political agents concerned whom he described as doing *a grand job” in support of the ^nglo-;»merican war effort. THOMPSON No. 357-3. Bri t i ah Re sid en cy &amp; 0ons u la te » Gene ra 1, Bush ire, the 1st May 1944. !opy forwarded, vdth compliments, to 1 . His Majesty’s secretary of ntate for India The India Office, Lcr^Brr , V' The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, iTSV, r DELHI. 2.h*h® CONFIDENTIAL. ^ ^ wars—*-...,, ')«C* No. a/*7 EX'l ^isoa h • y I The Hon^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to . / oO ’« c% * 944 * ^ to v r^nrao^rc. n The India Office, LONDON, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain. D a ted... 1&amp;S.. St h.., ^ r i ±..IS$4 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Residency demi-official *\inerican Minister at Baghdad Letter No. C/3, dated the tour of the Persian 9th April 1944, with Gulf. enclos ur es. w ki w |( -^1 )| fr. i mV -*'• (Received under Baghdad Bmbasay Endorsement Ho« 306/16/44 dated 28 th March 1944). f &gt; q _____ I I C) yJ Q (§r* No. 306/16/44. British Embassy, Baghdad^/ A 28 th liarah 1944. _ My dear Minister, Many thanks for your letter of March 25th, in which you were so good as to express your appreciation of the courtesies and facilities which British officials were able to extend to you during your recent tour in the Persian Oulf. I am very glad that you should have had an opportunity of meeting them and have had much pleasure in sending them copies of your kind letter. Yours sincerely, Sd. KINAHAN CORNWALLIS . His Excellency The Hon'ble Loy W. Henderson. Legation of the United States of America* Baghdad, March 25 th, 1944. Dear Mr* Ambassador ; I would be grateful if you would inform the appropriate British authorities of my appreciation of the courtesy which was shown to Consul Fletcher of Basra and myself by the British Political Agents at Kuwait and Bahrain during my recent visit to those Shaikhdoms* No one could have been more considerate and helpful than was Mr. Pelly, whose guests we were while at Kuwait. As a result of his helpful attitude, we were able to meet the Shaikh as well as all the members of the British and American colonies^ and also to acquaint ourselves to a most satisfactory degree with the town of Kuwait and the adjacent countryside. MT. Higginbottom was similarly cooperative and helpful at Bahrain. He left nothing undone to make our visit there a success. He assisted us in meeting the Shaikh, and through his friendly hospitality we also became acquainted with a number of the more prominent British officials on the island. I may add that both Mr. Flethher and I have been deeply impressed by the excellent work for our common cause which the self-sacrificing British Political Agents are carrying on in the Persian Gulf. I wish also to thank you for notifying these officials in advance of our visit. Sincerely, 3d« Loy W. Henderson. His Excellency, Sir Kinahan Cornwallis, British Ambassador, Baghdad.ii-m 1 | 25 APR 1944 ^^^mis^Majesty’s 'Ambassador . WTtfi th» Q^mjtl man^fe ^ British.. Embassy, of tk« ^ a Bagdad. Under &amp;*»** rfcary of State . for Foreign Affaire vtf* 28 th. March,..., 1944 .... Reference to previous correspondence .sy/uyiAi/^^/f. Foreign Office tele gram No.133 of 18/2/44 (1*50 Description of Enclosure. l^DCtCL, Tinii ah Name and Date. Subject. Bagdad No.306/16/44 of 28th March, 1944 from Ambassador to American Minister. U.S.Legation No.- of March 25th,1944 from U.S.Minister to Bagdad Ambassador. U.S.Minister’s tour in Persian Gulf. Expression of appreciation of courtesies extended by British officials in the Persian Gulf. (Copies sent to P.R.in the P.G., P.A.Kowi #K*. &gt; i f. 2 -5 APR 3x.Affs,Dept New Delhi, P.A., Bahrein and €»it) *v. 3479 21952—1 (4)€ gOFY Legation of the • United States of America. Bagdad, arch 25,1944. Dear Mr. Ambassador! I would be grateful if you would Inform the appropriate British authorities of my appreciation of the courtesy which was shown to Consul Fletcher of Basra and myself by the British Political Agents at Kuwait and Bahrein during my recent visit to those Sheikhdoms. No one could have been more considerate and help ful than was Mr. Pelly, whose guests we were while at Kuwait. As a result of his helpful attitude, we were able to meet the Sheikh as well as all the members of the British and American colonies, and also to acquaint ourselves to a most satisfactory degree with the town of Kuwait and the adjacent countryside. Mr. Higginbottom was similarly cooperative and helpful at Bahrein. He left nothing undone to rake our visit there a success. He assisted us in meeting the Sheikh, and through his friendly hospitality we also became acquainted with a number of the more prominent British officials on the island. I may add that both Mr. Fletcher and I have been deeply impressed bv the excellent work for our common cause which the self- sacrificing British Political Agents are carrying on in the Persian Gulf. I wish also to thank you for notifying these officials in advance of our visit. Sincerely, Sd/- Loy W. Henderson. His Excellency Sir Kinahan Cornwallis, British Ambassador, Bagdad•s 1 168 5^ 7 ^ • *'&lt;&lt; iu. -w C^&gt; Vf(th th« &lt;sif tl»» Under &lt; **m***m*$ *f for Forefgn AVf&amp;Jre | 044 Secret from b^gd^d to foreign office &gt; 0 T DEPARTtlENT^L NO.l, Mr. Thompson No. 291. BTnlprTl, 1944. D. 5.58 p.m. G.M.T. ,8th April, 1944, R. 6.25 p.m. D.B.S.T.Sth April, 1944. [][][] ill w , H Bagdai tel§ A . , s , i , nQ f his return on March 31st the United States Minister has talked, quite a lot about his visits to Koweit and Bahrein out witnout indicating that they had any particular objective other than those outlined by His Majesty*s Ambassador in his telegram under reference. 2. It is^satisfactory that Mr. Henderson was much pleased with his reception by the political agents concerned v/hom he described as doing 'a grand job” in support of Anglo-American war effort. O.T. as[CYPHER] *ttth cr * .♦ary *tat# Undo*’ - . ' Attains tor r v.t -»■» ^._ ., DEP.'iRTimiTAL KOi -1. &lt;S&gt; kTT. ,hR^ i) FROM BAGDAD TO FOREIGN OFFICE.: Sir A* Cornwallis No&gt; 224 21st March 1914 O J D. 3o50j p.nj G1.!T March 19d4 R. 6.20. p.n. BST 21st March 1941- 8 8 8 8 3ECRBT _, r i ^, /Jb , o Your telegram No» 155. ~ ^ O j H^Ouuelli)}^ United States Minister’s 1?our is 'being nade on instructions iron State Department. He is being accompanied by United States Consul Basra. He discussed details of his itinerary with me and I requested British authorities Persian Gulf to extend usual courtesies and faculties. I have no information regarding any special object of this tour but assume he is ’’getting acquainted” with United States oil installations and personnel at Bahrein and elsewhere while at the same time studying political conditions and investigating trade possibilities. Abile at Basra before leaving for Koweit ne visited Khoramshahar (where there is considerable American military and shipping activity, concerned principally with add to Russia) and Abadan. All this dove tails with what I have already reported about increasing United States political-economic interest in Middle East. 2,. I will endeavour to elicit Mr. Henderson’s impressions on his return.. O.T.P. {hdia »• « /INDEXED OUTWARD TELEGRAM © H X-,* : / 1 *'&gt; f r A 1 i z. ^ J E.1657/-/&amp;1 [CYPHER] With the O*moment® of triG Under Sgo for Foreign Affairs 5 . ,544 tary #f 127 Tz V .J 2 2 i^Aft DEP.\RTMEMTi\L H0-. 1 1 PROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO BAGDAD No« 135 18th March 1944 n n D« 7 #35 p.m, 18th Iviarch 1944 n Political Resident in Persian Gulf reports that American Minister Bagdad is at present touring Arab coast of Persian Gulf, Do you know the object of this tour? It would interest us if you were able to elicit his impressions when he gets back as they will no doubt colour Mr.Wallace Murray's views when he comes to London.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000009_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/906</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000009</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/906</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 1078/44 'United States Minister, Baghdad: Tour of Arab Coast of Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-20T22:11:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (17 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 19; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding a tour of the Arabian coast by Loy W Henderson, United States Minister to Iraq, and his interactions with the Political Agents at Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat, and with Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. As well as Mr Henderson, the primary correspondents are: Government of India; India Office; Foreign Office; British Legation, Baghdad; Political Agency, Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Tours</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ambassador to Iraq</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000009#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>