<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00014b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:07:34.275Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">mmr c SECRET D.O. No•2043-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, datedt the 27th November 1947. ( 3 ; Please refer to Jackson's demi-official letter No C/1116 dated the 18th November 1947 on the subject of pearling banks. Vv-vU 2. I forward herewith a copy of Ireply to Donaldson's letter No Ext. 2116/47 dated the 3rd October. The map to which I refer as being in my possession is that forwarded with your office Printed Letter No 1509-10/6 dated the 24th August 1941. 3. Would you kindly confirm that Bahrain has no interest in the pearling banks north of latitude 27 5'N. J. Pelly Esq, Q.B.E-r-, Political Agent, Bahrain, I.C.H. Confidential. bah^mh RECETKT. It 73D.O. No. C/1171. The 8th of December, 1947. My dear Belgrave, Sir Rupert Hay has inquired from rae whether Bahrain has an Interest in any pearling banits north of lat. 27°5 , N. Could you confirm that Bahrain has none? No' banKs are shown north of this on the Arabic map ordinarily used: but it is. of course, possible that Bahrain boats may go further north. Yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Rsq., C.B.5., Adviser so the Bahrain f}overnment2&gt;°l ,^ © Adviserate, December 20, 1947, $ 7 - Reference your D.O. No. c/1171 dated 8th December 1947. The Bahrain Nakhudas say that they do not generally dive on the banks which lie to the north of lat B7-30 because they are not very productive compated to the southern banks. They state that there have never been any restrictions against Bahrain boats diving there. The Kuwait boats come every year to the south banks which in these days are the best. Bahrain fishing boats go regularity to the islands of Farsi and Harkus which are on lat £0° north. The map published by Shaikh Mane al Maktoom describes the banks between the Arabian and Persian coasts”. It is thought that he left out the northern banks because they are now little used. I think it can be said that although Bahrain diving Nakhudas do not now work the northern oyster beds they used to at one time and if these beds become productive again Bahrain divers would go to them. I fear that this is not a very clear reply to your letter but the Nakhudas themselves are somewhat vague on the subject. C. J. Pelly, Bsquire, O.B.2., I.C.S., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. BAHK R3CEIPT.SECRET D.O. Ho.C/1235 POLITICAL AGENCY Bahrain. The 28 th of Deceruber, 1947 Dear Sir Rupert r? n please refer to your demi-official letter No. 2043-S, dated the 27th November. 1947, on the subject of pearling banks. northern oyster beds though they used to ac one time, and if these beds ever became productive again Bahrain divers would probably want to go to them — this at least is Belgrave's opinion, but I myself am very doubtful as to whether the pearling industry will ever revive enough, in its old form at any rate, to make the Bahrain divers wish to extend the area of their activ ities. It cannot, therefore, be said that Bahrain has no interest in the pearling banks north of latitude 27 0 5 , L. though, for practical purposes, this seems to rae to be the case. Bahrain diving nakhudas do not now work the Yours sincerely The Hon'ble Lt-Col. Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., political Resident In the Persian Gulf Bahrain.oj!&lt;CHi2&lt;i • f Copy of a.o. fetter i«o.2044-o dated 27th i'.ovemoer 1947 from oir »i).rt.Hay to jsajor hl.P.O'c. 1'anay. lofitioax Agent, Kuwait. Certain oil interests are contemplating exploiting the sea bed east of the oaudi Arabian coast from the southern boundary of the neutral fione to t&lt;as lanura, ana 1 have De ^ asked to ascertain to what extent the pearling banks are likely to be affected oy such exploitation. oo far as i can discover Bahrain has no interests m the pearling uanks north oi about 27 b’ latitude n. laole il on pages 2273-2276 oi ^onmer Volume l Part ll shows that there are a certain numoer oi pearling oanKS between this latitude and the southern Umi of tne 'eutra 1 Zone. Could you kindly ascertain whether huwait has any interests m these oanxs and if not, who, ii anybody, has? Copy of B.O.ho.C/811 dated the 18th December 1947 from major Tandy to oir ^.‘^.hay • Please refer to your demi-official letter no. 2044-3 dated the 27th novemoer, 19 47. 2. Kuwait pearlers have, in the past together with Saudi Arabian boats iron Qatif and Juoail&gt; exploited oanns as far south as has Tanura and Bahrain. ho prescriptive right of any particular Bhaikhdom to any particular pearl- bank appears to be recognised? in iact in 1^40 when a oed oi pearl-oean ng oysters was discovered at umm al Maradim island it was cleared out in ten days or so oy several iar'ge pearl- ooats from Bahrain. The Kuwaitis, m whose territorial waters the beds undoubtedly lay, secured only a small part of the haul. 3. Kuwait has definitely an interest in the peari- banks you mention, and i should oe inclined to say that ootn uahrain and the Ha's a ports could claim an equivalent interest. SECRET © PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, Bahrain, No.2276-S T the 31st December 1S47 Cspy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, BAHRAIN 5 with reference to Residency demi-official letter No.2043-3 dated 27th November, 1947. •LB’ Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT/ nBritish Embassy, Jedda. Copy of an extract from Monthly Economic Report - Saudi Arabia - April 1948, No.385/8/48G, dated the 24th May, 1948. 3. Negotiations affecting the proposed off-shore oil concession for the Central Mining Company (see section E, paragraph 3 of our March report) are proceeding slowly, since nothing can be settled unless and until some acceptable de finition of the Saudi Arabian Government title to oil deposits in the Persian Gulf has been agreed upon. At a later stage difficulties may arise out of the company’s intention to offer sterling terms for royalties payments. Unless means can be found to engineer a major increase in exports from the sterling area to Saudi Arabia&gt; such terms seem certain to prove unac ceptable.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00014b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/888</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00014b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/888</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 39/22 Bahrain pearling banks in strip of seabed leased by Trinidad Leaseholds Ltd'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-23T21:04:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 9-10. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 11; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 3-8; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Agent at Bahrain, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain regarding the use of pearling banks within areas of oil interest near Ras Tanura.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Ras Tanura</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Pearl industry and trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00014b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>