<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:33:41.502Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">* No. //s -S Of 1923 . British Residency and oonsnlate—General, Bub hire , IGth March 1923* Copy of the andermentioned papers is forwarded with compliments to the political Apent , Mascat , for ormation. By ord er, Capt ., Cinder Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter No. 24d/71'&gt;~Ert . dated 2/th February 1 &gt;23 and its accfl^Saniments , from the Government of India in the Roreipn and political Department to the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, political Department, regarding a complaint against Ris Highness the Sultan of Muscat.No* From To The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign ani Political Department, The 3ecretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Depiirtinent. Dated Delhi, the J??/ February 1923. / Complaint against His Higimess the Cultan of Muscat. With reference to your letter No. 955,dated the 17th January 1923, I am directed to request that the Representative of the Amirs of Jallan may be informed that the Government of India regret that they are unable to intervene on their betudf. 1 have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd. E.B.Howell, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Copy, ”lth copy of the letter replied to (with enclo sure) is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rushire, for Information./■ V7 Copy of a letter No# 955, dated the 17th January 1923, from the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department# Complaint against His Hlglmess the Sultan of Muscat. I am directed by the Govemor-ln-Council to forward for disposal a letter dated the 10th Jamary 1923,from the Representative of the Amirs of Jallan to the address of the Private Secretary to His Excellency the viceroy and Governor-General of India complaining against certain actions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. Confidential, and veby SECRET. C/O Messrs.Mantri &amp; Co. 99 Medows Street.Fort, Bombay,10th January 1923. The Private Secretary to His Excellency The Viceroy and Governor-General of India, P, .6 1 ft, 1.... Sir, 1 have the honour As the representative of His High ness the Amirs of Jallan to address your honour as under (1) I have the honour to state that His Highness the Amirs of Jallan and their ancestors are and were at all times most loyal and faithful to the King Emperor of England and on all occasions rendered very high and valuable services when required from the.-,.from time to time. (2) I have the honour to state further that the father and grand-father of the present Amirs supported and helped the late Sultan of Muscat at the time of great difficulty and calamities and remained as his loyal and faithful ally. About 40 years ago Syed Turkey the late Sultan of Muscat was driven out by the Ornanies Imara(or high bishop) but the father of the present Amirs defeated the saidsaid i.rk jn ana placed the Sultan of Muscat on the throne. Again about 29 years ago during the time of Sayed Faisal the tribes of Oman revolted against the Sultan of Muscat and drove him out at the instance and instigation of the said Sayed Faisal but the father of the present Amirs came imiediately to Muscat with his Forces fiought against the Omanies and put them* to flight after a great bloodshed and put the Sultan of Muscat on the throne. In consequence of the great help ^oid assistance rendered as aforesaid the Sultan of Muscat and his successors and followers agreed with the Amirs of Jallan their descendants and followers to remain as a loyal and faithful ally to the Amirs and their successors and followers, and not to inter fere in intermeddle with any political and other matters regarding the tribes and provinces belonging to the Amirs for Centuries. In consequence of the aforesaid help and assistance it was also agreed that the Sultan of Muscat and his successors and followers should pay to the Amirs of Jallan their successors and followers a tribute of 100 foliars every month and in addition to that arms and amnunition and other articles things, and other gratuities to be offered to the Amirs and their followers or dele gate whenever they visited the Sultan at Muscat. 1 have the honour to state that the present Amirs were receiving 100 dollars every month as agreed upon but the other terms conditions and rights regarding arms and ammunition and other articles, things and gratuities and presents have not been carried out by the Sultan of Muscat.The tribes of the present Amirs are clamouring for the observance of the said terms, conditions and rights by the Sultan of Muscat. The said tribes have become impatient and eager for the said rights and are likely to disturb and break down peace and to make a revolt but the Amirs of Jallan have kept them under strict control with great difficulties with promises and persuations that the Government of India would certainly interfere in the matter and the old rights would be restored to them very shortly. (3) The Sultan of Muscat not only infringed upon the aforesaid(6) aforesaid rights of the Amirs and his succe r &gt;c»rs nd followers hut has been ralso bringing pressure upca the Ardrs of Jalian to allow him to open a Customs i ou3 J port of Soor Slagah which is the port belonging to th : (4) The population of Jalian is in a very poor circum stances. There are no irrigation works. The Amirs have got are owned by their poor people for their petty business with other ports belonging to the Government of India or under the protection of Government of India. The owners of the said crafts are presented with troubles and distur bances when they go to the said ports for their trade purposes. I therefore request your honour to do the needful in uhe matter • There is no other kind of substantial look to the patronage and favour of the Government regard ing the development of their business in their territories. There is a large .scope for business in Amirs territories. to grant me an interview in the course of the month to enable me personally to explain your honour confiden tially regarding the mineral products and other matters as your honour will find in the accompanying letter from the that they themselves have requested your honour to allow me to have an interview especially for the above Jalian province for centuries past and has been writin: letters after letters through Ms Ministers. The Sultan of Muscat has notMng to do, or any right with the said port wMch ftx is a specially populated by the tribes of Amirs known as Biniboali since man^y centuries. certain number of country crafts under his control wMch business in the territories of the Amirs and the Amirs A&amp;) Hegarding mineral products which have been explored after a prolonged search and a great deal of expenses. Further products will be explored by the help of the experts and Engineers with the help of the Govern- ment of India. I have therefore to request your honour \ &gt; . matters(6J I have the honour to request you tc kindly go through the records of the late Political Agents at r.uscat especially of the period of Ool.Pelly , Sir Percy Cox and Mr#Wingate and others in support of the above facts, and to intervene in the matter and to restore the Amirs of Jallan in their original position and to direct the Sultan of Muscat to abide by his mutual conditions and to fulfil all the terms and conditions and ri$ite agreed upon and not to interfere in the Political and other matters of the Amirs of Jallanr to remove the troubles and disturbances regarding the Provinces and tribes of the /imirs and grant the same kind of freedom to the as has been granted to other Arab Chiefs by the Government of Inoia, and to keep direct connection end communications concerning the prosperity and affairs of the provinces belonging to the ^mirs either direct from the Government of India or through the Political Agent at Muscat as was being done originally for several years. And some of the said correspondence between the late Political Agents and the late and present ^mirs are with me which is a clear proof of the Ami^s loyalty and the services they have rendered to the Government all the matters and facts which will remove all the doubts and differences of the Government of India for which act of kindness the Amirs of Jallans and I shall remain ever grateful and pray for your honour’s longlife and prosperity. at some critical times and to grant me a personal interview to explain I have, etc., Sd.Abdulla Saleh, Representative of the ivmirs of Jallan.Abstract from the letter of His Highness the Amirs of Jallan dated 18th Rabi-u-aval 1341.Higgri. TO The Private Secretary to His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor General of India,Delhi. Sir, After due respect and thankfulness I request your honour to allow an interview to our Representative Mr* Abdulla Saleh El Habas'ni to explain before your honour all the confidential matters* We have etc*, Sd. All bin Abdulla and Mahomed bin Nasir Ali Homood H.H. The Amirs of Jallan. Respectfully submitted through the Secretary to Government of Bombay,Political Department, Secretariat. Bombay*/(7tL No. 446-S of 192b. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire, 28th November 192b. A copy of the undermentioned paper, received under ; cover of foreign and Political Department endorsement No. !-N., dated the 16th November 1925, is forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, for favour of early report.From 7 Hanidia Mansion, MOtlinai atreot, waai* iiyuulla Club, aMuay, dated 8 .II.I 725 . Molicuned bm Masir i»lnuned /Mr of Jalun, Southern Muscat. I'lit; jj'orniiji Secretary, HOfoe and Politic;,! Deparnnent, uovGrnmant of iiiata, Delhi. Sir, j.fter due respect 1 infora you that I have come to Bombay for the medical treatment of ray children. On my \/ay to India 1 had been to Muscat and I came to know that the British hesident in Persian oulf intends to send some British 3nglnoai*s and same reinforcement to a . certain place in rry territory in order to explore mines and oil, so 1 bring to your kind notice that tne same should not be inforced unless the uoverunent consults aa in tms rnxtter. As tiiere are .tany wild tribes in those places so they are repaired to oj consulted and instructed oefore it.nd. If the uoverrraent neeils any sort of arrangement in my territory it should be coumunicated to me before hand and I shall do, which will be benefited to both. s Hoping to receive an early reply and thanking in anticipa Yours faithfully. 3d/- nohaaad bin r^ sir j.ll^medConfidential* (5) no.as. From The Political Agency and Britiah Consulate ruscat 7th Deoember 1925* Lieut*Colonel C* 0. Crosthwalte 9 C* B. fi* # I olitical Agent and H # B. 'e Coneul 9 Muscat, Cir 9 The Secretary to the Hon'ble the lolitloal Heeident in the Persian Oulf 9 Btiehire* Z have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your endorsement ^o.446-A dated the 28th November 1925 forwarding a copy of a letter from Moh&amp;raed bin hasir Al Haioed to the foreign Secretary to the Government of India* 2* Mohamed bin Hasir and his uncle,Ali bin Abdulla,are known as the Amirs of Jaalan* The former visited Muscat on his way to India,and he was told of a proposed visit of the Anglo Persian Oil Company's geologists to the mainland oppo* -site the island of Masirah* This place lies within the sphere of Influence of these Jaalan Amirs and there is a ravine there in whioh there is a reported oil seepage* It is proposed that when H*M..'Triad' is bringing back Hie Highness the lultan from Dhofar at the end of January next a brief halt be made at laasirah with a view that the oil seepage be examined* Ao further aotion has been taken in the matter as it is realis* •ed that the return of Mahomed bin hasir from India must be awaited* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut*Colonel, Political Agent and TT*B*H f s Censul,Huscat*No. 486-F&gt; of 1925. 10 British Residency and Uonoulate-General, Bushire, 19th December 1925. ?rom The Hon’ble Lieut-Ool. F. B. ^rideaux, C.S.I., Political Keeident in the Persian Gulf. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. MUHAMMAD BIN NASIR OF JAALAN. I have the honour to refer to Government of India endorsement No. 272-N., dated the 16th November 1925, under which was forwarded to me a copy of a letter, dated the 8th November 1925, from Shaikh Muhammad bin HasirAl,Hamad, Amir of Jaalan, on the subject of the proposed visit-of geologists of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company to Southern Oman at the end of January next. . ^ '-S 4 2. I enclose a copy of a letter No. 8b, dated the 7th December 1925, from the olitical Agent, Muscat, who was addressed in the matter. 3. &gt;haikh Muhammad was interviewed in September last I by Captain Alban, who reported that he had/ promised his support for the expedition and undertaken to write to Shaikh J Mansur bin Nasir, who controls the area under consideration. 4. It is not, therefore, apparent ytyy the Shaikh has petitioned the Government of India in the matter, as there has never been any Intention of ignoring his position and influence over the tribes of Batain 5. . The Amirs of Jaalan, who reside at f&gt;ur, cure not very loyal to the Sultan. If they had done their duty and given the Wali of Sur all the, support he was entitled to i . ffP there *“-5 »/,there would have been no queetion of paying a ransom for the release of the Hindu, Kersandas L&amp;lji, who was kidnapped by a Bedouin last April, vide paragraphs 24 and 32 of the Recidency Siqjan&amp;ry of Hews from the Arab States tor April ana I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3d/- F. B. FRIDEAUX. Lieut-Col., Political Resident in the ersian Gulf. 2 10 © - J/hnjL- Ho. 488-S of 1925. Sty' British Residency and Consulate-General Bushire, 19th December 1925. A copy of the foregoing letter is forwarded ^ the Political Agent, Muscat. , By order, ' ¥B V Under Secretary to Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram ( Code ) Prom Political, Muscat. To Secretary to Govt of Jombay, No. 53 dated llth January 1926. Following for Mahamad bin Nasir, Amir of Jaalan, residing Vasiamul Building, Charni Road, begins}Reference your telegram of 9th instant imports of arms and ammunition into Oman are governed by His XxghHKJB Highness* notification 11(a) dated 4 th June 1912. Matter will therefore be referred to His Highness on return to Muscat, but if you desire to purchase one rifle and 250 rounds as an urgent matter a No Objection Certificate will be issued on receipt description of rifle~]ends. POLITICAL.I.R.No. U 13/l/26. V From Telegram (Code) PoliticaljiJushire, Political t Muscat, To JNo*25 dated 13th January 1926* PRIORITY^ Muhammad hin I^asir of Jaalan has requested permission of Government of India to purchase in hombay 10 rifles and 10,000 cartridges for the of himself and his 'bodyguards in Jaalan and import them via Sur» iffhat are your views on this? Matter is urgent* POLITICAL.w % {•3 » / - , i From Political To P. R. lushire 1 Reference your Ro 25 dated the 13th January nahamad 'bin Uasir addressed me direct and l replied as follows begins ends • •... i desire to discuss matter with Sultan on his return and in any case consider number of cartridges asked for as excessive* Cjj |S|l1 t 2?J. liEilatr 0 ^ * -mm .. Telegram......(CODE) Prom .Resident,3.I.M.S. ,, Lawrence ,, via Henjam Radio, To Political, Muscat, 0615 dated 15th January 1926. Poliowing have been sent to Government of India Uo.5 begins Reference application of Amir of Jaalan for permission to purchase rifles I recommend he be told to apply through Government of Muscat to Political Agent for No Objection Certificate. It is questionable whether assent should be given before the case of kidnapping and ransom of Hindu is satisfactorily settled.On this point opinion of Political Agent and Britsh Consul Muscat is awaited.ends. Bushire,Muscat. Resident. ^ iCt cf 9i. &lt;\ ^ xj (Skc^Cz* C&gt; exx &amp;Z,- Tv*-&lt; L J - lrf//a 6. IX) CX ^&lt;Xjcx£x*a. + €cPe cx&amp;m/' /sr mX'&amp;z* fi+Z' £&lt;cui^ - farCONFIDENTIAL. yyj U'! Sat fh is No. 12-S of 1926. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 13th January 1926. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, for favour of remarks in continuation of this office telegram No. *25, of today’s date. 2. A list of such of the enclosures to the Amir’s letter as emanated from the Political Agency, Muscat, is attached. It is requested that copies or translations thereof may he forwarded to this office. By order, Capt., Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter No. 294-N., dated 28th December 1925, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, with enclosures. I -Confidential . No.?94-N. F rom Tho Deputy Secretary to th^ Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hon’blo the Political Resident in th* Persian Gulf. Dated Delhi, the ^8^ December 1925. Application of the Amir of Jalan to export arms and ammunition from India. Sir » I am directed to forward the marginally cited Letter from Amir of Jalan dated 2nd December 1925, enclosures. wi th in original an* to r«qu^st that th« Government of India may be favoured at an early date with an expression of your views. 2. I am to request the r eturn of the enclosures to this letter with your reply. I huve th” honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 5d/- n. a. wiconachie. Deputy Secretary to the Government of IndiaJ' * ^ - COPY. Kis Excellency the Governor-General of India and the Members of the Council. May it please Your Excellency, I,the undersigned, Amir of Jalan, have the honour to address this for the kind consideration by Your Excellency in Council. As Your Excellency and the Members of Your Excell- -ency’s Council are aware, Jalan is an independent state situated in Southern Arabia to the South Muscat. ,As announced by the Government of India in the General liotice Zo# iqt * * dated first Ra mzan 1538 that the Principality of the Amir of Jalan are allies with.the Muscat Government and the Tranelatie -ion of the same is herewith attached for your information. The State of Jalan comprises a territory of about 500 miles and has the population of about a lac. The Amirs of Jalan and their ancestors have at all times remained loyal and faithful allies of the British Gov- -ernment and ha^e on all occasions rendered very high and valuable services to the British Empire, as shown by the letters written by Sir Percy Cox and the true translation of the same is annexed hereto. During the Great War, I, as the present Amir of Jalan State, not only remained neutral byt remained Rfixkx rendered very valuable assistance to the British and their allies, and among other things I may mention that when the crew of a British ship which was stranded in the Port of Ras Rakhaba we rendered very valuable assistance, which has been recognised by the British officials If necessary I beg to refer to the letters of recognition of the services rendered, written by the Political Agents of Muscat and Consulate of Muscat. We 'We further draw your attention that during the War there was a restriction of export of rice from India, and we approached the Government of India through our representative at Bombay directly and our request was granted, without any consultation or confirmation, as a special case, and the copy of the same sanction is attached herewith f India for about a month more. ‘ ft In view of the facts and circumstances mentioned above, I have the honour to request a favour. Formerly we were getting all the arms and ammunit- -ion from Muscat and also direct from Europe, but since the War, as Your Excellency and His Council are probably aware, the importation of arms and ammunition in Muscat has become difficult and we cannot get there direct arms and ammunition for our own territory. I intend therefore to make purchase of some arms and ammunition fax in Bombay for the purpose of taking them to Jalan or to order them direct to hi Jalan through Sur, which is a port dtf my territory, and with merchants in Bombay and carried on correspondence with the Political Agent in Bombay, but in reply to my request the Political Agent has written to say that I should produce'a 'no objection' certificate from the Political Agent and Department of Bombay is not fair to me as the Ruler of an independent State and it would be highly detrimental to my dignity to ask for consent or certificate from the Political high regard but I think you will appreciate that I prefer, touring In that view I openednegotiations with the firm of ammunition His Britannic Majesty^ Consul at Muscat authorizing to i supply the rifles and ammunition'. I submit that this request of the Political Agent of Muscat. I hold the Political Agent at Muscat into preserve the dignity of my State, not to do an act detrimental to its independent possession. I may here refer to the sanction of the Rice Export v/hich was granted to me hy the Government of India as a special case without any interference of the Muscat Government. With that object in view I now request Your Excellency in Council to consider the whole case from my point of view and to give your necessary sanction that I may he permitted to take away with me a very small quantity of arms and ammunition at present that I may require for my own use. I may at once state that for the present I want to carry ten rifles and about ten thousand bullets for the use of myself and my body-guards. Further I may say that my desire is to buy arms and ammunition only of British make and not of any foreign make. In view of the relationship existing between my State and the British Empire I trust this small request will certainly meet with a favourable reply and I request Your Excellency in Council to dispose of this application as an urgent one as I wish to have your reply before I leave Bombay at the end of this month. Yours faithfully, Sd/- MAHOMED BIB NASIR ALIHAMUD, (Amir of Jalan). 2nd December 1925.COPY Telegram Wo. 38 Fs. Delhi, the loth January 1922.. Government of India. DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE AND AGRICULTURE ( Foodatuffa.) From India Revenue, Delhi. To Customs, nombay lermit Abaullali Saleh Agent Amirs of Jalaan to ship four thousand bags rice from .Bombay. -- INDIA KEVEUUE -- No. 39 FS. Cop^ forwarded to Modullah Saleh, Esquire, Agent to fetie ijnirs of Jalaan, Ramnavmi bmilaings, Eathabazar, j-&gt;omoay, v/ith refence to nis letter dated the 10th January 1922. hy order, Registrar, For UNDER*-SECRETARY.Hamid ia ^nsion, Mullibai street, Byculla Bombay, 4th B 0 cember 1925. X rom Moharaod bin Nasir ai Harud , ^mir of Jalan, I'he Forei^ ^Acr^tary, Government Political Department, i Government of India, Dei Delhi. I have the honour to draw your attention to my letter to you of the 8th November last. 1 have not as yet received any reply to my said letter, nor even an acknowledgment of the same, which I take is due to oversight. I shall feel obliged by your now acknowledging the receipt of my this letter. Ahe object of again drawing your attention to my letter of the 8th November last is that I have come to know that certain British iigineers have already reached unseat with the object of proceeding into my territory, for object of which 1 am not informed, but which 1 tatco'it to be to explore oil Fields in my territory, in order that my state may not come into any unforeseen trouble by reason of any injury to these iigineers by many wild tribes of my State, I respectfully draw &lt; the attention of the British Government to immediately take steps to notify to thos- -ng in ears, that if they go into my ^tate, they will do so at thnir personal own risk and responsi- y •bility and that in the ^vent or any mishap or injury occu^ing to them thev will not look to my state for the consequences thereof. If the British Government or Ind ian Government desires to open communication regarding the Gil Fields or other mineral resources of my state, I shall be pleased to furnish you with •any information that may be required *uc that is within my power isf\ power to the British Government or Indian Govnmrent. I hope to receive an early reply in this matter. Yours faithfully, Sd/- i^ohaned bin Nasir Al Ha mud • Copy of a letter No.272-N, dated Delhi, the 5th January 1926, from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the iorei^n and Political Department, to Shaikh Mohamed bin hasir Al aamud, '**'* . '^9 rj S Amir of JalaB, Hamidia i^ansion, iwotlibai street, Byculla, Hombay. Geological survey 01 Southern Oman, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letters of the 8th November and 4th December 1925, and to say that information has been received from the Political Ji^ent basket to the effect that the matter was discussed with you by Captain Alban in September last and that it is proposed to cohsult you a rain on your return to Masket. A copy of the foregoing, received under cover of Foreign and Political Department endorsement No. 272-N., dated the 11 th January 1926, is forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, with reference to correspondence ending with this office endorsement No. 488-S., dated the 19th December 1925. By order, * % Under Secretary lu the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Capt.,Re marginal querrieg about the Amirs of Jaalan. 1 . Is any thing known of the Kindly see slipV’file xvll /12 submitted herewith. A notice General Kotice dated the 1 st was issued by H.H. the Sultan signed by his Minister Mr Mcallum on the 1st Ramzan 1338 penal Zakat @ 25^ on certain unfriendly tribes of Oman and excepting the 3ani Su Ali from it. It is true that the word 'ALLLWS' is used for the Amirs of Jaalan in this notice, but it seems to have been used in the sense of'friendly tribe' i against the unfriendly iamos tribes on whom penal Zakat \v4s imposed. up. This happened in 1919. services to the Sultan in his expedition to Wadi Smail, lani Ruwaihah, specially because the Amir had represented that when $ 50 p.m. was paid to Shaikh Isa bin Salih of Sharqiyah^ why nothing was paid to him i.e. ^ the Amir of Jaalan. T^e Council has however no records about it. ! | The allowance continues. by all from whom I have enquired \ that the Shaikhs of Jaalan held ixtSL very influential nncsition in Jaalan even he-fere i Saiyid Muhammad ^'all of Matr and Khan Bahadur also hold ^his view. df India 20 th May 1920, imposing a 2. When a British ship was wrecked at Ras Rakhabah. 3. From what date Muscat Govt issued an allowance of $ loo p.m. for the Amirs Jaalan. and was any Sanad issued. The Council of Ministers state that • Saiyid Faisal granted this allowance from 1320 =1901 to Abdullah bin Salim al Hamudah « the ancestor of the present Amirs, in consideration of their; 4 . when was the title of Amir of Jaalan given There i 3 nothing on record, but it is unanimously held by5 Is Jaalan a part of the Muscat Sultanate. Jaalan is a district of the Oman Sultanate ( Vide LorimersGazetter Vol 11 pp 882, 6 . Search for old records in which the Jaalan Amirs have addressed H.H. , a subject tribe, and what are the old styles of addressing and styling* The Council of Ministers say that they have not got old records. With the permission of Saiyid Nadir I searched the Council records and have picked up a few letters throwing some light on the status of the Amirs of Jaalan. T^e letters are translated and submitted herewith. From these letters it may be seen that the Amirs of Jaalan address the Sultan as w King” and in a letter to the Wall of Sur, they deny the charge that they wish to join relations with Ein Saud and cut off from the M u scat G 0 vt.J $/?y26 . P .A „ I interviewed ShaiVh Hand an 'bin Nasir^ as instructed .end exj^leined to him the displeasure that his brother ShsiVh Muhammad bin Npsir icurred by making untrue statement in his letters to the Govt of India. Shaikh Harridan has written a letter which I submit with tran elation. Shaikh ifamdan is the youngest of the ^ brother of whbm Shaikh I. r uhamrrad bin Nasir is the eldest,, and most resr^onsible. . (h ■ Jootf&gt; Translation. TO Consul an^ Political Agent, Muecat. A/C. I have been given to understand that your Honour is displeased with my brother Muhammad bin Nasir about his demands from the Govt of India. I am unaware about it. I think Muhammad bin Nasir does not like to do any thing *•*/» against your orders and the orde rs of the Govt of Muscat, A' and even if he does so, we ( other brothers ) do not epprov of his opinion. We do not wish to act against your views. We can not dispense with your opinions. We request you to * forgive. I wish to call on you in order to explain the facts. ’U.E, Sd/ Hamdan bin Nasir al Hamudah.The respected, the esteeired, dear brother S?iyid Ha mud bin Hamad bin Hilal, ( Tali of Sur). A/C. Te have reached our home safely. Your letter has been received, along with the Ministers letter. Your are fed up with the question of the HIJRIYIN. No matter leave them off Te note what 1'uhammad bin Isa alludes to . He says ^KXBRRXKkstxaUraxaiiMQtKXtHX that we sent messengers to BIN SAITD. Now there is no truth in it. have no excuse against the orders p of Muscat Govt, unless they themselves separate us. Dated Jamadi ath theni 13^3. Sd/ All and Muhammad al Hamudah. ( Note. Attached to this letter is a letter from Muhammad bin Shaikh Isa bin Salih, of Sharqiyah, to the address of Tali of Sur, informing that AOULAD HAMTTDAH ( Amirs of Jaal»n) have sent messengers to their IMam BIN SAUD 0 )xhe esteemed, the Fing, the Sultan, the Spiyid Tairrur bin Faisal bin^sakx Turky, may God prolong his life. After Compliments, 0 ,Sultan, I request you to give me time to effect a settlement between the JANABAK (of Sur) if God wishes, some settlement will be arrived at, as desired, otherwise, the matter will refer to you. is The time required up to the end of H 8 bi al Awal. by which date the dispute may be settled . Otherwis *- the matter lies with you, before and after. Dated the 15th Shaban 1342. rnahCL Sd/ Fuham Muhammad bin Ns sir al Hamudeh (H.H.the Sultans Orders ) TO The Council of Ministers to my Govt. v ou see the request of this Shaikh. Within the'Salifeh' period,he can intervene as requested,but after the period,he is not to interfere in anything. Let it be known. Sd/ Taimur bin Faisal. From Taimur bin Faisal. To The dear and respected Shaikhs of AL ARANA, and AL MUFHANAH ( Sur) A/C. I am quite well. May God keep you well. In these days .during his stay here ( in Muscat SHAIKH MUHAMMAD BIN NASIR AL HAMUDAH has asked us t 3 let him make settlement between you,provided both parties agree. We have agreed to that and we do not stop him from a good work. Let it be know Da ted the 15th Shaban 134r. 2 j 1 l 24* Sd/ Taimur bin Faisal.P?.. ^pppMW - I Translation. TO Tne esteemed, the respected, the majestic, the’King, the Lord, Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal bin Turky,may God protect him. After Compliments, ^our kind letter has been received and we are glad to hear of your welfare. As regards the delay in ne settlement between AL JAFAPAH, this has displeased us, because the Ministers had authorized us about it, and to delay it now would be harmful. But we have delated it till we see your Fxceelency. W You wish that we should visit you after we send away these trbes. We shall be coming after a fgwxx few days. Dated the 12 th Rajah 1342. Sd/ Ali bin Abdullah and Muhammad bin Nasir al Hamudah.24/1/26. P.A . i Amirs of Jsalan and their rex resents, ti ons and status. History and. Description. As the subject is important and is likely to develop further and as the files do not contain sufficient information about Jaalan and the Amirs, I have therefore for convenience^ sake picked up and linked together full details from the Gazetteers and Col ^iles book, and beg to submit them herewith attached for your honours perusal, The notes are : Jaalan country ( pages Balad Bani Bu Ali.( page 6 ) Bani Bu Ali tribe ( page , in 18 2C ' 7 y British expeditionV against Bani Bu Ali (page ) VC Sur affairs. ( page \\ ) Independence coveted. Three files xr re Jaalsn Amirs are also submitted below and important letters flagged for perusal. In his letter to the Govt of India, the Shaikh Muhammad bin Nasir claims that Jaalan is independent of the Sultanate. The Wali of Matrah told me today that the intention of the Shaikhs is to become independent just like Shaikh Isa bin ^alih. There is nothing on record on these files or in the Gazetteer that may support the Amirs allegations. Jaalan is a district of the Sultanate, area,roughly speaking 50 miles by 40, inhabited by several tribes including Bani Bu Ali ,their rival Bo n i Bu HASAN, and a few others.Amirship. Shaikhs of Bani All only snd not of Jaalan. Warnings unusual &gt;; The title Amir is pffKMixscr to Oman and is considered to be a Wahhabi style. In the central Arabia - Nejd etc. Principal Shaikh is ix called an Amir. For instance when Amir Bin Seud, Amir Bin Rashid - even both were under the Turkish Govt. In Oman the xtyigx title Amir is used for the Principal Shaikh of Barii Bu Ali only. Shaikhs Fuhammed bin Nesir and Ali bin Abdulla are not the Shaikhs of the whole of Jaalan, but only of their tribe Bani Bu Ali. There are always blood fueds and fighting between Bani Bu Ali and Bani Bu Hasan. Bani Bu Ali are are ghafiris and and Bani Bu Hasan Hinawis. The formers are *ahhabis and the letters Abadhis. Out of the total population of jaalan - 13000, Bani Bu Ali are about 7000 according to Gazetteer ( and Wali of Matrah says they are far less than that ). The correct title therefore is Shaikh of Bani Bu Ali or Amirs of Bani Bu Ali. ..... • ••'■**' ’ • ' ' In September 1925 when Shaikh Muhammad bin Nasir came here to go to India the Council of Ministers described ± him in the Open letter as a resident of Jaalan’! Thi- annoyed him very much and he • insisted on « * being styled Amir of Jaalan. Finally the Council 'wrote ' Amir of Bani Bu Ali tribe of Jaalan M and this appears to be accurate title. The Govt of India in their letter No. 248/719 dated the 27th Feb 1923 ( vide flag N file 29/lo) refused to entertain Amirs complaint RgxxHt against H.H. the Sultan. In 1922 Major Rae and in 1923,Behaviour. Mr Wingate warned the Amirs to make their requests through the Sultan. ( Vide flag Z and P. File 14/19 I In the long list of the letters appended by them , they have very carefully avoided mention two . of these letters. the grant of permit for the export of rice by the Govt of India ,without reference to Muscat authorities must have been done in emergency. As regards the statement that they have been loyal to the British Govt, it is true that since the fighting of 182o-l, the tribe does not seem to have given any trouble, but last summer a Hindu was was a kidnapped by a Hakmani whose tribe is in friendly alliance with the Bgni Bu Ali 0 The Shaikhs state that they have been helping the Sultan. If they did so, it was more to keep off their rivals Bani Bu Hasan than any other motive Ihe Sultan 1 s Govt pay them a monthly allowance of jt ''- / 'nrOTiin I loo. Perhaps the High Govt will see fit to repeat once more in clear terms that the Amirs are subject of H.H.the Sultan whose passports they possess. But the tribe are good fighters and zealous -'ahhabis Consideration. . &lt;arTear of pro Bin Saud trend of mind and it mayyexpedient for a Company who may undertake working ouf^ oil sr or any other mineral from the place under the Amirs influence to dsai help them financially, in view specially of- the present incapability of the local Govt to exercise an effective control over the bedouins of the interior. Allowance Ci • Je rf ac&lt;-(-z6 s 5 SIJ A A I, A N. / / Jaalan is a district in the Oman Sultanate lying to the south east of Sharqiyah,of which some authorities consider it to be a division. Its greatest length is about 50 miles from the coast at LASHKHARAH north eastwards to the confines of BADIYAH in SHAROIYAH: its limits on the north east and south west are undetermined,so also is its extent upon the sea where, however, it certainly includes the strip from RAS AR RUFATS to LASHFHARAH; but its breadth appears to be somewhat less than its length. On the north it is shut in and overlapped by the easternmost hills of HAJAR: on the south it is enclosed by sandy desert. There is a hill called Jabal Qehwen belonging to this district which is situated 20 miles inland from the coast a little north of LASHFHARAH: its height is 2600 feet and it is probably a southern spur of the JABAL FHAFIS range of Hajar. Hills called JABAL FTJSHAIFH are said to occur near the west end of the district. Around HUFAIDHAH, FAFIL, and ’7AFI, streams afford abundant irrigation and the country is well cultivated. Between these villages and BALAD BANT BU HASAN is an extensive plain, khIs covered with acacia and consisting alternately of very loose drift sand and of whitish, indurated clay. From BALAD BANI BU ALI to LASHFHARAH the ground is at first level and firm 7 /ith a few acacias,then broken and sandy. For 25 or thirty miles south-south-west of BALAD BANI BU ALI there is an open waste without trees and water,then a narrow ridge of low calcareous hills,then mounds thickly interspersed with gum Arabic trees: these sandy mounds continue for several hours 1 journey. To the west of the last mentioned tract are arid plains without trees or bushes, dispLaying alternately a pebbly surface and saline incrustations. The chief permanently inhabited places which JAALAN contains are given in the following table, with the exception of RAS AR RUWAIS, SUFAIH,JUFAILAH, andBALAD BANI BU ALI. It is the principai Ghafiri settlement in the JAALAN district of the Oman Sultanate: it is situated about 40 miles south -south-v/est of Sur and 7 miles to the south-sout west of the rival Hinawi township of Balad Bani Bu Hasan. The houses number about 600, and the population which consists entirely of the Bani Bu Ali tribe may number about 3000 souls. The settlement boats about 2000 camels 800 donkeys and 4000 sheep and goats, but only a few horses; the date palms are estimated at 30000. r 111 ( Gazetteer Vol 11 pp 64.) BANI BU ALI tribe. Bani Bu Ali is the principal Ghafiri tribe of the Jaalan and Shrqiyah districts in the Sultanate of Honan.They are partly nomadic and partly sdentary: the bedoiun portion of the tribe inhabit JAALAN only and possess considerable herds of camels and goats,while the settled portion cultivate dates and grain in the Baled Bani Bu Ali oasis and are found also at Sur and at HAS AH RUTAIS,SUWAIH,Fhor Bani BU ALI, JUMAILAH, and Lashkherah on the South-Eastern Coast of Oman where they are mostly mariners and fishermen. A few occur also at Fhabbah in Tadi Fhabbah. T&amp;e following are the chief sections and sub sections of BANI BU ALI„ Section. Sub Section, Fighting strength Place of residence. Fahud. Fa hud 50. Cultivators. Baled Bani Bu Ali. i t Uuwaridah. 50. i t La shkharah * &gt; Ruwatilah. 50. Fishermen. HAS AR RUTAIS and SUR. JAAFPAH. Ghanabis. ,, Bani Ibrahim. , , A 1 BU UU0.BIL. ,, Aulad A SAFHILAH. ,, SALABIFHAH. 200 The Japfrah have their Headquarters at LASHFHARAH 120 . and are found at SUVAIH, their country extending for 200 . a considerable distance ?.± along the coast and at 40/ Sur. Fishermen, poor. 50. P.T.0.Section. Sub Section. Fighting strength. Residence. Bani Raziq. alHamudeh. 200 . Balad Bani BatR&amp;xxigx t f Bu Ali. The AkkABxMASfttf. AULAD HA SAIT. 100 . Principal Shaikh of Bani Bu Ali belongs to this section Aulad Abdul Jalil. ^ 0 . Aulad Khanjar. 40. Majaghamah. 60. In Jaalan and Sur. Mazamilah. ICO. About 1000 Bedouin Souls in addition belong to these Aulad S?if. 50. two subsections. The total number of the tribe appears? to be about 7000 souls. The B?ni Bu Ali became Waha.bbis at the time of the Najdi invasions of Oman nearly a century ago; and as late as 1845 they were strict,if not fanatical,in the observance of *?ahabbi principles. They have since relaxed something of their rigour and have resumed the smoking of tobacco; but they continue to be exact in their observance of the forms and times of prayer and are accounted the most religious tribe in the Oman Sultanate. They belong to a Wahhabi sect known as Azra.qah. The Bani Bu Ali are on the average men of middle size with short features and quick deep set eyes. A gloomy and determined expression which characterises some of them does not belie their natural character. They are a warlike, independent race and bear a high reputation for courage and dash. Their favourite weapon was originally a thin .straight, two edged sword,sharp as a razor and attached by a leather tkwR •thong to a shield 14 inches diameter, in addition to which they carried match locks;their armament is now of a more ers. modern character,but they Msixrx still have fe* breech loading The Barii Bu Ali are the only tribe of the Oman Sultanate that have met a British force on land. 0 n the 9 th F.T .0.of November 1820 they defee tec’ p force of British Indian Sepoys at their village of BALAD BANI BIT ALT, end on the 2 nd Kerch 1^21 suffered severe retribution near the same place. On the latter occasion the tribe lost heavily in killed and wounded,the town and fort were destroyed and alarge number of prisoners were taken including the Principal Shaikh Kuhammad bin Ali; but the date groves belonging to the place were spared,-- an act ofclemency that was much appreciated and is still remembered. The prisoners pfter being kept for two years at Bombay were repatriated and received grants of money from the Indian Govt to enable them to rebuild* their houses and restore irrigation. Since this episode the tribe have uniformly shown themselves well disposed to the British nation and have treated hospitably more than one British traveller visiting their country; but they have never fully regained their position in tribal politics. The Bani Bu Ali have a chronic fued with their neighbours the BANI BU HASAN; their present ( 1910). Tamimah is Abdullah bin ^alim of the Hamudah subsection, who reside near Lashkharah but some times visits Sur, where he has a house. ( Gazetteer V 0 1 11 pp 65,66,67 ) ( 1926) Note . The present princiial Shaikhs of Bani Bu A 1 are Ali bin Abdullah and Muhammad bin Nasir bin Abdullah. ( Col Miles description of the expedition follows on the next page. ) P.T.O.'Expeditions despetched by the British Govt in yeers 18P0 and 1821 against BANI BU ALI tribe of Jaalan. in 1820 a joint expedition was undertaken by the English and by Saiyid Saeed against the BANI BU ALI tribe in JAALAN, the immediate cause of which, so far as the British were concerned, was the murder of the interpreter of the Mercury brig which had been despatched to A 1 Askhara to enquire into certain piratical acts committed by the tribe. Part of the force, stetioned by Sir 'V.O.Keir in the Gulf, consisting of six companies of Native Infantry and six guns, was now embarked by the Political Agent, Captain Thompson, who had resolved on immediate hostilities, and taken from Kisham to Muscat. Saiyid Saeed had for some years been at variance with the Bani BU ALI tribe, on account of their having coalsced with the T .7ahabees and adopted tneir tenets in 1811, and he had since been seeking for an opportunity to crush them. The expedition was undoubtedly due in part to Saiyid Saeed f s instigation and encouragement, and he had been allowed to join it with 1000 men. Captain Thompson sailed from Muscat to Soor and the combined force marched from that port to BANI BU ALI country on November 1st 1820. The tribes were summoned to surrender, practically unconditionally by Saeed, but refused to give up their arms, and a contest ensued in which the British force was completely defeated with a loss of six officers,270 men and all guns. The survivors retreated by way of Al SHARCJYAH and Oman,through the Wadi Akk to Muscat, where they arrived on November 17th. Saiyid Saeed displayed great gallantry and coolness throughout the affair,and was wounded while endeavouring to save a British soldier. In acknowledg ment of his services a. sword of honour was presented to him by the Governor General, who in 1821 despatchedf Dr Jukes to Muscat to deliver it. To retrieve this disaster a large force 7 /as despatched,under General Sir Lionel Smith, from Bombay in January, 1821. The General attacked the BANI BIT All in March, and after severe fighting destroyed the forts and almost annihilated the tribe, which to this day has never recoveredits former strength and. prestige. Saiyid Speed was not permitted to take part in this compaign, though h 0 personally .accompanied the troops. A larp-e ^incLudmg the principal Chief luha mmad bin Ali&gt; number of prisoners of BA1TTT BU ALi^were carried £o Bombay by General Smith, where they were detained for about two years, when they were released and sent back to Oman with a sufficient sum to enable them to rebuild their houses and acoueducts. ( Vi&lt;£e Col Miles book Country and. Tribes / c . of the.Persian Gulf, 1919^' rp ( Similar description in Gazeteer pp &amp;:63,Vol 1 part I ihe Arabs relate that the annihilation was so serious that even the girls of the tribe were carried away by the British ships and the offsprings of those Ba.nu Bu Ali girls still live in Sn el?-nd. ( A Geneological tree of el Hamudah. AL HAMUDAH Ali I Muhammad ( who was taken prisoner I in 1820 and released I af ter two years ) SALT!' I Abdullah. Ali . Up s i r I y 1 uhammad. The present principal Shaikhs of Bani Bu Ali are Ali bin Abdullah and Muhammad bin Nasir bin Abduullah who act jointly. xxxxxxxxxxxxx -7. 'P'T'-O.Affairs at £ Sur. Sur is the port for the JAALAN COUNTRY. Sur, a town never submissive to the authority of the Sultans of Oman,had been hitherto neglected by ^aiyid Faisal,who did not once visit it during the first twelve years of his reign. In 1898 the inhabitants expelled the Sultan’s garrison by force but allowed it to be replaced on sufferance. By 1900 the people of Sur,especially those of the Jannabah tribe,had almost ceased,under French encouragement,to regard the Sultan as their master. at Sur In May 1900 Hilal bin Amr arrived from Fast Africa,joined hands with Ottawi, and began to inviegh against the Sultan and the British; and the spirit of the Jannabah was now such that , 7 /hen summoned by the Sultan to meet him at Muscat,they refused to go and insolently suggested that he should deal with them instead through the French Vice Consul. It was this state of affairs which obliged Saiyid Faisal in 1900 to make p visit to Sur,the first since his accession. His reception was more favourable to him than he had expected; for all the elders of the town immediately paid their respects to him,the chief Shaikh of the BANI BU All came down from the interior with a thousand men to do him honour, and, the Sultan was successful before he left in obtaining from the French flag-holders of the port,including the Jannubah,s formal profession of allegiance to himself and a renunciation of French protection. ( Gazetteer V 0 1 1 Part 1 pp 5 * 9 ) N °te. In 1926 the position about Sur province is this . Sur town is to some extent submissive to the Sultan’s authority and Sultan’s Customs is run,although most of the goods are smuggled away from Aiqah quarter of Sur; otherwise the interior^'-' Jaalan etc is practically as out of control of * the Sultan Govt as other 0 nly ^J- aE ^ Summer, the 0 h 8 cP * ts of 0lTiar! - ' '-fo tLx m 1 ^ leave, crr-ru-siPolitical Agency and British Conaulate, Muscat 8th Februjixy 1926« From Lieut •Colonel C*0»Croi3thwalte # C.B.L *, Political Agent and Consul # -«i-U£3oat # To The Secretary to the Uon’ble the Political Heaident in the Persian Oulf f Sir, Bushire# I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your endorsement Ho.l2-£ dated the 13th January 192G forwarding a copy of a letter 3 mo* 294-H dated the 28th December 1925 from the Govern- -ment of India in the Foreign and Political Department and calling for an opinion on the request of Mahomed bin hasir Al Hamad MM of the two Amirs of Jaalan.for permission to import via Cur 12 small here rifles and 10,000 rounds of ammunition* It ie also requested by you that copies of certain correspondence between this office and the Amirs of Jaalan be submitted* 2 # In this connection it will not be out of place to recora the recent doings of Mehcmed bin hasir,/anir of Jaalan; Mahomed bin .tfasir went to India via Muscat in September 1925, and while at Muspat he applied for and obtained a prssport from the Council of Ministers,thus admitting his connection, with the Muscat State* The Amire of Jaalan employ at Bombay a broker,who sells their date® and dried fish*and in return sends rice and other goods to sur* The name of this broker is Abdulla Saleh,a man of negroid extract- •icn,who dresses in very shabby European clothes and has a alight knowledge of English* It is generally considered that it is this individual who is to agreat extent the originator of the letters which liuhoraed bln A&amp;slr has deeroed fit to addresu to tue Government of India* Mr«£• b»Thamas'.Financial Adviser 9 was in iiorabay during the first half of last January with a view to proceeding on Triad' to Dhofar to embarl; Hie Highness the Buitan,and 9 acting on my suggestion,he put himself in touch with Liahomed bln Hacir,and with the approval of the Senior Ksval Officer offered him a passage to his country in order that he should nake preparations for the visit of the Anglo Persian Oil Company^ geologists* It had been arranged that these gentlemen would travel on !UM*3* 'Triad' to Phofar,survey thio place in so far time permitted,and would then visit a certain locality within the influence of the Amlrc of Jaalan and of Shaikh Hanrur bin Haair al Tajall* 3* Tahoned bin Hasir accepted the offer of the passage and. was die- -embarked in the limits of his eountry,H*ii*T*'Triad' then pro- -ceedlng to Dhofar* Slialkh Mansur hed been previously asked by this Political Agency to meet H*M*S # *Triad” and to exert his influence with the local Bedouin tribes to allow the geologists to carry out the survey of the mainland opposite the Island of Hamur an Hafar* On the arrival of H*M*S,'Triad” off Hamur an liafar island on her return from Dhofar both Shaikh Mansur and Mahomed bin Hasir were found to be present with a number of trlheoxaen* The geologists were met in a friendly aianner end were able to carry out their survey* The geologists presented on behalf of the An^lo Persian Oil Com- -pany Rs*750 each to the two Chiefs end two second hand rifles* Mahomed bin Nasir subsequently deputed his youngest brother. Shaikh llsmdan bln Basir,tc attend His Highness the Sultan up to Muscat* 4* 4*Shaikh Hamdan has had two interviews with me since his arrival* i He has evidently been Instructed by his brother to assert the in- •dependenee of Jsalan,while protesting that the 'Amirs' ore friendly allies of both Muscat and of the British* He was also to get permission to purchase 12 rifles and 10,000V v v ^1 rounds of amtunitlon* - I reminded Shaikh Kaxadan that ths ransom paid for the kidnapped Hindu was still out standing, but his only proposal wr^a that this sum should be forglren* He eventually said that he would bring the matter to his brothert notice# It is quite clear that the ' all of -hir has not the least chance of recovering this ransom money without pressure being exerted through this Political Agency on the Jaalan Amirs# The claim of the Jaalan Amirs that they are independent of Muscat is one that cannot otand a moment's scrutiny from the his«* -torical point of view# In 1820 during the reign of Pultun Saiyid &amp;aeed a dluasterous expedition was undertaken by this Sultan in conjunction with the British against the Beni bu Ml of Jaalan#?his tribe had embraced trie Wahabi tenets and in other ways had incurred His Highness' displeasure,and so far as the hrltieh were concerned,the tribes* •men had murdered the interpreter of !I#lf, 3#' Mercury** • The oom* •bined forces were shipped to Sur and thence invaded the Beni bu Ali country! They suffered a very serious defeat# In the following year, 1821,a large force was deapatohed under Ueneral Sir Lionel Smith from Bombay.which inflicted a decisive defeat on the Beni bu All# The ^ort of I&gt;ur has always paid customs duties to the Muscat State and still does so# Theoretically,and practically as regards the collection of cus- •toros duties at aur,the nmirs of Jaalan are subjects of His High- •ness the Sultan# These Amirs are also subsidised by the Muscat State,arm an allow- •anoe of 100 dollars a month is regularly paid by the Muscat State Treasury•This sum was apparently first paid in 1891,but the Muscat State Records are In such confusion that it is not pose* -ible to trace the full history of this allowance# As regards the origin of the title of 'Amir*by which these Jaalaf Shaikhs are known the same difficulty is again experienced owing to the lack of archives# It is however generally believed that this title was assumed—n I(£ by or firen to tho Boni bu Alt Blmtkh® in 1800 ®t the time of the Wahabi acoendenoy* As in well known to the Honourable the Political Resident,this title in Arabia is frequently conferred on Governors and Deputy Governoro • ao tts in the oaee of the Amir of Haaa« It jaay aleo be atroufoed tiiat these jutirs are by no means all powerful in Jaal&amp;n,as there is a large rival tribe antago* -nistio to them,the Beni bu liassan* The Beni bu All are Wahabis and of the Ohafirl political faction* The Beni bu Haesan are of the Abadhl si^ct and Hlnawl in politics* The Husoat State is at present weak and feeble 9 and in the circumstances any petty Chieftain or tribe can with impunity claim independence* I however trust that when the purchase of a steamer is completed and officials of the 8t«te ore enabled to travel up and down the coaut,a very considerable change for the better will occur* In this connection it may not be out of place to mention that since His Highness returned from Bhofar a very noticeable oliango is apparent in his interest in matters of State* Instead of reiterating to the Political Agent that any attention to public matters rmkoa him ftel giddy in his head,he now dis- •ousses State affairs with great interest and has announced hia intention to make a prolonged tour in the neighbourhood of Sehar after the Id* It is indeed most satisfactory to see this change in ills Highness* In view of the facts noted in this letter I would submit that the Government of India should take no notice of the Amir's claim for independence* As regards hia request for rifles and ammunition,I have discussed the matter with Tils Highness and the latter is of opinion that it is undesirable at the present Juncture to re» •fuse jja toto the request*The only place in His Highness' ter£l~ •tory where traces of oil have been found is within the Jaalan Amir's territorial influence* He suggests that a 'Bo objection Certifioute ,, for 5 rifles and1 9 000 rounds bs issusd t and X sgrss witu His Highness 1 views* Should the Hon'ble the Politioal Resident concur,I recom- -jiiend that the Aoiir of JaaXan be given to understand that any further sanction for rifles and ammunition will depend on a satisfactory termination of the Hindus ransom claim* Z attach ooples of such documents mentioned by the Amir as having emanated from this office as can be traced* In no way can such documents be held to denote the independence of the Amirs* It is customary for the Political Agentfliuscat,to address the Shaikhs of tribes direct and not through the Muscat Government* I have the honour to be. Your most obedient servant. Lieut*Colonel, Political Agent and H«B«lf 9 s Consul,Kuscat*H P.A. 7/2/26. I sub nit he rcnith a note about the 14 enclosures... being letters from the Political Agent to the Shaikhs Ali bin Abdullah and Muhammad bin ITasir. Of these, 4 important ones have been traced on the files and copies have been made in triplicate. As regards the rest,with the exception of two ,all have been traced in the Despatch Register ( Arabic) and abstracts have been copied in triplicate. ^about Most of the letters areVthe help rendered by. them in connection with the British ship Charles Tellier. V/ 'hich shipwrecked in 1S19. There is no letter in these confirming the independence of the Amirs of Jaalan, but it may be noted that Mr Wingate in the letter of recommendation dated 11th June 1921 c.nd the Permit to carry arms of the same date, called . Shaikh Muhammad bin JTasir , SHAIKH of JAAIAH and not a Shaikh, 7/i/i6 . G-TfavU '“'3 Utu. &amp; (?■ 61 ' Gz-^L /■ n z 6. //U-Ca- fee/'Enc. 5 £nc. ISno. Knc. Enc. md lOnc. 2 n«« Enel Enel . HO 36 ( mi 360) da^«d 3rd 1920. tttetnxmm In this latter the Politleal Agent infomed the Shaikhe that he will reaeh Sur on the 9th 'ay 1920. $ Letter HO. 49 dated the 8th June 1920. In this v the Political \sant aotaolodged thoir letter in whieh they mentioned their expenses on Charles Tellier, 7, Letter HO. 64 dated the 26th July 1920. In this letter the Political Agent informed the Shaikhs that Charles Ttllier would he atondoned and they could take it if they liked. ** ^ i'j 3. Letter HO. 10 dated the 3rd January 1S21. The Polltloal A^ent oeKnowlodged the Ticiiu'.s letter asking for 4000 ha^,a of rice other th&amp;Ai ^ 9. letter Ho. 35 det^d 5th April 1921. The Political Agent replies to Shaikhs letters the- 29th Janadi ath * M Thani and l^ajah, and inforia thea that the GoYt granted them #4200 for their expenses on Charles Tollier. the 1# # Letter Ho, 41 dated the 20th April 1921. In reply to the Political Agent Shaikhs letter dated the 4th Chahan informing* them that $ 4200 were paid over to their agent Salim kin Abdullah as requested by thejp. 11 Notification dated 1st Ran&amp;ar (not IBth) re penal Zikat, Cony is attached. 12. Permit to carry arms in Indie. Copy attached. 13. Letter of recommendation. Copy attached. 14. Cntraced.y N 0 ****** I 0 *. HMMHMMMMMHt is* It known to th* public that sone of the Omni* rebelled acainat th* I’ueOat Uoremnent haw* taken jossesa- ion unlawfully and a«atn*t th* luiiwh of sarden* belongine to ■ th* Wall ‘lohawsed bin ^haed and Sheikh iwohi' t i- Uaair and robbed their housau of their content* and re fused to return them to their *»id owners *v*n after the mediation of the Great British Ooyeramant, which mediation they themselTes had first naked and than refused. This nation shows tbe oppression and violence of the Oraani* which is against both th* 3iar*h law and the law of reaeon and by doing this they hay* broken th# haws ef God and lixa -trophet. Sow therefore to punish these owpreeeors and their followers, we erder th# iapeeition of a penal a»kat | af 35 * on Omani and iiharqi date# and SO* on pomegranates which may be brought on to the coaet. Thi# i# a temporary erder, based against these opnreesore and their followers. Consequently »* warn the purchasers of the date* and po- e- granate* that they should bear in mind while purchasing these kind* fror. these aforesaid that they should maJte their account accerdingly. This ie a penal 2akat and is in no sense an export duty and may be charged at the full market rate either in cash or kind, date* and pomegranate# which are exporv- ! ’ lU: *- hay* a eertlfieat# signed by the Muscat Customs to the effect that the legal Zakat ha* been paid, otherwise if exported without th# said certificate, they may he seized and confiscated* A» regafda the dates brought by the Baal Ghaiir aX Mayeha and th* place* ef the Banl Bu Ali under the Amir ef Jaalan who are alii** of th* Muscat Government only 5&lt; Zakat may be taken as before* Seal of H.H the Sultan. dated l&lt;|&amp;J}S9*&amp;a.l22§ 20 th Hay 1920. Seal of signature Yaimur with his own hen * T MV r*_ m m --— . ^Uuseat XIth Jun« 193X* P^mvr TO CAmY Am?. This Is to eortify that Shaikh Mahomod bin Hasir Mvl 9 Shaikh of Jaalan and prominent Oman Shaikh who is proceeding on a pil- -griaago to Msooa Tla Bombay with 15 foil owe re is permitted to carry with him from Huaoat 9 subject to the regulations of the port of entry 9 the following arms:* 14(fourteen) rlfles 9 14(fourteen Meggers 9 6(six)sowrds 9 (sd) Wingate 9 Z«C«S« Political ^ent and n«B*U f s Consul 9 ^usoat*Huscat IXth June 1921• Thu bearer Slmlkh Hahoxoad llaalr Alwi**&gt;huiich of Jaalon# la proceeding on a pilgrizaage to eooa Yia Bombay* He has recently been of considerable aooietance to the crew of of a wrecked British ship* It is hoped therefore that British officials will give him such assistance as he may stand in need of. (sd) R.iS.L.Ylng&amp;te, I.O.3., Political Agent and H.B.H«s ConsulMuscat*telegram code. From - Resident, Bushire. To - Political, Muscat* No. 250. Bated 10th (Reed.11th) April 1926 Your telegram dated March 24th, 32 Please inform Amir that certificates to import 10 rifles and 2000 rounds will he given as soon as he arranges refund to TTali of 3ur of ransom paid hy T.uscat Gtate fullstop.A H». ^ of 1926.. Muscat 9 the Ptli A p r«i 1 1926. LA-fc-V Co ’r^r^ So • The Council of ' inioters to Ills Highness tlie '^iltan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat*. I.. , “ ^\*i Af ^ er Otw^plimeniap Ol&amp;\ As Your honours are aware a Tritish subject named Kersandas Lwi. * * - . Lalji was kidnapped from r&gt;oor by the /V 5 ' • '* ikmon tribe during tlie summer of last o*;). C&gt;^&gt; i; (j^Jj rttn5#oia m ' P 11 ^^ ^ Shaikh Mahomed bin and was held to ransom* 1 understand that the s' r.aair of the hani bliuAli tribe, who ^ (SVfjSi\ +i» ^ ^ thereupon obtained the release of Kersandas ^ dutfi I ^ I have now the honour at to request that I may be informed what if ^ fll any steps liave been taken to punish the Hlkman tribe and to prevent a repitition of their criminal action. m . . liasir Hie para lount Ohaikh of tlie Rikra&amp;n (i^b Is SQiaikh Maliomed bln L m * )aJL — as well as of the I'ani hib All or If no t in what way did the kidnapping and return of Kersandas concern him* This is what had to be said and salaams. Os ^ V Political Atent &amp; h. i„ l» 0 Consul. Muscat. * n Asrarrs^Er *swr-«rTranslation -Prom The Council of Ministers to H.H. the aultan of Muscat and Oman• TO 1-ajor O.C.Barrett, H.B.M. f s Consul, Muscat. After Compliments, V/e have the honour to reply to your letter dated the ath April and 17tn April 1926. We have understood all that you mentioned about the ALHalman who had kidnapped the iiindu by name Kersandas who v/as ransomed and about whom the amount of ransom was received by Shaikh Muhammad bin riasir from the Govt of Muscat. We have forwarded your letter with our letter to the Mftaxkhg Ali bin Abdullah and Muhammad bin -Wasir, Shaikhs of Bani Buali r We have asked for a refund of the amount of ransom as Shaikh Muhammad bin Basir had promised in his letter to get refunded from the A1 Hakman S2 for each SI paid. Bated the 9th Shawwal 1344 22 23rd April 1926. Sd/ ^aiyid Aadir. Sd/ ^aiyid Muhammad. Sd/ Shaikh Mashid. ^d/ ^aji Aubair.. _T 2 _ Confidential. SjUt* No . 206-S• of 1926. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 22nd May 1926. The Political Agent, Muscat. * / Sir, I am directed to forward a copy of a letter dated Bombay, the 15th April 1926, and received by the Hon’ble the Political Resident from Abdulla Saleh, who calls him self the representative of the Amirs of Jaalan. 2 . I am to request you to inform the gentleman with reference to his letter that no communication^from him regarding the affairs of the Amirs of Jaalan can be attended to by this Residency or the Muscat Political Agency. The Amirs* proper course, in matters concerning themselves which call for consideration by the representa tives of His Majesty’s Government, is to address the Political Agent, Muscat, direct. I havejthe hhnour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, ( Capt., •fin Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL . Railway Hotel, Charni Road, Bombay, 15th April 1926. Prom Abdulla Saleh, Representative of Amir of Jalan. To The Resident, British Government, Bushire. Re: Exploration of oil wells iii Jalan, Massira and neighbouring territories and sanction of ten rifles and 10,000 ammunition. Bear Sir, In the first place I consider it a privilege to introduce myself as an authorised representative of the Amir of Jallan, Kassira and the neighbouring territor- ies. I am directed by tht/ Amir and Shaikh Mansoor to communicate with\ you direct from Bombay regarding your proposals and views of survey thereof as well as for the sanction of the aforementioned Arms for which the brother of Amir in the month of February while he had been to Muscat discussed the matter with British Consulate who was pleased to allot the Arms and also informed him that a sanction will follow soon after. Awaiting for your favourable and early reply at your convenience. I remain, Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, SD A. Saleh.' L ' iv~ No. f^oS 1926. Politioal /»ctrioy and Coneulat#, Muscat, tne 12th June 1926. &amp; i T .'r. Abdulla Galuh, HailTr y Hotel, Charai Koad, Bombay • lEIvIOH/JIDUM . With reference to your letter aated 15th /.pril 1926 to the address of the Hon*ble the Political Reoident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, I have to inform you that no communications from you regarding the affairs of the Araire of Jaalan can be attended to by the Bushire Residency or the Muscat Political Agency. The Amirs' proper course in matters concerning themselves which call f consideration by the representatives of Hie Majesty's Government is to address the i^olitical Agent, Muscat, direct. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. /A; ' J \X LOGICAL Tics: OF THE AIIIRS ( BAIT I BUALI ) JAALAIT. ,&lt;-x- »■#*** x--* 0 AIT ] HAT TAB I - i 'fom (f) © SALT!' AB DULLA H Ct) * / 1 HAPCJD * BA3IR al: SALIM @ I/IUHAJ MAD HAMDAIT. P. A. (^Karachi) The Above has heen prepared from the local krrov.rle.dgQ* There is already a tree of the family on the file of the Amirs of Ja&amp;lan, which was •• prepared in Col Crosthwaite f s time. • The present AM1H3 are Shaikh All hin Abdulla and his nephew Muhammad 'bin i^asir. They act jointly and si^n all correspondence jointly. There was never Before a JO HIT AMXRSHIP in this fatally and there used to he one Amir Aniy. Shaikh Abdulla held the Amir ship for about a century with the exception of a few years when Muhammad bin Majid tamp or airily gained ' the . 1 Amirship ( but soon lost it in favour of Abdullah .) his ’Then Shaikh Abdullah died, £hx eldest son Basir had already died and Muhammad hin Baeir was a minor, the tribes recognized Muhammad bin Basir and his uncle Ali bin Abdullah as joint Amrs. &lt; * Muhammad bin Basir is at present aged .Albout 32 •• and _a\li bin Abdullah ,, T7 'Then Lorcf Curzon visited Muscat in 1903/4 Shaikh Abdullah was introduced to ills Excellency. Avery body v/as bowing down and saluting the viceroy. But Shaikh Abdullah did nothing of the sort, ne came up and addresses nis Excellency a&amp; below: * r..Translation Dated 15th Dhil Qaad 1344 1st June 1926. TO Major C.C.Barrett, H.B.M.’s Consul, Muscat. After Compliments f We 2 have received your letter which was a reply to my l2 our letter. We have understood all that „ you mentioned about your coming to Sur. We regret that we could not meet you. You have mentioned that at present you can not can not come to Sur owing to excessive heat. We know that and and you are excused. You say that after 15 days you will proceed to India. We wished to reach you and resolved to do a so but as you know the time is short and journey long. On your return from India we will meet at Sur as promised by you, in health and pleasure. And salams • Sd/ Ali bin Abdullah. Muhammad bin Nasir. xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/61</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/61</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File XXXVIII/2 Sur and the Amirs of Ja‘alan. Amirs of Ja‘alan 1923. 1923 to 1926.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1920/1926</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-07T11:10:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (94 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 96; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-95; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of letters, enclosures and reports related to the Amirs of Ja'alan [Emirs of Ja‘lan] Bani Bu Ali and their claim of independence in Sur. Considering themselves to be independent rulers over southern Oman, the Amirs of Ja‘alan requested that the Government of India consult them before any planned visit to the region by geologists of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company.The file contains correspondence regarding an application from the Amir of Ja‘alan to export arms and ammunition from India. It also contains correspondence regarding a proposed visit to Sur by the Political Agent, Muscat. In addition, the file contains a detailed report (ff 40-50) issued by the Political Agency, Muscat, about Ja‘alan, its Amirs, the Bani Bu Ali tribe and the areas and tribes belonging to them, and the affairs at Sur.The main correspondents in the file are the following: the Amirs of Ja‘alan; the Political Agency, Muscat; the Political Residency, Bushire; the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Delhi. Most of the correspondence in the file is dated 1926.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000295#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>