<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001f5_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-08T11:52:48.691Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">4 exported to Aden, Zanzibar and East Africa. The weaving is done on hand looms in various Baluch homes but is merely a cottage industry. No machi nery is employed and no State encouragement is given. (E) Communication and Transport. State of communications generally. —Transport along the coastal towns is still carried out by sailing vessels and remains the cheapest means of convey ance. Light cars can run some 280 miles up the Batinah Coast to Kalba but the unsuitability of the existing tracks for anything in the nature of lorry traffic precludes any attempt to introduce road transport for commercial purposes. The only properly constructed road in the country is between the towns of Muscat and Matrah on which motor cars ply daily. Transport rates by car. Name of town. No. of miles. Bate per trip. Muscat to Matrah . 21 R8. A. P. 18 0 „ Bait-al-Falaj . , 31 3 0 0 „ Wutaiyeh . , 10 4 0 0 ,, Sib . . t . 36 12 0 0 „ Birka ..... 56 15 0 0 „ Musna .... 731 20 0 0 „ Siiwaiq . . . 87 25 0 0 „ Khabura , . , , HO ■ 35 0 0 „ Sahana ... 128 . 40 0 0 „ Sahar . . , , 60 0 0 „ Kids-el-Hasa 165 55 0 0 „ Murair-el-Matariah . 192 65 0 0 Air Service. —The Imperial Airways have an aerodrome which is a refuelling station on the Makran Coast at Gwadur a possession of the State of Muscat. The Air Route parses over the Sultan’s territory approximately half way between Muscat and Ras Masandum but has Only an emergency landing ground on the mainland. (F) Social. Standard of The majority of the indi genous population is completely poverty ridden and live a hand to mouth existence, generally in cumbered with debt. They subsist chiefly by fishing and on the date harvest. In most eases a date crop is mortgaged a year in advance to speculative exporters and the cultivator rarely derives the full .benefits of his toil. Like many impoverished people the local inhabitant is hardly but spendthrift and, expending what he has while he has it, has little heed for the morrow. Employment. —Un-employment in the main towns of Muscat and Matrah is rife. Public Health and Hygiene. —Hygiene and sani tation are conspicuous by their absence. Various forms of eye and skin diseases and malaria abound everywhere. During the period under review work was started on the erection of up to date fish and meat markets ^ and slaughter houses in both the towns of Muscat/ and Matrah. A scheme has also been put in hand for the filling and draining of the notorious Muscat. “ pond ” a pestilential swampy area of several acres in extent situated almost in the centre of the town and a prolific breeding ground for malarial mosquitoes. Mumcipality.^-A municipality exists in name but has neither the funds nor the administrative ability \ to effect any improvements. R. P. WATTS, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. Date Trade of Muscat. One of the two main products of the Sultanate of Muscat is dates. These are grown both in the interior of Oman proper and in groves extending northwards for some 150 miles along the Eastern littoral from a point approximately 30 miles north of Matrah. ’ This area is known as the Batinah. 2. The dates may be divided into two categories, viz., (a) w T et and (6) dry. The former comprise the following varieties :— (1) Fard. (2) Khanisi. (3) Burni. (4) Hanzal. (5) Abu-Nar&amp;nj. (6) Khalas. (7) Khassab. (8) Farfarah. (9) Barshi. (10) Nagal, (11) Madluki. (12) Hawami. whilst the latter consist of :— (1) Mubsali. (2) Gaah Abunaranj. (3) Hamzal. (4) Hawami. 3. Fard dates, which are of premier quality, are mostly the produce of Oman proper. They fetch high prices and are exported to both the United Kingdom and the United States of America. 4. Inferior quality dates such as :— (1) Hilali. (2) Muzarib. (3) Sarma. (4) Zabid. (5) Muzang. (6) Gash-Barash. (7) Sidi. (8) Nagal Hilali. (9) Gash-Mushfah. (10) Shabrut. (11) Ainbukar. (12) Nizad./ Notes. Register No. P. 3588/36. SECRET. Minute Paper. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT - Dated Bee. 193 . To Under Secretary... Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... SUBJECT. Muscat Trade Report for the year 193U-35* Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. SEEN rwfri itical COMMITTf* 9 JUN 1936 Previous 'papers This report is more encouraging than its predecessor, which will he found at P.Z. 1499/35* Both imports and exports have increased hy over 6 lakhs and it would seem that trade in general is at last on the upward grade, after the lengthy period of depression since 1929* From the Indian point of view the increase of Japanese competition is, however, disturbing# Japan has strengthened her hold on the piece-goods market and it is doubtful whether it would he possible for Indian goods to avail themselves of the suggestion^made by the Political Agent on page 3» W**) /A'i ^ ' \s Cl x / COP v V&gt; . ) 1 i AoisH*** Letter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, No. 14 of 1936, dated* the 4th January 1936. I have the honour to forward two copies of my Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1934-35, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me.Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1934-35. &amp; PART i. General description of the Sultanate of Muscat. Muscat is the capital of the independent Sultanate of that name situated on the Eastern Coast of Arabia. ■With the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Musandum Peninsula between Dibba and Khor Kalba, which is under the independent control of minor Shaikhs, the sea-board of the Sultanate extends in the north from Tibat, on the western shores of the Musandum Peninsula, to Has Dharbat Ali in the south, situated some 290 miles due north of the extreme westerly point of Socotra Island. Inland the Sultanate extends to the borders of the Rub al Khali or to give it its local name—the Great Desert. Of late years the Omanis have become autonomous, the writ of the Sultan merely runs throughout a coastal belt varying in depth from some 15 to 30 miles. The interior is fot the most part mountainous, the main ranges running approximately parallel to the sea coast with barren, rocky offshoots extending in places down to the sea. The higher inland ranges, with a comparatively good rainfall, are wooded in places and generally fertile. The sea coast for some 190 miles north-west of Muscat is known as the Batinah. It consists of a fertile strip covered for some 100 miles of its length with extensive date grooves. The remainder of the coast line within the limits of the Sultanate are barren and forbidding, with the notable exception of Dhofar in the extreme south. This southern province of Dhofar extends from Murbat in the east to RaS Dharbat Ali in the west, and is bounded on the north by the Qura mountains. Being well within reach of the monsoon rains and being blessed with several perennial streams, this area, particularly round Salalah, is extremely fertile, The town of Muscat, once important and pros perous, has given place to the adjoining port of Matrah as the trade centre and focus of commercial dealings with the Batinah and the interior. Muscat however still continues to be the seat of Government and the capital of the Sultanate. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa dollar and the copper coin, known as the Baiza, minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and rupees are generally accepted, but the dollar is the only currency recognised in the interior. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value con siderably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrain pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohammadis and Gajh, hypothetical units of which the former com prises two species, the black and the white. The latter is used as a basis of calculation in whole sale transactions, whilst the black Mohammadi, twenty and a half of which constitute a dollar, is used for petty retail trade. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohammadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh . . . . .1 Mohammadi. Mohammadis . &gt; .1 Dollar. 100 „ .... 1 Toman. Exchange Rate. Exchange for 100 Maria Theresa Dollars. 1932-33. 1933-34. 1934-35. Es, a. p. Rs. A. P. Rs. A. P. Highest bazaar rate . 86 8 0 96 0 0 114 4 0 Lowest bazaar rate 75 8 0 85 0 0 90 0 0 Average baianr rate . 80 14 0 90 8 0 101 0 d Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department prescribed in Muscat, Matrah and the Coast towns are :— 1 Kiyas , . * . . The Weight of 6 dollars or 5-9375 o/.s. 24 Kiyas . . . . .1 Muscat Maiind. 10 Muscat Maunds . . .1 Farasalah. 200 Muscat Maunds . . &lt; 1 Bahar. Rice is sold by the bag ; other cereals by the following measures — 20 Palis ..... 1 Farrah. 20 Farrahs . . . .1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Auqia * equals eight “ Misqals ”,w 1 2 Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr . . . . .1 Hand or 4| inches 4 Shibrs . . . . .1 Dhira or cubit. 4 Dhiras . . . . .1 “Ha ” or fathom. Legislation. The Government of the Sultanate is conducted hy the Sultan and is of the oriental type tempered by Treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The heads of the various State Departments carry out their administrative duties under the orders of His Highness and the Walis (or Governors) in charge of districts are directly responsible to the Sultan. Civil and Criminal Courts are presided over by a Chief Justice, but cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases of British sub jects and Protected persons against Muscat subjects are decided in the Muscat Courts, in which the right of Consular representation is held and exercised. Customs. Reciprocal Customs treaties have been executed by the Sultan of Muscat and Oman with Great Britain, Prance and the United States of America, in accordance with which all goods have been sub jected to an import duty of 5 per cent ad valorem determined at current market prices. In April 1934, however, in view of the parlous state of Muscat finances the Governments of the two first named countries agreed to modify their treaty rights and to consent to an imposition of 10 per cent on certain goods classified as coming under the category of luxuries. There is no duty levied on goods exported from the State but produce from the interior brought into the Coastal towns for sale or export is charged with an octroi duty of 5 per cent. In all districts subject to the Muscat Government’s authority the ancient Islamic tax known as “ Zakat ” of 5 per cent ad valorem, is enforced on the principal products of the country, in this case limes, dates and firewood. The revenues derived from Customs and the above taxes constitute the main source of the State’s income. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Matrah has been taken but a rough computation fixes the figures at 4,500 and 8,500 respectively. The large majority of the Indian trading commu nity consisting of Khojas and Banias which formerly inhabited Muscat has since moved to Matrah where greater facilities exist for direct trade with the interior. Shipping. The principal steamship lines which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report were as follows :— (1) The British India Steamship Navigation Ltd. (2) The Strick Line of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman &amp; Bucknall Steamship Co., Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. (5) The Yamashita Steamship Co., Ltd. 176 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 725,659 tons entered and cleared these ports during the year ending 31st March 1935. Of these 136 with a total tonnage of 444,365 were under the British Flag whilst 32 German (Hansa Line) vessels, with a total tonnage of 241,418 tons, 4 Japanese with a total tonnage of 16,852 tons and 4 Italian with a total tonnage of 23,024 tons, entered and cleared the ports of Muscat and Matrah. The British India Steamship Navigation Co.y Ltd., has maintained a weekly mail service from Bombay and Basrah. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— To Bombay and Karachi:—- Rs. A. Dry Dates 0 14 per bag. Wet Dates 11 0 per ton of 20 ewt. Wet Dates in cases 17 0 per ton of 40 c. ft. Dry Fish in bundles 1 0 per bundle. Pomegranates in crates 1 1 per crate. Raw wool . . 7 8 per bundle. Cotton piece-goods and woollen goods 14 0 per ton of 40 c. ft. To Colombo :— Dry Fish 33 0 per ton of 20 cwt. or To United States of America £ s. d. Wet Dates in bags or in cases . . 3 0 0 per ton of 40 c. ft. or 20 cwts. To London:— Wet Dates in bags or in cases . . 2 17 6 per ton of 40 c. ft. or 20 owt. PART II. (A) Trade. General Conditions. —There was an improvement in the import and export trade during the year under review. Imports show an increase of Rs. 6,05,494 over those of 1933-34, which is due to the increase in the3 at )rt import of textiles, rice and coffee. The value of exports also shows an increase of Rs. 6,80,077 accountable by the greater export of dry dates and dried fish. As in the past, rice, coffee, textiles, sugar and ^ spices formed the principal articles of import. India ■ c^kinues to be the sole supplier of cereals. Sugar is imported from Java and Belgium and spices o., mainly from India and China. Japan not only heads the list in the piece-goods trade, as the following table of the value of piece- goods for the years 1933-34 and 1934-35 will show, ng but continues to strengthen her position in the market n g year after year :— th sh 1933-34. 1934-35. a Rs. Rs. tal al India . . . 1,17,674 1,22,123 he United Kingdom 28,190 36,215 I., &lt;T ctpctn • • • . 3,62,579 5,33,623 ay China . . . 87,739 Other countries . . 21,260 68,849 Total . 5,29,703 8,48,549 Imports from Germany which amounted to Rs. 33,180 in the previous year dropped down to Rs. 29,979 in the year under review, the chief articles imported being whisky and brandy, hardware, lamp- ware and perfumery. China is a new comer in the silk market with a total of Rs. 60,679. Suggestions for meeting the competition. —As pointed out in the Trade Report for 1933-34, the popularity of the Japanese goods is mainly due to their cheap ness. British goods, though superior in quality, ft are beyond the means of the local inhabitants. Re duction in prices, study of the tastes of the people and proper advertisement would be steps in the right direction in the revival of British trade. Over-trading. —No over-trading was noticeable during the year under review. Commercial morality. —Generally speaking is sound. (B) Financial. Ready-money. —Money was easy during the year. Bankruptcy. —No insolvency cases were filed during the year. This shows that the financial position of the merchants was comparatively sound. Banks. —Banks being non-existent all transactions are met by hundis (drafts) on India. (C) Agriculture. There does not appear to have occurred any im provement in the agriculture or the irrigation of the country. The modern methods of irrigation and cultivation are altogether unknown to the Omani and he appears to be quite content with what little he can grow by his primitive methods. Dates, limes, tobacco pomegranates, sugar cane (very small quantities for local consumption) and Luban— resin of the alder tree which is used as a substitute for frankincense—remain now, as in the past, the principal crops of the country. (D) Industry. A small local industry exists in Matrah for the manufacture of turbans and loin cloths which are exported to Aden, Zanzibar and East Africa. The weaving is done on hand looms in various Baluch homes but is merely a cottage industry. No machinery is employed and no State encouragement is given. (£) Communications and Transport. State of communications generally. —The chief and cheapest means of commercial transport between the coastal towns is still by dhows as, although light cars ply and afford rapid means of communica tion throughout the Batinah, the unsuitability of the existing tracts for anything in the nature of lorry traffic precludes any attempt to introduce road transport of commercial utility. Transport rates by car. Name of town. No. of miles. Rate per trip. About Rs a. r. Muscat to Matrah . . 24 1 8 0 „ Bait-al Falaj • 34 3 0 0 „ Wutaiyeh . 10 4 0 0 „ Sib . . 36 12 0 0 „ Birka . 56 15 0 0 „ Musna . 734 20 0 0 „ Suwaiq . • 87 25 0 0 „ Khabura . . 110 35 0 0 „ Sahara . 128 40 0 0 „ Sahar . 144 50 0 0 „ Kids-el-B asa . 165 55 0 0 „ Murair-el-Matarish • • 192 70 0 0 Air Service. —The Imperial Airways have an aerodrome which is a refuelling station on the Mekran Coast at Gwadur—a possession of the State of Muscat. The Air Route passes over the Sultan’s territorywmmm 4 approximately lialf way between Muscat and Ras Massandum but has only an emergency landing ground on the mainland. (F) Social. Standard of living. —The maj ority of the indigenous population is completely poverty ridden and live a hand to mouth existence, generally encumbered with debt. They subsist chiefly by fishing and on the date harvest. In most cases a date crop is mortgaged a year in advance to speculative exporters and the cultivator rarely derives the full benefits of his toil. Like many impoverished people the local inhabitant is‘ hardy but a spendthrift and, expending what he has while he has it, has little heed for the morrow. Employment. —Un-employment in the main towns of Muscat and Matrah is rife. Public Health and Hygiene.- —Hygiene and sanita tion are conspicuous by their absence and to this may be largely attributed the great prevalence of malaria and the various forms of eye and skin diseases which everywhere abound. Municipality. —A municipality exists in name but has neither the funds nor the administrative ability to effect any improvements. R. P. WATTS, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. Date Trade of Muscat. One of the two main products of the Sultanate of Muscat is dates. These are grown both in the in terior of Oman proper and in groves extending north ward for some 150 miles along the Eastern littoral from a point approximately 30 miles north of Matrah. This area is known as the Batinah. 2. The dates may be divided into two categories, viz., (a) wet and (fe) dry. The former comprise the following varieties (1) Fard. (2) Khanisi. (3) Burni. (4) Hanzal. (5) Abu-Naranj. (6) Khalas. whilst the latter consist (7) Khassab. (8) Farfarah. (9) Barshi. (10) Nagal. (11) Madluki. (12) Hawami. of:— (1) Mubsali. (2) Gash-Abunaranj. (3) Hamzal. (4) Hawami. 3. Fard dates, Which are of premier quality, are mostly the produce of Oman proper. They fetch high prices and are exported to both the United Kingdom and the United States of America. 4. Inferior quality dates such as :— .. lK .(l) Hilali. (2) Muzarib. (3) Sarna. (4) Zabid. (5) Muzahg. (6) Gash-Barash. (7) Sidi. (8) Nagal Hilali. (9) Gash-MuShfah. (10) Shabrut. (11) Ainbukar. (12) Nizad. are more generally used for local consumption, but small quantities find their way to the Trucial Oman and South East Arabian ports. Dry dates are chiefly exported to India. 5. The date harvesting season extends from July to September and the first consignments Usually leave Muscat about mid-August. 6. Wet dates on arrival from the interior are delivered in Matrah where they are selected, pressed and packed in boxes of 12 lbs. and 108 lbs. each. Some are also packed in cartons, which in turn are packed in wooden boxes containing 100-115 lbs. net. 7. The date trade is practically in the hands of the Indian trading community, many of whom also act as commission agents for the producers. 8. The price of dates is quoted by the Bhar (equivalent to 1,800 lbs.) except when packed in boxes or packets. The following are the average prices per bhar that have prevailed during the last three seasons - 1932-33. 1933-34. 1934-35. Its. Rs. Rs. Dry dates produced in Oman 81 86 89 Dry dates produced in Ba- tinab .... 45 44 45 Wet dates produced in Bati nah .... 39 46 27 Fard dates .... 53 69 37 Fard dates packed in boxes, per box .... •• 15 9 Fard dates packed in packets. per packet •• 9 6 9. During the last three seasons the following quantities have been exported from Muscat: Year. Bags. Value (in Rs.). Dry dates .... 1932-33 79,876 6,88,712 1933-34 98,748 8,71,317 1934-35 12,390 11,22,7)5 Mats and boxes. Wet dates .... 1932-33 46,223 2,38,165 1933-34 44,512 2,52,906 1934-35 62,300 2,64,373HL.i_ GOt ^ ^5 ^ &amp; 1499 i N yi \Q7^ u,' 1 ™ a- ■••B 1»1 to' ■SJfif5','StSSw;. C “ ul ' '' ” I have the honour to forward two copies of my Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1933-34, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Uilf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me. 1NDI Le l C£Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1933-34 / PART I. General Description of the Sultanate of Muscat. Muscat is the Capital of the independent Sultanate of that name situated on the Eastern Coast of Arabia. With the exception of a email strip on the east coast of the Musandum Peninsula between Dibba and Kher Kalba, which appertains to minor Trucial Sheikhs, the sea-board of the Sultanate.extends in the north from Tibat, on the western shores of the Musandum Peninsula, to Has Dharbat Ali in the south, situated some 290 miles due north of the extreme westerly point of Socotra Island. Inland the Sultanate extends to the borders of the Great Desert, now better known perhaps as the Ruba’ Khali. Of late years the Omanis having become autonomous, the writ of the Sultan merely runs throughout a coastal belt varying in depth from some 15 to 30 miles. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the main ranges running approximately parallel to the sea coast with barren, rocky offshoots extending in places down to the sea. The higher inland ranges, with a comparatively good rainfall, are wooded in places and generally fertile. The sea coast for some 190 miles north west of Muscat is known as the Batinah. It consists of a fertile strip covered for some 100 miles of its length with extensive date groves. The remainder of the coast line within the limits of the Sultanate are barren and forbidding, with the notable exception of Dhefar in the extreme south. This southern province of Dhefar extends from Murbat in the east to Ras Dharbat Ali in the west, and is bounded on the north by the Qura mountains. Being well affected by the monsoon rains and being blessed with several perennial streams, this area, particularly round Salalah, is extremely fertile. The town of Muscat, once important and pros perous, has given place to the adjoining part of Matrah as the trade centre and focus of commercial dealings with the Batinah and the interior. Muscat however still continues to be the seat of Government and the capital of the Sultanate. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa Dollar .and the .copper coin, known as the Baiza, minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and rupees are generally accepted, but The .dollar is the only currency recognised in the interior. The Maria Theresa Dollar fluctuates in value considerably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrein pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohammadis and Gajh, hypothetical units of which the former comprises two species, the black Mohammadi and the white. The latter is used as a basismf calculation in whole sale transactions, whilst the black Mohammadi, twenty and a half of which constitute a Dollar, is used Tor petty retail trade. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohammadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh .... 1 Mohammadi. 11£ Mohammadis . . .1 Dollar. 100 „ ... 1 Toman. Exchange Rate. Exchange for 100 Maria Theresa Dollar. 1931-82. 1932-33. 1933-34. Rs. A. P. Re. A. P. Rs. A. P. Highest bazaar rate . 84 8 0 86 8 0 96 0 0 Lowest bazaar rate 63 0 0 75 8 0 85 0 0 Average bazaar rate . 73 0 0 80 14 0 90 8 0 Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department prescribed in Muscat, Matrah and the Coast towns are :— 1 Kiyas . . • The weight of 6 dollars or 5*9375 ozs. 24 „ . . .1 Muscat Maund. 10 Muscat maunds . 1 Farasalah. 200 „ „ . 1 Bahar. Rice is sold by the bag ; other cereals by the follow ing measures — 20 Palis 1 Farrah. 20 Farrahs . . . • I Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the dollar, of which the weight is called “ Auqia ”, are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One ' Auqia ” equals eight “ Misqals ”. Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr . . .1 Hand or 4£ inches. 4 Shibrs . . .1 Dhira or cubit. 4 Dhiras . . .1 Ba’ or fathom.2 Legislation. The Government of the Sultanate is conducted personally by the Sultan and is of the oriental type tempered by Treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The heads of the various State Departments carry out their administrative duties under the orders of His Highness and the Walis (or Governors) in charge of districts are directly responsible to the Sultan. Civil and Criminal Courts are presided over by a Chief Justice, but cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases of British subjects and Protected persons against Muscat subjects are decided in the Muscat Courts, in which the right of Consular representation is held and exercised. Customs. Reciprocal Customs treaties have been executed by the Sultan of Muscat and Oman with Great Britain, the United States of America and France in accordance with which all goods are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent ad valorem determined at current market prices. No export duty is levied but a charge of 5 per cent, is imposed in Muscat and at all coastal towns on dates and other commodities from the interior. The revenues derived from Customs constitute the main source of the State’s income. Population. No regular census of the populations of Muscat and Matrah has been taken but a rough computation fixes the figures at 4,500 and 8,500 respectively. The large majority of the Indian Trading Com munity which formerly inhabited Muscat has since moved to Matrah where greater facilities exist for direct trade with the interior. The deserted quarters of these emigres, having gradually fallen into a state of disrepair and ruin, lend an air of mournful desolation to the once thriving town of Muscat. Shipping. The principal steamship lines which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report were as follows— (1) The British India Steamship Navigation Company, Ltd. (2) The Strick Line of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman and Bucknall Steamship Co., Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. 123 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 434,658 tons entered and cleared these ports during the year ending 31st March 1934. Of these 115, with a total tonnage of 375,097, were under the British flag whilst 8 German (Hansa Line) vessels, with a total tonnage of 59,561 tons, entered and cleared the port of Matrah. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Ltd., has maintained a weekly mail service from Bombay and Basrah. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the War has not been resumed since. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— Rfi. A. To Bombay and Karachi:— Dry dates . . 0 12 per bag. Wet dates . . 10 0 „ tonof20cwts. Wet dates in cases . 10 0 „ „ „ 40 c. ft. Dry fish in bundles 1 0 „ bundle. Pomegranates in crates . .10,, crate. Raw wool . .78,, bundle. Cotton piecegoods and woollen goods 13 0 „ ton of 40 c. ft. To Colombo :— Wet dates . . 33 0 „ ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c. ft. Dry fish . . 33 0 „ ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c. ft. To United States of America :— £ s. Wet dates in bags or in cases . . 2 15 ,, ton of 40 c. ft. or 20 cwts. To London :— Wet dates in bags or in cases . . 2 15 ,, ton of 40 c. ft. or 20 cwts. PART n. (A) Trade. General Conditions .—The year under review has unfortunately not justified the slight indications of optimism prevalent at its outset. Imports have shown a decline of Rs. 4,63,396 in value, a decrease attributable more to the cheap quality of the goods imported than to the quantity. Japanese goods have been largely responsible for this falling off. The value of exports also shows a decrease of Rs. 1,46,024 as compared with last year’s figures. The total volume of trade for the year 1933-34 amounted to Rupees 48,89,532 as compared with Rs. 54,98,952 in 1932-33. The following comparative table shows at a glance the value of exports and imports for the years 1932-33 and 1933-34 1932-33. 1933-34. Rs. Rs. Imports . . . 34,71,618 30,08,222 Exports . . . 20,27,334 18,81,310 Of the total imports goods worth Rs. 19,09,922 were borne in steamers, whilst goods valued at Rs. 10,98,300 were imported in sailing craft.3 Export figures for goods borne in tbese two forms of transport were Rs. 14,93,890 and Rs. 3,87,420 New Items and Channels of Trade.—No new items of trade were developed during the year and no new channels explored. foreign Competition.—The chief and victorious nSipetitor in the field of trade in piece-goods this year has been Japan. Reference to last year s figures will show that the value of Indian imports in cotton goods alone amounted to Rs. l,/^,yoo and that of “ other countries ” (including Japan) to Rs. 3,59,049. This year Japan heads the list in the importation of piece-goods with a total of whilst India is a poor second with Rs. 1,17,0/4. The total value of piece-goods imported during the year from various countries is as follows Japan India United Kingdom Other countries Rs. 3,62,579 1,17,674 28.190 21,260 5,29,703 This signal success in their trade enterprises in the Muscat market is very largely due to the assiduous study by the Japanese not only of the trade situation and local requirements, but of the condition and tastes of the people to whom they hoped to commend their goods. By the despatch to Muscat of a com mercial agent to enquire on the spot into such matters the Japanese efforts have been crowned with a striking success which will undoubtedly still further manifest itself next year. Throughout the bazaars of Muscat and Matrah Japanese goods are everywhere in evidence. Artificial silk, cotton piece-goods, shoes, crockery, glass, toys, haberdashery, cigarettes and matches, all of Japanese make, predominate, whilst the con siderable local demand for a cheap cement gives rise to the certainty that this will figure largely in the list of Japanese imports for 1934-35. . In contra-distinction to this Japanese achieve ment, attention is invited to the decline m impor s of piece-goods from the United Kingdom, which has fallen in value from Rs. 1,38,515 m 1931 32, Rs. 43,765 in 1932-33 to Rs. 28,180 in 1933-34. The main reasons for this will be discussed under a sub- “TermaMtaport) trade efforts are chiefly directed towards hardware, toilet requisites, perfumery and cheap “ Whisky ” and brandy. There is not however a &lt;rreat demand for these commodities, the latter two of which only appeal to certain elements whose consciences and physical strength of constitution permit of them drinking these poisonous concoctions. Suggestions for meeting competition.— The present success of the Japanese efforts is attributable to the cheapness of their goods, their acumen and business endeavour. British goods (with the exception of gramophones alcoholic liquors and provisions) a J e ^ ted to the background primarily because of their bitant cost and secondly because no manufacturer attempts either to study local conditions, tas‘e s ot requirements and to adapt his wares accordingly With the notable exception of Messrs. Dakin Bros (wholesale druggists and surgical mstmment makers) no British firm has for a considerable number of years (if ever) thought it worth while to send a re presentative to these parts to study conditions and to advertise their products. ■R r ;+; C5 'h The advent of travellers on the part of British concerns to study problems in si/tt and to teke^m s for the adoption of their produced smtloca! taste and requirements should do much to further British m Attractive and suitable advertisements in local languages to “catch the eye” the adoption of original, if dazzling, wrappers and boxes m whic goods for sale are packed, are all methods by which the lost footing can be regained. It is however impossible to hope for any revival m the denial for British goods, superior as they may b&lt;„ substantial reduction in sale prices is effected^ _ local inhabitant does not require a vest to last him three years, or a cloth that wil! carry iim to the grave. He requires a cheap, serviceable article that^will carry him from one month s pay daj ti the next but one. If only for diversity, he would prefer to have three cheap articles to one that will Lt him longer but of which he will tire from con stant use and which in any case is beyond his actua F The Indian manufacturer has realised this, but, in spite of reducing the sale price of commodities he has not yet been enabled to e ffect » ^fficie reduction to compete with Japanese good . endeavour however is there. Over-trading. —Over-trading has not been notice able with the exception perhaps of ak^hciiquors. The chief licensed importer has been forced b) th terms of his contracts with certain European ex porters to import more than his requirements the latter having from various causes considerably ^Cammercial Morality.—Commercial morality generally speaking is good. (B) Financial. Ready money.—Money has been slightly easier during the year due to more settled conditions prevailing in'India but export merchants have been hit considerably by the fall in price of fish products and the cheaper form of date exported to India and ^Bemkruptcy .—Seven cases of insolvency were filed during the year under review. Most of the. were due to a combination of failure to realize de t&gt; ^ from others and a slackening of the trade indulged in.4 Banks. —Banks are non-existent all transactions being met by hundis (drafts) on India. (C) Agriculture. Agriculture is practically limited to the cultivation of dates on the Batinah seaboard as mentioned elsewhere, but limes, mangoes and pomegranates are also grown successfully. The best varieties come from the valleys of the Oman hinterland where water is comparatively abundant. In Muscat territory proper the dearth of water and the primitive system of irrigation by wells pre cludes any large cultivation of cereals and such as are grown are insufficient to meet local requirements. In the more fertile valleys of Oman sugar cane is grown in considerable quantities but the methods of oultivation and subsequent production for sale are primitive in the extreme. In the remote Southern Province of Dhefar the chief exports are cocoanuts and frankincense, the latter commodity being largely exported to India. (D) Industry. A small local industry exists in Matrah for the manufacture of turbans and loin cloths which are exported to Aden, Zanzibar and East Africa. The weaving is done on hand looms in various Baluch homes and can but be regarded as a cottage industry. iN’o machinery is employed and no State encourage ment is given. (E) Communications and Transport. State of communications generally. —The chief and cheapest means of commercial transport between the coastal towns is still by dhows as, although light cars ply and afford rapid means of communication throughout the Batinah, the unsuitability of the existing tracts for anything in the nature of lorry traffic precludes any attempt to introduce road transport of commercial utility. Transport rates by car. Name of town. No. of miles. Kate per trip. About Jl*s. A. P. Muscat to Mat rah , 2* 1 8 -0 „ „ Bait al Falaj 8* 2 4 6 „ „ Wutaiyeh - | V) 3 12 0 „*&gt;ib - 36 15 0 0 ff ,, Berka - 56 22 8 0 „ „ Musna . 73* 26 4 « ,, Suwaiq 87 30 o e „ „ Khabura . 110 37 0 0 • &gt; „ Saha® • • . 128 St £ 0 19 „ Sahar 1« 52 8 0 9» „ Kids-el-Hasa . . 165 60 0 « ” „ Murair-el-Malarish 102 75 e -o Air Service. —The Imperial Airways route lies through Gwadur, on the Mekran Coast, but advant age has not hitherto been taken of this means of transport which is beyond the resources of the average trade. (F) Social. Standard of living. —The majority of the indigenous population is completely poverty ridden and live a hand to mouth existence, generally encumbered with debt. They subsist chiefly by fishing and on the date harvest. In most cases the date crop is mort gaged a year in advance to speculative exporters and the cultivator rarely derives the full deserts of his toil. Like many impoverished people the local inhabitant is hardy but a spend thrift and, spending what he has while he has it, has little heed for the morrow. Un-employment in the main towns of Muscat and Matrah is rife. Public Health and Smallpox which appears to be endemic in most parts of Arabia, broke out in epidemic form during the year under review in both Muscat and Matrah. It raged for some months both in the Batinah and in the coastal villages south of Muscat but the two main ports were declared free of infection in November 1933. Hygiene and sanitation are conspicuous by their absence and to this may be largely attributed the great prevalence of malaria and the various forms of eye and skin diseases which everywhere abound. Tuberculosis is largely on the increase and is conspicuously so amongst the Khoja and Hindu community of Matrah, and the Baluch inhabitants of Muscat. This is chiefly due to over crowding in squalid quarters, to the filthy habits of the inhabitants and to the prevailing insanitary conditions. Municipality. —A municipality exists in name but has neither the funds nor the administrative ability to effect any improvements. A feeble effort is made to scavenge and sweep the main thoroughfares of the bazaars but, in the entire absence both of a public spirit and of adequate means to cope with refuse and other nuisances, the municipal areas of both Muscat and Matrah remain in a deplorable | condition. C. E. U. BREMNER, Ma;tor, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. Date Trade of Muscat. One of the two main products of the Sultanate of Muscat is dates. These are grown both in the interior of Oman proper and in groves extending northward for some 150 miles along the Eastern littoral from a point approximately 30 miles north of Matrah. This area is known as the Batinah.X RL. 19234/1935. COPY. COMMONWEALTH OP AUSTRALIA- 0**. 437/5/97. Australia House, Strand, LONDON, W.C.2. 12th December, 1934. Sir, I am in receipt of a raeraorandum from the Secretary of the Department of Commerce, in connection with statistics of the import and export trade of Arabia. The memorandum requests that copies of the following documents he obtained and forwarded, viz:- 1. The Trade and Navigation Report of Aden. 2. The latest Annual Report of the British Political Agent at Muscat, and 3. A translation of the present Tariff of Saudi-Arabia which, it is understood, was published in the Umm-al-Qura of 5th May, 1933, with amendments dated 23rd June, 1933, and 15th June, 1934. The High Commissioner would be glad if he could be informed where copies of these publications can be obtained. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) for Official Secretary. The Comptroller-General, Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, S.W.l.“DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE. (l MP. 35, Old Queen Street, London, S.W.i r &gt; '‘11 . U L » vj I 20486/Z Sir, 12th January, 1935 With reference to your letter of December 12th cm the subject of your desire to obtain copies of certain documents dealing with the trade of Arabia and to your letter of January 7th cm the same subject, I am directed by Lt.-Ool. J. Colville to state, with regard to the Aden Trade and Navigation Report, that the High Cccmiissioner for India in London has copies of these monthly and annual reports. The report for 1933-4 is still only in the proof stage. The report is an expensive one to purchase and a copy of the latest printed report could be seen at India House, Aldwych, London, W*C.2. 2. Your enquiry with regard to the latest Annual Report of the British Political Agent at Muscat is still under examination and a further letter in The Official Secretary, Commonwealth of Australia. regard/- 2 - regard to this report will he addressed to you in due course. 3. With regard to the present tariff of Saudi- Arabia it is understood that this matter has formed the subject of telephone conversations between yourself and a member of the Tariff Section of the Department of Overseas Trade. 4. I am to express Colonel Colville f s regret that an earlier answer has not been sent to your letter under reply. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, IaR for the Comptroller-GeneralRL. COPY* 19234/1935. DEPARTMENT OP OVERSEAS TRADE. r &lt; , 35, Old Queen Street, D v ; CJ i* LONDON, S.#.l. ComrA37/5/97 19th January, 1935 20436/Z Sir ^ith further reference to your letter of December 12th on the subject of Arabia, I am directed by Lt.-Col. J. Colville to enclose herewith a copy of the latest printed report by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty 1 s Consul at Muscat on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1932-33. I am Sir Your obedient Servant (Sgd.) The Official Secretary, Commonwealth of Australia.X p 2937a / Office of the High Commissioner for India. Address for J/rtawd Telegrams — Telephom HICOMIND, ESTRAND, LONDON. Cables —HICOMIND, LONDON. TEMPLE BAR 8484. Please quote the under-mentioned reference, and address any further commumcahon to The High Commissioner for India, PUBLIC Department, India House, Aldwych, London, W.C. 2, and not to any individual by name. P.253.1,2/5. li+th July, 1934 Reference Sir I am directed “by the High Commissioner for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No* P.Z. 3748/34, dated 9th Juity, 1934, forwarding two copies of the Muscat Trade Report for 1932-33. I am, Sir Your obedient servant, The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.V Letter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, No. 123 of 1934, dated the 3rd February 1934. I have the honour to forward two copies of my Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1932-33, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me. r-,.——— tr.CLCUJRE | iNOIA FOREIGN ; 'Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1932-33. Introduction. Muscat is the Capital of the Independant Sultanate of that name situated on the Eastern Coast of Arabia. With the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Mussandam Peninsula between Dibbeh and Khor Kalba, which appertains to minor Trucial Sheikhs, the sea-board of the Sultanate extends in the north from Tibat, on the western shores of the Mussandam Peninsula, to Has Dharbat Ali in the south, situated some 290 miles due north of the extreme westerly point of Socotra Island. Inland the Sultanate extends to the borders of the Great Desert, now better known perhaps as the Ruba’ Khali. Of late years the Omanis having become autonomous, the writ of the Sultan merely runs throughout a coastal belt varying in depth from some 15 to 30 miles. The interior is for the most part mountainous the main ranges running approximately parallel to the sea coast with barren, rocky offshoots extend ing in places down to the sea. The higher inland ranges, with a comparatively good rainfall, are wooded in places and generally fertile. The sea coast for some 190 miles north west of Muscat is known as the Batinah. It consists of a fertile strip covered for some 100 miles of its length with extensive date groves. The remainder of the coast line within the limits of the Sultanate are barren and forbidding, with the notable exception of Dhofar in the extreme south. This southern province of Dhofar extends from Murbat in the east to Ras Dharbat Ali in the west, and is bounded on the north by the Qura mountains. Being well affected by the monsoon rains and being blessed with several perennial streams, this area, particularly round Salalah is extremely fertile. The town of Muscat, once important and prosper ous has given place to the adjoining port of Matrah as the trade centre and focus of commercial dealings with the Batinah and the interior. Muscat however still continues to be the seat of Government and the capital of the Sultanate. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa Dollar and the copper coin, known as the Baiza minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and rupees are generally accepted, but the Dollar is the only currency recognised in the interior. The Maria Theresa Dollar fluctuates in value considerably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrain pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh, hypothetical units of which the former comprises two species, the black Mohamadis and the white. The latter is used as a basis of calculation in wholesale transactions, whilst the black Mohamadi, twenty and a half of which constitute a Dollar, is used for petty retail trade. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh . 11£ Mohamadis 100 1 Mohamadi. 1 Dollar. 1 Toman. Exchange Rate. Exchange for 100 Maria Theresa Dollars. 1930-31. 1931-32. 1932-33. Rs. A. P. Rs. A. P. Rs. A. P. Highest bazar rate 88 5 0 84 8 0 86 8 0 Lowest bazar rate 67 4 0 63 0 0 75 8 0 Average bazar rate 75 6 0 73 0 0 80 14 0 Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department prescribed in Muscat, Matrah and the Coast towns are :— 1 Kiyas , 24 „ . . 10 Muscat Maunds 200 , The weight of 6 dollars of 5-9375 o/.s. . 1 Muscat Maund. . 1 Farrasal. . 1 Bahr. Rice is sold by the bag ; other cereals by the following measures :— 20 Palis 20 Farrahs • • • .1 Farrah. • • • • 1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the Dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Auqia ” equals eight “ Misqals ”. ^2 Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr . . .1 Hand or 4£ inches. 4 Shibrs . . .1 Dhira or cubit. 4 Dhiras . . .1 Bah or fathom. Banking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among the merchants of issuing hundis (drafts) is in practice and as trade methods are primitive there are no sufficient inducements for the estab lishment of a Bank. Trade. The total volume of trade for the year 1932-33 amounted to Rs. 54,98,952 as against Rs. 54,44,445 of the previous year showing an increase of Rs. 54,507. Imports by Steamers as well as by Sailing Vessels show a decrease of Rs. 2,65,500 as compared with the previous year. Exports by Steamers as well as by Sailing Vessels show an increase of Rs. 3,20,007 as compared with the previous year. Of the total trade for the year the share of the Sailing Vessels is Rs. 15,90,037 and that of the Steamers Rs. 39,08,915. Share 6f Trade. Countries. Import. Export. Total. Percent age. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. India ■. .»■ 1 20,00,563 12,01,332 32.01,885 58-23 Persia 2,56,263 1,25,347 3,81,610 6-94 United Kingdom 1,51,380 6,750 1,58,130 2-88 Africa 81,803 45,155 1,26,958 2-31 Aden 12,430 9,500 21,930 0-40 United States of America 14,672 40,825 55,497 101 Germany. 277,550 2,77,650 5-05 China. 21,625 21,625 0-39 Singapore . 14,000 14,000 0-25 Other Countries includ- 9,54,507 9,54,507 17-35 ing Germany and Japan. Ceylon 2,06,735 2,06,735 3-76 Persian Gulf 78,525 78,525 1-43 Totai, . 34,71,618 20,27,334 54,98,952 100 00 Though it will be observed from the above figures that India still holds the field in both import and export trade, a reference to last year’s report will show a very heavy decrease under these items with the United Kingdom. This in the main is attribut able to the flooding of the market with Japanese goods of every description. The determined attempt of Japan to corner the local market seems destined to succeed if resolute measures are not adopted to lower the price of British commodities. This is I particularly applicable to piece goods of all descrip- 1 tions and to dry goods and metal ware. Imports. Total imports for the year amounted to Rs. 34,71,618 as against Rs. 37,37,118 of the previous year showing a decrease of Rs. 2,65,500. Of the total imports goods worth Rs. 23,26,605 were carried by steamships and Rs. 11,45,013 by Sailing Vessels. Exports. Total exports for the year under review amounted to Rs. 20,27,334 of which goods worth Rs. 4,45,024 were carried by Sailing Vessels and the balance by steamships. They show an increase of Rs. 3,20,007 from the previous year’s figures. Cotton goods locally manufactured were exported to Aden, Zanzibar and Africa : dry fish to Ceylon and Germany. Muscat manufactures—turbans and lungis. These are exported to Zanzibar, Africa and Aden. A considerable export of these articles passes through the post office and does not appear in these returns. The Post Office returns for the year under report show that goods worth Rs. 45,389 were thus export ed. Legislation. The Government is of the oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of the British subjects, over whom the local authorities have no jurisdic tion. The Government is carried on by His High ness the Sultan assisted by a Financial Adviser and an adviser of the Interior. The Civil and Criminal Courts are presided over by a Chief Justice. Cases against British Subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat subjects are decided by the Chief Justice but the right of Consular representa tion exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been execut ed by the Ruler of Oman with Great Britain, the United States of . America and France. In accord ance with the terms of these Treaties all goods im ported into Oman are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent, ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied but a charge of 5 per cent, is imposed in Mus cat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior. The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income. Transport. The chief and cheapest means of commercial transport between the coastal towns is still by Dhow as, although light cars ply and afford rapid means of communication throughout the Batinah, the un suitability of the existing tracks for anything in the nature of lorry traffic precludes any attempt to introduce road transport of commercial utility. A rough fair weather motor track has been con structed to Swakim about 50 miles from Muscat but financial stringency does not permit of coping with the serious natural obstacles to be met with in coit* tinning the track to Sur.3 Transport Rates by Car. Name of towns. No. of miles. Rate per trip. About Rs. A. p. Muscat to Matrah .... 21 18 0 „ „ Bait-el-Falaj 31 2 4 0 „ „ Wutaiyah. 10 3 12 0 „ „ Sib . 3(5 15 0 0 „ „ Berka .... 56 22 8 0 „ „ Musana .... 731 26 4 0 „ „ Suwaiq .... 87 30 0 0 „ „ Khabura .... 110 37 0 0 „ „ Saham .... 128 52 8 0 „ „ Sahar .... 144 52 8 0 „ „ Kids-el-Hasa 165 60 0 0 „ „ Murair-el-Malarish 192 75 0 0 Agriculture. Date growing is the principal agricultural interest of the inhabitants of the Sultanate. Limes, man goes and pomegranates are also successfully grown the best varieties in each case coming from the Jebel Akdar region. Cereals are also grown in quantities restricted by the absence of an adequate water supply. The Omani of the better watered interior grows sugar cane with considerable success but the methods of cultivation and subsequent production for sale are primitive in the extreme. Shipping. Steamers .—The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. The principal steamship lines which called at Muscat were as follows :— (1) The British India Steamship Navigation Co., Ltd. (2) The Strick Line of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman and Bucknall Steamship Co., Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. 123 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 4,54,936 tons entered and cleared the port during the year ending 31st March 1933, Of these 115 with a total tonnage of 4,05,013 were under British flag. 8 German, Hansa Line Vessels with a total tonnage of 49,923 entered and cleared the port. The British India Steam Navigation Company* Ltd.,- have maintained a weekly mail service both from Bombay and Basrah. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the War has not been resumed since. Sailing Vessels .—106 Sailing Vessels of all natio nalities with a total tonnage of 11,401 entered and cleared the port during the year of which 68 were from British India, 6 Vessels from Persia and 32 Vessels from other countries with a total tonnage of 7,635 300 and 3,466 respectively. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— Population. No regular census of the populations of Muscat and Matrah has been taken but a rough computa tion fixes the figures at 4,500 and 8,500 respectively. The large majority of the Indian Trading Com munity which formerly inhabited Muscat has since moved to Matrah, where greater facilities exist for direct trade with the interior. The deserted quart ers of these emigres, having gradually fallen into a state of disrepair and ruin, lend an air of mourn ful desolation to the once thriving town of Muscat. Public Health. The climate of Muscat and its immediate neigh' bourhood is extremely trying. The intense heat, accompanied by heavy moisture, is most oppres sive in May and June, whereafter the distant effects of the Indian monsoon slightly alleviate conditions till September, which month usftally heralds the malaria season. From December till February climatic conditions are ideal and afford a slight respite from the remainder of the year. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 114-1° and the lowest 53-4°. The total rainfall during the year was 3*22 inches. Rs. A. To Bombay and Karachi:— Dry dates . . . 0 12 per bag. Wet dates . . . 0 12 „ „ Wet dates in cases .16 0 „ ton of 40 c.ft. Dry fish in bundles . 1 0 j, bundle. Pomegranates in crates .10,, crate. Raw wool . . .60,, bundle. Raw cotton . . .38,, „ Cotton piece goods and woollen goods . .30,, bale. To Ceylon :— Wet dates . . . 36 0 „ 40 c.ft. or 20 cwt. Dry fish . . . 33 0 „ Ditto. To United States of America :— £ 8 . Wet dates in bags and in boxes . • ' • 2 15 ,, Ditto, To London:— Wet dates in bags and in boxes . ' • . 2 16 ,, Ditto. Sd. C. E. U. BREMNER, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.16 TABLE No. l-C—contd. Principal Articles and Countries from which imported during the years 1930-31, 1931-32 and 1932-33 — contd. Quantity. Value. i\RTICL.ES AND \JUUNJyKlUiS 1930*31. 1931-32. 1932-33. 1930-31. 1931-32. 1932-33. By Sailing Vessels— contd. Textile —contd. Cotton goods— Persia ...... . Pkgs. 8 £ Rs. Rs. 1,575 India ...... 27 33 33 346 3,321 7,161 Africa ...... • 99 .. .. 5 • • •• 860 Twist and yarn— India ...... • 99 11 8 8 158 1,214 1,635 Haberdashery— India ...... • 99 32 91 141 72 2,619 4,355 Carpets— Persia ...... • 99 5 11 6 128 3,046 310 Old clothing— Persia ...... • 99 2 .. 14 . . # . Sail cloth— India ...... • 99 12 20 .. 70 2,963 . # Gunny bags— India ...... • 99 23 377 619 216 18,353 27,975 Hemp—• India ...... • 99 1,342 13,558 Twine—• India ...... • 99 5 11 36 809 # 0 Wool— India ...... • 99 .. 6 . • • • 93 •* Medicines and Drugs. Medicines— India ...... . Pkgs. 17 29 32 734 Persia ...... 44 1,737 220 69 4,656 1,386 Other countries .... • 99 • • 25 • . *. 354 .. Drugs— Persia ...... • 584 2,154 India ...... • 99 • • • • 28 .. .. 544 Attaree— Persia ...... • 99 688 981 .. 271 5,178 • • Tobacco and Smoking Requisites. Cigarettes— India • Pbg 3 7 10 27 712 680 Tobacco— Persia ...... 79 72 64 73 769 567 India 5 15 • . 75 1,426 Snuff— India ...... 10 21 64 1,748 Wax paper—■ India ...... 1 10 Building materials— India ...... 16,052 4,330 4,919 1,120 15,005 13,390 Africa ...... 427 511 426 • . 5,646 Persia ...... 190 10 6,041 41 70 496 Other countries .... 26 • • 1,905 r • Candles— India . . ... 1 9 Stationery— India . . . . '. • 99 8 10 • 10 65 1,343 1,151# rrmi 19 TABLE No. 2-B— contd. Total Export of Principal Articles during the years 1930-SI, 1931-32 and 1932-33— contd. Articles . Quantity. Value. 1930-31. 1931-32. 1932-33. 1930-31. 1931-32. 1932-33. £ Rs. Rs. By Steamers — conid. Paints, Dyes and Colours. Waras (ochre) ..... Henna leaves ..... . Pkgs. • ** 2 8 •• .. 30 8 • • •• Precious Stones, Gold and Silver. Pearls Gold . Tins . Tolas 1 2,000 2,040 10,500 6,030 167 2,533 61,000 3,600 1,62,500 Textile. Cotton goods ..... Carpets ...... Twine ...•••• Silk Yarn . Pkgs. 138 1 13 51 23 4 4,638 80 30 35,800 16,625 2,000 Tobacco and Smoking requisites. Tobacco ...... . Pkgs. •• .. 32 1,000 Medicines and Drugs. Medicines ...... . Pkgs. 21 51 •• 13 2,250 •• Miscellaneous. * . . Copper Soap ...»••• Goat skins ...••♦ Goat hair ..•••• Hides and Leatherware .... Mattings . _ • Building materials .... Perfumery ..♦••• Motor cars ...••• Articles not specified above . . Pkgs. • 99 • 99 • 99 • 99 • 99 • 99 . Nos. 7 2 119 7 11 29 235 15 4 78 50 1 150 11 4 2 17 2 1,081 7 ‘ 72 24 90 20 . 8 240 2,460 ' 710 15 80 105 70 ”300 5,200 Total Export by Steamers .. • • 121,971 15,10,437 15,82,310 By Sailing Vessels. . Cereals. Puls© . Tons •• 2 •? • • 270 Fishes. • • Fish, dry and salted .... Sardine, dry • • - • ' Mother of Pearls Cuttles . • • • • Cowries ..•••• . Pkgs. • • 99 • 99 • 99 . Tina 4 6,957 '210 118 15 10,197 '153 57 132 28,303 23,850 ”602 11 1,416 ”99 50 • 155‘ 30,775‘ 710' 450 735 10,625 86,425 1,560 Fish oil ..**•• Fish manure • • • • ' Sharkfins . • • • . Pkgs. • 99 •• 4,501 257 •• r* 6,910 3,370FILE COPY '“TTz. ;iso , I 935 , # C fl£ U^KTC*/ H- c - 't B| T&amp;&amp; Letter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, No. 1006—25-14, dated the 21st September 1932. I have the honour to forward two copies of my Eeport on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1931-32, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me. ENCLOSURE IN LNDIA FOKi£l€N SECRpTaRv's Let ton N/} fl7g 4. 22DtC 1932 |R-' 9 JAM. 1933Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1931-32 Introduction. Muscat is the Capital of the Independent Sultanate of that name situated at the easterly corner of Arabia. Its seaboard is nearly 900 miles long and extends from Tibbat on the west side of Cape Mussandam round Ras Rajir rather over 200 miles due north of the Island of Socotra, with the excep tion of a small strip of the east coast of the Mussandam Peninsula from Dibbeh to Khor Kalba which is in the administration of the minor chiefs of Trucial Oman. The Sultanate extends inland to the borders of the Great Desert but of late years the Omanis have become autonomous and are now subject to the Imam of Oman and his Lieutenant Sheikh Isa bin Salih. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the high country extending down to the sea coast in a series of arid rocky heights though vegetation exists on the higher mountains. North west of Muscat the sea coast littoral tract is fertile and prosperous and date groves extend along it for over 100 miles. This strip is known as the Batinah Coast. The remainder of the coast with one notable exception is barren and forbidding and rarely visited by Europeans. The exception is Dhofar which is the name of a small fertile district comprising a group of villages at the south-west corner of the Sultanate. Gwadur, a port on the Mekran Coast, and a small tract of country round it, also owns allegi ance to Muscat. It is the last remnant of the Omani possessions on the Persian side of the Gulf. The town of Muscat, once so important and pros perous, has been falling into decay for years now. Most of the trade goes to the sister port of Matrah which is the starting point of the trade to the interior, but Muscat remains the capital and seat of Govern ment. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa Dollar and the copper coin minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and rupees are generally accepted. The Maria Theresa Dollar fluctuates in value considerably being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrein pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh, Imaginary coins. There are two kinds of Moha madis, black and white. Black 20|= 1 Dollar. The white is used in wholesale trade accounts and the black for fruits, vegetables, etc. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh . Ill Mohamadis . 100 Mohamadis 1 Mohamadi. 1 Dollar. 1 Toman. Exchange Rate. — Exchange per 100 Maria Theresa Dollars. 1929-30. 1930-31. 1931-32. Us. A. P. Rs. A. P. Rs. A. p. Highest bazaar rate . 125 0 0 88 5 0 84 8 0 Lowest bazaar rate . 97 8 0 67 4 0 63 0 0 Average bazaar rate . 116 8 0 75 5 0 73 0 0 Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department prescribed in Muscat, Matrah and the Coast town are:— 1 Kiyas . . 24 Kiyas . 10 Muscat Maunds 200 Rice is sold by the following measures :— 20 Palis . 20 Parrahs . The weight of 6 dollars of 5-9375 ozs. . 1 Muscat Maund. * 1 Farrasal. . 1 Bahr. bag; other cereals by the 1 Farrah. 1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the Dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Auqia ” equals eight “ Misqals.” 1 Shibr 4 Shibrs 4 Dhiras Measures (Linear). • • .1 Hand or 4J inches. . . . 1 Dhira or cubit. • . . 1 Bah or fathom. Banking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among the merchants of issuing hundis (drafts) isin practice and as trade methods are primitive there are no sufficient inducements for a Bank to be established. Trade. The total volume of trade for the year 1931-32 amounted to Rs. 54,44,445 (£395,958) as against £415,275 of the previous year showing a decrease ot £19 317. Imports by steamers as well as by sailing vessel show a decrease of £10,689 as compared with the previous year. , ... , Exports by steamers as well as by sailing vessel show a decrease of £8,628 as compared with the previous year. , Of the total trade for the year the share of the sailing vessels is Rs. 16,36,859 and that of the steamers 38,07,586. Share of Trade. Countries. Imiort. Export. Total. Percent age. Rs. Rs. Rs. India 22,36,897 9,43,880 31,80,777 58-42 Persia 3,09,907 49,077 3,58,984 6-60 United Kingdom 2,49,509 15,540 2,65,049 4-88 Africa 1,55,924 45,350 2,01,274 3-69 Aden 23,648 4,290 27,938 0-52 United States of 9,907 29,520 39,427 0-72 America. Germany . 3,76,920 3,76,920 6-93 China .. 37,000 37,000 0-68 Singapore 13,665 13,665 0-23 Ceylon 1,92,085 1,92,085 3-53 Other countries 7,51,326 7,51,326 13-80 Total • 37,37,118 17,07,327 54,44,445 100-00 As will be seen from the above figures India has played a prominent part in the year’s trade. Cotton goods locally manufactured were exported to Aden, Zanzibar and Africa ; dry fish to Ceylon and Germany. . Muscat manufactures— turbans and lungis These are exported to Zanzibar, Africa and Aden. A considerable export of these articles passes through the post office and does not appear in these returns. The Post Office returns for the year under report show that goods worth Rs. 40,250 were thus eyf ported. Note —The figures for 1930-31 converted @ Rs. 15 to the £ and those for 1931-32 @ Rs. 13-12 to the £. Legislation. The Government is of the oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by His Highness the Sultan assisted by a Financial Adviser and an adviser of the Interior. The Civil and Criminal Courts are presided over by a Chief Justice. Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat subjects are decided by the Chief of Justice but the right of Consular representa tion exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been executed by the Ruler of Oman with Great Britain, United States of America and France. In accordance with the terms of these all goods imported into Oman are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent, ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied but a charge of 5 per cent, is imposed in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior. The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income. Imports. Total imports for the year amounted to Rs. 37,37,118 (£271,789) as against £282,478 of the previous year showing a decrease of £10,689. Of the total imports goods worth Rs. 22,97,149 were carried by steamships and Rs. 14,39,969 by sailing vessels. Exports. Total exports for the year under review amounted to Rs. 17,07,327 (£124,169) of which goods worth Rs. 1,96,890 were carried by sailing vessels and the balance by steamships. They show a decrease of £8,628 from the previous year’s figures. Transport. Teansport along the coast is by sailing vessels and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by pack animals and is difficult, dangerous and expensive. The rates depend upon the distance the goods have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the journey. Communication by car has been opened up with the Batinah Coast through the construction of a motor road between Muscat and Matrah. and its extension some 30 miles beyond Matrah. ars can now run some 200 miles up the Batinah Coast to Kalba, and a motor bus runs daily to Sib some 30 miles from Muscat.-s 3 A rough fair weather motor track has been con structed to Swakim about 50 miles from Muscat. It may be possible to continue this track to Sur. Transport Rates by Car. Names of Towns. No. of miles. Rate per trip. , About Rs. A. P. Muscat to Matrah . n 1 8 0 „ Bait-el-Falaj . 31 2 4 0 „ Wutaiyah 10 3 12 0 36 15 0 0 „ Berka 56 22 8 0 „ Musana . 731 26 4 0 „ Suwaiq . 87 30 0 0 „ Khabura no 37 0 0 „ Saham . 128 52 8 0 „ Sahar 144 52 8 0 „ Kids-el-Hasa . 165 60 0 0 „ M u r a i r-el- 192 75 0 0 Malar ish. Agriculture. Date growing is the real industry of the country. Limes and mangoes are also successfully grown while pomegranates are the products of the Jebel Akhdar. Cereals are grown on a small scale and could not be further developed owing to the limited quantity of water. Cultivation of sugarcane in Jebel Akhdar and its environs has been successful. Some of the tribesmen have imported crushing machines from India for the manufacture of jaggery. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Matrah has ever been taken. It is therefore not possible to give exact figures. But it has recently been estimated at 12,580, viz., 4,340 are in Muscat and 8,240 in Matrah. Owing to the dearth of trade the Indian trading community which inhabited the town of Muscat and handled 95 per cent, of trade have disappeared and almost all their business pre mises are empty and in ruins. The second port of Matrah, which has conveniences and communica tion with the interior of Oman, is now fairly well populated and its trade is much improved. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is somewhat trying, in summer the weather is oppressive in May and June but July, August and the first half of September are not unpleasant tempered as they are by cool monsoon breezes. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 114* 8° and the lowest 51'3 0 . The total rainfall during the year was 1-16 inches. Shipping. Steamers. —The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. The principal steamship lines which called at Muscat were as follows :— (1) The British India Steamship Navigation Company, Ltd. (2) The Strict Line of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman and Bucknall Steamship Co., Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. 162 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 614,527 tons entered and cleared the port during the year ending 31st March 1932. Of these 136 with a total tonnage of 454,155 were under British flag. 26 German, Hansa Line vessels with a total tonnage of 160,372 entered and cleared the port. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Limited, have maintained a weekly mail service both from Bombay and Basrah. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the War has not been resumed since. Sailing Vessel. —131 sailing vessels of all nationali ties with a total tonnage of 17,167 entered and cleared the port during the year of which 125 were from British India, 3 vessels from Iraq and 3 vessels from Persia with a total tonnage of 593 and 180 respec tively. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— To Bombay and Karachi:— Rs. A. p. Dry dates 1 0 0 per bag. Wet dates 0 12 0 Wet dates in cases . 0 8 0 per case. Dry fish in bundles . . 1. 0 0 per bundle. Pomegranates in crates 1 0 0 per crate. Raw wool . . .. 7 8 0 per bundle. Raw cotton 3 8 0 Cotton piece goods and 0 0 per bale. woollen goods 3 To Ceylon:— Wet dates 36 0 0 per 40 c.ft. or 20 cwt. Dry fish . . • • 36 0 0 Ditto. To United States of America £ s. d. Wet dates in bags and in boxes . . • • 2150 Ditto. To London:— Wet dates in bags and boxes . , • • 2 15 0 Ditto. R. G. E. W. ALBAN, Captain, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.Office of the High Commissioner for India, vj ' — j &lt; S- ' Address for Inland Teleqrams — HICOMIND, ESTP AXTr * Tr.xrnnxr s Telephone- TEMPLE BAR 8484. Please quote the under-mentioned reference, and address any further communicatio'i The High Commissioner for India, Public Department, India House, Aldwych, London, W.C. 2, and not to any individual by name. P.25542 255.1.2/5 Reference 4th April, 1952 Sir I am directed by the High Commissioner for India to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of two copies of the Report on Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1950-51, forwarded under your reference P.Z. 1814/52 dated 2Srd March, 1952, and to observe that copies of the report for the year 1929-50 do not appear to have been received at this Office. 2. In this connection I am to say that the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India intimated in a letter No. D.5179-N/50 dated 29th July, 1950, that the supply to the India Office was being increased in order that two copies could be supplied to this Office, one of which was to be transmitted to the League of Nations. I am accordingly to ask that if possible copies of the report for 1929-50 may now be furnished. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant for Public The Under Secretary of State Political Department, India Office, Whitshall, S.W.l.Letter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, No. 990 of 133!, dated the 18th September 1931. I have the honour to forward a copy of my Report on the Trade and Commerce o*. Muscat for the year 1930-31, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me. enclosure IN , INDIA KOREISN SECRETARY o . No 33 m. ; Letter r -r MAD 1039Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1930-31. Introduction. '^uscat is the Capital of the Independent Sultanate ow\hat name situated at the easterly corner of Arabia. Its seaboard is nearly 900 miles long and extends from Tibbat on the west side of Cape Mus- sandam round Has Rajir rather over 200 miles due north of the Island of Socotra, with the excep tion of a small strip of the east coast of the Mus- sandam Peninsula from Dibbeh to Khor Kalba which is in the administration of the minor chiefs of Trucial Oman. The Sultanate extends inland to the borders of the Great Desert but of late years the Omanis have become autonomous and are now subject to the Imam of Oman and his Lieutenant Sheikh Isa bin Salih. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the high country extending down to the sea coast in a series of arid rocky heights though vegetation exists on the higher mountains. North-West of Muscat the sea coast littoral tract is fertile and prosperous and date groves extend along it for over 100 miles. This strip is known as the Batinah Coast. The remainder of the coast with one notable exception is barren and forbidding and rarely visited by Europeans. The exception is Dhofar which is the name of a small fertile district comprising a group of villages at the south-west corner of the Sultanate. Gwadur, a port on the Mekran Coast, and a small tract of country round it, also owns allegiance to Muscat. It is the last rem nant of the Omani possessions on the Persian side of the Gulf. - The town of Muscat, once so important and prosperous, has been falling into decay for years now. Most of the trade goes to the sister port of Matrah which is the starting point of the trade to the interior, but Muscat remains the capital and seat of Government. Currency. —black and white. Black 20£=1 Dollar. The white is used in wholesale trade accounts and the black for fruits, vegetables, etc. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh . Ill Mohamadia 100 Mohamadia 1 Mohamadi. 1 Dollar. 1 Toman. Exchange Rate. Exchange per 100 Maria Theresa Dollars. 1928-29. 1929-30. 1930-31. R8. A. P. RS. A. P. RS. A. P. Highest bazaar rate . 131 8 0 125 0 0 88 5 0 Lowest bazaar rate 125 8 0 97 8 0 67 4 0 Average bazaar rate . 128 0 0 118 8 0 75 5 0 Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department prescribed in Muscat, Matrah and the Toast town, are :— 1 Kiyaa 24 „ . 10 Muscat Maun da 200 „ The weight of 6 Dollars of 5-9375 ozs. 1 Muscat Maund. 1 Farrasal. 1 Bahr. Rice is sold by the bag ; other cereals by the following measures :— 20 Palis 1 Farrah. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa Dollar and the copper coin minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and rupees are generally accepted. The Maria Theresa Dollar fluctuates in value con siderably being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrein pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh, Imaginary coins. There are two kinds of Mohamadis 20 Farrahs . • • • • 1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the Dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Auqia ” equals eight “ Misqals ”. 1 Shibr 4 Shibrs 4 Dbiraa Measures (Linear). . . . 1 Hand or 4J inches. 1 Dbira or cubit. . . . 1 Bab or fatbom2 Banking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among the merchants of issuing hundis (drafts) is in practice and as trade methods are primitive tbere ** re , ^ sufficient inducements for a Bank to be established. Trade. The total volume of trade for the year 19S&lt;/3l amounted to £415,275 as against £459,446 of the previous year showing a decrease of £44,17 . Imports by steamers as well as by sailing vessels show a decrease of £34,817 as compared with the previous year. Exports by steamers as well as by sailing vessels show a decrease of £9,354 as compared with the pre vious year. Of the total trade for the year the share of the sailing vessels is £123,104 and that of the steamers £292,171. Share of Trade. Percent- Countries. age. £ £ £ India 18. r s,,fiS2 83,048 268,680 64-70 Persia 35,908 7,419 41,327 9-95 United Kingdom 16,219 741 16,960 4-08 Africa 13,288 4,463 17,751 4-27 Aden 1,082 312 1,394 0-54 United State* of 73 12,424 12,497 3-09 America. tiermany 5,787 5,787 1-35 Singapore . 340 340 0 08 Ceylon 14,828 14,828 3-57 China 3,435 3,435 0-82 Other Couatric* . 32,276 52,276 7-77 Total 282,478 132,797 415,275 10000 As will be seen from the above figures India has played a prominent part in the year’s trade. Imports. Total imports for the year amounted to £282,478 as against £317,295 of the previous year showing a decrease of £34,817. Of the total imports goods worth £170,200 were carried by steamships and £112,278 by sailing vessels. The import of rice by steamers as well as by sailing vessels shows an increase. The bulk of the rice imported and appearing in these returns came from Karachi. It is cheaper than Calcutta rice and is consumed by the poorer classes both in Muscat and in the interior. Exports. Total exports for the year under review amounted ir&gt; £132 797 of which goods worth flOjS-h were carried by sailing vessels and thebalande by rteam- ships. They show a decrease of £9,3o4 from tUe previous year’s figures. Cotton goods locally manufactured were exported to Aden, India, Zanzibar and Africa : dry fas^ Ceylon. Muscat manufactures—turbans and lungis. There are exported to Zanzibar, Africa and Aden. A con siderable export of these articles pass through the ~post office and does not appear in these returns. The Post Office returns for the year under report , .1 , J z-l. Cd OFiA 1 x1 —- Legislation. The Government is of the oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by a Council of 4 Ministers (President, Minister of Justice, Minister of Finance and Minister of Religious Affairs). Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat Subjects are decided by the Council of Ministers, but the right of Consular repre sentation exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been executed by the Ruler of Oman with Great Britain, United States of America and France. In accrodance with the terms of these all goods imported into Oman are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied but a charge of 5 per cent, is imposed in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior. The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income. Transport. Transport along the coast is by sailing vessels and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by pack animals and is difficult, dangerous and expen sive. The rates depend upon the distance the goods have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the journey. Communications by car has been opened up with the Batinah Coast through the construction of a motor road between Muscat and Matrah, and its extension some 30 miles beyond Matrah. Cars can now run some 200 miles up the Batinah Coast to Kalba, and a motor bus runs daily to Sib, some 30 miles from Muscat.-. — s s' \ (n2 A rough fair weather motor track has been con structed to Swakim, about 50 miles, from Muscat. It may be possible to continue this track to Sur. Transport Rates by Car. Names ot Towns. ^ No. of miles. Rate per trip. About. Rs. A. P. Muscat to Matrah 2* 1 8 0 ,, „ Witayah . 10 5 0 0 ,, ,, Ohvllah . 25 13 0 0 „ ,, Haiar 30 13 0 0 ,, „ S&gt;vakim . 47 20 0 0 „ „ Sib 30 20 0 0 ,, ,, ftorka 50 30 0 0 ,, „ Sabar 120 80 0 0 „ ,, Kalba 200 100 0 0 Agriculture. Date growing is the real industry of the country. Limes and mangoes are also successfully grown while promcgranates are the products of the Jebel Akhdar. Cereals are grown on a small scale and could not be further developed owing to the limited quantity of water. Owing to good rainfall during the year, efforts were made to cultivate wheat ex tensively. But unfortunately when the wheat was in ear parasites and rust destroyed the whole crops throughout. Cultivation of sugarcane in Jebel Akhdar and its environs has been successful. Some of the tribesmen have imported crushing machines from India for the manufacture of jaggery. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Matrah has ever been taken. It is therefore not possible to give exact figures. But it has recently been estimated at 12,580, viz., 4,340 are in Muscat and 8,240 in Matrah. Owing to the dearth of trade the Indian trading community which inhabited the town of Muscat and handled 95 per cent, of the trade have disappeared and almost all their business premises are empty and in ruins. The second port of Matrah, which has conveniences and communication with the interior of Oman, is now fairly Well populated and its trade is much improved. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is somewhat trying, in slimmer the weather is oppressive in May and June but July, August and the first half of September are not unpleasant tempered as they are by cool monsoon breezes. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 114° and the lowest 51-6°. The total rainfall during the year was 4-53 inches. Shipping. Steamers .—The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. The principal steamships hues which called at Muscat were as follows :— (1) The British India Steamship Navigation Company, Ltd. (2) The Strick Line of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman and Bucknall Steamship Co., Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. 139 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 402,607 tons entered and cleared the port during the year ending 31st March 1931. Of these 125 with a total tonnage of 303,695 were under British flag. 14 German Hansa Line vessels with a total tonnage of 98,912 entered and cleared the port. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Limited, have maintained a weekly mail service both from Bombay and Basrah. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the War has not been resumed since. Sailing Vessels .—'278 sailing vessels of all national ities with a total tonnage of 33,422 entered and cleared the port during the year, of which 254 were from British India, 16 vessels from ’Iraq and 8 vessel* from Africa with a total tonnage of 31,546, 1,396 and 480, respectively. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :—■ Per ton. Rs. A. p. Rs. Bombay and Karachi : — Dry dates 1 4 0 per bag 15 Wet dates 0 10 0 „ box 15 (24 boxe*). 99 99 • * 1 0 o „ bag 15 Dry fish in bundles 1 0 0 „ bundle. Pomegranates 1 8 o „ crate. Raw wool 7 8 o „ bundle. Raw cotton . 3 8 0 „ 99 Cotton piece goods . 3 0 0 „ bale. To Ceylon:— Wet dates . .36 0 0 of 40 s. ft. or 20 cwt. Dry fish . . 36 0 0 Ditto. To United States of America :— £ ». d. Wet dates in bags and in boxes .3 6 6 Ditto. To London:— Wet dates in bags and boxes . . 3 0 0 Ditto. R. G. ALBAN, Captain, Political Agent and Hit Britannic Majesty’s Consul t Muscat,^1. ?t|l i 1 ' t ' i \ r it * • From To Sir, ft J: . file copy i 1875 ! I-io. F.413“N/30. l - ’ '' r ' ! 9 3 i mo 'i'he Foreign Secretary to the Grovernment of India, The Under Secretary of State for India, * Political Department, India Office, L o n d o n .t. * Dated New Delhi, the // March 1951. Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1929-30. ” a ^ With reference to Mr• Laithwaite T s letter iio. P.Z.492/31, dated the 5th February 1931, I am directed to forward two additional copies of the Muscat Trade report for the year 1929-30* It is regretted that through an oversight six copies, instead of eight, were sent with Foreign Secre tary’s letter No* 3, dated the 8th January 1931# &gt;1. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient servant. f.v, &lt; for Offg* Foreign Secretary to the Government of India At/ Letter from the Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, No. K-103-25-14, dated the 8th October, 1930. I have the honour to forward a copy of my Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1929-30, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me. ENOLOSLTIE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S j „ Letter No O'*2 Banking. There are no banks in Mascat. The system among the merchants of issuing Hundis (drafts) is in practice and as trade methods are primitive there are no sufficient inducements for a bank to be established. Trade. The total volume of trade for the year 1929-30 amounted to £459,446 as against £510,120 of the previous year showing a decrease of £50,674. Imports by steamers as well as by sailing vessels show a decrease of £26,622 as compared with the previous year. Exports by steamers as well as by sailing vessels show a decrease of £24,052 as compared with the previous year. Of the total trade for the year the share of the sail ing vessels is £110,284 and that of the steamships £349,162. Share of Trade. Name of Country. Import. Export. Total. Percentage. £ £ £ India 214,998 100,089 315,087 68-57 Persia 21,875 5,988 27,863 606 Africa 12,850 5,041 17,891 3-89 Ceylon 14,783 14,783 3-22 United Kingdom 19,374 2,300 21,674 4-72 United States of 262 9,790 10,052 2-18 America. China 2,665 2,665 0-59 Aden 1,892 1,892 0-42 Singapore 440 440 0-10 Other Countries 46,044, 1,055 47,099 10-25 Total . 317,295 142,157 459,446 100-00 As will be observed from the above figures India has played a prominent part in the year’s trade. Imports. Total imports for the year amounted to £317,295 as against £343,917 of the previous year showing a decrease of £26,622. Of the total imports goods worth £220,306 were carried *by steamships and £96,989 by sailing vessels. The import of rice by steamers as well as by sail ing vessels show a decrease. The bulk of the rice imported and appearing in these return came from Karachi. It is cheaper than Calcutta rice and is consumed by the poorer classes both in Muscat and in the interior. Exports. . x Total exports for the year under review amounted to £142,151 of which uoous w«ith £13,295 were carried by sailing vessels and the balance by steam* ships. They show a decrease of £24,052 from the previous year’s figures. Cotton goods locally manufactured were exported to Aden, Africa and Zanzibar : dry fish to Ceyloh and Waras (ochre) to Aden. This last item is used for dyeing clothes by the Arabs. Muscat manufactures turbans and lungis.^ihese are exported to Zanzibar, Africa and Aden., considerable export of these articles passes through the post office and does not appear in these returns. The post office returns for the year under report show that goods worth £8,375 were thus exported. The export of dates, which is the most important items of Muscat export, fell from £110,347 to £90,801, or about 17 *70 per cent. The decrease is attributed chiefly to scanty rainfall and partly to the invasion of locusts. As will be seen from the statistics no ‘ Fard ’ dates were exported to United States of America during the year under report. Legislation. The Government is of the Oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over w T hom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by a Council of four Ministers (President, Minister of Justice, Minister of Finance and Minister of Religious Affairs). Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of Uaw adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat subjects are decided by the Council of Ministers, but the right of Consular re presentation exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been execut ed by the Ruler of Oman with Great Britain and France. In accordance with the terms of those all goods imported into Oman are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied, but a charge of 5 per cent is imposed in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior. The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income. Transport. Transport along the coast is by sailing vessels and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by pack animals, and is difficult, dangerous and expensive. The rates depend upon the distance the goods have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the journey. A road to link up Matrah with the Batinah Coast ports is still under constructions, but the road from Muscat to Matrah was completed in October 1929. The hire of a car is Rs. 2 per trip and annaa 4 per head.X 3 b 2 Agriculture. Bate growing is the real industry of the country. Limes and mangoes are also successfully grown, while pomegranates are the product of the Jebel Akhdar. Cereals are grown on a small scale and could not be further developed owing to the limited quantity of water available. Inadequate rainfall in Op^an for several years past has been the cause of r ^ for many date gardens ; well have become dry and brackish. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Matrah has ever been taken. It is therefore not possible to give exact figures. But it has recent ly been estimated at 12,580, viz., 4,340 are in Muscat and 8,240 in Matrah. Owing to the dearth of trade the Indian trading community which inhabited the town of Muscat and handled 95 per cent of the trade have disappeared and almost all their business pre mises are empty and in ruins. The second port of Matrah, which has conveniences and communica tion with the interior of Oman, is now fairly well populated and its trade is much improved. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is extremely unhealthy and the heat is excessive, especially at night. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 110° and the lowest 66 - 2°. Shipping. Steamers .—The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. The principal steam ships lines which called at Muscat were as follows :— (1) The British India Steam Ship Navigation Company, Ltd. (2) The Strick Line of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman and Bucknall Steamship Co., Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line Steamers. 140 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 335,091 tons entered and cleared the port during the year ending 31st March 1930. Of Jdiese 136 with a total tonnage of 315,205 were under British flag. Four German Hansa Line vessels with a total tonnage of 19,886 entered and cleared the port. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Limited, have maintained a weekly mail service both from Bombay and Basrah. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the war has not been resumed since. . Sailing Vessels .—89 sailing vessels of all nationali ties with a total tonnage of 11,413 entered and clear ed the port during the year, of which 87 vessels were from British India and 2 vessels from Persia with a total tonnage of 11,045 and 368 respectively. Freights. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— Per ton. To Bombay and Karachi— Rs. A. p. Rs. A. p. Dry dates 1 4 0 per bag 15 0 0 Wet dates . 0 10 0 per box 15 0 0 (24 boxes) Wet dates . 1 0 0 per bag 15 0 0 Dry fish in bundles 1 0 0 per bundle Pomegranates 1 8 0 per crate To Colombo— Wet dates . . .. 36 0 0 of 40 c.ft. Dry fish . . • • 36 0 0 per 20cwts. To United States of America— Wet dates in bags and in boxes To London— •• 3 10 0 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c.ft. Wet dates in bags and boxes • • £ 3 2 6 per ton of 20 cwts. and 40 C.ft. T. C. FOWLE, Major, Political Agent and Hit Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.19 TABLE No. 2-C. Principal Articles and Countries to which exported during the years 1927-28,1928-29 and 1929-30. Quantity. Value. iARTICLES AND UOUNTRIE.S TO WHIOU 1 1927-28. 1928-29. 1929-30. 1927-28. 1928-29. 1929-30. £ £ £ By Steamers. . Cereals. Rice— Persia ..... Pulse— • . Tons 10 . .. 6 10 •• 60 Persia ..... Wheat Flour— • . Cwt. * * * * 81 Persia ..... *• . Tons •• 7 * ’ * * Fish. Sardines, dry— India ..... . Pkgs. 66,132 30,790 25,715 8,817 3,902 5,143 Persia ..... Ceylon ..... • 99 25 18 177 3 2 60 Fish, dry and salted—• India . . . . • Ceylon ..... Africa ..... China ..... . „ 1,571 24,472 164 24 16,657 54 56 14,713 1,361 21,209 142 93 23 13,940 64 60 14,577 Other Countries „ 93 • • Fish bones— India ..... • „ 3,677 10,260 7,738 490 1,258 1,016 Fish Maws— China ..... • 99 14 81 70 12 156 210 Sharkfins— China ..... • 99 622 849 868 1,645 2,427 2,315 India . . . , . Africa ..... • 99 40 156 • . 80 300 •• Mother-of-Pearls— India ..... United Kingdom . Cases 203 207 133 '457 36 ’ 810 333 923 578 2,300 180 Other Countries . Pkgs. 83 ’ * Cuttles— India ..... • 99 168 184 90 130 132 58 Cowries— India ..... 99 104 267 20 187 180 20 Tortoise shells— China ..... . Cases •• 11 •• •• 140 Fruits. Dates, dry— India ..... . Tons 4,300 4,476 4,540 62,434 63,985 67,990 Dates, wet— India ..... Singapore .... Colombo .... 668 976 827 10,776 14,617 12,405 • It • 99 178 13 106 4 25 8 3,565 227 1,7 SO 65 100 7,130 440 146 United Kingdom United States of America . • 99 6 375 450 .. 9,790 30 Other Countries • 99 2 * ** Dates, Fard— United States of America . • tf 552 482 .. 10,520 22,670 Limes, dry— Persia ..... India ..... Other Countries • 99 • 99 • 99 75 3 100 4 1 116 5 3,366 135 3,661 127 30 4,612 180 Pomegranates — India ..... Persia ..... • 99 4,429 1,765 18 2,636 4,712 1,775 12 2,154 Fresh Fruits —■ India ..... Persia ..... . Pkgs • *&gt; •• 5 43 •• 4 30X f Letter from Major G. P. Murphy, LA., Political Agent and Hi* Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, No. 821, dated the 23rd July 1929. I have the honour to forward a copy of my Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1928-29, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, It is requested that 24 Printed Copies may be sent me.Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1928-29 Introduction. is the capital of the independent Sultanate of that name situated at the easterly corner of Ara bia. Its seaboard is nearly 900 miles long and extends from Tibbat on the west side of Cape Mussen- dam round Ras Sajit rather over 200 miles due north of the island of Socotra, with the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Mussendam peninsula from Dibbah to Khor Khalba which is in the administration of the minor chiefs of Irucial Oman. The Sultanate extends inland to the borders of the Great Desert but of late years the Omanis have become virtually autonomous and are now more subject to the Imam of Oman and his lieu tenant Shaikh Isa bin Salih than to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the high country extending down to the sea coast in a series of arid rocky heights though vegetation exists on the higher mountains. North-west of Muscat the sea coast littoral tract is fertile and prosperous and date groves extend along it for over 100 miles. This strip is known as the Batineh coast and it is to here that the hillmen from Oman, finding the struggle for existence too keen in the face of a decreasing water supply, are gradually descending and forcing out the date and fisher folk. The remainder of the coast with one notable exception is barren and forbidding and rarely visited by Europeans. The exception is Dhofar which is the name of a small fertile district comprising a group of villages at the south-west corner of the Sultanate. Gwadur, a port on the Mekran Coast, and a small tract of country round it also owns allegiance to Muscat. It is the last remnant of the Omani possessions on the Persian side of the Gulf. The town of Muscat, once so important and prosperous has been falling into decay for years now. Most of the trade goes to the sister port of Mattrah which is the starting point of the trade route to the interior, but Muscat still remains the capital and seat of Government. Currency. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value con siderably being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrein pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh imaginary coins. There are two kinds of Moha madis—black and white. Black 20^=1 dollar and white 111=1 dollar. The white is used in whole sale trade accounts and the black for fruits, vege tables, etc. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh 1 Mohamadi. 11| Mohamadis . . .1 dollar. 100 Mohamadis . . . .1 Toman. The average rate of monthly exchange between the Maria Theresa dollar and the rupees varied from Rs. 125 to Rs. 131*5 per 100 dollars, the lowest being in March 1929 and the highest in October 1928. The dollar rate fluctuated from Rs. T23-5 to Rs. 13T00 per 100 dollars. It was lowest in March 1929 and highest in October 1928. Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department are prescribed in Muscat, Mattrah and the Coast towns. They are :— 1 Kiyas . . . The weight of 6 dollars or 5'Q375 ozs. 24 „ ... Muscat Maund. 10 Muscat Maunds . . Farasala. 200 „ „ . . Bahr. Rice is sold by the bag ; other cereals by the following measures :— 40 Palis 1 Farrah. 20 Farrahs . . . .1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Aukia ” equals eight “ Misqals.” The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa dollar and the copper coin minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Mattrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and Indian rupees are generally accepted. 1 Shibr . 4 Shibrs . 4 Dhiras . Measures (Linear). , . 1 Hand or 4£ inches. . , 1 Dhira or cubit. . . , 1 Bah* or fathom.2 Banking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among the merchants of issuing Hundis (drafts) is in practice and as trade methods are primitive there are not sufficient inducements for a bank to be established. Trade. The total trade for the year 1928-29 amounted to £510,120 as against £518,944 of the previous year showing a decrease of £8,824 or about 1*70 per cent. Imports by steamers show an increase of £567 whilst imports by sailing vessels a decrease of £27,309. Exports show on the whole an improvement over the figures for last year. Of the total trade for the year the share of the sailing craft is £123,576 and that of steamships £386,544. Share of Trade. — Imports. Exports. Total. Percent age. Aden 2,943 836 3,779 •74 Africa 6,481 3,163 9,644 1-89 India 258,589 107,599 366,188 71-80 Ceylon . • • • 14,007 14,007 2-74 China. •• 2,647 2,647 •52 Persia 16,282 5,655 21,937 4-30 Singapore . •• 1,785 1,785 •35 United Kingdom. 20,710 711 21,421 4-20 United States America . of 859 29,800 30,159 5-91 Other Countries . 88,553 88,553 7-55 TOVh 343,917 166,203 510,120 100-00 As will be noticed from the above figures, India has played a prominent part in the year’s trade. Imports. Total Imports for the year amounted to £343,917 as against £370,659 t)f the previous year showing a decrease of £26,742 or about 7-21 per cent. Of the total Imports goods worth £242,067 were carried by the steamships and £101,850 by country craft. The Import of rice by steamers as well as by sailing vessels shows a decline. The bulk of the rice imported and appearing in these returns came from Karachi. It is cheaper than Calcutta rice and is consumed by the poorer classes both in Muscat and in the interior. Exports. Total exports for the year under report amounted to £166,203 of which goods worth £21,726 were carried by sailing craft and the balance by s^^m- ships. They show an increase of £17,918 ov^Nst year’s figures. Cotton goods locally manufactured were exported to Aden, Africa and Zanzibar, dry fish to Ceylon and Waras (ochre) to Aden. This last item is used for dying clothes by the Arabs. Muscat manufactures Turbans and Lungis. These are exported to Zanzibar, Africa and Aden. A considerable export of these articles passes through the Post Office and does not appear in these returns. The Post Office returns for the year under report show that goods worth £6,330 were thus exported. The export of Fard dates to the United States of America amounted to £22,670 as against £10,520 of the previous year or an increase of £12,150. This is due to the good rains we have had during 1927-28. Legislation. The Government is of the Oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by a Council of four Ministers (President, Minister of Justice, Minister of Finance and Minister of Religious Affairs). Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat subjects are decided by the Council of Ministers, but the right of Consular representation exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been execut ed by the ruler of Oman with Great Britain and France. In accordance with the terms of those all goods imported into Oman are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied, but a charge of 5 per cent is imposed in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior, The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income. Transport. Transport along the coast is by sailing vessels and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by packanimals, and is difficult, dangerous and expensive. The rates depend upon the distance the goods have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the journey. The local Government is now constructing a road to link up Muttrah with the Batineh Coast ports. A road from Muscat to Mattrah is also under construction. Agriculture. Date growing is the real industry of the country. Limes and mangoes are also successfully grown, while pomegranates are the product of the Jebel Akhdar. Cereals are grown on a small scale and could not be further developed owing to the limited quantity of water available. Inadequate rainfall in Oman for several years past has been the cause of ruin for many date gardens ; wells have become dry and brackish. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Mattrah has ever been taken. It is therefore not possible to give exact figures. But it has recent ly been estimated at 12,580, viz., 4,340 are in Muscat and 8,240 in Mattrah. Owing to the dearth of trade the Indian trading community which inhabit ed the town of Muscat and handled 95 per cent of the trade have disappeared and almost all their business premises are empty and in ruins. The second port of Mattrah, which has conveniences and communication with the interior of Oman, is now fairly well populated and its trade is much improved as compared to previous years. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is extremely unhealthy and the heat is excessive, especially at night. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 110° and the lowest 58 , 9°. Shipping. Steamers. —The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. 130 steamships of all Nationalities entered and cleared the port during the year, representing a net tonnage of 424439-48 and 84 sailing vessels with a tonnage of 10376-26. Of the 130 steamships which entered the port, 8 were from the United Kingdom, 112 from India, 8 from Persian Gulf, 1 Russian and one Italian from ’Iraq. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Ltd., have maintained a weekly slow mail service both from Bombay and Basrah. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the war has not been resumed since. Freights .—The statement below gives the average rates of freight:— Per ton. Rs. a. r. Rs. a. P. Dry dates . . 1 4 0 per bag 15 0 0 Wet dates in mat bags 1 0 0 „» 15 0 0 „ boxes . 0 10 0 per box 15 0 0 (24 boxes) Dry fish to Colombo ... 36 0 0 (per Owt.) Pomegranates . . 1 8 0 15 0 0 Dry Limes to Persian Gulf . . .10 0 0 30 0 Wet dates to U. S. A. (per ton of 40 cubit feet) . . ... £ 3 10 or Rs. 46 8 0 0 0 G. P. MURPHY, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Museat,22584/1929 The Comptroller-General, Department of Overseas Trade, presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State, India Office, and with reference to the letter 22633/27 of April 11th, 1927, begs leave to express the hope that in future printed copies of the Muscat Trade Report might be sent in duplicate to this Department. DEPARTMENT OR OVERSEAS TRADE, 35 Old Queen Street London, S.W.l Ijgth January, 1929.LMter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, No. 1066, dated 11th September 1928. I have the honour to forward a copy of my report on the trade and commerce of Muscat for the year 1927-28, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the lion ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent me. J-'ftp. Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1927-28. Introduction. ^^cat is the capital of the independent Sulta nate of that name situated at the easterly corner of Arabia. Its seaboard is nearly 900 miles long and extends from Tibbat on the west side of Cape Mussendam round Ras Sajit rather over 200 miles due north of the island of Socotra, with the excep tion of a small strip on the east coast of the Mus sendam peninsula from Dibbeh to Khor Khalba which is in the administration of the minor chiefs of Trucial Oman. The Sultanate extends inland to the borders of the Great Desert but of late years the Omanis have become virtually autonomous and are now more subject to the Imam of Oman and his lieutenant Shaikh Isa bin Saleh than to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the high country extending down to the sea coast in a series of arid rocky heights though vegetation exists on the higher mountains. North-west of Muscat the sea coast littoral tract is fertile and prosperous and date groves extend along it for over 100 miles. This strip is known as the Batineh Coast and it is to here that the hillmen from Oman, finding the struggle for existence too keen in the face of a decreasing water supply, are gradually descending and forcing out the date and fisher folk. The remainder of the coast with one notable exception is barren and forbidding and rarely visited by Europeans. The exception is Dhofar which is the name of a small fertile district comprising a group of villages at the south-west corner of the Sultanate. Gwadur, a port on the Mekran Coast, and a small tract of country round it also owns allegiance to Muscat. It is the last remnant of the Omani possessions on the Persian side of the Gulf. The town of Muscat, once so important and pros perous, has been falling into decay for years now. Most of the trade goes to the sister port of Mattrah which is the starting point of the trade route to the interior, but Muscat still remains the capital and seat of Government. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa dollar and the copper coin minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Mattrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and Indian rupees are generally accepted. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value considerably being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season» and by the state of the Bahrein pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh imaginary coins. There are two kinds of Moha madis—black and white. Black 20^=1 dollar and white 11£=1 dollar. The white is used in whole sale trade accounts and the black for fruits, vege tables, etc. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh . . . , .1 Mohamadi. !1£ Mohamadis . . . .1 dollar. 100 Mohamadis . . . .1 Toman. The average rate of monthly exchange between the Maria Theresa dollar and the rupees varied from Rs. 126-6 to Rs. 132 per 100 dollars, the lowest being in February 1928 and the highest in June and July 1927. The dollar rate fluctuated from Rs. 126-5 to Rs. 133 per 100 dollars. It was lowest in February 1928 and highest in June 1927. Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department are prescribed in Muscat, Mattrah and the Coast towns. They are ;— 1 Kiyas . 10 Maunds . 200 ;; Rice is sold by the following measures :—- 40 falis . 20 Farrah? . The weight of 6 dollars or 5-9375 qzs. . Muscat Maund. , F arasala. , Bahr. bag; other cereals by the 1 Farrah. 1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Aukia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Aukia ” equals eight “ Miskals ”. Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr . . . .1 Hand of inches. 4 Shibrs . . , ,1 Dhira or cubit. 4 Dhiras . . . .1 Bah’ or fathom. Banking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among the merchants of issuing Hundis (drafts) is in practice and as trade methods are primitive there are not sufficient inducements for a bank to be established,2 Trade. The total trade for the year 1927-28 amounted to £518,9?4 as against £474,202 of the previous year showing an increase of £44,742 or about 9 per cent. Imports by steamers show a decrease of £10,379 whilst imports by sailing vessels show an increase of £54,104. There is an increase of £45,309 in the value of rice imported by sailing vessels. Exports show on the whole a slight improvement over the figures for last year. Of the total trade’ for the year the share of the sailing crafts is £140,811 and that of the steamships £378,133. i Share of Trade. — Imports. Exports. Total. Percen tage. £ £ £ y- A mail Aden 2,570 1,013 3,583 ■69 Africa 5,304 4,006 * 9,310 1-80 India 293,402 100,617 304,019 75-9? Ceylon . . . 21,436 21,436 4-13 •; 1. - China 938 1,657 2,595 •50 Persia . . f , 18,513 4,is&amp;: 22,698 4-37 Singapore 30,974 3,565 34,539 ft-66 United Kingdom 13,878 830 14,708 2-84 United States of America. 1,975 10,520 12,495 . 2-40. ■o Other Countries 3,105 456 3,561 •69 Total 370,659 148,285 518,944 100-00 As will be noticed from the above figures India has, as usual, played a prominent part in the year’s trade and Singapore comes next in order. Nearly £31,000 worth of coffee beans were im ported from ' Singapore during the year. This is a new item as coffee used usually to be imported from India and Ceylon. Imports. . { L .S/i r • L ' j ti k t Total imports for the year amounted to £370,659 as against £326,934 showing an increase of £43,725 or about 7 per cent. Of the total imports ^goods worth £241,500 were carried by the steamships and £129,159 by country craft. The import of rice by steamers shows a slight decline whereas the import of the same commodity by 4 , sailing craft shows a marked improvement of £45,309. The money market was tight and there was no demand from the interior for rice of good quality and consequently less rice was imported from Calcutta. The bulk of the rice imported and appearing in these returns came from Karachi. It is cheaper than Calcutta rice and is consumed by the poorer classes both in Muscat and in the interior. There has been no direct import of rice from Rangoon but a small quantity of this kind of rice came via Bombay and has been included under India. i Exports. ^ Total exports for the year under report amounted to £148,285 of which goods worth £11,652 w^re carried by sailing craft and the balance by Steam ships. They show a slight increase of £1,017 dver last year s figures. A glance at the statements will show that excepting for the items noted below which show increased exports the exports to every other country have suffered. Singapore Africa . Ceylon , Aden ., 3,56, 2,37 11,575 1,013 Dates were exported to Singapore, cotton goods, locally manufactured, to Zanzibar and Aden, dry fish to Ceylon and War as (ochre) to Aden, This last item is used for dying clothes by the Arabs. Muscat manufacture turbans and lungis. These are exported to Zanzibar and Aden. A consider able export of these articles passes through the Post- Office and does not appear in these returns. The export of Fard dates to the United States of America, which is the most important item of Muscat export, has suffered loss for several suc cessive years owing to the absence of rains in Oman. Towards the end of 1927 there was good rain, and it is hoped that the date crop will improve. Legislation. The Government is of the Oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have ho jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by a Council of four Ministers (President, Minister of Justice, Minister of Finance and Minister of Religious affairs). Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat subjects ate decided by the Council of Ministers, but the right of Consular re presentation exists and is exercised. , . . Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been exe cuted by the ruler of Oman with Great Britain and France. In accordance wdth the terms oi those, all goods imported into Oman are subject to an. import duty of 5 per cent, ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied, but a charge of 5 per cent, is imposed, in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior.3 The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income. Transport. Transport along the coast is by sailing vessel and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by pack animals and is difficult, dangerous and ex pensive. The rates depend upon the distance the goffa have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the journey. The local Government is now constructing a road to link up Mattrah with the Batineh Coast ports. A road from Muscat to Mattrah is also under construction. Agriculture. Date growing is the real industry of the country. Limes and mangoes are also successfully grown, while pomegranates are the product of the Jebel Akhdar. Cereals are grown on a small scale ana could not be further developed owing to the limited quantity of water available. Inadequate rainfall in Oman for several years past has been the cause of ruin for many date gardens ; wells have become dry and brackish. Population. No regular census of the Population of Muscat id Mattrah has even been taken. It is therefore )t possible to give correct figures. Bu t it has cently been estimated at 12,580, rtz., 4,340 are Muscat and 8,240 in Mattrah. Owing to the &gt;arth of trade the Indian trading community hich inhabited the town of Muscat and handled 5 per cent, of the trade have disappeared and ;most all their business premises are empty and , ruins. The second port of Mattrah, which has mveniences and communication with the interior : Oman, is now fairly well populated and its trar e much improved as compared to previous years. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is extremely unhealthy and the heat is excessive, especially at night. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 1H - and the lowest 53-2°. Shipping. Steamers. The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. 126 steamships of all nationalities entered and cleared the port during the year, representing a net tonnage of and 107 sailing vessels with a tonnage of 11,808-48. Of the 126 steamships which entered the port 6 were from the United States of America, 4 from the United Kingdom and 116 from India. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Limited, have maintained a weekly slow mail ser vice both from Bombay and Basra. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the war has not been resumed since. Freights. The statement below gives the average rates of freight:— Dry dates Wet dates in mat bags Wet dates in boxes . Dry fish to Colombo ton of 1 cwt.) Pomegranates . Per ton. Rs. A. p. Rs. A. p. 1 8 0 per bag 19 8 0 1 0 0 „ 18 0 0 0 10 0 per box 25 0 0 (per 36 0 0 1 's 0 16 8 0 5ulf' 10 0 0 70 0 0 (per 52 8 0 G. P. MURPHY, Major, LA. Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat.m j 'J The Secretary, lolitical Departrrent, India Cilice presents his compliments to the Comptroller-General, Department ol Overseas Trade and with reference to his letter 22584/19 29 of 15 th January 1929 be^s to forward a further copy of the l/uscat Trade Report 1927 - 8 . The oversight is re ^retted* jfidia Office, 18 th January 1929 .Letter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, No. 36, dated the 18th January 1928. I have the honour to forward a copy of my report on the trade and commerce of Muscat for the year 1926-27, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Busffire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent me.Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1 926-27 Introduction. Muscat is the capital of the independent Sultanate ct*^at name situated at the easterly corner of Arabia. T Veaboard is nearly 900 miles long and extends from ^ . • i /~1 At.n rvi -rrMvnri Ra inoaru is ncaiij ,t on the west side of Cape Mussendam round Kas ^sajir rather over 200 miles due north of the island of Socotra, with the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Mussendam peninsula from Dibbeh to Khor Khalba which is the administration of the minor Chiefs of Trucial Oman. The Sul tanate extends inland to the borders of the Great Desert but of late years the Omanis have become virtually autonomous and are now more subject to the Imam of Oman and his lieutenant Shaikh Isa bin Saleh than to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. The interior is for the most part mount ainous, the high country extending down to the sea coast in a series of arid rocky heights though vegeta tion exists on the higher mountains. North-west of Muscat the sea coast littoral tract is fertile and prosperous and date groves extend along it for over 100 miles. This strip is known as the Batineh Coast and it is to here that the hillmen from Oman, finding the struggle for existence too keen in the face of a decreasing water supply, are gradually Tescen - ing and forcing out the date and fisher folk. The remainder of the coast with one notable exception is barren and forbidding and rarely visited by Euro peans. The exception is Dhofar which is the name of a small fertile district comprising a group of villages at the south-west corner of the Sultanate. Gwadur, a port on the Mekran Coast, and a sma tract of country round it also owns allegiance to Muscat. It is the last remnant of the Omani posses sions on the Persian side of the Gulf. The town of Muscat, once so important and prosperous, has been falling into decay for Tears now Most of the trade goes to the sister port of Mattrah which is the starting point of the trade route to the interior, but Muscat still remains the capital and seat of Government. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa dollar and the copper com minted m 1895 to the order Ut His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Mattrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and Indian rupees are generally accepted. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value considerably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrein pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh imaginary coins. There are two kinds of Mohamadis —black and white. Black 20£=1 dollar and white 11|=1 dollar. The white is used in wholesale trade accounts and the black for fruits, vegetables, etc. Most Hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh ...... 1 Mohamadi. 1H Mohamadis . . .1 Dollar. 100 „ ... 1 Toman. The average rate of monthly exchange between the Maria Theresa dollar and the rupee varied from Rs. 128-6 to Rs. 150 per 100 dollars, the lowest being in March 1927 and the highest in June 1926. The dollar rate fluctuated from Rs. 128-4 to Rs. 152-8 per 100 dollars. It was lowest in March 1927 and highest in May 1926. Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department are prescribed in Muscat, Mattrah and the Coast towns. They are— 1 Kiyaa 10 Maunds 200 . the weight of 6 dollars or 5-9375 ozs. . Muscat Maund. . Farasala. . Bahr. Rice is sold by the bag; other cereals by the following measures:— 40 Palis 20 Farrahs 1 Farrah. 1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Aukia are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “Aukia” equals eight “ Miskals. 1 Shibr 4 Shibrs 4 Dhiras Measures (Linear). 1 Hand of 4£ inches. 1 Dhira or cubit. * 1 Bah’ or fathom. Banking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among e merchants of issuing Hundis (drafts) is in practice d as trade methods are primitive there are no fficient inducements for a bank to be established.2 Trade. The total volume of trade for the year 1926-27 amounted to £474,202 as against £673,817 of the previous year, showing a decrease of £199,615 below the previous year or 30 per cent. The above decrease is largely due to the decreased imports of rice, other cereals, sugar, coffee, cotton goods, twist and yarn from India and other goods from the United States of America and decreased exports of dry fish, dry and wet dates to India and Fard dates to the United States of America as in dicated below :— Imports. India ...... United States of America Other Countries ..... f£ 105,063 7,009 8,901 Exports. C* India . • United States of America Other Countries ..... X 63,826 13,529 1,284 Of the total trade for the year under report £90,496 represents the share of sailing vessels. Share of Trade. Countries, Import. Export. Total. Percen tage. £ £ £ £ Africa 3,586 392 3,979 •84 Aden 671. ? • 671 •15 India 280,776 111,328 401,104 84-58 Persia 15,802 7,546 23,438 4-94 United Kingdom 9,405 •• 9,405 200 United States America . . of 2,903 12,896 15,799 3-33 Ceylon .. 9,729 9,729 204 China 367 1,565 1,932 0-40 Other Countries . 4,334 3,812 8,146 1-72 Total 326,934 147,268 474,202 100-00 The above figures show that as usual India has taken the largest share in the year’s trade. Imports from the United Kingdom show a decrease of £2,928 and export to that country was nil against £6,230 of the previous year. Imports. The imports fot the year under review amounted to £326,934 as against £447,910 of the previous year, showing a decrease of £120,976 or 27 per cent. Sailing craft carried imports to the extent of £75,055, showing a decrease of £10,457 or about 14 per cent less than the previous year. The imports of rice by steamers have suffemL+o the extent of £63,188 and the reason for this fiPVvg off is that large stocks of rice of previous yea rgfr^ e on hand unsold and Muscat demands were few^r The imports of sugar show a decrease of £10,702 and those of piece goods £7,037. Decreases in these commodities are due to rigid supervision of the Persian Customs authorities on the Persian ports which makes smuggling of these articles difficult. Another reason is that the Cutch merchants used to import sugar into Muscat and re-export it to Cutch to avoid duty. This practice has been discontinued and now they import it direct into Cutch. Total exports for the year amounted to £147,268 as against £225,907 of the previous year, showing a decrease of £78,639 or about 35 per cent. The share of the sailing vessels in this year’s exports amounted to £15,451 as against £48,721 of the previous year, showing a decrease of £33,270 or about 68 per cent. The export of dry sardines and dry fish by steamers has further improved this year and the result is an increase of £2,348 over last year’s figures, whereas it shows a decrease of £22,630 by sailing vessels. The export of dry and wet dates also has decreased and shows a falling of £50,051. The reason is as stated in the last year’s report, viz., Oman has not had sufficient rain for over 8 years and date gloves have died away for want of water and people of the interior have emigrated to other parts. Legislation. The Government is of the Oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by a Council of four Ministers (President, Minister of Justice, Minister of Finance and Minister of Religious Affairs). Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat subjects are decided by the Council of Ministers, but the right of Consular representation exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been executed by the Ruler of Oman with Great Britain and France'3 In accordance with the terms of those, all goods imported into Oman are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied, but a charge of 5 per cent is imposed in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior. The Customs revenue is the main source of the irernment’s income. Transport. Transport along the coast is by sailing vessel and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by pack animals and is difficult, dangerous and expensive. The rates depend upon the distance the goods have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the journey. No means of development of transport and com munication exist at present owing to the exceedingly primitive methods of the people of the country. The Local Government is now constructing a road to link up Mattrah with the Batineh Coast ports. A road from Muscat to Mattrah is also under construction. Agriculture. Date growing is the only real industry of the country. Limes and mangoes are also successfully grown, while pomegranates are the product of the Jebel Akhdhar. Cereals are grown on a small scale and could not be further developed owing to the limited quantity of water available. Inadequate rainfall in Oman for several years past has been the cause of ruin of many date gardens ; all wells have become dry and brackish. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Mattrah has ever been taken. It is therefore not possible to give correct figures. But it has | recently been estimated at 12,580, viz., 4,340 are in T ^ fMuscat and 8,240 in Mattrah. Owing to the dearth ' of trade the Indian trading community which inhabited the town of Muscat and handled 95 per cent of the trade have disappeared and almost all their business premises are empty and in ruins. The second port, Mattrah, which has con veniences and communication with the interior of Oman, is now fairly well populated and its trade is much improved as compared to previous years. Natural Resources. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, have carried out a preliminary survey in the Muscat Territory during the year, but the prospects of finding mineral resources in paying quantities appear to be very poor. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is extremely unhealthy and the heat is excessive, especially at night. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 112-8° and the lowest 66-0° F. Shipping. Steamers. —The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. 117 steamships of all nationalities entered and cleared the port during the year, representing a net tonnage of 401,089 and 64 sailing vessels wuth a tonnage of 8,445. Of the 117 steamships which entered the port 4 were from the United States of America, 5 from the United Kingdom and 108 from India. The British India Steam Navigation Company* Limited, have maintained a weekly slow mail service both from Bombay and Basra. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the war has not been resumed since. Freights.—The statement below gives the average rates of freight:— Per ton. ... Rs. A. p. Rs. A. P. Dry dates 1 4 0 per bag 16 4 0 Wet dates in mat bag 0 1 4 0 „ 17 8 0 Wet dates in boxes . 0 10 0 25 0 0 Dry fish to Colombo (per ton of c.ft.) . 25 0 0 Pomegranates 1 12 0 20 0 0 Dry limes to Persian Gulf Wet dates to United States 10 0 0 70 0 0 of America (per ton of 40 c.ft.) 52 8 0 * * - * G f P. MURPHY, Major, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. &gt;9 jtMfxV KES sOjihk AArlfct 'V? )2SZl/ti’Y MEMORANDUM The Comptroller-General of the Department 22653/27. of Overseas Trade presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and with reference to his memorandum of the 22nd March, P.1252 and to the arrangement whereby one copy of the printed edition of reports received from His Majesty's Consular Officers at all posts on the Persian Gulf is sent to the Department of Overseas Trade, ventures to express the hope that in future such reports may if possible be sent in duplicate. 22633/27. DEPARTMENT OF OVERSEAS TRADE 35 Old Queen Street, S.W.l \- April, 1927$2 q 19*^ 1 ' Letter from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, No. 1453, dated the 29th December 1926. I have the honour to forward a copy of my report on the trade and commerce of Muscat fo* the year 1925-26, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent me. enclosure in INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S♦ Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1925-26 Introduction. Muscat is the capital of the independent Sultanate of that name situated at the easterly corner of Arabia. Its seaboard is nearly 900 miles long and extends from Tibbat on the west side of Cape Mussendam round Has Sajir rather over 200 miles due north of the island Socotra, with the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Mussendam peninsula from Dibbeh to Khor Khalba which is the adminis tration of the minor Chiefs of Trucial Oman. The Sultanate extends inland to the borders of the Great Desert, but of late years the Omanis have become virtually autonomous and are now more subject to the Imam of Oman and his lieutenant Shaikh Isa bin Saleh than to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. The interior is for the most part mounta- nous the high country extending down to the sea coast in a series of arid rocky heights though vegeta tion exists on the higher mountains. North-west of Muscat the sea coast littoral tract is fertile and pros perous and date groves extend along it for over 100 miles. This strip is known as the Batineh Coast and it is to here that the hillmen from Oman, finding the struggle for existence too keen in the face of a decreasing water supply, are gradually descending and forcing out the date and fisher folk. The re mainder of the coast with one notable exception is barren and forbidding and rarely visited by Euro peans. The exception is Dhofar which is the name of a small fertile district comprising a group of villages at the south-west corner of the Sultanate. Gwadur, a port on the Mekran Coast, and a small tract of country round it also owns allegiance to Muscat. It is the last remnant of the Omani possessions on the Persian side of the Gulf. The town of Muscat, once so important and pros perous, has been falling into decay for years now. Most of the trade goes to the sister port of Mattrah which is the starting point of the trade route to the interior, but Muscat still remains the capital and seat of Government. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa dollar and the copper coin minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Mattrah Sovereigns, Indian currency notes and Indian rupees are generally accepted. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value con siderably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrain pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh imaginary coins. There are two kinds of Mohamadis —black and white. Black 201=1 dollar and white 11|=1 dollar. The white is used in wholesale trade accounts and the black for fruit, vegetables, etc. Most Hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh 1 Mohamadi. 11£ Mohamadis . . . .1 Dollar. 100 „ .... 1 Toman. The average rate of monthly exchange between the Maria Theresa dollar and the rupee varied from Rs. 156-9 to Rs. 185-5 per 100 dollars, the lowest being in March, 1926 and the highest in April, 1925. The dollar rate fluctuated from Rs. 156-9 to Rs. 185-5 per 100 dollars. It was lowest in March, 1926 and highest in April, 1925. Weights and measures. The weights used in the Customs Department are prescribed in Muscat, Mattrah, and the Coast towns. They are— 1 Kiyas 24 „ . 10 Maunds 200 Rice is sold by the following measures :— 40 Palis . 20 Farrahs . the weight of 6 dollars or 5-9375 ozs. . Muscat Maund. . Farasala. . 1 Bahr. bag ; other cereals by the ... 1 Farrah. ... 1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola, and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Aukia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Aukia ” equals eight “ Miskals.” Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr ... . • ■ 1 Hand of 4| inches 4 Shibrs . . . . 1 Dhira or cubit. 4 Dliiras . . . . .1 Ba’ or fathom. Ranking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among the merchants of issuing Hundis (drafts) is in practice and as trade methods are primitive there are not sufficient inducements for a bank to be established.2 Trade. The total volume of trade for the year 1925-26 amounts to £673,817 as against £612,883 of the • previous year showing and increase of £60,934 over the previous year or about 10 per cent. The above increase is largely due to the increased import of rice from India, and other goods from the United States of America and other countries as indicated below :— £ In &lt;h'a 42,267 United States of America . . . 9,912 Other countries ..... 9,121 Of the total trade for the year under report sailing crafts carried £134,233 worth of imports. Share of Trade. Countries. Import. Export. Total. Percen tage. £ £ £ £ Africa 1,286 4,370 5,656 •84 .India 394,839 175,164 570,003 .Ji&amp;U Pera'a 17,046 6,383 23,429 3m7 United Kingdom 12,333 6,230 18,563 2 76 United States of 9,912 26,425 36,337 5-40 America. Ceylon 3,379 3,379 •51 China.... .. 1,386 1,386 •20 Other Countries . 12,494 2,570 15,064 2-23 TOTAL 447,910 1 225,907 673,817 iwoo Imports from India show an increase but imports from the United Kingdom show a decrease of £1,782. Imports. The total imports carried by steamships during the year under report amounted to £362,398 as against £327,341 of the last year showing an improve ment of £35,057 or about 9 per cent. Sailing vessels carried imports to the extent of £85,512 showing an increase of £19,479 over pre vious years or about 6 per cent. Of the above increase more than half is due to in creased imports of rice. The imports of sugar show a decrease of nearly £10,000 and those of piecegoods of over £8,000. One reason for decreases in these two commodities is probably due to the fact that the smuggling of these articles to the Persian Coasts is not so easy as it used to be in former days. A secondary reason is that formerly Cutch merchants used to import sugar into Muscat and then re-export it to the Cutch ports merely to avoid duty. This practice has been dis continued and merchants now import sugar direct into Cutch. Exports. Total exports carried by steamships during the year amounted to £177,186 as against £179,675 of the previous year showing a decrease of £2,489. Exports carried by sailing craft amounted to £48,721 showing a slight increase of £8,887 over last year’s figures or about 3 per cent. The export of dry sardines has improved and the result is an increase of £13,647 over last year’s figures whereas the export of dry and wet dates has decreased and shows a falling off of £54,134. The reason is not far to seek. Oman has not had suffi cient rain for over. 7 years and date groves have died away for want of water and people of the interior have emigrated to other parts. The produce of dates is yearly becoming poorer in quality and the quantity is diminishing. Poverty in Oman has in creased on account of the absence of rain. Legislation. The Government is of the Oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by a Council of 4 Ministers (President, Minister of Justice, Minister of Finance and Minister of Religious Affairs). Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases against Muscat subjects are decided by the Council of Ministers but the right of Consular re presentation exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal commercial treaties have been executed by the ruler of Oman with Great Britain and France. In accordance with the terms of those, all goods imported into Oman are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent, ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied but a charge of 5 per cent, is imposed in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior. The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income.3 Transport. m. Transport along the coast is by sailing vessel and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by pack animals and is difficult, dangerous and expensive. The rates depend upon the distance the goods have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the journey. No means of development of transport and com munication exist at present owing to the exceedingly primitive methods of the people of the country. Agriculture. Date growing is the only real industry of the country. Limes and Mangoes are also successfully grown while pomegranates are the product of the Jebel Akhdhar. Cereals are grown on a small scale and could not be further developed owing to the limited quantity of water available. Inadequate rainfall in Oman for several years past has been the cause of ruin of many date gardens ; all wells have become dry and brackish. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Mattrah has ever been taken. It is therefore not possible to give correct figures. Owing to the dearth of trade the Indian trading community which in habited the town of Muscat and handled 95 per cent, of the trade have disappeared and almost all their business premises are empty and in ruins. The second port, Mattrah, which has conveniences and communication with the interior of Oman, is now fairly well populated and its trade is much improved as compared to previous years. Natural Resources. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited have carried out a preliminary survey in the Muscat Territory during the year but the prospects of finding mineral resources in paying quantities appear to be very poor. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is extremely unhealthy and the heat is excessive, especially at night. Ihe highest temperature recorded in the year was Ill'S and the lowest 10-2° F. Shipping. Steamers .—The usual statement showing figures is attached to this report. 119 steamships of all nationalities entered and cleared the port during the year representing a net tonnage of 407,076 and 77 sailing vessels with a tonnage of 8,813-77. Of the 119 steamships which entered the port 4 were from the United States of America, 4 from the United Kingdom, 1 from Sweden and 110 from India. The British India Steam Navigation Company Limited have maintained a weekly slow mail service both from Bombay and Basra. The fast mail service which was discontinued during the war has not been resumed since. Freights .—The statement below gives the average rates of freight:— Per ton. Rs. A. V. Rs. A. p. Dry dates .... 1 8 0 Per bag. 19 8 0 Wet dates in mat bag . 1 0 0 20 0 0 Wet dates in boxes 0 10 0 25 0 0 Dry fish to Colombo (per ton of 40 c.ft.) . .. 30 0 0 Pomegranates . . . 1 12 0 20 0 0 Dry limes to Persian Gulf 10 0 0 70 0 0 Wet dates to United States of America (per ton of 40 c.ft.) • 45 0 0 G. P. MURPHY, Major, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat,Letter from the Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, No. 1305 of 1025, dated Muscat, the 28th September 1025. I have the honour to forward a copy of my report on the trade and com merce of Muscat for the year 1924-25, the original of which has been sent to tin* Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Kesident, Persian Gulf Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent me. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter N&lt;&gt; £9 f/1. Dated 17 DEC 1925 Received ^REPORT ON THE TRADE OF MUSCAT FOR THE YEAR 1924-25. II Introduction. Muscat is the capital of the independent Sultanate of that name situated at the easterly corner of Arabia. Its seaboard is nearly 900 miles long and exten s from Tibbat on the west side of Cape Mussendam round Ras Sajir rather over 200 miles due north of the island Socotra, with the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Mussendam peninsula from Dibbeh to Khor Kalba which is the adminis tration of the minor Chiefs of Trucial Oman. The Sultanate extends inland to the borders of the Oreat Desert, but of late years the Omanis have become virtually autonomous and are now more subject to the Imam of Oman and his lieutenant Shaikb Isa bin Saleh than to His Highness the Sultan of Oman. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the high country extending down to the sea coast in a series of arid rocky heights though vegetation exists on the higher mountains. North-west of Muscat the sea coast littoral tract is fertile and prosperous and date groves extend along it for over 100 miles Tins strip is known as the Batineh Coast and it is to here that the hillmen from Oman finding the struggle or §&lt;( s' existence too keen in the face of a decreasing water supply are gradually descending and forcing out the date and fisher folk. The remainder of coast with one notable exception is barren and forbidding and rarely visited by Europeans. The exception is Dhofar which is the name of a small fertile district comprising a group of villages at the south-west corner of the Sultanate. Gwadur a port on the Mekran Coast and a small tract of country round it also owns allegiance to Muscat. It is the las remnant of the Omani possessions on the Persian side of the Gulf. The town of Muscat once so important and pros perous has been falling info decay ioT J 6 ?™ 110 ']; Most of the trade goes to the sister port of Matrah which is the starting point of the trade route to the interior, but Muscat still remains the Capital and seat of Government. Currency. The Currency of the country is the Mana Theresa dollar and the copper com minted in K9o o order of His Highness the Sultan. In Mm'at and Matrah sovereigns, Indian currency notes and Indian rupees are generally accepted. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value con siderably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrain pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohamadis and Gajh, imaginary coins. There are two kinds of Mohamadis —black and white. Black 20|—1 dollar and white 11|—1 dollar. The white is used in wholesale trade accounts and the black for fruit, vegetables, etc. Most Hundis from India show their face value in Mohamadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh . . .1 Mohamadi. Ill Mohamadis ... 1 Dollar. 100 „ ... 1 Toman. The average rate of monthly exchange between the Maria Theresa dollar and the rupee varied from Rs. 181 to Rs. 192 per 100 dollars, the lowest being in March 1925 and the highest in November 1924. The dollar rate fluctuated from Rs. 180 to 192 per 100 dollars. It was lowest in September 1924 and highest in November 1924. Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Departments are prescribed for use in Muscat Matrah and the Coast towns. They are :— 1 Kiyas . . . the weight of 6 dollars or 5-9875 ozs. 24 „ .... Muscat Maund. 10 Maunds .... Farasala. 200 „ ... 1 Bahr. Rice is sold by the bag ; other cereals by the following measures :— 40 Palis .... -1 Farrah. 20 Farrah s . . . . 1 KhandL The rupee which weighs one tola, and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Aukia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Aukia ” equals eight Miskals. Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr 4 Shi hr s 4 Dhiras 1 Hand of 4J inches. 1 Dhira or cubit. 1 Ba’ or fathom. 4Banking. There are no banks in Muscat. The system among the merchants of issuing Hundis (drafts) is in practice and as trade methods are primitive there are not sufficient inducements for a bank to be established. Trade. The total volume of trade for the year 1924-1925 amounted to £6,12,883 as against £5,59,855 of the previous year showing a very modest increase of £53,028 over the previous year or about 9 per cent. The above increase is entirely due to the increased trade with India and United States of America as shown below :— £ India 27,000 United States of America . . . 29,000 Of the total trade for the year under report £1,05,867 represents the share of sailing craft. Share of Trade. Countries. Import. Export. Total. Percent- a^e. £ £ £ Africa 5,027 2,670 8,2C7 1-35 3,52,572 1,58,857 510,829 83-35 Persia 17,687 10,930 23,667 4-68 United Kingdom 14,115 1,361 15,476 2-52 United States of America 38,748 38,748 6-32 Ceylon 4,762 4,762 0-78 China 1,142 1,142 0-18 Other Countries . 3,373 1,589 4,962 0-82 T IT AT, 3,93,374 2,19,509 612,880 100-00 A glance to the above figures will show that as usual India has taken the largest share in the year’s trade and United States of America comes next in order. Imports. The imports for the year under review amounted to £3,93,_374 as against £3,90,46H-Tof the previous year shmUing an improvimentTof £2,914 over pre vious year’s imports or about -74 per cent. Sailing craft carried imports to the extent of £86,033 showing the decent increase of £13,240 or about 20 per cent, more than the previous year. The imports of rice by steamer have suffered to the extent of £54,788 and the reason given for this falling off is that the nee market in India ruled high and Muscat demands were few. Exports. The total exports for the year amounted to £2,19,509 as against £1,69,395 of the previo s year showing an increase of £50,114 or about 29 per cent^^. The share of the sailing craft in the year’s export^^ amounted to £39,834 as against £47,604 of the pre vious year. The increase in exports shown above are entirely due to increased exports carried by the steam vessels. More than half of the above increase was carried to the United States of America. The date crop was better than for several years before and more “ Fard ” dates were exported to United States of America than in several years previously. Legislation. The Government is of the oriental type tempered by treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The Government is carried on by a Council of 4 Ministers (President, Minister of Justice, Minister of Finance and Minister of Religious affairs). Cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, on principles of law adopted from British India Cases against Muscat subjects are decided by the Council of Ministers but the right of Consular repre sentation exists and is exercised. Customs. Reciprocal Commercial treaties have been exer cised by the Rulers of Oman with Great Britain and France. In accordance with the terms of those all goods impo ted into Om n are subject to an import duty of 5 per cent, ad valorem determined by the price current in the local market. No export duty is levied but a charge of 5 per cent, is imposed in Muscat and at the Coast ports on all dates and other fruits from the interior. The Customs revenue is the main source of the Government’s income. Transport. Transport along the Coast is by sailing vessel and is cheap. Transport inland is carried out by pack animals and is difficult, dangerous and expensive. The rates depend upon the distance the goods have to be conveyed and the difficulty of the j urney. No means of development of transport and com munication exist at present owing to the exceedingly primitive methods of the people of the country. Agriculture. Date growing is the only real industry of the country. Limes and Mangoes are also successfully grown while pomegranates are the product of the3 Jebel Akhdhar. Cereals are grown on a small scale Mid could not be further developed owing to the ^^nited quantity of water available. Inadequate rainfall in Oman for several years past has been the cause of ruin of many a date gardens; all wells have become dry and brackish. Population. The population of Muscat is about 2,000 and that of Matrah about 20,000. The majority of the houses in Muscat are empty or are in ruins. Sur is a sail ing vessel port with'a population of about 12,000. The difficulty of obtaining water alone prevents the increase of population there. It is quite impossible to estimate the population of the interior. The majority of the population are settled Arabs. Natural Resources. It is hoped that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, who are arranging to prospect for mineral oils in Muscat territory will succeed in working out the mineral resources of the country and thereby ; increase the country’s revenue. The Company hope to start prospecting in the autumn, 1925. Public Health. The climate of Muscat is extremely unhealthy and the heat is excessive. The highest temperature recorded in the year was 113-0 o and the lowest 67-3° F. J Shipping. Steamers. —The usual statement showing shipping figures is attached to this report. 115 steam ships of all nationalities entered and cleared the port during the year representing a net tonnage of 339,658 and 47 sailing vessels with a tonnage of 5427’37. Of the 115 steamships which entered the port 4 were from United States of America, 5 from United Kingdom and 106 from India. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Limited, maintain a weekly slow mail service both from Bombay and Basra. The Fast Mail Service which used to serve the port weekly both ways was withdrawn during the War and has not been resumed since. Fmgrfas.—The statement below gives the average rates of freight. Per ton. Rs. A. p. Rs. A. T. Dry dates 1 8 0 per bag 19 8 0 Wet dates in mat bag. 1 0 0 „ 14 0 0 Wet dates in boxes . 0 10 0 per box 25 0 0 Dry fish to Colombo . .. .. 37 0 0 Pomegranates . 2 8 0 per crate 17 8 0 Dry limes to Persian Gulf 10 0 0 per bundle 35 9 0 Wet dates to United States of America . Sh. 571 per totu R. G. ALBAN, Captain, Acting British Consul, Muscat,v~ &gt;qp*n« INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record Ref. no. IOL: IOR: Date Name P hotocopying process No. of exposures 1 2 3 4 5 6 KEFER to the specialist CONCERNED —&lt;y D.Q. HQ. 21B7.10/1S. v i U-. M fa PERSIAN GUtF RESIDENCY. BAHRAIN* 18th October, 1947. Dear Hallows, The Treasury have asked to see the latest ✓ Trade Reports tor the Persian Gulf Agencies urgently* I enclose herewith copies of the Kuwait and Muscat reports for 1946-47* The Bahrain report Is expected to be ready by the end of this month* If you see no objection would you kindly send the reports to Thorley* Yours sincerely, W.R. Hay, R*I. Hallows, Esquire, U*B*E*, Commonwealth Relations, Office, Whitehall* LONDON*PERSfciH GULF RESIDEHCYf BAHRAIN* 13th October, 1947. Dear Hallov;s, The Treasury hare asked to see the latest Trade Kepcrte Tor the Persian Gulf Agencies urgently. I enclose herewith copies of the Kuwait and Muscat reports for 1946-47. The Bahrain report is expected to be ready by the end of this month. If you sec no objection would you kindly send the reports to Thorley. Yours sincerely, W.R. Hay. R.I. Hallows, Esquire, U.5.E., Commonwealth Relations, Office, Whitehall, LONDON.ILE COPY. EXT \¥\ 6476 ^ ^r— MUSCAT TRADE REPORT FOR 1942-43 Printed by Manager, Government or India Press* SimlaREPORT ON THE TRADE OF MUSCAT FOR THE YEAR 1942-1943. PAKT I. _ (a) General description oi the Sultanate of Mus- PART n, (a) Trade. (t) Imports .—Goods to the value of Rs. 63,40,702 were imported during the year under report as against Rs. 53,12,403 during 1041-1942. There was an increase of Rs. 10,28,299 in the value of imports. The principal articles of import were cereals, tea and textiles. Imports from India were 89% during the year under review against 79% in the previous one. The following table shows the decrease (—) or increase (-(--) in value of imports of the principal commodities during 1942-1943 as compared with those of the previous year :— Articles. 1941-1942 1942-1943 Decrease or increase Rice . . 22,13,738 18,12,414 —4,01,324 Wheat and wheat flour 3,34,907 2,99,016 —35,891 Coffee 5,57,220 83,473 —4,73,747 Sugar 1,57,830 60,838 —96,992 Tea 21,221 12,12,045 + 11,90,824 Cotton piecegoode , 11,36,079 11,94,343 + 58,264 Twist 1,47,094 1,64,146 + 17,052 Wines and spirits 23,348 14,324 —9,024 Miscellaneous , 1,09,002 1,94,762 + 85,760 The increase in the value of imports during the year under report over those of 1941-1942 was chiefly due to rise in prices. The quantity ac tually imported was less than those in 1941-1942, (ii) Expoits .—The exports during the year under report totalled Rs, 81,08,976 as against Rs. 38,68,298 in the previous year, showing an increase of Rs. 42,40,678. The principal indigenous articles of export were dates and fish. The following table shows the decrease (—) or increase (X) in the value of exports of principal articles during the year under review as compared with the exports of 1941-1942 :— Articles 1941-1942 1942-1943 Decrease or increase. Dry dates . 16,42,642 30,52,235 + 14,09,593 Wet dates . . 2,45,934 11,83,499 + 9,37,565 Fish manure . 1,70,953 34,120 —1,36,833 Salted fish . 8,52,503 3,55,578 —4,96,930 Sardines 1,08,754 2,42,599 + 1,33,845 Cotton piecegoods . 93,910 3,05,751 + 2,11,841 Coffee . . 69,617 2,38,883 + 1,69,266 Sugar . . . 4,073 1,59,248 + 1,55,175 Tea ... 11,488 7,17,848 + 7,06,360 The increase of over forty two lakhs cf rupees in the value of exports during the year under re port over those of the previous year is chiefly due to the upward trend of prices due to the war. (b) Financial. Money was easy and could be raised at from 6% to 10% interest during the year under report. Muscat has a double currency system (Maria Theresa thalers in the interior, Dhofar and on the Batinah Coast, and Government of India rupees in the towns of Muscat and Matrah). The dollar and rupee rate of exchange fluctuates and rose from Rs. 141 to Rs. 235 per 100 dollars during the year under report.- Due to the favourable conditions prevailing during the year under review both merchants and date garden owners made good profits. There were a few small cases of bankruptcies of littl® importance, (c) Agriculture. No change. (d) Industry. No change. No change, except that the estimate of the population given in the report for 1941-1942 seems high. (b) Customs. No change.2 (c) Communications and transport. (?) Freight. —Freights ruling during the year under report were as follows :— (1) To Bombdy. (a) Dry dates In bags (b) Dry datog in cases (c) Wet dates in bags (d) Wet dates in cases (e) Salted fish in bundles Rs. 2/1 per bag. No shipment went forward. Rs. 26/8 per ton of 20 Cwt. Rs. 26/8 per ton of 40 Cft. Rs. 3/5 per bundle. (/) Pomegranates in crates Rs. 2/4 per crate. (sO General cargo . . No shipment wont forward. ( 2 ) To Karachi. (a) Dry dates in bags (b) Dry dates in cases (c) W'et dates in bags (d) Wot dates in cases (e) Salted fish in bundles. (/) Pomegranates in crates (g) General cargo . , Rs. 2 per bag. No shipment went forward. Rs. 25/8 per ton of gOCwt. Rs. 25/8 per ton of 40 cft. No shipment went forward. No shipment went forward. No shipment went forward. (f) Social. (?) Standard of living. No change. (n) Emjfloyjmnt. There is no unemployment at present. During^^ the summer able bodied persons leave Muscat and Matrah for work in the date gardens on the Bati- nah. There is steady employment for fit men on the South Coast at Masirah and Has A1 Hadd. (ii) Public Health, No change. (tv) Municipality. No change. (3) To Colombo. (n) to (d) and (/) and {g) (c) Saltod fish in bundles No shipment went forward. Rs. 70 por ton of 20 Cwt. upto 9th Sept. 1942. Rs. 93/8 per ton of 20 Cwt. from 10th Sept. 1942 to 31st March, 1943. A. C. GALLOWAY, Political Agent, Muscat, (4) To London. (a) to (d) . . .No shipment went forward. (ii) Shipping. ^ The principal steamship line which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report was the British India Steam Navigation Company Limited. J 59 steamers in all aggregating 45,190 tons en tered and cleared these ports during the year ending 31st March, 1943. All of these steamers were under the British Flag. (Hi) Roads. No change. (iv) Transport No change.EXTERNAL PabBc &amp; Judieial Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. REGISTER NO. Sxt.6215/41. 19 Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Muscat Trade Report 1939/40. Secretary of State Committee 3f.X 2 A Under Secretary Secretary of State Perusal FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. oc The total/imports during the year shows a decrease on 1938/1939 and the total of exports a slight increase. c ., SE&amp;N COMMITTEg, i 5 NOV 1341 The figures of the last three years are given below. Those in red refer to Indian trade. (10308) ( 10853 ) Wt.l3fl71/P.159 1,000 5/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Wt,18826/P.221/2 7,250 (15 sorts) 6/39 „ Gp.685 »» Imports/IMPORTS 1937/38. Rs. 1938/39 Rs. 1939/40. Rs. 41,67,125 &lt;2&lt;2 , Ao ^ &lt;g 2^. 43,76,193 IQ (A, 46,49,765 &lt;2 7, f 9 y (&gt; ' £ '1' 1957/58. Rs. EXPORTS 1938/39. 1939/40. Rs. Rs. 32,99,015 16 , A 3, £40 33,31,939 J6 / 'll 34,55,798 M, *3, &gt;i°«- From the 15th September 1939 all freight charges were increased, and On the 22nd February 1940 customs duties on certain imporWarticles, such as grain, petrol and piece-goods^ were raised. India entered into competition with Japan and captured over 25/ of the cement trade. The export of gold and silver declined owing to restrictions on the export of silver imposed in December 1939. Tobacco cultivated in the interior was smuggled to Dubai on the Crucial Coast and shipped from there. The manufacture of fish meal and manure decreased owing to the loss of the German market. The 1938/39 and 1937/33 Trade Reports both referred to the 1936/37 Report, which stated that the standard of living was lo’w and that unemployment was rife in Muscat and Matrah. The 1939/40 Report, however, while agreeing about the standard of living,says that there is no unemployment during the date season 7 and very little during the rest of the year. K. f . 1Letter from Major T. Hickinbotham, O.B.E., Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, No. 740, dated the 7th April 1941. I have the honour to forward, herewith, two copies of my report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1939-40, and to request that twenty-four printed copies may be sent to me. 2. A copy of the report has been sent to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S LETTER No. date r .eived -57 - 9- 7 2 2-9-1941Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1939-40 PART I. General description of the Sultanate of Muscat. Muscat is the capital of the independent Sultanate of Muscat and Oman situated at the easterly corner of Arabia. Its seaboard is nearly 1,000 miles long and extends from near Tibba on the west side of the Musandam Peninsula round to Ras Darbat Ali. Ras Darbat Ali marks the boundary between the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman and the terri tory of the Sultan of Kishen and Socotra, a Sultanate within the Aden Protectorate. A small strip of the coast on the east side of the Musandam Penin sula from Dibbah to Khor Kalba is administered by minor chiefs of Trucial Oman, independent of the Sultan. The Sultanate extends inland to the borders of the Ruba al Khali or Great Desert. Phy sically Muscat and Oman consists of three divi- «ions—a coastal plain, a range of hills, and a plateau. The coastal plain varies in width from ten miles in the neighbourhood of Suwaiq to practically nothing in the vicinity of Matrah and Muscat towns where the hills descend abruptly into the sea. The moun tain range runs generally from north-west to south east. It reaches its greatest height in the Jebel Akhdar region, where heights of over 9,000 feet occur. The hills are for the most part barren but in the high area round Jebel Akhdar they are green and there is considerable cultivation. The plateau has an average height of a thou sand feet. With the exception of oases there is little or no cultivation. North-west of Muscat the coastal plain is known as the Batinah. It is fertile and prosperous. The date gardens extend for over 150 miles. The Batinah dates are famous for their flavour. They ripen in the first half of July well before the Basra dates. The coast line between Muscat and the province of Dhofar is barren and forbidding. The fertile province of Dhofar lies on the south-eastern coast of Arabia. Its principal town is Salalah on the coast while Murbat is the port. The last remaining possession on the north coast of the Gulf of Oman is the port of Gwadur and a small tract of country surrounding the town. The town of Muscat is the capital and the seat of Government. At one time a town of some commer cial importance it has of recent years lost most of its trade which has been transferred to the adjacent town of Matrah. Matrah is the starting point for the trade routes into the interior. The area of the Sultanate has been estimated at about 82,000 square miles and the population at 5,000,000, chiefly Arabs, but there is a strong infusion of negro blood, especially along the coast. The towns of Muscat and Matrah are composed of one-third Indian, one-third Baluch and one-third negro. There are few Arabs resident in these two towns. The present Sultan is His Highness Sir Saiyid Said bin Taimur, K.C.I.E. (born August 13th, 1910), who succeeded his father Saiyid Sir Taimur bin Faisal, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., in 1932, as the 13th of his dynasty to be Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Currency. The currency of the country is the silver Maria Theresa Thaler or Rial and a copper coin, known as the Baiza, minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah Indian currency notes and rupees are generally accepted, but the Rial is the only currency recog nised in the Interior. The Maria Theresa Rial fluctuates in value consi derably, being affected by the world price of silver and the local supply and demand. Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department in Muscat, Matrah and the coast towns are :— 1 kiyas 24 kiyas 10 Muscat Maunds 200 Muscat Maunds . The weight of 6 dollars or 5*9375 ozs. . Muscat Maund, . 1 Farasalab. . 1 Bahar. Rice is sold by the bag ; other cereals by the following measures :— 20 Palis . . .1 Farrah, 20 Farrahs . . .1 Khandi. The rupee which weighs one tola and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “Auqia” is equal to eight “ Misqals ”. Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr . . if hand or, 41 inches. 4 Shdbra . . 1 I^hira.or cubit. 4 Dhiras . . 1 Ba’ or fathom.2 Legislation. Population. The Government is autocratic. The heads of various State Departments carry out their adminis trative duties under the orders of His Highness the Sultan and the Walis (or Governors) in charge of districts are directly responsible to him. Civil and Criminal Courts are presided over by Qadhis. Cases against British subjects are tried in the Agency Court in accordance with the Indian Criminal Procedure Code and Indian Penal Code. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Matrah has been taken but a rough computation fixes the figures at 4,500 and 8,500 respectively. In Muscat there are 206 British Indian subjects and 1,063 in Matrah. There are small colonies of British Indian subjects in the more important towj^i^ on the Coast, the largest colony being at the bu^ port of Sur where there are 76 persons. Customs. Customs duties on imports during the greater part of the year under report were levied at the rate of 5 per cent, ad valorem on foodstuffs and general merchandise, 10 per cent, on certain goods classified as coming under the category of “ luxuries ” and 20 per cent, on liquors. By a notification issued by His Highness the Sul tan on the 22nd February 1940 the customs duties on various articles imported from abroad were increased. The following are some of the rates of duty charged :— 1. Wheat, rice and 7£ per cent, ad valorem. grains. 2. Petrol . . .8 annas a tin of 4 gallons. 3. Coffee . . •7} per cent, ad valorem. 4. Tea . . .10 per cent, ad valorem. 5. Cotton piecegoods . 7£ per cent, ad valorem. 6. Silk and woollen 17£ per cent, ad valorem. piecegoods. 7. Matches . . 121 per cent, ad valorem. 8. Carpets . . .171 P er cent, ad valorem. 9. Motor cars and 20 per cent, ad valorem. motor parts. 10. Opium . . .75 per cent, ad valorem. No duty is levied on goods exported from the State but there is an octroi duty of 5 per cent, on produce from the Interior brought into the Coastal towns for sale or export. In all districts subject to the Muscat Government’s authority the ancient Islamic tax known as “ Zakat ” of 5 per cent, ad valorem is enforced on the principal products of the country, in this case limes, dates and firewood. A tax of one anna per package is charged on all merchandise in addition to the customs duties mentioned above. Receipts from this tax are credited to the Municipality. The revenue derived from the Customs and the above taxes constitutes the main source of the State’s income. Shipping. The principal Steamship Lines which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report were as follows :— 1. The British India Steam Navigation Company, Limited. 2. The Asiatic Steamship Company. 3. The Hansa Line of Steamers until September 1939. 4. The Yamashita Steamship Company, Limited. 5. The Mitsui Bhusan Kaisha Line of Steamers. 123 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 449,217 tons entered and cleared these ports during the year ending the 31st of March 1940. Of these a 105 with a total gross tonnage of 339,871 were under the British Flag, 4 vessels with a gross tonnage of 30,549, were under the German Flag, and 14 vessels with a gross tonnage of 78,797 under the Japanese Flag. Freight (Steamer). Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— 1. To Bombay and Karachi from Muscat— Dry dates in bags Wet dates in bags Wet dates in cases Dry fish . Pomegranates . . Re. 0-15-0 upto the 15th Sep tember 1939 and thereafter Rs. 1-3-0. . Rs. 12-4-0 per ton of 20 cwts. upto the 15th September 1939 and thereafter Rs. 15-8-0. . Rs. 12-4-0 per ton of 40 c.ft. upto the 15th September 1939 and thereafter Rs. 15-8-0. . No shipments went forward. . Rs. 1-3-0 per crate upto the 15th September 1939 and there after Rs. 1-8-0. Cotton, wool, cotton No shipments went forward, piecegoods and woollen piecegoods. 2. To Colombo from Muscat— f Wet dates in cases . Rs. 24-4-0 per ton of 20 cwts. upto the 15th September 1939 and thereafter Rs. 30-8-0. Dry fish . . . Rs. 28-0-0 per ton of 20 cwts. upto the 15th September 1939 and thereafter Rs. 35-0-0.3 By dhow. 3. To Bombay from Gwadur— Article— Wet dates in bags By steamer. Dry fish in bundles Cotton in bundles 4. To Karachi from Gwadur— Wet dates Rs. 15-8-0 per ton of 20 cwts. upto the 15th Septem ber 1939 and Rs. 19-8-0 there after. Rs. 12-0-0 per ton of 20 cwts. upto the 15th September 1939 and there after Rs. 15-0-0. Rs. 3-4-0 per bundle upto the 15th September 1939 and thereafter Rs. 4-0-0. Dry fish . Cotton in bundles 4 annas Rs. 9-0-0 per ton of per bundle 20 cwts. upto the of about 15th September 80 lbs. 1939 and there after Rs. 11-4-0. . .. Ditto. . .. Rs. 2-8-0 per bundle upto the 15th September 1939 and thereafter Rs. 3-2-0. The import of rice increased by Rs. 2,87,949 due to merchants’ ordering extra supplies in view of the disturbed political situation in Rurope. The value of imports of textiles amounted to Rs. 9,24,436 as against Rs. 13,69,900 in 1938-39 being a decrease of Rs. 4,45,364. ihe decrease was due to surplus stocks from the previous year and to the increase of prices in Japan after the out break of the war. Although Japan continued to be the chief supplier of textiles, cement and matches, as the following tables show, India has now come into competition and has acquired a substantial part of Japan s trade in cement. Textile Fabrics. India United Kingdom Japan 5. To Colombo from Gwadur— Dry fish 6. To Zanzibar Gwadur— Mats in bundles from Rs. 22-0-0 per ton of 40 c.ft. upto the 15th September 1939 and there after Rs. 27-8-0. Rs. 4-8-0 per bundle upto the 15th September 1939 and thereafter Rs. 5-10-0. I ’ 5 fe' Total Cement. Japan India Other Countries Total Matches. 1938-39. 1939-40. Rs. Rs. . 3,39,749 2,49,590 . 15,466 7,872 . 7,82,827 4,85,701 . 11,38,042 7,43,163 38,146 27,764 • 10,300 . 1,475 38,146 39,539 Japan 17,255 25,423 PART n. (A) Trade. Imports. Goode worth Rs. 46,49,765 were imported during the year as against Rs. 48,75,973, in 1938-39 being a decrease of Rs. 2,26,208~mTEevalue of imports. The principal articles of import were cereals, toffee, sugar and textiles. India continues to enjoy a monopoly for the supply of cereals. It can be seen from the above tables that the value of imports of textiles from India decreased by Rs. 90,159 and those from Japan decreased by Rs. 2,97,126 as compared with the previous year. The value of sugar imports increased by Rs. 89,856. The import of dollars fell from Rs. 3, ^,600 in 3 &gt; 1938-39 to Rs. 29,200 in the year under review. Exports. The total exports amount to Rs. 34,55,798 as against Rs. 33,31,939 in 1938-39. Principal articles of export were dates, fish and limes. The export of dry dates increased by Rs. 2,49,382 whereas the export of wet dates fell from Rs. 2,65,867 in 1938-39 to Rs. 1,99,803 in 1939-40. In spite of the fall in the export of wet dates the total export of dates showed an increase of Rs. 1,83,318.4 The value of exports of limes this year amounted to Rs. 1,26,979 as against Rs. 1,15,315 in the pre vious year. The export of sardines in 1939-40. amounted to Rs. 2,17,595 as against Rs. 4,46,038 in 1938-39. Export of dry fish rose from Rs. 7,55,278 in 1938-39 to Rs. 8,97,835 in the present year. The exports of raw cotton increased by Rs. 51,017. The export of gold and silver declined from Rs. 1,14,700 in 1938-39 to Rs. 66,900 in 1939-40. This was due to the restrictions on the export of silver imposed in December 1939. (B) Financial. It is difficult to assess the average state of the market where a dual currency subject to fluctuation exists, but on the whole it may be said that ready money was easy during the year. There was the usual seasonal rise in the value of the Rial against the rupee during the date harvest and just after when there is always a demand for dollars for pay ments to growers and the usual seasonal fall in the Rial as against the rupee in the early spring of 1940 when rupees were in demand to meet bills from India. There were no insolvency cases in the Agency Court. Banks .—There are none. (C) Agriculture. The principal occupation of the people is the cul tivation of date palms and the harvesting and ex porting of dates. Date palm cultivation is carried on on the Batinah plain and also in the principal \-alleys of Oman. Grapes, walnuts and pomegra nates are cultivated in the mountainous region known as Jebel Akhdar while limes and mangoes are grown in the same areas as the date palm. There is a considerable export of pomegranates and limes, the latter being dried before export. Tobacco is cultivated in the interior of the country and at one or two places on the Batinah plain. There is a considerable export of this commodity but it is npt possible to state with any degree of accuracy the value of these exports as a large quantity of tobacco is smuggled out of the country and shipped from the port of Dubai on the Trucial Coast. It has been suggested that the quantity exported from Dubai can be valued as high as five lacs of rupees a year. Gum tragacanth and gum sandarac are exported from the province of Dhofar. Sweet potatoes, carrots, onions, cucumbers and spinach are cultivated in the date gardens for local consumption. Tomato cultivation has recently been introduced and is spreading but it is unlikely that there will ever be an export demand. A considerable area of land on the Batinah plain could be brought under cultivation but the Omani is not sufficiently energetic nor has he the financial resources necessary to open up new cultivation and sow a more paying crop. Mention must be made of Omani cotton which is^t of fine quality and which is khaki in colour. There is little doubt that the cultivation of this cotton can be considerably increased if markets can be found. (D) Industry. Fish meal and fish manure are manufactured by a Khoja company in Matrah. Fairly large shipments were made prior to the outbreak of the War to Ger many, Holland and England. Since the War trade with Germany has naturally ceased and the firm has found it difficult to obtain freight space to other countries. There are several firms who are engaged in the packing and exporting of boxed dates. Kasha fish and salt and dry fish are exported by several merchants to Colombo, and the Far East. Turbans, shawls and lengths of cloth are woven on hand- looms from cotton locally grown. Khaki cloth lengths woven from the natural coloured cotton are nine yards long and about 20 inches in breadth and vary in retail price from Rs. 1-12-0 to Rs. 5-0-0 a length. (E) Communication and Transport. Intercommunication between the coastal towns is carried on principally by sailing vessels. All mer chandise from the Interior is brought to the coast on camels and donkeys. Taxis run from Muscat to Khor Fakkan in the north and from Muscat to Qariyat in the south. So far no lorries have been introduced but there is no reason why lorries should not make use of the motor tracks during dry weather. The fact that they have not been introduced is pro bably due to cheap sea communication and lack of urgency in distributing and collecting merchandise. (F) Social. Standard of living .—The standard of living is low. Although the majority of the inhabitants live a reasonably happy life there is no doubt that they suffer from under-nourishment due to a lack of grazing facilities for animals. The principal em ployments are fishing and agriculture and the diet of the labourers consists principally of rice and fish with a small quantity of vegetables on the coast, and dates and rice and a larger quantity of vegetables in the Interior.* Employment. —During the summer months there is no unemployment as every man, woman and ? f ^ child that can leave Muscat and Matrah goes to WO rk in the date gardens in the Batinah. During the remainder of the year there is very little unem ployment and for the East very few beggars. Public health .—The roads in the towns of Muscat and Matrah are kept clean and the Sultan has under ^^consideration the introduction of a Public Health Department which will probably start functioning next year. This Department will be responsible for the sanitation of the towns and will make a determined effort to eliminate malaria from Muscat town. Municipality. —The Municipal Committee are yet young iu experience and the Municipal President moves slowly having had no previous experience in town government. However in spite of these dis advantages the Municipality have succeeded in improving the sanitary condition of the towns of Muscat and Matrah. A providential fire destroyed the insanitary market outside the Bab A1 Saghir (Small Gate) and the Municipality have very wisely refused to permit •*of its being rebuilt. They have erected two rows of concrete shops and a semicircular market for the sale of vegetables at a little distance from the Bab A1 Saghir. T. Hickinbotham, Major, Political Agent &amp; H. B. M.'s Consul, Muscat21 TABLE No. 2-A. Total Exports during the years 1937-38, 1938-39 and 1939-40. • Countries. 1937-38. 1938-39. 1939-40. Ks. Rs. Rs. ■India . • • • Germany ■ • . .. Ceylon Africa . • • • • Singapore ..... China ..... Aden United Kingdom United States .... Persia (Iran) .... Persian Gulf .... Iraq . . - Other countries .... . 16,43,240 2,08,469 9,17,785 80,593 17,694 37,419 . 57,472 . . 14,370 . . 20,834 10,750 . 2,46,179 12,491 31,719 16,71,210 2,79,858 7,30,647 76,083 260 26,180 . 2,71,751 19,000 3,379 31,679 1,36,422 77,453 7,847 20,63,406 64,433 9,02,536 27,054 29,465 1,20,475 2,450 05,235 1,40,866 39,878 Total 32,90,015 33,31,939 34,55,798 V'' t- TABLE No. 2-B. Total Exports of Principal Articles during the years 1937-38, 1938-39 and 1939-40. Value. Articles, 1937-38. • 1938-39.* 1939-40. —— ’ Rs. Rs. • Rs. By Steamers. • * • • Fishda._ 2,64,092 3,25,821 1,05,480 Sardine, dry . • • • * * * .* 9,02,788 7,51,438 8,66,678 Fish, dry and salted • • • • 32,594 20,790 25,400 Shark fins . • • • • • • • • ’ 22,830 5,225 15 100 2,450 Mother of Pearls 3,000 6,465 Fish Maws 100 100 Cowries . . • • • 400 93 3,260 Prawns • • • • * 4,170 Fish Meal .■(•*• Fruits o'-£ ; . . . • . 8,02,918 7,18,106 9,29,240 Dates, dry . 1,59,915 1,71,658 1,56.513 Dates, wet . • * • • , . • • 23,274 • 31,748 27,012 Pomegranates . . • • • ' • * * . 21,122 47,550 71,386 Limes, dry and fresh • • Provisions. TOi 1 P . 2,000 Sug?.r • * * * * • •.. - * 1.250 Miscellaneous Provisions . i ' 05 ' *920 • • \220 Ghee. • i -MMSubject: JriLRoIiiN GULF. Lius oat Trade Report, 1958-59. Total import and export figures for the last 3 years are given below 3 including separate figures for India. Imports . ( in lakhs of rupees ). 1936-7. 1937-8. 1938-9. * r H O &gt; _ r co m o m O 2 Crt - C=&gt; fT? § Total 44.7 41.7 India 24.2 22.2 Exports. Total 32.5 33 India 16.3 16.4 48.8 30*7 33.3 16.7 This report covers a pre-war period and so seems more out of date than usual. It is noted that there is a considerable increase in imports, due mainly to replenishments of stock in the sugar and rice markets. japan increased her imports/ (15146) Wt.l7760/P.106 6,000 6/40 A.&amp; E W.Ltd. Gp. 6852 imports of textile goods consid at the expense of India, Export trade varied little the previous year. For information. Secretary, E»-&amp; 0. Dept. Secretary, Financial Dept., To see.iNDH.* £0 file copy n Letter from Captain J. B. Howes, Political Agent and H. B. M. s Consul, Muscat, Camp Ziarat, No. Z/90, dated the 12th June 1940. I have the honour to forward, herewith, two copies of my report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1938-39, and to request that twenty-four printed copies may be sent to me. 2. A copy of the report has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S LETTER No. DATE RECEIVED 130 1 7 9 9 -12- 1940Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year I 938-39. PART i. General description of the Sultanate of Muscat. (See report for the previous year. Currency. See report for the previous year. the year ended 31st March 1939. Of these 104 with a total gross tonnage of 340,877 were under the British Flag. 10 German vessels with a gross ton nage of 71,425, 13 Japanese with a gross tonnage 73,740 and 2 Dutch with a gross tonnage of 12,133 entered and cleared the ports of Muscat and Matrah. Freight. Weights and Measures. See report for the previous year. Measures (Linear). Same as last year. Legislation. See report for the previous year. Freights ruling during the (1) To Bombay and Karachi— Dry dates Wet dates Wet dates in cases Dry fish in bundles . Pomegranates in crates Cotton in bundles Cotton piece-goods and woollen goods year were as follows :— Rs. a. 0 15 per bag. 12 4 per ton of 20 cwts. 12 4 per ton 40 c. ft. 1 0 per bundle. 1 3 per crate. 3 8 per bundle. 14 0 per 40 c. ft. Customs. Same as last year. Population. Same as last year. Shipping. The principal Steamship Lines which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report were as follows :— (1) The British India Steam Navigation Com pany, Limited. (2) The Asiatic Steamship Company. (3) The Mogul Line of Steamers. (4) The Strick Line of Steamers. (5) Silver Java Pacific Line of Steamers. (6) The Hansa Line of Steamers. (7) The Yamashita Steamship Company, Limited. (8) The Mitsui Bhusan Kaisha Line of Steamers. 129 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 498,175 tons entered and cleared these ports during (2) To Colombo— W T et dates in bags . . 24 4 per ton. Wet dates in cases . . 24 4 ^&gt;er 40 c. ft. Dry fish . . • . 28 0 per ton of 20 cwts. (3) To United States of America— £ s. d. Wet dates in cases . 4 13 0 per 40 c. ft. of 20 cwts. up to 16th Septem ber 1938 and there- afte r£5-5-0. (4) To London— Wet dates in cases . 3 10 0 per 40 c. ft. ol 20 cwts. PART II. (A) Trade. It will be seen from the following table that there was an increase of Rs. 7,09,068 in the value of the total imports, as compared with the figures of the previous year. Value of imports. Rs. 1937- 38 . 1938- 39 . • • • 41,67,125 48,76,1932 The principal articles of import were rice am cotton Piecegoods valued at Rs. 15,50,154 am . • AU ! 91 ’ 434 respectively. There was an increas m the imports of rice, sugar and cotton piecegood by Rs. 4,69,563, 1,07,211 and 3,74,458 respectively 1 he increase in the imports of sugar and rice wa mainly due to shortage of stocks in the market. India continues to be the sole supplier of cereals Japan continues to be the chief competitor in tk ie d ot textile fabrics, cement and matches as thi tollowing table will show Textile Fabrics. 1937-38. 1938-39. Rs. Rs. India United Kingdom Japan • 4,54,714 1,375 4,24,810 3,39,749 15,466 7,82,827 Total 8,80,899 11,38,042 Cement. Ja P an • • . . 31,575 38,146 Matches. Ja P an • , . . 12,990 17,255 It can be seen from the above table that the value of imports of textile fabrics from India decreased by Rs. 1,14,965 whereas those from Japan increased by Rs. 3,58,017 as compared with the previous y r ear. Japan has not only continued to be one of the main suppliers of piecegoods, but her share in the trade increased by 13 per cent in the year under review. Cement and matches are almost exclusively imported from Japan. Imports of petrol decreased by Rs. 1,36,181 in 1938-39 owing to the transfer of Imperial Airways from Gwadur to Jiwani. ^ There was a slight increase in the imports from Germany, the chief articles imported being the same as in the previous year. The imports from China increased to Rs. 64,341 as compared with Rs. 33,278 the last year’s figures. principal articles of export were dates, fish, limes and dollars. The export of dry dates decreased by Rs. 1,20,072 whereas those of wet dates increased by Rs. 12,744, given below :— 1937-38. 1938-39. Rs. Rs. Dry dates 9,99,248 8,79,176 Wet dates 2,53,123 2,65,867 The export of Sardines in 1938-39 amounted to Rs. 4,46,038 as against Rs. 3,18,681 in 1937-38. There was an increase of Rs. 71,389 in the value of exports of dry sardines to Germany. The export of silver coins increased by Rs. 1,21,090 in the year under report. Oyer-trading .—No over-trading was noticeable during the year under report. (B) Financial. Same as last y T ear. (C) Agriculture. Same as last year. (D) Industry. Same as last year. (E) Communication and Transport. Imperial Airways’ Gwadur Office was shifted to Jiwani in May 1938 and since then the aerodrome at Gwadur was not used by any of the Imperial Airways or K. L. M. machines. (F) Social, Same as last year. Exports. (Sd.) J. B. Howes, The total exports amounted to Rs. 33,31,939 as against Rs. 32,99,019 in the year 1937-38. The Political Agent &amp; H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat.15 TABLE No. 1-C— contd. Principal Articles and Countries from which imported during the years 1936-37, 1937-38 and 1938-39— contd. -39. Articles and Countries from which imported. By Sailing Vessels — contd. Cereals —concld. Vermicelli- :,94i Africa . India Persian Gulf . 181 Starch— 259 India • Tin Provisions— India r,738 Groundnuts— India 1,184 973 Persian Gulf . Pkgs. Oi Kerosene Oil— Persia (Iran) » Fish Oil— 2,204 Aden Africa . 325 India . Oil of all kinds— 376 India Persian Gulf . Other Countries &gt;,557 Sweet Oil— India 11 356 Africa . Pa Paints— India 254 Colours— India 7,119 Waras— Aden 5,220 2,880 1,267 Cotton Goods— India 860 Persian Gulf . 2,697 Africa . Other Countries . Twist and Yarns— ‘491 India Haberdashery— . India 968 Sail Cloth— India 3,153 Persian Gulf . 39 Gunny bags— 3,115 India Other Countries 1,232 Hemp— -'282 India 1,319 Twine— India Galls. Tins Paints, Dyes and Colours. Textiles Pkgs. Pkgs. Quantity. Value. 1936-37. 1937-38. 1938-39. 1936-37. 1937-38. 1938-39. Rs. Rs. Rs. 616 889 476 2,428 3,332 2,356 56 7 3 1,507 556 35 10 •• 122 123 285 170 1,444 3,910 2,342 138 28 2,015 728 •• 302 626 211 2,378 4,613 1,810 •• 1 • • • • 6 4,000 2,300 2,250 1,545 875 1,273 5,347 3,656 4,646 13,195 63 9 398 .. 75 8,616 9,976 24,791 37,388 28,083 45,118 108 197 . . • • 572 124 244 759 299 421 374 13,030 # . •• 5 42 * # 13 65 8 213 763 139 40 n 6 109 359 98 7 •• 14 1,210 •• 1,078 57 140 221 12,138 22,208 22,141 307 244 90 12,687 18,140 12,023 1 200 . . 38 • • •• 6,398 •• •• 65 82 83 5,346 7,023 2,797 17 .. . • 3,246 •• •• 23 22 86 4,263 1,689 4,635 .. 2 •• •• 20 1,120 1,182 1,059 42,637 36,096 32,451 34 • • 9 211 •• 302 419 324 374 8,019 4,753 6,115 17 9 21 1,455 661 1,190India Office, CoPK of, P.Z.5590/39. 1 7hi teha 11 , London, S.17.1. 28th June, 1939. Dear Clough-Taylor, I spoke to you last February about a request from the Japanese Embassy for trade statistics in respect of Bahrein. The request led us to enquire whether the annual Trade Reports for Bahrein (and for Koweit and Muscat) were to be treated as confidential, or ’for official use only’, or whether they were in fact made available to the public generally. The result of our enquiry, which I promised to let you know, shows that all these Trade Reports are given a fairly wide local distribution; they are compiled with a view to assisting trade interests generally and are regarded as in no sense confidential. In the circumstances the Political Resident and the Government of India see no objection to the Japanese Embassy being given a copy of the latest Trade Report/ E.L.F. Clough-Taylor, Esq., Department of Overseas Trade, 35, Old Queen Street, q n 1 o • u • -L •2 . Report for Bahrein. v ’e feel hov/ever that this is hardly the time to be helpful to the Japanese and v/e propose not to send the report to the Embassy unless they again ask for the information. They have not made any reference to the matter since last February. Yours sincerely. rststi ' p Ci\BSON■nan Iff. Letter from Major R. P. Watts, I.A., Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, No. 1491-XIV of 1938, dated the 31st December 1938. I have the honour to forward two copies of my report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1937-38 and to request that twenty-four printed copies may be A copy of the report has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1937-38 PART I. General description of the Sultanate of Muscat. See report for the previous year. Currency. See report for the previous year. Exchange Rate. Bazaar rate. Exchange for 100 Maria Theresa Dollars. 1935-36. 1936-37. 1937-38. Rs. A. Rs. A. Rs. A. Highest .... 149 0 139 0 140 0 lowest .... 118 0 125 0 100 0 Average .... 132 0 135 0 120 14 Weights and Measures. See report for the previous year. Measures (Linear). Same as last year. Legislation. See report for the previous year. Customs. Same as last year. Population. Same as last year. Shipping. The principal Steamship Lines which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report were as follows :— (1) The British India Steam‘Navigation Com pany, Limited. (2) The Strick Lines of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman and Bucknall Steamship Com pany, Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. (5) The Yamashita Steamship Company, Limited. r (6) The Mogul Line of Steamers. (7) The Mitsui Bhusan Kaisha Line of Steamers. (8) Silver Java Pacific Line of Steamers. 81 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 117,563 tons entered and cleared these ports during the year ending 31st March 1938. Of these 63 with a total tonnage of 43,534 were under the British Flag. Seven German vessels with a total tonnage of 28,127, 8 Japanese with a total tonnage of 27,557 and 3 Dutch with a total tonnage of 18,445 entered and cleared the ports of Muscat and Matrah. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— To Bombay and Karachi:— Rs. Dry dates . . .0 Wet dates . . .11 Wet dates in eases . 11 Dry fish in bundles . 1 Pomegranates in crates . 1 Wool in bundles . . 7 Cotton in bundles . 3 Cotton piece-goods and woollen goods . .14 To Colombo :—• Wet dates in bags . 24 Wet dates in cases . 24 Dry fish in bundles . 33 A. 14 per bag up to 8th Aug, 1937 and thereafter As. 15 per bag. 0 per ton of 20 cwts. up to 8th Aug. 1937 and there after Rs. 12-4-0 per ton of 20 cwts. 0 per ton of 40 c. ft. up to 8th Aug. 1937 and there after Rs. 12-4-0 per ton of 40 c. ft. 8 per bundle up to 8th Aug. 1937 and thereafter Rs. 1-12-0 per bundle. 1 per crate up to 8th Aug. 1937 and thereafter Rs. 1-3-0 per crate. 8 per bundle. 8 per bundle up to 8th Aug. 1937 and thereafter Rs. 4-0-0 per bundle. 0 per ton of 40 c. ft. up to 8th Aug. 1937 and there after Rs. 15-8-0 per ton of 40 c. ft. 4 per ton of 20 cwts. 4 per ton of 40 c. ft. 0 per ton of 20 cwts. To United States of America :— £ s. d. Wet dates in cases 3 0 0 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c. ft. To London :— Wet dates in cases 2 17 6 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c. ft.2 PART n. (A) Trade. General condition .— It will be seen from the fol' lowing table that there was a decrease in the value of the total imports and a slight increase in the total exports as compared with the figures of the previous year. 1936-37. 1937-38. Increase (-f) Decrease (—). Rs. Rs. Rs. Imports . . 44,65,861 41,67,125 —2,98,736 Exports . . 32,51,741 32,99,015 +47,274 The decrease of Rs. 2,98,736 in the total imports in the year under report was mainly due to the decrease in the imports of rice, sugar, cotton piece- goods, twist and yarn, silk goods and artificial silk by Rs. 1,46,074, 1,67,974, 47,903, 23,871, 1,53,628 and 34,250 respectively. There was however an appreciable increase in the imports of coffee, petrol, stationery, porcelain-ware and dollars over those of the previous year. The principal articles of imports were rice and piecegoods. There was a great fall in the import of sugar, chiefly due to the large stock of previous year having remained un sold in the market. India continues to be the sole supplier of cereals. Foreign competition .— Japan still continues to hold her position in the market as the chief com petitor in the field of textile fabrics,' cement and matches as the following table will show :— Textile fabrics. 1936-37. 1937-38. Rs. Rs. India 3,27,387 4,54,714 United Kingdom 28,776 1,375 Japan • 5,82,985 4,24,810 China # 2,36,053 33,278 Other Countries . • .• 83,348 64,740 Total 12,58,549 9,78,917 Japan Cement. ' 27,529 31,575 Japan Matches. 5,761 12,990 Japanese goods being very cheap find a ready market and are popular in sale amongst the local buyers who are generally poor. Cement and matches are now exclusively imported from Japan. Imports from Germany slightly increased during the year under report, the chief articles imported being the same as in the previous year, i.e., imitation whisky, brandy, lubricating oil, stationery, per fumery, hardware and lampware. The imports from China decreased to Rs. 37,278 against Rs. 236,053 last year, there being no demand on account of their greater cost as compared with Japanese goods. Over-trading. —No over-trading was noticeable during the year. Commercial morality .— Generally speaking was sound. (B) Financial. Same as last year. e (C) Agriculture. Same as last year. (D) Industry. Same as last year. (E) Communication and Transport. • Same as last year. Air Service. —Same as last year except that Royal Dutch K. L. M. aeroplanes have also been granted permission by His Highness the Sultan to use the same air route and aerodrome at Gwadur as the Imperial Airways. (F) Social. Same as last year. ... R. P. Watts, Major, I.A., Political Agent and H. B. M.'s Consul, Muscat. Date Trade of Muscat. Same as last year. The following are the average prices per Bahar that have prevailed during the last three years :—• 1935-36. 1936-37. 1937-38. Rs. Rs. Rs. Dry dates produced in Oman 84 120 so Dry dates produced in Batinah .... 50 75 40 Wet dates produced in Batinah .... 29 35 55 Fard dates . 42 70 Fard dates packed in boxes per box .... Fard dates packed in packets 14 !4 14 per box .... 14 14 14 During the last three seasons the following quan titles have been exported from Muscat:— Dry dates Year. Bags. Value in rupees. • . 1935-36 1936- 37 1937- 38 104,803 103,503 13,472 Mats and Boxes. 9,29,610 9.58,060 8,02,918 Wet dates • . 1935-36 1936- 37 1937- 38 35,645 45,775 6,884 2,37,084 2,05,063 1,59,915Letter from the Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, No. 1318-242 of 1937, dated 20th December 1937. I have the honour to forward two copies of my Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year 1936-37, the original of which has been sent to the Forei gn Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me. ENCLOSURE !N j HCIA FOREiGN SECRETARY’S letter No. 2 5 Hated 3 MAPReport on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1936-37 I PART L General description of the Sultanate of A/TnsrAt. Muscat is the capital of the Independent Sultanate of that name situated on the Eastern Coast of Arabia. With the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Musandum Peninsula between Dibba and Khor Kalba, which is under the independent control of minor Shaikhs, the sea-board of the Sultanate extends in the north from Tibat, on the western shores of the Musandum Peninsula, to Has Dharbat Ali in the south, situated some 290 miles due north of the extreme westerly point of Socotra Island. Inland the Sultanate extends to the borders of the Rub-al-Khali or to give it its local name—the Great Desert. Of late years the Omanis have become autonomous, the writ of the Sultan merely runs throughout a coastal belt varying in depth from some 16 to 30 miles. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the main ranges running approximately parallel to the sea coast with barren, rocky offshoots extend ing in places down to the sea. The higher inland ranges, with a comparatively good rainfall, are wooded in places and generally fertile. The sea coast for some 190 miles north-west of Muscat is known as the Batinah. It consists of a fertile strip covered for some 100 miles of its length with extensive date groves. The remainder of the coast line within the limits of the Sultanate is barren and forbidding, with the notable exception of Dhofar in the extreme south. This southern province of Dhofar extends from Murbat in the east to Ras Dharbat Ali in the west, and is bounded on the north by the Qura mountains. Being well within reach of the monsoon rains and being blessed with several perennial streams, this area, particularly round Salalah, is extremely fertile. The town of Muscat, once important and pros perous, has given place to the adjoining port of Matrah as the trade centre and focus of commercial dealings with the Batinah and the interior. Muscat however still continues to be the seat of Government and the capital of the Sultanate. Currency. currency notes and rupees are generally accepted but the dollar is the only currency recognised in the interior. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value con siderably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrain pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohammadis and Gajh, hypothetical units of which the former com prises two species, the black and the white. The latter is used as a basis of calculation in whole sale transactions, whilst the black Mohammadi, twenty and a half of which constitute a dollar, is used for petty retail trade. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohammadis and not in rupees— 20 Gajh .... 1 Mohammadi. 11J Mohammadis . . .1 Dollar. 100 Mohammadis . . .1 Toman. Exchange Rate. — Exchange for 100 Maria Theresa Dollars. 1934-35. 1935-36. 1936-37. Rs. A. RS. A. RS. A. Highest bazaar rate . 114 4 149 0 139 0 Lowest bazaar rate 90 0 118 0 125 0 Average bazaar rate . .. 101 0 132 0 135 0 Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department prescribed in Muscat, Matrah and the Coast towns are 1 Kiyas .... The weight of 6 dollars or 5-9375 ozs. 24 Kiyas 10 Muscat Maunds 200 Muscat Maunds 1 Muscat Maund. 1 Farasalah. 1 Bahar. Rice is sold by the following measures :— 20 Palis 20 Farrahs bag ; other cereals by the . . 1 Farrah. . . 1 Khandi. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa dollar and the copper coin, known as the Baiza, minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah, sovereigns, Indian The rupee which weights one tola and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Auqia ” equals eight “ Misqals ”,2 Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr . , . .1 Hand or 4£ inches. 4 Shibrs . . , . j Dbira or cubit. 4 Dhiras . . . . 1 Ba’ or fathom. Legislation. ^ overnmen t of the Sultanate is conducted by the Sultan and is of the oriental type tempered by Treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The heads of the various State Departments carry out their administrative duties under the orders of His Highness and the Walis (or Governors) in charge of districts are directly responsible to the Sultan. Civil and Criminal Courts are presided over by a Chief Justice, but cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent on principles of law adopted from British India. Cases of British subjects and Protected persons against Muscat subjects are decided in the Muscat Courts, in which the right of Consular representation is held and exercised. Customs. Customs duties on imports are at present levied at the rate of 5 per cent, ad valorem on foodstuffs and general merchandize, 10 per cent, on certain goods classified as coming under the category of luxuries and 20 per cent, on liquors containino r alchohol of the strength of 55° Under Proof or less! There is no duty levied on goods exported from the State but produce from the interior brought into the Coastal towns for sale or export is charged with an octroi duty of 5 per cent. In ^ all districts subject to the Muscat Govern ment’s authority the ancient Islamic tax known as Zakat ” of 5 per cent, ad valorem, is enforced on the principal products of the country, in this case limes, dates and firewood. The revenues derived from the Customs and the above taxes constitute the main source of the State’s income. Population. No regular census of the population of Mm and Matrah has been taken but a rough compi tion fixes the figures at 4,500 and 8,500 respectiv The large majority of the Indian trading c&lt; c ™; ists of Khojas and Banias which form, inhabited Muscat has since moved to Matrah wl greater facilities exist for direct trade with the ii nor. Shipping. The principal Steamship Lines which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report were as follows :— ^ (1) The British India Steam Navigation Com pany, Limited. (2) The Strick Line of Steamers. (3) The Ellerman and Bucknall Steamship Company, Limited. ^ r (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. (5) The Yamashita Steamship Company Limited. J * 135 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 484,911 tons entered and cleared these ports dur ing the year ending the 31st March 1937. Of these 117 with a total tonnage of 362,439 were under the British Flag, 10 Hansa Line vessels with a total tonnage 83,132 and 8 Japanese with a total tonnage of 50,340 entered and cleared the ports of Muscat and Matrah. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows To Bombay and Karachi:— Rs. A. 0 14 per bag. 11 0 per ton of 20 cwts. 0 per ton of 40 c.ft. 0 per bundle. 1 per crate. &gt; per bundle. Dry Dates Wet Dates Wet Dates in cases . Dry Fish in bundles Pomegranates in crates Wool in bundles Cotton in bundles Cotton piece-goods and woollen goods To Colombo :— Wet Dates Wet Dates in cases . Dry Fish in bundles To United States of America : Wet Dates in cases . To London :— Wet Dates in cases 11 11 1 1 7 3 8 per bundle. 14 0 per ton of 40 c. ft. 24 4 per ton of 20 cwts. 24 4 per ton of 20 cwts. 33 0 per ton of 20 cwts. £ s. d. 3 0 0 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c.ft. 2 17 6 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c.ft. PART n. (A) Trade. General conditions .—was an improvement m the import and export trade during the year under review. The following comparative table shows the value of imports and exports for the years 1935-36 and I / • Imports . Exports . 1935-36. 1936-37. Increase(-|-) Decrease(—). Rs. Rs. Rs. 38,37,835 44,65,861 + 6,28,026 32,64,948 32,41,641 — 24,297The imports show an increase of Rs. 6,28,026 which is due to the increase in the imports of rice, sugar and textiles. The exports show a decrease of Rs. 87,158 but this is due chiefly to the drop in the value of silver coins as compared with the year 1935-36. There- the export figures are satisfactory since the c imodities exported are more as compared with those during the year 1935-36. This decrease in exports is shown by the following figures :— Silver coins Dry Dates Sardines . Dry Fish 1935-36. 1936-37. Increase(+) Decrease^—). Rs. Rs. Rs. 9,42,992 3,67,400 —5,75,592 6,33,921 6,99,740 +65,819 1,18,265 1,88,566 +70,301 2,68,308 7,20,622 +3,52,314 As in the past, rice, sugar and textiles formed the principal articles of import. India continues to be the sole supplier of cereals, and there was an increase in the import of rice by Rs. 45,765 over the last year. Soft sugar continues to be imported from Java. Foreign competition. —Japan continues to strengthen her position in the market and is the chief competitor in the field of piecegoods as the following table of the value for the years 1935-36 and 1936-37 will show :— 1935-36. 1936-37. Rs. Rs. India . 2,02,931 1,66,138 United Kingdom 40,550 28,776 Japan . . . 5,52,887 5,76,868 China 96,202 1,47,900 Other Countries 39,150 1,484 Total . 8,48,549 9,21,166 Artificial silk goods are exclusively Japanese and are remarkable as much for their attractive and varied patterns as for their astonishing cheap ness. The following table of the value for the years 1935-36 and 1936-37 will show that a cheap brand of Japanese cement is making progress against the Indian and United Kingdom commodity :— 1935-36. 1936-37. United Kingdom Japan Rs. Rs. 4,073 14,866 27,529 Other lines in which Japanese goods predominate on account of their cheapness are canvas rubber shoes, enamelware, chinaware, glassware, hosiery and matches. Imports from Germany decreased from Rs. 39,527 in the previous year to Rs. 17,348 in the year under report, the chief articles imported being imitation whiskey, brandy, lubricating oil, stationery, perfu mery, hardware and lampware. China who was a new comer in the silk market with a total of Rs. 95,977 in the previous year, shows an increase to Rs. 1,47,900 in the year under review. Over-trading. —No over-trading was noticeable during the year under review. Commercial morality. —Generally speaking was sound. (B) Financial. Ready money. —Money was easy during the year. Bankruptcy. —No insolvency cases were filed during the year, which shows that the financial position of the merchants was comparatively sound. Banks. —Banks being non-existent all transac tions are met by hundis (drafts) on India. (C) Agriculture. The cotton cultivation near the Saham District has been satisfactory from an agricultural point of view though financially the experiment has shown a loss. As pointed out in previous years’ Trade Reports modern methods of irrigation and culti vation are altogether unknown to the Omani. Dates growing by primitive methods is the real industry of the country on the Batinah seaboard and in the Oman, while limes, pomegranates, mangoes, tobacco, sugarcane (very small quan tities for local consumption) and Luban, a resin of the alder tree used as a substitute for frankincense and grown in the province of Dhofar, constitute the principal products of the country. (D) Industry. A small local industry exists in Matrah for the manufacture of turbans and loin cloths which are exported to Aden, Zanzibar and East Africa. The weaving is done on hand-looms in various Baluch homes but is merely a cottage industry. No machi nery is employed and no State encouragement is given. (E) Communication and Transport. State of communications generally .—Transport along the coastal towns is still carried out by sailing vessels and remains the cheapest means of convey ance. Light cars can run some 280 miles up the Batinah Coast to Kalba but the unsuitability of the existing tracks for anything in the nature of lorry traffic precludes any attempt to introduce road transport for commercial purposes. The only properly constructed road in the country is between the towns of Muscat and Matrah on which motor cars ply daily.4 Transport rates by car. Name of town. No. of Miles. Rate per trip. K8. A. p. Muscat to Matrah 21 1 8 0 „ Bait-al-Falaj . 31 3 0 0 „ Wutaiyeh 10 4 0 0 „ Sib 36 12 0 0 „ Birka 56 15 0 0 „ Musna 731 20 0 0 ,, Suwaiq . 87 25 0 0 ,, Khabura 110 35 0 0 ,, Saham . 128 40 0 0 ,, Sahar 144 50 0 0 „ Kids-el-Hasa 165 55 0 0 „ Murair-el-Matarish 192 65 0 0 Air Service. —Imperial Airways have an aerodrome which is a refuelling station on the Makran Coast at Gwadur, a possession of the State of Muscat. The Air Route passes over the Sultan’s territory approxi mately half-way between Muscat and Ras Musandam, but has only an emergency landing ground on the mainland. (F) Social. Standard of Living. —The majority of the indi genous population is completely poverty ridden and live a hand to mouth existence, generally incum bered with debt. They subsist chiefly by fishing and on the date harvest. In most cases a date crop is mortgaged a year in advance to speculative exporters and the cultivator rarely derives the full benefits of his toil. Like many impoverished people the local inhabitant is hardy but spend-thrift and expending what he has, has little heed for the morrow. Employment. —Un-employment in the main towns of Muscat and Matrah is rife. Public Health and Hygiene. —Hygiene and sanita tion are conspicuous by their absence. Various forms of eye and skin diseases and malaria abound everywhere. The fish and meat markets and slaughterhouses in both the towns of Muscat and Matrah undertaken during the years 1935-36 were completed during the period under review. Municipality .—A municipality exists in name but has neither the funds nor the administrative ability to effect any improvements. R. P. Watts, Major, Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat. Date Trade of Muscat. One of the two main products of the Sultanate of Muscat is dates. These are grown both in the interior of Oman proper and in groves extending northwards for some 150 miles along the Eastern littoral from a point approximately 30 miles north of Matrah. This area is known as the Batinah. 2. The dates may be divided into two categories, viz., (a) wet and (6) dry. The former comprise the following varieties (1) Fard. (7) Khassab. (2) Khanisi. (8) Farfarah. (3) Burni. (9) Barshi. (4) Hanzal. (10) Nagal. (5) Abu-Naranj. (11) Madluki. (6) Khalas. (12) Hawami. whilst the latter consist of :— (1) Mubsali. (2) Gash Abunaranj. (3) Hamzal. (4) Hawami. 3. Fard dates, which are of premier quality, are mostly the produce of Oman proper. They fetch high prices and are exported to both the United Kingdom and the United States of America. 4. Inferior uality dates such as :— (1) Hilali. (2) Muzarib. (3) Sarma. (4) Zabid. (5) Muzang. (6) Gash-Barash. (7) Sidi. (8) Nagal Hilali. (9) Gaeh-Mushfah. (10) Slyibrut. (11) Ainbukar. (12) Nizad. are more generally used for local consumption, but small quantities find their way to the Trucial Oman and South-East Arabian Ports. Dry dates are chiefly exported to India. 5. The date harvesting season extends from July to September and the first consignments usually leave Muscat about mid-August. 6. Wet dates on arrival from the interior are deli vered in Matrah where they are selected, pressed and packed in boxes of 12 lbs. and 108 lbs. each. Some are also packed in cartons which in turn are packed in wooden boxes containing 100—115 lbs. net. The date trade is practically in the hands of the Indian trading community, many of whom also act as commission agents for the producers. 8. The prices of dates is quoted by the Bhar (equi valent to 1,800 lbs.) except when packed in boxes or packets.yj i 1 . ( I 8727 i 1930 w£ U rj \ _ «» * .» Muscat No. 823-242 of 1936, dated the Letter from the Political Agent and H^Ma.e^ Consul, Muscat, I have the honour to forward two copies of my Report on the Trade and Commerce of Muscat for the year ms-Bd, the original of which has been sent to the Foreign Office, London. A copy has been sent to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire. It is requested that 24 printed copies may be sent to me. enclosure in INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Lettar No 2 2 7 W * 1 Dated IfY;: i n\ i ‘arf 1Report on the Trade of Muscat for the year 1935-36. part i. General description of the Sultanate of Muscatt Muscat is the capital of the Independent Sultanate of that name situated on the Eastern Coast of Arabia. With the exception of a small strip on the east coast of the Musandum Peninsula between Dibba and Khor Kalba, which is under the independent control of minor Shaikhs, the sea-board of the Sultanate extends in the north from Tibat, on the western shores of the Musandum Peninsula, to Has Dharbat Ali in the south, situated some 290 miles due north of the extreme westerly point of Socotra Island. In land the Sultanate extends to the borders of the Rub-al-Khah or to give it its local name—the Great Desert. Of late years the Omanis have become autonomous, the writ of the Sultan merely runs throughout a coastal belt varying in depth from some 16 to 30 miles. The interior is for the most part mountainous, the main ranges running approximately parallel to the sea coast with barren, rocky oSshoots extending in places down to the sea. The higher inland ranges, with a comparatively good rainfall, are wooded in places and generally fertile. The sea coast for some 190 miles north-west of Muscat is known as the Batinah. It consists of a fertile strip covered for some 100 miles of its length with extensive date groves. The remainder of the coast line within the limits of the Sultanate are barren and forbidding, with the notable exception of Dhofar in the extreme south. This southern province of Dhofar extends from Murbat in the east to Ras Dharbat Ah in the west, and is bounded on the north by the Cura mountains. Being well within reach of the monsoon rains a ad being blessed with several perennial streams, tais area, particularly round Salalah, is extremely fertile. The town of Muscat, once important and pros perous, has given place to the adjoining, port of Matrah as the trade centre and focus of commercial dealings with the Batinah and the interior. Muscat however still continues to be the seat of Government and the capital of the Sultanate. Currency. The currency of the country is the Maria Theresa dollar and the copper coin, known as the Baiza, minted in 1895 to the order of His Highness the Sultan. In Muscat and Matrah, sovereigns, Indian currency notes and rupees are generally accepted, but the dollar is the only currency recognised in the interior. The Maria Theresa dollar fluctuates in value considerably, being affected by the world price of silver, by the local demand in the date season, and by the state of the Bahrain pearl market. Trade accounts are kept in Mohammadis and Gajh, hypothetical units of which the former com prises two species, the black and the white. The latter is used as a basis of calculation in wholesale transactions, whilst the black Moham- madi, twenty and a half of which constitute a dollar, is used for petty retail trade. Most hundis from India show their face value in Mohammadis and not in rupees. 20 Gajh . ... 1 Mohammadi. 11^ Mohammadis . ♦ • 1 Dollar. 100 Mohammadis . . • 1 Toman. Exchange Rate. Exchange for 100 Maria Theresa Dollars. 1933-34. 1934-36. 1935-36. Be. a. p. Es. A. P. Be. A. P. Highest bazaar rate . &lt; 96 0 0 114 4 0 149 0 0 Lowest bazaar rate . 85 0 0 90 0 0 118 0 0 Average bazaar rate . 90 8 0 101 0 0 132 0 0 Weights and Measures. The weights used in the Customs Department prescribed in Muscat, Matrah and the Coast towns are , . . . The weight of 6 dollars or 5*9375 ozs. 1 Kiyas • • 24 Kiyas • • Id Muscat Maunds 200 Muscat Maunds 1 Muscat Maund. 1 1’arasalah. 1 Bahar.2 Rice is sold by the bag; other cereals by the following measures :— 20 Palis 1 Farrah. 20 Farrahs . . • *1 Khandi. The rupee which weights one tola and the dollar of which the weight is called “ Auqia ” are used for weighing drugs and perfumes. One “ Auqia equals eight “ Misqals Measures (Linear). 1 Shibr .... 1 Hand or 4£ inches. 4 Shibrs . . . . 1 Dhira or cubit. 4 Dhiras .... 1 Ba’ or fatbom. Legislation. The Government of the Sultanate is conducted by the Sultan and is of the oriental type tempered by Treaty for the benefit of British subjects over whom the local authorities have no jurisdiction. The heads of the various State Departments carry out their administrative duties under the orders of His Highness and the Walis (or Governors) in charge of districts are directly responsible to the Sultan. Civil and Criminal Courts are presided over by a Chief Justice, but cases against British subjects are tried by the Political Agent on principles _ of law adopted from British India. Cases of British subjects and Protected persons against Muscat subjects are decided in the Muscat Courts, in which the right of Consular representation is held and exercised. Customs. Customs duties on imports are at present levied at the rate of 5 per cent, ad valorem on foodstuffs and general merchandize, 10 per cent, on certain goods classified as coming under the category of “ luxuries ” and 20 per cent, on liquors containing alchohol of the strength of 55° Under Proof or more. There is no duty levied on goods exported from the State but produce from the interior brought into the Coastal towns for sale or export is charged with an octroi duty of 5 per cent. In all districts subject to the Muscat Govern ment’s authority the ancient Islamic tax known as “ Zakat ” of 5 per cent, ad valorem, is enforced on the principal products of the country, in this case limes, dates and firewood. The revenues derived from Customs and the above taxes constitute the main source of the State’s income. Population. No regular census of the population of Muscat and Matrah has been taken but a rough computa tion fixes the figures at 4,500 and 8,500 respectively. The large majority of the Indian trading commu nity consisting of Khojas and Banias which formerly inhabited Muscat has since moved to Matrah where greater facilities exist for direct trade with the interior. Shipping. The principal Steamship Lines which called at Muscat and Matrah during the year under report were as follows :— (1) The British India Steamship Navigation Co., Ltd. (2) The Strick Line of Steamers. (3) The EHerman &amp; Bucknall Steamship Co.&gt; Ltd. (4) The Hansa Line of Steamers. (5) The Yamashita Steamship Co., Ltd. 165 steamers of all nationalities aggregating 613,473 tons entered and cleared these ports during the year ending 31st March 1936. Of these 133 with a total tonnage of 396,047 were under the British Flag, 20 (Hansa Line) vessels with a total tonnage of 155,898, 10 Japanese with a total ton nage of 51,488 and 1 Norwegian with 10,040 tons, entered and cleared the ports of Muscat and Matrah. Freight. Freights ruling during the year were as follows :— To Bombay and Karachi:— Dry Dates . Wet Dates . Wet Dates in cases Dry Fish in bundles Pomegranates in crate . Raw wool Cotton Cotton piece-goods and woollen goods . To Colombo :— Dry Fish Wet Dates . To London:— Wet Dates in bags or in cases Rs. A. 0 14 per bag. 11 0 per ton of 20 cwts. 17 0 per ton of 40 c. ft. 1 0 per bundle. 1 0 per crate. 7 8 per bundle. 3 8 per bundle. 14 0 per ton of 40 o. ft. 33 0 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c. ft. 33 0 per ton of 20 cwts. £ s. d. 2 17 6 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c. ft. To United States of America :— Wet Dates in bags or in cases . . .3 0 0 per ton of 20 cwts. or 40 c. ft.w* '~*A, 3 PART n. (A) Trade. General Conditions. —There was an improvement in import and export trade during the year under , review. The following comparative table shows the value of Imports and Exports for the years 1934-35 and 1935-36 : 1934-35. 1935-36. Increase. Rs. Rs. Rs. Imports . 36,13,716 38,37,835 2,24,119 Exports . . 25,61,387 32,64,948 7,03,561 The imports show an increase of Rs. 2,24,119 which is due to increase in the imports of textiles, wheat flour, tea, spices, twist yarns and oils. Exports show an increase of Rs. 7,03,561 but this is due solely to the exports of Maria Theresa Dollars to the value of Rs. 7,86,042 and Specie and Silver Krans to the value of Rs. 1,12,400. Other wise a decrease of exports of the usual commodities is shown compared with last year. This decrease in exports is shown by the following figures :— 1934-35. 1935-36. Decrease. Rs. Rs. Rs. Dry Dates . 11,22,715 7,13,330 4,09,385 Wet Dates . 2,64,373 2,37,084 57,289 Dried Fish . 4,06,006 1,43,785 2,62,221 I The decrease in the value of dates is due to the lower prices ruling than last year, while the ship ment of dried fish heavily declined as a result partly of the Italo-Abyssinian war but chiefly on account of the refusal of the chief importer, Germany, to take any of this produce except on a barter basis which for Muscat has been found to be impracticable. At the close of the year large stocks of dried fish were on hand in the local warehouses and if these cannot be disposed of severe losses will be suffered by the merchants concerned. As in the past, rice, coffee, textiles, spices and sugar formed the principal articles of import. India continues to be the sole supplier of cereals, though the import of rice was less by Rs. 94,409 than last year. Soft sugar is imported from Java, loaf sugar from Belgium and Saffron from Spain. Foreign Competition. —Japan continues to strength en her position in the market and is the chief com petitor in the field of piece goods as the following table of the value for the years 1934-35 and 1935-36 will show :— 1934-35. 1935-36. Rs. Rs. India . 1,22,123 2,02,931 United Kingdom 36,215 40,550 Japan . 5,33,623 5,52,887 China. 87,739 96,202 Other Countries . 68,849 39,150 Total . 8,48.549 9,31,720 Artificial silk goods are exclusively Japanese and are remarkable as much for their attractive and varied patterns as for their astonishing cheapness. The following table of the value for the years 1934-35 and 1935-36 will show that a cheap brand of Japanese cement is making progress against the Indian Porbundar cement:— 1934-35. 1935-36. Rs. Rs. India .... 38 413 Japan .... 11,328 14,866 Other lines in which Japanese goods predominate on account of their cheapness are canvas rubber shoes, enamelware, chinaware, glassware, hosiery and matches. Imports from Germany which amounted to Rs. 29,979 in the previous year, increased to Rs. 39,527 in the year under review, the chief articles imported being imitation whisky, brandy, lubricating oil, stationery, perfume, hardware and lampware. China who was a new comer in the silk market i with a total of Rs. 60,679 in the previous year, shows an increase to Rs. 95,977 in the year under review. Overt-rading. —No over-trading was noticeable during the year under review. Commercial morality. —Generally speaking is sound. (B) Financial. Ready-money. —Money was easy during the year. Bankruptcy. —No insolvency cases were filed during the year. This shows that the financial | position of the merchants was comparatively sound. Banks. —Banks being non-existent all transactions are met by hundis (drafts) on India. (C) Agriculture. As an experiment, cultivators this year near the Saham District have been supplied with free cotton seeds. Apart from this, no further efforts appear to have been made to improve the agriculture or the irrigation of the country. As pointed out in the last year’s Trade Report modern methods of irrigation and cultivation are altogether unknown to the Omani. Datei growing by primitive methods is the real industry of the country on the Batinah seaboard and in the Oman, while limes, pomegranates, mangoes, tobacco, sugar cane (very small quantities for local consumption) and Luban, a resin of the alder tree used as a substitute for frankincense and grown in the province of Dhofar, constitute the principal products of the country. (D) Industry. A small local industry exists in Matrah for the manufacture of turbans and loin cloths which are</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001f5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2958</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001f5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2958</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/6 'Muscat: Trade: Annual Reports 1924-'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-06T22:01:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (290 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 293; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains reports on the trade of Muscat for the years 1924-25 through to 1939-40, and for 1942-43. The reports were prepared by the Political Agent, Muscat, and consisted of a short prose introduction followed by tables of trade statistics. Some correspondence concerning the distribution and confidentiality of the report is contained within the file. Correspondents include the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, India Office, Department of Overseas Trade, High Commissioner for India, and the Official Secretary to the Commonwealth of Australia.The reports for the years 1940-41 and 1941-42 are not contained within the file and according to a manuscript note (folio 5) were never received at the India Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign Secretary</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Department of Overseas Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>International trade</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001f5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>