<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00036d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T13:53:29.554Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Translation of letter dated 4:tn Sdawal 1356(7tii December 1937) from Sbaikii ’Abdullah bin Qasim Al Thani, C-I.E., Ruler of ,atar, to the Hon’ble Lieut-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle,KCIE*, CBE., Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. After Compliments. % With reference to the conversation which took place between us on your arrival at Dohah on the 7th December 1937 and the request which I made to you for the arms which I contemplate importing from abroad, I should be grateful if you would kindly sena me a No Objection Certificate for 500 rifles and 500 rounds of ammunition for each rifle. 400 rifles, out of these, should have ammunition of the same pattern,i.e., 3.3 as you directed, and that I should select the other 100 rifles which are specially for me from any suitable pattern as was decided in the said conversation. I request you to expedite sending the No Objection Certificate in question to enable me to import them as 1 have no suitable arms in my possession and am in need of them. Usual Ending* LConfidential. No. C/906-1.a/5 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—- The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Qulf, Bushire• and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). I 2 !* v i e /^ of the correspondence loading up to the Resident's ?^. C/62 dated the llth April 1937 to the Shaikh of n a tar, the Shaikh s present letter possibly does not contain a correct account of the recent conversation at Dohah. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 14Deceml:)e r 1937. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. tetter dated the 4th Shawal 1356 (7th December 1937) from the Shaikh of Qatar to the Political Resident in the Persian Culf. Subject. Arms for Qatar.Confident!al .882-3 of 1937. British Residency «5c Consulate-Cieneral, Buahire. the 23r4 December, 1937. Memorandum • V • the Shaikh of 1 enclose herewith a letter for tar, which explains itself, and which please forward to him. Copy is enclosed for your file • 2. If the Shaikh agrees to ray proposal, and gives you the necessary details, please report to me with your recommendations . sd. T.C.Fowls. Political resident in the Persian Ctalf. At te sted . for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian uulf. LJks3 ‘La jSo- t r-' V i AV r_ &lt; ~C-' ~! * ‘-J o^-*J ^ LJ U^^r. 1 £)_,) ’*_yJ i (j~ f , (j— . (j-i &lt;5&gt; * -s' —* «• -»&lt;-«— o LsJtu- I J'j I &lt;&gt; J / Llf^J tu / fl* J I^J * t cJ cJ^&gt; _ &gt;| _^J , ^&gt;1 J-I Is* lL'l* ,SI r^^LL) 3 &gt; LaJ^, x / L/J ^ y^' / VC'o'i &gt; /X Translation of letter dated 8tn Dliul v*aaa 1356(10-1-1938)from Shaikh f Abdullah bin .^asim al Thani, C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar, to Mr. H.Weightman, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. i was very glad to meet you on your visit to Doha, and have to offer my gratitude to you for your kinaness ana excellent manners, i hope tnat you have daa a very comfortable journey down to Bahrain. ••itn reference to our conversation on tne subject of the arms which 1 contemplate to import, i have written to the Political Resident regarding 5U rifles of the type desired by me and 1 have no objection to the rest being of the type whicn can fit with 303 rounds to whicn His Honour referred, fou will find enclosed a letter for His Honour. I request tnat you may be good enough to sene me a Eo Objection Certificate for tne arms about which I wrote to His Honour after obtaining his aavice on the subject. I would tnen let you nave the type ol the 50 rifles which I wish to keep as t special weapongfor me. Usual Ending.Trpnslation of letter da tea 8txi Dhul i^aaa 13b6(lUtn January 1937)from Shaikh T Abdullan bin Qasim al Tham, G.I.h., Ruler of ,atar, to The Honourable Lieut-Coionel Sir Trenchara Fowle K.C.I.E., C.B.E., Political Resiaent in the Persian Gulf. After Compliments. ^ I have been honour/^a by the receipt of your letter datea 23rd December 1937 equivalent to 19tn Shawal 13b and noted what you have mentioned regarding tne arms, about which I spoke to you on your visit to Doha. I informed you that it was necessary for me to have 100 rifles of the type desired by me and suitable for me if it was not possible for me to get the whole quantity. You replied that you would think over the matter and 1 felt sure then that you will sent me a No Objection Certificate for the same m view of my neei ol special arms suitable for me which I have already disclose' to you. You informed me in your letter under reference that you agree to 20 rifles only which is a small quantity in comparison with my requirement. I, therefore, request you, i view of the special friendship existing between your Honour ana myself, to agree to bo rifles, if not to 100 , of the tyq desired by me. 1 have no objection to the rest being of the type which can fit with 303 round. I, therefore, re L uest y. to write to our iriend the Political Agent, Bahrain, on tae subject and ask him to send me a No Objection Certificate ft 50 rifles separately ol the type desired by me with boo rou oi ammunilion for each rifle ana also another No Objection Certificate for 4bo^riiles)ot the type which can fit with 333 rounds oi ammunition, to which you had ref erred, wi tli buO rou of ammunition for each rifle. i shall be extremely grateful to you for your kind attention ana i have a sanguine hope that you will ac&lt; to my request. Usual ending.C/48-1.a/5 ,/ t I l No. The* Political Agent, Bahrain, presents liis compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). 2. Our main object has now been assured in that 450 rifles are to be .303 bore, and I see no particular harm in increasing the num ber of non-.303 rifles from 20 to 50. It will be possible to delay the issue of a No Objection Certificate for them until the .303s have been ordered. As I understand the Shaikh’s lexter he has left the selection of the make of .303s to the Political Resident. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian G-ulf. Dated dam ary 1938. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency memorandum No. 882-3 dated the 23rd December 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Pi Letter dated the 8th Dhul Oada 1356 OlOth January 1938) from the Shaikh of Qatar to the Hon’ble the Politi cal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject. Arms for Qatar.CON F10 £N' I’l A L. &gt; T/T i 1 GOVEENMENl’ OF iNDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N.B % This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use oj the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and formalities it is woraed and signed as if it had been so despatched,] i’fcoaa I* Political Agent, Kuwait. 2 &gt;|: 1 The Hon*1316 the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. 7th January M3q 4 SUBJECT: - Nasr 'bin Jasim hin Thani. On the 5th January, Nasr 'bin Jasim “bin Thani passed through here on his way to Baghdad, for medical treatment. (He is still using crutches owing to a fall from his mare last year.) 2. According to a telegram received from rbn Saud hy his Agent here Nafisi, he was to he given every assistance at his, Ihn Saud’s, unconditional expense. The telegram did not say hy which route he was travelling. 3. He arrived hy road and he was travelling on a Saudi Arabia Certificate, No.4 of 25th Shawwal i356 (28th December 1937) issued in Hasa and showing him as a Saudi subject. 4 * He not call on the Ruler of Kuwait, but wrote him a brief note of excuse from the Nafisi *s house. /i 7 Captain, Political Agent. K S. 6.V IS- [ SJ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communioation more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and tu obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] UliiC© Of 'ti2€ PoXl'tlC&amp;JL RGSldCll't in tne Persian Gulf, No* C/12 of 1938, Camp, Kuwait. Bated Me 17 th January 1938. ifio Jj'rom Political Resident, joushire, at Kuwait^ To * Political Agent, Bahrain. V Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. my aub.lect : ^asr bin Jasim bin Thani. Reference Political Agent, Kuwait* s Express Letter Bo.C/15 of 7th January 1938. xou will see that Rasr was travelling on a Saudi Arabian certificate, which technically makes hi® a oaudi suoject. bin Baud may produce this fact, somehow or other, as an argument in favour of his claims to v^atar, out I do not see that we can do anything about it. Sd. T.C. Powle, Political Resident in the Persian &lt;julf. attested for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian sulf. 'l vt (Signature) S. 44. (Designation)16 No. jZP/9/94. n The Secretary to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to AX ac Z'i and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. $ Dated../7.... February ? _ 1936 . &gt; .D« Reference to previous correspondence : is Printed Letters Los. 54-9/1 &amp; C/48-4.a/5 of ICth end 17th January, 1^38, respectively, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. i •.T.' .etter No. 38, dated the IPth February '1938, to Lhaikh Abdullah bin Q,asim .1 Thani, CLE, Ruler of Qatar. Subject. Arms for QatarNo • 3 &amp; of 1SW. (S) . BrUlah ll«3l4enoy &amp; Oona-latt Gtntrai Buablre, 12tb Ifebruary 1938. TO k ihaikh 'A^auilah oirj ^ajim aX ly vJ • X* &amp;•» iiul«r or ^a^ar. AX't^r Uoia v iiai;atvi. iiie Honourable ttie rolltloal' Aijoiaeut haj reoelvea your letters of December 7th ana January 10th j on tht£ subjeot of the issue of ’•Ho Objeotlon Certificates* for &gt; rifles ana ammunition* He notes with pleasure that you aesire to order 450 *303 rifles together with 500 rounds of ammunition for eaoh. Jill you please confirm that the type you desire is that which was shown to you in May 1936 by Captain X. Hl3*inbotham, Political Agent Banrain, the cost of which you wwre informed would be £• 3/- plus fcttcrtoost of packing and freight. 2. The Honourable the Political Hesiaent has considered the request which you made to him regarding rifles ol the other type desired by you. He is referring to those which will not take a .303 bullet. In view of the good relations which have existed for so long between your itute and the High BritishCrOvt rumenti, iit id ^rc^artu to agree to your iiayortlng fifty rifled of that tyye in stead of twenty as previously sanotionea. hia reoeiving an oruer from you regarding tru^450 .303 rifles and ammun^pn he will cause the necessary 'Ho Objection Certificated* 1 for all the rifles of both sorts to be issued. Usual incline. heorotary to the j. critical ^ side at in the i.-erdiau Gulf.1 y CONFIDENTIAL. No. q/243 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his conapliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s).with the request that the Shaikh of qatar may be informed that in view of his remarks about the rifles shown to him by Captain Hickinbotham the Political Resident prefers to leave it to him to order the .303 rifles himself from England. That the other permit has been made out for Mauser rifles which the Political Resident presumes he re quires. If not, will he please say what make he does require• Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Dated. ..ISfch.APEiL .A?.?.?.... Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Translation of letter dated 9th Moharram 1357 (12th Feb- ruary 1938) from the Shaikh of qatar. ARMS FOR QATAR. Two No Objection Certificates (Nog.C/241 &amp; C/242 of 12/4/3aj| in triplicate.Translation of a dated Pth Moharram 1357 (Ifith FebEuary 1938) from Sheikh Abdullah bin Qasim VI Than!, Ruler of Qatar, to Cep tain Hicktnbotham, Secretary to the Honourable the Political Rea dent in the Persian ^ulf* After Compliments. I haa the honour of receiving your letter dated 12th February 1938 corresponding to 11th Dhii-Hejjah 1356 and I thank you very much for what stated by you with regard to the arras sb out which i have menti oned to the Honourable tue Political ^ea dent in the Persian Gulf who stated that the type desired by me should be that already shown to me by Csjptai-a Hickinbothara. I have al rea&lt;iy stated to His Honour that I want a good type which suits rae and meets my requirement. And as His Honour considers that referred to by you is a good tvpe, I see no other alternative but to agree with nis Honour and yield to his selection. But I have to make some observation. The barrel of the type which I saw with Captain Hickinbothara has been affected owing to process of time, it has become wider toaftits ordinary size on account of abundance of shots fired from it, and this is the defect which I see in this rifle. And if you could get from the type you refer- -red to a good sort, the month of which has not been widened and you consider it a good one and the price which you have mentioned for it is £3/- in note, i have no objection. i should be obligee if you ^ would kindly import 450 rifle, wita 500 rounds from |\ ,' the good ones newly made, with each rifle. If it is impossible and the honourable the Political Resi- -dent in the Persian *&gt;ulf considers and agrees to my importing 450 rifles from England from‘303 type, I request/2 . revest you to send the two permits, one permit for 450 rifles which I have already mentioned about it, from tue type of '303 ana another permit for 50 rifles from the type which 1 choese and which would suit my desire from wherever may be and 500 rounds with each rifle. I hope you will oblige me by sending to me soon the said permits to enable me to import them as soon as possible. Unles you would be kind enough to import for me what I mentioned already about the 450 rifles which should be of a good quality and the price should be as stated to you £ 3/- note, I should be muSfe obliged But the other 50 rifles I suall import them myself of any type which t choose myself ana which suits my desire fron any piece which may be. uidual enaing*NO. C/241 dated the 12th April 1938 NO OBJECT I ON CISRT IF I CATS CiuHTIFIED that there is no objection to Shaikh Abdulla bin ^aaim al Thani, Kuler of ..atar, importing into ^atar via Bahrain the follov/infc arms and ammunition from England. 450 rifles .303 bore. 225,000 rounds of .303 ammunition for the above. 2* The validity of this certificate is restricted t o s iac months. for Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bahrain. Forwarded, in triplicate, to the Political Agent, Bahrain.No,C/242 dated the 12th April 1133 NO -OBJ^CTiaN C^PTI?IC^ CERTIj?IBD that there is no objection to Shaikh «Abdulla bin qasim al Thani, C.I.HS., Ruler of Qatar, importing into Qatar the following arms and ammunition via Bahrain. 50 }.Iauser rifles 7.9 m.m. bore. 25,000 rounds of 7.9 m.ra. ammunition for the above. 2. The validity of this certificate is restricted to six months. for Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Forwarded, in triplicate, to the Political Agent, Bahrain.Translation of letter dated 21st ^afar 1357 (22nd April 1333) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, i^uler of Qatar, to the Political Agent, Bahrain* I was honoured by receiving your letter dated 16th April 1933 corresponding to 15th Safar 1357 and vras acquainted with its contents. I offer my grateful thanks to you for sending the’L.o Objection Oertificate” which I asked you previously for importing arms and am very grateful to the -on*ble the Political Resident for his kindness and the assistance which he has afforded in this respect. As you have referred to the point I raised in my letter dated 3th I^oharram 1357 and stated in your letter quoted above that the non'ble the Political Resident prefers to leave the matter to me to put in the order myself, I consider that it is due to his kind attention in this matter and am most grateful for his kind appreciation. i may state for your information that the object of expressing my view was that the rifles should be good and serviceable, j. ^ now oDliged to send Salih al i-ani r to Bahrain in connection with some urgent affairs and 1 have to send him in order firstly to maxe arrangements for the importation of the said arms, secondly m connection with some special affairs concerning myself and thirdly to consult lour honour about the importation of the arms and to discuss with you certain matters which cannot be described in letters out has to be discussed verbally. 1 W ° Uld be Very ^teibl if you would very kindly assist me in getting permission for Salih to come to Bahrain, i shall be highly obliged if you do this favour to me. Salih will have to carry two rifles with him in order to select a sample out of them, with your conealtation, for the purpose of importing from England the large quantity from the type of rifles mentioned in yon letter and in the 'No Objection Certificate'. 1 would be gratefMl if you would favour me with an answer. \ ^ vU* u su al An ding.Dated the 24th April 1938. D.C. No. C/274-1.a/5 The Shaikh of Oatar has written to me asking if he may send Saleh A1 Vana' here to consult me on certain mat ters, and in particular about some rifles which v/e are allow ing him to purchase. He says that he would like Saleh to bring over two rifles with him to show to me. 2. I trust the Bahrain Government will have no objection to this. alrymple Bel^rave, Esquire, C.B.E., Auvieer to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain./ D.O. No. 402/S.F. April 25, 1938. Dear Weightman, Heference your D.O. Do. G/274-l.a/5 dated the 24th April 1938. I cannot reply to your letter without asking His Highness which I will do at once. Yours sincerely H. Weightman, Hsquire, I.G.S., Political iigent, Bahrain.e Translation of letter oatea l^itn liabi al Awwal 1357(12-5-38) from shaikh ’Abdullah bin ^asim al Tham, C.I.E., Ruler ol i^atar, to Mr.H.Weightman, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. 1 have received ^our letter No.C/280 dated 28th April 1938 corresponding to/27th Safar 1357 and understood its contents. It is necessary, in view of the present situation, to remind you again ol the second paragraph of Captain Kickinbotham’s letter fto.C/54:9-4r/l3 dated 14th July 1937 and the third paragraph of his letter No.C/563-4/13 dated 19tn July 1937 and in tdis connection I beg to refer to your letter No.C/l65 of 1938 dated 6th Marcn 1938. In view of my reliance on tde contents of tiie abovementioned paragraphs and your letter quoted above and tne existing relations between us, I wrote to you expressing my desire to send my Adviser in connection witn some afiairs which I could not entrust to someone else. I requested you to allow him to come and see you as an official messenger and I am very sorry that my desire was not accomplisded. You will undoubtedly realise what difficulty I experience by not getting in touch witn you whenever I have an important matter to consult and discuss with you through a person in whom I have confidence. I am not able to find any other person to whom I can entrust my important affairs except this person and for this reason I am very sorry for what had happened. I do not understand how the visit of an official messenger to you in connection with affairs between me and you would harm the Bahrain Government and for what reason they look on Salih with much dislike as pointed out by you . This man has not done anything other than The principles of honour require one to respect and appreciate the fulfilment of his duties and to be mindful of his responsibilities within the limit of such duties, and I think you concur with me, as a gentleman who appreciates the duties and respects tne principles of honour. After Compliments. what was necessary to do in the fulfilment of his duties.3 ! - 2 - Ag I am now unable to send Salih to Bahrain in oraer to arrange lor what I have mentioned above and to discuss matters with you I was obliged, in order to save time, to send tne two rifles with the bearer of my letter, Abduj. Aziz al liana ? so that he may show them to you and consult you about their type. I have asked him(Abdul Aziz) to enquire, if they prove suitable, about the price of each ri^le in England, taking into consideration the quantity required, and inform me on his return. abeyance until I see you as I could not get in toucn with you through my adviser. I hope that you are in the best of health and look forward to see you. Usual Ending. as regards #/** other matter^I will keep them in33 Transition ol letter Qated 12tn Rabi al A'OT/al 13bV i yasira al Than!, C.I.E., After Compliments. In view ol the present circumstances I do not like to import the arms, which I wish to oraer from hurope, via Bahrain in order to avoid any objection which may be raisec by the Bahrain Government such as demand ol' duties etc. Therefore please aevise me by which way I can more conveniently import the arms. I myself prefer Dubai unless you preler another place or know that tne - u ahrain Govern ment will not raise any objection about taxes etc, if I •C.S., Political Agent, import the arms via Bahrain. I should be grateful if you would kindly let me have your views in the matter. Usual Ending.(g) COPT 74- 5 THE E/ASTERN BANK LDilTED, A.L.No.29/139. London, 18th May, 1938. OUTWARD BILLS. The Manager, THIS ISAST -.EN BANK LTCITED, BAHRAIN. (9 r Dear Sir, B.S.A. GUHS LTD . Iiamadiately we received your cable of the 15th 14ay we continued your enquiry on behalf of HLa Jfixcellency the Ruler of Qatar to B.S*A. (June Ltd., who under date the 17th May write us as follows t- tr e thank you for your letter of yesterday’s date, and we hope to be in a position to write to you very shortly in re$urd to the supply of Rifles and Ammunition for Hie Excellency the Shaikh of Qatar. l, V*e o'oservo that you mention ivlark 7 Service Rifles, but we should quote for the Mark 3 Rifle. This is the service type and t.he ;aark 7 is not known to us. ♦Mark 7 refers, mg iiangine, to the ammunition which is the present type. ♦* 'Ve would draw your attontion to the reroarks with regerd to the mark of the Rifleu. Any quotation which we receive from 3.3*A. Onus Ltd. will be con tinued by cable us requested* Tours faithfully, «?d. Manager. Copy to H.B.Ii. *s Political iijent, 3a}irain, reference his telephone 15th May 1938. tical iijent, 3a}irain, 2 phone neaa a^o of ^(• 7f) B.S.A. Guns Ltd*| Birmingham. To/ May 24th f 1938. The Eastern Bank Ltd, 2 oc 3 Crosby Square, Bishopsgate, London,E.C.3. Dear Sirs Further to our letter of the 19th instant, we are awaiting a rep^y from the \7ar Office before being in a position to submit our quotation as we cannot, under present circumstances, promise delivery without first receiving the sanction of the Home Authorities. In the meantime we have to advise you that we have received a request direct from the Heprementation Office of the Government of Qatar for 450 Rifles, but they do not make any mention of ammunition. ...... Yours faithfully: Copy to H.3.M. *3 Political A^ent, Bahrain, re hi 3 telephone oo muni- cation of 12th Hay, 19138.(Original on file 12/15) Extract from P.A^ Note dated the 30th May 1938. NOTE ON VISIT TO DOHAH. f ** ** ** ** ** ** B. PURCHASE OF ARMS . I told him Abdul Aziz al Mana* was still in Bahrain awaiting quotations from England. T explained that the de lay was probably due to rearmament in England. He expressed gratitude for the assistance given.* ALL LCTTCRS TO ■■ A DDR CSS K D TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TKI-KGAA»&gt;HIC AODAKSS EASTERTIDE. INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) X??’ BiAhrain. Dear Sir, the &gt;i;ier of : ’Tith r^forenor© to the qn^utry for Rifloe and ^munition which we are v ivitin 3 on behalf of the abovo Rnlor, w© bavo roooived to-day the following telegran fron our London Office j your wire 29th May, Q,atar, poatin^? copy of letter giving cpiotatl ono. 'Poo involved to telegraph. ” Tron the above, v/e ah on Id. expect to receive the quotations in about five days when the^r can be banded to Taji Abdulaziz JLna to be taken by bl*i to ^etar.No. -‘V/lof 1357 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, R/Thany 2. 1357 June 1, 193o C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I am instructed by His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Alkhalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., to write to you on the subject of Abdul Aziz Al Mana who came from Qattar on 13th May 1938 with messages from the Shaikh of ^attar to you. His Highness approved of his coming in the capacity of an official messenger but His Highness is surprised to find that Abdul Aziz is still in Bahrain and has not returned to matter. Furthermore it has come to His Highness ! s ears that Abdulaziz is making large purchases of goods in the bazaars and is frequenting places where the public assemble and discussing the political situation which exists between Bahrain and Qattar. His Highness thinks that this is undesirable. His Highness enquires whether the presence of Abdul Aziz in Bahrain is required by you and asks that —- 2 - that if you do not require him here he should return to his own country. If it is essential for you that he should stay here His Highness considers it necessary to keep him under observation. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government/ \r Quotations received from B.S.A.Guns Ltd, Birmingham, as per their letter dated 31st May, 1938• 450 British Service •SOG” S*M.L«E*Rifles« Mark III Pattern with Cut-off and Fixed Cap Backsight. Stocks to be Oiled Finish, as usual. 250,000 Mark VII Cartridges suitable for the above Rifles. // £• 7.12.6 each. £• 7.17.6 per 1000 . 250.000 Cartridges t Can be made in 2 months @ 7.17.6 per 1000 todays rate equals Rs. 106-10-6 per 1000. » ! 450 Rifles; Can be made at the rate of 25 each week^ / §£.?-12-6 each Rifle &amp; todays rate equal Rs. 103-4-0 each.'' All C.I.F. Bahrain. Rupee / Sterling rate liable to fluctuation«INDIA OFFICS; EXPRI1SS IiITTDR (A 15 MAIL). From Secretary of State for India To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 5 repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department and Political Agent, Bahrein. Dated 8th June, 1938. telegram No.1091 of 50th March 1937 on the subject of Arms for Qatar. . 2; War Office report that B.S.A.Guns Limited have received an enquiry from the Government of Qatar to quote for the supply of 450 Rifles L.E.Short Mark III to standard War Office specification and 250,000 rounds of .303 ammunition. 3. Please telegraph whether you see any objection to Company accepting the order if placed with them. No.P.Z.3990/38. Please refer/to the correspondence ending with my The issue of the above has been duly authorised. (Sgd.) J. P, GIBSC» — T — jj L^J J^^'L c5 ^ i I ^y •w&gt; &gt;il wfi s r- LpL -‘ •l 3^^ J j iU, ^•1 yv—♦ 1 ^ ■ o^ o • LT^J l ,y Lj Up^j^ 5 Jj J J l* - 2 - actually informed the Shaikh of Dubai that you, my friend, have been given a permit to import these rifles and ammu nition via Dubai. I presume you will send an agent there at the time when they are expected to arrive. 3. If you wish my assistance in any other way in regard to’these rifles I should only be too glad to help you as much as I can. I trust you are in good health and that all is well with everyone in Qatar* Usual Ending* Political Agent, Bahrain.f s Political Agent t Bahrain* f Dear Sir, His Excellency Shaikh Abdulla bin Qasim A1 Than!, C.I*E* Huler of Qatar* tsssxssxsassKas ;ss esc 2ssc ss i With raference to the order for 450 Rifle* and 250,ooo round* of ammunition which has been placed through us with B.S.a. Guns Ltd. London, we have to state that we have just received a letter fron the Shaikh in which he indicates his preference that the arms and amauni- tions be shipped to Dubai instead of to Bahrain, as this would be con siderably cheaper* xt i H ® ha3 alS0 3mt us one copy of the No-Objection Certificate No.C/241 of 12th April, 1936, issued by The Honourable The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, the validity of which will expire on l*-th October, 1938. This Certificate restricts the import of the goods into Qatar via Bahrain and, further, the authorised anount of the anminition is 225,000 rounds and not 250,000 whiAis the amount which hue been under discussion between us and your goodself and the *»*&gt;•»*► Shaikh’s representative since the patter was first opened. In the terms of the quotation from the Manufacturers, they state that the aimunition can be supplied within .About 6-8 weeks after re ceipt of the order, but that the delivery of the/ cannot be comenced un^il at leeat 25 weeks after the receipt of the order, and thereafter can only be given at the rate of 25 rifles per week. Under the circum stances, the No-Objection Certificate will require modifications : 1. To cover the import of the goods into Qatar via Bahrain and/or via Dubaii 2. To allow for the validity of the Certificate to cover the whole period of time which may be taken in executing the order and shipping it to its destination: and 3. To allow for the increase in the amount of the aciiunition to 250,000 rounds. The N6-0bjection Certificate is enclosed herewith and we shall. be grateful if an amended Certificate might be granted in favour of His«*i 2 *8 Political Agent, Behrain, 18th June, 1936. Excellency the Ruler of Qatar and a copy handed to us as soon as possible for despatch to the Manufacturers. Yours faithfully, Manager. 3 .Confidential « No. 0/404-1.a/5 Political Agency t Bahrain f the 21st June 1938. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Care of Postmaster Karachi. Memorandum , Ln With reference to your No Objection Certificate, No. C/241 d^tred the 12th April 1938, for 450 .303 rifles and ammu nition for the Shaikh of Qatar, I have ventured to make out a fresh certificate with one year’s validity, as the B.S.A. Com pany can only begin supplies in six months time. I have also made it good for import via Dubai in view of the difficulties of import via Bahrain. 2. I trust that this action will be approved. Political Agent, Bahrain.5 ^ No. C/403 PolltlGal Agency| Bahrain, the 20th JUne 1933. SO.QM.-CTXck. CKHTIFIED that there is no objection to Shaikh 1 Abdallah bln Qasim al Than!, C.I.E., Buler of Qatar, importing into Oatar via Bahrain or T)ubai the following arms and ammunition from England. 450 rifles .303 bore 225,000 rounds of .300 ammunition for the above. 2. The validity of this certificate is restricted to one year. Political Agent. Bahrain, (On behalf of) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. q &lt;5No. C/412-1.a/5 5 I /SC Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd tTtme 1938. To The Manager, The iSastern Bank Limited, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, /F 1 //-HP With reference to your letter of the 18th June re garding importation of certain arms and ammunition by the Shaikh of Qatar, under cover of which you returned No Ob jection Certificate No. C/241 of 12th April 1938 for amend ment, I enclose two copies of a fresh No Objection Certifi- cate providing for Importation via Bahrain or Dubai and have extended the validity to cover a period of one year from its date of issue. ^ ^ 2. I am unable to increase the quantity of ammunition. Yours faithfully, d- for Political Agent, Bahrain.to Political Agent, 'Bahrain, re our letter of date e 18th June 38 His Excellency Shaikh Abdulla Kasslm A1 Thanl, C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar, ^atar. Your i&amp;cellancy, We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated 8th June (10th Rabia Than!) and we have debited your current account with Us. 10,000 and have remitted the equivalent in sterling, £1,331.7.2 to our Lon don Office in connection with your order for 450 Rifles and 250,000 rounds of amunition. from B.S.A. Guns Ltd. London. We have to-day received from your re presentative the No-Objection Certificate from the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, but as the Certificate restricts the shipment to Bahrain, gives the amount of ammunition as 225,000 instead of 250,000 rounds, and as it is only available for six months which will not be sufficient for this order, we have returned it to the Political Agent and asked him to issue a fresh ^ertifi-cate in your iSxcallency’s natis and head it to us as soon as possible. As soon as this is received, we shall place the order with Messrs. B. S. A. Guns Ltd. Meanwhile, we have advised than that you wish the shipment to be C.I.F. Dubai and that you are accepting their quota tion. Wo have the honour to bo Your iSatcellency’s Most Obedient Servants, Manager| ^ f s Political Agont, *e our letter of date. JV Haji 3caah Sul sin an A1 liana, Keprotentative to His Excellency the .H&gt;iler of '^atar, Bali rain. Dear Haji Suloh, Thank you for your letter No.7/269 of 17th June. On L”th June we adTiaed our London Office to infom Mauare, B.3.n.. Gune Ltd. that Hi® jixcelloncy v*na accepting thotf r quotation and that the No-Objection Certi ficate txxm the Honoural)l« the Political Resident in tho Persian Oulf would follow in due course with our confirmation of your oreor. On reeding the No—Objection Certificate which you sont ua, we found ; !• xhnt it ic 'mlid only for six months and so will not cover the tine nece ssary for tho execution of the order. 2. That it restricts the ahipiaont to Bahrain. 6. ihat the authorised anount of ucuiuni- tion is shewn as 225,000 ro'inds and not 850,000 round 3 i and we have therefore returned the Certi ficate to the Political Agency in Bahrain •r2 t- for anendraent and it will be sent to B.S.A. Guns Ltd. with the order as soon as we re ceive it back. Yours faithfully, Manager. \ ■ VTranslation of letter dated 25tn mbi al Tliani 1357(24-6-1938) from Shaikh ’Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar, to Mr. H.Weightman, Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. I have received your esteemed letter No.C/383 of 1938 dated 13th June 1938 corresponding to 14tn Rabi al Thani 1357 and was acquainted with its contents regarding the rifles and ammunition which I wisn to import. I am grateful to you for the assistance which you have rendreu in this matter. The Manager cd of the Eastern Bank has communicat/to me the details which he had received from London about this and I have already sent him the / / 7 Permit as directed by you and received a reply from him saying that he has received the Permit but that it does not serve the purpose as its validity is restricted to 6 months which period is not enough for the order to be complied with. Also it has been mentioned that the importation is to be made via Bahrain whereas it has now been decided that the importation should be made via Dubai. A request for 250,000 rounds of ammunition was made but the Permit contair^only 225, ,000 rounds. I was informed by the Manager of tne Bank that he forwarded the Permit to you to be corrected as desired. I trust that you have returned the Permit to the Manager of the Bank duly corrected, for which I shall be extremely grateful to you. It was mentioned in the details sent by the Company from Birmingham that steps would not be taken to provide the arms until alter 25 weeks alter the receipt of the order. As this will cause considerable delay to the achievement of my object, I should be obliged ii you would kindly help me in making some arrangements so that the order would be taken in hand earlier and I may get them(arms)soon. I have informed the Manager of the Eastern Bank that the arms s will be imported via Dubai. I tnank you most sincerely lor talking to the Ruler of Dubai about this matter and I am doing as you have suggested. i! U sual Ending.33ESH — T ll ( ^4^* ^ J L&lt;c^ jJLiw iS {y* j A^viaP V Laa* I L^«JLfr &lt;Lfcg_nJ 1 (&gt; H#I * i?***' ^ J -* ^ (^r* o»» l* ^ i^iSyLJI a;jJj U j^jI r-f** ft'jfi t - *! 4 ' x * j?j£ \ ^ &gt; ^■*‘** 0 ^ —- ! J o^ i#6 j ^I^L&gt;-I J j^jL ji-^jC j |Jla -2- I would willingly help you to get them sooner if it were at all possible, but as /ou know all the really good armament factories are very heavily engaged, and u.^er'e is bound to be delay in obtaining really first class rifles such as you re quire • To tell you the truth I was afraid that there would be even more delay than the Company states and it was a pleasant sur prise to me that they have undertaken to start delivery in 25 weeks’ time. 4. I trust that you are in the best of health and that all is well with your State# Usual Ending# sS ' 1 cr* St {J++tj * rl . i/ Political Agent, Bahrain#GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). JN.B -—(This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication man \ expeditious than the ordinary niail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated^ on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible ofjicer of the Department.] No , //6o -9/17. D&lt;aed w ISm ’^kai 1 * 6 ***** t the 21 at jun#, 2.2 ^ To I«ii« Office, London, fttpeated to • * oreign, siala lUpo.tad to - Political, Bahrain. &gt;/ i A*'- * » crtlfl.au ..... 1Ha . ... f „ ttflaa .303 bore, and 22,600 round* .303 ammunition. I ^USIJEST Usue ol the above has been authoriatd peretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* (Signature) s. 44. r^ 1048 84P —(M.2042)—17-12-87—20,000. (Designation)No.C/423 of 1938. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Karachi. Dated the 5th July 1938. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject : Arms and ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar. Memorandum. Your memorandum No. 21st June 1938. C/404-1.a/5 dated the 2 . Action approved. Sd. T. C. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. ()(pr^ for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf-No.C/242 dated the 12th April 1^38 NO OBJECTION C}5RTI?ICAT^ CERTIFIBD that there is no objection to Shaikh * Abdulla bin ^asim al Tiiani, Ruler of ^atar, importing into ^atar the following arms and ammunition via Bahrain. 50 Mauser rlflfca 7.9 m.m. bore. 25,000 rounds of 7.9 m.m. ammunition for the above. 2. The validity of this certificate is restricted to six months. for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Office of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Forwarded, in triplicate, to the Political Agent BahrainNo. C/457 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 11th July 1938 r NO OBJECTION CB3TIFICATS. CERTIFIED that there is no objection to Shaikh ’Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, C.I.S., Ruler of Qatar, importing into '&gt;atar the following arms and ammunition via Bahrain or Dubai. 50 Mauser rifles 7.9 m.m. bore 25,000 rounds of 7.9 m.m. ammunition for the above. 2. The validity of this certificate is restricted to one year.Confidential No. C/459-1.a/5 Political Agency| Bahrain, the 11th July 1938. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject ?- Arms and ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar. Memorandum. /v t Reference your memorandum No. C/423 dated the 5th July 1938. ^ m2* The Shaikh of Oatar has also asked for a revised ^ certificate for the 50 Mauser rifles and ammunition, to pro vide for one year’s validity and importation via Dubai. In this case also I have issued him a fresn permit signing on behalf of the Political Resident, since it would necessarily involve at least a fortnight’s delay to obtain a revised per mit from Bushire, and I am particularly anxious that the Shaikh of Qatar should not discover by any chance that he can get rifles from Germany without a No Objection Certificate at all. I happen to know that he has sent his order to Undue^sh already* Political Agent, Bahrain.(tastrrn ^ INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 16th July, H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Bear Sir, I.'C' V No Objection Certificate No.0403, dated 20th June, 1938, good for one year, enabling Sh. Abdulla bln Kassim Althani, Ruler of Qatar, to import into Qatar via Bahrain and/or Dubai 430 Rifles and 223,000 rounds of ammunition. With ze ference to the above Certificate, we have to advise that we are placing the order for these rifles and ammunition with Messrs. B. S. A. Guns, Ltd., Birmingham, on behalf of the Ruler of Qatar. As the Manufacturers cannot commence delivery until after 25 weeks from receipt of the order and as thereafter delivery can only be given at the rate of 25 Rifles per week, it is likely that the validity of the No-Objection Certificate may expire before the Soods are shipped to the Shaikh of Qatar, and our London Office request that you would be good enough to extend the terra of the Certificate to cover the possibility of f -he ' ^1938 at destination after the period of one year from 20th June, 193 ^ Yours fh^ti«fi.illy,No* 467-1.a/5 Political Agency* Bahrain, the 18th July 1938* To The Manager, The Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain* Dear Sir Please refer to your letter of the l%th July in which you passed on a request made toy your London Office that the validity of No Objection Certificate No* C/403, dated the 20th June 1938, be extended to cover the possibility of the shipment of arms and ammunition arriving after the expiry of the period of one year. 2 . It is unnecessary at this stage to revise the Certificate. On the information given the whole corv- signment should have been despatched from England within the period covered by the Certificate, and in that case no difficulties will be raised at this end. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain.OBERMDCRFfiECKAR ■ds. 18 .Date- - ' Tim* : ^ m. Remarks. LC SALEH ELLON A QATAR BAHRAIN AL AMOUNT FOUR' HUNDRED NINETY POUNDS OPEN CREDIT HAMBURG 'PORT PERMIT MAUS E RV / E R K E . i~ MARK YOUR REPLY IS* No enquiry respecting this Telegram can be attended to without the production of this CopyConfidential -It (g) D«0,No,C/470-1,a/5 Dated the 19th July 1933, I ID i/anv thanks for your letter and for the copy of the e/fble for Saleh al Mann* 2. I nave no objection to this message being passed on provided Petconcess are prepared to frank it, but it is puvely a matter for them to decide whether they will do so or not, Yours sincerely, uPenfold, Esquire, Officer-in- Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain* 1OS) I'y NO.C/241 dated the 12th April 1938. NO OBJECTION OKRTIFISATB CSRTIFI'gD that there is no objection to Shaikh Abdulla bin 'j,asim al Thani # Ruler of ^atar, importing into ^atar via Bahrain the following arms and ammunition from Bngland. 450 rifles *303 bore. 225,000 rounds of ,303 ammunition for the above. 2# The validity of this certificate is restricted t o s im months. Forwarded, in triplicate, to the Political Agent, for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Bahrain* i No. C/242 dated the 12th April 1938 NO OBJECTION CERTIfflflATR CERTIFIED that there is no objection to Shaikh •Abdulla bin qaeim al Thani, C.I.S., Ruler of $atar, imparting into Qatar the following arms and ammunition via Bahrain. 50 Mauser rlfl%e 7.9 m.m. bore. 25,000 rounds of 7.9 m.m. ammunition for the above. 2. The validity of this certificate is restricted to six months. Forwarded, in triplicate, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.Confidential . No. C/503*1.a/5 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd August 1938. From Captain J.B. Kowes, X.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Honourable the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Sir, . 'ik A I have the honour to enclose, for purposes of your / records, a copy of a letter which was addressed to you, as PoliUcal Agent, Bahrain, by the Ruler of Qatar, in which he asks to be allowed and assisted to obtain an annoured car. 2. I see from the note which you left on the file, that the question of an armed car has been under consideration, but a search of the Agency records has not brought to light any copies of correspondence on the subject. 3. I have therefore the honour to request that I may be furnished with the information necessary for a reply to be made to the Ruler of Qatar. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. 'irgT''rnOTi~iTir3. GOV^^ 'll € (tl)f €a0tmt lUwk limits. The Politioul Baji^tdu. 1 ) Daar air» tho iiuler of ^atur - Ho Objoction Oortificate dated iiOth June 1930 for 450 Rifles and 225,000 rounds of Ainunition. o si «■ **-t ra s» s» » a 11« as *S ta a »; « tt S* SI r: as Si :•! * = « rs ii « a * ** s-* »s *: a « a £ J IS r; n ss * r •-ss » « a ITe have to inforn you that v/hen the order for the above ama and aromition was passed on by our london Office to Itessrs. B*3*.«t* Chins Ltd. , Biminghari, the Manufacturers stated that the War Office had info rood them that tho Political lieoident in the Persian Gulf had authorised the Ruler of flatar to purchase only 22,500 rounds of annunition, but that in view of the Ifo Objection Certii icuto which we sent then, they did not consider that any further question o*o ilii be raised.on this point. It would appear that the figure of 23,500 represents a clerical error on tho part of sons employee in t.^e Jar Office , but we are bringing the natter to your notice in case the point is raised at a later date.2 'i 0 &amp; 3 # The Shaiicn or ^atar has alae raised tne question of obtaining one or two irrJ&amp;oured cars and I shall address you 1‘urtner on tnis matter snortiy* sd/- h.Weigntman Offg. Political resident in tne Persian uulf. attested* Secretary to tne Political Resident in tne Persian tiulf.CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (/$• 2 # The correspondence of 1935 is that commencing with ^ ' i* * Political Resident’s telegram No.T/130 dated the 9th May 1935 to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, and ending with the latter's reply No. 1463 v dated the !2t^^ May 1935, copy of which is on the Agency records. ^ Dated. September 1^0. O^f^geofthePolTtical Resident, Persian Gulf, camp bahra^. Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain letter No.C/503-la/5 dated the 2nd August 1938. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Note dated the 14th September 1938 by Mr. H. Y/eightman, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Armoured cars for the Shaikh of Qatar.This file should be shown to Sir Trenchard Fowle on his return, since it is most important to know, and it is not absolutely cle^ir from the files, whether he ^ r H A &lt;&gt;k - : i communicated H.M.G*s decision about the armoured or armed cars to the Shaikh of Qatar in May iy35. If so, then, subject to any different decision arrived at as a result of the discussions with A.O.C's representative in regard to Defence, it will only be necessary to remind the Shaikh of Qatar that he had already been told that H.M.G. saw no reason to enable him to obtain armoured cars in 1935y and nothing has happened since to justify a variation from that decision. 2. On the other hand if this decision was no£ communicated to the Shaikh I could probably put him off by saying that although I had reported his request I saw little possibility of his receiving any reply for at least a year (and possibly much longer) since rearmamant in Europe makes it quite impossible to obtain even machine guns, and much less armoured cars, at this time. 3. A copy of this note should be given to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Intd. H. V^. 14th September 1938rfluficieniltA D.O. Ho. C/()07-l.a/S The 2nd October 1938 /f fv v.ill you please reff^x* to n&gt;y note of tue 14t.h Sep tember 1938 on the Residency file in regard tc the ouee- tim of obtaining armed care for the Shaikh of Tatar? 2m Although in 1935 His lajesty'c Oovernment were very definite in refusing to alloy; the Shaikh of Qatar to have in^r to v;erk out scheme* of internal security indicates thrt Government to reconsider their decision# The ‘loyal j ±r Fovoe ie responsible for the defence of -mtar in war, and since they will have heavy commitments both in 1 Iraq and Shaikh of Q&amp;t’&amp;r to add fliawerially to a def^ince scheme# 3# I presume that efforts will continue to draw up security schemes to cover all our comiTiitflients on this side 01 ^ le Rersien ^If, end if you approve, T might invite the views of the expert rho will presumably be visiting this Agency in the real* future to complete the task tfken up by M« t ior Young. either armoured or armed ears , recent nxpeiience in ettempt- thore might veil be advantage in requesting His I'ejesty*s up an&lt;i down the ^’oaat, it seers probable that they would welcome any arrangement which night be made to enable the Yours sincerely, V- Lieutenant-Colonel '^nchard Fowle, KCIE, CBS, Political iesidont in the Persian ckilfXPTIWWPWjW... CONFIDENTIAL. 0.0. No.c/? 37 of 1938, ' i3 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to H. Veightman Esquire, Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned 1 documents (s&lt;). ”1 fo Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,qonfld«ntlal* •Offloe of the Polltieal Healdent in the Pereiun CKilf ff Oaap f Kuveiit • Dated the 7th Oetober t 1938. vhen the ^atar Oil Company obtained their oil concession from the shaikh of c^atar in May 193b. ae you are ae&amp;re His Majesty* s OoTernment promised him protection from external aggression by land, and the responsibility for implementing this promise falls on the Poyal Air yorce. 2. Vith a Tie# to inoreas ing the aasiatance which the Ihalkh could give in co-operating with the Foyel Air Force in an emergency 1 euggeated at the time that the Shaikh might be allowed to purchase armed oars, which he was anxious to do. His Majesty’s Coverm&amp;ent however were not agreeable, fh* Shaikh has again returned to the charge, tfhen the question of la tar dsfcnoe Is taken up (vids lelghtm&amp;n's demi-official (f *1*4 'b) letter Ho.C/313, dated the 8th August 1938) the question of allowing the Shaikh to purchase armed cars might be kept in mind and. if from the defence point of view you consider that these csrs would be a help. His ilRjesty Y 8 Government can again be approached. • I am sending a copy of this letter to 7eightman. Yours sincerely, sd • T . C .Fowl e* Air Vice Marshal J.H.a.Tyseen. II.C.. A ir Off io er Comuand ing, British Forces in Iraq. Uabb&amp;niya. * sent under Printed letter Ho.C/737 of the 7th October 1938.w 15 ' /V- iJubai, 17 th 0^ t ^bhul x&gt;atif, vjxs - The •secretary to the Govt, of ^atar has sent nis representative namely uassan bin .limad el-,jnim with a letter to our Office, asking for delivery of 20 cases expected to arrive fjom Germany The nili of .aain^ is in noosession of uassan nin .Junad el-.vinim and on my inspec tin 0 ^it^ 1 found it is ior twenty oases of cartridges axiu arms a^id ammunition etc, to oe transhipped at sombay to Jubc-ii• ,^ ne cases i n question nave xiot ^et arrived here and 1 have replied in writing to tne secretary of ^.ovt. of ^atar as under That the have not yet arrived here. That the nill of nading is not endorsed by tne ^.astern ^ank jjtd. Cas ,s been endorsed by the shippers to the order of tne ^ank) fhat tne steamship Jompany at nombay are not aole to effect transhipment of the cases to nubai in absence of a ' Ro Objection ’’ Certificate ' from the ..onouraole the iolitical \esident in nushire* fhat he should obtain and send us tne necessary Certificate so that we may send it to our combay merits, to enable them to tranship the 5*0 jds to rubai. nassan ran /dimad el-.jnim, however, informed us that tne xolitioai authorities at nahrein had given permission for tne purunase oi txie goods, and i have duly advisea him to get tne necessary ^o Objection certificate as witnout this document the oases will never oome forward here. if tne goods come to rubai 1 wiio. inform you as soon as possible. I am sending you this letter in duplicate in case Khan ^ahib ^eyyed ^bdul HazzaG will stay ; ^ , 1 close wicn best regards and salacmis to both you and K. b. ^eyyed /vbdul Hazzaq. o usiu, cott 4 -. o, C' so, Abdul ratif nsq., Residency .^gent, gharjah. fours very.sincerely, ?/KD.o. No* C/GSy^i*ai/5 The 23rd October 1938* Reference our conversation regarding the Shaikh of Qatar’s rifles, I enclose herewith a certified copy of the No Objection Certificate as promised* If Youra sincerely, K* Campbell, Esquire, r easrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, BAHRAIN*By Air Mail. p.z. 19 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, It. rj.. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by Sm MaiL 1 4963 2000 7.36I 1 (Original iri file 12/15 page ) Dated the 16th January 1939 D.C. No* C/25-12/15 Dear Sir Trenchard, This is just a news letter ^bout the visit which I paid to Tatar last week end, 2. I stayed in the P.C.L. camp at Jebel Dukhan and found them all very cheerful. They have built a very pleasant small camp and have nine or ten people there who seem to get on very well together and also with the Catar coolies. They are down to 2050 ft. and are setting casing to th't depth this week. Afterwards they start drilling again in^o what may oe the first oil hoj'izon. There has been a little . r as showing but it is still too soon to say whether there is more than a 30 - 50 chance of oil. Relations between the Company and the Shaikh are now excellent, after a little dif’lenity in the late summer which Packer succeeded in putting right. 3. I went across to see the Shaikh in \ayan and found him in excellent health end very cheerful. He was extremely affabl* and complim nts flew about in all directions. I handed him a translation of the Bahrain counter-claim to the Hewar Islands Cf. my Express letter No. C/10-1.a/29 5 and asked him to let me have dated the 5th January 1939. ; . m ^ 9 u&gt; rejoinder as soon os he pooaicly could. He complained that the Bahrain Shaikhs are very hostile towards him and are trying to seduce some oi his Bedu from him. As a matter of fact I believe there is some thing in this as &lt;ine of the sim leaders named Hansur, who is in charge of the gu&amp;rd at the Oil Camp, has been in correspond ence with Shaikh Abdullah bin * Isa and will probably come acres \ to/- onour^ble Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Fowle, C.B.S., Political lesident in t Bushire.- 2 - tc Bahrain with hia followers before very long. The fact is that although most people in Qatar quite like the old .Shaikh they cannot, bear Shaixh iiamaci, his son, or Saleh al &amp;ana*, both of whom try to loot them. However I said to the old Shaikh th^t I did not see that ho had anything to worry about provided he kept his Bedu happy. This was a gentle hint not to hang on to all the oil money hiiaself| as he has done hitherto. 4. The Jhaikh raised the question of his armou ed cars, Cf. Correspondence resting v/lth your 0 and I told him that the Printed letter No. 5 5 tion and that I hoped to fly across his territory shortly with sorae experts who would be abla to advise whether armoured cars would be of any use or not. This I should be doing tomorrow | f I with Price. The Shaikh mentioned the point that though His Majesty’s -rovernment had undertaken to give him protection against outside aggression by means of the Hoyal Air Force 9 still they do ©erect him to co-operate; and he felt quite sure that he could co-operate best by having armoured or armed cars. He was not very much in favour of the Kuwait type, though I pointed out to him that really heavy armoured vehicles would never be able to get round his country. 5* He protested against the continuance of the Bahrain boycott, and I must say that I sympathise with him. vVhen we to try to induce the Shaikhs to resume normal relations with 7th October 1938 5 matter was under considera- heve finished here with oil concessions and 'reforms 5 * T h6oe bd/- H. Weightmanfrom the Ruler of . &lt;a tar to tne Political Agent, Baurain. I am very pleased by the receipt of your kind letter No. C-46^1. datea 19th January 1939. to your conversation witn me about the armourea car which I desire to import, anci about your 1 light over the country with an expert who nad tne desired opportunity (of seeing the country). Your alssj) mention that you will send a fuller reply alter tne expert is able to consult witn nis superiors. I am grateful to you for this explanation. I will be waiting for your reply on this matter. the last visit with which you nave honoured us, this is ideed enviable and we become more pleased by more frequent visits, and hope that you will honour us always witn more visits which will be the more pleasing to us. In your promise we have a strong hope of seeing in the very near future while enjoying the best of health. U.E. After compliments, I am ve I am very grate!ul to you for giving fuller details As to your remarks about the pleasure you had onA ?/ Of p.z.1426/39 ' U The under Secretary of State for India presents his compliments to the Secretary to the Board of Trade and, uitii reference to Board of Trade Memorandum No. E.L.330207 aateo 4th March, 1938, covering copy of an application from B.o..,. Guns Ltd. for a licence under the Arms Export Prohibition Order 1931 to export 225 rifles and 113,000 rounds of .303 ammunition to the Sheikh of Catar, desires to inform him that the Secretary of State for India seed i C no oosection to the issue of a licence on this application. The no objection certificate No. C/403^dated 20th June 1938 signed, by the Political Resident in-the Persian G-ulf is returned herewith in original. It is noted that the certificate covers a quantity of 225,000 rounds of ammunition whereas the present application and che application dealt with in December last by exuort licence Jo. 227427 relate to a total quantity of 225,500 rounos. The excess is however relatively small, and it has//d • aas not been thought necessary to consult the ^ in the Persian Gulf (to v/hom the matter will 1 before approving the present application. I)IA OFFICE, Oth March, 1939. Cf authorities e reported)• |0 Translation of a letter dated 28th J&amp;mad al 1358 (18.7.39) from the Ruler of Qatar to the Political Agent, Bahrain After compliments, I hope that you are in the best of health ani that everything goes well with you, may Allah lead you to success. I beg to refer to our discussions on your visit to Rayyan on Tuesday the 9th May 1939 (19th Rabi ul Thani 13$) about armoured cars m th machine guns. Your Excellency informed me that these cars are of no beneficial use.in a desert such as ours owing to their heavy weight and irregular movements, that they have become of no practical value and that you ana strong prefer cars with heavy/wheels on which machine guns can be mounted and which will be of more beneficial use and generally more effective. You have promised to enquire and inform me about these cars, their prices and about the machine guiB from those concerned. In view of the discussions which took place about the same I write to remind you a-nd to reqiest you to inform me what you have done in the matter as I desire, with Your Excellency^ help, to place an order of the type mentioned by you. I write this letter solely in this connection and I am awaiting a reply from you about the matter. I hope to receive a favourable reply from you for which my thanks and gratitude will be due to you for your kind help. U.E. I l o C\1 t fl}. Translation of a letter dated 15th u amadi al Thani 1358 (2nd august 1939) from the h u i er 0 f Qatar to the Political Agent, Bahrain. o ry A - c - ./ I thank you very much for your kind letter No.C/433, dated 19th &lt;J u ly 1939 (3rd Jamadi al Thani 1358). I have noted your remarks about the cars on which machine- guns are mounted. I understand from your remarks that it is difficult to make arrangements for the supply of the same in view of the present state of affairs in Europe. As they are urgently required by me I request you kindly to do the needful in getting the necessary permit for inporting five of the same. Then I get the permit I will ask one of my friends to order them from England. I request you kindly to send the permit as soon as possible and I hope that you will help me in this matter for which I will be very grateful to you. Bsual Ending* • &gt; E. &lt; ‘V'U/ sd. HW. A T a R tribal sections (not migratory to'' Saoudi Arabia) to the Shaikh Nassir bin lasim took upon himself to sneak plainly to the Ruler and warn him that his niggardliness in money matters and handling of employment in the oil Co was losing him the support of the tribesmen he needed to control £atar and his prospective oil field, and helping his Bahrain enemies to undermine his authority. (The Bahrain Shaikhs who were responsible for the departure, last year, of the Ruler of Qatar’s strongest adherent in western Qatar Mansur bin Khalil of the Bani- Hajir, who was very active on the Qatar side in the Naim clash, never lose an opportunity of spreading discord in the west and north.) r * The Ruler was apparently impressed and sent to Bahrain on 15th October for Rs 40,000. Jasim Darwish, brother of Abdulla Darwish (Shaikh Hame d' s confidant), was entrusted with funds to pacify the tribesmen. He was empowered to pay amounts of Rs 10 - 15 per family. This u apparently did not satisfy the recipients. Shaikh Ali bin Jasim el Thani was also sent without success. Rather than increase his money offers the Ruler advised by Shaikh Hamed sanctioned a scheme to patrol the north vest coast of Qatar by launch and prevent emigration l to B ahrain. Dissatisfaction at this stage appeared even among the Ruler’s bodyguard, some of whom applied for 10 days leave which Shaikh Hamed refused regarding it as a pretext for a visit to the malcontents to share in possible benefits from Bahrain, ''hey were told that they could leave behind the Ruler’s rifles (new) &amp; go for good. A ruling was apparently given that persons desirous of leaving Qatar could do so provided they settled their debts in Dohah etc. (b) it would seem that the causes of dissatisfaction in Qatar are : ii. The Ruler’s and his son Kamed’s greed which makes them not only retain all the oil money but also control for their own benefit employment in the oil Go. Neither can see that Arab standards of life are changing &amp; the rising generation with its contact with the outside world can no longer be deceived and repressed. iii. Intrigues from Bahrain. i. Poverty due to the pearl slump &amp; lack of employment aggravated by2 Ite f ■ en iployment of guards in tile oil Cn i = entirely in the hands of the Shaikh and as security responsibility the Co. cannot interfere with the actual 18 recruitment. Payment is effected through the Shaikh^ undoubtedly takes a large sharp T^hnnSo-no 6 bn ^ ikl:L who the Shaikh's representative'but'paid in full^ dir^tlv^the ® 11 «r;ke t of iS f-'? ei ‘ tain that th6 Sha1 ^ ° r his so - ,J^ S m ®ans that the Shaikh has every inducement to recruit his adherents over whom he has the'closest ennt^ni and the majority of the Qatar population derive no leTetll’ from the supposed fabulous wealth of the oil Co. Denerlt The obvious remedies judicious distribution of oil monies and employment 'without'rake off' are not so simple at this early stage in the oil Co. operations. P degree. Beduwins are insatiable, ungrateful &amp; disloyal to a Subsidies must be small &amp; periodical to be successful The Shaikh must consolidate his own position &amp; retain the ioya! support of some sortof striking force before he can afford to discard favouritism in employment matters. As the oil Co. operations expand and money and employment becomes more plentiful the Ruler will''have an opportunity to shew that he is capable of wise and~ disinterested rule. Meanwhile he might perhaps be made to see that it is unwise and unnecessary to hoard his annual oil monies at this stage and by judicious distribution he will strengthen his position for the future. Further it is unwise to antagonize the few adherents who do benefit from the oil Co. already by large rake offs from their pay. Shaikh Abdulla can perhaps be persuaded to adopt such a policy. Should he die however serious dislocation of existing control is to be expected. Shaikh Hamed is giving already the clearest indications that he intends to control all oil Co. contacts with the Qataris for his own personal gain. It is most unlikely except under strong and continual pressure by a British Government representative that he will be prevailed upon to adopt the broad-minded policy of a ^ successful Ruler. Ref.(iii) Further particulars may be of interest. These intrigues commenced in 19?]Jf with the clash over the ownership of Zubarah. Naim tribesmen financed and armed largely ( ^rom Bahrain were defeated by the Shaikh of Qatar in a bloodless battle in which the casualties were two on each side. The loss of prestige was felt very deeply by the Bahrain Ruling family. ^then the majority of the Naim have been subsidized by Bahrain and live in Bahrain or Arabia. A section of the Bani- &gt; Kajir under Mansur bin Khalil formerly a staunch adherent of ^baikh Abdulla of Qatar were next alienated by money and presents* Shaikh Mansur draws Rs 60 p.m. and 25 of his followers Rs. 11 each. /•' I 1u ^ &gt; r- » s f v rlr^ - 3 - v , ( Bis-gruntled members of Shaikh Abdulla’s family were also encouraged to leave Qatar and reside in Bahrain where \they ’were given presents &amp; salaries (including a motor car or it\ use). Two of them were taken to India with H.H. Shaikh Hamadh S Dohah’s most reputed merchant was recently invited to sever his connections in Qatar &amp; settle in Bahrain. The^ inability of the Ruler of Qatar to move with the times is exploited to the full by Bahrain. The latest trouble was caused by a disgruntled Qatar /arab from Khor who visited Bahrain returning with funds and propaganda. fUnktlq Sections affected were : A Sl-Sulta - (Ibrahim bin Nasr) 300 strong. Some of the leading men were recently in Bahrain and received cash presents from the Ruler. Bani-Hajir - (Mansur bin Khalil) Once over 1,200 strong, they have dwindled in Qatar to 5 families. The last big batch to leave Qatar for Arabia was a party under Mansur last year. This move was brought about by the Bahrain Shaikhs (see para./#). Mansur who held a lucrative job in the oil Co. in Qatar is considering a return to the oil Co. and his old grazing, grounds. lie has just gone on a hawking trip to Saoudi Arabia with Shaikh Abdulla bin Isa of Bahrain. Naim - 600 - 800 strong - Under Rashid bin Mohammad. These were involved in the Zubarah clash. Subsequently practically to a man they were bought over by Bahrain and settled in Saoudi Arabia &amp; Bahrain. A few are reported to be drifting back to Qatar. Mehanda - Khor District - Leader Ahmed bin Ssa. Said to be 600 strong and closely allied to the Bani- Ka jir. Other Q^itar tribal sections not reported to be affected so far but likely to appear in the picture eventually are : Bu-Kuwarra - 100 strong - Leader Ali bin Shahin. This section is spread over central &amp; northern Qatar and the N.V/. shores. Mananiaa - (Nasir bin Abdulla Atiya) 9° strong. The Ruler’s wife comes from this section. Nasir is visiting Ibn Saoud at present for financial help. Bl-Qaslm - (100 strong). Tnis is the section of the Ruling family. Bl-Chebarah - (Khowair area) 50 strong - Leader Saleh bin Dasm. Ch&amp;ban - (Nomadic) under Khamis bin Saraiyu. Chief among sections of Saoudi Tribes migrating into Qhtar for grazing are : , J * i. Bani-Ha.iir (see note above on this section;. ii. Manasir - 300 strong. iii. El-Murrah.4 These Saoudi tribes pay camel &amp; goat taxes tn Thn q ^ and nothing to Ojatar. Ibn Saoud’s tax collectn^%^i Ib ud tribes into Q^tar to collect, if necessary? f ° U0W the Taxes collected &amp; subsidie s paidby the Shaikh of ; H t»r. . , ^ i ^ e OU£li u ‘ 0:£ ' Qatar takes no animal taxe s from Qataris due S s reVenUe 001,168 fr ° m pearl - diTl ^ boat taxes aM C^slom annum. He ^ pays a few tribal leaders some Rs 40. ner -no-r» Tribesmen with rifles receive per family per m?nth 1 Bag of rice 160 lbs. of dates 4 lbs. of coffee. Household and body-guards get from Rs 5 to not satisfy them in these days. 8 which does 2 . PoqSI BI-lIIT off XHTHixluiL DISTURBANCE S IN CATa? 'tT i-v denies emphatically that possible discontent is likely to lead to open revolt. lu . , Mansur Khalil an independent source with close knowledge of Q,atar and in a position to judge of the practical effect of the Bahrain intrigues considers that Shaikh Abdulla the Ruler is wise enough to avoid any threatened storm but should he die ^hai'h iamed T s stupidity, obstinacy, unpopularity and lack of administrative ability &amp; statesmanship will constitute a real danger. iP' That Shaikh Abdulla drew Rs 40,000 to use partly at least ^ in propitiating his tribes &amp; family points to the fact that he is alive to the danger and prepared for conciliation. That Shaikh Abdulla of Bahrain, who is the most active among the Bahrain Shaikhs in the plans to sow discord in Qatar together with Mansur bin Khalil to whose inf]uence &amp; personality tne Bahrain Shaikhs attach much importance, have just left on a hawking expedition to Arabia, appears a very clear ip ication that no disorder fomented by Bahrain is hoped for in the near future. Arab opinion is also that Great Britain is the best friend they are likely to find and it is in their own interests to ensure that she is not hampered in the present war by the internal squabbles of her small Arab allies. This view is put -Ward quite seriously by responsible types and seems to carry weight. HA WAR ISLANDS. To add to the friction between Bahrain &amp; Qatar the ownership of the Kawar group of islands by Bahrain is contested b y Qatar.I ^ L ^ 1 \ This problem is comolicAtpfl ■h-tr -t-u , ownership of the various rooks Isle^ t0 lay down in the Hawar area especially as aoms c ,J. cl re ff?. and 3il0 al waters mile' limit. y aS some are Wlth in star's 'three Bahrain have been n in nosse^^lnn^ n-p 4 -V 1 • for some time &amp; in a position to annenrh ° f , tae maln HaWar Islanc pleased within reach of their for?? marl£ an y^ing they annexations S have heermade^tertaSw 1 ^, docuinenta the Mohd. bin A.hmad bin Shah in hau sari given hi^bv^Sh i&gt;h d r by ° ne Bahrain has been in all nroViblltv 1 v ? 7 Shalkh Isa of only nine names wer ®| 3 M^ted by him. ' arably exceeded, as against their decisio^that 1 Haw&amp;r t belongs t to t Ba l r r -’ tiSb G ° Vt ‘ an early delimitation of a boundary tbe S K.ii B 7 . B ? U v aln iv As re Sards s, 1 ::' '' i » * h ‘' »■ *“• sizing the islands and his somewhat idle boastings h«ve reached the Bahrain Shaikhs, and have not improved relations. In fact a solution of the Hawar question will not imnrove matters to any extent as from the Bahrain side the real quarrel is in connection with their claims to Zubarah. quarrel Ba B r !, in Shaikhs are 33 intensely bitter as ever on r,7ib-b P ^ r + nd there seems no prospect of a settlement. The iwler of t^itar approached the Euler of Bahrain recently but eived a reply calculated to end further attempts at correspondence. p 4 - MISS5LLANE 0US - PEESSNTS BY TEE EULER OF QhTAfi TO IBK SAOUP. '•/ . ' nf&gt; __ Shaikh Abdulla has recently sent to Ibn Saoud a present oi oo camels by Ganim bin Saif a minor Beduwin Shaikh. L' 5&gt; gHJEOSSP ITS'/! CAS00. DRILLIKG CA?v!P HEAR SILWAH (on the south western boundary of Qatar)? 0 presence of Saoudi guards at the oil Camp near the &lt;3 border may be expected to have a steadying effect in U* ^ a0U(i i tribes migrating into Qatar. ) V /© Confiden^icq, D.O.No.C/802 Bated the 5th December 1939* &lt; /V X enclose herewith a very interesting note which ha 3 been srit to me by Facker, the Ujcal ; anager of Petroleum Concessions Limited and Petroleum Development ( atar) Limited. Packer visited c atar recently and picked up a certain amount of infer- nation there, but still more of it, I think, comes from Panaur oin Khalid of the Beni Hajir who used to be in the Company's employment and whom I know as an unusually reliable member of the Beni Lajir tribe* I have made various marginal comments on / acker's note, largely designed to tone down the impression that the Bahrain Shaikhs are organising a secret campaign in atar to knock down the A1 Than! fanily. 2 * ** of course perfectly true that the Bahrain Shaikhs lose no opportunity of aiding residents of ^atar whose allegi ance to Shaikh Abdulla bin assim br a worn thin. The A1 - h^iifah family will never be reconciled to the loss of ^ubarah so long as Shaikh Hamad, shaikh tSohammad and Shaikh Abdulla are alive. i ohmmad feels the H los8 ,, of Zubarah most bitterly r indeed is inclined to be hysterical about it, while Abdulla Lo B stav»in| one could hardly say that they have organised L ifth Column in C^atar, The fact is that Bahrein is beseiged avarice of Shaikh Abdulla and of the impositions of his eldest •on Shaikh Hamad. I have from time to time tried to induce Sfcoikh Abdulla bin Oassim to loosen the strings of his money looks after contacts with people in Qatar who wish to transfer by all kinds of people from C'atar who are sick to death of the“ A— adviser Saleh al Sana' in the contrary direction has been too strong. There is at least some satisfaction to be derived from the fact that the Shaikh of Qatar has now distributed a little money • 3 . y personal belief is that so long as the old Shaikh is alive Qatar will muddle along somehow, since he is personally quite popular both with the townsfolk (if one can use the word 'town' for places like Doha or Wakrah) and with the Bedu. The only people who really hate him are some of his own relatives But when he dies and Shaikh Hamad comes into power 1 should anticipate ra &gt;id acceleration of the tempo of agitation. I doubt very much if there will be any armed rising, for the Ruling Family have the best arms by a long way. But I should certainly t,r:ticipate a murder and quite candidly I think it would be to Qatar's advantage in the long run if Shaikh Hamad bin Abdulla passed out. We have of course recognised him as heir-apparent but that does not involve us in protecting him from *sassin% fortunately; and since I should not anticipate fighting we have not ing much to worry about so far as the oil camp at Zekrit is concerned. For the present there is nothing to cause real concern. ±he old Shaikh is amazingly healthy and tough; and I should think that he has many years of life before him. Yours sincerely.D0/Mso/5798 m PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULP. 19th December, 1939 Dear Herewith a small note on the Qatar emigration which may be of interest. Yours sincerely, Enclo. H.Weightman, Esq., I.G.S., The Agency, Bahrain.Mansur reports today that three of the Mehanda tribe yesterday arrived at Bahrain. They are led by Hilal bln 3ad, brother of Khamie bin 3ad, the leading mGri :-&gt;hakhariah (a village North of Khor) who died only ten days ago. iarlier arrivals were ^li bin ns a «iad wooien (hia sister and wife) with a maid-servant. This Ali is brother of /yhmed, the Ohief of the Bukawaru tribe. He has now settled in Kufa (Bahrain). Ti’ie launch which the Ruler of Qatar had kept at Has-Reken to patrol and prevent Irregular emigretion has been recalled and ie row at hohah• There is no patrolling of the coast at present. There is no important change in the situation. Isolated cases are occurring of Qataris leaving or wish ing to le^ve Qatar to seek better means of existence in Bahrain.Conriciential D.O. No.C/220 - l.a/5 Cated the 18th March ld40 Packer, the hocal Manager of Petroleum Concessions Limited, has informed me of a rumour going round in Qatar that Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim is trying to get hola of an 'Iraqi to be his aaviser on foreign affairs. 2 . fm-re is something of this sort in the »inu since aoout a month ago »e saw a letter written by Saleh ai Mann to Ibrahim del% ai Omar, Press Director, Baghdad, offering him employment as an 'Oil Specialist' in Qatar. Ibrahim replied that he himself could not accept the post but asked for more particulars as he thought he might be able to recommend some one. So far there does not seem to have Doeii any lurtner reply from the Qatar direction. Yours sincerely. f tfoaour&amp;ble lieutenant '-Colonel C. G. Prior, C.I.L., Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf, BUblilRL.I- 1H iViAH. 1940 petroleum concessions ltd. BAHRAIN Pear ivfa k ILdr / \l '&gt;* 0*1 / QATAR AFFAIRS PERSIAN GULP. 18th. March 1940. You may be interested in the following a-n-io-; .*&gt; my last visit to Qatar in early March. ^ arising from Iraqi or Persian Foreign Ad viser to Qatar (or Secretary - ) There is good reason to believe that the Ruler has been oil foreign r a?fairf! rtS t0 find PerS ° nS t0 deal witl1 his He has approached Abdul Aziz Helmi- the AIOC man whn traveis the Gulf on local sales etc. - aid also a ^n nLed Ibxahim H elmi al-Omar said to be in the Census or Censor^ ta P f‘i nf 5 -? e Kf lrSt f0r direct employment &amp;the secold to find him a suitable man at £ hO p.m. Nothing has yet been settled. (b) Co. Representative The Ruler asked when an administrative type of Co.official would be expected in Qatar suitable for them to contact freely at this stage only a junior type working under Mr. Dickson 4ould be expected he changed his mind at once and asked chat the present periodical contacts with Mr. Racxer from Bahrain should be continued until reconsideration oi the position might become necessary in the future. (c) Shaikh^ Representative - Saleh el Mana The Abdulla Darwish - Shaikh Hamed combination seems as strong as ever and Saleh is losing ground. Abdulla Darwish appears at the ShaiKh*s conferences and takes a seat witJ^Less diffidence as though confident that his status will protect him against any suspicion of over familiarity. Abdulla Darwish still caters for Hamed's illicit pleasures and shares with him the profits of his business enterprises. The latest is a contract for Rs 20,000 for certain stone &amp; mud work. (8.) General The Shaikh spent 3 days at Dukhan &amp; was shewn the well &amp; the oil flowing &amp; burning. sr Mw2 ■ w • The next stage in the development of thp -p-ioiH explained to him and the ' party broxe un in f ld WaS spirit. It looks however as if sooner or la-i-ar cor&lt; ^^ a l Hamed &amp; Abdulla Darwish will reach a stage where ft 8 *!?? ^ an adverse effect on the Co's operations Ld it will V6 necessary to come to an understanding. The longer fL b unpleasantness can be postponed the better as It &lt;-■ Co. is consolidating its position ^ 11 tlme the its Qatari workers and promoting sound &amp; enn?? confidence of of service. The positio? is°tha! tKabou^rfarl cheerfir and obedient workers under Co. sunervi si nn ana &lt; -p ™ eer ful protected from the Abdulla Darwishes &amp;'Hameds a^d thf CaQ be introduction of Iraqi raises &amp; trouble breeders? Yours sincerely, H. Weightman Esq., I.C.S., Bahrain.confidential -'&gt;•0. T»o« C/225 — l,a/5 Date the 20th March 1940 v J any thanks for your letter of the 18th March about Qatar Affairs which is most interesting, 2 . I think Ibrahim Helmi al Omar has refused the job as adviser himself but has asked for more details before -'ecommondin^ any one else* e have not seen any reply from Oatar. Incidentally Saleh appears to be handling this corresoondence* Yours sincerely (A V, Packer, Esquire, Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited BAH H AINConfidential D»0« No »C/226~ 1•a/5 12 ? \\t 3ated the 20th March 1940 •V I enclose herewith a copy o/ a latter which I have received from Packer about affairs In latar for your information, 2 . T have already referred to point Ca) in his letter in ray demi-official letter No. C/220 dated the 18th I'arch 1940. ('Mr Yours sincerely, A f 16 Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel C. G. Prior, C.I.S., Politics! Resident in the Persian Gulf, PUSHTU , aConfidential The Residency, H.Q.Hq.III-S Dear Weightman, 1/. 'I L ^ Please r^fer to your demi-official letter No .C/220-1.a/b, dated the 18th March 1940, re garding an Iraqi adviser for Qatar. 2 . I think you will agree that, although we are not entitled to object to a-aoh an appointment under the Treaty, yet, nevertheless, there are obvious objections to such an appointment, and hope that you will do your best to prevent it being made. Nightman, ^sq., I.C.S Political Agent, Bahrain.Dear I send herewith a report which is probably of no importance - The incident may however reach you in exaggerated form. Yours sincerely, Enel. H.Weightman, Esq., I.C.S., The Agency, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL QATAR INTERNAL TROUBLES reported that, following a petty squabble between minor members of the Qnsim (Ruler's father) and Ahmed sections of the Qatar Shaikly family on May 30th, Shaikh Hamed (heir apparent) tried to turn it into a major issue and talked of brin^inc matters to a head and either disarming the Ahmed party or arranging for their deportation. y The Ruler held a conference of his section and excitement ran high. The matter has, in all probability recourse to any drastic measures but this still remains to be confirmed Hamed s attitude is probably influenced by troubles following the distribution or perhaps non-distribution of the oil money paid out on the 17th May.CONFIDENT! AT.: BAHRAIN, The temporary banishment of two youths was ordered by the Ruler and all is now quiet again Yours sincerely, H. Weightman.Esq.,I.C.S., The Agency, Bahrein.Telegram 'Q' From Political, Bahrain Political Agent, Bahrain, at Ziarat 300 To No. Dated 22nd August 1940 4 1**1 Shaikh Hamad of Qatar now' v/ants to go to Iraq in his launch for medical treatment (?). You have file about Iraq adviser idea. For the moment I have stalled him off on grounds of special arrange ments being necessary for entry to Shatt el Arab under v/ar conditions, also by demanding photographs of whole party. I have suggested he sticks to his original idea of going to India. 2. What comments or instructions ? Howes r *A. c/o Foreign, Simla.Telegram R No. 3253 dated 27th august 1940. From Yrfeigjritman, bimla. To ......Political, Bahrain. (&gt; Your telegram No. 300 dated 22nd august. Please repeat gist to Political resident and add following In my view it is most undesirable that Sheikh Hamad of Qatar should go to Iraq but we cannot flatly refuse passport etc. we should however say plainly to Sheikh of i^atar that if his son really requires medical treatment India offers far superior facilities and by going there he sill avoid difficulties which journey by launch to Iraq in war time will involve. ’ Correspondence on above lines could be spun out for considerable period if necessary. ! i 1 ..... »»«.«••* MR. WKIGHTMAN. LM.Telegram From To No. Dated Q. i olitical Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Camp, Shiraa. 316. 29th August 1940. Hamad, son of Shaikh of Qatar, has asked me to arrange facilities for him to go to Iraq in his own launch on pretext of medical treatment. The Shaikh has for some time had the idea of getting an Iraqi adviser. (I imagine there has been correspondence with the Residency on this subject but have not got the file here). 2. I have temporarily stalled him off on grounds of special arrangements being necessary for entry to Shatt al Arab under war conditions, and have suggested he goes to India instead. 3. Nr. V.eightmm has directed me to repeat this information to you and add that though he considers it is most un :esirable that he should go to Iraq, we cannot absolutely refuse passport. He suggests that we put forward superior medical advantages of India and avoidance of travel difficulties, spinning out correspondence to the limit. 4. I learn from Petroleum Concessions Limited that Shaikh Hamad has asked them to send urgently 'details of arrangements made', so is evidently anxious to leave. * 5. Your instructions are requested. PoliticalGOVERNMENT OE INDIA, - ——— Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N. IS.-This is an ORIGINAL MUSS AGE, sent by post to save lekaravUc expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sane time and formalities it is worded and signed as'if it had been From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bahrain. N0 ’ C/939 D 2nd December 194# 3 ' A letter has been received dated the 25th Shawwal 1359 (25th November 1940) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qassim A1 Thani, Shaikh of Qatar, stating that he intends to pro ceed on pilgrimage to Mecca. The date of his departure has not been intimated. Enquiries are however being made by me and the result will be communicated. Political Agent, Bahrain. 4003&amp;P—(M 480)—26-7-34— 2,00,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, — Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B, This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sate telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. V 0 , Dated 103 . C/974-1.a/5 15th December 1940 V&gt; In continuation of my Express letter No. C/939 dated the 2nd December 1940. 2. Information has now been received that the Ruler of Oatr,r f Shaikh Abdullah bin ^asim al Thani has gone on pilgrimage to Mecca accompanied by the heir-apparent Shaikh Hamad and some seventy members of his family and servants. He expects to be a way approximately two months. The eldest son Ali is acting Tor his father. u a Political Agent, Bahrain. s. e. MFP— 40 O 5 J&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. DO/CAU. 1/2288 3 r( i February, 1941. Dear U H^OtCUi^n ] \ VICTORIA RUPEES AND HALF RUPEES We propose to inform the Shaikh of Qatar that the Victoria Rupees and Half Rupees are to be withdrawn from circulation and we are sending him a copy of the Bank circular to this effect. It will doubtless cause a certain amount of alarm in Q,atar and before taking any action we should like your views. It can be taken as inevitable that the Shaikh will ask for our assistance in despatching and changing his coins. The matter will doubtless be complicated by the refusal of the Bank to accept counterfeit or doubtful coins. Perhaps you may think it advisable to mention this matter to the Shaikh on your impending visit. Yours sincerely, Major R. G. Alban, H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain.Repo rt on visit to Qatar* ^ 7 ) \Vt On landing at Doha I went to the Majlis of Salih al Man-a, the Shaikh's Private Secretary. Prom conversations with him I gathered that he is, like all a ’ 811 Arabs and Muslims, anti-Italian, and J alth ° Ueh h6 W3S gUarded at I encouraged him to talk freely and he appeared to be anti-British also. I went with him to Rayyan and he informed the Shaikh about.the previous evening's radio news and then began to express his views about the war. He did not seem to be genuine in expressing his views to the Shaikh but appeared to be expressing them in the manner the Shaikh likes them to be. The Shaikh was enthusiastically anti-German and anti-Italian and seemed to be genuinely so and not pretending. This impression was confirmed by Salih's artificial expression or ks 4 expression of his views before him. Sh. Hamad, the Shaikh's son, was silent all the while but from expressions shown on his face at some of his father's remarks he does not seem to hold the same views as his father. The Shaikh thinks that the defeat of the Italians is due to the reluctance of the Italian army to sacrifice their lives Just because Mussolini wants to have some more colonies. He condemned Hitler for starting ! this war and for invading peaceful people's countries and hoped to . see him down soon. After half an hour at Rayyan we returned to Doha and were invited to coffee by Jsim bin Darweesh, the A.I.O.C agent. He grumbled about the A.I.O.C. encrouching on his territory by making direct oil deliveries to the Qatar oil company and said that their action constitutes a breach of contract because his agreement with them covers the whole of Qatar, and said that alth ough he protested to them several times his protests went unheeded. We then returned to Salih*s house and he became more confident and began to talk more freely. He informed me that he wants to engage a person who has a good knowledge of the law and oil affairs as We H, and said that he had found such a person, an Iraqi lawyer, who has good knowledge of English and experienced in oil affairs a nd that he had actually engaged him for a monthly salary of ^•£). 40 plus house and conveyance allowances but that all the Otters which he sent to him, asking him to come, including some re gistered ones did not reach him. He thinks that either the oil COrn Pany,through w h om he sends his letters for posting at Bahrain, 0r the Censor at Bahrain withheld these letters. He even thinks If Ithat the registration receipts brought to him by the oil company from the Bahrain post office are false. He says that out of the ^ many letters which he sent to the Iraqi lawyer only one reached him but that the essential parts of that letter were deleted. He said tha' the company's camp manager suggests to him from time to t± M time that if he requires an interpretor he should get one through the P.A. Bahrain but he thinks that such a person would prove unsuitable because he would always be under the orders of the P.A. and the oil company and would act in their interests. He thinks that the oil I company's officials besides being men of great knowledge and experience are very tricky and he should always be on guard against their tricks. Therefore he feels that he needs the help of an experienced lawyer who knows about oil affairs to act as additio nal Shaikh's representative with the company. He also thinks that the Rulers of Bahrain and Kuwait are very negligent in having their local representatives either local persons with limited knowledge and experience or persons choosen for them by the P.As or the oil companys. He also wants to engage an interpretor to act as correspon T dence clerk between him and the oil company and as spare time English teacher for some of his relatives at a salary of Rs.150/- plus boarding and lodging. On my enquiring about local education he informed me that the Shaikh does not like his subjects to learn more than reading the Qoran and on asking him about the reason he replied with a laugh 'well, you know, clever Shaikhs like to keep their subjects in ignorance'.' From the manner he uttered this boast it seemed to me that this is due to his 'clever' advice to the Shaikh. In the afternoon I went to the ba^ar and fortunately met Hasan al Umaim, a Kuwaiti who was once my father’s clerk at Karachi. He had been in the service of the Shaikh of Qatar for some years in various Postsa and had a fair knowledge of local affairs. Last year he has been appointed as supervisor of the customs because revenues topped considerably and the Shaikh suspected that the Director and staff were helping themselves, fcx In 1938 the customs revenues were ^ s * 31,000/- and in 1939 they increased to Rs,45,000/-. Hasan infor- Be&lt; l me that the people are suffering from extreme poverty and that tne stoppage of trading with Bahrain had hit local trade very hard th °ugh the Shaikh pretends that the present state of affairs with Sahrain is beneficial to him and is in his interest. He told me thatffl ° St ° f the Pe ° Ple are s ° ^norant that they do not V about the war beyond the fact that there is anythlne genral feelings about the war are thos 0n - ^ about a dozen persons who g0 every ev i° UnCOnCern eX ° ept amon g Majlis to , 6 t0 Salih al M an'a-s Majlis to listen in to the only radio in Qatar an, k influenced by his views. He also i„f Q ' h ° “nst be very jealous of Salih al Man's h ^ Hamad iS , .. n al Man a because of the income he gets as bribes from the public and from the percentage of e / 10 %) he extracts from oil eo ‘ rnlneS (m ° Stly irom oil company coolies, drivers and :: ;r —«« a brother of the A T n r- a. ^^weesn, . * # ag6n Wh ° besides bei ng the director of c ls * 1 *» contractor .1th th. oil „„ mn mr n 11 com Pany and has er occupations, to extract such sums for Shaikh Hamad from company employees, and to do it gradually until Salih is put out his business. I have also learnt frr.m u learnt from Hasan that Salih is not » e ood terns ,1th co„ra» y omc!,!, lh , t ^ ^ nformed th. Shaikh that Salih h „ b « n „ kln( , fro&gt; ^ Shd asked th. Shaikh .heth.r they should chary, such deliveries „ f duor to his account, ,„d that th. Shaikh „s „„ch .„„oy«, .it h S«llh and told the c,„„.„y „„t t o yiv. hi. ,„y Uj „or. , Uo Informed me that th. Shaikh dislikes Salih for h,l„y , drunkard and a .an of vie. but h. Is compelled to retain hi. because he feel, helpless .Ithout hi.. Hasan Informed me that some of our Kh.lasls were mistaken by some people for being members of a party of soldiers which has come to occupy the town. This was confirmed by 0mS 01 th6 Khalasis 'ho heard some persons making such remarks. 1 'ent with Hasan through the bazars and he took me to some of the ants who appeared to be ignorant and were eager to know omething about the war. Some did notion which side is Italy.lhe rollowlnc stor&gt;r is told b y a Kuwaiti Nakhuda, Shain bin Yusuf bin Shahin, who has just arrived from Qatar. He is .a very reliable person:- A Dervish arrived recently at Doha and on his arrival he net a funeral party and followed it. After the burial he sat beside the eraxve and cried bitterly until the last members of the parti- left. Then he leit and followed two of them and after going ahead he turned round facing the two persons and began to* walk backwards v.hile gazing at one o. them, Abdul Aziz al Bakir, and crying. He did this all the way from the cemetry to the ba-ar (more than half a mile). At the bazar Abdul Aziz sat^Ffriends' shop and the Darvesh^tood opposite him fixedly gazing at him and crying. He was obsessed by this and went inside the shop and sat behind the wall adjoining the door so as to screen himselfthe Fakirs view but the latter entered the shop and sat opposite him still gazing and crying. Some persons tried to persudde him to go way but he did not do so and did not utter a word so that the people about thought he was dumb. After Abdul Aziz left he walked backwards in front him a s he did before, and when he entered his house the Dervish waited outside. When some persons came to drag him away he requested in Afgahanese (or some Indian language) that he may be allowed to gaze at Abdul Aziz for a quarter of an hour each day. i These were the only words he uttered which were interpreted by another Dervish who was for a time in Doha and knew Arabic. This went on for a few days until the Nakhuda left Doha. He describes the Dervish as having brown hair and blue eyes and white complexion, 1 He says that some people suspect that he is an Italian. He wears Afghan clothes. He may be an enemy spy pretending madness or trying to play a trick through which he may make the people believe him a holy man.Confidential D.O.No.C/296. J eted the 2nd April 1941. / y I forward herewith the copy of a story related by a Nakhuda fron Qatar. The man is probably an Afghan 'Fakir', but I would be grateful if you could kindly let me know if you hear any more about the matter. Perhaps your Agent at Doha might be able to make gome enquiries. Yours sincerely, L i S. V. Packer, Esq., Petroleum Concessions Limited, »; jn ! BahrainBAHRAI N , I*? PE RS I AN GULF. PERSONAL &amp; CONFIDENTIAL 5th April 1941 (Aleycn Clifton, Dear With reference to your D.O.No.c/295 dated the 2nd of April 1941 I suggest, if you agree, that I write to Abdullah Derweesh Fukhroo who is A.I.O.C. Agent in Dohah and also in receipt of an honorarium from us. He is intelligent and perhaps no more of a rascal than the others. ( Our Agent Mohammed Al Mana is absent from Qatar at present ). Abdullah Derweesh that we disapprove of his taking Dubai merchants to Dukhan. He will assume that this affair of the Fakir is another case in point. have a curious and in some cases not too creditable a record, and the interest the Fakir took in Abdulaziz may not be entirely chance. There is a Mohammed Bakir who n advises n the Shaikh of Ras Al Khaimah.The Bakir family seems to have been based^ on Qatar. They have had considerable connections with Bahrain and Bombay. Members of the family work ihSmission Hospital Bahrain, Bapco and at least five in Dukhan Camp. A launch will be going to Qatar Sunday or Monday, and if you think it a good idea to use Abdullah Derweesh the letter can go on this launch. When I was in Qatar the other day I mentioned to It may interest you to know that the Bakir family I attach a ' tree M in case it is of interest. Yours sincerely, Major R.G. Alban, Bahrain.t'ersonaj. Sc Confidentis i The 6th April 194i.. t!.r-nks ior your rcry info; Ef ti»e letter about the 'rokir'' end your suggestion stout using Abdullah bin on-set sh. I agree thet this would be £ good idee, tna would be {rr teful if you could kindly let me heve t:ny further informetion collected. Yours sincerely, L ^ V. Packer, Esq., Petroleum Concessions Limited, B A H R A I NT PERSOMA.L &amp; GOMFIDEKTTuT P- Sl 1 Bahrain, PERSIAN GULF. 13th April, 1941. Dear A \ Reference your D.L. dated the 6th of April 1941 , I forward herewith a reply from Qatar. Yours sincerely, Enclosures.TRANSLATION, To Mr. E.V. Packer. Kindest Regards 2 (1) Here are the particulars required 2 of e yarch° f them arrlved at 1)0hah on Thursday the 13th (2) &amp; (3) They had come from Dubai, having left it by one of the launches on Sunday evening the 9th of March. It took them four days across on account of adverse winds. (4) We found no Travel Documents with them, and made no particular enquiries in this regard at the time. (5) They seemed to speak the Persian language. One of them however pretended not to know any language that might give him away. (6) They had no apparent association with anybody in particular, except coffee shop frequenters where thev used to sit. (7) As regards their talks, one of them used to talk to foreigners and pleasure seeking people here, whilst the other avoided every body as he pretended to be ignorant of the two languages spoken in Dohah viz Arabic and Persian. (8) They showed no desire to visit the Oil Wells. I have given you in detail the information required. It appears so far that these two persons arrived at Dohah as mentioned, and there was nothing out of the ordinary that could draw our attention to them. Their intention is apparently to proceed to Al Hassa and from thence to Hidjaz, as is usual with their fellow countrymen. One of them had a letter from the Ruler of Dubai (with whom they got in touch) requesting his help for their journey to Al Hassa. Since their arrival they had been living here in Mosques as Fakirs. One of them has a strong inclination to seeking pleasure with tender youths, and is known to have possessed some money in currency notes. The other did not expose himself by any talk or otherwise.Arabic timfon J th lnsta ^ at five driver by the name of Mohammed bin lzwiyeHn^ 0f a ° amel uin Azwayed and known as 'Jalmud'. o I received your c P ri on or about’ the 8 * 5th 6 ins tan™ and y if°thev b rt arr J vin S at Dohah Al Hassa on Saturday the 12th Aprll^mf d0 n0t the7 WDUld reaoh be made regarding theirnationalitv S and i0ient i “ Testi Sation would submitted to you in due course After nem Ve ? ent ?£ whioh would be require further particulars which w! pel ? sln g tMs if you please let us know that we may take n^essa^ s?ejs? t0 SUPPl7 keep my eyL^pirfor^sufeicious^arri^LrVth f d Sha11 precaution. I assure you that I am very glaTt^ o'f^ervice to to any person^juft Is^^av^guarded your^onh 3 ° f ia lliS letter thank you for the trust you lay in me. ^ Side ' and fish out P f.!rth^r e I / f 1 at heart * 1 sil all spare no pains to Dohah. furtiler facts in regard to these men on their return to Usual Compliments. (Signed) ABDULlA DERWEESH FUKHROO. _Note. ^ ^ wh0 fo ll° wed the footsteps of Abdulaziz had pressed that he was infatuated with the said youth, but he had no secret connections with him or any talk of a suspicious nature. Please let me know if any further particulars are wanted m case they come back to Dohah.Personsi The 20th /pril 194.. Thsnk you very much for your letter of the Uth April 1941 about the Afghan H Fekir\ It ves really &lt;.pod of you to have taken ell this troulle to get me tne information. Yours sincerely, U- L V. Packer, Lsq. t Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrein.sfi 0 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULP. CONFIDENTIAL 21st May, 1941. Dear I enclose herewith a letter given to me by Saleh Al Mana, Qatar, for translation. We propose to reply that we do not think that the subject matter is of any importance and does not justify waste of time by our translator. It struck me, however, that you might be interested. The idea seems to be a new form of League of Nations supported by International Police. I suppose it is a new scheme to extract money from native potentates. I do not think Mr. Flory Monacell knows much about Arab Rulers if he hopes to obtain money from them. Yours sincerely, Enel. Major R.G.Alban, Bahrain.T Confidential B.O. N*. C/495 Dated the 34th Kay 1941 Many thanks for your confidential letter dated the 21st Kay and enclosure. Very Interesting. I agree that Arab Rulers are pretty tough nroposltione.Confl. entl.-il, D.O. No. C/642 ^)atecl the 23rd June 1941 . / A \ see in one of vour Kotor, to Wol C htaian you montionea that the Sheikh of * a t«r had been trying to obtain the services of an •Irani as Adviser in oU matters, etc. I have also fro* time to time heard this proposal ^ich appears to emanate from ^eh cl 16 Sv nf0rmtton was that he had found an •Tra^i laWyef r ^ ^ t0 ^ a food knowledge of ^U.h anu to be experienced in oil affairs 'and that this man had .e. n ent.ncod on a monthly salary of ID. 40 nlns house and conveyance allowances. That was in February of this year. 2 * 1 W0Uld be fratef ’ 11 ^ could kindly lot ae know the position is regarding this man at the present moment. ’/ours sincerely, Packer, Ssq., * ,t ‘n u gdr | L. Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bai train.2 DO/SAA.2/2522 (contd.) keeping with position and status without a definite indies M laSS °, f PerS ° nS U was P^PO^ed to emplo“ a ' ^ and any other Qatari were to be given the jobs Rs.10° or so was sufficient. Eventually after in+er minable discussions stretching over a year or more the agre ® d ^o P a y Hs. 1250/- per mensem to include both draws Rs^^S/ Nn - thlS SUm Saleh admlts th ^ he arahs Rs.250/-. No other representative has been nominnt.ed “rr; sSr sl ’* i “ H *” a You will realize that the Company, having reached agreement with the Shaikh at Rs.1250/-, would not be prepared to re-open the matter except perhaps in some special circumstances at the request of His Majesty’s Government. . ., We d o not ^ow of course, the origin of your interest m the matter at this stage, but if there is any question of an oil or general adviser to the Shaikh of £atar being put forward or nominated by His Majesty’s Government, we should like to be kept informed if this is possible. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.Alban, K.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidantla^ D.G. No. C/684 Dated the 30th JUne 1941 Iraol /dylser for Qatar Reference iteff? (6) on the list of subjects for discussion at Bahrain. 2. The proposal appears to emanate from Saleh el Mans and the latest Information (February) on my file is that he had found an Iraqi lawyer who is alleged to have a good knowledge of English end to be 'experienced in oil affairs', and that this man had actually been engaged on a monthly salary of XD.40A plus house and conveyance allowance. 3. I asked Packer if he had anything to add to this and he says that he was in ^atar in the middle of ?4ay but has heard nothing further of the proposal which he thinks is in abeyance and likely to remain so until the Shaikh offers more attractive terras end the Iraq situation becomes nornal. 4. If I hear anything further I will let you know. Yours sincerely a’ble Lieut-Colonel S. Prior, C. I. £., •olitical Resident in the i. Persian Gulf, Bahrain .gonfldentlal D, 0. No# C/685 Ttoted the 3Cth June 1941# --W \&gt; Reference your demi-official letter cf the 29th June 1941# 2 * r/any thanks for your information about the ’Irani dvieer*. I had nothing in mind rhen making this query beyond wanting to keep my record of this matter up to date. I would be vex*;? grateful if you could aak Abdullah Darwlsh or anyone else if they have any further information# 3# I would be grateful te receive a copy of your note on the subject of oil advisers which you mention in paragraph 2 of your letter.D. 0. No. C/1032 T &gt;ated the 4th November 1941. This Is just to inform you that I visited star on the 30th October. I took with me the Assistant Political Agent and the Agency Surgeon. At Dukhan we had lunch with the Acting Manager of Petroleum Development (^atar) Limited at the Camp and afterwards proceeded to Dohah by car. v 'e arrived at Raiyan, the Shaikh’s palace, at sunset and were met by Shaikh Abdullah bin &gt;aalm, hia son and heir Shaikh Hamad and others. The Shaikhs appeared to be in good health and were pleased to see us. T presented *Id greetings on behalf of the Political Resident and inyself and later in the evening we were entertained at the evening meal. ^ e spent the night at the Company’s Rest Reuse in Dohah, some seven or eight miles further on. On the next day (31st) we visited the village of Khor some 4C miles to the north near which the Company are prospecting for e terminal port. There is r very wide and shallow inlet of the sea at this place. The village is of considerable size but the Khor is useless for anything except shallow craft. On the way we stopped at one of the Shaikh’s gardens. On return we visited Wekrah to the south of Dohah. At one time Wakrah was a town of seme importance but it is now merely a rather large fishing and pearling village. The same evening we took a meal with Abdullah bin Darwish, the A.I.O.C. agent at /- ble Lieutenant-Colonel • R. Hay, C.T.&amp;., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.2 - at Doha. On the next day we returned to the Company's camp at Zekrit and thence to Bahrain. I gave Shaikh Hamad a present of some rifle cartridges at which he seemed pleased. The presence of Dr. Steele was much appreciated and he was called out to see several cases amongst the more important people. Shaikh Hamad, the heir, was himself examined at his own request. According to the Gazetteer Shaikh Abdullah is aged about 66 and his son Hamad about 46 although locally the Shaikh is considered to be much older. He is in good health andvery active. Most of his time is spent in camp, hawking or shooting game. He is gradually leaving the Government in the hands of his son Hamad who although grasping and oppressive is a man of some character. 2. There are not many people of importance at Dohah. Saleh el Mana acts as Secretary to the Shaikh and is an astute little man. Like nearly all the others he is of Ne t 1di extraction. He is fond of alcohol. Abdullah bin Darwish is the A.I.O.C. agent and has the confidence of Shaikh Hamad. He is a man of Persian extraction. 3. The Company's camp at Zekrit is situated very plea santly by the sea. As there is no local water supply, there is no greenery of any sort. The place is however healthy and everyone seems reasonably contented. About 8 Europeans including Americans are employed. The Company is always very helpful and affords us every faci lity when proceeding on tour. Yours sincerely, / u-x .CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/621 of 1941. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1« O.K.C&amp;roe Esquire* 031. # CIB.,103. t Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. 2. R.T.Peel Esquire, CBi;.,hC., 9he India Office, J^ondon, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documen t^ . British Consulate-General, BU8HIRE. Caap, Bahrain. Dated.. .10. th M py ember. 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. \&lt;r' 7 ^ Subject. Letter No.0/1032 of 4th Novenibor 1941 from the Political Agent, Bahrain. J Cop#; forwarded, with c 03.^. .Political Agent, ompl Political Agent Balirain'e visit to Qatar. iments, to Major R.G.Alban, Bahrain, for information. L. t^//(r ' ’ |&lt;i^ Translation of a letter dated 26th Jamarfi TT' 11th July 1942) from the Ruler of JaUr to ^he Folitical Agent, Bahrain. A. C. I have to draw your attention to our conversation on the subject of my need for rounds of ammunition, a specimen of which I showed you, and ^machine guns. As the present situation calls for taking- precautionar measures and as our rifles have no rounds of ammuni tion, as I told you verbally, I write to draw your attention to your promise to help in supplying me with rounds of ammunition and machine guns. I am awaiting the result of our conversation on the subject. I request you to do all you can to intervene in supplying me with what I mentioned from any place which the authorities u sual ~nding. may choose./ 5 Confidential* Ko .C/1074 To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 20th July 1942 The Hon* hie the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum I enclose a copy of a letter dated 11th July 1942, to gether with a translation, which I have received from the Shaikh of Qatar. 2. When I was at Dohah at the beginning of this month the Shaikh told rae that he wanted to be in a position to protect him self and his people rl if the enimy c©flie n # He asked me whether X could secure for him a machine gun and ammunition for it. I told him that it was most unlikely that a machine gun could be spared at the present time. The Shaikh then went on to say that he badly needed ammunition for the rifles which had been n supplied to him by the British Government'. He said that the Government had pro mised to keep him supplied with ammunition, but that he had not been given any recently and his stock was running low. I asked what the ammunition had been used on. He replied 'On gazelle', vshen I asked the Shaikh what kind of ammunition he wanted, he produced as e sample a .303 bullet, hard nosed, Mark VXX, made by Kynoch. 3. Since my return to Bahrain I have looked up the records in the Agency, and find that the Shaikh imported into Qatar in 1939 450 rifles .303 bore ^ith 225,000 rounds of ammunition. The purchase of these rifles and the ammunition had, of course, been previously authorised by the Political Resident (vide Residency Memorandum V&gt; I*} 8o.C/500 dated 4th August 193S). 4. I should have liked, while I was at Dohah, to check the number of rifles kept by the Shaikh, and to find out how much nomunition he really had left. His replies to my questions on these points were evasive. I suspect that he has more ammunition than be admits, as he is an inveterate hoarder, but reliable information could not be obtained.- 2 - (&amp;) ) W 5. Under Article III of the 1916 Treaty with Qatar the British Government is under an obligation to grant the Shaikh facilities to purchase and import from an approved source such arms and ammuni tion as he may reasonably need. In my talks with him the Shaikh did not specify the quantity of ammunition which he required, in spite of my asking him more than once how much he wanted. His reluc tance to state a definite amount was probably due to the hope, which he undoubtedly entertains, that a free issue of ammunition will be sad# to him; end the amount of free ammunition he would like would obviously be greatly in excess of the amount which he would be pre r ' e ol^ 1 - to be informed in due course what reply should be given to the Shaikh. The British Government appear to Muauuxwiuu as ne may reasonably need, and, viewed in the light of present world conditions, his request for one or more machine guns with ammunition and for cartridges for his .303 rifles does not seem unrest enable* At tne same time, the supply of arms and ammunition available at the present time is presumably strictly limited, and I suggest that the Shaikh*s request should only be seriously enter tained in so far as it relates to the replenishment of his store of •303 ammunition* pared to pay for. Folitio4 fj m Lfi:; r&lt;M mu w\ ^jf- idi' IW. I-olitloal Besident, Busdire. J.’idea3t» Oairo. Ooveroment of India, Hew Delhi. Tenth Array, Bagdad. No.1505. Dated the 1st August 194-i, 0 Ju. h . Shaikh of ^atar has asked to he sullied with machine gun and ammunition. 2. In Qatar Defence Scheme which ?/as drawn up in 1339 it was recommended that the Shaikh should he encouraged to huy 6 'Bren'’ (or Lewis) guns and mount them on light trucks, 3. Shaikh has recently received great blow in cessation of Petroleum Concessions Limited # s operations. He has accented this rather more gracefully than was expected. 4. ^ould it he possible to present Shaikh with from to 6 Italian machine guns with adequate supply of ammunition for them? 5. Shaikh has also asked for supply of .303 ammunition for rifles in his possession, under Treaty we are hound to facilitate purchases and import of arms and ammunition. I am postponing the making of any recomiiendatio % on this request until I know whether it is possible to supply him with machine guns.■■■■■■■snflnsi • '• m • ' Mn-'-g /• c/r /^O ( D.O.No. C/660. office of the Political Resident in the Persian i»ulf. Camp. Bahrain. hated the 17th August, 1943. © ' Please refer to correspondence ending with my telegram t i a ted the 1st August 1942, to tuceast. I forward herewith a copy of mideasfs telegram No. , da ino • 1505 2 * SD 34115, dated the 10th August 1942. 3. Please consult Hewitt regarding the suitability of the Breda machine guns for the purpose required and let me know the result* 4 . pf the machine guns are suitable we might perhaps ^ for four for qatar and four for Bahrain cf. paragraph 5 V ^'demi-official letter no.C/595, dated the Uth August 1942. Please consult Wakefield by post about this ani also enquire from him how much .303 ammunition if any he thinks we should give or sell to the Bhaikh cf ^atar. 5. X am sending a copy of this letter and its enclos- r * ure and also of my telegram NO.1505, dated tne st August 1942, to Wakefield* i baptain ML*G*Dixon, Ao-^nt Assistant Political Age , Bahrain*Telegram XDV* From Mideast, Cairo. To Political Resident, at .bahrain. Armindia for Government of India. No. SD 34115. Dated 10th received 15th August 1942. (Relayed under Bushire telegram No. 1605, dated the 14th August 1942). tv Your telegram No.1505 of August 1st. 1. Can release eight .88 millimetre Breda machine guns minus mountings and 5000 repeat 5000 rounds per gun.These guns ex captured armoured cars should fill role of your para graph two. 2. What quantity of .303 ammunition required 9 - MIDEAST.(&amp;) Ifel-P Extract ffom Residency D.O. No.C/595 dated 11th August 1942 (original on file 28/1-G page 71) 5. I understand tnat Shaikh Salman has complained that the machine guns which were presented to Shaikh Hamad for his own use are now being monopolised by the regular forces and the special Police. Will you kindly let me know what the position is ? If more machine guns are required by the Bahrain Government I will see if anything can be done to obtain them.lb^ 28/1-0, 28/l-F &amp; l.a/5. o.o.wo.c/ias?. The Agency f Bahrain, the 20th Auguet 1942 ^ Please refer to para 5 of your demi-official letter No .0/596, dated 11th August 1942 • 2m Before the war the Bahrain Government acquired 12 VmSm Light Machine Guns for their State Police, of which 8 were lent to the Defence Officer in the winter of 1940-41 for the purpose of A«A« defence* These 8 guns are no longer required for this purpose and Major Hewitt suggests that 4 r©turned to the State Police and the other 4 given to the Special Police. I am writing officially to Belgrave; I gather from him that Hie Highness the Sheikh is likely to concur in this suggestion. 3* In view of this development, I do not think we shell want 4 Breda Machine Guns for Bahrain, as suggested in pars 4 * c? m of your demi-official latter No.0/660, dated 17th Auguet 1942. I have written to Wakefield, asking for hie views on this and the other questions raised in your lettes. Sd. M.G* Dixon Hon 1 ble Lieut.-Colonel W.K.Hsy f C.I.S., Political Beaident in tha Persian Gulf Camp, Bahrain.Telegram 9/55 &amp; 73/68 Copy to To From I*D*V. Political Resident, at Bahrain Middle East, Cairo# Government or India, Ne* Delhi, No. T/ 553 Dated the ii^th August, 194 k.# Your telegram No# SD o411l /ugust 10th I am grateful for offer of machine guns, i hope to telegraph further both about these and • 60iS anaaunition in a fortnight»s time# Copy forwarded tot The Secretary to the Government of India, External yffairs Department, New Delhi* #/l Z 7 /»/ with reference to Mideast telegram No. SD 34115 d-tcd the loth i ugust, 194£# with reference to Residency demi-official letter No. C/Obj D; ted the 17th August, 1 - RESIDENT - NCJ CONFIDENTIaL NO# C/7,6 Oitic© oi the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# Camp, Bahrain# £4th August, U 4 ii_ - - ... ■ 9/55 ft 79/88 Int. Ord* i^olit^oal Re8ident f at Bahrain. Middle Sa&amp;t 9 Cairo. Te le gram From To No. T/642 Dated the 7th September, 1942. /kJV** Correspondence ending with your telegram SD 43355 September 2nd. 2. I ehould be gaateful for 6 Breda machine gune with 5000 rounds each. No .303 ammunition required at preeent. 3. Bahrain Petroleum Company are willing to arrange for transport of machine guns by one of their tankers to Bahrain if they are handed over to their agents Messrs. Cory Bros, at Suez. Please telegraph if you agree to do this in order that Company may be asked to issue necessary instructions. - RBSIDSHT - CumDUHTIAI. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Camp, Bahrain. 7th September, 'y&gt; ^ Copy forwarded to: The Secretary to the Government of India* External Affairs Department, ^ Mew Delhi. with reference to Mideast telegram No, SD cintea the 2nd September, 1942, The Political Agt-nt, Bahrain, with copy of telegram under reference. « .[»T Dll oT • oft tad ?0i i.V Your T/64S ol* September 7th. Bahrain petroleum Company have been asked to make necessary arrangements. in Tele gram Inter. From To political Agent, Bahra in. political Resident, Bushire No.623 Dated 21st September 1342 Following from Middle E„ast addressed to you at Bahrain begins x \ % \&gt; -Political-Confidential * No.C/1427 . To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st September 1942. ammunition per gun. You very kindly told me on September 5th that, if these were handed over to Messrs. Cory Brothers at Suez, arrangements would be made to bring them to Bahrain by the first ' available tanker, Government paying all extra charges involved. 2. Would you be so good as to issue the necessary instruc tions to Messrs. Cory Brothers. Yours truly &lt;i for Political Agent, Bahrain.Si? l-ali'* The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, CON-249. 23rd September, 1942. Arms and Amraunition for the Shaikh of Qatar. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, BAHREIN. ’ Dear Sir, I am, pleased to actaiowledge your confidential letter No. C/1427 dated 21st September, 1942 and to advise you that in pursu/ance thereto the following cable has teen despatched to Cory Brothers, Suez, who act as Agents for our associated companies* vessels ”0n behalf Political Agent Bahrein contact headouarters Kiddle East and receive for shipment to Bahrein via El Segundo or first available tanker 6 machine guns 30,000 rounds ammunition for Sheikh Qatar and advise when forwarded - Bahrein Petroleum. ' I shall be pleased to keep you advised of developments in this connection. W. P. Anderson n Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED -^T%. i. the Bahrein petroleum Company limited &amp; Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, si?. i'x I/ -' \ 26th October, 1942. No. CON-306. His Biritannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, / Please refer to your letter No. C/1427 dated 21st September, and my reply letter Con-249 dated 23rd September, 1942. The vessel M E1 Segundo** arrived this morning and when the captain was approached regarding the shipment of 6 machine guns and 30,000 rounds of ammunition for the Shaikh of Qatar, he handed over the enclosed Secret Message addressed to the Shaikh of Qatar, which is being sent to you for further despatch as necessary. The Captain advises that this message was received by him from Messrs. Cory Brothers with advice to the effect that the message would explain the failure to make shipment. If the message requires any further action in which I can be of assistance, kindly advise. W. P. Anderson. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.m Ho. C/ US'S. Political A^oncy, Bahcain, the 2dth October 1^4^, l“7E To The Chief Iiocal Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company hi mi ted Bahrain. hear 61r. ft 0 Please refer to your letter Ko.COfl-odo dated #6th Ocdober lc?42« I have opened ine envelope addressed to the Shaikh of Qatar, and Its sole contents were two vouchers, which I enclose for your inspection and favour of return to me. Cory Brothers send to your cable of £6tn October (vide your letter xNo.COW-607 dated 26tn October lv4‘c). Y«/ith thanks for your assistance, I am. Yours truly. I snail De interested to hear what repljr Messrs Political Agent, Bahrain|.a{* the Bahrein petroleum Company limited CONFIDENTIAL Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. w October 31, 1942. t i [ No. PA*520. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S POLITICAL AGENT Bahrein. ’ 0) n-u Dear Sir, Thank you for your letter C/1653 dated October 28, 1942, enclosing for otir inspection the two vouchers contained in the envelope addressed to the Shaikh of Qatar, which are herewith returned. We hope to advise you further on this subject when reply from Messrs. Cory Brothers is to hand. W. P. ANDERSON. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. SW: Jag. Attachs:IE2 Ttlegra* prom Political Resident* at Bahrain. Minister of state 9 Cairo. V/5S &amp; 79/88 S Ho. T/678 Dated the 28th Hovember 9 1942. / 1 Your telegram No. 39 November 25th. Machine guns for Qatar# I fully agree with your views, political considerations render it essential guns be given not repeat not sold to shailch. CONFIDENTIAL Office of the political Resident Copy with copy of telegram under reference forwarded to the Political Agent* Bahrain* with reference to his telegram No. 629 dated the 21st September* 1942. Ho« C/iteO in the Periian Gulf. Camp* Bahrain. Dated the 28th November* 1942* \BAHRAIN, PERSIAN 12th December, j. . Dear Herewith the letter of which I spoke to you on the telephone this morning. Yours sincerely, Hncl. E.B.Wakefield Esq., I.C.S., Bahrain. G U LF. 1942.—So.C/1891. political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th December 1342. To The Chiei* Local Representative, Bahrain petroleum Company, Ltd., Awall. Dear Sir, Will you please refer to the correspondence resting with your confidential letter N 0 .PA- 02 O dated 31st October 1342. 1 I shall be obliged if you will Kindly ensure that any packages or letters addressed to the Shaikh of Qatar which come to your Company for onward trans mission may be sent to me for disposal. Tnis request applies equally to letters or packages addressed to the Shaikh of Qatar by Military Authorities. With thanks for your assistance. I am. Yours very truly. Political ent, Bahrain(• | S'' CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/947 of 1942 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. h ' ^ Gamp, Bahrain . Dated. .1.4 th De ce.ihbe r ,194 2 1 H \3^ / Reference to previous correspondence : Residency endorsement Fo.G/92C of 28th TTovember 1942. / !■ - . ■ • - Description of Enclosure. / - / Name and Date. 1 . Telegram No.T/754 of i3th December i942 to Subarea Basra• 2. Tele gram ITo.Y/755 of l3th December 1942 to Minister of State, Cairo. Subject. I • j- ■ i:sl Machine guns for Shaikh of '^a t ar •3/55 &amp; 73/88. Telegram From To No. T/754. I.D. Political Resident at Bahrain. Subarea Basra, for Basloc. Bated 13th Becember, 194&amp;. Important Please see copy of 'most secret 1 ' 99 v w oucher No. S/32 /3 from Port Aauaunition Office ^ Basra dated 7th December 1942 to D.S.O*. PAI- FORCE of which we have just intercepted copy addressed to Shaikh of x atar. Under no cir cumstances should Shaikh be addressed direct b^ut only through Political Agent Bahrain. JA.. - Resident.Telegram From To Repeated Inter# Minstate, Cairo. Basrah. No.^8. political, Bahrain, no.41. / Dated and received 17th December 1942. T.0.0. 0020 hrs. T.O.R. 0810 hrs. T.O.D. 1010 hrs. Understand 19 boxes containing 50,000 rounds ammunition are lying in Basrah addressed to the Shaikh of Qatar, please hold up despatch pending further instructions and make every endeavour to ensure that knowledge of the existence of tnis consignment does not reach ShaiKh. - MINttlATk - Copy for Political Agent, Bahrain.9/55 &amp; 79/88 I Te legraro S • From Minstate, Cairo. To H.tt.Ooneul-Genersl* i&gt;asru. lio.iii* Repeated i'olitical Agent, Barirain. 1^0.42. Dated l7th received 18th December 1942* IMMEDIATE . .•&gt; ky telegram Mo.28 to Basra and telegram /' Ro.4l to Bahrain December 16th. i now under &amp; tari d six ireda eight milXiiDet* re machine guns also probably in Cory^s hands for Shaikh of -^atar. Please also try and hold these up in same way* • Minstate • Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain# y/Te le gram S • From Minister of State, Cairo* To Political Resident, at Bahrain. flo.43. Dated 18th received 20th December 1942. £ iour telegram JNo.T/755 December 12th. Both guns and ammunition have been despatched but as you will see from my telegrams Uos.28 and 29 to Basra repeated to you as numbers 4i and 42 1 am trying to hold them up. 2. As J- understand it original idea of giving these arms to Q,atar was put forward by British Consul Bushire as a measure of compensation to Shaikh for cessation of Petroleum Concessions* operations. (See British Consul’s telegram no.1505 August 1st.) Does this reason no longer hold good ? 3. if you wish delivery to Qatar to be cancelled and if we succeed in doing so, to which Shaikh do you wish arms to be given and for what reason ?Telegram S. From Political Resident at Bahrain. *o Hj.M’s Minister of State » Cairo Copy by hand to Political Agent, Bahrain* No. T/802. ^ •^ated 22 nd December, 1^42. Your telegram No. 43 December 18th. 2* Hay certainly contemplated some measure of compensation to Shaikh of Qatar for his disappointment over cessation of Petroleum Concessions operations, but proposal had its origin in Qatar D e f e nce Scheme which provided for six Bren or 'ewis guns. 3. We are still responsible for Qatar*s defence but with closing of oil operations our interest is naturally diminished. On the other hand Debai and Sharjah now have im portant Royal Air force installations in their Shaikhdoms and have been most helpful in meeting the demands made on them. Both have had trouble with Bedouin from interior in past and both would be strengthened by grant of two machine guns each. I therefore think that best distribution would be two for Qatar two for Debai and two for Sharjah. 4* Shaikhs should not of course be addressed direct but through Political Agent Bahrain to whom all weapons and ammunition should be sent for distribution. We have already intercepted some vouchers addressed to Shaikh of Qatar. - Resident./ ' ' CON-372 °h (-*'/S^ THE BAHRAIN PETROLELW COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrain Island, Persian Gulf. December 22, 1942. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrain, wf^ Dear Sir, ^Please refer to my letter CON-307 of October 26th, 1942 and CON-348 of December 2nd, 1942 regarding guns and ammunition to be shipped from Suez for the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Qatar. This is to advise you that the T.V. n El Segundo' has recently arrived v/ith no advice of the shipment. She will shortly sail again for this port and you may wish to make further inquiry through your channels regarding the shipment in question. For your information present orders indicate that this vessel will not be returning to Suez for some time after this trip; however there will of course be other vessels in this service. I shall be pleased to keep you advised of further developments and to assist you in any way possible in this matter. Yours very truly, Sd. W.P. Anderson. Chief Local Representative THE BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.I*/S The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. January 6, 1943. C/PA-S. His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir: In continuation of my letter Number C0N J 372 of December B2, 1942, I am now in receipt of a com munication from the Company's agents in Suez reading in part as follows: 'We have now received definite information from the Military Forwarding Office that the case delivered to us on the 4th October, 1942, without any information as to its contents and/or particulars relating to consignors or consignees, is intended for Sheikh Q^atar, and we are therefore accordingly effecting ship ment by the next available tanker.' I shall advise you further upon receipt of more specific information. W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDConfidential . No.C/45 . To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Awali. Dear Sir, c ^ *’■ 1 I am grateful to you for the information contained in your letter No.C/PA-2 dated 6th January 1943 about the case for the Shaikh of Qatar. 2. It is of great importance that the Shaikh should hear nothing about the case being consigned to him, and I shall be grateful if you will ensure that any communication for him which may come into your hands is s ent to me to be dealt with. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th January 1943. Yours truly, Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 5-S of 1943 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Reference to previous correspondence: 1 . Minister of State, Cairo, telegram l T o.46 of 28th December 1942. 2. Residency telegram Uo.4 of 1st January 1942. THE POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BU3HIRE. A.?*?. Copy of Residency telegram Ro.T/802 of 22 nd December 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Dfite. Subject. Machine guns for ^haikh of ^.atar.Tele gram Int• From Minister of State, Cairo. To ®ritconsul, Bushire*. ^o. 46. Dated 28th received 29th December 1942. Political Resident Bahrain now proposes that six machine guns originally destined for VShaikh of ^atar should now be equally divided between Shaikhs of ^atar, Sharjah and Debai. Does Colonel Prior concur ? - Minstate. Te legram From To No. 4. Dated the Political Resident, Bushire. Minister of State, Cairo. 1 st January 1942. Following from Prior. v v &lt; Your telegram -No.46 December 28th. There appears to be some misunderstanding. Your earlier telegrams were addressed to ,l Political ,, Bahrain which is Political Agent*s telegraphic address, he of course pasted them to me and 1 replied signing telegram 'Resident' which is my telegraphic address on Arab side. Proposals were therefore actually made by me. Britconsul. W.L/• ^/j'. m Telegram From To Repeated Ti I.D. Mideaet Cairo. Troopers (No.SD 93922) Britconeul Bushire. ('o.i) Dated 8th received 9th January 1943. v On the request of Resident at Bahrain 6 -Breda 8 mm. M.G. 60 magazinee and 30,000 rounds 8 mm, ammunition despatched Basra for Shaikh of ^ATAR mid Sep. for mounting light trucks as part of qatar defence scheme. - r 4 2. Resident now wishes to distribute this equipment equally between Shaikhs of &lt;S^atar, Debai and Sharjah importance of ^atar's defence having diminished owing to closure of ail operations while others now have important R.A.F. installations in their Shaikhdoms. Equipment has been held at Basra pending decision. 3. grounds to present equipment as a gift to atar as a measure of compensation for cessation of Petroleum concessions operations and to others in recogniti/fion of helpfulness in meeting demands made on them in conncection witn R.A.F. install ations. Also we are responsible for defence schemes in these Shaikhdoms. Minister of State supports. Request authority for gift. ^ P OX' Resident considers it essential on politicalConfidential C/PA-IS -tiitii i’ETitOLBUM COMPANY LPVIITED Awali, Baiirein Island, Persian Culf His Britannic ifejesty*s Political Agent, The Political Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir : ^ Date February 3,1943 No 1 ^ ±L '\n* ' / P* ' ^ /T Please refer to my letter No. C/PA-2lof January 6th and your letter . C/43 of January 12th regarding a shipment sent from Suez to the Shaikh of Qatar in care of the Bahrein Petroleum Co., Ltd. The vessel carrying this shinment was diverted, while enroute here, to Abadan. The vessel is now in port here and we have been advised by the master that, the case was discharged at Abadan on January 7th. As we have no regular vessels calling at that port you may wish to make arrangements through your channels to have the case dispatched here by use of the 'Khuzistan' or other vessels. I am attaching the Bill of Lading and manifest covering this ship ment for your use. If I can be of any further assistance in this matter please advise. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Telegram From S (20? To Consul-General, Basrah. Political Resident, Bushire. No.31. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. No.4. Cairo, for Minister of State. No.11 Dated 11th received l£th February 1943. Yo)*f telegram No.539 repeating Bahrain telegram No.110 of December 25th. MACHINE GUNS FOR QATAR. Please inform me of name of tamper manifest number and cargo item. On instructions from Minister of State Cairo 19 boxes BREDA ammunition consigned to the Shaikh of Qatar stopped here by Security Officer on December 17th while on same date consignment of Breda machine guns for Shaikh was expected shortly here. Nothing heard of their arrival. ? Identity of guns and ammunition ? ex tanker at Abadan may be resolved if you can supply information requested above. My telegram of December 17th. AMMUNITION FOR SHAIAH OF QATAR. Should be grateful for instructions regarding disposal and if possible indication of reason for detention as Ordnance Officer here reported restive by Security Officer. - BRITCONSUb - Telegram S From To Consul-General, Basrah. Cairo, for Minister of State. No.12 Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. No.32 Political Agent, Bahrain. No.5. - BRITCONSUD -bid*Telegram S (j y From Political Resident, at Kuwait. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.T/32. Dated 22nd received 23rd February 1943. 0* P- Reference my endorsement 30-S January lith. Following is repetition of Minister of State* telegram No.3 February 12th repeated Basrah No.l begins Your telegram T/802 December 22nd. GUNS FOR \ V \ SHAIKHS. It has now been agreed by all co-ncerned that two BREDA machine guns and j 10000 rounds of ammunition should be given as free gifts to each of the Sheikhs of Qatar Dubai Sharjah. 2. 3000 rounds of this ammunition are already lying in Basrah. The ? 6 guns are (group mutilated) en route and may have arrived. 3. Piease arrange onward despatch and delivery to Shaikhs in consultation with Consul-General Basrah. Ends. - RESIDENTot © Telegram S To From Political Resident, at Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated Consul-General, Basrah. No.T/33- Dated 22nd received 23rd February 1943. My immediately preceding telegram repeating Minister of State Cairots telegram No.3 February 12th. onward despatch of guns and ammunition to you at X Bahrain in accordance with suggestion in paragraph 3 of your telegram 110 February 8th (repeated Basrah under my telegram 539 February 9th) and inform me of ? tneir arrival. 3. To Bahrain only. No repeat no action should as yet be taken regarding delivery to Shaikhs. Please arrange direct with Basrah for RhSIDRNTFrom Political Agent, Bahrain. To Consul-General, Basrah. No.155. Datea the 54th February ld43. /f' He^rence Political Resident»s telegrams T/32 and T/33 February 25nd. Grateful for advance information about snipment guns and airmiunition which may please be consigned to me. It is very important that name Qatar be obliterated from cases. - POLITICAh - nTe le gram From To inter urdy. Ordinance Mut . Political Resident, / \ v Bueli ire. ^o. Nil Dated llth, received the 14th February 1943# Follov/ing addressed to Middle Sast repeated British Consul Buahire received from Troopers .No# 50615 UM February 6th begins p / 9 ^ * our SD/93922 January 8th. Distribution as gift repeat gift agreed. CONFIDENTIAL Wo. 155-S British Residency A Consulate General, Bushire, the 14th February 1943. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, BAHRAIN . with reference to Residency endorsement wo. the nth January 1943. 30-B datedTexegram From To No. Inter Ordy. Consul-General, Basrah. Political Agent, Bahrain. £r Dated Sdth Feb. received 1st March 1943. arrange shipment one case machine guns and ammunition now in I.V».T. warehouse Abadan to Political Agent Bahrain. 19 cases ammunition nere awaiting transport arrangements. In accordance with your wish request being made to obliterate name qAXaR from all cases. Tne preamble (consisting of 23 groups) of the above telegram is in a code not held by us. repetition in G.l.C. ? GUNS FOR SHAIKHS Local M.'V.T. requested to - COHSUij-GLHERiUj 1 p ^ / rr y &amp; tTelegram Inter Oray. From Consul-General, Basrah. _ . &gt; To Political Agent, B&amp;nrain. Wo.8, Bepeatea Britconsul, Bushire. Wo.44. Reference my telegram Wo.30. p } Political Agent, Kuwait. Wo.7. Reference his telegram T/33 to Bahrain Cairo. Wo.15. Reference their telegram Wo.l to Basrah \ '• Datea 2&amp;th February, repetition received 4th March 1943. GUNS FOR SHAIKHS. Local M.Vv• T• requested to arrange shipment one case machine guns and ammunition now in I.W.T. warehouse Abadan to Political Agent Bahrain. 19 cases ammunition here awaiting transport arrangements. In accordance with yaur wish request being made to obliterate name qATAR from ail cases. — CONSUn gbwbral — I&amp; I n/C The Agsncy, Bahrain. s.s.' BARCD/k n which arrived here from Basrah on the 11th oi Inarch, lyt^, discharged the following cargo for the Agency:- rOL. AGE1T 1 (Jase machinery which have since been l^inded.*^ The above is for your information. — IbihAGrUR IKPOKT Y^SiJ, A .h.( 214 ; DEBIT NOTE No. C &amp; F/ /) Dr. to GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO., LTD., BAHREIN. —4 packages, as per margin Clearing u ^charges incurred Shipping on ex s.s. per Voy. No. to ===== Clarks &amp; Nos. i&gt; Particulars of charges Customs Revenue Stamp Landing charges Import Yard charges Customs duty Coolie hires Loading/Unloading Khanchies Rs Porterages Rs Amendment fee Rs Cert. Stamp Rs. Export charges. Freight to £ @ e x.... Rill of Lading fee Rs. No. Insurance Premium £ Policy No Boat hire to steamer Rs Petties Rs Loading into boat Lorry hire and handling Agency fee Rs. *: qj. Rs. &lt;r /(' P u 15 3 - d E. &amp; O. E. BAHREIN,. •' I .^±.4 For GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO., LTD., i . I f 4i Manager.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY-LIMITED lb charges in connection with the shipment of six machine guns &amp; ammunition for the Shaikh of &lt;&lt;tatar from Suez. Ref. Our letter C/P A-14 of February 7th, 1943. Ra* 45. 10. 0 (Rupees forty five &amp; annas ten only)GO-10*2 BP (50M-7-38) THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED BAHREIN ISLAND, PERSIAN GULF. October 5l&gt; 1943. Political Agent, n) TA 193 . Manama, m Bahrein. ^2RESS Rj&amp; .irrANOBS TO THE COMPANY - NOT TO KDIYIDUAI3'OR DiiPTS SHIPPED TO =^= FROM DATE F. O. R VIA CAR NO. FRT. PPD. OR COLL FOR CUSTOMER'S USE TERMS CALCULATIONS T. V. 10-30 CUSTOMER’S ORDER NO. REQN. NOX ^ ^ INV. NO. - It}- ^ additional charges incurred by Cory Bros, at Suez in connection with shipment of Machine Guns and Anmunition for Sheikh of Qatar, additional charges incurred by Cory Bros, at Suez in connection with loading on board s.s.El Segundo 2 captured Italian Guns. / Rs. 28. 0. 0 ' 120. 5. v 0 Rs.148. 5. 0 Rupees one hundred &amp;• forty eifght annas five/only) refer our le^^r C/PA-14 dated ?th February 1943). /Da*Vi INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record Ref. No. IOL: I OR Date Name Process No. of exposures 1 2 3 &gt; 4 5 6 REFER.TO THE SPECIALIST CONCERNED INDIA OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM — I ? St V' '</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00036d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/142</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00036d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/142</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/A/5 II Administration: Qatar affairs'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-21T18:19:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (239 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are filed in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 218-238). Circled serial numbers in red ink, which occur occasionally in the papers, refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 241; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 4-240; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence concerning Qatar affairs, particularly the supply of arms and ammunition to Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, the Ruler of Qatar [‘Abdullāh bin Jāsim Āl Thānī].The principal correspondents are the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Shaikh Abdullah; HM Minister of State, Cairo; Ernest Vincent Packer, Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, and Petroleum Concessions (Qatar) Limited; other British officials in the region; and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO), the Eastern Bank Limited, and the Government of Bahrain.The papers cover: the granting of permission to Shaikh Abdullah to import 450 rifles, .303 bore, with 225,000 rounds of ammunition, and fifty Mauser rifles, 7.9 mm bore, with 25,000 rounds of ammunition, December 1937 - March 1939 (folios 6-104); a request by Shaikh Abdullah for the supply of armoured cars fitted with machine guns, July 1938 - July 1939 (folios 81-109); reports on Qatar affairs from Ernest Vincent Packer, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain, and by the Political Agent, Bahrain (including relations between Qatar and Bahrain, and correspondence concerning the appointment by Shaikh Abdullah of an Iraqi adviser on oil affairs), December 1939 - November 1941 (folios 115-157); and a further request by Shaikh Abdullah for machine guns and ammunition, the resulting dispatch to the Gulf of six captured Breda machine guns and ammunition, and the Political Resident's decision that the machine guns should be distributed equally between the Shaikhs of Qatar, Dubai, and Sharjah, 'the importance of Qatar's defence having diminished owing to the closure of oil operations, while others now have important R.A.F. installations in their Shaikhdoms' (folio 199), July 1942 - October 1943 (folios 159-212).The Arabic language content of the file consists of approximately thirty folios of correspondence (with translations into English) between the Political Agent, Bahrain, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the Ruler of Qatar.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Armoured cars</topic></subject><subject><topic>Machine guns</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Qatar</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited, Manager, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Ammunition</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rifles</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00036d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>