<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000102_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-18T10:27:48.832Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Cover for Enclosures in Weekly Letter No. dated from Secretary, Political and Secret Department, India Office, to Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Government of India. MISCELLANEOUS PAPERSI V o r fpJ&lt;PRNiW|pNT OF INDIA. / 6T9 jDepartment. ^ EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). ^ ''' * — Thii i* an ORIGINAL rmssige aanl by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication mors expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hai been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in toe form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 143 - 80/39. Dated ^the 9th January, 1946. 19 To RETAXANDUM LONDON Repeated FOREIGN NEW DELHI POLITICAL KUWAIT /W^W^fXour express letter No. 1^x1.^142/ 45 dated the 27t)v actober, 1945, paragraph 3. Surplus Vehicles. 2. In view of the acute shortage of motor vehicles in Kuwait the Political Agent requests that Kuwait may be allotted a share of surplus vehicles available for export. Following are requirements conditional upon shipment being made within the first half of 1946 : - Ten passenger cars of not less than 20 Horse Power (saloon or tourers) and ten light lorries of up to one ton capacity, preferably with open-box bodies. Failing these ten station wagons would be accep table. American makes are preferred to British comparative ease of obtaining spares, should be the most recent models if Political Agent 1 s request can be met at = BRITAIN = the above has been authorised. 7 . - Secretary th the Political Resident in th&amp; Persian Gulf. G.A.M. owing to the All vehicles obtainable. 3. Grateful an early date. The issue of S. 44 (Signature) (Designation) MGIPC—SI—2385(S&amp;P)MFP-(M-1744)—3.12-40—20,000.DEPTL. No. S—*- 6 j- DRAFT TELEGRAM m Wt CYPHER (l- tii mwmm ** ( W|| 1 ( dSUlUKIli' —tiii No.. 1 ?/'. ^ 0 . 0 . 'Hx, Your Express Letter No. F.40(21 )-ME/45 of 8 th January. Supply of lorries to Persian J3ulf. Maximum of 12 lorries may be supplied -Wide ^ ^ for Persian Gulf from Mutual Aid stocks as special case. Careful note should be kept From Secretary of State for India Tr) Government of India, External Affairs Dept. Repeated to ... /2^4&gt; W* of proceeds as vehicles concerned may eventually have to be regarded as included in those supplied to India on repayment basis. _ (4302) Wt. 41647—P171 25m. 12 44 G.S.St. Gp. fi20The Secretary External Department, n7 The question of the supply of Mutual Aid lorries to the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms has been discussed with the Treasury and as a result Treasury concurrence has been obtained Wfs, the grant of special permission for the supply of Mutual Aid vehicles up to a maximum of 12, The position in regard to the supply of vehicles from Canada to India was that some portion of the supply were regarded as provided for the purposes of under Mutual Aid and that a further proportion was regarded as supplied to the Government of India partly under Mutual Aid and partly on a repayment basis. The actual proportions have yet to be determined but it may be necessary to regard the lorries sent to the Persian Gulf as forming part of the lorries for which India will have to pay. For this reason a careful record must be kept of the proceeds and I suggest that you should reply to the External Affairs Department on the lines of the draft telegram below. I think that it would be advisable to telegraph because Canadian supply questions are being discussed in Ottawa this month and India may very shortly be called upon to negotiate with the Canadian Government on this subject. // / /}i Telegram®i (Shipping) “SHIPMINDER, TELEX, LONDON.” (Inland Transport) “TRANSMINR^TEmL^ONDON.” Telephone: ABBEY 7 WTN 1g) 'SHIPMINDER, TELEX, LONDON rransport) 'TRANSMINRY^TELEX-^Of TILE COPt; / Ch ) 0 arm / U ^4 Any further oommunication should be addressed tck;jL* '*** THE DIRECTOR GENERAL (address as opposite) and the following -reference quoted :— ZV. 27/1/3. Your Reference. v MiNisfRY of War Transport, v W $/ 3 , Fitzmaurice Plap^ Berkeley Square, London, W.l. * 9. 8 DEC 1945 Dear Sir, This Ministry has now discontinued the issue of licences to acquire new vehicles. Consequently the allocation of new vehicles to Government Departments from the production available for civilian requirements will no longer be the concern, of this Department, Any future requirements of new vehicles you may have should be made the subject of a direct order on the Ministry of Supply (F.V.2. - Mr. Hart), The Adelphi, Strand, W.C.2. 5 1 'NOjA &lt; -me hS, A Yours faithfully, G.D. FRAZER.I Zlfaocpf' • Jiixt. 60 ^ 7/45 &gt;»,&lt; y* &lt; •. r • Dexr Fraser, V/ We have been approached for assistance in obtaining *?rl &lt;&gt;. nuLiber of oare and. other vehicles by the British Adviser to the Government of Bahrein (Persian (kOf) a British protected state. The Adviser, who is at present in this countiy, hes approached various manufacturers here for the supply of motor vehicles with very little success. Ho considers tha eailp supply of two cars absolutely essential. He has obtained a conditional promise of delivery for one and has as ed us whether it will be posrible for a seoond to be obtained from the M.W.T. pool. I am accordingly writing to ask whether the M..7.T. woulu be prepared to make available a second-htiwi saloon car ox about 2.0 h.p. for the Bahrein Government. We can certiiy that the Bahrein Government’s need is most serious and deserving to be met if possible, and would be willing for the cost to be borne by this Department in the first instance, ourselves recovering it from the Bahrein Gover^iment. Yours sincerely, ir * A. K. HARRISON G.D. Frazer, Bsq., kinistiy of War Transport, 2/3 Fitzmaurice Place, Berke ley s quai’e, W . 1 .— Telegrams! (Shipping) “SHIPMINDER, TELEX, LONDON.” (inland Transport) 'TRANSMINRY, TELEX, LONDON.” Telephone: ABBEY 7711 EXTN. Any further communication should be addressed to— THE DIRECTOR GENERAL (address as opposite) ind the following reference quoted ZV.30/33 Your refew^^e . 6097/4.5 Dear narrison, Ministry of War Transport, 2/3, Fitzmaurice Place, Berkeley Square, London, W.l. 31st December, 1945. With reference to your leuter of 27tu December, our pool of cars nas now all been allocated, and we are not therefore in a position to allocate a car to the (rovernment of Bahrein, but. in any case we ceased supplying cars from our pool for use abroad some months ago, as the few cars we nad left were required for use in this country. Yours sincerely. sUja F.A. K. narrison, 3sq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.^’Xt. 6097/45 27 th Deooiiiber, 1945 JDear Belgrtive, I have taken up with our J£. &amp; 0 , Xtoijartiaont her© th© question of obtaining cars for Bahrein about which you have spoken to ja©. The business of supply ing goods 1 ° i r ^ lG ^e^sian U-ulf has now boon taken over by a branch of tue Migh 0OiIFi^is£:ioner , s Office viz. the India Supply Commission, 45/47 Mount St., W.U They have been sent a copy of th© noting on the subject and are now looking to see wliat can be done to help you either tlirou^i the Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders, the Department of Overseas Trad# or the Board of Trade. I have itself written to the M.J.T. to oak whether they can make one car available from their pool. If you have the time it ;:dght possibly be v^orth your while calling cn Mr. Benjar-iin of tte India Supply Commission, though as I said they are setting the wheels m motion uhere. Another possible source which has been suggested to us is the Surplus Stores Division of the Ministry of Supply, Great ©stminster House. Thep ..daht not agree to release a car for export to Be. i ire in, but it might possibly be worth your while trying thorn. I understand that there will probably be no u iff iculty in arranging an air passage for you about the ioiddle of January. Yours sincerely, * A. • # 0. Dalrymple Belgrave, Ksq., C.B.K 1 Queens Gate i lace, S.W.7. Harrison, 4 ^’ Secretaiy, External Department, Motor cars for civilian requirements are still in short supply. Manufacturers’ order books are full. Export control of ”destinations” has been removed and the manufacturer is free to sell where he wishes. I can think of no good reason why a manufacturer should give priority to Bahrein over other customers; it is not likely to be an important market for good cars. But Mr. Belgrave might be able to persuade a manufacturer other than Humbers to give him priority for at least one car. It might be worth while contacting the Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders, G-.H.Jeans of the Department of Overseas Trade and the Board of Trade (Mr. Benjamin of the India Supply Coranission could give you the name of the man in the Board of Trade to contact). I think you should try the M.W.T. pool, though I share your doubt that they would release a car for export to Bahrein. Mr. Belgrave might try the Surplus Stores Division of the Ministry of Supply, Great Westminster House, but I doubt also whether they would release a car for export. I assixne there is no reason why Bahrein should not buy a car in America if they wish to do so and have the dollars to spare and this might help in discussion with the Department of Overseas Trade* As you know, however, this Department is no longer actively engaged in work of tliis nature and I would suggest/suggest that either you or Mr. Belgrave should consult Mr. Benjamin of the India Supply Commission- who, I an sure, will be ready to do all he can in the matter.Secretar E, &amp; 0 , ent&gt; Please refer to the Express Letter of 27th October below which was drafted by your Department* Mr*Belgrave the Adviser to the Bahrein Government is at present in this country and has approached various manufacturers here for the supply of motor vehicles. He tells me that none of them, with the exception of Humbers, will under take to accept orders even for delivery at some distant date* Mr.Belgrave says that the Bahrein Government are in extremely serious need of motor vehicles and many of those at present in service are literally falling to pieces* He has a detailed and fairly lengthy list of requirements. He considers the very early supply of two cars absolutely essential; one of these he thinks he can obtain now from Messrs*Huabers if he places a more considerable order for delivery at a later date* He has enquired whether we can obtain a second car for him from tiie M.W, T, pool either new or secondhand^ aiw+r 2 c / From M,W,T 1 s letter of the 19th April flagged, it seems that the M.W,T. mi^at be able to help from their pool, though I am not sure whether they would regard the Government of Bahrein as eligible to draw on it* It should be worth trying anyway* Perhaps however you know of some other way in which the Government of Bahrein* s requirements might more readily be met (see paragraph 3 of our Express Letter of 2?th October), I should be grateful for any comments or ^'ugmacs'+'.'i rvr&gt; Q_v IIIDIA OFFICE, EXTERNAL DEP.JlTi^Hr EXPRESS LETTER OiXR i.-uilL) From: Secretary'of State for liidia ^ To: Government of India, External Affairs Department, -Repeated to: Political Resident m the Persian Gulf and Political Agent, Bahrein Dated: ^-October, 1945• No, Ext♦5142/45 Your express letter, D. 10865~i.ll/45 dated 25th September, enquiring about the possibility of obtaining motor vehicles fran the United Kingdom for the Bahrein Government, •‘4L1 types oi motor vehicles caniiiipw be obtained from the United Kingdom aaid manufacturers are permitted to undertake production for export without restriction as to type. Load carrying vehicles are naturally in great demand and delivery may be protracted, II it is desired to obtain supplies of new motor vehicles orders should be placed as soon as possible direct with the manufacturers, as in most cases orders are executed strictly in accordance with the dates on which they are received, 3* there are a certain number of surplus vehicles of all types available for export. If it is desired to investigate the possibility of obtaining a.y of these surplus vehicles full details of the numbers and types required must be given so that steps may be taken to approach the Department responsible for granting release, -SjfcO A. K. HARRISON The issue of the above has been duly authorised,J E 5142 r !L-\ rn on rt'P iTv %^4 q iixt To - Zenodotia* London. No. D.10865-Mfi/45.Dated ^5^ Septr. *40. Bahrain Grovernment enquire whether in view of acute shortage of motor transport in Bahrain there is any possibility of obtaining motor vehicles from United King dom. 2. Please telegraph if vehicles obtainable and if so what types i.e. new or secondhand, cars, trucks, lorries, or station wagons. Issue of above has been authorised. Sd: Raja Ram Assistant Secretary to the Uovt of India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000102_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3696</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000102</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3696</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/115(1) 'Provision of vehicles for the Shaikhdoms'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T22:36:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (23 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 25; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the supply of cars and lorries for Bahrain, Kuwait and Persian Gulf shaikhdoms.The file contains correspondence between the Government of India, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Secretary of State for India, the Ministry of War Transports, and the Political Adviser to the Government of Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Transport</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Cars</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000102#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>