<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003ae_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:10:03.204Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">£v». My dear Sir Rupert, -5 Please refer to your demi-official letter No. 101-3 dated the 12th Jan ;;a ry, 1948. Tile Shaikh informs me that the informal agreement in question referred only to visas for the Lebanon, but that he had heard privately from Izzat Jaafar who is now in Syria that the Syrian Government were likely to follow suit and permit the entry of ai r-travellers from Kuwait without visas* Yours sincerely, Sd. M.P.O’C. TANDY. The Hon'ble Lt.-Colonel Sir Rupert Hay, K. C. I .K. ,C.3.I ., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. Ho . ZH 9 * -3. 1. 2 . 3.. 4. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 27 th January 1948. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, LONDON ,^ The British Middle East Office, CAIRO , His Majesty’s Minister, BEIRUT, His Majesty’s Minister, DAMASCUS, in continuation of Residency endorsement No.lQ2~S dated the 12th January 1948. RHL.Please refer to your demi-official letter No*35 dated the 6th January 1948 regarding the foreign relations of Kuwait. 2. I agree with the views expressed in your third paragraph. 3. Will you please confirm that the informal arrangement relates only to visas for the Lebanon and does not also cover visas for Syria. 3d/- Yv.R. Hay. Major M.P. O'C Tandy, Political Agent, KUWAIT , LB f CONFIDENTIAL No.102-3 •oOo* PAH 3IAN GLLF HE31DENGY BAHRAIN , the 12th January, 1948. Copy, with copy of letter under reference forwarded with compliments to:- Kis Majesty^ Secretary of St^e for Commonwealth Relations, L ONDON 2. British Middle Bast Office, CaIRC, 3. His Majesty’s Legation^ BmlxNJT .. 4. His Majesty’s Legation, D/uuASCUS . ’LB'EXT J TBE POLITICAL AGENCY, KUV/iilT the 6th January, 1948 Foreign Relations of Kuwait My dear Sir Rupert, The following paragraph appeared in the magazine A1 Za’tha for December 1947 which is published in Cairo by the Kuwait Educational Mission '•Between Kuwait, Syria, and Lebanon, His riighness Shaikh Abdullah A1 Mubarak is issuing visas on the passports of persons wishing to travel to Syria and Lebanon in accordance with the agreement reached between Kuwait and these'two countries.' 2. I asked Shaikh Ahmed the same day as I saw it what was the meaning of the notice, and he expressed annoyance with the author for misrepresenting the correct facts which, he stated, are as follows:- Shortly after the Middle East Airlines started flying fruit and_vegetables to, Kuwait one of their technical managers called T'auzi al Hass came to Kuwait and was informed that Kuwaities would find it difficult to make use of Middle East Airlines aircraft for return to the Lebanon because of delay in obtaining visas for that country. In due course he replied that M. Bechara al Khomy had agreed that Kuwaities going to the Lebanon by air would be given Lebanese visas on arrival and could safely leave Kuwait without any visa. There has been no 'agreement' between the two countries. Shaikh Abdullah al Mubarak does not issue visas but merely 'exit permits'. ■ L ^ consider that there would be any advantage in drawing attention to the report by having it officially contradicted. Yours sincerely, Sd/- M.F.O'C Tandy, The Hon*Die Lt.Colonel Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003ae_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3389</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003ae</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3389</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 27/26 ‘PASSPORTS. VISAS FOR TRAVELLERS TO SYRIA AND THE LEBANNON. FROM KUWAIT.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-19T23:47:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 5; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Agent at Kuwait, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf , regarding visas for travellers to Syria and the Lebanon from Kuwait.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Lebanon</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Syria</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Visas</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0003ae#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>