<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:53:02.397Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CQmD^riAL . D.O* »#. C/229 political AOKifcnr, BAHRAIN. 12th February 1945. (My dear Sir Geoffrey) A deal 1* heard these days about how necessary it is for the export trade of the United Kiugdom to be increased on the termination of the present war but little appears to be being dona, anyway through official channels, to brinf about this desirable state of affairs, v/hile 3nr manufacturers are silent and, as I was given to understand vhen in Cairo in October of last year, the Board of Trade do not welcome even semi-official support for British business advertising, our American friends are losing no time in endeavouring to acquire markets left vacant by the Germans and the Japanese. American advertising literature not only in the form of the periodical T, Life H but also as special sales catalogues is arriving in Bahrain anr' o'\ th^ frucisu* coasts, but I have yet to see any individual or collective attempt by British business t# draw tue attention of Persian Gulf merchajits to British products. £, It is now that our mnufacturers should be working to acquire control of the per&amp;iAr GvJLf market and should be doing all in their grower be secure the whole or at least a part of tha trade which was in the of Japan and Germany uu till Defore thl' war. Why endeavours are not /being The Hon^le Sir Geoffrey prior, K.C.I.iT.» The Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE*2 y being made by British manufacturers at this present ^mcture to establish agencies in Kuwait, Bahrain, and Muscat and on the Trucial coast I cannot understand* It is net because there are no local merchants prepared to accept such agencies for I have personal knowledge of respectable and able businessmen who are anxious to accept agencies for British manufactured goods* I am not suggesting that our manufacturers should necessarily go to the advertising length of the •philoo* corporation of America who have recently offered a free passage to and from the rmited States of America to an employee of their Agent in Bahrain who would be given a fre? course at the expense of the Company in radio repairs and air conditioning i maintenance but I do consider that we should do all we can to keep the names of well known British products before the public eye and that this should be done both by advertising and by personal contact by travellers* 3. Our foreign trade when this war is over will be of the.greatest Importance and nothing should be left undone which can in any y/ay aid in acquiring new markets* I can see no harm in pressing our wares to the utmost extent of our power at the present time nor can I see any reason why our manufacturers in the United Kingdom should not book orders for fulfilment at some future date* Let no promises to deliver be made, and no commitments as regards the » y**-—^ ... ? . V-A period of time which will elapse before delivery can be made, but manufacturers should maintain lists of provisional orders to be carried out in rotation. when it seems reasonably possible that any particular order can be executed then the purchaser could be given an estimate of cost, a forecast of time required for delivery, and be asked whether he wishes to confirm his order* be are not committing ourselves in any way.3 4 # jt is not only British manufacturers who would do well to interest themselves more closely in the markets of the Persian Gulf but also Indian manufacturers for while air conditioning, machinery, electrical appliances, and manufactured wool/en goods of high quality may oe cousiuerer to be fields in which the United Kingdom with her equipment and resources is best qualified to compete India is by far the best equipped to acquire practically the whole of she cotton piecegoods market of the Gulf which v/as unsil almost entirely was in the hands of Japanese manufacturers* Instead however of pressing her wares on the Persian Gulf market India has made the export of cotton piecegooas irom India to the Persian Gulf so difficult that only the threat of nakedness itself suffices to force the peoples of this area to compete with the thousand and one regulations which must be complied with before goods can be exported from Indian ports* Such regulations and restrictions have caused merchants to look to the Vest for their better quality cotton goods and the United States of America will very shortly be holding a market which might easily have been acquired by businessman in India* Once this has happened Indian manufacturers will find it very difficult to eliminate j\ ^ United States goods and will have to be content vith supply-n^g the cheaper qualities of cotton piecegoods dntil $uch time as some enterprising country follows in Japan*s footsteps and drives out Indian goods from this very profitable market. During the years which I have spent in this part of the world I have never seen an Indian trade Journal in the hands of local businessmen. 5. I suggest that the Ministry of Information in the V /United KingdomUnited Kingdom and the Information and Broadcasting Department of the Government of India should produce small advertising pamphlets printed in Arabic and Persian designed to bring to the notice of local merchants leading British and Indian manufactures. The cost of such publications would be covered by the income from the sale of advertising space. Yours sincerely,V CONFIDENTIAL . No.3076-36/43.b. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 30th July, 1945. From To Esq., C.J. Pelly, n 0.B,E., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. The IIon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre. jm Sub.1ect» Cotton placegoods from the United Kln/.;, 0 !a. Sir, I have the honour to say that some merchants in Bahrain have had samples of cotton piecegoods sent to tht.m, without any request being made by them, from American firms in the United States of America. One merchant in particular, Mr. J.K. Khedouri, who has for many years dealt entirely in British piecegoods has expressed the fear that unless more piecegoods are made available from the United Kingdom, American manufactures may, during the period of restriction of imports from the United Kingdom, capture the market. He points out that a particular pattern or design of piecegcods, if once established in Bahrain and once having acquired popularity with the people, would be difficult to oust from the market. 2. The posJ tion regarding piecegood supplies for Bahrain as I understand it (and I am liable to correction not being in possession of all the facts) is somewhat as follows. Bahrain, for her essential requirements during the war, has been considered to be dependent on India and has been allotted a quota of 400 tons for 1945. At the same time there is an allotment of 96 tons for 1945 from the United Kingdom and 76 tons from the Uaited States of America. Imports from all sources for the years 1935-36, 1936-37 and 1937-38 were 2067 tons, 1672 tons and 1878 tons respectively of which an average of 13# was from India, 3# from the United Kingdom and 84# from Japan. Imports from the United States of America were negligible. 3. Middle East Countries, through the Middle East Supply Centre, are entitled to Cotton Board Replacement Certificates for yarn, and manufacturers in the United Kingdom are able more easily to supply their demands than is the case for Bahrain for which releases of yarn are not provided foi. In effect, manu facturers of piGcegoods in the United Kingdom report that without yam releases they, even if they succeed in obtaining the piece- goods for export, cannot supply them in any quantity or at a price comparable with that for Middle East Countries for instance!- Voil quality No.18944 has been quoted at 17i d. per yard for Saudi Arabia. Voil quality No.3j8944 has been Quoted at 30 to 36 d. per yard for Bahrain. 4. Whilst therefore it may be desirable for Inaia to retain her responsibility for meeting Bahraini essential requirements, I am of opinion that every assistance should be given to merchants to obtain a higher proportion of piecegoods from the United King dom in order to retain what was at one time a predominantly British market - a market which was last invaded by the Japanesee&gt; 2 « article /and now may be stolen by .America v s business enterprise unless some action is taken by His Majesty's Govormaant to ensure the release of manufactures for Bahrain. I am also under the impression that the piocegoods market In this part of the world should, with the disappearance of the Japanese article, prove an excellent field for British manufactures and might compensate for a loss of trade In piecegoods elsewhere e*£«. in India itself. I have the honour to be, Your most i servant, Political Agent, Bahrain.V D.O.No. C/254. OFFICE OF THE POLITICAL RiiSIDBWT IN TJffi KHSIAN GULF. CAMP, SHIHAZ. the 11th September, 1945. (Jalifain Receipt rr I am forwarding you a copy of Pally 1 # latter No, 3076-36/43.b. dated Bahrain, the 30th July, 1946, on the subject of cotton plecegoods from the United Kingdcnu Pally points out that there is a promising market in Bahrain for piecegoods from the United Kingdom which ijaericrin enterprise is already seeking to supply. I agree with the conclusions at paragraph 4 of his letter, and merely add the co ment that India need have no anxiety in seeing British plecegoods flow increasingly into Bahrain. Even if India herself should not have her hands more than full for some years in supplying her needs and the needs of the Far East, which will offer a market the more vast because, presumably, Japanese competition will be restricted. I point out that British plecegoods may be expected to be or luxury or near-luxury quality and will compete, not with Indian, but with merlcaxx lines of a similar high quality. 3. X have already reco amended elsewhere (vide ray telegram No. T/134 of the 18th July, 1945) and the Government of India have supported the proposal, vide Foreign telegram No. 6794 dated the 9th August, 1945, that an increase of shipping space from the United Kingdom to the Gulf should be provided early. I trust the India Office will be able to Implement this move since the threat of American compfetition provides further grounds for ensuring that an increased flow of goods from United Kingdom and Empire sources reaches the Gulf. I hope it will be possible to persuade the home authorities to take action, which must be urgent if foreign enterprise is to be forestalled, to provide for Bahrain and the Gulf states generally competitively-priced British piecegoods in liberal quantity. I am sending a copy of this letter with the enclosure to Donaldson. Yours sincerely, Sd. A. G. Galloway. Lieutenant Colonel R. R. Burnett, C.I.E., O.B.E., Joint Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Depart ant, New Delhi. « Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain.INDIA OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/369</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/369</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/24 I Post-war trade'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-03T09:44:53</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folio 9. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional incomplete foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-9; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence sent and received by the Political Agent at Bahrain concerning measures to increase the export of goods from the United Kingdom and India after the end of the Second World War, when American products started arriving in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>