<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00007a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T02:03:47.512Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 58383/13. Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ** A j January 9th, 1914. With reference to your letter P.3054 of the 7th. August respecting the acquisition of land adjoining the Legation House at Gulhek, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that His Majesty’s Minister having reported that the land in question could be he has authorized a suggestion of Sir W. Townley that the balance should be expended on enclosing it with a wall, a work for vfoich it appears that credit would, in any case, have been asked at a later date. I am to express the hope that Sir E. Grey may assume his action has the concurrence of the Secretary L,213. bought for One thousand two hundred end thirteen pounds of State for India in Council I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant le Under Secretary of State, India Office.14064. I. 1529. 1000—10/1912. iteference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Letter No. Rec. /(/191 g _ ‘m ^ Referred to day of 4 ^ 191 g k c^ju ? r - ^ (WVU^ . i ^ ^Jt ti ^ ^5 . &lt;&lt;7 ^ iy \4 ■:&lt; In any further comnnmication on this subject, please quote no. 52239/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Office, London. Sir:- 03. I Foreign Office NOvemlDer 24th, 1913. 4 c s ^ ? With reference to your letter of the 13th. February P.4980/12 reppecting the building of a new dippenpary at Oulahek, I am directed by Secretary Pir E. Orey to tranpmit to you a further letter from Hip !!ajepty'p Office of r orkR recommending additional expenditure on the object in queption which will caupe an excepp on the original eptimate of One hundred and three poundp. Fir F. Grey approvep thepe recommendationp and I am to enquire whether, in the circumptancep, the Secretary of State for India in Council would be dip- poped to concur in a moiety of the paid excepp being borne by Indian revenue p. I am COPY TO INDIA 191.S. Sir, Your mopt obedient. humble Servant, * 25N0V1S13 C e Under Secretary of Ptate, India Office.ia- *259) IHS MAJKSTY'S OFPICK UP WORKS, tc., STORE'S GATii, iasriausTjSK, sa. 15th i'.ovei ber, 1913. Sir reieranc© your iotter oi tiio 24th ©bruaxy last (/J'ih/1^;, i am directed by the First Coraiiissioner of his itaje^ty s Works, etc., to enclose, x'or the information of becreta^ dir h. Grey, an extract from a letter of the 12th August last xrom Dr. Ueligan, the Physician to His Majesty*8 Legation at ahran, reco iuending cortain improvenents to ul G ^iypensary at Gulhok wiuch has been erected at an aopro^mte cost of £155. The recoranendations are endorsod by His majesty's Minister and the Board agree that it is desirable that the Dispensary should be properly equipped from the beginning. -'( 2. Dr. Heli&amp;an had previously suggested several other improvements, all of which appear to be reasonable, and if T,aoy are included the total excess on the original estimate will be £103 made up as follows (a) Under Secretary of State(a) Water reservoir under store roo.:, extra closet, and provision of two sinks £32. (b) Direct water supply from the Kanat £53. (c) Cement floors and plaster ceilings in three rooms £18. (3) In the event of Sir K. Grey approving these recommendations, the Board will be obliged if . o will submit them to the India Office at an early date with a view to obtaining the approval of that Department and an undertaking to defray a moiety of the cost in the usual course.Extract from Letter from Dr. Neligan, Dated 12th Au/axet, 1913 . iio nev; dis )ensan/ : I was on leave when the plans for this building were drawn up. The amount of accommoda tion provided for is satisfactory but I have now to propose that an addition bo made to the original estirahoe for the provision of :- 1. Direct water supply by pipes from the Kanat. It is obvious that a large and constant supply of fresh water is moi..t necessary in a hot weather dispensary. lo lay in water as I sUf^gost would of course be more expensive than to arrange for water to be supplied by the ordinary primitive methods of this country: but in my opinion the expense would be more than justified by having a constant and absolutely clean supply. Mr# George tells me that there is already a certain amount of piping in the Legation which might be used for the purpose I suggest. 2. Cemented floors. Floors made of tne best cement procurable locally should be laid down in three of.the five rooms in order to bo able to properly disinfect them. LathLath and plaster coilin^e should be nade for the same rooms with a like object. I ujay bo allov/ed to add that a further reason for granting the small extra expenditure demanded by the above works is the fact that the old dispensary will next year become quarters for the ghulams, and that thereby I is !.ajest; r, s Treas ivy /ill effect a considerable saving, for roo.--s for the ■diula/is would have had inevitably to be builtMin I Under Secrete (Jommi Under Secrete PrevioiCode telegram to Sir W. Townley (Tehran) Foreign Office, October 30th, 1913. No. 448. Your telegram No. 245 (of 22nd June Gulhek Legation). Treasury sanction immediate acquisition of plots B. C. and D. at cost of £1100 for B and £300 for C. and D. You are authorized to act accordingly. Purchases must he completed before 31st March next.Copy. r 85. i ^ Lrr.'iediate. (49240) HI3 MAJESTY'S CW1CB C£ T.OHKS &amp;c., 3T0HSY' 3 GATH, WB3T;:.im3H, 3.,/. 29tn. October 1913. 3ir: - / With reierence to your coiiiaunication oi tiae 9t i. August last (36507i am directed by the i?irst Commissioner of His majesty’s V/orks &amp;c., to state, for the information of becretary bir 12. Orey, that the board having represented to the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury the urgent necessity for the acquisition of certain land to the .est of iiis Majesty’s Legation Grounds at Gulhek, have now ootained Their Lordships’ sanction for the imaediate acquisition of the plots referred to as H, C and D in bir Walter Langley's letter of the 27th. June last U .0.26610/13) at an estimated cost of LI,ICO for plot 3 belonging to the Gulhekis and ~3GC for plots C and D belonging to ilukhoer ed Bowleh. 2. As His Majesty's Minister at Tehran has represent ed The Under becretary of btate, foreign Office.represented that the decision to purchase should in no case be deferred beyond the present month, i am to suggest that he be at once aithorised by telegraph to enter into negotiation lor the acquisition of the land at prices not exceeding those specified. 3. it is important that the purchases je completed before the 31st. harch next, as funds are only available during the current financial year. it will not 00 necessary, however, to press for the payment of the moiety to be contributed by the India Office in anticipation of the ordinary annual adjustment of accounts between the Imperial and Indian .•Jxcnequers, I am, &amp;c., W. Toroy. (di gned)7 In any further communication on this subject, please quote N „. 33531/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Office, London. mediate. Sir: - U.S / Foreign Office July 29th, 1913. With reference to recent correspondence regard ing the summer quarters of His Majesty's Legation at Teheran (Gulhek) exchanged between His Majesty's Minister, this Department and His Majesty's Office of Works, copies of which have 'been forwarded for the information of the Marquess of Crewe in letters from i this Office of 19th May, and 11th and 27th June, I am directed hy Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith to be laid before His Lordship a further letter from the Office of Works on the subject. Sir E. Grey feels convinced that after a perusal of the papers, Lord Crewe will share his opinion that it is essential to the welfare of the Legation that the land in question should be acquired by His Majesty's Government and in view of the imperative need of arriving at a decision before October, I am to U 30 M ^ e Under Secretary of State, India Office.(33531/13). to express his earnest hope that His Lordship may see his way to render the purchase possible hy undertaking to advance half (viz. about Seven hundred pounds) of the purchase money, should the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty^ Treasury approve the payment of the other half out of Imperial Funds. In view of the urgency of the matter I am to request that an answer may be returned at your early convenience. I am Sir Your most obedient humble Servant?y 3531). 1 p HIS I'.AJESTY'S OFFICE OF V'ORKS, Lc., STOREY'S GATE. WESTTvIINSTER, S.W. 18th July, 1913. *' ir:- With reference to your letter of -v r* cr A OU 0 4 *i t tha_ , P l T l' l h v 1'LLt4gno (28610/13), I am directed hy the First Commissioner of His liaiesty's Works, cic. to state, for the information of Secretary Sir £. Grey, that in the light of the facts reported hy Sir W. Townley, the Beard are disposed to recommend to the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury the purchase of the plots of land (B.C. and L. on the plan returned herewith) adjoining the grounds of His Majesty's Legation House at Gulhek when funds are available. They note that definite action in the matter cannot safely he deferred beyond October next and they will he prepared in view of this to consider in September the state of the Vote for Diplomatic and Consular Services with a view to deciding whether adequate savings can he expected. Representations have, however,already been made to Their Lordships as to the pressing necessity for the purchase of sites for Con sular ie '^sr Secretary of State, Foreign Office.Consular buildings at Saffi and Fez (see Treasury Let ter 13265/13 to the Foreign Office of the 14th instant) and as it is doubtful whether savings sufficient to cover all three services will be available I am to enquire whether Sir E. Grey has any views as to the relative urgency of them* The estimated expenditure involved in the various cases is:- Saffi - site for Vica-Consulate .... Fez site for Consulate Gulhek - Plot B .. PlotsC. and D... 300) As regards uhe penultimate paragraph of your letter iv, musu 00 pointed out that, as the annual adjustment % of accounts between the Imperial and Indian Exchequers ie not made until after the close of the financial y ear, the willingness of the Indian Government to bear a moiety of the cost of this purchase, which it is stated may be assumed, will not relieve the Vote for Diplomatic and Consular Buildings during the present year unless some exceptional procedure is authorised in the present instance,and it is suggested that inquiry should be made as to whether the India Office -would be prepared to advance its share of the purchase money,if purchase is approved by the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury. /riJ T am uc. . (Signed) W.Af Robinson.Minute Paper. Register No put away with I 7— Political Department. a y Letter from cP . o Dated o, , x _ N 'v,-2« y lice. Formally acknowledged Initials. Under Secretary OM Secretary of State / Committee *r ?.iv. // Under Secretary 2~U Secretary of Sta£^ Council 2 3 iu.ij Copy to Fiir r ‘ n o:. rt' citable for perus'! 24 JUL1913 SEEN COUNCfL: a. btett l - w Utfi ui i913 CP. h't*$&lt;*+so ^ A** fijf'u. , Cfri/* ^ a^rA^-f J&lt;f.C*o Previous Papers : — 230* \ \ &gt; ' 37l 2- I. 1354. 2000.—7/1908.In any further comtuunica- tion on this subject, please quote No - IlQiS. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for a and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop lie of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ay , igij Reference to previous letter : Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Sfj-QJL L Cc oj icrrssko. y^T Subject. -Lev &lt;&gt;j^ S-Q- / -TO 2828610/13. ? . .• i.. Juno 27 th. 1513 I directed by ii^cretmry *iir ^dward Drey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter 85 of the cCth. u tiao regarding the neceeeity of rurchaaiiv^ certain plots of land adjoining the r rounds of iie Majesty’s Legation Uouee at ^ulhek. 1 as to 8tate 9 in reply, for the inforoation of Aarl Be8uehmn f that wir Grey did not fail to brin ' the points raised in your letter to the notice of * is Majesty*s iSnister at Teheran whose reply has just teen received. 5ir %». Townley states that the owners of plot • are natiree of tiulhek and that prerioucly the boundary was fired by cocoon consent. The Jowe who have offered a higher price do not wish to buy the plot as a speculation but to build md live on it tbeoeelves, a fact which affords a far nore objectionable proerect ecretexy to the Cffice of *orks.(26610/1^ \lQ t proen^ct, an tha con«truotlon of hoaoeu t\u* becoocc « cortainty. ir ownlcv ^tatat th®t the rurchnse of the lamd it aott nocottftry m only by that ;iitane can the shutting in of tbs Lsgsiion by natito housss bs prafsntsdj and at rs^ardt an ontion on the r©party ho rojmrkt that tha natter can be doferrad until October but thould not bo doleydd any Ion or. As re^rdt the penultiaate paragraph of your letter, he points out thnt ?lot L. could easily be dotaloned for building rurpotee even if the pretent owner of Plot C. were to refuse to sell. ith regard to the l«»tt paragraph of your letter, ^ir .. iownley renorte that the cott of lots C end D would ba about One hundrao and fifty pounda each and that it would be ▼ery important to acquire the » miring the lifetii^ of the proteni owner, kiukhbor ed howl eh, whoso health it bad. he addt that it is essential at all ©rente that part of each c,i % tnaa thoula be secured in order to prevent the approach to the Legation being blocked by native hou^ea and to se&lt;cu' -* ,700. (28610/13) J secure access to the new dispensary of hie uajesty’s Legation. In view of theee facte and of the opinion of hir ... Townley that the acquisition of Plot B. is absolutely essential to the welfare of the legation, I an to exnreee # iiir d. Grey 1 e earnest hone that His Lordship will see his way to urge the consideration of the whole question unon tho Lords Coraai as loners of Lia Majesty’s Treasury for a dafinite decision before it is too late. It say be aesuaed that the norernnent of India would be willing to bear half the cost and the liability to oe borne by laperial funds would nrobably not exceed Seven hundred pounds. The plan in ^ir W, Townloy’s desnatch Ho.01 is returned herewith for facility of referonce. I Lir f four tool obedient, humble Servant, &lt;SIGN£D) LOfcMS MALLfcX.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received June 23, 11-50 a.m.) ^ i s Tehran, June 22, 1913. ’ (N°. 24d.) R. \ (June 22, 1' SO pm.) 'I YOUR telegram No. 2G0 of 6th June : Land at Gulhek. Owners of plot B are natives of Gulhek and previously [group omitted : ? it] was fixed by common consent. Jews do not want to buy as a speculation but to build and live on the land themselves, a much more objectionable prospect. Purchase of land is most necessary, and is the only way to prevent shutting in of the legation by native houses; it can be deferred until October, but should not be delayed any longer. Plot B could be easily developed for building purposes even though present owner of C should refuse to sell. Cost of plots C and D would be about 150£. each. It would be very important to acquire them during the lifetime of the present owner, Mukhber-ed-Dowleh, whose health is bad. It is essential that at all events part of each of them should be secured to prevent the approach to the legation being blocked by native houses and to secure access to new dispensary. COPY TO INDIA 1 9 1 3.. * SECfiETARY'S \ * 24JUN1913 ,CONHDENTIAL Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 260.) R. Foreign Office, June 6, 1913, 5‘50 p.m. YOUR despatch No. 81 of 15th April. Office of Works surmise that owners of plot B are under some obligation to His Majesty’s Government, as they would sell to latter at much lower figure than to speculative Jewish builders. If acquisition of land is imperative, and purchase can alone prevent building on it, they suggest option on property might be obtained until Board could include provision in next year’s estimates, or say definitely whether they can purchase in October. Board question whether plot B could be developed for building purposes so long as C remains in hands of owner well disposed to His Majesty’s Government. Further, as sale of plots C and D for building is contingency not to be overlooked, Board desire to learn probable cost of acquiring them in order to consider whole question of extending legation grounds to main road.Mir f Under Secret ret, Comm | Under 4 Secretcopy. 85. r (25019) HIS fAAJESTY'S OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;C., STOREY'S GATE, WESTMINSTER, S.W. 30th May, 1913 Sir: - With reference to your letter of the 19th instant I (20564/13), I am directed by the First Comiesioner of His Majesty's Works, &amp;c., to state, for the informa- 'N tion of Secretary Sir E. Grey, that, in the absence of funds and of any certainty of savings being effected on the Diplomatic and Consular Buildings Vote for the current yea 1 ', the Board fear that it would be useless for them at present to propose to the Lords Commis sioners of the Treasury the purchase of the plot of land adjoining the grounds of His Majesty's Legation House at Gulhek, and marked B on the plan returned herewith. It would appear, however, from the Minister's des patch, a copy of which was enclosed in your communlca- tion, that the owners of the plot are under some ob ligation to His Majesty's Government, as they are will ing to sell it to them at a much lower figure than has been The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.been offered by the speculative builders. If, there fore, Sir Edward Grey Is satisfied that the protec tion of the health of the Legation Staff demands the prevention of the use of this land for building pur poses, that there Is, in fact, a real risk of Its being so utilized, and that purchase is the only possible remedy, it is suggested that the Minister might ob tain an option on the property for so long as would enable the Board to include provision for the purchase in their Estimates for 1914-15, or at least to say de finitely whether they can effect sufficient savings during the current year. The latter date may be taken to be about October 1913. The Board observe that their contention that the suggested purchase of plot E in 1911, was scarcely justifiable, is now virtually admitted by the Minister, and, though they are prepared to admit that the arguments which were adduced in favour of that pur chase have more force when applied to the present pro posals, they are by no means convinced that plot B could, in fact, be developed for building purposes so long as plot C remains in the hands of an owner who is well-disposed to His Majesty's Government. This point willwill require further consideration as affecting the urgency of the proposed purchase. The Minister apparently regards the sale of both plots '0' and 'D' for building purposes as a contin gency which n TUst not be overlooked, and as the ques tion of the purchase of these plots also must inevitably arise out of the present proposal, it would be very useful if he could ascertain the probable cost of ac quiring them, in order that the question of extending the Legation grounds to the main road which runs along the further side of plots *C n and 'D' may be con sidered as a whole. I am &amp;c., (Signed) W.A. Robinson.CONtlDENTlAJ. r ” c , &gt; o I Sir Edward (drey to Sir W. Townlev (Tehran). ('So. 260.) R. ii. ^ YOUR despatch No. 81 of 15th April. Foreign Office, June 6, 1913, 5*50 p.ai. Office of Works surmise that owners of plot B are under some obligation to His Majesty’s Government, as they would sell to latter at much lower figure than to speculative Jewish builders. If acquisition of land is imperative, and purchase can alone prevent building on it, they suggest option on property might be obtained until Board could include provision in next year’s estimates, or say definitely whether they can purchase in October. J Board question whether plot B could be developed for building purposes so Ion 0, as C remains in hands of owner well disposed to His Majesty’s Government. Further, as sale ^ of plots C and D for building is contingency not to be overlooked, Board desire to learn probable cost of acquiring them in order to consider whole question of extending legation grounds to main road. COPY TO | M n| A 13 JUN1913 | 1790-103'In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop t to of the nnder-mentioned papery Name and Date. ^ (j. 7, v la l 2c U r*,.. &lt;p/. OsJPXxX t'S. ^ L&lt;r / /vT^v/a?^- (Similar letter sent to Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter : j* b-d' A-o. ^ ^ *Sj)- 1 f' Description of Inclosure. Subject ^ L-'L (T L~ 21MAY1 7^ - '3 MAY 1913I!opy. Io. 81. 20564). Sir:- 7ith referance to my predecessor's despatch No. 60 of April 20th,1911 and the subsequent correspondence and telegrams relative to the proposed purchase of land adjoining the Culheic Legation, I 'nave the honour to inform you that this question has again become acute. In order to make what follows more clear, I enclose a plan of the land and adjoining parts of the Legation. The present position is as follows. The owners of the piece of land marked B have been offered a high price (Five Krans per square zsr) by a number of Jews who wish to build houses upon it right up to the Lega- iiOi. boundary. It is open to His Majesty's Government to acquire this land at a very much smaller figure, namely Three brans per square tar. I have no hesitation in repeating ail the old arguments in favour of this step, and of insisting that it is absolutely essential to the welfare of the Legation. As to the land marked £ the purchase of which was i hs Right Honourable Sir E. Grey, Bart., K.G., M. &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c., 23 fvlAY 1913 i /* 1 .y*o ■ ’r m urgedurged by my predecessor, I am of opinion that the S' buii'iing of houses upon It is not nearly so serious k a question as^v/hat is now threatened. It has become impossible to put off the owners any longer and I have consented to their building. With regard to the plots of lane marked C. and D. # the&gt; belong to Mukhber ed Dov/leh, and I have reason to believe that he would not allow buildi?ig upon them if he thought uhat we would object. He Is^ however, an old man and in bad health and should his heirs wish to dispose O: this land for building purposes, it ’would become essential to acquire possession of it. i The really urgent question is, as I have said. that of the plot marKed B. I respectfully urge that the very strongest representations be made to His Majesty 1 s of Works, in favour of purchasing it &gt;230 zars at i t will coat approximately £1,100. It can be let to wans i)590 a £1100 * 3aBayith3 * 0: ‘ agricultural purposes, or it can be thrown into the Legation. If let it is estioated that it would bring in about £12 a year. A &amp;ar = about 40 inches.lopy- P564/12. Sir:- FOREIGN OFFICE. May 19th, 1913. With reference to your letter 21056 of the 7th of March 1912 regarding the acquisition of certain land adjoining the property of His Majesty's Legation at Gulhek, I a''* directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to tranaalt to you herewith, to be laid before the Earl Beauchamp, a copy of a despatch from His Majes ty's Minister at Tehran on the subject, from which it will be seen that the plot of land (marked E. on the accomparying plan) which it was Impossible to buy last £140. year at a cost of One hundred and forty pounds for want* of funds has now been built upon, as Sir W. Townley found hlmsolf unable to delay matters any longer. The question, however, of the lane to the North West of the Legation has now reached a critical stage, as an offer lias actually been nude to the owners by a Kra.S. group of Jaws who cue prepared to offer Five Krans per square zar. On the other hand it is possible for His Majesty's Government to acquire the land at the rate of fr 8 Secretary CC ^ | 23 MAY 1 SI 3 SECRETARY'S n: 21 to the Office of Works.of Three kruna per square zar. The Importance ol preearvin^ intact the open space to the North West of the Legation property is evident as it is the one quarter from which the only breeze during the summer months can reach it and the need to do eo has now been emphasized by two Bucceeelve Ministers at Teheran and also by Mr. Marling, when Chiti. ge d Affaires there in If’10. Moreover, It was recog nlzed in your letter 41423/11 of 30th May mi. In view ol these facts and of the urgency of the question, I aa to express 3ir E. Grey's earnest hope that Lord Beauchamp will feel Justified in urging the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treeaury to authorize the purchase of the plot B. at a total cost of about One thousand one hundred i&gt;ounds if the Secre tary of State for Inoia will agree that half of that sura shall he borne by the Indian Exchequer. I am &lt;s;c., (Signed) W. Langley.. s . ~ . V. - v - _ y In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 53728/12. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Oiiicc, London. r p 4 c 8 ! %/ i 9i 2 Foreign Office ember 24th, 1912. Sir:- i I am directed by Secretary Sir E.Grey to transmit to you herewith, for submission to the karquess of Crewe, a copy of a letter received from His Majesty's Office of Works on the subject of an application re ceived from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran for the erection of a new dispensary at Gulahek. I am to enquire whether the Marquess of Crewe would be disposed to give the concurrence requested in the second paragraph of the enclosed communication. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, pie Under Secretary of State, India Office.HIS MAJESTY'S OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;C., STOREY'S GATE, WESTMINSTER, 13 ^ O -I- 4 ' 1 h S.W. December, 1912. Sir:- | 0 ;'&gt; ^ » tZ... . ~ c .. . I arn directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty*s Works, etc., to state, for the information of Secretary Sir E. Grey, that an application has been received from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran for the erection of a new Dispensary at Gulahek. The position of the present Dispensary, at one of the main exits from the Legation, is regarded as a source of danger to the Legation staff; moreover the existing rooms are required for the accommodation of the Gholams, who are now living in a tent. A The Board propose to include provision for this service, which is estimated to cost £155, in the Estimates for the ensuing year, but before doing so they will be glad if the concurrence of His Majesty's Secretary of Sta/te for India can be obtained with a view to sharing the cost. Certain Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.bnUi 3 - , Certain minor works to the extent of about are also under consideration, which are not strictly in the nature of maintenance hut none of which is expected to cost more than £100. The most important is an extension of the Legation at Tehran to in crease the accommodation in two of the bedrooms. It is presumed that minor services of this nature need not be reported in detail for the precedent approval of the India Office. I an, &amp;c., (Signed) V/. Torpy.04 In any farther communica tion on this subject, please quote No. to / and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Tfie Under-Secret dry of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copC^ of the under-mentioned papery Foreign Office, /e , igi2. SECUE7 AP. Reference to previous letter: iq Us* 7 1 ?f /n. Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Aa 33 I SubjectHNI Telegram to Sir W.Townley (Tehran). Foreign Office. May 16th 1912, 4 p.m. No.336. Sir G.Barclay’s Despatch No.25. (Gulhek Legation Land). Can you induce Russian Minister to help in any way? There are no funds available this year but it may be possible to buy the land in 1913-1914, if not built upon./l2. 2 ). PII3 kAJESTY 1 3 OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;c., STOREY'S GATE, WESTMINSTER, S.W. exarch 7th 1912. Sir:- With reference to your letter of the 27th ultimo. 7189/12, transmitting copy of a further despatch from His majesty's .inister at Tehran on the subject of the suggested acquisition of a certain plot of ground ad joining the Legation property at Gulhek, I am directed by the First Comiiiissloner of His ^ajesty's Works, kc., to state, for the infoi*mation of Secretary Sir E.Grey, that the Board foresee no prospect whatever at present of their having funds at their disposal during the coming financial year to enable them to effect the purchase of this land, and it is obviously too late to conclude the transaction in time for the expenditure to fall on this year's vote. In these circumstances they regret that it is useless for them to approach the Treasury in the matter os they otherwise would have done - although they must confess to still feeling some diffidence as to the necessity Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.necessity for the purchase, and In particular they do • sl\- .(M not understand why a consideration, which it was previously stated need not he insisted on, is now ad vanced as one of the main reasons for advocating the proposal. I aiii &amp;c., (Signed) Schomherg K.McDonnell fiflU 1V' ■ ■ 7109/12. fGUMM mitt*. February 2 1 * 1912. 3xr:- iiilih reference to your letter 41422/11 of 30th. I o.y last reapectin.^ the desirability of acquiring certain land near His Majesty*a Legation at Griilhek, I am directed by secretary dir Ldward Grey to transmit to you, to be laid before the Hirst Commissioner of His Majesty*a Works etc., a copy of a further despatch from His Majesty*s Minister at feheran on the subject, showing that the Hussian Legation are not in a position to prevent building on the land to the west of His ajesty f a Legation and that operations are in fact only now being deferred until a decision lias been arrived at by His lajesty’s GoVvirninent. 1 am at the same tine to point out that the two main reasons for advocati^ the acquisition of the land in ques tion vis: the danger to His Majesty’s Legation of cholera ■he Secretary to His majesty's Office of Works. andand other diseases owirv; to the proximity of native houses and the risk involved in having the Lection coit^ound coinruinded in case of disturbance by native houses are not contested in your on the west side will not of necessity entail the purchase of the land to the north of the road f as re gards which a certain aiflount of pressure can be brought to bear by his Majesty's Legation. In view of these facts and of the desirability of acting in the matter without delay, I aai to express nir E. Jrey's earnest hope that Earl Beauchamp may see his way to submit for the favourable consideration of the bords Commissioners of ilia tejesty's Treasury the purchase of the land in question at a total cost of One hundred find forty pounds of which one half or Seventy pounds would be borne by Imperial funds. 1 am, Sir* four most obedient, humble Servant*y. 25. 89). Sir With reference to your telegram No. 173 dated June 1 st, 1911 I have the honour to inform you that I have sounded the Russian Minister about the possibili ty of preventing building on the site mentioned in my \ '' Despatch No. 60 of April 20th. Monsieur Poklewsky in forms me that the only way to achieve this object is for His Majesty's Government to buy the ground and I understand that building is only postponed pending a definite decision by His Majesty's Government on this point. In view therefore of the objections to native houses being put up along the Legation wall (see Despatch referred to above) I feel compelled to ask once more that the land in question may be bought by His Majesty's Government. Right Honourable Sir Edward Grey, Bart., M.P. &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.,Register No. l4£TLt-% Political Department. .(a Letter from 3v Dated ^ * Dec. &amp; Formally acknowledged SUBJECT. 191 / ^ Secretary^of^Sfeate^. | Committee f. Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Date. Initials. OM LI. \ % r//. Wc 1 crsta % H ' ft.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No . 30907/11. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. /A. Vforks. he Under Secretary of State, India Office. Sir:- With reference to the letter from this Office of May 15th last, relative to additional accommodation required at His Majesty's Legation at Gulahek, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to trananit to you herewith copy of a letter from the Office of Works, from which it appears that only one story of the contemplated addition can be completed for the sum sanctioned and that provision will be made for the construction of the second floor in the estimates for 1912-3. I am to express Sir E. Grey's hope that the Marquess of Crewe may see his way, in the meantime, to obtain the assent of the Government of India to the charge on Indian funds of one-half the increased / expenditure involved, as desired by the Office of I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Copy. 42048/11• (30*07) Sir KIS MAJESTY'S OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;C., STOREY'S GATE, WESTMINSTER, S 4th August, 1911. (3^ Adverting to the Board’s letter of trie 6th hay last in reply to your letter of the 12th April, 12254, on the subject of the provision of additional accommodation at Gulhek, I am directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty’s Gorks, etc., to state for the information of Secretary Sir B. Grey, tnat this work is proving more costly than was anticipated owing to the great increase which has taken place in the price of materials at Gulhek since the estimate v;as framed. The Board’s Superintendent of horks reports that only one storey can be completed for the sum of £300 which xias been sanctioned and that another £200 will be required for the second storey. As the Board nave no funds at their disposal for meeting this expenditure this year, they propose to provide for it in the Estimates for 1912-13, and they would be glad if in the meantime the assent of the The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.CONFIDENTIAL. / ' ij K ^ Put away With! lHlJj.%- - r '“\ 2 JUNI 911 Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay {Tehran), (No. 173.) R. ’ Foreign Office, June 1, 1911. YOUR despatcli No. 60. U Office of Works unwilling to approach Treasury with a view to purchase of land in question. They enquire whether you cannot invoke aid of Russian Legation^ as last year, to stop building from being begun. Would this be possible ? J &gt; V'V r k- . .P 'P ‘v x \P l TV' /\ MV. i ^ - ^ I'*'In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. (7 &lt;7 3^ and address— I The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. r [ 12 ] T/ie Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop cu of the under-mentioned papers. Foreign Office, fF , igff . Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ■sJc-a sr- c p piA^ i nc &amp;JOLn CX A /\d~ (o O r\I \.q Ac o ' / 0 I/O &amp; r Cs. Treg : l ,L .0 Copy. Iehran. April Sir, I hrve the honour to trajinmlt here./ith a copy of a Memorandum hy Dr religpin on the building of native houses a-gninst the V^estern boundary of the Legation grounds at Oulhek. I consider the natter of great importance and endorse all that Dr ! elignn says about it. I therefore venture to hope that you vfill be able to bring it to the notice of His Kajesty's Gomrrdsnloners for V r orhs and that the proposal to purchase the land in question will re ceive their favourable conniderrtion. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect. Sir, Your moat obedient, h vt T.b 1 e S e rv ant. he (signed) G. Barclay. i r ht Honorable Sir E Grey, Baronet, H.PSir, ■ Tehran, 1 7937 . WAY J2_J9IJy April 18 X9II Sir, I have the honour to nubir.it to youa Memorandum on a subject of* great importance to Uie future comfort and well being c** Ki b Majee.y’n Legation when in r so Hence at Julhe’:, There ie,Sir,aa you linow,and an I have tried to show in the accompanying rough pi an,a long irregular strip of ''artly waste end partly cultivated ground,along the Western boundery of the Legation garden,- between it and the main road from Tehran to lulheh,torgondeh and the otlier villages in Shimran. The district is becoming more and mere populous,and the owners of part of thiis piece of ground .y* eh oc bu^ld houses on ( t # If the 3 ^ are pei^r.itted uo do thb n,I would submit that it will most seriously affect the legation and its occupants. Hjr reasons for holding this opinion r.re:- I. P-’ve of the 8 Legation houses are built near this boun dery wall. There is practically no sanitation in this coun^ry,cholera has come to &gt;e a yearly menace,and native houses give rHe to noHe and smells. A row of them put up along the icundary wall would therefore mal:e things most unpleasant ^or the occupants of the houses inside it. 2. i.h €&gt;vening freeze,to »fhich everyone looks fori/ax*d on a ot summer’s day,blows from the : erth V/est. There is little enough of it,and what there is would be Obstructed by a row of houses built on the land in question which,as I h evo said,abuts on the western boundary of the Legation. It would further become laden with that extraordinary variety cf smells which accompany the pret'aration of a native dinner. &lt;5 ‘' 1r a * ?Rr =’5*y, Tr .c.ir.Q.,c.v.o. ~ c * &amp;C, £ 0 , ifSH B ft3. The Le£Pt^on gei^len han oho very great advantage of being very nearly completely Isolated on all sides. In my humble opinion,to allow a row of native mud houses to be built along one nido of ^t would be a very great pity,and would create an unfortunate imprornlon. It would mean that the side towards the main road of the district would be con cealed from view,and that the main gate would be approached between native houses. The late Mr McIntyre,who measured and valued the lanu in quest!on,shortly before his death,held similar views to mine,and advanced the further one which I do not think need be insisted on. It wo.s that in the event of disturbances it would be exceedingly bad if the legation v/ere commanded by a number of native houses. He probably had in his mind his experiences during the revoluticn,v/hon shrapnel and bullets fell into the Legation grounds in Tehran. I have given my objections to mowing the land in question to bo bdilt on. They are not only mine but are shared by other members of the Legation Staff,and most strongly by Mr Marling,with whom I discussed the question last Summer when you were in Surope and he was in char 3 ©j also by Mr George,the representative of His Majesty's Office of Works and,an I have aaid,by his predecessor Hr TT cInt^r©. The question now arisen as .c how building is to be prevented. In conridering this,it is necessary to first describe the land more in detail. Referring to the rough plan,it will be seen that the land in question may be di vided up into two parta:- A. That which is north of the main west gate of the Leg- ation. H. That which is south of the gate. A, The land which is north of the gate may be further di vided into two parts: — I. Hie large part which is cultivated and directly abuts ont,Jne LeeaMon boundary. 2, A fsoraetfhati narrow strip,uncultivated,between the com field and the main read. Fortunately not the whole of this land is at the mo- rent tht threatened the hu5.Her, and furthermost of ■’t, (though all 1s situated in the village of Zergendeh) belongs to inhabitants of Qulhek,over who© a certain amount of pressure can be brought to bear as regards the disposal of their land. The part on which its three owners wish to build is south of the legation gate,- and the most southerly part of that portion,- an area roughly 2987 Zars. The reso enf the ground here,v1. 2719 Zars,belongs to &gt;fukhber-ed-Dowleh who,an the largest house owner in the village,and a friend the legation,would not probably wish to bu^ld on it. The owners of this area o** 2987 Zars are pressing hard to be allowed to begin building at once. Bast year the foun dations of a house were actually dug out,but ^rther work was kindly stopped by the Russian legation at y r vr request. On the south border of this strip of land an arak( native spirit) shop has already been put up,it does not however coincide with the Legation boundary wall. The only way to prevent kXLtafc bull ling is to buy the ground, and I would sub mit that I have shown that 1 j would be to the Interest of the- 1 Legation if His Majesty’s acvemment would do tills. Th. land has been roughly raeraured out. It would be sold for Krone 2.^0 a Zar. The total cost in Znglish money would be about £ 140. If the land 1s acquired by Kis Hajesty's Government, the best that could be done with -*t would be to plant a ''ew low-growing trees such an mulberries which would not keep out the breeze but would lessen the dust and l-.eat in the neighbouring part the 'gabion. The soil is too poor for anything else. I have the honour to be, etc etc (signed) ^.R. T eligan. ??.D»17939/11 wmzii om®, Lay , 1911 i aia directed by Secretary liir Edward Grey to trananit to you herewith copy of a deapatch fror.- His Lajesty , 8 ;inister at Tehran representing the desirability of buying on behalf of His lajesty f s Governrpnt a piece of land lying against tiie western boundary of Ilia I a jo sty 1 s Legation grounds at Gulahek in order to prevent the erection of iiative houses there. I a&amp; to express Sir K. Grey’s hope that it aay be found possible to give favourable consideration to the proposed transaction, in view of the manifest objections to the presence of native houses in the in-iediate neighbourhood of ills Lajcsty’s Legation. Your most obedient I am humble Servant Sir fL; Secretary to the Office of works f Signed) TT. Lanqlty-In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. I3l&lt;j and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. c X iV T L 3,^' MAVI911 T/?e Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copj of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, /S' , 19 ff Reference to previous letter: JO Arc., v? Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. C ^ £&gt;o-nr/V&gt; it b** C Subject. (A vcv^ c c cr c&lt;&gt;&gt; &gt; tc C ^ i ^iur^kx. A V1 v ■ 35w r- p73/ll. IttO • Sir: - HIS MAJESTY'S OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;C., STOREY'S GATE, WESTMINSTER, S.W. 6 th May 1911. With reference to your memorandum of the 12th ul timo, No.12254, transmitting copy of a letter addressed to the Treasury on the subject of the additional accom modation required at Gulhek, I am directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty’s Works, &amp;c., to state, for the information of Secretary Sir E.Grey, that this Department has now been authorised to proceed with the execution of the work on condition that savings are effected on the Vote for Diplomatic and Consular Build ings to met the cost. A copy of the Treasury letter is enclosed. As it is anticipated that this can be done without much difficulty, the Board are giving instructions for the work to be carried out. I am to add that the question of the ultimate re covery from India of a moiety of the cost is not of practical concern to this Department which has to bear the hs Under Secretary of State, foreign Office.[ 12 ] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. I£~8 C J 7 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for &lt;Jy\%,a ^ ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , igif - Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 7 fr-'-nc'.' »o 1 ' k / • 3 MA' f 1911 )TREASURY CHAMBERS. 28th April 1911. Sir: - With reference to Mr.Mullet's letter of the 12th instant (12254/n) I aoi directed by the Lords Commission ers of His Majesty's Treasury to transmit herewith, for the information of Secretary Sir E.Grey, copy of a let ter of to-day's date which They have caused to be ad dressed to the Office of Works on the subject of certain proposed additions to his Majesty's Legation house at Gulahek. ff nder Secretary of State, Foreign Office. I am &amp;c., (Signed)1) TREASURY CHAMBERS. 23th April 1911. My Lord:- I arn directed by the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury to transmit to you herewith a copy of a letter dated the 12th instant from the Foreign Office relative to certain proposed adaitions to His Majesty’s Legation house at Oulahek. this work and the charge to the Vote for Diplomatic ana Consular Buildings 1911-12 of the expenditure involved (within a limit of £300, half of which will ultimately he recovered from India) provided that it can be cone without causing an excess on the total provision of the Vote. My Lords wish it to be understood however that They are not prepared to submit to Parliament a Supple mentary Estimate in respect of this ser In the circumstances represented by Sir E.Orey My Lords are prepared to authorise the execution of (Signed) I am &amp;c.HIS MAJESTY'S OFFICE OF WORKS, ETC, STOREY'S GATE. WESTMINSTER. S.W. lBt». April, 1911. Sir:- With reference u&gt; your communicutxon of the let. ultimo. No. 6733, tranemitt^ng a copy of the letter of the ^2mi. ultimo from the Inaia Office relating to that Department's liability in the matter of certain works, some proposed and some executed, at Tehran and Gulhek, I am directed by the First Commissioner of His ajesty's Works, etc., to state, for the information of Secretary Sir E. Grey, that owing to financial exigencies, the Treasury disallowed the provision of £300 inserted in the Estimates of this Department for 1911-12 on account of the additions to the accommoda tion at Gulhek suggested by His Majesty's Minister xn his letter of the 22nd. August last* I am &amp;c., (Signed) W. J. Downer. Under Secretary of State, foreign Office.3Vi %r/ n) .(wj . TORKION OFFICE, April 1911. -ir:- I an directed by secretary Sir Edward drey to tranaalt to you herewith copy of a letter from Hie ajasty'a Office of fcorke, etc., stutlng th&lt;.t, owing to financial ezigencieB, the Lords Oommisaloners of it ’’ajaBty'a Treasury have alsallo»vea the provision of Thraa humirad pounds insartad in tha estimates of th .t ^ipurti.ont for 1911-12 an account of certain bduitione to Hi© Majesty 1 s l^gfition ho^ibe at Oulahek jested by Hi© Majesty 1 © Minister at Tehran. Otpiee of the other papers bearing on the iu ca tion have doubtless already been forwarded to yw by the Office of Works in making their application for the insertion of the above sum in the estimates and accordingly none are enclosed. I am to submit for the consideration of the lords Oonraissloners that the state of affairs re- ■ D’ bl0 c f e Memory to tha Treasury. voalod(12254/11) by air 0. Barclay in hi a d«#p»teh No.l^ of N Ai 0 Mt 2 2nd last, *hlch th« o*i&gt;«nuitur« of this sum ia &lt;i«siEn#o to remedy, la Inconaiatont with tha position of one of Mia yajaBty‘B 'Repreaentatives abroad and I am accordingly to express the hope that Their Ix&gt;r&lt;i^!ip8 may see their wey to reconsider their refusal to include this amount in the eetlnttee 1 fiia further to point out, in support of this application, that, as ap-wars from the India Office }&amp;l*^ let tor of Fobmury last, that Dopartmsnt luivi already consontfO to tho ctuir ftp on Inc&gt;lan funcis of half the expentilture involved and that a refusal on the part of Hie fcajaety’a Government to pay their share would therefore be productive of inconvenience 1 am, Sir, Your most obedient,r ^ Dear Wallis, In our letter to the Foreign Office of 25th November last regarding the proposed extension of the Legation House at Gulaheh we asked, towards the end of, the letter, whether the figures of expenditure on builaings shown in the statements of diplomatic . and consular expenditure by your Department in Persia in 1907-8 and 1908-9 which have been furnished to this Office, viz .. &lt;£4761. 13. 1 and £3648. 5. 3, respectively, included the outlay at Gulahek shown in the Appropriation Accounts (£3,093. 14. 3 and £1984. 18. 2) . Your letter of Jan. 13th does not answer this question. You told me in conversation that the answer is in the affirmative, and I could of course mention what you said. But there is another point on which we ought, I think, to have information in writing. I am afraid that . without the explanation of the purposes to which the money was applied, asked for in our letter of 11th May 1907, it will be difficult for the Secretary of StateState for India to say that he is willing to share the expenditure in question, or the further expenditure mentioned in your letter of 12th September last 32251/10. Could you send us info't'viation off icially 071 both points? We have been keeping back our annual claim pending your reply to our letter of November, but the time is now getting short , and it seems a pity to send it in while any point is outs tanding. Yours &amp;c..1(3554/11) Sir I transmit to you herevdth copy of e letter from the Office of Works relative to a request received from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran for the erection of wash- GuleheK and a waiting room for the dispensary of that at Tehran. I am to state that Sir E. Grey concurs in the opinion expressed in this letter that the request is a reasonable one and to express the hope that the Earl of Crewe may see his way to permit the charge on Indian funds of one half the expense entailed by the work / which is estimated at houses for His Majesty’s Legation houses at Tehran and £180. One hundred and eighty pounds in all. I am, Sir, ^ v Yourj^ost obedient, humble Servant, uncu ftie Under Secretary of State, India Office. tocopy- 40257/11. (3554) * HIS MAJESTY*S OFFICE OF WORKS, kc. f STOREY * S GATE, WESTMINSTER, S.w. 27th January, 1911. Sir:- I Qin directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty*s Works, etc., to transmit to you, herewith, for the information of Secretary Sir E. Grey, a copy of a despatch received from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran together with copies of two memoranda enclosed therein, recommending txie erection of wash-houses at Tehran and Gulhek and a waiting-room for the dispensary of His majesty's negation at Tehran. The total estimated cost of the proposals is, it will be observed, £180. The Board consider the request reasonable and if Sir E. Grey concurs he will no doubt refer the matter to the India Office with a view to recovering from that Department a moiety of the expense. In accordance with the wish expressed in your letter of the Kith instant, ne Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, (No. 273/11), S.w.TEHRAN, December 26th, 1^10. Sir: - I beg to transmit tv«o memoranda from Dr. Neligan tue physician to His majesty's Legation on the necessity for building:- (1) Wash houses in the Legations at Tehran and at Gjlhek. (2; A waiting room for patient? at the dispensary at Tehran. I entirely agree with what Dr. Leligan has written trust that His majesty's Commissioners will sanction the necessary expenditare. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) G. Barclay. Secretary to the Commissioners, His majesty's Office of Works, Westminster.TEHRAN, Leceiiiber 26th, 1^1^. Sir: - I have the honour to address you on the subject of v/ash houses tor His Majesty’s Legations in Tehran and in Gulhek. In each Legation there is one wash house but each is inadequate for the requirements of the Staff, half of which ha.s to send its washing to Persian washermen outside the Legation. On medical grounds this is most undesirable. I have seen two Europeans lately who had contracted skin diseases in this way. But there is another and more urgent reason for providing adequate accommodation within the Legation walls for the washing of clothes, and that is the practical certainty of a Cholera epidemic here next summer. Should it come, it will be necessary for me to forbid clothes being taken outside the Legation to be washed. I therefore recommend that extra accommodation for washing be provided in the two Legations as speedily as Barclay, K.C.m.G., », t.c., &amp;c., His Britannic majesty’s minister.as possible. I have requested i^r. George to give me an estimate for the work, it is £85 for the Legation at Tehran and £60 for that at Gulhek. I have, &amp;.C., (Signed) A. R. Neligan. M. D.TEHRAN, December 28th, 1510. Sir:- I have the nonoui' to address you on the necessity foi building a waiting room ior the dispensary of His Majesty’8 Legation at Tehran. The only room in which patients can at present wait tneir turn, is the one in which the dispensing is done. It is small and dark and the dispenser is badly hampered in nis work oy the crowd of patients. Those who cannot get into the room have to stand in the open air, and as you yourself know the winter at Tehran is sufficiently severe to make this unpleasant for healthy people, end much more so for those who are sick. Mr. George estimates that a suitable room can be built for £35. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) A. R. Neligan. M.D.[ 12 ] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 6 FlB 1 S11 *nd address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for ^ ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop' of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter : A,-. t'S Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. &lt;Y (\xy r Kx Subject. 71 tH ccxfcopy- L 40236/11. Sir:- HIS WESTY’S OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;c., STOREY * S GATE, WESTMINSTER, S.W., January 27th, 1911. With reference to your letter of the 13th instant, 273/11, on the subject of the procedure to be adopted in regard to the execution of new works at His Majesty’s Legation and Consulates in Persia, I am directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty's Works, &amp;c., to state, for the information of Secretary Sir E. Grey, that the Board propose, in accordance with the wish ex pressed by him, to incur no expenditure on such v/orks in future without consulting your Department, although they cannot but think that if the precedent consent of the Government of India to such works must be ob tained, inconvenient delay will often result. I am, &amp;c., (Signed) Schomberg MacDonnell. U Q Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. XW V md address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Ix&gt;ndon. * i-t &amp; Foreign Office, A. CX. Reference to previous letter: R L^. !?, CjU.;opy- flo.94- ( 17469 ) Sir: - TEHERAN, 8th May, 1907. With reference to rny despatch No.44 of 28th to submit for the employment of the moneys which His Majesty's Office of Works have affected to new build ings for His Majesty's Legation, viz: a total of £6,950 (including £1,200 for the Assistants' House) of which £3,000 have been allotted for expenditure in 1907-8. The works to be executed are:- (l) Completion of the Assistants' House.the house will actually cost about £1,000. (2) This as I have reported in ray despatch above- mentioned involves building a new house for the Councillor, for which a detailed proposal has been submitted. It will be necessary to effect some repairs to the smaller house, to the extent of perhaps £40, and eventually to add further accommodation costing say Tomans 1,000, but there is so much other more urgent work to be done that it will not be possible to take it in hand this year, and I will defer making definite proposals for the present. (3) Enlargement of Chanceries at Gulahek and Teheran. Authority for the former has already been given. As regards the enlargement of the Teheran Chancery, you will remember that the question is to some extent bound up with that of providing additional accommodation for the Minister's private residence, by removing the Consulate and library from the quarters they now occupy in the private part of the Legation House, and that I suggested that for this purpose a storey might be added over the East wing of the Legation. I am informed, however, that there are considerable technical diffi cultiesdifficulties in the way of this plan. Inasmuch as it involves taking down the iron roofing, which is formed of plates rivetted together, and there are no competent workmen in Teheran to do the work without destroying the roofing. The proposal is moreover not altogether free from objection on aesthetic grounds, as the second storey would dwarf the main building and spoil the effect of the clock tower. I am not sorry therefore to abandon it in favour of another proposal which though the cost may be slightly greater, is free from these objections and has special advantages of its own. The proposal is briefly as follows:- (a) to erect a new building consisting of three rooms (two for Consular Offices and one for the Representative of the Office of Works) abutting on the North end of the new Assistants' House, and between it and the main gate. The site is eminently suitable and the establish- ment of the Consulate in a separate building at a distance from the Legation would add greatly to the amenities of the Minister's house by removing from the vicinity of his front door the numerous persons. chieflychiefly distressed British Indians and small Persian traders who have business with the Consul. A sketch of the ground and of the proposed building is enclosed. The cost of the building would be about Tomans 11,085. (b) To remove the library into the Billiard Room. The latter room is at present used for the purposes for which it was built not more than two or three times a I year. The billiard table is of course there, but in the climate of Teheran has, owing to the impossibility of procuring skilled attention to it, 'become scarcely worth playing on. I do not think therefore that there is any ©ejection to abolishing the table and converting the room into a library a use for which with some small alterations It would be excellently suited. It would in any case be necessaiy soon to consider how the collection of books belonging to the Legation is to be housed as it is already growing too large for its present quarters. % proposal will meet this difficulty. It has another advantage also in that it would be available as a waiting room for visitors to the Minister; at present there is no such accommodation except in the State drawing room, and my visitors have to wait in the corridorcorridor, an arrangement scarcely suitable for Foreign Representatives or Persian Dignitaries. * (c) Enlargement of diplomatic chanceries at Teheran and Gulahek. The simplest plan for the former appears to be to enlarge the existing room at the Northern end of the East wing by throwing it out 15 feet to the Eastwards and adding a small room on the North side of the new building to serve as a map room. This will involve a minimum of interference with ex isting building and will provide sufficient extra space. The cost. Sergeant Last informs me, will not exceed Tomans 600. I propose also to provide lavatory accommodation for the Chancery by utilising for the purpose the small room now used as a stationery closet; the stationery can be perfectly well stored in presses in the corridor outside the Chancer/. The enlargement of the Gulahek Chancery is now in progress. (4) House for the Military Attache in Teheran. It would, I think, be a mistake to encroach on the garden south of the Legation and the new Student Interpreter’sInterpreter’s quarters, and in the circumstances the test if not the only possible site is the ground between the main gate of the compound and the existing Councillor’s House in the North-eastern angle of the garden. I shall have the honour of submitting a sketch plan of a house costing from £1,600 to £1,800, but it will not, I fear, be found possible to do more than get the walls above ground this year and I would therefore allot Tomans 2,500 for the work. (b) Alteration of the dispensaries. The required expenditure has been sanctioned, and the work at Gulahek is approaching completion. It will be noted that the estimates submitted above are given in Persian currency only; I have thought it better to do so, as exchange which now stands at 47| Krans to the £. a.s against 55 last October, is still likely to fall, and sterling figures which are accurate now might prove in six months time to be 8 or 10 per cent too low. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) Cecil Spring Rice.Estimate for building Consulate at His Britannic Majesty^ Legation, Teheran. 8L5 loads of stone at -/60 1.500 Mans Lime at 9.500 1st quality brick at Sb/ 1 '' 000 10.000 2nd ' M at 70/l^ 000 24.000 3rd ' w at Sb/ 1 ^ 000 5,000 Mane (typsum at ll/ 0 / 0 2,600 loads of earth at -/30 400 Ivlans of straw at 25/ 350 paving bricks at 750 Moulded Bricks for windows at 25/°/° 90 poles for Roof Beams at 12/bO 120 aers Matting at -/bO 15 loads of Reeds at 4/- 110 Zers Lathing at l/25 4 Kooks for Lamps 2/50 150 Glazed tiles at -/30 7 Doors at 120/- 13 Windows at 80/- Colour and painting Glazing 13 Windows at 20/- Lab our Russian Stoves 2 Total (Signed) A. Last, Sergeant, P.E,GULHEK. copy* No. 117 . (18876) May 24th, 1907. Sir:- With reference to my despatch No.44 of February 2o ui) last, I beg leave to offer some further sugges tions as to the accommodation provided at Gulhek for the staff of this Legation. The observation made in the Office of Works' let ter of December 12th last (enclosed in your despatch No.185 (4182S) of December 17th last) that suitable quarters for the student interpreters can be found by enlarging the 'Bungalow' is, I think, hardly practic able and is certainly undesirable. The Bungalow stands in the very hottest corner of the compound be tween the Chancery and the present Councillor's house, and any addition to it would render the latter even less tolerable as a summer dwelling than at present. To speak frankly, I think that both these buildings should be pulled down; the Bungalow is scarcely more than a hovel; it consists of three rooms connected b Sir ‘ Edward Grey, Bart., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.. amm a verandah with a small kitchen and an amhar; the Councillor's house is scarcely better, though it contains 5 rooms and has a detached kitchen and am- bars, but the stabling attached to this house is within four yards of the kitchen, an arrangement which is neither agreeable nor sanitary. I have no hesitation in saying that both buildings would be condemned by every sanitary authority in England as unfit for a labourer's cottage. The climate of Gulhek in summer, it is true, makes it possible to do without much that is indispensable In damper countries, but only provided that there is plenty of air space round the house, and if one of the ex isting buildings is to be utilized to provide quar ters for the student interpreters, the other must he pulled down in whole or in part, and a new house of four rooms for the Oriental Secretary (or Vice-Consul) erected on a different site. Of the two houses the Councillor's is certainly the less desirable, as it stands wedged in between the Bungalow and the wall of the Compound within 10 feet of a public road be yondbeyond which are sandhills, the heat reflected from which makes the house almost uninhabitable in the hot test month. I would, therefore, recommend that this house be demolished and a couple of fair-sized rooms added to the bungalow on the East side; the kitchen &amp;c. of the Councillor•s house being retained, but the stabling removed to a suitable distance. Mr. George estimates the cost of the enlargement of the Bungalow at Ts. 6tO and of a new house for the Oriental Secretary at Tomans 1,500. I have &amp;c.. (Signed) Cecil Spring Rice.Sir:- With reference to your communications of the 5th and 15th ultimo (18876), I am directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty's Works, &amp;c., to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State, a copy of a letter which the Board have ad dressed to His Majesty's Minister at Tehran on the subject of the provision of improved accommodation for His Majesty's Legation at that capital and at Gulhek. I am &amp;c. (Signed) J. Fitzgerald* Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. ■HIS MAJESTY'S OFFICE OF WORKS. July 3rd, 1907. Excellency Sir:- Your Excellency's despatches of the 8th and 24th • May last having been communicated to this Department hy the Foreign Office, I an directed by the First Com missioner of His Majesty's Works, &amp;c., to transmit to you herewith a Statement which has been prepared in this Department showing the original proposals for im proving the accommodation at Tehran and Culhek and those which it is understood are now recommended by you. This Statement is sent to you for confirmation, and assuming that it is correct, the Board authorize you to put in hand those works against which an as terisk has been placed. The alterations to the dis pensaries at Tehran and Culhek, referred to in Your Excellency's despatch of the 8th May, have already been ordered and the cost will be defrayed out of the pro vision for 'Minor Works' in the Estimate for Diplomatic and Consular Buildings. The Board will be glad to learn the nature of the alterations Sir Cecil A. Spring-Rice K.C.M.G.,alterations which it is necessary to make to the Bil liard room at Tehran to adapt it for a Library. The cost of the Consulate rooms is estimated by you at 11,085 tomans. This is assumed to be krans. It is observed that you condemn the bungalow at Grulhek as being M unfit for a labourer's cottage' and, in these circumstances, it is a question whe ther this Department would be justified in expending the sum of £155 in enlarging it. In the second paragraph of your despatch of the 24th May you state that it is 'hardly practicable and certainly undesir able' to enlarge the bungalow, which is represented to be a mere hovel which should be pulled down; but notwithstanding this in the penultimate paragraph of your communication you recommend that two add- tional rooms should be added to it. The Board are unable to reconcile this recommendation with the galow and before authorizing any expenditure upon it they desire to be furnished with further informationThe sum of £3,000 has been provided in the present year's Estimates on account of the above mentioned works, hut it is doubtful whether this amount will be expended unless greater progress is made with the erec tion of the house for the Military Attache at Tehran than is allowed for in the tabular statement accompany ing this letter. I have &amp;c.. (Signed) Schomberg K. McDonnell.copy- 12168/10. (273) HIS MAJESTY'S OFFICE OF WORKS, &amp;c., Storey's Gate, Westrninster, S.W. January 2nd, 1911. Sir:- Jith reference to your memorandum of the 5th ul timo, 43024, transmitting copy of a further letter from the India Office on the subject of the proposed additional accommodation required at Gulhek, I am di- ✓ rected by the First Commissioner of His Majesty's Works, ac., to state, for the information of Secretary Sir E. Grey, that in regard to the question now raised by the Secretary of State for India in Council, the outlay at Gulhek shown in the Appropriation Accounts for 1907-8 and 1908-9 was, as a matter of fact, in cluded in the statements of diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia for the 3 /'ears mentioned. I am to observe, however, that it is only during tiie last few months taat this Board have become aware of the purpose served by the information set out in the statements of expenditure referred to. They now understand that such information is required for the mS Under Secretary of State, purpose Foreign Office.r' purpose oT making the annual adjustment of accounts as 'between the Horne and the Indian Exchequers I am &amp;c., (Signed) W. J. Downer.(273/11). upon Indian Revenue the moiety of the expenditure in the present case. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, /. U&lt;C€ /HHAFT .LFiTTJiRx. ^ ^' INDIA OFFICE, 05 i9i^ j^e Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. zi ir. y? .W° &gt;9^ I an directed to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of the 2nd instant,with inclosure, regarding the proposed extension of the Legation House at Oulahek. ^ In reply I am to say, that before : ing-to shar^the cost of this extension the Secretary ^f State for jfj t (as^ ^ tu^c ^ :U hr IdZ- ^ 21' ^ ^ /^3l . ^ In44-&amp; i-n Counoi 1 - desFr^s to call the aJb±zntioTi-Qf-3ir-E.{h*ey 4o £ke fo 1 lowin-g—c-t^eumsi-onc-es. In Sir Francis Campbell's letter of the 16th f J^e-y ' ii ^ f' *~~ r. .j April 1907, No. 41j29,h)6, ^FJwas informed that His Majes ty' s Off ice of No rks and Public Buildings had included in the estimate for Diplomatic and Consular Buildings for 1907-8 a sum of &lt;£3,000 on account of a total of £6950 for ''erection of houses for Military Attache and Student Interpreters, enlargement of Chancery and adaptation of Madame Vartini's house' at Oulahek, and that it was i proposed to claim from Indian funds in the annual adjustment of accounts the repayment of half the costMi suffice stated (Sir A.Godley's 1 letter of 11th May 1907) that a moiety of the sum required (&lt;£1800) j or the purchase of Madame Vartini's property at Julahek had already been acceptea as a charge on Indian revenues: but that,before agreeing to treat the further outlay then proposed m a similar manner, the Secretary of State for India in Council would be glad to be favoured, with a view to consulting the Government of India i f necessary,with a more detailed account of the purposes to which the expenditure was to be applied. This information not having been suppl ied^Lork ^Jorle^has hitherto assumed that the proposals of 1907 had been abandoned or postponed. His attention has now been called, however, to entries in the Appropriation Accounts for 1907-8 (page 52) and 1908-9 (page 44) from which it appears that sums of £209 k— 14-3 and £1984-18-2, respectively were spent in these years on the buildings and alterations referred to in Sir F. Campbell *s letter of 16th April 1907. I am accordingly to inquire whether the figures of expenditure on Buildings shown in the statements of diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia in 1907-8 and 1908-9 which have been furnished to thisthis Department, vis: &lt;£4761.13.1 and £3648.5.3, respective!y, included the outlay at Julahek shown in the Appropriation Accounts. If that is the case, the Secretary of State for India in Council fails to understand howjthis heavy outlay came to he included in the annual claims against this Officeffn view of the terms of Sir A. Godley's letter of 11th May 1907 So referred to abovSj ’j Y/x. . / ^wnce coihmittee make no observations 2 3 NOV. 1910Political and Secret Department. Reference Paper. Letter No. Ree. 191 . Referred to T:ie expenditure of 00 now proposed appears 5 063 Je '' esira ble in itself, and, as it has no . . connection with the proposals of 1907, I think we not answered the questions put to then in our letter of 23rd September, as to the details of the proposal of 1907, J have just discovered - from the Appropriation Accounts of the Treasury for 1907-8 and 1908-9 - that the expenditure of &lt;£3,000 which we were asked in 1907 to share was actually incurred in 1907-8, and that there was further outlay ^or the same purpose in 1908-9. The entries in the Appropriation Accounts are as follows:- Accounts for 1907-8,page 52, Vote 7 (Diplomatic and Consular Buildings) Tehran and dfulahek: Erection of Houses for Military Attache and Student Interpreters, enlargement of Chanceries and adaptation of Hadame Vartini *s house. dtff will be noticed that the Foreign 0 K ffice have I. 1662. 1000.—9/1910. Vote £3000 Expenditure £3093.14. 3. Total estimate Expenditure to 31st March 1908. . ,36950. Balance ,38194. 4. o. AccountsAccounts for 1908-9,page 44, sane item:- Vote J2000 Expenditure £1984.18. 2. Total estimate £3950 Expenditure to 31st March 1909 £5740.14. 2. Toe Foreign Orfice have never mentioned, nor even hinted, in the present correspondence that these sums have been spent. In tne statement oj their diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia in 1907-8, uhich was adjusted last in Persia was shown, but no details were given, and the SeJtP.I f s 7,(5 ^ c hallenged . 2imilarly, in the statement for 1908-9, which is at present under consideration, there is an entry of £3648.5. 3 for expenditure on buildings, without details. From the entries in the Appropriation Accounts I am inclined to think that these figures include the outlay at 7ulahek in 1907—8 and 1908-9 which is shown in the Appropriation Accounts. If so, the Foreign Office have not dealt fairly by us. I attach a draft letter March, an expenditure of £-.761.13. 1 on consular buildingsIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 2 A ind address * ae Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 7 Jic Under-Seenetary of State for Foreign sijfairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for J^dia ' - ^ an d, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cofj of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, A, ^ , /^/o. Reference to previous letter: &amp; / LjFJVf-It Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ Ko Sd zy | ~TrTTtrgTv g tr- 10 a.m. ! , '' l 7 3! jO 1 /a r** •*** f*U ..6*+\Cf~! CfS v 155 / 10 . £40^ HIS MAJESTY 1 S OFFICE OF WORKS, 3cC, STOREY'S GATE, WESTT, f IMSTER, S.W. 27th October, 1910. Sir:- With reference tc your letter of the 19th instnat, 34558/10, on the subject of the proposed extension to the Legation House at Gulhek, I an directed by the First Commissioner of His Majesty's Works, etc., to state for the information of Secretary Sir E. Grey, that the works now contemplated have no connexion with the proposals* of 1907. The total amount proposed to be expended on the alterations under consideration is £300; provision for this expenditure not having been made in the Estimates for the current year, the Board ore of opinion that the work should be deferred until 1911 - 12. The extension consists of an additional two storey wing at the East comer of the Legation to provide a pantry, lamp-room and accommodation for European servants; the last does not at present exist. Treasury J nder Secretary of St 4 te, foreign Office.i Treasury authority will he required for ary pro vision in the Estimates of 1911 - 12 for this service I am, &amp;c., (Signed) W. F. Kerr.Under Secret; Comm Under Secret; Counc I y revu:^/3 J 34553 / 10 ) Sir:- U 4 0CT1910 4 NS/. .^&lt;0 FOREIGN OFFICE. October 3 . 1910 I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknow ledge the receipt of your letter of the 23rd. ultimo, relative to the proposed expenditure on His Majesty^ Legation House at Gulahek, in which you request that an] estimate of the total amount proposed to be expended may be furnished together with a statement of the man ner in which it is to be employed. In reply I am to state that the proposals of Sir C. Spring Rice in this matter which were received in June 1907 were referred in the first instance to the Office of Works with a view to communicating with your Department as soon as their comments were received. e Office of Works addressed certain criticiams on th rc~ JO &amp;..m. 4 Wfoposals direct to His Majesty's Minister at Tehran, ECTA amCE. ““'‘and Sir E. Grey is unaware what answer was returned by him. There is no later correspondence on the subject m The Under Secretary of State, India Office.^ kC.i/io ). W' V' Sir: - ioi? FOREIGN OFFICE, September 42- 1910. ^(13 SEP 1910 c) I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to £300. transmit to you herewith copy of a despatch from His Lajesty's Minister at Tehran suggesting a means by which the present inadequate accommodation at His Majesty's Legation House at Gulahek may be remedied at a cost of Three hundred pounds t I am to state that Sir E. Grey is recommending Sir G. Barclay's proposal to the favourable considera-| tion of His Majesty's Office of Works and to express the hope that, should it be adopted by that Depart ment, Viscount Morley may see his way to sanction the charge to Indian revenues of one half the expense involved in carrying it out. io fc.wi, OFriO^.J be Under Secretary of State, India Office. i am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, rr * Vy. V* ftGULHEK. 22nd August, 1910. Sir:- I desire tc call attention of His Majesty's Office of Works to the inadequacy of the accommodation which is provided in this Legation at Gulhek in two respects In the first place there is no pantry nor any room where lamps and hoots can he cleaned, so that these operations are performed at one end of the verandah on to which the drawing-room and other reception rooms of the Legation open, and are of couT’se in full sight ol the large tent generally used to receive guests who after luncheon or dinner are consequently compelled to listen to the clink and clatter of silver and glass in the process of being washed and the chatter of the native servants in their shirtsleeves. The second deficiency is the absence of any accom modation for European servants. The total sleeping accommodation of the Legation consists of six rooms, all small. Right Honourable Sir Edward Grey, Bart., &amp;c., &amp;c., cS&amp;C . r ^Mi fc o.^w^ Ov?) small, three of them scarcely more than dressingrooms, and all opening on to the upper verandah. There are but two closets, and there Is no room which could serve as a servants' hall. I feel sure that the commlbolon- ers will agree with me that such accommodation Is wholly inadequate and requires supplement. For this purpose I would suggest that a small building, of which a plan prepared by Mr. McIntyre is enclosed, should be added to the east end of the Legation. As will he seen on | -| the plan it provides on the ground floor a pantry, lamp room and servants' hall, and on the first floor three bedrooms and two closets, and the cost Mr. McIntyre places at £300. ■ l venture to hope that sanction will oe ^iven for this very necessary expenditure in time to allow of the work being put in hand at once, so that it may he com- jj pleted in time for occupation next summer. I have, &amp;c .Register No. Minute Paper. So-jS Political Department. Dated Letter from Z2 190 Ust^ }pU^- Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee ./ Under Secretary Secretary &lt;f)f State flonnoil fjidLdJLes^ ■ ^ cvM. L/^j^avb^ 1$us? G&amp;s(r*J@*ijL 'I^e. . ic^ .In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 15835. and address— s'rx. 1V Ft The Under-Secretai’y of State, Foreign Office, London. ft2?MAY,907 t Foreign Office \ N v , \ •. a \* May 22nd, 1907. Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to ac knowledge the receipt of your letter of the 11th in stant, relative to the question of meeting the ex pense to he incurred in respect of certain necessary improvements in the premises of His Majesty’s Lega tion at Gulahek, in which you state that, before agreeing to accept responsibility for half the amount actually spent under this head, Mr. Secretary Morley would wish to receive a more detailed account of the purposes to which this money will be applied,, with a view to consulting the Government of India. I am to inform you, in reply, that in a des patch, dated February 28th last. His Majesty's Min ister at Tehran wrote that 'very soon submit propos als as to the manner in which this money should be employed'. These proposals will doubtless furnish all the information The Under Secretary of State, India Office.r information desired dy Mr. Morley and I am to state that, so soon as they are received at this Oifice, Sir E. Grey will at once communicate them to him. I am. Your most obedient. humble Servant, iTim Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, liondon. _! Ip '\pp|0r' 7 £5,000. £6,950. Foreign Office April 16th, 1907. Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to inform you that His Majesty's Office of Works and Public Buildings have included in the estimate for Diplomatic and Consular Buildings for 1907-3 a sum of Three thousand pounds on account of a Total of Six thousand nine hundred and fifty pounds for 'erec tion of houses for Military Attache and Student In terpreters, enlargement of Chancery and adaptation of Madame Vartini's house' at Gulahek. I an to state that it is proposed to claim from i Indian funds In the annual adjustment of accounts the repayment of half the cost of any actual expen diture which may he incurred undor this head. received 10 a.m- \ 0 APR. 1S07 &gt; ^ i a r\ rT-j '•'‘H' Your most obedient. ^ie Under Secretary of State, India Office. humble Servant,Tn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 33150/06. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office January 8th, 1907 Sir:- The Secretary of State for India is doubtless aware that His Majesty* s Legation at Tehran exer cise over the village of Gulahek, where their sum mer quarters are situated, a j_urisdiction which, though it reposes solely on custom and has no basis in law, has nevertheless for many years been re- j by foreign subjects resident in the country. In the exercise of the rights v/hich they un doubtedly possess. His Majesty’s Legation have been accustomed to forbid the holding of land or house property in Gulahek to all foreigners other than Per sian subjects, a rule the application of which it is most desirable to maintain since any foreign sub ject in such a position might easily set at naught the authority of His Majesty’s Legation and, if sup ported 'Hie Under Secretary of State India Office.a ^ , &gt;&gt; supported by the Representative of his own Govern ment, initiate a controversy by which, if he were successful, British prestige would suffer and the position of the Legation at Gulahek would become most difficult. Early in 1905 it was brought to the notice of Sir A. Hardinge, then His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, that a property, consisting of a garden of some six and a half acres, in which are one large and four smaller houses, which adjoins the Legation at Gulahek, was in the possession of an Armenian lady named Vartini who had inherited it by will from the late Mr. Alison, a former British Minister at the Court of Persia, and who continued to hold it in spite of the fact that she had subsequently be come, by marriage, a Russian subject. In view of the considerations set forth above and of two further facts - firstly, that the Rus sian Legation showed some signs of a desire to in terfere with the property on the ground of the ow ner’s nationality and, secondly, that the space was required to improve the accommodation of the * st af fstaff of His Majesty’s Legation, it seemed to Sir A. Hardinge to de very desirable to acquire the hold ing of Madame Vartini with as little delay as pos sible. This view' was shared by this Department and after a long and voluminous correspondence the de tails of which it is unnecessary to recapitulate, the Treasury sanctioned the purchase of the property for the sum of Ten thousand four hundred tomans (about One thousand eight hundred pounds) and it will be usea to supplement the accommodation at the dis posal of the staff of His Majesty’s Legation which is at present very inadequate. His Majesty's Minister at Tehran will be in structed in due course to pay over the above sum to the present owner of the property and I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to state, for Mr. Mor- ley's information, that he proposes to include the charge in the general statement of expenditure to be shared by His Majesty’s Government with the Govern ment/ ■ J I • ' 11 / I ;ll : Government of Inaia in order that it may be dealt with in the yearly adjustment of accounts I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, &gt;*r ' f •Political, No. 73. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to your letter of the 4th March 1909, No. 33, submitting a comparative statement Expenditure on Diplomatic and of expenditure on Diplomatic and LonsuLar services in Persia m ^ a • • ^ • 1907-08 Consular Services m Persia in 1906-07 and 1907-08, I forward herewith a copy of a Memorandum prepared in this Office, and request' that I may be supplied at an early date with the information desired therein. The mket convenient course would be that a revised statement of expenditure should be furnished embodying the additional information required. 2. The increase in expenditure in 1907-08 is very considerable, amounting, even after deduction of the special payment of Rs. 60,000 in respect of Koweit under the Agreement with the Sheikh of the 15th October 1907, to 8,135Z., and I request that, in addition to the information asked for in the Memorandum, I may be furnished with a brief statement in general terms of the chief causes of this increase. I observe that certain of the payments in 1907-08 are stated to include considerable sums in respect of 1906-07, but I presume that there were also considerable arrear payments in 1906-07. Some explanation is required of the continuous growth of the charges shown under the head of “ contingencies.” 3. A statement^ of the outlay at Imperial posts in Persia during 1906-07 and 1907-08 is inclosed . * Inclosure in Foreign Office letter of p ? . T 'ist April 1909 (3194/09). ±or purposes of comparison. It will be observed that the total outlay in 1907-08 was somewhat less than in the previous year. 4. With reference to the special item of expenditure at Koweit, I have to remark that such expenditure cannot properly be included in a statement of charges incurred in Persia. But it will be convenient to effect in connection with the annual settlement of the Persian charges an adjustment of the expenditure incurred at places in the Gulf and its 6314. I. 1416. Avicinity outside Persia which the British Treasury have agreed to share ; and I request that a statement of any charges of this kind up to the 31st March 1908 which have not yet been adjusted may be appended as a supplement to the statement of expenditure in Persia. I also request that this procedure may be followed in future. 5. It is extremely desirable, as I have said, that the information should be given to me at an early date. I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Morley of Blackburn.ENCLOSURES. Enclosure No. 1. MEMORANDUM. .Persian Legation. Contingencies .explanation given of the expenditure under the nead Contingencies ” should apparently read as follows:—“ Of this ■&lt; , • . 13 &gt; : ' !;:i5 is 011 account of Jask Royalty for 1905-06 and „ 1j 06 -07, being Rs. 17,647. 1. less Rs. 4,292. 1. (Krs. 14,593) repre- sentmg deductions, &amp;c.” E fort Charges. The explanation given of the increase of Ks. 5L,o4l. 1. 2. in the Escort Charges is not quite clear. The Crovernment of India should be asked to state :— (а) The amount refunded to the Imperial Government in 1907-08. It is not clear from the statement whether this was Rs. 26,280. 1. 4. or Rs. 13,140. 0. 8. (б) How much, approximately, of the remaining expenditure in 1907-08 was for the first time charged in full to Indian revenues (in other words, what amount would under the system previously followed have been shared by the Imperial autho rities in the firsi instance or through the Account Current, and so excluded from the statement) ? Special payment—Hlaz special payment of Rs. 60,000 by the Accoun tant-General, Bombay, being on account of Koweit, should be excluded from the statement of expenditure in Persia, and arrangements for recovery of the portion chargeable to Imperial revenues should be made separately in accordance with the instructions in the last paragraph of the covering Despatch. Seistan. Salaries. The extent to which arrear payments enter into the figures of expenditure in 1907-08 makes it difficult to understand the exact position of affairs in the two years. If the expenditure in 1906-07 similarly includes arrear payments, the amount of these should be stated. In the correspondence between the Secretary of State and the Government of India regarding appointments in Seistan, the term ^ ice-consul has apparently been used only of the minor appointment at Koh-i-Malik Siah, held originally by Mahomed Ashraf Khan. The references to Lieutenant Daukes and Captain Kelly in connection with this appointment are not understood and should be explained. Contingencies.—No explanation is given of the increase under this head. Civil Buildings. Iso information has apparently been furnished to the Secretary of State regarding the buildings in question. General .—The rate of expenditure at this Consulate appears to be very high. Excluding medical expenditure in connection with the plague (which shows a decrease in consequence of the cessation of the plague), there is an increase in the charges in 1907-08 of Rs. 29 343 (1,965Z.)■~r'THTr Meshed. Pay and Allowances. —It is not clear whether the figures given include the cost of the Military Attache, whose temporary appointment was covered by the terms of the letter from the Treasury to the Foreign Office of 25th January 1907, No. 1447 (see Enclosure No. 2 in Despatch from Secretary of State to Government of India, No. 34, 29th March 1907). The Government of India should also be asked to say whether the expenditure on the Military Attache prior to 1906-07 was included in the previous annual statements of diplomatic and Consular expenditure in Persia. Permanent Establishment. —The increase under this head seems to have been very heavy. Contingencies. —No explanation is given of the increase under this head. Turbat-i-Haidari. Salaries. —Presumably the payments to Captain Keyes and Captain Franklin in respect of periods in 1906-07 which are referred to in the “Remarks ” column were made in 1907-08? Contingencies. —The increase under this head is not explained. General. —The rate of expenditure at this Consulate seems high, and the increase in 1907-08 considerable. Kerman. General. —The increase of expenditure at this Consulate is very large, the explanation given being that it is due to the inclusion of expenditure for several months of 1906-07 in the accounts of 1907-08. Before the accounts are forwarded to the Foreign Office information should be obtained as to the amount of increase under each head which is due to this cause. The Government of India should also state whether the expenditure in 1905-06 does not also include arrear payments, and, if so, to what extent. Bam. With reference to Enclosure No. 5 in the letter to the Foreign Office, of 17th March last, a copy of which was forwarded to the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department on the 4th June 1909, the Government of India should be asked to state whether the expenditure at Bam in 1906-07, which was shown in the statement accompanying their letter of 20th September 1908, No. 165, included the whole of the outlay in connection with that post. If not, particulars of the outlay omitted should be furnished. The date on which the expenditure in connection with Bam ceased, and the approximate amount included on account of Bam in the accounts of expenditure at Kerman in 1907-08, should also be stated. Kermanshah. Supplies and Service and Contigencies. —Some explanation of the increase under this head is desirable. Arabistan. An explanation should be furnished of the increased expenditure on Allowances, and of the increase of Rs. 4,610, under Supplies and Services and Contingencies, independent of the amounts attributable to the Mohammerah launch and the Oil Syndicate Camp charges.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00007a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/229</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00007a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/229</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 741/1912 'Persia: Tehran Legation; purchase of land at Gulhak. Additions to Legation House at Gulhak'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1907/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-27T23:41:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (172 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. The subject 741 (Persia: Tehran Legation) consists of 1 volume, IOR/L/PS/10/229.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 172; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, notes, estimates and statements of expenditure, relating to the purchase of land adjacent to the British Legation in Gulahak in Tehran. The discussion in the volume relates to the cost of improvements in the premises of the legation at Gulahak and how these costs should be borne between the British government and the Government of India.Further discussion surrounds the criticism by the Office of Works of the plans for refurbishing the accommodation and the response of the Foreign Office; also an explanation by the Foreign Office as to why they had not previously consulted the India Office about such expenditure. Included in the volume are number of financial accounts, such as 'Statement of Expenditure in Persia in 1906-07 and 1907-08 incurred by the Imperial Government' (ff 169 - 170).The principal correspondents in the volume include: Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Sir Edward Grey; Ambassador to Persia, Cecil Arthur Spring-Rice; First Commissioner of His Majesty's Office of Works.Each part includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, year the subject file was opened, subject heading, and list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Office of Works, First Commissioner</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Gulahak</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Embassy buildings</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Tehran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00007a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>