<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002de_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-12T20:28:29.053Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">)\ ExtJ762/47 DRAFT EXPRESS LETTER Frcsn: To: Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations Political Resident, Persian Gulf. fcJfc &lt; *h) A 6 AUG 1947 /j u -&gt; ivly telegram No.3945 of 24th Marcl^ Copy /to: Muscat telephones. Foreign Office G.P.O. (ML ecc®pHlunications ,^5ept.) C.C.C. (Col^ambra.) Board of T 2 ra.de (Jsqport Prompxion Depv;) /4 - $ r***dJ‘ e/JuA Ufa. CtJrk C- ■ MS'- enclosed herewith of letter from r'eless Ltd/ 3 2 . Cable and Wir'^fess ' They consider that Automatic Telephone and Electric Company’s tender, enclosed with my express letter Ext.438/47 of 26th February, 1947, is of little use from the Sultan’s point of view, since it is incomplete. They are themselves proposing to prepare comprehensive sc! for supply of material as sub-contracts from various firms including Automatic 3SjLng i,o prepa ( U&gt; ;neme and/mvx re a f te tenders m ■ Telephone and Electric Company. 3. cyu, P-*■ ^4«) t P. UOMAUNOMTelephone Temple Bar 1222' j ( Telegrams Empi^egram Estrand Londa CABLE AND WIRELESS LTD ELECTRA HOUSE VICTORIA EMBANKMENT LONDON WC2 T14/W/P6/1A. Reply to the Chairman quoting reference and date F.A.K. Harrison, Esq,, India Office, LONDON, S.W.l. I 'l Dear Mr. Harri’son, 13th August. 1341. fjJL CL4U Z r exth ^ 17.' ‘», ‘t %i f&gt;- 1/W^' Muscat: Telephones . ^ T , 1 ^ We have recently received Colonel / Bloodworth's preliminary report on his visit m June last to Muscat &gt; of investigation of '/f/^ the possibilities of providing a telephone system in Muscat and Mutrah. This report contains the broad outline of a scheme for connecting 100 subscribers at the commencement ana rising to a maximum of 200 subscribers. The scheme was not discussed with the Sultan who was absent in Salalah. We have agreed in principle to the Company going ahead with the proposal and our Divisional Manager will now inform the Sultan pi our plans ana obtain the latter^ agreement before preparing details. We will communicate with you again when this next stage is reached. Yours sincerely. Traffic Manager.* CT^c- a*, ^ ^ x&lt; •CasCi+w 0tsCC+^C6 '^-+* sC^*% Mizsoafe '■ Autoniatia Telephone Syeteia &gt; 11« Investigation of the requirements has been somewhat v ^ delayed as a result of a slight misunderstanding over the proposed visit of a Cable &amp; Wireless* Ltd*, engineer and a subsequent absence of transport,* The situation has now been, cleared up satisfactorily* and the engineer should arrive toward** the end of Aprilc Once agreement has been reached with the Sultan as *o the term^ under which the installation is to be operated* completion of the project should take very little time* as suitable material is available for almost immediate delivery &amp;!/,v ' f Wr F INWARD TELEGRAMS &gt;^SK *2 821 'IL^xi .. y if if ^, Allotted to Exte rnal Dep artment s Fi*om To Dated 3K5Wl3i erslan Gfclf O OHFIDMTI4L Political Keside; Secretary of State for India Bahrein* 11*40 hours* 17th April 1947 Received 11*15 hours* 17th April 1947 No* 447, Rexerence to India office expx*ees letter No» Ext a 436/4 7 26th February* Telephone instali©tione at toscat* /&amp;&amp; spar© copies of tender referred to those received under India office printed letter dated 4th March or are complete duplicates of papers which have been transmitted to Sultan being forwarded*(\o) INWARD TELEGRAM iNDEXED * n Ql IQ Allotted to gxte'rnal Departn^nt „ fI ^ ~ 4100, Cop ies t qi Perm. US. • PS*, to US, LL Depy. US ' PS. to Parly.US Asst. U8 ? s. _ Mr. Turnbull. -« , for Burma. * Mr, floyce. Asst. US. for Burma. Resident Cleric. Pd. to SS. Capt, BrocInman (4). a CONFIDENT CAL OOPS O.f.li f Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ^ Secretary of State for India. r Bahrain* 17*00 hours. 4th March, 1947. 22.80 hours, 4th March* 1947. Fr cm To Dated Received fro. 280* 'Paragraph No. 3 my telegram No.245 February 26th. 2. Political. Agent, Muscat, reports that it now appears in January 1946 Hirst suggested to. Sultan that Cable and Wireless would be the best people to install telephones and Sultan agreed; afterwards Cable and Wireless indicated that, they were not interested and referred Hirst to Automatic Telephone and Electric Company. If at our instance Cable and Wireless now reverse their former* decision it will still be necessary to inform Sultan as in paragraph No.3 of my telegram first quoted. cy~ ‘' / A| uUl lJUJ* UAX ’*- /Pi.AUTOMATIC TELEPHONE &amp; ELECTRIC CO. LTD. , AegHiertd OH%c* Sr Works STROWGER WORKS- LIVERPOOL 7 Telephone So.- 9TONEYCROFT 4830 is LINES (OltlVATC BRANCH CXCHANOI Telegrams anti Cablegrams STROWGER '. LIVERP bEPARTMENT. E . NORFOLK ST. WC 2 REFERRINS TO TO and quote in reply Telephone No.: TEMPLE BAR 9262-0 (PRIVATE BRANCH EXCHANGE) Inland Telegrams: ••AUTELCO. ESTRAND, LONDON” Cablegrams : ‘‘AUTELCO. LONDON” Codes: WESTERN UNION ”5 LETTER” BENTLEY'S ACME PRIVATE 25th February 1947 a^/rrD/EQ844. ‘HE company The India Office, Whitehall, S«W.1. Dear Sirs, For the attention of TT r. F. K. Harrison. TT uscat. ■ You have very kindly promised to convey the enclosed tender for telephone equipment to the British Political Agent in T 'uscat. We do not know whether the tender has been rightly addressed to the ''Technical Adviser 11 , but we assume that HWH• The Sultan v/ill have somebody in his entourage who can advise him on the merits of the technical plan submitted. We shall be much obliged if you would advise the British Liaison to follow up this matter and communicate with us at his earliest convenience, nfortunately we have not got a representative in that part of the country, though perhaps the Resident Station Manager of Cable Wireless could be asked for technical advice. We have sent a copy of our quotation and notes to C. &amp; W. for conveyance to their permanent Resident in Yuscat. We should like to express again our thanks for your kind support in this matter. Yo ur s fa i thfly^ AUTOMATIC TELEPHONE &amp; ELECTS WARD.i copy. rV ^ it.' vii P' 'J^jArsCk ' \ a eon i »». \ m/t.fi/u 14993/38 t9 l»f} /,cac r— ^SLjL.cjl a, ,CA /* $k /// V 4.ca^caj ^C /, 7 February, 19V7* j-^- ^ySU^^JLJL -C-oA/~^ Sir, (foyy ' JCS - PG.f&gt;Cy. &lt;\ P.f*l. vXtw^-t^t ’ /y^ v\ // &gt; GV I am directed by the Postmaster General to refer to the o rrespondeoce between your Company and the India Office about the proposed installation of an automatic telephone system in Muscat and to infom you that a reply to the questionnaire, which was sent by the Automatic Telephone and Telegraph Company to Major Hirst, Military Adviser to the Sultan of Muscat, has now been received by the London firm, (Mr* Westgartta) and they are considering the information it contains* It is understood that the Automatic Telephone and Telegraph Co^any v 'ho are supplying the equipment for Bahrein, hold the view th t it would be convenient if the Muscat scheme could go through at an early date so that the same party of experts could supervise installation at both places* As already indicated in the letter of 4th June 1946 to your Company from the India Office the question of operotion (and possibly installation) of the system by your Company now arises, and in view of your similar interests in Bahrein and Kuwait the postmaater General would be glad to learn whether the project will be undertaken by your Company. It is understood that Colonel Hay, the political Resident of the The Chairman, Cable and Wireless Ltd* Persian/c AUTOMATIC TELEPHONE &amp; ELECTRIC CO. LTD. W i yi Ttltphont No.; IP' EXPORT DEPARTMENT. NORFOLK HOUSE . NORFOLK ST. p LONDON • W • C • 2 o K/ Minima (JUxct &amp; Works STROWGER WORKS- LIVERPOOL 7 Telephone No.' STONEYCROFT 4830 is LINEH IPMIVATS ■•I.NCM CXCHANO. Telegrams and Cablegrams 'STROWGER . UVERPOO f».- ERRING TO YOURS Telephone No.; TEMPLE BAR 9262-8 {PRIVATE BRANCH EXCHANGE) Inland Telegrams'. 'AUTELCO. ESTRAND. LONDON” Cablegrams : 'AUTELCO. LONDON' Codes: WESTERN UNION '5 LETTER” BENTLEY’S ACME PRIVATE Extn.8605A6' India Office, Whitehall, LONDON, S.W.l. PLEASE ADDRESS THE COMPANY AND QUOTE IN REPLY ? M/JMP/EQSljij. 6th January { ^j Attention of Mr Booth Dear Sir, Many thanks indeed for your letter of the 51st December attaching a letter of 3rd June from Mai or Hirst to Messrs Telephone Manufacturers of India, Calcutta, on the subject of telephone equipment for the Sultan of Muscat. We are investigating the requirements mentioned therein, and if there is any further information which is necessary, we will contact you before going further. /^hanking you for your co-operation. iff 7 jt\ M47 Yours faithfully, AUTOMATIC TELEPHONFT&amp; ELECTRIC CO.LTD. R. WESTGARTH.Jib Cuui FILE COPY. MPttkSS LLTiIr C' fo o vJ jUDEXED^ 0 ^ ^ - From political Resident, per^-^n Gulfi aboard S.Y. ^Kiftg-Faloal To Retaxandum, London. y Repeated political, Muscat. No.C/499. Dated the 15th December 1946. Reference your telegram No.20901 dated the 29th N ovember 1946 , 2. Reply to questionnaire received from the Automatic Telephone and Electric Company Limited (c.f. your express letter No.Ext.3747/46 dat ed 4th^ June 1946) was sent to the Indian agents of the firm irT'Juhe (copy enclosed) and nothing has been heard from the firm or their agents since in spite of reminders. 3. Cable and wireless informed me in London that they were not interested in the Muscat project as it Was not proposed that they should work it them selves. It is however desired that the Company should operate the system themselves and the Company’s Manager at Muscat has told me that he would undert&gt;ake responsibility for this with the addition of only two skilled workmen to his staff provided an engineer with experience of automatic telephone systems is posted to his regular staff. 4. present position is most unsatisfactory and I strongly recoaimend that Cable and wireless should be urged to undertake responsibility for sully ing, installing and working system subject to prior examination of financial implications. 5. Grateful for very early action as matter has now been pending for about nine months. t NPG,□ o o TM/6. Muscat, i 3rd June, 1946. » I Telephone Manufactures of India Ltd., 6, Lyons Range, Calcutta. Dear Sirs, With reference to your No.TM¥-l£24/6543 of 1-2-46. I have received a questionnaire from the automatic Telephone &amp; Electric Co. Lta., which I am forwarding to you. I regret that it is not possible to reply to many of the points noted and think it would be of more assistance to you if I gave you our requirements on broad lines. 1. The existing mains supply is D.C. 2. The mains supply, if provided by the Consulate power House is reliable, if supplied by the State Power House it is doubtful. 3. There is no particular building selected for housing the equipment as yet. 4. Initially 50 lines would be required, it is not possible to give any accurate estimate of the possible expansion but is not thought that it would ever exceed 200. 5. Strowgers RAX 50-8B appears to be the most suitable equipment. I imagine that when it became overloaded another could be added quite easily? 6. The type of wire which would be suitable for distance over 1^- miles would be 150 lbs. per mile iron wire or 70 lbs. per mile bronze. The distance between the two adjacent towns of Muscat and Matrah is approximately 3 miles. It is presumed that if the exchange was situated between the two towns a lighter wire could be used. Yours faithfully.Extract from Notes on visit to the Persian G-ulf, October, 1946, from Telecommunications Attache to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated 20th October, 1946* + + + + + + + Telephone Installation - Muscat 16. The Divisional Manager of Gable and Wireless Ltd. states quite openly that as a result of the Company's none too happy experiences with telephones in Bahrein and Kuwait, there have been no very strenuous moves regarding the proposed Muscat installation, and have been waiting for further information from the manufacturers as to the availability of the necessary apparatus. It is suggested that this matter is left for further discussion with the India Office and Cable and Wireless Ltd. in London.I spoke to Mr* G&gt; R. Maitland of the automatic Telephone and Electric Company ■who confirmed that the position was as stated in Cable and jj/ireless letter® He said that his Company did not in fact to make any money out of this business but were prepared to accept it from wider consideration So They could however not do more than supply and instal the equipment, so it will presumably be necessary to ran upon Cable and Wireless to assist in its operation* Mr* Mai tland agreed however that it would be premature to pursue this with Cable and Wireless at the memento f ft. *Mr*Harrison, (fa l^iany thanks for showing me these papers* xhe Automatic Telephone and Electric Company are at present looking for orders all over the world as the cessation of their war contracts threatens them with an unemployment problem* It is quite true that the Automatic Telephone and Electric Company are not an operating concern—they are merely plant manufacturers. There is, however, an Associated Company of which Sir alexandep Rogers, the chairman of the Automatic Telephone and 3]lectric Company,is also % chairman which deals with the operation of telephone installations overseas*.I should have thought the latter Company would have been the one which might have been I suggested for this Muscat installation instead of Cable I and Wireless Limited* As you will no doubt be aware the Cable and Wireless Limited are shortly to be taken over by Government. It seems to me a little doubtful whether the new Government concern would be an appropriate one to run overseas installations of tlis kind* I agree,however, that it is probably premature to pursue this question of the operating Company further at the moment. (xtCiVu. »&gt; i\ Exto 3747/4^ (S) DRAFT EXPRESS LETTER Prom:- Secretary ’of State for India Q.iA^h j To?*--. Political Resident Persian G-ulf, Repeated to Government d? India, External Affairs Department and Political Agents Muscat* / '4- N 0&gt; 1 0 C^r- »i p~ ^ '• ^ (i) ft u L* v i ■ 'J ImA i/t Cf- # • Reference yo«r/Express Letter No* 501-S of 26tlaisiApril, installation of # ^ i 9 v « telephone system at Muscat* 2* Copy of correspondence with Maamem £r Cable and Wirless Limited is forwarded herewith for your information* It has been flu confirmed fror^/Autoiaatio Telephone and Electric Company Li mi tod - that the position is as stated in the penultimate paragraph of Cable and Wireless letter of 27th May , and that they are at present awaiting a reply to their questionnaire from/fciilitary Adviser to the Sultan of Muscat* It is /&amp; /£* understood that/^ activity oj^Automatic Telephone and Electric Company would be /limited/ Ejct.3747A6 draft letter c ) ■ The Chairman, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd* , 4 JuN 1946 Slectra House, Victoria Embankment, W.C.2* Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your letter No# TJ5/P*6/3 a of 27th May !U t&amp;llation of an automatic telephone system in Muscat* l, it is understood from the Automatic Telephone aM Electric Company that their oporafiemfi in the event of their tender being accepted would be limited to the supply arid installation of the equipment^ and it may therefore be necessary at a later stage to Jcb Cal ^ fl gV your Company &gt;fog-aaoiatance-iH the n 1U u*~tt4**,*rt r * * r operation of the system* This question may however perhaps be postponed until it has been decided whether the Automatic Telephone /Companya. memm T M/ P.6/U &gt; f 3747 /I c E.P. Donaldson, Esq., C.M.G., India Office, Whitehall, ^ S.W.l. j v Sir, I acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your letter Ext.3503/46, dated the 22nd May, 1946. The facts, as we understand them, are as follows:- At the end of December 1945 the Sultan of Muscat approached an American manufacturer regarding the installation of a local automatic telephpne system in Muscat and district to provide for 40. rising to 1^0 subscribers, the installation to be state-owned. , Company's Manager at Muscat, when conveying to us the above information, said that the Sultan might be persuaded to entrust the installation and operation to us if we so desired. i We have close working relations with the British organisation, the Automatic Telephone and Electric Company, Ltd. and as the Muscat telephone proposal appeared to be a’matter of more interest to that organisation than to ourselves, we replied to our Manager that we were not particularly interested but had passed the information to the above-mentioned Company. We learnt later that Major Hirst, Military Adviser to the Sultan of Muscat, had visited Karachi in January 1946 in order to contact the Indian agents of the Automatic Telephone and Electric Company, and that Please see over.PH subsequently that firm was asked to submit a quotation. The London office tells us that the necessary questionnaire has been prepared and submitted to Major Hirst and that as'soon as his reply is received, the appropriate quotation will be made without delay. In the above-described circumstances, we should be glad to be advised of your wishes in the matter. Yours faithfully,• &amp; Managing Director.V 'Z.o. India Office, XilUjft ’Whitehall, ( o vr A \J.^~ Ext. 3503/46 Sir, y**' «u»i Ua -y ^ h6 ‘ ^p 0 ■ The Secretary of State understands that 'the Sultan of Muscat is considering the introduction of a'telephone system in the towns of Muscat and Matrah (about 80 - 100 connections would be required) and has been in touch with an American firm on the subject. The Local Manager of your Company has apparently been informed of this but after reference to his head office lias stated tliau the Company are not interested in the project. 2. *The Secretary of State attaches importance to this business being undertaken by a British undertaking, and, in view of their existing connections with the Persian G-uIj- , where ohey already operate a telephone system at Koweit and are about to do so at Bahrein, he would see advantage to British political interests if your Company were to undertake this project in Muscat. 3. I should be grateful if I might be informed whether the attitude of tiie Company has been correctly reported in Order that further consideration may be given to the matter. I arn, Sir Your obedient Servant, The Chairman, Cable &amp; Y/ireless Ltd. Electra House, Victoria Embankment, E P. DONAklW* *WKT i ! X I i* f\LL wOPY GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. T&lt; •' J. J- .4 - »- 'a 1 tu sl EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL)! L [N.B. Th\&amp; ts an ORIGINAL message Bent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Persian Guliff Residency, Bushire. Dated — , the 26th iipril 1946. Nq- 501 - 6 . To Re oe a te d New. Delhi Retaxanduia, London. Foreign, New Delhi. Political, Muscat. m Me. w \ x O A y0rl 5 — &gt; my oultan oi i.iuscat is considering introduction of telephone system and is understood to have been in touch with American firm for its installation. Local manager of Gable &amp; tireless was ap.oarsntly informed of this and referred matter to his head office. He has received reply that Company is not interested. 2 * F °r obvious reasons it is desir a ble that work should be undertaken by a British Company, and since Cable &amp; tireless already operate the telephone system at Kuwait and are going to do so at Bahrain and are most conveniently situated to undertake it in Muscat, it is requested that you will urge on Comoany desirability of their undertaking installation. feleohones would be installed in towns of Muscat and Matra and it is estimated that 80 to 100 connections would be required. .3d. G-EOFFRLY PRIOR. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. AT TESTED . , /KU'-f for Becrexary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. HDN. S. 44 . MFP—1015 S&amp;P—(M.1870}—9-2-39—20,000. {Signature) {Designation</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002de_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/4156</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002de</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/4156</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 35/48 'Muscat: installation of automatic telephone system'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-29T23:03:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (38 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 40; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the installation of telephone equipment at Muscat by Cable and Wireless Limited.The file contains correspondence between: the Foreign Office; the India Office; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Cable and Wireless Limited; the General Post Office; and Automatic Telephone &amp; Electric Company Limited.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>General Post Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002de#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>