<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000219_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T03:36:00.100Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SELECTIONS FEOM THE * llcco^isi of tlte (fBomumettt of f nto, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. I HSTc. GLXV'. • * i , REPORT ON THE ADMINISTRATION . # OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY and .MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY For the Tear 1878-79. By Lieutenant-Colonel E. C. HOSS, POIilTICAIi EESIDENT, PETtSPAN GULJf. by gitttltonty. CALCUTTA: OFFICE OF THE SUPERINTENDENT OF GOVERNMENT PRINTING. 1880.COlsTXIBIbTTS. Voo Page. Letter from Lieutenant-Colonel E. C. Ross, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, transmitting the Administration Report for the year 1878-79 ... 1 PART I. General Report for 1878-79 ... 'Omaji. Arab Coast' . Bahrein . Nejd, El Hasa, El Katr Southern Persia . Bassidore . • • Establishments Slave Trade . . • • _ i j j • f n j Table showing force and prevailing directions of winds and recorded ramtall at Bushire for the year 1878-79 Abstract Table of Meteorological Obseryations for the year ending 31st March 1879, taken at the Residency Observatory, Bushire Meteorological observations taken at Shiraz, 1878-79 . ... Description of. the Bahrein Islands by Captain E. L. Durand, First Assistant Resident, Persian Gulf •_ ' Memorandum on the Topography, &amp;c., of Khuzistan or Persian Arabia, by P. J. C. Robertson, Esq., Assistant Political Agent, Busrah Routes to Ispahan from Bunder Deelam and Hindian . . . •' • PART II. Report on Trade of the Persian Gulf for 1878. Grain, &amp;c., opium Mother o pearl, cotton, dates and fruits, Persian tobacco, cotton-goods, sugar, specie, copper . • . • • Steam communication ... Trade between Persian Gulf and India . Local impediments to British trade Opportunities for extension of British trade Memorandum on the opium of Persia . ^ Memorandum of cultivation of a village Shiraz 2 ib. 4 5 7 10 ih. 11 12 13 14 15 19 26 27 28 29 ih. 30 31 ib. n one of the Boolooks (districts) of fisheries and fishing boats on the List of vessels engaged in trade and pear coast of 'Oman . . . • List of vessels engaged in trade of Bahrein List of vessels engaged in trade and fisheries on the Persian Coast from Lmgah to Dayer . . • . • • u td * Statement showing the total value of import and export trade between the Fresi- dencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind, and the Persian Gulf, from the year 1872-73 to 1877-78, as shown in the Indian Trade Returns . • • • ' • * ' ' . * 34 40 41 42 45IV CONTENTS. •i 46 47 Statement showing the total value of the import and export trade 'between Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind and P,,.,.!' from the year 18 7 5-76 to as shown in tho Annual S^ 8 o^ Irade of those Presidencies UI Statement showing the total value of the import and export trade beWn+k' Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind ar !? terntoriesof the Sultan of Muscat in Arabia, from ?hr4ai 187^ 1877-78, as shown in the Annual Statements of Trade of those Presidencies Statement showing the total value of the import and exoort frado w ,, Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Proving of ^ ^ ^ Oratories -of States other than Muscat from the year ^ 18/ 7-78, as shown in the Annual Statements of Trade of those Presidencit Statement showing the total value of the import and exnorf Wo w Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the CviSfof « -?Tr B ^ of Busrah in Turkish Arabia, from the year 1875-76 to 1877 78 a ^ in the Annual Statements of Trade of thS prSencies ' ^ Statement showing the total value of the import and exnort trad^ England and Persia from the year 1873 to 1878 as shown in fv, a weei ? Trade Eeturns ofBushire, Ling'ah and Bunder Abbis ^Annual Statement showing the total, value of the import and exoort nf P • Abstr ll^: Abstract Table showing the total estimated value of the nrmciral anrl cles of trade exported from Bushire during the ^ wT! aad ^ ^ Abstract Table showing the total estimated value of the principal and ofW cles of trade imported into Lingah during the year 1878 and other a* Abstract Table sbowing the total estimated vnlno u. • • i , , cles of trade exited from BaS totglc /ea^S ^ arti - Pri-ipal and other' arti-' the Pirate CoasT eriend n» i m?' ln the Eer8ian Gulf k''™ year 1878 . n J5as-el-kbyma to Aboo Zhabi during the Abstract TaWe^jving^tota^estimidpd lvalue of th; prindpal'and otbe; arti-' the Pirate Coas? extending A ^ ^ ln tho Persian Gulf k 'own as year 1878 ' 0 rom ^as-ebkhymah to Aboo Zhabi during the ^^W^ZrinVtt^^^riS ^ 8 dMCri P^ on of good^ imported into Bushire during the yTara^Fand ^g7 8 descri I )tion . of &amp;' 00(1 s exported from lingah during the yeafs 1877 and 1878 deSCription of ^ oods im P orte d into 50 90 100 101CONTENTS. V Page. Contrasted Statement showing the value and description of goods exported from Lingah during the years 1877 and 1878 . . • . . . . • 103 Contrasted Statement showing the value and description of goods imported into Bahrein during the years 1877 and 1878 . . . • • • • • 105 Contrasted Statement showing the value and description of goods exported from Bahrein during the years 1877 and 1878 106 Contrasted Statement showing the value and description of goods imported into the Arab Coast in the Persian Gulf known as the Pirate Coast, extending from Ras-el-khymah to Aboo Zhahi, during the years 1877 and 1878 . . 107 Contrasted Statement showing the value and description of goods exported from the Arab Coast in the Persian Gulf known as the Pirate Coast extending from Ras-el-khymah to Aboo Zhabi during the years 1877 and 1878 . . 109 Table showing average tonnage of vessels entering and leaving the port, of Bushire during twelve months in 1878 HO Table showing average tonnage of vessels entering and leaving the Port of Lingah during twelve months-in 1878 HI Table showing average tonnage of -vessels entering and leaving the Port of Bahrein during twelve months in 1878 . . . • • • .112 Table showing average tonnage of vessels entering and leaving the Port of 'Oman in Persian Gulf during twelve months in 1878 .... 113 PART III. Administration Report of the Political Agency, Muskat, for the year 1878-79 . 114 Memorandum on Geography of 'Oman by Lieutenant-Colonel S. B. Miles . .117 PART IV. 120 Trade Table showing average tonnage of vessels entering and leaving the Port of Muskat during twelve months 1878-79 . . • ' . • • • Export. Estimate for the year 1878-79 . . . . • • • -122 Imports. Estimate for the year 1878-79 . .124 Contrasted Statement showing the number of vessels entering and leaving the Port of Muskat. Estimate for the year 1878-79 1-8 Contrasted Statement showing the value and description of goods exported from Muskat. Estimate for the year 1878-79 .1^9 Contrasted Statement showing the value and description of goods imported, into MuskatANNUAL EEPORT on the ADMINISTRATION of the PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY and MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR THE YEAR 1878-79. No. 251, dated Bushire, 18th July 1879. From— L ieut .-C ol . E. C. R oss , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To— A. C. L yall , Esq., Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Dept. I have the honour to transmit, for the information of His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor General in Council, the Annual Administra tion Report of this Residency and the Muskat Political Agency, ioi the year 1878-79. 2. The report is divided into the following- parts :— Pae/t I. —General Report. Appendix A.—Meteorological Observations. ^ - ^ t Appendix B.—Description of Bahrain Islands by Captain E. I j. Durand. . tvt t&gt; t n Appendix C.—Memorandum on Khuzistan by Mr. r. J. b. Robertson. Appendix D.—Routes to Ispahan. ^ Paet II. —Report on trade of the Persian Gulf. ... Appendix A.—Memorandum on agricultural system in Districts of Appendix B.— Tables of native shipping of ports on Persian and Arab coast. i t ht t Appendix C.—Tabular statistics of trade compiled by Mr. Lucas. Part III. —General report of Muskat Political Agency. Appendix A.—Geographical memorandum by Lieutenant-Colonel Miles. Part IV.—Trade report of the Muskat Political Agency. 3. I am indebted to Mr. R. Paul and Messrs. Malcolm for much of the general information in the trade report, and the statistical informa tion has been, with much care and industry, collected and compiled &gt;y Mr. Lucas.S ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 4, I should be glad of ten printed copies of the report^ and beg- also # T j respectfully to request that a few copies of Parts II and IV* may be supplied in separate form. PART I. GENERAL REPORT FOR 1878-79. The following headings comprise the territories to be noticed in connection with the political supervision and relations of this Resi dency :— 1. 'Oman, under the rule of His Highness Seyyid Toorkee. 2. The Arab Coast, under petty independent Chiefs. 3. Bahrain, under Shaikh ■'Eesa-bin'-Ali. 4. Nejd, El Ahsa (or El Hasa), andEl-Katr or Guttur, more or less subject to Turkey. 5. Southern Persia, Provinces of Arabistan, Ears and Persian Beloochistan. 6. Bassidore. 1.—'oman. 2. The Political Agent's Report is submitted as Part III. The po litical condition of this principality has been exceptionally satisfactory, and happily there was no occasion for any intervention of the British Government. 2.— A rab C oast. 3, There are no changes to record amongst the Trucial Chiefs on (1) Ras -el -Kheimali; (2) Umm-el- ^is coast who rule the marginally enu- Kawain ; (3)'Ejaian ; (4) Shargab ; merated ports. (5)Dabay; (6) Abu-Zhabi. 4. The Chie ^ Hameyd-bin-Abdullah, -r,, , ^ ^ ias continued to fulfil his engagements a s icima ' satisfactorily. A vessel belonging to one of Ms subjects having embarked Bedouins at El-Bidaa, was seized and used by them for piratical purposes and eventually released. The Chief was desired to keep the Nakhoda under surveillance, in order to his pi eduction in case of it appearing he acted in collusion with the pirates. 5. A vessel of Ras-el-Kheimah was plundered off El-Kateef by Bedoum pirates of property estimated at 330 dollars, and Shaikh Hameyd placed the matter in the hands of the Resident. 6. Ihe Chiefs, Ahmed-bin-Abullah, Rashid-bin-Hameyd and Zaeed- ^ Umm-el-Kawain, 'Ejmau and Abu- bin-khaleefah, have given entire satisfac- Zll!lljl ' _ _ tion in their relations with the Residency and shown their 'willingness to do justice in matters connected with Brit ish Indian subjects, and to abide by the Trucial Regulations.RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOE 1878-79. to bi 7. Shaikh Salih-biu Sultan^ having informed the Native Agent of his intention to despatch material of war (involving armed men and boats) by sea to the Batinah coast to coerce alleged disorderly dependents in that quarter, the Agent required him to desist pending reference to the Resi dent. Permission was not accorded, and the design was therefore aban doned. 8. Affairs generally at this port have gone on satisfactorily. « 9. Shaikh Hashar-bin-Maktoom is a person of, even for an Arab, singularly quick and impetuous temper, I)abay * which leads him occasionally to commit irregularities himself and to excuse them in his people. With consider able obstinacy, and in spite of friendly remonstrances made in the first instance by the Resident and Agent, as well as in opposition to the advice of his own relations, he neglected demands for redress in three cases, in which his responsibility was fully established by evidence. (1). The first of these was a claim for indemnity due by Shaikh Hashar for illegal and unjust detention at Dabay of a Persian vessel. (2). The second complaint established was an attack by Dabay boats on a Persian boat at Delma Island, and abduction of a sailor therefrom, with other violence. (3). Thirdly, Shaikh Hashar had used undue and unjust harshness towards Indian traders residing at Dabay, on false allegations. 10. It was eventually necessary to enforce compliance with our demands by presence of one of Her Majesty's vessels of war at Dabay. Lieutenant-Colonel Miles, at the Resident's request, accompanied Captain Wodehouse, the Senior Naval Officer, in Her Majesty's Ship Teazer, and a satisfactory settlement was obtained. A suitable fine was imposed, and the boat which had been employed in the Delma aggression was burnt off the port. 11. Shaikh Hashar thereon came to his senses and wrote a suitable and ample letter of apology, which was accepted, and the usual friendly relations resumed. The proceedings were approved by the Government of India. 12. During the summer of 1878 much fever prevailed on the pirate coast, apparently of a malignant type, and some hundreds of persons died. Scarcity and dearness has also caused much distress. 13. There has been a general cessation of warfare by land, which is said to be partially attributable to the impoverished condition of the various tribes. 14. In February Her Majesty's Ship Spartan visited this coast with the 2nd Assistant Resident, on which occasion the usual presents were distributed to the Trucial Chiefs. 15. The township of Dabay has of late years increased in population and importance, and it is now the most considerable port on the coast. Abu- Zhabi, on the other hand, has decreased. The combined number of boats of all sorts and sizes on this coast is estimated at about 3,000, giving employment to some 40,000 persons. A Table has been drawn up showing approximately the relative pros- Vide Appendix B, Part II. perity of the different ports.4 administration hepoet of tije persian gulf political 3.—B ahrain. 16. The Reports for the two years preceding that under review de scribed these islands as exempt from external dangers, though the in ternal administration and affairs were not wholly satisfactory. During the past year circumstances have combined to cause excitement and panics, and to necessitate some vigilance and attention on the part of the officers of the British Government, and measures to prevent the spread of disorder and to protect our interests. 17. The inhabitants of Bahrain have suffered both from marauders on the islands themselves and from the depredations of pirates operating from the opposite mainland. 18. The robberies which were alluded to in the last Annual Report were followed by other cases' and geireral insecurity and nervousness prevailed. The Chief, Shaikh, Eesa, was at last roused to take effectual repressive measures, and succeeded in arresting the ringleader of the robbers, Ali-bin-Jabir, and six of his followers. Four of the latter were punished by amputation of their hands, and this severity served to check the spread of disorder. Unfortunately Ali-bin-Jabir was allowed to escape from prison and gained the mainland, where he joined a band of Beni-Hajir pirates, and guided them to a point on the Bahrain island, where they landed and stole a number of sheep. Ali-bin-Jabir was subsequently seized at Ojair by the Turkish Deputy Governor and sent in fetters to El Hasa. The Chief of Bahrain requested the extradition of the offender, and this was assented to by the Wali of Busrah, but the order has not yet been acted on by the Governor of El Hasa. 19. The depredations of piratical bands of Beni-Hajir and other Bedouins on the coast opposite to Bahrain, besides the actual loss in flicted, injuriously affected Bahrain. In some ten instances vessels be longing to the islands were seized and plundered, and communication with El Kateef was for a time interrupted. In addition to the excite ment and apprehension caused by the proceedings of the pirates, the Chief of Bahrain entertained fears of an attack in force by the mainland Arabs under his cousin, Nasir-bin-Mubank, who, with Jasim-bin-Mo- liammed of El-Bidaa, assembled a force of Bedouins in November and attacked and destroyed the town of Zobarah. 20. On this occasion the Chief of Bahrain, whose former connection with Zobarah will be borne in mind, was anxious to be permitted to proceed to the relief of his quondam allies, but was prohibited from doing so. The Resident and Senior Naval Officer, however, visited Jasim- bin-Mohammed's camp near Zobarah aud ascertained that no attack on Bahrain was contemplated. 21. During the existence of alarm for the safety of the Bahrain islands, armed boats belonging to the Chief were, under direction of Her Majesty's Naval Officers, stationed to watch certain points within the limits of Bahrain waters. On two occasions those in command of the boats ex ceeded their orders, and took action beyond their assigned limits. Shaikh Eesa was required to show his disapproval by fining his officers for their irregularities. 22. Her Majesty's vessels of war have, during late disorders, kept vigilant watch on Bahrain and rendered important services in checking piracy. Through the exertions of Commander Pringle, Her Majesty sresidency and muskat political agency for 1878-79. and coiiec Ittfi ii) eir ^ ; fininf i Ship Vulture, and his officers and men, some stolen Bahrain vessels have been recovered and restored to the owners. 23. In February Captain E. L. Durand, 1st Assistant Resident, took up his residence temporarily, at Bahrain, with an escort of Native In fantry. It is thought that this measure had a satisfactory effect, and the Turkish Authorities having also taken action on the mainland in the cause of order, by the month of April confidence was so far restored at Bahrain as to permit the withdrawal of the Political Officer and escort before the setting-in of the intense heat of summer. It may here be noted that, during his residence at Bahrain, Captain Durand brought to notice the existence on Awal island of vast numbers of sepulchral mounds, evidently of great antiquity, some of which he opened experimentally. 24. In December it was reported that Mohammed and Abder- Rahman, sons of the late Wahabee Prince Sa'ood-ibn-Feysal, after un successfully operating against .the Turks about Kateef had landed at Bahrain. The inexpediency of countenancing persons so lately concerned in disturbing the territories of a neighbouring and friendly power was suggested to Shaikh 7 Eesa, who was only too glad to part from his un welcome visitors as soon as they could be induced to take their departure. 25. When Kateef was beleaguered, some inhabitants of that district fled for safety to Bahrain. As they had formerly been subjects of Bahrain, the Chief detained their boats and exacted a money-payment, but was induced to release the boats and remit the fine. 26. Pearl-diving was conducted under favourable circumstances dur ing the summer of 1878. A table showing approximately the number of vessels and boats sailing from Bahrain will be found in the Appendix. (Appendix B, No. 2, to Part II.) 27. An interesting general description of these islands, written by Captain E. L. Durand, is attached to this Report as Appendix B to Part I. 4.—Nejd, El Hasa, El Katr. A 28. A few remarks in explanation of the past and present acceptation of the names selected for this heading may be conducive to accuracy in treating of the current history of these tracts, and are, under this im pression, here inserted. 29. Nejd in Arabic signifies a 'high' or ' table-land,' and form erly, according to Arabian geographers (El Edrisi, Abu-l-Feda and others), in its geographical sense it comprised the whole Central Arabian region lying between Yemen on the south to the Persian Gulf, and to the north and west, from the neighbourhood of El Medinah to the northern shores of the Persian Gulf, that is to say the tract between the Hejaz and 'Irak * The term u Nejd ' is said to be in contradistinction to ' Tehamah,' the more low-lying lands of Arabia. It is easy to understand how the limits of so vague a geographical term should vary according to different authors :— 30. In its geographical sense Nejd comprises the following districts :— Wed. —Jebel-Shammar (Hayel) and 'El-kasim (capital 'Oneyzah). Central. —Sadeyr, El-Washam, El-'Aredh (towns Riadh and EU Dereyyah), El-Khorj and El-Harik (or Yemamah). East. —El-Hasa or El-Ahsa. * This is Abu'l-Feda's definition.6 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL South. —Wadi-Sabey, Wadi-Sbahran, Wadi-el-Dowasir. 31. At the zenitb of tbe Wabbabfs power tbe political corresponded in extent with tbe geograpbical Nejd, but it need not be said that at present the representative of the Amirs may claim at most to be the ruler of the town Rmdh. • 32. The Turkish Government having occupied El-Hasa and the seaports of El-Katif and 'Ojair, ■'Abdallah-ibu-Feysal is completely cut off from the Persian Gulf, and the sect of Wabhabis, with the temporal rule, is fast on the wane; the tales of their fierce doings have become stereotyped history of the past. 33. The reported negotiations between 'Abdallah and the Turkish Authorities mentioned in the last Annual Report came to nothing. His nephews, however, the sons of Sa'ood-bin- Feysal, endeavoured to raise a rebellion against the Turks, or were induced to lend their names to it, and Katif was closely invested by BedoUin bands, by land and sea, and owed its relief, primarily, to the appearance of Her Majesty's Ship Vulture cruising against pirates. Later large re-inforcements were sent from Baghdad and Busrah, and the insurrection was quelled. 34. Sa'eed Pasha has been appointed to the vacant post of ' Mutaser- rif ' or Governor of El-Hasa, which now forms a province of the Valayet of Busrah. He is reported an officer of some intelligence and activity, but, in common with so many high officials of his nationality, has been the subject of insinuations somewhat depreciatory of his earlier career and the services which gained him patronage. 35. The Mutaserrif of El-Hasa has control of the entire sphere of Turkish jurisdiction in this quarter, the Deputy Governors of Katif and Ojair being subordinate to him. His residence and seat of Government is usually at El-Hasa some 50 miles inland. The word ' Hasa ' means water found by digging through sand, and the plural form is Ahsa. Both forms are used in designating the district, El-Ahsa being most used locally. 36. The seaports El-Katif and ^Ojair or 'Okair, forming, as they do, the natural outlets, are under the existing regime by force of circum stances included in the province of El-Hasa. But it may be interesting to note that, according to Arabian writers, the name Bahrain, now re stricted only to the islands so called, once extended to a tract of mainland including El-Katif and El-Katr.* 37. The disturbances which occurred during the summer in the vicinity of El-Katif were accompanied and followed by a renewal of piracy on a serious scale all along the coast from Katif to El-Bidaa. The principal offenders were, as usual, the irrepressible Beni-Hajir Bedonuis. These freebooters, who, as stated in the previous report, had been dis turbed from their former place of resort, ^Odeyd, transferred their opera tions to the neighbourhood of Kateef in Turkish territory and operated with much boldness and success from Dhahran, Dareyn, &amp;c. Tbe most daring of their exploits was conducted by their best-known leader Kaeed-bin-Mohammed, who crossed the Gulf in a captured vessel from * The following passage is from Beladzori; — ' It is said the apostle of God removed 'Ola from office and placed Abban-bin-said- bin-Assi hin-Omeyah over El-Bahrain. Others say 'Ola was over that part of Bahrain which is El-Katif, and Abbun over that in which is El-Katr; but the first accouut is more probable.'wasit, 2li(| residency and muskat political agency fotl 1878-79. 7 El-Bidaa and landed for booty on the island of El-Kais. On the whole, v there were, during the year, more than twenty instances of seizure and plunder of boats, many of which belonged to Bahrain. Probably the loss of property amounted to two or three thousand pounds. As the culprits acted from Turkish territory and retired there with their plunder, representations were made to the Turkish Authorities in each instance, and they were eventually moved to take some preventive and punitive measures. The latter have been, however, ill-directed; and whilst a handful of unarmed fishermen at El-Hasein suffered vicariously for the misdeeds of Zaeed and his gang, the latter have continued to enjoy with impunity the fruits of their exploits, and none of the plundered property has been recovered. Her Majesty^s Ship Vulture, under Captain Eliot- Pringle, R.N., rendered excellent service by the capture of a fleet of boats of the Omeyer tribe and the recovery of stolen Bahrain vessels under very difficult circumstances. 38. In the month of August a piratical attack on passing vessels was made under the sanction of the Shaikh of the town of Zobarah on the Katr promontory, and the Governor of Busrah was asked to punish the offenders. But before His Excellency took any steps, Jasim-bin Mohammed-bin-Thani of El-Bidaa, with Nasir-bin-Mubarik, the Bahrain refugee, appeared at Zobarah with a force, and razed it to the ground. The inhabitants took refuge in the adjacent fort of Moreyr, where they were for some time closely besieged and eventually had to accept hard terms. The destruction of the town rendered any further measures for punishment of the inhabitants unnecessary. 39. During the year the old Shaikh of El-Bidaa, Mohammed-bin- Thani, who had always been friendly to the British, died. His son Jasim had for many years been de facto Shaikh of El-Bidaa under Turkish patronage. Vide Appendix C to Part I. 5.—Southern Persia. Provinces of 'Arabistdn, Fdrs and Persian Beloochistdn. 40. 'Arabistdn. —An account of the topography, government and population of this province, which has by Europeans been often called Persian-Arabia, written by Mr. P. J. C. Robertson, Assistant Political Agent at Busrah, is given in the Appen dix to this part, and the following par ticulars of recent occurrences there are chiefly on the same authority. 41. FeldJiiyah. —In the month of May 1878, the hereditary Chief of the Eelahiyah Section of the Ka^ab (Cha'ab) Arabs, Shaikh Lufti- bin-Imbadir was murdered by his cousin Ja'afer-bin-Mohammed, and Shaikh Ramah, another cousin^ was nominated Chief of Felahiyah, the revenue and pishkash of the district being fixed at 10,00U tomans. The districts Deh-ul-Moolla, Jerrahy, Hindiyan and Bunder Mashoor, previously belonging to Felahiyah, were now detached from it, and Amir Abdullah of Deh Moolla was appointed Chief of the new group, on agreeing to pay 12,000 tomans, revenue and pishkash, in addition to 9,000 tomans already due by him for Deh Moolla. As the year proved a bad one from want of rain. Amir Abdullah only succeeded in paying8 administration report of the persian gulf political 9,000 tomans and will probably have either to fight for the balance or seek safety in flight. 42. At Felahiyah Shaikh Rahmah^s authority has been feeble and* he has only been able to raise 4,000 tomans from the tribes. On arrival of the Prince Governor at Shushter the Shaikh sent word that he was unable without assistance to obtain the full revenues, whereupon the Prince sent his Wazeer, Assadoolah Khan, with a battalion of infantry to his aid. The Shaikhs of the principal tribes, however, seemed dis posed to hold out and declined to visit the Wazeer. 43. Hawaizah. —Some disturbances occurred between the partizans of Moolla Mattub, the ruling Chief, and those of his rival Moolla Nasrullah, but the former prevailed. The amount of revenue and pish- kash is to be raised from 21,000 to 30,000 tomans. 44. Mohammerah. —This port has been brought into telegraphic communication with the capital. 45. In February 1879 the old Shaikh and Governor Haji Jabir Khan Noosrut-ul-Moolk proceeded to Bombay for medical advice. His eldest son. Shaikh Mohammed Khan, conveyed to the Prince Governor at Shushter the revenue and pishkash due from Mohammerah, hoping to avert a personal visit on the part of His Royal Highness. Shaikh Mizal Khan, Haji Jabir^s second son, was meanwhile left in charge of Moham merah. Shaikh Mohammed Khan was favourably received, and the Prince Governor consented to a proposal that Haji Jabir Khan and the Wazeer Assadoolah Khan should jointly farm the districts of Felahiyah and Ramis during the coming year. The Prince informed Shaikh Mohammed that a report was current at Tehran that Haji Jabir Khan had proceeded to Bombay in pursuance with an intrigue with the British Government, and that it was advisable he should return without delay. Subsequently Haji Jabir Khan returned to Mohammerah, and the Prince's visit took place with the usual financial result. 46. The Bakhtidri. —In the spring of 1878 the Abdul Khan Section' of the Beni-Lcim, who wander between Turkish and Persian territory and plunder in both on occasions, made a raid on the environs of Shushter and carried off mules, sheep, &amp;c. The Persian Prince Governor ordered the Bakhtyari Chief, Hussein Kooli Khan, to retaliate, and he surprised the Abdul Khan in Persian territory and nearly annihilated them. The Bakhtyan Chief, however, omitted to restore the property of the Shushter people which he had recovered, and the Persian Government fined him in consequence 30,000 tomans. A breach has occurred between Hussein Kooli Khan (El Khanee) and his brother Imam Kooli Khan (El Begee), which may break their strength to some extent. 47. His Royal Highness Prince Hamza Mirza, the Hishmat-ed- Dowlah, remains in charge of the administration of 'Arabistan. 48. Fdrs, Shiraz. —His Royal Highness Prince Firhad Mirza, the Mo'temid-ed-Dowlah, has continued to govern Fars, and under his rule security has been generally maintained on the routes. The Governor of Behbahdn, Prince ; Owais Mirza Ihtisham-ed-Dowlah, made, as usual, a tour through the Bushire and neighbouring districts. 49. Some local disturbances occurred at Bunder Reesr owing to change of headmen. 50. In the summer of 1878 Captain E. L. Durand proceeded on aj propsriT eesidency and muskat political agency for 1878-79. 9 tour through a portion o£ Ears and visited His Royal Highness the Mo^temid-ed-Dowlah at Shiraz. Captain Durand explored the districts north-west of Shiraz as far as the Dina mountains^ and has embodied the results of his observations and surveys in a report and map which have been separately submitted to Government. 51. Bushire. —Haji Mohammed Baker Khan has continued to be Governor of Bushire. During the year certain instances of unjust treatment of British subjects formed subject of complaint, and as re dress could not be obtained locally, representations were made to Her Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at the Persian Court, and eventually to Her Majesty's Government. The necessary support being accorded, the Persian Government issued orders to the provincial and local autho rities to afford the satisfaction at first denied, and then matters were arranged. The local authorities have since evinced a conciliatory and friendly disposition, and cordial relations exist. 52. Mirza Ali Akbar Khan, a gentleman who has enjoyed the ad vantages of early education in Europe, was in the autumn appointed Persian Foreign Office Agent at Bushire. The results of this excellent selection have been markedly beneficial. 53. The customs of Bushire are farmed by the Nasir-ul-Mulk of Shiraz, who employs an Agent named Haji Ibrahim. 54. Large exports of wheat and barley took place during the year both during and on the raising of the prohibition, which has been re- imposed and is now more strictly enforced. 55. Tangistan and Bashfi. —In Tangistan Haider Khan is Chief solely, his cousin Ali Khan having been expelled. Since the death of Haider Khan Dashti his brother Mohammed Khan is Governor of that district, which has remained undisturbed. 56. In the Bushire and adjacent districts of the plains the harvests are small from want of rain, and scarcity and dearness prevail. 57. Gaobandee -Kongoon District. —In this district are comprised the sea-ports of Kongoon, Nakheeloo, Assaloo, Tahiree, &amp;c., and the islands of Shaikh Sho'aib and Hinderabee and some thirty villages inland. Shaikh Mazkoor-bin-Jabbarah, as stated in last year's report, was replaced in this Government, but is reported to be again in conflict with the authorities. . „ _ 58. In May 1878 Shaikh Mazkoor, in pursuance with a feud against Abdullah-bin-Mohammed, Chief of Beni-Hamad of Kalat, and joined by Shaikh Mohammed Hassan, Chief of Charek and Hamad-bin-Ismail, Chief of the Abeydil of Cheeroo, attacked and plundered the village of Marbakh, killing seventeen men. The Kowwam-ul-Mulk, Governor of Lar, despatched a force of 200 Sirbaz and 700 irregulars under Aga Fath-Ali-Khan of Gerras with one gun against Shaikh Mazkoor in July, but the force was surprised and defeated by Shaikh Mazkoor and his followers. . , • 59. In February the Kowwam -ul-Mulk arrived in person with troops at Sheebkoh. , , 60. Cheeroo-Kaldt, ChdveJc and Moghoo. —At Charek Shaikh Moham med-bin-Hassan has been dispossessed in favour of Abdullah-bin- Musabbah and fled to the island of Kaiss. These districts are all somewhat unsettled, the control of the Government being uncertain and spasmodic.10 administration jiepoiit of the persian gulp political 61. Ling ah. —In the month of November the short and uneasy career of the young Shaikh of Lingah^ AH-bin-Khaleefa was brought to an end by his murder at the hands of one Shaikh Yusuf. When the former Shaikh Khaleefa died, he appointed Shaikh Yusuf guardian and adviser of his son Ali, but the latter some time afterwards dismissed Shaikh Yusuf, who however, having tasted power, was not likely to sit down patiently in exclusion. The young Shaikh's youth and inexperience and want of powerful and trustworthy supporters and advisers, gave his enemy the advantage and put opportunity in his way. Shaikh Ali, appa- rently unsuspicious of danger, had gone to sleep in a house in Mehrakan a few miles from Lingah, when Shaikh Yusuf's followers attacked him during the night and killed the Shaikh and several of his attendants. 62. It does not appear that the Persian authorities have objected to the proceedings of Shaikh Yusuf, who is still associated in the adminis tration of Lingah. Shaikh Yusuf was directed to appear' at Shiraz but has not done so hitherto. 63. No disturbances occurred at Lingah, but the neighbourhood is unsettled. ^ 64. Bunder Abbass. —The titular Governor of Bunder Abbass is the Nasir-ul-Mulk, who resides in Shiraz and is also nominal Governor of Lingah and farmer of the Bushire Customs. This official appointed Haider Kooli Khan, Deputy Governor of Bunder Abbass, but the latter, suffering from the climate, has returned to Shiraz. 65. Nasir-bin-Rashid, for many years Farmer of Customs, died during the year, and his son Mohammed Hussein is now customs master. 66. As concerns British commercial interests the local authorities of Bunder Abbass have given satisfaction during the year. 67. 1 ersian-Beloochistun Coast. —This region appears to have been on the whole quiet during the year and the telegraph line unmolested, but owing to absence of the Political Assistant no summary of events has been received. 68. A detachment of the 21st Bombay Native Light Infantry, under a Subadar, has been stationed at Jask, and accommodation erectedc 6.—bassidore. 69. A Company of the Bombay 21st Native Light Infantry, which ™ ^ een stationed at Bassidore, was withdrawn on account of the suffering of the men from the unhealthiness of the place and placed at ask instead. The Resident visited the station in March in Her Majesty's Ship leazer, and found everything satisfactory. ESTABLISHMENTS. 70. Political Sj' Consular.—YLer Majesty's Commission has been con- erred on the Resident appointing him Consul-General for the Province or .bars and the Coasts and Islands of the Persian Gulf within the JJomimons of Persia. lo tit r * Edwards was on sick leave from July to January. . Naval. Her Majesty's Ships Teazer, Arab, Vulture and Spartan^ers^l 1 residency and muskat political agency for 1878-79. 11 have served on the Gulf Station during 1 the year, and in March His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief visited Muskat and Lingah in Her Majesty's Ship JEuryalus. The Resident proceeded to the latter port to meet Admiral Corbett, as the Flag Ship could not conveniently proceed further north. 73. Postal. —Investigations have been continued regarding mis carriage of certain official documents. The Persian inland post works regularly and efficiently. 74. Observatory. —Remarks on the weather and tables for the year will be found in the Appendix. (Appendix A to Part I.) I aittl SLAVE TRADE. 75. No fresh cases have come to light, and former pending cases have been disposed of. The orders of the Government on the subject have been, according to rule, widely made known. (Sd.) E. C. ROSS, Lieutenant-Colonel, Resident, Persian Gulf. Idtkresidency and muskat political agency eoll 1878-79. 15 APPENDIX B to PAKT I. Description of the Bahrain Islands hy C aptain E. L. D urand, First Assistant Resident, Persian Gulf. Interior of the islands. —The interior of tlie islands of Bahrain, and of the large one in particular, presents some very marked features. Beginning at the centre, and looking outwards taking one s stand on the Jebel Dukhan or ' Hill of Smoke,' the whole lies below m full view. Firstly the hill itself, which seems to be of limestone and stands up some 400 feet above the sea level, looks as if it were the old crater of a volcano (if this could be), with encircling ring of cliffs facing inwards some three or four miles off. Really, however, I fancy that it would be more correct to say that a space of land all round the Jebel and contained in the circle of cliffs has sunk, for the hill cliffs are of limestone and present no appearance of course of volcanic action having taken place. From the outer crest of this ring of cliffs the land slopes moie oi ess gradually down to the sea on all sides. • &lt; j i j . i „ The Chart* of Bahrain Harbour, though scarcely intended to be an , accurate land survey, shows the he ot the * By c 0 ™ mander C r • irm ground more truly than does the small Lieut. Wish, resurveyed in 1872-74! &amp; ^ ir? i r -|\/r„ TVinrnsmi by Messrs. Thompson and Cuthbert map supplied to yourse by • j of H. M. S. Schooner Constance. where an exaggerated importance, not found in the original chart, is given to the Jebel Dukhan and the encndmg cliffs^ ^ ^ ^ ^ is i an d S eems very bare, but almost due west of the Jebel groups of palm begin to line the coast and stretch from thence all round the northern shore to the north-east. These must, of eourse, all be abundantly supplied with water, and Bahrain indeed is wonderfully gifted in this respect. , . jfater,—I have already noticed the springs that burst out fiesh in tlie Forster 0 mentions that the Arabs consider these, as well as others on the mainland, to have their source in an underground river from the Euphrates. As he puts it, this is most clearly the 1 lum p quod Euphratem emergere putant' mentioned in this quarter b y ' n f- at is not an uncommon thing in Persia to see wells sunk apparently in hopeless ground, and to find that they tap a small stream running Und T r he r P^cipal springs arc the GassSri, on the road from Manameh to the Bellad -i-Kadim. The Umm Shaoom, a mile to the eastwaid Manameh the Abu Zeidan in the Billad-i-Kadim and the Avan, which hs^sTp es many miles of date-groves through a canal of ancient last supplies 11 workmanship (whose stone-bound banks f I had some pearl divers with me, now [ n som e places falling m), With a ^h:ToutrAh:rtl.en lid lik U e perfect river Of fast-running water, so^e pigmies about a foot high. xo feet broad by 2 m depth, ine spring itself is some 30 to 35 feet deep, and rises so strongly that a diver is teed upwaids on Hearing the bottom. I do not mean that you eaanot reach it t but merely that the force of the water is felt against you The water where it rises in this deep spring, whose basm artificially16 administration report OF the persian gulp POLITIC \r banked is some 22 yards across by 40 long, is as clear as crystal o slightly green tint and very beautiful. It holds a shoal or two of large fish and many water-tortoises. It is , „ ,, .. not .Perfectly sweet, and applies to L a ' ly nn allthe d ™ k ^ water cliffs. connoisseurs being brought on camels . . ; from the wells of the Umm Koefih and Hanaim, said to be 20 fathoms deep, in the hills of Rifa-a* The water is conducted from these various wells by ordinary unbanked channels, the larger of which have come to look like natural streams Where it is necessary to raise it, this is done from wells by the ordinary skin-bucket let down oyer a pulley, and walked up to the cistern level by cattle pulling down an incline from channels, generally by leverage of a date-trunk lightly swung by ropes to a frame and balanced at one end by a basket of earth, into which it is inserted, so that little exertion is required to lift up the water. The Jebel Dukhan, as I said above, seems to be of a sort of lime stone. I found some fossil shells upon it. The surrounding cliffs were where I saw tiiem, I think, of sandstone j but they are generally limestone and this stone was enormously quarried from here, I take it to build the dead houses under the tumuli. On nearing the coast, white dusty ground, the cerecloth of dead t I append a sketch of one group races and habitations, intrudes every- hLmd Se ' the largesfc on tlie wbere as if to enforce attention, and . ' , .. . mighty mounds,t bare of vegetation, tower above the palm groves. The map gives a very slight idea of this most noticeable feature. Mass upon mass, mound upon mound, these mounds stretch on in endless chains all round the slope that falls from the cliffs to the sea, clino-inc more particularly perhaps to the higher ground, but found in separate clusters near the coast itself. Ihe parent group is perhaps that at Ali,J a modem village, but J See map. other large ones are to be found at many Tz ,. ' places, noticeably those in the Bilad-i- Kadim, the red ones on the left of the high road to Rifa-a, and the chain ot five or six large ones facing the northern sea near the village of Sirabe, which are only some out of very many groups, all more or less worthy of notice. 1 shall have to recur again to these monuments later on. Salt in considerable quantity is said to be obtainable at the southern § P ^ n .Y-—Houses built of ' fossil end of the island, (as also, I am told, on s;; ^ ^ d „ j r n ArT land - ) s on Bahrain, which is strongly im- account Ot the houses built of salt§ ID pregnated with salt). 0 these parts and 'mended with-salt water douches.^ On this subject an Arab from the mainland assured me that in one place, where they now quarry salt, the remains of old buildings and pillars are often seen. 2'rees and Plants.— Poremost amongst the trees is, of course, the date, ana some ot the date-gardens are extremely fine. Many however are ^? ir !^. a11 f^ n j ruin; the result of bad government on the part of the ai , and indeed in some places that were once flourishing gardens not a bearing tree remains.RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 17 The almond, with its broad and coloured leaves, grows well and is seen to great effect amongst the palms. The citron grows well in a garden now under Shaikh Ahmed. I saw many acres of these trees all bending with such masses of golden fruit that they seemed scarcely able to bear the weight. These were interspersed amongst palms, peach and almond trees, and Some 20 inches or more in circum- themselves were covered with scented ference. blossom as well as fruit. The tamarind flourishes, having probably been imported from India. Date Palm. Peach. , The castor oil plant, that hardy invader of every eastern soil, flourishes here as elsewhere. Lucern grass is very largely cultivated, and (with dates) is about the only food-supply grown or used for the animals of this island. Were the least attention given to this branch of agriculture, almost every known vegetable could be produced here, as the climate is good for at least six months out of the twelve, and water is abundant. Animals. —The list of animals is not a large one; camels, horses, cows and donkeys (with the inevitable eastern dog) are to be found in different parts of the island. All these feed principally upon lucern, supplemented with dates. The camels are mostly from Arabia, though they are now bred here in the marshes. A few good ones for riding purposes are owned by the Shaikhs. These feed even when going at a sharp trot, giving the unaccustomed rider an odd feeling of helplessness, as the long neck disappears in front and the head becomes mixed up with the animals^ legs. This feeling is soon replaced by one of implicit contidence when you get accustomed to the acrobatic performance and find that no harm comes of it. The horses, all rejoicing in some high sounding tribal or family name, appear to me, with the exception of some old brood mares, to have been crossed with an inferior breed. They stand unused and unclothed and uncared for, summer and winter, in the same place, and eat their dates and lucern contentedly. Breeding is carried on from the most unsound and helpless cripples, some of whom can barely stand from disease; and as the colts get little or no exercise, the result of the breeding arrangements cannot be very satisfactory. The Shaikhs are, of course, the only owners, and consider their misshapen cripples to be of enormous value. It is not worth while to undeceive them, as no one in his senses would think of buying one. The cows were famed and are still good, but the race is dying out as no poor man or cultivator can keep them. The white donkeys were famed but are few and far between now, except those owned by the Shaikhs and a few big men. They are not so fine as those I have seen in Persia, and a much higher price is asked for them. The ordinary little dwarf, grey donkey, who picks up a subsistence as best he can round the villages, is plentiful and Vine. Fig. Pomegranate. Almond. Bair. Tamarind. Citron. Apricot. Mulberry. I give a general list in the margin, but perhaps not quite a full one. c18 administration report of the persian gulf political used, generally raw with sores, to carry date-branches, wood, &amp;c. to market in the town. Wild animals. —The wild animals are few. The gazelle, the hare and the mongoose are all that I know of. The Arab gazelle, in its perfect and slender beauty of proportion differs as much from the Persian or Mesopotamian, as a thorough bred does from a cart horse. The hares are about the size of a three-quarter grown English rabbit • very small and blood-looking with prominent eyes. This casty look is noticeable in every Arabian animal, man included. The Arab horse is well-known, but the Arab greyhound, of which a really good specimen is seldom obtainable, is a most beautiful animal, so light and slender as to seem useless for work, but when going, appearing rather to fly than gallop. These hares are easily tamed. I had two, rescued from a hawk and a grey-hound respectively, which after four days became so tame that they played about the room, hopping up occasionally to see what I was doing, and only retiring behind a box on the arrival of a stranger. The mongoose runs about in broad day everywhere. There are several sorts of fish in the fresh water. One with peculiar marking drew my attention. I have never seen him noticed. The dorsal fin is the centre of three circular, or oval bands of dark colour which show very plainly against the silver sides of the fish, and present an odd effect when he swims. The largest I saw was only probably a few ounces in weight. It would almost seem as if he had caught the colour of his coat from swimming constantly in these shallow crystal waters, shaded by the long thin spikes of the date palm, but perhaps this is too Dar winian, as, although fish do constantly take, and even change, their colour from the sort of water they live in, they would scarcely take their marking in this manner.RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 19 APPENDIX C TO PART I. Memorandum on the Topography, 8fc. } of Khuzistdn or Persian Arabia, hy P. J. C. R obertsoN j Esq., Assistant Political Agent, Busrah. Topographical. —The Persian Province of Arabistdn, as at present constituted, includes the mountainous country occupied by the Lur tribes, the Feyli-Wand, Bakhtiari, &amp;c., as well as Khuzistdn or Persian Arabia, properly so called, whose boundaries are, roughly, the Bakhtiari Hills, the river Kerkhah, a line drawn from Hawaezah to Mahamrah, the Shat-ul-'Arab from Mahamrah to the sea, the Persian Gulf, and the river Hindian. The country between these boundaries, excepting the towns of Shushter and Dizpul and the village of Ramis, whose populations are Iirr „ hybrid, is inhabited by Arabs, either i. e., a r or e u. settled in villages or nomadic.* Its area is about 10,000 square miles, and its present population is estimated at 167,000 souls. Its surface is quite flat with the exception of^ one narrow, rocky range of hills, varying from 50 to 250 feet in height, which runs from north-west to south-east across the middle of it, and a series of undulations which rise gradually towards the Bakhtiari Hills. The river Karun issues from the hills, a navigable stream at Shushter, and, bisecting Persian Arabia, runs by one mouth into the Persian Gulf, and by another into the Shat-ul-'Arab at Mahamrah. A description of this river will be found in the account of a trip which I made to Shuster and Dizpul in 1876. A smaller stream, the Jerrahy, enters the plains at Ramis, and loses itself in the marshes around Felahiyah. There is therefore no lack of water, were it utilised; but the dams on the Karun and Jerrahy, which diverted their waters by canals in all direc tions over the country, have been swept away, and hardly a trace of any of them, except that at Ahwaz, remains, while the canals themselves have been filled up by drifting sand. The soil is generally exceedingly fertile, and when cultivated and sufficiently watered yields extraordinary crops. The last dam on the Karun was one constructed of turf by the Kab Arabs at Mand, some eight miles above where Mahamrah now stands. It turned the Karun bodily towards the Kaban, then the capital of the Kab nation, and the country through which it passed, irrigated by innumerable small canals, whose remains are still to be seen, produced abundance of sugar, cotton, indigo, sessame, dates, wheat, rice, &amp;c., which were largely exported to India, Turkey and Persia. When the Kab Arabs underwent the usual process of internal dissension, intrigue with Turkey and Persia and decay towards the end of last century, the dam was allowed to fall to ruin, and, the Kamn taking its present course, the Kaban became the parched desert it now is, and had to be abandoned altogether. The Kab moved their seat of government to Dorak or Felahiyah, as it is now called on the Jerrahy, but their decline in enterprise, as in numbers and power, has been steady since then. Such crops as are now raised in Persian Arabia depend for water, with few exceptions, on rain or the accidental overflowing of the river. There is still one partially efficient dam on the20 ADMINISTRATION EEPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL Kerkhab at Nahr Hashem, and subterranean canals, flowing from the Diz, irrigate a small portion of the country between that river and the Shatart, as the western branch of the Karun from Shushter to Banawdah is called. Wheat and barley are grown around the towns and villages, and here and there on the banks of the rivers, and rice is cultivated iu the marshy districts of Hawaezah and Felahiyah. The date-palm is now almost confined to the banks of the Shat-ul-'Arab and the Karun for the last six miles of its course. Around Mahamrah and Kasbah, near the mouth of the Shat-ul-^Arab, the groves are kept in good order, but elsewhere the trees are dying of age and neglect. They are the property of the Persian Government, and the Arabs who inhabit them have little interest in their welfare. The cultivator and his Shaikh are aware that any appearance of prosperity would be followed by unduly increased taxation, and they prefer to let decay take its course. Government. —The appointment of Governor of Arabistdn is usually held by a member of the Persian Royal family. The present bolder of the office is Prince Hamza Meerza, better known by his title of Hishmet-ud-Dowleh. The Princess nominal residence is Khorama- bad in the Luristan, but he is generally engaged for the greater part of the year in collecting the revenue of Persian Arabia, with the aid of two or three Fauj-es of Persian infantry and a contingent of Lur horse. The collection of revenue is the only function of Government which the Prince Governor performs, all other matters being left to the discre tion of Chiefs or Governors of the six districts, into which Persian Arabia is divided. The revenue is of two kinds : ' diwan, ' which goes to Tehran; and ' pishkash,' which the Prince Governor takes for himself. The six districts, their present Chiefs, estimated population and the revenue of both kinds which they pay this year are as follows:— D isteict. Mohamrah . Fel&amp;hiyah . Bamis. Shushter , Dispul, with '1 Katheer Arabs ) Hawaezah Present Chiefs or Governors. Haji Juber Khan, Nasrat-ul-Mulk. Vacant Shaikh Jabarah Meerza Abdul Wahab Khan. Hadayatallah Khan . Mola Matlab Estimated Population. 45,000 30,000 7,000 22,000 30,000 33,000 167,000 R evenue. Tomans. Tomans. Diwan Pishkash Diwau Pishkash Diwan Pishkash Diwan Pishkas Diwan Pishkash Diwan Pishkash 23,000 10,000 16,000 6,000 9,000 18,000 4,000 33,000 22,000 9,000 22,000 24,000 ^ OQ ooo 6,000 ) dU,UUU 14,000 7.000 21,000 Tomans . 137,000RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 21 0 ) iowhj f ' riv, oefHil IMS Bima 10, £1! 6,1 19,MO ^ 18,000 1 gi 24,000 1 g 6,W) HOW 11| pi Mohamrah. The districts of Hawaezah and Felahiyah are remnants o£ independ ent Arab principalities which were pow- Hawaezah aud Felahiyah. er f u | in the;r day) an d their Chiefs or Governors are still always members of the old ruling families, the Mualy of Hawaezah and the Abu Nasir of Felahiyah. It is necessary in practice that the Governors of these two districts should be acceptable to both Prince and people, for the Shaikhs of tribes will not pay tribute to a Chief who has been placed over them in opposition of their wishes. It sometimes happens, on the other hand, as at Felahiyah just now, that the people insist on having as Governor a Chief to whom the Prince or the Persian Government objects. The Arabs then become what is termed ' ^asi,' or rebellious, decline to pay tribute, and, if pressed, retire to the marshes. A com promise ensues, and the Prince generally consents to nominate the popular candidate in consideration of an increased pishkash. The marshes of Hawaezah and Felahiyah afford handy refuge to the dis contented, and the ease with which the Arabs can retire to them is a wholesome check on Persian rapacity. The town of Mohamrah was founded by Shaikh Mardaw of the Muhaesen, one of the Kab tribes, father of Haji Jaber Khan, the present Gov ernor. The district was then Turkish territory, and remained so until forty years ago, when, the Pashalics of Baghdad and Busrah having been enfeebled by the great plague, the Persians quietly took posses sion of it. Haji Jaber Khan is a man of great natural ability, and although now very old and physically weak, he is still the most influen tial personage in Khuzistan. The present village of Ramis stands on the side of Ram-Honmuz, of which few traces remain. The district Ilamis ' is exceedingly fertile and well-watered by the Jerrahy, and numerous springs which dot the plain; but being generally farmed by a son of Haji Jaber Khan or Houssein Kuly Khan, of the Bakhtiari, whose object is to extort as much as possible during his tenure of office, the condition of its inhabitants is particularly wretched. There are naphtha springs in this district, which, were boring instruments applied to them, would probably be valuable. Of Shushter and Dispul the latter is now the more important and , ,, , populous place. After the destruction Shus ter an ispu. 0 f Awaz by Tfmurluk, towards the end of the fourteenth century, Shushter, already an ancient city, became the centre of commerce in Khuzistan, and continued to be so until the great plague of 1831-32. The plague, which dealt lightly with Dispul, left few living people in Shuster. The Lurs and Persians, whom its magnificent and warlike Khans had hitherto kept at a respectful distance, fastened on the weakened, but still wealthy city, and plundered it unmercifully. The surrounding country became infested by Lur and Arab robbers, and the Persian trade, which had been prosecuted by the Karun, Shushter and Ispahan took other and safer routes. One of these was that by Amarah on the Tigris, Dispul and Khoramabad, and Dispul thus benefited by the ruin of Shushter.i n ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL JI 1 ■■ eiil' 11 [f r IL ^ p |S ■■■ It is now a thriving and busy place, and a contrast to the rest of the province. I have heard the present population of Shushter variously estimated at from 6,000 to 20,000 souls. From personal observa tion I should think that the former number is more nearly correct for, although the town is large and the houses numerous, many of them are in ruins and uninhabited. Dispul has from 15^000 to 20,000 inhabitants. The Prince Governor makes it his head-quarters when in the low country, and leaves a lieutenant there when he retires to Khoramabad. Every third or fourth man one meets in the streets of Shushter and Dispul is a Seyyid, and their authority and insolence are great. Telegraph communication between Tehran and Shuster via Dispul has just been completed, but I understand that the line is badlv made and unlikely to last. 7 Arabs and Persians.—'The Arabs of Khuzistan strike one as being exceptionally intelligent, which they probably owe to contact with the subtle and witty Persians. They have adopted various Persian ways and customs, such as bowing instead of raising the hand to the forehead, which is the ordinary Arab salutation. Their manners on ceremonious occasions are altogether rather Persian than Arab, and their dress, with the excep tion of the head-dress, is often Persian. Persian women, being excellent cooks, are highly esteemed by them as wives. But although the upper classes mix familiarly and the Arab learns from the Persian, their mutual dislike and contempt are inwardly strong, the Persian looking on the Arab as a dull fellow only fit to be mulcted and cozened, and the Arab regarding the Persian as a cowardly rogue who has got the better of him by stratagem and intrigue. The Arabs firmly believe that if they could but combine, the expulsion of the Persians would be an easy- matter, but they know that for them combination is impossible for no man can be sure of the members of his own family, far less of the Chiefs of other districts and tribes. Between the lower classes of Arabs and Persians the hostile feeling is undisguised. Tribes.—The following list of the tribes of Persia a Arabia contains all those which are still of importance and some which are no longer of any. Oi the 72 tribes which composed the Kab nation some have emigrated to Turkish territory; others have died out, and of others mere fragments remain. The Kab tribes which are still influential are the Al-B ^bS FeM^h ^ Hlma£iral1 A6akirah ' Mu j eddem and In the Hawaezah district many of the tribes are Muntafik, which have crossed the Tigris to escape the exactions of the MuntafiklShaiks. S Hawaezah is strong, they pay him tribute, and when he is weak they decline to do so. The subdivisions or branches of tribes are innumerable. Only those which have quite separated from the parent stem and become independent ot it appear in this list. 1RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 27 PART II. REPORT ON TRADE OF THE PERSIAN GULF FOR 1878. The diversion of the trade channels from the north to the south of Persia which was noticed as an effect of the Russo-Turkish war, although in its nature on the whole temporary, is said to have left, in some instances, so far, permanent results. The advantages of the south ern route, increased by the introduction of more frequent steam commu nication, have undoubtedly made themselves felt. The import trade of this part of Persia has become more English or at least^ less affected by Russian commerce, which, after having made itself felt in the markets as far south as Shiraz, and even Bushire, has, of late, been thrown back, the Western European commerce having assumed predominance from the sea-coast to Ispahan. 2. The difficulty of obtaining trustworthy and accurate data is so great; the conditions, subject to climate and other important influences are in South Persia so shifting and precarious that it is not surprising to find persons well acquainted with the country holding widely different opinions as to its trade, prospects and possibilities; some considering operations, both import and export, already overdone and taking a de sponding view of the future; others considering the commerce still capable of great development under more favourable conditions than exist. ^ The real issue probably is whether the required ameliorations come within the sphere of practical discussion. 3. The harvests of 1877 and 1878 were plentiful, and shipments of wheat and barley in the latter year were Qra%n, fyc. still greater than in the former. Even tually the Persian Government reimposed prohibition on the exportation of grain, and this was more effectually enforced than at first. The high prices ruling in India and Europe, together with the abundant surplus from the previous harvests in South Persia, caused the increase in this branch of trade, which under similar conditions might be expected further to develop. 4. The rainfall in the winter of 1878-79 was deficient, and the gram trade therefore is arrested for the present. 5. Cultivation of the poppy in Persia and exportation of opium, through Bushire and Bunder Abbass, Opium. steadily increases. The returns for Bushire show an increase in that article over the previous year of rupees 17 54,000. The quality of the Persian opium of 1878 is said to be superior to that of previous years. Some superintendence is said to be exercised to prevent adulteration,* and * Chests are occasionally examined considerable attention is naturally be- by experts. stowed on a branch of commerce which is becoming a mainstay of the customs receipts, and which has already conduced to better the condition of the classes engaged in the various stages of the operations.28 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL f ' : e \ When thG Persian opium trade was in its infancy, the cW Java and thence re - shipi ' ed ia The Dutch Government, however, having imposed certain restriction, at Java, Aden was subsequently selected as a port of transhipment aj later Suez, at which port no duty is levied for transhipment. ' 7. The Persian Steam Navigation Company now send oecasioml steamers from the Gulf to Galle for conveyance of opium when a suffi cient quantity is collected to remunerate by freight. 8. Poppy seed having risen in price in Europe, a considerable auant^ was in 1878 shipped hence to England for the first time. eraDle 9. A considerable trade in mother o'pearl shells has of late spruii ff Mother o'pearl. U P ^^en the Gulf and England. The . shells are mostly shipped from Lingah to London, and there is said to be a good, though decreasing, demand for them on the continent. 10. Cotton of good quality is grown in Persia, and an increasing Cotton. quantity is exported to India, where prices have been favourable. 11. There was a decrease in quantity of dates and fruits exported in Dates, fruits. ow ™8 &gt; to partial failure of the harvest. Persian tobacco. . A prohibitory duty having been 0 , imposed in Turkish Arabia, a direct trade with tsyna has sprung up. 13. Of the imports to Persian ports there has been a large increase in Cotton goods. cotton stuffs, to be attributed partly to a m , « . , . , portion of the supply for Tehran and Tabreez having been imported through Bushire, instead of by the north ern routes, and partly by reductions made at Shiraz in duties in favour of Persian merchants. The goods have not proved remunerative, the market being over-stocked. 14. The trade with Java in sugar has fallen off, and instead of the Sugar. . description of that place, loaf-sugar is imported from Europe and Mauritius. * Appendix C. The tables* will show the variations in other articles. 15, The inconvenient scarcity of Persian money in South Persia was Specie. alluded to in the last Annual Report, and this inconvenience is still felt. In Bushire. .^ ails „ are the rate of 220 per 100 rupees. Until last year the quan- ^ i y or specie exported from Persia had for generations exceeded the import. But m 1878 the import of silver in rupees, dollars and also bars was considerable, and much in excess of the export. The silver 1 mported is mostly sent to Tehran, where it is coined into krans. 6. An increase in the quantity of copper is thought to denote im- Copper. provement in the domestic condition of , . „ the agriculturists, especially those engag ed m cultivation of the poppy.EESIDENCT AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 29 17. The mail steamers of the British Indian Steam Navigation Com pany continue to run between Bombay Steam communication. an d Busrah weekly, touching fortnightly at Gwadur, Muskat, Jask and Bahrain. 18. Direct steamers between the Gulf and London were run for a time fortnightly during the past year, but owing to imposition of em bargo on exportation of grain at Busrah and Persian ports, monthly sail ings have been resumed. 19. The rival company, called the Persian Steam Navigation Com pany, continue to run steamers with more or less regularity. Steamers of the Austrian Lloyd's Company also, and others belonging to private firms, frequently visit the Gulf and Busrah. 20. Turkish trading steamers have of late years discontinued run ning between Busrah and other parts of the world. 31. There are at Bushire agencies of three Marine Insurance Com panies, viz:— The Marine Insurance Company. Agents, Messrs. Gray, Paul and Company. The Union Insurance Company of Canton. Agents, Messrs. A. and T. J. Malcolm. The Swiss Lloyd's; Messrs. Hotz and Zoon. The English Lloyd's Agents are Messrs. Gray, Paul and Company. Persian merchants, as a rule, abstain from insuring goods. 22. Reference to the Annual Report for 1873-74 will show that it was gathered from the returns of the Trade hetween the Persian Gulf I nc [i ail Custom Houses that from 1869- and India. 70 to 18 72.73 the total value of the trade between Calcutta, Bombay and Kurrachee on the one hand, and the Persian Gulf on the other, had decreased steadily. This fall ap pears to have continued during the subsequent year 1873-74. Since then the returns show a constant and considerable rise in the aggregate value of the trade referred to, which has nearly doubled in the last five years. This will be seen by a glance at Appen ix . Table No. 1. It has to be borne in mind that the trade of Busrah and Muskat is included under the general heading 'Persian Gulf;' but from the year 1875-76 distinct headings have been introduced, and the Table No. 5 will enable the proportionate deductions to be made on account of Busrah for the subsequent three vea rs. 23. During the past three years the trade of India with South Persia has increased by about 50,00;000 Vide Table No. 2. rupees. So far as we can judge from the imperfect local returns arrived at, the direct trade between the t W p N o g Persian Ports and London has trebled in the last five years, and that with Java Vide Table No. 7. has somewhat fallen off. 24. That Persia does not enjoy the full degree of commercial pros perity which might be expected from her natural resources and advan tages is admitted on all hands, by none more freely than the Persians, who, from the governing classes downwards, have much platonic sym-30 ADMINISTRATION REFORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL pathy to bestow on the condition of their less fortunate countrvmpn but any practical attempts to improve matters are rarely beheld 25. Persian rulers understand perfectly well that on the wp II being of the working classes depends that of all, and that the general interests of the country require security and encouragement to be pt tended to the population. Unfortunately those in immediate authoritv under the system adopted, too generally are impelled by their immedi J p interests, and even necessities, to a course of action leadino- to verv difterent results. 0 J 26. A Zabit who has, from desperation, or perhaps from enmitv to his neighbour, engaged to pay more revenue than his district can fairlv yield is m no mood for philosophical reflections, but will proceed straie-hf way to extract what he can from those delivered over to his chafo-e It they resist, he wil appeal for support, probably with success. When oftice is systematically given to the highest bidder without reference to any fixed and well-grounded assessment, and where taxes of dis tncts are gradually being raised without corresponding increase of pro' duction, such cases might be expected to occur. It is generallv believed they do occur with the inevitable result of disturbances and the gradual depopulation of once flourishing districts. Under such a system there can be no appeal open to the peasant. • Vl r 1 etu ™ for hi 8 contributions to the revenues, it is difficult to point to the benefits conferred by the Government on the husbandman JNo roads are constructed, no courts of justice constituted, no personal* protection provided. In a district where feuds are frequent (e. a. JUashtistan) the peasant ordinarily prepares himself for his night's repose by arming himself to the teeth. A military force is certainly main- tamed, but the most frequent active employment of the soldiers is operating against the peasantry to enforce payment of revenue. e g enera l wants felt by all engaged in commerce in South General requirements. Persia are such as depend for their i , « , . . . su PPv on the introduction of an im- proved system of administration and need scarcely be specified here. 29. At the larger ports of the Persian Gulf, the administrative Local impediments to British does not provide adequately for trade. etticient, speedy and authoritative hear- i ^ p . . . an( i decision of suits brought by i f 0re,gI1 . S ^ ects a S ainst subjects, feeourse is usually had to a council of merchants, but this arrangement is on no ™^ baS1S ; a . nd . re sp™s'bility is not sufficiently determined. The nShWW ^ commercial Courts has been suggested and would probably best meet the requirement. R -.f l; Trai 1 1S1 v t c , luties ^ re * tm levied . though in an indirect form, on to ml f ^ L p Ween Bushlre aild Shlr az. At present the muleteer has to hhTcharge^or carriage. P r0 68 ^ ^ting the amount on Bushire anTother ports.' 1 0£ drawbacks ^ con sidered disadvantageous at^DMSS, \ RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1 878-79. 31 32. The most promising project in view to facilitating and stimu lating the commerce of Persia to the Opportunities for extension of ig undoubtedly that which has British trade. ^een the subject of prolonged discussion, the opening of the Karoom river, and of a caravan line from Shuster to Ispahan. Whilst the immediate object which is expected to be attained is shortening and cheapening transit communication between the sea and Ispahan^ the central mart for north and south Persia, a second scarcely less fruitful result would be the extensive trade which would almost certainly be inaugurated at the same time with the richly pro ductive districts from Disful northwards, bringing Persian Irak within the sphere of our commerce. The difficulties experienced in obtaining the necessary concessions for carrying out the operations so advantageous to Persia are characteristic. The present route to Ispahan from Bushire through Shiraz is very roundabout. A much shorter line would be from Deelam through Behbahan, to Kumesha and Ispahan. It is probably more the wildness of the inhabitants than the physical difficul ties which have prevented the use of such a route. 33. It is said that a line from Ram Hormuz to Ispahan would present few formidable physical difficulties were the time ripe for con struction of a railroad. (Sd.) E. C. ROSS, Lieutenant- Colonel, Resident, Persian Gulf. Memorandum on the Opium of Persia. For the last two years the Persians have shown unprecedentedly great activity in extending and improving the cultivation and growth of opium in the country. The heavy losses which they suffered on more than one occasion from their badly prepared and adulterated stuff, and the tempting profits which they found were obtainable from better produce, have apparently impelled them to the course now taken. While a few years ago a case of Persian opium weighing 18 Tabreez mun, or 140 lbs., would not fetch in China more than 280 to 350 dollars, it has recently realized from 500 to 615 dollars. This change cannot of course be attributed altogether to the improve ment in the quality of the Persian drug, as prices are regulated by the state of the Indian produce and by the demand in the China markets. The Bengal and Malwa crops failed in the last two years owing to drought and other circumstances, and the limited outturn, coupled with heavy speculation, tended towards the increase of prices. The prospect of the crops of the current year is said to be favourable, but the trade in opium is not expected to be very remunerative. To return to the Persian opium, from the time the attention of the native merchants was attracted to the trade in this article, about 25 years ago there has been, with two or three exceptions, a gradual annual increase in the production of the drug. But this increase has never before been eo very considerable as to become prominently noticeable.32 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL . It was reported in 1859 that about 3,000 Shah mun. or 300 cases of opium were produced in Persia, and in 1861 that about 10,000 Shah mun or 1,000 cases, were expected to yield from the crops of the year a quantity which was then noticed to be double the outturn of the vious year. ^ UJ ' In the trade report of this Residency for the year 1874-75 the flue- tea Th68 69 t^874 7r &gt; eStlraa ^ d P r0 ? uce °P ium in from the year 1868-69 to 1874-75 were shown in a tabular statement attached to a special report on the subject. The largest produce for any one year did not exceed 3 600 cases (a quantity inappreciably small in regard to the demands in China) and in 1874-75 it had fallen to some 2,000 cases. In the following year there was a further decline, the exports amounting- to about 1,890 cases. Since 1876-77, however, a re-action appears to have Bunde^bb^abne ^ ^ '*** ^ ■ Bushire aad In the early part of 1877-78, the probable yield of the crons was ps timated at 3,500 cases, but the actual number exported from Bushire and Bunder Abbass amounted to 4,730 cases. vi aS c Sf ( 1878 ' 79 ) the outturn was stated to have been 6,700 cases while 5,900 were exported from these ports. ' The probable yield of the crops of the current year 1879-80 is at present estimated to be as follows^ y ou is at In Khorasan about „ Kennan „ „ Yezd „ „ Ispahan „ „ Neereez „ „ Shtiraz „ „ Kazran „ ,, Shushter „ Shah Mun. Cases. . 14,000 equal to 950 . 4,500 „ 300 . 15,000 „ 1,000 . 37,000 „ 2,400 . 6,000 „ 400 . 20,000 „ 1,300 . 1,500 „ 100 . 1,500 „ 100 T0T ■'■ 99,500 „ 6,550 In addition to the above 6,650 cases o'ium, S 3 000 Shah mua or say 550 cases, are expected to come to Yezd from Herat, making the whole stock about 7,100 cases. The Shushter onium is sent through Mohammerah direct, and sometimes ma Bushire to Mus- kat for transmission to Zanzibar; bat a part of it is supposed to be Stn d no t0 Il ' dlan f ™j tier ,I )I ' ovinces vld Mekran and Beluchistan. Thus, 7,000 cases are expected to be available during the current vear for export, hreugh Bushire and Bunder Abbass, to Chfna ^Englnd ' quantities of opium are said to be grown in Tehran Tabrcez and Kermanshah, but these mostly find their way to Europe Turkey' Smyrna being, it is alleged, the port where it is mainly taken to aid markets 1 he l0CaI d '' Ug and fOTWa rded to the Continental in nlimber frortTofi to iqa CakeS Taryin f ? Weight imm i to H Ibs - and 1 -J rom 96 to 192, or more ; and these are packed in fie- or vine fX 1 w ton Sbt m ? 0r Stalks ' into cases containing each English^ hah mUnS ' a Shah mun beill S to about ifj lbs.11« in Cues, RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 33 The object in so packing in cases, as regards weight, is that the contents, after the deficiency caused by drying up in course of transit, which is calculated at from 5 to 10 per cent., may realise at destination, China, one ' picul,' which is about 135 lbs. Another reason is, that the weight is arranged for conveyance of carriage by pack animals, generally mules, employed in these regions. About -f lbs. of the produce of opium prepared in Persia are intended for China. The drug suitable for that market, being required to be fine and prepared with oil, and not rich in morphia, permits its being swelled up with foreign substance, and thus being, as far as practicable, adulterated to the extent to preclude discovery by the modes of testing or (( touching ' used in China. It is said that pure and superior opium, though not so finely manipu lated, has been rejected in China, while the fine opium containing admix tures has found favour and fair market. The preparations made for the China marts, being, say, of a quality of 80 'touch-' (containing 80 per cent, pure juice and 20 per cent, foreign substance) yield from 9 to 10 per cent, morphia. The preparations for England which have recently been specially made pure, and which have come into favour in Europe and America, have, it is said, yielded morphia averaging about 12 per cent. The average price for fair quality of opium suited for the China market has been for the last two years about Rs. 950 per chest; and for the special preparations for England, about 100 rupees more. To these are added the charges of transit and other contingent ex penses, from the place of product to the port of shipment, amounting to about Us. 30; and further a custom and octroi or other duty of about 20 rupees payable by a Persian, or 5 per cent, ad-valorem by a British or other foreign merchant. (Sd.) G. LXJCAS, Uncovenanted Assistant to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire. nihty, o34 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL APPENDIX A TO PART II. Memorandum on cultivation of a village in one of the BoolooJcs [districts) of Shiraz. A village with an area of land sufficient for sowing 18,000 to 20,000 roaunds of grain, is valued at 60,000 krans. Government taxation on such a village would be about 2,500 krans per annum, which is considered to be more or less reasonable. This area is divided into three parts, of which one part only is culti vated during the year, the other two parts being allowed to remain fallow awaiting their turn for cultivation in subsequent years. The ' shatwiy' or autumn sowings for the year in such a village necessitate the outlay of seed in the following proportion :— Barley ...... 2,000 maunds. Wheat 4,000 do. The ' saifee ' or spring sowings are proportioned as under K'ice ...... 400 maunds. Maize 200 do. Cotton 200 do. Sesame, &amp;c 100 do. The outturn of shatwiy sowings is tenfold in a good year and five fold in a bad one. The results of saifee sowings are— Rice 30-fold during a prosperous year. „ 10-fold during an unfavourable year. Maize 50-fold during a good year. „ 20-fold during a bad year. Irrigation may be natural, such as by rivers and springs or artificial by means of kanats. A kanat is invariably private property appertain ing to the village, and involving an annual expenditure of 500 krans to keep it in repair. If the village happen to be irrigated by a river, the proprietor of that village has to pay for his share of the watercourse leading to his lands. If irrigated by a spring, disputes very frequently arise on account of proprietors of other villages attempting to draw away more water than is their due. This is due to the insufficiency of water supplied by a spring. ^ An outlay of 600 krans is necessary towards obtaining a favour able or just decision. Such a village should entertain forty ryots irrespective of their families and strangers, and have twenty u bands ' (pairs) of beasts of burthen or forty oxen. The ryots find themselves altogether. The outturn is divided into three parts ; one-third for the ryots and two-thirds for the proprietor. / If the proprietor should wish to bring his share of the produce to town he must defray the expenses of the carriage. All taxes on the land and water are paid by the proprietor, the amount of which in most cases varies in proportion to his position and influence^ for he either manages to pay the taxes as per ancient Govern-residency and musk at political agency for 1878-79. 35 raent ' tooroar' (tariff) wliieh is generally on a low scale, or contrives to lessen a certain amount from the new and higher rate of taxation, the deficiency in which latter case is bnrthened on the revenues of a neigh bouring village, whereof the proprietor may be less influential. Taxation on villages is very irregular, and in most instances extremely oppressive. Wealthy and prosperous villages worth about 50,000 krans are known to pay only 300 to 500 krans per year. Whereas smaller and less prosperous villages are subjected to a payment of 10,000 to 12,000 krans per year. In the later case the owner necessarily is a ruined man and always in trouble with Government, whose officials become liberal with the bastinado and imprisonment for default of pay- rtent. It is not at all a paying thing in the end to be a farmer in Persia, unless however the proprietor *is a really influential man or a moola or a mojtehid. The difficulties experienced by a proprietor are as follows Want of protection against the robberies of the ryots ; the heavy Government taxation, ordinary and extraordinary, and the constant and false claims set up against the property. This last is a characteristic feature in Persia, especially as there is no law for the punishment of a false claimant. Many bond fide landowners therefore have been utterly ruined. Such false claims are always tolerated both by the Government and priesthood, as it constitutes a sure source of income to them. The taxes are paid in kind on the shatwiy sowings, and in cash on the saifee sowings. There are two classes of ryots, viz., one called the a ryot-i-padishah ' who pay only ' sarmardy' or poll tax, and no change of residence to how ever great a distance from his original place of abode will exempt him from the levy of that tax. The ryots of Dashty are in this category. The other class pays no samardy, but a sum of about 20 krans is annually taken from each ryot towards the maintenance of Government sowars, &amp;c. But in many instances where the kadkhoda or the landlord possesses any influence, this payment is successfully resisted, the actual taxation on the land and cultivation, however, being payable by the owner. The proprietor provides for the seed. Labour during cultivation up to collection after harvest is undertaken by the ryots. Education is totally neglected, but each village is bound to have one person able to read and write. A ' motesadee ' (overseer) is entertained by the proprietor receiving as his salary 3 per cent, on the produce. A kadkhoda is also appointed by the proprietor taking 5 per cent. This person is obliged to entertain the proprietor whenever he should call at the village, as also all persons deputed by Government that may be passing there on duty. The kadkhoda is expected to have one mare at least. The expenses incurred by the kadkhoda for the occasional entertain ment of the owner and his servants may amount to thirty tomans annually, his own (kadkhoda's) private expenses not exceeding that amount. It is not customary for the proprietor to make a long stay in his village, and there are landlords who have never seen their pro perty.36 ADMINISTRATION REPOUT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL A systematic spoliation is carried on by the ryots both during the season for sowing and gathering in the harvest, and in no instance has a farmer been able to check these robberies, or ascertain the exact quanti ty of his harvest, notwithstanding the motesadee and kadkhodah have pretty often administered the bastinado. The value of the produce on the spot may be quoted as under Wheat at 25 cents per maund. Barley ,, 124 « » }&gt; Rice « 50 „ ,, „ Cotton „ 1-50 kran „ ,, Maize ^10 cents „ ,, • Sesame, &amp;c. „ 70 „ „ „ The value of the forty oxen varies from 30 to 100 krans, thus averag ing about 6 tomans per head. As a rule, the oxen are brought and maintained by the ryots them selves ; but in cases where the ryots are unable to do so the proprietor provides the cash and reimburses himself after the harvest. The annual cost for the maintenance of an ox is about 15 krans, but no cash is laid out for that purpose, as the food is grown on the land itself, cotton seeds forming the principal and most nourishing part of it. The agricultural instruments principally in use are the following :— * m, • • , , , Khish (plough) very rude. * The gram is separated from the ^ husk by means of a machine with .oOrre. . sharp circular hoops or wheels, which Aubs60 (pitch-fork for winnowing). are drawn on the grain by donkeys, Daus (scvthe, sickle Or hoe). &amp;c. This is the horre or 'cutter.' Threshing is not in nse. ) • Beel (spade). Two or three sieves. Jawal (another sort of sack.) Ropes. A supply of at least 50 krans worth of implements required for Or 'gav,' meaning 'ox,' the extent each gao is furnished by, and ap- of land ploughed with one ox. pertain to, the ryots. Two hundred krans may be taken as an approximate estimate of the annual expenses of a ryot and his family. In no case does the value of the furniture of a ryot, consisting of copper utensils, a couple of inferior carpets, a few earthen jars, beer or soda-water bottles, exceed twenty tomans. A proprietor is often obliged to construct a wall round the village with a gate and a tower or two. The ryots build their own quarters and at their own expense. Every ryot invariably undertakes a small amount of cultivation on his own private account, which is called khassee and in which the pro prietor has no share whatever. Cultivation in Kazeroon is undertaken as follows :— Shatwee or Autumn Sowings. The land in Kazeroon is private property. If the cultivation be un dertaken by the landowner himself he has to provide seed for an areaEESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY POB, 1878-79. 37 i. e., ox. of one gao* o£ cultivatioiij viz., 1^000 lbs. wheat and 1,000 lbs. barley, and pay- about 14 krans for the labour of ploughing and sowing. He pays in kind 11 per cent, of the yield of his harvest to Government and 20 per cent, to the reapers who have to undertake all the duties appertaining to the collection of the harvest and the carriage into the stores of the landlord. The landowner also pays 2 to 4 per cent, for threshing or treading the corn. Other than a landowner undertaking a cultivation has to pay to the landowner 9 per cent, in kind, from the outturn of his harvest as rent for one gao of ground and 14 per cent, to Government as tax. His other expenses are the same as above. The agriculturists of Kazeroon are of two classes, viz. , the ryot-i- padishah and the non-ryot, the former being always looked down upon by all classes and subjected by Government to more oppression than the others. The ryot cultivator thus not only pays more taxes to Government, but has to pay his taxes in cash instead of in kind and at 30, per cent, above market-value. He is also obliged to give a certain quantity of straw to Government officials whenever required. A ryot when a landowner, and cultivating his own grounds, has to pay 15^ per cent, on his harvest in cash at the above enhanced valuation. A poor ryot pays about 60 krans annually in cash to Government. There is another class of ryots who are obliged to buy at 30 per cent, above market-value a certain portion of the produce received by Govern ment as taxes. A wealthy ryot is entirely at the mercy of the authori ties, a sum of about 1,000 krans being annually levied from him. The value of one gao of land is from 100 krans to 600 krans according to the locality. To start a cultivation an expense of about fifteen tomans is necessary, viz.:— One ox valuing ... 50 krans. Seed „ ... 60 „ Labour about ... 14 ,, Straw and cotton seeds 16 ,, Sundries 10 ,, t One donkey is also maintained by a ryot when undertaking four or more gaos of cultivation. About 2,000 lbs. of grain are sufficient for cultivating one gao of ground at Kazeroon. In the case of saifee cultivation, no distinction is made by Govern ment between a ryot and a non-ryot. Saifee sowings are always undertaken by proprietors of water and agriculturists conjointly, the proprietor providing the water and the ground, and the agriculturist finding the seed, labour, implements, &amp;c. Should the waterowner, however, not be a landowner as well, any other landowner would be but too glad to permit his lands to be used for saifee cultivation gratis, inasmuch as the soil becomes enriched, by manuring which the saifee cultivation necessitates. l\ \38 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL The time taken up for saifee sowings is about seven months the following- being cultivated: tobacco, watermelon, mashmelon, vege tables, cotton, sesame seeds, lentils, &amp;c., rice, gram. A tax of 20 per cent, ad valorem on the outturn is levied by Govern ment, three-fifths of which is payable by the proprietor of the water and two-fifths by the cultivator, and the balance is equally divided between the proprietor and cultivator. Rice and gram, however, form an exception, and are cultivated under the following conditions :— The agriculturist recoups himself for the quantity of seed supplied by him, after harvest. He then goes into equal shares with the water- owner who alone pays Government taxes as follows : if a ryot, he pays three-fifths of his share to Government ; if a non-ryot, he pays only half, the agriculturist paying no tax on his share. In all cases the Government share of the produce is to be carried to Government stores at the cultivator's expense. The approximate value of the produce on the spot is— Wheat at 40 to 60 cents per Kazeroon maund. Barley a 25 &gt;&gt; 30 Gram }&gt; 50 80 Sesame }&gt; 70 100 Maithee » 15 20 )) Dhoil &gt;} 15 20 Cotton )} H 3 krans Rice }) 50 80 cents The expenses of a ryot cultivator in Kazeroon, supposed to have one wife and two children, are ten tomans per annum. The yield of wheat and barley is from ten to twelve-fold in a good year and three to four in a bad one. Rice in a bad year yields twenty-fold and in a very good year sixty- fold. Cotton five-fold in a bad year and ten-fold in a good year. Irrigation in Kazeroon is generally conducted by means of kanats, and the water thereof should in all cases be allowed free passage across grounds, even though not belonging to the proprietor of the kanat. Should the proprietor of a kanat not wish to undertake any saifee cultivation, he would still be made liable by Government to such taxes as may be due by the cultivation. The land in Kazeroon is sown every alternate year. The portions remaining fallow are ploughed. No taxes whatever are levied by Government on gardens at Kazeroon. In the cultivation of the poppy at Kazeroon, the proprietor provides the land, seed and expenses of sowing ; the cultivation is then made over to the ryot who undertakes all the labour necessary for the tending of the crop till the season of collection, when the proprietor pays for the labour of incision, say one kran per man per day. The outturn is then equally divided between the landowner and ryots. No taxes are levied by Government on the cultivation of opium at Kazeroon. There are large tracts of land in Fars with plentiful supply of water, but owing to the perennial growth of rank grass, cultivation is impeded© RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 39 to the ruin of the landowners and that of the ryots, who are obliged by compulsion to stay permanently in those spots. A good deal of water is wasted in Persia owing to the long distances it has very often to travel before reaching a land eligible for its security against raids, &amp;c., and to damages constantly sustained by watercourses, which, owing to the social conditions of the country, it is very often beyond the reach of the ryot to travel out of the jurisdiction of his village to repair. There also large tracts of fertile land which remain waste owing to their proximity to the main roads, as no village having cultivations on such spots can possibly prosper or enjoy the least immunity from the pestering visits of Government officials, and thefts and robberies com mitted by the Iliyat tribes on their passage along the country thorough fares. uleficd plrofRESTBENCY AND MUSK AT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. S i APPENDIX C TO PART II. eowsiSTiKS or THE FOLLOWING TABULAR STATEMENTS 1. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Expoit Tiade between the Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind and the Persian Gulf, from the yeai 1872-73 to 1877-78. 2. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Jlixport Trade between the Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind and Persia, from the year 1875-76 to 1877-78. , 3. Statement showing the total value of the Import and -Export Trade between the Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind and the territories of the Sultan of Muskat in Arabia, from the year 1875-76 to 1877-78. 4. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Export Trade between the Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind and the Arabian territories of States other than Muskat, from the year 1875-76 to 1877-78. 5. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Export Trade between the Presidencies of Bombay and Bengal, and the Province of Sind and the Port of Busreh in Turkish Arabia, from the year 1875-76 to 1877-78. ^ 6. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Export Trade between England and Persia, from the year 1870 to 1878 7. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Export Trade of Persia with Batavia (Java), from the year 1873 to 8. Abstract Table showing the total estimated value of the principal and other articles of trade imported into Bushire during the year 1878. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. 16. Do. Do. Do. Do. Do. Do. Do. Do. 17. Do. 18. do. do. do. do. do. do. do. do. do. exported from Bushire during the year 1878 do. do. do. do. do. do. 19. 20. imported into Lingah do. exported from Lingah do. imported into Bunder Abbass do. exported from do. do. imported into Bahrain do. exported from do. do. „ . ^ imported into the Arab coast in the Persian (jult during the year 1878. n ii? exported from the Arab coast in the Peisian Gulf during the year 1878. Contrasted statement showing the value and description of goods imported into Bushire during the years 1877 and 1878. exported from Bushire during the years 1877 and 1878. imported into Lingah during the years 1877 and 1878. Do. Do. do. do.ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 21. Contrasted statement exported from Lingah during the vpar« 1877 and 1878. ^ imported into Bahrain during the vears 1877 and 1878. ^ exported from Bahrain durinar the vears 1877 and 1878. ^ imported into the Arab coast in the Persian Gulf during the years ]877 and 1878. exported from the Arab coast in the Per sian Gulf during the years 1877 and 1878. 26. Table showing average Tonnage of Vessels entering and leaving the Port of Bushire during the twelve months in 1878. 27. Do. do. the Port of Lingah during the twelve months in 187 8. 28. Do. do. the Port of Bahrain during the twelve months in 1878. 29. Do. do. the Port of Oman in Persian Gulf during the twelve months in 1878. 22. Do. do. 23. Do. do. 24. Do. do. 25. Do. do.50 ADMINISTUATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL Table No. 6. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Export Trade between England and Persia from the year 1873 to 1678 as shown in the Annual Trade Returns of Bushire, Ling ah and Bunder Abhass. Year. Imported into Persia. Exported from Persia. Total value. Rs. Rs. Rs. 1873 .... 7,79,080 3,27,007 11,06,087 1874 .... 6,07,610 4,84,179 10,91,789 1875 . . . . 15,80,150 2,90,800 18,70,950 1876 .... 19,74,960 6,96,500 26,71,460 1877 .... 7,00,800 8,01,320 15,02,120 1878 .... 21,10,900 12,53,000 33,63,900 N. B. Extracted from the Annual Trade Returns of the British Presidency in the Persian Gulf. Table No. 7. Statement showing the total value of the Import and Export Trade of Tenia with Batavia [Java) from the year 1873 to 1878, as shown in the Annual Trade Returns of Bushire and Bunder Abhass. Year. Imported into Persia. Exported from Persia. Total value. Rs. Rs. Rs. 1873 .... 9,05,000 60,434 . 9,65,434 1874 .... 11,36,850 ^ 1,65,650 13,02,500 1875 .... 4,29,975 68,500 4,98,475 1876 .... 5,48,300 1,25,300 6,73,600 1877 .... 6,39,600 24,700 6,64,300 1878 .... 7,51,600 16,000 7,67,600 N, B. Extracted from the Annual Trade Returns of the British Presidency in the Persian Gulf.average Noiaber, 21 16 91 61 111 RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOE 1878-79. Table No. 29. 118 Tadle shalving Average Tonnage of Vessels entering and leaving the Fort of Oman in Persian Gulf during twelve months in 1878. C lass A.—E uropean. C lass B. — N ative C raft. a o Ph o f-l / W m. Where trading or description. Square-rigged, Europe Ditto India Ditto Java Ditto Aden Ditto Muskat Steamers, Mail Ditto Merchant Ditto Pilgrim . T otal India ..... Muskat and Dependencies Arab Coast, Persian Gulf, Bahrain Persian Coast, Mekran . Koweit, Busrah and Kateif Zanzibar .... T otal GRAND TOTAL Average Number. 8 190 25 410 11 6 650 650 Average Tonnage of each Vessel. 80 24 24 33 70 80 Total Average Tonnage. 640 4,560 600 13,530 770 480 20,580 20,580jH ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL PAET III. ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSKAT, FOR THE YEAR 1878-79. The last official year opened favourably. Tranquillity prevailed Politieal generally over all ''Oman, and hopes were entertained by many that the year would pass quietly. The position and tenure of power of His Highness Seyyid- Toorkee had been undoubtedly strengthened by the collapse of the re bellion in the preceding year and the repulse of the attack on Muskat, while their discomfiture had as certainly diminished the influence and prestige of Sheykh Saleh-bin-Ali and the other rebel leaders. The dis affected and turbulent tribes of El Sharkiyeh had also been taught a lesson which it was hoped would not be lost on them. 2. At this time Seyyid Abdool Azeez was in Jaalan residing with the Beni Boo Hassan tribe, and though unceasing in his exertions to enlist a party in his favour his prospects of doing so were believed to be not very brilliant. No signs of movement among the tribes were observed until the month of June when the Sultan received information that Sheykh Saleh in the name of Seyyid Ibrahirn-bin-Kais had succeed ed in forming a fresh coalition of the tribes and would shortly march on Muskat. This news produced an immediate panic in the town and many of the inhabitants withdrew to the Batineh and other places for security. No tidings arrived, however, of the invaders^ approach, and after some time it was reported that dissensions and affrays had occurred among them and that the coalition had come to a premature end. This was in the beginning of July, and the Sultan felt so confident in the dispersion of his enemies that he left Muskat and proceeded to Burka, where his son was lying ill. Her Majesty^s ship Arab which had re mained for the protection of Muskat also left for Kurrachee to give leave to her men. , 3. Hardly a week had elapsed before disturbing rumours again pre vailed in the town, and it was now said that Seyyid Abdool Azeez, having succeeded in collecting a following, had quitted El Sharkiyeh and reached Semed, expecting to gather further adherents on his way down. At the request of His Highness Seyyid Toorkee, who had in the meantime re turned to Muskat, the Political Agent wrote to Abdool Azeez counselling him to desist from hostilities against his brother and return to allegiance. This advice Seyyid Abdool Azeez did not think proper to accept, but continued his march to Semail, where he arrived on the Mth July. Here he was opposed by a Ghaffiree force assembled by the Governor, Nasir- bm-Mohammed, which was soon supported by a strong reinforcement sent up by Seyyid Toorkee, under his son Feysal, and Abdool Azeez, who haa only about 400 men with him, found himself greatly outnumbered and his further advance effectively checked. Notwithstanding this iavourablo state of affairs and the improbability of Abdool Azeez forcing is way through unless joined by Saleh-bin-Ali or some powerful Sheykh, lus operations caused the greatest consternation in Muskat. The suburbs ou si e e walls were completely deserted and most of the families''IISIU Uj, the R esidency and muskat political agency for 1878-79. 115 ST iii. qp T residing inside removed with their property on board vessels in the THE POljn- harbour. This demoralisation was owing- no doubt to the terror inspired ffiE cru elties and excesses committed by the Bedouins composing the force under Seyyid Ibrahim and Saleh-bin-Ali after their repulse the fayonratk T - y ear before. -ral]j over'aj]Tk' ^ ^ ie en ^ after some desultory skirmishing between the rtained br m .i'' ; forces of Abdool Azeez and Feysal-bin-Toorkee at Semail the rebellion K of nrir' {I ^ came to an end. Dissensions had arisen among the rebels, which had been much in creased by the payment of 1,000 dollars to Hamood El Jahafee, one of the Ct leaders, by the inhabitants of Upper Semail, and Seyyid Abdool Azeez ■ retired to Kuriateyn, from whence he ultimately removed to Semed. 5 5. In August a freebooter of El Dhahireh, known as Walad El hd afeig Metowwa, raided the Batineh, and after harassing the country and com- w lost on tfenL mitting several murders, retired with a large booty plundered from the ^ ffas i Jajjju ? poorer inhabitants. On the 11th August the Sultan left Muskat for Ueeaaafa^ Burka with the object of undertaking an expedition against El Hazam rts of doin^ so and destroying the property of Ibrahim-bin-llais in its vicinity, but finding, wyement ainosj: ~ 0Q reaching Burka, that the enemy were more numerous and better intheSultiD rood- prepared than he expected, he gave up the enterprise and dismissed his '' ' ' force. 6. In September Saleh-bin-Ali announced his intention of rising — Mffleki- a g a i ns t Muskat and endeavoured to close communication between this port he Batineli ana i an( l El Sharkiyeh. Nothing however appeared to result from this declara- er of themrafc ■ tion of war, and Saleh-bin-Ali, if he ever really intended to do more than msm aod im create alarm by his boast, must have had reason to give up his con- ^ , ■ templated design. In November fresh disturbances occurred in the c u t iT ^ L el Batineh and several lives were lost in skirmishes between the belligerents, tan eli so kli Tranquillity was not restored until the following month. The tribes that suffered most were the Yal Saad and the A1 Boo Rasheyd, and their ajestrs siup J® losses were estimated at 10,000 dollars. also left for lint 7. In December discord appeared in the ranks of the Harth tribe to which Sheykh Saleh-bin-Ali belonged, and a clique was formed against him idistnrkng mmt by a large and powerful section which repudiated his authority and set iat Seyyiditself to thwart his schemes. The effect of this could only be to diminish juittedElSkkiTii his influence and weight still further in the country, rents on his war k In January 1879 two Sheykhs of the Beni Boo Hassan tribe named who had in tkiK Amir and Rashid, who had been released from prison by the Sultan two rote to Abdool ias® years before and had since rebelled against him, arrived at Muskat and brother and retold made submission through the mediation and under the protection of some not thint projfftn 6 Ghaffiree tribes. About the same time Sheykh Hamood-bin-Said El mffldonthelitiifc Jahafee, having been discarded by his own tribe, the A1 Waheebeh, be- nbled br tie Goft* came a client of the Jenebeh and also offered his submission but was not ted bv a stran? allowed to enter Muskat. F d and8- In March Seyyid Salim bin Hilal A1 Boo Saidee was murdered at m'J t 5 Semed by a party of the Beni Ruweyheh in revenge for the murder of lj 56 Xorffii^ Sheykh Hamad oE that tribe last year. In this affair it is reported Seyyid Abdool Azeez lent his connivance and gave the murderers the [jilitr of shelter and cover of his house from whence they made their attack. .All or r ^ 9 The year closes, as it began, in tranquillity and there is no im- tionm-M®* j mediate apprehension of disturbances occurring. But it may be added ^ and most a -'1IG administration report of the pehsian gulf political that Sheykh Saleh has announced his intention of again leading an ex- pedition against Muskat this summer. 10. At the present time the distribution of power in the various towns and districts of ^Oman is as follows :— The greater part of 'Oman from Dhofar to Khosab with Muskat as capital. S eyyid T oorkee bin S aid bin S ultan. Sohar. S eyyid M ohammed bin T oorkee. Burka. S byyid F eysal bin T oorkee. Semed. S eyyid A bdool A zeez bin S aid , independent. Rostak and El Hazam. S eyyid I brahim bin K ais ; indepen. dent. The following towns and forts are governed by Walees appointed by Seyyid Toorkee ;— Soor. Gwadur. Seeb. Semail. Khasab. Mesnaah. Nezwa. Zikki. Muttrah. Nakhl. Soweyk. Dhofar. Kuriyat. Shinas. The remaining towns and forts are Id Slave Trade the hands of the tribes occupying the respective districts. No importations of African slaves by sea are known to have taken place during the year 1878-79 into 'Oman. In August two Indians, a woman and a boy_, who had been brought from Hydrabad in the Deecan, were released from slavery at Rostak by the Sultan. The woman died on the way to Muskat, but the boy was recovered and sent to Bombay.; In December three more Indian children, two boys and a girl, were released from slavery and sent to Bombay. They had been brought from Hydrabad in the Deccan by a party of Hadramies who had offered them for sale at Soor. On the 9th March 1879 the ship Marian Moore, bound from Calcutta Mai . ;ne with rice, was wrecked about 5 miles S. E. of Muskat. The crew were all saved and subsequently arrived at Muskat. Part of the cargo was received in damaged condition. The circumstances were enquired into by a Naval Court at Muskat. (Sd.) S. B. MILES, Lieut .-Colonel, //. B. M's Political Agent and Consul, Mudat.'Gtlh RESIDENCY AND MUSKAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878 19. 117 iy APPENDIX A TO PART III. Memorandum on Geography of 'Oman hy Lieut.-Colonel S. B. MILES, The kingdom of ^Oman may, geographically speaking, be considered to include that part of North-Eastern Arabia extending along the coast from Ras-el-Ahmor in Kuria Muria Bay to the Snbkha in Longitude 52°, Latitude 2 4the boundary on the western side being a line subtended between those two points. The political limits, however, do not at the present day coincide with the above description, the Sultan's authority towards the north ending at El Bereymi and Khasab on Cape Mussendon, with the exception of the strip from Marrir to Dibba, which belongs to the Joasmees. Like the rest of Arabia, this division of it has never been properly explored, and our maps are consequently very deficient. A very large portion of the kingdom is an almost waterless desert; but even of the habitable area much remains a terra incognita, and entire districts or provinces have been as yet untrodden by an European. Of the coast line we possess an acurate knowledge from the surveys made by the officers of the Indian Navy by order of the East India Company, but of the interior our knowledge is limited to the general features of the country and to the position of the principal towns that happened to fall in the route of the few travellers who have passed through the country. The list of Europeans to whom we are indebted for our slight ac quaintance with this country is not an imposing one. The first who gave any account of the interior of ''Oman, vague and inaccurate as it is, was the geographer El Edrisi, a Spanish Moor, who in A.D. 1153 wrote a description of the world in Arabic for the King of Sicily. His work was printed at Rome in A.D. 1592, and continued the sole authority on the subject down to the visit of Carstern Niebuhr, for the Portuguese, who in the meantime had held possession of the coast during the sixteenth and part of the seventeenth centuries, had unfortunately been able to contribute no information regarding the interior. Niebuhr's work a De scription del' Arabic/' published in 1779, contained a map of 'Oman, the first ever constructed. This, though very meritorious, was of no real value, as Niebuhr did not visit any part of the interior, and his positions were consequently only put down at haphazard from native information. The next after Niebuhr to throw light was an Italian named Vincenzo, who in the beginning of this century took service with the Sultan, the late Seyyid Said-bin-Sultan, and during the fourteen years he remained in the country visited Rostak and other parts of the interior. In 1819 Vincenzo published in London a history of Seyyid Said, in which he gives a plan of M uskat and treats us to an account of his own services, but the most valuable part of Vincenzo's manuscripts appears never to have been published. Sixteen years later a traveller landed at Muskat who has, beyond all others, done the most to extend our knowledge of this portion of Arabia. This was Lieutenant Wellsted of the Indian Navy, who in the years 1835-36 spent several months journeying about in the PlBl li ■ m li IrJi H !118 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PEliSIAN GULF POLITICAL interior, dwelling with the tribes and collecting information regarding tlie country and people, the results of his observations being embodied in his travels in Arabia published in 1838, accompanied by a map. The map was the first trustworthy delineation of a country hitherto unknown to Europeans, and imperfect as it is, is still the most valuable we possess and it has served as the groundwork of all subsequent ones. Lieutenant Wellsted claims to have laid down his positions accurately from astro nomical observations, but I may remark that they are not all to be quite depended on, the important town and valley of Semail, for instance being placed some twenty miles too far west. Wellsted was accom- panied during the greater part of his journey by Lieutenant Whitelock I. N., who also traversed a considerable tract alone, at one time visiting Rostak and at another crossing from Shinas to Shargah. These routes are shown in Wellsted^s map, which Whitelock assisted to produce. Whitelock's account of his journeys was presented, I believe, to the Bombay Geographical Society, but it has not appeared in their transac tions and has hitherto unfortunately been allowed to remain in obscurity. Several other officers of the Indian Navy made trips into the interior about this time, and one, a Mr. Cole, journeyed from El Ashkareh to Muskat by way of the Green Mountains, but none of these can be said to have added to our geographical information. In 1838 a French Botanist, named Aucher Eloy, a man of the most indefatigable energy and per severance, visited Muskat and traversed a considerable extent of the country on foot in search of plants and other natural history specimens, of which he made a large collection. He visited the Green Mountains by way of Nakhl, a route untraversed by Wellsted or Whitelock, and returned by Zikki and the Wady Semail. He died shortly afterwards in Persia on the way home, but his journals were published by Jaubert in 1843 with a map, in which Aucher Eloy^s route through •'Oman was shown. In 1845 Colonel Hamerton, the Political Agent at Muskat, made a journey from Shargah to El Bereymi, and thence to Sohar, of which a short notice appears in the Bombay Government Selections, Volume XXIV, and he is said to have made other trips, but no record of them is known to me. Ten years later, in 1855, El Bereymi was again visited from Shargah by Lieutenant Chester, I. N., who returned the same way. Subsequently, when Acting Political Agent at Muskat, Lieutenant Chester proceeded to the Green Mountains for the benefit of his health, which had broken down, but, his illness increasing while on the road, he was compelled to return before reaching them. In 1862 Mr. W. G. Palgrave visited ^Om^n and has described his experiences in his well-known travels in Central and Eastern Arabia. Mr. Palgrave touched at Sohar and was shipwrecked near Burka, from whence he travelled by land to Muskat. The information given by him, however, does not appear to be of much value. Many of the localities mentioned are not recognizable and are unknown to the Arabs so far as my enquiries extend, while other names have unmistakeably been copied from Wellsted, who again had copied from Vincenzo in whose book they had been misprinted. In 1860 Lieutenant Stiffe, I. N., surveyed the harbour of Muskat and executed a plan of the environs which has been published as Admiralty Chart No. 2869, and leaves nothing to be desired so far as it goes. Lieutenant Stiffe also visited the town of Bosher, 20 miles from'Wellad,, UE^IDENCY AND MUSK AT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1878-79. 119 Muskatj and an account of the journey with sketch-map of the route was published in the transactions of the Bombay Geographical Society. In 1865 Lieutenant-Colonel Disbrowe, Political Agent at Muskat, accompanied by Lieutenant Powell^ I. N., made a journey from Dibba to Ras-el-Khyma, and a sketch-map of the route by Lieutenant Powell was lithographed in Bombay. Colonel Disbrowe also travelled along the Batineh coast about this time, but I am not aware whether he made any geographical notes of his journey. Here the record of the labours of past explorers in 'Oman comes to an end. The Peninsula of Arabia, large as it is, is still so much a terra in cognita and so little attractive to geographers that separate maps of it are very rarely to be found in Atlases. The map of Arabia engraved by J. Walker for the Honourable East India Company in 1819 is a splendid work as regards general execution and as an exposition of the then existing state of geographical knowledge of the country, and it is projected on a larger scale than any other maps of Arabia probably ever produced. It is now, however, of little value, being much behind present requirements. A new edition on a similar scale would be most useful. The most correct and complete map of Arabia now extant, I believe, though on a very small scale, is that of Kiepert, dated 1872. It contains a sectional map of 'Oman on a larger scale. Or particular maps Wellsted's is the first to be mentioned in point both of time and value. It is still the ground plan upon which we must work until some explorer enables us to supersede it. The next is that of the Reverend Mr. Badger, given in his ' Imams and Seyyids of 'Oman.' This is certainly an advance on Wellsted's as regards orthography, but it added little or nothing to our geographical information. The latest map of 'Oman is Lieutenant-Colonel E. C. Boss', compiled for official use and lithographed in Bombay. This comprises the distribution of the tribes and much additional information, obtained from native sources, not given in former maps. It is on a much larger scale than the two preceding, and is the most generally useful and reliable map we have to refer to. I have been for some time collecting geographical information regarding the country and hope before very long to be able to submit the result, (Sd.) S. B. MILES, Lieut.-Colonel, II. B. M.'s Political Agent and Consul, Muskat, of^ADMINISTRATION KEPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL PART IV. TRADE. During the year under report there was a general decrease in the trade of Muskat. This decrease occurred principally under the head of Exports, as_, owing to a great failure in the date crops, the export of that article was on a much smaller scale than usual. The date crop at first promised to be a flourishing one, even more so than the year before, but owing to the untimely and heavy rainfall which occurred just as the dates were getting ripe, most of the crop was damaged and was con sidered as unfit for export. As regards imports, also, the year compares unfavourably with the previous one. (Sd.) S. B. MILES, Lieut.-Colonel, H. B. M.'s Political Agent and Consul, Musical.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000219_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/V/23/36, No 165</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000219</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/V/23/36, No 165</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Report on the Administration of the Persian Gulf Political Residency and Muskat Political Agency for the year 1878-79.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1880/1880</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T02:22:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (72 folios)</extent><extent>The report is arranged into a number of sections and subsections, with statistic data in tabular format directly following written sections. There is a contents page at the front of the report (folios 100-101) that lists the report's contents and uses the report's own pagination sequence.</extent><extent>Foliation: There is a foliation sequence, which is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins on the first folio, on number 98, and ends on the last folio, on number 169.Pagination: The volume contains an original typed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Administration Report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency and Muskat [Muscat] Political Agency for 1878-79, published by the Office of the Superintendent of Government Printing, India (Calcutta), forming part of the Selections from the Records of the Government of India, Foreign Department, and based on reports sent to Government by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Political Agent at Muscat.The report is divided up into a number of sections and subsections, as follows:Part 1,is a General Report (folios 102-107) written by Edward Charles Ross, Resident in the Persian Gulf that gives a summary of developments in the region during the past year. It is divided up as follows:1. 'Oman;2. Arab Coast;3. Bahrain;4. Nejd, El Hasa [Al Hasa], El Katr [Qatar];5. Southern Persia;6. Bassidore [Bāsa‘īdū];7. Establishments;8. Slave Trade.Part 1 contains the following appendices (folios 107v-115):Appendix A: contains a number of meteorological tables in Bushire and Shiraz during the previous year.Appendix B: 'Description of the Bahrain Islands' by Captain Edward Law Durand, First Assistant Resident, Persian Gulf.Appendx C: 'Memorandum on the Topography, &amp;c., of Khuzistan or Persian Arabia, by P J C Robertson, Esq., Assistant Political Agent, Busrah [Basra].Part 2, is a Report on Trade of the Persian Gulf for 1878 (folios 116-119) written by Edward Charles Ross, Resident in the Persian Gulf. It also contains a Memorandum on the Opium of Persia written by George Lucas, Uncovenanted Assistant to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.Part 2 contains the following appendices (folios 119v-159):Appendix A: Memorandum on cultivation of a village in one of the Boolooks (districts) of Shiraz.Appendix B: Three tables related to the number of vessels engaged in trade in Oman, Bahrain and from Lingah to Dayer.Appendix C: A series of 29 tabular statements relating to numerous aspects of trade in the region.Part 3, is an Administration Report of the Political Agency Muskat, for the year 1878-79 (folio 159v-160) written by Samuel Barrett Miles, Political Agent and Consul, Muskat. The report provides a summary of developments in Muskat and the surrounding region during the previous year.Part 3 contains the following appendix:Appendix A: 'Memorandum on Geography of 'Oman' by Lieutenant-Colonel Samuel Barrett Miles, Political Agent and Consul, Muskat.Part 4, is a Muskat Trade report written by Lieutenant-Colonel Samuel Barrett Miles, Political Agent and Consul, Muskat (folios 162v-169). The report contains a number of tabular statements related to trade to/from Muskat during the previous year.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Political Agent in Turkish Arabia, Busrah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Uncovenanted Assistant Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Agriculture</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Meteorological data</topic></subject><subject><topic>Opium trade</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x000219#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>