<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002b6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T15:33:27.785Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&lt; HF. /*??/&lt;(?. Jlo^« 13* It 1» un€ltrflto&lt;jd that th« B*0 .a.C. are to resiain in Sharjah Indefinitely and tnat there i® no queetion at present of Cable and Wireless Limited taking over the wireless station from them. Tide India Office telegram ifo* &amp;947 dated 11th &amp;ay 1947a Wote 14a The required information is as follows* (a) number of telegrm&amp;s despatched by ihibad b) Humber of telegrans received for Dubai g) Humber of telegrams despaired by Sharjah d) Kumber of telegrams received for Sharjah 2478 • 360 *• 490 • 2231 approxim ately. It will be seen that there is a good ease for the installation of a telephone or telegraph line between Dubai and Sharjah.2 . roposal of Air India to run service calling at Sharjah A c.f, ray telegram No. 6713 of 23rd Hay) 5. K.A.F, requirements . Reference paragraph A. R.A.F. have a continuing long terra interest in Sharjah. A list of buildings which R.A.F. will require permanently is attached herewith. Air Ministry consider that it will be better also to retain the few buildings surplus to their • requirements rather than tha.t they should be demolished or abandoned. 6. You now have authority to inform Sheikh that&gt; he will be paid ground rent for R.A.F. camp from date of cessation of hostilities with Japan. I should bo glad to have your recommendation as to the amount of rent which should be offered to him. I should also be glad to have your recommendations with regard to form of future air agreement. 7m \ OUTWARD TELEGRAM External Dei *#«»««*» » mmma *o*j« «*' nt CJi 3 *Jo From io Repeated to Secretary of State for India Political Resident.* Persian Oulf P Bahrein Government of India P External Affaire Department^ K.M. Airibaasadorj, Bagddad s and Political Agents Koweit Despatched llo30 houre, 23rd l,;ay 1947 No* 6713 , COZfFIDSttTIAi-.. Government of India’s telegram 3026 of 18th Aprils paragraph K.M^G* have no objection to Air India opei’ating service calling at Sharjah ana Bahrein on basis of existing facilities as long as these continue. It is impossible to see very far ahead but following is present position: (a) Sharjah * B#Q.A.C, now have no service calling there but at requestor liinistry of Civil Aviation are continuing for present to man fort and provide communications requirements for Persian Gulf air route as a whole* RoA-F. have continuing interest in airfield* presumably these facilities T/ill suffice for needs of Indian air service, but it is difficult for us here to be sure of this without further detailed information* (b ) Bahrein* With reference to paragraph 2 of ycui* telegram 543 of 1st May Air Ministry state that R.a.F* are maintaining aecoiamodation for 160 permanent staff and 100 passengers^ Provided that there is no night stop scheduled by Indian service B*Q.A.C. would no doubt provide emergency night- stop accommodation by arrangement with Air India* ab regards •signals facilities we are not sure what Indian servicers point to point requirements will be* with this possible exception adequate signals facilities should be available® Please sea my immediately succeeding telegram» It is not cl.ear whether Air India are interested in possibility of call at Koweit* H.M.G* are not ther..selves interested in making Koweit an aerodrome for operating of scheduled services and any facilities for Indian services ^ould probably have to be provided by oil Company* 3® I suggest as first step representative of Air India should get into touch with B CUA.C.’s representative in India to make sure that requisite facilities for operation of service will be available* if this is cleared satisfactorily you might then inform Sheikhs of Sharjah, and Bahrein of proposed service*- 4 Apprdach -o Iraqi GoveiTOwit proposed in paragraph 5 of Govemiuent of India's telegram 5025 might perhaps be deferred until it is clearer what facilities will be available on pers Gulf route© reian- 'h OUTWARD TELEGRAM External Departm ent, CYPHSR (OcT.P.') Prom Secretary of State for India Political Heeidentj, Persian Gulf, Bahrein Peptd«to Govemiient of India p External Affairs Dapartmentp H» hi 0 Ambassador, Baghdad, and Political Agent, Koweit Despatoheci 09»45 hours, 23rd hay 1947 K 0967 O 8 , QQNPIDMTIAL , Baghdad telegram No*11 of 18th April to Koweit, and your telegram 610 of 19th ^ay. H.L«G. have not rejjeat not authorised Iraqi Airways service* They are not themselves interested in making Koweit an aerodrorae for operation of scheduled services with attendant obligations and had in fact been considering possibility of letting Koweit Air Agreement lapse after May 1948* If however Iraqi service is to be run by agreement with Oil Company and to meat their needs H*fcLG. will not raise objection, but Oil Company-s position vis-a-vis under terms of Koweit Air Agreement appears to need explaining to Oil Company and regularising, e»g« H.M.O* are paying Sheikh £500 per annum for lease of aerodrome and are entitled to retain landing fees* /Conies to 8md/JIA 14998/38 /(,' Hay, 184T. Dear Innes, With reference to /our furrier letter of the 2£th Ux&gt; r about your proposal to operate a wireless station at Sharjah because of the withdrawal of B*0«A.0.» I am sorry not to h&amp;wo been able to reply sooner on this subject* As I mentioned on Wednesday the delay has been due to some doubt aa to the future pluis of B«0*A*C* and even now 1 am unable to ooouront* I understand the Ministry of Clril ATlatlon Is looking Into the matter* but there Is no danger of the sudden withdrawal of B*G*A*C* without girliig us time to make alternative arrange ments* I will let you know as soon as the position become 3 clear* fourn blncere 1/, j.Innes* £au *9 C*B**M*X*&amp;*£*Tel. : Whitehall 9000 Ext 1.083 Grosvenor 3961 Ext. 17 BJCB/726P/90 D.C.H.Abbott, j^sq., &amp;.P.O. ® '' BRITISH JOINT COMMUNICATIONS BOARD, c/o ADMIRALTY, LONDON. S.W.I. 1st April, 1947 We have no comments to make on your letter to Mr. Harrison reference 14993/58 of the 27th idartih. €. Major R. Sigs., for Secretary BRITISH JOOT CO {MOOCATICSIS BOARD. Copy to:- India Office. Mr. P.A.K.Harrison._y . \o K % India Office, Whitehall, S.W. !• Ext,65V^7* 1947. ypUfiO' I forward herewith a oppy of a letter from the General Post Office dated 27th i.larch enclosing one fran Cable and Wireless Limited dated 19th March about the with enclosure. ) establishment of a wireless telegrapn station in Sharjah. You will remember that the question of the wireless station at Sharjah was raised in a letter from the political Resident, Persian Gulf, dated 17 th February, a copy ot ^ h was sent to you with my letter to Low, Ji*t.47v4/ dated ^th Jlarch. Proa Low* s reply of 28th March, now received, it appears that B.O.A.O. still intend to keep signals pers nnel at Sharjah, in which case they may he able to maintain their present comnercial wireless serrice with Bahrein, I should be grateful if you could clarify the matter in order that we may bo in a position to deal with the G-.P.O’s lettere j Low. I an sending a copy of this letter and enclosures to #• $ j A)e«iaoui» wu.»o A A. K». HARRISON Major H. Jones, .Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, W.C. 2«o Telephone: HEAdquarters 123^- Telegrams: Gentel, Cent, London Your Reference P.O. Reference 12 f 993/38 Vi* 4 * M _ ... . .,V fyji- /-/tCu TELECOMMUNICATIONS DEPARTMENT, GENERAL POST OFFICE, wm %r LONDON, E.C.I. -70 Mar*,. 19 W. iEXEO I enclose 4 a otpy of a letter whWh we have received from Cable and Wireless Ltd* about the establishment of a wireless telegraph station in Shariah. We should be glad to know whether there wculd be any objection m principle to their seeking a new concession, or a transfer of the existing concession; if not the Company would pursue with you the negotiation of a suitable concession. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Cole, British Joint Cormnunications Board and to Shaw-Zambra, C.C.C. for any comnent they may have. Yours sincerely.—Cable ahd Wireless Ltd. , Electra House, Victoria Embankment London i T^/w/p 6 / 3 19 th riarch, 1947 Dear Townshend, Sharjah, Persian Gulf . In the past the B. O.A.C. have operated an aeronautical wireless station at Sharjah which is on their Basra-Bahrain-Sharjah air route to India. By arrangement with -Hie B.O.A.C. a ccrcmercial wireless circuit has been operated between Sharjah and our Bahrain wireless station, each party earning 30 centimes per full rate word on traffic passing over this section. Certain changes by B. O.A.C. in its operations in the Gulf are taking place and we understand that Karachi will replace Sharjah as the next stage beyond Bahrain. Consequently the 3.O.A.C. will be withdrawing from Sharjah and no means of telegraphic ccranunication will exist for the commercial community remaining. In order to provide for this need, we propose erecting and operating the necessary wireless plant at Sharjah for communicating with Bahrain, and opening our own office there. I should be glad if you would kindly let us know whether the various interested parties have any comments to make on our proposal. Yours sincerely. (Sgd.)J.Innes. Managing Director. H. Townshend, Esq., C.B., General Post Office, London, E.C. 1.* f ^ Cbccs^c^ '9^7 • ^ BoOw\cC a . acting fc;a the Amenta of Cabla &lt;t ^ineleefe Ltd* * thfn» aS no reason to fieatsrae that B«0»A*C, will al?raj8 saeint^in &amp; ground organisation st Sharjah# and thoy have in fact# already sugges ted to Gah/.c &amp; Wireless^ Ltd* r that the latter should tali© over the commitment in the normal xmimep* It has also o&amp;qti suggested that as the RAF will probably maintain their Station at Sharjah# they should te&amp;e over the present B.O.AcO^ oorianitments including civil traffic, Inxt even should the RAI’ 1 ag;'ee to this proposal, which is considered no&amp;t unlikely In view oi accounting and other difficulties, it is not considir^^d a satisfactory eclutioiw It is recoiasnendtod tb^t Gable &amp; Wireless# Ltd*, should be prepared to take over 1 froir B.O.AoC* ®t some future date, although if B*OoAoO* are to remain in Sharjah for any considerable time, it would be uneconomical for two separate stations to operate in so small a locality, and Cable &amp; Wireleae, Ltd*, need not move in until B*G.A*C* leave. from Sharjah/Dubai for the past six months should foe examined,' as it would then be possible to estimate whether the proposal made by the local Postmaster to install a telegraph circuit between the two towns, would be justified* 14® It is &amp;3.8Q recommended that traffic figures to and U/t)Draft Letter Form B. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Sir, J 1 am directed by the Secretary of State in Council to enclose, for the information of the Government of 2. I am to enquire whether any objection is seen to this appointment and am to request that, if there is no objection, it may be recognised by the Government of India. 3. If it is considered that there may be any objection as for atYour reference: S. &amp; 0.8026/36 S. &amp; 0.307/37 P. 0.Reference 112504/35. TELECOMMUNICATIONS DEPARTMENT, GENERAL POST O^ICE, LONDON, E.C.l. 24th March, 1937. Sir, With reference to your letters of the 7 th of December and 4th of February on the subject of Wireless Stations in the Persian Gulf, I am directed by the Postmaster General to enclose, for the information of the Secretary of State, 2 / a copy of a letter from the Director General of Posts and / Telegraphs, New Delhi, and a copy of this Departments reply. No doubt the Secretary of State will be so good as to deal with the points raised in paragraphs 1 and 2 of the Director Generals letter. I am, etc. , (Sgd.) J.Louden. The Under Secretary of State for ^ndia, Economic and CTerseas Department, India Office.COPY. Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department. The Director of Telecommunications, General Post Office, London. No. W-4371, dated New Delhi, the 25th January 1937. Sir, I am directed to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of information regarding wireless stations of the Koweit Oil Company Limited at Koweit and Bahrah forwarded with your letter No. 44250/36 dated the 30th December 1936, and to say that this Department has no definite information as regards the terms on which the Company has been permitted to erect and operate these stations. I am therefore to refer to the correspondence ending with the India Oft ice letter No. E. &amp; 0. 8026/36 dated the 8 th December 1936 and to request that, if His Majesty’s Postmaster-General has no objection, full details together with a copy of any specific authority which may have been issued may kindly be forwarded for the information of this Department. 2 . In this connection I am to refer also to the wireless stations at Gwadar, Sharjah, Banrein and Bushire. It is understood that the stations at Gwadar and oharjah are operated by Messrs. Imperial Airways Limited while those at Bahrein and Bushire are operated by Messrs. Cable and Wireless Limited, the latter stations having been , taken over by the Company with the assets of the late Indo/2. Indo European Telegraph Department. Definite information of the terms on which these Companies have been permitted to operate these stations is also not available in this Department and, before addressing the Companies, I am to enQuire whether the British Post Office have issued any formal authority or could supply any information on this subject. 3. I am also to say that similar information is also required in respect of the station recently proposed by Messrs. Cable and Wireless Ltd. at Aden for which callsign XZY was allotted by this Department. Although, as explained by the tndia Office, the position in respect of this station will change from 1st April 1937, it appears that the station should be regarded as authorised by this Department for such period as it continues to use callsigns allotted from the Indian series. In this connection I should refer you to tnis office endorsement No.W-4371 dated the 20th January 1937 forwarding a notilication to the International Bureau that the callsign will be changed from XZY to VTQ from 1st April 1937 and to enquire whether it is proposed to allot a callsign to this station from the British series on the transfer of Aden from Indian control. I have, etc., Sgd. P.J. Edmunds. Deputy Director-General, Wireless.TELECOMMUNICATIONS DEPARTMENT, GENERAL POST OmCS, LOl^DON, E.C.l. March, 1937. Your reference W. 4371. P.O. reference 44250/36. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 25th of January, I am directed by the Postmaster General to say that the British Post Office has not licensed or authorised the erection or establishment of any wireless stations in the Persian &gt;-rulf or at Aden. The conditions under which such stations are established and operated are laid down by the foreign and Political Department of the Government of India. A copy of your letter has therefore been sent to the Secretary of State for India. A wireless call sign from the British Colonial series is now being allotted to Aden. I am, etc. Director General of Posts and Telegraphs, New Delhi.r • /L&lt; * l 488 ^9 v. v_y JAIR MINISTRY, ADASTRAL HOUSE. KINGSWAY. W.C.2. 13th July, 1935, Dear Laithwaite, it v\ iZ n There is a small question outstanding in connection with the wireless service at Sharjah, Messrs, Cables &amp; Wireless wrote to us some time ago intimating that they wished to introduce a Deferred Letter Telegram service between their station at Bahrein and Sharjah, We informed them that pending the settlement of the controversy which had arisen with the local Sheikh regarding the profits accruing from the public correspond ence service, we considered it inadvisable to extend the public facilities at Sharjah in any way. Can you say how this matter now stands. My last information is your letter P.Z.1420/35 of 1st March to Colonel Powle. The matter is not one of much importance so that it might be allowed to slide if you think it undesirable to re-open discussions with the Sheikh. We did, however, tell Cables &amp; Wireless that we would let them know in due course whether their proposal could be accepted. Yours sincerely, J.G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S. W.l. Yc; /No.P.Z.1420/35, dated the 1st March 1935 on the subject of the wireless station at Sharjah. 2. I have informed the Shaikh of Sharjah on the 31st March last that no subsidy could or would be paid to him. The status quo , therefore,continues and the wireless telegraph station at Sharjah will remain open for commercial traffic unless and until the Shaikh objects which he is unlikely to do. Yours sincerely, Sd/- T.C.Fowle. J.Gr.Laithwaite,Esquire,0*1 .E., India Office,London. Hraft of above letter was approved of by Colonel Eowle who had no time to sign before leaving Bushire.INDIA OFFICE, ^ Air Mal1 -. LONDON, S.W.l. P. Z. X420^ / 5 | 5_._ lst Maroh 1335 . My dear Fowle, Would you please refer to my letter of 12th October, P.Z. 4606/34 ? You will remember that in the ligot of discussion with you it was agreed that you should take up with the Sheikh the question of the wireless station at Shargah and explain that it is not possiole to grant him either a lump sum payment or a share in the profits and ask him whether in those circumstances he now wished the station to be closed for public messages or whether he would prefer that it should remain open to the public. 2. The Air Ministry have asked us whether any decision has yet been reached as the result of your discussion with the Sheikh and we should be very grateful if you would let us know what reply we should give. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Political Agent, Bahrein. Yours sincerely, J.G.LAITHWAITE. The Hon»ble Lt.Col.T.C.Fowle, •^ushire.By Air Mail. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 12th October 1934. Io Air Ministry d/- 1 st Aug.1934. i'rom Air Ministry d/- 8 th Sept .1934. My dear Fowle, With reference to our discussion on 10th October about the wireless station at Shargah, I enclose a copy of the correspondence noted in the margin. In the light of our discussion we propose to inform the Air Ministry that the Resident will now take the matter up again with the Sheikh and explain that it is not possible to grant him either a lump sum payment or a share in the profits and ask him whether, in the circumstances, he now wishes the station to be closed for public messages or whether he would prefer that it should remain open to the public. A copy of the correspondence is being sent to the Government of India. We should be grateful if you would in due course let us know the result of the reference to the Sheikh. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) J.G.Laithwaite. The Hon’ble Lt. C ol. T. C. W. E owl e , C . B. E. , H.B.M.Consulate-General, Bushire.■216428/32/S.6 AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, W.C.2. 8 th September, 1934. Sir, I am commanded by the Air Council to refer to India Office letter E. &amp; 0. 4003/34 dated 1st August, and to acquaint you for the information of the Secretary of State for India that the contents have been referred to Messrs.Imperial Airways, Ltd., who, in view of the political aspect of the question, do not feel competent to express an opinion as to whether the Sheikh should be paid or not. A division of the profits would, however, be more acceptable to them than the payment of a lump sum. The Company point out that the service was originally instituted for the benefit of the Sheikh’s subjects, and that for their part they would now prefer to be without it. It has recently been found necessary to appoint a European operator to Sharjah at an increased expenditure of £15C per annum. The Company feel in consequence that if any payment is made to the Sheikh, the charge for telegrams should be increased ccmmensurately with such payment. I am to enquire whether this suggestion is likely to be acceptable to the Sheikh. I am , et c. , (Sgd.) J.A.Webster. The Under Secretary of State for India, Economic and Overseas Department, India Office, S.W.l.E. &amp; 0.4CC3/34. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 1st August 1934 Sir, v'ith reference to correspondence ending with this Office letter of 5th January, E. &amp; 0. 8549/34, regarding the Sharjah Wirelese Station, I am directed the Secretary of State for India in Council to enclose copy of papers noted in the margin. With regard to the ••ram Government of India, dated ''') 9th June, 1934, with enclosures. ) jnrcrc C. &amp; W. Ltd., dated 12th July. ) Political Resident’s letter of ?8th April, I am to state that the Secretary of State would te glad if the position vis-a-vis of the Sheikh, as described in the Political Resident's letter of 28th A^ril could be explained to Imperial Airways, and if he could be informed wdiat view the Company take of the Sheikh’s proposals. The question of the arrangements for notification will be dealt with separately. I am, etc. , (Sgd.) E.J.Turner. The Secretary to the Air Ministry,IH&gt;Ia iCX 9 xil L # S. Tr # 1 ilie 0* i^oartauit here are uarltiiir to you of iolally by to-^ay^ r»ii the subject of the registration of the wireless station at har^ah ^hioh forraed the subject of previous correspond once ending *ith ?oreira and Political &gt;eparti5erit letter of 26th June # Bo. F.115~M/M # y&gt;u will have seen, the aovernraent of India at the date of that let er ^ere very reluctant to astmae rospmsibility fear the registration of the aha n-ah wireless station. e had meant to dieeuas the poin. with y&gt;« during your leave* but did not h*vs an opportunity to do ao. It is a relatively mail one, but as y &gt;u will see fro* our official letter referred to above, while we reco;?au 3 e the force of the arguments adduced by the Ooverattest of India against registration of Lhe awtion being undertaken by them* ve think it very important* eepocially now that the Colonial Office has ceased to the Eon’ble Mr. L Metcalf foreign eoretary to vhe dovornaent of India hew ^elhi* etealfe©rerclse &lt;iay rea^nslblllty in respect of tile Gulf &amp;&amp;£ that its affaire are eoor&lt;U&amp;at©d by the Gpvc. of India and the India office* to avoid the l^tarodictioii of any outside imperial authority, jaore r^urticuii-rly in a relatively petty faeat Ion such an the preaent, and on a uubjeot other aspects of which are already handled solely by the Government of India. 1e hop© very muoh 9 therefore, that the Government of India will In the elrou^stanoe described In our official letter see no difficulty about undertaking registration, and will be grateful for any aa i stance you can give us. Years siaoerely.a''. *1 JAK l January 1954. Vith reference to your letter of the 26th June, 1933, fo• ^53, relative to the registration of the wireleae station at C'hargah, X cum directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that he? has given conaiderationto the arguments advanced therein against tae regiatration of this station being undertaken by the Government of India* 2* As the Government of India are aware, consideration of the somewhat analagous case of the Owadur Station, has made it clear that there are difficulties in the completion of formalities such as registration in regard to wireless telegraph stations in the protected areas of the Gulf region. The Rulers of the helkhdoms in which they are situated are not themselves signatories of the demc Convention; they are precluded by the terras of their Treaties from dealing with foreign powers etc., and, on general political grounds, it is desired to excite the minimum of internitjxnal interest in their position and their special treaty relations with Hia Majesty*s Government. The choice, therefore, lies between discharge of such f notions on their behalf by His Majesty’s Government in the hi ted Kingdom as the pow^r responsible for the conduct of their political relations or by the Government of Inula as the Government directly concerned with the local political administration of these areas. Your letter of the 26th June set out various arguments in favour of the former alternative to which the Secretary of State has given his consideration, but apart fro i circumstances special to tlu? present case, he has decided that it is unuesirable that either Th# foreign Secretary to the the Government of Inula, Foreign and Political Department.the present or other Wireless Telegraph stations which may be established in the tribal areas of the Gulf, should be dependent on any authority other than that which is responsible for the immediate control oi’ their affairs* and which already exercises Aftny of tae functions of Government in connection with Post Offices established in this area» The connection of the Indian administration with this area has of course become even closer d ring recent months* as the result of transfer to the India /, / 1 st ovenber Office of the functions previously performed by the Colonial Office in regard to the Persian Gulf, and the primary responsibility for the administration and for the conduct of the political affairs oi the Gulf Sheikhdoms is now concentrated in the India Office and the Government of India* Unless, therefore, the Government of India desire to call attention to any consideration of substance in connection with this matter, which has been hitherto overlooked, the Secretary of dtate would be glad if the necessary steps for the registration of the Chargah station nry be taken by the Government of India without further delay. A copy is enclosed of a further letter from the /dir Ministry setting out certain additional particulars. The Government of India will no doubt consider whether a change in the call sign of the station is desirable. 3 * I am to forward with this letter copy of a letter from the Air linistry relating to an enquiry by Imperial Airways in regard to the registration of telegraphic addresses at 3hargah. In this matter as in others, the Secretary of State considered it desirable that stations in the Gulf area should conform generally with the Indian system, and he will accordin, ly be glad if the Government of India will take the necessary steps in correspondence with(y) with the local repreecntatives of Imperial Airways, to regularise the awetngeaents for telegraphic addresses at ahargah on the analogy of the India i Eegulations* I tm, Sir# Your obedient Servantt (Sd.) E, J. TURNER.U'p^aj I'.c P.Z.7600/33. / tic ■« GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. EXPRESS LETTER (Alfi MAIL). No.C/142 of 1933 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. 15th November, 1933 Prom - Resident, at Bahrain, To - Foreign, New Delhi. Repeated Retaxandum, London. Political, Bahrain. 4f Vi &amp;,/■*? ' Reference correspondence ending with my Express letter No.1491 of 13th July 1933. I enclose herewith 1. Letter No.240 dated 13th July 1933 ) copies of to the Shaikh of Sharjah. ) 2. Letter No.689 aated the 11th October ) correspondence 1933 from the Shaikh of Sharjah. ) 3. Letter No.C/141 dated the 15th November) noted in the 1933 to the Shaikh of Sharjah. ) margin. The Shaikh’s reply to my first letter was vague and so I have addressed him another. (Sd.) T.G. Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. (Sd.) J. Croning. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.To No.240 of 1933. British Residenoy &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, 13th July 1933. Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar, Chief of Sharjah, Sharjah. After Compliments, With reference to your letter No.405 of 19th Zilhijjeh 1351 (14th April 1933) on the subject of the opening to the public of the Imperial Airways Wireless Station on the aerodrome in your town. I have now been instructed by my Government to ask for your formal sanction for the opening of the said wireless station, which - as you are aware - has been in fact open to the public for some time. You will remember that when we discussed the matter you agreed that a public wireless station v/as a benefit to your people, but that you wished to be consulted officially before it was opened. The concession which you give for the opening of the said Wireless Telegraph Station to the public will be to His Majesty’s Government, who will appoint Imperial Airways Company as their agents. Usual ending. sd/- T.C. Fowle, Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.&lt;1#&gt; No. 689 o Dated Slst Jamadi-al-Aukhir 1358. (11th October 1933). Prom Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar, Ruler of Sharjah, Sharjah. To The Hon’ble Lieut.-Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.P., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. After compliments, 'vTith reference to your letter No.240 dated the 13th July 1935, asking me to sanction the opening of the wireless station for the public. I therefore beg to state that the Imperial Airways Company already opened it for public without my having come to any arrangements with them through Your Honour and though I had not permitted them to do so. I now request Your Honour to effect a satisfactory arrangement and agreement in the matter. And Your Honour is worthy of doing all good deeds. Usual ending.No.C/141 of 1933 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. 15th November, 1933. To Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar, Ruler of Sharjah. After Compliments, I have received your letter No.689 dated 21st Jamadi-al-Aukhir 1352 (11th October 1933). I do not quite understand what arrangement and agreement you wish me to effect. The opening of a public wireless station is a benefit to your people and all that is now required, as I stated in my letter No.240 dated the 13th July 1933, is your formal sanction for the opening of the said wireless station. Usual ending. (Sgd.) T.C. E 1 ov/le, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulfjr. * „. 4734 GOVERNMENT OF|@gL§ British Goneulats-gerrmcT,— BUSHIRK* EXPRESS LETTE '1. WJU^y [iV, Z&gt;. —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended, to be treated, on To foreign, Simla* 1491. l»ishire, noted the 13th July -^3 Reference correspondence ending with the foreign and Political Department letter fio*F*ll&amp;-K/55 dated the 26th June 1955 to India Office» London. 2. Shaikh of Shargah has seen communicated with but hie reply has not yet been received. ' I suggest that action regarding notification to Berne be not taken until reply is received from shaikh. The issue of above has been authorised. Secretary to the Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian uulf. fO i 665S&amp;P ~ (M * 1821 -~ 270 ' 32 ~ 2 ' 00,000 * Copy to the India Office* London*Minute Paper. P.Z.4515/33. political Department. 1712r! 5000 3/33 Secretary, E. &amp; 0. Department, I am not very convinced by the Government of India’s letter below. Nor do they seem to have adopted a particularly helpful attitude in regard to the registration of the wireless station. As was recognised in our letter to them, we are to some extent asking them to stretch a point by making themselves responsible for jthe registration and they are, of course, quite entitled to say that they are unwilling to go as far as the Secretary of State would like them to. On the other hand, the Government of India are responsible for the running of the Bahrein Post Office, which is very much farther west than Shargah. Their Director at Karachi has been in correspondence in regard to the Post Office at Shargah with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and they are also responsible for the postal arrangements in Muscat. (I do not press the fact that Indian stamps are used in Koweit or that the Government of India have been closely associated with postal arrangements there, because the postal arrangements in that State are at present under reconsideration). There seems in the circumstances, particularly having regard to the general desirability of keeping responsibility for Gulf administration in the hands of the Government of India, something to be said for raising the point with them again in the light of the considerations adduced above. However I do not wish to press for this - the question being of insufficient importance to be worth controversy if we can persuade A.M. jor G.P.O. to make the registration. 2. If, on the other hand, it is decided to accept the/Draft Paper. political Department. DRAFT LETTER. The Secretary, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, W.c. 2m 1712a 5000 3.33 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the letter to the Government of India dated 19th May, No.P.Z.2515/33, on the suhjec of thefegistration of the public wireless telegraph station at Shargah, of which copies were sent to the Air Ministry under India Office letter of 19th May, No.P.Z.2515/33. 2. The Government of India have now * replied strongly urging that they should ♦ not be asked to accept responsibility I for registration of the Shargah wireless station. They recognise that the station at Gwadur has been assigned a call sign from the series allotted to British India, but they differentiate between the Gwadur and Shargah stations by pointing out that the Gwadur station * lies on the Indian side of the Persian frontier and very much closer geographically to India than Shargah. They further represent that, as the Shargah station will be open for public international correspondence the rates of charge should be notified rs internationally through the International Bureau of the Telegraph Union at Berne * » * and that the station must be entered in the/the international list of telegraph offices, and they represent that the fact that the Government of India have no concern with the fixation of these charges is an additional reason in favour of the notification of the necessary information to the Bureau either by the: Air Ministry or by the General Post Office« A further argument in favour Of this course is that they understand ths similar action has been taken in other cases in respect of wireless stations With which the Air Ministry is concerned in various parts of the world* 3. The Secretary of State does no wish to press the Government of India on the matter in view of their obvious 9 reluctance to undertake registration of this station and he would suggest that in the circumstances the simplest course would be that either the Air Ministry or the G.P.O* should make themselves responsible lor registration* It may be remarked that if this suggestion is accepted it will have the effect of regularising thb use of the existing call sign G.P.O., since it is clearly desirable that call signs for the station should be chosen irom those allotted to the controlling administration* 4. A copy of this letter is being sent to the G.P.O*.i3i ±j jjrom To • T 1 *. 6 * f. Xl 6 -l&lt;y 33. The T’orei n -secretaiyjjto tnje Government of India, ,t The Under oecretary of Gtate for muia, Political department, Inaia Office, .uondon. datea oimia, tue ^ 6 ^ June 1^53. Registration of the public -wireless station at ohargah. j rtith reference to the corresponaence ending with tne Secretary of state's express letter o. 2895/33 aatea the £ 6 tn x^ay 1933, on the suoject of the registration of the wireless station at dhargah, I at airectea to say that the Government of xndia have no doubt that particulars connected with tms station should oe communicated to the International bureau of the Telegraph union at ^erne by the ^ir ministry or British Post Office rather than by the Government of India, for the following reasons. 2 . x.o analogy can oe drawn between the present case and that of the Gwaour wireless station, referred to in mt.W alton 1 s letter dated the i9th may 1935, since the Gwadur station lies on the Indian side of the Persian frontier and had been assigned a call sign from the series allotted to British mdia. On the other hand the Government of India are in no way concerned with the much mo re distant station of onargah, which is situated m .maoia. moreover, as the st *tion will be open for public international correspondence the rates of cn&amp;rge snould be xxo tifiea intern^rldnail^^through tne bureau and the station must be entei/a the Intew^bional list oi telegraph m 3 4Utai3 % off ic es.oi'xices. India has no concern with the iixation oi these charges, and lor this reason also the inforoiation should not be notified by this country. it is observed that tne reason lor which the Secretary of State, though recognising a slight anomaly in notiiication by the lovernment of rriuia (it appears to tne Government of Inuia to be v»hori.y anomalous^, desired tnat tnis course s^oald be adopted, was trie undesirability on polrtical grounds of permitting the auhesron ol Rulers or ^he xersian .i-ulf international conventions or allowing them to communicate direct with foreign powexs or international oooies; while no tii io o.tron could not oe ^ade oy luiperial Airways. ine possibility uowever of a notification oeing -iade by the Air ministry or oy the Britisii fost Or rice docs not appear to have been considered, and the Government ox j-ndia axe qj. tue opinion that as His majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom are much more closely connected with ti-e es^ablisnment and \»oxKxng of the Shargali station, tne necessary communication to the Herne bureau should be mane oy them. It is understood that similar action has been taken in other cases in respect of wireless stations with which the Air ministry is concerned xn various parts of tne World. Incidentally the procedure suggested would regulai'ise, the use of the existing call-sign 1 G F 0 * since it is desirable tnat call-signs be chosen from those allotted to tae controlling administration. 4 . Por these reasons it is suggested action oe taken oy the Air in is try or the Britisn Post office. me Government oi India regret they are unable to ao so. I have the honour to be, Offg. foreign Secretary to tne Government of Inuh.ti/ E.&amp; 0. 4447/33. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 22nd June 1933. Dated 19th May 1933 and enclosure. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that the Air Ministry have recently established a receiving and transmitting wireless telegraphy set working on 900 m. long wave and 45 m. short wave at Shargah, which is 7 miles north of Dabai, on the Arabian Coast, for air service purposes. The installation which is operated by Imperial Airways Limited was owing to misunderstanding on their part recently made available also for the reception and transmission of public messages. After inter-departmental consideration with which the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf was associated during his recent leave, it was decided that, subject to the consent of the Sheikh of Shargah, the station, which pending the formal consent of the Sheikh continues to operate as a public station, shall be established permanently for the reception and transmission of public radio messages and shall be notified to the International Bureau of the Telegraph Union at Berne for registration as a public station. A copy is enclosed, for the information of the Imperial Communications Sub-Committee of the C.I.D., of a letter which has been sent to the Government of India asking them to take the necessary preliminary steps to give effect to these decisions. I am, &amp;c•, (Sgd.) C.H. SILVER The Secretary, Imperial Communications Sub-Committee, Committee of Imperial Defence, 2, Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1. Vv&gt; &gt;station at Shaj^gah, I am commanded 'by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to suggest for the consideration of the Secretary of State for India in Council, that the Imperial Communications Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence should he informed of the action in the matter. Copies of this letter have been sent to the Foreign Office and Air Ministry. The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.V/.I.' Dear Mr, AIR MINISTRY. &lt;• - &gt; * &lt; ? 3 ADASTRAL HOUSE. KINGSWAY. W.C.2. 10th May, 1933. /S Y. Laithwalte, i With reference to your letter, addressed to Flight Lieutenant Duncan, and dated 9th May, 1933, in which you request details of the wireless station at oharjah, I enclose a schedule which gives all the informaticn which the Government of India will require for the registra tion of the station. Flight Lieutenant Duncan is abroad and we do not expect him back before the end of the month. Yours faithfully. J.G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.C4-9J Register No. P.Z SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. letter Telegram from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. To Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee (. /o-r. d / Under Secretary Secretary of State.... SUBJECT. Arab Air ifoute . Sharjah . (a) IMauthorised opening of public wireless station by Imperial Airways ana action to be taken; (b) Ine Sbargab. beacn pyjama incident. r /J i k Copy ^ to •j j r . FOB USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Alnute commenting. Draft letter to the Government of India (repeated Bushire) covering instructions on (a). 15 mAK 1935 Previous Papers :■Minute Paper. political Department. 1212 5CP0 9.32 Our agreement with the 3heikh oi Shargah for the establishment of a.n air station at Shargah is flagged, on P.Z.4664^As will he seen, no specific mention is made in it of the erection of a wireless telegraph station even for merely air purposes. Colonel Powle, in paragraph 8 of his aespatch of Jth August 1932, on P.Z.49?9/32, comnented on this, ana recoraed conversations between Colonel Dickson ana the Sheikh which seemed aaequately to cover the point so far as | communication between the air station and aircraft on air purposes was concerned. 2. Prom Colonel Powle's despatch of the 9th March, on P.Z.ltfif?/33, it will be seen that Airways, without consultation with the political authorities or with the Sheikh, subsequently opened a public wireless station at Shargah f and notified that messages might be transmitted through it both in Shargah and in Dibai, with the result that a formal protest was received from the Sheikh. On the matter being taken up with the Air Ministry here it appeared that there had been considerable correspondence on the natter between the Civil Aviation Branch of the Air Ministry and Airways, who had represented that the opening of the station was at the request of the local sheikh. If this is in fact correct it was no doubt based on some quite casual and polite remark by the Sheikh to which definite effect was not intended to be given. The incident has resulted in a general overhaul of the question of air procedure in regard to stations on the Arab Air Route, the I outcome of which will be submitted for consideration separately in a few days. i 3/2. 3. Advantage has been taken of Colonel Powle's presence here to go into the shargah incident, with the result shown in my d.o. letter to Plight Lieut. Duncan of the Air Ministry of the 20th April, No. P.Z.2266/33. The provisional conclusions of that letter were confirmed at an interdepartmental meeting the Poreign Office and at the Air Ministry, attended hy/Colonel Powle, on 25th April, and we are now in a position to issue instructions to the Resident. A draft is attached. 4. In connection with Shargah, reference may h made to the Political Resident's despatch of 5th April, on P.Z.2515/33, reporting the teach pyjama incident. The correspondence speaks for itself. It is obviously quite undesirable that European laaies should wander about Shargah in beach pyjamas and it is to be hoped that the Resident's letter to the Sheikh of 30th torch and his representations to Imperial Airways will secure that passengers shall not be allowed to enter the town. This is incidentally desirable from quite another point of view, for it will help us to keep a check on the activities of concession hunters, etc. We have just heard that the Iraq Petroleum Company have applied for visas for the Trucial Coast for a representative and, while these have been refused,communication between passing passengers and the Sheikh such as appears to have been taking place since the opening of the air station would obviously make it much more difficult for us to exercise the control which we desire. O', &lt; /7T ■0* if / Draft Paper. ( ' » ft Pc ' JK* (*n) &gt; (ffifi \^ z^. fh IRAFT jLETTER , Air Mail. Department. 19 MAY 1955 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to the Government of India’s express letter, No.D.1131-N/33, of 24th March and connected correspondence on the subject of the action of Imperial Airways in opening a public wireless telegraphy station at Shargah, which was reported in Bushire letter of 9th March 1933, No.C.65. 2. Enquiry of the Air Ministry showed that the action in question had been taken under the apparently erroneous ) impression that it was in response to tis ( wishes of the Sheikh. Advantage has been taken of Colonel Fowle’s recent visit to this country to discuss the whole question in detail. The results of the discussion in question are embodied in the demi-official letter from the India Office to the Air Ministry, No.P.Z.2266/33, dated 20th April, of which a copy is now enclosed, the provisional conclusions recorded in which were subsequently confirmed at an interdepartmental meeting attended , 7-rw A. by the-Resid«ttt. 3. I am to ask that if no objection 1712a 5000 3.3:1 isis seen^the Resident may now be instructed to take steps to give effect to the conclusions in question. On a minor but important point I am to say that it will, of course, be ( necessary that the public station at Sharg^^should^be^ notified to the The Secretary of State recognises that it isperhaps slightly arnmalous that steps for such notification should be taken through the Government of India. On the other hand, the undesirability on political grounds of permitting the adhesion of the Rulers of the Persian Gulf to international conventions or of allowing them to communicate direct with foreign powers or international bodies is generally accepted. A notification cannot be made by Imperial Airways and in all the circumstances the most satisfactory course appears to be that it should be made through the Government of India, as in the similar case of the Gwadur wireless station (see correspondence * ending with the letter from the Industries and Labour Department of 26th May 1932, No.W.l). The Secretary of State trusts that having regard to the special circumstances they will see no objection to taking the necessary steps. In anticipation of their concurrenceDepartment — concurrence he is taking steps to obtain from the Air Ministry, for transmission to them as soon as possible, precise details of the entries to be made under the various columns in the International List of Fixed and Land Stations and he will be glad to receive a copy of any communication addressed by the Government of India on the subject to the ^fHbv^rsal Fe-ybal Uniun. 4. Copies of this letter are being jsent to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. J. c. WAU'OA.P.2.2515/33. INDIA OFFICE, .VHITSHALL, 1. 9th M y 1933. Daar Duncan, I write with reference to our previous discussion on the subject of the regularisation of the public wireless station at jhargah to say that we shall shortly he addressing the Govenment of Inula on the question, suggesting to them that registration should he undertaken by then*. I understand that they will require precise details of the station as in the form of whicn I enclose a copy. Will you he so kina as to obtain tnase ana let me have them as early as conveniently possible? Yours sincerely, J.G. LAJTHWAITE• Plight Lieutenant w.A. Duncan, Air Ministry. yUiastral House, Kingsway, w.c.a.r 1/ P.Z.2266/33. iI ndia office, WHIHEHALL, S.W.l 22nd April, 1933. JL® ^ ii. Dear Duncan, In paragraph 1 of my letter to you No.P.Z.2266/33 of 20th April, I referred to the date of the next Air Route meeting as Wednesday, 26th April. this is, of course, a mistake for Tuesday, 25th April. I take the opportunity to refer to one point which was not touched on in my letter of 20th April. The Resident mentioned at our meeting that there was some risk that the Sheikh might expect an addition to his subsidy in return for the grant of permission to establish a public wireless station. «'/e gathered that while Airv/ays, if they operate the station, will be prepared to carry the Sheikh 1 s official messages free 01 charge, there could be no question of payment of any special additional subsidy to him. If this is correct and he does put forward such a suggestion the answer must presumably be that we are not prepared to make any additional payment m respect of the opening of the public station and that if the Sheikh insists on it we shall have no option but to close the public station down. I am sending copies of this letter to Bertram, Blaxter and Warner of the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely, (SD.) J.G.LAITHWAlTE. Flight Lieutenant V/.A.Duncan, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kings way, W.C.2r - ■ p.zT^ 2266 1 1933 political Department. * IV LETTER . 2 0 APR 1955 Plight Lieut. W.A.. Duncan, Air Ministry, AcLastr&amp;l House, Kingsway, W.G.2. '^U gp I'TIER iNCLOSURE IN WnEKlY No 17 2?APft 1333 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL and ftFO RET DEPT. INDIA OFFIOE SENT ST Am MMN 0 °^ i- 1401 5000 i:.32 Dear Duncan, I write to put on record that the position in regard to the Ghargah wireless station was informally discussed on the 19th April at a meeting atfwfiich the Political Resident and representatives of the Foreign Office and Offioft were present and which you kindly attended. Provisional conclusions were reached as to the hestnethoas of dealing with this problem and it was agreed that I should put them on record in a letter to you and that they should he brought up for consideration at the Air Route meeting which has been fixed for Wednesday, 26th April, in JSheImerdine's room. 2. It was agreed in the firstplacey frftgrt in the light of the information ! . tzr which you gave us the proposal that this question should be referred to the Imperial Communications Committee should be let drop am tnat tejsSoula A* IAJLkJI AAA. f-A. tic K tlcAX^y , be poos-ib-le to secureCits expeditious iisposal in the ordinary way. 3. As ^.t was rridde clear at the Meeting at Gwyayr House on the 3rd April, wa her^ see no objection to the/■■HI the maintemnce of a public wireless station at Shargah (and, indeed, some possible advantage) so long as it is placed on a regular basis and the Sheikh’s consent obtained. On general grounds we are, however, definitely inclined to think that there is much to be saia for the i concentration of responsibility for public wireless arrangements in the Gulf under I. &amp; I.G. and if possible we should have preferred that responsibility for the Shargah station should be taken over by them. I understand from you, however, that this could not be done save at the cost of a subsidy which the Air Ministry are ruturally very reluctant to have to pay and furtner that, while it may be anomalous that Imperial Airways should be responsible for running a private station, there is no objection of principle to their doing so if/circumstances seem to make this desirable. 4. After discussion the general sense of the meeting was that it was desirable to retain a public station at Shargah, subject to the Sheikh’s consent being obtained and to the necessary steps being taken (through the Government of India) to notify its existence to Berne; that in principle there seemed to be strong arguments in favour of the concentration under I.&amp; I.C. of 7 r Draftr Draft Paper. Department. r tut that in the circumstances hescrihed a.hove it would he test tha at any rate for the present responsibility for operating the Shargah station should rest with Imperial Airways, the question of the transfer of responsibility to the Communications Company being reserved for consideration if at some future date receipts became sufficiently substantial to make it possible for the Communications Company to take over the station without the assistance of a Government subsidy; ana finally, that while Airways, in these circumstances, should operate the station it woula be desirable that the concession to be granted by the Sheikh for its maintenance ^iould be granted to H.M.G., Airways being appointed^as the*Agent -nf If this view is accepted by next Tuesday’s meeting we will write to the Government of India as regards the notification of the station to jBeme and will also arrange for the iaespatch of the necessary instructions to the Gulf as to the reply to be maae to the Sheikh of Shargah* s protest and the concession to be obtained from him for the retention of a public station. —5. On a connected point you were gooa enougn to say that you woula make enquiries of Imperial Airways as to the presort position in regard to the acceptance of public traffic at the Gwadur wireless station, i 6. I am sending copies of this letter to Warner, Bertram and Blaxter. J. Q. LA1THWA1TE.-'j - | ,'^.lr ' \ QOV Foreign and Poll INDIA. rt ment. pK-’S?; ^ ioa t 5 Ll^gl^tAIR r/ L | [N.B. -This is an ORIGINAL message sent, by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, -with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. D. 1131-U/33. Dated New Delhi ,the March 19 ZZ* The Secretary of state for India, London. b &lt; Reference ^ Bushire letter of 9th March 1933, No. C.65 of 1933, copy of which was sent to you direct. Opening of Public w/T Station at Shargah. 2. We agree with Political Resident and recomriend that action be taken as suggested in paragraph 4 of his letter. 1 V THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS KEEN AUTHORISED. w,% for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. &amp; Au (Designation)Minute Paper. Sf) v political Department. The Shurgah wireless inciaent was discussed at an interdepartmental meeting at the i^ir Linistry on 3ra April. It was agreed that the general question should he referred to the Comnuni cat ions 3uh-Committee of the C.I.D. with a view to ascertaining whether it would not he possible to coordinate all wireless arrangements in the Gulf under the Communications Company, hut that pending this reference and in the interests of convenience the public station regularly operated by Imperial Airways should he allowed to remain in being. It was further agreed that this natter should he dealt with urgently in the interests of giving a reply to the Sheikh's protests.Extract from Private and Personal Air Mail Letter from Mr. Laithwaite to Colonel Fowle, dated 31st March 1933. We have jurt had your despatch about the Shargah wireless station* I need not say that neither we nor uhe Foreign Office have ever been consulted by the Air Ministry about the proposal to establish a public wireless station there and we entirely share your views about it. Arising out of the Bahrain Air Agreement and the renewed request for facilities at Gwadur and Bahrain by the Dutch, etc., we are now inclined, particularly in view of the wireless station incident at Shargah, to wonder whether we should not do better to adopt a rather different procedure as regards civil air arrangements in the Gulf generally. We are, of course, anxious to help Imperial Airways as much as we can and to secure that the air route shall run without any hitch or disturbance. On the other hand, we have in the first place to look after the interests of our various sheikhlyjclients in the Gulf, and secondly to endeavour to secure that no complications arise with any foreign government consequent on any incident between their air lines and Imperial Airways in respect of the use of aerodromes etc. Finally, our policy being to keep this area closed except to Airways and the one or two regular foreign lines who may bejgranted permission to use the same facilities and to exclude the private flyer so much as possible, we shall have to make provision to deal with that matter. For there is probably little doubt that the unauthorised private flyer will before very long try to fly down the Arab coast and jump facilities in the various places/places at which they exist and this we want to he in a position to deal with. In these circumstances what we are rather thinking of is the drawing up of sealed pattern regulations to govern the landing of aircraft of any kind in Koweit, Bahrain and Muscat, these regulations to be made by the Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrain and by the Sultan of Muscat, to be quite general in character and, so far as possible, to cover all the political aspects. 2.g«» they would include a prohibition against the landing in the States in question of private flyers and prescribe the penalty (shall we say confiscation of aircraft?) to be imposed on aircraft so landing. In addition, such regulations could cover such matters as customs, passports, quarantine, police, etc. Within the terms of such regulations it^would be possible to appoint Airways (subject, of course,/a fee to the Ruler in respect of the use of the aerodrome and a composition possibly of the nature suggested by you in respect of customs and other dues) as managers of the aerodrome on behalf of the Sheikh, the understanding being that Airways would have no freedom whatever to take any steps outside the strict terms oftheir licence save with the approval of the local ruler, obtained through the Political Agent or the Political Resident as the case migjit be. If something on these lines (we propose to discuss it. with the Air Ministry next Monday) should prove possible, it would in practice entirely alter the character of the agreement to be negotiated with Airways in respect of Bahrain etc. The agreement could be very much snorter and would, of course, be rather different in scope. Secondly, it would, we think, reduce the risk of incidents such as the/A / r the Shargah wireless incident. Thirdly (and to this we in the India Office attach considerable importance) it would keep Airways out of politics and would ensure tnat the real responsibility lay between the political authorities in the Gulf and the local rulers. We should be much interested to hear what you think of action rather on these lines when you come home. I ought perhaps to add that it would of course be open to Airways under such a procedure to make charges on the Dutch etc.for the use of facilities such as oil, petrol, water, air, mechanics* services, etc. The landing fees to be paid by foreign aircraft using the aerodromes and their disposal could, if necessary, be prescribed in the general regulations and I am not sure that this would not be the better course. In this connection I have been trying to find out what exactly the present arrangements are at Gwadur in respect of payment to the Sultan for the use of his aerodrome there. All the air arrangements in the Gulf grew up in ratner a casual way and the present seems a good opportunity to try and get them straightened out and to apply the *ame principles in respect of all stations. If, as the Air Ministry understand is the case, Airways pay no rent in respect of Gwadur aerodrome to the Sultan, I am inclined to think tha^ we might very well alter this and subject them oo rather the same type of conditions as we contemplate in respect of the aerodrome at Bahrain.31st March, 1933. Dear Laithwaite, Reference your letter, P.Z.1657/33 of to-day's date, Burkett has already spoken to you on the question of the public wireless station at Shargah, and there is no need for me to say anything further on that sublect in this letter. With reference to the other points you raise, I will deal with them in the order mentioned in your letter: - (a) Bahrein. The actual information we have had with regard to the lease at present held by the R.A.P. came from the India Office , your reference P.Z.1460/33, dated 15th March, 1933. I am afraid there is nothing I can add to the information contained therein, reference to which will no doubt answer your enquiry. (b ) Wireless facilities at present available. Imperial Airways at present use a pack set loaned by the R.A.P. free of charge. With regard to the proposals of Imperial &amp; International Communications Ltd., no definite conclusion has been reached since the meeting held June last year, but the suggestion is that the Air Ministry shall pay Imperial &amp; International Communications Ltd. an appropriate sum for the modernisation of their equipment in order to adapt for working with aircraft._ It is also proposed to pay to Imperial 8c sum per annum J.G. Laithwaite Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. in it • tsll ttiXwXcixva XU Xo ct X o \J o vi U O J International Communications Ltd. an agreed In return for making the service /availableavailable for aircraft. I hope that this matter will be settled shortly. At the present moment, we are in negotiation with Imperial Airways with regard to the company's contribution towards the cost of adapting the equipment. (c) There is no formal lease in respect of our use of Gwadar. Ihe Sultan agreed to its use and to its extension, and there the matter has ended so far as we are concerned. No rent is paid for it. You are correct in your understanding that the wireless facilities there available are at present solely in connection with the working of the air route and that there is no public station. The Government of India have, however, recently proposed that the station should be open for public traffic, and this aspect of the question is still under consideration. As Rendelhas a copy of your letter under reply, I am also sending him a copy of this letter. Yours sincerely.1 3 INDIA OPPICS, aHIT-ilALL, 3.W. 1. P.2.1657/53. 31st March 1933. Dear iielmeralne. Not vlshia^ to bother you on a point oX detail I have asked your private secretary If he would be so kinfl as to let us know what the real position Is as regards the approval stated In the correspondence forwarded under the iolltlcai Hesident’s despatch No.0.66 of 9th March, of which copies were sent to the Air ministry for Inions. tion under our printed letter Mo. P.2.1657/33 of 27th inarch to have bean given by the Air Ministry to the establishment by Airways of a public wireless station at aharg&amp;h, as we are anxious if possible to discuss this point with you at the meeting next ttonday. Partly In connection with this question and partly In connection with the general question of future civil air arrangements on the arab air aoute, which I mentioned to you on the telephone, we should be most grutexul 11 the Air Ministry could let us have some Lt.Col. P.C. .jht-liaerulne, C.!.£., O.B.S., Air ministry, Dwyoyr House. Whitehall, 3.S. 1. further/urtner inroruution on Uie follo«inu points - ^gain jf it, can be done without great inconvenience in tiae for Monday 1 s meeting* (a) Bahrain* Particulars of the le *.sq at present held by the R.A.F.,*ad of the aerodrome there -nd of its terms; (b) Particulars of the wireless facilities at present available and used by the R*A*F. ana by Imperial Airways at Bahrein and oi the financial and other terms governing their use* We had a meeting at the Air ministry at which Bertram presided on 24th June of last year, at which arrangements for wireless facilities at ^ahr&amp;in in connection with the air route were discussed. It was then understood that Imperial and International Coixunications Ltd* would submit certain proposals vhich we understood would be the subject of further Interdepartmental discussion before any decision was taken, but we have heard nothing since and do not know how the mutter stands* (c)/A (6f (c) particulars of tne nature of tne lease In —~ respect of Gwadur. 3o far as I can gather from our papers, no rent is at present paid to tae iultan in respect of the Gwadur landing ground. The wireless facilities there available appear to be solely in connection with the working of tne air route and there is no public station. Could you confirm that tnis is the case ana let us know here, as in tne case of Bahrain, what financial or other terms are attached to the use of the station We should be most grateful for any assistance you could give us on these points. I am sending a copy of this letter to Rendel. Yours sincerely. J.G. LAITHV/AITE.9619/AF/VA3. 3 IK - 3H ARGAH CIRCUIT . Dear ,'jarrington-MorriSr Further to our telephone conversation of yesterday afternoon, see my letter to the Imperial &amp; International Communications Ltd. I don’t think you need take up this natter further. IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIU TED. AIRWAY TSRLINU3, VICTORIA STATION, S.W. 1. 8th Larch 1933. Yours, etc. (Sd.) A. FLETCHER. Wing Commander .i.D.7/arrington-Lorris, J .Li.C •, 0 • . E., Signals Branch, air Ministry, Adastral House, King sway, ,V. C.2.The Gen (Co Imper Co,* COPY. 9617/AP/VAS 7th March 1933. ^ 3jUiI^IN-3HAHGAH C I RCUIT . Dear Sirs, Further to the writer's conversation with your Lr. Kschhacher to-day, it appears that your representatives at Bahrein have not been informed of the arrangements re the transmission of commercial messages from shargah as set out in this office letter 9135 of the 4th January; neither have your people in India and Iraq and elsewhere been informed that my Company's station at Shargah is open to accept commercial traffic. This is a result, I believe, of your not being specifically informed that the service had been commenced in accordance with our letter of the 13th January, No.9204. If you will take steps to adjust these two points the service should proceed without any further trouble. Yours faithfully, For and on behalf of IIPK^L ALWAYS LIMITSD The General Manager (Communications), Imperial &amp; International Ground Services Manager Communications Ltd., A. Fletcher. Blectra House, Ivborgate. i •«IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD., AIRS'/AY TERI'ilNUC, Victoria Station. S.W.l. 28th February, 1933. Sir, I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.218428/32/Signals dated 24th February, and to attach copy of my letter to our representatives in the ear East, which I hope will adjust the matter. I am, etc., Sd. A Fletcher. Ground Services Manager. The Secretary, Air Minist iistry, Adastral House, Kingsway f W.C.2.LOUDON OFFICE. Manager No.2. Operating Division. 9564/AF/VAX. 28th February, 1933. Attached copy of letter has been received from the Signals Branch of the Air Ministry. I cannot understand why ourW/ T Station at Bahrein is receiving this commercial traffic, unless it is through Shargah calling him direct. I cannot see also, how the Imperial and International Communications Companiy ard at any loss. However, these messages must be transmitted to the commercial station at Bahrein. Will you please issue the necessary instructions.218428/32/Signals 24th February 1933 Gentlemen, With further reference to your letter 8879/AF/VAS, dated 15th November 1932, I am directed to inform you it is understood from Messrs.Imperial and International Communications that commercial traffic handled at Sharjah is being transmitted to the aerodrome W/T station at Bahrein. It was not intended when giving covering sanction in Air Ministry letter of even number, dated 3rd January 1933 that traffic should be passed to the station operated by your Company and I am to request that you will cable instructions to your local representative to route such traffic in all cases to the Imperial and International Communications station at Bahrein. I am, &amp;c., (Sgd.) *■ Head of Signals. Imperial Airways Ltd., Airway Terminus, Victoria Station (Continental Departures), S. W. 1.218482/32/D.D.C.A 3rd January 1933 ? Gentlemen, I am commanded by the Air Council to acknowledge the receipt of your letterof 13th ultimo, 9121/AF/VAS, forwarding a copy of a letter dated 12 th December from the General Manager of Imperial and International Communications. I am to inform you that the Council, without prejudice to the general question of the propriety of a ? certain share of these and similar receipts enu rin g to public funds, have no objection to the charges to be made to the public for the transmission of public telegraphic messages handed in at the Wireless Station at Sharjah. I am, &amp;c«, - (Sgd.) S. DANNREUTHER. &gt; Imperial Airways Limited, Airway Terminus, Victoria Station, (Continental Departures), S. W. 1.IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED, AIRWAY TERMINUS, VICTORIA STATION, (CONTINENTAL DEPARTURES), LONDON, S.W.l. g]_ 2 ]_/^p/VAS # 13th Decemher 193S» W/T COMMUNICATIONS AT SHAROAH. Sir, I am directed to rel'er to your letter No*218248/32/ D.D.C.A., dated 8 th instant, and to forward herewith copy of letter dated 12th instant received from Imperial &amp; International Communications Limited* It will he seen that the Imperial &amp; International Communications Company suggest a charge of 60 centimes (gold) to he divided equally between the two Companies. At the present rate of exchange this would bring approximately 4d* per word to my Company, and is in keeping with the proposed aircraft charge as laid down in Air Ministry letter No*124278/31/S*6*, dated 16th September 1931* It is admitted that this sum was assessed specifically for the transmission of messages from The Secretary, aircrait,/ Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, W. C. 2.qD aircraft, 'but I would point out that although the wireless plant at Shargah is Air Ministry property, my Company are responsible for its maintenance and operation, the latter involving the permanent employment of a skilled W/T Operator, and the part time employment of a skilled engineer to maintain the generating plant. Finally, I am to request an early decision on this matter, as it is desired to afford the inhabitants of Shargah and Dabai these communication facilities as early as possible. I am. Sec •, (Sgd.) A. FLETCHER. Ground Services Manager. - i i The Secretary, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, W.C. 2.r COPY OP LETTER PROM IMPERIAL &amp; INTERNATIONAL COMMUNICATIONS LTD. 9095/AF/VAS, of the 9th instant, and to inform you that the charges for telegrams exchanged with Shargah will he those in for the wireless transmission between Bahrein and Shargah. We would suggest that the latter mi^it he fixed at 60 centimes (gold) to he divided equally between Imperial Airways and ourselves, so that the total rate between Shargah and the United Kingdom, for instance, would he as follows:- shall he pleased to supply you with a full list of rates on that basis to all parts of the world. GMC/PE/26/B2. 12th December 1932* Dear Sirs BAHREIN - SHARGAH CIRCUIT We beg to acknowledge the receipt of your letter operation with Bahrein, increased by an amount to be fixed Imperial Airways I.&amp; I.G. Bahrein to U.K. F. cts. .30 .30 2.60 2.90 TOTAL RATE: : :Fr.3.20 (gold). If this suggestion meets with your approval, we Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) General Manager (Communications).218428/32/D.D.C.A 8th December 1932 Gentlemen, I am commanded by the Air Council to refer to your letter dated 15th November 1932, 8879/AF/VAS, with enclosures, in which you enquire whether they would have any objection to the wireless station at Sharjah being used for the transmission and reception of public telegraphic messages as occasion may require* I am to state, in reply, that the Council will raise no objection to this proposal provided that the volume of public messages handled is not such as to interfere with the normal working of the station for the purposes of the England-India air route* The Council will be glad to be informed as soon as possible on what basis charges are to be made for the transmission and reception of public telegrams at Sharjah in order that consideration may be given to this aspect of the matter. I am, &amp;c.. (Sgd.) C.R. BRIGSTOCKE* Imperial Airways Limited, Airway Terminus, Victoria Station, (Continental Departures), S. W. 1*IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED, AIRWAY TERMINUS, VICTORIA STATION, (CONTINENTAL DEPARTURES), LONDON, S.W.l. 8933/AP/VAS, 22nd November 1932. WIRELESS COMMUNICATION AT SHARGAH STATION. Sir, I am directed to refer to this Office letter No.8879/AP/VAS, dated 15th November, subject as above, and to enquire whether an answer may shortly be expected, as the matter is of some moment to the people of Shargah. I am, &amp;c•, (Sgd.) A. FLETCHER. Ground Services Manager. The Secretary, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, W. C. 2.IIT-MAI, AIRWAYS LILITED , AIRWAYS TERMINUS Victoria Station, 8d/ 9/AFAAS LONDai, S.W. 1 15th November, 1932. Sir, I am directed to invite your attention to the attached letters which have passed between the Imperial and International Communications Company and my Company regarding the employment of the W/T installation at Sharjah for the reception and transmission of public radio messages. As is doubtless known, there is no means of wireless or telegraphic communication between Sharjah and the outside world, except the aircraft installation operated by my Company at that place, and ordinarily public messages are held for the fortni^itly visit of the B.I. steamer which then transmits them to Bahrein and Karachi as necessary. Before submitting the matter to the Air Council the opinion of the Imperial and International Communications The Secretary, Air Ministry Adastral Souse, Kingsway, Y/.C.2 Company/0$ Company has been taken, and it will be seen from their letter (M3/Ct/B2 dated 11th November, that they are in agreement with the proposals. I am therefore to enquire whether the Air Council will give their early approval to the scheme suggested, and if so outline generally the conditions under which the service may be operated. I am, etc. For and on behalf of IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED. (SD.) A FLETCHER. Ground Service Manager.mam mm c8823/AI'AAS 7th November, 1932. Dear Sirs, As you doubtless know, the Air Ministry have established a receiving and transmitting W/T set working on 900 m. long wave and 45 m. short wave, at SHAHG-AH, which is 7 miles North of DABAI, on the Arabian Coast, for air service purposes, and we have received applications from the local sheikh to receive and transmit public messages. It appears that at present all public messages are held for the arrival ofthe B.I. steamer which calls at DABAI fortnightly, when messages are relayed to KARACHI for the East, and BAHREIN for Western traffic. With the establishment of this plant at SHARGAH, and having a certificated Company Operator always available, I am to enquire whether you have any objection to my Company receiving and despatching messages as necessary, as is done with the mail steamer, i.e.we will receive from and transmit to your station at BAHREIN all traffic to and from SHARGAH. Before/(?0N * A/ , W w Before putting this proposal to the Air Ministry we would appreciate your views on the matter. Yours faithfully For and on behalf of IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED. Ground Services Manager A.Fletcher. The General Manager &amp; Secretary, . , . n T , , Imperial &amp; International Communications Co.Ltd., Electra House, Moorgate, E.C.2COPY OP LETTER PROM IMPERIAL &amp; INTERNATIONAL COMMUNICATIONS LTD • GMC/Ct/B2 Hth November, 1932. Dear Sir, BAHREIN -SHARGAH CIRCUIT We acknowledge receipt of your letter No.882^/AF/VAS of the 7th instant concerning the establishment by the Air Ministry of a receiving and transmiuting wireless set at ShargaJh. We are in agreement with your suggestion to exchange public telegrams betv/een Shargah ana our S Lation at Bahrein ard will take the necessary steps in connection with the preparation of tariffs and working when the proposal has been agreed with the Air Ministry and await your further communication on the subject. Yours truly, (SD.) L.HOWITT CONTROLLER OF TELEGRAPH SERVICES.m fc- v . CONFl DENTIAL . No. C-65 of 1933 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to ii.M’e. Secretory of State for Inciis, London, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of tfm undermentioned docu- Name and Date. Subject. Letter No. C-65, oatec 9th Opening of Public W/T March 1933 to the Ooverrnnert Station at Shar^th. of Indio.1657 ! No. C -66 of 1933. f Off ide of the Political Peslcent i}\ tjie*'Pe*-*ian dhlf. H.M.S. 'BIDEFORL*. 9tn inarch 1933. From To The Hon’ble Lieut-Col. ^.C.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Hepicent in the Persian Oulf. ^he Foreign Secretary to the Govei nnc nt of Inaia, New reini. OPENING OF PUBLIC W/T. STATION AT SHABftAH. Sir, I he.ve the honour to enclose nerev/ith copies Letter No. C-c3 # catea kbth. February 1933,) oi the corresponoence from the Political Agent, Bahrain, V;ith } noted in tne margin, enclosuiee. J which explains itself. The Shaikh having complained that a Public station had been opened at Shargah without hie knowleoge, I hac asked the Political Agent, Bahrain, to enquire Into the matter. 2 . On y visit to Shargah yesterday the Shaikh appicached me on the subject. Hit attitude was reasonable. He has no oojection in principle to the opening of the W/T station, in fact he agrees that it woulo be a convenience for his people, but he feels indignant that this should have been done without reference to himself, and - though ne will permit the office to continue working as a temporary measure - he insists that a proper written agreement should be made between himself anc Aessrs Imperial Airways. I entirely agree with the Fhaikh. The installation of wireless telegraphy at Shargah, even for communication withI with the aeroplanes of the Company only, was not epecif- - tally coverec by the Agreement with the Shaikh of 2£nci July 193/ ( vice pragraph S of my letter No. 509-^, catec 9th August 1932 ); still less the opening of a public fc/T station. Shargah belongs to the Shaikh, not to us anc Imperial Airways have no right whatever to establish such a station wihout the Shaikh’s per* -mission obtained through the proper official authority: the Political Resident. 3. An unfortunate eflect has been prooucea in fhargah by the action of the Company, which, according to the memorandum of 20th February from the Station Superintendent, Imperial Airways, Shargah, to the Political Agent, Banrain, appeals to have had the sanction of the Air Ministry. I hear that some mal- - contents have taken the opportunity to irritate the Shaikh by pointing out that the opening of the W/T station without his permicrion is a high-handed act which was only to be expected once ne had allowed the British to ectablirn an sir port in nia territory. This is precisely the impression which it ie most desir- -&amp;ble to cvcic, both as regards Shargah itself, ano as regards the rest of the Arabian Coast, where we may want further facilities in the future, and where in any case the spread of suen ideas is to be deplored. 4 . In conclusion I would be gra Ministry arid Messrs. Imperial Airways of the situation, and advised to enter with the Snaikh of Shargah, through me station which the latter require. teful if the Air could be informed into negotiations public , for 'the/W/TCopy of letter No. C-83, oatea £bth February 1933, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Hon'ble the Political Kesibent in the Persian Gulf. -s- Sir, I have the honour to enclose a copy of the 1. No. C-67, dated 14-P-33, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Station Superintendent, Imperial Airways Station, Shargah. 2 . No. WJ/334, datea 20-P-33, from the Station Superintendent, Imperial Airwaye Station, Shargah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. marginally noted memoranda regarding the opening of the Imperial Airways Mreleee Station at Shargah to commercial traffic through Bahrain. 2 . I enquired from the Officer in Charge, Imperial anc International Communications Company, Ltd., Bahrain, whether he knew of this arrangement. He krew that hie Company were negotiation# with the Imperial Airways Limited on tine subject, but ?/as awaiting orders from them. He understood that the matter war celayed pending forme.l action at Berne to have the Shargah tireless Station recognised internationally. In the meantime it seems that the Shargah Imperial Airways lireless sends commercial messages to the Imperial Airways kireless at Bahrain, which they pass on to the Imperial and International Communications Company, Ltd., who receive the messages as emanating from Banrain. Ofticially, they know nothing of the messages having been sent from Shargah oy the Imperial Airways tireless.C«py of Coni iaentifei anc Urgent fflemtrandum No. C-67, dated the 14tn February 1933, froro the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Station Superintendent, Imperial Airways Station, Sharjah. I underetanc that the Wireless Station of Imperial Airways, Limited, ^lt Sharjah was recently tnrown opne to public traffic, but that the Shaikh of Sharjah objected tc this having ceen cone cecauae he had not been consulted in the matter. 2. It ie requested that you will kindly let me know wnat happened, anu, if tne wireless station was actually thrown open t© public traffic, you will kindly furnish me with a copy of the orders authorising thisWith r el ere nee t® your meaioranc-uni lie. C/67 aateci 14th instant, ®n tne 27th ultiar® X receiveo C®py ®f oiein®ranQuin N®. WJ/334, aated 20th February 1933, frem the Station Superintendent, Imperial Airways, Limited, Sharjah, te the P®litical %gent, Bahrain. instructions from the Centre! Office at Cairo t© the effect that the wireless s tat ion was to be opened immediately for the acceptance ef commercial traffic; and accordingly the merchant* ef Sharjah ana Bibai herewith; and in a subsequent memorancum from Cairo, it ie stated that the Head Off ice of the Imperial and International Communications, Limited, T ondon, conclucec these atrangements with the Air Ministry some time age. were notified C®py of Cairo's instructions are attached</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002b6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/4116</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002b6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/4116</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 35/13 'Persian Gulf: public wireless telegraph station at Sharjah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-23T22:16:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (88 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 89; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the establishment of a wireless telegraph station at Sharjah.The file contains agreements with the ruler of Sharjah for the establishment of an air station by Imperial Airways, and correspondence related to the opening of a wireless telegraph station at Sharjah.The file is composed of correspondence between: the Foreign Office; the India Office; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Trenchard Craven William Fowle; the Secretary of State for India; Imperial Airways; the Air Ministry; the Admiralty; the ruler of Sharjah, Shaikh Sultan II bin Saqr Al Qasimi; the General Post Office; and Cable and Wireless Limited.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>General Post Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Airways</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Sharja</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Wireless telegraphy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Post offices</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0002b6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>