<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00033d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T14:24:14.910Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">[SS 6u&gt; r r [Confidential.] y- v^ Note on the feasibility of abolishing that part of the Inland Cvsioms Line which on the frontier of Bajputana (in- is eluding JBhaioalpur) and the Native States of Central India. This portion of the Inland Customs Line extends from the Indus to the Tapti passing round the Northern Frontier of Bhawalpur, then turning across the Satlaj southwards and hugging the boundary of British Territory till it reaches the Narhada. Crossing this, it turns to the west, and, direrging from the Narhada, reaches the Tapti at Burhanpur. The total length is about 1,200 miles. It cost in 1872-73 £105,728. The es- tablishment entertained on it consists of 8,578 officers and men. The main object of this Line is to pre vent salt, the produce of Native States, entering British Territory, unless it has paid a duty of Rs. 3 per maund. A subsidiary object is to tax all sugar exported across the Line at the rate of 1 Eupee per maund for refined sugar, and 6 annas per maund for unrefined saccharine produce. In the year 1872-73, about 30 lakhs of maunds of salt were imported across this portion of the Line paying duty exceeding £900,000. With the exception of nearly 7 lakhs of maunds, the produce of salt works in British Territory, but outside the Customs Line, the remainder of the salt imported was r from Rajputana. The 23 lakhs of maunds were from the following places:— Bhartpur Sambhar Didwana Pachbhadru 12 lakhs of mds. » }» » tt 1J 6 ' '( 2 ) The sugar duties on exports across this portion of the Line amounted to £142,000. These, it may be said, fell on the con sumers in the Native States outside the Customs Line. Thus the whole revenue was nearly £1,044,000, from which rather more than 10 per cent, must be deducted for cost of collection. It is evident that unless we are prepared to give up this large amount of revenue, we must either maintain the Customs Line, or resort to some other plan for securing the duty on the salt. I can imagine no other plan but one, namely, that of excis ing the salt at the places of its produc tion. But all the places above mentioned are situated in the three Native States of Bhartpur, Jaipur and Jodhpur, and there are many other places in Rajputana where salt is produced which would be imme diately imported into British Territory if the Customs Line were removed, unless the production was prohibited or the salt was excised at the same rate as at the places above mentioned. To carry out this measure would there fore require the consent of all the Native States in which salt can be produced, and would involve the taxation of all the sub jects of the Native States in Rajputana and Central India consuming such salt. It has hitherto been assumed,—and, per haps, correctly, though I am not aware that the matter has ever been carefully con sidered or reported on—that such measures as these have been from political and other causes practically impossible. The position of the British Government has re- centlv been much altered by our getting •/ hold of the Sambhar Lake, and will be still more improved when the Lake is connected by Railway with Agra and Dehli. When the Railways are com pleted, it is quite possible that only Sam-( 3 ) bbar salt will be imported from Rajputana into British Territory. During the last three years that the Lake lias been under British management, the average annual quantity of salt manu factured has been loj lakhs of maunds, after allowing a deduction of 10 per cent, for wastage. In ordinary years, when the rainfall is not excessively great so as to weaken the brine, which seldom happens, there is practically no limit to the quantity which might be manufac tured in a year if labor were available. Owing to the fact that the greater part of our charges, i, e., the rent of the Lake and the cost of establishment, are fixed, while the actual cost of manufacture is extreme ly small, the more salt we make, the less it costs per maund. With increased labor, or, what amounts to the same thing, in creased mechanical facilities for extracting the salt, we could easily make double the quantity hitherto manufactured. The salt would then cost about 44- annas per maund at Sambhar. The Railway charge to Agra should not exceed 4 annas per maund, and to Dehli very little more. At these prices Sambhar salt would en tirely command the market at Dehli and Agra, and even in Bajputana itself. The price might still further be reduced by our giving up, as under treaty we have a right to do, the Nawa-Godha works, and concentrating the manufacture on the south side of the Lake. This would bring down the cost of the salt at Sam bhar to about 2f annas per maund. At this price with the Railway in our hands, we could defy competition from Nawa and Godha. It is anticipated, even now, that Bhartpur salt, from its inferior quali ty and comparatively high price, although produced near the Line of Railway, will not be able to compete with Sambhar salt. Didwana and Pachbhadra, being far from the Railway and dependent on car riage by camels and Banjara cattle, could not come into competition.( 4 ) Under these circumstances, the various salt sources would yield a very small re venue to the Native States in which they are situated, and any negotiations on a liberal basis for excising the salt at the various places of production or closing the manufacture would be much faci litated. The British Government could afford to be liberal, for, as above stated, it would subject to taxation the whole of the con sumers in Hajputana and Central India, who at present pay us no taxes whatever except those on imported sugar. In fact, it could afford to give up the whole amount derived from this new taxation. It would not be just to put this taxa tion on the people of the Native States without relieving them at the same time from taxes which they at present pay. The unpopularity of such a measure would probably prove an insurmountable obstacle to its enforcement. A grand opportunity would be afforded of getting rid to a great extent of the transit duties, by which, to use the words of Sir Madhava Ilao, the trade of these Native States is now tied hand and foot. That Minister told me that he found it impos sible to propose any measure to abolish the transit duties in Holkar's Territory, unless he was prepared with some equi valent which would realise the same amount of revenue. I would propose to do that for the Native States which we have done for ourselves in British Terri tory, and which they cannot combine to do for themselves. The introduction of high salt duties in Madras, Bombay, the North-Western Provinces, and the Punjab was in each case accompanied by the abo lition of transit duties on innumerable articles, which duties formerly covered the face of the land as they do now in Native States. The policy pursued was to con centrate on one article of universal con sumption taxation which hampered the( 5 ) trade in almost every article of commerce. That policy has been most successful, finan cially, in British Territory ; and there is no reason to suppose that it will not be equal ly successful in Native States. It is a point that is generally lost sight of in dis cussing the question of high salt duties that they were imposed in lieu of a wide spread system of transit duties. It should be remembered that if we were to abolish the Customs Line, we should at the same time abolish the sugar duties which cost the people of these Native States more than £140,000 per annum. I be lieve that the introduction of duties on the single article of salt in lieu of the innumerable transit duties now collected in Native States would be a popular mea sure with both the rulers and the people, though it might be unpopular with the persons who are at present employed as tax-gatherers, and who, while they oppress the people, defraud the State, and are a heavy charge upon both. In introducing such measures as these, the Native States with whom we should first have to deal, would be those in whose limits salt is or can be produced. I have already mentioned Jodhpur, Jaipur and Bhartpur. There is in the Gwalior Terri tory much saline earth from which salt is made, but this salt, from its inferior quality, does not at present cross the Customs Line. At liatangarh in Bikanir salt is made. I understand that earth salts are manufactured in the Bhawalpur State, and there may be other States in Rajpu- tana capable of producing salt. I believe, however, that few, if any, of the States in Central India except Gwalior have salt, and that they are dependent for their supplies on Rajputana and Gujarat. The first step would be carefully to ascertain exactly in what localities salt is or can be produced, and at the same time approximately what revenue is derived by the Native States from their salt and( 6 ) from their transit duties. On these sub jects confidential reports could be ob tained through the Political Agents. As before observed, the connection between Sambhar and Agra and Dehli by Railway- will probably much reduce the value of all other salt works in Raj putana and Gwalior, and of the revenue derived from them. The Railway will also reduce the transit duties of the States through which it passes. When these effects have been accomplished, we shall be in a favorable position to make overtures to the States in which salt works exist or might be started. Without their co-operation, we cannot remove the Customs Line, except with great danger to our salt revenue. With their assistance it is possible that this might be done. At the principal salt sources, such as Pachbhadra, Didwana, Bhartpur and Dig, it would be necessary to surround each work with a cordon, and to allow no salt to pass out without the payment of duty. I do not advocate any other interference with the manufacture. The manufacture of salt in other places should either be entirely prohibited, or be restricted to the quantity necessary for purely local consumption, so that it should not assume the proportions of a trade to any distance. The amount to be paid annually to each of the Native States concerned would have to be determined, partly with reference to the population in them consuming the duty-paid salt, and partly with reference to the amount of transit duties which they would be asked to give up. No duty of any kind, except the Imperial duty, should be per mitted to be levied on salt. I may here remark that since our assumption of the Sambhar Lake, the Jaipur Darbar, besides receiving a large rent from us, has put a duty of one rupee per maund on all salt consumed in that State, being thus doub ly compensated for the loss of the Lake.( 7 ) This duty would have to be absorbed in the Imperial duty. The Salt works in British Territory out side the Customs Line, i. e., those in the Gurgaon and Rohtak Districts and in Ajmir, would be treated as those in Na tive States, that is, the excise duty would be taken before the salt left the works. If these measures were carried out, the Native States which possess no salt would be entirely at our mercy. Their people would be obliged to eat duty-paid salt. They would not be in a position to enforce any compensation for this extra taxation thrown on their people. But I think that it would be a wise as well as a generous policy to grant them some of the proceeds of the tax on the condition of their abo lishing at least an equivalent amount of transit duties. We could afford to do this, as the proceeds of the tax would be large, and it would be politic to do it, as it would convert an unpopular into a popular mea sure. It will be seen from the figures given in the beginning of this note that the sugar duties more than cover the cost of the Line which it is proposed to abolish, and that therefore Government would lose the differ ence. But the proposed measures would enable us to abolish that part of the Bombay Frontier Line which is maintained to prevent the import of Rajputana salts into that Presidency. I gather from paragraph 24 of Mr. Pedder's report, dated 22nd August 1870, on the Bombay Frontier arrangements, that the portion of Line referred to consists of three sections, the Marwar, Myhee Kanta and Rewa Kanta sections, aggregating 250 miles in length, and costing more than £ 1,800 per annum. The salt which is kept out by this Line,— for none comes across it paying duty and all other is prohibited,—is chiefly that produced at Pachbhadra and in the vicinity of the Luni Biver in Marwar. If the( 8 ) llajputana State Railway is continued from Ajmir to Disa, an impetus will be given to the manufacture of salt in this locality. The considerations which led to the assumption of the Sambhar Lake by the British Government in view of the Railway communication with the Lake, point to the advisability of our adopting a similar measure for the Pachbhadra salt works. With a Railway from Disa to Ajmir, and from Ajmir in one direction to Agra and Dehli and in another via Nimach to Indor and Khandwa, the Pachbhadra salt might prove a formidable rival, from its excellent quality, to Sambhar salt, when the two were thus brought into compe tition. Mr. Hume ascertained that the average price of Pachbhadra salt on the spot was 5 annas per maund, of which only 3| annas go to the manufacturer and 1 j anna to the Jodhpur State. The salt can therefore be manufactured at a cost of less than 3| annas per maund. This furnishes another argument for our keeping down the price of Sambhar salt, which can only be done by increasing the quantity manufactured. To recapitulate,—the measures which I venture to suggest are :— 1^.—That careful inquiries be made as to the situation and capa bilities of the different salt sources in the Native States outside our Customs Line, both those which now produce salt and those which are not now worked. 2nd. —That the amount of revenue derived by the Native States from their salt works be ascer tained. 3rd. —That as much information as possible should be collected as to the nature, rate, &amp;c., of( 9 ) the transit duties levied in the different Native States of Bha- walpur, Raj putana, and Central India, and the amount of reve nue obtained by each State from these transit duties. The above should be the subject of con fidential reports from the Political Agents. 4M.—That every effort be made to in crease the quantity and thus to reduce the price of salt manufactured at the Sambhar Lake, and, if possible, to concentrate the vrorks at the south side of the Lake. The contemplated tramway into the bed of the Lake will do much to effect this, and it may be worthwhile to import labor to Sam bhar when the Eailway is completed. The Railway freight charges on the salt taken from Sambhar should be reduced to a minimum. It might be even worthwhile to carry the salt at first at a loss to the Railway Depart ment, if thereby a larger gain was made by the Salt Depart ment, which could make up the deficiency to the Railway Department. hth. —That the effect of the Railway communication with Sambhar, and generally of the State Railways in Raj putana, on the different salt manufacto ries and on the Native transit duties be watched and report ed on. §th. —That when the above information has been obtained, and the Railway communication, and other works connected with( 10 ) the Sambbar manufactures be carried out, negotiations be entered into with the Native States in whose limits salt is or can be produced with the following objects:— (a), to allow us to put a cordon round all works where salt is per mitted to be produced to any large extent, and to excise such salt at a rate not exceeding Ks. 3 per maund before it is permitted to pass out of the works; (i), to suppress all other salt works, or to restrict them to pur poses of purely local con sumption ; (c), to determine the amount which each Native State should receive from the taxation thus thrown on its subjects; (d), to abolish transit duties and duties on salt in each Native State to an amount equivalent to that which it will receive from the salt tax. 7/A.—That the salt works at Noli, Sul- tanpur and Sambhar be dealt with in a similar way. It may be even advisable to shut up the works at Noh. 8th. —That, finally, the 1,450 miles of Customs Line above referred to be abolished. Such is the scheme which I would ven ture to submit for consideration. I may mention that in the last cold season in Rajputana I discussed these questions with Colonel Brooke, Colonel Beynon, and Major Walter then at Bhartpur. These officers spoke favorably of the feasibility of the scheme. In a short(g) ( 11 ) conversation with Colonel Daly, I under stood him to be inclined to favor it. In a recent communication from Colonel Watson, he spontaneously asked me whether it would not 'be possible for the Government of India to monopolise all the salt trade of the Peninsular, buying up the interests of all Native States therein on condition of their taking the amount off their transit dues or other ' pernicious imposts ' as Sir Madhava Rao calls them.' I hope, therefore, that this note may be taken into consideration. The object aimed at is, I think, admitted by all to be a good one, and I see no other feasible means of attaining it. There is no doubt that if the different salt sources were all in British Territory, we should put an excise duty on the salt at the places of production instead of letting it escape free to be caught again hundreds of miles off by an enormous Customs barrier. Does the fact that many of these sources are in the limits of our Native Feudatories raise an insurmountable obstacle to our levying the salt duty by a rational and economical method instead of by the ex pensive and semi-barbarous contrivance of an army of preventive officers posted along a line several hundreds of miles in length passing through the heart of a peaceable country the whole of which is subject to one paramount power ? G. H. M. BATTEN, Commissionev, Inland Customs. 30-9-73.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00033d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/74</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00033d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/74</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter and memorandum by George Henry Maxwell Batten, Commissioner of Inland Customs,concerning the abolition of the customs line between Rajputana [Rājasthān] and the Central Indian States.</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1873/1874</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-25T13:29:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The file has been foliated in the front top right corner of each folio with a pencil number enclosed in a circle.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Letter from George Henry Maxwell Batten, Commissioner of Inland Customs, regarding Lewis Pelly's desire to abolish the customs line between Rajputana [Rājasthān] and the British Territory.The letter encloses a confidential memo which Batten wrote at Lord Northbrook's request on the feasibility of such a proposal and goes on to detail the only way in which the customs line could be abolished. Batten's proposal is to levy excise duties on salt at their place of production however this subsequently raises the practical difficulties of how to ensure salt is only manufactured for trade at those places the excise duty is being levied.The enclosed memo, dated 30 September 1873 is titled "Note on the feasibility of abolishing that part of the Inland Customs Line which is on the frontier of Rajputana (including Bhawalpur) and the Native States of Central India".It outlines details of the customs line including costs, manpower requirements, its purpose and the amount of taxation produced by it and the difficulties that would be encountered in abolishing it. Batten goes on to outline the only way he can see to abolish the line by levying excise duties on salt production and gives considerable detail on the way in which he believes such a proposal could be implemented.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Commissioner of Inland Customs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00033d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>