<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001df_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-05T14:03:59.783Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">($) kvi P. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l (E 2471/246/25) 14th April, 1939 My dear Gibson, Would you please refer to your letter P.Z. 783/39 of the 14th March on the subject of Ibn Baud’s attitude to the Arab Rulers in the Persian Gulf? 2. You will have seen from our despatch No. 101 of^ the 12th April to Jedda, a copy of which has been sent to you officially, that Oliphant took the opportunity during a conversation with the Amir Faisal to lay at rest any apprehensions which Ibn Saud may have with regard to our alleged ’’forward policy** in the Gulf. 3. I now enclose a letter from Bullard which shows that he also has spoken to Sheikh Yusuf Yasin on the same lines. Yours ever J. P. Gibson, Esq. FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND g£nf&lt;FT nrpr iwniA nFFio.F ENCLOSURE IN AIR UAiL LETTER— COPY n a n ' * &lt;1. &lt; T U J (K 2471/P46/25) No. 518/1177/2. !bo/ BRITISH LEGATION, JEDDA, SAUDI ARABIA. March 8th., 1939. vT «T My dear Baxter, You will have seen a copy of the confidential letter D.O. No. 105-S , which Powle sent to Peel on January 23rd., on the subject of Ibn Saud*s attitude towards the Arab rulers of the Persian Gulf. I spoke to Shaikh Yusuf Yasin a few days ago in the sense of this letter, pointing out that we had refrained from interfering in the internal policy of the shaikhs, and that the establishment of administrative councils at Kuwait and Dubai had been due to disregard of our advice to set up advisory councils to act as safety valves. Yusuf Yasin said that the King had a double interest in the matter: he did not wish anything to happen which would expose His Majesty’s Government to criticism, and he wished the personal position of the shaikhs to be maintained. Yusuf Yasin has doubtless repeated to Ibn Saud what I told him, but the King has not sent any comment. During the last few days I have been discussing the Kuwait Agreements with Shaikh Yusuf, and I took the opportunity to point out how very much Saudi policy towards Kuwait during the last few years had weakened the King’s position as between Saudi Arabia and Iraq. The Iraq propaganda for the annexation of Kuwait had drawn/ C. W. Baxter Esq., M.C., Foreign Office.drawn from the King the quite accurate statement that Kuwait meant more to Saudi Arabia than to Iraq; hut suppose Iraq said that as Saudi Arabia had got on without Kuwait for so long, she had proved that Kuwait was of no interest to her? But I have no doubt that Ibn Saud's suspicions of Kuwait, both as a home for smugglers and as a possible source of political intrigue, have been very strong, and they are not necessarily weaker now: only, the other considerations which I suggested in the despatch on which Fowle has commented would seem to have tipped the balance the other way. I am sending copies of this letter to Fowle and de Gaury. Yours ever, (Sgd.) R. W. Bullard.In any further communication on this subject, please quote ^ k°£oQU//'?//££ -SA- and address—;/&lt;?/ to any person by ncnne, but to— A ^ “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I* ty. j THE Under-Secretary of State for Affairs presents his compliments to &lt;p ^/ck&amp;s o^o^cst. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop UL4 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, (&lt;+ *^c , 193 ?: Reference to previous correspondence : ¥ o. LOU /* oj (4 -(L fi~JL Description of Enclosure. 14 Similar letter sent to cj o . TV/ 'c o 6130 15844 ( 4 )o r\ ■■ ^ No. 101 (E 2241/177/25) 1 u ~ ■&gt; FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 12th April, 1939. Sir, In my despatch No. 86 of the 29th March, I informed you that the Amir Feisal had seen Sir Lancelot Oliphant on the 24th March immediately after his conversation with myself and had continued with him the discussion of certain points arising out of the prime Minister 1 s letter of the 23rd March. 2. His Royal Highness told Sir Lancelot Oliphant that he was very appreciative of the warm terms in which the prime Minister’s letter was couched and then enquired, as I recorded in my despatch under reference, in what form, and how quickly Saudi Arabia might expect help should a situation arise in which the commu:*ity of interests between Saudi Arabia, and Great Britain led to their being faced with a common enemy. This is a point on which you will receive instructions in due course. 3. His Royal Highness then alluded to the phrase ’’potential aggressors” which occurs in the sixth paragraph of the Prime Minister’s letter. He asked whether it was the opinion of the Foreign Office that, in the present unstable state of the world, some form of aggression might be exercised against Saudi Arabia. He was told, that any act of aggression in the near future seemed very doubtful. Indeed, Herr Hitler’s recent activities could not have /been Sir Reader Bullard, K.C.M.G., C.I.E. @'fcc•j sto# ^ etc., Jedda.■been welcome to those who had hitched their chariot to his star, and it was unlikely that any country which had done so would willingly undertake intensive activity in Arabia. But in Herr Hitler’s case it was no longer a question of dealing with a normal, logical man, and it was always possible that he might incite those whom he regarded as his friends to ~'Ihv him even now* It might, however, be doubted whether Italy, if pursuing her claims against Prance, would simultaneously show any aggressive action in the East. It was not possible to say any more than this. 4c His Royal Highness then spoke cf Koweit, and asked whether there was any likelihood of His Majesty’s Government allowing its incorporation in Iraq. The answer was an emphatic negative. 5. His Royal Highness finally turned to the situation in the Persian Gulf. He was assured that, far from it being the policy of His Majesty’s Government to encroach upon the autonomy of the local Sheikhs, His Majesty’s Government had always been most careful to preserve their autonomy. He was reminded that his brother, the Amir Saud, when he had visited Bahrein some fifteen months ago, had been impressed by the absence of any signs of dictation by His Majesty’s Government. He was also told, by way of illustration, that although His Majesty’s Government had met with considerable difficulty in establishing an air port on the Trucial Coast, yet later, when the Sheikh of Debai saw that the freedom of the Sheikh of Sharjah had been in no wise diminished since the Imperial Airways service had been introduced, this Sheikh /hadhad himself pressed for the air port to be transferred to Debai. 6. His Royal Highness seemed satisfied, and left after a conversation which had lasted nearly an hour. I am, with great truth and regard, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) (Sd.) LACY BAGGALLAY*nonfIdential . -LAw’ T ^ e Residency, Bushire, the 23rd January, 1939 D»0»yo»105-S cCc&lt;^ru ^&lt;-cC Could you please refer to Bullard^ interesting despatch tfo .231 of 13th December 1938 to the Foreign Office on the sub ject of Ibn Saud’s attitude towards the Arab Rulers of the Persian Gulf* 2 # it is of course all to the good that Ibn Saud*s attitude has somewhat changed especially towards the Shaikh of Kuwait. If only this change of heart had come earlier the troublesome question of the Kuwait - Saudi blockade, whicn. we have been pressing Ibn Saud to remove for many years past, would have been settled long ago. Bullard emphasises the new attitude which Ibn Saud now adopts towards the Shaikh (para graph 3 of his letter); 'If there was nothing novel in the King’s praise of the Shaikh of Bahrain on this recent occasion, to hear him praise the Shaikh of Kuwait was certainly quite new. Hitherto we have always been given to understand that he regarded the Shaikh as the leader of a gang of smugglers responsible for the loss of an immense annual revenue to Saudi Arabia# How, however, I was told of the traditional bonds between Ibn Saud and Kuwait, and assured of his desire for the maintenance of the Shaikh’s position and dignity; and was asked to expedite the conclusion of that Saudi - Kuwait Agreement for which he had previously R.T.Peel Esquire, M*C.» The India Office, London.1: ? - 2 - shown so little enthusiasm. M Personally I have never been inclined to take I bn Saud*s protestations as to KUwait-Saudi Arabia smuggling altogether literally, any more than I am inclined to take Iraqi protestations on the same subject at their face value# In each case whatever may be the real grounds of complaint personally I have no doubt that these have been much exaggerated owing to extraneous politi cal influences, amongst others jealousy of the independence of Kuwait and a desire to annoy the Shaikh and M put him in bad M with His Majesty’s Government. x In regard to Ibn Baud’s fears of our w forward policy” in the Gulf, I think it would be a good thing if these could be laid at rest, more especially as we have an excellent case in this 0 KvJ . lM cc(^ ^Pect. Our policy in the Gulf Kvide correspondence ending with my letter No.14-5 of the 5th January to Weightman, copy sent to the India Office and the Government of India under my Printed better HQ. 15-S of the same date) has been consistently, and after due consideration, one of strict 'non-intervention”, in spite of the fact that the opening up of the Arab side during the last ten years or so would have given us a good excuse for instituting a forward policy had we wished to do so. In Bahrain, for instance, in spite of the establishment of a large oil field, which naturally considerably increased our interests in that State, and the presence of a British Adviser, the Shaikh and his family have remained as independent as ever, a fact which was favourably commented on by the Amir Baud on his visit to Bahrain in December of 1937. (Vide paragraph 4 of my letter H0.12-S of 3rd January 1938 to Metcalfe, copy sent to the India Office, Bullard and Weightman under my Printed letter Ko.lS-S of the same date). In the/3- the same way our interests on the Arab side have been much increased by the establishment of the Air Route along it but we have been careful not to make this an excuse for interfering in the internal affairs of the Sheikhdoms,e.g. on the Trucial Coast. Here there was considerable opposition to our obtaining air facilities, since the Shaikhs and their people feared that this would be a preliminary to their losing their independence. When however after considerable difficulty we established an air port at Sharjah, sad the Shaikhs saw that this did not lead to our *»taking over” Sharjah in any way, public opinion completely veered round and the Shaikh of Debai who previously steadily refused to give us air facilities in his State, seeing the financial advantages which were accruing to the Shaikh of Sharjah, actually asked us to move the air port from Sharjah to Debai. If Bullard sees no objection he might like on the next opportunity to make an explanation on the above lines either to Ibn Saud or Fuad Hamza* 4. With regard to the C ouncils at Kuwait and Debai which seem also to be exercising Ibn Saud^ mind, Bullard writes (para graph 3 of his letter)i (Ibn Saud) 'There is no doubt that although he/takes his own decisions he does listen to the opinions of the ulama and of the tribal shaikhs; but he thinks it wrong that the Shaikh of Kuwait should have to listen to a 'self- appointed” council containing elements which, in Ibn Saud’s opinion, are far from having the necessary prestige or position. But, says Ibn Saud, it would have been quite proper for the Shaikh to summon men of position to fonn a council and to ask their advice.” This /This is precisely what I have thought all along and you will remember that His Majesty’s Government through me gave some good advice to the Shaikh of Kuwait before the recent crisis to cease his purely autocratic method of goverment, which was against Arab traditions, and associate himself more with his people by summoning a Council such a£ had existed in the days of the Great Mubarak. This advice the Shaikh did not follow. If he had done so his present council would have been an Advisory one and not an Executive one forced upon him. The difference between I bn Saud and Mubarak and the Shaikh of Kuwait is that while Ibn Saud is a statesman, as was Mubarak, the Shaikh unfortunately is far from being one. The course of events at Debai was exactly the same as at Kuwait, when a popular agitation began there for reforms I advised the Shaikh to nominate an Advisory Council. This occurred after the formation of the Council at Kuwait but the Shaikh,in spite of having this lesson before him, refused to make any concessions to the popular party and in consequence was likewise saddled with an Executive Council. We do not want to leave Ibn Saud with the impression that it was we who forced the Councils on the Shaikhs, so perhaps an explanation to him by Bullard on the above lines at some suitable opportunity might do good. 5* I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe, with a copy of Bullard’s letter, and to Bullard, Weightman and de Gauiy, without. * sent under Printed letter N 0 .IO 6 -S of the 23 rd January ,19 39./V- CONHUlckM UA* W * 0 In any further couimunioation on thi^subject, quote ^9 no. E.^6/2it6/?jr address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for For 3ign j presents li? compliments to S3 / ii&lt;— ^ J z 1 J ■= s(.g/£W and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copr^ of the under-mentioned paper. UhU^Lm^ n • re c \ / I m A-i A'-. J Foreign Office, ^ , 193^-. // [s) Reference to previous correspondence c ^' h%/* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Pa Subject. % POL. l;?t. ENGLOSUdE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 5 TOM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE 3 0 JAN INDIA urriCE ; 1 ^ 2 ^ 6130 17930 ( 4 ) I111 THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT EASTERN (Arabia). January 10, 1939. ^ ^ Section 1. , . Copy No. Sir R. Bullard to Viscount Halifax:—{Received January 10, 1939.) (No. 231.) My Lord, Jedda, December 13, 1938. IN my despatch No. 224 d ated the 5th December I had the honour to report to you on the changed attitude of Ibn Saud towards Koweit, and on the 6th December I addressed a letter to Mr. Baxter in which I mentioned Ibn Saud's reluctance, as reported by the manager of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company, to allow a British firm to establish itself on the mainland of Hasa. At the risk of some repetition, 1 now furnish a brief report on Ibn Saud's general attitude towards the Arab rulers in the Persian Gulf. It is well known that he has always resented his dependence on Bahrein if not on Koweit as well, that he despises the smaller sheikhs, and that he considers that the policy of His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom in the Persian Gulf has the effect of hemming him in. During the last year or two various new factors have been introduced into the problem : the discovery of oil in various Arab territories; the increase in the influence of Iraq; movements in Arab territories which for con venience can be described as democratic; and the real or simulated belief in some Arab circles that His Majesty’s Government are engaged in a “ forward move ment ” in the Gulf; and it will be convenient to make a brief survey of the whole position in the light of these new factors. 2. The personal respect which Ibn Saud has for His Highness the Sheikh of Bahrein was shown when the Crown Prince of Saudi Arabia visited Bahrein a year ago and on the occasion of the return visit of the sheikh to the Hejaz shortly afterwards. The King, when speaking to me about the visit, praised the sheikh as an excellent man, and, moreover, of the same tribal origin as himself, while the Amir Saud spoke of the difference between the sheikh and the other Arab rulers, whom he described as rather Boeotian. During my recent visit to Riyadh Ibn Saud spoke with concern about the sheikh, whose position he con sidered was endangered by the Persian intrigues, which, in his opinion, had caused the recent agitation. He became quite animated in his sympathy. There was the Zubara question, too. he said, that remained open. I said I thought this question had been settled (I did not say that the decision of His Majesty's Government was not to support the Bahrein claim), but the King said it was by no means settled. This was the first reference to the Zubara question since the conversation with Fuad Hamza which I reported in my despatch No. 18 of the 1st February, 1938, except that some months ago one of the Mecca newspapers printed an obscure paragraph, which did not mention Zubara by name but referred to what could only be the Zubara dispute, and alleged that it had been exacerbated by the discovery of oil at the place concerned. 3. If there was nothing novel in the King’s praise of the Sheikh of Bahrein on this recent occasion, to hear him praise the Sheikh of Koweit was certainly quite new. Hitherto, we have always been given to understand that he regarded the sheikh as the leader of a gang of smugglers responsible for the loss of an immense annual revenue to Saudi Arabia. Now, however, I was told of the traditional bonds between Ibn Saud and Koweit, and assured of his desire for the maintenance of the sheikh’s position and dignity; and was asked to expedite the conclusion of that Saudi-Koweit Agreement for which he had previously shown so little enthusiasm. A year or two years ago the Saut-al-Hejaz would not have published the article on Koweit which appears in the issue of the 6th December. This article begins : &lt;c Koweit is a pure Arab country, distinguished by its mild ness and tranquillity. Its people are known for their Arab nobility of character, which they have inherited from their honourable ancestors.” In my above- mentioned despatch I tried to provide some explanation for this change of attitude, and suggested as the principal causes a growing realisation that Ras [505 k—1] CONFIDENTIAL. [E 246/246/25]2 Tanura may be less successful than was hoped; suspicion of Iraq; and appre hension at the movement in Koweit which has resulted in the establishment of a council to assist in the government of that territory. It is early to give a decided opinion about Ras Tanura, and it might perhaps be justifiable to draw the opposite conclusion, viz., that the possession of a port of his own made Ibn Saud believe that few, if any, imports would now come in through Koweit; but it is certain ^ that the other two considerations have had some influence on Ibn Saud’s mind. The course of events in Koweit has not been in accordance with his conception of constitutional procedure in an Arab and a Moslem State. Some time ago he told me that he listened to the advice of his people and then governed in accordance with the principles of Islam, and he assented to my suggestion that his country was under a religious constitution. There is no doubt that, although he takes his own decisions, he does listen to the opinions of the ulema and of the tribal sheikhs; but he thinks it wrong that the Sheikh of Koweit should have to listen to a “ self- appointed ' council containing elements which, in Ibn Saud's opinion, are far from having the necessary prestige or position. But, says Ibn Saud, it would have been quite proper for the sheikh to summon men of position to form a council and to ask their advice. 4. I must repeat that Ibn Saud apologised, when I made some deprecating remark, for speaking about the internal affairs of Bahrein and Koweit, and explained that he was thinking of his own position, which might be affected by that of his neighbours. 5. Ibn Saud was indignant at what he had heard of Iraqi designs on Koweit. The efforts made by the Iraqi Government this year to draw tighter the com mercial, financial and military bonds with Saudi Arabia have not weakened his suspicions, and their desire to have a port at Koweit—perhaps as a prelude to absorption—is the last straw. He did not refer to Iraqi propaganda elsewhere, but it was no doubt present to his mind, for Arabic newspapers have referred more than once to the populations of the minor Arab States in the Gulf as looking towards Iraq. Ibn Saud’s jealousy of Iraq has been exacerbated recently by the rather flamboyant statements made by the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs about Palestine on his return from London, and just as he is trying to prove, by his negotiations in connexion with the forthcoming London discussions, that, as he has claimed in so many words, it is he and not “ certain others ” who is the leader of the Arab world, so he may be wishing to counteract Iraqi influence in the Gulf by concluding the Koweit Agreement, thereby enhancing the position of the sheikh and emphasising the importance of the relations between Koweit and Saudi Arabia. 6. Ibn Saud made no reference to the minor Arab rulers during my visit to Riyadh, but Fuad Hamza asked me, obviously on instructions and with much earnestness, about the possibility of a solution of the eastern frontier difficulty. Moreover, when the King was deprecating hostile action against the Yemeni forces in Shabwa, Fuad said that our action would inevitably be linked up in the public mind with what is regarded as our “ forward policy ” in the Persian Gulf. When called upon to define this policy he could only say that some Arabs attributed the establishment of the council in Koweit to the British, who had found the sheikh too independent and desired to have a more subservient instrument, and refer to a movement in the direction of councils in some of the minor sheikhdoms. Fuad did not pretend that he himself held any such belief, and admitted that he had brought back from Koweit, where he stayed on his way from Bagdad, a more reasonable theory; but it is admitted that His Majesty’s Government have thought it necessary to extend and strengthen their control in the Hadhramaut, and Arabs cannot be blamed if they look for signs of a similar process nearer home. Ibn Saud has no love for the minor sheikhs, least of all for the Sheikh of Qatar, but a general movement towards the reduction of the status of Arab rulers could not be pleasing to him. His low opinion of the young men in the Hejaz, who are supposed to desire the modernisation of Saudi Arabia, has been expressed more than once, and he would naturally regret the appearance at his door, in however rudimentary a form, of a system which he is resolved not to see established in his own country. 7. Finally, in spite of his general desire to work with His Majesty’s Government, and of his assertion that, on grounds of security, he would rather have the British as his neighbours than the Amir Abdullah or the Iraqi Govern ment, he would certainly not welcome an increase in British control in the3 territories of his Arab neighbours in the Gulf. He must be well aware of the tendency of European control in eastern countries to spread, and of the keenness of the competition for oil-bearing lands, and the unfortunate course of the Jabal Nakhsh affair seems to have caused him to believe that our policy in the Persian Gulf is influenced by oil interests. I do not doubt, therefore, that in conversation ^iyith Mr. Lenahan he did show some reluctance to allow a British firm to establish themselves at Ras Tanura, which is to be the port for the shipment of Hasa oil. In the end the unique position which Messrs. Gray Mackenzie already hold in the Gulf, and the facilities which they are consequently in a position to offer, should enable them to secure the permission they require, but they will have much suspicion to live down. It is to be expected that Ibn Saud’s attitude towards them will be influenced not only by what happens in the Gulf, but by the result of the London discussions on Palestine, and even perhaps by the outcome of the Anglo- Yemeni dispute about Shabwa and Abr. Our position will be none the easier if, as is reported by His Majesty’s Embassy at Bagdad, there is to be a German mission at Jedda, unless the Germans are so foolish as to overdo their propaganda —a great mistake where Ibn Saud is concerned. It is to be hoped that the Hansa Line, who are said to have been making strenuous efforts to establish themselves at Bahrein, will not succeed in their attempt to obtain permission to extend their activities to the mainland. It is certain that the California Arabian Standard Oil Company are well content with the services rendered by Messrs. Gray Mackenzie, and would like to be able to utilise them at Ras Tanura; nor is there any outward sign that the Saudi authorities are considering the Hansa Line application; but the Germans may be expected to offer favourable terms, and they have the great advantage that their country cannot be accused of hemming Ibn Sand in. 8. I am forwarding copies of this despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassadors at Cairo and Bagdad, to the Hon. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, to the Political Agents at Koweit and Bahrein, to his Excellency the Governor of Aden, and to his Excellency the High Commissioner for Palestme at Jerusalem. I have, &amp;c. R. W. BULLARD.the whole position in the light of these new factors. 2, The personal respect which Ihn Saud has for --O ■lis ilighness the Shaikh of Bahrain v/as shown v/hen the Crown Brinee .of S^udi Arabia visited Bahrain a year ago and on the occasion of the return visit of the shaikh to the dejaz shortly afterwards. The king,when speaking to me about the visit, praised the Shaikh as an excellent man, and moreover of the so 'e tribal origin as himself, while the Anir Baud snoke of t^e difference between the Shaikh and the ot^er Arab rulers, v/hom he described as rather Boeotian- I&gt;irirg m&gt; r recent visit to kiyadh Ibn Baud spoke with con- ern about the Shaikh, v/hose position he considered was endangered by the Persian intrigues which in his opinion had caused the recent agitation. Be became quite animated in his sympathy. There was the Zubara question too, he said: that remained open. said - thought this question had been settled (I did not say that the decision of His Majesty’s Government was not to supuort the Bahrain claim/, rut the King said it v/as by no means settled.. j -his was the first reference to the ^ubara question since the conversation DU- with Kuad Hamza which I reported in my despatch Ho. 1_8_ (222/469/3) of February 1st,. 1938, except that some months *VO£»oji«V t'OC tv f t){p&lt;q&gt;M ago one of the Iecca newspapers printed an obscure paragranh v/hich did n^t mention Zubara b 7 r name but referred to what could only be the Zabarn disnute and alleged that it had been exacerbated by the discovery of oil at the place concerned. 3. If there was nothing novel in the King s praise of the Shaikh of Bahrain on this recent occasion, to hear him praise the Shaikh of Kuwait was certainly quite new. Hitherto we have always been given to understand that he / regarded3 Aw(p| &lt;tk &gt;o reg^rrled. the Shaikh Pb the leader of a gang of Gmugglers reenonGihle for the I ops of an immense annual revenue to Saudi Arabia• 1 ow&gt; hov/ever&gt; — was told of the tradition al bonds between -bn ^aud and Kuwait, arid assured of his desire for the maintenance of the Shaikh’s position and dignitr; and was asked to expedite the conclusion of that Saudi-Kuwait Agreement for which he had ureviously shown so little enthusiasm. A year or two years ago the ”Saut ^ al llenaz’ 1 would not have -published the article on Kuwait whicA a t, pears in the issue of December 6th. ^his article begins' ’Kuwait is a pure Arab country distinguished by its mildness and tranquility. its peonle are known for their rah nobility of character, which they have in herited from their honourable ancestors’'. in my abcve- -mentioned despatch I tried to -provide some explanatior ( for this change of attitude, and suggested as the nrin- cipal causes a growing realisation' that Kgs Tanura may (b) be less successful than was hoped; suspicion of Iraq; {€) and apprehension at the movement in Kuwait which has i resulted in the establishment of a council to assist in the government of that territory. - L t is early to give a decided oninion about Kgs Tanura» and it might perhans be lust if i able to draw t^e on-nosite conclusion, viz. that the possession of a -port of his own made ibn °aud believe that few if any imports would now come in through Kuwait; but it is certain that t^e ether two considerations have nad some influence on Ibn baud’s mind. ^-he course of ev ents in Kuwait has not been in accordance with his con ception of constitutional procedure in an Apgb and a Koslem state. borne timu ago he told me that he listened / to/ *\ CO 1/ 4- to the advice of his neo-nle and then governed in accord ance with the principles of Islam, and he assented to my suggest ion that his country wfes under a religious con stitution. There is no doubt that although he takes his own decisions he does listen to the opinions of the ulama and of the tribal shaikhs; hut he thinks it wrong that / the shaikh of Kuwait should have to listen to a ’'self- -appointed' council containing elements which, in Ibn Saud’s opinion, are far from having the necessary pres- f tige or position. But, says Ibn B a ud, it''‘'would have been quite proner for the Shaikh to summon' men of position to form a council and to ask their advice. 4 . I must reneat that Ibn S a ud apologised, when I made some dcurecating remark} for Speaking about the in ternal affairs of Bahrain and Kuwait, and explained that he was thinking &gt;f his own position which might be affected by that c^ his neighbours. S. Ibn S a ud was indignant at what he had heard of Iraqi designs on Kuwait. The efforts made by the Iraq Government this year to draw tighter the commercial, finan cial and military bonds with Saudi Arabia have not weakened r his suspicions, and their desire to have a port at Kuwait - perhaps as a nrelude to absorption - is the last straw. Be did not refer to Iraqi propaganda elsewhere, but it was no doubt present to his mind, for Apabic newspapers have referred more than once to the populations of the minor Arab states in the Gulf as looking towards Iraq. Ibn Saud’s I jealousy of Iraq has been exacerbated recently by the rather flamboyant statements made by the Iraqi Minister for I’oreign Aff a ip S about Palestine on his return from rjondon, and .just as he is try trig to prove • by his negcMoM ns in / connectionconnection with the forthcoming London discussions, that, as he/claimed in so many v/ords, it is he and not ’'certain others' who is the leader of the world, so he may he v/ishing to counteract Iraqi influence in the Gulf hy con cluding the Kuwait Agreement, thereby enhancing the posi- tion of the Shaikh and emphasising the importance of the relations between Kuwait and Saudi Arabia. 1 6. I-bn Gaud made no reference to the minor Arab rulers during my visit to kiyadh, but I'uad Hamza asked me, obviously on instructions and v/ith much earnestness, about the nossibilitv of a solution of the eastern frontier dif- : ficulty. Moreover when the King was deprecating hostile action against the Yemeni forces in Shabwa, Huad said that our action would inevitably be linked up in the public mind with what' is regarded as our 'forward policy' in the Persian Gulf, /hen called unon to define this policy he could only say that some Arabs attributed the establish ment of the council in Kuwait to the British, who had found the Shaikh too independent and desired to have a more subservient instrument, and refer to a movement in the direction of councils in some of the minor shaikh- ^ domer K'uad did not pretend that he himself held any such SkhUv voo4 fo f, j :)e ^j_ e p ; and admitted that he had brought back from Kuwait, where he stayed cn his way from Bagdad, a more reasonable theory, but it is admitted that His Hajesty’s Government have thought it necessary to extend and strengthen their control in the Hadhramaut, and Arabs cannot be blamed if they look for signs of a similar nrocess nearer home. Ibn Sand has no love for the minor shaikhs, least of all for the Shaikh of Katar, but a general movement towards the / reductionvJ K reduction of the ointus of ^rah rulers could not he rleaB- ing to hin. r ip low opinion of t^e young men in the He;j 9 z v/ho are supposed to desire the modernisation of Saudi Arabia has heen expressed more than once, and he would naturally regret the appearance a+ his door, in hawever rudimentary a form, of a system which he is resolved not to see established in v is own country. 7 . -inally, in suite of his general desire to work with is J aiesty’s Government, and of his assertion that, on grounds of security, he would rather have the British as his neighbours than the Amir Abdullah or the irsq Gev- ernment, he would certainly not welcome an increase in - in the a uL£. British control in the territories of his A r gh neighbours / He must be well aware of the tendency of European control in eastern countries to spread, and of the keenness of the competition for oil-bearing lands, and the unfortunate course cf the fT gq n ]_ hakhsh affair seems to have caused him to believe that cur policy in the Persian Gplf is in- fluenccd by oil interests. I do not doubt therefore that in conversation with ^ r. -^enahan He did show some reluct- ance to allow a British firm to establish themselves at Pas Bnnura, which is to be the port for the shipment of Hass oil. in the end the unique position which -essrs. Gray ; ackenzie already hold in the Gulf, and the' facilities which they are consequently in a position to offer, should enable them to secure the permission they require, but they will have much suspicion to live down. it is to be expected that i-bn Grubs attitude towards them will be influenced not only by what happens in the Gulf, but by the result of the -•ondon discussions on Halistine and even perhaps 1 y the / outcomeT outcome of the Anglo-Yemeni dispute about Shabwa and Avir. Our position will be none the easier if, as is reported ly tis aicsty’s Embassy at Bagdad, there is to he a German mission at Jedda, ‘.mless the Germans ore sc foolish as to overdo their propaganda - a great mistake where Ihn S a ud is concerned,. It is to he h°ped that the iiansa ^ine, who are said to have been making strenudus efforts to esta^-r lish themselves at Bahrain, will not succeed in their attempt to Phtain permission to extend their activities to the mainland, It is certain that the California Arab ian Standard Gn Commany are v/ell content with the ser vices rendered by essrs. Gray Mackenzie and would like to be able utilise them at Ras lanura; nor is there any outward sign that the Saudi authorities are considering the Hansa Line anrlicati^n; but the Germans may be expected to offer favourable terms, and they have the great advantage that their country cannot be accused oi hemming L bn Saud in. 8 , I am forwarding conies of this despatch t* -^is i'ale sty’s Ambassadors at Cairo (ho. ) and Bagdad (ho. 2708 / 469 / 18 ) , to the »ncurablu. the Poli+iaal Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire (ho. 2709 / 469 / 18 ), to the Political Agents at Kuwait (No. 271 $/ 46 f/l 8 and Bahrain- (ho, 2711 / 469 /lB. . to ’is ^x^ellency the Governor of Aden (h 0 . 2712 / 469 / 18 ), and to iis ^xoellency the high Ccmmis- sioner for Palestine aw Jerusalem (ho. 27 l 3 / 469 /l 8 ,’. I have the honour to be. with the highest respect, ' y Lord, Yrvur L^rdshin ’ s most obedient, bumb 1 e s e rrra n+ty;o~p»ny, la at prwaant in adds m5goti«r ing for per- Iftslon to eatabllah an office at &lt;aa Tanura# considers that the andl hopes baaed on km Tenure have b«? n for higher than the Ircu atonies cnrer wairanted. He believes that hey have evon at times envisaged Has Tenure as an enormoue entrepot eerving as a port of traneit for Bahrain and thus reversing the present position so galling to Ibn &amp;aud; whereas in hie opinion there is no need to have wharvet and warehouses at iise ' onura or indeed to land cargo there at all: it can best be used* he maintains, «e a deep-water anchorage where tankers can take Ad oil from the ttaea oil field, and cargo for ^audi Arable can be transhipped Into bargee for despatch under tow to A1 Khubar and elsewhere, for the oil field, and to Wqair, fo** hofuf and Kiyadh* t 1® interesting in this connection to ^uote Fuad Bey Hamse, who returned from Iraq, via Kuwait, while I was at Riyadh. He spoke of the nearness of Kuweit to Riyadh by car, and pointed out that for a person ravelling from Klyadh by car, it took no longer to reach Basra, with its air-lines connecting with urope and the set, than Hofuf# This is true, and the traveller at Hofuf la atill a diffi cult day's journey by car from Has Tanura. It may be, tnen, that the Saudi authorities recognise that even if Haa Tamra can be made iato a good port, it la not very convenient cm to situation. 4» Ibn i&gt;aud la also worried about Iraqi designs on Kuwait - another o bjcct which he brought up during my visit. I p ve reasons for believing that Kuwait would not easily be swallowed up by Iraq, but the ling may think that i the position of Kuwait would be s ronger if he had signed the proposed agreement, which would tend to show that / SaudiSaudi ^rofcla and not Iraq, is the proper hinterland of Kuwait* It la natural that 2bn laud should not want to eee hie terrltoiy ahut off t row Kuwait by the relatively power ful e ate of Ira^« 5 - Finally, Ibn Saud nay wish to see the peraonal position of the Shaikh of Kuwait strengthened, lie sfroke to me one day about the Shaikis of uwait and Balu*ain - his traditional connection with then, hie personal synpathy with them aa fellow Areb rulers, and hie regret at recent events which night have damaged their prestige, e.g. the riot in Bahrain, which he attributed to Persian machina tions, and the appeintnwmt in Kuwait of a council composed of elements which were not all, he thought, of the highest quality, de said that he apologised if he ^ae stepping outside his jurisdiction (I had indeed made some deprecating remarks), bu he felt very strongly on the subject. It seemed to ne that the King felt that his own position was affected by the re ent constitutional change in Kuwait, and thought it was t ime for ^rab rulers to help one another. 6% whatever the motives behind the king^ request for the speedy conclusion of the proposed greement, I hope, as I caid in the eecond of the two shove-mentioned telegrams, that we shall seise the opportunity. T am sending copies of this despatch to His Majes ty's Ambssrador at Bagdad (No.2*91/381/24), The honourable the foil 4 leal Agent in the Persian Oulf at Buehlre (Ko.2f592/ 361/34) and the P olitical ^gant at Kuwait ( &lt;o. 2693/361/34)• I h ve the honour to be, with the highest respect, fy Lord, Your Lordship*s most obedient, humble servant, R* K. 'Hillard</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001df_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3909</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001df</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3909</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/172 'Attitude of Ibn Saud (Saudi Arabia) towards Arab rulers in Persian Gulf and P. Gulf affairs.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-05T22:45:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (32 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 33; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence from British officials concerning the attitude of the Government of Saudi Arabia (specifically that of its king, Ibn Saud [Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd]) toward the rulers of other Gulf states.The correspondents include HM Minister, Jedda (Sir Reader William Bullard), and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Sir Trenchard Craven William Fowle).The comments are made against the background of the discovery of oil, and the increasing influence of Iraq in the region, and particularly concern Kuwait, Bahrain, and Dubai. The correspondence also discusses the issue of popular movements and administrative councils in Kuwait and Dubai, and the need to assure Ibn Saud that there was no British 'forward policy' in the Gulf.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Foreign policy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001df#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>