<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000137_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:15:53.299Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">C 5.37. I Q) TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED With reference to conversations with Mr.Weightman, Mr.Skliros, Managing Director, Iraq Petroleum Co.,Ltd., will be visiting Bahrein in early June in one of the three Iraq Petroleum Company’s aeroplanes with British registra tion. They are registered in the name of the Iraq Pe troleum Transport Company. and are flown by Imperial Airways pilots. We will inform you as soon as possible which aeroplane is to be used and the date of arrival. Will you please inform us if any more particulars other than the above are required. DIRECTORS : Sir John Cad man, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) BAHREIN R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) ' ( W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) Kessler (Dutch) ^Cayl^T??©. ,^,'S^C^ (££&lt;th) - -efroy J. r\. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R W. Sellers J. Skliros PCL/CAQ4/,|tf^']. CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF 30th May 1938. j To H.B.M’s Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir .fe I.P.C. AIRCRAFT VISIT TO BAHREIN All are De Havilland Twin engine 'Rapide* Type G ^ D N H G A D N I G A E S R (with W/T) Yours faithfully, For and on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED MANAGERC 5.37. TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A- Agmun CiB.C. ^JdWtS. R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.8.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J^^^A. Kessler (Dutch) . Lefroy I. «. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R W. Sellers J. Skliros I- PCL/CAQ4/ii&gt;&amp;0 OONFIDSKTIAL To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF May 31st, 1938. Dear Sir, I.P.C. AIRCRAFT VISIT TO BAE I In continuation of our No.PC 1/0^0,4/1047 dated 30th May,1938. The Iraq Petroleum Company aeroplane to land at Muharrak aerodrome in the near future is the De Eavilland Twin Engined 'Rapide* - British registration mark 'G&amp;ESR*. According to present arrangements the aeroplane will land on the 4th.June,1938 ex Basrah and Kuwait and return to Basrah on the afternoon of the 5th June. The aeroplane will be carrying:- PASSENGERS : J. Skliros - Managing Director, Ir^q Petro leum Co.,Ltd., PILOT: P.G.Allen - Secretary. J. Wheeler ENGINEER : C• Barnes W/T OPERATOR : J.E.S.Walsha. We shall be grateful if formal permission can be obtained to the landing. Yours faithfully, For and on behalf of FM CONCESSIONS LTD.,Political Agency f Bahrain, the 31st May 1938. No. C/360-10/12 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BA H 3 A I N . Memorandum . Mr. Skliros, Managing Director of the Iraq Petroleum Company, will be visiting Bahrain on the 4th June 1938 in an aircraft belonging to the Company and will leave on the afternoon of June, the 5th. He will be accompanied by Mr. P.G. Allen - Secretary Mr. J. toheeler - Pilot ^: r * C. Barnes - Engineer and to. J.E.S. Walsha - W/T Operator. 2. I should be obliged if permission could be granted for the aircraft to land at I'uharraq Aerodrome. I give be low the necessary details required under the Air Navigation Regulations: Registered Owner Iraq Petroleum Tyne of aircraft. Registration Mnr — — Be Havilland Twin GAESR Engined 'Rapide' GAESR Company Lui‘ Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain* /TV No. of 1357 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated- R/Thanv 2, 1357 R/Thanv 2 June 1, 1^00 H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. c 3 Memorandum:- With reference to your memorandum No. C/360 10/12 dated 31st May 1938 I forward herewith six copies of special authorisation for the aircraft of the Iraq Petroleum Company to land in Bahrain. Adviser to the Government &amp; y | A ■j \l /J itGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. TERRITORY OF BAHRAIN SPECIAL AUTHORISATION FOR AIRCRAFT TO LAND IN MUHARRAQ AND FLY OVER BAHRAIN. 1. The Shaikh of Bahrain hereby authorises the flight within the limits of Bahrain of the following aircraft of nationality. Registered owner. Iraq x avroitfua Type of aircraft. Registration marks. i/v £ fnia * (*) 2. This authorisation is limited to the period from Inclusive, and is granted subject to the following conditions. to (*) T} } e aircraft their crews and passengers shall be liable to ail the legal obligations which arise from general legislation and import and export regulations and any regulations which may be laid down Mr public safety as well as the air navigation . f regulations. &amp; (it) The aircraft shall not use as a place of landing or departure within Bahrain any place other than the aerodrome at Muharraq and the published conditions governing the use of the said aerodrome shall be observed. (m) This authorisation or a certified true copy of it shall be carried in the aircraft and be produced on demand for the inspection of any authorised person. &gt;5 Adviser to the Government. (Authorised by His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Al-Khafifahr Shaifth of Bahrain.) . X * /•*&gt; j IConfidential , No* C/362-10/12 Political Agency, Bahrain, dated the 1st June 193 To &amp; The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limit.jd, B A H R A I N * Dear Sir, £ V With reference to correspondence ending with your letter No. PC'/CAQ4/1050 dated the 31st May 1938, I for ward herewith three copies of a Certificate of Authorisa tion permitting the Iraq Petroleum Company’s aircraft 'Rapid©' to land in Bahrain. Yours faithfully, it Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain Q Oy ]By Air Mail. P.Z. 6'#'3'b / 19 H INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, ?f SEP I93fl Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. T W Fnrpi t cra. Secretary, Govexmnent of lxubhp-. The Political llesidem in the Persian GUdh t ft njkAju^- 4963 2000 7.36p.Z.6456/38. COPY. PETROLEUM BEVELOPfflKT (TPJJCI.'iL COAST) LTD, Prom London Memorandum No. PC. 28/773 Late 16th September, 1938. To Bahrein Copies to Political Agent Muscat. Subject SUPPLIES 0? SPIRIT A1TD OIL. /''N Me iiientioned to you in a previous letter that permission had been obtained by the Company from the -go draw up to 200 gallons of Aviation Spirit at any time from H.A.F. Stocks at the various landing grounds on the Trucial Coast and that of Oman. In adcd-.ion to this, we are now am anging distribution of stocks i Cj. ourselves,dand in this connection please nuce the attached copies of letters Nos. PC.27/1^2 and P.C\ 27/123 sent by us to the A.I.O.C. and to Messrs., Nassio bin Mohammed &lt;1 Son. respectively. If these matters, m so far as they refer to the Trucial Coast, £UC 01 i n tercst to the Political Agent, Bahrein, please inform him. (Sgd.) S.H. LONC-NIGG. line Is.P.Z.6456/58 I Petroleum Development (Oman and Dhofar) Limited . PC.27/123. 14th September* 1938. Messrs. Khsn Bahadur Nsssib bin Mohammed &amp; Son* MUSCAT. Oman. n Dear P.i ir ? T 7e confirm the receipt of your telegram dated 10th September: « .y*K yt &lt;*r ’'REFERENCE 27103 AND TELEGRAM CONFIRMED PLEASE. NASSIBI. u The following is the text of a telegram despatched by us to you today: 1 ' AIT GL 0 - IRAN I AN WITHIN 12 DAYS TILL DELIVER SUPPLIES AVIATION PETROL AND OIL TO MUSCAT CONSIGNED TO US STOP DISTRIBUTION TO AND TEMPORARY SAFE STORAGE AT HAND 1300 GALLONS PETROL AND 30 OIL MASIRAH 1000 AND 20 SHUVAMIYAH 900 and 20 MURBAT 1200 AND 10 IS REQUIRED FOR USE OUR AIRCRAFT STOP PLEASE CABLE CONFIRMATION THAT YOU CAN COMPLETE THESE ARRANGEMENTS BY DECEMBER FIRST LATEST. u PETCONCESS T 7e await your confirmation in the above sense. ■7e imagine that you will have no difficulty in arranging the necessary transport for this petrol and oil to the Aerodromes mentioned, but we are less certain regarding the possibility of storage under safe custody there. You are, however, no doubt already in touch with the persons at each place who are responsible for the F.A.F. fuel supplies. As our exploration party will reouire to transport certain stores, camp equipment etc. by sea from one landing ground to another, the Company will require to hire two sailing dh 07/ s of medium or medium large size* each equipped with the necessary supplies and crew. ”;e assume that you will be able to arrange these at short notice, and if so, the matter can wait until the arrival cf the undersigned at Muscat on October 18th Yours faithfully, for PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (OMAN &amp; DHOFAR) LTD. (Sgd.) 8.H. LONGRIGG.38. // ■D X • /_J # oleum jevelo pmeir^ ^Omaii and Dhof ar)^ PC. 27/122 14th Septenfoer 5 1938. I 1 he hnglo-Iranian Oil Co. Ltd., 3ri ta nnic Hourse, Pinsbury Circus, 'P p o Por the so ant ion of Mr . H. J. _ Germain . Dear Sirs, In confirmaoion of telephone conversations between ■che undersigned and Mr. Germain, we reejuire delivery by you to us at Muscat of the following quantities of Aviation Spirit and Aero Shell Heavy Lubricating Oil: Aviation Spirit 3,800 gallons and Oil 80 gallons. This should be sent to us care of our Agents Messrs. Mohammed bin Kassihi C-. Co., Muscat. Import into Muscat will be duty free in accordance with our Concession from H.P. The Sultan, The oil should, if possible, be in one gallon tins. It ins been understood from you that you can effect delivery by the 24th instant. Our Agents are being informed accordingly, and will thereafter undertake distribution to 'Giie landing grounds where supplies will be wanted. Further quantities of 5,000 gallons of Aviation Spirit and 80 gallons of Oil will be required at Sharjah. It is understood from you that these will be available from existing stocks. If this is not so, we anticipate that you will increase such stocks accordingly before .December 1st. Yours faithfully, for PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (OMAN e DHOFAE) LTD. (Sgd.) S.H. Longrigg.—Form 110. C. 3.38. Copy of Telegram 517 FROM BAGHDAD TO PETCONCESS MEBEItt. DA TED 19th October 1938 RECD ...,19th Oct. 3.8. 41 -P.JU.) FOLLOWING IS FOR PACKER E.V. FROM ALLEN BEGINS SATCHELL E.A AND COLE W.E.D. PROP0SE LEAVING GAFFC EN ROUTE BAHREIN AND QATAR VIA BASRAH FULLSTOP CREW OF AIRCRAFT WILL BE PILOT J.L.C. BANKS ENGINEER F.W.BROWN AND WIRELESS OPERATOR E.F.WALSHA FULLSTOP PASSPORTS VISE WILL BE ARRANGED HERE FULLBTOP CAN YOU GET PERMISSION LAND BAHREIN TUESDAY AND R ? ) AND ALSO ARRANGE IES. (DECODED MESSAGE) BAGHDAD MONDAY AFTERNOON BY COMPANY AEROPLANE /Urgent ;1v) r No. C/649-10/12 Political Agency y Bahrain, 20th October 1938. l! To (i) The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN. Vemorandum Petroleum Concessions Limited have informed me that they wish to obtain permission for a landing at Muharraq aerodrome, the particulars of which are as follows Date of arrival October 24th. Passengers Crew Registered Owner Tvne of aircraft Registration Mark E. A. Satchell W.E.D. Cole (Oil field technicians) J. L. C. Banks F. W. Brown E. F. Walsha • • .. .. Pilot Engineer W/T Operator Iraq Petroleum Company De Havilland Twin Kngined Rapid. GAFFC 2. I have drawn the attention of the Company'a local representative to the provisions of the Air Navigation Regulations, of which I have provided him with a copy. 3. The Company are arranging for passports and visas through the Baghdad Legation. 4. Messrs. Satchell and Cole intend to proceed to Qatar, probably by launch; though they may possibly apply to me to approach the Shaikh of Qatar for permission to land there. In this case, they will require to land in Bahrain on their return, the date of which will necessarily be uncertain. 5 /- V, fl5. I aee no objection to the proposed flight, and should be grateful therefore if you would approach His Highness with a view to obtaining his sanction; and, if he approves, would furnish me with six copies of the special authorisation in time for the Company’s local representative to wire the would-be aviators to 'go ahead'. Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain,Form 103 C. 3.38. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS. BAHREIN g) CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) G. Legh-Jones R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidjj (U.S.A.) R. W. Se J. Ski 5 ^ PCL/GAQ.4/1814. K To H.B.M.*s Political Agent, Bahrain. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 20th October, 1938. Dear Sir, I.P.C. AIRCRAFT VISIT TO BAHRAIN With reference to conversations with Mr.Howes this morning Messrs. E.A.Satchell and W.E.D.Cole have asked for permission to land at Bahrain in a Company aeroplane and we shall be greatly obliged if you will issue the necessary permit. Permission was also requested for the aeroplane to land at Q#tar, but we have replied that owing to the shortness of time this cannot be arranged. According to present arrangements the aeroplane will leave Baghdad on Monday afternoon 24th October en route Bahrain via Basrah. The aeroplane will be carrying : Passengers: E.A.Satchell - Pipeline Superintendent, Iraq Petroleum Co.,Ltd. W.E.D.Cole - Fields Manager, Kirkuk; Iraq Petroleum Co.,Ltd. Pilot: J.L.C.Banks Engineer : F.W.Brown. W/T Onerator : E.F.Walsha. The aeroplane is one owned by the Iraq Petroleum Company, Ltd. and is a De Havilland twin-engined w Rapid«J» -2 - British registration mark GA.FFC. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of M CONCESSIONS LIMITED, 1No. 14-7 3-^ of 1357 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Shaaban 27, 1357 October 22, 1938 H. B. M ! s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: i / With reference to your memorandum No. C/649-10/12 dated 20th October 1938, His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain has no objection to the visit to Bahrain of the aircraft and 1 enclose herewith six copies of the opecial .authorisation which authorises the aircraft V w/VA to alight twice on the Muharraq aerodrome with the period of one month from this date. I would request you to ask the company’s Local Representative to advise us beforehand of the arrival of the aircraft in question. Adviser to the Government. Enclos:-GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. TERRITORY OF BAHRAIN SPECIAL AUTHORISATION FOR AIRCRAFT TO LAND IN MUHARRAQ/AND FLY OVER BAHRAIN. Aerodrome 1. The Shaikh of Bahrain hereby authorises the flight within the limits of Bahrain of the following aircraft of nationality. Registered owner. Type of aircraft. Registration marks. Iraq Petroleum Company. De Havilland Twin Engined Rapide G-AEFC / a ;—; 6T 2. This authorisation is limited to the periodylrom inclusive, and is granted subject to the following conditions. 10-38 to 23-11-38 both dates inclusive (To alight twice) from customs and excise legislation {%) The aircraft, their crews and passengers shall be liable to all the legal obligations which arise from general legislation/ and import and export regulations and any regulations which may be laid down for public safety as well as the air navigation regulations. (it) The aircraft shall not use as a place of landing or departure within Bahrain any place other than the aerodrome at Muharraq and the published conditions governing the use of the said aerodrome shall be observed. (m) This authorisation or a certified true copy of it shall be carried in the aircraft and be produced on demand for the inspection of any authorised person. Adviser to the Government. (Authorised by His Ebdc^teSi^aRBaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Al-Khalifah, Shaikh of Bahrain.) Bahrain, .QGtob.ex...I9 38.Form 103 C. 3.38. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE It PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) G. Legh-Jones R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser. C.B.E. , C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliro»j/'*v PCL/CAQ,. 4/1226. H.B.M.*s Political Agent, Bahrain. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 24th October, 1938. LA/lo. Dear Sir, I.P.G AIRGRAPT VISIT TO BA AE&amp;AIN With reference to our letter of 20th October recuesting you to grant permission for an I.P.C. aeroplane to 'land at Bahrain we would now inform you that we have received telegraphic intimation from Baghdad that Messrs. Satchell and Cole are arriving by Imperial Airways. We regret that you have unduly been put to the trouble of issuing a landing permit and would thank you for the steps taken.Confidential Political Agency, Bahrain, the 24th October 1938 No. C/662-10/12 From H. Weightman, Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain To Sir I hove been informed this morning that the * Iraq Petroleum Company^ aircraft, for which permission was granted in your letter No. 1473-30 dated ^e 27nd ( ctober 1938, is now not visiting Bahrain..^ 2. The Company apologize for the trouble caused, and have asked me to pass on their thanks lor the steps takan in connection with the issue of the special authorisation. 3. I am retaining one copy of the special authorisation for ray file, and return the remaining five copies herevvith. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain.Referencej- 11081 / 9 /ivjtr» Air Hcadquarterc, Britioii Forces in ’Iraq, HkHBAHIYA, 1 Iraq. 28iul October # 1983, Dear Sir, Attached hereto ore letters to the local authorities autnurislng the pilot of aii^craft 0/A*K # 0#U. of the PetroleiSLi Development (Trucial Coast) Coni &gt;any, to uplift fuel in emergency itoei Royal Air Force stocks. It will be noted that the amount is limited to S00 gallons petrol and 16 gallons oil, and that such uplifts can only be made in emergency and then on only one occasion from each Store. to the note that the pilot must settle all bills in respect of any native labour hired, at the time of call at the landing grounds. following places and keys to the petrol stores are held us shown*- I should like to draw your attention There ore no caretakers at the Officer Commanding No- 808 (qh) Squadron Basrah, -ditto- Officer Cparuiaiaing t llo* 84 (B) suaibah. Yours faithful , Copies to:- P litical Agent, 1SJSCAT lit leal Agent, BAHRKni. ■’* A.L.O. BAHREIN. Peti'oleum Dcvclopnent (Trucitd Coast) Ltd City-Oate House, Finsbury Square, London, i:,c. 3,— Form 103 C. 3.38. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN hJ CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE 1 /A v PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) G. Legh-Jones R. Cayrol, D.S.O.. D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) H. G. SelA'' (U.S.A.) R. W. Se J. Sklitos PCL/SxiD. 4/1E85. UEGENT BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 9th December, 1938. To H.B.K.’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, IRpvQ, PSTROLEUM TR^IMSPORT AlRCHa.PT / I’-i 1. With reference to our conversation on the -oecember, 1933. Our London principals inform us tha^ arrange ments were made with the India Office in edrly ...aj year for the use of our aircraft in tue ar^isian Gulf, Muscat, Dhofar, etc. \ ’ rx V a a ^ 2. Particulars of the Company aircraft which will pass through Bahrain probably on the 10th December en route to Sharjah are as under : \ Registered owner - Iraq. Petroleum fransport Go. Type of aircraft - Scion Senior four engined monoplane (land machine). Registration marks- G-^SCU We shall be grateful if formal permission^can be accorded for the machine to land in Bahrain and other Persian Gulf landing grounds as necessary. 3 The Company’s programme of air surveys as discussed with the India Office by our principals earlier in the year was assumed by them to have the approval of the India Office. If any further action is required by us locally we shall be glad to be informed. • • •73 - 2 - 4. We are assuming that Mr.Longrigg made any local arrangements necessary with the Political ^gent, Muscat during his stay there in October Sc early ITovemher of this year. r-\ Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of petrclhxj:.: cgi.^sioys lh-Hted, Copy to: Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., London. I'r.S.R.Longrigg, Dubai. rvConfidential No. C/756-10/12 Political Agency* Bahrain, the 12th December 1938. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government. BAHBA I N. I&lt; emorandum Petroleum Concessions Limited have informed me that they wish to obtain permission for one of their machines to land at S-uharraq aerodrome en route to Sharjah, The parti culars of the machine are as follows:- 2. The use of this aeroplane down the Coast has been approved by His Majesty's Government and I should be grateful therefore if you would approach His Highness with a view to obtaining his sanction to it landing here, and would flirnish me with six copies of the special authorisation. Date of arrival ii Registered Owner 10th December 1938 (probably) Iraq Petroleum Transport Co. Scion Senior four-engined monoplane (land machine) Type of aircraft Registration Mark G-AECU Political Agent, Bahrain., Confidential. dSL — ^ No. Bahrain, 19th Shawal, 1357. Bated, 12th Deer. 1938. w From To SlK, C. Balrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gplf. / H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. V* 4 &gt; i 'po /f - I have the honour to acknowledge your letter No. C/756-10/12 dated the 12th December 1938 and to f enclose herewith six copies of Special Authorisation for the Scion Senior four-engined monoplane of the Iraq Petroleum Transport Company. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Enclos. 6Cl^Q GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. TERRITORY OF BAHRAIN SPECIAL AUTHORISATION FOR AIRCRAFT TO LAND IN MUHARRAQ AND FLY OVER BAHRAIN. 1. The Shaikh of Bahrain hereby authorises the flight within the limits of Bahrain of the iollowing aircraft of nationality. Registered owner. Type of aircraft. Registration marks. Ir&amp;c transport Cc#Bpar*y. •&gt;cioa fourwen^ned aonoplan© {land suachlfiej G-ABCV 2. This authorisation is limited to the period from inclusive, and is granted subject to the following conditions. ' 10 l.n. oc ; , 0 1 • I A. 4 ^ vi. 1 (f) The aircraft, their crews and passengers shall be liable to all the lecal obl.Winn. ■nhtch arise from general legislation and import and export regulations and anv regulations^ ^ “ d ° Wn f01 ' PuMic safety ^ ^ ^ aHav^aSn m ^aee ir otke, “°,‘,, USe “ ? ^ of landin g or departure within Bahrain any place other than the aerodrome at Muharraa and fbn y governing the use of the said aerodrome shall be observed. h d COndltlons (in) This authorisation or a certified true copy of it shall be carried in the aircraft ami )e P r &lt;&gt;duced on demand for the inspection of any authorised person. Bahrain, «»•••• ••• «•«•••«•• »«.« * * ,J. Q U ' ( Adviser to the Government. (Authorised by His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Al-Khalifsh, Shaikh of Bahrain.)^CTN r, C.» V. S iklir Confidential ' ’ i^l T'l D.O. No. C/775-10/12 Dated the 15th v 'ecenrt&gt;ep 1938. /i .If Your letter No. PCL/3'D.4/1285 dated the 9th December 1938. 2 . I enclose herewith authorisations for your Company 1 s aeroplane to land In Bahrain. J must point out that appli cation was made somewhat late for this purpose. 3. /s for your third paragraph, no further formalities are required save that in terms of the letter from the India Cilice to Longrigg, No. P.Z. 6033/38 dated the 1st September 1938, I should be kept informed of plans for flights based / on and covering any part of the Trucial Coast and its hinter- / land. Yours sincerely f / u 7 k/ E. V. Packer, Esquire f Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, ^ Bahrain. i \ 71 /Form 103 C. 3.38. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS. BAHREIN PETROLEUM DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman. G.C.M.G. (Chairman) G. Legh-Jones R. Cayrol. D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fra*er. C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy h. A g''JJ;'S, PCL/SiU). 4/1299 R. W. Sellers i. Skllroy^ /Q'l'-**' CONCESSIONS CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE , 0 LIMITED H.B.M.*s Political Agent. Bahrain. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 17th December, 1938. Dear Sir, a IRAQ PETROLEUM TRANSPORT C^. AIRCRAFT you for your letter No.C/775-10/12 dated the 15th December, 1938. ' l .Ve observe that the authorization for G-ABCU to land in Bahrain only covers »the period up to the 31st December, 1938. ^ In our letter Ro*1285 dated the 9th December we asked if permission could be accorded for our machine to land in Bahrain and other Persian Gulf landing grounds as necessary• / + that the Bahrain authorization (up to 31/12/38) will not be sufficient to cover the free use of the aeroplane in the Gulf this season and we suggest the Government may be prepared to extend the period to cover 1939. It is certain that the machine will need on occasion to land at Bahrain if only d.n its return journey. We note that no further action is required from us regarding the fulfilment of the Company's programme of air surveys except that you should be kept informed of plans for flights based on and covering any part of the Trucial Coast and its hinterland. Vie are forwarding a copy of your abovementioned letter to Mr.Longrigg who will no doubt take any action • • •in this respect necessary Copy to: Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED, MAmGER. ^ Petroleum Concessions Limited, .London with copy of P.A.'s C/775-10/12 of 15.12.38. i^xed, Mr.S.H.Longrigg, Dubai ' n &amp; copy of authorization to be handed to the pilot of G-AECU.Confidential No. C/786-10/12 Jo Political Agency, Bahrain, the 20th December 1938. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Dovernment, B H B A_T N. Memorandum C lefei \io Reference correspondence ending with .your letter No. 1856-29, dated the 12th December 1938. 2. Petroleum Concessions Limited have now requested that a further authorisation covering the year 1939 may be issued for the use of their aeroplane. 3. I should be grateful therefore if you would approach His Highness with a view to obtaining his sanction to this request, and would furnish me with six copies of the special authorisation. Political Agent, BahrainNo. Bahrain, Bated, f q 2_ 2 J o 29th Shawal, 1357• 22nd December 1938, From C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Bahrain, Persian Gulf, I have the honour to acknowledge your letter No. C/786-10/12 dated 20th December 1938 and to en close herewith six copies of Special Authorisation for the Scion Senior four-engined monoplane of the Iraq Petroleum Transport Company, I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Adviser to the Government. Enclos. 6GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. TERRITORY OF BAHRAIN SPECIAL AUTHORISATION FOR AIRCRAFT TO LAND IN MUHARRAQ AND FLY OVER BAHRAIN. 1. The Shaikh of Bahrain hereby authorises the flight within the limits of Bahrain of the following aircraft of nationality. 2. This authorisation is limited to the period from , to _ inclusive, and is granted subject to the following conditions. 1 / 1/ 1 - » ~ C “• x J (*) The aircraft, their crews and passengers shall be liable to all the legal obligations which arise from general legislation ^nd import and export regulations and any regulations which may be laid down fq* *- public safety as well as the air navigation regulations. (it) The aircraft shall not use as a place of landing or departure within Bahrain any place other than the aerodrome at Muharraq and the published conditions governing the use of the said aerodrome shall be observed. (Hi) This authorisation or a certified true copy of it shall be carried in the aircraft and be produced on demand for the inspection of any authorised person. (Authorised by His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Al-Khaiifah, Shaikh of Bahrain.) Bahrain, Dated,... 19Confidential No. C/6-10/12 Political Agency, Bahrain, 5th January 1939. To The Local Manager, Petroleum Concesaions Limited, BAHRAIN Dear Sir, In accordance with your letter No. PCL/3AD.4/1299, dated the 17th De cember 1938, I enclose herewith auLhoriaations valid till the 31st December 1939 for your company’s aero plane to land in Bahrain. Yours faithfully, Captain, for Political Agent, BahrainCONFIDENTIAL BAHRAIN, PERSIAN GULF. PCL/CAq.4/387S. 21st February, 1939. Dear USE OF POL AIRCRAFT IW THE GULF. It is possible that Mr.Skliros or some senior Company official may find it desiraole to fly down to Bahrain or some other point in the Persian Gulf in our concession areas in Company f s aircraft. It is possible, too, that some emergency may arise involving the use of a Company plane. other planes besides G-AECTJ which is the only one witn an authorization to land in Bahrain (valid up to the end of 1939) . I L VV cular one of these machines to be used for the Persian Gulf for reasons you will no doubt realize and if you see no objection it would be convenient if all could be issued with the authorization to land, in the case of Bahrain on the usual printed permit. and without renewed reference to higher authority, we should be pleased, but if any difficulties are antici pated and the p] ‘ '* ‘ °' ur aircraft in the pplica- tion, we do not resent. Perhapi v/hat you think : 3* The Iraq Petroleum Transport Co. have three It is not possible to arrange for any parti- If this can be arranged without much trouble H. Weightman Es- The Agency, Bahrain.Confidential 0.0. No. C/131-10/12 Dated the 25th February 1939. •-ill you please refer to your letter No. PCL/CA0.4/ 3876 dated the 2iat February 1939 ? 2. I gather from this letter that your Company^ object is to obtain permission for the more or less unrestricted use of its aircraft in Bahrain and any concessional area up and down the Arab Coast f including presumably Nuscat. As you know ix^ls not a ratter which can be arranged locally and it is one in regard tc which an official approach by your Comoany to the India Office in the first instance will be necessary. 3. I might -.dd that the authorisation given for the Iraq Petroleum Transport Company^ plane G-AFCTT was for the specific purpose of geological exploration. Yours sincerely f (J c/\ V. Packer, Esquire, Petroleum Concessions Limited BahrainCOPY. (Received under India Office endt. No. Ext. 1146 dated iBth April 1942.) P.Z.2926/37. INDIA OFFICE WHITEHALL, S. W. 1. 18th Fay, 1937. Sir, In reply to your letter of the 24th Larch, No. P.C. 27/23/30, I am directed to inform you that His Majesty’s Government see no objection in principle to 'the use of aircraft for transport or survey in the Persian Gulf area, provided (a) that the consent of the Sheikh concerned is obtained beforehand and the area over which the Company would propose to fly explained to him, (b) that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf or the Political Agent concerned is kept in close touch with the.Company’s plans and is consulted as to the suitability of the aircraft^and equinment (e.g. wireless), which would in any case conform to the regulations regarding airworthiness etc. which apply in Bahrain (or Muscat), (c) that any air survey company which may be employed is a British firm of undoubted repute under entirely British direction and employing British nationals or natives of the Arab State concerned. 2. As regards the specific proposals of the Company, His Majesty's Government are of opinion, after consulting the local political authorities, that it would be best to postpone any air survey (or the use of aircraft for transport) on the Trcial Coast until thj* concessions have actually be$n obtained from the Rulers. The use of aircraft is provided for in the draft concessions, and when these are obtained there will be a ceriai v ‘ obligation on trie Rulers concerned to co-operate in the matter. But in the meanwhile it would not be possible to count on the Rulers' co-operation except as a special favour (for which they might expect some return), and it would appear undesiraole at this stage to ask more favours of them than is absolutely necessary. 3. The same reasons against any immediate action apply to Muscat with greater force, in view of the fact* that the negotiations with the Sultan have not Jjegun. 4. As regards Qatar, the previous permission of the Ruler is specifically required (under Article 6 of the Concession) ior the use of aircraft. His Majesty's Government see no objection to the Company approaching the Shaikh (through the local political authorities) for^the necessary permission^ but they are anxious pi at flights over the extreme southern section of the territory lying within the boundary of the oil concessions should, as far as practicable, be avoided or at any rate limited to a course lying well within the concessions line. They would also like to'be informed through the local Political authorities well in advance before any regular flights are begun in the southern area. 5: Since His Majesty's Government have had this matter under consideration, there have, as you know, been reports of differen arising between the Sheikh of *atar and certain tribesmen in the neighbourhood of Zub^rah. The Company will of course appreciate that these occurrences might necessitate some postponement of the approach to the Sheikh which is envisaged in the preceding paragraph. I am, etc. ,r / Confidential. bahrain^receipt. -«»•••«* Date.....;..,...,, PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. DO/C^.4/4051 Dated 1st September, 1945. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. My dear Bird, P.C.L. COUP AIT AIRCRAFT In 1938/1939 Company aircraft were permitted t operate in the Persian Gulf and necessary landings were mad^ at Kuwait, Bahrain and Sharjah. The planes were employed ojflrspecial jobs to transport senior Company staff to Bahrain and for geological exploration over the Trucial Coast and Muscat territora^^ that there was no objection to Company planes landing at Qatar and the Company could make the necessary approach to the Ruler as laid down in the Qatar Oil Concession. The India Office also agreed to the Company constructing its own landing ground adjacent to the field. Up to that time the India Office had not arranged for the issue of general regulations for civil aircraft in Qatar. 3. The matter has now been re-opened by Haifa consequent upon a London query, asking if our machines can be permitted to land at Kuwait (for refuelling), Bahrain and Qatar. 4. We should be very grateful for information on the following points:- (a) Can it be assumed that there is no objection from and in Muscat, i.e. in territories over which the Company holds oil agreements (excluding, of course, areas which may be specified by His Majesty’s Government from time to time where ownership is controversial). 2 . As regards Qatar the India Office in 1939 intimated His Majesty’s Government or any other official source to our planes landing at Kuwait, Bahrain and Qatar. Can similar landings be made on the Trucial Coast Contdr - 2 - (c) To whom should we make prior reference in respect of landings in various territories? (d) In what Shaikhdoms do general regulations for civil aircraft already exist and if non-existent what is the alternative procedure? permission to cover any number of landings at all places over a period of at least a year or more provided all planes to be used are listed on the respective permits? Company is free to proceed with the construction of its own landing ground at Qatar, if it so desires, acting on the India Office 1939 permission and that the R.A.F. and/or B.O.A.C. angles need not now be taken into account? place until might arise would be ne para 4(a) a the Politic could be tb (e) Will it be possible at this juncture to obtain general (f) Can it be assumed now that the war is over that the 5. 6 . Capt. R. E. R. Bird, Agency, Bahrain.Telegram Prom ’•S'* Political, Bahrain. To Galloway, Bagh-i-Shaikh, Shiraz* No. 498. Dated the 10th of September, 1945. In my absence Packer of Petroleum Concessions Limited addressed a number of queries to Bird regarding future operation of his Company’s aircraft in areas under your political control on Arab side of Persian Gulf. He asks for early * information on following point quote Can it be assumed that there is no objection from His Majesty’s Govern ment or any other official source to our planes landing at Kuwait, Bahrain and Qatar unquote. I may have submissions to make regarding last two sheikhdoms but meanwhile should be grateful if you would deal with query regarding Kuwait. Copy of letter will follow in due course. =P0LITICAL=SECRET D.O. No* C/904. Dated the 22nd September, 1945 Dear Colonel Galloway, / lose a copy of Packer’s Demi-official letter No. D0/&lt; 4021 dated the 1st September, 1945, to Bird which I mentioned in my telegram No. 498 dated the 10th September, 1945, to you. 2. Packer has a genius for writing portmanteau letters including the questions to cover every possible and impossible contingency and the copy enclosed is an example of this. After consulting my records, the following is the best I can do in the way of suggestions for replying to the questions at (b) Similar landings can be made on the Trucial Coast provided previous notice of the landing-grounds or areas in which landings will be made is given to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and his agreement to such landings obtained. (c) To the political Agent concerned. (d) Only in Bahrain. For other areas, previous reference to the political Agent concerned is all, that is required. (e) Before this question has been replied to, a list of the landing-grounds or areas in which it is proposed to land should be submitted.— (f) Yes. (Reference is Sir Trenchard Fowle's Express letter No. 171-3 dated the 13th March, 1939, to the Secretary of State for India). g. I should be glad if I could be informed whether I may reply to Packer as suggested and if a reply could also be given to him regarding the areas not included in the Bahrain Agency. paragraph 4 (a) There is no objection in principle. (The reference seems to be India Office letter No. P2.2926/37 dated the 18th May, 1937, received with India Office endorsement No. Ext.1146 of the 18th April, 1942.) L Yours sincerely, The Hon’ble Lt-Col ' ~ ‘ ^ ~ 1 Political Resident in the Persian Gulf i (Camp) Shiraz .GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. E C E £ T EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). L TMt i* an ORIGINAL mwige ttnl by AIR MAIL which provides a meant of communication mart expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated t on receipt, with the same expedition as if had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] m rqq q Bushire Jlft* ~ • 'JUsmla , the 8th October 1945. ^New-Ddhi 19 To Political Bahrain^/'*' Repeated Retaxandum London. foreign New Delhi. Political ’V^cat. Political Kuwait. ) with copy al letter under reference. From Britain Bushire. my W\r?T\ j [Clio : BAHRAIN RECE1 y t (l (A Date ..-!?].{?-! .4 Use of Aircraft W Petroleum Concession^ T Ltd Your letter No. C/904, dated 22nd September 1945. 2. The Shaikh of Kuwait has intimated that he has no objection to P.C.L. aircraft visiting Kuwait provided they comply with the air regulations in force. You may therefore reply to Packer as suggested, subject to the following modifications (b). Add “Flights and landings in Muscat territory should be subject to any restrictions that may be imposed by His Highness the Sultan relating to prohibited flying areas, low flying, etc.' (d). For “Only in Bahrain* 1 bubstitute “Only in Bahrain and Kuwait'• 3. A copy of your reply to Packer should be forwarded to this Office and to the authorities to whom this Express Letter has been repeated. Sd/- A.C. Galloway Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. . / for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. YG. (Signature) (Designation) s. 44. MGIPC—SI—2385(S&amp;P)MFP—(M-1744&gt;—3-12-40—20,000.&amp; i D.O. No. C/983. The 15th of October, 1945. My dear Packer, 4fe Jf please refer to^yotir No. DO/CQ.4/4021, dated the 1st September, 1945, to Bird. 2 . The replies to the questions in paragraph 4 of your letter under reference are as follows (a) Therfe is no objection in principle. (b) Similar landings can be made on the Trucial Coast provided notice of the landing grounds or areas in which landings will be made is given to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and his agreement to such, landings obtained. Flights and landings in Muscat territory should be subject to any restrictions that may be imposed by His Highness the Sultan relating to prohibited flying areas, low flying, etc. (c) To the Political Agent concerned. (d) Only in Bahrain and Kuwait. (e) Before this question has been replied to, a list of the landing grounds or areas in which it is proposed to land should be submitted. (f) Yes. 1 % E.V. Packer, Esq., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., r a h r a 1 n. Yours sincerely, a j NS. Copy sent to India Office, Govt, of India, P P A., Muscat, and P.A. , Kuwait, under endorsement No. C/985, dated the 15th of October, 194o, with reference to Residency X.L. No. 339-S, ^ated 8.1 . • R. ^ • 45 .- v DC/C^ 4/4059 My dear Bird, i 3 Petroleum. Concessions Ltd., Bahrein, 15th October, 1945. No Confidential. ^AHRAJN RECEIP^. Reference i,Ty No. DO/C^.4/4021 dated 1st September 1945, Haifa have enquired if we have any information to pass on to then. An assurance that vompany machines can land at Nuvm.it, ?N: r in .nd Sharjah provided the usual regulations applicable are complied ia ith, would make a good interim reply. It is probable that some of our V.I.Ps are contemplating visits. Yours sincerely, Capt. R. E. R. Bird Agency, / Bahrein.€ DO/CQ,. 4/4041 Petroleum Concessions Ltd Dated 16th October, 1945, • * My dear Pelly, Reference your DO.u/983 dated the 15th October 1945. I am sorry to trouble you again but it would be a great help to us at this juncture if we can be given an assurance reference our respective sub-paras {e) that we can rely on obtaining general permission to cover any number of journeys over a period of at least a year in respect of the undementioned places:- •w*'' Kuwait Bahrain * Uatar i Sharjah IJJubai and the Landing Ground near Muscat town itself. Any other locations where special conditions or circumstances are involved couMbe the subject of special applications pending further^idormation on the proposed movements of our exploration'pearties. Meanwhile i enclose a copy of our interim telegram to Haifa lours sincerely 4^ n.a.M’s Political Agent, .Bahrein. jlucI:POLITICAL AGENCY, ^ BAHRAIN* Please refer to your Demi-official letter No. DO/CQ.4/4041, dated the 16th of October, 1945, to pelly. 2. I should be glad to know the reason for the inclusion of Dubai where there are no alighting areas other than for flying boats. Yours sincerely, E.^ Packer, 4 Messrs. Esq., M.B.iii*, Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., B a h r a i n.DO/CQ.4/4050 2 &gt;*\' M T’lpqt petroleum concessions ltd. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. 7tli November, 1945. 1'ty dear Colonel, Many thanks for your D.O.No.C/1050 dated tne 6th November 1945. The reasons I included. Dubai were (a) the use of a flying boat by the Company, conceivably on charter, although unlikely, not be outside the bounds of possibility, (b) at some future date the Company might find it convenient to have a landing ground for land planes in the Dubai territory to serve an oil camp if only in emergencies. 3. No importance need be attached to either of these aspects particularly at the present time, and if there ° r difficulty in respect of Dubai, this shaikhdom could be taken out of the list. Yours sincerely, Lieutenant Colonel A.C.Galloway H.B.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. O.B.E.,POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN EXPRESS LETTER Prom Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire To No. C/1065. Dated the 11th November, 1945 Reference Pelly^s letter No. C/983 of the 15th October, 1945, to packer forwarded under endorsement No. 6/985, dated the 15th October, 1945. He agrees that Dubai could be taken out of the list as there are at present no alighting areas other than for flying boats. I see no object in this since conceivably the company may charter a flying- boat or find it convenient to use a landing area to serve an oil camp in an emergency. 3. I therefore propose to ask for the general permission for landings in Bahrain and Qatar and to inform the Shaikhs of Sharjah and Dubai that these may take place in their respective territories. I shall await your confirmation before taking action. 4. Packer has asked for an assurance that a like permission will be given as regards Kuwait and Muscat. I should be grateful for material for a reply. 5. Packer adds that any other places where special conditions or circumstances are involved could be the subject of special applications pending fuller information on the proposed movements of P.C.L. explora tion parties. 2 Packer has now written to say that P.C.L would like general permission over a period of at least a year to land in the following placess- Kuwait Bahrain Qatar Sharjah Dubai Qatar ^ Sharjah £ ' and the landing ground near Muscat town (Sd.) A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. NSGOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This in an ORIGIN A L message, sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] No. 937-S. To Repeated Bushire Dated Simla Nett Ddfti ’ the Political Bahrain Retaxandum London Foreign New Delhi Political Muscat Political Kuwait Persian Gulf Residency. 19th November 1945. . ) ) with copy of Bahrain ) Express Letter under ) reply Reference 1945. your my Use of aircraft by Petroleum Concessions Limited Your Express Letter No. C/1065 dated 11th November bait :A' ; RECEIPT./ :o Paragraph 3. I agree. E 5 * . Paragraph 4. You may give assurance as regards Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat, has been asked to obtain concurrence of Sultan and a further communication will follow. Sd/- Geoffrey Prior Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. YG, {Signature) (Designation s. 44. MFP—1015 8&amp;P—(M-1870)—9-2-39—20,000.86/20 Dated To Telegram No From Q Political Resident, 3\ Political Agent, Muse* 17th November 1945# 1686 Correspondence ending with Bahrain endorsement No. C/985 October 15th. Facilities for P.C.L. aircraft. Request has now been received from Company for general permission over a period of at least one year to use i landing ground at Beit al Falaj. 3* Please approach Sultan and telegraph result. Company has right to use aircraft under Article 13 (a) of concessiorfs. You should inform Sultan of restrictions mentioned in (b) of endorsement under reference. CON FIDENTIAL Persian Gulf Residency, Copy forwarded with compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain with reference to his Express Letter No. C/1065 dated 11th November 1945. Bushire No. 938 - S 19th November 1945GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. Conf icentia.l. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. Thi$ an ORIGINAL mesBMB sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication mors expeditious than the ordinary miil and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition at if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it it drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] ho. 937-b, dated the 19th November, 1945. Please inform Petroleum Concessions, Limited, (a) that the sultan of Muscat has no objection to the use of the Beit al Falaj aerodrome by the Company's aircraft, (b) that the Company should approach the Royal Air Force, by whom the aerodrome is maintained, through the Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain, for permission to use the landing ground, and for information regarding its serviceability and the types of aircraft for which it is suitable, and (c) that the Lultan has requested that the Company should approach him airect in such matters, to which course no political objection is seen, but that it is incumbent on the Company to keep the Political A^ent informed. 2. V.ith regard to (b) above please inform the Royal Air Force through the Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain, that there is no political objection to the use of the aerodrome by the Company. No. 95o-s Dated Bushi re, Sdnta , 23rd November, 1945. ^ . New Delhi * To Repeated Re t ay an c; urn, London. Foreign, New Delhi. Political, Muscat. Use of Aircraft by Petroleum Concessions. Ltd . In continuation of last sentence of my Express Letter Sd• GEOFFREY PRIOR. Political Resident, Persian Gulf ATT LAI'EL S. 44. (Designation) MGIPC—SI—2385(S&amp;P)MFP-{M-1744)—3-12-40—20,000.D.O. No. C/1090 Hie 29th of November, 1945 My dear packer, Please refer to your letter No. D0/CQ«^/4041, dated the 16th October, 1945, in which you asked for an assurance that you would obtain general permission for landings at Kuwait, Bahrain, Qatar, Sharjah, Dubai and at Beit al FalaJ. at Kuwait and Muscat and will inform you concerning the other places when I have received replies from the Shaikhs concerned. (a) that the Sultan of Muscat has no objection to the use of the Beit al Falaj aerodrome by the company’s aircraft, (b) that the Company should approach the Royal Air Force, by whom the aerodrome is main tained, through the Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain, for permission to use the landing ground, and for information regarding its serviceability and the types of aircraft for which it is suitable, and (c) that the Sultan has requested that the Company should approach him direct in such matters, to which course no political objection is seen, but it is incumbent on the Company to keep the Political Agent informed. E.V. Packer, Esquire, M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., I am now to give you this assurance with regard to landings 2. In regard to Muscat I am to say Yours sincerely, \ BAHRAIN NS.No. C/1091. POLITICAL AGENCY, The BAHRAIN. 29th November, 1945. To Bie Air Liaison Officer, B a h r a i (^fo) MJSMORANDTTWL ^ ^ Reference sub-paragraph 2(b) of my Demi-official letter No. c/1090, dated the 29th of November, 1945, to Mr. Packer, copy attached. There is no political objection to the use of the aerodrome by the Company; NS. Political Agent, Bahrain.Extract from the Political Agent's D*0*No.c/1090 dated the 29th of November, 1945, to Mr. Packer of Messrs. petroleum Concessions, Limited. xx XX XX XX In regard to Muscat I am to say (a) that the Sultan of Muscat has no objection to the use of the Beit al Falaj aerodrome by the Company's aircraft, (b) that the Company should approach the Royal Air Force, by whom the aerodrome is main tained, through the Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain, for permission to use the landing ground, and for information i regarding its serviceability and the types of aircraft for which it is suitable. xx XX XX XX7 No. C/1092 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN The 29th November, 1945. To The Acting Adviser to in Government, - Bahr a i n. MEMORANDUM . \ / Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Limited, have informed me that they wish to obtain a general per- a period of at least a year. 2. The Hon’ble the Political Resident sees no objection to these landings and I should be grateful therefore if you would approach His Highness with a view to obtaining the sanction required. 3. i will supply you with the particulars regarding the type of aircraft to be employed, their registration marks, etc., when His Highness’ sanction for these landings has been obtained. mission for landings in Bahrain by their aircraft over Political Agent, Bahrain NS./?Jf\ C&gt;o s fc c a s T. fJBLJftlkfc From t TbP under Beoret^ry to the &lt;#&gt;vemBK&gt;nt of Indi^ In the External Affaire mprtmnt* xo i The Hon*ble the Political aidant in the Persian Bashirc • Memorandum Po« D» 16035*^ 9 ^ # /45» ipkted TTev Delhi 3 , the M December 1945 # SUBJECT Uee of aircraft by retroleum cemo^art aa, Ltd. ConHdential. your expreee letter Tfo.96B-S dated the?3rd iTovember 194S. S 3? 2. It would be useful from the operation al stand point, particularly in connection with the aircraft distraus operations which might be required in the Persian Gulf ^ to obtain tha following information regarding the Oom^nj 1 » organiea l ion (2) eh^re the airereft are normally baaed* (3) particulars of radio apparatus installed* (4) Narn^s and p^rticuU rs of pilots employed* If you see no o^octlcn) the iOlltlc&amp;l Agent 9 Bahrain, may be requested to make the necessary enquiries and to coojnunlcate the* result to the Goweramtxit of India* (1) dumber and type of aircraft operated* Sd/- T*E* Brownsdon. under Secretary to the cjovt* of India* Agent, Bahrain* By order, etc*, Under Secretary to the Govt, of India* JJks*@&gt; £&gt;[ .- 1 0 ^'* letter dated 30th Dil Hiiiah 13o4 0-12-45) from the Shaikh of Dubai to J the Political Agent, Bahrain. ZL/.'\ , Confidential. .».C. I -'J / o 1 A ’ &gt; ‘ Bahrain receipt. /'—V' KoJ.JhS.. four kind letter dated 25th Dll Hijjah 1364 corresponding to 29th November 1945 has been received and I have noted that within the 13 next months the aeroplanes belonging to the Petroleum Concessions Limited will land at Dubai, ihere is no harm and we are the same.0 ^ Translation of letter lo.4 of U65, dated 2nd It'uharram 1365 (7-12-45) from the Shaikh of Sharjah to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.C. Confidential. BAHRAIN RBCEIPTy KQ.LJ.kb ...Data.. your letter I.o.C/1094, dated I have rece 25th Dil Hijjah corresponding to 29th November 1945 containing your information to me regarding the landing of the aeroplanes belonging to the Petroleum Concessions Limited at Sharjah aerodrome which have got the approval of His Majesty’s Government. I have noted it. U.E.4&gt;r POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN Please refer to my letter C/1090, dated the 29th November, 1945. I now able to give yon this assurance with regard to landings at Dubai and Sharjah. E.V. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., vs. Petroleum Concessions, ^ B A H R A T M. Yours sincerely NS.Translation of letter dated 14th iuharram 1365 (19-12-45) from H.E. the Shaikh of ^atar to the Political %gent, Bahrain. 4 , A y — Confidential. BAHRAIN RSCEIRT. . I// I have/received Your Excellency's letter a.C. No.C/10^3 dated 29th November 1945 (2oth Oil Hijjah 1364), contents of which I have noted, ivlr. Packer of Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited has asked Your Excellency if we would allow the landing at Qatar of aeroplanes belong n ing to the Petroleum Concessions Limited for a period exceeding a year at least. There is no harm about it, but I request your Excellency to inform zr.Packer to discuss this quostion with us, so that we may know the period required for landing of the aeroplanes and as the above aeroplanes are civil, it is necessary for an agreement with him (Mr.Packer) in accordance with the normal principals and Inshallah an agreement will be reached by both^T ♦ yi/f • U.E.&lt;g&gt; H PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN DO/C^.4/4092 My dear Colonel, SITUATION 30TH DECEMBER 1945 ON THE USE OF COMPANY AIRCRAET IN THE PERSIAN 5^* PULE . c _ /Many thanks for your two letters DO.C/1090 and C/il38 dated the 29th November 1945 and 24th December 1945 respectively. 2. The situation to date appears as under (a) Kuwait (i) G-eneral permission for landings has been obtained by you for us. (ii) It will be necessary for us to submit the registered numbers of all aircraft likely to land for inclusion on the Kuwait official licencing form. It is assumed that this form is similar to that used by Bahrain. It is gathered that this list is to be submitted to the Ruler of Kuwait through the Political Agent, Kuwait, and printed forms are required if available. This form of license merely contains clauses on fees and miscellaneous regulations for the air craft using the landing ground. No difficulty, therefore, is anticipated in respect of Company aircraft landings. (b) Bahrain (i) G-eneral permission has not yet been arranged by you for us. (ii) As soon as the general permission is obtained lists of aircraft will presumably have to be submitted through you or direct to enable a2 DO/CQ,.4/4092 (contd.) Bahrain license for any number of journeys over any period to be issued by the Bahrain Government who use a special prints license ibrm. (c) Qatar You have not yet confirmed general permis sion for landings and Qatar apparently has not framed any form of license. In these circumstances the Company would like to know the procedure to be substituted, if any. If there is no form of license perhaps lists of aircraft could be dispensed with. It will be remembered that in the Qatar Concession Article 6 states that the Shaikh T s specific permission must be obtained on every occasion for the use of aerial transport. In this connection Article 6 of His Majesty ! s Government’s agreement with the Company reads as under: 'Any right given to hie Company under its agreement with the Shaikh to utilize means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil air craft made by the Shaikh on the advice of His Maje sty’s Gove rnmen t'. Shaikh’s restriction on the Company was apparently made in order to leave control in the hands of the British Government end in these circumstances and as the Shaikh has repeatedly reiterated to the Company representative that he has no objection, there should be little difficulty in obtaining the general permission desired. (d) SharjahDO/CQ.4/4092 (contd.) (e) Dubai (i) General permission for landings lias been obtained by you for us. (ii) The licensing documents or the Shaikh 1 s regulations in lieu are renuired. (f) Muscat we (i) Again general permission has been arranged in that the Sultan has no objection but in addition, in this case of Muscat, permission to use the landing ground must also be obtained from the R.A.F. This leads us to the assumption that regulations or licenses must be settled with the R.A.F. If this is so it would seem that it is possible that there are still some forma lities to be agreed to with the R.A.F. at other landing places as well such as Sharjah. Many thanks for your help and apologies for the trouble are giving you. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, G.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to Mr. G.E.Heseldin, Iraq Petroleum Oo. Ltd. , Hai fa.V PCq.4/4096 5th January, 1946 To Air Liaison Officer Bahrai n* Dear Sir, USE OF MUSCAT LANDING GROUND Af WrT SL FAtif r^C.L.AlP craft V'q recently approached H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, on the subject of obtaining general permission for Company aircraft to make landings as necessary on the landing ground at Muscat. In his reply the Political Agent informed us that H.H. the Sultan of Muscat has no objection to the use of the Beit el Falaj aerodrome by the Company’s aircraft as far as he (the Sultan) is concerned. The Political Agent further instructed us to approach the Poyal Air Force (through you) by whom the aerodrome is maintained for general permission for any Company aircraft to use the landing ground at any time and for information regard ing its serviceability and types of aircrafts for which it is suitable. We shall be very grateful if you will arrange for the general permission required and give us the information you think we need. If any form of printed or typed permit is in use perhaps you could send us copies with instructions as to procedure. In connection with this license or permit the Company will, if required, furnish registered numbers and types of the machines likely to be used and keep the Air Force informed of any changes. Yours faithfully, For &amp;, on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Copy to H.B.M’s Political A-gent, Lem a « jl** . Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date..fe.T.i7 * PC'}.4/409? 5th January, 1946 To Hie Highness Sultan Saiyid Said Bin Taimur, Sultan k Ruler of Muscat and Oman, The Palace, Muscat, Your Highness, As Your Highness is aware we recently approached H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, with a view to obtain ing general permission for landings on Muscat landing ground. We were subsequently informed by Political Agent, Bahrain, that Your Highness has no objection. In these circumstances, we are therefore, approaching the Royal Air Force by whom, we understand, the aero drome is maintained for general permission to use the landing ground. We have the honour to be Your Highness’s most obedient servants, For k on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (OMAN 3c DHOFAR) LTD. ( SgcL ) i' MANAGER Copy to H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain ACMPETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF DQ/PCQ,.4/4098 Stl ~ 1946. My dear Bird, We are writing as indicated by Col. Galloway to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat on the question of the use by company aircraft of the Muscat landing ground. I enclose a cover and if there is no objection should be grateful if this could be sent by your Agency bag to avoid delay. Yours sincerely, Capt. R.S.R.Bird The Agency, Bahrain.e NO. C/61. To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 12th of January, 1946. The Hon*ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. MEiuORANDUT^ . Reference correspondence resting with your ^ Express Letter No.- 958-S, dated the 23rd of November, 1945. 2. I enclose copies of the marginally noted cor- 1. nr. Packer's letter No. DO/CQ.4/4092, dated the | respondence. 30th of December,1945. | 2. Sheikh of Qatar's letter dated 19.12.1945. ' fo * 3. I should 3. Agency D.O. No. C/62, dated the 12th January, 1946, to Mr. Packer. J be grateful for instructions with regard to paragraphs 4, 5, and 6 of my letter to Mr. Packer. 4. In regard to paragraph 7 ibid, I should be grateful to know whether I am to approach the Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain, or whether you will approach the R.A.F. Political Agent, Bahrain. NS.D.O. No. e/62. rhe 12th of January, 1946. My dear Packer, you please refer to your letter No. D0/CQ.4/ 4092, dated the 30th of December, 1945* ' 2. As regards 2(a)(ii):- The matter has been referred. It seems unlikely that printed forms will be available. . gards 2(a)(ii):- The matter has been It seems unlikely that printed forms will 3* As regards (b):- permission has not yeo been received. 4. As regards (c):- I enclose a copy of the Sheikh of Qatar’s reply. It would seem best if you were to discuss the matter as the Sheikh suggests after which His Majesty’s Government would be asked to convey approval. I am asking the Hon’ble the Political Resident, if he approves. 5. As regards (d) I suggest that you need not raise the question of licensing documents but if you wish me to do so I will. A fee of Rs.5/- per landing is payable to the Sheikh under the Civil Air Agreement. 6. (e) Dubai as per (d). 7 . (f). i am making enquiries if anything further is required in the way of formality with the R.A.F. to cover Doha and Sharjah, Dubai and Bahrain as well as Jfuscat. Yours sincerely. &amp;.V. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs, petroleum concessions, Ltd., Bahrain.3 «/// . Ho. of 1265 Office of the Adviser to tiie Government, Bahrain Dated, 10th Safer, 1365 January 13, 1946. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo randum: - Reference your memorandum No. C/109B dated 29th November 1945. His Highness Shaikh Sulman has sanctioned the landing in Bahrain of the aircraft mentioned therein. Ag. Adviser to the Government. S.Z. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.e?7pl POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN I). 0. ;o. c/79. The 15th of January. 1946. My dear Packer With reference to .my letter No. c/62 dated the 12th January, 1946, paragraph 3, ' T is Hignness has now sanctioned the landing of P.C.L. aircraft in Bahrain. No.C/80 Forwarded with compliments to the Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bushire with reference to Agency Memo.No.C/61 dated the 12th January, 1946. Yours sincerely. V. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs.Petroleum Concessions, Ltd.,r I 0 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD * BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULP. 19th January, 1946. My dear colonel, Many thanks for all your letters regarding the use of the Company aircraft in the Persian Gulf and for all the trouble you have taken. 2. Am I correct now^in assuming that Company aircraft can land at Kuwait, Bahrain, Sharjah, Dubai, Muscat, without prior application to the Political for permission; also with the exception of Bahrain it is not necessary for the Company to obtain the printed form of authorisation which would include the registered numbers of all the aircraft which might make landings. o, 1 note that the Ruler of Qatar has no objection but wants some more information from the Company. As regards la tar, the matter is not urgent in that the Company has not yet constructed its landing ground and it needs to be con firmed that Doha landing ground is suitable for the types of aircraft to be used by the Company. 4.^ On receipt of your reply we propose to notify our Haifa principals that Company aircraft can be used with immediate effect as regards permission to land at Persian Gulf landing grounds with, of course, compliance with current regulation on procedure, fees, etc. b. enclosed is a draft telegram which we propose to send to our General Manager in the Near East, Haifa, and acting on which he might send Company aircraft to Bahrain, etc. Mill you please confirm that this telegram is in order. DO/PCQ.4/4114 Yours sincerely, Enel. Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, O.B.B., H.B.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Confidential. Bahrain receipt. *°. 1 °&lt;.draft Baspetco Basrah Following for Heseldin Situation to date regarding use company Aircraft general permission received landings Kuwait Bahrain Sharjah Dubai Muscat fullstop Suggest Company pilots however should be satisfied that landing grounds suitable to their type aircraft fullstop Shaikh Qatar no objection but no suitable landing ground yet constructed adjacent Company locations fullstop So far Bahrain only have printed authorisation forms covering one year but suggest advantageous we have here description and registered numbers of all Company aircraft to be used = Packer =!).0. No. C/88 '?] 'he 20vh of January, 1946. / My dear Packer, The Government of India are collecting particulars, in connection v/ith distress operations, of aircraft and pilots likely to be used in the Gulf. T \'ith this in view I should be grateful if you would supply information on the normally based. following points:- (1) Number and type of P.C.L. aircraft to be used. (3) Particulars of radio apparatus installed. (4) Names and particulars of pilots to be employed Yours sincerely. &lt;1 E.Y. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Limited B A H R A I K. NS.No. c/89. 1 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 20th January, 1946, To The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . MEMORANDUM . Reference my memorandum No. o/6l dated the 12th January, 1946. ^ C3 2. I enclose a copy of P.c.L. letter No. DO/ PCQ.4/4114 (and its enclosure) dated the 19th January 1946 and would be grateful to know whether I am to give Mr. PacKer the assurance and con firmation asked for. I should be grateful for a telegraphic reply. £• NS. Political Agent, Bahrain.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. li In BAHRAI N PERSIAN GULF. £2nd January, 1946. My dear Colonel, will you please refer to your c/88 dated the 20th January, 1946. I have referred your queries to our General Manager in the Near JSast, Haifa. Meanwhile, you will rememher that the company wish to use company aircraft in the Persian Gulf landing at Kuwait, Bahrain, Sharjah, Dubai, Muscat as necessary. Q,atar will also come into the picture when a suitable company landing ground is constructed. It would seem that at this juncture, at any rate, Qatar is the only location where company air-port facilities will be needed as B.O.A.C. or K.A.F. (Muscat) have all that is necessary at other landing grounds. S-6&gt;o. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway,. O.B.E., H.B.M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. copy to: Iran petroleum Co. Ltd., Haifa, with copy of Political Agent’s C/88 of 20/1/46, to furnish information required. Confidential. BAHRAIN' RECEIPT. N«...1'AI * Telegram G.T.C From Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. To No. 145 Dated the 29th received 30th January, 1946. &lt; 5 'b S • &lt;£) * y / Your letters Nos.C/61 and C/89 of January 20th. Qatar . P.C.L. should endeavour to obtain permission by exchange of letters referring to Article VI of Oil Concession. Approval of His Majesty's Government can then be sought. 3* Sharjah and Dubai . No licences are necessary. Information communicated appears sufficient. Mu scat . P.C*L.yshould proceed as instructed in my express Letter No.953-S of November 23rd. 5. As some landing grounds are maintained by R.A.F. you should inform R.A.F. through Air Liaison Officer that there is no’ political objection to P.C.L. using them. P.C.L. should be advised to obtain technical information regarding landing grounds direct from R.A.F. / « No objection to your and confirmation mentioned in your letter No.C/89 PRIOR = LEI. I.R.No.31.D.O. No. C/122. The 2nd of February, 1946 My dear Packer, 2 . please refer to correspondence ending with your No. DO/PCQ.4/4144 dated the 19th January, 1946. (a) As regards Qatar you should endeavour to obtain permission by an exchange of letters with the Shaikh referring to Article VI of the Oil Concession. The approval of His Majesty’s Govern ment can then be sought. (b) As regards Sharjah and Dubai, I con firm that no licences are necessary. I am informing the Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain, that there is no political objection to P.C.L. using any landing ground in the Arab Shaikh- doms which is maintained by the Royal Air Force and advise you to obtain technical information regarding these landing grounds direct from the R.A.F. In view of the above I am to give you the assurance and confirmation asked for in your letter under reference. Yours sincerely E.V. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Limited, BAHRAIN . NS.No. C/123. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd February, 1946. To The Air Staff Liaison Officer, B A HRAIN. Memorandum- 0 jn continuation of my memorandum No. c/1091 dated the 29th of November, 1945. 2. I have now to inform you that there is no political objection to the use by Messrs, petroleum concessions, Limited, of any landing ground in the Arab sheikhdoms which is main- tained by the Royal Air Force. 3. I am advising Messrs. Petroleum concessions, Limited, to obtain technical information regarding these landing grounds direct from the Royal Air Force. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.My dear Colonel, With reference to your D 10th January, 1946, I enclose memo No.GF/E/a/2265 dated the furnishes the information you The delay is regretted. ^ € ^ «- PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULF. 7th March, 1946. .O.No.c/88 dated the a copy of our Haifa 4th February 1946, which requir e. Yours sincerely, Enel. Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, H.B.M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. [*' y' Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Dj.teCOPY IRAQ, PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. MEMORANDUM From: HAIFA Mail Division MANAGEMENT. To: PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD.,BAHREIN. Memo No .GF/E/a/2265 Subject: USE OF AIRFIELDS IN PERSIAN GULF Date 4th February, 1946 . Reference your letter D0/PCQ,.4/4118 of 22nd January 1946 to H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, of which you sent us a copy. I The information required by the P.A. in his letter to you, D.O. No. c/88 of Jan. 20th 1946 is :- (1) Five (5) D-H 89As. Registration Letters : G-AGOR G-AGOP G-AGDP G-AGTM G-AGTN (2) The aircraft at the moment are based at Haifa. They will probably be based at Bahrein when detached for duty in the Persian Gulf, until an airfield is prepared at Qatar whey they will be based there. It is the intention at a later date to have air craft permanently based in the Gulf area and the base will probably be at Basra. Full information on this matter will be passed to the Political Agent as and when the changes occur. (3) Radio Apparatus installed in al 1 aircraft is for Telegraphy and/or Telephone. Fixed and Trailing Aerials are fitted. Transmitters are Type AD77. Medium and short Wave. Receivers are Type AD6872C. ” w ' ' Call signs used are Registration letters of air craft . (4) Pilots are :- Messrs. F.R.Tomkins. K. Lingford. E.P. Cook * R.M.Hackney R.H.McIntosh * J.O.Penrose. All the above hold t B T Licences. Those marked * hold 2nd Class Navigations Certificates. It would be of value to our Aviation Department if you could let us have the amount of fuel stock held at the various airfields under consideration, together with informa tion regarding refuelling facilities at each place. (Sgd.) J.J.Page c.c. Mr . He s e1din.CONFIDENTIAL. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No. C/269. The llth of March? 1946. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments ,to: NAME &amp; DATE. SUBJECT. The Hobble the political Residen in the Persian Gulf, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned - 'documents REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: r Residency Memorandum No.14-3 dated the 5th of January^ 1946* Descri p- t -p Qn 0 p Enclsoure . 1 P.C.L. 1 PLANES.Governrasnt of India. Sxternal Affaire Department Biorasa Letter. From t Foreign, Nee Delhi,3. To Britain. Bushire, Repeated Political, Bahrain.*/ NO.D.16S3-UB/46. Dated , £ March 1946. S. Foreign memorandum No »D .16035 MS/45 dated the 14th December 1945. Use of aircraft by Petroleum Concessions Limited. 2. Grateful to knot ehen reply may be expected. The issue of the above has been authorised. Under Secretary to the Government of India. XJUL- Confidential. BAFn* UN - RECEIPT. * —/.'....Date 3. 0D.O. No.C/560. My dear Packer, Please refer to your letter No.PCQ.4/4227 dated the 22nd May, 1946. The 30th of May, 1946. 2. His Majesty*s Government require me to refer to them again after the exchange of letters between yourselves and the shaikh of Qatar has been completed. In the meantime, therefore, it would not be appropriate for you to take the action you con template in your last paragraph. Yours sincerely, L, /• Packer, Messrs. Esq., M.B.E., Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. NS.CONFIDENTIAL PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RA IN PERSIAN GULF. My dear Colonel, DO/PCQ,. 4/4254 2nd June 1946 Will you please refer to your jmo. C/560 dated the 30th of May 1946. It is very probable that our Company planes will wish to land in Qatar during the next month or so and possibly before the formali ties and final approval by H.M.O. are completed in respect of general permission. In view of the fact that the Ruler has already agreed to general landings, I am wondering if you would agree to an interim procedure by which we give you prior notice of each proposed landing, but dispense with notifications to the Ruler. As far as we can see, no useful purpose could be served by the Company sending motor transport from Dukhan camp to Doha and back, a journey of 130 miles, to ask for a permission which the Shaikh from his side has already granted. Our proposal would leave control of each landing in your hands until h.M.Gt. is ready to regularise general permission. lours sincerely Lt.-Col. A.C.Calloway, O.B.E., ■ti.b.^'s Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GULF. DO/QCQ,. 4/4278 6th June, 1946 My dear Colonel, ^^r,, — CEMJ^RxlL PEHIvlISSION FOR COMPANY AIRCRAFT TO LAND _ffl_^TAH p ^ v ' In continuation of my No.C^CQ.4/4225 dated the 22nd of May 1946 addressed to the Shaikh of G^atar, of which I sent you a copy. ^ r I enclose a copy of the Shaikh^ reply, from which you will see that he is postponing confirmation of his verbal agreement to general- landings although he does not repudiate it. His intention is apparently to try to use this general permission to force the Company to comply with certain of his demands which are under consideration and entail reference to London. It was my first intention to address the Shaikh again before writing to you, but, as you are visiting Qatar within the next two or three days I am sending you a copy of ny No.0,00,.4/4257 -which is a second attempt to get the Shaikh to confirm his verbal promise. I shall be most grateful if you can settle the matter with the Ruler when you see him. If the Shaikh takes the view that favours should be reciprocal, it should be remembered that he has just taken an advance of five lakhs, his ice machine, Buick cars and Chevrolet utility are all presents from the Company, and more Buick cars are en route. Yours sincerely, Ends.2 Confidential. Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, O.B.E., H.B.M* s Political Agent, Bahrain.COPY (Translation) From: Abdulla bin Qasim al Thani, R.'. To: The most respected, the Manager of P.D.Q,. Ltd. Compliments - r 1 I have received your kind letter jno.QCQ,. 4/4225 dated May 22nd, 1946. In view of our interview with you on May 11, you have only referred to certain things and left the remainder, while we were expecting reference to them all. This being the case, we are awaiting information from you about all our discussions which took place on the mentioned date. After looking them over, we shall form an opinion on the matter which we tell you of later on. Final compliments - Seal Abdulla bin Qasim Date: DJamada 11/27/1365 May 28/1946.CONFIDENTIAL © PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. B A H R A I N PERSIAN GULF. DO/ Q,CQ,. 4/ 4313 23rd June, 1946 My dear Colonel, ^ ' CENKRAL PEHHI^IOn FOR COMPANY AlKCHAbl* T’Q^AND IN QA’TAK Will you please refer to my D0/Q,CQ,.4/4278 dated the 6th June 1946. We have had another evasive letter from the Ruler of Qatar (copy attached; which indicates that he still intends to withhold v{ritten con firmation as explained in para 2 of my abovementioned letter/^Ruler♦s last letter was probably written before your visit and we shall be very interested to hear if the matter came under discussion during your stay. As far as the Company is concerned, we have already protested against the nonfulfilment of his verbal promise, and it seems that our pi’otest will be fruitless. In these circumstances and as H.M.G. is concerned, we are wondering if any action is possible from you, which could be justified or based on the Ruler T s verbal agreement and that the Shaikh*s present tactics are not of a nature which should be employed in negotiations involving Govern ments and Oil Companies. Apart from this fact it is against the Shaikh’s own interest to obstruct the Corpany’s work. Incidentally, it is our belief that many of the letters now being received do not originate from the Shaikh himself and are not even seen by him, although his seal is appended. On ray last visit in May, although I saw the Shaikh twice, the majority of the points for discussion were dealt with in other meetings with Shaikh Hamed. Yours sincerely Enel Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway,/(T.li.E., H.JB.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. C.I.E.translation /fr /. From: ABDULLA BIN QASIM AL THANI, THE RULER OF QATAR. To: The Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. After compliments - I am in receipt of your kind letter No.QCT.5/4264 dated the 5th of lime 1946, and have followed all your points. To me the letter contained nothing new to the views you had already expressed during our (last) discussion with you, and to some of which I had raised objections (at the time). 1. I should like to make it clear, in this note, that it was not my opinion that any port other than Dohah itself should be used for importing your material, as is (clearly) laid down in the Concession. I had further explained that during the interim period your use of another port had given rise to financial losses; and to make good any (further) derangement that may arise, should this state of affairs continue, (I had proposed that) Dohah should be the sole port for the import of goods. This is what I had expressly pointed out, and I am surprised to find that you (now) mention having written to the General Manager, London, (telling him) that I hold a different view, and that you are leaving the matter undecided until you receive their reply. This is not a satisfactory solution to the problem, and I cannot take up any other matter for discussion until I find a satisfactory solution to the point in question, as it is the most important point in the whole matter. 2. It is not fair at all that you should allow only 20% as increment on the two Representatives’ pay and we (take this opportunity to) remind you that you had offered this (figure) to us during our discussion, but that we did not endorse it. We hope you will reconsider the point, and (please note that) we shall not, as a final solution, agree to anything less than what we already pay or decide to pay, to our employees, in general matters necessitated by the Company’s requirements. Usual ending - (Seal) ABDULLA QASIM AL THANI Dated, the 12th Rajab 1365 (C/t. the 12th June 1946). cpd/ACMCONFID -iNTIAL . D.O. No, 0/632 Dated the 29th June, 1946 Please refer to correspondence ending with your letter No, D0/QCQ,4/4313 dated the 23rd June, 1946. 2. I raised this point myself and asked the Shaikh why he was not implementing his word by the letter he had promised you. This brought a perfect hornet’s nest of complaints against the Company upon my head, and Shaikh Hamad - Shaikh Abdullah was more or less sick - made no bones about his desire to use the non-confirmation of his word in writing as a lever to force the Company to meet his requests. 3. His main points were that the Company were not using Dohah as the port of entry for all Company material and (b) that P.C.L. had closed down during the v;ar and so the Shaikh had lost a great sum of money. 4. As regards (b), I pointed out that that was no fault of the Company and that Qatar should be thankful to be still Qatar. I did not expect any appreciat ion of this point and got none. 5. As regards (a), I had rot heard any complaints against the Company, and since the matter was under the consideration of the Company I thought that this was not the time to deprive the Shaikh of his imagined lever. Had I done so he would inevitably and quite soon have come back at me and with the ration issue still undecided I did not wish to put myself under an obligation to him. 6. Shaikh Hamad assured me that he would not delay H.H.G’s business and would write the letter in due course. 7. I should withhold any further Quick cars, if I were you. They are not suitable for people with so poor^an idea of the proprieties. 3, V. Packer, esquire, iki.b.a., Petroleum Concessions Limited Bafrmln. JANCC.12.37. * TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN Be 11 CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : f iiir Aw A% a-c-r&lt; n r M G, (Thniiiww) A. G4&amp;S - 3-a Nt* 5 ■■CiB.i. »l, PwiOn Pf&amp;i' W. Fraser, C.8.E. C. S. Gulbenkian {formerly Armenian) i. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lafi-tyy Q &gt; 1. A ^mhiIi^ f' * CfA, U. jUrf,Ai) R. V' ^ filers i. Sa. js Aim* ^ n i 'yf-- 2&gt;. PCQ,»4/4468 CONFIDENTIAL BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 5th September, 1946. To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. ft p*' P.C.L.AIRCRAFT LANDINGS IN QATAR ’ 1 i) V/ill you please refer to our letter No.QCq.4/4435 dated the Elst August 1946 including its attachment No.QCQ.4/ 4425 dated the 22nd May 1946 addressed to the Ruler of Qatar, both enclosed herewith. ^ fcb. 2. We enclose also a copy of the Ruler f s reply to our 4435 confirming his agreement to the general use of aircraft in Q^tar. 3. As explained to the Ruler in our No.QCQ.4/442boated the 22nd May 1946, this agreement constitutes an amendment to Article 6 of the Concession, and we understand reference to H.M.G. is now necessary. 4. Meanwhile, we suggest that should we require to land our aircraft before n.M.G’s final approval to general landings is received, we should inform you only. Apart from the difficulty of contacting him, the Ruler will not understand and possibly misconstrue the continuance of a procedure to the cancellation, of which he has signified his agreement. Enclos. Por &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Copy to P.C.L., London, with copies of all enclosures. Confl'Iesiaal. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date..?:.. ACMNo.C/1015 political Agency, Bahrain The 8th September 1946. To The Hon*ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . Memorandum dated the 29th January, 1946 29th January, 1946. 2 I forward herewith copies of P.C.L* letter No. PCQ.4/4468 dated the 5th September, 1946, and its enclosures. 3. I can see no objection to P.C.L. adopting the procedure suggested in paragraph 4 of their letter and would be grateful to know if I may confirm Mr. Packer^ suggestion. Sd./- J.E.H. HUDSON In the absence of the political Agent, Bahrain Attested for Assistant political Agent, L Bahrain. ^(oo)tOA GOVERNMENT of INDIA. qpOTrjarTi^L Department, EXPRESS LETTER fjV B -This vs an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by j&gt;osl to save tdegraphU expense and undue use of the wires, bid intended to be treated, or. receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, lo save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Bahrain. political Agent, Bahrain. # 0 . 746-8 Dated 11th September, 19*6 Reference your memorandum No. C/1015» dated the 8 th September, 1946. 2 , please confirm that the Royal Air Force have been informed tV»t there is no political objection to P,0.L..casing their landing ground at ^atar, vide para. 5 of my telegia::; ..o. dated the 29th January, 1946. 145, 3 # In the meantime there is no objection to your confirm ing to Mr. packer the suggestion made in para. 4 of his letter No. PC^.4/4468, dated the 5th September, 1946. rX- Sd/- W.R. HAY, Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested• for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I .G.H. S. 6. ifFP—1196 S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000. Confidentiai BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ^ Date. rGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depaeimbht. EXPRESS LETTER [A^. B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa&gt; e time and formaluies it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From political Agent, Bahrain. To political Resident, Bahrain . No. C/1032. Dated the 14th Septr., ^6 X, rfl Reference your Express Letter No.746-S dated the 11th September, 1946, paragraph two. 2. I confirm that the Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain, has been informed that there is no political objection to P.C.L. using any landing ground in the Arab Shaikhdoms which is maintained by the R.A.F. Sd./~ J.E.H. HUDSON In the absence of the Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . JV'TC for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. 1 NS. S. 6. MFP—601 S&amp;P-(M-820)—23-7-30—300,000.No.C/1033. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 14th September, 1946 To The Manager, Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Limited, B a h r a i n Dear Sir Reference your letter No.PCQ.4/4468 dated the 5th September, 1946. 2. There is no objection to your adopting the procedure suggested in paragraph four of your letter. Yours faithfully for political Agent, Bahrain 1cGOVERNMENT OF INDIA- Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). 2 hie ta an ORIGINAL message, sent by AIR MAIL which provide* a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] Bahrain, Datcd ^^ 24th September, 2-9 46- /W From To Repeated Political Resident, Bahrain. Retaxandum, London. Foreign, New Delhi. ^ Political, Bahrain, Reference ynne- correspondence resting with Priori express letter No.958-3 dated the 23rd November 1945. Use of Aircraft by Petroleum Concessions Limited. 2. Copy is enclosed of the marginally noted correspondence ^■lb ;r;';;:rT: with th. request that 1; Political Agent, Bahrain*s memofandum ) No.C/1015 dated 8th Sept. 1946. $ Hi) 2) Political Resident, Bahrain*s express ) letter No.746-S dated 11th Sept. *46. ) 3) Political Agent, Bahrain*s express ) letter No.C/1032 dated 14tfi Sept. *46, ) S 7^ of Qatar and Petroleum Concessions Limited. approval may be accorded to the agreement arrived at between the Shaikh ATTESTED. (SGD.) W.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. i BAHRAIN RECEI. . ft I NPG. {Signature) {Designation) S. 44. MFP—1450 S&amp;P-(M-2388)—28-3-40—15,000.JS i II CODES : BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS /y. A. &amp; A S ^ Sir &lt;»kw Cadmao. fi f.J-l-G. (Cbo****) fw ' At Agnewr-Gift^. ‘/-/S &amp;H-&amp;ONiff S ft. c«yrcL p.s^wr-t&gt;&gt;s,c» . / - /\&gt;| u 7“ nr W. Fraser, C.B.E. (4. / V I* / « C. s. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B A. Kessler (Dutch) A * y ^ Sk**, L. Mi Letrey* ^ R. W. Sellers J SkUros PCQ,. 4/3868 BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 19th October, 1946. To H.B.M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. P. C.L.Aircraft Landings, Bahrain &amp; Q,atar s , V You will doubtless recall that in correspondence ending With your No,C/122 dated the 2nd February 1946 and no.C/lOsfdated the 14th September 1946, general landings by our Company aircraft were regularised both for Bahrain and ^atar^^ Within the next few days such landings are expected. vmi nlreadv have the registration numbers of the OompaS Planes sent you under ^rDO/PC^.4/4159 dated the 7 th March 1946, and we are assuming that nothing, is required from us. For Sc on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED ACM Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. n.,/ 0.7n tti GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [JV, R ,—This is an OJilGIJS AL MESSAGE, sent hy post to sa r e telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, bat intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa'e time and formalities it is woraed and sigi.ed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain. f To Political Resident, Bahrain. C/1186. thjl'd 21st October, ^Bacxx ^ &lt;*0 . Reference correspondence endirig with your Express Letter No.774-S dated the 24th September, 1946. 2 4 &lt;-v *4 Petroleum Concessions Limited have informed me that within the next few days Company aircraft are expected to make landings at Bahrain and Qatar. _ S- O 3* They have already sent us the registration numbers of their aircraft, vide my printed Letter No.c/266 dated the 11th March, 1946, and they are assuming that nothing further is required from them, but I am asking them to give prior notice of landings of individual aircraft at Bahrain to the Officer Commanding, Royal Air Force, Muharraq, whenever this is possible. I an ‘ informing the Adviser to the Bahrain Government and the Air staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain, that landings in Bahrain are likely in the near future. ATTESTED. Sd./- H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain, for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. r NS. S 6. M FP— 400S&amp;P— (M-480'—26-7-34—SjOO.OU).0..K \\M No. C/1187, /fvoi Political Agency, Bahrain, The 21st October, ’46. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum. &lt;0^ Reference correspondence ending with your Memorandum No.159-381 dated the 13th January, 1946. 2. please inform His Highness that the following P.C.L* aircraft will land in Bahrain in the near future; Registration Letter . g-agor w G-AGOP 4 G-AGDP G-AGTM G-AGTN Sd./- H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain. Type 1. D-H89A 2. D-H89A 3. D-H89A 4. D-H89A 5. D-H89A ATTESTED. for Assistant Political Agent,^ Bahrain. NS.No.C/1188 blltical Agency, Bahrain, The 21st October, 1946. To The Air Staff Liaison Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum. ■&lt;\ Reference my Memorandum No.c/123 dated the 2nd February, 1946. 2. Within the next few days P.C.L. aircraft are expected to make landings at Bahrain and Qatar. ✓ 3. I am asking Messrs. Petroleum concessions Limited to give advance information of the landings at Bahrain of individual aircraft to the Officer commanding, Royal Air Force, Muharraq whenever this is possible. ATTESTED. Sd./- H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.asz POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 21st October, 1946. Messrs. Petroleum Concessions L^nitea, Bahrain . Memorandum. ,^-r ^ ■ 1 ■ 11 Reference your letter No. PCQ-4/3868 dated the 19th October, 1946, regarding P.C.L. aircraft landings in Bahrain and Qatar. 2. Will you please ensure that whenever possible the Officer Commanding, Royal Aii\ Force, Muharraq, is informed of the approxi mate time of the landings of individual air craft? No.c/1189. t 'V TO fnV-i nror^orrr»'r» political Agent, Bahrain. NS.&lt;i 3: &lt;j C 5 37. TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN %% II &amp; '1 CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED October 1946, the Company aeroplane will be making flights to Qatar today 23rd and tomorrow 24th return ing each day to Bahrain. It is expected that the plane will return to Iraq on Friday the 25th. We trust this information is sufficient for your purpos es. DIRECTORS : frr Mm dmimmx, C.C.M.G. (6»w SiC.M.ff (Oiu.ujiaii) /V BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF S. Gulbenkim (formerly Armenian) J. B A. Kessler (Dutch) *** 2&gt;. ^ (formerly Armenian) Ir A. Me IV (Frenrfrj IUC. CulJU R. W. Sellers J. Skliros PCQ.4/3918 23rd October, 194 6. To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. P.C.L. AIR CRAFT MOVEMENTS Further 19th For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED V' MANAGER Confidential . ACMC.1.40. / CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED x if -j. it jt C. T- n A- 7 F, nv.T.E.ritui * J. mauiv ■ 1 w — ' • a&gt;./is4+fr&lt;«rueL. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF CONFIDSirriAL Q,SD.4/4558 291/11 October , 19 46 • To H.B.M’s Political Agent, To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. QATAR AERIAL SURVEY Our London principals inform us that they are negotiating with aerial photographic Companies to carry out an aerial survey and construct a topographic map by photography covering the entire peninsula of ^atar and perhaps some of the outlying reef areas. In the absence, as yet, of a proper and suitable landing ground in Qatar, it would be essential to use the koharraq^ aerodrome as a base for approximately two weeks’ work. 2. T 7e have made unofficial and tentative inquiries from the R.A.F. regarding facilities which could be made available at Moharraq if the project is approved, and, as far as the use of t he aerodrome is concerned, we understand no difficulties need be anticipated. 3. We shall be pleased if yoi will inform us whether there is any objection to the Company’s proposal to carry out this aerial survey, or if you have any conditions to put forward. For Sc on benalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED MANAGER Copy to: Mr,N*E.Baker, London. -i ' Assistant General Manager, Haifa (for information of Mr. Baker if passing through Haifa) . ACM ConfidentiaL BAHRAIN RECEIPT.HXPRESS LSTTEB '7th -'I ^ &amp; / From, Political, Bahrain. To. Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrain. No. C/1243 Dated the 7th November, Reference correspondence ending with India Office Complimentary Slip No.P.Z,696 dated the 3rd February, 18&amp;&amp;* • 2 # I enclose a copy of Petroleum Concessions Limited Letter No.^SD*4/4558 dated the 29th October, 1946 regarding an aerial survey the Company wish to make of the ^atar peninsula. 3 # i purpose to remind the Company that no flight should be carried out in the extreme southern section of the peninsula. 4 ^ There is also a possibility that the survey may cover reefs and islands in the Bahrain Additional Area, but I can see no reason why any restriction should be imposed on the flight in that area. Sd/- H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. ltd. J.A.N.C. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. / ' / cI ^ fflCTEBMAL oecret .^ry of State for India. Political Resident, Persi n Gulf, Bahrein. Repeated to: Governiaent of India, Sxtemal \ffairs Dept., r&amp; i^&gt;litical Agent, Balirein. Dated: October, 1946. hi 3 Ct.6729/46 U .. C Reference your Express Letter Ko.77VS aated 24 th Septe^r^ airci ‘ aft by COnC0S Ltd. in Qatar. 2 I appx'ove the agreement reached in the exchange^ of^ ^ let cars betv/een etroleum Concessions Ltd., and the Sheixh of atar. It has been ascertained from the Company a they do not require that the wording of 6 of o iw Concession Agreement should be forraally ainonded, ana that their requirements are adequately coverea y exchange of letters. TVie issue of the above has been duly authorisea. F. A. K. HARRISON Confidential. BAHRAIN RSCEIFT. Date All'JlZGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department, EXPRESS LETTER —This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From To Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. I ii I j i # / V Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1017-S. Dated 16th November ^5=1946. Reference your express letter No.1243/C dated the 7th November 1946. Aerial Survey of Qatar. 2. I agree that the Company should be warned that no flight should be carried out in the extreme southern section of the peninsula and also that no restrictions should be imposed on a survey of reefs and islands included in the additional area. With regard to the former point it would be as well if no flights were to be carried out south of 25 of^ latitude but if necessary they may be permitted up to the red line shown in the tracing enclosed cf. the fourth enclosure to India Office printed letter No.Ext.1146/42 dated 18th April 1942. (SGD.) W.R.HAY. * . I i/ni** Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. S. 6. MFP—119G S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000. onfidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT D.ite ng...'JL 3 ^ •EXPRESS LETTER . From - political Agent, Bahrain, To - political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/1325. Dated the 25th of November, 1946. Reference your Express Letter HO.1017-S dated the 16th November, 1946. 2. I should like to venture to point out that if petroleum Concessions Limited carry out unrestricted survey flights over the BAPCO additional area I am sure that suspicion will be aroused in the mind of the Shaikh of Bahrain, and possibly BAPCO may object. 3. I suggest that after the word 'area' the following words are inserted: 'provided that prior permission from the political Agent is obtained'. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrali. ATTESTED . for Assistant political Agent, Id Bahrain. NS.GOVERNMENT OE INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER JV B This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent Iw post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as i it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. To 1083-S - V Dated BAHRAIN, the 27th Novr. 1946 . - Political Agent, BAHRAIN . ' c, q*) Reference your express letter No.0^1325 dated tl&gt;e 26th November 1946. 2 . I agree to the insertion of the words suggested in your paragraph 3. ■ • (SGD.) R.R.HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. &gt;ipp—275 S&amp;T—676*^—(M-676)—27-7-43—1,000,000. WPG. v Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT N« ./yet .Date. w.'.la.i9 No.G/1414 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 23rd December, 1946 To The Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited Bahrain. Dear Sir Will you please refer to your letter No. QSD.4/ 4558 dated the-29th October, 1946? out an aerial survey of the Qatar peninsula provided that no flights are carried out over the extreme southern section of the peninsula and that my prior permission is obtained before any flights are made over outlying reefs in the area commonly known as the Bahrain Additional Area. It would be as well if no flights were carried out south of 25° of latitude, but if necessary they may take place up to the red line shown in the tracing enclosed. please see in this connection India Office letter No. P.Z.4429/38 dated the 7th July, 1938, to your Company (copy enclosed for ready reference)*^ t ’ A}' 3. I presume that the Air survey Company to be employed is a British firm under British direction, and that it will employ British nationals or natives of Qatar only. 2 There is no objection to your Company carrying Yours faithfully Political Agent, Bahrain NS. 09C.2.40. CODES : BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE t27 4. R. oU Mvy+Caifcu J&gt;. BAHREIN Confidential Q3D.4/4674 PERSIAN GULF 4th January, 1947 To H.B.M*s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir AERIAL PHOTOGRAPHIC SU We thank you for your No.c/1414 dated the 23rd December 1946. 2. We note that your permission is to be obtained before any flights are made over outlying reefs in the area commonly known as ’the Bahrain Additional Area’. 3. We presume you refer to fligits for the purpose of air photography as distinct from the daily flights from Moharraq to Qatar to reach the areas being photo graphed, which would normally be the shortest route. 4. We should prefer that flights take place up to the red line shown in your map as this photography is an expensive matter and we would wish the map to be as comprehensive as possible. 5. Reference your para three, we are assured by our London principals that British nationals only are being employed on this air photography. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED MANAGER »•...&amp;?. ....Date, M-'-faL.. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT, ACM17 4m I ^ [it Conf identlal ^ D.O. 1?o*C/39. My dear Packer, The 8th of January, 1947. Will you please refer to your letter No. ^JD-4/ 4674 dated the 4th January, 1947? 2. The presumption in your paragraph 3 is confirmed. 3. As regards your paragraph 4, I agree and since the area contained between the red line and latitude 25° has now come into prominence in connection with p.C.L. development it is probable that flights will be necessary up to the red line. In that case you have authority, and I think that should be sufficient. 4. If, however, you require further confirmation it would gain point if you took the matter up shortly before the survey is due to begin. yours sincerely, % E.V. PacKer, i sq«, M.P.E., Messrs, petroleum concessions Ltd., a h r a i n .C.2.40. 3el ! I CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED N.A tx/hn , V-sU tier* Directors : L&lt;mo cabman. g.c.m.g. (chairman), r. Cayrri,,&gt;D. g,0^ r, J. B. A. KESSLER (dutch), L. M. LWRDT; J. A. IRWI |)-W. Fraser. C.B.E.. C. S. Guubenkian (formerly Armenian) ,3. h. a. seioel (u.s-a4. r. w. sellers, j. skliros^ *&gt;8. &gt;6. /?. HordUiiUyu' 2 &gt;'^- QQ.5/4587 To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 20th January, 1947. Dear Sir, Chartered Plane TJAAB Landing at Moharraq Wq have just received a telegram from our Basra office informing us that a chartered plane w TJAAB n with Messrs. Akin, Lawn and Elder, members of our Qatar staff, will be arriving at Moharraq at about midday today the 20th January, and will be returning immediately to Basra for Mr. G.E.Heseldin, our Assistant General Manager, Mr. Robinson and Mr. Gibson, vjho are also coming down on a temporary visit to Qatar. We are assuming that general permission given for landings of our Company aircraft at Bahrain will cover this landing also and nothing further is required from us. We are notifying the Officer Commanding, R.A.F., Moharraq, of this landing as indicated in your No.C/1189 dated the 21st October 1946. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of fcOLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED AGER ACM Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT /3 ? Date.C.2.40. CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED Directorsi C N .A 6r4 £ 5 &lt;r-(eTTOn J. B. A. Kessler (dutch). ■&gt;). H. CAIHUL, P.3.O.. P.i (KWMSiO^W. Fraser. C.B.E., C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) F (FRRUCRf. »t. «r8BIBBI R. W. SELLERS. J. SKLIROS^ &amp; .&amp;.£ ft a./)- . BAHREIN Q.SD.4/4704 PERSIAN GULF 22nd January, 1947. E.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. A Dear Sir, Chartered Plane - TJAAB V/e beg to confirm herewith the verbal details given you yesterday that our chartered plane TJAAE would fly over Q,atar today with Captain 'Challenger” and Commander Dan and one other officer. The necessary instructions have been given to the pilot to restrict his flights to the limits as outlined in your D.O. No.c/39 dated the 8th January 1947. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of tOLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED / s JpNAGER ' ACM BATP Con&amp;len&amp;jL rs becetpt. Z.IB'rora* Political, Bahrain# To# No. C/122 RSPGU, Bahrain. Dated the 25th January, 1947# Reference with your Express Let 27 th November, 1946• responderce ending No. 1083-S dated the 2. On the 23rd January Petroleum Development C^atar) Limited informed me that their chartered plane TJAAE would fly over Watar with Captain Challenger*, Commander Dan, and one pilot officer, and that the pilot had been instructed to restrict his flights to the limits laid down in correspondence under reference# Sd/- H.D#H. RANGE in the absence of the Political Agent, Bahrain# Attested for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain#r 1 CONFIDENTIAL &lt; ' My Dear Colonel, in your letter Ho. C/1414 dated the 23rd December 1946, you mention the area commonly known as 'the Bahrain Additional Area’. We have no map here showing this area. I shall be most grateful if you could give me, or lend me, copy. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A. C.Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. EA&lt; Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. r' k ‘‘D.O. NO.C/159 The 6th of February, 1947 My dear Packer Will you please refer to your letter No. QiSD.4/4716 dated the 4th February, 1947? 2. I have no map of the ’‘Additional Area r ‘ and, indeed, this area has never been delimited. In my letter I mentioned the area ’’cooreonly known as the Bahrain Additional Area* and by that I meant an area or areas of shoals and islands between Bahrain and ^atar. These are shown on the maps appended to the various draft leases drawn up durin the negotiations for the *Additional Area” or ’’Shoal Area” or whatever it may have been, but which, though sometimes approximately defined in the texts, have never been finally agreed. 3. I am sorry that I cannot be more explicit. riS © yours sincerely tr/v £.V. Packer, Esq., K.B.K., Messrs, petroleum concessions, Ltd., Bahrain.EXPRESS LETTER, I URGENT. From - political Agent, Bahrain. To - Political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/179. Dated the 11th of February, 1947. Reference your Express Letter No.1083-3 dated the 27th November, 1946. 2. Wallings, Assistant chief Geologist of P.C.L., has informed me verbally that P.C.L. have chartered an aircraft for aerial survey work on the Qatar peninsula region. The 'plane is now in Qatar and P.C.L. wish to start work immediately. 3. , The programme of operations can be divided roughly into three main categories: (a) Air-survey of the Qatar main-land , as far south as the red-line, vide enclosure to Residency Express Letter No.1017-3 dated the 16th November, 1946. (b) Qatar territorial waters, and (c) the area bounded on the west by the red-line marked on chart Asia, Persian Gulf, vide my Express Letter No.c/1450 of the 31st December, 1946. So as not to delay work and cause unnecessary expense to P.C.L. as regards (a) I stated that I had no objection to the starting of the work. As regards (b) I stated that I had no objection to the work being carried out over Qatar territorial waters to the east of the peninsula. As regards (c) I stated that I was unable to give permission myself, and that I would refer the matter and endeavour to give a reply within a few days to avoid closing down the survey. 5 * (c) can be sub-divided in four sub-heads. (i) (ii) (lit(ill) (iv) The shoal waters to the east of the red line. As regards (i) Hawar should be excluded and indeed I understand that P.C.L. do not propose to fly over it. Hawar. The Hawar Group as enumerated, vide , &gt; ;&gt;d my Express Letter No.c/1450, dated the 31st December, 1946. Deebal and Jaradeh features. /As regards....As regards (ii). The 'Islands” have already been awarded to Bahrain, and there is no reason to suppose that that decision will be reversed. The composition of the group, however, is still under con sideration, and though it is clear that the majority of the Island will go to BAPCO, if doubt exists it will be concerning Janubiyeh. I have suggested, vide my Express Letter No.c/170 dated the 10th February, 1947, that BAPCO should postpone ground operations, and it is only logical to maintain a similar embargo for P.C.L. pending the decision on the ownership question. It is not feasible to permit both companies to operate because they are rivals in this region and particularly so at Janubiyeh. A possibility of the exchange of information exists, but I neither recommend it nor think it practicable. I, therefore, suggest that P.C.L.' should be requested to postpone the air-survey. . of these features is also sub judlce though there is a possibility that Bahrain’s claim will not be substantiated. It further differs in that BAPCO have already carried out certain operations on the features. None of this inclines me to the view that P.C.L. should now be allowed to operate which would be in competition with BAPCO. My opinion is that until a decision has been reached by His Majesty's Government the features (as delimited in my Express Letter NO. c/1450) should be considered closed to operations whether aerial or surface. (iii) As regards Deebal and Jaradeh the ownership » W u. V-l 1 vJ p'' X C* X w CA w w v-/ v v&gt; A. J (ii) and (iii) I see no objection to the proposed air survey. (iv) With the exception of areas covered by (i), 6. I should be grateful for very early instructions. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS.CONFIDENTIAL URGENT PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. EXPiiESS LETTER From Political Resident, Persian Gulf. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 296 - S. Dated the 14th February, 1947. Reference your expressletter No. C/179, dated the 11th February, 1947.' 2* I agree with your proposals throughout. Please take action accordingly. Sd. W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATT ESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. G. A. ivt. Confidential. BAHRAIN RHaEIET. h....2:E? 9 /,. noD.O. No.C/218. The 17th of February, 1947. My dear Packer, With reference to ray conversation with Messrs. (a) the Qatar main-land as far south as the red-line shown in the tracing enclosed with my letter No.G/1414 dated the 23rd December, 1946. (b) Qatar territorial waters to the east of the peninsula. the peninsula excluding the Deebal and Jaradeh features and Hawar and its group t • of islands. E.V. Packer, Esq., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. Lermitte and sellings I am authorised to say as follows. 2. There is no objection to P.C.L. carrying out survey flights over (c) Qatar territorial waters to the west of yours sincerely. v\ NS.BAHRAIN CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF. DO/qsd.4-1/4749 25th February 1947. My dear Colonel, P.C.L.AERIAL SURV5Y &amp; MAP OF QATAR r 'O Will you please refer to your D.O. No.C/218 dated the 17th of February 1947 with particular reference to para two (c), and subsequent conversa tion at your office with Mr. Lermitte on the 24th of February 1947. Our London principals in an early letter on the above subject pointed out that the map and photo mosaic to be made by the Company is to be purely topographic (not geological) and in this case they could not see any grounds for Political objections in respect of the inclusion in the map of all visible reefs within the area outlined on map A (enclosed for reference and return), particularly as they understand that the Bahrain Petroleum Company carried out geological exploration of parts at least of reefs off the North-West coast of Qatar. 2. We are now directed to write to you again bring ing the above points to your notice and requesting permission to photograph the Tt Dibal n and n Jarada w reefs. We would add that we believe we are correct in saying that Bapco have already carried out geophysical work on and around these two reefs. 3. As the aerial survey is for a few weeks only and is an expensive matter, we should be grateful for a reply at your earliest convenience. Our principals have stressed to us their hope and desire that permission will be accorded locally, but in the event of this not being possible they would like, with your approval, to approach the India Office themselves, to avoid unnecessary detention of the aeroplane at Bahrain. On;J.;ntial. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., BahrainD.O. No.C/268 The 28th February, 1947 My dear Packer, Will you please refer to your letter No. DO/QiiD*4-1/4749 dated the 25th February, 1947? 1 2. I have again referred the matter and shall Inform you of the result in due course. 3. I return your map herewith. Yours sincerely, E.V. Packer, Ssq., Messrs, petroleum concessions Limited Bahrain.IU EXPRESS LETTKR. From - political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bahrain. No. C/269. Dated the 28th of February, 1947. Reference correspondence ending with your Express Letter N0.296-S dated the 14th February, 1947. 2. Messrs, petroleum concessions Limited have now written saying that their London principals in an earlier letter on the subject of Deebal and Jaradeh point out that the map and photomosaic the company require to make are to be purely topographical and not geological, and in that case they see no grounds for political objections to the inclusion of visible reefs, which include the Deebal ^ and Jaradeh features. This is particularly so since, they understand, BAPCO have carried out geological explo ration on parts at least of reefs situated to the North- West of the coast of Qatar. As regards Deebal and Jaradeh they believe that they are correct in saying that BAPGO have already carried out geological work on and in the vicinity of the two reefs. 3. in view of the above they request the removal of the objection to their photographing the Deebal and Jaradeh features and that permission can be given early so as not to delay the survey which is an expensive undertaking. 4. P.C.L. state that they hope to obtain this permission locally, but should this not be possible, wish to know if there is any objection to their taking the matter up themselves with the India Office in London, in order to assist P.C.L. in their work which has already been handicapped severely you might consider revising your decision and agree that permission may be accorded. I should be grateful for early instructions. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. £ NS.r- ■ 117 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH RAIN PERSIAN GU LF. DO/QSD.4-1/4769 My dear Colonel 6th March, 194?. P,C,L. Aerosurvey - Qatar Will you please refer to my No.DO/Q§D.4-1/ 4?49 dated the 25th February 1947* We are now informed that the aeroplane will be completing its work in ten days* time. In these circumstances, which leaves us very little time to communicate with our London principals in the event of this proving necessary, we trust that you will not think it inappropriate if we inquire as to the situation. Lt.-Col. A. C.Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. (on{ Jeatial. BAm \ r 'J h^eipt. Yours sincerelyU R GENT. No.C/317. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 8th March, 1947. The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the under mentioned document with the request that an early reply may kindly be given. Reference to previous Correspondence: f'li Agency Express Letter No.c/269 dated 28th Feb., '47. % . --- - — Description of Enclosure. NAME &amp; DATE . j SUBJECT,. Letter No. DO/QSD. 4-1/4769 dated the 6th March, 1947, from M/s. petroleum Con cessions Limited, Bahrain, to the political Agent. ' Ml o 3 P.C.L. aerial survey 5 of Qatar. 5 3 0 3 3 0 3 3 3 3 3D.O. No.C/318 The 8th of March, 1947 My dear Packer, Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No. do/QSD. 4-1/4769, dated the 6th March, 1947? 2. I regret that X have received no reply.from the Political Resident to whom I referred the matter. I shall send him a copy of your letter with the request for an early reply. Yours sincerely. E.V. Packer, Esq., M.B.B., M/s. petroleum Concessions Ltd., Bahrain .. s Or Cut A * i Telegram From To I' o • ^ • Political Resident, Bahrain. India Office, London. 279 // \ Dated the 4th March, 1947. Correspondence forwarded with Printed Letters Nos 297-S and 298-S February 14th. Aerial Survey by Petroleum Concessions Limited. 2 . Company have represented that they only wish to carry out topographical »ir survey of Dibal and Jaradah and have requested early permission for this so as not to dealy survey which is expensive undertaking. 3 # I am now inclined to grant permission on the understanding that no surface operations of anv kind are involved. Do you see any objection ? No. 419-S. V hi \ -HAY- PERSIAN GULF RE3IDFI CY, BA FTP A IN. the 5th March, 1947. FGrwarded with compliments to i- the Political Agent, BnN'j.IN , BR.- Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. , If •...iff.?..! Date3 ?/ i l 86/20 Telegram From To Repeated No 309 Dated the 9th March| 1947. Pepgu, Bahrain. India Office, London. Political Resident, at Kuwait. Resident 1 s telegram No 279 March 4th. Aerial survey by Petroleum Concessions Ltd. 2. Grateful for early instructions as P.C.L. say aeroplane will be completing survey in 10 days’ time. - REPGU - CONFIDENTIAL No 447-S 4 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 9th March, 1947. / ^Vs Copy, with copy of telegram referred to above, forwarded with compliments toj«» The Political Agent, Bahrain. with reference to his Printed Letter No C/317, dated the 8th March, 1947. #Telegram From To No 279 Dated the 4th March, 1947. Political Resident, Bahrain. India Office, London. Correspondence forwarded with Printed Letters Nos. 297-S and 298-S February 14th. Aerial Survey by Petroleum Concessions Limitecf. 2- Company have represented that they only wish to carry out topographical air survey of Dibal and Jaradah and have requested early permission for this so as not to delay survey which is expensive undertaking. 3. I am now inclined to grant permission on the understanding that no surface operations of any kind are i involved. Do you see any objection ? Copied I.C.H.CONFIDErlTlAL L F F £, O :•: L T T h F From P.epgu, Bahrain. To Political, Bahrain No.465- Dated the 13th March, 1947 c.v^ Reference my endorsement No.447-S dated the 8th March, 1947. Aerial survey by'Petroleum Concessions Limited. Following is extract from India Office telegram No.3346 doted the 12th Mirch, 1047. ^ ^ ”2. Your telegram No.279 r ' of March 4th. Permission may be granted to Petroleum Concessions Limited on condition mentioned in your paragraph 3.' The issue of the above has been authorised For Secretary to the^Political Resident Persian Gulf. ’LB’ BAHRAIN RECEIPT.URGENT D.O. No.C/354 The 15th of March, 1947 My dear packer, Will you please refer to the correspondence resting with ay deal-official letter No.c/318, dated the 8th March, 1947. 2. There is no objection to your photographing the Dibal and juradeh reefs provided that no sur face operations of any kind are involved. Yours sincerely E.V. Packer, Esq., M/s. petroleum Concessions, Limited Bahrain.IMMEDIATE. EXPRESS LETTER. I #&gt;-' t From ~ political, Bahrain. To - political Resident at Kuwait, (by telegram). . Repeated to Repgu, Bahrain (by Express Letter). No.C/364. Dated the 17th of March, 1947. Your Express Letter No.465-3, dated the 13th of March, 1947. ^ 2. petroleum concessions Limited have represented that they do not wish to undertake surface operations,- but after photographing reefs may need to land .thereon to take observations or alternatively to station boats off reefs for same purpose. This is required in order to orientate photographs correctly and to ascertain exacts distance of reefs from mainland of Qatar. 3. Grateful for immediate orders authorising me to permit P.C.L. to land on reefs or station boats for purpose stated. +Sd./- C.J. FELLY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. \ / NS.—— t a i Telegram From political, Bahrain. To Resident, Kuwait. Repeated to Repgu, Bahrain (by Express Letter) No.68. Dated the 17th of March, 1947. IMMEDIATE . / your Express Letter No.465-S, dated the 13th of March, 1947. ^ vT , S 2. petroleum concessions Limited have represented that they do not wish to undertake surface operations, but after photographing reefs may need to land thereon to take observations or alternatively to station boats off reefs for same purpose. This is required in order to orientate photographs correctly and to ascertain exact distance of reefs from mainland of Qatar. 3 . Grateful for immediate orders \ authorising me to permit P.C.L. to land on reefs or station boats for purpose stated. -POLITICAL- NS38/11. Telegram 'S'. From political Resident at Kuwait. To No. 1/ Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 18th Received 19th March, 1947. IMMEDIATE. Your telegram No.68, March 17th. 2. P.C.L. must not repeat not land reefs nor station boats within three miles of them.D.O. Ho.C/368 The 19th of March, 1947 My dear Lermitte, Reference our conversation of the 17th of March in which you told me that your company might need, while photographing the Dibal and Jaradeh reefs, to land thereon to take observations or to station boats off the reefs for the same purpose. 2. I am sorry to have to inform you that you should not land on the reefs nor station boats within three miles of them. Yours sincerely, 8.H. Lermitte, y M/s. petroleum concessions. Ltd., Bahrain.C.12.46 TELEGRAMS : PETROQAT, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED Directors « J. W. bovle. C.B.E.. Sir W. Frasfr, C.B.E., N. A. Gass. C. S. Gulrenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler, (dutch) V. oe Metz, (french) R. de Montaiqu, (french) R. W. sellers, m.c., D. A. Shepard, (citizen of u.s.a.) J. Skliros. o.a.e. Dear Sir, We attach herewith a copy of a letter (No.247/67) dated the 15th April 1948 received from the Representa tive to the Ruler of Qatar. We have no information regarding this landing, hut we understand one Bustani had called on you at Bahrain before he took off for Qatar. We are therefore replying to the Representative to the Ruler of Qatar that we are referrirg the matter to you and that we will advise him as soon as we hear from you. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF Q/Lsn/5786 Confidential 18th April, 1948 / R.B.F's Political Agent Bahrain. Yours faithfully, For &amp;, on behalf of !UM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED MANAGER Encl.l fma/acm Confidential -r ■\T -nTranslation No.247/67 Dohah, 13th April 48 Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. After compliments - Recently a plane piloted by one Bustani, said to be a Lebanese, flew over Qatar and then landed in the Company air field, where the said pilot met the Fields Manager, although under no circumstances it is allowed for other than Company planes to fly over Qatar or land. His Excellency would be pleased, therefore, if you will give us tiiljB information about this plane and the purpose of the pilots visit and how he happened to come to Qatar without prior notice to or permission by His Excellency. Usual e nding - (Sgd.) Saleh al Mana\ / ^ No. C/431 To. Denr Sir| The 28th Aprllj 1948. The Manager, M/s. Petroleum Concessions Limited, BAHRAIN. • ! to your letter \ In rep^ly No. Q/Lsn/5786 dated the 18th April 1948 I am to say that I have written j/ - direct to the Secretary to His Excellency the Shaikh of Qatar regarding the circumstances of M.Bustan^s flight to Qatar. Yours faithfully, $&gt;. for Political Agent, Bahrain. ®/r IC.12.46. TELEGRAMS : PETROQAT. BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED I* w Boyu:, C.B.E., Sir W. Frasfr. C.B.E.. N. A. Gass, C. S. Gulbenkian. (formerly Armenian) J. b. A. Kessler, (dutch) ,KTZ &gt; (french) R. ok Montaiou, (french) r. w. Sellers, m.c.. D. A. Shepard, (citizen of u.s.a.) J. skliros, o.b.e. Dear Sir, We have been advised by our Beyrouth office that a charter Dakota with fifteen persons of the Contracting and Trading Co., is arriving Bahrain on Thursday the 18th November. These 15 persons are for our construction programme in Qatar, and, owing to the shortage of accommodation in Bahrain, we propose to fly them to Qatar, immediately on arrival, by Aerovan plane which is also arriving here today. We are advising the Rule r of Qatar of this non—Company plane landing in Qatar in terms of our Concession Agreement, and we hope this landing will also have your approval. We will collect their passports and forward them to the Agency on Saturday, the 20th November. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF QQ.7/7580 URGENT 18th November, 1948 Yours faithfully. For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED omiM a MANAGER fma/ach 'No...—m - i»- — / y 13/34 &amp; 38/11* Confidential. No.C/Q-95. Dear Wilton, Political Agency, Bahrain, 22nd April, 1960. Please refer to your letter No.20/41/50 of 28th March. 2. As a result of exchange of letters between the Shaikh of Qatar and P.D.Q., the Shaikh Agreed in writing in September 1946 to suspend the operation of the pro visions of Article 6 of the Concession Agreement and agreed to ^(general) landings as and when required for such necessary business”. 3. Sir Rupert Hay apparently holds that the Oil Company landing strips in Qatar can only be used with their permission. This is the view upon which Lermitte acts. 4. I am inclined to think that in the absence of any Civil Air Agreement or the like with us, the Shaikh as Sovereign must have at present at least an inherent right to decide who lands in Qatar; though presumably this is limited in a general way by our insistence that we control the grant of visas for Qatar. However this is a matter for settlement by a Civil Air Agreement. Sir Rupert Hay has asked the Foreign Office when we may expect to receive instructions about negotiating an air agreement with the Ruler of Qatar. Yours sincerely, A.J. Wilton, Esq., Political Officer, ^atar, Doha., 38/11 . t 1 ■ (19) Issued Memo. C/786 dated 20/12/38 to Adviser Bahrain Govts • (20) Letter No. 1922-30 dated 22/12/38 from Adviser, Bahrain Govts / (21) Issued letter No C/6 dated 5/1/39 to P.C.L.Bahrain. (22) ' • Letter No PCL/CA*.4/3876 dated 21/2/39 from P.C.L.Bahrain. .. 7 ■ ’• • ( 23 ) Issued D.O. No. C/131 dated 25/2/39 to Mr Packer, P.C.L. • - (24) Copy of letter No P.Z.2926/37 dated 13/5/37 from 1.0. London. • (25) Letter No DO/CQ.4/4021 dated 1/9/45 frpij P.C.L. Bahrain. (26) Issued tel No. 498 dated 10/9/45 to P.R.Shiraz. (27) Issued D.O. No. C904 dated 22/9/45 to P.R.Shiraz. (28) X.L.No. 839-S dated 8/10/45 from P.R. Bushire. (29) Issued D.O. No. C/983 dated 15/10/45 to Mr. Packer of P.C.L. • (30) Issued Sndst No. C/985 dated 15/10/45 to 1.0. ,G of I, P.R. P.A's Muscat and Kuwait. (31) D.0./C^.4/4039 dated 15/10/45 from Mr. Packer of-P.C.L. (32) DO/C'4.4/4041 dated 16/10/45 from Mr. Packer of P.C.L. Please re-submit as soon as possible. All the action required seems to be for us to write to the administrations concerned marked at 'B' of the p.u.c. and for P.R. to be addressed regarding the other two. But please note. ITD C.J.P. 20/10. May send a copy of p.u.c. to P.R. under Memo ? D.F.A. P.A. may also wish to see the various Civil AirAgreements. 38/11. 4. 5. a) With Bahrain ( copy b) With Dubai c page c) With Sharjah c page below) 28 of F.13/2-VI) 30 of 13/2-VI and 2 of 13/2 -I) There Is no agreement with Qatafc. P. A. X ITD J.A.N.C, 24/10 In respect of Sharjah, Dubai and v^atar is there any need to ask the Shaikhs ? Will it not be sufficient simply to inform them that the aircraft will land during the year ? ITD C.J.P. 25/10 We might do this in respect of Sharjah and Dubai, but not, I think, in respect of ^atar. Please see ^atar Oil Concession Article 6 of Commercial Agreement. 1.0. have given P.C.L. permission to build an aerodrome at Ciatar, vide p. 192 of F.10/3-X, but their permission is necessary before any flights are made over the southern area of ^atar, vide s.24 of file. In their letter at p.176 of F.10/3-X P.C.L.gave 1 .0. an undertaking that they would instruct their pilots not to fly over this area and we should remind Mr Packer of this when replying to his letter. ITD. J.A.N.C. 30/10/45 P. A. The correct course seems to be to ask permission from the Shaikhs of Bahrain and Qatar - to inform Sharjah, but I would confirm from P.R. before doing this and before doing that - I would ask Mr Packer what be wants H in respect of u Dubai . other than the alighting area for flying boats there is no sfaf aerodrome in Dubai territory. ITD C.J.P. 33/10/45 May enquire from Mr Packer as suggested by Mr. Pelly ? D.F.A. P. A. 8 Issue draft ITD A.C.G. $ 5.11.45I : *# 3* ' * 38/11 ( (33) Issued ©.0. No« C/1050 dated 6/11/45 to Mr Packer of P.C.L. (34) D.O. No. DO/C^.4/4050 dated 7/11/45 from Mr Packer of P.C.L. It hardly seems worth while asking the Sh. of Dubai for feneral permission for landings for a year ahead dif no use is going to made of it. When P.C.L. build an aerodrome oi* charter a flying boat we may do so. Regarding s.32 we still have to inform P.R, of Ef.C.L. requirements in tespect of Kuwait and Muscat, and ask him to confirm proposals in respect of (a) Bahrain and ^atar, and (b) Sharjah, vide pages 2 and 3 of note sheets. D.F.A. ITD J.A.N.C. 11/11/45 P. A. Issue ITD A.C.G. 11/11/45 (35) Issued X.L. No. C/1065 dated ll/ll/45 to P.R.Bushire. X (36) X.L. No. 937 dated 19/11/45 from P.R.Bushire (37) Endst No. 938-3 dated 19/11/45 from P.R.Bushire. (38) X.L, No. 958-3 dated 23/11/45 from P.R.Bushire R#f s.36-33 We may reply to Mr Packer 1 s letter at s.32 giving him the general assurance he asks for in respect to Muscat and Kuwait. D.F.A.I May send copy of this letter under memo to A.L.O. d *f.a.ii May ask Adviser for general permission in regard to Bahrain. D.F.A.Ill May ask Shaikh of ^atar for general permission. D.F.A.IV May inform Shaikhs of Sharjah and Dubai of landings. D.F.A.V P.A. may wish to see Bahrain, Dubai, and Sharjah Air Agreements and ^atar Oil Agreement (Article 6) befor he approves of drafts. . % ITD. J.A.N.C. 28/11/45 9. 10. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. 16 17.Lett er da ted 19.12.45 from Shaikh of Vatar . (50) Letter No. DO/C^.4/4092 dated 30.12.45 from P.C.L., Bahrain. (51) Letter No. PC^.4/4096 &amp; 78 dated 5.1.46 from P.C.L., Bhn. (52) ^ Letter No. DO/PC^.4/4098 dated 5.1.46 from P.C.L., Bahrain. Ref. S.49 . 23. The word 'over' meaning 'throughout or during' has been rendered in our letter to Shaikh at s.42 by the Arabic equivalent of 'over and'above'. There would seem however fcs no political objection to Company approaching Shaikh for the permission they want and we may inform them to this effect, adding that it is incumbent on the Company to keep the •Political Agent informed. Before doing this a prior reference to P.R. seems necessary, vide Mr. Packer’s letter at s.50. Ref. S. 50 . , , 24. May send copy under memo, to P.R. 2.(a) (ii). We may suggest asking Mr. Packer to 25. address P.A.K., vide para 2(c) of our letter at s.29. 2.(b). We may ask Adviser to expedite reply before 26. commenting to P.R. D.F.A. 2.(c). We may suggest replying to Mr. Packer as at 27. noting under s.49 above. 2.(d) A (e). I do not know of any licencing documents 28. that would be required for landings by P.C.L.' aircraft at Sharjah and Dubai, but there is landing fee of Rs.5/- to be paid for each landing by a commercial aircraft. Please see Sharjah and Dubai Air Agreements placed below. 2.(f). As regards Muscat Mr. Packer has now written 29. to A.S.L.0., Bahrain, vide s.51, and we may suggest to P.R. that he refers to A.S.L.0.in every case where P.C.L. propose to use a landing ground in use by the R.A.F. Besides Sharjah and Dubai there is possibility that P.C.L. may use R.A.F. landing ground at Doha in C^atar, vide s.25. May issue reminder to Adviser today. 30. This cover is being sent by Fooshing due 7.1.46. 31. Id./- JANC., 6 /1. Issue drafts as spoken. Id. / (53) Issued Memo. No.C/61 dated 12.1.46 to P.R. (54) Issued D.0. No.C/62 dated 12.1.46 to Mr. Packer, P.C.L. 32, - A.C. G. , 10/1/46.38/11 33, 34 35 With regard to Bahrain I have reminded the acting Adviser. ITD. A.C.G. 12/1/46. (55) Memo No. 159-381 dated 13/1/46 from Acting Adviser. May inform Mr Backer. D.F.A. P.A. Issue. ITD. J.A.N.C. 15/1 ITD. A.C.G. 15/1/46 (56) Issued D.6. No. C/79 dated 15/1/46 to Mr Packer of P.C.L. 36 38. (57) Issued Endst No C/80 dated 15/l/46 to P.R. Bushire. (58) Bushire Memo No. 14-3 dated 5/1/46. (59) Letter No. DO/PC^.4/4114 dated 19/1/46 from Mr Packer of P.C.L. Ref s.58. May inform Mr Packer. D.F.A.I Ref s.59. The following points are for consideration a) the form of licence required at Kuwait is still under reference vide s. 53 and 54. b) particulars regarding P.C.L. planes, radio apparatus and pilots is now required by Govts of India, vide s. 45 and s.58. c) we have never given P.C.L. to understand that prior reference t to the P.A. concerned would not be necessary in regard to landing in P.G. 0 please see s.27 and 29 of file) and we may still deem if necessary to forbid the landing of P.C.L. planes in certain of the ^rab Shaikhdoms should the situation seem to require it. Suggest we send copy under Memo to P.R. and ask for telegraph! reply. D.F.A. II ITD. J.A.N.C. 20/1/46 P»A. Issue ITD. A.C.G. 20/1/46.i 38/11 /•vV 44. 1 (68) Letter No. D-1663-ME/46 dated '20/3/46 ‘from Govts of India. We have sent this information to P.R, vide s.67. May file ? P.A. (69) ITD J.A.N.C. 25/3 ITD. A.C.G. 25/3/46 Letter No PCQ.4/4227 dated 22/5/46 from P.C.L. Bahrain. 45. 46. 47. 48. 49 In regard to assumption that immediate effect may be given to Rulers permission, P.l. may please see s.63 and 64 of file. Article 6 of Political Agreement is also relevant. May refer to P.R. May inform Mr Packer he should await our reply before acting on last para of his letter ? P.A. ITD J.A.N.C. 26/5/46 We need not inform P.R. at this stage. Issue draft. ITD A.C.G. 29/5/46 (70) « Issued D.O. No. C/560 dated 30/5/46 to Mr Packer of P.C.L. ' 9 * ' (71) ' ' ' DO/PCQ.4/4254 dated 2/6/46 from P.C.L. Bahrain We have not yet received any letter or the copy of any letter form the Shaikh of Qatar giving this general permission. P.A. may wish to refer matter to P.R. P.A. ‘ Issue draft. ITD. I.A.N.C. 4/6/46 ITD A.C.G. 6/6/46 50, 51. Draft cancelled. ITD L.R. 8/6/46. (72) D.O. QCQ.4/4273 dated 6/6/46 from P.C.L. Ref s.71 and 72. May add to cases P.A. is to discuss at Qatar. P.T.O.78 The map referred to in N/para 77 is a Bapco map and our copy of the map sent to P.R. showing the Bahrain enclosure to east of the Bahrain - 4atar line The Additional Area has never been defined but its 79. boundaries are approximately those shown in the blue print attached to the P.C.L. draft lease for the Shoal area, submitted below. If P.A. agrees we may send this to Mr. Packer and ask for its return. ltd. JANG 6/2/47 P.C.L. have the drafts. Issue draft below. 80. ltd. A.C.G. 6/2 (102) . Issued D.O. No. C/l59 dated 6/2/47 to Mr. Packer, P.C.L. Cl° 3 &gt; P.D. (C})Ltd. letter No. WQ.5/4747 dated 6/2/47 May File ? (R. to 38/11-A) 81 ltd. A.J.S. 8 / 2/47 ltd. A.C.G. ltd. H.R. 11.2.47 8/2/47 P.A. A.P.A. (104) Issued X.L. No. C/179 dated 11/2/47 to P.R., Bahrain. (105) . . Residency X.L. No. 296-S dated 14/2/47 (106) ltd. JANC 15/2 P.A. Issued D.O. No. C/218 dated 17/2/47 to Mr. Packer, P.C.L. ' (107) ' Letter No. D0/QSD.‘4-l/474 dated 25/2/47 from P.C.L., Bahrain / (108) Issued D.O. No. C/268 dated 28/2/47. to Mr. Packer, P.C.L. (109) Issued X.L. No. C/269 dated 28/2/47 to P.R., Bahrain. (110) Letter No. DO/WSD.4-1/4769 dated 6/3/47 from P.CL., Bahrain. (ill) Issued P.L. No. C/317 dated 8/3/47 to P.R., Bahrain</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000137_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/868</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000137</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/868</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 38/11 P. C. L. Planes'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-24T11:49:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (167 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to the movement of company (Petroleum Concessions Limited) planes in the Persian Gulf. The main correspondents are: representatives of Petroleum Concessions Limited and its subsidiary companies (Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited and Petroleum Development (Oman and Dhofar) Limited); the Political Agent at Bahrain; the Political Residency at Bushire (later Bahrain) [Persian Gulf Political Residency]; Sir Charles Belgrave, Advisor to the Shaikh of Bahrain; the India Office; the Air Vice-Marshal, Commanding British Forces in Iraq; the Government of India, External Affairs Department; Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani [‘Abdullāh bin Qāsim Āl Thānī], ruler of Qatar; Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr [Sulṭān bin Saqr Āl Qāsimī], ruler of Sharjah; Shaikh Said bin Maktum [Sa‘īd bin Maktūm Āl Maktūm], ruler of Dubai; and the Political Agent at Muscat.The papers within the file are mostly concerned with permission for landings and flyovers by company planes in Bahrain, Qatar, Kuwait, Sharjah, Dubai, and Oman. These permissions are sought by the company from the appropriate ruler (as sovereign) and the RAF (for use of the airfields), via the appropriate British Government officer (in this case, the Political Agent at Bahrain). The permissions sometimes include details of the planes, such as name, registration, passengers, pilot, engineers, and wireless operators.Other matters covered by the file include:the distribution by the company of their own aviation fuel to aerodromes across the region;the planning and permission of an aerial photographic survey of Qatar and its territorial waters carried out by the company in early 1947.There is a gap in the correspondence between 1939 and 1945, due to the Second World War.Folio 123 is a sketch map of southern Qatar, showing the limits of the proposed aerial survey.Folios 159-68 are internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Development Oman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Officer Commanding, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Dubai, Āl Maktūm dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Qatar Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Qatar</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Aerial photography</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000137#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>