<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003b0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:16:47.907Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SECRET No. C/943 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd December 1940. '.To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Memorandum During the absence of the Political Agent Bahrain, Mr. Veightman, on recess in India from the 5th August to the 25th September 1940 the current work of the Political Agent was performed by Captain Howes. It is noticed from the Register of Marriages that a marriage was solemnised by Captain Howes on the 13th of August 1940. ' ' V 2. According to King 1 s Regulation No. 2 of 1922 the Indian Christian Marriage Act of 1872 has been applied to Bahrain and the Political Agent for the time being, being a Christian, is appointed Registrar of Martriages. According ii \ to the Bahrain Order in Council 1913, paragraph 4, the 'Political Agent' means 'His Majesty's Agent at Bahrain ■. . / ■ \ \ appointed by the Governor General of India in Council including a person acting temporarily with the approval : /. ;/ V of the Governor General of India in Council for such Political Agent'. There is nothing on record in this Office to show that the approval of the Governor General of India in Council was accorded to Captain Howes' acting as Political Agent. It appears therefore that if such approval was not accorded Captain Hov^s was not able to perform the duty of a Registrar of Marriages and the i , marriage therefore appears to be invalid. *1 V x 3. The matter is reported for the information of the Political Resident and for such orders as he may wish to issue. (l: Political Agent, Bahrain. 6]c -'•i-'elegram Q. From Political Resident at Kuwait. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/134 Dated and received the 25th ¥ arch 1941. Reference registration of marriage. Please instruct Howes to take action indicated in my note. Hesident - A'. L.AIR IIAIL. No.F.912-N/40. aOVERMEKT OF IMDIA. External Affairs Departinent• Dated New Delhi ,theliarch 1941. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. By order, etc.. Asstt.Secretary e Oovernment Letter to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, No.912-N/40,dated the 10th llarch 1941, with enclosure.To From No.F.912-N/40. The Deputy Secretary to the Grovernment of India in the External Affairs Department, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. Dated New Delhi,the 10th March 1941. Subject;-Question of regularising the action of Captain Howes in respect of a marriage performed by him at Bahrain. I am directed to refer to your letter N0 .155-S, dated the 13th February 1941, and to state that Section 2 of King's Regulation No.2 of 1922 vests the jurisdiction of a Registrar of marriage not in any Political Agent at Bahrain but m the Political Agent for tne time being at Bahrain, and it is obvious on the face of the definition in Article 4 of the Bahrain Order in &gt; Council that two persons cannot simultaneously occupy the position of the Political Agent for the time being at Bahrain. Kven on the dubious assumption therefore that a fictional retrospective appointment to an Executive office would validate action statutorily incapable of being taken otherwise than by the incumbent of the' office, a fictional retrospective appointment of Captain Howes as Additional Political Agent, Bahrain, for the relevant date would manifestly oe of no avail. 2. The Grovernment of India are advised that a possible remedy would lie in the making of a King's Regulation under clause (a) of Article 70 of the' Bahrain Order in Council for the validation of the marriage. The formula used in that clause (for the peace and good government of the relevant persons) confers a plenary power of legislation in respect of those per sons ? and there seems to be no doubt that a King's Regulation in the relevant sense would be intra vires of that clause. 3. A draft of such a King's Regulation is enclosed herewith. It is expressed in the negative form, inasmuch as the only legitimate object is to save the marriage from being invalidated by reason of the defect in the status of Captain Howes and tiiere is no case for validating the marriage absolutely against other potential defects. 4. The Government of India would be glad to learn if in your opinion there is adequate reason for preferring the cumbrous procedure of validation by legislation to the simple process of repeating the marriage ceremony in proper form.' Sir, I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient serva Sd/- H. .'eightman, Deputy Secretary to the Grovernment of India.npppvpsf Jo A.Full name and style of bridegroom. B .Full name and style of bride. G.Full name and style of Captain Howes. 1. The marriage between A and 3 purporting to have been solemnized cy 5 on the 13th August, 1940, at Bahrain under the authority of the Indian Ghristian Marriage Act, 1872 , read with the Christian Marriage Regulation, 1922, shall not be deemed to have been invalidly solemnized by reason only of the fact that the saia C was not on the said date the Political Agent for the tiaie being at Bahrain. 2. This Regulation may be cited as the Marriage Validation Regula tion, 1940.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003b0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/577</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003b0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/577</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 18/7 Marriage of Vallance Solemnised by Captain Howes when he was Acting as Political Agent'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-06-13T00:22:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at 1 on the front cover and terminates at 7 on the back cover. The numbers are written in pencil and appear in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomaly: ff. 5, 5A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to a question over the authority of the Acting Political Agent, Bahrain to act as Registrar of Marriages, in the light of the solemnisation of a marriage by Captain John Baron Howes in August 1940. The file includes correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and the Government of India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Marriage</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003b0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>