<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000bc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-09T11:32:53.281Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram ijtsK To From .Me. Enclair. Superintendent Post Office Polit1cal, Muscat. (j-. £1 . 19 / if sr Hyderabad Sind. Postmaster Abdul Aziz is at present suffering from Insomnia and is suspected by Medical officer to be developing an 'Anxiety Neurosis' . Medical Ufficer has therefore recoimnended grant of three months medical leave as soon as possible. Medical Certificate will follow by post. ,, Grateful if you will make .early arrangement to send relief for Abdul Agis. -Pol i t ical -Copy of Medical Ueptfr* on +he heel+h of Mr. Abdul - Ari?., Sub~Pos+ Musca+. Medical Hepor+ on Mr. Abdul Aziz, Pos+ Mas+er, Muscat. ''he above pa+ient is in my opinion suffering from an anxiety paresis . s I firs+ examinea him on 16-x-4o and in view of his highly emotional condi+ion I recommended that he be excused all duty for a week, and fur+her recommended +ha+ he be granted 3 months leave. On 34-1-45 I again examined Mr. Abdul -aziz ana ^ in .soi-^e of res+ and tonics, his condition iiad no + improved. He was depressed, was unable +o concentrate and insominico and nervous +remar were very marked symp+oms. Ai* + tr Mental Ca + harsis ^giving -^he pa + ien+ full rest +o describe his symptoms e+c.) on 38-1-45 he appeared +o improve ana on 30-1-4O he a-^tendeu his duties in connec■‘■ion/wi+h mail boa + . He honestly uiu his •'•o w^rk bu+ 1 found in +ne evening yhat he had 'over reactor' had symptoms of exceooive tiredness- audt. of a_I oropar + iG^a.+o tue aLioan+ of work actually uone. He was again very emotional, ana felt that he had com mitted several mis+akes, +ha+ he may be imprisoned e+c. i. m o-day 3-^2 -ao I have again seen the patient ana while all acute symptoms have subsided, I consider him cornple+ely unfi+ +o go back to au+y. Unless he is given a+ leas-*- + hree mon+hs leave, his condi + ion will go from a border line ca^e +o a defini+e men+al Kteuresis. od/— A.G.^. Matthews, Medical Officer, Agency Hospital, Museat- ^rab^a.POLTTXCAL AGENCY, rmscAT, Dated 3rd February, 1945. r /to /tO Jj C «fc-j.X#-' - » From U. Colonel A.C. Galloway, Political agent Gonsux, M_U_S_C_A_T. To The Director of Posts ard TelegrapbiS, Sind end Baluchi ft an Circle, l C E T, Sir, I enclose a copy of my telegram No. Go2I iatecl the I9t:i January, 1945 and the Wndlnel Officer's report on the health cf Mr. Abdullah Bin Aziz. 2. All work at the Post Office, except, the sorting of letters which is being done by the Postman, i«? a- a pt?Tidf still. Please ensure that a relief for Mr. Abdulla Bin tzix j ' o , chi.rkcd on the next steamer for Muscat. I have the honour to :&gt;o, Sir, Your rnst ocodiont servant, Political Agert &amp; H.B.M 5 s Consux •iunert. rie*© Telegram En clair. From Superintendent Post Offices, Hyderabad, Sind. To Post. Muscat. Repeated Political Agent, Muscat. No. B 2/23 Dated 21st and received 22nd February, 1945* Your P/M/20. Attasllih ordered relieve you on work meanwhile. ' s i * A Os CarryTelegram From To No. Dated © En clair. Political, Muscat. Director Posts &amp; Telegraphs, Karachi G.IOO. 7th March, 1945. My letter No.2I5/l2/lO February 3rd. Please confirm that relief of postmaster Abdullah bin Aziz is being sent by next up steamer. -Political-T elegram © En clair. From Director Posts and Telegraphs, Karachi To Political, Muscat. No. SB 144. r y,'o Dated I3th and received I4th March, 1945. Yout G.IOO coded MQI05/K 7th. Presumption confirmed. DPT Karachi.Telegram From To Superintendent, Posts, Hydoradad, Sind. No. 576. . * C' Dat^d tha 5th D :cernbor, 19^6. Reference correspondence ^'6'^earning Muscat Post Master resting with your telegram t'o. 3/2/23 of 21st F ebru ary, 1945. 2* Following is extract from Agency 3ui‘geon 1 s report of today 1 s date on present condition of Abdul Aziz (now in hospital). ‘ . ,f In my opinion Abdul Aziz is fast entering a stage of mania. He is not fit to do his work as Post Master * any longer. He will probably require nursing in a Mental Home ir India. He should in my opinion be invalided out of Government service'as mentally unfit for further duty.” 3 # Post Office is* now closed and kayw when found will bo deposited with me. 4. Grateful for. immediate arrangements for relief. -POLITICAL-En Glair. * Tologran From To No. 570. Political• Muscat. Post Master ; Karachi. Dated the vth December, 1945. Ten mail ba^s are stated to have been handed over to mail officer of Barbara. Receipt for nine bags m.ly was obtained. rloase check and 4 o ] ear o.ph rcsuit. 2I Recsiyei from the Postmaster. H'he following Remarks,/ ) Telegram En Clair. T J From Political, Muscat. To Postmaster, Bombay. No. 530. Dated the 8th December, 1945. Please confirm that you have received two mail bars from Muscat by Barjora which sailed from here on December 2nd. -POLITICAL-Telegram En Glair From To Political Agent, Muscat. Superintendent, posts, Hyderabad, Sind. No. 586. Dated the 15th December, 1945 lour telegram B 6T of _ ber 6th. 1 am surprised to find that no relief has been sent by SS Oradell whifah sailed from Karachi on 13th December. Mohomed Zaman postmaster, Duabi, arrived in SS Barala today cn route to India on leave. To deal with Christotes mail 1 have authorised him to open post office while this steamer is in port* 2 . rlease confirm that relief for Abdul Aziz will be sent by next steamer -POLITICAL-X From Superintendent, rosts, Hyderabad, Sind. To Mohomed Zaman, Postal clerk, Muscat. Hpeate Political Agent, Muscat. No. B2. Dated and Received the 16th December, 1945. Continue to work Muscat Post Office till relief Mohomed idan already at Karachi to sail arfives. Political Muscat. Reference his 586 D/- 15th. Ascertaining cause why relief missed steamer. ■y' 7~*\ Bn Clair. Political, Muscat. Superintendent, Posts, Hyderabad, Sind. Telegram i?'rom To No. 599. Dated the 16th December, 1945. IMMEDIATE. Your telegram B2 of December 16th. In the circumstances in which leave has been granted to Mohomed ^aman consider his being made to work here until arrival of relief for Abdullah Aziz will ■% bn unduly hard on him. As he has cleared iabils and on assumption that relief is being sent by next steamer which is expected here very shortly suggest your orders be cancelled and he be allowed to proceed to India. Please telegraph reply immediately as steamer sails PM 17th. -POLITICAL-Telcgraai From To ,/© Superintendcnt, rosts, Hyderabad, Sind. Political, Muscat. No. B61. Dated — Received the 20th December, 19^5. - ^ • / . . Your 576/5th. * 4 Wire whether Residency Surgeon considered competent author rt^for grant certificate under 442 and 447 C-S.R. If so obtain forward certificate prescribed form, official's date birth 18.6.1897 repeat 18.6.1897#En Glair, * Telegram F£om Political Agent, Muscat. To Postmaster, Bombay. No. 60o. Dated the 21st December, 1945. My telegram 530 December 8th. Please telegraph reply. -POLITICAL-&gt; C En Clair ,/^V Telegram From To Political Agent, Muscat. Superintendent, Posts, Hyderabad Sind. No. 617. bated the 30th December, 19^5. Your B61 of 20th December. Agency Surgeon is commissioned Medical Officer. Please see C.S.R. 442 (d). -POLITICAL-No. 55-12/10 To POLITICAL AGENCY AND H.B.M'S CONSULATE, MUSCAT. Dated the 6th January, ly-afi. The Superintondent, host Offices, Lower Sind and Persian tiuif Division, HYDERABAD . (SIND) / MEMOFANDU?^ . \ # Reference correspondence resting with this office telegram No. 617 dated the 30th December, 1945. 2. A certificate in the prescribed form is forwarded herewith.MEDIC/Uj CBRTIFIC/rS. Certified that X have carefully examined MJ* ALzbeoUz — son of Jsiir-fMr.-lte.’.U- 1 „ U» ZfxMeit :.-— IJtfll'- —. His ago is by uIb own siate- mont years, and by appearance //C ^ . . _ , aboib ———— SL ^years* i consiQ^^x — ~ to be completely and penanantly incapacitated for farther service of any kind V or in the Depart, ant to whicn ho belongs) in . dm4Ci*-c*z. conse^acnec oi 7 5lHis incapacity does not appear to to have been caused by irregular or intemperate habits* Muscat, The ^January, ld46 Medical Officer, Agency Hospital, Muscat,I, understand that amongst the pas sengers 4a your ship, you have the Postmast r from Dubai, who is proceeding to India on leave. I shall be very grateful if yon will kindly have him informed that I wish to see him as early as possible at the Agency in regard to an important matter. 2. The Agency whaler will wait at the ship to bring him ashore.i No. 1824. To HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, TLo 18th December, 1945. The Director General of Customs, M U S C A T. Mernoranourn. Six parcels Trom the lost OYfice for Major L.B# Hirst, Dr. Thoms, and the Off icer-in-charge, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., are sent herewith for assessment of duty and deli very to the addressees. for Consul, Muscat.1 / &lt;? - •• ♦ * ni Corr.-B 1 , INDIAN P- STS AND TELSTGnA »w&lt;? DEP' RTM~ NT. ESFRSSS LE J- Ji, If a [y.'B.— This is • n ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by pest to rave telegraphic expense ani undue i US'- of the vires, but intended to be treated, &lt;&gt;n re- ipt, with the same expedition as it it had been telegraphed. To s ve time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched, 1 . / No. Hated , the m &amp; lo ■a —No. 262-12/10. © POLITICAL AGENCY AND H.B.U'S CONSULATE, MUSCAT. Dated the 9th Feoruary, 19'±6. r- Leforenco yoot- letter No. Muscat- 232 dated the 2nd February, 1^6. 2 . As the seal of the bag containing the packet in question has been reported by you to ha ’O been found intact on arri/al of the mail bag at Muscat, an enquiry by the Foil tical Agent appears to be unnec essar^•L No. 301-12/10. POLITICAL AGENCY AND H.B.M*S CONSULATE, MUSCAT. Uatcd the 16th February, 39 46. To The Superintendent, Post offices, Hyderabad . (Sind.) Memorandum. Reference your letter No. C.70 dated the 17th January, 1946. 2. The medical certificate dated the 6 th January, 1946, is returned herewith duly completed. 3. The second medical certificate recommending leave has been cancelled by the Agency Surgeon. $ Political Agent, Muscat Yv\Telegram ■Krom To Wo. Nil. Dated and received h*n Clair • Superintendent, rost officer, Hyderabad, the 20th February, 1946. kindly refer rnycM 70 January 17th and arrange early return Medical certificate Abdulla Aziz after amendment. Your 66/42/10 January 6 th refers.. *i \ V INDIAN POSTS AND TeLEGR^PHS DEP^PTM' NX EXPRESS LETTER. % rvp.- ,Tii» it on OTtTOINAL MESSAGE, tent by p*st to save tdegrupKi* teryenze and mdw» ut« of the :gret, bet intended to be treated, •&gt;* rer.'ipt, with the same expedition ft? if it k-od been telegraphed, T* tiae time and formalities it is worded and signed AJ if it had been n despatched*} M®, BF.710/45 Dm&amp;d ft Sir, Bombay .^N ■ '1 , the 27th Dec.- ,4 q° ( S' ■ The political Agent, f&lt;~ V M us c at . ? i r. U 8 ^ ' , 1 have the honour to enclose for your information a copy, of this office letter of even . number dated the 13/12/45 addressed to tne FosoiiBste 1 , Muscat, with reference to your telegram IT©:605 aated 21/12/1945. \ . I have etc., -iLSvp*' Cop; With reference to your cablegram NqS^ vIR.^oO/l ociued the Sth current, enquiring about 2 mail bags Muscat despatched by the s.s. BARJC7A vihich sai^ea from Muscat on the 2/12/1945, inform you that only one sacs /Bombay Foreign despatch N 0 :8 received in Bombay on It contained 3c+2R empty bags ‘Muscat despatch Xo.ll dated the &gt;3/1V• ' 3 KD I have the honour to vides relating to Muscat dated 28/11/45 was - 10/12/45 by s.s.BABu ORA pertaining to Bombay/0 INDIAN POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT. SOTV TH&gt; C’-SV:. This is v «ass la which seven parker pens were found frosi London S # w, 11 registered packet ifo* 69bl d&amp;ted December 1945 against ItmAfrer 10 entered on the lace of the packet when it was opened at^scat at the time of delivery on 22 # 1 # 46 # The jacket was addressed to Messers yurshottam Madhavji Muscat and was sent by Messers Parker Ben Company Ltd# | London# London S.w* 11 registered packet No# 6931 was sent by the London (ost Office adotieed in its registered list dated the 8#li#X945 in a direct mail bag ior Bahrain# ill is mail bag travelled by sea and arrived at Bahrain on the 8#i#46# According to the 3ub Postaaater's report of Bahrain the mail bag vas received in the post office in good condition the registered packet referred to above i*jas also in good condition# when the same was cxeminod in the ordinary course* the registered packet v^as intended for Muscat it remained in deposit in the Bahrain post office till there was a steamer to go to Muscat# The registered packet retnained in the charge of Mr* Raimatulleh vrfco was the registration cler&amp; of the post office till 10*1*1946# hen he handed over charge of the registration branch to Mr# Shivdlyai another our*, of t*he post office# Shis registered packet remained in the custody of K ; r# ^ivdiyal in the post office till it was despsioched on the 17#1#I946 to Ltuscat by sea by the co# f stumer due to sail fbr Muscat# According to the statement of ^# Rahm&amp;tullah Clark Bahrein post office, the registered packet was in good condition, when it was received in the Bair ain post oil ice on 8*1*1946 and it vms in the same good condition when it was handed ever by him on 10#1#1946 to Mr# ^ivdiyai cleric on the transfer of the charge of the registration hr inch by him# According to the statement of Mr# .hivwiysl, the re^istex'ed packet was in good condition, when he received it while teeing over charge on 10#1 #1946 and it was in the same condition when it was sdespatched by him to Muscat post office on 17#1#46# According to the postal procedure, all registered articles are put in a bag known as registered bag and it is sealed# The * seal registered bag hs then p*t in axother beg kn^?.n as mail beg which besides Hie registered bag contains o&amp;y wait** matter# This mail bag is also, sealed# l&amp;is is how registered articles travel# The n?gietered packet under reference also travelled under these precautions# The mail bag prepared by Bahrain post office on 17#lk 1946 for Jiuecct post office was received at Muscat on 21# 1#1946 : # According to the statement of Mr# Mohd Idan Sub Postmaster Muscat the mail hag was received in good condition by him* 'it was evened aju tne registeroag contained in the msil t^g ms also opened* The xe^xalexed bag was in good condition# it was opened and the registered packet under reference remely London SW-11 registered packet No# 6981 dated December 1946 was found in a damaged condition so much so that the contents wfcere quite visible# it was weighed by the S*P#M# Muscat and found to weigh 38o grams U.T.O.)No.1108-12/ID. Ntj POLITICAL AGENCY AND HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, 'the 8th August, 1346. / . To HeaSL Hecorcj Clerk, J) R* M* S., Karachi. i Memorandum . Reference your Memorandum No.6/3 dated the 26th June, 1946. 2. In the absence of the original copy of the list of the registered letters dated Karachi the 1st November, 1945, appears Xo have been mislaid the information required can only be furnished on receipt of details of the contents of the registered letter which may please be obtained from the sender, lour letter under reference together with enclosures is returned herewith.No. 1312-12/10. POLITICAL AGENCY AND HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY 1 S CONSULATE, MBSC&amp;T. DATEDthe 17th. Oct. *46 The Superintendcnt, Posts and Telegraphs, Hyderabad, SIND. MEMORANDUM. Reference your telegram No.41F 129 dated the 15th Octooer 1946 and your endorsement No.F.129, dated the 22nd. June, 1946. Further enquiries have yielded no further information in regard to the abstraction of Parker pons from the Registered Packet in question. No reason has been discovered which would give cause for believ^ that the Postal Staff at Muscat are at faults On the contrary, it appears much more likely that the pens were removed at Bahrain where the parcel remained for a considerable time and where it changed hands before it could bo sent to Muscat 2. It is regretted that no further light can be thrown on this case at Muscat. s ^ Political Agent, MuscatNo • 1402«5 Pereian Gulf Residency* Bahrain» the 29th July 1947. To The Political Agent, Kuwait The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent* Muscat.^ Mi^QRANBUM. Copy i» enclosed of the Minutes of a Meeting held at the India Office on llth July 1947 on the future administration of postal eerrices in the Persian Gulf. 2. Please inform of the impending change in administration of the post office and of the proposal to introduce in due course British stamps overprinted with Indian currency values surcharged ■ l&amp;f** Muscat , To Muscat only . Please ascertain from the Sultan whether the proposal to impose the surcharge 'Muscat* on the stamps to he used in Muscat territory would he acceptable to him and telegraph his reply. Sd. a.c.gai*u&gt;*ay. Political Resident* Persian Gulf. Attested. for Seore Political Resident* Persian Gulf*1 V i r COI^imiTIAL FUTURE ADUNI^RiglON (J±? PQSIUL SERVICES IK THE EEjRSL jl'I GULP Hinutes pi' a maotinrj: ncld at the India Office on 11th July, 19L7 Present r*\ Mr. E.P. Donaldsen (indie. Office) in the Chair Sir Rupert Hoy hiss P.C. Shaw hr. L.F.L. lyman hr. F.J. Ford ) hr. E.P. Bell ) Mr, A. \/olstcncroft ) Lr. 17. A. Langton ) Mr. F.A.X. Harrison) hr. n.K. Reed ) Political Resident, Persian Gulf Treasury Foreign Office General Post Office India Office ^• Provision of Staff (a) Subordinate . The G.P.O. representatives stated that it would be impossible to obtain subordinate staff from this country and that they would have to be recruited either locally or from India, Since new staff could not be recruited and trained by April, 1943, it would be necessary to ask the Indian authorities to lend trained staff (presumably on ’•foreign service” terms) for a period after 1st April, 1943. Negotiations to this end would have to be undertaken with the appropriate Indian successor Government (presumably Pakistan since the Persian Gulf has hitherto been included in the Karachi circuit). _is regards future recruit ment of subordinate staff, it was agreed that this would ha.vc to be done through the Political Residency, (b) Superior . The Political Resident considered tha.t one British Supervisor would bo sufficient, at any rate at first, particularly in view of the shortage of living accommodation at Bahrein. He felt that a. salary sufficient to provide 9800 per annum clear (after deduction of income-tax), and free accommodation, would be reasonable. The tour of duty might be for 2 years $ Adequate home leave was necessary in view of the very trying climate. The Post Office representatives agreed to modify accordingly the proposed terms of service put forward by their Department and to examine such details as outfit allowance, travelling expenses and free a.ir tra.vel for leave. It w,as .■greed to defer consideration of the appointment of a British Deputy Supervisor until it could be examined in the light of experience, say after 6 months. Sir R. Hay suggested that it would probably oe possible for a member of his Office to deputise for short periods while the Postal Supervisor wan on leave or awry, so an to keep the machine running. The suggestion was welcomed by the G.P.O, 2. Division of responsibilities between the Political Resident 1 s Office and the! of the Postal Supervisor It was contemplated tha.t the Resident, in addition to recruiting subordinate staff for the posted organisation (see 1(a) above), should be responsible for the general supervision of a.ccounts and the submission of /returnsreturns t j the G.P.O. in London, end. for the provision of funds for the Post Offices. He \ 70 uld els 0 ..maintain a general responsibility for the efficient running of the postal orgenisation in the x-ersian Gulf. 3. Postage Rates » It was explained that at present the Gulf Post Offices charged Indian Inland Postal Rates. If the Post Office took over, they would wish to run them on a different system which would involve cite rat ions to existing postal charges. This would mean increased cost of postage from the Gulf to India, but perhaps cheaper rates from the Gulf to the U.K. There would bo inland rates between the different Gulf Post Offices. The Political Resident did not anticipate any serious difficulties in introducing these changes, and there might be some advantages. The G.P.O. represent olives mentioned that it would be necessary to negotiate a, postal agreement (or agreements) with the new Governments in India, regarding the , new arrangements for exchange of postal traffic. 1 , Special Services . The Post Office would be unable, at leant for the r\ time being, to provide any special services such os V.P. Parcels or Post Office Savings Bank facilities. They would, however, be willing to liquidate the responsibilities of the Indian Posts &amp; Telegraphs Department for Indian Sa.vings Bank .mounts and Indian National Savings Certificates in accordance with the agreement recently reached between the Government of India and the Treasury. 5. Posto^c Stamps . The Post Office proposed to introduce in due course British stamps overprinted with Indian currency values. It was agreed that the single surcharge ’’Persian Gulf .agencies” f or all the States had some advantages, but separate surcharges (i.c. 'lowcit”, ’’Bahrein”, '’Trucial Coast” and ’’muscat”) might be profera.ble as occupying less space on the stamps. It v;as agreed to ask the acting Political Resident to find out if the latter suggestion would be acceptable to the Sultan of muscat. 6 . Reference was made to the following matters of detail:- ^ (a) Oustoms Roquiremonts . These would vary with the different Sheikhdoms concerned. It would be necessary for tne G.P.O. t j ascertain the facts and insert details in their official handbook. •(b) Forms and Rubber Stamps . The existing ones could be taken over from ,the Indian Posts &amp; Telegraphs Department. (c) Hail Contract . The G.P.O. considered it better that the Government of India should maintain a general contract on present linos with the British India, (or other) line, and thal they should make use of these services by agreement with the Government of India., rather than that the G.P.O. should enter into a separate contract with a. shipping line. r (cO Buildings . The Political Resident thought all Post Offices, apart from those in the Muscat agency buildings, were rented. It would be necessary to ensure the rencvral of their leases. (c) Gwadur . The G.P.O. representatives said that they were not anxious to take on any telegraph commitments at Gwadur. It was agreed that it might be considered whether the Indian Posts 1 Telegraphs Department should not be asked to take these over, together with the land-line to | Panjgur. \ (f) Ko-. 70 it-Ba.srau Telephone Hinc&gt; The GJ.10&gt; • agreed to approach Cable &amp; lireless Ltd. regarding their taking over of tnc telephone line between Koweit and Basra. As)A / 2o C ONFIDENTIAL . No. 1424-S fv47 V/ - Hon f ole the Political fiesident i the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent 9 Bahrain* The Political Agent t Kuwait* The Political fgeot, Muscati 1 tUV Vv J and has the honour to transmit to him a copy op''rhe undermentioned document(sj. for imorjaation* PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated th&lt;| 31st J uly* 1947* Reference to pi^evious coi respor^ence Description of enclosure ; Number and Date Subject 1* Inula Office letter No* Ext. 1296/47| dated 18/6/47 2* Government of India telegram No. 6209. dated 8/7/47 3* India Office telegram No. 9684 9 dated 28/7/47 TRANSFER OF POSTS aND TELEGRAPH SERVICES IN THE Pi^SlAN GULF. G D A * Ivi.^— Ext. 1296/47 India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I. 18th June, 1947. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to Lord Pethick-Lawrence's Despatch External No. 1 of 4!th March, 1947 regarding the future adffi ^istratlon and control of His Majesty's Government's relations with the . r States in the Persian Gulf, and to the note the Indian Posts and Telegraph Services the Persian Gulf forwarded with Colonel Crichton's letter No. l*&lt;«)0)BPG/4b ol *. 6 th March, 2. The Government of India will no doubt agree that, as a necessary consequence of the transfer of administrative control In the Persian Gulf to His Majesty's Government, it follows that His Majesty's Government should themselves eventually assume responsibility the administration of the postal services in this area. On the a *?* l f p tion th^t the Gov rnment of India will £ ‘ 8 r ® e &lt; . consid 6 r ^^°L h f® given by His Majesty^ Government to arrangements fox the transfer of control to themselves. ^ His Maiesty^s Government contemplate that the pcstal administration in the Gulf should be placed under the general authority of the Political Resident who would be provided, by His Majesty's Postmaster General, with one official, anr necessary a deputy as well, to act as general supervisor of the postal agencies and as adviser to the Political xsi en on postal matters. It will not be possible to pro subordinate staff from the United Kingdom end it is contemplated that such staff would be recruited locally or from India. 4 . The process of transfer of control from the Indian Post and Telegraphs Department will, however, take time, and His Majesty s Government would propose that in the int- period the postal services should continue to be run on the present basis by the Indian Post and Telegraphuepartoent (any losses or profits being carried by that Department) until His Majesty's Government are able 1 take until 1st April, 1948, whichever is earlier. ^while E3s Majesty’s Government would be glad to be provided as as possible with certain additional intormation regarding receipts, expenditure and traffic, details oi ,.hich are given in the annexture of this letter 5. His Majesty's Government have also given preliminary consideration to the following matters of detail:- (a) ‘iv--ic. gr.,n-, Paolj itles . , It is contemplated that these should remain in the hands of Cable and wireless Limited (who have their ovn telegraph on ices in the Sheikhdoms) with the possible exception oi that part oP Kowelt-Basra land line, situated in Koweit territory, now maintained by the Indian Post and Telegraph Department. /(b)ui • 2 (b) feonev Orders * H will be necessary when His Majesty*s Government take over control that the Political Resident should be in a position to arrange for the supply of .'i funas in rupee currency to th^ local Postmasters to enable them to meet local demands. (c) Stamps . It will be a matter for consideration subject to the reccmmeAdation of the Political Resident what stamps should be used to replace the Indian stamps at present used. 6 . The Secretary of State would be glad to receive at an early date the views of the Government of India and the Political Resident (to whom a copy of this letter is being sent) on these proposals. Jl dill | 1 f Your obeiiant servant, Sd/ £.P. Donaldson I am. Sir Copied ML. / The Secretary to the Government of India External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations Department, New Delhi,A N H E X U i. E POST OFFIC ES IN THE PERSIAN Q»L£ Y« h rlv incorafi Call Post Offices) yearly E^i en-i ^ ** (all post Offices) Ri Ss Postage Stamps sold; For Postal purposes To stamp dealers Private boy fees Poundage on Lioney Orders Poundage on Postal Order Parcels (share ol revenu and ether fees) ► Telegraph an^-Telephone Wages Salaries/'and allowances Rent Rates, Lighting etc. Stores supplied Travelling &lt;$c Subsistence Conveyance of mails By land By sea evenue Parcel Post (terminal and 4* n r* 4 4* 1 ^ v\ m Ot Yy cs ) Miscellaneous Income (not inc?.tided above) Air toail payments Cost of rrail bsgs x Establishment cost incurred at Karachi in connection with Persian Gulf Post Offices (including costs of inspectioi Miscellaneous expenditure (net included above) Traffic Etc . An estimate of the yearly valume of Air Mail traffic, parcul traffic (inward and outward) and Money Order Postal Ofaer traffic. Figures giving the value of Post Office equipment at the various Offices.- Telegram S 3. (CYPHER TELEGRAM O.T.P. SECRET) Prom Government of India, Dept, of E.A. &amp; C.R. To India Office t London. Repeated Political Resident, Bahrain * , Ho. 5309 Dated 8 th received 10th July, 1947. Your letter Ext 1296/47 June 18th. TRANSFER OF POST AND TELEGRAPH SERVICES IN PERSI..N GULF. 2 Government of India agree to transfer of these services as corollary to transfer of Gulf administration. while Government of India cannot definitely nnmmlt*successor governments It is agreed that operation commit succes.orcgover me^ ^ ^ BR i ? talned on present basis by Government of Inala tc ^ 4 a. j «. successor cover nr. ^nt wlil agiee xc dfso thereafter UU H?”g! are ready to assume control -nd will even after the assumption of control be a b l« to depute subordinate staff as are required till H.K.G. are in a position tc supply taeir own staff. 4 . It will be necessary before assumption of control by H.M.C. to arrive at valuation of all P &amp; buildings'equipment etc in time. ._ t to see no^bjection to transfer of all such f^P^ g £ r u ** rir ftnf i o r e DrovisionAily prepared to base tiansitr o^bc^k values/ d’hey ™uld be glad to Know as soon as possible whether H.fi.G. accept this pioposul. 5 . It will be necessary for H.X.G. bo provide own pcstare stamps from date they assume control. To fscilitste withdrawal of existing Indian atamps ^ni will be used tlli that date Ccvernii.ent of India wo uld be glad to have longest possible notice of o te which H.M.G. propose to take cvei control. 6 Information called for in annexure (lihI) letter of ? June 18th is being collected and will be sent as soon es possible. - Foreign - CQPJLfcQ ML.HQtl India Office, London. Government of Indio., Department of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations• Political Resident, Eanrain. 9684 28th received 29tb July, 3947, your telegram No. 5309 July 8 th. Transfer of Posts and Telegraphs Services in Persian Gulf. 2. Ycur paragraph He. 3. As long term policy H.tf.G. propose to recruit subordinate staff on contract either locally or from India. You will appreciate that H.M.G. themselves will be unable to provide any trained subordinate staff by ^pril 1948 and it will therefore be essential for continued efficient running of ^ulf Post Office services (in which of course India herself has a~clbse interest) that such staff should continue to be loe.ne , to p.Vf.G. by successor Government for a oeriod after thrt date it is hoped therefore that successor Government will be agreeable to loan of permrinent staff on deputation terms. H.M.G. woula like to to able to arrange this as soon as possible, 3. Your paragraph ho. 4. H.M.G. while accepting in principle the suggesticr of Government of India thet all Posts and Telegraphs buildings, equipment etc. should be transferred at beck value would be grateful for details ci property involved. Information available here suggests thr.t all y buildings except Muscat are ranted. 4 . Your paragraph bo. 5. intend to provide their own postage stamps as soon as they assume control. They will give you longest possible notice of that date. £. *&amp;all contracts. Il.M.G are inclined tc think it will be preferable for Government of India to continue general contract on present linos with British India (or other line) and that H.Ii.G. should av.iil themselves of this contract f f*Qr purrosos cf Gulf Post office ziri'&amp;ngements by agreement with Government of India. f. In order to discuss various questions concerning transfer it 5s hoped it will be possible to send b G.P.O. representative to India for preliminary talks ir. October. This official might then tour ,the Gulf with an i.ndian Posts and Telegraphs official beforejreturning to India if n cessary tc enter on final negotiaticns. H.te.C. oo not intend to send Post Office representative to Gulf before then. gopied ML. Telegram Prom To Repeated No. Dated Retaxandum -5* Telegram From To No. zohe Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 872 Dated 6th received 7th August, 1947* Please let me have your recommendations as to/^uture of telegraph arrangements at Gv/adar including land line to^P^iijgur mentioned in paragraph 6 (e) of Minutes forwarded with my menorandum No. 1402-3 July 29th. - GALL0Y.AY - NCJTelegram GTG Political Agent. Muscat. His Highness the Sultan, Salalah. From To No. Dated G.237. 10th August, 1947. Consequent on the constitutional changes in India, His Majesty's Government propose to take over postal administration in Muscat and introduce in due course British stamps overprinted with Indian currency value surcharged Muscat. o # Grateful if Your Highness will please confirm that the proposal to impose the surcharge ’’Muscat” on the stamps will be acceptable. POLITICALTelegram From To No. &amp;ob€ Political A ent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bahrain. C/368 Dated the 10th August, 1947. Your telegram No. 872 August 6th. 2. Only alternative to asking Pakistan to accept responsibility for posts and telegraphs in Gwadur is to establish small wireless station there capable of communicating with Muscat. I understand equipment for this would not repeat not cost more than pounds sterling 1,000 and it could be run by one nan. It is doubtful whether traffic would be sufficient to meet expenses but if man in charge were placed also in charge of posts and whole drawn under supervision of Muscat Post Office I am sure profits in Muscat would more than cover any loss at Gwadur and arrangement would be more satisfactory both politically and from the point of view of communications. POLITICALTelegram From To GTC His Highness the Sultan, Salalah. British Consul, Muscat. No. Too 131600Z Dated 14th and received 14th August, 1947. 237 Yours G.273 August 10th. For some reasons consider proposed stamps should he without imposing surcharge 'Muscat ' 1 on them as in the case of Indian stamps. SAID. 0 . 12/10 Telegram Code From Political Agent, Muscat, To Political Resident, iahrain. No. C/373 Dated the 16th August, 1947. ij / Your memorandum No. 1402-S July 29th. 2. For some reasons Sultan considers proposed stamps should be without imposing surcharge ^Muscat* 1 as in the case of Indian stamps. - POLITICAL - NCJA2 3; 2-o . g't&lt; O . ( India Office* Whitehall» London* S.W.l, Ext • 1476/47 My dear Galloway* 19th July* 1947. I enclose for your information four copies of the Minutes of an Interdepartmental Meeting held here about the transfer of post and telegraph services in the Persian Gulf • 2. We should he glad if you would take up the point referred to in paragraph 5 about surcharges. The Sultan is perhaps the only rulef whom it will be necessary to consult* but we will leave this to you. 3. Before you receive this letter you will probably have read the repetition of a telegram from us to the Government of India in reply to their No. 5309 of 8th July. Yours ever, Eion Donaldson. Lieutenant-Colonel A.C.Galloway, C.I.E.*0.3 .E. * Persian Gulf Residency* Bahrain • Persian Gulf Residency* No. 1457-S . Bahrain, the 7th August 1947. Copy forwarded, with compliments* to The Political Agent, Kuwait . The Political Agent, Bahrain , The Political Agent* Muscat , . with reference to correspondence ending with Residency Printed Letter No. 1424-S dated the 31st July 1947. 2. The Minutes referred to were forwarded under Residency Memorandum No. 1402-3 dated the 29th July 1947. \T&gt;ft) /Z32- ? O &gt; $ lf ^ C ONFIDENTIAL . N o. 1458*3 • The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 7 The Political Agent, \ Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of '.he undermentioned documentj*'#/. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 7th Au gust 1947 Reference to previous coirespondence Residency telegram No *872 dated the 6 th August 1947 Description of enclosure : Number and Date India Office Express Letter No. Ext. 1582/47 dated the 29th July 1947. G.A.K. Subject Future telegraph arrangements at Gwadur. v S’IKDIA OFFICE, te r J. Department ) EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) From Secretary of State for India poiitleal ..esido at, Earsian u ali Dated No.^ 15a^47 Donaldson’s demi-official letter to Calloway dated 19th July, • 1476/47* Posts and telegraph eenrioes t lo Persian Sulf. 2 . Please let me have your recasmnendations as to future of telegraph arrangements at G-\maur, including land-lino of Panjgur mentioned in paragraph 6(e) of minutes of meeting of 11 th July. 3 . Spare oojy is enclosed for coo von Let ion to Political .gent, usoat. The issue of the above lias been duly authorised (Sgd.) E.P. Donaldson,PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN. EXPRESS LETTER* Repgu Bahrain* Retaxandum London Political Muscat. /2-9&lt;, - p (bU j / Dated the 14th August 1947. Reference your iixprees Letter Ho. Ext. 1582/47, dated 29th July 1947. FUTURE OF TELEGRAPH ARRAUGEilJSJTS AT GWADUR. ' f r 2. Gvadur is at present maintained hy the Indian Post and Telegraphs Department as a combined post and telegraph office. Its monthly income and expenditure as shown in enclosure IV of low’s letter No J?’.15^10/47» dated the 7th July 1947 to Donaldson is approximately Es 1252 and Rs 392 respectively. This does not include the proportionate cost of the carriage of sea mail nor the cost of maintenance of the Gwadur-Panjgur line viz. Es 625 per month. Even taking these two items into account it is probable that the office at present pays its way. 3. To take over only the post office at Gwadur would be uneconomical. To take over the telegraph office as well would involve the payment of heavy charges for the Indian Post and Telegraphs Department’s assets,.-vide enclosure to Low’s letter quoted above. Ihe installation of even a small wireless station communicating only with Muscat would cost an appreciable sun and the pay of an operator would be much more than that of a signaller of the Post and Telegraphs Department. It would also involve the wasteful scrapping of the present land line to Panjgur. 4. Prom the political point of view it would be preferable if Gwadur could be brought under the same postal administration as that of Muscat. I do not consider, , however, that there is sufficient justification for achiev ing this at the financial loss that would be likely to result. I recommend therefore that, subject to the consent of the Sultan of Muscat, the Government of Pakistan should be asked to continue the existing postal and telegraph arrangements at Gwadur. Sd. a. c. gallo way. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL.CONFIDENTIAL No.1598-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN. the 4th September 1947 My dear Donaldson, ^ 6 ^ Will you please refer to your letter No.Ext.1476/47, dated the 19th July, 1947, about the transfer of post and telegraph services in |he Gulf. 2. On being informed of the proposal to introduce in due course British stamps overprinted with Indian currency values surcharged ’’MUSCAT' the Sultan replied that the stamps should not be surcharged 'MUSCAT'• This is in accordance with existing practice, whereby Indian stamps without any surcharge are used in Muscat. nrc vi 3. The Shaikh of Kuwait, like the Shaikh of Bahrain (vide my Demi-official letter N 0 .I 666 -S dated the 28th August, 1947), himself raised the subject and suggested that the Indian Post-office should be replaced by a Kuwaiti one. He did not, however, mention the revenue accruing from the post-office. Tandy pointed out that the knowledge of international rules and agreements and of accounting involved was beyond that of any of the Shaikh’s subjects and he believes that the Shaikh realises that the post-office will have to be maintained under our direction. The Shaikh would, however, like as many Kuwaitis as possible to be employed and wishes the stamps used in Kuwait to bear his image and superscription. His wishes on these points could presumably be met. 4. I am sending copies of this letter to Stewart and Tandy. Yours sincerely, Sd/- A.C. Galloway E.P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office, King Charles Street, Whitehall, LONDON. S.W.l ’LB* No.1600tS PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY. BAHRAIN , the 4th September *47 Copy forwarded with compliments tos- 1. Major M.P.O’C Tandy, Political Agent, KUWAIT / 2. Major A.C. Stewart, O.B.E., Political Agent, MUSCAT •LB' t p &lt;?oiV 12/10 ‘ k /~\ Q Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat• 991 Dated l^th received 17th September, 1947. Paragraph 4 of ny Express Letter No. 1506-3 August 14th. Telegram From To No. Postal Arrangements at Gwadur. Please approach Sultan accordingly and telegraph his reply. NCJ GALLOWAY12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From H.M* s. Consul, Muscat. To H.H. the Sultan of Muscat, at Salalah (through R.-a.F. Aden &amp; Salalah) No. C/420 Dated the 18th September, 194V. In view of the impracticability of His Majesty's Government's Postal Administration maintaining the Gwadur - Panjgur telegraph line nis Ivfejesty's Government has suggested that subject to Your nighness' consent they should ask the Pakistan Government to accept responsibility for continuing the existing postal and telegraph arrangements at Gv/adur. I should be grateful if Your Highness could telegraph your viev/s. - CONSUL - NCJTelegram From To No. Dated 12/10 G.T.C. His Highness at Salalah. Political Agent, Muscat. Nil and received 20th September 1947. Important. Following for Consul Muscat. Begins. ^5 ^ 7. Your C. 420. If it is impracticable we shall be grateful to H.B.M. Government whom we shall authorise to make necessary arrangements which they may consider best for continuation of existing Postal and Telegraph Administration but we reserve right for any future arrangement ( if any) which our government may have in this connection. Ends. SaidTelegram Q. From Commonwealth Relations Office, London* To GoYeroment of Pakistan, Karachi* Repeated Government of India, Kew Delhi* Political Resident, Bahrain* Ko. 11048 Dated 26th received 27 th August 1947 My telegram to Government of India 14o*9634 of July 28th* Transfer of Posts and Telegraphs services in Persian Gulf* 2* Grateful for an early reply* On assumption that you will agree His Majesty’s Government are pro ceeding with ari&amp;ngements for General Post Office official to visit India as proposed in paragraph 6 of my telegram leaving United Kingdom about October 15th* Presumably Pakistan will be the Government chiefly concerned - RdTAXANDUM Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 50th August 1947 • Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Kuwait * The Political Agent, Bahrain , The Political Agent, Muscat , for information, with reference to Residency Printed Letter Mo* 1424-S dated the 51st July / (GOVJSRMiSNT OF INDIA Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations. EXPRESS DSTTER. Prom Foreign, New Delhi 3. To Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations., london. Repeated Foreign, Karachi. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. No. D.126-AWT/47. Dated the 3rd Sept., 1947. { *T) Reference Secretary of State for India telegram No. 9684 July 28th. Transfer of Posts and Telegraphs services in Persian Gulf. 2. Your Paragraph No•2. Lt. Col. Spear, Director General, Posts and Telegraphs of Pakistan had informed us that Pakistan Government will continue to maintain postal arrangements in the Gulf on deputation basis until His Majesty’s Government are ready to take over. 3. Your paragraph No.3. The list of property and equipment in the Post Offices in the Persian Gulf is enclosed. There are no buildings or land belonging to the Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department except the one at Gwadur. Two other offices at Pasni and Ormara^are housed in Posts and Telegraphs buildings but presumably they being on the Mekran Coast do not come in the Persian Gulf arrange ment. 4. Your paragraph No»b. Two mail contracts i.e. Bahrain and Kuwait are purely of local interest and should present no difficulty. As regards the contract with the B.I.S.N.Co. the Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department will continue to pay for it and whatever mails are carried by the steamers under contract with the Government of India will have to be paid for at the rates given in the Universal Postal Convention. His Majesty’s Government to pay for their benefits under B.I.S.N. contract. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd. J.N.DHAMIJA Under Secretary to the Government of India. No • ! (j ^ t —S. Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 11th September 1947. Copy (without enclosure) forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, KUWAIT, The Political Agent, BAHRAIN, The Political Agent, MUSCAT, w'* ' ' ) O ; j with reference to Residency Printed i dated the 31st July 1947. Letter N0.1424-S12/10 Telegram From To No. Q Political Agent, ■ iiscst. Political Resident, Bahrain. C/424 Dated the 22nd September, 1947. L&lt;6 Your telegram No. 991 September 16th. Postal Arrangements at Gwadur. 2. Sultan agrees to Pakistan Government being asked to continue existing arrangements but reserves “right for any future arrangement which our Government may have in this connection.“ - POLITICAL - « A/C J*100/7 I.W.C. Commonwealth Relations Office, London. Political Resident, Bahrain. 11615 Dated 13th and received 15th September, 1947. ( ^ c*c ( Your Express Letter No.1506-3 dated August 14th para 4. POSTAL ARRANGEMENTS AT GWADUR. Please approach Sultan accordingly. \ = RETAXANDDM = ONFIuENTIAL. No. 1656-5 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. the 16th September, 1947. V Copy forwarded, with compliments, to - The Political Agent, LUSCAT , in continuation of Residency telegram No.991 dated the 16th September, 1S47. CDS.CMDPID&amp;MTIaL From 2o 1 i UUUlA k &amp;JLIJLSL Political Resident f Ba^nrain E^M's Secretary of State Tor Commonwealth Relational Bond Political Agent| Muscat. / on. Repeated S0.16M-S Sated &amp;ahrain f the 23rd September 9 1947. -S' i Your telegram Ho#11615 September 13th. Postal arrangements at Gwadur. 2. Sultan agrees to Pakistan Government being asked to continue existing arrangements but reserves 'right lor any future arrangement which our Government may have in this connection'. Sd/» A.C. Galloway. Political Resident| Persian Gulf# m For Secretary to the Political Realdenti Persian Gull. • LB* //?Telagran From To Political Resident f Bahrain Commonwealth Relations Office! London No.999. Dated the 24th September, 1947. m mm- , Foreign Delhi Express Letter No.D.126 AWT 47 September 3rd 1947. 2 Postmaster Bahrain has received instruct ions from Director General Posts and Telegraphs Pakistan that stamps overprinted Pakistan will be released from 1st October and that all post offices should obtain these overprinted stamps and return absolute stamps. Over printed stationery is being introduced from 1st November. Sudden change of stamps may be misunderstood 3 cf my letters 1666-S August 28th and 1598-S Septarber 4th and I strongly recommend that Pakistan Government may be asked urgently on ground of impending transfer of post offices in Persian Gulf to H.M.G. to maintain until transfer existing arrangements viz. use at Bahrain and Kuwait of stamps over printed Bahrain and Kuwait respectively and at Sharjah Muscat and Gwadur of absolute stamps. 4 Continued use of existing stationery is also desirable if this could be arranged. EE£gIAB pyi?J£SIDEN£l! - GALLOWAY - bahraih, the 24th September, 1947 Copy forwarded with compliments toi- The Political Agent, KUWAIT . The Political Agent, BAHUAIK , The Political Agent, MUSCAT .100/7 Telegram Q From To Political Resident, Bahrain. Commonwealth Relations Office, London fto.1010. Dated che 29th September 1947 ■ &gt; Your telegram 12005 September 27th to Pakistan. TRANSFER OF POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS SERVICES IN THE PERSIAN GULF. 2. Postmaster Bahrain has received a further telegram cancelling original instructions and adding 'Further date introduction stamps over printed Pakistan will be intimated later”. - GALLOVvAY PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, deted 30th September 1947. No.l702-S Copy, with copy of London telegram under reference, forwarded with compliments to - The Political Agent, KUWAIT , The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , The Political Agent, MUSCAT , with reference to Residency endorsement No.lb89-S dated 24th September 1947. NPG@ From Telegram To Q Commonwealth Relations Office, London. Government of Pakistan, E.A.D. &amp; C.R. Repeated Political Resident, Bahrain. No.12005. Dated 27th, received 28th September 1947. IMPORTANT Correspondence ending with my telegram 11971 dated September 26th. TRANSFER OF POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS SERVICES IN THE.PERSIAN GULF. 2. * H.M.G. understand Postmaster Bahrain has received instructions from Director-General Posts and Telegraphs Government of Pakistan that stamps ( omission ) printed Pakistan will be released from October 1st and that all post offices should obtain these stamps and return stamps previously in use. 3. In view of impending transfer and to avoid misunderstanding H.M.G. would request the continuance of arrangements which have hitherto existed in accordance with which stamps overprinted 'Bahrain' and 'Kuwait' were used at these two places and stamps without over print were used at Sharjah Muscat and Gwadur. 4. H.M.G. 'would also appreciate arrangements for the continued use of existing stationery. KETAXANDUM - NPG./ it ‘fj'f 100/7 Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bahrain, Commonwealth Relations Office, London To No.1018 Dated the 2nd October 1947 Pakistan telegram No,374 September 29th 2, In circumstances explained there appears no alternative but to acquiesce in use of stamps overprinted 'Pakistan” in Muscat Gwadur and Dubai. Necessity for their temporary adoption will be explained to Rulers concerned. GALLOWAY - PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, dated 3rd October 1947 Copy, with copy of telegram under reference forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat, ) for action indicated ) The Political Agent, Bahrain, ) in last sentence. The Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. NPGTelegram 5 From To Repeated No.374. Government of Pakistan, Karachi. Commonwealth Relations Office, London. , Political Resident, Bahrain. Dated 29th, received 30th September 1947. IMPORTANT Your telegram No.12005 September 27th. 2. It is not correct that “Pakistan' will be over-printed on stamps in Bahrain and Kuwait where existing stamps will continue to be used. 3. In Muscat, Dubai and Gwadur stamps over printed 'Pakistan' v/ill be used until His Majesty's Government take over. This is necessary result of agreement with India to withdraw all unsurcharged Indian stamps from areas served by Pakistan Posts and Telegraph Department. Making of exception in case of Muscat, Dubai and Gwadur would as you can appreciate lead to endless complications. FOREIGN -100/7. Telegran Q. From Commonwealth Relations Office, London. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. 12171. Dated and received 6th October 1947. s Your telegram No. 1018 dated October 2nd. Pakistan stamps. 2. Please see ny telegram to Pakistan Government No. 12172. Unless change has actually been intro duced you should defer explanation to Rulers. 3. If British stamps were supplied for use in Muscat etc. could local arrangements be made if necessary for surcharge with values in rupee currency. - RETAXANDUM - RHL. 3.s c ♦ Ne • 17 30-S. r~ ^ 7 ) Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 7th Octaber 1947 • Gapy, with copy af Comnianwealth Relations Office telegram No.12172 dated the 6th Octaber 1947, farwarded ta sT / ) with a request that unless ) the change has already The Palitical Agent, Muscat ~ 'S . — — - v v'a The Palitical Agent, Bahrain, ) been introduced explanat- x) :* r - y) ^ J ions to Rulers cancerned shauld be deferred, 1 ltfy The Palitical Agent, Kuwait, far infannatian, in cantinuatian af Residency endorsement No.l7l6-S, dated the 3rd October 1947. / a r6 //e &amp; II /to (*1 RHLTelegram Fro* To Repeated No•12172* Dated and 100/7. Commonwealth Relations Office. London. Government of Pakistan, Department of External Affairs &amp; Commonwealth Relations. Government of India, Ministry of External Affairs &amp; Commonwealth Relations. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. received 6th October 1947. IMPORTANT. His Majesty's Government appreciate the difficulty which Government of Pakistan find in continuing use of unsurcharged Indian stamps at Muscat Gwadur and Dubai arising from their agree ment with Government of India to withdraw all such stamps from areas served by Pakistan Post and Telegraph Department. The Sultan of Muscat has however always objected to use of over printed stamps in his territories and has recently reaffirm ed this attitude when approached in connection with impending introduction of British stamps. His Majesty's Government therefore fedl that sudden introduction of over printed 'Pakistan 11 stamps (even though these would only be used for short period) would be misunderstood and would offend Sultan's susceptibilities. 2. In these special circumstances His Majesty's Government would be most grateful if Government of Pakistan would agree to seeking concurrence of Government of India to continued use of un-surcharged Indian stamps at Muscat and Gwadur until British stamps are ready. His Majesty's Government will do their best to expedite their preparations. - RETAXANDUM - RHL. 3sc.12/10 Political Resident, Bahrain. Political j* nt, Lius cat. 1036 Dated 10th received 11th October, 194 • « f Residency Endorsement no. 1730-S October 7th. 2. Please furnish urgently details of values to be suPcharged on British.stamps and number of each estimated to be required for 6 mon^.s for Lius cat and Gv;adur. - HAY -NCJ Mo. C/530-12A0 Political Agency &amp; H.M's. Consulate, Unseat. Dated the 12th October, 1947. To The Sub Post Uaster, Muscat. Memorandum t His Ifejesty's Government have decided to replace the existing Indian stamps by new British stamps. The new stamps will be overprinted with Indian currency values but will not be overprinted with the word * MUSCAT. * Please ftirnish urgently details of values which should be surcharged on the new British stamps and state the number of each denomination which would be required for six months./^S NCJ Telegram From To No. 12/10 G.T.C. Political Agent, Muscat. British Agent, Gwadur. C/437 Dated the 12th October, 194V. Please obtain from Post Master Gvra.dur recommendations for details of values to be surcharged on new Fritish stamps whjch are to replace existing Indian stamps. New stamps will be overprinted with Indian currency values but will not repeat not have M MUSCAT” overprinted. Please telegraph urgently number of each denomination to be required for 6 months. - POLITICAL -Telegram Q From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. C 438 Dated the 13i?h October, 194'?. ,S Your telegram No. 1036 October 10th. Please confirm that there will be no radical change in existing postal charges for letters Muscat *■ India - United Kingdom etc. POLITICAL12/10 Telegram From To No. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 1044 Dated 14th received 15th October, 1947. a Your telegram No. C 438 October 13th. Information requested in ny telegram ^o. 1036 October 10th may be prepared on the assumption that no radical change in rates is contemplated. - REPGU - NCJ12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From British Agent, Gwadur. To Political Agent, Muscat# No. C 366 Dated 13th received 17th October, 1947. Your telegram No. C 437 October 12th# (1) All existing denominations up to Rs#10/- (2) Post Master Gwadur has already received orders to use postage stamps overprinted ^PAKISTAN** from October 1st 1947# He uses axyacsxxxtsttx approximately Rs. 1,500 postage stamps of various denominations monthly but regrets his inability to indent for British stamps without permission of Superintendent of Post Office Quetta# - BRITAGENT »'X*tt***l(*MM**»» Telegram From To No. G.T.C. Political Agent, Muscat# British Agent, Muscat# c/ua Dated the 17th October, 1947# IMMEDIATE Please report immediately if stamps overprinted 'PAKISTAN* are now actually in use. 2. Please instruct Post Master to give approximate numbers of each denomination required for six months. POLITICALD»Q» No , C« 545-X2A0 Political Agency* Muscat* 19th October 1947. Will you please refer to the correspondence ending with Colonel Galloway*s telegram No. 991 dated the 16th September 1947 on the subject of postal arrangements at Gwadur. In arriving at the conclusion that the Pakistan Government should be asked to continue the existing postal arrangements at Gwadur* primary consideration appears to have been given to the financial aspect of the question. The P°lltical aspect is* however* of perhaps greater Importance and while I Imagine it must have been given more consideration than appears from the correspondence which has been forwarded to me* in order to be sure that this side of the question has not been overlooked* I should be grateful if you would confirm that you do not desire me to take it up as a separate issue. 3* Even from the financial aspect I am not altogether satisfied that we are correct in suggesting that to take over the Post and Telegraph Office at Gwadur would be a financial liability. It seems to me that Gwadur should definitely be regarded as a Sub Post Office of Muscat and as such* its figures of profit and loss should be read together with the profit and loss account of the Muscat Post Office. If this is done I think it can be readily assumed that the over-all profit would be sufficient to give a very reasonable return on any capital expenditure to which the General Post Office nay be put in establishing a small wireless installation at Gwadur which could communicate through Muscat with the outside world. / Viewed The Hon , ble Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident Persian Gulf* Bahrain.- 2 Viewed purely from the point of view of communications and the convenience of the inhabitants, a small wireless station would certainly be preferable to the present unreliable land telegraph line which could then be dispensed with without any obligation on the part of the General Post Office to accept financial responsibility for Indian Posts and Telegraph Department's assets other than perhaps the actual buildings.POLITICAL 12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 1067 Dated 25th received 26th October, 1947. Please telegraph : (a) How long existing stocks of unsurcharged Indian stamps at ?rtuscat will last and (b) Whether Post Master has received any orders to introduce stamps overprinted PAKISTAN. - REPGU - Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Iftiscat. To British Agent, Gwadur. No. C 452 Dated the 26th October, 1947. IMPORTANT Please telegraph how long existing stocks of unsurcharged Indian stamps will last.12/10 ^0 POLITICAL Telegram From To No. Q Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bahrain. C 455 Dated the 27th October, 1947. / Your telegram No. 1067 October 25th. 2. I hold roughly two years supply of stamps in Treasury which can be drawn on as required. 3. Post Master Muscat has not yet received any instructions to introduce overprinted •'PAKISTAN* stamps nor is he in possession of any. Recent communication from Director General of Posts and Telegraphs to Director of Posts and Telegraphs Karachi copied to Post Master Muscat by mail indicates however that it is proposed to introduce stamps surcharged 'PAKISTAN' as soon as they can be delivered. 4. Position regarding Gwadur is somewhat obscure. Sultan has given his consent to introduction of unsurcharged British stamps while we on the other hand propose asking Pakistan to administer Post Office. Presumably they would not repeat not agree to do this and issue British stamps. Post Master Gwadur received orders to introduce new 'PAKISTAN' overprinted stamps from October 1st but as he is not in possession of any of new stamps has not yet been able to comply.12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From British Agent, Gwadur. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 378/C Dated 28th received 29th October 1947. Immediate In continuation of my telegram No. 375 C October 27th. Postmaster Gwadur received stamps overprinted PAKISTAN' October 28th# I have given him written instructions not to use them pending the receipt of final instructions which may be telegraphed immediately. BRITAGENT12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Muscat. To British Agent, Gwadur. No. C 464 Dated the 29th October, 194V. IMMEDIATE Your telegram No. 378/C October 28th. I confirm your action until you hear further from me. - POLITICAL - &gt;■/ w w w w w w Telegram Q From Political Agent, Muscat* To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. C 4^5 Dated the 29th October, 1947. , - ' Rfor telegram No. C/455 October 27th paragraph 4* 2. Post Master Gwadur received Pakistan stamps on October 28th and since he comes under control of Karachi Post Office correctly states he must introduce them in compliance with previous instructions. I have told British Agent Gwadur to give him written instructions not repeat not to use them pending further communication from me. - POLITICAL - NCJTelegram G.T.C. From British Agent, Gwadur. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. C 375 Dated 27th received 30th October, IMPORTANT Your telegram No. C 453 October 26th. Existing stocks are likely to last for a week but Post Master will start using stamps overprinted PAKISTAN immediately on receipt in accordance with existing orders. 2. Post Master suggests further information may be obtained from D.P.T. Karachi in this connection. BRITAGENT - NCJwmmu&amp;k K X P B £ s g fr 3 T Prom To Political Resident, Bahrain. H.M*s Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London, Repeated Political Agent, Muscat. Ho.1845-8 Dated, BAHRAIN, the 25th October, 1947. My telegram No.1035 dated the 10th October, 1947 (not repeated Muscat). 2. 5 ^ Enclosed is a copy of Muscat telegram No.C/443 dated the 21st October, 1947, giving details of values in rupee currency to be surcharged on British stamps and number of each estimated to be required for six months for Muscat and (if required) Gwadur. Similar details for Dubai will follow. Sd/- W.R. Hay, Political Resident, Persian Gulf. mmm- For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. •LB* J/i 10 s/f k m/ 100/7 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident^ Bahrain* Tp Commonwealth Relations Office, London* No. 1077 Dated the 27th October, 1947. fiiiy Express Letter No. 184b-S October 25th* SURChARGED STAMPS. Please defer action as it v,111 probably be possible to reduce number of denominations. Further communication will follow by air mail. = HAY = CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1849-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAi RAIN, the 27th October, 1947 Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, - LUbCAT . CLE. / /C ifi l ^100/7 Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bahrain, To Commonwealth Relations Office, London. Mo.1089. Dated the 31st October 1947. nl Hi Correspondence ending with my telegram No,1077 October 27th. LURCiiARGED FT Alt PS. 2. Position is Pakistan stamps are already in use at Dubai. Postmaster Muscat has not yet received any instructions to introduce Pakistan stamps and does not possess any. Correspondence received by him however shows that it is proposed to introduce Pakistan stamps as soon as they can be delivered. Political Agent has sufficient unsurcharged Indian stamps in stock to last for two years. At Gwadur Postmaster has received orders to introduce Pakistan stamps and supply arrived October 28th. Political Agent has ordered British Agent to instruct postmaster not to bring them into use pending further communication. 3. I am inclined to think we should accept position and inform Sultan regarding proposed use of stamps over printed 'Pakistan” and circumstances which have led to this. It is unlikely that surcharged British stamps will reach Muscat before Pakistan stamps and in any case use of sur charged British stamps could presumably only be introduced by agreement with Pakistan Government who are running postal administration. So far as I am aware such agreement has not been obtained. 4. With regard to Gwadur I consider Political Agent should be asked to cancel his instructions to British Agent at once without consulting the Sultan, be shall be in an awkward position if Pakistan Government take exception to them- 2 - them and refuse to carry on with the postal administra tion. Sultan has agreed that Pakistan Government should administer this Post Office for the present (vide Residency express letter N0.1684-S September 23rd) and cannot logically object to use of that Government 1 s stamps. 5. Please telegraph urgently whether you concur. - HAY - No.1875-3 PERSIAN GULP RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, dated 31st October 1947. Copy forwarded with compliments to - THE POLITICAL AGENT, MUSCAT. THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.12/10 Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bahrain To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 1112 Dated and received the 5th November, IS-a?. IMPORTANT My Endorsement No# 1875-S October 31st# Surcharged Stamps* Please take action indicated in paragraphs 3 and 4. NCJ HAY12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Muscat To British Agent, Gwadur. No. C 479 Dated the 6th November, 1947. ' A 1 '’’ Ity telegram No. C 464 October 29th. Please cancel your previous instructions and inform Post • . Master he may start issuing Pakistan stamps when he wishes. POLITICALTelegram From To No. Dated 2 . over postal administration to H.M.G. and introduction of British stamps, postal services are continuing as before under control of Karachi Post Office. Karachi Post Office is however now issuing ordinary Indian stamps surcharged ’•PAKISTAN*' to post offices under its control and for a few months until H.M.G. can complete transfer there appears to be no alternative but to use these stamps at Muscat and Gwadur. I trust your Highness will agree. 12/10 G. T.C. Political Agent, Muscat. H. H. the Sultan at Salalah. C. 4S0 6th November 1947. Reference ny telegram No. G. 237 August 10th. Pending completion of arrangements for handing CONSULCONFIDENTIAL No, I7SO j-fi (til 0 The Hon r ble the Political Resident. Persian Gulf, presents his compliments tos- Tbe Agent, Kuwait. Th® Political Agent, Bahrain* TUe Political Agent, Muse*' and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document »). . ,, , . Dated the 15th ^otooer 1947, PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN R EFERENCE TO PR EVIOUS CORRESPONDENC E Residency endorsement L0*1631-3 dated 11th Sept* 1947. Description of Enclosure Number and Date Subject Gevomment of Pakiotan Express Letter No •jj 1 •0*42/47 elated 4ta October 1947* Transfer ef Pesta and lelagcjAph Servioee in reraian Gulf*BY AIK MAIL. SEGRlilT • GOVERNMifiHT OF PAKISTAN MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND COMAONWEALTH RELATIONS, EXPRESS J 4 ETTER. Foreign, Karachi. Re tax&amp;ndum, Lq nd o n • Repgu, Bahrain, From To Repea ted - No.F ,0.42/47. 1 Dated Karachi, the 4th October, 1947. Subject:- Transfer of Posts and Telegraph Services in Persian Gulf. IruS /? &amp; Reference Foreign, New Delhi, Express Letter to you D. 126-AWT/47, September 3rd. 2. The Statement in paragraph 2 of the Express Letter is confirmed. 3. A further communication will follow in regard to Gwadur. 4. Paragraph 4. The local mail contracts at Bahrain and Kuwait will be maintained as usual. As regards the contract with the B.I.S.N. Company, the Government of PaFistan concur in the arrangements proposed by the Government of India. ^ JrQ 5. Paragraph 4 of your telegram 9684, July 28th. ♦Copy sentThe position is stated in this Ministry’s ♦telegram , to Foreign p V'l New Delhi .No.374 , September 29 th. 6 . The presumptions in parugruph Z of your telegram t’ 11048 August 26th are confirmed. A 7. Paragraph 6 of Foreign telegram 5309 July 8 th. It is thought that most of the information required in the p U(&gt; Annexure to India Office letter N o.Ext .1296/47, dated 18 th June 1947 has by now been supplied though some details nay remain. Such further particulars, if any, as can be collected will be sent in due course. Issue of the above has been authorised. Sd. M.G.DIX0N. Deputy Secretary to the Govt, of Pakistan.i 12/10 Tclograni From To No. Q Political Resident, Bahrain* Political Agent, Muscat* 1154 Dated 11th received 12th November, 19&lt;±7* Demi-official* Your demi-official letter No* G 5^5 October 19th. Gwadur Post Office. 2. Appelby has informed me that from point of view of H.M.G. he does not wish to take post office over owing to small receipts and he also states Pakistan authorities are not anxious to retain it. I doubt if Pakistan will administer post office efficiently and 1 consider it likely that land line to Panjgur will very soon cease to function. From general political point of view 1 dislike idea of postal and telegraphic matters at Gwadur being left in hands of Pakistan. 3* My provisional view is that we should dispense with post office at Gwadur and press for a small wireless station only which would presumably have to be run by Cable and Wireless* Do you agree or have you any other suggestion to make ? NCJ - HAY -12/10 r Telegram From To Q Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bahrain* No. C &lt;±98 Dated 12th November, 19&lt;±7. Your telegram No. 1112 November 5th. Sultan agrees to use of Pakistan stamps at Muscat and Gwadur pending introduction of British. - POLITIC/Uj - Telegram Q From To No. Political Agent, Muscat, political Resident, Bahrain. C &lt;*99 Dated the 12th November, 1947. ' . Your telegram No. 1154 November 11th. 1 agree that it would be preferable for H.F.G. to take over post and telegraph matters in Gwadur* I think it would be difficult however to dispense with the pos^ of! ice ano it may be possible if Cable and Wireless open a wireless station to get them to run the post office as a sub-post office of Muscat. If you agree 1 will discuss with Appelby when he passes through. - POLITICAL - NCJ1 12/10 (&amp;&gt; Telegram From To No. Political Resident, Bahrain Cat Kuwait; Political Agent, Muscat* T/15&lt;± Dated loth received loth November, ld&lt;±7. Your telegram No. C 499 November 12th. Gwadur Post Office* . 2. I have already discussed question with Appelby and shown him recent correspondence. No objection to your discussing it with him further. 3. Please explain why you think it would be difficult to dispense with post office. u. Can you maxe out a case for opening wireless station at Gwadur on other than purely local grounds* No oo^ection to your discussing matter with Muscat Cable and wireless Manager* /''N - HAY - NCJV Telegram From Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, at Kuwait Q 12/10 To No C 512 Dated the 16th November, 19^i7 Paragraph 3 of your telegram No. 't/154 November 15 th. There has been a post office at Gwadur for many years and from point of view of Muscat State it seems a clear duty to continue this public utility. Since however we have accepted responsibility for administering postal services in Muscat territories i. think Sultan would be uuoll within his rights if he insisted on our taking the bad with the good and continuing maintenance of a post office at Gwadur. POLITICAL NCJEXPRESS LETTER. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCE, BAHRAIN. From - REPGUj Bahrain. To • POLITICAL Bahrain. POLITICAL Kuwait ^POLITICAL Muscat•u^'' No. 3406. Bahrain 10th Novenbar, 1947. As you art awart tha British Qansral Post Offics will bs taking ovsr responsibility for postal arrangements in the Gulf with effect from the 1st April 1948* 2. A British Superintendent of Post Offices will be attached to this Residency and will be responsible for postal matters generally. It will however be necessary for this Residnncy and its subordinate offices to arrange the recruitment of staff and to regulate their conditions of service. 3. The Pakistan Government have agreed to allow permanent employees of its P. &amp; T. Department to continue to serve on deputation on the usual foreign service terms. Will you kindly furnish as soon as possible a list of all such employees serving in post offices in your Agency with details of their pay and allowances and indicating whether they are willing to continue to serve on deputation on the usual foreign service terms or alternatively to accept a three-year contract for service under His Majesty's Government subject to the terms being acceptable to then. It is my intention in the very near future to work out contract terms for the Indian ministerial staff of this Residency and the Agencies and I propose to recommend similar or identical terms for the Indian postal staff. 4. Please also let me have a statement of any Indian temporary staff employed in the post offices giving their pay and allowances and indicating whether they are willing to accept a contract on the lines described above. There will be no question of their serving on deputation and receiving a foreign service allovance. 5 . Please also furnish a similar list of the locals employed in the post offices with their rates of pay and allowances, (it is not necessary at present to consult them about their willingness to continue to serve under His Majesty's Government but I should be glad to know whether you recommend any revision in their rates of pay and allowances. I consider it should be our policy gradually to replace our Indian postal employees by locals. If any of the present Indian employees are unwilling to serve after the 1st April on the terms proposed would kindly let me know whether it will be possible to replace them by locals or whether we shall have to recruit other Indians in their stead.1 6/Pl«as« traat this matter as urgent* « REPGU The issue of the above has been authorised for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf*( COP Y ) EXPRESS LSTTSH PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHR/ylN From REPGU, Bahrain. T# POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. POLITICAL, KUWAIT. POLITICAL, MUSCAT. N®. 3406 Bahrain, 10th November, U^7. As y«a are aware the British General Pest Office will be taKin^, ever responsibility for postal arrangements in the Gull with effect from the 1st April, 19^8. 2. a British Superintendent ef Pest offices will be attached to this Residency and will be responsible for postal matters generally. It will however be necessary for this Residency and its subordinate offices to arrange the recruitment of staff and to regulate their conditions of service* 3. The Pakistan Government have agreed to allow permanent employees of its P* &amp; T. Department to continue to serve on deputation on tne us xal foreign service terms* Will you kindly furnish as soon as possible a list of till such employees serving in post offices in your Agency with details of their pay and allowances and indicating whether they are willing to continue to serve on deputation ©n the usual foreign service terms ©r alternatively to accept a three-year contract for service under His Majesty’s Government subject to the terms being acceptable to tnem. It is my intention in the very near future to work ;ut contract terms for the Indian ministerial staff of this Residency and the Agencies and ± propose to recommend similar or identical terms for the Indian postal staff* Please als© let me have a statement of any Indian temporary st«aff employed in the post offices giving their pay. and allowances and indicating whether they are willing to accept a contract on the lines described above. There will be no question of their serving on deputation ana receiving a foreign service allowance. 5. please also furnish a similar list of the locals employed in the post offices with their rates of pay and allowances. 6. Please treat this matter* as urgent. - REPGU - The. issue of the above has boon authorised. Sd. J. Craning. for Secretary to the Political Residency in the Persian Guxx. Mo. C/581-12AO To Political Agency &amp; H*M*s. Consulate, Muscat • Dated the 19th November, 1947. The Post Master, Muscat, with the request that he will Political Resident, urgently. NCJ furnish ne with naterial for a reply to the© 'S J LUO. 17/3 &amp; C.u. 12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From political iigent, Ivluscat. To • British Agent, Gwadur. No. G 343 Dated the 26th November, 1947. pAJ)- % telegram No. G 331 November l6tb. host ^fester should also be asked to give Mr. Appelby all facilities to examine post office. - POLITICAL - NCJTelegram G.T.C. From Political Resident f Bahrain. To Political Agent f Muscat. No. 1223 Dated 25th received 26th November 1947. Hr telegram 1152 November 11th. Walters and Appelby due Muscat about December 1st and Gvadur about December 3rd. HATPrinted in England Nov 19-»5.(15.000pads) 5/-168 CABLE &amp; WIRELESS LTD ' (INCORPORATED IN ENGl-AND) VIA The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order nar^ Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number ot Wo k ^o, Date. Time handed in and Official Instructio ns—if any. CIRCUIT CLERK'S NAME TIME RECEIVED * AN D VL 2319 T//* 1 *T ( ISSUING OFFICE i n KSNM\6 KARACHI POST MUSCAT 4? = YOUR XF/MG/1420/15 AAA ATTAULLAH 12 5/- SPD PAY ■ 3'//- G C P 10/^ CUSTOM PAY 20/- CA 40/- HR 15/- PE'C'R' 112/- TOTAL 359/- AAA JAFFAR SULE.MAN PAY -e -m v 4* -yt, 26/- P PAY 5/3 G C P 12/- MOHN ALLMU 7/8 TACA) 57/8/- TOTAL 103/3. V \1 Enquiry respecting this telegram should be accompanied by this form and may be made at any of the Company's officesNo* C/596-12/10 Political Agency &amp; H.M's. Consulate, Muscat. JDated tho 1st December, 1947* To The Sub-Post Master Muscat* Memorandum ^-5 7 s Reference your letter No* 283 dated the 26th November 19*7 2* Foreign Service terms are as follows Permanent Staff. Pay and allowances - at the same rates as at present plus 2o % Foreign Service Allowance* This allowance will be calculated on pay, special pay and good conduct pay, but not on allowances, of post filled. Dollar Exchange Compensation Allowance at 27 % of emoluments, Travelling Allowance, leave, medical attention, quarters and leave and pension contribution - in accordance with Government of India rules. Local Staff. Same rates and terras as at present polit [.M’s. Consul, Muscat. NCJ/ 6. EXPRESS LETTER From POLITICAL MUSCAT To REPGU BAHRAIN No. C/597-12/10 Dated the 1st DeceTibor, 1947. Your express Letter No. 3406 November 10th. 2. Muscat Post Office staff are as follows (a) Permanent - Sub Post Master Mr. Attaullah. Cb; Temporary - Nil tc; Local - Postman jaffer Suleman. 3. Ratos of pay of Ca) are Basic pay 125-0-0 (scale; 40-5-140) Special pay 37-0-0 Good conduct pay 10-0-0 Customs duty refund allce. 20-0-0 Compensatory allowance 40-0-0 House rent 15-0-0 Dollar exchange compn.all.112-0-0 (fluctuates) Usual total 359-0-0 4. Rates of pay of (b) are i- Basic pay 26-0-0 Special pay 5-3-0 Good conduct pay 12-0-0 Mutrah allowance 7-3-0 Dollar exchange compn.all. 57-8-0 (fluctuates) Usual total 108-3-0 c ... 5. (a) accepts terms given in your telegram No. A/655 August 26th but has following provisos :- (i) that he is given free accommodation instead of House Rent of o.l5/- (ii) that ho receives fe.43/- in addition to his salary, irrespective of calculations relating to Dollar Exchange, making a total of Ks.402/-. (b) is willing to accept contract provided he receives an additional 7-12-0.2 6 # Your paragraph 6 . 1 do not rccooimend any change in rates of pay of local employee and 1 fear it would not bo possible to find anyone locally capable of replacing the Indian staff. NCJa ■ M* v I % &amp; CONFIDENTIAL EXPRESS LETTER Political Resident, Bahraip. Political Agent, Muscat*/ From To No.1973-S Dated, BAHRAIN, the 18th November, 1947 Will you please obtain from the Gwadur Post Office figures of telegraph traffic \ to and from Gwadur for the past 6 months ? Sd/- W.R. Hay. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. \SV ATTESTED. For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf f LB' [J UU1 3 A M Copy to:- Mr. ApplebyCONFIDENTIAL No o 2015 -S The Hon'fcle the Political Resident, presents his compliments to;- Persian Gulf,' The P©litical / Agent, MUSCA T and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document(s)o PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN Dated the 25th November,1947 » REFErlENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPOFDE NCE Pes'criptien of Enclosure. Number and Date W. Appleby, Esquire, British Post Office Representative's n©te dated the 24th November 1947 t© the Political Resident, Bahrain. Subject 9 Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, demi-official letter N©.2014-S dated the 25 th November, 1947 to A.Apple by, Esquire, Bahrain. ' LB' LB o TRANSFER OF PERSIAN GULF POSTAL ADMINIS T RATION TO HIS /MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT ; t? 2 f 11 A -&gt; / /Thft H«»id#nt f fmllmwtng upmm my rmcmnt prmliminmry diteutslo&amp;s vlth th« Pakistan pasta! autharitiss, my inspsctlan af tha Bahrain and Kuwait Past Offlcas 9 and my dlseusslans with pan ragardlng tha taking ovar bp tha British Past Offles an tha 1st af April 1948 af tha eantral af tha pastal 9 ate. services la tha Persian Gulf 9 I think It wall (l.a. be fare np departure fran Bahrain) ta sat aut belew tha pesltlea as 1 sea It up-te- date, and tha rec emend a tie ns whleh 9 an the data available, I prapase ta wake ta np Headquarters as te the servlees ta be prevlded. It will be seen that it Is prepesed ta maintain existing services sa far as practicable, but as pea will readllp appraclate t It will be necessarp ta altar the existing postage rates ar charges In neap Instances, as wall as the cendltleas applicable ta particular services, sa as ta fit in vlth tha machinery af tha British Past Office. One af the mast Inpertant alteratlens will be tha change-ever fren 'Inland' ta 'foreign' rates and conditions as regards postal matter pasted In tha Persian Gulf Agencies addressed ta Pakistan and/er India, Inasmuch as anpthing going overseas from the Gulf, even te Pakistan and/er India, will have ta be treated as Imperial and Foreign matter under the British Past Office Act and tha Postal Union Convention. (l.e. Services within the Agencies ar between Agencies) T 3«rvlc« Prap««.d of Obwv*U»ai Letters. Far first 4 talas Xi as) A reduction as compared Each additional 2 Tls. 1 as ) with existing rates. Postcards Single Beplp i annas 1 annas Be change L. rasa Delivery! Ha Service Ha demand far this Serv. Business Baplp ' Envelopes dt ' ■i.jrfBI&amp;JL.t.... 1 , Ha Service Ha demand far this Serv. Beak Packets Far first 8 Talas 1 as Each additional 8 Tls. i as Slight Increase as camp* arad with existing rates Varp little demand far inn.. Patarn and ) Sample Packets ) Same rates as far Book pkts* subject te a minimum af li as far the first 10 talas increase as comp ared with existing rates. ) Varp little demand far l tbli.. fftnlst Blind Literature) Registered Hews*) PlPtfi Clfl. He Service ) Ha demand far Service Service ta be discontinued ) JMlMl .s exchanged Parcels ) Present ratesof 6annasper) each 40 tolas should caver ) total casts and prapasa ta ) retain these rates. ) la. af parcel! between Agenaias varp snail, prebablp net nara than ana a month. Ha parcel service within .AltfiSltij / Registration.••Z- ka eoocuifflic rate covering the whele cf Indie end/er Pafciaten, and the uee of Indian air service a. would be about 6 annas per half ounce (this Is Inclusive ef 9 and net additional te ordinary postage). It night however else be practicable te effer a separate air pestage rate far letters addressed te Pakistan net requiring Internal air transmission within Pakistan, visi 3g annas per half ounce. the latter rate would be extremely beneficial for air nail letters addressed only te Karachi. the air pestage rates te ether countries will be affected by reason ef the fact that the Gulf ports are in a different financial sene free India for the purpose ef air conveyance charges, and It seems likely that the rates te countries west wards can be reduced while the rates for countries east* r ■ j may have te be increased.£eg« 4 )eMpllcat«d •achia^ry f*r )m ••rvlc« for which there Parcels ' i )&amp;xlstlng postage rates fer ) )all countries everseas, ex* ) )eept India and/er Pakistan ) )te be maintained. ) )Postage rates te India and/ ) )or Pakistan te be fixed ) )later, l.e. after final dls*) )cusslens with Pakistan postal F.D.D. Service (Payment ef Customs charges by sender) &gt; Re service ) jThis service is available )la India and/er Pakistan, )but there appeers te have )been no demand fer such a )service in the Persian )Gulf . — &gt; i am MAIL SERVICES - The wain effeet ef the change ef centre! will he that cemualeatien with India and/er Pakistan will be Internatioaal instead ef internal . This aaaas that the existing cheap air wail fates free tne Persian Calf te India and/er Pakistan will hare te be increased*/. Fer exaaple t an air postage rata ef 6 annas per half ounce could perhaps be justified fer letters addressed te the United tiagden (ascoppered with the existing week rate ef IS annaa per half ounce)• Air nail rates fer the Western Hemisphere generally wight be at slightly less then these existing at presentt possibly the sun ef the rates free the agencies te the United £lngdew y and free U.k. te destinetlen 9 e*g* about IBs. per half ounce fer legtors fer the U.8.A. An air letter fern at 6 annas night be allowed te any country f including the Western Henisphere. The whole question ef the air postage rates is 9 however, already aider consideration by ny Headquarters 9 and full details will be forwarded te you as seen as a decision has been reached. PmtHtt »lr nULmric. Bwt The position is as explained in ay report ef the 14th ef Novamber. Stilagg The British Pest Of flee ie net anxious 9 at any rate et the outset, te provide feeilities ef this klnd 9 but is pro* pered f if desired 9 te liquidate responsibility ef the Indian Feat £ Telsgraph uepartnant fer Indian Sawings Bank Accounts and Katienal Sawings Csrtifleates. During wy prellwinary discussions st Karachi, It was suggested infernally, that the best solution would perhaps be fer the Inhabitants ef the Gulf Agencies te be advised as early as possible that (I) the Indian Pest A Telegraph Department was giving up the centre! of the pastel, etc. services in the Perslen Gulf en the 31st ef Kerch, 1948, and that after that data the British Pest Office would take ever, and (II) as a rasult these persons holding Indian• p&amp;f• 6 • Indian savings Bank Account# f Katioaol i&gt;avi Certificates onA other Cooorneeiit oocuritioo should take Immodlato action to close their accounts* Any applications for withdraws! received after th* Slat of March, 1948 to ho passed to tbs p,l ^» t * n authorities ot Itsrschi for settleeent* Thus tne British Post Office would be relieved of any responsibility* X do net think that the withdrawal of these facilities will involve rauch hardship* saviags could be paid Instead Into the local banks. The question is however new receiving efficial consideration by the Pakistan authorities* and tha final decision will be communicated as soon as possible. 3i ire less Licences It appears that licences are net at present necessary for receiving sets* and that applications for trans mitting licences, which are rare, are subject te the Joint approval of the Shaikh concerned and yourself. 1 understand that It is your view that this practice should be jaaintained, i.e* applications for transmitting licences and for allocation of freSSendes to be dealt with locally as they arise. Itililiifti janiatt Honey Orders (QrdiflftPi There appears te be little demand for this service, and it is proposed te discontinue it. The less complicated Postal Order system should suffice• do To be maintained. kuch use is made of this service Little demand. Te be discontinued. Little use is made of this facility (at present confined te Kuwait), and it will remain for further consider ation whether or not service should be maintained. 1. Between U.K. end Agencies 2. Local service between Agencies 3. Between Agencies &amp; India 4. Between countries ether than U.K.and India and the Agencies Waomt Ord.r* (Tel.graab.) 1. fc«tc.«n O.K. *ad J&lt;gencl«s 2. Between Agencies &amp; India 3. Between Agencies fMtai gftfffiui 1. Imperial Postal Order Scheme 2. India Rupae Postal Orders Te be maintained. Much use is made of the service* So demand. Te be discontinued To be continued. Te be discontinued. /Postage Stamps.••£*§• 6 - talllt ■ ifaMBM Britluh ov«rprint«4 ••BAHRAIN 1 * fc«4 ^ Mi All* 1 ra8p«ctiv«ly| and to baar th# amounts In local curroncy* aro feslr*g provided at tr*« outsat in tho following donoatinatleiiss A d stamp overprint • 1 d stamp overprint i efiria Ig d stamp overprint 1* annas 2 d stamp overprint 2 annas 2i d stamp overprint 2$ annat 3 d stamp overprint 3 annas 6 d stamp overprint 6 annas A siailar range of British stamps ovorprinted with anrva values, hut not hearing tho naao of tho territory, is being provided for use in Muscat, Dubai and, if necessary, Mt Gwadur# I ii«ve also recosRKendod to »y Headquarters of tho desirability of providing as early as possible evorprinted stamps of the 1 rupee and 2 Rupee deaesainatieos for use at all Agencies, and intend, furthermore, t© reco»aond tne prevision of at least on* higher value overprinted ataiap, eay for 5 or 1C rupees, t© mat tho postage on heavy air mail packets• Tbltgraftfrga-.tta* At yai^aln ^ Cable ar*d biroloss performs the collection and delivery of telegrams, and tho local administration handles nt&gt; telegraph traffic* At jftigftUtt Cable and tireless performs the collection and delivery and there is no inland telegraph system* The position in regard to the taking over of the huaait - Basra land*line was explained in my report of the 14th of Ncrvemfear* I have net yet visited Muscat. Dubai er Cwadur, but I understand that at Muscat Cable end tireless perf&amp;rras the collection and delivery of telegrams, and that there is no local telegraph adminiatratien# At M hsrlah the B*C*A*C* at present operate a wirelbss circuit with Cable and tireless at Bahrain* Dubai, the commercial centre of this area, is ae*e 10 miles from Sharjah, and our only inferwfttlen so fer is that telegraph traffic between the tee places is conveyed by B*0 .a*C* meter transport* there is little information of fi yfdqr * Traffic from this area aaA reaches D*K.* fre® the Indian Department at Aarachl or Bombay* th* British Pest Office is net anxious to assume control of th# telegraph arrangements, *Rd to take ever only the Pest Office at Gwadur would be most uneconomical* The postal receipts average about Ha*80/-&gt; a month* The ! ritish Post Office would much prefer therefore, subject to the consent ©f the Sultan of Auscet (which consent, with reservations, has, I understand now been obtained) that the Pakistan Government should be asked to continue the existing pest©l and telegraph arrangements* As thB volume oi postal traffic between Muscat and Cwadur is probably very small the British Pest Office would have m reluctense, *$ If the point is raised, te handling the traffic for the reduced inter-port postage rates under arrange ment with Pakistan*X uxkd«r«t&amp;nd y h*w*v«r 9 that (1) from a ganaral political point of view you dislike the idea of postel »nd telegraphic natters st Cwadur being loft in the hands of Pakistan* (ii) you are of the opinion that tha land lino between Gwadur • Panifur la in bad condition 9 needs considerable repair 9 and Is in any case likely toon to cease to function (ill) your provisional vies is that pressure should be put on Cable and tireless to run a s$all wireless station for communication with (a) India and Unseat or (b) Muscat only* In that event It sight be possible to arrange for Cable and tireless to run the Post Office so a sub-post office «f Muscat* It soess therefore that the future of Cwadur is dependUmt upon (1) the willingness of Cable and Hrelesa to open up a wireless station there and (2) If so* the length of tine required to open it up* &amp;ven if willing to do so 9 provisional arrangements would have to be aado for the running of the Post Office unless the wireless station was ready by the 1st of &gt;ipril 194&amp;* Although you dislike the idea of Pakistan carrying on with the postal and telegraphic business at Cwadur as a perman ent Measure* you sight perhaps be prepared to ask then to continue the present arrangements until such tiae as a definite decision on the natter has been reached* It is understood that you propose to engage now staff* and* if possible locals* on contract terras 9 say for a ported of 3 years* those of the present employe as who wish to carry on undor His Majesty's Govern*ant| and who are now oraployed by the Indlan/Pekistaa Government on ponsienablo tens* will bo advised to consider tne question of terminating thoir service &gt; with the Indian/kaklstan adninistratlon* taking such pension as they way be entitled t© 9 and to outer Into a contract* as raontloned above* for service under His Majesty's Governaent* In the meantime, present IndiaV^eklstaa staff to bo retained* if they are willing* on deputation terms* cASiMiU. aalii , „ iii w&lt;$xini&lt;&amp;r&amp;m&amp;• 2t b »* fe ?» n r*e®m«*nd*« t« »y oadquartors that the British Postal Superintendent slieuld bo posted to Bahrain as soon «* possible in the Mew year t© give him an opportunity for inspecting the Post Office which will bo under his control* the class of staff employed and their seethed* of working* l understand that rent free acccstfaedation will be X found for hln* It seems desirable that aecon^odatlon should* if possible* be near tha Peat Office* and 1 gather that you are endeavouring to obtain such accommodation* Xt also seans desirable that the Festal Superintendent should have a personal clerk* If possible a elm t hand typist and preferably an Indian, and it Is understood that you will endeavour to engage such an officar* Parat+Ets ef ealurlea. etc. It le prwp*ee4 that the salary el the testaJ iuyer 1 r.ter.cSer.t shevld he p*l&lt;S by jeu, as Political Resident* The actual amount to be paid each mnth $ l*e* after deduction ef British Income tar* to he advised to you by the accountant General's Department* G*f*G** bondon* etc »a.ges of subordinate staff* rents for Post Office property t® be paid by the Postal Superintendent*fgg* 8 mum Tit© fip€irtttl«n #f the peetel services to be * setter entirely fer the new Pastel Superintendent* The letter will kenvever be required te refer te yeu ell questions ef pelicy 9 end te consult yeu en eny leper tent setter* He nay however seek your advice whenever he needs assistance* 1 understand that is is year desire that the goners! supervision ef acceunts fer all festal agencies should &amp;e under* taken by the festal Superintendent! and that yeu vill need te be furnished only with a statenant say, each quarter 9 shewing briefly the lucerne and expenditure particulars ef each ef the agencies* 1 understant that, subject te authority frets His Hajestyi Government yeu will undertake te provide the Postal Superintendent with funds for use In connexion with the operation ef the postal etc* services should this become necessary (which is unlikely)* km..miZL t $2miu. m m* n m » All Pest Office st&amp;res t except steeps or ether valuable Items* te be sent direct te the festal Agency concerned* Steeps and ether valuable items, te be sent te the Politic*! Agent fer tr^e appropriate Agency fer distribution te the festal Agency as and when required* The question as te whether this should be taken ever by His Majesty's Government and the price, te be considered In connexion with tne general question ef the handing ever ef political buildings in the Gulf from the Indian Government te His Majesty's Government* 1 shall be very glad to be advised whether yeu concur generally In the recommendation* and remarks quoted above* • IB' British Pest Office Representative £// lA, Meveeber, 1847v — -D .O. No.2014-S CONFIDENTIAL PKRSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, the 25th Nsvember, 194 Dear Appleby, I acknowledge with many thanks y®ur note giving details of the recommendations which y©u propose t© make to your headquarter regarding the postal services to be provided in the Gulf States. I concur generally in y@ur recommendations and have only the following comments to make. 2. With regard to your remarks regarding wireless licences at page 5 the position is that the granting of licences for amateur wireless transmitting sets is contingent on the joint approval of the Political Agent and the Shaikh after the local Service authorit ies e.g. the R.A.F. have been consulted. The Middle East Communic ations Beard are then asked if they have any objection. If they have none the Government cf India are asked to allot a call sign. I presume that when the G.P.O. have taken over they will deal with the allotment of call signs. The procedure described m this paragraph may be held t® apply to all the Gulf States except Muscat though it has up t© date only been followed in Bahrain and Sharjah as n® application for a licence has been made in any other State. 3 . With reference t© the remarks regarding telegraphs at Kuwait ©n page 6 the collection and delivery ©f telegraps despatched and received over the Kuwait-Basra land line is I believe performed by the post office and not by Cable and Wireless. 4 . With reference t© your remarks about Gwadur at pages 6 and 7 I should be grateful if you could let me have a further note after you have visited the place. I would suggest that the present ©verland postal service should be abolisned and that mails should be despatched by B.I. steamers which k call regularly in each direction once in-six weeks. This should result in a consider able saving and the service should I think be sufficient fer the needs of the place in view ©f the fact that telegraphic facilities are available. With reference to your remarks about staffing ©n page 7 the Pakistan Government will have to be consulted abcut the further employment of the present staff and may. have their l iv\r views ©n the subject. I will endeavour to obtain a personal clerk for the Festal Superintendent but am very doubtful if I shall be abl to find a satisfactory shorthand typist. I should be grateful for early information regarding the date fr©m which tne clerk will be required. 6. I should like te take this opportunity ©f expressing my appreciation of the thoroughness with which y©u have examined ®ur postal system here and @f all the trouble you have taken in working out the arrangements for its transfer t@ His Majesty's Government. Sd/~ W.R. Hay. Appleby, Esquire, BAHRAIN •LB'Telegram From To No. 12/10 G.T.C, Folilic^l Agent, Muscat. British Agent, Gwadur. G Datea the ^th December, 1947. Flease telegraph figures ol telegraph trailic to and from Gwadur for the past six month. , 7 - POLITICAL - NGJCONFIDENTIAL NOo «e~6€r -s The Hon f ble the Political Resident presents his compliments to?- Persian Gulf, !• Th« Political Agant, KUWAIT 2. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN S. The Political Agent, MUSCAT and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document(s). PERSIhN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN I Dated the—gag December, 1947. REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CQRRE SPODPENCE Pescriptien ef Enclosure. Number and Date Subject *X.L. Co&amp;iaonwealth Relations Officj; London,No* t* L531/47 6+ted the 20th| November, 1D47 e &gt; TRANSFER OF PERSIAN GULF POSTAL ADMINISTRATION TO HIS MAJESTIES GOVERNMENT —Hbit 1 LB c / R //cfUCOMMONWEALTH RELATIONS..OFFICE? • LONDON External Department . EXPRESS LETT E_B (Air Mail) Frem Secretary ef State for Cemmonweallih Relations. T# Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated 20th November, 1947 No.Ext.2531/47 Correspondence resting with your Express Letter No.l913-S of the 7th November* . Postal arrangements in the Persian Gulf. 2. Surcharged British stamps are expected to be available for issue in the Gulf and at Muscat by the end of March 1948. , The issue of the above has been authorised Sd/- R.I. Hallows. •LB 1 ♦copy not sent to Agencies.NCJ No. C 634-12/10 Political Agency &amp; H.HPa. Conaulate, Muscat* Dated the 19th December, 1947. To The British Agent, Gwadur. Memorandum Postal Arrangements Reference oorrespondenoe resting with this Agency telegram No. C 479 dated the 6th November, 1947. 2. Surcharged British stamps are expected to be available for issue by the end of March, 1948* Political Agent &amp; H.M' 3 . Consul, Muscat.NCJ 12/10 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 1304 Dated 18th received 19th December, 1947. Your telegram No. C 556 December 16th. 2. Please telegraph receipts in cash. - REPGUNCJ 12/10 Telegram En clair From Political Agent, Muscat To British Agent, Gwadur. No. C 559 Dated the 20th December, 1947&lt;. Your telegram No. C 415 December 8th. Gwadur telegraph traffic. 2. Please telegraph receipts in cash. - POLITICAL -V A Telegram From To No. 12/10 G.T.C. Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bahrain. C 567 0 KfZ Dated the 23rd December, 1947. A Your telegram No. 1304 December 18th. Gwadur telegraph traffic for past 6 months:- Inland Foreign Total Rs. 3,584 Rs. 1,833 Rs. 5,417 POLITICALThe political &gt;'d*n^ ' Persian Gulf', aW8»R. CWA2V* I was not able to visit Gwadur on my return visit to Karachi as the boat did not stay long enough at the port, but I discussed the poisitton fully with M.Jor Stewart at Muscat and also with his agent at Gwadur(tbelatter boarded the kaartx boat for about half an hour during her stay at the port). As a result,! forced the opinion that it would be most un-. desirable to worsen the existing postal or telegraphic faci lities. Tie port has very poor communication, ships rarely call and mails are conveyed by camel once a fortnight to Delhi via Qu tta, taking a minimum of 13 days in transmission. No air service as available. The existing telegraph line, Gwadur Panjyur appears to be in bad condition, but it is very ess ential to the native popul tion(about 10-12,000) for trading purposes* They deal mainly in the export of fish, and I am advised that the cutting off of Telegraph facilities would strangle trade and possibly result in the evacuatioii of the inhabitrints to Karachi. The inhabitants have been pressing for a' long time past for better communication facilities and there is no doubt that there would be a great uproar #f the present poor facilities were worsened* Your suggestion that Cable and Wireless should be approached with the view of setting up a small wireless station at Gwadur for communication with Muscat and /or India and at the same time run the Post Office as a sub office of Muscat, would give a solution to the problem, and I am representing the matter to my Headquarters accordingly to see whether, it will be possible to taka any action to this end. You will be advised of any developments as early as possible. I have also since discussed the matter with Col.Spear,Director-General,Posts and Telegraphs,Pakistan, and he advises me that the Pakistan Administration will be prepared to continue the present postal and telegraph arrangements at Gwadur until such time as a decision has been reached. He expressed the view, however, that so long as the Pakistan Administration runs the postal and telegraph services at Gwadur, no change should be made in tie existing services, conditions and postage rates, etc., i.e.Gwadiu 1 should bo rega rded during this period as part of Pakistan for postal and telegraph purposes. S JT JLF.J1I_N_G • I have advised the Director-General^posts and Telegraphs,Karachi of your proposals in thisrespect, and in anticipation of your concurrence, have intimated to him that you will no doubt to communicating with him on tie subject before long. As regards a personal clerk for the British Postal Superintendent, this officer would not be required until the' 1st of April 1948, the date on which the British Post Office takes over control. I am sending a copy of this report to Major Stewart for information respecting Gwadur. British Post Office Representative, December 1948* A /AM-CONFIDENTIAL N o.2260-S The Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:- The Political Agent, MUSCAT and has the honour to transrr the under mentioned document(s) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN Dated the 30th December, 1947 REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE Description of Enclosure Name and Date Subject D.O. letter No .2257-S dated l 30th December, 1947 from 5 Commonwealth Relations Office London. 11cmmMUd* B 1 P 1 the 30th December 1947 Please refer te my Express Letter Ne»1506-S dated the 14th August. 1947 ea the subject ef the Pest and Telegraph Office at Gwadur. 2. I discussed the whale questlea with Appelby while he was here and ferward herewith a cepy ef a aete he has recarded after talks with Stewart aad the British Agent at Gwadur. 3. Malls frea Gwadur are carried by caael te Pasal eace a fertnlght and thence by lerry te Quetta. Telegraas are sent te Paajgur by a land-line which Is frequently Interrupted. Sheuld there be any deterieratien in the adalnlstratien ef Mekran, which is, I think, net Isprebable, bath the nail and telegraph services night be suspended indefinitely. 4. Fran the general pelltical aspect, especially in view ef the Khan ef Kalat's claln te Gwadur, it is, in ny eplnien, undesirable that we sheuld centlnue te depend upen the Pakistan Gevernnent and the Kalat State adnlnlstratlen far the maintenance ef pest and telegraph services at Gwadur. I understand fren Appelby that the Pakistan autherltles themselves weuld be glad te be relieved ef their respenslbility. 5. I therefore strongly recenmend that if passible Cable and Wireless sheuld establish a snail wireless statlen at Gwadur far cennunicatlen with Muscat enly and that as suggested by Appelby the nanager ef the statlen sheuld run a Pest Office as a sub-efflce ef the Muscat Pest Office. Mails sheuld be carried by sea. In view ef the fact that nail steaners call at Gwadur in bath dlrectiens ence every twe er three weeks, the service sheuld be alnest as frequent as the present ene. 6. The managern ef Cable and Wireless at Muscat inferned ne that it sheuld be passible te run the prepesed wireless statlen quite cheaply with ene engineer whe ceuld be relieved every six ^ months fren Muscat. There is accenmedatlen available far hln either in the Pest Office Itself er in the Rest House which is presunably what is described as an Inspection bungalow in paragraph IV ef the enclosure te Lew^ letter Ne.F.15-BPG/47 dated the 7th June, 1947. 7. If we do net take ever the land-line the cast ef the buildings etc. we shall have te acquire is net very large, c.f. the note referred te above, and I see ne reason why the cenblned wireless statlen and pest office sheuld net be run at a profit. Stewart has Informed me that the value.of the telegraph traffic far the last six months is Rs.54,017. I 8. I sheuld be grateful If the proposals contained in this letter ceuld be given early consideration. It is desirable te let the Pakistan authorities knew whether we wish them te administer the Gwadur Pest and Telegraph Office indefinitely er if net when we shall be ready te take it ever. / . r ■ E.P. Donaldson, Esquire. C.M.G., Cennenweilth Relations Office, Downing Street, LONDON, S.W.l 1 LB* Sd/- W.R. Hay. 10Telegram Frew I# Repeated Ne.14752 \ Q Ceneeriwe&amp;lth Relatlens Office, Gevernnent ef Paklstaa, Karachi Pelitical Resident, Bahrain. Lenden. ■(S . N*.14751 Dated 26th and received 28th Dece*her 1947. / Reference yeur express letter Ne.F.0.42/47 Octeher 4th. Postal services in the Persian Gulf. 2. H.C. Breach has been appointed Festal Superintendent British Pest Offices in the Persian Gulf and will leave this ceuntry by air fer Bahrain early in January. He is net due ef ceurse te take ever responsibilities until April 1st / but there is a considerable aaeunt ©f detailed preliainary work te be done. 3 , , Arrangewents are being made by Pelitical Resident fer his accenoedatien in Bahrain and I should be / grateful if any necessary facilities fer prelininary work in consultation with Pakistan Postal authorities nay be afforded to Breach. - BBERO - Wo .2272-S (II PERSIAlt GOLF RS3IDEWCX SAffiAIS. the 30th December 1947 C.py forwarded with c.«pll*enta t.i- The Political Age at, KUWAIT The Political Agent, BAHRAIN The P.litlcal Agent, MUSCAT with reference to Residency Printed Lettej^4in^l780-S dated the 13th October, 1947. LB S\Sh \ t 1. , V A &gt;C) | ' '.'C J A j i /e &lt;r3 12 A k&lt;rCONFIBKNTIAL lit EXPRESS LETTER From POLITICAL, MUSCAT. To REPGU, Bahrain. No. C 81-12/10 Dated the 2nd February, 1948. Roforonco paragraph 7 of enclosure to your Printed ( Lottor No, 2^60-S dated the 30th Docombor, 1947. Gwadur Telegraph Traffic. 2. Tho figure Tt 54,017 M appears to bo a typie error and should road r * 5,417 f * » vido my telegram No. C 567 dated the 23rd December, 1947. % Political Consul, Muscat. NCJ100/7 r M ^ ■w ti nn Telegram /rom To Repeated No. 54 Dated 5th and received 6th January 1948. Government of Pakistan, Karachi. Commonwealth Relations Office, London, Political Resident, Bahrain. Paragraph No. 3 of your telegram No 14,751 December 24th. Postal Services in Persian Gulf. 2. Facilities will be gladly afforded. = FOREIGN = No. 60-S .. i (6 V ^ ^ PERSIAN GULF ffiSIDENCY, BAHRAIN, dated the 7th January 1948. Copy forwarded with compliments tos- 11(1 The Political Agent, Bahfain. 525 The Political Agent, ^pwalt., _j,'S *■ The Political Agent, Muscat, ^ with reference to Residency endst No, 2272-S, dated the 30th December 1947.CONFIDENTIAL No.150-S 2 The Political Resident, Persian Gulf, presents his compliments to:- The Political A^nt, ' MUSCAT ^ and has the’ honour to transmit to him the under mentioned document(s). / (\W PERSIAN GULI 1 RLSID hNCY BarlRAIN Dated the 16th January, 1948 REFEREN CE TO PREVIOUS GORRESPONDERCE 3 I f Residency Printed Letter No.2260-S dt. 30/12/1947. Description of Enclosure Name asnd Date Subject Commonwealth Relations Office5 ^ TT London, ’endorsement No.Ext. I POST AND TE.LEG^ArH ^ 3018/47 dated the 6th JanuaryH F,vCllJTi^o rA G-'-^UtE 1948. % • LB'COP* P.O* Rcf # 70145/46. ^ostal Services Depart,:iant, Gkaier? 1 Past Office, TaO;!'-' • f 1. 3 ta Deco ner, 1947* Dear Harrison, Persian Gulf Agencies Appleby has just returned fror.i the Persian Gulf and has submitted a re K&gt;rt, a copy of which is attached, on the situat -on at Gv^adur. x ur ca &gt;ress letter No. Kxt. 2215/47 of the 16th of cctobcr to the Government of Pakistan also refers - I assume you have not yet had a reply to this - and I would be glad of your further views on the subject. It is of course on the telegraph side only that we have foreseen any difficulties in taking over the Gwadur office, and in this connection we have noted Donaldson*s letter of the 19th December to Cable and Wireless imited, about their Llusc t concession, in which he tells the Company of the Political Resident*s views about the establishment of a small wireless station at Gwadur. The Company viere not previously interested in taking over Gwadur services, but probably the matter was approached purely from the oo leroial aspect, and you will no doubt advise us further on the political aspect when you have received the Political sident * s iurthcr couHunia t . n. Yours sincerely, (Signed) F. Bard. P. A. K. Harrison, Esq. ,CIRCULAR No. 7 [ XF 232 (4/47) Foreign Office, 21th January, 1948. Restricted Export of British Postage Stamps Sir, I have to inform you that under new regulations British postage stamps, being of philatelic interest, are subject to licence if exported outside the sterling area. The export of British postage stamps in letters sent through the Foreign Office bag by friends and relatives in this country of staff abroad, therefore, can no longer be permitted. 2. To obviate difficulties thus caused, Heads of Missions may order postage stamps through the Foreign Office, against prior repayment by means of cheques drawn in favour of the Finance Officer, Foreign Office. Arrangements should be made for their distribution only to persons entitled to bag facilities (including personnel of Information and other sections of your staff), on whom it should be impressed that friends and relatives must not be asked to send additional supplies to them direct. 3. A similar circular has been addressed to His Majesty’s Representatives (as No. 013). I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ERNEST BEVIN. His Majesty’s Superintending Consular Officers 14524—1 34 7 h_ 25 aCory of letter Ho.830 ORB dated the B6th January, 1948/from the Accountant Oeneral. Ccncral r o^t Office, London, addressed to the non*!)!? the # Political Resident in the Per nan Gulf, Bahrain. I have to inform you that Postal Orders overprinted for use on and after 1st April, 1.948, at the British ^ost Offices in the Persian Gulf, are being despatched to you for safe custody. The first portion of the supply is being sent by Air Mail, and the balance by Surface Mail. Mr. Preach is beinsr advised to deterrrine ^hat supplies should be provided for use at the offices under hi? control, and arrange for then to be despatched to the Political Agents concerned. .* j Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, No.?$-9/2. 7th February, 1948. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent Bahrain/Kuwait/Auscat, for information. Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. xda C //? J ( Z- Zi /z. fTo The Sub-Post Master, • Muscat. Quarters Memorandum / Reference your letter No. 453 dated the 25th February, 1948. 2. As there are no government quarters for you In Muscat, you will be entitled to House Rent in lieu. I am ooramunioating with the Hobble the Political Resident on the subject of your proposed House Rent allowance and will inform you of the outcome in due course. Political Agent &amp; H.-tf’-s. Consul, Muscat NCJ12/10 ,/^s Telegram From To No. G-.T.C. political Agent, I.fuscat. Political Resident, Bahrain. C 86 Dated the 28th February, 1948. ITJy Express Letter No. C 597-12/10 December 1st. postal staff. 2. Paragraph 5 (a) (l). Post Master is again pressing for free quarters. There are no government quarters available but I strongly recommend payment of Rs.50/- (half 100) per month in lieu, ihis is minimum amount for which a house with only three living rooms can be rented in Lius cat. - P OLITICiiL - NCJ' 21 , i-k? No. 577-3. To Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 13th March 1948. The Political Agent, The Political Affent, The Political Officer, KUWAlt. M USCAT S' Trucial Coast, SHARJAH. MEMORANDUM. This hag contains two parcels of British stamps and one parcel of British Postal Orders. These Kuwait should please he handed over to the Post Master Muscat Thihni on the afternoon of March 31st 1948. 2. He may also please be informed that the stamps are in your safe custody, on their arrival. 3. Please acknowledge. Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL.r 1^(0 N0.587-S, The Secrets.r&gt; , to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, presents his compliments to The Political A&amp;ent, BAHRAIN . ri^ The Political Agent, KUWAIT, The Political Agent, HU 1 GAT and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document* ^ Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 17th March 1948, Reference to previous correspondence* Residency endorsement Jlo # 6Q-S dated the 7th January 1948* I Description of Sncloauret Notification regarding postal arrangements in the Persian Gulf from 1st April 1948. - » ‘ T ' ^POSTAL ARRANGE'ENTS PERSIAN GULF. On and from the 1st of April&gt; 1948, Post Offices in the Persian Gulf (Bahrain, Kuwait, Dubai and Muscat) will be administered by H...L Government. STAMPS. Overprinted British stamps as shown below'will be on sale at the Post Offices and the present Indian stamps will no longer be valid for the prepayment of postage. (a) (b) (c) id. stamp overprinted i anna 5 Id. 1 ' i ltd. 1 -g-annas } 2 d. 2 M 5 2 id. 2i ' 5 For use at Dubai and 3d. 3 ' 5 Muscat. 6 d 6 11 { 1 rupee 5 2/6 2 rupees i A similar range of stamps over- ][ printed with place name Bahrain in { addition to the above-mentioned 5 For use at Bahrain, values. 5/- stamp overprinted J overprinted 5 rupees and place $ name Bahrain. ' ][ A similar range of stamps over- 5 printed with the place name Kuwait 5 in addition to the above-mentioned 1[ For use at Kuwait, values. 5/- stamp overprinted } 5 rupees and place name Kuv/ait $ PObTaL ORDERS. The following range of British Postal Orders with poundage overprinted in Indian currency will be on sale at the Post OfficesThey will be issued and paid at the^ fixed equivalent in Indian currency shown on a Conversion Table held by v each oUb-Postnaster. Sterling denomination Poundage 6 d l/~ !/6 2 /~ 2/6 3/- 3/6 4 /.. 4/6 v* 7/6 10A 15/- 20 /- l-J annas li n 2 ' 2 M 2 ,r 2 n 2 «' 2 ' 2 n 2 ' 2 i 2 i Indian rupee Postal Orders will no longer be issued or paid at Persian Gulf Post Offices, but exceptionally Indian rupee Postal Orders issued not later than the 31st of March will be paid. Money Orders ....v ✓ -4- Correspondence and Parcels for Imperial and Foreign countries (including Aden, Burma, Ceylon, India, Nepal Pakistan and Portuguese India) Letters . Great Britain &amp; Eire British Empire and territories under British Mandate, U.SoA. and Egypt All other countries Post cards all destinations Printed papers including book packets Samples v Registration Insured service pa rcels . 2~k annas first ounce 1 anna each addition al ounce 3 annas first ounce 1 - 2 * annas each addition al ounce 2 anna s i Io anna each 2 ounces anna first 4 ounces anna each additional 2 ounces annas Limit of weight 4 lbs. Limit of weight 4 lbs. Limit of weight British Empire 5 lbs. Other countries 4 lbs. Limit of weight British Empire 5 lbs. Other countries 1 lb. 5 annuls compensation to equivalent of £12 2 annas each additional £12 up to £200 (maximum) Aden, India &amp; Pakistan 6 annas per lb Other destinations As at present.No.C 160 - 12/10 Political Agency &amp; H.M*s Consulate, Muscat. dated the 24th March, 1943. To The Sub -Post Wester, Muscat . Memorandum. Two parcels of British Stamp® and one of British Postal Order® have been received and are in safe custody of the Political Agent. 2. These will b* rtede over to you on the forenoon of March 31st, 1948, as directed. for Political Agent &amp; H.M»s Consul, Muscat. asr.r N No.C 161 -12/10 Political bgtncy, Muscat dat«d 24th March, 1948. To The Secretary to The Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum. Refercnca your Minorandiun No.577-S dated 13th March, 1948. 2. Two parcels of British Postage stamps and one of British Postal Orders have been received and are held in safe custody as requested. The Sub-Post Master has been in formed accordingly. asr for Political Agent, MuscatReceived from the Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, TWO parcels of British Stamps and ONE parcel of British Postal Orders. Political Agency &amp; H.M's Consulate, Muscat. dated April 1st, 1948.'7^ 7 . GWADUH POCT Or^FICE No repairs have been carried out for seven years and it will probably collapse within a year or two if not repaired. Mails are still coning overland although B.I. mail- boats are now calling regularly. Have the Pakistan authorities been approached on this subject? when I was in Gwadur there was direct telegraphic communication with Karachi but I was informed that the line is frequently out of order. Whether vie should press for a wireless station in Gwadur depends on our future policy towards the place, a subject on which I propose to address the F.O. The Pakistan Government have introduced their own coinage and have announced that Indian currency will only be legal tender until September 30th next. The Sultan is contemplating making the Indian rupee the only legal currency for official purposes. Compilations will arise if the Pakistan Government insist, as Is probable, that only Pakistan currency shall be accepted in the Owadur Post Office, if it remains under their control after September 30th. I am therefore of opinion that the G.P.O. should take over the Owadur ?. 0 . not later than October 1 st. Arrangements might be made to pay rental for a portion of the telegraph line until a decision is reached on the question of installing a wireless station. (ltd.) Y/.R.H. 6/4/4 S', No. G/20. OFFICE OF THE POLITICAL RESIDENT PERSIAN GULF, Camo, MUSCAT, the 7 th April 1948 Copy f orwardr J ^ KPG.Tele^ran GTC From To No. 328 Political Resident, Bahrain Political Ardent, nscft Dated tie 13t}i received the 14th April, 194 » Surplus funds of Post Office at Muscat should be credited to General Post Office in your Foreign Office account. Letter follows. Prodrome.B&gt;. Tb' Ki' AL un, r j-.j I 'l £' T COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS CNFICE EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) From Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations To . government of Pakistan, Ministry of Foreign Affairs 6 c Commonwealth Relations Repeated to Political Resident, Persian Gulf United Kingdom High Commissioner, Karachi. 30th March, 1948. No.Ext.807/48 /&gt;? Reference your express Letter No.0/42/47 of 19th January. Gwadur Post Office. 2. Since my express letter to you of 16th October was written question of future post and telegraph arrangements at Gwadur has been under further consideration in light of report by represent ative of British Post Office who recently visited the Gulf (my express letter No.Ext.332/48 of 5th February refers). 3. It is understood that under hitherto existing arrangements mails from Gwadur are carried by camel to Pasni once a fortnight and thence by lorry to Quetta. Telegrams are sent to Fanjgur by a land-line which is subject to frequent interruption. Messrs. Cable and Wireless Limited have now stated their willingness to establish a small wireless station at Gwadur for direct^communicat ion with Muscat (and so with Cable and Wireless network) and to provide in addition necessary staff to operate postal business carried on at Gwadur. It i£ suggested that mails should be carried by sea. In view of the fact that mail steamers call at Gwadur in both directions once every two or three weeks the service- should be almost as frequent as the present one. It would be possible to dispense with land-line to Panjgur. 4. I should be glad to know whether the Pakistan Government would be agreeable to Messrs. Cable and Wireless Limited proceeding to make arrangements as outlined in para. 3 above with a view to their taking over post and telegraph business at Gwadur from the Pakistan Government as soon as they are in a position to do so. For this purpose Cable and Wireless would propose to instruct their Divisional Manager at Karachi to obtain detailed particulars of the buildings, etc. at Gwadur which it would be necessary for them to take over, and suggest that further negotiations should be continued locally. Meanwhile United Kingdom Government would be very grate ful if Pakistan administration could continue to maintain postal and telegraph arrangements at Gwadur. The issue of tl 1 ’ been duly authorised. CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY No. 714-S BAHRAIN Dated the 7th April 1948 Copy forwarded with compliments to:- The Political Agent, MUSCAT . for information only. U/&gt;^ ‘LBjjo. 949-93/6 PhirtS IAN GULF RESIDE&lt;3Y BAHRAIN. 2nd April, 1948• Dear Agency, It has been agreed with the Post Master that any surplus funds resulting from the business of the Post Office at 1. Bahrain/Dubai 2 * Muscat 3* Kuwait / should be handed over to you for use on official expenditure incurred by you on behalf of the Foreign Office. They should be credited to the G.P.O. in your Foreign Office accounts. This procedure may obviate your having to draw Bills of iuxchange on the Foreign Office to keep your Agency in funds. 2. We should be glad therefore if you would arrange to receive these surpluses from the post Office. Yours ever The Residency A The Political agency, Bahrain. The Political agency, Muscat. The Political agency, Kuwait.Ho.C 222-12/10 Dear Residency, His Britannic Majesty 9 s Consulate, dated the 27th April, 1943. &amp; . A s Reference your letter No. 949-93/3 dated 2nd April, 1943. Arrangements have been made to receive surplus funds from the Post Office for use on official expenditure Incurred by this Consulate on behalf of the Foreign Office, fv j ' M i t . Agoney- Persian Qulf Residency, iahraln . asr.Q Telegram From To No. C 201 Dated the in code concerning Savings Bank accounts which cannot be with drawn by local investors. He informs me that approximately Rs. 10,000/- has yet to be withdrawn and that the public is now becoming somewhat difficult when payment is withheld. 2. As Post Office is situated ift the Agency, it is wrongly but inevitably regarded in Tfluscat as being part of the Agency and I should be most grateful if you could help in effect ing prompt withdrawal of outstanding deposits. I regret interference but Agency would become involved in any local resentment. Political. Political Agent, Muscat Political Resident, Bahrain 15th June, 1948. Following for Breech. Your telegram No. P4 June 5th to Post Muscat. Muscat Postmaster has asked me to telegraph you asrHis Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain presents his compliments to:- The Political Agent, j Muscat and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, 3A1L1AIN . Dated the 1st July 1948. 1^' Reference to previous correspondence Muscat telegram C/21 of the 16th June 1948, Description of enclosure Note P.16 dated the 23rd June 1948 from Mr. Breach Postal Superintendent, Bahrain to The Secretary to the Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Post Office Savings Bank accounts.COPY P.16 British Postal Agencie Persian Gulf) Bahrain. 23rd June, 1948. Referring to the telegram from Political Agent, Muscat, to the Political Resident, Bahrain, No. C/21 of the 16th June, 1948. The following telegrams relative to the subject were exchanged between this Office and the G.P.O. London Received 9th May 1948» i* Breach. Postal Superintendent^ Bahrain* Pakistan pressing for restoration facilities for withdrawal from existing savings bank accounts national savings certificates and c a sh certificates stop if we approve could such facilities be given without undue trouble for three months june to august. Postgen (G.P.O* London). u Despatched 9th jlay. 1948. «» Postgen OMB London Reference yours eighth withdrawal facilities savingsbank national savings and cash certificates could be restored without undue trouble on return to respective offices of all relative records which have been forwarded to Pakistan. Breach n No further information on the subject has been received but I have notified G.P.O. Londdn of the position as indicated by the telegram from Political Agent, Muscat, and have asked if restoration of the facilities can be expected in the near future. Sgd. X.C. Breach. Postal Superintendent. The Secretary.\ \A vc^vv Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, No.3B&gt;'- 9/2. 8th July, 1948. -TTnN % Forwarded with compliments to: The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, /The Political Agent, Muscat, for direct disposal. Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ncls. Acknowledgment for Postage stamps Muscat £ 210 do. Muscat 3000 „—dxu Gwadirr-' 300-/K No, C 317-12^0 Political Agency, Muscat• dated the 27th July, 1948# ^jeraorandum. Pleaee intimate this office whether British Stamps, as indicated in letters dated the 27th February, 1948, from the Post Office Stores Dept,, London, have been received by you. 2. Letters are enclosed for your information. . Political Agent, MuscatNo. C 346-12A0 Th® Political Agent &amp; His i.lajesty*s Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to : The Secretary to H.E. the Political Resident^ - ^ Persian Gulf, Bahrain . and has the honour to ^transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document (?) for information. / ttp) Political Agenty &amp; H.M*s Consulate, Tihiscat. dated the 23rd August, 1948. REFERBIICE TO PREVIOUS CORRhSl'O^DEI.'CE, Residency Complimentary slip No.331-9/2 July Sthj^B. :vame &amp; date. Description of enclosure. Subject . 1.Let ter No. 230 dated the 11th Aug., 1948, from Sub. Post Master, Muscat 2. Two letters dated the 27th May, 1948, from the Post Office Stores Dept., London.* I From Political Resident, Bahrain To Political Agent, ffascat No. 790 Dated the 11th received the 12th September, 1948. fjii % endorsement No. 714~S April 7th and your telegram No. C 424 September 22nd 1947. 2. Government of Pakistan is pressing to continue running Post and Telegraph Services at Gwadur on a permanent basis on following grounds : (i) Gwadur is surrounded by Pakistan territory (ii) Close trade and commerce connexions (iii) Successful administration in the past. 3. Cable and Wireless are now prepared to run the service on behalf of Sultan. Final decision is called for and you should therefore point out the political implications to Sultan and telegraph his reply to me. 4. Correspondence is being forwarded by hand of H.M.S Wren. Galloway. asr. *R Telegram From Political Agent, Muscat rj -o Political Resident, Bahrain No. C 253 Dated the 16th September, 1948 Your telegram No. 790 September 11th. Gwadur &gt; Post Office. 2. I have discussed matter vdth Sultan who has no strong viev/s, but favours accepting offer of Cable &amp; Wireless 3. He thinks Pakistan Post Office in Gwadur is not efficient at present. I am asking British Agent for report. Ellison. Telegram GTC From Political Agent, Itoscat fo British Agent, Gv/adur No. C 254 Dated the 16th September, 1948 Please report your views on present efficiency of Gwadur Post Office. Ellison(W 4066/956/801) confidential FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1 26th August 1948 r' Dear Residency, ]% No. M/103 1771758) * his Majesty’s Political Resident at Bahrain presents his compliments to Political Agent Muscat and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. finthdi.. Residency., Bahrain, Per si afi' Gulf V &gt; September., ll.th., 194.8... Reference to previous correspondence: Residency telegram No.790 dt. 11th Sept. 1948 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Foreign Office, General Departments letter (W 4066/956/801) dated POST &amp; TELEGRAPH 26th August 1948 with SERVICES IN GWADUR enclosures. ie 22nd April to ^es in Gwadur. the Government of 3 Government will Dst and telegraph le place is entirely i it has many akistani inhabitants. Djections to the ?vices, and we doubt Pakistan postal in Gwadur. 3 enclosed copy of i Relations Office) still wish them to a political one. • Government of all find it difficult relinquish them to for your observations, ents we might use our change of policy. are now pressing us reply by telegram. department. 3479a 3434G (8)(W 4066/956/801) confidential FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 26th August 1948 / Dear Residency Please refer to your letter of the 22nd April to Stewart, about the post and telegraph services in Gwadur. 2. In a letter dated the 23rd June, the Government of Pakistan express the hope that His Majesty’s Government will agree to their continued operation of the post and telegraph services in Gwadur. They point out that the place is entirely surrounded by Pakistan territory, with which it has many commercial ties, and includes a number of Pakistani inhabitants. (A copy of their letter is enclosed). 3. We recognise the force of your objections to the continued operation of Pakistan of these services, and we doubt whether the Sultan of Muscat would wish the Pakistan postal administration to gain a permanent foothold in Gwadur. Cable and Wireless (as you will see from the enclosed oopy of their letter to Harrison of the Commonwealth Relations Office) are willing to take over the services if wb still wish them to do so; the decision is therefore entirely a political one. + 4. Since we previously requested the Government of Pakistan to undertake these services, we shall find it difficult to give cogent reasons why they should now relinquish them to Cable and Wireless. We should be grateful for your observations, and for any suggestions regarding the arguments we might use with the Government of Pakistan to justify our change'of policy. 5. Since the Government of Pakistan are now pressing us for a decision, we should be grateful for a reply by telegram. Yours ever general department. $ , H 8 ( f&gt;Gvc, tT) The Residency Bahrain. ’LB’The High Commissioner for Pakistan presents his compliments to the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, and has the honour to refer to his express letter Ext.807/4P dated March 30th, 1948. In paragraph three of the letter, enquiries were made as to whether the Government of Pakistan would be agreeable to Messrs. Cable and Wireless Limited, establishing a small Wireless station at Gwadur, and taking over from the Pakistan Government the Posts and Telegraphs business there. tEhe Government of Pakistan have given their careful consider ation to the question, and have stated as follows: \ 'A year ago, prior to Partition, it was agreed that the United Kingdom Government should take over the administration of the Persian Gulf, including the running of the Posts and +Telegraphs, and with the concurrence of the Government of India that the Pakistan Government should continue to administer the Posts and Telegraphs until the United Kingdom Government Were in a position to take them over. The Govern ment of Pakistan agreed to this arrangement for reasons of territorial affinitv and other allied considerations. v c.n* 'The United Kingdom Government subsequently proposed, in SECRO Express Letter No.Ext.2215/47 dated October 16th 1947, that the administration of the Posts and Telegraphs services in Gwadur should remain in the hands of the Government of Pakistan. We are ourselves disposed to agree with that proposal in view of the administrative considerations involved, and we feel that as Gwadur is on its land frontiers, entirely surrounded by what is now Pakistan, with which it has close trade and commercial connexions, and contains tmong its inhabitants a large number of Pakistanis, any step that would loosen the links between Gwadur and the adjoining Pakistan territory, such as the handing over to Messrs. Cable and Wireless Limited of the Posts and Telegraphs system in Gwadur, which the Postal authorities in what is now Pakistan have run successfully for so long, would be regrettable. We are actuated also by considerations of security H The Government of Pakistan would accordingly be glad, if, for these reasons, the Government of the United Kingdom would agree to their continuing to run the Post and Telegraph services in Gwadur. In view of the circumstances pointed out in the Secretary of State’s letter of October 16th, 19474 quoted, and particularly the opening portiorv6f paragraph three, the Government of Pakistan trust that the Government Of the United Kingdom would agree”. London, 23rd June, 1948. 'LB*sec/t/bw 27th July 194P. Dear Mr.Harrison, Referring to your letter of the 30th ultimo to Mr. Stewart at the Foreign Office (a copy of which you sent to Mr. Chapling here*), we telephoned Mr. Stewart last week, as you suggested, concerning the likely reply to be given by the Foreign Office to the Pakistan Governments desire to continue running the Post and Telegraph services in Gwadur. Ms we understand the matter has been referred back to the Political Resident, Mr. Stewart saw no objection to our Divisional Manager in the Gulf proceeding to discuss with the Sultan of Muscat the Gompany^ draft concession with the reference to our establishing a wireless station at Gwadur deleted. We are instructing the Divisional Manager accordingly, at the same time supplying him with the necessary amendments relating to Gwadur, to enable him to introduce them without delay if this question is settled by the time the draft has been otherwise agreed and the Sultan is ready to sign. A copy of this letter is being forwarded to Mr. Stewart and to Miss Bridger at the Post Office, for their information. Yours sincerely, F. Lansbury F.A.K. Harrison, Esquire, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, S.W.l. 'LB*:-- t INo. 3uu-12/48 British h^ency, Grwadur, The 27th beptemoer 1948 To yrorn The Br i ti sh ^ent, dvraciur. The Political igent h His liajesty's Consul, n o o o -f xuuscat. \ Sir, datea the 16th September (received 2tp&amp; September) 1948, concerning the G-wadur Post Office, I have one honour to report as follows: 1. hails: Mails are still despatcneu, received ana aistriouteu fortnijitly via the overland route and the system, though far below the expectations and requirements of the traders ana the general puolic, is wonting satisfac torily. It may oe mentioned that people generally send their letters with passenger's to Karachi for posting to avoid delay* 2* T^ie^rams: Telegraphic traffic is in a most deploraole condition. Since I have arrived in Gwadur I have never found it woritirg without serious interruptions lasting ior several days, bametirte it is the Karachi** Bela section of the line which breaks down; sometime it is the Gwadur-Turbat section which holds up traffic. These interruptions cause serious set-back to business since telegrams are then delivered as much as 7 days late from the date of origin. 3. I have no comments to offer on the rest of tne postal system which appears to be working fainy well. x I may add in the end that the present Sub Post Master nas completed almost 3 years in Gwadur and is enaeavourir^ to go on leave. I have tne honour to be, bir, Your most ooeuient servant,•'X Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, lAiscat 18?, Telegram GTC From. To No. &amp; Dated theSth received the 9th October, 1948. Breach wishes to employ now Ali Yousuf as clerk under training in Muscat Post Office to replace present Post master next year. Please report particulars and suitability for employment timder General Post Office. Prodrome.Telegram From To No. Political Agent, 'fuseat Political Resident, Bahrain 1 Dated the 18th October, 194&amp;. /i * hjl y telegram No. C 253. Gwadur P.0. 2, iigent reports despatch of mails still working but below public requirements. any letters are sent privately to avoid delay. Telegraph is in deplorable condition. Rest of postal system works fairly well. 3. On grounds of public convenience I think we should accept Cable and Wireless’s offer if we can find reasonable pretext.Telegram From To No. GTC Political Agent, :!uscat Political Resident, Pahrain 2 Dated the l&amp;th October, 1°4^« / f• ^ ^ Your telegram No, 8 October oth. Puscat Post ^fester. 2. All Yousuf is a nice bright boy but young for his age (17) and much too young and inexperienced for suggested post. He might make a good clerk under postmaster and get promotion in four or five years tine. Rllison.Telegr&amp;m From R f''us cat Political Agent, To Political Resident, Pahrain No. 8 Dated tie 19th October, 194^* X ■ 'h Your telegram No. 790 September 12tl, Post Office at Gwadur. 2. Sultan today expressed strong hope that Cable and Wireless would take over Gwadur Post Office. T think he is distinctly nervous of continued presence of Pakistan Government office in G?/adur. Ellisont The Political Agent and compliment to His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document^), Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. Dated October 21, 1948 . Reference to previous correspondence : Agency telegram No. 1 dated 18th October, 1948 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No. 300-12/48 dated the 27th September^ 1948 from the British Agent, Gwadur. Report on the Gwadur P/0 L?&lt; asr.Telegram From To No. Inter 2 Political Resident, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat IB Dated the 26th received the 27th October, 1943 Secret. Your telegram No. 8. Our records do not show whether Sultan has ever been consulted regarding proposals ? that Cable &amp; Wireless should conjointly V establish a small wireless station at Gwadur in addition to running Post Office. If you see no objection ? please ascertain informally whether he agrees to this and will be willing to include Gwadur in the Cable and Wireless Concession. Hay.Secret. Your No. C/69 &lt;7/- /48). Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Aboard L.T. Nearchus, At Sea. 29th November, 1948. trie Political Resident. Copy of Sir Rupert Hay*s letter No. Tour No. C/69 C7/-/48) of the 29th November, to Air. Burrows, Foreign Office, London, without enclosure, with reference to his P.L. No. C 3g3-12/10 of the 21st October. /■ r (35/?/48) of the 22nd •)Lce. y of a more detailed report ritish Agent, Gwadur. ter with the Sultan personally nd Wireless should take over sh a wireless station there d to think that the longer t are we likely to find it t to clear out. ;his letter to Grafftey-Smith. fay). British Bal: Pers ency, Offi-^^, Aboard L.T. -B* At Sea. Nearchus .. ^Ipyem})eri948 /y gecfct, Tour No. C/69 &lt;7/- /48). Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Aboard L.T. Nearchus, At Sea. 29th November, 1948. v, .. j Please refer to my letter (36/2/48) of the 22nd October, about the Gwadur Post Office. 2. I enclose herewith a copy of a more detailed report which has been received from the British Agent, Gwadur. 3. I have discussed the matter with the Sultan personally and he is now anxious that Cable and Wireless should take over the Gwadur Post Office and establish a wireless station there as soon as possible. I am inclined to think that the longer we delay matters the more difficult are we likely to find it to persuade the Pakistan Government to clear out. I am sending a copy of this letter to Grafftey-Smith. 3.A.B. Burrows, Esq., The Foreign Office, London. (Sgd. W.R. Hay). / in/-J i I n 5/ tu TJb (:h f.Mscat Post Office, Please take the following action in regard to the case of the present Sub-Postmaster. ' f^ p/^rh . (1) Obtain from the Agency Surgeon a medical e^rtiriuile. % (2) Ascertain.the amount of leave due to the Sub-Postmaster. (3) ^Kis length of service in the Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department and the number of years he has to put in font his entitled full pension. 11/hen this becomes possible, I should like to have figures of the mail handled in Muscat during the past year and also figures indicating the Sub-Postmaster’s responsibilities in money matters such as payment of telegraphic money orders. Please also put up any manuals that we may possess of the Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department in regard to the terms of service of the personnel. / 4th. December, 1945. * 1. Agency Surgeon asked to send medical report which will be submitted by him to-day. I 2. Amount of leave due cannot be ascertained in the absence of his Service Book, which must be in Karachi. 3. He joined service in 1922 vide pages ^2 and 75 of File 12/5 and has to put in 7 years service for full pension. 4- The Sub-postmaster himself could give figures of mail handled during the past year which he is unable to do in his present condition. 5. He has been drawing Rs.50,000/- to Rs.1,00,000/- per month from the Treasury for payment of telegraphic money orders. / v v \ b, ,, ^Fundamental and supplementary Rules and Civil Service Regulations ° ‘ ^ t * :9 T * personnel in regard to terms of service.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000bc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/413</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000bc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/413</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 12/10 Post Office - Muscat &amp; Gwadur'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-21T22:20:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (208 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers in red and blue crayon (red for incoming, blue for outgoing correspondence) refer to entries in the notes on folios 195-209.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 210; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-98; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns postal services at Muscat and Gwadar. The arrangements for postal services in the territories of Muscat and Oman were complicated from 1947 by the independence of India, and the transfer of responsibility for postal services from the Government of India to the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, and by the question of whether newly-independent Pakistan should be asked to provide post and telegraph services at Gwadur [Gwadar].The papers include: staffing matters at Muscat, 1945; British Government plans for the future administration of postal services in the Gulf, 1947 (including minutes of a meeting at the India Office, 11 July 1947, folios 41-42); the attitude of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] to the proposed continuation of existing postal arrangements at Gwadar by the Government of Pakistan; correspondence concerning the temporary use of stamps overprinted 'Pakistan' at Muscat, Dubai, and Gwadar, following agreement with India to withdraw unsurcharged Indian stamps from areas served by the Pakistan Posts and Telegraphs Department, and the introduction of new British stamps to replace existing Indian stamps, 1947; recommendations of the British Post Office representative (W Appleby) concerning the takeover of postal services in the Persian Gulf on 1 April 1948 (folios 120-130); details of Post Office staff at Gwadar, 1947; and the Foreign Office's initial decision to ask the Government of Pakistan to take over responsibility for postal services at Gwadar (folio 154), and ensuing difficulties following the Political Resident's recommendation that responsibility for services at Gwadar be handed over instead to Cable and Wireless Limited, 1947-48.The file includes correspondence from the Political Agent, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the British Agent, Gwadar; the Commonwealth Relations Office; and the Government of Pakistan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Pakistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Gwadur</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Postal services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Postage stamps</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000bc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>