<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000122_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T04:01:38.085Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM ssfeSiINDEX TO FILES 19/128 and 'C 10' BAHREIN. and 19/98 Vol. II. Pracis - loans by to Sheikh 1900. • 9 Eatif, proposal survey 1901. Wahabis and Turks 1902. Rumoured acquisition of land in Bahrein by Russian and German Consuls 1902. ■ Visit of Lord Curson. 1903. * Reported petroleum spring on Halul I. 1904. -—— — /' 9/98&lt; Vol. II. Asphalt deposit - notes on and correspondence regard I \tri V No. &lt;SV C. v 7 PEOM The Secretary to the Government of India in the ^Foreign Department. TO Lieutenant Colonel C.A.Kemball,C.I.E. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated,Viceroy's Camp,the December,1903 Sir, I am directed to forward for record, copies of notes on the private interviews which were granted lay His Excellency the Viceroy to the Shfeikh of Bahrein on the 27th.November, 1903,and to the Sheikh of Koweit on 29th.lTovember,1903. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Secretary.Hot« on interview between HIS ZKCELLEliCY VICSHOY j 0.? BAlIRi 1} on the th*H0Tttsbejr 1 1903 • His Sacoellenoy the Viceroy accorded a primte interview to mi&amp;iMi Im bin All of Bahrein on R .I .M»S.*ilardinge» at U A»M» today. The Sheikh to. car,a with his son Sheikh iteed.who ma r.cos- nlsed as hie imooenBor by the aov of India in 1901. Hr.Dane.yorelgn Sec re taiy,Colonel Kemhall.Hesldent in the Gulf, '■*' * ' ' '■ ! ' ^ • asi'.irjjAasistant Polltio^l A.jentiBahrein translated# The Sheikh had apologised to Colonel Kemball for the inadequate arrangements mde for the landing of Hie Sxoelionoy and swite on the previous afternoon and for his discourtesy in leaving before the ' ho e party had got off safely and no reference was made to the matter at the interview. He was asked if he had any re nests to prefer but raid that he had none# His Excellency then said that he wished to siention two inatters • One was the arrangements in progress to secure redress for the imirder of the Sheikh* b cousin Selmn bin DiaiJ with his follow ers by the iiehaih near Katlf in r,&lt;900.the position waa that His Majesty*s Government had tried to secure redress through the Porte,which had called for a report through the Vali of Basrah.A reasonable time must be allowed for the receipt' of the reply;but,if the Turks would not o* could n ot secure, redress, Cis •xcelloncy ''ould consider what further steps souid be taken.He wished to know what action the Sheikh desired-The Sheikh replied that he would like to have the offenders made over to him,bu',if this could net be arranged he would accept pecuniary compensation# His Sccellency then said that the second matter was more important#He had ascertained that the customs of Bahrein were farmed wfAJTEMMl out to Indian hmtmm and that th# revived con- «idemblj than wtiat might raasoaably »Q&gt;eot«d from th» total ▼oX'ia® of th« trade of th® islaade •Horsovor tha waa in the haMt of drawing i^oa the baniaa in advance thereby involving Mssneif in debt 9 and pledging the resourcee of the State, ©jia syetexa was a 'bad one both for the Chief himself and for the State* Ihe .xheikh .replied that this was a private ssatter and he trust* ed that His acoelleney would leave hia to mena^po it in Ms own way«He eventually asked what reason His Eacoellenoy had for ask* ing him to mice a change.His Excellency replied that he had three reasons (1) To free the Shei&amp;h from debt. (2) To increase the revenue of the State# (3) To ensure that Sheilch ilamed t «hosi the Government of India had agreed to recognise as the Sheikh's heir, should not succeed to a State in an embarrassed or irapecunious condition,though he hoped that the date of his succession would be long deferred, 1!he Sheikh was very obstinate but could not^ when pressed offer any reason against the reform,^hi©h,a8 His Excellency pointed out,had been most successful in aefcat,where the Sultan who had originally resented its introduction had recently thanJced His Excellency for having induced him to adopt it, Ihe Sheikh then tried to get the matter postponed during his lifetime,but His Excellency pointed out that he was only 57 and hie uncle and predecessor Sheikh Mohasaied had lived to bw over 80. Eventually the Shei&amp;h said that lie would wish to consider the ^ subject with his eons and brother .Ms Sxcellency agreed that % this was a very proper course,but warned the Sheikh that he must understand clearly that the matter could not be dropped and that Colonel Kemball would be instructed to report after consulting the Sheikh what course he would recomsen^to secure the execution of the reform .The Sheikh could not enjoy all the advantages&amp; of the Britijsh ?rot«otomt«,to he his position mid aeeurity without diaclmrglns the obligations ^uleh It Itrrolved* Hi# Sheikh produeed the old treaties to sltow thmt he ttoderfitood hie position. Ihe interview Whioh had lasted for over half an hour then oloeed and the Sheikh withdrew# At the formal intenriew on the prerloua dear the SheiWi had kept on hie eand&amp;le thou^i the reminder of hie party removed theirs Ha was very nervous at meting His Exeellenoy for the first tlm I Whioh my have aocotmted for his ojaisslon to observe this mark of respect .At the private interview above resordsd he had r«ioved his sandals. L .Ban# « CdAAjz^yfr cuo , CCuraon).-aifir ' From To No«— $ &amp; .E/A. The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Major P. Z. Cox, C.I.E., OfTg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla, the June 1904. Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 134, dated the 18th May 1904, regarding a supposed naptha spring near Halul Island. S. In reply I am to state that the Government of India approve of your suggestion to ask the Senior Naval Officer to have the matter carefully investigated as soon as a ship can be spared for the purpose. A report of the result of the investigation should t&gt;e submitted in due course for one information of the Government of India. Iff L O Js &lt; J % hP''j. ' ' '' I / / 1 Li I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, r ^ A - # Under Secretary to the Government of India.No 3761 E Government Foreign Departm ated Simla the Novr b* REPLY. No, 3 J/ , dated / To for P. Z, Cox, Off9 Pol: Residen Persi Subject,, 'upposed Naphtha Sp sland ^ 'ir, I am directed at- ention to the lette l ov eminent of India department No 2055E % A, ^9th June 1904 and he (rovemment of formed in the columh he approximate dat 'eport therein calle xpected, I am also hat the reply to ay be sent not la st December 1904: % I have etc The Secretary Government Foreign Sir, I have the in reply to your adj oining column present time it found possible to as no ship has be When the 'Lawrence'' Bombay a visit wi and I hope to be to submit a report I have Captain, F, A, for P. (Sd)C,Sormrs Cocks. Asst Secy toHo: of 1906. J^ritish Besiclenoj and Gonsula'te-ileneral }aishlr9 J June 1905. To, ( t . Filrrim faquirs. Geological Survey of India 0/0 U *3 Vice-consul K'mz* Sir, With reforence to ny letter } r o:569 dated 'Tth Aoril 1905, I have the honour to reauest that you will be good enough to furnish ine,at your earliest convenience» irith fenieport on the result of your visit to Halul and Bujima in search of the Haptha ^'prin^r said to exist in tiat locality. I have the honour to be Bir Your nost ooed ent servant P - J lag or Off f•: Political Eesident in tiie Persian ■•MlfIdentlal• From The 'Deputy Seoretp ry to the -lovernment of Indie To Sir, Lieutenant Colonel P.z.Cox, C.S.I. ,C .I.'E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Dated Fort illiam, the Dece-riber 1910, jith reference to your official letter Ho. 439 dated the 15th September 1905, I am directed to forward a copy of letter, with its enclosures, from the Secretary, Revenue and Statistics Department, India. Office, dated the and Decoraber 1910, and to re quest that ■'■on will report whether the ikh of Bahrein -would have any objection to granting concessions / 1 / / or licenses to work the asphalt deposits in the island.. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. 1 Deputy Secretary to the .Government of IndiaCopy. India Office, London. 2nd December 1910. m | Dear Sir, I forvsp-rd, for information, copy of the papers noted in _4 ter from Imperial Institute dated l^th Angast ) the margin, on the sub- D and reply thereto dated 7th Septeribei . ) ) ter from Imperial Institute dated 25th ) ject of the likelihood ember 1910 (with enclosure in original) and ) ly thereto dated 2nd December 1910. ) 1 1 of concessions bein-- granted for working asphalt deposits in Bahrein. It will be observed that Professor Dunstdn has been told that a further communication will be mp de to hi i when informs ti n has been received from ndia. I am, etc ., 3d. T.7. H ol de rne ss . Secrete ry. Revenue and Statistics Department To the Secretary to the Government For ei gn Depart men t . of IndiaCopy. OL~ *r&amp;-. /s£/ 7th September 1910. Sir, In reply to your letter of the Igth Lvrvst , Wa.S850/1910, I cm directed to inform you thct the asphalt deposits in Bahrein e owned 'by the Chief of Bahrein. With regard to steamship services I am to say that regular mail services are provided by the British Indian Steam Eavigation Company from Bombay. The ssels of the Bombay and Persia Steam navigation Company madfe frequent calls, and those of the Anglo- Algerian Steamship Company and the Hamburg-Araerika Company occasional calls at Bahrein. I am to add that if the information is sought on behalf of an inquirer of other than British nationally, it would be conve nient that it should not be communicated to him direct, but that he should be referred by the Imperial Institute to this Office. I am to point out that s &gt;rac facts regarding the asphalt deposits of Bahrein are given on pages 149-155 of /olune XX:(I Part 4 of the Memoirs of the Geological Survey of India (1908). I am, etc,, Sd. Colin &amp;£ampbell. The Director, T ;mperial institute.f India Office %S: o ?nd December 1S10 Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the *?5fh November, lo. 4087/1910, on the eubject of samples of asphalt rock from Bahrein and the likelihood of concessions being granted to work the deposits. In reply I pm to s'2Y thf 1' a copy of your letter, with its enclobiire has been forwarded to the Government of India, and that an receipt of their reply a further communication will be ad dressed to you. The Director, Imperial Institute, South Kensington, s.w. True Copy. I am etc., Sd. T. 7- Holderness. Secretary, 'Revenue and Statistics Department Superintendent Foreign Department.No. of 19 1Q POLITICAL AGENCY, BAKPAIN, PEBSIA1T GULF, From jor S. Ct . Knox, C. I. E., x Political Agent , Bahrain. To Colonel P. 2. Cox, C. S. I., C. I. E., Political Besident in the Persian ''lull, Bushire. 1} y ■ Dated Balirain, 17th 'Deceiriber' ] i ^10 Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 3215, dated the 4th instant, together with its enclosure as well as this Office file regarding Asphalt 'Deposits at Bahrain. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient sew ant. Major. Political Agent, Bahrain.% Ho. £ 5 / of 1911. British Residancy and Uonaulate-ueneral, Buahire, J? '/ January 1911. To The Political -tgent, Bahrain. Liir, ,,'ith raforenca to your office letter ^o. &lt;301 dated the 17th June 1910, 1 have the honour to inform you that it is thought thtt British Firms might be interested in the asphalt deposits, and the wovernment of India desire rao to report svhethar the oheiJih would have any objection to granting Oonoasaions to /ork the deposits to a British Firm. Please tafia a suitable opening for sounding the Jheiith on the subject and let ma jaiow the result. I have the honour to be liir, iour most obedient servant, xjieut-Colonel, jpolitioal resident in the Persian uulfGOVERNMENT OP INDIA. foreign Nod^fJT4 datec^tha 2.£~ 'r. 19// To Lituttnant--Colonel P.Z# Cox, C.S.I, C.I.E. Political Besident in the ^ersiAn Gulf, Bushirt., Subject. Enquiry as to the likelihood of the grant 'by the Sheikh of Bahrein of con- -ctssii^s^ or licensee to work asphalt d tposits a ^Eahrein. Sir, I am directed to invite attention to the onr - communicatior\ noted in No. ^ ^Aaated ^ F.A. (Con) 51 -124he margin and to request %. f dated jp ' that (with the ^cxxuiiaioii •ei— the Government of India may be informed, in the column opposite, of the approximate date on wliiph a repiy may be expected. I am to ask that the Government of India may be favoured with an early reply to this reminder. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Repfy. No. , dated 19 To The SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of INDIA, / / Deputy Secy. to the Go S. il.Wo. ^4^of 1911. British Eesidency and Oonaulata-iieneral, Bushire, /^ April 1911. From L1out onant -C olone 1 P .Z. ^ox, G .C .I., .1.K. Political fiesidtmt in the Persian Gulf. To i'he Uonourable Lieutenant -Colonel Sir A.u.LoMahon, xx.G.I.K.,u.S.I. Secretary to the Government ot India In the Foreign Department, SIMLA. Sir, With raferonoe to the concluding portion of Foreign Departmont Letter Mo. 2790-ii.A. dated 31et December 1910, and reminder of 2Bth torch 1911. l' have the honour to re port that the Political Agent fell 111 just after reoslpt of instruotlona to sound the Lihalkh, and no opportunity then occurred until I vlalted Bahrein a fortnight ago, Htien the eubject wae brought up In comveraatlon and ShalKh Ksa expressed himself as quite ready, subject to our ad vice, to entertain a proposal fro. a British Fi™ for .or. ing the asphalt deposits referred to. i have the honour to be Sir, Your moat obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.dS» jonfidentialj i Ho . S.A. REC El P vssz- r mbI3:iuu9ii N ^- A copy of the foregoing- letters is forwarded to the lolitioal Besident in the Persian Gulf ( for infor- rcation v.ith reference to his letter Ho. 949 (confidential) i dated the 13th April 1911. By order, etc.. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Lepartitent; J Simla, The /$£I 1. Letter to the Secretary, Revenue ani Statistics Department, India Office, dated the 27th April 1911. 2. letter from the Secretary, Revenue and Statistics Department, India Office, Ho. E.&amp; S.1272, dated the 2nd June 1911, and enclosure. *Confidential. From To ( Copy. ) The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Sir T.W.Holdernesa, K.C.S.I., Secretary, Kevenue and Statistics Department, Indi* Office, L 0 I D 0 ST . Dated Simla, the ETth April 1911, I am sorry for the delay which has occurred in answering your letter 3So, E &amp; S 2740, dated the 8nd December 1910, on the subject of the likelihood of con cessions being granted for working asphalt deposits in Bahrein. The Political igent fell ill just after the insv tructions to sound the Shaikh reached him, and it was not until Lieutenant Colonel Cox personally visited Bahrein, at the end of March, that an opportunity occurred for ascertaining the Shaikh's views. It has now been ascertained that the Shaikh is willing, subject to our advice, to entertain a proposal from a British Fira for working the asphalt deposits referred to. JSL \( Copy. ) India Office, London, Snd June 1911, lo, E. &amp; S. 1272. c ll!y ^,ear KoKalion, With reference to your letter of the 27th April, I forward, for infortEation, copy of the papers noted in j To Director, Imperial Institute, E. S.1272, Imargin, on the subject dated the Slst Kay 1911. of the Bahrein Aaplialt deposits. I an, &amp;c., Sd/- T.W.Holderness, Secretary, Revenue and Statistics Department, To € The Secretary to the Qovemment of India, Foreign Department.• • (s^ ( Copy. ) India Office, 31st May 1911. E. &amp; S. 1872. Sir, In oontinuatlon of t?te letter frcm this Office, E. &amp; S. 2740, dated the 2nd December 1910, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to infonn you that proposals from a British film to work the asphalt depositi at Bahrein would be entertained, subject to the advice of the Political authorities, by the Sheikh; and to suggest that any such proposals should be addressed in the first instance to the British political Agent, Major S.G.Knox, C.I.E., I am, &amp;c., Sd/- E.Bitchie. The Director, Imperial Institute.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000122_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/317</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000122</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/317</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 19/98 II, 128 (C 10) Naphta Spring Near Halul Island + Miscellaneous Correspondence + Viceroy’s Interview 1901. 19/98 II Asphalt Deposit’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1901/1911</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (104 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end. On folio 2 there is an index of the topics contained in the file (without page numbers).</extent><extent>A bound correspondence file of which some sheets have come unbound and are now loose. The volume is foliated from the first page of text to last page of text, with small circled numbers in the top-right corner of each front-facing page.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains - in the following order - correspondence between the Residency in Bushire and the Agency in Bahrain regarding a debt owed by Shaikh Isa bin Ali Al Khalifa of Bahrain to a Mr. Francis; discussions concerning the dispatch of a gun ship to Katif (Qatif) and a proposed survey of the area; discussion (and dismissal) of rumours that the Russian and German Consuls in Bushire had acquired plots of land in Bahrain; matters related to the arms trade and arms seizures in the region; a proposal to establish a small agricultural garden in Bahrain; discussion related to an article in an Arabic newspaper published in London that contained quotes from a book (by Samuel Zwemer) that were critical of British rule in Bahrain; notes on an interview between Viceroy Curzon and Shaikh Isa of Bahrain; reports of a supposed Naptha spring near Halul Island and a technical study of asphalt deposits in Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000122#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>