<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:36:26.395Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">.&lt;&lt;? w Tel. No. Holborn 3434. Any communications on the subject of this letter should be addressed to :— THE SECRETARY, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, ' London, W.C. 2 . and the following number quoted :— ^36592/3.6. ^3 SECRET. Sir, j[iJ&lt; giu. (AIR MINISTRY, U LONDON, W.C.2. hi February, 1957 .ttijc, 11 I am commanded t&gt;y the Air Council to refer to th penultimate sentence of India Office letter P.Z.2057/36 of the 16th April, 1936, on the subject of the proposed appointment of an Air Liaison Officer for the Persian Gulf and to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that they have chosen Squadron Leader A.R.M. Rickards, O.B.E., A.F.C. to he the first holder of this post. I am to add that until suitable accommodation is available at Bahrein the Council propose that Squadron Leader Rickards should use Basrah as his base. I am,Telegram Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chairman T Under Secretary Secretary of State... Commitiee Under Secretary Secret/ry of State... &gt; 0/fi* ^ ^ ^ H-i&gt; IL A'. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. ; a Previous Papers :— 4475a 1000 5.30Minute Paper, P.Z. 2057/3 6. political Department. 3939 5000 7/35 Please see the d.c. correspondence between Air Vice Marshal Mitchell, Air Officer Commanding British Forces in Iraq, and Colonel Fowle, on the subject of a proposal to create the appointment of Air Liaison Officer in the Persian Gulf. The correspondence is arranged immediately below to read downwards, and consists of the A.O.C.’s letter of 17th December, Colonel Fowle’s reply of the 8th February, and A.O.C.’s final letter of 24th February. It will be seen that Colonel Fowle does not like the idea, though it w'ould appear that Colonel Loch has no objection to it. Colonel Fowle is, however, prepared to accept the proposal if it is pressed. Both the Air Officer Commanding and the Air Ministry are very keen on having an Air Liaison Officer in the Gulf, particularly in view of their increasing commitments in C^atar and along the Trucial Coast, and the Air Ministry have written us an official letter (of 13th March at P.Z. 1847/36) saying that they accept Colonel Fowle’s conditions and are taking steps to appoint an officer to i the post. 2. Although the Air Ministry letter shows a certain disposition to short-circuit the Secretary of State, it is difficult to resist their proposal which in fact has certain obvious advantages. The Air Force are the people who will, in fact, be responsible for protecting Qatar and possibly, later on, the Trucial Coast sheikhdoms, especially Abu Dhabi. They are therefore entitled to demand that they should have an Intelligence Officer in the area in question. Such an officer might, moreover, be of considerable value as he !would be able to spend his whole time wandering about and would not be tied to any office or court work which takes up so much of our Political Officers’ time. It is, of course/ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTKR no. 17 2 3 APR 1936 SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE COPY SENT ^ and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, of which he has received a. copy. In the circumstances and in view of the assurance of the Air Council that they will take appropriate steps to ensure that the conditions which Colonel Powle considers should be attached to any such appointment will be laid down, Lord Zetland concurs in the proposal to create the appointment. His Lordship notes that the name of the officer selected will be ft ^ notified to Whirs'Department in due course. He assumes that the appointment will be of an experimental nature in the first instance and that the position will be carefully re-examined from time to time in the light of the experience gained. (Sgd.) (VI. J. CLAUSON 4599 5000 2.36mmSECRET. Reference No. 3,10805/13. Air Headquarters, British Forces in ’Iraq, Hinaidi. 17th December, 1935. My dear Fowle, I am writing to you on the subject of the Royal Air Force Intelligence System. As you Imow, we still maintain our own Intelligence system in 'Iraq, and an officer for intelligence duties is stationed at each of the following places - Mosul, Sulaimania Baghdad and Basrah. In deference to ’Iraqi susceptibilities, they are not called 'Intelligence Officers', but are known as 'Air Liaison Officers'. These officers render reports direct to Air Headquarters on all tribal and military intelligence which would be absolutely essential to us should we be called upon to come to the assistance of ’Iraq under the terms of the Treaty. They also form the nucleus of a more extensive intelligence system which would become necessary should we have to come to the assistance of ’Iraq under the terms of the Treaty. As regards the Persian G-ulf, this work has hitherto been done by Coates, who is borne on the establishment of No. 203 Squadron as Intelligence Recording Officer. Now that our commitments in the Persian Gulf have increased and are increasing, the Air Ministry is very anxious to extend our existing system by appointing an i Air Liaison Officer for the Persian Gulf. There is, for I example, the measure of protection for QATAR which we have recently undertaken to provide. One of the conditions under which we agreed to guarantee that protection was that 'certain air facilities, such as air intelligence organisation must be provided,' I understand, also,that at the 42nd Meeting of the Middle East (Official) Sub committee, one of the recommendations was 'that the Air Officer Commanding in ’Iraq might be informed that inter vention on land in the Trucial Shaikhdoms was an additional commitment which he might in certain circumstances be called upon to meet'. I have not yet seen a copy of the Minutes of that meeting, but I hope to receive one from the Air Ministry in the near future. In the circumstances, therefore, it appears most desirable that we should appoint an Air Liaison Officer for the Persian Gulf, and I think the obvious place to locate him would be at BAHREIN, where he would be in close touch with the Political Agent. Lieutenant Colonel T.C. Fowle, C.B.E. , Hon. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Residency, BUSHIRS. / DuringDuring my visit to BAHREIN last week, I discussed the question in general terms with Loch; he raised the point, which I think is a reasonable one, that the Air Liaison Officer in the course of his duties might he dragged into political questions which did not concern him. Apart from this, however, Loci did net appear to have strong objections to the scheme, and in fi ct said that he thought an Air Liaison Officer of the right type would probably be of assistance to him. The duties of the officer would, of course, be the same as those of the existing Air Liaison Officer, that is, he would keep us in touch with all intelligence which would be of use to us in the case of our having to under take operations in the Gulf. The success of the scheme will, of course, depend very largely on the personality of the officer selected for the job. He must obviously be the type who will get on well with the Political Agents, with the Naval officers in the sloops, and in fact, be in general a good 'mixer”. He must also be an individual of character and common sense, so that he will not involve himself in political matters which are outside the scope of his duties. Provided that a suitable person can be found, I think he will be able to carry out his work quite satisfactorily without treading on anybody’ toes. At the moment, Coates, as you know, is going home and I have no one in this Command whom I consider suitable for this particular job. If, however, af$er considering the matter you find it possible to agree in principle to the appointment, I will ask the Air Ministry to look out for a suitable officer to fill the post, as both the Air Ministry and ourselves are very anxious that this appointment should be established. Yours (sgd. ) W. ftlfckeUConfidential D.o.lo* 9#-3 of 11^6 Buenire* the 8th February 1^56 Could you please refer to your deaii-ofticial letter Ho # 10805/13 of the 17th December 19 35 in which you put forward, a pr epos al ^ which had the sanction of the Air i or a Hoyrl Air Fores Intelligence Officer with Headquarters at Bahrain to be posted to the Hulf* I presume that this officer w &gt;uld work only on the Arab side ? 2. In my demi-official letter So. 1049-i of 30th December 1935 I replied that I would talk the matter over with loch when I next visited Bahrein. I have recently returned from a visit to Bahrain and am therefore in ® position to give my views, which are as follows. 3. There is a large aroount of information already to hand on the whole of the Arab Coast of the *ilf. I*orimer’e Gazetteer, for instance, gives a most complete picture of all geographical, statistical and tribal features. There is also 0* Connor’s 'Military I epoert on the Arabian shores of the Per elan Gulf' issued by the General Staff, India, In 1933, and various other publication®. 4. There are political Vents at Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat and e Residency Agent at Sharjah for the Prucial 'oast, who are of course closely in touch with their respective areas, concern ing which they already collect Intelligence, and issue fortnight ly Intelligence eports, copies of which are sent to you. If there are any features of special interest to the Rotyal Air Force not covered in these Reports, can easily instruct the Political / ir Tice Marshal v. 8 # 3. i t C he 11, CB. , 0 B ». , DH0 . , MC • , PC • , Air Officer Com^nd ing, British Forces in ‘Iraq, Bogftdd.Politic'1 /gents to include them. 0 . This being »o I venture to suggest tnat tne first step towards collecting information in tne Gulf from the Uoj i r F«r ce point of view might be to ’comb 1 tae ample information already available in the various official Reports on the subject. here in these eports there were gaps in itrao of information of importance to the oyal ^ir orce # or where sueh items needed bringing up-to-date as in Lorimer, a queat-omm tr« covering these points could be oiroulated by you through me to the Political Agents, who would then fill in the blsnlis. o assist them in this work an Officer of your Staff could be detailed to visit each Political Agent in turn. The result of these combined labours, (which could, be revised from tme to time in a similar &gt;mnner), would be an up-to-date and comprehensive eport which should - 2 Imagine - be most useful to the Reyal 2ir ^orce against all eventualities. But for this purpose it hardly seems necessary to me to appoint a res id ent Intelligence Officer in the Gulf. 6. The other main duty of such an Officer would presumably be to w&amp;rn you of impending trouble in a particular area which might affect the Royal Air Force in any way. But the Political Agents are already in close touch with the affairs of their Agencies, and if anything is brewing warn me fey telegrams which are repeated to you if the Roy^l Air orce are likely to fee involved. Personally I do not see therefore that the presence of an Intelligence Officer would help in this direction. Moving about as presumably he would do fron area to area 1 do not think that he could have his finger on the local pulse of any particular district as closely as any-3- Political Agent who 'lives, novee and mu His toeing* In hie Agency month in month out* on the other hrnd the present syeten toy which whenever the t oysl Air y rce are concerned in any Agency, a epecial Hcyal Air Force Officer ie sent there who 'liaises* with the local Political Agent, /rorics well* 7. ^aklng all the above into coneid eratten therefore, frankly 1 do not see the necessity of the Intelligence officer in question, and am inclined to think that he would be the fifth wheel in the coach - always rather an awkward faature. hat 1 suggest, as a first step at epy rate, is for a preliminary collection of information to toe nude as explained in paragraph 5 above. The special Royal Air yore# fi :cer detailed for this work could gain Valuable experience of local conditions, and of 'liaising* with the Political Agents concerned, and if it were finally decided (see para graph S below; to poet a resident oyal Air ^oree Intelligence Officer to the Gulf he might be the one so appointed* 8. I do not wish te toe obstructive where a Royal ir Force project is concerned, the pretence of the oyal Air Force in the Gulf from the political point of view ia indeed most helpful, and if the Air Ministry finally decide to post an Intelligence Officer to Bahrain, as far as 1 am e ncerned I shall not oppose it. Loch - with whom I suppose ths intelligence Off icer will hsve most to do — is quits prepared, to assist him in every way, as I am my self. There are, however, a few oondj tiona which 1 think should govern ths appointment, and which - without handicapping the Officer concerned - will prevent any chance of confusion or mis understanding* /mi *unti er • ta ndl ng, (a) ?h* r )f fic er should be oarefuUy aelected. ’his is a point you mentioned in your letter of 13tn December, and - if 1 my say so - 1 am sure that any Officer who is approved of by you will be acceptable to me. (b) He should confine his activities to getting information useful to the / oys 1 Air Force, and keep clear of local politics. I understand from Loch that, in the course of an inform*! dis cussion which you had with him on the subject at Bahrain, he brought up thie point, and that you quite agreed. the danger in this direction will lie not with the Officer, but with the Arabs. The letter have nothing to do in their opart time, of which they hate plenty, except to talk and intrigue. they will naturally be unable to distinguish between the spheres of an Intelligence and of a Political Officer, and unless the former makes It q ite cleftr to them that he has nothing whatever to do with their loc^l quarrels and intrigues, and shuts them ap when they begin pouring these into his ears, he may find himself encroaching quite unintentionally on ’natters which he Is not suppossd to deal with. (c) 1 understand from Loch that you yourself made the suggestion that the Officer should submit no report without giving a copy of it to the Political Agent concerned. :’he same suggestion was made by a predecessor of yours, Brooke-Pophau, when he made the same proposal of an Intelligence Officer to Biscoe some years ago (vide 3rooke*Pophais &lt; • demi-official letter So.51/20 of the bth arch 1930). I quite agree. (d) Any negotiations for P oyal Air Force facilities with Shaikhs should of course be made, as heretofore, by the Political Authorities.(e)/Relations between the Officer and Stu Ikiui anould be conducted threugH tut local ^olitictl ^ent. ^ higher authoritlte nad better know of your proposal, and of riews tnereon, ao I am aending a copy of tnia letter to Metealle, mi ton «t tne India Office, as well as to Locn, Watts and de Caury. Yours ever, sd. T.C.Fowle.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 190-S of 1936. 1 8 i 8 I &lt; \ o n The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Hon’ble 3ir Aubrey Metcalf e,KGlS., CSI. ,MVO. # foreign Secretary to the Cover orient of India, Mew Delhi. 2. o.G. , alt on Bequir e # CK. ,’1C., / The India Office, London. V' 3. Lieut.-Colonel Gordon Loch, CIS., Politics! Agent, Bahrain. 4. lajor R.p./atts,!A. ,Politiccl /gent, lAuscat. 5. Captain O.S.H. de Maury, Mp. , Pol it ical Agent, Kuvmit. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s ^/^ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. 5th.March..1936. Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident’s Printed Letter Uo.97-3 of the 5th February 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Demi-official letter No. S.10805/13 of the 24th February 1936 from the Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Iraq, Hinaidi. Subject. Proposal for a Royal Air Force Intelligence Officer with headquarters at Bahrair to be posted to the Gulf.K Ref erence:- B. 0/S. 10805/13. Secret. 18 45 * A.r Headquarters, British Forces in Iraq, Hinaidi, Iraq. -I Q Q 24th February 1936. ±&gt;J O O ) Lieut. Hon. My dear Fowle, Please refer to your demi-official letter ffo.96 -S of 1936, in which you give your views on the appointment of an Air Liaison Officer, Persian Gulf, with headquarters at Bahrain. Most certainly this officer’s activities will be confined to the Arabian side and there is no intention what soever that he should concern himself with Iran. I fully appreciate your points about existing informa tion on the Arabian Coast of the Gulf, but perhaps you do not know that we have started to collate all the information available, from which we hope eventually to produce a handbook covering all our requirements. T.t will be some time before we can get this material into shape for publication, and the work of bringing the information up to date, checking it over wi th Political Agents, and arranging it in a suitable form, will be one of the responsibilities of the Air Liaison Officer. In this connection, we have found Lorrimer’s Gazetteer most useful, but O’Connor’s military report of 1933 has disappointingly proved to be of no great value. From the subsequent paragraphs of your letter I get the impression that you feel that this extension of the R.A.F. Intelligence system is a super imposition upon the oi*ganizat ion which is at present maintained by the Political Agents in the Gulf. Sucii an idea is far removed from our in tentions and j regard this appointment as a supplement to your existing arrangements, which, it is hoped, will not only meet service needs, but will also be of material assistance •Colonel T.C.Fowle,CBE., t0 ^ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire.to your political Officers. In tiioae countries where responsibility for security has been allotted to the Hoyai Air force, our experience has been that the extra facilities afforded by our presence have been fully utilised by the political authorities, and that a liaison, closer than is possible where other services are concerned, is maintained with the administration, especially amongst those whose duties take them to outlying districts. I am, therefore, optimistic that cordial relations will exist between your officers and the proposed Air Liaison Officer. You will, I think, agree that developments on the Arabian shores of the Persian Gulf have occurred with unexpect ed rapidity during the past year or two, ana there are sound grounds for supposing that commercial undertakings, a notice able increase in air traffic, and the like, will give added importance to this area in the near future. With such developments in prospect, and bearing in mind the security respons ioilities which have devolved on the Air Force, I do not think that the work of the Air Liaison Officer will be a sinecure. 1 a* n in agreement with the conditions limiting the activities of the Air Liaison Officer, which you propose in the la&lt;3 c paragraph of your letter, and I am naturally prepared to accept the inforiaax,ion provided on political matters by those officials who are in constant touch with local affairs, /hen the appointment of an Air Liaison Officer is finally approved, I intend to draft detailed, instructions defining his duties, and I will refer this paper to you for any modi fications and suggestions you may care to put forward# Yours ever, sd. Hitchell.f Any communications on the subject of this letter should he addressed to :—• Tel. No. Holborn 3434. f T) &lt;7. 5 * 1 1 8 4 7 3.0- 2 0 ^ THE SECRETARY, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, W.C.2. and the following number quoted :— SECRET. S.36592/S.6. /3 Marcn, 1936. Sir, I am commanded by the Air Council to refer to India Office memorandum No. P.Z.1475/1936 dated the 4th March, 1936 forwarding a copy of a letter from the Political Resident, Persian Gulf regarding the proposed appointment of a Royal Air Force Officer with Headquarters at Bahrain. The Air Council are glad to learn that the Political Resident has no objection to the appointment of an Air Liaison Officer for the Persian Gulf and they will take appropriaii e steps to ensure that Colonel Fowle’s wishes concerning the appointment are met. I am to add that the name of the officer selected will be notified to your department in due course. I am, Sir, Your obedient Serv ;. A' / m r - The Under-Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, S.W.l. ENCLOSURE' IN WEEKLY LETTER o. 17 2 3 APR 1936 D | COPY SENT TONotes. Register No. Minute Paper. P.z. 1475/36 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated 193 . Rec. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee PERSIAN GULF. Question of appointment of Royal Air Force Intelligence Officer with headquarters at Bahrein to be posted to the Gulf. Under Secretary Secretary of State Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. Previous papers :— Please see the previous papers on this file, viz. P.5980/29 and 6569/29 about the question of appointing an R.A.F.liaison officer in the Gulf. That proposal ^ d fa 1929 but there has recently been a certain amount of discussion on the desirability of some kind of Intelligence Officer v/ho would collect information of a kind required specially for Service purposes ^'which he would incorporate in periodic report j&gt; and would work in with the Political Officers in the Gulf, particularly, one would assume, in respect of such places as Qatar, where the Air Force have got particular responsibilities in the way of defence—-- ^ ^ tCU A* f tAAJf^oU^f . We now have a copy of a letter dated 8th February from the Political Resident to the 3330 1000 12.34 Air/Air Officer Commanding 'but we have not got a copy of the letter to which it is a reply (I understand that the Air Ministry have not got one either). It is however possible to understand the scope of the proposal from Colonel Fowle’s letter. It will be seen that he is personally opposed to the scheme hut that he is prepared to acquiesce in it on certain conditions if necessary. It seems unnecessary for us to take any action at this stage. No doubt Colonel Fowle will discuss this question with the Foreign Department when he is at Delhi this month v 'fhTo Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... Itj, to, n 1m (fk PURSm GULF: Question of appointment of R.A.F, Liaison Officer to .work with the Political Resident. ^. JU, /»&gt; Copy to UEEH ►emiCAi coMMim^ Previous Papers 3287 2000 12.28 FOR INFORMATION. Please see previous submission on P. 5980/29 below, and Colonel Barrett’s letter of 11th September, from which it appears that the Air Officer Commanding, Iraq, has for the present dropped the question. The proposal was raised by Sir Hugh Trenchard and the Air Ministry with Colonel Biscoe recently. Colonel Bisco© informed them that he would not be prepared to agree to any arrangement on the lines originally suggested, but, after considerable discussion, Sir Hugh Trenchard, I understand, indicated that all he wanted was that there should be a liaison ofxic 3r, and that he would be prepared to fall m with any suggestion,tne Political Resident^ might make. They finally agreed tiiat a V compromise mi^ht be found the attachment of a special service officer to the Resident's staff/&lt;v staff, to work under his control and in his office. Full facilities would be given him for seeing all that went on, but he v/ould not be independent of the Resident. It is probable that an arrangement on these lines will be reached later. t i itjcai comwmti 2 8 OCT 1929A*-.- D.O. Ko. 429-3. V 1 ^ ■&gt; '+ Bear Acheson. Please refer to lay demi-official letter 1-To. 332-3 of 9th August last regarding the proposal to appoint a Royal Air Force liaison officer in the Gulf. Air Commodore Burnett has now informed me that in view of the points I have raised the Air Officer Commanding in Iraq will not press the matter, although at a later date circumstances may arise whicn would « make it desirable for the Royal Air Force to do so. Yours sincerely, Sd. C.C.J.Barrett. •J. G. Ache son, Esquire, C.I.E., Deputy Secretary (Foreign) to the Government of India,/iL' 4^ _ seen by sir a. hirtzel SEP 1929 Colonel Barrett makes out a conclusive case against the proposal, at any rate in present conditions. Colonel Biscoe f s views on it will be seen from his private letter of 21st September below.I enclose copies of certain demi-official correspondence which has taken place 'between me and Air Commodore Burnett, the Chief Staff Officer at Baghdad. I thought you would like to know about the proposal to appoint a Royal Air fforce Liaison officer in the Gulf and my objections to it. . Air A junior Royal/Force officer,probably with no experience of the East, could not help interfering in political affairs and sooner or later he would rouse every Political Agent in the Gulf and cause the Air Ministry and India Office to have diametrically opposed Gulf policies. Already the Senior Naval Officer v/rites long reports to the Admiralty, in which he occasionally criticises the Resident’s policy* In 1926, Colonel Prideaux had to write to the Senior Naval Officer, Captain Parry, to reprove him for acknowledging the succession of a Shaikh of Abu Dhabi, without reference to the Residency. Last April the Commander of the M Lupin M is said to have fined the Shaikh of Shargah Bs. 2000/- for a misdemeanour. The fine was levied by order of Sir Frederick Johnston, but comment shows how, since the Political Resident became immobilised through lack of a despatch vessel, the Navy have elbowed the Political service out of the Trucial Coast in general estimation. The Royal Air Force are very helpful when they stick to their job, but I do not welcome the idea of loot turning them loose in the Gulf. We would probably have demands for the bombing of Abu Dhabi or Ras al Khaimah, in fact another incident such as the Navy’s escapade at Dubai in 1912. J.G.Acheson, Esquire, C.I.E., Deputy Secretary (Foreign) to the Government of India,Simla. Yours sincerely, Sd. C*C.J.Barrett*Secret ir Extract from letter No.D.0.1/8/34, dated the 11th July 1929, from Air Commodore C.S.Burnett, C.B.,C.3.E., Chief of Staff, Air Headquarters, Iraq Command, Baghdad, to the Hon’hie Lieut. Colonel C.C.J.Barrett, C.S.I.,C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 1. The A.O.C. has just left for England to attend a conference and will probably be away five or six weeks. 2. He has asked me to write to you and get your opinion and advice with regard to putting an R.A.E.Officer at Bahrain or some such central place in the Persian Gulf. This officer’s duties would roughly be (a) To make all local arrangements with regard to petrol and oil supplies for the flying boats; (b) To make a coastal reconnaissance survey of the Arabian Coast such as will be required by the Plying Boat Plight in the future; (c) To be a liaison officer with your people and with the Arab Shaikhs as required to fulfil (a) and (b) above; (d) To collect tribal and other information of general interest and for the revision of the Gazetteer of the Persian l( Gulf and Handbook of Arabia, the latter publication particularly being inaccurate and out-of-date in many particulars; (e) Liaison with the S.N.O. Persian Gulf in all matters of mutual interest to the S.N.O. Persian Gulf and the Persian Gulf Plight. He would act under the direct orders of this Headquarters, any tours which he thought necessary to carry/out must have the prior sanction of the Resident to whom also he would furnish copies of vwffaiinra : reports for his information. 3. The above ?/ould be his chief duties and I should be glad t to get your remarks and what you think of it,unofficially, as of course the matter will have to be taken up later with the Air Ministry in order to get the necessary personnel and financial sanction.The Residency, Bushire, 9th August 1929. Bear Burnett, Please refer to your demi-official letter No.1/8/34 of 11th July. I do not think it necessary to detail a Royal Air i&lt;orce oiiicer to Bahrain or other place in the Gulf for the objects you mention. The local arrangements with regard to petrol and oil supplies for the flying boats can easily be made by Mespers in Bahrain, Xuwait or Muscat and by the Residency Agent*s man on the Trucial Coast. Could not the coastal reconnaissance survey be made by Howe during his flights? The more he makes of these the better, as the Arabs will come to regard them as a normal feature of existence on the coast like the visits of the Britisn. India mail and Royal Navy ships. I think a liaison officer is hardly necessary at present. As far as the Shaikhs are concerned it will only complicate masters. It is better for them to look to one British officer rather than to confuse them with two or three separate and independent authorities. Even at present we have the Senior Naval Officer reporting direct to the Admiralty. On the whole the system has worked better than might have been expected as the Senior Naval Officer is always an officer of experience, who is careful to work in Y*ith the Political authorities. There have however been occasional difficult situations in the past. If such have occurred when the Senior Naval Officer is a senior Captain of the Navy, there are likely to be serious clashes if you depute a Flight-Lieutenant or squadron Leader as your liaison officer. I doubt if the natureof his duties would j^retify the appointment of an officer of superior rank. . Already the^lgilitical Agent at Kuwait has complained to me about the presence there of a Special Service Officer when no active operations were in progress. The Shaikh of Kuwait also seized an opportunity for short-circuiting his Political Agent by applying to the Special Service Officer at Nasiriyah for certain equipment. I mention these two matters merely to show the difficulties that must arise if we have a Royal Air Force officer in the Gulf reporting direct to you free from the Residents control, but merely sending him copies of his reports. I have consulted the various Political Agents and all are willing to undertake the revision of the 'Handbook of Arabia' for their own area. It is work they ought to do and I think that with the information they acquire in their nnr'TTng ordinary way of business, they would be in a better position to make a good job of it than any other. I had an interesting twelve days’ trip down to the Trucial Coast. I was sorry to miss Howe at Bahrain, but I had been long absent from Headquarters and had moreover to consider the programme of the Senior Naval Officer, who was kindly carrying me in 'Triad'. Prior has put off his recess for a bit in order to render any assistance he can to Howe on his return flight. Yours sincerely, Sd. C.C.J.Barrett. Air Commodore C.S.Burnett, C.B., C.B.E., Chief of Staff, Air Headquarters, Iraq Command, Baghdad.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3653</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3653</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/77 'Appointment of an RAF Liaison Officer for the Persian Gulf, with headquarters at Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T10:50:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (27 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 29; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the proposed appointment of a Royal Air Force (RAF) Liaison Officer for the Persian Gulf, with headquarters at Bahrain, 1935-1937.The file is composed of correspondence between the Air Ministry, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, and the Air Headquarters for the British Forces in Iraq.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>RAF, Iraq Command</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Forces in Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Employment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>