<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000181_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T05:29:03.916Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">'V' Z.2664/38. i India Office, Whitehall, London, S .T r . 1, 14th April, 1938. Muscat Treaty With reference to the Secretary of State's telegram of to-day on the subject of the Treaty discussions with the Sultan of Muscat, I am desired to forward for information (1) a copy of the provisional draft treaty, prepared J.n the light of the Government of Inaia's views and in consultation with the Foreign Office and the Board of Trade, which was offered to His Highness on the 30th March, (2) notes of the five meetings at which the draft was discussed with the Sultan, and (3) a copy of the letter sent to His Highness on the 11th April, enclosing a revision of the provisional draft, E, The provisional draft proceeds on the basis that the Sultan's fiscal powers in relation to British subjects are limited only by the obligation to give both national and most favoured nation treatment. 'National' treatment has been introduced in Article 3 of the provisional draft, and to this Article the Sultan has taken no exception, prey Metcalfe, KCIE., CSX., MYO, ,\ l n / jcretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department.3 In preparing the draft a number of drafting amendments have been made in the text of the existing treaty and in other ways it has been moaernised as far as seems desirable, NCL/*' \ S - 3. Of the Sultan's draft, Articles 7 (Shipping dues), 11 (deserters from Ships) and 17 (municipal taxes) have been omitted, while Article 19 (expulsion of British subjects) has been withdrawn by the Sultan himself. It is not considered necessary to retain provisions similar to those of his Articles 11 and 17, but an Article relating to shipping dues is desirable, as otherwise the Sultan will be completely free in the matter, subject to the provisions of Article 3 of the revised provisional draft. 4. Article-8 of the revised provisional draft (import and export restrictions) has been inserted in substitution for Article 4(2) of the Sultan's draft. 5. The Articles of the existing Treaty dealing with jurisdiction have been considerably rearafted, on the basis that, while Jurisdiction is reserved in civil and criminal cases against British subjects, ex-territorial rights generally are surrendered. In the absence of Omani legislation applicable to the case the British Consul would be free to apply whatever laws His Majesty's Government desired/u 3. desired in the exercise of his jurisdiction over British subjects. But, since it would follow that in the absence of any other provision the Sultan would be free to legislate for British subjects in all matters, an Article {Article 14 of the provisional draft), to which special importance is attached, has been introduced to ensure to us a right of control over the application of Omani laws and regulations to British subjects. Much difficulty is being experienced in securing the Sultan's acceptance of this Article. It is gathered that he would not wish to interfere with the application to British subjects in the Consults Court of the body of law applied miuer the existing Order in Council. What particularly concerns him is his desire to have an unrestricted right to tax all residents in his territories and to avoid any deWy in the imposition of taxes and particularly of customs duties. The original draft has been amended in the hope of making it more acceptable to him in this respect. 6. Among other points under discussion in the provisional draft are the following:- (a) Article 1; Definition of Nationals of His Majesty as extending to all British protected persons. Here Fowle sees no objection (subject to the Government of India 1 s/India^ views) to excluding the subjects of the Gulf States^ and the Colonial Office are .toeing consulted in respect of the Aden Protectorate and Zanzibar. (b) The provision inserted in Article S (1) relating to the movements of British subjects in Muscat ? put forward on Fowle 1 s suggestion, as a substitute for the Sultan's addition in Article 4 paragraph 1 of his draft., with the object of preventing the movements of British traders from being hampered by the imposition of unreasonaole restrictions bj the Sultanate authorities. (c) Monopolies^ Article S, (2) and (3), based on Article 14 of the Anglo Siamese Treaty of 19£5 has been proposed to the Sultan in place of Article 4 (3) of his draft, but so far it has been impossible to secure his agreement. (d) Restriction on the sale etc. of immovable property. The Sultan insists on retaining Article 5 of his draft. (e) Article 6 (6). The Sultan insists that 'weighing'f fees should be included, asserting that all the fees here j mentioned have been levied for years past, having been introduced with the concurrence of the Political Agent when the Muscat customs arrangements were reorganised in 1920, and therefore that the exclusion of weighing fees would/would deprive him of a recognised right. His assertion cannot 'be checked here in the absence of detailed information regarding the reorganisation of the Muscat customs. (f) Article 6 (2). The Sultan objects to the draft, partly on the grouna that 'wholesale' is, according to him, a meaningless term in relation to Muscat where all the trade is retail, partly for 'the imaginary reason that the final worcis of the paragraph would deprive him of part of his existing revenue. He wishes to retain the phrase employed in his own Article 8, paragraph 2. 7. There is not sufficient time to obtain the Government of India T s views on these and other points before the discussions with the Sultan are continued next week. It has however been maae clear to him that the discussions are informal and that the provisional draft is subject to the further views of His Majesty's Government ana of the Government of India. 8. A copy of this letter and its enclosures is being given to Fowle and copies sent to Weightman and Watts,f* tfi,* So Item ' 1 ■ muscat treaty * ProTisional draft* Preamble. His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and tlie British. Dominions beyond the Seas, Shiperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, desiring to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations which now subsist between them and to promote and extend their commercial relations by the conclusion of a new treaty to replace the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and navigation signed at Muscat on the 19th March, 1891, which terminates on the 11th February, 1939, Have accordingly appointed as their plenipotentiaries:- His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond' the Seas, Smperor of India (hereinafter referred to as His Maj esty): For Great Britain and Northern Ireland: For India: The Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies (hereinafter referred to/&lt; 1% to as the Sultan), in person; Who have agreed as follows: -* Articl e I. For the purposes of the present Treaty - (i) The terrr: 'territories of His Majesty' or 'territories of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean the United Kingdom of G-reat Britain and 'M or them Ireland and India, and any territories to which the present Treaty applies by reason of extensions under Article or accessions under Article : and the term 'territories of the Sultan' or 'territories of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean Muscat and Oman and their Dependencies. (ii) The term 'nationals of His Majesty' or the term 'nationals of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to.His Majesty shall mean all subjects of His Majesty and all persons under His protection, wherever domiciled: and the term 'nationals of the Sultan' or the term, 'nationals of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean all the Sultan's subjects, wherever domiciled. For the purposes of Articles the word 'nationals'/(0 'nationals' shall be deemed to include corporate bodies created under the law of the territories of the High Contracting Party concerned. (iii) The term 'British vessels' or 'vessels of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean all ships registered under the law of any part of the British Commonwealth of Hation§ including any territory under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty: and the term 'Muscati vessels' or 'vessels of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean all ships entitled to fly the flag of the Sultan. (iv) The term 'British aircraft' or 'aircraft of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean all aircraft registered under the law of any part of the British Commonwealth of Nations, including any territory under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty. (v) The terms 'most favoured nation' or 'foreign country' shall mean in relation to His Majesty any country or territory not under the. sovereignty, suzerainty, protection or mandate of His Majesty.II Arti cle B, (1) There shall be perfect freedom of commerce and navigation Ijetween the territories of the High Contracting Parties. Each High Contracting Party shall allow the nationals of the other to enter all ports ? creeks and rivers with their vessels and cargoes, also to travel, reside and pursue commerce and trade, whether wholesale or retail, in the territories of the other, except that special permission shall have to he obtained before entering those places in the hinterland of Muscat which owing to c onditions of lawlessness and insecurity shall have been notified unsafe by the local authorities, and provided, as regards nationals of the Sultan, that they satisfy and observe the conditions and regulations applicable in the territories of His Majesty to the entry, travel, residence and departure of all foreigners. Further, each High Contracting Party shall allow in his territories subject to the provisions of Article 8, the nationals of the other, whether personally or by agent, freely to bargain for,buy,barter and sell goods, articles of import,or. local production, whether intended for local sale, use or consumption, or for export. (2)7-Article S (contd .) / (2) The Sultan undertakes to inform His Majesty of his intention to establish in his territories any monopoly, with a yiew to securing that the monopoly shall interfere as little as possible with the trade between the territories of the High Contracting Parties, or with trade carried on in his territories by the nationals of His Majesty. (3) In the event of the establishment of any such monopoly the question of the payment of compensation and the amount; if any, of such compensation which shall be paid to the nationals of His Majesty established in the territories of the Sultan shall be settled by mutual agreement by the High Contracting Parties or by arbitration.li A rti cle 3, , Nationals of His Majesty shall enjoy throughout the territories of the Sultan with respect to cornmerce, shipping and the exercise of trade, as in every other respect, all the rights, privileges, immunities, advantages and protection, of whatsoever nature, which are or hereafter may he enjoyed by or accorded to the subjects of the Sultan or to the subjects or citizens of any other foreign country. They shall more especially not be liable to «ther or more onerous Taxes, duties, imposts, restrictions or obligations of whatever description, than those to which the subjects of the Sultan or the subjects or citizens of any other foreign country now are or hereafter may be subjected. In all that relates to navigation and the treatment of shipping the Sultan undertakes to treat British vessels not less favourably in any respect than his own vessels or the vessels of any other foreign country. The provisions of this Article relating to vessels apply also to the passengers and cargoes carried therein.Ik Articl e k. Nationals of Kis Majesty shall 'be permitted? throughout the territories of the Sultan? to hire or to acquire hy gift? purchase? intestate succession? or under will, or any other legal manner? land? houses? and property of every description? whether moveable or immoveable, to possess the'same; • and freely to dispose thereof by sale? barter? donation or otherwise on the same conditions as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of the most favoured foreign c ount ry.Art icle 3 * (1) Articles produced or man-ofactured in the territories of His Majesty imported into the territories of the Sultan? from whatever place arriving^, shall not 'be subjected to other or higher duties or charges than those paid on the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No other or higher duties or charges shall 'be imposed in the territories of the Sultan on the exportation of any article to the territories of His Majesty than such as are or may be payable on the exportation of the like article to any other foreign country. (3) The import duties leviable in the territories of the Sultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty the King and Emperor? and on goods imported by British subjects into the said territories? shall be paid at the port or other place in the Sultan T s territories where the goods are first imported? and on payment thereof such goods shall thereafter be exempt within the said territories from all other Customs duties. {k) There shall, howeve-r? be exempted from payment of customs duty the fo11owing ? namely:- (a)/Article 3 • (continued). (a) All goods and merchandise which, bein , destined and manifested for a foreign country5 are transhipped from one vessel or aircraft to another in any of the ports or airports of the Sultan or which have 'been for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the 3ultan t s custom houses to await the arrival of a. vessel or aircraft in which to be reshipped abroad. But goods and merchandise so landed shall be exempted only provided that the consignee or his agent shall have, on the arrival of the ship or aircraft, handed over the said goods to be kept under Customs Seal, and declared them as landed for transhipment, designating at the same time the foreign place of destination and also provided that the said goods are actually shipped for the said foreign country as originally declared, within a period not exceeding three months after their first landing and without having in the interval changed owners and' that all other customs Charges are paid before they are reshipped. (b) All goods and merchandise which, not/Article 3• (continued). not 'being consigned to the territories of the Sultan have 'been inadvertently landeds 'provided that such goods are reshipped y /ithin a month of being so landed and transported abroad. Should, however? such goods or merchandisey here spoken of, be opened or removed from the custody of the Castoms authorities, the full duty shall then be payable on the same. In both cases all customs charges are to be paid before the goods are reshipped or transported abroad. (c) Goals? fuel and oil? Naval and Royal Air Force provisions? Stores and fittings the property of His Majesty landed in the territories of the Sultan for the use of the ships of His Majesty's Navy and the aircraft of the Royal _.ir Porce. Duty shall? however? be payable if any of the goods thus exempted are sold or otherwise disposed of in the local markets. (d)/It Article o (co n t d,) (d) Al 1 goods and merchand.ise transhipped or landed, for the repair of damage caused 'by stress of weather or fiisasters at sea or in the air, provided the cargo so discharged shall 'be re shipped and taken awa^r within a period of three months from the elate of the original landing after all customs charges have been paid. In the cases referred to in sub-paragraphs (a) to (d) above customs formalities in respect of landing, examination, clearance and shipment of goo^s are to be observed. (5) All goods remaining uncleared in the Sultan^ customs houses after six months f rom the date of their original landing shall be disposed ox by the Sultan's customs authorities by a public auction after notifying the steamer agents concerned-. Their sale proceeds, after payment, of the. auctioneering charges, customs duty and charges shall be kept in deposit for a period of one year and refunded to the owner if the, claim is established during this period, after which no claim shall be entertained, (6) In this Article the words 'customs charges' shall mean charges other than customs duties and shall include/Article 5 (o o ntcU ) include landing, wharfage, ground rent, supervision and overtime fees, it being understood that all such fees will 'be assessed on a reasonable scale in strict relation to the cost of the services thej^ are intended to cover.^0 Article 6 . (1) All customs duties leviable in the territories of the Sultan shall be paid in cash and not in kind* (2) The value of the merchandise, goods or produce on which duty is to he levied shall 'be fixed according to their ready money wholesale market price at Muscat, less the customs duties payable on importation. (3) The Sultan* s Gove rnment sha11 have the right to fix valuations for customs purposes of any descriptions of goods or produce for any period provided such valuations are fixed by a tariff board appointed by the Sultan consisting of equal numbers of the Sultan's subjects and British subjects representing the merchant Community and presided over by the Director of the Sultan's Customs. (k) In the event of any dispute arising between a British subject and the Customs House Authorities regarding the value of any goods, this shall be determined by reference to two experts, each party nominating one, and the value so ascertained shall be decisive. Should however these experts not be able to agree, they shall choose an umpire, whose decision is to be considered a^ final.Artic l e 7 . Internal duties, taxes or fees levied v/itiiin the territories of either High Contracting Party for the benefit of the State, or of organs of local or municipal government, on or in connection with goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the other Party/ shall not he other or greater than the duties, taxes or fees levied in similar circumstances on or in connection with goo^s of national or any other foreign origin.' I 1 p- Art icle (1) I n T o prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the importation into the territories of the Sultan of any article, from whatever place arriving, produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty the King and Emperor which shall not equally extend to the importation of the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the exportation of any article from the territories of the Sultan to the territories of His Majesty the King and Emperor which shall not equally extend to the exportation of the like articles to any other foreign country. (3) Exceptions to the general rule laid down in the foregoing paragraphs may be made only in the case of (a) prohibitions or restrictions imposed in the interests of public security; (b) prohibitions or restrictions regarding traffic in arms, ammunition and implements of war, or,in exceptional circumstances, all other military supplies;2-0 Art. V (Contd.) (c) prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of public healthy (d) prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of animals or plants, including protection against diseases, degeneration or extinction, as well as measures taken against harmful seeds, plants and animals.The Sultan engages by the present Treaty to prcyide and give orders to his officials that the movements of goods in transit shall not he obstructed or delayed in a vexatious manner by unnecessary Customs formalities and Regulations, and that every facility will be given for their transport.Article IQ. ^ Either of the two High Contracting Parties may appoint consuls to reside in the territories of the other, subject to the consent and approval of the other as regards the persons so appointed and the places at which they reside. Such consuls shall at all times be accorded in the country in which they reside treatment and privileges not less favourable than consuls of the most favoured foreign country. Each of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his own subjects to be ax^pointed to Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party, provided always that the person so appointed shall not begin to act without the previous approbation of the Sovereign whose subjects they may be.Arti cl e 11 . (1) British vessels or aircraft coming to the territories of the Sultan^ in distress^ shall receive from the local authorities all necessary aid to enable them to re-victual and refit so as to proceed on their voyage or journey. (2) Should a British vessel or aircraft 'be wrecked off the coast of or in the Sultanas territories, the authorities of the Sultan shall render all assistance in their power to save the vessel or aircraft, its cargo and those on hoard; they shall also give aid and protection to persons saved, and shall assist them in reaching the nearest British Consulate- they shall further take every possible care that the goods so recovered are safely stored, and kept for the purpose of 'being handed over to the owner, Captain, Agent of the ship or aircraft, or British Consul, subject always to rights of salvage. (3) The Sultan T s authorities shall further see that the British Consulate is as soon as possible informed of such disaster having occurred, (4) Should a British vessel or aircraft, wrecked on the coast of or in the Sultan^ territories be plundered/■2. Article 11 (Gont.) plundered ? the authorities of the Sultan shall, as soon as they come to know thereof 5 roider prompt assistance and take all possible measures to pursue and punish the rolooersj and recover the stolen property. Likewise 9 should a vessel or aircraft of the Sultan, or of one of his nationals^ enter a British port in distr.ess , or 'be wrecked off the coast of or in His Majesty^ territories, the like help and assistance shall he rendered hy the British authorities.Article 12 . 1. The consular authorities and courts of His ivaajesty in the territorico of the Sultan shall try and determine (i) all criminal charges against nationals of His Majesty; (ii) all civil suits in which nationals of His Majesty are defend ants ; (iii) all 'bankruptcy cases in which the bankrupt or the person whom it is sought to make bankrupt is a national of His Majesty; (iv) all proceedings connected with administration of the estate of a deceased national of His Majesty? and all questions of personal status where the person whose status is in question is a national of His Majesty? always provided that where such person is a Moslem the consular authorities may remit the case for decision 'by a Moslem religious court of the Sultan on such conditions as they may determine. 2. All criminal or civil cases in which a national of His Majesty is complainant or plaintiff and the accused or defendant is a national of the Sultan or a national of a third country/I Article 13 (Contd.) country shall be tried and determined by a court of the Sultan. In any such case notice shall be given, and an opportunity to attend the hearing and be present at the final decision afforded, to the consul of His Majesty or his substitute and the proceedings and final decision shall not be valid unless such notice and opportunity has been given. 3, A national of His Majesty shall not be arrested or his property seized, nor his house, office, warehouse or other premises occupied by him entered and searched Y /ithout his consent, by an officer of the Sultan save under an order signed by the consul of His Majesty. Any national of His Majesty arrested and any property of a national of His Majesty seized shall be in the custody of the consul of His Majesty; always provided that in case of necessity for the prevention of breaches of the peace the authorities of the Sultan may arrest a national of His Majesty or take charge of his property without such order, but in this case the person arrested and any property seized shall be handed over without delay to the consul of His Majesty. 4-/Article 12. (ContdQ . U. -i-h© Sultan may recj_uGSt th.6 consular authorities of His Majesty to -expel from his territories any national of His Majesty the King and Emperor on the ground that his actions and 'behaviour have 'been such as to Warrant the conclusion that his continued presence there is harmful to the interests of the Sultanate 9 and the consular authorities of His Majesty shall investigate the matter and shall order his expulsion if satisfactory evidence of such action or 'behaviour is produced.Art i cle 1 3 In the exercise of their respective jurisdictions under It- paragraphs (1) and (2) of Article,.^', the authorities of the Sultan and the consular authorities of His Majesty shall afford every aid and facility for satisfaction of the rightful claims of the nationals of one High Contracting Party against nationals of the other.Article 14 . In order that legislation of the Sultan, whether for the imposi t ion of taxes or duties or otherwise, shall aj.ply to and 'be enforceable 'by the consular authorities of His Majesty against nationals of His Majesty, it is necessary that the text of the law or regulation shall have 'been exhibited 'by the consul of His Majesty at his office for' a period of not less than 10 days unless in a case of urgency the consul decides to accept a shorter period. The consul of His Majesty shall, on the request of the Sultan, exhibit the text of such laws or regalations without delay, except in cases where the consul submits to the Sultan serious reasons for the non-application of such legislation to nationals of His Majesty in whole or in part. The Sultan will in this event consider the withdrawal of his request or a modification of the law or regulation in question or the submission of the matter to His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom.Article l ':3 o With the consent of the Sultan iv '3 the provisions of Articles &gt;5 and y* shall apply to the nationals of any third State in the same way as they apply to nationals of His Majesty if the G-overnment of that State had requested His Majesty, 1 s G-overnment in the United Kingdom that this jurisdiction over its nationals should 'be exercised 'by the consular authorities of His(V^T Ar ticle 16 ^ The provisions of Articles il? \Y ^and shall apply to nationals of the Sultan or a third State who are in the regular service of the consul of His Majesty as if they were nationals of His Majesty provided that, if any such person should 'be charged with a crime or a serious offence, and sufficient evidence is produced to the consul to satisfy him that the charge should he proceeded with, the consul will discharge such person from his service so as to allow the charge to 'be tried by the authorities of the Sultan,Article 17 . Nationals of the two High Contracting Parties shall, within the territories of each other, enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all forms of religion, provided that such exercise does not wound or outrage the religious susceptibilities of the country in which it is proposed to 'be practised, and the right to 'build edifices for religous worship in places specified for the purpose 'by local authorities. Nothing shall 'be done 'by either High Contracting Party that may disturb existing places of worship 'belonging to nationals of the other.3^ Articl e 18, All the provisions of the present Treaty providing for the grant of the treatment accor'ded to the most favoured foreign country shall 'be interpreted as meaning that such treatment shall he accorded immediately and unconditionally5 without request or compensation.Article 19 , (l) His Majesty may through his Consular Officer at Muscat give notice of his desire that the present Treaty shall extend to any of his colonies., overseas territories or protectorates, or to any mandated territory in respect of which the mandate is exorcised 'by his Government in the United Kingdom, and the Treaty shall he extended to any territory specified in such notice as from the date thereof. (2) After the expiry of a period of two years from the coming into force of the present Treaty, either High Contracting Party may, 'by giving twelve months 1 notice, terminate the application of the present Treaty to any territory to which it has 'been extended under the provisions of the preceding paragraph.Article 20 . (l) The High Contracting Parties agree that His Majesty n£jp 'by notification given through his Consular Officer at Muscat accede to the present Treaty in respect of any Member of the British Commonwealth of Nations whose G-overnment may desire that such accession should 'be effected. Any such accession shall take effect as from the date of notification thereof. (2) After the expiry of a period of two years from the coming into force of the present Treaty either High Contracting Party may ? 'by giving twelve months 1 notice,, terminate the Treaty as regards any country in respect of which notification of accession has 'been given under paragraph (l) of this Article. (3) Any notification made under paragraph (l) of this Article may include any dependency or mandated territory administered hy the Government of the country in respect of which notification of accession is given; and any notice given under paragraph (2) of this Article shall 'be applicahle to any such dependency or mandated territory which was included in such notification of accession.7, G &lt;v f A rticle 21 &gt; (1) So long as in any territory referred to in Articles 19 and 20, to which the provisions of the present Treaty are not applicable, either hy virtue of accession under Article 20 or 'by notice of extension under Article 19? goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the Sultan are accorded treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country? goods produced or manufactured in such territory shall likewise enjoy in the territories of the Sultan treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) Goods? the produce or manufacture of Palestine? shall not be debarred from the benefits of this Article by reason only of any special customs privileges which may be accorded in Palestine to goods the produce or manufacture of any State the territory of which in 1914 was wholly Included in Asiatic Turkey or Arabia.Li- 0 Article 22 . (1) The present Treaty has heen executed in guadruplicate, two copies being written in English and two in Arabic. These are understood to be of similar import and signification; in the event? however? of doubt hereafter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations? the English text shall be considered decisive. (2) The present Treaty shall be ratified? and ratifications shall be exchanged at (Muscat). It shall come into force on the 11th day of February? 1939f or on the date of exchange of ratifications? Y /hichever date be the later.■A rticle 23 « After the lapse of twelve years from the date on which the Treaty shall come into force ? and on twelve months' notice given 'by either party, this Treaty shall 'be subject to termination. In witness whereof . . . on behalf of His Hajesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British -Dominions 'beyond the Seas, fimperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, on his own behalf, have signed the same and affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat, this • day of 193 ? corresponding to the of the year ..... Hejira. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies./t/V lr MUSCAT TREATY. Note of first meeting xrlth the Sultan ? 30th March at The Dorchester Hotel. Present- His Highness the Sultan., The Political Resident (Sir Trenchard Powle) 3 and Mr. J .p .Gibson (India Office). Sir Trenchard Fowle began by saying that His Majesty's Government welcomed, as he understood the Sultan did also, the opportunity afforded by the presence of His Highness in London to have an informal discussion of the Sultan's proposals for the revision of the 1891 Treaty and to explain to His Highness the conclusions which His Majesty's Government had provisionally reached in the light of the views expressed by the Government of India. The matter had been discussed that very morning by the Departments concerned, and, while an important part of the Treaty proposals had still to be examined by them, he. was able to give the Sultan His Majesty's Government's provisional draft of the .earlier articles of the Treaty. Sir Trenchard then gave His Highness a draft, as in the copy attached herewith, of the Preamble and Articles 1 to 10. He explained that there was no question of the Sultan committing himself at this stage and that he proposed, after going through the draft and explaining the variations from the Sultan's proposals, to leave it to be considered by His Highness at his leisure. He then proceeded to explain the draft Article by Article. The Sultan's comments were as follows Preamble : no comment. Article l(i): For the phrase 'Muscat and Oman and Their/2. Their Dependencies' His Highness said he v/as inclined to prefer simply 'Oman'. Articl e l(ii) : The phrase ' ,r al 1 persons under His MaDesty T s protection puzzled His Highness Y /ho remarked that it was more extensive than the phrase in the existing Treaty (which was limited to the subjects of the Indian States) and said tha^t he would wish to have a definition of it 3 as otherwise he might he at a loss to know whether he or His Majesty's Consul was entitled to have jurisdiction over a particular person. With regard to the definition of the Sultan's subjects His Highness thought it should cover all persons under his jurisdiction? i.e. in addition to his own subjects, foreigners in his territory other than British subjects and British protected persons. It was explained to him that the term 'Nationals of His Ivlajesty'' did not include foreigners who being in British territory were subject to His Majesty's jurisdiction. The Sultan apparently thought that some such phrase was needed to balance the reference to persons under His Majesty's protection. He wished to consider the extension of the term 'Nationals' to cover 'corporate bodies'. Article l(iii) - For 'Muscati' His Highness preferred 'Omani'? and wished the definition of his ships to read 'all ships registered by the Oman Government and entitled to fly the flag of the Sultan'. Article Kiv)^ His Highness thought it would be desirable to insert a definition of Omani Aircraft. Article 2(1): His Highness pressed for the omission of the words 'in the hinterland of Muscat'. For/LfW- 3. For the words 'of all foreigners' at the end of the second sentence he preferred a reference to the most favoured nation ('of the nationals of the most favoured foreign country'). Article 2 (2) and (3 ): His Highness wished to think over these provisions regarding monopolies (particularly with reference to the question of compensation) and desired to know whether they occurred in other Treaties. He was informed that this was so and that the provisions were in fact based on those in a recent Treaty with His Made sty's G-overnment. Article 5 (Lj.)('b): His Highness wished to consider whether the words ' manifested and consigned' which appeared in his draft ought to 'be retained. Article 3 (3) » For the proposed 'Six' months at the beginning of this paragraph His Highness preferred to retain the 'three' months of his draft explaining that warehousing space in Muscat was very limited and that embarrassment might be caused if goods were allowed to lie in it for so long as six months. Article 3 (6) ^ His Highness promised to give an explanation of the terms used in his draft ? which had been supplied to him by his director of Customs. He i i said that all these fees ? including weighing charges, had been levied at Muscat for many years past by an arrangement approved by the Political Agent. To cut out an item like 'weighing charges' would therefore be to deprive him of a right which he already enjoyed. Sir Trenchard observed that presumably His Highness referred to the reorganisation of the Muscat Customs by an Officer of the Indian Customs Service in about 1920/k. 1920. His Highness confirmed tiiis. Article 6 (2) : His Highness wished to omit the word 'wholesale', explaining that it had no meaning in Muscat, where all the trade was retail trade, the merchants baying wholesale in India and selling in small quantities in Muscat. Article 7 ° His Highness wished to consider this further. Article 8 (3) • His Highness wished to consider this 'exceptions' paragraph further. Apart from the ahove comments His Highness raised no otgection to Articles 1 to 10 on his first reading of them. It was arranged that the next meeting should 'be held on Friday, 1st April at p »m.MUSCAT TREATY . Note of second meeting with the Sultan; 1st April, Present; H.H.the Sultan, Sir Trenchard Fowle and Mr. J.P.G-ibson, The remaining Articles of the provisional redraft of the Treaty were given to the Sultan (as in the copy attached) and were briefly explained to him. Article 11 . His Highness suggested the insertion of the word tf possible ,? 'before 'aid' or ^assistance' in paragraphs (l) and (2). Article 12 (2) , Although it was pointed out to His Highness that there was nothing in this paragraph to fetter his jurisdiction he objected to the inclusion of the second sentence unless accompanied by a reciprocal provision for the attendance of a representative of His Highness at the hearing by the British Consul of proceedings instituted againo-t a British subject one of his subjects. He said that it would always be open to a British subject who thought he had been unjustly treated to appeal to the British Consul to make representations on his behalf. Article 12 (4) . His Highness objected to the latter part of this paragraph, stating that he would not ask for the expulsion of a British subject without good reason and that his request ought to be accepted without being subjected to investigation by the British Consul Article 15 . His Highness wished to insert the word 'possible' before 'aid'. Article 14 . His Highness took exception to the second and third sentences, which he said would put him in an awkward position because they differentiated too much in favour/r- w Sir T.Powle )inted out it he did | think that delay was 3 to 111 had been Lting for 3 list of ses and Las from 3 Muscat fernment. as favour of British subjects* He ?:as anxious to give equality of treatmentj 'but those provisions v .oulcl make it impossible for him to anticipate that a neu tax v /ould apply to all alike, and if the procedure contemplated in the last sentence were carried out years mi^ht elapse before taxes could be imposed on British subjects. His experience v /ith regard to the introduction of municipal taxation did not encourage him to think that the delay entailed by the procedure would be only negligible. 5 Article 15 . His Highness would prefer the omission of this Article 9 w r hich he said would put him in an awkward position notwithstanding that no effect could be given to it without his consent. Article 16. His Highness wished to consider this further, Article 17. His Highness had no comments. Article 18 . His Highness could not understand the last four words. (it will be explained to him that these words only mean that most-favoured-nation treatment must be extended to British subjects without waiting for any request for it on their part and without making it conditional on some counter-consideration to be given by them.). Articles 19-21 . His Highness desired to consider these further. There was not time to explain them in detail, but he was told that they were common form in treaties now made by H, M, G, Article 22 , His Highness appeared disappointed at the provision that the Treaty would not come into force before next February, He v/as informed that it arose from the circumstance/u 3. circumstance that certain Dominions were a party to the existing treaty^ and that, if it v /ere proposed to terminate the present treaty before the end of the period for which it was extended consultation with the Dominions concerned would he necessary and would prohably entail such delay as might in any case prevent the new Treaty from coming into force 'before next February. It was arranged that the next meeting should 'be held on Wednesday morning, 6th April./ ..Muscat Treaty. Note of third meeting y /ith His Highness the Sultan, 7th April. Present His Highness, Sir T.Fowle, and Mr.Gibson. It was suggested, and His Highness agreed, that the most convenient plan to those concerned for the conduct of the discussion after the 11th April would be for His Highness to go to Paris, as arranged, on the 12th April, spend a week there and return to London on the 19th or 20th April. Sir T. Fowls said he would in the circumstances postpone his departure until the 27th April. The draft Treaty previously left with His Highness was then taken up and the following Articles were discussed: A rt.1; (i) For the final words His.Highness said he definitely preferred 'Oman and its Dependencies', omitting the reference to Muscat. (ii) His Highness took strong exception to the inclusion in the definition of 'British protected persons' for the purposes of the Treaty of the natives of the territories in Arabia under His Majesty's protection, particularly the natives of Koweit, Bahrein, Qatar, the Trucial Coast and the Aden Protectorate. About Palestine he was not sure.' He felt that it would be inconsistent with his position as an independent Arab Ruler if the Arabs of the neighbouring territories were withdrawn from his jurisdiction. He was not satisfied with the explanation that His Majesty's Government were bound to give to the natives of the territories named above the same protection in foreign countries as would be given to British subjects. As regards corporate bodies His Highness was told that this definition was common form and was essential in a commercial treaty. Despite the explanations given he still wished// b '° 2. wishad to think the matter over and aslced to be supplied with a written explanation of the meaning and effect of the phrase. He was told that the Board of Trade would be asked to supply this. In (iii) (iv) and ( y ) His Highness again represented that territory under the pr otection of His Majesty should not include the territories of the Arab States under His Majesty's protection. In (iii) His Majesty objected to the phrase, ships registered 'under the law of any part of the British Commonwealth &amp;c.' f His objection appeared to be that it might be possible for a Muscati to secure for his dhow the treatment accorded to British ships by having the dhow given through the British Consul a registration, e.g. in Australia or Canada. He suggested the substitution of the phrase - registered 'in the territories of His Majesty'. The real objection to this amendment (that in virtue of the definition of 'territories' it would exclude from the definition of British ships ships registered in the Dominions which do not accede to the Treaty) was not explained to His Highness but he was told that his fears were unfounded, that it was believed that British law would require the owner of the ship to be domiciled {or if a ccmpany, registered) in the territory in question, and that the phrase in the draft was common form. He asked that here also he might be given an explanation in writing and was promised that this too would be sought from, the Board of Trade. Article 2 (l); His Highness pressed his previous objections to the insertion of the words 'in the hinterland of Muscat'. He also wished to delete the word ' lawlessness ' and the reference to notificatio n. He said that Indian trader s were settled at various ports in Oman and he had no wi sh/wish to turn them out. But difficulty might arise when a trader wished to go to some other place in his territory which Indian traders did not frequent; he might not be in a position to protect such persons and yet would be held responsible by His Majesty*s GoYernment if anything happened to them. After much discussion he said he would not object If an arrangement was made by which an Indian trader, wishing to move to some other place in Oman, should be required to inform the local authorities, who might in certain cases think fit to notify him that owing to conditions of insecurity the place proposed to be visited was unsafe, and if it was understood that no responsibility for the person's safety attached to the Sultan's Government if, notwithstanding the notification, he should proceed to carry out his proposed visit. The Sultan drew attention to the phrase regarding the conditions and regulations applicable to his nationals when visiting the territories of His Majesty and claimed that he should not be denied any right of controlling the movements of British subjects within his territory, where conditions were much more insecure. (2) and (3): Hig Highness complained, almost bitterly, that these paragraphs about monopolies would leave him no free hand. He was not interested in an offer to make them reciprocal, as he had no trading interests likely to be affected by British monopolies. Only about a third of Muscat trade was in the hands of British Indian traders. His own people would therefore be proportionately more affected than British subjects by the creation of monopolies. He was, however, very anxious to avoid disturbing trade; on the contrary he wished to see trade between India and Muscat increase. It was represented to him that by the present draft His Majesty's Government were making a considerable advance/4. 6'^ advance in that they were withdrawing the existing prohibition on monopolies ana were anxious to insert the r&gt; present paragraphs only as a safeguard against any serious disturbance of trade or of the interests of British traders which might result from the exercise of the Sultan^ freedom to create monopolies. For this reason they attached importance to the inclusion of these paragraphs. The Sultan gave no indication that he was prepared to accept the paragraphs, which were left over for further discussion. Article 3 . The Sultan has no objection. Article 4 . His Highness is anxious to draw a distinction between immoveable and moveable property, giving nuf.n. treatment in respect of both but national treatment only in respect of the latter. He would accept the Article if the last phrase ran, 'on the same conditions in respect of immoveable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the most favoured foreign country and in respect of moveable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of the most favoured foreign country'. Article 5, (4)(b ) For the phrase 'not being consigned', y/hich in the Sultan's draft was amended to 'not being manifested and consigned', he now wishes to substitute the phrase in Article 5 (4)(a), via. 'not being destined and manifested'. Article 5 (6 ) His Highness explained that 'landing fees' were^aid to the man who performs lighterage (which is given out on contract)♦ The word 'or' should be inserted between 'wharfage' and 'ground rent' , the latter being levied in the ports where there were no wharves, and either term being equivalent to demurrage or warehousing charges/5. charges. His Highness repeated that weighing ch arges we re intr odu ced in the reorganisation of the Muscat customs in 1920, and should be retained* 3rm Article 6 (2). His Highness said again that the t 'wholesale 5 ' is meaningless in Muscat, and argued that the qualification 'less the customs duties payable on importation' would in effect deprive him of a certain amount of revenue which he had derived in the past, and would only put some extra profit into the pockets of the traders who would continue to sell at the old retail price while paying less duty. He would not object to 'ready money retail market price' but otherwise preferred no change. His attention was drawn to the Indian practice as shown by sections 22 and 30 of the Indian Sea Customs Act, 1878, and he ?/as told thao the draft was an attempt to introduce a more rational procedure based on the recognised practice elsewhere. His Highness, however, insisted that what was a suitable system for highly developed conditions elsewhere was not appropriate to the conditions in Muscat, and he therefore wished things to go on as in the past. Article 6 (3). His Highness said that he now thought it unreasonable, seeing that Indian traders dealt v/ith only a third of Muscat trade, that the tariff board should consist ■ e ^ aa l numbers of the Sultan f s subjects and British subjects. He would prefer to amend his draft so that the numbers of either nationality were proportionate to their interest in Muscat trade. It was represented to him that it would be very difficult to give effect to such a provision and further that, under the Sultan's own proposal, the tariff board consisted of five persons so that British subjects were in a permanent minority. This did not seem to move His Highness who said he would think the matter over. Article ?, His Highness has no objection. Article 8,/ k6. Artlcle^g. : His Highness proposed the addition of the words 'or religious belief' at the end of para.3 (c), hut did not press it when it was explained to him that paragraphs (l) and (2) allowed him power to impose any prohibitions or restrictions on imports provided there was no discrimination against His Majesty's Government. He said that he was thinking of such a thing as alcoholic liquors. He agreed that whatever prohibition he put on the importation of alcoholic liquors would not extend to prohibiting such importation for the use of the British Consulate. His Highness suggested the omission of para.3 (b) dealing with traffic in arms, etc. His suggestion was noted for consideration. Article 9 : No objection. Article 10 : ITo objection. It was arranged that the next meeting should be held on Friday, 8th April, at 10 a.m.Note of fourth meeting with His Highness the Sultan, 8tli April. Present: His Highness, Sir T. Pov/le and Mr. Gibson. The following points were dealt with. Article 2(1): in place of the words lr except that, as regards nationals of His Majesty, special porraission shall have to 'be obtained before entering those places in the hinterland of Muscat which owing to conditions of lawlessness and insecurity shall have been notified unsafe by the local authorities 1 ' the Sultan, who objected to the phrase on several grounds, was prepared to accept something on the following lines:- 'Nationals of His Majesty shall, before proceeding from the place where they reside to another place in the territories of the Sultan, notify the local Omani authorities of the place in which they reside, and such authorities shall inform them whether the intendec destination is suitable for them to travel to or not. If the authorities in question notify the said nationals in writing that the intended destination is unsuitable, and if the said nationals persist in travelling to their destination, or should they fail to notify the local authorities of their intended movements, then they will proceed at their own risk ^/and if harm befall them no claim will lie against the Omani GovernmenUy 1 ' (the words in brackets to be omitted if it transpires that they are covered by 'at their own risk'). It was explained to His Highness that a provision of this kind was suggested in order to avert the risk of local authorities holding up/up the movements of Indian traders for quite insubstantial reasons. Article 2,(2) and His Highness asked whether his view would he met hy the substitution of some such phrase as 'Should the Sultan wish to establish any monopoly in his territory such monopoly will he arranged in such a way that it will not he detrimental to the trade of British suhjects.' He at once enquired who was to decide what was 'detrimental' and said he aid not wish to leave open any grounds for disputes hetvveen him and His Majesty's Government. T.'hen pressed to explain his objections to the present draft he said he had no intention of doing anything which might affect trade between Muscat and British territories, and therefore accepted the principle of the draft article down to the word 'parties': but he wished to be free to Institute a monopoly affecting trade Inside his i^errj-tories, and even here he had not in mind anything which would interfere with existing trade that in rice. What he was thinking of was circumstances m which, wishing to encourage the setting up of an ice plant, he should give a monopoly for the manufacture of ice; or, to take another example, a monopoly for the sale of beef. The paragraphs were left for further consideration in the light of His Highness's views. A-^igle § IALl The Sultan said he was willing to agree to the provision In the existing draft providing for equal numbers of Muscati and British Nationals on the board, under the presidency of the Director of the Sultan's Customs. Article/! 3. Article 12 . (l)(i) His Highness proposed the omission of the words 'and courts 1 '• (1)(iv) His Highness asked for^ and was promised, an explanation of 'questions of personal status'. (2) His Highness preferred in the first sentence 'The Courts' of the Sultan. He maintained his objection to the second sentence as a reflection on the standard of justice administered in his courts, and said he could not agree to it even if a reciprocal provision were inserted allowing an opportunity for his representative to be present in the Consul's court. If a British subject were dissatisfied with the decision of the Sultan's Coiu't he would have a right of appeal to the Sultan himself, (3) His Highness desired that in the latter part of the paragraph an insertion should bo made giving his authorities also the right of entry and search, i.e. that words similar to those in the beginning of the paragraph should be inserted in the latter part. (4) After considerable discussion directed to showing His Highness that the Consul hnd not a free hand for the deportation of British subjects and that some such provision as was proposed in our draft was necessary in our' view the Sultan desired the cancellation of the whole Article. He said he could not agree to any provision requiring the production, or taking, of evidence in connexion with a request of his for the expulsion of a British subject, and he therefore preferred to withdraw the Article suggested in his draft (Article 19). Article 14 , So far as this Article v/as discussed it became clear that the Sultan's objection, at least as stated by him on this occasion, Y /as to the delay which he might experience, as a result of the proposed procedure, in imposing taxes and above/■ ■above all in imposing customs duties. A delay of ten days after publication of the proposed duties yould, he said, enable traders to import goods from India before the duties -ere enforceable and so would deprive him of revenues. Further consideration of the Article v/as promised. Article 15 . As His Highness maintained his objection to this Article it was agreed that it should be omitted. Article 16, His Highness desired the insertion of a provision relating to nationals of His Majesty in the Sultan's service which would enable notice to be given to him before they were arrested. Article 18 . The meaning of the words 'without request or compensation' was explained to the Sultan but he pressed for their omission and this was agreed to. The Sultan referred to Article 7 of his draft,regarding harbour dues etc. He was asked to accept Article 8 of the existing Treaty ? but objected on the ground that he wanted, or might want, to raise funds for the improvement of his harbours. He said he was quite willing to leave undisturbed the existing lights maintained by the Persian Gulf Lighting and Buoying Committee. Pie was prepared to pay a subsidy to cover the cost of the lights which would be deducted from the dues collected by him. He was further prepared to agree that such ■ harbour dues should be levied on a scale corresponding to that levied by international custom, and he would agree to British representation on the special board provided for in his draft. He was promised that the matter would be considered in the light of what he now said. The next meeting was arranged for Saturday morning, 9th April.sy ■MUSCAT THSATY Note of fifth meeting with His Highness the Siiltan ? 9th April. PreGent! His Highness, Sir T.Powle and Mr. Gihson, The following matters were dealt v/ith:-- Article 1: The Sultan asked that from the term 'persons under His Majesty^ protection' should 'be excluded the subjects of Koweit ? Bahrein, Qatar, the Trucial Sheikhs, the Aden Protectorate and also of Zanzibar, and similarly that these territories should he excluded from the territories under His Majesty's protection referred to in (iii), (iv) and (v). He wished the exclusion to operate throughout all the Articles of the Treaty and not only in respect of those dealing with personal jurisdiction. lie was told that the Government of India would he consulted in respect of the Persian Gulf States, and the Colonial Office regarding the Aden P r otectorate and Zanzibar. (ii). His Highness would like a note assuring him, with regard to 'corporate 'bodies', (a) that individual employees of a Company, if not British subjects, would he unconditionally subject to his jurisdiction, and (h) that in case of conflict 'between the terms of a concession given to a Company (or other contract het¥/een the Sultan and a Company) and the terms of the Treaty, the terms of the concession etc. would prevail. Subject to the above, His Highness was satisfied with this clause, and also with the reference to registration of British shipping in (iii), in the lirht of the explanations supplied by the Board of Trade, Article 2 (l) . The amendment suggested at the fourth meeting wa s/ho 2. was further cllscussoci ancL ? v /i'tn. on© or 'by/o arriencirn,6rrts 9 accepted 'by the Sultan, Article 2 (2) a nd (5) . The following alternative was suggested to the Sultan:- 'The Sultan will not establish in his territory any monopoly in respect of a trade in v/hich nationals of His Majesty are at the time engaged without compensating such nationals for their loss of business either by permitting them to share in the monopoly on equitable terms or otherwise. Further, the Sultan undertakes to secure that any monopoly established by him shall interfere as little as possible with the trade between the territories of the rligh Contracting Parties. ' His Highness had no objection to the second sentence. Further 9 he said that if we wished it he was quite prepared to accept the first sentence also ? but he pointed out that it left him free on his return to Oman to institute monopolies in every matter in which British Indian traders were not now doing business, t'hus preventing them from acquiring any claim to compensation in such matters in the future. The question was left over for further consideration and discussion. Article 4 . It was proposed to His Highness that a sentence might be added to the existing draft as follows , o - 'Notwithstanding the provisions of the previous paragraph of this Article the Sultan may impose restrictions on the purchase of land outside the towns in his territories by nationals of His Majesty provided that the same restrictions are imposed on the/61 3. the nationals of the most favoured foreign country.' He said this did not meet him ? as he wished to exercise a control over the acquisition 'by foreigners of immovable property anywhere, hoth land and buildings, 'by requiring, as in his draft, that permission should 'be obtained. He remarked that with the existing draft, with or without the proposed addition, it was open to him, without infringement of the Treaty, to secure his object by issuing orders to his own subjects.that no immovable property was to be disposed of to foreigners without his permission. The orders would not apply directly to British subjects: the latter when desiring, say, to hire or purchase a shop, would approach an Omani subject for the purpose, that is, I h S b dealings would be with a private individual, not with the Omani Government, while the Omani subject before consenting to dispose of the property would refer to the Sultanate authorities for permission. The Sultan would outwardly be controlling only the actions of his own subjects, as he was entitled to do, and - yet vi(ould be able to secure his object. His Highness therefore suggested the retention of his own draft (i.e. the proviso to his Article 5). Sultan T s Article 7 (^arbour dues) His Highness proposed that the three points which he - was prepared to accept in respect of this Article (see note of fourth meeting) should be recorded in a letter and not in the Treaty itself, since he wished to avoid hampering his freedom in negotiating a treaty with a foreign power (particularly in regard to British representation on the special board) # Article 12 (lUiv) . It was explained to His Highness that questions of/A4. of personal status related to family law generally (marriage5 divorce^ legitimacy etc.). He said he wished that any dispute of this kind 'between Moslems, e.g. divorce proceedings, in which one of the parties is an Omani ? should 'be tried 'by Sharia law, i.e. in a Moslem religious court. The Article leaves this optional in the case of Moslems generally; His Highness wished it to 'be obligatory where an Omani is a party to a dispute. Article 12 (2). In place of the second sentence His Highness is prepared to accept a sentence suggested to him provided it runs as follows:- 'The national of His Majesty shall have .a right of appeal to the Sultan, in accordance with the procedure prescrihed in the Omani Courts, against any decision given against him in any such case if the Consul of His Majesty shall so request. If the Sultan should 'be absent the appellant may, if he so desires, as3£ that the appeal may 'be heard 'by the Sultan's representative. Article 12 (o) . An amendment to cover the point mentioned 'by His Highness at the fourth meeting was given to him. He also asked that the proviso in this paragraph should 'be extended to enable his officials to arrest a British subject who was found breaking a regulation of the Sultan which had been published and communicated to the British Consul, Article 14. His Highness made the following points. He is anxious/anxious to 'be able to impose customs duties without delay. He would accex^t an amendment providing that legislation imposing taxes or duties should 'be exhibited automatically. He would prefer to substitute 5! for a suitable period' for the reference to the period of ten days etc. ? leaving the exact period to he settled by an exchange of letters. In the last sentence,, which would now refer to legislation other than that imposing taxes or duties^ he wished to substitute 'consider the matter' for 'consider the withdrawal of his request or a modification of the law or regulation in question' 9 and was anxious that delay should be avoided in the event of the matter being submitted to His Majesty's Government, Further, he wanted liberty to apply to British subjects temporary emergency legislation in the interests of public security, tide 16 . His Highness would accept this Article, subject to the deletion of the v.ords 'and sufficient evidence proceeded with' and 'discharge such person from his service', and to the addition of the following sentence 'No criminal or civil proceedings shall be taken before the consular authorities of His Majesty against any national of His Majesty in the service of the Sultan unless notice of the- proceedings has been previously given to the Sultan or his representative.' It was agreed that the next meeting should be held on Wednesday, 20th April, after the return of His Highness from Paris and that a revised draft of the Treaty should if possible be given to him before leaving London.INDIA OFFICE, T/HITEHALL. LONDON, 3.¥.1. 11th April, 1938 Your Highness As was promised to Your Highness at our last meeting I enclose herewith a copy of a revised provisional draft of the Treaty which embodies the results of the informal conversations which Sir Trenchard Powle and I have so far had with Your Highness? and which also includes a number of small verbal improvements in the text given to Your Highness at our first meeting. provisional draft are purely tentative and are subject to the further views of His Majesty's G-overnment and of the Government of India. Your Highness for the very helpful attitude you have adopted in the course of our conversations and loolc forward to resuming them on 'Wednesday morninj the 20th April, as arranged with Your Highness. As explained to Your Highness the terms of the Sir Trenchard Fowle and I are most grateful to Your Highness' sincere friend? s Highness Saiyid Said bin Saiyid Taimur 9 KGIE. ? Sultan of Muscat and Oman? Dorc Vioc, ter Hotel? (Sgd.) J. P, GiMUSCAT TREATY. Igjise'l proYisional draft. 11th April, 1938. Preamble . His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, ^esiring to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations which now subsist between them and to promote and extend their commercial relations by the conclusion of a new treaty to replace the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation signed at Muscat on the 19th March, 1891, which terminates on the 11th February, 1939, Hare accordingly appointed as their plenipotentiaries:~ His Majesty the King of Great Sri cain, Ii eland and ciie Bx'i ti sh Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India . (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty) : For Great Britain and Northern Ireland: For India: The Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies (hereinafter referred to as the Sultan), in person; Who have agreed as follows:- Article 1 ./Article 2 . (1) There shall 'be perfect freedom of commerce and naTigation 'b etween the territories of the High Contracting Parties. Each High Contracting Party- shall allow the nationals of the other to enter all ports, creeks and rivers with their vessels and cargoes, also to travel, reside and pursue commerce and trade, whether wholesale or retail, in his territories provided, as regards nationals of the Sultan, that they satisfy and observe the conditions and regulations applicable in the territory of His Majesty in question to the entry, travel, residence and departure of all foreigners, and provided, as regards nationals of His Majesty, that before proceeding from the place where they reside to another place in the territories of the Sultan where foreign subjects do not already reside they shall notify in writing the local Ornani authorities of the place wherethey reside, and such authorities shall inform them whether the intended destination is suitable for them to travel to or not; if the authorities in question notify the said nationals in writing that the intended destination is unsuitable, and if the said nationals persist in travelling to their destination, or if the3r should fail to notify the local authorities of their intended movements, they will proceed at their own risk. Further,4S c The question of inoriopolies, dealt with in paragraphs (S) and (3), is reserved for further discussion. W subject to the provisions of Article 8, each High Contracting Party shall alloy/ in his territories the nationals of the other^ whether personally or by agent, freely to bargain for, buy, barter and sell gooas, articles o^ import, or local production, whether intended for local sale, use or consumption, or for export. (2) The Sultan undertakes to inform His Majesty of his intention to establish in his territories any monopoly, with a view to securing that the monopoly shall interfere as little as possible with the trade between the territories of the High Contracting Parties, or with trade carried on in his territories by the nationals of His Majesty. (3) In the event of the establishment of any such monopoly the question of ohe payment of compensation and the amount, if any, of such compensation which shall be paid to the nationals of His Majesty established in the territories of the Sultan shall be settled by mutual agreement by the High Contracting Parties or by arbitration.0 The que dealt wj (E) and for furl■Article 3. (1) Nationals of His Majesty shall enjoy throughout the territories of the 3ultan with respect to commerce 9 shipping and the exercise of trade? as in every other respect 3 all the rights, privileges, immunities, advantages and protection, of whatsoever nature enjoyed 'by or accorded to the nationals of the Sultan or to the nationals of any other foreign country. (2) They shall not he liable to taxes, duties, imposts, restrictions or obligations of whatever description, other or more onerous than those to which the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of any other foreign country are subjected# (3) In all that relates to navigation and the treatment of shi,ping the Sultan undertakes to treat .iritish vessels not less favourably in any respect than his own vessels or the vessels of any other foreign country* The provisions of this Article relating to vessels apply also to the passengers and cargoes carried therein.0 For further consideration-, as His Highness desires to retain the proviso to his Article 5 regarding iimoveahle property. Article k * Nationals of His Majesty shall he permitted in the territories of the Sultan to hire or to acquire 'by gift, purchase, intestate succession? or under T/illj, or any other legal manner, land, houses, and property of every description, whether moveable or immoveable, to possess the same, and freely to dispose thereof by sale, barter, donation or otherwise I on the same conditions as are or may I be established with regard to the ! nationals of the Sultan or the | nationals of the most favoured foreign I country.0 For fur' as His ] retain ' Article immovealI ^ Articl e 3» (1) Articles produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty imported into the territories of the Sultan ? from whatever place arriving, shall not he subjected to duties or charges other or higher than those paid on the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No other or higher duties or charges shall 'be imposed in the territories of the Sultan on the export a Irion of any article to the territories of His Majesty than such as are .payable on the exportation of the like article to any other foreign country. (3) The import duties leviable in the territories of the Sultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty and on goods imported by nationals of His Majesty shall be paid at the port or other place in the Sultan f s territories vhere the goods are first imported, and on xoayment thereof such goods shall thereafter be exempt within the said territories from all other Customs duties. (i-l-)Customs duties shall not be levied in the territories of the Sultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty or imported by nationals of His Majesty in the following cases, namely:- (a)/12 A rticle J3. (continued). 'being so landed? and that all customs charges are paid before the goods are reshipped. (c) On coal? fuel and oil? Naval and Air Force provisions and stores and fittings? the property of His Majesty? landed in the territories of the Sultan for the use of the ships of His Majesty's Naval Forces and the aircraft of His Air Forces. Duty shall? however? 'be payable if any of the goods thus exempted are sold or otherwise disposed of in the local markets. (d) On all goods and merchandise transhipped or landed for the repair of damage caused hy stress of weather or disasters at sea or in the air? provided the cargo so discharged shall 'be left in the custody of the customs authorities and be reshipped abroad within a period of three months from the date of the original landing and that all customs charges have been paid. In the cases referred to in sub-paragraphs (a) to (d) above customs formalities in respect of landing? examination? clearance and shipment of goods are to be observed. (5) All goods remaining uncleared in the Sultan's customs houses after three months from the date of their original landing shall be disposed of by the Sultan's customs authorities ■ . 'by/Article (continued). (a) On all goods and merchandise which, being destined and manifested for a foreign country? are transhipped from one vessel or aircraft to another in any of the ports or airports of the Sultan or which have heen for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the Sultan ? s custom houses to await the arrival of a vessel or aircraft in which to he reshipped abroad; hut goods and merchandise so landed shall only he exempted if the consignee or his agent shall have? on the arrival of the vessel or aircraft? handed over the said goods to he kept under customs seal? and declared them as landed for transhipment? designating at the same time the foreign place of destination and if witnin a period not exceeding three months after their first landing the said goods are actually shipped for the said foreign country as originally declared and without having in the interval- changed owners and if all customs charges are paid before they are reshipped. (b) On all goods and merchandise which? not being destined and manifested for the territories of the Sultan have been inadvertently landed? provided that such goods are left in the custody of the customs authorities and are reshipped for a destination abroad within a month of be ing/is further.ra. (2) is reserved )r further consideration. (1) All customs duties leviable in the territories of the Sultan shall 'be paid in cash and not in kind. (2) The value of the merchandise, goods or produce on which duty is to be levied shall be fixed according to their ready money wholesale market price at Muscat? less the customs duties payable on imp ortat ion. (3) The,Sultan*s Government shall have the right to fix the valuations for customs purposes of any descriptions of goods or produce for any period provided such valuation are fixed by a tariff board appoint^ .'py the Sultan consisting of equal numbers of the Sultan's nationals and nationals 'of His Majesty representing the merchant community and presided over by the Director of the Sultan's Customs. (U) In the event of any dispute arising between a national of His Majesty and the Customs House Authorities regarding the value of any goods5 this shall be determined by reference to two experts, each party nominating one. and the value so ascertained shall be decisive. Should however these experts not be able to agree 3 they shall choose an umpire ? whose decision is to be considered as final. 111 Ar ticle 7. Internal duties, taxes or fees levied within the territories of either High Contracting Party for the 'benefit of the State, or of organs of local or municipal government, on or in connection with goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the other Party, shall not he other or greater than the duties, taxes or fees levied in similar circumstances on or in connection with goods of national or any other origin.Article 8 . (1) No prohibition or restriction shall 'be imposed or maintained on the importation into the territories of the Sultan of any article5 from whatever place arriving, produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty which shall not equally extend to the importation of the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the exportation of any article from the territories of the Sultan to the territories of His Majesty which shall not equally extend to the exportation of the like articles to any other foreign country. (3) Exceptions to the general rule laid down in the foregoing paragraphs may be made only in the case of (a) prohibitions or restrictions imposed in the interests of public security; (b) prohibitions or restrictions regarding traffic in arms, ammunition and implements of war ? or? in exceptional circumstances? all other mili tary supplie s; (c)/Article 8 (continued) (c) prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of public health; (d) prohilDiti ns or restrictions imposed for the protection of animals or plantsj including protection against diseases, degeneration or extinction* as well as measures taken against harmful seeds, plants and animals.Article 9 , The Sultan engages l3y the present Treaty to provide and give orders to his officials that the movement of goods in transit shall not 'be obstructed or delayed in a vexatious manner 'by unnecessary customs formalities and regulations and that every facility will he given for their transport.Article 10 . Sither of the two High Contracting Parties may appoint consuls to reside in the territories of the other&lt;, subject to the consent and approval of the other as regards the persons so appointed and the places at which they reside. Such consuls shall at all times be accorded in the country in which they reside treatment and privileges not less favourable than consuls of the most favoured foreign country. Each of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his own nationals to be appointed to Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party5 provided always that the person so appointed shall not begin to act without the previous approbation of the High Contracting Party whose nationals they may be.n Artlclo 11 . (1) British vessels or aircraft coming to the territories of the Sultan5 in distress9 shall receive from the local authorities all possible necessary aid to enable them to re-victual and refit so as to proceed on their voyage or journey. (2) Should a British vessel or aircraft be wrecked off the coast of or in the Sultan's territories, the authorities of the Sultan shall render all possible assistance to save the vessel or aircraft ? its cargo and those on board; they shall also give all possible aid and protection to persons saved ? and shall assist them in reaching the nearest British Consulate, they shall further take every possible care that the goods so recovered are safely stored, and kept for the purpose of being handed over to the ovmer, Captain, Agent of the ship or aircraft, or British Consul, subject always to rights of salvage. (3) The Sultan's authorities shall further see that the British Consulate is as soon as possible informed of such disaster having occurred. {k) Should a British vessel or aircraft, wrecked on the coast of ■ a In or/J?- O tv Ar ticle 11 (c ont i nue d) or in the Sultan^ territories be plundered? the authorities of the Sultan shall^ as soon as they come to knov thereof? render prompt assistance and take all possible measures to pursue and punish the robbers? and recover the stolen property. Likewise? should a vessel or aircraft of the Sultan? or of one of his nationals? enter a port in His Majesty's territories in distress? or be wrecked off the coast of or in His Majesty's territories? the like help and assistance shall be rendered by the authorities of those territories.8^ Article 1 .3. In the exercise of their respective jurisdictions under paragraphs (l) and (2) of Article 12, the authorities of the Sultan and the consular authorities of His Majesty shall afford every possible aid and facility for satisfaction of the rightful claims of the nationals of one High Contracting Party against nationals of the other.Article l/ .j. (cont. ) consider the withdrawal of his request or a modification of the law or regulation in question or the eubrnission of the matter to His Majesty'&gt;3 Government in the United Kinp:dorn. I IArticle 16 . Nationals of the two High Contracting Parties shall, within the territories of each other? enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all forms of religion, provided that such exercise does not wound or outrage the religious susceptibilities of the country in which it is proposed to 'be practised, and the right to build edifices for religous worship in places specified for the purpose by local authorities. Nothing shall be done by either High Contracting larty that may disturb existing places of worship belonging to nationals of the other.if f Article 17. All the provisions of the present Treaty providing for the grant of the treatment accorded to the most favoured foreigh country shall 'be interpreted as meaning that such treatment shall 'be accorded immediately and unc o nd i t i o na 11 . 'I Article 18 . (1) His Majesty may through his Consular Officer at Muscat give notice of his desire that the present Treaty shall extend to any of his colonies, overseas territories or protectorates, or to any mandated territory in re spe c t of V/hich the mandate is exorcised 'by his Government in the United Kingdom, and the Treaty shall 'be extended to any territory specified in such notice as from the date thereof. (2) After the expiry of a period of two years from the coming into force of the present Treaty, either High Contracting Party may, 'by giving twelve months' notice, terminate the application of the present Treaty to any territory to which it has 'been extended under the provisions of the preceding paragraph.Ar ticle 1 9. (l) The Hj_gh Contracting Parties agree that His Majesty may hy notification given through his Consular Officer at Muscat accede to the present Treaty in respect of any Member of the British Commonv/ealth of Nations -.vhose Government may desire that such accession should he effected. Any such accession shall take effect as from the date of notification thereof. (8) After the expiry of a period of two years from the coming into force of the present Treaty either High Contracting Party may, 'by giving twelve months* notice, terminate the Treaty as regards any country in respect of which notification of accession has 'been given under paragraph (l) of this Article. (3) Any notification made under paragraph (1) of this Article may include any dependency or mandated territory administered 'by the G-overnment of the country in respect of which notification of accession is given and any notice given under paragraph (2) of this Article shall he applicable to any such dependency or mandated territory which was included in such notification of accession*( ■ ? IP Article 20 . (1) So long as in any territory referred to in Articles. Ig and |l| 5 to which the provisions of the present Treaty are not applicable, either by virtue of accession under Article jCj or by notice of extension under Article Ig^ goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the Sultan are accorded treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country, goods produced or manufactured in such territory shall likewise enjoy in the territories of the Sultan treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) G-oods, the produce or manufacture of Palestine, shall not be debarred from the benefits of this Article by reason only of any special customs privileges which may be accorded in Palestine to goods the produce or manufacture of any State the territory of which in 1914 was wholly included in Asiatic Turkey or Arabia.A rticle 21 . (1) The present Treaty has loeen executed in quadruplicate, two copies being written in English and two in Arabic. These are understood to 'be of similar import and signification; in the event, however, of doubt hereafter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive. (2) The present Treaty shall be ratified, and ratifications shall be exchanged at (Muscat). It shall come into force on the 11th day of February, 19395 or on the date of exchange of ratifications, whichever date be the later.Art icle 22 , Afcer the lapse of twelve years trom the date on which the Treaty shall come into force, and on twelve months t notice given 'by either party, this Treaty shall be subject to termination. In witness whereof on behalf of His Hajcity the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said 'bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, on his own behalf, have signed the same and affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat, this day of 193 ? corresponding to the of the year ..... Hejira, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies.-is , ■ &lt;?? Telegram Q # i'rora Politic X Resident, Bushire, at Bahrain To H»M f s Secretary of State for India, London^ v Coiov by air niail &gt; Secretary to the Government of India External Affairs Depa: tment. Hew Deliii^ lk)*T/128 Dated 4th May 1938o Bemi^official a Fowle to (jibson # Could you please suggest to Sultan of Muscat that if treaty is ready for signature before his departure from India for Muscat I could meet him in Karachi for stlgnature. Resident# Copy sent to GrOVt._of India under P.L Hotc/309, dated 4.0.38. HiIW lEDIA OF.PIGS, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. 19 7 6/38. I 28th April 1938. Muscat Treaty. jv / With reference to Gibson's letter of the 14th April, ed / No. P. Z. 2664/38, I am desired to forward a copy of a letter h / II. addressed to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat enclosing a draft representing the results of the informal discussions with His Highness in London in connexion with the revision of the 1891 Treaty. llotes of the meetings held with ^/Sis Highness between the 20th and 23rd April are also ed / enclosed herewith, together with a copy of a letter 4/ III. explanatory of a point in Article 1 (ii) which was sent to the Sultan on the 22nd April. 2. It will 'be noted that His Highness has been informed that the draft is subject to the views of the Government of India and the further views of His Majesty's Government. As the discussions have been conducted in close consultation with the Legal Adviser of the .Foreign Office/ Aubrey Metcalfe, KCIE. ,GSI. ,MV0. , Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department. Is.lol Office and the Board of Trade it is not expected that any fresh points or criticisms of the draft will be made from here, except possibly with regard to the Sultan's proposed amendments of Articles 1 and 19, as to which the Colonial Office will wish to consult the Aden and Zanzibar authorities. I am to ask that the draft may be examined as soon as possible in order that any observations which the Government of India may wish to make may be considered here and the necessary instructions issued at an early date for any further discussion with the Sultan that may be necessary, or for the final conclusion of the Treaty. His Highness' present intention is to reach Bombay at the end of May and after three weeks' stay there to return to Muscat in the last week ojy^xme, 3. The more important changes introduced in the present draft compared with the revised provisional draft of 11th April are as follows:- Article 2 : The paragraphs dealing with monopolies gave much trouble and the present paragraph (2) was the best that the Sultan could be brought to accept. Article 4 : It was found necessary to concede to the Sultan freedom//ov- 3. freedom to impose restrictions with regard to the purchase etc. of immovable property by British subjects which would not be applicable to his o?/n subjects. Articles 5 (7) and 6 (2) : The Board of Trade would not object to these paragraphs as at present drafted and Sir Trenchard Powle thinks they may be accepted, provided that it is confirmed that the charges referred to in Article 5 (7) are in fact of long standing, as alleged by the Sultan. As Indian traders and Indian trade are the most affected the (xovernment of India may have special views on the paragraphs* Article 7 : The Board of Trade would be prepared to accept this Article (regarding harbour dues &amp;c.) in the light of the assurances which the Sultan is willing to give. Article 9 : With regard to paragraph 3 of this Article, it should be explained that some doubt was felt regarding the inclusion of exception (b) relating to the importation of arms, but the Foreign Office Legal Adviser and the Board of Trade considered that it might on the whole be as well to retain (b) in view of the possibility that the Treaty might be used by the Sultan as a model f or/4. f 0 r treaties with other Powers. Paragraph (3) was therefore retained in its common form. Arti cle 15 (Jurisdiction): The comparatively minor points raised by the Sultan have been met. Art icle 15 : Article 14 of the draft of 11th April was the one which caused most difficulty, and as His Highness's objections were in great part due to its appearance in a published Treatj^ it was decided to deal with the essential parts of the Article by means of a confidential letter to which His Highness eventually agreed. 4. Copies of this letter and enclosures are being sent to Powle at Bahrein and to Watts. Yours sinQ®r©*y« to**-**loU' INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I, 26th April,1938. your Higiiness, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose the draft of the Treaty representing the result of the informal conversations which Sir Trenohard Fowls and Mr. Gibson haye had with Your Highness. It is felt that these informal conversations have been most valuable and that they will greatly facilitate the final conclusion of the Treaty on Your Highness 1 return to Muscat. The Government of India are being consulted on this, draft. Subject to any views which they may express and to any further view of His Majesty's Government, and to the settlement of any outstanding points, it is hoped that it may be possible to arrange that Sir Trenchard Powle may proceed to the formal conclusion of the Treaty with Your Highness on the lines of the enclosed draft within a reasonable time after the return of Your Highness to Muscat. ■ May I express on behalf of the Secretary of State his appreciation of the extremely helpful attitude which Your Highness, ,has adopted in the course of the informal discussions and which has enabled them to be concluded in so short a space of time? Your Highness' sincere friend, (Sd.) J.C. WALT Oil. ss Saiyid Said bin Saiyid fuimur, IC.C.I.E., u itan of Muscat and Oman.^ /OS- MUSC AT TREATY, Draft embodying the results of the informal discussions with Kis Highness the Sultan in London; April 1938. Preambl e. His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat andj Oman and Dependencies, Desiring to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations Y /hich now subsist between them and to promote and extend their commercial relations by the conclusion of a new treaty to replace the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation signed at Muscat on the 19th March, 1891, which terminates on the 11th February, 1939^ Have accordingly appointed as their plenipotentiaries:- His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty): For Great Britain and Northern Ireland: For India: The//ijJ » x — yiA-jfA t) 4^ /aa t-'idsi/y eh ^'^ o } Gl^- A — -'/UvX t 'Vv Article 2, /o^ (1) There shall be perfect freedom of commerce and navigation between the territories of the High Contracting Parties ■iach High Contracting Party shall allow the nationals of the other to enter all ports, creeks and rivers with their vessels and cargoes, also to travel, reside and pursue commerce and trade, whether wholesale or retail, in his territories provided, as regards nat ionals of the Sultan, that they satisfy and observe the conditions and regulations applicable in the territory of His Majesty in question to the entry, travel residence and departure of all foreigners, and provided that nationals of His Majesty-' proceeding from the place where they reside in the territories of the Sultan to another place in his territories where foreign itj^L 0 / subjects do not already reside -B-hall, before doing so, notify in writing the local Qmani authorities of the place where they reside, and such authorities shall inform them whether the intended destination is suitable for them, to travel to or not; if the authorities in question notify the said nationals in writing that the intended destination is unsuitable, and if the said nationals persist in travelling to their destination, or if they should fail to notify the local authorities of their intended movements, they will proceed at their own risk. Further, sub.1 ect/110 subject to the proYisions of Article 9, each High Contracting Party shall allow in his territories, the nationals of the other, whether personally or by agent ? freely to bargain for, buy, barter and sell gooas, articles of import, or local production, whether intended for local sale, use or consumption, or for export. (2) Should the Sultan wish to establish any monopoly in any part of his territory such monopoly will be arranged in such away that it will, not be detrimental to the trade in which nationals of His Majesty are at the time occupied in that part of his territory.Ill \ Article 5. (1) Nationals of His Majesty shall enjoj throughout the territories of the Sultan with respect to commerce, shipping and the exercise of trade all the rights, priYileges, immunities, advantages and protection, of whatsoever nature, enjoyed 'by the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of any other foreign country. {2) They shall not W liable to taxes, duties, imposts, restrictions or obligations of any description whatever, other or more onerous than those to which the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of any other foreign c ount ry ar e sub j e c t e d. (3) In all that relates to navigation and the treatment of shipping, the Sultan undertakes totreat British vessels not less favourably in any respect than Omani vessels or the vessels of anj other foreign country. The provisions of this Article relating to vessels apply also to the passengers and cargoes carried therein.Ill Ar ticle 4 . Nationals of His Majesty shall be permitted in the territories of the Suit slii to hire or to acquire,, 'by gift, purchase, intestate succession, will, or any other legal manner , land, houses, and property of every description, whether moyable or immovable, to possess the same, and freely to dispose thereof by sale, barter, donation or otherwise on the same conditions in respect of immovable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the most favoured foreign country and in respect of movable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of the most favoured foreign country.-v 112 , . tt ^ t*)^'l • Ar ticle 5 « (1) Articles produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty imported into the territories of the Sultan? from v/hatever place arriving, shall not he subjected to duties or charges other or higher than those paid on the like articles produced or manufactured in' any other foreign country. (2) No other or higher duties or charges shall 'be imposed in the territories of the Sultan on the exportation of any article to the territories of His Majesty than such as are payable on the exportation of the like article to any other foreign country. (3) The import duties leviable in the territories of the jultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty and on goods imported by nationals of His Majesty shall be paid at the port or other place in the Sultan 1 s territories -./here the goods are first imported ? and on payment thereof such goods shall thereafter be exempt within the said territories from all other Customs duties. (i4-)Customs duties shall not be levied in the territories of the Sultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty or imported by nationals of His Majesty in the following cases? namely;- (a)/L /4tv&gt; ■ &lt; &gt;■ : / ' , m Article 5 (continued), (a) On goods which, being destined and manifested for a foreign country, are transhipped from one vessel or aircraft to another in any of the ports or airports of the Sultan or which have 'been for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the Suit an 1 s cu st om houses to awai t t he arrival of a vessel or aircraft in which to loe re shipped abroad; but' goods so landed shall only be exempted if the consignee or his agent shall have, on the arrival of the vessel or aircraft, handed over the said goods to be kept under customs seal, and declared them as landed for transhipment, designating at the same time the foreign place ox destination, and if within a period not exceeding three months after their first landing the said gooas are actually shipped for the said foreign country as originally declared and without having in the interval changed owners, and if all customs charges are paid before they are reshipped. (b) On goods which, not being destined and manifested for the territories of the Sultan have been -Wt&amp;r ^ inadvertently landed, provided that f0 j . such goods, are left in the custody oj. the customs authorities and are reshipped for a destination abroad within/[p~ ^ J A| , ' /ir Ar ticle 5 .(continued) # s within~€t montIV of being so landed, and that all customs charge's are paid 'before the goods are reshipped. (c) On coal ? fuel and oil, Naval and Air Force provisions and stores and fittings, the property of His Majesty, landed in the territories of the Sultan for the use of the ships' of His Majesty^ IT aval Forces and. the aircraft of His Air Forces: duty shall, however, be payable if any of the goods thus exempted are sola or otherwise disposed of in the local markets. (d) On gooas transhipped or landed pending .the repair of,damage caused to the vessel or aircraft by'stress of weather or disasters at sea or in the air, Tjrovided the cargo so discharged shall be left in the custody of the customs authorities and be reshipped abroad within a period of three months from the date of the original landing and that all customs charges have been pai d, (5) In the cases referred to in paragraph (4) above customs formalities in respect of landing, examination, clearance and shipment of goods Eire to be observed. (6) All goods remaining uncleared in the Sultan's customs houses after months from the date of their original///6 Article 5 {continued). original landing shall be disposed of by the Sultan's customs authorities by a public auction after notifying the steamer or aircraft agents concerned. Their sale proceeds, after payment of the auctioneering charges customs duty and charges shall be kept in deposit for a period, of one year and refunded to the owner if the claim is established during this period^ after which no claim shall be entertained, (7) In this Article the words 'customs charges 11 shall mean charges other than customs duties and may include landing, transit, weighing, wharfage or ground rent, supervision and overtime fees, it being understood that all such fees will be assessed on a reasonable•scale.i X /'] Article 6. (1) All customs duties leviable in the territories of the Sultan shall be paid in cash and not in icin^U— (2) The value of the goods on which duty is to be levied shall be. fixed according to their market price following the normal usage of trade in Muscat• (3) The Sultan's Government shall have the right to fix the valuatiotis for customs purposes of any descriptions of goods fo-r any period provided such valuations are fixed by a tariff board appointed by the Sultan consisting of equal numbers of the Sultan's nationals and nationals of His Majesty repre s e nt ing the mer chant communi ty and presided over by the Director of the Sultan's Customs. (4) In the event of any dispute arising between a national of His Majesty and the Customs House Authorities regarding the value of any goods ? this shall be determined by reference to two experts, each party nominating one and the value so ascertained shall be decisive. Should however these experts not be able to agree ? they shall choose an umpire, whose decision is to be considered as f i rial.'I ^.rticlG 8 &gt; Internal duties, taxes or fees levied within the territories of either High Contracting Party for the benefit of the State 9 or of organs of local or municipal government, on or in connection with goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the other Party? shall not he other or greater than the duties? taxes or fees levied in similar circumstances on or in connection with goods of national or any other origin.I&gt; 0 Article 9• (1) No prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the importation into the territories of the Sultan of any article, from whatever place arriving? produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty which shall not equally extend to the importation of the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the oxportation of any article from the territories of the Sultan to the territories of His Majesty which shall not equally extend to the exportation of the like articles to any other fore ign c ountry. (3) iixceptions to the general rule laid down in the foregoing paragraphs may be made only in the case of (a) prohibitions or restrictions ■imposed in the interests of public security; (b) prohibitions or restrictions regarding traffic in arms? ammunition and implements of war? 5r ? in exceptional circumstances ? all other mi1i tary supplies; \/3.I Art icle 9 (continued) (c) prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of public health; (d) prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of animals or plants, including protection against diseases? degeneration or extinction? as well as measures taken against harmful seeds? plants and animals•,vv Article 10&gt; The Sultan engages hy the present Treaty to provide and give orders to his officials tho.t the movement of goods in transit shall not 'be obstructed or delayed in a vexatious manner 'by unnecessary customs formalities and regulations, and that every facility will 'be given for their transport.I /» ' ' sMJ- 0 'U Article II , Either of the two High Contracting Parties may appoint consuls to reside in the territories of the other? subject to the consent and approval of the other as regards the i)ersons so appointed and the places at which they reside. Such consuls shall at all times 'be accorded in the country in which they reside treatment and privileges not less favourable than consuls of the most favoured foreign country. Sach of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his own nationals to be appointed to Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party? provided always that the person so appointed shall not begin to act without the previous approbation of the High Contracting r-A Party whose nationals they- may be.|&gt;M- 12^ (l) British vessels or aircraft coming to the territories of the Sultan 5 in distress9 shall receive from the local authorities all possible necessary aid to enable them to re-victual and refit so as to proceed on their voyage or journey. (2) Should a British vessel or airaraft 'be wrecked off the coast of or in the Sultan 1 s territories^ the authorities of the Sultan shall render all possible assistance to save the vessel or aircraft 9 its cargo and those on board; they shall also give all possible aid and protection to persons saved, and shall assist them in reaching the nearest British Consulate, they shall further take every possible care that the goods so recovered are safely storedy and kept for the purpose of being handed over to the owner. Captain, Agent of the ship or aircraft, or British Consul, subject always to rights of salvage. (3) The Sultan 1 s authorities shall further see that the British Consulate is as soon as possible informed of such disaster having occurred. (Lj.) Should a British vessel or aircraft, wrecked off-the coast of or/Article 12 (Gontinued) or in the Sultan 1 s territories be plundered, the authorities of the Sultan shall, as soon as they come to know thereof, render prompt assistance and take all possible measures to pursue and punish the robbers, and recover the stolen property. (5) Likewise, should a yessel or aircraft of the Sultan, or of one of his nationals, enter a port in His Majesty's territories in distress, or be wrecked off the coast of or in His Majesty's territories, the like help and assistance shall be rendered by the authorities of those territories.j&gt;fe p / / r •&gt;/! j, &gt; aLL-J' '» h&gt; /i i'l-t hAstnry~~*U*- &lt;^Ui / ^ ^AAJ^I' fi/ r &lt;&lt;iA^ (T '■' ■ u**~* kdbUx ' /[JUo~ £- v- ^ t LAA ^a~. { %' . ) cff—- ^ CUX 4&gt;(j^ 1 ^ A^\jrvTsy~ s? fM*U (U ^ ' /c?/^ T^./ H i •/V^w 4^&gt;L- K^t. ■wC4*UC./jt-0 ( ko^ JJ\j /! s Article 15. (I) The Consular authorities of His Majesty in the territories of the Sultan shall try and determine / (i) all criminal charges against nationals of His Majesty; (II) 0.11 civil Bu.its In which nationals of His Majesty are defendants; - (M) all 'bankruptcy cases in which the 'bankrupt or the person whom it is sought to make 'bankrupt is a national of His Majesty; (iv) all proceedings connected with administration of the estate of a -V deceased national of His Majesty, and all questions of personal status where the person whose status is in question is a national of His Majesty, always provided that where such person is a Moslem the consular authorities may remit the case for decision hy a Moslem religious court of the Sultan on such conditions as they may determine and shall so remit the case if any other party to the proceedings is a national of the Sultan. (2) All criminal or civil cases in which a national of His Majesty is complainant or plaintiff and the accused or defendant is a national of the Sultan or a national of a third country shall he tried and determined 'by the courts of the/ji PLIC-L j-O _ ^ 0 Oil bCU ) the Sultan. The na.tional of His Majesty shall have a pi ■ of - appeal to the Sultan, in accordance with the procedure prescrji'bed in the Omani courts, against any decision given against him in any such case if the consul of His Majesty shall so request. If the Sultan should he absent the ax ^pellant may, if he so desires, ask that his appeal may 'be heard 'by the Sultan's representative. (3) A national of His Majesty shall not 'be arrested or his property seized, nor his house, office, warehouse or other premises occupied 'by him entered and searched without his consent, 'by an officer of the Sultan save under an order signed 'by the consul of His Majesty and any national of His Majesty arrested and any property of a national of His Majesty seized shall he placed in the custody of the consul of His Majesty: always provided that, in case of necessity for the prevention of 'breaches of the. peace or a breach of a law or regulation of the Sultan which has been made applicable to nationals of His Majesty under Article 15, the authorities of the Sultan may without such an order arrest a national of His Majesty or take charge of his property or enter and search his house, office, warehouse or other premises occupied by him, but in this case the proceedings shall be/'be at once reported, and the person arrested and any property seised handed over without delay ? to the consul cf His Majesty,Artic le 1 4, In the exercise of their respective jurisdictions under paragraphs (1) and (2) of Article 13, the authorities of the .Sultan and the consular authorities of His Majesty shall afford every possible aid and facility for satisfaction of the rightful claims of the nationals of one High Contracting Party against nationals of the other.I m B.E. agrees that the L ed ure for giving L c t to this Article Lid be laid down in Ijonfidential letter, utile terms of the ^ |Li 0 Cached draft, to be Hdressed to him hy the fflitical Resident and Llmowledged hy him. ) Ibo Article 15 . The consular authorities of His Majesty will, at the request of the Sultan, apply in the exercise of their jurisdiction under Article 13 all laws and regulations of the Sultan which it is desirable to apply to nationals of His Majesty in the territories of the Sultan, including, in particular, laws and regulations imposing taxation or duties and police and municipal regulations,Ill ' ^ ^ ^ fjtt* &lt; ct •' ' v-t-- V '/^M^^dc^ Wrf't &lt; t ^/- A^...&lt; 5 j/' • '^ £-fw\.h J ' A - ' ^ ^ ^ &lt;ZL-+xA~&lt;ZcA — Article 16_. (1) The prorisions of Articles 13, 14 and 15 shall apply to nationals of the Sultan or of another foreign country who are in the regular service of the consul of His Majesty as if they v/ere nationals of His Majesty provided that, if any such person should be charged with r c(JL£JU£: S a crime foxc—ar—s^r-i-ottis-• •o-r^e-nc'e^ the consul will allow the charge to be tried by the authorities of the Sultan. (2) No criminal or civil proceedings shall be taken before the consular authorities of His Majesty against any national of His Majesty in the service of the Sultan unless notice of the proceedings has been previously given to the Sultan or his representative.Article 17. Nationals of the two High Contracting -arties shall, r/ithin the territories of each other? enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all forms of religion, provided that such exercise does not wound or outrage the religious susceptibilities of the country in which it is proposed to he practised, and the right to 'build edifices for religious worship in places specified for the purpose 'by local authorities. Nothing shall he done by either High Contracting '.arty that may disturb existing places of worship belonging to nationals of the other.Article 18 . All the provisions of the present Treaty providing for. the grant of the treatment accorded to the raost favoured foreign country shall be interpreted as meaning that such treatment shall he accorded immediately and u nc o n d i t i o na 11 y.ArtiolQ 2n^ (1) The Hj _gh Contracting Parties agree that His Majesty may 'by notification given through his Consular Officer at Muscat accede to the present Treaty in respect of any Member of the British Commonwealth of Nations v.hose Government may desire that such accession should he effected. Any such accession shall take effect as from the date of notification thereof (2) After the expiry of a period of two years from the coming into force of the present Treaty either High Contracting Party may, 'by giving twelve months' notice, terminate the Treaty as regards any country in respect of which notification of accession has 'been given under paragraph (l) of this Article. (3) Any notification made under paragraph (l) of this Article may include any dependency or mandated territory administered 'by the Cxovernment of the country in respect of which notification of accession is given and any notice given under paragraph (2) of this Article shall 'be applicable to any such dependency or mandated territory which was included in such notification of accession.A rticle 21. (l) So long as in any territory referred to -in Articles 19 and 20, to which the provisions of' the present Treaty are not applicable, either by virtue of accession under Article 20 or by notice of extension under Article 19^goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the Sultan are. accorded treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country/'goods produced or manufactured in such territory shall likewise enjoy in the territories of the Sultan treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country.^' (2) Goodsj the produce or manufacture of Palestine (including Trans Jordan),shall not be debarred from the benefits of this Article by reason only of any special customs privileges which may be accorded in Palestine to goods the produce or manufacture of any State the territor of which in 1914 was wholly included in Asiatic lurliey or Arabia.fil Article 22. (1) The present Treaty has 'been executed in quadruplicate, two copies being written in English and two in Arabic. These are understood to be of similar import and signification; in the erent, however, of doubt hereafter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive. (2) The present Treaty shall be ratified, and ratifications shall be exchanged at (Muscat). It shall come into force on the 11th day of February, 1939 if ratifications have been exchanged before that date, cr if they have not then been exchanged on the date of exchange of ratifications.lit Article 23* (1) The present treaty shall remain in force for a period of 12 years from the date of its entry into force. Unless one of the High Contracting Parties shall have given to the other notice of termination one year 'before the expiry of this period, the present treaty shall remain in force until the expiry of one year from the date on which such notice shall have 'been given. (2) A notice given under this Article shall not affect the operation of A &amp; $ the treaty as between the Sultan and any f ■■ • t/f , t y a country or territory in respect of vliich notification of accession has been given under Article 20. It shall however apply to any territory to which notification of extension has been given under Article 19* In witness whereof on behalf of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Tairnur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, on his own behalf, have/iXj Article 23 (continued). have signed the same and affixed thereto their respective seals« Done at Muscat? this# day of. 193 j corresponding to the. .of the year. Hejira. Sultan of Muscat and Ornan and Dependencies. For Great Britain and Northern Ireland. For India ; m 11 ) ■/\l txd-'iA, COHPIDENTIAL L3TTER /UP*,- /o' /fa* &lt;/ $lh/ jr^\ £o&gt; M Tfith reference to Article 15, I desire to place on record the procedure which has been agreed on for the operation of this articlec 1. If the Sultan desires that any law or regulation shall be made applicable to nationals of His Majesty, h^ will communicate a copy thereof to the consul of His Majesty. The consul will post a copy of the law or regulation in his office and the law or regulation shall become applicable to nationals of His Majesty one month after the date on which it is posted. It is, however, understood that at the request of the Sultan in case of urgency a shorter period shall be adopted. 2. (1) In the case of legislation imposing taxes or duties and of municipal or police regulations, the consul will always post the laws or regulations within tv^/o weeks of the receipt of the request from the Sultan (or within a shorter period in special cases of urgency) unless the laws or regulations are in conflict with Articles 2, 3, 4, 5, 8 or 10 of the present Treaty, (ii) In the case of legislation imposing customs duties, unless the law or regulation is in conflict with Articles 3, 5 or 6 of the present Treaty, the consul will post the law or regulation immediately upon receipt of the request from the Sultan and the law or regulation shall become applicable to nationals of His Majesty within such period as the Sultan may direct. (iii) The same procedure as in sub-paragraph (l) above will apply in the case of all other laws and regulations, unless in any particular case the consul of His Majesty submits to the Sultan serious reasons for the modification/ .1 ••/W ~ 2 ~ modification of the laws or regulations to render them suitable for application to nationals of His Majesty or reasons why such application is unnecessary. In the event of the consul submitting such reasons the Sultan will consider the matter 5 and 3 if he does not see fit to accept the suggestions 01; the consulwill request that the question of the application of the law or regulation in question should be immediately referred to His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom=MJgCAT TREATY . Note of Sixth meeting with His Highness the Sultan, 20th April. Present: His Highness, SirT. Fowle and Mr. Gibson. With reference to the revised provisional draft the following points were discussed Article 1: It was suggested to the Sultan that his proposed amendments to this Article might be more acceptable to the Colonial Office if he would agree that the exclusion of the British protected persons named 'by him should operate only in respect of the jurisdiction Articles so that these persons should be amenable to the jurisdiction of his courts but should at the same time enjoy the trading benefits accorded by the Treaty to British Subjects, His Highness was unable to agree pointing out that this would mean that nations say of Debai would enjoy trading privileges in his territory while his own subjects would have no corresponding advantages in Debai. The point was left for further consideration. Article 2 (2) and (5) : A further and unsuccessful attempt was made to secure the Sultan's acceptance of these paragraphs* He repeated that he had no desire to interfere with trade between Muscat and British territories but insisted on complete freedom to establish monopolies affecting trade carried on inside his territories. The matter was left over. Article 4 . The Sultan insisted on his desire to impose restrictions if necessary on the acquisition of immovable property - houses, shops &amp;o. as well as land - fey/Ik 1 * ■by foreigners and said he could only accept the present draft if the words T, tiie nationals of the Sultan or' were deleted. This, as he said, would leave him free to impose unlimited restrictions on all foreigners alike. He was howeyer willing to substitute for the last four lines the proviso at the end of Article 5 of his own draft. The article was left for further discussion. Article 6 (S) : The Sultan agreed that a representative of the Board of Trade might be invited to discuss this paragraph y/ith him and Mr. Dulichand. Article 14 : The Sultan expressed a number of objections to this Article which he said was new and created a very unwelcome impression that there were two governments in his country. He was quite content that British Subjects should be tried in the Consul's Court and he was not interested in the civil and criminal laws applied to them by the Consul. What he did want was that British Subjects should, like his own Subjects, be subject to municipal regulations and the like, for example to regulations relating to curfew, prohibition of smoking during Ramadan*, motor traffic &amp;c. It was explained to him that the Article was considered essential in consequence of the surrender of the full ex-territorial rights conferred by the existing treaty, that it was considered necessary to provide machinery for removing any doubt, as to the laws which were applicable to British Subjects in Muscat, and that His Highness need have no apprehension that regulations of the kind he referred to would not be exhibited and enforced in the Consul 1 s Court against British//IfW British Subjects. It proved very difficult to satisfy tiae Sultan on these points and further examination of the Article in the light of his views was promised. The next meeting was arranged for Thursday morning 21st April, at 10 a.m.MUS CAT TREATY . 'Note of seventh meeting' with His Highness the Sultan, 21st Aioril, Pr e s e nt: Hi s Hi ghne ss ; Sir T. Fowle, Mr, Gi'b s on, and, for the discussion of Article 6 {2), Mr. Shackle (Board of Trade) and Mr. Dulichand. The following matters were dealt with:- Article 1 (ii ); It was explained to the Sultan, with reference to his enquiry at the fifth meeting, that (a) the rights to 'be granted to companies under the proposed draft are solely rights of the companies as such and would not in any way limit his jurisidction over non- British employees of the company as individuals, and (b) in the event of a British Company obtaining a concession or contract wherein they accepted the imposition of certain conditions or restrictions 'by the Sultan 7 s Government the terms of the concession or contract would be upheld in the Consul's court even though the conditions or restrictions involved a surrender of rights which might otherwise have 'been claimed for the company under uhe Treaty. He desired to have this explanation in writing and said that in the light of it he was satisfied with the draft Article. Article S ( 3) a nd (3 ) t The Sultan was asked to substitute for these paragraphs the draft paragraph proposed go nim at the fifth meeting, which it was understood at the time he was prepared to accept, and he was told that we were prepared to take the risk of his using his powers in a way/■ ; way that would deprive the paragraph of some of its value, He however now raised certain objections to this craft. (a) He wished to have it amended so as to appear less harsh, i.e. so as to begin n The Sultan shall have the right to create monopolies, but in the case of any monopoly established by him in respect of a trade in which nationals of His Majesty are at the time engaged ho will compensate such nat i onals etc. etc,' (b) He wished to have an assurance that he would be the final authority to decide what compensation, if any, should be given. (c) He objected to the inclusion of the last sentence and said it wa s sufficiently covered by the first sentence, which, he said, covered both internal and external trade carried on by British nationals. He was told thao it was understood that he had hitherto always accepted the principle of the last sentence, that in our view it was a quite reasonable as well as a desirable provision in the Treaty, and that it was designed to cover the case of trade carried on say between Muscat and India which was not handled in Muscat by British subjects. Further there was no undue restriction, if indeed any, on the oultan's freedom of action, and the clause was one T/hich would be and has been accepted by several countries. It proved impossible to overcome the Sultan's objections and finally he said he was willing to accept oi .tnu.L_ o^e o .ii .-.t oer .tc.nee (subject to the points (a) and (b) above), or the second sentence, but not both, or, as an alternative to either, the formula suggested to him at the fourth meeting, viz.. 'Should the Sultan wish to establish any monopoly m his territory such monopoly will be arranged in such a way that it will not be detrimental to the trade of nationals of His Majesty' 1 . Article 3 (1)/ i| ;Ilfl ' : ! I Article 3 (1 )t The Sultan showed some sign of objecting to 11 national' treatment in this paragraph which he said did not occur in the present Treaty. He was asked to, turn first to the next Article. Article 3 was not further discussed but. it was inferred from a passing remark of the Sultan at the end of the meeting that he (^i d not attach much importance to his objection. Arti cle 4: The Sultan was informed that we would be satisfied with thb formula for the last few lines of this Article which he said at the fourth meeting he would accept (i.e. national ana most fayoured nation treatment in respect of movable property. Most favoured nation treatment only in respect of immovable property). His Highness confirmed that he accepted the formula. (It is thought, though the point was not put to him on this occasion that this will remove his objection to 'national' treatment in Article 3 (1)). Article 5 (6 ): In addition to 'weighing' the Sultan now wishes to insert 'transit' fees, explaining that both these charges, like the others mentioned, are already embociied in the customs regulations which have been in force in Muscat for many years. He also presses for the omission of the words 'in strict relation to the cost of the services they are intended to cover' at the end of the paragraph, urging that 'on a reasonable scale 11 is quite sufficient. Article 6 (2 ): Mr. Shackle explained at length the reasons for which this paragraph was considered u.esirable, pointing out that it was in accordance with the almost universal practice, and citing as an example the treaty provisions in force in Morocco for many years. H I Mil ii |iV 4. / matter was not of great importance under existing conditions, but it might well be important in future when changes were made in the Muscat tariff, and it was very desirable that traders should know on what basis customs duties would be levied, Mr. Dulichand urged, that the existing system was satisfactory, easily worked, and well known to all the traders concerned, who would experience much difficulty, as would also the customs staff, in getting used to the procedure indicated in the draft. It might well be that it would be found desirable to adopt this procedure in the future when considerable changes were made in the tariff, but there was no present intention of making such changes and they would therefore prefer to continue the existing system. Mr. Dulichand \ms understood to propose that the draft should run 'according to their market, price (or market valuation) at Muscat.' 1 He said the -phrase 'ready money' was a source of dispute, since traders frequently made their sales on three months' or six months 1 credit and would argue that the price on which customs duty should be assessed should be, not what they were due to receive at the end of the period of credit, but the smaller price which the goods would fetch if sold at once for cash. It was eventually agreed to leave over the paragraph for consideration by His Highness in the light of the discussion. Article 12 (.1) (iv ) : To meet His Highness the audixion of the following words at the end of the Article was proposed and agreed to: 'ana shall so remit the case if any other party to the proceedings is a national of the Sultan'. Article IB (£)/Article _18_[_2) : In the first sentence His Highness desired 'the courts' in place of 'a court' (of the Sultan). For the seoona sentence it was agreed to substitute the alternative two sentences in the margin. Article 12 (5 ): To meet His Highness it was proposed to insert, after 'for the prevention of breaches of the roeace', the words 'or a breach of a law or regulation of the Sultan which has been made applicable to nationals of His Majesty under Article 14'. The Sultan could not agree to these words until Article 14 was discussed. Article 14 : This article was discussed at considerable length, and to meet some of the views expressed by His Highness at the previous meeting it was proposed to him that the second paragraph should run 'In the case of police or municipal regulations or of legislation imposing taxes or duties the-text of the laws and regulations, or of the relevant provisions thereof, shall always be exhibited .etc.'. It was represented to the Sultan that this met his practical objections, and the general purpose of the Article and its necessity from our point oi viev/ was explained to him. He could not be brought to accept it, even with the offered deletion of the thiru paj.a &amp; raph which, it was explained, was inserted in his own interest. He objected to a new article which showed that there were two Governments in his State, and he could not a D ree bo the machinery by which his laws were enforceable against British subjects only when exhibited by the Consul. Certain of his remarks suggested however that his objection was largely to the appearance of the Article in the Treaty and that he might be less reluctant to accept the principle of the Article if it were embodied in an unpubli shed/unpublished exchange of letters. The matter was left for further discussion. The next meeting was arranged for Friday afternoon, 22nd April, at 3 p.m./i' L'lUSGAT TR EATY. Note of eighth meetin^ with His Highness the Sultan, 22nd April. Presentj His Highness^ .Sir T. Powle a nd Mr. G- i'b s on. Article 1 (iii) j His Highness desires the last.words to read (as he formerly proposed) 'registered 'by the Omani Government and entitled to fly the flag of the Sultan'. Article 2 (2) and (3) ° His Highness was offered? and accepted? the alternative clause which reads 'should the Sultan wish to establish any monopoly in his territory such monopoly will be arranged in such a y /ay that it will not he detrimental to the trade in which nationals of His Majesty are occupied.' After the meeting? however? he indicated his wish to amend the paragraph so that it would read? 'should the Sultan wish to establish any monopoly in any part of his territory such monopoly will be arranged in such a way that it will not be detrimental to the trade in which nationals of His Majesty are at the time occupied in that part of his territory'. article 3 . His Highness now takes exception to the provision according national treatment in paragraph (l)? though he has no objection to the similar provision in paragraph (2). In paragraph (l) he said that this new provision? which does not occur in the existing Treaty? went much too far? and he was not prepared to waive his objection when it was pointed out that similar provisions occurred in the majority of commercial treaties? including treaties made e.g. with Germany? Austria and the United Kingdom. article//ri-' 2. Article 6 (2) « His Highness said he had not come to any definite conclusion on this paragraph, but his feeling was that there was no need to disturb a procedure which had been in force in Muscat for many years and worked satisfactorily to all concerned. Article 12 (3) » The amendment proposed at the seventh meeting was agreed to, in view of the conclusion reached on Article 11+. article lU » A proposal was made to the Sultan that only a short Article should be inserted in the Treaty and that the procedure contemplated in the present article should be agreed upon in an exchange of letters which would be confidential. i* draft article and draft letter were handed to him. After considerable discussion and with some reluctance the Sultan was induced to accept the proposalj subject to certain amendments in the text of the drafts. (The amended text will be included in the fresh revise of the provisional draft Treaty.) Sultan's article 7 . His Highness agreed to substitute for (b) of the points to be dealt with by an exchange of letters the following {, ('b) that the dues levied at each port should 'be on a scale commensurate with the expenditure incurred on the harbour and light facilities at that port.' He wished to supplement (c) by the words 'presided over by the Sultan's Port authority.'.ISA MTSG^T treaty . Note of ninth meeting with His Highness the Sultan^ dated 23rd ^pril. Presents His Hi.hnesSj Sir T. Powle and Mr. Gibson. The outstanding points we re discussed. Article 2 . The alternative clause offered to His Highness at the eighth meeting with the amendments proposed hy him was adopted. Article 3 (i) « / The Sultan was informed that considerable importance was attached to the principle of freedom of trade ? and for that reason ,it was felt to he necessary to press the reouest for 5f national u treatment in matters of trade. But it was not considered necessary to retain the words n as in every other respect'9 which were copied from the present Treaty. The Sultan said he had no objection to these words if they referred only to m.f.n. ? and not to national5 treatment. It was proposed to him that these words might be deleted while retaining the provision for ^national' treatment and after some discussion the Sultan agreed. Article 6 (2) . as the Sultan vms still unable to accept the draft it was proposed to him that/subject to the views of the Government of India as the party principally interested in trade with Muscat, the following simplified formula might be adopted, 'according to their market price following the normal usage of trade in Muscat'. His Highness agreed. Artic le i L l . The Sultan was informed that the amendments suggested 'by him Y/ould be adopted and he agreed to the Article and draft » letter as now amended. Th iS //# 2. This concluded the Treaty discussions as the Sultan said he had no further points to raise on the draft. It was arranged tnat he would be sent a letter enclosing a copy of the draft Treaty which represented the final outcome of the discussions with His Highness5 with the explanation that it would 'be subject to the views of the Government of India and to any further views which His Majesty ? s Government might wish to offer.lSt&gt; INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.!• 22nd April, 1938. Your Higimess, I understand that Your Highness desires to receive an explanation in writing of two points which you have raised in respect of the reference to 'Corporate bodies' in Article l(ii) of the revised provisional draft Treaty. I am accordingly directed 'by the Secretary of State to give Your Highness the following explanations: (a) The rights proposed to be granted to corporate bodies under the proposed draft are solely rights of the corporate 'bodies as such and would not in any way limit the jurisdiction of Your Highness over non-British employees of a corporate 'body as individuals. (h) In the event of a British company obtaining a concession or contr6.ot wherein they accepted the imposition of conditions or restrictions by the Government of Your Highness the terms of the concession or contract would be upheld by His Majesty's Consul even though the conditions or restrictions involved a surrender of rights . T^hich might otherwise have been claimed by the company under the Treaty. Your Highness' sincere friend, (Sd.) J.C. WALTON. I Highness I Saiyid Said bin Saiyid Taimur, K.C.I.E. , Sultan of Muscat and Oman.imik ornci. April 193a. Muscat Treaty as it hns ar.er^ed froj^ our informal conversation?? with the Stilton. 2m There is no need for me to supplitment in detail 3ife»on* s notes? on our cof!Ter?»ntien« with the Sultan and on their results, 'but it may be useful if I give my viewf? on eertnin general ^??peetfi ■ ; 1 ch influenced me in wy conduct of the negotiations. 3. In the first plaee tltere the 'ult^n*v impregnitble position. In most Treaty negotiations there ^re hmrgmtning counters on both sidefu In thin particular one the Sultan held all the card** since# briefly, if no treaty were signed before ifebrosry 1939 9 our whole position in his territories would fnll to the ground. 4. The point I was most anxious ?• bout before we .knew/ H.A«FjLfete*afe, K.C .I. I. # C.B .I. # ' .V.C. luteitifil Affairs Department, Government of India.in 2* knew the general tenor of th« Sultan*^ terms, wan th?it of Jurisdiction. If His Highness bai refused to continue thm extr^-territorial privileg© of the old Treaty under which our subjects should under the jurisdiction of the Concul 4 the result would b^ve been most awkward to eaj the lemst of it* As you are mware, not only did the Sultan not refuse this concession, but he ^ii not even nak# use of it s strong h&amp;Tgmining counter, m® I mm afraid 1 should hare been inclined to $0 if I had been in His j ^osition I This in itself, I think, argues s. considerable nmount of good will towards us on his ps rt ♦ 5» In the second place I considered it si# art important that the treaty , if possible, should be t-n agreed *im &lt;2 not an imposed** one from our side ss the stronger power. 9 lm pose^^ Treaties in the long rim do not paj, espeeimlly if with dictators, snd, of course, the ''ultsn in his sm^ll way ^nd In his own territory is a dictator. He was firmtsk enough to point out to us that in various wm.fm he could defeat the object of T^rious drsft Articles, sna still keep within the letter of the Inw, smd the instances//rt 3. instance!? be mentioned were confirmed by Beckett # to whom we referred thm point. His followed thim up by sj^ying. whieh I think is miite true, fcbmt h# by no si@an» intended to %mk% such net ion* At the nm® time, if any considerable eoreneee is left behind in his mind the result of the Treaty, the danger of hi?? succumbing to some such testation may be difficult to resist. I do not know whether by my exercising •pressure' we could h*nre obtained better terms on paper in some directions, but for the reasons just eriven, I did not think it worth while, fro® the long ■point of Tiew # to do so. the only Article over which I displayed some (cmlctil^ted) inpatienee mt His fii#hness*s attitude* was at the last interview, over the important Article 14, (now article IS) concerning which w© had gone a long way to fleeting his views, an4 Mis Highness forthwith gnr® wmy. 6. The other Article over which His Highness showed si^ns of being unreascn^fele (whether we agreed or not with him on other points he generally h«4. fairly reasonable grounds for his views? was Article 19 of his drr^ft Treaty, concerning which he strongly insisted for some time th^t the expulsion of British subjects should be at his demand alone and not, %s we put/pat forward, cm the production of evidence sufficient to satisfy out Consul* It was luite impofisible for us to mgr&amp;e to this 4mmn£ w und finally His Highness withdrew his Article in toto * 7. As things stand we think th^it, generally «fc s aking» the result of our informal conversations hus been *» dr^ft Treaty which ew^bodiss w&gt;iat we eould reaiionsbly «sTpeot ♦ snd f wh«t I regard ms stoost eoually importrmt # that tbis result has been obtained with the streti^thenin t ^nd not thm menkmnin,% of the genuimely friendly f©sling whicti His Highness hnn towards His Msjesty 1 s Soverr^ent. Tli# Br^ft Tresty if* of course subject to the further eonsideration of His Mmjssty*s SoTernment the SovernBsnt of India. 8. Both Gibson 5snd mysslf ?ars considerably imjirsssfEd with ability witli wlticH His Ei^tosss conductsd t&gt;ie negotiations w'Hieh, it ^u^t be reraip?bared # wer-e csrried on in s ls,ngusg€ (^Bglisli) foreign to hte* lytn though the Sultsn 'mmm English well, it wn mt times naturally difficult for him to express ex ctly whst hi® ideas ^-ere, whivh usees sit sted not only -i eert^in amount of f^.tience on our pert, but also involved us in drafting for him as well ss for ourselves* 9* In conclusion 1 should like to acknowledge the/the rnluable ?it^-nce which I h'-re received from Gibson t ^it^out whom it would been quite impossible to hnve nrriT€&lt;! nt the present dr«ft in so thort a time. I nm also Ptich indebted to Beckett of the 'oreign Office, ^uch of who^e time Gibson ^nd 1 took up, and from whom we received much expert advice. Sheckle of the Be*rd of trade ftlfte materially nnminteti. n* with his advice when eomtreinl ^^eetiens were under consideration. I m giving a copy of this letter to Walton r, )j xj the Residencyi Buahlre, the Htn May 1958, , ^ V / 'mid you please refer to correspondence / * flrtdimz witn ay letter aated, London, tne 2Btn April 193 g # ^ j\Qi an&lt;l copy my telegrsoa ifo.t/igB, dated 4th May 1936, forwarded under ray Printed Letter Ho*G/309 of same date, on the subject of the Muscat treaty. 2 # I do not Know whether the Government of India will have their views ready fcy next month feut, if ao, it would be most convenient if I could meet the Sultan in India either at Karachi or at Bombay, where I understand he will be for some three weeica from the Beginning of tfune. in the first place it would be more easy for me to get to Karachi than to Muscat by a day 1 ® flight either from here or Bahrain, wnile the journey either from here or Bahrain to Muscat would involve four or five days ty snip. In the second place prior to actual signature there will doubtless be some final points which %m aovernment of India would liice me to discuss with the liultan. fhis discussion will probably ta&amp;e some little time, and could be carried on more comfortably and with better chances of agreement in the comparative cool of Karachi than in tne trying summer temperature of Muscat I 5. lven if it is impossible for the treaty to be ready for signature in June, it would be a decided ad vantage to reach a final agreement then with the Sultan on/ Wbrey letcalfe, K.C.I.K.,0.3.1.,ll.V.O. Secretary to tli« SoTarnment of India in tne SjcternaX Affair a Department, Simla.on any outatandtnu points* this would enatue tae worie of translation to 6e begun. The Arabic text could then be sent to the sultan for his acceptance. thia having been done (all of which will taice time) I could Tisit Husoat In st or ember for the formal signature. 4. The actual translation of tae Treaty also baa to be considered. I find from ay arcaivea that tnis gave rise to a good deal of trouble and delay over the 1891 Treaty. I pointed out to ulbson la i.onacn that my Ternacular staff &gt; though quite adequate for ordinary translation duties, were not up to translating a document of the importance and complexity of tne Bew Treaty. 1 suggested tnis could be carried out in Xondon either by the arable expert in the India Office or by the Professors of Arabic at Oxford or Cambridge, or by the staff of the School of Oriental Studies. Alternatively the translation could be done at Simla, as was the case la the 1891 Treaty. I am sending copies af this letter to til bson and Watts. ♦ sent under P.L.Jlo.246-3 of 14/6/384 5i / 5145/38 BUSH'R' r esidency. A/o...''46'? Late- 6/^8 C0?4FiXNTlAL RECORDS INDL. OFFIGS, rt^HITEHALL 5 LONDON, S.¥. 1. 5th May, 1938 y^' /(&gt;$ y Would you kindly refer to your telegram of the Uth May, N o «T/128, a'bout the Muscat Treaty. The Sultan left London finally on the 1st May, so that I have no longer any direct contact with him. But apart from that I am afraid it would be impossible for a number of reasons to contemplate signature of the Treaty before the Sultan leaves India for Muscat. The Dominions Office are informing the Oominions^on our advice, that it is hoped to proceed to the signature of the Treaty in July , and this was earl;;/ enough from their point of view, since they wished to leave the Dominions a reasonable opportunity to raise any points about the Treaty if they should want to do so. The Colonial Office, too, wish to consult Aden and Zanzibar in connexion with the Sultan's - i A6 1 amendments of Article 1, and that is bound to take a little time. Above all we have still to receive the views of the Government of India, who will wish to examine the draft carefully. And once there is general agreement on the text there/ lie Lt.Gol. Sir Trenchard Fowle, KCIE. , C3E. IM's Consulate General, Bus hi re.% 2. there remains the matter of the translation into Arabic, which you asked us to have done in London. 7iQ propose however, if* you agree ? to have a translation made of the present draft 9 and, leave it to you to make any subsequent adjustments in the text and to prepare fair copies for signature. But in any case; much as I sympathise with your distaste for the July heat of Muscat; and although we will do what we can to accelerate matters? I am afraid we cannot see that it would be possible to hope for signature in June. I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe. At***Ji'/ss. ,1» No-^^/v-U HO IA 0?P ICE 5 1—^•cTnFWTlAL KECOROS J LONDON, S.W.I 5th May, 1938. Muscat Tre aty. i IU jx * ^^fpz+rCc' t I enclose for jrour information a copy of correspondence with Shackle about item (c) of the letter which (as shown in the margin of the draft) will he written with reference to Article 7 of the draft Treaty. Will you kindly try to hsve the suggested amendment adopted when the time comes? It does not seem likely to cause difficulty, and I understand that, subject to this amendment, the Board of Trade would be satisfied with the Article if accompanied by a letter in the terms shown m the margin. Whether the letter is written by the Sultan and acknowledged by you, or vice versa, seems immaterial. Perhaps the latter would be the more convenient, the letter then running to some such effect as, With x^ference to Article 7 of the Treaty signed by us this day I understand I/' that you are prepared to give an assurance to the following effect, etc., etc.'. 'We Lieutenant Colonel 3ir Trenchard Fowle, ICG IE . ,CBE. , H.B.M. f s Consulate General, BUSHIRE* This/ J.P.2. This ? of course^is subject to the viev/s of the Government of India on Article 7 and the proposed assurances of the Sultan,, and I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosures to Metcalfe, cm^ cth-3172/38. f&amp;] BOARD OP TRADE, GREAT GEORGE STREET, S.W.I 27th April, 1938. Dear Gibson, You may remember that one of the points made by our Mercantile Marine Department on Article 7 of the Sultan's draft relating to harbour etc. dues was that the f, {f9 meaning of his proviso (c) is not clear as it stands. We suggest that it should be amended to read as follows 'That the special Board, v/hich will be presided over by the Sultan's Port Authority, shall consist of Omani members and British members in equal numbers ,, . We realise, of course, that this arrangement will mean that the casting vote will remain always with the Muscat authorities, but that appears inevitable. If you see no objection would you kindly have our revised wording incorporated in the draft Treaty which you are about to send to the Sultan. Yours sincerely, (SD.) R.J.SHACKLE. p.Gibson, Esq,,2,5172/38. INDIA OFFICE 5 17HITEHALL, S.7.1 5th May, 1958, Dear Shackle, I am/sorry for the delay in thanking you for your letter of the 27th April (O.H.T.7154/33) in which you/suggested an arnendiiient of the Sultan's promise (c) in the letter which will refer to Article 7 draft Muscat Treaty (harbour dues etc.). It was unfortunately too late to incorporate your suggestion in the draft which was given to the Sultan, hut we Y/ill ask Fowle to note the suggestion and try to have the revised wording adopted when he meets the Sultan in Muscat. Yours sincerely, iSgd.) ii, p. QimoM Shackle, Esq,, |oard of Trade, G-t.George Street S. ;W. 135/86 / 61 telegram ^ i-rom Political Heaident, iiuahire. •i'o Hia Majeaty's aeoretary of State for India 9 London* Copy l^y post to Secretary to the Govermient of India, External iiffaira department, Simla Ho. 192. Dated the 19th ^ay 1938 • S'owle to Gibson# I have asked Watts to let you hare his address and suggest you show him Muscat draft treaty on which his local knowledge would be useful especially in regard to Articles 4 to 7, 13, 15 and 16« i suggest his comments if any be sent to Goverianent of India and myself as soon as possible# BRITOOmUL. 19^*08 . d. ivr.'sf).n» , JCTERNAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT. SIMLA, the . ^ ^ 1958 * / ^ Forwarded with the oorr .pliments of the Secretary. ® (Demi -official letter to India Office, London. No .F.65 -1 ^8, dated the May 1938). Ri )SH1RE RESIDENCY. Wo-.. Date..m/^-- To CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS The Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel Sir T.C J/. Fowle, , KCIE., QBE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ( U\fh )3*1 Telegram Frora To Repeated to ii.M , a Secretary of State for India, London* Political Keaident, Bushire# Secretary to the Government of india, iSxternal Affairs Department, Simla* Mo. 1005 Dated 26th received 27th May 1938• i'owle from Gibson* of 4 th te.y My letter dated 5th May Ho •V.Z.ZlAb Translation of Draft Muscat Treaty* Do you agree with procedure proposed^ Translation in London would have to be entrusted to School of Oriental Studies who estimate cost at £ 77/ odd which includes one duplicate copy* Secretary of State for India. /K/l^ Copy sent to P#A®Muscat under i ; «L*i y io«296 , -S, dated 27»5*38. ^l&gt;' .J/ ''is!si m Tele gram From To Repeated to Political Hesident, -tfushire. H.M l s Secretary of State for J-ndiat London. Secretary to the Ggvernmeiit of J-ndia, External Affairs Department, Simla. '^opy 'by post Political Agent, Muscat. Kb. Ill Dated 27th May 1938. P y] b Your telegram Ho. 1005 of May 26th. Muscat Treaty. 1 agree. I presume translation can be sent by air mail to -fc-arachi before middle of June ? itowle. CloDy sent to P .A.Muscat under P.L. Ho •296-S, dated 27.5.3835^6 gogfldential Residency, Bu ah Ire, the 2b th May 1956 f), r&gt; ,^0# ^00' 3 '] b 0 A c please refer to corresponaence eiiaiag witn my telegram 50.111, dated 27tn May 193B, regarding trie Muaoat Treaty. 2. There is one important matter which is not provided for in the Treaty, and which we muaz get settled eitner in the Treaty or ay a letter from tne aultan i.e. oonaular exemption from customs dasa (Article 5) and from the prohibitions which the Sultan can iapose under ^ p • 15- O Article 9. Otherwise the CJonsjiil may not be atole to get nig wtsialtyi or arms for hla own use, at all, or only after paying a prohibitive duty, suca as there is e .g. in Iran. Likewise there is tae qaeBtion of the importation of cars, furniture etc., etc., Hitherto, taou^n it was not apeo- ifically laid do^ in the axistiny treaty, the Oonsul a,i*i his ataff have enjoyed exeuptloa fran payment of cuatoras duty (no question of prohibition has arisen as that ia not permitted under tne existing treaty). «e shall not therefore be asking for anything whxen we nare not enjoyed in tne past* 3. I recollect that at one of our conversations in connection witn Article 9 (3)(c) of the draft Treaty the sultan wisned to nave alcohol specifically mentioned. We pointed out to him that this was unnecessary as he already nad general powers of prohibition. I added that I presumed/ Gibson, inquire, The India Office, Xond on.presumed he would have no objection to tiie Consul getting his alcohol, and he said none whatever, so there should rl ot be much difficulty in getting thia privilege, but we had better have it down in writing. l*nis is all tne niore necessary as in uheee days consular status does not ipso facto in most countties, e.g» in Iran, accord customs exemption, 4, The Sultan is more likely to agree if we had these privileges recorded in a letter and not in the freaxy, and I enclose a draft of a letter from him to me. It is of an omnibus nature and, so far as customs dues are concerned, covers not only alconol but the oxher articles indicated in paragraph 2 above. 5. rhere Is also the somewhax more complicated question of consular immunity from ttxati (a) State Ta-xes. The mo^t sweeping of these which the Sultan could impose would, I luaasjine, be c -ji Income taxs I suppose tnat tnere Is no qufotion of the Consul or nis staff having to pay vhi&amp; as their income is derived from outside tne country• V q do not, for Ingtanofe, pay this tax in Iran, where it nas been impb^ed in laxe years. I do not know whether there are ariy other similar xaxes of a general nature which could be applied to the uonsul and nis staff ? (fc) Municipal Taxea. W sucn tax levied on houses would presumably not be paid either oy the Consul or tnose of hia staff who lived in nouses owned oy Government. Otner municipal taxes would De xnose not levied on tnis basis e.g. for sanitary services in tne town. I tninK that/-3- m th^t aa a matter of principle the Consul snoula not pay municipal taxes, but that his staff might pay such taxes unless it is possible to secure exemption for them. In the draft letter, viae G tnereof, I have included exemption from taxation for tne consulate staff. If tne Sultan objects strongly to this however, I propose to mafce a gesture by substituting the following: That as heretofore His Majesty's Consul shall be exempt from all forms of taxation. (ii). That the staff of His Majesty's Consul shall be exempt from all forms of taxation otner than municipal.* I nmild be grateful for an early reply, if possible by telegram, as to whether I car' proceed on trie above line© when I meet ;he Oultan# I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalte and *atts. sent under P # L.Ho.301-3 of 28/b/38.Draft letter from HI3 Highaesa tne Sulsafl of Muscat to the Hon 1 Die the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. With reference to the conver^ati on which we had on the , on the subject of the new Treaty between His Majesty's Government and aiyself» I am pleased to confirm A- tnat the following roods chall be exempted from payment of customs dues: {i) goods imported for cffioial use of His Majesty 1 s Consulate. (ii) goods imported for their personal use cy His Majesty's Oonsiil ana xxis staff. B. that any prohibition or restriction impose on the importation of goods into Oraani terr itory shall not apply to the goods mentioned in paragraph A (i) and (ii) above. C* Tnat as heretofore His Majesty's Coneul ana his staff shall be exempted from all i orms of taxation./SO P .Z. 3527/1938. Enclosure in Colonial Office Covering Hote dated 18th May, 1938. Colonial Office, Downing Street, 16 May, 1938. Sir, ^ I have the honour to refer to my despatch No.213 of the 24th of September last enclosing copies of 229 25th correspondence relating to the desire of the Sultan of Muscat to revise the Anglo-Muscat Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation of 1891. 2. Negotiations for the revision of the Treaty have recently taken place in London ana I now enclose, for your p. ■ information, the draft of a new Treaty embodying the results of the informal discussions with the Sultan. A p it-y - copy of a let er to the Sultan is also enclosed. 3. An important difference between the present draft Treaty and the Treaty of 1891 is that whereas the latter applied only to British subjects, including subjects of the native States in India, the draft Treaty covers all subjects of His Majesty and all persons under Hie protection wherever domiciled. In this connection it will ■. i ; , ' i ^' ^0 *0 f «* £ | be observed from the marginal notes to Articles 1 and 19^ that the Sultan desires to exclude :frooi the scope cf the proposed Treaty the British-protected persons belonging to the Arab Sheikhdoms of the lersian Gulf and to the I to tectorates of Aden and Zanzibar• 4. m OFFICES ADMINISTJ'.HING THE GOVERNMENT OF181 4, So far as the Arab Sheikhdoms ara concerned, the iolitioal Resident in the i-ereian Gulf sees no otijeotion to the atnendnents desired by the Sultan and the India Office would prefer that hio wishes in regard to Aden and Zanzibar should be met if this is at all , cosible. The India Office have requested that the oatter my be regarded as urgent and I should th erefore bo obliged if you will inf orm tac b tele graph as soon as possible'whether you see any objection to the exclusion of tien from the scope of the Treaty. Zanzibar 5, SO far as the question of extrc-terr iter ial jurisdiction is concerned, there is no legal objection in principle to differentiation between British subjects and British protected persons for this purpose. In the event, therefore, of yowr desiring that A ^ eR should be permitted to accede to the Treaty you may be'willing to agree that persons under Ilia lisjesty's protection in the V^Tl ■„ rotecLorate should be excluded from Zanzibar the privilege of trial by the Consular authorities uaaer p.l^k Article 13 of the draft Treaty. 6. The Sultan made it clear, however, in the course of the discussions, that he wished also to exclude such persons from the trading benefits accorded in the draft Treaty. I am not isiosed to meet the desire the Sultan on this point sinee acquiescence tnerein would -.... I jm i ii ■tiiwri r r' i '' »:&gt;-&gt;•.&gt;: ■ '*&gt;'**• •■«■««! iiiiimiWi api^F~to 'create an ut.xciru: ie precedent. It would also mean that, for all practical .urposeu, ac^assion to the Treaty would be of no advantage to Adey Zanzibar0/B&gt; 7, As it will probably be very difficult, however, to move the Sultan from the position which he has taken up in regard to this point I truat that you will be able to reech the conclusion that it is not neceseary for Ade.Q ' —| ^ to accede to the freaty. 8 # I am addreaeing a similar, doapatch to the m-itish resident at Zamihar * Governor of Aden# I have, otCe (Signed) HAELH;OE. doj^ u^t k K—' PL. Af-So^Telegram i'roia To Repeated to Secretary to the Cioveninient of indiaj External Affairs Department, ^irala. Political Resident, xiushire. a Secretary of State for India, London. 1*0.883 Dated and received 30th May 1938 Deiai-official, .For Fowle. of 14th May. /r Itour demi-official letter i'»o.245-S iiuscat Treaty. 2. We have not yet formulated our views on final draft of Treaty but will endeavour to do so by June 7th. We agree that provided we can have our views ready in time it would be oon- -venient for you to meet Sultan in J-ndia. 2 I Meanwhile we suggest that you should get into touch with sultan as soon as he arrives at -oombay and arrange meeting with him provisionally for some time in the middle of June either at Karachi or Bombay as may be convenient. We will let you know as soon as possible when our views on Treaty will 'be ready. Forei gn \^h ^ /&gt; C t ^ c &gt;Tele gram irora s Secretary of i&gt;tate for India, ^ London. 10 Secretary to the Uovernraent of mdia External Affairs department, ^imla# Repeated to -folitical iiesident, ^ushire# ^o#1038 Bated lat received 2nd June 1938# Metcalfe from Peel, *our telegram Mo. 883 of May 30th to itowle• Muscat Treaty# While there might be advantage in a discussion at Bombay on any points in draft which Government of mdia may wish to make such discussion could hardly take the form of final agreement on text. Any alteration of the existing draft would of course be subject to the approval of ills Majesty 1 Government. further even if Colonial office dif- -ficulty over 3ultan f s amendments of Article I is removed in time there remains the difficulty that Dominions have been given to understand that Treaty will not be finally concluded before July. Whether or not i^'owle meets Sultan in India in June we are inclined subject to your views to think it desirable to carry out programme agreed to v/i th Sultan in London viz. Resident should visit Muscat in ^uly for conclusion and signature of treaty V This would seem to be possible unless Sultan should raise some fresh points or Government of india see substantial difficulties ocdSKlxtog: in existing draft. Question of preparing Arabic trans- -lation/2 V 3 translation is presumably of urgency only if we are to look forward to signature in Uuly# ±&gt;o you consider it preferable that translation 2houId be done in London isee Gibson's telegram of 26th May to itowle regarding cost) or in Simla# if translation is to be treated as matter of urgency and is to be done in London it might save time if existing draft were translated at once leaving subsequent amendaents of text to be translated by i^'owle who would also prepare finally approved text for signa^ •ture« Sucess of this procedure depends on whether Government of India are likely to accept draft sub- -stantially as it now stands* We should be glad to have your views. Secretary of State for J-ndia. | Sovf' fa '6./ Telegram From Political Resident, -buahire. To Secretary to the UoverniDent of mdia iixternal Affairs Department, Simla. Repeated to H.M , s Secretary of State for India London* Copy by post Political Agent, Muscat# JN o. 219 Dated 3rd June 1938# j'ov/le to Me tcalf e • India Office telegram ^o. 1038 of lat June. Muscat treaty. I do not think it possible for xreaty to be concluded and signed at Muscat in one stage. of/meeting Sultan in India and settling with the con- -currence of His Majesty^s Government and the Hovern- -ment of i-ndia points if any raised by Government of India, also point (c) of letters connected with Artd- -cle 7 vide India Office letter ^o#P*2. 3172 of May 5th. (b) if translation of present draft and letters can reach Karachi in time getting Sultan's acceptance thereof. If not final, draft Arabic version will have to be sent to ^ultan later for his acceptance. His Majesty's Government of draft finally agreed on to Colonies and Dominions. -don or Simla of signature copies in Arabic and English. Jfirst stage would i suggest consist ia&gt; Second stage. Communication by lliird stage. Preparation in Lon- 5. of Treaty at Muscat Fourth and last stage. SignatureI&gt; 2. 6• I am telegraphing Sultan saying it may be necessary for me to meet him in India this month and suggesting dates* if'owle £ 1~i St^h. #19* j roin Political Resideiit;, Busuire. To Gniei Secretary to zae Government 01 Bombay KO.220 Dated trie 5rd June following tor Sultaii 01 Muscat begins J It may be necessary for me to meet /our Hignness in India i'or final discuss ion on rreaty oelore its signature at a later date in Muscat. As I cannot be absent from my post for too long would it be con venient for me to meet Your Hignness at Karacni wnere I can arrive on lotn June or 25rd June ? Jiscussions snould not taKe more tnan a weeic. Grateful if four Hignness would telegrapn reply. political nesiaent. Ends* Brit c oils ui. rfsi -By Air Mail. Bys^fTe res'DENGY! rm 3/6/J8 ea.if:32Nr,A!, REgQiffis v/i- INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, I MAY 1938 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. The Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf. 4963 2000 7.36I.Z.Sl 74 / 1938 * I(j0 18232 /38 I COLONIAL OFFICE, DOWNING STREET, S.W.I 26th April, 1938. IMMEDIATE. Dear Gibson, I have been looking at the draft Treaty with Muscat which I understand you propose to submit provisionally to the Sultan. My interest lies in the definition of 'nationals' which would exclude persons under His Majesty^ protection in the Aden Protectorate. We do not object, if you think it necessary, to the exclusion of such persons from the privilege of trial by the Consular authorities under Article 13 of the draft Treaty; but we consider that they should be entitled to all the coramerGial and trading advantages secured to British subjects by other articles of the draft. We should not, therefore, without consultation with the Aden authorities, willingly agree to the presentation to the Sultan of a draft Treaty which definitely excluded them from these advantages. The position of Zanzibar also requires consideration and Dawe will look into this and let you have his views as soon as possible. Yours sincerely (SB.) H. R. GOWELL p U , tvlo 4. ^ Gibson, Esq.IV INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.1 p 2,3174/38. May, 1938 # r Dear Gowell, I am sorrs/' for the delay in thanking you for your letter of the 26th April (No* 15332/38) aloout the Muscat Treaty. From the copies sent to Fleming you will have seen ^ K'i»1 f that in Article 1 of 1 the draft (and also in Article 19J we have shoY /n the amendments desired by the Sultan in the margin instead of putting them into the body of the draft. The Sultan seemed to attach a quite disproportionate importance to the exclusion from the scope of the Treaty of British -protected persons 'belonging to the Aden Protectorate and Zanzibar as Y /ell as to the Arab Sheikhdoms of the Gulf., and we tried unsuccessfully to persuade him to accept a compromise by y /hich these persons would come under his jurisdiction but at the same time enjoy the commercial advantages of the Treaty# All of them are of course excluded from the scope of the existing Treaty* and the Political Resident sees no objection to the Sultan's amendments so far as they refer to the States of the Persian Gulf. We should feel relieved if you could also agree in respect/ bell, Esq., C.M.G. , ( Colonial Office, S.W.I ^ p l ivU- 4- 6^«7,I*! 7 ' 2, respect of the Aden Protectorate and Zanzibar, but in any case we should be very grateful if any consultation v/ith the Aden and Zanzibar authorities that is thought desirable could be carried out as quickly as possible so that we may have your views at an early date. We hope that it may be possible to send the Political Resident the necessary instructions in time to enable him to negotiate and conclude the Treaty in July, Yours sincerely, J. P. QilSSOM113 Telegrara J^rom Secretary to the UoverniDent of india, External Affairs department, Simla. To K.M 1 s Secretary of State for india, London# Repeated to Irolitical Resident, -^ushire# Mq. 910 J3ated 5th received 6th June 1938. Peel from Metcalfe* Your telegram ^o# 1038 of 1st June /■ I ' ' and Fov/le * s telegram ^o» 2 19 of 3rd June. ' We have only a very few comments to make on final draft of treaty and hope that these will te ready in about a week s tine. consider it immaterial whether Js'owle discusses points ?/e pro- -pose to raise and other outstanding points in India within next fortnight or in Muscat after Sultan's return there♦ it would in any case appear improbable from stages enumerated in -b^wle's telegram that treaty will be ready for final signature in July. 2m it appears that -fc'owle will in any case have to see Sultan twice once for discussion of outstanding points and once for final signature of Treaty. ^e suggest that it should be left to him to decide in consultation if necessary with Sultan whether it will be more convenient for first interview to take place while Sultan is still in J-ndia or shortly after his return to Muscat. We could probably arrange for trans- -lation of draft treaty by an official of Punjab iiiduca- -tional Service at a cost not exceeding K s# 200/- • Please/m ^lease telegraph whether we should try to arrange accordingly if go translation of latest draft might be undertaken at once as we shall have very i?few) alterations to suggest# foreign Ccrb ^a Scnf u^sccl S &amp;35/86 11^ Telegram i .Uf .C. ^ rom Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay. To Political Resident, Bushire. Ko. Hil. Dated and received the 6th June 1938. Your telegram dated the 3rd June. Following from Sultan of Muscat begins: Thanks for your telegram. I shall be pleased to meet you at Karachi on June 23rd. Will leave T .■■II !■ .—A Bombay Jun e 21 st arriving June 23rd afternoon. Will stay at Killarney Hotel. Please confirm. Sultan of Muscat. Snds. SBOKBTaRY GOVBRNMEliT OP BOMBAY. ?^^ r 38.35/86 Telegram ^ iroiri Political Resident, -Bushire. 10 Secretary to the Goverrmient of India, External Affaira Department, fcttmla. Repeated to H.M t a Secretary of State for India, London. aopy by poat Political Agent, muscat. Ho. 229 Dated 7 th June 1938. [ CJorreapondenoe ending with your telegram -Uo. 910 of June 5th. Sultan haa telegraphed that he can meet me at -Karachi June 23rd on which date ± propose to meet hiro. 2. I suggest that translation of latest draft of treaty and connected letters should be carried - out as proposed in your paragraph 3 and be sent to me in duplicate care of General Post Office Karachi to await arrival. 3. As i t will not be much use my taking up with Sultan Government of jLndia*s points until con- -currence of His Majesty's Government in these have been obtained J- trust it will be possible for latter to be * communicated to me at Karachi. 4. I should also be glad to have approval of proposals re consular privileges contained in my letter ^o. 300 -S of 26th May to India uffice. iTowle « v Copy sent to Muscat under P.L..N0.343-i&gt; of 7.6.38 %ab/se in Telegram Q From Secretary of State for India, London* To Government of India, External Affairs Department^ Simla. Repeated Political Kesident, Bushire. No.lOYo# Dated bth received 9th June 1936. Metcalfe from Peel. jx * Your telegram No.910 of June Dth. Muscat Treaty. 2. V/e agree with suggestion in paragraph 2 of your telegram on the understanding that if Fowle meets Sultan in June it will not be for the purpose of final agreement on text and that any conclusions reached with Sultan are subject to the approval of His Majesty's Government. 3. My immediately succeeding telegram contains points so far raised here on existing draft which Fowle could discuss with Sultan at the same time as points raised by the Government of India. 4 # in view of heavier cost of translating the Treaty in London we should be glad if you would pursue your suggestion to have work done in India and let me know whether you have been able to arrange this. Will you also in that case have Arabic and English copies prepared for signature in due course ? Foreign Office will require one signed copy and one duplicate of each version. /As regards programme I should explain the second stage of Fowled telegram of June 3rd does not arise* Dominions have received present draft and no further communication is intended to be made to them or to the Colonies until Treaty has been signed• It does not yet seem necessary to rule out the possibility of signature in July and we might if you agree proceed at once to obtain the necessary full powers to enable Fowle to sign when Treaty is ready. A- 1 6. With reference to Fowle's telegram of June 7th and your telegram No 91b dated June 8th every effort will be made to communicate His Majesty's Government's views on Government of India's comments before June 23rd. Secretary of State for India C.V.A. oTelegram q ^om H.M. Secretary of state for Inaia, Londoa. T 0 Government of India, External Affairs Depart- ment, Simla. Repeated Political Resident, Busnire. fto.1076 Dated tne 8tn June received 9tn June 1956. Metcalfe from Peel &gt; 2. Muscat Treaty* Following are alterations in latest draft whicn nave been proposed nere up to present and to wnicn tfowle snould seek Sultan's agreement if ne meets nim in Inaia tnis montn to discuss points raised by Sovermaent of India. ^ ^ '/O^ u * i Article 1 (v). J'or tne present opening words substitute nne term foreign country snail mean etc.'. Explanation: tne pnrase ^rnost favoured nation^ does not appear in latest draft# (b) Article 7. As already indicated for para- grapn (c) or letter auOstitute 'That tae special board *aian will be presiaea over by Sultan's Port Autnonty snail con sist of Qtnani members ana Bricisn members in equal numbers'. (c) Article 13 (i)'. After 'saall' (15tn word) insert 'subject to any rignt of appeal wnicn His Majesty's Grovernment may provide 1 *. jiXplanat ion « It is obviously essential to Preserve existing rignt of appeal to court oi Political Resident. Tnere is no reason for supposixig taat Sultan would object to it and so far as ne is concerned amendment is pro bably unnecessary. It is tnougnt ctesiraoie only as saie- guard against possible objection hy a future Sultan baaea on exces sively/3&gt; jsi Xele gram if'rom To Repeated to Secretary to the UoTernment of Indian Bxternal Affairs Department,^imla* Political Kesident, -^uahire* H.M's Secretary of State for J-ndia, London. ^0.918 Dated and received 8th June 1938 /5 Jj'owle from Metcalfe. My telegram -^o. 910 of 5th June We are posting our oommenta on latest draft treaty by air mail of 9th June to India Office and to you at isushire via Bahrain. Foreign A'1^, IS 6 telegram i,roin Secretary to the UoverniDent of xndia, External Affairs Department, iiimla. 10 Political He si dent, i^ushire. Repeated to H.M's Secretary of State for India, Jbondo n# i^o. 925 Dated 8th received 9th June 1938. A'/f* - Your telegram JM q • 229 of 7th June. 2» Heference paragraph 2. in view of ahortneaa of time we are making arrangements for translation of draft treaty as proposed in paragraph ^ k ' 3 of my telegram Mo. 910 without waiting to hear further fuom His M.ajesty , s Government. iiJven so it is doubtful if translation will be ready for despatch to Harachi by 23rd June. K 3# Heference paragraph4. Sjb far as y Government of India are concerned they concur in proposals regarding consular privileges provided that no undertaking is given to Sultan for reciprocal treatment of his Consul in India, if such reciprocal treatment is demanded we should have to consider carefully and could probably not agree toib) and (c&gt;. foreigneM Tele gram s'toid To ^0.235 i)ated 9th June 1938. G.T.C. Political Resident, i^ushire -Political Agent, Bahrain. Government of India are posting you by air mail of 9th June papers for me. If received in time please send by up slow mail otherwise bring on board at Bahrain. Jj'owle 1 p J . , ^Jj J,;,'; 3i' i ; / '■ ; ■- ■ - uW ■ ^|i- isJU Telegram From To 4. Political Kesident, i3ushire« H.M'a Secretary of State for India, London. Bo .241 Dated iOth June 1938 • Muscat Treaty. Greateful if you could send say three spare copies of draft enclosed with your Printed Letter P.Z.2976 of April 30th to Bahrain where i call 19th June. J'owle •-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000181_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/412</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000181</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/412</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 35/86 V A. 77 Muscat Commercial Treaty'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (214 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: This file has foliation numbers that begin on the front cover and end on the back cover.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to the negotiations in London with the Sultan of Muscat over articles for inclusion in a new treaty 'to replace the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation signed at Muscat on the 19th March, 1891, which terminates on the 11th February, 1939.' The file includes drafts of the articles 1 to 23 with notes in the margin where the Sultan proposed a different wording. Correspondents include the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; India Office, Whitehall; Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department; and the Colonial Office, London.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Muscat (1891)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000181#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>