<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000074_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T04:37:38.940Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I I/&gt; Mr. Kordi^ , Accountant General’s Department y jT\ have a copy of my letter of to whicr^-tJ^ -attached is a reply. 3rd May to Major Dredge In the light of this reply I do not think we are required to take any action with the Government of India at this stage. The Government of India will, no doubt, submit their account in due course for reimbursement moiety of diplomatic and consular expenditure incurred by them with regard to posts on the Persian side during the year 1947/8&gt; *&amp;+ quite separately from their request for total reimbursement of money expended on behalf of H.M.G, under the Residency Budget (i.e. the Arab side). It is not clear how they will deal with expenditure on the P.W.D. staff which were emoloved both on the Persian and Arab sides jointly, but we may perhaps wait and see how the}’’ do it. In point of fa t we provided in the Residency Budget for one half of the total P.V/.D. grant covering joint establishment’for both the Persian and Arab sides. You may care to retain a copy of this note and of the Residency letter of 2jrd August for your file.hniv D.O. NO. 2176(93/5) FILP copy PERSIAN GllLF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 23rd August, 1948. s JF ~) l : n:&gt; ? * u / JLJ ^T'Sk. /u (NO ^XEO \ Would you please refer to your Demi-Official letter No. Pol(Ext) 15 964/48 dated the 3rd Lay, 1948, about the Residency budget for 1947-48? 3. Paragraph £(a). Indian Treasuries on the Arab side oi the Gulf did not pay any of the staff in the Persian posts during 1947-48 and it would, therefore, appear that their pay is a fair charge on His Majesty's Government. 3. Paragraph 2(b). The Public Works Department stair were entirely maintained by the Government of India and no- payments on the upkeep of the buildings tbn the Persian side were maae from Resiaency Funds provided by the United Kingdom Government. / -4 F.A.K. Harrison, Esquire. Commonwealth Relations Office,/ Downing Btrewt, Pol. Bxt. 1596^/46. Lr tL Dear Dredge, August, 1943. *ould you please refer to ray letter Pol. 15964/46, of the 1&gt;%C lihj, in connection with the Keside&amp;ey Budget for 1947-48. May I aspect ehortly to receive a reply to this letter. Yours sincerely. frA. ft WARfMS^.* A. L. A. Dredge Ksq. , Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrein.EXTOS? LETTER Fro® To Repeated RFFCrlJ BAHRAIN. FOREIGN NSW DEL T d CROSFC.LONDON. ACCOUNTS, NFT DF —61/2. Bahrain, the 31at ‘larch, 1948. R eapprorriation for the financial year.1947-48(fjoal ) Reappropriation Staterent duly sanctioned together with an explanatory statement of the anticipated excesses and savings in the Budccet Appropriations of the Persian Gulf Residency for the 1947-48(final) is forwarded herewith. 2. A statement showing the details of the arounts surrendered is also enclosed. = s == RFPGU®»= The issue of the above has been authorised Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bahrain.0) CQi'diCKyVEALTH ESLATIOKS OFFICE, EXTSRNiiL DSPiiRESNT EXPH3S3 LETTER (/JR I^JL) 4 it ihis an original message sent by air mail to save ^ W j uv^ ^^raphac expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the ■ A expedition as if it had been telegraphed; • Reptd.to• Political Resident, Persian Gulf, United Kingdom High Ext, 912/48 Your Express Letter No.P. 16/55/47 of 22nd January, 1946. Deputation of Major M.P.O'C. Tandy. 2. United Kingdom Government agree that instead of 'dearness allowance' of Rs.150 per mensem Tandy should receive 'war allowance' at Rs,263 per mensem for period of his deputation. In view of deputation allowance also being paid it is assumed that former local compensatory allowance of Rs.150 per mensem is not payable in addition*. ' L x 3* ^ _ii.is express letter is being repeated to the Government of India/ Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, with reference to para*5 of my despatch to the Government of India No. nxt,2ob0/47 of 26thJanuary, 1948, in connection with arrangements for payraent of Persian Gulf staff and audit for financial year 1947-8. Secretary oi State fer Co.m .on /ealth Relations To Government of Pakistan, Mi and Common 1 ./ealth Relation Ministry of Foreign Affairs Commissioner in Pakistan and Government of India, Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations Dated F. A. HAKRISOW The issue of the above has been dui}. authorised,( 'SQ3/34.K2 ( 3/4cS )g ) goi^ tdenti ol Dear Hay # FOHEIGIT OFFICB, .1. X5th Jraroh, 1948. Please refer to Caccia’s letter of 28th January to rae, copied to you, on the subject of the establishment of a lilseion Fund to meet certain representational expenditure previously covered by the item included in the Persian Gulf budget, to meet 'Secret Service Funds'. I am glad to say that we have now obtained sanction to Caccia’s recaouendation, namely that the sum of £1,000 be pix&gt;vided for an experimental period of one year from 1st April, 1948 for the creation of a Mission Fan^ from which expenditure coming under heads (a), (b) and (c ) as described in the first paragraph of Qaeda*a letter, is to be met. The allocation of the fund between the Residency and the Agencies is left to your discretion, but we should like to have details in due course of the amounts allotted to oach post. The Political Agents should report to you qu rterly details of the suras spent vith vouchers (if any), and we should lime you to let us have with your quarterly account a statement, in triplicate, showing the names and posts of officers who have drawn on the fund during the quarter, together with u brief report of the purpose of each payment, and the circumstances necessitating it. The statement shoule end with a certificate signed by you in the following terms 'I hereby certify that pounds ^avo been expended as shown in the above statement from this year’s Mission Fund of £ under my administration during the quarter ended that I have examined the subsequent accounts submitted to me by these officers, and that I am satisfied that the money has been spent for the purpose for wide h it was allocated'. Any vouchers submitted to you should be kept for a minimum period of two years and until they have boon seen by an I (Specter should he desire to examine them. The only vouchers which accompany your statement are receipts from the Political A cats for moneys allocated to them# As stated by Caccia in his letter referred to above the object of the Fund is 'care and main onance' and v/e would ask you to impress upon the Political Agents the need to keep expenditure as low as possible, that is within such limits as will enable them to maintain only those contacts likely to prove useful sources of information* Jmm s£' i From To Repeated EXPRESS LETTER . PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, REPffiU, BAHRAIN. FOREIGN, NEW DELHI. • CROSEC, LONDON. ACCOUNTS, NEW DELHI. BAHRAIN. No.426-61/2. Dated 16th February, 1948. A statement of anticipated excesses and savings in respect of budget grants for Bushire for the year 1947-48 forwarded by the Vice-Consul, Bushire to this Residency is enclosed. 2. As'posts in Persia are now under the administrative control of British Embassy, Tehran, a copy of the statement is being forwarded to them to deal with the matter from there. 3. a re-appropriation statement duly sanctioned to gether with an explanatory statement of the anticipated excesses and savings in the_Budget Appropriations of this Residency and its subordinate offices on the -'•Arab side of the Gulf for the current financial year has already been forwarded under this Residency Express Letter No.207-61/2, d ated th e 26th Janu ary, 194 8^_ = REPGU = The issue of the above has been authorised. c \ Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. t Copy to (1) The British Embassy, Tehran, for favour of necessary action. (2) The Vice-Consul, Bushire, with the remark that all budget and accounts matters con cerning Bushire should be referred to the British Embassy, Tehran. J ■IV Frof* Bahrain. FORKTON, Mew Delhi isxrm^s LFTTOR. ;o Repeated CROSSC, London ACCOUNTS, New Delhi No. £ o?-SI/' 5 Bahrain January, 194B Baapprojr iatio n fo r Y^ar IH/diS Reappropriation Statement No. ? duly sanctioned together with an explanatory statement of the anticipated excesses and aatin^s in the Budget Appropriations of the Persian Gulf Residency for the year 1947-48 is forwarded herewith. 2 # A statement showing the details of the amounts surrendered is also enclosed. r il « RRPdDf « The issue of the aboxe has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.&gt; EXTERNAL. Pi*fi«P^q|»4fei!^Department. NOTES FOR REGISTRY. ,/ REGISTER NO. Ext.2880/47. 194 s... Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary ' 1 A' Persian Gulf Residency Budget for Financial Year 1947/48. Secretary of State / A Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State Box/Table / / — / l Jjt’O tf U-' f) a fo« 0 __ Draf-TLqftter-to Government of India. FOR^USE.BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. hi Draft Letter to Political Resident. htjL (*A***L J|t) JAN \mttw- Political uesident^J Persian Gulf. DRAFT LlffTER U 2 6 JAN 1948 2 K y Sir, c °Py &gt;/, ^ ^A.G.Departmen^^ Services andyj’inance Trea« lepantment, ' j y, try. ■/y •■■ &gt; &gt;s y/ I am directed by the Secretary of State for Cenmonwealth Relations to refer to your printed letter No. 913-BFdatedL 16th April, 1947* on the subject of the budget estimates for the Persian Gulf administration for 1947-48, and to say that these estimates have no* received the approval of His Majesty's Government subject to certain modifications. These modifications together with the decisions taken on the question of travelling allowance, rules for the use of Government cars and the Political Resident's powers of re-appropriation are given in my letter No ffra^ited ^of which a copy is enclosed. X* &amp; In this connection I am also to /j % 0 &amp; L-c^Ut' l *-c l zvt~ l )&gt;'i lu^i forward for^nir information copies of the ftrp', /i. marginally noted inter-departmental A/« . //=*. lUo/o^ /correspondencecorespondence ancL a copjr of an analysis of 'the Goremment of India estimates. crlbu 3 . I ai» to add that for the current financial year the accounts of the Persian Gulf Rfesidency and subordinate $&gt;osts will be conducted and / / ' b?Ext.2880/47 Draft Paper. EXTEHHAL Department. 4 The Secretary to the G-overnment of India, Ministry of 3xternal Affairs &amp; ^ Commonwealth Relations, New Delhi* &gt;py with enclosures to:- /A.G. Dept. (Mr. Kordik (2)) ^/Treasury (Mr. Height on) /P.0, (Mr. A.J. G-ardener) Political Resident in the ^Persian G-ulf (as enclosure) - see Draft II j/N.K. High Commissioner, New Delhi &gt; spare copy to go to C/l j ^ / ( /V ^ ^ / 4.® 2 6 JAN 1948 Sir, I ara directed hy the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations to refer to Govern ment of India telegram No. 10391 dated 10 th December, 1947&gt; and to say that His Majesty's Government in trie United Kingdom gratefully acknowledge the action of the Government of India in agreeing to. their Auditor-General conducting the audit of the accounts of the Persian Gulf Administration for the current financial year aid that they accept the-tea*of -(C-JU TCP to(r4-f&gt;OuLb Rs. 10,000 as s&gt; for this service. 2. Subject to the observations given below, the United Kingdom Government approve the budget, of the posts on the Arabian shore in the Persian Gulf and at Muscat and Gv/adur for the financial year 1947 - 48 , forwarded with letter No.F. 15(11 )BHV'47 of 20th May, 1947 from the Secretary of the former Government of India in the External Affairs Department # -em i.t would be appreciated if the Auditor-General could be informed accordingly. 3. The following alterations in the Demands for Grants sanctioned try the Government of India have been approved by the Government of the United Kingdom:- I. (a) The grant of Rs.4#300 under the heal 'Pay of Officers' for all Bstablisnments for leave salaries is supplemented by a further provision of £ 12,000 to cover Leave and Pension Contributions. (10337) Wt.l4054/P.164 10,000 5/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685(t&gt;) 600 has been provided to cover sterling t overseas pay. II. Central Contract G-rant /Bahrein (Residency^. On the assumption that half the sum of Rs.40,000 is required for the Arab side ,£1,500 hnV&amp; been allotted Under this head. It is presumed that a by the G-overnment of IndiaJin therr ^‘ ir Consulates in Persia. III. Works Expenditure . On the suggestion made by the former Government of India in their letter F.15(ll)BPG/47 dated the 20 th Kay, 1947, that roughly half the expenditure provided for under the major head '50 Civil Works Central' is required for the Arab side, the sum of £8,325 has been provided for this purpose. IV. In addition, the following estimates have been approved under the head 'A#1. Major Works' - (a) Air conditioning of the Jufair Residency - £2,500 (b) Alterations to the Jufair Residency - £3,750 4 . In connection with arrangements for audit, I am to state that the United Kingdom Government have reached the following decisions which will have effect during the current financial yearJ' - (i) Travelling allowances for journeys on tour will be drawn by all persons serving in the Persian Gulf, including officers of the Foreign Service and those pn.contract, in accordance with Government of India rules. Journeys on transfer or on leave will be governed by^Foreign Office rules or by any special terms granted to the officers concerned. Personnel other than Grade A officers /willriQ&gt; Ki S r will draw all travelling allowances in accordance with Government of India rules. (ii) The use of Government motor cars will be regulated by the Government of India rules of 1912. (iii) The pay and allowances of officers will be drawn in accordance with the practice observed in the /(as amended by telegram No. 114 - 328 ) Foreign Service and explained in my telegrams / / No.14312 dated 19th November and No. 14492 dated Hi 3rd December, addressed to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, of which copies are enclosed. It is. essential for audit purposes in the United .' Kingdom that the certified accounts furnisned by the Auditor-General in India should clearly 4 exhibit in detail the sums included in the accounts in respect of the local advances of pay and allowances made to the individual officers in question. (iv) The powers of re-appropriation which the Political Resident previously enjoyed under the Government of India Budget Manual will continue. /u 5» 4 statement is enclosed showing the names of Grade A officers serving during the period 14-th August, 194-7 - 31st March, 1948 in the Persian Gulf and at Muscat, the date! of their appointment^and the pay and allowances per annum to whicn each is entitled. The conditions of leave and medical expenses to which these officers will be entitled are subject to the provisions of the Secretary ^ of State for Indian telegram No .9340 of 20th July, of / which a copy is enclosed. As the Government of India are aware, the Ministerial Staff of the old Persian Gulf s mm clerical cadre who were previously serving at the Residency and its subordinate posts on the Arab side, are to continue | to serve during the present financial year on terms agreed /upon 2upon with Jjhe United Kingdom Government, Nominal rolls giving details of these staff, together with copies of correspondence showing the terms of their service are / G-.of.I's telm. unnumbered dated 25*7. enclosed for the information of the Auditor-General, G,ii,0, telm, 10847 dated 19*3,47« '^Nominal Roll of Staff as at 15.8.47* Those on deputation from the Governments of India and Nominal Roll of Staff as at 1.10. 47 . ^ndia Office telm.9121 da 4td 16.7.47* Pol. Res. telm.812 dat^d'•24.7.47. G-.of.I's telm. unnumbered dated 25*7* enclosed for the information of the Auditor-General Pakistan will be entitled to the usual deputation ^copies only for G.of.I allowance of 25 per cent on their pay and special pay, in addition to their sanctioned emoluments. In this United Kingdom Government have agreed to payment of tuis staff on previous terms as stated up to 31 st llarch, 1948. Deputation allowance is not payable. I am to say that the United Kingdom Government also agree to the payment until 31st March, 1948 of a conveyance allowance to the Medical Officer^ (Assistant Surgeon) Koweit of Rs.70 per mensem, sanctioned by the Government of India, in Express Letter P/27(5)-£V / 46 of the 4th September. 7. In regard to the staff of the Public v/orks Department, The Government of India are aware that this question is still under consideration. The report referred to in their telegram No.9321 of 6 th November, is still awaited. 8 . On the question of the form which the audit certificate snould take, the Government of the United Kingdom are of the opinion that a simple certificate containing the words 'Audited and found correct' would be a sufficient indication of the proper scrutiny of vouchers and governing authorities, but they would be grateful for an assurance that audit of the accounts in question will be conducted no less strictly than has been the case in the past. 9. In conclusion, I am to request that the Auditor-General connection, x I am to enclose a copy of Express Letter / D.I.M./47 of the 29 th October from the Government of Pakist an -&lt; 6 . A list of Medical Staff is also enclosed. The / t: (flag Y)j \ v f © statement of account covering the period 1st April - iifth August, 1947 and thereafter for the submission of quarterly statements^ tiie last of v/hich ich to ■ ai recciveu by the 1 st September, 1943. As the appropriation account of the Commonwealth Relations Office has to be closed by the 30th September^the Government of India will appreciate the need for the final subraission of accounts by the 1 st September, 1948 at tne latest. 10 . A copy-of this letter is being sent to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ^ A. K. HARR/SONSecretary, External Dept « An amendment to para 3* I of draft I is suggested in pencil* In regard to para 3 this department has but scanty information in regard to the emoluments approved but it is observed that in the statement referred to (a) Major Moody* s ^ Foreign Service Allowance is given as £2300 instead of £1,300 ^ (b) Major Tandy’s Deputation Allowance is shown as Rs*373. Should t it not be increased to Rs* 400 fran 0/ 9th November*- Hfhen pay i plus Special Pay is increased to Rs* 1600? (c) Mr* Jones’s letter to ^ Mr* Harrison of 16th October presuraablv relates to Mr. Jackson’s appointment as Pol. Officer Trucial Cdpt and I presume that separate sanction was obtained to the rate of emoluments shown for the period while the officer was acting P.A. Bahrein and (d) Mr. Croning is not shown on the list although it was understood that he was on deputation from the Govemmant of India till the end of December. With regard to para 4- (iii) it is essential for Audit purposes that the certified accountsfurnished by India should clearly exhibit in detail the suras entered in the accounts K in respect of the local advances of pay and allowances made This Department would be glad to have two copies of the letter and enclosures as issued. , individua Lf^and perhaps you will be good yuCy' addition to this paragraph. No observations on Draft II. indTvidual^and perhaps you will be good enough to make a s MJB0) Secreta ry, A.G.Department (Mr. Kordik ) &gt;: &gt;/.■ Persian Gulf Budget - 1947-48 Please refer to your note of the 24th November. 2. The Government of India have now confirmed their agreement to their Auditor General conducting an audit of the Persian Gulf administration accounts for the current financial year and we are therefore now in a position to address them in detail on the subject and also to inform the Political Resident that the budget nas been sanctioned subject to certain modifications and to apprise him of the various decisions taken in regard to travelling allowance rules etc. 3 . I should be glad of your comments on the two drafts below. 4 . In regard to draft (i) to the Government of India, the Foreign Office have agreed to our suggestion that both travelling allowance rules and the rules covering the use of G-overnment motor cars for officers serving in the “ Persian Gulf administration should be those enforced by Government of India. The Treasury are still considering this and the draft is based on the assumption -UR they will also agree. 5. I have spoken to Robbins of the Treasury about: A, GL (a . 314,i 1948 TT — ^ the question of the fee of Rs. 10,000 to be paid to the Auditor General for his services, and the question of the form which the audit certificate should take and the assurances asked for in Knowlden's letter of the 15th October. /HeHe agrees that we are not in a position to question this sum and that in the circumstances we must accept it. He V also agrees that the assurances required by Knowlden would be covered by a request for comfimation from the Government of India that the audit of the accounts in question will be conducted no less strictly than has been the case in the pastr '%H0ar ''I** EXPRESS LETTER. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. I . , u-j t kXJ *-/ &lt;£&gt; /O? From To HEPGUj Bahrain* IND^C&gt; CROSEC, London. No. 3613-4/20* Bahrain 6th December, 1947. i Expenditure of Rs. 11,000 has been incurred on vaccines and^jedicines required o deal with the suspected ou^roreak of cholera on the Trucial Coast. I am making the money immediately available from the Residency Office Allowance but may have to apply for funds in replacement nearer the end of the financial r y ear - = REPGU = The issue of the above has been authorised* in h for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.w J t * •£ * * — Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office &gt;IQH V-v L indexed Allotted to external Department« CODE Prom: INDIA (GOVT) V Du R* 10.55 p.m#, 10th Decemoer, 1947. 8.25 p.m., 10th December, 1947. No.10391. Your tele ?ram No. 14403 November 27th regarding auditing Persian Gulf accounts for current financial year ConfirmedSeci -^ Wry, Sec retary, A.G.Department (Mr. Gam ) n - &gt; Revised estimates for 1947 - 43 in respect of the Persian Gulf Administration Please see your note of the 8 th December on this subject. &gt; 2. As regards (a) the figures shown in Donaldson’s letter to the Treasury of the 26th August, 1947, may be regarded as the revised estimate. A copy of the Treasury letter No. IF.140/04 of the 9th October approving the estimates for 1947-48 is attached. Your presumption regarding works expenditure (the air conditioning of and alterations to‘the Jufair Residency) is correct. In regard to (b) the intention is that expenditure on publicity at the rate of £1 ,£00 per annum divisible between H.M.G. and the Government of India will continue till the 31st December, 1947, and that thereafter the whole cost at this same rate will be borne by H.M.G. The provision under sub-head Z - appropriation in aid - for the receipt of £300 in respect of the sale of reading matter should be reduced to £ 200 . Treasury sanction has been obtained for the expenditure in 1946-47 of £2,314 vide their letter IF.182/274 of the 7th November of which a copy is attached. 3 . So far as (c) is concerned, I attach a copy of Treasury letter No. S.34653/3 of the 25th August, from which you will see that they have agreed in principle to the gift of ammunition to the Sheikh of Kuwait, but that they suggest that this amm u nition should be made available to the C.R.0. without payment and that the War Office and C.R.0. should arrange for a i suitable notation in their Appropriation Accounts. 57 / ih Uc-r Ujl^ U) - /*Nr * kj.Yi 1 1 / tT lu Cjl- ev. (''I / -Cx~&lt; — y? ^ C^A~ [ ^v' '7In connection with the preparation of revised estimates for 1947/48 in respect of activities in the Persian Gulf, will you please say:- , (a) Whether you agree that the figures shown in Mr,Donaldson*s l letter to the Treasury dated 26th August 1947 relating to the iQ^idency may he regarded as the revised estimate or do they require modification? ivvic ©ok* pJjLAAZ o* cAa it is presumed that the items under Subhead B viz., works expenditure, Jufair-adr conditioning and Jufair-Residency alterations, are to be borne on the India and Burma Services Vote ^ yy and not on the Ministry of Works Vote. *■ Jy (b) Whether you consider the original provision of £1,500 in respect of publicity in the Persian Gulf (salaries - £1,000; operational expenditure - £500) is still appropriate? Should provision still be made under Subhead Z - appropriations in aid-for the receipt of £300 in respect of the sale of reading natter and a contribution of 50^ of the net expenditure by the Government of India? Itovision must also be made for arrear charges frcm 1946/47 . Has Treasury sanction been obtained to the expenditure in 1946/47 amounting to £2,314? Your External 1022/47 refers. l \ (c) Whether you have any further information regarding a gift of ammunition to the Sheikh of Koweit (cost approximately £500) (£) ( External 1388/47 refers). If sanctioned, will you please furnish a ,v .copy of the Treasury ^authority and say when the bill is likely to be received and who frcm? An early reply would be appreciated.© Ext. 2683A? ^K^-Doocnbor, 1947 Dear Finch, You will ronoobor that I telephoned you rocontly on tho question of liability to British Incono Tax of persons serving under His Majesty’s Govormont in the Persian Gulf Administration, and nontionod that tho question had arisen from tho decision that from April 1st, 1947» His Majesty’s Government, should take over responsibility for administering this area from the Govomnont of India* From ttiis date until August tiio 14 th, however, tho Government of Indda continued to administer the Gulf on behalf of His Majesty's Government* I should perhaps mention for your information that for tho sake of convenience this Office will continue to deal with Persian Gulf affairs up to tho 1st April, 1948* when they v/ill be transferred to the- Foreign Office* 2* Hiring tho current financial year there will bo tho following categories of personnel at tho Persian Gulf ho si doncy and subordinate postst- I* Officers* / G*J, Finch, Esq#, Board of Inland lie venue Somerset House, Strand, Xu C.2*Vsl I« Offieora . (q) of the fbrcijjn Sorvico - (4)* (b) on contract - ( 5 ) # (c) on cloputation - a). I'oCical Gtaff . (a) Inoian Medical Dopartr.iont Jur^oons and Assistant Surgeons who aro t continuo on tiicir previous onolunonts. (b) Locally rocruitod subordinate staff who r/ill rocoivo tho seno pay and allowancos as before* Ministerial Staff . (Indian and iui.jlo-Indian) (a) Lemon on t noabors of tho fomor Persian Gulf Clerical cadre* (b) Staff who were recruited temporarily during tlic bar and who have agreed to continuo to servo in tho Gulf on their previous toms of service* Iv * A-C- ■■A .rks. Loo a. rt i on t Staff. (In di an ) (a) pomanont nenbers of tho Department. (b) persons rocruitod on a temporary basis during tho war* I (a) and (b) will have their Incano Tax deducted by tho Accountant General * s Department of this Office in the usual way. I (e) concerns Major H.L.O* C* Tandy, who is on deputation from the Government of Pakistan until the end of March, 1948 , on tho folio wine toms:- tino scale pay up to 8 th November, 1947 xvs .1300 and thereafter lis.HOO, Simptuaiy lvs.100, Lanpuaco Pay hs* 100 , Special/ny j.vs* 200, Dopu■fcnti on /illowr.nco ns* 373* Stcrlinr^ Ci.orsoaG -.’ny £25* Troasuiy sonction is also boin&amp; sou^t for paynont to I la jo r Ton ''y of a Doamoss ^Jlov/ancc of iis.lpO nonthfron tho 15 th iju^ust, 194 ?. 4* Noninol rolls of I.Ioclioal Staff, Ministerial Staff and Public V&lt;crks Dopartnont Staff, which Give tho details of each individual and show their pay and allowances are enclosed. Hie position of tho Public V&lt;brks Department Staff has not been finally decided thou gIi it is likely that some of then, at any rate, will bo on deputation from the Government of India, All Staff on deputation, either from India or Pakistan receive a deputation allowance amountinG to 25 per cent of their tine scale pay and special pay, 6 , I should 00 Grateful if you would lot nc know as scon as possible the nones of the individuals employed in tho xorsian Gulf ^icninistration (oxcludinG those in catoGcries 1(a) and (b)) who will bo liable to British Income Tax and tho^ method of deduction to bo adopted. If, as soa.is probable, those on low salary scales will be exempt, I should 00 Glad if you would confim that no further nctivm in thfcir case is required, I would mention here that in the case of cata tJ orios 1(c) II, III and IV an allowance to compensate for Income Tax will have to bo provided should it bo found that tho personnel concerned are subject to British Income Tax, Yours sincerely /?./. Halloas y —Extract from P«R f » letter dated 15th May 1947 t^) ; V. MfiSQICAL ScaVICiSS, (a) Residency and Agency Medical Officers and subordinate itaff* A complete and up-te-date list ef the medical staff in the Gulf is attached* It will take some time to obtain the '^K.feapraation required by the Geremment of India regarding t he «ilingneas ef the rarious members of the staff to continue to serve in the Gulf* This information is being collected and a separate report will be submitted in due course* (b) quarantine ^ r ^A;,.eu&lt;ents * I have as yet submitted no proposals regarding the future quarantine arrangements in the Gulf as I have been without ex pert advice* A medical officer has now been deputed by 11*M.G* to examine the subject and is likely to arrive in Bahrain on the 1st June* So far as 1 am aware Indian pilgrims will be very little affected by any quarantine arrangements we may make in the Gulf ports* Probably 95?» of such pilgrims whether bound for Kerbela or Mecca disembark at Basra* Unless there happened to be a serious epidemic in Iraq, when we should have to put a quarantine station on the Iraq-r.uwait land frontier, such pilgrims would not come within the scope of our quarantine operations* I think practically all quarantine buildings and equipment proper in the Gulf are owned by the States concerned* This point is being checked* There is, however, a considerable amount of equipment in Government dispensaries which is the property of the Government of India either solely or jointly with H*M*G* Lists of such equipment are being prepared*COI'.E.-m.HEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE, EX.TEPJTAL DEPAKTI-CNT 4 * EXPRESS LETTER (AIR ^IL ) (N.E. - This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed). Prom:- The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations. To:- Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Dated 1st December, 19V7« No. Ext.2415/47. Your demi-official letter No.2186-93/2(b) of 18th October. Buildings, A ''2. Treasury sanction has now been accorded in respect of the Arab side to (a) one half of total Persian Gulf F.W.D. budget for 1947-48 (b) following items under Central Contract Grant in Residency budget for 1947-43 Muscat Agency Rs. 4,000 Bahrein ' Rs. 1,600 Residency and Koweit Agency Rs 20,000 3. You will appreciate that expenditure on Arab side has been borne wholly by H.M.G. since 1st April, 1947 whereas that on consulates on Persian side remained divisible with Government of India until 14th August at least (position thereafter has not yet been properly classified - c.f, P.0, letter to Tehran dated 17th November, copy of which was forwarded under our Ext,2589 of 26th November, and para. 4 of Government of India's telegram No.9321 of 6th November) Reappropriation as between Arab and Persian sides is not therefore practicable#. The only way to interpret sanction under 2(a) is to divide each item by two, and to treat one ha,lf only as pertaining to Arab side. P.VA.D. establishment has of course hitherto covered both Arab and Persian sides but for accounting purposes expenditure on establishment can be treated as divisible as above v Report by Central P.F.D. special officers referred to in Government of India’s telegram 9321 of 6th November is still awaited, and question of estab lishment will be gone into as soon as this is received. Meanwhile you should carry on as best you can using your own discretion. 4. I trust that you will be able to manage on the grants already sanctioned for present financial year. Amounts sanctioned appear j here to be fairly liberal, particularly when regard is had to the / / additional £3,730 sanctioned for alterations to the Residency. If, however, you still consider that the amount is insufficient for immediate needs please make self contained submission in light of position as explained/explained above. Any works not immediately required might be included under next year's estimates. I should mention that Ministry of Works have stated that Turner has recently informed them that in addition to the sum of £500 .already approved (from Central Contract Grant) necessary to cover the cost of petty repairs, he considers that other improvements are essential and these are estimated to cost net less than a further £500 viz construction of a temporary kitchen, •an additional bathroom, insulating of roof of Residency, minor alterations to Secretary’s house, office block and Servants's quarters. It is not clear to us hovr far these can be covered from funds already sanctioned, and we should be unable to make submission to Treasury without further elucidation. . The issue of the above has been duly authorised. F. A. K.. HARP ISONINDEXED The Secretary, External Department, A copy of a letter from the E.and A.Dept., on the eubject of audit arrangements is attached. It will be seen that we are required to give an assurance as to the adequacy of the Aud.General 1 s examination. While it is clear that the Indian Authorities are in a much better position than ourselves to examine payments made in accordance with Indian regulations we should be on difficult ground if the amounts of local expenditure included appreciable disbursements under somewhat complicated regulation^ unfamiliar to the Indian authorities. This department, therefore, agrees with the suggestions in Mr.Harrison*s note. Should the Treasury refuse, consideration might be given to arranging that only advances should be made locally against any claims under Foreign Service Regulations, final settlement being made by adjustment in the officer 1 s account here. In regard to the question of audit several points ^ arise, viz:- (a) the form of the audit certificate (b) continuance of audit beyond 14th August 1947 (c) payment of the fees asked for by the Auditor-General. / - I la «/ As regards (a) I should have thought that the aingie form by the Auditor-General - ’’Audited and found correct ” - implied proper scrutiny of vouchers and governing authorities but in view of Beighton’s letter, ref.I.F.333/47, we have to ask for the assurances suggested in para.2 of Knowlden's letter to Robbins of 15th October. Knowlden’s letters make no reference to the constitutional changes and it must therefore be presumed that they see no objection to continuance of India audit beyond 14th August. Anything short of continuance to 31.3.48 would certainly lead us into difficulty bdt it is necessary to ask the Auditor- General to confirm that he is willing to continue responsibility to that date. As regards the fee of Rs.10,000 4 £7 50)asked f 0 r by the Auditor General, I am afraid we have no means of satisfying ourselves as to the reasonableness of the amount asked for (about %% of the expenditure) and it is not clear that Beighton*s letter, ref.I.F.333/47, can be taken as accepting this figure. I presume you will be informing Beighton that we have asked for the assurances suggested by the C.and A.G. and the matter could perhaps be settled by adding that we presume there will be no objection to the charging of the fee of £750 against the Vote of this Office. A further point that will have to be determined soon is the date of submission of the accounts. We shall have to advance from the Vote before 31st March next such amount as India estimate they will have spent to that date and to arrange that the certified accounts are in our hands by 1st September 1948 - so that the final adjustment of this advance can be made before the close of the Appropriation Account on 30th September.. It seems desirable that the above considerations should be brought to India*s notice now and it might be wise to ask, in order to reducethe lag in bringing charges to account, for the submission at an early date of an audited statement covering the period 1st April to 14th August 1947 and for further audited statements to be sent quarterly, the final quarters account to reach us by 1st September, 1948* November. 1947 . {COPT Reference C.R. 3/47-4B. EXCHEQUER AND AUDIT DEPARTMENT, audit house, victoria embankment, LONDON. E.C. 4. 15th October, 1947. Dear Janes, I am sorry it has taken so long to send a reply to your letter of the 21st August (A.C. 11905/47 E) about expenditure in 1947-48 on the Political Residency in the Persian G-ulf. We shall be glad to help as far as possible to avoid the need for sending to England all the vouchers and detailed accounts for what is only a temporary arrangement for carrying on the service, but I must point out that the correct way to look at the audit by the Auditor General of India is to regard it as a service rendered to you and not to us. We have no authority or discretion to substitute audit by the Auditor General of India for audit by the Comptroller and Auditor General, but the latter is empowered by statute (after satisfying him self that the vouchers have been examined and certified as correct by an accounting department) to have regard to the character of the departmental examination, and to admit the sums so certified without further evidence of payment in support of the charges to which they relate. In a case like this one our view is that audit by the Auditor General of India, if applied under arrangements approved by you, is the equivalent of a departmental examination, and we can be content if you can assure us (a) that the Auditor General* s certificate leaves no doubt in your minds as to the adequacy of the examination, and the sufficiency of the vouchers and governing authorities, and (b) that any defects reported by him are disclosed to us. I hope this does not sound excessively meticulous, as I think you will find that we do not want to put difficulties in your way. /Perhaps R. A. Janes, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Oft ice, 28, King* s Road, S. W.3* MJBPerhaps I should add, to avoid risk of misunderstanding, that the fee to be paid to India must be borne by you and not by us. Since you wrote I have also had a letter from the Treasury enclosing copies of two to you from the G-ovemnient of India, One of them stated that the cost of the audit, recoverable from His Majesty* s G-overnment during 1947^48, would be Rs, 10,000 approximately, and the other was from the Deputy Auditor General of India about the form of the audit certificate to be given, Robbins asked whether we had any conuients, and a copy of my reply to him is enclosed for your information. Yours sincerely, SGD. A.J, KNOWLQEN.15th October, 1947 G • R« 5/47 ~48* Dear Robbins, I have your letter I.F. 140/04 of 27 September 1947 on the subject of audit of expenditure in 1947-48 on the Political Resiaency in the Persian G-ulf. The Commonwealth Relations Office, Division B, had also sought our views on the proposal to have this expenditure certified by the Auditor General of India, and I enclose a copy of my reply to Janes, to whom I am also sending a copy of this letter. Without knowledge of the local conditions, I am afraid we cannot express any opinion as to whether Rs. 10,000/- is a reasonable estimate of the cost of audit. My letter to Janes states broadly our attitude to the audit, but perhaps I may add, with regard to the form of audit certificate, that I think that we all should wish to be assured that the simple form of certificate proposed does not mean that the examination to be applied to this expenditure will be something less than that normally given to Indian accounts, and in particular that it does not intend to disclaim responsibility for seeing that the expenditure is properly supported by authority. Your sincerely, H.Robbins, Esq., Treasury Chanbers, Great George Street, S.W.1. SGD. A.J. KNOWLDBN! Canmonwealth Relations Office, 28 King’s Road, London, S*W#3* 11905/47 E 21st August, 1947* Dear Knowlden, I am writing about the examination of accounts for expenditure on the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf for which for the first time provision has been made in the India and Burma Services Vote* This approach to you should have been made earlier but extreme pressure here, caused by constitutional changes, has resulted in delay, which I regret* You will want seme background on this subject* Until recently H*M* Government’s representation in the Persian Gulf has been conducted through officers who were European members of the Indian Political Service and who were servants, like their subordinates, of the Government of India* Officers and staff were paid by the Government of India who bore some of the cost finally* It became certain in 1946 that political developments in India would make changes necessary and a ministerial decision passed to the India Office the duty of taking over direct responsibility frem the Goverrment of India from 1st April, 1947# and stated the aim that the Foreign Office should take over by 1st April, 1948* This decision was taken before the decision to transfer power in India on 15th August* A scheme for the transfer of responsibility from the Goverrment of India was drawn up and sent to that Government* The assumption then made was that during the transition period, which was expected to coincide with the current financial year. A.J* Knowlden Esq*, Exchequer &amp; Audit Department, Audit House, Victoria Snbankment, E*C* /paypay and allowances of personnel could continue under Indian rules, disbursements being made by the Govemnent of India, as agents of H.M. Government, at the expense of Imperial funds. The scheme included an invitation to the Auditor General of India to audit the Political Resident’s accounts durung the period of transition. On this last point the Goverment of India replied that the Auditor-General of ^\ h i d .T e8d take “P ®udit on behalf of H.M. Govemnent' this audit having to be treated as being done on a consent asis. xhey added that the cost of the audit would ordinarily be recoverable fron H.M. Govemnent and promised a further conmunication, which has not yet arrived, on that subject. oe !* ha “ e a *° Ve t0 138 further examined in the change of circunstances frcm 15th August, tine appointed day for independence for India. Endeavours are being made to retain oimer European officers, either under contracts or by recruit- ! 0reign Service, and Indian permanent staff are Indi! th ® seivioe °f the Govemnent of India. To the latter it is proposed to admit the sane rates of pay and allowances as before. There is now an Auditor- of'pas^ t f th6 mT' ° aainlon of India and Auditor-General* of Pakistan. The former is auditing the accounts of transactions up to 14th August of the late Central Goverment and mIi 8 n Ut a t * r date al;L transactions are to be divided and will appear in the accounts of one or other of the Dan inions - there will be no central accounts. - ° bvl ? U3 ?; y ’ discussion on the question of audit examination of accounts has to be taken further; it has to be decided whether the proposed audit by the Auditor-General of I ndi a should stop snort at 14th August, if indeed it is acceptable . to that date. We, of course, do not actually know whether he would still be willing to function beyond that date, yments after that date will be a mixed lot and, because the /India-based...* 5 ? India-based staff greatly exceed the European officers, the prospect of the examination and defence here of vouchered and detailed accounts cannot be viewed without misgiving. This letter, though lengthy, may not be full nough to enable you to foxra your views on the above. If that is so would you like to see our file at this stage or would you care to arrange with me for a talk on the subject? Yours sincerely, (Sgd) R.A. Janes 21st August, 1947*External D enartaen l; Si.l5l3^4T7 ^ \ Prom To Repeated to CCHPIDMTIAL CODE Seoapetary of State for India Political Resident in the Persian Golf, Bahrain Government of India, External Affairs &amp; Consnonwealth Relations Department 33espatched 02 o 30 hours, 20th July 1947 IMPORTANT No»9340 « Reference icy telegram No*9123 of July 16th* paragraph 5 (not repeated to Government of India)* 2* Following conditions of service for officers accepting three year contracts have Been agreed* (a) L eave All officers who have had service of 10 years or more with Government of India shall he entitled during the currency of their contract to 160 days absence (including both ordinary leave and travelling time) from their post* They will be entitled to full transportation costs of one passage to U*K. and back by an appx^oved route for themselves their wives and their dependants (as defined in the Foreign Service regulations) once during the period of the contract, and the cost of a passage to UoK. at the termination of the contract* Leave may be taken, at the discretion of the Political Resident, in instalments, subject to a maximum of 90 days absence at any one time, but no leave may in any case be taken before 1st June 1946* officers with less than 10 years service with Government, of India will have the total leave entitlement referred to above abated by 35 days* Officers who have applied for leave during the current hot-weather, e*g* PELLY, JACKSON / and HUDSON, may take leave up to a total of 2 months if due to them under Indian rules* Question whether all or any of this leave taken after August 15th should count against leave due under contract is under consideration* (1&gt;) Medical E xpenses Officers will be entitled to medical expenses on the same lines as u.K* -based Foreign Service officers abroad, l*e*, they may charge to public funds two-thirds of medical expenses i ncurred abroad (5*o*not in U.K*) by themselves and their famllTcs* time being medical staff attached to Persian Gulf establishment will be expected to continue to px*ovide free treatment* (c) Tr avelling allowances on duty Separate letter follows from Foreign Office giving surrmary of their rules applicable to payment of travelling allowances and forwarding copies of appropriate claim forms* 3* Minis terial sta ff ,T«mr '.mnmMTmjjmwrm r—■inr? maunmxarmwz) Please refer to my telegram No* 9124 of 16th July* /(a) Permanent(a) Permanent staff seconded for period of one yeiir will fc© entitled to re tom passage to India. They will he also entitled to one month's leave or one month's pay in lien thereof* (b) Temporary ministerial staff on contract will he entitled to receive the leave and leave travel facilities agreed to in their present contracts* Mr* sllirSBURy Treasury* Mr* Oardener* ^r. pyiaan. Mr* Henderson, foreign Office. S.d a.P^partment* Financial Department. A*0**8 Department (Ur* Gander)* O/I* (Lt«Oolo Crichton).Secretary of State for In&amp;ia Political Resident in the Persian G^XT 10o15 hours, 16th July 1947 \ Addressed Political Res ideate copy W mail to GoYemment of India* My telegram Hqo912X to GoTemmozxt g India* are most anxious to secure services of officers and staffs at pressaat in post© /igressnent lias □eon reached that this can hast he done 'by offering to keep on officers and staffs at approximately present rates of pay and conditions of 8 err Ice at any rate for time being.* 2* Following emergency terms ha Ye been worked out for following officers at posts named at a meeting here. \,1% u.a proposed if you agree that on Hay*s return frcs. 2save you shoul take over as P.A. Kuimit and Tandy if ho is billing should relieve Pettigrew) r (1) tellgway c Political Agent Kwait* Salary aim® pli^s language allowance .£90* Personal allowance £S300® Grille acting as Political Resident above allowance to be 5,ncreaped by £300* (2) Felly » political Agesxt, Bahrain« 3ala5?y £1330 nlus language allowance ^90* Personal allowance £1700* (5) S tewart a .4a he has 'been accepted for Foreign Scx*vioe no contract offer ie required but intention is to post him as Political Agent to Muscat with provisional foreign j- allowance of £1600 e u (4) Jaci^son* Same as for Stewart g but intention is to post him as PoUTicel Officer, Truclal Coast *. with provisional foreign allowance of £1075 and language allowance of £90 * (5) Tendy* Secretary, Bahrtiin^ Salary £900 plua larigv.age allowance £9*0^ Personal allowance £1376» (6) Hudson. Unaer-’Seerstai’y* Bahrain* Salary £676 plus £90 language allowance® Personal allowance £750® (7) Pettigrew. • As this officer wishes to leave Gulf anyway present pay and allowances will, be continued in accordance with Indian rules if, as is hoped* he mdll continue to serve as Seoretaz^f Bahrain until Political Resident can .release him or until Slot December next whichever is soo ner. If he accepts please report bio exact present pay and allowances&lt; , - (8) Ranee® Assistant Political Agent Bahrain* Salary £900* Personal allowance £14^5, 3* Above salaries md language allowances are subject to U*K* ineome tax* Porsonal and foreign allowances are note Furnished quarters will be provided in addition where available 1 or rented as a charge to H.M.Ck where not^ ForeignOUTWARD TELEGRAM £t 4^ Fcreiga would like to offe? Hos 71. '2 f ^ and 8 above 5 year contracts (or 18 months if prefaced.) these places on terms given above* Please approach officers urgently and telegraph T?hethor they would be willing to accept If any of above are admitted to Foreign Service sutbsequently onti^act terms would automatically lapae» If Ranee obtains employment subsoquently 'Bider Colonial office we would not allow contract now. offered to stand in his way&lt;&gt; 5* 'Sir R„ Hay attended meet teg at v'hlch above scheire was worked out* Both he and ourselves very much hope officers named will accept offers which arc generous hy Foreign Service standards^ If officers act in posts other than those designated personal allowances will be subject to variation oil which views of Political Resident will be sought* Copies of this i” ogram are being sent to those officers on leave in this country to whom we are making offers direct. Conditions regarding leave etc* are being worked out and a separate telegram will follow cn this subject* W-easa see my insaeciatsly following teleg-’em alscut. Suborainsto staff* Treasury* Foreign, office *“ do ^ ^ do ** do ** «* do Caccla)« GarLenorj * pyman) ♦ Kendereon) [Mr* Fisher)* 8&lt;4 Ca Department* Financial Department (Mr, R*S&lt; Brown)« A«Oa *s D epartment {Mr •&gt; Conder) »• of India (LtnCol, Crichton)^7 ScVet^o-fi 148X4A/. .i. 30* t ber f 1947* r\ S i-ch ifsfere co to the ccrresT ojidence reatrn^ -with your letter o. v C1/34K2/ dated 8 th i\pril t 194 /f I aia directed to inf f m u that the sum of £18:-:- has been received from Messrs* Cable and irel ss Ltd* on account of the rent of the old wireless building at Bashire for the period from 16th October, 1946, to 16th October, 1947* This sum is equally divisible between H*t'* (government and the overnxjent of India and on receipt of a receivable order the sum of £9 will be tr&amp;ns-erred to the credit of K*M* Paymaster General,at the Baiuc of ]Sn land* I air*, jlr. Tour obedient dervant. Accountant general division B of itate. The Under iocretiiry foreign Office, 3.-V.1*(&amp;) Extract frcia Letter from The Residenqy, Bahrain, No. D. 0. No. 1735~S dated 8 th October, 1947# * * + * + * 2. Would you also kindly let me know as soon as possible how the officers concerned (including myself) are to draw their pay. Hallows said something about officers being permitted to draw their pay from the local treasuries at the old rupee rates leaving adjustments for income-tax etc. to be made later but no instructions appear to have been received to this effect. Ik) officers here have yet received ary pay for the period subsequent to August 15th. ♦ * ♦ * . * *r Td. No.: Whitehall 1334. Your Reference- TREASURY' CHAMBERS, ' GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. Treasury Reference . ^ October, 1947 Please refer to our cor: it the budget for the under the control of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ending with my letter of the 9th October, which left the question of audit outstanding. We have now heard from the Exchequer and Audit Department and Knov/lden has also written to Janes (your ref. CR3/47-48) • The Treasury for its part would have no objection to the proposed audit by the Auditor General of India subject to the Comptroller and Auditor General being satisfied on the points raised in Knowlden* s letter of the 15th October. I am sending copies of this letter to Gardener and Knowlden. Yours sincerely, J.D.K. Beighton. E.P.Donaldson, Esq., C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations OfficeftvX. Tel. No. : Whitehall 1234 ~\ L Your Treasury Reference * lc^) D^ar Donaldson, ^ •-S^' IMDCXHO l/b H TREASURY CHAMBERS, GREAT GEORGE STREET, &gt; &gt;&gt; 7 oir • . /a i ’j •• « ^ A 1 ‘ ■ 31.1 ■s „ w I refer to your letter of 26th August about the budget for the posts under the control of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for the financial year 1947-48* In the circumstances explained in your letter we approve the estimates as they stand for Subhead A and Subhead B subject to adjustment as a result of your approach to the Government of India on the question of division (Persian side of the G-ulf) between Indian and U.K. revenues. As regards Subhead C: Telegrams and Telephones, we recognise ^.? y^T that it is late in the year to effect much saving but we must ask that every effort should be made to economize on telegrams in accordance with our instructions to the Foreign Office. On the subsidary points raised in your paragraph 6 we agree that the Political Resident's powers of reappropriation (virement) may be continued till the end of the current financial year. We also agree that as the Indian Treasury Offices will be maintained for Indian purposes it will be convenient to use them until 31 st March next. We are consulting the Comptroller and Auditor General on the question of audit arrangements and I willyrite to you when we have received his reply. I am sending a copy of this letter to Gardener at the ^oieign Office. Yours sincerely, J.D.K. E.P. Donaldson, Esq., C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office,s Mr. R.S. ^rown . llr» Kordik . I have spoken to Mr. Fisher of the Foreign Office about the method of payment of salaries to Foreign Service and contract officers serving under the Political Resident. His reaction was that since their engagements were with the Foreign Office salaries ought to be issued in London^ presumably through the Foreign Office who knew the rules applicable^and the audit arrangements in respect of these officers should be carried out in London and not by the Indian Auditor General who would be ignorant of the rules. 1 said that it seemed to me that it would be very awkward if part of the Persian Gulf expenditure were audited here and part ay the Indian Auditor General in India and it would be essential in any case that the Indian Auditor General carried out the audit of that part of the Residency budget which would not be concerned with the payment of Foreign Service^contract officers. You will remember in this connection that the Treasury* s approval is still awaited to our suggestion that audit arrangements should be carried out by the Auditor General in India (see paragraph 6 ( 2 ) of Donaldson* s letter to Beighton of 26 th Augusl). Would it be possible for you to clear this matter with the Foreign Office (l think Mr. Minshull is the person concernedj and the Treasury (Mr. Blliman) to whom copies of the Political Resident's telegram No.A.684 have now been sent. It is really Impossible for this Department to discuss technical matters of this sort direct with other Offices. I should have thought myself that since the officers in question are to be paid rates appropriate to Foreign Office personnel, and will /bebe subject to British income tax, jUfttr the Jtoreign Office proposal was the most suitable, although I recognise, of course, that it means that Persian Gulf expenditure would be audited by two different authorities. This objection perhaps is not insuperable, and in any case the C. &amp; A.G. must take over the audit of the Persian Gulf expenditure next year. There is, however, one point not raised by Mr. Harrison, and that is that the Foreign Office proposal apparently means disbursement of salary by the Foreign Office, and presumably for the balance of this financial year they would have to recover from this Office. 23.9.47Telegraph : “ Travaux. Wjre, London.” Telephone: Reliance 7611. Our Ref: DC*24/195836 MINISTRY OF WORKS, LAMBETH BRIDGE HOUSE, ALBERT EMBANKMENT. LONDON, S.E.I. August, 1947 Dear Harrison 9 In connection with your telephone call of 15 th August about Bahrein, I enclose 4 copies each of the regulation^relating to occupancy of Embassy and Legation Houses and of the^?orras used for obtaining particulars of requirements to be covered by the 1948/49 Estimates* P*A.K* Harrison, Esq*, Commonwealth Relations Office, Whitehall, S.W.1*FOREIGN OFFICE, 8 Carlton House Terrace S.W.l 14th August 1947 Dear Donaldson, Now that the Persian Gulf administration after August 15th is taking shape I think it would he as well if we began to give our attention to the ultimate form v/hich these establishments are going to take in the estimates. We shall have to take them on our vote for the financial year 1948/49 from the beginning of that year, i.e. 1st April next, and we would want to have all the relevant information in our possession by October. It is no doubt too early to ask Galloway to do this now as neither he nor we yet know which of the Ministerial staff will stay and for how long. But I think it would be as well to let him know that we have to go forward with the estimates quite soon and if he would try and set out a complete statement of his establishment together with an estimate of annual expenditure at the post (which we can adopt for the estimates) to reach us by, say, the 15th September. We do this in the Foreign Office normally by showing the numbers in each grade at the post together with a statement of the cost of the salaries and* allowances of each grade, for example: 1 Ambassador, so much; 2 Consuls, so much; 5 shorthand-typists, so much: so that the whole staff is covered. The salaries should be shown separately from the allowances, and the various types of the^ latter should be described and distinguished one from another. Apart from pay and allowances there are the following annual items which v/e have suggested might be completed under the headings used in Indian accounts: Contingencies: Office expenses and miscellaneous. In this way we should cover the complete expenditure at the post. The above details will of course be required separately for the outlying posts at Muscat, Kuwait and Sharja as well as the Residency and Political Agency at Bahrain. I do not know what arrangements you yourselves are making to carry these establishments on the India Office Vote until the 1st April but you will presumably need very much the same information as ourselves. We have already certain lists of staffs with their pay but we cannot now use these since v/e do not know who will actually stay and who will be going. But it is none too early, I think you will agree, to start on this and you may v/ish to write to Galloway accordingly. Winter of the Ministry of Works probably knov/s what is happening but you might like to assure yourself whether they wish you to obtain any information for these estimates or whether they have their own channels. I am copying this letter to Y/inter. 2) Office allowance. 3) Postage and telegrams Supplies and Services Cars, launches, wireless, etc Yours sincerely E.P. Donaldson, Esq., C.M.G., India Office.jP-SIAN G-UL? RESIDENCY /4 ■ Buu;:oR', Accounts 'nd Audit A meeting -vvas held to disease this subject on 24th July The following were present. Mr. E.F. Donaldson in the Chair. Sir R. Hay Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Mr. R.S. Brown Pinancial Department. Mr. S.J. Gender Accountant General Branch. x. 0 . Kcrdik rt »f it Mr. A.B. Reed External Department After a full discussion the following conclusions were reached. 1 . The Foreign Office should be asked to inform the India Office as soon as possible, and not later than 15th August,, in what form they would wish the budget estimates for the Gulf posts for 1943/49 to be furnished. 2. The Political Resident should then be given as long notice as possible of any further financial details which he will be required tor furnish. 3. The India Office should ask the Treasury in what form., and in what detail, the budget for the current year should be submitted. This would be done in the form of a demi-official letter covering an analysis, to be prepared by the Accountant General’s Branch, of the expenditure expected to be chargeable in 1947/43 under the three general headings fA^ salaries etc. of officers, (b) travelling expenses and miscellaneous (GJ telegrams and telephones. 4. The Government of India should be asked by telegram whether their Treasuries in the Gulf will remain open after 15th August until 31st March, 1943. In the event of a negative reply, alternative arrangements would be made by the Accountant General to place the Political Resident in funds through the branch of the Eascern Bank in Bahrein. 5. Assuming that the Auditor General of India will audit the accounts for the current financial year, the Treasury should be asked to accept this, at least in resx^ect of the period up to 15 th August and, preferably, until 31 st March, 1943, instead of the audit being carried out by the Comptroller and Auditor General. This would be desirable in view of the difference between the accounting systems applicable in India end in this country.To London. Subject:- Future administration and control of His Majesty*s Governments relations with the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. Sir, 7/ith reference to the correspondence ending with Secret Air Mail letter No.F.15(II)-BPG/47 dated 18.6.47 from ‘ try to the Government of India in the Department of 'fairs and Common Wealth Relations to your address, ect mentioned above, I have the honour to state .ditor General has decided that an audit certificate le form, M Audited and found correct H , should be r the Accountant General, Central Revenues, the er, on the accounts of the Political Resident ; and ertificate should be countersigned by the Auditor ore transmission to the India Office. It is hoped dit certificate in the above form will be accept- * • Deputy Auditor General of India. Sir, Your most obedient servant, I have the honour to be,' t \ I should be grateful if the budget estimates for the Persian G-ulf Residency could be formally approved as soon as possible. If formal approval is likely to be delayed I would suggest that the Political Resident should be informed that he may go ahead on the basis of the estimates. Certain sums e.g. the Secret Service allotment have to oe distributed amongst the various Agencies and it is impossible for the Political Resident to make a distribution unless he knows what amount is likely to be sanctioned. I have already stated that if the Political Residents powers of re-appropriation remain unimpaired it is unlikely that he will have to apply for any extra grants during the current financial year, and I think same saving should be possible under the head 'Secret Service'. It may however be necessary to apply for extra funds under the head 'Hire of despatch vessel', as the provision is inadequate unless transport for touring is provided from time to time bv the Royal Navy or R.A.F. (Sgd.) ViT.R. H^r, 22/7.r;t ^l~/]/ot(-Lj ^ Pi ro^l D^^^Stment The estimates far 1947/48 submitted to the Treasury at the end of 1946 \vere based on figures supplied by ^fc^jjepartraent which wez$ in turn, based on 1946/47 estimates (vidfcr~yiag A). HlA ’ / The estimates now produced by the Government of India can be re-cast on the following lines Sub-head for I, 4b B*S* Sstimates Government of India Sub-head A, Salaries, etc. « * \ ( (i) ( (ii ((iii) ! Bay of officers Pay of establishment Allowances, etc. (excluding item 'Travelling and other allowances') B, Travelling and incidental expenses ( (i) ( (ii) Travelling and other allowances Other charges (excluding items shown below) • G, Telegrams and telephones ( (i) [ (ii) Service postage and telegram charges Koweit-Iraq Telegraph line' They give the following conparison:- Government of India Sstimates • , 1947/48 Preliminary Estimate submitted to Treasury . for 1947/48 Subhead A 39,680'(a) 54,896 (b) Subhead B 44,149 46,300 Subhead G i • 12,577 - n • £96,406 £0.,196 (a) Includes provision for 2 Surgeons and 2 Assistant Surgeons not provided for in (b); (b) Includes £13*300 in respect of leave and pension contributions no ponoien for which appears in (a), except for a sum of £360 in respect of leave salaries. The sum of £12,300 was conjectural, being, the contribution • f in 1943/44 for the Persian Basts and is, therefore, not directly related, apart from the inclusion of the Residency, to the posts covered by the present estimate (vide Flag b)* The rates of contribution appear to be in the region of 15-l^o each vide Rule 116 Fundamental Rules i. e. a total contribution of 3G-33j^ The estimate under consideration shows a total pay till of approx* Rs* 4,23,000 and on the above basis, leave and pensions contributions should amount to approx* £11,000* To this figure an amount will have to be added for contributions on Sterling Overseas Pay and, in the circumstances, unless you see ary objection, as it appears impossible to calculate the contributions accurately owing to the absence of individual data, it is suggested that a figure of £ 12,000 be included on this account i,e. an approximation of the original figure given (£12,300) less the £360 included by the Government of India* —| \ This/&gt; ( This re-casting does not give a completeiy accurate result, as, for instance, the 'service postage' item, if it were known, should appear under Subhead ’B*. It is understood that it has been finally decided that works charges are to be borne on the 1.0. Vote and therefore the sum of £8,325 must be included, on the basis of the statement in the Government of India*s letter dated 20th IJay that 50$ of the charges are related to the rjrab Side. • For the want of a more appropriate Subhead this charge should be included under Subhead 'B'. Further, in view of your comment regarding the ’Central Contracts Grant', on the assumption that the same division will apply, £1,500 has been deducted in respect of repairs etc. on the Persian side which will be divisible between India and the P.0. If this is agreed, it will be advisable to infonn the Government of Ii?fc^a accordingly in order that they may include the portion we have excludedS^i their Persian budget - an arrangement which has already been suggested by the Resident in his Express Letter dated 26th IJarch, 1947. . j The Government of India estimate does not include an item in respect of Sterling Overseas Bay which was included in the preliminary estimate submitted to the Treasury vide flag A. There is no information available in this Department to enable an estimate on this account to be assessed. Can this be calculated in your Department? — From the above, it would appear, therefore, that Treasury sanction is required for the following estimated expenditure:- Subhead A - Government of India estimate - Leave and pension c ontr ibu t ion - Sterling Overseas Pay £39,680 £ 12,000 ? £51,680 Subhead B - Government of India estimate - £44,149 Works expenditure * £ 8,325 £52,474 Subhead C - Government of India estimate ^- £12,577 Total £116,731 (excluding item for Sterling Overseas Pay) % It is suggested that when this budget is submitted to the Treasury, it is supported, in addition to the Gcverrment of India's estimates, with information regarding scales of salaries applicable to officers. The Treasury may also require scales of salaries applicable to clerks but perhaps these need not be given unless asked for. Information on this latter point is contained in the typewritten 1947/48 estimate previously received from the Resident (flag C). You will also presumably inform them that a further sum, 'amount at present not known, will have to be added to the works expenditure in respect of maintenance of the Japan Naval Base vide your Express letter to the Resident No. Ext. 1295/47 dated 18th June, 1947. . ^ . Regarding the question of the Resident being allowed to retain his powers of re-appropriation, there is no objection to asking the Treasury and in&gt; view of the estimated sura involved (£3,75o) and the fact that our division under the various Subheads is, of necessity, rather arbitrary, they may agree. Reference/Reference paragraph 2 of the Government of India letter, the question of audit of these accounts has been under consideration in this Department. The G. &amp; A.G. will be approached on the subject on the return of the file. Until the reactions to this approach are received, it is suggested that no reply on this point be sent to the Government of India. It would be convenient if, when the Resident is infonaed in due course of the Treasury decision on his budget he may be asked to submit his 1948/49 estimates to this Office by October 1947 at the latest as if not required for action by this Office, the Foreign Office will require them. i t ' , 5 C zjc\scf ‘ vw ^j ^ ^ , CUt v fkx C o? CJt, iwtUv x ^ ^ ^SiiCRi-T F! , Y No.F. 15 (II) -BF iioo INDEXED The Secretary to the Gov&lt; in the Department of / AIR C^of India S^clfernal Aff Co:ru;ionwealth RelatT6ns, I ti 7 airs and ‘ / jit SUBJECT The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, L 0 N D 0 N. Dated New Delhi 3, the [^(Z June, 1947. Future administration and control of His Majesty 1 s Government T s relations with the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. cK 7 ' Sir, I 3 J ^ External Affairs Department letter No.F. 1 5 (IT i- T’O/f? dated the 2gth I am directed to refer to para 2 of the Government of India, May 1947 on the subject noted above, and to state that the cost of aud recoverable from His Majesty T s Government during 1947-4$ as worked out by the Auditor^General of India with due regard to the principles enunciated in Fundamental .Rule 127, on the basis of the time spent b^' M the staff employed on the work, amounts to is. 10,000/- approximetely/ The amount is- based on the existing rates of pay and allowances of t staff in question and will not be increased when the revised pay scales— and allowances recommended by the Central Pay Commission are sanctioned, I have the honour to be Sir,IX BUDGET, ACCOUNTS AND AUD IT. No immediate action appears to be called for. The sanctioned estimates for the Persian Gulf for the current year have been forwarded to your separately. Requests from the Political Resident for sanctions for reappropriation or for further funds, will be referred to you as they arise. 2, The P.W.D, Budget for the Persian Gulf covers both the Arab and Persian sides, and ti will be necessary to arrive at some basis for dividing the accounts. This is one of the matters on which the Superintending Engineer, who it is proposed should shortly visit the Gulf, will be asked to make recommendations. It should not be hard to find an \ equitable basis for division.rom - .U eo c&lt;4 5(ll)-BPG/47. ' gflllL . H w Grovernment-of India in the External Affairs Department^ The Secretary to the 7 * To - The Under Secretary of State for India, ' . , India Office, London. ^ (U( V V / 3 Dated,New Delhi ,3, the May 1947 1 Subjects- Jhature administration and control of His Majesty’s Grovernment* s relations with the Arab States in T»he Persian Grulf. . *•••••• 3/^'- Sir, With reference to para 8 of the Outline Scheme attached to Lord Pethick Lawrence’s Despatch External No.l, dated the 4th March 1947 and in continuation of External Affairs Department letter No.F«15-BPG/47 f dated the 30th April 1947, J am directed to forward for the approval of His Majesty’s Government the extracts from the Demands for Grants, showing the sanctioned budget of the Arab posts in the Persian Gulf for the current financial year under the major head '35-External Affairs'. The budget estimates for 1947-48 for the various posts are as • ‘‘-U t r ■ L follows - Bahrain Residency FiS. 6,17,300 \ « • 9 JsJ • X Kuwait Agency ••••,•• &amp;. 1,49,100 Muscat .Agency(including Gwadur,Subsidy and special consular , expenditure). •••••• Es. 2,71,500 / Bahrain Agency(including Trucial Coast and medical arrangements. ...... 2,67;600 ■ o\ Ji I am also to enclose an extract from the Demands for Grants, showing the sanctioned budget amounting to 1^.2,22,000 for 1947-48 under the major head '50-Civil Works-Central' relating to works and Public Works Department establishment for the posts on both the Arab and Persian sides of the Gulf. It is not possible to give an accurate estimate of how much of this provision relates to the Arab posts in the Persian Gulf, but it may roughly be taken as 50% for the Arab side and 50% for the Persian side of the Gulf. Efforts are being made to reach a more exact distribution. p,r,o.f ■■I lit i 2^ I am also to add that the Auditor General of Ind.ia has agreed to take up the audit on behalf of His Majesty's Government, which will have to : be treated as beir^ done on a consent basis. The cost of audit will ordinarily be recoverable from His Majesty's Government. This question will be considered separately by the Auditor General of India and a further communication will be made in due course. «- • * '' ‘ 'i :jo I have the honour to be, &lt; - •x * • ■ , ■ ; ft K Sir, ’ \ • • t ^ \ s» «L - ‘ •. ..j ) , — Your most obedient servant, for Secretary to the Government of India. Cmh /S- e - Copy forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident- in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Copy also forwarded .to .the Auditor General of India with reference to his u.o.No.360-Admn/114-47, - &lt;dated the 1st .April 1947 for information and necessary action. 3 ■ . : J :. La t. ri. ^ |l]INWARD TE1EGRA Allotted to External Department . ' COHPIDEMTIflI. rifim 0 \ 10527 jfW/Ji From Dated Received Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Secretary of State for India Bahrein 9 17.30 hours, 13th June 1947 19.10 hours, 13th June 1947 1+ M4* IMPORTANT No.681. Reference your telegram No.7362, 7th June regarding extra demands by Political Agents; Please see item number IX enclosed with my demi- official letter 921-&gt;3 15th May to Log, ?* At present under Government of India rules I have unlimited powers of re-appropriation within sanctioned budget grants except under head of Secret Service and I trust H.M.G. will agree to allow this arrangement to stand for current financial year. 3. I expect sufficient savings in Residency Budget to cover comparatively small extra demands which are likely to be received from political AgWlts^r- ‘^ Ext. 1180/47 ilo £&gt;.0 dobA- l^&gt; l^**f ii-y imi IX. BUDGET. ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT (a) Budget # As presumably the sanction of H.M.G-# in addition to that of the (Government of India will he required for any expenditure in excess of budget sanction and in order to r present H#M#G-# with a true picture of the financial position I considered it necessary at an early stage to call attention to the fact that the forecast of expenditure under the heads 'Office Allowance' and 'Launch Grant' in the Agency budgets are not accurate and that extra funds will probably be required. In past years extra expenditure on this account has sometimes been well over Rs. 1 , 00 , 000 . 2. I have consulted Political Agents and ascertained that during the current financial year the extra expenditure is not likely to exceed Rs.50,000 and I hope to be able to meet this by reappropriation from my sanctioned grants if my powers in this respect remain unimpaired, as substantial savings are expected under some of the heads. If this expectation is not fulfilled I will apply for extra funds in due course.OUTWARD TELEGRAM it ' tftiihi Baternal D i &amp;aSM-X Dgpax»tacnt . COPY From To CYPHER (Q.T.P.) Secretary of State for India Government of India f Ocnmonwealth Retatfona &amp; External Affairs Department Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Despatched 17.30 hours, 7th June 1947 IMPORTANT No.7378. SECRET My predecessor's Despatch External No.l dated 4th March and your Secretary's letter dated ^ ^thj^ril No* 15-BPG/47• Persian Gulf admini at ra ti on. 2. H.M.G. agree that 1st April 1947 should be regarded as date from which transfer of control becomes effective, but since U.K. revenues will bear cost of administration Political Resident's- budget as well as proposals for additional expenditure, re-appropriations, etc# will require my sanction which P.R. should now seek direct (with copy to Government of India) instead of through Government of India. 3* It would seem appropriate that formal announcement should be made by Political Resident to all the Riders notifying change which has taken effect. Please telegraph if you concur in draft /texttext contained in my iamadiately following telegraa® gratefully accept Government of xnaia s willingness to continue to maintain staff and services as H«M.G. ‘a agents on the . understanding detailed in paragraph 3 of Crichton's letter© &amp;• Question of transferring subordinate staff is being separately examined. 6. H.U.G* note Government of India's desire to establish Indian Consulate at Bahrein but feel some difficulty in reaching conclusion until relationship of India to British Commonwealth and future status of Indian nationals can be more clearly defined. (In any case H.lU's exequatur could not be issued in favour of a British subject holding the King's Comnission). Meanwhile H.M.G. ^S ,d , we J c ? me .r urther indication of Government of ^ndia s intentions regarding scope of proposed Consul s functions in relation to Indian nationals, e.go would they expect that Indian Consul would exercise in respect of Indians extra-territorial jurisdiction conceded by the Sheikh to the British Crown? if not, could not Indian interests in Bahrein be equally well supervised by officer designated Trade Agent, whose appointment would not raise difficulties regarding Treaty position and influence of Political Agent which were seen by Government of India themselves in relation to proposed U.S. Consulate? (see Government of India oelegrams No.3566 dated 5th May 1943 and No.4865 dated 36th April 1944. * , H.M.G. are glad to note Government of India's willingness to transfer buildings and movable property not required for Indian representative at sn agreed valuation and look forward to receiving list of property available for transfer in due course. /QMjLea tog „OUTWARD TELEGRAM fioElgstgs PemuUSc Depy^US* . Asst.US 9 8* US.for Burmae Asst «US.for Burma* PS. to SSo PS.to US. PS. to Parly&lt;,USo Mr. Turnbull. Mr. Joyce. Residont Clerks Copies to :- Foreign Office (Mr. Pyman). ' '* (Mr. Gardener). Treasury (Mr. Helsby). M. of W. (Mr. Barker).Mr. Harrison, We are sending a copy of the full document to the Treasury and perhaps may await their reaction to this paragraph. I think we must expect that they will say that the sentence about maintaining the e;:#sting procedure for obtaining additional funds, sanetion|f for reappropriations, etc. M will not do. hould it be as well for us at once to write d.o. to the P.R. and say that we anticipate that the Treasury will expect to be consul^ed ‘ these points and that the existing procedure will£gaj suffice., Even if tiie P.R. applies to the Government of India for ^notion he will necessarily .ave to get approval from us/&gt;aid he might just as well put in his proposals here,simultaneously with the submission to the Government of India. In particular, his suggestion^that the office allowance and launch grants tim ted will rep^ure to be consider'edi a’k G. /cfij) Ao f~ fy-'i Gn 3 h') ^ &amp; .s- - % IX. BUDGET - ACCOUNTS &amp; AUDIT (a) Budget The Budget already presented by the Political Resident will be submitted to H.M.G. for approval. With reference to para.5 of the Political Resident's express letter No.502-S dated 26.3.1947, it is not possible at this stage to undertake a revision of the Budget which has already been sanctioned, nor do the facts presented by the Political Resident provide sufficient justification for this. During the current financial year when the Govt, of India is continuing to act as Agent for H.M.G. the existing procedure for obtaining additional funds, sanction for re-appropriations etc. will remain in force. It will therefore be open to the Political Resident to approach the Government of India in the normal manner, and provided his proposals are justified, there is no reason to suppose that they will not receive a normal sympathetic hearing. (b) A udit and Accounts . It appears that there will be no difficulty in the existing procedure for audit and accounts of expenditure in the Persian Gulf continuing during the financial year 1947-48.CONFIDENTIAL No. 913 -HF. n p r ^ jj i\ : ( - ^ /947 1/ / The Hon’ble the Political compliments to Hi'sitort in t;he Persian Gulf presents his v. . i«A 7A %ie Secretary of State for India, India Office, London and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). m mmm w F£RSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN * Dated... X8ttt April.X947. Reference to previous correspondence: Telegram No.4937 dated April 16th from Itr.Donaldson to — Colonel Hay Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. Budget Estimates for 1947-48 for Persian Gulf Besidency and Political Agencies, Bahrain, Muscat and Kuwait.■■ INWARD TELEGRA SNDEXED t x'n \ H 704 B P rom To Dated Received 466a Political Resident in Persian G-ulf Becretary of State for India Bahrein 18o40 hours, 20th April 1947 07 0 10 hours, 21st April 1947 lift- Donalds* n from Hay «&gt; Your telegram No h 4957_ / / • l.pril 16th» Budget estimates despatched by Air Mail Aprii 19tho I greatly regret that through an oversight they were not sent Before» in bealing with estimates please hear in mind what is stated in paragraph No*. 5 of my express letter No* 502-S dated March 26th. 4 . • BaPs estimates of exf.enfiitt.re during the current year have be^n forwarded. Actual budget is prepared on complicated printed form and details of past actuauss variations, sanctions, etc. are included* We have only one office coov of this and no spare form*. Printed copies will probably be available from the Government of India in about a month’ s^ime, i . complete -uai,.v Ip, urgently required we cou.-,d sene, you our u..■ ..c- and hope that.we shall not have tc refer uo it until erlnted ec y is received from ohe Government of mdia.5* A' copy of last yeat^ y* s c 8 estimates was forwarded demi official letter Nc« \ This may he useful forThe Accountant-General I do not think that I can offer any useful comments on Lt.Col. Hay’s letter of the 26th March, at the present moment, except to say that I am pretty certain that the Treasury will require some much closer budgeting than has been the practice during the war years. The system of estimating on peace-time figures with additional provision for sanctioned dearness allowances only, and for obtaining authority for additional expenditure by supplementary grants, will have to be severely modified* \■MM•V ^ yy\ / vi JNDE^ ED GOVERMENT OF INDIA, EXT • ■ ’’t ■* i * JL I 9 &lt;?V j cfc Depariment. fS EXPRESS LETTER [^, I?.—T^t« is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to saye'telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on ' receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities ti is worded and signed as if it had been /I 80 despatched,] From Political Real aurain. C tty ^ ^ ^ Alt Jncit Oce-A K* ^ ffun4 W f To Repo4ted Government of India 0 Hew Delhi* Secretary of State for Indiat London* / u/&lt;i‘ fo- i. 802-3. Dotal 26th March /shjcx 1947. ? 'T tS In eontinuation of my telegram Mo* T/38 dated 20th March 1947* 2. I have no further coionenta to mafce at this stage on paragraph 1 of the outlined scheme* d. tilth reference to paragra^ns 2. 5 and 4 of tne scheme, the P*ti # D* office which is at present located in Bahrain is still responsible lor works on both the Arab Ad Persian sides of the Gulf* Roughly speaKing 50&gt; of its work is on the Arab side and 50* on the Persian* Presumably under the new proposals His Majesty's Government will meet the whole cost of the office so far as tne Arab side is concerned and will share the cost in respect of the Persian side on the principles observed in the past* During the present period of transition it is un likely that any new works will be undertaken on either side, and if for reasons of urgency any new work on the Arab side is sanctioned by His Majesty's Government it will probably be possible for its construction to be arranged through the Ministry of tiorks. Similarly except in the temporary Residency (vide paragraph 4 of the scheme) where the Mla lltry of ^ork a, it is suggested, should take o ver responsibility at once , 'no special repairs or additions are^likely to be required* I would there fore suggest that the P«w*D* staff should be reduced at nee to the minimum required for maintaining tne record of tne buildings, the future of which will be decided in accordance with paragraph 2 of the scheme. If this is not done the cost of the office will be grossly dispdrportionate to the work it lias to do* S. 6. M I p—1200 SA P—(M-1723}—4-2-30—200,00(1 / 4 ,&gt;A - 2 - EXT ^ 7 A 19 3© lejid, &lt;*) 4* I have no comment* to make at present on Paragraphs 5, 6 and 7 of the scheme* t&gt; • »fith reference to paragraph 8 of the schema I should like to take the opportunity of pointing out that in tgp Bahrain, Muscat and Kuwait Agency budgets expenditure Under the head ’’Office Allowance' 1 ha* been substantially underestimated and the same aPpliss to the head 'Launch Grant' in trie Bahrain and Kuwait budgets* It has been the practice since 1959 for the Agencies to budget on the basis of peace-time figures making additional provision for sanctioned dearness allowances only and to apply for supplementary grants for extra expend iture necessitated by war and post-war conditions. The Government of India with the approval of the Qecretarytff 5tate for India have regularly sanctioned the additional expend iture cf* Jixternal Affaire Department letter o d ated 17th April 19 45 which regularised a net excess o He* l734T3B6/- during 1945-44 and forwarded a copy of the relevant correspondence with the Secretary of State for India viz. eternal Affaire Department l et ter^o»i * 26 * A/4 bdated 2 1st J uly 194 6 and India Office letter flo. SKT *2105/40 dated 27th March 1946. The grants concerned are non-auditable 'Contract Grants’* and the conditions necessitating the excess expenditure still persist* 1 propose to ask tne Political Agents concerned to forward accurate estimates of expenditure incurred and to recommend that the figures in ths budget submitted for His Majesty’s Government f s approval should be reviied accordingly. In the Residency budget the forecast of expenditure under the various grants is believed to be reasonably accurate, but 1 would note that the provision made under 'Central Contract Craiit' includes the requirements of the Persian posts which up to date have been administered by the Residency* 1 propose therefore to suggest that a portion of it should be transferred to the budget of the Bushire Consulate-General* ^Signed; ..k.HaY* Political'Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested* /V'Secretary to the Political Resident, Persisri Gulf.Kepfiu. Ihe iuBiie of the above hau b on ant wised. 3d/- Illegible. Secretary to the political Heeidont in the Persian iJulf. , Vi mSanctioned budget BAHRAIN (TRUCIAL COAST) . - Pay of ^stabliehment Medical Pstablisliment B . 3. - Allowances^ Honoraria, etc . Travelling Allowance 1,000 Dearness Allowance 2,000 B . 5. - Other C h arges Hospital Contingencies &amp; Medical Equipment 1,600 for 1946 - 47. Rupees 4,600 TOTAL ... BAHRAIN (TRUCIAL COAST) 9,200 BAHRAIN. C. 3(l). - Pav ibf Office rs Political Agent Assistant Political Agent Assistant Surgeon Indian Assistant 28,000 15.700 9,400 6,300 C x 3 (2). - Pav of Establishment Clerks, Munshis, etc. Medical Attendant 19,800 4,500 600 C.3(3). - Allo wances. Honoraria, etc . Sumptuary Allowance Travelling &amp; Other Allowance Dearness Allowance _C.3( 4). - Secret Expenditure Secret Service Money C. 3(5). - Other Charges Charges on account of motor boat and steam launch Central Contract Grant Rents, Rates h Taxes Service Postage and Telegram charges Office Allowance Passage Contributions 2,400 12,500 ) 1 ,900 ) 10,000 | 2,300 ! 300 9.000 1,600 1,600 35.000 22.000 1.000 1,83,900 Total « • ♦ BAHRAINSanctioned budget for 1946 - 47. BA NDAR ABBAS . (Continued) Rupees IL.-5 * - Other Cha rges Service Postage and Telegram charges Office Allowance Maintenance of launches 14.000 15.000 12.000 TOTAL ... BANDAR ABBAS 80,300 SHIRAZ Gardeners (Caretakers) House Rent and other allowances 1,400 200 TOTAL ... SHIRAZ 1,600 B USHIRS B . 1. - Pav of Officers Resident Secretary and Under Secretary Consul Vice-Consul Consular Agent at Lingah Surgeon and Assistant Surgeon Assistant Secretary Special Officer at Jask Treasury 0 ffi 9 er k Registrar Assistant Registrar Leave Salary g, - P^ y of Establishmen ts Residency Agent, Personal Assistant, Clerks. Vunshis. etc. Upper Division Clerks Increase in pay of Clerk, Sharjah Sscorts Probable savings B i 3 t - All owance.^ Sumptuary Allowance Travelling and other allowances Dearness Allowance 49,800 37.400 19,500 14.400 7,800 13.400 10.300 7,900 12.300 3,000 48,400 11,700 400 3,800 — 7,000 3,000 ) 1,200 ) 52.700 I 5,200 ? 34.700 ) 10,300 ) ^, 4 ^ - Secret E xpenditure Secret Service Money 1,000Sanctioned budget for 1946 - 47. BUSHIRE. (Continued) Rupees B. 5. - Other Charts Maintenance of launch, etc. Purchase and maintenance of motor cars, boats, etc. Service Postage and Telegram charges Contract Grant for Medical expenditure Office Allowance Central Contract Grant Other contingencies Passage Contributions 12,400 1,800 10,000 1.76.000 8,000 1.10.000 40,000 600 2,000 1,000 TOTAL ... BUSTOS 7,02,000 SUMMARY | TOTAL - PAY OF OFFICSRS TOTAL - PAY OF ESTABLISHMENT TOTAL - ALLOWANCES, HONORARIA, ETC. TOTAL - SECRET EXPENDITURE TOTAL - OTHER CHARGES 3,71,000 1,44,100 2,61,900 2,500 6,48,600 GRAND TOTAL • 14,13,100PAGrS 2 WAR SIP2NDITURS Sanctioned budget for 1946 - 47. EjOTMI. (Continued). K. 3. - Allowances. Honoraria, etc. Rupees Travelling and other allowances Dearness Allowance K. 4. - Other Charges. 2,200 6,700 Contingencies 8,200 TOTAL ... KERMAN 23,000 KHORRAMSHAHR K. 2. - Pav of Establishment Clerks and Munshi K. 3. - Allowances. Honoraria, etc. 5,600 House Rent and other allowance Dearness Allowance 2,800 5,900 TOTAL ... KHORRAMSHAHR 14,300 BANDAR ABBAS K, 2, - P^v of Establishment Clerks K. 3. - Mlowances. Honoraria... ete. 4,600 Travelling and other allowances Dearness Allowance 2,000 3,000 TOTAL ... BANDAR ABBAS 9,600 BUSHIRS K x 1,. - Pav of Officers. Superintendent K t 2. - Pav of Establishment 4,800 Clerks and Munshi Probable saving tt ( 3, - Allowances. Honoraria, etc. 39,600 — 9,600 House Rent and other allowances Dearness Allowance Probable savings Y x 4 t - Other Charges 16,500 28,400 — 11,200 Export on transport for the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 50,000AKuwaitl/h' ' S r The Secretary, External Departinent. The Treasury have been consulted about expenditure on the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf and have advised that it should be exhibited in the India and Burma Services estimates under the ordinary subheads 'A* Salaries, etc.”, 'B. Travelling arid Incidental Expenses” and 'C. Telegrams and Telephones'* Receipts, if any, should probably be provided for \mder 'Z* Appropriations in Aid'. The manner in which salaries have to be shown was explained verbally in your Department on 25th October, but ; for your assistance a copy is attached of the form on which the estimate will be sent to the Treasury and of the Estimates Circular, embodying regulations. Will you please supply particulars of the estimate of £100,000(' suggested by you for 1947/48 Jana lysed in the manner laid down by the Treasury. The Treasury add that work done on such an analysis will not be wasted. If the final decision is that some other Vote should bear this expenditure it will still be necessary for this Office to supply particulars for the use of the sponsoring Department. The estiirate is already overdue and a very early reply is requested. It would be convenient if the Estimates Circular could be returned as soon as possible as it is much in demand. It is understood that it is considered improbable that this Office will be called upon to bear any expenditure on this service on the India and Burma Services Vote this year. If there is such expenditure a supplementary estimate will have to be presented to Parliament and particulars of it will be required by the Treasury by 31st December. Will you please advise well before that date whether there will be expenditure necessitating a supplementary and supply particulars of any such expenditure. Expenditure/Expenditure in the Persian Gulf is outside the India and Burma Services Vote as at present defined by Ifert I of the estimate. Do you concur in a proposal to amend 'sundry India and Burma services' in Part I to 'sundry India, Burma and Persian Gulf services'?(8410) Wt.39743/Pl3 1,000 1/39 A.&amp;E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 CONFIDENTIAL. Political Department, 193 . The Secretary, Political Department, presents his compliments to the Secretary, Military Department, and begs to forward for his information, and transmission to the Secretary, Air Ministry, the annexed copies of correspondence received from th/^v. Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department.?&amp;•» Donaldson Ploase see Vicoroy , 8 tole .ram 2453S below. The position with regard to the Cabinet's oo elusion of 4th September is now as follows *• Bgglelon to aseqie iu, rai)iJly &amp;c p.^oible direct oo.itrol of and resoon lability for the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and his suborOinate Agoncloto* , The position as regards control of the Persian Gulf esidency and subordinate Agencies is that when the Iraft Cabinet Paper (which we have Just sent to the Departments concerned for their comments) has been approved by the Cabinet we shall, with the agreement of the Treasury, be able to say to the Gcveran' nt of India:- Ip lUM.G, would like to take over the whole responsibility for the Persian Gulf and themselves to bear the expenditure involved as from April 1st, 1%7&gt; or possibly sooner. (Co . ont : It is possible that the Government of India will not be willing to go on paying for the Residency etc. so long as until the 1st /’pril next. From the practical point of view this is touch the simplest date to dtu*. at). 2. H.M.G. would, at the same time, like to take over from the Governaent of India certain of the buildings at present used by the political authorit os in the Gulf. ( Cotranant t The Agencies etc. are all owned by the Government of India awi they will have to bo asked how much they want for them. The Treasury and ?lnistiy of Works however will presumably, before agreeing to take them over, wish to be satisfied that they are all necessary anl worth buying and will also require to insnect them before acce ting the Goverriment of India's figures). 3. H.M.G. would also like to obtain the services of certain me ibere of the Indian Political Service with special experience/experience of the ?• sian Gulf, or fbr other reoacxiB regarded as particularly suitable* ( Garment * Col* Hay is anxious that the officers in question should \&gt;e allowed to continue to y ^ belong^to the Indian Political i^jrvioe so long as that service ^ exists* It will presumably be neoessaxy, in consultation with . the Political esident and the Government of India, to draw up ^ a list of officers to be selected; Hdic terms of employment to be offered to them will presumably vary in accordance with the amount of service they still have to do* In the case of the more senior officers they will perhaps be offered a contract for a limited nunber of years while the more junior officers may be absorbed into an established service of H*U*G* e*g* foreign Service)* In connection with the financial aspects of H*M*C* 9 s desire to take over control of the Persian Gulf, in the negotiations with the Government of India there will inevitably arise the question of the division as between H*M*G* and the (kivenyaent of India of special wartime expenditure in the Persian Culf*which has , been incurred during the war years* This has amounted, I think, to something like .CdG,OXD a year and except for the Muscat Defence Tubddy of £13, XO a year (which is included in the £lp,000 and the incidence of which as between the Government of India and H*M*G* has been fixed as 55 to 45) the proportion has not yet been agreed* I presume that,as the first step, when we put to the Government of India out proposals to take over control of the Persian Gulf, we shall confine ourselves to the statements ^ 1, 2 and 3 above without attempting at that stage to go into fell the financial ejections involved and that we shall await the Government of India*s reactions before preparing detailed financial proposals* Investigation of the Consular Posts in Persia which it will be necessary to maintain and staff by ibi eian Wrvioe Officers with reinforcement from the I*P*S+ The latest paper on this subject is foreign Office telegram 1240 /Financial Department F.13060/46, Heference to:- Tht^ Secretary, External Department. We seem to have made the following subsidies and gifts to the Sultan of Muscat during the war 1 - , (b) A war subsidy terminating at the end /2*(&lt;rv *' of 1946. (b) and (c) and the difference between concessional cost and the actual cost of the arms and auaunitlon in (d) are being shared between India and in the proportion of 45 : 55 and are being adjusted through the Elan, but h-is been charged wholly to Ihe Treasury, in Mr.Fetches letter to Mr. G&amp;rist of the 26th February, pointed out that it was decided at the time that incidence of cost of these stores should be discussed at the end of the war, and suggested that the 45 : 55 proportion should be applied to them as well. Ibu will see from Mr. Alexander*3 letter of the 28th October that the External Affairs Denartment of the Government of India do not agree with the Treasury. I propose to transmit the substance of Mr.Alexander's remarks to Mr.l'CEwing, who has succeeded Mr. Fetch at the Treas uy, but before doing so I should be glad of any observations you may wish to offer. (a) A gift of arms in 1939* (c) A gift of arms on the termination of the subsidy. (d) Sale of anas and ammunition at concessional price* (Sgd. ) E. 3. Brown, 5A1A6.(V iSi. S#3. BifjtTn. ( 2 ] Mr. Condor (. ,G. Dept.) •&gt;’e imve now obtained the agree lent of the Foreign Office to the India Office bearing on its vote the running of the Political Residency in the Persian (?ulf during the transitional period -ro a the Lime probably in the near future T ,vhen h*/4*G. will undertake entire control of the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf until the time that it can be transferred either to the Foreign Office cr the Colonial Office as the case may be. It lias been suggested that the roost convenient time for tf.i.i.G. to take over the financial responsibility from the Government of India would be the beginning of the next financial year. The upkeep of the actual , buildings will it is oonteirplated be undertaken by the ministry of oiks and the cost bomo on the vote for buildings overseas which I think is the responsibility of that Department. It will now be noceisary to secure the agreement of the ireasuiy to this arrangement, and it is pi'oposed to hold a meeting with th-t Department shortly at w: ioh it is hoped that A.G. and Financial Department will be represented, I will let you know further about this, aieanw .ile I atta&amp;h a statowient of the sanctioned bud et for 1946-4/ for the Political Residency, You will see that the ponts on the Persian side (wiiich will be taken over by.the Foreign Office) are yiven sepai'atedy from .those on the . r-b i ide, which will be under the India Oifice,Sxplanation oi' heads. B.l or C.3 (1) B.2 or C.3 (2) B.3 or C.3 (3) B.4 or C.3 (4) B.3 or c.3 (5) Pay of Officers Pay of establishment (Clerks, munahis, etc.) Allowances, Honoraria, etc. Secret expenditure Miscellaneous (postage, telegrams, maintenance of transport, contingencies). K.l Pay of officers ) K.2 Pay of establishment | Details as above, but K.3 Allowances temporary expenditure sanctioned for liar K.4 Miscellaneous ) duration only. K.3 Secret expenditure ) g_ot_e. The expenditure for the separated Kesideney at Bahrein and the Consulate-General Bushire has been calculated in some cases for 1546-47 sanctioned expenditure and in others from 1547-48 estimated expenditure. These i igures should therefore be taken as approximate only.1&gt; IRANIAN LEGATION. Statement of atfual expenditure incurred by the Government of India on Diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran for the year 1944-45 as compared with the previous year. Description of Charges 36.—External Affairs. Pay of Officers —• ^ Liaison Officer Comparison between Actuals for Actuals for columns 1 1943-44 1944-46 and 2» (1) (2) -f Increase, —Decrease. , R». ' Ra. Rs. Remarks. Nil 37,224 -j-37,224 (a) (a) New appointment. Total—Pay of Officer Nil 37,224 +37,224 Pay of Establishments — Escort . ... 828 828 Total—p^y of Establishments 828 828 Allowances —- Travelling Allowance Ration Allowance to Escorts . Subsistence Allowance . Allowances to Treasury Officer House-rent and other Allowan ces. Total—Allowancbs Contingencies — Postage and Telegram Charges Liveries and Warm Clothing . Agency Contingencies and Mis cellaneous. Total—Contingencies Total—35.—External Affairs Deduct 4,274 +4,274 (“) 1,645 2,007 +362 (b) 1,800 4,481 +4,481 (a) 1,800 (6) Vide remarks in 120 107 —is last year’s state ment. 3,565 12,669 +9,104 Net Total—35.—External Affairs. 57.—Miscellaneous. Loss by Exchange on Local Transactions. Total—57.— Miscellaneous , GRAND TOTAL M471AGCR 76 —76 274 4is + 144 295 426 + 131 645 844 + 199 5,038 51,565 +46,627 5,038 51,565 +46,527 —1 ' 4,807 +4,808 (d) —1 4,807 +4,808 5,037 56,372 +51,335 Tehran Legation Advance. &gt;SHIRAZ CONSULATE. Statement of actual expenditure incurred by the Government of India on Diplotr^^c and Consular Services in Iran for the year 1944-45 as compared with the previous year. Com par is ou between Actuals for Actuals for columns 1 Description of Charges. 1943-44 1944-45 and 2, (D (2) + Increase, —Decrease. Its. Rs. Rs. Remarks. 35.—External Affairs. Pa]f of Establishments —- Gardeners (Caretakers) . . 1,160 1,580 +430 (o) (a) Vide remarks in last year’s stats- ment. Total—Pay of Establishments 1,150 1,580 +430 Allowances — House-rent and other Allowan ces. 320 276 —44 Total—Allowances 320 276 —44 Works — Special Repairs •• •• Total—Wobks •• •• Total—35.—External Affairs 1,470 1,856 + 386 Deduct •• •• •• Net Total—35.—External Affairs. 1,470 1,856 +386 57.—Miscellaneous. w Loss by Exchange on Local Transactions. •• •• •• Total—57.—Miscellakeotts GRAND TOTAL 1,470 1,856 +3863 BtJSHIRE RESIDENCY. Siateu^xt of actual expenditure incurred try the Government of India on Diplomatic and (Xmular Services in Iran fen- the year 1944-46 as compared with the previous year. Description of Chargoi. 35.—External Affairs. Pay of Officers — Resident . . . t Surgeon .... Secretary .... Confidential Assistant now Asistant Secretary. Under Secretary . Personal Assistant Assistant Surgeons Registrar and Treasury Officer Vice-Consul .... Assistant Registrar . Consul .... Consular Agent, Lingah . Officer on special duty, civil wireless station, Jask. Total—Pat of Officers Pay of Establishments — Clerks ..... Escort Charges Bassidue Coal Depot Total—Pat of Establishments Allowances — House-rent and other Allowan- ces to Secretary and Under Secretary. House-rent and other Allowan ces to Consular Agent, Lingah. Travelling Allowance House-rent Allowance to Trea. sury Officer and Registrar. House-rent Allowance to Vice- Consul and Consul. House-rent and other Allowan ces to the Political Resident. House-rent and other Allowan ces to Establishment. House-rent Allowance to Sur geons and Assistant Sur geons. Sumptuary Allowance . Medical Treatment of officers . House-rent and other Allowan ces to Confidential Assistant now Under Secretary. House-rent and other Allowan ces to Assisant Registrar. War Allowance to Officer on Special Duty at Jask. Total—Allowances Actuals for 1943-44 (1) Rs. Actuals for 1944-45 (2) Re. Comparison between columns 1 and 2, Increase, —Decrease. Rs. Remark*. 49,800 5,126 22,737 6,088 12,326 8,351 6,786 12,875 4,781 14,857 2,419 3,762 51,748 6,310 21,427 7,139 13,596 5,934 7,256 12,443 4,500 14,083 *7,200 7,920 -f 1,948 (a) 4-1,184 (b) —1,310 (c) 4-1,051 (a) 4-1,270 (c) —2,417 (d) +470 ( 0 ) —432 (e) —281 (d) —774 (c) +4,781 (e) +4,158 (e) (а) Due to appoint ment of a substitute during leave (б) Unlike last year the post was not vacant. (c) Due to change of incumbents. (d) Post remained vacant during leave. (e) Post filled up for the whole year. 1,49,908 1,59,566 +9,648 ' . 39,012 42,162 +3,150 (/) (/) Due- to change 2,610 3,763 + 1.153 (?) of incumbents. i 41,622 45,925 +4,303 (g) Increased expen- 2,019 2,400 +381 (c) (h) Vide remarks in the last year’s state ment. , 967 3,930 + 2,963 {•) 44,269 43,244 —1,025 (t) Due to introduo- 5,020 4,026 —994 (c) tioUof war allowance. 1,770 2,121 + 351 (x) (1) Last year’s figures included 2,100 1,852 —248 {h) arrears of dearness allowance. 50,749 37,916 -12,833 (f)k(l) (x) Includes adjust- 6,017 5,535 —482 (d) ment of arrears. 3,452 4,204 + 752 («) 3,953 2,483 —1,470 (I) 5,337' 3,181 —2,156 (l) •• 298 +298 (♦) 1,25,653 1,11,190 —14,463X BAHREIN AGENCY. Stutsment uf actual expenditure incurred by the Government of India on Diplomatic Consular Services in Iran for the yexr 1944-45 as compared with the previous year. * * Description of Charges. • Actuals for 1943-44 ( 1 ) Rs. Actuals for 1944-45 ( 2 ) Rs. Comparison between columns 1 and 2 , -f- Increase, —Decrease. Rs. Remarks. 35.—External Affairs. &lt; Pay of Temporary Establish ment. 3,523 4,355 + 8,32 (a) (a) Due to change of incumbents and accrual of increment. Total—Pay ot Establishment 3,523 4,355 4-832 Allowances, honoraria, etc.-— Dearness allowance Travelling Allowance to Establishment. 2,203 418 1,940 —263 (b) (b) Last year’s figxrre* included arrears of dearness allowance. —418 (c) Total 2,621 1,940 —681 Contingencies — \ Hospital Contingencies and Medical Equipment. 3,492 3,334 —158 (c) ( c ) Less expenditure. Total 3,492 3,334 —158/ \ Total 35.— Exteknal Affairs 9,636 9,629 —7 [G. I. External Affairs Deptt. Memo. No. F. 18 (10)—E. (A)I3&amp;, dated 29-7-38.] SUPPLEMENTARY STATEMENT A. Miscellaneous Charges. Actuals Description of Charges. for Remarks. 1943-44. Rs. Cost of stationery, typewriters, books, forms, etc., supplied 4,181 to the Consulates in Iran and the Persian Gulf Charges for the carriage of Air mails and Official telegrams 48,600 sent to pests in Iran Chargs» for “ Jungle ” and “ Terai ” telegrams Total 52,781SUPPLEMENTARY STATEMENT B. » Muskat Political Agency. [Vide Secretary of State's Despatch No, 73 {Political), dated 30th July 1909.] Inscription of Charge*. Actuals for 1043-44 (D Rs. Actuals {or 1944-45 ( 2 ) Rs. Comparison between columns 1 and 2 , -f Increase, —Decrease. Rs. Remark* 85.—External Affairs. iftcial Charge *— \ Charges in connection vith the suppression of Slave Trade. Nil 195 + 193 GRAND TOTAL . Nil 193 + 193 ■ %. SUPPLEMENTARY STATEMENT C. Bahrein Agency. [Vide Secretary of Slat g’s Despatch No. 73 {Political), dated 30th July 1909.] Comparison between Description of Charge*. 85.—External Affairs. Special Charge*— Actuals for 1943-44 (D B*. Actuals for 1944-45 ( 2 ) Rs. columns l and 2 + Increasev —Decrease. Rs. Remark*. Charges in connection with the suppression of Slave Trade. Nil Nil GRAND TOTAL .] 6 SUPPLEMENTARY STATEMENT F. Statement of passage contributed for the year 1944-45. * {Vide India Office letter No. A. G.-3903, dated the 29th April 1931, and this office letter No. G. A. F. Main-27th 31-5725, dated the 24th September 1931, to the India Office.) Class of Officers. Amount of contribution. Its. ▲. p. I. C. S. Officers 2,450 0 0 Other Civil Officers .,..•••••••• 1,002 0 0 Military Comilkissioned Officers in permanent civil employ . . • , • $,196 0 0 Totax . 12,648 0 0 Audit Certificate, Certified that all charges included in the annual statement of expenditure in curred by the Government of India on Diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran in the year 1944-45 are properly divisible between Imperial and Indian Funds. RAM GOPAL, Accountant General, Central Revenues, M471AGCR—25—29-4-46—GIPS&gt;v 'fSMENT OF EXPENDITURE INCURRED ON THE KUWEIT AUEN 21 DURINu THE YEAR 1944-13. Actuals Descriptions of charges. for 1943-44. Ra. 85.—External AfTalrs. Pay of Officers — (1) Political Agent . . 18,687 (2) Assistant Surgeon 4,909 (3) Officers on special duty Total—Pat of Officers 23,596 Pay of Establishments — (1) Clerks .... 11.999 (2) Passport clerks .... 1,800 Total—Pay of Establishments 13,799 Allowances — Travelling Allowance . . 4.980 Sumptuary Allowance . 1,200 House-rent and other Allowances . 2,476 Dearness allowance .... 10,089 Total—Allowances 24.745 Sunnlies and Rp . rnir . es — Maintenance of Launch 5,939 Maintenance of Electric Plant 843 Maintenance and Renewal of Agency Furniture 440 Total—Supplies and Services . 7,272 Secret Service Expenditure . , . 300 Contingencies — Office Allowance . 18,308 Postage and Telegram Charges 19,584 Tour Charges 10,051 Kowoit Iraq Telegraph Line . 4,159 Total—Contingencies 52,702 Total—35.—External Affairs , 1,22,474 Deduct . 8,530 Net Total—35.—External Affairs . . 1,13,944 60.—Civil Works ..... . # . Deduct x . • •• Total—50.—Civil Works Remark*. Pnasport fe('» .. 8 . Miscellaneous 221 30‘J 8,f&gt;30 Gband Total 1,13.914Tala ran; tirade C. t pj ^ T • • HAY 'IRKSg 687,5 Foreign New iiellii From i ’ 0 No» T/b69 jatad ii7th (it reed. 28th) Auguati 1946. ^4 r &gt; p Transfer of Residency* £• Following are my proposals regarding transfer of Treasury* (a) Bushire Treasury to be transferred to Bahrain with effect from September IBth# (b) Eastern Bank Bahrain to act as Government Bankers* (c) Treasury Officer and staff excluding SHROFF v/ill be transferred to Bahrain Residency* (d) Senior Indian clerk with accounts experience will be left at Bushire to work as head clerk and accountant under Consul v n will himself function as ex OFFICIO Treasury Officer in same manner as Consuls at Kerman and Khorramshahr* (e) Bushire sanctioned buget grant for current year will be split up to provide funds separately for Bahrain Residency and Bushire Consulate for remaining period of financial year* The Treasury Officer is already preparing Budget estimates separately for Residency and Consulate for the next financial year* S* Grateful for approval of Government of India to above proposals and issue of specific authority by AGCR for items (a) and (b) in para 2 * •••••* iu ENCLOtUft* IN INSIA, roftllQN IWMTAIW'i tiff It Mo. OAT* 7 7 ■0° r /i '■t. Uk. No.F.4(33)-FII/4i. c Q 7 ', OFSHNiUfiOT OF IliOlA. vj O f J OOV^MiiNT OF ItJOlA. FINANCiS 0KPARTM1SSIT. Ul Oaiai.THIS 14TH SifTiil JciK, ‘ 1946* Hal oahib O.P. Oupta. Aaaiatant Secretary to the Government of India* The political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subject:- Transfer of Bushire Treasury to Bahrain. • • • • y Sir f _ . I am directed to convey the sanction of the Grovernment of Inaia to the transfer of Residency Treasury from Bushire to Bahrain with efiect from the Ihth September 1946. The cash business of the Treasury at Bahrain may be transacted by the Eastern Bank Ltd. 9 Bahrain. 2. Necessary correction to the •Listol Treasuries and dub-treasuries In India and Burma* will/be issued in due course. (i) I have the honour to be f Sir t Your most obedient servant, bd/- O.P.Gupta Assistant becretary to the Govt, of India. ■Xq.P a 4(B3)-FII/46. Copy forwarded to the following the External Affairs Department with reference to their u.o. No• ii/46, dated the 10th beptember 1946. Their papers are returned herewith. (ii) The Chief Accountant , Reserve Bank of India, Central Office. Bombay. ♦ Uii) The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. m By order, etc., Gd/- O.P. Gupta Assistant becretary to the Government of India. . • . \ I- 1AU1 S&amp;P—(M-23e) 7 5-41—400,000S. 6. expense and undue use oj the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedilio/i as if it had been telegraphed, J c save time and formalities it is worded artd signed as if it had been so despatched.] Fkom REPGU BAHRAIN r To FOREIGN NEW DELHI So. 3120 - 66/10* Bahrain, Dated 27th September, 1946* Reference Government of India telegram No. 223/E/ -r Camp/46 dated September 18th. I 2. As stated in my telegram No. X/5 dated the 11th September, 1946, gratuities were proposed for menials who have to be discharged as a result of transfer of Residency and who are either not required by us or do not wish to serve in Bahrain. Finance Department office memorandum referred to in your telegram appears only to relate to temporary Government servants who rendered approved service in the period from 3rd September, 1939, to 31st October, 1945, and who are discharged on account of reduction of establishment in the period from 1st August, 1945, to 31st October, 1946. Submit general terms of the memorandum do not apply to special case was most important to close our account in Bushire and to compensate promptly servants of ours (some of long standing) whom we were getting rid of practically without notice. A further Rs.3,000/=, I now estimate, ought to meet the balance of the gratuities proposed. Grateful therefore if Rs.7,500/= in all be sanctioned for expenditure under this head. 4. Gratuities are being paid at rate of half a month pay for every year of service. question of menials/in Bushire. 3. Have alrea Have already spent Rs.4,300 in gratuities as it = R E P G U = The issue of the ised. Secret! esidentI - POLITICAL R ZJIDI^CY The follav/ing arc the Officers at the Headquarters of the i oULtical Reiildtonqy, Persian Gulf, now situated at B hrein:- (1) A Holilical Resident ( 2 ) A ^ocr^t-xry and an Undej^-jocrctary to the Political iesidcnt. (3) A Residency ..ur. con and an Assistant Residency ^ur^^eon. (4) A Confidential Assistant* (b) A Treasury Officer and Registrar» and an Assistant Registrar* These eight caaprioe the whole of the British Officers of the dency. Thera is in addition an ustablishaent of a _ ^ent, a •ersonal Assistant, cl rks, inunshis, etc., filled loainly by Indian or by localiy-recruitod personnel* u - QLxric.x /vG;aci.di (kow: jt* bail: xi &amp; muu: vg) There are also throe Political .Agencies - at Koveit, Muscat and Bahrein, v/hich latter covers the Trucial ( oa t and star* The Officials are:- (1) u.L&gt;c'-vt » A iolitlcal gent (also ('onsul), cui issi/j^ant alit£c&lt;Al A^ent * a Treasury Officer and a Medical Officer. ( 2 ) Zwclt * A Political Agent and an ssistant ourgecn (3) Bahrcisi * A Political gent , an ssistant politiciU. gent , and an Indian Assistant; an Agency Burgeon; a Residency AgenF T'and a lolitical Officer f or the Arucial Coast* Aach Agency has an establishment of cl&lt;rk:s, inunshis, etc. The Official Personnel for the Residency and the gencies arc ai i supplied by the Indian Political crvice* The expenditure is • u borne by the Gov mment of India, except for a half-share in thf cost of the Residency and the Agency at Koweit, which is contributed by tii© Poreign Office* The ov rail eo t, at resent rates of pay etc*, works out at about £75#OOC p*a.Dear Donaldson, This is a brief note on the point I put to you over the telephone concerning the Persian Gkilf establishments. The figures o^ cost extracted by your Department as ^detailed in the statements accompanying the India Office note cover as far as can be ascertained only actual expenditure wrought to account in India. If you will refer to the statement in your possession of D. &amp; C. expenditure in Persia etc. for 19A4-45, you will see that in addition to such actual outlay the charges to be adjusted with the Foreign Office include, vide the supplementary statements at the end, leave and pension contribution, as well as sterling overseas pay with appropriate contribution addition. The former is'a sizable item, totalling Rs. 1 , 64,411 or over £ 12,000 and the ether accounts for nearly £4,400. I also notice a*n entry of Rs.S2,78l, mainly for oommunications charges, arising in India vi .e supplementary Stateiiient A, the corresponding item to which is almost certainly not apportioned out in the figures extracted by you; though on the other hand the passage contribution charge in Statement P is so broken down. I accordingly sug ;est that in calcuting the gross cost of the establishments to be borne by H.14 i/it is essential to acui se/eral items of quite appreciable amount in all. What the figures should be is not within our power to estimate, as (a) ohe largest item, leave and pension contributions is consolidated and cannot be apportioned here to the various posts and (b) the cost of Bahrein and Misoat does not enter into the D. &amp; C. adjustments. It seems that, as the D. &amp; C. adjustment requires a separate compilation for Koweit, only in tha o case is it possible to get at the approximate gross cost by a combination of the two sources of information.FUTURE ARR^U'/GEiuUrTT3 REGj^RDING AES'lEFISTR. iTION ,JlD COUEROL IW THE iHE'LB SHEIIjm^ OF THE PERSIST GULI* 1 Note by Colonel Hav Tae Cabinet have decided in principle that II.;..G. should take over froL: the Government of India responsibility for dealings with the Arab 3bates in the Persian Gulf, arising from this decision the following points are for immediate consideration:- ( jj -) what dote will H.ii.G. take over responsibility ? 2. The interim Government in India have not yet been informed of ri.w.G.‘s decision and it is not known what attitude they will adopt. It io however important that in order to prevent Indian interference with our essential interests in the Persian Gulf H.L.G. should take over administrative control without delay. The Government of India are only likely to agree to this if financial responsibility is tolcen ov^r s imul t ane ou s ly. The expenditure involved is normal expenditure of about ,€70,000 pur cjmum (of which about €23,500 is already borne by H.li.G.) plus spcciia Wartime^ expenditure oi about €34,000 (which is divisible between H.L.G, and the Government of India in a proposition not yet agreed) some of which wi1.l now have to bo continued in peacetime. It is proposed with the G 1 Qnc ^ rcnGc 01 * tllc ‘ Foreign Office that for the tine being the India Office should continue to deal with the Persian Gulf, and that the expenditure should do borne on the Indi,. Office vote. 4. It is accordingly suggested that H.iI.G. should take over all responsibility including financi 1 responsibility from the earliest possible date \/hich might be fixed not later than 1st April, 1947. ( B ) the .Gulf posts to be staff ed after H.H.G. have talcen over? 5* _ j-s suggested that for the present the existing staff should be retained in its entirety and that the Government of India should be asked to supply reliefs, disburse salaries, etc. as in the past, acting as agents of H.A.G. ^ (C) On p/h at terns \/il.I officers, ministerial fie, clerical) staff, etc, in the Gulf continue to serve? o. It is suggested that for the present the existing rates jf pay and allowances and any concessions enjoyed should be retained. If the Government of India is to continue to provide reliefs for officers from the Indian Political Service it is clearly desirable that the existing conditions of service should be retained. When the Government of India Act is repealed changes will be introduced in the terms of service of officers appointed by the Secretary of State for India. It will then be necessary to determine what officers and other staff H.ii.G, intend t a employ in the Persian Gif If posts and what terms they will offer those officers whose services they wish to retain. (O) Hoy is the Government of India 1 s prQwerty in the Gulf, c.a. buildings, furniture, office cquiment to be dealt with? 7• Tt is suggested that this should all bo teikon over at a valuation as S3on as possible. If this is not done it is possible that the Government of India may try to insist on appointing their own / represent at ivorepresentative in seme ef the C-ulf States cud. en their tricing over Government of India property. In these circumstances officers may find themisclves without accommodation :nd offices. (Sgd. ) \i. H. Hay 23.10.Aj6. // India Office, Whit chall, S. W. 1. Ext, 6309/46 . 2 6 SEP W*6 I not sure whether you intend to circulate a record of the meeting held in your room on 11th September to discuss action to be taken on the recommendations in t.he Cabinet Paper CP( 46)329, but I have already sent to T. J.Wilson budget estimates showing the cost of maintaining the establishments staffed by the Government of India at the various diplomatic and consular posts in adjacent countries which it is contemplated that His Majesty* s Government will, sooner or later, have to take over. 2* It seems to us, however, that our first attention ought really to be given to the Persian G-ulf Residency and its subordinate posts. You will ranombor that the Cabinet decided 'to assume as rapidly as possible direct control of, and responsibility for, the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf and his subordinate agencies'. For this reason, and also because the question has arisen in practical fom already, I think we should now make up our minds on a recommendation to the Treasury as to the vote on which the cost of maintaining the Residency etc. is to fall when the control of the Persian G-ulf posts is taken over by His Majesty* s Government from the Government of India in accordance with the Cabinet decision. So far as I can make out from the data available here, the cost of running the Residency and Agencies works out at something like £75,000 a year. 3. Until May last, the Political Resident had his Headquarters at Bushire in Persian territory (where, since 1878, he had been recognised by the Persian Government as Consul-General). Ho is now, however, by Cabinet decision, restricted to exercising his functions on the Arab shore of the Gulf and is camping out in temporary accommodation in the Naval Base at Jufair (Bahrein). He has been forced to incur certain expenditure estimated at about £ 2,300 on adapting the naval buildings for his use, but you will see from the enclosed letter to Winnifrith that the Government of India will not supply funds for the conversion of these buildings; first, because H.A.Caooia, Esq,, C.M.G,, Foreign Office, 8, Carlton House Terraco S.W, 1, /the /the Cabinet decision to move the Resident 1 s Headquarters from Bushire was taken in spite of their strongly expressed disapproval, but also because they (in the person of Weightman, the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department) know that His Majesty* s Government are very soon going to take ^ over control of the Residency, Y/e are accordingly asking tho Treasury if the expenditure may be sanctioned. 4. The Political Resident has local charge of His Majesty* s Government's relations with the principalities of the Persian Gulf, (all of which - except Muscat - are British Protected States and none of whose rulers - except the Sultan of Muscat - have ary direct foreign relations^; he is not therefore a 'diplomatic' Representative, He is moreover responsible for a mass of internal administration work, most of which has been dealt with hitherto by the Government of India but some of which has to come home for approval. As examples of this I would mention that the Political Resident is responsible for the control of the movement of foreigners, the functioning of the local Agency courts (in respect of foreigners and British subjects and protected persons) whore Indian law is applicable, supervision of the working of the oil companies; civil aviation and telecommunications concessions, and quarantine administration. It is also likely that responsibility for lighting and buoying in the Persian Gulf and for the postal administration in the Sheikhdoms and Muscat will also have to be taken over by the Home Government. Apart from these matters, there is of course the financial administration of the establishments, the posting of officers and the recruitment of subordinate staff, for all of which the Political Resident is at present responsible to the Government of India. 5* Eventually cither the Colonial Office or the Foreign Office will presumably have to take ovor the Residency and all its works as a charge on its vote, but owing to the necessity for a transitional period during which the Government of India's control could be gradually transferred, and because of the hitherto predominantly Indian character of the administration, it may be thought convenient that this transfer should, during the transitional period, bo supervised by the India Office, the cost being borne on our vote3. e until the of control and absorption of personnel etc. is complete. with the other departments concernod and, meanwhile, I am sending a copy of this letter to Winnifrith at the Treasury. As to the subsidiary question when such discussion should take place, we think that it would be more profitably conducted if we had the Political Resident available to participate; and we have just heard that Colonel Hoy will be coming home on deputation in about a week* s time. 7* I also enclose a copy of a letter I am sending to Winnifri regarding sanction for the item of expenditure referred to in paragraph 3 above. figt) fc* p. J - NALDStta</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000074_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3555A</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000074</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3555A</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/2(4) 'Financial arrangements involved in the transfer of the Residency; budget file 1947-1948'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-01T10:57:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (188 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 189; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the financial aspects of the transfer of the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf from Bushire to Bahrain.The file is composed solely of internal correspondence between British officials including the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, HM Treasury, and the External Affairs Department of the Government of India.The correspondence relates specifically to the following:'Future arrangements regarding administration and control in the Arab Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf';budgets of British Consulates in Iran, Political Residency and Political Agencies in 1946-48;war expenditure;demand for grants for building works;application of Foreign Service Regulations to the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>British</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000074#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>