<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000392_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-12-05T11:47:25.561Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with, unless required for official use List o( — 1949 1 Permanent and Temporary Officers of His Majesty’s Foreign Service at Consular Posts AUGUST 1949 CONSULAR OFFICERS SHOULD IN ALL CASES BE ADDRESSED NOT BY NAME BUT BY OFFICIAL DESIGNATION [ANY CORRECTIONS SHOULD BE NOTIFIED TO THE RECORDS SECTION, PERSONNEL DEPARTMENT]1949 Permanent and Temporary Officers of His Majesty’s Foreign Service at Consular Posts [To avoid delay in communicating with British Consular Officers, they should be addressed not by name but by their official designation, i.e., British ^ Consul-General, Consul, Vice-Consul, or Consular Agent at .] &lt; ! Notes. —(C.O.)—Paid by Colonial Office. (P.)—Personal rank. (L.R.)—Local rank. # Temporary Officers holding the King’s Commission. Temporary Officers of His Majesty’s Foreign Service are shown in italics. CONSULAR POSTS ABROAD Country AND KESIDENCE Rank Titular Officer Date of Appointment AFGHANISTAN— Jalalabad Consul( a ) Khan Sahib Abdur Rahman ... April 17, 1944 Kandahar Consul( a ) ... ... Khan Bahadur Ziauddin Ahmad June 5, 1942 ALBANIA— . ARGENTINE REPUBLIC— Buenos Aires Consul-General Vaughan-Russell, J. F. R. Dec. 10, 1947 Consul Vice-Consul Coates, P. U. (designate) Kelly, B. ... Feb. 26, 1941 Vice-Consul Dawson, L. J. ... Jan. 1, 1946 Feb. 10, 1943 Pro-Consul ... Spillcr, A. G. A. ... Oct. 9, 1948 Bahia Blanca ... Vice-Consul Summerbell, S. L. Mar. 1, 1942 Comodoro Rivadavia... Vice-Consul Charles, W. Oct. 25, 1948 Concordia Vice-Consul (Acting) Tail, J. A. ... Oct. 11, 1948 La Plata Vice-Consul Puleston, W. W., M.B.E. April 25, 1933 Pro-Consul ... Johnson, 0. Feb. 19, 1945 Mar del Plata Vice-Consul (Acting) Flint, G. A. June , 1947 Mendoza Vice-Consul Walker, R. 1. Nov. 9, 1948 Puerto Deseado Vice-Consul Bateman, H. April 21, 1942 Kio Gallegos ... Vice-Consul (Acting)( c ) ... Rae, G. T. Nov. 19, 1946 Rio Grande (Tierra Vice-Consul Bridges, G. P. April 21, 1942 del Fuego) San Julian Vice-Consul Scott, J. ... Sept. 17, 1948 Santa Cruz Trelew Vice-Consul Vice-Consul (Acting) (Vacant) ... Bideleux, A. F. ... April 1, 1946 Rosario Consul ... Dempster, E. N., O.B.E. April 5, 1949 Pro-Consul... Hibbert, L. J. July 23, 1948 Cordoba Santa F^ (Closed) Vice-Consul Macintosh, J. N. ... Feb. 29, 1940 AUSTRIA— Vienna Consul (L.R.)( d ) ... Vice-Consul Reuterdahl, J. K., M.B.E. (desig nate) Hallett, N. M. May 27, 1948 Innsbruck Vice-Consul (L.R.)( b ) Consul (L.R.) Auger, A. S. Landale, R. T. Mar. 5, 1949 Feb. 27, 1949 Vice-Consul Murray, F. W. W Aug. 15, 1949 BELGIUM— Antwerp Consul-General Sebastian, E. G„ C.B.E., D.S.O. Nov. 14, 1944 Consul (L.R.) Arning, C. W„ M.B.E Mar. 4, 1949 Vice-Consul (L.R.) Niblett, A. E. Dec. 12, 1939 Vice-Consul (L.R.) Overlaet, C. G. (Naturalised B.S ) Dec. 1, 1944 Dec. 1, 1944 Ca) Maintnined by Government of Pakistan (&lt;') Is also Vice-Consul for Santa Cruz (b) Has local rank of Third Secretary (d) Has local rank of First Secretary 14601—3 3748822 Country and Residence 1 Rank J Titular Officer Date of Appointment URUGUAY— Montevideo • Consul (with rank of First Dalton, P. G. F. ... May 27, U*7 * Secretary in charge of Consular Section) Vice-Consul( a ) Barker, L. A. P. ... Oct. 18, 1948 Pro-Consul ... McIntyre, A. T. ... Nov. 20, 1947 Maldonado Vice-Consul May, B. W. Anson- Oct. 5, 1948 VENEZUELA— Caracas Consul( b ) Robinson, J. Mar. 31, 1947 Consul (Acting) Broker, R. Dec. 6, 1948 Pro-Consul ... Stem, C. M. Jan. 17, 1949 Caripito Vice-Consul (Acting) Murphy, H. C. ... , 1943 Carupano Vice-Consul (Acting) Franceschi, J. (French Vene- Feb. 6, 1943 Ciudad Bolivar El Callao La Guaira Vice-Consul (Closed) Vice-Consul zuelan) Fox, A Sept. 2, 1940 Las Piedras ... Vice-Consul Anderson, Capt. J. B. ... Mar. 1, 1940 Maracaibo Puerto Cabello and Vice-Consul Pro-Consul ... Vice-Consul Hill, F.B Wareham, S. W. , 1946 Mar. 1, 1945 Valencia Puerto La Cruz Vice-Consul ... ... YUGOSLAVIA— Belgrade Consul (L.R.) (with local Manning, W. Dec. 3, 1948 rank of Second Secretary in charge of Consular Section) Pro-Consul Simon, T. G. April 13, 1949 Sarajevo Skoplje(°) (Closed) Consul (L.R.) Leonard, G. S., M.B.E. ... Sept. , 1949 Ljubljana Zagreb (Closed) Consul-General Stevenson, R. C., C.B.E. Nov. 25, 1947 Vice-Consul Kay, T. H. (Naturalised B.S.) ... Dec. 24, 1945 Vice-Consul (Inf.) ... Gibbs, J. S. Sept. , 1946 Vice-Consul Riederer, G. A Jan. 1 , 1949 Split( c ) Consul (L.R.) Burton, Major G. H. Oct. 1, 1948 (a) Holds local rank of Second Secretary (c) Career post (b) Holds rank of First Secretary. Exequatur as His Majesty’s Consul not granted by the Venezuelan Government.6 Country and Name Designation Residence and Telephone Number CHILE (continued) Senor Don Humberto Videla ... * Minister-Counsellor Flat 7, 24 Lowndes Street, S.W. 1. SLOane 9724 Senorita Mercedes Videla (Daughter) Senor Don Pedro Enrique Alfonso * Commercial Counsellor Villa d’Arno, 5 Albany Park Road, Kingston-on-Thames. Senor Don Horacio Suarez 1st Secretary Flat 45, 60 Park Lane, W. 1. GROsvenor 2897 Commander Kaare Olsen * Naval Attache 3 Southwick Street, W. 2. PADdington 6868 Squadron Leader Anibal Solminhiac * Air Attache Flat 5, Audley House, 9 North Audley Street, W. 1. Senor Don Juan Jose Fernandez 3rd Secretary Ditto. Senor Don Jose Antonio Gandarillas* Secretary 14 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, S.W. 3. FLAxman 3695 Senorita Carmen Gandarillas (Daughter) Senor Don Calixto Rogers * Attache 44 Mitcham Lane, S.W. 16. STReatham 8544 CHINA His Excellency Dr. Cheng Tien-Hsi * Ambassador Extra 49 Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 5194 Miss Cheng Ying-Wan ordinary and Plenipo tentiary (Daughter) Dr. Tuan Mao-Lan Minister-Counsellor 10 Lansdowne Road, W. 11. PA Rk 6263 Dr. Seymour C. Y. Cheng Counsellor 49 Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Tan Pao-shen Counsellor, 1st Secretary Flat 161, Rivermead Court, S.W. 6. Miss Tan Sien F'en (Daughter) RENown 2696 Mr. Chen Yao-sheng * 1st Secretary 32 Maxwell Road, North wood, Middlesex. Mr. Lee Yone-Ming * Ditto Northwood 2134 Heathside Cottage, 8 Heathside Close, Mr. Ho Sze-ko ... Ditto ... Northwood, Middlesex. Northwood 590 49 Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Wang Ting-Shan ... * 2nd Secretary Ditto. Mr. Kuan Chuan-Tsai ... 3rd Secretary Ditto. Mr. Lin Chih-chi * Ditto 32 Maxwell Road, Northwood, Middlesex. Mr. Lee En-Kuo 3rd Secretary and Northwood 2134 49 Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Kwoh Tseh-ching ... * Attache to the Em bassy Ditto 103c Greencroft Gardens, N.W. 6. Mr. Chao Chin-Yung * 3rd Secretary MAIda Vale 3305 “ Collingwood,” Joel Street, Pinner, Middle Mr. Wan Moo Chou Attache sex. PINner36\l 49 Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 5794 Mr. Wang Shih-Yong ... * Ditto 36 Goldhurst Terrace, N.W. 6. Mr. Tai Erh-ching * Ditto 49 Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 5194 Mr. Lai Tien-Chang Ditto Ditto. Mr. Johnson Cheng * Ditto Ditto. Mr. Fan Kuang-Tao * Ditto 39 Highbury Hill, N. 5. Mr. Liu Wei-Hsiung • • • Ditto ... 49 Portland Place. W. 1. WELbeck 579419 24 - Country and Name Designation Residence and Telephone Number PORTUGAL (continued) Commander Jose Conceifao da Rocha, O.B.E. * Lieutenant-Colonel Luiz Maria de Cajaara Pina, O.B.E. Senl^ Jose Manuel de Magalhaes Pessoa e Fragoso Senhor Antonio Potier Naval Attache Military Attache 3rd Secretary Ditto ... 32 Walton Street, S.W. 3. KENsington 7837 20 Draycott Avenue, S.W. 3. KENsington 8785 11 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. SLOam? 6444 103 Sloane Street, S.W. 1. SLOane 0095 Senhor Luiz Leotte do Rego ... * Commercial Attache ... Ditto. Senhor Joao Antas de Campos * Ditto 17a Carlton Road, W. 5. ROUMANIA His Excellency Monsieur Mihail Envoy Extraordinary 1 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. KENsington 4836 Macavei * and Minister Plenipo Monsieur George Macovescu . * tentiary 1st Counsellor of Lega Ditto. Monsieur Paul Cornea ... * tion Press Counsellor Ditto. Monsieur Eugen Mantu * 2nd Secretary 26 Cadogan Square, S.W. 1. Mile. Vera Simon 3rd Secretary 1 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. Monsieur Jacques Berman .. * Commercial Counsellor 56 Stanhope Gardens, S.W. 7. Mme. Elisabeta Cornea • at* Ditto 1 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. SAUDI ARABIA His Excellency Sheikh Hafiz Wahba, K.C.V.O.* Monsieur Shaher A1 Samman ... ►£&lt; Ambassador Extra-’ ordinary and Plenipo tentiary Counsellor 30 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. Ditto. SLOane 3898 Mile. Sahab Samman (Daughter) Monsieur Ahmed Safei El Din * 2nd Secretary Ditto. Monsieur Abdel Rehman Helaissi Ditto Ditto. Monsieur Fuad A. Nazir * 3rd Secretary Ditto. Monsieur Abdulgani Ydlibi Monsieur Mohammed Mahdi Muslih Hon. Commercial At tache Attache Ditto. Ditto. SIAM His Serene Highness Prince Nakkhatra Ambassador Extra 23 Ashburn Place, S.W. 7. FRObisher 2983 Mangala Kitiyakara * ordinary and Plenipo Luang Phinit Akson * tentiary Counsellor Ditto. Luang Chamnong Dithakar 2nd Secretary Ditto. Nai Sawet Tantraporn * Ditto Ditto. Nai Klin Devahastin * Ditto Ditto. Nai Pun Chongprasoet* 3rd Secretary Ditto. Nai Sophon Chuenchum * Ditto Ditto. Nai Thiem Ladanon* Attache Ditto.24 Country and Name UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA (continued) Designation Residence and Telephone Number Mr. R. G. Malloch Brown * 3rd Secretary New Barn Cottage, Colgate, Nr. Horsham, Sussex. Fay gate 236 Mr. J. B. Mills ... * Ditto 28 Overbury Avenue, Beckenham, Kent. Beckenham 1054 112 Great Russell Street, W.(^. MUSeum 8954 Mr. G. V. Doxey Ditto Brigadier H. G. Willmott, C.B.E * Military Adviser 21 De Vere Gardens, Kensington, W. 8. WEStern 0582 Lieutenant-Colonel C. Gey van Pittius * Air Liaison Officer Rose Cottage, Thorpe Lea, Egham, Surrey. Egham 39 Mr. A. P. van der Post * Senior Trade Commis sioner Flat 10, Porchester Gate, Bayswater Road, W. 2. BAYswater 6114 Mr. J. Mockford * Director of Public Rela tions 120 Chiltern Court, Regents Park, N.W. 1. WELbeck 5544 Mr. V. O. Reid ... * Mining and Minerals Adviser “ Green Shaw,” Spring Woods, Virginia Water, Surrey. Wentworth 2\9% UNITED STATES His Excellency the Honourable Lewis Ambassador Extra 14 Prince’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 1089 W. Douglas * ordinary and Plenipo tentiary [Offices of the Embassy: 1 Grosvenor Square, W. 1. GROsvenor 4111] Miss Sharman Douglas (Daughter) Mr. Thomas K. Finletter * Minister-Chief of Mis sion for Economic Co operation 1 Grosvenor Square, W. 1. GROsvenor 4\\\ Miss Margot Finletter (Daughter) Mr. Julius C. Holmes * Minister Plenipotentiary, Counsellor of Embassy 50 Chester Square, S.W. 1. SLOane 4406 Brigadier-General Marshall S. Carter* Minister-Special Assist ant to the Ambassador 2 Park Street, W. 1. MAY fair 8166 Mr. Erie R. Dickover ... * Counsellor (Far Eastern Affairs) Flat 41, No. 3 Grosvenor Square, W. 1. MA Yfair 5742 Mr. Don C. Bliss * Counsellor (Economic) 83 Harley House, Regent’s Park, N.W. 1. WELbeck 1837 Mr. Gerald Keith * Counsellor 3 Wilton Street, S.W. 1. SLOane 7023 Mr. Mallory Browne * Ditto Garden Cottage, Wentworth, Virginia Water, Surrey. Wentworth 3209 Mr. John W. Bailey, Jr.* 1st Secretary Hendon Hall Hotel, Ashley Lane, N.W.4. Hendon 1456 Miss Frances E. Willis ... Ditto Flat 16, 60 Park Lane, W. 1. MA Yfair 7906 Mr. William C. Trimble * Ditto 10 Radnor Place, W. 2. AMBassador 5891 Mr. G. Lewis Jones Ditto 8 Abbey Lodge, Park Road, N.W. 1. A MBassador 3622 Mr. Henry E. Stebbins Ditto Mayfair Chambers, 1 Balderton Street, W. 1. MA Yfair 4354 Mr. James C. Sappington * Ditto 14 Montpelier Square, S.W. 7. KENsington 9143 Mr. Basil D. Dahl Ditto 301 Stratford Court, Oxford Street, W. 1. MAY fair 1414 Mr. Frederic P. Bartlett Ditto Flat 21, 32 Grosvenor Street, W. 1. MA Yfair 6935 Mr. Samuel D. Berger ... * Ditto 19 Salisbury Place, W. 1. WELbeck 7875 Miss Kathleen Molesworth Ditto Flat 25, 32 Grosvenor Street, W. 1. MAY fair 0865 Mr. Joseph E. Charles * • Ditto 12 Cresswell Gardens, S.W. 5. FREmantle 7375 Mr. David A. Thomasson * Ditto 18 Moore Street, S.W. 3. KENsington 1844 Mr. W. Stratton Anderson. Jr. ... * 2nd Secretary Flat 4, 3 Stanhope Place, W. 2. A MB as sad or 3752 Mr. Fritz A. M. Alfsen * Ditto 1 Cranley Mansions, 160 Gloucester Road. S.W. 7. FREmantle 1694 Mr. William Hamilton * Ditto Arbrook Cottage, Claygate, Surrey. Esher 956 Mr. Cornelius J. Dwyer * Ditto 1 Lansdown Walk, W. 11. PARk 9238 Mr. Herbert F. Propps ... 3rd Secretary 42 Clarendon Road, Netting Hill.26 Country and Name Designation Residence and Telephone Number UNITED STATES (continued) Dr. Thomas Park* Attache 1 Stanford Road, Kensington Court, W. 8. Mr. Harris R. Hungcrford * Ditto ... WEStern 2734 Flat 11, Harrowby Court, Seymour Place, Mr. William C. Buell ... * Ditto W. 1. PADdington 9176 Flat 1, 15 Chelsea Embankmcr^ S.W. 3. Mr. Sargent B. Child * Ditto FLAxman 7168 51 Murray Road, Wimbledon, S.W. 19. Mr. Ernest A. Lister ... * Civil Air Attache Cape Cottage, 18 Neville Drive, Hampstead Mr. Leo F. Centner * Attache Garden Suburb, N. 2. SPEedwell 9424 8 Edwardes Square, W. 8 WEStern 6524 Mr. John E. P. Grant* ... Ditto Flat 19, 47 Grosvenor Square, W. 1. Mr. William H. J. McIntyre * Ditto GROsvenor 2484 Flat 36, St. James’s Close, Prince Albert Mr. Peter Abeille * Ditto Road, N.W.8. PRImrose6m Flat 12, Park West, Edgware Road, W. 2. Mr. Findley Weaver * Ditto PADdington 1280, Ext. 12 16 Winnington Road, N. 2. MEAdway 2120 Mr. J. David Linebaugh * Ditto 9 Carlyle Close, Hampstead Garden Suburb, Mr. Richard P. Taylor ... * Ditto N.W. 11. MEADway 2982 3 Roedean Crescent, Roehampton, S.W. 15. Mr. Barrett Parker Ditto PROspect 3130 7 Spanish Place Mansions, Manchester Mr. Carl Ginsburg * Ditto Square, W. 1. WELbeck 2121 21 Knightsbridge Court, Sloane Street, Mr. William B. Hussey * Ditto S.W. 1. SLOane 8783 “ Queme,” Stubbings, near Maidenhead, Mr. John J. Coyle * Ditto Berks. Little Wick Green 79 907 Howard House, Dolphin Street, S.W. 1. Mr. Paul H. Green Ditto Victoria 3800, Ext. Howard 907 Flat 714, Nell Gwynne House, Sloane Mr. Paul Felix Warburg * Ditto Avenue,Chelsea, S.W. 3. KENsington 9777 10 Wood’s Mews, Park Lane, W. 1. Mr. Joseph Polakoff * Assistant Attache MA Yfair 1213 Flat 71, Park West, Edgware Road, W. 2. Mr. Conrad J. Thoren ... Ditto ... PADdington 1280, Ext. 71 Flat 19, Dorset House, Gloucester Place. Mr. Felix S. Verity Ditto N.W. 1. WELbeck 5522 Winfield House, Outer Circle, Regent’s Park, Mr. John A. Cimperman Legal Attache N.W. 1. AMBassador 5 192 4 Dudley Court, Upper Berkeley Street, W. 1. Mr. Sidney J. Kennedy * Treasury Attache PADdington 0192 8 Queen Anne Street, W. 1. LANgham 1443 Mr. William L. Hebbard * Financial Attache 41 Frognal, Hampstead, N.W. 3. Mr. Charles R. Harley ... * Assistant Financial Attache Attache ... 27 Lindfield Gardens, Hampstead, N.W. 3. Mr. Norman R. Hagen * 15 Whitelands House, King’s Road, Chelsea- Mr. Winston M. Scott ... * Ditto ... S.W. 3. ' SLOane MU 33 Swan Court, Chelsea, S.W. 3. Dr. Arthur S. Osborne ... * Ditto FLAxman 2353 Stiver’s Corner, Coke’s Lane, Chalfont St. Mr. Glenn D. Fields * Ditto Giles, Bucks. Little Chalfont 2X11 702 Drake House, Dolphin Square, S.W. 1. Special Victoria 3800, Ext. 702 Mission for Economic Co-operation Mr. Henry Siegbert * Deputy Chief of Mission Dorchester Hotel, W. 1. MAY fair MM Dr. John Cassels* Economic Commissioner 40 Green Street, W. 1. Mr. Elmer N. Holmgreen * Ditto ... Collet Court, 126 Sloane Street, S.W. 1. Miss Shirley Anne Holmgreen (Daughter) SLOane 7578 Mr. James S. Killen* ... Economic Commissioner 35 Kingston House, Prince’s Gate, S.W. 7. Mr. Alfred D. Lindley ... * Ditto KENsington 6973 15 Montpelier Square, S.W. 7. Mr. Tremper Longman ... * Ditto KENsington 9515 39 Orchard Court, Portman Square, W. 1. WELbeck 544628 Country and Marne Designation Residence and Telephone Number YUGOSLAVIA His Excellency Monsieur Obrad Cicmil Ambassador Extra 24 Harrington Gardens, S.W. Dr. Franc Kos * ordinary and Plenipo tentiary Counsellor [Offices of the Embassy: 25 Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400] 25 Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. Monsieur Erik Kos * Ditto KENsington 3400 Ditto. Monsieur Hugo Havlicek* Commercial and Finan 195 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Dr. Josip Presburger * cial Counsellor Secretary (Consular 25 Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. Monsieur Miroslav Milutinovic * Dept.) Secretary KENsington 3400 Ditto. Monsieur Velimir Rodica * Ditto Ditto. Lieutenant-Colonel Mate Jurcic * Acting Military, Air and 1a Palace Gate, W. 8. Major Rade Trost Monsieur Branko Japundzic ... * Naval Attache Assistant Military, Naval and Air Attache Commercial Attache ... [Office: 195 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 5439 and 3400] 195 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Monsieur Mihovil Kapetanic ... * Ditto KENsington 3400 Ditto. Monsieur Stevan M. Nikolajevic Special Attache 25 Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. Monsieur Jovan Jovasevic Financial Attache Ditto. Mme. Desanka Bilic Attache Ditto. [Office: 195 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400] LIST OF PERSONS NO LONGER INCLUDED IN THE FOREGOING LIST BUT STILL ACCEPTED BY HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT AS PERSONALLY POSSESSING DIPLOMATIC PRIVILEGES Name Rank Residence and Telephone Number His Excellency Monsieur August Torma * Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary Counsellor of Legation, 1st Secretary 167 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 5473 and 5474 Monsieur Ernst Sarepera* Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Charles Zarine * Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary 87 Eaton Place, S.W. 1. SLOane 2564 Monsieur Teodots Ozolips * Counsellor of Legation Ditto. Monsieur Olgerts Rozitis 3rd Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Bronius Balutis* Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary 17 Essex Villas, W. 8. Monsieur Vincas Balickas * Commercial Counsellor, Acting Counsellor of Legation Ditto. Monsieur Petras B. Varkala * Agricultural Attache ... 105 Hillfield Court, Belsize Park, N.W. 3. PRImrose 17972 ENVOYS EXTRAORDINARY AND MINISTERS PLENIPOTENTIARY Iceland Liberia Luxembourg Guatemala Dominican Republic Transjordan Lebanon Austria Finland Ecuador Roumania Hayti ... Republic of the Philippines Switzerland El Salvador Ethiopia Honduras Cuba ... + Monsieur Stefan Thorvardsson. + Baron Robert Aernout de Lynden. + Monsieur Andre Clasen (absent). + General Don Miguel Ydigoras Fuentes. ^ + Sefior Don Andres Pastoriza. + His Highness Amir Abdul Majid Haidar. Monsieur Victor Khouri. Monsieur Heinrich Schmid. * Monsieur Eero Aarne Wuori. + Sefior Don Jorge Carrera Andrade. + Monsieur Mihail Macavei. -i- Monsieur Frederic Duvigneaud. + The Hon. Ramon J. Fernandez (absent). + Monsieur Henry de Torrente. + Senor Dr. Don Carlos Leiva. Ato Abbebe Retta (absent). + Dr. Don Tiburcio Carias, Jr. + Senor Dr. Don Roberto Gonzalez de Mendoza y de la Torre. CHARGE D’AFFAIRES Costa Rica ... ... Senor Dr. Don Guillermo Padilla Castro (absent). CHARGES D’AFFAIRES (ad interim) and ACTING HIGH COMMISSIONERS Spain Afghanistan ... Peru ... Uruguay Bolivia Australia Soviet Union ... United States Embassies and High Commissioners' Offices Duke of San Lucar la Mayor. Monsieur Mohamed Tahir Safi. ... + Senor Don Miguel Grau-Price. Sefior Don Gustavo A. Rey Alvarez. ... + Sefior Don Roberto Querejazu Calvo. ... +Mr. N. Mighell, C.M.G. ... + Monsieur Vladimir Ya. Yerofeev. ... + Mr. Julius C. Holmes. Paraguay Philippines Bulgaria Hungary Ethiopia Luxembourg Panama Syria ... Legations .. + Sefior Dr. Don Luis Maria Ramirez Boettner. .. * Dr. Jose F. Imperial. .. + Monsieur Boyan Athanassov. Monsieur Gabor Pulay. Ato Yohannes Reda-Egzy. .. + Monsieur Georges Heisbourg. Senor Don Manuel Antonio Icaza. Monsieur Rafic Jwejati. 4- Married. * Married, but not accompanied by wife.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with, unless required for official use | List of Permanent and Temporary Officers of His Majesty’s Foreign Service at Consular Posts FEBRUARY 1949 CONSULAR OFFICERS SHOULD IN ALL CASES BE ADDRESSED NOT BY NAME BUT BY OFFICIAL DESIGNATION [ANY CORRECTIONS SHOULD BE NOTIFIED TO THE RECORDS SECTION, PERSONNEL DEPARTMENT]1949 Permanent and Temporary Officers of His Majesty’s Foreign Service at Consular Posts [To avoid delay In communicating with British Consular Officers, they should be addressed not by name but by their official designation, i.e., British Consul-General, Consul, Vice-Consul, or Consular Agent at .] Notes. —(C.O.)—Paid by Colonial Office. (P.) —Personal rank. (L.R.)—Local rank. * Temporary Officers holding the King’s Commission. Temporary Officers of His Majesty’s Foreign Service are shown in italics. CONSULAR POSTS ABROAD Country AND KeSIDENCE Rank Titular Officer Date of Appointment AFGHANISTAN— Jalalabad Consul^) Khan Sahib Abdur Rahman ... April 17, 1944 Kandahar Consul( a ) Khan Bahadur Ziauddin Ahmad June 5, 1942 ALBANIA- ARGENTINE REPUBLIC— Buenos Aires Consul-General Vaughan-Russell, J. F. R. Dec. 10, 1947 Consul Jones, P. S. June 17, 1948 Vice-Consul Kelly, B. ... Feb. 26, 1941 Vice-Consul Dawson, L. J. ... Jan. 1, 1946 Feb. 10, 1943 Pro-Consul ... Spiller, A. G. A Oct. 9, 1948 Bahia Blanca ... Vice-Consul Summerbell, S. L. Mar. 1, 1942 Comodoro Rivadavia... Vice-Consul Charles, W. Oct. 25. 1948 Concordia Vice-Consul (Acting) Tail, J. A. Oct. 11, 1948 La Plata Vice-Consul Puleston, W. W., M.B.E. April 25, 1933 Pro-Consul ... Johnson, 0. Feb. 19, 1945 Mar del Plata Vice-Consul (Acting) Flint, G. A. June , 1947 Mendoza Vice-Consul Walker, R. I. Nov. 9, 1948 Puerto Deseado Vice-Consul Bateman, H. April 21, 1942 Rio Gallegos ... Vice-Consul (Acting) Rae, G. T. Nov. 19, 1946 Rio Grande .(Tierra Vice-Consul Bridges, G. P. April 21, 1942 del Fuego) San Julian Vice-Consul Scott, J. ... Sept. 17, 1948 Santa Cruz Trelew Vice-Consul Vice-Consul (Acting) (Vacant) ... Bideleux, A. F. ... April 1, 1946 Rosario Consul Sedgwick, R. J. P. July 12, 1946 Pro-Consul ... Hibbert, L. J. July 23, 1948 Cordoba Vice-Consul Davis, H. J. Aug. 12, 1941 Santa Vice-Consul Macintosh, J. N. ... Feb. 29, 1940 AUSTRIA— Vienna Consul Baillie, J. Gilroy- Oct. 10, 1947 Vice-Consul (L.R.)( b ) Vice-Consul (Acting) Auger, A. S. Hallett, N. M May 27, 1948 Innsbruck Consul (L.R.) Landale, R. T. , 1949 BELGIUM— Antwerp Consul-General Sebastian, E. G., C.B.E., D.S.O. Nov. 14, 1944 Consul (L.R.) Blood-Smyth, J. V. Mar. 2, 1948 Vice-Consul (L.R.) Niblett, A. E. Dec. 12, 1939 Vice-Consul (L.R.) Overlaet, C. G. (Naturalised B.S.) Dec. 1, 1944 Dec. 1, 1944 Vice-Consul (L.R.) Janssens, A. July 9, 1945 Pro-Consul ... Lees, D. C. Nov. 12, 1947 (a) Maintained by Government of Pakistan ft) Has local rank of Third Secretary 14601—2 364002 Country and Name Designation Residence and Telephone Number AUSTRALIA His Excellency The Right Hon. J. A. Beasley ►£&lt; Mr. N. Mighell. C.M.G Mr. V. C. Dufty, M.V.O High Commissioner Deputy High Commis sioner Acting Official Secretary Australia House, Strand, W.C. 2. T EM pie Bar 1567 Mr. J. D. McAteer Assistant Secretary Mr. C. E. Critchley, M.B.E. ... Mr. J. E. Cummins Senior Trade Commis sioner and Economic Adviser Scientific Adviser Mr. J. B. Todd ... Mr. N. W. Lamidey Assistant Trade Commis sioner Chief Migration Officer Mr. W. H. Coulson Mr. B. R. King ... Supply and Development Adviser Taxation Adviser Mr. C. C. Twelftree Mr. Peter Heydon Mr. Hugh Gilchrist Mr. Brian Hill ... Director, Australian News and Information Bureau External Affairs Officer (Counsellor) Assistant External Affairs Officer 3rd Secretary ... Mr. John Rowland Ditto Mr. H. R. Price ... Customs Representative Mr. J. Bridges ... Trade Publicity Officer... Air Vice-Marshal J. E. Hewitt, C.B.E. Captain (S) P. Perry. O.B.E., R.A.N. ... Joint Service Liaison Officer Naval Liaison Officer ... Canberra House, 85-87 S.W. 1 Jermyn Street, WHItehall 2\Q[ Commander V. A. Smith, D.S.C., R.A.N. Brigadier E. W. Woodward, D.S.O. ... Colonel B. B. Watchorn, O.B.E., M.C. Air Commodore E. G. Knox-Knight, O.B.E. Assistant Naval Liaison Officer Australian Army Repre sentative Deputy Australian Army Representative Air Officer Command ing Overseas H.Q., R.A.A.F., London AUSTRIA His Excellency Monsieur Schmid Dr. Walter Wodak Heinrich * Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipoten tiary 1st Secretary 27 Pembroke Gardens, W. 8. WEStern 4614 [Offices of the Legation: 1 Hyde Park Gate, S.W. 7. ^ WEStern 0297-9] 40 De Vere Gardens, W. 8. WEStern 5506 Dr. Albert Filz* 2nd Secretary 21 Campden Grove, W. 8. WEStern 5278 Dr. Heinz Laube * 3rd Secretary ... 5 Bina Gardens, S.W. 5. FREmantle 3902 BELGIUM - His Excellency Vicomte Thieusies Monsieur Gerard Walravens Obert de * * Ambassador Extra ordinary and Plenipo tentiary Counsellor of Embassy 36 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. SLOane 1752 [Offices of the Embassy: 103 Eaton Square, S.W. 1. SLOane 921\/2] 82 Eaton Place, S.W. 1. SLOane 8857 Monsieur Amaury Holvoet * 1 st Secretary 55 Eaton Place, S.W. 1. SLOane 78666 Country and Name /■ Designation Residence and Telephone Number CHILE (continued) Senor Don Leon Subercaseaux * Minister-Counsellor Flat 29, Hereford House, W. 1. MAY fair 5148 Senorita Juanita Subercaseaux (Daughter) Senor Don Humberto Videla ... * Minister-Counsellor Flat 7, 24 Lowndes Street, S.W. 1. M^Oane 9724 Senorita Mercedes Videla (Daughter) Senor Don Pedro Enrique Alfonso * Commercial Counsellor Villa d’Arno, 5 Albany Park Road, Kingston-on-Thames. Senor Don Horacio Suarez 1 st Secretary Flat 45, 60 Park Lane, W. 1. GROsvenor 2897 Senor Don Hefren Silva Secretary 6 Bourdon Street, W. 1. MAYfair 591% Commander Kaare Olsen Naval Attache 3 Southwick Street, W. 2, PADdington 6868 Squadron Leader Anibal Solminhiac * Air Attache Flat 5, Audley House, 9 North Audley Street, W. 1. Senor Don Gonzalo Mera * 3rd Secretary 24 Matlock Court, Netting Hill Gate, W. 11. PARk 4611 Senor Don Jose Antonio Gandarillas* Secretary 14 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, S.W. 3. FLAxman 3695 Senorita Carmen Gandarillas (Daughter) Senor Don Calixto Rogers * Attache 44 Mitcham Lane, S.W. 16. STReatham 8544 CHINA His Excellency Dr. Cheng Tien-Hsi * Ambassador Extra ordinary and Plenipo tentiary (Daughter) 49 Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 5794 Miss Cheng Ying-Wan Dr. Tuan Mao-Lan f -4 Minister-Counsellor 10 Lansdowne Road, W. 11. PARk 6265 Dr. Seymour C. Y. Cheng Counsellor 49 Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Tan Pao-shen Counsellor, 1st Secretary Flat 161, Rivermead Court, S.W. 6. RENown 2696 Miss Tan Sien Fen (Daughter) Mr. Chen Yao-sheng * 1 st Secretary 32 Maxwell Road, Northwood, Middlesex. Northwood 2134 Mr. Lee Yone-Ming * Ditto Heathside Cottage, 8 Heathside Close, Northwood, Middlesex. Northwood 590 Mr. Ho Sze-ko Ditto 49 Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Wang Ting-Shan * 2nd Secretary Ditto. Mr. Kuan Chuan-Tsai ... 3rd Secretary ... Ditto. Mr. Lin Chih-chi * Ditto 32 Maxwell Road, Northwood, Middlesex. Northwood 2134 Mr. Lee En-Kuo 3rd Secretary and Attache to the Em bassy Ditto ... 49 Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Kwoh Tseh-ching ►F 103c Greencroft Gardens, N.W. 6. MAI da Vale 3305 Mr. Chao Chin-Yung ... * 3rd Secretary “ Collingwood,” Joel Street, Pinner, Middle sex. PINner 3617 Mr. Wan Moo Chou ... N ... Attache ... 49 Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 519A Mr. Wang Shih-Yong T&lt; Ditto 36 Goldhurst Terrace, N.W. 6. Mr. Liu Ying-Tsun Ditto ... 49 Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 5194 Mr. Tai Erh-ching * Ditto ... Ditto. Mr. Lai Tien-Chang Ditto Ditto. Mr. Johnson Cheng * Ditto Ditto.12 Country and Name Designation Residence and Telephone Number HAYTI His Excellency Monsieur Frederic Duvigneaud Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary (Daughter) 41 Cadogan Gardens, S.W. 3. SLOane 4739 Mile. Gisele Duvigneaud ... Mile. Denise Duvigneaud ... Ditto mp Monsieur Jean Duvigneaud 1st Secretary 41 Berkeley Square, W. 1. HONDURAS His Excellency Dr. Don Tiburcio Carias, Jr. Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary HUNGARY His Excellency Monsieur Janos Eros ^ Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary 35 Eaton Place, S.W. 1. SLOane 7191 [Office: 46 Eaton Place, S.W. 1. SLOane 4048] Monsieur Gabor Pulay Counsellor 8 Clarendon Street, S.W. 1. Monsieur Pal Sebestyen 2nd Secretary 9 Lowndes Close, S.W. 1. SLOane 4048 Monsieur Laszlo Ujhazy Monsieur Pal Ignotus Commercial Attache ... Press Attache ... 63 Warwick Square, S.W. 1. Victoria 1956 [Office: 35 b Eaton Place, S.W. 1. SLOane 6842] 625 Chelsea Cloisters, S.W. 3. KENsington 3968 ICELAND His Excellency Monsieur Stefan Thorvardsson Monsieur Petur Eggerz ... ... ^ Monsieur Eirikur Benedikz ... ^ Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary 1st Secretary 2nd Secretary Oatland Park Hotel, Weybridge, Surrey. [Offices of the Legation: 17 Buckingham Gate, S.W. 1. Victoria 5551-%} 12 Onslow Gardens, Sanderstead, Surrey. Sanderstead 2788 Home Farm, Bampton, Oxon. INDIA His Excellency Mr. V. K. Krishna Menon Mr. A. K. Chanda, O.B.E Captain (S) C. Srinivasan, R.I.N. Mr. Prithi Singh High Commissioner Deputy High Commis sioner Principal Private Secre tary and Political Liaison Officer Private Secretary India House, Aldwych, W.C. 2. T EM pie Bar 8484 Sir Dhiren Mitra, C.B.E. • Legal Adviser Mr. M. J. Desai, C.I.E., I.C.S. Commercial Adviser ... Mr. A. S. Lall, M.B.E., I.C.S. Financial Adviser Lieutenant-Colonel C. L. Pasricha Medical Adviser Brigadier M. S. Wadalia Military Adviser Commander B. A. Samson, R.I.N. Naval Adviser ... Group Captain Shiv Dev Singh, R.I.A.F. Air Adviser Mr. A. S. Lall, M.B.E., I.C.S India Trade Commis sionerCountry and Name Designation Residence and Telephone Number PORTUGAL (continued) Commander Jose Conceiyao da Rocha, O.B.E. * Lieutenant-Colonel Luiz Maria de Camara Pina, O.B.E. Sen hoj^ Jose Manuel dc Magalhaes PesfTl e Fragoso Senhor Antonio Potier ^ Naval Attache Military Attache 3rd Secretary Ditto ... 32 Walton Street, S.W. 3. KENsington 7837 20 Draycott Avenue, S.W. 3. KENsington 8785 11 Belgravc Square, S.W. 1. SLOane 6444 103 Sloane Street, S.W. 1. SLOancW)95 Senhor Luiz Leotte do Rego ... * Commercial Attache ... Ditto. Senhor Joao Antas de Campos * Ditto 17a Carlton Road, W. 5. ROUMANIA His Excellency Monsieur Mihail Macavei ^ Monsieur George Macovescu ... ^ Monsieur Eugen Balas ... ^ Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary 1st Counsellor of Lega tion Counsellor 1 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. KENsington 4836 Ditto. 1 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. Monsieur Paul Cornea Press Counsellor 71 Knightsbridge, S.W. 1. Monsieur Eugen Mantu * 2nd Secretary 26 Cadogan Square, S.W. 1. Monsieur Jacques Berman * Commercial Counsellor 1 Culford Gardens, S.W. 3. Monsieur Jacob Magura * Commercial Secretary Ditto. Mme. Elisabeta Cornea Commercial Secretary ... 71 Knightsbridge, S.W. 1. SAUDI ARABIA His Excellency Sheikh Hafiz Wahba, K.C.V.O.* Monsieur Shaher A1 Samman ... ^ Ambassador Extra ordinary and Plenipo tentiary Counsellor 30 Belgrave Square, S.W. 1. SLOane 3898 Ditto. Monsieur Ahmed Safei El Din * 2nd Secretary Ditto. Monsieur Abdel Rehman Helaissi Ditto Ditto. Monsieur Fuad A. Nazir * 3rd Secretary Ditto. Monsieur Abdulgani Ydlibi Monsieur Mohammed Mahdi Muslih Hon. Commercial At tache Attache ... Ditto. Ditto. SIAM His Serene Highness Prince Nakkhatra Ambassador Extra 23 Ashburn Place, S.W. 7. FRObisher 2983 Mangala Kitiyakara * ordinary and Plenipo tentiary Luang Phinit Akson * Counsellor Ditto. Luang Chamnong Dithakar 2nd Secretary ... Ditto. Nai Sawet Tantraporn * Ditto ... Ditto. Nai Klin Dcvahastin * Ditto Ditto. Nai Pun Chongprasoet* 3rd Secretary Ditto. Nai Sophon Chuenchum * Ditto ... Ditto. Nai Thiem Ladanon* Attache Ditto.Country and Name SIAM (continued) Designation Residence and Telephone Number Colonel M. C. Jitkjanok Kritakara * Military and Air Attache 23 Ashburn Place, S.W. 7. FRObisher 2983 Captain Ananta Pibulsonggram * Assistant Military At tache Ditto. Captain Swai Sribhadung, R.S.N. * Naval Attache Ditto. _ SOVIET UNION His Excellency Monsieur Georgi Ambassador Extra “Harrington House,” 13 Kensington Palace Nikolaevich Zaroubin * ordinary and Plenipo tentiary Gardens, W. 8. BA Yswater 3628 Monsieur Georgi Saksin* Counsellor 16 Lancaster Lodge, Lancaster Road, W. 11. Monsieur Vladimir N. Pavlov ... * Ditto 10 Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8. Monsieur Nikolai B. Korovin ... * Ditto 5 Leinster Square, W. 2. Monsieur Josif Baikov * 1 st Secretary 22 Lansdowne Crescent, W. 11. Monsieur Vladimir N. Kramelashvili 2nd Secretary ... 18 Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8. Monsieur luri D. Milovzorov ... * Ditto 3 Rosary Gardens, S.W. 7. FREmantle 1815 Monsieur Vladimir A. Legeev ... * Ditto 84 Ladbroke Road, W. 11. Monsieur Mikhail Shishkin * Ditto 21 Ladbroke Square, W. 11. Monsieur Alexandre Fomine ... * Ditto 5 Kenilworth Court, Putney. PUTney2129 Monsieur Vladimir Naboichenko * Ditto 13 Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8. Monsieur Sergei Goussarov * 3rd Secretary ... 18 Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8. Monsieur Nikolai Mescheriakov Ditto 13 Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8. Colonel Iakov P. Gorshkov * Acting Military and Air Attache 5 Addison Road, W. 14. [Office: 16 Kensington Palace Gardens] Colonel Victor M. Poudov * Assistant Military tache At- 26 The Boltons, S.W. 10. Lieutenant-Colonel Timolei Samarin * Assistant Military tache for Air At- Flat 2, 9 Palace Court, W. 2. Lieutenant-Colonel Sergei A. Edemsky * Assistant Military tache At- 20 Ladbroke Gardens, W. 11. Lieutenant-Colonel Alexandre Plekha- nov ^ Ditto 42 Peter’s Court, Porchester Road, W. 2. Captain Alexandre Ilichev * Ditto 26 The Boltons, S.W. 10. Commodore Vassili D. Iakovlev, C.B.E. Naval Attache ... 89 Addison Road, W. 14. Lieutenant-Colonel Georgi Gladys * Ditto 19 Basset Road, W. 10. Captain 2nd Rank Ivan I. Agafonov * Assistant Naval Attache 19a The Lodge, Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 11. PARk 5900 Monsieur Mikhail Svirin * Attache ... 9 Clarendon Road, W. 11. Monsieur Georgi Sinitsin * Ditto 22 Lansdowne Crescent, W. 11. Monsieur Venidict Cherkasski ... * Ditto 32 West Hill, Highgate, N. 6. MOUntview 1907 Monsieur Alexander I. Romanov * Ditto 51 Linden Gardens, W. 2. Monsieur Anatolin Gorshenev ... * Ditto 11 Orme Court, Bayswater, W. 2. BA Yswater 3588 Monsieur Valentin Zouev * Ditto 13 Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8. Monsieur Alexandre Malikov ... * Ditto Ditto. Monsieur Mikhail Borinskih ... * Ditto 3 Rosary Gardens, S.W. 7. Monsieur Sergei Voronin * Ditto 13 Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8.26 Country and Name Designation UNITED STATES (continued) Mr. William C. Buell * Attache Mr. Sargent B. Child * Ditto Mr. Ernest A. Lister * Civil Air Attache Mr. Leo F. Gentner * Attache Mr. John E. P. Grant ... * Ditto Mr. William H. J. McIntyre * Ditto Mr. Peter Abeille * Ditto Mr. Findley Weaver * Ditto Mr. J. David Linebaugh * Ditto Mr. Richard P. Taylor ... * Ditto Mr. Barrett Parker Ditto Mr. Carl Ginsburg * Ditto Mr. William B. Hussey * Ditto Mr. John J. Coyle * Ditto Mr. Paul Felix Warburg Ditto Mr. Joseph Polakoff * Assistant Attache Mr. Conrad J. Thoren ... Ditto Mr. Felix S. Verity Ditto Mr. John A. Cimperman Legal Attache ... Mr. Sidney J. Kennedy * Treasury Attache Mr. Norman R. Hagen * Attache Mr. Winston M. Scott * Ditto Dr. Arthur S. Osborne * Ditto Mr. Glenn D. Fields * Ditto Residence and Telephone Number Flat 1, 15 Chelsea Embankment, S.W. 3. FLA xman 7168 51 Murray Road, Wimbledon, S.W. 19. Flat 139, Dorset House, Gloucester Place, N.W. 1. \^Lbeck 5522 Connaught Hotel, Carlos Place, W. 1. GROsvenor 2211 28 Hertford Street, W. 1. GROsvenor 4291 Flat 36, St. James’s Close, Prince Albert Road, N.W.8. PRImrose 6888 47 Romney Court, Shepherd’s Bush Green, W.12. SHEpherds Bush 3237 16 Winnington Road, N. 2. MEAdway 2120 9 Carlyle Close, Hampstead Garden Suburb, N.W. 11. MEADway 2982 3 Roedean Crescent, Roehampton, S.W. 15. PRO sped 3130 7 Spanish Place Mansions, Manchester Square, W. 1. WELbeck2\2\ 21 Knightsbridge Court, Sloane Street, S.W. 1. SLOane 8783 “ Oueme,” Stubbings, near Maidenhead. Berks. Little Wick Green 79 907 Howard House, Dolphin Street, S.W. 1. Victoria 3800, Ext. Howard 907 10 Wood’s Mews, Park Lane, W. 1. MAY fair 1213 Flat 71, Park West, Edgware Road, W. 2. PADdington 1280, Ext. 71 Winfield House, Regent’s Park, N.W. 1. Winfield House, Outer Circle, Regent’s Park, N.W. 1. A MBassador 5 192 4 Dudley Court, Upper Berkeley Street, W. 1. PA Ddington 0192 5a Duke Street, W. 1. WELbeck 3245 Park Lane Hotel, Piccadilly, W. 1. GROsvenor 6321 33 Swan Court, Chelsea, S.W. 3. FLAxman 2353 Stiver’s Corner, Coke’s Lane, Chalfont St. Giles, Bucks. Little Chalfont 2\11 702 Drake House, Dolphin Square, S.W. 1. Victoria 3800, Ext. 702 Special Mission for Economic Co-operation Mr. Henry Siegbert Dr. John Cassels* Mr. Elmer N. Holmgreen Miss Shirley Anne Holmgreen Mr. Alfred D. Lindley* Mr. Tremper Longman Mr. Richard S. McCaffery Mr. Abbot Low Moffat Miss Nancy Moffat Miss Jane Kerin Moffat ... * * Deputy Chief of Mission Economic Commissioner Ditto (Daughter) Economic Commissioner Ditto ... Ditto ... Ditto (Daughter) Ditto * Married, but not accompanied by wife. * Dorchester Hotel, W. 1. MA Yfair 8888 Flat 11, Harrowby Court, Seymour Place, W. 1. PA Ddington 9176 Collet Court, 126 Sloane Street, S.W. 1. SLOane 7578 15 Montpelier Square, S.W. 7. KENsington 9515 39 Orchard Court, Portman Square, W. 1. WELbeck 5446 2 Mount Street, W. 1. 10 Green Street, W. 1. MA Yfair 2824 MA Yfair 614428 Country and Name Designation Residence and Telephone Number YUGOSLAVIA (continued) Lieutenant-Colonel Vangel Cukalevski * Lieutenant-Colonel Mate Jurcic ►£&lt; Major Rade Trost Monsieur Avram Adanja ... ^ Monsieur Branko Japundzic ... ^ Monsieur Jovan Jovasevic Mme. Desanka Bilic Military, Air and Naval Attache Assistant Military At tache Assistant Military, Naval and Air Attache Assistant Commercial Attache Ditto 25 Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400 [Office: 195 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 5439 and 3400] 1 a Palace Gate, W. 8. 25 Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. Ditto. Financial Attache ... Ditto. Attache Ditto. [Office: 195 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400] LIST OF PERSONS NO LONGER INCLUDED IN THE FOREGOING LIST BUT STILL ACCEPTED BY HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT AS PERSONALLY POSSESSING DIPLOMATIC PRIVILEGES Name Rank Residence and Telephone Number His Excellency Monsieur August Torma ^ Monsieur Ernst Sarepera* His Excellency Monsieur Charles Zarine ^ Monsieur Teodots Ozolips ... ... Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary Counsellor of Legation, 1st Secretary Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary Counsellor of Legation 167 Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 5473 and 5474 Ditto. 87 Eaton Place, S.W. 1. SLOane25bA Ditto. Monsieur Olgerts Rozitis ... ... ... 3rd Secretary ... ... Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Bronius Balutis* ... Monsieur Vincas Balickas ^ Monsieur Petras B. Varkala ... ^ Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo tentiary Commercial Counsellor, Acting Counsellor of Legation Agricultural Attache ... 17 Essex Villas, W. 8. Ditto. 105 Hillfield Court, Belsize Park, N.W. 3. PRlmrose 1797LIST OF THE PERMANENT AND TEMPORARY STAFFS OF HIS MAJESTY’S EMBASSIES, LEGATIONS AND POLITICAL MISSIONS ABROAD LIST 1 : SENIOR OFFICERS 15th JANUARY, 1949 [NOTE.—Any corrections should be addressed to Records Section, Personnel Department] 14148—3 36328List of the Permanent and Temporary Staffs of His Majesty’s Embassies, Legations and Political Missions Abroad List 1: Senior Officers Country. January 1949 Name. Designation. AFGHAN ISTAN Sir Giles Squire, K.B.E., C.I.E. ... Mr. D. M. H. Riches Mr. P. J. Keen Ambassador. First Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. A. J. Evans, M.B.E. ... ... Second Secretary. Lieutenant-Colonel J. H. Prendergast, Military Attache. D.S.O., M.C. ARGENTINE Sir John Balfour, K.C.M.G. REPUBLIC Mr. G. P. Labouchere Mr. A. H. Lincoln ... Mr. L. M. Minford Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Ditto. Chancery. Mr. J. G. Lomax, C.M.G., M.B.E., M.C. Mr. W. G. R. Howell, O.B.E Mr. A. C. Maby ... Mr. I. F. S. Vincent, M.B.E. Mr. J. F. R. Vaughan-Russell ... Mr. P. G. H. Dorchy, M.B.E. ... Mr. E. E. Young ... I Mr. W. H. Bremner, D.S.O., D.S.C. ... Captain D. E. Holland-Martin, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Brigadier R. G. Fullerton Air Commodore H. E. Walker, M.C., D.F.C. Mr. R. H. Haven-Dyke, M.B.E. Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. Mr. E. J. Toogood ... Major T. A. Rattray Mr. P. A. Miller Minister (Commercial). Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Ditto. Counsellor and Consul-General. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). First-Secretary, Visa Officer. Naval Attach^. Military Attache. Air Attachd. Assistant Air Attache. Civil Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Agricultural Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Civil Attache. AUSTRIA ... Sir Bertrand Jerram, K.C.M.G. Mr. N. J. A. Cheetham ... Mr. J. E. Galsworthy Mr. R. J. Blair Mr. P. M. Foster ... Mr. S. E. H. Daw ... Mr. A. E. Cox Mr. R. J. R. Trefusis Mr. F. S. Fielding ... Mr. J. G. Baillie ... Mr. R. A. Long Mr. G. M. Young ... Mr. G. Berry Mr. A. S. Auger Captain J. Bell-Irving Mr. A. Bennett Minister. Counsellor. Second Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial) (local rank). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Ditto. First Secretary and Consul. Administration Officer, Second Secre tary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (local rank), Head of Visa Section. Third Secretary (local rank). Military Liaison Officer. Labour Attache.3 3632b c Country. Name. Designation. BELGIUM Sir George Kendel, K.C.M.G. Mr. W. H. Moatagu-Pollock, C.M.G. ... Mr. P. F. Hancock Mr. T. IP D. Belgrave ... Mr. D. W. Hough ... Mr. J. Morley Mr. E. J. Joint, C.M.G., O.B.E. ... Mr. A. Duncan Mr. W. C. R. Aue Mr. S. A. Lockhart, O.B.E. Mr. E. J. W. S. Foote Commander E. Neville, K.N. Colonel D. P. Fabin, M.B.E Group Captain J. Grandy, D.S.O. Air Marshal D. Colyer, C.B., D.F.C. ... Mr. C. F. Heron ... Mr. C. S. Collinson, O.B.E. Mr. I. W. Dollar Mr. C. J. T. Spearman Mr. G. W. Ethall Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Ditto. Third Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Consul, First Secretary. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Military Attachd. Air Attache. Civil Air Attache. Labour Attach^. First Secretary (local rank) (Visa Sec tion). Third Secretary (local rank) (Visa Sec tion). Administrative Officer, Third Secretary (local rank). Food Attachd. BOLIVIA Mr. T. Ifor Bees, C.M.G. Mr. H. Osborne Mr. D. F. Muirhead Group Captain H. M. Pearson, C.B.E. ... Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. ... Mr. W. E. Oakley-Evans ... Mr. K. A. Murdoch Ambassador. First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Air Attache. Civil Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Civil Attache. BRAZIL Sir Nevile Butler, K.C.M.G., C.V.O. . Mr. G. P. Young ... Mr. R. A. Burroughs Mr. A. H. W. King, C.B.E Mr. W. A. T. Sowden, M.B.E Mr. J. A. Burns, O.B.E. ... Mr. L. P. Bridal Mr. R. J. Stratton Mr. G. M. F. Stow Mr. N. D. T. Sutton Mr. D. McEwen ... Captain B. J. Fisher, D.S.O., R.N. Brigadier J. C. O’Dwyer Group Captain D. W. Bayne Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. .. Mr. L. Mitchell Ambassador. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Minister (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Ditto. Third Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). Naval Attach^. Military Attache. Air Attach^. Civil Air Attach^. Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank).Name. 4 Designation. Country. BULGARIA BURMA CHILE CHINA Mr. P. Mason, C.M.G. (designate) Mr. D. A. Greenhill, O.B.E. Mr. R. O. A. Gatehouse ... Mr. D. I. Dunnett Mr. S. P. House Mr. K. W. Lee Mr. H. N. Walmsley Mr. J. D. Blakeway Commander J. W. E. D. Cowgill, R.N. ... Colonel G. G. Green, D.S.O. Major B. G. Merrivale-Austin ... Wing Commander A. R. Collins ... Mr. R. J. Bowker, C.M.G. Mr. G. E. Crombie Mr. G. H. Baker ... Mr. E. F. James, O.B.E. Mr. E. Morgan Mr. C. C. Clemens, M.C. ... Mr. L. C. Glass Mr. W. K. Smith ... Mr. F. A. G. Cook, O.B.E. Mr. A. W. R. Taylor Mr. H. Kay Mr. H. Reith Mr. A. Brandon Mr. H. W. Speck, M.B.E. Mr. J. H. Leche, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. G. L. McDermott Mr. C. D. Wiggin, D.F.C., A.F.C. Mr. J. Currie Mr. S. J. Lovell Air. D. R. Roper (designate) Mr. D. R. Dick, O.B.E Mr. R. H. Edmondson Captain J. J. Weld, R.N. Commander F. V. Vaughan, R.N.V.R (Retd.) Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C.... Air. W. E. Oakley-Evans ... Air. W. J. McLaughlin Sir Ralph C. Skrine Stevenson, G.C AI G Mr. L. H. Lamb. C.Af.G., O.B.E. Air. J. Af. Addis ... Mr. R. A. Sykes, M.C Mr. J. K. Drinkall Air. J. P. Coghill ... Air. H. D. Bryan ... Mr E. Youde Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancer' Second Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary. First Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial) (lo&lt;^ rank). Vice-Consul, Third Secretary. Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attach^. Military Attach^. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attachb. Ambassador. Counsellor (local rank). First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Ditto. Third Secretary. Oriental Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). Counsellor and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (loca'i rank). Administrative and Accounts Officer (Information). Administrative Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). Ambassador. First Secretary and Consul. Third Secretary. First Secretary (Commercial). Market Officer, Third Secretary (Com mercial) (local rank). Commercial Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attach^ Hon. Assistant Naval Attach^. Civil Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). Ambassador. , Alinister. hirst Secretary and Head of Chancerv. Second Secretary. Third Secretary. Counsellor (Chinese Secretariat). First Secretary (Chinese Secretariat;. Third Secretary (Chinese Secretariat)5 (5=) Country. Name. Designation. CHINA Mr. J. C. Hutchison, C.B.E. Minister (Commercial). (continued) Mr. I. C. Mackenzie First Secretary (Commercial). Mr. H. H. Thomas Counsellor (Financial). Mr. P. A. North ... Consul, First Secretary (local rank). ** Vice-Consul, Third Secretary (local rank). Mr. D. MacFarlane First Secretary (Information). Mr. R. F. J. Harris First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Mr. R. L. Wood Administration Officer and Accountant (Information). Mr. S. Knowles Editor (Information). Mr. H. McAleavy ... Chinese Adviser (Information). Captain V. d’Arcy Donaldson Naval Attach^. Brigadier L. F. Field, C.B.E. ... Military and Air Attach^. Lieutenant-Colonel K. E. F. Millar, Assistant Military Attachd (Shanghai). M.B.E. — Lieutenant-Colonel G. P. Fawcett Assistant Military Attachd. Major C. M. D’Arcy Irvine, M.B.E. Assistant Military Attach^ (Peking). Wing Commander C. W. K. Nicholls, O.B.E., D.S.O. Assistant Air Attache. Squadron Leader P. I. Howard-Williams, D.F.C. Assistant Air Attach^ (Shanghai). Mr. E. M. Hunt ... Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). Miss E. M. Hinder Attache. Mr. W. G. E. Beckmann Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). COLOMBIA ... , Mr. G. MacKereth, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. G. H. S. Jackson Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Mr. L. A. Scopes, O.B.E. Mr. A. M. Turner ... First Secretary (Commercial) and Consul. Second Secretary (Commercial). Mr. L. Boas Mr. F. J. Allsopp ... First Secretary (Information) rank). Assistant Information Officer. (local Captain W. G. Brittain, C.B.E., R.N. .. Group Captain A. P. Bett Mr. C. A. Bryer ... ... ... &gt;. Mr. G. 0. McEntee Naval Attache. Air Attach^. Labour Attach^, First Secretary rank). . Market Officer. (local COSTA RICA Mr. B. P. Sullivan, M.B.E Minister. Mr. C. C. Whitaker Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Naval Attach^ and Naval Air Attach^. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attach^. Air Attache. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). CUBA Mr. A. Holman, C.M.G., M.C. (designate) Mr. T. Brimelow ... Mr. R. P. Pinsent ... Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery, First Secretary (Commercial) anc] Consul. First Secretary. Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. ... Naval Attache. 363286 Country. Name. Designation. CUBA (continued). CZECHO SLOVAKIA DENMARK DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., Air Attach^ D.E.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson ... ... ... Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Mr. P. J. Dixon, C.B., C.M.G Sir Anthony Rumbold, Bart. Mr. C. A. Thompson Mr. K. Unwin, O.B.E Mr. A. G. Spinks ... Mr. A. R. C. Bolton Mr. R. A. F. Wallis Mr. L. L. Noquet ... Mr. W. L. Wakefield Commander (E) E. A. Read, R.N. Lieut.-Colonel F. A. A. Blake, O.B.E. .. Captain G. D. M. C. Wheeler Wing Commander G. F. A. Skelton Mr. P. T. G. Carlyon Mr. W. H. Taylor Mr. A. W. G. Randall, K.C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. H. Beeley, C.B.E. (designate) Mr. F. J. Leishman, M.B.E. Mr. C. L. G. Phillpots Mr. S. Simmonds, O.B.E. Mr. L. E. Tudor ... Mr. J. L. Murray ... Mr. D. Wyndham Harris Mr. L. Mitchell Commander (local Captain) R. S. Christian-Ed wards Commander (E) H. G. R. Binning Lieut.-Colonel J. H. Mallard Group Captain W. R. Sadler Colonel N. Craig. D.S.O., O.B.E. Mr. R. Metcalfe ... Mr. R. Ede Mr. W. W. Wilson Reverend T. H. Croxall ... Mr. R. E. Bishop, M.B.E. Mr. S. H. Gudgeon, C.B.E. Mr. H. R. Hambleton, M.B.E., M.C. ... Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. Counsellor ‘(Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Liaison Editor. Consul, in charge Consular Section, Second Secretary. Attache for Naval Questions. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attache. Social Secretary. Administration Officer. Ambassador. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Third Secretary (local rank). Counsellor (Commercial) and Consul- General. Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Head of Visa Section, Second Secretary (local rank). Naval Attachd. Assistant Naval Attache (Technical). Military Attache. Air Attache. Honorary Attache. Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). Agricultural Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Market Officer. Chaplain. Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul.7 5 ^ Country. Name. Designation DOMINICAN Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. REPUBLIC Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., (continued). D.E.C. Naval Attache. Air Attache. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). ECUADOR Mr. J. E. M. Carvell ... ... Mr. A. H. B. Hermann ... Mr. J. Robertson, M.B.E. Captain W. G. Brittain, C.B.E., R.N. ... Group Captain A. P. Bett Mr. C. A. Bryer ... Minister. First Secretary and Consul (Head of Chancery). Vice-Consul and Second Secretary. Naval Attache. Air Attache. Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). EGYPT (Embassy) Sir Ronald Campbell, G.C.M.G., C.B. ... Mr. E. A. Chapman-Andrews, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. D. D. Maclean Mr. A. L. Mayall ... Mr. R. H. G. Edmonds, M.B.E. Mr. J. G. Tomlinson Mr. M. W. V. Maude Mr. G. T. S. Hinton Mr. G. M. F. Alston Mr. T. C. Ravensdale Mr. C. F. R. Barclay Mr. W. Morris Mr. W. J. Johnson, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. A. N. Cumberbatch, C.B.E. Mr. W. S. Laver ... Mr. E. B. Dunipace Mr. P. Gent Mr. J. B. Flux, M.B.E Mr. A. H. King Mr. E. P. Wiltshire Mr. M. Henderson ... Mr. A. A. F. Haigh Mr. R. W. Parkes, O.B.E Mr. E. Main, M.B.E Mr. R. Tristram, O.B.E. Mrs. E. B. Ratz Mr. P. E. L. Fellowes Brigadier R. N. Thicknesse Major A. T. Fisher Air Commodore G. W. Hayes, O.B.E. ... Flight Lieutenant D. A. Stevenson Dr. E. D. Pridie, C.M.G., D.S.O., O.B.E Mr. A. McDougall ... Mr. M. T. Audsley, C.M.G Wing Commander C. J. Lewin ... Mr. H. W. Gunningham, O.B.E. Ambassador. Minister. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank), Private Secretary to Ambassador. Second Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary (local rank). Oriental Counsellor. Second Secretary and Assistant Oriental Secretary. Ditto. Counsellor (Financial). Minister (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Ditto. Ditto- Counsellor and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul. First Secretary (local rank) and Head of Visa Section. Counsellor (Information). First Secretary (Information). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information). Press Officer. Social Reform Officer. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attache. Assistant Air Attach^. Health Adviser, Counsellor (local rank). Legal Adviser, Counsellor (local rank). Labour Attach^. Counsellor (local rank). Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Administrative Officer, First Secretary. - D* 368288 Country. BRITISH M1DBLL EAST OFFICE ETHIOPIA FINLAND FRANCE (Embassy) Name. Sir John Troutbeck, K.C.M.G. ... Mr. J. W. Wall Mr. A. G. Maitland Mr. A. J. Wilton Mr. W. F Crawford, O.B.E. Dr. E. D. Pridie, C.M.G., D.S.O., O.B.E. Mr. M. T. Audsley, C.M.G. Sir Herbert Stewart, C.I.E. Dr. J. Murray Mr. V. K. Maitland, C.S.I., M.C. Mr. A. R. Waterston, F.R.S.E. ... Mr. E. W. Noonan Mr. L. Waight Mr. G. Wilson Mr. D. W. Lascelles, C.M.G. Mr. W. B. C. Weld-Forester Mr. J. A. F. Gethin Mr. A. T. Curie, D.S.O., M.B.E. ... Mr. S. N. Sedcole ... Wing Commander C. J. Lewin ... Mr. 0. A. Scott, C.M.G., D.S.O. ... Mr. H. A. F. Hohler Mr. R. Bosley Mr. R. F. Muston Mr. W. J. S. Laing Mr. F. 0. A. H. Finney, M.B.E. Mr. L. L. Atkinson, M.B.E. Mr. R. W. Cole Mr. J. 1. McGhie (designate) Mr. J. Brooke Colonel J. H. Magill Wing Commander D. H. Fleet, M.B.E. Mr. C. L. Thomas Sir Oliver Harvey, G.C.M.G., C.B. Mr. H. Ashley Clarke, C.M.G. ... Viscount Hood Mr. G. E. Millard ... Mr. F. G. K. Gallagher ... Mr. R. C. Hope-Jones Mr. P. W. Mathews Mr. H. B. McKenzie Johnston ... Mr. J. E. Jackson Miss B. M. Alison Mr. C. H. Bourke Borrowes Viscount Duncannon Mr. A. R. Fraser, K.B.E., C.M.G. Mr. L. G. Holliday Designation. Head of Office. Head of Political Section. First Secretary. Third Secretary. Counsellor (local rank), Head of Develop ment Division. Health Adviser. ® Labour Adviser. Agricultural Adviser. Statistical Adviser. Adviser in Soil Conservation and Forestry. Entomological Adviser. Petroleum Adviser. Financial Adviser. Temporary Administrative Assistant. Minister. hirst Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. First Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Second Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul. Civil Air Attach^. Minister. I irst Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Assistant Commercial Secretary (local rank). Secretary (local rank), Visa Officer. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rankb Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Labour. Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Ambassador. Minister. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Ditto. Ditto. Third Secretary. Ditto- Ditto (local rank). Third Secretary (local rank). Private Secretary to Ambassador, Secre tary (local rank). Minister (Commercial). Counsellor (Commercial).36328 d* 2 Country. Name. Designation. FRANCE Mr. W. I. Combs First Secretary (Commercial). (continued). Second Secretary (Commercial). Mr. N. G. Beckett Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Mr. J. F. C. King Ditto. ^ ' Mr. R. H. Tottenham-Smith, C.B.E. ... Minister in Charge of the Consular Section. Mr. P. I. Lake, M.C. (designate) Second Secretary and Consul (local rank). Mr. H. J. Dorey, M.B.E Third Secretary (local rank) and Vice Consul. Mr. A. L. C. Paton P.C.O. First Secretary (local rank). Mr. C. de Salis, M.B.E Assistant P.C.O. Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. P. F. D. Tennant, O.B.E. ... Counsellor (Information). Mr. U. 0. V. Verney Assistant Information Officer, First Secretary (local rank). Mrs. H. de Vivenot Assistant Documentations Officer (In formation Deijartment). Mr. W. E. Curteis ... Press Relations (Information), Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. R. J. T. Griffin Broadcasting Officer (Information), Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. C. A. Whitney-Smith ... Provincial Posts Officer (Information), Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. C. P. Hope ... Administrative Officer, First Secretary (local rank). Captain C. D. Howard-Johnston, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Cdr. (E) E. A. Read, R.N.' .' Ditto. Cdr. J. de F. Jago, R.N. ... Assistant Naval Attache (Air). Major-Gen. A. G. Salisbury-Jones, C.B.E., M.C. Military Attache. Colonel B. A. Pearson, D.S.O. ... Assistant Military Attach^. Major B. W. Pain Ditto. Captain W. R. L. Turp ... Ditto. Air Vice-Marshal R. A. George, C.B.E., M.C. Air Attache. Wing Commander W. G. Moseby, D.S.O., D.F.C. Assistant Air Attache. Wing-Cdr. P. J. F. Stephenson, D.F.C. ... Ditto. Air Marshal D. Colyer, C.B., D.F.C. ... Civil Air Attache. Mr. W. E. Davis, C.B.E Labour Attache, Counsellor (local rank). Mr. H. A. Bulpitt Assistant Labour Attach^, Second Secre tary (local rank). Mr. G. M. Herbert-Smith Representative of Ministry of Food, First Secretary (local rank). Mr. N. Smith Coal Attach^. Mr. A. Hartshorn ... Scientific Attach^ (Ministry of Supply). Mr. J. C. D. Scarlett, O.B.E Financial Adviser, First Secretary (local rank). Bishop Chambers ... Chaplain. Mr. J. K. Rooker, C.B.E., M.C. ... Honorary Attach^. Mr. T. H. Greene Ditto. Mr. A. S. Gilbert ... Ditto. Mr. R. J. Molland Superintending Archivist. Mr. W. V. Deacock Chief Accountant Mr. E. J. Oddy Market Officer (Commercial Section). O.E.E.C., Sir Edmund Hall Patch, K.C.M.G. Permanent United Kingdom Representa PARIS tive on Organisation for European (U.K. Co-operation. Delegation) Mr. H. Ellis Rees, C.M.G Minister. Mr. J. E. Coulson, C.M.G. Minister (local rank). Mr. E. Roll Ditto. Miss M. W. Dennehy Counsellor (local rank). Mr. C. T. Crowe ... First Secretary. Mr. D. F. Hubback First Secretary (local rank). Mr. J. A. Turpin Second Secretary. Mr. C. W. Howard Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. W. Price Ditto. Mr. A. D. Mallet ... Higher Executive Officer.10 Country. GEKMANY ... (Frankfurt) GREECE GUATEMALA Name. Mr. C. E. Steel, C.M.G., M.V.O. Mr. I. P. Garran ... Mr. D. S. Laskey ... Mr. J. E. Killick Mr. D. R. Ashe Mr. D. L. Stewart Mr. K. M. Wilford Mr. A. D. Wilson ... Mr. R. A. A. Chaput de Saintonge Mr. R. F. O’N. Bashford Major B. O’Leary ... Mr. B. C. L. Hockey Lieut.-Colonel R. C. Thomson, I.S.O., M.B.E. Mr. K. M. Duke Dr. W. H. C. Frend Mr. T. D. Williams Mr. L. W. Blackwell Mr. C. D. W. O’Neill Sir Clifford Norton, K.C.M.G., C.Y.O. ... Mr. P. M. Crosthwaite (designate) Mr. J. G. Tahourdin Mr. J. C. A. Roper, M.C. ... Mr. C. N. Halidas, M.B.E Mr. A. A. Duff, D.S.O., D.S.C Mr. A. M. Rendel, M.B.E. Mr. P. Whinney ... Mr. R. S. Isaacson Mr. J. R. Wraight Mr. A. F. Comfort Mr. W. Hillier, M.B.E Mr. A. G. R. Rouse, O.B.E Mr. J. G. McMinnies Mr. R, T. Eland Mr. W. C. Scott, M.B.E. ... Mr. C. S. Palmer Mr. J. Lant Colonel A. C. Shortt, O.B.E Major K. W. L. Roberts, M.B.E. Mr. F. Hampton ... Mr. F. R. G. Rudge Reverend D. A. Duncan ... Mr. W. H. Gallienne, C.B.E. Mr. C. C. A. Lee Mr. J. C. Jeaffreson Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Designation. President of Governmental Sub-Com mission. Chief, Political Division. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Ditto. ^ Third Secretary. Ditto. Head of German Political Branch. Head of Governmental Structure Branch. Press Officer. Head of Visa Section. Assistant Head of Visa Section. F.O./State Department Documents Unit. Assistant Editor, German War Docu ments Project. Ditto. Ditto. Administrative Officer. First Secretary. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Ditto. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Ditto. First Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Ditto. Consul and Administrative Officer, First Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Assistant Administrative Officer. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Labour Attach^, Counsellor (local rank) Assistant Labour Attache, Third Secre tary (local rank). Chaplain. Minister and Consul-General. First Secretary, First Secretary (Com mercial) and Consul. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Naval Attache and Naval Air Attache.11 Country. GUATEMALA (continued). HAYTI HOLY SEE ... HONDURAS... HUNGARY ... ICELAND IRAQ ... Name. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. A. C. Routh Mr. E. D. Watt, M.B.E Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. J. V. T. W. T. Perowne, C.M.G. Mr. J. S. Somers Cocks ... Mr. R. J. Fowler Mr. A. T. Eades Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Acting Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. A. K. Helm, C.M.G., C.B.E. Mr. W. H. Young Mr. H. F. G. Morris Mr. F. G. Burrett Mr. J. A. Ford, M.C. Mr. E. P. Southby Mr. C. H. Eborall Mr. H. T. A. Overton Mr. R. C. Hannah (designate) Mr. H. F. Donner Commander J. W. F. D. Cowgill, R.N. ... Colonel B. R. Col will Lieut.-Colonel P. C. Capron Wing Commander W. M. Bisd^e Squadron Leader V. C. Otter, O.B.E. ... Mr. P. H. Munro-Faure ... Mr. C. W. Baxter, C.M.G., M.C. Dr. Clara G. Thornton Mr. F. J. Welham Sir Henry Mack, K.C.M.G. Mr. H. Trevelyan, C.I.E., O.B.E. Mr. J. F. Brewis ... Mr. D. M. Summerhayes (designate) ... Mr. D. A. Roberts Designation. Air Attache. Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Minister and Consul-General. Consul and First Secretary (local rank). Naval Attache. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank) Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Naval Attachd. Air Attachd. Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). Minister. First Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary. Ditto. First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Third Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary and Consul (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attachd. Military Attachd. Assistant Military Attachd. Air Attachd. Assistant Air Attachd. Petroleum Attachd. Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Ministry of Food Representative. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. Third Secretary and Private Secretary to the Ambassador. E* 36328V2 Country. Name. IRAQ ... ... Mr. L. F. Hooper ... (continued). Mr. J. C. B. Richmond Mr. G. G. Arthur ... Mr. F. H. Gamble Mr. W. Boyes Mr. C. Howson, M.C. Mr. A. M. Williams Mr. F. Wells Mr. G. N. I. Morrison Mr. C. P. Rossiter ... Lieut.-Colonel J. H. R. Orlebar ... Mr. B. G. Barnard Reverend C. V. Roberts Designation. Second Secretary (local rank). Oriental Secretary (with local rank of Oriental Counsellor). Third Secretary (Oriental). Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (l^al rank). Third Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary and Consul. Third Secretary and Vice-Consul (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Military Attache. Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Honorary Chaplain. ITALY Sir Victor Mallet, K.C.M.G., C.V.O. Mr. J. G. Ward, C.M.G. ... Mr. M. S. Williams Hon. H. A. A. Hankey ... Wing Commander Verschoyle ... Mr. A. R. Moore ... Mr. D. V. Bendall, M.B.E. Mr. C. L. Silverwood-Cope Mr. F. G. Adams ... Mr. C. F. Rolo Mr. F. W. Tooby ... Mr. A. D. Trounson Mr. W. N. R. Maxwell Mr. C. Empson, C.M.G. ... Mr. R. A. Daniell (designate) ... Mr. J. G. Boyd Mr. J. C. W. Bushell Mr. C. H. Henderson Mr. J. P. Reeves, O.B.E. ... Mr. I. H. P. McEwen Mr. J. A. Pilcher ... Hon. E. B. C. Howard Captain J. D. Shaw-Hamilton, R.N. ... Commander (E) E. A. Read, R.N. Colonel G. A. C. Macnab ... Major J. M. Jourdier Major J. M. Pyne ... Group Captain A. G. Adnams Mr. W. H. Braine, C.B.E. Miss E. Lapthorn ... Mr. J. Mallet, M.V.O Mr. G. G. Hannaford Mr. M. C. Adams Mr. T. W. Glover. M.B.E. Dr. S. Cremona, O.B.E. ... Mr. C. T. Tsolani Mr. D. F. N. Charles Reverend C. S. Powers Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Ditto. Second Secretary. Ditto. Ditto. Third Secretary. Ditto. First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Minister (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial), Second Secretary (Commercial). Ditto. Third Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary and Consul. First Secretary (local rank). Visa Officer. First Secretary (Information). Assistant Information Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). Naval Attach^. Assistant Naval Attach^ (Technical). Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Ditto. Air*AttachA Labour Attach^, Counsellor (local rank). Ministry of Food Representative, Second Secretary (local rank). Attach^ and Private Secretary. Legal Adviser. Property Adviser, First Secretary (local rank). Administrative Officer. Head of Press Reading Section (Informa tion). Head of Features Section (Information) Films Officer (Information). Chaplain.13 36328 E* 2 Country. Name. Designation. JAPAN Sir Alvary Gascoigne, K.C.M.G. Mr. I. T. M. Pink Mr. H. H. Thomas Mr. R. G. H. Watts Mr. H. C. Hainworth Mr. C. P. Scott, O.B.E Mr. P. A. G. Westlake, M.C. Mr. J. Quine Mr. P. V. St. J. Killick ... Mr. E. R. Lingeman, C.B.E. Mr. A. J. Goodman Mr. H. C. Lepper ... Mr. L. S. J. PI ill Mr. H. R. Sawbridge* Mr. L. Pickles Mr. K. A. Geary ... Mr. H. V. Redman, O.B.E Mr. E. C. Blunden Mr. A. R. Boyce ... Mr. J. H. Ewing, O.B.E Mr. J. L. Allaway Captain C. B. Tidd, R.N. Commander C. N. R. Barham, R.N. Sub-Lieutenant (S.) G. N. Shaw, R.N.V.R. Brigadier A. K. Ferguson, C.B.E. Lieut.-Colonel J. G. Flggess Group Captain G. R. Montgomery, C.B.E. Flight-Lieut. A. Bell Mr. E. G. Wilson ... Mr. A. D. Tarr United Kingdom Political Representa tive. Counsellor. Counsellor (Financial). First Secretary, Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Ditto. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Economic Adviser. First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary and Head of Consular Section. First Secretary and Consul. Ditto. Counsellor (Information) (local rank). P'irst Secretary (Information) (local rank). Ditto. Counsellor (Purchasing and Selling). Attach^. Naval Adviser. Assistant Naval Adviser. Secretary to Naval Adviser. Military Adviser. Assistant Military Adviser. Air Adviser. Assistant Air Adviser. Labour Adviser to U.K.L.M. Shipping Adviser. % LEBANON Mr. W. E. Houstoun-Boswall, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. T. E. Evans, O.B.E Mr. C. N. Jupp Mr. M. Arab, M.B.E Mr. W. J. M. Paterson Mr. R. H. Newall ... Mr. B. C. MacDermot Mr. W. G. Clifford Mr. E. J. Howes ... Mr. W. H. M. Hindle Lieut.-Colonel V. D’O. Harmar Major D. J. P. Beaumont-Nesbitt, M.B.E. Mr. J. G. Hart Minister. First Secretary, Oriental Secretary. Second Secretary. Assistant Oriental Secretary, Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). P'irst Secretary and Consul. Passport Control Officer, Second Secre tary (local rank). First Secretary (Information). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Military Attachd. Assistant Military Attach^. Attach^. Head Office of Consular Section, U.K.L.M., in Japan is at Yokohama.14 Country. Name. Designation. LEBANON ... (continued). Wing Commander C. J. Lewin ... Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Reverend H. Adkins Honorary Chaplain. Mr. H. C. Birtles, M.B.E Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). LlBEJttlA ... Mr. J. Bowering ... ... Minister and Consul-General. LUXEM BOURG Mr. G. C. Allehin, C.M.G., M.C. (designate) Colonel D. P. Eabin, M.B.E. Minister Military Attach^. MEXICO Mr. T. C. Rapp, C.M.G., M.C Mr. A. C. E. Malcolm Mr. W. W. McVittie Mr. A. A. W. Landymore Mrs. D. H. Cockburn, M.B.E. ... Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery, First Secretary (Information). Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Assistant Information Officer. Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C., R.N. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Naval Attache. Air Attache. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). NEPAL Lieutenant-Colonel Sir George Falconer, K.B.E., C.I.E. Lieutenant-Colonel R. R. Proud ... Ambassador. First Secretary. NETHER LANDS Sir Philip Nichols, K.C.M.G., M.C. Mr. B. E. F. Gage ... Mr. J. H. Peck Mr. R. H. MacDonald Miss J. C. Petrie ... Mr. F. G. Shubothain Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Ditto. |Mr. L. B. S. Larkins, O.B.E. Mr. C. E. Emerson Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Mr. M. A. M. Robb Mr. J. O’Connor Howe First Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). First Secretary, Visa Officer. Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attach^. Military Attache. Air Attach^. Civil Aviation Attache. Mr. J. H. Mockford Commander E. Neville, R.N. Commander (E) E. A. Read, R.N. Colonel R. A. G. Bingley, D.S.O., O.B.E. Group Captain J. Heber-Percy ... Air Marshal D. Colyer, C.B., D.F.C. .:. Mr. A. Greenhougli Mr. G. W. Ethall Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). Food Attache. NICARAGUA... Mr. N. 0. W. Steward, O.B.E Minister and Consul-General. Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Naval Air Attach^. Assistant Naval Attach^. Air Attach^. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Mr. F. R. Jeffers ... Vice-Consul and Second Secretary (local rank).15 Co untry. NORWAY PANAMA PAKAGUAY ... PERSIA Name. Sir Laurence Collier, K.C.M.G. ... Mr. E. E. Crowe ... Mr. H. F. T. Smith Mr. J. Inman Mr. L. C. S. Barber, M.B.E. ... Mr. J. C. Aird, M.B.E Mr. D. M. Edwards Mr. F. C. Mason ... Mr. G. R. Coate Mr. W. K. Liversidge, M.B.E. ... Mr. W. D. Shanks Captain R. E. D. Ryder, V.C., R.N. Lieutenant-Colonel K. G. Treseder, O.B.E. Wing Commander J. B. Coward ... Miss N. Bing, M.B.E. Mr. J. D. Greenway, C.M.G. Mr. G. W. Kirk Mr. J. M. Leadbitter Captain J. Holmes, R.N. Commander (E) J. E. Best, R.N. Commander F. H. E. Hopkins, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. I. L. Henderson (designate) Captain D. E. Holland-Martin, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Air Commodore H. E. Walker, M.C., D.F.C. Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. ... Mr. E. J. Toogood ... Sir John Le Rougetel, K.C.M.G., M.C. Mr. M. J. Creswell Mr. A. D. M. Ross Mr. C. T. Gandy Mr. M. F. Albrecht Mr. I. T. Milne, O.B.E Colonel G. E. Wheeler, C.B.E., C.I.E. Mr. S. J. Whitwell, M.C Mr. J. Walker, O.B.E Mr. D. A. Logan ... Major R. Jackson, M.B.E. Mr. D. W. T. Smithies Designation. Ambassador. Counsellor, Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary and Consul. Third Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul. First Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information). First Secretary (local rank) and Head of Visa Section. Third Secretary (local rank), Visa Sec tion. Naval Attache. Military Attache. Air Attache. Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). Minister and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul. Second Secretary (Information). Naval Attach^ and Naval Air Attache. Assistant Naval Attach^ (E). Assistant Naval Attach^ (Air). Air Attache. Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank) Minister and Consul-General. Naval Attach^. Air Attach^. Civil Air Attache. Labour Attache (resident in Buenos Aires). Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Oriental Counsellor.. Assistant Oriental . Secretary, Second Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Market Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). • First Secretary (local rank) and Head of Consular Section.16 Country. Name. Designation. PERSIA (continued). Mr. C. W. Hart, M.B.E. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Colonel D. L. Betts, O.B.E., R.A. Wing Commander W. I. C. Inness Mr. B. G. Barnard Mr. K. J. Hird Military Attache. Air Attache. Civil Air Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Labour Attach^, First Secretary (k-al rank). Dr. H. Cohen Embassy Physician. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.l. Mr. A. L. A. Dredge, M.B.E. ... Mr. A. J. Johnson, M.B.E. Political Resident. First Secretary (local rank). Administration Officer. Lieut.-Colonel W. J. Moody Medical Adviser to His Excellency the Political Resident and Chief Quaran tine Medical Officer, Persian Gulf. PERU Mr. J. L. Dodds, C.M.G. (designate) ... Mr. R. H. K. Marett, O.B.E Ambassador. First Secretary and Consul (Head of Chancery). Mr. W. G. Bruzuud, O.B.E. Mr. D. A. Malcolm First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Mr. R. J. Kirwin, M.B.E. Mr. P. H. Barker Benfield Vice-Consul and Second Secretary. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Captain W. G. Brittain, C.B.E., R.N. ... Group Captain H. M. Pearson, C.B.E. ... Mr. W. E. Oakley Evans ... Naval Attache. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary Hocal rank). PHILIPPINES Mr. L. H. Foulds, C.B.E Mr. J. H. Dickinson Mr. R. Milburn Minister. First Secretary and Consul, Head of Chancery. First Secretary (Commercial). POLAND Sir Donald Gainer. K.C.M.G., O.B.E. ... Mr. R. H. S. Allen Mr. A. J. Edden ... Mr. M. B. Winch ... Mr. D. F. Murray ... Mr. L. H. Massey Mr. R. Sneddon Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary. Third Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Mr. J. P. Summerscale ... Mr. R. S. Smith Mr. J. H. Wolfe Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (local rank). Mr. L. J. A. Parish Mr. J. Grant Purves Mr. P. N. Cleary-Fox Mr. F. Cox ... Mr. J. A. Riddell First Secretary, Consul (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Editor. Assistant Editor. Captain J. H. Ruek-Keene, O.B.E., D.S.C., R.N. Lieutenant-Commander J. A. Holds- worth, R.N. Colonel T. A. H. Coltman Major R. G. Marshall, M.B.E. ... Group Captain C. H. Turner Squadron Leader P. M. Dobree-Bell, A.F.C. Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attach^. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attach^.17 Country. Name. POLAND ... Mr. R. B. Kirby [continued). Mr. A. C. Mftule ... Designation. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Administrative Officer, Third Secretary (local rank). PORTUGAL ... Sir Nigel Ronald, K.C.M.G., C.V.O. Mr. P. Grey (designate) ... Mr. R. W. J. Hooper, D.S.O., D.F.C. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Mr. M. S. Henderson Mr. J. H. Lewen Mr. W. H. A. Gilman, M.B.E. ... Mr. F. B. G. Bevan Mr. F. A. Wise Mr. G. F. Pinney ... Commander J. W. McClelland, D.S.O., R.N. Lieutenant-Colonel A. J. E. Gordon M.C. Wing Commander C. E. A. Garton Mr. T. H. Froebelius, M.B.E. ... Counsellor (Commercial) and Consul- General. Second Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Commercial Attach^ (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Visa Section). Naval Attach^. Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attach^. Archivist. ROUMANTA ... Mr. W. St. C. H. Roberts, C.M.G. (designate). Mr. R. F. G. Sarell Mr. J. 0. Wright, D.S.C. Mr. R. A. Hibbert ... Mr. R. A. I. King Mr. J. 0. May, O.B.E Mr. J. S. A. Selwyn Mr. H. S. Marchant, O.B.E. Mr. F. E. H. Bennett Commander J. W. F. D. Cowgill ... Colonel R. G. Turner Major C. 0. I. Ramsden ... Wing Commander J. V. Hoggarth Squadron Leader P. C. Cleaver, O Mr. P. H. Munro-Faure M.C. Minister. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. Ditto. Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary, Head of Consular Section. First Secretary (Information). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attach^. Military Attach^. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attach^. •B.E. Assistant Air Attach^. Petroleum Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). SALVADOR... Mr. H. N. Steptoe Mr. A. M. Earle Mr. S. M. Stadler, O.B.E. ...' ' Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D S 0 D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Commercial Attache and Vice-Consul. Naval Attach^. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank).18 Country. SAUDI ARABIA SIAM ... SINGAPORE... SOVIET UNION Name. Mr. A. C. Trott, C.M.G., O.B.E — Mr. G. H. Clarke ... Mr. G. F. Rodgers Mr. M. W. Errock Mr. D. J. McCarthy Mr. G. H. Thompson, K.C.M.G. Mr. R. Whittington, O.B.E. Mr. A. K. Rothnie (designate) ... Mr. G. C. Madoc ... Mr. P. V. W. R. H. O’Regan Mr. S. H. J. Read Mr. B. J. Garnett ... Mr. A. C. Buxton Mr. D. A. Batwell Mr. D. C. Rivett-Carnac Mr. P. Wilkinson ... Commander D. F. Townsend, R.N. Colonel E. T. Heslop Wing Commander J. N. H. Whitworth, D.S.O., D.F.C. The Right Hon. M. MacDonald ... Mr. P. S. Scrivener, C.M.G. Mr. J. D. Murray ... Mr. 1). T. West Dr. W. M. Clyde, C.M.G. Mr. R. G. Stone ... Mr. St. J. Donn-Byrne ... Mr. H. J. Collins ... Mr. F. G. J. Roberts Mr. W. R. Innes ... Dr. H. W. Jack, O.B.E. ... Mr. R. M. Hallows, M.B.E. Mr. C. Whitworth, M.B.E. Sir Maurice Peterson, G.C.M.G. Mr. G. W. Harrison, C.M.G. ... Mr. G. C. Whitteridge, O.B.E. ... Mr. G. M. Warr ... Mr. H. T. Morgan Mr. J. P. Waterfield Mr. M. E. Bolland Mr. H. Braham Mr. W. Barker Mr. H. A. Eunghi ... Mr. H. M. Hayward Mr. P. J. Kelly Designation. Ambassador. First Secretary, Consul and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Third Secretary and Oriental Secret®’'. Third Secretary. Ambassador. Counsellor and Consul-General. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Ditto. Third Secretary. Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial). Commercial Assistant. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Naval Attachd. Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Commissioner-General for His Majesty s Government in the United Kingdom in South-East Asia, with personal rank of Ambassador. Deputy Commissioner-General. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. Director of Economic Activities. First Secretary (Economic). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Regional Security Officer. Assistant Regional Security Officer. Commodity Officer. Agricultural Adviser. Regional Security Officer, First Secre tary (local rank). Head of Administration. Ambassador. Minister (local ranit;. First Secretary and Head of Chancery First Secretary. Second Secretary. Third Secretary. Ditto. Counsellor (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary. Third Secretary (local lank). Ditto. Ditto.19 Country. Name. SOVIET Mr. J. A. Dobbs UNION (continued). Mr. R. D. Fyfe Lieutenant A. G. Howard, R.N Lieutenant-Colonel F. R. Hulton, R.A Air Commodore N. C. Ogilvie Forbes O.B.E. Squadron Leader C. A. Alldis, D.F.C. . Dr. M. T. Gillies Mr. S. L. Harrison ... Mr. V. Bulmer Mr. H. D. S. Bridge Mr. A. R. Johnstone Miss M. King (cA- Deaignation. Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attach^. Military Attach^. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attach^. Physician. Security Officer. Attache (Commercial). First Secretary (local rank). Editor (Information). Assistant Editor (Information). Archivist. SPAIN Mr. D. F. Howard, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. C. H. Johnston Mr. B. Malley, M.B.E Mr. J. C. Petersen Mr. D. A. Bristow ... Mr. B. E. Wallace ... Mr. G. C. Pelham, C.M.G. Mr. G. F. Hiller, D.S.O. ... Mr. 0. T. Rayner ... Mr. W. B. Milton, M.B.E. Mr. D. Cameron Mr. E. U. Penrose-Fitzgerald, O.B.E. ... Mr. F. L. Adams ... Mr. R. Walter Mr. J. H. Thom Cmdr. C. H. de B. Newby, R.N. Brigadier 0. C. B. Smith-Bingham Major E. J. Tonson-Rye ... Wing Commander J. W. Monk ... Professor W. F. Starkie, C.B.E. ... The Rev. H. Brown Mr. A. Fenner Mr. F. 0. Grant Mr. J. M. N. Jeffries Charge d’Affaires. •First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary (local rank). Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank) (Head of British Government Purchasing Mission). Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary (Consular Section) and Consul. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). First Secretary (local rank), Visa Section. Naval Attach^. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attach^. Attach^ (British Council Representative in Spain). Attach^ (Chaplain). Security Officer. Market Officer. Special editor (Information Department). SWEDEN Mr. H. L. Farquhar, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. A. E. Lambert Mr. G. S. Littlejohn-Cook Mr. E. E. M. Nielsen Mr. G. A. Urquhart, M.B.E. ... Ir. D. J. Gibson Ambassador. Counsellor. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Third Secretary (local rank).20 Country. Name. Designation SWEDEN {continued). Mr. N. S. lloberts, O.B.E. Mr. R. H. Traviss, M.B.E. Mr. M. A. C. Silverwood-Cope Mr. M. A. Wenner Mr. J. S. Bennett Commander F. W. R. Darken, R.N. Commander (E) H. G. R. Binning, R.N. Lieutenant-Colonel P. H. Graves-Morris, D.S.O., M.C. Major Count P. F. de Salis Wing Commander M. Wyatt, D.F.C. ... Squadron Leader M. T. Whinney, M.B.E. Mr. C. D. Insall Mr. P. R. Williamson Reverend C. H. Jones, M.A. Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Second Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial). 'First Secretary and Consul. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attach^. Assistant Naval Attach^ (Technical). Military Attach^. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attach^. Second Secretary (local rank), Head of Visa Section. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Honorary Chaplain. SWITZER LAND Mr. T. M. Snow, C.M.G. ... Mr. T. S. Tull, D.S.O., O.B.E. Mr. R. V. Johnston-Smith Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. W. Harpham, O.B.E. Mr. Jackson Smith, M.B.E. Mr. H. J. Legg Mr. P R. Larke ... Mr. F. Dixon Mr. A. G. Michelsen Mr. J.'N. Elliott Commander (E) E. A. Read, R.N. Lieutenant-Colonel G. S. Wilmot-Sitwell Wing Commander R. N. Smith, O.B.E. Lieutenant-Colonel H. N. Fryer ... Mr. S. J. Peskett ... Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Consul (local rank) and Second Secre tary (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank), Head of Visa Section. Attach^ for Naval Questions. Military Attach^. Air Attach 6 . Attach^. Market Officer. SYRIA Mr. P. M. Broadmead, C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. C. A. F. Dundas, O.B.E Mr. P. J. E. Male, M.C Mr. G. D. Little Mr. A. Halsey, M.B.E Mr. J. E. P. Leslie Mr. W. Kirkpatrick Lieutenant-Colonel V. D’O. Harmar ... Major D. J. P. Beaumont-Nesbitt, M.B.E. Mr. W. C. Brayne Minister. Oriental Secretary, First Secretary (local rank) and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial) and Consul. Commercial Assistant and Vice-Consul (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Military Attach^. Assistant Military Attach^. Archivist and Accountant, Third Secre tary (local rank). TRANS- Sir Alec Kirkbride. C.M.G.. O.B.E., M.C. Minister. JORDAN Mr. C. M. Pirie-Gordon ... Mr. W. F. H. Roblou Mr. C. J. Cowan ... Mr. E. W. Noonan First Secretary and Consul. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul (local rank). Third Secretary (local rank). Petroleum Attach^.21 Country. TRIESTE ') m TURKEY UNITED STATES Name. Mr. \V. J. Sullivan, U.I3.E. Mr. E. C . Bateman, M.B.E. Sir David Kelly, K.C.M.G., M.O. Mr. H. M. Eyres ... Mr. A. C. I. Samuel Mr. H. P. L. Attlee lion. R. J. M. Wilson Mr. T. ( 1 . A. Muntz, O.B.E. Mr. A. H. Ballantyne Major P. R. Reid, M.B.E., M.C. ... Mr. J. G. Whittall Mr. H. A. R. Philby Mr. W. Hickson ... ... ... • Mr. W. E. D. Allen, O.B.E Mr. E. E. Redward Mr. F. V. Michell Mr. A. Whittall Captain R. J. S. Brown, R.N Lieutenant-Commander G. V. Corbett R.N. Brigadier C. S. Clarke, M.C Major P. H. V. de Clermont Air Commodore C. G. Wigglesworth, C.B., A.F.C. Wing Commander S. N. L. Maude, O.B.E., D.F.C. Wing Commander P. A. L. Cooper Wing Commander C. J. Lewin Reverend C. W. Piper Sir Oliver Franks, K.C.B., C.B.E. Mr. F. R. Hoyer-Millar, K.C.M.G., C.V.O Mr. J. W. Taylor, C.M.G., M.B.E. Sir R. Gordon Munro, K.C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. J. H. Penson, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. E. A. Cleugh, O.B.E., M.V.O. Mr. H. A. Graves, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. C. A. G. de J. Meade Mr. J. E. S. Fawcett Mr. W. D. Allen Mr. A. N. Morgan Mr. P. S. Stephens Mr. J. F. Ford, O.B.E Mr. T. E. Bromley Mr. F. W. Marten, M.C. ... Mr. J. A. Judson ... Sir Robert MacKenzie, Bart. Lord Jellicoe. D.S.O., M.C. Mr. J. N. Henderson Mr. D. C. Tebbit ... Mr. P. M. Dwyer ... Mr. P. Casson Mr. M. B. Thresher Designation. British Political Adviser to Commander, British/United States Zone, Free Territory of Trieste. Assistant to Political Adviser. Ambassador. Minister. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Third Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial) (Istanbul). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (local rank) (Istanbul). Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Counsellor (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Istanbul). Second Secretary and P.C.O. (Istanbul). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Ditto. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attache. Ditto. Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Chaplain. Ambassador. Minister. Minister (Commercial). Minister (Financial). Adviser on German Affairs. Counsellor and Consul-General. Counsellor. Ditto. Legal Adviser. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. Counsellor (local rank). First Secretary. Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. First Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Second Secretary. Ditto. Ditto. Second Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary’ (Private Secretary to Ambassador). Second Secretary (local rank).22 Country. UNITED STATES (continued). URUGUAY ... Name. Mr. W. N. Storey, O.B.E Mr. A. E. Percivnl Colonel P. J. E. Rowell, O.B.E., M.C. ... Mr. K. 1). Jamieson Miss L. M. Rainbow Mr. R. Thistlethwaite Mr. G. E. McDougall Mr. C. B. Wilson ... Mr. H. F. A. Gates, M.B.E. Mr. E. Williams ... Mr. W. P. \. Edwards, ( .B.E. Mr. N. W. H. Gaydon Mr. M. W. Pritchard Mr. G. Huson Captain J. Holmes, R.N. Commander (E) J. E. Best, R.N. Commander F. H. E. Hopkins, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Colonel J. C. Windsor-Lewis, D.S.O., M.C. Group Captain R. C. Jonas, O.B.E. Squadron Leader J. N. Stacey, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. C. Clarkson, A.F.C. ... Mr. E. I. R. MacGregor ... Mr. E. E. Jones, O.B.E. ... Dr. W. F. A. Macfarlane ... Mr. A. K. Longair ... Mr. A. McD. Gordon, C.M.G. Mr. T. Thom as Mr. R. It. B. Bannerman Mr. F. V. Cross Mr. A. N. Duckham, O.B.E. Mr. P. J. Macfarlan Mr. E. E. Sabben-Clare Miss I. F. M. Boyle, O.B.E Mr. G. L. Payne ... Mr. H. L. Rowland Mr. W. F. Redmond, M.B.E. Mr. G. S. McWilliam Mr. W. F. Oram, M.B.E. Mr. P. C. Pell Mr. F. R. D. Cutler Mr. F. W. James Sir Gordon Yereker, K.C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. P. G. F. Dalton Mr. Jocelyn Speck, M.V.O. Mr. D. R. Smith-Bingham Mr. C. G. Harris ... Mr. L. A. P. Barker Mr. N. P. A.-Swan Captain D. E. Holland-Martin, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Designation. Counsellor (Commercial). Ditto. First Secretary (General Economic Department). Second Secretary (General Economic Department). Second Secretary (General Ecoi^mc Department). Second Secretary (local rank) (General Economic Department). First Secretary (Raw Materials Section). Ditto. Administration Officer, First Secretary. First Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Counsellor. (Head of British Informa tion Services). First Secretary (British Information Services) (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attach^ (E). Assistant Naval Attach^ (Air). Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attache. Civil Air Attache. Assistant Civil Air Attach^. Petroleum Attach^. Health Attache. Attach^ for Scientific Questions. Assistant Scientific Attach^. Labour Attach^, Counsellor (local rank). Deputy Labour Attach^, First Secre tary (local rank). Assistant Labour Attach^, Second Secre tary (local rank). Shipping Attache. Agricultural Attache, Counsellor (local rank). Assistant Agricultural Attache. Attach^ for Colonial Affairs. Attach^. Ditto. Ditto. Head, Telegraphic Communications. First Secretary (local rank). Higher Executive Officer. Civilian Staff Officer. Head Archivist. Higher Executive Officer. Accountant. Ambassador. First Secretary and Consul. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. First Secretary (Commercial). Vice-Consul, Second Secretary (local rank). Information Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). Naval Attach£.Country. Name. Designation. URUGUAY ( continued ). ‘y* VENEZUELA YUGOSLAVIA UNITED NATIONS (New York) Air Commodore H. E. Walker, M.C., D.F.C. Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.E.C. Mr. E. J. Toogood ... Mr. S. G. Cornah ... Captain H. Cross, M.C. Mr. A. M. Dick Sir John Magowan, K.B.E., C.M.G. Mr. J. Robinson Mr. A. 0. Bray Mr. M. Gale, M.B.E. Mr. E. P. Lecours ... Captain B. J. Fisher, R.N. Group Captain A. P. Bett Mr. C. A. Bryer Sir Charles Peake, K.C.M.G., M.C. Mr. C. E. King Mr. E. S. Keyser, M.B.E. ... Mr. D. Floyd Mr. T. A. K. Elliott Mr. H. T. Kennedy Miss C. E. Ludlam Mr. W. Manning ... Mr. D. G. Crichton Commander W. W. Fitzroy, R.N. Lieutenant M. J. Connor, R.N.V.R. Lieutenant-Colonel C. H. Dewhurst, O.B.E. Major L. T. Tomes Wing Commander P, J. Sanders, D.F.C. Mr. A. S. Hindle ... Miss A. Tillyard ... Mrs. V. E. Price ... The Right Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan, G.C.M.G., K.C.B. Sir Terence Shone, K.C.M.G. Mr. V. G. Lawford, M.V.O. Mr. P. S. Falla Mr. A. R. K. MacKenzie ... Mr. I. Anstruther ... Sir James Chadwick, F.R.S. Mr. H. M. Phillips Mr. R. T. D. Ledward Mr. J. T. Fearnley Air Attache. Civil Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Assistant (Commercial). Acting Market Officer, Attach^ (local rank). Assistant to Commercial Secretary. Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Ambassador. First Secretary (Head of Chancery). Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Third Secretary. First Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary and Consul (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attache. Attache. Ditto. Administration Officer. Archivist and Accountant, Third Secre tary (local rank). Permanent United Kingdom Representa tive to the Security Council, and United Kingdom Representative on the United Nations Atomic Energy Com mission. Deputy United Kingdom Representative. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary in Charge of Public Relations. Private Secretary to Permanent United Kingdom Representative. Scientific Adviser and Alternate Repre sentative on Atomic Energy Com mission. Counsellor for Economic and Social Affairs. First Secretary. Third Secretary.24 Country. UNITED NATIONS (New York) {continued). UNITED NATIONS (Geneva). Name. Mr. D. L. Cole ... Mr. J. Fletcher-Cooke Designation. C.R.O. Representative, Second Secre tary (loeal rank). C.O. Attache. Mr. J. E. S. Fawcett, D.S.C. Counsellor, Legal Adviser. Mr. H. A. Cooper Mr. C. Winson Administrative, Finance and Establish ment Officer. Staff Officer. Mr. E. R. Warner, O.B.E. Mr. R. D. Thrupp Mr. E. C. Gamble, M.B.E. Head of United Kingdom Delegation. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. CORPS OF INSPECTORS Senior Inspector: Mr. A. B. Hutcheon, C.M.G., M.B.E. Inspectors: Mr. A. S. Paterson, C.M.G., O.B.E. Sir Andrew Noble, Bart., C.M.G. Mr. D. L. Busk, C.M.G. Mr. D. V. Staines, O.B.E.29 Place. Addis Ababa Amman ... Angora ... Asuncio^^ Athens ... Bagdad ... Bahrein ... Bangkok Beirut Belgrade Berlin Berne Bogota ... Brussels Bucharest Budapest Buenos Aires Cairo Caracas ... Ciudad Trujillo Copenhagen Damascus Guatemala Havana ... Helsingfors Jedda Kabul ... Katmandu La Paz ... Lima Lisbon ... Guide to countries in which places (in index) are situated Country. Place. Country. Ethiopia. Madrid ... • •• Spain. Transjordon. Managua • •• Nicaragua. Turkey. Manila ... Philippines. Paraguay. Mexico City Mexico. Greece. Monrovia Liberia. Iraq. Montevideo Uruguay. Persian Gulf. Moscow ... Soviet Union. Siam. Nanking ... China. Lebanon. Oslo Norway. Yugoslavia. Panamd ... Panamd. Germany. Paris France. Switzerland. Port-au-Prince ... Hayti. Colombia. Prague ... Czechoslovakia. Belgium. Quito Ecuador. Roumania. Rangoon Burma. Hungary. Reykjavik Iceland. Argentine Republic. Rio de Janeiro ... Brazil. Egypt. Rome Italy. Venezuela. San Josd Costa Rica. Dominican Republic. San Salvador ... Salvador. Denmark. Santiago Chile. Syria. Sofia Bulgaria. Guatemala. Stockholm Sweden. Cuba. Tegucigalpa Honduras. Finland. Tehran ... Persia. Saudi Arabia. The Hague The Netherlands. Afghanistan. Tokyo Japan. Nepal. Warsaw ... Poland. Bolivia. Vienna ... Austria. Peru. Washington United States. Portugal.LIST OF THE PERMANENT AND TEMPORARY STAFFS OF HIS MAJESTY’S EMBASSIES, LEGATIONS AND POLITICAL MISSIONS ABROAD LIST 1 : SENIOR OFFICERS SEPTEMBER 1948 [NOTE.—Any corrections should be addressed to Records Section, Personnel Department] B* 14148—2 f85783]List of the Permanent and Temporary Staffs of His Majesty’s Embassies, Legations and Political Missions Abroad List 1: Senior Officers September 1948 Country. Name. Designation. AFGHAN- Sir Giles Squire, K.B.E., C.I.E. ... Ambassador. ISTAN Mr. D. M. H. Riches First Secretary. Mr. D. U. Jackson ^... Second Secretary (Oriental) Mr. A. J. Evans, M.JB.E. Second Secretary. Lieutenant-Colonel J. H. Prendergast, D.S.O., M.C. Military Attache. Mr. W. S. Sinclair . v ... ... ... Archivist. ARGENTINE Sir John Balfour, K.C.M.G. Ambassador. REPUBLIC Mr. G. P. Labouchere Counsellor. Mr. A. H. Lincoln ... First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Mr. J. A. D. Lawson Second Secretary. Mr. L. M. Minford Third Secretary. Mr. J. G. Lomax, C.M.G., M.B.E ., M.C. Minister (Commercial). Mr. W. G. R. Howell, O.B.E. ... • . . Counsellor (Commercial). Mr. W. W. McVittie First Secretary (Commercial). Mr. A. C. Maby ... Ditto. Mr. P. G. H. Dorchy, M.B.E. ... First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Mr. E. E. Young ... Assistant Information Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). Captain D. E. Holland-Martin, D.S.C., R.N. D.S.O., Naval Attache. Air Commodore H. E. Walker, D.F.C. M.C., Air Attach^. Mr. R. H. Haven-Dyke, M.B.E. Assistant Air Attache. Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. Civil Air Attach^. Mr. E. J. Toogood Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Major T. A. Rattray Agricultural Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Mr. P. A. Miller ... Civil Attach^. Mr. A. H. Coldham Archivist and Accountant. Mr. S. N. Oerton ... Archivist. AUSTRIA . Sir Bertrand Jerram, K .C.M.G. Minister, Mr. N. J. A. Cheetham Counsellor. - Mr. A. K. Rothnie ... Second Secretary. Mr. P. M. Foster ... Third Secretary. Mr. S. E. H. Daw ... Counsellor (Commercial) (local rank). Mr. A. E. Cox Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Mr J. M. Crofton ... Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Mr. F. S. Fielding ... Ditto. Mr. J. G. Baillie ... ... First Secretary and Consul. Mr. G. M. Young ... Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. P. G. Martin-Smith Third Secretary (local rank). Mr. G. Berry First Secretary (local rank), Head of Visa Section. Mr. A. S. Auger Third Secretary (local rank). Mr. A. Bennett Labour Attach^. \ Miss G. Stenning ... ... Archivist and Accountant.3 Country. BELGIUM Name. Designation. Sir George Rendel, K.C.M.G. Mr. W. H. Montagu-Pollock, C.M.G. .. Mr. P. F. Hancock (designate) Mr. T. R. D. Belgrave Mr. D. W. Hough Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. E. J. Joint, C.M.G., O.B.E. ... Mr. A. Duncan Counsellor (Commercial). Counsellor (Commercial) (local rank). Mr. W. C. R. Aue Consul, First Secretary. Mr. S. A. Lockhart Mr. E. J. W. S. Foote First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank).- Commander E. Neville, R.N. Colonel D. P. Fabin, M.B.E. Group Captain J. Grandy, D.S.O. Air Marshal D. Colyer, C.B., D.I.C. .. Naval Attachd. Military Attachd. Air Attach^. Civil Air Attach^. Mr. C. F. Heron Mr. C. S. Collinson, O.B.E. Mr. I. W. Dollar ... Mr. H. M. A. Montgomery Mr. C. J. T. Spearman Mr. G. W. Ethall ... Labour Attachd. First Secretary (local rank) (Visa Sec tion). .. Third Secretary (local rank) (Visa Sec tion). Specialist (Visa Section). .. Administrative Officer, Third Secretary (local rank). Food Attachd. Mr. H. Williams ... Archivist and Accountant. BOLIVIA Mr. T. Ifor Rees, C.M.G. Mr. H. Osborne Mr. D. F. Muirhead Group Captain H. M. Pearson, C.B.E. Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. Mr. W. E. Oakley-Evans Mr. K. A. Murdoch Mr. R. Huxley-Hall Ambassador. First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Air Attache. Civil Air Attach^. Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). Civil Attachd. Archivist, Accountant and Cypher Officer. BRAZIL Sir Nevile Butler, K.C.M.G., C.V.O. Mr. G. P. Young Mr. R. A. Burroughs Mr. J. H. Innes, M.B.E. ... Mr. A. H. W. King, C.B.E. Mr. W. A. T. Sowden, M.B.E. ... Mr. J. A. Burns, O.B.E. ... Mr. L. P. Bridal ... Mr. R. J. Stratton Mr. G. M. F. Stow Mr. N. D. T. Sutton Mr. D. McEwen ... Captain B. J. Fisher, D.S.O., R.N. Brigadier J. C. O’Dwyer Group Captain D. W. Bayne Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. ... Mr. L. Mitchell ... Mr. F. C. Hensby ... Ambassador. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Minister (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Ditto. Third Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). Naval Attach^. Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Civil Air Attach^. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local • rank). Archivist. c* 357834 Country. Name. Designation. BULGARIA .. Mr. J. C. Sterndale Bennett, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. D. A. Greenhill, O.B.E Lieutenant-Colonel R. 0. A. Gatehouse Mr. D. I. Dunnett Mr. A. M. Brooks ... Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary. Third Secretary (local rank). Mr. S. P. House Mr. K. W. Lee First Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Mr. G. R. A. Conquest Mr. J. D. Blakeway Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Ditto. Ditto. Commander J. W. F. D. Cowgill, R.N. ... Colonel G. G. Green, D.S.O. Major B. G. Merrivale-Austin ... Wing Commander A. R. Collins Naval Attachd. Military Attachd. Assistant Military Attachd. Air Attachd. Mr. H. N. Walmsley Archivist. BURMA Mr. R. J. Bowker, C.M.G. Mr. G. E. Crornbie Mr. G. H. Baker ... Mr. C. C. Clemens, M.C. ... Ambassador. Counsellor (local rank). First Secretary and Head of Chancery Third Secretary. Mr. L. C. Glass Oriental Secretary. Mr. W. K. Smith ... Counsellor (Commercial). Mr. F. A. G. Cook, O.B.E Mr. A. T. Cox, M.B.E Counsellor and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul. ' • !?' • . ' T • Mr. H. Kay Mr. H. Reith Mr. A. Brandon First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Administrative and Accounts Officer (Information). Mr. H. W. Speck, M.B.E. Mr. R. B. Smedley Administrative Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). Archivist. CHILE Mr. J. H. Leche, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. F. C. Mason ... Mr. C. D. Wiggin, D.F.C., A.F.C. Ambassador. First Secretary and Consul. Third Secretary. Mr. J. Currie Mr. C. W. Arning Mr. S. J. Lovell First Secretary (Commercial). Commercial Secretary (local rank). Market Officer. Mr. D. R. Dick, O.B.E Mr. R. H. Edmondson First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attach^ Hon. Assistant Naval Attache. Civil Air Attachd. Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). Captain W. G. Brittain, C.B.E., R.N. ... Commander F. V. Vaughan, R.N.V.R. (Retd.) Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C.... Mr. W. E. Oakley-Evans ... ' - f Mr. W. J. McLaughlin Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). CHINA Sir Ralph C. Skrine Stevenson, K.C.M.G. Mr. L. H. Lamb, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. J. M. Addis Mr. J. K. Drinkall ... ... Ambassador. Minister. First Secretary. Third Secretary. T/K 1 • 1 '• Mr. J. P. Coghill ... Mr. H. D. Bryan ... Mr. E. Youde Counsellor (Chinese Secretariat). First Secretary (Chinese Secretariat). Third Secretary (Chinese Secretariat)5 Country. CHINA (continued) Name. Mr. J. C. Hutchisor^ C.B.E. Mr. I. C. Mackenzie Mr. H. H. Thomas Mr. P. A. North Mr. D. McFarlane Mr. R. F. J. Harris Mr. R. L. Wood ... Mr. S. Knowles Mr. H. McAleavy Captain V. d’Arcy Donaldson ... Brigadier L. F. Field, C.B.E. ... Lieutenant-Colonel K. E. F. Millar, M.B.E. Lieutenant-Colonel G. P. Fawcett Major C. M. D’Arcy Irvine, M.B.E. Wing Commander C. W. K. Nicholls, O.B.E., D.S.O. Squadron Leader P. I. Howard-Williams, D.F.C. Mr. E. M. Hunt ... Miss E. M. Hinder Mr. W. G. E. Beckman Designation. &lt;. u . 1 . Minister (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Counsellor (Financial). Consul, Second Secretary (local rank). Vice-Consul, Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Information). v First Secretary (Information) (local rank). . Assistant Administration Officer and Accountant (Information). Editor (Information). Chinese Adviser (Information). Naval Attache. Military and Air Attach^. Assistant Military Attachd (Shanghai). Assistant Military Attachd. Assistant Military Attach^ (Peking). Assistant Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attach^ (Shanghai). Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Attache. Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). COLOMBIA ... Mr. G. MacKereth, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. G. H. S. Jackson Mr. L. A. Scopes, O.B.E. Mr. A. M. Turner ... Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. • - , yr ; First Secretary (Commercial) and Consul. Second Secretary (Commercial). Mr. L. Boas Mr. F. J. Allsopp ... First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Captain W. G. Brittain, C.B.E., R.N. ... Group Captain A. P. Bett Mr. C. A. Bryer ... ... ... Mr. G. 0. McEntee Mr. D. Reis Naval Attach^. Air Attach^. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Market Officer. Archivist and Accountant. COSTA RICA Mr. B. P. Sullivan, M.B.E. Mr. R. Bray Minister. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul (local rank). Naval Attach^ and Naval Air Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attach^. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O, D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mrs. W. Neus Archivist. CUBA ... Mr. J. L. Dodds, C.M.G, Mr. T. Brimelow ... Mr. R. P. Pinsent ... . Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery, First Secretary (Commercial) and Consul. Second Secretary. Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attach^. 35783 c* 26 Country. CUBA (continued). CZECHO SLOVAKIA DENMARK DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Name. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mrs. E. S. Mackenzie, M.B.E. ... Mr. P. J. Dixon, C.B., C.M.G. ... Sir Anthony Rumbold, Bart. Mr. A. J. Williams Mr. I. L. Henderson Mr. A. G. Spinks ... Mr. A. R. C. Bolton Mr. H. C. L. Gibson Mr. H. K. Ziegler ... Mr. R. A. F. Wallis Mr. L. L. Noquet ... ... , ... Commander (E) R. S. Hawkins, R.N. Lieut.-Colonel F. A. A. Blake, O.B.E. Captain G. D. M. C. Wheeler Group Captain W. H. Merton, O.B.E. Mr. P. T. G. Carlyon Mr. W. H. Taylor ... Mr. W. S. Forbes, M.B.E. Mr. J. R. M. Beardmore ... Mr. A. W. G. Randall, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. E. M. Rose Mr. F. J. Leishman Mr. L. Mitchell .... Mr. S. Simmonds Mr. L. E. Tudor Mr. J. L. Murray ... Commander (local Captain) R. Christian-Edwards Commander (E) H. G. R. Binning Lieut.-Colonel J. H. Mallard Group Captain W. R. Sadler Colonel N. Craig, D.S.O., O.B.E. Mr. P. H. Andrews Mr. R. Metcalfe ... Mr. R. Ede Mr. W. W. Wilson Reverend T. H. Croxall ... Mr. R. E. Bishop, M.B.E. Mr. H. R. Hambleton, M.B.E. ... Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Designation. .•fir Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist. Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (local rank). Head of Visa Section, First Secretary (local rank). Assistant to Head of Visa Section, Second Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (Information)’. Liaison Editor. Attach^ for Naval Questions. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attache. Social Secretary. Administration Officer. Archivist. Translator. Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Ditto. Counsellor (Commercial) and Consul- General. Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). S. Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache (Technical). Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Honorary Attache. Attach^ (Ministry of Food), First Secre tary (local rank). Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Agricultural Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Market Officer. Chaplain. Archivist. Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul. Naval Attache. Air Attach A Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank).D* 35783 7 Country. ECUADOR Name. Mr. J. E. M. Carvell Mr. A. H. B. Hermann Mr. J. Robertson, M.B.E. Captain W. G. Brittain, C.B.E., R.N. ... Group Captain A. P. Bett Mr. C. A. Bryer ... Mr. N. Pettigrew Designation Minister and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul (Head of Chancery). Vice-Consul and Second Secretary. Naval Attachd. Air Attache. Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist. EGYPT (Embassy) Sir Ronald Campbell, G.C.M.G., C.B. ... Mr. E. A. Chapman-Andrews, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. D. D. Maclean (designate) Mr. A. L. Mayall ... Mr. G. W. Courtney Mr. J. G. Tomlinson Mr. M. W. V. Maude Mr. R. H. G. Edmonds, M.B.E. Mr. T. C. Ravensdale Mr. F. H. Tomlyn, O.B.E. Mr. C. F. R. Barclay Mr. W. Morris (designate) Mr. VV. J. Johnson, C.M.G., O.B.E. Mr. A. N. Cumberbatch, C.B.E. Mr. W. S. Laver ... Mr. E. B. Dunipace Mr. P. Gent Mr. J. B. Flux, M.B.E. ... Mr. A. H. King iV^r. E. P. Wiltshire Mr. M. Henderson ... Mr. A. A. F. Haigh Mr. R. W. Parkes Mr. E. Main, M.B.E Major R. T. Landale Miss M. Gilruth Mrs. E. B. Ratz Mr. P. E. L. Fellowes Brigadier R. N. Thicknesse Major A. T. Fisher Air Commodore G. W. Hayes, O.B.E. ... Flight Lieutenant D. A. Stevenson Dr. E. D. Pridie, C.M.G., D.S.O., O.B.E. Mr. A. McDougall ... Mr. M. T. Audsley Wing Commander C. J. Lewin ... Mr. H. W. Gunningham, O.B.E. Mr. H. W. Fairman Mr. E. H. Avery ... Mr. W. E. Fuller ... Miss K. Nathan Ambassador. Minister. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank), Private Secretary to Ambassador. Third Secretary. Oriental Counsellor. First Secretary and Assistant Oriental Secretary. Second Secretary and Assistant Oriental Secretary. Ditto. Counsellor (Financial). Minister (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. Counsellor and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul. First Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul. First Secretary (local rank) and Head of Visa Section. Counsellor (Information). First Secretary (Information). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Press Officer. Ditto. Social Reform Officer. Military Attaehd. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attache. Assistant Air Attach^. Health Adviser, Counsellor (local rank). Legal Adviser, Counsellor (local rank). Labour Attachd, Counsellor (local rank). Civil Air Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Administrative Officer, First Secretary. Attache. Archivist. Archivist (Commercial). Archivist (Consular Section).8 Country. BRIliiSR MIDDLE EAST OFFICE ETHIOPIA ... FINLAND FRANCE (Embassy) Name. Designation. Sir John Troutbeck, K.C.M.G. ... Head of Office. Mr. J. W. Wall (designate) Mr. A. G. Maitland Mr. A. J. Wilton (designate) Mr. W. F. Crawford, O.B.E Dr. E. D. Pridie, C.M.G., D.S.O., O.B.E. Mr. M. T. Audsley ... Sir Herbert Stewart, C.I.E. Dr. J. Murray Mr. V. K. Maitland, C.S.I., M.C. Mr. A. R. Waterston, F.R.S.E. ... Mr. E. W. Noonan Mr. L. Waight Head of Political Section. First Secretary. Third Secretary. Counsellor (local rank), Head of Develop ment Division. Health Adviser. Labour Adviser. Agricultural Adviser. Statistical Adviser. Forestry Adviser. Entomological Adviser. Animal Husbandry Adviser. Petroleum Adviser. Financial Adviser. Mr. G! Wilson Mr. C. W. Courtness Temporary Administrative Assistant. Accountant. Archivist. Mr. D. W. Lascelles, C.M.G. Mr. W. B. C. Weld-Forester Mr. J. A. F. Gethin Mr. A. T. Curie, D.S.O., M.B.E. ... Mr. S. N. Sedeole ... Wing Commander C. J. Lewin ... Mr. C. T. McGurk Mr. 0. A. Scott, C.M.G., D.S.O. ... Mr. H. A. F. Hohler Mr. R. F. Muston Mr. W. J. S. Laing Mr. F. 0. A. H. Finney, M.B.E. Mr. L. L. Atkinson, M.B.E. Mr. L. H. G. Girling Mr. R. W. Cole ... Mr. D. R. Roper ... Mr. J. Brooke Colonel J. H. Magill Wing Commander D. H. Fleet, M.B.E. Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. First Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Second Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul. Civil Air Attache. Archivist and Accountant. Minister. First Secretary and Consul (Head of Chancery). Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Assistant Commercial Secretary (local rank). Secretary (local rank), Visa Officer. Ditto. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Military Attache. Air Attache. Mr. C. L. Thomas Mr. T. J. McGurk Mr. H. Dewdney Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist. Accountant. Sir Oliver Harvey, G.C.M.G., C.B. Mr. H. Ashley Clarke, C.M.G. ... Viscount Hood Mr. G. E. Millard Mr. R. A. Burrows ... Mr. F. G. K. Gallagher ... Mr. R. C. Hope-Jones Mr. H. B. McKenzie Johnston ... Miss B. M. Alison Mr. C. H. Bourke Borrowes Viscount Duncannon Mr. A. R. Fraser, C.M.G., M.B.E. Ambassador. Minister. Counsellor and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Ditto. Ditto. Third Secretary. Ditto (local rank). Third Secretary (local rank). Private Secretary to Ambassador, Secre tary (local rank). Minister (Commercial). Counsellor (Commercial).35783 d* 2 0 Country. Name. Designation. FRANCE Mr. K. Unwin, O.B.E. First Secretary (Commercial). (continued). Mr. W. I. Combs ... Second Secretary (Commercial). Mr. N. G. Beckett Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Mr. J. F. C. King Ditto. /-V Mr. R. H. Tottenham-Smith, C.B.E. ... Minister in Charge of the Consular Section. Mr. J. B. T. Judd First Secretary and Consul. Mr. H. J. Dorey, M.B.E. Third Secretary (local rank) and Vice Consul. Mr. A. L. C. Baton P.C.O. First Secretary (local rank). Mr. C. de Salis, M.B.E Assistant P.C.O. Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. P. F. D. Tennant, O.B.E First Secretary (Information). Mr. U. 0. V. Verney Assistant Information Officer, First Secretary (local rank). Mr. W. E. Curteis ... Press Relations (Information), Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. R. J. T. Griffin Broadcasting Officer (Information), Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. C. A. Whitney-Smith ... Provincial Posts Officer (Information), Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. C. P. Hope ... Administrative Officer, First Secretary (local rank). Captain C. D. Howard-Johnston, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Naval Attachd. Assistant Naval Attache. Cdr. (E) R. S. Hawkins, R.N. Ditto. Cdr. J. de F. Jago, R.N. ... Assistant Naval Attache (Air). Major-Gen. A. G. Salisbury-Jones, C.B.E., M.C. Military Attach^. Colonel B. A. Pearson, D.S.O. ... Assistant Military Attache. Major B. W. Pain Ditto. Captain W. R. L. Turp ... Ditto. Air Vice-Marshal R. A. George, C.B.E., M.C. Air Attache. Wing Commander W. G. Moseby, D.S.O., D.F.C. Assistant Air Attache. Wing-Cdr. P. J. F. Stephenson, D.F.C. ... Ditto. Air Marshal D. Colyer, C.B., D.F.C. ... 4 / 7 7 Civil Air Attach^. Mr. W. E. Davis, C.B.E Labour Attache, Counsellor (local rank). Mr. H. A. Bulpitt Assistant Labour Attachd, Second Secre tary (local rank). Mr. G. M. Herbert-Smith Representative of Ministry of Food, First Secretary (local rank). Mr. N. Smith Coal Attachd. Mr. A. Hartshorn ... Scientific Attachd (Ministry of Supply). Mr. J. C. D. Scarlett, O.B.E. ... Financial Adviser, First Secretary (local rank). Bishop Chambers ... Chaplain. Mr. J. K. Rooker, C.B.E., M.C Honorary Attache. Mr. T. H. Greene ... Ditto. Mr. A. S. Gilbert Ditto. Mr. R. J. Molland Superintending Archivist. Mr. W. V. Deacock Chief Accountant Mr. A. D. Morgan ... Archivist. Mr. J. G. W. Priestwood ... Accountant. Mr. E. J. Oddy Market Officer (Commercial Section). O.E.E.C., Sir Edmund Hall Patch, K.C.M.G. ... Permanent United Kingdom Representa PARIS tive on Organisation for European (U.K. Co-operation. Delegation) Mr. H. Ellis Rees, C.M.G Minister. Mr. J. E. Coulson, C.M.G Counsellor. Miss M. W. Dennehy Counsellor (local rank). Mr. C. T. Crowe ... First Secretary. Mr. D. F. Hubback , First Secretary (local rank). Mr. J. A. Turpin ... Second Secretary. Mr. C. W. Howard Second Secretary (local rank). . Mr. W. Price Ditto. Mr. A. D. Mallet ... Higher Executive Officer.10 Country. GERMANY ... (Frankfurt) (Liibbecke) GREECE GUATEMALA Designation. Mr. C. E. Steel, C.M.G., M.V.O. Mr. I. P. Garran ... Mr. D. S. Laskey ... Mr. J. E. Killick Mr. D. R. Ashe Mr. D. L. Stewart Mr. K. M. Wilford Mr. A. D. Wilson ... Mr. R. A. A. Chaput de Saintonge Mr. R. F. O’N. Bashford Major B. O’Leary ... Mr. B. C. L. Hockey Lieut.-Colonel R. C. Thomson, I.S.O., M.B.E. Mr. K. M. Duke Dr. W. H. C. Frend Mr. T. D. Williams Mr. L. W. Blackwell (designate) Mr. C. F. O. Gibson, M.B.E. Mr. C. D. W. O’Neill Mr. P. Pares Sir Clifford Norton, K.C.M.G., C.V.O. ... Mr. D’A. P. Reilly, O.B.E Mr. J. G. Tahourdin Mr. J. C. A. Roper, M.C. ... Mr. A. A. Duff, D.S.O., D.S.C Mr. C. N. Halkias, M.B.E Mr. N. D. Clive, M.C Mr. A. M. Rendel, M.B.E. Mr. P. Whinney Mr. R. S. Isaacson Mr. J. R. Wraight ... , Mr. A. G. R. Rouse, O.B.E. Mr. J. G. McMinnies Mr. R. T. Eland Mr. W. C. Scott, M.B.E. ... Mr. J. Lant Mr. A. L. Nicholson Colonel A. C. Shortt, O.B.E. Major J. T. Harington, D.S.O., M.B.E. ... Mr. F. Hampton ... Mr. F. R. G. Rudge Mr. W. Hillier, M.B.E Reverend D. A. Duncan ... Mr. G. W. R. Gilbert Miss J. E. Ridler Mr. W. H. Gallienne, C.B.E. ... Mr. C. C. A. Lee Mr. J. C. Jeaffreson Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Name. President of Governmental Sub-Com mission. Chief, Political Division. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Ditto. /p^ Third Secretary. Ditto. Head of German Political Branch. Head of Governmental Structure Branch. Press Officer. Head of Visa Section. Assistant Head of Visa Section. F.O./State Department Documents Unit. Assistant Editor, German War Docu ments Project. Ditto. Ditto. Administrative Officer. Archivist. First Secretary. First Secretary. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Counsellor (Financial). First Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Ditto. Consul and Administrative Officer, First Secretary (local rank). Assistant Administrative Officer. First Secretary (local rank) (Visa Section). Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Labour Attach^, Counsellor (local rank). Assistant Labour Attach^, Third Secre tary (local rank). Attach^ (Commercial). Chaplain. Archivist, Chancery. Accountant, Chancery. Minister and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Naval Attachd and Naval Air AttaohA Assistant Naval Attach^. Military Attach^.Country. GUATEMALA [continued). HAYTI HOLY SEE ... HONDURAS... HUNGARY ICELANu IRAQ ... Name. Wing-Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. H. Bradley Mr. A. C. Routh ... Mr. E. D. Watt, M.B.E Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. J. V. T. W. T. Perowne, C.M.G. Mr. J. S. Somers Cocks ... Miss E. K. Tindall ... Mr. R. J. Fowler Mr. A. T. Eades Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Acting Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. H. Laines Mr. A. K. Helm, C.M.G., C.B.E. Mr. W. H. Young Mr. H. F. G. Morris Mr. F. G. Burrett ... Mr. J. A. Ford, M.C. Mr. E. P. Southby Mr. C. H. Eborall ... Mr. H. T. A. Overton Mr. L. C. Pettitt ... Mr. H. F. Donner Mr. D. Wyndham Harris Commander J. W. F. D. Cowgill, R.N. ... Colonel B. R. Col will Lieut.-Colonel P. C. Capron Wing Commander W. M. Bisd^e Squadron Leader Y r . C. Otter, O.B.E. ... Mr. P. H. Munro-Faure ... Mr. A. H. Birch ... Mr. E. W. Marchington ... ... . ... Mr. C. W. Baxter, C.M.G., M.C. Dr. Clara G. Thornton Mr. F. J. Welham Mr. C. R. Wrigley ... Sir Henry Mack, K.C.M.G. Mr. H. Trevelyan, C.I.E., O.B.E. Mr. J. F. Brewis Mr. P. L. Carter Mr. D. A. Roberts ... Designation. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist. Minister and Consul-General. Consul and First Secretary (local rank). Naval Attache. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank) Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Registrar. Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. Naval Attache. Military Attache. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist. * Minister. First Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary. Ditto. First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Third Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (local rank), Head of Consular Section. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attachd. Assistant Air Attachd. Petroleum Attachd. Archivist. Accountant. Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary and Vice-Consul (local rank). Ministry of Food Representative. Archivist. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Third Secretary and Private Secretary to the Ambassador.12 Country. 1EAQ ... (continued). ITALY Name. Mr. L. F. Hooper ... Mr. J. C. B. Richmond ... Mr. G. G. Arthur ... Mr. F. H. Gamble Mr. W. Boyes Mr. C. Howson, M.C. Mr. A. M. Williams Mr. F. Wells Mr. G. N. I. Morrison Mr. C. P. Rossiter ... Lieut.-Colonel J. H. R. Orlebar . Mr. B. G. Barnard Reverend C. V. Roberts Mr. E. Farmer, M.B.E. ... Mr. J. O. Chubb ... Designation. Second Secretary (local rank). j Oriental Secretary (with local rank of Oriental Counsellor). Third Secretary (Oriental). Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). I / Third Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary and Consul. Third Secretary and Vice-Consul. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Military Attache. Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Honorary Chaplain. Archivist. Ditto. Sir Victor Mallet, K.C.M.G , C V O Mr. J. G. Ward, C.M.G Mr. M. S. Williams Hon. H. A. A. Hankey ... Mr. A. R. Moore ... Mr. D. V. Bendall Mr. C. L. Silvenvood-Cope Mr. F. W. Tooby ... Mr. A. D. Trounson Mr. W. N. R. Maxwell Mr. C. Empson, C.M.G Mr. J. 0. May Mr. J. G. Boyd Mr. C. H. Henderson Mr. J. P. Reeves ... Mr. K. C. Benton ... Mr. M. N. F. Stewart, O.B.E. ... Hon. E. B. C. Howard Captain J. D. Shaw-Hamilton, R.N. Commander (E) R. S. Hawkins Colonel G. A. C. Macnab ... Major J. M. Jourdier Major J. M. Pyne Group Captain A. G. Adnams ... Mr. W. H. Braine, C.B.E. Miss E. Lapthorn ... Mr. J. Mallet, M.V.O Mr. G. G. Hannaford Major C. Hayes ... Mr. M. C. Adams Mr. T. W. Glover, M.B.E. Dr. S. Cremona, O.B.E. ... Mr. C. T. Isolani ... Mr. D. F. N. Charles Reverend C. S. Powers ... Mr. A. T. Lamb, D.F.C. ... Mr. E. Hewitt Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Ditto. Third Secretary. First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Minister (Commercial). 1 ( irst Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary and Consul. First Secretary (local rank). Visa Officer. First Secretary (Information). Assistant Information Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache (Technical). Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Ditto. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, Counsellor (local rank). Ministry of Food Representative, Second Secretary (local rank). Attach^ and Private Secretary. Legal Adviser. Security Officer. Property Adviser, First Secretary (local rank). Administrative Officer. Assistant Administrative Officer. Head of Press Reading Section (Informa tion). Head of Features Section (Information). Films Officer (Information). Chaplain. Archivist. Accountant. L13 Country. Name. Designation. JAPAN /N Sir Alvary Gascoigne, K.C.M.G. Mr. I. T. M. Pink Mr. It. G. H. Watts Mr. H. C. Hainworth Mr. C. P. Scott, O.B.E. ... Mr. P. A. G. Westlake, M.C. . Mr. J. Quine Mr. P. V. St. J. Killick ... Mr. E. It. Lingeman, C.B.E. Mr. A. J. Goodman Mr. H. C. Lepper ... Mr. L. S. J. Hill Mr. C. H. Archer* Mr. L. Pickles Mr. K. A. Geary ... Mr. H. V. Redman, O.B.E. Mr. E. C. Blunden Mr. A. R. Boyce ... Mr. J. H. Ewing, O.B.E. ... Mr. J. L. Allaway Captain C. B. Tidd, R.N. Commander C. N. R. Barham, R.N. Sub-Lieutenant (S.) G. N. Shaw, R.N.V.R. Brigadier A. K. Ferguson, C.B.E. Tueut.-Colonel J. G. Figgess Group Captain G. R. Montgomery, C.B.E. Flight-Lieut. A. Bell Mr. E. G. Wilson ... Mr. A. D. Tarr Mr. J. M. Clague ... Mr. B. A. M. Buchanan ... United Kingdom Political Representa tive. Counsellor. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. First Secretary. Second Secretary. Ditto. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Economic Adviser. First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Counsellor and Head of Consular Section. First Secretary and Consul. Ditto. Counsellor (Information) (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank), Ditto. Counsellor (Purchasing and Selling). Attach^. Naval Adviser. Assistant Naval Adviser. Secretary to Naval Adviser. Military Adviser. Assistant Military Adviser. Air Adviser. Assistant Air Adviser. Labour Adviser to U.K.L.M. Shipping Adviser. Archivist. Accountant. LEBANON Mr. W. E. Houstoun-Boswall, M.C. Mr. T. E. Evans, O.B.E. ... Mr. C. N. Jupp Mr. M. Arab, M.B.E. Mr. W. J. M. Paterson Mr. R. H. Newall ... Mr. B. C. MacDermot Mr. W. G. Clifford Mr. E. J. Howes ... Mr. W. H. M. Hindle Lieut.-Colonel V. Major D. J. P. M.B.E. Mr. J. G. Hart .. C.M.G., Minister. First Secretary, Oriental Secretary. Second Secretary. Assistant Oriental Secretary, Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary and Consul. Passport Control Officer, Second Secre tary (local rank). First Secretary (Information). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Ditto. Military Attach^. Assistant Military Attach^. Attach^. Head Office of Consular Section, U.K.L.M., in Japan is at Yokohama. D’O. Harmar Beaumont-Nesbitt, 35783 e* 214 Country. LEBANON (continued). LIBEKIA ... LUXEM BOURG MEXICO NEPAL NETHER LANDS NICARAGUA... Name. Wing Commander C. J. Lewin Reverend H. Adkins Mr. H. C. Birtles, M.B.E. Mr. D. Marston Mr. J. Bowering Colonel N. Watson ... Colonel D. P. Fabin, M.B.E. Mr. T. C. Rapp, C.M.G., M.C Mr. A. C. E. Malcolm Mr. R. A. Daniell ... Mr. A. A. W. Landymore Mrs. D. H. Cockburn, M.B.E. ... Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C., R.N. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. N. R. W. Smith Lieutenant-Colonel Sir George Falconer, K.B.E., C.I.E. Lieutenant-Colonel R. R. Proud ... Mr. E. C. C. Crapp Sir Philip Nichols, K.C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. B. E. F. Gage ... Mr. J. H. Peck ... Mr. R. H. MacDonald Mr. J. H. Lambert Mr. L. B. S. Larkins, O.B.E. Mr. C. E. Emerson Mr. M. A. M. Robb Mr. J. O’Connor Howe Commander E. Neville, R.N. Commander R. S. Hawkins, R.N. Colonel R. A. G. Bingley, D.S.O., O.B.E. Group Captain J. Heber-Percy ... Air Marshal D. Colyer, C.B., D.F.C. Mr. A. Greenhough Mr. G. W. Ethall Mr. A. J. Allen, M.B.E Mr. N. O. W. Steward, O.B.E Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Mr. F. R. Jeffers ... Designation. Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Honorary Chaplain. Archivist and Accountant. Administrative Officer. , Minister and Consul-General. Chargb d’Affaires ad interim and Consul Military Attache. Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Information Officer. Assistant Information Officer. Naval Attachb. Air Attache. Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist and Accountant. Ambassador. First Secretary. Archivist and Accountant. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Third Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attache. Air Attachb. Civil Aviation Attache. Labour Attachd, First Secretary (local rank). Food Attache. Archivist and Accountant. Minister and Consul-General. Naval Air Attachb. Assistant Naval Attache. Air Attachb. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist.Name. Designation. Country. NOItWAi T /•s Sir Laurence Collier, K.C.M.G. ... Mr. E. E. Crowe ... Mr. W. K. Liversidge, M.B.E. ... Mr. H. F. T. Smith Mr. J. Inman Mr. L. C. S. Barber, M.B.E. Mr. J. C. Aird, M.B.E. Mr. D. M. Edwards Mr. K. Kenney, O.B.E Mr. G. R. Coate Captain R. E. D. Ryder, V.C., R.N. Lieutenant-Colonel K. G. Treseder, O.B.E. Wing Commander J. B. Coward ... Miss N. Bing, M.B.E. Mr. W. T. Smith Ambassador. Counsellor, Head of Chancery. First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Third Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul. First Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information). Naval Attache. Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Archivist, Third Secretary (local rank). Accountant. PANAMA Mr. J. D. Greenway, C.M.G. Mr. G. W. Kirk ... Mr. J. M. Leadbitter Captain J. Holmes, R.N. Commander (E) J. E. Best, R.N. Commander F. H. E. Hopkins, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson .. r Mr. H. Brace .... Minister and Consul-General. First Secretary and Consul. Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attach^ and Naval Air Attache Assistant Naval Attach^ (E). Assistant Naval Attach^ (Air). Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank) Archivist. PARAGUAY... Mr. J. R. M. Fell Minister and Consul-General. Captain I). E. Holland-Martin, D.S.O., Naval Attach^. D.S.C., R.N. . , ' , , Military Attache. Air Commodore H. E. Walker, M.C., Air Attache. D F C Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.F.C. ... Civil Air Attache. Mr. E. J. Toogood Labour Attache (resident in Buenos Aires). Mr. IT. G. Young Archivist and Vice-Consul. PERSIA Sir John Le Rougetel, K.C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. M. J. Creswell ... Mr. A. D. M. Ross Mr. C. T. Gandy Mr. M. F. Albrecht Colonel G. E. Wheeler, C.B.E., C.I.E. ... Mr. S. J. Whitwell, M.C Mr. J. Walker, O.B.E. (designate) Mr. D. A. Logan Major R. Jackson, M.B.E. Mr. D. W. T. Smithies Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Oriental Counsellor. Assistant Oriental Secretary, Second Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). Market Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (local rank) and Head of Consular Section. Third Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul.16 Country. Name Designation. PERSIA ... Mr. C. W. Hart, M.B.E. (continued). Colonel D. L. Betts, O.B.E., R.A. Wing Commander W. I. C. Inness Mr. B. G. Barnard Mr. K. J. Hird ... Dr. H. Cohen Mr. C. E. A. Carney, M.B.E. Mr. G. E. Anderson, D.F.C. hirst Secretary (Information) (local Ri rank). Military Attach^. Air Attache. Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Labour Attach^, First Secretary (l(f .] rank). Pi Embassy Physician. Archivist. Accountant. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I. Mr. A. L. A. Dredge, M.B.E. Mr. A. J. Johnson, M.B.E. Political Resident. Secretary. Administration Officer. Iiieut.-Colonel W\ J. Moody Medical Adviser to His Excellency the Political Resident and Chief Quaran tine Medical Officer, Persian Gulf. PERU Mr. W. St. C. H. Roberts, C.M.G., M C Mr. R. H. K. Marett, O.B.E. Mr. W. G. Bruzaud Mr. D. A. Malcolm Mr. R. J. Kirwin ... Mr. P. H. Barker Benfield Captain W. G. Brittain, C.B.E., R.N. Group Captain H. M. Pearson, C.B.E&gt; Mr. W. E. Oakley Evans ... Mr. H. Paton Johnson Mr. H. E. Skinner Ambassador. First Secretary and Consul (Head of Chancery). Eirst Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial). \ ice-Consul and Second Secretary. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attach A Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary flocal rank). Assistant and Accountant. Archivist. R PHILIPPINES Mr. L. H. Foulds, C.B.E. Mr. R. Milburn Mr. W. C. Hacon ... POLAND ... Sir Donald Gainer, K.C.M.G.' O.B.E. Mr. R. H. S. Allen Mr. A. J. Edden Mr. M. B. Winch ... Mr. D. F. Murray ... Mr. L. H. Massey Mr. J. P. Summerscale ... Mr. R. S. Smith Mr. J. H. Wolfe Mr. Jj. J. A. Parish Mr. J. Grant Purves Mr. P. N. Cleary-Fox Mr. F. Cox ... Mr. J. A. Riddell ... Captain J. H. Ruck-Keene, 0 B E D.S.C., R.N. * ‘ ' Lieutenant-Commander J. A. Holds- worth, R.N. Colonel T. A. H. Coltman Major R. G. Marshall, M.B.E. ... ’’’ Group Captain C. H. Turner Squadron Leader P. M. D. Bell, A.F.C. Minister. First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary and Consul. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary. Third Secretary (local rank). Counsellor. Second Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary, Consul (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Editor. Assistant Editor. S Naval AttachA Assistant Naval AttachA Military AttachA Assistant Military AttachA Air AttachA Assistant Air AttachACountry. POLAND (continued). % PO’RTUGAL ... ROUMANIA ... SALVADOR... Name. Mr. R. B. Kirby ... Mr. A. C. Maule ... Mr. D. G. Mitchell Sir Nigel Ronald, K.C.M.G., C.V.O. ... Mr. C. N. Stirling, C.M.G Mr. R. W. J. Hooper, D.S.O., D.F.C. ... Mr. N. C. C. Trench Mr. M. S. Henderson Mr. J. H. Lewen ... Mr. L. H. Dismore Mr. W. H. A. Gilman, M.B.E Mr. N. McNichol ... Mr. F. B. G. Bevan Mr. F. A. Wise Commander J. W. McClelland, D.S.O., R.N. Lieutenant-Colonel A. J. E. Gordon, M.C. Wing Commander G. T. B. Clayton, D.F.C. Mr. G. B. Taylor, M.B.E. Miss B. de Moura Mr. A. Holman, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. R. F. G. Sarell Mr. J. O. Wright, D.S.C. Mr. R. A. Hibbert ... Mr. C. W. Robinson Mr. A. C. Kendall, O.B.E. Mr. J. S. Bennett ... Mr. F. E. H. Bennett Commander J. W. F. D. Cowgill ... Colonel R. G. Turner Major C. O. I. Ramsden ... Wing Commander J. V. Hoggarth Squadron Leader P. C. Cleaver, O.B.E. Mr. P. H. Munro-Faure ... Mr. D. J. Lloyd Mr. H. N. Steptoe Mr. A. M. Earle Mr. S. M. Stadler, O.B.E. Commander C. E. A. Owen, D.S.C. Wing Commander K. P. Smales, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. R. Tennyson Designation. Labour Attache, First Secretary (local rank). Administrative Officer, Third Secretary (local rank). Archivist. Ambassador. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial) and Consul- General. Second Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Commercial Attach^ (local rank). Assistant Market Officer. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Military Attach^. Air Attachd. Assistant Air Attache. Archivist. Archivist (Consular Section). Minister. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. Ditto. First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary, Head of Consular Section. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attache. Petroleum Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist and Accountant. Minister and Consul-General. Second Secretary (local rank) and Vice- Consul. Commercial Attache and Vice-Consul. Assistant Naval Attach^. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank).18 Country. SAUDI AKABIA SIAM ... SINGAPORE... SOVIET UNION Name. Mr. A. C. Trott, C.M.G., O.B.E.... Mr. G. H. Clarke ... Mr. G. F. Rodgers Mr. M. W. Errock ... Mr. D. J. McCarthy (designate) Mr. R. E. Perfect ... Mr. W. J. Horne ... Mr. G. H. Thompson, C.M.G. ... Mr. R. Whittington, O.B.E. Mr. P. V. W. R. H. O’Regan Mr. S. H. J. Read Mr. B. J. Garnett ... Mr. A. C. Buxton ... Mr. D. A. Batwell Mr. D. C. Rivett-Carnac Mr. P. Wilkinson ... Commander D. F. Townsend, R.N. Colonel E. T. Heslop Wing Commander J. N. H. Whitworth, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. A. M. Berriff ... The Right Hon. M. MacDonald ... Mr. P. S. Scrivener, C.M.G. Mr. J. D. Murray ... Mr. R. G. Stone Mr. St. J. Donn-Byrne Major A. W. Alexander ... Captain Lord Kerr ... Mr. E. C. Van Helden Mr. W. R. Innes Dr. W. M. Clyde, C.M.G. ... Dr. H. W. Jack Mr. R. M. Hallows Mr. C. Whitworth, M.B.E. Mr. W. Hair, M.B.E. Sir Maurice Peterson, G.C.M.G. Mr. G. W. Harrison Mr. G. C. Whitteridge, O.B.E. ... Mr. G. M. Warr Mr. H. T. Morgan Mr. J. C. W. Bushell Mr. J. P. Waterfield Mr. H. Braham Mr. W. Barker Mr. H. A. Lungin ... Mr. H. M. Hayward Mr. P. J. Kelly Designation. Ambassador. First Secretary, Consul and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Third Secretary and Oriental Secretary, A Third Secretary. Archivist. Accountant. Ambassador. Counsellor and Consul-General. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. Third Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial). Commercial Assistant. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Naval Attachd. Military Attache. Air Attachd. Archivist. Commissioner-General for His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom in South-East Asia, with personal rank of Ambassador. Deputy Commissioner-General. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. First Secretary (Economic). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Assistant Information Officer. Private Secretary to Commissioner- General. A.D.C. to Commissioner-General. Commodity Officer. Ditto. Food Adviser. Agricultural Adviser. Security Officer. Head of Administration. Head Archivist. Accountant. Ambassador. Minister (local rank). First Secretary and Head of Chancery First Secretary. Second Secretary. Ditto. Third Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary. Third Secretary (local lank). Ditto. Ditto.Country. SOVIET UNION (continued). Name. Mr. J. Dobbs Lieutenant A. G. Howard, R.N. ... Lieutenant-Colonel F. R. Hulton, R.A. Air Commodore N. C. Ogilvie Forbes, O.B.E. Squadron Leader C. A. Alldis, D.F.C. ... Dr. M. T. Gillies Mr. S. L. Harrison Mr. V. Bulmer Mr. H. D. S. Bridge Mr. A. R. Johnstone Miss M. King Mr. J. C. Gamble ... Mr. S. F. Mullard Designation. Second Secretary (local rank) (Visa Officer). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attachb. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attache. Assistant Air Attachd. Physician. Security Officer. Attach^ (Commercial). First Secretary (local rank). Editor (Information). Assistant Editor (Information). Archivist. Accountant. SPAIN Mr. D. F. Howard, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. C. H. Johnston Mr. B. Malley, M.B.E. Mr. J. E. Galsworthy Mr. D. A. Bristow Mr. B. E. Wallace ... Mr. G. C. Pelham Mr. G. F. Hiller, D.S.O Mr. 0. T. Rayner Mr. W. B. Milton, M.B.E. Mr. D. Cameron Mr. E. U. Penrose-Fitzgerald, O.B.E. ... Mr. F. L. Adams Mr. R. Walter Mr. J. H. Thom Mr. N. E. Cox Cm dr. C. H. de B. Newby, R.N. Brigadier 0. C. B. Smith-Bingham Major E. J. Tonson-Rye Wing Commander J. W. Monk ... Professor W. F. Starkie, C.B.E. ... The Rev. H. Brown Mr. A. Fenner Mr. F. 0. Grant Mr. J. M. N. Jeffries Miss W. Bowen Miss G. McAleer Charge d’Affaires. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary (local rank). Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank). Third Secretary (local rank). Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank) (Head of British Government Purchasing Mission). Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary (Consular Section) and Consul. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). First Secretary (local rank), Visa Section. Attach^, Visa Section. Naval Attache. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Air Attache. Attach^ (British Council Representative in Spain). Attachb (Chaplain). Security Officer. Market Officer. Special editor (Information Department). Archivist (Chancery). Accountant (Chancery). SWEDEN . Hr. H. L. Farquhar, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. J. T. Henderson Mr. G. S. Littlejohn-Cook Mr. G. A. Urquhart, M.B.E. Ambassador. Counsellor. Second Secretary. Second Secretary (local rank).20 Country. Name. Designation SWEDEN (continued). SWITZER LAND SYRIA TRANS JORDAN Mr. H. L. Setchell, C.B.E. Mr. R. H. Traviss, M.B.E. Mr. M. A. Wenner Mr. M. A. Cope Mr. M. E. Taylor, M.B.E. Mr. J. I. McGhie ... Commander F. W. R. Darken, R.N. Commander (E) H. G. R. Binning, R.N. Lieutenant-Colonel R. H. Barry, O.B.E. Major Count P. F. de Salis Wing Commander M. Wyatt, D.F.C. ... Squadron Leader M. T. Whinney, M.B.E. Mr. C. D. Insall Mr. P. R. Williamson Mr. E. E. M. Nielsen Reverend C. H. Jones, M.A. Mr. R. L. Harris ... Mr. H. S. Langford Mr. T. M. Snow, C.M.G. ... Mr. T. S. Tull, D.S.O., O.B.E Mr. W. Harpham, O.B.E. Mr. Jackson Smith, M.B.E Mr. H. J. Legg Mr. P. R. Larke ... Mr. F. Dixon Mr. A. G. Michelsen Commander (E.) R. S. Hawkins, R.N. ... Lieutenant-Colonel G. S. Wilmot-Sitwell Wing Commander R. N. Smith, O.B.E. Lieutenant-Colonel H. N. Fryer Mr. S. J. Peskett ... Mr. E. A. F. Seaman Mr. P. M. Broa^mead, C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. C. A. F. Dundas, O.B.E. .. Mr. P. J. E. Male, M.C Mr. A. Halsey, M.B.E. Mr. J. E. P. Leslie Mr. W. Kirkpatrick Lieutenant-Colonel V. D’O. Harmar Major D. J. P. Beaumont-Nesbitt, M.B.E. Mr. T. H. Froebelius, M.B.E. ... Sir Alec Kirkbride, C.M.G., O.B.E., M.C. Mr. C. M. Pirie-Gordon ... Mr. W. F. H. Roblou Mr. E. W. Noonan Mr. C. J. Burgess ... Counsellor (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Third Secretary (Commercial). Assistant to Commercial Counsellor. First Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Information Officer. - j Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache (Technical). Military Attache. Assistant Military Attachd. Air Attache. Assistant Air Attache. Second Secretary (local rank), Head of Visa Section. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Attache (local rank) and Translator. Honorary Chaplain. Archivist. Accountant. Minister. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). Second Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Third Secretary (local rank), and Acting Consul (Consular Section). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Attache for Naval Questions. Military Attache. Air Attache. Attache. Market Officer. Archivist and Accountant. Minister. Oriental Secretary, First Secretary (local rank) and Head of Chancery. Third Secretary. First Secretary (Commercial) and Consul. Commercial Assistant and Vice-Consul (local rank). Information Officer. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attachd. Archivist and Accountant, Third Secre tary (local rank). Minister. First Secretary and Consul (local rank). Second Secretary and Vice-Consul (local rank). Petroleum Attachd. Archivist.Country. Name. Designation. TURKEY Sir David Kelly, K.C.M.G., M.G. Mr. H. M. Eyres Mr. A. C. I. Samuel Mr. H. P. L. Attlee Hon. R. J. M. Wilson Mr. T. G. A. Muntz, O.B.E Mr. A. H. Ballantyne ... , Major P. R. Reid, M.B.E., M.C. ... Mr. J. G. Whittall Mr. H. A. R. Philby Mr. W. Hickson ... Mr. W. E. D. Allen, O.B.E Mr. F. E. Red ward Mr. F. V. Michell ... Mr. A. Whittall Captain R. J. S. Brown, R.N Commander (E) F. L. Tewkesbury, R.N. Lieutenant-Commander G. V. Corbett, R.N. Brigadier C. S. Clarke, M.C. Major A. D. Ashley, M.B.E Air Commodore C. G. \\ igglesworth, C.B., A.F.C. Wing Commander S. N. L. Maude, O.B.E., D.F.C. Wing Commander P. A. L. Cooper Wing Commander C. J. Lewin ... Reverend C. W. Piper Mr. W. C. Brayne Ambassador. Minister. First Secretary, Head of Chancery. Second Secretary. Third Secretary. Counsellor (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). Second Secretary (local rank). First Secretary (local rank) (Istanbul). Second Secretary and Vice-Consul. First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Istanbul). Second Secretary and P.C.O. (Istanbul). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Ditto. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attach^. Ditto. Air Attache. Assistant Air Attache. Ditto. Civil Air Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Chaplain. Archivist. UNITED Sir Oliver Franks, K.C.B., C.B.E. STATES Mr. F. R. Hoyer-Millar, C.M.G., C.V.O. Mr. J. W. Taylor, C.M.G., M.B.E. ... Sir R. Gordon Munro, K.C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. J. H. Penson, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. F. G. Lee, C.M.G Ambassador. Minister. Minister (Commercial). Minister (Financial). Adviser on German Affairs. Minister (local rank). Mr. E. A. Cleugh, O.B.E., M.V.O. Mr. H. A. Graves, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. C. A. G. de J. Meade Mr. B. Cockram, C.M.G., O.B.E. Counsellor. Ditto. Ditto. C.R.O. Representative, Counsellor (local rank). Mr. W. D. Allen Mr. A. N. Morgan Mr. J. F. Ford Mr. T. E. Bromley Mr. J. A. Judson ... Mr. F. O. Darvall ... Sir Robert MacKenzie, Bart Lord Jellicoe, D.S.O., M.C. Mr. J. N. Henderson Mr. D. C. Tebbit ... Mr. P. Casson Mr. M. B. Thresher Mr. W. N. Storey, O.B.E. Mr. A. E. Percival Mr. J. E. Chadwick ... Colonel P. J. E. Rowell, O.B.E., M.C. ... Counsellor and Head of Chancery. Counsellor (local rank). First Secretary. Ditto. Ditto. First Secretary (local rank). First Secretary. Ditto. Second Secretary. Ditto. Ditto. Second Secretary (Private Secretary to Ambassador). Second Secretary (local rank). Counsellor (Commercial). Ditto. First Secretary (Eonomic). First Secretary (General Economic Department). Second Secretary (General Economic Department).Country. UNITED STATES (continued). URUGUAY Name. Miss L. M. Rainbow Mr. R. Thistlethwaite Mr. A. F. Maddocks Mr. G. E. McDougall Mr. C. B. Wilson ... Mr. H. F. A. Gates, M.B.E. Mr. W. P. N. Edwards Mr. N. W. H. Gaydon Mr. M. W. Pritchard Mr. G. Huson Captain J. Holmes, R.N. Commander (E) J. E. Best, R.N. Commander F. H. E. Hopkins, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Colonel G. E. Prior-Palmer, D.S.O. Group Captain R. C. Jonas, O.B.E. Squadron Leader J. N. Stacey, D.S.O., D.F.C. Mr. C. Clarkson, A.F.C. ... Mr. E. I. R. MacGregor Mr. E. E. Jones, O.B.E Dr. F. N. Woodward Mr. A. K. Longair Mr. A. McD. Gordon, C.M.G. Mr. I. Thomas Mr. R. R. B. Bannerman ... Mr. F. V. Cross Mr. A. N. Duckham, O.B.E. Mr. J. P. Macfarlan Mr. J. A. Young ... Mr. E. E. Sabben-Clare ... Miss I. F. M. Boyle, O.B.E. Mr. G. L. Payne ... Mr. W. F. Redmond, M.B.E. Mr. H. D. Hodgkinson Mr. G. S. McWilliam Mr. W. F. Oram, M.B.E. Mr. I. S. Robertson Mr. W. L. Tyson ... Mr. P. C. Pell Mr. F. R. D. Cutler Miss R. Ayley Mr. H. R. F. Brett, M.B.E. Mr. H. W. S. Cornish Mr. G. Lee Miss E. A. Symes Sir Gordon Vereker, K.C.M.G., M.C. ... Mr. P. G. F. Dalton Mr. Jocelyn Speck, M.V.O. Mr. D. R. Smith-Bingham Mr. C. G. Harris ... Mr. N. P. A. Swan Captain D E. Holland-Martin, D.S.O., D.S.C., R.N. Designation. Second Secretary (General Economic Department). Second Secretary (local rank) (General Economic Department). Third Secretary (General Economic Department). First Secretary (Raw Materials Sect*^ ). Ditto. Administration Officer. First Secretary (local rank) and Consul. Counsellor. (Head of British Informa tion Services). First Secretary (British Information Services) (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Second Secretary (Information) (local rank). Third Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attach^ (E). Assistant Naval Attach^ (Air). Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attach^. Assistant Air Attache. Civil Air Attach^. Assistant Civil Air Attache. Petroleum Attach^. Health Attache. Attach^ for Scientific Questions. Assistant Scientific Attach^. Labour Attach^, Counsellor (local rank). Deputy Labour Attach^, First Secre tary (local rank). Assistant Labour Attach^, Second Secre tary (local rank). Shipping Attache. Agricultural Attach^, Counsellor (local rank). Assistant Agricultural Attache. Ditto. Attache for Colonial Affairs. Attach^. Ditto. Head, Telegraphic Communications. First Secretary (local rank). Temporary Assistant. Higher Executive Officer. Civilian Staff Officer. Executive. Chief Clerk. Head Archivist. Staff Officer. Higher Clerical Officer. Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. Ambassador. First Secretary and Consul. Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. First Secretary (Commercial). Information Officer, Second Secretary (local rank). Naval Attach^.Country. URUGUAY ... [continued). VENEZUELA YUGOSLAVIA UNITED NATIONS (New York) Name. Air Commodore H. E. Walker, M.C., D.F.C. Group Captain D. S. G. Honor, D.I.C. Mr. E. J. Toogood Mr. S. G. Cornah ... Captain H. Cross, M.C. Mr. A. M. Dick Sir George Ogilvie-Forbes, K.C.M.G. Mr. J. Robinson Mr. A. O. Bray Mr. M. Gale, M.B.E. Mr. E. P. Lecours Captain B. J. Fisher, R.N. Group Captain A. P. Bett Mr. C. A. Bryer Mr. R. J. Farman Miss V. Redman ... Mr. A. W. Davidson Designation. Air Attache. Civil Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Assistant (Commercial). Acting Market Officer, Attach^ (local rank). Assistant to Commercial Secretary. Ambassador. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial) (local rank). First Secretary (Information) (local rank). Naval Attache. Air Attache. Labour Attach^, First Secretary (local rank). Archivist (Chancery). Archivist (Commercial Section). Accountant. Sir Charles Peake, K.C.M.G., M.C. Mr. C. E. King Mr. E. S. Keyser, M.B.E. ... Mr. D. Floyd Mr. D. P. S. Cape Mr. D. A. H. Wright Miss C. E. Ludlam Mr. D. G. Crichton Commander W. W. Fitzroy, R.N. Lieutenant M. J. Connor, R.N.V.R. Lieutenant-Colonel C. H. Dewhurst, O.B.E. Major L. T. Tomes Air Commodore F. Beaumont ... Mr. A. S. Hindle Miss H. M. Bird, M.B.E. The Right Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan, G.C.M.G., K.C.B. Mr. V. G. Lawford, M.V.O. Mr. P. S. Falla Mr. A. R. K. MacKenzie ... Mr. J. W. Hamilton Sir James Chadwick, F.R.S. Mr. H. M. Phillips Mr. R. T. D. Led ward Mr. J. T. Fearnley Ambassador. First Secretary (Head of Chancery). Second Secretary (local rank). Ditto. Third Secretary. First Secretary (Commercial). Third Secretary (Commercial). First Secretary and Consul (local rank). Second Secretary (Information). Naval Attache. Assistant Naval Attache. Military Attache. Assistant Military Attache. Air Attache. Attach^. Administration Officer. Archivist and Accountant, Third Secre tary (local rank). Permanent United Kingdom Representa tive to the Security Council, and United Kingdom Representative on the United Nations Atomic Energy Com mission. Counsellor. First Secretary and Head of Chancery. First Secretary in Charge of Public Relations. Private Secretary to Permanent United Kingdom Representative. Scientific Adviser and Alternate Repre sentative on Atomic Energy Com mission. Counsellor for Economic and Social Affairs. First Secretary. Third Secretary.UNITED NATIONS (New York) (continued) UNITED NATIONS (Geneva). Mr. B. Cockram, C.M.G., O.B.E. C.R.O. Representative, Counsellor (local rank). Mr. D. L. Cole C.R.O. Representative, Second Secre tary (local rank). Mr. J. E. S. Fawcett, D.S.C. Counsellor, Legal Adviser. Mr. H. A. Cooper ... Administrative, Finance and Establ^^- ment Officer. Mr. C. Winson Staff Officer. Mr. 0. R. O’Rafferty Higher Clerical Officer. Mr. E. G. Harman Assistant Administrative Officer. Mr. F. W. Cooper ... Archivist. Mr. E. R. Warner, O.B.E. Head of United Kingdom Delegation. Mr. R. D. Thrupp ... Second Secretary (local rank). Mr. E. C. Gamble, M.B.E. Ditto. Mr. E. A. D. Smith Archivist. CORPS OP INSPECTORS Senior Inspector: Mr. A. B. Hutcheon, C.M.G., M.B.E. Inspectors: Mr. A. S. Paterson, C.M.G., O.B.E. Sir Andrew Noble, Bart., C.M.G. Mr. G. C. Allchin, C.M.G., M.C. Mr. D. L. Busk, C.M.G. ■ Mr. D. V. Staines, O.B.E.29 / Williamson, P. R., Stockholm. Wilmot-Sitwell, Lieut.-Colonel G. S., see Sitwell. Wilson, C. B., Washington. Wilson, E. G., Tokyo. Wilson, G., B.M.E.O., Cairo. Wilson, W., Rome. Wilson, W. W., Copenhagen. Wilson, Hon. R. J. M., Angora. Wilton, A. J., B.M.E.O., Cairo. Wiltshire, E. P., Cairo. Wind***. B., Warsaw. Winson, C., U.N., New York Wise, F. A^, Lisbon. Wolfe, J. H., Warsaw. Wood, R. L., Nanking. Woodward, Dr. F. N., Washington. W'raight, J. R., Athens. Wright, D. A. H., Belgrade. Wright, J. O., Bucharest. Wrigley, C. R., Reykjavik. Wj'att, Wing Commander M., Stock holm. Y Young, E. E., Buenos Aires Young, G. K., Vienna. Young, G. P., Rio de Janeiro. Young, H. G., Asuncion. Young, J. A., Washington. z Ziegler, H. K., Prague. Guide to countries in which places (in index) are situated Place. Addis Ababa Amman ... Angora ... Asuncion Athens ... Bagdad ... Bahrein ... Bangkok Beirut Belgrade Berlin Berne Bogota ... Brussels Bucharest Budapest Buenos Aires Cairo Caracas ... Ciudad Trujillo Copenhagen Damascus Guatemala Havana ... Helsingfors Jedda Kabul Katmandu L*a Paz ... Lima Lisbon ... Country. Place. Ethiopia. Madrid ... Transjordon. Managua Turkey. Mexico City Paraguay. Monrovia Greece. Montevideo Iraq. Moscow ... Persian Gulf. Nanking ... Siam. Oslo Lebanon. Panama ... Yugoslavia. Paris Germany. Port-au-Prince ... Switzerland. Prague ... Colombia. Quito Belgium. Rangoon Roumania. Reykjavik Hungary. Rio de Janeiro ... Argentine Republic. Rome Egypt. San Jose Venezuela. San Salvador *... Dominican Republic. Santiago Denmark. Sofia Syria. Stockholm Guatemala. Tegucigalpa Cuba. Tehran ... Finland. The Hague Saudi Arabia. Tokyo Afghanistan. Warsaw ... Nepal. Vienna ... Bolivia. Washington Peru. Yunnanfu Portugal. Spain. Country. Nicaragua. Manila ... Philippines. Mexico. Liberia. Uruguay. Soviet Union. China. Norway. Panamd. France. Hayti. Czechoslovakia. Ecuador. Burma. Iceland. Brazil. Italy. Costa Rica. Salvador. Chile. Bulgaria. Sweden. Honduras. Persia. The Netherlands. Japan. Poland. Austria. United States. China.I I I I4 Country. Chile— continued. China Name. Designation Residence and Telephone Number. i i Senor Don Pedro Enrique Alfonso ►£&lt; Commercial Counsellor ... Villa d’Arno, 5, Albany Park Road, Kingston-on-Thames. J Senor Don Horacio Suarez ... 1st Secretary Flat 45, 60, Park Lane, W. 1 . GliOsvenor 2897 Senor Don Hefr4n Silva ... Secretary ... 6 , Bourdon Street, ^Ll. MA Y/air ,Wr 8 Commander Kaare Olsen ... * Naval Attach^ 3, South wick Street, W. 2. PADdington 6868 Squadron Leader Anibal Solmtnhiac * Air Attache Flat 5, Audley House, 9, North Audley Street, W. 1 . Senor Don Gonzalo Mera ... * 3rd Secretary 24, Matlock Court, Netting Hill Gate, W. 11. PARk 4611 Senor Don Jose Antonio Gandarillas* Secretary ... 14, Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, S.W. 3 . Senorita Carmen Gandarillas ... (Daughter) FLAxman 3695 Senor Don Calixto Rogers ... ❖ Attach^ 44, Mitcham Lane, S.W. 16. SI 1 Reatham 8544 His Excellency Dr. Cheng Tien -Hsi Ambassador Extraordinary 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Miss Cheng Ying-Wan * and Plenipotentiary WELbech 6794 • • (Daughter) Dr. Tuan Mao-Lan ... * Minister-Counsellor 10, Lansdowne Road, W. 11 . PARk 6263 Dr. Seymour C. Y. Cheng ... ... Counsellor 49, Portland Place, W. 1 . Mr. Tan Pao-shen * Counsellor, 1 st Secretary... Flat 161, Rivermead Court, Miss Tan Sien Fen (Daughter) S.W. 6 . RENoivn 2696 Mr. Ghen Yao-sheng o * 1st Secretary 32, Maxwell Road, Northwood, Middlesex. Northwood 2134 Mr. Lee Yone-Ming... * Ditto 114, Green Lane, Northwood, Middlesex. Northwood 2374 Mr. Ho Sze-ko * Ditto 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Wang Ting-Shan * 2nd Secretary Ditto. Mr. Kuan Chuan-Tsai 3rd Secretary Ditto. Mr. Lee En-Kuo ... 3rd Secretary and Attach^ to the Embassy Ditto. Mr. Kwoh Tseh-ching ... Ditto 10, Stanley Gardens, W. 11. PARk 7593. Mr. Chao Chin-Yung * 3rd Secretary “ Collingwood,” Joel Street, Pin ner, Middlesex. PINner ‘ibll Mr. Wan Moo Chou... ... Attache 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WEI.beck 5794 Mr. Wang Shih-Yong * Ditto 36, Goldhurst Terrace, N.W. 6 . Mr. Liu Ying-Tsun ... * Ditto 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WELbech 5794 Mr. Tai Erh-ching ... * Ditto Ditto. Mr. Lai Tien-Chang... ... Ditto Ditto. Mr. Fan Kuang-Tao * Ditto 39, Highbury Hill, N. 5. Mr. Liu Wei-Hsiung Ditto 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 5794 Mrs. Lee Liang Yin Lang ... o o Ditto Ditto. Colonel Han Tsun-Chang ... * Military Attache ... 138, Hurley Street, W. 1. WELbeck 0744 Major Liang Piao-Chang * Assistant Military Attache Ditto. Colonel Lai Ming-tong o © • • • * Air Attach^ Ditto. WELbeck 0715 Major Choong Tsain-Chow ... * Assistant Air Attache Ditto. Commander Chen Tsui-Tsang * Acting Naval Attache Ditto WELbeck 0926 Dr. Wang Cliing-Chun* * Commercial Counsellor ... Mount Royal Hotel, Marble Arch, W. 1. MA Yfair 8040 Dr. Yui Ming Press Counsellor ... 152 Haven Green Court, W. 5. PE Rival c 5918 Dr. Chen \\ ei-cheng * Counsellor, specially at tached 182, Kew Road, Richmond, Surrey. Richmond 1592 * Married, but not accompanied by wife.24 * Married, but not accompanied by wife. Country. .Name. Designation. Besideuce and . Telephone Number. Venezuela— continued. Senor Bacalao Lara ... 2nd Secretary 96, Park Line, W. 1. Senorita Miriam Blanco-Fombona... Special Attache ... 7, Cumberland House, Kensing ton Court, W. 8. Yugoslavia His Excellency Monsieur Obrad Ambassador Extraordinary 24, Harrington Gardens, S.W. Oicmil and Plenipotentiary [Offices of the Embassy: 25, Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400] Dr. Franc Kos ... ... Counsellor... 25, Kensington Gore, S.W.7. KENsington 3400 Monsieur Hugo Havlicek* ... Commercial and Financial Counsellor 195, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Dr. Josip Presburger ... ^ Secretary (Consular Dept.) 25, Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400 Monsieur Miroslav Milutinovic ^ Secretary ... Ditto. Monsieur Velimir Kodica ... Ditto Ditto. Lieutenant-Colonel Vangel Cuka- Military, Air and Naval Ditto. levski Attache [Office: 195, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 5439 and 3400] Lieutenant-Colonel Mate Jurcic Major Bade Trosi ... Assistant Military Attachd Assistant Military, Naval and Air Attach^ 195, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Monsieur Avram Adanja ... Assistant Commercial A ttach^ 25, Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. Monsieur Branko Japundzic ^ Ditto Ditto. Monsieur Jovan Jovasevic ... Financial Attach^... Ditto. Mine. Desanka Bilic Attach^ Ditto. [Office : 195, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400] List of Persons no longer included in the foregoing List but still accepted by His Majesty’s Government as personally possessing Diplomatic Privileges Name. Bank. Besidence and Telephone Number. His Excellency Monsieur August Envoy Extraordinary and 167, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Torma ►P Minister Plenipotentiary KENsington 5473 and 5474 Monsieur Ernst Sarepera* . . Counsellor of Legation, let Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Charles Envoy Extraordinary and 87, Eaton Place, S.W. 1. Zarine * Minister Plenipotentiary SLOane 2564 Monsieur Teodots OzoliqS . .. * Counsellor of Legation ... Ditto. Monsieur Olgerts Bozitis 3rd Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Balutis* Bronius Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary 17, Essex Villas, W. 8. Monsieur Vincas Balickas .. * Commercial Counsellor, Acting Counsellor of Legation Ditto. Monsieur i’etras B. Varkala * Agricultural Attach^ 105, Hilltield Court, Belsize Park, N.W. 3. PRlmrosc 17974 Country. Chile— continued. China Name. Designation Kesidence and Telephone Number. Senor Don Humberto Videla * Minister-Counsellor Flat 7, 24, Lowndes Street, Sefiorita Mercedes Videla • • . (Daughter; Commercial Counsellor ... S.W. 1. SLOane 9724 Senor Don Pedro Enrique Alfonso^ Villa d’Arno, 5, Albany Park Senor Don Horacio Suarez ... 1st Secretary Hoad, Kingston-on-Thames. Flat 45, 60, Park Lan^W. 1. Senor Don Hefr6n Silva ... Secretary ... GROsvenor 28w Commander Kaare Olsen ... * Naval Attache 3, Southwick Street, W. 2. Senor Don Gonzalo Mera ... ❖ 3rd Secretary VADdington 6868 24, Matlock Court, Netting Hill Sefior Don Jose Antonio Gandarillas* Secretary ... Gate, W. 11. PAlik 4611 14, Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, S.W. 3. Senorita Cdrmen Gandardlas ... (Daughter) FLAxman 3695 Senor Don Calixto Kogers ... * Attachd 44, Mitcham Lane, S.W. 16. His Excellency Dr. Cheng Tien-Hsi Ambassador Extraordinary STReatham 8544 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Miss Cheng Ying-Wan * and Plenipotentiary WELbeck 6794 • • . (Daughter) Dr. Tuan Mao-Lan ... * M i nister-Counsellor 10, Lansdowne Hoad, W. 11. Dr. Seymour C. Y. Cheng ... ... Counsellor PARk 6263 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Tan Pao-shen * Counsellor, 1st Secretary... Flat 161, Hivermead Court, Miss Tan Sien Fen • • . (Daughter) S.W. 6. RENown 2696 Mr. Chen Yao-sheng * 1st Secretary 32, Maxwell Hoad, Northwood, Mr. Lee Yone-Ming... * Ditto Middlesex. Northwood 2134 114, Green Lane, North wood, Mr. Ho Sze-ko * Ditto Middlesex. Northwood 2374 Mr. Wang Ting-Shan * 2nd Secretary 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Kuan Cbuan-Tsai 3rd Secretary Ditto. Mr. Lee En-Kuo 3rd Secretary and Attachd Ditto. Mr. Kwoh Tseh-ching to the Embassy Ditto 10, Stanley Gardens, W. 11. Mr. Chao Chin-Yung * 3rd Secretary PARk 7593. • “ Collingwood,” Joel Street, Pin- Mr. Wan Moo Chou... Attache ner, Middlesex. PINner 3617 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Wang Shih-Yong * Ditto WELbeck 5794 36, Goldhurst Terrace, N.W. 6. Mr. Liu Ying-Tsun ... •b Ditto 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Mr. Tai Erh-ching ... * Ditto WELbeck 5794 Ditto. Mr. Lai Tien-Chang... ... Ditto Ditto. Mr. Liu Wei-Hsiung ... Ditto Ditto. Mrs. Lee Liang Yin Lang ... o o ... Ditto Ditto. Colonel Han Tsun-Chang ... * Military Attache ... 138, Harley Street, W. 1. Major Liang Piao-Chang * Assistant Military Attache WELbeck 0744 Ditto. Colonel Lai Ming-tong * Air Attach^ Ditto. Major Choong Tsain-Chow ... * Assistant Air Attachd WELbeck 0715 Ditto. Commander Chen Tsui-Tsang * Acting Naval Attache Ditto Dr. Wang Ching-Chun* Commercial Counsellor ... WELbeck 0926 Mount Royal Hotel, Marble Arch, Dr. Yui Ming * Press Counsellor ... W. 1. MA Yfair 8040 152 Haven Green Court, W. 5. Dr. Chen Wei-cheng * Counsellor, specially at- PERivale 5918 182, Kew Hoad, Richmond, * Married, but tached not accompanied by wife. Surrey. Richmond 159224 * Married, but not accompanied by wife. Country. .N ame. Designation. Residence and Telephone Number. Yugoslavia His Excellency Monsieur Obrad Oicmil Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary 24, Harrington Gardens, S.W. [Offices of the Embassy: 25, Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. KEN sing ton 3400] Dr. Franc Kos * Counsellor... 25, Kensington Gore^^W.7. KENsington . X)0 Dr. Milivoje Perovic * Commercial and Financial Counsellor Ditto. » Dr. Josip Presburger * Secretary (Consular Dept.) Ditto. Monsieur Miroslav Milutinovic * Secretary ... Ditto. Monsieur Yelimir Rodica ... * Ditto Ditto. Lieutenant-Colonel Vangel Cuka- Military, Air and Naval Ditto. levski * Attache [Office: 195, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 5439 and 3400] Lieutenant-Colonel Mate Jurcic Major Rade Trost * Assistant Military Attach^ Assistant Military, Naval and Air Attach^ 195, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Monsieur Avram Adanja ... * Assistant Commercial Attach^ 25, Kensington Gore, S.W. 7. Monsieur Branko Japundzic* Ditto Ditto. Monsieur Jovan Jovasevic ... ... Financial Attach^... Ditto. Mine. Desanka Bilic ... Attachd Ditto. [Office: 195, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. KENsington 3400] List of Persons no longer included in the foregoing List but still accepted by His Majesty’s Government as personally possessing Diplomatic Privileges Name. Rank. Residence and Telephone Number. His Excellency Monsieur August Envoy Extraordinary and 167, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Torma * Minister Plenipotentiary KENnngton 5473 and 5474 Monsieur Ernst Sarepera* . . Counsellor of legation, 1st Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Charles Envoy Extraordinary and 87, Eaton Place, S.W. 1. Zarine * Minister Plenipotentiary SLOane 2564 Monsieur Teodots OzoliijS . .. * Counsellor of Legation ... Ditto. Monsieur Olgerts Rozitis 3rd Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Balutis* Bronius Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary 17, Essex Villas, W. 8. Monsieur Vincas Balickas .. * Commercial Counsellor, Acting Counsellor of Legation Ditto. Monsieur Petras B. Varkala * Agricultural Attach^ .;. 105, Hilltield Court, Belsize Park, N.W. 3. PEJmrose 17974 Country. Chile— continued. China Colombia ... Name. Designation Kesidence and Telephone Number. Commander Kaare Olsen * Naval Attache Senor Don Gonzalo Mera * 3rd Secretary Sefior Don Jose Antonio Gandarillas* Senorita Cdrmen Gandarillas ... Senor Don Calixto Rogers ... Secretary ... (Daughter) Attach^ 3, Southwick Street, W. 2. PADdington 6868 24, Matlock Court, Netting Hill Gate, W. 11. PAPk 4611 14, Cheyne Walk, Chels&lt;^S.W. 3. FLAxman 3695 44, Mitcham Lane, S.W. 16. ST Peat ham 8544 His Excellency Dr. Cheng Tien-Hsi Miss Cheng Ying-Wan * Dr. Tuan Mao-Lan ... * Dr. Seymour C. Y. Cheng ... .. Mr. Tan Pao-shen * Miss Tan Sien Fen • • Mr. Chen Yao-sheng * Mr. Lee Yone-Ming... * Mr. Ho Szo-ko * Mr. Wang Ting-Shan * Mr. Kuan Chuan-Tsai ... Mr. Lee En-Kuo ... Mr. Kwoh Tseh-ching .. Mr. Chao Chin-Yung * Mr. Wan Moo Chou... Mr. Wang Shih-Yong * Ambassador E x traordin ary and Plenipotentiary (Daughter) Minister-Counsellor Counsellor Counsellor, 1st Secretary... (Daughter) 1st Secretary Ditto ... ... Ditto 2nd Secretary 3rd Secretary 3rd Secretary and Attach^ to the Embassy Ditto 3rd Secretary Attach^ Ditto 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeclc 5794 10, Lansdowne Road, W. 11. PARk 6263 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Flat 161, Rivermead Court, S.W. 6. RENown 2696 32, Maxwell Road, Northwood, Middlesex. NoxJthwood 2134 114, Green Lane, North wood, Middlesex. Northwood 2374 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Ditto. Ditto. 10, Stanley Gardens, W.ll. PARk 7593. “ Collingwood,” Joel Street, Pin ner, Middlesex. PINner'dbll 49, Portland Place, W. 1. IVEl.beck 5794 36, Goldhurst Terrace, N.W. 6. Mr. 1 An Ying-Tsun ... Mr. Tai Erh-ching ... Mr. Lai Tien-Chang... Mr. Liu Wei-Hsiung Mrs. Lee Liang Yin Lang ... Colonel Han Tsun-Chang ... ; Major Liang Piao-Chang Colonel bai Ming-tong Major Choong Tsain-Chow ... Commander Chen Tsui-Tsang Dr. Wang Ching-Chun* Dr. Yui Ming Dr. Chen Wei-cheng * * * * * * * * * Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Military Attache ... Assistant Military Attache Air Attach^ Assistant Air Attach^ Acting Naval Attachd Commercial Counsellor ... Press Counsellor ... Counsellor, specially at tached 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 5794 Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. 138, Harley Street, W. 1. WELbeck 0744 Ditto. Ditto. WELbeck 0715 Ditto. Ditto WELbeck 0926 Mount Royal Hotel, Marble Arch, W. 1. MA Yfair 8040 152, Haven Green Court, W. 5. PERivalc 5918 182, Kew Road, Richmond, Surrey. Richmond 1592 His Excellency Senor Dr. Don Ambassador Extraordinary Domingo Esguerra and Plenipotentiary Senor Antonio Angel Escobar ...i Counsellor... * Married, but not accompanied by wife. 63, Cadogan Square, S.W. 1. SLOane 1526 [Chancery: SLOane 8352] Ditto.24 List of Persons no longer included in the foregoing List but still accepted by His Majesty’s Government as personally possessing Diplomatic Privileges Name. Rank. Residence and Telephone Number. His Excellency Monsieur August Envoy Extraordinary and 167, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. Torma ^ Minister Plenipotentiary KENsington 5473 and 5474 Monsieur Ernst Sarepera* ... Counsellor of legation, 1st Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Charles Secretary Envoy Extraordinary and 87, Eaton Place, S.W. 1. Zarine ♦ &gt;{&lt; Minister Plenipotentiary SLOane 2564 Monsieur Teodots OzoliijS ... Counsellor of Legation ... Ditto. Monsieur Olgerts Roziti* 3rd Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Bronius Envoy Extraordinary and 17, Essex Villas, W. 8. Balutis* Monsieur Vincas Balickas ... ^ Minister Plenipotentiary Commercial Counsellor, Ditto. Monsieur Retras B. Varkala Acting Counsellor of Legation Agricultural Attach^ 105, Hillfield Court, Belsize Park, N.W. 3. PRlmrose 1797 * Married, but not accompanied by wife.Country. Chile— continued. China Colombia ... Name. Commander KaareOlsen ... ^ Senor Don Gonzalo Mera ... Seftor Don Jose Antonio Gandanllas* Senorita Carmen Gandardlas ... Senor Don Calixto Rogers ... ►£» His Excellency Dr. Cheng Tien-Hsi Miss Cheng Ying-Wan * Dr. Tuan Mao-Lan ... * Dr. Seymour C. Y. Cheng ... • • Mr. Tan Pao-shen * Miss Tan Sien Fen Mr. Chen Yao-sheug * Mr. Lee Yone-Ming... * Mr. Ho Sze-ko * Mr. Wang Ting-Shan * Mr. Kuan Chuan-Tsai 1 ... Mr. Lee En-Kuo ... Mr. Kwoh Tseh-ching ... Mr. Chao Chin-Yung * Mr. YVan Moo Chou... ... Mr. Wang Shih-Yong * Mr. Liu Ying-Tsun ... ►P Mr. Tai Erh-ching ... * Mr. Lai Tien-Chang... ... Mr. Liu Wei-Hsiung Mrs. Lee Liang Yin Lang ... ... Colonel Han Tsun-Chang ... * Major Liang Piao-Chang ... Colonel Lai Ming-tong * Major Choong Tsain-Chow ... * Commander Chen Tsui-Tsang * Designation Residence and Telephone Number. Naval Attach^ 3rd Secretary Secretary ... (Daughter) Attach^ 3, Southwick Street, W. 2. PADdington 6868 24, Matlock Court, Netting Hill Gate, W. 11. PABk 4611 14, Cheyne YY r alk, Ch^^ea, S.YV. 3. FLAxman c &gt;5 44, Mitcham Lane, S.W. 16. STReatham 8544 Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary (Daughter) Minister-Counsellor Counsellor 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 6794 10, Lansdowne Koad, W. 11. PARk 6263 49, Portland Place, W. 1. Counsellor, 1st Secretary .. (Daughter) 1st Secretary Ditto Ditto Flat 161, Kivermead Court, S.W. 6. RENown 2696 32, Maxwell Road, Northwood, Middlesex. Nortlnvood 2134 114, Green Lane, Northwood, Middlesex. Northwood 2374 2nd Secretary 49, Portland Place, W. 1. 3rd Secretary Ditto. 3rd Secretary and Attach^ to the Embassy Ditto 3rd Secretary Attache Ditto Ditto. 10, Stanley Gardens, W. 11. PARk 7593. “ Collingwood,” Joel Street, Pin ner, Middlesex. PINnerZbll 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WELbcck 5794 36, Goldhurst Terrace, N.W. 6. Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Military Attach^ ... Assistant Military Attache Air Attach^ Assistant Air Attache 49, Portland Place, W. 1. WELbeck 6794 Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. 138, Harley Street, W. 1. WELbeck 1491-4 Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. Acting Naval Attache Ditto Dr. Wang Ching-Chun* Dr. Yui Ming Dr. Chen YVei-cheng ... Commercial Counsellor ... ►p Press Counsellor ... Counsellor, specially at tached Mount Royal Hotel, Marble Arch, YV. 1. MA Yfair 8040 152 Haven Green Court, W. 5. PERivale 5918 182, Kew Road, Richmond, Surrey. Richmond 1592 His Excellency Senor Dr. Don Ambassador Extraordinary Domingo Esguerra and Plenipotentiary Senor Antonio Angel Escobar ...i Counsellor... * Married, but not accompanied by wife. 63, Cadogan Square, S.W. 1. SLOane 1526 [Chancery: SLOane 8352] Ditto.24 v ► List of Persons no longer included in the foregoing List but still accepted by His Majesty’s Government as personally possessing Diplomatic Privileges Name. Rank. Residence and Telephone Number. - His Excellency Monsieur August Envoy Extraordinary and 167, Queen’s Gate, S.W. 7. 5474 Torma * Minister Plenipotentiary KEJSsinyton 5473 and Monsieur Ernst Sarepera* . Counsellor of Legation, 1st Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Charles Envoy Extraordinary and 87, Eaton Place, S.W. 1. Zarine * Minister Plenipotentiary SWane 2564 Monsieur Teodots Ozoli^S . * Counsellor of Legation Ditto. Monsieur Olgerts Rozitis 3rd Secretary Ditto. His Excellency Monsieur Balutis* Bronius Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary 17, Essex Villas, W. 8. Monsieur Vincas Balickas . * Commercial Counsellor, Acting Counsellor of Legation Ditto. Monsieur Petras B. Yarkala * Agricultural Attach4 105, Hillfield Court, Belsize Park, N.W. 3. PEImrose 1797 * Married, but not accompanied by wife.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000392_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1424</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000392</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1424</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Pol Ext 8428/49 'Foreign Office Lists: representatives of foreign states and commonwealth governments in London'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-30T23:51:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (131 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 133; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains a series of booklets that are lists of permanent and temporary officers of the British Foreign Service at consular posts, but also those of representatives of foreign states and commonwealth countries in London. The lists are organised by country, include most dignitaries, officers, and attaches of the respective country's diplomatic mission, and cover the years 1948 and 1949.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Military liaison</topic></subject><subject><geographic>London</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000392#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>