<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000236_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T16:33:03.300Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">^O' c&gt;tV C (o (i i. i*?/? THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. I 4th April 1943. ■ &gt; PA-822 E. B. Wakefield, Esq., His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Reference our recent discussions, the Company would very much appreciate the privilege of being allowed to send and receive telegrams to and from its New York Office in code and/or cypher. This privilege would greatly facilitate the Company's operations. It is tentatively proposed to use the Company's code with a superimposed cypher. An early reply would be much appreciated. Yours W. P. Anderson Chief Local Representative The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. WPA; SW 2Confidential Ko. 0/476 Political policy, Bahrain, the 7th April 1943. Political A To The Honourable the Political eaident in the Persian C ?ulf f Camp Bahrain* i » ,, ,i wwlOM o copy of o letter No. P'-82S Jpted the 4th j ril 1943 which I have received from the Bahrain Petrolemn Company Liaited. 2. The great majority of th'i Company's cables to New York involve references, direct or Indirect, to questions ox personnel, food supply, oil production, shipping, tools and machinery, etc. Censorship in Bahrain ensures that Infornation of potential use to the enes^y is not sent by Cable and ireless but this restricts to a degree which the ompany find most embarrassing the scope of the references which they can male to New York. 3. Cables from the Company to New York, other than those &gt;hlch can without objection be sent en clair, may be divided into two categories t- (1) security cables, i.e. cables con taining information which is not secret and could not by iw self be of direct use to the enemy, but which, taken in con- Junction with other information available to the enemy, mirht prove useful to him; and (2) secret cables i.e. cables cc^ taining information which would be of direct use to the 4. If the Company's present proposal is approved they would continue to send secret cables through the Navy or, occasionally, if political matters were beintf discussed, through the Political Agent. They wish, however, to send security cables by means of a secret Company code which would have, for purposes of further security, a transposition cypher superimposed, lioch cables, I should add, which deal mainly with technical oil matters, cannot conveniently be transmitted in service codes. 5- ^he Company have, of course, no objection to all their cables bein&gt;; censored in Tiahrain before transmission. 6. It is understood that if the Company are permitted to transmit messages in code from Bahrain the United States authorities will agree to their reception at the other end. 7. I shall be grateful to be informed as soon as possible what reply 1 should send to the Company's reference. 1 trust that I may be authorised to give a favourable reply. enemy. Sd/- E. Be Wakefield Political Agent, Bahrain./ troa &gt;oiitioal ilcaiaant, at Bahrain, ro Svart tary of State for India, London. Joiiea to OoT«rnwtnt of India, Senior Haral ^flctr, JrtriBian Gulf. Z -alf oro«. &gt;olitioHl A^tnt, Bahrain. llo.T/303. J&gt;ated 9th April 1943. iaiualn oil aabi^a to K«w yoiK fall Into three olas^es (a) jiti Jlair tranaeitted tiirou^i Catle und ^ireleee. C^neoruhlp at Bahrain ariiiuree that inforwatlon of potential uee to the eneny la not Inoluded in this olaas. (b) Security' cable a, containing iuforniatioii which ie not in itaelf aecrct but which in conjunction with other information zsl^ht be ueeful to the eneoy (c) secret cables, containing matter of direct uae to the enerQr • {h) and (o) have hithsrto baen tranmittcd •Ithar throi«h the HaTal author! tie a or the Political Agency* 2* Oonpany find that censorship on (a) greatly reatrlcts scci e of reference a which they can make to Be* York and request penolaulon to exchange telegrams with Hew York In secret Comiai^ code with transposition cypher superimposed for security. It Is understood that If pennlsslcn la acocrded for transmission of auch messages frosi Bahrain the United States authorities would agree to their reception at destination. Keaaagee con cerned deal mainiy with teohnical oil siattevs, which cannot aon-reuiently be transniltted in ^errloe codes. Cca^ai^y would continue to trausiiiit nessages falling In class (c) through Nawal ^thorltleft oi', oaoaslonally, if political matters VConfidential No. C/617 / / .V Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th May 1943. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, A Plecse refer to your letter No. PA-822 dated the 4th April 1943 regarding the proposal to use a secret Company code for transmitting your cables to New York. 2. There is no objection to transmission of Company messages to New York in the Company^ secret code, provided that (a) All secret messages, i.e. messages containing information which would be of direct use to the enemy, especially those containing information relating in any way to movements of ships, parti cularly tankers, continue to be sent through the Navy, or if political matters are involved, through me; and (b) A plain language version of all messages transmitted in the Company^ secret code is supplied to the 3. Will you please signify your acceptance of these conditions, and let me know when the new procedure comes into operation. Censor Yours truly, Politica ^gent, Bahrain. Cupy sent oo i . .. under i .L. No, -/ 61^ dated Gth i.lay 1943t /( The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. &gt; C ONFI DiLNT IAL C/PA~50 E. B. Wakefield, Esq., His Britannic Mggesty f s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir, 8th May, 1943 V v A ' . N-V r s / x - (/ V a $.7 Please refer to your letter No. C/617 dated the 6th May 1943 regarding the use of a secret Company code. Before giving formal acceptance to the proposals stated in your letter I wish to refer the matter to the Company^ Principals in New York. . ^ , T am attaching a telegram which T would appatreciate your sending via your facilities to New York. On Receipt of their reply T will advise further. Yours ver W. P. Anderson Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. WPA:SW Attach: 1Awali, 8th May 1943. (■ / DONALD HANNA BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY / NEWYORK FROM WARD ANDERSON begins: 360 HAVE NOW RECEIVED WRITTEN APPROVAL' TO USE'COMPANYS SECRET CODE ^VITH FOLLOWING RESERVATIONS (ONE} / MESSAGE^ CONTAINING INFORMATION OF / DIRECT USE TO THE ENEMY ESPECIALLY INFORMATION RELATING'IN i \NY WAY TO' SHIPS MOVEMENTS ETCETERA TO BE SENT THROUGH ^AVAL^CHANNEL'S AS AT PRESENT (TWO) MESSAGES REGARDING POLITICAL MATTERS''TO BE SENT THROUGH POLITICAL AGENT (THREE) ■ PLAIN LANGUAGE VERSION OF ALL MESSAGES TRANSMITTED VIA PROPOSED COMPANY CODE TO BE'SUPPLIED TO LOCAL CENSOR (STOP)' MODIFIED ' COMPANY CODE AS SUGGESTED BY YOU'IS ACCEPTABLE (STOP) THESE REGULATIONS^ SATISFACTORY WITH ME ' (STOP) PLEASE ADVISE SOONEST IF ^SATISFACTORY YOUR END / AND IF SO WHEN MAY WE EXPECT ^COMMENCE THIS SYSTEM message ends 'STelegram Inter. From Political Resident, Bushire. To PAIFOH:E, Baghdad. Repeated Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf* Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1129 Dated 20th received 21st May, 1943. ' T* &amp;r4 Your telegram X2/6931 May 13th. 2. Bahrain Petroleum Companyi private code has not repeat not been vetted. 3. Grateful if SNCPG could arrange for Naval Officer in Charge to do so. NCJ - BR1TCONSUL - / X* J^/ 310/1 Telegram Prom To No. 365 Dated the 25th May, 1943 Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Buahire 5^ / £;.|o Your telegram 1129 May 2uth. / 7&gt; Following Is repetition of PAIPOHCE telegram No. X2/9773 May 21st addressed Political Agent Bahrain begins: Your 1129 • • • • • arrive. Ends. 2. Company are awaiting instructions from New York regarding method of using code in conjunction with cypher, way 1 accept PAlFCmCE offer when material is ready for examination ? - POLITICAL - NCJS. o. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depa rtment. SECRET. EXPRESS LETTER a [N, B % — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent ly post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if if had been telegraphed, / u save time and formalities it is wdXied and yiyned as if it had been so des'patched.] &lt; 0 ^ / F rom To Political Resiaent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• Political Agent, Bahrain. No, 447-3. Go ci e. Dated the 28 th May |3&gt; W43 , Your telegram No«365 dated 25tli May 1.943* BAPCO 2. Paiforce offer may be accepted. .M Sd. C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. MFP—1211 S^P—(M-2312)—7-5-41 400.000.r7 saCRET EXPRESS LETTEP From Political Agent, Bahrain. To PAIPORCE No C/742 Dated the Slat my 1943, Reference your telegram No. X 2/9773 dated; ny ^Ist in which you suggested that a Cypher Security ( f^icer o your Command should vet the private code which the Bahrain Petroleum Company propose to use for York. (Political Resident 1 s telegram No. 1129 dated the 20th May 1943 refers). 2. Your suggestion is accepted with thanks, ihe Company have not. however, received details of the cypher ^hich i is proposed to use in conjunction with their private code. I will inform you as soon as full details of the system to be used l^y the Company are available. Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 \ c # Political Agency, No. C/743 Bahrain, the 31st May 1943. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to his express letter No. 447-S dated the 28th May 1943. £ &lt;r♦ . J/o Tekegram Inter* From Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Basra. To PAIC, Baghdad. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. / Political Agent, Bahra in. No* 06452 Dated 1st received 3rd June, 1943. Further to 1521 May 21st United States Naval Observer has now given me a personal assurance he has confirmed from Washington that all traffic routed to ? W S L New York is fully censored. NCJ - SNOPG - /yf SO' j/&lt;rTelegram From To ■Repeated No. 0859z Dated 11th received 12th^uli ■ Inter Ordinary (1936 cypher) Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf. P.A.I.C. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent Secret ^nut. Laenx, Busnire. it, Bahrain. Q ' h iwi ejuxy, 1943. I \ -Smnt . this code NCJ Concur your 181745 June fliut. Regret I have no officer qualified to vet - NAVYCHARGE BASRA -I ? ■ ' n Ko #0/1498. Political Agency, Bahrain, 3rd November 1943. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd., Bahrain, MEMORANDUM % i£ C4eneral Headquarters, PAX FORCE have now intimated that it would be difficult to release the Cypher Security Officer to visit Bahrain at present. They suggest that a copy of the Code should he sent hy safe hand to Baghdad for their examination. 2. If you see no objection, I propose to send my copy of your Code by safe-hand by the first opportunity. {tt/H Political Agent, Bahrain. tyc''N C/PA-10S 5.'ji jiAiiitilXiJ EEBJOI^uy UuiIPAi'.i LUilEal) Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Culf His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agen Bahrein, Dear Sir, CODES File 009.34 The contents of your letter C/1498 of the 3rd November are noted and I fully concur with your suggestion. Yours very truly, Date November 4 1943 \ R. i , &gt;* ■ for W. P. Anderson Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd,I S. 13i20f. rS r&gt; NAVAL MESSAGE. rs For use in Cypher or Coding Office oihly Oiriginators Instructions ; (Indication of Priority, Personal, NOTWT For Exercise). Intercept Group. TO: • From: — .... - —— , Cook or Table to be used for Initials of Time of Receipt in Cypher or Coding Office, Date. Cyphering or Codmg. Recyphering or Receding. Cypherer or Coder St 2002 A. H. Pbttifer, Actino Govt. Printer.Subject CIVIL CODBS /Personal Political Agent BAHREIN 5 ■SCIGT Tel 92 PAI Force / 9/1/x * 5 Nov 43 Ref your Ilemo G/1 544 of 10 Nov 43* 1 * The Code proposed for use by the California Texas Oil Goopany Ltd has been examined and it is considered that it offers such small resistance to organized cryptography that it has no security value whatsoever. It is, therefore l recoisnended that permission to use this Code for messages which may be of any value to the enemy, should not be granted,, Early confirmation of this would be appreciated. 2m The code is being returned by safe hand under separate cover* iVon Brigadier. S. 0. in G. (L.R.0. WATSON, Lt. Col.)Political v^ent, Bahrain Political ^esidont, Bahrain (ly hand) Retaxandom, London 820 4th December 1943. 7*1 My telGgra/n No ,^72 vjctobor 8th, ^ 2. Security v^ficcr P.AI^O'^B considers thit tho uil ComDany , s proposed code which he has vetted offers such small resistence to organized cryptography that it has no security value wh*tso- ever and therefore recommends that permission to use this code for nurooses originally intended should not be granted. 3. hay I inform Company accordingly? PolitiaalSECRET Political Agency, No .C/l r 58. Bahrain, 18th Doc ember 1943. To The Chief Local RepresentntiTe, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd.,, Bahrain. , m y * uFMWAmm Raference my memorandum No.C/1498 dated the 3rd November 1943. 2. Scrutiny by our military security authorities has revealed that the code offers such small resistenc® to organizad cryptography that it has no security value r/hntso- ever anil as such I fear it should not be used for the purposes originally intended. /?!&lt;$,-u Political Agent, Bahrain.f THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED c^ c0 ' Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. loll SECRET 24th December, 1943 3&gt; G/PA-112 H.B.M* s Political Agent, The Agency, Manama. CODES Ir File 009.54 Dear Sir, I have noted the contents of your letter No. C/1758 dated December 18th 1943. C, I am informed that the code in question was allocated for the Company's use by the United States Navy Department and also that codes of this type are regarded in U.S. Military circles as being among the most secure known and that such codes are used for the most secret messages. In view of this, I am somewhat surprised to hear of the findings of your military security authorities. Possibly the authorities who examined the code do not understand that each page of the pad of sheets is used only once and destroyed. Thus the code is never repeated, in fact the code changes with each succeeding letter of the message; when the pad of sheets is exhausted, it is necessary to procure another set of pads. Further, this particular code is intended to be used exclusively by the Company between Bahrein and New York so that any one sheet or part of a sheet is used for one message only. It would seem unlikely that your military security authorities are not fully familiar with the correct use of this -^ype of code but before I report their findings I wish to check this point in order to avoid possible embarrassment. I will be pleased if you would verify the above point at your earliest convenience since, if indeed the code is insecure, the United States authorities will be anxious to know about it as soon as possible. Yours very truly. W. P. Anderson Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. WPA:SW10/1. Telegram From TO repeated to /A o. //; Secretary of otate for ^nclin, Loiidoa* ' i'olitical Hesident, Bushire, Political .-.^Gnt, Irhrain. Senior 1 aval Officer in the Persian Gulfj H.i ' s Ambassador, In. ,hdad for P .m.I.e. No. 29462. Dated 27th received 28th lecenber, 1943. si Reference your telejram To. T/1246 of December 6th and Political Agent, Bahrain telegram No. 820, s tat-in.: that Security Cfficer I . . .T.C. reported that the Bahrain Petroleum Conpany's code had no security value. United Itates Chief of Cnble Censorship hns urgently requested permission for this code to be used which he underst-nds' is r one time, pad similar to that used by the I inistry of ar Transport in London. Grateful for your observations and those of P .A.I .C. r..D. - Retax^ndum - If $ /. Date of despatch , List of enclosures. - DEPARTMENT /OFFICE. File No. Serial No. _ Letter _ g-- Draft Memorandum 0 Telegram No. IMPORTANT Political w ^ Bushiro. Reference Secret? rv of State for T India's telegram No.29462 dated 27th December. 2. I confirm that code is a one time pad. The Chief Local Hepresentative has Informed me that the'code was allo cated to the Company by the United States Navy Department. Political (Aporoved by P.^.) r. S-5 (Small) B. P. C7G7/A/S-79 — 2 5-5 -42—50,000 pads. ^ tkx. tUwu*, fytrb/ /, I'. 1' 5-^ 0 V 79/53. Telegram S« From Political Resident, Buehire. To India Offioe 9 London. Repeated P.A.I•0* Baghdad. Senior Nayal officer, Persian Gulf. No• 31. Dated 4th January 1944. Your 29462 December 27th. ^ political Agent confirma coda ie one way pad and was allocated to Company by U.o.a . Navy Department* As pad is apparently similar to that used by M.i.T. there does not appear to be any objection from political point of fiew to its use. - BRITG016UL - 3BQRKT. No.12«S. British Residency &amp; Oonaulate*General, Bush ire, the 4th January 1944. A dopy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrai n, with reference to Bahrain telegram fto.89t dated the 29th December 194 3. m ASECRET No.C/89. To olitical Acency, Bahrain, 12th January 19^14. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. ^ . mio.tuig) r JM Reference ypiiir memorandum No.C/l768 dated the 18th December 1943. 2. The objection to the use of the Code has now been withdrawn on the understanding that the pad is not worked through more than once. 3. Will you please inform me from what date you propose to put the Code into use. m i /m( Political Agent, Bahrain.c 10/1 Telegram From To Repeated No. 1032 India Office, London. Political He^ident, B'^shire. P.A.I.C. (through Britconsul Baghdad) Political Agent, Bahrain. Senior N-val Officer Persian Gulf, Basra. Dated 15th received 15th January, 1944. , s vi Your telegram 31 January 4th. Bahrain Petroleum Company may be informed objections to their code are v;ithdrawn with proviso pad is never v-orked through more than once. - RETAXANDUM - NCJ t K. V 0 ; 5a 'S /• *4THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 0 ^ Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, 15th January, 1944. CONFIDENTIAL C/FA)117 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agen The Agency, Manama. Dear Sir, CODES File 009.34. £ Thank you for your memorandum No. C/89 of the 12th January 1944 on the above subject. The Company will commence using this system as from today (January 15th 1944) and will conform to the restrictions and procedure as outlined in Mr. Wakefield*s letter No. C/617 of May 6th 1945. In connection v/ith the stipulation that a plain language version of all such messages shall be supplied to the local Censor, the Company proposes to send these to you unless it is advised to the contrary. Yours very truly, for W. P. Anderson Chief Local Representative The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. It A' No. PA/14 \ V v va VA January 17, 1944. W His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. File 009.34 $ Dear Sir, Further to my letter No. C/PA/117 of 15th January, I attach hereto a plain language copy of the Company's cable No.302 to its New York Principals, the code version of which was sent to Cable and Wireless this afternoon. It is appreciated that the contents of this message are fairly innocuous and the message is being sent more as a test case than for security reasons. Yours very truly, ?. AHDERSON Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COIvIPANY LIMITED. Attach ,——10/1 fcs Telegram From To Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire India Office, London Government of India, New Delhi P.A.I.C. \ 1 S Political .gent, Bahrain, r 1 No. 62 Dated 17th January 1944. IMPORTANT Reference India Office telegram No.8538 dated 30th April 1943. Bahrain Petroleum Company cables to Ne/' York. 2. Code brought into use from 15th January repeat 15th January subject to restrictions and procedure outlined in telegram under reference. PoliticalPRINTED IN U. 8. A. Outgoing Telegram Class of Service: CODE! TO BAHREIN PETROLEUM COT. NEW YCRK. FORM BP 122 ( IOOM-1 1-»8) \vfc Awali, Bahrein date Jan. 17, 1944. dept . Production. No.302 - Tour 318: Hay© only three 87 foot derricks not erected; can release two now and one when rehabilitation underway, (stop) Would ship derricks complete with relegs in good condition approximate cost handling and preparing #175.00 each; shipment in wired bundles, no lumber for boxing. - WARD ANDERSON -PA-2^6 The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 22nd. August, 194-5. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Manama. BAHREIN . Dear Sir, Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. y.f. Date..A Sub.lect: Codes and Cables . File; 009.^4 At the outbreak of hostilities in 1939 we received instructions from our New York office that for the duration of the war we would not be permitted to use the company ! s private cable code between this office and those of London and New York. We have recently had advice from our New York office that they expect to commence the use of the company^ code again shortly and I presume that the necessary clearance has been, or is being, obtained from the appropriate authorities. Would you kindly advise whether there is any local objection to the company resuming the use of it's private code on the same basis that it was operated before the war. With the resumption of the code in question the use of the present cypher.which has your approval,would, I presume be discontinued. Yours very ^rul w .P.ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.^ -oCP h \&lt; the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, PA-^41 31st January, 194-6• r\ His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, The Agency, Manama• CODES AND CABLING File 009.34 Dear Sir: Reference is made to your letter No, C/89 of the 12th January, 1944, assenting to the use of the Company's Code, two copies of which were handed to you by Mr. R. M. Brown or the 19th October, 1943• It'is presumed that under present conditions you have no further use for these two copies, and if you agree the Company will appreciate the return of them. Yours very truly. W. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ConfidentiaL BAHRAIN RECEIPT.No .c/172. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 13th February 1946. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain ^troleum Coi, Ltd., \ B-a h r a i n . Dear Sir, Thank you for your letter No. PA-341 dated the 31st January, 1946. 2. I should be grateful if you would send one of your staff to collect the documents. He could let me have a receipt at time of taking them over. Yours faithfully. NS. Political Agent, Bahrain.c*'* -oO lo l THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 5rO l8tb February, 194-6 Received from His Britannic Mejesty T s Political Agent two copies of a cypher, the property of the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, W. P. ANDERSON it| CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED totifideatial. BAHRAIN' RECEIPT.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000236_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/423</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000236</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/423</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/5 BAPCO CODES'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (54 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order. There is an index at the end of the file (folios 51-52). The index is arranged chronologically and refers to documents within the file; it gives a brief description of the correspondence with a reference number in blue or red crayon, which refers back to that correspondence in the volume.</extent><extent>The foliation begins at the first page of writing and runs through to 53, which is the inside of the back cover of the file.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and telegrams between the Political Agent in Bahrain, the Political Resident in Bushire and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited on the use of a cypher code for their cable communications with New York and on the agreement of the code.There is an index at the end of the file (folios 51-52).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Ḥamad bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah, Hakim of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Bahrain Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia Sa'ūd bin 'Abd al-'Azīz Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000236#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>