<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000225_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:07:26.438Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">With tha ©f th« Under Socretary of State &amp; • U3« &amp;• O-ll^ * [This Document is the Property of Hi8 a Britannic-Majesty’s Government, and should be kept It is recommended that a suitable announcement should be broadcast in English and, if you wish, in other European languages but not (repeat not) at present in Persian programme, stating that Pensmark, the Danish Minister to Persia and Iraq, has severed relations with the German-controlled Government in Copenhagen. Reference should be made to similar action by Kauffman at Washington in 191-0. The Danish Minister’s action follows Germany* s complete disregard for terms originally imposed on Denmark and Germany's recent action in forcing Denmark to renounce political neutrality as evidenced by recognition by Copenhagen of Croatia and Manchukuo and particularly by severance of relations with Russia. These actions show clearly the strength of German pressure on Denmark and give a false view of the country’s real feelings. Only Danes abroad can speak freely for their country. For these reasons Fensrnark has declared that he will represent the Government of Free Denmark which originally appointed him to Tehran and will contribute to the common cause with the help of the Danish technical experts and other Danes in the Middle East. t [Cypher]. FROM PERSIA . FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Sir R. Bullard. No. 1156. THth November, 19V1. D. 9 # 30 p.m. 18th November, 194-1. R. 7.55 a.m. 19th November, 1941. vvvvvvv INDIV.fTVv £ • U) • R • ojf^- ( y E-YSV» 3 S^ 3 ^ FILE COPY l [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government, and shook [CYPHER] 7 nn A 1 o **/ CM fcuQ.t6 y 7390 POLITICAL DIS'iElBUTIONi, Under Sec mr Fereift* Affaifa FROM; PERS! K W1 «* 1941 FROM ;TEER,\N TO FOREION OFFIC E, Sir R, Bullard Nor 1143 D a 10 rt 20 p c m., 15th November, 1941. R„ 11c55 aoiiic 16th November, 1941. 15th Hovenber, 1941, Vtobf attex* ftKAxh* Repeated bo Tovernment of India No. 942 1 . . 1 r ' Bagdad No, 477. 0 0 0 0 Your telegram No,, 922nob rnpeatal to Bagdad.F• o*^ —' With the straport of the Soviet and British representatives the Danish Charge d‘Aifaires informed the Persian Government that he proposed to break-off relations with the German- controlled Government at Copenhagen while remaining representati^ of the free and independent Danish Government which^appointed him^ The Minister for Foreign Affairs has given him oral assurance* in the name of the Cabinet; that ne may remain here as the Danish Charge d T Affaires and that the Persian Government will not recognise any other person as Danish representative. 2. Mr. F, has telegraphed to his Government to this effect and when the telegram has had time to reach Copenhagen he will give me a statement to be broadcast from London and Delhi* He will duly inform the Iraqi Government to which he is also accredited., RECo. POL, DEPt, HN0Vi941 INDIA OFFICE^rrr' ' n('« W ^ M ■ l\ - . OUTWARD TELEGRAM XjU mL.T*' - [This Document ia the Property of His Britannic Majasty’s Governme nt, and shoald be kept under Lock and Key.] vO “ r( S41 © [This telegrain is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on]. (E 6669/5326/54) [Cypher]. WAR CABINET DISTRIBUTION , To: PERSIA SECRET j^rora FOREIGN OFFICE To TEHRAN . No. 922 17th October, 1941. D. 9,15 p.m, 17th October, 1941. Repeated to Government of Indip No, 15084 WWW IMEDIATE . Your telegram No. 1001 [of 15th October: Danish Chargd d 1 Affaires]. As Soviet Government are now prepared to support Danish Chargd d'Affaires, you may certainly do likewise, e 9 g. on lines proposed in your telegram No, 931 [of 7th October], 2, I suggest that, provided your Soviet colleague agrees, you might arrange for Danish Chargd d'Affaires to assure Persian Government, in return for their recognition of his independent status, that he is entirely independent of the Danish Government in Copenhagen/ will have no connexion with Denmark and will confine his activities to representing the Danish colony in Persia. / J iW 7 ;- /o (tibu £ (obLcfjSij- C /l/- / CtfpjL (X-j AJL^.Y/v s With the Camplimants of the Linger 9»©r^ta^y of State for Foreign Affairs *«OCT 194J ^P^ 0 + e ^ eg 5 a vf ■'■5u 0 ^ P^f t i9 u -'- ar secrecy and should he retained hy the authorised recipient and not passed on.] [Cypher] WAR CABINET DISTRIBUTION FROM: PERSIA. •SHCftf-j- FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Sir R. Bullard No&gt;951 , 7th October, 1941 D, 2.30 p*m. 7th October, 1941. R. 4.45 p.m. 7th October, 1941. Repeated t o Government of Indiac. [][][] / U u ‘ &gt; ' telegram Noc898. ■PrvMn ( ^ , 4^ : ^ a: ^ res ^ as received reply from Danish Minister in Washington advising him to thf 0 Dan^h S o lan Gove ™ en l of h ' s independenceof*^ the Danish Government and saying that the United S+afpq ^cu^fhP r e rea ^ y to support S him at Moscow to approval of the Soviet Government. Charg^ d Affaires would like independent status of his 3 ®ti°? tobe acknowledged by the Persian Government be mfq?h?P 0U n treat y- That will hardly ?? the Persian Government are not ^^t^ftty txred of for ever making fresh concessions +h» l^t^At-K^t^ 1118 ln retur n, but if so instructed the Soviet Ambassador and I could inform the Persian ^ clause about the not Sply to Danish 1 ? ° reign ^P^^ntatives didV Ith thfc Compliments of the Under Secret ary of State f«r Foreign Affairs oct m? [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained fev the authorised recipient and not passed onj. For report on Danish Charge d r Affaires see my Heads of Missions despatch No, S2 July 3rd. My Netherlands and Norwegian colleagues and I know him much better than Unitea States Minister does and we consider him^reliable. Reference could be made to Norwegian Charge d Affaires at Moscow# 2. He has helped in arranging important Danish firm of contractors Kampsax to sever relations with enemy territory and to work for the Allies in Persia. He is himsell breaking off relations with Danish Government and has informed Danish representative in Persia to that effect. I recommend that when treaty with Persian Government is concluded, I should ask them to recognise him as head of Danish community unless some more official status can be secured for^him. My Soviet colleague is telegraphing to his government in much the same sense, having I understand become convinced that Mr. F...# is pro-Ally. [Cypher] WAR CABINET DISTRIBUTION FROM PERSIA FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Sir R. Bullard, No. 898 2nd October 1941 D. 2.22 p.m. 2nd October 1941 R. 8.00 p.m. 3rd October 1941 Repeated to Moscow No.292, Your telegram No. 816 not repeated to Moscow</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000225_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/670</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000225</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/670</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 7390/41 ‘Severance of relations by Danish Legation in Tehran with German controlled Danish Govt’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-07T09:08:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a number of telegrams sent between Sir Richard William Bullard, HM Minister to Persia [Iran]; and the Foreign Office. The subject matter is the severance of relations by the Danish Chargé d'affaires at Tehran, Mr A C Fensmark, from the Danish Government in Copenhagen, and his recognition by Persia of his status as representative of the Danish community in Persia.A list of correspondence references by year can be found on the front cover.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Danish Chargé d'affaires to Persia and Iraq</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000225#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>