<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00021d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-13T12:50:21.578Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">XH3ZA CTTIOS, VOTCHRAU.* 3. w. 1. boon aafeod to acnd you, for your poroaned ona ccrjfidantlai InfOmoUan, the eneXosed copy of a report by / Rondel or the roeeiRn offise on his recent tour In the orotan Oulf and Saudi Arable. Rcndel has ashed us to do tide and hes oatplained that he does so because Garoe hss euereeted that It mlsht be of interest to you in eoraneotion ulf affaire Generally. Copies hare been for their personal Infomntioo. Xou «tU pjcsbnbli- not wait to bother about the Saadi Arabian part of the report but you sill find the ■anatwr part quite readable and probably of interest. hen you hare done with It peshape you el 11 kindly either return it to us, or destroy it* or tnJso it beek to India, tree tins it ee a secret import 3.U.I. Sgi!.; Wl. J. 3UAUS0NM. J.Clauson, Esq.. , India Office. With Mr. Rendel ! s compliments. FOREIGN OFFICE, July 31st 1937.'rJi. Gs'-? IN Din. OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.I. 1. 6th July, 1937. Ly deir Loch, Very miny thanks for your helofal letter aboat the Bushire customs, which I have passed on to Caroe. I am enclosing for your personal and confidential information a copy of endel’s report on his recent tour of the 1 iddle ,ast, which we thought might be of interest to you. Rendel has mentioned to us several times how kind everybody was to him in the Gulf, and in particular what a great deal of trouble you and ! rs. Loch took over his Bahrein visit. You may care to keep the report, in which case you will of course take all the necessary precautions to safeguard its confidential nature, but if you prefer not to be saddled with it, we should be quite glad to have it back for our own use. (Sgd.) 1J.J. Clauson. s Lieut.-Colonel P.G. Loch, C.I.S., Binns, LINLITHGOW.Foreign Office, S.W.l. 1st July 1937. My dear Claus on, Many thanks for your letter of to-day, asking for an additional copy of my report. I enclose two, as I have several to spare. I quite agree with v/hat you propose to say to Loch, but you realise, of course, that parts of the report are confidential - particularly as regards what passed with Ibn Saud, so you may like to give Loch a v/ord of warning and ask him to treat is as a confidential paper. Yours sincerely M.J. Clauson, Esq., India Office.My dear Rendel, tfould you kindly refer to your correspondence with Walton about your report on your trip to the Middle East? Before he went on leave Walton asked me to ask you whether you could spare a further copy for us to send personally to Colonel Loch, who is at present on-leave. You said when I spoke to you that you thought there would be no difficulty in producing a copy. I have looked through the reoort and I think it will be quite suitable to send to Loch in its present fora. In our covering letter we could refer to the lact that you had spoken to us very warmly about the great kindness shown to you by the Lochs in Bahrein. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON G• ~v• Lendel, i sq., Foreign Of fl ce.7 ©) / / v lilDIA Ui’KCOE, VfTOTStlALL, 3. W. 1. ► ^ 1 /v&gt; 1 ' v (f U 24th June, 1937* \ I enclose copy of an interesting report by Rendel ocf his recent tour in the Gulf* He has kindly let us hare four copies for limited confidential distribution* Copy is also enclosed of extracts from correspondence with Rendel regarding certain passages in the report about Kuwait f which I think explains itself* I hesitate to send you these papers* knowing how busy you must be* but I know you will be interested in Rendel 9 s report and if you hare time to glance at it one evening you will find it quite amusing after-dinner reading* I am, of course, sending copies of the report to Metcalfe, Fowle and de Gsairy and will ask Rendel for one for Loch. ^ (Sd.) J. C. WALTON* J* G* Laithwalte* liaq*, C.I*E. * Private Secretary to H* K* the Viceroy* Viceregal Lodge* Simla.I enclose copy of an interesting report by Rendel of his recent tour in the Gulf. He lias kindly let tts have four copies for limited / confidential distribution# Oopy is also enclosed of extracts from correspondence with Rondel regarding certain / passages in the report about Kuwait, which I think explains itself# / / I an sending copies of the report to Fowle and de Gaury and also one to Laithwaite as he knows Rendel well and may be personally interested, and I will ask Rendel to let as have a copy for Loch (Sd. ) J. 0. WALT OR, also# Sir H# A# P# Metcalfe, I. • C# X# L ,C# 3* X# ,M# V« 0* , Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, India# ihwia OFFICE 9 WHITBIiAiiaj g 3.W.I. 84th June, 1937* / / (Ixy I enclose copy of an interesting report by Rendel of his recent tour in the Gulf* He has kindly let us hare four copies for limited confidential distribution* Copy is also enclosed of extracts fran correspondence with Rendel regarding certain passages in the report about Kuwait, which I think explains itself. Copies of the report are being sent to Metcalfe and do laury and I will ask Rendel for one for Loch . (Sd. ) J.C. WALTON. Phe Hon. Lt. -Col. Sir T.C.W.Powle, K.C.I.E. ,C.B.B. , H. B. M. Consulate-General, Bushire.If I INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL , 8.W.I. 84th June, 1937* M, j* AM^ry / / / / I enclose copy of an interesting report by Ren&amp;el of his recent tour in the Gulf* He lias kindly let us hare four copies for limited confidential distribution# Copy is also enclosed of extracts frorj correspondence with Rendel regarding certain passages in the report about Kuwait, vftiich I think explains itself# Copy of the report is being sent to Fowle* (Sd.) J. C. WALTON. Captain G# S# H# de Oaury, M# 0 #, Political Agent, Kuwait#Foreign Office, S.W.l. 2nd June 1957. My dear Walton, Following on my letter of May 22nd, I now enclose four further roneod copies of my report^for the limited confidential distribution which you originally suggested. In sending these cox^ies to Gilbert Laithwaite and the other people^who you suggested might like to see it, you will no doubt wish to add a coverer qualifying the passages regarding the Sheikh of Kov/eit. More copies of the report are available if required. Yours very sincerely J.C. Walton, Esq., C.B., M.C., India Office.I £ ' f: r O ro o&gt; CM CM A X y.J (?, ' '' * ■ '* J jSORKia^ OFFICE, S.W.l. 21st May, 1937. a . ip ' i My dear Walton, Please forgive me for not having written earlier to thank you for your letter of May 11th and for all the kind things you say in it about my report. I am very glau you have found it interesting and that you do not think it likely to cause any resentment in Government of India quarters. Our printers here are apparently very overloaded with work in connection v/ith the Imperial Conference, and so it io I has been decided that my report vt&amp;sj not to be printed but Lie rely roneoed. I am, however, getting a fair number of copies made and shall be very glad to let you have as many as you need for the careful and limited unofficial distribution which you suggest. as regards making alterations, I have been through paragraphs 36 to 40 again and have deleted one or two adverbs in the hope of making them a little less controversal But without complete rewriting I doubt whether there are any alterations of substance that can easily be made. Your J . C • V/ a 11 o n, Esq., C • B •, M »C •Your raore important suggestion is in regard to the paragraphs dealing with the Koweit. But heremy difficulty is rather the same. I could, of course, put in a couple of paragraphs in defence of the Shei&amp;iof Koweit, hut the difficulty is that a good many copies of the report have already gone out, and I am not sure whether so important an alterations is practicable without a good deal more labour than would be justified. Moreover, we have now discussed the whole question of Koweit at the interdepart mental meeting which took place here on May 18th when the various points you make in your letter were very fully gone into. In the circumstances might it not be enough to insert a passage in any covering letter you send to the recipients of the report, explaining that you have drawn my attention to the possible unfairness to the Sheikh in the passages in question and that the whole matter has now formed the subject of further discussion in the course of which a somewhat new light was thrown on the problem, so that this particular part of the report should be read in conjuction with the 7 X record of that discussion and not independently. /I hope that this may perhaps meet your point, and it would, of couisej be/be very uuch simpler than rewriting the relevant bit and having those particular pages recopied. Although the roneoing of the report is in hand, it will, of course, take a little time as our typists here are also very much overloaded. I doubt then whether I shall have it until my return from Geneva towards the end of next week, but I will send you the copies as soon as possible thereafter. Yours very sincerely,* (£ @ view whether teere are ny small otr.iseions which it would be on the safe side to wake. 1 have no very grave criticism ae to what you have indicated of the India cffice and Government of India point of view. In what is said about policy in Koweit, however, I do not think that it is quite correctly described, as at the end of paragraph 3o, as 'mainly negative ’. AB regards the attitude of the Sheikh also there is, I think, one factor of importance which is not mentioned, i.e.. the fact that the Sheikh has for long . years had two legitimate grievances against his lajesty's Government - namely the non-fulfilment or delayed fulfilment of our promises about the date gardens and helping to secure the removal of Ibn Gaud’s blockade. !• have, of course, done our best, and are continuing to do so, but it would not be surprising if the Jong wait had made the Shaikh somewhat bitter, as he struck me when he was here (rather than quite happy about, the situation, as you describe him in paragraph 32); and it seems a probable partial explanation of his somewhat unamenable attitude/attitude. Die Sheikh of Bahrein, with whom you contrast him, has nothing to comolain of, and has flourished like the fp*een bay tree under our protection. The fact that Koweit, unlike Bahrein, is on the mainland wedged between two larger States is also another factor which makes things much more difficult for the Sheikh of Koweit, as well as for us. I do not know whether you would care to add something on these points, in order to avoid any risk of doing an injustice to the dheikh of Koweit through the omission of factors which are very likely relevant to his attitude. Only one other ooint. Does it give quite the right impression to a ay (paragraph 32) that most of the Sheikh*s subjects seem to do a thriving trade in smuggling? No doubt they import the goods into Koweit, but we have always been told that the smuggling across the frontier into Iraq is done by Iraqis (De Gaury confirmed this to me orally the other day), and I think a large part of that into Mejd is done (^s it not?) by Ibn Baud’s tribesmen. (Sgd.) J.C. Walton.ISir, FOREIGN. OFFICE, April 25rd.I957. I have the honour to submit 8. report on the journey which I recently undertook to the Persian Gulf and Saudi Arabia. The places I visited and the personalities I met were so many and so diverse that it has been impossible to make the report as short as I could have wished. But I have divided it into sections under separate headings, of which a contents list is prefixed above, in the hope of making it easier for those who have no time lor the whole of so bulky a document, to pick out any parts of it likely to be of interest to them. The account of our trip across Arabia and visit to Jedda will be found in paragraphs 58 to 126. Much of the rest is of less general interest, but I have thought it well to make the narrative complete, as the trip w r as unusual, and a full record of it may be useful for future reference. INTRODUCTORY . 2. Soon after the Amir 3aud r s visit to England in the summer of 1955, I received, through the Saudi Minister in London,, an invitation from King Ton Saud to visit Riyadh, with my wife, and to cross Saudi Arabia from the Persian Gulf to the Red Sea. Owing to the Abyssinian crisis, it proved impossible to accept this invitation at the time, but, on its being renewed last To the Right Honourable Anthony Eden v M B C.,M.P., etc., etc., autumn3 , autuinn, I was able tc obtain sanction to undertake the journey early this year* My time was necessarily limited, but I was nevertheless able to see a great deal, and to have many interest ing conversations, not only with the British representatives in the countries I visited, but also with prominent local personalities, and particularly with King Ibn Baud himself. Although I was careful, in accordance with the instructions I had received, to make it clear in every case that these conversations were en tirely private and unofficial, I hope that they may still have served some useful purpose. They have certainly been of the greatest value to me. OUTffARD JOURNEYc 3, I left England with my wife on February 9th and travelled overland to Brindisi, and thence by the Lloyd Triestino direes service via Cyprus to Haifa. From Haifa we travelled Dy nairn Car, past the beautiful Vale of EdraeIon,through the hills of Galilee, scarlet with anemones, down to Tiberias, and round the back of Mount Hermon by a rather dull Syrian road to Damascus. In order nor to overload this report I am submitting separate notes (i) on my visit to Cyprus, where we were most kindly received by the Governor and the District Commissioner of Larnaca; (ii) on my various experiences of Italian shipping lines and their connexion with the development of Italian in fluence in the Middle East; (iii) on the impressions I derived from my hurried passage through Palestine; and (iv) on the Bairn Convoy Service from the Mediterranean to Bagdad. DAMASCUS....4 0 tfe arrived at Damascus on February 15th. Plis Majesty's Consul-General, Colonel MacKereth and his wife, who both seem deoerved.ly popular in Damascus society, entertained us to tea. I a^so met an old acquaintance, Major Longrigg, of Petroleum Concessions Limited, whom I found much depressed over his oil negotiations with the new Syrian Government. The details of these hcrve been lully reported elsewhere, and I only mention them aS trey were frequently quoted to me as a typical example Oa. one incompetence and muddle-headedness of the new native Syric Government, who apparently were unable to make up their minds on point, and had only the haziest idea of what they wanted, or of what it might be practicable to obtain. The French authori ties, who are equally interested with ourselves in getting this business settled, seemed no less despondent about it. on While I was at Geneva in January M. Vienot, the French under Secretary ox State for Foreign Affairs, had specially asked me to try to get into direct touch with the French High Commissioner when I passed through Syria, and do anything I could to make sure that there was the closest possible co operation between the British and French authorities in any countries I might Visit in the Middle East. My wife and I were therefore very glad to accept an invitation to dinner that evening with Comte de Martel, who was paying a brief visit to Damascus 0 Colonel and Mrs. MacKereth were also invited, and one party included the French delegate for Damascus and his wife, anci vari eus members of the High Commissioner’s staff. As this J_s a franic and confidential record I may say at once that I founcMe do Martel uninspiring e He made few efforts to initiate conversation and we all found him heavy going. He struck rn ao a man who had lost interest in his job since his own policy had been overridden and ihat of the hastily concluded Franeo- Syrian Ti’eaty imposed on him instead. He spoke witn bitterness of the pretensions of the 'Parks and the weakness of the ireii&gt;.-;i Government over Alexandretta^ but had littl.e to say cooiiu the future of Syria. 6, Bearing LL Vienot's remarks in mind, I took the opportunity of a private talk witn M, de hart el to asxi whether he was entirely satisfied v/itn tne ainouni- of co-operation he was receiving 1 rcm the various Biltioh authorities with whom he had to deal, jie said he was, qualifying this affirmative, however, with a mild exception in regard to Captain Glubb in Transjordan, whom he accused of tampering with the allegiance of Syrian tribes, an old mare's-nest, and I did my best - quoting my personal knowledge of Captain Glubb T s character and activities - to allay these suspicions, which I believe to ce quire uniuand-G. 7, Comte de Martel was anxious to get into personal touch with Sir A, Clark Kerr, but had apparently - in view of misunderstandings in the past with tne former BritxSii authorities in Iraq - hesitated to take any steps uo about a meeting, I promised to take the master up in Bagdad and duly did so, and when I left Iraq dir A, Clark Kerr already corresponsing with Comte de Martel thiougn Hie ireucL Minister at Bagdad about a possible meeting? 1 * This meeting has since taken place 86 . 8o The track from Damascus to Bagdad has been much improved of late, and we had a comfortable journey via RutDa where we dined, arriving at Bagdad at 6.50 on the morning of February 17. B AGDaD. 9. Our first day in Bagdad was marred by a dust-storm - the first, I was told, for some weeks. It is difficult to describe the discomfort of these frequent afflictions, which are one of the greatest drawbacks of Bagdad as a post. The atmosphere not only looks like a London fog, but chokes and suffocates one even indoors. Everything is rapidly covered with a layer of foul and gritty dust. No amount of cleaning removes its traces, and the vegetation and ouildings of Bagdad in contrast to those of Cairo - always bear a dusty and slightly sordid look in consequence. 10. Soon after my arrival I was asked by sir A. Clark Kerr to take part in a series of informal conversations about outstanding questions with him, Captain dolt (the oriental Secretary to His Majesty r s Embassy) and Mr. C^J. Edmonds (the Adviser to the Ministry of the Interior)* The results oi most of these conversations have been recorded separately. \(o discussed in particular the question of the Perso-Iraqi frontier, and I was able to explain to Bir A.Clark Kerr and Mr. Edmonds the results of the latest interdepartmental discussions in London. Sir A. Clark Kerr gave me a number of sidelights on the local aspect of the problem which I have found of great value. Before I left Bagdad I also had....7. had some useful talk on this question vri'T Mr. MacDougail, the Legal Adviser to the Iraqi Ministry for Foreign Affairs. 11, Another question which came up for discussion was that of Koweiti-Iraqi relations, with particular reference to the problem of smuggling. Sir A. Clark Kerr gave me a clear and complete picture of the Iraqi aspect of this complicated question, and asked me to do what I could to clear up certain miscoriceptions under which the authorities in the Persian Gulf seemed to be labouring in regard to it. I later took this up at Koweit and Bushire and reported the results to Sir A.Clark Kerr in letters copies of which have been entered separately. I am inclined to think, however, that the problem of Koweit is too complex for purely local settlement. I am submitting a separate note on this question (see a]so paragraphs 29 and 30 below). Meanwhile, I was able, while I was at Bagdad, to explain to Sir A. Clark Kerr the peculiar nature of the dif ficulties with which we are faced in dealing with Koweit, and I think he realised that it was not practical politics to bring about what might be called the ideal Iraqi solution. Later Captain Holt and I also talked over certain aspects of the Assyrian question, and I explained certain aspects of the problem on lines which had been previously agreed upon at home, I have dealt with these conversations in a separate note. 12. On the evening of February 17th Sir A. Clark Kerr gave a men T s dinner-party of 27 at the Bmbassy to enable me to meet the Prime Minister, Hikmat Beg Suleiman, and other members of t he.....@) the Iraqi Government. The Embassy staff and most of the British Advisers to the Iraqi Government, many of whom I already knew, were also invited. At the Ambassador's suggestion, I had a long informal talk with the Prime Minister after dinner, for which Captain Holt acted as Interpreted. I later prepared for Sir A. Clark Kerf a separate note of this conversation, of which a copy is being entered separately so that I need not record it again here. 13. My general impression of the Prime Minister was that his intentions were admirable and that he was genuinely anxious to stand well with us. He struck me as more cultivated and intelligent than I had expected, and I should imagime him capable of aiming quite sincerely at a policy of moderate and en lightened reicrm. But, while I entirely agree with Sir A. Clark Kerr's view that it is most desirable for Iraq that the P^eseiiu Government should remain in power for some years at le^so, I confess that Hikrnat Bey gave me personally little impression of force of character. I distrust first impressions, bat my o.&lt;n, for what it is worth, was of a man coping with a task on rather too big a scale for him, and also a little too anxious to give explanations of the motives of his policy, - explanations which, in one or two cases at any rate - notably that of the alleged Iraqi fear of attack from Persia - I iound somewhat unconvincing. 1±. On the evening of February 13th Dr. Naji el Asil, the Iraqi Minister for Foreign Affairs, gave a dinner for me at the new Town Hall, attended by some 50 guests, including members cf9o of the Iraqi Government, the senior ofiicials ot the xia^i Government departments and the Embassy staff. On this occasion Sir A. Clark Kerr and I had a long conversation with Dr, Naji, who speaks good English. I recorded ihe substance of the more Important parts of this conaer^uoion in a separate memorandum which I gave to Sir A, CiariC Karr and of which he has since sent home a copy in his despatch NOo77 of February 19th, la. Dr. liaji struck me as having gained much in confidence and personality since the remote days v/hen he used 10 sit as the discarded and discredited unofficial agent m London of the late King Hussein of the Hejaz - outside the doors Ox the Eastern Department of the Foreign Office. Bur he still seems to me a light weight - though he is pleasant and frienu.i.y, I fear he carries little conviction in daudi Arabia where the Arabs I met spoke slightingly of him, but possibly tn±s may be due to prejudice against his past. 16. Some of the other members of the Cabinet - notably the Minister of Education, with whom I li-d a longish calk at tn^ Iraqi dinner - struck me as intelligent and capao.LW. uiit although my visit to Bagdad has certainly made me readier than I was before to believe in the new Iraqi Government's good will, I cannot say that it has much increased my confidence in their ability to stay the course. 17, With the Ambassador's approval I had seme interesting talk with one or two of the local Christian authoiita.es regarding..•••10, regarding the position of the Assyrians on the K3.ia.bur and of the Christian minorities in Iraq. The general conclusion of these talks was somewhat depressing, but in order not to overload the present report unduly I am recording their substance in a separate note. 18c Before leaving Bagdad I attended a tea party given by the Saudi Charge d f Affaires. Ibrahim Ibn Muammer (whose pro-Saudi intrigues have apparently aroused the resentment of the Iraqi Government), and met various other foreign representatives, including the Egyptian, German, Italian and (later) French Ministers. I thought inournt the Egyptian intelligent and interesting, the German rather assertiv the Italian frothy, and the Frenclunan extremely well- disposed and well intentioned, but inclined to be a little fussy and ridiculous. Nothing passed of sufficient interest to be worth special mention e Basra AN N Till GHATT Eh ARAB. 19 o ’;Ye left Bagdad on the evening of February 19th in a saloon carriage kindly put at our disposal by the Iraqi Railways at the request of the Iraqi Government, and were met at Basra the next morning by Colonel V#arb ? the Director of the Port of Basra and now also of the Iraqi Railways, who is an old friend of mine. 20, Colonel yard, in whose house we stayed, and whose unflagging drive and efficiency are a perpetual wcnder to me, began by showing us over his new airport at Maqil - a magnificent piece of work, of which he is justly proud. Full particulars of....c li. of this are no doubt available elsewhere, so I will only say that it struck me - except for certain very minor drav/oacks, such as the small size of some of the bedroom windows and of the bedrooms themselves - as a first class organisation, conceived on a large scale with a clear eye to future needs, for both land and sea aviation. The cost is being met, I understand, from the revenues of the Port of Basra, and it is expected that it will almost immediately become self-supporting. Trie total cost of the whole place including the buildings appears to be about four-fifths of what has been estimated for the erection of the proposed new Residency at Bahrain.' 21. Colonel ward then took us, with breathless speed, in one of his new fast launches, down the Shatt-el-Arab to Abadan, where I was anxious to discuss with him on the spot the question of the proposed concession to Persia of an anchorage extending up to the thalweg of the Shatt. I wrote a long letter about this a few days later to Sir A. Clark Kerr, who sent a copy of it to the Foreign Office at the time, so that I need not discuss it further here, except to say that the visit was, I think, useful in enabling me to clear up with Colonel Ward certain obscurities in the situa tion which had previously threatened to cause much misunderstanding Colonel Ward was also able to explain to me personally his views and projects - which are interesting and important - on the future conservancy of the Shatt. 22. On our way down the Shatt we passed three of the new Persian sloops, looking unexpectedly smart. We also passed a Persian naval tug bringing a dhow up to Mohammerah with a prize crew...e12. i crew on board. This was presumably one of the Arab dhows whose arrests have formed the subject of recent correspon dence, although I heard nothing of the matter at Kcweit or Bushire. 25 0 Returning to Basra, we called on His Majesty's Consu 1 , Mr. Brickell, a comparatively new arrival from Hew York. We also met in the attractive garden of His Majesty's Consulate some of the officers of His Majesty's sloops 'Leptford-’ and 'Bideford ” 9 and various members of the British colony. A short talk I had with Judge Lloyd on the tedious and intricate question of the date gardens of the Sheikhs of Moharnmerah and Kuweit did not lead us any nearer a solution of the problem. BALRA TO KOffalT. 24. We left early next morning, February 21st in a hired Ford car for Koweit. The smiling date ga.rdens and green canals of Basra give way abruptly to salt mud flats and a stretch of desert which seems to form the natural boundary between Iraq and Arabia. The last Iraqi town, Lubair, is purely Arabian, and was our first sight of the local colour of the desert. It has something of the air of a desert fort, and the streets run between blind mud walls only broken 'ey occasional heavy decorated doors. The population wore the universal kefiyeh, igal, and brown abba, and were for the most part congregated in the market place, where a kind oi fair was being held - complete with swingboats - to celebrate the Id at incongrous and rudimentary the close of the pilgrimage.25. A slight difficulty in going to Koweit on the way to Persia is that a passport to be valid for Persia must not bear any indication of having been used for Koweit or Bahrain, or the Persian authorities will refuse to recognise it. Two separate passports are thus necessary, a duplication liable to cause much inconvenience and confusion. I note this trivial complication as it is one of the many minor drawbacks of the present undigni fied anomalous situation in which the Persians refuse to recognise the existence of the Gulf States or our own position in regard to them. 26. It is four hours by car from Basra to Koweit. Zubair is within an hour of Basra and it is about an hour and a half further to the Koweit boundary at Safwan, where we found a relief car sent by the Political Agent at Koweit, Captain de Gaury, to meet us, with an English speaking armed retainer of the Sheikh of Koweit as escort. Another hour across a desert singularly green after recent rain, and with occasional large patches of closely growing deep blue iris, brought us to the head of Koweit Bay, with Koweit standing apparently straight out of the sea at its south-eastern corner. Captain de Gaury met us outside the town and took us on to the Agency in his own car. KOETEIT. 27. Koweit is an interesting town and lives up to its reputation for striking local colour. Its complete circle of walls and series of v/ell defended gates are comparatively new - the late Sheikh Mubarrak is alleged to have told the American Mission, settled on the outskirts of v/hat was then an undefended town, that no wall was necessary as M he would be their wall” - but they give it much of its character. The various harbours for the pearl14. pearl fishing fleet and sea-going dhows are curious and interesting. But it would be out of place in this report to embark on a purely picturesque description of scenes and customs which are already fully and better described in ordinary narratives of travels I will only mention in passing that, owing to the Id, we found Koweit,like Zubair, en f£te , every dhow oeflagged, the market place thronged, and the Sheikh himself watching a ceremonial sword dance by his bodyguard, which he invited us to witness in his company. My wife sat beside His Excellency, unveiled, on a high settee. Our presence, though conspicuous, apparently caused no adverse comment. 28. The Sheikh dined at the Agency the same evening, and invited us to dine with him, in company with Captain de G-aury, on the following day. Captain de G-aury, who seems to have established a remarkable position for himself, and whose local knowledge struck me as not only profuse but profound, proved a skilful interpreter, so that I was able to form some idea of the Sheikh T s attitude and character. Captain de G-aury and I had several long conversations on outstanding questions - notably the difficult problem of smug gling, which is poisoning Koweiti relations both v/ith Iraq and with Saudi Arabia, and I gave an account of some of these conversations to Sir A. Clark Kerr in a letter, copies of v/hich I gave to Captain de G-aury and to Colonel Fowle at the time. Copies of this letter, and of a later letter which I wrote to Sir A. Clark Kerr on the subject from Bushire, have been entered separately. 29. I have long been uneasy about our policy in regard to Kcweit and my visit did nothing to allay my uneasiness. I am submitting a separate note on this question, which seems to me impoi'tant in view of the key position which Kcweit holds in relatione to the Eastern air route, to the Shatt-el-Arab, and to the Persian Gulf generally. I...~T c * special readiness to accept British guidance in the conduct of affairs, or to co-operate without important reservations in the policy of His Majesty’s Government, Meanwhile the serious friction which is a constant feature of the relations of Koweit with its two neighbours is one of the most tiresome and potentially dangerous of the minor problems with which we are faced in the Middle East. 52, The Sheikh himself is quite happy about the situation - and, as lar as one can see, so are his subjects under his paternal rule. I was much struck by the general cheerfulness of the in habitants, Possibly this is due to the fact that most of them seem to do a thriving trade in smuggling, and I am told that smugglers are naturally happy people. The Sheikh’s contentment seems to be due partly to robust health and an active mind, and partly to the fact that according to local gossip he is putting by some £ 20,000 a year. 55. February 22nd, our second day at Koweit, was wet - a dis appointment to us as we were to have attended an Arab feast in the desert and a dancing display in the afternoon. But the Sheikh was radiant at what he called our n green coming”. I had crossed swords with him on the subject of smuggling at a conference at the India during his last visit to London, but he was good enough to assure me that, in view of the rain I had brought him, our difference would be forgiven (which I was glad of), and forgotten (which was more than I desired). 34. Sheikh Ahmed prides himself on his modernity. Dress trousers and patent shoes boldly showed below his sober black 'thoub” (a kind of cassock or long skirted gown worn in Arabia under the abba or cloak), and he gave us a European meal, in cluding French coffee, in a very European (and indeed slightly surburban) drawing room, full of cuckoo clocks and other gewgaws. Otherwise Koweit is still essentially mediaeval; but the discovery34 (§&gt; 17. discovery of oil (though still in douotfully pacing quantities) and the influx of American oil drillers viill hardly allow it to preserve its simple outlook and local colour long. I am including a note about the new political agency building at Loweit in paragraph A/ celor. 55. Before we left Koweit we raise net Colonel and hrs. Dickson (Captain de G-aury's predecessor and now local representative of the Koweit Oil Company - a strong out not a silent man) ? various other local notabilities, and the officers of the Drench sloop d’Iberville, wnich was carrying out a cruise in the Gulf. The French officers were partic ularly cordial and insistent on the need for Irnnco-British co-operation in tne bast. -e left Koweit on February 25rd in the Britisn India S.S. ’‘Bandra'S in which we were the only passengers; and we arrived at Bushire on unc following morning. BuSlilHC aKu bKIKAC. 56. Bushire, wnich looks attractive from tne sea, owing chiefly to the fine range oi mountains on bno mainl^ind — thirty miles away from where the town lies at the extiemit^ of its long flat peninsula - struck me as a difficult and inconvenient harbour. Even the inner anchorage, where we lay, is two miles from the snore and can, I understand, become inaccessible in rough weather. Our ship was immediately subject to a rigorous control by Persian olhicials, As a result of telegraphic instructions from Tehran, my wife and I were treated with every courtesy end our luggage was allowed through the customs unopened and without delay. But I gathered that this was most unusual, and that arrival at Bushire is seldom so comparatively easy and agreeable. Indeed it seemed to me that the Political resident s poisonax Assistant/18. Assistants who carne on board to meet us ? was treated with scanty considerations and the residency launch was so badly nustleds under the impassive eyes oi the Persian polices by tne Persian dhows crowding round our ships that Sue nearly had her ensign snapped off - nots I thinks wholly accidentally. Our landing was hardly more dignifieds and we were obliged to scramble ashore from the launch over a maze of dhows ? on to a quay so congested with heaps of ill-stacked and damaged crates and packing cases (mostly containing American cars and lorries) that progress was most difficult. 57. Bushire struck me as sordid and depressed, and I was glad to pass out of it into tne open country. The Resident’s dwelling house and private office are some seven miles from the town, in an attractive countryside, with a pleasant garden and fine views. e were most kindly received by Colonel and Mrs. Powle, who proved charming hosts. Indeed I feel that after all their friendly hospitality, and the close agreement which Colonel Powie and I reached on tne great majority of questions v/hicn we discussed, it must seem ungracious of me to strike a critical note even on an entirely impersonal point of policy. But there is one such point on which I feel that I should be failing in sincerity, and impairing any usefulness this report may possess as a frank statement of my experiences and impressions, if I did not put my views on record. This is the old question oi where the Resident's head-quarters should be. 58. Almost from the first moment of my arrival, I was impressed by the ^nomalousness, and indeed indignity, of the Political Resident's position in Persian territory.. The Political Resident is oi course the highest British authority in the Persian Gulf, and is virtually Governor of the Arab States/19. States under our protection on the Arab shore. But in Persia he is merely a Consul-General, with no ofiicial privilege of any kind, and legally at the mercy of the whole clumsy machine of ignorant and obstructive officialdom which is the mark of tne modern ultra-nationalist oriental State. No communication addressed to Colonel Fowle as Political Resident is delivered, and his connexion with the Arabian coast is of course neither recognised nor even admitted. But this camouflage of his status as Consul-General of Bushire is hardly t aken seriously - indeed, as far as I could see, only a small proportion of the Residency w r ork has an even remotely consular character. The whole establishment is far more of the type associated with a Provincial Governorate than with anything in the consular service, and the complex organisation of the Residency with its various separate official houses and offices, its engineer and treasurer, its special quarters for 'recess ' 1 at Shiraz, suggests nothing so much as that of an administrative unit of the Government of India. It is hardly surprising that the Persians look on this institution with suspicion and dislike. 39. It seems to me a great tribute to our prestige, and a striking instance of the Persian dislike of finality, that the Persian Government have not yet launched a determined attack on this paradoxical state of affairs. Indeed, locally, the Resident himself is still greeted with some state. He receives military salutes, guards are turned out for him when he passes and his personal authority and prestige seemed to me comparatively well established. No doubt this is in 1irge measure due to the personality and tact of Colonel Fowle himself. But the whole situation, which is an unmistakeable relic and insistent reminder of the days when we virtually administered Southern Persia and the Persian shore of the Gulf, car/can only act as a constant irritant at Tehran; ana it seems to me at any moment the Central Government may well decide to take up this anomaly and place us in the position of having to beat an ignominious retreat. The inconvenience of attempt ing to administer the Arab coast from a distant point on foreign territory, with imperfect and inconvenient communic ations . is a matter which mainly affects the Government 01 India, so that I do not want to stress this aspect of it unduly. But it does, in fact, also affect foreign Office interests 5 by slowing down the conduct of our relations ^itn the Arab rulers of tne Gulf and thereby further complicating their relations with their foreign neighbours, e„g. Saudi Arabia and Iraq, Loreoever, I am more than ever convinced, as a result of my visit, that, apart from all these objections to any continuance of the present system, there is little hope of placing Anglo-Persian relations on a really satisiactory basis so long as the Britisn Official who is virtually the Governor of our client States on tne Arabian coast Ox bue Gulf, retains his official headquarters on Persian soil, AO, I had some talk with Colonel Fowle on this question, and ventured to urge once more that every effort should be made to speed up the transfer of the Residency to hamein a move which has already been agreed to in principle by his Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom and by tne Govern ment of India, and wiiicn seems to be held up entirely on com paratively secondary questions 01 finance, the importance o.l which is insignificant in comparison with the political issues involved I understood Colonel Powle to take the view that, now that agreement had been reached in principle as to the desirability of the transfer, and now that arrangements 101 it were in fact in train, there was no need to snow undue But I must confess that, although we agreed on almost every/ haste.21 o every other subject, I was left with the impression that he was not inclined to attach the same importance and urgency to this question as we nave been inclined to do in London. 41. February 24th and 25th were almost entirely taken up with conversations with Colonel Fovle on various outstanding questions, more particularly that of the south-eastern front iers of Arabia, which I had been asked by the kiddle .last Official Sub-Committee to discuss with him, and that of Koweit-Iraq smuggling, about widen Sir A. Clark Kerr had asked me to give Colonel Fowle certain further oral explanations. I recorded the result of our discussion on the first point in a note to Colonel Fowle, (of which a copy has been entered separately), and on the second in a private letter to Sir A. Clark Kerr (of which a copy has also been separately entered (see paragraph 11 above). We also discussed some other questions of lesser importance, and I think the con versations were useful to both of us. Indeed, Colonel Fowle was good enough to say that my trip would have been fully justified if only for the new light which I had been able to throw on the question of the south-eastern Arabia frontiers. 42. Colonel Fowle had been anxious that if I went to Bushire I should pay a flying visit to Shiraz in order to get a glimpse of modern conditions in southern Persia. e accord ingly left Bushire at 6 a.m. on February 26th, in a hired car, returning three days later. I need not attempt any detailed description of this journey, which is of course well knov/n. I would only say that the grandeur and variety of the scenery of the seven passes which the road has to scale - each higher than the last, until the final ascent to some 7,000 feet - came as a revelation to me. The journey to Shiraz although # the distance is only about 180 miles, normally takes twelve hours, but in bad weather is known to have taken as much as five/22. five days. Indeed? our own return nearly came to an abrupt end? as we ran into a rain-storm at Kazarun which had turned three formidable passes into mud-slides. We were obliged to take most of the hairpin bends on these by a series of skid-turns? and at one point of the descent span round till v, r e faced uphill on the edge of a precipice. Fortunately? our driver had expected snow and carried chains? which we fitted? and which enabled us to negotiate the rest of the route with a certain measure of precarious safety. I note these incidents for the guidance of future travellers. 43. dork was actively proceeding on the road? in antic ipation of an impending visit of the Shah? who was expected to travel from Bushire to Shiraz about the middle of March. Feverish efforts were in particular being made to repair and complete the execrable thirty miles of road and so-called track between Bushire and the foot of the mountains at Burazjun. Triumphal arches were being laboriously erected not only at Bushire? Kazarun and Shiraz? but in every village on the route. When we were leaving Persia a few days later? however, we heard that the Shah had said that he wanted no decorations? and much uncertainty prevailed whether they would not all have to be taken down. In view of the Shah's coming visit? the road was also the scene of much military activity. The troops we passed were, generally speaking, comparatively smart, and the Arnmieh guards we met struck me as efficient. They certainly seemed to have established a remarkable degree of security. 44. At Shiraz we were entertained to a luncheon for twelve by the Governor General, Abul Path Dowlet Shahi? and his wife. M. Ali Askar Soheily, the brother of the new Persian Minister in London? was also present. This was the first occasion on which His Excellency had entertained His Majesty's/23. Majesty's Consul (with whom we were staying and who was therefore also invited). the Governor General impressed me favourably. He was exceedingly uropean in appearance, manner and outlook, and seemed cultivated, intelligent and keen, though possibly somewhat lacking in vigour. host of the party were very presentable, and the ladies - only recent ly freed from the chuddar - were well dressed and as agreeable as an imperfect knowledge of any common language permitted. The atmosphere was m st cordial, and hr. /atkinson agreed that the party nad been useful in breaking some very thick ice, although, of course, few if any Persians are yet allowed to visit His Majesty's Consulate. Indeed the position ot His Majesty’s Consul must be lonely and diflicult, and 1 could not help doubting whether the retention of the ;ost ns altogether justified. But I hesitate to say even this with- H out knowing more about the views on this point of His Majesty s Minister at lehran. 45 0 to visited the mosques and bazaars of Shiraz under the guidance of an active and efficient Persian police officer put at our disposal by the Governor General. Although the mosques are fine, with some very beautiful tile- work and some striking colonnades of unusual design.; and the bazaars are architecturally interesting, the preva;. _ impression left on me here, as indeed at Bushire ana c&gt;. along the route we followed, was one of almost inuescr -1 cable sordidness and squalor, owing to the fact that every mu r ', woman and child, without exception (except for oiiicials, soldiers and police — who are comparatively well drcsstv.), now v/ears what were once European clothes. Kashqai shepherds wear the aged relics of Komburg hats and the ragged remains of overcoats issued in the remote past to the employees/ -24. @) employees of the London General (Tunious Company. ,/omen wear tattered out gau.' n y European hats and odds and ends of coats and skirts, apparently salved iron -he ruohish iieaps and bonfires whj.ch should have been their final home after their discharge from their last slop-shop. I am told that at Bushire all the women were ordered to the police scation so that their transformation might be verified and olessed. hut at the last moment only a dozen hats were available, the women of Bushire formed up in groups oi twelve and the hats were passed from head to head, until the whole town was de-chuddared. I found the bazaars ol Shiraz, like those I visited in Arabia, stocked with the nastiest products of Czechoslovakia and Japan. I was told that local cicit- manship is still carried on to a certain extent in Isfahan, but in Shiraz it seemed to be restricted to a few rather inferior metal workers. Altogether a depressing impression, only compensated by the interest of the remarkable new discoveries at persepolis, and by the striking natural beauty of the surrounding country. 46. It would be impertinent for me on so short an acquaintance to generalise about the Persian oharac-e^. But I cannot refrain from recording the extent to which I was impressed by the contrast between the manner and ap;&gt;wc: ance of the Persians and of the Arabs. The curious, slight ;/ effete effeminacy of the Persian, and his lack ol humour about himself, his queer gentleness and his all pervading vanity, are particularly noticeable 'when contrasted with the rugged virility, comparative simplic-^y blulf se-.,se of humour of the Arabs of Arabia. BAHREIN AND QATAR- 47. be left Bushire on H.M. sloop 'Deptford” (Captain Bowlby)/25. Bowlby) on the evening of March 2nd. Colonel Fowle had originally intended to go to Koweit hy the slow mail, prior to a visit to India, hut as a result oi our discuss ions on the question of the south-eastern Arabian frontiers, he decided that it would he preferable to tackle the frontier question at once. He therefore decided to change his plans and to accompany me to Bahrain, where he arranged for Captain de Gaury to meet him, in order that we might discuss tne frontier question further with Colonel Lock, and, if we thought it desirable, fly over the disputed frontier together, in order to see the position for ourselves. 48. Nothing could have been kinder than the way in which we were received and looked after by Captain Bowlby and the other officers of H.M.S. 'Deptford'. Ue were a large party and must have imposed a considerable strain on the resources of so small a ship, but the sixteen hours we spent on board her were among the pleasantest of our whole journey, and I think we were all sorry to part when we reached Bahrein on the morning of March 3rd. H.M.S. 'Deptford*’ remained for some days at Bahrein where she was joined by H.M.S. 'Bideford' (Captain Faulkner), and Colonel Fowle, Colonel Locn, Captain de Gaury and I had several interesting and useful conversations about Gulf affairs with both Captain Bowlby and Captain Faulkner during this period. 49. Shortly after our arrival at Bahrein, the Sheikh paid a formal call on us at the Agency, and half an hour later Colonel Fowle, Colonel Lock and I returned it, at the Sheikh's town palace. The ceremonial was similar to that followed in Hasa and presumably elsewhere in Eastern Arabia - /26. coffee with cardamon was served at intervals (any dregs being tnrown on the carpet or drunk by the servant), rose water sprinkled on us from a silver sprinkler, and incense in a small brazier was broughtround to each guest in turn. There is a special technique for dealing with the incense, but it can be mastered without difficulty. The conversation was purely general; but Sheikh Hamad showed, as on the other occasions on which we saw him, grace and skill in making a few appropriate remarks to each member of the company, and in keeping the ball of conversation gently rolling at an even pace - an accomplishment many Arabs lack. 50. On March 4-th Colonel Fowle, Colonel Loch and I, having previously discussed every aspect of the frontier question in the light of the latest maps I had brought from Air Headquarters at Bagdad, were taken for a long flight round the disputed frontier and the Qatar peninsula in a Royal Air Force Singapore flying boat which the Air Officer Commanding, Iraq, nad kindly placed at our disposal. I am submitting a separate note giving a detailed record of our flight. For the purposes of the present report it will be sufficient to say that we flew for nearly six hours, crossing to Qatar by Hawar Island (attributed to Bahrein and disputed by tne rival British and American oil companies); thence down the best coast of Qatar to the Jebel Nakhsh, which had been specially marked for us by a party sent out by the Sheikh of Qatar, and round which we circled several times, taking a number of air photographs; thence to Qasr-es-Salwa, which appeared quite deserted, and eastwards past Sakak and Anbak (also deserted), along the proposed frontier line to the Khor-el-Odeid. be made a careful inspection of the Khor - regarding which important correspondence had recently c orne/ The Jebel Nakhsh and the Khor-el-Odeid are two of the dis puted points over which the frontier negotiations with King Ibn faud nave hitnerto broken down.27o come to light (see separate reports), &amp;nd tfien tried to locate the ridge and/or wells of Sufuk in the area known as tne Sabkhat Matti. The configuration of tnis area proved different from what we had previously been led to expect, and though we circled over it many times we were none of us able to locate either of these features. be returned along the 'last Coast of Qatar via Has Musheirib, bakra, Doha and the north end of the peninsula, and just before landing at Bahrein obtained a very striking and curious panoramic view of all the islands, which I found particularly interesting. 51 . vr e were able as a result of our flight, to establish beyond any doubt that the Jebel Naknsh is merely the south end of the Jebel Dukhan ridge and geographically an integral part of the Qatar peninsula, and that tne knox-el Cdeid can he of no use as a harbour owing to the long winding channel of silting sand which separates it from the sea, here in any case a mass of reefs. But we were unable to solve the problem of Sufuk - hitherto described as a key point - and we dad no alternative but to ask Colonel Loch to arrange with the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi to nave the place marked, as m tne ca.se of tne Jebel Kakhsn, when Colonel Loch would fly over *f- n r* a/i in tbp second pilot's sent nnd got it again , I was placed m tne secjn., an excellent view throughout the iligut. 52. The flight was invaluable, and greatly helped us * Colonel Loch has since done tnis, and has established that Sufuk lies twelve miles from the sea (See Bahrein telegram No. 65 of March 24 to Bushire, and Bushire telegram Ko. 332 of March 24 to India Office).28. to clarify our ideas about the frontier line in this area. e covered a wide area of country, little known even to the local authorities. It was a remarkable experience which I should have been very sorry to miss; and I am most grateful to the Air Ministry and to the Air Officer Commanding Iraq, for having made it possible. As a result of this personal inspection of the frontier I was able to speak with much more authority when later Oir R. Bullard and I discussed the matter first with tne Saudi Government and afterwards with King Ibn Baud himself at JeGda - see paragraphs 113 and 121 be 1 ova 53. While we were at Bahrein we saw a good deal of Sheikh Hamad, on whom we all paid a further call on March 5th at his country palace, where he greeted us with great cordiality. It was an interesting visit. Mrs. Loch and my wife accompanied us, and we all sat in a row on the floor in a large reception room, with the Sheikh’s sons and retain ers facing us. The Sheikh is a much older man than Sheikh Ahmed of Koweit, although his dyed beard gives him a misleading sir of early middle age. He is said to suffer from diabetes. Sheikh Hamad, possibly because his territories are islands, has accepted our tutelage with a good grace. fie seems to have given his admirable British adviser, kr. Belgrave, a free hand to undertake a great deal of necessary administration reform. Mr. Belgrave's smart].;/ uniformed police with their red turbans and Khaki shorts are much in evidence and seem efficient. It is a great pity that there is no corresponding British administrative adviser of this type in Kov/eit. 54. Providence has been kind to Sheikh Hamad. Just as the/■■■I 29. the pearl trade fell on evil days, plentiful and excellent oil was discovered in Banrein - though, owing inairily to lack ol foresight on the part of British oil interests, who would take no interest in the concession when they could nave nad it, tne exploitation of tnis oil nas fallen into Aiiierican nands. fne estahlishinent of the new British naval station and air port has brought much trade and orosperity to the islands. The oil royalties assure the Government a steady and growing income. It seems hard on Ion Baud, whose needs are so much greater, tnat his infinitely larger neighbouring territory should so for have produced no natural resources in paying qualities. 55. Be were taken over the oil field and tne various installations of the Bahrein Petroleum Company or 'iBapco'', (the local subsidiary of the Standard Oil Company of California), by Lr. Skinner, the local manager - a keen and capable American. I am no judge of the tecnmcal sine of this kind of organisation and can only say that it seemed to me efficient and well run. What we were better able to appreciate was tne new town mien tne Company are building for their employees, and tne amenities provided lor in it. Tiie nouses wnich tne Company are erecting seem eminently suitable to local conditions. They are all provided with deeo fly and mosquito-proof verandahs, air cooling and conditioning plant, electric refrigerators, bath rooms, and modern interior sanitation.. They are well built ox neat resisting material with a good surface, and are easy to run with a small staff. Their appearance is in keeping with the/so. the surroundings and neither pretentious nor unsightlj. Upte on Arch itecture in t he^ersian^Gulf^ 56. These new American buildings seemed to me to afford a striking contrast to most of the Government of India buildings which I visited in the Gulf. me latter all impressed me as belonging to a past age, and as ill- adapted to modern requirements. The Agency at Bahrein is a somewhat decrepit and inconvenient building 01 undis tinguished appearance, approached by a steep and awkward staircase. Several of the main rooms in it are so dark as to necessitate the use of electric light even at midday. It struck me as inconveniently planned and awkwardly placed. Moreover although it is on the edge of the sea, so that sea water could easily be used both for baths and for flushing drains, it has no kind of interior sanitation. 57. The buildings at Bushire seemed to me almost equally unsuccessful and inconvenient. They struck me as badly built, rambling structures, with all the drawoacks indicated above, conceived entirely in the spirit ox the India of the last century. It is true that the Residency building at Risher has an attractiveness of its own, and is not so ugly as some.- Indeed its large mosque-like open roof, with isolated bedrooms scattered among the wide white columns like tents in a viceregal camp, lias a certain exotic charm. But tne building is full of defects, and seemed to me, as in the case of Bahrein, quite unsuitable to the conditions of today. 'ven at Koweit, where a new ambitious .agency building has recently been erected, it seemed to me, speaking quite personally, that the resultk 31. (g) was far from successful. The new Koweit Agency is built of yellow brick - v.-nich I should have thought would have held the heat - and consists almost entirely of a more or less crescent shaped fa$ade, conspicuously devoid - to my mind - of artistic merit. The architecture is institutional anu military and seemed to me out of keeping with the surroundings I still cannot understand why the appropriate and attractive features of the local architecture, suen as the large central courtyards and graceful native plaster work of Bahrein, Hasa and Riyadh, can not be adopted and utilized in our own build- i ' .At Koveit a;..-.in, although the new agency is •■ithin a fe w yards of the sea, and ms only just been built, no attempt seems to have been made to instal ihtem 1 sea sanitation. I feel bound to mention these purely personal criticisms - though I do so with much diffidence and reluctance after all the friendly hospitality 1 received - since we are about - I trust - to erect a new Political residency at Bahrein, where a site has been chosen, and for wuich plans are being drawn up. It would be deplorable if what will eventually be the British headquarters in the Gulf were to be no more worthy of our position and prestige than the present buildings, I can only express the earnest hope taat trie, precedents of these buildings will not be followed, tnat tne opportunity we now have will not be missed, and that something different and better than what we have become used to will emerge. 58/32. BAHREIN TO ?1aS„ 58. We left Bahrein early on March 6 th, in a converted dhow sent from Ujair hy the Saudi Government to fetch us. It was a strange craft of XVIIth Century appearance, with a high halustraded poop covered with Persian carpets for our Benefit. 59. The journey from Bahrein to Ujair normally takes some seven hours. In spite of a choppy sea we managed to consume without undue difficulty the series of meals, endless cups of coffee, and glasses of tea provided for us By our thoughtful crew. The Dohat es Salwa Gulf, which we had to cross diagonally from North-East to South-^/esb, .is pracuicaily unsurveyed, except cursorily from the air. Our course ran through numerous reefs and shoals, and the approach to Bjair round Ras Sayia looks as though it might Be difficult to negotiate for anyone not closely familiar with these waters. The distances were all much renter than i had exp-Ctea. 60. Ujair is a tiny place consisting of one round tower, a small fort, a fairly new Customs : uilding, hall a dozen mud huts and a diminutive quay. Beside the quay lay six dhows unloading smelly sacks of fish alleged to Be used as camel food. 61. We were warmly welcomed By Sheikh Hafiz fatiba, the Saudi Minister in London, who was our host throughout the trip, and By a dozen or so local personalities. These included the Amir of Ujair, a refined and dignified old man with a melancholy smile, and the rather less attractive local Director of Customs, who knew a few words of English. While tea was Being served a Bale was Brought in containing the AraB clotnes which ...«MHi which Sheikh Hafiz had provided for us - a formidably heavy hut very fine black and gold abba for my wife, and a headress and brown abba for myself. My wife provided her own veil and eventually became skilled at shrouding herself more or less completely as circumstances required. I found my own trappings tolerable enough and a welcome means of avoiding remark in a crowd. Indeed, even my wife would sometimes take me in the distance for an Arab. But my kefiyeh was hot and tiresome in the sun, and I never learnt to keep my abba in control, so that on windy days or nights it was fatally apt to catch in thorn trees, lighted lanterns and other obstructions. 62. We left Ujair at about 4.30 with an advance convoy of 3 Ford cars and a Ford brake. The rest of our caravan was awaiting us at Hasa. 63. The route across Arabia is described by Captain de Gaury in the Air Ministry's ’’Handbook of Field Hot Saudi Arabia” (1935), and has also been described els es on ewhere by Mr. Philby and others, so that I need not describe it again here in any great detail. The following notes on our own journey and experiences may, however, be of some interest. 64. On leaving Ujair the route starts at once inland across a wide area of low dunes of wind-blown silvery sand. These grow higher and their colour grows finer as one leaves the coast- Their shapes, curves and ridges, extending to the horizon in all directions, are reminiscent of a high alpine landscape in midwinter. Near the coast, and also later towards the inland edge of the dunes, there are a few bushes and sparse tufts of grass, but the centre of the area has little or no vegetation. I understand that it is in fact a northern spur of the great south eastern desert. There is no track, but cars can cross the dunes by an apparently o • •apparently fairly well-known route without great difficulty, particularly if there has previously keen some rain to hind the sand, though the steeper edges of the dunes must he avoided. Speed is essential to reduce the risk of sinking in soft patches, and the rapid motion over the sharp rises ana falls oi the dunes is exhilarating. Pressure in the tyres is reciucea oO give a 'better grip, and cars stop every ten or lifteen miles to allow 'Wie engines to cool. 65. After 25 or 50 miles of sand dunes the route crosses a large sakkhat or salt plain, impassable in wet weather, when cars must make a wide detour to the south on to higher stonier ground. Towards the inland limit of the sand, groups oi palms began to appear, and shortly afterwards we passed two large fortified villages on the edge of the hasa oasis. The town of Hofuf, now generally called Rasa (a name formerly used omy ior tnc whole province), is about fifty miles from Uiair, and in normal conditions the run should not take more than two hours. bniubS the sand is very soft it is not difficult or tiring. HASA 66 . The Hasa oasis is large and fertile. It consists of groups of gardens separated by liotle lanes between mud walls and irrigated from the numerous large springs for whicn the oasis is famous. I was told that these gardens extend for some 20 miles from north to south and for some ten miles Iron east to icst. ii figures of the population are contradictory. Captain de G-aur} puts the population of the whole oasis at about o0,C00. On the other hand Abdurrahman Qusaibi, a prominent member of the well- known local family of that name, with whom I had much talk, asserted that the total population of the oasis was in the neighbourhood • • •&lt;^7 f 7 r neighbourhood of 200 , 000 , and that of the tovvii of Easa not less than 25,000. Certainly the tov/n seems large and (for Arabia) prosperous, and I should have been inclined to accept this figure for it. Qusaibi said that there were some 70 or 80 villages in the oasis. On our own short route I certainly saw 4- or 5. I am inclined to think, therefore, that Captain de Gaury’s figure is an underestimate. 67. The springs and gardens are most attractive. The 6 or 7 springs we visited rose perpendicularly from large well-like holes, some six to ten feet in diameter and apparently of great depth, in the middle of pools of clear water of a beautiful peacock green colour flowing over silver sand. The water is led from these pools by fast-flowing streams, generally some 6 or 8 feet wide, and distributed among the gardens, which are exceptionally fertile. The gardens are full of well-tended palm trees which bear a valuable date crop. Below these, and shaded by them from the summer heat of the sun, are orchards of peach, pomegranate, a citrus tree bearing a fruit with a very rugged skin the size of a small melon, and an excellent dwarf lime. As in the volcanic parts of Italy, the same soil will bear in addition various crops of vegetables. Some of the gardens grew only wheat and barley below the palms, and there were a few cornfields without any palms at all. The richer inhabitants of Rasa have small summer pavilions in their gardens, attractively built with high arcaded diwans. Some have charming bathing pools. ..e visited several of these gardens and found each mors delighful thar the last. Some of the springs are warm and sulphurous. Two in particular have special bathing pools, much frequented for their health-giving properties. My wife caused a mild sensation by visiting the women's half of the largest pool. The v/omen bathers were clothed from top to toe in long bathing gowns, but all hurried • • •56, hurried out of the water at her approach and formed an in quisitive circle round her 5 from which she only extricated herself with difficulty. 68 . The town of hasa has an outer wall hut also contains an inner walled city, with separate fortified gates, known as the kut or citadel. We were housed in this in an attractive guesthouse attached to the amir's Palace, and used hy King Ikn Saud on his comparatively rare visits. The guest-house was architecturally interesting, and we found it comfortable and agreeable to stay in. Its furniture was limited, of course, to the inevitable carpets and cushions on the floor, but we had the use of our camp beds and of the European chairs and tables which Sheikh Hafiz had brought for us on one of the lorries. 69. Shortly after our arrival, I was taken by Sheikh Hafiz to pay a formal call on Saud Ib-n Jiluwi, che present Amir of Hasa. Our progress along the white roofs and ramparts of the citadel, preceded by an armed retainer of the Amir’s with a lantern and a sword, had a fine dramatic atmosphere. But the • Amir himself, who had created a bad impression on Sir A. Ryan and Captain de Gaury in November, 1955, impressed me no more favourably. His expression was shifty, though this may have been partly accounted for by an extreme inward squint. He made little or no effort at conversation, and was generally unresponsive to the polite remarks which I addressed to him. His retainers, who sat in two rows at the far end of the long saloon in which I was received, seemed a gloomy crowd, and from what I heard while I was in Rasa I got the impression that he was a colourless creature with little authority or energy and unlikely to prove much of a successor to his ruthless and successful father, he were • 0037. ^ were shown his stahles with a large number of Arab horses, including some fine greys, but I gathered that he had abandoned horse-racing and was not much interested in horsemanship, and that the stud was rather going down-hill. He seemed as careless of his gardens as of his stud. But I may be doing him an injustice, for I only saw him twice and got nothing out ol him. Silence is not necessarily uncivil in Arabia, and I later found that he had sent us a car of his own as a relief on hearing that some of ours were in difficulties. 70. Our chief hosts in Hasa were the Qusaibi family, who were most assiduous in their attentions and took a gieat deal of trouble to show us round and make us comfortable. Abdurrahman Qusaibi acted as our guide and I found him agreeable and intelligent. His brother Saad, who at first impressed me less favourably, thawed as our visit went on, and, although he seemed a little suspicious of the presence of my wife and appeared to be a strictei* roslem than his brother, he parted from us when we left on the most cordial terms. My wife had the opportunity of paying an interesting visit to the ladies and children of the joint Qusaibi household. 71. The Qusaibi family play an important commercial, and indeed political, role in this part of ^rabia, and we have had reason in the past to suspect them ol creating difficulties in regard to the reopening of trade between Saudi Arabia and Koweit, in view of their special interest in trade passing through Bahrein. I would not put it past them to grind their own axes when it suits them, but on the whole I was pleasantly impressed by them on this occasion. H A S ii TO RIYADH 72. We left Hasa with regret on March 8 th. be now had our full train of four cars, four lorries and one Ford shooting brake. There were t • •88. .vere some 25 men attached to the convoy including the guides and our own Berberine servants. Our route ran at first m a north westerly direction, through changing and broken country, passing several curious ranges of sandstone hills, many of which are eroded into fantastic shapes. At the time of our journey much of the country was green, being covered by sparse grass or scrub and numerous small bushes. The colour of the hills was varied and striking. Some 50 miles from Hofuf we reached a wide area of soft sand inwhich our lorries stuck badly several times, causing some hours' delay. Hardly were the lorries out when our own car also stuck, and eventually had to be abandoned with a burnt-out clutch; but we continued in a relief car sent from Kasa. Eventually, after crossing a very large, flat, salt area (the Sabkhat et Ur aira) we reached Uraira Wells, an interesting deserted settle ment of the Ajam tribe, with several weil-huilt houses in good condition but completely deserted since the rising of 1929. There are some fine tamarisk trees at these wells, and the general appearance of the surrounding country at this time of the year was fairly fertile. A number of small caravans passed us, and severa herds of camels were being pastured in the neighbourhood. 75 , we camped for the night under the shelter of a ridge to the south of us, some 50 miles beyond Uraira. For some hours we feared we might have to sleep supperless in an open car, since several of the lorries had again stuck and others had taken wrong track following on a difference of opinion with the guide. It was a disagreeable prospect, as a gale had got ap, it had become bitterly cold, and our rugs and bedding were m the lorry. But the straying lorries were eventually almost miraculously retrieved the camp was set up at 11 p.m. and we ended by passing a comfortable night in a palatial tent, vaguely suggestive of the Field ...39 e Field of the Cloth of Gold, which had hecn provided for us by the Saudi Government. 74. It should he explained that although maps of Arabia are often dotted with names s there are, in fact, hardly any places which in any other country would have names of their own. Frequently there is no sign of human habitation - beyond a few black camel-hair Bedouin tents - for two or three hundred miles, and some of the most important wells marked on route charts and maps as conspicuous centres, consist of no more than an almost hidden hole in the ground, which can only be found by those familiar with the configuration of the hills and rocks in its vicinity. The majority of the places marked on Hunter’s and other accepted maps, which we certainly ought to have passed, appeared to be unknown, and non-existent, while many wells or conspicuous features which we did in fact see are not shown on these maps at all. A new survey seems badly needed. 75. The best-known tracks are frequently completely un marked on the ground and cars select any route they like across the flat open country; but, in certain areas where mountains or rocky outcrops close in on either side, deep wheel ruts will sometimes continue for miles. These, however, often offer worse going than the open plain, since they are apt to be worn so deep in the soft ground as to make it difficult for any car that has not got an exceptionally high clearance to run in them without striking its under-carriage. This is particularly the case in the sandy areas, where the wheel ruts rapidly become too deep to follow, while the sand itself is often deceptive, and what seems to be a hard patch will prove so soft that even the lightest car will stick in it. On the other hand, there are generally 20 or 30 men attached to each convoy, and they seem to take the extri cation 0*040. which • • • extrication of cars from sand-drifts as a matter of course. I give full marks to the men of our own convoy for unfailing cheer fulness and perseverance in the laborious work of extricating cars from drifts and bogs, as against all this 5 there are many long stretches of gravel or hard earth where the going is almost as good as on Daytona Beach. 76. The country we traversed on March 9th was, for the most part, a kind of steppe which, at this time of the year, was well-covered with thin vegetation, including a great many small flowering plants and low bushes. Towards mid-day, we dropped from a high stony rather barren tableland on to the Dahana belt. Although this is marked as sandy on most maps and contains a few streaks and patches of sand, it is for the most part flat, open featureless but fairly green grazing country extending unbrokenly to the furthest horizon in all directions. There were a large number of camels, in this area, some of which were milked for us. We found the fresh milk excellent. 77. After some 120 miles we left the Dahana for slightly more broken country of a different type and stopped at about 4.30 at an important group of wells known as Hamah. Here a message reached us from the Amir Saud at Riyadh suggesting that we should halt at his hunting-camp of Rumheya, some 10 or 15 miles further on, although he would not be there himself. As we were already late it was eventually arranged that we should spend the night in the campt where we were luxuriously housed in the amir’s own tent - a large double pavilion, as usual carpeted with fine Persian rugs but furnished only with cushions on the floor. 78. Our visit to this camp .was an interesting experience. After inspecting the camp, I joined the men at their evening meal,which was the usual Arab dinner of sheep roasted whole, eaten with the hand without knives or forks. I found the proceedings somewhat complicated. The initial attack with one hand only on the smooth surface of a freshly cooked leg of mutton is embarraas- ing. I will not describe my own clumsy effort at it. But I was relieved to realise that one was not expected to make a large meal to eat everything placed before one. It was apparently legitimate to make a selection of the titbits pressed on one by friendly hands, and I was able to avoid many of the more unappetising morsels without causing undue offence. Incidentally, ■ and for the benefit of future travellers, I may say I found the tongue definitely preferable to the eye. 79. Before we left Rumheya camp early next morning (March 10th) three herds of camels, a large herd of black desert sheep and the Amir's hawks were marshalled group by group for our inspection. They were a fine sight which I shall long remember. The hawks were particularly alluring birds. They each answered to their names, and seemed to be very jealously tended by the respective keepers. 80. We left at about 8 a.m. in a large Buick car sent by the Amir Saud for us, and reached Riyadh at 11 after a 3 hours' run over increasingly stony desert country. The track crosses two ridges of hills by very steep gradients, and there are some fine views of distant mountains of a curious purplish red colour; the general elevation of the plateau steadily increases as one goes westwards. I was unable to take the total distance from Hasa to Riyadh on our own speedometers owing to our frequent changes of cars, but Captain de Gaury gives it as 520 kilometers, i.e. 325 miles. We were met a few miles from Riyadh by Mahomed Shalhoub, the aged but still vigorous director of finance of Rejd, whom the Amir Saud had sent out to greet us. I understand that he is a sort of Grand Old man of local politics. We saw a good deal of him and I rather liked him. RIYADH.: 2 e RIYADH cl. Yhe compcirati a/ eiy lertile oasis o! Riyadh lies on a high stony table land bare or any other vegetation. The town is surrounded by a wall ±rom 15 to 2 U feet high with the usual towers and gates, but is smaller and poorer than Rasa. It is dominatel by tne Royal Palace, a high strongly xortiiied structure, and a network of palaces occupied by Ibn Baud's sons, which are ai.tacneu to the main palace by passages and archways. In front of the fliaxii entrance of the palace there is a large open square where the beduin collect when they come to see Ibn Baud in the summer. Along one sice of this there is a guest house where the tribal Sheikhs are housed and where they and their tribesmen are fed for a period of three days,at the King's expense. The bazaars, which I visited next day under the escort of the Chief or Police, struck me as poor. They were as usual filled with inferior Japanese, CzecuoSlovak and German articles. Rice, spices and some other consumption goods come from India. almost the only native produce appeared to be dates and seeds, and rather crudely painted doors. for British trade to attempt to compete would be as useless as for Harrods to attempt to compete with ’•colvcrtVs in a slum. Gs. he were housed in the new Radia Palace some 4 or 5 miles north west oi t e town on the edge of the comparative].'/ fertile wadi Hanifa. This is one of two summer palaces built by the King and the Amir Staid, standing against a long line of gardens somewhat similar, but inferior, to the gardens of Hasa* Peaches are cultivated below the palm trees, which shelter them from ..„45 . from the summer surij but they are poorer in quality than those of ilasa, and I saw no citrus. But there were a fair number of walled-in corniields, particularly higher up the Wadi Hanifa, at Dereyah and Aweina. All these gardens, like those nearer the town, are irrigated from numerous deep wells, the water of which is pulled up in skins by teams of white donkeys - generally 6 or 4 to a well. The creaking of the pulleys of these wells - each on a slightly different note - is a curious and constant sound, known locally as the donkey's orchestra. 83. The new Badia Palace is a charming building looking over attractive gardens at the back arid built round two colonnaded courts. The style of architecture and interior decoration is striking and original. Both this style and the somewhat different &gt; style of the buildings of Hasa might well form usexul models for some of the new buildings which we shall certainly have to erect in the near future in the minor Arab states of the Persian Gulf.* I do not wish to overload this report with unnecessary descriptions - but I took a number of photographs of these buildings which are available if required. 84. The Amir Baud received us in his palace in Riyadh shortly after our arrival and was exceedingly cordial and friendly. He was full of reminiscences of his visit to London in t 1 'e summer of 1935, and of pleasurable anticipation of his impending visit for the Coronation. It was arranged that he should come back and lunch with us informally at the Badia Palace. We therefore returned thither with His Royal Highness in a very gorgeous royal car, with two of the royal ... Cf. paragraph 57 above.44. r °y - 1 00 ( i 2 ^gaaid in brilliant scarlet and gold uniiorms, armed with riiles and swords s standing on the steps 5 and a relief car imn^d^ctuly beniiid. All this escort pi*oved xully necessary, as the iinal approach to the Badia Palace is across the soft sand of tne Wadi Haniia in which cars almost invariably stick and out of which they have to be ignominiously pushed. Ours was no exception. 8b. We had four or live meetings with the Amir, and dined with him quietly in his palace on the evening of March lithe On that occasion we brought our own Berberineservants, so that my wife could be unveiled. He proved a charming host. 88 There were only two occasions on which political subjects were discussed. The first was when the Amir received us on the morning oi March 11th in a small room in the presence of five or six of his cousins and other members oi the Saudi Royal family. After a little general conversation he explained that he wished to take the opportunity oi their presence to say publicly and formally before them all, what might carry less weight if said privately, that the key-stone or Saudi policy was friendship with Great Britain. He hoped that this guiding principle would always be maintained. I replied that I knew that His Majesty’s Government were actuated in their relations with Saudi Arabia by similar principles, but that the wisdom and sound judgment of King Ibn Saud had fik^de the task oi drawing our relations closer very much easier for us. 87. The second occasion was at dinner the same evening, when the amir said that, although he did not wish to discuss politics in general, he could not refrain from asking me for some explanation oi the situation, and of recent events, in Spain. I aid my best to give His Royal Highness a clear and impartial account oi the origin and development of the present trouble, quoting some— 45» of my own experiences when I had been myself a Secretary at Madrid many years earlio. o I laid particular stress on the efforts which His Majesty's Government had made to prevent the present wretched civil war from spreading and leading to wider hostilities in Europe. I emphasised the part which Mr. Eden and Lord Plymouth had played in this effort, and the measure of success which had been achieved by the Mon-Intervention Committee under Lord Plymouth’s guidance. In the hope 01 avoiding too much tedious solemnity I told the amir that since the Spanish war had become so largely a matter for foreign armies, it was now being currently rumoured in Europe that General Franco and Senor Largo Caballero were about to apply lor membership of the Non- Intervention Committee. He seemed to appreciate the suggestion. 88 . The atmosphere of the palace at Riyadh struck me as purely mediaeval. I received the impression or a civilisation and an outlook on liie based on standards and a sense of values remote from those or the modern world, and in many ways more admirable - or at least more consistent and less materialistic. Incidentally I was much struck by the natural dignity and fine bearing of the Amir's retainers, of whom there were always some 20 or 50 at hand. They were for- the most part good looking. virile men with clear cut intelligent face: The scene was reminiscent of the best drawings of Eric Mennington. Like most Arabs of ^rabia they had a keen sense of humour, and seemed a cheerful company, although life in Riyadh can possess but few compensations. 89. On the other hand some of the notorious faults of the46 the Arab character were irach in evidence. Iruprovidence and lack of practical eniciency v/ere conspicuous« Small instances were for example the condition of the ro^d to the Badia Palace, to which I have already referred. .apart from the sand drift of the V/adi Hanifa, it was impeded by every sort of unnecessary obstruction. A few days labour 'would have sulk iced to make the track reasonably practicable. But no exhort was ever made to deal with it, although cars use it many times a day and must suffer constant needless depreciation in consequence. Again, there is round Riyadh an abundance of excellent stone. But practically all buildings are built 01 mud, and are apt to fall at a touch. At the Badia Palace itself one of our cars struck a column supporting the roof of a garage shed. It proved to be of painted mud and loose stones, and immediately crumbled, letting down a large section of the roox. Larger buildings often melt awaydu dng exceptionally hec.vy rain, and every ceiling showed traces of the last storm. Fo doubt,the methods of administration in Riyadh itself would xurnish many much more serious instances of incapacity. There were of course no signs of any attempt at sanitation, and the spread of disease can only be checked by the excellency of the air and the power oi the sun. In Riyadh itself, and more particularly in the kadi Hanifa, there seems no lack ox water, and the instalment ol a few pumps might produce a much improved and far less wasteful supply. 90. Before we left Riyadh we paid a visit to the ruins of Dereyah, the ancient capital - still a remarkable monument of the ancient greatness cl the Wahabis. The surrounding gardens seemed particularly rich and prosperous, and there were some signs of resettlement in progress. RIYADH • 0947. RIYADH TO T-iIF 91. »/e left Riyadh - after much typically unnecessary delay - at 10.00 a.m. on March 10. The route we followed leaves Riyadh by a wide bend to the north, passing the striking ruins and long straggling modern village ox Aweyna (given by Philby as Ayaina) lying among cornfields towards the head of the fertile i^adi Manila some seventeen miles from Riyadh. Thence the track climbs through a green valley to a low pass and crosses into a new type of rather barren country between the great red bluffs of ihe Tuwaiq Hills. after crossing some wide grass-covered plains, it skirts the south edge of the curious brilliant coral coloured sands ol the Nefud Turaif. There are three fortified villages on this sector of the route - Barra, awainid, and - after a long stretch ox plain - Marat. The latter, winch 107 miles from Riyadh, is built of deep red mud reminiscent of parts of Devon, and stands among many fertile looking palm gardens. After this the scenery changes again to a plain of basalt outcrops, and then the route crosses the worst and longest area of sand we had 3 r et encountered,tHenKeiud el Sirr. Ye found that the only comparatively safe track across this was along the deep and uneven wheel ruts of former travellers; and for about an hour we were buffetted along this track at high speed, xor xear ex sticking, with all the sensations of being in a small skiff on an exceedingly rough sea. Eventually we reached Duwadmi (about tw r o hundred miles irom Riyadh), an ■' insignificant little village, with a fev r wells and a large fort and petrol store. Except for the fort a l Muweih two hundred and xiity miles further on, this is the only fixed human habitation between Marat and Tail', a distance of nearly rive hundred miles. All the rest ox our convoy, including our tents, camo «.o47 48, camp beds and food, had stuu’c icr the night in the sanns ol the Nefud el Sirr, So we were housed in the guest room o± the ioi u (clean, carpeted and becushioned but otherwise rare), wnere we slept supperless but in tolerable contort on the tloor. Fortunately we had some biscuits and mineral water with us - am a small surreptitious Ilash. 92« Our next day’s run, on March lb, was just under two hundred miles. The route ran at nirst through grcuiit^ c Aiiiury with high oddly shaped, tors, and later across wide silvery green plains fringed with jagged rose coloured and purple hills. we met, particularly at the well of Afif, a number of tightly packed lorry loads of pilgrims returning iron Mecca to Eastern Arabia - the camel caravan route runs further to Mne south, so that w r e only passed mrs. we eventually iound a good camping ground among large sulam bushes, at D^iina. wells. we had now recovered most of our convoy and slept very coinortc^oly in car own tent. One or the food lorries was still lost, but tne personnel oi the convoy made up lor this by killing and eating a sheep which they had purchased at Duwadmi, and whose melancholy face, looking over the side of the lorry, and filled wita presentiment of doom, had haunted us at intervals all nay. 9b. On March 14 we had a shorter and easier run than usual, from Daiina to Ashaira. mter crossing a wide sabkhat or flat salt plain (the Sabkhat Daiina - described by Philby as the Khabra Khal), parts of which were so thickly covered with salt as to look like ilelds of freshly lallen snow, we reached Muweih ...95o e © © 49. Muweih xort and petrol store ? a gloomy structure built of black basalt, surrounded by heaps of refuse and empty petrol drums. According to Sheikh Haxiz this point marks the boundar- oetween Fejd and the Hejaz, which begins immediately to the west above a long dark brown escarpment of igneous rock. dhe routevhich had been taking an increasingly southerly direction, here turns due south. Afterr running down the sandy kadi Huwwa for a lew miles it leads on to a wide light gravel plain known as the kuqba, fairly thickly covered with salam bushes, some reacning to ten feet in height. Going is excellent and three cars abreast were able at times to get up to seventy miles an hour, although we were still steadily rising. After this we crossed a wet patch of sandy soil where a rain storm had burst the previous day, &lt;-,nu where one of our cars had to be laboriously extricated ircm a bog. Soon after this the track crossed a corner of the great Harra belt of black volcanic boulders which lay to the west of us, and almost immediately alter, at about 5 p.m. v/e reached Ashaira wells. These wells are about 4, 7 00 feet above the sea, loQ .•il^s from Dafina and some 950 miles from Riyadh. The place is one of Ibn Baud’s xavourite carping sites, in attractive park-like country, just under the south edge oi the narra. Almost ao ohe same moment (by skilful synchronization) Sir Reader Bullard and Mr. Eyres arrived, having come up t e day’s journey irom Gedda to meet us. 94. After a pleasant night in camp ^t Ashaira we left uhe next morning for Tail where we arrived at 10.50 a.m. on March is. The total distance from Riyadh to Taif by this route was just under six hundred miles. We had come about 1125 miles from Ujair.TAIF AND 3H/1FA 50 c 95. Taif was a disappointment to me - at any rate at first sight. It lies badly, where the north-east foothills of the Shafa mountains meet the Central Arabian plateau, and has no view to speak of. Most of the town outside the old walls is still in ruins from the days of the Great War or of that against the Hashimites, and most of what is not in ruins is unfinished. The pavilion and guest house where we were lodged were exceptions, were pretty and well built and had a pleasant garden with a foun tain. But most of the town - even within the old walls, where tall semi-Turkish houses still stand with some air of dignity and there are a couple of tolerable Mosques - bears a decaying and derelict look, 96. We were received with the usual quietly solicitous cordiality - the Arabs we met never fussed. Sentries and an armed guard of be-khakied Hejazi troops were posted at our gate and presented arms meticulously and smartly whenever we passed. The Amir of Taif and his Secretary and Aide-de-Camp came to greetus.cncur arrival, and the accommodation put at our disposal was comfortable and clean. But on the first day we only stayed an hour or so, as a further expedition had been planned for us, which it may perhaps be worth briefly describing, 97. Sheikh Hafiz had insisted from the first that we must visit the mountains of Shafa, south of Taif, and scale a hilltop that would have shown us all the Tihama. The climb was to be three hours from the end of the last practicable car track and we were to begin cur ascent at 2 p.m. It was typical of '.rabia that, when we were already late at the meeting point, our hosts must needs have51. a six course luncheon cooked ? and a tent set up for us to eat it in, so that we started the climb well after four. 98. he were a long caravan mounted on ponies and donkeys with two camels bringing up our bedding. The track climbed thrown fine valleys between rising granite hills past apparently unnameo villages, or rather groups of huts, each with its fort and wat^h tower dating from precarious Turkish and Hashimite days. To each group there would be two or three wells, worked by donkeys or lightly built Indian humped cattle, and perhaps a dozen cornfields and orchards enclosed by mud or granite wails. Then a climb among granite boulders up a hillside rich with lavender in full flower, to what we thought our final ridge. 99o Here our last hope of reaching our mountain top before nightfall vanished, and it was settled we should sleep in a 7,000 feet high village, where some of us set up our hods in the fort and others in the open on the terrace outside it. A meal was produced, and we spent the rest of the evening watching the villagers and our own escort vying with each other round a camp fire in a competition of extempore verse, dance and song, which was one of the strangest spectacles we witnessed during our journey. 100. Next day we had no choice but to return to Taif, Sheikh Hafiz bewailing the almost American haste which had placed his mountain top out of our reach. I shared his disappointment - but we had promised to lunch with the Amir of .Taif, and it would have been fatal to fail him. Besides we had had a fair sight of the mountain country, which had exceeded y expectations. 101. Our luncheon with the Amir was successful but unin spiring. He was almost as silent as the Amir of Hasa, though his manner . O o(g) 52. manner was charmingly courteous and his pleasant and rather melancholy smile disarming. Such conversation as there was was suitable and firendly - but ininformative. The Amir's house viere we ate, seated at a long table in the European manner, sue vied- like most things in Tail* - signs of ruin and decay. The windows were partly shuttered with packing case planks marked in English i! This side up, with care'A Art Sheikh dafiz spoke well oi His Excellency, who made a good impression on Sir R. Bullard, and who certainly took a lot of trouble to give us a good reception. 102. After the luncheon we visited the gardens of the Leiyah valley, some 15 miles e^st of Taif. The valley is rich in water at a depth of a few feet only, and the gardens irrigated from these shallow wells extend for a length of some thirty miles. There are few palms, but a great deal of corn and fruit orchards of various kinds, notably lemons, apricots and quince. v;e were given tea on the terrace of a large and well built house in one of the numerous villages scattered along the valley and were told that this was a favourite summer camping ground of the Amir Reisal, who, as Viceroy of hecca and Linister for Foreign Affairs has to spend most of the year in the Hejaz. T.ilF TO Jim,. 103. Re left Taif on March 17th for Jedda. Through Mecca the journey only takes five hours, hut this route was closed to us as non-Moslems. The Wadi Fatima - a seven or eight hour alternative route known as the Christians' way - was reported impassable for cars owing to recent rain. So we were obliged to make a great detour to the north of Ashaira to strike the Arabian Mining ...53 o Mining Syndicate's nevy road through the volcanic Karra, and thus spent some 12 hours on the journey» 104. I made detailed notes of the route, which is an un usual one, and which, though for the most part tedious, has the advantage of having a toieraole and well engineered road for a great part of its length. But I understand that the Mining Syndicate may he able to let us have their own maps and route notes, so my own rougn notes can go into cold storage, and need only be very briefly summarized here. 10^ o Some ten miles after Ashaira i.e. some 60 miles north of Taif, the route strikes at right angles the Mining Syndicate's road from Jedda to their mine at Lahad. Gold has been found in the mine, but work is held up for lack of water. The route then fol lows tne Syndicate's road westwards for endless miles across the Harra - a desperately dreary wilderness entirely covered with black lava boulders of varying size. Eventually it drops from the edge ° f thS Plateau by vve11 g ra(ie( i curves, falling from shelf to shelf nncon ioothills until it reaches the semi-tropical coastal plain. Parts of the descent through the foothills are fine, and there is one ° pa ” Lm ” rove oasis at Madhraqa where we lunched, and finally Shed our Arab clothes. After Another 70 miles or so the road leave* the mountains altogether and emerges on the Red Sea coast to the north of Jedda, where its construction seems to have beer, abandoned and cars have to plough through some miles of heavy sand. . + 106 ‘ We Were met 0Utslde Jedda by the Kaimakam and an Under eCrt fr ° m th ® Saudi For eign Office,with a small escort of A puncture at this moment rather spoilt the effect of our entry ...54, entry, but we eventually reached His Majesty’s Legation soon aiter A, so p.m. The distance from Taif by this route was approximately 225 miles. Our total distance from Ujair had been 1550 miles. JLDDA AND KING I3N SAU'Dc 107. I had arranged to stay with Sir R. Bullard at Jedda, but on the eve of our arrival my plan was nearly wrecked on the rock of the Arab code of hospitality, which apparently demands that the stranger shall be your guest until he leaves your country. Arrangements were, it seemed, already in train to place a palace at our disposal, and it required much tactful diplomacy to convince the Saudis without offence that the Legation was the right place for us to stay in. 108. King Ibn Saud had been at Mecca all through February for the Pilgrimage and when we arrived was paying one of his rare visits to Jedda before his return to Riyadh. Sir R. Bullard had had one short meeting with him - his first since he had taken up his post - and was to have his second - for the purpose of present ing his new credentials - on the morning of March 18th. It was arranged that I should be presented to the King immediately after this ceremony. 109. The palace lies a mile or two south-east of Jedda, where, according to His Majesty, there are breaths of desert air and he car- escape from the stuffiness of the town. It is an adequate though modest two-storied modern building approached by a reasonably good desert track. I was met at the entrance by Bheikh Hafiz and a secretary and escorted up a stairway past rows of Kejdi retainers, all armed with rifles or swords, and suggesting Kennington’s drawings no . o ©55. no less than did the Amir's retainers in Riyadh, to a wide sunbaked terrace with more retainers who stood to attention as I passed. At the far side of the terrace was a large diwan or reception room with a square open bay at its furthest side where the King sat on a high settee with open lightly barred windows round and behind him. when we later sat in this bay, the effect was as though we were in the open air, - an appropriate atmosphere for our discussions,and incidentally a very refreshing way of holding a long meeting. The King watched me narrowly as I walked alone with such slow dignity as I could muster, first across the sunlit terrace and then through tne dark ciiwan. But this was my only ordeal. He received me wi ih the utmost friendliness, which hadevery appearance of being genuine. 110. King Ton Baud's photographs do him scanty justice, and quice fail to suggest the extraordinary charm of his personality, x’o± one thing, uhey are nearly all full face, with the result that his features seem heavier, and his expression more rigid, than in reality. His fAce, though massive, and cast in the same generous mould as the rest of his person, is not ponderous or immobile, but finely proportioned and intensely full of vitality and mobility of expression. he has a well-shaped, aquiline nose, an immensely strong chin, and a curiously disarming smile. It is easy to understand uhe ruthlessness of which he has so often showed himself capable, and I do not want to exaggerate his charm; but the general impression ne gives at first sight - or at least gave me, and not at first sight only - is one of kindliness and straightforwardness, and one finds oneself feeling an instinctive liking for the man from one’s first meeting. The large scale of his mind and outlook is at once apparent. ...apparent 0 He obviously dislikes the irrelevant, the pernickety or the tedious - though he can sometimes lose himself a little in reminiscence, particularly to a new listener. Like other rare large-minded men, he seems to bring fresh air into any disc .ssion, to brush away trivialities, and to inspire in others a similar broad method of approach. It is perilous to attribute complete sinceiity to anyone where international politics are concerned, a.nd iO aoubt there are some matters - such as the frontiers and the Koweit blockade - where for his own reasons Ibn Saud is in no iiurry to settle with us. But, subject to this caveat, I would say that ± na'/e seldom met anyone who gave me so strong an impression of sincerity and directness. 111. The King sat generally cross-leg ed and shoeless, on a high settee in the middle of the bay. Sir R. Bullard and Sheikh Yusuf Yasin sat along one side of the bay on his right, and I and Sheikh Hafiz Wahba along the other on his left. ..hen the Amir Pei sal joined us, he sat below Sheikh Hafiz. All the talks we had were pleasantly informal, and at all our business meetings the translation was very skilfully performed by Sir R. Bullard and oheikh Hafiz wahba, the former translating into English and the latter into Arabic. Sir R. Bullard's knowledge of Arabic was, of C0U1 ° e ? invalua ble, and has done much to smooth his path with The King. But the King generally spoke so clearly and slowly, and with so personal a note, that I found myself occasionally almost catching his meaning, even where I could not understand the words. 112. At tnis first preliminary interview Sheikh IL.fiz was not iJreSent ’ and Isinail Efendi ' the very capable Legation interpreter - took his place. The King enquired about our journey, and 1 thanked him o o •57. him warmly for all he had done for us, for the very complete and successful arrangements which had Deenraaie to meet or forestall our every want, and for the way in which the Amir Saud had re ceived and entertained us at Riyadh. I also expressed special appreciation of the untiring efforts which Sheikh Kafiz had made for us and for all that he had done for us on our journey, and I made one or two other suitable acknowledgments. I expressed my deep regret that I could not speak Arabic, saying that I was like a man who was deaf and dumb, but that I could still use my eyes. The King seemed to like this comparison, and repeated how useful it was to meet people face to face; no amount of correspondence could mean as much as personal discussion, even when it had to be carried on through an interpreter. After some further conversation on these lines, I said that I had been particularly impressed by the complete security I had found in the desert, which we had crossed practically unarmed, and where, although there had for centuries been insecurity, conditions now seemed more peaceful than in many European states. Ibn Saud replied that this was not his doing, but was due to the facts that the people of his kingdom were united by their religion, that they were true to their principles and that they knew that he was devoted to the welfare of all of them, even the humblest, and that there was equal j stice for all. I made an appropriate rejoinder, and, although at one moment the shadow of Palestine flitted across the conversation, the interview could hardly have been more cordial or encouraging. lib. Shortly after our interview with the King, Sir R. Bullard took me to call on the Mir Feisal, who is titular Minister for Foreign Affairs. Sheikh Hafiz wahba and Sheikh Yusuf Yasin were both . O O58. both present. The conversation was general, and non-politica.1, for the nost part about the Amir's various visits to England, and the friends and acouaintances he had made there. ao this inter view I thought the hvlv looked older, thinner, and more listless than when I had seen him last in the summer of 1952, but he brightened up later, and my wife, who met him a few days later in the Palace, when calling on some of the gueens, thought that he seemed brighter and happer than when she had last seen him in England. I find it hard to believe however, that he will ever prove a ruler. 114. The same night the King gave a dinner party for some 80 guests. Practically all the Legation staff were invited, but no other foreigners (except I r. PKilby, who is virtually a member of the court), the remaining guests being Arabs. The dinner was in a long narrow room in the Palace, and was served in European fashion, our own Berberine servants being called in to help. It was well managed and well cooked. Sir R. Bullard sat on the King's right and I on his left with Sheikh Hafiz beside re to interpret. 115* The King was in excellent form, and, even through an interpreter, a stimulating conversational companion. He talked well about a number of subjects. Someone having mentioned national characteristics, I told him the old series of definitions and distinctions between one, two and three Englishmen, Germans, Frenchmen, etc. — a chestnut which was fortunately new to him, and which he apparently appreciated. He spoke with heat and feeling about the evils of European dictatorships, of which he is clearly nervous. (lie would, I think, hardly class himself as a dictator, as he would say he was only the interpreter and trustee of accepted princirles .. u59. « principles, acting with the support and approval of his people). I gathered that he distrusted Soviet Russia and Turkey no less than Italy and Germany, regarding them as equally totalitarian and koth dangerously anti-religious. 116. He has a pleasant sense of humour and an appropriate jest delights him. He had a great joke with Sir R. Bullard about a Saudi shell which fell near the British Agency in 1925 when Ibn Baud was besieging Jedda, and oir R. Bullard was British Agent thpre. The King clearly felt this had placed him under a special obligation to Sir Reader, whose providential escape was prophetic of their present friendship. On another occasion I told His Majesty how, when the Amir Baud had visited Ascot in 1935, his retainers had proved such good judges of horse-flesh that some of my colleagues had so far forgotten themselves as to contemplate forming a syndicate to exploit their talents. Unfortunately, at this point their good advice had broken down, and the project had had to be ignominously abandoned. The King followed up this ssory, with a view, he told me, with a twinkle in his one good eye, to reprimanding severely those who had dared to give 'his friends' such bad advice; but he then found that the delinquents were not Arabs from Nqjd at all, but two oyrians attached to the Amir’s suite. ^his pleased him greatly, and the next day he told me that ne had discovered the source of the trouble, advice of Syrians about horses', His Majesty n If you will take the said, 'what else can you expect.'' 117. Though simple in his personal tastes - he is plainly dressed, likes fresh air and early hours, and always seems eager to g6t D '' Ck to the aesert ~ he keeps up considerable state, has three huge special negro slaves in scarlet robes to wait on him, and a host o o •60 . host of retb.iners within cull, and when he goes to the Jedda mosques for Friday prayer, has a Ford lorry in the procession with a rather sinister machine gun ready mounted to deal drastically with any disturbance. The Hejaz has of course never whole heartedly accepted Nejdi domination. 110. The next day, March 19th, it was arranged that - Sir R. Bullard and I should have a series of conversations with Sheixh Tusuf Yasin and Sheikh Kafiz Wahba on outstanding Anglo- Saudi questions. As Sir R. Bullard has explained in his despatches Nos. 40 and 54 of March 23rd and April 1st, Fuad Bey Hcjnza hu.d unexpectedly left «jedna, for reasons at which we could oftly guesb. We had several long conversations of some importance. We spent the whole morning discussing the question of the South- hastern Arabian frontiers. A full record of this conversation and of subsequent developments regarding the frontier question is contained in Sir R. Bullard's despatch No. 47 of March 27. As recorded by Sir R. Bullard, I subsequently found an opportunity to raise this particular question with King Ibn Saud himself, (see paragraph 1^5 below) but Mis Majesty's attitude suggested that it may be difficult to reach an early settlement of it. In the afternoon, we had another long meeting at which we discussed the questions of Koweit smuggling and of the Transjordan frontier. Sir .. 0121 /,.. Sir R. Bullard has reported separately on these two discussions in his despatches No. 52 of April 1, and No. 42 of March 23, respectively. I think these talks did a good deal to clear the air and to dissipate unnecessary misunderstanding. Sir R. Bullard has also reported separately (see his despatch No. 54 of April 1st) on an interesting confidential conversation which we had with oheikh Hafiz .«ahba after a small luncheon party which Sir R. Bullard gave that do.y to some of our Arab friends. 119. Sheikh Yusuf made a not unfavourable impression on me. He struck me as less intelligent than Fuad Bey, nervous lest his master should think he had given something away, and dee-ly suspicious of possible snags, particularly in any proposals we put forward. But he became more and more friendly as our dis cussions proceeded, and I think we succeeded in disarming some oi his woist initial suspicions. On the whole I think he may be easier to deal with th^n Fuad, and I should be inclined to rate his sincerity and honesty reasonably high. l-oi:. On the evening of the 19th the Amir Feisal gave a dinner at the j ddn house of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, which followed the general lines of the King's dinner on a smaller scale. The combination of many hours of argument with Sheikh Yuoiil j cAXi of the sudden plunge into the hot and relaxing air of Jed la after the invigorating air of the central deserts, must have begun to tell on me, for I found it rather unnecessarily heavy going. Nothing passed of any interest.62 . 121. On Saturday the 20th we embarked on the scries of conversations with King Ibn oaud which bir R. Bullard has so fully and accurately reported in his despatch No. 41 of March 25rd and to which he has referred in other despatches and telegrams, notably his telegrams Nos. 20 of March 24, and 26 of March 28. I need therefore do no more here than briefly mention a few of the more important points which arose in the course of our talks. 122. The King was clearly anxious about the situation in the Yemen, which he regarded as full of danger. He was disturbed also about any possible threat to his own security which might follow on a collapse of authority in the Yemen and possible foreign intervention in that country. He clearly would have welcomed some sort of British guarantee against such an emergency. Bir R. Bullard and I explained to him why any such guarmtee was impossible, but we drew His Majesty's attention to the declaration contained in the Rome Understanding of 1927 (the text of which had already been communicated to him and of which Bir R. Bullard gave him a further copy) to the effect that His Majesty's Government regarded it as a vital British imperial interest that no European Power should establish itself on the Arabian coast of the Red Bea. I suggested that it could reasonably be assumed from this that any threat by a European Power to the independence and integrity of Baudi Arabia would involve a threat to our own imperial interests. If therefore a conflict developed it would almost certainly be a general one, in which we should also be involved, and in that event it was difficult to see any circumstances in which we should not find ourselves aligned side by side. I could not of course speak officially, and I was only giving my own impressions, for what they were worth,125. 65. worth, but this was how I read the situation 0 6 ir R. Bullard endorsed my views and emphasized that community of interests was often a stronger bond than many alliances. I afterwards heard from bheikh Hafiz Y/ahba that this conversation had given King Ibn o&amp;ud great satisfaction, and had served to allay some of His Majesty's anxieties. bheikh Yusuf Yasin later spoke in a similar sense to bir R. Bullard (sec oir R. Bullard's telegram No. 25 of March 25). 125. On another occasion, King Ibn baud having asked why we had not wished the Arab rulers in the Persian Gulf under our protection to accede to the oaudi-Iraqi treaty, I took the opportunity to emphasize that, while His Majesty's Government desired, and would always respect, the independence and integrity of baud! Arabia and of the independent Arab btates, the Arab btates under our protection were in a different category. From the international point of view, these btates were under our suzerainty. Our relations with them were of very long standing (I took the opportunity to explain their origin) and not only gave us certain righi-s, but also involved us in certain obligations. It was for this reason that His Majesty's Government were so anxious to clear up the question of the south eastern Arabian frontiers. It was clear, however, that the King was extremely reluctant to commit himself to any final settlement of this question. 124. Another point of special importance which was raised by King Ibn baud was the question of Palestine. I have recorded my impressions of the King's attitude on this question in a separate memorandum which I submitted on April 12, and bir R. Bullard has also referred to the matter in his telegram No. 20 of March 24 and in subsequent communications. I will not therefore develop this point further here; but it was clear that it was one on which the King felt very strongly.64- e 125. Lastly, it is perhaps worth drawing attention to the declaration, which King Ihn baud made more than once, that, rather than be untrue to his religion or his principles, he would gladly give up his throne. My impression was that his religious principles are strong and genuine, and that in making this declaration he meant what he said. 126. On the afternoon of March 20 we attended a tea-parcy given by Sheikh Abdulla buleiman, the Minister of Finance, mainly with the object of enabling King Ton baud to meet my wife. The marked cordiality with which he received her, and the departure which this entailed fccmhis usiio-l practice in regard to Kuropean ladies, have been sufficiently reported in bir R. Bullard's despatch ho. 40 of March 25. 127. On the evening of March 20th we all dined with Mr. Philby at his house outside the town. Mr. Philby is an old acquaintance of mine, and, though I am under no illusions about his failings, I have always appreciated his good qualities. He was friendly and interesting, but I was by that time too tired to make as much of the evening as I should have liked. My wife, however, had a good deal of interesting and useful conversation with him. 128. In the intervals of meetings with the King and of official entertainment, I managed to see practically the whole of the British and American colony at Jedda and one or two of the foreign representatives - mostly at tea or sherry parties given by bir R. Bullard, who is a very popular host. The British colony consists of the staff of His Majesty’s Legation., the engineers attached to the Saudi Arabian Mining Syndicate, and the staff of the various other British enterprises and institutions which carry on a more or less precarious existence in Saudi Arabia. The American colony consists mainly of the headquarters65. headquarters staff of the American Oil Company, which is endeavouring-to find oil in Hasa. This is a branch, known as the California-Arabian Oil Company, of the standard Oil Company of California, and works in close association with the Bahrein Oil Company (see paragraph 55 above). Mr. Thornburg and Mr. Davies, two directors of the American parent Company, and Mr. Hamilton, their London representative, were also in Jedda. We had already met them in Bahrein and they had followed us across Arabia in rapid stages in two light Ford cars. They were extremely friendly and when we left gave us a great send off on board our ship. It is doubtful, however, whether oil will be found in Hasa in commercial quantities, and the future of the Company is there fore still uncertain. If the enterprise fails it will be a great blow for Ibn baud, who desperately needs some reliable source of revenue. The only other foreigners I met were the new Italian Minister - 'who did not impress me very favourably, although he did not appear to be ill-intentioned and took some trouble to be civil, and his Vice-Consul, a Levantine Italian, whose looks I did not fancy, M. Maigret, the French Minister, who has recently returned from the Yemen and is a somewhat notorious figure in Jedda, was ill, but sent me a very civil card of apology and regret for not having been able to call on me c 129. Apart from this, my time was too limited and too full of official engagements to enable me even to see the town and bazaars. My wife, however, was able to see a little, and notably to pay a most interesting visit to King Ibn Baud’s favourite wife Umm Mansur (i.e. ’’the mother of [the Amir] Mansur’ - since a woman is nearly always known in Arabia as the mother of such and such a son, if she has one). It would■■■■paHHB iwji. «i|P &lt;x u — 66 . would be beyond the scope of this report to reproduce my wife's description of this visit, but it is perhaps worth noting that, according to confidential information we had received, Uram Mansur was originally a Christian girl from the Lebanon, sent by the Turks to Ibn baud as a gift in the early days of the war. I gather she now seemed happy enough, and she impressed my wife as a woman of personality and character. 150o Jedda is so well known that it is unnecessary for me to say much about it in this report, which is already too long. But there are two points on which a word or two may perhaps not be out of place. The first is the great contrast I found between the climate of Jedda and that of all the other parts of Arabia I visited. Up to the western edge of the Hejaz hills, where we began dropping down to the coastal plain, the climate had been dry and invigorating, and we had hardly felt a moment of fatigue. In Jedda everything became rather an effort - even in mid-March, which was still the cool season - and tropical clothes were almost essential. Y/e arrived with a south wind, and found it difficult to sleep without electric fans. The wind changed on the following day, which was pleasant enough, though still very hot; but the south wind returned a few days later. The mosquitos were a particular affliction and showed great skill in finding chinks in the wire gauze of the windows or in our mosquito curtains. I feel more than ever that the climate of this post imposes a very exceptional strain on the men who work in it, and that every possible facility should be extended to them for local leave, e.g. to Egypt or Palestine, and, I hope, eventually, when political conditions permit, for visit to Taif, the Hejaz Kills, and the central plateau. In spite of all this I was much impressed by the unfailing cheerfulness of everyone I;*rO 67. I met on the btaff of His Majesty's Legation. 131. The other point that impressed me was the comparati've inadequacy of the Legation house. I feel hound to say that the present Legation - and particularly its situation - struck me personally as hardly worthy of our position and prestige. I am not sure how far oir R. Bullard would support this view, as, when I mentioned the subject to him, he said he thought that the house was one of the best in Jedda. I therefore only express it with diffidence. But I cannot help feeling that any house rising directly from the street, with no outer wall or enclosure, exposed to all the dust of passing traffic and with most of its rooms overlooked from neighbouring buildings, is far from ideal as the official residence of His Majesty’s Diplomatic Representative in Arabia. The house is very near the sea and has a good terrace which might have a pleasant view. But it is cut off from the shore by the condenser plant, a hideous erection resembling a gas works. It is also almost immediately next to a prison. The Legation house is of great height with stairs of extraordinary steepness. It contains much ancient woodwork, which seemed to me to have suffered from the climate of Jedda and to give the house a rather decayed appearance. It is, however, well furnished with good English furniture, and both bir R. Bullard and his predecessors have clearly done what good taste can do to make it tolerable. Nevertheless it looked to me as though it might at any time need extensive repairs. I realise of course that in present financial conditions any attempt to build or acquire a really suitable building for His Majesty's Legation would be out of the question. But I feel bound to record my personal impression that the present residence of His Majesty's Minister could be greatly improved upon. Mr. Philbymrn r-\ 60. :ir. i J ]iilby for example has a fine (though badly built) low house with wide court-yards, standing well outside the town, ihere see is to oe plenty of space available, and if a good and well-designed 10 'em building suited to the climatic conditions could oe erected under European supervision outside, or at leaot nearer to, the town walls, it might not only make conditions more tolerable for His Majesty’s Minister and the Legation utaff in a climate which is peculiarly disagreeable ana unhealtny, but might also have a useful propaganda effect. j. should add, however, that 1 never heard a word of complaint on this subject while 1 was in Jedda. The opinions expressed in this paragraph arc entirely my own. KOLIHwARD JOURLdY. lo2. ,/e lett Jedda on March 22nd after what turned out in the end to be lar too short a stay. He were again obliged to travel in an Italian ship, this time owing to difficulties arising Iron Hie fact that the only British ships either carried returning pilgrims and were thus liable to long quarantine delays, or stopped only at Port Sudan and had long been fully booked up. ho sloop could be made available at the requisite date. The local Italian Red Sea service we travelled by has a poor reputation, but proved comfortable enough. The officers of the ship were most friendly, but - li:vc&gt; those o± che other Italian ships we travelled on — nervous md unhappy about the international situation, and apparently anxious to see Anglo-Italian relations re-established on a better basis. I suggested to them they they should begin by dealing with Dr. Gayda. 15b. we reached ouez on March 25th, and I was able on the road between Suez and Cairo to meet Sir H. Lampson, who Wc.s on his way to Sinai, and to have half an hour’s conversation with69. with him in ths desert. I gave him a short account of my conversations with King Ihn baud, and we briefly discussed the question of the probable reaction of the Arab countries to the eventual report of the Royal Commission on Palestine and the ultimate decision of His Majesty’s Government thereon. He agreed that the prospects were extremely disquieting,, I have quoted his views on this point in my note of April 12th referred to in paragraph 124 above. be also had a useful talk about Italian activities in the Middle East. we spent two nights in Cairo as the guests of Mr. and Mrs. SternGale Bennett, of His Majesty’s Embassy, and left Egypt by the Italian S.3, 'Esperia” on March 27th, arriving in London on the evening of April 1st. I resumed my duties at the Foreign Office on April 2nd. CONCLUSION. 154. Before ending this report, I feel I should place on record in the first place my appreciation of all that ths Saudi authorities did to make our visit a success. The hospitality extended to us by King Ibn baud was indeed almost overwhelming, and must, I fear, have involved the Saudi Govern ment in very considerable expense. The Amir Saud, in particular, took an infinity of trouble to show us every possible courtesy during our visit to Riyadh; and the Governor of Taif, no doubt under the King’s instructions, also made the most elaborate arrangements for our comfort and convenience in Taif and in the Shafa hills. But my greatest debt is probably due to Sheikh Hafiz bahba himself, who was our constant companion and personally supervised all the arrangements for our visit. We found him unfailingly friendly and helpful; and, although I knew him well before I went to Arabia, I can sincerely say that in the course of our journey I grew to like70. like him steadily better - a somewhat unusual experience with travelling companions. 135. Peeing that our journey was entirely private and unofficial, I was at first somewhat at a loss to account for the amount of trouble which the oaudi authorities took over it. I have now come to the conclusion that they must have regarded it as an opportunity of making some return to nis Majesty’s Government, through the official mainly concerned with Arabian affairs, for the hospitality extended by His Majesty’s Govern ment to the Amir baud and to the Amir Feisal during their various visits to England in recent years. If I am right in thinking this, it may be that a word of appreciation conveyed to King Ibn baud through His Majesty’s Minister at Jedda might not be inappropriate. 136. Finally, I wish to record my gratitude to all the British officials with whom we stayed or who helped to facilitate our journey. I am particularly grateful to bir Reader Bullard, who was our principal host, for his generous hospitality, unfailing kindness and friendly cooperation, and to bir Archibald and Lady Clark Kerr at Bagdad, to Colonel and Mrs. Fowle at Bushire, to Colonel and Mrs. Loch at Bahrein, and to Captain de Gaury at Koweit, for the endless trouble they took to make our visits to these places a success. I am also very grateful to Colonel .yard at Basra, to oir Richmond Palmer and Mr. otanley at Larnaca, to Mr. Keith Roach at Haifa, to Colonel and Mrs. MacKereth at Damascus, to Mr. and Mrs. bterndale Bennett in Cairo, and to Mr. watkinson at bhiraz for all their help and hospitality. I must also again record my gratitude to the Admiralty and to Captain Bowlby of H.M.b. Deptford for the passage they provided for us from Bushire to Bahrein, and to the Air Ministry, to the Air Officer Commanding Iraq, and to the Commanding Officer of the bingapore flying boat, for71. Gr. 'il o P bii DiSL • for the flight they were good enough to arrange for me over the Qatar peninsula on March 4th. There was nowhere on our route where we were not received with the utmost kindness and courtesy and made to feel that we were among frienas 0 I have the honour to he s bir, Your most obedient, humble bervant,✓ $-I (§) ' March 26 Thursday Arrive Suez by train to Cairo. I ” 27 Saturday By train to Alexandria leave by Italian s.s. 'Esperia' for Naples and Genoa. * 51 Wednesday Arrive Genoa 8 a.m. leave by train for London. April 1 Thursday Arrive Victoria 5.20.t 1 V c f i 956 j ( s2 groups) (L' l&lt;)- 5730. DECYPHER OF TELEGRAM. Prom Dated Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for Indiao Risher, 14th December, 1936 0 Personalo Following for Rendal* Begins » We shall be delighted to put you up and arrange for your trip to Shiraz, which however you may not be able to do with the (? omission) at your disposal Letter follows by air mail of December !6tho</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00021d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/218</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00021d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/218</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 8747/36 ‘Tour of G.W. Rendel, C.M.G., Foreign Office, to the Middle East, 1937. Report by Mr G.W. Rendel’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-08-31T22:06:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (103 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 102; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-102; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists largely of a report by Mr George William Rendel, Head of the Eastern Department of the Foreign Office in London, on his private tour to the Persian Gulf and also to Saudi Arabia at the invitation of King Ibn Saud, in February and March 1937. This personal account of his trip is preceded by a small amount of correspondence in 1936 relating to his travel arrangements, and is followed by post-tour correspondence in 1937 about the drafting and circulation of his report, on a confidential and limited basis, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Political Agent at Kuwait, the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department and other British officials in London, India and the Middle East. The main correspondents are Mr George William Rendel of the Foreign Office and Mr John Charles Walton, Foreign and Political Secretary to the India Office in London.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Tours</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Assistant Under-Secretary of State for India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office, Eastern Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight George William Rendel</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Saudi Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00021d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>