<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003e5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:28:25.959Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I/'Q CD N0.1371-S. Persian Gulf Residency, Baiirain, the 21st July 1947.- To The Political Agent, Bahrain . memor a ndum . Will you please arrange to supply me as soon as possible ^ith 3 copies of the “Report on the Agricultural Development of Bahrain Bahadur M. Fateh-ud-Bin, copy of whi to you under Residency Express Better No. C/2'95 dated the 3rd August 1939• - V rain” by Khan ^ i ch was for voided 'sftr Sd. a. c. galloway. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL. S 3&gt; &gt;No. To -6/44 Political Agency, Bahrain. The 27th July, 1947. The Acting Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum &gt; Reference your letter No.135?/42 dated the 13th August 1939 and connected correspondence. ' 1 2. The Political Resident requires three copies of the !f Report on the Agricultural Development of Bahrain” by Khan Bahadur M. Fateh-ud-Din, and I should be grateful if you could kindly supply me with them. 1SMA for Political Agent, Bahrain■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■ &amp; POLITICAL AOBNCT, BAHRAIN. -6/44 Th« 3rd August, 1947, |U- S' To The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, naVi-ra - ? n. Memorandum : 5-' Refereiice your memorandum No.l371-S dated the 21st July, 1947. 2. Only one copy of the ’’Report on the Agricul tural Development of Bahrain” by Khan Bahadur M. Fateh- ud-Din is available, and it is sent herewith. It is req uested that it may be returned- when done with. The Adviser lias no other copy. MMA for Political Agent, Bahrain.1 Adviser to the Government, S.Z. / No.^&gt;y/^: yS of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 2nd Dulhaj, 1366 October 16, 1947 /U4. 17 )' # 1 * Reference your memorandum No.2461-6/44 dated 27/28th July 1947. I should be obliged if you would return the copy of 'Report on the Agricultural Development of Bahrain' which was handed over to you personally by the Acting Adviser on 29th July 1947. &amp;No. 3416-6/44 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 29th October, 1947. To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . Memorandum Reference my memorandum No.2542-6/44, dated the 3rd August, 1947. 2. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government has asked for the Report on the Agricultural Development of Bahrain, which may kindly be returned, if done with. Political Agent, BahrainNo.^ 7 / »6/44 n, To Politic-1 Agency, Bahr-in f the /S&gt; ^ November, 194? The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, JLAJjJLAJUL Reference your memorandum No, 2418-42, d-ted the 16th October, 194?, 2,*’ The Report on the Agricultural Development of B«hr«in is returned herewith. ibv\ Politic-1 Agent, Bahrain</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003e5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1262</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003e5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1262</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/44 III Miscellaneous correspondence with the Adviser and deputation of certain personnel to Bahrain State'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-30T18:10:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel Arnold Crawshaw Galloway), Political Agency in Bahrain, and the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain (Charles Dalrymple Belgrave). The correspondence concerns the transfer of a report on the agricultural development of Bahrain by Khan Bahadur M Fateh-ud-Din, former Agricultural Expert for the Bahrain Government, between the Adviser and the Political Residency.Folio 9 is internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003e5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>