<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000330_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-22T09:27:07.271Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">\i' (\S° \bjh CONFIDENTIAL. No. rr/94 of 1937. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Political Agent, Muscat. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain j v ?• ' &gt;? \ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents/l/* Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, MUSCAT. 27 th April 1937 Dated. Reference to previous correspondence: .A . Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Political Resident's telegram No.T/69 of the 27th April 1937. Subject. Assistant Engineer for Bus hire. 4Telegram G.T.C yrom To Political Resident, Buehire, at Muscat. Government of India&gt; Department of External Affairs, Simla. Copies by post to Political Agent, Muscat, and Political Agent, Bahrain. Bo. T/69. Dated the 27th April, 1937. Reference Assistant Engineer for Buohir e. 2. Political Agent Muscat informs me that PRADHAK 3.INGH Persian Gulf Sub-Division Overseer at Muscat wishes to be considei’ed for post of /»saistant Dngjreer. He holds the Diploma of Sub-I3ngineer Rocjkee iiigineering College end has a practical knowledge of electricity. ABDUL 7 AHAB also Persian Gulf 3ub-Division 3 Overseer likewise wishes to be considered for post of Assistant Engineer. I believe he has not same technical qualifications as Pradhan Singh. Public tforka Department may wish to consider 4 candidatures of Pradhan Singh and Abdul /aha^ but it is of course their entire responsibility to select either of th^m or anyone else they think fit. 5. I suggest that whoever is appointed as Assistant Engineer should be for the firct six months on probation. RE3IDI3KT.cm tiai. - aagxsximi). D.O. No. 13 ?l+. Dated the2l- July, 1938. ) It- follows. ' 4 % The Assistant Engineer wrote certain 'private' letters to overseer Pardhan Singh, copies oi which I enclose, i.e., pages 1 to 50 of file 64/2o4. Pardhan Singh sent copies of these letters to me, as well as of copies of his replies, and these copies are the papers referred to above in file 64/kio4. 3. In the Assistant Engineer’s letters there are the following accusations against Pardhan Singh, all of which concern his time at Muscat, vide paragraphs 2 to 9 of pages 2 to 10 of file 64/254, In addition to these accusations there is also a general accusation, vide para graph 10 of page 3 of file 64/254, which in fact appears to concern Punkahs at Gwadur, vide paragraph 3 of letter No.259, dated the 27th June, 1938, marked 'A* • On this subject there are also letters, No.67 dated ^ 8 th peoruary, 1938, marked ’B’, and No.115 dated 3rd April, 1938, marked 'O', which are relevant to the investigation. Further copies of letters to help in your investigation are marked ’B 1 copy of letter No.151 dated 25th April, 1938, marked ’E Major R.P.Watts, I.A., Political Agent, Muscat.f © copy of letter No. 49 dated 15 th February, 1938, marked F* copy of letter No.69 dated lot March, 1938, marked G ! copy of letter No.2o3 dated 21st June, 1938. Also are enclosed copies of letters marked ’X 1 and , Y I from a firm in Karachi regarding the Punkahs. There is a further letter, marked ’H’ , with the relevant measurement book and running account bill, which amounts to an accusation by Abdul Wahab having bearing on the whole matter and demand ing investigation. From the evidence at present before Sir Trenchard, and owing to the fact that the correspondence between the Assistant Engineer and Pardhan Singh appears to be of a pseudo '•private” nature, it is impossible for Sir Trenchard to decide whether a court of enquiry should be held on these accusations, or not. Sir Trenchard, therefore, requests that you will make a preliminary, but thorough , investigation into the accusations in question and submit a report as soon as possible. Vide our telegram No.278, dated the 18th July, 1938, you are being asked to call Pardhan Singh from Gwadur to Muscat, so that he will be able to answer any questions you have to put to him perso- On receipt of your report Sir Trenchard will decide whether a court of enquiry should be held, and charges —-—'A' 0 JTo. 259 of 1938. Muscat, dated the 27th June, 1938. COHFID&amp;NTIAL To The Assistant Jingineer, PpW.D., Bushire. Sir, Subject - Purdhan Singh, Overseer Prom a reliable source I came to know that Mr.Pardhan Singh asked the late wife of Abdul Latief (Khanaum) to give him a statement to this effect that she was &amp;is made servant, and on this ground he took her to Bahrein. But she refused to give him any statement, on this ground that he failed to give her Rs. 50/- per month as he promised to do so, while she remains with him as mistress, and for the last 16 months he has not paid the amount, and she is going to claim that amount from him through court. 2 . Having failed to get her thumb impression on the typed paper, he was abl e to get a thumb impression from one prostitute who was his mistress also, and her name is SABIHUE, and it is likely he may submit the forged document as evidence, so I warn the head office about this affair in advance • 3. Further I was able to trace this information that 3 punkhas were taken from the Agency godown and delivered to Mr. Pardhan Singh, who took them to Gwadar. The man who gave the 3 punkhas was the Agency Farash then, and his name is Muhammed Abdullah and now he is a painter. If his state-Sir, 10 210.67 of 1938. Guadur, dated the 28th 3*6b. 1938. The Assistant Engineer, P.W.D., Bushire Subject - Measurement Book Mo.1221. I beg to state that I checked the office furniture , crockery, lamps, etc., in the Political Bungalow at Guadur, and found them correct, with the exception of 3 punkhas please vide measurement book Mo.1221, page 7, purchased at Rs. 48/- each are old ones and X am quite sure they were not imported from India. Because I have reason to believe that they were brought from Muscat, and shown in the measurement book, as if they were new and paid for. In fact the 3 punkhas are of different shape and size. If they were puxj based from India they should be new, and more or less of the same size and shape. But they are not. With the exception of cotton rope which is new, the rest of the parts are old. 2. Similar punkhas are still lying in the P.W.D. quarters at Muscat. Apparently they became useless after the installa tion of the electric fans in the Agency. 3. The matter appears to be serious, so I beg to request prompt inquiries may please be made as to their origin. Measure- ment book will follow by slow mail. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (Sd.) Abdulwahab Supervisor* /&gt; ' © / \ Ij No.115 of 1938. Muscatf dated the 3rd April, 1938. To The Assistant Engineer, P.W.D*, Bushire. Sir, Subject - Furniture for the political Bungalow at Guadur. With reference to your No.8/358 dated the 24th March, 1938, I beg to state that so far my knowledge is concerned I can dare say that the 3 punkhas lying at Guadur are old ones. 2 . As for the proof to show that they were sent from Muscat appears to be a puzzle, but a mothers instinct is such that she can pick her child in the midst of a crowd so I think and I can prove th/ough direct if I am given old records of the Muscat Agency, or indirect through some argument . 3. All this means full and detail report, this can only be done while I prosecute the case myself. I am afraid if you like to conduct the case with the information at your elbow, it may be possible through your influence you will be able to give him a sack, but one should have facts to prove a case without prejudice. Justice demands it. So in the interest of Government I may please be called to Bushire. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant (Sd.) Abdulwahab Supervisor50.151 of 1938 Hus ca t, dated the 25th April, 1938. To The Assistant j^ginaer, V. Bushire. Sir, Subject - Spiral staircase complete. With reference to your If0.6/431 dated the 13th April, I beg to state that the spiral staircase complete is nothing to do with other stairs. Please read my letters carefully, there is clear mention of old stair case and sweepers stair case from the Agency Surgeon* s house. 2. If the case against Mr. Pardhan Singh is to be con ducted on these lines, by putting a cart before a horse, I am afraid you are trying to do me harm by your uncalled for remarks. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant. ( &amp; d.) Abdulwahab SupervisorBahrein, dated the 15th February, 1938# To The Assistant Engineer, P.W.D., Bushire• Sir, Subject - Government materials In continuation of my Ho.37, dated 7th instant, I beg to state that the following building materials belonging to the Political Agency, at Muscat are to be found in a godown of a merchant, at Muscat. If these articles were sold to him, Bushire office must have a record, if not the articles were sold to the merchant by private arrangement or the Overseer L himself has left them there just to avoid detection. T irons ^from the Political Agents office Praquite floor boards removed from the Agency drawing roo# Sweepers stair case removed from the Agency Surgeon’s house 2 . I shall be obliged if I am informed at what price the old Sind tiles removed from the Political Agent’s Office were sold. I find some of the tiles used in fish market built by Mr. Pardhan Singh, Overseer, Muscat. r I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant (Sd.) Abdulwahab SupervisorI \ \ m) No.69 of 1938 Guadur, dated 1st March, 1938. f The Assistant Engineer, P.W.D., Bushire. Sir, Subject - Government Property With reference your note asking me the name of the person in whose godown the Government properties are lying, I beg to state that a man of my status dare not mention the name of a respectable merchant in whose godown the properties are lying. 2 . If you are satisfied that they were not sold, the case is clear, fcnd if you care to take any action you can do so, and you can cite me as a witness. 3. At this stage my mentioning the name of the merchant would mean the turning of the tide against me. Let the matter go to the Residency, then I will disclose it. I I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant ^Sd.) Abdulwahab Supe rvisor» No. 253 of 1938. Muscat, dated the 21st June, 1938. To The Assistant Engineer, P.'A.D., Bus hire . Sir, Subject - Charges. I shall be thankful if you kindly send me a list of those charges that were sent to you by me and the reply thereof obtained from the overseer concerned. I want ottly those that concerns my statement, t and not those ouside it, because I am not concerned. a I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (Sd.) Abdulwahab Supervisor.Muscat, dated 3rd June, 1938 SECRET To The Secretary to t he Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, Subject -- Fraud. I beg to state that I may please be excused for directly addressing this letter to you. The reason for doing the same is to avoid public scandal. But professional honour demands that the culprit should be brought to the alter of JUSTICE. 2. SnclOeed a Bill prepared by Mr. Pradhan Singh, in connec tion with the construction of servants quarters at Muscat. Item 13 of the Bill in fact was not done, but falsely entered and paid for, thus he has committed fraud to the extent of Rs. 104 and thus put the Government to a loss of Rs. 104/-. 3. A shrewd and cunning man is always a danger to the society i and unreliable. I beg to remain Sir, Your most obecibnt Servant (Sd.) Abdulwahab Accom 1 Bill Supervisor3 * ) P W. A. 27. &gt; f [Final payments must invariably be made on forms printed on yellow paper which shonld not be used for intermediate payments.] RUNNING ACCOUNT BILL Q t [P. W. A. Code, paragraphs 284, 288 and 289.] (I'or Contractor! and Supplier !.—This form provides oniy for payments for work or supplies actually measured. PaoviNOE Division. Bjulnch L Sub-Division. Cash Book Voucher No. Name of Contractor Name of Work* dated. or or Supplier &amp;UQ * 1. “ Stock ” Purpose of Supply f 2. “ Purchases for issue Serial No. of this Bill. X- No. and date of his last Bill for this work Reference to Agreement to (contractor) direct to work/’ m-JLjjL /?3y- I.—Account of work done or supplies made. Quantity executed (or supplied) up to date as per measurement book. Items of work or supplies (grouped under “ sub-heads ” and “ sub-works ” of estimate). Bate. fcjLiAAj tbit Af fjcAf. •+&lt;&gt; — Aji.^vkaT if C/:2:4j /A Q % t / &lt;JCVA Wiryfa. c, 1^4 AA* 0 - cuauJ* ]L t ** • Ao“ AjzJ^ ^ r &gt; v y^ rf Rb. r» 3 V ‘s/* l /y , * i^u Lm*J • / iiw- ' » /r _ • * s y*-* i^rxJK “■'X’ctj;'.''*-'' &lt;• &lt;. JL ' V' Carried ovw l* ~ AajtouKT. lUp to da,te. J Since previous bill (Total for each sub-head). 6 Rkmarks. R*. /277 AV lg yirj tr 27&lt;f &lt;// fee £ *9 AW /o v«* &gt;// Rs. 'V / e» /*&gt; V I ^2 X. &lt;^5^6 * The full name of the work as given in the estimate should be entered here except in the ca;-® of bill* for stock ’ material*, f The *‘ purpose of supply ” applicable to the case should be filled in and the rest scored out. * If the outlay on the work is recorded by sub-heads, the total for each sab-head should 1&gt;« shown in column 6 and against this total there thou Id Lc an i ntry in column C also. In no other case should any entries be made in column 6.Unit. * Quantity exeented Items of work or supplies (or supplied) up to date as per (grouped under “ sub-heads ” and measurement “ sub-works ” of estimate). book. S 3 Brought orsr .. Rate. Jlmocjtt. Since previous bill (Total for each sub-head). 6 Rs. a. r. Re. R*. Unit. Quantity e (or supplie to date a: measure booh Deduct value of work o Net value of work or s Figure (F) in tvorda- The measurem at page without detailed m fifths wil lUL Dated signature of contractor.t- ■'ibaA Amount. Unit. Quantity exeeuwi (or supplied) up to date as per measurement book. Items of work or supplies (grouped under “ sub-heads ” and “ sub-works ” of estimate). Rate. Up to date. Since previous bill (Total for each sub-head). Remarks. 1 2 3 • 4 6 6 7 Brought over Its. lla. Rs. value of work done or supplies made to date Deduct value of work or supplies shown on previous bill Net value of work or supplies since previous bill Figure (F) in rvorda - (A) (F) % hoty 1 * II—Certificates and Signatures. The measurements were made by JXLA and are recorded at page^^r.t of Measurement Book — No advanoe payment kaa been made previously without detailed measurements. r /-Lzl Dated signature of officer /O, -r- zT) sn r \ ^ ^Dated signature uj yg p/ $1$^ preparing the bill {Rank)- /fikU4t^XJL^y y 7V t S Dated signature of contractor. * Dated signature of officer authorising payment. (Rank)- • This signature is necessary only when the o^icer •r natures are essential. who prepares the hill la not the officer who authorises the pejus wit. la such a case two wlP.0, Box 34, McLeod Road, Karachi, 6 th May, Bo. 53/37. The Assistant Engineer, British Consulate-General, Bushire• Dear Sirs $ Re:- Supply of 3 wooden punkahs for the Political Bungalow at Gwadur. Mth reference to your letter Bo.8/524 dated 27-4-38, we beg to inform kh you that our Proprietor L.Ramdass, M.A., is at present out of station and is expected here in the course of next week. We shall revert to the subject on his return. Yours faithfully, (Sd.) for Ram Company, Manager • Of 1938.RAM COMPANY JP • 0• Box 3 Ay I Me Leod Road, Karachi, 11th May, 1938. Mo.76/106. To The Assistant Engineer, British Consulate-General, Bushire. Dear Sir, Re*- Supply of 3 wooden punkhas for the Political Bungalow at Gwadar. With reference to your esteemed favour Ho.8/361 dated t 24th March, 1938, and the subsequent reminders we regret to state that due to heavy pressure of work, on account of our financial year closing on 31-3-38, we could not attend to your enquiry earlier and we offer you our apologies for the incon venience this delay might have caused your goodself. Coming to the subject of your enquiry we cant trace out the relevant records on the subject, but as far as we can remember we had placed our order for new punkahs with a local firm of carpenters who have since closed their show and gone to their native places of which we have got no information and hence we could not further follow up this enquiry. Thanking you for your past favours and assuring you of our best attention at all times. Yours faithfully, (&amp;d) for Ram Company. ProprietorConfidential D.O. Mo. C/U7 £ August 9 th, 1938. A Will you please refer to your demi official letter No. 1384 dated 22nd July 1938 on the subject of certain allegations brought against Fardhan Singh? 2. Fardhan Singh is expected to arrive here by today's steamer. The delay in his arrival is due to the fact that iqy telegram sunmoning him here which was sent on receipt of your telegram No. 278 of 18th July (received here on 21st July) did not reach Gwadur owing to breakdown of the Gwadur- Panjgur telegraph line until the departure of the last mail steamer from that port i.e. on July 26th. 3. As instructed by Sir Trenchard Fowle I shall carry out a thorough investigation into the matter and the result will, I hope, be ready for despatch to you by next Mail. v Jt, /- ■i, Captain A.C. Galloway, I.A., Secretary to the Hon'ble the Folit!cal Resident- in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.D.O.No. C/123 of i93B. Political Agency &lt;5- li.B.M's Consu.Ate Muscat| the 26 th August I93^'» Subject:- Accueatione againet Pradhan Singh Overseer F.W.D* Dear Galloway, Would you please refer to your demi-official letter F 0 .I 384 dated 22nd July 193®* 2 # l forward herewith a report on my investigatior: into this case which I have endeavoured to rake as thorough as possible. 3 . The enclosures to your above mentioned letter File 64/254 and P.W.D.Measurement Book) are returned herewith. Yours sincerely, Captain A.C.Galloway, I.A., Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Keport on the i^veetigationB made into certain accusations against Pradhan Singh .D.Ovsrsser. From the papers enclosed with Captain Ga&amp;loway'e ae d official letter to me No.13^4 of 2ind July I have made out the following list which appears to include all the accusations made against Irauhan Singh both by the Assistant Engineer and Abdul ahab, Supervisor P.w.D. In addition ceitain further accusations were maae in my presence during the course of the investigations by Abdul ahab against radha? Singh and these have been included under the relevant connected item. In accordance with Sir Trenchard Fowle’s instruction I have made a thor u£h investigation into all the accusations This has necessitated taking a considerable amount of detailec evidence which has resulted in a some what lengthy report. List of accusations brought against Pradhan Singhs- 1. Obtain! g the thumb impression of a certain woman named Sabihue with the intention of using it for an illegal purpose. 2 . falsely showing in estimates names of two coolies as contractors. 3. Usiiig tiles belonging to Goverijnent (Sind tiles from *olitical Agentfs Office) on private work and not accounting for these tiles. 4. Selling, or concealing with ii tert to defraud certain Government property ( iron stair case,turn, mi i niM—' iwi - 'l &amp; T iron flooring ruaterial# sweeper’s staircase, balcony railings and Venetian shutters, ■t'ost Office Door) and not crediting proceeds to Government. 5.Showing in a Measurement Boo* certain work(fiy proofing of fan lignts in Agency Medical Officer’ house) as having been done and charging lor ti.em but which in reality was never carried out. 6 . preparing a false voucher and receiving payment for woric not executed, (lime plastering on roof of S•A•S* s quarters)• 7. Using old cement blocks belonging to Government in the construction of a cistern and charging for new blocks. Q.Hemitting such amounts of money to India as could only have been obtained by defrauding Government. 9. (a) Taking old puntdius to Gwadur signing in a Measurement Book as having been received new from India as part of tne political Bunge.lo^ iftirniture. (b) Kot accounting for old Agency pumdias. 10 .Charging in a Measurement Book for the use ol certain materials in a Government Building(Cast iron pipes irjfeervants' quarters in Agency) and not having used then on that work and misappro priating the money drawn for the work. il.Sending an estimate for certain wora to be carried out ( lime plastering in the .treasury Officer * s quarters) with intent to deiraud in that actual work was carried out by Central Contract Grant). iM.Preparing estimate with intent to defraud. (Intention alleged of using oxd material for new dressing room in Medical Officer's house). IS.Using Government materials for wiring a private&gt;4 ad -3- house for his own use and not ±&gt;a&gt;ing for ail currenl consumed. 14.ilaicing a false claim from Government for services ol a ^unicha puller. 15.Absconding from Iraq after misappropriating large amounts of the Iraq Government's money and being liable to arrest on entering that country. The result of my investigations made into the above accusations are given in the following paragraphs. 3. On the commencement of my investigation Abdul v/ahab asKec to be Allowed to make a statement which he said he desired to be taken down in writing and submitted/ with this report. This statement is attached marked H A H . v Reference accusation Ko.i. Obtaining the thumb impression of a certain woman named Sabihue with the intention of using it for an illegal purpose. Iradhan denied the accusation entirely* Roth women mentioned in Abdul wanab's letter of 27th June (Statement M A W oi enclosures to your demi official letter No.1334 of 22nd July 1^38) were summoned before me. The woman Chanum stated that rradnan Singh asked her to is sign a paper alleged to contain a statement that she was his maid servant. She refused because she was owed money for her services in that capacity by iradhan Singh. She denied ever having been his mistress, iradhan Singh agreed that some money was owing to her by him and promised to pay up her dues. (The woman was instructed to make a report to me if her claim were not settled within the next few days). The woman Sabihue denied that i^radhan Singh had ever asked her to put her thumb impression on any document. No further evidence could be produced by Abdul •ahab of his accusation which could not therefore be substantiated* There is evidence available tnat rradhan Singh has been mixed up in an unsavouring affair witn this woman .dianum who is a notorious ^restitute unaer circumstances which do him no4 credit* Various accusations were brought against him in the Agency Court in 1^36 by the woman’s fonder husband the late Abdul Latif, but nothing could be proved to justify legal action being ta^en though I administered a warning to rardhan Singh on his conduct. A detailed report on this case can be submitted if desired. Reference accusation ho.2. Falsely showing in estimates names of two coolies as contractors. Fradhan Singh states that both the men referred tc Hussain bin Mazar and Mohammed bin Sonia are not coolies but Master Masons. The first named he says has been known to the late Assistant Engineer, Mr.Fatahali Sheikh, for many years and for the last five years has been wording as a contractor in the Agency with the knowledge and a^provax of that officer. A reference to the P.w.D. records in the Residency would, he felt confident, confirm his statement. Mohammed bin Sonia it api^ars has left Muscat but Hussain bin Mazar was present and appeared before me. He confirmed Fradhan Singh statement mentionea above and denied that he had ever sworn to any one that he had never worked as a contractor to x'radhan Singh or that he was always employed as a cooly on daily wages. He was he declared a Master Mason. From the man’s appearance and demeanour I certain! do not think he is a cooly but is what he declared himself to be i.e. of the artisan class. Fradhan Singh stated that it was a common practice in the F.«.E. to give out contracts for comparatively big amounts l in this case the sums of iis 600 to Rs 2800 odd in each case were involved) to men of the class of individuals in question i.e. Master Masons etcetra and his action in this matter was in no way irregular. On tiiis point of course I am not competent to judge Reference accusation ho.3 UsingUsing tiles belonging to Government (Sind tiles from Political Agent’s Office) on private work and not accounting for these tiles. Pradhan Singh pointed out that the Fish Market at Muscat (a work he carried out under my orders by permission of the rolitical Resident for the Muscat Government) was completed before the floor of the Political Agent's oliice was taxen up and so the Sind tiles therefrom could not have been used in the contruction of the Fish Market. This fact is correct. The Fish Market was completed and handed over to the Muscat Government on 19Lh August x937. The Political Agent’s office floor was taken up some time afterwards. Abdul V.ahab when asked to explain why he had brought the accusation in view of its obvious imvosBiMUty in the face of these facts f replied that he hud made it alter seeing the P.W.D. Measurement Book in which he thought the date of dismantlement of the floor was prior to i9th August. Asked to produce the Measurement Book he said it had been sent to the Aesistant Engineer at Bushire. Subsequently Abdul Wahab admitted that he had found omongat the P.w.D. records evidence tnat the floor had in tact seen tti^en up after the date of completion of the Fish Market. On being questioned as to how he could then account lor his accusa- f tion Abdul Wahab replied mat the oind Tiles must have been put on the Fish Market for some reason probably to ornament it after its completion and handing over to the Muscat State Authorities. Comment on this last statement is 1 think unnecess ary. This accusation in my opinion is clearly a false one. Pradhan Singh admits there are some Sind and other odd tiles in the Fish Market. These he says he obtained from the ruins of an house demolished under the Muscat Improvement Scheme. As regards the disposal of the old Sind Tiles removed from the Political Agent's office rradhan Singh stated the mojority were unserviceable and scrappedn scra r i&gt;ed and the reiuainder stored under the Agency verandah. They were he says too fe# to ta&amp;e on charge. X can obtain no evidence either in su^ort oi or in contradiction oi tx*is statemerit. deference accusation No.4. Selxin^ or concealing with intent to defraud certain Government property (iron staircase* 1 iron flooring material* sweeper’s staircase, balcony railings, &amp;nc 2 Venetian shutters* post office door; and not credit ing proceeds to Government. fradhan Singh said that the iron staircase had been f handed over to his successor hohammed Ishaq with other materials and a copy of the list of materials was sent to tne Assistant Engineer Bushire. Abdul Wahab admits the staircase is in the r.fc.D. godown 'on cnarge' so presumably XTadhan Singh's statement as regards this article is correct. As regards the T ironsftnese articles t rad nan Singh admitted were lying in Uie store room of a certain idadhuji* a British Indian subject, fradhan Singh's explanation of this is as follows:- H vhen the T irons were dismantled I was engaged in carrying out under Political agent's orders a number of vorics for the uscat Government under what is Known as the Muscat Improvement Scheme. The materials used on this worit were stored by me in a godown hired from a merchant iiadhuji. e Owing* to a miaunuerstending the coolies when ordered to remov the T irons and remnants ox the staircase from the Agency too jc them to tnis godown in Vadhuji* s store instead of to the f.W.B. godown as intended by me, and in the preoccupation ! of the extra worx 1 was then doing* were lost sight oi. hen I left xruecut m August ±9Z7,1 ixanded over to my successor Iionammeu Ishaq all Government's property on my charge but quite forgot about tne T.irons owing to their small value. Shortly after I had left fcuscat I thought I might possibly-7- i&gt;ro,erty so I wrote ^riTately to hr.k’asiruJ. Haq- then Acting Treasury Wficer- and requested hi* to enquire from stf successor hohaamed Ishaq if any r.W.D.nrticles were snort in which case I could explain and take fuli responsibility. (Kotes- Kasirul Haq, Second Clerk, »as sommoned ana confirmed that he had received a private letter from Pradhan Singh to that effect and that he had m^e necessary enquiries from Mohammed Ishaq vho stated that he was unable to find tnat any P.W.D. property sas unaccounted for). Moreover when the Assistant Engineer wrote and enquired from me the whereabouts of these materials I at once replied in my letter of 13th April 1938 that they were I thought lying in a store at Muscat. *o attempt was therefore made by me to conceal the existance of these articles when asked about them though 1 admit 1 snould have hanaed over and not left them lying in a private store. To verify that the T irons were actually in Madhuji's store I instructed hr.taqbul Husain .Uian, Treasury omcer, pradhan Singh and Abdul Wahab to proceed there and report what had been found. Some 1? T irons said to be from the roliticai Agent's office floor were found inhadhuji's store ana I gave orders they were to be removed to the P.W.D.store and taxen over by Abdul lahab. Abdul Wahab said that he had seen some other articles in Madhuji's store which he felt certain were Government's property and which he suspected Pradhan Singh had misappropriated i.e. a piece of wooden balcony railing and a pair of Venetian shutters. Accordingly I ordered the articles to be brought at once to the Agency ana Madhuji himself to before me. Abdul ..ahab produced a smalx *iece of &gt;«ood utiich he declared he had found on his first visit to the godown and which he said was a piece of the parquet flooring of the Agency drawing room. Mr. kaqbul Husain Khan Treasury Officer stated while searching the godown Abdul Wahab had produced the piece of wood saying he hsd found it lying on some boxes but he had not{% v) - 8 - not seen Abdul Wahab actually picjc it up. When he saw it the Aood was in Abdul bahab's hands, ^radhan 8 ingh decalred that Abaul Wahab lirct snowed the piece of wood lying in his hand and did not draw the attention of himself or Mr.Maqbul Husain Khan to it lying in tne godown. Owing to the very small size of the piece of wood hradhan Singh declared it could easily have been concealed in Abdul Wahab’s hand brought to the godown r}^ and sudenly produced as hating been found lying there or again such a small piece could quite easily have been thrown from the road through the o^en door to tne place where it was alleged to have been found.. rraohan Singh admitted that the piece of wood appeared to be a portion of the old parquet flooring but contended that ADdui toahab’s statement that it had been found in Madhuji’e store was false and was not substantiated by the evidence. As regards the flooring material and sweeper^ staircase my explanation is as follows:- When X took up the parquet floor of the Agency drawing room to lay down a new one the dismantled portions were mostly unserviceable and not of sufficient value to be taken on the P.W.D.books. Pieces I considered might be of use for small worxs I first stored in one of the Agency spare rooms on the ground floor, similarly with the sweeper’s staircase it was nearly ail 'scrap' when dismantled, lortions I thought would be of use I stored with tne remnants of the parquet flooring in one of the Agency gowdowna. About tnis time Dr. Hynes, the iedical °fficer had asked for a portion of the side verandah of his house to be partitioned off to form an extra room. I said that the work could be carried out very cheaply from the Central Contract Grant if I could be allowed to make use of old material lying in the Agency. You agreed to this subject to your approval being taiten on the actual estimate which I was to maxe out. Accordingly I started to pick out any pieces of wood etcetra from old material lying in the Agency. As there was no mention of a permanent transfer I presumed I was returning to Muscat and in order to avoid the material Imm some other purpose by mieteke I thought it would he good idea to store it in the Medical Officer's garage which was empty. I asked Er.Hynes if I could do this and he agreed. I obtained the key from him placed the material in it, and locKed the door, and returned the key to Cr.Hynes. The material 1 collected unless removed by some one should still be there. Dr.Hynes was summoned and corroborated *radhan Singh's statement as regards the lending of hie garage for the purpose of storing some materials which he was given to understand was to be for use in building a partition in his verandah, he confirmed that he had given the key of the garage to iradhan Singh about a year ago and had received it back a few days back since which time it had been in his possession ana so far as he was aware had never been in any other person's hands* 1 obtained the key from Dr.Hynes and proceeded to inspect the garage. In it were found a heap of parquet flooring material and a bundle of tea* wood pianica. Abdul Wahab declared that about five weeks ago on paying a stealthy visit to Madhuji's store he found the uoor open and eaw that the parquet flooring was no longer lying there. He eaid be believed that some how it had been removed thence to the garage} the small amount of dust on tne articles showed he added that they had not been lying there a whole year The Treasury Officer and myself both examined the F ieee of flooring. There was dust all over them but whether the amount was equal to that which would be deposited in that particular place during a period of twelve months I am not prepared to give an opinion without the assistance of Mr. Sherlock Holmes in person. Reference the -balcony Railings* In the Agency courtyard after examining the contents of the garage Abdul Wahab said he would lime to show me a place on the roof of the Medical Officer's house which he said showed signs of recent demolition, with iradhan Singh and-iO- and tne Treasury Officer I went to tne place indicated and Abdul Wahab pointed out pieces of wood in two buttresses some fourteen feet apart on Uie western side of the roof of Medical Officers house, and evidently part of the foot rail of a balcony which had been removed. According to Abdul ^ahab this had been recently done. Abdul Wahab said he was ready to take an oath that in 1*32 the balcony was still in site* He explained:* 'Y/hat I mean is that the floor boards were there, but I o*nnot say whether the remaining portion of the balcony i.e. hand rails and uprights were also there or not but having found what I consider is clearly the hand rail and uprights of the balcony in Kadhuji*s store i think it probable that Pradhan Singh must have removed and not put them on charge and hidden them in hadhuji's store 11 • Pradhan Singh denied that he had ever demolished this balcony and declared this statement of Abdul iahab was a complete falsehood. He stated he could bring evidence to show the balcony had been demolished some years before he was posted to Muscat. On 14th August Abdul Wahab/stated that he now on further inspection saw that the piece of balcony found in kadhuji's house did not fit the portion between the buttresses so it could not have come from that portion of the roof. He therefore admits that his accusation of Pradhan Singh having demolished that portion of the balcony and put it in Madhuji’s * house falls to the ground. He admits he brought this accusation rashly. Heference Venetian shutters. Madhuji produced his account books before me in which was an entry for the purchase of the shutters in a public auction of property belonging to the late All /Juan— a lormer well known merchant of Muscat. Abdul Wahab stated that if one of Ali Ahan *8 sons were summoned they woudd testify tnat the shutters had never been in their father*s house. Asked by me if reliance could be placed in the sworn testimony of Ali rChan* s sons Abdul «ahabmmm# - 11 - replied it could not and admitted tliat under these circumstances there was no use after all in summoning these persons. I know something about Ali chan’s sons and their disreputable character. I quite agree with Abdul wahab that it would be of no use summoning theia to give evidence and I therefore did not do so. Abdul Wahab then said that he had a number of Venetian shutters removed from the Agency in the P.W.D.store and that if some were brought and mixed up with the ones found in Kadhuji's store it could be immediately seen that they were of the identical pattern and type. I agreed with tue suggestion and said I would give orders the following day at what time I desired this identi fication carried out. The next day it was reported to me by the Treasury Officer that Madhuji had removed the Venetian shutters from the Agency without permission# I gave orders for the shutters to be brought back immediately and summoned ttadhuji to give an explana tion. He declared that he had removed tne shutters under a miss- apprension that they were no longer required. As this action seemd to me suspicious I considered it advisable to go and search his store room and house personally especially as Abdul Wahab had informed me that he had found some more Government property in Madhuji’s house. Accordingly I carried out a thorough search of the godown but could find no articles of Government property. In the courtyard of his house which adjoins the godown is a out house the folding door of which Abdul Wah&amp;b declared was Govern ment property and came from the iiost Office in the Agency when dismantled to make room for a pillar box. He said he accused Pradhan Singh of illegaly giving or selling the door to Wiadhuji. Pradhan Singh on being asked for his reply to this accusation said the doors were demolished and the work carried out by a Postal Contractor from Karachi. Sanction/ for this had previously been obtained from the former Political Agent Uajor Bremner, but the work not started until later. He# Pradhan Singh had nothing to do with the work whatsoever and the question of how the doors were disposed of could only be ascertained from themm-13- ' 1 'he lly proofing of the fan lights was duly carried out together with the doors in the Medical Officer's house. # When the work was completed it was found that the fan lights could not then be opened owing to the presence of the gauae. By orders of the then Assistant Engineer Er.Fatahali Sheikh the wire gauze over the fan lights was removed. Being of a peculiar shape the wire gauzing was of little use for any other work so was not taken on the books. It was stored in the Agency and part of it used for patching. The completion certificate was signed by the Political Agent which shows that the work was carried out M . It is correct statement that 1 signed the usual .Political Agent's completion certificate for this work and so far as 1 can remember /.hen I loo&amp;ed over the work the fan iignt wire gauze was in position. After ascertaining from the Medical Officer that the work had been carried out to his satisfaction I signed the completion certificate. Whether as a matter of fact the fan light gauzes were removed by orders of Mr.Fatahali Sheikh that officer alone apparently can confirm. Reference accusation ho. 6 . Preparing a false voucher and receiving payment for work not executed. Pradhan Singh declares he carried out the work and obtained a completion certificate from the Political Agent, and the work was inspected and passed by the then Assistant Engines: (j&amp;r. Fatah all Sheikh). The completion certificate was signed by me after having seen the woric. In addition there is evidence from the Treasury Cffic&lt; Mr.Maqbul Husain /Chan, that the work was apparently properly carried out and not M faked* to pass a Political agent's inspection- not a difficult matter in such technical matters-. Mr.Maqbui Husain khan's house overlooks the roof of the Sub- Assistant Surgeon's quarters and he states he clearly remembers seeing the work in progress.14- &lt;£T) This accusation therefore appears to me definitely to be a false one. Reference accusation Ro.7. Using old cement blocks belonging to Government in the construction of a cistern and charging for new blocks. Pradhan Singh denies the accusation. He says the work was carried out by a contractor named Husain bin Mazar, whom he produced in front of me. The man declared he had carried out the work himself and had used his o?m materials throughout. The assistant Engineer in his letter to Pradhan Singh has asserted that the blocks used inside the cistern are (a) hollow clocks which generally are not used for such work (b) therefore he considers they must be old Government material. Pradhan Singh denies this and declares that (a) hollow blocks are frequently used in such works (b) the blocks are not old Government property. as regards point (a) This is a technical matter of which I am not competent to express an opinion; regarding (b) there is no evidence available either from the Assistant Engineer's letters or from Abdul Wahab to show they are Government property. It would appear therefore that this accusation has not been substantiated and that in the absence of evidence to the contrary Pradhan Singh’s explanation can be accepted. Reference accusation Ho.S. Remitting and taking such amounts of money to India as could only have been obtained by defrauding Government. pradhan Singh states that he has not remitted or taken from Muscat larger amounts of money than his pay and allowances have enabled him legitimately to do. Th£. assistant Engineer's statement in this connection is vague and as he gives no particulars m hisHMHHflHNNNV -15- accusation regarding tlie sums alleged to have been remitted anu taken to india by Iradhan Singh I have been unable to obtain evidence to substantiate it. Reference accusation No. 9. (a) Taking old punkhas to Gwadur- Signing in a Measurement Book as having been received new from India as part of the political Bungalow furniture (b) Not accounting for old Agency punkhas. xTadhan Singh stated this accusation was ialse. He said he had never taken any old ivgency punkhas to Gwadur. The three punkhas for which he had signed in Measurement Book No.1221, were those he had found in Gwadur bungalow amongst the furniture sent from India which he had under orders taken on charge. He denied that they were old ones and said it could be seen that they were a different type to the old ones dismantled from the Agency. Abdul Wahab in his letter No.259 of 2Vth June 1936 (statement *A' of enclosure to your demi official letter 1364 of 22nd July 1938) had stated that a certain Mohammed Abdullah, an ex /vgency karash, had told him that he himueil had given three punkhas to rradhan dingh irom the Agency store. Abdul tfahab had further stated before me tnat this man declared he himself had helped to laod tne punkhas in the boat in which Bradhan Singh had left from the Agency steps to embark on the steamer. I nad Mohammed Abdullah called in the presence of Bradhan Singh and Abdul Vk'ahab. As the man seemed distinctly nervous I told him he need have no fear from anyone and should speak the truth. I then asked him about the truth of the allegations mentioned above. He denied on oath that he had ever made any such statement to Abdul Wahab or had in fact taken three punkhas from the Agency and given them to Bradhan Singh or helped load such things in his boat,when the latter was leaving for the steamer. In answer to a question by xradhan ^ingh-16- \ - irracUian biniih, KoimzuKed Abdullah admitted that he had received some money a short time ago from , bdul V,ahab but it wao» he a&amp;id 9 because he was eicjt. My own oi/inion ie that this man’e evidence cannot be relied u^on in the slightest degree, he was for some months a fa rash in the Agency but I had to get rid of him owing to his habitual lying habits and generally unsatislactory conduct. Irndhun Singh aSKed to be allowed to call ir. hasirul Haq, Second Clerk, Muscat Agency, who was at the time in question Acting Treasury Officer. Mr.Kasirul stated that he had no ^nov*ledge of any Agency ^un^has being taken away or hand ed over to piadhan Singh. He was present when rradhan Singh left the Agency steps to embark on the steamer and saw nothing aiuongst his luggage which resembled three punkhas. Abdul fcahab had stated in his letter to the Assistant hngxneer JNo.67 of 2oth February statement 'B of enclosure to your demi official letter previously relerred to) that the old punkhas in his l.W.D. store bore a strorig resembdance to those in the Gwadur Bungalow. I therefore ordered him together with the Treasury Officer to go and bring for my examination a specimen which he considered was, amongst those with him, the nearest in appearance to the ones at Gwadur The one produced is an ordinary type of punkha with a wooden pole and fringe of matting, i could see no marked resemblance between this and the Gwadur punkhas though I could not recollec very clearly what the latter look like for the reason that since the completion of the Political Bungalow under a private arrangement with Imperial Airways electric current has been made available and the punkhas in consequence have never been used and are lying stored in one of the empty servants* quarters. On my visit to Gwadur therefore which 1 carried out partly for this reason I examined the three punkhas there. They certainly bore no great resemblance to the specimen^* produced before me by Abdul Wahab and in one detail are quite different, i.e. the fringes are of khaki cloth and not ofmm -17- matting as is possessed by the former. They do not seei ones and appear to be in the condition one would expect to find them in after lying anused for some eighteen months in I asJced Mr.Haiiz Ismail* the British A^ent, Cwadur, who had unpacked the furniture for the bungalow on its arrival from India and he replied tnat it had been done by him and after taxen over by iradhan Singh on his arrival there. Mr.Ismail said the punches now in the bungalow store room were those which had arrived with the other furniture. A statement to that effect signed by Mr.Ismail is attached marked 'C'. It struck me on close examination of these iiunxhas that though new, their quality was not what it might be and it may be that the firm had an uneasy conscience of this fact when they re±/lied to the Assistant Engineer* s query as their letter certainly does not seem quite a straightforward one. Though they say they ordered new punkhas rrom the makers they give the impression of not wishing to accept any responsibility in the matter (vide letters marked 'X' and 'Y' enclosures to your demi-official letter under reference). From all the evidence I have been able to obtain I am of tne opinion that the punxhas did come from India, were not old ones and that the accusation therefore is a false one. (b) Bot accounting for old Agency punxhas. Pradhan Singh explanation is as follows:- M When the Agency was electrified the work was carried out by a private firm under the close personal supervision of the late Political Agent. The old punxhas were not dismantled by me or handed over to me nor did I receive any orders from the Assistant Engineer or any one else to take them over. I do not know what has happened to them.” There is nothing on the Agency records to show what happened to the old punKhas. Three are with the r•w.u.i .W.D.Supervisor who says he found them in his store ahd the remainder I am given to understand were probably cut up and used in making a wooden balcony on the Agency terrace and other odd wood work. Under these circumstances I do not think that any responsibility lies on Pradhan Singh, to account for them. Reference accusation No.10. Charging in a Measurement Book for the use of certain materials in Government Building (Cast iron pipes in servants* quarters in the Agency) and not having used them on that work and miss* appropriating the money drawn for the work. Pradhan Singh admits that the pipes in question were never placed on the building though charged for in the Measurement Book. His explanation is as follows:- H When the servants* quarters were being completed in March 1935 it was found that the dram pipes on the western side of tiie main Agency Building were in a very bad condition. Ihe Political Agent at that time (Major Bremner) was most anxious to renew them as the front of the building had recently been changed to that side. After making certain tests it had been found that water from the roof of the servants* quarters was carried off by the short drain pipes clear of the wall and so the down take pipes had become unnecessary. With the approval ti.erefoi'e oi the Assistant Lngineer the down take pipes were placed on the Main Agency western wall instead of the servants* quarters. It will be noticed from the Public Aorks Department Measurement Book that the cost only of the pipes was charged for and no labonr for fixing which shows that no fraud was intended, had fraud been intended labour also would certainly have been charged for. 1 * mrI went and inspected the pipes. I asked iradhan Singh if the length of the four pipes he indicated was as described in the Measurement Book i.e. 104*. He replied that the total length was less as pipes of this sort are usually ordered in 6 * lengths which are cut to requirements and as could be seen each pipe was made up of cut and uncut sections to get the correct total length in each. Altogether sixteen lengths were used. Thus the total would with 'bends** and joints be less than 104 feet. I pointed out that the Measurement Book showed 3' pipes and the ones indicated to me were clearly larger than that. ±xachan Singh agreed and said actually these were 4** pipes and were supplied by the contractor who could not obtain 5 H pipes. It would appear that only a reference to the late Assistant Engineer Mr.Fatahali Sheikh can confirm the correctness or otherwise of Pradhan Singh’s statements above mentioned. Accusation ho.11. Sending an estimate for certain work to be carried out (lime plastering in the Treasury Officer’s quarters) with intent to defraud in that actual work was carried out by Central Contract Grant. To tliis accusation iradhan Singh gives the following explanation:- 'An estimate for this work was prepared and sent by me to the Assistant Engineer. Meanwhile the Treasury Officer in whose quarters the work was to be carried out requested the Political Agent to allow it to be done forthwith from the Central Contract Grant in order to avaoid further delay and inconvenience to him, this was sanctioned by the political Agent. Before the work was completed I left Muscat. I did not draw the money for it20 - on the estimate sent to the Assistant Engineer. I do not know whether tne money was actually drawn or not or who drew it. This point can be ascertained from the W.D.books, H Abdul Wahab could not throw any light on this point as he had not, he said, the measurement books, which had been sent to the k.W.D.Office Bushire. Tne Agency records show that the work was in fact yziiQ. bj the Central Contract Grant. Whether any payment was made ana to whom for the estimate sent to the P. */.D. 0 ffice Bushire presumably the Assistant Engineer should be in a position to ascertain. heference accusation No.12. preparing estimate with intent to defraud. (Intention alleged of using old material for new dressing room in Medical Officer's house). This is an accusation of intention defraud which is naturally denied by Pradhan Singh. I cannot obtain any evidence 01 this alleged fraudulent intention brought by the Assistant Engineer. Reference accusation No.13. Using Government materials for wiring a private house for his own use and not paying for all current consumed. (a) Pradhan Singh declares he purchased the materials in the bazaar. All Government property was handed over by him to his successor and a receipt obtained. No charge of shortage of materials has been made against him. (b) pradhan Singh says he paid for all current consumed, by him. Finding the rates too expensive for him he «Tuly aiscontinued the current on 1 st 1937 . if he could Abdul V.ahab asked throw any light on the matter produced the P.W.I). monthly statement book in which entries are shown of amounts paid by pradhan Singh for current consumed4 consumed in M&amp;y and June 1937, I cannot find out any further evidence to support tne Assistant hn^inee^s accusation* Perhaps he himself can elucidate the matter* Reference accusation No.14. Maying a false claim from Government for services of a a punkha puller while obtaining current from a Government electricity supply. Pradhan Singh states that he charged for and actually employed puno.-cha puller lor his office as ne was entitled to do under p.W.D.regulations. His office he says not connected withA^e Agency hiectric riant I have not been able to obtain from Abdul Vtahab or elsewhere any evidence either in support of the Assistant Engineer's accusation or to rebut Pradnan Singh’s explanation which presumably therefore may be accepted. Reference accusation No.15* Absconding from Iraq after misappropriating large amounts of the Iraq Government money and being liable to arrest on entering that country. * • V This accusation does not strictly come within the scope of my investigation since it concerns certain conduct of Pradhan Singh alleged to have taken place in Iraq* iradhnn Singh however requested to be allowed to maxe a statement for inclusion in the report of this investigation ’'This accusation is absolutely false. The true facts of my service in Iraq and the reasons why I left that country are in the records of the .British Consulate at J3asrah and can be ascertained by a reterence to tnat office*.-22 The following ia a suiru ary of my investigations into the 15 accusations brought against rradhan Singh as detailed in theproceeding paragraphs* Accusation Ho.ib is outside the proper scope of njy inquiry* Accusations Kos* 1 , 3, and 4 (items 1, 3, 5 and 6), 6 and 9 appear from the evidence to be false and deliberately concocted* Accusations Nos^t 4 ( items 2» 4 and 7), 7,3,11, 12, 13, 14 have not been proved* Accusations Nos* 5 and 10* To these accusations Pradhan Singh has given his explanations which, however, lack corroboration. This it seems can only be obtained by a reference to Mr.Patahali Sheikh, the Assistant Engineer at the time the alleged irregularities took place* Finally I would draw attention to the statements handed in by Abdul Wahab and Pradhan Singh ( harked 'A' and 'B') respectively)* From these statements it would appear there are /Ka-oCcL- grounds for believing that a definite attempt has beer^/not only to bring to light certain alleged irregularities but in addition to work up a case against pradhan Singh with a view to forcing him to resign from Government service. Yours sincerely. VStatement of Mr. H.M.Ismail, British A^ent,^waaar tsuten on 21.8.58. 'When the furniture for the new Political Bungalow arrived, at Gfwaaur, it was unpacked in my presence. Amongst the furniture were 6 punklia.s ana the punkhas now lyin^ in the out houses are the same ones. /4^L. (J.M- ^D.O. No. to £7 - British Consulate-General, Bushire. Dated the i^August, 1933. Uj ' v ^ cC ' I send you a copy of a further letter I have received from Abdul Wahah, and suggest that you might go into that while Abdul Wahah and Pradhan Singh are still in Muscat. The result of your investigations will he considered with the previous enquiry, the results of which I have not yet seen. Major R.p.watts, I.A., Political Agent, Muscat.(Copy) CONFIDENTIAL. No.323 or 1935. Muscat, dated the 10th August, 193 To The Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, Subject - some more charges I beg to submit another list of charges against Mr. pradhan Singh, Overseer, for your information. 2. It appears the Treasury Officer askea Kassim, our engine driver in power house, who has married KHANUli, whe ther Kassim will side me or Mr. praahan Singh. One of the clerk who is in good books or the political Agent, Muscat, b ROTI ML.lllli t ^urt™J*.':^*v~~******m* _ in an indirect way some 4 days back asked me whether the Punkah belonged to the Agency or the Public works Depart ment. To this I replied I do not knew. Yesterday evening Mr. pradhan Singh returned from Gwadur, and as soon as he landed, he straight way went upstairs and saw the Political Agent. From all these I am forced to think that there is something against Mr. pradhan Singh. His men are running here and there and there is a conference between him, kaduji the merchant in whose godwwn Government things are lying, and Hussein the mason, the coined'contractor. 3. I am afraid Muhammed Abdullah who was once a peon and now a painter, whose name was mentioneu as the man who took 3 punkahs and delivered to Mr. Pradhan Singh is working this morning in Treasury Olficer’s house without any infor- mation to me. From this I suspect that he may be maue to say nothing against or about the punkhas. If such be the case, it will be a bit difficult to prove that the punkhas- 2 - were sent from here, hut I have indirect proof to show that they were not sent from Karachi. 4 . i want your help, cooperation and support in dis charging my self-imposed duty to the entire satisfaction of the Department. In view of this the attached list is submitted to you for your information, with the re quest that I may he permitted to give a copy of the same through the Political Agent, Muscat, to kr.Pradhan Singh, at a convenient time, when I think it necessary, and request him to get a reply from Mr. pradhan Singh. 5. Finally I request you to he considerate on my honesty and to help me in the name of administration to eradicate the evil from the Department. If I have the chance of meeting you, and explain the things to you, I am sure you will start liking me, and thus encourage me. I heg to remain, Sir, your most obedient servant, (Sd.) ABDUL WAEAB Supervisor.(Sd.) ■ Ci£)Xj\jU ^ iiilidD 1. Dismantling Agency Compound wall tor building servants quarters. what has happened to solid pacca teak door? 2. Building servants quarters - 2 hath places in down stalls and 4 places in 1st floor were provided in the estimate. How many hath places you huilt ? 3. Extra cement plaster to the Agency was done hy you in 1934, to which portion of the Agency this extra plaster was done and in subsequence years you aia lime or cement plaster to the same building, where ana to what place? 4. Lime and niru plaster to the west wall was proviaea to the height of 5 feet and throughout its length, was it done according to the estimate ? 5. Four water spouts to the power house were sanctioned, how many you provided ? 6 . In 1934, lime and niru plaster to ground ana 1st floor of the verandah were provided to the Agency surgeon's house, was the work done according to the estimate. 7. Lime and niru plaster to ground floor and 1st floor of 2nd clars clerks* quarters were proviaed in 1934, was the work done in accordance with the sanctioned estimate 8 . 1935 cement plaster was provided to the verandah floor of the kitchen of 1 st class clerks, was the wor^ done in accordance with the sanctioned estimate. 9. Repairs to drain of 1st class clerks'quarters was pro vided, was this work done in work liKe manner. 10. Cement floor ng to 4 rooms in servants quarters, in 2nd class clerks’ quarters were sanctionea. Did you plasta* all the 4 rooms. 11. In 1936, opening to the ends of beams of the Agency and filling them with cement concrete was sanctionea. Was the work done as provided in the sanctioned estimate 12. Did you repair the floor of Jamadars quarters - verandah few years back. seeing its present condition, can it be said that it was repaired ?Confidential D.O. No. C/141. Political Agency &amp; H.M*b Consulate, Muscat, the 12th October 1938* Heference your demi official letter to me Mo* 1581 dated the 30th August 1938 which was forwarded on to me on recess. Abdul Wahab has returned to Muscat and Pardhan Singh being still here I have, as you suggested, endeavoured to go into the further list of charges brought by the former against the latter. 2. As regards charge No. 1 Abdul Wahab declares the door in question was demolished during the period when Pardhan Singh was stationed in Muscat. The latter declares this is not so but that all the demolition of the old servants' quarters was completed before his arrival here and this fact can be verified from the P.W.D. records in Bushire. As regards the remaining charges Abdul Wahab says that the re levant Measurement Books are a 11 in Bushire. In the absence of this necessary information contained in these books 1 have been unable to Investigate further these charges. In this connection, however, I forward a statement by Fardhan Singh giving his explanation regarding the charges brougit against him. Captain A.C. Galloway, I.A., Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.• * r&gt; No. C^y Muscat, elated 28th September, 1938. To The assistant Engineer, British Consulate General, Bushire. Subject Appointment of assistant Driver. Sir, Ali bin Juma, ?/hose real name is ali bin Nasar was employed by supervisor Mr Abdul ftahab as Assistant Driver from the 1st of July,1938, for 3 months on probation at hs. 26/- per month,please see your letter No. 6/758 dated 23rd of July, 1938, and on acquiring complete practical Knowledge of running the plant during 3 months probationary period his pay to be increased to Rs. 40/- per month, and he to be taken up on the permanent establishment,and curing the 3 months probationary period of Ali bin Juma, y^assam has been given an increase of Rs. 20/- per month for training him in electric line. As the 3 months probation period of the assistant driver completes on the 30th of September, 1938, therefore as desired in your No.6/758 dated 33rd of July,1938, I beg to put up report on the assistant driver for your consideration and necessary action. Mr Abdul Aahab when handed over the charge of the plant to me, had some difficulty to express his opinion on this man, and later on hesitatingly he said, 'Though he can assemble parts of the en^in but he does not understand mechanism'. I put up the question to Ali bin Juma in the presence of ult abdul- tiahab, V.hether he can run the engin in the absence of Qassam, his reply was definite NO. Then Mr Abdul- Aahab told him something in arabic, there upon he timidlv said. that, ha nan start thoonenn. and wnrVit f but if any thing &amp;oes wrong in the engin, he can neither detect it, nor can put it right, as to his knowledge of electricity for the training of which ^assam has been paid Ks. 20/- per month for the last 3 months, he was sent for to remove a fan regulator from the switch board in the office of the Political Agent on the 16th of September, 1938, which he was very much afraid to touch, and stated that as he has never been told how to remove the regulator, and that he was afraid that if he tried to remove the re 6 ulator he might 0 et shock. v assam had to be sent'for to remove the switch board and regulator. . ^now It might interest you to the personaiit,) of the assistant driver, therefore I may state, that he has white in both of his eyes, and he is practically blind of one eye although he can slightly see from his other eye. Eis buth hands tremble either due to his over drinking or to the fact that he has suffered from syphlis in the past. No doubt he is a son of on ordinary black smith who works for Sultan on Rs. 10/- per month and not a mechanic as Mr Abdul tahab has said in his letter No. 263, dated 28th of June, 1938, for Sultan has no tiling to work on for such a mechanic. His father tried to make him a smith but owing to the above stated physical defects he has been an utter failure,and his father had turned him out of his work-shop. Ali bin Juma was also employed at Rs. ib/- per month mm as an oil man on the Agency plant in about i936 f and he worked for about 2 months or so but he was turned out from the job ov^ing to his short sightedness and inefficiency. A few months before coming to the Agency- Plant as assistant driver, he was employed in the state power house as an oil man on 50 local baizas a day, which is equal to Rs. 7/8/- per month, but was dismissed from there owing to the same reasons as from the A^encv clant.@ ^ It is not easy for me to find out the real motive of ikU* Abdul i.ahab in engaging a man of the type of ali bin Juma at a handsome pay of Bs. 40/- per month, but I am told that the man is related to Mrs Abdul Wahab, and just to find a job for his wiles f relative Mr Abdul Wahab has probably provided this employment for him. In order to acquire ^assams* ( engin driver) support in the matter, it will be seen that the latter has been offered Bs. 20/- extra per month for 3 months, and I understand has been given a promise of leave. It does not appear, that the Political Agent Muscat was consulted as suggested in your letter No (/6o9 dated u^nd of June 1938,para 2, 1 am sure, if he would have been consulted, he would have never given his approval, not only this, but I am certain that if you would have seen the assistant driver personally,you would never have given your approval for the appointment. The man no doubt is very inefficient and utterly unfit for the job, during the last three months of nis probationary period he has learnt nothing, it is my confirmed opinion that this man would never make a good driver, and no man who knows him would ever think of employing him as a driver. I beg to remain, Sir Your most obedient servant Overseer,?. »uD. muscat Copy to the PoliticalAgent Muscat for information pleaseCopy of letter fto 231 dated Muscat the 8th June 1938, from Mr Abdul Wahab Supervisor to the Assistant- Engineer, P.W.D. Bushire. Be-- Appointment of Assistant Engin Driver. At present the engin works for 24 hours, as such I would strongly recommend that an Assistant driver as provided in the sanctioned estimate may please be provided.*HW g) ^ Copy of letter No. 263 dated Muscat the 28th June 1938, from Mr. Abdul Wahab supervisor to the Assistant Engineer. P.W.D. Bushire. Re- Appointment of Assistant Engin Driver. With reference to your No.6/659 dated 22nd June 1938,asking me to recommend a suitable man as Assistant Driver on Rs.60/- per month, I beg to state that no good driver with knowledge of electricity is available here, but there are 2 good oil engin drivers one is working with R.A.F.Rest house on Rs. 1-12-0 perd^ and he is ready to leave his job and take up with us on condition that his salry will be Rs.40/- per month and he will be retained permanently, and there is a second man named Ali bin Juma, who is not only a good driver but a fitter as well, and his father is a good mechanic of the Sultan. I propose taking him as an apprentice on Rs. 25/- per month with effect from 1st July,and he will be trained in electric line by Kassam, and subject to your approval, Kassam may be given a bonus of Rs.25/- per month for 3 months, the period of apprenticement of Ali. After that Ali may be taken on permanent establish ment on Rs. 40/- per month, provided his work is satifact tory, so that he can relieve Kassam when hev wants to go on leave in winter.Copy of letter No. 6/758 dated Bushire 23rd of July 1938, from the Assistant Engineer,British Consulate General, to Mr. Abdul Wahab P.W.D. Supervisor Muscat. Subject Appointment of Assistant Driver. Reference your letter No.263 datedthe 28th June 1938. The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is pleased to approve the appointmentment of Ali bin Juma as Assistant Driver on 3 months probation with effect from 1st July,1938. During the period of probation of 3 months his pay should be Rs. 25/-p.m. and on completion of the probation nery period,his pay would be increased to Rs. 40/-p.m. if he is reported to have acquired complete practical knowledge of running the plant. 2. The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is also pleased to sanction an increases of Rs.20/-p.m. in the pay of Kassam Driver for 3 months only from 1st July,1938.Copy of letter No. 6/659 dated Bushire the 22nd June 1938, from the Assistant Engineer, British Consulate General,to Mr. Abdulwahab, P .W.D.Supervisor Muscat. Reference your letter No.231 dated the 8th June 1938. Please recommend the name of a suitable man to work as Assistant Driver. The pay sanctioned for the post in question is Rs. 60/- p.m. In case of emergency a suitable man may be appointed forthwith with the approval of the Political Agent Muscat. The name of the man appointed may please be reported atonce, for obtaining approval of the competent authority.MMi CONFIDtiii UAL. No. C/139. 0 0 Political Agency &amp; H.M* 8 Consulate, Muscat, the 11th October 1938. Prom To Major H.P. Watts, I.A., Political Agent &amp; H.M* s Consul, Muscat. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire • Sir, I have the honour to bring the following matters to your notice for any action that may be considered necesaaiy: 2. On 22nd June 1938 the Assistant Engineer wrote to Mr. Abduf Wahab, P.W.D. Supervisor at Muscat permitting him to engage a suitable man as an Assistant Driver for the Agency Power Plant, the sanctioned pay being fis 60/- per mensem vide copy attached for ready reference. It will be seen therefrom that 'in case of emergency' permission was granted to engage a suitable man forthwith with the approval of the Political Agent. Immediately on receipt of the Assistant Engineer^ letter Mr. Abdul Wahab engaged what he considered a suitable man but without the approval of the Political Agent and without any reference to him. when this fact was brought to my notice,(vide report of the Overseer Mr. Pardhansingh No. 87 dated 28th September 1938 to the Assistant Engineer Bushire, copy to me), I asked for an explanation from Mr. Abdul Wahab and he replied that since he had engaged a man for less than is 60/- no approval of mine was necessary. This answer of course is a mere quibble and an attempt to excuse a sheer disobedience of his superior officer 1 sofficer’s orders. It has been ascertained that in the otfice copy of Mr. Abdul dahab’s letter No. 263 of 28th June to the Assistaht Engineer informing him that a driver had been engaged an endorsement has been made to the ellect that a copy was sent to the Political Agent. No trace of thib copy can be found in the Agency records and I am convinced that it was, in fact, never sent. In view of Mr. Pardhansingh* s report I had the eyesight of the man in question tested by the Agency Doctor whose report is attached, it will be seen therefrom that the man is totally hling in one eyeand has impaired vision / in the other. The Medical Officer considers that he is unfit to look after machinery. .rfhy Mr. Abdul tfahab picked out an obviously un suitable nan for the purpose is no doubt best known to him though the probable reason is that he has personally bene- fitted thereby in some illegal way. As the break down of the Electric Light Plant which might quite easily take place when in charge of anyone with defective eyesight would in a place with the notoriously bad climate of Muscat be a matter of extreme inconvenience to all members of the Agency besides probaly involving Government in serious pecuniary loss I suggest that orders be issued to the Assistant Engineer to dispense with this man's services and a some one with two good eyes engaged forthwith. 3 . A few days ago the Agency Medical Officer reported to me that a drain near the Sub—Assistant Surgeon s house was giving off an ofiensive odour and that on examination he found that it was of recent construction and of a type unsuitable and insanitary for covered drains. Further inquiry brought to light that some four months ago L.r« Abdul iahab without any reference to me (and without obtaining the ai&gt;proval at the time of hie superior officer the Assistant Engineer) had broken up the drain and made a new one of unsuitable materials* The only explanation Mr* Abdul Wahab couJd give was that in accordance with instruc tions from the Assistant Engineer he prepared estimates for certain works to be carried out; amongst these was the drain in question and to make the estimate he had to demolish the drain and build another one* This I believe to be a false hood, but what I have to complain of is that the work was carried out without informing me* JFonnal sanction of the work has, it appears, only now at the end of September been received from the Assistant Engineer while Mr* Abdul tfahab tooK it upon himself to do this about four months previously. On the advice of the Medical Officer I have given orders for this drain to be demolished and one of suitable ty. type constructed* The cost of this work in my opinion should, be recovered from Mr* Abdul Wahab* 4 . On my return from a recent absence from Muscat I found that Mr* Abdul #ahab without any reference to the Treasury Officer - who on such occasions is in charge of the Agency - had built four unsightly stone pillars in various spots in the Agency premises* Concerning one of these I have received a complaint from the Officer in Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited as it has been built just outside their office door on their terrace without consulting him. He declares it is a source of great inconvenience to his staff when entering and leaving their office, a possible danger at night as the terrace is not lighted* Mr* Abdul Wahab states he constructed the pillars to carry out orders of the Assistant Engineer to take obser vations for signs of subsidence of the Medical Officer’s house* I am informed that it is quite unnecessary for such pillars to be constructed for the parpose but whatever the Cflse- 4 - case may be I consider that X should have been informed before hand of the proposed work. 5 , On a number of occasions recently I have sent for Mr. Abdul tfahab on matters concerning Agency repairs etc. but he could not be found either in his office or at the Power Station. I have now found out that these absences of his were accounted for by the fact that he has been for some time past doing unauthorised private work in the town in supervising and helping a friend in his work. Mr.Abdul Wahab when asked by me if this was true vehemently denied it m but I have ample andxeliable evidence available which if required can be forwarded to you in the form sworn written statements* that these facts are true. 6 . Finally I wish to report that Mr. Abdul tfahab has/ grossly impertinent to me in the presence of the Treasury Officer when 1 was questioning him about about the matters mentioned above. I object very strongly to the insolent attitude of this P.tf.D. subordinate and request that he may be transferred from Muscat as soon as possible. I have the honour to be* Sir* Your obedient servant* been ^ ^ Major* Political Agent &amp; H.M* e Consul* Muscat.© neport on the eyesight of Ali bin hasar. i have examined the eyesight of Ali bin hasar by orders of the Political Agent and beg to report as follows, Kight eye Total blindness due to a central corneal scar caused by previous ulceration, .Left eye ••••• bight moderately good, btates he cannot see very well at night. May suffer from night blindness. Remarks..... Due to the above, I am of opinion that this man should not be employed to work on any machinery. Medical Officer, Muscat.® £ h het)ort on the drain between the quarters of the Treasury Officer and hr. Desa^s. XXXXXJUCXXXXXJC This drain still gives off foul odours and is not of a suitable pattern as it does not permit easy cleaning 6 th October 1938 Medical Officer, Muscatt D.o. No. ! *4 December 8 th, 1938. I enclose herewith a copy of a letter from Pardhan Singh, P.W.D. Overseer, to the Assistant Engineer Bushire on the subject of the Gwadur Bungalow. 2. At Pardhan Singh’s request I went up on the roof of the bungalow while he dug several holes in the roof. I saw that under a thin layer of mud the remaining portion of t the roof was formed of rubbish (pieces of old r^gs, sticks, animal dung and other dirt) evidently gathered from the nearest Baluch refuse heap. I believe in the estimate for tne bungalow the roof was to be of solid mud on mat foundation has and this/been apparently charged for. 3. The very first rains which fell after completion of the bungalow went straight through the roof and did con siderable damage to the furniture, curtains and carpets. Had the roof been built according to the estimate I doubt whether this would have happened. 4 . tfould it be possible to get the Assistant Engineer to take some interest in the bungalow. He has not been over to Gwadur since he too* over his appointment nearly two years Captain A.C. Galloway, I.A., Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIHENo. 104 To The Assistant Engineer, British Consulate General /./V. Bushire. ^c&gt;\^ Subject Guwadur Bungalow. Sir, I beg to report that under your instructions contained in your letter No 8/911 dated 28th of September,1938, I opened the roof of the bungalow on some places to prepare the estimate, and found that the roof,when it was constructed by Mr. Mohd Ishaq was not constructed according to the specifications, and there by it appears he has saved and pocketed k 173/- from this single item of the roof. If the cost of chandles,bamboos,and mattings be considered along with it, it will come to about k 300/- and a- little over, which were saved and pocketed for his personal gratifications,on a single item of roof of the bungalow. Similar]/ if the investigations are made on the full work of the bungalow I consider it will easily be proved, that not less than k 3000/- were saved from this single work, and all this money was pocketed by Mr. Mohd Ishaq for his personal gratifications. There are funny tales told about this work, if you have the regular enquiries instituted many things will come to light, and it will be proved beyond doubt that k 3000/- was actually saved from this work, and out of it fc 1000/- was paid to a certain person on a certain date to keep his lips closed. I give below a few points just to convince you that how funds were squandered away on one single item of roof :- 1- Chandles were purchased very cheap and of very bad quality,the bamboos and mattings have been used very sparingly,there by a saving of fe 200/- has been effected. 2- Mud of the roof has been put at randum with-out dressing or wetting and beating there by a saving of fe 40/- has been effected.3- Pure and clean sand collected from the site of work with a few clods of hard mud has been used in place of good mud, and there by a saving of &amp; 55/- has been effected on the roof of servants quarters alone. 4- Dung,straw,and leaves(dirt of Baluch encampment) have been used to keep the roof as light as possible in place of mud ,and there by a saving of Rs 787- have been effected on the roof of Mai Building verandah alone. S The dung,straw and leaves it appears have been used to keep the roof as light as possible there by to hide the defect of weak chandles. A sample of dung and straw etc is sent to you in a separate cover for your inspection. From the above you will please see that how the money has been saved,not only bad materials but un-suitable materials have been used, and there by the Govt, has suffered a loss of Rs 700/- on one single item of roof only. There fore it is requested that you will please have the necessary enquiries instituted. I request that this roof may please be inspected by some responsible person to stand witness to my above statement before you order its dismantling for re-roofing. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Copy to the Political Agent Muscat,with a request,that as the work of the bungalow is under your jurisdiction,there fore you will kindly take necessary steps to have the necessary enquiries made. The roof is a definite proof of dishonesty and squandring of Govt funds. There fore some action may be taken before the Assistant Engineer orders its dismantling and re-roofing. I am afraid the Assistant Engineer is trying to shield Mr.Mohd Ishaq and has not taken any action on my previous reports.D.O. No.^\n*\ -64/254. Dated the 16th December, 1938. of 1938 with enclosures, on the subject of certain alls gations against Overseer Pradhan Singh. 2 . Sir Trenchard has gone very carefully into the matter, and he desires me to enclose herewith his comments on your report. Sir Trenchard desires that you should take the following action: (a) Sir Trenchard is of the opinion that allegation 4, in particular tne natter of the l T f irons, should form the basis of a criminal charge by you against Mr. Pradhan Singh who apparently had charge of the property and Madhuji in whose godown some of the property at least was discovered. The suitable sections of the Indian Penal Code would appear to be 409 (for Pradhan Singh) and 424 (for Madhuji). (b) With regard to allegation No.7 on the subject of using old cenent blocks and charging for new blocks, we have now obtained the Assistant Engineer* s statement narked ’AS a copy of which is enclosed herewith. Briefly the Assistant Engineer states that the blocks used in constructing the cistern were old hollow blocks filled with cement, while Pradhan Singh, on the other hand, in his bill charged full estimated rates as for new blocks. You should get Pradhan /Singh* s or R#P. ^atts, I.A., Political Agent, Muscat.2 - Singh's explanation in writing and forward this as soon as possible, with any comments you have to offer. 4. With regard to the remaining allegations. some of them leave an unpleasant impression on Sir Trenchard's mind but he is not of the opinion, as you will see, that definite action can be taken against Pradhan Singh on them. 5. Finally with regard to allegation Ho.5 Sir Trenchard notes that you as Political Agent signed the completion certi ficate for a certain piece of work. He understands that it has been the practice for the Political Agent to do this for some time past, but it is entirely unnecessary and even objectionable. The proper official to sign the completion certificate is the Assistant Engineer whose responsibility it is and not that of the Political Agsnt to see that the work has been properly completed. ^ ^ e V 'MfPKDH 7 0 Comments by Sir Trenchard le on Major Watts' invettigation into certain allegations against Overseer Pradhan Singh. ACCUSATION 1. 'Obtaining the thumb impression of a certain woman named Sabihue with the intention of using it for an illegal purpose'. P.H. agrees with Major Watts that no legal action can be taken in this accusation, and notes that Major toatte has administered a warning to Mr. Pradhan Singh on his conduct. ACCUSATION 2. 'Falsely showing in estimates names of two coolies as contractors'. P.R's opinion on this accusation is that it is impossible to say whether the two individuals concerned were or were not contractors. ACCUSATION 3. 'Using tiles belonging to Government (Sind tiles from Politi cal Agents Office) on private work and not accounting for these tiles'. P.R. is ol the following opinion, that as the work in the fish market was completed before the floor of the Political Agent's office was taken up, i.e., before the Sind tiles from this office, could have been available, (as pointed out by Major Watts) there is no basis for this accusa tion. ACCUSATION 4. 'Selling, „or concealing with intent tp d®^ raud certarn Government property (Iron stair-case, 'T' irons, flooring material, sweepers' stair case, balcony railings, Venetian shutters and Post Office door) and not crediting proceeds to Government. &lt;(a) Selling and concealing an iron stair-case. This stair-case is in the P.W.D* godown. P.R's opinion therefore is that there is no case. (b) Concealing and selling 17 ■T*irons. These were found in the godown of one Madhuji Mr. Pradhan Sing*s accieation is that the coolies who were removing the , T I irons i by mistake* instead oi putting tnem into the P.W.D. store took them to that of Madhuji. Major Watts expresses no opinion on this explanation but P.R. considers this explanation quite inadequate. Major Watts has ordered the , T* irons to be taken back to the P.W.D. go down and Madhuji to appear before him. Major Watts does not state wh^ t action he has taken against Madhuji. (c) Concealing and selling a piece of wooden flooring belonging to the Agency. Mr. Pradhan Singh explains that with Major Watts* sanction he put aside this flooring for use in the Medical Officer’s house* and stored it in the Medical Officer’s garage with the permission of the Medical Officer. The Medical Officer confirms that Mr. Pradhan Singh put the wood in his garage and the wood was found there by Major Watts. P.R. does not understand why the wood was stored in tne garage instead of the P.W.D. store, but wood was found in the garage and there is no sufficient evidence to uphold this accusation. (d) Concealing and selling the sweeper’s stair-case. Major Watts makes no comments on this. He can go fully into the matter later.(e) Concealing and selling balcony railings. Major ^atts reports that Mr. Abdul Wahab, *ho originally brought this accusation, now admits, having inspected the site, that this accusation has no basis. P.R. agrees. (f) Concealing and selling Venetian shutters. It appears that Venetian shutters were found by Mr. Abdul *abab in Madhuji^ snop, and he alleged that they were Government property. There is no doubt that the shutters *ere in Madhuji’s shop but he says that he puj&gt; chased them from Ali Khan*s house. Major Watts ordered tne return of the shutters and they \*ere brought back, but the next night Madhuji without permission removed the shutters and Mr. Abdul Waha b states that he saw them being brought back in the morning. T.O. is witness to this. Later T.O. states that he saw Mr. Abdul Wahab cleaning and polishing fittings, his object being to make the makers name visible to prove that the shutters were the same as those which were earlier in the P.W.D. godown. Major Watts dismisses this charge on the grounds that Mr. Abdul Wahab was tampering with evidence. It seercs to P.R. that the matter wants going into further, and Major Watts should do so ACCUSATIOM b ••Showing in a Measurement Book certain work (fly proofing of fan lights in Agency Medical Officers house) as having been done and charging for them but which in reality was never carried out'. The P.R. is of the opinion that this is a case of inefficiency on the part of Mr. Pradhan Singh who should of course have na de the fan light gauzes of the proper shape so that the windows could be opened. p.ia not of th« opinion tnat aaj accusation lies that the wor* in question *ae shown in the measurement book as done wnen it was not done. Major Watts on being informed tar the Medical Officer that the work had been completed (the work was for the Medical Officer's house) signed the completion certificate* Tne P*R* does not understand why it is necessary for Major Watts as Political Agent to sign the completion certificate, as such work is the business of the A.S. The latter should undertake the matter in future* v t ,. r j i&gt;- ccrwr* _ .'i' 'ff r 141 \GCUS ,\TIOy 6 s, 'Preparing a false voucher and receiving payment for work not executed» (lime plastering on roof of S.A.S'e quarters)'*. As the completion certificate was signed by Major latts, who states that he saw the wor* wnen it was com pleted, P.R. is of the opinion that no case lies. AGCUSATIOJJ 7. 'Using old cement blocks belonging to Government in the construction of a cistern and charging for new blocks'. P.R. does not agree with Major Watts that this accu sat ion has not been substantiated in as much as the A*S. has pulled the cistern to pieces in places to prove the matter. Major Watts to go further into the matter. ACCUSATION 8 . 'Remitting such amounts of money to India as could only have been obtained by defrauding Government'. Major Watts points out that the A*-S. can apparently produce no proof of his accusation. P.R. has asked the A.S. for his proof, this the latter has been unable to JL@ 7 9 -5- produce satisfactorUy. P.H. is of the opinion that no case lies under this accusation. ACCUSATION 9. (a) 'Taking old punkhas to G*adur signing in a Measurement Book as having been received new from India as part of the Political Bungalow furniture'. ( a ) Ths P.R* is of the opinion that in the first place this is a p*tty case on the value of three punkha poles which is ver.y small and in the second place he accepts, of course, Major Watts* statement that he saw the poles in Gwadur, that they appeared to be new. (b) 'Not accounting for old Agency puakhas'. (b) p.R. agrees with Major Watts that no responsibility rests on Mr. Pradhan Singh as the disposal of the punkha poles was not his affair. As Mr. Pradhan Singh suggests, tne punkha poles were perhaps cut up and used for odd repairs about the Agency. ACCUSATION 10. 'Charging in a Measurement Book for the use of certain materials in a Government Building (cast iron pipes in servants' quarters in Agency) and not having used them on that work and mis appropriating the money drawn for the work.' P.R. agrees with Major Watts that only a reference to the late A.k. can clear this question up satisfactorily and since the value of a few feet of iron piping can only be smallt he does not consider this worth-while. The P. R therefore is of the opinion that no accusation lies under this heading. ACCUSATION 11. 'Sending an estimate for certain carried out (lime plastering in Officer's quarters) with intent in that actual work was carried Contract Grant'. work to be the Treasury to defraud out by Centrall I A.B’s statement is as follous:- 'ItemlJo.ii is for the niru plaster on the ifcalls of 2 round floor rooms. The first time, I came to know that the work has already been done and paid from C*G.G. was from the report of Mr. Mohamtd Ishaq (page 178). The Treasury Officer^ reply is on page 200. The Political Agent inspected tne work done by Mr. Pradhan Singh, and ordered Mr. Mohamed Ishaq on 27th September (vide endorse ment on page 200) to replaster both the rooms. The Poli tical Agent could have called for the explanation of Mr. Pradhan Singh for doing such a bed work that it was found necessary to re-do it after two months, or he could have reported the matter for suitable action. Ho notice was apparently taken by him of this bad work'*. P.R. is of the opinion that the matter is not sufficient to warrant further action. accusation 1 *. 'Preparing an estimate with intent to defraud. (Intention alleged of using old material for new dressing room in Medical Officer’s house ) ! * A.E *8 statement is as followsi- The estimate for special repairs to Agency Sur ' 3 ge on* s house is on page 265. Item Ho .2(a) is for teakwood windows and item Ho.3 is for tiles, flooring to the dressing room. Please read iqy letter (page 267) and Mr. Pradhan Singh’s reply (page 277). 'The explanation is far from satisfactory. The overseer admits that windows and tiles were in stock. After painting, old windows would have looked as good as new. The old tiles are in a first class condition. They were required for a dressing room and not a bath-room© -7- (¥id« page a 6 o item 3x). Therefore white tiles were not at all necessary*. P.R. is of the opinion that only intention could be proved and that the matter is not sufficient to warrant further action. A.CCUSATIOS 13. 'Using Government naterials for wiring a private house for his own use and not paying for all current consumed'. P.R. is of the following opinion: The case cannot be proved unless proof can be brought that: (i) the house was wired with Government material, and (ii) that current was consumed without being paid for. P.R. does not see how these points can be proved and therefore no accusation can lie. The position now is that Mr. Pradhan Singh is certainly not using current as he states it was too expensive. In the P.fc.D. books be was shown as paying for current for May and June, 1937. ACCUSATION 14. 'Making a false claim from Government for services of a punkha puller'. P.R. is of the following opinion:- That from local investigation Major Watts should certainly be able to ascertain on what date Mr. Pradhan Singh*s office was supplied with Government electricity, and whether Mr. Pradhan Singh after that date drew allowance for an office punkha coolie. As no records are available in Bushire, P.R. does not think, in view of the non-existence of proof about accusation 13 to go further into the matter at presentACCUSATION 15. come not 'Absconding from Iraq after misappropriating large amounts of the Iraq Government *t money and being liable to arrest on entering that country'. P.R. agrees with Major Watts that this does not withing the scope of his enquiry, and therefore need be considered.3»cretary, (n) 7?^ K cement concrete cistern vrae constructed near the Power House at Muscat. During my inspection in November 1937 I got part of it dismantled, and found that old surplus holloa blocks were used, after filling them with cement concrete. Fill estimated rates were charged for this work. Similar hollow cement blocks were lying in the power House compound 12 / 12 /zaCONFU &gt;EWnMj ' D*0 .No* C/13 (g) 7/ The political Agency, Muscat. Dated the 17th January 1939. v Dear Galloway, Please refer to your demi-official letter Ko.&lt;U/9- 64/254 dated the loth December 1938* Your v ara 6 ra ±'* 1 3( a ) I have aa instructed charged ^radhan Singh under Section 409 Indian renal Code in tne matter of the'T’ irons etc He has asiced for certified copies of certain correspondence enich passed between him and the Assistant Engineer as given in the attached list, which he requires for his defence, lay the copies be sent to me please. I am also proceeding with the case against Madhuji. Your paragraph 3 (b) Attached is pradhan Singh’s explanation regarding the cement blocks together with my comments tnereoi. Yours sincerely, Captain A.O. Galloway, I.A., Secretary to tne Hon'ble the roliticai Resident in the Persian Gulf,n) Co^y of assistant Engineer Note dated 24th oi March 1938 addressed to Mr.Pradhan Singh. Co^y of re^iy to the above note from Mr.rradhan Singh. Assistant Engineer’s No.C-A/H dated 9th A^ril 1938. ^radhan letter No .29 dated 13th April 1938 in reply to Assistant Engineer’s No.C-A/H dated 9th April 1938. Assistant Engineer’s No.C-A/10 dated 6th April 1938. Mr.Pradhan Singh’s letter No.28 dated 15th April 1938. Statement from Assistant Engineer to the eifect that rubiic tforKS Department had any stores at Muscat with reference of vouchers for the payment of the rent of the stores, No.102 of 20th October 1938. Relevant measurement booic shewing removal of 'T'irons from the political Agent’s 01lice. SET3) The accusation against .iradhan Singh in tins matter by the Assistant Engineer can be divided into two ^arts. (1) Using old cement blocks instead of new ones charged for (2) Using surplus blocks belonging to Government and charging for new ones. As regards (l) the Assistant Engineer bases his opinion on the two follow! tig alleged iacts wc-ret Scruf fz 1 w ~ (a) He states he broice open ^ bxocKyano. found old one* (b) Coolies who carried out the work imormed nim that old blocks had been used. Iradhan Singh’s answer to (a) and (b) abovei- re (a) ” The blocks w^^broken open six months after the worx was completed. After the lapse oi such a time it is impossible for any one to say what was the c ! v - original condition of a cement block which had been covered with cement mortar'. re (b) ' The Assistant Engineer has not given the names of the coolies; if they are produced their statements can then be considered in comparison with that of the mason in charge of the work who at the investi gation carried out in August stated beiore the political Agent that new blocks were used'. Reference (a) of accusation Ho. 1 The Assistant Engineer declares he could tell from the examination of a block when broxen open that it was originally an old one; xradhan oingh retorts this is an impossibility under the circumstances. Here are t.*o qualified engineers in dispute over a technical question which 1 consid er could only be decided by a cement expert and I therefore am unable to express an opinion on it. ReferenceReference (b) of accusation No.l The contractor who carried out the work iniormed me that the coolies engaged by him for the purpose were Kadir and Ali. I summoned these men before me. They declared on oatn that (l) they had never stated to the Assistant Engineer that the blocks were old ( 2 ) the blocks used were in fact new ones. The Assistant engineer may perhaps be asited if he agrees that the names of these coolies as given by the contractor are correct. If so in the absence of evidence to the contrary I am of the opinion that their statements made on oath before me should be accepted. If ( Assistant Engineer declares these men were not the coolies I consider he should produce evidence as co wh« in fact they were and they can then be examined. As regards ^art 2 oi the accusation . If the blocks belonged to Government presumably it would be possible to ^rove this by a reference to the rublic ^orks Department Stock Books. I can see no reference in any of the correspondence on this subject to it having been found tnat any Government biocxs were missing. The Assistant Engineer states the blocks used were similar to tnose lying near the rower House but that is no t a proof that they ^Government property. To sum up. It seems to me that as regards part (l) of the accuse-— tion . , . , ,, The statements of coolies can rarely be relied on, the only means therefore, I consider, of arriving at a decision is to dismantle the whole cistern and obtain the opinion oi an impartial expert i.e. an engineer. As regards part (2) of the accusation. It seems to me that on this point the Assistant engineer should produce further evidence to prove that the blocks in question were Government property.toe#' CONFIDENTIAL. No. TT The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s). Owing to clerical error the omiecion in the first instance i is very much regretted. Political Agency and British Consulate. Muscat. at '^19th January 19 39.- Reference to previous correspondence : Reference ray D.O. No. C/13 dated the 17th January 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Dato. Subject. (ll Explanation of Mr. Pradhan Singh. Case against Pradhan Singh.D.O.No. 25 Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat the 21st .February 1939. i Subjects- Trial of Pardiian Sin^h, P.W.D.Overseer . Under instructions from Sir Trenchard Powle I have tried Pardhan Singh for certain offences alleged to have been committed by him in Muscat. In the course of the trial copies of certain letters said to have been written by Pardhan Singh to the Assistant Engineer were exhibited but could not be 'proved' owing to the absence of the originals. dated 17th January 1939 I had asiced Galloway in my 15.0. to him No.C/13 to A send certified copies of these letters to me and he infor med me verbally when in Muscat that all the letters for which irardhan Singh had allied wore with the corres pondence already sent me. A search through our records has however failed to produce them and it appears that the originals of the letters referred to must be in the poss ession of the Assistant Engineer in Bushire. To enable me to write my Judgment in the case I should li^ce to know a whether the copies of these letters handed in to Court by rardhan Singh are true copies of the originals or not. Would you therefore please compare these copies which are attached herewith, with tiie originals and if correct tele graph me the one word ’•confirmed' or 'unconfirmed' as the case may be. On receipt of your reply I can then write my Judgment. The file of Pardhan Singh’s case is I believe with Galloway but I am writing to you regarding confirmation Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A., Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.- 2 - 1 of the true copies of the letters which are probably with Assistant Engineer to avoid further delay in this case which has been dragging on for some time*D.0. NO. C/40 14th March 1939 Subject:• Pradhan Slnflh. P.W.D. Overceer. Please refer to your D.O. No. 2179-64/P54 dated 16th Deceraber 1938. p, I forward herewith copy of ny Judgment in the cases brought against Pradhan Singh and Madhuji. As you will see I have discharged Pradhan Singh and acquitted Madhuji for the reasons given in my Judgment. 3 # Ax instructed by Sir Trenohard Fowls vide enclosure to vour D.O. quoted above I have made further investigations into the 3 accusations mentioned i.e. No. 4(d), 4(f) and 14 and forward the results as given in the attached statement. Major A.C. Galloway, I.A., Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,/'A • ' (&amp;) 8* 1 Reference Accusations 4(cU. Sweeper 1 s atair-Case. This staircase was dismantled in September 1936. According to Rradhan Singh's statement he actually did this in the presence of the late Assistant Engineer, Mr. Fateh Ali Sheikh, who decided that the staircase was unserviceable and should be scrapped. A few sound pieces of wood therefrom were deposited in the Agency for any odd purpose they might be required and these Pradhan Singh declared were amongst the material collected by him for use in the Medical Officer's house and stored and found in the latter's garage. The only person who could rebut or corroborate Pradhan Singh's statement is Mr. Fateh Ali Sheikh,the late Assistant Engineer, and as recourse to him is hardly practicable I consider this portion of accusation No. 4 should be dropped. Reference accusation 4(f). Venetian shutters found in the house of Madho.ii. I did not go further into this matter for reasons I give below and which through an oversight I regret I omitted to include in the report of my investigations. ( 1 ) Abdul Wahab who brought this accusation against Pradhan Singh was unable to show that any shutters were missing from the P.W.D. Stores. (2) According to the Agency records no Venetian shutters are missing from the Agency. (3) Madhuji was able to prove prima facie from his accounts that he purchased the shutters at an auction. (4) Madhuji, produced in his defence, four shutters, lent him from the Sultan's storehouse, exactly similar to those in question in order to disprove Abdul Wahab's statement that such a pattern was to be found only in the Agency. ( 6 ) Abdul Wahab's action in bringing P.W.D. shutters from his store mixing them up with those from Madhuji's house and endeavouring to make them all resemble one another. This added to the above facts convinced me that Abdul Wahab had / deliberatelydeliberately concocted this accusation and that it was a false one. Reference accusation 14. Electric installation, in the O ffice . An examination of the house occupied by ^radhan Singl while at Muscat shows that wiring is in existence in the verandah, kitchen and one living room and there is no trace of any wiring having been put up elsewhere. Pradhan Singh states that his office was on the ground floor and he actually did use a punka coolie for this room. In the absence of proof to the contrary 1 think his statement should be accepted.■ — ■ —■HHRPPPM MHOTHPP mmm Political Agency 3c H.M* s Gonsilate, Muscat» March 29th» 1939* To The Secretary to The Hon’hie the Political Resident in Ihe Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Subject: Mr. Pradhansingh 1 s resighation from Government service. Memorandum. I forward herewith an application dated 28th March 1939 from Mr. Pradhan Singh, Overseer,P.tf.D now at Muscat tendering his resignation from Govern ment service for disposal. Major,I.A, Political Agent 3c K.M's Consul, Musca tMHnn /N Muscat. 25th March 1939. To The Political Agent &amp; s Consul, Muscat. Respected Sir, I most respectfully beg to state that the feet that several allegations were recently brought against me by my superior officer, all of which have after thorough investigation by your goodself been proved false, has made my position in my present service very difficult and awkward. I do not think that it would ever be possible for me to please the Assistant Engineer who has been prejudiced against me for reasons which I do not consider necessary to mention here. I in therefore consider my remaining the Government service under the existing circumstances would be deterent to my own intere sts. I therefore most submissively beg to tender this my resignation from the Government service with effect from the 15th April 1939 and should be very grateful if you would kindly forward it to the Honourable the political Resident in the Persian Gulf for his acc eptance • I beg to r ena in Sir, Your most obedient servant, i.e. Pradhan Singh Overseer P.W.D. at Muscat.D.O• No. C/55. Political Agency &amp; H.li 1 s Consulate, Muscat, A^&gt;ril 5, 1339. Pardhansingh* s resignation from Government Service. Would you please refer to my demi official letter No. 409 dated the 27th March 1939 with which I forwarded an application from Pardhansingh asking to be allowed to resign from Government service. You will remember that when you passed through 2 Muscat last month I mentioned to you that he was trying to get employment under the Muscat Government and I have now ascertained from him that the real reason for his desiring to resign from Government service is that he has heard privately and unofficially from the Sultan with whom he is well acquainted as a result of the work he carried out for the State in the Muscat Improvement Scheme in 1936-37 that he would be willing to employ him in a private capacity. 3 . I have confirmed this from the Sultan, who stated that Pardhansingh* s work for the Muscat Improvement Scheme impressed him very favourably. I pointed out to the Sultan that I had just finished a long inquiry^ including a formal trial into numerous allegations of dishonesty made by his superiors against rardhansingh and that although he had been acquitted some incidents left a somewhat bad impression. The Suita n however declared that he was quite willing to give him I a trial as he would employ him on ^contract under which he could be dismissed at short notice if anything irregular occurred i H.D. Huston, I.A., Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Guif, Bushire2 occurred* 4* That is now the situation. I really do not think lardhansingh is at bottom any worse or any better than the usual P.W*D. subordinate and that if the Sultan likes to take him on, he can, if he finds out that he is a ‘'bad hat' summarily dismiss him. Under these circumstances it seems to me that there is no need for us to intervene in this matter.You wi 11 remember that uhen I passed through Muscat you mentioned to me the pos sibility of Pradhan Singh obtaining employ ment with the Muscat Government, r\ ki. I have mentioned the matter to the Poli tical Resident who desires me to say that prima- facie^ Pradhan Singh is not a suitable candidate for such employment, but he will not make fcn* a- decision until we hear further from you. Major R. P, ^/a tts, I .A. &gt; Political Agent, Mus ca t. -T X E G. H A-in Telegram From To Uo. Dated Date received ritconsul Bushire. litical Agent, Muscat. 047 - April the 8th, 1939, Fradhansinghs* resignation. It will be considered in the meantime he should not be appointed to any position under the muscat Government,1 ® if * TELEGRAM Dated Date received G.T.C. Britconsul Bushire. Political Agent, Muscat 2°.nd April 1939. ^,3rd Anril 1939. Following for Political Agent, Muscat. Pradhansinghs resignation nay be accepted with irmediate eflect. Letter follows regarding his employment with Muscat Government. ;Mr, Pradhansingh, Muscat. &amp;&gt; f( Political Agency &amp; H.M*s Consulate, Muscat, April 25, 1939. *o Memorandum. Reference your petition dated 25th March 1939 tendering your resignation from Government service. 2. I am directed by Ihe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to inform you that your resignation has been accepted and that it will have effect from the time you receive this letter i.e. 25th April 1939 in the forenoon. ' Major, Political Agent 8c H.M* s Consul, Mus cat. ■ mu iii w) No .185 of 1939• Muscat # dated the 25th April 39 Mr•Pardhansingh, Muscat* Under instruction received from the Assistant Sngineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub Division, Bushire,you are to be relieved atonce^and your charge is to be taken from you. Therefore is requested that all the cash vouchers,measure ment books,Scientific instruments,and tools and plant,belong ing to the Government,together with all the office files,wit^ you may please be delivered to me to-day the 25th instant at 4 P.M in P.W.D Office in the Agency,Museat* Supervi so r. Copy to the Political Agent,Muscat. Copy to the Assistant Engineer, ^shire. IIIIW ■The 26th A^ril 1939. To, The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* s Consul, Muscat Sir I beg to state, that as my resignation has been accepted therefore I sent the Government money in my possession to Supervisor Abdul Wahab but he has refused to tahe it and also he has refused to tahe over the Drawing instruments, therefore I request you Kindly to allow me to deposit all the money and materials with the Treasury Officer. I beg to remain Sir Your most obedient servantCONFIDENTIAL« D.O. No. C/178. July the 17th, 1939. Subject : Pardhan Singh . Please refer to Bushire telegram dated April 22nd No. nil. 2. May I be informed please when the letter referred to in the telegram under reference is likely to be received by me. Captain H.D. Rushton, I.A., Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushirey ^ | I distinctly remember drafting and signing a letter to you on the subject of Pardhan Singh but it appears that it was mislaid somewhere in my office and was never issued as no relevant entry appears in the despatch register. 3. 1 cannot now recall exactly what I said therein but it was to the effect that the Sultan^ attention should be drawn towards the allegations against Pardhan Singh and that he should be warned that if he employed him it would be in a purely private capacity and that we could accept no responsibility. Captain T. Hickinbotham, O.B.IS. , Political Agent, v Muscat.August the 14th, 1939. To Your Highness, I have now heard from the Hon*ble the Political His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Resident in the Persian Gulf in regard to the employment of Pardhan Singh. I am instructed to inform Your Highness that very grave allegations of dishonesty were made against this man when he was employed as a Public Works Department Overseer. On investigation he was acquitted but my predecessor who tried the case has left it on record that a bad impression remained inspite of the acquittal. I am further to inform Your Highness that Should Pardhan Singh be given private employment we cannot in any way accept any responsibility for anything that may occur. Your Highness' s sincere friend Captain,I./ His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.Translation of letter No.302 of 15th August 1929 from H.H. Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman to Captain T. Hickinbotharo, H.B.M f s Consul, Mused: \ A/C I am in receipt of your letter No.C/232 of 14th August 1939, for which I thank you. It is understood that you will not be responsible for any neglect of personal duti s of Pardhan Singh but only that justice will be performed if he were found guilty of any offence and it was submitted to your Consulate in a form of a case. U.ECONFIDENTIAL D.O. No. 2231/V/15 The 18th December 1939. Reference endorsement No. 30/728 dated the 28th November 1939 from the Assistant Engineer, Bushire to the Political Agent, Muscat. 2. I note from the above reference that it is proposed to post Abdul Wahab here again as Overseer on his return from leave. I have already expressed my opinion of this man to Saiyid Ghulam Murtaza and have asked him not to repost Abdul Wahab to Muscat. I entirely agree with the opinion expressed by Weightman in a letter which you will find on your files in which he stated that Abdul Wahab was both 'incompetent and impertinent'. I have borne with the man throughout the last hot weather and if he must be employed in the Gulf I shall be grateful if you will arrange for him to be posted elsewhere. I suggest that he is posted to Bushire where a careful examination of r“\ his work will, I trusty produce sufficient evidence to warrant his services being dispensed *vith. A* Captain A.C. Stewart, Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BushireCOffFIDSNTIAL, lor lofe .x D. 0. No. f &gt; / c / 5 ' January, 1940. ^sArtlAx Will you please refer to your demi-official No. 2231/V/15, dated the 18th December, 1939.? I have gone into the question of Abdul Wahab’s posting and find that owing to the fact, that no steps have yet been taken to replace Pradhansingh, the late Overseer at Muscat, who resigned last year, the Public Works Department is somewhat shorthanded, and has no one available to send to Muscat in place ofjo No. 41-S of 1941. British Residency &amp; Consulate General, Bushire, the 16th January, 1941. To Mr. Abdul Wahab, Supervisor, Public Works Department, Muscat. Memorandum. With reference to his letter No. 3, dated 7th January 1941, Mr. Abdul Wahab is informed that the Hon’ble the Political Resident is not prepared to consider him for the post of Assistant Engineer, Independent Sub Division, Persian Gulf, a post for which he considers him quite unsuitable. Sd./ A.C. Stewart. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.V / D.O. No. C/96. The 30th January 1941 Please refer to your D.O. letter No. P/C/5 dated the 11th January 1940. 2. I shall be ^ratafn-l to know whether during the last year you have succeeded in obtaining a replacement for Pardhan Singh. I again request that Abdul Wahab be transferred from Muscat. Captain A.C. Stewart, Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf BushireCONFIDENTIAL. D.O. No. C/316. Muscat, the 15th April, 1941. Abdul ■ vahab. P.Overseer. Please refer to my demi-official letter No. C/96, dated the 30th January, 1941. 2, I shall be grateful for a reply. Captain A.C. Stev/art, I.A., Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.a replacement for Pradhan Sin^Ji but was unable to do so. Arrangements are however being made to obtain the services of a new Assistant Engineer and as soon as these arrangements have been completed I propose to ask him to select and bring with him a replacement for Pradhan Singh. In the meantime as I have no relief I regret that I shall have to ask you to retain Abdul Wahab for a short time longer. To Major T. Hickinbotham,O.B.E., C/0 Postmaster, Ziarat.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 696-9. h\ The Hon’ble the Political Resid compliments to The ?olltloal Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, rsian Gulf presents his 9 The Political Agent, Mueoat, y His Majesty*8 Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr, Ay/ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. i ^7 up I I V^\ / Jj b r . Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. r 1 Name and Date. r\ Subject. Political Resident's letter Mo.626-3, dated the 2nd June 1942, to the External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi, Abolition of the Persian Gulf •independent sub-division of the Public Works Department, External Affairs Depart ments's telegram H6.626-B, dated the 29th June 1942, to the political Resident,Confidential From To tfo*525-8, British Besidenoy and Consulate-Greneral Bushire, 2nd June 1942, The Hon f hle Lieut,-Colonel Hf.R. Hay, 0,I,B,, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Secretary to the Government of India, Bxternal Affairs Department, New Delhi, V' Sir, I have the honour to refer to your telegram No• 411* dated the 13th May, and to say that the antecedents of the Danish engineer referred to have not yet been verified hy IU Najesty f s Legation, Tehran, hut that I do not in any case consider him as a suitable candidate in all respects as he is a mechanical rather than a constructional engineer, I there- li fore propose that for the duration of the war the Persian Gul Independent suh-division of the Public Torks Department should be closed and its funds for minor works and special repairs-- placed under my direct control as a contract grant, such of the P.W.D. staff as it is necessary to retain beir^ amalgamated’ for the time being into the Residency office staff and brought on to the Persian Gulf cadre. These posts are noted in the attached Proposition Statement. 2. This proposal has been prompted largely by the difficulty experienced in finding a suitable Assistant Bngineer. The present incumbent, Nr. Nurtaaa, wishes to volunteer for mili tary service and asked to be relieved in the autumn of 1940, since when all efforts to find a properly qualified successor have completely failed. It is most undesirable that i3r. Murtaza should be retained in the Gulf any longer against his f will. 3, It is also considered that in war time when for lack of material and other reasons construction and repairs are reduced to a minimum it is uneconomical to retain the present rather ^ top heavy P, V, D. staff. Lack of transport also makes inspect! 1 difficult and greatly reduces the value of an inspecting officer. As shown below my proposals will effect a saving of Ss.24,320 on establishment alone. 4, * The Proposals will throw a certain amount of extra responsibility on Political Agents and other executive officers# but it is considered that in present circumstances petty repair can ^robably be carried out more expeditiously and eoonomioallyll under their direct control than through the intervention of the T • W. D. 5. The only original works of importance in view at present are the re-construct!on of the Khorramshahr Consulate and the building of a hospital at Dubai, If the proposal to re construct the Consulate is proceeded with, which seems at present unlikely, some special local arrangement will have to be made. It is proposed to place an overseer in charge of the work on the Dubai hospital, and I am of opinion that the Political Agent, Bahrain, and the Residency Agent, SharJah, 4 will be able to exercise the necessary amount of supervision, 6. My detailed proposals are as followsi- (!) The abolition of the post of Assistant Engineer, Persian Gulf Independent sub-division. The pay of the present incumbent of the post is Es.690 plus allowances of Ks.170. Saving of 8s. 10,320 per annum.• 2 (ii ) The abolition of the poet of Accountant at present provided by the Accountant Creneral, Central Revenues* (This post will become unnecessary! as the special repairs and other grants will be administered as contract grants by the Resident* The pay of the present incumbent of this post is fe*200 plus allowances of Rs*150. Saving of per annum. It is suggested that in order to simplify accounts procedure, after the abolition of this post, the grants - if any - for original works should be managed as a contract grant under my own supervision* (iii ) The amalgamation of the I office with the Residency office* In detail, this involves s- (a) The transfer of Messrs* Uawazish All (P.w.D, accounts clerk) and Mukhtar Yassin (r.¥.D. clerk) to the Persian Gulf clerical cadre. Their present pay is Rs.150 plus allowances of l. 75, and it is proposed that they should be brought in as Lower til vision clerks at the level of&gt;fc&gt;,160 plus the . . , standard Lower Division allowances of ks,65. Subseauently, they may be promoted in the Persian Gulf cadre in the same way as other clerks, subject to their satisfy!^ the Resident of their capabilities. This would necessitate the provision of two Upper Jb (initially Lower) Division posts on the Persian Gulf Residency cadre, in place of the two present posts on the cadre of the X .W. D* Financial effect, nil, (b) The abolition of the P,W.D, travelling allowance grant of Rs*7,500 per annum, and increase of the Residency travelling allowance grant by fc,5 f 000 per annum (of, paragraph 9 below), producing a saving of Es.2,500 per annum, (o) The abolition of the P,W*D. contingent allowauce of fc.2,700 and of the P,W,D. office and petty estab- - &lt; lishment grant of Rs. 11,500 and the increase of the Residency Office Allowance by Es.6,000 producing a nett saving of Bs*3,200* (iv) The transfer of the present Assistant Engineer’s house from the P.V.D, to the Residency. The provision of a house for the Vioe-Oonsul, Bushire, has been due for some years, since the post was taken over from the Foreign Offioejr^ and the present Assistant Engineer’s house would be adequate. Sfo financial adjustment between the departments concerned need, it is suggested, be made, as the rental value of the house will be covered many times over by the costed value of the services rendered by the officers of the External Affairs Department w* in the administration of P,¥.D,, funds* Also the house can, if neoessaiy, revest to the Assistant Engineer if the appoint ment is revived after the war. No rsnt is at present paid by the Assistant Engineer for the occupation of the house and the financial result of the transaction will be nil, (v) The post of Supervisor, Bushire, should, It is suggested, by made a selection post* and should carry an additional allowance of Rs,75 as in the absence of an Assistant Enrineer its incumbent will have increased responsibilities, and will be primarily responsible for giving technical advice to the Resident and Secretary, Itoe post is at present suitably^ filled. (vi) The current expenses and income of the electric light plants at Bushire and Muscat, and of the water supply organisation at Bushire as well as the income occasionally derived from letting quarters in the Consulate building at Bush ire, the rent of the post office at Muscat, and the tennis COUftt•*V \ - 3 - eg? court at Kuwait, should he accounted for up to the end of the present financial year under Special Repairs, and thereafter in a separate profit and loss account. Replace ments (when necessary; may he governed hy the same considera tions as those governing replacements of launches, motor cars or other machinery maintained hy contract grants. 7. The nett financial effect of the proposals given above i is a saving of Rs.24 f 320 per annum, vide the proposition statement attached. 8. One post of overseer on fc* 1^0-5-150 plus allowances of &amp;.60 per mensem and the post of draftsman on fc.150-5-200 plus allowances of Ks# 85 have been vacant since March 1939 and May 1941 respectively. In order that the new scheme proposed may he a success it is most desirable that these posts should he filled as soon as possible and I would seleei- solicit the assistance of the Government of India in finding suitable candidates. 9. If it is at all possible I should be very grateful if the Government of India could depute from time to time, say once a year if possible, an Executive or Assistant Engineer to inspect the various buildings and report on their condition and generally to offer advice onP.W.D. matters to the Political Resident and his subordinate officers. The object of retaining as large a sum as Bs*5,000 from the P.W.D. travelling allowance grant - vide paragraph 6(iii)(b),is to make provision for the travelling expenses of such an officer. 10 . that If these proposals are approve I may kindly be.informed accord! d in principle I request ngly by telegram so that I can release Mr. Murtaza, vide paragraph 2. I have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient servant, ' : 3d. W.R.Hay. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. * f© g- UJT j-jtUt U 3 ITI Qj.il — Class or Grade and designation of Government servants affected. Number in each Class. Bates of pay per mensem. Actual present cost of establishment affected per annum. fe. Approximate extra cost involved by these proposals per annum. fe. Present Proposed . Present fe. Proposed Ss« Assistant Engineer One mi 860 mi 10,320 (-) 10,320 Accountant One mi 350 mi 4,200 (-) 4,200 p.l.D. clerics Two Two 225 225 5,400 Nil. each. each. . Supervisor, Bushire. One One . 330 405 3,960 (to 900 Draftsman, Bushire. Cue Oie 235 235 2,820 mi. Overseers Two Two 180 180 4,320 mi. each. each. Oontingenol es • - • 14,200 6,000 ' - (-) 8,200 per annum • per annum • . Travelling Allowance • 7,500 5,000 • (-) 2,500 per annum . per annum. * n miTT 3AyIUS k. 24,330, \ ~* H »Whhhrnbhvhhmmmmmbhi ^ Telegram G.T.O. From aoyernment of India, New Delhi* To Politioal He si dent, Bushire* No.526-2* Dated 29th Jane received 1st July 1942* vV^ Tour letter No.525-3 June 2nd. Tour proposal accepted in principle Mr. Murtaza my he released* NPGr.a) o N (0 pjc I f y ^Vyv&gt;v c.^“. iVia^Lux \o&gt;T ^ h, (ut) •« hi- Suhfci&amp;vh. May the letter placed below, which is addressed to Mr. Abdul Wahab be given to him ? A copy of the letter has been taken for onr record. F.E.P/27-1. Yes. Isn’t it time we got rid of him. Lets remind Captain Stewart. T.H./30-1. Draft demi-official letter is placed below for approval please. tv* 3-0, tJL l 0 ^' S.o. 5,o . WAwv Ko, C^i, j HI. /'’/v ,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000330_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/136</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000330</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/136</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/4 1. Pradham Singh 2. Abdul Wahab 3. Mohamad Ishaq'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-13T22:04:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (118 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. There are file notes at folios 118-119.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 120; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-26 and between ff 51-117; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file title contains an inaccurate spelling: Pradham Singh should appear as Pradhan Singh. The file mainly concerns two employees of the Government of India Public Works Department (PWD) at Muscat: (1) Pradhan Singh (also referred to as Pardhan Singh), PWD Overseer at Muscat, who was the subject of various allegations of dishonesty in the course of his official duties at Muscat by Abdul Wahab, PWD Overseer (also referred to as Supervisor) at Muscat, and the PWD Assistant Engineer, Bushire; and (2) Abdul Wahab himself.The papers include: correspondence concerning the applications of Pradhan Singh and Abdul Wahab for appointment as Assistant Engineer, Bushire, 1936-37; summary of the accusations against Pradhan Singh, including correspondence from Abdul Wahab and Pradhan Singh, a report on the accusations by the Political Agent and HBM's Consul, Muscat, and comments by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; correspondence concerning an allegation by Pradhan Singh that Abdul Wahab had appointed an assistant driver who was physically unfit for the job; complaints by the Political Agent, Muscat about the conduct of Abdul Wahab, and requests that he be removed from his post at Muscat; complaints from Pradhan Singh about the construction of the Bungalow at Gwadur [Gwadar] by Mohamed Ishaq; the acquittal of Pradhan Singh of the charges against him by the Political Agent, Muscat; Pradhan Singh's resignation, and employment by Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat and Oman; and correspondence between the Political Agent, Muscat and the Sultan, warning the Sultan about the previous allegations made against Pradhan Singh.The Arabic content of the papers consists of two items of correspondence between the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, and the Political Agent, Muscat, with English translations (folios 103-105).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Public Works Department, Overseer, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Allegations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000330#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>