<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00006d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T21:22:12.383Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H#M.Naval Base, Bahrain. No.503. llth February, 1941. Sir, I have the honour to request that the Assistant Political Agent at Sharjah may be asked to enquire whether the Shiekh of Debai would be prepared to sell or hire a 88 h.p. motor dhow which I understand he owns. If so could the dhow be sent to Khor Kuwai for inspection. 2. I should be grateful if this information could be asked for by next air mail opportunity and that reply may be given briefly by W/T in the form 'Yes or No”(indicating if prepared to sell or hire) and a date indicating when the dhow could be at Khor Kuwai. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, COMMODORE SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF. The Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrain. ' \i\ yThe Political Officer, Trucial Coast, 5 H A R J fi H the undermentioned document ( s ) s S' The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the 16th February 1941, Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No.503 dated ~lth Feb ruary 1941 from the oenior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, to the Political Agent, Bahr^n. . I Subject. Purchase of dhow from Shaikh of Dubai. f iConfidential No. C/160. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated. 2Cth February _1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.C/147 dated the isil- February 1941 from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Purchase of dhov;s from ShaiKh of Dubai.-T • Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. No. n. Dated the Sth March 1941. British Govermient are considering chartering a number of large ocean-going dhows of approximately 100 tons or more for transport of stores. Please enquire and report how many would be avail able from Trucial Coast. Political. .Confiden + 4 &lt;- 1 1 01 c( i URGENT No. C/221-5/11, Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th March 1941. To The Director of Customs # Port Officer, B A H R A I N Memorandum i am informed taat a number of large ocean-going dhows of approximately 100 tons are urgently required for use by the 'British Government. m 2. I should be grateful if you would make enquiries and let me know how many would be available in Rehrain, Political Agent, Bahrain.. y Copy given to P*A.Bahrain Tele gram From 3. jeolitical Agent, Muscat* To Senior .Naval officer, Persian Gulf. Repeated Political Resident at Bahrain. Uo.C/216 Dated and received the 8th Marchx i94i* Important * lour telegram flo. C92lz of March 6th* 2. .No dhows available here at present. Understand about ten dhov/e have recently returned to Khor Fakkan. Political Agent. AConfidential A. v K U^R^G^E^T, l No.C/221-5/11. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th March 1941 To 4 ». The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, BAHRAIN Memorandum I am informed that a number of large ocean-going dhows of approximately 100 tons are urgently required for use by the British Government. 2. I should be grateful if you would make enquiries and let me know how many would be available in Bahrain. i ft ^fi - 1 Political Agent, Bahrain. II. The Customhouse; Bahrain: 9th March, 1941., Reference above: Is the information sought to apply to sailing dhows, and/or motor driven launches ? If the latter, the particulars of the largest registered Bahrain craft haW^already been submitted to the Senior Naval Officer, please. Cf-zj}- a£&amp;lL^i ^ ^ oj/l* Ua. '111 1No: pa/cr//£/Yx To:- H.B.M’s Political Agent. BAHRAIN: MEMORANDUM:~ THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 11th March, 1941 ., 13th Safar, 1360 ., ^ In reference to your recent enquiry I enclose herewith Ba J lra in sailing craft of fifty feet in length or more, which I trust will be of assistance, please. Enclose- DlftECIOB^OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN: 10 ©! I i 1 INo.C/232-5/11. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th March 1941. To The Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf Bahrain Sir /p I have the honour to refer to your telegram No.0921z dated the 6th March 1941, and to forward herewith a list of available sailing craft prepared by the Director of Customs, Bahrain. The Director of Customs was not able to estimate the tonnage and has therefore given the length of each craft in feet. It is hoped that this will be of some assistance in estimating the approximate tonnage. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrain'ccret Office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.Naval Office, Bahrain. 9th March, 1941. Sir, I havn the honour to forward herewith a cop^ r of a message which I have received free the Senior British Naval Officer, Suez Canal Area. 2. I have consulted the Political Adviser to His Highness the Sheikh of Bahrain in this matter who has premised to give me details of divers who would be willing to undertake this work. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) Cosmo Gr^hsm COMMODORE SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy to i- The Political Agent,^ Bahrain. (S'? C 0 ^..ol.m^3gage., FROM Suez Canal, Request you will enquire whether there are any native divers available in your area to work naked in Suez Canal for location of mines. Egyptian naked divers are already doing this work in safety. Pay £1 per day whilst diving plusVt, ‘V 1 |'&gt; D/0 THE CUST014H0USE. BAHRAIN. 18th March, 1941., 2oth Safar, 1360 ., ftlcycrf' \ u V, ^ . In reference to the S.N.O^ recent enquiry as to the availability of local sea-going craft for service in the Gulf of Suez, I have submitted to you a list of such craft, all of which are registered Bahrain vessels. \\ Apart from those used by The Persian Gulf Lighterage Company for local steamers’ cargo work, there are a number of larger pearling dhows out of condition, laid up ashore, for want of funds to work at the pearling banks. If such were acquired, it would take nearly three months to get them into sea-worthy condition. The sea-going craft at present at work are those owned by Hajy Yusuf bin Ahmed Fakroo; and these are plying between Bahrain and Karachi for transport of bag cargo on account of the reduction in number of the^B.I. steamers calling here. In regard to the suggestion that such craft should be hired, there are certain difficulties, such as: ( 1 ) the amount t&gt;he hire, ( 2 ) the period of the hire, ( 3 ) the uncertainty of the craft returning to Bahrain at the conclusion of the hiring, and (4) the disinclination of the nukhudhas and their crews to go so far sway from their families as Suez. Difficult questions of compensation for wear and tear and damage might also arise later on. In view of this, I would venture to suggest that the simplest procedure would be for the Admiralty to purchase outright all the large craft now lying ashore, put them into condition locally, engage local crews, and sail them in ballast direct to Suez. This would be most helpful to the local boat-building industry, and also to tajirs impoverished by recent bad pearling seasons. The price of each craft could be fixed by arbitration: one assessor for the owner, one assessor for the Admiralty, with perhaps myself as the arbitrator. So that there should be/S?fficulty in acquiring these ^ craft, I might venture to suggest that His Highness the Ruler should, by proclamation, take power to acquire any such craft at a just valuation, and this would save the wastage of time that always occurs when an effort is made locally to carry through any purchase by negotiation. Believe me, To: - Major R.G.E.W.Alban O.B.E., I.A. The Agency, BAHRAIN: fj.Confidentia l ^ Office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.H.Naval Base, Bahrain, 25th March, 1941. I am forwarding herewith a copy of a letter which I have sent to Belgrave concerning the purchase of sailing dhows for use in the Suez Canal. Thank you also for your assistance. V j Major A,G.Alban The Political Agent, Bahrain.kgiridentlal SsOim* I have not? received infomatlcn that in view of the snail number of dhows available and the uncertainty of craft being able to reach ^uez it is proposed not to take up any sailing dhows for the present* Would you therefore take no further action in this ttatter. Thank you very much for all your assistance* /*&gt; Office of Senior h aval Officer, Persian Gulf, H*M*Nfivo.l Base, Bahrain. 25th March, 1941.Confidban'kial* l o *0/322-8/8(0). Ei'iuib*. _ency O-i-lc 1‘j - - * } 1C tL x ril 19^-1. \- To Tie Political iHent Reference your telegram 10.53 of Bcu.»i‘&lt; In • ■ tl. . rch, IClt 1 • Tliei'e are no l&amp;.r^e ocean goin^ d] ows of ICC tons or more available on the Trucial Coast. One dhow of 84 tons belonging to the people of Klior Fakkan is reported to be plying bet\.een 'Iraq and India. The rest are below 80 tons and all are sported to be working at present between India, Ku\/ait and ’Iraq. ^ Residency Agent,Sir r j ahTelegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain To -Residency Agent, Sharjah No. 197 Dated the 9th Junel941. Senior Naval Officer wishes either to purchase or hire 88-H.P. launch belonging to Shaikh of Dibai. Please telegraph purchase price or rent. - Political -Telegram From GTC. (2P) To Britagent, Sharjah Political, Bahrain No.437 Bated 11th June, 1941 Your telegram 197 of June 9th. Shaikh of Dubai willingly selling his 88 Horse Power launch for a fixed price of 30,000/- rupees repeat 30,000/- rupees doecs not want to hire for the present. Shaikh Said intends to leave for Muscat within a weeks time. \The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : His Britannic Majesty T s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. Advisers Office, No:- /SO Manamah, Bahrain. Dated July 3, 1941. \ Description of enclosure. Name and date • Subject. 1. Copy of Secret letter No.Def/Air/s/10 dated 1/7/41 from the Defence Officer, Bahrain, to the Adviser, B.G. Bhn. Launches and Dhows at Bahrain. 2. Copy of Secret letter No. /SF of 3/7/41 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Gov’t., Bahrain, to the Defence Officer, Bahrain. - ditto - Reference to previous corresoondence :—Copv of Secret letter No .Def/Air/S/10 dated 1st July, 1941, from the Defence Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Could you please let me have the information asked for below as soon as possible (a) Approximate Number of Motor Launches normally available at Bahrain. (b) Approximate Number of Motor Dhows. In addition to the above, the approximate number of either type of craft capable of carrying more than 25 passengers would be appreciated. This information is required to assist in a Special Reconnaissance of the Persian Gulf that is being carried out.No. I$.31- sr of 1360 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain* Dated, 9th J/Thani, 1360 July 3, 1941. The Defence Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum:- Reference your letter No. Def/Air/S/10 dated 1st July, 1941. The approximate number of launches available in Bahrain is 72. There are about 20 dhows fitted with motor engines, but about half this number is now away from Bahrain on diving etc. The approximate number of other craft avail able capable of carrying 25 passengers or more is about 279 of which nearly 220 boats are now away diving. Adviser to the GovernmentTelegram Q. From Political Resident, Bushire To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 717 Dated and received the 14th July 1941. I am under*the impression that Shaikh of Bahrain gave his launch to Senior Naval Cfficer in response to recent appeal. Please confirm. f v Cs~v /tx $&gt;Np f4&lt; 6 , ytsyf y-{ oh yjj( c^A « / 'Telegram From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident', Bushire. No. 234 Dated the 15th July 1941. Your telegram No, 717 dated July 14th. Belgrave assures me Shaikh has not given or sold his launch to Senior Naval Officer. He is using it out at his island at present. - PoliticalSECRET* H.M* Naval Base Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Mo. BA/37 18th October, 1941. Sir It is proposed to introduce a Mine-watching Organisation for Sitra Anchorage, Bahrain. 2.- This scheme will entail the stationing in the vicinity of the Naval Base of One Company of Indian State Troops, about 108 men. They will be transported by launch from the naval pier to dhows moored in the Sitra Anchorage, each night. 3*- In the event of a minelaying raid, the Manama anchorage will be closed. 4.- Your formal sanction to this Scheme is requested in order that steps may be taken to bring it into force as soon as possible. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant L LIEUTENANT COMMANDER, NAVAL OFFICER-IN-CHARGE.SECRET No.C/999* Political Agency, Bahrain, 20th October 1941. From Major R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain To The Naval Officer in Charge, His Majesty^ Naval Base, Bahrain. Sir I have the honour to refer to your letter No. BA/37 dated tfce 18th October 1941 regarding the pro posal to introduce a Mine-watching Organisation for Sitra Anchorage, Bahrain. 2. Subject to final confirmation by the Hon’ble the Political Resident, formal sanction to the scheme is hereby conveyed and the work may be proceeded with at once. I have the honour to be, Sir Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy, with compliments, to: 1. The Defence Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 2. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.\ Confidential No.'; -Gjfoo- 28/26. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bushire. the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for favour of confirmation. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 20th. October 1941^ Keference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date Subject 1. Letter No.BA/37 dated 18th b ^ i October 1941 from the Naval Officer in Charge, Bahrain. Introduction of Mine-watching 2. Letter No.C/999 dated 20th October 1941 from the Poll- Organisation for Sitra Anchor- tical Agent, Bahrain. a ge&gt; Bahrain.SECRET No. C/1002-28/26. The Political Agent, tfahrain, Presents his compliments to :— 1. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government 9 Bahrain. 2. The Defence Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for information. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 20th October 1941*. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject 1 . 2. Letter No. BA/37 dated 18tlj October 1941 from the Naval Officer in Charge, Bahrain- Letter No.C/999 dated 20th October 1941 from the Poli tical Agent, Bahrain. Introduction of Mine-watching Organisation at Sitra Anchor age, Bahrain. z4 *GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Confidenti&amp;l• Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. 11 is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Qf ^ p olltic&amp;1 ^eUdent No. C/4 6 i Dated the in tl e Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain • fg 26th October, 4i To - The Political Bahrain, y Repeated - The Secretary to the Government of India, } '.ath copy of External Affaire Gepartmer. t, ) Printed letter Pbw Delhio ) referred to ) and encloeuree Reference your Subject: Mine-watching organization for Sitra Anchorage 0 Your Printed letter To.C/lCCC, dated the 2Cth October 194p. Sanction confirmed* sd. C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested . U- f for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Signature) ( Designation) S. 44. MFP—1048 S&amp;P—(M-2042)—17-12-37—20,000.Confidential No.C/1021-28/26. Political Agency, Bahrain, 30th October 1941. To The Naval Officer in Charge, Naval Base, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference my letter No.C/999 dated the 20th October 1941. 2. The formal sanction granted by me, regarding the introduction of a mine watching organisation, has been confirmed by the Hon»ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. C. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram Inter From H.M, Ambassador, Cairo Addressed Bahrain, telegram Mo. 12 Repeated Delhi, telegram Mo. 2^8. Dated 12th December 1941. Following for Hay from Prior, Mo. 24 repeated Caroe. (Vvd. omit te d: Can you ?) snare any bulk oil barges ? If so what is price, capacity and draught ? Would they be self-propelled and/or could they be towed to Suez ? H.M. Ambassador oOo Repeated to P.R., Bushire, under Mo. 478 dated 13th December 1941.Confidential No. C/1161 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 13th December 1941. I have received an enquiry from TTis Majesty’s Ambassador, Cairo, asking whether any bulk oil barges are available for sale and if so details of price, capacity and draught*. Information is also requested whether they would be self-propelled and whether Uiey could proceed to Suez under their own power; or, if not, whether they could be towed there. 2 . I do not know whether you have any such oil barges available, but I would be most grateful if you could kindly let me have a reply as early as possible. Mr. M.H. Lipp, Bapco, Bahrain. Mr. F.W. Chliger, Casoc, DhahranThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. &amp; 14th December, 1941. CONFIDENTIAL PA-844 Major R.G.E.W. Alban, H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. V Dear Major Alban, Thank you for your letter C/1161 of 13th December 1941 on the subject of Oil Barges. The Bahrein Petroleum Company has no oil barges that can be spared for service elsewhere. Yours very truly, /&gt;/ Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company, Ltd jM A* 4i.fl /&gt;v i eDhahran, Saudi Arabia December 15, 1941 Major R. G. Alban, O.B.ID. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Manama Bahrein Dear Major Alban: In response to your letter C/1161, ✓ 1 am sorry that we have no oil barges for sale. The fact is that we ourselves are in the market for such a barge. Yours very truly, F'70 : j .-CD F. *V. OHLIGFR ^cXi~ ^C&lt;^CL. C? y/l ^ A.Telegram Inter From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Resident, Bushire No. 4 ?$. Dated the 17tn December 1941. Cairo telegram No. 12 dated 12th December. No barges available either with Bapco or CASOC. PoliticalCONFIDENTIAL. No. 20b-a of 1941 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the docement (sr^. honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned Britii^i-^onsulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated 22nd December 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : Correspondence ending with Bahrain telegram .no . 438, dated the I7th December 1941 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident’s telegram No. 463, dated the 22nd December uIL BARGES. 1941, to CairoTelegram 1* C*l» Prom Political Resident, bush ire. To H.M*a Ambaoaador, Cairo. Repeated uoverninent of India, new Delhi. -No. 465 Dated 22nd December 1941, Vor Prior from day repeated Caroe. four telegram 24 12th December. Wo barges available either with -Bahrain Petroleum Company or California Arabian Standard oil Company. R.oi.T. 22 / 12 . bRI?CONSUL -</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00006d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/716</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00006d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/716</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/26 Admiralty war requirements’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-26T21:06:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (39 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 39-40) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 41; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-38; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises copies of correspondence related to enquiries from British naval authorities in the Persian Gulf and Suez Canal, asking after the availability of various marine resources (motorised and sailing dhows, divers, barges) for procurement by the naval authorities for military means. The principal correspondents in the file are: the Political Agent at Bahrain (Major Reginald George Evelin William Alban); the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf (SNOPG: Commodore Cosmo Moray Graham); the Customs and Port Director at Bahrain (Claud Cranbrook Lewis DeGrenier).The file includes:an enquiry made in February 1941 by the SNOPG as to whether the Ruler of Dubai would be prepared to sell or lease his motor launch; with a reply in June 1941 that the launch can be brought for 30,000 rupees, but is not for hire (ff 2-4, f 19-20);an enquiry made in March 1941 by the SNOPG to the Political Agents in the Persian Gulf, as to the availability of large ocean-going dhows (over one-hundred tons), urgently required for use in the Suez Canal. Correspondence includes the Political Agent in Bahrain’s enquiry to the Port Director at Bahrain, and his replies, which included a list of sailing dhows at Bahrain (not included in the file) and his recommendation that laid-up dhows at Bahrain be purchased and refurbished by the Admiralty (ff 6-8, ff 10-12, ff 15-18);a request, forwarded by the SNOPG from the Senior British Naval Officer (SBNO) Suez Canal, dated 9 March 1941, for native divers to work in the Suez Canal, searching for mines (ff 13-14);proposals made by the Political Agent at Bahrain, and sanctioned by the Political Resident, of a mine-watching organisation at the Sitrah anchorage in Bahrain, entailing the stationing of a company of Indian State troops (ff 26-30);an enquiry made in December 1941, forwarded from Britain’s Ambassador at Cairo, for bulk oil barges available for sale, with details of price, capacity and draught, for use in the Suez Canal. Replies from representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) and the California-Arabian Standard Oil Company (CASOC) state that no such barges can be spared (ff 33-35).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Suez Canal</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Sailing vessels</topic></subject><subject><topic>Naval mines</topic></subject><subject><topic>Barges</topic></subject><subject><topic>Motorboats</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00006d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>