<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00029d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:00:07.757Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. b FT) ' / 0 of 1363 Office of the Adviser to the Government^ Bahrain Dated, 14th R/Awal, 1363 March 9, 1944. /, /?■ /j. t c /j ?• H. B. M’s political Agent, Balir ain. Memorandum: - The Bahrain Government has in the past paid Hi.200/- per month to the Agency on account of drugs used in the Victoria Memorial Hospital. This arrangement was made at a time when the Bahrain Government had no hospital or medical faci- t' lities and the V.M. Hospital was used very greatly, chiefly by the Police and prisoners. Daily sick parades were held at the hospital and the ward was used for in-patient police and prisoners. This work is now being undertaken by the Govern ment Medical authorities and all Government employees are. treated at the Government Hospital. In view of the high cost to the State of drugs etc., which are purchased and used in the Government Hospitals and clinics, for the most part for free treatment , I venture to suggest that the payment of ru.200/- per month, which is almost the cost of a Sub-Assistant Surgeon, should be discontinued. Adviser to the Government. 3 . 2 .No.7n -2/11. Political Agency, Bahrain. The /fOTarch 1944. To The Adviser to the Govemment of Bahrain. MKHIOHAN BUM . Reference your memorandum No.500-10 dated the 9th March 1944. 2. I have seen by reference to my files that this question was raised by you one the 16th of April 1939 in your Demi Official Letter No.451-10 I also have on record that my predecessor Mr. ;7eightman discussed the question with you on the 22nd of April 1939 and brought to your notice the attendance figures for the 3 months prior to that date. These attendance figures were 3726 fresh cases and 470 vaccinations. The attendance figures for the last two months i.e. from the 16th of January todate are 2738 new cases and 1528 vaccinations for 90% of which vaccine purchased with Govemment of India funds was used. From these figures it will be noted that there has been no falling off in the attendance either for medical treatment or for vaccination since this question was originally raised by you in 1939, in fact quite the reverse for the vaccinations at the moment average 764 a month as opposed to 235 in 1939 and the attendance 1369 a month as opposed to 1243 a month in 1939. 3 . It is true that the cost of drugs lias risen but the rise is not confined to the Bahrain Government State hospitals and we are ourselves finding approximately 2000 rupees a year at the moment t'or the purchase oi drugs for the treatment of patients, the vast majority of whom arc the subjects of His Highness the Shaikh and it would therefore seem more proper that the Bahrain Government should suggest an increment in their contribution for the purchase of drugs rather tlvan the cessation of their/ ' ^ ^ /sr. j 3 APE2AL. As the attendance of patients to the Victoria Memorial Hospital has considerably increased nowadays and the medicines are expensive and insufficient to deal with the sick, subscriptions from those willing to help to make up this need will be very much appreciated. u dated 21st March 1944. Medical Officer of the M.M. Hospital. A/ A to Ei A too o rvT H*:' s.(VO ^ ^ Bahrain^ f Dated the 1st ivlay, 1945. © v- I think we ought to take advantage of the amount of money now in circulation in the Gulf to consolidate the Hospital Funds in the various Agencies. A very substantial sura lias been collected on the Trucial assured and I wonder if you could raise any similar sum in your area for the Agency Hospital. The requirements at the various posts differ, but in all there is a shortage of equipment, and the work can be greatly expanded. ) J. Felly, Esq., O.B.E., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain . &lt;0 rD.O.No*2995-3/21* Political Agency, Bahrain, The 22nd July, 1945. My dear Colonel Please refer to Sir Geoffrey Prior 1 s € demi-official letter No.197 S dated 5th May, 1945, to me. As a result of an appeal by me to the leading merchants here Hs. 14,076/- has been collected. I shall consult Steele, the Medical Officer here, as to how this money can be best spent and shall let you have my proposals in due course. Steele, unfortunately, has just gone on leave. » ; Yours sincerely, The Hon’ble Lieut. Colonel A. C. Galloway, O.B.E*, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e.D.O, No. T?a!iram Receipt No \AL ft (.. Date fe. ■ - ' | ® ^ 1 Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz. Dated 11th August 1945. Thank you for your efforts in raising the sum mentioned in your demi-official letter , ■' • .''v • No. 2995-2/21 dated 22nd July, 1945. The hospital should certainly now be able to bring its equipment up-to-date in certain aspects. cx ^ J / 2 C.J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain . YG. A./. 4. rrftC.o- BAHRAIN ESCE 'K%Jk?r.k D.O.Wo.C/374 . Office of the Political Resident,Persian Gnlf, Camp, Bahrain, the 30th October 1945. official letter No.C/165, dated the 11th August 1945. has returned from leave will you please submit recommendations for the spending of the money? Reference my demi- Now that Dr. Steele C.J.Pelly Esquire, O.B.E.,I.C.S., Political Agent, B A H R AIN, RHL.* I fro. C/15 » uffice of the Political Hesident, Persian (iulf , L,T* ,, ^iearchus ,, , at sea, the 3rd March 19 46 • To The Political Agent, .bAHRAlfl# MJiMUHAUDUM* Please report the amount so far spent from the funds collected from the public for the Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain, and forward proposals for future expenditure. The Hon’ble the Political Resident would prefer that the funds be spent on separate projects of * permanent value rather than frittered away on numerous items which however necessary should be paid for from recurring grants• for becret&amp;ry to the Political Resident, Persian Ciulf. RHL. VNo. 2402-2/21 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 28th July, 1946. To The Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.C/15 dated the 3rd March, 1946. from the public for the Victoria Memorial Hospital are:- ( a ) Repairs to Hospital building^ Cementing of floors, provision of doors and partitions to the build ing • Es* 2500/- • (b) Surgical and medical equipment . (Ordered already and expected shortly) (d) Furniture and stores for clinical laboratory. 85/-. (e) Dynamo for hydraulic pump (order placed). 160/-. Bills in respect of items (b) and (e) are still awaited. The closing credit balance in the Fund on the 1st July, 1946, was Ks» 13,825/—. 3. Statements A and B showing the position respectively of the Medical Grant and the Victoria Memorial Hospital Fund are attached. The Office Allowance (Medical Grant) of Es.3400/- per annum, which is expended on the purchase of medical stores from the Government Medical Stores Depot and on the payment of the salaries of a compounder, a dresser and a sweeper has a debit balance of about Es.500/- per annum as shown in the statement. There is, therefore, no balance available in the Grant for meeting either recurring or occasional petty expenditure. 4. The average expenditure from the Victoria Memorial Hospital Fund on the local purchase of medicines which is estimated at Es.100/- per mensem (vide item 1 of statement B) is dependent on the supplies received from the Medical Stores Depot. As many of the medical stores required are listed as f not available* by the Stores Depot, local purchases have to be made at high prices. As detailed in statement B the annual expenditure from the Victoria Memorial Hospital Fund is about Rs.4200/- and the only income of the Fund is the sum of Ps. 2400/- received annually from the Government of Bahrain. Thus a recurring amount of approxi mately Es.1800/- per annum has to be paid from the capital 2. The amounts so far spent from the funds collected Down Brothers, London. Dakin Brothers, London Es. 1065/- approxi- 600/- (c) Purchase of linen . 155/ -.- 2 - in the Hospital Fund towards the maintenance of the Hospital* 5* The Medical Officer has suggested that the following improvements should be made in the Hospital buildings*- 6* If the improvements mentioned in the previous para graph are sanctioned a balance of Ks£245/- only will remain available to meet the recurring charge of Hs*1800/- per annum referred to in the last sentence of paragraph 4 above* There is at present no other source from which to meet this item, and it is therefore necessary to retain a fttmtW reserve for this purpose* —* Iiqprpy emenl^a. (a) Main Ward - Lavatory. Estimated cost Provision of a flush system* Ss* 600/ - (b) Laboratory - Clinical side room* Provision of an electric light plug, switch and a cement sink and tap. 150/- (e) Inspection room * Provision of (i) Two fly proof wire gauze doors* 735/- (ii) One additional light point, bracket and plug. 40/- (iii) Wooden panelling for walls up to upper level of doors* 600/-. (d) Hydraulic pump enclosure * Provision of a cement floor and of a platform for the pump and tank. 80/ -* (e) Provision of wire gauze for all exterior doors and windows. 550/-. Es* 2756/ - * Total Political Agent, Bahrain. C.STATEMENT OF YEARLY RECEIPTS AND EXPENDITURE = 4 * Office Allowance (Medical Grant)» JjL Victoria Memorial Hospital Fund* Receipts* Expenditure* Receipts * Expenditure* Budget grant = Ss*3400. Medicines from the Medical Stores Depot* Ss*1800** Pay of compounder @ Es* 80/- per mensem* 960* Pay of dresser &lt;§ Es. 55/- p.m* 660. Pay of sweeper @ Es*40/- p.m* 480* Total •*• Ss.3900. * This amount is only approximate and is sometimes less depending on the supplies made by the Medical Stores Depot. Estimated annual income 1 from the Government of Bahrain - Es.2400. 2 3 4 5 G Local purchase of medicines § Es. 100/- p.m. approximately. Es. 1200. Repairs - miscell aneous @ Es.40/- p.m. 480* Petty expenses - kerosene oil* bandage cloth, brooms* soap etc. @ Es*50/- p.m. 600. Rent of telephone and repairs &lt;§ Es.16/- P*m. 180. Electric charges @ Es. 50/- p.m. approximately. 600* Allowances to staffs Pay of additional sweeper, compounders assistant and dearness allowance @ Es.95/- p.m. 1140. Excess of expenditure over Budget grant Es. 500. Total @ Es.350/- p.m. Es.4200. Excess of expenditure over receipts Es.1800. —-oOo A g ^ ^ts* Opening balance Es. 13825/-. VICTORIA MEMORIAL HOSPITAL FUND * , Position on the 1st July. 1946 * Liabilities. 1. Cost of microscope etc. ordered from Messrs. Down Brothers (U.K.) £ 80 approximately Es.1065. 2. Cost of medical equipment ordered from Messrs. Dakin Brothers (U.K.) £ 45 approx. 600. - $ 3. Cost of dynamo /or hydraulic pump £ 12 ” 160. Es.1325*Colonel Moody spoke to me some days ago and asked me whether there was any objection'‘to the V.M.H.'s activities being restricted’to treatment of British Government staff and such 'contract' treatment as that given by the Agency Surgeon to B.O.A.C., the Banks, etc., i.e. none outside those categories would be treated by the Agency Surgeon, or, in point of fact, by his successor — the new arrangements would come into force on the appointment of Dr. Steele’s successor. The idea is that quarantine is really a full time job, and when it is wholly taken on by a new man he would not have time for private practice.- ~ I spoke to the Adviser on this subject today, and he stated he did not think the V.M.H.* was necessary for the treatment of private people as their needs are served by the Mission Hospital at this end of the town and by the Government Hospital at the other. I am inclined to agree with this. If it is decided to terminate this side of the V.M.H.’s activities, there is one point on which I would like further information. Do any funds exist subscribed by the public for treatment given to them by V.M.H. 9 Colonel Moody thought that they did. If this is the case, one can hardly stop giving treatment without doing some thing about the funds. I would like the reply to this on my return from tour — not before. A.iiy il, ltd./- C.J.P., 17 / 2 /’ 48 . /W f'—/ Aa— Os-* • &amp; (7L*, •• A e ^ ■' ft &amp; £~ k U- (yCdLe^OU**' n ~J K ^ „ . t O. CjzJ^x^ .• Cc*l* ~PA\Don at ions r eceived in Aprils 1944 for V.i.h Hospital . ' # 1. From Arab subscribers As.3160 - 0 - 0 2. From Persians / ns•4070 - 0 - 0 3. Received on 5-4-44 from Khalil Anjan and credited to Hospital - « Fund • Rs. 300 - 0 - 0 4. Received from Jewish community on 27-4-44 Rs, 575 - 0 - 0 Total • Rsi 8105 -0-0 2 - A. P . A« ltd* o / 5 M-.O. ■ Very creditabie indeed* It is particularly interesting 1 to note that the Persians are by far the chief supporters of the hospital* ltd.T.H. u , 3/5 ltd. Dr.&lt; Steele © D.O.No.1975 of 5-5-45 from the HoiySir. Geoffrey Prior # 3. I should like M.O^s opinion on this* ltd. C.J.P. 15/5 4. Q.M.O. to give his ideas. P. A. ltd. R.E.R.B. 16/5. In March 1944, the P.A. approved of the proposal to approach the merchants of the different communities in Bahrain for voluntary donations to the V.M. Hospital. The subscriptions were to be purely voluntary and on a limited scale. The leading merchants of all communities welcomed the idea and were very willing to donate. Haji Yusuf Kanoo, the Basams, Khosabies, Kunjies and Dhamanmal Issardas for the Indians all told me, they were willing to subscribe at any time funds were needed.’ The following amounts were subscribed. 1. Arabs. 2* Persians. 3. Indians. 4. Jews Rs* 3460/- 4070/- 2441/- 775/- Total Rsl0746/- • 6 . The sum represents the amount from a limited number of merchants, but very much more could be got I am sure if all merchants were included. I attach a list for approval. Many of the merchants named have done very well during the last 4 I years. 'I suggest the subscriptions be obtained on the same lines | as was done last March* Sd. M.L.A. Steele 19/5./i P.A, 7 . )r [*0« tells me the following are sorge of the items/ repairs required, 1. Microscope &amp; equipment, 2 * Linen e.g* blankets ? sheets, towels, 3, Crockery. • I . 4, Flush &amp; wash stand. 5, Repairs. •y - ^ ^ _ I Subscriptions were collected in March 1944 and I 8. am sure more will be forthcoming. If you agree I will draft a letter to the merehants9. listed by M.O. ltd. R.E.R.B. 25/5. Thanks. Please draft. 2. What is the Govt, grant for the V.M. Hospital? 10 . 11 . ltd. C.J.P. 25/5. I am donating this noting sheet as a preliminary subscription. * 2. The draft seems all right but (v 'A” of Q.M.O^ note) I would like to know how subscriptions were collected 'last March'. The file below does not show: indeed I am not sure to what matters it relates or why it is put up. 3. What is the Govt, grant to the V.M. Hospital? ltd. C.J.P. 27/5. Q.M.O. . How were subscriptions collected last March? ltd. R.S.R.B. 28/5. Lists were made out as above.. The letter above was translated by Ahmed in Arabic for Arab community and Mr. Siddiq in Persian for the Persians. The SiHdiax Indians &amp; Jews were in English. These lists were cir culated^ among the merchants, who entered their donations On completion the moneys were sent to me. The Persians Indians &amp; Jews sent a cheque each representing the amount subscribed by their community with a list of subscribers. The Arabs sent money or cheques indivi dually. All amounts were paid into the treasury. • Sd. M.L.A. Steele. 30/5. 1. Subscriptions were collected by sending a list round to merchants. M.O. agrees with me that a letter to each merchant would be better becaiise they ape very . touchy about their order of precedence etc. 11J&amp;J . 12 . 13. 14. 2. Government grant to hospital is Ite.3400/- per year under O.A. and out of .this we pay 1 dresser 1 compounder 1 swe^&gt;er Medical stores. 14 15. 16 .</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00029d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1078</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00029d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1078</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/21 Subscriptions to Agency Hospital Fund and proposals for expenditure'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-10T09:51:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (36 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes in the file, on folios 26-30. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 38; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-22; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and memoranda regarding expenditure on medicines and maintenance for the Victoria Memorial Hospital, and lists of individuals and companies funding the Hospital. The 1946 budget for the Hospital is also included.The principal correspondents are the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the Political Agent at Bahrain.There are some documents with Arabic translation within the file, templates for letters to raise funds for the Hospital.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Hospitals</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00029d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>