<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-19T14:26:47.526Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">nx till EXPRESS LETTER. From To PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN . _ 1 EXT X o, n 4 REPGU, BAHRAIN.^. | 'it I RETAXANDUM, LONDON. 7 &gt;uXHD j fJ J J No.1962-13/3. BAHRAIN 16th September, 1947. Reference Residency Express Letter No. 1612-13/3 dated 5th August 1947 . Italian subject Gionfrlddo stated to be a civilian internee on Bahrain Island. 2. ARAMCO, have stated that Gionfriddo was in their employ from the 24th July 1945, to 27th October, 1946, and that he was repatriated to Eritrea on the 27th October, 1946. 3. The Asmara office of the Company^ representative in Asmara has also stated that R Gionfriado left Eritrea for Italy in December, 1946, by SS 'Dorotea Paxes'. = REPGU « The issue of the above has been authorised. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.'■ — • i iJiaaa uud HAiaH^t &amp; ‘ # - . ill AHH-xQ t UO^.HH .mama t mj'mAXA'\.m .?^9I .•i»cl 1 ias l tqec d^dl WlAHHAd •isJ-J-aj 22©iqx3 xone^xasH sonsi^lsi: ,Vx'9I osx/^ija rf*a bacfjsf) S\-:i-2IdI .oli • bnsXal nl a ixlBQ ao saniaJTLt obblrincio -batfocrs •irad tpOMAHA .§ a. f c ‘91 ^IxfL xi^S 9rfj flioil ^olcirra 'xianJ- n± 3.377 bsjBi i^BqsTr 3 b./ eri bnB jiddc^oO ridVS .5M?I eiadodoO ridV2 arid no aeidiia od s^OBOiBOD arid lo soiilo s^uaA arid .2 »Brio bads.j 2 Ools 2 Bri nd a'/idBdnaaa'iqa'i t i3j-H90 0vj ad vl^dl 'lol Baxdidri dial obi iilnoiC . t: 30 xaq sadoicCI' o3 d . B±&gt;9I = VZ Wi » c e l • riaaiioridi/B naad SBri avoriB arid *io ax/asd ariT dxiabdaeH laoiddlo-i axid od yT&amp;fa'iosc *iol .IJjji) n.u. 2 :aq arid ridPHHT (V Ro. Z 7^86/6/22. 29 th August, 1947* I am sorry to hove been so long in letting you hove a reply to your letter of 19th February about signor Santo Gionfrlddo, said to be a civilian internee on Bahrein island* I have now been informed that there is no such person living in Bahrein island* It has been suggested that he may be employed by the Arabiau American Oil company at ohahran, Saudi rabia, but the Bahrein agent of this company has been ua&amp;ble to say whether this is so or not* (D* r ember ton Pigott) Signor paolo Office of Vita^Finsl, the Italian Government ' Representative, Three King f s Yard, &lt; U V* AT Vf , 14 # Three King’s Yard Davies Street. 4 . m &lt;1—1 (S' ' mfoiiTfld t- ( 3 ) In any further corhmunicatioi on this subject, please quote No.J* . and address, no# to any person by name, but to— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. pv I THE ^nder-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and is directed by the Secretary of State to enquire whether an answer may shortly be expected to the Foreign Office letter No.Z./^y^A^of the X* O' respecting / Foreign Office, /? ’ ', 194^ !VED REC ^ ZlUo. kw, . . COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE 17 31323—2 /c From To PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY* Bahrain. EXPRESS LETTER iiEPGU, BAHRAIN. RETAXA!©Ui , LONDON. No. 1612 - 13 /S.' Datea the 5th August, 1047. Reference your Express Letters No.Ext.672/47 JiP ril Srd and No.Ext.1507/47 July 17th. Case of Italian subject Santo Gionfriddo stated to be a civil internee on Bahrain Island. 2 - Local enquiries reveal that no such nerson is living in ^ ahrain * It is possible he may be employed by Arabian iimerican Oil Company at Dhahran, Saudi Arabia, but the Bahrain Agent of this company appears unable to confirm or deny this. He has been addressed repeatedly in the matter. - REPGU - The issue of the above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf SWA.Vl! f 4 * In anyljurtli^P t u^at-in n on this subject, please quote No. 2t 9ro/t&gt;/2.-L . and address, not to any person bv name, but to The L nder-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THL Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and is direcrea by the Secretary of State to enquire whether an answer may shortly be expected to the Foreign Office letter of the respecting ^ J Foreign Office, y . ,/ ti] 17 3132^—2BDonaaifX DEPART MSI'JT EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). The Soartitary of State for The Politioal esident, Persian Gulf# 6tli June* 1%7» EXT. 1236 A 7 * leferenoe my Express letter ?*&gt;• EL;T#67?/47 of the 3 rd April# Case of lanto Gionfrlddo stated to be Oirillan Internee of Bahrein Island# Grateful for an early repV* The issue of the above has been duly authorised#FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.1 4th June, 1947 (Z 1960/6/22) ^kexel Could you please refer to your letter of the 3rd April to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, about the case of an Italian called Santo Glonfriddo, said to he Interned on Bahrein Island, and let me loiow if you have as yet any information as to Signor Gionfrlddo’s whereabouts. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office.wmtmmm H- f j, c pa . t*- h&gt; }hM^ UP*~ t Colonial Office, Downing Street, '* 1 . 'nHXEtU 947. % As I mentioned on the te we have received a le.tter fro ephone the a - Xe. Foreign Office abotit the repatriation of an Italian frort^-B&amp;ftREIN 'Inland in the Persian Gulf. I am sending you the letter and enclosure in original and passing a copy of this letter v/ithout enclosures to Wilson of the Foreign Office. s F. A. K. HARRISON, ESQ INDIA OFFICE./V (z 1980/6/22) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 8th March, 1947. 2) £ K r . EXT rji 19 I enclose a copy of 1 a leltex- we have had. from the Italian Consul General asking for the repatriation of a certain Signor Gionfriddo from Bahrein Island in the Persian Gulf. I should he grateful if you could tell me what reply should he returned to this request. (John Wilson) C.B» Burgess, Esq., Colonial Office. 1 1 MAR 1947 • ■ I 4</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1198</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1198</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 672/47 'Santo Gionfriddo'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-07T22:37:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (18 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 20, these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of letters, telegrams, and notes between officials of the Foreign Office and the Political Resident in Persian Gulf regarding an enquiry from the Italian Ministry for Foreign Affairs in Rome requesting the repatriation of Santo Gionfriddo, an Italian citizen who is supposedly interned at Bahrain, Persian Gulf. The letters involve a search for Gionfriddo’s location. Also involved are the Bahrain Political Agent and the Arabian-American Oil Company.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Repatriation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Anglo-Italian relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001e3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>